<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5324</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO FEDERAL COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/04/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005324.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 13 APRIL 1980<br />
ADDRESS TO FEDERAL COUNCIL<br />
In this important year, I welcome the opportunity to address<br />
the 1980 Federal Council and, through you, all members of the<br />
Party throughout Australia.<br />
We meet at the beginning of a new decade, as members of a party<br />
in government which has given to the nation an impressive legacy<br />
of achievement. In spite of international difficulties, ours is<br />
a future in which change will provide challenge; in which challenge<br />
will provide opportunity; and in which the seizing of our<br />
opportunities will secure our success. Our successes of the<br />
recent past, give us the confidence to tackle the future<br />
together successfully.<br />
Wie meet at this council with an entitlement to proclaim our<br />
achiev~ t2:-. nts; with a justification for projecting our capacity<br />
to lead A" ustralia in the years ahead. In an election year, let<br />
us recap~ ture the spirit which has won acceptance in the minds<br />
of Successive generations of Australians. Let us reaffirm our<br />
philos::._-. y in action~ c has brought continuing growth and<br />
well-beia 4to ou, nation. Let us mobilise our commitment to<br />
Libera7iSrL which alone can harness the creativity and capacity<br />
of all Australians.<br />
Thi s is not the tiotne to hesitate in our convi~ tion. We should<br />
not slacken in our poursuit of electoral victory, this year or<br />
in any year. Liberalism in the future, can only be as strong<br />
as the willingness of those who, believing it, are prepared to<br />
fight for it. Because a great future of opportunity is unfolding<br />
before us, there can be no excuse for apathy in the face of political<br />
danger; for simplicity when confronted by political guile; for<br />
weak-and uncertain action in the face of attack.<br />
With our ideals to inspire us and our commitment to drive us,<br />
we will lead Australia to new levels of international and domestic<br />
achievement. The spirit of the times is one of -practical Liberalism.<br />
This involves bei. ng conservative enough to be able to identify<br />
accurately what is best in life and therefore worth conserving. But<br />
it also involves being practical enough to be flexible and v'ersatile<br />
in adopting new means and new attitudes to ensure the safety of<br />
Liberal principles. And it is these principl. es which will give us<br />
our vision in the decade ahead. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
They will inform our attitudes, guide our policies and secure our<br />
victory. That is our task as a party in the 80' s. In that task,<br />
the role of every Party member, in every State, in every arm of<br />
our organisation, will be central. This is especially true of<br />
Federal Council. Since the inception of the Liberal Party<br />
more than 35 years ago, Federal Council has played a role of<br />
great importance to our continuing electoral success. At it,<br />
the views of the membership have been refined into the Party's<br />
platform which has enshrined our Liberal principles. These have<br />
served us well. For more than 35 years, from this forum, our<br />
Party has proclaimed our commitment to the individual to the<br />
securing of his freedom; to the exercise of his initiative;<br />
to the expression of his individuality; and tohis acceptance of<br />
responsibility. From this forum, we have exalted the role of individual Australian<br />
rmen and women, while our political opponents have exalted the role<br />
of collective government. This weekend, as in this forum, we<br />
debate and deliberate, our concern is not with abstract theory,<br />
unrelated to the changing demands of the 80s. Ours is not a<br />
party wedded to inflexible and unchanging dogma. Our way is to<br />
S combine a vision of the future with existing realities so that<br />
Liberal government continues to be practical, effective and<br />
efficient. In 1975, we inherited problems of economic organisation and<br />
managerent, induced by the government of the day, and beyond its<br />
competence to solve. These problems threatened to test severely<br />
the will and capacity of Liberal government. During the last<br />
our years, we have ret that test with resolution. We have matched<br />
our reslution which achievement. From the outset, we sought to<br />
correct the imbalances in the economy. Then, as now, our first<br />
preoccupation was the fight against inflation.<br />
A society that does not attack the source of inflation is little<br />
better than one which ignores breaches of the law. For inflation<br />
robs people of their freedom and their security. In absolute<br />
-erms, we have been successful in reducing inflation from as<br />
much as 17% in the Labor years to the present level of<br />
Viewed in the international context, our record is superior to<br />
that of many other countries. In the 12 months to January 1980,<br />
the U. S. inflation rate, as measured by consumer prices, was<br />
13.9%, an increase of 4.5percentage points over the level of<br />
the previous year. In the it was 18.4%, an increase in<br />
12 months of 9 percentage points. The latest published Australian<br />
figures show ah increase in the 12 months to December 1979 of 2<br />
percentage points from 8% to 10%. One result of our success against<br />
inflation has been a substantial increase in our international<br />
competitiveness. Relative to some of our trading partners, our<br />
costs are down and we can now compete successfully on world markets.<br />
The Government has aided this improved position by its programme.<br />
of investment allowances; export incentives; and research and<br />
development grants. And published statistics tell the story.<br />
The volume of manufactured exports last year was 28% above the level.<br />
of the previous year. And our rural industries, even in the face<br />
of potentially serious drought conditions, are experiencing better<br />
returns, aided by the containment of'domestic inflation and<br />
strengthened by the Government's success in securing better access<br />
to overseas markets. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Indeed, the economy's performance in some areas has been somewhat<br />
stronger than that foreshadowed when we drew up the last budget,<br />
and this improvement in our expectations is a vindication of<br />
Government policies. Pleasingly, our economic performance has<br />
been reflected in an improved employment position. While<br />
unemployment is still too high, total employment in Australia<br />
in the year to February 1980 rose by over 155,000. These are<br />
significant achievements.<br />
They are the result of difficult decisions taken by government.<br />
They have involved difficult choices for many A-ustralians. But<br />
we are now seeing. that difficult decisions often contain the most<br />
rewarding solutions; that difficult choices often provide the most<br />
rewarding outcomes.<br />
Our central strategy of containing inflation has been supported<br />
by a necessary restraint in Commonwealth Government spending; a<br />
reduction in our budget deficit and an end to Government-i nduced<br />
erosion of private sector viability. By sensible management,<br />
governme-: nts can create an environment in which economic growth<br />
will develop and flourish. But, in the end, it is the private<br />
sector which is the engine of growth and progress. It is only<br />
when governments recognise this that they then seek to contain<br />
their own spending.<br />
In the 3 years to 1978-79, Commonwealth budget outlays showed<br />
virtually no growth in real terms. Yet, in the 3 years to 1976,<br />
they averaged a growth of over 10%. Is it any wonder, to<br />
acconTcazte this growth, that taxes went up; and as the Labor<br />
government grabbed more and more of the national wealth,<br />
individ,. als suffered, industry was squeezed and investment dried<br />
up. Another significant barometer of the Government's spending<br />
restraint is its success with Commonwealth employment levels.<br />
Prom June 1972 to June 1975, the number of Commonwealth Government<br />
employees rose by 52,000. We have reversed this trend; we have<br />
impoed efectve staff ceilings; and since we came to office the<br />
number of Commonwealth employees, in areas subject to staff<br />
ceilings, has fallen by 10,000.1<br />
The lesson is simple. It is a lesson being learnt increasingly<br />
around the world that government intervention in the economy,<br />
in areas where it does not belong, is damaging to economic growth<br />
and jeopardises national well-being. It is a lesson, the truth of<br />
which is well proven by our Government's performance. It is telling<br />
evidence of the extent of our performance that a new sense of<br />
confidence, pride, direction and optimism is at work in Australia.<br />
This optimism is soundly based, but it would be foolish to imagine<br />
that in the so-called lucky country, the luck is self-perpetuating.<br />
We have to do more to secure our future, than leave things to chance.<br />
All things do not come to those who sit and wait. Certainly, we<br />
are fortunate with our natural resource endowments. But, in the<br />
more than fortune will be needed to find these resources;<br />
to develop, process and market them; and to manage the enterprises<br />
which result from their development. Yet this is a challenge which<br />
should invigorate all Australians. For we have entered the new<br />
decade with a formidable legacy of achievements. The-foundations<br />
for national development are well laid. ./ 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
But such foundations are hard to build, easy to destroy. We began<br />
that building process when we first came to government in 1975.<br />
Indeed, ever since the Liberal Party gained office in 1949, it<br />
has given the highest priority to the creation of strong and viable<br />
industries of all kinds which can compete and expand in ' international<br />
trade. Australian wealth was created this way. our standard<br />
of living has depended more on the success of achievements of<br />
our industries than on anything else. But it cannot be overstated.<br />
that for continued national development, certain pre-conditions<br />
have to be met; a number of things have to be done.<br />
First, and most importantly, we need a strong economy. Our success<br />
in reaching this objective has provided the foundation from which<br />
we can begin to seize emerging opportunities. Secondly, it is<br />
only economic strength which gives us the capacity to attract<br />
the necessary capital, technology, expertise and skill for the<br />
kind of development that lies ahead.<br />
For these commodities, we will have to compete successfully on<br />
the international market and only a strong economy can attract<br />
them or, indeed, afford them. Thirdly, a nation can only attract<br />
investment when it offers a stable political environment in which<br />
consistency and continuity in the objectives of goverment policymaking<br />
enable businesses and large corporations to plan for the<br />
long term. Fourthly, for balanced development -in the future,<br />
* we will need an increasingly efficient ' and competitive capital<br />
market. A market which encourages the mobilising of equity and<br />
fixed interest ca-pite-1; which helps Australians to become partners<br />
and participants as investors in our development projects.<br />
A great programme of national development lies in front of us.<br />
Australia * Will be ca-2. ta. hungry in the 1980' s.-Funds will be<br />
needed-: r O. M overseams, but we will also need to mobilis~ e Australian<br />
savings for long. term investment purposes. And here lie new<br />
opport-, nitiesfor Australians. I can think of no more effective<br />
use for the investment of our present savings than in the<br />
development of o-r national energy resources; in the support<br />
of outward-looking and aggressive manuf acturing industries<br />
and in the provision of modern finance and servicing industries.<br />
The future is indeed promising for those with ideas and a<br />
willingness to implement them; for those with initiative; for<br />
those willing to accept challenges and seek the rewards fo~ r<br />
investment that will accrue from them..<br />
Trhis leads to a furt'her element-for our future development<br />
-the provision of adequate facilities which can accommodate the<br />
investme~ nt programme which lies ahead. This is the challenge<br />
we faced on coming to government. We knew that special<br />
measures would have to be taken. Because investment in Australia<br />
had ground to a halt, much had to be done to get it going a-gain.<br />
And the government wished to see that Australia's resource potential<br />
was realised without undue delay.<br />
In 1976, 1 had discussions with Sir Charles Court about the need<br />
for infrastructure investment investment in ports, pipelines<br />
and power generation plants which would be necessary if projects<br />
were to proceed. At an historic Loan Council meeting in November<br />
19793 the Commonwealth and States agreed to State borrowings<br />
totalling almost $ 1800 million for facilities designed to accelerate<br />
national development. 1 </p>
<p>Much of this was for the deveiopmr~ nt of our coal reserves and the<br />
provision of electricity generation based on coal. Within a year,<br />
the Iranian crisis of 1979 starkly focused the attention of the<br />
community once again on the world oil situation and in particular, on<br />
future energy costs and supplies. This underlined the wisdom of our<br />
decisions in November 1978. The price of OPEC oil rose by over 100%<br />
in 1979. Inevitably, the world oil situation was finely balanced as<br />
industrialised countries confronted a real energy challenge. But this<br />
challenge has provided opportunities for Australia opportunities we<br />
are prepared for and which we can successfully meet.<br />
world energy consumers are looking to politically stable countries<br />
with economic policies which secure reliable and cheaper supplies<br />
cof energy. This creates for us, in Australia, a wider opportunity.<br />
Because of international energy shortages; because of the existence<br />
here of competitive alternatives to petroleum products, the decade<br />
ahead will see national development gain a new momentum.<br />
R1ecognising this, at the Loan Council meeting in December 1979,<br />
we built on the initiatives taken in 1978. The Commonwealth<br />
approved a further borrowing programme of eight hundred million<br />
dollars. This meant that at two Loan Council meetings within 14<br />
months, the Commnonwealth had granted approval for the borrowing<br />
of over $ 2,500 million for Australian development projects.<br />
All but $ 100 million of this was for energy-related projects.<br />
$ 160 million was for coal loaders in Queensland and New South Wales<br />
and over $ 400 milli4cn for the Dampier-Perth gas pipeline.<br />
But th&amp;. bulk of the programme, a massive $ 1,300 million was for project<br />
t~ o incr-c-se oil sub,; zliution and3 our electricity generating capacity. The<br />
EavailadZility of adea'uate supplies of electricity will be an essential<br />
compor-eant in AustraliLa's development in the years ahead. Large<br />
resrvoef eas&gt;-Tned coal in eastern Australia are able to<br />
provid: E electric zower at very competitive rates.<br />
The product ion costs of this electricity are considerably lower<br />
than power prices in other developed countries; much less than<br />
those in Japan; and also cheaper than power-. costs from new<br />
generating plants in the United States. Recognising this,<br />
the Commonwealth further proposed at the December 1979 meeting<br />
with State Premiers, that in co-op~ eration with the Victorian<br />
and New South Wales' governments, investigation and planning<br />
should begin for the electrification of the Melbourne-Sydney<br />
rail link.<br />
It was also agreed that a joint study with all the States and<br />
the Northern Territory be undertaken on the practicability<br />
of electrifying significant parts of the government railways<br />
systems in Australia.<br />
Both studies are on schedule and results are expected to be * with<br />
governments by the middle of next month for consideration at the<br />
June Premiers' conference.' The availability of cheap electricity<br />
will be a vital-factor in future industrial development. if<br />
inadequate policies and the absence of proper government initiatives<br />
were to result in limiting electricity supplies, industrial<br />
development in Australia and the processing of our raw materials<br />
would be jeopardised. New South Wales has already had to turn<br />
away a proposal for the construction of an aluminium smelter<br />
because existing power resources were fully extended. / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
On the basis of the experience in some Australian States, a<br />
power station can take 8 years to come on line, double the time<br />
for the construction of an aluminium smelter. Hence, while<br />
State governments have an overall responsibility for the provision<br />
of electricity, land, harbours, and other elements of infrastructure,<br />
the Commonwealth, through these new borrowing programmes, has taken<br />
unprecedented steps to facilitate the development of industry and<br />
resource processing in Australia.<br />
Already, in the bauxite, alumina and aluminium industries requiring<br />
massive inputs of electricity, $ 4.5 billion of projects are either<br />
under construction or are about to go. All of these are expected<br />
to be completed by the mid 80' s. As well as this, a further<br />
$ 6 billion worth of projects in the aluminium industry are seeking<br />
an investment home in Australia. Such initiatives represent the<br />
encouraging prospect, in an energy scarce world, of the increased<br />
use of electricity as an alternative to expensive petroleum<br />
products. But in addition to electricity generating projects, the Commonwealth<br />
recently announzed an inquiry into electricity generation and the<br />
sharing of power resources in south eastern Australia.. This<br />
important matter was first raised by the Commonwealth at the<br />
Premiers' Conf'erence in 1977. It is a concrete example of the<br />
Government' s concern to ensure that Australia's domestic economy<br />
and future cormmerical opportunity should not be limited through<br />
any-lack of electriCity Supply facilities; or by inadequate<br />
co-operation between the States.<br />
This is the rore important with increasing overseas interest<br />
being in ener-,!-intensive industries in Australia. Parallel<br />
to this d~. velop-ment :) is that related to the second aspect of our<br />
abundan coal rese. rvas their export potential. The International<br />
Energy -Lgency est-4-. atd that Australia's annual coal exports will<br />
rise fron _ 38 to 20-. million tonnes by the year 2000.<br />
As part of this, th1-ey estimate an increase in steaming coal exports<br />
from 6 million tonnes a year to potentially over 100 million tonnes<br />
by the year 2000. That is why, at the Loan Council meeting in 1978,<br />
in anticipation of the magnitude of this increase in demand, the<br />
Commonwealth approved $ 160 million for the construction of coal<br />
loaders in Queensland and New South Wales. A year later, we<br />
sought the co-operation of these two * States in a study to determine<br />
the requirements that will facilitate the expansion of exports in<br />
steaming coal.<br />
This co-operation has been forthcoming and discussions have<br />
already taken place with coal industry officials in Japan,<br />
South Korea and Thailand. The study will identify the necessary<br />
transport and port facilities required so that increased export<br />
demands can be met as they arise.<br />
Co-operation of this kind at government level and between<br />
government and business is essential if national development<br />
is to be harmonious, continuous and productive. The existence<br />
today of this co-operation is in stark contrast to the Labor years,<br />
when business was bullied, enterprise was stifled; and development<br />
stopped. One example of this is the massive North-West Shelf<br />
discoveries, made in the early seventies. / 7 </p>
<p>.7 -7-<br />
While companies were keen then to proceed with development they<br />
were prevented from doing so by government policies. When we came<br />
to power, we co-operated with the companies concerned, and the<br />
Western Australian government, to encourage the successful<br />
development of this vast resource, and to provide the climate<br />
for it to go ahead. Upon completion, it will be a huge project.<br />
As well as supplying Western Australia with a much needed<br />
alternative to oil use, it will provide great economic benefits<br />
to Australia as a whole. All this is part of the catalogue of<br />
development either under way or about to take place in Australia.<br />
Yet this is only part of the story. In my election speech in<br />
1977, I announced to the Australian people:<br />
" Australia is ready to go with $ 6,000 million of development."<br />
In the two financial years which followed that statement, actual<br />
investment was even higher than I predicted, at $ 6,400 million.<br />
I indicated then, that:<br />
" In the coming 3 years, we can look to other vast developments."<br />
This has now., been, proven..<br />
Most recent figures indicate that almost $ 17 billion worth of<br />
mining and manufracturing projects are about to go ahead in Australia,<br />
or are 4in the final stages of preparation. $ 12 billion of these<br />
relate either to investment for energy projects which will provide<br />
alternatives to oil use; or investment in industries in which<br />
non-oil energy input is a large proportion of total cost.<br />
And even these Zftcures, if anything, understate-the likely<br />
explo--ation and develonment exoenditure in Bass Strait and the<br />
North-7W-est Shielf and do not include the giant Rundle Shale. oil<br />
project in Queensland. This project could involve a total cost<br />
of many billions of dollars and has the potential to reduce greatly<br />
Australia's deoendence on scarce and costly supplies of imported<br />
crude oil. I<br />
So that when we say, " Australia ison the go", iti sno t as logan,<br />
but a statement of action. It indicates the readiness with which<br />
the private sector will respond to an appropriate economic<br />
environment. Now, the demand for Australian products overseas,<br />
and the increasing interest being shown in Australian investment,<br />
indicate a new respect for, and confidence in our economy.<br />
This confidence stems from our capacity as a government to secure<br />
economic growth, and Liberal Party policies are unashamedly<br />
directed to this end. But this is not the sole objective of our<br />
policy initiatives.<br />
Rather, it is a means by which other goals are more easily--achieved.<br />
For the end result of all that we do is the well being of individual<br />
Australians. Our policies are designed to enable all Australians<br />
to save, be independent, to manage their own affairs, to make<br />
decisions about their families; and to secure their own futures<br />
through the rewards of their own endeavours. In this sense, Liberal<br />
policies are policies of opportunity. / 8 </p>
<p>' 4<br />
* But they are also policies of concern for those who are-disadvantaged<br />
and in need of more particular help. In meeting needs, one of the<br />
more pressing challenges of the 80' s will be to strike a balance<br />
between providing adequate welfare services and meeting the desire<br />
of the taxpayer to retain as much as possible of his own resources<br />
to support the living standards of himsel. f and his family.<br />
In the last four years, while practising government restraintour<br />
welfare commitment has not been compromised. On the taxation front,.<br />
we have, a number of times, increased the income at which tax<br />
first becomes payable by individuals or families.* In this way,<br />
approximately 500,000 Australians have been exempted from paying<br />
tax on their income. As a direct result of the Treasurer's<br />
announcement on March 6, a further 50,000 Australians will be relieved<br />
from paying tax. But since we came into office, th'e Governmenthas also cut maringal<br />
tax rates with the result that 90% of Australian taxpayers are now<br />
paying tax at the lowest marginal rate. By this simplification,<br />
a majority of taxpayers are able to increase their earnings<br />
through overtime or part-time work without moving rapidly into<br />
a higher tax bracket.<br />
These reforms are consistent with the Government's aim of lowering<br />
taxes. They also complement the Government's concern for the family.<br />
We have introduced family allowances designed to help low income<br />
families. By July 1, the spouse rebate will have increased from<br />
$ 400 S% 0 during our term of office. The sole parent rebate has<br />
risen f~ rom $ 200 $ 560 since we came to office, and in this period<br />
we have extended the supporting parent' s benefit to include<br />
suppor'_ n fathers. This is very substantial assistance to single<br />
income families. Further, we have concentrated assistance on<br />
the needs of handica; Dped children. We increased the handicapped<br />
child's allowance by Z; 0% soon after we came to office.<br />
At tha-tI'Me, i t was only paid to the severely handicapped.<br />
In 197-7 we widened the eligibility for the allowance to include<br />
substantially hanrdicapp~ ed children whose family income is low.<br />
And in 1973 we recognised the special needs of handicapped students<br />
when we extended the allowance to cover students over 16 and under<br />
who are in receipt of an invalid pension. Care for our<br />
aged is an important concern of the whole community as it is<br />
governments. Governments, like the community at large, must ensure<br />
that there is dignity in old age.<br />
In significant moves designed to achieve this, the Government has<br />
replaced the complex means test for aged pensions with an easily<br />
understandable income~ test. To ii~ rove levels of accommodation for the<br />
aged and the disabled the Government has spent or allocated some<br />
$ 210 million in the last four years. So far this has meant the<br />
building of over 500 new self contained hostel and nursing home<br />
projects. The Government has already approved a further $ 225 million<br />
over the next three years for these projects.<br />
in all industrialised economies today, unemployment is a vexing issue.<br />
We have attempted to face this problem in a practical and productive<br />
As a result of Government policies,-the improved economic<br />
health of the nation has resulted in 155,000 more jobs in the 12<br />
months to February this year. The Commonwealth has devised a range<br />
of schemes to assist the unemployed according to their different<br />
circumstances; in particular their different abilities, state of<br />
Education, training and work expericonce. By the end of the financial year,<br />
about half a million Australians, many of them Young Australians, will have been<br />
assisted in this way.../ 9 </p>
<p>Amongst these schemes is the provision of $ 150 million over f ive years for<br />
spe cial programmes designed to enhance the skills, employment prospects<br />
and the interests of young people as they move from school to work.<br />
Many young people find it difficult to get stable employment because<br />
they lack the required experience or qualifications. The Government's<br />
Special Youth Employment Training Programme provides incentive to<br />
employers to take on young unemployed people and bring them to a<br />
point at which they can adequately compete for jobs..<br />
Recently, the Government has<br />
strengthened its training programmes for the unemployed by increasing<br />
the! incentives to employers to take on apprentices. This gives the<br />
young unemployed the opportunity to acquire the necessary skills,<br />
to actively participate in the programme of national development<br />
that lies ahead.<br />
If the Government's initiatives for the unemployed are supported<br />
by teachers, parents and the community at large then their prospects<br />
of even greater success will be significantly enhance--d. I believe<br />
the Government has demonstrated, in this sensitive area of unemployment.<br />
commendable purpose. We have had the courage to stay with policies<br />
which we know will work, and which in the long-term will create<br />
the economic climate in which increased permanent employment is<br />
S possible. We have not succumbed to the easy temptation to pursue<br />
policies which might appear to assist the problem, but which will<br />
achieve nothing.<br />
Which brings me to the Labor Party' s ' make work' schemes. We have<br />
estimated that they would cost the taxpayer about $ 1,000 million<br />
on the cr-etext that_ they could provide a quick fix to what is<br />
a derna-d: ng interna-tonal problem. To suggest this is to talk<br />
economic and employment nonsense. Worse, it seeks to exploit the<br />
emotionsz and asc2ira--ions of young people as instruments of political<br />
succesS. Where su-cn sc . nemes have existed, they have resulted in an<br />
explosi:'. in costs and an increase in unemploment. For exyample,<br />
in thn unemnlc~ ment support schemes rose from 24 million pounds<br />
in 1975-76 to 410 : 7i'llion pounds in 1978-79. In that time, the<br />
unemployment rate in: reased from 3.9% to 5.7%.<br />
Now the Labor Partyi seeks to foist on the Australian community<br />
S$ 1,000 million o-f this kind of proven failure. The great<br />
W deception is the assertion that these policies would benefit the<br />
unemployed. But such a rampage in expenditure would accelerate<br />
inflation, destroy the profitability of industry and reduce overall<br />
prospects of employment. And if anyone had $ 1,000 million to spend,<br />
would they let it be spent on resurrected, re-named RED schemes.<br />
These schemes were abandoned by Labor in the 70' s. Recycled again,<br />
under a new name, they would fail again. But their very existence<br />
is part of the attempt by Labor to project an image of reasonableness<br />
and responsibility. We have seen it all before.<br />
In three areas alone, unemployment, housing and health,<br />
tno y have committed themselves to expenditure in the order of riot<br />
less than $ 1500 million on the most conservative estimates.<br />
When we get through the whole list of Labor promises, what would<br />
the bill be then? It would accelerate far beyond the national<br />
capacity to pay. The Labor Party commitment to a national tradingcorporation;<br />
an Australian manpower office; a national fuel and<br />
energy commission; an Australian hydro-carbon corporation; and a<br />
national investment fund.. All of these and many other examples<br />
of: costly intervention would create big government deficits and<br />
high inflation, the problems we have struggled for four years to<br />
___ successfully -surmount. </p>
<p>1.0<br />
And this expansion is threated in areas where governments should<br />
not be squandering taxpayer's funds. What is just as bad, is that<br />
the very existence of these government authorities would tend to<br />
drive out private enterprise; damage investment and development<br />
as they did before; and unwind the process of national progess<br />
that has been set in place so painstakingly over the. past four<br />
years. Such threats to our economic prosperity as are posed by our<br />
political opponents should not be lightly dismissed. They were<br />
endorsed by resolution at the A. L. P. conference in Adelaide last<br />
year. They are binding on all members of the party. They have<br />
been multiplied in their potential impact by the lurch to the<br />
left in recent months of the A. L. P. Indeed, the Leader of the<br />
Oppositionis the left's most eminent and willing prisoner.<br />
The wages policy he endorsed in Adelaide was described by<br />
the President of the A. C. T. U. as a " gutless sell out to the left".<br />
There was no anti-inflation policy. Mr Hayden's commitment to<br />
untrammelled power for the unions; his silence in the face of<br />
unacceptable militancy by union leadership; his intervention<br />
in the Queensland branch to give power to the Socialist left;<br />
his dumping of Dr Klugman after Mr Hayden had criticised him<br />
for being too concerned about Communism; his support by the<br />
Socialist left of the Victorian Labor Party; his own commitment<br />
to bigger and more centralised government all this completes<br />
the destruction of any image of moderation and responsibility<br />
that may have still resided with the Labor Party.<br />
In fact, VMr Hayden is unrepentant about the extent of the Labor<br />
threat. In March 1979, he argued that " there was nothing revolutionary<br />
or even particularly radical about the Whitlam programmes".<br />
In an interview with the Sydney Morning Herald ironically called<br />
' Insict into the 2C's', which became an insight into the real<br />
Labor Party, Mr Hayden said:<br />
" I would have thought that the things I have outlined in<br />
ter ms of revenue are somewhat more radical than had been<br />
outlined up to 1972. Unequivocatingly, I have committed<br />
my organisation to a capital gains tax, a resource rental<br />
tax, a levy on domestic oil producers, a number of initiatives<br />
in the tax area, and other measures of that nature...." ( 31 December 1979)<br />
This is doctrinaire Socialism gone mad Mr Hayden summed his<br />
own position up more adequately than anyone else could when he<br />
said last year:<br />
" The challenge to traditional, democratic Socialism...<br />
is the rapid spread of philosophies based on lower<br />
taxes and smaller government." Chamberlain Lecture,<br />
2 March 1979)<br />
sustained.<br />
Such a challenge must be For it is a challenge to the<br />
whole basis of our phil' h: t&gt; t A<br />
Aust:-l1ans have in their future. It a chale., nye which calls<br />
,' rom us all an obligation to defend our convictions and proclaim<br />
our beliefs. / ii </p>
<p>L1h<br />
The success of our achievements must be matched by a successful<br />
defence of the principles and the policies that made them possible.<br />
We cannot allow our national progress in the 80' s to be jeopardised<br />
and our successes of the recent past to be squandered. We have<br />
entered this decade in a more privileged position than that in<br />
many other countries.<br />
Tha; ough co-operation and dedication, no success is-beyond us.<br />
Mr President, you and your Executiv members of the various<br />
State organisations; the Federal Director and his staff; and<br />
of course, rank and file members of the Party, many not here<br />
today; all embody-this spirit.<br />
Together, we have the-obligation in the decade ahead to demonstrate<br />
that we know where our efforts should be directed. It is only<br />
the Liberal Party w-hich has the strength, the discipline, the<br />
resolution and the policies to advance Australia.<br />
It is only the Liberal Party that has the vision and the ideals<br />
which are in step with the nation's needs. It is only* the<br />
Liberal Party which will provide the strength and the discipline<br />
to give practical and effective expression to these ideals.<br />
That is the'Liberal task for the 80' s. Let us go forth and<br />
be confident and enthusiastic about our purpose and our obligation<br />
to Australia. Let us transmit this confidence and this enthusiasm<br />
to this nation. Let us do this by making Liberalism the driving<br />
force within all Australians in this decade.<br />
Let us determine to serve the nation with commitment, with humility,<br />
but wit-an utter determination about our purpose and our<br />
objectives. With that sense of unity and conviction, no task is<br />
beyond us. WhI-en other---s stand in our place let them be able to<br />
say that they were well served by this generation of Liberals. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
