<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1776</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS PM.NO18/1968 COMPETITION TO SELECT NATIONAL GALLERY DESIGNER STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001776.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
\ 9 ER'Sr<br />
FOR PRESS " 1 PM. No. 18/ 1968<br />
COMPETITION TO WSELECT NATIONAL GALLERY DESIGNER<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr John Gorton<br />
A competition will be held to select an architect to design<br />
Australia's National Gallery in Canberra.<br />
It is intended that the competition will be among architects<br />
practising In Australia including some of the younger men In the profession.<br />
The entries will be assessed by:<br />
1. Eminent architect and specialist in creative arts, Mr Robin Boyd<br />
2. Chairman of the National Capital Planning Committee, Sir John<br />
Overall.<br />
3. Vice President of the R. A. 1. Mr J. H. McCon nell.<br />
The aim of the Government and the Assessors is to obtain a<br />
vigorous and Imaginative architect with a touch of adventure. It is very<br />
Important that the design of the Gallery should reflect the most modern thinking<br />
of the present day, that it should be particular to Australia and be an<br />
expression of the national character.<br />
The limited competition Is for a design approach. The winqer<br />
will be commissioned to submit the actual design of the Gallery.<br />
A site has been nominated for the purposes of the competition,<br />
but the final site for the building is still to be determined by the Government.<br />
The services of a Gallery Director of world standing will be<br />
sought to assist in the preparation of the final brief for the appointed architect.<br />
The competition should enable the designer of the National<br />
Gallery to be chosen by June this year.<br />
By that time, the governing body of the Gallery should have been<br />
appointed and be available for the necessary consultations to enable the<br />
detailed design work to proceed.<br />
Planning for the project is directed towards having the building<br />
completed early In the 19701s.<br />
CANBERRA, 6 February, 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
