<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4794</transcript-id>
    <title>RURAL WRITERS INTERVIEW</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004794.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT<br />
RURAL WRITERS INTERVIEW<br />
23 August 197b<br />
QUESTION:........ are you in a position to tell us what attitude<br />
the Government will take to a strong line by the union if another<br />
situation blows up like last night's.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't want to elaborate in detail, but let me oniy say that<br />
the Government knows quite well that the sheep export trade<br />
is important to the growers concerned, important forAustralia,<br />
and it is the Government's intention that the trade will<br />
continue. The Government will not, and cannot, accept a<br />
situation in which a particular group of people can determine<br />
the nature or the direction of Australia's exports.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister will that include opening up new ports<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think it's much better not to go into too much detail about<br />
it. At the moment the trade is going ahead, and the statement<br />
of attitude that I have expressed is the Governments position.<br />
It is a very firm position.<br />
QUESTION: Going ahead until September 1, Sir, what happens after that?<br />
The moratorium finishes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think we need to see what happens.<br />
QUESTION: Would you allow a reversion to the previous situation prior<br />
to the last conference where they imposed a ratio of carcass<br />
to livesheep?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I have said that the trade has got to go ahead, and it would<br />
be much better I think if we could just take it as that at<br />
the moment because you go into the details ' if this', ' if that',<br />
and I think it's much better to see what does occur. </p>
<p>QUESTION:<br />
Tney have categorically said that they regard the situation<br />
as being clearly resolved by this meeting in Sydney, that<br />
no restrictions or bans will apply and they feel totally tree<br />
to do whatever they want.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Who is this.<br />
ANSWER: The growers. They regard that meeting which Mr Street convened,<br />
the result of that meeting as giving them a totally clean bill<br />
to do whatever they want to do.<br />
QUESTION: The AMIEU of course has said totally the Opposite.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, I know.<br />
QUESTION: Your answer, Sir, indicates that the Government will take the<br />
strongest possible line.<br />
PkcIMh; MINISTER:<br />
The uovernment will be supporting the trade, yes.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
Were you aware ot reported and alleged differences within the<br />
AM4IEU*? PRIME MINISTk; R:<br />
I nave heard there are differences, yes.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, do you think that there is any way that the<br />
ACTU can, if you like, get moderation in this dispute, get<br />
the union to come to the party?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER:<br />
I think it was the joint activities of Mr Hawke and Mr Street<br />
on the last occasion which did a great deal to resolve the<br />
issue, even if only tor a period. One of the problems ot<br />
this area is you are in the realm of " it" If something<br />
happens, if somebody does something, and it's -not a very<br />
good practEice in politics to respond on that basis because<br />
the conversation can so soon move to an area which can appear / 3 </p>
<p>to be nothing but provocative, and future events might unfold<br />
that that was unnecessary. I have stated the Government's<br />
attitude, and I really think that for the moment that ought<br />
to be adequate.<br />
QUESTION: You are hopeful that discussions in other words will still<br />
solve this problem.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Obviously I would sooner discussions solved the problem, any<br />
problem. It's much better to have that. Whatever anyone<br />
says the Government doesn't want confrontation. That doesn't<br />
mean to say the Government doesn't have a determined view.<br />
QUESTION: The union says that a lot of the problem is caused by the<br />
transitory nature of their employment they need adequate<br />
compensation. We know-about the shearers, they have<br />
compensation in their a-ward, and there is compensation in<br />
the award for AMIEU people, but what is your reaction<br />
to this claim that they do need compensation.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think that awards have taken that sort of thing into account<br />
and traditionally have in Australia. At the same time we need<br />
to understand that in a number of meatworks., not all, the<br />
seasonal nature of the business is much less than it used to<br />
be. There are some meatworks that used to go from, at the peak,<br />
employment of say 850 down to not much more than maintenance<br />
100 or 150, but now are able to maintain their peak, or something<br />
close to their peak all the year round. A lot work in<br />
Australia is seasonal, and awards have traditionally taken<br />
that sort of thing into account. There is nothing unusual in<br />
that.<br />
QUiESTiON: Prime Minister, will you do the same thing an d make these,<br />
pursue the ram embargo with the same sort of<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't see any problems in the rams going out.<br />
QUESTION: You don't?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. / 4 </p>
<p>QUE~ STION:<br />
how will they go out?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Again you are in the same position hypothesis.<br />
QUESTION: ' he Russians said they would have bought a hundred ramns in<br />
Melbourne if they had been confident they could have got them<br />
out. PI~ k; MINISTER:<br />
if they had asked me I would have said they would get out.<br />
QUESTION: So the Russians should come to you should they Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm not really saying that. It the Russians had gone to<br />
Ian Sinclair I am sure Ian Sinclair would have said the rams<br />
will get out, you can bid in complete freedom.<br />
QUESTION: Turn a blind eye to the ( remainder inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Again, why do you want to pursue the " if"?<br />
QUESTION:<br />
We have questioned Ian Sinclair on a number of occasions about<br />
what the Government might do, and he has responded in roughly<br />
the same way as you have: ' Let's wait and see what happens'.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
But look, the " if" doesn't help, it really doesn't in an<br />
industrial relations sense. i know because I think somewhere<br />
a wrong answer was given.<br />
QUESTION: would<br />
Some good western District rams/ have gone out.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well there were a lot of NSW rams there too.<br />
QUESTION: Ana some Nareen stuff? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
They won all the unhoused. But it really doesn't help to<br />
pursue the " if" situation. It really doesn't.<br />
QUESTION: But surely farmers need.<br />
PRI14E MINISTER:<br />
They need to know that the ramns will go out.<br />
QUESTION: They will go out?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I said I have absolute confidence that they will go out.<br />
And I'd say that to anyone who wanted to come and buy.<br />
QUESTION: If I could come back also to something....<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I was very surprised that the Russians hadn't bid. But I<br />
made some inquiries why and I think they got a wrong answer<br />
somewhere. QUESTION: Another thing I'd also like to bring on, with absolute<br />
interest to primary producers is the P. I. B. When will<br />
interest rates be structured, and is there any indication<br />
at all what the interest rates will be?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I can't add to what has already been published about this.<br />
QUESTION: What has been published?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'll check the tigures.<br />
QUESTION: Surely there would be a requirement if the Government has<br />
made In1' s available through the Budget, surely it would<br />
be reasonable to presume that </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The fact that I&amp; D's are available will enable the bank to<br />
ameliorate its rate of interest to some extent.<br />
QUESTION: Are they being told to do so?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It will enable them to do it.<br />
QUESTION: I understand the Government took legal advice on the use of<br />
IED's. surely if you are going to make this available<br />
it is to a certain extent controversial. Wouldn't you say<br />
to the bank it must be used to give concession?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it's my understanding that it's going to be. There is<br />
one argument here, a point of view, that I would like to put.<br />
Somebody has said lED is five percent, why can't it be much<br />
lower than the estimates appear to be? One of the things<br />
that needs to be understood of course with lED's is that<br />
there are very considerable tax advantages in IED's to<br />
farmers, and I don't want to lose sight of that now that<br />
they will be starting to get on to a better income basis<br />
the advantages of tax averaging conditions that we've<br />
introduced, and the advantages of lED's for farmers will<br />
really come to the fore. In periods of slack income it's<br />
a bit like saying that Christmas is around the corner when<br />
it never comes. Those who are getting out of a drought<br />
situation and beef producers are going to, through<br />
averaging and IEDs, obviously carry of past losses,<br />
through a combination of these three things they are given<br />
a real opportunity to rebuild their reserves.<br />
QUESTION: Can I ask you this. When Cabinet met in Perth,<br />
did it decide that the interest rates of the PIB would be<br />
11 percent?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't think I can say any more about it than I have...<br />
QUESTION: There is $ 8U million in the PIB account alone. I am told that<br />
if the Bank lends out 5O million in a year, sorry, borrows<br />
million in a year, and lends out $ 25 million, the contribution<br />
from the Federal Government $ 250,000 I think would be equal<br />
to dropping the interest rate one percent. Could you give some<br />
indication of this $ 80 million, ( inaudible)<br />
how much the Federal Government will be instructed to go into<br />
the PIB? </p>
<p>-7<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't think that's been finally determined.<br />
QUESTION: It could make a tremendous, a huge difference to what, how<br />
the Bank...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The main thing with the Bank, really it is, is to have the<br />
long-term finance available which we know quite well the<br />
traditional banks have not been particularly interested in and it's<br />
the period, the length of the term of the loan which has<br />
the greatest impact on the repayments which is the most important<br />
thing-whether or not the farmer can carry it. In addition to<br />
that, and this is confirmed by the success of the Commonwealth<br />
Loan, there's not the slightest doubt that interest rates are<br />
going to go on going down and I would hope that if we are<br />
in a position in which that movement downward in interest rates<br />
will, in a reasonable time, f low through into the rates which are<br />
of great importance to much of the productive sector of the<br />
community and to bank overdraft rates. I'm not putting any time<br />
on that but Government rates have moved down, a lot of finance<br />
rates have moved down, housing rates have started to move down..<br />
The one area that hasn't moved down are -the bank deposit and<br />
overdraft rates.<br />
QUESTION: So you are suggesting...<br />
PRIME MINISTER_<br />
What I'm suggesting is that with our economic policies,. with<br />
percent inflation, there is a light on the hill. That<br />
will be achieved unless something quite unforeseen happens.<br />
Overall, there is going to be a movement downward in interest<br />
rates. QUESTION: Eventually the interest rates of the Primary industry Bank<br />
will move down...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, they've got to move down with those whatever they are<br />
now, if general rates move down they'll have to move down too,<br />
of course they will.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
Will they be a concessional ratio all the time, to the ruling<br />
rate though? / 8 </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The use ot TED's is designed to enable them to shade their<br />
interest rates below that which they would otherwise be.<br />
QUESTION: Would you need legislation to use IED's?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'd have to check that. Ian Sinclair and tne Treasurer have<br />
been handling the details of this.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, back in 1975 when you became Leader of the<br />
Opposition, you were talking in Portland and Warrnambool, and<br />
you said then about the Primary Industry Bank, " We would<br />
propose that funds be available for the purchase of land for<br />
up to 30-35 years. The funds will also be made available<br />
for the purchase of producers equipment so that people don't<br />
have to buy their tractors and their combines on hire purchase<br />
terms." Do you still see the P'rimary Inaustry Bank making<br />
loans available to Primary producers over a 30-35 year period?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
They will certainly be making them available for extended<br />
periods. QUESTION: Can you put a figure on it for us?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. The bank will have to make its own judgements about that,<br />
but there will be nothing in its charter to prevent it.<br />
QUESTION: You're hopeful that they will be able to lend over a period<br />
of 30-35 years, depending<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I would hope they can lend up to that period, yes.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister can I say something in relation to the Budget?<br />
Would you agree that the new tax levels on fuel will discriminate<br />
heavily against the Primary Industry sector? 9 </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, they won't discriminate heavily against them, because<br />
fuel is a significant cost to a number of industries. It is<br />
a significant cost obviously in relation to Primary industries.<br />
It was a policy move that we felt it necessary to take. The<br />
directions I have had from the Primary Industry area are it<br />
received the Budget very well indeed, because they know<br />
inflation is going to come down and that means interest rates<br />
are going to come down. Farmers I think above all know that<br />
getting these two things right means much much more to them<br />
than outweighs any detriment that comes from the fuel tax<br />
for example.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
Well what are the costs likely to be in terms of international<br />
competitiveness? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I haven't the slightest, although they will be improved<br />
because inflation will be coming down and interest rates<br />
will be coming down. Inflation will be under that of many<br />
of our major trading partners, and our position, instead of<br />
getting worse as it has with high inflation, is going to<br />
improve, there is no doubt. Quite apart from that there<br />
are better markets at the moment.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, on this subject of markets overseas markets<br />
and overseas trade have you had any Japanese reaction at all<br />
to the increase in tariff ( remainder interrupted).<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I haven't had any. There's not an increase in tariffs. I have<br />
been given very firm assurances that they intend to be a stable<br />
market in the future, and I accept and believe those assurances.<br />
QUESTION: Could you get the same assurances from the MTN discussions?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We can get them from the Japanese, but the MTN's a lot of<br />
people, and in relation to a number of MTN countries we<br />
haven't got those assurances at all, as you know. I don't<br />
regard it as an extra tariff, I regard it as the community<br />
getting some of the monopoly profit from import quotas.<br />
QUESTION: They have to pay though. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. I think it will come out of the monopoly profit that now<br />
accrues to the holder of an import licence.<br />
QUESTION: What is the ASEAN reaction to the 12 l% increase in customs?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I haven't seen one. It's a monopoly profit, and ASEAN know<br />
quite well that their exports to us have been increasing at<br />
30%-40% a year for a long long while. They have got a better<br />
access into this market than they have into any other<br />
developed country market in the world. I'm not saying they<br />
shouldn't have, but they have. On a per capita basis,<br />
especially for sensitive goods.<br />
QUESTION: They are paying for the right, actually.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No they won't be paying for it, it will be the importer<br />
here that will be paying, not them. It will be the<br />
importer here. It is important really to get this all<br />
around the right way. But we need to recognise that 86% of<br />
ASEAN exports to us come in I think either duty free<br />
or under preference arrangements, about 3.6% comes in<br />
under quota, so it's only the bit that comes in under<br />
quota that is in any way affected. It's a very small<br />
part of the total trade with them.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, in the event that the EEC doesn't come up<br />
with anything particularly good in the way of agricultural<br />
trade concessions, is the Government prepared to consider<br />
retaliation moves?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There is work being done now, and there will be a submission<br />
coming forward from the Government which we'll take within<br />
the next few weeks on the totality of our trading relationships<br />
with the European community. Let me only say everything we<br />
have said about that subject we've said in great seriousness<br />
and we mean it.<br />
QUESTION: In other words we are ready to get tough with the EEC.<br />
How tough can we be? .11 </p>
<p>11.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh, they need a lot of things from us, and sometimes we<br />
have alternative sources of supply for what we need.<br />
QUESTION: The obvious question, resources diplomacy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh I don't think it's resources diplomacy, I think its<br />
a question of taking the totality of one's trading<br />
relationship into account.<br />
QUESTION: ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We can't offer any more. We have gone as far as anyone<br />
has gone, and that doesn't stand unless we get reciprocal<br />
benefits for Australia.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
Mr Ushiba was not very confident when we questioned him a<br />
couple of weeks ago that Japan could meet the Australian<br />
( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think we'll get an improved situation with Japan on meat.<br />
That's one of significant concern to us as you know, and I<br />
do believe that Japan is making every effort not only to be<br />
but to be seen to be very responsible member of the<br />
international trading community.<br />
QUESTION: That's from pressures from Washington isn't it. You brought<br />
up meat how concerned are we about the<br />
legislation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'd be very concerned about that.<br />
QUESTION: Are you concerned at this stage with what you know now, are<br />
you? / 12 </p>
<p>12.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. I would be very concerned if it was introduced.<br />
QUESTION: At the Ways and Means Committee last week, the second<br />
congressional committee approved it, although watered down.<br />
It looks like the administration, for varying political<br />
reasons, is going to also approve it. It may not affect<br />
us for up to five or six years, but what are we doing in<br />
the mean time?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What do you mean ' what are we doing in the mean time'?<br />
QUESTION:<br />
What can we do to counter the ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Press our case with the United States as hard as we can.<br />
QUESTION: Are you getting signs from the administration that they are<br />
really for it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I haven't.<br />
QUESTION: Any signs at all from them?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What I have been told was that they were opposed to it.<br />
QUESTION: And do you think that that will stick? It's an election year,<br />
and of course<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well everything I've been told would leave me to believe that<br />
would not be accepted.<br />
QUESTION: It has been watered down I understand and will be accepted. / 13 </p>
<p>13.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's not consistent with what I've been told. You've pointed<br />
out that it is election year. On everything* I've been told<br />
I've got every right to be confident, but I note your remarks<br />
about an election year. On the other hand you've got to<br />
understand also that for a number of months the United States<br />
has had a monthly inflation rate of around about That<br />
goes on and on and becomes 10% or 12% over a year. They are<br />
getting increasingly concerned about inflation and food prices<br />
have an obvious impact on that. My belief is that the United<br />
States economy and consumer is going to need more meat, and<br />
Mr Strauss said this in the plainest terms. This isn't just<br />
something up to Christmas. Their cattle numbers were 20 million<br />
down. QUESTION: I thought President Carter told an assembly of U. S.. cattlemen<br />
in Columbia, Missouri', that he would not allow unrestricted<br />
imports of these products.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It has never been suggested that imports would be unrestricted.<br />
They have been restricted for many many years. It's a question<br />
of what the word ' restriction' means, isn't it.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, on the question-of import tariffs, you have<br />
told us here in the past you consider the import tariff<br />
argument overdone as far as farm costs are concerned. There<br />
has been a lot of activity on tariffs in the meantime. Has<br />
your attitude to this question changed in any fundamental way?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No. QUESTION: Prime Minister, is the Government still-looking for some form<br />
of special unemployment benefits for rural producers other than<br />
what goes at the present moment. Understandably there are<br />
problems with legality at present...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't know that there are problems with the legality, I think<br />
there are problems with the way the present arrangements have<br />
been working, and it's not giving great benefit. This matter<br />
is still under examination. It does in a sense become less<br />
urgent with an improving rural outlook, obviously. ./ 14 </p>
<p>14.<br />
QUESTION: Brandy, Sir, and the excise. Some people would regard that<br />
as giving a glass of water to the drowning wine industry.<br />
What is your general appraisal of the situation of increasing<br />
the excise, which was a way of usingyof coursepwine excess.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I think the wine industry is going to be very greatly assisted<br />
by-the Budget.<br />
QUESTION: ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
You are saying it was a way of using excess grapes, but to the<br />
extent that grapes go into wine the industry is going to be<br />
assisted. This is one of the reasons why there weren't<br />
increases on wine, for example.<br />
QUESTION: I It was intended to in actual fact put wine in a better<br />
position in the market place than spirits?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that was in our minds, yes.<br />
QUESTION: ( first half inaudible) as I understand it the rather small<br />
fellows with 30 or 40 acre vineyards rely on getting their<br />
bottom of the market grapes into brandy as that's the only<br />
outlet for them or they're going to be in strife, because<br />
it's the increase in the excises that ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well if they are hurt by imports it's open to any industry<br />
to go to the T. A. A.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, do you think this idea of limiting the amount<br />
of non-farm income the primary producer can get under the<br />
averaging system to $ 5,000-$ 10,000 do you think this will<br />
affect the investment from ( inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't know that it will to a great extent, but I don't<br />
believe it's right I should get the benefits of tax averaging<br />
from a Prime ministerial salary for example. </p>
<p>QUESTION:<br />
What about Trust Accounts, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What about them?<br />
QUESTION: They seem to be hit. The Government a year ago was saying<br />
to Parliament ' go into trust accounts.'<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm not aware of that.<br />
QUESTION: I was aware of it.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The Government as a whole I don't think was saying it.<br />
QUESTION: But Trust Accounts have been hit.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Some trusts have been hit, because we believe trusts have been<br />
abused. There can be all sorts of trusts, and its a highly<br />
complex matter, and some trusts over a long period have been necessary<br />
proper and honourable mechanisms for helping to preserve a<br />
farm and keep assets together. Because of the public furore<br />
over some quite outrageous tax avoidance arrangements that<br />
have been made it has tended to bring the name ' trust' into<br />
disrepute. There is still an honourable and proper place<br />
for trusts, but it depends how they are used and in what way<br />
they are used. Trusts are still available of course, but it<br />
depends how they use a trust. It is always the way in which<br />
a trust is used, but I think part of this is the fact that<br />
we have abolished death duties, the fact that we have got tax<br />
averaging now really is an advantage, and Income Equalisation<br />
Deposits. All these things need to be taken together and they<br />
remove much of the need for complicated financial arrangements<br />
that previously have become necessary, especially in times of<br />
low income, to try and preserve the integrity of a farm. We've<br />
been seeking-to establish ways in which farmers can do this<br />
and leave a farm to their kids without having to go through<br />
all sorts of complicated devices, and I think that's the<br />
proper way of doing it.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, you seem to be banking a fair bit on a rural<br />
led recovery. </p>
<p>16.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, not rural led. To get the economy right you've got to<br />
get a lot of underlying factors in the economy right, and<br />
occassionaly we are accused of wanting it investment led, or<br />
consumer led, and now you've said rural led. You have<br />
got to get all the underlying factors in the economy right...<br />
inflation down, interest rates down, respectability of profits<br />
in all sorts of industries.<br />
QUESTION:<br />
Wages down?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Moderation in wages. When you say ' wages down', we still<br />
estimate that average earnings will increase this year.<br />
They increased last year, but at a much more moderate rate<br />
than previous years, and that's obviously an important<br />
element. Moderation in wages--wage restraint--is obviously<br />
an important element in it. But what I have said in terms<br />
of the recovery of Australia I think is this: get the<br />
underlying factors right and especially inflation and<br />
interest rates, and that makes it more profitable for<br />
people to invest whether it's on farms or in businesses<br />
of other kinds; it also makes us a preferred country for<br />
resource developments. If somebody from America wants to<br />
invest in a resource producing nation such as Australia,<br />
they will look at political stability, they will look at<br />
economic factors, and they will make a decision Australia<br />
or somewhere else. one of the things we want to do is to<br />
make this country a favoured country for that kind of<br />
investment, and if we do that I think we can do Australia<br />
a great service ( inauidible) activity in Australia,<br />
especially when world trade is difficult, slack. World<br />
markets aren't growing as much as they ought to to reduce<br />
the total level of world unemployment. But because we are,<br />
making better progress with inflation, and therefore will<br />
make better progress with interest rates, we do have a<br />
capacity to put Australia in a preferred position, to take<br />
advantage of whatever investment is going. The same<br />
circumstances put farmers into a better position for their<br />
own markets, for exports. I haven't looked up all<br />
the seasonal records, but I think you might have to go back<br />
years to find a year in which the seasonal prospects<br />
were as good, and in which you've also got beef, sheep and<br />
wool and wheat prices all looking good you have had<br />
good years for sheep, you've had good years for cattle,<br />
you remember a time in the past when cows were $ 200 and<br />
sheep were $ 1.50 or 50( but now they are all looking good<br />
and all being good together is going to be the best news<br />
for Australia's country towns, and I believe for many other </p>
<p>17.<br />
businesses around Australia that are suppliers to the Australian<br />
rural industries. I think one of the factors that has often<br />
been underestimated in this economy is the importance of a<br />
prosperous rural sector. If you have a depressed rural sector<br />
it has a dragging effect on the whole economy, and that affects<br />
businesses, it affects cities, it affects country towns.<br />
But if the rural industries are looking to the future with<br />
confidence then that's good for the whole nation. We have<br />
got those circumstances. You would have been around in<br />
country areas there is an optimism abroad which is great<br />
to see, and I haven't seen it for many, many years.<br />
QUESTION: Perhaps for the producer, but not for the person in the country<br />
town. You mentioned the word ' town'.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There is a lag.<br />
QUESTION: The producer has not been hit, or has been hit less by the<br />
Budget. The person in the country towns, the actual employee<br />
in the country towns.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm not talking about the Budget, I'm talking about the outlook<br />
in rural Australia. And when the times become prosperous farmers<br />
start to spend on deferred maintenance, replacing equipment and<br />
all the rest. They spend more in country towns. If they want<br />
to get some carpentry done, if they want an addition to a house,<br />
if they want something else improved a lot of that is work<br />
that comes out of country towns. Obviously there is a lag,<br />
but a prosperous rural Australia is reflected in prosperous<br />
rural towns, and that also has a flow through into other<br />
industries in major capital cities. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
