<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6283</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO THE CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY, CANBERRA, 2 DECEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006283.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
47-PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH TO TIHE CONFEIl I ON0 A USiTATN I1NND USTIRY, CANBERRA<br />
2 DECEMBER 1983<br />
IT (; IVES ME GREAT PLEASURE TO ADDRESS THIS, THE ANNUAL GENERAL<br />
MEETING OF THE CONFEDERATION OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY,<br />
THE CONFEDERATION HAS FOR MANY YEARS BEEN A FORCEFUL ADVOCATE<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS INTERESTS,<br />
THE PARTICIPATION BY THE CAI IN THE SUMMIT AND DON HUGHLS<br />
INVOLVEMENT IN THE EPAC HAVE BEEN ESPECIALLY APPRECIATED,<br />
THE COMMITMENT TO AND UNDERSTANDING OF CONTMPORARY AUSTRALIAN<br />
NEEDS DEMONSTRATED BY CA AND DON HUGHES PERSONALLY IN BOTH<br />
THOSE FORA HAVE CONTR: ' JTED IMPORTANTLY TO THE NATIONAL EFFORT<br />
TO ACHIEVE ECONOMIC RE2GVERY,<br />
THE CAI's CONTINUING C TRIBUTION TO PUB! IC AJWAFRENES, AND<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY DEVW -' PMENT IS AN IMFPJRTANT I: GhEbI ENT IN<br />
MY COVERNMENT'S EFFOR. T70 FORGE A NAIIONAL CONSENS1US AROUHD<br />
THE MEASURES NEEDED T. SURE SLUSTAINED ECONOMI: RECOVERY,<br />
WE MfUST BEGIN WITH THL <. cognition="" that="" evierythin65="" depends=""></.>
ON THE GOVERNMENT A) O PO! ICIE', AND SVCIJRING THU NE-[ : SARY<br />
CHANGES OF A TITUDES J! NESS ND UNINS, CHAT WIL. EN<br />
GROWTH TO BE SUSTAINE..<br />
THAT IS THE MAIN THRU' OUR POLICY EFF
OF PARTICULAR INTERES--YOUR MEMBERSHIP PAS BEEN THE<br />
APPROACH MY GOVERNMENT ADOPTING ON INDUSTRY POLICY, </p>
<p>TH.-RE A TriiRLL PRINCII AL ASPFCTS TO OU-I( J. Y Pol I( CY<br />
THl ENCOURAGEMENT OF STRONGER GROWTH, HFIE PROMtOTION OF<br />
EFFICIFNCY IN INDUSTRY AND THE DEVELOPMENT A FAIR AND<br />
EQUITABLE BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT,<br />
LET ME TAKE EACH OF THESE POINTS IN TURN,<br />
THERE IS NOW WIDESPREAD AGREEMENT HAT AUSTRAL.. IA HAS TURNED<br />
ITS BACK ON THE DISASTROUS ECONOMIC DECLINE THAT BEGAN IN<br />
1981, AND CAN LOOK FORWARD TO STRONG GROWTH IN PRODUCTION<br />
OVER THE NEXT YEAR OR SO,<br />
BUT THIS OF ITSELF, AS I HAVE SAID BEFORE, WILL NOT PROVIDE<br />
AN ANSWER TO AUSTRALIA'S ECONOMIC PROBLEMS.<br />
A<br />
THE EFFECTS OF THE STAGNATION, THE HIGH AND RISING<br />
UNEM( LOYMENT, THAT HAVE BEEN FEATURES OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
ECONOMIC LIFE OVER THE PAST DECADE, 1WILL NOT BE WIPED OUT<br />
BY A SHORT UPTURN IN LEVELS OF ACTIVITY.<br />
AUSTFRALIA NEEDS STRONG SUSTAINED AND WIDELY DISTRIBUTED<br />
GROWTH OVER A LONG PERIOD.<br />
WE HAVE TO REPLACE THE ENTRENCHED UNDFRPERFO-lrMANCF OF THE<br />
LAST DECADE WITH PERSISTENT GROWTH IN PRODUCTIVITY, ') iUTPUI<br />
AND EMPLOYMENT.<br />
THE SIGNS ARE ENCOURAGING,<br />
IHE PROSPECT AR. FOR SUR'STANTIA G( OWTH THP( H, l IRtI<br />
F INANCIAL YE/ P, </p>
<p>I H'DU~ iTHE LAi F INANC IAL YEAR THE RE AS YOU KNOW,<br />
A DECLINE IN OUIPUT.<br />
THIS YEAR'S iBU'DCET ANT IC IPA TED GROW'TH THROU( IH THE YEAR OF<br />
PER CENT IN NON-FARM PRODUCT, AND MORE IN TOTAL PRODUCT<br />
BECAUSE OF ' FHE STRENGTH OF THE FARH SF1P<br />
[ HIS TURNAROUND FROM DECLINE THiROU( GH 1982-83 TO VIGOROUS<br />
EXPANSION THROUGH 1983-84 IS REMARKABLE.<br />
A'ND ALL THE SIGNS ARE THAT THE BUJDGET FORECASTS W', ILL BF<br />
ACHIEVED AND POSSIBLY SURPASSED,<br />
IT IS PARTICULARLY STIR 1KNG THAT Et-PLOYMEN I GN) OWTH SI NCE<br />
THE SUMIMIT IN APRIL CONIT! NHES TO BtRELATIVELY STRONG AND<br />
EVERY INDICATION IS THAT THIS WILL CONTINUE IN THE YEAR . XHF-A1T'<br />
THE MOST lI-PO.-TArNT T--Ac K FOR THE GVPM2TH&gt; ER I S<br />
-0 " P, 3ADEN TH REC( OV. LR) Y A; D zUS AI ii I NIITC' li i FUTURL.<br />
THIS 11. L 1RFQOJ: RE A SCr. ON-; GRWNGIC D'S </p>
<p>IT IS MY GOVERNMENT'S FIRM VIEW THAT , TRON(, MANHiFArful I N<br />
AND SERVICE INDUSTRIES ARE NECESS'RY FOR IHE ACHIEVEMENT<br />
OF FULL EMPLOYMENT AND HIGH STANDARDS OF LIVING FOR ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS, ACHIEVE THIS NEEDS ACTION IN SEVERAL AREAS,<br />
FIRSTLY, THE RECOVERY IN ECONOMIC ACTIVITY MUST PROGRESS<br />
SMOOTHLY AND NOT BE ABORTED BY THE EMERGENCE OF BOTTLENECKS<br />
IN SPECIFIC AREAS,<br />
THIS WILL REQUIRE THAT ALL MAJOR SECTORS CONTRIBUTE TO THE<br />
CURRENT EXPANSION IN ACTIVITY,<br />
WE MUST BUILD ON THE RECOVERY NOW-BEGINNING AND ENSURE<br />
THAT IT IS BROADLY BASED AND SUSTAINABLE, RATHER THAN<br />
BASED ON ONE OR TWO SECTORS,<br />
NARROWLY BASED RECOVERIES IN THE PAST HAVE OFTEN BEEN SHORTLI<br />
VED,<br />
IN ADDITION TO THESE INDUSTRY-BASED CONCERNS, MACRO-ECONOMIC<br />
POLICIES HAVE TO BE SET TO CREATE A STABLE CLIMATE FOR<br />
INTEREST RATES, COSTS AND PRICES,<br />
WITHOUT THIS STABILITY WE COULD REPEAT ThE EXPERILINCE OF<br />
THE PAST DECADE WHERE RECOVER I -S WERE ABORTED, </p>
<p>IWITHOUT INVESTMENT THE ECONOMY CANNOT LXPERIENCE LONG<br />
PERIODS OF STRONG GROWTH.<br />
NORi CAN COMPANIES ADOPT THE INNOVATIVE APPROACH REQUIRED<br />
TO MAINTAIN COMPETITIVENESS,<br />
MY GOVERNMENT IS AWARE OF THE PARTICULAR IMPORTANCE OF<br />
INTEREST RATES TO THE BUSINESS SECTOR AND THAT INTEREST<br />
RATES ARE A SIGNIFICANT DETERMINANT OF A FIRM'S<br />
WILINGNESS TO INVEST AND EXPAND.<br />
To EASE THE POSSIBLE PRESSURE ON INTEREST RATES ARISING<br />
FRDM A LARGE PUBLIC SECTOR BORROWING REQUIR:-MENT OCCURRING<br />
AT THE SAME TIME AS PRIVATE SECTOR DEMAND FOR FUNDS RECOVERS,<br />
WE HAVE BROUGHT FORWARD MUCH OF THE'FINANCING OF THIS YEAR'S<br />
BUDGET DEFICIT TO PROVIDE FOR THE POSSIBILITY OF A<br />
RECOVERY OF PRIVATE BORROWINGS IN THE FIRST 1I'LF OF THE<br />
NE-i YEAR,<br />
AS THE PRIVATE SECTOR'S DEMAND FOR FU'DS INCREASES THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH WILL BE SFKING TO LIMIT ITS OWN nEMANDS IN<br />
THE CAPITAL MARKETS, </p>
<p>IN THE YEAR AHEAD THE , RA1E OF INFLAl ION SHOULD BE 31S( NIFICANTLY<br />
LDWER THAN IN PREVIOUS YEARS, THIS LOWERING OF THE INFLATION<br />
RATE COMES AT THE SAME TIME AS THERE ARE PRESSURES IN ; ANY<br />
OVERSLAS COUNTRIES FOR AN UPWARD MOVEMENT IN PRICES AND<br />
WILL CONTRIBUTE TO THE COMPETITIVENESS OF AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY,<br />
TO TAKE FULL ADVANTAGE OF FHE RE7' UCTION IN INFLATION, WE<br />
HAVE TO ESTABLISH A CLIMATE WHERE INFLATION AND INFLATIONARY<br />
EXPECTATIONS STAY ON A DOWNWARD PATH.<br />
IHE PRICES AND INCOME ACCORD IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE OTHER<br />
MACRO-ECONOMIC POLICIES WE HAVE ADOPTED IS THE ONLY WAY TO<br />
ACHIEVE THIS.<br />
IMPLEMtENTATION OF THE ACCORD WILL, . OF COURSE, REQUIRE THE<br />
SUPPORT OF THE WHOLE COMMUNITY.<br />
A FUNDAMENTAL PART OF THE ACCORD IS FULL COMPLIANCE WITH<br />
THE RECENTLY AN. OUNCED WAGE-SETTING PRINCIPLES OF THE<br />
ARBITRATION COMMISSION AND MODERATION IN NON-WAGE IN; COME CLAIMS.<br />
MR HOWARD'S SUGGESTION THAT A COALITION GOVERNMENT WOULD<br />
AMEND THE COMMONWEALTH CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION ACT<br />
TO PERMIT EMPLOYERS AND EMPLOYEES " TO EXCLUDE THEMSELVES<br />
FROM THE AMBIT OF THE COMMONWEALTH CONCILIATION AND<br />
ARBITRATION SYSTEM", RATHER THAN HAVING THE EFFECT OF<br />
ENSUFING COMPARATIVE WAGES JUSTICE WOULD INSTEAD MAKE<br />
ITS ACHIE'VLM; ENT VIRTUALLY IMPOSSIBLE, </p>
<p>A CENTRAL ISED SYSTEM IS ABSOLUTELY Ni CFSSARY 13O 1H1 FOR THE<br />
MAINTENANCE OF A STABLE INDUSTRIAL E-NVIRONMENT AND FOR THE<br />
PREF; ERVATION OF CONDITIONS CRITICAL TO A RAPID ECONOMIC<br />
RECOVERY. IF THE UNIONS ARE TO BE ASKED TO GIVE A ' COMMITMENT TO WAGES<br />
RESTRAINT, THEY MUST BE SECURE IN THE KNOWLEDGE THAT<br />
RESTRAINT WILL BE SHARED EQUITABLY ACROSS THE BOARD<br />
EQUALITY OF SACRIFICE UNDERPINS THE ACCORD AND IS MADE<br />
CREDIBLE THROUGH THE COMMISSION.<br />
THERE IS ALSO A NEED TO CHANGE PAST APPROACHES IN THE AREA<br />
OF INDUSTRY POLICIES.<br />
OUR POLICIES IN THIS AREA ARE DESIGNED-TO REINFORCE THE GROWTHl<br />
OF INDUSTRIES, TO IMPROVE THE EFFICIENCY OF THESE INDUSTRIES<br />
AND TO DEVELOP A FAIR AND EQUITABLE BUSINESS ENV'IRONMENT.<br />
FIRST, LET ME OUTLINE My GOVERNMENT'S POSITION WITH RESPECI<br />
TO EFFICIENCY.<br />
AS A SOCIETY AND NATIONAL ECONOMY, AUSTRALIA MUST BE MORE<br />
CAREFUL THAN IN THE PAST TO ALLOCATE RESOURCES TO THEIR<br />
MOST PRODUCTIV'E USES. </p>
<p>MY GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THE NEED FOR EFFICIENT AND<br />
COMPETITIVE INDUSTRIES,<br />
OUR GENERAL APPROACH IN THIS AREA IS TO ENCOURAGE THE<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF A COMPETITIVE ENVIRONMENT FOR FIRMS,<br />
BUT TO INTERVENE WHERE THIS IS NECESSARY TO CORRECT MARKET<br />
FAtLURF, OR TO ACHIEVE EQUITY,<br />
WE HAVE IN THE PAST FAILED TO GRASP OPPORTUNITIES TO IMPROVE<br />
ECONOMIC CONDITIONS IN AUSTRALIA AS A WHOLE BECAUSE, ON OCCASIONS,<br />
THERE HAS BEEN A SHORT-SIGHTED INSISTENCE THAT SHORT-TERM SECTIONAL<br />
INTERESTS SHOULD COME FIRST.<br />
WHILE THERE ARE MANY POINTS ON WHICH I WOULD FIND MYSELF AT<br />
ODDS WITH THE INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE { OMMISS ION, I DO AGREE<br />
WITH IT THAT:<br />
INCREASES IN REAL WEALTH, AND THUS IN THE LIVING<br />
STANDARDS OF AUSTRALIANS, DEPEND IMPORTANTLY ON<br />
ENCOURAGING THE DEVELOPMENT OF LOCAL INDUSTRIES WHICH<br />
USE THE COMMUNITY'/ S BASIC RESOURCES OF LABOURi CAPITAL<br />
AND LAND MOST EFFICIENTLY.<br />
THE EFFICIENT ALLOCATION OF RESOURCES BETWEEN INDUSTRIES<br />
REQUJIRES CHANGES IN THE TRUCTURE OF INDUSTRY AS THE<br />
ECONOMIC ENVIRONMENT CHANGES, THUS IMPROVED LIVING<br />
STANDARDS AND ECONOMIC GROWTH REQUIRE AN IND" STRY<br />
STRUCTURE WHICH HAS THE FLEXIBILITY TO RESPOND TO<br />
CHANGING ECONOMIC CIRCUMSTANCES,." </p>
<p>THI BRINGS US TO THE POINT OF ASKING, IF THESE OBJECTIVE-S<br />
ARE * TO BE REACHED, WHAT SORT OF POLICIES ARE MOST APPROPRIATE,<br />
AND IN PARTICULAR WHAT TYPE AND L[ VEL OF PROTECTION SHOULD<br />
BE AFFORDED AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY?<br />
WHILE OVER THE LONGER TERM AUSTRALIA HAS BEEN GRADUALLY REDUCING<br />
THE PROTECTION AFFORDED LOCAL PRODUCERS IN THE RECENT PAST<br />
THIS HAS BEEN REVERSED.<br />
THE IAC HAS NOTED IN ITS LATEST ANNUAL REPORT THAT THE<br />
AVERAGE EFFECTIVE RATE OF ASSISTANCE AFFORDED TO MANUFACTURING<br />
INDUSTRY INCREASED FROM 23 PER CENT IN 1977-78 TO 26 PER CENT<br />
IN 1981-82.<br />
THIS INCREASE HAS RESULTED MAINLY FROM ASSISTANCE PROVIDED<br />
BY WAY OF QUOTA PROTECTION'TO THE CLOTHING AND FOOTWEAR AND<br />
MOTOF VEHICLE INDUSTRIES,<br />
LET tIE FIRST SAY THIS MUCH: MY GOVERNMENT HAS ALREADY<br />
INDICATED THAT ! T WILL NOT REDUCE PROTECTION INDUSTRY<br />
DURING THE CURRENT ECONOMIC CRISIS,<br />
NOTWIiHSTANDING THIS, THE GOVERNMENT IS LOOKING FORWARD<br />
TO FUTURE OPPORTUNITIES TO REDUCE PROTECTION TO THE MOST<br />
HIGHLY ASSISTED INDUSTRIES IN AN ENVIRONMENT OF CONFIDENCE<br />
AND SUSTAiNEP CROWTH, </p>
<p>R).<br />
IN VIEW OF THE COSTS OF ADJUSTMENT AND DISLOCATION ASSOCIATED,<br />
WITH REDUCTIONS IN PROTECTION, ANY SUCH REDUCTIONS WILL BE<br />
INTRODUCED CAREFULLY AND GRADUALLY,<br />
A STEADY AND WELL CONSTRUCTED PROGRAM OF REDUCTIONS IN<br />
PROTECTION WILL RESULT IN SHORT TERM COSTS,<br />
HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT CONSIDERS THAT SUCH AN APPROACH.,<br />
PROPEFLY ENGINEERED, CAN MINIMISE SHORT TERM DISLOCATION.<br />
FURTHERMORE, AND MORE FUNDAMENTALLY, WE CONSIDER THAT ULTIMATELY<br />
THE LONG TERM REALITIES OF INDUSTRY PROTECTION MUST BE<br />
ADDRESS ED.<br />
THE REALITY OF PROTECTION IS THAT ALL PROTECTION INVOLVES<br />
A COST THAT MUST BE BORNE -1Y EITHER THE CONSUMER OR THE<br />
TAXPAYER, HOWEVER, THAT IS NOT THE END OF THE EQUATION.<br />
IF AUSTRALIA IS TO GRASP ITS OPPORTUNITIES IN THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL ARENA, AN EFFICIENT AND COMPETITIVE INDUSTRIAL<br />
B3ASE IS ESSENTIAL.<br />
AS I MENTrIONED RECENTLY IN BANGKOK, AUSTRALIA IS IN A<br />
UNIQUE POSITION IN THE WORLD. </p>
<p>OUR PROXIMITY TO THE GROWING MAPKETS OF ASIA AND THE<br />
PACIFIC PRESENTS THIS COUNTRY WITH ENORMOUS PROSPECTS FOR<br />
TRADE,. WHICH WOULD BENEFIT BOTH AUSTRALIA AND OUR TRADING<br />
PARTIJERS. HOWEVER, TO REALISE THIS POTENTIAL,. WE MUST MEET THE<br />
CHALLENGES THAT LIE BEFORE US,<br />
THE ONLY WAY THAT WE CAN TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THESE TRADING<br />
OPPORTUNITIES AND CONSEQUENTLY MAXIMISE OUR NATIONAL INCOME,.<br />
IS IF WE ARE PREPARED TO REDUCE PROTECTION AND ENCOURAGE<br />
OUR MOST EFFICIENT INDUSTRIES.<br />
OUR POLICIES WILL BE DESIGNED TO ENCOURAGE THE EXPANSION OF<br />
OUR MOST PRODUCTIVE INDUSTRIES AND 7O PROMOTE STRONG GROWTH<br />
IN THE PRODUCTIVITY OF ALL INDUSTRIES.<br />
THIS BRINGS ME TO THE ROLE OF NEWq TECHNOLOGY IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
THERE IS A CLEAR DISTINCTION WHICH NEEDS TO BE DRAWN BETWEEN<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF NEW TECHNOLOGY AND THE USE OF NEW TECHNOLOGY<br />
BY EXISTING INDUSTRIES,. BOTH OF WHICH HAVE AN IMPORTANT ROLE<br />
TO PLAY IN IMPROVING PRODUCTIVITY.<br />
THE U'SE OF NEW TECHNOLOGY By AuSTRALIAN INDUSTRY, AS IT<br />
BECOMES AVAILABLE, OFFERS THE POTENTIAL TO MAINTAIN INDUbFI;' kE,<br />
COMPETITIVENESS AND ALLOWS INDUSTRY TO GROW. </p>
<p>HOWEVER, NOT ONLY DOES INVESTMENT IN NEW TECHNOLOGY OFFER<br />
ADVANTAGES; FAILURE TO USE THE REST AVAILABLE TECHNOLOGY<br />
WILL PREVENT US FROM ENJOYING THE IENEFITO" IN TERMS OF<br />
HIGHER LIVING STANDARDS THAT THIS TECHNOLOGY OFFERS,<br />
WHILE LARGE INVESTMENTS WILL BE REQUIRED TO ADOPT NEW<br />
TECHNOLOGY, WITHOUT THAT INVESTMENT, B USINESS COMPETITIVENESS<br />
WILL SUFFER, INDUSTRIES WILL STAGNATE, AND THE NATION WILL<br />
BE DEPRIVED OF THE BENEFITS OF ECONOMIC GROWTH BROUGHT ABOUT<br />
BY THE EMERGENCE OF NEW INDUSTRIES AND THE REVITALISATION OF<br />
EXISTING INDUSTRIES.<br />
THERE IS NO REAL ALTERNATIVE TO STAYING ABREAST OF NEW/<br />
TECHNOLOSY ABROAD.<br />
OBVIOUSLY THE GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THAT THERE ARE PROBLEMS<br />
ASSOCIATED WITH THE USE OF NEW TECHNOLOGY,<br />
THE INTRCDUCTION OF SUCH TECHNOLOGY MAY LEAD To DIRECT DISPLACEMENT<br />
OF LABOUR.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME HOWEVER, WE MUST RECOGNISE THE POSITIVE AND<br />
D'JRECT IM'? ACT ON EMPLOYMENT GENERATED BY THE DEVELOPMENT<br />
AND INTRODUCTION OF NEW TECHNOLOGY.<br />
THE GROWTH IN REAL INCOME ASSOCIATED WITH TECHNOLOGICAL<br />
CHANGE AND THE ASSOCIATED ECONOMIC GROWTH SHOULD IMPROVE THE OVERALL<br />
DEMIAND FOR LABOUR, </p>
<p>13,<br />
DEMAND WILL ALSO BE STIMULATED BY THE PROSPECTS OF REAL<br />
PRICE REDUCTIONS BROUGHT ABOUT BY THE IMPROVEMENT TO<br />
EFFICIENCY ASSOCIATED WITH NEW TECHNOLOGY.<br />
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW TECHNOLOGY NEEDS TO OCCUR IN A<br />
BALANCED MANNER, AND FOLLOWING CONSULTATION BETWEEN<br />
EMPLOYERS, UNIONS AND GOVERNMENT,<br />
IN THIS WAY THE BENEFITS FROM THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW<br />
TECHNDLOGY AND THE SOCIAL COSTS ASSOCIATED WITH THE<br />
CHANGE ARE MOST LIKELY TO BE ACCOMMODATED.<br />
IN ADDITION TO INDUSTRY TAKING FULL ADVANTAGE OF AVAILABLE<br />
TECHNOLOGY, THERE IS A PLACE FOR INNOVATIVE AUSTRALIAN<br />
FIRMS TO CAPITALISE ONNEW DISCOVERIES AND APPLICATIONS<br />
TO BUILD FOR THEMSELVES A NICHE IN THE EXPANDING MARKET<br />
FOR HIGH TECHNOLOGY PRODUCTS,<br />
THE GCVERNMENT RECOGNISES THE NATIONAL BENEFITS OF THE<br />
EMERGENCE OF VIGOROUS, COMPETITIVE, HIGH TECHNOLOGY<br />
INDUSTRIES IN TERMS OF STIMULATING GROWTH AND HAS MOVED<br />
TO ASSIST THESE INDUSTRIES, </p>
<p>PERHAP S THE MOST IMPORTANT FORM OF SUCH ASSISTANCE IS<br />
THE E[ COURAGEMENT TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF A VENTURE CAPITAL<br />
MARKET it-AUSTRALIA TO FUND THESE HIGH RISK VENTURES.<br />
THiIs BRINGS ME TO THE LAST ASPEC-T OF OUR INDUSTRY POLICY:<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF A FAIR AND EQUITABLE BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT,<br />
ONE PARTICULAR FEATURE OF OUR POLICY FRAMEWORK IS DIRECTED<br />
TOWARDS SMALL BUSINESS.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THAT SMALL ENTERPRISES PLAY A VITAL<br />
ROLE IN GENERATING INVESTMENT AND EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES,<br />
IN PROMOTING COMPETITION AND IN PROVIDING THE MEANS FOR<br />
ENTRY INTO BUSINESS OF NEW ENTREPRENEURIAL TALENT,<br />
THIS GOVERNMENT ALSO RECOGNISES.. HOWEVER, THAT SMALL FIRMS<br />
MAY BE PLACED AT A DISADVANTAGE PURELY BECAUSE OF THEIR<br />
SMALL SIZE.<br />
ADDRESS THIS PROBLEM, WE HAVE ACTED TO INCREASE THE<br />
AVAILABILITY OF FINANCE FOR SMALL FIRMS,<br />
BOTH THE COMMONWEALTH DEVELOPMENT BANK AND THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
I\ DUSTRY DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION HAVE BEEN GIVEN GREATER<br />
SCOPE TO BORROW FUNDS FOR ON-LENDING TO FIRMS, </p>
<p>151<br />
IN ADDITION, THE NATIONAL COMPANIES AND SECHRITIES COMMISSION<br />
IS CURRENTLY CONSIDERING A PROPOSAL FOR AN OVER-THECOUNTER<br />
MARKET FOR UNLISTED SHARES IN SMALL PUBLIC COMPANIES.<br />
FOR THE GoVERNMENT'S PART WE ARE MOVING TO IMPROVE COMMUNICATION<br />
BETWEEN THE SMALL BUSINESS SECTOR AND THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
WE ARE KEEN TO ENSURE THAT WE RECEIVE ADVICE FROM PEOPLE<br />
WORKING IN SMALL FIRMS ON SOLUTIONS WHICH ARE APPROPRIATE<br />
TO CURRENT PROBLEMS EXPERIENCED BY SMALL BUSINESS.<br />
THE APPOINTMENT OF A REPRESENTAT! VE FROM SMALL BUSINESS TO<br />
EPACJ REPRESENTS THE ESTABLISHMENT OF AN IMPORTANT CHANNEL<br />
OF COMMUNICATION BETWEEN SMALL BUSINESS AND GOVERNMENT,<br />
ON ThE MORE GENERAL ISSUE OF EQUITY, THE GOVERNMENT HAS JUST<br />
COMPLETED A REVIEW OF CERTAIN PARTS OF THE TRADE PRACTICES ACT.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT HAS UNDERTAKEN THIS REVIEW FOLLOIUNG<br />
CRITICISMS OF PARTS FOUR AND FIVE OF THE ACT A, IT CURRENTLY<br />
STANDS., AND IN THE BELIEF THAT ALL MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY<br />
SHOULD BE PROTECTED FROM MISUSE OF MARKET POWER.<br />
HOWEVER, WE ARE CONCERNED TO ENSURE THAT THE PROVISIONS<br />
OF ii4E ACT SHOULD NOT STIFLE HEALTHY COMPETITION NOR INVOLV<br />
DROHIEITIVE COMPLIANCE COSTS. </p>
<p>WE PROPOSE TO RELEASE BEFORE THE END OF THE YEIAR AN EXPOSURE<br />
DRAFT TO ELICIT PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE PROVISIONS OF AN AMENDING<br />
B ILL.<br />
YOU WOULD APPRECIATE THAT IN PROCEEDING THIS WAY THE GOVERNMENT<br />
IS INTERESTED IN THE WIDEST POSSIBLE CONSULTATION WITH INTERESTED<br />
PARTIES. THE EXPOSURE DRAFT OFFERS A SPECIFIC BASIS UPON WHICH COMMEINTS<br />
CAN BE DEVELOPED.<br />
My GOVERNMENT' S AIM, AT LEAST IN PART, IS TO ENSURE THE<br />
MAINTENANCE OF COMPETITIVE MARKETS BY PROHIBITING UNFAIR<br />
BUSINESS PRACTICES.<br />
WAE BELIEVE THAT FAIR COMPtTITION IS ESSENTIAL IF EFFICIENT<br />
FIRMS, WHICH COULD BE THREATENED BY LESS EFFICIENT BUT<br />
MORE POWERFU4 COMPETITORS, ARE TO SURVIVE,<br />
IN CONCLUJSION, LET ME STRESS THAT NONE OF THE THREE ASPECTS<br />
CF THE GoVERNMENT'S INDUSTRY POI ICY CAN ALONE PRODUCE A<br />
PANACEA FO0R OUR INDUSTRY PROBLEMS.<br />
PIDREOVER, GOVERNMENTS ACTING IN ISOLATION CANNOT HOPE TO<br />
ACHIEVE THE NECESSARY CLIMATE FOR INDUJSTRY DEVELOPMENT, </p>
<p>17,<br />
TO BE A SUCCESS, INDUSTRY POLICY REQUIRES COMMITMENT AND<br />
CO-OPERATION FROM GOVERNMENTS, EMPLOYERS AND UNIONS.<br />
THE CHALLENGE IS TO DEVELOP A COMPETITIVE INDUSTRY WHICH<br />
WILL CONTRIBUTE TO THE IMPROVEMENT OF OUR STANDARDS OF LIVING<br />
AND TO A STRONG AND PROSPEROUS AUSTRALIA,<br />
LET US JOIN TOGETHER IN MEETING THIS CHALLENGE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
