<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7096</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH ANNE MCCAIG, 2WA, FOR STEVE RAYMONDS SHOW, 31 JANUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007096.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH ANNE-MCCAIG, -2WS, FOR STEVE-RAYMOND'S<br />
SHOW, 31 JANUARY 1987<br />
-ONLY----<br />
MCCAIG: Prime Minister your love for Israel goes back many years. What is<br />
. it about that country tha's capture your at-tentioh?<br />
-PM: Well it's a complex of reasons. I suppose-like very very many people<br />
around the world part of it and a large and immeasurable part was the<br />
sense of shared guilt that I had that the world had allowed the<br />
annihilation of 6 million Jews in the Holocaust. And in a way we all share<br />
share some sense of responsibility. And then I understood that the world<br />
had made the decision in the immediate post war period that the Jews were<br />
entitled to have a Land, a state of their own. Australia had played a<br />
leading role in that decision through Doctor Evatt in 1947. And then when<br />
I went there the world to a very large extent was standing fairly mutely<br />
by while they witnessed the attempts of states around Israel to destroy it<br />
And here was a democracy, as you saw it on your visit there,<br />
a remarkable democracy for instance which at that very time when its<br />
destruction was being threatened by force of Soviet arms supplied to<br />
others, allowed as part of its democratic process a Soviet oriented<br />
Communist Party. A vibrant democracy, not without its problems, not<br />
without its weaknesses. But for all those reasons I had this committment.<br />
But at all times from the beginning my views about Israel have been in<br />
association with a view that is my party's.-nd what the<br />
government's platform says, will require also a proper resolution of the<br />
problem of the Palestinians. So my love of the Israelis as you put it<br />
has not been exclusive of a concern for the rights of others.<br />
MCCAIG: You began this trip in Jordan and said you were convinced after<br />
meeting King Hussein of his committment to a peaceful solution. Did that<br />
visit change your perceptions of the Arab-Israeli conflict?<br />
PM: No. I think the right way of saying it is it reinforced the feelings<br />
I had because you'll appreciate I'd had the opportunity of going to<br />
Jordan in ' 78 and ' 80. I hadn't had the opportunity of meeting the King<br />
because on both those occasions he wasn't in the country but I'd had the<br />
long meetings with his brother the Crown Prince Hassan. So what the<br />
meeting with the King and Prime Minister did was to confirm the<br />
perceptions I had then but of course on this. occasion to hear in such<br />
strong language from the King and Prime Minister that committment was<br />
important. I guess the significant part of it was that it wasn't just<br />
a desire for some formal peace settlement. What they want to see is a<br />
peace settlement out of which can come constructive economic co operation<br />
between Israel and Jordan.<br />
MCCAIG: When you went to Jerusalem after your talks in Jordan did you<br />
get the impression from the Israelis that they are any closer to peace?<br />
PM: I t<br />
ycBo^ newSf Sl ict a Jordan and Israet. share the view that the possibility of<br />
Co~ L thi ey both share the<br />
_ V I uO , J -h </p>
<p>PM: ( cont'd)<br />
Thiere are obviously differences of view between Jordan and Israel and to<br />
sc,, te extent within Israel as to how those processes should be pursued<br />
bit I think they are both committed to getting workable processes.<br />
MOCAIG: The other major problem is just what happens to the<br />
Palestinian people. You said in Jerusalem that recognition by Israel and<br />
the of each other under certain conditions was a very<br />
important building block in the work towards peace. Given your own<br />
knowledge of the area and your personal interest, aren't you well placed<br />
to kick off that process in a sense by speaking to PLO officials?<br />
PM: Neither I nor the government woutld negotiate with the P. L. O. while<br />
the-P-7L-. 0.-main ta-irns-its-pr-es-enitofftctai pos itionr. Wha-t--Ve--b-e-ewsayi-nwis<br />
that I think a part of the process of effecting the ultimate<br />
resolution of the Israeli-Arab dispute is to translate what I think are<br />
the facts into a formal statement of those-facts. By that-I mean that<br />
-I believe that however reluctantly it is,-that I-think the leadership of<br />
* the P. L. O. understands-now as distinct from say in the 70' s that Israel<br />
is here to stay. And on the other hand I think that Israel recognises<br />
that there is a representativeness or representative capacity in the<br />
P. L. O. So what I'm saying is that I think it would be useful if you could<br />
get a situation where the P. L. O. translated what I think is a fact<br />
into a public statement of that fact. That would require acceptance of<br />
242 and 338 resolutions of the United Nations. Secondly and implicitly<br />
that follows from the first, the recognition of Israel and third, the<br />
repudiation of terrorism. And in response to that it would then be the<br />
obligation to say well in those circumstances we would treat in the<br />
overall direct negotiations with the P. L. O. as part of that process.<br />
MCCAIG: It would be politically difficult though wouldn't it, for either<br />
party to accept the other?<br />
PM: Well what I'm saying is that in a factual sense they both<br />
recognise the reality of each other. They don't like it but they<br />
recognise that they are there. Now what Ic&amp;' saying is that it just seems<br />
to me to be useful if that sort of fact of the recognition of each other<br />
could be translated under appropriate conditions into a formal<br />
statement. That of itself is not going to solve the problem, but it seems<br />
to me that it would be useful part of creating the necessary building<br />
block for a solution.<br />
But let me say in that... one has to take into account not only the<br />
considerations and interests of Israel vis a vis the P. L. O. but also the<br />
interests of Jordan because Jordan has its concerns about the P. L. O. as<br />
you'll appreciate.<br />
MOCAIG: In Jerusalem you met Palestinians... and they referred to the<br />
oppressive conditions faced by refugees on the t<br />
West Bank. Would it have helped your understanding to visit a refugee camp<br />
PM: Well I have in fact visited a refugee camp.-<br />
MCCAIG: As Prime Minister though?<br />
PM: Not as Prime Minister. I'm aware of the camps and. the problems and<br />
as you know I'm sympathetic to the problems of the Palestinian people<br />
you know fully sympathetic.<br />
So you know I didn't need a visit to, I think, increase that<br />
understanding. And what I said to the Palestinian repres; entatives I spoke<br />
to is that if they wanted to convey details to us, we would look at them<br />
and undertake to convey them to the Israeli authorities. / 3 I </p>
<p>9 a<br />
* MC ATG: It would have been a gesture though.<br />
PM: Well I don't think that the processes that we're talking about<br />
are processes of gestures. I think you would have found if you<br />
talked to the four Palestinians that I spoke to, that they had no<br />
question in their mind about my understanding of their problems.<br />
MCCAIG: Mr Hawke, Switzerland. If I can switch to the<br />
conference in Davos. Is there any joy for Australian farmers in<br />
your international trade proposals to break down protection?<br />
PM: Well there is if they were accepted and acted upon. But I think<br />
my friends in the Australian farming community know that they resolution<br />
of these matters is not something that's going to happen overnight.<br />
There's goi-ng to-be protracted discussions and negotiations involved.<br />
But I was pleased at the reaction I got to my proposals. I think you saw<br />
it was very widespread approbation of the speech and the proposals.<br />
so all I can hope is that that will serve to accelerate the processes of<br />
discussion. There are two strands if you like. There's now has been<br />
concluded in th'ese last few days in Geneva the formal arrangements,<br />
the administrative arrangements for getting the G. A. T. T. round, the<br />
Uruguay round, going. And so there'll be protracted negotiations there.<br />
What we hope is that the proposals I put may provide some basis<br />
for more immediate moves because not only can Australian farmers afford<br />
to wait, but in a real sense the world can't afford to wait for the more<br />
protracted negotiations under the G. A. T. T. round for any progress.<br />
We certainly look to those rounds for final resolutions of difficulties,<br />
but it's in everyone's interests that there should be some more<br />
immediate steps.<br />
MCCAIG: Finally, Prime Minister, I suppose it will be some time before<br />
you take another overseas trip because we have to go to the polls<br />
within the next 14 or 15 months. Will the election be sooner rather than<br />
later. Have you thought of a date?<br />
PM: I've got no reason to change wha-t I've said several times in<br />
Australia before I left... and that is the government will go its full<br />
term and that means as I've said, an electi'n some time in the<br />
period from the end of ' 87 into the early part of 88.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
