<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7417</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR HER MAJESTY QUEEN BEATRIX OF THE NEATHERLANDS CANBERRA -25 OCTOBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007417.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR HER MAJESTY<br />
QUEEN BEATRIX OF THE NETHERLANDS<br />
CANBERRA 25 OCTOBER 1986<br />
Your Majesty,<br />
Your Royal Highness,<br />
Distinguished Guests,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
I know, Your Majesty, that this is not your first visit to<br />
Australia. However, it is your first visit as Queen of the<br />
Netherlands and indeed this is the first time the reigning<br />
monarch of the Netherlands has ever visited our shores.<br />
I am, therefore, delighted to extend to you and to Prince<br />
Claus a very warm welcome as our guest in our Bicentennial<br />
year. Your visit is a significant reaffirmation of the close and<br />
warm friendship between our two countries.<br />
Coming on top of the Netherlands' involvement in many of the<br />
Bicentennial activities including the Parade of Tall<br />
Ships, the International Naval Salute, the Bicentennial Air<br />
Show and, here in Canberra, the generous Dutch participation<br />
in the Floriade your visit is also a timely recognition of<br />
the hundreds of thousands of Dutch men and women who have<br />
come to Australia to make their new home here.<br />
I am sure that you will both be warmly welcomed by all<br />
Australians as you travel around this country and no doubt<br />
you will be greeted with special enthusiasm by the<br />
Dutch-Australian community. I<br />
Australians are of course proud in our Bicentennial year to<br />
celebrate the achievements of the last two centuries, and to<br />
acknowledge our enormous debt to those who have built our<br />
democratic and prosperous society.<br />
But today we are particularly'aware that Dutch links with<br />
this continent extend back nearly another two centuries<br />
before the arrival of the First Fleet in 1788.<br />
The first Dutch contact with Australia was that of William<br />
Jansz in the vessel " Duyfken" in 1605. 2327 </p>
<p>Thanks in large part to the efforts of the Dutch United East P<br />
India Company, Australia's maps still bear testimony to the<br />
pioneering role of the Dutch navigators in exploring our<br />
coastline. Y( Di<br />
Indeed the whole continent was known for many years to the<br />
rest of the world as New Holland surely a title based more i<br />
on optimistic patriotism on the part of the Dutch sailors a<br />
than an objective observation of this large, dry and g<br />
occasionally mountainous continent. A,<br />
Dirk Hartog in the " Eendracht" left his famous pewter plate T<br />
fixed to a wooden pole on Cape Inscription in 1616. That e<br />
plate is currently touring Australia in the ' Shipwrecks' S<br />
Exhibition and we are most grateful to the generosity of the<br />
Netherlands' famous Rijksmuseum for. lending us a piece of C<br />
our shared history which is known to every Australian 0<br />
schoolchild. e<br />
The State of Tasmania bears the name of Abel Tasman who I<br />
sighted the western coast of the island in 1642. wi<br />
Two mountains in Tasmania have been named after Tasman'sr<br />
ships, " Heemskirk' and " Zeehan". I am delighted that youT<br />
will be able to unveil a fountain commemorating Tasman's T<br />
visit on Thursday during your visit to Hobart. P1 A<br />
Your Majesty, if the seventeenth century was the first 0<br />
period of Dutch contact with New Holland it was by no means A<br />
the only one. ei<br />
Because in this century, the people of Australia and the<br />
Netherlands fought and died together in defence of their<br />
common goals of democracy, freedom, tolerance and opposition t<br />
to totalitarianism. r<br />
And in the years after the Second World War, in a great<br />
surge of immigration, Australia was enriched by the arrival<br />
of large numbers of men and women from the Netherlands.<br />
Dutch Australians remain proud of their heritage. Indeed,<br />
more than 150,000 Australians identify themselves as of<br />
exclusively Dutch descent and more than 60,000 speak Dutch<br />
at home. within our multicultural society that does not<br />
make them any less Australian. They have through their<br />
enormous contributions to the building of our nation, proved<br />
beyond doubt their commitment and loyalty to their new home.<br />
The contribution of the Dutch to Australia covers a broad<br />
spectrum, including especially in the arts: the film<br />
director, Paul Cox whose most recent film honors Vincent van<br />
Gogh; the artistic director of the Dance Company ofNew<br />
South Wales, Jaan Flier; the director of the MildurA Art<br />
Gallery, Ernst van Hattum; to name a few.<br />
The older generation will certainly remember the radio<br />
comedian known as " Mo" who made a tremendous contribution to<br />
the development of Australian comedy in the first half of<br />
this century. His real name was Harry van der Sluys.<br />
2-. 928 </p>
<p>3.<br />
only this week, Victorians have been thrilled by the great<br />
performance of the famous Dutch cycli'st Adrie van der Poe1<br />
who won the Victorian Sun Tour.:<br />
Your Majesty, as well as the warm relat'ionship based on the<br />
Dutch community, Australia enjoys a close bilateral<br />
relationship with the Netherlands stemming from the historic<br />
involvement of both countries in the Asian/ Pacific Region,<br />
and the economic and commercial role of the Netherlands as a<br />
growing investor in Australia and as an entrepot. centre for<br />
Australian exports to Europe.<br />
The determination and adventurousne ss of the early Dutch<br />
explorers, who discovered Australia by-chance in their<br />
search for trading opportunities, can-provide a lesson today<br />
for Australia and the Netherlands. in the new trading<br />
circumstances of the late twentieth century there is the<br />
opportunity for Australia and the Netherlands to discover<br />
each other again, to the mutual benefit of both countries.<br />
In 1987 the value of exports to the Netherlands stood at<br />
$ A620 million and the value of Dutch exports to Australia<br />
was $ A560 million. This is a substantial economic<br />
relationship, but we can do more.<br />
Traditionally our trade relationship has involved Australian<br />
primary products such as coal and foodstuffs. Today we in<br />
Australia are convinced that we also have other things to<br />
offer in particular, as the spectacular growth of the<br />
Asia-Pacific region continues, I would particularly<br />
encourage Dutch businesspeople to pay regard to the<br />
investment potential of Australia.<br />
We have much to offer, both in our own right and as an entry<br />
to the markets of our region: our stable, political<br />
environment, our efficient financial system, our abundant<br />
natural resources, our well qualified reservoir of technical<br />
and professional expertise, and our highly competitive tax<br />
structure.<br />
The potential Australia provides for European countries<br />
looking for a springboard into the lucrative and developing<br />
financial and trading centres of this region cannot be<br />
overemphasised, for Australia has excellent relations with<br />
the countries of the region.<br />
The Australian Government is keenly interested in the single<br />
market process in Europe. Already, the European Community,<br />
taken as a whole, ranks as our second largest export market<br />
and our largest source of imports.<br />
The development of a single market with 320 million<br />
inhabitants a market larger than any other in the<br />
industrialised world will surely have a profound impact on<br />
global economic and trading relationships. 292P . </p>
<p>At the same time, Australia strongly believes that the<br />
positive rewards of the single European market, which is to<br />
be achieved by 1992, will not be reaped if an inward<br />
looking, " fortress Europe" approach is allowed to develop<br />
but I am confident that this will not eventuate.<br />
Your Majesty, the range of areas on which I have spoken<br />
clearly demonstrates the warmth and closeness in the<br />
relationship between the people of our countries.<br />
Already your visit is adding a new dimension to that<br />
friendship. I would like to give you our special thanks for<br />
agreeing to lend your name to the establishment in Canberra<br />
of the Queen Beatrix Floriade Sculpture Collection. This<br />
c6llection will not only reflect your personal interest in<br />
sculpture, it will also provide Canberra's young sculptors<br />
with a valuable opportunity to contribute to the aesthetic<br />
development of the nation's capital.<br />
I again welcome you, His Highness Prince Claus and your most<br />
distinguished party to Australia and wish you a most<br />
enjoyable visit.<br />
2930 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
