<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24202</transcript-id>
    <title>Copenhagen terror attack</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Government condemns the shooting at a free speech event in Copenhagen overnight.</p>
<p>The thoughts of all Australians are with the people of Denmark and, in particular, the family of the victim who lost his life and the police officers injured in this brutal act of terror.</p>
<p>As with the Charlie Hebdo atrocity in Paris, the Copenhagen attack is an affront to one of our most fundamental values – freedom of speech. We stand with the people and government of Denmark in confronting this cynical attempt to undermine that fundamental right.</p>
<p>There are reports several other people have been injured in a separate shooting incident near a synagogue in Copenhagen. Danish authorities have not yet established whether this is related to the earlier attack.</p>
<p>Denmark is a partner in the international coalition that is working to disrupt, degrade and ultimately defeat the Islamist death cult in Iraq and Syria. Recent attacks such as those in Copenhagen and Paris will only strengthen our resolve to combat ISIL, or Daesh, and the evil it represents.</p>
<p>Here in Australia, the Government will continue to do all it can to defend our way of life and protect our community from terrorism.</p>
<p>Our National Terrorism Alert level remains at High, which means a terrorist attack is likely.</p>
<p>All Australians should remain vigilant, and I urge people who see or hear something that they feel is not right to contact the National Security Hotline immediately on 1800 123 400.</p>
<p>15 February 2015</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
