<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1370</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE TOWNSVILLE ARMY BARRACKS, TOWNSVILLE, QUEENSLAND - 29TH JULY 1966 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/07/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001370.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF THE TO01ASVILLE ARMY BARRACKS<br />
TOWSVILLE, QUEENSLAND 29TH JULY, 1966<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
Major-General Mr. Premier, my Ministerial Colleague, Chief of<br />
the General Staff, Mr. Mayor, Parliamentarians, Ladies and<br />
Gentlemen and all distinguished guests assembled here today:<br />
This, as I said this morning at the first of the three<br />
functions which are making my day in Townsville such a memorable<br />
one for me, is a very happy occasion. Here we have symbolised<br />
in this morning's ceremony a great new university; the first<br />
university in the tropics of Australia. And now here this<br />
afternoon we have what my colleague the Minister for the Army<br />
has just described to you in some ietail as the outstanding<br />
military establishment tD be set up in Australia, with Townsville<br />
as its home. I think Townsville can claim itself fortunate to have<br />
achieved this quite remarkable double. It is said that the pen<br />
is mightier than the sword and I suppose that argument still<br />
continues. Well Townsville has both, and Australia neeas both.<br />
I don't know whether over the long period of years<br />
ahead, the University of Townsville will estalish itself as<br />
dominant over the military establishment. I suspect there will<br />
be encounters of an enterprising kind occasionally between the<br />
inhabitants of one establishment and the inhabitants of the other.<br />
But I hope nothing occurs which would be contrary to good order<br />
and discipline in either of these major establishments we are<br />
setting up here in this great Townsville area, the show place of<br />
the northern tropic part of Australia.<br />
This in a way symbolises what is going on throughout<br />
the Commwnwealth at this time. You and I can consider ourselves<br />
fortunate, I believe, to be living in our country in a period in<br />
which it is going through an exciting phase of development and<br />
national progress. Included in that progress has been the necessity<br />
to give greater emphasis to potentialities of the northern part of<br />
Ausiralia. Historically, and for various economic reasons, the<br />
development of the south has proceeded to a greater extent, but we<br />
recognise that if this continent is to be held secure, if we are<br />
to 4evelop its potentialities then we must press on vigorously<br />
with northern development. What could more clearly express that<br />
determination than these two major establishments, one in the<br />
academic field and the other in that of military security.<br />
Now, the Queenslander, and in particular the Northern<br />
Queenslander, has always been more conscious of the defence needs<br />
of Australia than people in any other part of the Commonwealth,<br />
and this proceeds, no doubt, from your geographical position. Y3u<br />
are more conscious and sensitive to the fact that you are close to<br />
the danger areas of the north. It is much the same distance from<br />
Saigon lo Darwin, for example as it is from Brisbane to Perth<br />
and those who live in the northern part of Australia realise tAeir<br />
proximity to the danger spots of Asia. And so it is appropriate<br />
that there should be established here in this northern city of<br />
Australia a modern, large, military establishment.<br />
You may be interested to know Mr. Premier, if you<br />
haven't already been told this, that the decision to establish a base<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
here was not primarily a military decision. In fact, I can perhaps<br />
for once be forgiven if I publicily narrate a military secret,<br />
But the military advice to us when it became necessary as a result<br />
of the expansion to which the Minister for the Army has referrel<br />
to set up nemlitary bases the military advice which reached<br />
us was tat this shoulid be done in the Mornington Peninsula of<br />
Victoria. There were some good technical reasons for that, and<br />
it facilitated co-operation with other services and it wastprobably<br />
a considerably cheaper way of getting the military result tan a<br />
decision to establish a militarybshe. Buwenecaet<br />
consider this in Cabinet, we felt that there were other factors<br />
which outweighed the purely military cnsiderations the development<br />
of the north the security Of he north, the fact that the<br />
people of the north had a right to feel that in their area of the<br />
worl bi 7 things wore moving which were contributing to the growth<br />
of Australia. These were some of the considerations which came<br />
into our minds when we considered the technical problems. And<br />
so the decision was taken, and I am sure it was a decision we in<br />
Australia will never regret. Certainly Townsville will never<br />
regret it because it will bring to your community joining the<br />
other members of the Australian Services already here a<br />
substantial community of people. For the most part, they will be<br />
young, lively and vigorous people with their families, and they<br />
will undoubtedly add to the diversity and richness of the community<br />
life of Townsvil le.<br />
In terms of trade, looking at these thing,, s in an<br />
economic sense, undoubtedly this will add to the population in<br />
a considerable way because there will be those comihg to the<br />
district who service the people who are in a military establishment.<br />
This is a cumulative process whereby the needs of one<br />
have to be satisfied by the services and activities of others.<br />
And so you will find a secondary growth for Townsville from the<br />
establishment of the barracks here.<br />
But today we think beyond that to the contribution<br />
which this barracks and the people w~ ho will be mann ing it make to<br />
the future of Australia. We have, as I stressed this morning,<br />
only a small population in this vast continent. So we must<br />
contrive as best we can that the people of Australia are people<br />
of quality, are people fully trained for the tasks which t hey<br />
are to per{ orm and that they manifest inside Australia and<br />
out of it the ; est characteristics which we believe make up the<br />
Australian temperament. And in what better environment for<br />
these purposes could young men be trained in the service of<br />
Australia than in this sunny, stimulating, invigorating atmosphere<br />
that they have here in Townsville.<br />
Now, it is part of my duty today to gve a name to<br />
these barracks. gave a -reat deal of careful thoughttohi<br />
because this in itself is a 0contribution to morale and enthusiasm<br />
that develops in a partictlar military venue. When we discussed<br />
the problem, we thought what could be more fittin than that we<br />
should select the name of a very distinguished Queenslander, a<br />
great fighting soldier and more than that, a great fighting_<br />
administrator. These barracks will be named after a native-born<br />
Queenslander who reached the highest level open to him in<br />
Australian military service. He became ChiefI of the General Staff<br />
and later Chairman of the Chiefs of Staff Committee, the highest<br />
body in the military services of this country. From there, having<br />
g iven distinguished military service, both fightin service in<br />
time of war and this service of leadership and1adm inistration in<br />
a period of peace, he became the first Australian-born Governor a* / 3 </p>
<p>5<br />
of the State of Queensland. And so it is with pride, and great<br />
satisfaction, that I name these barracks Lavarack Barracks, after<br />
Sir John Lavarack, the former Chairman of the Chiefs of Staff<br />
Committee, and the former Governor of your State. I am sure it is<br />
a choice you will all applaud.<br />
And now as I proceed to the formal task of unveiling<br />
the plaque which will name the barracks, may I on behalf of mself<br />
and my colleagues of the hovernment, congratulate all those who<br />
have played a part in promoting this great project, the work of the<br />
Minister and his colleagues in the Army, the co-operation which<br />
we have received, and for which we are suitably appreciative, from<br />
you Mr. Premier and from you Mr. Mayor. This eamwork is<br />
enali ng the wor here to go aead expeitiously and satisfactorily.<br />
I only hope that I will be aoble to come back year by year and see<br />
the progress which will have been made both here and at the<br />
university. It will be a constant attraction to be added to the<br />
many others I feel in the pull that North Queensland makes to me<br />
when I am in the south.<br />
Thanking you for your co-operation, I conclude with<br />
my best wishes to all who serve in this establishment. May<br />
Lavarack Barracks make a permanent contribution to the security<br />
of Australia to the morale of Australian military forces, and may<br />
it earn for itself a reputation of pride which will mark it out<br />
amongst the great military establishments of the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
