<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10957</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS AT HOLDEN&amp;#146;S 50TH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION                SOCIAL CENTRE, PORT MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much, Bill; to the Premier, Jeff Kennett; to the</p>
<p>   Lord Mayor, Jim Wiemels; my other parliamentary colleagues; ladies</p>
<p>   and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Nineteen forty eight, no, I had gone beyond the embryo stage but</p>
<p>   was the nine year old son of a garage proprietor whose main passion</p>
<p>   in life then was to survive in business long enough to see the end</p>
<p>   of petrol rationing and, of course, therefore, someone who grew</p>
<p>   up in a home in which cars were talked about a lot. And I'm</p>
<p>   very happy to say, given the nature of the occasion, that the longest</p>
<p>   owned vehicle in the Howard household  that is the John and</p>
<p>   Janette Howard household  was indeed a 1980 Commodore station</p>
<p>   wagon, purchased at time when the respective ages of our children</p>
<p>   were six, three and minus two months. And we owned that vehicle</p>
<p>   for 16 years and it did absolutely marvellous service, first as</p>
<p>   the family car and then as the second vehicle in which some of the</p>
<p>   learner drivers began to negotiate the roads of Sydney.</p>
<p>So from those remarks it's a suggestion of the kind of occasion</p>
<p>   this is. It's a mixture of pride and nostalgia but also a recognition</p>
<p>   in the way in which this remarkable company and its remarkable products</p>
<p>   have touched the lives of so many Australians. There can barely</p>
<p>   be a family in Australia that at one stage or another has not garaged</p>
<p>   a Holden vehicle. There can barely be anybody who doesn't have</p>
<p>   some recollection of a connection with one of the products of this</p>
<p>   remarkable company.</p>
<p>We celebrate a lot of things today. We celebrate the farsightedness</p>
<p>   of those involved with the company so many years ago and particularly</p>
<p>   the launch of the first Holden 50 years ago today. We celebrate,</p>
<p>   of course, a very important constant in the life of Australia both</p>
<p>   in 1948 and in 1998 and that is the ongoing association between</p>
<p>   our nation and the United States of America. We reflect with gratitude</p>
<p>   on the commitment of those who invested so much of their energy</p>
<p>   and their skill in the production of that first vehicle. We acknowledge</p>
<p>   the leadership displayed by the Prime Minister of the day, Ben Chifley,</p>
<p>   and others around him. Nineteen forty eight was a period in which</p>
<p>   Australia was still burdened by many wartime regulations but was</p>
<p>   lifting its eyes to a brighter and more optimistic future. The world</p>
<p>   has changed incalculably over that period of 50 years and so has</p>
<p>   Australia and in so many ways for the better but not in a fashion</p>
<p>   that we reject so many of the things that were valuable then and</p>
<p>   they continue to be valuable today. And an occasion such as this</p>
<p>   reminds us of so many of the threads in our national life that continue</p>
<p>   to be very strong and continue to be just as relevant now as they</p>
<p>   were 50 years ago.</p>
<p>We reflect with gratitude on those 50 years but we also, quite</p>
<p>   properly, look towards the future. And there can barely be, in the</p>
<p>   history of our country, a more exciting time to be alive and to</p>
<p>   be in some way in charge of events and affairs wherever we may be</p>
<p>   in this country of ours and right now. We are at the moment on the</p>
<p>   verge of celebrating some of the most momentous events in our history.</p>
<p>   We are to be showcased to the world again with the 2000 Olympic</p>
<p>   Games. We have extraordinary economic opportunities, particularly</p>
<p>   in our region. We are a quite remarkable intersection of culture</p>
<p>   and of history and geography in this part of the world. And the</p>
<p>   strength of our economy, as we come towards the end of this century,</p>
<p>   gives us a quite remarkable opportunity and a special capacity to</p>
<p>   play a role in the shaping of our region and a very positive role</p>
<p>   and a respected role. And the very strengths that are demonstrated</p>
<p>   by the achievement of this company are part of that story.</p>
<p>It is true, as Bill said, the Government, in 1997, laid out a plan</p>
<p>   for the Australian motor vehicle industry which was based on a very</p>
<p>   simple proposition and that it was inconceivable to me and inconceivable</p>
<p>   to the Government - and I know in stating this I would also have</p>
<p>   been expressing the views of the Opposition  it's inconceivable</p>
<p>   that Australia would not continue to have, for the foreseeable future,</p>
<p>   a strong and viable motor manufacturing capacity. And that plan</p>
<p>   and those decisions in relation to industry protection and industry</p>
<p>   arrangements were based on that philosophy. And we remain very steadfast</p>
<p>   in that goal and I believe that that commitment has created a climate</p>
<p>   which will beckon and provide a benign atmosphere for further investment</p>
<p>   in the industry. And it's a commitment to the lives of tens</p>
<p>   of thousands of Australians who are employed by this company. </p>
<p>I therefore do take the opportunity, Mr Wiemels, in particularly</p>
<p>   to you as the Chief Executive of the company, to congratulate you</p>
<p>   on this remarkable milestone, to thank you for what you have contributed</p>
<p>   over the years to Australia. I want particularly to record my appreciation</p>
<p>   for the tens of thousands of men and women who have worked for the</p>
<p>   company over the years because a successful commercial organisation</p>
<p>   is only ever the sum of the contributions of all of those who are</p>
<p>   in it and who work for it. And the dedication and loyalty of Holden</p>
<p>   employees over the years has made the company what it is, has enabled</p>
<p>   its products to become part and parcel of the Australian way and</p>
<p>   to be indistinguishable from the Australian way of life.</p>
<p>It is a wonderful occasion. It's an occasion of pride. It's</p>
<p>   an occasion of nostalgia but more importantly than that, it's</p>
<p>   an occasion to reflect upon the future for this country, for this</p>
<p>   company and the marvellous opportunities that lie before us as we</p>
<p>   move into the next millennium. I congratulate the company and I</p>
<p>   thank you most warmly for the invitation to be with you today. Thank</p>
<p>   you.</p>
<p>[ends] </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
