<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1582</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRLIAN WOMEN&#039;S LIBERAL CLUB, MELBOURNE - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT - 24TH MAY 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001582.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN WiOMEN'S LIBERAL CLUB, MELBOURNE V " ARY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR., HARCLD HOLT 24TH MAY, 1967<br />
Lady Coles, Sir Henry, Parliamentary colleagues, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
First, may I thank you on behalf of Mrs. Holt and myself very warmly<br />
for that gracious welcome you gave to us and for all the friendly support that<br />
this received from those around the room. Secondly, may I join with you in<br />
the congratulations you have expressed to our good friend Henry. It was a great<br />
joy to me, I can assure you, not only to see him back again, but for the proof<br />
it brought that Liberal support was as strong in this State as it has ever been.<br />
And for him to achieve that after twelve years of office and some difficult<br />
decisions, as I said to him at the time, or said publicly at the time, was a<br />
personal triumph and a notable political achievement. And this State can count<br />
itself fortunate that we have his sane, balanced, progressive leadership for the<br />
years that lie ahead I would think as mar y years as he cares to choose on<br />
the form that is so far disclosed.<br />
And may I also congratulate Mrs. Goble on having been elected and I<br />
say this in an Australian GVomen's Liberal Club. Vie are becoming more<br />
enlightened I think as we go on, we Liberals. WVe managed to elect a very able<br />
lady to the House of Representatives, the first time we've had one there for<br />
many years. In the Senate where we can organise these things rather better,<br />
of course, we are well represented by several lady Senators and I am glad to<br />
see Senator Breen here with us today and our joint friend Ivy ' iedgwood who<br />
chairs the Government Members' education Committee is also a very significant<br />
and valuable figure in the work of our Party. So that Henry and I have good<br />
cause to say thank you for what you are doing in giving us your support and<br />
from time to time sending from your membership people who can be good and<br />
worthy representatives in the Parliament.<br />
It sometimes makes me feel a little uncomfortable to realise that more<br />
than half my life has been spent in the national Parliament and in my early days,<br />
the only effective organisation we had in this State was the AWomen's organisation<br />
the Australian Viomen's National League as it was in those days. And I recall<br />
with great appreciation and gratitude the strength of support which they gave to<br />
us at that time.<br />
Sir Henry may be interested to know that at one stage when my electorate<br />
had become rather enlarged and I represented 80, 000 voters, 48, 000 of them<br />
were women voters, 32, 000 men voters. That gave a substantial majority of<br />
three lady voters to two men voters. I don't draw any significance from that<br />
because things have balanced out since that time and we've managed to maintain<br />
much the same sort of majority. But it gave me good reason to dwell on the<br />
value of the women voters in a particular electorate and on the support which<br />
came to us at the time from the women's organisation. And you've gone on<br />
giving us that loyal support down through the years.<br />
Now, after seventeen years of Liberal leadership I think we can all take<br />
some pride and a modest satisfaction in the state of our own Australia and those<br />
of us who have supported Liberal policies and Liberal leadership through ' hat<br />
period, either in the Federal or the State sphere, can justly claim that this has<br />
made a notable and significant contribution to the Australia of today. And<br />
whatever test you care to apply, I think we can fairly claim that this leadership,<br />
these liberal policies, have been good for Australia. 2/ </p>
<p>In the material tests we've more than doubled the gross national product<br />
of the country, we've developed the highest percentage of home ownership to<br />
be found in the more conspicuous evidence of an affluent society. We are a<br />
fortunaite people. And I would only hope and wish that sometimes those who are<br />
so critical of what they find in Australia would pause and count the blessings<br />
they enjoy in this country. It is I think unfortunately a weakness in our national<br />
life at the present time that we are always looking for trouble and the things<br />
that can be criticised rather than taking stock of how well we stand as a country<br />
and as a people and in comparison wi-th others around the world.<br />
However, having got that comment off my chest, let me turn to a couple<br />
of matters which are of topical significance politically for us. One of course<br />
is the political event immediately ahead, the referendum. I hope you won't<br />
mind me saying a few words about this because we haven't had the kind of<br />
opportunities we would normally enjoy in an election campaign of getting our<br />
message across as widely as we would wish. No political party has had the<br />
financial resources to conduct a large campaign on this matter and yet it does<br />
have an importance for good government in Australia and for Australia's standing<br />
in the eyes of the rest of the world.<br />
And when I say that I refer to two proposals I will take them in their<br />
inverse order, having stated them as I have, because I do believe that what we<br />
decide about the aborigine proposal will affect Australia's standing in the eyes<br />
of the rest of the world. I have every confidence that there will be an overwhelming<br />
YES vote. It is unthinkable that it could be otherwise. The purpose of the<br />
proposal is to remove from the Constitution references which in the one case<br />
produce an outmoded and outdated situation that is the item which talks<br />
about aborigines not being counted in relation to a census. Well, this was<br />
inserted in the Constitution at a time when aborigine people couldn't effectively<br />
be counted they were living either a tribal life or a nomadic life, and there<br />
weren't the facilities for checking that there are today. And it has no continuing<br />
place in a modern Australian Constitution.<br />
The other one which we suggest to be excluded is the only other reference<br />
which appears in the Constitution to aborigines, and although properly understood,<br />
it doesn't discriminate unfavourably against aborigine people it is regarc~ d<br />
widely both inside this country and outside this country as having that effect.<br />
And because we can still deal satisfactorily by the combined efforts of the<br />
Commonwealth and State Governments with the problems of people of aboriginal<br />
race without these specific references in the Constitution, and because there<br />
is lingering around the world a belief that somehow through this provision we<br />
discriminate against people of aboriginal race, we thought it should be out of<br />
the written text of the Constitution.<br />
But the other proposal is the one which causes more complexity for people.<br />
In the first place, it has associated with it the word " nexus". Some people have<br />
doubts as to just what " nexus" means, what its political or Constitutional<br />
significance may be. But it is really quite a simple business. In the early<br />
stages % lien the Constitution was being drafted, there was a feeling that more<br />
States would be created. So that there should not be an enlargement of the<br />
Senate relative to the House of Representatives which would diminish the stature<br />
of the House of Representatives, the planners of those days thought there ought<br />
to be a provision ensuring that the number of members of the House of<br />
Representatives was always at least twice that of the members of .~ ae<br />
' Well, as time has gone on, although there has been a lot of talk abou States,<br />
it hasn't come as yet to anything and there is no increase in the number of<br />
States in sight. But there lingers on in the Constitution this provision which<br />
throws on the House of Representatives the neceEsity, if at any time it wants to<br />
increase its numbers, of increasing the Senate to the extent of half of any<br />
increase in the size of the House of Representatives. o 3/ </p>
<p>Now,, I don't think there is much doubt around the community that a Senate<br />
of 60, and it was enlarged to 60 from 36 back in 1948, is large enough for<br />
Australia's needs at this time. -1he are not proposing that the Senate can never<br />
be increased. Vie are saying that we don't want to have to increase it every<br />
time growth in population and other f'actors would appear to make desirable some<br />
increase in the size of the House of Representatives. And so we want to gret rid<br />
of this formal obligation that we must increase the Senate any time we increase<br />
the House of Representatives. Very understandably, there are people who might<br />
think, "' Well, in those circumstances, won't there be a danger that the Senate<br />
will be reduced to too small a size, seeing that the Constitution at the moment<br />
only provides for a minimum of 36 Senators, whereas you have 60 in practice,<br />
and won't it leave it open to the House of Representatives to just increase its<br />
numbers at will to any size it chooses?" In order to meet that kind of concern,<br />
we have inserted two new safeguardsi or propose to insert them if the people<br />
will only give the affirmative vote we need. One safeguard is that the<br />
minimum number of Senators prescribed by the Constitution will henceforth<br />
be 60 as is the present number in the Senate, not 36 as the present Constitutional<br />
provision requires. And the sece-nd thing, is that we say you can't increase the<br />
size of the House of Representatives beyond a point taiat would leave a mk. I'mum<br />
of 85, 000 persons on average to e;-ch electorate. Now that is a very effective<br />
brake on the size of the House of Representatives.<br />
The authors of the NO case have made a quite misleading, and I would say,<br />
dishonest reference in the case that if the " nexus" is removed the one braking<br />
device in the Constitution groes with-it. iWell, I've already pointed out that<br />
there is this other very effective braking device, that you can't just go on<br />
increasing the size of the House of Representa-tives inordinately. It must relate<br />
to a minimum of 85, 000 persons. Now, how does that compare with other<br />
countries? In 1948, when the size of the House was increased, the increased House<br />
produced an average of 66, 000 persons. At the present time, there is an<br />
average of 94, 000 and if the Parliament runs its full course, it will get up to<br />
97, 003, and of course as other years go on, unless some change is made, the<br />
number to be represented by any one member will go on increasing.<br />
Well, you may ask why do we need more members, and in any event, why<br />
should we do this now? As to whether we need more, that's a practical question<br />
which I think could be sensibly argued. You need effective representation.<br />
When you get the member trying to represent too many people,. the individual<br />
elector doesn't get the same service that he or she is entitled to expect. And<br />
already the Australian National Parliamentarian is representing more people<br />
than a member of the House of Commons.<br />
Now, in the United States Parliament, they represent many more people<br />
but, in order to meet that situatiop, they had to build up big staffs around the<br />
member and instead of being able to get to your member to discuss your problems<br />
with him, you are liable to be with a second, or first, second, third or fourth<br />
secretary dealing with your particular situation. Now that's not in the British<br />
tradit-on and practice and we don't think Australians, accustomed to getting a<br />
persor. al response from their own member, would welcome the intrusion of some<br />
official betwveen uhenm ad the man or woman they have elected. And so we have<br />
picked on what seemrs tc, to be a reasonable minircum. You don't have to<br />
have a member C75, 000. It can go higher thalt. But you can't<br />
make more mrembers than a mpinimum of 85, 000 would stipulate. So there is<br />
this safeguard in the Constitution. 9 4/ </p>
<p>And there can be no argument e&amp; y one of us who has been in the<br />
Parliament for many years would be Able to affirm quite definitely that the<br />
complexity, the number, the scope of Commonwealth activities, these things,<br />
have grown enormously. As Henry and his colleagues here will know, in many<br />
fields which were originally exclusive to the States, not from choice on the part<br />
of the States but simply because of the demands of the electorate and financial<br />
and other limitations the Commonwealth has been brought into such fields as<br />
education, housing, into health and a variety of other matters. And then, of<br />
course, immigation. That programme has brought with it a whole range of new<br />
problems, and at the same time added many people who are not on the rolls<br />
as voters but whose needs have to be taken care of. With Australia's involvement<br />
in military operations and other commitments around the world, again you have<br />
repatriation problems, personnel problems of men and women in the Services,<br />
-which all have to be dealt with.<br />
But this, I repeat, is a matter of judgment. Whether we do it now, whether<br />
we do it five years, whether we do it ten years, fifteen years hence, is something<br />
for the Parliament to decide. The fact of the matter is that until you remove the<br />
nexus ( tape damaged) at the same time as you increase the size of the<br />
House of Representatives. And don't imagine that this is something that is going<br />
to happen very often. It's only happened once up till now in the history of our<br />
whole Federation. It took 47 years, from 1901, before the sizeof the Parliament<br />
was increased. If we go on to the next election, the House running its normal<br />
course, it woWd be 20 years since there was any increase, and the most that<br />
is proposed would be an increase of the order of 12, 13 or 14 members in the<br />
House without any addition to the Senate.<br />
WNell, you may say, why should we be bothering about this now? First,<br />
I would say, and on the evidence that we do this so rarely, it is very difficult<br />
to get a time when the three principal parties are all agreed that a change of<br />
this sort should be made and that this is the opportune time to do it. If this<br />
opportunity slips by I don't know when it* will occur again.<br />
The second thing is that we must have a redistribution, of the electorates,<br />
not to gain any political advantage for one party or another, but simply because<br />
over the years, and with the enormous growth around Australian cities in<br />
particular, they have become quite unbalanced. Mr. Calwell and I both<br />
represent, I think, electorates with less than 40, 000 voters, but Billy Snedden<br />
out in Bruce represents now well over 100, .000 by the time we get to the next<br />
election it will be nearer 120, COO. And this is not an isolated instance. Wherever<br />
the new growth has occurred around the capital cities, you find these abnormally<br />
enlarged electorates. In the heart of the cities, as people become more<br />
prosperous, they've tended to move out, and so the inner electorates have<br />
become smaller. Common decency and justice demand of us that we have a<br />
redistribution of electorates to help to balance out the representation. If we<br />
are going to do that, and if we have at any time over the next several years<br />
in contemplation some modest addition to the number of members of the<br />
Parliament, then surely it is appropriate we decide on that first and then have<br />
a redistribution on the basis of the numbers with which we agree should be<br />
brought into our account. And this is why, a very rare event for the Australian<br />
Parliament, you find the three leaders of the three principal Parties, the Liberal<br />
Party, the Labor Party and the Country Party, all coming to you urging at the<br />
one time that you give a Y21S vote on both of these proposals.<br />
Now the opponents are to be found in the ranks of the Democratic Labor<br />
Party, the two Senators in Canberra, and in a few Liberal and Country Party<br />
Senators who haven't gone along with the majority. In the House of Representatives<br />
and this I think is an impressive fact the voting in favour was unanimous, 9 0 </p>
<p>from all parties from all around Australia. In the Senate, although there is<br />
this handful of Senators who are taking the opposite line, the voting was 45 in<br />
favour to 7 against. And I think most people who have any doubts on this matter<br />
might have sufficient faith in the judgment of their representative and the<br />
democratic system to feel that when you get such an overwhelming support in<br />
favour of proposals as is evidenced in those voting figures, you can go along<br />
-Safely with what is recommended to you.<br />
I don't want to spend a great deal of time on the NO case, but there are<br />
just two or thlree aspects which I would like you to carry in your mind in case<br />
you encounter some waverers yourself. The NO case, the official NO case as<br />
printed, is I believe, a deplorable piece of argumentative presentation. I would<br />
have hoped that having a case prepared by members from Parliament, in this<br />
case from the Senate, we would have had a calm, logical analysis of the case,<br />
the arguments for, the arguments against, and we have tried to do that in the<br />
YZES case perhaps it has made it a rather more tedious and duller document<br />
for people to read but at least anybody who takes the trouble to go through it<br />
will find that this is the way in which the case has been presented. But the NO<br />
case sets out to conjure up all the fears, all the bogies, the whole string of the<br />
cliches you'd expect to find in some of the less responsible areas of the press<br />
about politicians too many politicians and howmuch they cost us, what damage<br />
we'Ire going to do to the Senate, and the damage-we're going to do to country<br />
interests. Well, let me take a few of those arguments in reverse order. The country<br />
interests -there are representatives from country electorates in the House of<br />
Representatives in each of the three Parties. The Country Party itself, of course.<br />
I n the Liberal Party we have as many representatives from country electorates,<br />
and the Labor Party has members from country electorates. And yet every one<br />
of those representatives from a country electorate ( tape damaged) a unanimous<br />
vote. The Senate is traditionally regarded as the custodian of the interests of the<br />
States, and yet, here again I repeat, 45 out of 52 voted in support of this. So<br />
you don't get much comfort out of that argument if you are a NO voter. Well,<br />
then, without going through all the rest of them, let me just say a word about the<br />
cost of all this. A great bogey is conjured up: " We've got enough Parliamentarians,<br />
we don't want more. It's going to cost us more in taxes. Well, I gave a figure<br />
in the House of Representatives the other night that the cost of the House of<br />
Representatives and of the Senate taken together worked out at less than 40 cents<br />
a year per head of the population as I put it just a little more than the price of<br />
a packet of cigarettes. And the cost of an individual senator or member of the<br />
House of Representatives and this includes his travelling expenses and matters<br />
of that sort worked out at about J of one cent.<br />
Now if we were going to increase members by about 12 or 14, the cost of<br />
those extra members of the House of Representatives would be somewhere between<br />
3 and 4 cents per head of population. I don't think that's going to represent too<br />
much of a financial burden on anybody. A par in the " Melbourne Herald" on<br />
Saturday night questioned my figure of 40 cents and said the figure was nearer<br />
79 cents. Well, my information had been given to me by officials in my own<br />
office having studied the Year Book which sets out the cost of Parliamentary<br />
government. I went over it again myself today and I found the only way you could<br />
build up the cost of the House and the Senate was by including furniture and<br />
services and matters of that sort. So I threw those in too. The argument was<br />
about additional members of Parliament, so you don't bring in the cost of the<br />
extra salaries of Ministers and extra Ministerial travel because the argument is<br />
not whether we have more Ministers we are not likely to have any more<br />
Ministers even if the number of the House increases slightly. And even throwing<br />
that in, it got up to a figure of the two Houses combined of under 50 cents or if you<br />
like a year. So don't be frightened by that particular bogey. 6/ </p>
<p>6.<br />
Now, what I would like to say before I conclude and it does have a<br />
reference to the Senate is a word or two about the course of conduct puvzsued<br />
by the Senate in this last Session of Parliament. As you know we came back from<br />
the last elections with a record majority, an all-time record majority in the House<br />
of Representatives. If ever a Government was entitled to claim that the people<br />
had given it authority, a mandate to govern, we could fairly claim that. And we<br />
have set quite briskly about the business of putting into effect the policy undertakings<br />
we gave at the election time. Several of them have already been given<br />
effect and others are well advanced, but we are finding increasingly that the<br />
composition of the Senate at present, in which you have the produce unfortunately<br />
of two deaths of staunch Liberal Senators, a situation now where the Australian<br />
Labor Party with the help either of an independent Senator, Senator Turnbull,<br />
or one of our own Liberal Senators who decides to desert us on a particular<br />
occasion in order to record a vote against us, or any one of that combination of<br />
the ALP plus the DLP can defeat the Government in the Senate.<br />
Now, the Senate was never designed for that course of conduct. It was<br />
designed es a House of Review so that it could study in a more leisurely way<br />
legislation coming up from the House of Representatives and send back suggestions<br />
for the consideration of the House of Representatives. It was designed, in<br />
addition, to see that the rights of the States were not trampled upon. But it was<br />
never intended to act as a block upon the legislative process and the capacity to<br />
govern of a democratically elected government. And I would never have assumed<br />
that a Labor Party which is pledged to abolish the Senate, would turn to the<br />
Senate, to use the Senate to defeat a democratic ally elected Government not<br />
just on some monor matter or some clause in a Bill but to defeat the financial<br />
programme of a government. Now I can say to his credit that this would never<br />
have been acceptable to the former Labor Leader, Arthur Calwell. Nor do I<br />
know any Labor leader in my time in Parliament who would have used the Senate<br />
or his numbers in the Senate in this way. ii. hen I have heard Mr. W. hitlam speak<br />
on occasion of the respective positions of the Senate and the House of<br />
Representatives, it would have been difficult to imagine that he would have lent<br />
himself as he has in recent times to this veto on the bill we put through in<br />
relation to postal charges.<br />
Now, we all know that increases in postal rates are urpopular. Of course<br />
they are. No government likes to put up charges for the services it gives. But<br />
if the wage bill is continuing to rise, and the Post Office is a very large user of<br />
labour and cannot escape the extra costs which regular increases coming out of<br />
the Arbitration Commission bring to its employees, then there has to be some<br />
adjustment. In point of fact, over the period since 1959, when these charges were<br />
last raised, consumer services have gone up on an average 22/ 0. In the Post<br />
Office the increase proposed was in the order of 1570 to meet the growing costs<br />
and to offset losses which were likely to accumulate. But the merits of the proposal<br />
is another matter to argue and we as an elected government have to accept<br />
responsibility for these decisions we take. What I'm putting to you now as a matter<br />
of high principle is whether a government, democratically elected as oulshas<br />
been, should be subjected to the resistance and the effective veto of a chance<br />
majority from a hostile political force in the Senate. I believe that, if the Senate<br />
pursues this course already, of course, it will have thrown out of balance our<br />
Budgeting for the next financial year we will have to review the whole financial<br />
position as a consequence of the denial to us of the extra revenue we believed to<br />
have been needed. But it is set now on a collision course with the government and<br />
with the House of Representatives, and is building up a constitutional issue of<br />
major dimension between the two Houses. I would hope that inside our own Party<br />
there is a clear appreciation that this is more than a piece of Party manoeuvring,<br />
more than an attempt to score a political point or two. The Senate would appear<br />
under the new Labor leadership to have set itself quite resolutely upon a course<br />
which must inevitably bring it into collision with the House of Representatives and<br />
with a democratically elected majority of record proportions. 7/ </p>
<p>,4 7.<br />
Now, how we deal with this in the future remains to be seen, but I hope<br />
we shall have your sympathetic understanding in any action that we have to<br />
take in relation to it.<br />
Now, that took me rather longer, Lady Coles, than I had intended to<br />
occupy you. Thank you for your very attentive hearing; thank you again<br />
all of you for the support you continue to brin. to our Liberal Party, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
