<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7802</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, EASTFIELD PHARMACY, THE MALL SOUTH CROYDON, 9 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007802.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, EASTFIELD PHARMACY, THEI MALL,<br />
SOUTH CROYDON, 9 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
X4 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Well what we've done is to put a package and I've<br />
written a letter to Jim Matthews, the National President.<br />
ThdL framework must stand and the implications of<br />
it. Now, if the Pharmacy Guild will accept that, come<br />
in and talk with us, well I've said that provided that<br />
basic of the budgetar-y implications are maintained,<br />
sure, we can talk. And if they come in we would want<br />
to see the pharmacists liave two members on the Trust which<br />
would administer the new provisions which are regarded<br />
as important, by pharmacists, professional allowance and<br />
may I say Just, having just had the opportunity of<br />
boing in here and having spelt out to me the sort of<br />
professional services that are provided by pharmacists<br />
I'm all the more reinforced In the necessity for this<br />
professional allowance concept. So Lhey would have two<br />
people on the Trust helping to administer that, they'd<br />
have a majority on that. I've also given the undertaking<br />
that at the first opportunity that arises there would<br />
be a person with experience in retail pharmacy go on the<br />
Pharmacy Remuneration Tribunal. So those things<br />
can be done aid we can talk about these issues within<br />
O that basic framework.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you consider $ 60 million to be enough<br />
or will there be more-<br />
PM: $ 60 million, $ 60 million is on top of what the Tribunal<br />
decided and think that that provides a very substantial<br />
advance and we've got to operate within that framework<br />
I think the pharmacists understand. We haven't got<br />
a bottomless pit. I mean, we Just can't everything<br />
you want and they I think they do recognise that,<br />
you know, can't yo on with d 25 percent markup concept<br />
especially in regard to the high cost drugs. But really,<br />
the thing to do would be, as the pilots, and say<br />
alright, we regard that framework as sound come in<br />
und vlt's talk about it. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
JOURNALIST: Kr Hawke, evidence was given in court today<br />
that You and Sir Peter Abeles struck a deal about how<br />
to handle the Pilots' dispute before the pilots took industrial<br />
action. Is that true?<br />
PM: No, of course not and the matter is subjudicy at<br />
any rate,. But by now You ought to have realised that<br />
the untruths that have been told in this on the part of<br />
the pilots, they're Just mountainous. I mean, they seem<br />
to forget that it was in February of-this year that they<br />
put out, in written form, a publication telling their<br />
members to prepare for a long battle. They prepared for<br />
it in February.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you discuss that with Sir Peter before<br />
the pilots took industrial action?<br />
PM: Discuss what, I mean<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you discuss the dispute with Sir Peter<br />
before the pilots took industrial action?<br />
PM: There was no dispute before there was industrial<br />
action. At any rate undex-sLdnd this matter is<br />
JOURNALIST: chemists your best and last offer?<br />
PM: I've answered that question.<br />
JOURNALIST; Mr Ilawke, the next one and the big one, when<br />
is the election?<br />
PM: Not to be announced here. Wouldn't you like that<br />
wouldn't you love that too? But I think it's likely<br />
to be in 1990 sometime.<br />
JOURNALIST: January 1990?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Peacock<br />
PM; Well Mr Peacock is all over the place in this matter<br />
Isn't lie. I mean; after all, they created the Tribunal,<br />
not us. I've said in terms of pharmacists' representation<br />
thaL when the opportunity arises, which I think is<br />
betore very long, we will see that there is pharmacists'<br />
representation on Lhe Tribunal.<br />
JOURNALIST: Andrew Peacock is actually sending letters<br />
to individual pharmacists Mr Hawke, urging them not to<br />
back the Government's package and saying that they'd do<br />
a lot better under the Liberal Party. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM:, I Just ask you go and have a look at the graph of<br />
pharmacists' income under the last Liberal Government<br />
of which Peacock was part. Have a look at what happened<br />
to their income under them, have a look at what's happened<br />
to their income under us. I tell you now, just give you<br />
guarantee I wish I'd been as certain as you<br />
know, knowing the winner of the Melbourne Cup under<br />
the Libs pharmacists' income went down, under us it's<br />
gone up. Just do the two graphs. So if the pharmacists<br />
believe the Liberals on what would happen to their income<br />
under them, they'd believe anything and I don't think<br />
they're that silly.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: You're quite right 12 percent under us over<br />
the next two years<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you concerned against you whenever<br />
the election is?<br />
PM: I'd rather thay weren't making those threats, but<br />
I think we can work these things out.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
