<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12597</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA    </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Australian Democrats; Stem Cell Research</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........  </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, How do you think the stem cell debate's going?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, it's a very interesting debate.  It's very important on issues like this that there is a free vote.   I think it brings out a lot of very thoughtful debate.  I have just heard a very thoughtful speech from Chris Pearce, who's still a bit of a marginal seat hero as far as I'm concerned.  He represented the turning of the tide last year and I was interested in his views.  I hope it's a very, and I know it will be, a very sincere debate.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>John Howard, what do you make of Natasha Stott Despoja's decision to resign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's always difficult when a leader gets in a difficult position with his or her party.  I've experienced that in the past.  I don't want to make any clever, smart alec remark about the internal affairs of the Democrats. Let them work that through.  I wish her well on the personal basis.  I don't agree with her on a lot of political issues, but I've always found her a courteous person to deal with and I wish her well.  It's not an easy time for her.  I wish Aden Ridgeway well and we'll just see how things work out.  But I don't think anything is achieved by leaders of other parties appearing to derive any pleasure from what's happened to another party.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What do you think it will mean to the Senate though and your negotiations of…</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It may not mean anything.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think the party will be easier to deal with, now that she's not…?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It may not mean anything.  I have been very reserved and careful about what I've said on this because I've not automatically assumed that what has gone in the Democrats will necessarily alter the prospects of getting legislation through.  I hope that we can get our unfair dismissal legislation through.  I hope that we can get our budget through.  But you should not assume, and I do not, that the changes in the Democrats will alter those prospects.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On George Pell, it' s brought up a lot of concern around… do you have any regrets on what you said last night?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, and I don't have anything else to say about it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On stem cells, would you be happy to see the bill split?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a matter for the Parliament.  It's a free vote.  So, the question of whether it is split or not is a free vote.  Self evidently, I introduced it as one piece of legislation.  So that really defines my position ultimately.  If I had thought it should have been split in the first place, I suppose it would have been introduced as two separate bills.  But if the Parliament were to vote to split it, well naturally I accept that, that's a matter for the Parliament.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How would you feel if it was defeated?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The bill?  Well, I'd rather it not be defeated.  I think the better outcome is for it to get through.  I think the national interest is better served.  I thought a lot about this and I find it quite a difficult issue and I respect the views of many of my colleagues and very close friends, who come to a different conclusion, but that's the nature of Parliament.  And I think everybody's being civil and reasonable about it and whatever the outcome is, the Parliament will have decided and I'm happy with that.  But my view is unmistakable, I'm in favour of it and I do think the cause of humanity is better advanced by this legislation going through and I would like to see a uniform position throughout Australia.  I think it would be very bad to have a disuniform position around the country.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well if that happens, I mean where do you stand then?  Do you have different legislation…?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I accept what the Parliament does.  I am a creature of Parliament.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Just on the Democrats.  Who would you like to see as leader?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's a matter for the Australian Democrats.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
