<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6296</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON THE OCCASION OF LAUNCHING OF PRIMARY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM, 23 JANUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/01/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006296.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST ELIVERY CHEC'K AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON THE OCCASION OF LAUNCHING<br />
OF PRIMARY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM 23 JANUARY 1984<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S OBJECTIVES IN SPORT ARE TWOFOLD;<br />
TO PROMOTE EXCELLENCE AT THE HIGHEST LEVELS IN A<br />
NUMBER OF SPORTS, AND TO ENCOURAGE ACTIVE PARTICIPATION<br />
IN SPORT AMONG ALL SECTIONS OF THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY.<br />
THESE OBJECTIVES ARE MUTUALLY REINFORCING: IF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC IN GENERAL, AND THE YOUTH OF<br />
AUSTRALIA IN PARTICULAR, CAN TAKE JUSTIFICABLE PRIDE<br />
IN THE PERFORMANCE AND CONDUCT OF OUR TOP SPORTSMEN<br />
AND SPORTSWOMEN, THEY ARE MORE LIKELY THEMSELVES TO<br />
SEE VALUE IN-PLAYING SPORT, AND IF ALL AUSTRALIANS<br />
CAN BE ENCOURAGED TO DO THIS, WHETHER IT BE<br />
COMPETITIVE OR NON-COMPETITIVE, WE WILL BE A HEALTHIER<br />
NATION FOR IT.<br />
AS A SPORT CRICKET HAS MUCH TO OFFER YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
IT HELPS TO DEVELOP CO-ORDINATION AT AN EARLY STAGE,<br />
PARTICULARLY OF HAND AND EYE, AND IT IS ALSO A TEAM<br />
SPORT, SO INTRODUCING YOUNG PEOPLE AT AN EARLY STAGE<br />
TO THE DISCIPLINE REQUIRED IN CO-OPERATIVE EFFORT.<br />
IT IS BOTH FOR THESE REASONS, AND BECAUSE I PERSONALLY<br />
HAVE DERIVED ENORMOUS PLEASURE FROM PARTICIPATING IN<br />
AND WATCHING CRICKET SINCE MY OWN YOUTH, THAT I AM<br />
DELIGHTED BY THE ANNOUNCEMENT TODAY OF THE PRIMARY<br />
DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM. </p>
<p>IT IS A PROGRAM THAT WILL GIVE AUSTRALIAN BOYS AND<br />
GIRLS A CHANCE TO ENJOY THEMSELVES, GAIN HEALTHY<br />
RECREATION, AND HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO LEARN HOW<br />
TO PLAY CRICKET,<br />
IT WILL ALSO CONTRIBUTE SIGNIFICANTLY TO ENSURING<br />
THAT CRICKET REMAINS AN IMPORTANT SPORT IN SCHOOLS,<br />
AND THE ENJOYMENT ASSOCIATED WITH THE GAME DOES NOT<br />
BECOME THE EXCLUSIVE PRESERVE OF THE " BIGGEST AND BEST",<br />
AND I AM PARTICULARLY PLEASED THAT A NUMBER OF<br />
PAST AND PRESENT AUSTRALIAN ( AND ENGLISH) TEST<br />
CRICKETING GREATS ARE PRESENT TODAY FOR THE<br />
LAUNCHING OF THE PROGRAM, THUS PROVIDING<br />
ADDITIONAL INSPIRATION AND INCENTIVE IF IT<br />
IS NEEDED FOR YOUNG AUSTRALIAN CRICKET PLAYERS<br />
IN PARTICULAR WE HAVE FOUR AUSTRALIAN<br />
CAPTAINS IN RICHIE BENAUD, IAN CHAPPELL,<br />
GREG CHAPPELL AND PRESENT SKIPPER KIM HUGHES,<br />
AND THE GREATEST FAST BOWLER OF ALL TIME IN<br />
DENNIS LILLEE AND ONE OF THE FASTEST EVER<br />
BOWLERS IN FRANK TYSON<br />
THE LEADERSHIP OF THESE FOUR CAPTAINS HAS<br />
CONTRIBUTED SIGNIFICANTLY TO AUSTRALIA'S<br />
OUTSTANDING RECORD AS A CRICKET NATION FOR<br />
MUCH OF THE LAST TWO DECADES </p>
<p>DURING THAT PERIOD THE INDIVIDUAL PERFORMANCES<br />
OF RICHIE BENAUD, IAN CHAPPELL, GREG CHAPPELL,<br />
KIM HUGHES AND DENNIS LILLEE HAVE ALSO<br />
CONTRIBUTED SIGNIFICANTLY TO THAT OUTCOME,<br />
AS WELL AS SUBSTANTIALLY REWRITING THE RECORD<br />
BOOKS AND I TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO PAY TRIBUTE TO<br />
THE CONTRIBUTION THEY HAVE MADE TO AUSTRALIAN<br />
CRICKET ( A CONTRIBUTION WHICH I TRUST WILL BE<br />
SUSTAINED IN THREE CASES WHEN THEY TAKE THE<br />
FIELD TOMORROW FOR THE PRIME MINISTER'S XI),<br />
IT IS AUSTRALIAN SPORTSMEN AND SPORTSWOMEN SUCH AS<br />
THOSE PRESENT FOR THIS LAUNCHING THAT HAVE GIVEN<br />
AUSTRALIA THE WORLD REPUTATION IT HAS AS A SPORTING<br />
NATION. IT IS EQUALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE STRIVE TO<br />
GIVE OUR YOUTH EVERY OPPPORTUNITY TO ENJOY HEALTHY<br />
RECREATION. " KANGA CRICKET" AS THE PROGRAM WILL BE CALLED IS A<br />
MOST IMAGINATIVE AND PROGRESSIVE STEP TOWARDS<br />
ACHIEVING THIS OBJECTIVE, AND I CONGRATULATE<br />
AUSTRALIAN CRICKET BOARD CHAIRMAN, MR FRED BENNETT<br />
AND HIS ADMINISTRATORS ON FORMULATING THE PROGRAM) AND<br />
MR MALCOLM VAWSER ON THE AUSTRALIAN DAIRY CORPORATION'S<br />
INVOLVEMENT, ,/ 4 </p>
<p>4,<br />
AND I TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE SOME OBSERVATIONS<br />
THAT I HAVE DEVELOPED MORE GENERALLY IN REGARD TO<br />
GOVERNMENT SUPPORT FOR SPORT IN A SMALLER DEMOCRATIC<br />
NATION SUCH AS AUSTRALIA, FIRST, WE FEEL THAT THE<br />
OBLIGATIONS AND BENEFITS SHOULD BE SHARED EQUITABLY WITH<br />
THE PRIVATE SECTOR, AS IS THE CASE WITH OTHER ENDEAVOURS<br />
IN OUR SOCIETY, SECOND, WE DO NOT WISH TO CONCENTRATE<br />
ALL OUR RESOURCES ON ELITE SPORTSMEN AND SPORTSWOMEN,<br />
AND RATHER TO ENSURE THAT SOME OF THESE FLOW THROUGH<br />
TO ALL MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY,<br />
THE CO-OPERATIVE EFFORTS OF THE AUSTRALIAN CRICKET<br />
BOARD, THE AUSTRALIAN DAIRY CORPORATION AND THE<br />
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WITH THE PRIMARY DEVELOPMENT<br />
PROGRAM ARE INDICATIVE OF WHAT CAN BE ACHIEVED<br />
WITHIN SUCH A FRAMEWORK,<br />
GOOD LUCK TO " KANGA CRICKET" IN THE YEARS AHEAD, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
