<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1840</transcript-id>
    <title>CONFERENCE OF PRESIDENTS OF CHAMBERS OF MANUFACTURES AND OF FEDERAL MANUFACTURERS&#039; ORGANISATIONS A.C.M.A. CONFERENCE CENTRE, CANBERRA 2ND MAY 1968 SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/05/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001840.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CON4FERENCE OF P~ tESIDENTS OF CHAMBERS 0~<br />
MANUFACTURES AND OF FEIRAL MANUFACTURERS'<br />
ORGANISATIONS<br />
A. C. Mi. A. C~ nference Centre, Canberra 2ND MAY 1968<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr John Gorton<br />
Mr President and Gentlemen: What I have to say to you, because of the time in<br />
which I can say it, will not be very deep, nor would you expect it to go<br />
very deeply into any of the many subjects which will be occupying your<br />
own minds during the course of the Conference. But you will, I ' know, be<br />
hearing from the Treasurer on matters financial, and I think the Minister<br />
for Denfence will be talking about those aspects of defence which impinge<br />
upon the manufacturing industry inside Australia. You will get from the<br />
acting Minister for Trade and Industry comments in that field of activity<br />
which are of interest to you. So really, the object of my being here is,<br />
firstly, to show publicly the respect and regard which the Government, on<br />
behalf of the people of Australia has for the Associated Chambers of<br />
Manufactures and for what they are seeking in one way or another to do<br />
for the growth of our country. It is a tribute to come, and that I think, you<br />
realise is the main object of my presence with you.<br />
I did notice that this was supposed to be a two-way<br />
flow of ideas that is, a flow of ideas from the Chambers to the Government,<br />
and on other aspects, a flow back from the Government to the Chambers.<br />
It will, I think, be a three-way flow of ideas because I have no doubt that<br />
at the meeting here itself, there will be a flowing of ideas from some people<br />
with some ideas as to what should happen and they in turn will be tne subject<br />
of discussion with others. You can do, and have done and can do more to<br />
dvance the possibilities of Australia's becoming more quickly than she<br />
otherwise would, a significant national power. I think it was Sir Robert<br />
Menzies, some time ago, who said he doubted whether any country had<br />
grown so quickly in so many fields in such a relatively short length of time<br />
fis has Australia since the end of the Second V~ orld ' Var. I don't thin.-<br />
that anyone could deny that the building-up of our manufacturing industry,<br />
the provision of new fields of endeavour inside it, has given to this country<br />
industrial muscles which, for a variety of reasons, are essential in these<br />
days, and has given that employment which makes possible the continuation<br />
of immigration policies which in turn make possible the growth of the<br />
nation. There will be argulrents as to how this can best be done,<br />
as to what price should be paid for what is being contributed by you. Of<br />
course there will. But that there has been a contribution, I think nobody<br />
can doubt. And so I hope you will take further advantage still of<br />
such export incentive schemes as have been or will be provided and take<br />
further advantage, too, of the ability to raise capital throughout the world<br />
in this comparatively safe haven of the world, in order further to expand / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
manufacturing activities. i don't suppose that twenty or twenty-five years ago<br />
it would have been possible for this nation to have gone through the<br />
period of drought in its most productive areas, which it has but recently<br />
gone through, without having been most visibly affected, and badly<br />
affected in its economic life. I think it is the growth of alternative<br />
avenues of employment, the growth of manufacturing which has not wiped<br />
out, but minimisect the economic effects of this drought which recently has<br />
hit us. Well, how best to continue these matters is first<br />
going to be the subject of discussion amongst yourselves, and secondly<br />
the subject of submissions made on your behalf to us, some of which,<br />
as you have indicated, may be difficult; some of which, it is not<br />
impossible, might not be accepted, but all of wich will be very carefully<br />
studied. We have for our part and I make this just a very<br />
brief thumbnail sketch we for our part have to try, as n-anagers in the<br />
way in which you are managers, to choose between what are in some<br />
respects contradictory requirements. I think we maust see that those of<br />
our citizens in Australia who are, as a result of the slings and arrows of<br />
outrageous fortune, crippled by illness, unable to live a full life in their<br />
age, invalids during the course of their productive life, are looked after<br />
by the community to a degree which provides a respectable life for these<br />
people. I know we have to supply for this country, more<br />
than ever before, a proportion of our production going towards defence<br />
greater than we have ever had to supply before except in tim. e of war, but<br />
one which must be kept down and is not allowed to grow disproportionately.<br />
Indeed, although the expenditure on defence will inevitably grow because of<br />
commitments already entered into in this coming financial year and possibly<br />
the one after, any increase in proportion must in the future be checked<br />
against the other requirements we have got.<br />
We have, at the same time as having to meet those<br />
requirements amongst many others, to endeavour to see that we leave in<br />
the hands of the individual citizen of Australia, and those who mobilise<br />
the individual citizen for work, such as yourselves, sufficient reward for<br />
what has been earned or what has been done to see that an incentive,<br />
a financial incentive for future advance still remains.<br />
We have to provide, and there are some here who<br />
have been active in urging that this must be provided, and rightly so<br />
we have to provide for even better educational levels than is provided<br />
now, and particularly seek to build up technical education at all levels.<br />
I would think that at a gathering of significant people in Chambers of<br />
Manufactures, I do not need to underline the essentiality of technical<br />
and technological education, in which I include such matters as retraining,<br />
and such matters as managerial training at various levels.<br />
All of these things, and of course many more are those<br />
between which governments as managers have to choose. On one occasion, / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
I said something of this kind to a Chamber of Commerce, and for some<br />
reason which I find it impossible to understand, was reported in the<br />
newspapers with a big headline saying :" More Taxatbn is Threatened".<br />
What I am really doing is putting before you all the different requirements<br />
which you want, and showing how, as managexs, one must choose between<br />
them all, and that is all I am doing. In a way, it is trying to do what each<br />
of you in each of your industries do<br />
Whatever choices we finally make, whatever area. it is in<br />
which we finally decide to try first because all of them cannot be all<br />
overcome at once I can tell you this, and I believe that you will believe<br />
me. We will, in this managerial role make choices which we arrive at<br />
on a completely honest assessment, right or wrong, but completely honest<br />
assessment of what we think to be the best for the present and future<br />
growth of this nation, and I would think that you gentlemen would do the<br />
same. If through your efforts, and if thrwugh the efforts of governments<br />
throughout Australia, we can infuse into the Australian people a belief<br />
that each one of them as an individual, in whatever it is that he is called<br />
upon to do by way of employment, that each one of them should follow<br />
the rule :" Whatsoever thy right hand findeth to do, do it with all thy<br />
might" in production, on the land, wherever it may be; if we can<br />
infuse into them the belief that in doing this they are contributing as much<br />
to the growth of a great nation, and a nation in which it is good to live, as<br />
is a soldier on the battlefield protecting Australia in Viet Nam, and that if<br />
they are doing this, they are doing it not merely for their own material<br />
advancement but also for the provision of a better material and spiritual<br />
m-ilieu for their children, then really, Sir, we will have done a great<br />
deal to make this a greater country than it is.<br />
I hope that out of this conference which I now declare open<br />
may come steps in that direction. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
