<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9300</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP NATIVE TITLE ACT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009300.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I PRIME MINISTER ( OVA~<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
NATIVE TITLE ACT<br />
Mr Downers position on abolishing the Native Title Act has revealed that he is a weak<br />
leader without vision, without policies and without a commitment to social cohesion and<br />
social justice.<br />
Mr Downer saw the opportunity to deliver a cheap political line in Western Australia and took<br />
it at the expense of one of the most important pieces of legislation ever enacted in this<br />
country. He is attempting to create damaging uncertainty for what he sees as short termn political gain.<br />
He has treated the Aboriginal people with contempt in exchange for some fleeting applause<br />
at a party conference. He is clearly trying to be all things to all people and told the Western<br />
Australian Uberals what he thought they wanted to hear.<br />
It is a further indication that Mr Downer has no policies and stands for nothing.<br />
What are the implications of Mr ' Downeres position on Mabo? Is he saying that he d ioes not<br />
accept the High Court decislon on Naiv~ title? Is he' saying that worse than having no<br />
policy he is simply happy to do what state Premiers, "' especially Richard Court', tell him to<br />
do? What would he do after the Act was repealed?<br />
What now of his coming PR stunt in the Northern Territory? Will he tell the aboriginal<br />
people of the Northern Terrior that he is going to wipe out Native Title? Will he tell the<br />
aboriginal people that land is no longer important to them? Will he tell them that they can<br />
have health and education but they can't have land, either through native title rights or the<br />
Land Fund?<br />
Is he going to tell the aboriginal people that Richard Court knows what is best for them?<br />
Mr Downer says he will announce his policies when he wants to, not when the press or I<br />
want him to. Apparently, now he plans to announce policies when Richard Court wants him<br />
to. Not now, not before the election but after the election.<br />
I AUGUST 1994<br />
BRISBANE </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
