<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4322</transcript-id>
    <title>ECONOMIC DEBATE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004322.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jj r ALI APMME<br />
BAINISTER<br />
FOR :? RESS 15 FEBRUARY 1977<br />
ECONOMIC DEBATE<br />
We have had the Wran plan, the Hawke plan, the Whitlam plan,<br />
and now we have the Hurford plan last but not least, in a<br />
long line of Labor plans to revive the economy that they did<br />
their best to destroy.<br />
Never has the Labor Party more justly earned their label as<br />
the party of planning one after another, they put forward<br />
facile plans, futile plans, foolish plans.<br />
It would be hard not to have some admiration for the Opposition<br />
for through the multiplicity of plans, there is a consistency<br />
and strength of purpose. Their solution to every problem is<br />
to spend up big.<br />
It is obvious that the Labor Party has once again panicked<br />
as the Leader of the Opposition has now admitted they panicked<br />
in the last threemonths of 1974. " Of course we panicked",<br />
Mr Whitlam said on the 8 February. " The Cabinet panicked,<br />
the Caucus did, they did in the last three months of 1974."<br />
Why did they panic because of the effects of the 1971/ 75<br />
budget. Alan Reid has discussed that budget making process very<br />
aptly. No wonder he is not the Leader of the Opposition's<br />
favourite journalist. The 1974/ 75 budget as Reid describes<br />
it " was not the product of considered overall policies. It<br />
was more like starving men surrounding a cooking pot, and under<br />
the eyes of an approving, and participating overlord,<br />
trying each to spoon out as large 2 share as possible,<br />
before the pot was emptied." ( page 181)<br />
That budget, which contributed so greatly to the present inflation<br />
and unemployment, was a high point in the application of<br />
Labor's consistent philosophy. In 1974/ 75 outlays rose by<br />
46% in a single year, and the deficit from $ 293 million in<br />
1973/ 74 to S2600 million almost a nine-fold increase.<br />
Unemployment more than trebled, increasing by almost 2: 00,000. </p>
<p>Averoage earnings rose by 22%, while. GDP did not increase at all.<br />
The CPT rose by 171 in the last quarter for which Labor<br />
Aas resonsible it rose by 5.60.<br />
At the same time, business was squeezed and business and consumer<br />
confidence undermined. In the face of this situation the*<br />
situation that they had created, even the short-sighted Labor<br />
Cabinet were caused to panic.<br />
Mr lflhitlam of course, with becoming modesty, omits to note<br />
that he had had the foresight tn panic as early as July<br />
leading the other members of his Cabinet and Caucus by two months.<br />
As another of the chroniclers of the Whitlam years, Paul Kelly<br />
described the situation: After July 1974 ' Whitlam became<br />
incredibly introverted some people said he was sulki~ ng<br />
others said he did not want to intervene in the economiLc<br />
debate until he had a policy to espouse. Whatever the reason,<br />
Whiitlam retreated to The Lodge for many weeks and his Government<br />
was left without strong leadership, in a rudderless condition,<br />
shifting from crisis to crisis, being discredited each day.''<br />
And what was the then P. M. doing at the end of 1974 when Caucus<br />
and Cabinet were panicking? He was dismissing Frank Crean<br />
because, as Treasurer, the Member for Melbourne Ports opposed<br />
attempts to raise money through Arab money lenders He was<br />
ignoring the questions asked by the Treasury about raising<br />
money through unnamed intermediaries. And he was touring<br />
foreign ruins, to get away from the ruins he had created in<br />
Australia. On his December 1974 holidays he toured overseas<br />
for 35 days, at a cost of $ 497,449 for his personal party alone<br />
exluding public servants.<br />
The manifest failure of the Labor Party's economic policies<br />
when in Government have not stopped it from continuing, lemming-like,<br />
on its incompetent economic path. Large numbers of them went<br />
over the cliff at the last election and the remainder<br />
of the Opposition is determined to follow them.<br />
We thought that the best had come when the Leader of the Opposition<br />
trumpeted the Whitlam five-point plan. For once it didn't involve<br />
raising money from the Arabs and Iraquis but it had everything<br />
else cuts in sales tax, cuts in company tax, increased tax<br />
rebates, no Medibank levy.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition advocated more government spending,<br />
more artificial employment schemes, full indexation and a<br />
variety of other schemes. In total, these would have added<br />
$ 1,000 million to the deficit.<br />
Thi~ s plan was soon forgotten, everyone realised that it made no<br />
contribution to solving our economic problems. This was not<br />
surprising. The Leader of the Opposition has told us he isn't<br />
very interested in economics. ./ 3 </p>
<p>ut to be dauntced the Shado,.. Freasurt-er, huntecr1 and<br />
haunted by the Shadow ,44nistcr for-Defence, put forward tho<br />
Hurford Plan. In the great tradition of Labor Treasurers,<br />
and Shadow Treasurers, the Member for Adelaide announced that he<br />
woull launch a further big spending campaign accompanied<br />
by tax cuts. Under this scheme, Australia could look forward<br />
to another large and growing deficit, and an outsized expansion of<br />
the money supply to further fuel inflation. The Shadow<br />
Treasurer proposed to " allow the money supply to increase<br />
to the rate of inflation, plus growth."<br />
He is thereby proposing an expansion almost identical<br />
to the one which so significantly fueled inflation in the<br />
Labor years.<br />
From 1973/ 75 real gross domestic product grew at an average of<br />
2% per year, and inflation at 16% per year and the volume<br />
of money grew at 17%. It is obvious that the Shadow Treasurer<br />
has gone back to the policies which caused economic chaos,<br />
which caused inflation, which caused unemployment.<br />
He is advocating the complete irresponsibility of the Labor<br />
years. The Hurford Plan advocates the resurrection of the<br />
artificial employment scheme that the Labor Government<br />
itself made the decision to abandon. The Hurford plan suggests<br />
that investment and depreciation allowances be abolished.<br />
It is clear that the Labor Party is in effect not only advocating<br />
policies which will fuel inflation, but which also stop economic<br />
growth. The tax increase that it involves would end the<br />
significant upturn in business investment in 1976. It would be<br />
a return to the position which existe,[ under Labor. A situation<br />
in which growth stopped, and investment in plant and equipment<br />
declined two years out of three.<br />
The " Plan" advocated that there should be a cut in indirect<br />
taxes. Here I am afraid even the Shadow Treasurer's otherwise<br />
iron-clad credibility is stretched rather thin.<br />
The Labor Party, now the champions of reducing indirect taxes,<br />
in their three years increased their receipts from indirect<br />
taxes from $ 2.6 billion to $ 4.7 billion. Their last budget<br />
the much vaunted Hayden budget, greatly increased the average<br />
Australian's indirect taxes. The duty on a packet of<br />
cigarettes was increased by 6 cents; the duty on beer was<br />
increased by 4 cents a ten ounce glass.<br />
Cuts in indirect taxes would compromise the fight against inflation<br />
for very little positive return. There is, however, one<br />
element in the Hurford Plan that I must admit I am attracted<br />
to, if only it were possible. The proposal that, while allowing<br />
an unrestrained increase in the money supply, a more aggressive<br />
approach could be adopted to selling government bonds without<br />
increasing interest rates. If the Shadow Treasurer can expand<br />
on low this could be done, he would dwarf all other economists past<br />
and present, and not only Australia, but the rest of the world would<br />
be in his debt and we would not be slow to acknowledge<br />
his achievelment./ 4 </p>
<p>Hle could then rest on his laurels and do something<br />
eas~ y like inventing a perpetual motion machine.<br />
The Hurford plan is as interesting for the things it omits,<br />
as for the things it includes. The subject that is not<br />
mentioned is wages policy. This leaves the disinterested<br />
observer with a number of possible conclusions to draw:<br />
Labor has no wages policy, Labor does not regard wages as<br />
relevant to a statement on the economy. Or are we to assume<br />
that the Shadow Treasurer disagrees with this aspect of the<br />
Whitlam Plan?<br />
The Leader of the Opposition, as honourable members will remember,<br />
in his plan called for full wage indexation a policy that<br />
would further fuel inflation. On a television interview towards<br />
the end of last year, however, the Member for Adelaide<br />
did not think full wage indexation was appropriate.<br />
It may be, that in their usual gentlemanly fashion, the members<br />
of the Opposition have agreed not to inflame conflicts within<br />
their party by ignoring wages policy. The minor problem of<br />
wages policy aside the approach the Shadow Treasurer is<br />
advocating is the same approach that the A. L. P. adopted when it<br />
was in Government.<br />
This approach which brought with it inflation and unemployment<br />
a policy which brought with it increases in inflation, excessive<br />
increases in wages, increases in unemployment.<br />
One thing must, however, be conceded to the Member for Adelaidehis<br />
almost disarming candor. In this morning's " Canberra Times"<br />
he conceded that " The dangers in Labor's approach is the possibility.<br />
of further prolonging of inflation." But as he continued:<br />
" The Labor Party Parliamentary executive was well aware of this<br />
when preparing the proposal."<br />
What makes tI' HLhr'F(' rL. I'. 1 even -more absurd than it appears<br />
to be on its face, is that it is made at a time when the indicators<br />
of economic recovery are firming.<br />
Take inflation first. In the final year of Labor's administration<br />
calendar 1975, the rate ( based on aggregate expenditure<br />
deflators) was 17.2%. In the half year ending September 1976<br />
inflation was running at an annual rate of about 10.5% O.<br />
Consider growth. In its last year of office, Labor presided<br />
over the physical decline of most of the productive<br />
output of the economy. In calendar 1975 gross non-farm<br />
product fell. By September 1976 we had reversed that disastrous<br />
position. In the September quarter real gross non-farm product<br />
was, as shown in the national accounts, above the level<br />
of the previous December quarter. </p>
<p>Private invos tment subje~ ct to the Gov rnmeit s invcstmeut<br />
allowance rose in real terms by 4.3% 0 in the September half-year<br />
of 1976 compared with the previous half-year. This is the allowance<br />
which Labor says was ' only marginally useful."<br />
Since September there is evidence of further firming in<br />
production. In the December quarter, production of 23 of the<br />
31 items for which statistics are available increased on a<br />
seasonally adjusted basis compared with the previous quarter.<br />
In the December quarter the value of approvals for factories<br />
shops, warehouses, and other business premises was up by<br />
36% compared with the same period a year earlier.' In December<br />
the value of retail sales was 13.5% above the corresponding<br />
m1onthi in 1975.<br />
This recovery has seen the beginning of a reversal of the<br />
distortion of the profit-wage share which took place under Labor.<br />
Wher. we took up office, the ratio of gross operating surplus<br />
of trading companies to gross non-farm product at factcor<br />
cost was 12.4%. In the September quarter 1976, the ratio was<br />
14z%-still below the long run norm, but nevertheless. in the<br />
process of recovering. There is, inevitably, a delay before<br />
these recovery trends are reflected in greater employment.<br />
To begin with, C-s&gt;;,' 11O Shed less staff, then provide more<br />
overtime working for existing staff. But the decline int<br />
emp -oyment opportunities which was proceeding under Labor<br />
has been arrested.<br />
Finally, we have laid the foundations for continuing sound<br />
expansion of production, investment and employment.<br />
We have removed the arbitrary taxation bias introduiced by Labor<br />
a -gainst the mineral industry, and the benefits in terms of<br />
heightened exploration, discovery and development are now being seen.<br />
Labor killed off the search for oil in Australia at a -time when<br />
further discoveries were vital to our future. I am glad<br />
to ' report that with the abolition of the $ 2 a barrel levy on<br />
oil from new discoveries and the tax incentives announced in the<br />
last budget, oil exploration has revived. Last year 21<br />
exploration wells were drilled throughout Australia. This year<br />
the number is expected to be up to 44.<br />
In the private sector we have encouraged investment not<br />
damned it and penalised it. Under the new exchange rate mining<br />
companies will enjoy better opportunities to maintain and increase<br />
their share of world trade in minerals. Manufacturing companies<br />
will si! Pilarly be in a stronger position to compete both on<br />
the domestic market and in international markets. Investment<br />
opportunities will continue to grow, leading to higher<br />
employment. The policies underlying this improvement included a very deliberate<br />
ree. uction in the -rate of government spending, the holding of the<br />
rate of increase in money supply to levels consistent with a </p>
<p>progressive reduction in the rate of inflation, and a major<br />
refoc--i in thc perso: nal and income tax systems based on<br />
indexation and cost of sales valuation adjustment.<br />
The taxation reforms which we have made will amount to over<br />
$ 3000 million by'the end of the second year of operation.<br />
Those who look to overseas experience and believe that other<br />
nations particularly the U. S. and Japan are moving ahead<br />
faster than us in tlicfield of tax reform, should look at the<br />
facts clearly. No major tax reductions have been made or<br />
foreshadowed in Japan. The proposed but not implemented tax<br />
cuts in the U. S. the " once only" rebate are equal<br />
to less than $ 200 million if transposed to Australia.<br />
Compare the $ 990 million saving to taxpayers we brought about<br />
with tax indexationin 1976/ 77 and the $ D050 million savings anticipat.<br />
for 1977/ 78. We have always been, and still are, the first to<br />
point out that the inflationary momentum built up into our<br />
economy through the Labor years must be removed before the<br />
expansion I have referred to can be regarded as having taken<br />
firm roots.<br />
The Government is us-ing the arms of economic policy to continue<br />
the fight against inflation and continue progress towards sustained<br />
economic recovery. Policy action is being taken in all major<br />
areas monetary, budgetary and ~ wages.<br />
The policy of monetary restraint we are iuirsIIIc has led to<br />
adjustments to Government security yields and raising the statutory<br />
reserve deposit ratio. Prevention of over-rapid expansion in<br />
credit will curtail inflation.<br />
Selection controls on capital inflow are now preventing an<br />
inflationary surge of capital for non-essential purposes.<br />
Fiscal restraint required further cuts in Government spending<br />
and a commitment to zero real growth in the next financial year.<br />
Public service ceilings will be reduced by a further 700 by the<br />
end of this financial year.<br />
The wage restraint necessary to facilitate a reduction in the rateof<br />
inflation and provide jobs for all those who want to work will be<br />
pursued in the next national wage case.<br />
Ash ae sidgood progress was made through 1976. We are<br />
goingy to build on that achievement in 1977. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
