<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6165</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006165.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA JULY 31, 1983<br />
The Tasmanian Premier, Mr Gray, is being politically duplicitous<br />
in his reaction to*-the Federal Government's decision to stop<br />
funding for the Crotty Road construction.<br />
The road was to have been the prime access to the<br />
Franklin-below-Gordon Dam.<br />
With construction of the Dam stopped, the Crotty Road is an<br />
expensive thoroughfare to nowhere.<br />
Only last Monday, July 25, at a meeting wi th me, requested by<br />
Mr Gray, the Premier volunteered that the Tasmanian Government was<br />
not in favor of the road being further extended to Kelly Basin.<br />
There was general agreement that until the management plan for the<br />
wilderness area was agreed to by both governments there was little<br />
point in continuing with building a road which could eventually<br />
be irrelevant.<br />
Mr Gray pointed out to me that the State's announced intention to<br />
proceed with the construction of the King River hydro scheme would<br />
mean the partial flooding of Crotty Road.<br />
In effect, Mr Gray agrees with the'Federal Government's decision that<br />
work on the Crotty Road should cease. His anger is contrived.<br />
It ill-becomes Mr Gray to accuse the Federal Government of showing<br />
" la callous contempt for the workers". 7_ -r -7,77 J' </p>
<p>2<br />
Prior to the High Court decision it was Mr c ray who delayed<br />
Government-to-Government meetings proposed by me as a means of<br />
identifying alternative employment schemes to ensure a speedy 0 0<br />
transfer of the Dam workforce.<br />
The Federal Government's proposal for such meetings was made<br />
shortly after its election, but because of Mr Gray's attitude<br />
the first meeting was not held until late June.<br />
In its dealing with Mr Gray, the Labor Government has adopted a<br />
bipartisan attitude of goodwill and has had the welfare of<br />
all the people of Tasmania uppermost in its mind.<br />
It is to be hoped that Mr Gray's ill1-considered statements over<br />
the Crotty Road decision are not a manifestation of his attitude<br />
to the necessary future negotiations.<br />
The cessation of Federal funding for the Crotty Road will mean<br />
some disruption and uncertainty for the people employed on the<br />
project, and that is a matter for regret.<br />
But so that Mr Gray may be able to understand it, let me repeat:<br />
The Federal Government has agreed to extend for another month<br />
arrangements for income maintenance for HEC employees and for<br />
financial assistance to contractors, including assistance for<br />
contractors' employees.<br />
In the meantime, the Commonwealth will continue as quickly as possible<br />
in co-operation with State authorities, to identify altern ative<br />
employment projects.<br />
Provided Mr Gray is prepared to co-operate, I am sure the<br />
present problems will soon be overcome. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
