<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5849</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005849.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, JULY 4 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The Minister for Education recently announced Commonwealth<br />
education funding for 1983 of almost $ 3,000 million.<br />
Since this announcement there has been some discussion about<br />
the Commonwealth Government's education policy, and it is<br />
important to look at some of the key questions, especially<br />
about school funding, in a broader context.<br />
There has been a tremendous increase in the allocation of<br />
the nation's resources to education over the last ten years<br />
such that. $ 7,000 million was spent by Commonwealth and State<br />
governments on education in 1980-81. The very large sums of<br />
money provided for the education of Australians underlines<br />
the Government's continuing support for education as a<br />
priority commitment. Within this total allocation, the level<br />
of support by the Commonwealth and the States for schools<br />
has expanded substantially. The latest available figures,<br />
for 1979/' 80, show that just under $ 5,000 million was spent.<br />
by both Commonwealth and State governments on all schools,<br />
an amount: almost two-thirds higher in real terms than that<br />
recorded in 1971/ 72.<br />
Since 19* 79/ 80, Commonwealth and State expenditure has<br />
continued to increase. While the States provide about<br />
of fuands for government schools and have total responsibility<br />
for their administration, the Commonwealth also has a significant<br />
role in Supplementing State efforts.<br />
Commonwealth Government expenditure directed towards schools<br />
has expanded over recent years. It is over 7% higher in real<br />
terms this year than it was in 1976. It is worth noting<br />
that for 1983, the Commonwealth Government's allocation to<br />
education includes a real increase of 2% in general recurrent<br />
funding for government schools, and almost 95% increase for<br />
non-governiment schools will be directed to those with the<br />
greatest need.<br />
To put a proper perspective on the levels of government support<br />
for education, it is worth looking at the earlier findings of<br />
a special committee, known as the Karmel Committee, set up<br />
in 1972 to recommend appropriate target funding levels for<br />
all schools to be achieved by 1979. These targets were met for<br />
government schools in most States three years earlier than<br />
had beer. anticipated. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I would like to reflect for a moment on the significance<br />
of this commitment by government and what it means at the<br />
student level.. Total Commonwealth and State recurrent<br />
expenditure in 1979/ 80 on government schools amounted to<br />
over $ 1,700 per pupil, having steadily increased by 68%<br />
in real terms since 1971/ 72. And average class sizes have<br />
falled. In 1971, for example, in government schools there<br />
were about 22 students for every teacher. By 1981, these<br />
ratios had fallen so that there were about 16 students on<br />
average for every teacher.<br />
Despite the : improved student ratios, despite the fact<br />
that on average government schools have better student<br />
teacher ratioDs than non-government schools, despite more<br />
dollars on average going into government schools per<br />
student; there has been amarked shift inenrolments away<br />
from government schools in recent times.<br />
In the three years to 1981, total enrolments at government<br />
schools fell by 2.5% while total enrolments at non-government<br />
schools rose by Indeed, except for a small decline in<br />
primary enrolments at non-government schools betweeen 1971<br />
and 1976, there has been a steady overall increase in enrolments<br />
totalling almost 12% at non-government schools over the last<br />
decade.<br />
The shift inL preference to non-government schools has been<br />
particularly marked at the secondary level, where enrolments<br />
at government schools fell by over 4% between 1977 and 1980,<br />
in contrast to nearly 6% increase in non-government secondary<br />
school enrolments. Everyone interested in the well being of<br />
government schools governments themselves, parents,<br />
teachers and students must be concerned at these declining<br />
enrolments at government schools. Why have these shifts in<br />
preference taken place?<br />
In the early 1970s, many people thought that big spending on<br />
education was all that was needed to provide the kind of<br />
education that parents wanted for their children. Some<br />
sectional interests in the community have suggested that the<br />
shift in enrolments away from government schools has been<br />
caused by a squeeze in funding for those schools and<br />
increasing funding for non-government schools.<br />
It is plainly obvious that that just is not so. Despite<br />
increasing Commonwealth assistance to non-government schools,<br />
combined State and Commonwealth grants are still a long way<br />
below expenditure levels for government schoo * ls. Total<br />
grants for non-government schools amount to only 45% of<br />
expenditure on government schools on a per pupil basis,<br />
and even when school fees are taken into account, the resources<br />
available in most non-government schools are about 30% below<br />
those avail~ able in government schools. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The argument should not be about the level of funding for<br />
schools. Rather the concern should be about providing the<br />
right kind of education to meet the communities' requirements.<br />
The Government, for its part, has a responsibility to take<br />
action in the face of its concerns about the direction of<br />
school education in Australia and it has faced that<br />
responsibility. For example, the Commonwealth has introduced<br />
the school-to-work transition programme which is proving<br />
particularly successful in helping those less academically<br />
inclined. We are providing $ 150 million over a 5 year period<br />
for transition activities in schools and technical and<br />
further education colleges. These grants are being adjusted<br />
for inflation.<br />
More generally, the Government recognises the requirements<br />
of the community in respect of a balanaced education system<br />
one that caters for those who are aiming at tertiary<br />
education but equally for those who are less academically<br />
inclined; one that acknowledges the right of freedom of<br />
choice in education; one that promotes an effective school<br />
system which meets the educational aspirations of the whole<br />
community.<br />
The Government's approach to education reflects its broader<br />
philosophy that Australian families have the right and the<br />
freedom to decide for themselves their own needs, their own<br />
way of-life.<br />
Governments have acted responsibly in providing the<br />
resources to allow all schools to move to a position where<br />
they can provide the kind of education system that the community<br />
desires. I believe that all young Australians deserve an<br />
education system that is flexible enough to give its students<br />
the skills and training appropriate to their individual<br />
abilities and ambitions. The great challenge facing educators<br />
in the 1980s is to ensure that the education system works to<br />
ensure that this is achieved. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
