<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4214</transcript-id>
    <title>STAFF CEILINGS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004214.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
.) AUSTRA LAF6 7<br />
FOR PRESSAUGUST 17, 1976<br />
STAFF CEILINGS<br />
The Government has decided on a further reduction in staff ceilings.<br />
during 1976/ 77, for Government Departments and for authorities staffed<br />
under the Public Service Act, of about two per cent.<br />
The decision follows reductions announced on 14 June in staff ceilings<br />
for Departments and authorities staffed under the Public Service Act<br />
of 1.6 per cent, and reductions in ceilings for other statutory<br />
authorities subject to ceilings of 0.9 per cent.<br />
After allowance for the reductions announced in June, the total reduction<br />
in ceilings in all areas of Commonwealth employment over 1976/ 77 now<br />
being aimed at amounts to 2.5 per cent.<br />
The further reductions in staff ceilings in the Budget context have been<br />
made possible by the Government's overall programme of restraint in<br />
expenditure. Within the Public Service Act area the Public Service Board has been<br />
asked to control recruitment carefully, in order to achieve the<br />
reductions by natural wastage and redeployment.<br />
Ministers have been asked to keep me informed of any difficulties<br />
encountered in achieving the new ceilings.<br />
The Government wants to see its objectives achieved without personal<br />
hardship to its employees and without impairing the services that<br />
must be supplied to the Australian public.<br />
00... F76/ 171 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
