<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18549</transcript-id>
    <title>Michael Jeffery to lead fundraising for the Queen Elizabeth Diamond Jubilee Trust</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Former Australian Governor-General Major General Michael Jeffery AC CVO MC (Retd) has been appointed to lead the nation's fundraising efforts for The Queen Elizabeth Diamond Jubilee Trust.</p>
<p>The Trust aims to provide an enduring tribute to Her Majesty's dedication to public life through investing in charitable projects that will make a real and lasting impact on the lives of people throughout the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>The appointment of General Jeffery to spearhead national fundraising activities will help lift the profile of the trust.</p>
<p>General Jeffery will promote the work of the trust and encourage donations from businesses, communities, and individuals all around Australia.</p>
<p>General Jeffery's standing in the community and past service to the Queen make him well-suited to the role.</p>
<p>The trust, which was announced by Prime Minister David Cameron of the United Kingdom at the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Perth in October, was launched officially on 6 February.</p>
<p>The Australian Government pledged up to $5 million to the trust in February as part of Australia's commemoration of the Queen's diamond jubilee in 2012. The Prime Minister has also written to the premiers and chief ministers of states and territories encouraging them to match collectively the Commonwealth's contribution.</p>
<p>Australians will be able to donate to the trust for the duration of the jubilee year, with disbursements from the trust to begin in 2013.</p>
<p>General Jeffery served as the 27th governor of Western Australia from 1993 until 2000 and the 24th governor-general of Australia from 2003 until 2008. His appointments as governor and governor-general followed a long and decorated career in the Australian army.</p>
<p>The Queen's diamond jubilee in 2012 represents the 60th anniversary of the Queen's accession to the throne and her time as head of the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>For further information about the Trust, visit: <a href="http://www.jubileetribute.org/">http://www.jubileetribute.org/</a>. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
