<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1251</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS OF VICE-PRESIDENT HUBERT H. HUMPHREY AT PRIME MINISTER&#039;S LUNCHEON - CANBERRA - 19TH FEBRUARY, 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001251_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDI S OF VIQE-PRESIDENT HUBERT H. HUPHIREY<br />
AT PRIME MINISTER'S LUNCHEON<br />
Canberra 19th February, 1966<br />
Mr. Prime Minister and the 111inisters of the Government of<br />
Australia; my good friend Mr. Calwell, the Leader of the Opposition,<br />
but great Australian, great citizen, my friend that has been<br />
conversing with me during these moments of our luncheon; the great<br />
presiding officer of the Senate of the Australian Parliament, Sir<br />
Alister Mc½ ullin, we've settled most of the problems over here; my<br />
esteemed friend, the Ambassador of the United States, 11Mr. Clark, and<br />
of course all of the many good friends that we have that are here<br />
from other nations; your Excellencies the Ambassadors and Ministers,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
I must say first of all that I have been touched by the references<br />
to the Vice-Presidency. I have been told and I was aware of<br />
the fact that this is the second time in ten years that Australia has<br />
been visited by a Vice-President, which shows the gentle nature of the<br />
American public and the great consideration that we have for your -: ellbeing<br />
here. You can only take one of these Vice-Presidents about<br />
every decade. I also have been reinded as to the uncertainties of<br />
the political future of the Vice-Presidency and I've been well aware<br />
of it, and I've been making the most of every day that I have.<br />
I can't help but say, since the other visitor from the office of the<br />
Vice-Presidency was Mr. Richard 111N. i xon, that I have always patterned<br />
mj life and tried to emulate a gentleman by the name of Richard IA.<br />
Johnson Vice-President under van Buren. And I want you to know that<br />
Van Buren was a Democrat; the only partisan reference that I shall<br />
feel free to make.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister you have mentioned so rmany things here that<br />
I would like to cornent upon that i'm afraid that you've touched the<br />
favourite nerve cell in my body, namely the talking cell. You<br />
ought to be waare of that. But I've been told by Ambassador Clark,<br />
and by you, Sir, and others, that in Australia you just get up and<br />
give forth as much and as long as you want. So lean back my friends<br />
and start to enjoy what you haven't intended.<br />
First I want to say to Ambassador Clark that we're very proud<br />
of his work here. lie's been entertaining a host of visitors from<br />
the United States, and he's been able to manage Congressmen and<br />
Senators better than he did the Speaker of the House of Representatives<br />
or the Presiding Officer of the Senate, and they've come in substantial<br />
numbers. Time and Life and Newsweek have arrived to be able to guide<br />
you in matters of foreign ane, domestic policy; and I understand that<br />
Ford and General Motors have made their appearance or will. And<br />
you will even have my good friend George Moore of the First National<br />
City Bank of New York.<br />
With this combination, plus the Vice-President once in every<br />
ten years, you ought to be able to survive. In fact I think you'll<br />
do well even if we hadn't have come. But the fact is that we're<br />
very, very pleased that we've received the kind of gracious, warm,<br />
friendly, home-like reception that you have accorded us.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, ou mentioned that I had some resoonsibilities<br />
in the field of Space. Well isn't it good to come and see friends<br />
who are with you both in heaven and earth. And you are here in<br />
Australia. I recall one of the first flights in our Gemini programme.<br />
We Americans listened on the radio to the broadcast of how the citizens<br />
of Perth were turning on their lights so that the Astronaut ight know<br />
that he was over friendly territory in Australia. We never had any </p>
<p>doubt about that even if your lights Were out we knew that there<br />
would be a friend waiting for us with a warm hand of friendship.<br />
I must say that our relationships have made us feel like<br />
brothers and sisters. And today you went the extra mile I just<br />
can't tell you how much I've appreciated everything that has<br />
happened. Last night when ve set foot on your precious soil and<br />
I lo6ked about it seemed like the sunset, in the great Mid-West as<br />
I would say if I were not under some constraints, but as I wo. uld<br />
say, as it were, in South-Western Texas.<br />
One can't say in Australia that it was a miniature because this<br />
country is so big. This is one of the few countries that mke the<br />
Texan feel like that he has an inferiority complex. You gave us a<br />
beautiful, beautiful entrance to your lovely and dynamic country and<br />
then this morning as I awakened and looked out and felt the crisp air<br />
I knew then it was almost like 1 nnesota, my State. And then when<br />
I came from the Parliament Building just after the noon hcur and<br />
I looked out front and there were the placards and amateur sign<br />
painters and all the demonstrators, I said; " 4hat this Prime Minister<br />
,-ill do to make me feel at home:" I just can't properly and<br />
adequately express my profound. gratitu e to him for this feeling of<br />
ease and adjustment that you give me as I stand on foreign shores.<br />
But I want you to know that my investigation indicates that while you<br />
went to great lengths to get that demonstration No. 1, it is not as<br />
large as we can produce at Berkeley. And, No. 2, the Leader was<br />
from America. One of our exports. We do it up well and the exchange<br />
programme continues.<br />
Next time vwe find a group of protestors in America I am going<br />
to ask if there is an Australian, and if there isn't, why, we are<br />
going to have to call off the protest. We believe in quid pro quo<br />
you laow, " fifty-fifty".<br />
Now in all seriousness, I do rant to say to all of our good<br />
friends here, the High Conrnissioners that represent members of the<br />
Commonwealth, to our friends of the Press of Australia and other areas,<br />
to the good citizens of this great country, and to my fellow: Americans,<br />
that it is a very re-assuring and gratifying and energizing experience<br />
to be able to exchange viewers with the Government people such as I've<br />
met here today in Australia.<br />
We have been able to talk frankly, candidly, expressing our<br />
points of view 7-ithout any fear or without any concern as to their<br />
being properly understood and accepted as the honest expressions of<br />
people with an integrity and sincerity of purpose. And I can say<br />
that in every free country we have opposition and it is the opposition<br />
which in a very real sense keeps us on course. Opposition in a<br />
democracy is as vital, may I say, as the seasons in a full year.<br />
And to Mr. Calwell, the Leader of the Opposition, may I express<br />
to you my personal thanks for your gracious remarks and for your<br />
presence here at this luncheon.<br />
I hadn't quite known ", hat I should say to you today, and I've<br />
decided that the best thing to do would be to talk to you as friend<br />
and neighbour. Last evening after having had the opportunity to go<br />
to the Ambassador's residence to unpack our cases and to just settle<br />
down, we placed a telephone call to a great anad distinguished<br />
statesman, not only of Australia but of the world, Sir Robert Menzies,<br />
and ve had a delightful hour and a half with this remarkable nan. </p>
<p>Sir Robert is a friend not only of the people of Australia and<br />
a leader in this great nation but he is a friend and leader for all<br />
of us. He has come to our country, the United States, on repeated<br />
occasions and he is accepted as a brother, almost as a fellow citizen.<br />
Yet he is so devoted to his own Australia that he would not want anyone<br />
to dilute his patriotic devotion to his own citizenship by even<br />
a remark that might be misunderstood or misinterpreted. \ Ve respect<br />
his judgment. We admire his patriotism, his courage, and we enjoy<br />
his wit. President Johnson considers him one of his close friends.<br />
And may I say to the distinguished new Prime Minister, Mr.<br />
Holt, that we look upon you, Sir, as a continuing friend. As one of<br />
whose counsel and advice we welcome and whose friendship we, too,<br />
cherish. And ve know that in the days ahead that the Prime Minister<br />
of Australia this Prime Minister will have in the hearts of the<br />
American people that abundance of affection and respect which was so<br />
evident for Sir Robert Menzies.<br />
So we feel at home, and I want to talk to you now as just<br />
neighbours. Australia, as the Prime Minister has so well noted, has<br />
been with us in peace and war, and we with Australia and Australians.<br />
Our sons and men have come here to meet you and marry your daughters<br />
and sisters. Our nations believe in parliamentary democracy.<br />
We have common ideals and in a very real sense common traditions.<br />
But our traditions and our ideals are not unique to ourselves. This<br />
principle and this belief in human dignity is no monopoly of Americans<br />
or Australians or the English. There are people of every race creed<br />
and nationality that believe in human dignity. And there are people<br />
of every region of this world and of every race, and every ethnic<br />
group, and of every persuasion, that believe in freedom. And<br />
I believe that most of mankind longs for peace.<br />
So that we have many things in common. And when we speak of<br />
consultation amongst ourselves Australians and Americans, the<br />
United Kingdom, and New Zealand. We do not speak of that consultation<br />
as an exclusive club. But rather we speak of it as one of the<br />
approaches to be of help to others, and to broaden that great community<br />
of free men and free nations so that we can work together in common<br />
cause and common purpose.<br />
The great need today of the freedom-loving peoples of this<br />
world is to recognize, No. 1, the problems that confront us, and agree<br />
upon those problems; and No. 2, the necessity of united purpose and<br />
the united effort in meeting those problems.<br />
A great American statesman and a great human being, Dr. Benjamin<br />
Franklin, once said that " We either hang together or we hang separately."<br />
And I might say that those words of wisdom, colloquial as they were<br />
have a universal application. And all through Asia and Africa and<br />
Europe, Latin America, North America, South America, wherever you go,<br />
free men and free nations and those who aspire to freedom had better<br />
rec nize that there are powerful forces arrayed against them. That<br />
there are difficult problems that yet beset mankind the problems that<br />
we spoke of here of poverty, of illiteracy, of disease, of despair,<br />
of hopelessness, of frustration that these are the common problems<br />
of most of mankind. and that we should unite in a common effort to<br />
overcome them.<br />
We should also recognize that the forces of tyrrany which are<br />
at work in the world today, while different in their methodology, are<br />
no different in their purpose than all of history. Tyrants are<br />
tyrants. Despots are despots. The method, however, and the<br />
strategy and the tactics of the 20th century tyranny are far more </p>
<p>sophisticated far more complicated than those that mankind has<br />
known in other cent ries.<br />
And it is because of this compleity of both the problems<br />
and the opposition, or the enemy, that we sometimes fall apart;<br />
that we sometimes have differences even though there need be<br />
none. It's because . we haven't as yet quite understood individually<br />
and collectively how best to approach this new set of<br />
circumstances that confronts us.<br />
President Johnson asked me to journey to Asia, South East<br />
Asia, and the sub-continent, and then down under to Australia and<br />
New Zealand. Not to tell people what to think, but to let you<br />
know that we're thinking about in our country and to try to find<br />
some common denominators, and to share in your wisdom, your<br />
observations, and to give you some of our observations and our<br />
considerations on these problems that affect our world. And<br />
I have reported today to this government, as I have to others,<br />
on the observations that w-e have made on this journey.<br />
This distinguished American statesman that is with us<br />
one of our seasoned diplomats a great public servant Governor<br />
Averell Harriman, Ambassador-at-Large for the President of the<br />
United States we have reported what we have witnessed in Vietnam,<br />
in Thailand, in Laos, in Pakistan, in India and we have shared<br />
views and thoughts with the leaders of your government.<br />
And how happy I am today to say that we see these things<br />
very much the same way. When I listened to the Prime Minister<br />
in his remarks, I said, tthealtl', s what I want to say." This<br />
is what I tried to say. But how well he said it.<br />
In my visit this morning with the Ministers and the Prime<br />
Minister I believe that I expressed about as clearly and w-ith as<br />
much articulation as I am capable of, .1what was said here today<br />
and what I hope now to be able to say to you.<br />
First of all let me say this: we must look upon Southeast<br />
Asia and the sub-continent as regions. We cannot afford<br />
to direct our energies toward individual nation-states if the<br />
problems of those nation-states were unconnected with other<br />
nation states. South-east Asia was looked upon by President Johnson in<br />
his memorable address at John Hopkins back in April as a region<br />
for economic development regional economic development.<br />
I submit that it is also a region in the conflict which is<br />
now under way. In that region we are fighting two wars and we're<br />
allies in those two wars. The Australians and the Americans,<br />
the New Zealanders and the Koreans, standing alongside of our<br />
good friends, the people of South Vietnam, -ho are bearing the<br />
brunt of the battle. Who have been pummelled, who have been<br />
attacked, who have been abused, whose leaders have been assassinated,<br />
who have been the victims of terror and subversion and<br />
propaganda the likes of which few people have ever been able to<br />
withstand or to take. </p>
<p>Let me say that we all owe a debt of respect to the people<br />
of South Vietnam. For years they have been under merciless attack<br />
not conventional war not with the rules of war as civilised<br />
nations have known them, but a new form of war the wars of<br />
National Liberation they call them from Peking. What a play<br />
on words: How the communists have destroyed the meaning of words.<br />
They speak of liberation when they mean oppression. They<br />
speak of a people's republic when they have no regard for the people<br />
and no definition or understanding of the world republic. They<br />
speak of the people's democracies and there is not a single<br />
democratic thought or institution thatTs been developed. The<br />
communists have polluted and adulterated the meaning of words that<br />
decent humanity has known for centuries.<br />
I think it is about time that we understood that fact. They<br />
not only fight us with weapons; they not only use every conceivable<br />
device that is known for the purpose of human destruction; they<br />
destroy the meaning of language. They destroy the meaning of the<br />
precious word. Words like " freedom". Words like " democracy".<br />
' Words like " liberty". Words like " justice". These are words of<br />
the spirit. These are precious words.<br />
The communists not only destroy the village and the hamlet in<br />
South Vietnam he not only attacks established government and tries<br />
to discredit it in nation after nation. He destroys the very<br />
meaning of life as one interprets it in the written word and the<br />
spoken word. So we have a newr war that we battle that we fight. We're<br />
really trying to save the moaning of our language. We are trying<br />
to save the legal definition of our constitutions. We're trying to<br />
protect if you please the territory and the geography of our land.<br />
But above all we are trying to save a way of life.<br />
Not the way of life in terms of the past but a way to approach<br />
life where mankind can be liberated from disease and from poverty,<br />
and from hunger.<br />
We are the revolutionists not the communists. Wie are the<br />
liberators not the communists. We are the agents of justice and<br />
reform not the communists. I for one don't intend to let them<br />
get by with claiming the honours that are due to the people that are<br />
in this room and other people around this world that believe in<br />
freedom and justice and independence.<br />
So, we find ourselves in conflict today in Vietnam. But<br />
. may I say quite frankly that we've also faced other dangers. The<br />
conxmunists would like us out of Berlin. And isn't it interesting<br />
that the very same people who advocate that we stand firm in Berlin,<br />
deep in the land of communist control, in an area that is militarily<br />
difficult to defend the very same people who would pledge all of<br />
our resources, as we said in our Declaration of Independence, our<br />
lives, our fortunes, and our sacred honour the very same people<br />
who say we must stand firm in Berlin regardless of the cost, can<br />
turn around and advocate that you forget Vietnam?<br />
I guess they may feel that somehow or other, whatever is<br />
going on in Vietnam, that the Viet Cong, represents a sort of an<br />
international reform movement. Frustrated social workers who<br />
believe in human progress: </p>
<p>Well lot mo assure you that that is not the Viet Cong. There<br />
may be those in the Viet Cong that are the victims of frustration<br />
and bitterness over the iany years of colonialism and the lack of<br />
opportunity and justice in Vietnam. But the Viet Cong is no social<br />
reformdo-gooder outfit. It is made up of a hard corps of<br />
disciplined warriors, backed by Hanoi and backed by Peking. Just<br />
exactly, mpy I say, as East Berlin is backed by the Soviet Union.<br />
So we have met the menaco of couniasm before. We mot it in<br />
Berlin and we didn't flinch. And because we didn't there's peace<br />
in Europe. We have met the nnace of com. munism in Greece. And some people<br />
said it was just a little civil war. But isn't it interesting that<br />
when Yugoslavia broke with the Soviet Union, or Marshal Tito broke<br />
with Stalin, closed the border then the lifeline from Moscow to<br />
Belgrade into the hills and the mountains of Greece when that lifeline<br />
was chocked off that the Greek Civil War came to an end?<br />
It wasn't a civil war as such. To be sure, there were Greeks<br />
involved. But it was one that was : master-minded in those days from<br />
Moscow, it was supplied from Belgrade, and it was fought on the plains<br />
and the mountains of Greece.<br />
Harry S. Truman, President of the United States, was the author<br />
of the Greek-Turkish Aid Programe. General Van Fleet from the<br />
United States xvent to Greece. W'e met the communist threat in Greece<br />
and by the strange developments of international politics over which<br />
we had no control the supply line and the efforts of the communist<br />
powers were cut off and the Greek Civil War ended.<br />
People say that you should be careful of these comparisons<br />
because they don't alrays add up the same. That's true. There are<br />
details that are different. But the fundamentals are the same.<br />
We met coimmunist power in Korea. We did not seek a battlefield<br />
in Korea. In fact we have said that we had no interest in<br />
Korea, or little interest. And that was the warning. That was the<br />
alert. The communist forces from the North struck South Korea,<br />
violating every international pledge and every international<br />
agreement. And we met the communist power in Korea.<br />
We met it in Berlin. We met it in Korea. We met it when<br />
Mr. IKhrushchev tried to put his missiles in Cuba, and now wre are<br />
meeting it in Vietnam.<br />
It's different this time. A new communist force. A very<br />
militant communist force. An aggressive militant regime in Peking.<br />
It has no regard for international law. It speaks with disdain of<br />
even its commnunist associates. It has little or no regard for<br />
standards for international conduct.<br />
What you see in Vietnam today is not a civil war, but you see<br />
the projection of a massive international communist doctrine at work<br />
wars of national liberation being tested in the test tube of Vietnam.<br />
The pilot project of cormmunist strategy. Peking to Hanoi bo the<br />
rice paddies and the mountains and the valleys of Vietnam. </p>
<p>And we have to meet it. We didn't choose the battlefield.<br />
We never will choose a battlefield. We can't as free people. We do<br />
not believe in attack. We do not believe in aggression. We do<br />
not believe in preventive war. We cannot select the time or the day<br />
or the enemy or place. It is impossible. We simply have to meet<br />
the attack where it comes.<br />
Now the lessons of history teach us and surely Australians<br />
have known it more than almost any others because even though you are<br />
far removed from many areas of the world you were among the first to<br />
recognize that the trouble in North Africa was your danger. The<br />
trouble in Korea thousands of miles away was your trouble. You have<br />
not failed to understand international responsibility and international interdopendence.<br />
And so today, Australia finds herself in Vietnam.<br />
Not only because of Australia, but because it understands that<br />
aggression unckecked is aggression unleashed. It understands that<br />
te aggressor's appetite is insatiable. It understands that<br />
aggression if left without being stopped can become a pattern of<br />
international conduct. And there will be no little nations left.<br />
The powerful will consume the small and the w; eak.<br />
So the United States of America and others, our good friends<br />
here in Australia, stand shoulder to shoulder. Not because there is<br />
an immediate threat to Australia. Not because of an immediate threat<br />
to the United States. In our lifetime we could maybe forget this and<br />
be buried in the knowledge that nothing had hit us as yet. But men<br />
in public life have a greater obligation than to think about the<br />
immediate. You must take a look at the future.<br />
And if there is any one lesson in history that should have<br />
been drilled into the minds of contemporaries it is this that you<br />
can never let the aggressor have his way. If he has his way then<br />
there is no way for free people except the way of despair and<br />
destruction. So, my message to you today is the old simple message that we<br />
must work together and we must work together not only militarily, but<br />
we must work together in the good works of mankind. We're not<br />
warriors. My country does not want to be known as a nation of<br />
warriors. We want to be known as a nation of healers, of educators,<br />
of engineers, of builders. We w-ant to be known as strong in spirit,<br />
not in flesh. We want to be known as a nation whose wealth and<br />
power is not for luxury or self-indulgence, but rather for service<br />
and for protection for the weak.<br />
That is the purpose of power, and that is the -purpose of wealth.<br />
We're blessed in our country with wealt' and with power. And I think<br />
that the real tribute to the United States of America and to Australia<br />
is that with our high standards of living we seek not to keep it just<br />
for ourselves. We ve abandoned selfishness and indulgence, and self<br />
indulgence. And we have recognised that there is a brotherhood that<br />
needs us and we need them. So we engage in the good works and that<br />
was the purpose of the Honolulu Conference.<br />
President Johnson went to Honolulu to revie. w, indeed, the<br />
military situation, but more importantly he went there to work with<br />
the leaders of South Vietnami in designing a social revolution for<br />
South Vietnam. To heli rebuild the villages and the hamlets that<br />
had been systematically decimated and destroyed by the Viet Cong<br />
the communists. To give the people hope the politics of hope.<br />
To lift their sights from the battlefields to the construction of<br />
new homes and villages and schools and hospitals. And it is in this<br />
part of the war, this other way, against man's ancient enemies that<br />
we need a great deal of help. </p>
<p>Everywhere I have been I have found Australia. I found Australia<br />
in India. I found Australia in the Colombo Plan in the Colombo Plan<br />
countries. I found Australia in Pakistan. I found Australia in<br />
Vietnam. I found Australia in the generous contribution to the Asian<br />
Bank. We have found Australian docLors and hospitals in Vietnam.<br />
' ie found Australian soldiers on the battlefield.<br />
And, may I say to you Australians ve are proud of you-proud<br />
of you as friends and allies. You imake our hearts grateful and warm<br />
and lad because this is real international responsibility. This is<br />
the real strength of a nation.<br />
The strength of a nation is not in its armament alone. The<br />
strength of a nation is in its people and their purpose. And, you<br />
have demonstrated that strength of people and purpose.<br />
Now I come away from this tour with what I said this morning<br />
was restrained optimism.<br />
I cannot say that all is going well because all is not going<br />
well. But, I can say in Australia that in the year 1942, in the year<br />
1941, you could not say that things were going well either, but you<br />
did not quit. As a matter of fact anyone that was looking at the<br />
realities of the time in 1940, just the sheer dark realities, would<br />
have said we are whipped.<br />
The difference was in spirit and determination. The English<br />
did not have a chance after Dunkirk logistically, in equipment and<br />
supplies, but they had a chance because they refused to give up.<br />
The Australiarsdid not have much of a chance either after Pearl<br />
Harbour, but you did not give up. And we did not have much of a one<br />
either but ve did not give up.<br />
So, to the doubters and we have plenty to those who feel<br />
somehow or other that this struglo in Vietnamo cannot be won I say<br />
to you it can: What is m. ore important I say to you it must.<br />
You cannot afford to lose it, because the first time that Free<br />
Nations lose a con. test with militant coim1munist aggression, the first<br />
time you retreat, the first time that you fold up your tents, the<br />
first time that a people are sold out on that day no one will over<br />
believe free men again.<br />
If I seei to be overly enthusiastic a I'm sometimes accused,<br />
may I say that I have history on my side. History on the side of<br />
human spirit. History on the side of people w ho love freedom.<br />
If you love it enough and if you stay united; if free nations<br />
will understand across this whole underbelly of Asia, and throughout<br />
the : orld, that there are poweful forces that would destroy every<br />
institution in which you and I believe, those powerful forces that work<br />
the free nations : ill understand that we have a coi7mmon cuse, and we<br />
have a coimmon purpose; that we need each other those forces of evil<br />
and destruction cannot win.<br />
The Indians in India have tasted communist aggression across<br />
their borders in the movement of armies from Communist China.<br />
The Thai are tasting infiltration and subversion now as even<br />
I speak to you.<br />
The Laotians have been plagued by the Pathet Lao now fortified<br />
the North Vietnamese regulars. </p>
<p>And Vietnam has been going through fire and devastation for<br />
years. lWhat more do we need to tell us that there is a great effort<br />
being made on the part of the Cormunist Chinese to exert its influence<br />
and its power and its control over the rice fields, the grea. t natural<br />
resources of the sub-continent, and South-east Asia, and the people<br />
thereof? Either direct control by conquest or control by fear and<br />
terror. And yet, this force need not win and it : ill not win and I will<br />
tell you why. Because the United States of America, in concert with<br />
its allies, will not let it win.<br />
And this is why freedom loving people everiyhere have a stake<br />
in South Vietnam.<br />
Maybe your contribution will only be a laboratory; maybe it will<br />
only be a Doctor, maybe it Jill only be a few people to help with the<br />
refugees. But in South Vietnam there ought to be on the part of<br />
freedom loving people some symbol of the unity of free nations on the<br />
part of every nation that loves freedom. If that symbolic unity is<br />
there, mark my words that Communism, the communist juggernaut, will<br />
be halted just as it wlas in wejt Europe when free nations banded<br />
together when 1IATA was designed, when the Marshal Plan went into<br />
action, when UN. Pii was applied, when one operation after another was<br />
brought to bear to unite the people to rebuild a continent and to<br />
revitalize nations. And it did not bring on a world war it saved<br />
a world from a world war.<br />
I conclude in this thought: Many people have said what we want<br />
is peace. May I say to you that the President of the United States<br />
is a man who believes in peace with a passion politically,<br />
spiritually, morally.<br />
But we wanted peace in 1939, in 1940 and in 1941. We did not<br />
fight Hitler for conquest or Tojo, nor did you. You fought in<br />
World War II for peace.<br />
We arc not fighting in Vietnam for conquest or for territories.<br />
We are fighting there for peace and we are prepared for peace. We<br />
have offered peace negotiations for peace, and conferences for<br />
peace. We have offered economic assistance to friend and foe alike<br />
if there be peace. We have been rebuked. We shall pursue the<br />
course for peace. We shall not be restrained because Hanoi and<br />
Peking have arrogantly cast aside our offers of peace. We shall<br />
pursue peace relentlessly and we shall also pursue the enemy relentlessly<br />
because I happen to believe that you will gain peace when the<br />
enemy finds out that he cannot gain his objectives by brutality and<br />
force. And as soon as it is crvstil clear that force is not to<br />
achieve the objective, then the hope of peace is all the better.<br />
Until that day peace will be elusive if not impossible. So<br />
may I thank you once again, our comrades in arms and our comrades in<br />
peace in Australia. Thank you for what you are. Thank you for what<br />
you've been. Thank you for what you will be, because your leadership<br />
in the Pacific, your leadership in the Indian Ocean area, and your<br />
leadership in Asia, is vital and may I urge upon you to work diligently,<br />
ceaselessly with those of like mind, wherever they may be, try to find<br />
the paths of peace and make those paths of peace the paths of the<br />
hearts of men. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
