<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9897</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP RESIGNATION OF PRIME MINISTER MURAYAMA </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009897.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I' 4o1Uu, 0u l1 . iJ/ I<br />
ACTING PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE HON KIM BEAZLEY MP<br />
RESIGNATION OF PRIME MINISTER MURAYAMA<br />
Prime Minister Murayama, who announced his resignation earlier today,<br />
made a major contribution to Japanese public life at an important time in<br />
Japan's history.<br />
He presided during a period of unprecedented change in the Japanese<br />
political scene and of great 9conomic challenges for Japan.<br />
He showed dignity and leadership in encouraging Japan to come to terms<br />
with the country's wartime past, especially through his comments marking the<br />
fiftieth anniversary of the end of the Second World War. Those comments<br />
were appreciated in Australia and in the region.<br />
His commitment to building a prosperous and stable future for the Asia-<br />
Pacific region was underlined by his leadership in APEC, including as chair of<br />
the most recent leaders' meeting in Osaka.<br />
Prime Minister Murayama has also made a notable contribution to further<br />
building Australia's unique partnership with Japan. The Joint Declaration on<br />
the Australia-Japan Partnership by Prime Ministers Keating and Murayama<br />
last May provided an enduring statement of both countries' commitment to<br />
strengthening our bilateral ties, and to working together to promote<br />
prosperity, and to enhance political cooperation in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
The Australian Government appreciates Prime Minister Murayama's<br />
contribution and looks forward to working closely with his successor.<br />
MELBOURNE January 1996 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
