<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4897</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN WOOLGROWERS&#039; AND GRAZIERS&#039; COUNCIL CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004897.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F7 8/ 2 42<br />
! 3<br />
1, A USTRA IA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 20 NOVEMBER 1978<br />
AUSTRALIAN WOOLGROWERS' AND GRAZIERS' COUNCIL<br />
CANBE RRA<br />
This is the first time, and as you know probably the last time,<br />
that I will be addressing an A. W. G. C. convention. The Council<br />
can look back with pride on the many achievements it and its<br />
predecessors have made since the formation of the Pastoralists<br />
Federal Council in 1890.<br />
Particularly we can recall the successful campaign in the<br />
1930' s to win the support of the industry and the Government<br />
for a wool tax to finance wool promotion and research a move<br />
which led to the formation of the Wool Board in 1936.<br />
Now the Council is in the forefront of the negotiations to<br />
establish a national farmers federation. I welcome the<br />
proposed establishment of the federation, and I congratulate<br />
this council on its determination to achieve a strong, united<br />
voice for Australian primary producers.<br />
The Government is committed to consulting closely' with<br />
representative organisations on rural policy. Our task is made<br />
far easier, and the consultations far more effective, if the<br />
rural community speaks with one voice.<br />
One issue on which all sections of the rural community have<br />
long spoken with absolute unanimity is the need to reduce<br />
inflation and keep rises in farm costs to a minimum.<br />
We recognise that the continuing viability of our export industries<br />
depends on our success in controlling inflation. The farmer<br />
is not generally protected by indexed prices for his products.<br />
His ability to make profits depends on his costs being low<br />
enough to enable him to sell his produce at competitive prices.<br />
The rural recession which we are only now pulling through was<br />
in large part due to a crippling increase in farm costs. In<br />
1974/ 75, these rose a devastating 30 per cent in just 12 months,<br />
at the very time when prices for farm products were actually<br />
falling. The result was that real farm incomes almost halved<br />
in that year. / 12 </p>
<p>-2<br />
The farming community was in dire straits yet Mr Whitlam<br />
had told them in February 1974: " You've never had it so good".<br />
Today better prices, a far lower rise in farm costs and good<br />
seasonal conditions are reflected in renewed optimism among<br />
farmers. The combination of these three factors will lead to<br />
an expected rise in over 30 per cent in average farm incomes<br />
in real terms this year.<br />
This expected increase is significantly helped by the good<br />
trends we are seeing in beef prices, which are far better now<br />
than for some years. This is partly as a result of the efforts<br />
made to get fairer and more secure access to overseas markets.<br />
Sheep and wool prices are also reasonably good, and we have this<br />
year moved up the wool reserve price by a further five per cent.<br />
The wheat industry is experiencing a boom year with a huge<br />
crop and good prices.<br />
The improved outlook for farmers is also good news for country<br />
towns and all those industries supplying equipment and services<br />
for our rural community. Farmers are now able to re-equip and<br />
undertake long-deferred investment in their properties and<br />
this will mean more jobs for those whose livelihood depends on<br />
supplying the needs of rural producers.<br />
We should never underestimate the close interdependence that<br />
exists between country and city. A depressed and impoverished<br />
rural sector depresses the entire economy, and conversely, an<br />
optimistic and strengthening outlook for farmers can provide a<br />
real boost to all sectors of our economy.<br />
Prospects for farmers will further improve as inflation keeps<br />
on falling, for we are far from satisfied that it is low enough<br />
yet. We are determined not to let up in the fight against<br />
inflation. Our aim is to get Australia's inflation rate well<br />
below that of our trading partners and competitors, and well<br />
below that of other countries which compete with us for investment<br />
capital. In this respect, I note that fundamental principles of the<br />
economic policies we have been pursuing are increasingly being<br />
embraced by many countries overseas, including such Socialist<br />
governments as the British Labour Government. They know, as<br />
we do, that is is essential to beat inflation, and that high<br />
rates of unemployment, which are a matter of great concern to<br />
us all, will never be eradicated unless inflation is cut right<br />
back. Our success to date in reducing inflation has also enabled<br />
wide-ranging cuts in interest rates. Interest rates for home<br />
loans were reduced last February. Interest rates for small<br />
overdrafts, personal loans and short term loans were cut by the<br />
trading banks three weeks ago, and a further cut in housing<br />
loan interest rates was announced last Friday. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Falling interest rates provide a substantial boost to industry,<br />
to home buyers and to small businessmen. The cut of one half<br />
a per cent in the rates set by the new Primary Industry Bank<br />
will be of direct benefit to many rural producers.<br />
Because of our commitment to the continuing strength and<br />
viability of our rural industries, the Government has assisted<br />
farmers in a variety of ways to get through the recent rural<br />
recession. This has been a high Government priority, even<br />
during a period of severe budgetary restraint.<br />
The special assistance we have made available to the beef<br />
industry and the new and comprehensive Rural Adjustment Scheme<br />
we introduced have helped a significant number of farmers through<br />
this most difficult period. Total payments under the Beef<br />
Incentive Payments Scheme alone have exceeded $ 100 million.<br />
The beef industry was particularly hard hit by the cost-price<br />
squeeze, and our support at a critical period enabled many<br />
cattlemen to remain in the industry and to take advantage of<br />
the higher prices now being experienced.<br />
We have also given high priority to such measures as the Fuel<br />
Price Equalisation Scheme, re-introduction of the Phosphate<br />
Bounty, increased support for rural roads, and the abolition<br />
of Estate and Gift Duty.<br />
Individual rural industries have received strong support too.<br />
Immediately upon coming to office, the first advance wheat payment<br />
was raised; the wool reserve price was increased; approval was<br />
given to the Australian Wool Corporation to borrow overseas and<br />
reduce its interest charges; new underwriting and marketing<br />
arrangements for dairying were introduced; and further help<br />
was given to the fruit industry.<br />
We have also introduced various measures of tax relief: Income<br />
Equalisation Deposits; a fairer system of tax averaging; Stock<br />
Valuation Adjustment which the Government extended to include<br />
livestock; the Investment Allowance; and tax indexation.<br />
In addition, even taking into account the temporary tax increase<br />
for this financial year, tax rates have been cut substantially.<br />
Now that farmers' incomes are improving, these measures which<br />
prevent sudden tax increases through inflation or fluctuating<br />
incomes will be of great assistance to the rural community.<br />
I would expect Income Equalisation Deposits, which currently<br />
stand at about $ 65 million, to become much more popular with<br />
farmers as their incomes increase. / 4<br />
1. </p>
<p>In our endeavour to minimise increases in farm costs, the<br />
Government is giving considerable support to industry<br />
research programmes. Recently the Minister for Primary<br />
Industry announced a grant of $ 12.5 million for sheep and<br />
wool research this financial year.<br />
In the meat industry, with its long and involved market<br />
chain, there would appear to be scope for significant<br />
cost savings.<br />
We hope that the work now under way with our support on<br />
meat classification will achieve an acceptable system,<br />
leading to a significant breakthrough in meat marketing.<br />
The release of the recent IAC Report on the Wheat Industry<br />
has, I know, sparked an intense debate on marketing reform<br />
in the industry. The Government has decided not to make<br />
a decision on this all important matter until growers have<br />
had ample opportunity to debate the matter fully. You may<br />
be sure that when the Government finally takes a decision in<br />
consultation with the States, your views will be given every<br />
consideration. The most efficient production and marketing systems are of<br />
little effect, however, unless the products can be shipped<br />
out of the country. We are determined to take every step to<br />
make sure that the deplorable interference with some rural<br />
exports which we have witnessed in the past 12 months is<br />
not repeated. Because we found during the live sheep export<br />
disputes that the relevant legislation had some deficiencies,<br />
we are moving to overcome them. on 26 October the Government<br />
introduced into Parliament new legislation to amend Section 45 ( D)<br />
of the Trade Practices Act, to provide a more effective legal<br />
remedy against any recurrence of such disruption.<br />
As a trading nation we are dependent on our sea and air links.<br />
These links must remain open so that we can export and import<br />
at times most favourable to our seasons, to our economy and<br />
to our balance of trade. Any disruption of overseas trade<br />
adds to the cost burdens borne by all of us. It strikes at<br />
the heart of the prosperity of our economy.<br />
I believe that the new legislation will be widely endorsed<br />
as a positive and effective measure to enable individuals<br />
and governments to deal quickly and decisively with crippling<br />
boycotts.<br />
A major objective of the Government during our term of office<br />
has been to help exporters, particularly agricultural exporters,<br />
to secure fair and adequate market access overseas for<br />
their produce. We have pressed our case with far greater<br />
vigour than in the past. We have made it clear that we are<br />
not prepared indefinitely to tolerate restrictions which<br />
completely close markets to our products unfairly<br />
discriminating against Australian farmers who in many cases<br />
are some of the lowest cost producers in the world. </p>
<p>The aim of our bilateral negotiations with the EEC has<br />
been to seek changes in the Community's Common Agricultural<br />
Policy which are quite marginal in their effect on the<br />
Community yet are quite essential for our primary producers.<br />
After two years of concerted effort, our arguments are<br />
beginning to have their effect.<br />
I have been much encouraged by the devastating criticism made<br />
by senior members of the British Government against aspects<br />
of the Common Agricultural Policy during the past week.<br />
Last Monday, Mr. Callaghan called for three changes in<br />
the a more liberal attitude to agricultural imports;<br />
more controlled use of subsidies for exports of food<br />
surpluses; and reconsideration of the Community's policy<br />
of annually increasing price supports for foodstuffs which<br />
are already over-produced.<br />
I note that criticisms of this kind are also increasingly<br />
being reflected in responsible European journals. The support<br />
we are now getting from many quarters gives me real hope that<br />
we will ultimately achieve a mutually satisfactory resolution<br />
of this important issue.<br />
Concurrently with our negotiations with the EEC we have been<br />
actively participating in the Multilateral Trade Negotiations<br />
in Geneva. Whether these negotiations can achieve a satisfactory<br />
solution still remains to be seen but from the outset we have<br />
made one principle absolutely clear to all parties involved<br />
in those negotiations. In our view, the negotiations cannot<br />
be completed or regarded as a success unless a new deal for<br />
agricultural commodities forms an integral part of the<br />
final agreement.<br />
Our prime aims in these negotiations are to secure better market<br />
access and to improve the trading rules, in particular<br />
restraining the use of subsidies on exports. At the same time,<br />
we are seeking to develop appropriate commodity arrangements which<br />
will provide greater stability in trade.<br />
In a genuine attempt to assist in securing a satisfactory<br />
conclusion to the negotiations, Australia is offering a phased<br />
reduction over eight years in industrial tariffs but this offer<br />
is conditional on Australia receiving fully reciprocal offers<br />
from other nations, particularly a fair deal for agriculture.<br />
Leaders at the Bonn Summit in July requested their negotiators<br />
to come up with an agreed package by 15 December less<br />
than a month from now. Yet significant differences still persist.<br />
We can only hope that, during the next few weeks, the major<br />
trading blocs will demonstrate a real commitment to achieving<br />
a fairer and more rational trading system. This will require<br />
further concessions to be made. / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
We are all watching their actions over the next few<br />
weeks, trusting that the many assurances they have given<br />
will be reflected in the final outcome of the<br />
negotiations.<br />
Mr. President, the rural industry and the Australian<br />
economy have both been through most difficult times.<br />
Just as the prospects for farmers are now looking better<br />
for the first time in some years, so the prospects for<br />
economic recovery for Australia are improving.<br />
What is required for full economic recovery to be achieved<br />
is the wholehearted commitment of all Australians, by<br />
working together, to put this country back on its feet<br />
so that we can once again achieve the growth, development and<br />
prosperity desired by all Australians. In the decade<br />
ahead, there is every reason for confidence that we can<br />
achieve this goal. With confidence in our ability, with<br />
faith in Australia's future, we can together make this<br />
country the great country we all know it can be.<br />
000---O </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
