<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16084</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia Supports Training of East Timorese Defence Force, Canberra   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister welcomed today the commencement of construction of a new specialist training wing for the East Timor Defence Force (F-FDTL) funded by the Australian Government's Defence Cooperation Program.</p>
<p>The new facility, to be built at a cost of $5.7 million, is being constructed at the F-FDTL's training base in Metinaro, East Timor. </p>
<p>Speaking during a visit to Australia by the Prime Minister of East Timor, HE Mr Kay Rala Xanana Gusmao, the Prime Minister said the new training wing would provide high-quality specialist training in areas such as communications, logistics, engineering and medical skills delivered by Australian Defence Force (ADF) personnel. </p>
<p>Construction, which began last month, would be completed in December and training would begin in January 2009.</p>
<p>The Australian Government will provide more than $8 million in assistance to East Timor through the Defence Cooperation Program this year, increasing to $13 million in 2009-10.  The program has focused on developing leadership and discipline, strengthening financial management, civil engineering and communications.</p>
<p>The Defence Cooperation Program is in addition to security support provided to East Timor through Australia's leadership of the International Security Force (ISF) and contribution to the United Nations police operation in East Timor.  There are currently around 750 ADF personnel deployed to East Timor as a part of the ISF and around 50 Australian Federal Police officers as a part of the UN police contingent.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
