<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6849</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO WELCOME HER MAJESTY, THE QUEEN OF AUSTRALIA, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 3 MARCH 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/03/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006849.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
TO WELCOME HER MAJESTY, THE QUEEN OF AUSTRALIA<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUJSE, 3 MARCH 1986<br />
YOUR MAJESTY; YOUR ROYAL HIGHNESS,<br />
IT IS MY GREAT PLEASURE TO GREET YOU ON BEHALF OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE.<br />
YOUR MAJESTY, YOUR VISITS HERE GIVE THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AN OPPORTUNITY TO DEMONSTRATE THE AFFECTION WITH WHICH YOU,<br />
AND YOUR FAMILY ARE REGARDED IN THIS COUNTRY. THIS VISIT IS<br />
CLEARLY NO EXCEPTION.<br />
I AM DELIGHTED THAT DURING YOUR VISIT YOU WILL BE ATTENDING<br />
THE 150TH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATIONS OF SOUTH AUSTRALIA. WE<br />
WERE DELIGHTED THAT THE PRINCE JAYD -PRINC13SS OF WALES<br />
WERE ABLE TO ATTEND VICTORIA'S CELEBRATIONS LAST YEAR.<br />
IN TWO YEARS TIME AUSTRALIA WILL CELEBRATE OUR NATIONAL<br />
BICENTENARY. AS WE APPROACH 1988, WE CAN REFLECT WITH PRIDE<br />
ON AUSTRALIA'S EMERGENCE AS A MATURE, STABLE, TOLERANT<br />
SOCIETY, VIGOROUSLY DIVERSE IN ITS POPULATION, WITH SOLID<br />
ACHIEVEMENTS IN ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, CULTURAL AND<br />
INTELLECTUAL LIFE AND SPORTING ENDEAVOURS.<br />
IT WAS PARTICULARLY APPROPRIATE, YOUR MAJESTY, THAT YOU WERE<br />
ABLE, YESTERDAY, TO PROCLAIM THE AUSTRALIA ACT. THE<br />
PROCLAMATION OF THE ACT COMPLETES A CENTURY OF<br />
CONSTITUTIONAL DEVELOPMENT WHICH HAS ENDED FOR ALL TIME ANY<br />
RESIDUAL SENSE OF AUSTRALIA NOT BEING IN FULL CONTROL OF ITS<br />
OWN DESTINY.<br />
THE DIVERSITY OF AUSTRALIA WILL BE ONE OF THE SOURCES OF<br />
CELEBRATION IN 1988 AND THE THEME OF THE BICENTENNIAL YEAR<br />
LIVING TOGETHER ALSO REFLECTS THE HIGHLY VARIED NATURE OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY AND THE DIFFERENT CONTRIBUTION MADE TO<br />
IT: BY THE ABORIGINALS, WITH THEIR UNIQUE CULTURE AND THEIR<br />
FEELING FOR THIS RUGGED CONTINENT;<br />
BY THE SETTLERS FROM BRITAIN AND IRELAND WHO BROUGHT TO<br />
US THE VALUES OF A LIBERAL SOCIETY, AND </p>
<p>BY THOSE IMMIGRANTS FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD WHOM THIS<br />
COUNTRY HAS WELCOMED, AND WHO TOGETHER WITH THEIR<br />
DESCENDANTS HAVE GIVEN AUSTRALIA ITS VIBRANT<br />
OUTWARD-LOOKING CHARACTER.<br />
WE ARE PARTICULARLY PROUD THAT OVER THE LAST TEN YEARS<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS RESETTLED AROUND A HUNDRED THOUSAND REFUGEES<br />
FROM ASIA.<br />
TODAY IN AUSTRALIA THERE' IS A NEW SPIRIT OF COOPERATION, TO<br />
MEET AND TO FACE THE CHALLENGES BEFORE US. GOVERNMENT,<br />
BUSINESS AND THE TRADE UNIONS ARE JOINTLY ENDEAVOURING TO<br />
ESTABLISH A FIRM BASIS FOR OUR FUTURE ECONOMIC GROWTH. WE<br />
ARE ALSO WORKING TOGETHER WITH OTHER COUNTRIES IN THE<br />
ASIA-PACIFIC REGION TOWARDS A SECURE AND PEACEFUL FUTURE, A<br />
FUTURE IN WHICH OUR REGION WILL REALISE ITS DYNAMIC ECONOMIC<br />
POTENTIAL.<br />
OUR BICENTENARY WILL BE AN IMPORTANT OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO<br />
REFLECT ON THE ACHIEVEMENTS OF THE PAST AND TO LOOK FORWARD<br />
WITH RENEWED VIGOUR AND CONFIDENCE TO THE FUTURE. AND THE<br />
FUTURE BELONGS TO THE YOUTH OF THIS COUNTRY. COLLECTIVELY,<br />
THEY ARE OUR GREATEST ASSET. THE GOVERNMENT IS GIVING A<br />
HIGH PRIORITY TO THE NEEDS, THE CONCERNS AND THE ASPIRATIONS<br />
OF YOUNG AUSTRALIANS.<br />
YOUR MAJESTY, YOUR ROYAL HIGHNESS,<br />
IT IS WITH A FEELING OF AFFECTION AND PRIDE THAT THE PEOPLE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA WELCOME YOU AGAIN. PLEASE FEEL AT HOME HERE<br />
BECAUSE YOU ARE AT HOME AND ARE AMONG FRIENDS WHO WISH YOU<br />
WELL. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
