<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4574</transcript-id>
    <title>WA PRESS CLUB LUNCHEON, 1 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004574.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EBFI1ARGO: -12.' 45 P. ti i<br />
W9. A. PRESS CLUB LUNCEON 1st December 1977<br />
There are just nine days to go to polling day, and ais each day<br />
passos the vast differences between tim Government parties and<br />
the opposition become more obvious.<br />
Let me tell you what I see those differences to be. Fii~ st, the<br />
Government has a coherent and proven strategy to beat inflation.<br />
By a combination of restraint in Government spending, firm<br />
control over the money supply, a responsilble deficit and encouraging<br />
wage restraint we have succeeded in gettLing inflation down.<br />
The three quarterly Consumer Price Index figures published so<br />
far this year show that inflation is now running at about 9%.<br />
And I expect that during the next 12 months it will be reduced<br />
to between 6-8%.<br />
Labor by contrast has no anti-inflationary policy. Their policies<br />
of increasing the money supply through big government spending,<br />
big deficits and high wage increases are patently all inflationary.<br />
All Labor can claim to offer in the fight against inflation is<br />
abolition of payroll tax which, even if it did result in some<br />
reduction in prices which is highly doubtful to put it mildly<br />
could only have a once-off effect on the Consumer Price Index.<br />
E . ven that would be rapidly outhalanced by the inflationary nature<br />
of their fiscal, monetary, and wages policies.<br />
-he second difference between the parties is on taxation. vie<br />
are firmly committed to low taxation, and we have taken major<br />
steps in this area. Tax indexation is one of the most fundamental<br />
steps that could have been tab-en to protect the taxpayer, and<br />
discipline Government expenditure.<br />
our reforms of the tax scale are just and equitable. They simplify<br />
the personal tax system in such a way as to benefit everyone, to<br />
reward initiative and enterprise for everyone, to encourage harder<br />
work and higher productivity for everyone.<br />
of taxpayers will be on the same standard marginal rate of<br />
tax 32 cents in the dollar. This provides incentive to everyone<br />
to increase their earnings, as the vast majority of people can<br />
earn more without falling into a higher tax bracket. In other<br />
words, it is now worth working overtime again. / 2 </p>
<p>I should also say that while the reformns estLablish 32% as the<br />
basic rate of taxation paid by the vast majority of taxpayers,<br />
the principle of progressive taxation is maintained. Because<br />
the first $ 3,750 of everyone's income is tax free, taxpayers<br />
on higher income-s will pay higher proportions of their total<br />
income in tax than taxpayers on lower incomes. For example,<br />
the taxpayer without dependanits earning $ 4,000 pays 8% U of his<br />
income in tax. on $ 10,000 he pays 20%, on $ 20,000 he pays<br />
28.8% and on $ 50,000 44.2%. The tax reform accords with the<br />
view of most taxation experts. It is overwhelmingly supported<br />
by the reports of the Committees of Enquiry Labor established<br />
when they were in Government. The Asprey Committee, the<br />
most comprehensive review of Australia's tax system in<br />
years, concluded the Australian tax system relies too heavily<br />
on personal income tax.<br />
The Mathews Committee concluded that high marginal tax rates<br />
encouraged tax avoidance and evasion. The Jackson Committee<br />
warned that: " We have a general impression that the reward<br />
differentials after tax are decreasing and may no longer be<br />
sufficient to encourage individual enterprise and effort in<br />
industry." Our tax cuts, as Mr. Hurford has belatefdly conceded, are a<br />
significant social reform. 225,000 additional low income<br />
earners, people with taxable incomes under $ 3,750 a year, will<br />
be exempted altogether from paying tax.<br />
But just as importantly tax cuts are an integral part of our<br />
strategy to create more jobs for those who want work. The<br />
February tax cuts will provide a responsibl. e and moderate<br />
stimulus, injecting $ 26.7 million per week into the economy.<br />
Because this injection takes place when inflation is falling,<br />
it will. have a positive impact on jobs, by lifting consumer<br />
spending. This will mean factories getting more orders,<br />
investment increasing further, and companies taking on more<br />
employees. Unlike wage rises of a comparable amount, which Mr. Hawke<br />
says he would prefer, an increase in disposable income through<br />
tax cuts is not inflationary provided it is funded properly<br />
through a responsible deficit made possible by responsible<br />
expenditure restraint. It does not cost employers an extra<br />
cent. It does not cause prices to rise.<br />
The tax cuts will, I believe, reduce the pressure for wage<br />
increases, and thereby contribute to reduce inflation and<br />
unemployment. Labor, by contrast, is living up to tradition as the high tax<br />
party. They would recall Parliament early to repeal the<br />
February tax cuts which will benefit so many. And it's clear<br />
that their commitment to tax indexation has been swept aside.<br />
And all for what? For a payroll tax scheme which ma ) or<br />
employers have said will not work; which Mr. Dunstan s<br />
South Australian experience has shown will not work; and which<br />
Bob Hawke is busily sabotaging ais fast as he can go.<br />
The parties differ fundamentally on the need for growth and<br />
development. We have given every encouragement to investment<br />
in all our industries. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Because of our tax concessions, our fair but flexible foreign<br />
investment guidelines, our decisions on crude oil pricing and<br />
uranium dcvclopment, and our success in reducing inflation,<br />
exploration and development are proceeding at a pace.<br />
Oil exploration is well uip, particul~ rly in this state. In the<br />
September quarter, private capital spending rose strongly by<br />
6.6% seasonally adjusted. And the A. B. S. survey of expected<br />
capital spending for the current six month period tips a growth<br />
of 14% a most encouraging sign.<br />
On Monday, I was able to provide details of $ 6,000 million of<br />
committed investment already under way or set to go. And there*<br />
is more than that again tied up in other investment projects<br />
which are likely to proceed though not yet formally committed,<br />
such as the great North West Shelf development.<br />
Labor's policies would effectively stop this trend to increased<br />
investment in its tracks. All the vital. tax concessions to<br />
business and the mining industry would be removed. Draconian<br />
and quite unrealistic foreign investment rules would be imposed.<br />
According to Labor's official platform, a capital gains tax would<br />
be introduced; and, of course, Labor's commitment to vast<br />
increases in Government expenditure would start the greatest<br />
investment-killer of them all inflation racing away again.<br />
Perhaps the most obvious difference between Government and<br />
Opposition in the past fortnight has been the cohesion of the<br />
coalition team and the bizarre series of contradictions and<br />
confusion in the Labor Party. Just consider some of these<br />
statements. First, on wage indexation: Last Sunday week, Mr Whitlam said<br />
Labor would support immediate full wage indexation and urge the<br />
Arbitration Commission to accept this at its first hearing<br />
after December 10. Three days later,-Hayden said " I can't<br />
tell when and if full indexation would be brought in it is<br />
not appropriate or wise to say what the Government's submission<br />
( to the Arbitration Commission) would be."<br />
On tax indexation: On Monday of last week, Mr W'illis and<br />
Mr Whitlam, while being evasive on whether tax indexation would<br />
be retained or scrapped this year, said Labor would introduce<br />
full tax indexation next July. Two days later, Mr Hayden said<br />
tax indexation " could be implemented only when the economy<br />
could properly cope with it."<br />
on payroll tax: In his policy speech, Mr Whitlam said Labor<br />
was going to abolish payroll tax. As recently as his Press<br />
Conference last Sunday he reaffirmed this as Labor Policy.<br />
Yesterday, the President of the Labor Party, Mr Hawke, said<br />
abolition of payroll tax would proceed only if employers<br />
guaranteed to take on more staff. He added: " If they were<br />
not going to agree to stimulate the economy and employment in<br />
that way, then the Labor Government would have to look at<br />
alternative methods." / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Other contradictions in Labor policy abound. Mr Whitlam attacks<br />
our promise to abolish estate and gift duties, while Mr Hayden<br />
and Mr Wran both say they favour abltin Mr Dunstan attacks<br />
our decision -to export uraniium for peaceful purposes, hile at<br />
the same time licensing a foreign multi_-na-tional to explore for<br />
uranium just 30 kiloinetres from Adelailde., and encouraging uranium<br />
to be mined and stockpiled at Roxby Downs.<br />
In the background of all this confusion and disarray is poor<br />
Mr Hurford, who said he couldn't say what Labor'i policy on tax<br />
indexation was because he had only read " The Cairns Post" a<br />
shocking slur on a fine newspaper. Wvho said last W,, ednesday that<br />
Labor could not responsibly make any economic decisions seven<br />
months in advance of the 1978 Budget, and who, within days of<br />
that stunning insight into Labor's forward planning, rushed forth<br />
with a hastily conceived tax scheme for the low income earners<br />
Labor had overlooked in their policy speech.<br />
Mr Whitlam, when asked yesterday about this latest switch in<br />
policy, surpassed himself by saying nothing new had occurred:<br />
" I have been saying it all along" he said. An ABC reporter<br />
present commented that puzzled journalists searched their notebooks<br />
in vain for any such previous comment.<br />
One senior Labor Party spokesman was quoted as saying " It's our<br />
fault, we just forgot to mention it". I am sure the quarter<br />
million pensioners, widows, students and others affected will<br />
not quickly forget that Mr Whitlam " just forgot" them. Labor's<br />
half dozen economic spokesmen are slugging out a fine election<br />
campaign among themselves. The campaign will culminate in one<br />
of them winning the post of Opposition Shadow Treasurer sometime<br />
after December<br />
There is also an absolute contrast between our policy of<br />
protecting Australian industry, of protecting Australian jobs;<br />
and the Whitlam Labor Party's obsession with reducing protection,<br />
with making unemployment a deliberate act of government policy<br />
by encouraging imports to undercut Australian manufacturers.<br />
Whe'n Labor was in office, their policies eliminated the traditional<br />
advantages which Australian manufacturers had enjoyed for decades.<br />
Instead of having wage costs far below those in the United States,<br />
Labor's high wage policy forced up wage costs sharply.<br />
Instead of industry benefitting from an inflation rate low by<br />
world standards, Labor set inflation roaring at a rate that<br />
rivalled that of some banana republics.<br />
At the very time that industry's costs structure was being overturned,<br />
Labor introduced the notorious 25% across the board tariff<br />
Cut. Even though they were advised that this would throw tens of<br />
thousands of people out of work.<br />
On 27 June 1973, Mr Whitlam directed that a report be prepared<br />
within three weeks on ways of increasing imports into Australia.<br />
On 15 July, he rece ived the report and three days later he cut<br />
tariffs across the board by 25%, totally indifferent to the fate<br />
of the tens of thousands he put out of work with a stroke of his pen. </p>
<p>lie cut tariffs despite the facL that the report showed, with the<br />
utmost clarity, that tens of thousands of Australian jobs would<br />
be lost. Despite the fact that the report went through ind: ustry/<br />
after industry showing unem-iploym,-ent. would bDe caused.<br />
The Liberal Government is giving Auscuralian industry the protection<br />
it needs. We have shown that it is possible simultaneously to<br />
give effective protection to industries and to reduce inflation.<br />
And we appointed an inquiry under Sir John Crawford to find the<br />
best ways of achieving long term structural adjustment of industry<br />
without unacceptable social costs.<br />
But to talk of rapid structural change for industry now, when<br />
many factories are operating below capacity, when unemployment<br />
needs to be reduced, is in practical terms sheer nonsense.<br />
Yet this is precisely the kind of unreal, impractical theory to<br />
which all but a minority in the Labor Party are firmly wedded,<br />
the type of gross generalisation reflected in Mr Whitlam's speech<br />
to the Press Club in July, when he said: " There is no doubt that<br />
Australian industry is lavishly protected that is the basic<br />
trouble with our manufacturing industry in Australia."<br />
The Liberal Government has taken firm action where necessary to<br />
protect industries under threat, to protect the jobs of the<br />
Australians which depend on those industries continuing.<br />
We have increased protection for industries with a total employment<br />
of over a quarter of a million Australians in major industries<br />
such as motor vehicles, clothing, footwear, textiles, plywood<br />
and many others.<br />
We rejected out of hand the disastrous T. A. C. draft report on<br />
textilesiclothing and footwear. We have taken decisions to<br />
protect those industries for at least three years. Our policy<br />
reflects and protects the interests of the worker in those three<br />
industries -Labor's policy is the precise reverse.<br />
As a consequence of that draft report, we decided to change the<br />
law governing the I. A. C. We have introduced legislation into<br />
Parliament to require the I. A. C. to report on: the assistance<br />
necessary to maintain present levels of activity in the industries<br />
they examine, how each industry's structure might be improved,<br />
the employment consequences of its recommendations, and their<br />
impact on decentralised industry.<br />
We have done this because we believe the I. A. C. shoul-d be required<br />
to take broader considerations into account and not just a narrow<br />
concept of efficiency which all too often seems designed to put<br />
people out of jobs.<br />
The Australian Confederation of Apparel Manufacturers recently<br />
sought assurances from the Labor Party that they would support<br />
our decision to maintain employment and productivity in the<br />
apparel, textiles and footwear industries for the next three years.<br />
There was yet another telephone hook-up an unhappy hook-up<br />
as it turned out between Mr Whitlam, Mr Hawke, Mr Hayden and<br />
Mr Young. / 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
They concluded that Labor would not be committed to maintain these three<br />
industries over the next three years. Labor's research officer siuirmed<br />
up their attitude by saying Labor was " a free trade party" and wa~ i<br />
committed to the restructuringj of industry.<br />
This makes a mockeryof Labor ' s statements of concern about the unemployed<br />
In government, Labor threw~ tens of thduisands of people out of work<br />
because of their decisions. Tjhey are still ref-usinj to protect<br />
Australian jobs. They are threatening the Jobs of over a quarter of<br />
million Australians in the industries we are protecting.<br />
What a contrast with our policies which give top priority to keeping<br />
Australians in jobs. The Labor Party has chosen sterile<br />
intellectual abstractions over jobs, over the interests of the<br />
working men and women of-Australia. Understandably the working<br />
men and women of Australia feel that they have been betrayed by Labor.<br />
This leads me to the final difference between the parties. That<br />
is the seeming unwillingness or inability of the Labor Party to represen<br />
the interests of Australian working men and women. Labor's policy<br />
on protecting jobs is one illustration of this, Labor's anti-development<br />
stand is another.<br />
The fact that Labor could mount as the centre piece of their policy,<br />
a proposal to transfer resources from taxp~ ayers at all income levels<br />
to large companies reveals the most fundamental loss of touch by<br />
the Labor Party with what was once regarded as its natural constituency.<br />
Many of Labor's traditional supporters are frankly puzzled and<br />
bewildered by this proposal.,. Many of them will reject the Labor<br />
Party because they remember the consequences of its actions<br />
between 1973/ 75 and because -they realise that Labor hasn't changed,<br />
and because of Labor's extraordinary tax proposal. A proposal which<br />
will have shattered many traditional allegiances.<br />
Today, the Labor Party is a minority party. It is no longer even the<br />
Party of the unions. It is a Party of the union leadership of the<br />
union hierarchy, and of those whose views are not based in reality.<br />
While this has been going on, the Liberal Party has been increasing<br />
its support amongst groups that some people regard outside our<br />
conventional constituency. Since we were elected the Liberal Government<br />
has undertaken some fundamental steps of social reform.<br />
Commentators have found it difficult to fit these reforms into their<br />
conventional stereo-types of what they call conservative parties<br />
and Labor parties. Our social welfare policies, have had as their<br />
major priority, the directing of assistance to those people most<br />
in need, our family allowances, our reorientation of the children's<br />
services programmes towards day care of children of working mothers,<br />
our experiments, and our initiatives in the ethnic area.<br />
The Labor Party's reputation as a party of social concern is based<br />
on past history rather than current facts. We have been the Party that<br />
has indexed pensions toincreases inthe Consumer Price Index. Wle ha , ve<br />
been the Party that has lifted the taxation burden for an additional<br />
225,000 lower incomeAustralians. We have been the Party that<br />
redistributed wealth by ending the tax rebates for children and<br />
replacing them with our family allowances. * 7/ </p>
<p>-7-<br />
Labor's tax proposals have underscored this contrast in the most<br />
pointed way. When formulating their policy speech, they simply<br />
forgot theimpact of their abandonment of our tax reforms on<br />
225,000 lower income earners.<br />
So across the broad range of policies the choices in this election<br />
are clear, clearer perhaps than in most elections that I can recall. An(<br />
when the parties programmes are considered, it is apparent that on<br />
one vital issue, economic policy, there is, in fact, no choice.<br />
For Labor has failed to offer any credible coherent alternative to<br />
the economic strategy which the Government is pursuing.<br />
I am confident that on 10th December, the Government will be<br />
handsomely returned to office for another three years. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
