<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2576</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 3 MAY 1972 - EDUCATION</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/05/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002576.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO NOT FOR RELEASELWORE 5.30 PM ( EST)<br />
MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRIME M" INISTE R, THE RT. HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CH, MP' 3 MAY 1972<br />
E D U C A T I 0 N<br />
Most of you will agree that our greatest resources<br />
as a nation are the talents and abilities of our young people.<br />
It is therefore absolutely vital to our future as a nation that<br />
education should have a high priority among our national goals.<br />
Education has this high Priority in the policy<br />
thinking of Liberal-Country Party Governments. That's why we<br />
have seen a rapidly-growing Commonwealth involvement in many<br />
areas of education. Our help to the States and thie non-Go. vernment school<br />
system at an accelerating rate are quite specific.<br />
Firstly, there is the need to increase the availability,<br />
or quantity of education as the population grows, and to meet the<br />
aspirations of children who wish to stay at school longer or to go<br />
on to higher education. Secondly, we aim to improve the quality of<br />
education. To achieve these two overriding objectives, we are<br />
committed, firstly, and very importantly, to our very strong<br />
belief, that people have a right to freedom of choice of schools<br />
for individuals or groups within our community. We also want to<br />
reduce inequalities of opportunity in education and we want to<br />
instill in all families a wish to encourage their children to make<br />
the most of their personal potential.. They are our major<br />
objectives. Our methods, too, are simply stated. We want to work<br />
in co-operation with State Governments and independent school<br />
authorities. We want to encourage much greater local intrest in<br />
the day-to-day running of schools. Above all, we want to avoid<br />
centralised monolithic control and enforced uniformity and<br />
conf ormrity. In a nutshell: The Liberal Party approach is aimed at<br />
releasing energies, removing obstacles and encouraging innovation. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Now you are entitled to ask: What have we done to<br />
achieve this? Let us take the ten years up to 1971 as an example,<br />
although we were already giving substantial help in educat ion before<br />
then, with universities and scholarships. one significant move by<br />
the Commonwealth was on aid to independent schools.<br />
This policy began in a limited way in Canberra many years<br />
ago, but the Liberal-Country Party coalitiomwas-tVe f irst Federal<br />
Government to act nationally on aid to independent schools, as part<br />
of programmes of direct Commonwealth assistance to all schools.<br />
We were the only major party to wholeheartedly accept the<br />
challenge of the plural society to help educate children outside<br />
the State system. But it would be grossly wrong to take this to mean that<br />
we do not have a significant and great concern for Government schools.<br />
The figures for direct Commonwealth assistance to state schools<br />
show that our support is weighted in favour of Government schools<br />
on that basis. Teacher training assistance is helping produce new<br />
teachers faster than new pupils. Average class sizes are coming<br />
down. In 1961, only 28 per cent of the 15 to 18-year-olds stayed<br />
at school. Last year, it was 42 per cent.<br />
We are moving into new areas of education support by<br />
helping migrant children to overcome the language barrier, and by<br />
special grants we are deliberately discriminating in favour of<br />
aboriginal students.<br />
There were over 600,000 more children in Australian<br />
schools last year than in 1961, many of them in the higher secondary<br />
classes where costs are greatest.<br />
Through our expanding general revenue grants to the<br />
States, it can be shown that the Commonwealth provides more than<br />
half of the total recurrent spending by Governments on education in<br />
Australia.. Since 1961, direct Commonwealth spending on education<br />
has gone up more than six times, and spending on universities has<br />
almost tripled. In the last Budget, the increase for education was<br />
14 per cent. In December, we deciced on a further $ 20 million<br />
grant to the States. This was the first time that Federal grants<br />
have been made specifically for primary and secondary school<br />
classroom construction. Sorte of that money is already being spent to replace<br />
and remodel old and outmoded schools in the cities.<br />
From the beginning of this year, we also substantially<br />
increased the grants to independent schools which we began in 1970.<br />
o / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
You can see our record is a-good one.; And you can<br />
count on us to improve-on it inr-the future.<br />
We aim to provide the maximum Commonwealth support<br />
to both Government and non-Government schools with the minimumof<br />
centralised controls.<br />
We do not want another bureaucratic apparatus in<br />
Canberra with the power to reach down into schools across the<br />
nation and dictate which shall grow and which shall wither by<br />
giving or withholding finance. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
