<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11185</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          INTERVIEW WITH STEVE LIEBMANN          TODAY SHOW, CHANNEL NINE                                     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Referendum, Constitutional Preamble</p>
<p>E&amp;OE.............</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, good morning to you.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Good morning, Steve.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Would you agree as we sit here this morning it would seem that Australia</p>
<p>   is going to remain a monarchy with the Queen as Head of State?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I'm not sure what the outcome will be. Of course many people would</p>
<p>   dispute whether our present arrangement has the Queen of the Head of State,</p>
<p>   many would argue, as I do, that the Governor-General's the effective Head</p>
<p>   of State, drawing his authority from our constitution. A prediction - I</p>
<p>   don't know. I've learnt after Victoria to suspect the opinion polls. My</p>
<p>   feeling is that it could be close. I hope the republican model is rejected</p>
<p>   because I don't think what is on offer would give us a better system than</p>
<p>   we have now. I think it would give us a worse system so that's why I'm voting</p>
<p>   no.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Can you tell me why, when 91 percent of Australians don't want the Queen</p>
<p>   as their Head of State, when the majority of Australians would prefer, in</p>
<p>   the broad sense, Australia was a republic and probably the majority of your</p>
<p>   parliamentary colleagues would feel the same way, why you don't?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I'm not sure that some of those figures are right. I mean, that 91</p>
<p>   percent derives from a poll that asked people intending to vote no why they</p>
<p>   were voting no. And the greatest number said exactly what I just said and</p>
<p>   that is that they don't want to change the present system because they believe</p>
<p>   it works extremely well. And many of them, another 33 percent, said they</p>
<p>   were worried about the way in which the republican model would work. I mean,</p>
<p>   my view is to argue for what I think is best for Australia. I think we're</p>
<p>   better served staying with a system we know is good and we know works, we</p>
<p>   know is democratic, we know allows this country to be totally independent</p>
<p>   around the world. Now, people can criticise that view but it's a wholly</p>
<p>   legitimate, authentically Australian view. We are careful, sceptical people</p>
<p>   of change unless we're satisfied that it is change for the better and I</p>
<p>   think we are right to be sceptical, we are right to be suspicious of people</p>
<p>   coming along and saying there'll be a new Nirvana if we become a republic.</p>
<p>   I mean, that's just not true. This is a good and decent country and if the</p>
<p>   public vote no on Saturday it will continue to be a good and decent country.</p>
<p>  Now, in the end, you've got to make a judgement about what you think is</p>
<p>   better for the country and my opposition to change is based on a belief</p>
<p>   that an accident of history has given us a remarkably effective system and</p>
<p>   I just don't want to risk changing it for something I'm unconvinced is better.</p>
<p>   Now, that's my view.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Talking of views, Michelle Grattan, in the Herald and the Age</p>
<p>   this morning is saying that you would be the first Australian Prime Minister</p>
<p>   to urge Australians to reject the question that your government has advanced.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I think I can turn that on its head and say I am the first Australian Prime</p>
<p>   Minister to facilitate the Australian people making a choice in favour of</p>
<p>   something that I personally don't support. Most prime ministers in the past,</p>
<p>   if they haven't supported something they haven't put it up. But I recognised</p>
<p>   the desire on the part of the Australian people before the turn of the century</p>
<p>   to have a vote on this issue. And even though I'm personally against it,</p>
<p>   I put it up. As Tom Keneally said at the Constitutional Convention it was</p>
<p>   the ultimate act of grace on my part being opposed to a republic to nonetheless</p>
<p>   give people a vote on it. So surely, if I may, I hope without being immodest,</p>
<p>   say that is a point in my favour rather than a criticism of me.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Given that the Queen is by law.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  The Queen of Australia, the Governor-General effectively by convention.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  But can you tell me why Australians should have to share the Queen as our</p>
<p>   Head of State with numerous other countries from New Zealand to Barbados?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, you make a judgement about that. That's one of the things you put</p>
<p>   in judgement. You say, well, okay, she's the Queen of Australia and she's</p>
<p>   also the Queen of a number of other countries and you think, well, okay,</p>
<p>   that's one argument. You then ask yourself, is that sufficient reason to</p>
<p>   sweep away a system that has worked so very effectively? Now, they're the</p>
<p>   judgements people have got to put in balance. Now, I say on balance it's</p>
<p>   not. And that was the view I put at the Constitutional Convention. Now,</p>
<p>   if people disagree with me, well, of course they'll vote yes. I mean, in</p>
<p>   a sense, this is what the debate is all about. I mean, we are an independent</p>
<p>   democratic country. Everyone knows that. Everyone knows that this has its</p>
<p>   own distinct identity. Nobody mistakes an Australian anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>   I mean, to suggest that we've got to vote yes to be Australian is absurd.</p>
<p>   That is the implication in so much of the republican advertisement. Their</p>
<p>   great failure in this campaign, in my view, has been they haven't persuaded</p>
<p>   us that this country will be better. I mean, you change something when you</p>
<p>   think it's going to be better as a result of the change. I don't believe</p>
<p>   in change for its sake.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  But why not encompass the best of the past with a move forward?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't think this model does that. I really don't. I mean, this model</p>
<p>   will have a President instantly dismissable at the will of the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>   This model will not.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Yeah, but there are riders attached to that.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, the rider is that what you get a vote of the House of Representatives.</p>
<p>   Well, can I say as the Prime Minister commanding a majority in the House</p>
<p>   of Representatives I would be hypothetically unlikely to do that unless</p>
<p>   I knew my party was going to back me. So really the endorsement by the House</p>
<p>   of Representatives means nothing.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  You said yesterday, I think I'm quoting you correctly, Australia's stability</p>
<p>   will be better preserved under our present system. Does that then mean that</p>
<p>   if we became a republic we would be less stable?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, what it means is that our present constitution is better able to cope</p>
<p>   with a crisis than the model on offer. I mean, any old constitution works</p>
<p>   when you don't have a crisis. I mean, you don't need a constitution when</p>
<p>   you don't have a crisis. But every so often some stress will come along</p>
<p>   and you need a constitution that handles the stress. And the test of a stable</p>
<p>   constitution is how it handles stress. So what I'm saying is that in the</p>
<p>   event of instability the present constitution would handle it better than</p>
<p>   the one on offer.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Does tomorrow's result have to be a resounding one either way?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, tomorrow's result will be what the Australian people want it to be.</p>
<p>   I mean, I hope that there's a resounding yes vote for the preamble which</p>
<p>   is the other question because the preamble is an opportunity for republicans</p>
<p>   and anti-republicans alike to combine to make an aspirational statement</p>
<p>   about our future. And for the first time we'll be putting something decent</p>
<p>   and noble in the Constitution about the indigenous people. I hope it is</p>
<p>   resoundingly carried. Look, I think the other one will be close. I don't</p>
<p>   know what the margins will be either way. I hope it's defeated. I hope it's</p>
<p>   defeated in every State. I think that would be good but, Steve, the customer's</p>
<p>   always right in these things. If the public votes no on Saturday, well,</p>
<p>   I accept that. That's the outcome I've been advocating. If they vote yes,</p>
<p>   I will accept that too.</p>
<p>  And can I just say, I notice in the last few days people are saying, oh</p>
<p>   you know, if it goes down, there'll be great bitterness and division. I</p>
<p>   don't think there will be. This is not that kind of country. We've had a</p>
<p>   fair contest and.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Has it been fair, there's been a lot of deceit and lies on both sides?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, yes, well, if you accept that, I don't know if I necessarily do but</p>
<p>   if you do, well, they've sort of cancelled each other out. I mean, everybody's</p>
<p>   had a go. The question is patently clear. The question describes exactly</p>
<p>   what the change is - the President replacing the Queen and the Governor-General</p>
<p>   and that President being chosen by two-thirds of the members of Parliament.</p>
<p>   I mean, that is what will happen if you vote yes. Now, people who complain</p>
<p>   about that are really sort of, you know, reflecting on their own inadequacy</p>
<p>   but I think this will be a stable decent country if it goes.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Either way.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Of course it is. We're a stable, decent good people.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  As you said, the customer's always right.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Absolutely.</p>
<p>  LIEBMANN:</p>
<p>  Nice to see you.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Thanks.</p>
<p>  [Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
