<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5358</transcript-id>
    <title>OLYMPIC GAMES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005358.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MIN~ ISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY 23 1980<br />
OLYM4PIC GAMES<br />
The Government has learned with regret that the Executive of<br />
the Australian Olympic Federation, in exercising its own<br />
independence of government, has rejected the strong advice of<br />
the Australian Government and today decided to send an<br />
Australian team to Moscow.<br />
In recent days, the Executive has been kept closely in touch<br />
with the view of the Government and with latest developm~ ents..<br />
The Government had indicated that an effective boycott is already<br />
in place with the United States, Canada and West Germany, amongst<br />
countries determined to stay away from Moscow.<br />
The decisions of these countries have been taken against<br />
the background of the continued Soviet invasion and repression<br />
of the people of Afghanistan, of the build-up of Soviet<br />
strategic facilities in Afghanistan,' with certain consequences<br />
for the reach of Soviet military power over the Middle East and<br />
the Indian Ocean.<br />
The Government had stressed to the Executive of the Olympic<br />
Federation that the decision being made today was not one<br />
involving sport and sport alone. It was one involving the<br />
future of all Australians, especially of young Australians.<br />
I pray that those Olympians who do go to Moscow will not pay the<br />
price that many of those who went to the Berlin Olympics paid<br />
once the World: War started in 1939.<br />
I prray, that the Soviet Union will not interpret this and other<br />
decisions of Olympic Federations as a weakening of Western will,<br />
as Nazi Germany did in 1936.<br />
The Government has repeatedly stated that the highest interests<br />
of national security are involved; that the Western world is<br />
now, with all the energy and determination that it can command,<br />
seeking to prevent the early years of the 80' s slipping<br />
inevitably to global conflict as di4d the later years of the 1930' s.<br />
The Executive of the Australian Olympic Federation had an*-.<br />
opportunity to contribute to that paramount objective by placing<br />
Australia first. It is with profound regret that I recognise<br />
that they did not take that opportunity. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
