<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6137</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAWKE, TO THE FOREIGN POLICY ASSOCIATION, NEW YORK, 16 JUNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/06/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006137.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1/<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TEXT OF SPEECH BY T1HE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAKE<br />
TO THE FOREIGN POLICY ASSOCIATION,<br />
NEW YORK,<br />
16 JUNE.<br />
AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB IN WASHINGTON YESTERDAY I HAD TH-E<br />
OPPORTUNITY OF OUTLINING MY NEW GOVERNMENT'S GENERAL APPROACH TO<br />
INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS AND ITS SPE. CIF-IC APPROACH TO OUR ALL-IMPORTANT<br />
RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES, I STRESSED THEN THE IMPORTANCE OF<br />
OUR MANAGEMENT OF OUR NATIONAL ECONOMY rO THE EFFECTIVENESS OF OUR<br />
FOREIGN POLICY, TODAY I WISH TO DEAL WITH OUR GENERAL APPROACH TO<br />
ECONOMIC AFFAIRS B0TH NATIONAL ANDI INTERNATIONAL, AND TO SAY<br />
SOMETHING ABOUT OUR SPECIFIC APPRO) ACH TO THE ROLE OF AMERICAN<br />
BUSINESS IN THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY.<br />
-YESTERDAY, IN SPEAKING ABOUT IN) ERNATIONAL RELATIONS<br />
GENERALLY AND THE LUNITED SlATES-AUSI1RALIA RELATIONSHIP IN PARTICULAR,<br />
I STRESSED THE THEMES OF CONTINUITY AND INTERDEPENDENCE THE<br />
ESSENTIAL CONTINUITY OF THE MAJOR DIRECTIONS OF FOREIGN POLICY AND<br />
THE BASIC INTERDEPENDENCE OF THE NAl IONS, THEIR ECONOMIES AND THEIR<br />
SOCIETIES. TODAY, I WISH TO TAKE UP THOSE THEMES AGAIN, IN THE<br />
CONTEXT OF THE ECONOMIC POLICIES 9JF MY GOVERNMENT.<br />
AMERICANS AND AUSTRALIANS SH414E SO MUCH IN THE WAY OF POLITICAL<br />
TRADITIONS, ECONOMIC INSTITUTIONS AND ECONOMIC INTERESTS THAT WE CAN<br />
AT TIMES ASSUME TOO EASILY AN EXACT IDENTITY OF VALUES AND INTERESTS.<br />
THIS CAN LEAD TO THE DISAPPOINTMENT OF EXPECTATIONS IN OUR<br />
RELATIONSHIP WITH EACH OTHER. THuIS IT MAY BE USEFUL FOR ME TO POINT<br />
OUT ONE OR TWO MORE WAYS IN WHICH OUR EFFORTS TO ACHIEVE NATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC RECOVERY DEPEND ON FEATURI&amp; S OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY AND<br />
SOCIETY THAT DIFFER FROM YOUR OWN.<br />
THE FUNDAMENTAL CONSTRAINTS ON AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC<br />
DEVELOPMENT ARE LITTLE AFFECTED BY A CHANGE OF GOVERNMENT, AS A<br />
LIGHTLY POPULATED COUNTRY, WITH LARUiE RESOURCES THAT CAN BE CONVERTED<br />
INTO INCOME AND WEALTH ONLY THROLIBH INVESTMENT AND INTERNATIONAL<br />
TRADE, OUR LIVING STANDARDS DEPEND HEAVILY ON THE MAINTENANCE OF A<br />
LIVERAL INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND PAYMENTS SYSTEM.<br />
OUR NATURAL PATTERN OF TRADE SPF-CIALISATION, WITH<br />
RELATIVELY STRONG EMPHASIS ON EXPOk'lS OF PRIMARY COMMODITIES,<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>CAUSES OUR ECONOMI. C FORTUNES 1o BE AFFECTED MORE THAN MOST<br />
INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES BY THE SITUATION IN THE LARGE ECONOMIES<br />
OF 1HF. NORTHERN HEMISPHERE.<br />
MORE IAN IN MOST OTHER INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES,<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC GROWTH DEPENDS UPON THE INFLOW OF CAPITAL<br />
FROM A&amp; ROAD. THUS IN AUSTRALIA, 1NIERNATIONAL FINANCIAL<br />
DEVELOPMENTS ARE IMPORTANT DETERMINANTS OF LONG TERM ECONOMIC<br />
GROWTH AS WELL AS OF SHORT-TERM ECONOMIC CONDITIONS.<br />
ANY AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT MUST COUNT AMONGST ITS MAIN<br />
TASkS THE MANAGEMENT OF DOMISTIC AND INTERNATIONAL<br />
RESPONSES TO AN EVER-CHANGING, WORL 1 ECONOMY. WITHIN THIS<br />
CONTEXT, OUR RELATIONSHIP WITH THI-UNITED STATES IS OF<br />
CENTRAL IMPORTANCE: AS ONE OF OUR IWO LARGEST TRADING<br />
PARTNERS: AS OUR LARGEST SOURCE OF DIRECT INVESTMENT: AS A<br />
PRINCIPAL. DETERMINANT OF CONDITIONS IN WORLD COMMODITY AND<br />
FINANCIAL MARKETS: AND AS THE MAIN SPONSOR OF THE LIBERAL<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADING AND FINANCIAL SYSTEM THAT HAS FACILITATED<br />
POSTWAR GROWTH IN AUSTRALIA AS IN THE WORLD AS A WHOLE.<br />
OVER THE POSTWAR PERIOD THERE HAS BEEN A REMARKABLE SHIFT IN THE<br />
GEOGRAPHICAL PATTERN OF AUSTRALIA'S RELATIONS WITH THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
ECONOMY, AWAY FROM THE UNITED KINGDOM AND EUROPE TOWARDS THE<br />
ASIA-PACIFIC REGION. THIS HAS HAD SEVERAL CAUSES. FIRST, THERE HAS<br />
BEEN THE RAPID GROWTH IN TRADING OPPORTUNITIES ASSOCIATED WITH THE<br />
' INDUSTRIALISATION AND STRONG ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE IN NORTHEAST ASIA,.<br />
AND MORE RECENTLY IN SOUTHEAST ASIA. SECOND, THE WAY IN WHICH EUROPE<br />
HAS TURNED INWARD, ESPECIALLY ON AGRI1CULTURAL TRADE, HAS PUSHED<br />
OUTSIDERS, INCLUDING AUSTRALIA AND ITS PACIFIC NEIGHBOURS, INTO<br />
CLOSER ECONOMIC LINKS WITH EACH OTHER AND WITH OTHERS OUTSIDE THAT<br />
INWARD-LOOkING BLOC. THIRD, THE WITHERING OF THE OLD IMPERIAL<br />
TRADING SYSTEMS HAS FREED AUSTRALIA TO TRADE MORE INTENSIVELY WITH<br />
ITS NEIGHBOURS IN ASIA. FOURTH, THE GOVERNMENTS AND BUSINESS<br />
COMMUNITES OF OUR REGION HAVE APPLIED CONSIDERABLE EFFORT TO BUILDING<br />
THE RELATIONSHIPS ESSENTIAL TO THE STRONG EXPANSION OF TRADE.<br />
CRUCIAL TO ALL. OF THIS HAS BEEN THE ROLE OF THE UNITED STATES:<br />
INDIRECTLY THROUGH ITS CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE UMBRELLA' OF POLITICAL<br />
STABILITY THAT WAS NECESSARY FOR 1H-EXPANSION OF ECONOMIC ACTIVITY<br />
AND TRADE, AND DIRECTLY AS A MAJOR PARTICIPANT IN THE ECONOMIC LIFE<br />
OF THE REGION.<br />
ADVERSE DEVELOPMENTS IN OUR INIERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ENVIRONMENT<br />
WERE PART OF THE CAUSE OF THE ACUTE ECONOMIC PROBLEMS IN AUSTRALIA<br />
WHICH MY GOVERNMENT WAS ELECTED TO OVERCOME. -WE WILL WORK TO IMPROVE<br />
THAT ENVIRNMENT, ALTHOUGH WE DO NOT DELUDE OURSELVES THAT A COUNTRY<br />
OF AUSTRALIA* S SIZE CAN EXERCISE MUCH INFLUENCE OUTSIDE ITS OWN<br />
IMMEDIATE REGION. BUT WE CAN AND DO AIM TO IMPROVE AUSTRALIA'S<br />
DOMESTIC POLICY RESPONSE TO INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC CONDITIONS.<br />
WITHOUT IN ANY WAY FIGHTING THE AUSTRALIAN ELECTION CAMPAIGN OVER<br />
AGAIN IN NEW YORK, 1 THINK IT IS FAIR TO S * AY THAT WHILE INTERNATIONAL<br />
CONDITIONS HAVE CONTRIBUTED CONSIDERABLY TO AUSTRALIA'S RECENT<br />
ECONOMIC PROBLEMS, THESE DIFFICUILTIES HAVE BEEN GREATLY EXACERBATED<br />
BY THE NATURE OF THE RESPONSE TO THE-M.<br />
DOMESTIC ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT<br />
WHEN MY GOVERNMENYT TOOK OFFICE IN MARCH, AUSTRALIA WAS<br />
EXPERIENCING INFLATION AT'OVER ELEVEN PER CENT PER ANNUM, OR TWICE<br />
THE RATE IN MOST MAJOR O. E. C. D. COLUNTRIES, AND UNEMPLOYMENT AT OVER<br />
TEN PER CENT. DATA RECENTLY TO HAND INDICATE THAT THE MARCH QUARTER<br />
THIS YEAR WAS THE THIRD SUCCESSIVF OUARTER, AND THE FIFTH IN TWO<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>YEARS, IN WHICH ECONOMIC ACTIVITY CONTRACTED.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY DURING THE ELECTION CAMPAIGN OFFERED A<br />
PROGRAM OF NATIONAL RECONCILIATION, RECONSTRUCTION AND RECOVERY. THE<br />
MANDATE CONFERRED ON MY GOVERNMENT E: Y THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA IS<br />
QUITE PRECISE. IT IS TO RESTORE GROWTH, REDUCE INFLATION AND ARREST<br />
THE EXPLOSION IN UNEMPLOYMENT.<br />
WE SAID IN THE CAMPAIGN THAT, UNDER OUR POLICIES, THE ECONOMY<br />
WOULD GENERATE IN THE ORDER OF HALF A MILLION NEW JOBS OVER THREE<br />
YEARS. THIS STOOD IN VIVID CONTRAS1 TO THE LOSS OF OVER ONE HUNDRED<br />
ITHOUSAND JOBS IN THE PREVIOUS YEA(. THE POLICIES THAT I WILL OUTLINE<br />
TODAY ARE DESIGNED TO FULFILL OUR COMMITMENT. WORK THAT HAS BEEN<br />
DONE SINCE WE TOOK OFFICE THREE MONTHS AGO SUGGESTS THAT OUR<br />
OBJLCTIVE IS WITHIN REACH. BUT EV-N SUCH A DRAMATIC REVERSAL IN THE<br />
TREND OF EMPLOYMENT WOULD MAKE TOO LITTLE PROGRESS IN REDUCING<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT. ACCORDINGLY, WE ARE COMMITTED TO ADDRESSING THE<br />
SPECIAL PROBLEMS OF; THE LONG-TERM UNEMPLOYMENT THROUGH A COMMUNITY<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT PROGRAM. WE ARE COMMITTED TO REVIEW THE WHOLE RANGE OF<br />
TRAINING AND RE-TRAINING SCHEMES TO ENSURE THAT THEY ARE RELEVANT TO<br />
' A RAPIDLY CHANGING ENVIRONMENT. WE ALSO AIM TO ENCOURAGE INNOVATION<br />
IN WORK PATTERNS, TO'ACHIEVE AS CLOSE A BALANCE AS POSSIBLE BETWEEN<br />
THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE WANTING JOBS AND THE NUMBER OF JOBS THE ECONOMY<br />
CAN DELIVER. BUT OUR MAIN INSTRUMENT IS IMPROVED MANAGEMENT.<br />
BEYOND SPECIFIC.,. GOALS,. THE ELEMENT OF OUR APPROACH TO<br />
ECONOMIC. POLICYTHAT MOST DISTINGUISHES US FROM THE FORMER<br />
GOVERNMENT IS OURCOMMITMENT TO THE SEARCH FOR COMMUNITY<br />
CONSENSUS ON THE./ GREAT ECONOMIC ISSUES, AND ABOVE ALL TO<br />
MORE CO-OPERATIVE AND LESS COMBATIVE MEANS OF DETERMINING<br />
WAGES LEVELS AND INCOME SHARES.<br />
WE BELIEVED. BEFORE OUR ELECTION, AND OUR BELIEF HAS BEEN<br />
CONFIRMED BY OUR EXPERIENCE SINCE THE ELECTION, THAT SUCH AN APPROACH<br />
IS MORE LIKELY TO'ACHIEVE THE RESTRAINT IN INCOMES CLAIMS ESSENTIAL<br />
FOR SUSTAINED NON-INFLATIONARY GROW1H.<br />
WE BELIEVE THAT A MORE CO-OPERATIVE APPROACH TO ECONOMIC<br />
POLICY-MAKING, INVOLVING CLOSE CONSULTATION WITH THE MAIN ECONOMIC<br />
INTERESTS, ESPECIALLY BUSINESS AND UNIONS, WILL FACILITATE<br />
ADJUSTMENTS NECESSARY TO RESTORE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC GROWTH. WE<br />
BELIEVE AS WELL THAT A REDUCTION IN INDUSTRIAL CONFLICT IN AUSTRALIA<br />
WILL IN ITSELF IMPROVE ECONOMIC PERFORMANCE.<br />
IN DRAWING UP OUR PROGRAM, WE HAD IN MIND TWO PRINCIPAL<br />
INSTRUMENTS FOR THE BUILDING OF NAllONAL CONSENSUS ON ECONOMIC POLICY<br />
ISSUES THAT HAD BEEN HIGHLY DIVISIVE IN AUSTRALIA. THE FIRST WAS A<br />
PRICES AND INCOMES POLICY, BUILT AROUND AN ACCORD PRIOR TO THE<br />
ELECTIONS BETWEEN THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY AND THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
COUNCIL OF TRADE. UNIONS. THIS ACCORD EMBODIES COMMITMENT TO<br />
CONSULTATION BETWEEN A: LABOR GOVERNMENT AND THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF<br />
' TRADE UNIONS ON MAJOR ECONOMIC POLICY MATTERS AFFECTING ORGANISED<br />
LABOR. THE SECOND INSTRUMENT. FOR.' BUILDING NATIONAL CONSENSUS ON ECONOMIC<br />
POLICY ISSUES . ASfA NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE, WHICH WAS<br />
HELD WITHIN A. MONTH OF'.. MY TAKING OFFICE. PARTICIPANTS INCLUDED<br />
ELEVEN MINISTERS. WITH'ECONOMIC RESPONSIBILITIES IN MY GOVERNMSNT, THE<br />
PREMIERS AND SENIOR ECONOMIC MINISTERS OF OUR STATE AND TERRITORIAL<br />
GOVERNMENTS, ALL MEMBERS OF THE EXECUTIVE OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL<br />
OF. TRADE UNIONS, THIRTY-FIVE LEADERS OF BUSINESS ORGANISATIONS AND<br />
./ 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
AuSTRALIAN BUSINESS, AND SIX LEADERS OF PROFESSIONAL AND COMMUNITY<br />
OHGA ISAT IONS<br />
ONE PARTICIPANT WHO WOULD HAVE BEEN KNOWN TO SOME<br />
OF YOU HERE TdDAY, WHO MADE AN IMMENSE CONTRIBUTION TO DISCUSSION AT<br />
THE SUMMIT, AS HE HAD THROUGHOUT HIS CAREER, TO AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS<br />
AND PUBLIC LIFE, WAS SIR KEITH CAMPBELL, CHAIRMAN OF THE COMMITTEE ON<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL SYSTEM THAT BEARS HIS NAME. TRAGICALLY, SIR<br />
KEITH DIED A FEW DAYS AFTER THE CONFERENCE, TO THE. GREAT LOSS OF ALL<br />
OF 1S. THE NATIONAL ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE IS WIDELY<br />
RECOGNISED AS HAVING CREATED A COMMUNITY OF OUTLOOK AMONGST THE MAJOR<br />
ECONOMIC INTERESTS THAT HAS NO PRECEDENT. IN OUR PEACETIME HISTORY.<br />
THE SUMMIT. WAS MEANT TO.-AND DID MARK THE BEGINNING OF CONSENSUS<br />
IN ECONOMIC POLICY-MAKING, NOT THE END. SINCE THEN. CONSULTATIONS<br />
WITH UNIONS AND BUSINESS HAVE LED TO AGREEMENT ON THE FORM THAT A<br />
PRICES SURVEILLANCE AUTHORITY SHOULD TAKE, NAMELY THE EXCLUSION OF<br />
AREAS OF THE ECONOMY WHERE THERE IS ADEQUATE COMPETITION, AND THE<br />
AVOIDANCE 7OF' COSTLY BUREAUCRATIC PROCEDURES. AGREEMENT HAS ALSO BEEN<br />
REACHED ' O. ijHE FORM AND ROLE OF AN ECONOMIC PLANNING. ADVISORY<br />
COUNCIL,, WI-ICH WILL CONTINUE THE WORK OF THE SUMMI1&gt; AS A MEANS<br />
THROUGH WHECH-THE GOVERNMENT CAN INFORM AND SEEK ADVICE FROM LEADING<br />
FIGURES FROM BUSINESS, TRADE UNIONS AND COMMUNITY GROUPS.<br />
I MUST EMPHASISE THAT OUR COMMITMENT TO CONSUL. TATION . WITH THE<br />
UNIONS. AND ' BUSI'NESS , AND OUR iSEARCH FOR. CONSE. NSUS,-DOES : NOT INVOLVE<br />
ANY ABROGATION' 0F10UR ' RESPONSBILTY AS A GOVER. NMENT... ULTIMATELY,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT ' ALONE RESPONSIBLE $ OR NATIONAl', ECONOMIC POLICY.<br />
BUT WE'BELI EVE AND THE. EXPERIENCE OF' THE SUMMIT AND BEYOND HAS<br />
BORNE" OUT OUR -BELIEF, THAT CLOSE CONSULTATION CAN ENRICH POLICY AND'<br />
STRENGTHEN THE ABILITY OF THE GOVERNMENT TO CARRY OUT ITS INESCAPABLE<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES. t.' REASURER,.' PUL. KEATING, PRESENTED TO THE SUt1SIT<br />
A DETeA iLED -STATEMENT' OF THE NEW GOVERNrENT ' S APPROAIñ TO ECONOMIC<br />
POL: IY. HE PROVIDED TO SUMMIT PARTICIPANTS, AND TO THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
COMMUNITY, MORE DETAILED INFORMATION ON AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC<br />
PERFORMANCE, POLICY AND PROSPECTS THAN HAD EVER BEFORE BEEN MADE<br />
AVAILABLE BY AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMEN1S. THIS SHARING OF ECONOMIC<br />
INFORMATION WILL CONTINUE TO BE A FEATURE OF ECONOMIC POLICY-MAKING<br />
UNDER THIS GOVERNMENT. A SHARED PERSPECTIVE ON ECONOMIC FACTS IS<br />
OBVIOUSLY A NECESSARY PRE-CONDITION TO SHARED PERSPECT. IVES ON POLICY.<br />
IN TURN, SUCH SHARED PERSPECTIVES ARE NECESSARY TO PROVE THE<br />
POLITICAL BASE FOR CONTINUITY OF POLICY. 7<br />
MY GOVERNMENT HAS STRESSED THE DEEP-SEATED NATURE . OF<br />
THE POOR AUSTRALIAN ECONOMI'C;. PERFOMACE IN : RECENT YEARS: THERE<br />
ARE NO-QUICK OR EASY SOLUT jONS. WE HAVE:. STRESSED THE NEED TO FIGHT<br />
INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT SI. MULTANEOUSLY. FOR THAT, CORRECTPOLICIES,<br />
STEADILY APPLIED . OVER' A LONG PERIOD, ARE NEEDED. AND I<br />
BELIEVE. THAT THIS IS NO W-BETTER UNIDERSTOOD : BY THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE<br />
THAN EVER BEFORE.<br />
DURINGTHE ELECTI ON CAMPAIGN : WE ARGUEDTHAT WAGE<br />
RES TqAT WITHiIN'AHE'PRICES:.. AND: INCOMES ACCORD. WOULD SUPPORT THE<br />
' U T. 0 NAT IONA4ECN ' C REOVERY THROUGH MCDERATELY*<br />
EXPANS1: ONARY FISC . POL'. CY. WE REM'AIN COMMITTED TO THAT. GENERAL<br />
APPROACH.-' HOWEVER INFORMATION PROVIDED TO US BY OUR OFFICIAL<br />
ADVISERS': SOON A4 TER . YWE TOOK OFFICE SUGGESTED THAT THE POLICIES<br />
HAST ILy'INTRODUCED BY THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT IN THE LEAD-UP<br />
TO THE ELECTION: WOULD ALREADY YIELD A BUDGET DEFICIT FOR </p>
<p>98~ q3-84 SIGNIFICANTLY IN EXCESS QI' WH4AT WE HAD IN MIND AS<br />
mODER -ILLY EXPANSIONARY'<br />
THE CONTINUAl ION OF INHERITED POLICIES AND PROGRAMS<br />
WITHOUT AM NDNENT WOULD HAVE LED TO A 1983-84 DEFICIT OF ABOUT<br />
DOLLARS 9.6 BILLION OR ABOUT 6 PERCENT OF G. D. P. BROAD ESTIMATES<br />
SUbI3EST THAT ABOUT HALF. OF THIS MAY BE CY CLICAL IN NATURE.<br />
B'UT ABOUT HALF, REPRESENTING AROUND THREE PERCENT OF GROSS<br />
DOMESTIC PRODUCT, SEEMS TO D'E STRUCTURAL, AND COULD BE EXPECTED<br />
TO CONTINUE EVEN IF STRONG RECOVERY OCCURS.<br />
THE REMOVAL OF THE STRUCTURAL COMPONENT OF THE<br />
DEFICIT, WHICH WILL BE NECESSARY FOR-THE MAINTENANCE: OF . ECONOMIC<br />
STABILITY IN T-HE LATER STAGES OF ECONOMIC RECOVERY-. 7WILL REQUIRE'<br />
CHANGES IN FISCAL SOE0KX. EEDOIIYT NLST-IMULUS*'<br />
PROV5DED BY THE STAUCTURAL, DEFICIT tIPRORTEFowl', 8384<br />
WH~ 7PI VAT E INVEST1E. NT I S EXPECTEDIS, -,,, REMANLWJIH<br />
RE.. CES SION CONDITION -Q'BUT',' THE SUSY E AUCC-OF-RECOVER'i I LL<br />
REQU RE-fACTIVE MEASURES TO HAULINj TCURL. ECT' I<br />
1 94~; AN 1I985-86 V E N'EI ! 93~ W2IT L; L BEJ; u SR<br />
T0B'ediWTHAT TASK' E 4? WRE EA TO AVOID-' PRESSURES. Ih -, i, 4N C<br />
MARkE* TS'-' S RECOVERY , pROCEEDS THROUG$ 5hEj YEAR.<br />
TH ONET MOVED QUICKLY AGAlINST,:. THE STRUCTUA. L. B U DG E TDEFICIT."<br />
WE -WER* E COMMIT'TED DURING.: THE-* ELEtCTION CAP1NTO. STIMULATE1<br />
THE HOUSING -INDUSTRY AND YOINROUEMPEWLOY_ ET..-<br />
PROGRAM. TtJMNTHS. AFTER'. 71AKI. NGB' OPCEWE.. , ANN OI1N PCZOMEASURES<br />
-WRCI 4; S ~ ULTANEOU -tN'-TED'. THES~ eEUEkf~, O-zRtf
PRd6R'AM, AND-t ORE ' THANOESE11TR'x*. f iN., I8 4 fH., ROIGH',.<br />
-1-R 4G E,, 7 OF 4' E EN a rl,: 5 '! NERTD<br />
. rq<br />
ADJUSTME 0SN GLONGSTANDI NG ' EPTSADCCESO. OR*--EXAMPLE-;-<br />
WE FOUND'. L~' EESSARY TO A 0P tCY( A 4N* CO kE-TE ST T40 CER-tAIN-' AGEPENS<br />
I REMOYE, PROSPECTjIYEL-Y4Q SO. ME7 OF, THEY-1AT:<br />
CONCESSIZONS: i't&amp; SOCIATED* WIHL1_ SI~ PRANNUATION'. 7T.-v<br />
NET--EF, S, TVUE~ S: O~ EUEi<br />
t ItS SQ. ETYE~ kS.. THIS R4tRESENT8':* A., RE uTj ON I1 THE<br />
STfUtTURA IfD9FI1C. 1T* I'N -T HE OUTERYASOFABU1 PE R' r~ F b . GR OS S<br />
DOMES T 1C-' PP RODUCT...<br />
T HE. OVERALL* AMO OUR B U DGE T &amp; TRATEGY.<br />
IOS ~ M1NTINSUBSTANTIAL FISCALtETIMULUS: 1NTE IDIAT E.<br />
FUTURE, t. BUT To: ENSURE THAT T HE6, STRU C TU R AL'!] D &amp; iC IT I S. ED<br />
BACK INTHE-COURSE OF RECOVERY-F-AS THE DEMAN6 õ OF ' PR IVAE"<br />
INVESTMENT ON FINANCIAL MARK ETS*.-4N CREASE<br />
OUR BUDGET : STRAT. EGY IS, O COLRSE, CLOS Et L IN KE D,. IT-; A . tl,, A P P R0A C H<br />
TO'fONE TARY: QPOLI. i-: WHILE WE--E~ jkT' THE:. BEI -" THT CO tRO ' F ',' TH* 4E<br />
lIN~ 1 "'~ AGREGATES-ALONE ' CAN .' DEL I VER NONIFA I'ONARY'%* kOT;'<br />
B EL IEV5-. . TNAt'.. T-E! RE IS A ROLE_ g1 GON-VLE TTAG-T&gt; O~<br />
MIOOFNJ OEHTFA' 4R'Y* kN, GERMWOW'r' ' TSHU PP~ Y CC-IT MISOO7T-uE lNTTH. ErNICT1EOSN T O3 IN'P4RINOLVQID UEP: TJIU-AS" TE ' yF~ CETO-: ftI--<br />
CONS fDR-' ESRAL AN FEAIE,~ -SEAR I NGI MN. I PR CLJT1<br />
WAGEG t Aq-GENERAT. ED W-I-. THIP4. IH-.; CNTA~' E'' GE-* , YT<br />
TR( S~ 1S AYOJ -D ESI GNED. 1T-! O ' CiB NLAT QAY1lPUssW<br />
P4TTINGB4-' k' :,, O. GR'OWTH -i441TrHIt-tal I S.' CNTE EZC~. OJC<br />
WAGS ~ T-iG-STEM"*.; 1 -NCURRENT-. TPRSE! T<br />
DEL~~ AA y, O-SRC IRCU TANCESXT-O-..<br />
LtS": NFATlbt4* A OUTLOOK WIL EREIlNFORPEDtbY* MON 41 Yr -p OLI-cy.",-<br />
THE ' SUMMI-T,.* SOMMUNIGUE RECOMMENDED-THE' . RE-TURN TO,--CENT* RAL1! ZEA..<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
WAGE-SETTING SYSTEM. STEPS HAVE BFEN TAKEN ALONG THESE LINES.<br />
WITHIN THE CENTRALISED SYSTEM WE ARE EXPECTING NOMINAL WAGE INCREASES<br />
IN THE ORDER OF 3 TO 4 PER CENT.. IN THE CURRENT CALENDAR YEAR,<br />
COMPARED WITH THREE OR FOUR TIMES THAT LEVEL IN EACH OF THE PRECEDING<br />
YEARS. I WOULD EXPECT AMERICANS . TO, BE-, SCEPTICAL ABOUT CENTRALISED,<br />
WAGE-SETTING, AND IN PARTICULAR ABOUT,: WHETHER IT WOULD BE CAPABLE OF<br />
-DELIVERING A GREATER DEGREE OF WAG. E RESTRAINT THAN COLLECTIVE<br />
BARGAINING ALONG AMERICAN LINES. : THIS IS ONE AREA WHERE AUSTRALIAN<br />
TRADITIONS AND-INSTITUTIONS ARE . HARKEDLY DIFFERENT FROM THE.. AMERICAN.<br />
IN AUSTRALIA,' STRONG TRADI. TIONS.," OF RIGID WAGE RELATIVITIES READILY<br />
TRANSFER WAGE GAINS BY STRONG&gt; UNIONS THROUGHOUT THE ECONOMY, EVEN IN<br />
THE FACE OF SUBSTANTIAL GENERAL ' UNEMPLOYMENT. THIS HAPPENED IN .1981<br />
WHEN WAGE GAINS BY SOME SECTIONS OF-THE WORKFORCE THAT WERE FAVOURED<br />
BY AN INVESTMENT BOOM IN THE-RESOURCE SECTOR LED TO A GENERAL WAGE<br />
EXPLOSION THAT WAS AN IMPORTANT CAUSE OF OUR CURRENT DIFFICULTIES.<br />
THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT HAS ACCEPTED.. THAT THE RETURN TO A<br />
CENTRALISED SYSTEM MUST BE. ACCOMPANIED. BY THE REPUDIATION OF<br />
SECTIONAL CLAIMS. IF THERE IS COMPLIANCE WITH THIS UNDERSTANDING,<br />
THEN THERE ARE GOOD PROSPECTS THAT ECONOMIC RECOVERY OVER THE NEXT<br />
FEW YEARS WILL BE ACCOMPANIED BY SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER RATES OF WAGES<br />
GROWTH THAN HAVE BEEN EXPERIENCED IN AUSTRALIA OVER THE PAST DECADE.<br />
SUSTAINED ECONOMIC GROWTH WILL REQUIRE COMMUNITY<br />
ACCEPTANCE OF TECHNICAL AND STRUCTURAL CHANGE IN THE ECONOMY<br />
TO FACILITATE INCREASES IN. PRODUCTIVITY AND INVESTMENT. ONE<br />
OF THE AIMS OF CONSULTATION AND CONSENSUS'WILL BE TO BUILD.<br />
COMMUNITY UNDERSTANDING AND . SUPPORT FOR ' SUCH CHANGE. ALREADY<br />
THERE ARE SIGNS THAT AUSTRALIAN WORKERS AND THEIR TRADE UNIONS<br />
ARE PREPARED TO ACCEPT CHANGES IN MANNING PRACTICES WHERE THIS<br />
IS RECOGNISED AS BEING IMPORTANT TO. PRODUCTIVITY INCREASES<br />
AND THEREFORE O. LONG-TERM EMPLOYMENTSECURITY. ALREADY WE<br />
ARE-SEEKING SUBSTANTIAL IMPROVEMEN: SN.:. INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS<br />
ON THE WATERFRONT: AND IN THE.: BU. DILiNG INDUSTRIES, WHERE IN<br />
THE PAST, EXCESSI. VE . DISPUTATION HASIMPOSED HEAVY COSTS ON<br />
AUSTRALIAN DEVELOPMENT. AUSTRALIA'S EXIERNAL POLICIES<br />
THE EXPLOSION OF AUSTRALIAN COSTS I-N 1981 AND 1982 WHEN THE<br />
UNITED STATES AND MUCH OF THE REST OF THE WORLD WAS ENTERING A<br />
REMARKABLE PERIOD OF DISINFLATION, LEFT THE AUSTRALIAN DOLLAR HIGHLY<br />
VULNERABLE. SINCE LATE 1976, THE IAILY.. VALUE OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
DOLLAR HAS BEEN SET BY REFERENCE TO A TRADE-WEIGHTED BASKET. OF<br />
CURRENCIES, WITH THE RATE BEING. VARIED FREQUENTLY BY SMALL AMOUNTS<br />
AGAINST THIS BASKET IN RESPONSE. TO MARKET CONDITIONS. I SUPPOSE THE<br />
SYSTEM CAN BE DESCRIBED AS A-HEAVILY MANAGED FLOAT. IN RESPONSE TO<br />
DOMESTIC INFLATIONARY PRESSURES,'. OUR AUTHORITIES WERE FORCED TO<br />
ENGINEER A SUBSTANTIAL DEPRECIATION OF THE DOLLAR AGAINST THE BASKET<br />
FROM AUGUST 1981 ONWARDS. A FURTHER ONCE-FOR-ALL DEVALUATION WITHIN<br />
DAYS OF THE MARCH 5 ELECTION RESTORED AUSTRALIA'S RELATIVE COST<br />
POSITION. THE PRESENT EXCHANGE RATE SYSTEM WILL CONTINUE.<br />
IN AUSTRALIA AS IN ALL COUNTRIES, DEEP RECESSION BRINGS PRESSURES<br />
FOR INCREASED PROTECTION. THE PROTECTION ISSUE CUTS ACROSS PARTY<br />
LINES IN AUSTRALIAN POLITICS. MY GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT<br />
AUSTRALIA'S INTERSTS WILL BE SERVED BEST BY CRHDUAL MOVEMENT TOWARDS<br />
LOWER PROTECTION. BUT WE DO NOT BELIEVE THAT THE INTERESTS OF<br />
PERMANENT MOVEMENT TOWARDS A MORE LIBERAL TRADING STANCE WOULD BE<br />
SERVED WELL BY RADICAL REDUCTIONS IN PROTECTION AT PRESENT, WHILE<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT REMAINS EXTREMELY HIGH. WE WILL NEVERTHELESS RETAIN<br />
./ 7 </p>
<p>pROGRAMS FOR GRADUAL LIVERALISATION OF IMPORTS IN THE TWO MOST HI; HL Y<br />
pROTFCTED AREAS OF AUSTRALIAN MANUFACTURING INDUSTRY, TEXTILES<br />
CLOTHING AND FOOTWEAR, AND MOTOR VEHICLES, IN THE INTERESTS OF<br />
PRESERVING CONTINUITY IN THE ECONIMIC POLICY ENVIRONMENT. SPECIAL<br />
DIFFICULTIES'MAY LEAD US TO PROVIDE SOME INCREASE IN ASSISTANCE FOR A<br />
STRICLLY LIMITED PERIOD IN ONE OR TWO OTHER AREAS. BUT THERE SHOULD<br />
BE NO DOUBT' ABOUT MY GOVERNMENT'S COMMITMENT TO TRADE LIBERALISATION<br />
AS THE ECONOMY STRENGTHENS IN THE YEARS AHEAD.<br />
I KNOW THAT THIS GREAT FINANCIAL CENIRE, NEW YORK, HAS A SPECIAL<br />
INTEREST IN OUR APPROACH TO REGULATION OF THE FINANCIAL SECTOR. THIS<br />
WAS THE SUBJECT OF THE MAJOR INQUIRY CHAIRED BY THE LATE SIR KEITH<br />
CAMP1F. LL. MY GOVERNMENT HAS RECENTLY ANNOUNCED A REVIEW OF THE<br />
CAMPBELL REPORT RECOMMENDATIONS IN THE LIGHT OF OUR OWN OBJECTIVES<br />
4ND PRIORITIES. ANY DFTAILED STATEMENT OF OUR POSITION MUST AWAIT<br />
IHE RESULTS OF THAT REVIEW, WHICH WILL NOT BE AVAILABLE FOR SEVERAL<br />
M'ONIHS. HOWEVER, YOU SHOULD KNOW THAT WE SEE NO VIRTUE IN REGULATION<br />
FOR ITS OWN SAKE.<br />
MORE GENERALLY ON FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY, GUIDELINES FOR<br />
FOREIGN INVESTMENT IN AUSTRALIA HAVE BEEN DEVELOPING UNDER SUCCESSIVE<br />
GOVERNMENTS SINCE THE 1960S.<br />
THERE HAD BEEN VARIOUS POLICIES ADDRESSED TO ASPECTS<br />
OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT BUT A COMPIEHENSIVE POLICY WAS NOT" FORMULATED<br />
UNIIL THE PREVIOUS LABOR GOVERNMLNI IN 19' 5. WHILE THAT POLICY WAS<br />
ELABORATED BY THE LIBERAL-NATIONAL PARTY COALITION, THE FUNDAMENTAL<br />
FEATURES HAVE REMAINED UNALTERED. THIS HAS REFLECTED THE<br />
CONSIDERABLE DEGREE OF BIPARTISAN POLITICAL SUPPORT AND, MORE<br />
GENERALLY, COMMUNITY SUPPORT FOR THE ROLE OF FOREIGN CAPITAL IN<br />
DEVELOPING AUSTRALIA'S INDUSTRIES AND RESOURCES.<br />
THE FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY OF SUCCESSIVE<br />
IAUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS HAS BEEN BASED ON THE TWIN PILLARS:<br />
FIRST, A RECOGNITION OF THE SIGNIFICANT CONTRIBUTION THAT FOREIGN<br />
CAPITAL CAN MAKE TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF AUSTRALIA'S INDUSTRIES AND<br />
RESOURCES: AND SECOND, OF THE IMPORTANCE, AT TIHE SAME TIME, OF<br />
PROVIDING ADEQUATE OPPORltJNITIES FOR AUSTRALIANS TO PARTICIPATE IN<br />
THAr DEVELOPMENT. IN ECONMIC TERMS, FOREIGN CAPITAL ENABLES<br />
AUSIRALIA 10 HAVE A HIGHER RATE OF GROWTH IN ECONOMIC ACTIVITY AND<br />
EMPLOYMENT THAN WOULD OTHERWISE BE THE CASE.<br />
WHILE RECOGNIZING THE IMPORTANT ECONOMIC BENEFITS FLOWING FROM<br />
FOREIGN INVESTMENT, GOVERNMENTS HAVE ALSO BEEN AWARE OF THE NEED TO<br />
BALANCE THOSE BENEFITS AGAINST AN EXCESSIVE INCREASE IN FOREIGN<br />
OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL OF AUSTRALIAN RESOURCES AND INDUSTRIES. THIS<br />
HAS NOT BEEN SO MUCH A MATTER OF CONCERN OVER THE POSSIBLE ECONOMIC<br />
COSTS OF FOREIGN OWNERSHIP. RATHER, IT HAS BEEN A RECOGNITION OF<br />
CONTINUING COMMUNITY CONCERN THAT THE DEGREE OF FOREIGN OWNERSHIP AND<br />
CONTROL SHOULD NOT EXCEED CERTAIN BOUNDS.<br />
VARIOUS STATEMENTS BY THE TREASURER AND MYSELF SINCE<br />
ASSUMING OFFICE HAVE AFFIRMED THE RECOGNITION OF THE ECONOMIC<br />
BENEFITS OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT AND ACCEPTANCE OF THE BROAD THRUST OF<br />
THE POLICY THAT HAS BEEN IN OPERATION FOR SEVERAL YEARS.<br />
THE TREASURER HAS ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT AN EARLY<br />
REVIEW IS BEING UNDERTAKEN. THE TREASURER HAS INDICATED<br />
THAT THE MAIN EMPHASIS OF THE REVIEW WILL BE ON POLICY CONTINUITY,<br />
ALTHOUGH THERE MAY BE SOME CHANGES OF EMPHASIS, PARTICULARLY IN<br />
RELATION TO REAL ESTATE, AND FOR LOCAL EGUITY REQUIREMENTS IN<br />
MANUFACTURING. ANY SUCH CHANGES OF EMPHASIS WOULD BE APPLIED<br />
/ 8 </p>
<p>FL-EXIB3LY SO AS NOT TO EXCLUDE INVFSTMENT THAT WOULD BRING DENEFITS TO<br />
4USTRAL1I4A UNDER THE ESTABLISHED POLICY, FOREIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSALS ARE<br />
CONSIDERED CASE-BY-CASE BY THE TREASURER, IN THE LIGHT OF ADVICE FROMi<br />
A FOREIGN INVESTMENT REVIEW BOARD.<br />
IN ITS FIRST TWO AND A HALF MONTHS IN OFFICE, THE GOVERNMENT<br />
CONSIWDERED 228 FOREIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSALS, OF WHICH 208 WERE<br />
APPROVED AND 20 WERE REJECTED. ALTHOUJGH THIS RATE OF REJECTION IS<br />
SOMEWHAT HIGHER THAN THAI UNDER 1HE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENI THE MORE<br />
RECENT FIGURES REFLECT A NUMBER OF FACTORS AND, ESPECIALLY AS THEY<br />
APPLY TO ONLY A LIMITED PERIOD OF TIME, SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN AS<br />
INDICATING ANY NOTABLE CHANGE IN POLICY.<br />
UNDER THE ESTABLISHED POLICIES WHICH WILL BE BROADLY MAINTAINED<br />
BY MY GOVERNMENT, AMERICAN CORPORATE, INSTITUTIONAL AND PRIVATE<br />
FINANCIAL GROUPS INVESTCD APPROXIM1ATELY DOLLARS 6 BILLION IN<br />
AUSTRALIAN ENTERPRISES DURING THE FIVE YEARS TO 1981-82. THE UNITED<br />
! STATES RETAINED ITS POSITION AS THE LARGEST SOURCE OF DIRECT<br />
INVESTMENT CAPITAL, WHICH IT HAS HELD FOR MOST OF THE POSTWAR PERIOD.<br />
A SUBSTANTIAL PART OF AMERICAN INVESTMENT IN RECENT<br />
YEARS HAS BEEN IN MINING AND RELATt D ACTIVITIES. THE<br />
TECH4NICAL AND MARKETING SkILLS, MANAGEMENT AND FINANCIAL<br />
STRENGTH OF AMERICAN CORPORATIONS MADE A CRUCIAL<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO T1HE DEVELOPMENT OF THE MINING AND<br />
PROCESSING INDUSTRIES WHICH PROVIDED THE MAIN IMPETUS<br />
TO AUSTRALIAN ECONOMIC GROWTH THROU6iH MUCH OF THE I<br />
PAST ONE AND A HALF DECADES. THE POLICIES OF MY GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL FACILITATE THE CONTINUED EXPANSION OF THESE INDUSTRIES<br />
AND THE CONTINUED PARTICIPATION OF FOREIGN CAPITAL IN THAT<br />
EXPANSION. THERE MAY BE SOME APPREHENSION AMONGST UNITED STATES<br />
INVESTORS ABOUT THE EFFECTS ON THE MINING INDUSTRY OF TWO<br />
ASPECTS OF THE PROGRAM UPON WHICH MY GOVERNMENT WAS ELECTED:<br />
THE COMMITMENT TO INTRODUCE A RESOURCE RENT TAX ON THAT<br />
PART OF MINING INCOME WHICH IS PROPERLY REGARDED AS<br />
ECONOMIC RENT: AND OUR POLICY ON URANIUM MINING.<br />
WHILE THE MINING INDUSTRY IS UNDERSTANDABLY ANXIOUS<br />
ABOUT ANY PROPOSALS TO CHANGE TAXAl ION ARRANGEMENTS, GIVEN<br />
THE NORMAL HUMAN TENDENCY TO FEAR THE WORST, I AM CONFIDENT<br />
THAT THE INTRODUCTION OF A RESOURCE RENT TAX WOULD INCREASE<br />
RATHER THAN DIMINISH INCENTIVES FOR EXPANSION OF THE<br />
MINING INDUSTRY. AT THIS STAGE OUR PROPOSAL RELATES ONLY t<br />
TO OFF-SHORE PETROLEUM AND COAL. THE PROPOSAL IS TO<br />
REPLACE HIGHLY DISTORTING EXCISES, ROYALTIES AND EXPORT<br />
TAXES BASED ON THE VOLUME OR VALUE OF PRODUCTION EBY A<br />
RESOURCE RENT TAX BASED ON CASH FLOW. NO LIABILITY FOR<br />
RESOURCE RENT TAX WOULD BE INCURRED UNTIL ALL CASH<br />
OUTLAYS HAD BJEEN RECOUPED WITH INIEREST AT RATES THAT<br />
WERL SUFFICIENTLY HIGH TO MAINTAIN INCENTIVES. UNLIKE<br />
THE CHARGES THAT IT WOULD REPLACE, THE RESOURCE RENT TAX<br />
WOULD NOT INHIBIT THE DEVELOPMENT 0OF MARGINAL MINES, OR<br />
THE FULL ECONOMIC RECOVERY OF LOW-GRADE OR LESS ACCESSIBLE<br />
PARTS OF MINERAL DEPOSITS. UNLIKE THE CHARGES WHICH IT<br />
THE EXTENSION OF OUR MARKETS BEYOND OUR OWN REGION,<br />
INTO MORE DISTANT PARTS OF THE WORLD WHI1CH YIELD LOWER I<br />
RETURNS AF7TER MEETING TRANSPORT COSTS. AS WAS UNDERLINED<br />
./ 9 </p>
<p>: S y DISCUSSIONS IN PARIS LAST WEEK, REFORMS ALONG IHESE<br />
. LI NL COULD BE EXTREMELY IMPORTANI TO OUR EMERGENCE AS<br />
MAJOR COAL SUPPLIER TO EUROPE.<br />
; uNDER AUSTRALIA'S FEDERAL CONSTITUIION, MY GOVERNMENT<br />
; HAS AUTHORITY WITH RESPECT TO OFF-SHORE PETROLEUM.<br />
jIN THE COAL I. NDUSTRY, HOWEVER, OUR POLICY CAN BE<br />
IMPLEMENTED ONLY THROUGH CO-OPERATION WITH THE STATES.<br />
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WILL NOT INTRODUCE A RESOURCE<br />
RENI TAX ON COAL UNLESS IT IS POSSIBLE TO REACH AGREEMENT.<br />
WIIH THE STATE GOVERNMENTS ON THE kLPLACEMENT OF<br />
DISIORTING CHARGES CURRENTLY APPLIED BY THEM.<br />
IN THE CASE OF URANIUM POLICY, SOME OF YOU MAY FIND<br />
nY COMMENTS OF LESS COMFORT. YOU WILL APPRECIATE THAT THIS<br />
IS AN ISSUE OF INTENSE DEBATE WITHIN THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
COMMUNITY, NOT LEAST IN MY OWN PARlY. OUR POLICY PROVIDES<br />
FOR THE CONTINUATION OF SALES UNDER EXISTING CONTRACTS.<br />
THERE IS A SPECIAL ISSUE IN RELATION TO FRANCE, BECAUSE<br />
OF THE TESTING-OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS IN THE SOUTH PACIFIC.<br />
PENDING A POSSIBLE RESOLUTION OF THESE PROBLEMS, PRESIDENT<br />
MITTERRAND AND I HAVE REACHED AN UNDERSTANDING THAT<br />
THERE WILL BE NO FURTHER SHIPMENTS TO FRANCE UNTIL AT<br />
LEAST OCTOBER, 1984.<br />
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC POLICY<br />
I HAVE ALREADY EMPHASISED THE IMPORTANCE TO AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT OF INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC CONDITIONS,<br />
AND OF A LIBERAL INTERNATIONA.'. TRADE AND PAYMENTS SYSTEM.<br />
SINCE LEAVING AUSTRALIA TWO WEEKS AGO, I HAVE<br />
HAD THE OPPORTUNITY OF LEARNING AT FIRST HAND FROM PRIME MINISTER<br />
SOMARE IN PAPUA NEW GUINEA AND PRESIDENT SOEHARTO IN<br />
INDONESIA, ABOUT THE DAMAGE THAT THE WORLD RECESSION HAS<br />
WROUGHT ON DEVELOPING COUNTRIES IN AUSTRALIA'S OWN REGION.<br />
PAPUA NEW GUINEA AND INDONESIA HAVE HAD REASONABLY GOOD<br />
RECORDS OF ECONOMIC STABILITY AND ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT OVER<br />
THE PAST DECADE, AND YET THEY HAVE BEEN FORCED INTO MASSIVE<br />
DOMESTIC ADJUSTMENT PROGRAMS BY THE CONTRACTION IN WORLD<br />
TRADE AND LOW COMMODITY PRICES OF THE PAST FEW YEARS. MANY<br />
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES, ESPECIALLY THOSE WHICH BORROWED<br />
ESTENSIVELY AND WERE ENCOURAGED TO DO SO ON INTERNATIONAL<br />
MARKETS IN THE 1970S, ARE EXPERIENCING EVEN GREATER<br />
DIFFICULTIES. TMEGE COUNTRIES, LIKE AUSTRALIA, MUST LOOK TO STRONG<br />
CXPANSION IN WORLD TRADE IN THE PROCESS OF INTERNATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC RECOVERY. ANY FAILURE OF TRADING OPPORTUNITIES<br />
WILL HAVE TRAGIC CONSEQUENCES FOR MANY DEVELOPING COUNTRIES.<br />
BUT THE CONSEQUENCES OF FAILURE WILL GO BEYOND THESE<br />
TRAGEDIES FOR INDIVIDUAL COUNTRIES, TO THE FOUNDATIONS<br />
OF INTERNATIONAL FINANCIAL AS WELL AS POLITICAL STABILITY.<br />
ON THIS VISIT I HAVE BEEN GREAILY ENCOURAGED BY THE EVIDENCE OF<br />
STRONG AND BROADLY BASED RECOVERY IN THE UNITED STATES ECONOMY. A<br />
STRONG UNITED STATES ECONOMY IS OBVIOUSLY NECESSARY FOR A STRONG<br />
WORLD ECONOMY.<br />
IT IS OF GREAT IMPORTANCE THAT THE WELCOME STRENGTHENING OF THE<br />
UNITED STATES ECONOMY SHOULD REPRESENT THE BEGINNING OF WORLDWIDE<br />
ECONOMIC RESURGENCE. I HAVE TWO KINDS OF DOUBTS ABOUT WHETHER THIS<br />
EXTENSION OF RECOVERY WILL OCCUR. FIRST, IN PRESENT CIRCUMSTANCES,<br />
J E ADDITIONAL PRESSURES IN FINANCIAL MARKETS ASSOCIATED WITH THE </p>
<p>1 0<br />
' RESURGENCE OF PRIVATE INVES7MENT IN THE COURSE OF ECONOMIC RECOvER,<br />
COULD ABORT RECOVERY AT A REL ATIVLY EARLY STAGE. SECOND, THE<br />
PROLIFERATION OF BARRIERS TO INTERNATIONAL TRADE THROUGH THE. RECENT<br />
RECESSION, IN CONTRAVENTION OF TH SPIRIT OF THE LIBERAL MULTILATERAL<br />
1RADING SYSTEM, COULD PREVENT STRONG EXPANSION IN MAJOR INDUSTRIAL<br />
COUNTRIES FROM BEING REFLECTED FULLY IN EXPANSION OF INTERNATIONAL<br />
TRADE. THE FIRST OF THESE THREATS REI&amp; IES TO THE LARGE STRUCTURAL BUDGET<br />
DEFICITS IN MANY COUNTRIES. IF THESE DEFICITS PRESIST THROUGH A<br />
PERIOD OF INTERNATIONAL. RECOVERY, IT IS INEVITARLE THAT THE NECESSARY<br />
INCREASES IN PRIVATE INVESTMENT WI1 BE REFLECTED IN HIGHER INTEREST<br />
RATES. ALL COUNTRIES HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY IN Ti1S REGARD: IT IS<br />
UNREASONABLE TO EXPECT THE UNITED STATFS ALONE TO CARRY T4E<br />
RESPONSIBILITY FOR MAINTAINING STARIILITY IN THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
FINANCIAL SYSTEM.<br />
ON THE SECOND THREAT TO THE EXIENSION OF THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
RECOVERY, I AM HEARTENED AT LEAST BY THE INCREASING REALISATION, AS<br />
PRESIDENT REAGAN TOLD ME ON MONDAY FOLLOWING HIS OWN PARTICIPATION IN<br />
THE WILLIAMSBURG MEETING, OF HOW MUCH IS AT STAKE FOR WORLD<br />
DEVELOPMENT IN THE SPREAD OF PROTECTIONISM. BUT RECESSION AND<br />
PROTECTION HAVE FED ON EACH OTHER IN RECENT YEARS TO SUCH AN EXTENT,<br />
IN AUSTRALIA AS MUCH AS ELSEWHERE, THAT IT WILL RE NO EASY MATTER TO<br />
RESTORE CONDITIONS UNDER WHICH WORI. D RECOVERY AND TRADE EXPANSION<br />
WILl BE MUTUALLY REINFORCING.<br />
THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY WILL NEED TO LOOK MORE<br />
CLOSELY AT THE PROLIFERATION-THRO16H THE 1970' S OF * EXCEPTIONS'<br />
TO THE GENERAL GOAL OF L'IBERAL TRADE. WE WILL ALSO HAVE<br />
TO BE CAREFUL THAT ATTEMPTS TO UNRAVEL THE PAST DISTORTIONS,<br />
IN A PEACEMEAL FASHION, DO NOT GIVE RISE TO NEW PROBLEMS<br />
ARISING OUT OF PRESSURES WITHIN BILATERAL TRADING RELATIONSHIPS<br />
BETWEEN LARGE COUNTRIES.<br />
AUSTRALIA AND ITS REPIDLY GROWING NEIGHBOURS IN NORTHEAST AND<br />
SOUTHEAST ASIA WONDER ABOUT A LIBERAL TRADING SYSTEM UNDER WHICH THE<br />
PRODUCTS OF THEIR OWN MOST PRODUCTIVE INDUSTRIES IN ONE CASE, FOOD,<br />
IN THE OTHER, TEXTILES ARE TREATVD AS ' EXCEPTIONS'. FOR OUR PART,<br />
WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR THE SUPPORT THAT THE UNITED STATES HAD GIVEN US<br />
ON FOOD TRADE ISSUES IN THE MAIN INTERNATIONAL FORUMS, BUT THE<br />
' EXCEPTIONS' REMAIN, I THINK THAT YOU WOULD UNDERSTAND THAT THERE IS<br />
SOME CYNICISM ON THAT SCORE IN AUSTRALIA, AND ELSEWHERE IN THE<br />
WESTERN PACIFIC REGION.<br />
THE SECOND TYPE OF PROBLEM FACED BY AUSTRALIA AND ITS DEVELOPING<br />
COUNTRY NEIGHBOURS IN THE WESTERN PACIFIC HAS BEEN EVIDENT IN THE<br />
BILATERAL TRADE CONFRONTATIONS BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES, JAPAN, AND<br />
THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES. WE ARE NATURALLY CONCERNED THAT THE<br />
RESOLUTION OF THESE CONFLICTS SHOULD NOT INVOLVE DEALS WHICH<br />
INCIDENTALLY DAMAGE OUR OWN INTERESTS. SIMILAR PROBLEMS COULD ARISE<br />
FROM ATTEMPTS BY THE LARGE INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES TO DEAL IN AN AD H4OC<br />
FASHION WITH THE TRADE PROBLEMS OF THOSE DEVELOPING COUNTRIES WITH<br />
THE MOST ACUTE DEBT PROBLEMS.<br />
AS I EXPLAINED IN WASHINGTON YESTERDAY, AND IN THE INTRODUCTION<br />
TO THIS ADDRESS, AUSTRALIA HAS A PARTICULAR INTEREST IN THE ECONOMIC<br />
AND POLITICAL LIFE OF THE ASIA-PACIFIC REGION. WE WOULD SUGGEST<br />
THAT THE UNITED STATES, TOO, HAS MUCH TO GAIN BY TAKING FULL ACCOUNT<br />
' OF THE TRADING INTERESTS OF COUNTRIES IN THIS REGION. NOWHERE IN THE<br />
; WORLD IS THERE A FIRMER BASE OF COMMITMENT TO THE EXPANSION OF<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADE </p>
<p>AUSTRALIA IS CONSCIOUS 0F, ITS SUBSTANIIAL RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
STHE GROWING ECONOMIC PARTNERSHIP THAT HAS EMERGED IN THE<br />
PAC IF IC.<br />
WE REMAIN A STRATEGIC SHEET-ANCHOR IN JAPAN'S RAW<br />
MATERIAL PROCUREMENTS. WE ARE AN INCREASINGLY IMPQRTANT. SUPPLIER OF<br />
RAW MATERIALS, FOODSTUFFS, AND MANUFACTURES TO ALL THE NEWLY<br />
INDUSTRIALISING COUNTRIES OF THE WESTERN PACIFIC.<br />
THE UNITED STATES RELAIIONSHIP WITH JAPAN IS HUGE AND IMPORTANT<br />
IN ITS OWN RIGHT. BUT UINITED) STATE-S DEALINGS WITH JAPAN ON ECONOMIC<br />
AND OTHER MATTERS ARE OF PARTICuLAR~ INTEREST TO AUSTRALIA AND OTHER<br />
COUNTRIES IN ITS REGION. IN THE NORMAL COURSE OF EVENTS, COMPARATIVE<br />
DIFFERENCES LEAD AUSTRALIA TO HAVE A TRADE SURPLUS WITH JAPAN,<br />
JAPAN WITH THE UNITED STATES AND THEL UNITED STATES WITH AUSTRALIA.<br />
IN SUCH CIRCUMSTANCES, BILATERAL. TRADING DEALS CAN CORRODE OUR<br />
COLLECTIVE INTERESTS AND RESPONSIULIIIES.<br />
TO BE SPECIFIC, WE IN AUSTRALIA HAVE A DEEP INTEREST IN ENSURING,<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, THAT TH4E ACCESS THE UNITED STATES GAINS TO THE<br />
REGULATED AGRICULTURAL MARKET IN JAPAN IS CONSISTENT WITH THE<br />
PRINCIPLES OF A MOST FAVOURED NATION TRADING SYSTEM. OUR OTHER<br />
NORTHEAST ASIAN AND SOUTHEAST ASIAN PARTNERS IN THE PACIFIC HAVE<br />
SIMILAR INTEREST IN OTHE R AREAS 0OF TRADE.<br />
THE STRENGTH AND THE SIGNIFICANCE Of" AUSTRALIA'S RELATIONSHIP<br />
WITH JAPAN IN THE WESTERN-PACIFIC MAY BE SOMET. IMES UNDERESTIMATED.<br />
AT TH4IS TIME, WHEN WE FACE LARGE PROBLEMS AND CHOICES IN THE<br />
DIRECTION OF THE WORLD ECONOMY, IT IS IMPORTANT NOT TO NEGLECT<br />
BROADER REGIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL INTERESTS AND COMMITMENTS IN OUR<br />
BILATERAL DEALINGS.<br />
THESE CONCERNS IN THE PACIFIC ARE CENTRAL TO THE BROADLY<br />
BASED INTEREST IN AUSTRALIA IN EXPLORING THE IDEA OF CLOSER<br />
ECONOMIC CO-OPERATION IN THE PACIFIC.<br />
AUSTRALIANS UNDERSTAND WELL THAT THERE WAS NO WAY THAT THE<br />
POSTWAR TRADING AND INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC SYSTEM, WITH ALL ITS<br />
BENEFITS TO INDIVIDUAL COUNTRIES LIKE AUSTRALIA, JAPAN, THE STATES OF<br />
EUROPE, AND THE NEWLY INDUSTRIALISING COUNTRIES, COULD HAVE EVOLVED<br />
WITHOUT UNITED STATES LEADERSHIP.<br />
LEADERSHIP, IN THIS CONTEXT, MEANT CARRYI NG THE PRIME<br />
BURDEN, INITIALLY IN TERMS OF AID F-OR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT<br />
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY IN TERMS OF THE COST OF TRADE ADJUSTMENT AND<br />
ECONOMIC LIBERALISATION, TO DELIVER THE POSTWAR RULES OF TRADE.<br />
NO SINGLE COUNTRY CAN CARRY THAT BURDEN ALONE TODAY. THERE IS A<br />
CLOSE ANALOGY HERE TO THE PROBLEM IN FINANCIAL MARKETS TO WHICH I<br />
REFERRED EARLIER.<br />
THE POINT IS THAT THE UNITED STATES AND AUSTRALIA NEED TO WORK<br />
IOGET14ER MORE CLOSELY WITH OUR OTHER PACIFIC PARTNERS TO ENSURE T1HAT<br />
OUR ACTIONS ARE CONSISTENT WITH MAKING OUR PRINCIPLES EFFECTIVE IN<br />
THE PACIFIC AND GLOBAL ARENAS.<br />
YESTERDAY AT THE-NATIONAL PRESS CLUB I CONFIRMED AUSTRALIA'S<br />
COMMITMENT TO THE ANZUS STRATEGIC ALLIANCE. IN CONCLUSION TODAY I<br />
WISH TO CONFIRM<br />
STHTIAV7TiE SS: Y STEMT HEW E LIARBOEUE RR APLLC OAMYMMUIILNTTGIM. LEOANUTTRE RTFAOUL L LA NTROPATADHREET R AAASN DL LAI PAASNYOCMUEER NCTELS E DO FS YBYST THEET MH. EF IUNNAWIINTTCEHIIDAN LI </p>
<p>1 2-<br />
AID THAT IS NECESSARY FOR DEVELOPMLNT AND POLITICAL STABILITY IN THE<br />
NEW NATIONS OF. THE SOUTHWEST PACIFIC: AS A RELIABLE SOURCE OF FOOD<br />
AND RAW MATERIALS TO THE RAPIDLY EXPANDING ECONOMIES OF NORTHEAST AND<br />
SOUTHESTr ASIA: INCREASINGLY AS A SOURCE OF MANUFACTURES AND SERVICES<br />
BASED ON THE SKILLS OF THE AUSTRAL. IAN PEOPLE: AND AS A NATION<br />
COMMITTED TO ACHIEVING ITS ECONOMIC GOALS THROUGH CLOSE CO--OPERATION<br />
WITH ITS NEIGHBOURS IN THE PACIFIC AND WITH THE WIDER INTERNATIONAL<br />
COMMUNITY. THE PATH4 TO ECONOMIC RECOVERY WILL BE A LONG ONE, EVEN FOR THE<br />
UNITED STATES, WHICH HAS MADE SUCH A GOOD BEGINNING. IT IS OUR HOPE<br />
THAT THE WORLDS'S RE-COMMITMENT TO THE GOALS OF THE LIBERAL POSTWAR<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND PAYMENTS SYSTEM WILL ALLOW THE EXTENSION OF<br />
THE UNITED STATES RECOVERY INTO TH REST OF THE WORLD, AND THE<br />
REINFORCEMENT OF THE UNITED STATES RECOVERY ITSELF.<br />
THE PATH WILL BE LONGER FOR AUSTRALIA, WHERE ECONOMIC ACTIVITY<br />
AND EMPLOYMENT WERE STILL FALLING 1RAPIDLY WHEN WE T00OK OFFICE THREE<br />
MONTHS AGO. BUT WITH OUR SEARCH FOR COMMUNITY CONSENSUS ON ECONOMIC<br />
POLICIES, AND WITH OUR APPROACH TO WAGES, FISCAL, MONETARY AND<br />
EXTERNAL POLICIES, WE ARE CONFIDENI THAT THE RESTORATION OF GROWTWiTH<br />
LOW INFLATION IN AUSTRALIA HAS BEGUN. WE LOOK FORWARD TO TRADE<br />
WITH AND INVESTMENT -FROM THE UNITED STATES PLAYING AN IMPORTANT PART<br />
IN THAT RECOVERY, JUST AS THEY HAVE IN EARLIER PERIODS OF POST-WAR<br />
PROSPERITY. AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB IN WASHINGTON YESTERDAY,<br />
IN SPEAKING ON AUSTRALIA'S FOREIGN * POLICY, I EMPHASISED THAT MY<br />
GOVERNMENT'S RELATIONSHIP WITH THE UNITED STATES WOULD ACCURATELY<br />
REFLECT THE CLEAR VIEW-OF THE PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA, AS TO THE<br />
FUNDAMENTAL IMPORTANCE OF. THAT-RELA-IIONSHIP. OURS IS A-RELATIONSHIP<br />
WHICH. GOES FAR BEYOND THE DEFENCE, STRATEGIC AND SECURITY CONCERNS,<br />
FORMALISED IN THE ANZUS TREATY. TU( ADE AND INVESTMENT FORM A<br />
SIGNIFICANT PART OF THE TOTAL RELAIIONSHIP. AND I AM ABSOLUTELY<br />
CONFIDENT THAT UNDER MY NEW GOVERNME: NT, THAT PART OF THE RELATIONSHIP<br />
WILL CONTINUE TO GROW AND FLOURISH, TO THE MUTUAL ADVANTAGE OF BOTH<br />
OUR GREAT COUNTRIES, FOR MANY YEARS TO COME. </p>
<p>-P TRANSCR-IPT: -, bUESTIONS AND'ANSWERS, FOREIGN POLICY<br />
ASSOCIATION. LUNCH,.:-PLAZA HOTELi NFW YORK, 16 JUNE 1983<br />
E AND 0 E -PROOF ONLY<br />
QUESTION: YOU ENTIONED THE ANZUS ALLIANCE. PERHAPS YOUACAN<br />
EXPTRANSCRIPT: UESTIONS AND ANSWERS, FOREIG N POLICYHERN<br />
. ASSOCIATION LUNCH,. PLAZA HOTEL, NE-W YORK, 16 JUNE 1983<br />
E AND 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
QUESTION: YOU MENTIONED THE ANZUS ALLIANCE. PERHAPS YOU<br />
CAN EXPAND A LITTLE BIT ON FOREIfGN POLICY IN THE SOUTHERN<br />
PACIFIC REGION, THE EXTENT TO WHICH YOUR GOVERNMENT PERCEIVES<br />
THE SOVIET THREAT AS BEING DIFFEREFNT FROM OUR GOVERNMENT AND<br />
SECURITY MATTERS IN THAT AREA?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: THANK YOU MR CHAIRMAN. I WILL ANSWER THAT<br />
VERY PROAD QUESTION AS BRIEFLY AS I POSSIBLY CAN. LET ME<br />
SAY FOUNDATIONALLY IN ANSWERING IHAT QUESTION THAT WE REGARD<br />
THE RELATIONSHIP, SECURITY AND DFFENCE RELATIONSHIP, BETWEEN<br />
OUR TWO COUNTRIES EMBODIED IN THF-ANZUS TREATY, AS I SAY,<br />
FUNDAMENTAL TO OUR POSITION. WE HAVE A SHARED PERCEPTION OF<br />
THE GLOBAL SECURITY THREATS TO US ALL. WE CO-OPERATE<br />
EFFECTIVELY AND CONTINUOUSLY WITH YOUR COUNTRY UNDER THE<br />
AEGIS OF THE ANZUS TREATY. IF YOU WANT TO LOOK AT THE<br />
PARTICULAR AREAS IN OUR REGION Of-IMMEDIATE CONCERN AND WITH<br />
WHICH WE ARE CO-OPERATING WITH YOU, I GUESS THAT THE ONE .,' HICH<br />
IS MOST OBVIOUS AT THE MOMENT IS IN INDO-CHINA. AND MAY I<br />
SAY IN RESPECT OF THAT ISSUE THAI WE SHARE THE VIEW<br />
OF THE UNITED STATES, INDEED OF IHE ASEAN COUNTRIES, AS<br />
TO THE ESSENTIAL ELEMENTS OF A RF-SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS IN<br />
THAT TRAGIC COUNTRY KAIPUCHEA. AND THEY ARE, OF COURSE,<br />
THAT THERE SHOULD BE A WITHDRAWAl OF VIETNAMESE. TROOPS<br />
FROM THAT COUNTRY AND A CREATION OF CONDITIONS WHERE THE PEOPLE<br />
OF THAT COUNTRY WILL HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY FREELY TO EXPRESS<br />
THEIR WILL AS TO THE FORM OF GOV-FRNMENT WHICH THEY DESIRE<br />
TO HAVE. I WOULD SAY TO YOU LAD) FS AND GENTLEMEN ./ 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
THAT WE BELIEVE, AND IT HAS BECOMF CLEAR TO US SINCE WE'VE<br />
COME INTO OFFICE, THAT WE PERHAPS ARE IN THE ALMOST UNIQUE<br />
POSITION TO PLAY A ROLE IN ACCELf-RATING THE ACHIEVEMENT OF<br />
THOSE BASIC CONDITIONS BECAUSE* WF-HAVE A WARM, CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
RELATION4SHIP WITH THE FI VE COUNTRIES THAT COMPRISE ASEAN. WE<br />
HAVE, AS YOU KNOW, A VERY CLOSE RFLATIONSHIP WITH THE PEOPLES<br />
REPUBLIC OF CHINA. OF COURSE, NO COUNTRY HAS A CLOSER RELATIONSHIP<br />
WE BELIEVE WITH THE UNITED STATES. AND WE DO HAVE A CAPACITY<br />
AS WELL TO TALK TO HANOI. AND) THE-REFORE WE ARE NOT GOING TO<br />
DO ANYTHING PRECIPITATE IN TERMS OF SOME SUGGESTED RESUMPTION<br />
OF AID TO VIETNAM WHICH WOULD DENIGRATE FROM OUR CAPACITY TO<br />
EXERCISE THAT UNIQUE OPPORTUNITY. AND I'M PLEASED TO SAY<br />
TO YOU THAT AS RECENTLY AS LESS THAN A FORTNIGHT AGO, WHEN I<br />
WAS IN INDONESIA TALKING TO MOCHIAR, THE FOREIGN MINISTER OF<br />
INDONESIA, THAT HE CONVEYED TO US THAT AFTER THE ASEAN MINISTERS<br />
MEETING WHICH IS TAKING PLACE IN A FEW DAYS IN [ BANGKOK, IT IS<br />
THEIR BELIEF THAT OUT OF THOSE DISCUSSIONS THERE MAY BE THE<br />
BEGINNING OF THE OPENING UP OF POSSIBILITIES OF FURTHER<br />
DISCUSSIONS WITH HANOI AND THAT 1HEY MAY ASK OUR FOREIGN<br />
MINISTER, MR HAYDEN, TO TAKE A MF-SSAGE FROM THE ASEAN<br />
COUNTRIES TO HANOI. WE ARE EXTRAORDINARILY PLEASED THAT WE<br />
MAY BE ABLE TO PLAY THAT ROLE. YOU WILL UNDERSTAND THAT WE HAVE<br />
A TOTAL SHARING OF PERCEPTIONS ANOUT THE DANGERS THAT EXIST,<br />
NOT MERELY FOR THE TRAGIC PEOPLE OF KAMPUCHEA, BUT THE DANGERS<br />
THAT ARE INVOLVED IN THAT TOTAL Ri-LIANCE OF VIETNAM UPON THE<br />
SOVIET UNION, A RELIANCE WHICH WAS REFLECTED IN AN INFLOW<br />
TO VIETNAM FROM THE SOVIET UNION OF ASSISTANCE TO THE ORDER<br />
OF ABOUT DOLLARS 3 MILLION A DAY. WE WITNESSED THE EXPANSION<br />
OF THE FACILITIES OF THE SOVIET IONION IN CAM RANH BAY WHICH<br />
ARE NOT ONLY INTRINSICALLY DANGEROUS, BUT WHICH PROVIDE A<br />
PLATFORM OF PROJECTION FOR THE SOVIET INTO AREAS OF<br />
IMPORTANCE TO YOUR COUNTRY AND To OURS. AND SO ITS IN OUR<br />
INTERESTS, ITS IN THE INTERESTS OF-VIETNAM, ITS IN THE<br />
INTERESTS OF ASEAN COUNTRIES, ITS IN THE INTERESTS OF THE<br />
UNITED STATES THAT WE ALL CAN DO WHAT WE CAN THATS POSSIBLE<br />
TO GET VIETMAN BACK INTO THE COMMUNITY OF NATIONS AND TO BRING<br />
AN END TO THAT ALMOST TOTAL RELIANCE THAT IT HAS UPON THE<br />
SOVIET UNION. WE ARE NOT GOING TO PURSUE THAT PATH IN A<br />
WAY WHICH PREJUDICES THE PERCEPTIONS OF INTERESTS OF THE<br />
ASEAN COUNTRIES, THE PEOPLES REPUBLIC OF CHINA OR THIS<br />
GREAT COUNTRY. WE ARE COMMITTED MR PRESIDENT, LADIES AND<br />
GENTLEMEN THEREFORE, 1-O TRY AND TAKE ADVANTAGE OF' THOSE<br />
OPPORTUNITIES THAT WE HAVE TO ACCF-LERATE THE OPENING UP OF<br />
THOSE DISCUSSIONS SO THAT OUR SHARED OBJECTIVES AND<br />
PERCEPTIONS IN THAT COUNTRY CAN 81-ACHIEVED.<br />
QUESTION: IF WE COULD MOVE FOR ONE FINAL QUESTION TO DOMESTIC<br />
MATTERS. THERE CERTAINLY IS A DIF-FERENCE OF VIEW AND<br />
PERCEPTION ABOUT THE ROLE OF PERSONAL INCOME TAXES IN 1IE<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
VARIOUS ECONOMIES OF THE WORLD, IHE EXTENT TO WHICH THEY<br />
REPRESENT A DE-INCENTIVE. COULD YOU COMMENT ON YOUR VIEWS<br />
ON THAT.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I GUESS WE ARE AI L AT ONE IN SAYING THAT<br />
WE'D LIKE LESS OF THEM AND I HAD INDICATED IN THE PREELECTION<br />
CAMPAIGN THAT WE WOULD AITEMPT TO MOVE TO SOME<br />
REDUCTION IN INCOME TAXES. THAI 1S NOT GOING TO BE POSSIBLE.<br />
I THINK THE OBJECTIVES THAT GOVERNMENT HAS TO HAVE IN MIND<br />
WHEN IT MAKES ITS FISCAL DECISIONS ARE THESE: WHAT SORT OF<br />
ENVIRONMENT CAN YOU CREATE WHICH IS MOST LIKELY TO ENSURE<br />
THAT THOSE FORCES WHICH CREATE AcIIVITY AND CREATE JOBS ARE<br />
GOING* TO BEST BE ABLE TO FLOURISH. WITHIN THOSE CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
AND I SPEAK NOW ABOUT flY COUNTRY, I'M NOT COMING HERE TO THIS<br />
GREAT COUNTRY AND PRESUMING TO Tf-I L THIS ADMINISTRATION HOW<br />
TO CONDUCT ITS AFFAIRS, BUT RELATING TO MY OWN WE BELIEVE<br />
THAT WE HAVE TO CONDUCT A FISCAL POLICY AND CREATE A FISCAL<br />
STANCE WHICH IS LEAST LIKELY TO CREATE UNACCEPTABLE UPWARD<br />
PRESSURES ON INTEREST RATES. IT WOULD PE NICE TO CUT TAXES<br />
AS I'D HOPED BEFORE THE ELECTION THAT WE COULD. BUT IF I<br />
WERE TO DO THAT WE WOULD BE VERY I IKELY TO CREATE A SITUATION<br />
OF AN INCREASED BUDGET DEFICIT WHICH WOULD MEAN THAT IN TERMS<br />
OF THE COMBINED DEMANDS OF THE PlJILIC SECTOR BORROWING<br />
REQUIREMENT, TOGETHER WITH THE HOPE FOR EXPANSION OF THE PRIVATE<br />
SECTOR, THAT THERE WOULD BE INTOI FRABLE INCREASES IN INTEREST<br />
RATES. SO WE ARE NOT GOING TO BF CUTTING INCOME TAXES IN THE<br />
IMMEDIATE FUTURE BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT AFTER ALL PEOPLE'S<br />
INTERESTS, WHAT THEY ARE CONCERN-I) ABOUT, AS IF THEY GET A<br />
REDUCTION IN INCOME TAXES THEY ARf-GOING TO BE BETTER OFF.<br />
NOW THEY'RE GOING TO BE BETTER OFF IF WE HAVE AN ENVIRONMENT<br />
IN WHICH THERE ARE LOWER INTERES1 RATES, IN WHICH THERE ARE<br />
HIGHER LEVELS OF ACTIVITY AND IN WHICH THERE ARE MORE JODS<br />
FOR THEM AND THEIR CHILDREN. SO IN THAT CONTEXT, MR CHAIRMAN,<br />
I GIVE YOU THE MESSAGE THAI THERF'S NO IMMEDIATE PROSPECT<br />
OF A REDUCTION OF PERSONAL INCOMF TAX RATES IN OUR<br />
COUNTRY. BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAI TO DO THAT WOULD BE TO AVOID<br />
THE ACHIEVEMENT OF THE MAJOR OBJFCTIVE THAT IS THE<br />
CREATION OF AN ECONIMIC ENVIRONMFNT WITHIN WHICH THE TOTAL<br />
ECONOMIC CAKE IS MORE LIKELY TO 6ROW. WE RECOGNISE THAT THE<br />
PRIVATE SECTOR, WHICH EMPLOYS 75 PER CENT OF OUR PEOPLE,<br />
HAS GOT TO HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY OF GOING TO THE CAPITAL<br />
MARKETS AT RELATIVELY ACCEPTABLE INTEREST RATES TO BRIN6' ABOUT<br />
THAT CONDITION. SO PERHAPS ITS NOT AN IMMEDIATELY HAPPY<br />
MESSAGE FOR THE ACTUAL AND POTENI TAL INCOME TAX PAYERS IN<br />
MY COUNTRY. BUT I CAN ASSURE THFM, AND THIS IS WHAT<br />
POLITICS IS ALTIMATELY ALL ABOUT AND THAT IS MAVING SURE 1HAI<br />
YOU HAVE THE RIGHT PERSPECTIVE, iHAT YOU DON'T hAVE DECISIONS<br />
IN TERMS OF IMMEDIATE PERCEPTIONS OF SELF-INTEREST, BUT THAT YOU<br />
GET THE LONGER TERM PERSPECTIVE. AND I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT IF<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>WE ATTEMPT TO TAKE THAT LONGER TVRM PERSPECTIVE THEN IT 4OULD<br />
BE COUNTER PRODUCTIVE TO HOVE TO A REDUCTION OF INCOME TAX<br />
RATES. ONCE WE GET THE ECONOMY MOVING AS WE WILL THEN I<br />
HOPE BEFORE THE END OF OUR FIRST TERM 6F GOVERNMENi WE MAY<br />
BE ABLE TO GIVE SOME RELIEF IN THAT RESPECi.<br />
QUESTION: ANOTHER AREA YOU DIDN'T COVER IN YOUR SPEECH<br />
IMMIGRATION IN AUSTRALIA YOUR PARTY'S VIEW ON THE ROLE OF<br />
IMMIGRATION AND DEVELOPMENT OF THi COUNTRY.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: YOU'VE GOT TO ANSWER THAT QUESTION IN TERMS<br />
OF IT BEING MY PARTY IN GOVERNMENT IN THE WAR AND POST-WAR<br />
PERIOD WHICH INITIATED THE GREATFF-T IMMIGRATION PROGRAM IN<br />
RECORDED HUMAN HISTORY. WE WERE AT THE END OF THE WAR A<br />
COUNTRY OF 7 MILLION PEOPLE, NOW 15 MILLION. THAT HAS<br />
TRANSFORMED US NOT ONLY IN ABSOLUlTE TERMS BUT IT HAS CHANGED<br />
THE DEMOGRAPHY AND THE ETHNIC COMPOSITION OF OUR COUNTRY AND<br />
HAS ENORMOUSLY ENRICHED US ECONOMICALLY AND CULTURALLY AND IN<br />
SO MANY OTHER WAYS. THERE IS AN ARGUMENT THAT WE SHOULD JUST<br />
OPEN-ENDEDLY PURSUE HIGHER AND HIGHER IMMIGRATION PROGRAMS.<br />
WE DON'T BELIEVE THAT THAT'S CORRFCT. WE BELIEVE THAT WITH<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT IN OFFICIAL TERMS OF OVER 10 PER CENT IT DOESN'T<br />
MAKE SENSE 70 HAVE A LARGE EXPANIU-D IMMIGRATION PROGRAM. SO<br />
WE HAVE SLIGHTLY CUT IT BACK AT IHE MOMENT. THATS NOT GOING<br />
TO HAVE SIGNIFICANT IMPACT IN THF AREA OF OUR COMMITMENT TO<br />
REFUGEES. YOU WOULD KNOW THAT NFXT TO YOUR OWN COUNTRY THERE<br />
IS NO COUNTRY IN THE WORLD WHICH HASTAKEN PROPORTIONATELY<br />
A HIGHER NUMBER OF REFUGEES IN RFCENT YEARS. WE ARE SUBSTANTIALLY<br />
GOING TO ADHERE TO THAT. BUT WE NELIEVE THAT WHAT WE'VE GOT<br />
TO DO IS TO GET OUR ECONOMY MOVINGi IN A WAY THAT WILL ENABLE<br />
US WITH CONFIDENCE AND WITHOUT THEF POSSIBILITY OF A SOCIAL<br />
CORROSION THAT MAY OCCUR WHEN UNFMPLOYED PEOPLE<br />
SEE MORE COMING TO CREATE THE CONIUITIONS WITHIN WHICH WE'LL<br />
BE ABLE TO MOVE TO A MORE SUBSTANiIAL INCREASE IN IMMIGRATION.<br />
AND LET ME, OF COURSE, MAKE THE P() INT THAT OUR GOVERNMENT<br />
REMAINS TOTALLY COMMITTED TO THE PROPOSITION THAT THAT<br />
IMMIGRATION SHOULD BE ON THE BASIS IRRESPECTIVE OF<br />
COLOUR OR CREED, BUT IN TERMS OF IHE NEEDS OF PEOPLE WHO WISH<br />
TO COME TO OUR COUNTRY AND OF THF ECONOMIC REQUIREMENIS AND THE<br />
LABOUR REQUIREMENTS OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
ENDS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
