<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5705</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE PREMIER OF WESTERN AUSTRALIA: CLEARANCE OF UNEXPLODED ORDNANCE AT WARNBRO</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005705.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 3 DECEMBER, 1981<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE PREMIER<br />
OF WESTERN AUSTRALIA: CLEARANCE OF UNEXPLODED ORDNANCE<br />
AT WARNBRO<br />
For the past two years, the Commonwealth Government and the<br />
Government of Western Australia have been co-operating in<br />
the clearance of unexploded ordnance from the former artillery<br />
range at Warnbro.<br />
This project entailed several new features: it has been<br />
conducted under the auspices of the State Government by trained<br />
civilian contractors, but with Commonwealth technical and<br />
financial support.<br />
In' the light of our joint experience, the Commonwealth and<br />
State Governments have agreed on a formula which will allow<br />
the project to move forward to completion without interruption.<br />
The Commonwealth has agreed to provide the funds *' necessary for<br />
clearance of the former Warnbro range to a depth of about one<br />
metre. In addition, the Commonwealth will fund deep clearance<br />
( to a depth of approximately three metres, beyond which U. X. O.<br />
are not found) in those areas at Warnbro which are designated<br />
for urban or industrial use. This includes other areas where<br />
there is a demonstrated requirement to excavate below one<br />
metre main drainage, heavy earthworks, etc.)<br />
Should other areas at Warnbro be re-zoned for-urban or<br />
industrial use at some time in the future, the Commonwealth<br />
will fund further deep clearance as may be necessary.<br />
The Commonwealth has allocated $ 1.306 million for the completion<br />
of the present Warnbro Clearance Project.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
