<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7211</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, ALICE SPRINGS AIRPORT WEDNESDAY 2 SEPTEMBER 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/09/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007211.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTERL4S<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, ALICE SPRINGS AIRPORT,<br />
WEDNESDAY 2 SEPTEMBER 1987<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, we missed the earlier comments you<br />
made about the compact or treaty. What exactly are you<br />
aiming for?<br />
PM; I think the word is not Important, the concept Is<br />
though. I want to see a situation where before the end<br />
of this year, before we go into 1988, that there be a<br />
sense of understanding in the Australian community as<br />
a whole that next year we are celebrating 200 years of<br />
European settlement in this country. And that Is 200<br />
coming on top of a history of 40,000 of aboriginal culture<br />
and experience. And I would want to see an understanding<br />
in the Australian community that we have an obligation<br />
to the Aborigines of Australia that in that 200 years<br />
of European settlement there have been many grave injustices<br />
done; that since 1967 when the Australian people passed<br />
the referendum giving power to the national parliament<br />
that much more has been done to recognise these injustices,<br />
to direct attention to specific areas of problems like<br />
education, health, employment, training, And indeed I<br />
would say in the last 43 years of acceleration of commitment<br />
and action, I think that we, as a people, ought to make<br />
a compact between one another. I use that word ' compact'<br />
I am not wedded to it. There should be a compact of<br />
understanding as we go Into 1988 of Just what that 200<br />
represents. It is, as I say, coming on top of 40,000<br />
years of aboriginal history, that we do have a continuing<br />
commitment, that we will continue and I hope in a greater<br />
way to address the issues of concern. And if we can have<br />
that compact of understanding then I think we as non-<br />
Aboriginals, non-Aboriginal people, are going to be better<br />
placed properly to celebrate 1988. And importantly that<br />
there can be a greater sense of community between the<br />
Aborigines and the non-Aboriginal people so that' 1988<br />
can be clearly celebrated, properly understood. by all<br />
the citizens of Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it something that you would place before<br />
the Parliament for a debate, for a vote, and that it would<br />
have any force in law? </p>
<p>PM: One suggestion that has arisen in the discussions<br />
I have been having quietly with a number of people is<br />
that perhaps the concept that I have could be included<br />
by way of pre-amble, a substantial pre-amble to the legislation<br />
that we would bring in to establish the commission. That<br />
is one possibility. But again I make the point that I<br />
don't think it is so important as to whether you call<br />
it a treaty the treaty doesn't appeal to me so much<br />
but it is not the word that matters or where but<br />
that the people as a whole accept the point of what is<br />
involved. It is terribly important, I think, not just<br />
for the Aborigines but it is just as important for the<br />
non-Aboriginal population, that we understand these things<br />
before we go Into 1988 so that we can have a sense of<br />
together and proper perspective. We wouldn't be celebrating<br />
1988 properly if we thought that there wasn't 40,000 years<br />
of history before we came here.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it-would have a greater impact<br />
though PM: When you say enforceable, you can't enforce attitudes<br />
by law. What I am about is trying to get a sense of understanding<br />
of commitment if you like, between the non-Aboriginal<br />
and the Aboriginal population. You can't enforce commitments<br />
or attitudes by law but it may, in fact, be useful to<br />
include these sort of concepts, as I say, in a pr-emble<br />
to the legislation. That may give it a greater sense<br />
of status but I repeat that I don't think you should<br />
get hung up on the words or the method, of commitment.<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible question..<br />
PM: The rights of Aborigines should be enshrined in the<br />
laws of this country with our deliberately and<br />
we do that in many ways already. In the areas of specific<br />
programs for housing, employment and so on. And r am<br />
not in saying that implying that we have done enough but<br />
the concept of having an overall treaty, I don't know<br />
that that is necessarily the right way or the necessary<br />
way to do it. As I say, to get the right attitude, it<br />
is the understanding of where we are In history, what<br />
our 200 years as Europeans. what that bit of history is<br />
about, what its right place is. And if we can get that<br />
sense of understanding then I think it is much more likely<br />
that in the whole range of our activities we will, as<br />
a total community, have a better attitude towards one<br />
another. JOURNALIST; SlutsziLtiua planning hais been going; on for<br />
two years now, you are opening yourself up aren't you<br />
to the cynical observation by simply talking about this<br />
now, that the whole thing is designed to mute aboriginal<br />
protests in the bicentennial year.<br />
PM: No, I don't think so Kerry-There are always going<br />
to be cynics around. All I can say is that from the time<br />
I have been Prime Minister I have said to the previous </p>
<p>PM cont: leaders of the Australian Bicentennial Authority<br />
and I have said it to Jim Kirk, that it is absolutely<br />
essential that we talk about the Bicentenary we talk about<br />
the 200 years of European settlement that there is nothing<br />
in language or in action which implies that the only thing<br />
of importance is the last 200 years. And I have always<br />
had the attitudeland I have conveyed it to those who have<br />
the responsibility for organisina 1988, that there must<br />
be an understanding of that fact. Simply now, as we get<br />
closer to the year, I want to accept what I see as the<br />
obligation Prime MInister to clearly get Into the<br />
minds of the Australian people these facts because they<br />
are facts. It is not a question of saying you can wipe<br />
QNQ years of history away and say that people who have<br />
beer or 200 years haven't got very significant obligations<br />
to those who have been here before. I think that I have<br />
the responsibility as we come up towards the Bicentenary<br />
to lead in this matter and hopefully to get that sense<br />
of understanding in the Australian community generally.<br />
And let me say this that it is not as though there is<br />
a desert of understanding out there. I think there is<br />
a very considerable understanding and I want to sharpen<br />
it. We shouldn't forget that it was 20 years ago that<br />
the Australian people, in that decision in the referendum,<br />
quite a remarkable decision in the history of referendums<br />
because they normally don't pass referendums. But by<br />
an overwhelming majority they made the decision that they<br />
wanted the national gover-nment to have responsibility<br />
in theae matters. It is appropriate that as w&amp; come to<br />
this important year 1988 that we remember those obligations.<br />
JOIJRNAI1TST: Just finally, and very briefly Mr Hawke,<br />
do you have any comment on the death of Alan Reid?<br />
PM: Yes, and thank you for asking that question. By<br />
any standards Alan Reid was giant in his profession.<br />
I had the opportunity and indeed the privilege of not<br />
only knowing Alan Reid but being able to count him as<br />
a friend over very many years. As a political journalist,<br />
Alan's work was marked by many characteristics. They<br />
included, firstly, his total integrity, his dedication,<br />
his range of contacts, his capacity for analysis. As<br />
I have said before, there is no other journalist, as fara<br />
as I know, who in fact has changed the structure of a<br />
major political party. It was Alan Reid's work in regard<br />
to the " faceless men" that 19Li my Party, the Australian<br />
Labor Party, substantially to change its constitutional<br />
structure and to bring the parliamentary<br />
representatives into its federal executive and conference.<br />
That was, as I say, an indication of the magnitude of<br />
his work. He was also, if I may say this, personally<br />
an. exceptionally good friend to me. He was prepared<br />
to share with me his incomparable knowledge of the federal<br />
parliament and the players of politics. And I certainly<br />
learnt very much from Alan. And I talke this opportunity<br />
of conveying to his wife, Joan, and to his family, on<br />
behalf of Haz3l and myself firstly, and on behalf of the<br />
Government and I think the people of Australia, our grief<br />
with them at his passing and our acknowledgement to them<br />
? A t iyslaa ble role that he played in political journalism<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
