<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4789</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH 0-10</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004789.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW WITH 0-10<br />
Question: Mr. Robinson, that he make a check of his evidence, to see<br />
if he still believed that was accurate?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No, the point was raised in this way; in discussions Eric<br />
Robinson indicated it was the fact of the ' phone conversation<br />
and not the substance of it that had been related in my office<br />
on the 17th. Now one of the things that had puzzled me was<br />
how Eric Robinson could have a clear recollection of it, when<br />
I had none. If a Minister comes into me and says he has spoken<br />
with his permanent head, I am not going to regard that as<br />
remarkable, if he came and said he hadn't spoken with his<br />
permanent head for three ftonths, I would regard that as<br />
remarkable. So the fact of the ' phone call in itself, was<br />
not remarkable and as it was put in that discussion, it gave<br />
me an explanatLion in my own mind, about Eric's recollection<br />
and my own complete lack of recollection. Now that was my<br />
interest in the matter and that was my only interest in the<br />
matter. It might have-ended up in one other sentence or two<br />
other sentences in the statement I made in the Parliament<br />
explaining the very point I have just made but could I make<br />
another point not really related to your question. I've had an<br />
extreme diffidence in talking about these matters. I do believe<br />
it is very important for conversations between ministers and<br />
conversations in a Ministry, because part of this conversation<br />
was in a Ministry conversation, to be confidential. That is<br />
absolutely vital for the proper operating of Government and<br />
it's only because something has been blown up out of all<br />
proportion that was entirely and absolutely innocent in its<br />
nature and intent, that with Eric Robinson's agreement and<br />
after discussion with the Deputy Prime Minister, Mr. Anthony,<br />
it was determined that I ought to take this course.<br />
Question: You did suggest, though, to Mr. Robinson, at a Ministerial<br />
Meeting, according to you statement here, that he put pen to<br />
paper on the issue of his recollection. He did do that.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Not on the issue of his recollection, in relation to the matter<br />
that he'd just put to me. The Bulletin has made the suggestion<br />
that I was saying to him write me a note saying your<br />
recollection was hazy or inaccurate. Now, that suggestion is<br />
totally and absolutely false.<br />
Question: The distinction is you asked him merely to confirm his<br />
recollection as he best could at that stage? ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Confirm what he had just put to me, but it was also put<br />
to him, before you do that, look at the evidence.<br />
Question: When this attached attached to your statement is a letter<br />
which he had proposed, he did put pen to paper. Now that<br />
says that he doesn't remember the detail of what Senator<br />
Withers did. Was that how it happened at that time?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
That was how it was related at the time amongst Ministers.<br />
Question: Him saying that though. Is that any retraction from his<br />
evidence given before the Royal Commission?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, I think his evidence before the Royal Commission needs<br />
to be looked at in total.<br />
Question: And do you say, why then wasn't the letter sent, that he<br />
did pen?<br />
Prime minister:<br />
Because that was Eric Robinson's decision and therewas certainly<br />
no pressure from me that it ought to be sent. I hadn't seen<br />
it until today and quite deliberately, although I had earlier<br />
known of a draft existence, quite deliberately had not. Why<br />
he didn't send it was on advice and on re-reading the evidence.<br />
His evidence.<br />
Question:<br />
Would you agree though that is a softening of the position as<br />
the evidence originally came out which led to a lot of these<br />
stories?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I accept the position in the evidence as it is taken totally.<br />
The totality of his evidence.<br />
Question: And his recollection, according to this letter, that is wasn't<br />
clear in detail?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm sorry, I don't understand that... </p>
<p>-3<br />
Question: According to his letter here, he says he doesn't really<br />
remember all the detail that Senator Withers did mention...<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Part of his evidence also says that. But in answer to other<br />
questions put differently, there is a suggestion that some<br />
detail at least was made available in my office.<br />
Question: So it is entirely up to Mr. Robinson that he didn't then send<br />
on that letter?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Absolutely and completely.<br />
Question: Would that letter have helped your position?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No, it wouldn't have made any difference except it would have<br />
explained to me, to myself, why he had a-clear recollection<br />
of it and why I had none. Because I mention it to you again,<br />
if a Minister comes into my office and says he has been speaking<br />
with his Permanent Head, that's not remarkable, it could only<br />
become remarkable because of the nature of the conversation<br />
or alternatively if he came in and said he wasn't on speaking<br />
terms with his Permanent Head. r I would find that remarkable.<br />
Question: Have you any idea why Mr. Robinson wasn't prepared to say this<br />
in the House? Is he under the same sort of strictures of<br />
Ministerial meetings<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
The question of Ministerial confidentiality between, amongst,<br />
Ministers, that applies to all of us.<br />
Question:<br />
But this letter attached could be the only thing around that<br />
any newspaper, or bulletin or whatever it be, could get hold<br />
of at this stage.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm not aware of anything else being around. I think it would<br />
be very unlikely that they could have got hold of this either,<br />
for that matter. But, that's up to them.<br />
Question: Speculation about leadership challenges, taking to the enth<br />
degree some of the newspaper articles that have come. Have<br />
you considered that seriously? </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No, not for one minute.<br />
Question: You didn't think it was ever on at all?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No<br />
Question: Is the issue closed now?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I've got no doubt that the Australian Labor Party will continue<br />
to try and press around in the peripheral matters in politics<br />
because they haven't mounted an argument against the Budget.<br />
They haven't mounted an argument against any of the mainstream<br />
policies of the Government. They know quite well that this<br />
Budget is being very well received in the business sector.<br />
and very well received in financial markets overseas. They also<br />
know that that reception will be conducive to more and increased<br />
investment in Australia from Australian investors and from<br />
overseas investors and that's one the things that will certainly<br />
assist in economic recovery and in~ the creation of jobs.<br />
Question:. Can I put just one final point that the Opposition has made?<br />
They said that by your own admission on April 16th you say<br />
then that you knew about it, yet on the 23rd, one week later<br />
and I think about five weeks later again, terms for the<br />
Royal Commission were announced. It wasn't until May 26, some<br />
five weeks later that you actually included Senator Withers<br />
in it. Why was that?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
On the 23rd of April the matters before us were the allegations<br />
against Eric Robinson. In addition to-that, as I've made plain<br />
in the Parliament, there was evidence before us about how<br />
the name could have been changed relating to Senator Withers.<br />
The Attorney-General took quite specific action to make sure<br />
that that evidence would be available to the Royal Commission.<br />
Indeed, in relation to that part of it, the terms of reference<br />
were draw in such a way that all the evidence could, would<br />
and did, come out---and it was only when matters began to<br />
unfold at a later point in evidence, Mr. Pearson had given<br />
evidence, Senator Withers had given evidence, that highlighted<br />
matters that had been said in the Senate on the 4th of November<br />
and consequently other debates in the Senate, all these matters<br />
came together and threw a greater importance on this particular<br />
matter and as a result of that, the terms of reference were<br />
widened in relation to a finding but there was no need to<br />
alter the terms of reference in relation to substance, to<br />
eliciting all the facts because the original terms of reference<br />
were adequate for that and the. Attorney-General, in the name<br />
of the government, took very specific action to make sure<br />
that all the evidence would come out. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
