<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>555</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, TO THE GREATER WOLONGONG CHAMBER OF COMERCE AND INDUSTRY - 12TH JULY, 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000555.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R. G.<br />
INZIES. TO THE GrATR I OT. O GONG CHAMBR OF<br />
COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY<br />
12TH JULY. 12<br />
Sir, Mr. Mayor and Gentlemen<br />
It's not my fault that I am standing up here in<br />
the pulpit. ( Laughter) I was told that this was the drill.<br />
" Timotheus placed on high, amid the tuneful auire, with flying<br />
fingers touched the lyre." ( Laughter) I think that for e<br />
man who lives a dull, uninteresting life as I do, ( Laughter)<br />
to come here and be confronted by I don't know how many hund:' eds<br />
of Wollongong businessmen, is a great ordeal; because, looking<br />
around you, and I can only see the ones who are nearest me, I<br />
would think that if I took a Galli'p Poll among you, I would not do<br />
all that well. ( Laughter) ( Applause) And as I'have unter my benign<br />
exterior, a certain combative streak, that's what I like.<br />
I can remember once going to the Annual Dinner<br />
of the Chamber of Manufactures in a city that shall be nameless<br />
and being received with frosty silence that would have established<br />
air-conditioning in any house in the tropics, ( Laughter) But,<br />
in the long run, I warmed them up a bit. In fact, I did<br />
frightfully well that night; I got 30% of their votes at the<br />
next election, ( Laughter)<br />
But I like coming to Wollongong, You might think<br />
that that is not true because it is some years since I was here,<br />
but as I said to you, Mr. Mayor, this afternoon in that Reception<br />
that you were so pleased as -o give me, so kind, I have a soft<br />
spot for Wollongong, because I remember so well coming down hero<br />
you don't mind me repeating this when there was a little<br />
" trouble"; ( Laughter) and largely as a result of innate stupidity,<br />
I have always believed that you ought to go to where the trouble<br />
iSo ( Laughter) Now I came down here, and I drove down the<br />
main street; there were placards out; they reflected on my<br />
ancestry. ( Laughter) They invited me to go home, and there was<br />
a certain amount of fun and games and, in the upshot, it is to<br />
Wollongong and Port Kembla that I owe the one title of honour<br />
that I possess. ( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />
( Voice in background) " Name it"<br />
" Pig-iron Bob" ( Laughter)<br />
You know it is very amusing, really, If you<br />
get a title like that, a tag put on to you, you can do one of<br />
two things. You can become very angry about it, and I have<br />
known people silly enough to become angry about such things.<br />
Or you can wear it like a ribbon in your coat, and I must say<br />
I went on wearing it like a ribbon in my coat, until today if<br />
somebody is sufficiently out-of-date or sufficiently inebriated<br />
at the back of a political meeting to say " Pig-iron", everybody<br />
roars with laughter, and I take a bow. ( Laughter)<br />
Now, of course Gentlemen, I road the newspapers,<br />
or some of them ( Laughtor) and I occasionally look at the<br />
Gallup Poll or some of it ( Laughter) and when I do, I remind<br />
myself of a famous occasion when I was Leader of the Opposition,<br />
Some of you are so young, so boyish, you don't remember me as<br />
the Leader of the Oppcsition. ( Laughter) ( Applause) But at that<br />
time, among the Members of tho Opposition we used to have a Party<br />
meeting, it was a courteous thing to do; we had 17 seats in a<br />
&amp; 0005 / 2 </p>
<p>House of 71+. You've forgotten this. ( Laughter) But we had<br />
a Party meeting from time to time and, one day, Billy Hughes,<br />
who was a Member of that Opposition, was sitting there, wiring<br />
himself up to whatever leads might come ( Laughter) from here<br />
or there; my former colleague and great friend, Phil McBride,<br />
was up making a speech. Well, everybody knew but nobody but<br />
Billy was rude enough to mention the fact that at the previous<br />
general election, Phil McBride had been defeated for the<br />
Senate. but by the inexorable law of the Constitution, he was<br />
still a Member of the Senate until June the 30th and tnerefore,<br />
there he was, in the Opposition Party meeting, and he offered<br />
some very sensible views. Little Billy listened to it and<br />
nodded his head. He always nodded his head when he disagreed.<br />
( Laughter) And the moment Phil McBride finished, Billy got<br />
un and said, " Oh, well, you know, my friend McBride; he speaks<br />
with a falling inflection." ( Laughter) Now. Sir, why, having<br />
read the last Gallup Poll, did I remind myself of that story?<br />
( Laughter) Well, I leave it to you,<br />
But, anyhow, before I disappear into the abyss, if<br />
that's the drill, I would like to say that no Prime Minister<br />
of Australia with my experience in that office and with my<br />
knowledge which I ought to possess of our problems around the<br />
world, could fail to be interested in coming here and in talking<br />
to you, because you represent, in this area, a microcosm of the<br />
whole Australian economy and development; the great industry<br />
of iron and steel with all its ramifications, the great primary<br />
industries down on this coast all of these things, coal, coal<br />
exports one could talk about themn for a long time. But you<br />
are very fortunate in being here in an area not unlimited in<br />
point of size, but an area in which primary industry, secondary<br />
industry, tertiary industry, local industry, export industry,<br />
are all to be found. And if this great area continues to<br />
develop as it has so splendidly, then it is reasonable to say<br />
that Australia will develop splendidly in the future, ( Hear,<br />
hear) We can be on the home ground here, We can discuss any<br />
aspect of politics in this city and feel that we are at home<br />
with some aspect of whatever problem it may be. And that is,<br />
I think, tremendously important,<br />
And it i. s tremendously important, in particular I<br />
think, for two reasons there may be four or five or six<br />
but within the limits of time, I would like to talk about a<br />
couple of them.<br />
And the first reason is this: it is much easier to<br />
be on the outside of Government, looking in, than it is to be<br />
on the inside of Government looking out, I hope you will agree<br />
with that, A Government at Canberra with acutely limited powers<br />
must do its best to direct, not to control., the economic development<br />
of the nation, And this is a tremendous problem,<br />
There are somei things that are not within our control,<br />
* o have nothing to do and nothing to say about many of the<br />
aspects of the economy that the outsider would look at, But<br />
we do have a groat responsibility for the Budget, for monetary<br />
control, for the determination as to whether credit is to be<br />
easy or credit is to be tight. I know all this. These things<br />
are very true, And we found ourselves, not all that long time<br />
ago, looking at a state of affairs in which there was a great<br />
inflationary boom going on in Australia, I don't think anybody,<br />
sensibly, denies it, Our overseas balances were running down<br />
fast Now, of course, I am able to tolk to you because you<br />
are businessmen and you understand thcse things, but there are<br />
so many people who do not b,-gin to understand why you should<br />
worry about the overseas balances of a country, failing to<br />
0 0 8 3 </p>
<p>realise that the first thing that I heard about iri -uaela when I<br />
was; there the other day was their balarce of trade and payments;<br />
a balance problem which is beginning to worry them. And what's<br />
happening in Great Britain? The problem of the balance of<br />
payments, the problem of keeping the export market up, of<br />
keeping the importation of material within reasonable limits.<br />
This is a universal problem, not peculiar to us, not peculiar<br />
to the Menzies Government, not created by some arrant folly<br />
on our part. This is a problem which bemuses the whole of the<br />
Western world,. I mentioned America. You know, it is only a few<br />
years ago isn't it, that dollars for us wore as scarce as hen's<br />
tooth, ' No, you can't have them", " There are great restrictions<br />
on access to dollars" And that was because at that time the<br />
dollar was the commanding currency of the free world. But<br />
if you went into VWashington today, and talked with Finance<br />
Ministers or bankers or high people in the Administration, the<br />
first thing they would want to talk to you about would be their<br />
balance of payments problems, How long can they continue to<br />
find a billion dollars or two billion dollars in their language,<br />
or foreign aid for helping weaker nations in the world, Lecause,<br />
the fact is that in the last twelve months, gold has been running<br />
out from Fort Knox and gold has been running out from Canada<br />
whose gold reserves are singularly depleted of late. We are<br />
not the only people to have these problems.<br />
But we, in Australia, decided that we were not going<br />
to allow this problem to become acute, We were going to try<br />
to deal with it. And you can't deal with any problem of an<br />
economic kind in our country without irritating and infuriating<br />
a lot of people, We just have to put up with that, The fact<br />
is that Australia, for the last eighteen months, has had a<br />
balance of payments position, a state of reserves overseas which<br />
is, on the wholo, the envy of those other countries that I have<br />
been referring to, ( Hear, hear) ( Applause) This is not<br />
unimportant, It is not unimportant to know that you have under<br />
your control overseas a volume of overseas reserves which could<br />
sustain a blast of imports or some fluctuations in export income<br />
for quite a long time. This is tremendously important. And as<br />
I have lived long enough and been a Prime Minister long enough<br />
not to care unduly whether I am tossed out, I propose to continue<br />
to do what I think is good for this country. ( Hear, hear)<br />
( Applause) This is oL, of the great things that has happened.<br />
Now, we also set out to restrain inflation in Australia,<br />
Now again, gentlemen, don't let me pretend about this matter.<br />
There may be many of you here tonight as there are many people<br />
engaged in enterprises in Australia who have no objection to a<br />
spot of inflation ' What's wrong with a little inflation?"<br />
" All this boosts up the equities, it develops a state of<br />
affairs in which the population rises and we are all optimists."<br />
I understand all that. But inflation is the most unjust tax<br />
in the world, and it is one of those unjust taxes which fails<br />
most heavily upon the people who cannot afford it. And therefore<br />
we set out to say, '" oll, wo must restrain inflation,"<br />
I have never understood the principle on which<br />
headlines arc allotted, ( Laughter) I always appear to get into<br />
them at the w rong tim, ( Laughter) But I do want to remind you<br />
that for the last eighteen months, that's a long time, the<br />
consumer price index in Australia has been stable. In other<br />
words, for the last eightecn cnrcnts, wo have -ad no inflationary<br />
pressure rcflecting itolf in the price levels. I wondcr if<br />
there is any other country in the w orld on our side of the<br />
Curtain that could say tht. I doubt it, I know we've had our<br />
0 Z 0 3 C 1 / 4 </p>
<p>great periods of inflation caused by causes which you are all<br />
familiar with but in these eighteen months of unpopularity<br />
( Laughter) it is still true that we have had stability in the<br />
consumer price index, Aren't these important matters?<br />
Now somebody and this is the first point I wanted<br />
to make to you somebody will be heard to say, Oh, yes, but<br />
this Government is unduly concerned with stability." I've<br />
heard this. You must not suppose, gentlemen, that because one<br />
lives some of the time-not much-in Canberra that one lives in<br />
what they describe es an ivory tower and is unaware of what<br />
people say. If anybody around Australia says something in my<br />
favour, I never hear it? but if somebody says something against<br />
me, I hear it next morning. You needn't worry about this.<br />
( Laughter) This is all quite simple and quite clear, and I<br />
know that a lot of people, some of you perhaps, have been saying,<br />
" Oh, yes, Stability. That's very good, but what matters in<br />
Australia is growtho And these boys who are interested in<br />
stability are not interested in growth," Now would you allow<br />
me to say ho. silly that is.<br />
Why do you want stability in Australia? Why do you<br />
want the value of money in our own country to maintain itself?<br />
Because you want to be able to invest money in Australia with<br />
some belief in the soundness of the currency. Because if you<br />
are like all of us you want to see your country grow, you want<br />
to see investment in it increase, and as 10-million people<br />
can't find all the money for capital investment that is needed<br />
for a continzat, you want to feel that investors from other<br />
parts of the world will be prepared to put their money into<br />
this country, put it at risk, in order to develop some industry<br />
in this country. This is, I think, elementary.<br />
You can't have growth on an unstable foundation. I'd<br />
like everybody to think about that because there are quite a few<br />
people who believe that the very definition of " growth" is to<br />
have an unstable foundation, to have the value of your money<br />
rocketing up and down. I don't believe it for a moment, and if<br />
there is one reason more than another why, in this period of<br />
stability brought about by painful means, we have continued to<br />
attract to Australia capital investment on the private field<br />
more than perhaps any other country in the world, it is because<br />
we have offered them a firm foundation,<br />
Now, I wonder Sir, if I might illustrate that just a<br />
little. I don't want to be too political about this matter, but<br />
these are great national problems. For the last eighteen<br />
months, we have had this hard-won stability in the currency, this<br />
hard-won stability in the price level, this remarkable achievement<br />
in the overseas balances. Has this meant stagnation in Australia?<br />
Because, you know, thero are a lot of people in the world who are<br />
bemused by words. If you say " stability", they say, " Ah, that<br />
means stagnation." Very simple, dogmatic statemont. Has all<br />
this meant stagnation? Well, really, Sir, I applied myself,<br />
with the aid of my staff, to the problem of Greater Wollongong.<br />
I don't need to talk to you about the development of your great<br />
city. but I was interested to note this: that in the two years<br />
of alleged stagnation, what has happened here has been that the<br />
vessels entering the port have increased from 1,025 to 1,091.<br />
That is, perhaps, no great matter. The coal exports from here<br />
have risen from 628,000 tons to 805,000 and the iron and steel<br />
exports from 149,000 to 454,000. Now I invite you Sir, to be<br />
proud of this place, I invite you to Lake the lessons that you<br />
have learned here in your own place and apply them to our great<br />
country. In this period, when people have been talking professionally<br />
about stagnation what has hapccned here has been the<br />
0 </p>
<p>greatst-s proof of dynamism in the Australian economy that I<br />
could possibly imagine.<br />
As I said this afternoon when the Mayor was kind<br />
enough to give me a civic reception, my memory of the coal<br />
industry goes back a long way. In my earlier and more<br />
respectable days at the Bar, ( Laughter) I appeared for the<br />
coalminers and for the coalovmers and conceived modified<br />
rapture about both of them ( Laughter) and when, in the<br />
inscrutable wisdom of the electorate, at the end of 19+ 9,<br />
I was plucked out of being Leader of the Opposition and<br />
became your Prime Minister, we were importing coal, the coal<br />
industry was in the doldrums South African coal, Indian<br />
coal and some of you may recall on the charter-parties, a<br />
heavy seller's market. There we were, trying to boast that<br />
another half million tons of coal had been secured from some<br />
other country to this wonderful coal-producing country, and<br />
today, the expore of coal has become a substantial industry<br />
and when these coal-ports are completed, like the groat one<br />
going on now here, the export of coal from Australia will<br />
become a very heavy export earner for Australia, And I would<br />
like every manufacturer to reflect that the more we export,<br />
the greater our export income, the more we can afford to pay<br />
for our imports, over 70o of which come directly in aid of<br />
manufactures in Australia.<br />
And, therefore Sir, I find myself in a community<br />
which ought to be, and I am sure is tremendously optimistic,<br />
* ihich sees in all these things the graphic evidence of the<br />
fact that stability is not stagnation, that you can have<br />
stability and have expansion and growth at the same time<br />
because one comes in aid of the other. Now, Sir, that is<br />
really the first point that I wanted to make to you,<br />
The second thing I would like to say something to<br />
you about is that by common consent I get it from everywhere<br />
and I know it in my own bones, there is a certain uncertainty<br />
in the market, a certain hesitation, a certain lack of complete<br />
confidence because of the Common Market discussions. You<br />
know, we are a little bit inclined, Sir, in Australia to think<br />
that the things that happen to us have never happened to<br />
anybody else, a little bit disposed that way.<br />
All I can tell you is, that in London I would<br />
encounter people who would say, " Well, you know old man, there's<br />
a certain amount of uncertainty because we don't know about<br />
the Common Market," And in the United States of America, one<br />
of the factors in their recent recession which would be put to<br />
you would be, " Well, you know, there's a feeling of uncertainty<br />
about the Common Market." And, of course, it is true here,<br />
although the first thing I want you to remember is that it is<br />
true everywhere; because-rhese Common Market negotiations, the<br />
great problem as to whether Groat Britain goes into Europe or<br />
not is one of the great revolutionary decisions in modern<br />
history. Don't let us underestimate it.<br />
People are now all, of course, becoming increasingly<br />
scientific and therefore I regret to say they don't read<br />
history any longer, but anybody who has read any history will<br />
tell you that since at least the middle of the eighteenth<br />
century, classical British policy, foreign policy, has been<br />
to remain out of Europe but to exercise the balance of power,<br />
If the Prussians got too strong, put a hand on the scale; if<br />
the French got too strong, put a h-: ndl on the scale, but stay<br />
outside of Europe and influence the balance of Europe, And<br />
some of the great leaders in Great Britain have decided, I<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>think, thait; this has gone far enough. They say " Well, twice<br />
in this century we, the British, and we, the Australians, have<br />
been involved in wars which began in Europe. It is high time<br />
we, Great Britain, went into Europe and exercised our. influence<br />
from within." Now, all this is very intelligible, Nobody<br />
need scoff at it. It is a great historic conception. The<br />
only point I want to make to you is that it involves a radical<br />
departure in British foreign policy, No longer the balance of<br />
power from without but the influence from within, And this<br />
is not to be underestimated.<br />
The historians in a hundred years' time will write<br />
about this as ore of the great climactic periods in British<br />
history. And it is because I know that, because I believe it,<br />
that I am not at all disposed to be dogmatic on these things.<br />
But what I do know is that if Great Britain is to go into ttle<br />
European Community, if Great Britain is to accede to the<br />
Treaty of Rome, then the terms and conditions now being hammered<br />
out with the six European members of the Community are of<br />
tremendous importance for us because we, practically all of<br />
us in this room, in our adult years at least, have grown up<br />
to take for granted a pattern of external trade which has<br />
been primarily the Commonwealth pattern of trade advantages<br />
on dairy products, advantages by the sugar agreements, advantages<br />
in relation to dried fruits and canned fruits, advantages in<br />
relation to wheat, advantages in relation to meat.<br />
All these things have become part of the stuff of<br />
our living in Australia and now they are exposed to challenge<br />
because there are countries in Europe who, quite intelligibly,<br />
would say, " WJell yes, you had it, It was very good while it<br />
lasted, but if you want to come into our Common Market, our<br />
customs union with internal free trade and a common external<br />
tariff, then you must play the game according to the rules."<br />
And so Australian dairy products or Australian canned fruits<br />
or dried fruits must pass over the common external tariff<br />
barrier and, quite frankly, that's not much good to us, because<br />
we have disadvantages by distance and otherwise, and by the<br />
very standard of our living, which are not to be ignored;<br />
and, consequently, wo, Australia, have from the very beginning<br />
I want you to understand this quite plainly adopted a completely<br />
active and constructive attitude on those matters.<br />
For the last year or more, Australian officials have<br />
been sitting down with British officials with European officials<br />
hammering out, commodity by commodity, what should be obtained<br />
in order to preserve, if not in its pure form, at any rate in<br />
substance the pattern of Commonwealth trade. This, after<br />
all., was the great reason why I w*' nt abroad in June, because<br />
I thought that by September when the Prime Ministers meet, it<br />
might be too late, I don't think so now, but I thought that<br />
at that time. It might have been too late; perhaps attitudes<br />
might have been crystallised by that time and, therefore, the<br />
right thing to do was to go there while things were still in a<br />
state of flux and, similarly, to America while things were in<br />
a state offlux. I am not at all disappointed with the results<br />
of these errands. Not at all, I don't know what the result<br />
will be but I have no doubt whatever that both in London and in<br />
Washington our position is at any rate clearly understood.<br />
( Hear, hear) ( Applause)<br />
. e are not sitting in judgment, nor should wo, on<br />
the political question, as to whether Groat Britain should go<br />
in to Europe, We may h-. e our own privaet views on those<br />
matters, but in the long run, this greatc, historic decision<br />
must be made by her. Thi: t does not m on to say that we are<br />
not interested. We are, but in the long run, she will make that<br />
decision and on that decision there is an immense complex of<br />
o0o. // 7 </p>
<p>divided, opinion at this very moment in Great Britain itself.<br />
But when it comes to how far our pattern of Commonwealth<br />
trade a pattern which has determined so much local development<br />
in Australia, not something that can be cancelled overnight,<br />
so much development, so much settlement, so much direction of<br />
activity on that matter, we say, must be consulted, our<br />
view must be listened to with respect," and both of those are<br />
completely accepted and, in the long run, we must be quite free<br />
to say whether we approve or disapprove of the results that are<br />
achieved. Now that's fair enough,<br />
The one thing that troubles me about all this is that<br />
I think that there may be exaggerated views, as if we wore now<br />
facing some disaster. Now, I beg of you, don't got into that<br />
frame of mind. I don't beliove, myself, for one moment, that<br />
any British Parliament would allow any British Government to<br />
go into the Common Market on terms which would eliminate all<br />
Commonwealth preferences by 1970. I don't believe it for a<br />
moment. I may be right or wrong on that. I'm pretty sure<br />
I'm right. And that means that there will be negotiated<br />
arrangements on a great variety of matters.<br />
Now, we are not to fall into a panic about this,<br />
What we have to do is to realise perhaps that the old and<br />
simple days may be coming to an end, I don't mean by that<br />
that all preferences are coming to an end. The old, simple<br />
outline of it may have to be modified in future. And it may<br />
very well be, and I am sure it is, that Australia will be<br />
increasingly looking for now markets in the world, and not<br />
only for existing commodities, but for new commodities And<br />
this is the one point, really, that I wanted to make to you.<br />
Here you have in this versatile community, here, with<br />
its immense variety of production and of interest, a great<br />
opportunity for looking at the world and saying, " Well. if<br />
there is to be some modification of our entrance into our<br />
traditional market in Great Britain, if this is to be modified<br />
in some way, then at any rate, we have the world open to us<br />
and we must increasingly find to what countries we can sell<br />
what goods, And the thing I want to say to you about that, and<br />
I believe it is very important, is that we tend, and you the<br />
business community tend, to be a little conservative in our<br />
thinking. W hen we talk about new export markets to the great<br />
countries of South-. East Asia, what do we do instinctively?<br />
We think in terms of butter or meat or wheat or something that<br />
we have boeen in the habit of exporting. It is quite clear<br />
that, increasingly, and I know that the best minds are directing<br />
themselves to this, we must increasingly seek to vary our<br />
exports in ordor to discover into which of these countries we<br />
may sell things that we have never thought of selling before,<br />
There is very active work being done on this on the dairy side<br />
by examinations of the possibility of selling milk in other<br />
forms in South-East Asia, as you know. This is admirable,<br />
It may be that there are things that we can produce in Australia<br />
which we have not so far produced, which are not orthodox for<br />
which a market can be found in a variety of these countries.<br />
Don't underestimate the incredible scientific ability<br />
of the Australians. The C. S. 3I. the people who are engaged<br />
in research, these are remarkable people ard, constantly, they<br />
are discovering now things, now ideas, new processes, but so<br />
far, we have not hnd quite the pier. fct liaison between thor / 8 </p>
<p>and the manufacturing -,; o-rld or producing world, because<br />
somebodyr perhaps snys, ' 1Ob. 1 well, that's someting ne-u,<br />
1Te ' re doing very nicely, than you, cun2itg S14h 1. ine_, 1<br />
ar ging to be fa ce d2 i rat BiAtai roes -into<br />
tUhe Coieimon Market on any terms tha-t are noai ceinprohens'bl a<br />
by m'e, we are going to be., faced, not withi disaster, de'. r-me,<br />
no. but withi a challengre to g: et cracking, to di scover new<br />
in wiaici we can build up our income . broad. and thel'efore)<br />
ncO'. r ways in / ich we can increase our eve-lopment alut-; ome.<br />
I' 1knou more about this after the 2e'atombe-r conference and<br />
whon i come backx from T w! ill take an early oppor'; Lunity<br />
in he Parliament of telling thie Parliament and the pcoepL<br />
thie nature of tiie chiallengo lUhat I t,, ii'nk. is pre3sented to us<br />
and 1 will, end u~ p by saying7, or if I don't say JLI, I imay noG<br />
rcmemnber t, but by tMhikcing thiat once a criallongre is presovlted<br />
to my own people, in mry own ceunt: y, thoy hnava never yet failed<br />
to meet it . c-1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
