<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1961</transcript-id>
    <title>SLARIES BILL 1968  SECOND READING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. J.G GORTON  27 NOVEMBER 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001961.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
69/ 174<br />
SALARIES BILL 1968<br />
Second Reading Speech by the Prime Minister,<br />
the Rt. Hon. J. G. Gorton 27 NOVEMBER 1968<br />
I move that the Bill be now read a second time.<br />
This Bill arises from the Government's decision to<br />
increase the salaries of $ 15, 000 and $ 17500 for Permanent Heads<br />
of Departments of State and certain Statutory offices and to provide<br />
for the payment of annual allowances additional to these salaries.<br />
The new salaries will be $ 19, 500 and $ 22, 750 and the annual<br />
allowanceswill be 1, 000 and 500 respectively, with effect from<br />
1 December 1968. The Bill provides the new salaries and allowances<br />
for the holders of the Statutory offices included in the First<br />
Schedule to the Bill and, by an amendment to Section 30 of the<br />
Public Service Act 1922-1967, for the payment of allowances to<br />
Permanent Heads. The existing salaries of these senior officers date<br />
from 1 November 1964. During this period there have been many<br />
changes in other salaries in the Commonwealth Service, including<br />
the substantial increase of December 1966 in the Second Division.<br />
The margin between the Permanent Head's salary of $ 15, 300 and<br />
the highest Second Division salary has been reduced to only $ 272,<br />
There have also been substantial increases in other comparable<br />
salaries. The annual allowances are for the expenses of office<br />
in which these senior officials are necessarily involved but which,<br />
by their nature, cannot be met by direct re-imbursement. Similar<br />
allowances are paid to senior officers in the New South Wales Public<br />
Service and in related Government employment and, of course, in<br />
many positions in private enterprise.<br />
In reaching its decision, the Government has taken<br />
account of the constantly increasing demands placed upon the<br />
Permanent Heads of the Departments of State and statutory off ice<br />
holders and their very heavy responsibilities in the affairs of our<br />
country. I commend the Bill to the House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
