<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5485</transcript-id>
    <title>THE QUEEN&#039;S VISIT TO AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005485.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
_ j. LJk^ yJ EMPARGO: 6: 00<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 20 NOVEMBER, 1980<br />
THE QUEEN'S VISIT TO AUSTRALIA<br />
The Queen, accompanied by the Duke of Edinburgh, will<br />
visit Australia next year. They will arrive in Melbourne<br />
by air from London on Saturday, 26 September, and will<br />
leave Australia from Adelaide on Monday, 12 October.<br />
The primary purpose of the Royal Visit is to enable the<br />
Queen, in her capacity as Head of the Commonwealth to be<br />
present in Melbourne when the Co,-=-onwealth Heads of Government<br />
assemble for their Meeting in 1981 and to meet the<br />
respective Heads of Government.<br />
As already announced the dates for the Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government Meeting are Wednesday 30 September to Wednesday<br />
7 October 1981.<br />
In addition, Her Majesty and His Royal Highness have accepted<br />
the Goverrunent's suggestion to extend their stay. An<br />
itinerary has been accepted that will take the Queen and<br />
the Duke of Edinburgh from Victoria to Tasmania, Western Australia<br />
and South Australia, in that order.<br />
The precise timing of the Royal Visit itinerary has yet to<br />
be determined.<br />
Consultation between the Commonwealth and States to be visited<br />
will take place to prepare a program of engagements for the<br />
visit. Those details will be announced as soon as practicable<br />
when an approved program has been decided.<br />
The Queen and the Duke of Edinburgh visited Australia in<br />
May this year when 1er Majesty opened the new High Court Building<br />
in Canberra and thereafter made one dCa visits to Sydney and<br />
Melbourne. Her Majesty and His Royal Highness last visited<br />
Tasmania, Western Australia and South Australia in 1977, the<br />
Silver Jubilee year of Her Majesty's accession to the Throne.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
