<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5175</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF &#039;AM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005175.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 17 OCTOBER 1979<br />
from the Press Office SUMMARY OF<br />
The Federal Government's amendments to the Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Commission will go into the Senate this afternoon<br />
with the Government determined not to make any alterations to<br />
the legislation. That is despite the concern expressed by one<br />
deputy president and 25 commissioners. Representatives of the<br />
commission will. be meeting with the President of the Commission,<br />
Sir John Moore and representatives of the deputy presidents to<br />
discuss their opposition to the Bill. Later today the<br />
amendments will go before the Senate, traditionally the chamber<br />
where Government backbenchers have been able to force changes<br />
to legislation,-howeverp, while some Senators are likely to be<br />
critical of the amendments, it is unlikely that any will go<br />
as far as crossing the floor. The weekly joint Party will be<br />
held this morning and backbench dissatisfaction is expected<br />
to be delt with there. Potentiall more damaging for the<br />
Government is the meeting in Sydney today of represenatives<br />
of the Commissioners Association with the President of the<br />
Association and some of the 8 deputy Presidents. Should any<br />
of the other deputy Presidents support the 25 Commissioners,<br />
the Government could be face with what Mr Hayden described<br />
yesterday as a full scale revolt. In other developments, the<br />
matter of Justice Staples' letter was raised at a council<br />
meeting of the New South Wales Bar Association yesterday.<br />
It is understood that there are plans for a motion to be<br />
moved calling on the Association to express its support for<br />
Justice Staples. In the committee stages of the ASIO<br />
debate in the House of Representatives last night, former<br />
Labor Minister for Industrial Relations, Mr Cameron, alleged<br />
that ASIO had tapped' the private telephone of r'Ir Justice Staples.<br />
Mr Cameron who appointed Mr Staples to the Commission said that<br />
he had been informed that the tap had been taking place for<br />
nearly three weeks with the Government's knowledge. The<br />
Attorney-General's office had no comment to make on the allegations.<br />
The sharpest, most . immediate reaction to Western Australia's<br />
new industrial legislation has come from the moderate unions<br />
who claim that their very survival is at stake. According to<br />
the assistant secretary of the Clerks' Union the legislation<br />
will merely polarise all of the union movement. However, the<br />
Minister for Labour and Industry, Mr Ray O'Connor, says the<br />
public will agree with the State Industrial Commission having<br />
more power to intervene in disputes.<br />
In London, the Zimbabwe-Rhodesia conference has concluded its<br />
first full session without the Patriotic Front. Lord Carrington<br />
had earlier issued an ultimatum that the Front could only rejoin<br />
the Lancaster House talks if they agree to Britain's draft<br />
constitution proposals. In calling for a summit of the<br />
' front line African states', President Nyerere has played<br />
down the Lancaster House deadlock, but'-in London, ambassadors<br />
of the front line states have endorsed the statement by the.<br />
Commonwealth Secretary General, Mr Ramphal, that any settlement<br />
of Zimbabwe can only be reached with the agreement of the<br />
Patriotic Front. Mr Ramphal said that when the* Commonwealthi<br />
leaders met in Lusaka, they did not envisage an agreeement that<br />
was not endorsed by all sides. Mr Fraser played a leading role<br />
in organising the Lancaster House talks, though when asked to commen ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
on Mr Ramphal's statement, he declined, saying he * was not yet<br />
briefed by the Foreign Affairs Department.<br />
President Nyerere has called an emergency meeting with the<br />
front line states and it is clear that he is doing everything<br />
possible to avoid a complete breakdown of the London talks with<br />
the inevitable result that the guerilla war being waged by the<br />
Patriotic Front could drag on possibly for more years than<br />
anyone would like to anticipate. Inspite of this obvious concern<br />
for the successful outcome of the London talks, it is not really<br />
clear what President Nyerere hopes to achieve by calling the<br />
emergency meeting, particularly since he believes the dead lock<br />
is the result of a simple misunderstanding over the question of<br />
payment of compensation of white Rhodesian farmers who might<br />
have their land taken from them by a black majority government.<br />
Nyerere says the Patriotic Front objects to paying this<br />
compensation if the British government expects the new black<br />
majority to provide the money, but he says, the Patriotic Front<br />
accepts the principal if Britain is prepared to put up the money<br />
in the same way as it provided money for white farmers in<br />
Kenya to be compensated for a loss of their land after<br />
independence.<br />
The decision by Libya and Iran to boost oil prices has caused<br />
dismay in the United States. The influential Saudi Oil Minister<br />
feels that Iran and Libya, by their unilateral action, had<br />
created a chaotic situation, and did not know what the<br />
consequences would be. He implied that the other oil<br />
exporters could well be forced into joining the price rise<br />
move when they held their next meeting in December.<br />
State Department spokesman, Mr Hodding Carter, says each<br />
time there is another turn in oil prices, world inflation<br />
is fed, and that.-market conditions at this time do not<br />
justify such an increase.<br />
New York: It is now a week since the Mayor threatened to<br />
broadcast the nam es of men convicted of using prostitutes<br />
but it is felt that prostitution is intimately connected<br />
with organised crime and that it is the far more dangerous<br />
associated evils and violence that are really the target.<br />
The fishing agreement between Australia and Japan is to be<br />
signed in Canberra today. One puzzling aspect of this<br />
controversial agreement has been the sudden'change of heart<br />
by the Queensland government, where Premier Petersen now says<br />
he is in full agreement with'-the signing. However, David Thomson,<br />
Federal National Country Party member, has expressed<br />
reservations. Says the agreement does not go far enough to protect<br />
the marlin and that we need a much bigger buffer zone in which<br />
the longliners will not be able to fish.<br />
Premier Doug Lowe has promised a full public debate before<br />
any final decision is made to flood part of Tasmania's last<br />
remaining wilderness areas for a hydro electric scheme, but<br />
as far as the director of the Wilderness Association is concerned,<br />
the public has already made up its mind.<br />
The President of Pakistan has announced the indefinite postponement<br />
of the general elections scheduled for November 17, saying that<br />
martial law will be enforced in its true sense. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3-3<br />
A meeting of senior Western lawyers and politicans in London<br />
has concluded that the plight of Soviet Jews has remained<br />
unchanged, and even worsened in the past five years.<br />
Australia's representative at the meeting was Senator John Wieldon.<br />
Interviewed. oOo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
