<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>240</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES - Establishment of the National Library of Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000240_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>1. Introduction History</p>
<p><br />This is the first major Bill on library services to be introduced into this Parliament. It provides for the ostablishuent of the National Library of Australia, Honorable<br />Members will of course understand that we are not in reality<br />creating a new institution, but are rather proposing that the<br />library services of the Commonwealth which have grown up<br />without formal provisions since Federation should now be the<br />subject of legislation by this Parliament. But we are also<br />looking to the future in that we seek to define the functions<br />and role of an institution which will increasingly play a<br />national role of the greatest irportance similar to that of<br />the great national libraries in other countries.<br />The existing National Library collections and<br />services are already widely used throughout , ustralia and are<br />increasingly known abroad. Members are aware that they grew<br />directly from the Library of the Commonwealth Parliament.<br />The first Federal Government and the first Joint<br />Library Committee of Parliament gave imaginative and farsighted<br />consideration to library needs and took expert advice both<br />from within Australia and abroad. It is worth noting that by<br />1907 the idea of a national library had crystallised and was<br />reported to Parliament as follows<br />" The Library Committee is keeping before it the ideal of<br />building up, for the tine when Parliament shall be<br />established in the Federal Capital, a great Public<br />Library on the lines of the world-famed Library of<br />Congress at iJashington; such a Library, indeed as shall<br />be worthy of the Australian Nation; the home of the<br />literature, not of a State, or of a period, but of the<br />world, and of all time<br />The development of such collections was limited<br />during the first 27 years in Melbourne both by the resources<br />available and by the presence of the excellent collections of<br />the Public Library of Victoria and of the Library of the<br />Parliament of Victoria in whose promises the Library functioned<br />However successive Library Cormmittoes were ? ctive in collecting<br />and publishing material of australian interest.<br />The Petherick Collection Act of 1911 brought to the<br />national collection a great contribution of Australiana. It<br />was developments such as these, culminating in the purchase<br />of the notable collection of Captain Cook manuscripts, which<br />led the Library Committee in 1923 to adopt the name " Commonwealth<br />National Library" by which the institution has been<br />increasingly known since.<br />It is important to remember that these national<br />collections and services and many others which have developed<br />since which are in fact records of Australian life and<br />achievement have not been sc : arated from the collections and<br />services for the Parliament itself. The need for some<br />identification of the extra Parliamentary services of the<br />Library was recognised as early as 1935 when a sum was<br />placed on the Estimates of the Prime Minister's Departent for<br />the purposes of the National Library. In explaining the new<br />item the Minister representing the Prime Minister said that<br />" because of the Australia wide nature of these services,<br />which are of benefit to scholars and libraries throughout</p>
<p>.4 the Comnonwealth, it is nit thought fitting that<br />appropriation for then should continue to be made on<br />the vote for Parliai-nt."<br />As these services developed and their cost<br />increased, the Prime Ministe: o becao-. e responsible to Parlianent<br />for the greater part of library expendituro. At the same time<br />the Presiding Officers woer becoming increasingly responsible<br />for library . atters outside their nor'nal sphere of interest.<br />2. The Paton Connittecls Report<br />By 1956 the Governcont felt that the time had cone<br />to review the functions and the form of control of this<br />growing research and reference institution which was discharging<br />nation wide responsibilities, It therefore set up a<br />representative Committee on the whole question and to advise<br />on the future developyeont of the library.<br />The National Library Inquiry Co: ittee, under the<br />chairnanship of Sir Georgc Paton, Vice-Chancellor of the<br />University of Melbourneo, included throe nenbors of Parlianent<br />representing all parties and both Houses. The Report of the<br />Connittooee was tabled and ordered to be printed and the<br />Govern ent is most indebted to the Connitte for its worlk.<br />Its imain reco ^:-endations were as follows<br />there should be a Parliamentary Library and 2. National<br />Library of Australia, each to be a separate<br />institution, though closely related to achieve<br />maximum efficiency and ; con) iy;<br />the Parliaentary Library sh) uld be controlled, as at<br />present, by the Pr with the advice of a Joint Coim'ittoo of Morbers of<br />both H. uses;<br />the National Library should be controlled by a body<br />with substantial responsibility for its developre-nt;<br />the present Division of the Library concerned with the<br />records and archives of the Cononwealth Governumnt<br />should become a separate agency of Governm: ent undcr<br />the control of a Director, within an appropriato<br />Departiont, the Minister for which should appoint a<br />small comm1-ittooee fr his 3uidanco;<br />the National Library should be provided as soon as<br />possible with a bui. lding appropriate to its functions<br />meanwhile the separation sheould be put into effect so<br />far as possibl;<br />during this tine the positions of Parliainentary Librarian<br />and National Librarian should be filled by the one<br />person;<br />an exanination should b. : ade as soon as possible by the<br />body controlling the National Library into the<br />desirability of securing a greater co-ordination of<br />Comi: yonwealth G-rvcrnent Library Services.<br />as these recone.. ondations appealed to the Govoernrnt<br />as providing a satisfacto-:; basis for future devolop-cnt it<br />set up an Inderdop:'. rt~ ental Comnittoe in 1959 to advise on the<br />detailed easures nccesscry to make then effective,</p>
<p>3.<br />The Cormittee worked in the closest association with<br />the Presiding Officers and the Parliamentary Library Comiiittee<br />whose co-operation and assistance have been most helpful to<br />the Governmont in reaching the decisions on which the present<br />Bill is based.<br />3. The Governorunt's consideration of the Matter<br />In reaching the conclusions to which the present<br />Bill seeks to give effect, the Governient has boon groetly<br />assisted by having before it the views of the Poton Coi;:, ittoe,<br />of the Inderdepartmental Coimrittee, and of the Parliar-ontary<br />Library Committee. The Government gave special consideration<br />to the following -atters<br />the separation of Governrnent archives from the National<br />Library;<br />the maintenance of library services to Parliame'. nt<br />the functions of the National Library<br />the form of control of the National Library.<br />I should like to say a few words on each of these<br />natters, before passing on to soie of the more detailed<br />matters dealt with in the Bill.<br />First, Archives.<br />Until 1942 the records and archives of the Departm.<br />ents and authorities of the C'on-uonwealth Government were<br />wholly under the control of the agencies which created then.<br />Administrative arrange., ints were then made which brought<br />archives and semi-current records under the Ministerial<br />control of the Prime Ministcr, advised by a Coi. m onwealth<br />Archives Committee of historians and senior officials presided<br />over by Dr. C. E. ii. Bean, Official Historian of the first dorld<br />. Jar. The Archives themselves were provisionally administered,<br />initially by the Conmionwealth National Library and the<br />Australian Jar Merorial jointly and more recently by the<br />Library alone. During this tine systems have been developed,<br />in co-operation with Governomnt Dopartments, to bring the<br />Archives toethor and under systematic control,<br />The Government reached the conclusion that, as these<br />Archives are essentially a collection of the Government's own<br />papers, iany of which iust remain confidential until at least<br />a certain time had elapsed, they should come directly under<br />the control of a Departmental authority as roco'mended by the<br />Paton Committee, rather than under the Governing Body of the<br />National Library. My own experience has convinced me that this is<br />desirable. I attach great importance to the necessity for<br />effective control over the disclosure of archives, particularly<br />those a private or semi-private nature. In my time as<br />Prime Minister i have had applications made to me by authors<br />and other people for access to certain documents written by my<br />predecessors. -Jhen I have found that the document involved in<br />a particular case has been marked ' confidential" or " private",<br />I have always said that it c uld not be disclosed unless the<br />person who wrote it was available to give his consent or his<br />personal representatives expressed their views on the matter.<br />That, I think, is th, proper approach.<br />Whether any part of the non-governmental -rchivos in<br />the possession of the National Library should pass to the</p>
<p>Ialrchivos OrgPanisati-n I s we tiiink a matr , i, cc nD ost<br />be loft to the National Library C -uncil Lind tho 2rchi-1_ val.<br />Orl-a-nis:. tion to conside) r. In any vont threk m--. ust lwa: ys be<br />ti-ic clos st co-opc rati.. n bctuw en ti-c two authoritie-s.<br />Ne xt, s to Parlia-ment. The Ge) v.. rnmont ; a : o( n<br />cinoorned to onsurc that th-i dovolop: ien1, t of the: Nn~ lti-ral<br />Libra-ry a-s a sprWinstitution should not prejudico, but<br />rather stre: n-gthen, the) r_ f,. roncc and r,-; ading,-s-Urvicos av: vailadc<br />toth Prla-mt itself. mthe G oenm-en t a h<br />P'r-, liar.-, ent of theo Commi-jnonwalth n) Oods ti-ic best librov sovico<br />that can be provided fur it1. ' Mun2--bers should be a. blo drau<br />, vith freedom and cm) fide-nco in facts and opinions affecti-ng<br />th ipotnt public issues with whichi the-y haavo It aca.<br />Thei Bill therefre imos a2 special rcs,-, isibility<br />in Se ction 6 th-e 1ovcrn ing body of thec Natio,-nal Libra-ry to<br />pro) vide services to, the Parliame nt. The natur, -and extant of<br />these will clearly depend on theo nceds of the Pa-rliamien t a7' nd<br />on arrangeme-nts , iado fromzl to) time, between thi-iC scpuctivc<br />O-verning bodies. C o -op or at i un be tweeon h-ese b-od ieS 5 hc<br />will nucessarily bo m.-ost clo,-se during the perid6 oif so-cratijn<br />of collections and services, will be zrea tly _ tssistod by the<br />prcusence on ti-ic National Library Ciuncil two rm&amp; l.. bors of<br />Pa-rliai-eint. This will be faci2itated by the 1face tat a<br />least durinrg this period, the one person Will ,(, Ccu. py the<br />positions of N-, ti ) nal and Parliw~ i. ontary Librar,. an.<br />TI-i provis ions in the-' 3ill to onabl. e th1e n1fo( o<br />-iucll of ex-isting colle ctions a ' nd ser~ vices to tlfe Na).-ionai,<br />Library will, we beliLvc, enable " tie Pnriamentary Librar y to<br />retain mnd develop spocialis_ C services and -a speei_, ised<br />collectio-n -au rial dos i~ gid to meet theo articu1la<br />re. quiroments-of the Parlia;., me<br />Theo statome,. nt offptons in S, ctior. 6 of the Bil-l<br />is a very ge,, neral one. It rofleacts the Libraryls picsermt<br />aciiie u rovidos for their dnvolopr~ ont, This bill is<br />so dr fted as to permit aind encoura * o the C un cil to adapt the<br />gfrowtht of the Natienal Libra~ ry of .' ustralia to national needs<br />as they do vnlop and in the fullest co-operation withi other<br />authorities prDviding library services.<br />Mem-bers will be aware of the powers 2, nd cs-, oisibilities<br />for the provision of basic library services for the<br />people. The rem-_ arkable prog ress of r~ cent years i. Thicft has<br />brought free public library sorvices to so many local<br />C~ j-unities tharoughiout . listra-, lia for the first time-, re(-flect<br />great credit on State and local_ õ ovurnmo,, nts. Univkersities<br />libraries arc also being, .;, rc-itly encouraued, a. nd m,. any poublic<br />autho-. rities and priva-te , rganisatio: ns, including busine-iss<br />firm.-s, lave kiso set up librarie-: s. Together_, those libraries,<br />which ce-operate freey. ake up a n-, tii) na3l system, of library<br />services whichi can be , r--atly stren hed -hrunth e<br />, levelopiment of a -roeat natui.) na library. dIrea, dv 1-uc! li is being<br />dine in associat Jion with-the ustralian ZL-is,,-ry C ~ uncil en<br />~ 3ibliograplaical Services -vhlichIi reuresents all iaiob ra ries<br />in astralia. Union catalogues are oe bc~, compile-d wiich! il<br />ultim,-ate-1ly revel to inquirers the lcation alny im-.-portant<br />book ' or periodical in ti-c_) un"' ry.<br />ts to the contr-ol of the_, Nalltional L-ibrary, the bill<br />sekstoesabis -he libra_ ry on a : rm. al basis a.. s abody<br />corporate,. The : rneiis21lwtheo pa-ttern for, such-bodies<br />and thne provisio'ns are broaidiy sitla t Lhosc of otherc<br />goveornme. nt instrul-ental. Jios -n rela,_ Ld fiel1ds, Thc i nte ntion<br />is thnat the i--ffa-irs of the lfitrary will be effe2ctively under<br />thne control Of a smal conc* l1 of nine rersntcao nd<br />experie,, knced en . nd women. hnrbl brstkow the</p>
<p>council has already boon established on an interima basis,<br />with Dr. A. Gronfell Price as chairnamn, two memnbors of<br />Parliaae! nt the President of the Sonato ( Sir , lister Mc-<br />Mullin) and the hon rable i. erobcr for Parkes ( Mr. Haylon) and<br />six others: Mr. K. 3. Myor; Dr. H. 3. ;. iyndhal; Mr. Justice<br />Crisp, of Tasmania; 1srseocfieatses or Kathlcon Fitzpatrick*;<br />Professor L. G. Huxlcy, the new Vice-Chancellor of the . ustralian<br />Nrtional University; and Mr. E. J. 3. Foxcroft, of my own<br />depart. ent, who is a man of groat and special interest in those<br />natters. This council has already met, and the Government has<br />had the benfit of its advice, and that of the parlionentary<br />Library Coiniittee, in framing this bill. The Government is<br />confident that the National Library wrill flourish under the<br />control of this cuncil, comrising as it does a group of<br />people who are eninent and oxperiencod in many walks of life<br />in the Australian conmm-unity.<br />There' are some other provisions of the bill which I<br />should perhaps montion. It makos the nora. provision, as I<br />have said, fur a council controlling a c rporat body. It is<br />the view of the Governmont that the library should be a<br />substantially autononous body, with mninisterial responsibility<br />lii: itod wherever possible. The finance which will be<br />provided, of course, by annual appropriation the st,. ffing<br />which will cone under the Public Service Act and the other<br />matters provided for in the bill all are quite consistent with<br />the substantial autonomy of the c; uncil in the discharge of its<br />respnsibiliti: s. wo then think about a Nati nal Library building, Sir.<br />are under enor1: ous pressure in Canberra in relation to<br />building. This library is a g ing and growing concorn<br />with some 500,000 books, as well as pictorial aterial, caps,<br />films and so on. . All those things lack a suitable building.<br />mt present, the library is accmm. clodated in various places in a<br />nakeshift and highly inconvenient f-shion and, I would have<br />thought, in rather dan-gerous situati ens, soLno atrial being in<br />a factory building in this city and other mnaterial being in<br />these elogant igloos here.<br />Mr. Thomopson: There is a rrdo ad to the library.<br />Mr. MENZIES: Yes. That is one "' hing,. The G vernmlont has<br />agreed that design and planning work for a now National<br />Library building should be in, and the interim council is now<br />discussing roquiroonts with the National Capital Devel) opont<br />Co; i ssion. The Governmont is very m-uch aware that the library<br />is oxperiencing acuto difficulties in its day-to-day work and<br />that these will increase as the collections grow, and therefore<br />we are keen to see a suitable building, I cannot hold -ut any<br />particular da-to t, honorable r. o bers. The first thing to do in<br />this iacter it will not be sim-ple but will require a lot of<br />work is to have consultations betwoon the council and the<br />National Capital Developont Commn-ission in relation to design<br />and roquiroeents. It m-ay occur to some honorable mem-_ bors t! hat the<br />matter of copyright should be dealt with, because one of the<br />oldest concepts of a national library which has persisted and<br />has boon adopted by many countri. s, including our own, is that<br />a national library is the proper place to collect and<br />preserve, for current and uspecially future use, matrial of<br />all kinds illustrating the life nd achievemeonts of tilhe peoplo. e,<br />This activity is usually supported by the law of copyright<br />deposit, and provision was made in the Copyright Ict 1912 for<br />such deposit of copyright work in the library of the<br />Connwalth Prlianmont. T he Pt n Comittee recoinu: ndod that</p>
<p>this priviloe be transferred to the National Library. All I<br />nlood say, Sir, is that this is just one aspect of the copyright<br />law. Together with others, it is receiving the<br />Gcjvrnients attention. The -tt ) rnoy-General ( Sir. Garfield<br />Barwick) would li!: ke to have a comprohonsive piece of<br />loislation on that m. atter. . io propose that until that is<br />produced the mnatorial continuo to be deposited in the library<br />of the Parliwanont. It can be transforrod to the National<br />Library as wo adopt the change.<br />Mr. Boazloy I should like to ask a question about the site<br />for the no-w National Library building. Is it to be dowrn by<br />the lake?<br />Mr. P-lMNZIES I cannot tell the honorable ebici: r. I have had<br />it said to o with what authority, I do not know that the<br />building would be near the lake and on the flank, so to speak,<br />of the proposed now Parlianmont House,. But I have son so many<br />other things that have to be done in Canbjrra that I have not<br />allowed my mind to speculato so mnuch.<br />ir. IHaylen the right honorable gontlnan has refused to be<br />out-flanked, as it wuro.<br />j. HENbZjIE-Yes. The Governrontts aim in giving the N: tional<br />Library a statutory basis and a wide chartor is to . llow it to<br />play a significant and appropriate part in the L. ustralian<br />Library systo and in iustralian life generally. This, as T<br />do not need to emphasiz to the House, is of groat importance,<br />Sir. W4e have, uo think, done a good deal and so have<br />governments over a long time to intensify resoarch and<br />inquiry throu7h universities and through a variety of<br />research bodies and a encies of -overniioont. The developmont<br />of library resources is a necessary and natural corollary.</p>
<p><br />I think that before I conclude I should pay a<br />special tribute to the successive Library Corittees of this<br />Parliament. These comitteos have over m-any years, by their<br />far-sightod policies, laid the groundwork for the institution<br />which this bill, when it is passod into law, will wnake a<br />r( cality.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
