<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2810</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTERS PRESS CONFERENCE AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002810.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T1HE PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
AT PARLIANEI\ TT HOUSE, CANBERITA<br />
, TUESDAY, 6 FEBRUARY 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Wfell ladies and gentlemen, I have tried to get some<br />
of these conferences in time for the afternoon papers. This is one<br />
of the few occasions when I have been able to do so, but I will have<br />
to rush off because of the Federal Executive resuming at 2 o'clock<br />
and then I am sorry to have kept you waiting I came as quickly as<br />
I could get something to eat after the Cabinet meeting.<br />
First then, the Cabinet decisions:<br />
Senator Wriedt will be making a statement at 5 o'clock or if he<br />
makes it before that it will be embargoed until 5 o'clock concerning<br />
adjustment assistance for rural industries. The embargo is required<br />
because the Premiers have to receive the contents of the Cabinet<br />
decision before they hear it otherwise. It has been announced to the<br />
members of the Agricultural Council who have been meeting with Senator<br />
Wriedt and, of course, Mr. Enderby, the Minister for the Northern<br />
Territory, this morning and yesterday. Senator Wriedt partly<br />
because of the preparations for the Agricultural Council meeting<br />
was unable to prepare by Friday ( which is the closing date for<br />
Cabinet agenda items) proposals for conducting the referehidum on<br />
merino exports. He hopes to have that next Tuesday. He has discussed<br />
it with the State ministers on the Agricultural Council.<br />
There were two Tariff Board reports concerning by-law admissions<br />
by Senator Murphy as Minis-ter for Customs and Excise. There was a<br />
inter-departmental committee set up by the previous Government it<br />
hasn4t met it has been reconstituted and its membership broadened.<br />
It is to have membership from the Prime Minister's Department, Treasury,<br />
Customs and Excise, Overseas Trade and Secondary Industry. It will<br />
cover the whole question of the effect of imports under by-law<br />
exemptions and the effect they have on costs and on protection.<br />
There were seven submissions by Senator Murphy, as Attorney-General<br />
on extradition treaties with Germany, Australia, Italy, Israel, Sweden<br />
and the United States, and amendments to our extradition legislation.<br />
Further details on these matters by-laws and extradition can be<br />
got from Senator Murphy.<br />
There was a submission by Mr. Barnard concerning the use of V. I. P.<br />
aircraft. The present rules were tabled by Senator Drake Brockman<br />
in September 1970. New rules will be tabled when the Parliament sits.<br />
In essence they amplify the old rules in two respects. Firstly, it<br />
will be plain that a V. I. P. aircraft can only be used when there are<br />
not appropriate other commercial forms of transport available. I should<br />
add, that there has been no suggestion that any of the V. I. P.<br />
applications by ministers could have been fulfilled by commercial<br />
aircraft. The other amplification of the rules is, in effect, that if </p>
<p>-2-<br />
members Of a V. I. P'S family other than his wife are sought to be<br />
included the case must be referred to the Prime Minister for<br />
consideration. In the same context, perhaps I should mention that when<br />
the week after next I go on my visit to Indonesia I will be<br />
accompanied by my daughter who, hitherto, has lived with us and is<br />
dependent on us and who was invited by the President to accompany us.<br />
Also, as unofficial members of the party, there will be the President<br />
of the Commonwealth Conciliatiion and Arbitration Commission, Sir<br />
Richard Kirby, and his wife, and Mr. Bruce Grant.<br />
Sir Richard Kirby is coming in the party because he represented<br />
Australia on the Good Officers' Committee in the 1940' s and is<br />
remembered with affection in Indonesia and is visited by any<br />
distinguished Indonesians who come to Australia. And Mr. Bruce Grant,<br />
as you know, has long been interested, academically, in Indonesia and<br />
has written several books on it the first when President Sukarno was<br />
still in office.<br />
It is very likely that you have heard of the matters about<br />
possible Australian representation in Hanoi.' I might therefore state<br />
that the Government's consideration for legal and practical questions<br />
associated with possible Australian representation in Hanoi is nearly<br />
complete. I expect to be instructing officials to seek to start<br />
discussions with the North Vietnamese shortly. We have already informed<br />
a number of neighbouring and associated countries of our intentions.<br />
Once it is clear that the ceasefire has been established and that<br />
there may be a contribution in aid by Australia, we can give further<br />
consideration in the light of requirements the qid requirements of<br />
the countries concerned, the likely contribution from other donors and<br />
North Vietnamese willingness to accept aid.<br />
Gentlemen, those are the only announcements I have to make.<br />
2Sir, why did you move the motion at yesterday's Executive to<br />
congratulate the Cabinet on the prompt and effective steps to control<br />
the price and volume of mineral exports? Was it designed to strengthen<br />
your hand against any Minister, in particular Dr. Patterson, in any<br />
action you might take?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Proceedings at the Federal Executive of the party are<br />
in the province of the Federal Secretary, Mr. Young, to announce. Hie's<br />
already made statements on this and answered questions about it. The<br />
resolution to which you refer arose out of an agenda item on the<br />
Federal E7xecutive's papers. You mention about Dr. Patterson: at the<br />
Cabinet this morning it was agreed that Mr. Connor and Dr. Patterson<br />
would confer before any further statements were made on the export of<br />
minerals. QSir, the A. L. P. Platform attacks the former Government's refusal<br />
to inform the Parliament and the public of the general purposes and<br />
possible consequences of the joint defence installations and facilities<br />
at Pine Gap and Nurrungar. Will you arrange for the press to have an<br />
unrestricted tour of Pine Gap and Nurrungar so that we may inform at<br />
least the public of the general purposes and possible consequences of<br />
those bases? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PRIL1E MINISTER: I thank you for quoting what the Party says on this.<br />
You'll notice that we have criticised the former Government's failure<br />
to inform the Parliament and the public. We will be informing the<br />
Parliament and, through it, the public, including the Press.<br />
Q. Mr. 1Whitlam, also quoting the Party Platform which says:<br />
" Australian forces should not be committed overseas except subject to<br />
clear and public international agreement." Will there be such an<br />
agreement covering the logistic force in Singapore?<br />
PRIMCE MINISTER: There is. Gentlemien, there is I'm sure you know an<br />
agreement published in the Australian Treaty series two years ago the<br />
Five Power defence arrangements a summary of them was included in<br />
my Policy Speech, and perhaps I should read that to you.<br />
" Pending neutralisation we will honor the full terms of the<br />
Five Power Arrangements under which Australia agrees to provide<br />
Malaysia and Singapore with personnel, facilities and courses for<br />
training their forces and assistance in operational and technical<br />
matters and the supply of equipment. We will be willing to make similar<br />
arrangements with Indonesia, Papua New Guinea, New Zealand and Fiji.<br />
The Five Power Arrangements do not require an Australian garrison in<br />
Singapore; the battalion and battery there will not be replaced when<br />
they complete their tour of duty."<br />
I've noticed many references to the Party's policy in this matter.<br />
Therefore, may I quote the relevant passages from the 1971 revision<br />
of the Platform. Many people quote the Platform or resolutions as<br />
they left earl. ier conferences in 1969. I will quote the two passages<br />
which bear upon this subject in the 1971 Platform. First under the<br />
heading of Defence: " A strong defence capability can be further<br />
enhanced by participation in mutual defence arrangements with other<br />
nations in South-East Asia and the Pacific and Indian Ocean areas<br />
consistent with the requirements of the United Nations Charter and the<br />
objectives of existing treaties". And secondly under Foreign Affairs:<br />
" Australian forces should not be committed overseas except subject to<br />
clear and public international agreements."<br />
There is a clear and public international agreement. Under it we<br />
are fulfilling and continuing to fulfil the obligations which the<br />
Party Platform envisages which the Policy Speech reiterated. I'm<br />
surprised that there's been a great number of figures given as to the<br />
number of soldiers that will remain. I was askzed last time whether<br />
there'd be 500 or 600. I said " Yes". That's the total number, and<br />
that's all forces.<br />
Q. Does this include the Air Force?<br />
PRIME MINIJSTEIR: No. Singapore includes the Air Force yes.<br />
Q. Your interpretation of garrison, Sir. A lot of people have<br />
interpreted... J? 1LIN~ E MINISTER: There will be no combat troops -there. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Q. But a garrison under the strict definition doesn't necessarily<br />
mean combat troops... 500 or 600 people could be termed a garrison.<br />
In your interpretation it's not a garrison?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, yes. These are logistic and other training<br />
matters in the terms of the agreement. I pointed out the agreement<br />
did not refer require the presence of a battalion or a battery. That<br />
is the combatant ones. And they'll be coming out at the end of their<br />
tour of duty and, as I was told in an answer to a question last year:<br />
" 4th Battalion R. A. R. and 106th Field Battery. Both will complete their<br />
tour of duty in Singapore as part of ANZUK force in January 1974."<br />
You might find other relevant matters in this in that answer on the<br />
17th October last.<br />
Q. Was this matter discussed at Cabinet this morning.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
Do you expect it to be discussed tomorrow at the Caucus Meeting?<br />
Do you expect it to be endorsed at the Caucus Meeting?<br />
PRIME . MINISTER: The Caucus ieeting tomorrow is being called under the<br />
Standing Orders as stated in the telegram I despatched summoning the<br />
meeting to discuss projected legislation and, accordingly, Ministers<br />
will be putting to the Caucus the subject matter of legislation which<br />
the Cabinet has asked to be drafted.<br />
Q. Sir, After the battalion comes back in early 1974, will another<br />
battalion go out on location for a month or two or something like that?<br />
PRII ME MINISTER: No.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There may be training exercises, yes, and that may be<br />
a two-way thing.<br />
Q. But it has not definitely been decided yet?<br />
PRIfME MINISTER: No. Nobody wants to be precise on these things. The<br />
Malaysians, the Singaporeans, the British have rmade no proposals this<br />
way. But, as you know, as we've stated for years we are very happy to<br />
have joint exercises and training and communications and procurement<br />
programs with not only Malaysia and Singapore but with all our neighbours<br />
as I stated in the Policy Speech on the last occasion.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, could you give us a breakdown of the 500 or 600<br />
troops that are going to remain there in Singapore?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. No, I can't give that.<br />
Q. Can you tell us, Sir, whether the Five Power Agreement has been<br />
jeopardised in any way by Australian policy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
Q. It hasn't?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. </p>
<p>Q. The Lord Carrington talks made no difference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I had quite a. time with Lord Carrington last Thursday<br />
and last Friday and there was no suggestion of any jeopardy to the<br />
arrangements for all five nations and, of course, I discussed them with<br />
Mr. Kirk two weeks ago, and they suit all five members.<br />
Q. Mr. Whitlan, you said that it was agreed that Mr. Connor and Dr.<br />
Patterson would confer before making statements on the export of minerals.<br />
Was that an agreement reached by the two men, or was it an agreement<br />
made by the Cabinet?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, there was a discussion and they agreed. I've got<br />
no more to say on that.<br />
Q. Does it apply to all exports of minerals or only those that come<br />
from the northern..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I said the export of minerals.<br />
Q. Why is it necessary for two Ministers to come to that agreement?<br />
Why not just..<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I've got no more to say on this.<br />
Q. Sir, would you care to comment on the Queensland Government's decision<br />
to oppose your decision to have the export control of all minerals?<br />
PRIME~ MINISTER: They're entitled to take any action which commends itself<br />
to them. We will of course resist any such claims. I've no doubt we'd<br />
win in the courts.<br />
Q. Sir, just before the election Mr. Brnard suggested that Australia<br />
should seek access to ocean surveillance information gathered by U. S.<br />
satellites and U. S. aircraft in return for America's use of Australian<br />
bases. Has the Government taken this up with the U. S. authorities and,<br />
if so, with what results?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Government has. I've not discussed this with<br />
Mr. Barnard.<br />
Q. Sir, since the last press conference, you apparently have received<br />
formal requests for a Premiers Conference. Could you tell us whether<br />
you've given any further consideration to this and whether there will<br />
be a Premiers Conference in February or March?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER: There will not be a Premiers Conference in February<br />
or March. My general attitude to these matters is that if any variation<br />
is required in the financial arrangements for any particular year<br />
any variation of the formula or of the arrangements made at the regular<br />
Premiers Conference, then it should be backed by a proper submission<br />
that there should bc some headings and some documentation to justify<br />
them. Up to now Premiers Conferences have had an agenda in this area<br />
there's been a one-line entry Commonwealth/ State Financial Relations.<br />
The new Federal Government will require something more explicit than<br />
that. Our general attitude is that there should be proper investigation </p>
<p>-6-<br />
of all Government expenditure which the Commonwealth undertakes or<br />
which it is asked to underwrite. We want to seek advice, and in many<br />
cases we will be making that advice public. Now there have been some<br />
statements that there was a firm undertaking to have a Premiers<br />
Conference this month. There was no such firm undertaking. I was<br />
interested to notice that when Mr. Snedden, who was the Treasurer at<br />
the time, made a comment on this subject a couple of days ago he didn't<br />
assert there was a firm undertaking. lie knew there was not a firm<br />
undertaking. I1 reiterate what I said a week ago: There were proposals<br />
put by all the Premiers in some cases orally in other cases in<br />
writing largely in the context of employment creating work, but<br />
sometimes also in connection with programs which were announced for this<br />
financial year in the Party's Policy Speech. In each of those cases<br />
the Premiers' propositions were examined by the Federal officials.<br />
In each of these cases I have written in reply. Now if there's any<br />
variation, I take the basic proposition that if people can't put a case<br />
in writing, they haven't got a strong case.<br />
Q. Sir, have you received the report of Mr. JusticeMoore on the<br />
inquiry into 13. H. P.? I. Then do you expect you might receive it, and<br />
when you do receive it, when do you think it might be made public?<br />
Finally, are you in a position-yet to tell us the name of the company<br />
which followed B. II. P.' s example with a request for an investigation?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER: I haven't yet received Mr. Justice Moore's report. I<br />
don't know when I will receive it. I would expect that I would release<br />
it very soon after receiving it. I would obviously want to show it to<br />
the Treasurer and to the Attorney-General because the three of us 0 -ev<br />
up the terms of reference for Mr. Justice Moore. I haven't followed<br />
up whether I can release the name of -the company which did apply, but<br />
without their permission I don't think I could release it.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, according to Lord Carrington the A~ ustralian<br />
Government has not had time to consider the question of nuclear shio-s<br />
entering Australian ports. ' Then is this likely to be considered, and<br />
what is your attitude?<br />
PRIM IINIST3R: The Government only considers matters which come before<br />
it by way of Cabinet submission and the procedure is for these to be<br />
given to me on the Friday at the latest and then I can list them for<br />
-the next Cabinet on the Tuesday. There's no submission on this subject.<br />
11r. Barnard and I were pretty fully briefed about this matter before<br />
Lord Carrington arrived because we knew that he would be w., anting to<br />
discuss this matter. We are looking at it in the general context of<br />
the safety for Australian ports and the people living near them or using<br />
them as far as nuclear-driven ships naval and mercantile sare<br />
concerned. It's not just ships such as submarines. It's also ships<br />
like the ' Savannah'. I think the " lest Germans also have a nuclearpowered<br />
ship. There is an international agreement concerning nuclearpowered<br />
ships mercantile ships merchant ships. The whole question<br />
is being examined. Ile will of course have in mind the safety of people<br />
living near our ports or coming into them.<br />
* If asked by -the Federal Executive, will you accept the position as<br />
Federal President? </p>
<p>-7-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'll wait till I'm asked. I never knew of the<br />
proposition until I read it in today's papers. I'm immensely<br />
flattered at the suggestion, but I would think it could be more<br />
appropriately held by persons other than members of the Parliament and<br />
that it should rotate every couple of years. Look, I haven't been<br />
asked. Q. With the decision of -the New Zealand Rugby Union to go ahead with<br />
the Springbok tour, is our position absolutely unchanged and do you<br />
. see that this might place in jeopardy the Commonwealth Games; and<br />
w ill Australia do anything to help or hinder the actual staging of those<br />
Games? PRIME MINISTE1: There has been no reconsideration sought of the<br />
Government's decision to deny entry or transit to racially selected<br />
sporting teams. I fear that if the New Zealand football authorities<br />
persist and succeed in having a visit by a Spring bok team this will<br />
very seriously truncate the Commonwealth Games which are to be held in<br />
Christchurch later this year. The Australian Government hasn't taken<br />
any steps it's not likely to take any steps to prevent Australians<br />
playing what they like and where they like. I am, however already<br />
asked our missions in all Commonwealth countries to ascertain the<br />
effects of a Spring bok tour of New Zealand on the Commonwealth Games<br />
in New Zealand. It's quite clear that half the Commonwealth countries<br />
would not be able to participate in those Games because half of them<br />
depend on Government assistance to participate. That Government<br />
assistance would be withheld if New Zealand condones the New Zealand<br />
Government doesn't but if New Zealanders appear to condone the<br />
racial discrimination policies which the South African Government<br />
imposes on South African sporting teams representing South Africa, then<br />
there can be no question that the Commonwealth Games will be in peril<br />
and all of us interested in sport or interested in the Commonwealth<br />
will be disadvantaged by the stubbornness of that single section of the<br />
New Zealand population. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
