<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9945</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE WITH PARTIES TO THE CAPE YORK AGREEMENT, RADDISON HOTEL, CAIRNS, SUNDAY, 18 FEBRUARY 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009945.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
19/ 02 ' 96 07: L5 1 ' 61 6 273 2923 PMl PRESS OFFICE @ l~ l<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MiP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE W) ITH PARTIES TO THE CAPE YORK AGREEMENT. RAW~ SON<br />
HOTEL, CAIRNS, SUNDAY, 18 FEBRUARY 1996<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I have had a meeting today with my colleagues who are with me who-are the parties<br />
to the Cape York Land Use Agreement. and .1 must say, I have beoti tremendously<br />
impressed with the attitudes which have been expressed in the meeting. The<br />
decjarations of good wi1 which people have had and, I think, the recognition that to try<br />
to give people the benefts of the Cape and the quiet enjoyment of iffe free of<br />
perpetual litigation, free of arguments about land use, free of conflicting pressures<br />
over its heritage values, but rather to come together and see this as a way in which<br />
all the parties can secure something greater for themselves and the country is the<br />
way lo proceed.<br />
It is the very: essence of an act of regional. reconciliation and the whole process of<br />
reconciliation which. I think, has been mightily advanced by Mabo and the Native Title<br />
Act. In a sense by empowering Aboriginal people and giving them legal rights over<br />
lands for which they have traditional soiaio has meant that this has started to<br />
move the log ) amn In some of these regions so that we can perhaps approach them<br />
now on a regional basis.<br />
You might know that under the Native Title Act there is a provision there for regional<br />
agreements. What we have here is not a regional agreement as under the Native<br />
Title Act, but a movement a long way towards one with the land use agreement within<br />
which the interests of the pastoralists represented here by the Cattlemen's' Union, the<br />
Aboriginal people by the Cape Yorki Land Council and the ATSIC Regional Council<br />
and also by, of course, the conservation foundation and The Wilderness Society in<br />
terms of the w~ orld heritage values.-it offers us a very uplifting opportunity to actually<br />
see the Cape being developed on a sustainable basis, operated on a sustainable<br />
basis where the heritage values are protected and where we have a secure pastoral<br />
industry. but one which itself operates in a way which is harmonious with the<br />
aspirations of Aboriginal people on the Cape.<br />
This is the very essence of what the Commonwealth Government has sought to do<br />
with the recnciliation process and with the Native Title Act and also with those other<br />
policies such as Landcare land use programs such as Landcare and the Rural<br />
Adjustment Scheme which we have introduced as more general programs which will<br />
aiso have application on the Cape. Looking at property planning, whole of farm<br />
management sustainable agriculture and then later if we are to head towards 8 full </p>
<p>1% 9/ Y0~ 61' 96 607 : 52 73 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE02<br />
2<br />
regional agreement whiere we would, at that point need to inrvolve the State of<br />
Queensland we* can took then at the proper resourting of the area in terms of<br />
sewerage, environmental health issues, roas, housing, et cetera.<br />
For the moment. -I think this is if you like, a cofltfion of very significant concessions<br />
which have been made to accommodate each of the parties aspirations and I am<br />
very happy to Support the agreement and we will jupport the agreement on the basis<br />
of an assessme. nt of the Worid Heritage values ' and establsh a fund of $ 40 million<br />
over four years which, of course, we have provided funding for In the Labor ParIs<br />
funding arrangements for the ensuing Parliament But it will be $ 40 million in a fund<br />
for over four years for the non-compulsor acquisifon of high conservation value<br />
pastoral hoidings and alao using part of the fund to support sustainable management.<br />
Theme is no one " uhortty that can speak for this region. There is no one group and It<br />
we are to reafise its great heritage potential and underline its sustanablity, at the<br />
same time provide for the more adequate enjoyment and use of the land by<br />
Aboriginail people then this I'm sure, is the way to go and I would like to take the<br />
opportunfity of very sincerely congratulating the parties on this very great initiative. It<br />
is an -absolute model of reconciition of differences and advancement of a common<br />
interest and I hope it can be a model to be used -further in Australia and hopefully, at<br />
some point~ move down the road of a full regional agreement under the Native Title<br />
* Act Perhaps I could also say with the tourism assets in this region that ame also so<br />
manifest and with the World Heritage area the Daintree that which the Government<br />
has already undertken in funding the Daintree and World Heritage area back in the<br />
1980s and now committing another, with the State of Queensland, $ 22 million to<br />
buying back the properties in the hoie-ir-the-heart. It rually means from Mo~ man to<br />
the top of Cape York we can onceive of an area where with somne recognition of<br />
everyone's irnterests, Gupport for the heritage values, understanding the importance<br />
of sustabity and some financWa support from the Commonwealth through this and<br />
with more generaffy fta other Landceare programs we can conceive an area whc very<br />
few courdries would ever have the opportunity of ever being able to consider for the<br />
ntational heritage of their country as wse can this for Australia.<br />
I am very happy to finish my remarks there. I am not sure whether my colleagues<br />
would likte to add. to them, If they do they are welcom, otherwise I am happy as 1 am<br />
sure they are, to take questions.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you think that this process implicitly recognises that resolution of<br />
Native Tis issues through the tribunal process is flawed, that it isn't working?<br />
PM: No, no, rnotatell-It isjutttevenwhen UWyare wrng tey are going to take<br />
time and even if they take time there is going to be a legal process which is not<br />
necessxarily going to suit all of the parties. Wheres what is being offered here is a<br />
process which is one where all of the parties interests are beinmg met and this is the<br />
beat way to advance it That is why in the Native Title Artwedcid conceive of the<br />
notion of regional agreements. This Is a regional land use agreement, but part of that<br />
land use agreement wl go to resolution of some of the native title issues which win<br />
more adequately and expeditiously resolve some if the outstanding issues of which,<br />
of course, on the Cape there are many.<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 07: 51U012 </p>
<p>19'/ 2V 6' 16 60: 522 73 2923 PJ1 PRESS OFFICEQ~ 013<br />
3<br />
J: Do you think there is a better way forward than relying on the native title<br />
PM: No. AIis just a case of both because in some places such agreements wi" not be<br />
entered. I mean, such good-wil will not be shown where it can't be conceived that<br />
interests can be met and they will be resolved by the proces of the Native Tide Act.<br />
Part of the aft, ~ ton, the claity and strength of the Native Tifte Act is to let people<br />
know that Aboriginal people do have rights aod they are going to need to be<br />
accmmodted and to bring people to this sort o'a, process.<br />
J. How do you expec the Stale Government to regad to this and how important is their<br />
ag reemeit to it?<br />
PM: I don't know. I don't know wtat a Borbidge governments, attitude would be to this. I<br />
think we will consult wfth them over the agreement arnd plans for World Herltage<br />
asessmenit and nomination, we wfi do that. I would like to think that like the Goss<br />
government they will recognise. the considerable regional benefits for people here on<br />
the Cape. In the end, it is not simply about the heritage vakues, but rather about the<br />
communities on the Cape and that is important to. us and I should imagine it would be<br />
important to the Borbidge government too. BuA in the end, in respect of these issues<br />
the ultimate determinants of the issues here are the parties because we are not<br />
seeking from the Borbidge government a full reqional Agreement. Not at this point<br />
anyway.<br />
J: Mr Howard has announced this morning that not only will he commit up to $ 40 rrullion<br />
to protevting the high conservation areas of the Cape, but he will m~ so, engage in<br />
discussion with Bob Borbidge and the Federal and Queensland Coalitons to work<br />
together, to best implement the protection of these regions. * Has he stolen your<br />
thunder and would he be better equipped to gain agreement from a Queensland<br />
Coeon government<br />
PM. He doesn't befieve in these issues, you know that. He has discmvered the<br />
er-vronmerlt about two weeks ago. I mean, the Natie Title Act, his party said was a<br />
' day of shame' when we passed iL It is the strength of the Native Title Act and also<br />
our inter" s in the World Herftage areas from the -1980s onwards and our continuing<br />
inrin theCape, think, whic providsao to fnanarement ofthis kind.<br />
It is not just money it i3 commitment Mr Howard has neither the money nor the<br />
commitment because he has said, apparently, that any funding of Cape York would<br />
be dependent on the sate of Teistre and he knows that is not going to happen. It is<br />
not going to proceed. He will not get the sale a( Telecom through the Senate.<br />
Thefefvrehe has no funding for Ktand a3Mr Beazley made carlast week. he has a<br />
$ 3 billion deflency in the funding he has already provided. So, he can afford to do<br />
none of the things he is saying he will do.<br />
J: Mr Kesting, would you not proceed with World Heritage nomination without the<br />
agreement of the State government?<br />
PM: I wouid firstly, raRther than jump at that, baulk at that particular propoaition, pay the<br />
State goverme~ nt the courtesy, as I would any State governmeMt of seeking to<br />
interest them in these values, If are tatking about en area whiich~ has the potential<br />
of a World Heritage listing we are talking about something very unique and you have<br />
got to be a very strange government not to be interested in somethin like that. I<br />
qnvfImothat thay wuni IdheV<br />
1 19/ 02 ' 96 07: 52 </p>
<p>19/ 26 1' 66 0: 2537~ 3 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE<br />
4<br />
J: unnecessary precondition though for proceeding?<br />
PM: I would crtainly, beore I did anything else, have a very real and meaningful<br />
discussion with the Borbidge government about ita<br />
J: Does this agreement need to have legislative backing either at the State or Federal<br />
level and what are the implications on both fronts?<br />
PM: It would need, obviousty, an appropriation from the Commonwealth and it would be<br />
for these World Heritage and management purposes here on the Cape. We would<br />
make that clear because of its unique character and because what the parties have<br />
done here is. I think. unique. We would propose to both houses of Parfiament an<br />
appropriation to fund the agreement because the agreement is something in the<br />
Commonwealth's imterest, in the nation's interest and worthy of that funding.<br />
J: What agency. Mr Keating, do you im-egine managing the $ 40 milion fund and<br />
carrying out the environ mental assessment?<br />
PM: That is somnething we would need to think about. As you know we already have a<br />
World Heritage Admini~ stration here Wert Tropics Adminiatrwtion " e ame speaking<br />
here not of Wet Tropics, but we are spealing of sornethIng simiar. So, we would<br />
need to think about that, whether Aist under the Department of the Environment or to<br />
what edent we engage the Deparment of Primary Industries and Energy because of<br />
a very large component of this Is the sustainability of pastoral practices and the<br />
patoral industry, the development and growth of the pastoral industry on the Cape.<br />
J: You were saying that there would be non compulsory acquiltn, but if theme was an<br />
area of particularly high conservation value, potentially World Heritage value, do you<br />
think there is a case for compulsory acquisition?<br />
PM: It depends on whiethier they have been managed sustains* l. No one is going to cit<br />
the land off, excise it off and floatit out to sea. ltI ging tobe threandIt is just a<br />
matte of whether It is being managed sustainably. Therefore, I just don't thnk the<br />
notion of compulion is appropriate here, It is a huge area of Australia and it can only<br />
really be preserved if all the parties are interested in at. There is no government<br />
authortty, no one authority can do this, It has got to be done by the people who live<br />
there. Mr Diowney,-does the comments made by the Prime Minister today, bring the ACF<br />
firmly boa in behind the Labor Patty, pertirularty in light of the commitments of Mr<br />
Howard also seems to have made..<br />
JO: That might be a point for me to make a couple of introductory comments if you don't<br />
mind and I'll get to that question. About 10 minutes ago, I don't know wther people<br />
are aware, but today is adluaty the highest tie in North Queenisland and it ooure<br />
at 10: 30amn and ( think there are parallels we can* draw and say that the fide has also<br />
turned for one of Austraba's natural and cultural areas and that is Cape Yorkc<br />
Peninsula. In an age, as I have said before, when so many of this countys wild plae have<br />
hman Ine anoq qwrfVarat itne4. a tho efPctrtinn thsat 1% 4 rnm u&amp;* k w*, n' 0m Zi014<br />
1 19/ 02 ' 96 07: 53 </p>
<p>19/ 6' 019 0 76: 42 73 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE l 1<br />
industia~ tion ' and in an age where 70 per cent of the country is in some form of<br />
degradation and in an age where those greet wild p~ aces that haven't been protected<br />
in the last deae and are not protected in the* no~ decada will almost certainly be<br />
lost. Australians have stood up and said they want their icn 2reas protected. Over<br />
the last decade we have had the big ones Kakadu, the Wet Tropics and the<br />
Dainre, Frasr Island, the western forests of Tasmania and let's make no mistake<br />
about it, Cape York Peninsula is also one of those big ones that ranks up there with<br />
those. Whether it is because Cape York Peninsula contains one fift of Austrea's rain forest<br />
including the largest low land tropical rain forest left in the country, whether it is<br />
because it contains and significant vast amounts of old growth forest. tropical<br />
savanna woodland that is probably the largest outside of Africa in the world, whiether<br />
it is because ft contains the largest and richest and most diverse wetlands and<br />
mangrove com munities in this county, 60 per . cent of Australia's butterflies. 80 per<br />
cent of our orchard species, one pastoral lease on Cape York Peninsula contains a<br />
quarter of all Austratlian frogs, all those natural values Cumulatively can only draw one<br />
conclusion. That Cape York is, in fact, one of our great icon natural areas.<br />
For that reason, today's announcement is a momentous occson. It does rank up<br />
there with~ the big ones, the Kakedu the Wet Tropics and the Dahinre and the Fraser<br />
island. I guess what I would like to say in conclusion and this drws me to your question, I'd<br />
like to put out a call as the Executive Director of the Australian Conservation<br />
Foundiation to al people in the conservation movement, to other groups and<br />
environmerntaly. conscious voters out there in the community to get behind what will<br />
be one of Australias greatest conservation achievements and that is the protection of<br />
the nature and culture of Cape York Peninsula.<br />
At the mwment, at least on one side of politics, I have seen the words, from the Prime<br />
Minister as to what the ALP is prepared to commit Itseff to. I haven't seen the<br />
Coalitions words, but what I would say is that there is one issue that is not a small<br />
mater, andthati io u aa elTestato raisethe dough to pay for what yousay<br />
you are going to do, then there is no way in my investigations over the last week and<br />
a half and discussions with the Democrats, the Australian Greens and the Western<br />
Australian Greens, that Teistra is gOng to be sold in the next term of the Parliament.<br />
it is just not going to happen. This has to call into question the ability of the Coalition<br />
to fund not only the $ 1.1 billion, by our calculations there Is $ 993 million, that won't<br />
happen when Telstra isn't sold that it also means that the funding, I think, at this point<br />
unless. there is a dramatic turn in the next week and a half of the protection of one of<br />
Australia's great natural and cultural areas woon't happen either.<br />
So, in condluding and I hope that has answered your question. In conclusion I would<br />
like to say agpin that I am putting a call out to anl environmentally consckous people in<br />
the community and the conservation movement to get right behind what will be one of<br />
Australia's greatest conservation achievements<br />
J: Mr Downey, when Mr Howard announced hMs policy a couple of wveeks ago in the<br />
Dandenong you were standing in front of a microphone saying that the Coalition<br />
policy was fantastic and that it puts both parties on equal footing. If in fadt Mr Howard<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 07: 54Q 0 is </p>
<p>19/ 2 61' 66 7.: 52 73 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE<br />
6<br />
has offered a similar amount of monery for a Cape York agreement. where are you<br />
placed now?<br />
JD: On the day that Mr Howard announced his policy I said three things. I can't help it ly<br />
people just want to report one of the three, but the three were that there was some<br />
excellence In the content of the poliy, there was significant uncrtinty as to whether<br />
it could ever be delivered because of the Jink with Telstra and there was<br />
disappointmnent -The disappointment being therabandonment of the Three Mines<br />
Uranium policy which wigt almost cettainly mnean a big hole, in the middle of Kakadu<br />
National Park.<br />
Now, those three things were made very clear on the day. The next day we wrote to<br />
Mr Howard expressing our serious concern about the ink with Teistra and the<br />
uncattainty thiat that meant for the funding of his environment package, he hasn't<br />
withdrawn that As Isay f there is o change in the next two weekstenour view s<br />
that his environment package can't be defrered.*<br />
J: So therefore, you are still holding out to the last minute to decide where your<br />
allegiance will fie?<br />
JD: What Ilil say isthat flt of all, Idon't got avote# asto the position of the ACF in the<br />
election. that is up to my 37 eledted councllors. They will be holding a ballot on<br />
Wednesday and we will make an announcement as to our position in the eleio on<br />
Thursday. At the moment I can say without pre-empting that announcement that as<br />
we stand here there is at least three major differences between the major perties as<br />
we go into this assessment process that we will complete in the next three clays.<br />
They are certainty for the protecton of one of Australia's great natural and cultural<br />
areas ie Cape York Peninsula, the issue of the: abandonrnerit of the Three Mines<br />
Uranium Policy which wa3 confirmed yesterday with the Coalition's release of their<br />
Energy and Resources Policy and if you believe ERA Ltd that means a big hole in the<br />
middle of Kakadu National Park and the undeierablity of the Coafition's environment<br />
package while it stays linked to Teistra. Unless there is a change In the next week,<br />
that is the basis upon which we will be prooedng up to our announcement on<br />
Thurdy.<br />
J: Mr Downey, is Cape York in your view the d~ tning environmental issue of this<br />
election campaign?<br />
JO: I would have to say that the field has been narrowed down a fair bit. Look, I really<br />
-think tiat we made it clear 12 months ago that Cape York Peninsula waS going to be<br />
a priority of ours in the lead up to the election. On behalf of the Australian<br />
Conservationi Foundation it has been a campaign that has at least been running for<br />
years and moved through mining at Shellboume Bay to the proposed space<br />
station in the late 1980s with The Wilderness Society, Starcke and Silver Plains etc,<br />
the land use strategy. It has been a long campaign. And for that reason, anid<br />
coupled with its significant heritage values, it is definitely a priority.<br />
As the field has got narroed down and as we have got into the eled~ ion, I think, from<br />
the ACF's perspective it has emerged as the major priority. But. let's not forget a big<br />
hole in the middle of Kakadu National Park i3 ilso a priority and whether or not<br />
$ 993 million of a Party's policies can acually be defivered is a major issue as well.<br />
1 19/ 02 ' 96 07: 55 </p>
<p>1' 9U/' 2660 1: 566 273 2923 PM1 PRESS OFFICE j01<br />
7<br />
J1: You seemed to be saying before that you think Labor is better equipped to deliver on<br />
Cape York, than the Uiberai Party or the Caartion.<br />
JD: Well, you see, the Coalition has got three problems, until they unhook from Telstra<br />
they can't fund it that is number one. Number two, they have got to get it past the<br />
Queensland National Party Federal Senators and Members, they have got to get it<br />
past Mr Borbidge who is on the record as saying ' That World Heritage is nothing but a<br />
disguise for a black land grab',-when referrng to Aboriginal people. And, thirdly,<br />
Mr Howard has got to hold some pretty, I wouid suggest, meaningful disaissions with<br />
the mining industry to be able to fund the heritage protecion in Cape York Peninsula.<br />
For those three or four reasons, not the least of which is the funding issue, I think the<br />
ALP is in front in terms of being able to deliver what will be a great conservation<br />
outcome.<br />
4: You almost seem to be advocating now a vote for Labor, don't you?<br />
JD: Well I am not advocaing a vote for Labor, I am drawing attention to the differences<br />
between the major parties. As I say, our announcement as to the elcto will be<br />
trade on Thursday, I don't get a vote, there are 37 other people who do. But I know<br />
weighing heavily in their minds, from discussions over the Last couple of days. the<br />
three things I have mentiooed Te~ sre, uranium, and Cape York are weighing<br />
heavily in their thin king.<br />
J: The Prime Minister was just sayin that Atis a big step forward. How far are we? Are<br />
we sort of half way there, a quarter of the way there? Is it achieving what soft of<br />
goals you would eventualy like to achieve? It is a long process. Obviously, these<br />
talks started in 1994<br />
JD: Well the argy bargy over Cape York. really, in terms of land use decisio making, has<br />
probably been going on for 20 years. To implement the agreemett I mean, therm are<br />
a number of steps that have to be done the funding is over four years. I think that is<br />
a reasonable amnount of time to progress the agreement, it is a reasonable amnount of<br />
time to get the pastoral Industry seurity on a sustainatle basis, to get te Woold<br />
Heritage assessments done, to get the nomigation in accss agreements for<br />
Aboriginal people. sorted out. You know, we do ha ve some time to go.<br />
This is a significant agreement and I am certainty, from the ACF's perspectie not<br />
going to suggest we rush the whole thing and got It over and done with in so: months.<br />
But, you know, we can spend a bit of time.<br />
J: What is the rough timnetable? Are you looking at, say, by 2000 and have the issues of<br />
Cape York resolved?<br />
JD; Look, I think, in the next term of the Parliamnent wouid be a fair timeframne, over the<br />
next three years.' I mean we are going to continue our discussions with Aboriginal<br />
fraditional owners and the Catiernen's Union. World Heritage assessments arm not<br />
small matters in themselves again. I rnean the World Heritage Bureau knocks back<br />
morm listings than wh~ at it accepts at the momenta. nd it has got to be done property<br />
and it has to be rigorous and that takes a bit of time.<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 07: 56Q017 </p>
<p>19/ 02 ' 96 07: 57 % Y õ 273 2923PM RESOFC 408<br />
J: I don't know if it is potsible. but can the Prime Minster respond to that as well? Does<br />
he expect it to be done in the term of the next Parliament?<br />
PM: The World Herftage risting. do you mean?<br />
J: To have the issues finalised yes, the nomination?<br />
PMV: Oh, I think. that is a reasonable aspiraton. -As Jim said, this is a matter which has<br />
drawn owtain peoples attention now over a couple of decades and there has been<br />
some substantial progress already been made. The other thing is, I( think, larnd care<br />
and suxtainable land use has become, you know, so broadly accepted now flowing<br />
from the Landcare program and the interests of people in agriculture in Australia that<br />
we are not dealing with the same sort of issues, I think, we were deal'ing with half a<br />
dozen years ago.<br />
In other words, I think, people now believe sustainability [ s important, it is an objective<br />
in itself, and Nf it is sustainable then proper land use management means that any<br />
heritae task becomes that much more achiSvable. And dt you have got agruement<br />
to do this you know, not just agreement, not just somne resigned agreement, but an<br />
actual w~ firngnes. s to do this and to be party to an arrangement like this I think, then it<br />
makes a very great difference about how quickly you can actually get these<br />
utrucu458 into place.<br />
J: Can I ask Noel Pearson a question? This agreement involved a lot of trust building<br />
between all the parties. Do you think the approach taken hems Is applicable in, say,<br />
WA and the NT where sorme of the disputes between parties have perhaps been<br />
even mome bitter there than they have been here?<br />
NP: Yes. . Iwant tosay thatIhave got agretdeal ofoptimism about thsgeementand<br />
about the direction, I think, we are leading the country in. When we passed the<br />
Native Title Act in late 1993, folowing the High Court's decision on, Mabo, I thought<br />
this is areybgopportun havnCaeYork e w rk hard. We havesa big<br />
opportunity, we have an apparatus in place that provides for claims to the National<br />
Nativ Title Tribunal and for a process of regional agreement if we can get the major<br />
players to come to common positions.<br />
So we had thi apparatus put in place in late 1993 that Provided so much promise, so<br />
much opportunity, so much cause for optimism. But I have got to say we are not<br />
Ongfl to capitallse on those opportunities and possibilities until the parties on the<br />
ground State Governments, regional Governments, Local Governments, industry<br />
organizations, loby groups, and Aboriginal people are prepared to put the wor pu. t<br />
the elbows the wheel, to make these opportunities materialise.<br />
And the Prime Minister said to me some timne ago,. that you know you are gOng to get<br />
agreement vrith these people if you frorit them, and you talk to them, and you come to<br />
compromises with them because that is the framework of the legislation that has<br />
been put in place.<br />
So I gave that route a try because we had a iigation grinding on in the courts with the<br />
Wick action and I gave the option of getting agreement with the Cattlemen's Union<br />
and the conservation groups, I gave that option a try, and I fronted at Musgrave a<br />
gmaiI rdftlp ntq$ nn in thp ri&amp; n Lf r~ f ~ rm PeriinattIn in tho m~ 1xrtf R fho<br />
. PM PRESS OFFICEQ018 </p>
<p>19/ 6' 019 0 76: 72 73 2923 PMX PRESS OFFICE 1<br />
9<br />
turmoil after th Qlueensland Government's -announcement of the East Coast<br />
conservation zone, a great deal of anxiety, confusion, anger, frustration, and on the<br />
Pori oi pasoralist and Abio mi-ai ' eo* i And fiew jio Mus~ rave and i rernember<br />
the charter ffying around and there was one hundred Toyotas parked out the front.<br />
And I was about the only Aboriginal person in that gathering.<br />
And by the end of -that meeting we had an unequivcl resolution from the<br />
Cattlemen's Union that we ' wre going to settle these things by negotiation. We were<br />
going to settle fthse things by negotiation founded on the principlee that the<br />
Cattlemen's Union had set out a year earlier. Those piinoiples were about mutual<br />
securtty, mutual benefit and mutual guarantee of rffesyle and culture.<br />
And we got Rick Farley involved, and we worked -over a two to three month period to<br />
put together the Heads of Agreemoent that we are now all conmitted to.<br />
I have gotto syttaksa great dea ofwork, ittakes agreat dealf goowl1 and I<br />
am just very pleased that the ldnd of promise and fah and optimism I had about the<br />
Mabo decision and about the enactment of the Native Title Legislation, has yielded<br />
fruit positive fruit in Far North Queensland. And it is fruit that we, as organisations,<br />
on the ground are determined to hold, notwithstanding an of the politcal vagaries.<br />
I have got to say that It is the route of agreement, rather than litigation is just one of<br />
the two routes available under the Native Tie apparatus. We now need to go<br />
through the next step of forrmalising agreements between lease holders and<br />
traditional owners for accss arrangements and for the settlement of these issues<br />
relating to Native Titie.<br />
Two weeks ago, ithere was a High Court Decision in yaspedt of the Wasnyi peoples in<br />
the Gulf a( Carpentaria where the High Court was asked by the Aboriginal dlaimants<br />
and by the various parties to the litigation, asked' to determine the question of pastoral<br />
leases and Native Titie. And the High Couts view wa that we have an apparatus in<br />
the Native Title Act that provides for mediation and negotiation. An apparatus that<br />
doesn't arbitrarily extinguish Native Title, it leaves that question for the court, to<br />
determine. But it provide a proes of mediation and negotiation to settle these<br />
issues. So, basicaly, the leadership of the High Court has been to you hrave an<br />
apparatus, you have a process, go and work out those things through compromise<br />
I use N you are going to come through litigation to the High Court. there will be<br />
losers. if you are -going to come through litigation in the High Court, there will be<br />
losers.<br />
So there was a sieven-rul judgment in favour of the negotiation and compromise route<br />
and I beleve that we have identified in this Heads of Agreement a compromise that<br />
wil work best onf the ground In Cape York Peninsula, that provides security for John<br />
Purceirs mob, for my mob and also secures the national interest in conseration<br />
hefit" g.<br />
So. I think, that I suppose not having participated In the debate down sot and<br />
over the past two years, I have been buried up heme tyng to work on this agreement<br />
am a bit dismayed about the cynidsm that seems to pervade the country, about the<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 07: 57Q019 </p>
<p>19/ 02 ' 96 07: 58 V~ 61 6 273 2923PM RESOFC02<br />
real possibilities that lie within our grasp, the real potentials and possibilities that lie<br />
within our grasp.<br />
And I have got to say that those possibilities .0aim<br />
prelared to butt heads and come to corn prrni~ c* arid, i thiink, U-ic C-Opc York<br />
agrevitr coming around a torturous route to answer your question I think this<br />
agreement can be a model for other areas in. the country. Bt one of the great<br />
impediments to reaching the stage where we have reached, is the political reluctance<br />
of regional Governments.<br />
I mean had we had intervention at the Stete Government level, we would never have<br />
reached the stage we have reached now. We have come to this point because for<br />
commercial, social, cultural reasons, just the, relationship with people who Wie in<br />
Cowan, blein and white people who have to live with each other in Cooktowri. Those<br />
are the imperatives that have led to us coming to this compromise and Kf we had<br />
listened to the machintions and advice of people living in Brisbane, then I don't think<br />
we would have reached this mzge.<br />
And, I think, that it does involve leaerhip, it does involve leadership from the<br />
Aborlglnsai community, from the pstoral industry community, end importantly, I think.<br />
from the conservation movement We have taught the conservationists something<br />
about coming to compromise because we are not going to secure a comprehensive<br />
conservation and sustainble development reguie for the Peninsula unbi we<br />
understand. in the rest of Australia, that these things need to be done in cooperation<br />
with the land owners and the people who live in the region.<br />
So I am extrem* l pleased to see that the country and I could never have imagined<br />
this could have been the case two or three years ago, and I am very pleased that<br />
here in Far Nofth Queensland notwithstanding anything that might happen outside<br />
of the region that we have reached this state -of affairs with the Cattlemen's Union,<br />
The Wilernes Society' and the Australian Conservation Foundation.<br />
I think that issues in the Kinberleys in Western Australia, etsewhere in Queensland.<br />
that we provife at an example of the way to settle these land use questkons.<br />
Isu~ ppose the issue that I am most concerned about in terms of the implementation of<br />
this agreem ent, relate to two questions. One is, what will happen with mining in a few<br />
key regions in Cape York Peninsula. They are really key questionts of great concern<br />
to the Aboriginal community.<br />
Mining at Shellboumne Bay, in particular, is an Issue of great concern. We would be<br />
concerned that, all politial parties commit themnselves to rullng out minoing on<br />
Sheliboumne Bay.<br />
Secondly, the other question we ae very concerned about 13 the arbitrary wthoWlee<br />
extinguishment of Native Title in pastoral leases. We believe that the question of<br />
Native Title in pastoral looses can and should be addressed as the High Court said at<br />
could be through the apparatus of the Native Trtle Act, through mediation and<br />
negotiation. I am extremely coincered by comments from Richard Court that there is a Coaliton<br />
PX PRESS OFFICEa02O </p>
<p>19/' 6019 0 76: 92 73 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE j2<br />
11<br />
concerned about Mr ichers recent statements that seem to confirm the existence<br />
of this bidden agenda.<br />
I can tell you that the Catflemen showed the fakh in Cape York Peninsula that we can<br />
settle this question of Native Title through negotiation and we accepted tha good<br />
faith. And it was an agreement that came to pas notwithstanding the legal change<br />
and the political changes. Like one week, we had a negative decision from Juctice<br />
Drummond this was about three Yweeks, ago. -Justice Drummond said, There is no<br />
Native Title in pastoral leases'. And I thought, oh, shit. John Purcell is going to walk<br />
away from this agreemnent now. He has got what he wants. he is gone. Butno, he<br />
said, ' We are sticking by the termis of this agreement.<br />
The next week, the High Court ruled that the whole question is still afive. The whole<br />
question of Native Title and pastoral leases was still allve. So I immediately wrote to<br />
John and said, listen, we are sticking to the terms of this agreement, there is no kind<br />
of grabbing ours and running. And I have got to say thet I want to publy commit<br />
myself to sticking by the terms of this agreement, notwithstanding the legal and<br />
political changes that might happen. Thank you.<br />
J lIam just wondering 9f 1culd ask you Mr Purcell hoW does tlIs oompare with the<br />
regional proposal of the Goes Government that involved 11 properties? Is this a<br />
wider thing now, are there more properties involved and will this make the task more<br />
compficated, can you get their agreement? 7<br />
JP: Yes, just to answe r your question. Obviusly, the East Coast wlderness, as proposed<br />
by Premier Goss prior to the election on 15 July, is somnething that we couldn't come<br />
to agreement amongst the parties, it was set " sdo-But wm have been able to<br />
resolve to our sabtiadion the situetion as far as the people we repreit and the<br />
Department of the Environment, Herftae, and Lands. Mu what the attitude of the<br />
incom ing Government is on that zone I don't know.<br />
Burt I guess in common with others, I would like to address the broader question<br />
about this agreement. The firvt thing I would say is we~ are not about party polfdcs, we<br />
aro-not about saying this side is better than the other side we are about an outcome<br />
for the people within the Cape York Peninsula area.<br />
And as Noel Pearson has said, we have achieved by the signing of this Heads of<br />
Agreement a situation that spells out the principles of the pastoralists, of the<br />
Aboriginal communities, and of the environmentalists, that is above poitics and is<br />
above the decision of the High Court, the Federal Court, or any other court of appeal.<br />
The catle industry in Cape York Peninsula is currentty in a state of declne. The<br />
signing of this agreement, in my view. brings a much brighter fute for the cattle<br />
industry. What we have* got to reconise in this country is that we have got to<br />
genierate export income and we have got to pay our bill internatinally and,<br />
therefore, vm have got to have export earning capacity.<br />
Cape York Peninsula with its d~ ose proximity to South East Asia olfers that to the<br />
cattle industry and if we can exercise live cattl trade through the port at Weipa. that<br />
is crtainly one way to go, and that is supplemented by the increase in consumption<br />
of manufactured and proesed beef out of this country.<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 07: 59[ a 021 </p>
<p>19/ 0 619 6 068 : 02 73 2923 PH PRESS OFFICElih 022<br />
12<br />
The other thing I would rike to say. probabl the most contentious issue that we have<br />
had to face in this whole debate, is the question of World Heritage. World Heritage, in<br />
my view, has a place but the stments that have been made Irrespnalbty by some<br />
peopthattewhoe ofe apewasing tobe locked upand put under Word<br />
Heritage is just so much rot.<br />
The process of ahieving registration of World Heritage, has to go through a torturous<br />
program. -There are areas. of significant conservartion values In the.. Cape. we<br />
recognise that, and they should be protected. I think you have also got to realise that<br />
there is a very firmn commitmient in the Heads of Agrerement that outlines that World<br />
Heritage itseff does not necessarily mean the exclusion of the livestock industry. In<br />
our notes accmpanyig that Heeds of Agreement, multiple land use is crty speft<br />
out. Now just in condlusion, I think, that what this has done is brought together parties with<br />
diverging views, we have done it in a very short period of time, whereas the courts<br />
haven't been able to decide it, whereas the pliticins :. with all due raspedt have not<br />
also been eble to-tie ittogether, I thinkthat wat whav done is set in place a<br />
principle that will have application in other areas: lB. A the factors in other arees are<br />
going to be very. different than that in Cape York. u<br />
The Heads of Agreement thst we have come to in [ Cape York Peninsula, address the<br />
various problems and challenges that we have got tq fae in the Cape and, I think.<br />
that all of the signatories have said here today that we are all clearly going to stick<br />
that agreemeit and the safeguards for all of the parties are built in.<br />
And I would just, again, like to put on recrd the fedt that all of us enitered theme<br />
discussions in good-faith and with trust In spite of mischief from outside sources that<br />
tried to divie tesignatodes, we are rock solid on what we have signed and there is<br />
a lot of mrischief based on misunderstanding and I hope that we can get the message<br />
out to people that thssnot about Wcing up the Cape, itis notabout ocking out the<br />
beef cate industry. But, rather, it is something that we have put together for the wvelbeing<br />
of the people in the Cape and tha is our bottom fine and we are happy to party<br />
to the agreemient:<br />
4: Mr Purcel, would you agree with Mr Pearson th; t this could be a model for other<br />
areas of Australia?<br />
JP: Yes, I do. But I would again agree vrith Noei that particular circumstances in the<br />
Cape Wil probably differ to cirumstances that exist in the Gulf region of Queensland,<br />
or in, the Kimberteys. There are differenit players, there are different attitudes and<br />
there wre also differenit problems.<br />
J: Mr Keating, can I just ask you a question on another subject? Mr Howard has today<br />
made an enormous pith for families with a $ 1 billoi tax bonus for families. Can<br />
Labor match this?.<br />
PM: Well that is cynical and unacrpulous because he is happy to play a confidence trick<br />
on Australian families with promises he knows he can't possibl fun~ d. He has no<br />
hope of ever delivering and to be doing this at this point in his politicatl career, in<br />
desperation to try and win an elecion, says nothing I think about the integrity of him<br />
rnr $ ha I O) tamI Pat~ v<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 08: 00 </p>
<p>'' 61 6 273 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE<br />
13<br />
J: So is this a lest minute ditch by him to grab the family vote?<br />
PM: Yes, well it is a very late policy speech adkiti; eYt rh.-last minute ditch around<br />
a cynical ploy that has no chance of, ever, woming to rcality.<br />
J: Can I just ask Mr Purcell another question? Does the Native Title Act still need<br />
amending then to dcear up whet have been called anomalies, difficulties, with regard<br />
to pastoral leases?<br />
JP: My understanding is, and I am not into the politics of course, but both the<br />
Government and the Opposition have said that the Native Tfitle does require some<br />
amendments.<br />
ends<br />
19/ 02 ' 96 08: 01U023 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
