<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9044</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP. -CNN-WORLD BUSINESS TONIGHT SEATTLE, U.S.A - THURSDAY 18 NOVEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009044.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IPRIME MINISTER<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME NMSTER, THE HON P J<br />
KEATING, M. P. CNN WORLD BUSINESS TONIGHT<br />
SEATTLE, USA THURSDAY 18 NOVEMBER, 1993<br />
J: Mr Prime Minister, APEC is being asked by the Eminent Person's Group to<br />
convert into what it calls a true Asia-Pacific Economic Community. Is this kind<br />
of a economic repudiation of Europe that is turning inward these days?<br />
PM: I don't think so, it's just that the great preponderance of United States trade is in<br />
the Pacific already. $ 300 billion of U. S. trade is in the Pacific and $ 200 billion is<br />
in the Atlantic. The $ 200 billion is growing slowly and the $ 300 billion is<br />
growing quite rapidly. And there is the possibility of increasing the velocity of<br />
trade and investment. And APEC is about that. It's about open regionalism. It's<br />
not a block and it's certainly not a Treaty of Rome arrangement.<br />
J: Would you want to see it become a block though?<br />
PM: No, I think that the benefits really are in the opening up and in doing things which<br />
some of the Asia-Pacific economies don't quite have. That is, for investors being<br />
able to litigate their property rights; being able to litigate equity issues; to<br />
standardise products; to standardise professional standards; to establish funds<br />
management arrangements all the things that many countries in the area don't<br />
have. So that's what APEC's about. It's about, how do we improve the whole<br />
trading and investment climate of the Asia-Pacific? How do we make a good<br />
thing better?<br />
J: Australia so often likes to say it's part of Asia. You're not really, you're on the<br />
edge of the Pacific. Why do you want to be part of Asia?<br />
PM: We don't. We are not an Asian country but we are part of Asia. And three<br />
quarters of our exports go to the APEC area, already. See, one of the things about<br />
APEC which I think isn't quite understood is that it's even more integrated than </p>
<p>NAFTA or the European Community. It trades with itself in a more concentrated<br />
way than those two areas. 66% of APEC's trade is from member countries. The<br />
same figure is 61 for Europe and about 42% for NAFTA. So this is already a<br />
highly integrated area and Australia has very large trading arrangements with<br />
Japan, with Korea, with other countries in the area. So, we're a natural for it. But<br />
we say the U. S. is too because so much of its potential growth will be linked to<br />
the Pacific.<br />
J: Would Australia be more acceptable to Asia than it is now if you broke ties with<br />
the British Monarchy?<br />
PM: I don't know about more acceptable but we'd be more as we are. That is, Australia<br />
is now a multicultural country, we would be representing ourselves more as we<br />
are rather than as some derivative which still has as a Head of State the Queen of<br />
Great Britain. The person who should be the Head of State of Australia should be<br />
an Australian person.<br />
J: Do you intend to step up your proposed timetable, particularly as a result of<br />
winning the Olympics? For the year 2000 I think you've talked about the year<br />
2000.<br />
PM: Well, the Olympics are on in October or November of the year 2000 and it is the<br />
centenary of Federation in January in the year 2001 so there's only three months<br />
of difference and in speaking about one, ipso facto we're speaking about the other.<br />
J: Do you think you'll be able to pull this off<br />
PM: Well, I think so. I think there's a good debate running in Australia now, about<br />
this. And I think seven years gives us plenty of time to consider all the issues and<br />
make such a change.<br />
J: Tell me a little about the state of the Australian economy. You're having an<br />
extremely, stubbornly slow recovery. What is it going to take to get your<br />
economy really growing?<br />
PM: Oh, it's not that slow. We're growing as fast as the United States or faster. We're<br />
growing at around 3% at the moment and we've been doing that growing<br />
between 2% and 3% for the last 18 months. We've got inflation at around 2%,<br />
we've got exports booming, we've got a very big pick-up in consumer sentiment.<br />
So all the signs are there. But, of course, what we won't have is the silly lending<br />
of the eighties. The same thing you won't have now. We're going to have a<br />
recovery which is non-inflationary, firmly based, no crazy credit growth but </p>
<p>-3-<br />
focusing on innovative products, elaborately transformed goods and services<br />
and a very large part of it going to Asia.<br />
J: One final question. How are you going to reduce Australia's dependence on<br />
overseas capital?<br />
PM: Well, by lifting our domestic savings, the same thing you're doing here. The same<br />
thing the President is doing. That is, we are pulling the public sector back to a<br />
very modest deficit in a couple of years time. And we've also encouraged a<br />
national pension scheme. We have now, at this stage, got every employee in the<br />
country contributing 5% of their income to long term pension arrangements. This<br />
will become 10% over time, over the next few years, half dozen years. This will<br />
put an enormous stock of savings into Australia. It's one of the ways we think we<br />
can grow faster without growing our current account deficit.<br />
J: Thank you very much. Paul Keating, Prime Minister of Australia.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
