<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9382</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP - COMMONWEALTH CULTURAL POLICY LAUNCH TUESDAY 18 OCTOBER</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009382.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MIPCOMMONWEALTH<br />
CULTURAL POLICY LAUNCH<br />
TUESDAY 18 OCTOBER<br />
This is a very great pleasure.<br />
No government has ever delivered a national cultural<br />
policy for Australia on anything like these dimensions.<br />
I'm not sure many national governments in other countries<br />
have delivered cultural statements.<br />
The Americans are in the process of formulating one at<br />
the moment for delivery towards the end of the century,<br />
I understand.<br />
We need this statement.<br />
As the document says, it is long overdue.<br />
We have had a cultural debate running in this country for<br />
a very long time.<br />
our post-colonial status guaranteed that there would be a<br />
lot of questions asked about who we are, what level ofculture<br />
we might reasonably aspire to, whether we should<br />
be transplanting European culture or fostering an<br />
indigenous one, what the worth of such a strange hybrid<br />
would be.<br />
These arguments run right through our history in this<br />
century.<br />
At the extremes it was " evening dress and the opera"<br />
versus the " wattle and bottle".<br />
Anglophilia and Anglophobia.<br />
The debate tended to lurch between the cultural cringe<br />
and cultural swagger.<br />
It has taken us a long while to find what Robert Hughes<br />
recently called " a relaxed uprightness of carriage."<br />
The two extremes don't make much sense. </p>
<p>Both are narrow, both inclined to xenophobia.<br />
And both fatally missed the point that our development<br />
was bound to reflect the accumulation of cultures which<br />
of necessity an immigrant society creates and that from<br />
such variety great riches flow.<br />
The simplest truths can be the hardest to grasp.<br />
The idea that a cosmopolitan Australia might be a<br />
worthwhile aspiration and not a nightmare was a long time<br />
coming. To imagine a culturally diverse Australia and enjoy the<br />
idea meant overturning a lot of received wisdom.<br />
The notion that we were a country without history, for<br />
instance. It meant recognising that, far from lacking history and<br />
culture, we were the beneficiaries of an extraordinary<br />
heritage: that settlers in Australia, whether they<br />
arrived from Great Britain and Ireland in the nineteenth<br />
century, or Europe, or the Middle East or Asia in the<br />
twentieth century no settlers in this country ever<br />
entirely left their culture behind.<br />
To recognise that was to recognise the depth of our<br />
history and heritage.<br />
And in the last twenty years we have recognised it.<br />
Essentially, I think that is what multiculturalism means.<br />
We have recognised that from new settlers we can derive<br />
more than raw energy, skills and ambition there is a<br />
cultural dividend.<br />
In recent years we have also come to the realisation that<br />
it is our great good fortune to share in the magnificent<br />
heritage of the oldest civilisation on earth.<br />
These are watersheds in our cultural development.<br />
It has been truly a sea change the tide of our national<br />
consciousness has turned.<br />
And nothing, it seems to me, has done more to free us<br />
from our insecurities.<br />
Yet recognising the great wealth of culture we have<br />
inherited cannot obscure or deny the fact that culture is<br />
built in large part on the experience of the last two<br />
hundred years of living in this continent.<br />
Our traditions are still firmly fixed in that experience,<br />
and they remain alive in our art and literature and film. </p>
<p>3<br />
That is a heritage which we must preserve, a set of<br />
recognisably Australian values which must continue to<br />
inform the creative life of the nation.<br />
That these intangible things are powerful forces in the<br />
national life might be measured by the inclination of<br />
Australians to watch Australian television shows, or read<br />
Australian books.<br />
You might see it in the huge success of the Golden<br />
Summers exhibition a few years ago, or films like<br />
Strictly Ballroom, or at another level the impact<br />
which the Entombment of the Unknown Australian Soldier<br />
had on the nation last year.<br />
Australians do still read Henry Lawson and Banjo<br />
Paterson.<br />
They do still look at Streeton and Roberts.<br />
They still love them.<br />
But these days they know there is so much more in the<br />
cupboard.<br />
And what is so encouraging these days is the new<br />
confidence the unashamed enthusiasm.<br />
It distinguishes some of those recent films.<br />
It was there in some of the acts I have seen yesterday<br />
and today.<br />
It is there in the reviews the Australian Ballet just<br />
received in Washington.<br />
I wouldn't want to pretend to argue the finer points of<br />
dance technique with Clive Barnes.<br />
I am very pleased that he finds them technically in the<br />
forefront of the world's ballet companies.<br />
I like that, but I love it when he says that they have " a<br />
very real spirit, an individuality that is fresh and open<br />
and quite original.<br />
It is the sort of energy and open freshness that people<br />
associate with Australia itself."<br />
I find myself pleased to hear Clive Barnes approving of<br />
our dancers and absolutely delighted to think that our<br />
dancers might convey to the world the message that there<br />
is a great optimistic spirit at large in Australia.<br />
The first is satisfying, the second is moving. </p>
<p>4<br />
Creative Nation does not attempt to impose a cultural<br />
landscape on Australia but to respond to one which is<br />
already in bloom.<br />
I hope that in time this statement will be seen as the<br />
day we drew a line under our post-colonial era and said<br />
good-bye to it.<br />
I don't think we should look back in anger to the<br />
generations who conducted the cultural debate in that<br />
era.<br />
We've come by stages to where we are and a lot of<br />
cultural wealth has come with us.<br />
We may even be a lot wiser for having been through the<br />
cringe, and even censorship.<br />
Just the same, as the statement says, today I hope we are<br />
also saying a final goodbye to all those manifestations<br />
of cultural insecurity including cultural jingoism.<br />
And goodbye forever to the days when our best talents<br />
left Australia because there was not enough here to<br />
persuade them to stay.<br />
The statement is not about looking back.<br />
It is very much an attempt to lay the foundations of a<br />
new era: to pull the threads of our national life<br />
together, so that we can ride the waves of global change<br />
and create our own.<br />
I've said elsewhere that as a government our great<br />
ambition has been to bring cultural issues into the<br />
mainstream of our national life, and national decisionmaking.<br />
That's why, for instance, we brought the arts into the<br />
Cabinet, and subsequently combined the arts with the<br />
Department of Communications.<br />
We emphatically believe that cultural issues should be at<br />
the core.<br />
on the one hand, this is because no economic or social<br />
decision is without a cultural consequence.<br />
The quality of our lives, the opportunities for self<br />
expression, the integrity of our heritage cannot be left<br />
to chance.<br />
They can no longer be the last consideration.<br />
That, it seems to me, is one of the responsibilities of a<br />
mature country and one of the imperatives in this era<br />
of globalisation and the information revolution. </p>
<p>On the other hand, we are putting cultural issues at the<br />
centre because the more we succeed in encouraging a<br />
creative spirit and the flow of creative ideas, the more<br />
we will succeed as an economy and society.<br />
There are huge economic benefits to flow from a confident<br />
and secure, innovative and imaginative culture.<br />
And direct social benefits direct national benefits.<br />
There are still a few people who believe that culture<br />
belongs on the margins.<br />
We take this opportunity to say that they are wrong.<br />
This statement does not cover every element in our<br />
national life.<br />
It does not go to every city and every community.<br />
But we hope it signals our intention.<br />
It is a national policy.<br />
It will have a national effect a national benefit.<br />
The statement aims at excellence at creating the<br />
conditions in which Australian talent can reach the<br />
highest standards and Australians can ejy the highest<br />
standards.<br />
No cultural policy could aim at anything less.<br />
The statement is also concerned with access at making<br />
our arts and heritage accessible to everyone.<br />
We aim to do this through partnerships with State and<br />
other levels of government and through private<br />
benefaction wherever possible.<br />
As an example of the pursuit of excellence we are<br />
creating with the Victorian Government a National Academy<br />
of Music in Melbourne.<br />
A school of music of the highest standards for students<br />
from Australia and overseas.<br />
With the Queensland Government we are establishing the<br />
National Indigenous Performing Arts Institute, a centre<br />
of excellence to preserve and foster Australia's unique<br />
indigenous art forms and heritage.<br />
Here in Canberra, in association with the ACT government,<br />
the Gallery of Aboriginal Australia will be established<br />
on the Acton Peninsula on the shores of Lake Burley<br />
Griffin. </p>
<p>6<br />
The Gallery will be co-located with new premises for the<br />
Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait<br />
Islander Studies.<br />
I should here pay tribute to Rosemary Follett for her<br />
initiative and vision, and not just so far as the Gallery<br />
of Aboriginal Australia is concerned.<br />
Here at the NGA, the ACT governent will partner the<br />
Commonwealth in the construction of a purpose-built<br />
exhibition space to house major national and<br />
international exhibitions.<br />
In the pursuit of both excellence and access to it, we<br />
will continue to develop the National Museum in ways<br />
which will enable maximum public access to the nation's<br />
cultural heritage, through a combination of touring and<br />
use of new multimedia.<br />
New museum gateways are being developed at Old Parliament<br />
House Canberra, and Sydney Customs House.<br />
In time I hope the National Museum will be an umbrella<br />
organisation which provides access to the holdings of all<br />
our national collecting institutions.<br />
The National Sound and Film Archive is the repository for<br />
much of Australia's audio visual history and therefore a<br />
unique and valuable history of the evolvement of<br />
century Australia.<br />
The premises which the Archives currently occupies do not<br />
provide an adequate facility from which these treasures<br />
can be viewed or heard by large numbers of visitors.<br />
We will rectify the difficulty that the archives<br />
presently faces of a shortage of exhibition, display and<br />
laboratory space.<br />
In Melbourne the Australian Cultural Foundation will be<br />
established to gather more effectively into the cultural<br />
development of Australia the humanities and social<br />
sciences.<br />
To give the Foundation a firm base from which to start it<br />
will operate as part of the Australia Council, at the<br />
same time providing the Council with a Melbourne<br />
presence. The Australia Council continues to be pivotal in the<br />
nation's artistic life and cultural development.<br />
It has played a crucial role in our reaching the levels<br />
of excellence and wide participation in the arts we<br />
currently enjoy.<br />
Important though it is, it cannot however continue to be<br />
merely a grant giving body. </p>
<p>7<br />
The Commonwealth believes that the Australia Council must<br />
now spend more of its resources in audience development,<br />
creating linkages with new broadcasting technologies,<br />
market development here and abroad and in stimulating<br />
more participation in the arts from the private sector.<br />
The Government is confident the Council is determined to<br />
take up the challenge but recognises it cannot hope to<br />
succeed without additional funds.<br />
We want a Council which continues to do the things it<br />
presently does so well: so we are providing an increase<br />
in base Council funding of $ 18 million over four years,<br />
particularly to assist individual artists.<br />
This will also help to meet the cost of increased wage<br />
obligations caused by a recent arbitrated wage increase<br />
for actors and dancers.<br />
But we want it to do more and that is why, among other<br />
things, we are introducing triennial funding, and a new<br />
major organisations board.<br />
We have long recognised the need for the Council and its<br />
clients to operate in an atmosphere of stability and<br />
predictability so that they may undertake better forward<br />
planning in the same way as any other business enterprise<br />
does. The Council has already done some preliminary work to<br />
identify organisations which will be funded through the<br />
new board, and I expect that they will be announced<br />
shortly. The Government continues to believe adamantly in the<br />
principles of peer assessment and arms length funding-so<br />
it will not be intervening in the selection process,<br />
though the Minister will be consulted.<br />
However, it is reasonable to expect that two<br />
organisations which will become part of the MOB are the<br />
Australian Chamber Orchestra and the Sydney Symphony<br />
Orchestra. The ACO is an orchestra of international quality, and a<br />
world leader in its field.<br />
The Sydney Symphony Orchestra, we also believe has the<br />
potential to be one of the great international<br />
orchestras. In keeping with other truly great orchestras, the SSO<br />
will be allowed to operate under its own local control<br />
allowed to draw on the resources, enthusiasm and<br />
character of Sydney. </p>
<p>8<br />
The Commonwealth will maintain its funding in real terms,<br />
but through the Major Organisations Board of the<br />
Australia Council, rather than the ABC.<br />
The Government will also be providing additional<br />
assistance to augment the Orchestra to full international<br />
size and enable it to enhance its current touring and<br />
recording program.<br />
By agreement, the Orchestra will also maintain<br />
facilitational and media linkages with the ABC.<br />
We have begun with the Sydney Symphony Orchestra.<br />
The way is open, however, for the other orchestras to<br />
follow if they wish.<br />
If these initiatives are taken in the pursuit of<br />
excellence, several others announced in this policy will<br />
create access to excellence in music for many thousands<br />
of Australians.<br />
There are extra funds provided for Musica Viva's schools<br />
program enabling it to tour Australia wide.<br />
We are also providing extra funds for opera on tour.<br />
In another initiative, calculated to join music to our<br />
national life, I am pleased to announce today the<br />
Commonwealth will provide a prize of $ 100,000 for an<br />
original symphony to commemorate the centenary of our<br />
nationhood in the year 2001.<br />
Film and television production constitute another great<br />
success story of our recent history.<br />
No other medium, perhaps, offers ordinary Australians<br />
such insights and access to the national character,<br />
heritage and identity.<br />
And no other medium carries the image of Australia so<br />
pervasively abroad.<br />
The film and television industry is a vital resource, an<br />
essential element of the national culture.<br />
Australians have demonstrated their desire to see more<br />
Australian product on screen, and Australian producers<br />
have amply demonstrated their capacity to deliver quality<br />
programs, provided funds are available.<br />
Therefore, the Government will establish a special<br />
Television Production Fund providing $ 20 million per<br />
annum for three years from the next financial year. </p>
<p>The Fund, which will be located in Melbourne, will<br />
support the production of Australian drama, children's<br />
programs, documentaries and the developing and marketing<br />
and multimedia applications.<br />
It is aimed expressly at the quality end of the film and<br />
television market.<br />
At least 50 per cent of the Fund will be available to<br />
independent producers, the balance will go to the<br />
networks for in-house productions.<br />
And productions financed from this Fund will not count<br />
towards existing Australian content quota requirements.<br />
SBS too has suffered from a shortage of production funds<br />
and has had to rely increasingly on overseas material<br />
which does not of itself reflect the Australian<br />
multicultural community.<br />
The Government, therefore, will provide $ 13 million over<br />
four years to SBS to commission high quality Australian<br />
programs. This will enable SBS to utilise the language skills base<br />
of contemporary Australian society and make programs for<br />
sale into Asian and European markets.<br />
I am also pleased to announce today that after<br />
negotiations with the Commonwealth Government and subject<br />
to the settlement of some final details, The News<br />
Corporation Limited and its film production company,<br />
Century Fox, have agreed to establish a movie studio in<br />
Australia to produce major international length feature<br />
films. The establishment of the studio offers large potential<br />
benefits to Australia.<br />
With distributional links through Fox and other world<br />
distributors, Australia can become a larger part of the<br />
world trade in entertainment, while establishing itself<br />
as a hub for content in the rapidly growing Asia-Pacific<br />
markets. Linkages with internationally integrated multimedia<br />
companies will also help Australia become a greater<br />
participant in the burgeoning markets for content that<br />
will be carried over the world's information highways.<br />
The planned facility will include three sophisticated<br />
sound stages equal to any in the world, with all the<br />
associated pre and post production facilities.<br />
The studios will be available to independent Australian<br />
film makers and are expected to attract independent<br />
production companies from overseas. </p>
<p>S-*<br />
The Commonwealth Goverrnent and 20th Century Fox have<br />
discussed locations for the studio in Sydney and believe<br />
the Showground site to be the most suitable this, of<br />
course, is a matter for discussion with the<br />
government. The Commonwealth will assist with site preparation and<br />
development. Our cultural policy directly addresses the challenges<br />
which confront Australia in realms of information<br />
technology and multimedia.<br />
It was in recognition of these challenges that the<br />
portfolios of Communications and the Arts were combined.<br />
The move was made to deal with the convergence of<br />
broadcasting, telecommunications, computing and creative<br />
industries and technologies.<br />
It is true that we have in Australia one of the more<br />
advanced telecommunications networks in the world, and<br />
there has been substantial investment in our information<br />
highway. Australians will have access to the interactive<br />
multimedia which is already changing our lives and<br />
creating extraordinary new possibilities in education,<br />
the arts and information; the way we learn; the way we do<br />
business. In 1993 the Commonwealth established the Broadband<br />
Services Expert Group to report on the implications for<br />
Australia of developments in multimedia and broadband<br />
services.<br />
The group nominated content as the critical issue for-<br />
Australia. Indeed Australia has the opportunity to become a world<br />
leader in the production of content.<br />
We can, for instance, if we move rapidly, gain a<br />
significant share of the CD-ROM market.<br />
In the longer term though not very much longer we can<br />
create a dynamic multimedia industry in Australia.<br />
our strengths in film and television, literature, music<br />
and art, in combination with our highly educated<br />
population, give us an excellent platform on which to<br />
build.<br />
Multimedia thus creates the potential for expanding our<br />
cultural industries.<br />
It provides new opportunities for people especially<br />
young people with creative talent. </p>
<p>So that we can take full advantage of the opportunities<br />
open to us, and guarantee that we enter the 21st century<br />
in the front rank of nations, the Government has<br />
announced in the cultural policy five specific and<br />
complementary measures costing $ 84 million over a five<br />
year period.<br />
We will establish a coordinating body known as the<br />
Australian Multimedia Enterprise; several Multimedia<br />
Development Centres; and a series of national Multimedia<br />
Forums.<br />
We will also be commissioning CD-ROMS involving material<br />
from our major cultural institutions for Australian<br />
schools.<br />
And we will provide specific assistance to foster our<br />
film agencies move into multimedia.<br />
If we are to rely on talented Australians using their<br />
imagination and creativity to provide us with the content<br />
for new media, we have to ensure that they get a fair<br />
return for their efforts.<br />
You will find in the document a range of measures that<br />
we've taken to protect the intellectual property of our<br />
content providers.<br />
As this launch is taking place in the National Gallery,<br />
it is particularly appropriate to mention one of them<br />
the Government will be providing $ 1 million to assist<br />
with the setting up of Viscopy a copyright collecting<br />
agency for the visual arts.<br />
This copyright society will ensure that artists,<br />
including Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander artist&amp;,<br />
whose work is particularly prone to unauthorised use,<br />
will obtain a proper financial return for the use of<br />
their work.<br />
With the growing ability to reproduce visual images<br />
through digitised technology, an increasing source of<br />
income for our artists will be the fees collected from<br />
such reproduction.<br />
This policy has taken some time to formulate.<br />
That is no bad thing.<br />
We think it will boost the quality of Australian life now<br />
and in the future.<br />
It will boost the creative element in our national life.<br />
It will create new cultural industries.<br />
It will mean more work and opportunities for Australian<br />
artists, writers and other creative people. </p>
<p>12<br />
It will make us a more cohesive country.<br />
It will enrich us for years to come.<br />
I hope it will be seen as a landmark a moment which we<br />
confirmed our faith in the life we have built here, and<br />
our ability to meet the challenges which the future<br />
holds. In the preparation, many people deserve our thanks.<br />
Not least among them was the Cultural Advisory Panel we<br />
appointed and who provided, in a sense, the kernel of the<br />
Statement. It has grown like Topsy since but their report was an<br />
essential starting point, and I thank them for their<br />
efforts and wisdom.<br />
I must also thank the three Ministers who preceded<br />
Michael Lee David Simmons, Wendy Fatin and Bob<br />
McMullan.<br />
And I must thank Michael for his contribution.<br />
Many Australians contributed to the formulation of the<br />
policy through the submissions they made to the<br />
Government, and through their attendance at public<br />
forums.<br />
There are many others.<br />
Most of all I want to thank the creative artists of<br />
Australia and I mean all of them, from the stars and<br />
the major organisations to the people in communities all<br />
over Australia who engage in works which enrich theirlives<br />
and countless others.<br />
This cultural policy of necessity has addressed some of<br />
the great questions now facing Australia.<br />
And, by and large, that is what I have addressed in this<br />
speech today.<br />
But you will find there is a good deal in this policy for<br />
all those engaged in the creative life of the country a<br />
good deal I truly believe for all Australians.<br />
With this policy we have set out to devise a better<br />
creative climate in Australia.<br />
With it we recognise the value of creative effort and<br />
what it means to our future.<br />
We are spending $ 252 million to build the infrastructure,<br />
boost the funds, create the industries which will employ<br />
and reward creative effort. </p>
<p>This statement goes a long way towards bringing culture<br />
and creativity into the mainstream.<br />
The opportunities will be there in the future. The<br />
openings will be there for talent and industry.<br />
It will be a new environment, and one in which success<br />
will depend less on governments and more on the creative<br />
initiatives of Australians.<br />
We will all be richer for the effort all so much more<br />
aware of what it means to be Australian.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
