<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12133</transcript-id>
    <title>Shoalhaven Cadets</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that the Commonwealth will provide $63,000 for the establishment of a new cadets project in the Shoalhaven.</p>
<p>The project involves a partnership between community organisations, schools, local businesses and the Commonwealth Government and will run for 36 weeks.</p>
<p>It will enable 100 young people to volunteer to undertake training as cadets for three hours a week within a range of community organisations. Participating organisations include the State Emergency Service, the Rural Fire Service, Shoalhaven high schools, St John's Ambulance, National Parks, Surf Life Saving Clubs and Volunteer Coastal Patrol.</p>
<p>Local businesses and community organisations are sponsoring the project. Sponsorship and the services to be contributed by the community organisations involved are worth an additional $96,000.</p>
<p>The project will allow the cadets to gain accredited training and, with the involvement of local schools, it will complement their education.</p>
<p>Importantly, it will enable and encourage young people to give something back to their community from an early age, and will foster the volunteering spirit of the Shoalhaven area.</p>
<p>I would like to thank the Federal Member for Gilmore, Mrs Joanna Gash, who raised the idea for establishing a local cadets programme with me eighteen months ago.<br />
Mrs Gash has been the driving force in bringing this project to fruition.</p>
<p>Mrs Gash has been able to bring together people from the Shoalhaven including individuals who had previously been involved in a local Work for the Dole project. This group studied similar cadet programmes in Western Australia and held public meetings locally to build broad support for the cadet programme.</p>
<p>I congratulate everyone who has given their support to this important project.</p>
<p>1 June 2001</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
