<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1287</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M. NO 34/1966  NEW COMMONWEALTH LOAN FOR BRIGALOW SCHEME STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001287.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS : 66049 P. M. No. 34/ 1966<br />
NEW COMMONWEALTH LOAN FOR BRIGALOW SCHEME<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
It will be recalled that at talks in Canberra last<br />
month, I assured the Premier of Queensland that Queensland's<br />
request for financial assistance for the development of further<br />
Brigalow lands in the Fitzroy River Basin of Central Queensland<br />
would be brought promptly to the Cabinet for its consideration.<br />
This Cabinet consideration has now taken place, and I have<br />
been very pleased to write to the Premier conveying the<br />
Commonwealth Government's approval of his request. The terms<br />
of my letter are as follows<br />
" Dear Mr. Nicklin,<br />
Since our discussion in Canberra on 4th March<br />
my Government has considered your request for financial<br />
assistance, in the form of a loan for the development<br />
of further Bri galow lands in the Pitzroy River Basin of<br />
Central Queensland.<br />
The area that you now propose be developed<br />
consists of some 6 million acres in the Mackenzie-Isaac<br />
River Basin north of your State's Central Railway Line,<br />
and is separate from and additional to the areas<br />
currently being developed south of the railway. As you<br />
know, the Commonwealth undertook in 1962 to rovide<br />
assistance of up to 614 500,000 to finance he cost of<br />
the current Brigalow Scheme, although you have advised<br />
me that, on the latest estimates it is expected that the<br />
final cost will be some 63,000,00 less than this.<br />
You also advised me that the estimated cost of<br />
the proposed new Brigalow development is $ 11,500,000,<br />
towards which the amount not now expected to be required<br />
for the current scheme could be applied. You asked<br />
whether the Commonwealth would be prepared to provide<br />
assistance by way of a loan to finance the project.<br />
In considering the proposal, my Government had<br />
before it your reports on the progress being made with<br />
the current Brigalow Scheme and was impressed with the<br />
success which as attended this development, despite some<br />
difficulties caused by drought. It was also aware, of<br />
course, that the area you now propose for development<br />
has been the sub ject of an investigation by the Bureau<br />
of Agicultural Economics, which reported very favourably<br />
on its economic potential.<br />
I am pleased to inform you that the Government<br />
has agreed to your request for financial assistance in<br />
the form of an interest-bearing loan of up to Wii, 560, O00 2 </p>
<p>E, 2<br />
" to finance this new project. This amount, of course,<br />
includes the amount that the Commonwealth will not now be<br />
required to provide for the current Brigalow development,<br />
which you have estimated at $, 000,000.<br />
It will be necessary to enter into an areement<br />
covering various matters of detail concerning the<br />
financial assist. nce proposed, and if you are agreeable,<br />
I propose that Commonwealth and State officers should confer<br />
on this in the near future.<br />
With your areement, I propose to release the terms<br />
of this letter to the Press. Yours sincerely,<br />
HAROLD HOLT."<br />
CANBERRA April, 1966. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
