<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3857</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER, FOR OPENING OF ST BASIL&#039;S HOMES, LOURANTOS VILLAGE, LAKEMBA, NSW, 23 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003857_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH NOTES FOR PRIME MINISTER, FOR OPENING OF ST BASIL'S HOMES,<br />
LOURANTOS VILLAGE, LAKENBA, N, S. W,<br />
23 AUGUST 1975<br />
1. IT GIVES ME VERY GREAT PLEASURE INDEED TO BE PRESENT FOR<br />
THE OFFICIAL OPENING AND BLESSING OF THIS MAGNIFICENT<br />
LOURANTOS VILLAGE WHICH OPERATES UNDER THE AUSPICES<br />
OF THE GREEK ORTHODOX CHURCH FIFTH LARGEST DENOMINATION<br />
IN AUSTRALIA. YOU HAVE AS YOUR PATRON His EMINENCE<br />
ARCHBISHOP STYLIANOS WHO HAS ONLY BEEN IN THIS<br />
COUNTRY SINCE APRIL THIS YEAR, BUT WHO FEELS SO FIRMLY<br />
COMMITTED TO THE PASTORAL NEEDS OF GREEK-BORNUSTRALIANS<br />
THAT HE ! NTENDS TO SEEK AUSTRALIAN CITIZENSHIP.<br />
AUSTRALIA IS HONOURED BY HIS INTENTION. I CAN ASSURE<br />
THE RESIDENTS, THE DIRECTORS, THE SUPPORTERS OF<br />
-ST BASIL'S HOMES THAT YOUR PATRON IS HERE TO STAY.<br />
2. 1 WAS ANXIOUS TO MEET ARCHBISHOP STYLIANOS AS SOON AS<br />
POSSIBLE AFTER HIS ARRIVAL, BECAUSE I FELT I HAD SO<br />
MUCH TO TALK TO HIM ABOUT FOLLOWING MY VISIT TO CRETE<br />
IN JANUARY THIS YEAR. QUITE APART FROM ALL THE TIES<br />
OF AUSTRALIA TO GREECE THROUGH OUR IMMIGRATION PROGRAMS,<br />
I HAD LEARNED THIS HIS FATHER HAD SERVED ALONGSIDE<br />
AUSTRALIAN SERVICEMEN IN CRETE DURING THE SECOND WORLD<br />
WAR. WHILE I WAS RETURNING FROM DARWIN, MY WIFE VISITED THE<br />
SITE OF THE BATTLE AND CEMETRY AT RETHYMNON WHERE THE<br />
TOWNSPEOPLE ARE ERECTING A MEMORIAL TO THAT AUSTRALIAN<br />
PRESENCE, AND SHE WAS DEEPLY MOVED BY THE EVIDENCE OF<br />
THE CONTINUING TIES OF FRIENDSHIP BETWEEN OUR PEOPLES./ 2 -ILQ4 </p>
<p>I<br />
3. ARCHBISHOP STYLIANOS, ACCOMPANIED BY MR SAMIOS, A DIRECTOR<br />
OF ST BASIL'S HOMES, LUNCHED WITH ME AT THE LODGE AT THE<br />
END OF IT WILL NOT SURPRISE YOU TO LEARN THAT<br />
THEY TALKED AT LENGTH ABOUT THIS GREAT SOCIAL UNDERTAKING<br />
HERE AT LOURANTOS VILLAGE3<br />
I EXPRESSED MY OWN INTEREST IN THE PROJECT, BECAUSE OF<br />
MY OWN CONCERN AT THE NEED TO PROVIDE LOVING CARE AND<br />
ACCOMMODATION FOR ELDERLY PEOPLE WHO HAVE SPENT THEIR<br />
LIVES IN THE SERVICE OF THEIR FAMILIES, OF THEIR<br />
COMMUNITIES, OF THEIR HOMELANDS, AND WHO DESERVE THE<br />
ATTENTION AND CARE OF THE COMMUNITY. I KNEW T-AT THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ' GOVERNMENT HAD CONTRIBUTED TO THE ESTABLISHMENT<br />
OF LOURANTOS VILLAGE UNDER THE AGED PERSONS HOMES AND<br />
HOSTELS ACTS.<br />
BUT I REALISED ESPECIALLY THAT THIS GREAT UNDERTAKING<br />
TO PROVIDE ACCOMMODATION FOR OVER 80 ELDERLY PEOPLE<br />
ø.. UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE GREEK ORTHODOX CHURCH<br />
ALTHOUGH IN ITS CHARITY IT IS NON-DENOMINATIONAL REPRESENTS<br />
THE COMMITMENT OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY IN AUSTRALIA TO<br />
ALL THOSE WHO NEED CARE IN OUR COMMUNITY, WHATEVER<br />
THEIR COUNTRY OF ORIGIN OR CHOICE,<br />
4, SO I WAS DELIGHTED TO ACCEPT THE INVITATION EXTENDED<br />
THROUGH YOUR DIRECTOR, MR SAMIOS, AND YOUR PATRON,<br />
ARCHBISHOP STYLIANOS, TO SHARE THIS OCCASION WITH YOU.<br />
IT IS APPROPRIATE THAT WE ARE HERE TOGETHER, CHURCH AND<br />
STATE, BECAUSE OF THE CO-OPERATION THERE IS BETWEEN<br />
CHURCH AND STATE IN THIS COUNTRY IN ALL AREAS OF SOCIAL...<br />
RESPONSIBILITY BUT ESPECIALLY THAT OF CARE FOR THE3Aft, </p>
<p>THIS IS THE FOURTH OLD PEOPLES HOME I HAVE OPENED IN<br />
NEW SOUTH ' WALES IN THE LAST THREE MONTHS. ALL HAVE<br />
RECEIVED SUBSTANTIAL GRANTS FROM THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT WHICH IS ANXIOUS TO PROVIDE MAXIMUM ASSISTANCE<br />
TO THOSE PHILANTHROPIC AND CHARITABLE ORGANISATIONS BEST<br />
FITTED AND MOST COMPASSIONATELY MOTIVATED IN THIS AREA<br />
OF CARE FOR THE AGED.<br />
I AM SURE THAT LOURANTOS VILLAGE WILL BE A PLACE OF<br />
COMFORTING AND COMFORTABLE INDEPENDENCE FOR ALL THOSE.<br />
'' WHO COME TO LIVE HERE. I KNOW THAT THE PERSONAL<br />
INVOLVEMENT OF THOSE CONNECTED WITH ST BASIL'S HOMES WILL<br />
EASE MANY OF THOSE INITIAL FEELINGS OF ISOLATION WHICH<br />
CAN MAR THIS PARTICULAR KIND OF " MOVING HOUSE", AND<br />
:: LL PROVIDE INTEESTED COMPANIONSHIP IN THE YEARS<br />
AHEAD. CERTAINLY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S GRANT<br />
CF $ 1,234,000 IS JUSTIFIED AND CAN BE SEEN AS AN<br />
INVESTMENT, ' NOT IN MONETARY TERMS, BUT IN THE SERENITY<br />
AND HAPPINESS OF THE RESIDENTS AT THEIR NEW ADDRESS,<br />
IN THEIR NEW HOME.<br />
6. IT MUST BE A GREAT JOY FOR MR NICHOLAS LOURANTOS TO BE<br />
HERE TODAY TO SEE SO MANY OF HIS OWN DREAMSREALISED,<br />
BECAUSE HE HAS BEEN SUCH A GREAT BENEFACTOR TO THIS<br />
CHARITY. AND IT IS FITTING THAT THIS COUNTRY SHOULD<br />
NOW HAVE A LOURANTOS VILLAGE TO COMMEMORATE A MAN<br />
CALLED NICHOLAS LOURANTOS WHO LEFT HIS HOMELAND, THE<br />
ISLAND OF TSIRIGO, TO COME TO A NEW LAND OVER SIXTY-FIVE<br />
YEARS AGO. THAT NEW LAND, AUSTRALIA, HAS BEEN ENRICHED<br />
BY HIS COMING, AND MEMORIES OF HIS HOMELAND LIVE ON 4.. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
THROUGH HIS PART IN THE ENDOWMENT OF THE CHAIR OF<br />
MODERN GREEK AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY. IT'S A<br />
LITTLE LATE FOR ME OF COURSE; I STILL CLING TO THE<br />
CLASSICS. BUT GENERATIONS OF YOUNGER AS WELL AS<br />
OLDER GREEK-SPEAKING RESIDENTS OF AUSTRALIA WILL<br />
REMEMBER NlICHOLAS LOURANTOS FOR HIS PHILANTHROPY,<br />
FOR HIS CHARITY,<br />
7, IN THIS CONTEXT IT IS INTERESTING TO REFLECT ON THE<br />
TIES BETWEEN THE OLDER GENERATIONS OF OUR HOMELANDS,<br />
IN THE YEAR 1974-75,' 3,334 AGED OR OTHERWISE DEPENDENT<br />
PARENTS WERE NOMINATED FOR ENTRY TO AUSTRALIA, ROM<br />
GREECE, AN" D 4,837 WERE NOMINATED FOR ENTRY AS NONDEPENDENT<br />
PARENTS. THE URGE FOR FAMILY REUNION IS<br />
IMMENSE AND GRATIFYING, IT IS AN INDICATION OF THE<br />
E/ TENT TO HjICH AUSTRALIA HAS BECOME HOME FOR A<br />
YOUNGER GENERATION. BUT ALSO A REMINDER OF THE PHYSICAL<br />
DISTANCE SEPARATING US FROM OUR EUROPEAN HERITAGE.<br />
I WAS ACUTELY CONSCIOUS OF THIS ON MY VISIT TO<br />
GREECE AND OTHER EUROPEAN COUNTRIES EARLIER THIS YEAR.<br />
IT MADE ME ALL THE HAPPIER FOR MY GOVERNMENT'S MOVE<br />
TO INTRODUCE PORTABILITY OF PENSIONS OVERSEAS, AT<br />
PRESENT AUSTRALIAN SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS ARE GOING<br />
TO 571 AGED PENSIONERS LIVING IN GREECE, 316 INVALID<br />
PENSIONERS, 149 WIVES AND 149 WIDOWS AND 7 SUPPORTING<br />
MOTHERS, OF THIS TOTAL OF 1,192, 484 HAD CONNECTIONS<br />
IN NEW SOUTH WALES, MANY OF THOSE PEOPLE-WOULD BE<br />
KNOWN TO THIS AUDIENCE. S </p>
<p>AND WHO KNOWS HOW MANY OF THESE ELDERLY PEOPLE<br />
DRAWING THE AUSTRALIAN AGE PENSION AT HOME IN GREECE<br />
MIGHT HAVE BEEN TEMPTED TO REMAIN HERE HAD THEY BEEN<br />
ABLE TO LOOK FORWARD TO RETIREMENT IN A PLACE LIKE<br />
LOURANTOS VILLAGE.<br />
I HAVE VERY MUCH PLEASE INDEED IN DECLARING OPEN<br />
THIS LATEST VENTURE OF ST BASIL'S HOMES LOURANTOS<br />
VILLAGE. I'AY ALL WHO COME HERE ENJOY A PEACEFUL AND<br />
HAPPY RETIREMENT, 1<br />
ø y o<br />
: t </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
