<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6635</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006635.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jjj&gt; A. UTALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA -2 JUNE 1985<br />
Employers who provide child care facilities for their<br />
employees are eligible for a range of tax deductions under<br />
the Income Tax Assessment Act.<br />
My Department recently sought clarification from the<br />
Australian Taxation Office on the applicability of the<br />
relevant sections of the Act to the provision of child care<br />
facilities. As a result, the Commissioner of Taxation,<br />
Mr Boucher, has advised of a wide range of deductions.<br />
It is the Government's policy to expand the provision of<br />
child care facilities and, in particular, to encourage<br />
the growth of work-based and work-related child care places.<br />
By the end of 1987 the Government will have doubled the<br />
number of community-funded child care centres. When we camne<br />
to office only 4.5 per cent of Australia's children aged<br />
under 5 had access to a government centre; by 1987 9 per cent<br />
will have access.<br />
A number of private sector employers, especially some who are<br />
participating in the Affirmative Action Pilot Program, are<br />
increasingly recognising the need to prov~ ide child care for<br />
their employees. I hope the deductions available under the<br />
Income Tax Assessment Act will encourage the provision of<br />
high quality care by private sector employers to supplement<br />
those provided by the Government. These deductions are<br />
outlined in the Status of WOmen Report, prepared by the Office<br />
of the Status of Women and published in the June issue of<br />
The Australian Women's Weekly.<br />
Day-to-day running costs, including salaries and wages of<br />
child care attendants, power, heating, lighting and rent<br />
are treated as normal business expenses and are fully tax<br />
deductible. Expenses incurred by an employer in fitting out a child care<br />
facility qualify for. the special rate of depreciation allowed<br />
for employers who provide certain facilities for their<br />
employees. Expenses such as lockers and kitchen facilities<br />
are deductible at a depreciation rate of thirty-three and a<br />
third per cent per annum. Toilet and washing facilities attract<br />
the ordinary rate of depreciation. </p>
<p>E 2.<br />
Construction costs and building alterations for the<br />
provision of child care are also deductible at a rate of<br />
four per cent under the Government' s increased tax relief<br />
to business for building construction. Any business which<br />
incurred capital expenditure for a child care facility after<br />
21 August 19.84 would be eligible for this rate. Costs of<br />
construction or alterations begun between 19 July 1982 and<br />
21 August 1984 are deductible at a lower rate of 2.5 per cent.<br />
Building expenses incurred before that period are not<br />
deductible. The Taxation Commission advises that claims relating to the<br />
provision of child care facilities must relate to expenditure<br />
incurred to produce assessable income. Some expenditure<br />
might not be wholly allowable, such as in cases where an<br />
employer derived exempt income as well as assessable income<br />
from business pursuits. Each claim would be considered in<br />
the light of its own facts.<br />
Some employers may, however, prefer to develop child care<br />
facilities with assistance from the Children's Services<br />
Program. Under that Program, where Government subsidies for both<br />
capital and recurrent costs are available, a proportion.<br />
of child care places must be reserved for members of the<br />
general community.<br />
The June Status of Women Report also provides information<br />
about the Federal Government's plan for creating 20,000<br />
additional child care places within the next three years<br />
through the Children's Services Program. My colleague,<br />
Senator Grimes, the Minister for Community Services, has released<br />
further details of this plan.<br />
The Report includes an exclusive survey of the views of<br />
women's organisations on tax reform options, and a guide to<br />
how to use the Family Court. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
