<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3608</transcript-id>
    <title>MINISTERIAL STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/02/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003608.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Ministerial Statement<br />
in the House of Representatives by the Prime Minister on<br />
11 February 1975<br />
I wish to report to the House and to the Australian<br />
people on my recent mission abroad. It<br />
was, I believe, the most arduous and comprehensive<br />
overseas visit ever undertaken by an<br />
Australian Prime Minister. It was also among<br />
the most necessary and productive. From<br />
Australia's point of view it was long overdue; in<br />
each of the countries I visited it was welcomed<br />
without reservation. It enabled me to put<br />
Australia's views, to hear the views of our<br />
friends and trading partners and to strengthen<br />
our goodwill in regions of undoubted importance<br />
to us. I count it an unqualified success.<br />
Between 14 December and 21 January I visited<br />
Sri Lanka, Belgium, the headquarters of the<br />
European Communities in Brussels. Britain,<br />
Ireland, Greece, the Netherlands, France. Italy,<br />
Yugoslavia, the Soviet Union, the Federal<br />
Republic of Germany, Pakistan and<br />
Bangladesh. I had intended also to visit Malta,<br />
but because of my return to Australia after the<br />
disaster in Darwin. the Special Minister of State,<br />
Mr Lionel Bowen, who accompanied me<br />
throughout my mission, visited Malta in my<br />
stead. Mr Bowen and I were accompanied by a<br />
team of senior officials, including the Secretary<br />
of the Department of Minerals and Energy, the<br />
Secretary of the Department of Overseas Trade,<br />
the Deputy Secretary of my own Department, a<br />
Deputy Secretary of the Department of Foreign<br />
Affairs and for part of our visit, a First Assistant<br />
Secretary of the Treasury and the Secretary of<br />
the Attorney-General's Department.<br />
It will be seen from the duration of my trip, from<br />
the number and range of the countries visited<br />
and from the number and seniority of the<br />
officials who accompanied me, how highly I<br />
rated the importance of this mission and the tasks I undertook on Australia's behalf. No Australian<br />
Prime Minister had visited the Soviet<br />
Union in the 33 years since diplomatic relations<br />
were established between the Soviet Union and<br />
Australia. Many of the other countries I visited<br />
had not previously been visited by an Australian<br />
Prime Minister. Yet the nations of the European<br />
Economic Community constitute Australia's<br />
second largest trading partner after Japan. The<br />
Soviet Union is one of the world's two superpowers-<br />
one of the nations whose policies<br />
determine the fate of all mankind. More than<br />
one and a half million citizens have come to<br />
Australia from the nations of continental<br />
Europe. We share with many of the countries I<br />
visited economic and social problems which it<br />
was clearly in our interests to discuss together.<br />
I saw my mission as an essential part of my duty<br />
as a head of government. It had already been<br />
postponed for six months because of the action<br />
of the Opposition in refusing Supply and forcing<br />
an election last May. I did not believe it should<br />
be postponed again. Quite apart from the<br />
inconvenience and disruption this would have<br />
caused to the Governments I visited, the issues<br />
we discussed were so important, so pressing, so<br />
central to Australia's immediate and long-term<br />
interests, that a further postponement could not<br />
be contemplated.<br />
I stress that point because, for some weeks, the<br />
Australian people witnessed a persistent and<br />
often unscrupulous campaign by sections of the<br />
media to deter me from my visit, and when I was<br />
not deterred, to disparage what I did. The<br />
specious view was put forward that a Prime<br />
Minister's duty is to stay at home at a time of<br />
economic difficulty. Now however serious our<br />
own problems and however acute my concern </p>
<p>about them-and I trust my concern is not in<br />
question-I believe a Prime Minister, in the<br />
nature of his office, has a special and at times an<br />
overriding duty to promote Australia's place in<br />
the world. This is not to say that our economic<br />
problems are unimportant. I agree that domestic<br />
matters, inflation and unemployment,<br />
have a greater priority in our thinking and are<br />
more important to the nation's welfare than any<br />
of the matters with which I had to deal overseas.<br />
The point is really this: while it was possible for<br />
my colleagues to deal with our domestic problems<br />
in my absence, it was not possible for anyone<br />
other than the Prime Minister to deal with<br />
the matters that arose during my mission.<br />
That is the crux of the matter. In all the denigration<br />
of my visit I have not seen this point<br />
acknowledged, let alone refuted. Only a visit by<br />
a head of government enables Australia to put<br />
her point of view at the highest level and in the<br />
most forceful terms. Only a visit by a head of<br />
government obliges the countries visited to<br />
clarify and co-ordinate their policies towards us.<br />
Only a visit that includes all European countries-<br />
or at least the majority of those of importance<br />
to us-can generate a cumulative impact<br />
and promote Australia's advantage on the<br />
widest scale.<br />
Our economic problems, far from being irrelevant<br />
to the matters discussed on my trip, in<br />
fact bore closely upon them. One of the themes<br />
of my mission was the essential and growing<br />
interdependence of nations in dealing with their<br />
economic problems. It would have been curious<br />
indeed if I had given the impression to our<br />
friends and trading partners, by cancelling or<br />
again postponing my mission, that Australia is<br />
the only country whose problems can be<br />
isolated from the rest of the world. The whole<br />
point of my mission, the point persistently<br />
ignored by the critics, was that Australia cannot<br />
isolate herself. Our inflation and unemployment<br />
are to a large extent linked with the present<br />
economic recession in the United States and<br />
much of Western Europe. I left Europe with the<br />
feeling that despite our temporary difficulties,<br />
Australia's economy is healthier and basically<br />
sounder than those of most of the countries I<br />
visited. I left Europe with the sure knowledge<br />
that the management of the western monetary<br />
system and the western economy is, along with<br />
the maintenance of peace, the greatest and most immediate problem of 1975. In meeting<br />
that problem, Australia, like every other advanced<br />
industrialised nation, has a part to play.<br />
For the information of honourable members I<br />
shall give a brief outline of my itinerary and<br />
official discussions before dealing with particular<br />
issues.<br />
I left Sydney on 14 December and made an initial<br />
stop in Sri Lanka, where I had talk: s with<br />
President Gopallawa and Prime Minister Bandaranaike.<br />
The following day I flew to Brussels<br />
for a stay of four days, during which I was<br />
received by their Majesties the King and Queen<br />
of the Belgians and had discussions with Prime<br />
Minister Tindemans. I had talks in Brussels with<br />
the President of the Commission of the<br />
European Communities, M. Ortoli, and with the<br />
Vice-President, Sir Christopher Soames. I<br />
addressed the International Press Centre there<br />
on 18 December.<br />
On 19 December I flew to London for a five-day<br />
visit, which included an audience with Her Majesty<br />
the Queen of Australia and discussions<br />
with Prime Minister Wilson and the Leader of<br />
the Opposition, Mr Heath. I sought to define<br />
Australia's relations with Britain in my speech at<br />
the Mansion House at a luncheon given by the<br />
Lord Mayor of London.<br />
On 23 December I paid a short visit to the Irish<br />
Republic for talks with the Taoiseach, Mr<br />
Cosgrave, and other Senior Ministers. I was also<br />
received by President O'Dalaigh.<br />
On my return to Europe I visited Greece, where I<br />
had talks on 3 January with the recently elected<br />
Prime Minister, Mr Karamanlis. The same<br />
evening I flew to The Hague for a two-day visit.<br />
There I was received by Her Majesty the Queen<br />
of the Netherlands and had talks with Prime<br />
Minister Den Uyl and other senior Ministers<br />
On 6 January I went to Paris for two days of<br />
talks with President Giscard D'Estaing Prime<br />
Minister Chirac and other French Ministers. In<br />
Paris I attended a ground-breaking ceremony at<br />
the site of the new Australian Embassy building<br />
and a civic reception in the Hotel de \ lille. I had<br />
talks with the Secretary-General of the<br />
Organisation for Economic Co-opeiation and<br />
Development, whose headquarters are in Paris.<br />
From Paris I travelled to Rome, where I had discussions<br />
with President Leone and Prime Minis-</p>
<p>ter Moro, the Foreign Minister, Mr Rumor, and<br />
several other senior Ministers. During my visit to<br />
Rome I signed a Cultural Agreement between<br />
Australia and Italy.<br />
I flew next to Yugoslavia, the first Australian<br />
Prime Minister to visit that country. I had talks<br />
on 9 and 10 January with Prime Minister<br />
Bijedic and met President Tito.<br />
On 12 January I flew to Leningrad and two days<br />
later to Moscow where I had wide-ranging discussions<br />
with President Podgorny and Prime<br />
Minister Kosygin of the Soviet Union and signed<br />
cultural and scientific agreements between the<br />
Soviet Union and Australia.<br />
I visited the Federal Republic of Germany from<br />
16 to 18 January. In Bonn I met President<br />
Scheel and had talks with Chancellor Schmidt<br />
and other senior Ministers. I addressed a meeting<br />
of bankers and industrialists at the Federation<br />
of German Industry in Cologne on 16<br />
January. On my way back to Australia I paid a brief visit to<br />
Pakistan on 19 January for talks with Prime<br />
Minister Bhutto, and Bangladesh, where I met<br />
Prime Minister-now President-Sheikh<br />
Mujibur Rahman. Joint communiques were<br />
issued after my visits to Yugoslavia and the<br />
Soviet Union.<br />
The EEC-Uranium<br />
It became apparent as my visit to the seven EEC<br />
countries progressed that Western Europe's<br />
demand for uranium in the late 70' s and the<br />
will be very substantial. Our role as a<br />
potential major supplier of uranium means that<br />
Australia's importance to these countries will<br />
increase.<br />
In Brussels, London, The Hague, Paris, Rome<br />
and Bonn, as well as in Moscow, I consistently<br />
asserted Australia's wish to develop her own<br />
enrichment capability so that as much uranium<br />
as possible should be exported in an enriched<br />
form. There are important policy issues to be<br />
resolved, such as the choice of enrichment<br />
technology, the capital investment required,<br />
and the extent to which we may be prepared to<br />
sell unenriched uranium both before and after<br />
we have our own enrichment capability. I am<br />
convinced that my visit, and the fact that the<br />
Head of the Department of Minerals and Energy,<br />
Sir Lenox Hewitt, accompanied me, has greatly facilitated the Government's consideration<br />
of the total uranium supply and demand<br />
situation over the next decade.<br />
The obvious interest shown throughout Europe<br />
in Australia as a supplier of uranium suggests<br />
that we shall exercise considerable influence in<br />
this important area.<br />
The EEC-Beef<br />
In each European Community capital I took up<br />
forcefully the Community's current import restrictions<br />
on beef. I left heads of Government in<br />
no doubt about our attitude to the Community's<br />
action in imposing restrictions without warning<br />
or consultation. I pointed out the disruptive and<br />
harmful nature of this action to the Australian<br />
meat industry and urged on European leaders<br />
the need for stable long-term marketing<br />
arrangements. The response of individual<br />
Governments was, in the main, apologetic and<br />
sympathetic. I believe that my visit has made it<br />
more likely that the Community market will be<br />
re-opened to Australian beef, if not later this<br />
year, then by mid-1976. I was informed that<br />
the total market could return to about 400 000<br />
to 500 000 tons by mid-1976. This total market,<br />
of which we would have a share, would<br />
mean that we would be still selling less beef<br />
than we did before the market was closed, but it<br />
would be an improvement. I also believe that<br />
the strong stand which I took on this matter and<br />
the interest of the European countries in Australian<br />
uranium will make it much less likely that<br />
such restrictive actions will be taken against<br />
Australian commodities again.<br />
Energy In a number of countries I discussed in some<br />
depth the energy crisis and the Middle-East. I<br />
assured European leaders that while we agreed<br />
that an increase in the price of oil was justified,<br />
we did not wish to see a confrontation develop<br />
between cartels of producers and consumers. I<br />
asserted strongly our attitude that while producers<br />
have every right to negotiate with consumers<br />
for fair prices for their resources, we will<br />
also work to harmonise the interests of producers<br />
and consumers with proper concern for<br />
the international situation as a whole.<br />
The Middle East<br />
In my discussions on the Middle-East I asserted<br />
the right of all countries in the Middle-East, </p>
<p>including Israel, to secure and recognised<br />
boundaries. I believe that Israel's integrity as a<br />
State must be upheld. At the same time, a lasting<br />
solution in the Middle-East wil' -? quire<br />
withdrawal from occupied territories and<br />
measures to meet the legitimate needs of the<br />
Palestinian people. While I cannot go into the<br />
details of private discussions, I was not discouraged<br />
by my discussions in the Kremlin and<br />
in Belgrade on this matter.<br />
The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty<br />
I took the opportunity in a number of capitals to<br />
urge greater support for the Nuclear Non-<br />
Proliferation Treaty. In particular I did so in<br />
Paris, Bonn and Rome. Australia wants to see<br />
the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty<br />
strengthened and all countries accept the<br />
multilateral obligations which the Treaty<br />
embodies. I sensed that there is a real possibility<br />
of movement by the governments in Rome and<br />
Bonn, which is most encouraging. In France I<br />
explained frankly the problems of selling<br />
uranium to countries which had not ratified the<br />
NPT or adhered to the International Atomic<br />
Energy Agency safeguards. Although France<br />
has not signed the NPT, I believe that she too is<br />
concerned about the proliferation of nuclear<br />
weapons and I hope that she too will sign.<br />
Meanwhile, France has said that she will behave<br />
as if she were a party to the NPT and that<br />
she already applies the safeguards adopted by<br />
the International Atomic Energy Agency.<br />
The Non-aligned Movement<br />
I discussed with Mrs Bandaranaike in Sri Lanka<br />
and with President Tito and Prime Minister<br />
Bijedic in Yugoslavia Australia's interest in the<br />
Third World and the non-aligned movement.<br />
Although Australia is an aligned country-and<br />
there can be no doubt about this-we have<br />
interests which overlap those of the Third<br />
World. Many of the non-aligned countries-like Sri<br />
Lanka-are within or on the borders of the<br />
Indian Ocean. I explained to Mrs Bandaranaike,<br />
President Tito and Prime Minister Bijedic our<br />
interest in attending future meetings of the<br />
non -aligned group either as a guest or as an observer.<br />
I found all three appreciative of the<br />
interest of Australia in the problems of the Third<br />
World and the objectives of the non-aligned movement and sympathetic to our association<br />
as a guest or as an observer with future meetings.<br />
We shall in the future be examining further the<br />
possibilities of our attendance in this capacity at<br />
future meetings of the non-aligned countries<br />
with other important members of the movement<br />
in Asia, Africa and the Middle East.<br />
The Indian Ocean<br />
I had discussions on the Indian Ocean while I<br />
was abroad. Honourable members will recall<br />
that I raised this matter in the United States and<br />
that the Government had raised it previously<br />
through diplomatic channels in both Washington<br />
and Moscow. I took the opportunity of my<br />
visit to Moscow to refer to this matter at the<br />
highest levels in the Kremlin. The Soviet<br />
Government understands our attitude. In the<br />
joint communique issued after my visit to Moscow<br />
the Soviet Government endorsed ' its readiness<br />
to participate' in ' seeking a favourable sol<br />
ution to the problem of making the Indian<br />
Ocean an area of peace'.<br />
I believe that in urging mutual restraint on the<br />
great powers we are on the correct course. To<br />
support any further development of bases in the<br />
Indian Ocean-or any long-term naval deployments<br />
in the area-is to support escalation and<br />
a heightening of tension in the region. We reject<br />
that course.<br />
Investment<br />
While in Western Europe, and especially in<br />
Bonn, I had full discussions on the question of<br />
investment in Australia. I made it plain that the<br />
Australian Government continues to welcome<br />
foreign investment but that we wish as far as<br />
possible to control our own industries and<br />
resources. I agreed that a West German mission<br />
should visit Australia in the near futuire to discuss<br />
in detail all aspects of investment in<br />
Australia. I agreed also to take up with the Australian<br />
taxation authorities the strongly expressed<br />
interest of the Belgian, Netherlands and<br />
Italian Governments in negotiating a double<br />
taxation agreement with Australia.<br />
The International Court<br />
Honourable members should know that I took<br />
advantage of my visit to The Hague-the city in<br />
which the International Court of Justice is<br />
based-to refer to our warm support for the </p>
<p>principles and objectives of, the International<br />
Court and to urge that the international community<br />
give greater attention to the Court as an<br />
instrument for world peace and harmony. I<br />
urged that the Court's jurisdiction should be<br />
made compulsory and universal. Honourable<br />
members will know that it has been the practice<br />
of most countries, including Australia, to accept<br />
the Court's jurisdiction only with reservations or<br />
with the exclusion of certain categories of dispute.<br />
I take this opportunity to inform the House<br />
that, as an earnest of our respect for the Court,<br />
Australia proposes to forgo her existing reservations,<br />
and in any dispute which we litigate before<br />
the Court, to accept its judgment unreservedly.<br />
Relations with Britain<br />
In London I had useful and cordial talks with<br />
Prime Minister Wilson on important issues<br />
including energy problems, unemployment,<br />
inflation, the dangers of a world recession, British<br />
attitudes to the re-negotiation of the Treaty<br />
of Rome, and Constitutional issues including<br />
the right of appeal to the Privy Council. I have<br />
today introduced Bills to give effect to the<br />
Government's policy on Privy Council appeals.<br />
That policy can be stated simply: we do not believe<br />
that Australians should litigate their disputes<br />
before the Courtsof another country. I believe<br />
that attitude is understood and accepted in<br />
Britain to a greater extent, regrettably, than it is<br />
in some quarters in Australia.<br />
In case there are any lingering misconceptions<br />
about the Government's approach to its relations<br />
with the United Kingdom, at the Mansion<br />
House I made it clear in a speech, which was<br />
widely publicised and applauded by the British<br />
media, that changes in the world situation had<br />
naturally led to changes in Australia's traditional<br />
relationship with Britain. I made it clear<br />
that those who saw the Government's recent<br />
actions concerning Britain as a manifestation of<br />
strident new nationalism or anti-British sentiment<br />
had completely misread the Government's<br />
intentions. What we are seeking to do is<br />
establish an independent Australian identity in<br />
the world and especially in our region. We have<br />
grown up. Our actions are in no way anti-<br />
British; they are simply pro-Australian. Contrary<br />
to a popular impression, I did not raise in<br />
Britain the question of State Agents-General. I<br />
made it clear that the traditional understanding and affection between Australia and Britain,<br />
based on strong historical and family connections,<br />
would deepen rather than diminish as<br />
Australia assumed her rightful place as an<br />
independent nation with a distinctive Australian<br />
role and a distinctive Australian voice in the<br />
South East Asian region, in the Commonwealth<br />
and in the world at large. We see particular<br />
value in our continuing associations with the<br />
Commonwealth. With the majority of member<br />
nations of the Commonwealth now lying in and<br />
around the Indian and South Pacific Oceans,<br />
Australia is geographically closer to the centre<br />
of the modern Commonwealth than is Britain<br />
herself. The Soviet Union<br />
It is thirty-three years since a former Labor<br />
Government established diplomatic relations<br />
with the Soviet Union. When I spent more than<br />
six hours in discussions with Chairman Kosygin<br />
and President Podgorny in the Kremlin it was<br />
the first time that Australia's views on a wide<br />
range of important issues had been put at this<br />
level. We discussed such matters as the situation<br />
in the North Asian region, Japan, China,<br />
Korea, detente and disarmament.<br />
I was also able to raise a number of human<br />
rights issues. While the Soviet Union maintains<br />
that these are matters within its domestic jurisdiction<br />
it is not insensitive to representations on<br />
these matters. I raised the matter of Jewish<br />
emigration. I raised the matter of ' Operation<br />
Reunion', that is, the scheme under which persons<br />
resident in the Soviet Union seek to join<br />
relatives or friends in Australia. Prime Minister<br />
Kosygin listened with courtesy to my presentation<br />
and replied in some detail on the question<br />
of Jewish emigration from the Soviet Union and<br />
on the question of ' Operation Reunion'. The<br />
Soviet Government takes the view that these<br />
are matters of purely domestic concern.<br />
Australia for her part, believes that on any matters<br />
involving broad humanitarian rights<br />
nations have a duty to put their viewpoints<br />
strongly. No purpose is served if we avoid issues<br />
where agreement is unlikely. The Soviet Union<br />
has a better understanding of our views and, I<br />
believe, a greater respect for our candour.<br />
France In France I had substantial and lengthy discussions<br />
with President Giscard D'Estaing and<br />
Prime Minister Chirac. I believe it is true to say </p>
<p>that my visit and my reception by my hosts in<br />
Paris put the seal at the highest level on the<br />
resumption of normal relations with France following<br />
the strains which had developed over<br />
France's atmospheric testing in the Pacific. This<br />
testing has now ceased.<br />
Arising from my visit to Paris, it was agreed that<br />
a French trade mission should visit Australia in<br />
the coming months to explore the possibility of<br />
increasing commercial exchanges between our<br />
two countries. Businessmen in Australia should<br />
understand that there is no political constraint<br />
upon their initiating contacts with France. It was<br />
agreed also to negotiate a cultural agreement<br />
between Australia and France and an agreement<br />
on co-operation in science and technology.<br />
It was further agreed to hold regular<br />
consultations between officials of the Australian<br />
Department of Foreign Affairs and the Quai<br />
d'Orsay. The first round of these consultations is<br />
likely to be held towards the middle of this year.<br />
Bangladesh My visit to Dacca brought into focus the issues<br />
involved in responding to Bangladesh's enormous<br />
needs, especially for food. I explained the<br />
great sympathy which the Australian Government<br />
and people felt for the people of<br />
Bangladesh in their struggle to feed their population.<br />
However, I felt obliged to point out to<br />
Sheikh Mujib that while Australia is willing to do<br />
as much as we can for his country, it is not right<br />
that the whole burden for supplying as aid, or<br />
selling on credit, wheat for Bangladesh should<br />
fall on the relatively few countries which produce<br />
surplus grain. I suggested international<br />
arrangements under which some of the<br />
developed Governments with capital, such as<br />
the Federal Republic of Germany or Japan, or<br />
the oil-rich Middle Eastern countries, might use<br />
some of their petrodollars to finance the purchase<br />
of wheat on credit from the grain producers.<br />
Detente I turn now to the broader issue of world peace. I<br />
see the peace of the world as resting on the progressive<br />
reinforcement of the network of accommodations<br />
and understandings between<br />
the two superpowers, the United States and the<br />
Soviet Union. This network of understandings is<br />
itself part of a wider balance of interests involving the other principal powers, China, Japan<br />
and the enlarged European Community.<br />
If peace is to be preserved-and in the ultimate<br />
analysis nothing is more important than thatthe<br />
interests of the United States, the Soviet<br />
Union, Japan and China and those of the enlarged<br />
European Community must be kept in balance<br />
in Europe and in Asia. Each must live with<br />
respect for the legitimate interests and aspirations<br />
of the others. Only in this way will<br />
detente become durable and global. Only in this<br />
way will peace be secured.<br />
It is the duty of the middle powers and the<br />
smaller powers to make their views heard in<br />
seeking to strengthen the structure of peace.<br />
This must be a common collective concern, not<br />
something left to the major powers alone. The<br />
future belongs to us all and, as I said in my address<br />
to the General Assembly last September,<br />
the Government rejects a concept of a world in<br />
which a handful of powerful men in charge of<br />
the most powerful nations chart the course for<br />
the rest of us to follow.<br />
Some may ask what influence a country like<br />
Australia has in the White House, in the<br />
Kremlin, in the Councils of Europe, in th~ e Great<br />
Hall of the People, or in Tokyo? I believe we can<br />
and do have influence. I believe at the very least<br />
we should not fail to try to exert some influence<br />
for the causes in which we believe. We should<br />
not permit our views on major international<br />
problems like the proliferation of nuclear<br />
weapons and access to markets to go by default.<br />
I had a number of objectives in undertaking this<br />
journey and I believe I fulfilled them all.<br />
I wanted to emphasise Australia's continuing<br />
and substantial interest in Europe and to<br />
strengthen Europe's awareness of Australia. I<br />
have done so.<br />
I wanted to complete. as far as possible:, the pattern<br />
of visits which my Foreign Minister and I<br />
have been undertaking abroad to outline<br />
Australia's policies in a number of areas following<br />
the first change of government in twentythree<br />
years. I have now largely completed that<br />
pattern of visits.<br />
I wanted to establish or strengthen personal<br />
contacts with the heads of government of<br />
important countries and exchange views with </p>
<p>them on matters of international concern and on<br />
common economic problems including inflation<br />
and unemployment. I have done so.<br />
I wanted to discuss at first hand Australia's<br />
interest in long-term arrangements for the<br />
access of our commodities in markets in Europe<br />
and I have done so. It is less likely, I believe, that<br />
Australia will ever again be subjected to summary<br />
and restrictive closures of markets which<br />
we have carefully nurtured.<br />
I wanted to discuss at the highest level the international<br />
energy situation and to form my own<br />
assessments on the major policy issues involved<br />
in the sale of Australia's bountiful mineral<br />
resources, especially uranium and coal, to the<br />
countries of Europe. I have done so, and I believe<br />
the outlook for Australia in the area of energy<br />
supply is immensely encouraging.<br />
I wanted to discuss with those countries whose<br />
people have contributed to Australia's cultural<br />
heritage and economic development the<br />
present attitude of the Government towards<br />
immigration. This I did in Britain, Ireland, Italy,<br />
Greece, Yugoslavia and the Netherlands.<br />
I wished also to explain Australia's policies on<br />
foreign investment and to remove any uncertainties<br />
about these policies. I have done so.<br />
Finally, I wanted to examine ways in which<br />
Australia might make its contribution to<br />
strengthening the fabric of co-operation between<br />
Australia and Europe and to explore, at<br />
the highest level, the attitudes of countries like<br />
the Soviet Union, France and Yugoslavia to<br />
detente and to the Middle-East, which are<br />
essential to forming any sound assessment of<br />
the prospects for world peace. I have done so.<br />
I regret that many of these things, these<br />
immense and tangible benefits for Australia,<br />
have been obscured from the Australian people.<br />
I do not resent fair criticism from the media.<br />
Everyone in public life accepts such criticsm and<br />
frequently benefits from it. Even my worst enemies<br />
would concede that I have rarely<br />
complained about the media's treatment of me,<br />
that I have been more accessible to the media,<br />
more frank in my dealings with them, than any<br />
of my predecessors in this office. A free press<br />
has an essential and constructive role in democratic<br />
society. I regret however that on this<br />
occasion the Australian public was not served by the media as objectively or as intelligently as<br />
it deserved. Too often matters of substance<br />
were subordinated to reports of trivia. It was<br />
repeatedly suggested that much of my time was<br />
taken up with sightseeing in visits to<br />
archaeological sites and museums. Very little<br />
time was taken up with these things and most of<br />
it was during public holidays and weekends.<br />
Such diversions, of course, are a normal part of<br />
the hospitality extended to visiting heads of<br />
government, and I make no apology for my<br />
interest in the culture and histories of the countries<br />
I visited, of the countries from which so<br />
many of my fellow citizens have come.<br />
We are not a nation of Philistines; we should not<br />
be content with an image abroad based mainly<br />
on Barry McKenzie. I take some pride in the<br />
extensive and sympathetic presentation of my<br />
mission in the media in all the countries I visited.<br />
I found immense goodwill, not just for me, but<br />
for Australia. This goodwill was expressed and<br />
symbolised in many different ways. In<br />
Bangladesh, for example, there was a warm appreciation<br />
of Australia's food aid programs. In<br />
the visits of the Special Minister and myself to<br />
war cemeteries in France, in Belgium, in Crete,<br />
in Athens, I found deep and genuine gratitude<br />
for the contribution of Australian soldiers to the<br />
allied cause in two world wars. In many countries<br />
there was a ready understanding of the<br />
links forged by our immigration program.<br />
Everywhere in the media of the countries I<br />
visited I found a full appreciation of the importance<br />
and urgency of the matters I sought to<br />
raise. I regret that I found much less understanding<br />
in the media of my own country.<br />
Over a year ago, on my return from China and<br />
Japan, I had occasion to say that Australia had<br />
at last got her relations right with the four<br />
powers of most immediate concern to us-with<br />
Indonesia, our nearest neighbour; with Japan,<br />
our largest trading partner; with China, the<br />
most populous nation on earth; and with the<br />
United States, the world's most powerful nation<br />
and our firmest ally. My visit to China ended a<br />
generation of lost contact with a quarter of the<br />
world's people. My visits to the United States,<br />
Japan, Indonesia and India consolidated,<br />
improved and matured existing relationships of<br />
great importance to us. My visit to the Soviet<br />
Union has marked a new stage in the development<br />
of practical and realistic relations with the </p>
<p>other powerful nation on earth. My visit to<br />
Europe has reasserted our strong and continuing<br />
interest in the European Community, and I<br />
believe, rekindled Europe's interest in a strong,<br />
progressive and independent Australia. Taken<br />
together, we have begun to fashion a more contemporary<br />
relationship with Europe-East and<br />
West-more appropriate to the changed conditions<br />
of our time. We can now say confidently<br />
that Australia has got her relations right, not just<br />
with the countries nearest to us but also with<br />
most nations of importance, and regions of<br />
importance, in the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
