<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2652</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY - FUND-RAISING DINNER, BARTON ELECTORATE SANS SOUCI, NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002652.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
LIBERAL PARTY<br />
FUND--RAISING DINER, BARTON ELECTOPATE<br />
SANS SOUCI, NSW. 31 JULY, 1972.<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. William<br />
McMahon,<br />
Mr. Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
I accepted the invitation to come here without any<br />
hesitation at all. There is a very simple explanation why I<br />
wanted to come.<br />
I want Barton back into the Liberal fold as I want<br />
St. George back, too. I want Vince Bruce to take his place with<br />
with us on the Government benches, and with your help I believe<br />
he is a certainty. He is an excellent candidate. Everyone who<br />
knows him will vouch for that. He will be an excellent member,<br />
because he is young, talented and a good Liberal.<br />
Most of you already know and if you don't I am<br />
telling you now that he will do a first-class job representing<br />
the people of Barton as well as representing the Liberal Party<br />
and I believe when he represents you, you will find that<br />
Australia as a whole is proud of him. The experts say we need<br />
a swing of about 3 to 4 per cent to recapture this electorate.<br />
With the candidate and the organisation we have got, that's easily<br />
attainable, provided we can all get the truth driven home to the<br />
voters in this and in all other electorates.<br />
It is of critical importance that the Government's<br />
achievements should be better known and its programmes better<br />
understood. We have a first class team of Ministers, who are giving<br />
this nation sound and effective administration. But from now on,<br />
as we move into the election period, we will all need to redouble<br />
our efforts to get our message across, and counter the propaganda<br />
of our opponents. In the last eighteen months, I've been to every state in<br />
Australia to some of them several times and recently I've<br />
toured the Northern Territory. </p>
<p>In that time, I've seen the country pause and adopt a " wait and<br />
see, attitude. In recent months, too, I've seen it putting caution<br />
aside and getting into its stride again and the pace is steadily<br />
quickening in response to government measures deliberately taken<br />
during the last eighteen months<br />
to stimulate growth<br />
to create employment<br />
and at the same time to keep the brake on<br />
inflation<br />
Not one single area of government activity has been left out of<br />
our continuing process of reviewing our policies, overhauling them<br />
and developing them in new directions.<br />
Our policy thinking goes on in the knowledge that Australians<br />
are individuals and fiercely individual in the values they hold<br />
dear, and the kind of society in which they want to live.<br />
In today's world, there is an increased awareness of the<br />
individual's responsibilities to his society. The Australian<br />
people have delegated to us, as their Government, some of those<br />
responsibilities, and before long, they must decide at the polls<br />
whether we have kept faith with them.<br />
Therefore it is important that we, as Liberals, should be<br />
articulate in restating for the nation what we, as a Party, see<br />
as our objectives and how we, as a Government, are going about the<br />
business of achieving those objectives.<br />
The Liberal Party shares with other parties of goodwill<br />
the desire to create a society in which the individual can live in<br />
peace and dignity, can enjoy the liberties which our civilisation<br />
prizes and in which his enthusiasm and energy can find full<br />
expression and potential. But unlike others, we are not a Party<br />
representing sectional interests. Our concern is to build<br />
Australia for all Australians.<br />
In doing this, we look primarily to individual initiative and<br />
enterprise as the dynamic force of proarss. Of course, if<br />
experience shows the Government intervention is necessary to<br />
protect the Australian people against exploitation, from whatever<br />
source, then we stand ready to act and will act.<br />
But the progress achieved since crld War 11, in the<br />
development of this country within the private enterprise system,<br />
vindicates our confidence in this approach.<br />
Let us look at how our Party's objectives and its<br />
pragmatic political philosophy relate to the issues of our time.<br />
Take first our foreign relations. Proud as we are to be<br />
Australians, we are also conscious that we are members of a world<br />
community. All Australians want to assist in creating and<br />
preserving for others the same freedoms and prosperity as we seek<br />
for ourselves. / 3 </p>
<p>Our concern naturally focussos on the hunger and strifo affecting<br />
the countries of our own region. It is for them alone to decidc<br />
the road they wish to follow in seeking to better their lot. But<br />
we think Australians are anxious to nurture their efforts.<br />
Liberal Governments have assisted with material aid and<br />
training, and by participating in joint economic and defence<br />
endeavours. Following my recent visit to Indonesia, for example,<br />
we are arranging naval exercises between the two countries. We<br />
already play our part in the Five-power Defence Arrangements with<br />
Malaysia and Singapore. During my recent personal discussions<br />
with President Soeharto, Prime Minister Lee Kuan Yew of Singap~ ore<br />
and Prime Minister Tun Razak of M1alaysia, the single fact that<br />
stood out above all others was the degree of confidence they have<br />
in us: That is the degree of confidence they havo in you the<br />
Australian people.<br />
They know they can trust: us. They know the part we have<br />
played and that we will continue to play in the region and I am<br />
confident they also know that if we were to leave, if we were to<br />
lose our interest in this region, a vacuum would be created, which<br />
might well be filled hy another influence not as friendly, nor<br />
as trustworthy. So that our efforts to contribute to the stability<br />
and pros perity of countries in our region are not only a moral<br />
responsibility. They help to lessen tensions and misunderstanding.<br />
They also represent an important contribution to our defence.<br />
Regrettably, tensions and misunderstandings still persist.<br />
For these reasons, our policy is to continually strengthen the<br />
capability of our defence forces and to effsctively maintain our own<br />
defence alliances, as for example, our alliance under ANZUS and<br />
with the United States and New Zealand. Our policy is also<br />
designed to protect the liberties of others whilst emphosising<br />
the primary effort must be our own dcfence, and then the contribution<br />
we can make to world stability and prosperity.<br />
Another important issue of our time, an&amp; ono that is of<br />
immediate importance to us in the maintennce~ of public law and<br />
order. One of the basic freedoms is the right of the inc'ividual to<br />
build his life within a stable framework of just laws. No<br />
individual c-an rest secure,/ or cnnfidently plan his own and his<br />
family's future outside of such a framework. We in Australia have<br />
been fortunate in the stability of our society, but we would he<br />
unwiso to assume it is an inevitable featurc of Australian life.<br />
Like all worthwhile things: it must be protected and preserved.<br />
Today we see it threatened by a growing di srogard for the<br />
observance of our laws and the processes by which wc arrive at<br />
them, whether in the industrial or the political sphere.<br />
Draft resisters are encouracd by individuals and groups<br />
who themselves aspire to the responsibilities of office , protesters<br />
resort to violence and vandalism in the name of goodwill. Unionists<br />
blackmail the community and threaten the livelihood of their<br />
fellows when arbitral decisions are not to their liking. The whole<br />
basis ef public law and order within our community is threatened<br />
by these actions. </p>
<p>Unfortunately, many of the: people responsible are wellmeaning<br />
individuals who fail to see the grave consequences which<br />
can flow from these actions. Liberal Governments -and you who are<br />
Liberals will know are committed by our Party platform to the<br />
principle of " Parliament controlling the executive and the law<br />
controlling all". My Government has stood firm and we will continue<br />
to stand firm, to ensure respect for all constitutionally valid<br />
laws. I should not let this opportunity pass without referring in<br />
this context to the critical situation that has been reached in<br />
the oil industry strike. On television last night I stated that<br />
we as a GovernTment would not permit any one person or group to<br />
determine who will or who will not receive fuel: We hold to that.<br />
We are also determined that the arbitration system will be upheld.<br />
The alternative, I repeat, is industrial anarchy.<br />
Today's events have shown that the emergency proposals<br />
under which only some of the strikers return to work are not good<br />
enough. And to show clearly how political this is, Mr. Hawke has<br />
now allowed free access to petrol in South Australia because it<br />
happens to be a Labor-dominated State. The men on strike have<br />
already received in an interim decision from the commission, a wage<br />
increase of $ 4.80 per week for tradesmen and $ 3.60 for trades<br />
assistants. Some of the strikers still refuse to accept the<br />
umpire's decision. I ask those still on strike to return to work so that<br />
their outstanding claims can be dealt with by the Arbitration<br />
Commission. There is still time.<br />
We are not seeking confrontation. The confrontation is<br />
in the defiance of an arbitrated decision by a diminishing number<br />
of union meCmers. Turning to the economy, we see an area whcre our philosophy<br />
puts us furthest apart from our political apponents. Our primary<br />
concern is with the creation of wealth in which employer and<br />
employee can share as co-operators not with the re-distribution<br />
of the community's wealth at the risk of economic stagnation.<br />
We see our success not only measured by gross natinal<br />
product, but also in terms cf our objectives of full employment and<br />
improved living standards.<br />
Running a government is just like running a business. In<br />
any financial enterprise, one must expect some setbacks. This also<br />
applies in the national context, where some of the difficulties are<br />
not within our own national control.<br />
Economic problems overseas have reacted to the detrir-ant of<br />
our own economy. There have been seve; re difficulties in the rural<br />
economy which are being steadily overcome, due in part to the<br />
fall in overseas prices. </p>
<p>Our difficulties hia becn compounded by inflationary<br />
pressures, due in part to irrosponsible domnnds for unrealistic<br />
wages and conditions. But I assure you now re~ covery is well under<br />
way. With a continuation of the same prudent management, Australia<br />
in 1973 will see a continuation of the prosperity which has been<br />
a feature of successive Liberal Governments.<br />
Finally, I want to speak about the wonderfully<br />
descriptive, but ill'-defined term, the " quality of life". Our<br />
Party objectives have long recognised that a government's<br />
responsibilities go far beyond simply prctecting the individual's<br />
freedoms and creating conditions of material well-bing.<br />
We view the availability of comprehensive educational opportunities<br />
for all as an essential element in the soci. pty we are working to<br />
create. We do so, because it is essential to provide the skills<br />
and knowledge needed by industry, and because we know education<br />
develops the spirit of true citizenship, and provides a basis for<br />
a fuller and a more meicaningful life. Liberal Federal Governments<br />
have been responsible, together with the states, for the great<br />
expansion of tertiary education ever recent years.<br />
Now we are becoming increasingly involvK-in socondary<br />
education. Policies dosigned to encourage cultur. al activities are<br />
a logical extension of our educational objectives. We look<br />
ultimately to tho time when community interest in the arts is<br />
sufficient to provide the finance nccessary to sustain and encourage<br />
national cultural activities.<br />
Meantime, we are continuing to provide modest support and<br />
broadening the basc of Australian artistic cndeavcurs, by<br />
initiatives like the national film schoci.<br />
We have also been responsive to the recently awakened<br />
national concern for the protection and improvemont of the<br />
environment in which we live. With the States we have established<br />
the Australian Environment Council for consultation and co-ordination<br />
between us in environmental matters. We are concerned to maintain<br />
the fine qualities which have characterised life in our great country.<br />
We take pride in our whole Australian heritage both the country<br />
and its people. Wo will work to protect and nurture buth.<br />
Time alone prevents mae giving further examples of how our<br />
dedication to political liberty and the freedom and dignity of man<br />
guides cur policies. But the matters I have touched on uc. onstrate<br />
the continuing relevance of Liberal Party objectives to our national<br />
destiny. Naither time nor events have outmoded them. Mo~ reover, our<br />
Party has the human resources and the purpose to lead the Australian<br />
nation forward towaras; the goals the people themselves have chosen<br />
I certainly have an abundance of confidence. We are confident that<br />
a majority of the Australian people share our ap~ preciation of the<br />
important issues of our national life and will yet again place their<br />
confidence in our Government when the elections occur towards the<br />
end of the year.<br />
My personal and my wholehearted belief is this. With a<br />
candidate of the kind we have in our prescnce here tonight, with the<br />
support I know we can expect and will in fact get from the people<br />
who are here representing as they do Liberal thought, Liberal<br />
ambitions and Liberal ideals, I feel absolutely certain that you </p>
<p>will put Vince Bruce back thcre and you will make certain of<br />
a magnificent victory in this election.<br />
Give us the opportunity to govern, and I can assure<br />
you that we will cary on the tradition of the last twenty-two<br />
years. But above all, we will do more than carry on in that<br />
tradition. With an economy as soundly-based as ours is, with<br />
increasing diversity and increasing strength, we will be able to<br />
do all the things that you want us to do better health,<br />
better education, better transport, and above all, a feeling<br />
of confidence in the community. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
