<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5055</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO THE PARLIAMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/05/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005055.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRRMEF MNISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 29 MAY 1979<br />
STATEMENT TO THE PARLIAMENT<br />
The package introduced by the Treasurer last week was one of<br />
economic responsibility. It puts the economic health of<br />
Australia and the well-being of all Australians wherever*<br />
they may be, whatever their occupations may be, foremost in<br />
the Government's mind.<br />
The Government's commitment to responsibility is critical to<br />
economic recovery. Because of our policies inflation has been<br />
substantially reduced. The competitiveness of Australian<br />
industry has greatly improved. New private fixed capital<br />
expenditure is up 26 percent in the year to March 1979. In<br />
mining capital investment is particularly strong 46 percent<br />
up in the year to March of this year and the mining industry<br />
expects a further 32 percent throughout the course of 1979.<br />
oil exploration and development are taking off. The rural<br />
economy is having its best period for a very long while,<br />
making up for some of the very lean and difficult times it<br />
has had over recent years. Business profits are rising.<br />
Private civilian employees, seasonally adjusted, have risen<br />
for seven months and that's the best result since 1974.<br />
Retail sales for the March quarter were up significantly.<br />
The Treasurer's package continues the thrust of economic<br />
responsibility. It consolidates the gains that we have made<br />
over three and a half years. It will strengthen confidence<br />
in the Australian economy strengthen control over our own<br />
expenditure. There will be substantial savings in health,<br />
in education, in payments to primary industry and transport<br />
and in other areas. These expenditure reductions show the<br />
determination of the Government to control its own expenditure<br />
and they also foreshadow stringent control at the Premier' s<br />
Conference in June and at the Budget in August.<br />
The fLull year savings and the forward estimates and the new<br />
policies-~ for the programme-s already-announced include $ 290 million<br />
or a LYittle more in health, and over $ 60 million in primary industry.<br />
Further savings in other portfolios can clearly be expected.<br />
The Government's record of expenditure control is clearly shown<br />
by the fact that today's deficit as a percentage of Gross<br />
Domestic Product is significantly less than it was under the<br />
Labor government. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Government has also acted to raise further revenue.<br />
OPEC induced price increases will be reserved for the community<br />
and not for companies. New oil to be discovered will be<br />
unaffected and therefore exploration incentives will be<br />
maintained. The coal export levy at the reduced rate will be<br />
continued. The trading stock valuation adjustment, applied by<br />
firms to increase after-tax profits rather than to adjust their<br />
internal stocktaking accounts, and therefore being used in a way<br />
not foreshadowed by Mathews is being removed. of course, the<br />
liquidity position of companies is infinitely better than it was<br />
when the adjustment was first allowed. So in many senses it<br />
has achieved a real purpose.<br />
The carry forward of paper losses under tax avoidance schemes which<br />
Labor did nothing to prevent is not going to be allowed, and<br />
of course we are extending the existing PAYE schedules to<br />
November 1979 or to some earlier date to be proclaimed. That<br />
plainly means that there is no change in current PAYE rates<br />
and no change in current weekly deductions.<br />
One of the deceits of the Australian Labor Party is that they<br />
sought to have people believe that there is going to be a tax<br />
increase from the 1st of July. A tax increase of course was<br />
never in mind. It's a question of whether tax reductions<br />
foreshadowed at the time of the earlier budget could in fact<br />
be consummated.<br />
Personal tax rates for the whole of 1979-80 together with a<br />
decision on indexation will be announced at the same time as the<br />
Budget. I would like to emphasise what the Treasurer said.<br />
There is no prospect of removal in full of the surcharge together<br />
with full implementation of tax indexation when that announcement<br />
is made. And the final decisio * n will not be possible until we<br />
have the complete information available to us at the time of<br />
the Budget.<br />
The package introduced by the Treasurer is balanced and is<br />
equitable both on the expenditure side of the account and on<br />
revenue. It protects those in need. The health changes will<br />
continue to protect pensioners and the socially disadvantaged<br />
and will establish the circumstance where people can pay the<br />
small bills for themselves but be protected against the major<br />
accounts that cancompletely break the individual or any family.<br />
And I indicated earlier that if there was a virtue in regular<br />
Medibank I as opposed to the programme that had been introduced<br />
or maintained earlier, it was that the original Medibank scheme<br />
together with the changes that have been introduced since,<br />
established universal health cover for all Australians.<br />
I suggest that the price paid for that was a high one by the<br />
Australian community as a whole. But it's worth noting that<br />
we have preserved that universal health cover for all<br />
Australians with changes now introduced. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-4<br />
The 4 percent wage decision was more than hoped for by the<br />
Government. At the same time inflation in a number of<br />
countries is running much higher. In the six months to<br />
March of 1979, inflation is running at an annual rate of<br />
10.1 percent in the United States, 10.7 percent in the United<br />
Kingdom, 10.5 percent in Canada, 15.4 percent in Italy,<br />
10.1 percent in New Zealand. Even in Germany, which has<br />
a very good anti-inflationary record, the inflation rate has<br />
about doubled during this year. All of these figures show<br />
that inflation prospects in many countries are much less<br />
favourable than in Australia.<br />
Many of these factors, especially prospects for the rural<br />
community and miners have healthy effects on the economy,<br />
but they also have an impact on inflationary pressures they<br />
have an impact on the money supply. And, as a result of these<br />
changes, inflationary pressures increase and there is a clear need<br />
for Government action to maintain control over the economy.<br />
Particularly so since the 5 percent inflation forecast in<br />
Budget Statement No. 2 will not be obtained.<br />
Before last week's package the Government had already acted<br />
to adjust interest rates to changed circumstances; to introduce<br />
changed methods of financing the wheat crop; and to make<br />
calls on SRDs. These actions alone were not enough. They had<br />
to be strengthened by further actions if undue strain was not<br />
to be placed on monetary policy.<br />
In the total picture of economic recovery with its consequent<br />
inflationary threats, a lower deficit is all the more<br />
important. The Budget must give total confidence so that<br />
there will be a downward pressure on prices on inflation. In all<br />
these circumstances a tax cut of over $ 1,000 million on<br />
1 July would have been irresponsible and would have destroyed<br />
that confidence.<br />
The Government plainly is disappointed that it has not been<br />
possible to remove the surcharge immediately, as forecast at<br />
the time of the last Budget. But I must say unequivocally that<br />
our anticipations proved to be wrong by later events.<br />
That's a cross that the Government must bear. We regret the<br />
fact that we are unable to remove immediately the surcharge<br />
and introduce tax indexation. We certainly make no apology<br />
for it, because we have taken the right course for the economy<br />
and for the people of Australia.<br />
The step we have taken will build confidence in the Australian<br />
economy and there should now be no pre-Budget doubts about the<br />
Goverpment's resolve. There will be no pre-Budget doubts<br />
about investment decisions; about the value of the<br />
Australian . dollar and about the growing confidence throughout<br />
all sections of the Australian community. </p>
<p>3-<br />
The package brought forward by the Treasurer responds to<br />
improved business and rural conditions. We provided help to<br />
rural industry when it greatly needed it and if the same<br />
circumstances arise again we will certainly do so again.<br />
For example, there was special beef assistance for the beef<br />
industry in 1977-78 but quite plainly that special assistance<br />
is not required under the current circumstances.<br />
In addition, the stock valuation adjustment followed the<br />
liquidity difficulties that many industries and companies were<br />
experiencing at earlier times. Today business liquidity has<br />
greatly improved.<br />
We make no bones about the fact that the last Budget committed<br />
the Government to taking off the surcharge. That commitment as I<br />
have made plain, as the Treasurer has made plain, was made in<br />
good faith. But after tightening expenditures and raising<br />
more revenue it was clear that the only responsible course<br />
was to keep open options on tax indexation and on the<br />
surcharge until the Budget in August.<br />
I stress that * this does not involve any increase in weekly PAYE<br />
instalment' deductions on41 July. It was never a question<br />
of an increase over and above current rates. It was a question<br />
of the possibility of a decrease. There will be no change<br />
in take-home pay as a result of the decisions that the<br />
Treasurer announced.<br />
Many figures in the Budget are predictions; based on the best<br />
advice and knowledge at the time. The forecasts for the<br />
1978-79 Budget were in the context of two years of falling<br />
inflation and of falling monetary growth.<br />
Certain Budget forecasts are critical, but if they do not<br />
eventuate the Government has no responsible option but to<br />
compensate by other Government action. And since the Budget<br />
a number of things have happened which put some of the Budget<br />
perspectives out. The economy is not static it is not<br />
fixed by words in a Budget. It's a living thing affected<br />
by the actions of changes within and without Australia.<br />
And much has changed since the Budget. I mentioned before<br />
the deteriorating strategic situation in Iran and Indochina.<br />
That was not foreseen by anyone. Accordingly this Government<br />
has properly made decisions to spend more in real terms on<br />
defence. oil prices have increased because of Iran, more than anticipated<br />
at the time of the Budget. There is therefore a greater push<br />
for im,, flationary expectations. Beef price increases are 35 percent<br />
higher than the Bureau of Agricultural Economics forecast at<br />
the time of the' Budget. The Wheat harvest is more than 50 percent<br />
above last August's forecasts. There has been a dramatic<br />
improvement in some commodity prices in this financial year<br />
aluminium over 20 percent, copper over 30 percent, lead over<br />
100 percent and zinc, over 40 percent. Moreover for the<br />
second successive year, estimates of revenue in the Budget<br />
appear likely to exceed the revenue outcome. / 4 </p>
<p>The Government is determined to take the right course. We<br />
will respond to chanqes and to influences as they arise and<br />
will change policy as necessary.<br />
The package that was introduced by the Treasurer is a mark<br />
of strength and determination to act in the interests of all<br />
Australians. It is the mark of a determination to respond to<br />
new conditions that arise either here or overseas.<br />
The judgement of the Australian people will go far beyond<br />
the petty actions of the Opposition in this Parliament because<br />
the package will be respected. It takes the right course for<br />
Australia as a document of economic responsibility.<br />
The Government will not sacrifice economic management for<br />
political expediency. We will keep fighting inflation. We<br />
will keep fostering economic activity that will provide<br />
lasting jobs; will keep taxes at the lowest poss õ ible level.<br />
It's been a long fight to strengthen the Australian economy.<br />
and to achieve our goals. We never disguised this. And we<br />
never have.<br />
But now there is an upturn in the Australian economy and<br />
recovery is under way and that's not doubted except by the<br />
blind men of the Australian Labor Party.<br />
The vision that brought this Government to office has not<br />
been dulled. That vision keeps us on our path and gives us<br />
the courage to respond to reality effectively and in the<br />
interests of Australia.<br />
Under Labor the Government deliberately and constantly raised<br />
false expectations. It bred a greater dependence by people<br />
on the Government. Labor destroyed the capacity of Australian<br />
industries to employ. They destroyed the independence of<br />
people by breeding the view that the Government only had to<br />
be asked and it would provide. They established the philosophy<br />
that Governments have unlimited resources because they could<br />
go to the printing press and that Governments have to provide<br />
the answers to all problems. They established the false view<br />
that people could be paid according to their own estimates of<br />
themselves. They set about destroying Australia by creating<br />
a web of deception by deluding Australians that living from<br />
tax dollars without contributing to Australia does not hurt<br />
f Ilow Australians.<br />
Labor tried to put Australia on the path that throughout history<br />
has taken once strong and vibrant nations to their very<br />
destr'uction. But Labor failed. Their philosophy was<br />
overwhelmingly rejected by the Australian public in two elections.<br />
The task of this Government has been to rebuild the strength and<br />
the independence of this nation: to reassert the fundamental<br />
principle that Governments can establish the circumstances,<br />
the opportunities for people to achieve and create and that<br />
ultimately it's only an independent, self-reliant society<br />
that can develop Australia. ./ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
We've been working to establish the circumstances in which<br />
Commonwealth and State Governments live within their means;<br />
the circumstancesin which Australian industries will<br />
once again be independent, excell in the Australian market,<br />
move out into export markets and employ more people.<br />
We've been working to establish the circumstances in which<br />
people can be self-reliant; the circumstances in which the<br />
weak and the poor can be protected; where families are<br />
protected when illness strikes and which they can't be expected<br />
to cope with from their own resources.<br />
We've been working to strengthen the life, the vitality, the<br />
vigour of the Australian people.<br />
That's what we've been working to. And that is what we have<br />
been achieving.<br />
We have a vision of a Liberal society of free, independent<br />
people with a pride in being able to do things for themselvesan<br />
Australia of growing strength, unequalled as a place to<br />
bring up a family; unequalled in freedom and unequalled in<br />
opportunity. A nation creating our own distinctive culture,<br />
our own identity out of the culture and history that so many<br />
people have brought to us from so many different lands.<br />
This can only be achieved by a Government that established<br />
the circumstances which enable individuals and businesses to work<br />
out their own future in their own way. A Government which<br />
recognises that it should not seek to do for people what they<br />
ought properly to do for themselves.<br />
The Australian Labor Party sought to destroy the initiative<br />
of Australians. The inflation created by Labor undermined<br />
industrihs; the inflation created by Labor degraded individuals;<br />
it weakened the old and harmed the weak, more than anyone<br />
else in the community.<br />
Repairing the damage of Labor was a great task but we are well<br />
along that road and we are doing this by facing up to economic<br />
realities and by not allowing expediencies to determine our action.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
