<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4421</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RIGHT HONOURABLE JM FRASER CH MP, TO THE AUSTRALIA BRITAIN SOCIETY/COOK SOCIETY, CAFE ROYAL, LONDON, 13 JUNE 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/06/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004421.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN HIGH COMMISSION LONDON<br />
AUSTRALIA HOUSE STRAND WC2B 4LA TEL. 01-438 8000<br />
j AUSTALIA<br />
Please quote in reply<br />
Branch: EMBARGO: 2.15 p. m.<br />
Our Ref: CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
Direct enquiry 01-433 ADDRESS BY THE PRIME 1MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
THE RIGHT HONOURABLE FRASER, M. P.,<br />
TO THE AUSTRALIA BRITAIN SOCIETY/ COOK SOCIETY,<br />
CAFE ROYAL, LONDON, 13 JUNE 1977<br />
It is a great pleasure to have this opportunity to speak to you.<br />
Your Societies' purpose of fostering the ties and understanding<br />
between our two countries is an important one. The importance of<br />
this task is in no way diminished by -he fact that our nations<br />
share a common history, common democratic traditions, and<br />
commitments. On the contrary, the situation which our two countries<br />
along with other liberal democracies find themselves makes it<br />
essential that we fully understand a-n clearly state the bonds we<br />
have, and the interests we share. The nature of this relationship<br />
the common interest of the democracies, is rarely sufficiently emphasised<br />
or explored.<br />
This is a somewhat meaty offering as he final course of a very good<br />
lunch. But, I do intend to speak to : ou in a serious vein this<br />
afternoon. This is a rare opportunity, and you will forgive me if I<br />
am tempted to use the occasion to touch on some questions facing your<br />
country and mine. The answers may ietermine future developments,<br />
not only in Australia and Britain, but in other nations that<br />
cherish free and democratic systems of government.<br />
We are aware, but give little thought to the fact that the military<br />
strength of authoritarian regimes is growing; the number of<br />
nations committed to liberal democratic ideals has declined;<br />
and around the world, human rights are still grievously infringed.<br />
These circumstances are not irrelevant to our own policies<br />
and our resoonse should be based on a global perspective.<br />
Although the democracies are dispersei around the world, our future<br />
is fundamentally a collective one. e need to understand<br />
our inter-dependence, that we draw our strengths from one another,<br />
commercially, politically, strategically, and perhaps most<br />
important of all, philosophically. need to state openly<br />
our common interests, and values. need to recognise that our<br />
strength does not lie exclusively in t-he United States, Europe and Japan<br />
not in any single region of the worii, but in our collective strength<br />
and our collective purpose.<br />
We cannot allow ourselves to be isclated from one another, either<br />
strategically or commercially. Neith-er our national security, nor our<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>economic well-being can be assured unless we take such a global<br />
perspective. To ask for this approach is not to ask for too much.<br />
For our; Societies are outward looking ones which do thrive on<br />
their inter-connections with one another and with the rest of the<br />
world. if we ignore this interdependence if for instance, we<br />
take some temporary commercial advantage at another's expense then<br />
we will have done damage to th. e interests we have in common.<br />
We not only face important international challenges, but also major<br />
domestic ones: the challenge of maintaining freedom and unity;<br />
the challenge of relating expectations to resources; the challenge<br />
to politicians to explain the problems they face-to the people;<br />
the challenge of holding to good, and powerful ideas.<br />
Perhaps the basic challenge is that maintaining freedom and unity.<br />
We all know that no society can operate properly without a degree<br />
of unity and cohesion. Maintaining our essential unity when there is<br />
no single, overwhelmingly recognisable danger has always been a<br />
fundamental problem for democracies. Today, the task of maintaining<br />
liberty and unity is a more urgent problem than ever before.<br />
Some people demand greater and greater freedom while rejecting the<br />
legitimacy of any voluntary restraints and obligations. But freedom<br />
is only possible if some degree of voluntary restraint and some degree<br />
of political and social obligation is accepted. Democracy and anarchy<br />
are not synonyms.<br />
It is not a paradox to assert that to preserve the greater<br />
freedom democracy'allows, some restrictions of freedom must be<br />
voluntarily and responsibly accepted. Changing power relationships<br />
and changing attitudes within democracies threaten that essential elemr<br />
The proper authority of Parliament is challenged i its capacity<br />
to resolve problems is put in question.<br />
The second challenge is theproblem of rising expectations and th-..<br />
inescapably reality of limited resources. Free men's aspirations<br />
always reach out to a better society. This is one of democracy's<br />
motive forces. one of the power forces for progress and achievement.<br />
But there are'times when expectations so far exceed reality that<br />
the result is hot progress but disillusion. We must all promote<br />
an understanding of the limits of what is possible of the fact<br />
that unreasonable gains by one group will involve unacceptable<br />
deprivations for others. And we must promote this understanding<br />
without forsaking our ideals of what should and can be achieved<br />
in the future. Otherwise disenchantment with democracy and democratic<br />
leaders will result.<br />
As much as anything, the cause of unrealistic e:. ppecations lies<br />
in the belief that government can year after : ear spend more<br />
money than they raise. Keyne's view that high spending was<br />
appropriate in times of high unemployment, low inflation, and low<br />
interest rates has been translated by others into a policy for<br />
all circumstances. The belief that we can spend our way out of<br />
recession when inflation and interest rates are high, is a nonsense,<br />
and needs to be put aside. </p>
<p>The nature of the democratic system played a major part in<br />
fostering this illusion and promoting unrealistic expectations.<br />
C6mpetitive bidding for electoral support has too often been allowed to<br />
replace objective judgemenit and sound policy. This is based on a<br />
somewhat cynical view of the-people's intelligence. A cynicism<br />
democracies can no longer afford.<br />
Economic reality, plain truth and their national acceptance<br />
are now a pre-eminent requirement. The magnitude of the economic<br />
problems we face suggests that any other course would involve<br />
considerable danger. The competitive bid is no longer an option.<br />
Democracy depends on the good sense of people That good sense<br />
and judgement has seldom been adequately tested.<br />
The final point I want to make is concerned with the democratic idea.<br />
The democratic idea was once powerfully held and vigorously propounded.<br />
With this idea aa a level, people'removed massive obstacles to freedom<br />
and created liberal democratic societies. That power in that idea gave<br />
birth to free societies.<br />
Today, while people still believe that democracy is better than<br />
other systems, there has emerged a doubt about the capacity<br />
of our system to cope with contemporary problems, and a complacency<br />
about the security of democratic institutions and values.<br />
This doubt, this complacency must be dispelled. We must<br />
revive the power and vitality of liberal democracy's fundamental idea.-<br />
The importance of free people in human affairs; the fact that free<br />
men andwomen can influence and shape reality not merely reflect it.<br />
So long as we do this, so long as we do not lose our sense of<br />
ourselves, our sense of purpose, and so long as we seek to understand<br />
and strengthen one another, we will surmount whatever challenges there<br />
may be. 000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
