<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16743</transcript-id>
    <title>Government to work with AFL to kick goals for climate change  Prime Minister Minister for Climate Change Minister for Sport</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/08/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>On the eve of the first ever ‘Green Round', the Rudd Government is teaming up with the Australian Football League (AFL) to help footy fans take action on climate change.</p>
<p>A new partnership between the Government and the AFL will promote action that fans and players can take on climate change, and help grass roots football clubs become more climate friendly.</p>
<p>Australians want to do their bit to tackle climate change, and this partnership will help AFL fans and footy clubs achieve that.</p>
<p>Activities under the partnership could include:</p>
<p>•                an interactive climate change awareness program for families and children involved in junior football programs;</p>
<p>•                a targeted carbon pollution reduction program across the AFL and grass roots footy clubs; and</p>
<p>•                the introduction of a new program to support local clubs taking action on climate change to reduce their carbon pollution and save money on energy bills.</p>
<p>There are simple things that football fans can do to be a part of the climate change solution, even while watching or playing their favourite game.</p>
<p>The AFL will be encouraging footy fans to use public transport, cycle or car pool to get to games this week for the Green Round.</p>
<p>When fans leave home for the Green Round this week, they can turn lights and heating off and make sure appliances are switched off at the wall.</p>
<p>The Government welcomes the AFL's decision to actively and publicly be a part of the climate change solution and looks forward to building on the partnership announced today.</p>
<p>Australians have made it clear they want the Government to take action on climate change and we know that the time to act is now.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
