<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10591</transcript-id>
    <title>Enhancing Business and Community Sector Partnerships </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today I wish to announce measures to improve links between Australian businesses and the community sector.</p>
<p>The community sector comprises a large number of non-profit organisations engaged in a broad range of activities including welfare service delivery, sporting and cultural pursuits. These organisations typically rely heavily on volunteer assistance, and each year around 2.5 million Australians participate in voluntary work.</p>
<p>Many of these organisations have special insights and capacities to resolve social problems, and can provide a vital integrating force between different sectors of society.</p>
<p>While governments have an on-going role in facilitating the community sector's work, including financial support, the business sector also has a role to play.</p>
<p>Consultations indicate a strong interest by business to become more involved, as only a small proportion of the non-profit community sector's funding is derived from corporate Australia.</p>
<p>As a result the Government has decided on the following approaches to promote closer partnerships:</p>
<p>* I will convene a round table of business and community leaders early next year to develop specific strategies to improve business and community sector partnerships;</p>
<p>* from 1998 I will present Prime Ministerial awards in recognition of business and individual philanthropy;</p>
<p>* the Minister for Family Services, Warwick Smith, will examine other ways to improve philanthropic recognition, to educate Australians about philanthropy and enhance links between the business and community sectors.</p>
<p>Strong corporate citizenship is an issue I have felt strongly about for many years. Today's announcement follows the recent Business Against Domestic Violence initiative.</p>
<p>On a related matter, I announce the Government will not proceed with the remaining package of recommendations from the Industry Commission's 1995 Report into Charitable Organisations. This announcement will remove any uncertainty within the community sector about the Government's intentions in this regard.</p>
<p>19 November 1997</p>
<p>Today I wish to announce measures to improve links between Australian</p>
<p> businesses and the community sector.</p>
<p>The community sector comprises a large number of non-profit organisations</p>
<p> engaged in a broad range of activities including welfare service delivery,</p>
<p> sporting and cultural pursuits. These organisations typically rely</p>
<p> heavily on volunteer assistance, and each year around 2.5 million</p>
<p> Australians participate in voluntary work.</p>
<p>Many of these organisations have special insights and capacities to</p>
<p> resolve social problems, and can provide a vital integrating force</p>
<p> between different sectors of society.</p>
<p>While governments have an on-going role in facilitating the community</p>
<p> sector's work, including financial support, the business sector</p>
<p> also has a role to play.</p>
<p>Consultations indicate a strong interest by business to become more</p>
<p> involved, as only a small proportion of the non-profit community sector's</p>
<p> funding is derived from corporate Australia.</p>
<p>As a result the Government has decided on the following approaches</p>
<p> to promote closer partnerships:</p>
<p>* I will convene a round table of business and community leaders early</p>
<p> next year to develop specific strategies to improve business and community</p>
<p> sector partnerships;</p>
<p>* from 1998 I will present Prime Ministerial awards in recognition</p>
<p> of business and individual philanthropy;</p>
<p>* the Minister for Family Services, Warwick Smith, will examine other</p>
<p> ways to improve philanthropic recognition, to educate Australians</p>
<p> about philanthropy and enhance links between the business and community</p>
<p> sectors.</p>
<p>Strong corporate citizenship is an issue I have felt strongly about</p>
<p> for many years. Today's announcement follows the recent Business</p>
<p> Against Domestic Violence initiative.</p>
<p>On a related matter, I announce the Government will not proceed with</p>
<p> the remaining package of recommendations from the Industry Commission's</p>
<p> 1995 Report into Charitable Organisations. This announcement will</p>
<p> remove any uncertainty within the community sector about the Government's</p>
<p> intentions in this regard.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
