<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10289</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS CHAMBER OF COMMERCE LUNCHEON, SHANGHAI, BEIJING</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010289.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from<br />
MAR 30 ' 97 04: 07P 38/ 03/ 97 28: 52<br />
Mairch 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON . JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS<br />
CHAMBER OF COMMERCE LUNCHEON, SHANGHAI, BEIJING<br />
E O E<br />
Question: Mr Prime Minister ( inaudible) Air International. There has been a lot of discussion here<br />
about Australian businesses and their future in China, I think Australian businesses show<br />
the same tenacity and determination to never say die, the ability to comeback from<br />
nowhere as you have in your political career then they are guaranteed-of success in China.<br />
Would you agree?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I've never met him before in my life.. I promise you that. Yes.: of course I do.<br />
Question: Stephen Morgan from the University of Melbourne. We've talked a bit about services<br />
and the importance of promoting Australian services and technology, Quite clearly there<br />
are opportunities here. What do you think are the prospects for, say the insurance sector,<br />
in the near future ie Colonial Mutual or National Mutual winning a ( inaudible) operating<br />
licence? Prime Minister:<br />
I have to say they are good. hi fact I hope they are very good. And I will certainly be<br />
pursuing that cause in Beijing in the discussions that I have with th Premier and-also<br />
with the President, most particularly with the Premier and with the Vice Ptemier and the<br />
other leaders with whom I will be having a dialogue. I think the importance and the real Pg: 1<br />
P. 1/ 4 </p>
<p>Fax fromt 30/ 03/ 97 20: 52 pg: 2<br />
significance of the fact that this is a combined grovernment and businiess mission to China<br />
is that it demonstrates the commitment of the Australian government to the cause of<br />
Australian business in China. The seniority of the bxisiness delegation demionstrates the<br />
seriousness with which the business community in Australia views that association and<br />
also very importantly it communicates to the Chinese government the fact that we are<br />
Working together and I think that is important. Sometimes in the Austral 1an context there<br />
can be the view that the goverrnent aind the business community is not always working<br />
together and sometimes It's a good ideafor the business community not to hear anything<br />
from the government for a while because sometimes goverments gei in the way of<br />
business. But when you are dealing with other nations with other societies, when. you are<br />
deulina with systems that are differentr and have their ow, n pm-ticular way of doing things,<br />
it is important I think to communicate that mnessage that we are looking at China together.<br />
We won't always agree with everything that is put forward by a constituent part of the<br />
business coiz'unity and it may in turm not always -agree with every sigedecision the<br />
government has taken but what has pleased rme inunonsely about what wve have been able<br />
to put together over the last little: while and is represented here x'~ ry much in this room, is<br />
a determined partnership between the two of us to do something for the national ii~ terest<br />
and we are certainly not going to leave any stone unturned in trying to achieve that goal.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, Serena Lilywhite from ( inaudible) University. I am very encouraged by<br />
your governxnents commitment to-the Asia Pacific region. However, I would like to har<br />
from you as to howv you believe the possible demise of Radio Australiamay be<br />
interpreted in this region and I certainly hope that it doesn't happen. Tiank you.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, that is a decision that will be.* taken ultimately will be taken in a sense in the<br />
context of our Budget preparations but the option of phasing down Radio Australia is an<br />
option that emerged initially fromn within the ABC as a method of achieving the<br />
expenditure savings that had been fixed by the Expenditure Review Committed of our<br />
Cabinet. We did, in Australia the new Government did inherit a underlying deficit of<br />
billion and with one or two exceptionas tvery iector has hiad to make a contribution and<br />
the ultinmate decision is really a question of priorities itot entirely or certainly not alone<br />
within the government but also within the ABC itself and I understand the importance,<br />
attached to Radio Australia by some parts of the Asi4 Pacific region. I also recognise that<br />
in oqter parts the type of service offered by Radio Australia has been-to a significat<br />
dcgrce replaced by different technology and different delivery systems. Now I know that<br />
doesn't apply to some of the remoter areas of China and I know it doesn't apply in Some<br />
of the other remoter areas of the region but cert ainly the advances that have occurred in<br />
rcwnt years have dramnatically altered the relative significance of Radio Australia. So<br />
that is the background and we will be taking a decision in discussion with the Australian<br />
Broadcasting Corporation but you must understand that the initial impetus for it was as an<br />
option developed within the ABC as a method of achieving the savings. </p>
<p>Fax from 00/ 7205 g<br />
3/ 63/ 7 2: 52 Pg: 3<br />
Question: Mr Prime Minister Glenn ( inaudible) Shanghai ( inaudible) Automotive Suspension<br />
Components. The way You opecaie i this -part of thc world or anywhere else joint<br />
ventures depends largely on the' strength of our holding cdrnpanies back in Australia. We<br />
in the automotive industry here in Shanighai are particularly interested in the direction of<br />
tbe automotive industry and-the future of it in Australia. Would you care to comment on<br />
where you see that going and the future of that industry please.<br />
Prime Mihister:<br />
Yes, I would be very happy to. We -have* a Productivity Commnission fitial report due in<br />
about two months time and the government will then,, I expect quite quickly take a<br />
decision in response to thiat report. And there is a debate about whether and at what rate<br />
there should be further tariff reform in Australia. I've said a number of things which have<br />
put down some principles about how we would approach it. We'll endeavour to take a<br />
decision which is in the overall interests of the Australian co mmnilty and the Australian<br />
economy. We will also be very mindful of the hipoitunce of preserving a stiong motor<br />
manufacturing capacity in Australia. I have said on a number of occasions in the past. and<br />
I amn very happy to iepeat it'here, I can't envisage Australia without an effective and<br />
strong motor manufacturing capacity. Now you are aware and all the Austxaiians in the<br />
room arnd I'm sate all of the Chinese peopic in the rooin are equally awNare that the debate<br />
about tariff reform and change aud the contribution it makes to employment is an old<br />
debate and its ani ongoing debate. There is littki doubt in my mind that Australia has<br />
enormous benefits to reap from greater trade liberal isation. It's always bard to sell in a<br />
political -sense the broader benefits of trade liberalisatian because what you're really<br />
talking about is the movement of capital into areas which it is not previously been<br />
invested and it is a lot harder to benchmark, to measure and to say weU,. as a result of this<br />
decision we've created 500 jobs. It is always a l ittle easy to say if there is an industry<br />
protection change made or a tariff chanige wnade. As a result of that a certain niumber of<br />
jobs have been lost but I think it is imaportant to remember, particularly in the context of<br />
the Asia Pacific region that trade liberplisation underpins APEC.<br />
Without trade liberalisation and the common commitment of dhe mnemnber states of APEC<br />
to trade liberalisation, we won't achieve those goals and we won't get tho jobs that new<br />
investment in industries, itew industries will provide to the populations of those<br />
countries. These decisions are never easy and you can never reduce argumnents about<br />
industry protection to simplicities but we ' ll1 endeavour to take a dccision that fits those<br />
broad criteria and I want to see a motor manufacturing capacityv in Australia. I think the<br />
quality of the Australian motor industry has improved enormously oVer the last 20 years.<br />
It really has and it's achieved things, particularly in the export area that a lot of people<br />
didn't think possible. Some of that achievement has been the result of competitive<br />
pressures of industry policy anid wv've got to bear that in-miad so it's rcally ia question of<br />
marrying all of those considations up but I can assure you that we're not. going to a sort 3 </p>
<p>Fax from of a slash a burn approach to tariff policy. ccrtainly not. On the other hand 1 don't think<br />
it's something that can be reduced to simplicities and if the ultimate. goal is a more, a<br />
greater degree of liberalisation, particularly in the context of APEC than obviously you<br />
have to keep that goal firmly in front of you. 38/ 83/ 97 20: 52 Pg: 4 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
