<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8114</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, MADANG RESORT HOTEL, MADANG - 5 SEPTEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008114.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, MADANG RESORT HOTEL, J4ADANGSEPTEMBER<br />
1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, is there likely to be any fall-Out<br />
from the Daily Mirror's article<br />
PM: some fall-out within the Daily Mirror. But I've<br />
said all I want to say about it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is Mr Nainaliu likely to say anything about it?<br />
PM: He was very grateful that I said what I did and I think<br />
he hopes that that will have its effect. It ought to.<br />
JOURNALIST: As it comes towards the end of your trip, how<br />
would you describe it?<br />
PM: It's been eminently successful. It's been frank,,<br />
direct. The Prime Minister and his Ministers have put<br />
themselves at my disposal and all the issues between us have<br />
been discussed in the most amicable and direct and<br />
constructive way. I believe that as a result of the visit<br />
the relationship's on an even firmer foundation and we will<br />
see ways in which the forms of assistance that we give can<br />
be made even more relevant, I think, to the issues and<br />
problems confronting the country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have the concerns of the<br />
expatriot Australian businessmen here in any way altered<br />
your perceptions of the problems of law and order in this<br />
country? PM: No. They weren't overboard about the issue. They<br />
rightly and understandably stressed the significance of it.<br />
But they also indicated the confidence they have in the<br />
country. I think they have the right sort of balance about<br />
it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you said in your speech, you<br />
talked of possible restructuring of PNG defence forces. Do<br />
you think that it's possible that PNG is better served with<br />
a single security force, amalgamation of police and defence<br />
forces? PM: The issue has theoretically been in the minds of some<br />
people. And if you were looking at it theoretically you<br />
could argue that case. But we don't live in a theoretical </p>
<p>world. The fact is that you have now developed two separate<br />
forces, the military forces and the constabulary. I think<br />
the important thing is to look at how the provisioning<br />
aspects of training can be to some extent co-ordinated. I<br />
think there are ways probably and I think our friends here<br />
in New Guinea think that. There are ways in which there may<br />
be able to be some greater degree of co-ordination. But I<br />
think the reality is that the two separate entities would<br />
remain. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, your discussions on constitutional<br />
change here, does that give you any more confidence that a<br />
halt will come to the turnstile government up here?<br />
PK: What is clear from the conversations I've had is that<br />
both within the opposition and the Government there is a<br />
conviction that there has to be reform followed through<br />
which will bring an end to the possibility of constant<br />
change so that there can be a greater period in which<br />
governments can be sure that they will be immune from these<br />
destabilising no-confidence motions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Any details about helping PNG with the<br />
reconstruction on Bougainville?<br />
PM: No, they didn't want us to pursue that in any detail at<br />
the moment. it was premature. All they wanted to know, and<br />
I was prepared to say, that once they'd settled the issue<br />
between themselves that they should know that we'd be<br />
prepared to help. That's as far as it went.<br />
JOURNALIST: And your assessment now of-the future of<br />
Bougainville? PM: Well one can't be immediately confident. But I would<br />
have thought that now that the people up there have seen the<br />
preparedness of the central government to actually deliver<br />
the goods and services, they were there ready to be<br />
delivered, and the people on Buka, ordinary people seem to<br />
want then delivered, but it was prevented by the<br />
intervention of the BRA. I think that will have its own'<br />
impact in its way.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have you had a chance to talk<br />
to the new Prime Minister of New Zealand and if so what have<br />
you said to him?<br />
PM: I haven't spoken to him in his capacity as Prime<br />
Minister. Of course I've known him and I've spoken to-him<br />
in the past. I have sent a message to Geoffrey Palmer and<br />
there has been a message sent to Mike Moore. We wish them<br />
all well.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, it's been said in the past that<br />
you were more pessimistic about PNG's future than some other<br />
members of your Cabinet. Are you, after having been here<br />
for four days, been outside Port Moresby, more. optimistic: of<br />
this country's future? </p>
<p>PM: I think the right way of putting it is that I've<br />
probably got a detailed, a more detailed knowledge of Papua<br />
New Guinea, its history, its creation as an independent<br />
nation than probably anyone else in the cabinet. I don't<br />
say that egotistically. It just happens to be the fact<br />
through my long experience going back to the 60s here that<br />
I'm. able to say that. So I was perhaps a bit more conscious<br />
than some of my colleagues of the range of rather deep<br />
problems that confront the country. I think what I can say<br />
is that following this visit I've got a firmer degree'of<br />
assurance in my mind a) of the fact that the leaders here<br />
understand the nature of those problems and b) are committed<br />
to addressing them. That gives me confidence.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, did Mr Namnaliu express to you any<br />
concerns about the sort of media coverage, and in particular<br />
the business at the Travelodge<br />
PM: Yes he did. He was very very upset about it. And in<br />
my opinion, understandably so.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did it concern you though that raskols were<br />
able to break into the hotel, a hotel where the Prime<br />
minister was staying?<br />
PM: Not as much as the absolute misrepresentation and<br />
beatup in the papers concerned me. That was much more of<br />
concern. JOURNALIST: In discussions about the Defence<br />
Co-operation Treaty, were there suggestions that it should<br />
be altered in any way?<br />
PM: Not the structure of the Treaty and the framework<br />
within which we co-operate. The area to which the talks<br />
went were what is the best sort of PNGDF for the governments<br />
of Papua New Guinea in the future to look together at the<br />
issues of what possible changes there may be in training and<br />
so on that will best equip them for that future task. So<br />
that's what the talks were about, rather than changing the<br />
framework within which we operate.<br />
JOURNALIST: equipment too. Was there a suggestion that<br />
maybe there's too much reliance on Australian equipment?<br />
PM: That point wasn't specifically raised. But I think<br />
there won't be any limits to the range of discussions we'll<br />
have. The important thing that's been agreed is that we are<br />
at one in saying that it's sensible to look at how the PNGDF<br />
is equipped, trained and how it operates and are there ways<br />
in which together we can make it better equipped for future<br />
tasks-That has all been on the basis of not us saying<br />
that's what's got to happen but a shared view of it. They<br />
understand that Australia speaks from a position of having<br />
now since independence put something like half a billion<br />
dollars into the PNGDF. So we have a real interests </p>
<p>A 6<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it possible that pol-ice training could<br />
come under the Defence Co-operation program?<br />
PM: We've discussed that and I'd just like to say these<br />
things and I'm sure Rabbie would like to make his<br />
comments. I think it's right to say that we agree that<br />
as far as you can see into the future there will be two<br />
separate PNGDF and there will be the police. But I<br />
think we both agree that there will be a complementarity<br />
of their roles in many respects and that it may be that<br />
you can get a degree of integration in regard to<br />
procurement issues perhaps and some elements of training.<br />
So in our thinking about the PNGDF we'd be thinking about<br />
that side as well.<br />
JOURNALIST: on Bougainville, what is the<br />
Government's stand now that the suspended provincial<br />
government that's refused to recognise the administrator<br />
that you appointed.<br />
NAMALIU: The administrator is appointed under our<br />
constitution under the law of provincial government.<br />
As far as we are concerned, he is the administrator of<br />
the province.<br />
JOURNALIST: control of the situation again. Is that<br />
true? NAMALIU: I think it is more likely to that description<br />
is more apt for the BRA leadership than it is for the<br />
position JOURNALIST: You are not dealing with the BRA.<br />
NAMALIU: That's right.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you dealing with them?<br />
NAMALIU: The BRA?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
NAMALIU: Well as you know, there are leaders who have<br />
been involved in the negotiations which resulted in the<br />
Accord that belong to the BRA. There are those that<br />
belong to the self-styled government of the republic<br />
of the North Solomons. There are those that come from<br />
the community generally. So they are the leaders that we<br />
were dealing with. They were Bougainville leaders and we<br />
would like to regard them as that rather than belonging<br />
to a specific group like the BRA.<br />
JOURNALIST: Who are they<br />
NAMALIU: You know who they are. You know Mr Kabui, you<br />
know Bishop Singkai, you know Mr Peter sorry, not<br />
Peter, but you know the other people involved. It<br />
includes people who are very close to Mr Ona. But Mr </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
