<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6222</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/10/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006222.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-j AU6 RALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 5 October 1983<br />
The Leader of the Opposition was briefed this afternoon on the<br />
reasons for, and the timing of, Australian Federal Police<br />
decisions to connect, disconnect, reconnect and disconnect<br />
certain authorised telephone intercepts.<br />
He was briefed in my office by the Commissioner of the Australian<br />
Federal Police, Mr R. A. Grey, as to the facts.<br />
Mr Peacock was told that all decisions to discontinue telephone<br />
intercepts were made by Commuissioner Grey personally and that<br />
no political or other pressure was brought to bear upon him in<br />
respect of such decisions.<br />
Some intercepts were later reinstated at the request of<br />
Mr Justice Stewart.<br />
The Government would, in normal circumstances, be most<br />
reluctant to disclose any details of police operations.<br />
However, I was gravely concerned at the imputations by the<br />
Leader of the Opposition that the AFP had been influenced by<br />
political pressure in the conduct of a drug offences<br />
investigation. No more serious charge could be made against the integrity of any<br />
police force.<br />
Because of the damage these allegations could do to the standing<br />
and morale of the AFP if left unchallenged it was decided that<br />
Mr Peacock should be made aware of the facts and the complete lack<br />
of foundation for the imputations he has made.<br />
In these circumstances, and with the knowledge that he now<br />
possesses, Mr Peacock should immediately withdraw any imputations<br />
against the integrity of Commissioner Grey and the AEP. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
