<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3508</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT OUR LADY OF MERCY COLLEGE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON. E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., ON DECEMBER 1 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003508.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SKL( H AT OUR LADY OF NF RCY (' 01. I l<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON. E. G. WHITLAM, MY.,<br />
ON DECEMBER i, 1974.<br />
YOUR EMINENCE, SISTER PAULINE, DISTINGUISHED GUESTS,<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN AND, ESPECIALLY, GIRLS.<br />
YOU WILL PROBABLY KNOW THAT I HAVE RETURNED<br />
FROM CAMPAIGNING IN QUEENSLAND IN ORDER TO KEEP A LONG<br />
STANDING PROMISE TO MY COLLEAGUE RAY THORBURN, M. P. FOR<br />
COOK, IT WAS VERY TEMPTING TO STAY NQRTH OF THE<br />
BRISBANE LINE, ESPECIALLY AS TODAY IS THE 75TH ANNIVERSARY<br />
OF THE WORLD'S FIsrT LABOR GOVERNMENT, A QUEENSLAND<br />
GOVERNMENT, HELD UNDER A TREE AT BARCALDINE ON THE TROPIC<br />
OF CAPRICORN. I AM NOTHING IF NOT ALIVE TO THE LURE OF<br />
ANNIVERSARIES. THEY PROVIDE SPLENDID OPPORTUNITIES FOR<br />
SAYING ALL THOSE THINGS THERE IS NORMALLY LITTLE CALL FOR<br />
SAYING. TODAY, OF COURSE, IS A VERY SPECIAL DAY FOR<br />
OUR LADY OF MERCY COLLEGE. I AM SURE IT WILL ENTER YOUR<br />
ANNALS AS A SPECIAL ANNIVERSARY ALONG WITH MORE SANCTIFIED<br />
FEAST DAYS. AT THE SAME TIME, TODAY IS A VERY SPECIAL<br />
DAY FOR ME. </p>
<p>IT IS TWO YEARS TODAY SINCE MY LAST DAY AS<br />
LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION IN THE AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENT.<br />
IT IS TWO YEARS TOMORROW SINCE THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE<br />
RETURNED MY PARTY To GOVERNMENT THE FIRST AUSTRALIAN<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT IN 23 YEARS. IN THE LAST FEW DAYS<br />
I HAVE INDULGED IN SOME NOSTALGIA IN VARIOUS RADIO AND<br />
TELEVISION INTERVIEWS. IN EACH INTERVIEW AND I<br />
SHOULD NOTE IN PARTICULAR AT THIS GATHERING THE ONEI<br />
GAVE To 2SMl ST MARY'S IN SYDNEY I WAS ASKED WHAT<br />
ICONSIDERED OUR GREATEST ACHIEVEMENT IN THOSE TWO<br />
SHORT BUT VERY FULL YEARS. IN EACH ANSWER I REPLIED<br />
UNHESITATINGLY: EDUCATION. IHAD BECOME THE MEMBER OF<br />
THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES FOR THIS DISTRICT 25 YEARS<br />
AGO. IN MY FIRST YEAR IN PARLIAMENT I TWICE URGED THAT<br />
THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE TO TAKE THE SAME<br />
DEGREE OI INTEREST IN SCHOOL EDUCATION AS IT WAS ALREADY<br />
TAKING IN UNIVERSITY EDUCATION.<br />
SO IT IS MOST APPROPRIATE THAT I SHOULD OPT OUT<br />
OF A POLITICAL CAMPAIGN TO COME HERE TODAY IN ORDER TO<br />
PARTICIPATE IN THE OPENING AND DEDICATION OF YOUR NEW<br />
LIBRARY BLOCK. THIS IS A TANGIBLE ILLUSTRATION OF MY<br />
BELIEF THAT LABOR'IS OUTSTANDING MONUMENT WILL PROVE TO BE<br />
WHAT WE HAVE TRIED TO DO, WHAT WE HAVE ACHIEVED, IN THE<br />
EDUCATIONAL FIELD. . t3/, </p>
<p>THERE HAS NEVER BEEN ANY QUALIFICATION ABOUT<br />
my GOVERNMENT'S COMMITMENT TO EDUCATION.<br />
IN MY POLICY SPEECH IN NOVEMBER 1972. JUST<br />
TWO YEARS AGO, I PROMISED THAT EDUCATION WOULD B E THE<br />
MOST RAPIDLY GROWING SECTOR OF PUBLIC SPENDING UNDER A<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT. I SAID THEN: " EDUCATION SHOULD<br />
BE THE GREAT INSTRUMENT FOR THE PROMOTION OF EQUALITY."<br />
WE SAW EDUCATION AS THE PRIMARY INSTRUME NT FOR IMPROVING<br />
THE QUALITY OF LIFE FOR OUR PEOPLE AND PROMOTING EQUALITY<br />
OF OPPORTUNITY FOR OUR CHILDREN. WE PROPOSED A NEW<br />
CHARTER FOR THE CHILDREN OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
WITHIN A YEAR THAT CHARTER HAD BEEN PROCLAIMED,<br />
ITS MAI-N PROMISES ENACTED, ITS ESSENTIAL FUNDS PROVIDED.-<br />
ITS INSTITUTIONAL FORMS ESTABLISHED. ITS GREAT AND<br />
LASTING BENEFITS CONTINUE TO FLOW TO THE CHILDREN OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, ALL OVER AUSTRALIA.<br />
MY OWN EXTENSIVE TRAVELLING THROUGH THE LENGTH<br />
AND BREADTH OF QUEENSLAND IN THE LAST FEW WEEKS HAS<br />
CONFIRMED ME IN MY RESOLUTION THAT CHILDREN EVERYWHAERE<br />
IN AUSTRALIA ARE ENTITLED TO, AND SHOULD RECEIVE, AS<br />
EXCELLENT AN EDUCATION AS CHILDREN AN{ YWHERE IN AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>IF YOU GO TO SCHOOL AT BURRANEER YOU SHOULD HAVE THE<br />
SAME GOOD OPPORTUNITIES AS IF YOU GO TO SCHOOL IN<br />
BRISBANE OR AT BURNIE IN TASMANIA OR AT BRIDGETOWN IN<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA. IF PARENTS'ARE OBLIGED TO MOVE<br />
INTERSTATE TO PURSUE EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES, THEY<br />
SHOULD NOT HAVE TO WORRY ABOUT THE QUALITY OF<br />
EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITY AVAILABLE FOR THEIR SCHOOL<br />
CHILDREN, IAM QUITE SURE THAT THE GREAT CATHOLIC<br />
TEACHING ORDERS WHICH HAVE DONE SO MUCH TO PROMOTE<br />
SCHOOLING IN THIS GREAT BUT STILL YOUNG COUNTRY OF OURS<br />
WOULD HAVE NO QUARREL WITH my GOVERNMENT' S DESIRE. TO<br />
PROMOTE THE INTERESTS OF THE CHILD IN RELATION TO THE<br />
TOTAL COMMUNITY. THE DEDICATED NUNS AND BROTHERS WHO<br />
LEFT ALL THAT WAS DEAR TO THEM IN IRELAND IN ORDER TO'<br />
UNDERTAKE THE LONG INHOSPITABLE VOYAGE TO SMALL PARISH<br />
SCHOOLS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA WERE VERY'REAL EXPONENTS<br />
OF THE DESIRE TO GIVE PEOPLE AND ESPECIALLY THE<br />
CHILDREN IN THEI" R CARE A PROPER CHANCE IN LIFE.<br />
.85/. 9 </p>
<p>ONLY TWO WEEKS AGO I HAD THE VERY REAL PRIVILEGE<br />
OF ATTENDING A DINNER IN MELBOURNE IN HONOUR OF THAT CITY' S<br />
NEW CATHOLIC ARCHBISHOP. DR FRANK LITTLE. AN IMPRESSIVE<br />
AND CHARMING MAN, ARCHBISHOP LITTLE WAS, AMONGST OTHER<br />
MORE OBVIOUSLY EXALTED TITLES, PARISH PRIEST OF ST MONICA'S<br />
IN THE MELBOURNE SUBURB OF MOONEE PONDS WHEN HE WAS<br />
APPOINTED ARCHBISHOP OF MELBOURNE. HE HAD ATTENDED<br />
ST MONICA'S SCHOOL AS A CHILD IN THAT PARISH. LIKE SO<br />
MANY OF THE HIERARCHY OF THE CATHOLIC CHURCH IN AUSTRALIA.-<br />
HE HAS A VERY REAL APPRECIATION OF THE PROBLEMS WHICH HAVE<br />
FACED THE PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS IN THE PAST AND OF THEIR<br />
VERY REAL NEEDS IN TRYING TO COPE WITH THE DEMANDS PLACED<br />
ON THEM BY EXPANDING SCHOOL POPULATIONS AT A TIME* OF<br />
INCREASING SOPHISTICATION IN THE TECHNOLOGY OF EDUCATION.<br />
THE SAME PROBLEMS ARE AFFLICTING CATHOLIC<br />
SECONDARY SCHOOLS. OUR LAD OF MERCY COLLEGE HAS A TOTAL<br />
ENROLMENT OF 496 GIRLS, ENCOMPASSING THE YEARS FROM FORM I<br />
TO SCHOOL CERTIFICATE. I UNDERSTAND THAT WHAT WOULD BE<br />
AND 6TH FORMS ARE EFFECTIVELY COMBINED AT DE LA SALLE<br />
AND THIS IS A SENSIBLE WAY OF ACCOMMODATING THE FINAL YEARS<br />
OF SECONDARY EDUCATION. BUT INCREASING COSTS MAKE THE<br />
PROSPECT OF RUNNING A SECONDARY SCHOOL OF ANY SIZE SOMETHING<br />
LESS THAN A SUNDAY-SCHOOL PICNIC. WE RECOGNISE THIS AND<br />
HAVE TAKEN SPECIAL MEASURES TO HELP. 116/ 1 </p>
<p>61<br />
IWAS, THEREFORE, DELIGHTED TO READ<br />
ARCHBISHOP CARROLL'S RECENT REMARKS PAYING TRIBUTE<br />
TO THAT ASPECT OF OUR APPROACH TO EDUCATION. HE<br />
WAS SPEAKING AT THE OPENING OF A NEW SCHOOL LIBRARY<br />
IN MARRICKVILLE, STRANGE HOW ATTRACTIVE LIBRARIES<br />
ARE TO US ALL, AND HOW LOQUACIOUS THEY MAKE ARCHBISHOPS<br />
AND PRIME MINISTERS ALIKE.<br />
ARCHBISHOP CARROLL SAID: " UN DER THE MANY<br />
PRESSURES OF THE POST-WAR YEARS, CATHOLIC SCHOOLS HAVE<br />
BEEN THREATENED WITH WHOLESALE CLOSURE DUE TO MOUNTING<br />
FINANCIAL PROBLEMS.<br />
" HOWEVER, WE ARE BOTH PLEASED AND PROUD TO<br />
RECORD THAT SUCCESSIVE GOVERNMENTS, STATE AND FEDERAL,<br />
HAVE ENABLED NON-GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS TO SURVIVE AND<br />
PROSPER BY MAKING AVAILABLE GRANTS, FIRST FOR RECURRENT<br />
COSTS, THEN FOR CAPITAL, NOW ALSO FOR MANY SPECIAL<br />
PROGRAMS, SUCH A\ S FOR DISADVANTAGED AREAS, FOR TEACHER<br />
DEVELOPMENT, FOR LIBRARIES..<br />
A WEEK BEFORE, THE CATHOLIC WEEKLY REPORTED<br />
ON THE MOST RECENT MEETING OF THE NATIONAL CATHOLIC<br />
EDUCATION COUNCIL i@ 71e </p>
<p>THE COUNCIL WAS KIND ENOUGH TO ADOPT THE<br />
FOLLOWING RESOLUTIONS:-" THE NCEC ACKNOWLEDGES AND APPRECIATES THE<br />
ACTION OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IN MAKING<br />
SUPPLEMENTARY GRANTS IN THE 1974 BUDGET, THEREBY<br />
INCREASING EDUCATIONAL FUNDS FOR 1974 AND 1975 TO<br />
OFFSET THE EFFECTS OF INFLATION ON THE VALUE OF'GRANT S<br />
PREVIOUSLY ANNOUNCED, AND<br />
" THE NCEC IS PLEASED TO SEE THAT THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS COMMISSION' S REPORT TO THE MINISTER<br />
FOR EDUCATION, SUPPLEMENTARY FUNDS FOR PROGRAMS<br />
ADMINISTERED BY THE SCHOOLS COMMISSION, WHICH FOLLOWS<br />
LINES RECOMMENDED BY THE NCEC AND OTHER INTERESTED<br />
BODIES, WAS ACCEPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT."<br />
NATURALLY, I AM DELIGHTED TO LEARN THAT OUR<br />
EDUCATION PROGRAM HAS SUCH RESPONSIBLE ENDORSEMENT<br />
FROM THE NATIONAL CATHOLIC EDUCATION COUNCIL.<br />
BUT I WOULD BE LESS THAN FAIR TO THE COUNCIL<br />
AND THE CATHOLIC WEEKLY IF I DID NOT ALSO REFER TO<br />
ANOTHER COUNCIL RESOLUTION FROM THE SAME CANBERRA<br />
MEETING. </p>
<p>THE COUNCIL REGRETTED THAT THE AMOUNT<br />
ALLOWABLE IN CALCULATING INCOME FAX AS A DEDUCTION<br />
FROM INCOME FOR EDUCATION EXPENSES WAS " tABRUPTLY<br />
AND SEVERELY DIMINISHED"<br />
THE COUNCIL BELIEVED THAT THIS ACTIONWOULD<br />
HAVE A SIGNIFICANT ADVERSE EFFECT ON THE<br />
FINANCIAL CONDITION OF PARENTS WHO MAINTAIN CHILDREN<br />
IN NON-GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS, PARTICULARLY-AT THE<br />
SECONDARY LEVEL. THE CATHOLIC WEEKLY ALSO STATED IN AN EDITORIAL<br />
IN THE SAME ISSUE:<br />
" MR. WHITLAM'S DECISION NOT TO RESTORE THE<br />
STUDENT TAX CONCESSION MAY BE THE MOST DISASTROUS HEHAS<br />
EVER MADE. s<br />
" No MATTER WHAT CLAIMS ARE MADE THAT INDEPENDENT<br />
SCHOOLS NOW RECEIVE ' STATE-AID', THE MERE FACT OF<br />
REDUCING THE TAX DEDUCTION HAS DEPRIVED THOSE SCHOOLS<br />
OF SOME FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE AND INSTEAD OF BRINGING<br />
THEIR PUPULS TO EQUITY WITH THOSE AT STATE SCHOOLS, IS<br />
TAKING THEM BACK TO OLD TIMES."/ 1 19/, </p>
<p>9.<br />
TH E EDITORIAL GOES ON TO SAY THAT THE DECISION<br />
IS DISASTROUS TO PARENT TAX-PAYERS AND ItTHAT IT IS<br />
DISASTROUS ON PRINCIPLE BECAUSE IT RESTORES THE OLD<br />
PRACTICE OF DISCRIMINATION IN EDUCATION, TAXATION JUSTICE<br />
AND CITIZENSHIP RIGHTS."<br />
HARSH WORDS INDEED ABOUT AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT WHICH HAS DONE MORE THAN* ANY OTHER AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT IN HISTORY TO DO AWAY WITH DISCRIMINATION IN<br />
ALL -ITS GUISES, TO ADHERE TO THE PRINCIPLE OF TAXATION<br />
JUSTICE AND TO ENCOURAGE EVERYONE TO EXERCISE HIS OR<br />
HER RIGHTS AS A PERSON, CITIZEN OR OTHERWISE.<br />
Now, I CAN UNDERSTAND WHY MANY OF YOU ARE<br />
CONCERNED ABOUT my GOVERNMENT'S DECISION THAT THE FIGURE I<br />
SHOULD COME DOWN FROM $ 40OO PER YEAR MAXIMUM DEDUCTION<br />
TO $ 150 A YEAR MAXIMUM DEDUCTION. BUT I REFUTE<br />
ABSOLUTELY THE SUGGESTION OF THE CATHOLIC WEEKLY EDITORIAL<br />
THAT IT REPR" ESENTS A RETURN TO THE BAD OLD DAYS.<br />
NOTHING COULD BE FURTHER FROM THE TRUTH. IWELCOME<br />
THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLAIN THAT DECISION TO YOU TODAY. </p>
<p>TO EXPLAIN PROPERLY, I MUST TAKE YOU BACK<br />
TO THE EARLY YEARS OF THE MENZIES REIGN WHEN THE<br />
DEDUCTION WAS FIRST INTRODUCED. IN 1952/ 53, THE<br />
DEDUCTION WAS $ 100 WHICH WAS A NOT INCONSIDERABLE<br />
AMOUNT OF MONEY THE YEAR THE QUEEN WAS CROWNED, THE<br />
YEAR MENZIES PROCLAIMED HER QUEEN OF AUSTRALI A, THE<br />
YEAR THEY CONQUERED EVEREST. BUT THAT WAS ALSO A<br />
TIME WHEN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT SPENDING ON EDUCATION<br />
IN THE STATES WAS NON-EXISTENT. IT WAS VERY MUCH<br />
LATER INDEED THAT MENZIES TO HIS ETERNAL CREDIT<br />
FIRST GAVE COMMONWEALTH MONEY, THROUGH GRANTS, TO<br />
THE UNIVERSITIES. IT WAS EVEN BEFORE STATE AID.<br />
THE VERY LEAST THEY COULD DO WAS INSTITUTE A TAXATION<br />
DEDUCTION FOR SCHOOL EXPENDITURE,<br />
IN 1952/ 53 SCHOOLS OTHER THAN THE FEW RICHI<br />
WELL-ENDOWED PRIVATE SCHOOLS, MOST OF THEM NON-CATHOLIC,<br />
WERE REALLY NOT THE KIND OF PLACE WHERE* A THINKING<br />
PARENT OF TODAY WOULD WAN[ HIS OR HER CHILD) REN TO<br />
SPEND WHAT ARE ALWAYS PAINTED AS THE HAPPIEST DAYS OF<br />
OUR LIVES. .11/. </p>
<p>WE HAD, MOST OF USI GONE TO SCHO OL AND LEFT<br />
SCHOOL WITHOUT MUCH COMPLAINT. WE HAD NOT BEEN LED<br />
TO EXPECT ANYTHING BETTER, SO WE DIDN'IT. IF IT WAS<br />
GOOD ENOUGH FOR OUR PARENTS IT WAS GOOD ENOUGH FOR<br />
US, IF IT WAS GOOD ENOUGH FOR US THERE WAS NO<br />
REASON WHY IT SHOULDN'IT BE GOOD ENOUGH FOR OUR<br />
CHILDREN. SOME PARENTS WERE ABLE TO AFFORD TO PAY<br />
TO MAKE IT BETTER; SOME WERE NOT, AND THAT WAS JUST<br />
BAD LUCK FOR THE CHILDREN.<br />
FORTUNATELY, ALL THAT HAS CHANGED, CHANGED<br />
UTTERLY. AND I AM PROUD INDEED THAT ONE OF THE MAIN<br />
REASONS FOR THAT CHANGE IS THE OVERWHELMING BELIEF OF<br />
my GOVERNMENT THAT IT IS ONLY THROUGH EQUALISING THE<br />
EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES OF AIL CHILDREN IN AUSTRALIA<br />
THAT WE CAN FULFIL OUR OBLIGATIONS TO ANY. CHILD IN<br />
AUSTRALIA. IKNOW THIS AUDIENCE TODAY WILL SYMPATHISE<br />
WITH THAT CONTENTION. I K( NOW YOU WILL NOT BEGRUDGE<br />
WHAT WE ARE GI\ VING IN BENEFITS TO CHILDREN LIVING IN<br />
ISOLATED AREAS OF AUSTRALIA, THE QUEENSLAND SITUATION<br />
HAS REMINDED ME VERY FORCIBLY OF THE IMPORTANCE OF THAT<br />
NEW EDUCATIONAL BENEFIT WE INTRODUCED LAST YEAR. </p>
<p>12.<br />
LAST FINANCIAL YEAR WE SPENT OVER $ 8 MILLION TO HELP<br />
OVER 13.. 000 FAMILIES OR 19,000 INDIVIDUAL CHILDREN<br />
IN ISOLATED AREAS WHO UNTIL NOW HAVE SUFFERED<br />
CONSIDERABLE DEPRIVATION BECAUSE OF THE INADEQUACY<br />
OF FURTHER EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES IN THEIR AREAS.<br />
IKNOW YOU WILL NOT BEGRUDGE WHAT WE ARE DOING AT<br />
LAST TO IMPROVE EDUCATION FOR ABORIGINAL CHILDREN.-<br />
FOR MIGRANT CHILDREN,. FOR HANDICAPPED CHILDREN, FOR<br />
AUSTRALIAN CHILDREN WHER EVER, WHOEVER,. THEY MIGHT<br />
HAPPEN TO BE. AND IN CASE YOU ARE WONDERING,. I AM NOT<br />
REALLY GETTING OFF THE TRACK. THE POINT I AM TRYING<br />
TO MAKE IS THAT MY GOVERNMENT IS DOING FAR MORE FOR<br />
INDIVIDUAL AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLCHILDREN THAN ANYONE<br />
MIGHT HAVE DREAMED OF.<br />
AND THAT'S NOT 1-O MENTION OUR CAPITAL<br />
ASSISTANCE PROGRAM,. OR RECURRENT GRANTS,. OR LIBRARY<br />
AND SCIENCE GRANTS,. ALL OF WHICH ARE AVAILABLE AND<br />
HAVE BEEN TAKEN ADVANTAGE OF THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA.<br />
WHAT IT ALL ADDS UP TO IS AN ESTIMATED $ 1,535 MILLION<br />
EXPENDITURE ON EDUCATION BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT1<br />
THIS YEAR. AN INCREASE OF 344L PER CE 4T ON THE LAST<br />
FULL YEAR OF THE LIBERAL-COUNTRY PARTY GOVERNMENT<br />
WHICH SPENT A THEN RECORD OF $ 346 MILLION ON EDUCATION<br />
IN 1971/ 72, It71I </p>
<p>13.<br />
DIRECT EXPENDITURE ON NON-GOVERNMENT SCHOOLS<br />
HAS RISEN FROM $ 39 MILLION IN 1971/ 72 TO AN ESTIMATED<br />
$ 126 MILLION IN 1974/ 75 A RISE OF 223 PER CENT.<br />
So LET ME RETURN TO MY GOVERNMENT'S<br />
DECISION TO REDUCE THE MAXIMUM TAXATION DEDUCTION FROM<br />
$ 400 PER PUPIL TO $ 150 PER PUPIL, IT WAS A DECISION<br />
THAT WAS NOT TAKEN LIGHTLY NOR WANTONLY, IT WAS A<br />
SOUND ECONOMIC DECISION ALBEIT AN UNPOPULAR ONE. No<br />
GOVERNMENT THAT CUTS CONCESSIONS CAN EXPECT TO BE<br />
CHEERED IN THE STREETS, OR, IN THIS CASE, IN THE CHURCH<br />
SCHOOLS. IT WAS A DECISION TAKEN INLINE WITH MY<br />
GOVERNMENT'S GENERAL POLICY OF CUTTING OUT DISGUISED<br />
SUBSIDIES. WHICH IS WHAT THIS WAS.<br />
IN SIMPLE FACT, TREASURY FIGURES INDICATE<br />
THAT* TAX-PAYERS ON HIGHER INCOMES SAVE MlORE THAN THOSE<br />
ON LOWER INCOMES AS A RESULT OF THE PROGRESSIVE TAX<br />
RATE SCALE. IN 1971/ 72 THE GREAT MAJORITY OF TAX-PAYERS<br />
WHOSE CHILDREN ATTENDED GOVERNMENT AND PAROCHIAL<br />
SHCOOLS DID NOT NORMALLY CLAIM AMOUNTS OF MORE THAN<br />
$ 150 P. A. FOR EACH STUDENT CHILD. .1LI/. I.. </p>
<p>141<br />
THE AVERAGE DEDUCTION DID NOT REACH $ 150<br />
UNTIL NET INCOME REACHED $ 9,000. IT CANNOT<br />
REASONABLY BE ASSUMED THAT PEOPLE EARNING $ 9,000<br />
IN 1974/ 75 WOULD SPEND MORE ON AVERAGE THAN $ 150<br />
PER CHILD. My GOVERNMENT DECIDED THAT A CUT-OFF<br />
FIGURE OF $ 150 REPRESENTED A REASONABLE-COMPROMISE.<br />
THE STATISTICS DEMONSTRATE THAT THE HIGHER'<br />
A TAX-PAYERS'IS INCOME, THE MORE LIKELY HE IS TO CLAIM<br />
LARGER DEDUCTIONS FOR EDUCATION EXPENSES.<br />
THE PRESENT TAXATION SCALES ENSURE THAT<br />
WHERE TWO TAXPAYERS CLAIM THE SAME DEDUCTION, THE<br />
TAX-PAYER WITH THE HIGHER INCOME GAINS THE GREATER<br />
BENEF-IT. THE SYSTEM PRODUCES THE SITUATION THAT THE<br />
RICHER THE PARENT, THE MORE DOLLARS HE IS LIKELY TO<br />
CLAIM AND THE MOR~ E HE GETS BACK OUT OF EACH DOLLAR<br />
HE CLAIMS. </p>
<p>iL<br />
I-HIAS NEVER I3LEN LXP" ECTLfD THAT CONCESSIONAL<br />
C( 0V: F LLIL-I id ) 1 URE OF A PERSONAL OR DOMESTIC<br />
NATUJRE. REAL-ISE THAT SOME PEOPLE H1.! E C ( l TO<br />
Yie.~: r THEN AS A RIGHT, BUT THEY ARE NO MiORE THAN<br />
T/ AX CONCE'SSIONS, INUTENDED TO T'AIKE SOME LURDEN FRWi~ l<br />
TAX -PAYlffEf T-lE' ARE NOT IMNiLUTABLE rHOI GM TI EIR<br />
THE 1fE0DrMU C$ L-TDI( Oi( UT O 1iU: UI LL RESULT<br />
A N 1' 0d IN A FUI. L. YEAR OF ' O MMII I NLLVENU'L[-<br />
TliX'T'S NOT REALLY A GRi. AT DEAL. OUT OF OUR' TOTAL<br />
0F. KT 1 3Ur IT DOES MEAIN Ti-AT O iT il I OW HAS EJEFN<br />
r virC fi AC2-i:/ L FUNY' ING -F<br />
L1DUCAIION AT ALL LEVELS. IT IS PART OF THIS YEAR'S<br />
PCCRDil EXPENDITURE OF .$ 1535 MILLION, AND THIS<br />
MILLION WAS TAKEN INTO ACCOUNT WHEN WE WERE<br />
DRAWING UP THIS YEAR' S BUDGET, I REMIND YOU AGAIN<br />
THAT MY GOVTRrINEN1' S DIRECT EXPENDITURE ON<br />
Ixi GOVERNrI1ENr SCHOO1-S THIS YEAR WILL BE $ 1.26 MILLION<br />
At-1 INCREASE OF 223 PER CENT ON THAT OF 1971/ 72 WHEN<br />
THE $ 400 DEDUCTION WOTH $ 30 MILLION APPLIED.<br />
I DON'T EXPECT THAT I HAVE CONVERTED YOU,<br />
BUT I HAVE READ YOU A LITANY OF SOME OF OUR<br />
ACI-IIEVEMENTS IN EDUCATION, OF WHICH IAM LINASHAMEDLY<br />
PROUD. </p>
<p>16.<br />
ISPOKE EARLIER OF INEQUALITIES.<br />
THE KARMEL COMMITTEE REPORT COMMENTED ON<br />
THE INEQUALITY OF EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITY FOR GIRLS.-tI<br />
AND IN JULY THIS YEAR IT WAS DECIDED TO UNDERTAKE<br />
A SPECIAL STUDY OF THE EFFECTS OF SOCIAL CHANGE ON<br />
THE EDUCATIONAL NEEDS OF WOMEN AND GIRLS. THIS I<br />
WIDE RANGING STUDY WILL COVER SUCH AREAS AS<br />
ACHIEVEMENT, VOCATIONAL GUIDANCE, PARENT AND TEACHER<br />
ATTITUDES, TEACHER TRAINING, BEFORE AND AFTER SCHOOLI<br />
CARE, AND ANY OTHER MATTERS AFFECTING THE EDUCATION<br />
OF WOMEN AND GIRLS A FINAL REPORT WILL RECOMMEND<br />
IROGRAM4S AND CHANGES TO CORRECT THE PRESENT IMBALANC'r<br />
WHICH HAS RESTRICTED THE CAREERS AND<br />
TO WOMEN AND GIRLS.<br />
My GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT GIRLS SHOULD II<br />
BE ENCOURAGED TO CONSIDER THE WHOLE RANGE OF OCCUPAT ; IS<br />
N TO THEM. THEY SHOULD BE MAZ-c AWARE OF THlE<br />
POSSIB3ILITIES AND MEANS OF ACHIEVING OL-Cu...<br />
AND NOT MERELY INFORMED OF THE BARRIERS IN THEIR'~.<br />
GROWING FAMILIARITY WITH THE RANGE OF IDEAS<br />
, JND1IN FORMATION AVAILABLE THROUGH YOUR NEW LIBRARY IS<br />
ONCL-DISCOVERING THE POSSIBILITIES OPEN TO YOU.<br />
1. 171. </p>
<p>171<br />
A RECENT EVALUATION REPORT ON OUR LIBRARIES<br />
PROGRAM SUGGESTED THAT NEW FACILITIES WERE ENCOURAGING<br />
NEW PATTERNS OF TEACHING AND LEARNING. a<br />
THiE REPORT STATED THAT " THESE NEW PATTERNS<br />
INCL. UDE MORE INDIVIDUALISATION OF INSTRUCTION,. MORE<br />
OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE LEARNERS TO PARTICIPATE IN THEIR<br />
EDUCATION, TO BE ENTHUSIASTIC ABOUT IT AND ' ro BE MORE<br />
RESPONSIBLE FOR THEIR OWN PROGRESS."<br />
THAT AUGURS WEL. L FOR THIS NEW LIBRARY AND<br />
THE CONTRIBUTION IT CAN MAKE TO THE LIFE OF THE<br />
SCHOOL. IAM QUITE SURE THAT ALL OF YOU -SIST<br />
PALINE, STAFF AND GIRLS W'IL L ENJOY DISCOVERING<br />
AND REAPING THE BENEFITS OFTHIS NEW LEARNING CENTRE<br />
WITHIN OUR LDY OF MIERCY COLLEGE. I<br />
( Rj'a) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
