<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5594</transcript-id>
    <title>RETIREMENT OF MR R HAMER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005594.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA THURDAY, MAY 28 1981<br />
RETIREMENT OF MR. R. HAMER<br />
I would like to pay a tribute to a-great Australian and<br />
a great Victorian who is stepping down after 19 years / of<br />
service in the Victorian Government, including almost a<br />
decade as Premier.<br />
Dick Hamer has served Victoria well. He has been a great<br />
Premier and a strong voice on behalf of his State a much<br />
stronger voice than many know, and a man who has given good<br />
government to Victoria. The people of Vit1oria endorsed his<br />
leadership and his government in. three successive elections..<br />
As Prime Minister, I have valued my relationship with Dick Hamer.<br />
I am grateful for his co-operation and support.<br />
There is now a great obligation on the part of the Members of<br />
the Victorian Parliamentary Liberal Party as they meet to choose<br />
a new leader, to re-establish their purpose, their unity, anrid to<br />
carry Victoria forward in accordance with the great Liberal<br />
tradition of that State. </p>
<p>2<br />
Division must be put aside and the new leader, with his<br />
colleagues, will have our total support as he takes up the reins<br />
of Government. I have no doubt that if the new leader is given the<br />
full support of his party the Liberal Party will win the next<br />
State election -* and win it comfortably. The Federal Governmlent<br />
stands ready to co-operate with " the new Ministry in Victoria.<br />
I pledge the total support of myself, Sir Phillip Lynch and<br />
the Federal'Liberal Party for the new Victorian Ministry.<br />
We must remember that, while the Liberal Party is important, it<br />
is the people of Victoria who are affected by the decisions that<br />
are made.<br />
I make this statement now to pay tribute to Dick Hamer,<br />
whom I have -known for many years.. J.. thank-him for his-1<br />
services to Victoria, and to Australia. I do so before<br />
the Party Meeting which will elect his successor so fhat<br />
Victorians'-will: know that this support is not just for a<br />
person but for the ideal of the Liberal Party and for the way<br />
of life for which Dick Hamer strove so hard. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
