<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11888</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop, Brisbane Airport </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>APEC; relations with Indonesia</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>19 October 2001</p>
<p>E&amp;OE……………………………………………………………………………………</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Looking forward to your trip Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I think it’s a time when the Prime Minister of Australia should be at this meeting, it’s the biggest assembly of world leaders since the terrorist attack on American on the 11 September. It does bring together a wide range of major powers and it is very important for me to be there. It’s only two days and I think I can do the right thing by Australia by attending the meeting.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard there’s some suggestions done on the ABC of government officials that the relationship between Indonesia and Australia has never been so bad. Do you think this will hinder any bilateral meeting you hope to have with Megawati?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don’t accept that the relationship is in that condition. There have always been strains in the relationship following East Timor. And nobody should discount that but I think the relationship given all the circumstances is quite strong but in the end Prime Minister’s represent national interests and my responsibility is to represent as best I can the interests of Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you hope to meet with Megawati?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I will have plenty of opportunities to talk to her one way or another and I’ve not doubt that such things have been on the agenda between us over the last few weeks will get discussed.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you expect to farewell troops soon after you get back?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I’ve no doubt that will happen. Just exactly when I’m not in a position to say.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>From Perth?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well when there’s something solid I’ll let you all know.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard at the end of this summit what would you like to come out with? A concrete guarantee on some sort of issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>A strong condemnation of terrorism and a commitment of all of the countries to cooperate in ways they best can to fight it.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
