<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5244</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED: MELBOURNE AIRPORT ON DEPARTURE FOR UNITED STATES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005244.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT MONDAY, 28 JANUARY, 1980<br />
PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED: MELBOURNE AIRPORT ON DEPARTURE<br />
FOR UNITED STATES<br />
Question<br />
Mr. Fraser, rutile is on everybody's lips this morning.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Yes, it is. Let me say something about that in just a moment.<br />
I do want people to concentrate and keep in mind the main<br />
issues that confront us. The main issue, as I have said on<br />
many occasions, is not a particular aspect of our reaction,<br />
whether it is the Olympic Games or something in relation to<br />
rutile, it is the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and what needs<br />
to be done about that. Now, the United States has taken a<br />
number of measures. The President, I believe, the United<br />
States, Britain, other countries, deserve support in the<br />
general moves that they are undertaking to try and see that<br />
there are no more Afghanistans. I have also said that the<br />
weight that 14 million Australians can throw onto the scales<br />
is obviously limited, but that does not mean to say we should<br />
not use what weight we have. If the scales were evenly balanced,<br />
and what Australia can do or Australia can say, is the one thing<br />
that tips the scales the right way, then we would never forgive<br />
ourselves if we just sat back and said " well, we can leave it<br />
all to other people". Afghanistan is important for a number<br />
of reasons. It is the first time the Soviets have used their<br />
armies against a non-aligned country not part of the Soviet<br />
power bloc in the post World War sense. That is very significant<br />
for the non-aligned world. As I have said on many occasions,<br />
it also gives an opportunity to have an influence over Middle<br />
East oil supplies, striking at the heart of the economies of<br />
advanced industrial countries. Now, having said all that,<br />
that is the reason I am going overseas. Andrew Peacock is in<br />
South East Asia, India and Pakistan. In our own future policy<br />
development, it is very important for Australia to have as good<br />
an understanding at the highest level possible of the views of<br />
our close friends and neighbours, but also of the United States<br />
and of the United Kingdom. As you know, I will also be having<br />
discussions with Giscard d'Estaing and Helmut Schmidt. So, I will<br />
have a good understanding of the United States' and the European<br />
view when I come back. That will be of enormous help. I think<br />
it is essential in framing our own policy attitudes for the future<br />
on these matters.<br />
You asked me about rutile. I have spoken to Mr. Anthony this<br />
morning and that particular contract is under suspension. We had<br />
announced some time ago a complete review of our relationships<br />
with the Soviet Union, and that includes we have announced a<br />
number of specific decisions but that review obviously included<br />
trade aspects, matters that could be important in a strategic<br />
sense. In the light of what occurred when I was in Tasmania, we<br />
have asked that a study of that particular aspect be expedited.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
I can say a little more about that because in the past we<br />
have had a list of strategic materials that have not been<br />
exported to certain places. I will be discussing, in the<br />
United States, the need to have that kind of list again.<br />
But that particular contract, after discussion with Mr. Anthony<br />
this morning, is under suspension and so we will be able to<br />
look at that quietly. But, let me again make the point, that<br />
is not the issue. The issue is the Soviet invasion of<br />
Afghanistan. Question How much ( inaudible) contract worth, do you know?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No, I don't know.<br />
Question<br />
Mr. Carter has already taken a very strong stand on the issue.<br />
Do you think your voice will make that stand even stronger?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The President of the United States' task it is an awesome onebut<br />
also I think the loneliest job in the free world, in the<br />
world of independently-minded nations that want to govern their<br />
own affairs. I think it is terribly important that, where<br />
we believe the United States is right, where we believe that the<br />
United States is supporting the general interests of independent<br />
nations, that we say so. I think it is encouraging for anyone<br />
to know that he has his own people with him. I believe it<br />
would be encouraging both for the United States' people and<br />
for the President to know that in broad terms a country such<br />
as Australia supports'what they are seeking to do in a matter<br />
as important as this. I certainly know it would make a<br />
difference to me, feeling as I do on ' an issue like this. But<br />
I carry the goodwill of a great majority of Australians in the<br />
discussions that I will be having over the next ten days.<br />
Question Do you believe the weight of the Western world will be able<br />
to force the Russians out of Afghanistan?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think that is very difficult. I would like to think so.<br />
But I have also said in the past that once armies have moved<br />
it is very difficult to get them rejected, to get them out.<br />
The critical matter therefore for independently-minded nations<br />
is to make sure that there are no more Afghanistans.<br />
Question will defence in the Indian Ocean be the main topic of<br />
discussion? / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The Indian Ocean, obviously, will be an important element<br />
of the discussions, and why the Chief of Defence Staff is<br />
coming with me is to enable him to have discussions with<br />
his counterparts on the best way in which we will be able<br />
to assist in the patrolling and surveillance over the<br />
Indian Ocean area. We have equipment in our defence forces<br />
that are very well suited to this task, and we will be able<br />
to expand our effort. We have! already told the United States<br />
that, so there will be some discussion of it. Broadly, the<br />
political, economic and strategic consequences of the Russian<br />
move into Afghanistan that is what the conversations are<br />
all about.<br />
Question Has the fact that our own Olympic Committee not supported a<br />
boycott of. the Olympic Games will that embarass your talks<br />
with Mr. Carter?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No, it will not be embarassing, but I would have hoped that<br />
the Olympic Committee would have a view of their own that they<br />
would put. The United States Olympic Cormmittee has taken a<br />
firm view. The indications around the world are that a number<br />
of countries have serious reservations about the Olympic Games<br />
in Moscow. We would all love to be able to say politics and<br />
sport are separate, they have nothing to do with each other.<br />
But we know from the days of apartheid in sport, apartheid<br />
that came out of a Government decision, that it is not possible<br />
to keep politics and sport separate. We also know that a country<br />
such as the Soviet Union would use the athletes of the world<br />
going to Moscow for the Olympics as a marked propaganda occasion;<br />
all the world in a sense coming to pay homage to the Soviet Union<br />
in Moscow and the fact that it was an international Olympic event,<br />
and not a Russian event would become lost and submerged in the<br />
Soviet handling of the event. That needs to be very much<br />
understood. The advisers that we have, and who have studied<br />
the Soviet Union very very closely indeed, they tell us that no<br />
other single act would bring home to the Soviet Government and<br />
to the Soviet people so strongly, so vehemently, our strength of<br />
feeling about Afghanistan, as a boycott of the Olympic Games.<br />
Question Is the prime motive of this trip tactical, or as a show of<br />
support amongst Western nations?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No, the prime purpose of this trip and this is the element<br />
in which I certainly believe that I have the support of a great<br />
majority of Australians is to make sure that I am as well<br />
advised as possible, the thinking at the highest levels, the<br />
United States and the United Kingdom so we can exchange views.<br />
In matters as important as this, countries do not go off<br />
I </p>
<p>-4<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
on separate and independent tangents. There is a general<br />
interest here, an interest for all governments, for all<br />
countries, that want to maintain the independence of nations.<br />
Against that background, the consultation, understanding of<br />
each other's mind, is of vast importance, as I have said, for<br />
Australia. Quite apart from the normal diplomatic exchanges,<br />
consultations with Andrew Peacock in South East Asia and in<br />
India and Pakistan, that is one element, and then my own<br />
conversations in the United States, Britain, France and Germany,<br />
will give-me an insight on how they see these matters. It<br />
does not mean to say we just sit and listen. It will be a<br />
general exchange of view and hopefully a meeting of minds.<br />
Question Do you hope to bring about possible retaliatory action by<br />
the Soviet Union in terms of trade with Australia?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Oh look, if that happens, that happens. But we go into that<br />
sort of thing with our eyes wide open, because there are more<br />
important issues at stake. The kind of country that we leave<br />
our children we-are nearly at the end of this century, we<br />
will get into the year 2000 before very long, in two decades<br />
the kind of country we leave our children as we go to the<br />
year 2000 and beyond, that is the important thing. That is the<br />
obligation and responsiblity on us when there are great issues<br />
at stake. There should not be anything else in our minds.<br />
Question Do you hope to bring concrete proposals back to Cabinet?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do'not think it is really that kind of a mission. Nobody,<br />
out of these discussions, is going to get the sudden answer, the<br />
final solution to the problems the Soviets have posed by<br />
Afghanistan. There is not some sudden, easily found key which<br />
will give us the total solution. I think that what we are really<br />
seeking to establish is a feeling of determination, of resolve,<br />
amongst countries such as the United States and Australia and<br />
many, many others around the world, and determination that we<br />
will need to keep with us not just for a few days, weeks, or<br />
months, but for years, because the Soviet Union has shown us<br />
again what she is capable of, what prepared to do, if the guards<br />
of, again, free and independent nations, is relaxed.<br />
0 00---<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
