<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5037</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT ONTHE VISIT TO AUSTRALIA BY HIS EXCELLENCY CHOI KYU HAH, PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/05/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005037.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
iiMBA-G0( 74: 001<br />
L K j7 U&gt; 92)<br />
FOR MI) IA 2 MAY 1979<br />
JOINT STATIEMENT ON THE VISIT TO AUSTRALIA BY IllS EXCELLENCY<br />
CIIOI KYU HAI, PRIME MINISTER OF THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA<br />
Iis Excellency Choi. Kyu Hah, Prime ., Minister of the Iepublic<br />
of Korcea, visited Australia from 29 April to 3 May 1979 at<br />
the . invitation of the Austra[ ian Government. The Pr: i. mc Minister<br />
was accompanied by lis Excellency Chang Yie Joon, Minister for<br />
Energy and Rcsourccs, and a number of senior officials of<br />
the Republic of Korea Government.<br />
The Korean Prime Minister paid a courtesy call on His Excel ] ency<br />
the Governor General, Sir Zelman Cowen, and laid a wreavb in<br />
memory of Atstral ian war dead at the Australian War Memorial,<br />
Canberra. lIe al.. so visited Sydney and Melbourne.<br />
The Korean Prime Minister held discussions with the Austral. ian<br />
Prime Minister, the Rt. lIon. Malcolm Fraser, and a number o;<br />
senior Cabinet Ministers on a wide range of issues. These talks<br />
took place in a most cordial and friendly atmosphere and<br />
inc. I ided a frank exchange of views on the international situ;, tion,<br />
with particular reference to recent developments in the<br />
Asia/' aci fic region. ' The Korean Prime Minister outlined the<br />
current situation in the Korean peninsula including his<br />
Government's recent attempts to bring about a resumption of<br />
the dialogue between the south and north of Korea. The<br />
Australi an Prime Min: i. ster endorsed the importance of such attempts<br />
to reduce tension on the Korean peninsula.<br />
The two Prime Ministers referred with satisfaction to the<br />
continuing growth in bilateral relations in general in recent<br />
years, and to the strengthen: i. ng of ecopomic cooperation and.<br />
trade links between the two countries. They exchanged view:; on<br />
prospects for furtibe r deve. lopment of these relations and ejpl'a: i.'; scd the<br />
imporLance o: f stable conditions of access for, and re: Liab. l. e<br />
supply of, industrial raw materials, energy resources<br />
and agricultural products. They acknowledged the importance<br />
a. ta; Ve by each country to greater opportunities for its pyoducts<br />
in VO thor's marrzct. They also acnowledgod the necessity<br />
of expanding cu]. lural relations, including exchanges in<br />
the educational field. ./ 2 </p>
<p>Dur . ing the Koreani 1Pr imeO Minister' s vi s it the Nucl ear<br />
Cooperation and Safeguards \ groomcnt between Australia and<br />
the Republ ic of Korea was signed by the Austral ian, Deputy<br />
Prime Mini ster and Mini ster for Trade and Resources,<br />
the Rt. Hon. 3 D. Anthony and the Korean Ambassador,<br />
Hi. 1s Exte1 lency Mr. Lee Haa Lim.<br />
Both Prime Ministers expressed their belief that<br />
Prime Minister Choi ' s vit, the first to Austral ia by a<br />
Prime Minister of the Republic of Korea, had contribu ted<br />
signi ficantly to the promotion of the fri endly and<br />
cooperative relationship between the two countries. The<br />
Korean Prime Minister reaffirmed to the Australian Prime<br />
Minister the cordial invitation of his Government to visit<br />
the Republic of Korea at an early date. In response<br />
Mr. Fraser said that he warm: ly welcomed this invitation which<br />
he looked forward to taking up at a mutually agreeable time<br />
The Korean Prime Minister expressed his sincere appreciation<br />
to the Government and people of Aus tralia for the warm<br />
hospi taility extended to him and his party during their visit.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
