<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1984</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: AUSTRALIA DAY MESSAGE - FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON.</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/01/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001984.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FCR PRESS: P. M. No. 61969 K<br />
AUSTRALIA DAY MESSAGE<br />
From the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
This is the last Australia Day of the 60' s a decade marked<br />
by historic changes and by the quickening of remarkable growth for Australia.<br />
In a year's time, we will celebrate the 200th anniversary of<br />
Captain Cook's discovery of the east coast of Australia. just eighteen years<br />
after that famous voyage, the First Fleet arrived in New South Wales and a<br />
nation was born. So much has been done since then, There is so much yet to do.<br />
This is our National Day and I give special welcome to all<br />
those new settlers who, in the past year, have come to join us and to those<br />
new Australians of longer standing who have taken out citizenship. May<br />
Australia Day be a landmark each year of your lives, on your journey into<br />
a bright and happy future.<br />
For us all, old and new Australians alike, this is a time when<br />
we should acknowledge what the pioneers of this country have done.<br />
We should remember their triumph over the dangers of the<br />
unknown and their success in making a nation in a harsh and vast environment.<br />
We should remember the inheritance we have drawn from the<br />
older civilisations which have given us democracy and the rule of law, a<br />
great love of life and liberty and a resolution to preserve peace when we<br />
have it and fight for it when it is at risk.<br />
At the same time, we should recognise Australia Day as an<br />
inspiration for the future. I believe we are on the threshold of a tremendous<br />
surge forward as a nation.<br />
I believe that 30 years from now, by the year 2000, we could<br />
have more than twice as many people as we have today living in a free and<br />
prosperous country where need and poverty are things of the past.<br />
I believe we can make an increasingly significant contribution<br />
to peace and progress in South East Asia and the Pacific, and that our voice<br />
will be heard with growing respect in the world councils.<br />
But these things will not happen by the natural course of events.<br />
They will flow only from the energy, the enthusiasm, the skills and the<br />
loyalties of all Australians.<br />
These are the qualities that have advanced us to where we<br />
stand today, and which hold the key to a boundless future.<br />
CANBERRA 24 January 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
