<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4654</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004654.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JOINT STATEMENT<br />
The Prime Minister of Australia,<br />
The Rt. Hon. Malcolm Fraser, and the Deputy Prime Minister<br />
of New Zealand, The Rt. Hon. Brian Talboys, issued the<br />
following Statement following discussions in Canberra, and<br />
over the week-end at " Nareen", during which they were<br />
accompanied by the Australian Foreign Minister,<br />
The Hon. Andrew Peacock.<br />
Mr Talboys has come to Australia on this occasion as<br />
a guest of the Australian Government. He is visiting all<br />
the Australian States, as well as Canberra and the<br />
Northern Territory. He is meeting the State Premiers and<br />
Ministers of the State Governments. Mr Fraser warmly<br />
welcomed his visit as a confirmation of the special<br />
relationship that exists between Australia and New Zealand.<br />
Discussions in Canberra and at " Nareen" covered a<br />
wide range of subjects, in particular international trade<br />
issues, Australia/ New Zealand relations, the South Pacific<br />
and the Commonwealth.<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADE<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys discussed extensively current<br />
major issues in international trade. An expansion in world<br />
trade would facilitate more rapid progress in expanding<br />
trade between Australia and New Zealand.<br />
Australia and New Zealand have important interests in<br />
common with developing countries, as exporters of primary<br />
commodities, in seeking improved conditions for international<br />
trade in commodities. </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Multilateral Trade Negotiations have yet to<br />
achieve a meaningful liberalisation of interna~ tional<br />
trade in co-mmWcdities. The benefits of the Multilateral<br />
Trade Negotiations have to date been unequally shared.<br />
They have tended to favour the major industrial producers<br />
and have done little for commodity producers.<br />
Australia and New Zealand regard improved world trading<br />
conditions for agriculture as an essential ingredient of<br />
a satisfactory outcome to the Multilateral Trade Negotiations.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys agreed that there is a pressing<br />
need for substantially improved access for agricultural products<br />
into the markets of the major industrial countries.<br />
Both countries continue to support multilateral<br />
arrangements for appropriate commodities involving both<br />
producers and consumers as a means of achieving more stable<br />
world trading conditions. They wish to see the TNCTAD<br />
Negotiating Conference on the Common Fund resumed at the<br />
earliest opportunity and are willing to participate actively<br />
and constructively in these negotiations to achieve an early<br />
successful outcome.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys agreed that it is essential<br />
for all trading countries to commit themselves to work towards<br />
an expansion of world trade and world markets. Only in this<br />
way can an economic climate be created in which a solution<br />
may be found to the problems of developed and developing<br />
countries alike. A failure in or a merely face-saving outcome<br />
to the forthcoming round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations<br />
would give a further impetus to the emerging protectionism </p>
<p>3<br />
in the major industrial trading blocs. This could have<br />
very damaging consequences for the world economy.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys agreed on the need to<br />
establish an international trading system that will assist<br />
the developing countries to realise their full economic<br />
and social potential. Not only is this essential to meet<br />
the aspirations of the developing countries, but it should<br />
also serve to promote soundly based and sustained world<br />
economic growth. To achieve more equitable arrangements<br />
for international trade, it is necessary for the major<br />
industrial countries to make a new commitment to work with<br />
the developing countries to this end.<br />
It was agreed that officials in Australia and<br />
New Zealand should undertake as a matter of urgency a<br />
fundamental examination of these issues and of the prospects<br />
for achieving the twin objectives of an expanded and more<br />
equitable international trade system. There should be<br />
further discussions between Australian and New Zealand officials<br />
after consideration of these matters at the national level.<br />
The two countries should work together internationally to<br />
press for progress in these areas.<br />
AUSTRALIA/ NEW ZEALAND RELATIONS<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys affirmed that Australia<br />
and New Zealand are linked by deep ties of common origin and<br />
shared ideals and institutions which give a sound basis for<br />
the closest co-operation. The futures of the two countries<br />
are inextricably linked. By continuing to work closely<br />
together the two countries can strengthen each other and </p>
<p>4<br />
thereby make the best possible contribution to the peace<br />
and prosperity of the region in which they live.<br />
Extensive consultations and coordination between<br />
the two Governments already exist in many fields.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys recognised that there is scope<br />
for further facilitating and encouraging relations by the<br />
exchange of people and ideas between Australia and<br />
New Zealand. To this end, they decided to take several<br />
concrete steps.<br />
These include: S Exchanges of Parliamentary Delegations<br />
on a regular and frequent basis;<br />
S Exchanges of Australian and New Zealand<br />
Government officials from a variety of<br />
areas to work in each other's country;<br />
S Regular consultations on international<br />
legal and related matters;<br />
S Further steps to coordinate the activities<br />
of the two Governments in the field of<br />
development cooperation.<br />
Mr Fraser warmly welcomed a proposal by the<br />
New Zealand Government that a New Zealand-Australia Foundation<br />
should be established to help strengthen relations between<br />
the two countries. Mr Fraser stated that the Australian<br />
Government wished to be closely associated with the proposal<br />
by means of a parallel body in Australia. Mr Fraser and<br />
Mr Talboys agreed that the functions of the respective bodies<br />
should include encouraging the study and discussion of issues </p>
<p>5<br />
of interest to both Australia and New Zealand and the<br />
promotion of increased cultural and other exchanges between<br />
the two countries. Close contact would be maintained<br />
between the two bodies.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys welcomed the initiative<br />
taken by leaders in the private sector of both countries<br />
to form a committee of businessmen to promote trade and<br />
to assist the development of close economic relations<br />
between the two countries.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys reaffirme. d the signifi-cance<br />
which both countries attached to the maintenance and further<br />
development of bilateral economic ties. Since the<br />
New Zealand-Australia Free Trade Agreement ( NAFTA) was signed<br />
in 1965, the value of trade between the two countries has<br />
increased more than four-fold, and has now reached a level<br />
of nearly $ Al billion a year. Each country is the biggest<br />
market for the other's manufactured exports. Mr Fraser and<br />
Mr Talboys noted with satisfaction the recent commitment<br />
to the continuation of NAFTA until at least 1985 and the<br />
conclusion of a more enduring agreement on tariffs and tariff<br />
preferences. They looked forward to a further round of<br />
NAFTA discussions in April at which Ministers would assess<br />
current trade problems in detail and review progress in the<br />
trade field.<br />
The intention of the two governments in entering the<br />
NAFTA was the progressive removal of barriers to trade between<br />
the two countries with a view to the continued expansion of<br />
the free trade coverage. Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys agreed on<br />
the desirability of the further opening of bilateral trade, as<br />
conditions permit, with the objective of encouraging in both </p>
<p>6-<br />
Australia and New Zealand the development of efficient<br />
industries that can meet international competition and<br />
provide increasing employment opportunities.<br />
To help achieve this objective and strengthen the<br />
two countries' economies on complementary lines,<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys agreed that in considering<br />
questions of assistance for the development of particular<br />
industries in which the other country would have an<br />
interest, each Government should take into account the<br />
situation and prospects for the industries concerned in<br />
the other country. A consultative mechanism should be<br />
established to make possible full consultation between<br />
Governments before decisions are taken on these questions.<br />
Procedures should be elaborated at the NAFTA Ministerial<br />
meeting in April.<br />
Mr Fraser and Mr Talboys emphasised the importance<br />
for regional stability and economic development of a<br />
healthy economy in both countries. They recalled that<br />
the 1977 ANZUS Council Communique stated that<br />
" Ministers recognised that the health of the economy of<br />
the three partners is of concern to each, for it affects<br />
their capacity to play the responsive and responsible role<br />
that world and regional circumstances demand of them and<br />
which is their common desire. They therefore agreed that<br />
they would consider their economic relationships and mutual<br />
problems within this larger framework". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
