<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9914</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP &quot;OUR LAND&quot; STATEMENT ALBURY, 24 JANUARY 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009914.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
" OUR LAND" STATEMENT<br />
ALBURY, 24 JANUARY 1996<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
First, let me thank Professor Blake, the Vice-Chancellor of Charles Sturt<br />
University, and Professor Cullen, the Director of the Cooperative Research<br />
Centre for Freshwater Ecology, for their invitation to open this research<br />
facility for the Murray Darling Freshwater Research Centre.<br />
There is great work being done in Australian research, and I sincerely hope<br />
that this event will help to advertise that fact.<br />
Research of the kind being done here is essential because it seeks solutions<br />
to the problems of living on this continent which we simply must solve. It<br />
adds to our body of knowledge, and thus contributes vitally to Australia's<br />
future. The work here is unique, but there are parallels across the country. We are<br />
doing a great deal in the field of environmental research, we are doing a<br />
great deal to restore and protect the environment, and each year we do more.<br />
Since 1988/ 89 the Commonwealth has spent nearly $ 350 million on<br />
vegetation-related projects alone. Nearly 700,000 hectares have benefited.<br />
Nearly 200,000 Australians have been involved.<br />
Or, to quote another example, since 1989 the Commonwealth together with<br />
State Governments have spent over $ 300 million to address the damage to<br />
our greatest river system, the Murray-Darling Basin and this investment has<br />
leveraged an even greater contribution from the community and private<br />
sector. I am continually impressed by the quality of the people involved in the handson<br />
environmental effort in Australia. </p>
<p>It is easy enough to be passionate about the environment, and we need<br />
people to be passionate. But to succeed we need to be wise and passionate.<br />
We need to be practical. And, because we won't repair the damage of two<br />
centuries and we won't create a sustainable Australia overnight, we need to<br />
be dedicated.<br />
No one should imagine this is a task for the short term, any more than they<br />
imagine that governments and dollars alone are the solutions. Success<br />
requires a sustained national effort a communal, generalised effort.<br />
If after all the expenditure of money and energy and expertise in recent years,<br />
we feel daunted by the task that still lies ahead, there are only two remedies.<br />
The first is broaden the effort: involve more people and communities, more<br />
companies, more landowners make it a more coordinated nationwide drive,<br />
make it inseparable from the nation's progress, build the energy of private<br />
interest into the public environmental good. That's the first remedy.<br />
The second is more of a spiritual cure. Go to Daintree, go to the Franklin<br />
River or Kakadu, or Shoalwater Bay or Jervis Bay. Go to the places which<br />
have been saved. Go to the environment itself. Go to the places up the<br />
Murray from~ here which Greening Australia and the local communities are<br />
making a corridor of green; or walk along the Hawkesbury or the Yarra which<br />
unemployed people with local communities are renovating under REEP<br />
schemes financed through Working Nation; or go to any of the thousands of<br />
Australian farms where Landcare has made a visible difference.<br />
As works in progress go, this is more rewarding than most: the evidence of<br />
each step we take is so gratifying. This huge continent throws up a huge<br />
challenge, and at times it will look like we are not making progress but we<br />
are. And as a nation it would be disastrous if we were to lose our nerve.<br />
Today we take some more steps big steps. And most importantly, we pull<br />
all the elements of the national effort, into step.<br />
This is a very big policy initiative. All up, it involves expenditure in the region<br />
of almost half a billion dollars.<br />
It is also very good policy: it goes to the heart of the problem, it builds on<br />
proven programs, and in the longer term it will produce far more savings and<br />
far more national wealth than we intend to spend.<br />
In a real sense it will be the test: when these programs are fully implemented,<br />
we will have a very clear idea of whether the concept of sustainable Australia<br />
can be made a reality.<br />
If it can, the rewards will be immense: for our prosperity, for our quality of life,<br />
for our relationship with this land, for our farmers, for our children. </p>
<p>It is a statement in two interrelated parts: the first concerns the task of<br />
creating a sustainable rural Australia; the second is directed at meeting our<br />
responsibility to conserve our natural environment. It is a statement about<br />
the relationship between our natural riches and the economic wealth that we<br />
create from it. It constitutes by far the most dramatic single response any<br />
Australian government has ever made to the challenge of protecting the land.<br />
Australia is an environmentally rich nation.<br />
We have diverse biological capital: numerous species that are not found<br />
anywhere else; ecosystems in coral reefs, rainforests, wetlands and deserts<br />
which are things of wonder for the whole world.<br />
We also have huge and diverse areas of farmland which provide high quality<br />
produce over long seasons. Over the years, this has helped us build<br />
considerable national wealth through the export of our commodities.<br />
But Australia is also environmentally fragile.<br />
Recent assessments have shown us just how fragile and how difficult is the<br />
task of repair-<br />
In Singapore recently, I drew attention to the environmental challenges facing<br />
a rapidly growing Asia. Many of these challenges are shared by Australia.<br />
Soil erosion, salinity, water pollution and loss of biodiversity are all too well<br />
known to us.<br />
The challenge of protecting our land is inextricably linked to our economic<br />
well being. The two go hand in hand. That is sustainable development. The<br />
links are obvious, but always worth re-stating.<br />
Our farms must be profitable if we are to maintain the capacity to invest in the<br />
conservation of our environmental assets. To be profitable, we must add<br />
maximum value to our produce and link producers and processors closely<br />
with consumer demands.<br />
Maximum value can only be added over the long haul if our produce is clean,<br />
as our consumers will demand, and if our resource base remains productive.<br />
Our resource base can only remain productive if ecological processes and<br />
biological diversity are maintained. And that demands a strategic network of<br />
nature reserves joined with conservation measures on and off farms.<br />
And so the circle is closed. With this Statement we enlarge the circle<br />
hugely.<br />
Today, we make another very significant down payment on securing the<br />
future of our land a major investment in our capacity to profit economically<br />
from the land and protect the diverse life the land itself supports. </p>
<p>Some 60 per cent of the land is managed by our farming families. Last year a<br />
great many of these families depended on us to survive the drought. The<br />
much more common reality is, of course, that Australia depends on them.<br />
At present our agricultural industries are finely balanced. They face<br />
substantial opportunities for growth and prosperity. But they also face<br />
significant environmental challenges if they are to remain productive.<br />
Farming families are already seeing an increasing proportion of their produce<br />
being processed in Australia, or being packed and exported quickly and<br />
reliably to premium price foreign markets. That is the way they will improve<br />
profitability and so be well placed to manage our natural resources in a<br />
sustainable manner.<br />
In turn, sustainable farming is essential if our products are to find favour with<br />
the burgeoning consumer classes across Asia. By the year 2000, spending<br />
on food in Asia will have increased by around $ US160 billion per annum from<br />
the 1990 level.<br />
Asian consumers will increasingly demand quality, and increasingly be<br />
subject to fAshion and.' market presentation.<br />
For Australian suppliers, continued product innovation, market development<br />
and reliable distribution will be essential to increased market share.<br />
The success of the rural sector in adjusting to change is demonstrated by the<br />
record of exports of high value added food products. In 1991-92, the year<br />
before the commencement of the Government's Agri-Food Strategy, these<br />
exports totalled $ 2.5 billion. We set an ambitious target of $ 7 billion of<br />
exports by the year 2000. Last year our high value exports had risen by<br />
per cent to over $ 3.7 billion, and we are clearly on track to meet and exceed<br />
our Year 2000 target.<br />
The Government will build on the success to date by pulling together the<br />
threads of natural resource management, on-farm performance, product<br />
development, market identification, transport, distribution, and consumer<br />
servicing. Industry leaders have suggested to me that the next phase of development<br />
should cement Australia as a major food exporter to Asia. I have agreed that<br />
the Government will join with and support strong private sector leadership in<br />
this endeavour.<br />
As part of this, we will energise the Agri-Food Council to develop and drive<br />
an Asia Food 2000 Strategy. The Council will report to me and I will chair at<br />
least one meeting a year. 4 </p>
<p>Further details of these reforms will be announced on Friday. For now I can<br />
say that the Council's general aims will be to improve linkages across the full<br />
production, processing, marketing and transport chain with the objective of<br />
promoting high value food exports.<br />
Yet the greatest imperative in the long run is sustainability.<br />
By the early 1 990s around 6 per cent or $ 1.5 billion of annual agricultural<br />
production was being lost to natural resource degradation. This is the legacy<br />
we are tackling in partnership with rural Australia at the level of individual<br />
farms, local communities and broader regions. It is only through such a<br />
comprehensive strategy that we can succeed.<br />
The Government cannot solve these major environmental problems in<br />
isolation. What is more, to attempt to do so, is to squander by far the largest<br />
source of energy and inspiration at our disposal. I mean communities, the<br />
people of Australia.<br />
Community involvement is a theme of this Statement the Government can<br />
set the policy goals and framework and provide the bulk of the funds, but the<br />
maximum return depends on how well we engage the community.<br />
The massive investment we are making today will help us arrest and begin to<br />
reverse the equally massive land and water degradation our land has<br />
suffered over the last 200 years.<br />
It will not mean the end of the problem. Only that we are not daunted by it.<br />
Unfortunately, much of the burden of turning this situation around has fallen<br />
to the current generation of farming families. In November 1994, I<br />
established the Land Management Task Force to investigate ways to improve<br />
land management in rural Australia. It reported that property management<br />
planning is an effective and essential tool in improving the financial and<br />
natural resource management performance of Australian farms.<br />
The National Property Management Planning Campaign we initiated in 1992<br />
has laid the foundations for a major expansion of more strategic farm<br />
planning practices.<br />
Property management planning helps farming families manage farms in an<br />
integrated manner, as both businesses and environmental assets. Through it<br />
they identify their goals, assess the productive capacity of their farms, create<br />
business plans for their properties, and allow for normal contingencies such<br />
as commodity cycles or drought.<br />
In response to the Task Force's recommendations, the Government will<br />
extend the National Property Management Planning Campaign for four years<br />
from 1996-97 at a cost of $ 35 million. </p>
<p>In addition, the implementation of property planning on farms will be<br />
supported through the Rural Adjustment Scheme, which will be strengthened<br />
with the introduction of a new sustainable farming component costing $ 12<br />
million dollars over 4 years.<br />
Planning at the individual property level by farming families will be most<br />
effective if it is supported at the community level in a broader geographical<br />
context. And that is where Landcare comes in.<br />
Landcare is a particularly successful, innovative and, I think, uniquely<br />
Australian approach to sustainable resource management. The concept was<br />
relatively new when the Government announced in 1989 that $ 320 million<br />
would be allocated to Landcare over the next decade.<br />
We said we hoped to have 1000 Landcare groups across the country by the<br />
year 2000. Today we have 2500 groups. Thirty per cent of broadacre farm<br />
families are involved. Awareness of Landcare in rural Australia grew from<br />
per cent in 1991 to 85 per cent in 1994, and in urban Australia from 10 per<br />
cent to more than 60 per cent. What Landcare did the genius of it was to<br />
tap the resilience of Australian farmers, their passion for the land and their<br />
determination to stay on it, and turn these qualities to the goal of<br />
environmenfal sustain-ability.<br />
Landcare has been one of Australia's most spectacular national successes.<br />
With the new spending in this Statement, total expenditure on Landcare since<br />
1989 will exceed $ 1 .1 billion more than three times our original commitment.<br />
Today's announcement not only substantially increases the Government's<br />
support for Landcare, it also directs more of those resources to community<br />
Landcare groups. The rapid embrace of Landcare has seen the funds often<br />
spread too thinly and many worthwhile projects inadequately supported.<br />
Importantly, the Government will provide $ 128 million to assist with the<br />
development and implementation of catchment plans by local communities.<br />
Changes will be made to the Regional Environmental Employment Program<br />
to improve linkages with Landcare activities and address national<br />
environmental priorities. We will appoint 10 environmental employment<br />
coordinators to increase the take-up of REEP.<br />
The REEP initiatives are just part of the Government's efforts to increase the<br />
positive environmental impacts of labour market programs. The Government<br />
has allocated more than $ 1 billion, through Working Nation programs,<br />
towards the development of green jobs. In 1994-95 there were approximately<br />
25,000 placements in Landcare, environment, conservation and cultural<br />
heritage projects at a cost of $ 252m. In the following three years these will<br />
increase by 90,000 placements at a cost of $ 936m. 6<br />
J. 7r 7. I 7 77rm </p>
<p>While many issues need a regional focus, some of the environmental<br />
challenges must be addressed across several States.<br />
Most notably, the Murray Darling Basin is Australia's largest and most<br />
important agricultural area. It contains 26 per cent of all Australian<br />
agricultural land, almost 75 per cent of irrigated agricultural land and<br />
accounts for over 40 per cent of Australian agricultural production by value.<br />
The value of agricultural exports from the Basin is around $ 6 billion per<br />
annum. In 1988 the Government, together with the relevant state governments,<br />
established the Murray-Darling Basin Commission, and the combination of<br />
significant funding, science and community effort has led to substantial<br />
progress in many areas. Witness the growth of the wine industry in<br />
Sunraysia or the dairy industry in the Goulburn Valley.<br />
However, it is all too clear that the Murray-Darling is still in trouble. It is<br />
sufficient to note that we have lost 500,000 hectares of land to salinity.<br />
Unless decisive action is taken now, around 1,500,000 hectares, much of it<br />
prime agricultural land, will be under threat by around 2040.<br />
The scale of the probl~ m clearly requires a national response, and the<br />
Government is prepared to meet that responsibility.<br />
The Government, in partnership with the relevant States through the Murray<br />
Darling Basin Council, has commenced a comprehensive natural resource<br />
management and rehabilitation program of the Murray Darling Basin. To<br />
reinvigorate this we will provide an additional $ 98 million over the next four<br />
years as part of the Murray-Darling Basin Sustainability Initiative. We will<br />
expect matched funding from the States.<br />
Comprehensive priority action will be taken on reducing waterway pollution<br />
arising from towns and cities, increasing salinity control, addressing land<br />
degradation and erosion, reducing the effect of agricultural run-off on<br />
waterways and protecting native animal habitat and remnant vegetation.<br />
For example, we estimate that through this and other initiatives we can<br />
reduce the amount of nutrients entering the river systems by a massive<br />
per cent. Over 1,600 kms of the most sensitive riparian zones on the major<br />
rivers will be rehabilitated. Dry land salinity will be tackled on a catchment<br />
basis including through extensive farm forestry.<br />
Let me now turn to the broader issues of nature conservation. In our largest<br />
program for this ever for the protection of biodiversity both on or off reserves,<br />
the Government will provide a $ 175 million program to expand the National<br />
Reserve System and to ensure that conservation is a priority outside that<br />
Reserve System. 7. </p>
<p>To this end, the Government will provide $ 70 million to maintain and extend<br />
the range of Landcare programs which have nature conservation as their<br />
primary objective. These programs, such as Save the Bush, National<br />
Corridors of Green and Waterwatch, have galvanised community action to<br />
protect our environment. Some 1200 grants have been made to community<br />
groups under Save the Bush. And more than 30 000 people have<br />
participated in Waterwatch.<br />
Funding for Save the Bush will be doubled and targeted to four key areas;<br />
namely, support for community activities, training Landcare facilitators,<br />
research into techniques of regeneration and conservation of grasslands.<br />
Funding for Waterwatch will be increased by 50 per cent and the program will<br />
be extended through to the year 2000. A priority will be community<br />
monitoring in the catchments of Australia's Ramsar Wetlands.<br />
The River Murray Corridor of Green program has deployed 90,000 hours of<br />
community labour to protect or re-establish over 4000 hectares of vegetation.<br />
We will provide $ 8.1 million to establish a National Corridors of Green<br />
program for similar projects in all States and Territories. The program will<br />
assist communities to enlarge and connect remaining patches of bushland<br />
and link thege with ne w plantings establishing a biodiverse " web of life".<br />
The driving force will be communities, and the advantages will flow to them as<br />
well as to the environment. They will flow particularly to young people.<br />
These programs have a multiplying effect; they raise understanding and<br />
awareness of environmental issues as they go, and that in itself is a<br />
substantial guarantee that future generations will not make the mistakes<br />
made by previous generations including ours.<br />
We have only recently become fully aware of the rate at which we are losing<br />
our native vegetation. That rate is ecologically unsustainable and has been a<br />
primary cause of many of our most difficult problems, including salinity, soil<br />
erosion and the lost of species.<br />
Fortunately, State and Territory governments are now addressing this<br />
important issue. To provide additional national momentum and a regional<br />
focus, I will convene a National Native Vegetation Conservation and<br />
Management Forum.<br />
This will bring together all governments, the farming, scientific and<br />
conservation communities and other relevant parties in a series of national<br />
and regional meetings and consultative processes around the country.<br />
The objective will be to seek a consensus on effective native vegetation<br />
management strategies. 8 </p>
<p>We will also increase our efforts to combat feral pests and weeds with the<br />
provision of an additional $ 13 million to create a comprehensive framework<br />
for the management of invasive species.<br />
This audience more than most will recognise the importance of our wetlands<br />
and waterways as the lifeblood of the system and as indicators of its health.<br />
We will allocate $ 15.3 million to establish a new National River Health<br />
program to create a scientific basis for understanding the flow requirements<br />
of our river systems. This work will feed into the reform agenda being<br />
pursued by the Council of Australian Governments.<br />
In March Australia will host the largest international environment conference<br />
ever held in this country. Representatives from around 100 countries will<br />
gather in Brisbane for the Ramsar Conference on Wetlands of International<br />
Importance.<br />
Wetlands are one of our most important ecosystems. To improve their<br />
management and conservation, we will expand the National Wetlands<br />
Program with extra funding of $ 6 million.<br />
The Governfrent accepts that management of land, including parks and<br />
reserves, is primarily a State responsibility. But in the case of World Heritage<br />
areas, there is obviously a role for the Commonwealth.<br />
million will be provided to improve management of priority areas,<br />
including Fraser Island, the Willandra Lakes, the Central East Coast<br />
Rainforest Reserves, Lord Howe Island and Shark Bay.<br />
While our World Heritage areas are the jewels in our crown, protecting the<br />
most rare and vulnerable species and examples of our major ecosystems,<br />
demands a comprehensive network of representative nature reserves.<br />
Through the National Reserves Program we started in 1992, the Government<br />
is working with the States and Territories, Aboriginals and Torres Strait<br />
Islanders, and the wider community to create this network.<br />
There have been some major acquisitions including areas like the Starke and<br />
Silver Plains properties in North Queensland and the Anglesea heathlands in<br />
Victoria. But the main focus of the first phase has been on planning and<br />
identification of ecological priorities.<br />
The Government will now provide $ 80 million to fund the second phase of<br />
establishing the National Reserves System. With matching contributions<br />
from the States, this should provide the momentum to develop by the turn of<br />
the century a system of parks and reserves second to none in the world. </p>
<p>The objective is to protect prime examples of our major ecosystems and the<br />
most important representative areas of biological diversity and wilderness.<br />
Protection of these areas will create havens for a range of endangered<br />
species. The Government recognises that we will need a range of measures to fully<br />
protect our biological diversity.<br />
In order to identify these strategies, I will propose that the Council of<br />
Australian Governments institute a major review process associated with the<br />
National Reserves System with the aim of removing unnecessary<br />
impediments to best practice in biological diversity conservation.<br />
It should also develop innovative means to complete the National Reserves<br />
System and increase the conservation effort off reserves. The review could<br />
cover the regulatory framework, economic instruments and voluntary<br />
measures.<br />
We will also establish, as part of the National Reserves Program, a<br />
million revolving Australian Nature Conservation Trust Fund for innovative<br />
and cooperative initiatives which may involve States, private sector and<br />
community 6ontributions. For example, this will provide opportunities to place<br />
conservation covenants on land which the Fund may purchase and on-sell.<br />
If it is true, and it surely is, that conservation of the environment represents a<br />
challenge for all Australians, this fund represents an opportunity for all<br />
Australians to respond. It is an opportunity for communities and individuals.<br />
It is an opportunity for private companies both big and small to play their<br />
part. It is not unreasonable to entertain the hope that the Government's<br />
million will be the seed of something much bigger.<br />
Of course some 15 per cent of Australia is currently owned by Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander peoples. The Government will consult with the land<br />
owners, as part of the National Reserves System Program, to develop an<br />
Indigenous Protected Areas Initiative. This will aim to establish reserve-level<br />
nature conservation management in areas of high conservation value, while<br />
maintaining indigenous ownership and control.<br />
The National Reserve Program will protect the habitats of many endangered<br />
species and ecological communities but attention needs to be given to<br />
individual species and particular communities.<br />
More than eighty per cent of Australian endangered and vulnerable species<br />
do not yet have a completed recovery plan in place. To respond to this need<br />
the Government will provide an additional $ 13.4 million to tackle the threats<br />
facing the most critically endangered species, both inside and outside the<br />
reserve system.<br />
So there it is.<br />
1, 1 1. f. or T. 7 T I 11, I I I V 17. yw 1 I I MM lql. tqt </p>
<p>A sweep of integrated measures, with new funding totalling $ 463 million, from<br />
the pure nature conservation of a world class National Reserves System,<br />
through Landcare and property management planning, to export market<br />
access for premium food products. Integrated, because the policy problems<br />
we are facing can only be properly understood by making these connections.<br />
This is the substance which underpins the concept of ecologically sustainable<br />
development. Historically we have not been kind to our environment. Nor have we<br />
observed the connection between the environment and production. Over the<br />
last decade, however, we have begun to see how thoroughly they are<br />
interwoven and, once we see them, we begin to see how urgent it is to<br />
repair the broken threads.<br />
Our economic health and environmental well-being cannot be separated.<br />
Treated apart, we are bound to fall short of success in both causes. Treated<br />
together, we have a chance of succeeding a chance to repair the damage<br />
done in the last two centuries and give to the Australians of the next century<br />
their birthright, a flourishing, natural Australian environment.<br />
At the same time, it will do them no harm to have flourishing rural industries<br />
and a rural culture and communities. Among other things, that will mean<br />
Australia is realising its unique potential.<br />
And it will mean that we have done the right thing by the future.<br />
We can be the generation which turned the tide. We have to be and I am<br />
certain that we want to be.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
