<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3290</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE PREMIERS&#039; CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 7 JUNE 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/06/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003290.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE HON. EgG. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
AT THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE, CANBERRAV<br />
ON 7 JUNE 1974<br />
IT IS NEARLY TWELVE MONTHS SINCE WE LAST MET IN THIS<br />
CHAMBER. IT HAS BEEN A MOMENTOUS PERIOD. OVERSHADOWING THE<br />
PAST TWO MONTHS HAS BEEN THE ELECTION. BUT THAT IS NOW BEHIND<br />
US, THE PEOPLE HAVE RETURNED MY PARTY TO OFFICE AND WE ARE NOW<br />
GETTING ON WITH THE BUSINESS OF GOVERNMENT,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED TO THE PROGRAMS OF SOCIAL<br />
PROGRESS WHICH IT HAS GOT UNDER WAY SINCE DECEMBER 1972. THOSE<br />
PROGRAMS HAVE GREATLY EXPANDED THE OPPORTUNITIES AVAILABLE TO<br />
AUSTRALIANS, BOTH AS INDIVIDUALS AND AS MEMBERS OF COMMUNITIES.<br />
MANY OF THEM, OF COURSE, INVOLVE THE CO-OPERATION OF THE STATES<br />
AND THEIR INSTRUMENTALITIES. IN MY OPENING SPEECH AT THIS CONFERENCE LAST YEAR I SET<br />
DOWN CLEARLY AND UNEQUIVOCALLY THE BROAD LINES WE WOULD FOLLOW<br />
IN OUR RELATIONS WITH THE STATES.<br />
THE STARTING POINT WAS SIMPLY THIS: WE BELIEVE THAT<br />
THE TOTAL AMOUNTS OF ASSISTANCE PROVIDED TO THE STATES IN THE PAST<br />
HAVE, IN TERMS OF THE TASKS LAID UPON THEM, BEEN INADEQUATE. THE<br />
RESULT HAS BEEN AN ACCUMULATION OF SERIOUS DEFICIENCIES ACROSS A<br />
WIDE RANGE OF FUNCTIONS OF CRUCIAL IMPORTANCE IN THE WELL-BEING OF<br />
OUR COMMUNITY: OVERCROWDED AND INSUFFICIENTLY STAFFED SCHOOLS,<br />
AN INEQUITABLE DISTRIBUTION OF HEALTH SERVICES, HOPELESSLY<br />
INADEQUATE AND UNCO-ORDINATED SYSTEMS OF URBAN PUBLIC TRANSPORT,<br />
A HUGE BACKLOG OF UNSEWERED HOUSING, AN OVERCROWDING OF<br />
POPULATION IN OUR MAIN CITIES, AND SO ON. / 2 </p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN A LARGE NUMBER<br />
OF IMPORTANT INITIATIVES DESIGNED TO TACKLE THESE DEFICIENCIES'.<br />
BROADLY, IT HAS MOVED ON TWO FRONTS. FIRST, IT HAS ESTABLISHED<br />
NEW INSTITUTIONS AND NEW MECHANISMS FOR ASSESSING, ON A NATIONAL<br />
BASIS BUT IN FULL CO-OPERATION WITH THE STATES AND THEIR<br />
AUTHORITIES, NEEDS AND PRIORITIES IN EACH OF THE MAIN AREAS OF<br />
CONCERN* THE SCHOOLS COMMISSION, THE HOSPITALS AND HEALTH<br />
SERVICES COMMISSION, THE DEPARTMENT OF URBAN AND REGIONAL<br />
DEVELOPMENT AND THE EXPANDED GRANTS COMMISSION ARE SOME OF THE<br />
MAIN EXAMPLES OF MANY THAT COULD BE CITED.<br />
SECONDLY, THE GOVERNMENT HAS, ON THE BASIS OF THESE<br />
EXPERT ASSESSMENTS, BEGUN TO PROVIDE LARGE AMOUNTS OF FUNDS TO<br />
THE STATES. IN RESPECT OF TWO AREAS TERTIARY EDUCATION AND<br />
PUBLIC HOUSING WE ASSUMED FULL FINANCIAL RESPONSIBILITY AND<br />
MADE APPROPRIATE ADJUSTMENTS TO THE LEVELS OF GENERAL PURPOSE<br />
FUNDS MADE AVAILABLE TO THE STATES. IN OTHER AREAS, WE<br />
UNDERTOOK NEW OR EXPANDED PROGRAMS OF SPECIFIC PURPOSE<br />
ASSISTANCE DESIGNED TO ADD TO EXISTING STATE PROVISIONS IN THE<br />
AREAS CONCERNED AND SO TO ACCELERATE IMPROVEMENTS IN STANDARDS.<br />
THE OPPORTUNITIES FOR A BETTER AND FULLER LIFE WHICH<br />
THESE PROGRAMS PROMISE ARE BECOMING INCREASINGLY EVIDENT AS TIME<br />
GOES BY. WE WILL GO ON WITH THEM. THERE IS, HOWEVER, A NEED<br />
FOR ALL OF US NOT TO TRY TO PUSH AHEAD SO FAST THAT THE ECONOMY<br />
IS UNABLE TO MEET OUR DEMANDS.<br />
I SAY THAT BECAUSE THE ECONOMY IS CURRENTLY<br />
THREATENED BY A SERIOUS INFLATION. THAT INFLATION MUST BE<br />
CURBED. THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO CURB I1% 9 o 93 </p>
<p>WE HAVE, IN THE PAST EIGHTEEN MONTHS, TAKEN MAJOR STEPS<br />
TO CHECK INFLATION. WE HAVE SET AN EXCHANGE RATE FOR THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN DOLLAR APPROPRIATE TO OUR CIRCUMSTANCES'. WE PUT A<br />
STOP TO THE EXCESSIVE INFLOW OF MONEY FROM OVERSEAS'. WE CUT<br />
TARIFFS SHARPLY ACROSS-THE-BOARD, WE INCREASED TAXES BY OVER<br />
$ 600 MILLION, ON A FULL-YEAR BASIS, IN OUR FIRST BUDGET.<br />
THROUGH THESE AN]) OTHER MEANS WE STEADILY DRAINED OFF THE<br />
EXCESSIVE LIQUIDITY PRESENT IN THE ECONOMY WHEN WE FIRST TOOK<br />
OFFICE. IN DOING SO, WE HAD TO ACCEPT MUCH HIGHER INTEREST<br />
RATES THAN MY PARTY FINDS PALATABLE. MANY OF THESE STEPS HAVE<br />
BEEN CRITICISED BY THE VERY PEOPLE WHO COMPLAIN MOST LOUDLY ABOUT<br />
INFLATION., I NOTICE, HOWEVER, THAT NEARLY ALL THE PROFESSIONAL<br />
ECONOMISTS WHO HAVE COMMENTED ON OUR POLICIES HAVE SAID THEY<br />
WERE RIGHT AND COURAGEOUS,<br />
IN MY PRESS CONFERENCE ON 7 MAY IN SYDNEY I SAID<br />
" WE ARE PREPARED TO STRENGTHEN ALL THE STEPS<br />
WE HAVE ALREADY TAKEN AND TO TAKE ANY OTHER STEPS<br />
WHICH OUR ECONOMIC ADVISERS BELIEVE NECESSARY TO<br />
DEFEAT INFLATION,"<br />
I MEANT THAT. AND I TRUST THAT NOW, IN THE LIGHT OF THE<br />
ELECTION CAMPAIGN, IT IS COMMON GROUND THAT INFLATION MUST BE<br />
DEFEATED'. IF THERE IS ONE THING THE CAMPAIGN HAS MADE CLEAR,<br />
IT IS THAT*. THERE ARE NO EASY WAYS OF CURBING INFLATION. NOR CAN<br />
IT BE CURBED BY PUSHING ALL OF THE BURDEN OF DOING SO ONTO A<br />
PARTICULAR GROUI'. A DOLLAR SPENT BY THE PRIVATE SECTOR ADDS<br />
AS MUCH TO INFLATIONARY PRESSURES AS A DOLLAR SPENT BY THE PUBLIC<br />
SECTOR. A DOLLAR SPENT BY A STATE GOVERNMENT. ADDS AS MUCH TO<br />
INFLATIONARY PRESSURES AS A DOLLAR SPENT BY THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMEN' 1. 4 </p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IS CURRENTLY SEEKING TO<br />
RESTRAIN PRIVATE SECTOR SPENDING BY KEEPING MONEY TIGHT, IT<br />
IS SEEKING TO ENCOURAGE SAVING AND) DISCOURAGE SPENDING BY<br />
INCR~ EASING THE ATTRACTIVENESS OF FINANCIAL ASSETS. HENCE THE<br />
RISE IN YIELDS ON GOVERNMENT SECURITIES THAT IS OCCURING IN THE<br />
MARKET*' WE ARE FOLLOWING SUCH A MONETARY POLICY, NOT BECAUSE<br />
WE LIKE ITS CONSEQUENCES IN TERMS OF FINANCIAL STRINGENCY AN)<br />
HIGHER INTEREST RATES, BUT BECAUSE WE HAVE TO IF THERE IS TO BE<br />
A CURB ON EXCESSIVE PRIVATE SPENDIN'<br />
THIS MEETING, OF COURSE, IS CONCERNED WITH GOVERNMENT<br />
SPENDING., THAT TOO MUST PLAY ITS PART IN ANY POLICY OF RESTRAINT.<br />
IT GOES AGAINST THE GRAIN FOR ME TO SAY THAT BUT ALL<br />
OF US HERE MUST ACCEPT THE REALITIES. INFLATION MUST BE CHECKED,.<br />
AND IT MUST BE CHECKED DECISIVELY*<br />
I KNOW I AM PREACHING TO THE CONVERTED BUT LET ME SAY<br />
A LITTLE ABOUT THE ECONOMIC SITUATION AND OUTLOOK.<br />
THE CONSUMER PRICE INDEX ROSE BY 13#. 6 PER CENT IN THE<br />
YEAR TO THE MARCH QUARTER. ITS RATE OF INCREASE WAS REDUCED IN<br />
THE MARCH QUARTER BUT THE FUTURE FOR PRICES REMAINS OMINOUS<br />
PRICES ARE BEING PUSHED ALONG BY A COMBINATION OF<br />
EXCESSIVE DEMAND AND EXCESSIVE COST INCREASE, INCREASINGLYj<br />
PEOPLE ARE ADJUSTING THEIR SPENDING BEHAVIOUR TO INFLATION,<br />
MAKING THE PROBLEM SELF-PERPETUATING.<br />
OVER THE PAST YEAR TOTAL SPENDING, IN REAL TERMS, ROSE<br />
BY 10 PER CENT. MUCH OF THAT INCREASE WAS SATISFIEDv NOT FROM<br />
OUR OWN PRODUCTION, BUT BY A VERY LARGE RISE IN IMPORTS', WE<br />
WANTED THAT TO HAPPEN, AND IT HAS'. EVEN SO, DEMAND HAS<br />
OUTSTRIPPED SUPPLIES SHORTAGES OF BASIC MATERIALS AND EVEN OF<br />
SOME CONSUMER GOODS ARE WIDESPREAD. INDUSTRY IS OPERATING AT<br />
FULL CAPACITY, SUBJECT ONLY TO CONSTRAINTS IMPOSED BY LABOUR AND<br />
MATERIAL SHORTAGES AND, IN SOME CASES, INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES'* </p>
<p>CREDIT AVAILABILITY RAS NOT SO FAR BEEN A MAJOR CONSTRAINT<br />
MONETARY TIGHTNESS IS AT PRESENT CHIEFLY SERVING TO LIMIT THE<br />
DEGREE TO WHICH PEOPLE AND FIRMS BID AGAINST ONE ANOTHER FOR<br />
ALREADY SCARCE RESOURCES'*'<br />
CONSUMER SPENDING IS BOOMING. PRIVATE INVESTMENT<br />
ALSO IS MOVING UP STRONGLY* ALTHOUGH THE SUPPLY OF HOUSING<br />
FINANCE HAS COME DOWN FROM THE EXTRAORDINARY HEIGHTS OF A<br />
YEAR AGO, THE HOUSING INDUSTRY IS STILL VERY MUCH UND) ER STRAINt<br />
IN THE RECENT MARCH QUARTER, FOR EXAMPLE, THE INDUSTRY COMMENCED<br />
MORE DWELLINGS, IN SEASONALLY ADJUSTED TERMS, THAN IT HAS EVER<br />
BEEN ABLE TO COMPLETE IN A QUARTER. s AT THE END OF MARCH,<br />
THERE WERE 100,000 DWELLINGS UNDER CONSTRUCTIOM' SOME 30 PER CENT<br />
MORE THAN A YEAR EARLIER. IT IS THESE PRESSURES THAT HAVE<br />
CAUSED HOUSE PRICES TO RISE SO EXORBITANTLY AND PREVENTED<br />
MONEYS APPROPRIATED FOR WELFARE HOUSING FROM BEING PUT TO<br />
EFFECTIVE USE*' ALTHOUGH, IN-THE YEAR TO THE. MARCH QUARTER,'<br />
MORE DWELLINGS IN TOTAL WERE COMPLETED THAN IN ANY PREVIOUS<br />
COMPARABLE PERIOD, THERE WERE FEWER COMPLETED IN THE PUBLIC<br />
SECTOR THAN IN ANY OF THE PAST 15 YEARS'.<br />
THE PUBLIC SECTOR TOO IS TRYING TO INCREASE ITS<br />
SPENDING FASTER THAN THE AVAILABILITY OF RESOURCES WILL PERMIV.<br />
TIS IS ESPECIALLY TRUE OF CAPITAL EXPENDITURES, WHERE SUPPLY<br />
CONSTRAINTS ARE PREVENTING BUDGETED FUNDS FROM BEING SPENT AND<br />
TENDER PRICES WHERE TENDERS CAN BE OBTAINED ARE BEING DRIVEN<br />
UP EVEN MORE THAN COST MOVEMENTS WOULD NECESSITATE. o<br />
OUR POLICIES WILL BE DIRECTED TO BRINGING DEMAND BACK<br />
TO AN APPROPRIATE LEVEL, WITHOUT THAT THERE CAN BE NO HOPE OF<br />
CHECKING THE ACCELERATING TREND IN MONEY INCOMES, INFLATIONARY<br />
EXPECTATIONS, SPURRED ON BY THE RAPID CLIMB IN PRICES, ARE<br />
LEADING TO PRESSURE FOR VERY LARGE WAGE INCREASES AND TO0<br />
EMPLOYERS PAYING THEM IN THE EXPECTATION THAT INFLATION WILL </p>
<p>CONTINUE AND THAT THEY CAN THEREFORE BE PASSED ON AGAIN IN PRICES.<br />
WE ALL OF US MUST BREAK THOSE INFLATIONARY EXPECTATIONSO;<br />
WE MUST SHOW THAT THOSE WHO BANK ON DOUBLE-FIGURE INFLATION<br />
CONTINUING WILL BE PROVED WRONG AND SEE THAT THEY FIND THE<br />
LESSON AN EXPENSIVE ONE. IT HAS FOR SOME TIME BEEN EASY TO<br />
BORROW MONEY, INVEST IN REAL ASSETS SUCH AS PROPERTY, AND<br />
EMERGE WITH A HANDSOME PROFIT ARISING NOT FROM PRODUCTIVE<br />
EFFORT BUT FROM INFLATION". WHEN, AS WE WILL, WE HEAR OF<br />
SOME SUCH VENTURES GOING BADLY WRONG IN THE PERIOD AHEAD,<br />
WE WILL KNOW THAT THE RISK ELEMENT HAS BEEN RE-INTRODUCED<br />
INTO SUCH FORMS OF INVESTMENT.<br />
OF COURSE, THE GOVERNMENT'S PRESENT POLICIES WILL<br />
STEADILY BRING DEMAND BACK INTO LINE. THEY WILL GRADUALLY<br />
SLOW THE INCREASE IN PRIVATE SPENDING AS TIME GOES BY.<br />
BUT THAT WILL NOT BREAK THE PRESENT SPIRAL. AVERAGE<br />
EARNINGS SEEM TO HAVE RISEN 16-17 PER CENT IN 1973-74 AND<br />
IF PRESENT TRENDS WERE TO CONTINUE THEY WOULD BE LIKELY TO<br />
RISE BY MORE THAN 20 PER CENT IN 1974-75. MOREOVER, WITH<br />
PRICES RISING AT THE RATE THEY ARE, DEMANDS FOR NEW WAGE<br />
INCREASES ARE BEING MADE LITERALLY WITHIN MONTHS OF THE LAST<br />
DEMANY. THE SPIRAL MUST BE BROKEN'. THE PRICES JUSTIFICATION<br />
TRIBUNAL, WHICH WE PROPOSE TO STRENGTHEN, CAN ONLY DO SO MUCHf.<br />
IF THE SITUATION IS ALLOWED TO DRIFT, WE ARE LIKELY<br />
TO END WITH THE WORST OF ALL WORLDS OUTPUT WILL SLOW, BUT<br />
COST AND PRICE LEVELS WILL GO ON RISING, THE GROWTH OF<br />
IMPORTS WILL EXERT A DAMPENING INFLUENCE: BUT THAT FACTOR<br />
CANNOT BE CALLED UPON FOR EVEW.<br />
I HAVE ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS ADVOCATED A REFERENCE OF<br />
POWER OVER PRICES FROM THE STATES TO THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT.<br />
SOME OF YOU, I REALISE, HAVE EXPRESSED DOUBTS OR MISGIVINGS ABOUT<br />
THE IMPLICATIONS OF ANY TEMPORARY REFERENCE OF SUCH A POWER'.<br />
o../ 7 </p>
<p>I DO FEEL, HOW EVE R, THAT THERE ARE ASPECTS OF THIS POWER<br />
CURRENTLY VESTED IN THE STATES W9HICH ARE NOT BEING<br />
EFFECTIVELY USED IN MOST STATES IN THE FIGHT AGAINST<br />
INFLATION. THE MOST OBVIOUS EXAMPLE IS THE RAPID<br />
ESCALATION OF LAND PRICES WHICH IN 1973 WERE OF THE ORDER<br />
OF 30 PER CENT AND 40 PER CENT IN THE MAJOR STATE CAPITALS**<br />
OUR CONCLUSION THEREFORE IS THAT VIGOROUS AND<br />
DECISIVE ACTION IS NEEDED NOW AND IN THE MONTHS AHEAD,<br />
INCLUDING IN THE BUDGET, TO TURN BACK INFLATION.<br />
IN THIS, EVERYONE WILL HAVE TO PLAY A PART,<br />
THAT INCLUDES GOVERNME~ NTS.* THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WILL<br />
DO WHAT IT HAS TO DO, BOTH IN THE AREAS OF SPENDING AND<br />
COST-PUSH INFLATION. I MENTION HERE IN RELATION TO THE<br />
LATTER THAT I HAVE ALREADY SET UP AN INTERDEPARTMENTAL<br />
COMMITTEE, UNDER THE CHAIRMANSHIP OF MY OWN DEPARTMENT,<br />
AND INCLUDING THE DEPARTMENTS OF THE TREASURY AND LABOUR,<br />
TO PREPARE A REPORT FOR THE CONSIDERATION OF MINISTERS ON<br />
THE VERY IMPORTANT CONFERENCE CALLED BY MR JUSTICE MOORE<br />
TO CONSIDER METHODS OF WAGE FIXATION,<br />
TODAY, HOWEYVER, WE ARE CONSIDERING ISSUES<br />
RELATING TO GOVERNM4ENT SPENDING. AS I HAVE SAID,<br />
GOVERNMENT SPENDING IS NOT MORE INFLATIONARY THAN PRIVATE<br />
SPENDING, AS SOME OF OUR WILDER CRITICS SEEM TO ALLEGE.<br />
BUT NEITHER IS IT LESS INFLATIONARY, IN ORDER TO HELP<br />
BREAK INFLATIONARY EXPECTATIONS, WE MUST NOW SLOW THE RATE<br />
OF INCREASE IN GOVERNMENT SPENDING. SOME PHASING DOWN<br />
OR DEFERMENT OF SOME EXPENDITURE PLANS MUST OCCUR.' / 8 </p>
<p>AS REGARDS EXPENDITURE PROGRAMS WHICH ARE WHOLLY OUR<br />
OWN RESPONSIBILITY, THE GOVERNMENT WILL BE LOOKING CLOSELY AT<br />
ALL SUCH PROGRAMS AS IT PROCEEDS WITH PREPARATION FOR ITS<br />
1974-75 BUDGET. WE ARE ANXIOUS TO SEE THAT THERE IS CONTINUED<br />
SUBSTANTIAL PROGRESS WITH THlE PROGRAMS WE HAVE BEEN IMPLEMENTING,<br />
ESPECIALLY IN SUCH VITALLY IMPORTANT FIELDS AS EDUCATION AND<br />
lEALTW.* AT THE SAME TIME, WE RECOGNISE THAT IT WILL NOT BE<br />
FEASIBLE, IN THE CIRCUMSTANCES,-T0 ACHIEVE IN THE COMING<br />
FINANCIAL YEAR THE RATES OF PROGRESS WITH ALL THESE PROGRAMS TO<br />
WHICH EARLIER PLANNING AND EXPECTATIONS HAVE BEEN PITCHED.<br />
WITH A NUMBER OF THM, WE WILL HAVE TO ACCEPT A SLOWER RATE OF<br />
IMPLEMENTATION THAN WE HAD BEEN HOPING FOR. AS PART OF THE<br />
BATTLE TO CONTAIN INFLATION WE WILL BE FOLLOWING A POLICY OF<br />
RESTRAINT IN OUR OWN SPENDING. WE WILL ALSO BE LOOKING TO<br />
THOSE OF OUR BUSINESS ENTERPRISES WHICH ARE NOT PAYING THEIR OWN<br />
WAY TH1AT IS, WHOSE LOSSES ARE BEING IMPOSED ON THE TAXPAYER<br />
TO LIFT THEIR CHARGES'. USERS MUST PAY MORE OF THE COSTS INVOLVEDM<br />
FOR THE MOST PART, THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S<br />
DECISIONS REGARDING EXENDITURE IN THE COMING YEAR ON PROGRAMS'<br />
WHICH ARE WHOLLY ITS RESPONSIBILITY MUST NECESSARILY AWAIT THE<br />
1974-75 BUDGET. BUT I ANNOUNCE NOW CERTAIN DECISIONS WHICH<br />
ILLUSTRATE, BY WAY OF EXAMPLE, WHAT OUR APPROACH WILL BE.<br />
THE POST OFFICE WE INTEND TO KEEP THE BUDGET ALLOCATION FOR THE POST<br />
OFFICE IN 1974/ 75 TO NOT MORE THAN THE ACTUAL AMOUNT ALLOCATED<br />
IN 1973/ 74. THIS WILL MEAN TWO THINGS'. FIRST, THE POST<br />
OFFICE'S CAPITAL PROGRAM WILL HAVE TO BE REDUCED BELOW THE LEVEL<br />
THAT'HAD BEEN INDICATED BY THE POST OFFICE'S FORWARD PLANNING' </p>
<p>SECOND, EVEN TO FINANCE SUCH A REDUCED PROGRAM IT WILL BE<br />
NECESSARY FOR THE POST OFFICE TO RAISE SUBSTANTIAL<br />
ADDITIONAL REVENUE BY WAY OF INCREASED CHARGES. THE<br />
TELECOMMUNICATIONS SERVICE IS AT PRESENT OPERATING AT VERY<br />
MARGINAL RATES OF PROFITABILITY, AND THE POSTAL SERVICE IS<br />
PRESENTLY RUNNING AT A LOSS WHICH WOULD BE OVER $ 70 MILLION<br />
IN 1974/ 75. POSTAL AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS CHARGES WILL<br />
HAVE TO BE INCREASED SO THAT AS A GENERAL RULE THE PRICES<br />
PAID BY USERS OF THE SERVICES WILL MORE TRULY REFLECT<br />
COMMERCIAL COSTS. ONE EFFECT OF THIS WILL BE TO REDUCE<br />
DEMAND FOR NEW TELEPHONE SERVICES, WHICH IS AT PRESENT<br />
INFLATED BY THE LOW PRICES BEING CHARGED RELATIVE TO THE<br />
COST OF PROVIDING THE SERVICES'.<br />
TO ILLUSTRATE THE SIGNIFICANCE OF WHAT I HAVE<br />
SAID, I POINT OUT THAT ADVANCES TO THE POST OFFICE REPRESENT<br />
THE LARGES~ T SINGLE ITEM OF AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT EXPENDITURE<br />
ON ECONOMIC SERVICES. ADVANCES TO THE POST OFFICE IN 1973/ 74<br />
WILL AMOUNT TO $ 385 MILLION OUT OF A TOTAL EXPENDITURE ON ALL<br />
FORMS OF TRANSPORT AND COMMUNICATIONS OF ABOUT $ 860 MILLION.<br />
AS I HAVE-INDICATED, IT WILL BE NECESSARY FOR THE<br />
POST OFFICE TO RAISE SUBSTANTIAL ADDITIONAL REVENUE BY WAY OF<br />
INCREASEr CHARGES. THIS IS ENTIRELY CONSISTENT WITH ONE OF<br />
THE FINDINGS OF THE COMMISSION OF INQUIRY INTO THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
POST OFFICE ( THE VERNON COMMISSION) NAMELY, THAT AN<br />
OBJECTIVE IN SETTING CHARGES FOR POSTAL AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS<br />
SERVICES SHOULD BE TO RECOUP FROM USERS THE COST OF THE<br />
SERVICES AND ALSO TO PROVIDE, TOGETHER WITH OTHER FUNDS<br />
GENERATED INTERNALLY SUCH AS DEPRECIATION AND PROVISIONS,<br />
AMOUNTS EQUAL TO 50 PERCENT OF CAPITAL EXPENDITURE IN EACH<br />
YEARO 00/ 10 </p>
<p>1O.<br />
CAPITAL WORKS AND OTHER CAPITrAL EXPENDITURE:<br />
WE INTEND TO APPLY MOST STRINGENT RESTRAINTS ON<br />
CAPITAL WORKS AND OTHER CAPITAL EXPENDITURE IN 1974-75 BY<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTS AND AUTHORITIES. THE<br />
APPLICATION OF THESE RESTRAINTS WILL EXTEND TO PROJECTS IN<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY AND THE NORTHERN TERRITORY,<br />
WITH DUE RECOGNITION TO THE GOVERNMENT'S PRIORITIES IN THE<br />
HEALTH AND EDUCATION AREAS. TILE FIELD Is A COMPLEX ONE AND WE<br />
SHALL HAVE TO SORT OUT OUR PRIORITIES IN THE TIME AHEAD. AS<br />
ONE SPECIFIC EXAMPLE, HOWEVER, I MENTION THAT IN THE CASE OF<br />
CIVIL AVIATION CAPITAL WORKS WE SHALL IN 1974-75 HOLD ACTUAL<br />
EXPENDITURE TO. NOT MORE THAN THE LEVEL OF EXPENDITURE. IN<br />
1973-74. TO THAT END WE WILL BE TAKING ACTION TO SLOW DOWN<br />
THE RATE OF DEVELOPMENT OF NEW AIRPORT WORKS. IN ADDITION, THE<br />
CAPITAL WORKS PROGRAMS FOR CIVIL AVIATION IN THE YEAR 1974-75<br />
WILL BE FRAMED ON THE BASIS OF THE GOVERNMENT'S DECISION TO<br />
BE RECOVERING BY THE END OF FIVE YEARS 80 PER CENT OF THE<br />
COST OF AIRPORT AND AIRWAY FACILITIES FROM THE USERS OF THOSE<br />
FACILITIES. ACHIEVING THIS POLICY OBJECTIVE IS INVOLVING<br />
MEETINGS WITH ALL SECTORS OF THE-AVIATION INDUSTRY, THE<br />
MOST RECENT OF WHICH WAS HELD LAST WEEK. I ALSO ANNOUNCE<br />
THAT WE SHALL LIMIT EXPENDITURE IN 1974-75 ON THE OPERATION<br />
OF AIRPORT AND AIRWAY FACILITIES TO THE SAME REAL LEVEL AS<br />
IN 1973-74. </p>
<p>PETROLEUM PRODUCTS PRICES SUBSIDY SCHEME:<br />
THIS SCHEME AT PRESENT OPERATES TO KEEP THE<br />
WHOLESALE PRICES OF PETROLEUM PRODUCTS IN AREAS OUTSIDE<br />
THE CAPITAL CITIES TO WITHIN 5 CENTS PER GALLON OF CAPITAL<br />
CITY PRICES. THE SCHEME WOULD COST ABOUT $ 28 MILLION IN<br />
1974-75. THE COOMBS TASK FORCE SUGGESTED THAT THE SUBSIDY<br />
BE ABOLISHED, AND WE WOULD CERTAINLY HAVE BEEN ADOPTING THAT<br />
SUGGESTION IN THE COMING BUDGET. WE SHALL IN FACT NOW ADOPT<br />
IT WITHOUT FURTHER DELAY, WITH EFFECT FROM 1 AUGUST 1974.<br />
AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE:<br />
IN 1974-75 WE INTEND TO APPLY A CEILING INCREASE<br />
OF 2.6 PER CENT ON THE GROWTH OF FULL-TIME STAFF EMPLOYED<br />
UNDER THE PUBLIC SERVICE ACT. AFTER ALLOWANCE FOR AN<br />
INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF STAFF EXPECTED TO BE ON VARIOUS<br />
FORMS OF LEAVE, THE CEILING INCREASE IN 1974-75 ON TOTAL<br />
OPERATIVE STAFF EMPLOYED UNDER THE PUBLIC SERVICE ACT<br />
WILL BE 1 PER CENT.<br />
THESE STAFF CEILINGS DO NOT OF COURSE TAKE INTO<br />
ACCOUNT ANY TRANSFER OF GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES INTO OR OUT<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE.<br />
THE FIGURE OF 2.6 PER CENT COMPARES WITH AN<br />
AVERAGE COMPOUND GROWTH RATE FOR THE PERIOD JUNE 1962 TO<br />
JUNE 1972 -THE LAST TEN YEARS OF LIBERAL-COUNTRY PARTY<br />
GOVERNMENT -FOR FULL-TIME STAFF EMPLOYED UNDER THE PUBLIC<br />
SERVICE ACT OF 3.87 PER CENT. / 12 </p>
<p>12.<br />
THE STRINGENT RESTRAINT ON THE GROWTH OF STAFF<br />
NUMBERS IN THE AUSTRALIAN PUBLIC SERVICE WILL BE REFLECTED<br />
NOT ONLY IN SALARY COSTS, BUT ALSO IN NON-SALARY DEPARTMENTAL<br />
ADMINISTRATIVE COSTS.<br />
A SIMILAR LEVEL OF RESTRAINT WILL BE APPLIED TO<br />
STAFF NUMBERS EMPLOYED BY AUTHORITIES THAT DO NOT COME<br />
UNDER THE PUBLIC SERVICE ACT.<br />
DEFENCE PROGRAM: IN THE DEFENCE FIELD, FURTHER ECONOMIES WILL BE<br />
ACHIEVED IN CIVILIAN MANPOWER. AS ANNOUNCED IN AUGUST 1973,<br />
A MAJOR REDUCTION IN CIVILIAN MANPOWER IS BEING MADE IN THE<br />
DEPARTMENTS OF DEFENCE AND SUPPLY DURING THE CURRENT YEAR<br />
1973/ 74. THIS LARGE SAVING IS BEING ACHIEVED MAINLY By<br />
ECONOMIES, AND THROUGH IMPROVED MANAGEMENT. IT HAS ALLOWED<br />
RE-ALLOCATION OF AVAILABLE FUNDS TO HIGHER DEFENCE PRIORITIES<br />
INCLUDING ESSENTIAL NEW FACILITIES AND EQUIPMENTS. PLANS<br />
FOR THE 1974/ 75 BUDGET AS PREVIOUSLY ANNOUNCED IN DECEMBER<br />
1973 ENVISAGE A FURTH-ER REDUCTION IN CIVILIAN EMPLOYMENT IN<br />
THE DEFENCE DEPARTMENT OF ABOUT 1500, EVEN THOUGH<br />
LEGISLATION TO IMPLEMENT THE DEFENCE RE-ORGANISATION HAS BEEN<br />
DELAYED BY THE PROROGUING OF PARL. IAMENT.<br />
IN THE MUNITIONS FACTORIES, THE REDUCED SCALE OF<br />
PRODUCTION NOW NECESSARY FOR DEFENCE PURPOSES WILL ALLOW THE<br />
RELEASE TO TI'E CIVILIAN WORKFORCE OF A SUBSTANTIAL NUMBER OF<br />
WORKERS INCLUDING MANY WITH SKILLS SCARCE IN THE PRESENT TIGHT<br />
EMPLOYMENT SITUATION. THIS SURPLUS OF LABOUR OVER THAT ./ 13 </p>
<p>13.<br />
ESSENTIAL TO PROVIDE THE SERVICES' REQUIREMENTS FOR MUNITIONS<br />
IS NOT A NEW SITUATION BUT IS ONE WHICH SHOULD HAVE BEEN FACED<br />
LONG AGO BY THE PREVIOUS COALITION GOVERNMENT. A SIMILAR BUT<br />
MUCH LESS SEVERE SITUATION APPLIES IN THE R D ESTABLISHMENTS<br />
AND TlIERE MAY BE A SMALL RESIDUAL PROBLEM IN THE SHORT TERM<br />
AT WILLIAMSTOWN NAVAL DOCKYARD.<br />
ANY REDUCTIONS IN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT EMPLOYMENT<br />
WILL BE MADE AS FAR AS PRACTICAL BY NOT REPLACING THE NORMAL<br />
WASTAGE OF PERSONNEL. RETRENCHMENTS WILL, HOWEVER, BECOME<br />
NECESSARY IN CERTAIN AREAS FOR ONE THING TO KEEP THE RIGHT<br />
SORT OF BALANCE IN EMPLOYMENT. WHERE DISMISSALS BECOME<br />
NECESSARY THE GOVERNMENT WILL ENSURE THAT STEPS ARE TAKEN<br />
TO HELP THE INDIVIDUAL CONCERNED TO MOVE INTO OTH-ER<br />
EMPLOYMENT, INCLUDING SOME FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE AND<br />
RETRAINING WHERE NECESSARY. I MIGHT ADD THAT THE GOVERNMENT<br />
NOW HAS, FOR CONSIDERATION, A REPORT OF AN INTERDEPARTMENTAL<br />
COMMITTEE, SETTING OUT GUIDELINES FOR ASSISTANCE FOR AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES WHO BECOME REDUNDANT AN]) WOULD MAKE ITS<br />
DECISION ON THE PROVISIONS OF THIS REPORT BEFORE DISMISSALS<br />
TPKE PLACE. A REVIEW OF THE ARMY'S REQUIREMENTS FOR LIGHT<br />
OBSERVATION HELICOPTERS HAS BEEN COMPLETED AND THE PRODUCTION<br />
PROGRAM WILL BE REDUCED FROM 75 TO 56 MILITARY AIRCRAFT.<br />
AS A CONSEQUENCE PROPOSED ASSOCIATED PRODUCTION OF 116<br />
HELICOPTERS WILL NOT NOW BE UNDERTAKEN. THE OVERALL SAVING<br />
IN THE PROJECT WILL BE ABOUT $ 12 MILLION OVER THE NEXT FIVE / 14 </p>
<p>14.<br />
YEARS. CONSEQUENTIAL EFFECTS ON EMPLOYMENT AT COMMONWEALTH<br />
AIRCRAFT CORPORATION WILL BE EXAMINED IN THE CONTEXT OF AN<br />
OVERALL RATIONALISATION OF THE AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY.<br />
I EMP111ASISE THAT THE FOREGOING ARE ONLY EXAMPLES<br />
AND DO NOT CONSTITUTE A COMPREHIENSIVE LIST OF DECISIONS.<br />
THAT MUST AWAIT THE PREPARATION OF THE 1974/ 75 BUDGET.<br />
BUT TI-E EXAMPLES I HAVE GIVEN ARE, I BELIEVE, SUFFICIENT TO<br />
DEMONSTRATE THE STRINGENCY OF THE APPROACH THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT WILL BE TAKING AT THAT TIME.<br />
AS REGARDS EXENDITUJRE PROPOSALS INVOLVING NEW<br />
OR ADDITIONAL SPECIFIC PURPOSE PAYMENTS BY THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT TO THE STATES, WE WILL ALSO NEED TO APPLY STRICT<br />
TESTS, BOTH AS TO HOW THE PROPOSALS MEASURE UP IN TERMS OF<br />
NATIONAL INTERESTS AND AS TO TIMING, BEFORE WE CAN<br />
CONTEMPLATE COMMITTING OURSELVES TO THEM.<br />
I CAN, HOXEVrP., AT THIS POINT INDICATE OUR<br />
PROPOSALS WITH RESPECT TO ROADS AND WELFARE HOUSING.<br />
NO DOUBT YOU HAVE ALL SEEN THE BUREAU OF ROADS'<br />
RECENT REPORT ON " ROADS IN AUSTRALIA". THIS RECOMMENDS<br />
THlE PROVISION OF AUSTRALIAN GOVERMIENT ASSISTANCE FOR ROADS<br />
OVER THE NEXT FIVE YEARS.<br />
WE HAVE DECIDED HOWEVER TO RESTRICT THE PERIOD<br />
OF THE NEXT ROAD ASSISTANCE LEGISLATION TO THREE ' YEARS.<br />
OVER THE NEXT 18 MONTHS WE SHALL BE WORKING TO RATIONALISE<br />
OUR SEPARATE ROAD AND URBAN TRANSPORT ASSISTANCE INTO A<br />
CLOSELY CO-ORDINATED) AND INTEGRATED SET OF ARRANGEMENTS. </p>
<p>AN IMPORTANT STEP IN THIS REGARD IS THE ACTION WE HAVE<br />
ALREADY TAKEN TO COMBINE THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S MAJOR<br />
TRANSPORT RESPONSIBILITIES UNDER ONE MINISTER AND WITHIN ONE<br />
DEPARTMENT. THIS WILL FACILITATE EFFICIENT ALLOCATION OF<br />
RESOURCES, BOTH BETWEEN THE VARIOUS TRANSPORT MODES AND<br />
BETWEEN TRANSPORT AND OTHER AREAS OF INVESTMENT, AND WE<br />
CAN NOW PROCEED MORE CERTAINLY TOWARDS THAT OBJECTIVE. MY<br />
GOVERNMENT HOPES TO LEGISLATE BY THE END OF 1975 FOR A NEW<br />
APPROACH TO TRANSPORT ASSISTANCE FOR THE STATES TO COMMENCE<br />
IN JULY 1977. A PRINCIPAL AIM IN OUR INTENTION TO<br />
LEGISLATE FOR THE 1977 TO 1980 PERIOD 18 MONTHS BEFORE ITS<br />
COMMENCEMENT IS TO ASSIST YOU WITH YOUR FORWARD PLANNING.<br />
IN THE MEANTIME, THE NEW ROADS ASSISTANCE LEGISLATION<br />
WILL BE INTRODUCED IN THE FIRST SESSION OF THE NEW PARLIAMENT<br />
AND WILL APPROPRIATE A TOTAL OF $ 1,120 MILLION AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT ASSISTANCE OVER THE NEXT THREE YEARS FOR ROADS<br />
IN THE STATES. THIS IS LESS THAN THE AMOUNT OF $ 1,345 MILLION<br />
THE BUREAU OF ROADS RECOMMENDED FOR THIS PERIOD; BUT THE<br />
BUREAU'S REPORT MUST BE LOOKED AT IN A TOTAL ECONOMIC<br />
CONTEXT AND IN THE LIGHT OF ALL OUR PRIORITIES RATHER THAN<br />
IN TERMS OF ROADS OR TRANSPORT IN ISOLATION. THE $ 1,120<br />
MILLION WILL BE MADE UP OF $ 348 MILLION FOR 1974-75,<br />
$ 367 MILLION FOR 1975-76 AND $ 405 MILLION FOR 1976-77.<br />
IN MY ELECTION POLICY SPEECH I ANNOUNCED THAT THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAD DECIDED TO PRESS AHEAD WITH THE<br />
CONSTRUCTION OF A NATIONAL ROADS SYSTEM IN THOSE AREAS WHICH / 16 </p>
<p>FALL WITHIN ITS OWN CONSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES AND<br />
THAT, IN PARTICULAR, IT WOULD IN FUTURE TAKE RESPONSIBILITY<br />
FOR THE WHOLE COST OF CONSTRUCTING AND MAINTAINING THE<br />
PRINCIPAL ROAD BETWEEN STATE CAPITALS AND OF EXPORT ROADS<br />
TO AIRPORTS AND SEAPORTS. OUT OF THE TOTAL OF S1,120<br />
MILLION PREVIOUSLY MENTIONED, WE WILL ALLOCATE A SUM OF<br />
1400 MILLION OVER THE NEXT THREE YEARS TO EMBARK ON THIS<br />
MAJOR NEW INITIATIVE.<br />
FULL DETAILS OF THE PROPOSED NEW PROGRAM OF<br />
ASSISTANCE FOR ROADS WILL BE CONVEYED TO YOU SHORTLY.<br />
IN DETERMINING THE OVERALL AMOUNT THAT WE-WOULD<br />
BE ABLE TO MAKE AVAILABLE FOR ROADS WE HAVE, AS I INDICATED,<br />
HAD TO TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION OTHER TRANSPORT PROGRAMS,<br />
PARTICULARLY IN THE URBAN AREAS. WE SEE IMPROVED PUBLIC<br />
TRANSPORT AS ESSENTIAL FOR IMPROVEMENT OF THE LOT OF OUR<br />
CITY DWELLERS, AND WE PROPOSE TO PRESS ON WITH THE URBAN<br />
PUBLIC TRANSPORT PROGRAMS WE HAVE INITIATED. THE<br />
TREASURER STATED IN HIS BUDlGET SPEECH LAST YEAR THAT IT<br />
COULD BE EXPECTED THAT OUR OUTLAYS IN THIS FIELD WILL<br />
INCREASE RAPIDLY IN 1974-75 AND BEYOND AS THIS MAJOR NEW<br />
CAPITAL WORKS PROGRAM GETS UNDER WAY. THAT PROSPECT STILL<br />
HOLDS. WE ALSO SEE THlE RAILWAYS AS HAVING A VITAL ROLE IN<br />
OUR ECONOMY, BUT THEY MUST BE MODERNISED AND MADE MORE<br />
EFFICIENT. SO WE ALSO INTEND TO PRESS AHEAD WITH OUR<br />
RAILWAY PROGRAMS. IN THIS REGARD, I RECALL THAT ONLY<br />
RECENTLY I SIGNED AGREEMENTS WITH THE PREMIER OF SOUTH @ 17<br />
16. </p>
<p>17.<br />
AUSTRALIA FOR THE NEW STANDARD GAUGE RAILWAY LINE TO ALICE<br />
SPRINGS AND ADELAIDE.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO ENSURE THAT LESS<br />
PRIVILEGED FAMILIES IN OUR SOCIETY ARE NOT DENIED THE CHLANCE<br />
TO LIVE IN ADEQUATE HOMES, AN) THAT MANY MORE LOW-INCOME<br />
FAMILIES ARE GIVEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO BUY HOMES OF THEIR<br />
OWN. OUR PRESENT POLICIES ARE DIRECTED TO BRINGING ABOUT A<br />
MORE BALANCED SITUATION IN THE HOUSING INDUSTRY AS A WHOLE.<br />
THEY ARE DESIGNED BOTH TO EASE THE PRESSURE ON RESOURCES<br />
AND THE CONSEQUENTIAL BIDDING UP OF COSTS AND PRICES IN<br />
THE INDUSTRY AND TO MAKE ROOM FOR A MORE REASONABLE LEVEL<br />
OF DWELLING CONSTRUCTION BY THE PUBLIC SECTOR. NOT ALL<br />
THE STATES WERE ABLE, IN 1973-74, TO EFFECTIVELY USE THE<br />
$ 218.5 MILLION ADVANCED TO THEM UNDER THE 1973 HOUSING<br />
AGREEMENT. AS A RESULT, SOME MONEYS PROVIDED UNDER THE<br />
AGREEMENT WERE NOT USED AT ALL AND WILL THEREFORE REMAIN<br />
AVAILABLE F~ OR USE IN 1974-75.<br />
SOME FUNDS WERE ALSO USED, IN 1973-74, AS IN<br />
PREVIOUS YEARS, TO PURCHASE LAND FOR FUTURE USE BY STATE<br />
HOUSING AUTHORITIES. IN THE YEAR AHEAD, HOWEVER, WE THINK<br />
THAT ADVANTAGE SHOULD BE TAKEN OF THE EASIER CONDITIONS<br />
LIKELY TO DEVELOP TO SWITCH THE BALANCE OF ACTIVITY FROM<br />
LAND PURCHASE TOWARDS INCREASED BUILDING. AS PART OF THE<br />
BATTLE AGAINST INFLATION MY GOVERNMENT HAS MADE AVAILABLE AND<br />
IS OFFERING FUNDS TO YOU TO SET UP LAND COMMISSIONS TO<br />
REDUCE LAND PRICES BY MAKING LAND AVAILABLE AT COST. WHILE </p>
<p>18.<br />
WE HAVE RECOGNISED THAT MONEY FOR WELFARE HOUSING SHOULD BE<br />
MADE AVAILABLE THROUGH THE HOUSING AGREEMENT AT AN INTEREST<br />
RATE OF ONLY 4 PER CENT, IT WOULD NOT BE APPROPRIATE FOR<br />
THIS MONEY TO BE USED FOR THE PURCHASE AND DEVELOPM4ENT<br />
OF LARGE ESTATES FOR SALE TO PEOPLE WHO WOULD NOT<br />
QUALIFY UNDER THE MEANS TEST FOR WELFARE HOUSING. WE<br />
LOOK FORWARD IN THE FUTURE TO THE STATE HOUSING AUTHORITIES<br />
OBTAINING MOST, IF NOT ALL, OF THEIR LAND REQUIREMENTS<br />
THROUGH THE LAND COMMISSIONS.<br />
IN THE CIRCUMSTANCES WE ARE PROPOSING TO MAKE<br />
ADVANCES OF $ 235 MILLION UNDER THE AGREEMENT IN 1974-75<br />
IN ADDITION TO THE AMOUNT CARRIED FORWARD FROM 1973-74.<br />
THIS WILL, IN FACT, MEAN A SUBSTANTIAL INCREASE IN THE<br />
FUNDS AVAILABLE TO THE STATES FOR EXPENDITURE ON WELFARE<br />
HOUSING. HOWEVER, IN VIEW OF THE LIMITATIONS WHICH THE<br />
HOUSING AGREEMENT PROVIDES IN RESPECT OF THE FUNDS FOR<br />
THE HOME BUILDERS ACCOUNT, IT IS PROPOSED TO DISCUSS WITH<br />
TPE STATES AN AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT WHICH WOULD<br />
PERMIT A HIGHER PROPORTION OF AVAILABLE FUNDS TO BE<br />
ALLOCATED TO THE HOME BUILDERS ACCOUNT WHEN CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
WARRANT. WE THUS LOOK FORWARD IN 1974-75 TO THE COMPLETION<br />
OF CONSIDERABLY MORE DWELLINGS IN THE PUBLIC SECTOR THAN IN<br />
1973-74. BUT I SHOULD ALSO SAY THAT, IN THE LIGHT OF<br />
DEVELOPMENTS IN THE INDUSTRY AS A WHOLE AS THE YEAR UNFOLDS,<br />
INCLUDING THE AVAILABILITY OF RESOURCES FOR HOUSING CONSTRUCTION<br />
AND THE ABILITY OF THE STATES TO PUT FURTHER FUNDS TO PRODUCTIVE<br />
USE IN WELFARE HOUSING, WE STAND READY TO CONSULT FURTHER<br />
WITH THE STATES ON THE PROVISION OF ADDITIONAL ADVANCES. / 19 </p>
<p>19.<br />
THE STATE GOVERNMENTS MUST ALSO PLAY THEIR PARTS<br />
IN BEATING INFLATION. MANY OF THE PREMIERS UNDERTOOK,<br />
DURING THE ELECTION CAMPAIGN, TO CO-OPERATE WITH AN L-CP<br />
GOVERNMENT, HAD THAT BEEN RETURNED, IN THE FIGHT AGAINST<br />
INFLATION. THE FIGHT IS ON AND I HOPE THAT THE FULL<br />
CO-OPERATION AND UNDERSTANDING OF THE STATE GOVERNN4ENTS<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, IN THE CONTROL OF LAND PRICES WILL BE<br />
FORTHCOMING. IN 1973-74 TOTAL PAYMENTS TO THE STATES GREW<br />
RAPIDLY. TAKING ALL FORMS OF PAYMENTS TO THE STATES<br />
TOGETHER WITH THE STATE GOVERNMENTS' LOAN COUNCIL PROGRAMS,<br />
THE INCREASE IS ESTIMATED AT OVER 20 PER CENT. EVEN<br />
ALLOWING FOR THE EFFECTS OF INCREASES IN COSTS, THIS<br />
REPRESENTS A VERY SUBSTANTIAL INCREASE.<br />
THE CRUCIAL QUESTION, OF COURSE, IS THIS:<br />
TO WHAT EXTENT HAVE THESE LARGE INCREASES IN FUNDS BEEN<br />
TRANSLATED INTO REAL IMPROVEMENTS IN THE STANDARDS OF<br />
STATE-PROVIDED SERVICES AND FACILITIES? IT SEEMS THAT,<br />
PARTICULARLY IN THE FIELDS OF HOUSING AND CONSTRUCTION,<br />
RESOURCES HAVE BEEN OVERSTRETCHED AND INFLATION HAS EATEN<br />
HEAVILY INTO THE MONEY SUMS AVAILABLE. BECAUSE OF<br />
SHORTAGES OF'LABOUR AND MATERIALS IN THESE AREAS, THE STATES<br />
AND THEIR AUTHORITIES HAVE IN SOME CASES BEEN UNABLE TO USE<br />
ALL THE FUNDS AVAILABLE TO THEM.<br />
THE PRESENT REVENUE ASSISTANCE ARRANGEMENTS<br />
BETWEEN THE AUSTRALIAN AND STATE GOVERNMENTS WERE </p>
<p>ORIGINALLY SETTLED IN JUNE 19) 70 AND WERE INTENDED TO APPLY<br />
OVER THE FIVE YEARS 1970-71 TO 1974-75. MY GOVERNMENT<br />
ACCEPTS THE OBLIGATION TO REVIEW THE ARRANGEMENTS BEFORE<br />
THE END OF 1974-75 WITH A VIEW TO DETERMINING WHAT CHANGES<br />
IN THEM, IF ANY, SHOULD APPLY FROM 1975-76.<br />
IN THE LIGHT OF WHAT I HAVE SAID ABOUT ACTION<br />
PROPOSED IN THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S EXPENDITURE PROGRAMS,<br />
WE HAVE GIVEN CLOSE ATTENTION TO WHAT WE CONSIDER IS BOTH<br />
APPROPRIATE AN]) FEASIBLE BY WAY OF ADDITIONAL REVENUE<br />
ASSISTANCE, AND SUPPORT FOR BORROWING PROGRAMS, FOR STATE<br />
GOVERNMENTS. ON THE REVENUE SIDE, I SHOULD FIRST EXPRESS<br />
OUR APPRECIATION OF THE MATERIAL YOU HAVE ALL PROVIDED ON<br />
YOUR FINANCIAL POSITIONS THIS YEAR, AND YOUR PROSPECTIVE<br />
BUDGETARY POSITIONS IN 1974-75.<br />
ALREADY, BOTH AS A RESULT OF THE OPERATION OF<br />
THE FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE GRANTS FORMULA AND OF THE SPECIAL<br />
FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE WHICH WE AGREED TO PROVIDE TO THE<br />
STATES THIS YEAR, TOTAL FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE GRANTS IN<br />
1973-74 ARE ESTIMATED TO SHOW AN INCREASE ON 1972-73 OF<br />
$ 208 ' MILLION. WE HAVE CONCLUDED THAT THERE IS NO CASE<br />
FOR ANY ADDITIONAL REVENUE ASSISTANCE THIS YEAR. WHILE<br />
MOST STATES APPEAR LIKELY TO INCUR BUDGET DEFICITS THIS<br />
YEAR, THE EXTENT OF THESE APPEARS TO US TO BE MANAGEABLE<br />
GIVEN THE OVERALL ACCUMULATED POSITIONS ON REVENUE AND<br />
./ 21 </p>
<p>21.<br />
LOAN ACCOUNTS COMBINED AS AT 30 JUNE NEXT.<br />
FOR 1974-75, THE OUTLOOK, AS PRESENTLY REVEALED<br />
BY THE INFORMATION PROVIDED, IS FOR SUBSTANTIAL DEFICITS IN<br />
THE ABSENCE OF ANY NEW TAXES OR CHARGES, AND BEFORE ALLOWING<br />
FOR WAGE INCREASES THAT CANNOT BE FORESEEN BUT WHICH WILL<br />
OCCUR THROUGH THE YEAR. IT IS HIGHLY RELEVANT THAT A<br />
MAJOR ELEMENT IN THE PRESENT AND PROSPECTIVE BUDGETARY<br />
POSITIONS OF THE STATES IS TO BE FOUND IN THE LOSSES<br />
BEING MADE BY THEIR BUSINESS UNDERTAKINGS PARTICULARLY<br />
THEIR RAILWAYS. HOWEVER THAT MAY BE, WE ARE LOOKING TO<br />
THE STATES TO CLOSE THOSE GAPS FROM THEIR OWN RESOURCES.<br />
THOSE RESOURCES, OF COURSE, INCLUDE VERY<br />
SUBSTANTIAL INCREASES IN THE GENERAL REVENUE GRANTS-PROVIDED<br />
UNDER THE FORMULA. EVEN SO, WE REALISE THAT THE CLOSING<br />
OF THE STATES' PROSPECTIVE REVENUE GAPS WILL NOT BE EASY.<br />
NOR HAVE MANY OF THE DECISIONS WE HAVE HAD TO TAKE DURING<br />
THE PAST EIGHTEEN MONTHS BEEN EASY. DECISIONS TO<br />
TERMINATE THE SUPERPHOSPHATE BOUNTY, TO PHASE OUT THE<br />
SUBSIDY ON THE PRODUCTION OF DAIRY PRODUCTS, TO<br />
TERMINATE THE INVESTMENT ALLOWANCES, TO REDUCE TARIFFS, TO<br />
REVALUE THE CURRENCY NONE OF THESE DECISIONS WAS EASY.<br />
WE TOOK THEM BECAUSE THE PREVIOUSLY PREVAILING SITUATION<br />
IN EACH CASE REPRESENTED A DISTORTION OF THE ECONOMY AWAY<br />
FROM THE PUBLIC INTEREST GENERALLY AND TOWARDS A SECTIONAL<br />
INTEREST. WE ACTED IN THE PUBLIC INTEREST; AND WE LOOK </p>
<p>22.<br />
TO THE STATE GOVERNMENTS TO DO LIKEWISE WITHIN THEIR OWN<br />
DOMAINS. FOR EXAMPLE, A MOMENT AGO, I REFERRED TO THE<br />
LOSSES OF STATE RAILWAYS. LET ME ADD A FEW WORDS.<br />
UNDER OUR URBAN PUBLIC TRANSPORT PROGRAM-AND<br />
IN OTHER WAYS, WE WILL BE ENDEAVOURING TO HELP IMPROVE<br />
AUSTRALIA' S RAILWAYS. WE HOPE YOU WILL COMPLEMENT OUR<br />
EFFORTS BY LOOKING CAREFULLY AT THE OPERATING PROCEDURES<br />
AND EXPENSES OF YOUR RAILWAYS. WE WOULD BE PREPARED TO<br />
PROVIDE FUNDS FOR SUCH INVESTIGATIONS THROUGH OUR<br />
PROPOSED TRANSPORT RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMS.<br />
AT THE PRESENT TIME THE STATE RAILWAY SYSTEMS<br />
ARE INEFFICIENT, OUTDATED AND FACING ENORMOUS DEFICITS.<br />
THIS IS WHY I OFFERED TO ACCEPT RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE<br />
RAILWAYS OF ANY STATE THAT WAS PREPARED TO TRANSFER<br />
THEM. THAT OFFER STILL STANDS AND WE WOULD HOPE THAT IN<br />
THE INTERESTS OF EFFICIENT TRANSPORT THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA<br />
THE GOVERNMENTS OF VICTORIA AND QUEENSLAND WILL<br />
RECONSIDER THEIR DECISIONS NOT TO DISCUSS THIS MATTER<br />
WITH US. I HAVE SEEN RECENT NEWSPAPER REPORTS OF STATEMENTS<br />
BY MR MORRIS, N. S. W. MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT, THAT HIS<br />
RAILWAY SYSTEM WILL HAVE A DEFICIT THIS YEAR OF<br />
$ 126 MILLION. TO OVERCOME THIS PROBLEM HE INDICATED IT<br />
WOULD BE NECESSARY TO ATTRACT MORE BUSINESS AND SEVERELY<br />
RATIONALISE RAIL OPERATIONS WHICH ARE NOT SOCIALLY OR / 23 </p>
<p>23.<br />
ECONOMICALLY VIA. BLE AT T~ lE SA. ME TIME MR MORRIS<br />
PLEDGED THAT THIS WOULD NOT INVOLVE THE SACKING OR<br />
RETRENCHMENT OF STAFF. I B3ELIEVE THIS IS A STEP IN THE<br />
RIGHT DIRECTION. RAILWAY DEFICITS OF THIS MAGNITUDE ARE<br />
UNACCEPTABLE AT ANY TIME BUT MORE PARTICULARLY SO IN THE<br />
PRESENT CLIMATE.<br />
WHAT I HAVE SAID EARLIER BOILS DOWN TO SAYING THAT,<br />
WHILE WE DO NOT INTEND TO PROVIDE ANY ASSISTANCE OVER AND<br />
ABOVE THAT ALREADY COMMITTED, WE ARE STANDING BY OUR<br />
PRESENT COMMITMENTS. ONE OF THESE PRESENT COMMITMENTS BY WHICH WE<br />
STAND IS TO HELP ALLEVIATE THE EFFECTS OF NATURAL<br />
DISASTERS. THESE CAN THROW UNEXPECTED FINANCIAL BURDENS<br />
ON THE STATES AND THEIR AUTHORITIES. I WROTE TO THE<br />
PREMIERS EARLIER THIS YEAR SETTING OUT OUR POLICY IN THIS<br />
AREA. I REAFFIRM THAT POLICY. IT PROVIDES VERY REAL<br />
PROTECTION FOR THE STATES AGAINST WHAT COULD OTHERWISE<br />
BE INTOLERABLE FINANCIAL BURDENS FOR THEM. IN ILLUSTRATION<br />
OF THIS, I POINT OUT THAT WE HAVE LEGISLATED FOR PAYMENT<br />
OF UP TO $ 71.5 MILLI-ON TO QUEENSLAND AND NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
FOR RELIEF AND RESTORATION MEASURES FOLLOWING THE FLOODS<br />
IN THOSE STATES EARLIER THIS YEAR, AND HAVE ALREADY<br />
PROVIDED SOME $ 20 MILLION OF THIS. THIS ASSISTANCE IS,<br />
OF COURSE, IN ADDITION TO THE QUITE LARGE COSTS OF MAKING<br />
AVAILABLE MEMBERS OF THE ARMED SERVICES AND THE CIVIL<br />
DEFENCE ORGANISATION AND THEIR EQUIPMENT FOR EMERGENCY / 24 </p>
<p>24.<br />
RESCUE AND RELIEF OPERATIONS.<br />
I MENTIONED EARLIER THE ADJUSTMENTS WHICH WE<br />
MADE TO GENERAL PURPOSE FUNDS PROVIDED TO THE STATES IN<br />
1973-74 TO OFFSET THE COSTS TO THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S<br />
BUDGET AND THE GAINS TO THE STATES' BUDGETS, RESULTING<br />
FROM OUR NEW OR EXPANDED COMMITMENTS IN THE FIELDS OF<br />
WELFARE HOUSING AND TERTIARY EDUCATION. THESE ADJUSTMENTS<br />
WERE MADE IN PURSUANCE OF A GENERAL PRINCIPLE WHICH<br />
MIGHT, IN SHORTHAND TERMS, BE REFERRED TO AS THE<br />
" OFFSETS PRINCIPLE". AND WHICH I OUTLINED IN MY OPENING<br />
SPEECH AT THE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE LAST YEAR. THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IS FIRMLY COMMITTED TO THIS PRINCIPLE<br />
AND WILL PURSUE ITS APPLICATION WHEREVER APPROPRIATE. I<br />
HAVE INFORMED PREMIERS OF OUR INTENTION TO DO SO IN<br />
RESPECT OF INITIATIVES WE ARE TAKING IN THE FIELDS OF<br />
ABORIGINAL AFFAIRS AND ASSISTANCE FOR DESERTED WIVES, AND<br />
I EXPECT THAT FURTHER CASES COULD ARISE AS WE DEVELOP OUR<br />
POLICIES IN OTHER AREAS.<br />
IN CONSIDERING THE SIZE OF THE LOAN COUNCIL<br />
BORROWING PROGRAMS* WE COULD SUPPORT, WE HAVE BEEN VERY<br />
CONSCIOUS THAT MANY OF THE PROJECTS BOTH THOSE ALREADY<br />
UNDER WAY AND NEW PROJECTS PROPOSED WHICH THE BORROWING<br />
PROGRAMS SUBMITTED BY THE STATES AND THEIR AUTHORITIES<br />
WOULD COVER WOULD BE VERY DESIRABLE. INDEED, PROGRESS<br />
WITH MANY OF THEM IS A NECESSARY INGREDIENT FOR<br />
ACHIEVEMENT OF OUR OBJECTIVES IN SUCH VITALLY IMPORTANT </p>
<p>AREAS AS EDUCATION, HEALTH, URBAN PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION<br />
AND URBAN AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT GENERALLY. WE WILL<br />
BE PROVIDING SUBSTANTIALLY INCREASED FUNDS IN THE COMING<br />
FINANCIAL YEAR, BY WAY OF SPECIFIC PURPOSE PAYMENTS,<br />
UNDER THE NEW PROGRAMS WE HAVE INITIATED IN THESE AREAS,<br />
AND WE WILL BE AIMING TO PRESS AHEAD WITH THESE IN<br />
CO-OPERATION WITH THE STATES.<br />
WE HAVE ALL RECOGNISED THAT CERTAIN ITEMS<br />
NAVE AN INDISPUTABLE PRIORITY AND URGENCY. NONE OF USCAN<br />
DOUBT THAT IT IS ONE OF OUR MOST PRESSING OBLIGATIONS<br />
TO INCREASE THE SUPPLY OF SERVICE) LAND FOR PROSPECTIVE<br />
HOME BUILDERS. THE PRICE OF LAND FOR RESIDENTIAL<br />
BUILDING MUST BE REDUCED. THERE . IS NO DISPUTE THAT A<br />
SUSTAINED COLLABORATIVE EFFORT IS REQUIRED TO ELIMINATE<br />
THE SEWERAGE BACKLOG IN OUR MtkJOR CITIES AND TOWNS. IT<br />
IS SURELY NOT A MATTER.-OF DE--ATE THIAT OUR INADEQUATE<br />
PUBLIC TRANSPORT'SYSTEMS NEED IMM1EDIATE IMPROVEMENT.<br />
ON ALL OF THESE MATTERS THE OBJECTIVES OF OUR<br />
RESPECTIVE GOVERNMENTS ARE EVIDENTLY IN HARMONY. OUR<br />
MUTUAL ASSESSMENT OF PRIORITIES SHOULD BE REFLECTED IN<br />
THlE WIAY W4E SPEND THE FUNDS AVAILABLE. WHERE WE HAVE<br />
PROVIDED ADDITIONAL FUNDS TO OVERCOME A BACKLOG SITUATION,<br />
SUCH AS EXISTS WITH RESPECT TO SEWERAGE AND URBAN PUBLIC<br />
TRANSPORT, THEN I AM SURE THAT YOU WILL WANT TO MAINTAIN<br />
YOUR OWN EFFORT IN THESE FIELDS.<br />
AGAINST TIHAT BACKGROUND, WE ARE PREPARED TO<br />
SUPPORT SOME INCREASE IN BOTHY GOVERNMENT AND " LARGER AUTNORITY" ./ 26 </p>
<p>26.<br />
BORROWINGS. IN BRIEF. OUR PROPOSAL FOR THE-BORROWING<br />
PROGRAMS FOR STATE WORKS AND THE " LARGER" SEMI.-GOVERNMENTAL<br />
BORROWING PROGRAMS IS THAT THE " BASIC" PROGRAMS BE INCREASED<br />
IN 1974-75 BY 10 PER CENT. IN THE CASE OF THE BORROWING<br />
PROGRAMS FOR STATE WORKS, THIS WOULD BE BEFORE TAKING<br />
ACCOUNT OF THE OFFSETS FOR TERTIARY EDUCATION. IN<br />
ADDITION, WE ARE PREPARED TO SUPPORT SPECIAL TEMPORARY<br />
ALLOCATIONS FOR QUEENSLAND, IN 130TH THE GOVERNMENTAL<br />
AND SEMI-GO'TEP. NENT AREAS, FOR FLOOD RESTORATION WORK,<br />
AND ALSO CERTAIN ADDITIONS TO THE " LARGER" AUTHORITIES<br />
PROGRAMS FOR NEW SOUTH WALES AND WESTERN AUSTRALIA A<br />
PERMANENT ADDITION FOR NEW SOUTH WALES AND A SPECIAL<br />
TEMPORARY ADDITION FOR WESTERN AUSTRALIA.<br />
IN FIGURE TERMS, THIS MEANS THAT WE WILL<br />
SUPPORT, SUBJECT TO THE USUAL CONDITIONS, A<br />
STATE GOVERNMENT PROGRAM OF ' 935 MILLION. THIS CONSISTS<br />
OF A " BASIC" PROGRAM OF i, 925 MILLION, WHICH IS AN<br />
INCREASE OF 10 PER CENT BEFORE TAKING ACCOUNT OF THE<br />
OFFSETS FOR TERTIARY EDUCATION, PLUS A SPECIAL TEMPORARY<br />
ALLOCATION FOR QUEENSLAND OF APPROXIMATELY $ 10 MILLION<br />
FOR FLOOD RESTORATION WORK.<br />
THE " LARGER" AUTHORITIES PROGRAM OF $ 636 MILLION<br />
WHICH WE PROPOSE CONSISTS OF A " BASIC" PROGRAM OF<br />
$ 610.5 MILLION AN INCREASE OF 10 PER CENT PLUS A<br />
PERMANENT ADDITION OF $ 10 MILLION FOR NEW SOUTH WALES AND<br />
SPECIAL TEMPORARY ADDITIONS OF $ 9.6 MILLION FOR QUEENSLAND / 27 </p>
<p>27.<br />
AND $ 6 MILLION FOR WESTERN AUSTRALIA<br />
IN ADDITION sTATES HAVE SUBMITTED<br />
AN ESTIMATED " SMALLER" AUTHORITIES BORROWING REQUIREMENT<br />
OF $ 162 MILLION, COMPARED WITH ESTIMATED ACTUAL RAISINGS<br />
THIS YEAR OF ' 0143 MILLION; IN LINE WITH PAST PRACTICE,<br />
NO OVERALL LIMIT lS PROPOSED FOR THESE BORROWINGS.<br />
DETAILS WILL BE CONVEYED IN THE LOAN COUNCIL<br />
MEETINGS. WHAT I HAVE SAID ABOUT ALL THESE PROGRAMS,<br />
WHETHER OURS OR THE STATES, HAS BEEN AGAINST THE SETTING<br />
THAT I MENTIONED EARLY IN MY STATEMENT THAT GOVERNMENT<br />
SPENDING MUST PLAY ITS PART IN THE POLICY OF RESTRAINT.<br />
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THIS WILL BE ACKNOWLEDGED BY THE<br />
PREMIERS AS IT IS BY US.<br />
HAVING SAID THAT, I WANT TO TURN FINALLY TO<br />
WHAT I SAID IN CONCLUDING MY OPENING ADDRESS TO THE<br />
PREMIERS' CONFERENCE LAST YEAR.<br />
I EXPRESSED THE HOPE THEN " THAT THIS WILL BE<br />
-BOTH THE LAST OF THE OLD-STYLE PREMIERS' CONFERENCE AND<br />
THE FIRST OF A NEW TYPE".<br />
I SAID THEN, AND STILL BELIEVE, THAT OUR EXISTING<br />
STRUCTURES ARE INADEQUATE FOR " TRULY CONSTRUCTIVE, TRULY<br />
CO-OPERATIVE FEDERALISM".<br />
DURING THE PAST 12 MONTHS WE HAVE-WRITTEN TO EACH<br />
OTHER IN GREATER DEPTH AND BREADTH THAN, I BELIEVE IT WOULD<br />
./ 28 </p>
<p>28.<br />
BE TRUE TO SAY, PRIME MINISTERS AND PREMIERS HAVE DONE AT<br />
ANY TIME SINCE FEDERATION. OUR OFFICERS HAVE MET ON<br />
MANY OCCASIONS AND SO ALSO HAVE OUR MITNISTERIAL COLLEAGUES.<br />
THERE ARE MANY AREAS WHERE WE HAVE FOUND<br />
DlFFERENCES, BUT THERE ARE MANY MORE IN WHICH WE HAVE<br />
QUICKLY BEEN ABLE TO REACH AGREEMENT. AND I PAY TRIBUTE<br />
TO ALL OF YOU FOR WHAT YOU HAVE DONE IN HELPING US IN<br />
THE NEW OUTREACHES OF GOVERNMENT TO SERVE THE PEOPLE<br />
THROUGH COMMITTEES AND COMMISSIONS OF INQUIRY ANI THE<br />
LIKE. I LOOK TO CONTINUING CLOSE CONTACT AND<br />
CO-OPERATION BETWEEN US. SUCH CONTACT AND CO-OPERATION<br />
EXTENDSACROSS THE FIELDS OF HEALTH, EDUCATION, HOUSING,<br />
TRANSPORT, LAND, THE ENVIRONMENT AND URBAN IMPROVEMENT<br />
AS WELL AS THE IMPORTANT AREAS OF MINING AND OF ABORIGINAL<br />
DEVELOPMENT. IF WE ARE TO MAKE PROGRESS TOWARDS A COW-ION<br />
UNDERSTANDING AND ATTITUDES TOWARDS NATIONAL PRIORITIES,<br />
IT WILL BE NECESSARY FOR US TO MAINTAIN REGULAR CONTACT.<br />
I LOOK TO CONSULTATION EITHER AMONG OURSELVES OR, WITH<br />
OUR AGREEMENT, AMONG THOSE OF OUR COLLEAGUES WHO ARE<br />
CARRYING THE MAIN RESPONSIBILITY, OR AT OFFICER LEVEL.<br />
ONE PARTICULAR AREA I HAVE IN MIND IS THE<br />
WELFARE AND ENVIRONMENT OF THOSE WHO LIVE IN OUR CITIES,<br />
AND PARTICULARLY OUR GREAT CAPITALS. WE WILL BE PROPOSING<br />
THAT MINISTERS AND OFFICIALS DEVOTE THEIR ENERGIES DURING<br />
THE REST OF THIS YEAR TO A RENEWED CO-OPERATIVE ATTEMPT<br />
/ 29 </p>
<p>29.<br />
AT CLARIFYING ISSUES ON WHICH CO-OPERATIVE ACTION IS<br />
ESSENTIAL AND ADVISING APPROPRIATE PROGRAMS.<br />
LET US DEMONSTRATE TO THE PEOPLE WHOM WE ALL<br />
SERVE THAT WE CAN TRANSCEND THE DIFFERENCES WHICH<br />
SEPARATE US AND SEEK TOGETHER A COMMON BASIS FOR ACTION<br />
ON ISSUES THAT AFFECT EVERY CITIZEN. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
