<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8757</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP RELEASE OF NATIONAL ESD NAND GREEN HOUSE STRATEGIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008757.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 189<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P 3 KEATING MP<br />
RELEASE OF NATIONAL ESD AND GREENHOUSE STRATEGIES<br />
The Council of Australian Government has endorsed the National Strategy for<br />
Ecologically Sustainable Development ( ESD) and the National Greenhouse Response<br />
Strategy. The Council also agreed to the release of the Compendium of ESD<br />
Recommendations as a record of how the Strategies agreed by Heads of Government,<br />
together with examples of present policies and programs, relate to each of the<br />
recommendations arising from the ESD process.<br />
Endorsement of the Strategies represented an important step forward and demonstrated<br />
that Australia was serious about seeking to achieve ecologically sustainable development.<br />
This was not, however, the end of the process. The Commonwealth would continue to<br />
discuss a range of ESD issues with the States and Terrtories and also with key interest<br />
groups. The Government would also take further initiatives within the Commonwealth's<br />
own areas of jurisdiction.<br />
Thec achievement of a broad national commitment to ESD was a tribute to the<br />
contributions that many individuals and organisations had made to the ESD process.<br />
Overall, governments have accepted more than 80% of the original recommendations in<br />
some form. Less than 4% had not been accepted, with the balance still under<br />
consideration. The National Strategy for ESD will play a crucial role in setting the scene for the broad<br />
changes in direction and approach by governments. It constitutes a substantial agenda for<br />
change and reform in the longer term. Such changes will present new opportunities in the<br />
future, in areas as diverse as ecotourism, agriculture and cleaner manufacturing processes.<br />
Major features of the ESD Strategy include initiatives to:<br />
endorse the ESD goal, objectives and principles and review of relevant agencies to<br />
incorporate these in charters and corporate plans;<br />
4702 </p>
<p>enhance the role of integrated and total catchment management in policies and<br />
programs; adopt a fisheries ecosystem management approach;<br />
promote adoption of best practice envirornental management by industry and<br />
whole-life-cycle methodologies by industry, and prepare a strategy for the<br />
environmental management industry;<br />
ensure mine sites are rehabilitated to sound environmental and safety standards;<br />
incorporate ESD principles in tourism strategies;<br />
establish criteria for access and use of protected areas consistent with ESD<br />
principles and objectives;<br />
extend the National Residues Survey to cover wildlife and the wider environment;<br />
finalise a national biological diversity strategy for consideration by Heads of<br />
Government; develop a national approach to the protection of rare, vulnerable and endangered<br />
species; assess the current rate of native vegetation clearing on a national basis;<br />
review national and sector balance sheets in Australian National Accounts;<br />
improve the coverage and effectiveness of the Environent Impact Assessment<br />
process; consider the need for a national approach to coastal issues following the Resource<br />
Assessment Commission's coastal zone inquiry;<br />
improve management of water allocations and determine the most appropriate mix<br />
of water resource management mechanisms;<br />
ensure waste disposal costs reflect externalities;<br />
establish an intergovernmental consultative forum for RD&amp; D; and<br />
establish an intergovernmental Ministerial-level Roundtable and establish ad hoc<br />
advisory bodies 4703 </p>
<p>The Council also endorsed the National Greenhouse Response Strategy ( NGRS) and<br />
committed governments to a range of actions aimed at limiting greenhouses gas emissions<br />
and reducing the level of uncertainty which is associated both with climate change<br />
predictions and the actions needed to tackle the problem. Greater effort will also be given<br />
to enhancing our capacity to adapt to climate change and involving interested community<br />
sectors in the future development of greenhouse responses.<br />
The first phase responses are mainly in the areas of energy production, distribution and<br />
use. This reflects the level of understanding of greenhouse gas emission mechanisms in<br />
these areas, and the reasonable scope for taking no-regrets actions. The measures<br />
included are consistent with the broader micro-economic reforms already underway in the<br />
energy sector.<br />
The NGRS; is broadly consistent with existing policies and programs, although it gives<br />
greater impetus to energy efficiency reforms both in the energy production and use<br />
sectors. Major features of the Greenhouse Strategy are initiatives to:<br />
promote more transparent and accessible energy markets<br />
develop and apply an integrated least cost approach to energy planig<br />
improve linkages between energy costs ( including externalities) and prices<br />
diversifying energy sources<br />
improve household, industrial and commercial energy efficiency<br />
improve efficiency of motor vehicles<br />
establish a National Greenhouse Advisory Panel ( NGAP)<br />
develop a National Greenhouse Gas Inventory<br />
Community involvement will remain central to the future development of both the ESD<br />
and Greenhouse Scrategies. As part of the monitoring and review process, the ESD<br />
Steering Committee and the National Greenhouse Steering Committee will report to<br />
Heads of Government within twelve months, and biennially thereafter, on the<br />
implementation of the Strategies seeking input and comment from key business and<br />
community groups.<br />
In addition to the intergovernmental Ministerial-level ESD consultative roundtable, to be<br />
held biennially as established under the Strategy, the Commonwealth will continue to<br />
hold more frequent ESD Roundtable meetings to provide opportunities for dialogue with<br />
community representatives at the peak national level.<br />
8 DECEMBER 1992 CANBERRA<br />
4704<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
