<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24458</transcript-id>
    <title>New medical school for Curtin University</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth Government will support Curtin University’s proposal to establish a new medical school that will help address the health workforce needs of Western Australia.</p>
<p>Curtin University will offer a new five-year undergraduate, direct-entry medical programme that will select and train students to work in areas of need around Western Australia.</p>
<p>Western Australia has fewer doctors per head of population than the rest of Australia.</p>
<p>This medical school will contribute to supporting the health needs of the Western Australian community.</p>
<p>In particular, rural and remote locations will be serviced by well qualified, highly-trained health professionals.</p>
<p>In partnership, the Western Australian Government and the University will be providing all capital funding for the establishment of the new medical school.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth will contribute through the funding of new medical Commonwealth Supported Places (CSPs) for the school from 2019-20.</p>
<p>When the school reaches full capacity in 2022, it will provide 110 new places per year.</p>
<p>The Western Australian Government will ensure that these students receive the further training they require once they have completed their medical school studies.</p>
<p>It will provide new clinical training and supervision, internships and specialist training places for all students of the new school.</p>
<p>This will be in addition to current training and internships provided to students of other medical schools in Western Australia.</p>
<p>17 May 2015 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
