<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7664</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH BARBARA WALTERS, ABC GOOD MORNING AMERICA, WASHINGTON DC, 27 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007664.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1KX<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH BARBARA WALTERS ABC GOOD MORNING;<br />
AMERICA, WASHINGTON DC, 27 JUNE 1989.<br />
Walters: Prime Minister Bob Hawke of Australia is in the United<br />
States for an off icial visit. Later today he meets with President<br />
George Bush and Secretary of State James Baker. It's the first<br />
Bush/ Hawke summit since Mr Bush was elected President and itts<br />
pretty certain that trade between the two countries will top the<br />
discussions. Right now the Prime Minister joins us from<br />
Washington. Walters: Good Morning Mr Prime Minister. It's a sad fact that<br />
most American's probably would not know unprompted, the name of<br />
the Prime Minister of Australia. Do most Australians know the<br />
name of the President of the United States?<br />
PMi They sure do.<br />
Walters: We are remiss. Most of what we know about Australia<br />
probably comes from Crocodile Dundee movies or commercials. Can<br />
you tell us, what should we know most about your wonderful<br />
country? PM: I think you should know there's a country of 17 million down<br />
there in the South Pacific and probably the strongest ally that<br />
the United States has. We fought together in wars side by side<br />
and that in peace time we've formed an alliance in defence an the<br />
9 vraelluaetsi onthsahti p wwea ss haarmeo. n gsTth e thper evmioosuts iPmproerstiadnetn t ansda idt hatth'ast tah ivsiew<br />
that this President shares. So I quess those are the Important<br />
sorts of things as well as the fact that we're able to knock you<br />
over pretty regularly at tennis and anything else you like to<br />
take us on at like sailing.<br />
Walters: Oh I see well as I was not going to bring it up Mr Prime<br />
Minister, but we saw youz play golf with President Bush, you were<br />
not great... ( laughter).<br />
PMi You didn't see me play golf. You saw a most unfair<br />
representation. My first shot after weeks on an aeroplane and<br />
sitting in rooms. Why didn't you show the second shot?<br />
Walters: Because you shot into the fairway but it was the wrong<br />
one. ( laughter) Well maybe we'll show the second one. on your<br />
agenda today I don't think you're going to be discussing golf Mr<br />
President. What is it? What are the biggest trade concerns.<br />
RN: well, we're a bit worried that the program you have here,<br />
your export enhancement program to protect your farmers is<br />
knocking the bojesus out of your own people here. It's coating </p>
<p>2<br />
( PM Cont) about $ 74 Billion a year, to your taxpayers and<br />
consumers. The 90 odd per cant are being taken for a ride in<br />
favour of a very small percentage and we're the ones that to some<br />
extent are getting hurt. But we're not going to allow that<br />
particular argument that we have to upset the firm understandings<br />
and points of agreement we have on just about every other issue.<br />
But that's a silly thing that's happening to American taxpayers<br />
and consumers. You are paying as I say the best part of a $ 100<br />
billion which increases your costs and your prices. That's<br />
stupid. We think it's stupid. The Europeans are doing the same.<br />
You're trying to beat them but in the process you're hurting<br />
yourself and the rest of the world.<br />
Walterst Do you think you're going to get that changed?<br />
PM: No. I have a great conviction inmow cwrs<br />
Mi die. l III1 01 m onrw<br />
lown in one day.<br />
Walters: Mr Prime Minister you know how concerned we have been<br />
about what's been going on in China and I'm sure you have as<br />
well. And you have trade with China. What is your attitude<br />
towards the Chinese? How far are you going in condemnation or<br />
restrictions? PM I've had the opportunity already on Sunday of having long<br />
talks with George Bush about this. Our positions are I would say<br />
identical. What we are going to do Barbara is two things and it's<br />
very difficult to walk the line between. Firstly we have to<br />
unequivocally condemn the barbarism, brutality, the<br />
unacceptability of what they've done in Tianaman Square on the<br />
fourth, and persecution and execution of people since then.<br />
There's no question about that. Secondly in the interests of the<br />
people of China themselves as well as the region and of the<br />
world. We mustn't close off the relationship with China and turn<br />
them in on themselves, because that would be bad for the Chinese<br />
people. it will stifle the moves that will inevitably go on<br />
within that great country for further not only economic reform<br />
but for further political reform. If we close ourselves off. if<br />
we don't cooperate in an acceptable way then we will be going<br />
against the interests of the very people we want to help. Now<br />
that's a difficult line which political leaders have to walk. But<br />
to attempt to walk it we must.<br />
Walters: I think it is very similar to the point of view of our<br />
President. PM: I think we are at one.<br />
Walters: Sir, you do have another problem, and that is that eight<br />
years from now Hong Kong goes back to the Chinese and are you<br />
concerned that you may have so many refugees from Hong Kong. Can<br />
you handle them, will you take them all. </p>
<p>3<br />
PM: I like the assumption in your question that we've got to<br />
handle them.<br />
Walters; Well, I've heard that a great-many of them have already<br />
buying homes in Australia and are thinking of going there.<br />
PM4: Well sure, under our immnigration program Barbara we have a<br />
business migration element in which we welcome people from there<br />
and other areas. It's going to be, if you take the most<br />
pessimistic scenario, and there isn't a decant relationship<br />
between China and Hong Kong and the rest of the world at that<br />
time, then all the world and particularly Britain that has the<br />
relationship with Hong Kong has to be prepared to do something<br />
about accepting those people who want to leave.<br />
Walters: We thank you for being with us. We hope that Americans<br />
will remember the name. I'm sure they all liked seeing you today,<br />
Prime Minister Bob Hawke of Australia. Thank you.<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
