<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6570</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/12/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006570.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ACTING PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 18 DECEMBER 1984<br />
The Acting Prime Minister, Mr Lionel Bowen, announced today<br />
new arrangements to provide a single source of funding for<br />
the Commonwealth's Aboriginal Health Programs.<br />
In the past, both the Department of Aboriginal Affairs and<br />
the Department of Health had provided funds for communitybased<br />
Aboriginal Medical Services ( AMSs). This dual<br />
funding arrangement was introduced in 1979 by the previous<br />
Government and had created inequities between AMSs. It had<br />
also proved to be administratively cumbersome for the<br />
Services. Proposals to introduce " single-source funding"<br />
have been under discussion by the Ministers and the<br />
National Aboriginal and Islander Health Organisation<br />
( NAIHO) in the past year.<br />
The new arrangement provides for all funds to be channelled<br />
through the Department of Aboriginal Affairs. This means<br />
that, except for claims against Medicare, all AMSs will now<br />
be financially accountable only to the Department of<br />
Aboriginal Affairs. The Department of Health will retain a<br />
policy advising role in Aboriginal health matters.<br />
As a result of a Budget decision, some $ 1.5m will now<br />
become available to assist in this rationalisation and to<br />
enable the establishment of up to 10 new AMSs throughout<br />
Australia. This is in addition to a total of $ 11.9m<br />
already provided for existing AMSs. Funds will also be<br />
provided for the next stage in the national program for the<br />
eradication of trachoma. </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Minister for Aboriginal Affairs will consult with NAIHO<br />
on the allocation of the new funds to AMSs, and on the<br />
allocation of funds for the eye health program. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
