<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6776</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR THE OPENING OF THE NEW WALTER AND ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH, MELBOURNE, 8 NOVEMBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006776.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY '-EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
FOR THE OPENING OF THE NEW WALTER AND ELIZA HALL<br />
INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH<br />
MELBOURNE 8 NOVEMBER 1985<br />
SIR ANDREW, MR PREMIER, MINISTERS, PROFESSOR NOSSAL,<br />
DISTINGUISHED GUESTS, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, I AM GREATLY<br />
HONOURED TO BE HERE TODAY ON THIS MOST SIGNIFICANT OCCASION.<br />
IT IS NOT OFTEN THAT A PRIME MINISTER CAN BE ASSOCIATED WITH<br />
AN EVENT INVOLVING AN AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTION ABOUT WHICH<br />
THERE CAN BE NO DOUBT AS TO ITS UNRIVALLED WORLD REPUTATION.<br />
THE FACT THAT WE HAVE HERE TODAY SUCH AN IMPRESSIVE<br />
CONTINGENT OF INTERNATIONAL SCIENTISTS TO HELP CELEBRATE<br />
THIS MILESTONE IN THE HISTORY OF THE WALTER AND ELIZA HALL<br />
INSTITUTE SHOWS THAT I AM NOT ALONE IN. MY VERY HIGH REGARD<br />
FOR THE INSTITUTE AND ITS RENOWNED WORK.<br />
I THINK IT IS APPROPRIATE IF, AT THE BEGINNING OF MY<br />
ADDRESS, I DEVOTE SOME TIME TO TRACING THE BACKGROUND AND<br />
EARLY DEVELOPMENT OF THIS GREAT AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTION. FOR<br />
IT IS AN INTERESTING STORY THAT INVOLVES A NUMBER OF PEOPLE<br />
WITH DIFFERENT BACKGROUNDS AND EXPERIENCES; PUBLIC SPIRITED<br />
PEOPLE, ALL OF THEM, WITH VISIONS OF WHAT WAS NEEDED IN THIS<br />
COUNTRY AND HOW AUSTRALIANS COULD GO ABOUT MAKING THESE<br />
VISIONS A REALITY.<br />
AUSTRALIA WAS INDEED FORTUNATE THAT, SO SOON AFTER ITS BIRTH<br />
AS A COMMONWEALTH, THERE HAD DEVELOPED A DESIRE TO FOUND A<br />
NATIONAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE TO ADVANCE THE HEALTH OF<br />
AUSTRALIANS. MUCH OF THE CREDIT IS DUE TO THE PROFESSOR OF PATHOLOGY AND<br />
DEAN OF THE MEDICAL SCHOOL AT THE UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE,<br />
SIR HARRY BROOKES ALLEN. HE SAW THE NEED FOR CLINICAL<br />
LABORATORIES FOR ROUTINE DIAGNOSTIC WORK AND FOR RESEARCH AT<br />
THE MELBOURNE HOSPITAL NOW THE ROYAL MELBOURNE.<br />
BY A HAPPY SET OF CIRCUMSTANCES, THERE ARRIVED ON THE SCENE<br />
OTHERS WHO M4ADE THIS DREAM A REALITY. </p>
<p>THE STORY OF WALTER HALL, OF COURSE, IS PART OF THE ROMANCE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA'S DEVELOPMENT. WALTER HALL ARRIVED IN<br />
AUSTRALIA IN 1852 AS A PENNILESS MIGRANT. BY THE TIME OF<br />
HIS DEATH IN 1911 HE HAD MADE A FORTUNE INITIALLY FROM<br />
INVOLVEMENT WITH COBB AND CO. COACHES AND LATER FROM<br />
INTERESTS IN THE MOUNT MORGAN MINING VENTURE IN QUEENSLAND.<br />
AFTER HIS DEATH HIS WIDOW, ELIZA, MAINTAINED A PRACTICAL<br />
INTEREST IN SOCIAL WELFARE, THE RELIEF OF POVERTY AND THE<br />
ADVANCEMENT OF EDUCATION. AS THE HALLS HAD NO CHILDREN, MRS<br />
HALL WAS RECEPTIVE TO THE IDEA OF BEQUEATHING A SUBSTANTIAL<br />
SUM TO SET UP A CHARITABLE TRUST FUND.<br />
THROUGH THE WORK OF SIR HARRY ALLEN AND A PROMINENT<br />
MELBOURNE BUSINESSMAN, RICHARD GARDNER CASEY ( WHOSE SON WAS<br />
TO BECOME LORD CASEY AND GOVERNOR-GENERAL OF AUSTRALIA) THE<br />
HALL TRUSTEES AGREED THAT PART OF THE INCOME FROM THE<br />
HALL BEQUEST OF ONE MILLION POUNDS, WHICH INITIATED THE<br />
WALTER AND ELIZA HALL TRUST FUND, SHOULD BE USED TO<br />
ESTABLISH THE WALTER AND ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE.<br />
THE INSTITUTE WAS ESTABLISHED IN MELBOURNE IN 1915. WORLD<br />
WAR I INTERVENED, HOWEVER, AND AUSTRALIA'S FIRST MEDICAL<br />
RESEARCH UNIT, ALTHOUGH OFFICIALLY ' FOUNDED' FIVE YEARS<br />
EARLIER, DID NOT GET DOWN TO SERIOUS WORK UNTIL 1920.<br />
THE EARLY YEARS OF THE INSTITUTE WERE NOTABLE FOR THE WORK<br />
OF DR CHARLES KELLAWAY, THE DIRECTOR FROM 1923, WHO<br />
ATTRACTED INTERNATIONAL ATTENTION FOR HIS RESEARCH INTO<br />
VENOMOUS SNAKES AND ANTI-VENENES. KELLAWAY'S EFFORTS LED TO<br />
FINANCIAL SUPPORT FROM THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT AND FROM<br />
THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION.<br />
THIS INTERESTING BEGINNING LAID THE FOUNDATIONS FOR THE<br />
FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF THE WALTER AND ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE.<br />
THE NEXT STAGE WILL ALWAYS BE ASSOCIATED WITH THE NAME OF<br />
SIR MACFARLANE BURNET WHO WILL FOREVER BY HIGH ON THE HONOUR<br />
ROLL OF AUSTRALIAN MEDICAL RESEARCH. I KNOW THAT MANY OF<br />
YOU WILL SHARE MY SADNESS THAT HIS RECENT DEATH MEANT THAT<br />
HE COULD NOT BE WITH US TODAY.<br />
UNTIL HIS RETIREMENT IN 1965, SIR MACFARLANE SERVED FOR MORE<br />
THAN 20 YEARS AS DIRECTOR OF THIS INSTITUTE. HE WAS<br />
INSTRUMENTAL IN DEVELOPING RESEARCH EMPHASIS IN IMMUNOLOGY;<br />
EXTENDING VIRUS RESEARCH INTO AREAS SUCH AS INFLUENZA,<br />
MURRAY VALLEY ENCEPHALITIS, HERPES AND POLIOMYELITIS. IT<br />
WAS FOR HIS WORK IN IMMUNOLOGY THAT SIR MACFARLANE RECEIVED<br />
THE NOBEL PRIZE IN 1960.<br />
SIR MACFARLANE BURNET'S LONG PERIOD OF SERVICE WAS FOLLOWED<br />
BY THAT OF SIR GUSTAV NOSSAL, WHO NOW HAS COMPLETED HIS<br />
SECOND DECADE IN OFFICE. SIR GUSTAV HAS MAINTAINED THE<br />
INSTITUTE'S COMMITMENT TO BASIC AND CLINICAL IMMUNOLOGY AND<br />
HAS EXPANDED ITS WORK TO TAKE IN A MAJOR EFFORT IN CANCER<br />
RESEARCH; INITIATIVES IN MOLECULAR BIOLOGY AND GENETIC<br />
ENGINEERING; STUDIES IN TROPICAL PARASITIC DISEASES<br />
PARTICULARLY MALARIA; AND TRANSPLANTATION TECHNIQUES FOR USE<br />
IN TREATING DIABETES. </p>
<p>WITH A STAFF OF MORE THAN 200 PEOPLE AND A BUDGET EXCEEDING<br />
$ 7 MILLION, THlE WALTER AND ELIZA HAL. L INSTITUTE TRULY HAS<br />
ESTABLISHED ITSELF AS ONE OF A HANDFUL OF GREAT INSTITUTIONS<br />
OF MEDICAL RESEARCH IN THE WORLD.<br />
THE INTERNATIONAL STANDING OF THIS INSTITUTE IS EXEMPLIFIED<br />
BY ITS OUTPUT OF PROFESSIONALS WHO HAVE ACHIEVED<br />
INTERNATIONAL DISTINCTION. IN ADDITION, THE RESIDENT TEAM<br />
OF HIGH CALIBRE SENIOR PERSONNEL HAS ATTRACTED VISITING<br />
RESEARCH FELLOWS AND ADVANCED TRAINEES TO THE WALTER AND<br />
ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE, INCLUDING, IN RECENT YEARS, FROM THE<br />
PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA AND SOUTH EAST ASIAN NATIONS.<br />
THE INSTITUTE IS DEEPLY COMMITTED TO VARIOUS INTERNATIONAL<br />
COLLABORATIVE PROGRAMS IN BASIC RESEARCH AND IN APPLIED<br />
SCIENCE. SUCH COMMITMENT HAS LED TO BOTH INTERNATIONAL<br />
RECOGNITION AND TO FINANCIAL SUPPORT.<br />
IN THIS REGARD, I MUST MAKE SPECIAL ACKNOWLEDGEMENT OF THE<br />
JOHN D. AND CATHERINE T. MACARTHUR FOUNDATION OF CHICAGO<br />
WHICH ENDOWED THE INSTITUTE WITH A MAGNIFICANT GRANT OF $ 2<br />
MILLION RESULTING IN THE DEDICATION, EARLIER TODAY, OF THE<br />
MACARTHUR LABORATORY. I SHOULD PAY TRIBUTE, AS WELL, TO THE<br />
ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION OF NEW YORK, THE NATIONAL INSTITUTE<br />
OF HEALTH OF THE UNITED STATES, AND THE WORLD HEALTH<br />
ORGANISATION AS PARTICULARLY FAITHFUL LONG-TERM SUPPORTERS.<br />
TURNING NOW TO THE AUSTRALIAN SCENE, THE WALTER AND ELIZA<br />
HALL INSTITUTE SHOULD INDEED BE PROUD OF ITS STATUS AS A<br />
PIONEER OF MEDICAL RESEARCH IN THIS COUNTRY. MEDICAL<br />
RESEARCH, BECAUSE OF THE OBVIOUS AND UNDOUBTED BENEFITS IT<br />
BRINGS TO INDIVIDUALS, FAMILIES, AND COMMUNITIES, IS<br />
PERCEIVED AS A VERY WORTHWHILE ACTIVITY AND ONE DESERVING OF<br />
STRONG AND CONSISTENT SUPPORT.<br />
THERE HAVE BEEN TIMES, HOWEVER, WHEN AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS,<br />
FOR WHATEVER FINANCIAL OR PHILOSOPHICAL REASONS, HAVE NOT<br />
GIVEN MEDICAL RESEARCH IN FACT THE ARTS AND SCIENCES IN<br />
ALL THEIR EXPRESSIONS WHAT MANY WOULD CONSIDER TO BE THEIR<br />
PROPER ENTITLEMENT FROM THE COMMONWEALTH BUDGET.<br />
I BELIEVE MY GOVERNMENT CANNOT BE CHARGED WITH SUCH A SIN OF<br />
OMISSION. IN 1983, WHEN THIS GOVERNMENT TOOK OFFICE, THE ALLOCATION TO<br />
THE NATIONAL HEALTH AND MEDICAL RESEARCH COUNCIL STOOD AT<br />
JUST BELOW $ 30 MILLION. IN SUCCESSIVE BUDGETS WE HAVE<br />
INCREASED THIS TOTAL BY 72% TO JUST OVER $ 50 MILLION IN THE<br />
1985/ 86 BUDGET.<br />
TRULY A REMARKABLE DEMONSTRATION OF OUR GENUINE COMMITMENT<br />
TO MEDICAL RESEARCH AT A TIME OF ACUTE BUDGETARY PRESSURE ON<br />
THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
FROM THESE FUNDS, OF COURSE, COME THE COMMONWEALTH GRA' 4TS<br />
WHICH, IN TOTAL, AMOUNT TO 50% OF THE RECURRENT FUNDS<br />
REQUIRED BY THE INSTITUTE FOR ITS FUNCTIONING. </p>
<p>4<br />
ON THAT NOTE IT IS APPROPRIATE FOR ME TO ANNOUNCE THAT, FOR<br />
1986, THE GOVERNMENT, ON THE ADVICE OF THE NATIONAL HEALTH<br />
AND MEDICAL RESEARCH COUNCIL, HAS INCREASED THE ALLOCATION<br />
TO THE HALL INSTITUTE TO $ 5,040,498. THIS TOTAL INCLUDES A<br />
SPECIAL GRANT, FOR 1986 ONLY, OF $ 150,000 FOR THE PURCHASE<br />
OF EQUIPMENT.<br />
WHILE THE GOVERNMENT IS GRATIFIED AT THE WAY IT HAS BEEN<br />
ABLE TO INCREASE THE FUNDS AVAILABLE FOR MEDICAL RESEARCH IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, IT KNOWS THAT ALL OF YOU HERE TODAY WOULD VOTE IN<br />
FAVOUR OF MORE FINANCIAL RESOURCES BEING PROVIDED FOR THIS<br />
IMPORTANT PURPOSE: AND, IN PARTICULAR, FOR THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
TO CONTRIBUTE EVEN MORE FUNDS.<br />
ONE FEATURE OF SUPPORT FOR MEDICAL RESEARCH IN AUSTRALIA<br />
PERHAPS AN UNFORTUNATE FEATURE IS THAT IT IS FAR MORE<br />
RELIANT ON GOVERNMENT FUNDING THAN IS RESEARCH IN THOSE<br />
COUNTRIES WITH WHICH WE ARE MORE CLOSELY RELATED AND<br />
EQUATED. AND I SAY THIS WHILE RECOGNISING THAT MANY<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMPANIES, INDIVIDUALS AND FOUNDATIONS HAVE<br />
ASSISTED GENEROUSLY THE CAUSE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH.<br />
NEVERTHELESS, THIS IS CLEARLY ONE ASPECT WHICH REQUIRES<br />
CAREFUL CONSIDERATION BY ALL ASSOCIATED WITH MEDICAL<br />
RESEARCH IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
HOWEVER, AS WELL AS INCREASING FUNDING FOR MEDICAL RESEARCH,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN IMPORTANT INITIATIVES WHICH, BACKED<br />
BY THE EFFECTIVE LOBBY OF THE MEDICAL RESEARCH COMMUNITY,<br />
SHOULD GIVE THE PRIVATE SECTOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO ASSUME A<br />
LARGER ROLE AS A PARTNER IN RESEARCH FUNDING.<br />
AS FROM THE FIRST OF JULY THIS YEAR, COMPANIES SPENDING<br />
MONEY ON RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT IN AUSTRALIA ARE ELIGIBLE<br />
FOR A 150% TAX DEDUCTION. INDIVIDUAL DEDUCTIONS ARE<br />
AVAILABLE UNDER THE EXISTING TAXATION ACT FOR GIFTS TO<br />
PUBLIC AUTHORITIES ENGAGED IN RESEARCH. THE NATIONAL<br />
BIOTECHNOLOGY PROGRAMME-RESEARCH GRANTS SCHEME GIVES<br />
PREFERENCE TO RESEARCH PROPOSALS WHICH INVOLVE DIRECT<br />
COLLABORATION WITH AUSTRALIAN-BASED INDUSTRY.<br />
THESE MEASURES ARE DESIGNED TO GIVE A FILLIP TO<br />
NON-GOVERNMENT SUPPORT OF MEDICAL RESEARCH AS A SIGNIFICANT<br />
COMPONENT OF SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH IN AUSTRALIA, AND, I HOPE,<br />
SOME NEW TARGETS AS YOU CAMPAIGN FOR INCREASED FUNDING OF<br />
MEDICAL RESEARCH.<br />
I UNDERSTAND, FOR INSTANCE, THAT THE BANKING SECTOR SUPPORTS<br />
RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT IN CANADA AND THE UNITED STATES<br />
WITH RISK CAPITAL. I WOULD EXHORT THE RESEARCH COMMUNITY IN<br />
GENERAL TO DIRECT THEIR EFFORTS TOWARDS CONVINCING NATIONAL<br />
BANKS AS WELL AS THOSE INTERNATIONAL, BANKS WHICH HAVE<br />
ESTABLISHED THEMSELVES IN AUSTRALIA, AS A RESULT OF MY<br />
GOVERNMENT'S DE-REGULATION OF THE BANKING SYSTEM TO<br />
CONSIDER THE BENEFITS OF INVESTING IN AUSTRALIAN RESEARCH. </p>
<p>THAT, OF COURSE, IS A MATTER FOR THE FUTURE. AND THE FUTURE<br />
IS WHAT WE ARE ABOUT TODAY. WHILE JUSTIFIABLY PROUD OF ITS<br />
PAST, AND ITS PRESENT, THE WALTER AND ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE<br />
OF MEDICAL RESEARCH IS, LIKE THE GOVERNMENT, EQUALLY<br />
CONCERNED FOR THE FUTURE. THIS MAGNIFICANT NEW BUILDING<br />
WILL PHYSICALLY EQUIP THE INSTITUTE TO CHART OUT ITS COURSE<br />
IN THE YEARS AHEAD.<br />
THE OPENING OF THIS NEW BUILDING FOR THE WALTER AND ELIZA<br />
HALL INSTITUTE REFLECTS A CLIMATE OF PROGRESS AND EXPANSION<br />
AND, I AM CONFIDENT, MARKS THE BEGINNING OF A NEW ERA FOR A<br />
RECOGNISED LEADER IN THE INTERNATIONAL FRATERNITY OF MEDICAL<br />
RESEARCH. AFTER YOUR PREMIER, JOHN CAIN, HAS SPOKEN I SHALL HAVE<br />
PLEASURE IN JOINING HIM IN OFFICIALLY DECLARING OPEN<br />
THE NEW WALTER AND ELIZA HALL INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL<br />
RESEARCH. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
