<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10735</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH KERRY O&amp;#146;BRIEN                7.30 REPORT, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Australia's Prime Minister John Howard of course has been</p>
<p>   following the progress of talks in Baghdad closely over the weekend</p>
<p>   and today and he joins me now from Canberra. John Howard, what is</p>
<p>   your immediate reaction? And how closely have you been briefed on</p>
<p>   what has gone on behind the scenes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well my immediate reaction is one of hope. I think that is the</p>
<p>   immediate reaction of all Australians. Nobody wants war, nobody</p>
<p>   wants bloodshed. My next reaction is, that if miraculously we do</p>
<p>   have something that is enduring out of this meeting then it will</p>
<p>   have been as a direct result, I believe in very large measure, of</p>
<p>   the leadership that the Americans have shown in making it plain</p>
<p>   that if the Iraqis were not prepared to comply with the United Nations</p>
<p>   resolutions then they would have paid a very heavy price. And I</p>
<p>   think that ought to be said at the outset.</p>
<p>Now, I haven't seen the text of the agreement and until I</p>
<p>   do, and I understand at this point the Americans haven't either,</p>
<p>   I can't make a judgement. Obviously if unrestricted access</p>
<p>   is to be made available then that is a big breakthrough. I do believe,</p>
<p>   however, that the printed word and the promise of Iraq has to be</p>
<p>   put to the test. And if there is something that is worthwhile persevering</p>
<p>   with then maybe a number of inspections should take place to find</p>
<p>   out whether the Iraqi leadership is as good as its word. And the</p>
<p>   idea of there being any troop withdrawal or any military run down</p>
<p>   until the veracity of the agreement has been tested by an actual</p>
<p>   inspection would, I think, be unacceptable.</p>
<p>But I am not able to make a judgement on behalf of my Government</p>
<p>   and therefore on behalf of the Australian people until I know the</p>
<p>   wording of the document. I am aware that there were discussions</p>
<p>   between the Secretary General and the United States Secretary of</p>
<p>   State and that they were moderately positive. I also know that there</p>
<p>   were discussions with the British Prime Minister with the same outcome.</p>
<p>   Of course, until those two Governments actually see the document</p>
<p>   themselves they are relying on the interpretation of the document</p>
<p>   and the gloss put on it by the Secretary General. Now I am not accusing</p>
<p>   him of any bad faith but we are dealing here, and I speak of Saddam</p>
<p>   Hussein, with somebody who has been fairly indifferent in the past</p>
<p>   about repudiating undertakings.</p>
<p>And whilst along with everybody else in the world I would sigh</p>
<p>   an immense relief if we can be spared military action, having gone</p>
<p>   through what the world has gone through over the past few years</p>
<p>   with this man it will take more than a piece of paper to persuade</p>
<p>   me that a genuine agreement has been reached and there has been</p>
<p>   a change of heart. I want to see the results of an inspection. I</p>
<p>   will want to see an independent adjudication before I would feel</p>
<p>   that we had a proper deal.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>I can understand your caveats, Prime Minister, but would you agree</p>
<p>   that given that the UN Secretary General is as seasoned a diplomat</p>
<p>   as he is with the weight of office that he has with him, and given</p>
<p>   that he has been dealing at such a high level with the Americans</p>
<p>   and the British, that he would be unlikely to sign off on a deal</p>
<p>   like this unless he was confident that it did meet the conditions</p>
<p>   that have been pre-set?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>One would not think so but stranger things have happened. But I</p>
<p>   would just make the additional point, Kerry, that it may well be</p>
<p>   that everything in the agreement is acceptable. It maybe that everything</p>
<p>   is acceptable to the Americans and the British and to us and to</p>
<p>   others. But until you actually carry out the inspections which are</p>
<p>   provided for in those agreements, then you are entitled to have</p>
<p>   reservations. So I am not looking around for a reason not to accept</p>
<p>   it, quite the reverse. I mean, everybody wants to avoid bloodshed,</p>
<p>   everybody, every decent man and woman wants to avoid bloodshed.</p>
<p>   But you are dealing here with somebody who has repudiated agreements</p>
<p>   at will in the past, and I just want to be, and I am sure most Australians</p>
<p>   would agree with me, want to be satisfied that the proof of the</p>
<p>   pudding is in the eating.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Do you agree that in all the circumstances it is now highly unlikely,</p>
<p>   even if America wants to take at least days to really examine the</p>
<p>   fine print of this, that the immediate heat is off?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, immediate in the sense of the next 24, 48 hours, but until</p>
<p>   I have actually seen that agreement I don't want to sign off.</p>
<p>   Look I am hopeful, I am immensely hopeful, everybody is entitled</p>
<p>   to be hopeful and I agree that it would be extraordinary if a man</p>
<p>   of this diplomatic experience had gone so far out on a limb as to</p>
<p>   so compromise himself. Yet sometimes in the transmission of one</p>
<p>   mans interpretation to another of a document that the other has</p>
<p>   not seen there can be misunderstandings. And until that document</p>
<p>   is actually sighted and is analysed by the Americans and the British</p>
<p>   and by us, then you can't really sign off on it.</p>
<p>And then there is also the question of what steps are taken to</p>
<p>   put to the test the offer which has apparently been made, or the</p>
<p>   agreement which has been conceded by the Iraqis of inspection. I</p>
<p>   mean that is what it is all about. It has been the objection hitherto</p>
<p>   of the Iraqis to allow in a proper, foolproof inspection, particularly</p>
<p>   of the Presidential sites, that has caused the trouble.</p>
<p>Now, I have got to be satisfied and I am sure the American and</p>
<p>   British leadership will want to be satisfied that not only has there</p>
<p>   been an expression of willingness to allow that, but it does, in</p>
<p>   fact, take place so that we can be satisfied it is a genuine agreement.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>And just on your concern that the military presence should remain</p>
<p>   in the Gulf, how long would you be prepared to support an allied</p>
<p>   presence in the Gulf while an inspection process presumably resumes?</p>
<p>   Would you like to see that for some months?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I am not going to put a time on it but I am going to describe</p>
<p>   what I would like to see. And I would be happy to support a continued</p>
<p>   presence until such time as we can be properly satisfied that this</p>
<p>   is an agreement that is going to be honoured. Now that maybe if</p>
<p>   possible within a short period of time, it may take longer, but</p>
<p>   I think most people would agree that there would be nothing more</p>
<p>   absurd than to have some kind of military withdrawal and then to</p>
<p>   discover that something was not being delivered. </p>
<p>Now it is just a question of a commonsense approach. If we have</p>
<p>   got an agreement, and I can't say that until I have seen it,</p>
<p>   but if we have, let's assume we have, then we want to be satisfied</p>
<p>   that it is going to be delivered on. It is a question of it being</p>
<p>   signed and sealed and we want some evidence that it is going to</p>
<p>   be delivered.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>And I assume that you would agree, given the kind of fragility</p>
<p>   of feeling particularly in the region, but also American public</p>
<p>   opinion and international public opinion, that if America did decide</p>
<p>   that its interpretation of that document was not the same as Kofi</p>
<p>   Annan's and that, in fact, it was going to proceed with military</p>
<p>   action. Kofi Annan's support of this agreement diplomatically</p>
<p>   does make that, that next step much tougher for America does it</p>
<p>   not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Kerry that is an entirely hypothetical proposition at the</p>
<p>   moment and we are dealing with the sort of issue about which I don't</p>
<p>   want to respond to hypothesis.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Ok. Can I ask you to wait there because we have one more story</p>
<p>   from our correspondent in Jerusalem that I would also like to get</p>
<p>   comment from you on.</p>
<p>[BREAK]</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, how do you react when you see that kind of sentiment</p>
<p>   expressed, those perceptions, at least, of double standard, within</p>
<p>   the Arab world?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You have got to look at the history of the Middle East for over</p>
<p>   40 of Israel's 50 years of existence, there was almost a united</p>
<p>   Arab view that the country should not even exist and, in fact, several</p>
<p>   attempts were made to destroy Israel as a political entity. And</p>
<p>   secondly, you have got to bear in mind that, unlike Iraq, Israel</p>
<p>   did not, in an unprovoked fashion, invade and occupy a neighbouring</p>
<p>   country. Thirdly, Israel has never used chemical warfare against</p>
<p>   a portion of its own population. Fourthly, for all that is hurled</p>
<p>   at Israel by its critics - and Israel is not without blemish, let</p>
<p>   me make that very clear and I'll come back to that in a moment</p>
<p>   - Israel, at least preserves the basic democratic traditions of</p>
<p>   government and elections and an incorruptible judiciary. </p>
<p>So, I think there is a lot that can be said which clearly marks</p>
<p>   out a country like Iraq from a country like Israel and I think the</p>
<p>   charge, against those sort of considerations of double standards,</p>
<p>   is unfair. But let me make it clear that Israel has not been without</p>
<p>   blemish and it is certainly the policy of my Government to try and</p>
<p>   encourage, as best we can, the peace dialogue to go on. We do support</p>
<p>   the aspirations of the Palestinian people, they are legitimate and</p>
<p>   they are proper. And I hope that one day they can be realised in</p>
<p>   harmony with a secure Israel, within borders that everybody continues</p>
<p>   to respect and honour, something which did not exist for more than</p>
<p>   four fifths of Israeli existence since her creation in 1948.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Do you believe that the pressure is now much more strongly on the</p>
<p>   United States to, in-turn, increase its pressure on Israel to do</p>
<p>   more to accommodate a genuine, lasting peace?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think all of us who are friendly towards Israel and respect</p>
<p>   what Israel has achieved in the last 50 years have that responsibility</p>
<p>   and the Americans, in particular, and the Americans are endeavouring</p>
<p>   to do that, and I think what President Clinton made plain to Benjamin</p>
<p>   Netanyahu, when he went to the United States a short while ago,</p>
<p>   bore that out. The Americans have made it clear, to be fair, particularly</p>
<p>   the current administration, that it is a two-way process in the</p>
<p>   Middle East and that America is not just there to do the bidding</p>
<p>   of Israel.</p>
<p>But, you have to take that longer view. And you must understand</p>
<p>   the history of that period that for a long time it was the declared,</p>
<p>   united, unmitigated policy of the Arab States to destroy Israel</p>
<p>   and you can therefore understand, against that background, some</p>
<p>   of the defensive action that Israel has taken.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Ok, if we can cross our fingers now and hope that this is a genuine</p>
<p>   breakthrough in the Middle East, if I can bring you back to some</p>
<p>   domestic issues. On your plans to change the tax system and introduce</p>
<p>   a new goods and services tax, you have been looking at this issue</p>
<p>   for some time now, in detail. When can we expect to be able to share</p>
<p>   in that detail? When can we expect you to conclude, complete, your</p>
<p>   tax reform policy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Kerry, I can't give you an exact time but I can assure you,</p>
<p>   and through you the Australian people, that there will be adequate</p>
<p>   time between the release of our tax policy. And it is not, as your</p>
<p>   question may have implied, just about an indirect tax, it is a total</p>
<p>   change to the tax system, including major changes and improvements</p>
<p>   to personal tax. I mean it is a total change to the tax system,</p>
<p>   including major changes and improvement to personal tax. </p>
<p>There will be adequate time for people to look at the package,</p>
<p>   assess the reform, see how it affects them before any election.</p>
<p>   We certainly don't intend to drop it the day before the election.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>So when you say adequate time, do you mean at least a couple of</p>
<p>   months before?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not going to try and sort of define that, but adequate</p>
<p>   time. There is nothing in it for us to play around with the Australian</p>
<p>   people on this. I wouldn't insult the intelligence of the Australian</p>
<p>   people by not giving them proper time to have a look at something</p>
<p>   like this and I think they will like it, because deep down people</p>
<p>   realise our present system is inadequate. The wholesale tax system</p>
<p>   is out of date, the personal tax system is unfair and they want</p>
<p>   a new and better deal.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>And when you say adequate time, you mean you will complete a policy</p>
<p>   and you will present a total picture with detail of the various</p>
<p>   elements?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, of course. Yes, that's always been or intention. I mean,</p>
<p>   the Labor Party wants to block tax reform, they want to stop it.</p>
<p>   I am very interested that Gareth Evans said today that if we did</p>
<p>   put forward a new plan and we won the election they wouldn't</p>
<p>   oppose it in the Senate. Well, I will remind Mr Evans and Mr Beazley</p>
<p>   of that quite a bit between now and the election. But I think, deep</p>
<p>   down, they would want to fight a negative, political campaign which,</p>
<p>   sort of, doesn't offer any kind of hope or inspiration about</p>
<p>   the future. I want this country to go into the 21st Century with</p>
<p>   a modern, better, lower tax system and it appears the Labor Party</p>
<p>   just wants to preserve a system that had its roots in the Great</p>
<p>   Depression.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>But at the moment, you have also got the possibility that business</p>
<p>   itself will not embrace this with open arms. You have got that broad</p>
<p>   coalition of business groups that have been very carefully going</p>
<p>   through what they regard as the right kind of tax reform and tax</p>
<p>   mix. They have been in discussion with the welfare lobby as well.</p>
<p>   Both of them have expressed opposition to the idea of using your</p>
<p>   GST to pay for the tax cuts, the income tax cuts, that would go</p>
<p>   with it. Now that must concern you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it doesn't. What I have seen doesn't concern me.</p>
<p>   We've talked very regularly with the business community about</p>
<p>   tax reform and also with ACOSS, representing the welfare sector,</p>
<p>   and we will go on doing that. At the end of the day, of course,</p>
<p>   we are there not to do the bidding of this or that interest group,</p>
<p>   we are there to present a package which we think best helps the</p>
<p>   totality of the Australian population. I am pretty confident that</p>
<p>   what we ultimately produce will draw very strong support.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>Very briefly, on Telstra, the Treasurer, Peter Costello, said today</p>
<p>   that he saw no logic in the public owning one third of Telstra and</p>
<p>   the Government owning two thirds. Do you support that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I certainly support selling a lot more and I have been on</p>
<p>   record for a long time as believing that privatisation of assets</p>
<p>   like Telstra makes a great deal of sense, full privatisation. But</p>
<p>   I am also on record as saying that if we are going to sell any more</p>
<p>   we will first seek the support and the approval of the Australian</p>
<p>   people before we do that. So that if we are going to do more, it</p>
<p>   would be part of our policy for the next election and the Australian</p>
<p>   people can then make a judgement, as they did last time. And I think</p>
<p>   they will judge us pretty favourably because the Australian people</p>
<p>   have done very well out of the sale of one third of Telstra. There</p>
<p>   are 600,000 Australians who have bought shares for the first time</p>
<p>   in their lives, in Telstra. Ninety two per cent of the employees</p>
<p>   of Telstra bought shares and the mums and dads that made investments</p>
<p>   have now already enjoyed a capital gain of about $1,000 per shareholder</p>
<p>   as a result of the increase in the share price. I think they will</p>
<p>   line up in thousands to buy a further slice in this great Australian</p>
<p>   company.</p>
<p>O'BRIEN:</p>
<p>John Howard, thanks very much for talking to us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
