<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21985</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview Robertson Barracks, Darwin </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/10/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, before the election you said there would not be a nuclear waste facility in the Northern Territory.  Why have you gone against your word?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, we have to solve this problem.  We started, as a country, 13 years ago to try and solve the issue of a nuclear waste dump.  We had an agreement and then when it came for that to be located in a particular part of Australia, all of the States and Territories just ran away from it.  And this issue has got to be brought to a head and it will be.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Why did you say that the Territory would be treated like the other states in the rights in respect to it (inaudible) this latest legislation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's not a question of the Territory being discriminated against.  I mean everybody is adopting the attitude of not in my backyard and in the end we can't sort of have the waste float out into the stratosphere.  It's not as simple as that and there has been to a solution.  Now if the Chief Minister can persuade all of her Labor colleagues to put the repository somewhere else then I'd be prepared to listen.  But I don't think that's going to happen.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what's your response to Jon Stanhope's decision to put the anti-terrorist legislation, draft anti-terrorist legislation on his website?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think that's irresponsible.  It's important that governments, no matter what political stances we might take, should have the capacity to talk to each other in confidence and that legislation was given in confidence. Let me say in relation to this issue that I can assure the people of Australia that the legislation finally presented to the Parliament will reflect the agreement that was reached by me with all of the State Premiers and Chief Ministers, no more, no less.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you disappointed he perhaps breached your trust on that matter?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I am.  But let's move on.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>One of the other issues in regards to that, one of the concerns has been that there's only going to be a one day in the Senate where the legislation will be discussed, etc, and concerns that there's not enough consultation.  What's your response to that and is there enough consultation?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there won't be one day in the Senate, there'll be a Senate inquiry.  But the legislation will be before the Parliament for a number of days.  And there'll be plenty of opportunity for it to be scrutinised and examined during that period.  This legislation is going to reflect the agreement I made with the Premiers and Chief Ministers.  It's important for the security of Australia.  It was unanimously agreed to by me with the eight Labor Premiers and Chief Ministers.  And we can't have any undue delay, but the legislation will be exposed for public scrutiny and it will reflect that agreement.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Labor's calling for that inquiry to be extended for more than a day, what do you say to that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Labor always calls for something different from the Government.  Thank you.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Princess Mary?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, well I'm very happy, the baby arrived safely.  Congratulations.  A healthy baby boy I gather, name unknown, but I'm sure all Australians will wish her and her husband well and congratulate them on a safe delivery.  It's every parent's greatest wish and I'm very happy for them.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you got a suggestion for the name?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no. I don't want to provoke any diplomatic incidents.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
