<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3474</transcript-id>
    <title>MESSAGE TO THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003474.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 374<br />
19 November 1974<br />
MESSAGE TO THE PRIME MINISTER OF THE<br />
HELLENIC REPUBLIC<br />
The Prime Minister today released the text of a<br />
message of congratulations to Mr Karamanlis, following<br />
the Greek elections at the weekend.<br />
" To His Excellency Mr Constantine Karamanlis,<br />
Prime Minister of the Hellenic Republic.<br />
In my message to you of 25 July this year I<br />
congratulated you on your restoration as Prime Minister and<br />
wished you well on your assumption of responsibility for<br />
conducting the affairs of your country. It now gives me the<br />
greatest pleasure to record the delight with which the<br />
Australian people in general, and in particular the very many<br />
men and women in Australia with bonds of family and affection<br />
for Greece, will welcome the manifestation in recent days<br />
of your success in restoring democracy to its birthplace.<br />
You have not only my warmest personal congratulations on your<br />
return to Government, but Greece itself and all political<br />
parties at the recent election deserve our admiration-for<br />
their co-operation in a noble democratic enterprise. I very<br />
much look forward to meeting you in December to pass on to<br />
you personally the hopes of all Australians for success in<br />
the important tasks which face your new Government. E. G. Whitlam"<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
