<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40951</transcript-id>
    <title>$50 million for new jobs at the future centre of excellence at Western Sydney Airport</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Turnbull and Premier Berejiklian have welcomed Northrop Grumman’s $50 million investment establishing a multi-million dollar Electronic Sustainment Centre of Excellence at the new Western Sydney Airport.</p>
<p>Northrop Grumman’s investment will generate new jobs in Sydney’s western suburbs, underscoring the vision to transform the regional economy under a City Deal for Western Sydney.</p>
<p>The Centre of Excellence is a key part of Northrop Grumman’s commitment to double its workforce in Australia to 1,000.</p>
<p>Northrop Grumman’s Centre will be the first anchor tenant in a new high-tech defence and aerospace precinct at the Western Sydney Airport, a key element of the deal. The Centre will be in a prime position to service and maintain aircraft and systems, including for the F35 Joint Strike Fighter and MQ-4C Triton.</p>
<p>The Centre will reach out to universities and training institutions to create partnerships and train the highly skilled technicians essential for Western Sydney’s future job needs.</p>
<p>The announcement by Northrop Grumman follows the Turnbull Government’s decision to build a new airport at Western Sydney. The $5.3 billion investment in the airport is giving businesses the confidence to invest, expand and create tens of thousands of new jobs in Western Sydney.</p>
<p>Northrop Grumman International President, Dave Perry has welcomed the Government’s investment.</p>
<p>"The Government's strong commitment to grow the defence industry in Australia gave us the confidence to make this significant investment in Western Sydney", he said.</p>
<p>All three levels of government are working together with business to secure economic growth in Western Sydney and the jobs and security that this brings.</p>
<p>The Government’s unprecedented investment in defence capabilities over the next decade, and the determination to maximise Australian industry involvement, will ensure Australia has a robust sovereign defence capability to keep us secure and meet our future strategic needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
