<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5277</transcript-id>
    <title>RUNDLE SHALE OIL PROJECT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/02/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005277.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER I,.<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY 28 FE1 J6 R190,<br />
RUNDLE SHALE OIL-PROJECT<br />
I have great pleasure in announcing that Southern Pacific<br />
Petroleum ( SPP) and Central Pacific Minerals ( CPM) have advised<br />
that, after evaluating a number of proposals for participation<br />
in the Runidle Shale Project, they have selected Esso<br />
Exploration and Production Australia Incorporated ( Esso) for<br />
furtCher negotiations. SPP/ CPM and Esso will enter immediately<br />
into negotiations with the aim of finalising a joint venture<br />
agreement as soon as possible.<br />
Esso ' s proposal to SPP/ CPM includes an offer for substantial<br />
financing of SPP/ CPM's-participation in project investment and<br />
also provides for SPPi'CPI4' s participation in project management.<br />
The proposal provides for a maximum Esso interest of 50 per cent<br />
in the project.<br />
The policies of the Commonwealth have been of fundamental<br />
importance in creating the circumstances in which this project<br />
is economically feasible. The viability of the project is<br />
under-pinned by the Commonwealth's policy on import parity pricing<br />
for crude oil. Without this assurance to the developers of an<br />
economic market for their product, it would not be possible to<br />
justify the enormous investments that will be involved.<br />
The project would not have been able to proceed without the<br />
Commonwealth's import parity pricing policy. By providing a<br />
long-term commitment that oil produced in Australia will be<br />
marketed at realistic prices, companies have been able to<br />
proceed to explore alternative sources of liquid fuels, which<br />
may not have been viable at lower crude oil prices. 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
The general economic climate, the encouragement given to<br />
investment, and the great prospects for development in Australia<br />
are all relevant to the decision to proceed with this very big<br />
project. The joint venture agreement and the project will, of course, be<br />
subject to all necessary Commonwealth and Queensland Government<br />
approvals, including environmental considerations, Foreign<br />
Investment Review Board approvals, and Reserve Bank approvals.<br />
The joint venturers and Esso plan an immediate start on a major<br />
research and engineering program for the project. Following this<br />
work, present plans envisage the construction of a pilot plant to<br />
prove the technical and economic viability of producing oil from<br />
Rundle oil shale. This plant is expected to take at least three<br />
years to construct and will cost several hundred million dollars.<br />
Employment at the plant will be about 500 and construction<br />
employment about 2000. M~ any more will be employed in support<br />
industries in Gladstone and other centres in Queensland.<br />
If the pilot plant is successful, the partners expect to expand<br />
production progressively to the deposit's full potentirl1 of<br />
around 200,000 barrels of oil per day, which is about 30 per cent<br />
of Australia's current requirements. Such prodJuction would<br />
augment the world energy supplies and would replace 70 per cent<br />
of Aust--ralia's present imports of crude oil. Import bills are<br />
currently running at about $ 1.9 billion per year. Production<br />
from Rundle could be particularly important to Australia as<br />
current projections show that output from Bass Strait will decline<br />
progressively from the mid 1980s.<br />
Esso's proposal to SPP/ CPM contemplates that all production<br />
would ultimately be upgraded to a synthetic crude oil for<br />
feedstock to Australia's refineries where it will be refined<br />
into normal petroleum products, including petrol.<br />
The development of Rundle to its full potential would involve<br />
expenditures by the partners of many billions of dollars.<br />
Employment during the construction period is estimated to be a. 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
between 6000 and 8000 people for several years. The project<br />
will be a very substantial addition to Queensland and Australials<br />
economy. It is difficult to overstate the importance of this project for<br />
the development of the State of Queensland and for Australia as<br />
a whole. The potential the project has for reducing Australia's<br />
dependence on costly imported crude oil is very great. At a<br />
time when world oil markets are uncertain, the Government gives<br />
very high priority to the development of indigenous sources of<br />
liquid fuels. This has, of course, been one of the major aims<br />
of the Government's oil pricing policies and it is pleasing to<br />
note the success of these policies in this particular area.<br />
It is likely that the successful development of this project<br />
will lead to-further exploitation of Australia's shale oil<br />
reserves. These subsequent developments will provide the<br />
opportunity for other interested parties, including our major<br />
trading partners, to participate in this industry.<br />
The participation of Esso in the project is to be Welcomed.<br />
Esso has already made a large contribution to Australia's<br />
development through its many investments in Australia, particularly<br />
in discovering and developing the Bass Strait oil fields in<br />
partnership with BHP. The Rundle project will provide an<br />
opportunity for Esso to reinvest in Australia the profits it<br />
has derived from the Bass Strait oil fields. The willingness<br />
of Esso to reinvest these profits in Australia is welcomed by<br />
the Government. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
