<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2057</transcript-id>
    <title>REMARKS TO PRESS AT LIBERAL PARTY RALLY - MT. BAKER, S.A. - 25 MAY 1969</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002057.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
REMARKS TO PRESS AT LIBERAL PARTY RALLY<br />
MT. BARKER, S. A. MAY 1969<br />
Q. PM. / 2<br />
If you were asked questions about why you haven't<br />
told them about Pine Gap or the F-Ills, why they are crashing, how<br />
will you answer them?<br />
If they ask me why are the F-llls crashing, I will say<br />
all aeroplanes in the course of development have a number of crashes.<br />
The F-ills at this stage of their development have had less crashes<br />
than any other aircraft. As to when we are getting them I can only<br />
answer by saying not until we are thoroughly satisfied that they are<br />
completely safe and will meet the specifications which we expect them<br />
to meet. Why haven't you been told about Pine Gap? Well, I<br />
think I answered that the other day. If yourmilitary advisers and<br />
your scientific advisers say that the giving of any information might<br />
be of assistance to an enemy just as in war you wouldn't give that<br />
information, so in peace you don't give it either.<br />
But there is a lot of unrest and a lot of feeling about<br />
Pine Gap. It is said we could become a prime nuclear target. We<br />
are being kept in the dark. Is this true? Are we being kept in the<br />
dark purposely? No. We are being kept in the dark because of the<br />
advice tendered that to say anything about the station would be of<br />
assistance to a potential enemy. It would help them to know sooner<br />
than they otherwise would. They will probably find out in eighteen<br />
months or a couple of years. But it would help them to know sooner<br />
than they otherwise would just what particular purposes the station<br />
is designed for. In the case of the North-West Cape station, of course,<br />
it was different because everybody knew what it was for anyway. It<br />
had been built in other parts of the world. It was a low frequency<br />
communications station. But these ones, for good and proper military<br />
security reasons, we are advised should not be spoken about.<br />
It seems almost out of place talking about this sort of<br />
thing at an LCL rally, but about this student unrest and the meeting<br />
on Tuesday. Can you predict any likely outcome of this meeting?<br />
What meeting on Tuesday?<br />
There is a meeting in Canberra on Tuesday discussing<br />
the student unrest. We were just wondering whether there were any<br />
possible outcomes regarding heavier penalties against student<br />
demonstrations.<br />
Q. PM.<br />
Q. PM. ( 0/ 063 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM. Well, I don't know what meeting is being held on<br />
Tuesday. It is not a governmental meeting, so I don't know quite<br />
what meeting you are talking about, but I think our own approach<br />
is the one which the Minister for Science and Education, Mr.<br />
Fraser, had the other day. This is primarily one doesn't<br />
object to dissent as such. This is good. This is questioning. This<br />
is putting forward different ideas. This is fine. But if it erupts into<br />
violence or the organised takeover of buildings in a university or<br />
something of that kind then that is in effect a negation of democracy<br />
because it means that people who can't get majority opinion are<br />
prepared to take action by force. And that, I believe, is quite<br />
wrong. But it is primarily a matter for universities to take action,<br />
and secondarily a matter for State Governments to take action<br />
because the universities are set up under State Government acts.<br />
If something boils over into the street and there is a riot of some<br />
kind or other then that clearly must be prevented and I hope would<br />
be prevented by State legislation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
