<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19285</transcript-id>
    <title>Gillard Government Announces Jobs Expo for East Devonpport</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/05/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Wynyard, TAS</p>
<p>Job seekers from northern Tasmania will once again have the opportunity to explore a marketplace of opportunities and vacancies when the Australian Government's Jobs and Skills Expo is held at the East Devonport Recreation Centre on Friday 21 June.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government's Jobs and Skills Expos have provided local job seekers with a great chance to connect with jobs and training opportunities in the region.</p>
<p>Job seekers will connect with employers, private recruitment agencies, Jobs Services Australia providers and registered training organisations.</p>
<p>They can expect to find opportunities from a great range of sectors and job types from retail and hospitality to resources and health care; from administration to tradespeople.</p>
<p>Hundreds of jobs seekers were connected with jobs and training opportunities at the previous Expo hold in Devonport in July 2010. This year in Tasmania we have already hosted a Jobs Expo in Hobart in March and there is one next week in Launceston. Now the Government is bringing back an Expo to Devonport to build on that success.</p>
<p>The Expos bring together employers, employment services providers and training organisations with job seekers on one day  -  creating a one-stop-shop for jobs and training.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government has a growth and jobs plan for Tasmania. The Government is fighting for jobs and opportunities for all Tasmanians.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government has delivered 76 Jobs and Skills Expos. We know that they work because we've now seen more than 26,400 Australians find employment by attending the Expos and many thousands more sign up for training opportunities.While Australia has one of the lowest unemployment rates in the developed world, finding a job can be daunting for some.</p>
<p>The event is a major chance for job seekers to talk to employers and sign up for jobs or training.</p>
<p>The Expo will be held at the East Devonport Recreation Centre, Carolyne Street, East Devonport from 10am to 3pm.</p>
<p>Those interested in exhibiting or registering a job vacancy at the Australian Government Jobs and Skills Expo in Devonport should visit the website at <a href="http://www.humanservices.gov.au/expos">www.humanservices.gov.au/expos</a>.</p>
<p>Employers can also contact their Local Employment Coordinator for North West / Northern Tasmania Priority Employment Area, James McCormack on 0428 299 262 any time or email <a href="mailto:james.mccormack@deewr.gov.au">james.mccormack@deewr.gov.au</a>, should they wish to follow up on available assistance. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
