<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18468</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia to further strengthen nuclear security practices</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard today addressed leaders and representatives from over 50 countries at the Seoul Nuclear Security Summit to confirm Australia's ongoing commitment to combat the threat of nuclear terrorism.</p>
<p>Speaking at the summit, the Prime Minister said the ultimate goal was to set up nuclear security practices that keep the world safe for the decades to come.</p>
<p>That is why we are today announcing further action in the following areas:</p>
<p> * 	Australia's ratification of the Nuclear Terrorism Convention.  Under this convention, any person who conducts an act of nuclear terrorism can be brought to justice irrespective of the territory in which they are found.<br />
 * 	The hosting of a regional nuclear security workshop to build further capacity and collaboration on nuclear security in South East Asia.<br />
 * 	A review of security arrangements at our nuclear science facility at Lucas Heights by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) in 2013.</p>
<p>Australia has a proud history of action in these areas. We have the strongest possible commitment to stopping the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction and to nuclear disarmament.</p>
<p>Today, we have worked to strengthen the global nuclear security architecture and ensure that countries make legally binding and other commitments to the highest standards of protection.</p>
<p>The world has become a safer place since the Washington Summit, thanks to the renewed focus on nuclear security driven by President Obama's vision and the work of many countries. </p>
<p>Australia looks forward to the final stage of the summit in 2014 and the long term future of nuclear security across the globe.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
