<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18833</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Doorstop Interview - Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Video Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What's the terror threat in Bali and are you worried going over there?</p>
<p>PM: Look, people should always check the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade travel advice warnings but I do want to be in Bali for the 10 year commemorations.</p>
<p>Families will be travelling there. It will be a day in which we pay our respects and remember what that moment was like for Australians.</p>
<p>JOUNRALIST: Do you feel betrayed by the Speaker Peter Slipper and the fact that you spent so much time supporting him yesterday for him only to resign two hours later?</p>
<p>PM: We supported Peter Slipper to become the Speaker by following his successful track record of service as Deputy Speaker. Now a lot has happened since Mr Slipper first became Speaker and these matters were fully dealt with in the Parliament yesterday.</p>
<p>We now have new Speaker and we're getting on with the job.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, some people have expressed concern about his state of mind and his health. Do you have those concerns and do you sympathise with him at the moment?</p>
<p>PM: Look, I said what I felt about this in the Parliament today following Mr Slipper's statement. I said anybody witnessing that statement would see the real human pain written across Peter Slipper's face.</p>
<p>He spoke in very emotional terms about the cost for his family and whatever other judgements people come to we've got to remember that there's a real live human being and his family at the centre of this matter.</p>
<p>He has now resigned and so I hope that he has the opportunity, with some privacy, to spend some time with his family after these events.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Was your defence of Peter Slipper in vein yesterday given his ultimate decision to resign?</p>
<p>PM: I didn't believe the Parliament should be a kangaroo court.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Tony Abbott says you should just ‘get over it': the gender issue, his comments yesterday. What do you say to that?</p>
<p>PM: Well that's a matter for Mr Abbott to explain what he meant by those comments.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What do you make of the worldwide reaction to your speech in Parliament yesterday? It got a bit of press overseas.</p>
<p>PM: I made my speech in Parliament yesterday because I formed the view, enough is enough. I've had enough. Australian women have had enough. When I see sexism and misogyny I'm going to call them for what they are.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
