<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10101</transcript-id>
    <title>Order of Australia Council </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/09/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010101.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Following consultation with the Governor-General, Sir William Deane AC, KBE, I am pleased to announce the appointment of seven new Councillors to the Council of the Order of Australia. The Council for the Order of Australia meets twice a year to consider nominations and to make recommendations for awards in the Order of Australia to the Governor-General.</p>
<p>Rear Admiral ( rtd) Peter Sinclair AC will be the new chairman of the Council, which next meets on 11 and 12 September. This follows a decision by the Chief Justice of the High Court,Sir Gerard Brennan AC KBE to relinquish the position.</p>
<p>The other new Councillors are:</p>
<ul><li>Rear Admiral ( rtd) Peter Sinclair AC - Former Governor of NSW</li>
<li>The Hon Sir James Killen KCMG  - Barrister and former Federal Minister</li>
<li>Mrs Marjorie Turbayne OAM  - President ACT Australia Day Council</li>
<li>Ms Anne Fulwood  - News Presenter and member of the Film and Literature Board of Review</li>
<li>Mr Allan Border AO -  former Australian Cricket Captain </li>
<li>Dr George Santoro AM  - Former President Australian Medical Association ( Victorian Branch)</li>
<li>Ms Sara Henderson  - Grazier/ Author</li>
</ul><p>Lois O'Donoghue CBE AM, Chairman of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commnission, has been reappointed to the Council.</p>
<p>All appointments are for two years.</p>
<p>I am delighted that these distinguished Australians have agreed to give freely of their time to this important national cormmittee. They bring with them a breadth of' experience and achievement which encompasses the whole community and which all Australians can respect and admire.</p>
<p>10 September 1996<br /> </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
