<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>156</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES AT THE OPENING OF JEWISH WAR MEMORIAL HALL, WAVERLEY ON SUNDAY, 7TH FEBRUARY, 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000156_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH 31-THE PRIMiE MINISTEi, THE RT. HON. R. G.<br />
MENZIES AT OPENIAIG OF JEJISH JA1i MEMiORIAL HALL,<br />
' VERLY ON SUNDAY 2T FIRIUAlRY 1960<br />
iMr, President, Your Excellency, distinguished visitors and<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
I think that this is a very happy occasion for a very<br />
material reason and I also have t. ro quite irrelevant reasons for<br />
being here this afternoon.<br />
The first irrelevant reason though perha: s it isn't<br />
irrelevant is that I have observed with great interest that<br />
your President's name is Felix I was going to say his<br />
Christian name but I suppose that wouldn't be right. ( Leughter),<br />
But his name is Felix which. if I remember my Latin correctly,<br />
means " happy" happy ( Applause). And I should tink he<br />
ought to be. The second irrelevant reason that I have in my mind<br />
is that the last time I had the honour of making a speech to a<br />
Jewish congregation in Melbourne I was a little troubled about<br />
having to wear my hat all the time. I look bad enough without<br />
a hat on, but when I have a hat on I look terribla ( Laughter)<br />
end I made a little bargain with the Rabbi who is a imost<br />
courteous and obliging man and he said: "' ell, if you start of.<br />
rith it on, you may then remove it and put it on again before<br />
you finish" and that's what I did. And this aftenocn Felix<br />
Happy here said to me just before ie cam ru " It's all right<br />
from now on it's hats off". Therefore I'm so speiaking cool,<br />
calm nd col. ected.<br />
Noj, S: Lr, I'm not going to detain you but just want<br />
to say two o-three things about you and about thi r" irkablc<br />
and interesting occrsion<br />
T'ere are three things that have alxays struck me<br />
about your ccmmunity I hope you won't mind a rank outsidei<br />
like myself, who is an unblushing Presbyteri2. n you ! know what<br />
I mean making a few obse-. vtions about a cnommunity, so many<br />
members of hich aie very close personal friends of mine, Dut<br />
three zhines have alv: ays struck me . nd I think thay' r worth<br />
mentioning. he I'i: cst is your adherence to your faith, You've<br />
been persecuted for it in the course of the centurie. sj you've<br />
been a:; tacked for it you've almost been or. dered to aibandon iLt<br />
from time to time and you haove adhered to it t* arough thick and<br />
thin until it has been hammered into true steel. Now th&amp; t's a<br />
wionderful thing, a wonderful thing your deep. loyal and abiding<br />
religious faith. I admire that enormously. Everybody does.<br />
It produces in any corimunity n element of sanity and balance<br />
and reliability which no comnriunity can afford to be without,<br />
I don't want you to think that people who are not of your par.-<br />
ticular religious faith necessaril/, or frequently, or at alLj<br />
object to you on that ground. Of course we don't. On th.<br />
contr.. ry. Any man, any woman, who has the flame burning qnd .: ho<br />
keeps it alight is a great mnz. n and a great woman and the<br />
community is proud of him and proud of her.<br />
That's the first thing that I've always liked and<br />
admired about the Jewish comnrunity. It's an enduring quality,<br />
And the second thing that I've always admi: ed is that<br />
Ireally think that you have a remarkable sense of family. I<br />
have met a few pe-ple in Australia not too many, I hope, but<br />
some who are a bit anxious to pass off the responsibilit-y for<br />
their fam'lies to somebody else. live never met a Je-w yho felt<br />
like that, I've never known a Jewish fAmily in which the w-Jlfare<br />
of every membe. of the family wasn't the constant task of<br />
the lot, Now thati's a marvellous thing because the family a<br />
L </p>
<p>good family, a iealth family, % proud famfily, a. famiJly generous<br />
in itself this is of the very essence Df cormunity life,<br />
There can be no , reat nations without great -famAly f1eeling and<br />
I adraire your community im-,, enseJ-y because all thnrough ray life<br />
I have observed this extraordinary, devoted sense of family<br />
pride and fawily resp. onsibility I hope that will s:; lwvays<br />
continue Your community is not a sep.ñ rate -body in a great<br />
nation. It's not a sort of colony. You have no intention that<br />
it should be. But your fuith -tnd your inheritead instincts are a<br />
g. reat contribution tL-otL -ha coni-, iunity in ; hich-you live.<br />
And the third -thing that's always excited my admi,-* ration<br />
i've said something d ut faith, faily117-i he third<br />
is friendliness. I rant to say a word to you -, bout f2iJendliness,<br />
if I may.<br />
I knowi that recently there hc-. ve been stra~ n-e people<br />
puttin, up strange slogans, you'LI* lLoxr met ays<br />
know a little bit about this kind of thin, because " Outl with<br />
* pig-iron Bob" or something ( LauLghter) ( Applause) h-as been on<br />
W every railway crossin, and every brIc walado cu en<br />
a low-down politician I've nev-, er ob. jeck-ed 1-oc it lbacai-use P've<br />
felt that this was unpaid pub. f -city ( ugtr. But I think<br />
that ' qe just want to have in ou2 minds thtthe-e 
be a fe-w people fho intend mi-ischief, who desirec to de-f". le the<br />
community, those rae_ 1d on't believe in tnt orly s: ystem-of<br />
g-overnment that . re believe in, th. at there T1.11 1waMys be a few<br />
people -rho -I-ant to mnake ruide noi1ses or mtupD of'fensi-ve slo. Tanc<br />
And if one coul. d g7rab one of them th-at ijouW. be the day never<br />
been able 3et one mys-elf ( Lauiar( er). They have ino in<br />
this country, They don't :' upresent any opinion in this country<br />
but as usual they've trace d ( Xouad them,; elves ~~ htmgtbe<br />
called " Ithe lunatic fring?". no -, cu i1ow . rKt I mean2' 7hc; are<br />
the silly well to use cood ~. ae~ oAustr-i! iln eco3ression<br />
the " 1ratbags" Arho say: " This is 1etty , gooc.; Uhs' 1d e n<br />
they will 5o . a-rua. nd chaikcin--uP cir painting vp slogans,<br />
I don t rant to discuss that problem iith-yr. e: cept<br />
to say this: that 99 87o of tne peoiule o2 Australia rc-ard thlese<br />
manifestations wi-th contemp,-t. These th-ngs don' c -u prosent a<br />
great movement in this count. ry. Nobody need e ver ' ear in your<br />
community that, in the case cf some of ynvu 7 out oX'<br />
great tribulation , nd poarseution into a country in whichi you<br />
might still be porse cut~ ed, Forget about it ( A'np2 auso). You Iye<br />
comte into the freest country in thie rol.( A'il e That<br />
tGhe 5reat charm about Australia; that's why my friend landa<br />
and I can be up here instead of biting ( each other's ! hea. ds off)<br />
( Laughter) and find our. solves on common gro-unrd, yo~ u kvoi, on<br />
common ground admiring this spec'" acu7-ar Cnd devoted piece of<br />
w-. ork, 3ut it's a fr2ee count.' y, It will rema. In e.<br />
You know I came down haore to do thi s J~ ob and I came<br />
do~ in yesterday and as I drcove in fro,-! the . Uirpor; the (-arstopped<br />
opposite a Hotel thc: 1.-0 twas a tr il lgh aainst<br />
us and it vias in one of those SUL--burb tha-Dt vote J'forLn<br />
and don't vote for Ikenzies you 1kno,; Tn-at 1 inean? ( Ap. plause,<br />
laiughter) arid in the charmfng e l fre-sco halbit that people have<br />
in Sydney there were three fel-loes sitt-ing-. n thae Joorstep Of<br />
the 3ar with their feet in " he strLu&amp;; Lhir-a d~ oin-. tnd there<br />
was arnother one a rather ill-condit-ioned of fellow%,, he<br />
didn't look entirely sober and the-firs. t thrac fellerfs waved.<br />
thleir beer mugs at me ( Ano. said. " Goec' on yor, 13ob" ( Laughter).<br />
fell I thought that was:. thaer nicc. And tlno next feloiw,<br />
sitting all hunched up by hm-e. f, 9 he Just locked at rio and<br />
said: " 1Huh, yei-big mug", ( Laugh.)-Or) Ncw r1-ir, 14A~ e thLat;<br />
I approve of that ve--y wairrmly., see llrl voary Prou: d to be<br />
the Prime Minister of a free countryIibl. toc be dismissed by<br />
the froe citizens one3 of the-(-se days, ' proud to be se-oving them </p>
<p>3.<br />
and with no complaints of what their decision might be because<br />
we are free people. ( Applause)<br />
Everyone of you who was born in Australia -' nows that;<br />
you don't need to be told by me. And those who have come into<br />
Australia, parti cularly since the aar, out of the horrors of<br />
Europe, in particuar, I know that you've breathed more freely<br />
since you came here and that you feel that you're in a free<br />
land where you have your own opportunity and where, by your<br />
great talents and irammense industry, you can make great places<br />
for yourself. And that being so, while I would wrillingly stamp<br />
my foot on one of the deplorable creatures who do these deplorable<br />
things, don't get that out of proportion. That doesn't<br />
represent anybody of intelligent, decent Australian opinion and<br />
it never will.( Applause)<br />
And so, Sir, I come back to There I bean. Im very<br />
proud to have been invited to come here. I think this is a<br />
marvellous development. Only people with vision and courage<br />
could have imagined this centre, with all its costliness, with<br />
all the hard work thathad to go into it. Only people with<br />
* vision and faith and imagination could have done it. And I<br />
want to say to you; " God speed". I think this is a great<br />
occasion, a great occasion in the history of your own religious<br />
community, a great occasion in the history of Sydney. I can<br />
well understand the M.' yor's pride of this in Javerley and I,<br />
speaking on behalf of Australia, if I might, am proud to think<br />
that such a work could have come jbout through faith, a feeling<br />
for the family and a friendliness which is, I assure you,<br />
reciprocated all round this country.<br />
And so, Sir, I say " Thankyou" for having invited me.<br />
I offer to the rhole of this immense audience or congregation,<br />
my warmest good wishes. I think it's a marvellous occasion.<br />
I'm proud to have been associated with it. ( Applause) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
