<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23227</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit by New Zealand Prime Minister John Key</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/02/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I look forward to welcoming New Zealand Prime Minister John Key, senior Ministers of his Cabinet and a delegation of New Zealand business leaders during their visit to Australia from 6-8 February 2014.</p>
<p>Our relationship with New Zealand is like no other. With the Centenary of ANZAC fast approaching, this visit is another opportunity to reflect on the unique bonds that bind our two nations, our shared history and our common values.</p>
<p>In addition to a joint meeting of Cabinet Ministers, I will meet with Prime Minister Key in Sydney on 7 February to discuss mutual economic opportunities. New Zealand is our seventh largest trading partner. In 2012-13, our total two-way trade was $21 billion.</p>
<p>The delegation of New Zealand’s business leaders accompanying Prime Minister Key, will work with their Australian counterparts to highlight and deepen our economic ties through the Closer Economic Relations (CER) agreement.</p>
<p>As this year’s host, Australia has invited New Zealand, along with Singapore, to participate in the G20 during 2014. The G20 Summit will be the most significant meeting of world leaders Australia has ever hosted.  As a country with strong economic growth, declining unemployment, reduced red tape and growing trade, New Zealand can bring both expertise and its own perspective to the G20’s work this year.</p>
<p>I will continue to work with the New Zealand Prime Minister and his Government to ensure that our two nations strengthen what is one of the warmest and closest international partnerships.</p>
<p>3 February 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
