<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1065</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF ROYAL AUSTRALIAN MINT AT CANBERRA BY HIS ROYAL HIGHNESS, PRINCE PHILIP, ON 22ND FEBRUARY 1965 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER,THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001065.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF 2OYAL AUSTIU. A, IAN MINT AT CAN, 3ER' 1iA<br />
BY HIS ROYAL HIGHNESS, PRINCE PHILIP, ON<br />
22ND FEBRUARY, 1965<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister the Rt. Hon Sir Robert ezies<br />
Your Royal Highness and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
This is not really my day. This is the Treasurer's<br />
day. The Treasurer has had all the travail of bringing into<br />
existence simultaneously a Mint and a near system of currency,<br />
and if anybody thinks that is easy, he should have been vTith<br />
us at any time over the last two or three years. And so this<br />
is the Treasurer's day and I don't want to steal any portion<br />
of it from him.<br />
My one simple and very pleasant task is to welcome<br />
His Royal Highness here. You have already made it, of course,<br />
quite clear to him how welcome he is in this country at any<br />
time, but it is particularly appropriate that he should be<br />
here today to perform this opening because this is something<br />
rather special if you come to thinc about it.<br />
Here is a relatively new country. Here is a<br />
relatively new city. Here is a brand new Mint. Here is a<br />
brand new system of currency coming up. There is a tremendous<br />
amount of novelty concentrated in today modern novelty,<br />
up-to-date novelty, and therefore it is very appropriate, if<br />
I may say so, Sir, that you, the most modern and up-to-date<br />
Prince in the wrorld should be here to perform this opening.<br />
( Applause) , Je, in Australia, frequently have occasion to think<br />
about you and to ta'. e pride in the fact that although some of<br />
us are a bit long in thne tooth is that the expression? and<br />
grey in the hair, you represent, in your own person the talent<br />
and enthusiasm and understanding and spirit of adventure of the<br />
second part of the twentieth century. It is a matter of immense<br />
pleasure to all of us and great pride that you should be here<br />
today to perform this opening.<br />
And now, Sir, having said this all too inadequately,<br />
I will hand it back to the Treasurer whose day it is and rho<br />
, Jill) I shrewdly suspect, make a speech to us about the Mint.<br />
2. 6 FEB 1966 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
