<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1943</transcript-id>
    <title>FEDERAL COUNCIL OF THE LIBERAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA - 21 OCTOBER 1968 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001943.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FEDERAL~~~ COUNCI OFTELBEA AT<br />
OF AUSTALI<br />
HoeCaner CabraACT<br />
DlgHtoeCla imCnab ra: aberA . T<br />
It is in some ways a very awesome thing to stand here in<br />
front of you at a place where two great leaders have previously stood and<br />
to address a Party which for so long has kept in power a government which<br />
has enabled Australia to be transformed. I think that most of you will<br />
understand the humility with which anybody must, for the first time, appear<br />
before you in a place where those other leaders have for so long appeared.<br />
I don't propose to talk to you for very long tonight, but there are some<br />
matters I think we must regard, as a party, as new matters for Australia<br />
to consider, as new matters for the members of this Party to solve.<br />
Some of them, of course, are not entirely new but they are<br />
new in the degree to which they impinge upon us, and one of those is the matter<br />
of defending our country. it has been since the last Federal Conferencq Of<br />
this Party that the final decision has been taken for the accelerated withdrawal,<br />
and what appears virtually a complete withdrawal, of the United Kingdom from<br />
the countries to our North and from East of Suez. And though for a lor~ g time<br />
we have been talking, all of us, of the need for more defence for Australia,<br />
of the need to look more to ourselves for our own security, yet this has only<br />
recently been brought home in the starkest terms.<br />
It may be traversing ground which ought not to be traversed,<br />
but yet we should have it in our mind that for nearly two centuries we lived<br />
under the protection of Great Britain. It was her Navy that kept us safe,<br />
and it was only when crises arose that young men and women flocked from all<br />
corners of this Cornonwealth and made sacrifices, at whatever level was<br />
required, during the time of conflict. In between little attention was devoted<br />
to defence. Now that has changed and must be accepted as a new situation<br />
facing Australia. So we find that we have had, as a government, to raise a<br />
vote for our own defences which was running at some $ 400 million a year<br />
to a vote which is running at 250 million and which in terms of money,<br />
I think, will over the years ahead need to Ire raised still more ( though not, if<br />
I can help it in terms of our gross national product).<br />
Not only has this new situation forced this vast diversion<br />
of resources upon us but it has exacerbated the solution of the other new<br />
problems to which as a nation and as a party we are pledged. And yet<br />
some of these problems cannot just be put aside. I hate, and I believe most<br />
of the peop le in this room would hate the thought of all those resources<br />
devoted to defence. When we think of the number of schools, of the number<br />
of hospitals, of the new freeways, of all the things for which the people of<br />
Australia are calling which could be provided with that sum of money, we </p>
<p>-2<br />
must regret that it is necessary for that sum to go to defence. However,<br />
schools, freeways, hospitals and all these other things are of little use<br />
unless they can be safely held and defended by the country which has them.<br />
But there are matters which cannot, in a modern nation<br />
with a modern conscience, be put aside or denied. Here, too, though these<br />
are not new matters yet, Sir, I think there needs to be a new approach, a<br />
new examination. You have all heard me speak from time to time of the<br />
essential need to care for the old, the ill, the handicapped in our population,<br />
But up until very recently we, as a Liberal Party, took the view that our<br />
contribution towards such people should be just that, a contribution, and<br />
that we would expect them to receive from other sources, from their<br />
family or from some charity, or from another source somewhere,<br />
additional assistance to enable them to live in reasonable self-respect.<br />
I don't believe that is an approach that can any longer be accepted by the<br />
Liberal Party. I believe that the new and necessary approach and the one<br />
which my Government will take must be to see that a contribution made to<br />
such people is sufficient for them to live in frugal comfort and with<br />
reasonable self-respect, so that there is no need for appeals to be made<br />
for blankets to keep them warm or for fuel for their houses in the winter<br />
or for additional food because they do not have enough. This, in a sense,<br />
is a new approach but it is an approach, Sir, that we must make.<br />
In its application it is not simple. Again, always in the past<br />
in seeking to help people of this kind, we have dealt with a broad buh. we<br />
have said, " Let us raise this pension or that pension by so much across the<br />
board. This approach, I think, is wrong and wasteful in that it on occasions<br />
leads to the provision of more than is required for the standards of which<br />
I have spoken to be attained, and on occasions leads to less. For that.<br />
reason we have, as a government, a Welfare Committee researching and<br />
searching into the requirements of people of this kind so that the aid ca * n be<br />
given where the need is greatest and so that there will be, from the resources<br />
available, sufficient to meet those areas where the need is great.<br />
This Committee, which has already resulted in your<br />
Government removing one great fear that was in the hearts of the Australian<br />
people and that is the fear of a long-continued illness being unable to be<br />
paid for by the community, is bringing down recommendations to us which<br />
will seek to attain the ends and ideals I have been putting before you. And<br />
while they are seeking to do that, they will also, as I believe from the ' work<br />
they have already done, ensure that in doing what I have suggested shoul d<br />
be done, they will not remove the incentive, will not remove the rewaroi for<br />
those who have saved to assist themselves over and above what the com~ munity<br />
may give them when they retire.<br />
We have, you have, all this period of time since 1949,<br />
created a climate in which, gradually at first, then with ever-increasing<br />
speed, Australia has become transformed. All that time ago, you rejected<br />
a concept which I believe was inherent in the philosophy of our opponents,<br />
and that concept was that the individual existed to serve the state and that<br />
the state did not exist to serve the individual. And from that grew an<br />
insistence on controls, unnecessary controls, and from that grew a .9/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
stagnation which became so impossible to bear, which resulted in a rate<br />
of unemployment of five per cent which was said to be all that a developed<br />
country could expect to attain, that you revolted against it and changed it<br />
and changed the philosophy. As a result, you brought about that climate of<br />
development, that Possibility for the individual to take his risks and reqp<br />
his rewards if he were successful and to take the consequences if he wasn'tt,<br />
according to his own efforts and according to his own ability and energy.<br />
So in that period of time, this country grew to the stage of incipient gr~ atness<br />
in which it now finds itself.<br />
It finds itself now in a position it has never been inbefore.<br />
This again is something new which faces the nation and which faces<br />
us as a Liberal Party. You all know of the enormous developments now<br />
taking place in the North of Western Australia, in the seas off the coast<br />
of Victoria, in Queensland, and of the immense material benefits which will<br />
flow and are flowing from them nickel, iron ore, oil, minerals of all<br />
kinds, requiring not millions, but billions of capital for their full and<br />
proper -development; another call upon the national resources which is<br />
new, a requirement as I believe, Sir, for this Party to accept that it is<br />
necessary, with these possibilities before us, with the capital required for<br />
their full development being hard to get, that priorities of development for<br />
the good of the nation need to be examined and need to be decided.<br />
Then we come to another matter, on upon which, Sir,<br />
we touched this morning, one which will be the subject of future discussion<br />
by the Party, and that is, in your own. words: What sort of a Federal<br />
system do w want, and how can we best make a Federal system work?<br />
Is it right and proper that nearly a quarter of a century after a general<br />
philosophical programme was adopted in a country which was then different<br />
from the position in which it now finds itself, in a country which had<br />
problems not measurable against those now to be faced, that we should look<br />
again to see whether the philosophy then adopted meets the requirement of<br />
a nation a quarter of a century later.<br />
This is new. It is good that it is new. It is good that<br />
it is going to be discussed. WV ith one of the points so long ago adopted', Sir,<br />
I believe there can be absolutely no question, and with that all here would<br />
agree, and that is enshrined in the words.. " the development to the fullest<br />
extent of a national spirit in Australia". It has been growing. I am su* re<br />
it will grow, and I am certainly going to do all that is within my power, as<br />
a leader of the Liberal Party to see that this national spirit is fostered and<br />
is developed and that everybody in Australia now, or in thirty years' ti me<br />
wnen we will be twenty-eight million people, will feel some kind of fire in<br />
the heart when they say, " I am an Australian" first, foremost and all the<br />
time. Then the next point which will be the subject of discussion<br />
is this phrase... " the maintenance unimpaired of a Federal system of<br />
government with appropriate divisions of power". We will need to examine<br />
what is meant by " unimpaired" because quite clearly it doesn't mean<br />
" unchanged'" or else we would not, as a Liberal Party, have changed as<br />
we have in such things as passing a referendum on aborigines and in other<br />
ways. What we need to work out in our philosophy is not the question of<br />
divisions of funds. This of course comes later. This of course is importart,<br />
but this of course is different from what I am now talking about. / A </p>
<p>-4<br />
What we need is to consider let me put it rather not<br />
in terms of what we need, but the kind of approach which I have in mind and<br />
with which some may agree, others may notj but which it is time for this<br />
Party to thoroughly examine.<br />
In my view, Sir, it would be unthinkable for an<br />
Australian Government not to have the overriding power over the maintenance<br />
of the Australian economy as a whole. It would be unthinkable to have a<br />
nation where an Australian Government could not assess the resources and<br />
materials available throughout the nation and could not, if necessary, let<br />
credit run so that all materials and all resources were used, and if necessary,<br />
restrict credit so that cost inflation because of an over-demand on materials<br />
and resources availabledid not occur. I don't really * think this is a subject<br />
of dispute, but it is the starting point from which I begin.<br />
I think that it is necessary for an Australian Government<br />
to be able to effec t the division of resources in the nation betweL:. 1 the public<br />
and the private sector according to its requirements of private development<br />
or of public development, and I know of no other way in which this can be<br />
done but by an Australian Government.<br />
I think that it is necessary, if these tenets I have put<br />
forward are accepted, that the major fields of taxation in Australia should<br />
be, as they are now under the Constitution, the responsibility of an<br />
Australian Government, both as to their use and as to the rates of taxation apphed<br />
within them. It would seem to me to be silly, if to meet some particular<br />
economic situation for the good of the nation, the Treasurer for example,<br />
lowered the rate of income tax in order to enable more to be available to be<br />
spent by the private sector and private people, and burdens to be taken<br />
off those who are now so heavily burdened, the middle range, and were to<br />
do this for economic reasons, and those taxes were to be arranged again<br />
by some other source. These are all matters o f overall economic management.<br />
These are all matters which now, under the Constitution, are the responsibility<br />
of an Australian Government. There are, of course, other fields in which much<br />
discussion can take place. I will deal with only one of them. I would ike<br />
the conference to feel, as I hope they do feel, that what I am saying to jhem<br />
is what I feel is for the good of Australia as a whole and a necessity if:<br />
Australia is to progress in the way it should. They are not just light or<br />
random thoughts. There is a need for an Australian Government to be ' able<br />
to move to a field of special assistance somewhere in Australia if that field<br />
of special assistance is going to be of benefit to this nation, and it cannot,<br />
without an Australian Government, be exp loited.<br />
if, for example, there is to be a requirement for cheap<br />
power to be provided somewhere in Queensland and it is known that if<br />
that cheap power is provided then there will be twenty other industries<br />
established to use it and a port will grow into a city as a result, but it<br />
will cost $ 200 million, then there would be a requirement for an Australian<br />
Government to be able to assist in that way. If there is to be a requirement<br />
for a pipeline to bring natural gas from somewhere in Australia to Adelaide<br />
and it cannot be achieved without assistance from a national government, then<br />
a national government needs to be able to have the right and the capacity to<br />
assist in that way. </p>
<p>I don't think I need to expand this list, but I would ask the<br />
conference to put this question in their minds. But for the use of grants<br />
such as Section 96, Sir, do you believe that we would now have a uniform<br />
system of rail gauges throughout Australia? You answer it in your own<br />
minds. I don't believe we would. ^ o there is a need, too, for this kind of<br />
assistance, and this kind of capacity for an Australian Government.<br />
Let me refer to another matter, another aspect of the same<br />
matter because these are all things that this Party must look at and malke<br />
up its mind about and they are important and they need not be the subject<br />
of snap judgments. I think that there is a demand from the people of<br />
Australia as a whole, and I think it is a just and a proper and a necessary<br />
demand that after general purpose grants have been provided to State<br />
Governments as they have been and will be in increasing amounts, there is<br />
a need on behalf of an Australian Government that certain responsibilities<br />
to the nation are met. There is a need, for example, to see that the<br />
facilities for the education of a child are roughly the same, no matter in<br />
what part of Australia that child may be born and grow up. There is a<br />
need and a requirement to see that the facilities for the care of the ill are<br />
roughly the same in Australia, no matter where it may be that a citizen<br />
falls ill. These, if they are demands and I believe they are and<br />
if they are proper demands and I think they are are again matters in which<br />
an Australian Government must concern itself.<br />
If it is true and I believe it is true, that in the world of<br />
today we must grow, not only economically but technologically, if it is true<br />
we must develop our own technology and train people in methods of operation<br />
and methods of building and methods of application of time, if this is<br />
true, then it is a national requirement that proper technical and technclogical<br />
education is applied throughout the whole of Australia. If that is a national<br />
requirement, then no national government can sit baclk and wash its hands<br />
of that responsibility and say, " Oh, but general purpose grants have been<br />
made and there is nothing further for us to do, even if this requirement<br />
isn't met. So I am glad that amongst the other new things that I have<br />
mentioned and the other problems which we face and the other calls upon<br />
us which prevent us from being able, because of a shortage of manpower and<br />
material to do all we want to do, that this other matter is to be a subject of<br />
discussion. I have sought merely tonight, because I thought it was my<br />
duty, to give an insight into some of my thinking to those of you who are here.<br />
I don't believe it would be true or right or proper to describe that thinking<br />
as the thinking of a centralist or a unificationist. It is the thinking of somebody<br />
who believsthat national requirements do exist, there is a responsibility on a<br />
national government to see they are met, but that after that, then the<br />
general grants made and made in increasing quantities are used and<br />
administered by those governments nearest to the people.<br />
So it will be an interesting discussion, a necessary discussion,<br />
a new approach. I think in any case that on the record of what we have done<br />
we ought to be able to solve the problems still before us With you, I<br />
look forward to that day I spoke of when we are not twelve but twenty-eight<br />
million and growing more rapidly to forty million and becoming a great<br />
material power, a power with a social conscience, applying those principles<br />
we are now working out and will begin to apply again in the next Budget, and<br />
giving to our people the feeling not only of material greatness but a capacity<br />
and an opportunity to develop themselves and their own individuality which<br />
after all was one of the reasons, if not the most important reason for the<br />
foundation of this Liberal Party. I think, Sir, we will be able to achieve these<br />
things together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
