<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4575</transcript-id>
    <title>TAX AND OVERTIME, 2 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004575.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F7 7/ 2 84<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 2 DECEMBER 1977<br />
TAX AND OVERTIME<br />
The tax reforms and tax reductions my Government has already<br />
made in the law which will apply in eight week's time on 1st<br />
February, help Australians in all income groups.<br />
Most people fall within the medium or middle income range<br />
and it is in this area that tax on overtime is a big factor<br />
for a lot of people.<br />
Under the old Labor tax scales, Mr. Hayden's 1975 tax scales,<br />
the penalty rates of tax took a large bite out of extra wages<br />
and the pay packet from overtime. Under that Labor policy, the<br />
high tax of.. 45 cents in the-dollar. came in at $ 200 a week, or<br />
$ 10,000 a year.<br />
our new tax reforms have ended that discouraging situation.<br />
The normal rate of 32 cents in the dollar will apply from 1st<br />
February, right up to $ 16,000 whether that includes overtime<br />
or not.<br />
We have achieved this by cutting back the number of tax brackets<br />
from seven to three. We now have a simpler and fairer tax<br />
system. It helps the man or woman who is prepared to work<br />
a little harder towards a goal in life by not confiscating<br />
a big part of overtime earnings.<br />
Mr. Whitlam and the Labor party want to go back to the days of<br />
penalty tax rates. This is a negative, discouraging approach<br />
which ignores the fact that Australians have as much initiative<br />
as any people in the world if only they are given the opportuinity.<br />
7-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
