<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1764</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF PRIME MINISTER&#039;S  &quot;MEET THE PRESS&quot; INTERVIEW</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/01/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001764.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
l" n .1t<br />
2 5 JAM t968<br />
EMBARGO: G) RA<br />
NOT FOR RELEASE BY ANY MEDIA UNTIL 10. 30 PM<br />
ON SUNDAY, 21 JANUARY, 1968<br />
TEXT OFPRIME MINISTER'S " MEET THE PRESS"<br />
INTERVIEW<br />
Following Is the full text of the interview given by the<br />
Prime Minister, Senator John Gorton, In the " MEET THE PRESS" programme<br />
telecast by BTQ Channel 7 inBrisbane tonight.<br />
The Prime Minister recorded the programme while In<br />
Brisbane a few days ago.<br />
Introduction by the Chairman, Mr Reg Leonard:<br />
From this studio, exactly nine weeks ago, I was privileged<br />
to introduce to you the Prime Minister of Australia. That, of<br />
course, was Harold Holt. Now I don't want to dramatise what<br />
has happened between and brought sorrow to this station, except<br />
to say that five weeks ago today, Harold Holt, as you all know,<br />
was swept to his death. And I want to add this. That tonight it<br />
Is my great privilege to introduce to you his successor, to pre~ mit<br />
In the second week of his high office, the new Prime Minister of<br />
Australia, Senator John Gorton. Good evening to you, Sir.<br />
PRIME MINISTER Good evening.<br />
MR LEONARD The panel are John Wakefield, Elgin Reid and John<br />
Athert on. We are going to talk to the new Prime Minister for<br />
minutes. If I may say so, with great respect, before the questions<br />
start, I have never known an Australian who has become so well<br />
known In a few days as our guest tonight. But let me say this:<br />
The Prime Minister Is no novice to politics. He has been around<br />
for quite a few years in Canberra, and he has been the Leader of<br />
the Government In the Senate. He Is,. If I may put It In a nutshell,<br />
a very rugged Australian, with a great war record and a distinguished<br />
academic record Master of Arts,, Oxford University.<br />
Now, with those few words, please start the questtong.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, what is the biggest problem that you face<br />
as Prime Minister in your view. Put another way: What do you see<br />
as this country's major difficulties over the next few years?<br />
PM: I would have to give a general answer, and I will give It In<br />
these general terms. Our great difficulty Is to try to see that the<br />
competing demands that are made upon Australia can be met withot<br />
putting burdens on the Australian people which might destroy their<br />
incentive to meet those demands. We have requirements here which<br />
have grown really enormously over the last few years. We have<br />
requirements for development which must take place if we are to<br />
grow into the nation that we can grow Into. We have requirements * e9oee/ 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
PM. for looking after our less fortunate citizens, and so on through<br />
( Contd.) education and health. Now there is also a limit to the amount of<br />
taxation that can be put upon Australans In order to meet these,<br />
and the real problem is the apportionment of resouirces amongst<br />
these conflicting demands, not only In our Government but in<br />
State Governments and Commonwealth Government.<br />
MR LEONARD: Forgive me for Intervening very briefly, Sir, you<br />
were asked about challenges to your Administration, which is very<br />
new; would you regard the current troubles with our postal workers<br />
and mail deliveries as a great challenge? I presume you would.<br />
I know there are great difficulties about commenting on this In<br />
any detail because the situation could change dramatically between<br />
the time we are recording and Sunday night when we go on the air.<br />
But wouild it be fair to ask you, as a general prlifcl' 4e in Industrial<br />
troubles of this kind which hold up the nation's business, would It'<br />
be fair to say that the Government would not retreat?<br />
PM: I think that in this case not as a general principle but<br />
answering you in this case, the Government could not retreat.<br />
At least, the Government could not allow Australian malls to<br />
pile up and not to be delivered. I think our attitude on this I can<br />
summarise in a few words. We hope that the striking drivers will<br />
go back to work as soon as possible and then use all the processes<br />
of Arbitration which are available to put their case. We hope that<br />
this will happen, but we can't wait Indefinitely for it to happen<br />
while mail is pilng up because Australia's life blood could be<br />
clogged If we did. We have no choice but to move the mail. We<br />
hope the strikers will go back<br />
MR LEONARD: I think, like you, most Australians will hope that by<br />
the time this goes on the air it will all be over. John Atherto<br />
Q. Prime Minister, getting away from that, Is there one particular<br />
achievement you wodil like to pull off during your term as Prime<br />
Minister?<br />
PM: It may surprise you to hear this: There are achievements<br />
In the field of social welfare which I would like to see brought to<br />
fruition during my time as Prime Minister. This I think will<br />
Involve some rethinking of the methods by which a uch things as<br />
pensions are paid, the methods by whicl uch things as<br />
Repatriation benefits are paid, the approach to health problems<br />
where at the moment somebody who has a long, continuing<br />
illness can, In fact, be ruined and face ruin because he cannot<br />
be covered. Now, what I would want to see, and It would not be<br />
easy to work this out and I don't pretend It Is worked out In my<br />
mind now, but what I would like to see Is a situation where<br />
somebody who was genuinely Indigent as a result of the slings and<br />
arrows of outrageous fortune not his own fault and had the<br />
fear of that and the burden of that lifted from him. I am ndt to<br />
be taken as saying I believe In a complete welfare state and handouts<br />
all down the line, but I would like to see real misfortune overcome.<br />
Q. Would you be Interpreted incorrectly If we said you were<br />
favouring some kind of national Insurance? a / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: It might turn out that that could be a correct Interpretat ion<br />
but that Is not the one which I give it at the moment. I will try to make<br />
It clear: I haven ' t plans but plans can be worked out. They may or<br />
may not involve national insurance.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, how do you propose to overcome your<br />
relative Inexperience In foreign affairs and your lack of contact with<br />
internatbnal leaders?<br />
PM! Well, let me remind you of a few facts. I was the Chairman<br />
of the Parliamentary Foreign Affairs Committee for a long timei After<br />
that time, I have acted as Minister for External Affairs on a number of<br />
occasions, and when the former Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies,<br />
took over the portfolio, I acted on all except policy matters. I have<br />
been In charge of the running of the Colombo Plan, for example, for<br />
a couple of years. I have met, and I know well, Harry Lee of Singapore.<br />
I know Tunku Abdul Rahman, I know Tun Razak, I know Malik from<br />
Indonesia. I don't claim great experience or great knowledge, but there<br />
Is some experience there.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, can you tell us please, we are assuming<br />
or we know that you will be elected to the House of Representatives<br />
next month can you tell us how soon after that you hope to be able to<br />
go to Viet Nam?<br />
PM: I think I must answer that, as much as I would like to,<br />
I see little prospect of going there until after this Session of the<br />
Parliament Is concluded which might be April or May, as far away as<br />
that. You see, there are meettin~ to be held before the House reassembles,<br />
there Is some preparation to be done. I see little prospect of getting<br />
away until the Session is over.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, It has been claimed in some circles,<br />
particularly overseas, that on Viet Nam you are a hawk. Are you,<br />
and how far you willing to go to support peace Initiatives, not<br />
necessVly ~ m America, on Viet Nam?<br />
PM: Well, bird-like labels always need a little bit of explanation<br />
before you can really know what they mean. On the whole, I think I<br />
would regard myself as neither a hawk nor a dove, but as an owl In<br />
this matter I don't mean you can't see very well, but you've got the<br />
reputation,, I hope, for wisdom In It. All we want there Is that there<br />
should be a cessation of fighting. Well, we could get that by withdrawing,<br />
of course. But a cessation of. fighting which would leave the South<br />
Vietnamese people able to work out their own destiny, and we hope<br />
with our and other people's assistance, build up their own economy.<br />
You have asked me, I think, about bombing. I have pointed out<br />
recently with this question that the Americans could, if they wished,<br />
comple tely destroy North Viet Nam, but that that would be a wrong and<br />
a stupid thing to do. The bombing Is trying to stop the flow of men and<br />
materials from the North Vietnamese to the South. It is hampering<br />
It; It is not stopping it, but It Is hampering It. If there were an<br />
undertaking, a package deal that talks would start when bombing stopped,<br />
and that the sending of men and materials from North to South would<br />
stop when bombing stopped, then that is a goal which I think we would<br />
all like to see achieved. 9 / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
Q. Do you think there Is any chance of peace talks with<br />
Hanoi be fore the next American Presidential election?<br />
PlMt I am afraid I must say I am doubtful because I think<br />
that the North Vietnamese are waiting and hoping that there may be<br />
a change in the United States at the next election, and may be quite<br />
intransigent until then. I hope not,, but I fear so.<br />
Q. Do you imagine there would be any dramatic changes<br />
if the Republicans won the Presidential elections? Last time it was<br />
being said It would be unthinkable they would step things up.<br />
PM:. Well, I don't like to comment on affairs in a foreign<br />
country. It depends. Some people in the Reputlicans have some<br />
views, some others.<br />
Q. I shouldn't have u~ ked that question, Prime Minister.<br />
Q. Does Australia under your leadership, Prime Minister,<br />
stand as firmly and as fully committed to the Viet Nam war as It has<br />
done up until this point, and are you willing, if it Is considered a<br />
military advantage, not necessarily a necessity, to Increase our troop<br />
commitment there, Including more conscripts?<br />
PM: The answer to the first part of that question is yes, we<br />
are committed for all the reasons we first went Into It. VIe think<br />
aggression must be stopped and must be seen not to pay. The answer<br />
to the second part of the question is, at this moment, no. You asked<br />
me If it wasn't a military necessity..... I believe we are now extending<br />
all the effort that we can extend as a nation of twelve million people<br />
with her other requirements In this kind of field.<br />
Q. This means, does It, Sir, that we have gone as far as<br />
we can go In Viet Nam?<br />
PM; Well, subject to some complete kind of change. You know<br />
we have recently decided to send the tank support and the engineer<br />
support. I am assuming you are meaning that?<br />
Q. Yes President Johnson has wished you well, Prime Minister.<br />
Like your predecessor, are you all the way with him, or will you be<br />
putting some new thoughts to Washilngton?<br />
PM: Well, I think my predecessor had a tag hung around his<br />
neck which was not really justified. He did say at the end of a rather<br />
jocular speech, I think at the White House, " I'm all the way with LBJO<br />
which at that time was an election slogan they were using, and this<br />
has been taken to mean that he was saying that Australia would<br />
slavishly follow the United States policy. Well It didift mean that<br />
then, and it doesn't mean that now. I can assure you it doesn't mean<br />
that now.<br />
Q. Will you be putting any new thoughts to Washington? 000 </p>
<p>PM: If we have new thoughts, we would not be inhibited In<br />
putting them to Washington.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, many people find it difficult to follow<br />
Labor's policy on Viet Nam, mainly because so many people for the<br />
party seem to speak on It. Now could you tell us what Is your<br />
Interpretation of official ALP policy on Viet Nam?<br />
PM: I don't think ar~ yhody could you tell you that for reasons<br />
that you have spelt out yourself, but I believe that th well, I<br />
know that the official policy of the governing Labor body Is that we<br />
should say to the United States " Cease bombing North Viet Nam at<br />
once; put your troops Into a holding operation" In other words,<br />
make them stand where they are and allow them to be attacked but<br />
don't allow them to attack...... " and If you, the United States won't<br />
do that, then we will withdraw our troops from Viet Nam Immediately."<br />
On the other hand, I did seem to remember during the Senate campaign<br />
some claim from Mr Whitlam. that he was El Supremo and it didn't<br />
matter what the Federal Labor Conference said. I doubt that, and<br />
I think his comrades don't believe him.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, during Mr Holt's two short years<br />
In office he made several trips to Vlashington for personal talks with<br />
the President. Do you expect to k1eep up this personal liaison with<br />
whoever will be President of the United States? Do you hope to?<br />
PM: I do hope to keep up a personal Rlson but whether the<br />
number of trips would be as many as Mr Holt took in those two years<br />
I doubt very much. Some of those trips Mr Holt took were In fact going<br />
over to a Prime Ministers' Conference in London or something of that<br />
kind and he called in on the way. But I think I probably would not make<br />
a large number of special trips.<br />
Q. Do you indicate by that answer that you think Commonwealth<br />
Conferences are falling on their face or<br />
PM: I was only really Indicating that a number of the visits<br />
that Mr Holt made to President Johnson were not specially for that<br />
purpose.<br />
Q. You might be going to Commonwealth Conferences then,<br />
I take it?<br />
PM: Well we'll wait and see.<br />
Q. Mr Holt also made quite a number of trips to South-East<br />
AsIa6 cb you propose to follow this pattern and visit Asia reasonably<br />
frequently and keep in contact, personal contact, with the leaders there?<br />
PM: Definitely. I think this was ene of the great things Mr<br />
Holt did was to get a personal contact with the leaders of the countries<br />
nearest to us with whom for years to come we will be most closely bound.,<br />
and for the first time really, show that kind of Interest of an<br />
Australian Prime Minister and get the benefits of the personal knowledge<br />
that flows from It. I would certainly hope to do this. 9 o / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Q. Conversely, too, Prime Minister, lately we have been<br />
asking more leaders to our own country. Do you hope to keep that<br />
policy going?<br />
PMkv Yes. I do. I hope that before very long the Prime<br />
Minister of India will be visiting us.<br />
Q. How deeply are you worried, &amp; Sir, a, bout Britain's<br />
earl y withdrawal from South-East Asia as it had been originally<br />
planned?<br />
PM: Quite deeply. Not from the point of view of the<br />
Austra lian Continent's own security. I am not worried about ta t.<br />
I haven't regarded the fox ce there, which is a small force, as<br />
something directed towards the defence of the Australian continent<br />
Itself. But I am worried about the removal of what, In effect, has<br />
been a police force, able to stop small Insurrections, able to stop<br />
small attacks by one country In the area on another. You will<br />
remember the parachute raids that took place on Malaya itself<br />
at one stage from Indonesia, the landing of troops. This kind of<br />
thing they were able to stop, nip In the bud before It grew and I am<br />
worried that this security Is removed from that area.<br />
Q. Sir, just for my personal Information, and probably<br />
for some of the others too, Mr Holt told us once in this programme<br />
I think It was when Mr Healey, the British Defence Minister was<br />
out that there was some examination going on regarding the prospect<br />
of a shared base by Britain and Australia In this country. Can you<br />
tell us what the situation is about that, now?<br />
PM: Only that military discussions have been taking place<br />
between the staffs in Australia ' and the staffs in Great Britain, but<br />
they ha-ie been confined to planning discussions which have not yet<br />
come up to either Government for consideration as to whether those<br />
plans should be put Into operation or what the cost of them would be<br />
or whether the cost could be borne.<br />
Q. Would the announcement by Mr Wilson In the past few<br />
days affect that plan work, do you think?<br />
PM: Well, Mr Wilson has stated that the main purposcs of<br />
the United Kingdom' s moves and decisions are to save foreign<br />
exchange and for economic purposes,. so It may be that this thinking<br />
could be affected.<br />
Q. Witb the British withdrawal, Prime Minister, from<br />
our near North, would you consider, if asked and I think indirectly<br />
the country has been providing Austinlian troops to fill up the gap<br />
In Malaysia and Singapore, and in the light of what you have told us<br />
now about our commitment In Viet Nam, could we ever really afford<br />
to do this? 2<br />
PM: Well, I wouldn't consider putting In Austr alian troops<br />
to fill up the gap the British had left because I don't believe we can<br />
afford to do this. o, o / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
Q. isn't it a fact that Australians must face up to It that we<br />
are going to drift In all fields further apart?<br />
PM: There will always, I think, be special ties between the<br />
United Kingdom and Australia, ties of family relationships, but I<br />
believe that just as the relQ-tionshlp between Australia and the United<br />
Kingdom now Is really quite different from what It was fifty years ago,<br />
so the future too will see changes compared with what the relationship<br />
Is now, but I think it must continue to be ties of sentiment, sentiment<br />
must continue for many years ahead.<br />
Q. Taken strictly, I know it isn't your Department, but can<br />
you see an appreciable weakening of our trade ties with Britain, in a<br />
way which may damage our rural economy particularly?<br />
PM: Wiell you are quite right. This Is the Minister for Trade's<br />
Department more than mine. But If Great Britain were to enter the<br />
Common Market, and no-one knows If this might at some future time<br />
be allowed to take place, then I think it could affect quite seriously some<br />
of our industries.<br />
Q. Sir, how do you see the future of the Commonwealth,<br />
having In mind Britain's attempt to get into the Common Market, and if<br />
it doesn't it won't be its fault, and the withdrawal from East of Suezdo<br />
you think the Commonwealth will endure, and In fact, that Britain<br />
really wants it to?<br />
PM: Again I wouldn't want to comment on what Britain might or<br />
might not want to happen. This would be quite Inappropriate for me, and<br />
besides it would be silly. I think we can only wait and see what the future<br />
brings and to provide in the future the answer to the first part of your<br />
question will It endure, and If so, in what way, In what form.<br />
Q. Now In our limited time, I think overseas matters and<br />
foreign policy have haid a fair go. Could we get on to something<br />
perhaps nearer home<br />
Q : Prime Minister, soon you will have to face a review of the<br />
composition of your Cabinet. Now, we don't expect you to go into<br />
details here. But do you undertakce, if any changes are necessary,<br />
that you will go ahead with them, no matter which personalities are<br />
Involved.?<br />
PM: I undertake that I will do all that is possible but one can't<br />
Ignore completely the representation from the States and things of that<br />
kind. But I don't think one needs to pay slavish adherence to them<br />
either. You can't ignore them completely, though.<br />
Q: ~ What we are getting at, Sir, is that If you have got a dud,<br />
no matter where he is, will you root him out?<br />
PM: Well, I wouldn't say we had any duds!<br />
Q. Again not going into details, Sir, could you just say are<br />
you planning great changes in the Mvinistry? v / 8 </p>
<p>-8<br />
PM: I wouln't say great changes, no.<br />
Q. You did talk at your press conference the other day<br />
of changes or a recllotment of administrative duties. What did<br />
that mean? It was rather a broad statement you made.<br />
PkMt Oh yes. It means and I am a little Inhibited in<br />
answering this because I don't want to go into too much detail<br />
but it does mean that some Department which at the moment<br />
has a number of functions to fulfil under what Is called an<br />
Administrative Order could perhaps have one of those functions<br />
taken away, and that function could be provided to a Minister In<br />
aiolher Department. I am not talking of really significant,,<br />
Important Departments, but there is, I think, a good deal of<br />
tidying up which could be done to regroup the functions of<br />
Departments. For example, just to give you a more concrete<br />
example of sotatthing which might happe.... We did pass a<br />
Referendum giving the Commonwealth authcrity to look after<br />
aboriginals. Now at the moment there Is within the Prime<br />
Minister's Department a Secretariat in charge of that with the<br />
Minister for Territories having some connection with it. Well,<br />
an Administrative Order change might put that under the more<br />
direct control of a particular Minister whose particular<br />
responsibility It would be. This is the sort of thing I see.<br />
Q. It wouldn't go as far as amalgamating If that is<br />
the word the Army, Navy and Air Force<br />
PM: L No, it wouldn't<br />
Q. Do you think, Sir, that 26 Ministers might be too<br />
many?<br />
PM: e I don't know how to answer that. On the<br />
whole, I think they all have a great deal of work to do, and also<br />
it does no great harm, in fact I think itc'. oes good for a Parliament<br />
to have in it somebody who is responsible to It for some part of<br />
public administration and for the expenditure of public money,<br />
and who can be crosc -questioned on it. Let us suppose, for example,<br />
ycu wiped out as people have suggested we should although I<br />
don't believe we should Army, Navy and Air and just -had<br />
Defence. I don't believe any Minister for Defence, even if he was<br />
a genius, could answer to Parliament for the expenditure in Army,<br />
In Navy, in Air and in Defence and would have to rely very, very<br />
much more than at present on the Public Service Heads of those<br />
Departments to provide him with information and he could indeed<br />
In those circumstances, I think, claim with reasonable fairness<br />
that he couldn't be expected to know all the details Parliament might<br />
want him to kncwv. There are arguments both ways.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, are you completely happy I don't<br />
imagine : Wu are how unhappy are you, I should say, that Mr<br />
McEwen, the leader of a minority party should dictate who will<br />
not be Leader of the Liberal Party? a0.00/ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
PM: I don't think Mr McC-wen did dictate who would not be<br />
the Leader of the Liberal Party. What Mr McEwen did say was<br />
that he wouldn't serve underneath one particular man. But that is not<br />
to say either that was a decisive factor In what happened to that<br />
particular man, and certainly Mr McEwen had nothing to do with<br />
the choice of any of the other candidates who stood for the leadership.<br />
Q. WTe don't want to embarrass you, Sir but assuming<br />
that the particular gentleman had been elected Leader and Mr Mc~ wen<br />
had carried out his threat,, what then would have been the future of<br />
the present Government?<br />
PM: Oh, I think It would have been extremely precarious.<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, are you confident, the way it has<br />
worked out, that the coalition can work smoothly, and tell us frankly<br />
I don't know why we shouldn't mention his name how are you going<br />
to get round the relationship between Mr McEwen and Mr McMahon?<br />
PM: Well, again, something of this kind was asked me only<br />
a day or two ago, and the answer I gave then, I give to you now.<br />
This is a new Government. We want to rule the book off and to<br />
start afresh. Given goodwill and I believe there is goodwill and<br />
given knowledge that we must work together for the good of Australia,<br />
I believe that the tensions which previously existed might not exist<br />
In the future, I hope o.<br />
Q. Will1 you forgive nm while I am on that point. I think<br />
you will agree there is one part of the book you can't rule off, and<br />
nobody knows better than you that you have got a hostile Senate...<br />
PM: Oh,, that is a different part of the book. On the other<br />
hand, I have had quite a lot of experience of the Senate when we haven't<br />
had a majority. Vie haven't had a majority for years and years and<br />
years. The DLP and Indeyt adents have held the balance of power for<br />
the last two years, and now It Is a switch to the DLP holding the<br />
balance of power. Well, one just does one's best and we do seem not<br />
to have done too badly in the Senate, and from a Parliament's point of<br />
view as opposed to an executive's. The Senate has made some<br />
improvements in bills. If they were stupid enough, and silly enough<br />
to reject the Budget or something of that kind, this would be quite<br />
wrong. They haven'c done that.<br />
Q. Also apropos of ruling off the book, Sir, Labor probably<br />
won't want to, and wouldn't you thinkc that the fact that the Deputy<br />
Pr! me Minister has said that he does not trust the Deputy Leader of<br />
the Liberal Party will be fully exploited by y. iir political opponents<br />
at election time?<br />
PM: I have no doubt whatever that they will seek to make the<br />
greatest use they can of this...<br />
Q. Do you think they will get much mileage out of it, Sir?<br />
0 0 0 </p>
<p>10<br />
PM: Well, It depends I suppose partly on how much it is<br />
overshadowed by what Mr Caiwell has to say about the present<br />
Leader of the Opposition.<br />
Q. Touche!<br />
QO Can we clear. up a point, Sir? In your candidacy for the<br />
Prime Ministership, did you enter into any agreements with any<br />
groups of supporters on mutual support for some other candidate for<br />
some other position or did you offer any promotions or anything?<br />
PM: Absolutely none. I am happy to say that there Is not one<br />
single person who can say that they were promised anything as an<br />
Inducement to support me, which Is a great benefit and a great help.<br />
There Is not one. What I did do was to advise Mr McMahon<br />
personally that I thought he would be wise not to stand for leadership<br />
but for stand for Deputy Leadership. If he did that, I thought he would<br />
consolidate his position. But that is not an Indication of any promise<br />
or any deal or anything of that kind.<br />
Q. As you made no arrangements or gave no guarantees and<br />
you don't expect many changes in the Ministry, I take it we won't see<br />
many new faces around the place at the Administrative level In<br />
Canberra?<br />
P K: Well, I was asked did I contemplate great changes, and I<br />
think that was the question I answered.<br />
Q. I was talking about personnel changes.<br />
Q. Sir, no doubt you have been appraising your opponent, Mr<br />
Whitlem for some time, just how serious a political rival do you<br />
regard him, having in mind the elections?<br />
PM: I think he has got a very good TV appeal, particularly if they<br />
don't make him up too much, and I think he presents a case very well<br />
Indeed, and has an appeal, and I would regard him as quite a competent<br />
Leader of the Opposition, a very competent Leader of the Opposition.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, perhaps you will concede, at this stage anyhow,<br />
more Australians know him than know you. Now, how are you going<br />
to pick up the leeway befcte the next general election?<br />
PM: If you ask me to come and talk to you again, I'll do that and<br />
that will help what has been happening now and I will be making up<br />
the leeway. generally<br />
Q. The House of Representatives, Sir, 18ka rather more turbulent<br />
Chamber than the Senate to which you have been used to. How do<br />
you think you will go in the House, and how do you think particularly<br />
you will apprcach Mr Whitlam, an experienced~ Representatives man,<br />
over the centre table?<br />
PM: Well I can tell you that I am not filled with any apprehension<br />
about this, and this Is partly, of course, because I am not only<br />
facing Mr Vihitlam, I am facing Mr Whitlam and the Labor Party,<br />
and I have behind me the Liberal Party and the Country Party, and I<br />
am happy in my support, so I have no apprehension. 0 0. a / 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
Q. Mr Prime Minister, would you concede that Mr VWhltlam has<br />
welded the Labor Party Into a greater force to be reckoned with than<br />
your side of the House has had to face In elections for some time?<br />
PM: On the surface It certainly appears that way, particularly<br />
when one doesn't look too hard at Victoria.<br />
Q. Tell me this. I think you will agree that one of the weapons<br />
in politics, particularly In the House of Representatives as long as I<br />
have known it anyway, Is this needling technique. Are you satisfied<br />
that you won't fall into traps caused by that?<br />
PM: You mean, will! I be able to dodge water quickly<br />
Q. Do you feel that you won't be ruffled by this kind of<br />
technique?<br />
PM: I can only say that I hope I won't be.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, how do you propose to acquaint yourself with<br />
the particular problems of the various States?<br />
PM: I haven't the slightest doubt, from experience and foreknowledge,<br />
that the particular problems of the various States will be presented with<br />
great force and clarity, and over and over again by the people speaking<br />
for the various States. I don't think there will be any chance that I will<br />
not be fully aware of the particular problems.<br />
Q. ' Would It be a fair thing to ask if you think they are getting as<br />
fair a deal as it Is possible at the present time?<br />
PM: t It is a question that could be looked at but I couldn't ansme r<br />
at the present moment. I think we must remember this that neither<br />
the State Governments nor the Commonwealth Government are able<br />
to do all the things they want to do and should do. Wlhat I mean by<br />
" should do is co~ uld do with advantage. There is a general feeling<br />
around that the Commonwealth can do anything, that the Commonve aith<br />
can do this or that. It can It. It is Inhibited too.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, will you give us a quick run-down, please,<br />
on your attitude to the contentious question of northern development.<br />
PM: Why is It contentious?<br />
Q. Because a lot of people think up here there is too much talk<br />
and not enough action<br />
I<br />
PM: I see. I was wondering whether you were thinldivg of the<br />
theory put forward by some social agronomists that you get greater<br />
return from Investment In the higher rainfall South than you do from<br />
investment In the North. Well, my approach would, I am sure, follow<br />
the indications which, before I assumed this office, I gave. I was<br />
responsible for telling the CSIRO to put the Tropical Pastures<br />
Laboratory in at Townsville. I took part In the decision made by the<br />
Cabinet not to build an Army camp in the South where, for military<br />
reasons and administrative reasons cud economic reasons It would<br />
have been better, but to remove It to Townsville. I have played,<br />
as I think they will tell you, quite a considerable part In helping to<br />
expand the university college at Townsville, and the teachers' college. **. 9e/ 12 </p>
<p>12<br />
PM This is perhaps not the ktind of development you are thinking of.<br />
( Contd. ) You may be thinking of roads, water conservation and things of that<br />
kind, but It is a very real kind of development.<br />
Q. Sir, we are not talking only about Queensland. We are talking<br />
about the North, too, and Western Australia where there have been<br />
problems, too.<br />
PM: L I see, I thought you were mainly referring to Queensland.<br />
Q. No, we are trying to approach this on a national basis.<br />
PM: I see. Well, then what I was trying to do was to give some<br />
indication which, quite fortuitously happened to be in Queensland.<br />
I think the development of the North is one of the real problems we<br />
have got. I am Inclined to think1 , although at this moment without<br />
being dogmatic, that the conser vation of water in that area is one<br />
of the great developmental projects which can take place. But I don't<br />
ever see a situation where the North will be as closely populated<br />
as the South. I don't see this happening becats e of some natural<br />
disabilities, but that doesn't stop It being developed to the top of Its<br />
bent.<br />
Q. What Is your attitude, Sir, to migration from Asia? In the<br />
last couple of years there has been some further liberalisation, Do<br />
you want this to continue, this coutinuing liberalisation of migration<br />
from Asia.<br />
PM: Well, I think so. What you are talking of Is the length of time<br />
people have to stay here before they become naturalised and that<br />
kind of thing. Yes, certainly, I agree with that. My general attitude<br />
to this problem Is thi1s. We have In Australia at the moment, I think,<br />
almost no racial consciousness, almost no colour consciousness.<br />
There is, I am afraid I must say this In some areas this kind of<br />
feeling against aboriginals, but against Asians, I believe It doesn't<br />
exist. Now I don't ever want It to exist. It Is a matter of judgment<br />
at what point, how big a percentage of the population you have before<br />
this kind of thing begins. 1~ YOU can avoid that kind of<br />
development, as long as yo a~ n%# p1ople In short supply who can<br />
help us nurses and doctors and dentists and people of that kind<br />
then subject to those two provisos, I am quite glad to see the path<br />
the Government has been following.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, what are your thoughts on conscription?<br />
Do you like our system at present of being able to call up young men<br />
for active service abroad under the lottery system?<br />
PM: L I can't think of any other way of doing It which could not be<br />
attacked on the grounds of complete unfairness. You would, I am<br />
quite sure, have suggestions of undue Influence, suggestions of<br />
well, corruption Is a word, if it couldn't be seen, and it couldn't<br />
publicly be seen that that was the way In which pecplc. were chosen.<br />
I think myself that it Is the fairest way.<br />
Q. When we mere kids this was long before your time, Sir<br />
we all had to go Into cadets. Everybody had to go In. Wouldn't that<br />
be a fairer way, assuming you could train them, of course? 9 o / 13 </p>
<p>13<br />
PM: Oh, well, of course If you put every twenty-year-old<br />
youth in the Army, then, clearly, there would be no need to select<br />
particular people, but In our day, all we needed was a tent and a<br />
303 and, I think, a clip of five rounds of ammunition. This wouldn't<br />
do nowadays. I think you would find the cost would be quite crippling,<br />
not only of equipping and housing the youths but of taking them out of<br />
the development of Australia.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, we just didn't clear up one little<br />
point " by lottery for overseas service".<br />
PM: Yes, well, you are suggesting they should be chosen<br />
by lottery for overseas service?<br />
Q. Oh, no. I am saying is It fair, or do you think it is<br />
fair? You said there is no alternative, or it is the best way to<br />
call up men for military training because there could be no rigging,<br />
but these lads have-to go overseas, some of them.<br />
PM!-Yes. What decides whether rtey go overseas or not<br />
Is the unit they happened to have joined, The initial choice is, as<br />
you say, by taking a marble out of a barrel. They then join a unit<br />
of one kind or another and are trained as a part of that unit. If that<br />
unit goes abroad, I think It would be quite impossible to start taking<br />
component parts or individuals out and send it away.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, you mentioned as one of your aims,<br />
or hopes on becoming Prime Minister e~ zRier tn this session, of<br />
helping the unfortunate. Now the Opposition claims that ten per cent.<br />
of Australians live below poverty level. Have you got any thoughts<br />
on what you feel about that?<br />
P ML Well, I don't believe that ten per cent, of Australians<br />
do live below poverty level, but I do believe that there are numbers,<br />
quite eignificant numbers of people, living in great hardship or In<br />
poverty, and those are the people that one wants to help, particularly<br />
if It Is not due to their own fault.<br />
Q. Very early in the programme you said that and<br />
expanded on it a little. Do you include In that a desire, If it is<br />
possible, to Increase the pensions for the unfortunate people?<br />
to achieve<br />
PM: Well, whatever means can be taken/ the end I have tried<br />
to set out will be taken<br />
Q. What about the thrifty, Sir, who are hit by the means<br />
test? Do you think abolition of the means test is ultimately practical?<br />
PM: I don't see it happening. 0 0YO say " ultimately".<br />
Ultimately is a long time. I see great difficulties in its way, although<br />
as an objective it Is part of the Liberal philosophy, of course. You<br />
remember in England there was a pension payable without regard to<br />
the recipient, and after a while It turned out that it was a small addition<br />
to people who had enough money but It wasn't enough to live on for thcas<br />
who had uo m~ oney at all, so there had to be a supplementary pension<br />
Introduced which was subject to a means test, and this Is the sort of<br />
problem you get Into, particularly as prices do and will rise gradually<br />
year by year. </p>
<p>14<br />
Q. Prime Minister, It has been said that the security<br />
authorities of this country, following the death of Mr Holt, and<br />
perhaps Influenced by the Incident with Mr Caiwell, want the Prime<br />
Minister of this country to have more consistent and constant<br />
security. Is this so, and what are your views on the question of<br />
guarding the country's leader?<br />
PM: I am not quite sure what the view of the Security<br />
authorities Is. I think it Is fair enough to attempt to guard a leader<br />
when he Is walking through crowds or in an election campaign In which<br />
he may be attacked, as on occasions Mr Holt was, but I can tell you<br />
that my own Ideas are that If I couldn't get Into my own car and go for<br />
a drive where I wanted to and visit some friends when I warted to<br />
without someone following me, I would tell the Security people what<br />
they had to do.<br />
Q. No matter how discieet the surveillance?<br />
PK. Yes, I don't like It.<br />
Q. Well, gentlemen, that Is a good point to close on, I<br />
think. You want to be free. You don't want to be watched?<br />
PML. Yes.<br />
Q. That's the freedom you seek and which no doubt you<br />
will. demand if you can get past the the Security boys, and I daresay<br />
the Prime Minister can do lots of things that ordinary people can't<br />
do. If you will forgive me now, I will close on that one and come<br />
back in a moment to thank you.<br />
Well, Mr Prime Minister, in the last week and a bit<br />
you have certainly had your share of television and press Interviews<br />
and I think It can be fairly said by people who don't share your<br />
political philosophy as well as those who do, that you have not<br />
attempted to dodge qiuestions but have been frank when you didn't<br />
know the precise answers, and who can blame you for that after only<br />
a few days in office. And I want to say, from this station's own<br />
point of view, that we are immensely proudto have had you he re within the<br />
first fortnight of your office, and we do want to thank you very, very<br />
sincerely for having come, and believe me, when you said half way<br />
throtgh this programme that you would come here again, we are<br />
going to take you up on it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
