<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9247</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING MP AGREEMENT WITH THE ACTU TO IMPLEMENT ACCORD MARK</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009247.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 48/ 94<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AGREEMENT WITH THE ACTU TO IMPLEMENT ACCORD MARK 7<br />
The Treasurer, Ralph Willis, the Minister for Industrial Relations, Laurie Brereton, and<br />
I met today with the ACTU's Wages Negotiating Committee to discuss the<br />
implementation of Accord Mark 7, " Putting Jobs First".<br />
The Accord partners reaffirmed Accord Mark 7, particularly its objectives of achieving<br />
a minimum of 500,000 net additional jobs over the three years to 1996 and cementing<br />
low inflation as a feature of the Australian economy. The Government proposed, and<br />
the ACTU agreed, that a package involving the two remaining Safety Net Wage<br />
Adjustments in Accord Mark 7 should, in this International Year of the Family, also<br />
incorporate consideration of direct assistance to workers with family responsibilities.<br />
The partners agreed:<br />
to support before the Australian Industrial Relations Commuission second and<br />
third Safety Net Wage Adjustments of $ 8.00 per week not before 1 July 1994<br />
and 1 July 1995 respectively, to be applied where agreement at enterprise level<br />
is not achievable in line with the processes set out in Accord Mark 7.<br />
that there should be a minimum period of 6 months between the first ( already<br />
achieved) and second safety net adjustments and a minimum period of 12<br />
months between the second and third safety net adjustments; and<br />
that for next year's Budget, the Government will have further negotiations with<br />
the ACTU about ways to assist families, and in that context give consideration<br />
to introducing a maternity allowance paid through the Social Security system,<br />
in the spirit of 110 Convention 103 ( Maternity Protection).<br />
This is a landmark agreement in the Accord mould which provides a sure foundation<br />
for sustaining the low inflation recovery in which the essential and characteristic<br />
Australian concerns for social equity continue to be addressed.<br />
A copy of the Agreement concluded today is attached.<br />
CANBERRA I JUNE 1994 </p>
<p>AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE FEDERAL LABOR GOVERNMENT AND<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL<br />
OF TRADE UNIONS REGARDING CONTINUING<br />
IMPLEMENTATION OF ACCORD MARK 7<br />
" PUTTING JOBS FIRST" Canberra, I June 1994<br />
The Accord partners hereby reiterate and reaffirm their shared commnitment to<br />
promoting sustainable job growth and substantially reducing unemployment.<br />
Accord Mark 7 " Putting Jobs First" was agreed in February 1993, to apply for the<br />
period 1993-1996 upon re-election of the Labor Government.<br />
In the Accord tradition " Putting Jobs First" is a comprehensive approach to economic<br />
and social policy, based on co-operation not conflict. Its basic objectives are:<br />
to increase employment by a minimum 500,000 net additional jobs over three<br />
years; to maintain low levels of inflation;<br />
to continue the devolution of wage fixation by encouraging bargaining at<br />
industry and workplace levels involving employees and their unions;<br />
to ensure that all workers are protected by a safety net of minimum award<br />
wages and conditions and have access to arbitration;<br />
to provide access to arbitrated safety net award adjustments;<br />
to increase living standards over time through:<br />
increases in real wages associated with improving productivity and<br />
implementing flexibility at industry and workplace levels consistent with<br />
the objective of low inflation;<br />
further improvements in the social wage, including substantial tax cuts,<br />
child care improvements, education and training;<br />
to provide a solid foundation for a long term retirement policy by improving<br />
the level of employer provided superannuation support in line with the SGC<br />
schedule;<br />
to continue the process of increasing equity in pay and conditions of<br />
employment for women workers;<br />
to give further consideration to measures designed to assist workers with<br />
family responsibilities. </p>
<p>Accord Mark 7 commits the Labor Government to " gearing the policy instruments at<br />
its disposal towards achieving a minimum of 500,000 net additional jobs" over the<br />
three years to 1996. The ACTU considers that the Working Nation package, together<br />
with the federal Budget, Uly reflects that commitment.<br />
With more than 230,000 additional jobs created since February 1993, the Accord<br />
partners agree that the recovery is on track to surpass the minimum target of 500,000<br />
additional jobs.<br />
Moreover, the Training Wage Award, combined with the White Paper package, will<br />
enable Australia to attack directly that hard-core problem of long-term unemployment<br />
in a uniquely Australian way, improving equity in the community and efficiency in the<br />
national economy.<br />
Accord Mark 7 commits the union movement to work towards " wage outcomes which<br />
are consistent with Australia maintaining an inflation rate comparable with those of our<br />
major trading partners". The Labor Government considers that the track record of low<br />
inflation rates achieved in Australia in the early 1990s fully reflects that commitment.<br />
The Accord partners agree that the 1 990s must cement low inflation as a feature of the<br />
Australian economy.<br />
Workplace bargaining is proceeding consistent with the broad Accord framework<br />
subject to the effective safety net provided uniquely in Australia by the award system.<br />
The first safety net wage increase contemplated in Accord Mark 7 has been achieved,<br />
albeit not in the agreed form. The parties remain committed to the process as agreed<br />
in Accord Mark 7, and will support access to the Accord Safety Net Adjustments<br />
( including the first) for all groups unable to reach an enterprise agreement, recognising<br />
there shall be no double counting.<br />
It is appropriate, in view of the continuing economic recovery and continuing<br />
achievement of the Accord's key objectives, that the quantum of the second and third<br />
Safety Net Wage Adjustments now be agreed between the parties, so the matter can be<br />
progressed expeditiously through the Australian Industrial Relations Commission.<br />
The Labor Government has proposed, and the ACTU has agreed, that a package<br />
involving the two remaining Safety Net Adjustments should, in this International Year<br />
of the Family, also incorporate consideration of direct assistance to workers with<br />
family responsibilities.<br />
Such an initiative is envisaged and embraced by Accord Mark 7' s key objectives. It<br />
complements and builds upon other initiatives, namely the significant increase in<br />
payments to low income families and in the number of child care places; the child care<br />
rebate which recognises that the cost of child care as an expense in earning an income;<br />
and the Home Child Care Allowance and Parenting Allowance which redirect<br />
assistance to parents caring for children at home. </p>
<p>3<br />
In agreeing to consider initiatives to directly assist workers with family responsibilities<br />
as part of an Accord package, the Government sought the unions' agreement to Safety<br />
Net Adjustments less than the maximum contemplated in Accord Mark 7. In view of<br />
the low inflation outlook, the ACTU has agreed.<br />
Accordingly: The Accord partners will support before the AIRC second and third Safety Net<br />
Wage Adjustments of $ 8.00 per week not before 1 July 1994 and I July 1995<br />
respectively, to be applied ( consistent with the Accord framework) where<br />
agreement at enterprise level is not achievable in line with the processes set out<br />
in Accord Mark 7, at paragraphs 5.10 5.13;<br />
there should be a minimum period of 6 months between the first and second<br />
safety net adjustments and a mninimum period of 12 months between the second<br />
and third safety net adjustments;<br />
for next year's Budget, the Government will have further negotiations with the<br />
ACTU about ways to assist families, and in that context give consideration to<br />
introducing a maternity allowance paid through the Social Security system, in<br />
the spirit of 110 Convention 103 ( Maternity Protection).<br />
This is a landmark Agreement in the Accord mould which provides a sure foundation<br />
for a sustained low inflation recovery in which the essential and characteristic<br />
Australian concerns for social equity remain in the policy mainstream. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
