<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5606</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY ART EXHIBITION, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/06/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005606.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' p e-4-L<br />
PRIME MINISTER FRIDAY,' 1-9 JUNE, ' 1981<br />
LIBERAL PARTY ART EXHIBITION, SYDNEY<br />
I would like to thank, because I have not been to many<br />
occasions in New.. South Wales since the last Federal Election,'<br />
Bruce McDonald and the State President, and all of those who<br />
worked so hard during a somewhat difficult period; all thos6<br />
people who * proved the polls wrong and led to a magnificent<br />
result in for the Federal Government. So, thank you al.<br />
very much.<br />
It is great to see Sir Kenneth Anderson, former Federal Minister for<br />
Health, because he has worked for the Liberal Party for so long<br />
and with such effect. Ken, good fortune to you and thank you<br />
for being here.<br />
It is a little changed being here, from. the company of the State Premiers I have<br />
been keeping during the course of the day. I owe them some thanks<br />
because at about 7 o'clock tonight I had-to-say to. them, nw.<br />
you know 1 have this commitment in Sydney which is about 6 months<br />
old, but if you want me to stay on for the Premiers' Conference, or<br />
for the Loan Council, I will. So if you want to go on working all<br />
night, I am prepared to, , otherwise I will come back into the whole<br />
of Saturday and all of Sunday, and most of Monday". Well, probably.<br />
most of them felt that there had been enough work done during -the<br />
course of the day. The Loan Council proceedings were over and<br />
finished. So they said, " you had better get on up to Sydney for<br />
the evening". I think probably a few of them had seen too much<br />
ome during the course of the day and were delighted to be<br />
rid of me. But anyway, it was a reasonably successful day in.<br />
terms of the economy of this country. I cannot say anything i~ ore<br />
than that because we are back there tomorrow. -Today's business is<br />
done, but there is more business tomorrow. So, I do not want<br />
to prejudice that.<br />
I would fike to thank all the artists who have their works hung<br />
around the walls today. I did not have a chance to have a look at<br />
all the paintings, but obviously there are some magnificent works<br />
of art and it is good to see. I saw one that I would have been.<br />
sorely tempted to buy, and then I went forwaid and approached it.-<br />
and started to pull off the red sticker that was already there.<br />
I was told I was not allowed to do that. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
One of the great things about the richness of life in Australia<br />
is our artists, our painters, our singers, musicians, the theatre,<br />
the ballet, the opera, and so it goes on. I suppose because of<br />
what we have argued we have had to do over the last five years,<br />
we areoften regarded as just being economic managers with not<br />
much concern for anything else. But in fact, a large part of trying<br />
to run an economy well is so that people will have money to spendon<br />
paintings, so that people will be able to support the opera<br />
and the ballet and all of those things that make the richness<br />
of life in a country.<br />
A large part of trying to run an economy well is so that not only<br />
people will have the resources they want for their own needs, bpt<br />
so that Governments will have the resources to do the things tbnLt<br />
Governments ought to support well. I was happy to be at a dinner<br />
and able to announce a week or so ago that we would be supporting<br />
a new home and a new headquarters for the National Institute of<br />
Dramatic Art, which produced magnificent actors and actresses over<br />
the years but in the most difficult conditions. That again, comes<br />
out of an economy that is better run because it gives us the<br />
resources to do it.<br />
There is a resurgence in the Liberal Party of N. S. W. and<br />
Bruce, I want to congratulate you on what you have already<br />
achieved, and I would like to congratulate you on the way you<br />
are challenging Mr. Wran and making him withdraw from the<br />
challenges. Hopefully there might be many occasions on which<br />
that can be done over the future days and weeks.<br />
I do not under-estimate the task in front-Of Bruc&amp;. It'is a<br />
massive one, because Mr. Wran has had much supporting him. He<br />
has had a honeymoon that has gone on over a long time.<br />
There is a great task, and there is a new heart. I believe that<br />
if people can understand some of the things that Mr. Wran is doing**<br />
that they are going to change their allegiances when the<br />
opportunities are offered. The corruption of the policies of<br />
public funding and the opportunities that opens for the most<br />
improper pressures upon people and individuals and companies, and<br />
tne kind of priorities it exemplifies it is more important to<br />
give money to the Labor Party than to a kindergarten or a chill<br />
care centre or to some other proper purpose. 4ut anyway, Bruce is<br />
in there fighting, on our behalf, for the Liberal Party in this<br />
State, and Bruce good fortune-to y. ou.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
