<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3846</transcript-id>
    <title>THE AUSTRALIA-JAPAN FOUNDATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003846.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J) AUSTRALIA PRESS STATEMENT NO. 543<br />
13 August 1975<br />
THE AUSTRALIA-JAPAN FOUNDATION<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, today announced<br />
that the Government had decided to legislate during the next<br />
session of Parliament for the establishment of an Australia-<br />
Japan Foundation. The objectives of the Foundation will be<br />
to deepen and widen contacts between Australia and Japan in all<br />
fields, including business, academic, cultural, scientific<br />
and the trade unions.<br />
The Pri. e .' inister said that the relationship<br />
bet~ en As---iria 2 J-an was of the highest importance<br />
t oth ccu-. r-ri all readily recognise this importance<br />
in the econcmiz field," said Mr Whitlam. " But there are<br />
wider interests between us which until now have been little<br />
explored or developed. It will be the task of the<br />
Australia-Japan F'undation to assist and encourage wellmotivated<br />
and cc.:: etent Australians and Japanese from all<br />
walks of life to tild knowledge, understanding and goodwill<br />
betw; een the t'-o c..--tries."<br />
The -: fration will promote mutual visits by<br />
selected persons a.-dc also research and comparative studies in<br />
depth of a diverse range of topics embracing but not limited<br />
to the social. institutions of the two countries, the social<br />
and natural scie-ces, industrial and creative arts and the<br />
humanities. rizeri-for assistance by the Foundation will<br />
be based or. crntribution proposals will make to knowledge of<br />
one country i--he other, to filling key gaps in mutual<br />
understanding and to extending the scope for fruitful cooperation<br />
between Australians and Japanese in each country. Those<br />
receiving assis-ance will be competent persons who are already<br />
making a contribution to their own sphere of activity.<br />
The proposed structure and functions of the<br />
Foundation have been under consideration since late last year<br />
by a Committee comprising Mr Kenneth Myer, D. S. C.,<br />
Professor E. S. Crawcour, Mr D. J. Munro, ( Department<br />
of the Prime Minister and Cabinet), and Mr J. R. Rowland<br />
( Department of Foreign Affairs), under the chairmanship<br />
of Sir John Crawford, C. B. E. The Committee's report<br />
recommended that the Foundation should operate as an<br />
independent non-governmental statutory body with an invited / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
national council of not more than 15 members drawn from<br />
key elements of Australian society to give it as wide a base<br />
as possible in the Australian community.<br />
The Prime Minister said that he had foreshadowed<br />
the establishment of -the Foundation during the visit to<br />
Australia last year by the Japanese Prime Minis-ter, Mr Tanaka.<br />
It was a logical next step following on the signature<br />
in Canberra last November of the Australian-Japanese<br />
Cultural Agreement. That Agreement, however, Mr Whitlam<br />
said, was concerned with a range of specific inter-governmental<br />
activities, and there was a need to go beyond it in order<br />
to deepen and strengthen Australia-Japan relations by fostering<br />
better understanding and greater tolerance through people-topeople<br />
contacts in all fields of mutual experience. Only<br />
in this way would each people be able to understand and appreciate<br />
the character, culture and outlook of the other.<br />
For the time being, the Office of the Australia-Japan<br />
Foundation Will1 be centred in the Prime Minister's Department.<br />
-L3EERRA, A. C. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
