<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6682</transcript-id>
    <title>TO THE CITIZENSHIIP CEREMONY IN WOODVILLE, ADELAIDE, 1 AUGUST 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006682.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
TO THE CITIZENSHIP CEREMONY IN WOODVILLE<br />
ADELAIDE 1 AUGUST 1985<br />
Lord Mayor, Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
Thank you for the opportunity to be with you tonight to<br />
participate in this most important ceremony.<br />
Those people who have received citizenship tonight come<br />
from very diverse backgrounds and from every continent<br />
on earth. Their act of commitment has been witnessed by<br />
members of their families, representatives of almost<br />
every ethnic organisation in SI-ith Australia, and by the<br />
community at large.<br />
I congratulate those taking this step. Through this act<br />
of commitment you have t's-e opportunity to become fully<br />
participating members of Australian society. We are<br />
proud to count you now as Australians.<br />
You will be eligible to obtain an Australian passport<br />
and receive the protection that this affords around the<br />
world. Importantly, you will become eligible to vote<br />
and participate in the democratic processes. Maybe some<br />
of you may wish to join the Public Service or stand for<br />
election to State or Federal Parliament. Indeed one of<br />
you may aspire to take over my job as Prime Minister of<br />
this country. All of these avenues are open to you.<br />
You h ave become citizens under the Australian<br />
Citizenship Act an Act which provides the basis for<br />
the citizenship of all Australians regardless of their<br />
oriqgin, culture or linguistic background. Under that<br />
Act people can become citizens by birth in Australia, by<br />
descent through birth of a child tc an Australian parent<br />
living overseas, or by applying to become a citizen anu'<br />
electing to take part in a ceremony such as this one<br />
here tonight. </p>
<p>My Government has taken steps to ensure that the<br />
legislation does not discriminate between persons on the<br />
basis of tneir sex, mar: ital status or present or<br />
previous nationality; we have also provided for review<br />
by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal of decisions to<br />
refuse citizenship under the Act; and are making sure<br />
policy in this area is thoroughly Australian in<br />
character. We aim to encourage new settlers to become<br />
fully participating members of our society as soon as<br />
possible. We have reduced the residential requirement<br />
from 3 to 2 years and have eased the English language<br />
requirement from an adequate to a basic knowledge of<br />
English. From my earliest time of thinking about our ' great<br />
country I have judged much of that greatness, and<br />
potential for greatness, to be associated with our<br />
readiness to open up our land to those who would join us<br />
from other countries.<br />
Australia has been immeasurably enriched by the<br />
contribution of immigrants to our national life. One of<br />
our nation's greatest achievements has been its<br />
acceptance of a wide and diverse range of people,<br />
regardless of race, religion or ethnic background.<br />
The fundamental principle of my Government's migration<br />
-program is that migration should continue to enrich our<br />
lives and bring social, cultural and economic benefits<br />
to our nation.<br />
This will only occur if the program is carefully<br />
designed and well managed.<br />
First of all as a-responsible and humanitarian memPber ' of<br />
the world community, Australia has a 6Iuty to make an<br />
appropriate contribution to the resolution of the world<br />
refugee situation.<br />
Secondly we have obligations to those Australians in our<br />
community who are separated from their immediate family<br />
( that is spouses, dependent children and aged parents,)<br />
and want to bring them here to join the family group.<br />
For the rest, potential migrants must be selected on the<br />
basis of their l* ikely contribution to Australian society<br />
if we are to maximise benefit, aid ou * r economic recovery<br />
and make immigration more acceptable to the Australian<br />
community.<br />
As more than one million people express an interest to<br />
migrate to this country every year we have to make<br />
choices carefully. </p>
<p>~ 1. j Our target level of immigration for 1985/ 86 is about<br />
84,000. At a time of unacceptably high-unemployment<br />
this level would not be responsible if it only added new<br />
migrants to unemployment queues and reduced job<br />
opportunities for the unemployed in Australia.<br />
To avoid this, selection is oriented towards those<br />
applicants most likely to find productive employment in<br />
Australia without competing with the unemployed for<br />
jobs. The increase in migration, therefore, in 1985/ 86 is<br />
focused on the economic categories skilled labour,<br />
employer nominees and business migrants.<br />
I believe that we will be able to increase migration<br />
levels further in the longer term as economic recovery<br />
strengthens, but only if we are selective and ensure<br />
that the program is structured in the short term to be<br />
of maximum benefit to our nation.<br />
I am firmly convinced that a sensitive and carefully<br />
managed migration program of this kind will cointribute<br />
to economic recovery and continue to enrich our society<br />
and our culture.<br />
In this recjprd, my Government believes that it is vital<br />
-that there be specially designed programs for new<br />
arrivals to settle successfully in this country. Since<br />
coming to office we have examined many of the programs<br />
which are provided for new settlers to ensure that they<br />
provide the best possible assistance for those in need.<br />
For instance we have increased the Grant-in-aid scheme<br />
to ethnic community organisations; extended thc a6ult<br />
migrant education program as well as those programs<br />
especially designed for migrant school children, and<br />
boosted the interpreter/ translator services. A review<br />
of all aspects of the adult migrant education program is<br />
now under way.<br />
We have done all this against the background of a keen<br />
appreciation that the commitment to this country our new<br />
citizens are making their full-identification with<br />
this nation imposes obligations and responsibilities<br />
on all of us.<br />
The commitment of citizenship we have witnessed tonight<br />
is important for the health of the nation and is<br />
necessary for full participation in the Australian<br />
community. On behalf of all Australians I welcome you as new<br />
citizens and hope that you are able to contribute as<br />
much to this country as the generations of migrants that<br />
have gone before you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
