<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10204</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP DOORSTOP - PHILLIP STREET SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010204.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME<br />
24 December 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MIP<br />
DOORSTOP PHILLIP STREET<br />
SYDNEY<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Ladies and gentlemen the decision of the High Court in the Wik case is disappointing.<br />
It has not resolved outstanding ambiguities concerning pastoral leases. I will seek<br />
urgent discussions with the State Premiers and Chief Ministers and also representatives<br />
of other interests, the Aboriginal community, miners and pastoralists.<br />
It seems to the Government on a preliminary reading of the majority judgement that it<br />
has overturned certain assumptions on which our response to the native title issue had<br />
been based and certainly on which the approach of the Keating Government had been<br />
based. People will be aware that the preamble to the Native Title Act states that the<br />
grant of a pastoral lease extinguishes native title. The belief then being, and certainly<br />
the belief entertained by my Government, that it so extinguish native title because it<br />
created a right of exclusive possession. Now, those beliefs and assumptions have been<br />
changed by the decision, indeed overturned, by the new decision of the High Court and<br />
as a result I've sought urgent further legal advice from the Attorney-General and that<br />
is underway. It has created a new ball game and we need all of us to reflect very<br />
carefu~ lly as to the consequences of the decision and to recognise that there will need to<br />
be understanding and goodwill from all of the people involved so that the remaining<br />
significant ambiguities and problems can be intelligently addressed. They do need to<br />
be addressed. I don't think anybody greets with any enthusiasm the possibility of<br />
endless years of protracted and complicated litigation which is one of the scenarios that<br />
some of the people responding to the decision believe might occur. And all of us have<br />
a responsibility to ensure that that scenario is not realised.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will there be a Premniers' conference next month then to look at the issue?<br />
' r :-6j 65: 9T 96/ ZL'VZ : WOJJ XV3 </p>
<p>PRIME NMISTER:<br />
I'll talk to the Premiers. The question of how we take it beyond that is premature for<br />
me to talk about. I will certainly talk to all of the Premiers who are interested in this<br />
matter. I've had correspondence from some of them already. I understand their<br />
concern. They have very legitimate concerns, This is a difficult issue for the entire<br />
community and we have to handle it in a way that's fair to all parties. And it's not a<br />
question of takcing sides, it's a question of getting a sensible resolution. But people<br />
have got to understand that we'd all operated on the belief; or in the belief, on the<br />
assumption that pastoral leases did extinguish native title. And the former government<br />
certainly represented to the pastoralists of Australia that that was the case. The<br />
Keating Government told the pastoralists time without number that they didn't have to<br />
worry. Now we find indeed that there is real doubt and ambiguity and the only way in<br />
which, according to the decision of the High Court, the status of individual pastoral<br />
leases can be resolved is not according to some general rule or principle, but on a case<br />
by case basis. Now, that only has to be said for people to realise that that could take<br />
years and years and years. And I can't think of anything worse to the future<br />
investment and development prospects of this country than to have endless years of<br />
litigation regarding the status of pastoral leases and the entitlements of the Aboriginal<br />
community as well as the entitlements of the mining industry and the pastoral industry.<br />
Those three sections of the Australian community have a joint interest in an intelligent<br />
response to this decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could new federal legislation be the key to solving this dilemma?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm not going to, at this stage, pre-empt what the Government will do. I'm stating the<br />
reality and that is that we do have a new ball game as a result of this decision. I'm<br />
seeking fuirther advice. I'm responding to a preliminary reading of the judgement. I'll<br />
talk to the Premiers. I'll talk to the Aboriginal community. I'll talk to the miners and<br />
the pastoralists. They all have an interest, a legitimate interest. I want to hear them all<br />
and I want to respond in a fair fashion. But the ball game has changed because of this<br />
decision and the community should understand that. And it may be necessary to have<br />
responses that are different from what were previously posed, but it is far too early for<br />
me to indicate what those different responses may be.<br />
JOURNALIST: IN&amp; H oward, the Native Title Tribunal suggested that this now opens the way for more<br />
meaningful negotiations between the parties. Are you suggesting that that's not the<br />
way to go, that there should be some clearer legislation instead of negotiations as has<br />
been suggested? 2<br />
z : ad 6S: 9T 96/ Zr/ DZ W'O0JJXJ XVa </p>
<p>PRIME MNISTER:<br />
I'm suggesting that we have a new situation, we have a new ball game and that there<br />
has to be a response developed to the decision of the High Court. I'm not going to<br />
comment on what Mr Justice French said. He is not of course speaking with any<br />
authority other than his position as chairman of the Tribunal. His view on the matter<br />
does not necessarily carry any more or less weight than anybody else's.<br />
JOURNALIST: There's no secret that there will be some dissension between the judges, but were you<br />
surprised with the way it went?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh look, for time in memorial courts have divided, there's nothing new about it. Let's<br />
understand something about the role of the Court in our system. It is the role of the<br />
Hgh Court of Australia to interpret and declare the law as it is at the time of a<br />
particular case brought before it. It is the role of the Parliament of Australia to<br />
legislate and to make the law. I'm not going to comment in any kind of peijorative<br />
way on the decision of the High Court. I, like everybody else, am bound by a decision<br />
of the High Court. And let me make it clear, you won't have any undermining of the<br />
role of the H1igh Court in the Government of this country by me or by any members of<br />
my Government. But I must also point out that it is the role of the Parliament if it<br />
thinks fit to change the law. And I noticed an implication in a comment made by the<br />
Opposition spokesman on Aboriginal Affairs that in some way the High Court's<br />
determination should be regarded as the last word on the matter. Now, the High<br />
Court's determination is the last word on the interpretation of the law as it now stands.<br />
But it's never been part of our system that the High Court makes the law, it's our<br />
system that Parliament makes the law and the High Court declares and interprets it.<br />
JOURNALIST: The CRA mining company says that the High Court decision is unlikely to have any<br />
impact on their projects. Doesn't that suggest that negotiated agreements are in fact<br />
the way to go? ( iaudible)-<br />
PRIE MISTER:<br />
I don't think you can read a general situation into the reaction of a particular company<br />
to that company's particular circumstances. Of course negotiation between parties is<br />
always preferable to litigation and that applies whether you're dealing with Aborigines<br />
and pastoralists or you're dealing with ordinary litigates. I mean, litigation is<br />
murderously expensive in this country. It delays things, it causes investors to lose<br />
interest. And I would always address a request to people to negotiate. The Century<br />
Zinc project has been the subject of protracted negotiation involving both my<br />
Government and the Queensland Government and I would like to see a negotiated<br />
settlement to that particular matter. Negotiation is always better than litigation.<br />
Litigation is rarely something that leaves people other than impoverished. And 3<br />
E 6 jd 65: 9T 96/ ZT/ i'Z NoOijJ AXva </p>
<p>although I am ' very proud of the fact that I'm still a solicitor of the Supreme Court of<br />
New South Wales, I don't want the winners out of native title to be the lawyers, I want<br />
the winners out of native title to be jointly the Aboriginal community, the pastoralists<br />
and the miners and the community generally of Australia. And we have to as a<br />
community, at a government and a non-government level, find a way around the<br />
ambiguities. But let's not kid ourselves. This decision has altered the ball game quite<br />
dramatically and has undercut certain assumptions, certainly on which our pre-election<br />
policy was based and certainly has undercut the assumptions of the former<br />
government. I mean, Mr Keating repeatedly assured the pastoralists of Australia that<br />
the grant of a pastoral lease extinguished native title because it gave a right of<br />
exclusive possession. Well, the High Court has now said, and I accepted it's a<br />
declaration of the law as it now stands, that that is not the case.<br />
JOURNALJIST: Mr Howard, perhaps you'd like to share with us your Christmas message, your first<br />
one as Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MMNSTER:<br />
Well, I would very much like to do that. I'd like, on behalf of my wife and my<br />
children, to wish all Australians a merry Christmas. I hope it's, for all Australians, a<br />
safe Christmas. People should drive very carefully. I know it may sound trite, but it's<br />
not meant to be. Don't celebrate and drive at the same time. It really is a very unwise<br />
thing for people to do because I don't want the family and personal enjoyment of<br />
Christmas to be blinded for any Australians by tragedies on the road or elsewhere.<br />
Christmas is for most Australians a time of comfort and enjoyment and celebration.<br />
But for some of our fellow Australians it is a time of difficulty and sadness. And I<br />
would like all of those who can afford to do so to dig into their pockets and give<br />
generously to those tremendous organisations like the Salvation Army and the St<br />
Vincent De Paul Society who look after the less privileged people. And the other<br />
thing that I think we ought to do at a time like this is to remember the tremendous<br />
assets that we have as a nation; our tolerance and our decency towards each other and<br />
the fact that we have an enviable reputation around the world for being a very free and<br />
open and welcoming people. And of course finally and certainly not least importantly,<br />
Christmas is a time for many millions of Australians of spiritual renewal because the<br />
Christmas story is the source of a lot of the spiritual strength to many millions of<br />
Australians. JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, what's Santa bringing you for Christmas?<br />
PRIE AMISTER:<br />
Well, I'm very, very happy to spend it with my family and some friends. And I hope<br />
that all Australians who wish to do likewise can have an equally enjoyable time.<br />
Thank you. 4<br />
1, ad 65: 9T 96/ ZT/" Z UO0JJXJJ XVJ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
