<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6498</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH DERRYN HINCH, 3AW </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006498.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>OCTOBER 9 1984</strong></p>
<p><strong>DH: </strong> On the issue of early elections would you give a guarantee now that if you win in December as is expected, your next government would go its full term?</p>
<p><strong>PM:</strong> Yes particularly in the light-Derryn of what I have been saying is that, we are not just having this early election that you keep referring to, what I am doing is saving the people of Australia an extra election. Now I want to come fully to answer your question. But whats got to be understood is that under the constitution, we have to have by April next, an election for the Senate. We must do that under the Constitution. Therefore what I am doing is to save the people an extra election, that you would have to have after that if the House of Representatives went on instead of two elections which wiil cost, which would have cost $ 49million I'm bringing the 2 together at a cost of 30 million.</p>
<p>By having the House of Representatives and the h Senate election together that will be the 23rd time that this has been done in our<br />history, but in doing that I am also putting to the people a referendum and this distinguishes me from what has happened in the past, I'm<br />saying to people here's a referendum, I'm asking you to vote for<br />simultaneous elections so that no' Prime Minister in the future will<br />be able to throw the electoral cycle out of kiltre by causing<br />unnecessary early elections. If the people support that referendum it will mean that a Prime Ministek will know that he will have to<br />take the Senate out with him. Thre will be no advantage in<br />trying to break the cycle. He woh't be able to do it under the<br />constitution. So I think that the Australian People are now<br />for the first time being given tho opportunity of unequivocably<br />getting this thing sorted out for all time int he future<br />t i</p>
<p><strong>DH</strong> Is it totally altruistic, or is it also because you feel that this is a good time to maximise your chances?</p>
<p><strong>PM</strong> We'd be in as good or better shape next year, but it is the case that the normal pattern of having the half senate election has been at the end of the preceding year. It has normally been held at this sort of period and iA this case I have gone as early as we can under the new laws and part of my reason for going early<br />is that the business community, many of them, have made representations<br />to me, they say, we know there needs to be an early election we<br />are saying to you go as early as possible because they say to me,<br />I. I<br />and it is interesting Derryn just how widely this view is put by<br />business, that the thread of an election hanging in the air by having<br />S it very late in the year or early [ in the new year, they say disrupts<br />S the Christmas retail trade so get it out of the way December the first<br />is as soon as we can have it, it Its there, it is done, and particularly<br />S if the Australian people will votj for the referendum, simultaneous<br />S elections, then we can look forward to future stability,. particularly<br />i<br />S stability. DH Malcolm Fraser used to talk about calling an election to<br />i<br />end the speculation which he had started and on this election your<br />speculation, personally seemed to start about last Christmas.<br />PM It was not speculation it was... I don't know what I can do<br />i<br />to satisfy you I didn't speculate, I said this is what we are going<br />to do. I'll tell the people not at the last minate, I've said I'll<br />v tell you as soon as possible so that the business community<br />more.... i i</p>
<p>S cont<br />electorate can know. Now I don't. know how you can ever be<br />satisfied I mean you are saying t4at I fuel speculation, I said<br />early this is what is going to happen, I won't hang around until<br />the last minute Mr Fraser did, and just spring it. Close the role<br />so that thousands and thousands of people couldn't get on the role<br />DH Thats true<br />PM We've had a campaign to jrge people to get on the role.<br />This is the thing which distinguishes us from all our predecessors.<br />We want everyone to have the opportunity to know there is going to<br />be an election not only get it out of the way but importantly for<br />the future to say now you are not going to have unnecessary elections<br />foisted on you in the future.<br />DH Are you concerned or embarrassed, perhaps by the fact that<br />while you have got an election carpaign now virtually underway<br />you have still got a Senate committee hearing the Justice Murphy<br />affair material, youv'e got the Ccstigan report to be tabled, these<br />things can/ will end up perhaps getting involved as election issues.</p>
<p><strong>PM:  </strong>No, not only not embarrassed, but quite positive about them. I've made it clear and I think yoq accept, I've got no reason to<br />believe that you don't that I have said in respect of what ever<br />investigations going on into any issue or any people, I've said<br />and I mean it let the cards fall ihere they may. I'm not in the<br />business of protecting anyone or any interests and that is my<br />position as far as the Costigan Commission report is concerned<br />I will ensure that that report is published as fully as it can be<br />on the basis of the advice from Mr Costigan himself, from the<br />National Crimes Authority, from te director of public prosecutions<br />more i" i<br />. N g. C;</p>
<p>4.... cont<br />from the head of the Australian Federal Police and from the<br />Attorney General's department. T) ey will all advise on what paths<br />should not be published so that p osecution will not be prejudiced<br />or the rights of individuals prejudiced and on the basis only of<br />their recommendations as to what Shouldn't be published I'll<br />see that the whole of the report is published. I've got nothing<br />to fear from it, the Government has nothing to fear from it, on<br />the contrary.<br />DH Would this be published bdfore the election?<br />PM Of course it will be.<br />DH The president of the ALP Ar Wran, his name is coming up in<br />evidence that Senate Committee enquiry, does that cause you some<br />embarrassment with an election coning up?<br />PM On the contrary, I have scid, I repeat on your programme,<br />that I have no evidence at all anq have not had at any stage, any<br />evidence which establishes any impropriety on the part of Mr Wran<br />and I don't know about you but I m never going to be part of the<br />process of smear, and innuendo and guilt by allegation that is<br />an extraordinary danger in our society. I'd never been one to<br />run away from friends or colleeues on the basis that they are being<br />smeared, or allegations are being made against them. Now there is<br />nothing at all of any evidence of any impropriety on Mr Wran's part<br />and any-one should be very careful of making any allegations against<br />him. DH agree with that, but he has, Mr Wran has made some, what<br />I would consider to be extraordinary and dangerous comments for<br />a Premier over the possible future of Mr Briese the chief stipendiary<br />magistrate in NSW who is currently under oath at a Senate. committee<br />Smore 4</p>
<p>cont<br />hearing. i<br />PM Derryn, there can be obviously arguments as to whether that<br />was a wise thing for Mr Wran to say. But I have been concerned.<br />to go to the wider point, people hafve grabbed hold of that and then<br />used it as a peg to make general allegations against Mr Wran. Thats<br />i.<br />what I'm not going to be in. I accept that there can be legitimate<br />arguments as to whether that was A wise thing to say.<br />DH I saw you on the Willese9 prqgram last night. Mike Willesee<br />raised the questions about your family and I think you said<br />something along the lines about them being perhaps being, part of an<br />election campaign argument of som4 sort and you said only disreputable<br />people would raise those questions and would get involved in those<br />questions. Is that right<br />Oh I don't remember my exa~ t words Mike did go to it. I'e<br />said that I believe that the events of recent weeks have once again<br />confirmed the continuing faith which I have had in the wisdom and<br />good judgement of the Australian 4lectorate. They don't like the<br />process of smear and allegation, personalisation of issues, they've<br />made that quite clear. Couldn't Iave made it clearer. I said in S.<br />respect of that issue that the children of non public figures Who<br />have suffered these particular softs of tragedies the attitude<br />of the community is that the major issue is to see how these unfortunate<br />people should be able to be rehabIlitated, get away from their<br />t rI<br />problem. That's what the attitud' of the community is. I think<br />rightly so.<br />DH With respect Prime Minister, I think that oneof the attitudes<br />of the community as well and followed by calls on programs such<br />as mine and mail we have received'is that the community, a large<br />more i k</p>
<p>6 cont<br />number of the community also feel' that it was a legitimate<br />question to ask you as Prime tMinipter where your daughter got<br />the money for her drug addiction hnd for how long she had that<br />drug addiction?<br />PM Well you can say that that is legitimate., I have made<br />the point publicly when that quesr-ion has been raised or alluded to<br />that as far as we are concerned it the police.., if the law<br />enforcement agencies have any questions that they want to direct<br />to anyone in the family then that what shoul~ d happen and thats<br />where it stands.<br />DH Have the police not asked'; you any questions?<br />PM No and let me say this, I~ am not going to subject my family<br />or myself to interrogation by you'or by anyone other than the police.<br />Its a matter for the police, its', their decision if they want to<br />ask these questions and thats for'them.<br />OH Were you tempted, I'm sure, you were, as a father to go<br />after the pushers, the scum of th earth who supplied the drugs to<br />your daughter?<br />PM Look, I think I have made: it clear, and I don't want to have<br />either my intelligence or the int~ lligence of your listeners insulted<br />by suggesting that I haven't got he deepest revulsi6n against those<br />engaged in drug trafficking. 1 s4id in a press conference that I<br />find it hard to control my ration4lity when I think about people<br />who profit from this trade, now. ti~ ats quite clear. I'm not goi~ ng<br />to go into some detailed exaninat on of what the feeling is that<br />I have about these people,<br />more.... 4~ I *. A<br />-~ iNO.</p>
<p>DH I admit I don't like having ito ask these questions.<br />P. M You say you don't like it D! rryn, I'm not going to get<br />into a question of what you like or ' don't like doing. You've<br />made your judgements about how you conduct yourself. Thats<br />for you. All I'm saying to you is # hat I'm not going to assist<br />your processes of examination of my. ifeelings about these things.<br />What my attitude is, is clear, it is the same as any parents would<br />be. One of total repugnance. I relard it quite frankly as<br />an insult to my intellcgence and fkankly to the' intelligence of<br />your listeners that there should be any -implication that I have<br />other than total repugnance of people engaged in the drug scene.<br />DH I don't make that inferrencb at all.<br />PM I don't care whether you want to go on and say you do<br />or do not want to make an inference. I am simply saying to you its I<br />i<br />a matter for Derryn Hinch's judgement what he does about disclosures,<br />what he does about prying into people's feelings, but all I'm saying<br />to you is that I'm not going to assist you for whatever reasons you<br />have in your mind about trying to probe my feelings about this.<br />My feelings are manifest and well known, I'd leave it at that.<br />DR Were you aware Mr Prime Minrister of Mr Costigan's family<br />problems? PM Not directly, no I wasn't. But I became aware after your<br />episode. That knowledge was in thq hands of a number of people in<br />the media who took a different view to you.<br />Doesn't it just show<br />PM Let me just say to you... ! I'm not going to be involved in<br />an analysis of your action, why yov did what you did, that's a matter<br />for you, a matter for judgement by others as to whether it was<br />appropriate. I simply say to you And I think you ought to know<br />that when I say something I mean i I am not going to get further<br />involved in an analysis of what you have done about this or not.<br />more SI</p>
<p>8 cont<br />That's for others to make their judgement. I'm not pursuing this<br />S matter any further down the track.<br />S DH Well I think, it sounds like you have made your judgement.<br />PM I may or may not have made my judgement. But I don't want<br />to intrude that judgement into the issue, because I happen to think<br />that 99% of the Australian people now that we are into an election<br />want to talk about other issues as to whether Derryn Hinch did<br />or not do the right thing in this isue. I<br /><strong>DH</strong> That wasn't the point I was trying to lead you to. The point I was trying to ask you...</p>
<p><strong>PM</strong> Derryn, what you may or may: not be trying to lead me to,ø</p>
<p>all I can go on is the area on which you have now spent a great deal.<br />of time on. I am not going to talk' any more about personal problems<br />that exist in my family or in Mr Costigan's family or Derryn Hinch's<br />actions in these matters. Now I am not going to talk anymore about<br />it it. i</p>
<p><strong>DH </strong>Right Mr Prime Minister. What do you see, a totally separate issue, as the main issue of the camipaign that will get you re-elected?</p>
<p><strong>PM </strong>Well it is quite clear, and that is that the Australian people<br />in this election are faced with alternatives. They are faced with<br />going back to what they had at the beginning of ' 83 the policies which<br />produced the disaster that was Ausiralia at the end of 7 years of i<br />government which Mr Peacock was a; leading minister of for nearly<br />the whole time, of which Mr Howard and Mr Sinclair were leading ministers.<br />Their policies produced the most divided and divisive and economically<br />SI<br />stagnant Australia since the depression, I promised Australia a<br />better course, I said, I offer National reconc: iliation and on that<br />basis, economic recovery. We have' produced that in auspectacularly<br />S' successful way thats the issue.<br />more 1<br />V y w , o r . T d.</p>
<p><strong>D H </strong>Does it worry you that some people who voted for you last<br />S time round will fall by the way-side this time, over such things<br />BSa s the uranium issue or things like; that.</p>
<p><strong>PM </strong>Well I can go on if you are talking about" some people will<br />fall by the wayside" if you want to say " some people will fall by<br />the wayside" all I can say is that comparing the election in March' 83<br />with today, it is clear that we havo a greater level of support now<br />than we had then. So we may have lpPst some, we seem to have gained<br />more.</p>
<p>DH Will you concentrate much of your campaign in Victoria? Where there is apparently the most narginal seats?</p>
<p>PM Oh Victoria is the second largest state with the second<br />largest number of seats and any political leader who didn't pay<br />a great deal of attention to Victoria would be quite stupid. Whatever<br />I may be I'm not stupid.</p>
<p>DH True, that is quite true. fr Prime Minister, I know you haven't got any more time, I thank you for your time, and I presume we will talk again in the campaign. i</p>
<p>PM Certainly Derryn</p>
<p>ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
