<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1845</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M .NO 58/1968  THE LODGE PREPARES FOR EXPRESSWAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/05/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001845.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 58/ 19 89<br />
THE LODGE PREPARES FOR EXPRESSWAY<br />
Preliminary surveying began around the Lodge in Canberra<br />
today in preparation for the widening of Adelaide Avenue.<br />
The roadwork, which is necessary to complete a dual<br />
highway lining Canklerra with new suburbs in the Woden Valley, will<br />
extend into a large section of the large gardens. The Prime Minister,<br />
Mr. Gorton, gave authority for the acquisition of the land so that there<br />
would be no delay in the expressway project, which will convert the<br />
present two-lane roadway into a six-lane highway. The four additional<br />
lanes will run through what is now part of the Lodge grounds.<br />
Work will begin later this month on the foundations of a<br />
new boundary wall to be bailt around the Adelaide Avenue and National<br />
Circuit frontages of the Lodge. The wall will be off-white in colour,<br />
seven feet high and has been specially designed. to act as a baffle to<br />
traffic noise. National Capital Development Commission architects<br />
have given close attention to the design and finish of the wall to ensure<br />
that it blends into the parkland setting.<br />
The main entrance to the Lodge from Adelaide Avenue<br />
will be resited to facilitate ease of access from the expressway. Because<br />
of the re-arrangements of traffic flow, this will be an entrance only. The<br />
gateway in National Circuit will be widened and will be the only exit for<br />
vehicles. To minimise inconvenience, the NCDC will start clearing<br />
and excavating during the Prime Minister ' s absence overseas at the end<br />
of this month.. The wall and associated work on the boundaries will<br />
take about six weeks to complete.<br />
CANBERRA 8 May 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
