<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11026</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM                 NIGHTLINE, CHANNEL NINE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>On coastal security, Defence Minister, John Moore, says Premiers Richard</p>
<p> Court and Peter Beattie have been making these issues up for parochial</p>
<p> political advantage, do you agree with that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they certainly have been scoring the odd political point, as</p>
<p> State Premiers always will...</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But they weren't making these boats up.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No and he didn't say that. And we're very serious about</p>
<p> examining whether our coastal surveillance arrangements at present</p>
<p> are adequate and that's why I've set up this very high level</p>
<p> task force. And that will report within six weeks or two months and</p>
<p> it will have the factual information arising out of both the Cairns</p>
<p> and Coffs Harbour landings to help it.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And when Peter Beattie says your Government is out of touch with the</p>
<p> urgent need for coastal security, Australians will "puke"</p>
<p> when they see you've called another inquiry.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's typical of State Premiers where they feel they can</p>
<p> kick the Federal Government to the sort of transient political advantage.</p>
<p> I don't remember Mr Beattie, the day before the landing at Coffs</p>
<p> Harbour when I spent the whole day with him, saying anything about</p>
<p> coastal surveillance.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But 15 boats so far this year with more than 250 people on board,</p>
<p> it is a serious matter - quarantine, risk of disease, all sorts of</p>
<p> things.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Paul, I'm treating it very seriously. And we have to be realistic</p>
<p> about what can be achieved. But I assure the Australian people that</p>
<p> we'll leave no stone unturned to give ourselves the best surveillance</p>
<p> system that we can afford.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>The two CARE Australia aid workers being held by the Yugoslavs, are</p>
<p> you completely satisfied that neither of them was working for western</p>
<p> intelligence?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the Foreign Minister dealt with that question yesterday and</p>
<p> I totally endorse everything he said in relation to that. And I ask</p>
<p> again that the authorities in Belgrade let them go. They're not</p>
<p> combatants. They don't come from combatant countries. They were</p>
<p> there on a humanitarian mission. And according to all of the normal</p>
<p> canons of civilised behaviour between nations they ought to be released.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But they're caught now in an international powerplay, aren't</p>
<p> they? They're effectively pawns in a very dark and dangerous</p>
<p> game.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, if that be the case, that is a reflection on Slobodan Milosevic</p>
<p> and the Belgrade Government. It is not a reflection on them. I want</p>
<p> the families of the two men to know that we have every diplomatic</p>
<p> and other resource that we can muster gathered to try and get them</p>
<p> out. We share their concern. We understand the anguish they must be</p>
<p> going through and I think all Australians feel for them very deeply.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Back home  do you see a link between Senator Harradine's</p>
<p> renewed call for youth allowance compensation and his vote on the</p>
<p> GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they're questions that should be directed towards Senator</p>
<p> Harradine. We naturally want his vote on the GST...</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>He wants about $100 million of your money in the May budget.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not going to talk about what's in the budget.</p>
<p> And I'm certainly not going to publicly canvass Senator Harradine's</p>
<p> motives. I've always found him a decent, reasonable man. I hope</p>
<p> he takes the view, as he should, that as the Australian people voted</p>
<p> for the GST then the Senate ought to put it through. And now you've</p>
<p> got all the States and the Territories backing the GST. You've</p>
<p> got three Labor, three Liberal Premiers all saying get on with it,</p>
<p> pass the GST. They're all happy with it. The Tasmanian Premier,</p>
<p> Senator Harradine's own State, said that he came away happy because</p>
<p> he got a good deal from the Commonwealth. Peter Beattie, Bob Carr,</p>
<p> positively lyrical about the benefits of a GST. Now, this is a message</p>
<p> going to the entire Senate: get on with it, do the will of the Australian</p>
<p> people.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>You're waiting until the end of the month for the critiques of</p>
<p> the John Howard/Les Murray preamble. Do you concede that at this early</p>
<p> stage you don't seem to have a hit on your hands?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I never concede anything in these things. They have a long winding</p>
<p> experience these things, and I've put it out for comment and</p>
<p> I'm getting a few. I'll get some alternatives...</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Most of the Premiers don't like it, and I notice Mr Murray's</p>
<p> had another go at it. He says your first joint effort was rather "baggy"</p>
<p> whatever that really means.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know what that means either. Paul, look, this is the</p>
<p> first time in a hundred years anybody has tried this, and never did</p>
<p> I think it was going to be universally accepted. Of course not. I'll</p>
<p> have a look at what people put up. I've asked the Premiers to</p>
<p> give me their responses. Some of them will give it in verse, some</p>
<p> of them will....</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>We could have the Jeff Kennett/Peter Beattie version?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You might have the first verse written by one and the second by another.</p>
<p> But we'll have all of those and I'll have a look at it all,</p>
<p> and I'm a reasonable man.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Finally, Victorian Premier Jeff Kennett says your Government is giving</p>
<p> quite serious consideration to buying a substantial property in East</p>
<p> Melbourne as a Prime Ministerial residence. Is this true?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it is not. There won't be any money made available to buy</p>
<p> further Prime Ministerial residences while I hold that job.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But if say a Prime Minister Costello were to be in office, he could</p>
<p> buy something in East Melbourne...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you can hypothesise about possible successors of mine, you can</p>
<p> hypothesise about what they might do. I'm just speaking for the</p>
<p> Howard Government. There are two residences, the Lodge and Kirribilli</p>
<p> House. I can say to the Australian people, I have got far more important</p>
<p> priorities with their money than to buy further houses for the Prime</p>
<p> Minister.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Thanks for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
