<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2516</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA DAY 1972 - MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002516.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E0T0AB0R1( 0 : h ours 26/ 1/ 72<br />
FOR PRESS: PM No 6/ 1972<br />
AUSTRALIA DAY 1972<br />
Message from the Prime M4inister, r.! Wr illiam Mc! 1ahon<br />
Australia Day is our own National Day. it is a day for<br />
Wreflection. A day when we should forget we live in States, cities<br />
and towns, and remember we are all citizens of one great nation,<br />
recognising no frontiers other -than the seas around us.<br />
In defying and defeating the worst floods, fires and<br />
droughts and winning the best from the seas, soil, iron ore<br />
mountains and our factories we have built a wonderful country<br />
for ourselves and our heirs.<br />
On thi-" s day we acknowledge with pride the successes of<br />
our forebears for whom few difficulties have been too great. Their<br />
spirit, I believe, remains with us in tChis busy, bustling technological<br />
age where we cannot yet presume to say " We have crossed our<br />
last frontier". As a nation where pioneering is part of the present as<br />
Swell as the past, we are strong, vigorous and growing. Few other<br />
countries are better equipped to face the future and exploit the<br />
ever-growing opportuhities. History supports this view and the<br />
future will confirm it.<br />
There is still much to be done. We should remember, too,<br />
that the immediate problems of the day are transitory. lie must not<br />
let them dampen our enthusiasm, or destroy our confidence in the<br />
future.<br />
Canberra 26 January 1972<br />
EMBARGO: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
