<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9607</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO 3LO, 1 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009607.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH DOUG AITON, RADIO 31-0, 1 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
DA: Mr Keating good afternoon.<br />
PM: How are you Doug?<br />
DA: Very well indeed, thank you. I can smell an election in the air.<br />
PM: Well you have got too good a nose, Doug.<br />
DA: Have I?<br />
PM: You have indeed.<br />
DA: Do you think that I am wrong in thinking that we are now into mild<br />
election mode?<br />
PM: Oh, y ou are indeed. I mean the Government brought down a serious<br />
Budget, I would say a sober Budget, to deal with the economic<br />
circumstances we faced. To get the Budget back into surplus to make<br />
this adjustment and it was greeted as, you know, an election Budget<br />
and the rest. That was the media's way of saying look this has really<br />
been a pretty good Budget. So good that they thought the<br />
Government could go to a poll on it. That doesn't mean that the<br />
Government thinks about it as being anything other than simply a<br />
serious policy change from which we can now carry on and see the<br />
economy go on to the sustainable level, which we saw in yesterday's<br />
National Accounts, 3.7 per cent for the year.<br />
DA: Well we do know, though, that the election at its latest, I think, will be<br />
in the early months of next year, won't it?<br />
PM: The full Parliament runs to about March next year, it is something of<br />
that order. </p>
<p>DA: Are you yet prepared to give us any indication as to when you are<br />
thinking of for an election?<br />
PM: Well, I must say, one of the happy elements of incumbency in this<br />
arrangement, Doug, is that in the Australian political system, there is a<br />
discretion in the Prime Minister as to when the elections can be held<br />
and none of them have been silly enough to give that away and I don't<br />
think I will be the first.<br />
DA: No, I don't expect you to be. But you can't blame me for trying.<br />
PM: Oh, no, no, go for your life.<br />
DA: I think also that one of the things that is taking our attention at the<br />
moment, the voters of Australia, is what are we going to be voting<br />
about. People are thinking in election mode, whether or not you can<br />
tell us when. I would suggest that what I hear most of all is that the<br />
gap between the rich and the poor is increasing. Now I am not all that<br />
sure that that's the case. I'd prefer to say that the number of rich is<br />
increasing and the number of poor is increasing and unemployment<br />
doesn't change much and it seems to me that you being the<br />
Prime Minister, that is the mood that you're going to face in an election<br />
campaign.<br />
PM: Well that may be right, but it is the wrong mood. You know we have<br />
now had 1.9 million jobs since the Government was elected in 1983<br />
and we have had, since the election, 630,000 jobs. Now if you go<br />
back to that election, Doug, the principal commitment that the<br />
Government made in that election was to restore growth to the<br />
economy and employment ard we have had now a 6 per cent and a<br />
per cent growth economy and now it is slowing to a rate sustainable<br />
at about 4 per cent, roughly, and we have had 630,000 jobs since the<br />
election, or 400,000 in the last year. So it is a much more fully<br />
employed country. I think only the United States is up with us in terms<br />
of employment growth.<br />
DA: Where does that put us in percentage terms as to the number of<br />
unemployed, the slice of the cake who are unemployed?<br />
PM: Well that is down to about, I think, 8.4 per cent. But can I say to you<br />
that is off a massive participation rate. I mean we have now got many<br />
more people looking for work. You see the unemployment rate is a<br />
proportion of those looking for work, the participation in the labour<br />
market. If we had the participation rate that John Howard left me in<br />
1983, we'd have unemployment I think around 5 to 6 per cent. If we<br />
we're comparing apples with apples. </p>
<p>DA: Yes I do. But is this the sort of figure that you would have hoped to<br />
have for unemployment? At the time of the last election, is this the sort<br />
of figure you would have hoped to have in June 1995?<br />
PM: I couldn't have hoped for anything like this because this is the largest<br />
fall in unemployment since we have been keeping the records. The<br />
last twelve months is the largest fall in unemployment since we were<br />
keeping the records. So we have gone from 10.7 per cent<br />
unemployment at the time of the election to now 8.4 per cent. That is<br />
a massive fall and picking up, of course, all those school leavers. See<br />
to get unemployment down, Doug, you have got to pick up all the<br />
people joining the labour market, as well as those in unemployment.<br />
And one of the happy things about this is we now have got a quarter of<br />
those jobs have gone to the long term unemployed, which shows that<br />
that policy statement Working, Nation is out there working to get the<br />
most disadvantaged people back-to work, whereas in the 80s we<br />
wouldn't have got anything like that number.<br />
DA: Well what do you see as the battles that you are going to fight the<br />
election on?<br />
PM: Well let me just say a couple of things about this question about,<br />
you know, how people are going because I know that Peter Costello is<br />
running around in the last day or so talking about battlers. I mean<br />
someone in the Liberal Party's advertising agency has given them a<br />
line about battlers. They said, " yes just keeping this line". So they are<br />
cynical. He said, " Australians are as poor as they have ever been", he<br />
said today on radio. Now let me just give the lie to that little claim and<br />
just tell you this. That the best measure of average living standards in<br />
Australia is real household disposable income because it includes<br />
wages and salaries, and supplements such as overtime, pensions,<br />
social security benefits and it is per person and it is after tax. So, I<br />
mean, it is the best measure. We have had a 40 per cent increase in<br />
household disposable income since 1983. In other words, a huge<br />
increase in disposable . incomfe since 1983 and if we take that per<br />
person, it was 19.8 per cent per person since 1983 and if we take the<br />
per person rate during the seven years of Coalition Government it was<br />
2.1 per cent. So we have had nearly as much growth in household<br />
disposable income per year as the Coalition had in seven years. So<br />
can I just make that point, therefore, that if you take that measure of<br />
wages, salaries, supplements, pensions, benefits, after tax and per<br />
person, household disposable income has risen by 40 per cent.<br />
DA: And you are making the point that Peter Costello and John Howard are<br />
saying that the battlers are turning to the Liberal Party.<br />
PM: Well I mean this is the stuff they get from the advertising. This is the<br />
Dollar Sweets man. This is from Peter Costello who went into the<br />
industrial arbitration system and argued in 1986 at the National Wage<br />
Case for a reduction in all award wages to $ 25 below the lowest award </p>
<p>rate then applying. This is the same crowd who say they wanted $ 3 an<br />
hour for teenage battlers. No award protection for adult battlers. For<br />
unemployed battlers they were going to kick them off the dole after<br />
nine months and for retiring battlers they want to knock off the<br />
Government's superannuation scheme. I mean they are unbelievably<br />
hypocritical.<br />
DA: How are you finding facing up to John Howard? It seems to me that<br />
they have put up against you, at last, someone who can match you in<br />
debating style.<br />
PM: Well they put him up against me and Hawke in 1985 to 1989 and it<br />
didn't do him much good then.<br />
DA: But you weren't both leaders then.<br />
PM: No, I know. But, I mean, in the end I had the job of blowing the<br />
Box Hill tax package apart in 1987 for John Howard. Look the thing<br />
about John Howard is he has only ever had three views in twenty<br />
years of public life. One is what he calls proper deregulation of the<br />
labour market, that is taking away the award underpinnings. Letting<br />
the whole lot fall out, particularly against the lowest paid. Kicking<br />
family benefits to the highest income earners and putting in a GST.<br />
They're the three general lines he has pushed in twenty years. So<br />
what I say about John is this. I have just come back from Japan. We<br />
have probably got now the best set of bilateral relationships with Asia<br />
we have ever had. We have got the most advantageous multilateral<br />
arrangements in things like ApEC. We are making the linkage to Asia<br />
as never before. We have got an open deregulated economy.<br />
We have got very low inflation in yesterday's National Accounts.<br />
When you compare where the Government is and where Australia is<br />
going, compared to somebody who has 1970s views coming from what<br />
he thinks are the rosy years in the 1950s, for Australia to step back<br />
down in that time tunnel and accept those views when we now have a<br />
much more dynamic buoyant economy, is I just don't think a<br />
proposition for people.<br />
DA: There was a time about ten years or so ago when you were Treasurer<br />
and he had been Treasurer where you and he seemed to have a<br />
certain personal regard for each other. That seems to have<br />
completely and totally evaporated.<br />
PM: No. I'd just make this point. There can be no honesty or credibility in<br />
politics without policies. And when John Howard runs around saying " I<br />
won't show that Prime Minister my policies". What he is really saying<br />
is " I won't show Doug Aiton, his listeners, or the Australian public my<br />
policies". I mean what he is really saying is " I am so monkey cunning<br />
and so tricky, they won't see the colour of my policies until it is too late<br />
for them". Now I think this is the sort of Liberal Party 50s, you know,<br />
" they are coming down to get us in their sampans, there are reds </p>
<p>under beds, the Indonesians are about to overtake us". That sort of<br />
cynicism is no longer a stock in trade of Australia in the 1990s.<br />
DA: Talking about your accusation of John Howard coming from the 1970s<br />
and inspired by the 1950s. Do you think that the Republic is going to<br />
be an issue in this election campaign, whenever it might be?<br />
PM: Yes, because there can be no complete expression of Australian<br />
independence and sovereignty while ever we are borrowing the<br />
monarchy of another country. So I go to Japan and say " here I am<br />
representing a country which is completely independent, proud of its<br />
culture, proud of its traditions, proud of its new role in the world.<br />
But, by the way, our head of state is the Queen of Great Britain."<br />
DA: I think that the pro-Republic argument seems to have stalked a little<br />
and I emphasise thie word stalled for one reason: the pro-republic<br />
people, even many of them are saying " but what sort of a republic<br />
do we want", and no-one has yet come up with the complete definite<br />
answer to that, and the Monarchists are making merry with that.<br />
PM: Let me tell you Doug, I'll make an announcement on your program,<br />
at 7.3Opm on next Wednesday night, I am responding in detail to the<br />
Republican Advisory Committee report, and giving the Government's<br />
policy on the republic, and it will probably be telecast on the ABC.<br />
DA: And in that you will be saying exactly what style of republic you will<br />
be pushing for?<br />
PM: What style of republic, the shape and nature of it, and why we<br />
believe it should be that shape. But let me just say, the republic<br />
debate was a mints and coffee debate after dinner until the<br />
Government took this up in the 1993 election. You know, people<br />
talked about the republican movement, and I am glad to have them<br />
there, but they weren't cutting any weight before a major political<br />
party picked this issue up. But again, because it is an issue that is<br />
going to matter to Australia now, in the future forever, it's incumbent<br />
upon us to think it through and get it right. So, I would rather<br />
respond after due consideration, than rush into it to keep<br />
enthusiastic supporters no matter how enthusiastic or helpful they<br />
may otherwise be to get this right.<br />
DA: Is it a driving motivation of yours that you would like to be<br />
remembered as the Prime minister who took us into being a<br />
republic?<br />
PM: I would like to be remembered Doug, as a person who had complete<br />
faith in the nation we have become. Australians who have made<br />
their own way in the world, who have changed in this generation<br />
probably as no other generation has changed before it, who have<br />
accepted the economic changes as never before, who have made </p>
<p>the connection and the leap into Asia as never before, who have<br />
found themselves at home in this part of the world, and who are now<br />
living in an interesting, dynamic, multicultural society. That's what I<br />
am interested in, and I don't think that can be reflected while ever we<br />
have the Sovereign of Great Britain as our Head of State.<br />
DA: Would you consider yourself to be a failure if you don't get us to be a<br />
republic before your Prime Ministership ends?<br />
PM: No. If you take a measure of my political life, it has been trying to<br />
international ise the Australian economy, and to not only to change<br />
structures here at home, but build structures abroad for Australia,<br />
and I was doing that just last week in Japan.<br />
DA: One other matter that is going to be brought up by the Opposition,<br />
and they also find the Australian people often seem to talk about<br />
against you, is what we might call Paul Keating's forceful, personal<br />
insults towards the Opposition, made usually in the Parliament.<br />
Are you going to continue that style, or do you think it might be<br />
losing you votes?<br />
PM: You see, it's all in a sense over-estimated. I don't believe in<br />
personal attacks I don't ever talk about people's personal lives,<br />
their family lives, their finances. When I say the Coalition may be<br />
hillbillies, or something like this as I have said at some stage in the<br />
past I'm talking about them in the sense of a corporate political<br />
put-down of them. But what I regard as personal attacks are people<br />
who go to personal lives, and the Liberal Party do that against me<br />
perpetually they're doing it again today, yesterday it goes on here<br />
all the time. So, when I refer to them in a corporate sense, I'm not<br />
dealing and never have: nobody can say over the 25 years I have<br />
been in public life, that anywhere have I referred to them in those<br />
sort of, if you like, hurtful, personal terms. But I have had a lot of it<br />
directed at me, and it has highlighted of course now that is, the<br />
Parliamentary debate is highlighted by television. But you<br />
notice... . you wouldn't have seen, perhaps, Mike Seccombe from the<br />
Sydney Morning Herald said is a column a week ago that<br />
Mr Howard's tactic is to disrupt the House of Representatives by<br />
interjections under his breath, by interjections which are out of the<br />
earshot of the microphone. He said that Mr Howard is a<br />
parliamentary sneak, and he better own up to having either some<br />
interest in the nature of his rhetoric about the Parliament, or simply,<br />
to be described as somebody who is prepared to disrupt the<br />
Parliamentary proceedings. So, this is the environment we live in<br />
here, and I think it has changed since the Parliament was televised.<br />
DA: A few years down the track, can you say that you still enjoy being<br />
Prime Minister as when you took over from Bob Hawke? </p>
<p>PM: I enjoy the policy changes. I was thrilled to be able to see the<br />
Treasurer say on Budget night that we will now have 15% of<br />
everyone's income going away in superannuation that no other<br />
generation of Australians will need to worry about their retirement<br />
income from now on. You know, that someone on average weekly<br />
earnings will end up with a nest egg of $ 500,000. They are the big<br />
changes that matter. Up in Japan last week, I walked away with a<br />
declaration from the Japanese a joint declaration of partnership<br />
between us, which said amongst other things that " Japan reaffirms<br />
that Australia is an indispensable partner in regional affairs".<br />
Now, when have you ever seen that sort of text, ever, in any<br />
relationship we have ever had with the largest power in Asia the<br />
largest economy in Asia or, let me read a couple of other points<br />
from it: " Japan and Australia have a relationship of unprecedented<br />
quality, they pledged to build on that foundation an enduring and<br />
steadfast partnership." You see, this is the country that matters<br />
most to us it is the largest in terms of trade, it's our largest trading<br />
partner, and to walk away with that sort of declaration and<br />
relationship, is the stuff of this job. And that's what gives you the<br />
kicks, as they say.<br />
DA: If you lose the election, are you going to stick around as Leader?<br />
PM: I'm not in the business of losing, and we have won 5 elections in a<br />
row, and I think we can make it 6.<br />
DA: But nevertheless, just if the unexpected happens, will you stay on?<br />
PM: Well, I would see at the time you see, I don't think the public are<br />
going to take somebody recycled from the 70s and 80s. They are<br />
too smart Doug, they have had too much quality in policy changes<br />
put to them to say " oh well, we will stop all that we will go back to<br />
sort of sitting back".. You know John Howard said a couple of weeks<br />
ago that he thought Australians had policy fatigue. You know, the<br />
only person who has got policy fatigue is him.<br />
DA: What about if you win are you going to stay on for a long time?<br />
PM: Long enough to do all the things that I think are consistent with this<br />
international isation of Australia, and also giving us that cultural and<br />
social identity which I think we now have. You know, 10 years ago,<br />
only 3 kids in 10 completed secondary school. Now, we have got 8<br />
in 10 completing secondary school, we have added 65% of places to<br />
tertiary education higher education, universities. In One Nation, we<br />
built up the TAFE system. In Melbourne this weekend, I am<br />
launching the One Nation train we will have the standard gauge for<br />
the first time from Brisbane through Sydney, via Melbourne to Perth,<br />
which will make Melbourne the transport hub of Australia. I mean,<br />
these sorts of changes of the nation coming together as we said at<br />
the time: One Nation is the thing which I have most dedicated </p>
<p>myself to. Because when I came here Doug, in the late 60s, the time<br />
I became a person of some significance in the front bench of the<br />
Labor Party in the late 70s, people had thrown in this Parliament<br />
had thrown the economic and social fight for just on then 40 years<br />
years. And all the policies to open the country up, to<br />
produce a naturally low inflation rate, to produce productivity,<br />
dynamism, import competitiveness, real product innovation, powered<br />
along by our education system all of those issues, people had<br />
thrown the fight on. And, for my part, I was not going to ever let<br />
anyone say of me that I did it too. So, that's what I am about I'm<br />
about, basically, kicking goals in policy. The other thing, let me say I<br />
want to see this terrific front bench we now have here, bring these<br />
people along. I mean, the number of people that can succeed me as<br />
leader are now manifest in the front bench of the Government.<br />
DA: Who are they?<br />
PM: There is, I suppose, all the obvious ones.<br />
DA: Gareth Evans?<br />
PM: Kim Beazley, Gareth Evans, Simon Crean, some of the younger<br />
members coming through as well, Carmen Lawrence from Western<br />
Australia, Ralph Willis the Treasurer. I mean, the front bench is so<br />
strong, the equivalent front bench is, of course, Tim Fischer,<br />
Costello and Downer. From our group there is a number of people<br />
who could be leader and Prime Minister and, I think, one of the great<br />
changes of the last 12 years is to have modernised the Australian<br />
Labor Party. The Labor Party will never regress to what it was in the<br />
1950s and I 960is 7It -is -now a modern party, a modern social<br />
democratic party, a modern party of government producing the sort<br />
of people I just mentioned.<br />
DA: How do you feel about Bob Hawke now?<br />
PM: I don't see Bob much these days. He is out leading his own life and<br />
good on him.<br />
DA: What do you think his place in Australian political history is?<br />
PM: I think, it will be one of somebody who was around presiding over a<br />
government which was dedicated to making these changes and the<br />
continuity of the policy changes I was just talking about a few<br />
minutes ago.<br />
DA: Mr Keating, thank you very much for your time today.<br />
PM: Good Doug, it is a great pleasure to speak to you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
