<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10144</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP ADDRESS TO METAL TRADES INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION ANNUAL NATIONAL DINNER - CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010144.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
21 October 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS TO METAL TRADES INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION<br />
ANNUAL NATIONAL DINNER CANBERRA<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Thank you very much Mr Thomas, the national president of the Metal Trades Industry<br />
Association; to Bert and Pauline Evans; to Kim Beazley the leader of the Opposition;<br />
Peter Reith, the Minister for Industrial Relations; other Parliamentary colleagues,<br />
ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It is true, as the national president said that I have been to many Metal Trades Industry<br />
Association occasions over the years. I've spoken at gatherings both here in Canberra<br />
and around Australia. I've attended annual meetings and annual dinners and heard<br />
addresses by Prime Ministers and Treasurers and industry Ministers and I have to<br />
confess there is a certain novelty about addressing this gathering for the first time as<br />
Prime Minister and I look forward to opportunity later in the evening of participating<br />
in what for me will be a very pleasant exercise in saying a few words about Bert Evans,<br />
a person with whom I've had a very long association.<br />
But tonight I wanted to address a few remarks to you about the priorities of the<br />
Government so far as they effect not only your industry but the Australian economy. I<br />
start by paying a very warm tribute to the MTIA. All of us have had to live with<br />
change, innovation, globalisation, greater competition, the demolition of distance, and<br />
the removal of things that previously provided comfort and protection.<br />
I think it is fair to say that the Metal Trades Industry Association and its members has<br />
responded very powerfully and very effectively to the changed world economic </p>
<p>environment that the past 15 20 years has delivered. Bert Evans summed it up very<br />
nicely to me once. He said :" John I can't get a quorum at National executive<br />
meetings anymore. I've got to go to Kuala Lumpur airport to get the necessary<br />
number." I think what he was saying very effectively and very powerfully was that for<br />
an industry that for a long time was the leading protagonist for import replacement, the<br />
leading protagonist of resisting changes to levels of protection, for reasons that I'm<br />
sure people on both sides of politics understood only too well.<br />
The industry realised the changed environment in which Australia found herself and set<br />
about doing something in relation to that environment. And I do believe that the<br />
members of your association have responded quite magnificently to the export<br />
challenge that has been ahead of Australia for a long time and still remains very much<br />
ahead of us. And you have been a very good example to the rest of industry about the<br />
need to adapt and change. In his remarks the national president talked quite properly<br />
of the challenges that are thrown up by globalisation, of the complete lack of<br />
sentimentality in world markets. He properly remarked that Australia has been better<br />
than most or faster than most in reducing levels of industry protection. I think it's fair<br />
to say that in the 1980s tariff protection in Australia was reduced at a very fast rate.<br />
And it was reduced as a result of I think bipartisan support.<br />
I've often said that I found a number of the economic measures taken by the former<br />
Government to be ones that we could support and support very warmly. We of course<br />
live in hope for reciprocation, but I won't dwell on that tonight. It would be churlish<br />
in the extreme for me to do that.<br />
But the tariff reduction measures announced in the late 1980s and the early 1990s did<br />
mean that Australia was in the forefront of tariff reduction and we can go to the<br />
international fora with very clean hands so far as the pace of adjustment is concerned.<br />
But I think industry is entitled to say well, we have done our part, we have borne the<br />
brunt of reduced protection, but have we seen sufficient matching of that reduced<br />
protection in the area of reduced business costs and in the area of reciprocation from<br />
our trading partners. I think most people would have to acknowledge that the answer<br />
is probably no to both of those questions. That is not to deny the inherent advantage<br />
to an economy of shifting resources into those industries that are more likely to attract<br />
them because of their naturally competitive edge. But I can understand the desire of<br />
Australian industry to say to Government, I can understand the feeling of Australian<br />
industry to say to Government :" Well, we have engaged in a lot of give-ups, we'd like<br />
a few give-ups in return". And I want to say to all of you tonight that I do understand<br />
that. And I also want to say to you tonight that, I suppose, the driving force behind<br />
many of the changes that my Government has advocated since it was elected in March<br />
and many of us advocated over a long period of time, particularly in the area of<br />
industrial relations, are designed to address the fact that the pace of reduction in levels<br />
of industry protection have not been entirely matched by the pace of reduction in the<br />
level of business costs.<br />
Our focus, since being elected, has really been economically in two areas. We have<br />
focused very heavily on fiscal consolidation. And I'm very proud of the fact that we<br />
were able to deliver a budget that was seen broadly by the Australian community and<br />
I know there were criticisms, I know there were criticisms from industry and I know </p>
<p>there were criticisms from sections of the community but broadly the Budget was<br />
seen as both strong and fair. It was seen as addressing the fiscal challenge, the need to<br />
reduce the deficit, and if we can get the Budget through the Senate then in year three<br />
of my Government's term in office we will have a budget that is in underlying balance.<br />
And given where it has recently been and where, I suppose, it is at the moment, that<br />
will be no mean achievement. And the contribution that that will make to the national<br />
savings effort, the contribution that that will make to underlying business confidence,<br />
the contribution that that will make to the attractiveness of Australia as a place for<br />
overseas investment, is quite incalculable.<br />
The other area, of course, has been a focus on micro-economic reform, and what I<br />
prefer to call reform designed to reduce the cost of doing business in Australia. And<br />
the forefront of that, of course, has been our commitment to bring about industrial<br />
relations reform. This has been a commitment of my Party and my side of politics for a<br />
long period of time. It's been something that has occupied a great deal of my own<br />
intellectual and political effort over the last ten years. I know that there are some in<br />
the MTIA who haven't always agreed with what I and my Party have argued for, and<br />
that could well still be the case. And I've always respected the candour and frankness<br />
and vigour with which we have been able to exchange views. Our commitment to<br />
industrial relations reform is not and never has been an exercise in union bashing. I<br />
have my views about the role of and the behaviour of areas of the union movement.<br />
I'm also prepared, as I have been in the past, to acknowledge the role of the trade<br />
union movement as part of the fabric of Australia's history and of Australia's life. My<br />
view is that trade unions in Australian society like so many other entities, as we go into<br />
the next century, will perish or survive according to their capacity to efficiently deliver<br />
services to their members and their supporters. There are no guaranteed market shares<br />
for you as businessmen and women. There are no guaranteed market shares for us,<br />
whatever our side of politics as political practitioners. And equally the philosophy that<br />
has underlayed our approach to industrial relations is that there should be no<br />
guaranteed market shares to any section of organised labour, or indeed, the organised<br />
employer associations.<br />
We are reaching the moment of decision so far as the industrial relations reforms of the<br />
Coalition are concerned. The Workplace Relations Bill has passed the second reading<br />
in the Senate. The committee stage debate will commence, I hope, in the next couple<br />
of weeks.<br />
I want to record publicly my warm thanks to my colleague, Peter Reith, for the patient,<br />
careful, painstaking and thoroughly professional way in which he has gone about his<br />
responsibilities. We take seriously the process of discussion and negotiation with the minor parties in<br />
the Senate. I deal in political realities, I don't deal in political ' what might have beens.'<br />
And I hope at the end of the day we can secure, through the Senate, the passage of the<br />
Workplace Relations Bill in a form that essentially keeps faith with the principles that<br />
have been laid down over quite a period of time. It will be a bill that will focus far<br />
more heavily on individual agreement between employers and employees. It will<br />
elevate the consummation of those agreements far more than does the present<br />
legislation. It will sweep away the ridiculous unfair dismissal laws that we have at the </p>
<p>present time. It will change the conveniently belong rule so that if it is desired,<br />
enterprise unions can emerge. It will, I hope, give expression to the desire to give<br />
people an effective choice between a workplace arrangement or continuation under the<br />
current award system. It represents a very important element of the new<br />
Government's reform agenda, as indeed does our commitment to revitalise the<br />
circumstances in which small business operates in Australia.<br />
Small businesses operate in every section of the Australian economy. And I know that<br />
within the membership of the MTIA the small and medium sized businesses bulk very<br />
large. And I hope to have in my hands within ten days a report from the taskforce I<br />
established under the chairmanship of Charlie Bell, the Managing Director of<br />
McDonalds, to advise the Government of ways and means of reducing by 50 per cent,<br />
the paperwork burden on small business during our first three years of office. It's an<br />
ambitious task, but a very important one. And in that context, if I can borrow from<br />
Bert Evans' anecdotes again I've never forgotten an interview he gave on PM one<br />
night, when somebody was complaining of about how not enough small firms had<br />
responded to a circular about award superannuation. And Bert said, ' well, I think the<br />
person who's complaining...' who I think had come from the Government '... ought<br />
to understand that most small shows, particularly the one-man, one-woman shows,<br />
operate on the basis that you get into the office, you open the mail, you grab the<br />
cheques and you throw the rest into the wastepaper basket and get on with trying to<br />
make a living.' And I thought it encapsulated the reality of how many small businesses<br />
are forced to operate, and the sheer absurdity of imposing upon the very small firms of<br />
Australia the compliance obligations that can be easily discharged by large companies<br />
that have a personnel or human resources department. I thought it made the point very<br />
eloquently and in a very cut-through fashion.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, we talk a lot about micro-economic reform. We talk a lot about<br />
economic theory. But at the end of the day the goal of economic policy and the goal<br />
of economic decision making is not to satisfy some kind of ideology, it is not to satisfy<br />
some kind of theory. The objective of good policy in the economic area is to generate<br />
greater economic growth and through that, to generate more jobs for Australians. And<br />
that is a solemn responsibility of all governments. It's a solemn responsibility of<br />
governments, it's a solemn responsibility of oppositions, to pursue policies which<br />
generate greater growth, and through that, generate more jobs. And as a small earnest<br />
of my view about that chain of cause and affect, and of my commitment to the<br />
importance of job generation, I've announced tonight that we're establishing for the<br />
first time an employment committee of the Federal Cabinet. I had announced at the<br />
time of the election and the formation of the Cabinet that we would have an economic<br />
committee that would have as its prime goal the pursuit of micro-economic reform.<br />
I've decided not to pursue that. I've decided rather to establish an Employment<br />
Committee of Cabinet whose prime goal will be to oversee the implementation of<br />
policies that are designed to boost employment. The doesn't signal any departure from<br />
previously stated policies. But what it does signal is a very direct commitment to pull<br />
together the various activities of government and the various policies of government<br />
and point them in the direction of job generation.<br />
A competitive economy or a more efficient economy from a micro-economic point of<br />
view is not an end in itself It is only a tool to provide greater growth, and through </p>
<p>that, more jobs for Australians, particularly for young Australians. None of us,<br />
whatever our politics or whatever our vantage point in industry or the trade union<br />
movement, should ever lose sight of the human and social responsibility that goes hand<br />
in glove with economic policy. And the creation of jobs and the provision of<br />
opportunities and hope, particularly for young Australians, does remain very much at<br />
the core of what government is all about. We had a lot to say about that during the<br />
election campaign, we had a lot to say about the role and the place and the<br />
contribution of the small business community towards it, and it remains very much in<br />
the forefront of our thinking.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, the MTIA has made an enormous contribution to Australian<br />
industry and to the Australian economy over a long period of time. Your members<br />
have witnessed the enormous changes in the Australian economy of the last 20 years.<br />
You have become active participants in the new globalised world economy. You are<br />
at the cutting edge of change and competition. I have enjoyed in the past a very close<br />
association, on occasions an association that has brought forth very vigorous debate<br />
and from time to time disagreement, but always on the basis of a well intentioned<br />
desire to serve the long term interests of Australia. And I want to say, at this the first<br />
dinner I have addressed of the MTIA as Prime Minister of Australia, I want to say that<br />
drawing upon that past association I commit my Government to close consultation, a<br />
very close dialogue with your members and with your association. I regard the free<br />
exchange of ideas and information and advice, and on occasions where appropriate,<br />
criticism and rebuttal, between governments and the business community, as being very<br />
important. I've often said that the Party I lead can proudly say it's not owned by any<br />
one section of the Australian community, and that certainly is a very emphatic<br />
declaration that I make. But it does not alter the fact that we are a Party that has<br />
always sought to have a keen eye to the legitimate concerns of the business community<br />
of this country the wealth generators, the job providers, the export providers, and the<br />
providers of the economic future of Australia. And I'd always want it to be seen that<br />
even if on occasions we might disagree, my Government and its various members listen<br />
very closely and carefully with what you have to say.<br />
Can 1, on behalf of my wife and myself and on behalf of my other colleagues who are<br />
here tonight and who won't be contributing to the proceedings, thank you most<br />
warmly for having us as guests. I wish the MTIA well. I look forward to the very<br />
closest possible consultation and cooperation between the MTIA and my Government<br />
in what I hope to be many years of a close partnership.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
