<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12219</transcript-id>
    <title>THIRD HOWARD MINISTRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce today the Third Howard Ministry the appointment</p>
<p> of which I will recommend to the Governor General. The swearing in of</p>
<p> the Ministry will take place on Monday afternoon, 26 November 2001, at</p>
<p> Government House, Canberra.</p>
<p>The Ministry has been chosen on the basis of both proven performance</p>
<p> and new members with a potential to contribute to the Government over</p>
<p> the longer term. There has been some restructuring of portfolios to improve</p>
<p> administrative efficiency and to fulfil election commitments.</p>
<p>There are three new Cabinet Ministers. The Honourable Dr Brendan Nelson</p>
<p> MP will become the Minister for Education, Science and Training. Senator</p>
<p> the Honourable Kay Patterson has been appointed Minister for Health and</p>
<p> Ageing. The Honourable Ian Macfarlane MP will become the Minister for</p>
<p> Industry, Tourism and Resources.</p>
<p>The new faces in the outer Ministry are Mrs Danna Vale MP, Mr Gary Hardgrave</p>
<p> MP, Senator Helen Coonan and Mr Kevin Andrews MP.</p>
<p>I take the opportunity to thank the Honourable Jackie Kelly, MP for her</p>
<p> work as Minister for Sport and Tourism over the last three years. She</p>
<p> indicated to me earlier this week that she did not wish to be considered</p>
<p> for a position in the Ministry because of family and other personal commitments</p>
<p> at this time. Ms Kelly has, however, agreed to my request that she continue</p>
<p> to serve the Government in the slightly less onerous but important role</p>
<p> as my Parliamentary Secretary. I would hope to consider Jackie Kelly for</p>
<p> reappointment to the Ministry when an opportunity arises in the future.</p>
<p>Senator Bill Heffernan will remain as Parliamentary Secretary to Cabinet.</p>
<p>I record my thanks and appreciation to the Hon Bronwyn Bishop MP for</p>
<p> her ministerial work over the last five and a half years, firstly in the</p>
<p> defence portfolio and more recently as the Minister for Aged Care.</p>
<p>The Honourable Bruce Scott MP has not been included in the Ministry due</p>
<p> to a reduction in the proportion of National Party Ministers. I express</p>
<p> the gratitude of the Government for his excellent work as Minister for</p>
<p> Veterans'; Affairs and Minister Assisting the Minister for Defence.</p>
<p>The Honourable John Anderson MP, Deputy Prime Minister, will remain as</p>
<p> Minister for Transport and Regional Services. I have decided to transfer</p>
<p> a number of regional policies and programmes from other portfolios to</p>
<p> the Department of Transport and Regional Services, including Area Consultative</p>
<p> Committees, Natural Disaster Relief Finances and the Regional Assistance</p>
<p> Programme.</p>
<p>It is my intention to appoint the Honourable Wilson Tuckey MP as Minister</p>
<p> for Regional Services, Territories and Local Government. However, he will</p>
<p> not be sworn in until the completion of a police investigation currently</p>
<p> underway into issues associated with the charter of aircraft in Western</p>
<p> Australia some years ago. Mr Tuckey has assured me that he does not believe</p>
<p> that he has been involved in any wrong doing and that he would wish his</p>
<p> reappointment to the Ministry to be delayed until the matter has been</p>
<p> resolved. Senator Ron Boswell will remain as Parliamentary Secretary in</p>
<p> the portfolio.</p>
<p>The Honourable Peter Costello MP will remain as Treasurer. Senator Helen</p>
<p> Coonan will be appointed as Minister for Revenue and Assistant Treasurer.</p>
<p> Senator the Honourable Ian Campbell will be appointed to the portfolio</p>
<p> as Parliamentary Secretary.</p>
<p>The Honourable Mark Vaile MP will remain as the Minister for Trade and</p>
<p> the Honourable Alexander Downer MP will remain as Minister for Foreign</p>
<p> Affairs. The foreign affairs portfolio will be augmented by the creation</p>
<p> of an Office of Trade Negotiations and the transfer of the overseas property</p>
<p> management function from the Department of Finance and Administration.</p>
<p> The Honourable Chris Gallus MP will be appointed Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> for Foreign Affairs.</p>
<p>I have reappointed Senator the Honourable Robert Hill as Leader of the</p>
<p> Government in the Senate and have appointed him as Minister for Defence.</p>
<p> He will be assisted by Mrs Danna Vale MP who will also become Minister</p>
<p> for Veterans'; Affairs. Mrs Fran Bailey MP will be appointed Parliamentary</p>
<p> Secretary for Defence. Emergency Management Australia will be transferred</p>
<p> to the Attorney-General';s portfolio.</p>
<p>I have reappointed Senator the Honourable Richard Alston as Deputy Leader</p>
<p> of the Government in the Senate. He will remain as Minister for Communications</p>
<p> and Information Technology. Senator the Honourable Rod Kemp will become</p>
<p> Minister for Arts and Sport. The portfolio will be augmented by the transfer</p>
<p> of the sports function, government information and the creation of a postal</p>
<p> industry ombudsman. Cultural heritage programmes will be transferred to</p>
<p> the Department of Environment and Heritage.</p>
<p>The Honourable Dr David Kemp MP will be appointed Minister for the Environment</p>
<p> and Heritage and remain as Vice President of the Executive Council. He</p>
<p> will be assisted by the Honourable Dr Sharman Stone MP who will remain</p>
<p> as Parliamentary Secretary in the portfolio.</p>
<p>The Honourable Tony Abbott MP will remain as Minister for Employment</p>
<p> and Workplace Relations and will be appointed Leader of the House and</p>
<p> Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for the Public Service. Mr Abbott';s</p>
<p> portfolio will gain responsibility for the Remuneration Tribunal and public</p>
<p> sector remuneration policy. The Office of Small Business will be transferred</p>
<p> to the new Ministry of Industry, Tourism and Resources.</p>
<p>The Honourable Mal Brough MP will remain as Minister for Employment Services.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable Amanda Vanstone will be reappointed as Minister</p>
<p> for Family and Community Services. The portfolio will gain responsibility</p>
<p> for youth affairs and programmes in support of indigenous young people</p>
<p> that are currently within the education portfolio.</p>
<p>The Honourable Larry Anthony MP will be appointed as Minister for Children</p>
<p> and Youth Affairs. Mr Ross Cameron MP will be appointed as Parliamentary</p>
<p> Secretary in this portfolio.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable Kay Patterson will be appointed Minister for Health</p>
<p> and Ageing. The change in the portfolio';s title reflects the Government';s</p>
<p> commitment in its third term to more thoroughly address challenges arising</p>
<p> from the ageing of Australia';s population. The portfolio will gain</p>
<p> the Commonwealth Rehabilitation Service from the Department of Family</p>
<p> and Community Services. Mr Kevin Andrews MP will be appointed as the Minister</p>
<p> for Ageing and the Honourable Trish Worth MP will be appointed as Parliamentary</p>
<p> Secretary.</p>
<p>Senator the Honourable Nick Minchin will become Minister for Finance</p>
<p> and Administration and Senator the Honourable Eric Abetz will remain as</p>
<p> Special Minister of State. The Office of Asset Sales and Commercial Support</p>
<p> will be abolished and its functions absorbed by the Department. Responsibility</p>
<p> for service charters will be transferred to my portfolio and administrative</p>
<p> support for Royal Commissions will transferred to the Attorney-General';s</p>
<p> portfolio. The Honourable Peter Slipper MP will remain as Parliamentary</p>
<p> Secretary in the Finance and Administration portfolio.</p>
<p>The Honourable Dr Brendan Nelson MP will be appointed as Minister for</p>
<p> Education, Science and Training. I have decided to transfer responsibility</p>
<p> for science policy and programmes (including CSIRO) to the education portfolio</p>
<p> to create better linkages between these sectors, particularly in light</p>
<p> of the substantial additional commitment of resources provided by the</p>
<p> Government in “Backing Australia';s Ability”.</p>
<p>The Honourable Peter McGauran MP will be appointed Minister for Science.</p>
<p>The Honourable Ian Macfarlane MP will become Minister for Industry, Tourism</p>
<p> and Resources. The inclusion of tourism in the title of the portfolio</p>
<p> is to more adequately reflect the growing importance of this sector in</p>
<p> the Australian economy. In view of the important linkages between tourism</p>
<p> and the small business sector I have decided to appoint a Minister for</p>
<p> Small Business and Tourism, the Honourable Joe Hockey MP. The Honourable</p>
<p> Warren Entsch MP will remain as Parliamentary Secretary in this portfolio.</p>
<p>The Honourable Daryl Williams AM QC MP will be reappointed as Attorney-General</p>
<p> and Senator the Honourable Chris Ellison as Minister for Justice and Customs.</p>
<p>I have decided that the Department of Reconciliation and Aboriginal and</p>
<p> Torres Strait Islander Affairs will be absorbed within a new portfolio</p>
<p> of Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs. The Honourable</p>
<p> Philip Ruddock MP will be the senior Minister in the portfolio and Mr</p>
<p> Gary Hardgrave MP will become Minister for Citizenship and Multicultural</p>
<p> Affairs. The Government will enhance its efforts to promote the concept</p>
<p> of citizenship as a unifying force in Australian society.</p>
<p>The Honourable Warren Truss MP will be reappointed as Minister for Agriculture,</p>
<p> Fisheries and Forestry. He will be assisted by Senator the Honourable</p>
<p> Ian Macdonald who will be Minister for Forestry and Conservation. Senator</p>
<p> the Honourable Judith Troeth will remain as Parliamentary Secretary to</p>
<p> the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry.</p>
<p>Mr Jim Lloyd MP, the Member for Robertson, has been appointed as Chief</p>
<p> Government Whip. He will be assisted by Stewart MacArthur MP and Joanna</p>
<p> Gash MP as Government Whips.</p>
<p>Full Ministry List Available:</p>
<p> PDF</p>
<p> format</p>
<p> RTF</p>
<p> Format</p>
<p>   Title</p>
<p>Minister</p>
<p>Other Chamber</p>
<p> Prime Minister</p>
<p>The Hon John Howard, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary to the Prime Minister</p>
<p>The Hon Jackie Kelly, MP</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary to Cabinet</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Bill Hefferman</p>
<p>Minister for Transport and Regional Services</p>
<p>(Deputy Prime Minister)</p>
<p>The Hon John Anderson, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Ian Macdonald</p>
<p> Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Ron Boswell</p>
<p>Treasurer</p>
<p>The Hon Peter Costello, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Nick Minchin</p>
<p> Minister for Revenue and Assistant Treasurer</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Helen Coonan</p>
<p>The Hon Peter Costello, MP</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Ian Campbell</p>
<p>  (Manager of Government Business in the Senate)</p>
<p>   Minister for Trade</p>
<p>The Hon Mark Vaile, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p>  Minister for Foreign Affairs</p>
<p>The Hon Alexander Downer, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary (Foreign Affairs)</p>
<p> The Hon Chris Gallus, MP</p>
<p>   Minister for Defence</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p> The Hon Danna Vale, MP</p>
<p> (Leader of the Government in the Senate)</p>
<p>Minister for Veterans' Affairs</p>
<p> The Hon Danna Vale, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p>  Minister Assisting the Minister for Defence</p>
<p>The Hon Danna Vale, MP</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Fran Bailey, MP</p>
<p>Minister for Communications, Information Technology and</p>
<p> the Arts</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Richard Alston</p>
<p> The Hon Peter McGauran, MP</p>
<p> (Deputy Leader of the Government in the Senate)</p>
<p>   Minister for the Arts and Sport</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Rod Kemp</p>
<p> The Hon Peter McGauran, MP</p>
<p>Minister for Employment and Workplace Relations</p>
<p>The Hon Tony Abbott, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Richard Alston</p>
<p> (Leader of the House)</p>
<p>Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for the Public</p>
<p>   Service</p>
<p>  Minister for Employment Services</p>
<p> The Hon Mal Brough, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Richard Alston</p>
<p>  Minister for Immigration and Multicultural</p>
<p>   and Indigenous Affairs</p>
<p>The Hon Philip Ruddock, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Chris Ellison</p>
<p>Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Reconciliation</p>
<p>  Minister for Citizenship and Multicultural Affairs</p>
<p> The Hon Gary Hardgrave, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Chris Ellison</p>
<p>  Minister for the Environment and Heritage</p>
<p>The Hon Dr David Kemp, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Robert Hill</p>
<p>(Vice-President of the Executive Council)</p>
<p>Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Dr Sharman Stone, MP</p>
<p>Attorney-General</p>
<p>The Hon Daryl Williams, AM QC MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Chris Ellison</p>
<p> Minister for Justice and Customs</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Chris Ellison</p>
<p> The Hon Daryl Williams, AM QC MP</p>
<p>Minister for Finance and Administration</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Nick Minchin</p>
<p> The Hon Peter Costello, MP</p>
<p> Special Minister of State</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Eric Abetz</p>
<p>The Hon Tony Abbott, MP</p>
<p> Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Peter Slipper, MP</p>
<p>Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry</p>
<p>The Hon Warren Truss, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Ian Macdonald</p>
<p> Minister for Forestry and Conservation</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Ian Macdonald</p>
<p>The Hon Warren Truss, MP</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Judith Troeth</p>
<p>   Minister for Family and Community Services</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Amanda Vanstone</p>
<p> The Hon Larry Anthony, MP</p>
<p>Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for the Status</p>
<p>   of Women</p>
<p>  Minister for Children and Youth Affairs</p>
<p> The Hon Larry Anthony, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Amanda Vanstone</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Ross Cameron, MP</p>
<p>Minister for Education, Science and Training</p>
<p>The Hon Dr Brendan Nelson, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Richard Alston</p>
<p> Minister for Science</p>
<p>The Hon Peter McGauran, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Richard Alston</p>
<p>  (Deputy Leader of the House)</p>
<p>Minister for Health and Ageing</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Kay Patterson</p>
<p> The Hon Kevin Andrews, MP</p>
<p> Minister for Ageing</p>
<p>The Hon Kevin Andrews, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Kay Patterson</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Trish Worth, MP</p>
<p>Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources</p>
<p>The Hon Ian Macfarlane, MP</p>
<p> Senator the Hon Nick Minchin</p>
<p>  Minister for Small Business and Tourism</p>
<p> The Hon Joe Hockey, MP</p>
<p>Senator the Hon Nick Minchin</p>
<p>  Parliamentary Secretary</p>
<p> The Hon Warren Entsch, MP</p>
<p>Each box represents a portfolio. Cabinet Ministers are shown in bold</p>
<p> type. As a general rule, there is one department in each portfolio.</p>
<p> Except for the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet and the Department</p>
<p> of Foreign Affairs and Trade, the title of each department reflects that</p>
<p> of the portfolio minister. There is also a Department of Veterans' Affairs</p>
<p> in the Defence portfolio.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
