<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9102</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING MP LAUNCH OF ANNE SUMMERS BOOK, &quot;DAMNED WHORES AND GODS POLICE&quot; SYDNEY 24,JANUARY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/01/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009102.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF ANNE SUMMERS' BOOK, " DAMNED WHORES AND GOD'S<br />
POLICE", SYDNEY, 24 JANUARY 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Anne, if I had of known you were this popular I would never have let you leave<br />
my staff. You must accompany me more often with this guaranteed turn out of<br />
media. Well, it is a great delight to be launching the book for an old friend, as Anne is,<br />
and to be doing so where it is recognised that of all her great achievements, this<br />
is perhaps one of her greatest, probably her greatest, because this book has<br />
been continuously in print for nineteen years and it has sold more than 60, 000<br />
copies. That must be a real feather in the cap for Anne, and for Penguin and<br />
now as Bob says the book has been revised and Anne has written a couple of<br />
new chapters at the beginning and at the end, and revised the work in its<br />
substance. One of the things which I thought touched me in the book, she says it is logical<br />
that the generation which launched the movement will have to see it through.<br />
There is a certain weariness about that statement, which I well understand.<br />
Anne is a baby boomer, and so am I, I was in the middle run of the baby<br />
boomers born in 1944, when I turned 50 the other day I knew that all the Peter<br />
Pan notions that we baby boomers have had, because we have resisted ageing<br />
as no generation before us has resisted ageing, and that basically it is a losing<br />
battle, a losing battle.<br />
But we are still in there punching away, putting our views about, trying to reform<br />
the place, moving the debate on. Anne is in that classic tradition of the activist<br />
baby boomers of Australia. So here she is with her famous publication doing it<br />
again, after having returned to Australia from a very exciting and interesting<br />
period abroad and re-establishing herself here and doing things, further things,<br />
for the Australian women's movement and for the status of women in this<br />
country. Now, this notion of hers, she said it was logical that the generation which<br />
launched the movement will have to see it through. And the other interesting<br />
thing she said when saying that, she said that when she was editor of Ms </p>
<p>magazine in the United States the staff came to see her about the management<br />
of the magazine and some of its content. And the presumption was by Anne and<br />
her partner, the staff would be pretty much wanting to see things the way she<br />
had seen things, and to be committed to, if not just simply the same ideals, the<br />
same vision, particularly for the status of women and women's issues. And they<br />
said to her, we are here to say that we did not want to be and don't want to be<br />
like the editors. In other words, the debate had moved on, and the success<br />
which women had had, particularly feminists in the ' 60s and ' 70s, with women's<br />
issues, changing the status of women, had been so profound that the next<br />
generation of people to follow them were in fact living in a different epoch and<br />
that their vision and vista and their objectives were not the objectives of those<br />
who had been the pioneers of change and of the movement.<br />
With some basking, I think, in the success which they had brought, Anne was<br />
then, as you know, running and editing a magazine where the staff were looking<br />
from a position for some plateau in the change of the status of women. In ways<br />
which were different to Anne, which drew upon the strength of the changes<br />
which people like her had made. And she said that we now have to, in making<br />
that statement which I said has weary overtones, have to start thinking about<br />
things like being frail and elderly, and the lack of economic independence. Well,<br />
she is not frail and elderly yet, but there may be some baby boomers who are<br />
frail and elderly. So in other words, the issues change, and we are going across<br />
the life cycle of a generation of women who started this at university, started<br />
these issues, being involved in these issues at university and have gone on to<br />
see the changes through.<br />
One of the things I thought was most telling, and she makes reference to it in the<br />
book, was the survey which was conducted in 1992 amongst Australian women<br />
about the attitudes of women to the changes which have taken place in society.<br />
And Anne was on my staff at the time and we considered the survey results very<br />
closely. Women were pleased with the changes in their lives, with the increased<br />
opportunities, with the greater freedom, with the independence coming from<br />
employment, the much higher participation rates in education in fact the<br />
dominate participation rates in education. They valued the choices which the<br />
changes of the ' 60s and ' 70s and the ' 80s had brought to them.<br />
And so one of, I think, Anne's conclusions upon returning to Australia from the<br />
United States was that women's lives have changed enormously in Australia<br />
across the course of the ' 80s at least, if not the ' 70s. But the changes were not<br />
only here to stay, but women were rejoicing in the changes and enjoying the<br />
choices and opportunities and that one of the frequent subjects of discussion<br />
was the role of men in coming to terms with the changes in their lives in their<br />
new relationship with women, their wives and partners, and that being part and<br />
parcel of the current debate.<br />
Now, I think it is true that those changes have been profound and that they are<br />
widely enjoyed by Australian women. Because there is no doubt, if I look at my<br />
political life, over 24 years, the status and opportunities of Australian women<br />
today are nothing like they were when I became a member of Parliament in<br />
1969. And a large reason for that is because of the pioneering work which has </p>
<p>been done by those interested in the status of women, the feminists, and by<br />
people like Anne Summers.<br />
Now these changes are very real, and I just mentioned a moment ago the<br />
participation in schools and in university, now there are of course, more women<br />
graduating from universities than men, in technical and further education this is<br />
also true, we have got a higher participation rate in secondary school now<br />
amongst women than men. And all of this has meant a dramatic change in the<br />
opportunities for Australian women.<br />
Now, we have had a lot of talk in this country in the last year or so about<br />
reconciliation between Aboriginals and non-Aboriginal Australians. The word<br />
reconciliation has been used a lot and used with all of the meaning that it<br />
deserves to be used with. But one of the great reconciliations which is underway<br />
now, is a reconciliation between men and women and the lives they now lead,<br />
with the changed role of women, the changed opportunities of women and it will<br />
be, I think, many a long year before that reconciliation is complete, if ever.<br />
But the progress and opportunities underlying it I think are fairly profound. And I<br />
think most men understand that and they are adjusting their view of life and<br />
society and opportunity, in terms of the changes which have taken place, and<br />
the reconciliation which is required of it. It's a major adjustment by men to the<br />
new order of life which has come about because of the efforts of many women<br />
like Anne.<br />
One of the things she talks about is domestic violence, and she laments the<br />
prevalence of it as we all do because there was a lot of violence against<br />
women in the early days of this country, and it's more the pity that it's still a partand-<br />
parcel of Australian life. It's something I think we all have to be conscious<br />
of. It's something which I think we all have to try and remedy. As much as one<br />
can make public policy remedy it, the Govt remains very interested in the subject<br />
and determined to do something meaningful about it. But again, it's something<br />
which only societal change and education and understanding can, I think, really<br />
make the difference in terms of that issue.<br />
One of the revelations in the book -Anne said of course she needs to bring it upto-<br />
date, and in a sense she's sort of admitting she's brought herself up-to-date<br />
by saying that she's now a fervent pragmatist. Now, these are words Anne<br />
would never have uttered not so many years ago. I could have saved her a lot of<br />
anguish if she'd asked me 19 years ago, but I'm not quite sure she would have<br />
been taking that kind of advice from me then. If even now. I know a lot of<br />
people think there is a great contradiction between pragmatism and ideals,<br />
between pragmatism and vision and the words become one which is overworked<br />
and, of course, misunderstood. But pragmatism is not cynicism. It is<br />
about learning the lessons of things, and seeing how one can advance visions<br />
and objectives. A lot of my public life in the years before were managed by<br />
ideology. We had the largely competing polarities the ideology that<br />
intervention by governments in society was the appropriate way society should<br />
run and then the competing ideology that the more unfettered is life and society<br />
from government intervention, the better. We've seen that pendulum swing over </p>
<p>the period between the Calvin Coolidges in the US and the Richard Nixons and<br />
the Ronald Reagans. Then on the other side, the planned economies of Eastern<br />
Europe and less so the social democratic parties' interventions in policy over the<br />
course of the century. These have been the competing ideological things. But<br />
what's happened, is that ideology has faded as in fact communities demand<br />
changes from governments and those people who are given a role in managing<br />
society. And so one looks for if you like visions and then objectives within<br />
those visions, and the going about of getting those objectives, and in the doing<br />
of it materially advance the welfare of people, of men and women. I think<br />
Anne's confession to being a fervent pragmatist, is that when she looks at the<br />
women's agenda in this country from the late 60' s onwards and so much having<br />
been accomplished when one compares Australia to other countries, not just in<br />
Australian terms, but it in international terms, so much in terms of the change in<br />
the status of women having been accomplished in this country she's seen<br />
being put into place like building blocks. One block, on top of another block, on<br />
top of another block the foundation, a structure and one moves on. In other<br />
words, it can't all be done instantly. And while it's idealistic, if it's simply<br />
ideological it probably won't happen or wouldn't have happened. The changes<br />
needed to be engineered by interested people who knew what they were doing,<br />
who set for themselves objectives at the time, and went and pursued those<br />
objectives and brought them home.<br />
Now, this is very much a commentary on life in general and certainly in<br />
government and something which I've very much subscribed to myself. One<br />
has a broad vision a big canvas as I've often called it -and then one sets up the<br />
objectives and goes after them, one after the other, until there is a coherent<br />
whole and when one reaches a plateau with a firm set of foundations, one<br />
builds on further and goes on further.<br />
Now, if that's called pragmatism, that's what's changed Australia from an insular,<br />
frightened society one not prepared to get out and trade, and to deal with the<br />
rest of the world in its own terms in the 60' s and 70' s to now a burgeoning,<br />
outward-oriented and confident society and economy. It's been done by that<br />
method. So too, have the changes in the status of women in this country been done in<br />
that way. That is, those achievable things are understood to be achievable, and<br />
those committed to their achievement go after it. It's sometimes called<br />
pragmatism, but it's very effective and it's the effectiveness which I think Ann<br />
recognises and nominates. Let me just give you an example. She came back to<br />
Australia, to. join my staff, and then set about feminising me which she knew<br />
was basically a hopeless task. But really what she set about was what she<br />
always set about -and that was how next to try and improve the lot and status of<br />
Australian women. With some other very committed people on my staff and in<br />
the Prime Minister's Department, and in the Office of Status of Women and,<br />
need I say, with an enlightened Cabinet we put together some changes which<br />
have been very material just over the course of the year, in further improving the<br />
status of Australian women. Child care, an issue which went to opportunity in<br />
work, was advanced by the Government announcing and setting into policy, the<br />
payment of a generalised child care rebate making this an area of availability in </p>
<p>the normal course of the Government's disbursement system, an opportunity for<br />
women to join the workforce. It's something which we'd never had before, even<br />
though the Government extended child care opportunities with child care places<br />
we'd never had a generalised rebate for child care. It's there now, and of<br />
course we announced further extensions of child care. The other change which I<br />
think, amongst many, which was notable, was the cashing out of the dependent<br />
spouse rebate into a home child care allowance which evened up some of the<br />
benefits and incentives of the tax-free threshold and income-splitting and<br />
recognised the fact that the primary chair at home had the responsibility and that<br />
there are payments to be made. Rather than simply a rebate for dependents,<br />
they were paid as cash by the Government to the accounts of that person<br />
mostly of course, the woman, the Mother, at home. That I think is going to<br />
change forever, the way in which we regard support for dependents in the<br />
Commonwealth, and the way in which we will support and make available to<br />
women in the main those direct payments, and the capacity that change provides<br />
to do other things in policy. It was a landmark change, and the women's<br />
movement have been arguing for it for many years and Anne was there at the<br />
key time to bring the enthusiasm about and to get support for and to drive it<br />
home. She's a great networker, she's a great talker. She's tremendously energetic and<br />
everyone who has known her, can only marvel at the depth of energy she's<br />
always been able to bring to bear on any subject, and the enthusiasm that she<br />
has. As well as that, she has that other glorious quality, and that is she has a<br />
great sense of humour. There are enough bores in the world without us needing<br />
to be burdened further all of us particularly in important areas of policy, by<br />
people who've got the blinkers on and are so serious, that it just becomes such a<br />
leaden issue that one can hardly deal with it. Anne's always had that lightness<br />
about her, that sense of fun, of joy, and I think this has made her so much more<br />
effective, and has given her a sense of balance on life which has been terrific<br />
for her and everyone associated with her.<br />
Now I know her Mum's here today, and Chip's here, and all the people who are<br />
close to her are friends to rejoice in the fact that this celebrated work by this<br />
very celebrated person, has been re-written for another generation of<br />
Australians men and women. It's a standard text now in our tertiary institutions,<br />
and as a consequence Penguin has a been on a winner for a long time, and it's<br />
likely to stay on a winner. So, could I say to Penguin, congratulations again<br />
first of all on supporting Anne in the first place and encouraging her through the<br />
years, to update this seminal work as the status of Australian women has<br />
changed. And congratulations to Anne, for putting, her mind again to this<br />
important work, which has traced over time the evolution from 1788 to the<br />
present, the threads of exclusion and oppression, the threads of<br />
misunderstanding and misrepresentation, the threads of prejudice, of<br />
victimisation, of the threads of violence. It's there, written tightly for all to read,<br />
recording the changes as we've made them. Congratulations, Anne. It's a great<br />
pleasure to be associated with you again on this happy occasion, and to launch<br />
if it needs launching again your seminal work Damned Whores and God's<br />
Police. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
