<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17961</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech at the Prime Minister&#039;s Literary Awards, Canberra</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I'm delighted to be here today at this haven of books and ideas.</p>
<p>Earlier on, I was delighted to meet our new National Librarian, Anne-Marie,and on behalf of all Australians, I congratulate her on being appointed to our country's pinnacle role in the care and custodianship of books and information.</p>
<p>Anne-Marie gave me a quick tour of the Library's online resource, Trove.</p>
<p>Appropriately named because it is indeed a treasure trove of information that used to require trawling through microfiche and dusty old records.</p>
<p>It's easy to see why this resource was the winner of the 2011 Excellence in eGovernment Award.</p>
<p>I congratulate the Library on reaching out to all Australians, no matter where they live, something we'll see a lot more of as the NBN makes its way into every Australian community.</p>
<p>This is the democratisation of information, and it points to some of the measures that will be embodied in our National Cultural Policy that Minister Crean has just mentioned.</p>
<p>Friends, we live at a time of tremendous change and transition for the arts, publishing and media.</p>
<p>For much of our history, human story-telling occurred through word of mouth  -  myths and sagas told and retold down the generations.</p>
<p>Today, we live in an era where for the first time in almost 600 years, the book is no longer synonymous with paper.</p>
<p>But lest we fall into a slump of existential despair, I'm here to say the demise of books has been vastly exaggerated.</p>
<p>Yes we might increasingly download our books on electronic devices.</p>
<p>Yes the big end of our book industry has taken some blows in recent months.</p>
<p>But the death of the book is vastly overstated.</p>
<p>We've seen Melbourne designated by UNESCO as a City of Literature.</p>
<p>And at the Sydney Writers Festival in May, we saw 80,000 people turn out to hear 400 authors and panellists talk about books and ideas.</p>
<p>And why?</p>
<p>Because books will never surrender their ability to capture our hearts and our imaginations.</p>
<p>Books are an antidote to isolation, boredom and ignorance.</p>
<p>Add a glass of red and a box of chocolates, and books can be the ultimate pleasure.</p>
<p>Books are a refuge and consolation.</p>
<p>They are a joy and a tonic.</p>
<p>Sometimes they are a weapon.</p>
<p>Affordable, portable, mass-producible books have literally changed the world.</p>
<p>A book can never be unprinted.</p>
<p>Its ideas can never be unthought.</p>
<p>The critic David Ulin once said literature at its best slices through the noise and ephemera of life.</p>
<p>Sometimes drawing us deep into reflection.</p>
<p>At other times, impelling us back into the world aglow with energy and indignation.</p>
<p>Friends, in Australia, the act of story-telling is as old as the human occupation of this land itself.</p>
<p>The printed word was carried deep in the holds of the First Fleet, amid the convicts and supplies.</p>
<p>Our first novel was published in 1831.</p>
<p>And long gone are the days when Australia needed to apologise for the quality of its writing, if we ever did.</p>
<p>Friends, if awards like the various Premiers' Awards and the Miles Franklin came into being in earlier decades to encourage a growing and somewhat uncertain industry, these awards now exist to celebrate success.</p>
<p>To celebrate a mature and confident publishing industry of which our nation can be very proud.</p>
<p>In 2011, the Prime Minister's Literary Awards continue to recognise the very best in Australian writing.</p>
<p>This year, for the first time, our prize money has been redistributed so all shortlisted authors achieve some financial benefit to help acknowledge their efforts and sacrifices.</p>
<p>Friends, I know many of you are also keen supporters of the proposed National Year of Reading in 2012.</p>
<p>This is an initiative of libraries and library associations around the country, and has quite rightly garnered support from many of you here today.</p>
<p>Of course, every year is a year of reading in this most literate and literary of nations.</p>
<p>But in 2012, we can take time out to affirm the place of books, reading, ideas and libraries in the fabric of our nation.</p>
<p>To that end, I'm proud to announce that the Australian Government will provide $1.3 million in funding to help make the National Year of Reading a success.</p>
<p>Minister Crean and I especially want to bring a culture of reading to all Australians, especially those who are reluctant readers and those who struggle with literacy.</p>
<p>Initiatives such as the One Country Reading program and the workplace literacy project will help achieve this.</p>
<p>Every Australian who is physically able to read deserves the chance to learn to read.</p>
<p>I feel it deeply that too many Australians still lack the gift of words and reading.</p>
<p>My hope is that the Year of Reading will be the catalyst for many to discover and rediscover the joy of reading.</p>
<p>It is such a fundamental aspect of our social compact and our vision of ourselves as a nation of fairness and opportunity.</p>
<p>Above all, that we should be a nation that values its own writers and itsown stories.</p>
<p>That is why I'm here today  -  amid a testing week in my political life  -  to celebrate with you and to extend my gratitude.</p>
<p>Today we honour 20 shortlisted books and four winners.</p>
<p>But in truth we celebrate the whole industry:</p>
<p>Its resilience. Its self-belief. Its success.</p>
<p>And how we could never imagine the contours of our nation without you.</p>
<p>To all the nominees, my sincere congratulations.</p>
<p>You have each enriched and enlarged our nation and brought us that little bit closer to our better selves.</p>
<p>So keep writing.</p>
<p>Keep thinking.</p>
<p>Never cease believing in what you do.</p>
<p>The journey is always, always worth it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
