<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9050</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP INTERVIEW WITH DAVID MARGAN, 7.30 REPORT SEATTLE, USA, 21 NOVEMBET 993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009050.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH DAVID MARGAN, 7.30 REPORT<br />
SEATTLE, USA, 21 NOVEMBER 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
DM: There's been an awful lot of discussion about what APEC should be.<br />
And certainly perhaps coming into this conference there were hopes<br />
within the Australian contingent, Singapore, South Korea and the<br />
United States, that perhaps the institutional basis of APEC may move<br />
forward fairly quickly. There was some discussion about whether it<br />
should really be a community, and in fact, you were suggesting the<br />
idea that the name be changed. None of that though really happened.<br />
PM: Now, some members of the APEC constituency thought the word the<br />
big community meant a Brussells style bureaucracy with supra<br />
national decision making in one place, that is, a bureaucracy able to<br />
make decisions for each of them. Now, none of us has ever envisaged<br />
that this is a much more lose arrangement without any formal treaties.<br />
So, it is a small community, but it is definitely a community. But the<br />
success of it can only be measured by the fact that all of the leaders of<br />
the APEC community met, including China, which is half the world's<br />
production, representing half the world's production and 40 per cent of<br />
the worlds population, and decided to meet again. So, decided to<br />
meet next year in Jakarta and adopt a whole range of things in the<br />
meantime which will then come up for endorsement at the Jakarta<br />
meeting. So, APEC Is off and running.<br />
DM: So, what was your reaction to certain elements of the Australian<br />
media, particularly in relation to your attempt to have the name<br />
changed, when they described that attempt as a failure, that you had<br />
been rebuffed?<br />
PM: It is foolishness bordering on what seems to me a sort of negativism<br />
and a complete lack of pride in anything Australia does. Some of the<br />
nit picking by Australian journalists abroad, I mean, what other country<br />
our size would put together a thing this large? When I first started<br />
talking about the APEC leaders' meeting, the same people were<br />
saying, oh well, it is beyond anyone's imagination, this won't happen,<br />
Mta -. Ptlo </p>
<p>Australia can't put a thing like this together. When it actually comes<br />
together then they say, well you want to get the name changed, so<br />
thats a failure too. Here's the rest of the Asia-Pacific basking in this<br />
sense of engagement, including and most particularly a US President<br />
who had lent all of his prestige to it, and large countries which have got<br />
very particular differences like China and Japan, and Japan and the<br />
United States all there trying to draw the best from it. So, it really puts,<br />
I think, some of the negativism by Australian based journalists abroad<br />
in its proper perspective. That is, when are they ever going to say,<br />
well this was a great thing Australia put together and it has actually<br />
come off, it has actually come off. That Australian diplomacy has<br />
again produced another very great change.<br />
DM. It is said by a number of people looking at this conference before it<br />
started that its success will be measured by how many concrete things<br />
It comes out with. I am particularly talking about trade liberalisation.<br />
There was some criticism of the Eminent Persons Group for having a<br />
timetable for discussion that didn't start until 1996, but it seems the<br />
conference has even thrown that aside and delayed the idea of trade<br />
liberalisation even further, and some would suggest it would be the<br />
year 2000 before they have even liberalised trade in snow ploughs.<br />
PM: Well four years ago APEC didn't exist at all. Four years later it has<br />
gone from a mini OECD information policy secretariat in 1989, to an<br />
executive Heads of Government body today in four years. But what's<br />
not adopted this year Is Invariably getting adopted the following year,<br />
you know what I mean, it takes people a while to warm up to see that<br />
there is no hidden punch, there Is no catch. You have got a very<br />
disparate group of economies. And what happens with some of the<br />
simple simons in our media, they are saying, hang on, look you have<br />
got this, now you said you were going to do this, but you never got<br />
there. I say, but hang on, look, four years ago this didn't exist, I mean<br />
this is a grouping of very disparate forces, people have been arraigned<br />
against each other for most of the century. Either we keep pushing<br />
and pull same of the others behind us, or we stop pushing and wait till<br />
they get some natural momentum. Now, if we do that it will be much<br />
slower. So, if you are sitting in Australia's seat or the US's seat, but<br />
particularly Australia's seat, as we have been the prime movers in this,<br />
you keep pushing, and then gather in the things which we have done,<br />
including now turning this into an executive body, and rapidly, and then<br />
going on as we have this weekend, on to design up a set of investment<br />
rules for an investment agreement between now and next year. I<br />
mean, who could have thought four years ago we would have had an<br />
Investment agreement in the Asia-Pacific, it would have been<br />
unthinkable.<br />
DM: In terms though of our sort of Immediate concr-ete results, would<br />
perhaps the unified position that this group has taken on the GATT<br />
Round be the most significant for the moment? </p>
<p>PM: Has the Position they have taken?<br />
DM: In that the APEC leaders have decided to take a unified approach to<br />
the GATT Round and have sent therefore a message?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
DM: To those talks.<br />
PM: We were saying to President Clinton yesterday, you have got to go for<br />
the triple whammy, that's NAFTA, APEC and GATT. He said, well I am<br />
going for it, I am telling you, I am going to go for it. And the statement<br />
we made yesterday about the GATT, I mean, that is coming from half<br />
the worlds production, that's representing half the worlds production<br />
saying to the French and the Europeans, get this finished, get this<br />
done.<br />
DM-. On another issue, perhaps the gloss of this event, this pride at the<br />
moment was taken away momentarily, perhaps, by the comments of<br />
-Conrad Black on an ABC television program.<br />
PM: No that is only just an Australian sleeve issue, I mean who cares about<br />
those things, they are just ephemeral day to day things. This is the<br />
biggest of the big pictures, and the Black business is just, not even a<br />
splash of paint on the picture.<br />
DM: But for some it Is a very Important matter of public policy. Some have<br />
thought it was a sleazy inside deal to give a foreigner some rewards,<br />
financial rewards.<br />
PM: No, Australian Governments have got to make decisions about equity<br />
issues in print and broadcasting and we will make them on the highest<br />
motives, and we have. But, you have only got to say Fairfax and the<br />
Fairfax joumno's go Into a tizz, and they play the first stanza and<br />
generally the ABC does the second stanza for them.<br />
DM: But so the issue of balance.<br />
PM: Break the mould.<br />
DM: Doesn't it seem a bit strange that we should discover this notion of the<br />
Prime Ministers view of balance in an investment matter that involves<br />
millions of dollars from a book published by Conrad Black himself. I<br />
mean, why wasn't this on the public record before. We have had these<br />
conversations, we have told him..<br />
PM: But all these things were discussed at the time. </p>
<p>DM: So, deciding, I mean, why did he in the end get 25 per cent?<br />
PM: I mean, this is just simply dust in the cracks of history. Just forget<br />
about it. I mean you are on the APEC picture, that's the picture to stay<br />
on, this stuff just slides into nowhere.<br />
DM: But it is an Important matter of public policy, our control of our media,<br />
how the deals are done, who gets what.<br />
PM: Compared to what has been done here, this last weekend it is hardly<br />
worth a mention.<br />
DM: So, you think the Australian public should have no concern about how<br />
its broadcasting policy is run?<br />
PM: Yes, but all in the right frame work, not juxtaposed with haughty<br />
subjects tike this.<br />
DM: I am still interested though, in the Prime Ministers notion of balance.<br />
Should you be the one who decides that, though?<br />
PM: Well Prime Ministers have got to decide, I mean, I noticed a bit of<br />
comment about this saying, well isn't it unusual that the Prime Minister<br />
has had to make a decision about the acceptability or otherwise of a<br />
particular set of proprietors. That's one of the things, I am afraid,<br />
Prime Ministers have to do. Because we are the ones who have got to<br />
take the decisions about who gets what in terms of equity. So, it may<br />
be an uncomfortable lot and a burden, but that is part of the job.<br />
DMV: Do you think the next media baron should come to you about<br />
questions of balance and objectivity, for your decision?<br />
PM: If they are foreigners, and if they want to buy a large ch'unk of<br />
Australia, yes.<br />
Ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
