<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6591</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 19 FEBRUARY 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006591.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>

PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E. -PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE -19 FEBRUARY 1985<br />
PM: Ladies and gentlemen I've just come from the Caucus where I<br />
made a lengthy report to the Caucus on a range of matters<br />
including, of course, recent events around the MX decision and my<br />
visit to the United States. I'm pleased to say that the Caucus<br />
without dissent endorsed the decision that was made by thd Federal<br />
Cabinet on this matter. I read the decision of the Cabinet which<br />
was, as I say, unanimously endorsed by the Caucus. It was in<br />
these terms-<br />
" Federal Cabinet today reaffirmed Australian Government<br />
policy on the basic issues of the Australia/ U. S. Alliance,<br />
ANZUS Treaty and on disarmament and deterrence.'<br />
Cabinet took these decisions today after it recevied and<br />
endorsed a report on my recent overseas visit.<br />
As a result of the discussions, and bearing in mind our close<br />
relations with both the U. S. and New Zealand, Cabinet will<br />
shortly consider a paper on the practical measures with<br />
regard to the U. S. and New Zealand for giving effect to the<br />
ANZUS Alliance following the recent New Zealand action to ban<br />
U. S. ship visits, and another paper elaborating on the<br />
relation between and the implementation of the Government's<br />
policies on disarmament and support for deterrence.<br />
The first paper will be prepared by the Foreign minister, the<br />
Hon. Bill Hayden, and the Minister for Defence, the Hon. Kim<br />
Beazley, and the second paper will be prepared by Mr Hayden.<br />
The Ca binet discussion was lengthy, amicable and conducted in<br />
an atmosphere of genuine desire to ensure continuing unity<br />
and cohesion both at the Governmet and Party level over these<br />
complex and sensitive issues. </p>
<p>There was also general agreement that both the Australia/ U. S.<br />
Alliance and the need to do all in our power to ensure the<br />
maximum possible progress on disarmament were essential to<br />
Australian foreign policy.<br />
All Ministers addressed the issue without rancour and with a<br />
desire to search for the best method of both implementation<br />
and understanding of these policies.<br />
An important theme of the discussion was the need to ensure<br />
that the decision making processes of the Government were<br />
directed most effectively to these ends."<br />
Now that was the decision of Cabinet. On 12 February it was<br />
unanimously endorsed by the Cabinet and that has in turn been<br />
endorsed without dissent by the Caucus. Let me comment on that<br />
before going to a second resolution which was passed by the<br />
Caucus. In speaking to this motion, as I had in my report, I made<br />
it clear that the papers that were being prepared did not go to<br />
the question of the policies. The first was a working, practical<br />
paper to look at the questions of how now in fact the relationship<br />
between the United States and Australia, under ANZUS, would be<br />
conducted and how the relationship between Australia and New<br />
Zealand would be conducted. While the second paper, as t1~ e<br />
Cabinet decision indicated, is one elaborating on the relation<br />
between and the implementation of the Government's policies on<br />
disarmament and support for deterrence.<br />
The second decision which was, as I say, passed by the Caucus was<br />
in these terms<br />
" Caucus renews its commitment to the goal of ensuring a long<br />
term reforming Labor Government.<br />
Towards this end, Caucus calls on all members, including<br />
Ministers, to participate actively in the Caucus decisionmaking<br />
process to ensure that the Government achieves the<br />
Party's objectives in the most effective possibl~ e way.<br />
Recognising the importance of the unity of the Government and<br />
of the Party, Caucus calls upon all members to promote the<br />
decisions of the Government, and so to ensure a unified and<br />
effective presentation of Government policies.<br />
Caucus further notes that there are long-standing processes<br />
available within the Party for the resolution of differences<br />
of opinion, and that it is in the best interests of the Party<br />
and the Government when debates are properly cofined to the<br />
processes of the Party."<br />
May I say, ladies and gentlemen, that the comment that I made<br />
and it was endorsed by the Cabinet as to the nature and<br />
character of the discussion in the Cabinet of this matter was also<br />
reflected in the discussions in the Caucus. They were useful, </p>
<p>constructive and harmonious and reflected the desire of the Caucus<br />
as of the Cabinet to ensur-e that the purposes of the Government<br />
are effective in the most constructive manner. And I believe that<br />
we have the basis of going into the Parliament now on a firm<br />
united basis, with the recognition that the events of the week<br />
before last had not been entirely helpful to the Government. And<br />
that is now reflected in, I believe, the unanimous view of the<br />
Caucus that we have the opportunity now in the Parliament and<br />
outside the Parliament of developing and presenting to the people<br />
of Australia the positive policies which are going to be to the<br />
immediate and the long-term benefit of this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, who moved and seconded the two<br />
resolutions? PM: I moved the resolution, the first one, which was an<br />
endorsement of the Cabinet resolution. I think it was seconded by<br />
Mr Bilney I can't recall. And the second resolution was moved<br />
by Mr Ron Edwards and seconded by Mr John Scott.<br />
JOURNALIST: What practical steps apart from the doubling in the<br />
number of Caucus Committees are being taken to improve the<br />
consultation and the decision-making process.<br />
PM: As I left the Caucus Mr Keating was reporting on behalf of<br />
the Kirribilli Committee. That discussion is still going on and<br />
as I understand there will be further discussions and then<br />
decisions at the next meeting of Caucus.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke were you asked to amplify the background to<br />
your decision on the MX?<br />
PM: I wasn't asked to. I did it without being asked.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you then asked whether or not you thought it was<br />
the right decision.<br />
PM: No I was not.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you suggest to the factional leaders, when you<br />
met them this morning for breakfast, that they should stop holding<br />
press conferences?<br />
PM: Well, obviously the whole question of public statements by<br />
individuals and groups was mentioned. And that was included in<br />
the discussion. And I think you will see that the intent of the<br />
second resolution that was passed by the Caucus would cover that<br />
situation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have the Left agreed not to hold press conferences?<br />
PM: Oh well, I am the Prime Minister and I'm speaking now on<br />
behalf of the Caucus. I don't presume to be the spokesman for the<br />
Left particularly. I think you should direct that question to </p>
<p>them. But I would believe that that practice wouldn't continue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is that just a matter of press conferences or would<br />
you exepct the factional leaders who are outside the Ministry not<br />
to make any public comment on matters of Government policy before<br />
the decision by Cabinet?<br />
PM: I believe that in terms of the resolution and the spirit of<br />
it that in future the discussions will be within the Party<br />
processes. JOURNALIST: Did you make your own views on this clear to the<br />
factional leaders this morning and did they agree to that.<br />
PM: Yes. I made my position clear. But let me make it clear<br />
that it wasn't a question of the Prime Minister having to impose a<br />
view. I think there was a general recognition amongst all groups<br />
that, as I've said earlier, that the events of the week before<br />
last were not helpful to the Party and to the Government. And I<br />
think there's a determination as reflected in the resolution to<br />
pursue a different course.<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes but you didn't seek, nor did they give, a<br />
guarantee that they wouldn't speak out.<br />
PM: Well I didn't feel it necessary to seek a guarantee because I<br />
felt from discussions that had taken place that there was an<br />
understanding that we needed to handle these things differently.<br />
That understanding was clear and I believe was explicitly<br />
reflected in the resolution passed by Caucus.<br />
JOURNALIST: pre-empting Party policy by, for example,<br />
speaking out on taxation matters before the Party's has decided on<br />
a formal policy?<br />
PM: As Prime Minister I have the right and the obligation to<br />
speak to the public on issues concerning the areas of Government<br />
initiatives. I don't pre-empt the decisions of the Government that<br />
will be taken in the area of tax. I expressed a clear view and<br />
made it clear in the discussion today, in my report which covered<br />
more than MX and the United States visit, that the Party will be<br />
fully involved in the processes of preparation of the White Paper<br />
which will be issued we hope in May or June before the Summit in<br />
the first week of July, there will be full involvement of the<br />
Party in those processes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well what about other people on taxation. Is that<br />
included in this resolution or do you think it's fair enough that<br />
people put a view on an issue like that which is not yet resolved?<br />
PM: Well I think in the spirit of the resolution that was passed,<br />
Michelle, that the way in which members of the Party will pursue<br />
that will now tend to be within the actual processes of the Party.<br />
Because what you've got to appreciate ' is that the Treasurer, </p>
<p>Mr Keating, will be discussing these matters with the Caucus<br />
Committee and so there'll be full opportunity within the processes<br />
of the Party for different points of view to be put.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke do you think, the first of a series of<br />
trying to heal the rift between the factions?<br />
PM: Well you say a rift between the factions I don't put it<br />
that way. What this morning was about was to address a situation<br />
that had arisen, where as I said, the Government had not been<br />
helped by the events of the previous week. And we were all of the<br />
mind that that was the case and it seemed to me sensible to bring<br />
the representatives of the groups together. They all positively<br />
responded. I think we all found it a very useful exercise.<br />
Whether that will be a regular feature no decision has been<br />
made. But certainly it was very useful and it may well be that<br />
something of that kind more frequently could be useful.<br />
JOURNALIST: Whose idea was it..<br />
PM: It was mine.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister was there any criticism of you for<br />
formally attending a meeting of a faction before Christmas\ and are<br />
you the first Prime Minister, Labor Prime Minister, to attend a<br />
formal faction meeting.<br />
PM: No there wasn't and secondly, I don't know.<br />
JOURNALIST: Now that harmony has been restored, Prime Minister,<br />
in the ANZUS/ MX affair is the Government in a position to re-open<br />
the offer to restore to the Americans the facilities to refuel<br />
their aircraft when..<br />
PM: You don't seem to realise, David, that there was a mutual<br />
decision between myself and the Americans that that was no longer<br />
required.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke what explanation did you give to Caucus<br />
about how you arrived at the original M4X decision.<br />
PM: I explained that the matter was brought to my attention in<br />
May of 1983, before I went to the United States. And it was<br />
pointed out to me then, by the then Minister for Defence, that<br />
this situation may arise in my discussions over there and that I<br />
had raised the question without making a decision at that point of<br />
the splash-down point that was proposed, and indicated that no<br />
splash-down point within any definition of Australian territorial<br />
waters would be acceptable if we were going to consider such a<br />
decision. Then, later in 1983, the question was raised with us<br />
were we going to provide the facilities and that a decision was<br />
taken by the three Ministers in good faith and in full integrity<br />
on 16 November 1983. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke when you were in Washington you were assured<br />
that Australia would not be involved in any research under the SDI<br />
program. I wonder whether you can assure us whether Australia, or<br />
whether you've received any guarantees that Australia will also<br />
not be involved in any subsequent testing, deployment or use of<br />
the strategic defence arrangements.<br />
PM: Well let me say two things in regard to that. Firstly, I<br />
made it clear both in my discussions with the President, the<br />
Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense that we could not<br />
support the SDI initiative. And secondly, I received assurance<br />
that the facilities, the joint facilities in Australia, were not<br />
and would not be involved in such research.<br />
JOURNALIST: How can you prevent the joint facilities being<br />
involved in the testing and deployment of missiles under the SDI<br />
though?<br />
PM: Well, following our accession to government in 1983 there<br />
was a review of the whole question of the facilities and the ANZUS<br />
relationship. We are in a position where we are involved in and<br />
know of the operations of the facilities. We have specifically<br />
put the question to the United States. They have given us an<br />
unequivocal answer and, as distinct from some people, I aiA not in<br />
the business of questioning the integrity of the United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could I take your answer to mean, research<br />
rather than anything further so that if the Americans deploy or<br />
even test..<br />
PM: I specifically put to Mr Weinberger, and I thank you Mike for<br />
your question because it makes clear what did emerge, that firstly<br />
I received the assurance that facilities were in no way involved.<br />
And further than that, I indicated that should there be any<br />
developments on the part of the United States which, on their part<br />
would contemplate the use of the facilities, then we would be<br />
required to be informed because it is not our position that we<br />
would be involved in the SDI.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, did the faction leaders at this<br />
morning's meeting seek any undertaking from you in return for<br />
their undertaking to to make any public comments?<br />
PM: No, there was no seeking of undertakings from me. We all<br />
recognise that there should be a use of the Party processes for<br />
expressing views, and for my part, as I have said previously, I<br />
welcome any moves that are going to facilitate the processes of<br />
consultation on the part of Ministers with the Caucus and through<br />
the Committee system. I have made that quite clear that I welcome<br />
that so the question simply didn't arise. I made that clear.<br />
They understood that. It was a shared view.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, could I just whisk you away from<br />
Caucus for one minute? Do you intend any further meetings with </p>
<p>the NSW doctors?<br />
PM: I will be actually having a meeting this evening with Mr<br />
Shepherd and Dr Blewett will be involved in that meeting and I<br />
hope that that may lead to some avenues for resolving the dispute.<br />
Let me make it clear, as we have in previous discussions, where<br />
the procedural specialists and the AMA were involved, that my<br />
Government will not brook any changes in the basic structures of<br />
Medicare we are not about that. But we are concerned with the<br />
great damage that is developing as far as innocent patients in NSW<br />
are concerned. And if we can, by meeting with Mr Shepherd, move<br />
towards or start to move towards a resolution of this dispute,<br />
then that is a good thing, but it should be made clear that we<br />
have responded to all the points that have been raised in our<br />
earlier discussions. We believe there is there a basis for a<br />
resolution of this dispute and I hope that as a result of these<br />
discussions we may be able to move more quickly towards resolving<br />
a dispute which is doing no credit to those immediately involved,<br />
but more importantly is starting to assume quite tragic<br />
proportions for innocent people in NSW.<br />
JOURNALIST: What changes do you intend to make to your own<br />
decision making process to prevent a repetion of the original MX<br />
decision?<br />
PM: well it is not a question of changing decision making<br />
processes. I have indicated in a previous answer here this<br />
afternoon how the decision was arrived at this particular<br />
decision was arrived at in good faith and in discussions with<br />
the Ministers concerned. Let me make it clear that no-one is<br />
suggesting no-one has suggested in any discussion with me that<br />
security matters are ones which can be a matter for Cauc us<br />
discussion and decision. No-one has put that. And I believe that<br />
the record shows in regard to general matters that, as far as I<br />
have been concerned, I discuss matters with Ministers widely.<br />
This is not an authoritarian government and certainly, however, we<br />
should all, all of us, all intelligent people, should learn from<br />
the difficulties of the previous week. The difficulties arose<br />
from reactions to a particular decision and so we have all<br />
sensibly got to make sure that as much consultation as possible<br />
takes place. On some issues there will be clearly a limited<br />
amount of consultation that will take place, but there should be<br />
as much as it is possible in regard to the issue with which you<br />
are dealing. I certainly have always, both before and since I<br />
have become Prime Minister, believed that the most effective<br />
decisions come from involving as many people as you can and that<br />
has been the hallmark for this Government. I will continue along<br />
those lines.<br />
JOURNALIST: blame the issue blowing up as it did?<br />
PM: I know that a lot of you have been almost exclusively<br />
involved in the question of blame allocation and that is probably<br />
an interesting exercise. I regard it as rather futile but I have </p>
<p>never believed in regard to this issue or any other that I am<br />
perfect. I think I have made that quite clear. And I am an<br />
intelligent person who can learn from experience. Now in regard<br />
to this issue three Ministers in good faith and with integrity<br />
made a decision. Our integrity and good faith was not questioned<br />
at all. It hasn't been questioned at all. Now, once, and I think<br />
this ought to be made clear once it became clear that there was<br />
a very broad concern about that decision, then I, I believe with<br />
complete responsibility, responded to that position. In other<br />
words, as I made clear in Washington, as I make clear again here<br />
in this press conference, I believe the two fundamental positions<br />
appeared to be in jeopardy if that position was adhered to. The<br />
first was that the continuing fundamentals of the Australia/ United<br />
States alliance relationship, the joint facilities/ bases, ship<br />
visits that those continuing, fundamental, important elements of<br />
our relationship were being put in possible jeopardy by a<br />
continuing adherance to a previous decision in regard to a matter<br />
which was transient was not part of the permanent, fundamental,<br />
important issues. And secondly, I believed that there could be<br />
some impairment of our capacity to proceed assiduously as we had<br />
done since we have been in government in the various areas of<br />
disarmament. And I wasn't going to allow either of those two<br />
fundamentals to be impaired or diminished. Now, if you want to<br />
say would I change that decision making process, I wouldn'$. I<br />
would always try and make the decision and be involved in<br />
decisions which are going to enable the fundamentally important<br />
issues of government to be pursued. It did not to me make-any<br />
sense to adhere to a position which was going to impair those<br />
fundamentals.<br />
JOURNALIST: If you say that security matters are not a matter<br />
for Caucus deliberation, how then do you get around another MX<br />
problem, I mean, given that you can't tell the Caucus about this<br />
decision, how do you get around the..<br />
PM: Let me repeat. No-one has put to me that those sorts of<br />
issues and decisions are for Caucus deliberations. No-one has put<br />
that. Now they will be handled by consideration within the<br />
appropriate committees which are established for that purpose.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you agree that the National and<br />
International Security Committee of Cabinet should report back to<br />
Cabinet on its decisions?<br />
PM: You are a bit out of date. It is no longer called that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sorry, the security committee.<br />
PM: Alright.<br />
JOURNALIST: As contained in the Party platform that it should<br />
report decisions back to Cabinet. Do you agree with that? </p>
<p>PM: Well, the position that we will adopt I think will be a<br />
flexible one that there is an attitude, I believe now, in the<br />
Party that we have to ensure that where the fullest range of<br />
consultations is possible, that that will be done and we will seek<br />
to do that. Now, these matters have been discussed and I think<br />
satisfactorily resolved within the Cabinet. There was an<br />
acceptance within the Cabinet discussion on 12 February that you<br />
have different categories of situations. Quite clearly I and the<br />
Ministers directly concerned in this area which is the Minister<br />
for Defence and Foreign Affairs will seek to involve as many<br />
people as we possibly can in the w-idest range of issues that we<br />
have a responsibility for dealing with.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you say the first resolution was<br />
passed without dissent. To what extent was there any criticism of<br />
you or of the decision in the first place in the Caucus debate?<br />
PM: What was the last part of your question?<br />
JOURNALIST: To what extent was there any criticism of your<br />
decision in the course of the debate.<br />
PM: As I recall, none.<br />
JOURNALIST: None at all?<br />
PM: None means none at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on the question of wider consultation..<br />
PM: Let me make it clear, that doesn't mean that in the minds of<br />
some people there might not have been criticism. I mean, some has<br />
been expressed before. I was referring to the meeting.<br />
JOURNALIST: On Caucus consultation, do you accept the structure<br />
put forward in the Dawkins paper?<br />
PM: I am not going to, now, break the unanimous decision of<br />
Caucus. What a question. I will be involved in the discussion in<br />
the processes of the Party. There are Party processes for dealing<br />
with these things, not at a press conference.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you aware that Mr Lange is<br />
planning to visit Australia in April?<br />
PM: No, I wasn't.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be seeing him when he comes here in April?<br />
PM: Are you joking, Laurie? Of course I will. I hope I can<br />
have a game of tennis with him. I don't think he would be as<br />
quick around the court as I would, but he might be. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have the Americans actually asked<br />
Australia to help support the SDI development or is it just an<br />
anticipating ( inaudible)<br />
PM: No, they have not asked. I am not anticipating one. I<br />
believe that I have an obligation to make my position clear on it.<br />
I did. And as I have said before, I think probably I have made<br />
the position of my government clearer and in less equivocal terms<br />
probably than any other western leader.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke do you think the Americans would have any<br />
grounds for concern about the Pacific allies of the alliance and<br />
what's happened recently, particulary in reference to the private<br />
member's bill that was introduced by Senator Chaney yesterday.<br />
PM: Well I think the answer to that question is perhaps best, as<br />
far as Australia is concerned, answered by the statements of<br />
myself and President Reagan on 7 February. I said, and hie agreed<br />
with my statement, I quote what I said<br />
" The relationship that is between Australia and the United<br />
States under the ANZUS treaty and the rights and obl~ gations<br />
assumed under the treaty were undiminished by recent events."<br />
And President Reagan said, at the same time he said, I quote him<br />
" Australia is a reliable'ally, an important trading partner,<br />
a trusted frienid in a fellow democracy."<br />
And he observed, I quote, that he-<br />
" could not overstate the value that the United States placed<br />
on its friendship with Australia."<br />
Now however much some people in Australia in the Opposition<br />
parties may seek to do a great disservice to the basic interests<br />
of this country by seeking themselves to undermine the<br />
relationship and the strength of the relationship, they will not<br />
succeed. Does anyone in this country who is trying to undermine<br />
the relationship between Australia and the United States, members<br />
of the Opposition who put in question whether recent events<br />
diminished that relationship, the President of the United States<br />
agrees that the relationship remains undiminished. Now if the<br />
President of the United States and the Prime Minister of Australia<br />
have that view and have that position as they do have, then it is<br />
an act grossly and manifestly against the interests of Australia<br />
and of the relationship for anyone in the Opposition to put a<br />
contrary view.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the recent experiences have been a<br />
salutory experience for you? </p>
<p>PM: Salutory experience for whom?<br />
JOURNALIST: For you and for the Australian Government?<br />
PM: I think that all experience you should learn from, but let<br />
me say this and of course I am never one to criticise the media<br />
you know that but let me say this. I think it may have been a<br />
more objective assessment of the visit to the United States if<br />
there had been a full exposition an objective exposition of what<br />
in fact was achieved there that is that we dealt with what was a<br />
delicate issue. We arrived at a mutually agreed position and one<br />
which the President of the United States and the Prime Minister of<br />
Australia agrees involves no diminution in the strength and the<br />
force of the relationship between us. And that in that process,<br />
as Prime Minister of this country, and as an aligned country of<br />
the United States, I however strongly put the position that we are<br />
not an aligned country which had to agree, or did agree with every<br />
single aspect of the policy-making and decisions arrived at.<br />
and I have indicated where that was the case. Now that is the<br />
strength of the relationship that is the strength of the<br />
relationship between two great sovereign, but allied democracies<br />
that is that you share certain basic perceptions. They are<br />
fundamental to our perception of how this country should operate.<br />
They are fundamental to the perception of how the United States<br />
should operate. We are committed to the same fundamental values<br />
and in recognition of those shared perceptions we have an alliance<br />
relationship which involves certain fundamental rights and very<br />
fundamental obligations on our part. s Those rights and<br />
obligations remain undiminished and it is within such a healthy<br />
strong relationship between two countries committed to democratic<br />
principles that you are able to have differences of opinion. And<br />
in the expression of those differences of opinion you not militate<br />
against the alliance. They are a reflection of its basic<br />
strength. JOURNALIST: You said there was a deliberate mis-reporting<br />
aspects of that.. Do you think there is a growing press bias<br />
against you and your Government?<br />
PM: No, I don't have a feeling against press bias. I simply say<br />
in respect of this visit that I believe there was a mis reporting<br />
there and when I returned. I mean, you are pursuing this<br />
question, not me. I am relaxed about you people. I think you are<br />
lovely. I think you are beautiful, but I don't think you always<br />
get it right and so, if you want me to give you an example, let me<br />
give it. One would have thought that by the time I got back here<br />
and there were the avenues you have available of finding out what<br />
happened, that you would be surprised by having a front page story<br />
in one of your papers that at the security committee meeting on 29<br />
January Mr Hawke did not raise the question. It was raised under<br />
the lines by Mr Beazley. That is absolutely wrong. It was<br />
raisedf by me. Now, I don't know why you get something as simple<br />
as that wrong. There must be a reason. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: You said it was deliberate, though. Inaudible.<br />
PM: Look, you are raising the question of bias. I haven't<br />
raised it. I didn't use the word bias. I am not using it. I am<br />
not here to complain about the press. I am not complaining about<br />
it.<br />
JOURNALIST: But you talk about mis-reporting. Is it deliberate<br />
mis-reporting?<br />
PM: Oh well, who am I to be here and enter into the minds of such<br />
a range of people as this. I mean, I don't know why things are<br />
got wrong. I mean, I just find it very difficult to understand on<br />
a simple thing like that about a security meeting where there is a<br />
deliberate assertion that Mr Hawke did not raise it. It was<br />
raised under the line by Mr Beazley. Now, it is wrong. It<br />
couldn't be more wrong.<br />
JOURNALIST: Deliberately wrong?<br />
PM: Well, let me say this. There is a way of finding out before<br />
going into print as to whether it was right or not and the<br />
processes weren't followed.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Inaudible) It's pretty hard.<br />
PM: Oh so you justify false assertions in that way. I don't<br />
think that is correct.<br />
JOURNALIST: Inaudible.<br />
PM: But listen, let me make it clear, I mean, you have gone down<br />
this path. I want to make it clear that I am not complaining<br />
about the coverage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, how much damage do you think has been to<br />
the Government electorally because of all the reporting over the<br />
past few weeks?<br />
PM: Let me make it clear, it is not the reporting. I mean, I am<br />
not trying to say..<br />
JOURNALIST: The headlines<br />
PM: Sure, about what has in fact happened. I mean, let me make<br />
it quite clear, I am not blaming anyone else outside the Party for<br />
what has happened within the Party. I think the Party will have<br />
suffered how much I don't know. But what I assert that it is<br />
very temporary because the position of the Government is, I<br />
believe strong with regard to the basics that concern the people<br />
of this country. That is the matter of sound economic management.<br />
And there would, however, I believe, have been some reaction to<br />
the public squabbling that took place. There would have been some </p>
<p>adverse reaction. I believe that will prove to have been<br />
temporary.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, when you have discussed this issue with the<br />
Party and also with the Cabinet, at any stage have you accepted<br />
yourself any blame for what happened in the MX and secondly,<br />
when it comes to the decision Cabinet took about consultation,<br />
have you changed the decision-making procedure at all. I think,<br />
from what you said earlier on, that security decisions don't<br />
necessarily have to go to the security committee of Cabinet. Is<br />
that still the situation?<br />
PM: No, in regard to the first question of do I accept any<br />
blame. I was involved with the two other Ministers in the<br />
decision that was finally taken on 16 Novembher. I can simply say<br />
this. I repeat what I said before. It was a decision taken by<br />
the three of us in integrity, and in good faith, and on the basis<br />
of what we believed, in the circumstances, was in the best<br />
interests of this country. Now, I can say no more than tfiat. I<br />
can then, in regard to that stage, then when I was confronted<br />
with the breadth of the reaction in this month of this yee~ r 1985,<br />
then I accepted the responsibility of leadership of responding to<br />
that. And I made the judgement that the continuing interests of<br />
this country in regard to those two basic issues of the continuing<br />
elements of the large relationship and the non-impairment of our<br />
capacity to pursue our policies in the area of disarmaftient, that<br />
they were not to be put in issue. I believe that I made the<br />
correct decision there.<br />
JOURNALIST: What about the second point<br />
PM: I have answered that question before. I have nothing to add<br />
to what I have said before.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said before that there obviously would<br />
be a limit to consultations. What matters other than security<br />
which you specifically mentioned does that apply to what matters<br />
won't Caucus be consulted about?<br />
PM: Well, if you want another example, on questions of the<br />
exchange rate, for instance. I mean, you obviously are not going<br />
to be discussing those with Caucus. I mean, that is a fairly<br />
obvious example.<br />
JOURNALIST: On that point, Prime Minister, the Australian Dollar<br />
in the last hour has slipped down to new low of 70 cents. Do you<br />
still believe the downward plunge a transient thing and unlikely<br />
to continue? Or do you think that the time has arrived for<br />
Government intervention appreciating the sensitivies?<br />
PM: e Appreciating what?<br />
JOURNALIST: The sensitivities to which you referred at the<br />
weekend. </p>
<p>14<br />
PM: Well, yes, and I am glad you acknowledge those. I don't<br />
believe it is helpful for me to say anything more than I said on<br />
Sunday and I don't intend to.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, a question on taxation in relation<br />
to your comments on the Sunday show. In relation to the question<br />
on the possible re-introduction of the broadly based indirect tax<br />
system, would you favour any exclusions leading to and/ or the<br />
operation of a differential tax base?<br />
PM: I'm not going any further than I did on Sunday. I stated<br />
the position broadly as I see it, and I would think as the<br />
majority of Australians are coming to see it. Now, the detailed<br />
work is going on at the level of officials and Ministers and will<br />
proceed within the Party. I don't intend, at this point, to go<br />
into any more details. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
