<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>634</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN PRIMARY PRODUCERS UNION OPEN CONFERENCE HELD AT CANBERRA ON 23RD OCTOBER, 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000634_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AU0) r. IVAL3* A. U, P?. IMART PRODUCEiS UI\ IION<br />
fCN 2~ R ,-) rZf T r 1L 6<br />
e iePieM~ itr the~ RJ. hon. R Me: n zicoe-<br />
, Li d ies and. Gentlemcn<br />
I thin~ lk 1 will foVollow my u lprdn; course and<br />
decla-re th e Confcrence open, Anything, I have to say thlen is<br />
9but TeConfirence Is now Oran,<br />
1 i. ave recollections of teA P.? 0 th. at go back,.<br />
a long ti. me., They are rnot all goode, I have forgo: ten hovw<br />
long ago i-t was tbhe belvtr parit of twenity years ei; en<br />
perac -bu Iremember going to 1Wrrnahibooil ' Jere any of<br />
y%: ou there that night9 It ias a very wet., &amp; dxaughity n: gh&amp;, t, just<br />
a very dra-ughty day, Th-je blew fr-Loi behind<br />
the olatfOrm at th~ e Town Ha1 nd( iv(-wore overcoalts a t tne<br />
top table; masses of food and drink.. z st.-i.. nngely ernougi, but<br />
no tiimle to apply ours'ilves to anny of tlhe;. j3, becau-: e theare wo(-re<br />
tweTntynirie speechaes ( Laughter) and mqy good ftrieiid, tihe Dote<br />
A1I. En McDonaid, v. who had -oersuaded me % to go, taci ! lecl me again<br />
a yeor or t-vo jate; r and cd " You must, cor." e. 0110!, 11 1 Said,<br />
711 don't think I can go ; rug tetnn speeches a gain.,"~<br />
Ihad to I.-sten to twerntyeighit, you s ee,. ( Laughte,). So,<br />
-1) yr. ow? 1 didnit go Yei d reporteu atrad ta hr a<br />
been a ; narked. improveiaeAu-you hnad oii. Ly twen tvthlre a ( Laughter)<br />
Lt tiI-U-he Ii: iliara t Con fererloc,<br />
But ith. o:. se we-?-e conja: atively early days. wore. nit<br />
thle y' And i muist seoy, p.:, rKcuay i1-the State of Victoria 9<br />
M17olt. Mta n d morng oSrinoOoutli A-ustralia and intLo<br />
thie hiverina and nrew vrith ver y clo: se tissociat. I-ons with Tasmania,<br />
th") e AO + PC La s b e. cmrce ra a and highJ. y-respecte'. bod~ y<br />
Ce1rbracing, of ccursef, myMany aspeets of rural liffe. I -3M<br />
always delig~ ted: 1 to fnd. bodiLes + iho are-actvivoe in this sense,<br />
becai1sSC unt ,4.1 we hav , e reached that sta-cge of perfect wbsdo. T inl<br />
which~-1 edtoha1': aet-h --J s. Ldo ~ ga it'sa a -very oodI<br />
-LifLrtg to htear botI sides of thie quesin. An I av e<br />
pa! rti-cuiariy consoicLus of in -hrntt + ies<br />
have Lad an L.+ L tca.--ñ aCL. p: b m and weLave no--vjr<br />
OX, coutroae2 an exter.-nal erobLom-develo. ping fairly quickly., Ja ch<br />
of thI-ese problems ' concerns pncd11-h -nd ustries that you<br />
s p eak f o r The i1nternal probleri is t! he problem of rnaintai:.-Ing<br />
a high rate of irnigralk-ion. encoiaragirng the davelop: aent; of-L<br />
secondarry and. tertCiary industry, as the industriLes whi. cl can<br />
give employment to a rapidly-g-owing poato -tee are<br />
Vep' 1m,, otalnt niatters, We nlever must consider thIem I nevrer<br />
do myselIf witUhout :-omembering that each. of' those matters can<br />
put OreSS'Ures on tLhe co st level i~ n Au!. stralia whI+ ich will ultimAtely<br />
come back to the primaily produicer0And I hope you irill allow<br />
moe sy tat as tI-e hec-ad of the Goverrnment, I take some<br />
pleasure out of the thiought thiat for a long time no-, w, the, better<br />
part of two years, there ' has bee.,, as viewed thI-rough-the consumer<br />
price index, stab+ Llity0<br />
Now what you want i-s stability of costs. lfh a t y ou<br />
wrould like oven more to see iw-oulIid be a edconoff cos-Ls0And<br />
( 3 0 00 06 b / 2 </p>
<p>ou2r great Jinternai -rob" -, T; is to See tha" t whatevor pressures we<br />
put on tal-e ccriomy, Jhcnwevc'r much -ee encoura go. th'Ie grCWt. h of the-,<br />
economy and. . Lin, nI 3; t17emc-ndously 1a oarat the grcwth of<br />
A'ist~~~' haO rwh or0pap uj.&amp; Lato it should all, be done<br />
on termis which enable the11-o or*. i. m-aryr industrie7, teget xot<br />
Lflg -Indutri~ es, not only to survive, but to be proofitable arid<br />
tIJo ex-oand as A astralia expands~, On the whole, we haven't been<br />
e,: ntirely withaout success in that field, but this last year Or<br />
eighteen months, several of -as as yeu Know have been iir-mersed<br />
in thne problems of the Common Markct.<br />
I thought I might just tell you a litt-le about that<br />
this afternoon. I dontt want to detain you too lon, But these<br />
are great problems end a Prime Ministers' Conference is in a<br />
sense not a very suitable piece of machinery for dealing with<br />
them. A lot of us, particularly old-fashioned fellows like<br />
myself, look back cn the Comrnonwealth and think of a few<br />
countries Gireu-t Britain, Canada, Australia, New Zealand<br />
what you the " old Corimonweicalth" where we hlad a greet<br />
deal of commrunity of inte~ rest, and you could really have a<br />
Conference and discuss most of your poroblems prett'-. y affoct,. ively.<br />
But -the Commonwalthi today has growna enorm'u sly, This last<br />
time in London, we had sixteen Pri. mo Ministers, orL their<br />
representatives, sitting at a long table, each accompanied by<br />
a Minister or two., a coip-le of ot'ficials, so that in the rjsult,<br />
we had in this Conference room not less th-An * 100 people. And<br />
thr-m becomes rather like a public meetLing, Itts not very easy<br />
to got intimate and matey with 10C, people at a Conferexnce, as<br />
you no doubt have discove-, ed., ( Lauighter)<br />
But more than that, we haave i* Lnterests wh1ich are<br />
diverse, We are greatly concernod, Ourselves, nbout our exports<br />
of whaeat, of mutton and lamb,, of beef and, 1 voci and dairy products,<br />
sugar, of metals i~ n various forms matters o) f this kind<br />
greatly concern and they conicern Canada, or some of them. do3<br />
they concern New Zealand, or seme of themr do; but thney don t<br />
greatly-concern an Asian country, except perhaps in some romrote<br />
s po ts f or s ugear0 T'hey donlt gr. eatly concern a West Indian<br />
countr;-excep.! for sugari: and the result is thlat we rapidly found<br />
-that we had a series 01' diverse-interests0 The Asian members<br />
of the ComrInnwa. thl Co) u-. d freelIy discuss the prrrticular problems<br />
that they had Like textiles arid matters of that sort, and tea.<br />
The Arancountries were greatlyv concornod about a vairiety of-Ltropi<br />
-cal r)-oductS, some of whiclh, of course, affect us in<br />
New Gluinea, and the Wes-st Z-ndies ,, ereagreatly concerned, of<br />
couse aoutsur as we ara. and othier tropical pr&amp;. oct~ cts,<br />
i~ n th e long run, the-1refore, we came to realise th--at the future<br />
of Aistralia Is inter-ests depeDndod upon a concentra tion of affort<br />
by oursolvcs end Canada and 11ew Zoaland upon -the matters which<br />
primarily co-icern us,<br />
On those topics the fact was, when the Conference<br />
met, that the negotiations botweon reat Britain and the SI~ X had<br />
not gone very far, There had been considerable discussion about<br />
cornmmdity agreements. li ll say sometiiing about that in a<br />
m-. oment, But on ail the other commodities thuft 1 have referred<br />
tthere had been no no-gotiat-ion3 There had been a great<br />
deal of to and fro between ourselves and Great Britain, for<br />
example, through offficials and Ministers, including myself, but<br />
no actual neg-otiation. 3 iA1l thatl is going on now, and until<br />
It is concluded, we won kno the nature of the bargai0 W<br />
do know that if', being con-stantly informed as we will be ais to<br />
hor it is going on, getting near-the ond of thne period, we want<br />
to have a farther conference za that we may, on the spot withl<br />
Grreat Britain, ompha13sise Our views, we can have it. That being<br />
so, I dont at all exclude the possibility that somebody will<br />
have to pack his bag-s and engage inthis kind of discussion again, </p>
<p>Tt s ea-y. The Six tool; years to cre-ate theo<br />
Treaty of Pome ye;; rs o-f di fl~ aic-ne go tiation, n hrfr<br />
you can hardly wondc-r a t it if The-ir attituda is~ " 1VIl1 it<br />
took us a long time to get t-eTrnoaty of Rome. You dori t think<br />
ar going to r'eopen tic waol~ e busi1necs ag-ain, do youcev<br />
1. s h: lghiy anderstandab-le,, But, of course, it is not theono.<br />
of the argumant, J-ust as Great Britain atahsL mu<br />
political importance -this is undoubtedlyr true to going j-n-to<br />
Europe, so I have a pretty shrewd idea,, that most of the European<br />
nations also attachi importance to Great, Britain. going in because,<br />
this will create a stronger Wstern Europe and that's wha-t theyi/<br />
alI want, 0 They Xnow that it can~ t be as strong as it otherwise<br />
wboeu l f Geat ritin is standing aslde from it.<br />
Therefore I think we ought to assxae one of the<br />
facts of life, that the British Government wants to go in for<br />
-Doli-tical reasonis and that the European nations, with one<br />
posibl exepton9also want Great Britain to go inl for<br />
political reasons. Well that's thieir judgment, not ours. We<br />
dontthave to determiine Zhat question, But it doesma I<br />
thiink, that one shouldn't despair too quickly abou-t something<br />
reasonable being hammered out en thce economic side as the price<br />
of entry,, Mind you I hiaven't yct seen any symptoms of it,,<br />
vl,, v read a 8reat I3ca! so far about Phasing out all the old<br />
preferences by 1970,. -whicha is moromTy postponing the evil hours<br />
not avoiding i-t0 B-L't We kncw whlat we want and the Britishi<br />
Government knows wvhat we want on theAnse matters aInd I've no doubt<br />
-that Mr. Heath as the chief negotiator will. do h1is best to<br />
achnieve the rfesults -that we are after.<br />
But there.. was one aspect1 of tUhe Conference in w'. ich<br />
I felt that we had made somec headway0You will all remcmbor<br />
itts years now sin1ce we first began, part. Lcula(-, rly through Mr,<br />
4o1E1A(.. n at vnrious ConforenCes, tdirect at-tention to the ,-jnde--<br />
l. ying fact of international, trade, a asLeaittdxe. heo<br />
sInce the war, and thiat Is that thie primary exporting countries<br />
like ; Iustvalia have ha7_ d theo terms of ty, ade move against triem<br />
steadily, year by year,. ' The price of what we buy has risen out<br />
of proportilon -to tii price of what we.. rE ell, anrd the te-rms of<br />
i-rade for a priinrary-pivoduciLng and. exporting country have fallen<br />
steadJ1. ly, lnde&amp; d IF th-irk they cre 4+ 0 per cent0 worse now thian<br />
they were eight or ten years ago,,<br />
We've boon directing at-tention to this and sa ying,<br />
in ef-fect5 to theo nations of th-e old wol-ld, the rich, industr!., aliZed<br />
nations, " There is not muchi point in your hLar.&amp; ing out mlin<br />
and mill1ions of eolI ars or pounds to help developing countries if,<br />
having ihelped them to develop thoir productlion, you refu~ se to buy<br />
their product on reasciiable torms0 1This is crazy, anld we have<br />
been saying so for years. T-Ihea ve pointed out that an increase<br />
of P trifling porcentago In the prices of-: primary products b-oughtJ<br />
by these industrialized countrics from overseas, an increase of'<br />
trifling percentage would mere tha-n compensate for the loss of<br />
financinl aid that has been gi-ven0<br />
It is oractical and sensible and. therefore we have<br />
constituted ourselves thlie great advocato for international<br />
coimodity agreements de~ s-Lined to produce payable prices for these<br />
conuiodities -and some stability of'th price level and some stable<br />
assurance of marketS for th", ese conmoditi--s0 Now this is<br />
tremendously importar-, n,, It, of cours-c. doesn't cover the w-, hole<br />
field., You ca' solvo 113' these pr-oblems by commocdity ag. ese<br />
but it is not difficutlt to thllin 0of a few in whiich the existence<br />
Of commodity agreernents subs cribe-d to by all the relevant countries,<br />
bothi sellers and buyers, would be of tromendous value to a country<br />
like our own. * 0 0 a a 0 // 4 </p>
<p>lWell., they have had a good deal of discussion about<br />
thatt t Brussels, They had particularly been decling with<br />
cereals and in Uarticular, in that bracket, with. whato Now,<br />
we have had a rather fluctuating experience of international<br />
wheat agreements and one of our principal buyers over a term<br />
cf years, Great Britain, has quite frankly never been very<br />
keen on commodity agreements. For a long time, she didn't<br />
associate herself with the International Wheat Agreement.<br />
She was never very keen on it, and that, of course, is something<br />
you can understand. There was what was called, in the early<br />
part of the century as part of the policy<br />
in Great Britain, " the cheap breakfast table". This is an<br />
intelligible doctrine. ' If we in Britain can buy our foodstuffs<br />
cheaply," the argument ran, " and sell our industrial commodities<br />
at a good price, well, we overcome our balance of payments<br />
problem and we are able to do things for other people in the<br />
world," Now that's very admirable, but the people who grow<br />
the commodities and who sell them and see them bei. ng destroyed<br />
in price by a temporary glut or messed around because of some<br />
loss of market or some particular treatment in another country,<br />
don't get much comfort out of knowing that people are buying<br />
these goods cheaply in some other country.<br />
Therefore, we were very anxious this time to see<br />
whether these negotiating countries were at last prepared to<br />
go seriously into the business of negotiating international<br />
commodity agreements, And the best thing that we came out<br />
of the Prime Ministers' Conference with was the communique<br />
which indicated that every Commonwealth country, includin!<br />
Great Britain, wanted to secure commnodity agreements of this<br />
kind, providing for a proper access to the market and a<br />
remunerative price level and that the countries of the Six<br />
were in agreement, in broad principle, that commodity agreements<br />
ought to be made,<br />
Now this is a good step forward. It won't be worth<br />
a thing if, having been written down, it is forgotten about,<br />
but I can assure you that we are ourselves, keeping up the<br />
pressure and, happily, keeping it up with the assistance of<br />
the United States of America, with the President of which<br />
had some most useful discussions earlier this yearo<br />
The United States is now armed with the Reciprocal<br />
Trade Act which gives the Administration of the United States<br />
great power to negotiate international arrangements and I think<br />
between one thing and another, if we can keep up the pressure,<br />
and we certainly will, we may very well expect to see, in the<br />
next year, effective steps in the direction of practical,<br />
determined negotiation, genuine negotiation for some commodity<br />
agreements. If we could start with wheat and get one est, blished<br />
there with the relevant countries involved in it, this<br />
would be a trial balloon' this would be something that would<br />
have great value in itself and by demonstrating that such<br />
agreements to preserve access and stabilize prices and keep<br />
them at an effective level can be achieved,<br />
All I want to say to you, ladies and gentlemen,<br />
is that I have been in a lot of these discussions this year<br />
over there twice, in America twice to have talks there and<br />
you need to have a lot of patience, I remember when I was a<br />
small boy in the country, somebody told me that the seed that<br />
would grow most quickly in the garden ( I was very young then;<br />
I wasn't in politics; I was about eight)( Laughter) was a<br />
radish. I'd plant them today and then at the end of the week<br />
pull one up to see how it was going. Well, we can't do that<br />
on this business. We will, I undertake to you, be unremitting COO&amp; o/ </p>
<p>iTh oil those Lratters., VIc will. righ. t ;: lrn ,.--. rnugh<br />
t-ie rert. ianing ngotia tions ' be in conston; and pec-l-Ps daily<br />
associaticn with thp . Er Llis-i negotiators on the cfficiz. l level<br />
ei weWl9a altm reserve to ourelves the right to<br />
say bofo: e finality is reached9 that we w; a nt Once more -to be<br />
her:;) d at; the topo leve'l in order that before they make the<br />
co., ncJ~ vded bargain, our interests will have been considered and,<br />
so far as we can b~ ring it about, reasonably proteocted,<br />
Now I am sorry to talkh so long about t;. iat, Sir<br />
It's all very old hat to you but I thought that spoalking<br />
directly to you 1lke -this you might be interested in one o~ o<br />
two of the aspects of a Cornforence tiic high paint of a series<br />
Of Conferences the most impartan-for -as, ever, in time of<br />
pea Ce, But -the whole objective must beg and. is, to improve<br />
our terms of trade, to give to ti-is exporting industries a pro per<br />
chance of risiLng-markets9 increasing access to thle buying<br />
comamunities of tbhe world and some price assurance which will<br />
moan that'k they can go along and produce witha thae-i cost level<br />
reasonabl. y held and therefore withi ev-ery possibility of expanded<br />
production. That's may' policy, as you rnigiat -sayq in a few<br />
sentences and having expounded it to you very briefly, I'll<br />
probably now go back anda get into some other argLunonts in<br />
t~ trhter place, burt I remind you that before I began, I declared<br />
-this Conference opon,<br />
1 conclude by sayinig that I wish you and your<br />
organisation tfte g.-eatest possible success. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
