<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1837</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER , MR, JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/04/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001837.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATE ZIONIST COUNCIL OF N. S. V1.<br />
JSRAEL'S NATIONAL DAY<br />
TOWN HALL, SYDNEY, N. S. W. 28 April 1968<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. Charge d'Affaires, Mr. Speaker, Rabbi Porush,<br />
Distinguished Guests and Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
Three days ago in Israel, near Gaza, there was dedicated<br />
a memorial to men from Australia and New Zealand and you may be<br />
sure that among them were many of the Jewish faith who rode and fought<br />
in that storied land a little more than fifty years ago, and who are still<br />
remembered by the people and the Government of Israel. They left behind<br />
them for some reason, in the country which is now Israel, feelings of<br />
friendship which have grown and flourished in the years since then as the<br />
eucalypts they planted there have grown and flourished and increased in<br />
those years. And it is possible, it can be argued, that the events of those<br />
days so long ago began not to lead to the seed of the State of Israel, because<br />
that seed had been nurtured in dreams for centuries, but perhaps with some<br />
first faltering steps to the germination of that seed, which thirty years<br />
later, and twenty years ago burst into life as the infant Jewish homeland<br />
began to grow. Now twenty years later you, as fellow Australians, have<br />
done me the honour to ask me to come and participate in your rejoicing,<br />
not at the establishment but at the re-establishment of the Jewish State.<br />
And so here in this city, this capital, where our ow;: i nation some<br />
years ago began, we all to. night, as I think it is fitting that we should, in<br />
this place where we began,, celebrate thne new begi: nin-1g of Israel some<br />
twenty years ago. This, Mr. Chairman, is a night to remember a nation that<br />
faith made real. A dream, that being cherished in hearts through centuries,<br />
ultimately became a concrete fact. And this is a night, too, to rerre mber<br />
that these kinds of developments come only through brains, devotion,<br />
dedication, unremitting effort and hard work and the willingness to sacrifice<br />
and fight to keep the reality a growing, pulsing entity. And that's been done.<br />
Sir, what a story is here what a story comes to mind,<br />
not just of that culmination of twenty years ago but of all the years and<br />
hundreds of years before that. A people conquered when? 2,00<br />
years ago a people which in spite of conquest adhered to their spiritual<br />
faith and their religious beliefs and which, because they adhered to their<br />
spiritual faith and their religious beliefs in that time, had their holy places<br />
defiled and'their cities destroyed and their nation dispersed to the corners<br />
of the earth. A people which can look back in those days on such epic<br />
stories, which can draw strength from reflecting on that human greatness<br />
which led to such actions as that thousand strong garrison of the fortress<br />
of Masada who fled, after the destruction of Jerusalem, to a high plateau<br />
and there were besieged by the Romans for two and a half to three years<br />
and held out against them all that time and then when the situation was<br />
quite hopeless, and the night before an inevitable conquest came about,<br />
killed their women and their children and themselves because they preferred<br />
to be dead than to be slaves. A people who can look back in sorrow to<br />
victimisation, persecution, massacre, injustice, in many of the lands<br />
/-3 </p>
<p>will be strengthened. So this is no time for me to talk for long. I have<br />
mentioned things, I have spoken of things which I believe must be deep<br />
in the consciousness of all people of the Jewish faith but whiCh are as<br />
true and as valid in the consciousness of people of any faith. And if in<br />
the course of speaking to you, as may be possible, I've touched on<br />
sentiments which I can feel but dimly, compared to the way they must<br />
be felt in the blood aid bone and hearts of many here, and if I have<br />
thereby trespassed perhaps, I ask your pardon. But I have done this<br />
for two reasons. Firstly because, however imperfectly, I think I have<br />
enough imagination, I think I have enough sentiment to begin to understand<br />
the pride and joy which you, as Jewish people, must be feeling today.<br />
And I want you to know this. And secondly, because I tall,, to you as<br />
Australian citizen to Australian citizen, as part of my n-ation yours<br />
and mine as I would talk to Australians of Scottish, or Irish, or<br />
Scandinavian, or whatever-it -may-be descent because in this we are<br />
one and I feel some right to rejoice with you.<br />
We have much to do here, you and 1, in this country of<br />
ours just as there is much to do in Israel, and as in Israel our far<br />
tomorrows may see greatness, if we have the passion to live and create,<br />
joined with a willingness to sacrifice and if need be die to preserve.<br />
In one sense, the creation of Israel might be regarded as<br />
a miracle, but as a great Jewish writer many years ago pointed out: " A<br />
miracle cannot prove that which is impossible. It is useful only of a<br />
confirmation of that which is possible". Perhaps everything is possible<br />
for Israel -and Australia, given the spirit, given the endurance, given<br />
the willingness, given the sacrifice, and I hope th at, both here and in<br />
Israel, things now thought to be impossible will be shown to be possible<br />
even if people may regard that as a miracle. One thing is sure and<br />
having said this I'll sit down one thing i3 sure, that the values of a<br />
human individual, the rights of a man to live ' his own' life without fear<br />
of those eternal allies of totalitarianism, the secret police, the torture<br />
chamber and the hangman, are rights which must be defended to the<br />
death, are rights which if they are defended will lead to that full,<br />
peaceful, happy life which yet eludes us, but for which you, as people of<br />
Jewish faith, have striven and will strive, and for which you, as Australians<br />
in Australia, will strive with me.<br />
I thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
