<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>87</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 28/1959 - DAIRYING INDUSTRY COMMITTEE - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R G MENZIES, CH, QC, MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/07/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000087.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PESS: P2M8./ N1O905.9 .<br />
DAIRYING INDUSTRY COMMITTEE.<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R. G. MENZISC. H.. Q. C. MP.<br />
In my last Policy Speech I foreshadowed the appointment<br />
of a strong committee to enquire into the various aspects of the<br />
Australian Dairying Industry. The reason for this announcement<br />
was that the Government felt and feels that the problems of the<br />
dairying industry need to be objectively examined with a view to<br />
evolving policies calculated to ensure efficiency and economic<br />
stability. We have now appointed a committee under the chairmanship<br />
of Mr. M. E. McCarthy. Its terms of reference are very<br />
comprehensive, It has to consider the conditions, structure and<br />
problems of the industry against the background of the overall<br />
interests of the nation.<br />
The committee will hold its first meeting in Melbourne<br />
tomorrow ( Thursday). I want to emphasise the extreme importance of this<br />
enquiry which will, 9 I hope, lead to conclusions of a comprehensive<br />
kind. The committee will visit many dairying districts in order<br />
to collect information on the spot. It will have, I am assured,<br />
co-operative help from the various State Governmenits and<br />
departments. Its work, if it is to be successful, will require<br />
full and frank expressions of opinion and propositions of fact<br />
from a great variety of people. This means that information has to<br />
be obtained not only from those who speak for various branches of<br />
the industry but from other citizens who may have criticisms to<br />
offer or suggestions to make. The greater the public interest in<br />
this enquiry, the more likely is it that the committee will be<br />
able to hear and consider conflicting views, not onl y from<br />
producers and from consumers but also from anybody else who<br />
appreciates the importance to the nation of having the whole matter<br />
put upon a sound economic footing.<br />
I express the hope, therefore, that there will be<br />
considerable public interest in the committee's proceedings and<br />
that anybody who feels that he or she has some useful suggestion<br />
or criticism to make should feel at liberty to present these to<br />
the committee. Mr. McCarthy himself is a man of immense experience,<br />
having dealt with many great problems for the Commnonwealth<br />
Government, He has an independent mind and he has with him a<br />
committee selected for its variety of experience and its capacity<br />
for study and judgment.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T.<br />
22nd July, 1959.<br />
FOR PRESS% </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
