<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4915</transcript-id>
    <title>FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004915.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRSS 5 DECEMBER 1978<br />
FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY<br />
The Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. J. Y1. Fraser, M. P.,<br />
announced today that he intended approaching the State Premiers<br />
with a view to developing a closer working relationship between<br />
the Foreign Investment Review Board and State Government<br />
authorities.<br />
Mr Fraser said that foreign investment has implications for<br />
State interests as well as national interests and the Government<br />
had always recognised the value of close liaison with the States<br />
on foreign investment matters. In this regard, ' the Government<br />
had made it a function of the Foreign Investment Review Board<br />
to establish appropriate liaison with State Government authorities.<br />
Mr Fraser said that the Board had developed the practice of consulting<br />
relevent State authorities on foreign investment proposals<br />
that had significance for the States in order that State views<br />
could be taken fully into account. The cooperation of the States<br />
in this regard had been mutually beneficial and the Government<br />
considered that there would be value in strengthening the existing<br />
relationships. In June last, Mr Fraser said, the Treasurer announced some<br />
changes to the foreign investment guidelines following a review<br />
of their operation over the preceding two years. It was decided<br />
in that review that the essential features of the policy announced<br />
in April 1976 should be maintained. The policy is designed to<br />
provide a favourable climate for foreign investment on terms<br />
consistent with Australia's national interests and the provision<br />
of maximum opportunities for Australians to participate in major<br />
projects. At the same time, the Government decided to relax a<br />
number of administrative procedures and special facilities were<br />
introduced to encourage predominantly foreign owned companies<br />
in Australia to move towards majority Australian ownership.<br />
Following the announcement of these changes, the Treasurer<br />
arranged for the Executive member of the Foreign Investment<br />
Review Board to visit the States to explain and discuss the<br />
policy with State Government officials. The subject was also<br />
raised at the Premiers' Conference in June. </p>
<p>2.<br />
In the course of the review of foreign investment policy,<br />
the Prime Minister said the Government noted that some<br />
foreign investors had expressed some concern about the<br />
possibility of State Government requirements on foreign<br />
ownership and control running counter to the Commonwealth<br />
guidelines. The view had been put forward that this could<br />
create uncertainties that might discourage foreign investment<br />
in Australia. The Government believes it would be in the<br />
interests of the Commonwealth and the States to make it clear<br />
to foreign investors that there is a common approach within the<br />
general framework provided by the Commonwealth's foreign<br />
investment guidelines'. The Prime Minister said he would<br />
be suggesting to the State Premiers that there should be<br />
further discussions between the Foreign Investment Review<br />
Board and State officials on this matter. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
