<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10857</transcript-id>
    <title>GREATER OPPORTUNITIES FOR WOMEN IN GOVERNMENT DECISION MAKING</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p> I am pleased to announce that the Federal Government has taken</p>
<p> another step in securing greater choice for women with an initiative</p>
<p> to place more highly qualified women on Commonwealth boards and agencies.</p>
<p>The Government today launches the Executive Search Pilot Programme</p>
<p> in a bid to further increase the representation of women on over 750</p>
<p> board and agency positions within the Commonwealth Government.</p>
<p>Executive search firm Profile Ray &amp; Berndtson will conduct a nationwide</p>
<p> search for suitably qualified women with high level skills across</p>
<p> a variety of fields.</p>
<p>The Government will also implement an "early warning system"</p>
<p> for all Commonwealth portfolios whereby the Office of Status of Women</p>
<p> will put forward details of suitably qualified women for upcoming</p>
<p> board vacancies approximately six months before any position arises.</p>
<p>Representation by women on Commonwealth Boards is now over 30 percent</p>
<p> but the Government will do more to provide additional support and</p>
<p> assistance for women in business.</p>
<p>The Government is also working with the Australian Council of Businesswomen</p>
<p> on a National Women's Leadership Project to select and train</p>
<p> suitable women candidates for possible appointments to private sector</p>
<p> boards.</p>
<p> Additionally, the Committee for Economic Development of Australia</p>
<p> (CEDA) has agreed in principle to supply mentors for participants</p>
<p> in the project and to provide networking at a very high level to maximise</p>
<p> opportunities.</p>
<p>The Government is also working with the Business Council of Australia</p>
<p> to identify the needs of women in small business and to foster a friendlier</p>
<p> environment for women entering small business.</p>
<p>These initiatives build upon my Government's strong commitment</p>
<p> to all women and will provide them with the choice, opportunity and</p>
<p> flexibility to develop their full potential in the workplace, home</p>
<p> and with the family.</p>
<p> 27 March 1998</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
