<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>449</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 17/1962 - CONFERENCE WITH BUILDERS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/01/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000449.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. / 62<br />
CONFERENCE ITH KT. TLP,<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt, Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
This evening representatives of the Master Builders!<br />
Federation of Australia discussed with the Prime Minister and<br />
other Commonwealth Ministers recent and prospective developments<br />
in the building industry.<br />
The Federation was represented by Mr. J0Bryant<br />
President; Messrs H. tilckens and A. V. Jennings; and Mr. LR.<br />
Dudley, -xecutive Director.<br />
Representatives of the Federation emphasised the<br />
desirability of a quick lift in employment. They submitted a<br />
number of short term and long term proposals designed co<br />
stimulate home building activity, and also commercial build. ing.<br />
The short term proposals were:<br />
Injection through Housing Societies and Savings Banks of<br />
funds to lift construction,<br />
An immediate release of overdraft accommodation by the<br />
Banks, and<br />
An increase in the size of maximum loans.<br />
In the longer term they recommended the establishment<br />
of a Federal Home Finance and Mortgage Bank to perform specialisfunctions<br />
in the home building field, encouraament of self-help<br />
through greater savings and housing bonds rith special<br />
conditions, and the announcement of 5-year targets.<br />
The Federation also proposed the immediate<br />
introduction of a depreciation allowance on income-producing<br />
buildings. Mr. Menzies said that the story told by those with<br />
practical experience in the building industry was most valuable,<br />
and that the proposals submitted by the Federation would be<br />
taken into consideration by the Goverr: rent in formulating its<br />
short and long term plans.<br />
CANBEPRA, January, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
