<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7568</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH GREG CARY RADIO 4BC 13/4/89</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/04/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007568.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A6 -M I<br />
fift<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH GREG CARY RADIO 4BC 13/ 4/ 89.<br />
E 0 E Proof only.<br />
CARY: Good morning Mr Hawke. The question is was* this the<br />
right time to honour the promise?<br />
PM: Well it is the time I said I'd deliver the promise, I ' said<br />
last year 12 months ago that we would deliver tax cuts from<br />
July 1 1989. It's not a question of whether it's the right time,<br />
it's the time I promised, therefore, it is the time it was<br />
delivered. CARY: Yes, even given the promise, if it wasn't economically<br />
the right time I think many would have forgiven you for holding.<br />
back a little.<br />
PM: Well it was the right time, because remember the<br />
circumstances of the delivery of the promise. I said then if we<br />
got a responsible wages outcome during 1988-89, that if restraint<br />
was exercised, and that on the basis of that we could get the<br />
promise of restraint for 1989-90, then we would deliver on 1<br />
July. Now, the first condition was met, the unions exercised<br />
very considerable restraint during 1988-89. . Now at the point<br />
when decisions had to be made about wages outcome for 1989-90 and<br />
the condition of restraint, remarkable restraint for this coming<br />
year, was the delivery of the tax cuts now.. It would have been<br />
the height of economic ( ir) responsibility not to have delivered<br />
because what you would have had then was a wages explosion which<br />
would have destroyed the economy.<br />
CARYs What then is the premise of what the Treasurer delivered<br />
last night? What do you hope or anticipate would be the outcome?<br />
PM: These outcomes. Firstly, I've gone to the major one that is<br />
a responsible wages outcome just let me point out the fact of<br />
history, briefly, that everytime in the past where you've had a<br />
surge of income that's associated with a high level of economic<br />
activity that we'vye got now, you'vye had a wages explosion which<br />
has led to a subsequent very serious recession, stoppage of<br />
growth and explosion of unemployment and prices. Now, on this<br />
occasion, as a result of getting the commitment of the trade<br />
union movement to a very restrained wages outcome in the 12<br />
months ahead, it means that we will have an economy which will<br />
continue to grow, not at the high level of growth we've had in<br />
the last 12 months because a s/ 2<br />
STER </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM ( cont): I<br />
we can't sustain that in terms of the level of imports, but we'll<br />
still have growth, employment growing, we'll have a downward path<br />
of inflation and we will create the conditions which when we've<br />
brought the level of economic activity down, we will start to be<br />
able to see interest rates coming down. So that's the overall<br />
economic strategy that we've shown that we can deliver. As the<br />
Treasurer said last night the key to the successful conduct of<br />
economic policy is wages policy. The other mob destroyed the<br />
economy because they didn't have a' ' wages policy and had tax cuts<br />
there in 1982 in the context of a wages explosion of about 17%.<br />
You can't carry that, what we've done is to give a wage increase<br />
equivalent in the order of about 12% on average but at a cost of<br />
about six and a half percent to employers.<br />
CARY; Yes, you talk about carrying that heavy load, I guess many<br />
will look to interest rates now and when you say you've delivered<br />
in certain areas I think many well you'd have to concede that<br />
inflation is high and looks to be going higher.<br />
PM: No it's not. The basic rate of inflation will be coming<br />
down. CARY: Well that's a projection.<br />
PM: Yes, but in fact the evidence sustains that proposition<br />
because with a six and a half percent wages outcome in prospect<br />
and taking productivity into account, the assessment of our<br />
advisers as well as our own is that the rate of inflation will be<br />
trending down, but you've got to have this qualification now as a<br />
result of the disastrous floods and I think everyone will<br />
understand we can't control the weather as a result of the<br />
floods you will have fresh fruit and vegetable prices will go up<br />
in the next quarter and that's unfortunate. But you take that<br />
aside and we're entitled to, you have the underlying rate of<br />
inflation will be coming down.<br />
CARYt Can you guarantee a rise in productivity though?<br />
PH: Yes, you see one of the cute little. exercises of these<br />
policy-less mob opposite us, the Howards and the Peacocks, they<br />
say we haven't had high productivity growth figures and they do<br />
that by measuring it against the growth in employment. Now, o~ f<br />
course, if you have a rate of employment growth which is twice as<br />
fast as the rest of the world and four times faster than the<br />
miserable effort they achieved in their seven years in office, of<br />
course if you've got high rates of growth in employment, then<br />
your labour productivity figures don't rise 5o much, but we will<br />
have a productivity performance I think in the next twelve months<br />
of which we will be able to be proud and which will mean that our<br />
growth in exports will continue. The important thing, and I do<br />
hope I can get this </p>
<p>-3<br />
PM ( cont)<br />
message across to your listeners, is that the secret is not just<br />
getting the growth in exports by becoming more competitive as<br />
we've shown we can do, but at the same time as we get this<br />
increase in exports we've got to make sure that we don't have<br />
imports growing at such a high level. Now, this is where your<br />
listeners can come into it. We can get the right policies in<br />
Canberra and if we can get the co-operation of your listeners and<br />
the Australian public in the way we have with wage restraint, the<br />
way each and every one of your listeners this morning can say now<br />
we' 11 play our part is by using the wage increases that will come<br />
this year and the tax cuts and the increases in family<br />
allowances, if they're. going to save thosethey are going to<br />
spend it, each one of them should say to themselves we're going<br />
to spend those things on Australian-made products. Each one of<br />
your listeners can play a part in getting the outcome that we all<br />
want. CARY: Can they always be guaranteed that the product they're<br />
buying, even if it says Made in Australia, is an Australian<br />
product? Many of our listeners complained that that's not the<br />
case. PM: The way they can do it is by looking at the Australian-made<br />
campaign and looking at the Australian-made logo the green and<br />
gold logo with the Kangaroo and that is only p * rovided to<br />
companies who are part of the officially-endorsed Australianmade<br />
campaign. if you look for the logo you can be sure that<br />
that is an Australian made product.<br />
CARY: I appreciate the point you're making and hopefully many<br />
will do that, but you say if our listeners choose to spend rather<br />
than save the wage rises and tax deductions, history proves<br />
doesn't it that people tend rather to spend the money rather than<br />
save it, would you like them to save the money?<br />
PM; Yes, I like to see some saving in fact the evidence of the<br />
last two years has shown an increase in the saving ratio, that<br />
people have been tending to save more. Now, of course, I'm not<br />
unrealistic, people will want to and need, to spend in many cases<br />
siginificant proportion of the cash in hand they get as a result<br />
of the tax cuts, the increases in family allowances, dependent<br />
allowances and so on, and the wages increases that come. I<br />
acknowledge of course they're going to need to spend, but to the<br />
extent that it's not necessary, Australia's interest would be<br />
served by them saving, but I get back to the point please and<br />
this is a personal plea to every one of your listeners, when you<br />
g0oOut to the shops and do your buying, try as far as you<br />
possibly can to ensure that it's an Australian made product that<br />
you purchase. ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
CARY: I made the point a little earlier, arnd a couple of<br />
listeners have made a similar point, not so much a point but ask<br />
a question, we're just getting mixed signals it seems to me<br />
anyway, a couple of weeks ago and last week even your saying the<br />
even basic problem was we had an over-heated economy that was<br />
spending too much and as you say a lot of that spending was going<br />
on products from overseas, and yet now we're getting more money<br />
to go out and spend more. I just can't add the two up.<br />
PM: , Well it's a fair question and let me give you the answer.<br />
We've had consumption growing in the last 12 months about 8% t and<br />
we've had production growing about Now the gap between the 4<br />
and the 8 is simply provided by imports. Now there have been<br />
very particular features in the composition of the high level of<br />
demand. investment has been at the highest level for 40 years as<br />
a proportion of our production, highest level for 40 years,<br />
massive investment in terms of hotels, factories, nonresidential<br />
buildings, in plant and equipment. Now we won't get<br />
that element of demand, that sort of increase in demand will not<br />
be reflected in this next financial year. Secondly, there has<br />
been this very big improvement in the terms of trade in the order<br />
of about 12% and that by definition has meant the influx of much<br />
more income into this country because of changes of that order in<br />
the terms of trade. Now what we're getting for our exports<br />
improving relatively to what we ar e paying f or our imports now<br />
that won't be repeated. So those two f actors together plus we<br />
won't get the repetition of the high level of house construction,<br />
all things will mean a lessening, a significant lessening in the<br />
level of demand and it's within that framework that you are going<br />
to be able to accommodate the sort of slight increases in<br />
consumer demand that will be associated with the decisions we<br />
made last night.<br />
CARY: At a time though when you're asking us to save more, why<br />
is there. no incentive there for us to save.<br />
PK4: There is every incentive because I think if people take the<br />
view that you're going to be looking at a long term lowering of<br />
the inflation rate, that's an incentive and I believe that is the<br />
situation. I think also people realise that it is in the<br />
interests of the country to save and as I say in the last couple<br />
of years there has been about a 2% increase in the savings ratio,<br />
and so it is working.<br />
CARY: We did a poll on the show yesterday Prime Minister, or<br />
the day before, talking about banks and these interest rates<br />
going up, and to use the jargon people think there's a giant con<br />
going on somewhere. We had a poll that indicated 98% don't trust<br />
the banks. That doesn't augur well, surely. </p>
<p>PM: -Well in a sense the community can't have it both ways. I<br />
mean there was overwhelming endorsement of what we did in 1983 to<br />
deregulate the financial sector by our actual decisions and also<br />
by bringing in a significantly larger number of banks from<br />
overseas so that the cosy little cartels that the Australian<br />
private banks had before was no longer operative. Now, people<br />
want a deregulated financial sector, it's there and it's now<br />
operating. Let me just make the basic point, however, about the level of<br />
interest rates. As I've said so many times and I want your<br />
listeners to understand it Bob Hawke's not dumb, I might be<br />
some other things but I'm not dumb or stupid and I want the<br />
electorate to be as happy as possible. I know that the<br />
electorate don't like high interest rates, I haven't got interest<br />
rates, and will not have them higher for one day longer than is<br />
absolutely necessary in terms of economic management. You've got<br />
three instruments that you can use to manage the economy, you've<br />
got what we call fiscal policy, Budget and taxes, that's what you<br />
do about the Budget and tamand so on and we've got that as tight<br />
as a drum I mean in terms of our public outlays, what we spend<br />
there's been three successive years of real reductions in what we<br />
spend as a Government and that's what the people want to see;<br />
you've got wages policy as tight as a drum because if we didn't<br />
do what we're doing now you'd have a wagesexplosion of about 16%,<br />
against the 6% we're talking about now. Now that leaves the<br />
third which is monetary policy. We can't have a position where<br />
we just have an economy bubbling away at such a high level that<br />
it's sucking in imports that we can't pay for by our exports. So<br />
you've got to bring down the level of activity a bit by having<br />
high interest rates. * I don't like to have to do it but that's<br />
all that Can be done and as soon as we have the economy coming<br />
down to a better level of equilibrium, at a lower level of<br />
growth, then monetary policy will be eased and interest rates<br />
will come down. The worst thing I could do for your listeners at<br />
the moment though would be to ease monetary policy because we<br />
then would have an explosion which would wreck the economy. 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
CARYs Yes, I just wonder and again it's been a response of a<br />
lot of our listeners over recent times, as you'd appreciate,<br />
who's looking at the banks? I guess people Just wonder if<br />
interest rates need to be as high as they are at a time when<br />
banks are making record profits. People just wonder why all the<br />
charges have to be implemented at a time when the banks are<br />
making record profits. Are you happy with the way the banks are<br />
operating in general terms?<br />
PM4: Well I think there is a natural enough tendency, not the<br />
one that I approve of, for them always to go a little bit earlier<br />
in terms of raising rates than maybe is absolutely necessary, but<br />
the fact and to be fair is that we are saying if there needs to<br />
be a tight monetary policy that interest rates do need to be high<br />
f or the reasons I've just outlined. That thing that we will be<br />
watching very closely, and this I think is the most important<br />
point, we will be watching very closely to ensure that when the<br />
signal is there for an easing of monetary policy and for rates to<br />
come down, that they move downwards with the same alacrity with<br />
which they have moved upwards.<br />
CARY: yes, we're talking about something that it is very hard to<br />
put timetables upon. But can you give us some kind of projection<br />
when we might expect some kind of easing?<br />
P14: I said in January of this year when asked I didn't<br />
volunteer the question but I was asked in Perth earlier this year<br />
did I think that interest rates would come down before the end<br />
of the year. I said yes. I've got no reason to change that<br />
answer. CARY: An early election totally out of the question?<br />
PM: Yes, absolutely, it's a funny one this. I promised in the<br />
' middle of last year that I'd deliver tax Cuts on July 1, I'm now<br />
being criticised by little Johnny Howard, saying " ooh Mr Hawke' s<br />
going to have an election, fancy him bringing in the cuts now"<br />
What would he have said if I hadn't brought them in when I<br />
promised twelve months ago " Mr Hawke breaks his promise". I mean<br />
with the Howards of this world you can't win, but let me say when<br />
I start winning with John Howard I'll be worried.<br />
CARY: One of the other problems our listeners are having are<br />
with those who aren't paying what they believe to be their<br />
responsible amount of taxation. The Treasurer addressed that to<br />
some end last night. / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
PM: Oh yes, we of course have done more than has ever been done<br />
before to make those with the capacity to pay, pay. You remember<br />
that it was Mr Howard's own Royal Commnissioner Costigan who said<br />
that in 1980-81 of the tax system of this country that the tax<br />
avoidance industry was the fastest-growing industry in Australia.<br />
Howard, under his Prime Minister and he had the major<br />
responsibility Howard allowed those with the capacity to pay,<br />
not to pay. Now we have done more to impose upon the rich in<br />
this community the obligation to pay where they weren't paying<br />
before and on companies to pay. Now in regard to this area of<br />
tax havens, we had to make sure in the legislation we bring in<br />
that we get it right, we have and it will mean from next year<br />
that those tax havens will be closed. They will not be able to<br />
be used by companies to avoid their obligations. As their income<br />
accrues they will have to pay their tax here.<br />
CARY: Why has it taken so long though?<br />
Pids It's a very complex issue because you've got to deal with<br />
the distinction between companies who are legitimately operating<br />
actual commercial activities and economic activities in these<br />
countries as against where they are just using these places for<br />
paper purposes, avoidance purposes; and you also have to get also<br />
arrangements and understandings with the countries concerned. it<br />
is recognised around the world as one of the most complex areas<br />
of tax decision-making and you've got to make sure that you get<br />
it right so that you are not going to make decisions which will<br />
act as a disincentive to legitimate economic operations of<br />
Australian enterprises overseas. Because you must understand<br />
that in this whole area of our external accounts problem that the<br />
earning of income overseas legitimately by Australian companies<br />
is something to be encouraged because it is an off-setting factor<br />
to our current account deficit. So you've got to make sure that<br />
the decisions you take which are targeted against people using<br />
these havens just for tax avoidance purposes, are not decisions<br />
which discourage legitimate economic activity by Australian<br />
companies overseas which can be to the benefit of Australia.<br />
CARY: Prime Minister I think it's fair to say that in the run up<br />
to the last election you indicated the worst was behind us.<br />
Things have been crook for the average Australian family, is the<br />
worst behind us now? </p>
<p>-8<br />
PM: Well I think as far as what we have to do in this country,<br />
that is it is a case it is in other words it is not until<br />
that we've felt that we have been in a position to make the<br />
substantial tax cuts and improvements in family allowances and so<br />
on that we have felt able to make now and to do the things for<br />
pensioners that I know they have welcomed. Now having said that<br />
we have always got to watch what happens overseas I mean if the<br />
world economy were to collapse then we would have to deal with<br />
that situation. But on-the assumption, Greg, which I think is a<br />
fair assumption that the world economy is going to continue to<br />
grow, that we're not facing a world economic recession and<br />
therefore a collapse of our commodity prices, then I think your<br />
observation is a fair one.<br />
CARY: And if you were to leave us with one observation about<br />
last night, if we were to take one thing in conclusion from it,<br />
what would that be?<br />
PM: I think it would be this. The Government has made the<br />
decision to make an increase in disposable income available-to<br />
the Australian people, they've earned it, they deserve it, and I<br />
want and plead with the Australian people, your listeners, to say<br />
now what is it that we can do in those circumstances that's best<br />
for Australia. I repeat the message, to the extent that they are<br />
going to spend what we have now put in their hands, spend it on<br />
Australian made products. That's the message.<br />
CAMY Good to talk to you.<br />
PM: Thank you very much Greg.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
