<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2145</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 85/1969 - RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS FOR 1969/1970 STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002145.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. L No. 85/ 1969<br />
RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL<br />
FOR THE ARTS FOR 1969/ 1970<br />
Statement by the _ Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
I have received from the Chairman of the Australian Council<br />
for the Arts the Council's recommendations concerning the major grants<br />
to be made by the Commonwealth Government in support of the performing<br />
arts in the current financial year.<br />
As I announced in August, the Commonwealth Government<br />
will be providing greatly increased support for the work of the Australian<br />
Council in 1970. The Government has done this because of its conviction<br />
that the arts have a vital role to play in the life of this country. Living in<br />
a technological age imposes great strains on an individual. People now<br />
live mainly in vast cities, subject to noise and speed and a multitude of<br />
stresses and strains, not the least of which is the feeling that somewhere<br />
in all this modern technological advancement the human individual has lost<br />
something of his dignity and value.<br />
The arts assert above all the value of the individual. The<br />
great legacy of world art is no more than the sum of individual talent,<br />
individual skills, individual imagination fired by personal vision. The<br />
urge to find expression for feelings and ideas by creating something, by<br />
seeking new words in poetry or prose, by shaping clay, by painting, or<br />
dancing, -by singing or making music or sculpture this urge is fundamental<br />
to man, and one of the great sources of enrichment of human life. Unless<br />
people have some contact with the arts, either creating them or enjoying<br />
them as spectators, their lives are greatly impoverished. In Australia,<br />
where we enjoy a very high standard of material living, it is all the more<br />
important for us to have access to the things in life which provide beauty<br />
and stimulus and a rich personal experience.<br />
In putting forward its proposals for the major grants for<br />
1969/ 1970, the Australian Council has adhered to the same principles<br />
which guided its policies in the past year. Because it-sees the Federal<br />
Government as having a responsibility to establish and maintain the highest<br />
possible standards of artistic endeavour, and to provide a possibility for<br />
talented young Australians to pursue a professional career in their own<br />
country if they wish to do so, it has recommended that the Government<br />
continue to support and develop national level companies in opera, ballet<br />
and drama. It is also concerned to see that standards of national training<br />
in the arts are as high as possible and it is proposing to expand its interest<br />
and responsibility in this area. It has also developed programmes to give<br />
increased access to the arts for country people, to encourage in young<br />
people a love and understanding of the arts, and to promote international<br />
exchanges between Australia and countries with different cultural traditions.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
One of the hopes of my Government in making funds available<br />
for the arts is that this will stimulate contributions from many other sources.<br />
I am particularly gratified to see that there have already been substantial<br />
increases in the present year, particularly from certain of the State<br />
Governments who have added considerable sums to the generous provisions<br />
which they are already making, often in the form of splendid buildings and<br />
homes for the arts. Because of the -generosity of some of the State<br />
Governments it has been possible to establish a new national theatre<br />
orchestra and one new State drama company, and there are instances of<br />
co-operative support in many ventures throughout the various States. As<br />
the years go by we will hope to expand this valuable co-operation with<br />
State and local governments throughout the Commonwealth.<br />
1969 was the first year of activity for the Australian Council,<br />
and the Government is proud of the progress already made. The Government,<br />
through the Council, was able to stimulate and support artistic activity of<br />
a very wide variety. As well as the major company activities which<br />
provided ballet, opera, puppets and drama in all States of Australia, the<br />
Special Projects Fund set up by the Council provided assistance to dozens<br />
of smaller companies throughout the country, and supported several projects<br />
of particular interest a retreat for playwrights at the University of New<br />
England, a competition for young music ensembles, a script writing contest<br />
for Australian writers, a visit to Australia by one of America's leading<br />
modern dance teachers, an experimental film and electronic production<br />
which will tour Australia in the coming year. New plays, operas and<br />
ballets were commissioned. More young people than ever before were<br />
allowed into theatres at concession rates. Australia was well represented<br />
abroad by two chamber groups and one choir, all of which received<br />
international acclaim for the standard of their work.<br />
Next year, with the increased funds available, promises to<br />
be very much more exciting. One of the world's most famous ballet<br />
dancers Rudolf Nureyev, will be coming to Australia to dance with our<br />
national ballet company. Sir Tyrone Guthrie, the world-famous producer,<br />
will be spending some months here working with the Melbourne Theatre<br />
Company, the Old Tote Company and possibly in Western Australia as well.<br />
Dance groups from Asia, opera and drama companies from Britain and other<br />
international groups will spend some time in Australia in the course of the<br />
year. We ourselves will be sending abroad an excellent new chamber<br />
orchestra recently formed in this country.<br />
The Australian Council has commissioned a number of<br />
reports, and has sought advice from its committees on new areas of<br />
work which it is hoping to undertake programmes of support for training<br />
professional theatre personnel, expanded assistance to music, an important<br />
new programme of assistance and stimulus for Aboriginal arts. </p>
<p>3-<br />
The Special Projects Fund, which was such a success in<br />
1969, will be considerably expanded for the coming year. It will provide<br />
a wide variety of professional services to small companies throughout<br />
Australia. It will bring in some of the best international teachers and<br />
producers to work with Australian artists. It will support a play-reading<br />
and advisory service for Australian playwrights and a workshop to allow<br />
young writers to see their work performed. It will provide assistance for<br />
the production of several new Australian plays and one new Australian<br />
musical. It will help develop, in conjunction with the trade unions, a<br />
programme of union interest and activity in the arts similar to those which<br />
flourish in some other countries. It will support experimental work and<br />
innovation in dance, drama, opera and music, and seek out new audiences<br />
for the arts in various ways. It will help in certain special areas such as<br />
New Guinea, and will generally seek to provide support wherever the<br />
possibility exists of stimulating interest or raising standards in the arts<br />
throughout Australia. In one area in particular a significant new step has been<br />
taken. That is in the Government's commitment to provide support for<br />
Australian film and television makers. The Government has accepted the<br />
report of the film committee of the Australian Council which recommended<br />
that a national film and television training school should be established,<br />
that a fund should be set up to provide assistance for experiment in film<br />
and television making, and that the Government should establish a National<br />
Film and Television Development Corporation to provide stimulus to the<br />
fiUm industry in this country. All of these proposals have been agreed to.<br />
The Interim Council of the Film and Television Training School has been<br />
announced and will shortly be beginning its work to determine a location<br />
for this important new national institution. Arrangements are at present<br />
being made for the administration of the experimental fund, and an<br />
announcement is expected early in the New Year. The Government will<br />
also be announcing its intentions before very long with regard to the<br />
National Film and Television Development Corporation.<br />
The Government is particularly pleased to be able to provide<br />
support for Australian film makers. It is aware of the representations<br />
which have been made over many decades for such assistance, and in the<br />
1970' s, where film and television will play such a major role in the mass<br />
communications of an electronic age, it is proper that Australian talents<br />
and skills should be developed so that the voice of this country may be<br />
heard and its image known abroad.<br />
From time to time during the year other grants recommended<br />
by the Australian Council will be announced. Meanwhile I have pleasure in<br />
announcing the first series of major grants recommended by the Council.<br />
CANBERRA 3 December 1969<br />
Note: This statement is being released in Sydney and Canberra. In Sydney,<br />
it will be issued at a press conference to be given by the Council's<br />
Chairman, Dr. Coombs, at 4 p. m. </p>
<p>GRANTS RECOMMENDED BY THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL<br />
FOR THE ARTS FOR THE YEAR 1969/ 1970<br />
1. TRAINING INSTITUTIONS<br />
a) National Institute of Dramatic Art 52,000<br />
b) Australian Ballet School 140,000<br />
c) Professional Training Programmes for<br />
Theatre Personnel 8,000<br />
2. NATIONAL TOURING COMPANIES<br />
a) The Australian Ballet 290,000<br />
b) The Australian Opera 290,000<br />
c) Elizabethan Trust Orchestra 380,000<br />
d) Marionette Theatre 40,000<br />
3. STATE DRAMA ACTIVITIES<br />
a) Old Tote Theatre Company, N. S. W. 100,000<br />
b) Melbourne Theatre Company 110,000o<br />
c) South Australian Theatre Company 31,000<br />
d) Queensland Theatre Company 27,000<br />
e) Canberra Theatre Trust 15,000O<br />
f) National Theatre at the Playhouse, Perth 30,000<br />
g) Tasmania 27,000<br />
4. REGIONAL THEAT11E ORGANISATIONS ASSISTED FROM<br />
THE SPECIAL PRcfCT I'* N<br />
a) New South Wales Professional Drama, Sydne<br />
Ensemble Theatre<br />
Independent Theatre) ( in total) 20,000<br />
Community Theatre)<br />
b) Victoria St. Martin's Theatre 8,500<br />
Victorian Opera Company 4,000<br />
Ballet Victoria 5,000<br />
c) South Australia<br />
Australian Dance Theatre 5,00<br />
d) Queensland Queensland Ballet Company) ( in total) 17,000<br />
Queensland Opera Company)<br />
e) Western Australia<br />
Western Australian Opera Company 10,000<br />
West Australian Ballet Company 8,000<br />
Hole-in-the-Wall Theatre 2,500<br />
f) Australian Capital Territory<br />
Canberra Repertory Society 3,500 </p>
<p>SPECIAL PROJECTS FUND<br />
A Fund to support a wide variety of activities in the<br />
performing arts such as the provision of professional<br />
services, sponsoring of internatilonal visits, underwriting<br />
special productions and productions of new<br />
Australian plays, operas and ballets, encouraging the<br />
interest of young people in the arts, supporting creative<br />
workers in the performing arts, assisting trade union<br />
arts programmes, programmes of experimental work,<br />
activities designed to develop new or special audiences<br />
and awards to encourage higher standards of criticism.<br />
Details still to be announced. 216, 500<br />
6. ABORIGINAL ARTS PROGRAMME<br />
( Details still to be announced) 60,000<br />
7. MUSIC ACTIVITIES<br />
( Details still to be announced) 50, 000<br />
8. FEDERAL CO-ORDINATING AND ENTREPRENEURIAL<br />
ORGANISATIONS a) Australian Elizabethan Theatre Trust for its<br />
administration, production division and entrepreneurial<br />
activities ( subject to agreement on grants to associated<br />
companies) 270,000<br />
b) Arts Council of Australia Federal Division for its<br />
administration and country touring programmes ( plus<br />
a reserve of $ 35, 000 for additional activities still to<br />
be developed) 40,000<br />
c) Musica Viva Society 8,000<br />
9. STUDIES AND REPORTS<br />
( Details still to be announced) 20,000<br />
INTERNATIONAiL TOURS<br />
a) Adelaide Festival of the Arts English Opera Group 18, 000<br />
b) Musica Viva Society South East Asia Tour by Robert<br />
Pikler Chamber Orchestra 10,000<br />
Further details still to be announced.<br />
11. FESTIVALS<br />
a) Adelaide Festival of Arts 15,000<br />
b) Festival of Perth 15,0( 0<br />
c) Moomba Festival 8,600<br />
Further details still to be announced.<br />
12. FILM ACTIVITIES<br />
The establishment of the Interim Council of the National Film<br />
and Television School, the Experimental Fund and Exhibiting<br />
Fund. Details still to be announced. 300, 000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
