<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9811</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH SARAH MACDONALD, TRIPLE J, 25 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009811.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 7.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH SARAH MACDONALD, TRIPLE J, 25 OCTOBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
MAC. Prime Minister, could France have done the world a favour by<br />
resuming nuclear testing?<br />
PM: No, but I think we have got to draw something good from the debris<br />
and what Australia has now decided to do, what this Government has<br />
decided, is that we will establish at the core of our policy a commitment<br />
to the complete elimination of nuclear weapons. That is, we will go<br />
beyond the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, that we will commit<br />
substantial resources to that, but we will go beyond that and seek to<br />
eliminate the 50,000 strong stock pile of nuclear weapons.<br />
Now as well as that, we will commit substantial resources to expediting<br />
negotiations on the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty as a first step<br />
towards eliminating nuclear weapons and we will kick start<br />
negotiations on fissile material production and stock piles also as a<br />
step towards the elimination of nuclear weapons.<br />
So, at the end of the Cold War and the changed strategic environment,<br />
we think it is now time, particularly with the heightened focus on what<br />
France has done and the objection to it, to actually now strike out and<br />
make a new direction, to actually not simply stop testing but to actually<br />
be rid of the weapons themselves.<br />
MAC: But if countries like France and China won't listen to us when we say<br />
stop testing, do you think they are going to listen when we ask them to<br />
get rid of their weapons as well?<br />
PM: Well, the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty which France has said it will<br />
sign and others may sign, we have had a very strong reaffirmation of<br />
the Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty this year. That was one of the<br />
things which, of course, soured us with the French. When there was<br />
so much optimism around about the Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty,<br />
the French then decided to test their weapons. But now they have </p>
<p>said they will sign the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty. The thing you<br />
have got to know about nuclear weapon states Is the thing they now<br />
fear, as the rest of us do. is that someone else will get weapons too.<br />
So, from their point of view there would be some clear interest on their<br />
part to make sure that the country next door doesn't get weapons. So<br />
they may sign and. I think. '. vill sign the Comprehensive Test Ban<br />
Treaty, it will then be a case of urging Russia and the United States to<br />
move forward on their START obligations and start to de-construct<br />
their nuclear warheads and then reprocess the material and that wouid<br />
be part of a generally broad policy of doing that.<br />
MAC: We'll talk about what Australia will do to achieve this goal. you are<br />
going to set up an eminent persons groups to report to the UN. what<br />
would you like them to report to the UN about?<br />
PM: I think practical and innovative thinking on ways to reduce existing<br />
arsenals and halt proliferation. Australia is not a weapon state, we<br />
don't have nuclear weapons but we have had some success, indeed<br />
quite a lot of success, with the chemical weapons convention. There<br />
we succeeded in abolishing a whole class and category of weapons.<br />
This is what we are seeking to do with another class and category of<br />
nuclear weapons. So. we will bring into a group those people who<br />
have a deep knowledge of the whole development of these weapons<br />
programs and of course disarmament and the treaties and processes<br />
to actually de-construct them.<br />
MAC: Why when Gareth Evans goes to the International Court of Justice,<br />
why would he argue that the Court shouldn't actually make a ruling<br />
about the legality of nuclear weapons, why shouldn't he just have our<br />
first scenario and that is that weapons should be illegal.<br />
PM' We are saying that the best option is for the Court to make no<br />
judgment because its finding either way legal or illegal will make<br />
nuclear disarmament more difficult. If the Court is to come to a<br />
judgement we would prefer it to find nuclear weapons illegal and to<br />
acknowledge the practical difficulties which follow. Because it has<br />
never been a legal matter as to whether they are legal or not, they are<br />
weapons of mass destruction. Their very design, building and<br />
potential use has got naught to do with legalities, it has got all to do<br />
with power and to do with defence or a deterrent defence. But, those<br />
who want to be rid of the things think that a judgement inside the<br />
courts may help, well if it is a judgement for their legality, of course, all<br />
the people who believe that nuclear weapons are abhorrent would<br />
have taken the step backwards. If to say they are illegal, I think, we'll<br />
find that you then have the major powers walking away from the<br />
International Court of Justice. Is that going to do us any good?<br />
MAC: You talked about it, it might be achievable I think some people think to<br />
get rid of the stockpiles, but do you really think that one day in your life<br />
time we will a world free of nuclear weapons? </p>
<p>PM WNell, I think. it is a possibility now. I never thought that too many<br />
years ago. But now the strategic environment of the bipolarity of the<br />
Cold War has changed and we are looking at regional problems and<br />
wve are also. I think? from the point of view of military hardware,<br />
witnessing the success of these pin point accuracy weapons where<br />
you don't need the mass explosion and the mass explosive force of<br />
nuclear weapons as a deterrent. You can see in Iraq how these pin<br />
point accuracy weapons were deployed. We may be getting to the<br />
point that people in defence administrations with defence<br />
responsibilities around the world, will think in terms of the precision of<br />
these sorts of weapons versus nuclear weapons.<br />
Such a process, that is removing the warheads, would have to take<br />
place within the context of a continuing deterrent policy whereby the<br />
deterrents which are held by the nuclear powers are gradually wound<br />
down. But, the main thing to begin with is to ban further testing, to kick<br />
start negotiations on fissile material production, to stop more of it being<br />
produced, to stop the diversion of materials and proliferation and then<br />
start grinding away at the stock piles. That is how I would see it and, I<br />
think those things are achievable.<br />
MAC: Why do you think the world is going to listen to Australia. as you said<br />
we are a relatively small country and we are not a nuclear weapons<br />
state. Why are they going to take notice of our move?<br />
PM: We have had a number of successes with the chemical weapons<br />
convention where we put our back to it with a number of other<br />
countries that succeeded in banning the use of a whole class or<br />
category of weapons. We have had success in other things such as<br />
the peace accords in Cambodia, APEC putting together a huge<br />
transpacific free trade agreement, free trade proposal and, of course,<br />
in Antarctica.<br />
Let me tell you about Antarctica. I first raised this actually with the<br />
former Prime Minister of France at a time when we were about to sign<br />
the Minerals Convention and that would have seen the green light to<br />
mining and exploitation of Antarctica and I put to Prime Minister<br />
Michele Rocard in 1988 that we shouldn't advance and sign the<br />
Minerals Convention, that there was a better way. We didn't<br />
understand Antarctica, that we shouldn't tear it to pieces, not in some<br />
sort of premature scramble for resources, particularly for oil, and that<br />
we should set aside the Minerals Convention which was ten years of<br />
work and seek to declare Antarctica a wilderness park. Now, that<br />
happened, it took some time and there were a lot of negotiations and a<br />
lot of consultations along the way but it happened. As the Chemical<br />
Convention happened. As APEC is happening.<br />
So, I think, because Australia has no axe to grind in these things, that<br />
it is not a weapons state but it does have mature foreign policy </p>
<p>processes and disarmament is one of the things we have specialised<br />
in. but not over played our hand in. that we can be effective and. I<br />
think, practical in getting results.<br />
MAC: Australia is still contributing to the nuclear industry by providing<br />
uranium and lots of environment groups say that this actually<br />
compromises our arguments in the world stage on nuclear weapons.<br />
PM: I don't believe it does. We don't provide uranium to weapons<br />
programs. They go to civil power programs and we have, of course,<br />
through the IAEA a set of international safeguards to protect against<br />
diversion to weapons programs. But if we stop the production of fissile<br />
material, then that doesn't become a question. And then, of course,<br />
you have got whatever will be the outcome of the intellectual tussle<br />
over greenhouse gas emissions from fossil fuels and the civil nuclear<br />
power. None of these things are simple, but Australia's position has<br />
always been that we have supported a Nuclear Non-proliferation<br />
Treaty and we have been opposed to the proliferation of nuclear<br />
weapons and the diversion of these materials. I think the fact that<br />
Australia is actually in the business and has a say in the IAEA and is<br />
regarded as a player with integrity in these issues makes us more<br />
effective.<br />
MAC-Would you like to use our strong position in Asia to convince countries<br />
like India and Pakistan which is where a lot of the world is worried that<br />
nuclear development may happen to actually go away from that goal?<br />
PM: Were we to succeed in moving towards this goal, the pressure will<br />
come on those countries to declare their hand and make clear where<br />
they are. But, there can be no such pressure while a major democracy<br />
like France is out there encouraging people to test weapons. That is<br />
our objection to the French. That is, that they are out there saying at a<br />
time when the rest of us trying to keep the horse in the stable, to not<br />
see the nuclear option bolt amongst a group of other countries, France<br />
is out there saying it is okay you can have as many bangs out there<br />
under ground or above ground as you like and, I think, that is the real<br />
sin that the French have committed.<br />
MAC: Were you disappointed today that Bill Hayden didn't bring up French<br />
nuclear testing in his speech to the UN?<br />
PM: Well, it is in the text and it is published for and on his behalf and on<br />
behalf of Australia. Whether he actually said it is a matter for him and<br />
his time constraints. This is the problem of these major international<br />
events, I think people only get about five minutes and that's it.<br />
MAC: Shouldn't he have put it up the top of his speech?<br />
PM: Well, it is about the UN, it is about a body which he had an<br />
involvement with as Foreign Minister. Obviously, it was in the speech </p>
<p>to be given, but what we have done here today is indeed far more<br />
significant than a comment about France. As I said to you earlier.<br />
what we have done here today, is establish at the core of our own<br />
policy a commitment to the complete elimination of nuclear weapons of<br />
all classes. No Australian Government has ever taken that position<br />
before.<br />
MAC: Finally, there has been a lot of hoo-ha today in the press about<br />
Cabinet meetings and sponsorship, do you reckon you are worth<br />
$ 20.000?<br />
PM: I'm not part of any sponsorship things and I didn't attend that<br />
gathering. The press are better off the trivia and onto the main things<br />
like you and I were just speaking about. You were going better before<br />
you got around to that question.<br />
MAC: [ laughs]<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
