<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10932</transcript-id>
    <title>22 October 1998                                                                 ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP                TO THE 10TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE OF BANKING SUPERVISORS                TOWN HALL, SYDNEY                 &amp;quot;RETURNING THE REGION TO SUSTAINABLE GROWTH&amp;quot;</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE............................................................................................</p>
<p> I am grateful for the opportunity to be here tonight. There</p>
<p> could hardly be a more appropriate time for you to meet in Australia</p>
<p> - for two reasons.</p>
<p>The first is that in Australia we have recently implemented major</p>
<p> reforms to the regulatory framework for our financial system. The</p>
<p> Treasurer is justly proud of these changes and the complementary corporate</p>
<p> law economic reform programme. He has already spoken to you about</p>
<p> them and I will not say more than that we believe we have a system</p>
<p> which is at the leading edge of the world's best practice.</p>
<p>Given the financial storm that has hit the world, we are very pleased</p>
<p> that we strengthened our system when we did. And that is the second</p>
<p> reason why your meeting is so timely.</p>
<p>We confront an unprecedented degree of instability in international</p>
<p> financial markets. The impact on Australia's region has been</p>
<p> colossal. The debate about reducing this instability is vigorous.</p>
<p> It is crucial that we reach practical conclusions as soon as possible.</p>
<p>We know that the problems that led to the present situation stem from</p>
<p> a variety of sources: inadequacies in the management of national economies,</p>
<p> inadequacies in corporate behaviour, and inadequacies in the world's</p>
<p> financial system.</p>
<p>Efforts to rebuild stability need to take account of the part that</p>
<p> each has played. As banking supervisors, you have an important role</p>
<p> in all of them. I will say something about the issues of national</p>
<p> and international financial sector supervision but I would first like</p>
<p> to put my comments in a political and an Asia-Pacific context.</p>
<p>Economic growth</p>
<p>The point that we need to remember is that the ultimate aim of our</p>
<p> activities as governments and financial market supervisors is to improve</p>
<p> the security and welfare of our people. The key to this is sustainable</p>
<p> economic growth.</p>
<p>Without sustainable economic growth, improved living standards are</p>
<p> not possible. Nor is better education for our children, nor are jobs</p>
<p> for them, nor are health services, transport infrastructure, pensions</p>
<p> for our old people and so on. Nor ultimately is our capacity to defend</p>
<p> our sovereignty and maintain our security.</p>
<p>In the past two decades, economic growth has transformed Australia's</p>
<p> region, the lives of the people in it and the relationships between</p>
<p> the countries in it. Starting with Japan after the war, East Asian</p>
<p> economies have grown at extraordinary rates. Millions of people were</p>
<p> lifted out of poverty. Countries in the region became politically</p>
<p> more stable and open. The region developed a sense of shared interests</p>
<p> and a sense of community. The foundation and consolidation of APEC</p>
<p> was a visible sign of this.</p>
<p>Many of these benefits are now threatened. At a human level, unemployment</p>
<p> has increased massively. Families face great hardship. Food shortages</p>
<p> and malnutrition have reappeared. Children are being withdrawn from</p>
<p> school. The internal political pressures created by these developments</p>
<p> are immense. Relationships between countries are tested.</p>
<p>The most important aim of these countries and the region as a whole</p>
<p> therefore must be to get back on to the path of sustained growth as</p>
<p> soon as possible. This must be the focus of the APEC leaders meeting</p>
<p> which takes place in Kuala Lumpur in mid-November.</p>
<p>What should we do?</p>
<p>Keeping economies and markets open</p>
<p>The first thing APEC can do is make sure regional economies and markets</p>
<p> stay open.</p>
<p>Recent financial instability and the role of hedge funds and short-term</p>
<p> money flows have revived fears of globalisation. By opening their</p>
<p> borders to the free flow of goods, services and capital, governments,</p>
<p> it is sometimes said, have cost their people jobs and surrendered</p>
<p> their countries' sovereignty. Others say open markets are all</p>
<p> very well in good times, but in bad times we need to raise barriers</p>
<p> to protect ourselves.</p>
<p>APEC must stand against that view. Open markets provide the opportunity</p>
<p> for economic growth and the enormous benefits from it.</p>
<p>The worst possible response to the crisis would be to put up the shutters.</p>
<p> That would result in competition to raise tariffs and barriers within</p>
<p> the region and outside. We saw the consequences of this sort of policy</p>
<p> in the Great Depression of the 1930s. Others won't keep their</p>
<p> markets open, if we don't.</p>
<p>In 1994 in Indonesia, APEC leaders committed themselves to free trade</p>
<p> and investment in the region by 2010 for developed economies and 2020</p>
<p> for developing economies. That commitment helped bring the Uruguay</p>
<p> Round of the GATT to a successful conclusion, and the implementation</p>
<p> of binding agreements to reduce trade barriers around the globe.</p>
<p>In 1998 in Kuala Lumpur, APEC must recommit itself to those goals.</p>
<p> I would like to see a concrete demonstration of that commitment by</p>
<p> agreement to move ahead with early liberalisation in the full range</p>
<p> of sectors agreed in Vancouver last year. I would like APEC to challenge</p>
<p> others to enter a new broad-based round of trade negotiations in the</p>
<p> World Trade Organisation.</p>
<p>Economic governance</p>
<p>The second vital step for APEC economies is to take decisive action</p>
<p> to improve the transparency and accountability of government and corporate</p>
<p> decision making.</p>
<p>In part, present problems can be ascribed to a weak capacity to manage</p>
<p> international capital flows, to the vulnerability of companies and</p>
<p> governments to special interests and political cronyism.</p>
<p>There is no point in denying this. Efforts to do so will be received</p>
<p> with scepticism. Reforms are needed to regain international confidence.</p>
<p>APEC economies should therefore undertake to work immediately towards</p>
<p> implementing the relevant codes of international best practice.</p>
<p>I have in mind as a start the Basle Core Principles for Effective</p>
<p> Banking Supervision. Other relevant ones are the principles of the</p>
<p> International Organisation of Securities Commissions for securities</p>
<p> regulation, their disclosure standards for cross-border offerings,</p>
<p> the IMF's special data dissemination standard and the IMF's</p>
<p> code of good practice on fiscal transparency.</p>
<p>This will not be easy for all APEC economies. They will need time</p>
<p> and help. That help can come from a great variety of institutions</p>
<p> and duplication needs to be avoided.</p>
<p>The Australian government has engaged a consultant to survey both</p>
<p> the needs of regional economies for technical assistance on economic</p>
<p> governance and what is being done to meet those needs. There are substantial</p>
<p> gaps.</p>
<p>I will be announcing in Kuala Lumpur a package of bilateral assistance</p>
<p> which will help economies fill those gaps, and I will be encouraging</p>
<p> other APEC members in a position to help to do likewise.</p>
<p>In Australia, we have been improving our own systems. I mentioned</p>
<p> our new corporate and financial regulatory framework.</p>
<p>We will shortly be introducing into Parliament the most fundamental</p>
<p> improvements to our tax system since the Second World War. The reforms</p>
<p> will make for a more efficient and reliable revenue base. They will</p>
<p> make industry and exporters more competitive. They will provide more</p>
<p> incentive for Australians to be creative and expand their horizons.</p>
<p>The government has invited the private sector to make proposals to</p>
<p> reform the corporate tax structure. We will build on the range of</p>
<p> tax measures we announced in December 1997 to make Australia more</p>
<p> attractive as a centre for financial services.</p>
<p>The government is committed to seeing a major Australian city become</p>
<p> a major world financial centre. I have charged the Treasurer with</p>
<p> producing an action agenda that will extend what we have already done</p>
<p> in order to achieve this outcome. In the new government, I have appointed</p>
<p> a minister for financial services and regulation specifically to work</p>
<p> on this with the Treasurer.</p>
<p>The international financial system</p>
<p>The third vital step for APEC is to put its weight behind proposals</p>
<p> for reform of the international financial architecture.</p>
<p>It is the case that many economies were ill equipped to manage capital</p>
<p> flows. It is the case that transparency and accountability were lacking.</p>
<p> But it is not the case that these economies got what they deserved.</p>
<p> Rather, they got a whole lot more than they deserved. And I don't</p>
<p> think anyone will dispute that.</p>
<p>Companies must take some of the blame. As the Treasurer said to you</p>
<p> the other night, sensible judgments about risk were abandoned. People</p>
<p> grew complacent, and got used to quick and easy profits. Then they</p>
<p> panicked.</p>
<p>The global financial system also failed us. The sudden withdrawal</p>
<p> of funds knocked companies and economies off their feet much as the</p>
<p> powerful undertow of an ocean wave pulls the feet from under swimmers</p>
<p> and drags them out to sea.</p>
<p>Economies all around the world have been affected by the contagion,</p>
<p> including some that are clearly well run. In mentioning Mr Stiglitz's</p>
<p> apposite analogy about even well-maintained rowing boats being swamped</p>
<p> at sea I don't want to be accused of taking sides in a sensitive</p>
<p> institutional rivalry.</p>
<p>I therefore strongly support President Clinton's call for urgent</p>
<p> action to reform the international financial system. The G22 has produced</p>
<p> some worthwhile discussion papers. We now need some practical outcomes.</p>
<p>To my mind three areas stand out as requiring action.</p>
<p>The first is the need for better targeted disclosure requirements</p>
<p> which would focus on the gaps in current information on financial</p>
<p> markets, including the major private sector participants. Measures</p>
<p> need to be developed for monitoring and supervising highly leveraged</p>
<p> short-term financial flows, off balance sheet commitments and derivative</p>
<p> transactions.</p>
<p>The second is the need for measures to better manage future crises</p>
<p> and to facilitate private sector involvement in crisis management.</p>
<p> These might include standfast arrangements to prevent lenders from</p>
<p> exiting economies in a destructive stampede, collective action clauses,</p>
<p> orderly workouts involving rollovers, reschedulings and debt-equity</p>
<p> swaps.</p>
<p>The third is the need for the IMF to be able to provide speedy and</p>
<p> substantial support to appropriately qualified countries caught in</p>
<p> international contagion, analogous to domestic lender-of-last resort</p>
<p> facilities.</p>
<p>Speaking to a group who might be dubbed the grand regulators </p>
<p> rather than masters  of the universe, I should probably say</p>
<p> quickly that I am not in favour of unnecessarily burdensome controls.</p>
<p> We do not want to constrain the natural workings of the market beyond</p>
<p> what is necessary to ensure its stable operation.</p>
<p>It is clear that the private sector must be included in discussions</p>
<p> on how to improve the international financial system.</p>
<p>That is why I have established a task force to report to me on these</p>
<p> issues. I will preside over the first meeting tomorrow afternoon.</p>
<p> It will be composed half each from the private sector and the public</p>
<p> sector, with some of the most senior banking and financial services</p>
<p> figures in our country alongside the heads of the relevant government</p>
<p> agencies.</p>
<p>I am looking for substantive and imaginative suggestions for Australia</p>
<p> to champion in the appropriate international forums.</p>
<p>APEC economies have a big interest in early harvests from discussions</p>
<p> about these issues. We need an effective regional voice in this debate.</p>
<p>That is why I strongly support the G22 as the most appropriate international</p>
<p> forum to develop these measures.</p>
<p>We do not need to completely rebuild the international architecture.</p>
<p> The IMF will continue to have a central role, and the other institutions</p>
<p> such as the World Bank and the Bank of International Settlements play</p>
<p> important roles - each in its own field.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the world has changed dramatically since these institutions</p>
<p> were established. In creating a consensus on improvements to the financial</p>
<p> system, a broadly based grouping of countries is a valuable asset.</p>
<p>I can see merit in a leaders level meeting of the G22 to lock in measures</p>
<p> to improve the financial system, and would willingly lend my support</p>
<p> to any proposals to that end.</p>
<p>Growth-promoting policies</p>
<p>These three steps are vital elements for returning to the path of</p>
<p> sustainable growth and restoring confidence in the region's economies.</p>
<p> The fact is, however, that they will inevitably take time to have</p>
<p> an impact. In the meantime we are faced with the short-term problems.</p>
<p>We must focus on what can be done now to ensure that growth resumes</p>
<p> and to avoid a major credit crunch.</p>
<p>In this regard, the focus has to be in the first place on the largest</p>
<p> and second largest economies in the world: the United States and Japan.</p>
<p>The recent steps taken by the United States to maintain growth have</p>
<p> been reassuring. They are a practical demonstration of President Clinton's</p>
<p> recent promise to keep the US economy growing and open to the products</p>
<p> and services of others.</p>
<p>Japan has made very generous contributions to regional countries hit</p>
<p> by the crisis, having already pledged support worth $42 billion. It</p>
<p> has not always received due credit for that.</p>
<p>The steps that it has foreshadowed to recapitalise its banks and stimulate</p>
<p> its economy are welcome. The rest of the world, however, is waiting</p>
<p> for a sign that the measures are biting. Confidence must be rebuilt</p>
<p> in Japan's economy both amongst its own people and in the rest</p>
<p> of the world. With over two-thirds of East Asia's GDP, Japan</p>
<p> must get back on the right track if the rest of the region is to dig</p>
<p> itself out of the hole it is in.</p>
<p>With bipartisan support, the Australian government has made a significant</p>
<p> contribution to cushioning the impact of the recession in the most</p>
<p> affected countries and to restoring their financial health. Altogether,</p>
<p> we have pledged $3 billion for the three regional IMF packages. In</p>
<p> addition, we made large increases in aid for Thailand and Indonesia.</p>
<p>We have also taken a prominent role in trying to generate international</p>
<p> support for these countries and to deepen the understanding of their</p>
<p> individual characteristics, especially in the case of Indonesia.</p>
<p>As for Australia's own economy, it is still growing strongly.</p>
<p> In the financial year just ended, it grew 4 per cent. We will be affected</p>
<p> by the slowdown in the region and we have been buffeted by currency</p>
<p> volatility. But with a strong budget surplus, low inflation and low</p>
<p> interest rates, greater diversification of exports and strong domestic</p>
<p> demand we are well placed to continue to grow.</p>
<p>Regional economies in recession must not be allowed to contract any</p>
<p> further than they already have. Domestic demand must be encouraged.</p>
<p> The plight of the poorest must also be taken into account  an</p>
<p> issue which the World Bank and the IMF have recognised through the</p>
<p> relaxation of fiscal targets.</p>
<p>Early this year, I personally urged the leaders of the major economies</p>
<p> and the World Bank to cooperate to ensure that trade finance was available</p>
<p> so that economic activity could continue.</p>
<p>Australia provided for an additional total of $1.4 billion in trade</p>
<p> credit insurance. Japan has recently announced a further $30 billion</p>
<p> worth of assistance some of which I understand will be available for</p>
<p> trade finance. Singapore's prime minister, Goh Chok Tong, has</p>
<p> made a proposal for a multilateral approach to trade credit. I think</p>
<p> it is time for a renewed effort to develop a coordinated international</p>
<p> approach in this area.</p>
<p>Neither pessimism nor optimism - but realism</p>
<p>Assessments of the region have swung all too quickly from extreme</p>
<p> and overblown optimism to extreme and unwarranted pessimism. We need</p>
<p> to keep a sense of perspective.</p>
<p>The impact of the financial crisis on the region has been huge, in</p>
<p> some cases devastating. At the risk of entering another ideological</p>
<p> struggle by mentioning Paul Krugman, I quote his calculation that,</p>
<p> were Thailand's experience translated to the United States, it</p>
<p> would be as if the $200 billion net inflow of foreign investment the</p>
<p> United States receives each year were suddenly to become in the next</p>
<p> year an outflow of $1 trillion.</p>
<p>I continue to be astonished sometimes by the lack of comprehension</p>
<p> of the scale of the impact of the crisis on a country like Indonesia.</p>
<p> We need to understand the huge task of political and economic restructuring</p>
<p> that is being required of Indonesia. Without being Pollyannaish, we</p>
<p> should recognise that despite all the difficulties it is indeed making</p>
<p> some progress. It needs help and it is worth helping.</p>
<p>We need to understand that not all countries in East Asia or even</p>
<p> Southeast Asia are the same as each other. Thailand's problems</p>
<p> are different from Indonesia's or Korea's.</p>
<p>The fact is that growth in the region hasn't been the result</p>
<p> of a miracle now gone bust or merely built on the back of speculation</p>
<p> and short-term capital flows.</p>
<p>It has been built on the hard work, the thrift, the skills, the ingenuity,</p>
<p> and the determination of people in the region to develop and to reap</p>
<p> the benefits of economic growth. And it has been built on the work</p>
<p> of regional governments in developing the infrastructure and systems</p>
<p> necessary to support and nurture that growth.</p>
<p>Those qualities, skills and infrastructure remain in the region. Many</p>
<p> - like Indonesia - are enormously rich in natural resources.</p>
<p>If APEC economies keep markets open, improve their economic governance</p>
<p> and engage in efforts to strengthen the international financial system,</p>
<p> they will regain international confidence and they will return to</p>
<p> sustainable growth.</p>
<p>[ENDS]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
