<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11179</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 RADIO INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES, 2UE                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: economy, ministry changes, current account deficit, trade</p>
<p> issues, lamb exports, manufacturing industry, foreign aid, industrial</p>
<p> relations reform, community violence, senate reform, business tax</p>
<p> reform, Collins Class submarines, republic referendum</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Prime Minister good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Alan.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you said in Parliament last week that Australia has</p>
<p> an economic self respect, quote: that I do not think I have</p>
<p> experienced in the 25 years I've been in public life'. How</p>
<p> do you measure that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I measure it by the straight statistical achievement. I also measure</p>
<p> it by the greater respect and deference that is paid to Australia's</p>
<p> economic performance by other countries and other leaders. I measure</p>
<p> it by the fact that against all predictions we were not overwhelmed</p>
<p> by the Asian economic downturn because we put our house in order.</p>
<p> And I measure it by the fact that the prospects of this economy remain</p>
<p> very strong, and also by the fact that we've been able in the</p>
<p> last few weeks to put through the biggest shake up of our taxation</p>
<p> system at least since World War II. So when you can do those things</p>
<p> the rest of the world takes a bit more notice.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Everyone likes to be recognised for their achievements. You've</p>
<p> never sought that sort of recognition but do you wonder whether people</p>
<p> fully understand the nature of the reform that's been undertaken</p>
<p> in the last few years? I mean gun laws, native title, and the battle</p>
<p> on the waterfront, trying to sell Telstra, the budget surplus, and</p>
<p> those sorts of things. Do you think that's fully understood by</p>
<p> the community?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think in those terms. I don't think people specifically</p>
<p> think gee it's a good thing that the budget's back in surplus.</p>
<p> But what they do think is a good thing is the fact that partly because</p>
<p> the budget is back in surplus they're paying $320 on average</p>
<p> less a month on their housing mortgage. The benefits of good policy</p>
<p> are understood and supported by the community when they are translated</p>
<p> into benefits for them. And the goal of the Government and the goal</p>
<p> of the Prime Minister is not to sort of list any personal achievements</p>
<p> but rather to deliver good outcomes for the Australian people and</p>
<p> the thing that pleases me most about our economic record is that we</p>
<p> have been able for most Australians to deliver good outcomes. Their</p>
<p> real wages are higher, their mortgage interest rates are lower, there</p>
<p> are 400,000 more jobs. All those things are tangible benefits. Now</p>
<p> there are some people who aren't getting that. I accept that.</p>
<p> And there are some sections of the community who are still suffering</p>
<p> and we have to work even harder to help them, and there still great</p>
<p> pockets of injustice and inequity in our society and no Prime Minister</p>
<p> even at a time when things are going strongly should ever lose sight</p>
<p> of that fact.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>You also said in the Parliament that tariff reform was one of the</p>
<p> five main areas of economic modernisation. You don't yet have</p>
<p> a minister for trade to replace Tim Fischer.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll be announcing this morning at a press conference before</p>
<p> I go that Mark Vaile will become the minister for trade. The ministerial</p>
<p> arrangements will involve him going to the trade portfolio and he</p>
<p> will do a very good job, as did Tim Fischer. And I'll be making</p>
<p> Warren Truss not only a Cabinet minister but I'll be recommending</p>
<p> to the Governor General that he take over the agriculture, fisheries</p>
<p> and forestry portfolio. And the newcomer into the ministry will be</p>
<p> Larry Anthony. It will be a third generation Anthony in a ministry</p>
<p> and he'll become the minister for community services.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Yeah, he's a first class young man Larry Anthony.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He's a very impressive young man. I think they're good changes.</p>
<p> I will work well with both John Anderson and Mark Vaile. Mark will</p>
<p> do a very energetic job in the trade portfolio and Larry will bring</p>
<p> a great deal of commitment and enthusiasm to the community services</p>
<p> portfolio.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Now on the question of trade though, does it worry you when you're</p>
<p> talking about modernisation that we are stuck with this $1.9 billion</p>
<p> trade deficit for April, marginally better for May, but the last 5</p>
<p> months have been absolutely horrendous? If we are constantly going</p>
<p> to live in deficit on trade, how do we pay for that deficit?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we historically run a current account deficit. We have for most</p>
<p> of our existence because we're that kind of country. We need</p>
<p> to export to survive. It depends on how big it is. It's too big</p>
<p> but it's manageable, and it's manageable because we can</p>
<p> service the debt far more easily than we could 15 years ago and it's</p>
<p> also manageable because we have a budget surplus and we have low levels</p>
<p> of inflation and low levels of interest rate and we do not have to</p>
<p> close the economy down as happened in the 1980s in order to control</p>
<p> the size of that trade deficit.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But you'll be talking to Prime Minister Obuchi and President</p>
<p> Bill Clinton. They don't have this view about level playing field</p>
<p> if it's likely to interfere with their own domestic position,</p>
<p> and the position you're talking to Clinton about, the lamb...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We haven't got an answer on lamb and lamb is quite a watershed</p>
<p> as far as the Americans are concerned. They are telling the rest of</p>
<p> the world there should be more open trade but they are....</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Don't practice it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's what I said to president Clinton. I had a conversation</p>
<p> with him three weeks ago and I put that very proposition to him. I</p>
<p> said President, if you close down our lamb exports to the United States</p>
<p> you will send a terrible signal to the rest of the world. You'll</p>
<p> be saying that we talk one thing we do another. Now he's very</p>
<p> conscious of that. I'm still not overly optimistic about what</p>
<p> the Americans are going to do but we are still in there punching and</p>
<p> we haven't heard yet, and I'm hopeful the Americans will</p>
<p> at the last moment see the wisdom of not interfering with a market</p>
<p> that we have worked very hard to win. I mean the reason why I argue</p>
<p> for more open markets Alan is that this is a lamb market we didn't</p>
<p> have a few years ago and as an exporting nation we have to win market</p>
<p> share overseas if we are to expand. And if we get markets overseas</p>
<p> than obviously people have got to have some capacity to trade into</p>
<p> this country. Now there is no such thing as a level playing field</p>
<p> as Tim Fischer was fond of saying, and you have to constantly make</p>
<p> pragmatic judgements in the best interests of Australia and that's</p>
<p> what we try to do on each issue.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Billy Wentworth, whom you know well, wrote the biography of Jack McEwen,</p>
<p> and he wrote: for 2 years McEwen was in the sweat box of international</p>
<p> negotiation. He saw Australia's trade competitors at work, he</p>
<p> heard them say one thing and watched them do another. He moved from</p>
<p> a stance of real hope for a world in which big and small nations would</p>
<p> transact business on a basis of fairness and equity, to one of skepticism</p>
<p> that the big would ever give an inch to the small. And he was utterly</p>
<p> convinced, not from theory but from practice, that the much vaunted</p>
<p> level playing field in world commerce was a myth'.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know that I disagree with that conclusion. I would</p>
<p> make the point though that our economic performance now is just as</p>
<p> strong if not stronger than it was at the time of McEwen. I mean we</p>
<p> have an economy now whose fundamentals are stronger than they've</p>
<p> been since the late 1960s.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But this is a big issue because.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>[inaudible] ......McEwen's contribution to this country,</p>
<p> but let's keep it in perspective.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Yeah but the Manufacturing Workers' Union are saying today that</p>
<p> manufacturing is at its worst post war level since the recessions</p>
<p> of the 70s, 80s and early 90s. It says manufacturing exports to Asia</p>
<p> have been cut by 40% but imports continue to rise. And they talked</p>
<p> about a Comalco aluminum plant in Queensland getting $100 million</p>
<p> in Commonwealth assistance but Australian firms excluded from the</p>
<p> deal. Now while ever we continue to support international companies</p>
<p> and leave Australians high and dry how can we sponsor a manufacturing</p>
<p> industry, or growth in manufacturing employment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'll say a couple of things about that. First is that any</p>
<p> loss of manufacturing exports to Asia is not due to tariffs, it's</p>
<p> due to the Asian economic collapse. And you can't blame tariff</p>
<p> changes for that. As far as that Comalco project in Queensland is</p>
<p> concerned, well, that hasn't come to fruition yet and the question</p>
<p> of whether or not there will be foreign firms or Australian firms,</p>
<p> therefore, can't be resolved.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But we are giving assistance to foreign firms, why don't we do</p>
<p> that for Australian firms?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Alan, hang on, hang on. We give assistance, Alan, to Australian-based</p>
<p> projects. And when you help an Australian project you help jobs. I</p>
<p> mean, one of the...</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Foreign jobs.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, no, no, I mean...</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>The profits are repatriated overseas.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well they do employ Australians and they pay Australian tax and the</p>
<p> company pays Australian tax. And we've just decided to give some</p>
<p> assistance to the establishment of a pulp mill by the Pratt organisation</p>
<p> in Tumut and that is going to generate hundreds of local jobs. I mean,</p>
<p> you have to remember that when you assist a project, even though there</p>
<p> may be some foreign investment in it, that it does generate jobs here</p>
<p> in Australia. And all of those things that you've mentioned would</p>
<p> generate Australian jobs and those Australians will pay tax and the</p>
<p> company will pay tax.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Well, one of the pluses you mentioned earlier on about achievement</p>
<p> and we talked about the waterfront reform and there's a second</p>
<p> slice of industrial relations reform, if you're introducing it</p>
<p> where do workers of Oakdale colliery and others fit in? There's</p>
<p> talk today that at least 3,000 employees of dozens of companies have</p>
<p> lost an estimated $30 million in entitlements in the past few years.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a result of some companies going bankrupt and their</p>
<p> money not being available to meet redundancy and leave entitlements.</p>
<p> And this is a problem. Two of my Ministers, Peter Reith and Nick Minchin,</p>
<p> who met industry people and union people a couple of weeks ago are</p>
<p> coming back to Cabinet with proposals to make changes in this area.</p>
<p> I think we do need changes.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Is it urgent?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is quite urgent, yes, but it's got to be handled carefully</p>
<p> because there are implications. If you go too far in one direction</p>
<p> there are implications for the ability of people to generate enough</p>
<p> cashflow to run small businesses.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But should liquidators and secured creditors get their money ahead</p>
<p> of workers?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is the issue that's got to be resolved. If they don't</p>
<p> then to the extent that that has some impact on the amount of credit</p>
<p> that is available for small business, that could in turn have some</p>
<p> impact on the capacity of those businesses to employ people. This</p>
<p> is an issue that in addressing this I think quite serious matter,</p>
<p> this is an issue that has to be resolved. I should say in relation</p>
<p> to Oakdale that as I've foreshadowed, I think when I last spoke</p>
<p> to you about this, that we have been in touch with the Australian</p>
<p> Securities Commission and the Australian Securities Commission is</p>
<p> investigating the circumstances of what's happened. Now, I'm</p>
<p> not raising any expectations in relation to that but you will remember...</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>So how do they pay their mortgages, Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>How do they pay their mortgages?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am acutely aware of that but I'm also acutely aware of the</p>
<p> fact that the capacity of small businesses to finance their operation</p>
<p> would be reduced if they are forced to put aside money that they might</p>
<p> otherwise invest in the operation of those businesses.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But if they're using employee entitlements as part of their cashflow</p>
<p> they've got to be pretty crook to start with.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, many small businesses do that, Alan, that is the...</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>We went through this before. It's not their money to use.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, all I'm saying, I mean, I agree with you that it is a very</p>
<p> difficult situation and these men have a lot of justice on their side.</p>
<p> I'm simply making the point to you, though, that if you make</p>
<p> a permanent change to the rule for the future and you prevent many</p>
<p> small businesses from using money that they habitually use now in</p>
<p> the cashflow daily operations of their business, that is going to</p>
<p> have an impact on them. Now, whether that is regarded as wise practise</p>
<p> or not, it is the reality, and you and I often talk about the need</p>
<p> to deal with reality rather than theory. Now, the reality of many</p>
<p> small business operations is that they do use money that is theoretically</p>
<p> entitled. It theoretically is meant to be earmarked for a future liability,</p>
<p> they use it in the daily operations of their business, otherwise they</p>
<p> would have to borrow more from the bank and many of them would, therefore,</p>
<p> go out of business.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>One of the phrases being used beneficially in the last couple of days</p>
<p> by your Employment Minister, Tony Abbott, is about moving away from</p>
<p> the culture of welfare. I think there is widespread understanding</p>
<p> of exactly what he's saying on that. What about the culture of</p>
<p> violence, how damaging is that and what prime ministerial initiatives</p>
<p> do you take to try and turn that around?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think it's one of the most serious things in our community.</p>
<p> The greatest thing we did in relation to that, of course, were the</p>
<p> gun control laws. And whilst I don't want to claim too many benefits</p>
<p> from that I do want to make the point that we've already seen</p>
<p> a drop in the number of deaths, homicides related to the use of guns.</p>
<p> I think you need, constantly as a community, to be encouraging the</p>
<p> habits of civility and courtesy. I think we do as a society have too</p>
<p> much violence through video games, too much violence on television</p>
<p> screens, in the end, the best regulators of this appearance. I think</p>
<p> we teach our children to acquire the habits of violence too early</p>
<p> and too often. And as a society we are not quick enough to condemn</p>
<p> violence when it occurs.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>You've been talking about further reform. You say the job's</p>
<p> not done, no Prime Minister ever gets to the top of the mountain,</p>
<p> there's always another hill to climb. Given that the Senate already</p>
<p> has challenged you on the tax reform, will challenge you on new industrial</p>
<p> reform, has challenged you about youth wages, has been intransigent</p>
<p> over the full sale of Telstra, doesn't seem committed to a 30</p>
<p> per cent corporate tax rate, how much is reform of the Senate part</p>
<p> of reform which remains to be done?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think that's something that will attract a lot of debate</p>
<p> in the months ahead. Once again, I've got to deal with the here</p>
<p> and now. Reform of the Senate inevitably conjures up the notion of</p>
<p> constitutional change and you know how difficult that is in this country</p>
<p> and you know how a country can get diverted from the day-to-day needs</p>
<p> of things with a debate about constitutional change. I think what</p>
<p> you have to do with these things, Alan, is you have to achieve what</p>
<p> you can with the existing mechanisms but recognise that they're</p>
<p> not perfect. And if the opportunity for change, beneficial change</p>
<p> which is fair to all parties, presents itself in the future you try</p>
<p> and bring it about.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>So if the Labor Party are prepared to support a capital gains tax</p>
<p> change, would you introduce that into the Senate quite separately</p>
<p> from corporate tax change?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think it's too early for me to speculate how I will handle</p>
<p> the tax.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>But we do need a change to capital gains tax, don't we?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we certainly need to remove some of the disincentive in the</p>
<p> capital gains tax and I can assure you that whatever is needed to</p>
<p> get that through we will undertake.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>I mean, our marginal rate, capital gains tax, as you now, is about</p>
<p> 49 per cent. In America it's less than 20 per cent.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's right.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>And it is a disincentive, isn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>In a global economy if it's more attractive to invest in the</p>
<p> United States than it is here, well, the investment will go to the</p>
<p> United States. That's one of the realities of life.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Just two quick ones before you go. The navy apparently is going to</p>
<p> submerge you on a Collins Class submarine to prove they work, are</p>
<p> you aware of that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I've read that and I'll give some consideration to...</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>Will it be one of those that needs $600 million to fix it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a disappointing project. I think the concept way back</p>
<p> may have been a good one but I'm glad that John Moore had the</p>
<p> foresight to get a couple of outside experts to have a look and really</p>
<p> reveal the extent of the problem. We are optimistic that when we get</p>
<p> the new weapons system and that when the defects are fixed that it</p>
<p> will be a first class piece of equipment. But I can't disguise</p>
<p> the disappointment I feel about the way in which the project has been</p>
<p> handled.</p>
<p>JONES:</p>
<p>And finally, Australia becoming a republic, is that part of your urgent</p>
<p> programme for change?</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
