<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17337</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Treasurer Minister for Innovation, Industry, Science and Research Sustainable energy boost for super telescope bid 9 June 2010</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Rudd Government will invest $47.3 million in Western Australian to ensure solar energy and the nation's largest direct heat geothermal facility power Australia's bid to host the world's strongest radio telescope.</p>
<p>Two key pieces of infrastructure being built to support the Square Kilometre Array (SKA) bid will now have full-scale, clean energy generation systems because of the investment.</p>
<p>     * The Pawsey High-Performance Computing Centre in Kensington, will now use hot sedimentary aquifers to provide cooling and ventilation in the largest direct heat geothermal demonstrator in Australia at 10 MWth; and</p>
<p>     * The Murchison Radio-astronomy Observatory will now use a full scale solar/storage/diesel energy generation system.</p>
<p>This investment has the potential to cut energy costs by $5 million per year, and reduce Australia's carbon emissions by 12,000 tonnes per year - the equivalent of taking 6,000 cars off the road.</p>
<p>The projects will also help the CSIRO, which owns or leases 1,000 buildings across 55 locations, achieve its goal to be carbon neutral by 2015.</p>
<p>The announcement will strengthen Australia and New Zealand's bid to host the mega-science $2.5 billion SKA radio telescope by ensuring it meets the international community's aspiration that sustainable energy be used for the project.</p>
<p>The Australian Government has demonstrated a strong commitment to the SKA bid with other important investments: $100 million for the SKA Pathfinder, $80 million for High Performance Computing for the SKA, and $25 million for an optical fibre backbone broadband link from Perth to Geraldton.</p>
<p>The SKA involves 20 countries and will have the potential for discovery ten thousand times greater than existing radio telescopes. It will explore a number of fundamental scientific questions such as the origin of the universe, the nature of dark matter and the existence of life in the universe.</p>
<p>Hosting the SKA will generate significant economic and scientific benefits, particularly to WA, including spin-offs in areas such as supercomputing, data transmission, renewable energy, construction and manufacturing.</p>
<p>The decision on the location of the SKA between Australia-New Zealand and Southern Africa is expected around 2012.</p>
<p>Construction on the energy generation projects is scheduled to commence in November 2010, be completed in August 2013, and support 62 construction jobs.</p>
<p>The $47.3 million Rudd Government investment is part of the Sustainability Round of the Education Investment Fund, which is seeing a $4 billion investment in world-leading, strategic tertiary education and research infrastructure.</p>
<p>To learn more about Australia and New Zealand's SKA bid - including access to images, animations and factsheets - visit <a href="http://www.ska.gov.au">www.ska.gov.au</a> </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
