<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7001</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit by Prime Minister of the Solomon Islands</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007001.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p> 12 SEPTEMBER 1986</p>
<p>The Prime Minister of the Solomon Islands, Sir Peter Kenilorea, is visiting Australia from 11 to 18 September as a guest of the Australian Government.</p>
<p>During his visit Sir Peter will have discussion with World Vision Australia to advance consideration of World Vision's rehabilitation program in the Solomon Islands after Cyclone Namu and attend the First National Prayer Breakfast being organised by the Australian Parliamentary Christian Fellowship. Sir Peter will hold discussions with the Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Hayden, and the Minister for Defence, Mr Beazley. He will also call on the Chairman of the Foreign Affairs and Defence Committee, Senator Sibraa, the Chairman of the Australian Parliamentary Christian Fellowship, Senator Tate, and the Director-General of the  Australian Development Assistance Bureau, Dr Dun.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said that Sir Peter's visit will further strengthen the goodwill and friendship between Australia and the Solomon islands. It would also provide an opportunity for Sir  Peter to tell the Australian Government personally of the progress being made by the Solomon Islands in reconstruction following Cyclone Namu in May. Australia provided emergency relief assistance to the Solomon Islands after Cyclone Namu amounting to over $ 4 million and is one of the countries assisting with post-cyclone reconstruction.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
