<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2425</transcript-id>
    <title>RELIEF FOR EAST PAKISTAN REFUGEES IN INDIA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002425.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS PM No. 59/ 1971<br />
RELIEF FOR EAST PAKISTAN REFUGEES IN INDIA<br />
Statement-bythe Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
The Government has been following closely developments in<br />
the regio-n of East Pakistan. Great distress has beer, caused by the fighting<br />
there and by the resulting economic and social disruption. Large numbers<br />
of people have crossed the border into India where they have claimed<br />
refuge. This has caused a serious problem for India.<br />
The Government has always had a deep concer-. n for the plight<br />
of refugees and victims of emergencies. Similar humanitarian considerations<br />
have influenced the Government in deciding to contribute to the international<br />
relief effort which is being organised by the United Nations for East<br />
Pakistani refugees in India.<br />
The Government has decided to provide half a million dollars<br />
in relief for the refugees. Emergency aid worth $ 239, 00 will be-provided<br />
immediately. This will consist of $ 50, 0-30 in cash and the despatch by air to<br />
the official Indian Government relief agency in Calcutta of vaccines,<br />
medicines and materials to provide shelter from the mron;-soon which is<br />
expected to break shortly.<br />
The further $ 3010, 030 of supplies, to be made available<br />
subsequently, will be shipped as soon as possible.<br />
The Government has already been in touch with relief<br />
organisations in Australia and will provide them with any iinformation<br />
and advice received from international bodies and other authorities which<br />
are concerned with the relief operation in India.<br />
CANBERRA 27 May 1971 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
