<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6762</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, CABLE BEACH HOTEL, NASSAU, 14 OCTOBER 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006762.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Z. O. E. -PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT 0V' PRE~ SS COMMEflNCE CJABLE BEACH HOTEL, NAV<br />
JOURNALIST Goner al? What camxe out of your mQting with the S<br />
PM: Well, we had a ve~ ry usoful discussion about how h õ sai<br />
the structure of tho maeting. And it is quito cloar hatt Ii<br />
the iscuo of Southorn Af rica will be the most inmportzn4 it(<br />
at thia M4octing. 1 we wnt over the tixnetabling of that4<br />
I don't think~ it ia a mattor which will be rooolvodL atithel! 3;<br />
boginning of the motingt although it will come up, : 1 oul.<br />
think, on tho first day. It is an ionue which will re uirLc<br />
I think, an amount of discuosion at tho retreat ovor low.<br />
JOURNALIMT Dlid he exproan concern that Brita'in might no~<br />
willing to co-operato in sianctions againot South Agric9<br />
P14: Obv~ ouily the pocition of Britain waz one of the mati~'!<br />
discuned by us, but we havo ccw= ion ground that tho id alj I.<br />
position irs one where out of diocuosion Britain wilcnt<br />
merit of having a unitod Comionwoalth view, which will lnv<br />
increcood proasurc in a number of ways upon South 2Afri-a t.<br />
try and achieve a porjition leading tow~ rdc tho dicamant ingjI<br />
apartheid in South Africa and a timataible undar which out:<br />
Agrica can mova to the emergconce oZ free anc2 liboral 00c:<br />
Now, no-ono, including npyelf, aa I made clear fromi thci I<br />
beginning, haa co~ o to thin conforence with a viaw to ryi:<br />
to ioolato or attch Britain. flath~ r# what we vrant tc Co<br />
by the force and pom~ or of argument to achieve a situat~ on 2<br />
we can, got a -c on pooition.[ 4<br />
JOUMlIALIST: bid you onlin Astralia'o idoa of a conittr<br />
Ani, iU co, what wiao M4r Romphal'g rosponso?<br />
PtI oitlineA that thait wan part o2 an overall Auctr4,1ia!<br />
approcch end tho Scrotay-Gonaral indicatod thfct ho ' oue<br />
thñ iz wao a vary ap-opriato part of an avo~ zll mochcni'mM<br />
you likG, to doal with thia Zund&amp; amntal icue.<br />
. MMI-M<br />
14=( W9W 0, </p>
<p>JOURNALISTz Prime Minister# is winning Kra Thatcher over KI<br />
now the main aim of this meeting?<br />
PM: Well, let me say thine that in the past the Commo~ wcal.<br />
has actad on the bamin of consennus and it is infinitew [ I<br />
preferabla that that be achieved on this occasion. And I r:<br />
hopeful that it ca~ n be done. , ii<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think you can persuade Mrs Thatch r?<br />
PM: I don't want to over-rate or over-atate my own ro3e.<br />
Clearly Australiao through mnyself, io going to have an<br />
iMpOrtant rol. e in this debate enid the omerqenoo of the<br />
Conutonwaalth paition. That hao been recognioad and accapt<br />
I hope by my contribution to bo able to play acme part in<br />
achieving tho consonoun which cloarly hoc tho potmition ofI i<br />
Britian as an intogral, important part of achieving coqoan, i<br />
So I will play my part, I hopo, in the parsuauiive procose.<br />
JOURlNALIST: bilatorally to rome of tho voters, 1 ko<br />
Canada and Now Zoaland. Will you ba fapoaking bilater illy<br />
kxofore tho confokonce ctarts with ? Nrs Thatcher? j<br />
P14t I would think so# yen.<br />
JO3RNtALISTs Do you think thare its a chance, Mr Hawkep of<br />
p~ rcucaainq 1,1ra~ Thatchor to ac mept the more limitad nan tic;<br />
that Vonaal eanctiono which aro being proposed by Mr Amp,-iIG<br />
PIA4: Lot no make it cloar. Mr Rampha2. in~ not talking oiL<br />
comyrohontvG mandatory sanctions. And nor do I bei~ e~ a . kt<br />
thatlo thca approoch which in achiavabiB o~ r appropriatoj, 1" 4<br />
acm to mo that rathar wo ought to bo talking at thoo 001<br />
eg arann %-hca, at this otoge, you ought to bo cblo totI<br />
vary Vanoral agreerantp to be looking at a gracduat~ d pro.-i<br />
But th; at all baing dono was tho clomont og an approcchKvihit<br />
cao-look iw* o arc not juct talking elbout canctionc, ao~ i,~<br />
economic pozource. M I hevo sai~ d at all tizaon, it ou<br />
b'a much bp-ttcr if you didn't have to rosoot to senctio.<br />
cll. Xt wculd be mvich bhottox if you could2 Vot utha 00<br />
&amp; Vrican mge~ ma to undorotand the incroeoing rp~ nne<br />
tho world to the operation og the ! parthoid sysJtom~ Qndj<br />
tham to undarsitand that thoy ought to otairt to tvlk to' ll<br />
tlia cluxonto wiithi~ n Ljouth Africa who aro going to bo<br />
inorta2t in Lachicoving a n3W South A61ica. Nowi, that a-j. w<br />
X hczvo-1% 3n talthing Libout, cnd will hGro talk 12) bOUtr ilo<br />
conoptoga group o: 2 rzinnt yo~ ono who will h. 2vo th<br />
rC) niñ 1A~ Vog ndxoooir-t h=. c., oivctn to tho Vooo, c Z2<br />
n 6eLnthCat, ac ta0Jdng to tho vcriosao; -1<br />
i~ iXtc-7A7 toS oth A. Oicnn Eogims to try nnd co an<br />
cccptac og? tho pvoilkion that chnnge voluntarily iwow: q<br />
o bnt,&amp;! ZN th2sfl oc_: thIx h e o Onu to imrcl3vDoan.<br />
h; 53 to go f , nth~ on ilt ir; tomh Imoro liholy in that </p>
<p>r L/ 1<br />
JOURNALIST: 14r Hawke, Glen Ella says South Africa is not s~ ji<br />
a bad place. What do you think of that? i<br />
PM: Well, I have not soon what Glan Ella has said. Rd 1L' 111<br />
don't viant to involve myself in any observations about len,<br />
I think that the world has an overwhelming amount of ev dant'<br />
that tho society of South Africa is totally objectionab. e<br />
JOURNALIST: Has he clmbarrassod you this week?<br />
PH: No, he hasnnt ambarrarissd me.<br />
JOURNALISTa Why did the Governent, Mr Hawkin, not put ore<br />
pressure on the Rugby Union to ban these players? I<br />
PH: Wall, that's something that I would rather loavo f r a<br />
later date. I havo at this ataga no roacon to baliavo hct<br />
the Auatralian Rugby Union ia going to participate or<br />
condona Auotralion involveint at an official level, a<br />
team lovol in compatition with South Africa, but the Hisnt i<br />
as you know, hao written to the Australian Rugby Union, landH<br />
I am optimiotic that out of the discuotiions that wiill t4eI<br />
place botvioen tho Minister anid the Rugby Union that wo %-4ill I.<br />
not have any infringement at that level of the Glaeaglos 1<br />
Agra= nt.<br />
i. JOURNALISTs Prigie N~ inistor, have you boon kept abrao of ' 1<br />
Aaonatan ivch ' Tvr. n .1ays s&amp; mnedia 1a~ e * Lma<br />
concern? .1<br />
PH: No, all I have Boon at this stage is the reforence 1cto<br />
twelve, I think, individuala. That is an initial cable tal<br />
I1 h~ vo -got. I will cortainly be seeking to romain fulN<br />
informed, but X have no more details at this etage.<br />
JOUIM3LIST: Do you think the frontlinie totatoo in Afric-wi 21<br />
oupport the coimitteo proceca? it would oem to be,.<br />
lanet ouprficially, a cof tening of thoir hLardlina poui ion<br />
to dicniantle nparthaid now, a they have said. 1<br />
PM: N~ o, but I think, Grog, that thrat queation in that orm0=<br />
mis-un eoFotandJ what we are talking about. If we viora j* U13t.,<br />
talking about a comittoe procaca, then I boliove thkt i<br />
would bo unaccaptablo. But it io as mart of an ovarvall onM.<br />
whicAh z~ citroan ouwcolvea C-Q quonzAOn OC how 4. tu<br />
exrinont parv~ onm who would bo add1ranaing thumolvcoJ to tI1V I<br />
procoune oC chango. X wkL-1hLn 4' d'hri oonwet. no 0 L<br />
will it be acceptnble, but will be welccmed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
