<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8817</transcript-id>
    <title>TOYOTA AUSTRALIA LINE-OFF CEREMONY PORT MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008817.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
II,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
TOYOTA AUSTRALIA LINE-OFF CEREMONY<br />
PORT MELBOURNE 16 FEBRUARY 1993<br />
Obviously this is a great day for the Australian car industry. We are here because<br />
Toyota is here for the long haul.<br />
It means1jobs. Long-term good jobs for Australians.<br />
It means another step has been taken in the development Of world-class manufacturing<br />
in Australia. It means another step in the integration of our economy wVith the world's,<br />
and more especially with the region and Japan.<br />
It means that the long relationship between Toyota and Australia continues to prosper<br />
and grow. This is good for us. Toyota is, without doubt, one of the great companies of<br />
the world. It is renowned for innovation, reliability and perfection.<br />
Yesterday I spoke at the Best Practice and Benchrnarking Conference in Sydney. It<br />
goes without saying that Toyota is a benchmark for any company in the world.<br />
It is therefore automatically of great benefit to our manufacturing industry to have<br />
Toyota here and expanding.<br />
Of course the outstanding advantage for Australia in the present economic climate is<br />
that Toyota's investment means long-term jobs for Australians.<br />
Everyone here will be aware that it is my Government's great ambition to increase the<br />
level of-investment -in Australia.<br />
It is the most effective remedy for unemployment, indeed the only answer to the<br />
entirely unacceptable levels of unemployment. we presently have.<br />
6364 </p>
<p>2<br />
That is why last Tuesday we announced that we will be cutting thecornany tax rate in<br />
Australia from 39 per cent to 33, to make us competitive not only with OECDi<br />
economics but with the economics of the Asia Pacific.<br />
It was for the same purpose that we introduced a new investment allowance.<br />
We are determined to bring forward the S130 billion worth of projects currently<br />
claiming the allowance granted in the One Nation statement of twelve months ago.<br />
We are also determined to get new investment going, particularly among small<br />
companies of the kind surveyed in the recent McKinsey Company Report to the<br />
Australian Manufacturing Council.<br />
Small to medium sized companies charactrnsed by dynamic leadership, innovation,<br />
attention to excellence, successful niche marketing and, no less, highly productive and<br />
skilled workplaces.<br />
There is no-one in this country, I should think, who does not recognise that we are<br />
embarked on a course to become a successful, modern manufacturing nation.<br />
I should think there is no--one who does not know that our way of life depends on it.<br />
Equally, we know that our success in manufacturing. and in exporting the things we<br />
design and make depends on new levels . of productivity.<br />
We will not succeed by employing old patterns of production.<br />
High levels of productivity, by definition, means fewer people making more and better<br />
things. It follows that the answer to unemployment is growth a proliferation of<br />
manufacturing effort and expertise. The key! 9ogrowth is investment..<br />
won't today go into the details of the investment strategy we launched last week. But<br />
I do want to talk about two broad related elements of Labor policy.<br />
We take the view that Australia needs a car industry, and we believe that the car<br />
industry in Australia needs an incentive to invest.<br />
Dare I say it might come as a surprise to my opponents to learn that we in Australia are<br />
not alone in the world in this.<br />
We would be alone if we were to go to zero tariffs in the car industry.<br />
We would be alone and without a car industry.<br />
So let me say very plainly we are commnitted to a 15 per cent tariff for the Australian<br />
car industry. 6365 </p>
<p>3<br />
We are also committed, you will know, to that mode of workplace bargaining known<br />
as enterprise agreements.<br />
in this we also take a different view to the Coalition. But, surprisingly enough. I will<br />
not expound on this today.<br />
I do not feel the need to proselytise because this project is built on a model enterprise<br />
agreement. An agreement signed in December 1991 with 6000 Toyota employees.<br />
It's an agreement linked to obtaining international best practice, and delivering to the<br />
company and its employees mutual advantages unimaginable under the old workplace<br />
arrangements of Australian industry and Australian industrial relations.<br />
Advantages, I venture to say, unattainable under any alternative scheme in which<br />
relationships are adversarial or unequal.<br />
700 new enterprise agreements have been entered into in the past seven months.<br />
They seem to me, like this one, clear evidence that we can achieve high levels of<br />
productivity, best practice, international benchmarks in other words the world-class<br />
manufacturing industry we need through enterprise agreements such as these.<br />
As I said in the speech in Sydney yesterday, what is unfolding in Australia now is<br />
' something like the realisation of a long-held ambition.<br />
I remember fifteen years or so ago, coming to the conclusion that the prevailing<br />
wisdom about Australia was all wrong.<br />
There was no need for us to always remain an exporter of commodities, with such<br />
manufacturing as we had crumbling away behind giant tariff walls.<br />
It seemed to me then that we could become a world-class manufacturer. It seemed to<br />
me very soon after, that if we did not, we had no future. it seems to me now in fact<br />
there is no doubt that we are becoming a world-class; manufacturer, and for that<br />
reason there is no doubt about our future.<br />
I could say a great deal more about the subject, but this is a day for Toyota's<br />
management and workers to celebrate. There is doubtless much for Australians and<br />
particuilarly the people of Melbourne to celebrate as well.<br />
For my part, and for John Button's rm sure, there is some measure of satisfation in<br />
having been involved in the creation of economic and industrial policy which has<br />
yielded such results as this.<br />
We are determined to continue the great drive to make Australia competitive in the<br />
world and in the region.<br />
We believe that the best way to do this is not by the imposition of a textbook blueprint<br />
or strict adherence to economic theory, but by a range of measures designed to take<br />
636C </p>
<p>4<br />
account of factors unique to Australia, to various industries and their comparative<br />
advantages and disadvantages.<br />
We want the most competitive industries it is possible to have.<br />
But we are not prepared to have major industries disappear for the sake of some notion<br />
of what constitutes pure theory.<br />
-Economic ~ policvs not a death or glory game. It requires a measure of subtlety, a<br />
recognition of differences, of the need for interventions.<br />
We might begin by reminding ourselves at the outset that there is no competition<br />
where there is no industry at all.<br />
And it doesn't hurt also to remember that in the end we want industry because we want<br />
secure, creative and rewarding employment for our people.<br />
That is what this $ 400 million investment by Toyota is creating.<br />
That, and further recognition that Australia has the investment climate and the<br />
workforce to make it a place where the best companies in the world can thrive.<br />
And those are reasons for all of us to celebrate today. 6367 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
