<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8600</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, QUEENSLAND STATE ALP FUNDRAISING DINNER, GREEK COMMUNITY CENTRE, 30 JULY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008600.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING HP,<br />
QUEENSLAND STATE ALP FUNDRAISING DINNER, GREEK COMMUNITY<br />
CENTRE, 30 JULY 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Ian McClean, the Lord Mayor, and of course the Premier,<br />
Ladles and Gentlemen.<br />
Well thank you very Much for those kind words, Wayne, and<br />
for so many of you coming along tonight. I don't know<br />
about the Canberra Raiders, I'll be gone by then, but I<br />
hope at the Grand Final when it really matters I can do a<br />
Lazarus too, and be there when it matters.<br />
But as Wayne and I came tonight into the building with<br />
the demonstrators outside, I thought of that remark<br />
passed by a predecessor of mine also in Queensland, I<br />
thought if I knew Wayne was that unpopular I mightn't<br />
have come with him. But jokes aside it's great to share<br />
a platform with him, the most popular Premier in<br />
Australia, a clean cut guy in every way. Clean cut<br />
personally, clean cut politically, given hope and heart<br />
to the Queensland Labor Party and restored it to its<br />
position in Government as the oldest Labor Party in the<br />
world, a real achievement.<br />
For some reason there's a great empathy between the New<br />
_.. ZuhWales Labor Party and the QueenslandLabor 95i-ty.<br />
When you go __ to a___ 07eensland1 Labor Party' ConTerne-yralways<br />
feel at home, there's always working people there.<br />
it has not been middle-classed, and it's always great to<br />
be amongst the Labor Party in Queensland, it feels like<br />
there just isn't a boarder between us.<br />
But ladies and gentlemen, I've had a wonderful week in<br />
Queensland and I must say that in the six odd months I've<br />
been Prime Minister no better reception and nicer time<br />
have I had than Townsville, Innisvale, Rockhampton,<br />
Glandstone and now in Brisbane. And the thought occurred<br />
to me today and yesterday as we talked to those<br />
communities, and also recently when I was in Newcastle in<br />
New South Wales, not long after recovering from an<br />
earthquake, and in Geelong in Victoria which of course<br />
has had more than its share of economic woes. But the </p>
<p>one thing I found in all of these places is a great sense<br />
of purpose as communities, cohesion, common sense, social<br />
partnerships and of course spirit, and I found that<br />
yesterday in Townsville, I found it at lunch at the Civic<br />
Reception given for us in Innisvale, in Rockhampton last<br />
evening, and in Glandstone, when a few years ago and I<br />
use to go there as a Shadow Minister for Minerals it was<br />
a small community of a few thousand, now grown to over<br />
23,000 and an international port city of Australia.<br />
And it just makes the point that these communities<br />
understand better, than perhaps Some in the major cities,<br />
about how to make Australia work, how to work together,<br />
how to achieve things, how to have pride and have that<br />
spirit and go out and grasp the future. Because that's<br />
what I found around Queensland, that great spirit of<br />
optimism, that spirit that says we're not going to let<br />
anything defeat us and we're going to get out there and<br />
grasp the future.<br />
We're pretty lucky in this country, we're the only nation<br />
in the world that has a content to itself. We've got<br />
what a lot of countries don't have and that is clean air,<br />
clean water, a lot of space and a great future. You know<br />
what they always say about real-estate ' position,<br />
position, position', well we've got the best real estate<br />
in the world. And that is, a continent in the South<br />
Pacific and the Asia Pacific area, which is the fastest<br />
growing part of the world, where we can carve out for<br />
ourselves a lifestyle and an existence which is unique<br />
amongst nations. That is a multicultural country,<br />
inheriting a continent, coming to terms with it, coming<br />
to terms with the resonances of Australia, the old<br />
continent of Australia, coming to terms with the first<br />
Australians, making a life for ourselves in this country,<br />
locking ourselves in with the Asia Pacific, and giving<br />
ourselves a style of living and an income which I think<br />
can be the envy of the world. Very few countries have<br />
those possibilities now, Australia still has it, and that<br />
great spirit I found in Queensland today is the thing<br />
that will capture it for us.<br />
Now ladies and gentlemen, It's a case of working<br />
together, of partnerships. And if you look at that<br />
tremendous community spirit in those towns and cities<br />
I've mentioned, it's all about partnerships, the<br />
community comes to you as a whole. They don't come to<br />
you as factions or with divisions, they approach you as a<br />
whole. And that's the great strength, and must be<br />
strength in pulling Australia together.<br />
Now we've had good times and we've had some tough times,<br />
we've been in a recession we're now into recovery, we've<br />
got unemployment as a result. But we've still come a<br />
long way. Our labour market today is 7 1/ 2 million. it<br />
was 6 million in 1983, even with the unemployment it's<br />
per cent bigger. In 1983 the size of the economy was<br />
worth $ 200 billion, GDP was $ 200 billion, today it's $ 400 </p>
<p>billion. And sure, the economy has not grown in the last<br />
18 months very much, ityVgr-owng again now. But as a<br />
result we've not had enough employment to take people up<br />
into the labour market and _ 4npeiR_; oYment has risen. But<br />
we'e arglyettTe jobs of the 1980s and we-had three<br />
times the employment growth of the western world then, we<br />
had very high work force growth coming from our natural<br />
population and migration, and we succeeded in taking<br />
those people up and bringing unemployment down and<br />
doubling the nominal size of our gross domestic product,<br />
not a bad achievement in that period.<br />
But now that we're in a position where we've been in a<br />
recession, again we've got to make it clear there's a<br />
role for government in directing Australia to the future.<br />
It's not simply a case of relying upon the old question<br />
of private initiative and private reward, as important as<br />
they are, it is not a matter of relying on those alone<br />
but having government create markets, making markets work<br />
and governments doing the things in infrastructure, the<br />
building which we know has made Australia great.<br />
Now I was at the South Johnstone sug9Ar mill yesterday and<br />
interestingly it wai W fff by-Fthe-6ueeniii Government.<br />
It's no longer owned by the Queensland Government, it's<br />
very competently managed now by the people who produce in<br />
the region. But it's another example of how Government<br />
can kick a community along when those resources don't<br />
exist. That's the attitude we've taken in the One Nation<br />
program, which Wayne mentioned, and where today Bob Brown<br />
and I announced a $ 2 billion road program for Australia<br />
and one of the biggest infrastructure spending programs<br />
ever 45 per cent increase in Queensland this year over<br />
last year, $ 600 million extra dollars from the One Nation<br />
package in roads.<br />
It's just another example of Government playing its<br />
proper role, in roads, in rail, in airlines, in all of<br />
the things we know a private company can't provide. A<br />
private company can't build a highway. A private company<br />
is not going to build a ring road around the capital<br />
cities. A private company is not going to build a<br />
railway line down to Robina. A private company is not<br />
going to restore the National Rail Highway of Australia.<br />
These things can only be done by Government. And there<br />
is a role for Government in providing that public<br />
infrastructure and kicking the economy along at a time<br />
when private spending is down, so when private spending<br />
picks up it can play its role as we know it has to.<br />
there is a real role there for Government, and part of<br />
that, of course, is even beyond those great building<br />
programs for which the Labor Party has always been proud<br />
and had a great history, but as well as that in the areas<br />
of social policy.<br />
Now Wayne mentioned earlier the fact that we're now an<br />
externally oriented country. This is true. We've thrown<br />
off the Menzold, Menzian era of believing that we were a </p>
<p>lucky country, and that we needed to nothing more clever<br />
than dig up another mount of minerals, grow another<br />
paddock full of wheat, grow a bit more wool and Bobs<br />
you're Uncle. Well Bob wasn't you're uncle. And we<br />
found by 1980 that we could no longer pay for our<br />
imports. And that the so called ' lucky~ county. was not<br />
really a very clever country, that the post war trade in<br />
goods and services had passed us by, that we were still<br />
buying things from the shelves of the world, computers,<br />
colour televisions, video tap recorders all the rest, we<br />
expected to have those things but couldn't pay for them,<br />
and then started to borrow to be able to maintain our<br />
standard of living.<br />
Now this Government said we can't go on like this, we'll<br />
end up like some of the South American economies, and how<br />
could you tolerate a position where you claim to be a<br />
smart society but only three children in ten completed<br />
secondary school, where the university system was falling<br />
to pieces, underfunded and under utilised. And so we<br />
started on that long road of getting from three kids in<br />
ten completing secondary school to seven in ten, now<br />
moving to nine in ten, we rebuilt our university system<br />
added 50 per cent of places, and in a great historic<br />
decision of two weeks ago, in which your Premier played<br />
an historic part, we're now going to build a National<br />
Training Authority to do for technical education what we<br />
did for universities.<br />
Now what we want to be is smart soclety. A smart society<br />
where kids are given an opportunity for training and good<br />
jobs. And we regard those years of 15 to 19 as a period<br />
of vocational preparation and we stream them through to<br />
the sort of clever jobs, the high quality jobs that we<br />
know that this country needs. Because what we don't want<br />
to go sell is selling our labour cheaply, we don't want<br />
to compete in the international division of labour in our<br />
neighbourhood in the world. I don't want to see<br />
Australians working for $ 1.30 a day as is the lot of the<br />
workers of Indonesia. That is not the league we want to<br />
be playing in, we don't want to be pushing wages down and<br />
selling our labour cheaply, we want to be selling our<br />
brains, our creativity, our ability and become as we've<br />
always been, a smart society which is capable of research<br />
and development, producing innovative products and going<br />
getting a premium for them and selling clever goods out<br />
there. That's Australia's role, that's Australia's<br />
future, not downgrading our people saying that they are<br />
incapable of it and that they've got to cut their wages<br />
to be competitive. That's not the society we want.<br />
in this great transition where we've lowered the tariff<br />
walls, where we've floated the exchange rate, where we've<br />
restarted Australian manufactuxring sotathsyr<br />
elaborately transformed manufactured exports where<br />
greater than rural exports or mining exports. That sort<br />
of important transition, the transition to services<br />
industries like tourism, which are now helping the </p>
<p>Queensland economy, didn't exist a decade ago. And which<br />
have come along because of this great transition, this<br />
great external transition. And it's that transition<br />
which is going to underpin our standard of living.<br />
So I put to you that a Labor Government, it took a Labor<br />
Government to introduce a market economy into Australia.<br />
A Labor Government to itouearemrkteconomy<br />
into Australia. But we did it with a Labor heart, we did<br />
it with a Labor heart. Because we grafted onto that<br />
economic policy a social policy which we think is the<br />
kind of policy that sticks with the central tenants of<br />
Labor's thought and philosophy, and keeps that<br />
egalitarianism and fairness of Australia together. And<br />
such things and the right of access to medical services<br />
is a basic right and we have it there with Medicare.<br />
Equal access to education, as I mentioned, giving all<br />
children the right to secondary education or tertiary or<br />
vocational education. Access to education is a basic<br />
Australian right, a right of everybody. Or the right to<br />
support women with childcare, or the aged with age care,<br />
decent pensions, geriatric assessment, the Home and<br />
Community Care program, the Hostel program, the Nursing<br />
H~ ome program. These are all the great reforms of Labor<br />
in the<br />
And of couree, no greater than access to occupational<br />
superannuation for the whole workforce, a right to a<br />
decent-r4t ement income. And it's that right to a<br />
decent retirement income which will do these two things:<br />
not only when my generation, when the baby boomers turn<br />
and there are twice as many retired aged people in the<br />
community as there is today, we won't put that terrible<br />
burden on our children to pay for us, that tremendous<br />
inter generational transfer which will occur as a huge<br />
aged population relies upon their children to provide for<br />
themi in later years, now's the time to provide for<br />
ourselves by saving and producing a decent retirement<br />
income. But in so doing, build 8 pool of national<br />
savings which will fund our development, fund our<br />
investment and fund our growth into the future.<br />
Because the problem we're all going to face in the 1990s<br />
is that the world economy of today was last like this<br />
before the first World War. This is the first time since<br />
1914 that the old Soviet States have rejoined the world<br />
economy, since China is now rejoining the world economy,<br />
India, the Americas, South America. And they'll be all<br />
out there in the ' 90s bidding for savings, bidding for<br />
investment capital, to rebuild Russia to rebuild eastern<br />
Europe, East Germany, India, China, South America, and we<br />
don't want to be out there with the savings begging bowl<br />
trying to fund our current account deficit. We've made<br />
the step already to do it with occupational<br />
superannuation, to put those savings into place.<br />
we'll have there by the end of this decade about $ 800<br />
billion, $ 800,000 million which is about five times our </p>
<p>6<br />
national debt, and we'll be in that comfortable position<br />
of being able to fund our investment programs and with it<br />
bring on the employment which is entirely necessary for<br />
giving us the kind of society that we've always believed<br />
we should have, one where a right to a job is a basic<br />
Australian right.<br />
So ladies arnd gentlemen, these are the things that Labor<br />
has done. We've introduced a market economy, we've<br />
opened Australia up, we've started to produce clever<br />
things again, we've opened ourselves up for services, but<br />
we've done it with a decent social policy. We've done it<br />
with a social policy that looks after the sick, the aged,<br />
the young, the poor, women, migrants. We've done it to<br />
keep Australia together. We've done it the Labor way.<br />
We've not been, as somebody said of Dr Hewson the other<br />
night who described him as a feral abacus, we are not a<br />
feral abacus. We're not about simply ticking of f numbers<br />
as though people don't matter, counting beads as though<br />
people don't matter. We're about developing Australia,<br />
interlocking it with the Asia Pacific, having an<br />
efficient economy but at the same time having a decent<br />
social policy.<br />
And we all know we're going through a phase where we're<br />
getting more output from fewer people. And it's<br />
producing unemployment. We're getting more production<br />
from a smaller workforce. Loads of productivity, it's<br />
called productivity, and we need it to be efficient.<br />
That is, we're getting much more production from those<br />
who produce it. So what does that mean if we're going to<br />
get unemployment down? What it means to get unemployment<br />
down is that we've got to produce even more output. if a<br />
given level of output produces only so much employment<br />
and it's not enough, the only thing to do is to produce<br />
even more output, and that means that the Australian<br />
economy has to grow at a reasonably fast pace. And to<br />
have it grow at a fast pace, and still control inflation<br />
can only be done with an incomes policy. It can't be<br />
done with interest rates, it can't be done with a central<br />
bank jumping on the economy because to do that it cuts<br />
the speed down and therefore cuts the employment growth<br />
o f-f.<br />
We've always had employment as an express objective of<br />
Government policy. It hasn't been a residual that fell<br />
out of the numbers. And when I used to stand up in the<br />
OECD in the 1980s and talk about employment being the<br />
express objective, some of those European Finance<br />
Ministers would look at me as though I had a case of<br />
leprosy. Because they are interested only in their<br />
current accounts and inflation.<br />
We on the other hand have always had employment as a<br />
c~ lear and express objective. And that means you must run<br />
with a high workforce growth of this country, even with<br />
modest immigration growth, without natural population<br />
growth, with workforce growth of 1.6 per cent a year, you<br />
n % A J L V L I I U V 1 11 F V Q I A </p>
<p>have got to run the ecoinmy at a reasonable speed. Every<br />
time we have done that before our incomes Policy, before<br />
the Accord, that speed spilled Into 8 price and wage<br />
round, and we ended up with higher inflation, lower<br />
growth, and higher unemployment. We beat that dismal<br />
legacy in the 19809 with an incomes policy. We ran the<br />
economy at quite a speed but still had decelerating<br />
inflation. So much so, that yesterday we chalked up the<br />
lowest figure in just on thirty years with 1.2 per cent.<br />
So, having the mechanism in place to let the economy grow<br />
and not kill it with interest rates to save inflation,<br />
and tolerate a pool of unemployment, means that you must<br />
have a conversation with organised labour and with<br />
business. Now, whether you call it cooperation, or<br />
discussion, or an Accord really doesn't matter. There<br />
has got to be a discussion about national income<br />
determination how much national income goes to wages<br />
and how much goes to profits. And it is in that model<br />
with the ACTU we have been able to run Australia quite<br />
fast and still have decelerating inflation.<br />
In contras4t D~ r niewson's model has unemployment as a break<br />
upon wage increases. In his model unemployment is<br />
actually sitting there as a tool, to actually moderate<br />
wage claims and to moderate inflation, but of course you<br />
will have no conversation with organised labour, and the<br />
central bank would simply be in instructed to lift the<br />
interest rates to sit on the economy. And so in his<br />
model, not only is employment not an express objective,<br />
unemployment becomes a tool of government policy. We<br />
reject that absolutely, totally.<br />
In the end the difference between the Labor Party and its<br />
opponents is a matter of heart. The Labor Party has it<br />
and they don't. The Labor Party grew with the soul of<br />
this country and the Liberal Party has tried to graft<br />
itself onto it, all these years. But this was never<br />
plainer then now, as Dr Hewson and that rotten remnant of<br />
the New R~ ights agenda, Fightback, comes-as the creed of<br />
the new conservative parties. But in the end, the proper<br />
end of economic policy is social improvement, and the<br />
notion we have heard him speak about in the last day or<br />
two about cutting wages, taking kids to $ 3.00 an hour,<br />
getting rid of awards, rates of pay, and conditions of<br />
employment to go to three quarters of average weekly<br />
earnings, or some such figure for the average person, is<br />
not social improvement.<br />
The point of economic policy is to lift people up, not<br />
push them down. Dr Hewson thinks it's a crime for me to<br />
say I want to see Australians with higher real wages. Dr<br />
Heweon I do. And I make no apologies for it. And we can<br />
do it by the sort of economic policies that Australia can<br />
have. But you won't get anywhere economically by destroying the<br />
country socially. So don't my word for it, ask all of </p>
<p>those people who fell through the social trap door in<br />
Britain and the United States. All those people, You can<br />
almost draw a line in Britain for the people who are<br />
lucky enough to enjoy the best of the British economy<br />
living South of London, arnd all the rest living in the<br />
North, broadly living in the North, who don't have that<br />
social improvement. Or in the United States, if you are<br />
unemployed there, like or Hewson after nine months, after<br />
six months your out with no support, no income support,<br />
no unemployment benefits, and if you are cold you huddle<br />
over a railway grate and try and live in the warm<br />
exhaust. That's not for us, and we are not having it.<br />
Or, in the United States if you are sick and you get<br />
admitted to a hospital and you get to the door, even if<br />
you are acutely sick, if that blue cross card isn't in<br />
your pocket they turn you away. Now you couldn't<br />
comprehend anybody with medical training turning someone<br />
acutely sick away because they are not insured and they<br />
don't have the card with them. That's what happens in<br />
the United States. We will never let it happen here.<br />
They get to this position where Dr Hewson is so down on<br />
-unions, but he is not down on the -DoctoruFn'aio n. He<br />
turned up to the AMA about six weeks ago on a weekend and<br />
said he will let the AMA set the common fee. Not the<br />
Commonwealth Government, which is now paying a large part<br />
of the health bill, but the AMA. And he will let doctors<br />
basically generate the incomes they think the traffic<br />
will bear. But If you are a working person three<br />
quarters of your pay for you and $ 3.00 an hour if you are<br />
a kid. That's his policy. And we are not copping that,<br />
policy, and we are not copping it for this reason that<br />
people will not be able to afford medical insurance. we<br />
are not having a position where low income people, or<br />
even middle income people with children, can't afford to<br />
insure themselves when they are sick and get access to<br />
medical insurance. Because under Medicare now you can be<br />
on an income in the $ 20,000s with a coul of children<br />
and pay no levy whatsoever, and society gives you that<br />
right to medical treatment because those of us who are<br />
earning the higher Incomes pay it for you under Medicare,<br />
which is an equitable policy.<br />
These are the things which are important. The same with<br />
education, Dr 1fewson has a voucherpoigy. Voucher<br />
policies have never worked anywhere in the world. You<br />
get virtually a bus ticket which has so many dollars<br />
written on it, you go and check it in at a university, or<br />
someone else. And he says this puts incentive into the<br />
system and the freedom to achieve. It costs $ 120,000 to<br />
train somebody for a Medical degree. What freedom does<br />
an ordinary working persons child have if they don't have<br />
the $ 120,000 for the full fee place, or the child of a<br />
working family that might want an Arts degree which is<br />
going to cost of the order of $ 20,000 to $ 30,000? They<br />
haven't got it. When we get as a society where the<br />
bright kids get jammed out of the education system<br />
because their parents can't afford it, that's the time to </p>
<p>pack it in, that's the sort Of policy he wants to put in<br />
education. These are the things that the next election will be<br />
decided on. It will be about bringing a recovery on,<br />
consolidating the recovery, having a role for Government<br />
to lift that spending, to be the catalyst in a recovery,<br />
to bring private Investment back up, and to see it go on.<br />
And at the same time to build on all of the social<br />
advances we have made and the things I have been talking<br />
about health care, education, childcare, age care, all<br />
of the other things, support for Aboriginals, migrants,<br />
all of these areas are the things which we will continue.<br />
But he has basically one policy with two prongs: higher<br />
prices end lower wages that's the policy. 15 per cent<br />
addition to prices, which will blow our inflation rate to<br />
pieces in an exercise in economic vandalism, that would<br />
be entirely culpable given the fact that we now after<br />
twenty years have the inflation rate under 2 per cent, to<br />
add a net 6 or 7 per centage points to the price system<br />
to take it back to double digits would be unconscionable.<br />
That's what he wants to do. And while he lifts those<br />
prices he cuts people's wages. Now you all know If you<br />
are on $ 20,000 to $ 30,000, whether you tax someone's<br />
income or their expenditure is entirely beside the point,<br />
because they are one in the same. An ordinary person<br />
spends every cent that they earn, so whether you tax it<br />
as income or as expenditure it is all the same. But the<br />
person on the high income spends only a proportion of<br />
their salary and saves the rest, and those people have<br />
the benefit of the proposals put by Dr Hewson and the tax<br />
benefits for them are paid for by the low income and<br />
middle income people who spend all their income in the<br />
supermarket or in their daily living.<br />
The OST will blow our inflation rate to pieces and with<br />
it d6r~ 1nterest rates. It will effect a huge transfer of<br />
wealth from the low and middle income earners to the high<br />
income earners. It will essentially derail Australian<br />
investment while at the same time the consensus we have<br />
had for a decade now about wages, profits end national<br />
incomes will be put asunder as he tries to abolish<br />
centralised wage fixation, the only thing in national<br />
wage cases which protects the low paid, as he tries to<br />
knock them off, knock of f federal awards and cut people'ss<br />
wages. This is what he holds. We don't need lower<br />
wages, the wage share and GDP at the moment Is in the<br />
1960s, at 1960s levels. We don't need to sell cheap<br />
labour to the rest of the world, we need to sell our<br />
brains to the rest of the world making smart products and<br />
educating people, and lifting our people up. And that's<br />
the difference between us.<br />
So, ladies and gentlemen I say this, I think as a Party<br />
we have been very fair in this sense. We have never said<br />
to Australian business, look we believe it can be all<br />
done on the public sector. When I became Treasurer the<br />
-4 </p>
<p>Commonwealth public Sector was over 30 per cent of the<br />
size of the economy, it is now about 24. It is 6 per<br />
cent of GDP smaller, or about $ 25 billion a year smaller.<br />
Ipso Facto the private economy is $ 25 billion bigger. We<br />
shifted the profit share so that people in business can<br />
af ford to invest by a higher level of profit, which we<br />
effected in the late 1980s and is fundamentally still<br />
there. As the volumes pick up the profits will go on the<br />
bottom line and the profit share will come up as we saw<br />
in last quarter's National Accounts. we have got that in<br />
place, we have got a 39 per cent tax rate in place for<br />
companies, we have got full dividend imputation, we are<br />
one of the few countries in the world that only tax<br />
equity and dividends once where most other countries tax<br />
them twice. We have got all of that sitting in place and<br />
a stock of savings coming down the pipeline of<br />
superannuation to fund the investments this country is<br />
going to need. We have given business a fair break, and<br />
as we come out of the recession into a strong recovery<br />
all of those benefits and low inflation will count for<br />
Australian business.<br />
But while we have done that we have understood the real<br />
traditions of Australia and we have stuck to them.<br />
Unlike the Coalition who say we are the tradition<br />
breakers, they're the people who attack the tradition,<br />
and the tradition is equality, egalitarianism, and<br />
fairness. That is, we don't have an under class left<br />
behind, we pull everybody along. We have business<br />
pulling along, tugging along, and with it the workforce<br />
and with it the aged, the sick, the poor and the young,<br />
with proper social policies. And if some group drops<br />
back we lean our caring arm out and pull them up, pull<br />
them up with us, and move along as a community and a<br />
society. And that's the basic difference between us and the<br />
conservative parties. The Labor Party is a true<br />
political party, it has feelings, it has a soul. it is<br />
not simply an organisation committed to getting votes<br />
like some sort of business group, or some sort of<br />
business organisation, it's a political party with<br />
feelings, with substance, with loyalties. And our<br />
political party demands that as we progress ourselves we<br />
take Australian society along, all of us along, and we<br />
produce the sort of country we have always had but a more<br />
prosperous one.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen, that's what the contest is about<br />
in Australia. Never before have we seen such a contrast,<br />
well we have, but not recently between the parties,<br />
between the philosophy of the Coalition and the<br />
philosophy of the Labor Party. And we say to<br />
Australians, you're in a fundamental transition from the<br />
old Australia locked up behind a tariff wall, which<br />
disfavoured the big agricultural and mining States like<br />
Queensland and Western Australia, to the advantage of the<br />
industrialised areas, locked up behind a tariff wall and </p>
<p>TEL: 3. Aug. 92 18: 09 No. 018 P-11/ 1<br />
basically becoming uncompetitive. That's not the sort of<br />
position we want to see. we have taken it, we have<br />
changed that, but we have changed it in a way where we go<br />
forward. We don't need to smash the place socially to<br />
advance ourselves economically. And we won't, that's<br />
what the basic contest will be about.<br />
So when we go to the election sure we will have had the<br />
aftermath of the recession and the attendant<br />
unemployment, and we are doing everything to be rid of<br />
that. But as that goes down we say to Australians, stick<br />
with the change, stick with the basic historic transition<br />
to a modern society, to a modern Industrial state locked<br />
into the Asia-Pacific, one with a great bountiful<br />
continent with fresh air, clean water, space and a decent<br />
environment, loyal to our original Australians, and at<br />
the same time giving ourselves a decent standard of<br />
living. i don't think they will take the hard-hearted<br />
alternative. I don't think they will take the clinical<br />
technician, because in the end I don't think he has got<br />
much to of fer. Pain for pain's sake, misery for misery's<br />
sake, cutting ordinary people back and disadvantaging the<br />
poor never did anything for anybody. And that's why we<br />
have all got to move together as a group, and that's why<br />
it is important for Labor Governments to stick to their<br />
guns, have faith in their creed, and see the difficult<br />
changes through. And that's what has put this Government<br />
of yours together in Queensland under Wayne Goss, that's<br />
what will restore and retain us in the national arena<br />
because we are basically better, we basically can think<br />
better, and as importantly as that, we think with a heart<br />
and 8 soul.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, I thank you very much for coming,<br />
you have done me a great honour, and the Queensland Labor<br />
Party has done me a great honour in inviting you and<br />
assembling such a large audience of people, arnd I thank<br />
the members of the business community who have come along<br />
tonight. I will just say, you have always been part of<br />
us from the 1980a onwards, as the whole constituency of<br />
Australia is part of us. Whether it is the rural<br />
community, or the business community, or the poor, or the<br />
sick, or the aged, they are part of the Labor family.<br />
And we will go together as a family, and we will stay<br />
together as a family.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
