<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16023</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Statement by the  Prime Minister and the Premiers of  New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia and the Chief Minister of the Australian Capital Territory. Water Contingency Planning in the Southern Murray-Darling Basin</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Governments have received their eighth report from senior officials on dry inflow contingency planning in the southern Murray-Darling Basin (MDB). First Ministers have agreed to the recommendations made in the report.</p>
<p>The key message of the report is that the 2008-09 water availability outlook for the southern MDB is serious and has deteriorated through March - June. The report indicates that across much of the MDB the water available for irrigators, communities and the environment remains at record low levels. Water available in the Murray System is being shared between New South Wales (NSW), Victoria and South Australia in accordance with the special sharing arrangements agreed to by First Ministers on 5 February 2008. These special sharing arrangements are likely to be required throughout the water year 2008-09 and the need for contingency planning continues.</p>
<p>Rainfall over most of the southern MDB was below average for the 2007-08 water year. Hot and dry conditions in autumn 2008 in the southern Basin have resulted in diminished tributary inflows and increased losses. Little improvement in water availability was seen in the first half of 2008. Even with average rainfall in 2008-09, inflows could likely remain well below average because of dry catchments reducing runoff. Full recovery of the system is likely to take several years of above average rainfall. The Bureau of Meteorology's seasonal outlook for July to September shows increased chances of drier conditions in the southern part of the MDB.</p>
<p>Stream flow records in the southern MDB show that a dry autumn and early winter increases the chances of low inflows to storages over the reminder of the water year.</p>
<p>Compared to the rest of the MDB the south western corner of the Basin, which covers the lower reaches of the River Murray, received relatively little rainfall over summer. This area has also experienced higher than normal temperatures which has increased evaporation and exacerbated water quality concerns, particularly in the Lower Lakes. Lake Alexandrina and Lake Albert are currently experiencing unprecedented adverse environmental impacts as a consequence of the drought. These impacts include increasing salinity and the high risk of acidification and mobilisation of metals as a result of the exposure of acid sulfate soils.</p>
<p>Murray-Darling Basin Governments recognise the severe problems facing water users from the River Murray as a result of the drought. This is placing pressure on all water users, impacting on communities, production and the environment.</p>
<p>Based on the current water availability and assuming inflows at or above historic minimums, there would be sufficient water for critical human needs and water quality maintenance upstream of the Lower Lakes through 2008-09. However, if inflows are less and losses greater than expected, further contingency measures may be required to be implemented to secure critical human needs.</p>
<p>Governments are actively managing the Lower Lakes and Coorong situation and are providing $6 million through the MDB Commission to support the emergency measures to reduce the risk of environmental damage to Lake Albert. A range of medium and long term risk management strategies for the Coorong and Lower Lakes are being developed. Pumping of water from Lake Alexandrina to Lake Albert is underway as an emergency response to maintain current water levels and prevent potentially irreversible ecological consequences.</p>
<p>Governments understand that continuing low water availability over the coming months will particularly impact on irrigation and other water-dependent industries and the environment. Water users will need timely and accurate forecasts of water allocations over coming months, so that they can make key management decisions. To ensure that information is available for this purpose, governments will continue to work closely with industry associations and stakeholder groups. The Murray-Darling Basin Commission will continue to provide regular drought updates.</p>
<p>Work is continuing on contingency planning in order to protect critical human needs for 2009-10 should inflows remain at or below record minimums through winter. Governments would also need to consider how they would set aside water early to protect critical human needs for 2009-10. Governments have agreed to the following principles that will underpin the arrangements to meet critical water supplies in 2008-09. These principles are:</p>
<p>     * The special sharing arrangements agreed to by First Ministers on 5 February 2008 are still required for the 2008-09 water year and contingency planning needs to continue.</p>
<p>     * All Governments will be working co-operatively through the Senior Officials Group and implementing contingency planning for sharing water through this difficult time. The first priority for Governments in this very low water availability situation is to meet critical urban, stock and domestic water supplies for communities relying on water from the southern MDB.</p>
<p>     * In managing the impacts of dry conditions, water trading markets should be used to the maximum extent possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
