<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7710</transcript-id>
    <title>PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON HIS OVERSEAS VISIT TO EUROPE, THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM 17 AUGUST 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007710.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ON HIS OVERSEAS VISIT TO EUROPE,<br />
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA<br />
AND THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM<br />
17 AUGUST 1989<br />
Madam Speaker<br />
I seek leave to report to Parliament on the two overseas<br />
visits I undertook during the Parliamentary recess: to<br />
France, the United Kingdom, the United States, the Federal<br />
Republic of Germany and Hungary between 16 June and 3 July;<br />
and to the South Pacific Forum in Kiribati, between<br />
9 and 12 July.<br />
Both missions advanced Australia's interests and re-attested<br />
Australia's high international standing.<br />
0 The visit to the Unitee, States enabled me to renew a warm<br />
personal association with President Bush and to consolidate<br />
Australia's close contacts with the new Administration.<br />
My visit to Britain and West Germany re-affirmed our strong<br />
and significant association with both countries; and, in the<br />
case of Britain, furthered the common endeavour to place the<br />
historic and traditional relationship between our two<br />
countries firmly in the context of modern realities.<br />
My visit to France confirmed the transformation which has<br />
occurred in French-Australian relations since the change of<br />
Government in France last year. I should mention here,<br />
Madam Speaker, that the Prime Minister of France, Mr Rocard,<br />
will be our honoured guest in Canberra tomorrow.<br />
The visit to Hungary the first by an Australian Prime<br />
Minister took place at a time of profoundly significant<br />
change in that country and elsewhere in Eastern Europe.<br />
Throughout this mission, the focus was placed on the<br />
advancement of Australia's commercial and economic<br />
interests. The reasons for this, Madam Speaker, are plain.<br />
The United States, Britain, France and West Germany are all<br />
among Australia's 12 largest trading partners. Together<br />
they account for around 30 per cent of Australia's total<br />
two-way trade and nearly 50 per cent of the total stock of<br />
foreign investment in Australia. Most importantly, the<br />
visit took place at a time when the whole world trade<br />
community is coming to grips with the implications of Europe<br />
1992 the creation of a single market in Western Europe. </p>
<p>It was within this framework that I addressed major business<br />
and official gatherings in each of the countries I visited.<br />
It was for these reasons I was joined in Paris, Bonn and<br />
Budapest by a delegation of senior Australian business<br />
executives. In London, more than 100 representatives of<br />
Australian business attended the Trade and Investment<br />
Conference which met under the auspices of the British and<br />
Australian Governments. At all these meetings they were<br />
able to observe at first hand the dimensions of change<br />
taking place in Europe, with all the challenges and<br />
opportunities it offers Australian industry. I pay tribute<br />
to the contribution which the Australian business<br />
representatives made to the success of my visit.<br />
In Paris, London and Bonn I reiterated publicly and<br />
privately Australia's concern about the Common Agricultural<br />
Policy and protectionist practices covering other<br />
commodities, such as coal.<br />
In all these capitals I made it clear that, despite our<br />
concerns on specific matters, Australia wholeheartedly<br />
welcomed the growing unity of Europe, as a force for peace<br />
and progress in the world. Prime minister Rocard, Prime<br />
Minister Thatcher and Chancellor Kohl each stressed their<br />
government's commitment to making the single market a free<br />
and fair market place for all. Australia values these<br />
assurances.<br />
And, madam Speaker, I assure the House that Australia will<br />
be following developments very carefully, and staying in<br />
very close communication with EC member Governments and the<br />
European Commission, as we approach 1992 and beyond.<br />
In Washington, I re-affirmed Australia's strong desire that<br />
the United States should continue to play a leading role in<br />
achieving a successful outcome to the Uruguay Round,<br />
especially in respect of agricultural trade. While<br />
accepting that the American Export Enhancement Program was<br />
not intended to harm non-subsidised agricultural exporters<br />
-like Australia, I stressed that Australia had nevertheless<br />
found itself in the crossfire of an escalating subsidy war<br />
and that our grain exports, in particular, had been<br />
adversely affected as a consequence. I am pleased to<br />
report, Madam Speaker, that the United States Administration<br />
agreed to examine my suggestion to-seek a'linkage between<br />
the provisions of the 1990 Farm Bill and the outcome of the<br />
Uruguay Round. Such a linkage would help achieve our<br />
declared common objective of a more open international<br />
trading system.<br />
In Washington, I was also able to have useful discussions<br />
about Australia's regional economic initiative. As<br />
honourable members will know, the United States<br />
Administration endorsed this initiative. Specifically,<br />
Secretary of State Baker endorsed my proposal for greater<br />
regional economic consultation and co-operation as ' an idea<br />
whose time has come. The United States will be represented<br />
at the ministerial-level conference in Australia, planned<br />
for November. </p>
<p>My discussions at all levels underlined the fundamental and<br />
far-reaching changes underway in East-West relations.<br />
Nowhere was this more evident than in Hungary. The great<br />
significance of the changes in Hungary is that they are<br />
being shaped by the Hungarian leadership, in response to the<br />
clear wishes of the Hungarian people. This difficult,<br />
complex and, may I say, Madam Speaker, courageous course is<br />
based upon the recognition of the inescapable link between<br />
economic reform and political reform. President Bush, who<br />
was in Hungary two weeks after my own visit, stated publicly<br />
that he shared my view, as I had put it at the White House,<br />
that " the West must do everything we can to encourage the<br />
positive developments in Hungary".<br />
To give practical substance to our hopes, Australia has<br />
agreed to negotiate a Double Taxation Agreement with<br />
Hungary, to explore the possibility of an investment<br />
protection agreement and to seek ways of providing access<br />
for Hungary under the Australian System of Tariff<br />
Preferences. Madam Speaker<br />
on peace and disarmament questions, I can report that each<br />
of the countries I visited welcomed Australia's initiative<br />
in holding a Government-Industry conference on chemical<br />
weapons, to be held in Canberra next month. This conference<br />
will provide a unique opportunity to develop strategies for<br />
a comprehensive Chemical weapons Convention to prevent the<br />
spread of this hideous scourge.<br />
Madam Speaker<br />
Over the range of issues I discussed in each capital<br />
Southern Africa, the middle East, Afghanistan, Indo-China<br />
and the Pacific the tragic events in China and Lebanon<br />
loomed especially large. President Bush, Chancellor Kohl,<br />
President Mitterrand and Prime ministers Thatcher and Rocard<br />
all shared the Australian Government's feeling of obligation<br />
to express, as they have all done forcefully, condemnation<br />
of the brutal suppression of human rights which has occurred<br />
in China. Like myself, these Western leaders will be<br />
watching closely the fate of all those prominent in the<br />
pro-democracy movement; and also other Chinese leaders,<br />
particularly Secretary-General Zhao.<br />
All the leaders with whom I spoke are concerned about the<br />
continuing tragedy in Lebanon. This is a matter of special<br />
concern to Australia because of its impact on our Lebanese<br />
community. As I said in the Parliament on 15 August,<br />
Australia firmly and unequivocally supports the Arab League<br />
initiative aimed at bringing the main protagonists to the<br />
negotiating table. We stand ready to support any United<br />
Nations initiative on Lebanon and I am in continuing<br />
communication with President Bush and President Gorbachev on<br />
this tragedy. </p>
<p>we applaud current French diplomatic efforts on Lebanon and<br />
I look forward to detailed discussions on the situation<br />
there with Michel Rocard tomorrow.<br />
Madam Speaker<br />
Consistent with my Government's strong policy for the<br />
protection of the environment, it was appropriate for me on<br />
this journey to seek support for Australia's initiative for<br />
a comprehensive Environmental Protection Agreement covering<br />
the Antarctic, the world's last and greatest wilderness.<br />
This I did. I found ready support in Paris and a<br />
sympathetic understanding of Australia's position in both<br />
Bonn and Budapest. I regret to state that neither Britain<br />
nor the United States is yet ready to support the position<br />
on which I believe honourable members of this House stand<br />
together. But I am confident that growing community<br />
awareness and concern world-wide, will ensure that<br />
governments everywhere become more responsive to the need to<br />
address this question, and ultimately come together in a<br />
common resolve to protect this precious part of our<br />
endangered planet.<br />
In Paris, Prime Minister Rocard and I agreed to the<br />
formation of a Working Group to pursue environmental matters<br />
of common concern. The Working Group had its first meeting<br />
in Paris last week and I fully expect that Prime Minister<br />
Rocard and I will be able to announce further steps after<br />
our talks tomorrow.<br />
Madam Speaker<br />
I should now report to the House on the twentieth meeting of<br />
the South Pacific Forum which I attended at Tarawa, in the<br />
Republic of Kiribati, on 10 and 11 July. The Forum<br />
coincided with the Kiribati's celebration of its tenth<br />
anniversary of independence and I was honoured to represent<br />
Australia at this special anniversary.<br />
* Two matters of fundamental importance dominated the Forum<br />
the serious threat posed by drift net fishing in the<br />
Southern Pacific Ocean; and the implications for these<br />
island nations of the " greenhouse effect".<br />
It is no exaggeration to say, Madam Speaker, that for some<br />
of our neighbours and partners in the South Pacific these<br />
two issues represent, almost literally, matters of life and<br />
death. I now table the Communique adopted by the Forum and the<br />
Tarawa Declaration on Pelagic Drift Net Fishing.<br />
Madam Speaker<br />
The Tarawa Declaration set out the member nations' profound<br />
concern at the damage being done to the economy and the<br />
environment of the South Pacific region by this<br />
indiscriminate, irresponsible and destructive fishing<br />
technique. </p>
<p>Pelagic drift nets vary in length between 30 and<br />
kilometres I repeat 30 and 60 kilometres and reach a<br />
depth of some 15 metres. They have aptly been described as<br />
" walls of death". The threat they pose to Southern Pacific<br />
fish stocks and other marine species has been compounded by<br />
massive increases in the number of fishing vessels from<br />
Japan and Taiwan using drift nets. The scientific evidence<br />
available to us at the Forum indicates that the present<br />
indiscriminate use of drift nets threatens the very<br />
existence of the Southern Pacific tuna fishery, and<br />
therefore, the very livelihood of the people who depend so<br />
deeply upon its existence.<br />
The Tarawa Declaration seeks to ban pelagic drift net<br />
fishing from the region and calls for a meeting of regional<br />
experts to develop a convention to achieve this objective.<br />
This meeting will be hosted by New Zealand. The conclusion<br />
of a convention of this nature raises complex legal and<br />
related issues. To be effective on the high seas, it will<br />
require the support, or at least concurrence, of the major<br />
fishing nations. The gravity of the threat requires urgent<br />
action; and Australia readily accepts its responsibility to<br />
take a lead in advancing this important objective of the<br />
Forum. It was with that responsibility in mind that I had<br />
already raised this matter in the United States and Europe,<br />
as part of Australia's efforts eventually to secure a<br />
world-wide ban on this fishing technique.<br />
At the Tarawa Forum, members also expressed concern about<br />
the possible effects on island countries of rising sea<br />
levels resulting from global warming the " greenhouse<br />
effect". Forum members welcomed my re-affirmation of<br />
Australia's decision to fund a project to establish a<br />
network of regional monitoring stations. The information<br />
these stations will provide on trends and fluctuations in<br />
climate and sea levels will provide an accurate data base on<br />
climatic change within the region. This project will<br />
require a long-term commitment on our part, if it is to<br />
produce worthwhile data; and I was pleased to be able to<br />
offer such a commitment to Forum members.<br />
Other issues addressed at the 1989 Forum included the<br />
situation in New Caledonia, and administrative and program<br />
issues arising in the Forum Secretariat and regional bodies<br />
associated with the Forum. The Forum welcomed the positive<br />
measures being pursued by the French Government in New<br />
Caledonia to promote political, economic and social<br />
development in the territory, and urged all parties to<br />
continue to work towards the successful implementation of<br />
the agreements concluded in Paris in June and August 1988. </p>
<p>Madam Speaker<br />
It is particularly pleasing to note that, even with the<br />
growth in Forum membership and the growing complexity of its<br />
affairs over the past 20 years, we still meet in the words<br />
of the 1971 Communique " as neighbours and partners" with<br />
great informality and a great degree of consensus. I am<br />
confident the South Pacific Forum will acquire further<br />
standing and authority as the pre-eminent regional<br />
organisation in the years ahead. And I am equally confident<br />
the Forum will enhance its special indeed its unique<br />
character and significance as a gathering of neighbours and<br />
partners in the South Pacific. The new arrangement for a<br />
post-Forum dialogue between Forum members and important<br />
outside countries with interests in the region Canada,<br />
France, Japan, the United Kingdom and the United States<br />
which was initiated in Kiribati, will strengthen this<br />
development. Let me conclude, Madam Speaker, by saying that far beyond<br />
the South Pacific, andfar beyond our own great region,<br />
Australia's reputation as a good neighbour and a world<br />
partner in the cause of peace, progress and freedom has<br />
never stood higher. I am convinced that this cause<br />
despite all the tragedies, perplexities and complexities<br />
besetting our age, can now enter a more hopeful period than<br />
any we have experienced since the Second World War. These<br />
visits which I have been privileged to undertake on behalf<br />
of the Australian people have re-inforced that fundamental<br />
conviction. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
