<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1105</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP, ON VIETNAM - MINISTERIAL STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/04/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001105.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH By<br />
* The Rt. Hon. SIR ROBERT MENZIES,<br />
M. P.,<br />
ON<br />
VIETNAM<br />
MINISTERIAL STATEMENT<br />
[ From the " Parliamentary Debates," 29uth A pril' 19651<br />
Sir ROBERTI MENZIES ( Kooyong-<br />
Prime Minister).-by leave-The House in<br />
recent weeks has conducted an important<br />
debate on foreign affairs in which the situation<br />
in Vietnam was fully and anxiously discussed.<br />
My colleague, the Minister for<br />
* External Affairs ( Mr. Hasluck) devoted a<br />
large part of his statement to Vietnam, explaining<br />
developments there and the critical<br />
significance of those developments for South<br />
and South East Asia as a whole. Nor of<br />
course do the implications end with South<br />
and South East Asia. Whether an externally<br />
directed Communist guerrilla subversion is<br />
to succeed or fail has world wide consequence.<br />
It has particular consequence for<br />
Australia. In the first half of 1962 the Government<br />
decided, following Upon a request from the<br />
Government Of South Vietnam, that AuIstralia<br />
should contribute militarily to the<br />
defence of South Vietnamn. We sent at that<br />
time a group of some 30 military instructors<br />
to provide military training assistance. Since<br />
then additional military aid has been provided.<br />
The strength of the Army training<br />
team was, in the first place, doubled, and<br />
later still-comparatively recently-increased<br />
to 100. A flight of six CaribouI<br />
transport aircraft has been provided. We<br />
have progressively increased our programme<br />
of economic aid to South Vietnam<br />
5040/ 65. so that it now runs at the rate of about<br />
fLI million a year. A devoted body of ALIStralian<br />
experts is at present at work in different<br />
parts of South Vietnam, experts in<br />
agriculture and the like. In addition to Australia<br />
and the United States, some thirty<br />
other countries are providing assistance or<br />
have undertaken to do so in the military<br />
or non-military aid fields. This includes<br />
assistance from a significant and important<br />
group of Asian countries, including the<br />
Philippines, Malaysia, Japan, Thailand, and<br />
the Republic of Korea, who are contrihuting<br />
either economic or military aid.<br />
The Australian Government is now ill<br />
receipt of a request from the Government<br />
of' South Vietnam for further military assistance.<br />
We have decided-and this has been<br />
after close consultation with the Government<br />
of the United States-to provide an<br />
infantry battalion for service in South Vietnarn.<br />
In case there is any misunderstanding,<br />
I think I should say, Sir, that we decided<br />
in principle somic time ago-weeks and<br />
weeks ago-that We would be willing to<br />
do this if we received the necessary request<br />
from the Government of South Vietnam<br />
and the necessary collaboration with the<br />
United States. This is not to he regarded as<br />
something that has suddenly arisen Outt of<br />
more recent events. </p>
<p>There can be no doubt of the gravity<br />
of the situation in South Vietnam. There<br />
is ample evidence to show that with the<br />
support of the North Vietnamese regime<br />
and other Communist powers, the Vietcong<br />
has been preparing on a more substantial<br />
scale than hitherto insurgency action<br />
designed to destroy South Vietnamese<br />
Government control, and to disrupt by<br />
violence the life of the local people. The<br />
rate of infiltration of guerrillas from North<br />
Vietnam has been increasing and last year<br />
rose to some 10,000. The infiltration of a<br />
battalion of the North Vietnamese regular<br />
Army has recently been confirmed.<br />
We have not of course come to this<br />
decision without the closest attention to the<br />
question of defence priorities. We do not<br />
and must not overlook the point that our<br />
alliances, as well as providing guarantees<br />
and assurances for our security, make demands<br />
upon us. We have commitments to<br />
Malaysia which we are meeting. We have to<br />
bear in mind, and make preparations against,<br />
the possibility of other developments in the<br />
region which could make demands on our<br />
Australian defence capacity.<br />
Assessing all this, it is our judgment that<br />
the decision to commit a battalion in South<br />
Vietnam represents the most useful additional<br />
contribution which we can make to<br />
the defence of the region at this time. The<br />
takeover of South Vietnam would be a direct<br />
military threat to Australia and all the<br />
countries of South and South East Asia. It<br />
must be seen as part of a thrust by Communist<br />
China between the Indian and Pacific<br />
Oceans. The task of holding the situation in<br />
South Vietnam and restraining the North<br />
Vietnamese is formidable. But we are conscious<br />
of the magnitude of the effort being<br />
made by the Government and people of<br />
South Vietnam in their own defence. In<br />
recent months the United States has taken<br />
historic decisions to extend further military<br />
assistance to South Vietnam. South Korea<br />
has also committed substantial forces.<br />
We have noted and welcomed the attempts<br />
to open the way to agreement which<br />
have been made, so far unsuccessfully, by<br />
President Johnson and by the Prime Minister<br />
of Britain through his representative, Mr.<br />
Gordon Walker. We also welcome President<br />
Johnson's proposals for a wide-ranging<br />
economic programme. We will certainly continue<br />
to play our part in the economic<br />
development of the region. I make it clear that the Government has<br />
no desire to have Australian forces in Vietnam<br />
any longer than is necessary to ensure<br />
the security of South Vietnam. In terms,<br />
that is practically what President Johnson<br />
said quite recently about the presence of<br />
American forces in Vietnam. We and our<br />
allies are not seeking to take over North*<br />
Vietnam. The North Vietnamese must not<br />
take over South Vietnam by armed force<br />
or subversion.<br />
Let me add one item to my statement.<br />
Arguments have been going on for sonimc<br />
time, publicly and privately, about this<br />
matter. Some attempt has been made<br />
occasionally-I do not think in this House<br />
-to suggest that we are in some way at<br />
odds with the United States on this question.<br />
Therefore, I am happy to tell the House<br />
that today I received from the President<br />
of the United States of America a message<br />
which I have his full authority to make<br />
public. Mr. Jamnes.-Oh!<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIFS.-Yes, I am<br />
like that. 1 never publish a message without<br />
having full authority to make it public.<br />
Therefore, the honorable gentleman may<br />
he interested to hear it. I do not assume for<br />
a moment that he will like it, but I think<br />
he ought to hear it. It is in these terms-Am<br />
Dear Mr. Prime Minister: I amn delighted at<br />
the decision of your Government to provide : I<br />
infantry battalion for service in South Vietnam<br />
at the request of the Government of South<br />
Vietnam. This action simply underscores the full co-opcration<br />
and understanding that has existed between<br />
our two Governments, and between both and the<br />
Government of South Vietnam, in assisting South<br />
Vietnam to maintain its independence. Like you,<br />
we have no desire to maintain military forces in<br />
Vietnam any longer than necessary to ensure the<br />
security of South Vietnam. But we share your<br />
belief that we must both respond to the needs<br />
brought about by the aggression being carried on<br />
from North Vietnam.<br />
More broadly, this action proves again the<br />
deep ties between our two countries in the cause<br />
of world peace and security. As you know, my<br />
personal experiences in association with Australians<br />
during World War II have made this<br />
a particularly deep and abiding feeling for me.<br />
I am confident that our two nations, working<br />
together, can continue to make great contributions<br />
to checking the spread of aggression and to<br />
bringing about the peace that South Vietnam and<br />
South-East Asia deserve. Sincerely yours,<br />
Lyndon B. Johnson. w<br />
BY AUTHORITY: ARTHIIUR, COMMONWAI. T11 C( OVERNMENT PRINTER. CANBERRA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
