<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20906</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Parliament House  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/09/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
   9 September 2003</p>
<p>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</p>
<p>Subjects: international visits; proliferation security initiative; Mr John Anderson;   Indonesian President.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE…………………………………………………………………………………….</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>….Chinese President has accepted your invitation to visit?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I am. I';m delighted that sometime in the next little time we';ll have in Australia in fairly close proximity not only the President of the United States but also the President of China. It symbolises the diversity of Australia';s relationships. It demonstrates that the closeness of our relationship with the United States in no way inhibits our close relationship with countries in Asia, in this case China. We are unapologetic about our relationship with the United States and the world knows that, but it doesn';t alter the fact that we have a very close relationship with China and that is to our benefit and it';s something that I';ve worked very hard to bring about.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Chinese officials have been briefed by a senior DFAT official about the proliferation security initiative.  What feedback have you got about whether…any concerns they have about that, if they';re modified, and how they feel about the exercise this weekend?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I haven';t had any feedback about that. I wouldn';t imagine that there would be any difficulty because it';s not something that should be of any concern or worry to the Chinese. There';s nothing in it that';s antagonistic to China';s interests. But we talk openly and frankly about these things.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] John Anderson staying on as well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I';m delighted that John';s staying on. I have said before that he';s the most intrinsically decent person I';ve met in public life. I enjoy a very close relationship with him. I trust him. He';s done great things for rural Australia. He';s worked very hard to get the water agreement up. There';s a lot of work ahead in implementing it and also further rail reform is necessary and he really is the one person around who can drive that through to finality.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It';s the second anniversary of September 11 this week.  Any thoughts [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I expect to be saying something about that on the actual anniversary itself.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] decision Prime Minister, does that give you more flexibility, more stability going into an election year now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The Government has been very stable for seven-and-a-half years. It';s been one of our hallmarks. Obviously John staying is a boost because he';s very experienced. That';s no disrespect to Mark Vaile, he';s very experienced too. But John';s a relatively young bloke and he';s very experienced and he';s done a lot of good things and I';m very happy and indeed that he';s staying.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does it give you more flexibility though when it comes to making a decision on when to go?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>On what?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>When to go to an election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh dear oh me. Dear oh dear oh me.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you disappointed the Indonesian President won';t have time to meet with you next month when you get to Bali?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I understand why. I';ve known for some time that President Megawati because of other commitments wouldn';t be able to come to Bali. I understand that one of her very senior ministers will representing her at the service. I';ve known about this for some time. I will see her in Thailand at the APEC meeting, what, ten or eleven days later. This is no surprise to me, it';s no disappointment to me.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How important is the exercise being conducted this weekend?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think all of those exercises are important and they';re useful.  As for the details of it you better talk to the ministerial expert Senator Hill.  Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
