<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22133</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian National Council on Drugs Appointment of the Hon Dr John Herron as Chairman </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>It is my great pleasure to announce the appointment of The Hon Dr John Herron as Chairman of the Australian National Council on Drugs (ANCD).</p>
<p>  The ANCD is the Australian Government's principal advisory body on illicit drugs policy.  It has played an important role in the development and implementation of effective strategies to address illicit drug use in our communities.  Dr Herron brings a wide range of relevant experience and the right mix of skills to the role of Chairman of the ANCD following the retirement of the inaugural chairman Major Brian Watters.</p>
<p>  Dr Herron has had a distinguished career in the medical profession and public life, most recently as the Australian Ambassador to Ireland and the Holy See and has a proven track record of delivering outcomes for the benefit of the wider community.  He is a Fellow of the Royal Australasian College of Surgeons and the Australian Medical Association, and has served as a Senator for Queensland and as the Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs.</p>
<p>  Dr Herron has also made a significant contribution to the Australian community including as President of the Bennelong Society, a group devoted to the improvement of the welfare of Aboriginal people; Patron of the Queensland Council of Family Associations; a Board Member of the National Seniors Foundation; and a Foundation Member of the Down Syndrome Association of Queensland.  He has worked as a volunteer doctor for CARE Australia in a Rwandan refugee camp.  This vast range of experience will serve Dr Herron well in tackling drug use in our communities.</p>
<p>  Since 1997, the Government has provided over $1 billion under the Tough on Drugs Strategy to tackle the problems of drug and alcohol abuse.  As I said on the retirement of Major Watters, there is no doubt that many Australian lives have been saved and their families and friends spared the trauma of drug addiction as a result of the contribution of  the ANCD.  While we have had many successes, the problems of drug and alcohol abuse are not easily solved and governments, businesses and the community need to retain their commitment in the fight against drugs.</p>
<p> The role of Chairman of the Australian National Council on Drugs is an honorary position.</p>
<p>I look forward to working with Dr Herron in addressing the many complex and challenging issues in our fight against drugs.  It is a fight that must be won.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
