<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19197</transcript-id>
    <title>Proposed Appointment of Departmental Secretary</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>I am pleased to announce that I will be recommending to the Governor-General, Her Excellency Ms Quentin Bryce AC CVO, that she appoint Mr Simon Lewis PSM as the Secretary to the Department of Veterans' Affairs.</p>
<p>Mr Lewis' appointment will follow the retirement in July of the present Secretary, Mr Ian Campbell PSM. </p>
<p>Mr Campbell had previously advised that he would not be seeking further appointment after his current term as Secretary expired in September this year. </p>
<p>Mr Campbell will now be taking a period of leave from early May 2013 for surgery and subsequent recovery and has decided to retire as Secretary from July so as to avoid any disruption in the leadership of the Department.   </p>
<p>Mr Lewis will act as Secretary while Mr Campbell is on leave for medical reasons. </p>
<p>Mr Lewis is currently an Associate Secretary and Chief Operating Officer in the Department of Defence. Prior to joining Defence, Mr Lewis had an extensive and lengthy public service career in the Department of Finance and Deregulation where he was responsible for asset management (including Comcover), government advertising and procurement policy. </p>
<p>Mr Lewis has tertiary qualifications in economics, public administration and computing studies and is a graduate of the Joint Services Staff College.   </p>
<p>The Governor-General will consider the recommended appointment under amendments to the Public Service Act 1999 which commence on 1 July 2013. The appointment would be for five years.</p>
<p>I take this opportunity to acknowledge the outstanding service provided by Mr Campbell over his career in the Australian Public Service and wish him well in his retirement. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
