<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8821</transcript-id>
    <title>GST AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT - TRUST ME, SAYS HEWSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008821.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STTI T BY T= PRIME MINISTER, THE iON P. J. KFATING, MP<br />
GST AND LOCAL GOVEIENT TRUST ME, SAYS tMWON<br />
Dr He mwon's own teaam has been caught out again telling the<br />
truth about the GST.<br />
In the process they have reminded people of just how far<br />
this tax will reach into people's daily lives.<br />
Opposition frontbencher Ian McDonald says the GST will now<br />
apply to the water and sewerage services on your rates bill.<br />
lie's also conceded that other council services such as<br />
transport and garbage collection could be taxed.<br />
But Senotor McDonald says the public will have to wait until<br />
after March 13 before decisions are made about how the GST<br />
will affect council rates.<br />
He says the GST Is too complicated and the details will have<br />
to he worked out later.<br />
This is confirmed by another Coalition spokesman, Geoff<br />
Prosser, who said on Perth radio on Tuesday:<br />
" I think that in this whole program we have put forward<br />
we have generally set the guidelines down and we need<br />
to sort of sit down with councils and go through these<br />
Gorts of things.<br />
This can mean only that the Coalltion Is incapable of<br />
telling people how the GST will work, or they won't tell<br />
people how it will work.<br />
Dr Hewson knows the GST will hit people in almost every<br />
aspect of their lives but he won't say so.<br />
If the GST Is so good for people, if it really is going to<br />
create jobs " from day one" why is Dr Hewson saying, " Trust<br />
me, I'll give you the details after the election.'<br />
John Hewson is sounding more and more like Jeff Kennett.<br />
With Dr Hewson it's a case of vote now pay later.<br />
MELBOURNE February 19 1993<br />
54 4 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
