<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9063</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP QUEENSLANDS NATIVE TITLE BILL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009063.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 138/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
QUEENSLAND'S NATIVE TITLE BILL<br />
I congratulate Premier Goss for the Native Title ( Queensland)<br />
Bill introduced into the Queensland Parliament today.<br />
The Queensland Bill will operate in conjunction with the<br />
Commonwealth Native Title Bill.<br />
As the Premier of Queensland correctly said " the choice for<br />
the States is clear. It is a choice between accepting the<br />
High Court decision and participating in a national<br />
legislative response on the one hand, or, alternatively taking<br />
the path of legal uncertainty and confusion".<br />
Queensland has decisively chosen the former course, and this<br />
decision will benefit all Queenslanders Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander people and others.<br />
In stark contrast, Western Australia alone among the States<br />
has tragically chosen the course of legal uncertainty and<br />
confusion. The ill-concieved and discriminatory Western Australian<br />
legislation was guillotined through the upper House last<br />
night. As of today, Aboriginal people face the prospect that<br />
native title has been extinguished across the entire State.<br />
The only thing standing in the way of this extinguishment of<br />
the legal rights of West Australians is the Commnonwealth<br />
Native Title legislation.<br />
I again urge the passage of the Bill by the Senate.<br />
Queensland is a case study in how States and Territories can<br />
work effectively with the Commonwealth legislation. It is<br />
proof that cooperation can work.<br />
The cause of justice, and sound and certain management of land<br />
across Australia, will be served by passage of the<br />
Commonwealth Bill and by other States and Territories<br />
following the Queensland example.<br />
CANBERRA 2 December 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
