<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4372</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER - 20 APRIL 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004372.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER 20 April 1977<br />
Mr. Speaker, I seek leave of the House to make a statement regarding<br />
the Heads of Government Agreement for a three month price and wage<br />
halt<br />
At the Premiers Conference on 13 April, the seven Heads of<br />
Government agreed that they should unite to hasten the success<br />
of the fight against inflation and unemployment.<br />
The agreement to which all seven Heads of Government appended<br />
their signatures was directed to breaking the price-wage cycle.<br />
None of us imagined that this was more than a supplement to<br />
other action we would need to continue to take, such as through<br />
our budgets and through monetary policy, collectively and<br />
individually, to deal with our national economic problem: s.<br />
We knew that implementation of this proposal would not ' be a simple<br />
matter. We believed that given the existence of a national willingness and<br />
the collective will and backing of the seven governments,<br />
the incomesvprices halt offered a chance to resolve<br />
Australia's economic problems more rapidly.<br />
There was an agreement that went beyond political divisions.<br />
Let me read the quite brief text of the agreement to you:<br />
Its message is clear: " Prices and incomes restraint. The<br />
Heads of the Commonwealth and all State Governments, meeting in<br />
Premciers Conference in Canberra today, unanimously called for<br />
a three month halt in price and wage increases.<br />
They agreed that such restraint was urgently needed if Axustralia<br />
is to overcome its current economic problems.<br />
It w~ as agreed that all Heads of Governments will approach<br />
employer and professional organisations and put to them the<br />
proposal that their membership should voluntarily commit themselves<br />
to a pause for a period three months from increases in the prices<br />
of their goods and services.<br />
At the same time, all Heads of Governments will be making an<br />
approach to the A. C. T. U. and other employee organisations to<br />
seek~ a voluntary commitment to a three months pause from wage<br />
increases. Governments would not expect either the business organisations<br />
or the union organisations to agree to such voluntary restraint<br />
agrEements without agreement by the others.<br />
Immediately following agreement to the proposal for a voluntary<br />
general pause from increases in prices and incomes approaches<br />
would be made to the Arbitration Commission and the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunal for the implementation of the general pause. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Goverments would also use their influence and the powers available<br />
to them towards achieving a successful outcome. Governments<br />
will commit themselves to not increasing their own charges during<br />
the period of the pause.<br />
Local Government will be expected to do likewise.<br />
All Heads of Government commit themselves to work for this voluntary<br />
pause. Upon its achievement a further conference of Heads of Government<br />
will be held to consider what further steps should be taken.<br />
The Heads of Government called on all members of the Australian<br />
Community to give full support to this vital endeavour to help<br />
overcome inflation".<br />
The Statement was signed by myself and all six Premiers.<br />
The Statement was agreed to after the possibility of a national<br />
conference was canvassed and rejected as unnecessary and impractical.<br />
All Heads of Government agreed on the principle of a wage/ price<br />
pause and were willing to use existing institutional machinery<br />
for carrying it into effect. Given these cond-itions<br />
there was little that a national conference could add.<br />
We also saw that a national conference could mean delay, posturing,<br />
rhetoric, recriminations, and very likely, no constructive outcome<br />
whatsoever. In thr! discussion at the Premiers Conference nobody raised the<br />
quesIC. Lon of tax cuts.<br />
We also saw overwhelming problems because of constitutional and<br />
administrative considerations in attempting to impose<br />
mandatory controls.<br />
The Heads of Government agreement reached beyond partisan politics<br />
to the nation's interest.<br />
Such,. &amp; n Agreement between the Heads of Government, despite<br />
different party alliances, was remarkable in the best sense of the word.<br />
The Agreement of Heads of Government reflected a unanimous<br />
bipartisan convictionof the need to defeat inflation.<br />
The overwhelming majority of Australians, irrespective of party<br />
loyalty or sectional interest, desire an enduring solution to the<br />
problem of inflation.<br />
The Heads of Government iranslated this national aspiration into<br />
political agreement. The next task was to convert it into practical<br />
reality. </p>
<p>Heads of Government clearly understood that if the proposal was to<br />
have a reasonable Prospect of success it was not sufficient mnerely<br />
to accetpt its desirability, but to pursue it with unity and<br />
enthusiasm. There was every reason to believe that all the State Governments<br />
did enter into the Agreement with the intent of making it work.<br />
This in turn crea-ted the conditions for the widespread community<br />
acceptabnce of the desirability and equity of a wage/ price pause.<br />
After the initial agreement by the seven governments, there were<br />
inevitz. bly many detailed matters which needed attention.<br />
TogethEr with the States, we moved rapidly to attend to these<br />
questions, and within a day the machinery was set up with the<br />
States for close coordination.<br />
For our part, we sought immediately to implement the agreement.<br />
We sent. messages to over 200 major national employer employee<br />
professional and community groups.<br />
We inserted advertisements in newspapers on 16th April in all State<br />
capitals seeking support for the Heads of Government Agreement.<br />
The Minister far Business and Consumer Affairs wrote to the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunal asking the Tribunal to defer decisions on<br />
price rises and to monitor and investigate any claims that price<br />
rises had occurred.<br />
We also obtained agreement from some companies which had been<br />
granted price increases to defer implementation of such rises<br />
and agreement from companies which had applied for increases to<br />
defer their applications.<br />
All Comm~ onwealth Ministers and Departments were informed that there<br />
would b2 no increases in commonwealth charges or fees. On<br />
April, I and three other Ministers met with representatives of<br />
natinal employer organisations. They indicated their willingness<br />
to supprt the initiatives of the seven Governments.<br />
This was a most encouraging response and a telex was sent -to the<br />
Premiers providing details of the organisation.<br />
Preparations were made to implement the Agreement. On 17 April<br />
it was announced that a special committee comprising representatives<br />
of empl-yers, employees, and the P. J. T. would be constituted to<br />
advise on the implementation of the Heads of Government Agreement<br />
including the question of whether amendments to the Prices Justification<br />
Act wouLd be appropriate to support the agreement.<br />
Peak Coancils were invited to meet today with myself and other<br />
Commonwealth Ministers.<br />
At the same time, we had received : eports that the State Premiers<br />
were co-isulting with employers and employees and taking other<br />
measures to encourage compliance by all sections of the community<br />
with the wage/ price halt. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
It was clear that the public reaction to the plan was one of<br />
overwhelming approval.<br />
We were encouraged by a private survey which indicated that<br />
the vast majority of Australians including the great majority<br />
of trade unionists supported the concept of a simultaneous<br />
freeze in prices and incomes.<br />
And one of the critical preconditions for the plans success employer<br />
support for a prices-incomes freeze was evident.<br />
Yesterday, the Arbitration Commission called a special hearing to<br />
discuss the call of the seven Heads of Government.<br />
Acting in the spirit of the Joint Agreement the Commonwealth took<br />
the unprecedented step of seeking the views of the States on a<br />
draft of the submission to be put at the hearing.<br />
It was at this stage that we became aware of indications that<br />
the three Labor Party State Governments were having second thoughts<br />
about the Agreement to which their Premiers had appended their<br />
signatures.<br />
There were public announcements of their disagreement with the<br />
text of the draft submission to be put by the Commonwealth to the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission.<br />
Because we saw the Agreement being of such great importance to<br />
Australia, we amended our submission to take into account the<br />
views expressed by the three State Labor Premiers.<br />
We hoped that by so doing, all State Premiers would continue to<br />
honour the Agreement they had signed.<br />
Here was the opportunity for Mr. Hawke to show that he and other<br />
union leaderswould put the nation' s interest, and the interest<br />
of his own constituen~ ts first and agree that a three month halt<br />
in wages would be matched by a three month halt in prices.<br />
Instead Mr. Hawke made the most blatantly political speech he has<br />
ever made before the Commission.<br />
He refused to support the Heads of Agreement made by all the<br />
Governments of Australia.<br />
He tried to suggest that it was entirely a federal Government initiative<br />
He described the Heads of Government Agreement as a " concoction<br />
foisted by an Australian Government".<br />
of course this was not so. To repeat, the Scheme was agreed to by<br />
all the Heads of Government as a Joint cooperation Community programme. </p>
<p>Plainly, what Mr. Hawke is about is to break the scheme.<br />
To make the fight against inflation that much harder in the hope that<br />
it wilL. embarrass the Federal Government.<br />
He is prepared deliberately to make it harder for people t~ o get<br />
jobs, harder for firms to earn profits and expand, all in the cause<br />
of try:-. ng to gain sorte short-term political advantage.<br />
Instead of speaking to the central issue of a price/ wage pause,<br />
Mr. Hawke put to the Arbitration Commission four other proposals:<br />
1. F1irstly amendments to the Prices Justification Act.<br />
The Government has already agreed to appoint a joint committee<br />
to look at this if employees accept the principle of: a price/<br />
wage halt.<br />
2. Deferment of an application for an increase in real wages,<br />
based upon past productivity increases.<br />
This was an application which had little relevance in<br />
the next three months.<br />
3. "' he convening of a national conference to discuss a] ll<br />
economic policies, to discuss the " whole question of the future<br />
course of the Australian economy".<br />
He wanted an ongoing opportunity " to work out what E! conomic<br />
policies in general and pricing policies in particul. ar"<br />
should be adopted.<br />
.' he convening of a national conference was rejected at the<br />
Premiers Conference, and,<br />
4. A cut in direct taxes sufficient and I quote him, to<br />
" produce a real after-tax level of disposable income!,<br />
equivalent to what would be necessary by way of monely wage<br />
: Lncreases to compensate for the March quarter C. P. I..<br />
iiovement".<br />
I will comment directly on this proposal in a moment.<br />
Sadly, and incredibly, the three State Labor Governments chose to<br />
depart from the Heads of Government Agreement to which they<br />
were parties and support Mr. Hawke's propositions.<br />
In return for the four concessions which Mr. Hawke demandedconcessions<br />
which fell outside the terms of the Heads of Government<br />
Agreement what did Mr. Hawke offer?<br />
Did he offer compliance by the A. C. T. U. with a three month halt in<br />
income : 3Z<br />
No his sole magnanimous offer was "' to convene a special Federal<br />
unions conference to consider the foregoing of the March quarter<br />
application. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
He went on to qualify even this offer,, he said " I am not saying<br />
that we can deliver the goods, I make no false promises about that".<br />
Honourable Members can judge for themselves the worth of Mr. Hawke's<br />
proposals.<br />
He absolutely refused to accept that in return for a halt in prices<br />
the Unions could voluntarily agree to a three month pause in wage<br />
increases. Instead he put forward proposals outside the Agreement.<br />
One of these was tax cuts.<br />
Mr. Hawke's notion that it is possible to substitute tax reductions<br />
for wage increases while being economically responsible is blatant<br />
nonsense. Let me give a few simple examples.<br />
3, The cost of reducing by 5 percentage points the 27 per cent tax rate,<br />
applying to incomes between $ 2260 to $ 5650 would be*$ 840 million.<br />
The benefit to most taxpayers would only be $ 3.27 a week.<br />
Honourable members may compare this with. the $ 5.70 a week increase<br />
recently granted by the Commission with which the A. C. T. U. has<br />
expressed strong dissatisfaction.<br />
2. For the critical 35 percent tax rate area covering incomes between<br />
$ 5650 and $ 11,300 a 5% reduction would cost $ 740M<br />
This would provide the following benefits to taxpayers.<br />
A taxpayer on $ 5650 or less would receive no I repeat no benefit.<br />
A taxpayer on $ 6000 a year would receive the magnificent benefit<br />
of 34 cents a week.<br />
A taxpayer on $ 80 00 a year would receive $ 2.60 a week benefit and<br />
a taxpayer on $ 10,000 a year0 which is about the level of average<br />
earnings, would receive a benefit ofl$ 4. l8 a week.<br />
If Mr. Hawke had done some very simple arithmetic, he would have<br />
discovered the absurdity of this sort of wage/ tax proposition.<br />
It would have taken these two proposals together to come anywhere.<br />
near offsetting the-last wage increase.<br />
That is a cost to the Government's budget of over $ 1600 million to<br />
compensate for just one single quarter. Clearly to implement literally<br />
Mr. Hawke's proposal, tax:. revenues would be slashed to anc-extent<br />
this country could not stand..<br />
ivis proposal is not in any sense a viable alternative to the evenhanded<br />
initiative to break the price-wage spiral embodied in the Heads<br />
of Government Agreement. </p>
<p>-7<br />
There was, of course, no suggestion from Mr. Hawke as to how the tax<br />
cuts a~ ere to be financed. He did not mention whether additional<br />
expenditure cuts should be made to avoid the inflationary effects<br />
of additional recourse to the printing press.<br />
The t. iree Labor Premiers who he forced into line have not indicated<br />
whether they are prepared to contribute to the tax cuts bV accepting<br />
pro-r. ata reductions in their financial assistance grants., We should<br />
certainly welcome any meaningful offers from them in this direction.<br />
It should be said that Mr. Hawke has not been alone in attempting<br />
to undermine the Heads of Government Agreement.<br />
With -: he honourable exception of the Leader of the Opposition, many<br />
Membercs opposite have attacked the Agreement. The Deputy, Leader<br />
of the opposition has said that the plan should be " abandoned".<br />
The Honourable Member for Oxley has attacked the plan devised by<br />
this Government and all six State Premiers as a " flimsy political<br />
gimmick". The Honourable Member for Adelaide, even though he poses<br />
as the Shadow Treasurer, refuses to give his support to the plan.<br />
He said yesterday he is cynical. I think he describes himself<br />
correctly, and he pays himself no tribute.<br />
The Opposition in this House, with the notable exception of the<br />
Leader of the Opposition, has taken every opportunity to attack<br />
and criticise the plan to which three of their colleagues; are<br />
partiE! s.<br />
They have missed every opportunity to give the plan the wholehearted<br />
support which the occasion clearly demanded.<br />
Mr. Speaker, the Government in its determination to make the price/<br />
wage halt work if at all possible, today met with peak Union Councils.<br />
We sought from the representatives of the peak Councils support<br />
in principle, for the objectives set out in the Heads of Government<br />
Agreement that they would accept the principle of a voluntary pause<br />
in waces corresponding to the voluntary pause in prices which is<br />
alreaf~ y substantially in effect.<br />
Mr. Ha. wke persistently evaded the questions I put to him. He recited<br />
a list. of difficulties he foresaw in resp-ect of prices. He refused<br />
to discuss a pause in wage increases.<br />
Mr. Hawke insisted that what was needed was a national conference sucl<br />
as had been rejected in principle by all Heads of Government at the<br />
Premiers' Conference no doubt to provide him with a forum for<br />
another of his gra -t-, 2itous and increasingly boring attempts to usurp<br />
the functions of Government.<br />
He specifically asked me to seek the views of the Premiers on his<br />
proposal for a national conference.<br />
In a final effort to try to prevent a complete breakdown of the Heads<br />
of Government initiative, I said that my Government would be prepared<br />
to approach the State Governments on the question of a national<br />
conference if we could obtain from the peak Councils support in<br />
principle to the objectives of the Heads of Government Agreement. </p>
<p>On being told that Mr. Hawke and the other representatives present<br />
could not commit their organisations, I indicated that I was<br />
prepared to acceptL a personal commitment from them. Mr. Hawke<br />
was not even prepared to do this.<br />
Since there was no willingness to give even an expression of<br />
support, there was no point in any national conference. The Unions<br />
had made it quilte clear they would not make any commitment even<br />
in the vaguest terms to the objectives of the Heads of Government<br />
Agreement. In thelight of this negative attitude of the Unions, the Commonwealth<br />
has made a further approach to the Premiers in an attempt to achieve<br />
the wages/ prices halt.<br />
We are proposing that an application be made to the. Arbitration<br />
Commission to take action on the wages front, action which would<br />
be consistent with the prices halt the Arbitration Commission has<br />
already recognised.<br />
We would hope that all businesses and other price setters will hold<br />
prices until the results of this approach is known.<br />
While the Commonwealth hopes that all Premiers will agree with this<br />
approach -, band w * e know that some Premiers will agre-e the<br />
Commonwealth has determined to take this course.<br />
Some may ask how can such an agreement be effective in view of<br />
Mr. Hawke's refusal to support the concept of a wage price freeze<br />
and in view of his publicly expressed view in 1973 that a wage/ price<br />
freeze will never be acceptable to the union movement.<br />
The answer is simple. We believe that on this issue Mr. Hawke<br />
and his colleagues are out of sympathy with the overwhelming<br />
majority of trade unionists.<br />
We believe that a decision of the Arbitration Commission which is<br />
seen to be emminently fair because a price freeze is in operation<br />
will receive the great weight of support of Australian employees. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
