<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8412</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,  THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP MR HAWKES RETIREMENT FROM PARLIAMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008412.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 17/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
MR HAWKE'S RETIREMENT FROM PARLIAMENT<br />
Mr Hawke's retirement from Federal Parliament today marks<br />
the end of an unparalleled period of success and achievement<br />
for an Australian labour leader.<br />
Moreover, it marks the end of a political career devoted to<br />
uniting Australians for the common good.<br />
Only Sir Robert Menzies served longer as Prime Minister, yet<br />
history will judge the Hawke era as contributing much more<br />
to Australia.<br />
Bob Hawke led this country during a period of historic<br />
change, a period of awakening in which Australians chose to<br />
join the world as a modern, diversified economy.<br />
This change was profound and difficult but the price of not<br />
making it would have been to deny Australia a future.<br />
Bob Hawke and I served as a team for eight years. It was a<br />
privilege to serve with him. We shared beliefs and goals and<br />
worked together to achieve to them.<br />
It is clear that the past year has been a difficult one for<br />
both of us but that does not diminish the camaraderie we<br />
shared nor the pride in our achievements together.<br />
I wish Bob and Hazel well. All of us in the Labor Party, and<br />
all Australians, owe them a debt of gratitude.<br />
CANBERRA February 20 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
