<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4349</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE HERITAGE INDUSTRIES VOCATIONAL REHABILITATION CENTRE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004349.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
U SA<br />
FOR PRESS 18 MARCH 1.977<br />
OPEN] Nx ; OF TE! K RI TAGri I NDUSTIRIES VOCAT] ONAL RElIA13ILITATTON CENTRE<br />
This is an occasion which represents the culmination of an<br />
i mporant cFort by the people of this community to provide<br />
moun ngful assistance to the handicapped members of our society.<br />
1 am particularly pleased that support for the centre has atso<br />
come from Western ' Victori a, and from my own electorate.<br />
This is very fitting because it reciprocates the assistance the<br />
peop of Mt Gambier gave us when we were setting up the<br />
sheltered worksh. ip in Hamilton. The people who were involved with<br />
the Ilamilton workship, including Tamie, visi ted Mt. Gambier and<br />
got some invluable advice on how to go about things.<br />
This centre will make a major contribution to the lives of<br />
the 120 handicapped persons it is designed to employ.<br />
My Governmtent is firmly committed to equality oF opportunity for<br />
all Austral ans. And we wholeheartedly support programmes<br />
striving to enhance the security, dciganity, self rel: iance and<br />
veoll being of the handicapped. She ltered workshops emal: n<br />
essential contribution to those ends, giving handicapped peopi<br />
the sense of purpose, and usefulness that is fundamental to<br />
personal dignity, and self-esteem.<br />
We aoe committed to the establishment of workships of h gh i; u : lity<br />
and officioney, which will contract better typos of work, aod<br />
increase handicapped empl oyees' opportunities to earn more income.<br />
WoL1hops which will increase the morale of the handicapped workers,<br />
and enable more people to acquire the confidence and work skills<br />
nece; sary to graduate to outside employment. Workshops whicht<br />
provide first and foremost, a practical moans by which peopl. e<br />
with residual disabilities can progress at their own pace, towards<br />
the day when they can compete wi. th others in the open employ: ient<br />
market.<br />
The sheltered workshop must also provide For those people who suffer<br />
from severe c'ronic conditions, and depend upon the workshop<br />
for Dermanen,. -thor than transitional employment.<br />
In cTtering this latter group, the sheltered workshop must:,<br />
at all coss . d any suggestion of stangnation. It scold give<br />
long torn 2 with st. ructnyl pro'gr: Immes, an access to qualityv<br />
w i tracl ; Ali wit ch' i'i vy" 1 </p>
<p>t Ministe" for Social Securi announced Ge<br />
s 21 mi . on three year programme under the<br />
H.,.. cappe. sons' Assiistance Act. This will enable<br />
el i-. ible ori,: i. sati. ons to establish and develop on a planncd<br />
ba . s services for the handicapped, such as sheltered wor: hlops,<br />
ac.'-vity therapy entres, and trairning cenLres and hostels.<br />
The Act underlines the importance of the partnership of Governnment<br />
and no; n-gover'ne'. ent bodies in the provi. sion of such facilities.<br />
' On-G overnm: enn last year also carried out a survey of both<br />
" Atefe!. w o,-orkshop.: s and act vI ity therapy centres, subs i di sed<br />
. th: n' Hanndicapped Persons' Assistance Act.<br />
The results of these surveys will aid in future government<br />
planning cni wi ll also bring into clear focus the overall effort<br />
of all the agencies and organisations involved.<br />
The National Advisory Council for the Handicapped, is also<br />
conducting research into matters which relate to handicapped<br />
people, and their speciaJ. la needs.<br />
The Government sees the partnership of voluntary agenci. es and<br />
government bodies, as a central theme of rehabilitati. on in<br />
Australia. In fact, t: he history of sheltered employment in<br />
Au: ra. lia is the history of a working partnership between the<br />
Coi: u:' onweal th Government, and voluntary organisations for the<br />
handicapped.<br />
Although the Commonwealth Government established its own<br />
rehabi. li tat ion service for handicapped people some twenty-nine years<br />
ago, i t has always refrained. from directly entering the field of<br />
sheltered workshops.<br />
The most obvious reason for this, is the fact that sheltered<br />
workshops are more effective when conducted by voluntary<br />
organisations with government funding and encouragement.<br />
Community organisations are often better able to determine<br />
community needs and prioriti. es andto respond to those needs with<br />
more sensitivity and awareness than remote bureaucracies.<br />
Before 1967 there had been comparatively little development of<br />
sheltered workshops in Australia, although there were some in most,<br />
if not all, of the States. In June 1967 the new Sheltered<br />
Employment ( Assistance) Act came into effect. And the succeeding<br />
ten years have seen amazing strides in sheltered workshops.<br />
The number of sheltered workshops and activity, therapy centres<br />
in Australia risen by over five hundred percent. By 1974<br />
gross product income of sheltered workshops had risen from<br />
$ 2.2 million ! a almost $ 1.7 million.<br />
This Centre r-:-esents an excellent example of the cooperation<br />
between a : n---:. cvernment organi sation, and the Commonweal. th<br />
Governen rD. iding a service which benefits everyone. / 3 </p>
<p>he sheltl ered n\ orkshop withi i ts cottage in dustry and mavke&amp; t<br />
ga udcn f iAiti es iloes no t only conrlU bute grcatl y to t' wol<br />
bying Ot Ft c mplo 0. It will cnrich thc e ife of youl en ire<br />
c : u': it an! can ser'o as a focus for furthcr endeavours<br />
cn: ch c02--: I'nnitv i<br />
thav yVOo u ) day's invi tatin w. hichi has gi. vofn me a welcome1<br />
opnort~ niy to . wt w ih members of your communi ty' nnd to<br />
at f. irws t hr: d, the results of your efEforts to provide for<br />
sone of the less privilJeged in your community.<br />
It g ives ne great pleasure to declare the Heritage I1ndustries<br />
Vocation: X Rchabiiitation Centre, official; open.<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
