<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3421</transcript-id>
    <title>RECEIPT OF TEMPORARY ASSISTANCE AUTHORITY REPORT - FOOTWEAR</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003421.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSlftALI( A PRESS STATEMENT NO. 344<br />
18 October 1974<br />
RECEIPT OF TEMPORARY ASSISTANCE AUTHORITY REPORT FOOTWEAR<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, announced that the<br />
Government had imposed temporary import restrictions on most<br />
types of footwear as from today. The import restrictions are<br />
intended to limit imports over the next twelve months to a level<br />
per cent higher than the level of imports in 1972/ 73, within<br />
each of the specific tariff items set out below. This would mean<br />
that imports over the next year would be at a level about 30 per<br />
cent less than in 1973/ 74. Imports of gum boots, wading boots<br />
and specialist sporting footwear would not be covered by the<br />
restrictions. Mr. Whitlam said that this action had been taken<br />
following the Government's acceptance in principle of the<br />
report by the Temporary Assistance Authority of 10 October 1974<br />
on Footwear. The Authority found that urgent action was necessary<br />
tp protect the Australian industry producing footwear and parts<br />
therefor in relation to the importation of footwear falling within<br />
tariff items 64.01.4, 64.02.3, 64.02.9, 64.03.9 and 64.04.9, which<br />
cover footwear with soles and uppers of rubber or plastic, with<br />
soles of leather or rubber, with outer soles of wood or cork and<br />
with outer soles of other materials.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that because of the possibility of<br />
substantial existing commitments to import, it would be some<br />
time before quota entitlements for individual importers could<br />
be determined. Initially, consideration will be given to entry<br />
of goods in transit and goods in bond as at the date of this<br />
announcement, and of goods covered by irrevocable letter of credit<br />
established on or before 11 September 1974. Allocation of quotas<br />
to individual importers would only be considered after these<br />
commitments were assessed. </p>
<p>In order to make the allocation of any such quotas<br />
more equitable, should a balance remain for allocation after<br />
accommodating the import commitments mentioned above, Mr. Whitlam<br />
said that the base period criterion for determining possible<br />
quota allocations would be widened to include importers in 1973-74,<br />
as well as 1972-73.<br />
Mr. Whitlam also mentioned that a reference on the<br />
long-term prbtective needs of the footwear industry had been<br />
sent to the Industries Assistance Commission, which had been<br />
asked to report its findings to the Government no later than<br />
April 1976. Further details of the Government's decision will be<br />
announced by the Department of Manufacturing Industry which will<br />
be responsible for implementation of the import licensing controls,<br />
in conjunction with the Department of Customs and Excise.<br />
Copies of the Temporary Assitance Authority's report are now<br />
available. CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
