<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7823</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE ACT OFFICE OF THE ZIONIST FEDERATION OF AUSTRLIA CANBERRA - 21 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007823.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF THE ACT OFFICE OF THE<br />
ZIONIST FEDERATION OF-AUSTRALIA<br />
CANBERRA 21 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
It is a great pleasure to be with you this evening to open<br />
the Zionist Federation of Australia's Canberra office.<br />
My Government and the Federation have always had an<br />
excellent working relationship, and although I would hate to<br />
think that at any time geographical distance might have<br />
constituted a barrier to communication, there is no doubt<br />
that the physical proximity to government that your new<br />
office gives you will make it easier for both of us to keep<br />
in contact on issues in which we have a mutual interest.<br />
Looking back over the years, the Federation can point to a<br />
number of impressive achievements, examples of the<br />
constructive things that can be accomplished when Government<br />
works closely with community groups such as your own. I pay<br />
particular tribute here to the energy and dedication of your<br />
President, Mark Leibler.<br />
In 1986, for example, the Federation drew to the<br />
Government's attention the difficulties faced by a number of<br />
Australians living in Israel who had acquired Israeli<br />
citizenship, not knowing that they would lose their<br />
Australian citizenship in the process. As a result, the<br />
then Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic<br />
Affairs, working closely with the Federation, was able to<br />
find a way to solve the problem satisfactorily.<br />
The positive achievements of the Federation are also<br />
reflected in our social security system. German restitution<br />
payments to victims of the Nazi period are now exempt for<br />
social security purposes a gesture of respect to those<br />
whose suffering we can never adequately compensate, but<br />
whose experiences we must never forget. </p>
<p>The Federation can also take credit for its active role in<br />
encouraging the Australian Parliament to pass its resolution<br />
calling for the rescission of UN Resolution 3379 equating<br />
Zionism with racism. Australia was among the first to pass<br />
such a resolution. It is heartening to see countries such<br />
as the United States and the United Kingdom, and the<br />
European Parliament, now following suit. Indeed the United<br />
States Congress passed a resolution based on the Australian<br />
one, a year to the day after it was passed in Canberra.<br />
Australia has begun a dialogue with officials of the Soviet<br />
Union with a view to achieving a different attitude to this<br />
issue by that country.<br />
As Senator Evans made clear in his statement this year to<br />
the United Nations General Assembly, Australia has<br />
consistently taken the position that countries should avoid<br />
using the United Nations to heighten differences or hinder<br />
the peaceful resolution of conflict with provocative<br />
resolutions such as this one. We must all hope that the<br />
changes at work in the world will soon lead to the<br />
rescission of this infamous resolution.<br />
The Zionist Federation can be proud of its achievements over<br />
the years in speaking out on behalf of Jews both in<br />
Australia and abroad. You are no doubt as heartened<br />
indeed excited as I am by the pace of change in the Soviet<br />
Union and other Eastern bloc countries since Gorbachev's<br />
accession to power. The dramatic events in East Germany<br />
illustrate the rapid change now transforming that part of<br />
the world. It is change of a speed we could not have<br />
imagined as little as a year ago. But it is change that was<br />
inevitable, as declining Marxist-Leninist states began to<br />
understand the cost of the historical neglect of the<br />
fundamental link that exists between economic prosperity and<br />
political freedom.<br />
The reforms now underway have had a particularly welcome<br />
effect on the outflow of people from the Soviet Union and<br />
other Eastern bloc countries. The Federation can feel proud<br />
of its record of pressure on the Soviet Union over<br />
refuseniks. Your efforts, letters, lobbying and meetings<br />
have now begun to bear fruit. More than 37,000 Soviet Jews<br />
have departed the Soviet Union so far this year. Last year<br />
the total was of the order of 19,000; in 1987, 8,000.<br />
But we cannot rest yet. There are still cases which will<br />
require determination and energy to resolve. And your work<br />
with refuseniks will still be needed so long as there are<br />
such cases. </p>
<p>The reforms taking place in the Soviet Union also offer an<br />
opportunity, after so many painful years of uncertainty, for<br />
a full investigation of the disappearance of the Swedish<br />
diplomat, Raoul Wallenberg who disappeared into Soviet<br />
hands in January 1945, after having worked through the war<br />
years saving the lives of tens of thousands of potential<br />
victims of Nazi terror in Hungary. One of the most moving<br />
moments on my visit to Budapest in July this year was laying<br />
a wreath on the recently unveiled, and very striking,<br />
monument to Raoul Wallenberg.<br />
I am pleased to announce that in the current parliamentary<br />
session I will move a resolution which urges all parties to<br />
co-operate in a comprehensive and conclusive examination of<br />
the circumstances surrounding Raoul Wallenberg's detention<br />
and disappearance. After consultation with the Opposition<br />
Leader, Andrew Peacock, I am confident that the resolution<br />
will receive bipartisan support.<br />
Australia remains deeply concerned about the unresolved<br />
problems in the Middle East. Let me state categorically we<br />
are committed to the integrity of Israel and its right to<br />
exist within secure and recognised boundaries. This goal we<br />
share. It must be part of any equation for a stable peace.<br />
The other side of the equation, as I have said many times<br />
before, involves the recognition of the rights of the<br />
Palestinian people.<br />
The ultimate resolution to the problems of the Middle East<br />
will only be found through a process of negotiation. I hope<br />
that the efforts of Shamir, Mubarak and Bush will bring all<br />
parties closer to the negotiating table and a lasting peace<br />
for the region.<br />
I talked to Secretary of State James Baker during his recent<br />
visit to Australia and was impressed by his commitment to<br />
facilitating negotiations between Israel and the<br />
Palestinians. Such negotiations could lay the groundwork<br />
for elections in the Occupied Territories and, in the longer<br />
run, a lasting peace.<br />
We are living at a time of rapid change. Global tensions<br />
have eased and changes, both inside and outside Israel, are<br />
creating an impetus for compromise and negotiation. Israel<br />
has demonstrated great valour and determination in war. In<br />
the interests of a lasting an ' d stable agreement, I fervently<br />
hope that Israel will demonstrate the courage we know and<br />
admire in the interests of peace.<br />
The Zionist Federation can be proud of its role in improving<br />
relations between Israel and Australia and in promoting<br />
informed discussion of the issues. Its conferences and<br />
functions have provided a vital forum for debate on those<br />
issues of concern to the Australian Jewish community. </p>
<p>4.<br />
The opening of this Canberra office will give the<br />
organisation a more tangible presence in the nation's<br />
capital, no doubt enhancing its capacity to continue keep up<br />
its good work.<br />
I hereby take great pleasure in declaring the Canberra<br />
office of the Zionist Federation of Australia open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
