<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5950</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO MTIA DINNER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005950.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, 25 OCTOBER 1982<br />
ADDRESS TO MTIA DINNER<br />
Mr President, Sir John Moore, my colleagues, ladies and<br />
gentlemen. Mr President, when you were speaking earlier,<br />
you mentioned the foundings of thi5; Association in 1073.<br />
You indicated that the Association had then been formaed<br />
to fight for various things, including a certain measure<br />
of protection that might not be much of an industrial base<br />
in Australia. Obviously the Association has had a very<br />
significant role to play, but wh you said reminded me of<br />
an argument that my grandfather had with David Syme in the<br />
early years of federation. My grandfather was a Senator,<br />
and you wouldn't have liked this, but he was a free trader<br />
in the old fashion sense of the term. David Syme had been<br />
a free trader but he became converted with total and<br />
absolute protection. He took it upon himself with a<br />
religious zeal to convert Senator Fraser to the Same<br />
philosophy. They started off a long correspondence which<br />
I have most of at home. It started off, My Dear Simon<br />
and My Dear David. A month or two on, Dear Simon and Dear<br />
David there were all sorts of arguments in the letters,<br />
not just that address. A little later, Dear Fraser, Dear<br />
Syme. Then the last letter, From Syme to Fraser. It said,<br />
Fraser, because of your intransigen. ice, your name will never<br />
again appear in the correspondence column of hhe Me3bourne<br />
Age. Well, what's new I might say? But that wasn't the end<br />
of the story. You got advertising rates for a lot, Jot less<br />
in those days and apparently on a miserable Senator's salary<br />
in 1904, the last letter went, Syme, you're wrong. Here's the<br />
first page advertisement that I have taken out covering a<br />
half a page in the Melbourne Age tomorrow morning. For three<br />
years, whatever the old bloke wanted published in the Melbourne<br />
Age he paid for. Quite literally.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, metal trades industries make an<br />
enormous contribution to this economy. You should never need<br />
telling, advising or reminding of the importance of your<br />
industry. Over 47% of the manufacturing workforce, over<br />
49% of manufacturing wages and salary, 44% of the turnover<br />
in manufacturing is in the industries that you represent.<br />
Quite obviously the competitiveness, the profitability,<br />
the capacity to sell what you are producing, the profitability<br />
of your industries is of vast concern not only to yourselves and<br />
your own employees, but to the well-being of Australia and<br />
right across the country. / 2 </p>
<p>M-T2I -<br />
Therefore, I hope that you would never believe any government<br />
has any doubt about the ir. portance of these industries. You<br />
know over recent times that the leaders of the industry, the<br />
Association has been in discussions with my government on many<br />
occasions. We meet informally and frequently and exchange views<br />
about what ought to be done. Obviously there is not always<br />
agreement, but often there is a fair measure of agreement<br />
about the sorts of things that are important.<br />
Wage decisions have been critical to this industry, and your<br />
decisions, the wage decisions affecting these industries<br />
are critical to the Australian economy because so often<br />
they are I was going to use that -awful word ' pace setters'<br />
but you probably wouldn't want me to do that -so often they<br />
establish the guidelines which are followed by other industry<br />
in other places and it is that that makes them important.<br />
But your industries have been affected not only by somecircumstances<br />
in Australia by a world economic downturn<br />
which has gone on longer and in a severer fashio-n than<br />
anything many of us can remember. It is the first major<br />
world recession since the end of ti-e World War. That indicates<br />
its seriousness and importance.<br />
It is important I think, no matt~ er how difficult things<br />
might be in Australia sometimes, to recal. what is happening<br />
overseas. I don't know how many people read the-fron-t page<br />
of the Sydney Morning Herald which related<br />
the employment position in many countries. I think in nearly<br />
every case,. Australia is a good deal better off.* I<br />
In the United Kingdom, it is 14%, the United States it is<br />
There are 32 million unemployed in the OECD countries<br />
alone and they are expecting that that unemployment is goinqf<br />
to rise significantly over the year ahead and nobody really<br />
has all that much confidence that it is going to start falling.<br />
after that.-<br />
Industrial production has been stagnant or h-as fal~ len in themajor<br />
world economaies, the major na tions, and trade has<br />
declined for the first time in over 20 years. It is<br />
worth noting that when this economy was growing very strongly<br />
and'the major world economies were moving forward at rates -of<br />
between 4 and 6 percent a year, that was at a time when -the<br />
value of world trade was growing by about 8 percent a year.<br />
Trade has been the engine of growth, progress and prosperity<br />
In most of the years since the last World War.<br />
Quite clearly, the current circumstances are having a very<br />
unpleasant and difficult impact on Australia. Many things<br />
arc hitting Australia hard. We are the world's 15th largest<br />
trading nation even though on a population base, we are<br />
much smaller than that. Clearly, when our commodity prices<br />
are down by 30 or 40 or in some cases, 50 percent, or where<br />
there are harder quantative restrictions against our exports,<br />
that is obviously going to come back on employment in Australia<br />
and on the kind of standard of life that Australia can sustain.<br />
Clearly, therefore, what happens overseas, the time and the<br />
manner in which the world climbs; out of the current recession<br />
is of enormous importance to us and of great consequence to<br />
all Australians.<br />
MTIA </p>
<p>MT~ 3A<br />
But there is still cons iderable strength in this economy, and<br />
sometimes I think we don't pay sufficient attention to it.<br />
Investment is down this year and will be running at a lower<br />
rate at the end of the year than at the beginning, but overall,<br />
investment in Australia is probably a good deal. stronger than<br />
in many other countries, and there * are other strengths, some<br />
of which I will mention a little l~ ater-.<br />
on top of all this of course, we have gjot one or-two hm<br />
grown problems. I don't know if there is any premier around<br />
or whether Mr Bjelke Petersen can break the drought. This<br />
unfortunately is not a power well, the constitution<br />
certainly didn't place it with -Federal Governments or<br />
Prime Ministers. -The Queensland Premier did lead the<br />
State of Queensland in prayer for r-ain on one occasion,<br />
but* I think he had had a very good look at the weather<br />
map before he did so. I have been watching the weather<br />
maps very, very closely for the last nine months, and I.<br />
haven't seen one weather map that would make it worthwhile<br />
taking the risk, even if Joh was along side nie in the same<br />
church. But the drought might well end up being the worst since the<br />
1930s and in terms of its extent, it could end up by being<br />
even worse than that. It is obviously one that has, signi fi cant<br />
impact across Australia. What happcns in Australia's rural<br />
areas is often understated in terms of its wider impact.<br />
The early stages of drought or rural recess ion aren't4 felt<br />
all that much in the major capital cities and industries,<br />
but it is felt quite soon in the smraller country towns<br />
than in the-larger provincial cities. As orders stop coming<br />
through, it then has a significant impact in the major capitals.<br />
As the drought goes on, it is not only for the rest of this<br />
year, but through next year that its impact is like). y to be<br />
felt, and felt severely. That of course on top of the world<br />
recession, just compounds the difficulty.<br />
But if we couldn't have helped. the drought, there are other<br />
things where we have damaged ourselves, where we certainly<br />
could have done something about it. Through last year, there<br />
seemed, to be a madness around with wage increascs of 15 to<br />
percent, pressures for shorLer hours-which were in soe<br />
cases, successful. All of this has compounded and made more<br />
difficult the competitive base of Australian industry. Coming<br />
at a time when the world recession was deepening, and perhaps for. the<br />
first time starting to bite in Australia, coming at a time<br />
when overseas countries were -achieving wage settlements of<br />
five or six percent, what happened through . last year was<br />
madness indeed. On top of that of course, there were industrial<br />
disputes which were the worst since 1974. Maybe the only good<br />
that has come out of that situation is that industrial<br />
disputation is now less than it has been for 12, 13, 14 years.<br />
If it stays that way then we have learnt that lesson at<br />
7 percent unemployment whereas in the United Kingdom they<br />
learnt it at about 12 percent unemployment. I suppose that makes<br />
us a little more sensible. ./ 4<br />
MTIA </p>
<p>25.10.82<br />
The consequences of what happened last year and of one or two<br />
other things, is partly seen by the September quarter Consumer<br />
Price Index which I believe is very discomforting and must<br />
be disturbing to all of us-an increase of 3 It is difficult<br />
to draw precise comparisons with earlier years because it is<br />
the second quarter of a new series and a number of things have<br />
been done differently. It is perfectly plain the wage decisions<br />
of last year and the first part of this year have started<br />
to flow through in a very significant way. In addition<br />
to that State taxes and charges which have gone up more this<br />
year than perhaps in any other equivalent period, will have<br />
a special significance. Gas, electricity, petrol taxes and<br />
transport fares, hospital charges are all included in these<br />
figures. In addition to that there has been a drawing forward<br />
in the counting some of the increases from the Federal Budget<br />
which normally would have been included in the December<br />
quarter figures a little later orn.<br />
So there has been a bunching of a number of factors in the September<br />
quarter which has given this very uncomfortable result.<br />
Part of it is not surprising when clectricity goes up in<br />
NSW 42% over the last 12 months, hospital charges in my own<br />
State by over 37% from lJuly, and I think some hospital charges<br />
by about 60% over the 12 months, public transport charges by<br />
and a number of other things where increases have been<br />
dramatic and draconian. I am only glad to know that at the<br />
last Premiers' Conference we had the foresight to say to all<br />
the Premiers, " However much money you want to borrow for your<br />
electricity authorities, you do it. The controls for the<br />
Loan Council have not been effective in relation to those authorities<br />
anyway, so for electricity, borrow what you want and be<br />
responsible for it". If we had not done that I have not the<br />
slightest doubt that I would har. e been personally responsible for<br />
all the increases in electricity charges that have gone on over<br />
the last 3 or 4 months.. That alibi was taken away by that<br />
particular decision.<br />
The wages and hours decisions of last year would have had a<br />
very particular impact because that is seen in the services crponent.<br />
of the CPI which has gone up by something approaching<br />
in the year to September. Clearly, manufacturers would have<br />
absorbed some of the earlier increases when they felt they<br />
were able to, but profits have been squeezed over the last<br />
year as I suspect everyone in this room knows very well.<br />
They fell by 4 in real terms in the last financial year<br />
and I do not suppose that leaves very much room to absorb<br />
further and additional costs.<br />
The September unemployment figure of a little over 7.3% is just<br />
as disturbing as the Consumer Price Index figure which I<br />
have just been talking about. That level of unemployment I<br />
suspect is an inevitable consequence of what happened through<br />
last year when you couple that with the world recession. Indeed<br />
one of the things that Australians are going to need to do is<br />
to work together harder than ever before to make sure that<br />
we can maintain employment levels that are significantly<br />
better than the employment levels in a large number of major<br />
industrial countries in the northern hemisphere.<br />
MTIA4 </p>
<p>25.10.82<br />
Being lower than many overseas countries is little comfort.<br />
It is not of any comfort to the particular people who are<br />
unemployed. because if there is a man or a woman who wants to<br />
work and cannot, then for that particular person, it is just<br />
as much a human tragedy as it is for every one of one. hundred<br />
thousand. It is like a bushfire. If it is a small one it<br />
does not get much sympathy. If a bushfire burns out half a<br />
State, it gets an enormous amount of sympathy, but for the<br />
person who is entirely burnt out in one small fire, it is just<br />
as bad, just as much a tragedy, as if they were part of a much<br />
larger configuration. In relation to unemployment is a little<br />
bit the same. Our consciences get moved when the numbers are<br />
ve-ry great, but for the individuals concerned, the John Smith<br />
or whoever it may be who is affected, we need to think about<br />
individuals more than about the large numbers.<br />
I suspect, and I wish it were otherwise, that the trend in<br />
employment can only really be reversed if wages are held back,<br />
if real wages fall over a period pexhaps because there has<br />
been too big an increase. We have been paying ourselves too<br />
much. Our income as a nation has fallen over the last year<br />
or. 18 months and we just have to recognise the facts of life.<br />
One of the easiest things in the world will be for the trade<br />
union movement to press for higher and higher wages over<br />
the period ahead of us, but if they do so they will know that<br />
those wages are going to be paid for not only by employers<br />
some of whom will go broke in the process, but by a larger<br />
number . of unemployed Australians. That I think is too high<br />
a price to pay.<br />
The problems we face are being understood by many<br />
more than before, but we must recognise the need to help ourselves.<br />
We cannot go and cry to the world and say save us. We are<br />
regarded by-everyone as one of the wealthier nations of the<br />
world. There are some people who think we do not always work.<br />
as hard as we should and on some occasions 1 suspect that that<br />
view is right, but Australians have acapacity to work as<br />
hard and well and efficiently as any people on earth and it is<br />
time we did it in working together to get out of these present<br />
difficulties. The fact that industrial disputes are indeed the lowest for<br />
a very significant period, for well over a decade, that the<br />
July 1982 days lost through disputes are less than half those lost<br />
through July 1981, I think they are encouraging signs. The<br />
Tripartite Conference that was held with the ACTU, employergroups,<br />
including representatives of MTIA shortly before the<br />
Budget was announced, . was a constructive and useful discussion.<br />
I believe that the Government listened very closely to what<br />
was put by this Association, by other representatives and by<br />
the union movement. At the same time, I believe when we<br />
brought down our Budget, we showed that we had done a great<br />
deal to introduce a Budget that would encourage, make possible,<br />
make it reasonable, to argue for wage restraint as a means<br />
for working our way out of presen difficulties.<br />
Since those discussions we have had some more responsible<br />
wage decisions. There have been one or two odd tribunals<br />
affecting politicians and academic salaries, ht more significant<br />
decisions-affecting the public services of the Commonwealth and<br />
a number of States. There have been some private sector / 6<br />
MTIA5 </p>
<p>decisions that have been even lower than the 6% or 7% which has<br />
become fairly cacrn in the public services. All of that is a vast improvement<br />
over last year, but the decisions are still perhaps too high.<br />
We need to know that the faster we can get back to a proper<br />
level of relativities, the faster we will be able to get<br />
out way out of the problems that are around us and the sooner<br />
will Australian industry be fully competitive again and able<br />
to hold its own fully within Australia and establish itself<br />
in markets outside.<br />
Of course it is here that the metal industries'case is critical.<br />
It does so often provide the guideline for other industries.<br />
Wage adjustments have obviously got to reflect the strength<br />
and the'weaknesses of a particular industries and the circumstances<br />
of any particular period and the metal industry, as I think<br />
are most others, are in real difficulties at the moment. I<br />
would not have thought anyone could expect significant increases<br />
If it can be recognised that the freeze advocated by<br />
MTIA is the best possible thing for everyone in the industry,<br />
then I have not the slightest doubt that a great service will<br />
be done, not only through. MTIA's own members;, but also to their<br />
employees and to all other industries who might be able to<br />
follow their example. We do need low wage increases. to protect<br />
the jobs of Australians and to prevent the dole list getting<br />
as long as it is in many other countries around the world.<br />
The Government is obviously concerned as imany other people are<br />
at this situation of the difficulties of unemployed Australians,<br />
but there is not any magic wand. There is no quick solution.<br />
We have to recognise the nature of the problem and work our<br />
way out of it. Job creation schemes as such we have always<br />
believed are not the answerand it seems to me there is nothing<br />
new in the whole argument because Abraham Lincoln said quite<br />
a while ago, you cannot help the wage earner by putting down<br />
the wage payer. That just about says it all.<br />
The Government's policies have tried in this last period to<br />
make it reasonable to argue for and to expect wage restraint.<br />
We have had to balance a number of factors in bringing down the<br />
Budget., the question of.: responsibility, and balance that against<br />
the need to assist people who might be in difficulty. I have<br />
got little doubt that if we had had a pure economist's hair<br />
Sshirt Budget with an overall surplus of billion or something<br />
like that, it. would be possible to do more for interest rates<br />
quicker, more to knockinflation quicker, but also the numbers<br />
of unemployed would have been significantly greater. Therefore,<br />
the Budget in the end was a compromise as any document of that<br />
kind has to be.<br />
Tax cuts of about a $ 1 billion this year, housing rebates,<br />
increases in family allowances have all been designed to<br />
establish the circumstance where families could be protected<br />
even if wages did not move much through this year. In addition<br />
to that, capital works by the Commonwealth and by the statutory<br />
authorities of the Commonwealth, increased very significantly<br />
this year compared to earlier years. Welfare housing was<br />
up about 27%, Ralph Hunt's new Bicentennial Road Development<br />
Program in getting underway is going to add significantly<br />
to the workforce in many different parts of Australia. As we<br />
approach that bicentennial year we will have a road network<br />
which I think few Australians have even dreamt of in the past,<br />
but which we are in effect going to build as a result of that<br />
decision. 7 </p>
<p>MTIA 7 25.10.82<br />
There were other things designed specifically to assist business<br />
an increased retention allowance, tax relief on dividend<br />
income saying something which I think is very important in<br />
terms of principle even if the initial start is a relatively<br />
modest one, and changes to encourage employee share participation<br />
schemes, again a modest start, but one which I think says<br />
something important in terms of principle and in terms of<br />
philosophy. It is-worth noting that a single income family on say $ 300<br />
a week, paying off an average size home loan of $ 20,000 to $ 25,000<br />
and with two dependent children will be $ 18 or $ 19 a week better<br />
off as a result of our Budget. I suppose that is the equivalent<br />
of $ 25 or $ 26 if that person has to get it from you as<br />
employers. One of the differences being, that if they had to<br />
get it from you as employers, some of you might cease being<br />
employers in the present circumstances.. I think it is worth<br />
contrasting that with what happened in the Victorian Budget<br />
for example where on Eric Risstrom's figures, the cost of that<br />
Budget for every Victorian family was $ 12 a week. So we<br />
we give $ 18 a week to each family or families on $ 300 a week<br />
and it gets taken away by increased taxes and charges in<br />
Victoria. One Budget working in one direction and one in<br />
exactly the opposite direction. The Victorian Budget and<br />
for that matter the NSW Budget will have hit families and<br />
employees. Tn my own State the Government's spending is up 24%.<br />
That almost makes Mr Whitlam modest because his first Budget<br />
was only up 20%, and his second Budget was up 46%, so I do<br />
not know what John Cain's second Budget will be up in terms<br />
of expenditure. Victorian taxes overall went up by a little<br />
over 30%, or the rates went up by<br />
It is not only a job for the Commonwealth Government. I thinz<br />
it would be much better if there could be a clearer view in<br />
relation to these matters involving the Commonwealth and the<br />
States because what I have just indicated shows that a Commonwealth<br />
Budget can be driving in one direction, establishing the<br />
circumstances where wage restraint or even no changes in wages<br />
is a reasonable thing to ask for,. and have that undermined by<br />
State governments' budgets which run very much in the opposite<br />
direction. Even though there are many problems, there are some positive<br />
signs. I do not want to overplay them because I think the<br />
signs are equivocal, but the fact that interest rates are down<br />
in the United States and there have been some falls in Australia,<br />
that inflation has come down markedly in the United States,<br />
Here the bond rate is down over 3% since early August and<br />
some private sector rates have also started to fall. These<br />
are encouraging signs, but it is going to be activity that<br />
counts in the event, and in the United States there is not yet<br />
much sign of increased activity. I am not going to predict<br />
when that comes. There are enough people in the business of<br />
prediction and we will be able to see it and measure it when<br />
it does occur. 8 </p>
<p>MTIA 8 25.10.82<br />
World recovery needs substantial economic growth and I believe<br />
very strongly that international action is needed to withdraw<br />
the kind of growth that we saw through the ' 50s and the<br />
and I suppose the early part of the 1970s. The Australian<br />
trade initiative which will be debated at GATT is designed<br />
to be one way of helping to re-establish growth. But let<br />
me just emphasise here we are not in the business of making<br />
unilateral decisions. If there can be multilateral decisions<br />
in which many countries are participating with consequential<br />
advantages for Australia, then that_ is something that we could<br />
participate in. But we are not in the business of opening up<br />
our markets for the dubious pleasure of some time in the<br />
future getting better access to other peoples' markets overseas.<br />
I do not want anyone to suggest that we are.<br />
I think there is growing support: for the matters that we have<br />
discussed, but what we have put runs very much counter<br />
to the increasing moves to protectionism that have come out<br />
of Europe . and the northern hemisphere over the last 12 months.<br />
But if the increasing moves for protection continue, well then<br />
the future for Europe is going to be a grim one indeed because<br />
they will not work their way out of problems. With increasing<br />
protection, maybe they won't work their way out of problems<br />
even by maintaining the. present levels of protection that<br />
Europe now has, levels of protection which I believe over all<br />
are very much greater than we have in Australia.<br />
There is also a role for action by the private sector, difficult<br />
as it is. We hope there can be investment in new technologies.<br />
There will obviously be rationalisation in the pursuit of<br />
greater efficiency. I hope very much that the depreciation<br />
provisions which were announced on 19 July can be seen as a<br />
positive contribution to encouraging industry to take advantage<br />
of opportunities that might be open as occasion arises. Because<br />
even if-there are difficulties, even if there are problems,<br />
there are always going to be opportunities for some industries<br />
to move ahead. There are always going to be opportunities<br />
for some new investment. Those depreciation allowances and<br />
depreciation on income producing buildings which is being<br />
introduced for the first time I hope will be useful and<br />
constructive in enabling industry to compete on more equal<br />
terms with its counterparts in other countries.<br />
There is obviously a great deal ahead of us, there is a great<br />
deal for us to do. Mr President you said something about the<br />
supercharged political atmosphere around this capital or<br />
Parliament House, I do not think it is particularly supercharged.<br />
I think people just need to get on with the job that they<br />
are paid to do and go about it. If there was less of a rumour<br />
mill operating, it would also be a much better and a much<br />
healthier place.<br />
You might be interested to know that last Wednesday in spite of<br />
all the significant problems that are before the Parliament,<br />
and all the significant legislation which the Government has </p>
<p>25.10.82<br />
introduced, all questions but one came to me from one side of<br />
the House and all but one of the questions on Wednesday that<br />
came to me were throwing mud at John Reid. I think there are<br />
better things for the Parliament to be doing than trying to<br />
slander somebody who has demonstrated his innocence in the clearest<br />
way possible, from the highest authority in the land, from the<br />
Chief Commissioner of Taxation. That just shows the way the<br />
Parliament can be diverted. I cannot stop the kinds of questions;<br />
that come to me from anyone in the Parliament. You respond<br />
to them as best you can. Do not let. anyone think that the<br />
Government is diverted just because. Question Time is wasted<br />
in a thoroughly base and useless way.<br />
We do need to recognise the. strengths that we have in Australia,<br />
the initiative of Australians, the capacity of people to work<br />
together, We need to recognise that while there are many count) ies<br />
that only have these things and can work their way through it,<br />
in addition we have vast supplies of raw materials, we are a<br />
great food producer, a great apparel fibre producer and<br />
we have raw materials of nearly every kind. It is up to us<br />
to make something of this for our children and to make something<br />
of all of this for Australia's sake. However difficult it might<br />
appear to be, we know quite well we are so much better off than<br />
people in almost any other country you can name.<br />
It is not often that we have things like the Cormmonwealth Ganmcr<br />
which sparked a sense of pride and nationalism in this country<br />
of a kind that has seldom been seen. I think everyone<br />
was enormously proud of what all of those young athletes did,<br />
but not only the athletes, the people organising the Games<br />
and who put it all together. If you had been, as I had,<br />
in Montreal to speak t-o some of our own athletes at the<br />
Olympic Games only a few short years before, or at Edmonton<br />
where we had also been wiped out by the Canadians and the<br />
English.-I say the English because the English are seven<br />
countries in the Commonwealth Games. They have Scotland, England,<br />
Wales, the Isle of Man, Guernsey and all the rest as you will<br />
have noticed -I think that is only so they get more votes;<br />
We were wiped out in Montreal, and wiped out in Edmonton, but<br />
our. sports organisations, working together with the Government,<br />
said this is not going to happen again. What is needed is<br />
training and opportunities in competition at the highest<br />
possible international level. The result was a morale amongst<br />
our competitors and amongst the sports organisations which<br />
Was certainly second to none. It was wonderful to see and it<br />
was wonderful to be there while it was all happening. I think<br />
they have set some kind of example to the whole country. We should<br />
see that this is where we were when Montreal and Edmonton<br />
happened, but that. Australia got it together<br />
during the period of those Commonwealth Games. We must make<br />
sure that it stays there. It is in our hands. We can work<br />
together and achieve it. If we are going to. pull ourselves<br />
apart by arguing with each other, whether it is Government<br />
or Opposition, or whether it is management and labour, then<br />
we won't. I think we owe our children something better than<br />
some of the arguments that have gone on in the past.<br />
MTIA9 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
