<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8528</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP OPENING OF YOUTH TRAINING AND EMPLOYMENT FORUM NATIONAL PRESS CLUB CANBERRA JUNE 2 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/06/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008528.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
OPENING OF YOUTH TRAINING AND EMPLOYMENT FORUM<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB, CANBERRA, JUNE 2 1992<br />
Thank you for the opportunity to open this forum. I am<br />
very grateful to the organisers for giving me the chance<br />
to speak.<br />
The issues of education and employment for our yon<br />
people are issues of national concern. 2n<br />
The cliches, of course, are easy but they are no less<br />
true for that.<br />
Young people are the nation's future. Our success as a<br />
nation depends upon their skills and resources and the<br />
degree of their commitment to this society.<br />
At one level, providing employment, education and<br />
training for our young people is a real test of our<br />
ability to create an efficient modern economy.<br />
But we won't do that without a social ethic. Our<br />
economic success is inseparable from our social successwe<br />
will succeed best in Australia if we raise the level<br />
of our care for each other.<br />
To a very considerable extent our success depends on the<br />
degree to which our young people believe in this country.<br />
It is perhaps another cliche to say they they won't<br />
believe in it if we don't.<br />
And it is hard to think of a truer measure of our belief<br />
than the investment we make in them.<br />
By any reasonable standards we have a duty to train and<br />
educate them, to prepare them for the future, to give<br />
them every possible chance.<br />
We have a duty as a community and a nation.<br />
If these are cliches, they are no less true for that.<br />
But we won't get anywhere by simply uttering them. </p>
<p>Understandably, with an issue which goes to the very<br />
heart of communities, we often end up with more heat than<br />
light.<br />
We need heat but we need more light.<br />
What we need from this conference, and in the press in<br />
discussions about unemployment and youth around the<br />
country are rea itic and effective ideas and<br />
strategies. When I became Prime Minister I gave a commitment to speed<br />
economic recovery and do everything we realistically<br />
could to reduce unemployment.<br />
The measures in One Nation were the first step to doing<br />
this.<br />
We introduced a $ 100 million package to boost new<br />
employment and training opportunities, save existing jobs<br />
and strengthen the economy. The package will provide<br />
assistance for nearly 40,000 young people.<br />
Young people will also benefit from the substantial<br />
increases in funding for labour market programs and for<br />
TAFE places. WVe provided an extra SlOOD iioT~ n in the<br />
November Economic Statement and a further $ 40 million in<br />
One Nation for an additional 50,000 places in TAFE.<br />
In the first ten months of 1991-92, almost 75,000 young<br />
people have been involved in vocational education and<br />
training placements.<br />
But clearly this is not enough. We need to work on long<br />
term solutions.<br />
In tackling the next stages, we need to be clear about<br />
the impact that the fundamental restructuring of the<br />
labour market has had on opportunities For yo'ung people.<br />
Major changes to industry structure and new technology<br />
are substantially changing the type of jobs available.<br />
In manufacturing, the old production line approach which<br />
produced a large number of the same standard item and<br />
which employed a large number of unskilled labourers is<br />
fast disappearing.<br />
It is being replaced with new, computer-based design and<br />
production techniques which place a high premium on both<br />
highly skilled and multi-skilled staff at all levels of<br />
the design, production and marketingprocesses.<br />
Similarly, in key service industries such as retail,<br />
hospitality and tourism, the quality of our skills will<br />
influence the standard of our service and hence our<br />
ultimate success. </p>
<p>These changes are common to all industrialised nations.<br />
They cannot be turned back.<br />
The challenge is to develop the means by which young<br />
people can gain the skills and experience they need.<br />
The challenge is made more critical by the fact that<br />
young people with little education and training are most<br />
disadvantaged in the labour market.<br />
There is one unmistakable fact about the modern labour<br />
market: those who do not complete school or a postschool<br />
qualification are twice as likely to be<br />
unemployed, and are unemployed for much longer.<br />
I can tell you. that the Goverrnent has accepted the<br />
challenge. And I have to say that we're not at all interested in<br />
John Howard's non-solution of dead-end jobs for young<br />
people, jobs which don't involve any training.<br />
As Ross Gittins wrote if we can't do better than that<br />
there won't be much hope for the rest of us.<br />
" An economy in which there is a great demand for<br />
unskilled workers", he said, " is an economy at the<br />
bottom of the pile in the international division of<br />
labour; one with a low standard of living, producing low<br />
value, labour-intensive goods and watching the nations<br />
with cleverer, better-equipped workers pass it by."<br />
The plain fact is that a competitive economy needs a<br />
highly skilled workforce. And surely we can muster the<br />
will and the resources necessary to create one.<br />
We have already made substantial progress.<br />
There has never been a group of school leavers in<br />
Australia with higher levels of formal education than the<br />
group now entering the labour market. In the last decade<br />
the proportion of young people completing secondary<br />
schooling has doubled from 35% in 1981 to 70% in 1991.<br />
Our higher education system compares well with the OECD<br />
average. In 1992 around 500,000 Australians are<br />
participating in higher education, an increase of over<br />
120,000 students since 1987 or the equivalent of 12 new<br />
universities. By 1994, we will have increased the total number of.<br />
Commonwealth-funded university places by 50% since 1983.<br />
Over the 1992-1994 triennium, the Government plans to<br />
spend a total of $ 13 billion on higher education. </p>
<p>We can see these changes reflected in the education and<br />
labour market profile of young people. In the mid 1960s<br />
nearly six in ten 15-19 year olds had a full-time job; by<br />
the early 1990s, this stood at less than one in three.<br />
Less than one in three were full-time students in the mid<br />
1960s; now six in ten are.<br />
In April 1992, 117,000 of our 1.3 million teenagers were<br />
seeking full-time jobs. One in ten young people is<br />
unemployed which is actually 32,000 less than the<br />
number seeking jobs in April 1983 in the last recession.<br />
Our goal is not simply to keep young people busy and off<br />
the streets. In conjunction with business and industry<br />
we must develop education and training systems which<br />
ensure that young people receive skills that meet their<br />
needs and the economy' s needs.<br />
Successful economies are characterised by high education<br />
standards; a strong emphasis on vocational preparation<br />
for young people; and close links between education<br />
institutions and employers.<br />
Plainly, in Australia the weak link is vocational<br />
education and training. It is the sector which most<br />
clearly falls short of the standards of our main<br />
competitors such as Germany and Japan and the emerging<br />
tigers like Singapore and South Korea.<br />
Australia must begin to value vocational skills as highly<br />
as academic skills, and expect excellence from both.<br />
This is why we are moving as quickly as we can to reform<br />
and expand entry-level training arrangements and the TAFE<br />
system.<br />
The most striking feature of Australia's vocational<br />
preparation system is that it is small. On one measure,<br />
only around one in five places occupied by a 16 or 17<br />
year old is in vocational preparation. The OECD average<br />
is one in two, and in Germany it is eight in ten.<br />
In Australia, apprenticeship is the largest form of<br />
vocational preparation, accounting for 60% of<br />
participation. But there are weaknesses with the<br />
apprenticeship system.<br />
The occupational and industry coverage is too narrow.<br />
There is little vocational preparation for the service<br />
sector which provides two thirds of employment for 15-19<br />
year olds.<br />
Young women, whose employment is concentrated in the<br />
service sector, are greatly under-represented in<br />
vocational preparation. </p>
<p>And there is a tendency for programs to rigidly separate<br />
general education from vocational training.<br />
The Carmichael Report proposes major initiatives to<br />
significantly increase the flexibility and quality of<br />
vocational training, as well as the number of work-based<br />
training places available to Australia's young people.<br />
Broadly speaking, in my view these are not options, but<br />
imperatives. And we need to move on them now.<br />
Expanding the industry and occupational coverage of<br />
structured training arrangements will provide greater<br />
training opportunities for all young people. We must<br />
work with industry, unions and training providers to see<br />
that it happens as quickly as possible.<br />
So far, there has been strong in-principle support for<br />
the thrust of Carmichael's proposals from the ACTU and<br />
peak employer groups including the BCA, CAI and the MTIA.<br />
There is also general support from the States, and the<br />
Minister, Kim Beazley, will be commencing detailed<br />
discussions with his State counterparts this week.<br />
The Commonwealth Government is committed to reforming<br />
entry-level training. I will be giving this a high<br />
personal priority over the next months.<br />
To accelerate the process, I will convene a series of<br />
meetings of peak business organisations, employers and<br />
the ACTU to advance the development and implementation of<br />
the pilot projects which will test the new approach.<br />
For the reforms to entry-level training to be successful,<br />
they must be backed up by a greatly expanded and improved<br />
vocational education and training system.<br />
I am convinced that the best way to achieve a truly<br />
national system of vocational education and training is<br />
for the Commonwealth Government to assume a key role.<br />
In One Nation I proposed that the Commonwealth enter into<br />
a partnership with the States, with the Commonwealth<br />
assuming full responsibility for the funding of the<br />
system, while the States retained responsibility for its<br />
administration, management and planning at a local level.<br />
To date we have been unable to reach agreement on this<br />
proposal. One option, which has many attractions, is for the<br />
Commonwealth to go further and assume full<br />
responsibility, not only for the funding, but also for<br />
the administration of TAFE.<br />
It would ensure an efficient and effective national<br />
vocational and educational training system. </p>
<p>It would allow a closer integration of TAFE and<br />
higher education policy.<br />
It would enable the Commonwealth to pursue its<br />
fundamental objectives of raising the system' s<br />
quality and diversity, and achieving across<br />
Australia a better match of training and the needs<br />
of young people, industry and the labour market.<br />
It is a step we are prepared to take.<br />
I recognise that we could not achieve such a system<br />
overnight. In the meantime, it is critical that the pressing demand<br />
for more places in TAFE be addressed. I would therefore<br />
propose for the 1993-1995 triennium that the States<br />
maintain their current effort on TAFE and, where<br />
necessary, lift their effort from their own resources to<br />
reach an agreed national standard of provision.<br />
For its part, the Commonwealth would commit additional<br />
funding for the growth and improvement of the vocational<br />
education and training system.<br />
As part of the arrangements for the triennium, we would<br />
seek an inter-governmental agreement at Heads of<br />
Government level to raise the quality and responsiveness<br />
of the mainstream TAFE system.<br />
In order to steer the system towards national objectives,<br />
the Commonwealth would use part of its growth funding to<br />
purchase courses directly from institutions and industry<br />
to encourage an active involvement by the private sector.<br />
Whatever happens, we must settle matters as soon as<br />
possible. The Government is determined that Australia will have a<br />
world class vocational education and training system and<br />
we will not be deflected from that objective.<br />
The Commonwealth will therefore support the development<br />
of a network of high profile institutions, catering for<br />
the advanced technical training needs of specific<br />
industry sectors.<br />
In this way the Commonwealth would also be in a position<br />
over time to build institutes of vocational education in<br />
connection with industry, as well as maintain our<br />
recurrent effort for the existing TAFE system.<br />
I have spoken today about the far-reaching reforms of the<br />
education and training systems for young people. But<br />
more can be done to help those young people who are<br />
unemployed now. </p>
<p>I In addition to the initiatives I have already mentioned,<br />
the Government is considering some measures in the Budget<br />
context. I am not convinced that more of the same is needed. This<br />
is why I was keen to address you today. One of the aims<br />
of this forum is to hear ideas from different sectors of<br />
society. I trust you will take my presence here as an<br />
indication that I want to hear the views of young people<br />
and others who are grappling with the issues.<br />
There is no one answer.<br />
I know from some initial discussions with business and<br />
industry that there are a lot of good ideas around many<br />
of them are already being put into practice.<br />
Business is saying that it has a role to play in<br />
addressing youth unemployment: that it is not the<br />
Government's sole responsibility.<br />
We need, I believe, a national effort to find solutions.<br />
In some cases, business is linking up with community<br />
organisations for example, by developing training and<br />
work experience programs for homeless kids.<br />
They are working in partnership with Government for<br />
example by employing young people through the<br />
Government's Jobstart program.<br />
In many other cases they are going it alone and employing<br />
unemployed kids above their normal requirements.<br />
In addition to considering our own initiatives on youth<br />
unemployment, I see a role for Government in<br />
consolidating and promoting the good ideas of others.<br />
I think we can encourage other businesses to consider<br />
what role they can play.<br />
I will be holding a national meeting of business people<br />
and others who are taking a lead in this area with a view<br />
to developing a national response to youth unemployment.<br />
A national initiative.<br />
I believe we can learn from each other. I believe we<br />
have to.<br />
This forum today will make a considerable contribution to<br />
the debate. Thank you again for inviting me.<br />
I wish you well in your discussions and I will be<br />
interested in your conclusions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
