<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8968</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING, MP ASIA SOCIETY, NEW YORK, 15 SEPTEMBER 1993 &quot;AUSTRALIA, THE UNITED STATES AND THE NEW ASIA&quot;</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008968.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL -I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
RMOMRGOED: Against Delivery<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE NON P. J. XEATING, MP<br />
ASIA SOCIETY, ME YORK, 15 SEPMhNER 1L993<br />
" AUSTRALIA, THE UNITED STATES AND) THE NEW ASIA"<br />
It is five years since I addressed members of this<br />
distinguished institution. They have been five years of<br />
extraordinary, momentous change. The end of the Cold War<br />
has greatly increased the level of uncertainty in the<br />
world, but as events in Washington on Monday this week<br />
dramatically showed, it has also greatly increased the<br />
level of possibility. The new world order now emerging<br />
is rich with possibilities which could scarcely be<br />
imagined'a decade ago.<br />
within the brief span of the last five years some of the<br />
deepest and most intractable issues of the post-war world<br />
have been put on a path to resolution.<br />
The Soviet Union has ceased to exist, Germany has been<br />
reunited, and we saw on Monday the beginnings of what may<br />
be a permanent peace settlement in the Middle East.<br />
For the first time since 1945, the United States is now<br />
free to concentrate on new challenges in new regions.<br />
my address today concerns one such possibility. I mean<br />
the opportunity presented by the economic advancement of<br />
East Asia the " new Asia" of my title today. For the<br />
centre of gravity in world affairs is moving inexorably<br />
from the Atlantic to the Pacific: and it is in the<br />
interests of both our countries to recognise the promise<br />
the region holds.<br />
in recent years and particularly in the twenty months I<br />
have been Prime Minister a substantial even a<br />
preponderant amount of the Australian Government's<br />
energies have been directed in varying degrees towards<br />
equipping Australia for the Asia-Pacific era which lies<br />
ahead. Equipping it economically, of course, but also as<br />
a society and as a nation. T1EL6:. Sep. 93 10: 21 No. 013 P. 01/ 09 </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
In the five years since I last addressed tis institution<br />
we have taken the reform of the Australian economy Rauch<br />
further# to a point now where it is as competitive as any<br />
in the OECD, and in certain essential respects, such as<br />
the rate of company taxation and incentives for research<br />
and development, comparable to the Asian economies.<br />
There have been profound changes in the shape and<br />
orientation of the Australian economy; namely, towards<br />
sophisticated manufacturing, towards exports, towards<br />
Asia. Equally priofound have been the-~ hdnges to the<br />
business and industrial culture necessary to initiate and<br />
sustain the pace of reform.<br />
But in making these essential changes, the Australian<br />
Government has been determined to ensure that social<br />
policy keeps up with economic change.<br />
We take the view that change comes more effectively and<br />
more rapidly when it comes cooperatively and with a<br />
substantial degree of social consensus. For example, we<br />
won industrial peace, a much more creative industrial<br />
culture, lower inflation and much else through an Accord<br />
between trade unions and the Government.<br />
we have always taken the view that a more competitive<br />
economy should not and does not mean the sacrifice of the<br />
social fabric. on the contrary, we have stuck fast to<br />
basic social democratic principles because we believe it<br />
is in them that the faith of the Australian people lies,<br />
and on that faith our progress depends.<br />
we recognise that the re-orientation of Australia towards<br />
Asia gives rise to a certain amount of apprehension among<br />
Australians accustomed to old European ties and<br />
attitudes. But we go to Asia without compromising our<br />
heritage or our beliefs or our democracy. In fact, we<br />
need to make them stronger.<br />
As a result of policies which might be generically<br />
described by the word " inclusive", we emerged from the<br />
1980s with an economy much more competitive and much<br />
better placed to take advantage of our opportunities: And<br />
with a first class national health system, And a social<br />
safety net the equal of any in the world, An the most<br />
advanced legislation effecting rights and opportunities<br />
for women, An-d a richly pluralist and remarkably peaceful<br />
society. it is in this-broad context that some other recent<br />
initiatives might be seen. We have opened up debate on<br />
the prospect of an Australian Federal Republic because it<br />
would seem to be singularly more appropriate to the<br />
reality of our position in the world, and our national<br />
identity and aspirations. T1E6L:. Seo. 93 10: 21 No. 013 P. 02/ 09 </p>
<p>TEL 3<br />
We are in the process of legislating a new deal for<br />
indigenous Australians because justice is long overdue to<br />
them and because, by delivering justice, we will raise<br />
the level of national unity and notional self -esteem.<br />
we are continuing to actively encourage the development<br />
or a multicultural Australia because, as the United<br />
states well knows, there is enormous strength in<br />
diversity. We are conscious of the fact that the reality of<br />
Australia does not accord with the image of Australia<br />
projected abroad. Pond as we are of our national legend<br />
and our native fauna, we are fonder still of our social<br />
and democratic institutions and values.<br />
You will understand how irritating it can be if you<br />
imagine the United States defined exclusively by coyotes.<br />
By way of a corrective I might quote an article in the<br />
Sydney Morning HaralA earlier this year written by one of<br />
your own -Susan Gaetner, a resident of Manhattan. She<br />
had gone to Sydney in 1991 believing, she said, that it<br />
was a place populated by " rubes and yahoos". She found,<br />
I am pleased to say that the standards of urban chic were<br />
at least as high as her home tows, the health care and<br />
social programs " light years ahead" and the quality of<br />
life " stunningly, resoundingly, overwhelmingly better."<br />
I imagine New Yorkers would find this hard to believe.<br />
More is the pity, so would many Australians. But I should<br />
hope it makes the point Australia is an advanced social<br />
democracy and a complex and modern even post modern<br />
society.<br />
The recession hit us hard in Australia and we have a<br />
major unemployment problem which, in the face of world<br />
recession or feeble recovery, all our efforts so far have<br />
failed to solve. But the reinforcements to the social<br />
fabric we have made have served us very well in binding<br />
Australian society together and making it possible to<br />
maintain the momentum of change and seize the<br />
opportunities which the world, and particularly the<br />
region, offers.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
in Australia, we understood very well when President<br />
Clinton emphasised in last year's campaign that foreign<br />
and domestic policy are now two sides of the same coin.<br />
These days, trade policy most decidedly is high policy.<br />
And there is no more iiiportant focus for trade poli~ cy<br />
than East Asia.<br />
Right round the Western Pacific we watched with great<br />
interest as, step by step, Hr Clinton began to swing<br />
America's interests towards the Pacific. TEL: 1~ 01: 62.1S eNpo.. 9031 6 ru~ u </p>
<p>TEL 4<br />
We saw early on that he recognised the link between the<br />
US budget deficit and its poor trade performance through<br />
the eighties. For the nations of-the Western Pacific,<br />
Mr Clinton's deficit reduction package meant he was<br />
acknowledging that America's trade problems cannot be<br />
solved without change at home.<br />
Then we saw that despite the clamour against it, he<br />
reaffirmed American commitment to the Blair House accord<br />
on world agricultural trade. A little while later, hie<br />
committed his administration to a speedy conclusion of<br />
the Uruguay Round and sought a renewed fast track<br />
authority from Congress to complete the round.<br />
For the nations of the Western Pacific, which have<br />
depended for their growth on an open world trading<br />
system, Mr Clinton's commitment to the Uruguay Round was<br />
good news indeed.<br />
Month by month Mr Clinton continued to confound the<br />
sceptics on our side of the Pacific, and confirmed that<br />
the US was on the right track.<br />
His American University speech at the end of February<br />
recognised the centrality Or Asia and of APEC to a<br />
strategy based on economic growth, increasin<br />
international competitiveness, and stronger trade.<br />
For the Western Pacific, Mr Clinton passed a crucial test<br />
when he successfully sought an extension at China's HFN<br />
status, conditional on human rights tests.<br />
in June, he began to reveal a long awaited package of<br />
proposals for enhancing US excports to Japan and we were<br />
relieved to find that the US would not seek preferential<br />
access, or trade quotas.<br />
Finally in July, in his Waseda University speech in<br />
Japan, Mr Clinton proposed to convene the first meeting<br />
of the leaders of the economies of the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. in mny discussions with the President yesterday we shared<br />
our visions of the future course of the Asia-Pacific<br />
economic community.<br />
The discussions confirmed my belief that the Clinton<br />
Administration has found a path out of the puzzling<br />
uncertainties of the late eighties.<br />
The path out is trade, and it goes west across the<br />
Pacific. Now in all this I believe Mr Clinton was recognising an<br />
unmistakable economic imperative. T1EL6:. Sep. 93 10: 21 No. 013 P. 04/ 09 </p>
<p>EL: 16. Sep. 93 10: 21 No. 013 P. Ut / U'j<br />
South-East Asia is now in the throes of an~ industrial<br />
revolution which is transforming the ASEAN economies from<br />
primary producers to major manufacturing centres.<br />
Manufacturing now accounts for over one-third of their<br />
GDP and around 60 per cent of their exports.<br />
Importantly for Australia, our . near neighbour, Indonesia,<br />
has achieved 25 years of sustained economic development<br />
and transition from one of the world's poorest countries<br />
to one standing on the threshold of the middle-income<br />
group. With the fourth largest population in the world, it is<br />
now launched on a strong growth path.<br />
For the first time in its history, Indonesia has become a<br />
significant industrial exporter.<br />
At the same time, radical reform of the Chinese economy<br />
has unleashed powerful forces of growth and<br />
industrialisation. I visited China in June this year and, particularly in<br />
Shanghai, was impressed by the resurgence of<br />
entrepreneurial drive and skill.<br />
The IMF and others have recently recalculated China's GNP<br />
on a purchasing-power basis.<br />
These calculations suggest that it might be more<br />
realistic to regard China's GNP as three or four times<br />
the official figure, making China already the world's<br />
third biggest economy after the United States and Japan.<br />
Each of the East Asian economies has started from a<br />
different base, with different resources and different<br />
economic circumstances.<br />
But there are common threads running through each story<br />
of success: the determined pursuit of economic growth qnd<br />
social progress, and a willingness to embrace domestic<br />
economic reform and outward-looking trade and investment<br />
policies. in the wake of sustained economic growth, East Asian<br />
societies are being transformed.<br />
Across diverse cultures, there is a common commitment to<br />
modern isation.<br />
There is a high premium on education and technical<br />
training which relate to modern economic sectors, as well<br />
as an international orientation in government and<br />
business. Demand for quality consumer goods, fashion,<br />
entertainment, leisure and travel is steadily growing.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>In developing East Asian economies including those of<br />
South-East Asia a substantial middle class is rapidly<br />
emerging.<br />
This has political as well ' as economic consequences.<br />
East Asian middle classes valui-political stability, but<br />
they also seek greater participation in the political<br />
process. Circumstances vary from country to country, but there is<br />
a welcome overall trend towards political pluralism and<br />
libera lisation.<br />
Indeed, judging by the examples of Korea and Taiwan, one<br />
could argue persuasively that, beyond a certain point,<br />
dynamic and internationally-oriented economic growth<br />
almost certainly requires progressive steps towards<br />
political liberalisation and democracy.<br />
in the cases of China and Vietnam, the question of how<br />
long economic liberalisation can be insulated from<br />
political reform is a fundamental question for the future<br />
of both countries.<br />
I think it should be emphasised to an Asia Society<br />
audience that the United States is benefiting enormously<br />
from the economic dynamic in East Asia and stands to<br />
benefit more as time goes on.<br />
The two sides of the Pacific now form an integrated<br />
market of two billion people, accounting for half the<br />
world's production and halt the worlds trade.<br />
it is a rn~ rket, a production zone, an economic community<br />
which for a decade has grown more rapidly than any other<br />
region of the world, and which is likely to continue to<br />
grow at twice the rate of Europe.<br />
we often think of the European Community as a model of<br />
economic integration. Or we think of the economic<br />
relationship between the United States, Canada and Mlexico<br />
as an example of a naturally integrated group.<br />
certainly these groups are closely integrated, but it is<br />
a surprising fact that the economies of North America and<br />
the Western Pacific are actually more closely integrated,<br />
without a regional trade agreement, than are the<br />
economies of Europe or of North America, with a regional<br />
trade agreement.<br />
man Americans think of East Asia primarily as a source<br />
of Tmports competing with US industry here or in thirdcountry<br />
markets.<br />
Anid certainly, it is true that the us market remains<br />
vitally important for most East Asian economies. </p>
<p>TEL: 16 Sep .93 1 U: 21 NO. VU,) LQ v<br />
7<br />
But over the last decade East Asia, Australia and Niew<br />
Zealand have become an increasingly important market for<br />
US exports. A<br />
Less than a decade ago, more than one third of Western<br />
Pacif ic exports came to the UniLted States.<br />
Today the proportion is less than one quarter.<br />
And over the same time-frame, the proportion of US<br />
exports which go to the Western Pacific has risen to well.<br />
over one quarter, on a par with those to the NAFTA<br />
partners and well ahead of exports to the EC.<br />
Since the mid-eighties the trend rate of growth of US<br />
exports to the Western Pacific has been three times the<br />
rate of growth of Western Pacific exports to the United<br />
States. in other words, East Asia is no longer just a production<br />
2one for exports to the United States it is also a<br />
thriving and rapidly growing importer of US imports.<br />
I believe that the Western Pacific today is your key<br />
market and it is not too much to say that the success<br />
of the United States In the international economy, Its<br />
success as an exporter, its success in regaining its<br />
confidence and belief in itself, depends on its<br />
continuing success in Western Pacific markets.<br />
Australia's trade orientation towards East Asia is even<br />
more pronounced.<br />
Around 60 per cent of our exports now go to East Asia.<br />
Indeed, without any formal arrangements, there is already<br />
closer integration between the economies of North<br />
America, East Asia and Oceania than between either the<br />
members of the EC or the members of NAFTA.<br />
Given the enormous stakes involved on both Bides of the<br />
Pacific, it seems to me important that we think<br />
creatively about what sort of policy and institutional<br />
framework will best maintain and strengthen the highly<br />
valuable economic linkages which now operate between East<br />
Asia, Oceania and North America.<br />
in my discussions with President Clinton in Washington<br />
yesterday, we were in ready agreement that the Asia-<br />
Pacific Economic cooperation or APEC process has the<br />
potential to play a decisive role in this regard.<br />
APEC is already showing great promise as a forum for<br />
promoting economic cooperation on a basis of open<br />
regionalism among the main economies of the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. </p>
<p>TEL: ib. Sep. 93 10: 21 rio.-<br />
APEC'a members are the United Statesi Canada, Japan,<br />
Korea, China, Taiwan, Hong Kong, the six ASEAN countries,<br />
Australia and New Zealand.<br />
But to succeed, this process will " also require close<br />
attention to other aspects of trans-Pacific relations<br />
outside the economic realm.<br />
We need to recognise, for exampfe, that the favourable<br />
strategic circumstances and promising economic outlook<br />
that now obtain in East Asia are partly the result of<br />
enlightened US strategic policy towards the region since<br />
the Second World War.<br />
Judging by the quality of the discussion I was privileged<br />
to have yesterday with the President of the United<br />
States? I am sure your country is sufficiently<br />
imaginative and big-hearted to meet this challenge.<br />
I left my meetings in Washington with a deeper conviction<br />
that Mr Clinton is putting the United States on the right<br />
path.<br />
A path west to the pacif ic.<br />
But at the same time as he resolved to rebuild America's<br />
competitiveness, he has signalled his determination to<br />
rebuild hmerican society as well.<br />
I was encouraged by his commitment to the Asia-Paciric<br />
economic community. And I was struck with the unanimity<br />
with which the President, his Cabinet and the<br />
Congressional leadership in both Houses and both Parties<br />
expressed their conviction that the US should assign a<br />
higher priority to its trading relations with the western<br />
Pacific and the Asia-Pacific economic community.<br />
May I also say that I appreciated the Administration's<br />
high regard for its relationship with my own country.<br />
We also discussed the importance of the Uruguay Round and<br />
the need to have a result by the middle of December a<br />
schedule which in the view of both my Government and the<br />
Clinton Administration leaves no room at all for<br />
reopening the Blair House accord on agriculture.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Tomorrow I go from New York to London: from a, country<br />
which scarcely notices the presence of an Australian<br />
Prime Minister to one whose popular press is driven to an<br />
orgy of insults by his impending arrival. There it was<br />
recently written that I was among other things a<br />
" barbarian" -which in the London tabloids is pretty well<br />
a synony m for Australian that I was bent on taking<br />
Australij towards " some hellish Japanese future": that<br />
the only solution to we hustralians was, to " shoot them<br />
all". rr. 1 Voi n </p>
<p>TEL: 16. Sep. 93 10: 21 No. 013 P. 09/ 09<br />
Ii 9<br />
I expect it will get qult-abusive when I<br />
arrive. I must say my sympathies are fundamentally with<br />
the British people who have to endure a press<br />
like this every day.<br />
Of course Britain remains an important trading<br />
partner, a firm friend, and, as with the United<br />
States, a source of much In the way of culture<br />
and institutions that we value.<br />
The British Foreign Secretary, Douqlas iurd,<br />
has made this very point to the Australian<br />
media in the past day or so.<br />
Certainly, the historical ties between Britain<br />
and Australin are unhrnnknbln. nut tlin ( AImn<br />
changnd a long timo ago, In pursuing tho<br />
possibilities which the Asia-Pacific holds<br />
Australia has simply recognised necessity,<br />
which Is to say the future.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
