<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1669</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO AUSTRLIA BY THE PRESIDENT OF ITALY, SIGNOR GIUSEPPE SARAGAT - SPEECH OF WELCOME BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT AT PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON, CANBERRA, ACT - 26TH SEPTEMBER 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001669.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO AUSTRALIA BY THE PRESIDENT OF<br />
ITALY, SIGNOR GIUSEPFPE SARAGAT<br />
SPEECH OF WELCOME BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD<br />
HOLT AT PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON,<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. 26TH SEPTEMBER, 1 67<br />
President Saragat, the President of the Senate, the Speaker, Ministerial<br />
Colleagues, Your Excellencies, Leader of the Opposition, Senators, Members<br />
and other Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It gives me very great pleasure, as I am sure it does all of<br />
you, to be able to join in this welcome here today to the President of the<br />
Republic of Italy. This is a notable occasion in the life of this Parliament and<br />
indeed it is an historic occasion for the Australian people. This is the first<br />
time that we have been visited by a European Head of State. I don't, of<br />
course, exclude Her Majesty The Queen because I ustralia is part of her<br />
home, and so we don't regard that as an official visit of this sort. But this<br />
is, I repeat, the first time that the Head of State of a European country has<br />
visited us, and it is particularly felicitous that this visit should be made by<br />
the Head of State of a country with which Australia has such warm, friendly<br />
relations and which is of so much significance to us in relation to the building<br />
of our nation and in the trade from the Commonwealth to the rest of the world.<br />
President Saragat is one of the great figures of post-war Europe.<br />
Being President of the Republic of Italy is a signif. cant and eminent<br />
achievement in itself, but we honour him because as we study his record over<br />
the years we find an outstanding degree of courage and of wisdom, of tolerance<br />
and of adherence to democraic principles. Whoever holds the office of<br />
President of the Republic of Italy has a considerable influence extending beyond<br />
the formal limits of his political power, and the President's political record<br />
suggests that he will use his undoubted influence for the benefit of Italian<br />
democracy, for the cause of international co-operation, for peace and<br />
international co-operation for economic progress.<br />
V. e welcome also Signor Fanfani who would have achieved<br />
distinction in his own right if he had not done anything else in the world<br />
but be an outstanding scholar. But in the company of Parliamentarians,<br />
perhaps what will strike us as even more impressive is that on no less than<br />
four occasions he has held the office of Prime Minister of his country.<br />
I question whether we could match that in the life of our Federation here in<br />
Australia. I may say, Mr Fresident, that studying the arrangements which<br />
apply in your Parliament, I found many things to envy, although one or two<br />
which I am glad we have avoided. I envy the fact that you have in your<br />
Parliament a five-year term for Members. The Australian electorate will<br />
not give us this period of grace, and I notice in New Zealand there has<br />
recently been a referendum which has destroyed any prospect of an extended<br />
term in that country. But they also have a provision in Italy that you are not eligible to<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>enter the Parliament until you have attained the age of twenty-five years.<br />
I pointed this disability out to Andrew Jones a little earlier in the day'<br />
On the other hand I gather that the Mfiister of the Government doesn', t<br />
merely have to explain his bills to one House of the Parliament he must<br />
explain it in person to both Houses of the Parliament, and that is an<br />
amendment -which we wouldn't adopt in a hurry in this country.<br />
Our welcome extends also. Senator Oliva and other members<br />
of the President's party.<br />
Italy has for this country a very special significance in a<br />
variety of directions. There is the contribution made through the<br />
centuries to civilisation by the peoples of Italy. Eternal Rome means<br />
eternal Rome not only in Italy itself Rome the Eternal City is Rome the<br />
Eternal City all around the world where men and women are sufficiently<br />
educated to know something of its significance. A~ nd it has a great<br />
significance for us.<br />
There were C'C people last year who visited Italy from<br />
Australia. They weren't all Italians who had settled here returning home<br />
for a visit to the land of their birth. Many of them were Australians,<br />
attracted by the beauty, the cultural feritage, the richness of Rome and<br />
of Italy itself, and we are in your debt for the contribution you have made to<br />
civilisation, Viestern civilisation in particular and to the way of life we enjoy<br />
in our country. But we don't speak of these things in terms of the grandeur<br />
of the past because over modern times the people of Italy have demonstrated<br />
vigorously a lively, inventive, enterprising, innovating spirit which still<br />
burns brightly within them. And you have contributed in these ways in<br />
modern times what we eat, what we wear, what we look at, what we<br />
drive in, what we fly in so many of the asi~ ects of modern, civilised<br />
existence. Perhaps in a parliamentary setting we should acknowledge<br />
the very early recognition given by the Italian people to the importance of<br />
Parliament. I think that the initial SPQR oSenatus Populus Que Romanus<br />
the Senate and the Roman p~ eople which dates right back to the earliest<br />
roeriod of Roman and Italian history, suggests the recognition of the<br />
importance of democratic institutions and the place that the people played<br />
in the life of the government.<br />
The President will be welcome to all Australians because we<br />
feel out own sense of gratitude for the arrival here of some 30C, CCC settlers<br />
from your country since 1'&gt; 45, and I am glad to say that they have produced,<br />
Mr President, between them some 16G, CA" C children since that time!<br />
After the British inflow, Italian migration is actually the<br />
largest migratory movement in the history of this country. It didn't begin<br />
just after the war. It began abott 120 years ago, and many of the Italian<br />
people came to us from the Southern part of Italy and from Sicily. They<br />
found Australia as do the migrant settlers of today a land of opportunity,<br />
with political and economic stability conducive to rapid national development.<br />
They find an envIronment in which they can breathe freely, where their<br />
freedom is assured to them and where there is ample scope for their own<br />
initiative. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Australia's Italian settlers and their children now number<br />
and this may interest our Italian visitors about the same as the citizens of<br />
Florence, Bologna or Venice, which range from Italy's seventh to ninth<br />
cities. The Italians who have come here have settled, prospered and become<br />
part of our way of life. They are making valuable contributions across the<br />
entire continent to industry, trade and development the food we eat, the<br />
clothes we wear, and to our community and cultural life.<br />
It is evident, as you will have gathered from the warmt: h of<br />
the welcome you received yesterday that they preserve a deep affection for<br />
Italy, a pride in Australia and its achievements. They love the land of their<br />
birth and they have an affection for the land of their adoption, and it is<br />
fortunate and certainly felicitous that the new Agreement on Migration will<br />
be announced in the course of your visit, and we are able to report the<br />
establishment, as evidence of our growing relationship of a new consulate<br />
in Milan. But it is not only because of the personal ties that I refer to that<br />
we have warm links with Italy. Both countries rank high among the trading<br />
nations of the world. You in Italy rank eighth, we in Australia twelfth.<br />
Our exports to your country have increased rapidly over recent years. Our<br />
purchases from Italy have trebled over the past ten years from $ 18 million<br />
to $ 53 million. And I have already mentioned the number of Australians who<br />
have visited you in the course of the year and who find Italy a strongly<br />
attractive country from the point of view of their interests.<br />
Our Governments consult at the United Nations on matters of<br />
common interest to the free world. You are a member of the European<br />
Launcher Development Organisation for which we have the privilege of<br />
conducting the operations at our own range at W7oomera.<br />
Your journey, Mr President, has taken you to three countries<br />
already which have derived their democratic institutions from British<br />
Parliamentary democracy, countries which nourish the principles of national<br />
liberty and personal freedom. You will be able to assess for yourself the<br />
value of the contribution which Canada, the United States and Australia are<br />
making to a better world order, the cause of peace and the growth of<br />
international trade. Our people, you will have observed, are primarily of European<br />
extraction, but we have in A; ustralia a special significance for the free world<br />
from our geographical position, and our growing relationships with the countries<br />
of Acia. Even putting it in the material terms of trade, this has grown since<br />
the 1550' s from 15 to 4L per cent. of our total trade.<br />
But the success of our immigration programme is not to be<br />
measured by numbers alone or the additions that are made to our country's<br />
work force. We measure it, as I think you would wish us to measure it, by<br />
the happiness, the prosperity, the progress that our migrants find here in<br />
Australia, and in this as in other ways, we believe Italian settlement has<br />
been among the most successful of all the nationalities to whom we have<br />
given a welcome to this country, and there are more than forty countries<br />
represented in Australia.<br />
Your stay, Mr President, will be brief in Australia. You will<br />
be visiting Melbourne and Sydney before you leave us on Sunday, and as you fly<br />
over much of the country during your journey, you will be able to appreciate for<br />
yourself the vastness of the country, the sparse population and the desirability<br />
on our part of encouraging continuing settlement from good people such as </p>
<p>those that we welcome from your own country.<br />
It is not possible, unfortunately, for anything more than a<br />
fraction of Australia's Italian settlers to see you for themselves, excect<br />
on the television screen, but on behalf of them, and all Australians, all<br />
here wish you a happy and not too strenuous visit and a safe return home.<br />
Your visit will focus an interest on Australia amongst your<br />
countrymen which we believe will be of mutual benefit, of value to the<br />
relationship between us. It cannot fail to add warmth and interest to that<br />
relationship and your presence here itself is a contribution to a deepening<br />
of the warmth and friendliness of the ties that link our two countries.<br />
We hope that italian/ A. ustralian friendship will long endure, and<br />
as it persists, it will go on i. n warmth and strength to the growing mutual<br />
benefit of our two countries.<br />
And now I am going to ask the Leader of Her Majesty's Opposition,<br />
Mr 7,' hitlam, to support me in these words of welcome to you, and this is<br />
one matter at least on which we can find no room for disagreement and can<br />
join in a common vote of sulport and applause.<br />
i, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
