<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>391</transcript-id>
    <title>SOUTH AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES DINNER, ADELAIDE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/11/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000391.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>SOUTH AUSTRALL-IN CHAMBER OF Mii. JF:: CTURES DINNER<br />, ADLLIDETH NOV M3ER J<br />Speech by the Prime Minister the Rt. Hon, R. G. Menzies<br />Sir, Mr. Premier Mr. Leader of the Opposition et hoc genus<br />omne. ( That used to be Latin in my timel)<br />I have hpd a most interesting night tonight. All the<br />time I have e-n saying to myself " ihat should I say?" and having<br />got a rough iaea about it I have then heard this one and that<br />one and the otner one pluck all the food out of the basket, and<br />I find myself left with only the crumbs that fall from the rich<br />man's tablel If I might start at the end, I ' want to say about young<br />Bob Anderson that having heard him tonight in full cry I hope<br />he never gets into the ' enate..., I won't dwell on it any more<br />than that. I beg of him as a frieuid not to becc're a Senator<br />because if he were in my House I could deal with him, but I find<br />it increasingly difficult to deal with Senators I hope you all<br />understand this travail.<br />Then, of course, the Premier who has been a Premier<br />for 23 years, seasoned not a novice like myself who has been a<br />Prime Minister man and boy only for l1~ years made a powerful<br />speech ( as he always does) and he went to some pains to explain<br />to you that South Australia is no longer a claimant State. You<br />know I've been waiting for that for a long time! When I think<br />of all the development that has occurred in this State, when I<br />think how increasingly difficult it is for me to get a majority<br />in this State, I've been waiting for the time when Tom would say<br />" We are no longer a claimant State". But although no longer<br />claimant, you take it from me South Australia is still clamant<br />( Laughter, applause)<br />In my earlier days when I was at school as no doubt<br />quite a few of you were in your own time somebody told 3<br />story, do you remember, about the old Bishop asking about : he<br />Angles and the Saxons who came in after the ancient Britons and<br />he was asked what they were, Angles or Angels a rather<br />difficult problem ( It's like claimant and clamant) and he said,<br />" Non Angli sed angeli". Now that was rather flattering; for<br />them to be converted from Angles to angels was something that<br />required a theological effort on the part of the Bishop. But<br />all that is needed in South Australia to convert South Australia<br />from being claimant into clamant is a characteristically nontheological<br />exercise by the Premier of South Australial<br />( Laughter, applause)<br />Jell, Sir, I've listened in and I've collected rhatever<br />crumbs I could find. I remember being here two years ago I<br />think two years ago. if I rememlber correctly ( but you will<br />correct me, won't you?). I was tolerably popular, I think so,<br />two years ago. And I went away feeling very content because I<br />thought that it was the finest Dinner of any Chamber of<br />Manufactures that I had ever attended in the world. And you<br />know, oddly enough I forgive you for everything you've been<br />saying in the last twelve months I still think sol<br />This is a remarkable occasion, and a remarkable place.<br />I did not know ( so brutishly ignorant am I) that South<br />Australia produced the first Chamber of Manufactures I might<br />have known it. Dear me, I haven't been in Parliament long<br />about 33 years one way and another, but I might have known that<br />all the troubles that I suffer from were bound to begin here!</p>
<p>You know it's ironical to think that in 1869 25 years<br />before I was born the seeds of my present troubles were being<br />scattered in this State! And it is a tremendous thing to<br />reflect that although at that time probably the manufacturers of<br />Melbourne and the free trade manufacturers in Sydney ( as they<br />were at that time) regarded South Australia as being rather<br />brash. It is a remarkable thing to recall that in these last<br />years or to be precise Mr. Premier, in these last 23 years,<br />this State has become a powerful manufacturing State, so that it<br />no longer needs to be looked at as the young brother who is<br />rather speaking nimself, but is, itself, a great<br />rcanufacturi..., -ommunity, a well-balanced community. Not a<br />community that forgets about primary industry because, just as<br />there was a temptation years ago for primary industry to forget<br />about manufacturing, so I want to say to you, never forget about<br />primary industry yourself because I am a believer in the<br />balanced economy of this country.<br />If something happens that is weakening to the primary<br />industries of Australia, the Australian manufacturers will find<br />it more quickly than anybody else. If something happened to<br />restrain the development of manufacturing industry in Australia<br />the man on the land would feel it more rapidly than anybody else,<br />: Je are no longer to engage in the false dichotomy that you are<br />for one or the other I am for both; and I am sure that you are<br />for both. It is the fact that Australia has developed a balanced<br />economy that has made us what we are today in spite of<br />temporary vicissitudes, a powerful and well balanced and strong<br />national economy. But we have problems in front of us. Some reference<br />has been made to the Common Market. I want to say, Sir that<br />I am afraid that an awful lot of people talk about the Common<br />Market just as they might talk about the blessed word<br />" Mesopotamia" without quite knowing what it's about. I<br />receive tLh most earnest letters from the most earnest people<br />who say, " What about a Pacific Common Market?". You know, it<br />sounds grand doesn't it? "' dhy don't we have a common market with<br />Japan and India and South East Asia? This is the answer", to<br />which I always reply that although I am not incapable of<br />certain stupid willingness to engage in a brawl, I wouldn't like<br />to have to look the Australian manufacturers in the eye and tell<br />them that I had established an internal free trade customs union<br />with the countries of Asia. I think that is right enough,<br />isn't it? Here we are, a great trading nation, most of our<br />exports primary products, but a perceptible and growing<br />percentage of our exports manufactured or processed goods, here<br />we are looking at the problem of the European Common Market,<br />lith Great Britain negotiating to go in, tthiet ho ne problem<br />that remains at all times as to the terms on which Great<br />Britain will go in and the terms will be terms that affect<br />first, Commonwealth trade, second, British agriculture, and<br />third, the European Free Trade area because Great Britain has<br />six associates in that area whose interests she must attend to<br />but from our point of view it is the interests of the<br />Commonwealth countries that are of first importance.<br />I am not here to make a prophecy about these matters.<br />All I want to say to you is that ever since the Goverrn-mnt of<br />the United Kingdom departed from the old statement that<br />agriculture was not to be in these negotiaticatns and began a<br />process of negotiation which includes agricultural products, my<br />own Government this is not a Party matter I'm sure that I<br />could speak for everybody in the Commonwealth Parliament has<br />been working on this matter, Ministers, officials, in London,<br />here, with the express purpose of protecting, so far as we can,</p>
<p>the patterns of trade which have made Australia, small as we may<br />be, one of the first ten intern: tional trading nations in the<br />world. I don't think that is always understood, that in<br />absolute terms, not per capita, but in absolute terms, this<br />country of ours in which you have such faith and I have such<br />faith, is one of the first ten international trading nations in<br />the world. ( Applause)<br />We have our own patterns of trade: we sell a great<br />deal to the old country, we sell a considerable amount to<br />European countries: we buy a great deal from the old country<br />and from European cuuntries, and it is our simple but difficult<br />task, to sLu..' for our own interests on these matters -not<br />preferring them to the interests of the peace of the world or<br />the strength of Europe, but as we are bound to do, standing for<br />Australia and Australia's future.<br />Therefore this thing won't come to a head in a day or<br />a week, or a month, or perhaps in two or three nonths and all I<br />want to say to you is ' hat I hope that in all these matters that<br />will be discussed we wi-l be able, whoever may be in office to<br />represent Australia with sanity and good judgment and with he<br />backing of the Australian people with the backing of<br />manufactures with the backing of people who are concerned with<br />growing wheat or butter or meat or wool, or whatever it may be.<br />Because I believe that these negotiations are the most important<br />economic discussions concerning us that will have occurred in<br />the lifetime of any man present tonight. Far more important<br />than the Ottawa negotiations, tremendously important, because<br />here we are witnessing a movement in Great Britain, our mothercountry,<br />which must lead to an enormous integration of the whole<br />of IWestern Europe; which must lead to a powerful association<br />between countries, some of whom have been at war with each<br />other in our own lifetime. And in all these matters we in<br />Australia, while not denying the importance of a powerful Europe,<br />are properly concerned to see that industries built up in our own<br />country on the pattern of British trade are not to be ignored,<br />not to be set on one side, but are to be treated with fairness,<br />with understanding and given some opportunity not just of<br />retreating a little but of expanding in the future.<br />Sir, these are tremendously difficult matters. But<br />there is one other that I would like to say a word about. What<br />do we export from Australia? ' Jell of course we export wool and<br />we export wheat, and we export meat and butter and dried fruits.<br />We export a great number of commodities of that kind and we<br />export some manufactured goods, " Some" growing, growing, I<br />agree, but still only " some".<br />Now why is South Australia no longer a claimant State?<br />Because South Australia has developed secondary industries in<br />balance with primary industries. Why is it that today in<br />Australia we need not fear that another 1929 will produce a<br />disastrous depression? The answer is because today in Australia<br />we stand on two feet ( you quoted my words on this matter, Sir),<br />we stand on two feet. Je are a great manufacturing country,<br />we are a great primary producing country; and if the wind blows<br />cold on the one it doesn't necessarily blow cold on the other.<br />! e have some balance, we can take up the shock. Je couldn't<br />take up the shock in 1929. But if we can't take up the shock in<br />1961 and 1962 then it will be incompetence on our part because<br />have all the foundations for it wre stand on two feet,<br />But in the world of exports we don't not yet, not yet,<br />Why don't we export manufactured goods? Now we've all spoken<br />about this, haven't we, before today and somebody says, " Oh, yes,<br />this is a very good idea, it's a very useful idea". -Je have,<br />within the limits of our imagination and competence done what we</p>
<p>can and we will continue to do more things as we think of them,<br />to develop, to encourage, the export of manufactured and<br />processed goods, But why don't we export more? Is it because<br />we are not as good at making things as they are elsewhere? I<br />don't believe it for a moment. Nobody can go around a great<br />factory in Australia and look at it, see the people on the bench,<br />talk to the people who are in charge, without saying to himself,<br />" But this is magnificent! There is a spirit there is a<br />vivacity in this thing'" Why can't we export? Somebody says,<br />" Well of course there are other countries that have a much bigger<br />turnover" and I if we just sit down comfortably and say,<br />" Jell, he " 71. s more therefore he can produce more cheaply",<br />that will be tne end of the question. I really want to say to<br />you 3entlemen, because I am a seetling mass of confidence in the<br />future of this country I just want to say to you: Don't adopt a<br />defeatist attitude on these matters. It may be that in order to<br />get exports somebody may need to take a little less piofit,<br />somebody may have to achieve exports without profit, or, if you<br />like at some technica] loss. But we will never be a great<br />country in the world, e. oncmically, until we are supplying this<br />massive mar! ret which lies just outside our doors,<br />With all the skill that we have, with all the<br />competence that we have, don't imagine for one moment that<br />because we pay people good wages ( as we should) and 4ive them<br />good conditions ( as we should) that we are contracting ourselves<br />out of the markets of the world. I don't believe it. I think<br />that this business of exporting the products of our factories is<br />the great matter which in the second half of this century will<br />determine the future of Australia. I believe that, I believe<br />that passionately. And if the day comes, not in my time -( but<br />then unlike the Premier I am not immortal!)-these things won't<br />come in my time, I don't very greatly mind that but I would<br />like to cock my ear up from whatever strange place it is that I<br />am in in another 40 years and discover that just as in my own<br />life time Australia stood squarely on primary and secondary feet<br />in her internal economy, sc she had taken her place in the world<br />standing on the same two feet, Because when she does, you see<br />what will happen, Why do we have troubles about the balance of payments?<br />Why do we have our overseas reserves running down? Why do crazy<br />Governments at Canberra get worried about the balance of<br />payments? though importers apparently are not. Why? Why?<br />Because, you see, w e believe and it is an old-fashioned beliefin<br />national solvency. We believe that a nation like Australia<br />ought never to get into a position in which she can't expect to<br />pay her debts abroad her debts for imports as well as other<br />things as they fall due. What we need to do in Austialia is<br />to get over all these fluctuations, which are inevitable in the<br />present picture. Ie can't control the price of wool re can't<br />control whether there is going to be a drcught or noZ and<br />therefore the sales of whbet, we can't control what the world will<br />pay for meat or for butter or for eggs; and as an exporter of<br />primary products we therefore stand right out don't we, in the<br />wind and the weathero If the price level falls then our overseas<br />income falls acutely; and if it falls acutely then we are right<br />up against the problem as to how we are to cut down our<br />expenditure on imports and we get right back to the old<br />argument about tariffs and import licensing and all the rest of<br />it. Now these are important matters, but speaking as the<br />temporary head of the Government of the Commonwealth of<br />Australia for another five weeks speaking in that capacity I<br />want to say to you that I don't like this state of affairs. I<br />would like to think that in due course we could take a</p>
<p>fluctuation in the price of wool we could take a fluctuation in<br />the world price of some primary commodity because we had built up<br />an export income of hundreds of millions in the products of our<br />factories? the products of our mines all these things on which<br />we are doing great and useful exploratory work today.<br />I hope, Sir, that I maake the point that I am trying to<br />make. There can be no avoidance of emergency economic measures<br />so long as the economic emergency is one a-ainst which you have<br />no protection. The right way to get a protection against it is<br />to encourage everybody who manufactures in Australia and I<br />think wvre can do it least as -, ell as anybody else in the worldand<br />to pers every one of them to get into this business of<br />exporting, to get into the business of making people in South<br />cast Asia, or whatever it may be, expect to buy Australian goods<br />because they are Good, because they are vell made, because they<br />have quality, and because they have a price that is competitive.<br />Is this impossible? If I thought it was impossible I<br />must confess I should go home and die in despair. I don't<br />believe it is impossiblf.. When I look back over what has<br />happened in this country of mine and yours in my own lifetime,<br />14hen I see the enormous development that has occurred, the great<br />surge of productive effort, the great increase in living<br />standards, I adopt as my mottc, that " nothing in my country is<br />impossible. ( Applause) And if that is right, and I make bold to<br />say, Sir, that it is right, then the kind of argument that we<br />have engaged in in 1961, 1960, with reserves runningdown and<br />emergency measures becoming necessary, will be looked back upon,<br />in another 20 or 30 years, as a sort of old wives' tale, just a<br />piece of ancient history. Just as we look back on what happened.<br />in 1929, when we didn't stand on two feet in Australia, as a<br />piece of ancient history, why shouldn't our sons look back on the<br />passing problems of 1961 as a piece of ancient history?<br />Here we are growing in population enormously. Does<br />everybody ' n Australia realise that we have received more new<br />citizens into Australia in the last l5 years than America did<br />pro rata in the great age of iimigration into that country? Are<br />we a+ iare of that? Don't we know that here we are living in a<br />country which is increasing its net population rather mor<br />rapidly than Japan is? tJe're a bit inclined to look about us in<br />a melancholy fashion, to think about the problems that this<br />population growth imposes on us. This is a magnificent thing, a<br />proud thing. It means that lO millions today, 20 milliorr then<br />milliorr, we can look at the future with confidence. Am I to<br />be told, or are you to be told, that with that -ro-th in front of<br />us we are incapable of meeting the competition of the world in<br />markets of hundreds of millions of people, with steadily rising<br />standards of living, only a few miles away from us? Sir, I don't<br />believe it. 4hat we need in Australia is a little less wingeing<br />about our temporary troubles, and a great deal more honest belief<br />in ourselves. This is a great country we may have confidence in it.<br />And the first thing to do to have confidence i your own country<br />is to have confidence in yourself. ( Applause</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
