<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3020</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, TO THE ANNUAL DINNER OF THE HEAVY ENGINEERING MANUFACTURERS&#039; ASSOCIATION, LAKESIDE HOTEL, CANBERRA, MONDAY 24 SEPTEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003020.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 9.00 p. m. 24 September 1973 Check against delivery<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E. G. WHITLAM, TO<br />
THE ANNUAL DINNER OF THE HEAVY ENGINEERING MANUFACTURERS'<br />
ASSOCIATION LAKESIDE HOTEL, CANBERRA, MONDAY, 24 SEPTEMBER 1973<br />
Some of you may remember, when we brought down our<br />
Budget, certain commentators describing it as Phase I of the<br />
Government's economic policy. I suppose this occasion will be<br />
branded as Phase IV of our manufacturing policy. Yours is<br />
the fourth manufacturers' dinner I have attended in the past few<br />
weeks. Now at last I am dealing with the heavies.<br />
Let me begin by proclaiming the fundamental community<br />
of interest between the Labor Government and your branch of<br />
industry. Rather, let me proclaim it in your own words.<br />
In one of your recent annual reports I found this passage:<br />
" Since its formation in 1968, the Heavy Engineering manufacturers'<br />
Association has consistently advocated Government-industry<br />
co-operation as the best means of attaining the national<br />
objectives of development, full employment and prosperity."<br />
I accept those words as an accurate statement of our<br />
common policy our shared objectives, our shared methods.<br />
I should add that my Government has been pursuing the same<br />
objectives since its formation in 1972. So we are both, in a<br />
way, fledgling organisations. You can be proud of your<br />
Association's achievements in the past six years. I am equally<br />
proud of the Government's record in the past 10 months.<br />
I return to those three objectives again " Development,<br />
full employment, prosperity". First, consider employment.<br />
There is nothing more central to our common needs, to our common<br />
philosophy, than the maintenance of full employment. You<br />
cannot afford the waste and losses which large-scale<br />
unemployment inevitably brings. We cannot afford them either;<br />
nor can be afford, or tolerate, the social axd political<br />
consequences. We inherited the worst unemployment for 10 years.<br />
We have restored full employment in less than 10 months.<br />
Second, prosperity. I venture to suggest that Australia<br />
is more prosperous today than it has ever been. In saying this,<br />
I do not overlook the vast areas of poverty that remain for<br />
many of our people, and I acknowledge that for such Australians<br />
the very word " prosperity" has a hollow ring. Nevertheless, it<br />
is true that for most of us consumer spending is running at<br />
record levels; profits are higher than ever; world demand<br />
for our exports is immensely strong. And nowhere is this healthy<br />
situation more' manifest than in manufacturing industry. In short,<br />
we have record prosperity. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Your third criterion is development. Let me assure<br />
you that the Government regards the development of strong,<br />
healthy Australian industries as a fundamental, long-term<br />
objective. It is one of our essential and unqualified<br />
commitments and it is reflected, I believe, in every major<br />
policy announcement, every major economic decision we have taken<br />
since coming to office. We are a Government of growth. Our<br />
success, perhaps our survival, certainly the achievement of our<br />
basic social objectives, depends upon the maintenance of strong<br />
and prosperous local industries. We need your strength, we<br />
need your growth, we need your prosperity.<br />
I think you will agree on reflection perhaps even<br />
my friend Senator Cotton will agree that our incentive in<br />
this matter is far more powerful than it was for our predecessors.<br />
It is precisely because we are pledged to certain reforms, to<br />
a program of social change and renovation which the Australian<br />
people entrusted us to carry out, that we are more than ever<br />
determined to maintain and develop the underlying strength of<br />
our industrial economy. Does anyone imagine that my Government<br />
of all governments can be indifferent to the needs of industry,<br />
and epecially of your industry an industry that provides<br />
the know-how and the muscle for important development developmental<br />
projects, for construction, for transport, for shipping or<br />
pipelines, for power supply and generation, for water conservation<br />
projects, for northern development, for vital defence industries<br />
( like light aircraft) that we are determined Australia shall<br />
maintain for herself? ( Now that a certain by-election is<br />
behind us, I might even mention such things as airports.) Of<br />
course your industry's prosperity is essential to us, essential<br />
to our plans, our vision, our whole philosophy. You are the<br />
businessmen, and yours are the industries, that will be needed<br />
to bring many of our plans to fruition.<br />
I give you this further assurance tonight: Nothing<br />
my Government does to correct our economic difficulties either<br />
those we have inherited or those we have imported will be<br />
allowed to jeopardise the fundamental strength of Australian<br />
industry. The very opposite is true. The whole burden of our<br />
attack on inflationary pressures has been through measures<br />
designed to strengthen industry, streamline it, to build up its<br />
efficiency and sharpen its competitive edge. We inherited<br />
a pattern of growing inflation. The great bulk of that inflation<br />
has been due to factors and pressures imported from countries<br />
where inflation is running at a high rate. It is as much an<br />
international as a national problem. There is no simple solution.<br />
But faced with this situation, what did we do? We did not throw<br />
up our hands in despair or bludgeon the economy to a standstill. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
We took prompt and responsible action. We initiated a series<br />
of carefully timed and related steps designed to increase our<br />
level of imports, build up the supply of goods and reduce<br />
domestic prices. We are now seeking a further weapon from the<br />
people direct power over prices. Depending on the attitude<br />
of the Senate, we shall submit that proposal to a referendum<br />
of the people before Christmas or as early as possible in the<br />
new year. That has been our approach a steady, responsible,<br />
coherent attack on the roots of the problem. How easy it<br />
would have been for us, faced with an inflationary problem,<br />
to act as other governments have done, and throw thousands of<br />
Australians out of work. How easy to take refuge in<br />
conventional remedies, despite their futility in the past!<br />
But what would be the effect on industry if we did? Loss of<br />
production, half-empty factories, businesses driven to the wall.<br />
Your industry, as you are all painfully aware, is only now<br />
recovering from the effects of the most recent attempt to<br />
restrain inflation by such means. Again, how easy it would<br />
have been for me and the Treasurer to yield to the clamour of<br />
our critics, the editorialists, the airmchair propagandists,<br />
and cut back on public spending in the Budget. Think of the<br />
plaudits we would have received for acting responsibly. But<br />
think of the consequences. We would have totally abrogated<br />
the trust placed in us by the people. We would have denied<br />
to industry, to you, to manufacturers, the great long-term<br />
opportunities that our program offers for investment and growth.<br />
Let me explain those opportunities. I have pointed<br />
out to manufacturers on other occasions that it is an absurdly<br />
over-simplified proposition to suggest than any increase in<br />
public activity, any widening of the public sector, is<br />
automatically at the expense of the private sector. For example,<br />
in our Budget this year we gave top priority to Education. We<br />
shall provide $ 843 million for Education in 1973-74, an increase<br />
of 92%. But governments do not manufacture the equipment,<br />
make the bricks, install the fittings that make a school.<br />
When governments spend on these items they provide new investment<br />
opportunities for the private investor, new scope for the private<br />
manufacturer. The same opportunities apply to our proposals<br />
in the cities, in hospitals, in transport, in development projects.<br />
When governments take initiatives where none existed before<br />
initiatives that would not otherwise be taken at all it is<br />
private investment and private industry which share in the<br />
benefits of such initiatives.<br />
I have not yet mentioned one great quality of your<br />
industry that commends it to the new Government. That is:<br />
you are an Austrdlian industry, you are overwhelmingly Australianowned<br />
and controlled. You exemplify what we hope to achieve in<br />
other sections of the economy: greater Australian ownership<br />
and control of our industries and resources. Moreover, as you<br />
yourselves have pointed out, the very platform of my party / 4 </p>
<p>recognises the importance of heavy engineering in the achievement<br />
of our national goals. Section 8 states that the party's policy<br />
is to encourage nationally the scientific development of our<br />
national resources through the use of our raw materials and<br />
human skills in the fields of metallurgy, metal fabrication and<br />
engineering. This is to be achieved through Government and<br />
private co-operation in the development of national industries<br />
for the greatest advantage to Australia. Section 5 of the<br />
Platform provides that the Government will protect industry by<br />
whatever means are necessary after thorough examination by an<br />
independent government authority.<br />
Many of the decisions we have taken reflect this<br />
awareness of your special importance, your central role in<br />
Australia's future. We established at the outset a new Department<br />
of Secondary Industry, and, within that Department, an Engineering<br />
Industries Division. You have always emphasised the need for<br />
co-operation between government and industry; so have we.<br />
My colleague Dr Cairns has announced his proposal for " industry<br />
panels" to bring together representatives of industry, government,<br />
the trade unions and consumers to advise on the development<br />
of industries. Your Association has had discussions with<br />
the Department of Secondary Industry on setting up a panel in<br />
the area of heavy engineering. We will strengthen the Australian<br />
Industry Development Corporation and free it from restraints,<br />
to enable it to play its full role in developing Australian<br />
industry and keeping it in Australian hands.<br />
I acknowledge the anxieties you have experienced<br />
recently over our tariff proposals. The Tariff Board completed<br />
a long review of your industry early last year. Our predecessors<br />
accepted the Board's recommendation for protection on the grounds<br />
that you are an efficient, economic industry and a national<br />
asset. I should not wish to dispute that finding for a moment;<br />
I wholeheartedly endorse it. But in-view of your application<br />
for a review of tariff levels in the light of our currency<br />
realignments, I do not wish to anticipate what future assistance<br />
your industry may receive or deserve. As you know, we have<br />
decided to transform the Tariff Board into an Industries Assistance<br />
Commission. It will co-ordinate all forms of aid to industry<br />
and improve the allocation of resources among industries throughout<br />
Australia. It will throw open the whole process of assistance<br />
to public scrutiny. It would be unfair to mislead you at this<br />
stage with predictions of what the new Commission will or will<br />
not do. But I assure you of this: no section ot industry ranks<br />
higher in our estimation, or higher in our priorities, than yours.<br />
I know the measures we have taken against inflation<br />
two revaluations, our 25% tariff cut, our policy on interest<br />
rates are not necessarily the measures you would have chosen<br />
yourselves. Yet I suggest that Australian industry, operating<br />
within a basically sound economy, is in a strong position to<br />
withistand the effects of our measures, and to respond to them<br />
in positive and beneficial ways. As you know, we have undertaken<br />
that the Government will assist any industry adversely affected<br />
by our revaluations or tariff cuts. We have set aside $ 25m to </p>
<p>help industries and employees hurt by our tariff measures.<br />
The latest information I have is that one Australian factory<br />
has claimed assistance. The total number of employees<br />
claiming benefits as a result of our measures is 25 throughout<br />
Australia. Three still remain to be placed in new jobs. That<br />
is how disastrous our measures have been to date. So let us<br />
be realistic. If you have worries or grievances we expect<br />
to hear from you. But we want to hear of specific and detailed<br />
cases. We do not want vague and generalised forecasts of<br />
unspecified calamities.<br />
There is no point in my coming before you pretending<br />
that nothing has changed since last December, or that Government<br />
decisions on which you based your plans and expectations last<br />
year will remain unaltered. You know as well as I do that much<br />
has changed. We have a new department with a new and able<br />
Minister at its head, dedicated to your welfare. New positions<br />
are being created and filled in that department. We are<br />
establishing new machinery for consultation and co-operation<br />
between government and industry. We are establishing new<br />
machinery to assist industry and assess its needs.<br />
I ask you to accept that all our reforms are designed<br />
with one purpose: to strengthen Australian industry. Not to<br />
benefit me, or the Government, but to benefit you and<br />
ultimately the Australian people. We have a new Government,<br />
a vigorous Government, a Government that is likely to be around<br />
for some years to come. I suggest that you accept that reality<br />
and work with us, beside us, for tChe welfare and progress of<br />
our nation. Because you are prudent men, realistic men, and<br />
in the last resort, courageous men, I know it is not in your<br />
nature to shirk the challenge of change and opportunity.,<br />
If I merely wanted to offer you comfort and reassurance, I would<br />
simply remind you, as I have already done, that we have your<br />
interests at heart and will safeguard your security. But I<br />
do more than that. I invite you to accept that our plans for<br />
Australian industry, undertaken now in the context of a sound<br />
and expanding prosperity, will lead us forward to a richer,<br />
more progressive, more exciting future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
