<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5553</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO THE MELBOURNE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005553.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8: 00 pm<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 26 MARCH, 1981<br />
SPEECH TO THE MELBOURNE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE<br />
This is a proud occasion for the Melbourne Chamber of Commerce,<br />
and I am very pleased to have been asked here tonight to<br />
celebrate with you the Chamber's one hundred and thirtieth<br />
anniversary. The Chamber is as old as the State of Victoria<br />
itself,, and during that long life has many achievements of<br />
which it can be proud.<br />
When considering the record of the Chamber, there is one area<br />
which, in iny view, stands out above all others. It is not a<br />
particular action, nor a memorable event. It is a tradition<br />
which has been expressed on many, many occasions in the work<br />
of the Chamber. I am referring to the Chamber's long support<br />
for the principle of freedom of enterprise.<br />
Freedom needs not only to be defended abroad, but at home as<br />
well, and the Chamber of Commerce has been a powerful voice<br />
over the last one hundred and thirty years for, the principle<br />
of freedom in economic life. That-" this expresses the commercial<br />
interests of the members of the Chamber in no way detracts<br />
from the value of the Chamber's role. In fact, it is the best<br />
security that the Chamber will continue in this role.<br />
I have no hesitation in saying that the Chamber's defence of<br />
freedom in commercial life has been an important element in<br />
preserving politica41 democracy in Australia. For while economic<br />
freedom does not guarantee political freedom and political<br />
democracy, I know of no free state that has survived without Ea<br />
substantial measure of freedom in economic life..<br />
The fre 6dom to set up a business, to trade, to identify needs'<br />
and to meet them supports political freedom in many ways.<br />
Economic freedom ensures that there are people of independent<br />
voice to advise and to check Government,, people who have the<br />
resources and the skills to organise to defend their point<br />
of view. Freedom-. means that power in a community is not<br />
concentrated in a few hands, but is shared so that the power of<br />
some checks the power of others. The history of the Chamber<br />
well illustrates that fact.<br />
At various times the Chambe of Commerce has campaigned<br />
strongly and effectively against efforts to concentrate<br />
economic power in the hands of the Government. Free enterprise<br />
does not only mean freedom for entrepreneurs. Just as important,<br />
it also means freedom for consumers. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Under conditions of market freedom, individuals have more power<br />
than under any other form of economic or'ganisation. In a market<br />
economy individuals can chooose where they will work, and for<br />
whom; what they will buy, and when. ' Businesses and governmentsmay<br />
sometimes feel uncomfortable with their deci-sions, but<br />
individual people are the ones who benefit. In exercising<br />
their freedom to choose, they create over time an economy and<br />
a society which is more likely to adjust to their needs than<br />
one which jis. centrally. controlled.<br />
While we celebrate tonight an organisation which has given<br />
strong support to our great democratic tradition, we would doo,<br />
well to remember that in other parts of the world men and<br />
women are still struggling to establish that freedom. In<br />
Poland tonight heroic people are striving to grasp the freedom<br />
that has been ours for more than a century.<br />
Excessive power in the hands of government stops people from<br />
effectively realising their own values, and inevitably leads<br />
to economic stagnation and social conflict; but any rela, , ation<br />
of that power gives to others a greater capacity to challenge<br />
that regime. When we look around the world at those countries<br />
which have shown a marked degree of economic success and<br />
sustained often spectacular rates of economic growth, we<br />
find that they are, virtually without exception, countries<br />
with a large measure of freedom for entrepreneurs and consumers<br />
in economic life.<br />
From the Nineteenth Century England ( and Australia), to the<br />
United States, the post World War II German miracle, to the.<br />
more recent miracle of Japan, and increasingly the ASEAN<br />
countries, we find that the free market economy has been the key<br />
to rapidly rising standards of living for ordinary people.<br />
Government has a vital role in establishing the framework of<br />
rules-' for a free economy. But if it taxes too much, spends too<br />
much, borrows too much, it can crowd out private enterprise and<br />
abtually undermine prosperity. The recognition of the importance<br />
of giving encourag~ nent to private enterprise and room for it to<br />
grow has lain at the heart of the economic strategy we have<br />
followed since 1975. The growth we see around us today -the<br />
prospects Australia now has before it are, I believe,<br />
fundameptally the result of policies based on that recognition.<br />
Our policies have sought to rein in Government spending and cut<br />
back on the deficit-so that competition between governments and<br />
private enterprise for scarce resources has been reduced.<br />
Our objective, moreover, has been to achieve these aims by<br />
expenditure restraint, not by imposing higher levels of taxatiLon.<br />
We need lower, not higher, taxes.<br />
It follows that efforts towards spending restraint at all<br />
levels of government must be doubled and redoubled. In that<br />
way, private enterprise wifl have the stimulus and the room to<br />
grow, and consumers will have increasing capacity. to spend the<br />
incomes they earn in the way that they see fit. / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
Governments can also impinge on the freedoms of individuals<br />
and businessmen through wasteful and ine~ ficient regulations.<br />
But the opportunities available to business in a free enterprise<br />
system are accompanied by inevitable risks. The possibility<br />
of profit, of innovation, of great achievement is matched by<br />
the possibility of loss. There has always been, and I suppose<br />
always will be, * a tendency when business is down to seek<br />
additional assistance and protection from Government to<br />
reduce the risks of competition in the interests of securit3K<br />
The Government is'well awar~ e of the legitimate claims of<br />
private enterprises for certainty and predictability in the<br />
economic environment. But we also need to recognise that<br />
Australian enterprise will not become strong on Government<br />
granted privileges, but in facing up and surmounting the<br />
challenges of a competitive economy. We are first and foremost<br />
a Government which believes that consumer interests and consumer<br />
decisions must be dominant determinants of the allocation<br />
W of resources among business enterprises. There is no cauge<br />
for apprehension on this score for Australian business Mis<br />
increasingly demonstrating that it has the capacity to hold<br />
its own with any in the world.<br />
Freedom, of course, has another side responsibility. A<br />
free society, and a free economy, will only work to the<br />
satisfaction of citizens, if freedom is exercised with<br />
responsibility. There are two areas in particular where our freedoms are under<br />
threat from those who ignore their responsibilities to their<br />
fellow citizens. The first I will--mention is tax avoidance<br />
and evasion. Some of the schemes which have been revealed<br />
in recent times must be viewed not only as the avoidance of tax,<br />
but as a tot~ al rejection by their beneficiaries of all<br />
obligation to support community services. Whatever the letter<br />
of the law may have been, its spirit has been wounded by those<br />
who have-sought to evade their obligations to their fellow citizens.<br />
L_<br />
The strength of a community should not be measured by the<br />
tightness of its laws and the stringency of its law enforcement,<br />
but rather by the recognition of the obligations we all have -to<br />
each othe-T. The community's intolerance of tax ' avoidance and<br />
evasion' is becoming increasingly obvious. And the Government is<br />
determined to eliminate such schemes by law. But from a<br />
broader standpoint, the need for such action is already<br />
an admission of defeat.<br />
There are many hilndreds of people here tonight who can truly<br />
be said in their own walks of life to be leaders in the community.<br />
The responsibility falls on all of us, in Government and in<br />
private enterprise, in public and in private, to stand for those<br />
codes of behaviour which strengthen, not corrode, the faith of<br />
people in their community., The selfish pursuit of private gain<br />
at the expense of the community erodes that faith?, and leads to<br />
demands for even more stringent laws. / 4 </p>
<p>* 6 -4-<br />
I am confident that I can call upon you-, the Melbourne Chamber<br />
of Commerce, for support in the caxnpaign'to re-establish that<br />
firm sense of community obligation which'dis the only solid<br />
foundation for a free society.<br />
There is another area, also, in which freedom is under<br />
challenge in Australia today. This challenge comes from<br />
militant trade Unions who strike to achieve financial gain or<br />
shorter hours or both for themselves regardless of the<br />
costs and hardship they impose on their fellow citizens.-<br />
In the Qantas dispute, we saw thousands of Australians strandd<br />
overseas because a few trade unionists claim the right to<br />
force acceptance of their demands. We have seen Sydney's<br />
beaches gflooded with sewage as a deliberate tactic by. a few<br />
to coerce their fellow citizens. Some extremists in the trade<br />
union movement now seem to be claiming an untramelled right<br />
to exploit their fellow citizens and to cause needless suffering<br />
if this will advance their pursuit of power.<br />
No decent community can accept such behaviour nor. I belfeveis<br />
it supported by the great bulk of trade union members. Once<br />
again, we will act against it with the full force of the law.<br />
But abiding by the law, being within the letter of the law, is,<br />
not the end of responsibility or moral obligation. If every<br />
wrongful act has to be proscribed by law we are going to be<br />
overriden by rules and regulations.<br />
One of the great strengths of the Australian people has always;<br />
been the sense of decency and respect for others, the desire<br />
to assist those in need, to lend a helping hand, to do the<br />
right thing by other people. The tax evader who imposes added<br />
burdens on other people, the union official who disregards the<br />
impact of his actions on others, are equally guilty, of<br />
breaking this code of behaviour. I simply do not believe that<br />
most decent union members support campaigns which inflict<br />
hardship and loss on their fellow citizens.<br />
The solution here 14es in the courage of those union leaders<br />
and members who see that this is the time to take a stand, who<br />
are prepared to work to change attitudes. Free trade unionism,<br />
like free enterprise, is a fundamental el~ ment in a free society.<br />
Exploft~ tive unionism, like exploitative business, is an attack<br />
on freedom and shows the need throughout the community for a<br />
strengthened awareness of our community obligations. We are<br />
all Australians and-we need to act with a clear recognition<br />
of that fact.<br />
it is to the great credit of the Melbourne Chamber of Commerce<br />
that it has taken its responsibilities to the community seriously.<br />
The toast to the Chamber is not only a toast to a-long existence;<br />
it is much more a toast to an organisation which has proudly<br />
defended sojme of the great traditions of Australians.<br />
Your Excellency, Mr. Premier, ladies and gentlemen, I ask you to<br />
rise and charge your glasses in a toast to the Melbourne Chamb3er<br />
of Commerce on its 130t * h anniversary. Long may it prosper.<br />
To the Melbourne Chamber of Commerce. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
