<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11186</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH JOHN GATFIELD, SKY NEWS                           </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: republic referendum; constitutional preamble; Rugby World Cup</p>
<p>   final; cricket Test.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE............</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, welcome to Sky News.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Very good to be with you John.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>Well as you're aware, the latest polls suggests that a majority of Australians</p>
<p>   do favour a republic, but not this particular model being put at the referendum</p>
<p>   tomorrow. That I suppose leaves you in the minority. Are you feeling at</p>
<p>   all uncomfortable with that?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I didn't know that the polls were saying that. But John I don't take</p>
<p>   too much notice of polls these days after the experience of the Victorian</p>
<p>   election. This is going to be a very tight result. I don't believe that</p>
<p>   the Australian people should vote for the republican model on offer tomorrow</p>
<p>   because I don't think it would deliver a better constitution. I think in</p>
<p>   some respects it would deliver in a difficult time a less safe and predictable</p>
<p>   constitution than the one we have at the moment. And after all, the onus</p>
<p>   is on those who want change to persuade us that it will be a change for</p>
<p>   the better. We are already an utterly independent country and I see no virtue</p>
<p>   at all in taking a punt on a model that has a lot of flaws in it, has drawn</p>
<p>   a lot of criticism, and clearly won't deliver a president who is as secure</p>
<p>   in his or her tenure of office as is the Governor-General under the present</p>
<p>   constitution.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>Why do you say that the president would not be as secure as the Governor-General</p>
<p>   is now?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well because he can be removed at the immediate whim, without any process</p>
<p>   of formal application, consultation etceteras, by the Prime Minister of</p>
<p>   the day. There's no republican constitution in the world that has a removal</p>
<p>   provision like that.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>But in some senses don't you have to have that to avoid the conflict, the</p>
<p>   potential conflict between the powers of Prime Minister and the powers of</p>
<p>   a president?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we don't have that conflict now.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Because the Governor-General doesn't have those same powers.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no. The Governor-General in an extreme constitutional difficulty does</p>
<p>   as we found in 1975. But he does it in a way that remits the whole issue</p>
<p>   to the public for a decision. I mean the very fact that 24 hours from the</p>
<p>   referendum these things are still being discussed and are still in doubt,</p>
<p>   underlines the fact that we are being asked to vote for something that could</p>
<p>   leave us in a difficulty. I'm not saying each day because any old constitutional</p>
<p>   will work when there's no problem there's no conflict. But an arrangement</p>
<p>   that could in a difficulty leave us with a less secure and predictable way</p>
<p>   of resolving it.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  But under the proposed model doesn't the Prime Minister have to go back</p>
<p>   to Parliament and get approval from Parliament?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Yes but he'd almost certainly get that because he's Prime Minister because</p>
<p>   he leads the majority party in Parliament. But even if Parliament were unexpectedly</p>
<p>   to say no the president would still remain dismissed. There is no provision</p>
<p>   for the reinstatement of the president. He or she remains dismissed full</p>
<p>   stop.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>There is this suggestion that a no vote if successful tomorrow will leave</p>
<p>   this country more divided than if the yes vote got up.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think that is a self-serving argument coming from the republicans.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>Well actually it comes from Peter Costello today.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Peter and I are on different sides of this argument, although I respect</p>
<p>   the way he put his case as he does respect the way I've put mine. But look,</p>
<p>   the outcome will be accepted by the Australian people whatever it is. I</p>
<p>   mean the Australian public once it's decided this issue will then move on.</p>
<p>   And this idea that in some way there's going to be great discontent if the</p>
<p>   yes vote fails, I think with great respect to those who want the yes vote,</p>
<p>   it's an attempt to sort of, you know, persuade by coercion and intimidation</p>
<p>   people into voting yes. I mean it's perfectly.if people have any doubt about</p>
<p>   this thing they should say no and it's perfectly legitimate for Australians</p>
<p>   to do that and they shouldn't be warned that there's going to be division</p>
<p>   and so forth by the republicans. There won't be any division. Australians</p>
<p>   will accept the result. I will accept the result if it goes yes. If it goes</p>
<p>   no everybody else will accept the result. There'll be disappointed people.</p>
<p>   People have poured a lot of energy into the debate on both sides will obviously</p>
<p>   be disappointed if it goes against them. But we are engaging in a great</p>
<p>   democratic process which drives home the point that we are an utterly independent</p>
<p>   country because here we are 24 hours out and we have the capacity to say</p>
<p>   yes or no to this change. There couldn't be a greater demonstration of our</p>
<p>   total and complete independence.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  With respect, surely if the no vote succeeds tomorrow the debate is not</p>
<p>   going to go away because Ted Mack today, the independent MP..former independent</p>
<p>   MP who's voting no because he believes in the direct election model, he</p>
<p>   is saying that if it goes down tomorrow there will be a campaign for another</p>
<p>   plebiscite, for a plebiscite at the next federal election in which he would</p>
<p>   expect the question to be do we want a republic or not?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well in a democracy any citizen or group of citizens has a perfect right</p>
<p>   to agitate for anything they want. And I haven't said and I'm not saying</p>
<p>   to you today that if there's a no vote people will stop arguing the case</p>
<p>   for a change, of course they won't, that's a democracy. What I'm saying</p>
<p>   is that I think the mood of the public will be that the matter won't come</p>
<p>   back in a hurry but I can't say that it will never come back. I'm not arguing</p>
<p>   that. I've never said that. I'm trying to be honest with people about the</p>
<p>   consequences of either outcome. If there's a yes vote then there, in my</p>
<p>   view, will be no chance of people ever having a vote on a directly elected</p>
<p>   President because the great bulk of parliamentarians in both parties are</p>
<p>   against a directly elected presidency and I don't think they'd ever put</p>
<p>   a referendum for that up. On the other hand, if there's a no vote I think</p>
<p>   the issue, people will want the issue to go away for a while. They will</p>
<p>   have had a say but that doesn't mean that at some time in the future people</p>
<p>   mightn't argue that it come back. But that is a democratic process. You</p>
<p>   can't have a situation where you say, for all time this is a one and only</p>
<p>   vote. I mean, nobody can ever say that about anything. I can only express</p>
<p>   a view as to how I think the public and the political parties will react</p>
<p>   to either of the two possible outcomes.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Are there circumstances under which you would consider going to the next</p>
<p>   Federal election for the plebiscite on the republic?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well look, I think it is absurd of me to try and answer questions like that</p>
<p>   when we don't even know the result of tomorrow. I mean, people should ask</p>
<p>   me about the future after we know the result of tomorrow. I don't presume</p>
<p>   that tomorrow is going to be a no vote. I don't know what the result is.</p>
<p>   I think it will be very close. I do hope that there's a yes vote on the</p>
<p>   preamble. I think the preamble is the one opportunity tomorrow where all</p>
<p>   Australians can come together. Those who are republican and those who are</p>
<p>   anti-republican, they can combine to say yes to a statement of common Australian</p>
<p>   values including, in particular, the reference to the indigenous people</p>
<p>   of this country - the first decent, positive, noble, gracious reference</p>
<p>   to them in our Constitution.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  I'll come back to the preamble in just a moment but just looking at that</p>
<p>   question of a possibility of another plebiscite, are you saying that it's</p>
<p>   foolish then for people like Ted Mack to say that, yes, we could have another</p>
<p>   vote at the next election?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, no, you're asking me whether something would be part of Coalition policy</p>
<p>   at the next election. What I'm saying to you is that I will talk about the</p>
<p>   future after tomorrow.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  But it's just that people like Ted Mack are holding that out as a great</p>
<p>   possibility.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  But nothing I will say will stop Ted Mack arguing that.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  No, but if you said there's no chance of having a plebiscite that would</p>
<p>   kill his argument.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I'm not going to start answering hypothetical questions at this point. The</p>
<p>   first I'd heard that he'd argued that. But look, our view is very simply,</p>
<p>   John, that if there's a yes vote I don't think there's any hope of there</p>
<p>   ever being a referendum on a direct election because the great bulk of people</p>
<p>   in both parties are against that. And I think once the republicans got a</p>
<p>   republic they wouldn't want to then give the people an opportunity of changing</p>
<p>   the type of republic we have. I think that really is a pipe dream. If there's</p>
<p>   a no vote I think the mood will be, look, we've had a debate, the people</p>
<p>   have spoken, let's get on with other things but there will always be some</p>
<p>   people in the community who will want to argue for further consideration</p>
<p>   of it. And I understand that but I can only answer the question as faithfully</p>
<p>   and as best I can and that is my feeling. The mood of the country will be,</p>
<p>   look, we've had a lot of debate on this, spent a lot of money on it, let's</p>
<p>   just give it a rest for a while. But that doesn't mean to say that in the</p>
<p>   future people mightn't revive it and argue for it and I can't say for all</p>
<p>   time we're never going to have another vote. I've never said that and I</p>
<p>   can't, it would be stupid of me to say that.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  One of the interesting things about the polls so far anyway, it suggests</p>
<p>   that younger people, the 18 to 24 year-olds, are supporting your case, they're</p>
<p>   supporting the Constitutional Monarchy. Is that something that surprises</p>
<p>   you and is it reflected in your own family?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I prefer not to talk about my family. They're young adults and if</p>
<p>   people want to know their views they should ask them. A good way to preserve</p>
<p>   a good relationship with your kids is never presume to speak on their behalf.</p>
<p>   They're very intelligent young adults and they've got their views and they're</p>
<p>   entitled to them. Can I say that it doesn't entirely surprise me. I think</p>
<p>   young people are unmoved by this debate. I saw an interview last night with</p>
<p>   a panel on Lateline and David Malouf, the author, made a very powerful</p>
<p>   point when he said that this has not been a grassroots movement. This idea</p>
<p>   that you can bring about a change like this by, in effect, brow-beating</p>
<p>   people from the top into accepting it by a sort of celebrity cavalcade,</p>
<p>   an avalanche of names, I don't think that wins the hearts and minds of people.</p>
<p>   If you really are to find a genuine desire for change in a big way on something</p>
<p>   like this it has got to come out of the spirit and out of the grassroots</p>
<p>   of the people. And I think that younger section of the age group who are</p>
<p>   very savvy, they are very switched on, and I think they, sort of, feel that.</p>
<p>   Now, that's not to say a lot of them won't vote yes. A lot of them will</p>
<p>   vote yes, a lot will vote no. But there was a mistaken assumption made by</p>
<p>   republicans that because this was a change then the young would automatically</p>
<p>   support it. They are not quite like that. They are interested in outcomes</p>
<p>   and, I think, many of them are unpersuaded that the outcome of this will</p>
<p>   be a better Australia.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Now, let's come back to the preamble for a moment, and I know you are a</p>
<p>   passionate supporter of that, is there a danger that it might go down and</p>
<p>   what dangers are there for us as a society if it is defeated?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't think there is any danger for the society if it's defeated.</p>
<p>   But I think it would be a great pity if it does go down because this is</p>
<p>   an opportunity for the whole country to say yes to something that encapsulates</p>
<p>   some commonly held Australian values, recognises the contribution of immigrants,</p>
<p>   the contribution of our veterans, the contribution of Aboriginal and Torres</p>
<p>   Strait Islanders as the first people of the nation. This will be the first</p>
<p>   time they have been referred to in a positive way in the Constitution. And</p>
<p>   it will, if passed, it will make a contribution towards reconciliation and</p>
<p>   I think that is a first class thing and I'll be very disappointed if it</p>
<p>   goes down.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  That, I guess, is the danger then, if it does go down it fails to move on</p>
<p>   towards reconciliation.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I don't think reconciliation is conditional upon this being carried</p>
<p>   but I think if this is carried it will be very good news for reconciliation.</p>
<p>   So if you really care about reconciliation you ought to get behind the preamble</p>
<p>   in a big way.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  I notice in one of today's papers there was a letter saying "let's</p>
<p>   vote down the preamble because this is badly written, let's have another</p>
<p>   go. This is just the first effort."</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I can understand some people saying that but you will never get total</p>
<p>   agreement on the wording of something like this. I think you have total</p>
<p>   agreement though on the values and I think that is very important. And,</p>
<p>   of course, as you said immigrants in particular have . Meg Lees has supported</p>
<p>   this one too. She says that it's so important that we should acknowledge</p>
<p>   the contribution that migrant groups have made to Australia.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, it's the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders, migrant groups, our</p>
<p>   common commitment to the rule of law, the equality of people before the</p>
<p>   law, the equality of men and women, the contribution of those who died defending</p>
<p>   this country. All of those things are an important part of the Australian</p>
<p>   story and it will be very nice if this version of the Australian story were</p>
<p>   adopted into our Constitution.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  It does seem though that discussion on the preamble has been somewhat lost</p>
<p>   amongst the republican debate though?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I guess it was inevitable that the republican debate would dominate the</p>
<p>   airwaves and that was inevitable and unavoidable. But equally to hold a</p>
<p>   separate referendum on the preamble alone would have been criticised by</p>
<p>   many people as being too expensive. And it seemed logical to link the preamble</p>
<p>   with the republican referendum. And I don't know how else one could have</p>
<p>   done it. I think if I'd have had a separate referendum on the preamble people</p>
<p>   would have said: well, this is a terrible waste of money, why don't you</p>
<p>   link it with some other change. And, you know, we are back to where we are</p>
<p>   now.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Just changing the subject slightly now and what we hope is good news. Australia</p>
<p>   started the first Test well in cricket, of course, and we have the World</p>
<p>   Cup Rugby coming up on Saturday night. You must be hoping for a dual success.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I certainly hope for a no vote but as far as rugby is concerned I</p>
<p>   will unite with Australian republicans and anti-republicans alike in cheering</p>
<p>   the Wallabies. I stayed up to watch the game last week and can I just say</p>
<p>   to John Eales and all the boys in Cardiff: good luck, I'll be there cheering</p>
<p>   in the early hours of Sunday morning. And I think they'll give a great account</p>
<p>   of themselves. And it'll be tough. The French played very well, but we have</p>
<p>   superbly risen to the occasion. And all our thoughts and barracking and</p>
<p>   cheers will be with the Wallabies on Sunday morning.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  And I suppose a little bit of trans-Tasman rivalry doesn't go astray when</p>
<p>   we know that the Springboks have beaten New Zealand into fourth place today.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, I don't want to get into that. I am only ever interested in Australia</p>
<p>   winning, I don't really mind who has the runner-up places.</p>
<p>  GATFIELD:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister John Howard thank you very much for joining us on SKY News.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
