<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4094</transcript-id>
    <title>PREMIERS&#039; CONFERENCE - 9 APRIL 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004094.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS APRIL 9, 1976<br />
PREMIER'S CONFERENCE<br />
The Commonwealth and State Governments today made piogress<br />
and agreement on a wide range of Federal issues, including<br />
the principles of a new tax sharing arrangement with the States.<br />
T~ ne meeting was a highly successful working conference on<br />
a number of difficult and fundamental issues, at which progress<br />
was possible because of the cooperative and understanding<br />
attitude adopted by all who took part.<br />
The Conference made a firm decision that local government<br />
would participate in the new tax sharing arrangements as<br />
from 1976/ 77. We agreed to establish State Grants Commissions<br />
in those States which do not already have such a Commission.<br />
There will be a further meeting with the Premiers in June.<br />
At this Conference it is hoped to be able to give an indication<br />
of the assistance which local government might expect to<br />
receive under the new arrangements in 1976/ 77.<br />
As a result of todays meeting there is a strong feeling of<br />
confidence that the June Premier's Conference will lead to<br />
agreement on implementing the new tax sharing system in<br />
1976/ 77.<br />
Details of issues on which agreement was reached are contained<br />
in an attached document.<br />
Working parties of Commonwealth and State bfficials will beset<br />
up, and will report to the June Premier's, Conference.<br />
Todays ieeting also resulted in agreement establish an<br />
Advisory Council on Intergovernmental Relations. The proposed<br />
charter for this Council is also attached to this statement.<br />
The Commonwealth Government will introduce the apprcpriate<br />
legislation to establish the Council during the current<br />
parliamentary session. </p>
<p>ATTACI HMEN T<br />
PERSONAL INCOME TAX SHARING ISSUES SETTLED BETWE'EN<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH AND STATE GOVERNMENT FOLLOWING MEETING<br />
ON FRIDAY 9 APRIL 1976<br />
Following is a very brief summary of issues which have<br />
been settled:-The scheme will be related to personal income tax<br />
not company tax and not including withholding taxes on<br />
interest and dividends.<br />
The scheme will be introduced in two Stages.<br />
Stage 1 Stage 1 will be introduced as from the beginning of<br />
1976-77.<br />
' The States' entitelements under Stage 1 will<br />
represent a specificed. percentage of Commonwealth<br />
imposed personal income tax and State legislation<br />
will thus not be required in regard to State 1.<br />
The " base: to which the percentage will be applied each<br />
year will be personal income tax collection in the year.<br />
The percentage figure will be cater-mined by reference<br />
to the relationship between the financial assistance<br />
grants in 1975-76 and personal income tax collections<br />
in that year.<br />
Personal income tax collections in the Territories<br />
will be included in the base figure but with this<br />
subject to review in the light of developments<br />
in public finances in the Territories. </p>
<p>2<br />
The yield or costs of special surcharges or rebates<br />
applied, in appropriate circumstances, by the<br />
Commonwealth will not be included in the base figure<br />
from which the States' entitlements will be calculated.<br />
There will be a " guarantee" arrangement to ensure<br />
that the States' Stage 1 entitlements in any year are<br />
not less, in absolute terms, than in the previous year.<br />
This arrangement will be supplemented in the first three<br />
years of the new scheme 1976-77, 1977-78 and<br />
1978-79) by a further undertaking that the entitlements<br />
will not be less in a year than the amount which would<br />
have been yielded in that year by the financial<br />
assistance grants formula as laid down in the States<br />
Grants Act 1973-75.<br />
A total entitlement for all States will first be<br />
determined, to be then divided between the States<br />
The initial per capita relativities between the States in<br />
their Stage 1 entitlements will be the relativities in<br />
the financial assistance grants in 1975-76.<br />
( 11) Subject to ( 13) below, and to any absorption of specific<br />
purpose payments, these relativities will be carried </p>
<p>forward into subsequent years in such a way as to<br />
maintain the proportionate relationships between the<br />
per capita entitlemients of the States.<br />
( 12) hne four less populous States will continue to be free<br />
to apply for grants on the recormnendation of the Grants<br />
Commission in addition to their basic entitlements ayielded<br />
under the arrangements suimLarised above.<br />
( 13) There will be a periodic review of relativities between<br />
all States.<br />
Stage 2<br />
( 14) Under Stage 2 each State will be able to legislate to<br />
impose a surcharge on personal income tax in the State,<br />
( but not company<br />
taxation or withholding tax on dividends and interest)<br />
additional to that imposed by the Co. monwealth, or to<br />
give ( at cost to the State) a rebate on personal income<br />
tax payable under Corrnonwealth law and to authorise the<br />
Commonwealth to collect the surcharge or grant<br />
ebate as its agent.<br />
Any State surcharges or rebates will be expressed in<br />
percentage terms.<br />
( 16) Assessment provisions, and the basic income tax rate<br />
structure, will continue to be uniform throughout<br />
Australia, these being r?. a tters for thR<br />
to determine. </p>
<p>4<br />
( 17) The Cori-on. wealth will at all. tim: es remain the sole<br />
collecting and administrative ageiicy in the income tax<br />
field.<br />
( 18) The level of any State surcharges or rebates ill be a<br />
matter for consideration by each State; relevant<br />
decisions will be taken within an appropriate framework<br />
of consultation with the Commonwealth and other States,<br />
but ultimately the level of surcharge or rebate will be<br />
a decision for each individual State. In exercising<br />
. these nowers the States will accept responsibility to<br />
work in parallel with and not in negation of the overall<br />
economic management policies of the Cormonwealth.<br />
( 19) Equalisation arrangements will be made so that less<br />
populous States will be enabled to obtain the same<br />
relative advantage from a surcharge as the States with<br />
a broader tax base.<br />
The Grants Commnission will be responsible for assessing<br />
amounts payable under the arrangements referred to under<br />
( 19).<br />
( 21) An officers' working party will be established to<br />
foraulate detailed proposals to implement Stage 2. The<br />
firm target is to have an appropriate framework<br />
established, relevant matters agreed and necessary<br />
legislation prepared in time for Stage 2 to commence from<br />
the beginning of 1977-78. </p>
<p>( 22) At an appropriate time thfe Co-innlonealth will consider<br />
what ilicat ions Stage 2 might have in relation to Llh'<br />
Territories.<br />
Local Government Assistanice<br />
( 23) Ther-e will be a new scheme of local goverrnment.<br />
assistance, beginning in 1976-77, un-der which such<br />
assistance, to be distributedi th-rough the Statas, will be<br />
related to the yield of Coifwmonwealth personal incoim-. Lax.<br />
( 24) T'he arou-nt of such assistance in 1976-77 will be<br />
determined by the Comnonwealth Government having<br />
to its overall budget considerations.<br />
Imlications -for TLax; 7 Fo-rms and Assessment Notices<br />
In relation to tax forms, chang:, es will be minimal apart,<br />
from necessary changes to take account of surciiarges or<br />
rebates.<br />
( 26) Assess-: 2ent notices will be changed only to accom. nodate<br />
State surcharges or rebates ( any Co-n-oonaealth surcharge<br />
or rebate would, of course, also be shoTin), wit<br />
in-formiation on disposition of Counon-ealth tax to States<br />
andC] local g-over-nt ent provided to . Le-x--, a-ers seoarately b-u-t<br />
in conjunc-tion with assessment notices.<br />
Review of Total Tax Sliari-P. Arran~ ernents<br />
( 27) There will be a review of the tax sharing, arrang ements<br />
as a whole periodically. The f irs t -reviw " ill7 be malde at </p>
<p>ADVISORY COUNCIL FOR INTER-GOVERNMENTAL RELATIONS<br />
CH A1RTER<br />
DECL.. AATION OF PURPOSE<br />
Section 1. Successful operation of our system of federal<br />
govelnment demands the fullest co-operation and co-ordination<br />
of activities betweeni all spheres of gove'n! iient. . n increasigly<br />
complex society in future years suggestLsthat an Advisory<br />
Council for Inter-government Relations be est. ablisbed to give<br />
contiiuing attention to inter-goverrnnental problems.<br />
It is intended that the Advisory Council, in the<br />
preformance of its duties, will bring together representatives<br />
of the Federal, State and local gcvernments nd private citizens<br />
for the consideration of commnon problems.<br />
Premiers' Conference will refer to the Council<br />
subjects for . dvice. Local government authorities, through thei<br />
State organisations, will be able to submit mttters to their<br />
respective Premiers, for consideration by the Premiers'<br />
Conference for reference to the Council. It would also be<br />
open to the Council itself to request that matters be referred<br />
to it for advice.<br />
DUTIES OF THE COUNCIL<br />
Section 2. It shall be the duty of the Advisory Councilto<br />
engage in such activities and to make such<br />
studies and investigations as are necessary or<br />
desirable in the accomplishment of the purposes<br />
set forth in section 1 of this charter;<br />
to consider ways and means of fostering better<br />
relations between the spheres of government;<br />
To submit reports on matters referred to the<br />
Council to the Prime Minister and the Premiers<br />
for tabling in Parliament; and to submit an annual<br />
report on or before 31 August each year to the<br />
Prime Minister and the Premiers for tabling. in<br />
Parliament.<br />
LEG BASIS<br />
Phe Council is to be established by a memorandum<br />
of agreement between the Prime Minister and the Premiers at<br />
the Premiers' Conference. The Commonwealth alone will<br />
introduce any necessary legislation. 2/. </p>
<p>COM. P ) SITION OF THE COUNCIL<br />
The Council is to comprise three Government and two<br />
Oppc3ition members of the Commonwealth Parliament; one<br />
representative from each State; three representatives from/<br />
local government to be elected by the Local Government Association<br />
of Aistealia and preferably to be selected from separate<br />
States; and five citizens to be selected by the Commonwealthi<br />
in consultation with the States having regard to the various<br />
areas and sections of the community and with a view to ensuring<br />
that States without local government representation having<br />
citizens selected.<br />
ROTA" TION OF MEMBERS<br />
Nomination of Commonwealth and State representatives<br />
by the Government of the time will ensure rotation of those<br />
members in the normal course of electoral change. The local<br />
government representatives and the citizens to be appointed for<br />
a three-year term with a limit of two consecutive terms.<br />
Re-election after a break in office would be permissable.<br />
STATUS OF MEMBERS It would be open to Governments to decide whether<br />
to appoint Ministers or backbenchers to the Council.<br />
CHAIRMAN The Chairman is to be a citizen nominated by the<br />
Comiionwealth in consultation with the States.<br />
BUD( ET Funds for the Council to be limited to S$ 300,000 in the fii. st<br />
yeai with the proviso that the Commonwealth and the States<br />
would meet the cost of fares and accommodation for their<br />
repi , sentatives.<br />
COS' SHARING Costs will be shared:<br />
Commonwealth 45% or $ 135,000<br />
Local Government 10% or $ 30,000<br />
States 45% or $ 135,000 </p>
<p>be asked<br />
share.<br />
NT. S. W.<br />
Vi c<br />
Old S. A.<br />
W. A.<br />
Tas The Local Government Associatfion of Iutrndi i. will<br />
to assess the method of al local ina tht I ocal govcrinen.<br />
The State share will be al oc(: a ted is f. o'ows:<br />
S35,500 S30, OO<br />
; 21 .500<br />
S17,500 S1 7,000<br />
S13,500<br />
CANBERRA 9 ADril 1976 </p>
<p>ISSUES STILL BE TO RESOLVED<br />
A number of issues still remain to 1) e resolved,<br />
but they are technical matters and not issues of.<br />
principle. We do not foresee difficulties in deciding<br />
these issues. They will be considered by w-orking parties<br />
of Commonealth and State officials who will report to<br />
Heads of Government. One of -the tasks remaining, is to establish<br />
procedures and guidelines for reviewing periodically the<br />
relative shares of personal income tax revenue to go to<br />
each State. The Commonwealth feels strongly -that the<br />
appropriate body for this task is the Grants Commission.<br />
' More workH is -to be done to determine the legal<br />
framework which will be required for the imposition of<br />
surcharges or the granting of rebates under stage 2 ofthe<br />
tax sharing arrangements wh-ich will come into effect<br />
in 19' 77/ 73. To minimise any difficulties for employers<br />
and employees which may result from changes PAYE<br />
processes, there will need to be close consultation as<br />
to the timing of the introduction of any changes.<br />
The single most important issue outstanding<br />
is the question of which specific purpose payments to the<br />
States are to absorbed into the gIIeneral revenue<br />
arrangements. A good deal of consideration will need<br />
to be given to this matter and a working group of officers<br />
will be examining the whole range with a view -to decisi~ ns<br />
being made durir9 the course of-the next financial year. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
