<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4223</transcript-id>
    <title>SENIOR GOVERNMENT APPOINTMENTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004223.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS SEPTEMBER 6, 1976<br />
SENIOR GOVERNMENT APPOINTMENTS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Malcolm Fraser,, today foreshadowed<br />
senior Government appointments.<br />
Mr Fraser said that, with the greatest regret, he had to<br />
announce that Sir John Bunting would not be able to remain<br />
for his full term as High Commissioner in London, where, as<br />
in Australia, he is very highly regarded.<br />
Earlier this year in London Sir John had a major emergency<br />
operation. From this he has recovered well, but with<br />
impairment for the time being of his voice.<br />
After medical advice, Sir John has told the Prime Minister<br />
that, given particularly the heavy representational role in London,<br />
he feels it best that arrangements for appointment of a<br />
successor as High Commissioner now be set in train.<br />
Mr Fraser said that Sir John, who is at present in Australia<br />
on leave and consultations, has agreed to return to London<br />
later this year, pending arrangements for his successor to take<br />
up his duties as High Commissioner early in 1977. Sir John's<br />
future plans will depend on medical advice, but the Prime Minister<br />
said he hoped very much that Sir John's vast experience, wisdom<br />
and judgement would continue to be available to his Government.<br />
Mr Fraser said that the unexpected vacancy of High Commissioner<br />
in London would bring in train several appointments. Pending<br />
completion of formal processes, full details could not be<br />
publicly announced, but Mr Fraser said that some changes at the<br />
departmental head level would be included.<br />
Mr J. L. Menadue, at present Secretary to the Department of the<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet, will vacate that position to accept<br />
another senior Commonwealth Government appointment. Mr A. T.<br />
Carmody, currently Secretary to the Department of Business<br />
and Consumer Affairs,, will succeed Mr Menadue.<br />
Mr Fraser paid tribute to Mr Menadue's competence, impartiality<br />
and discretion. Mr Menadue had given unstintingly of his energies<br />
and managerial skills in serving as the confidential adviser to<br />
the Prime Minister and Cabinet in the important transitional<br />
period of the Liberal National Country Party Government,, as he<br />
had done for its predecessor.<br />
Mr Fraser added that fuller announcements would be made as soon as<br />
the formal processes for these and other related appointments are<br />
completed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
