<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9218</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS, NATIONAL PRESS CLUB 5 MAY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009218.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS, NATIONAL PRESS CLUB<br />
MAY 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Q: Robert Garran from the Australian, Mr Keating. You seem to be<br />
proposing to pay for the White Package through a growth dividend<br />
arising from faster economic growth and from asset s-ales. Some<br />
pundits, including Reserve Bank Governor, Mr Fraser and Ross<br />
Garnaut, have argued that the growth dividend should be used to wind<br />
back the discretionary rise in the Budget deficit of the last three years.<br />
The bond market's response to the White Plaper suggests that many<br />
investors agree with them. Are they wrong?<br />
PMV: Yes. In short, yes. The notion is that there is a discretionary thing<br />
here. That this is a matter of luxury. That the discretion actually<br />
extends to some sort of measure of luxury. You know, this is a gold<br />
plated thing the Government might not do. Well the critics of the policy<br />
number among those who say, " let's leave them. Let's forget them,<br />
let's side line them". Because they know anyone who has any<br />
economic credentials knows that looking at the 80s experience, or any<br />
other, economic growth will pick up the new entrants to the labour<br />
market, but it won't pick up the long term unemployed. And the Green<br />
Paper estimated that even with ' economic growth of the magnitude in<br />
question, by the end of the century we would still have 300,000 people<br />
long term unemployed. Now one of the points I made yesterday, I will<br />
make it again today, compliments to skill formation in this recovery will<br />
not come from migration. They will come only from our own workforce,<br />
and people joining our own workforce as new entrants, or re-training<br />
and replacing those who are long term unemployed. So, therefore, if<br />
we want to keep a high rate of growth and keep away from skills bottle<br />
necks, and sustain that rate of growth and get down the natural rate of<br />
unemployment with a sustenance of stable rates of inflation, the only<br />
way is to reform the labour market. Therefore, I reject the notion that it </p>
<p>is luxurious or that it is discretionary. If you then accept that it isn't<br />
discretionary, that it is a thing that any civilised country with sensible<br />
and sane values should do, it is something that a Government does.<br />
The main thing is that the things are workable, that they are efficient,<br />
that they are well targeted, that there is a very large bang for every<br />
dollar bang for the buck here in the program design and delivery.<br />
And if you accept those things then the deficit which falls from the<br />
budget numbers, in whatever equation of growth and diminished<br />
outlays, or pick up in receipts, is the one that is appropriate for the<br />
country. But the one that we will have with this program, inclusive of<br />
this program, will be one within the previously determined target by the<br />
Government of a Budget deficit around 1 per cent of GDP by 1995-96.<br />
Now people are aguing that the marginally diminished financing effects<br />
of the $ 1.7 billion diminished deficit will outstrip the macro-economic<br />
efficiency effects of case managing half a million people back into the<br />
labour market. That is absolute bunkum, absolute nonsense. And are<br />
we to say to a financial market, which lemming like has sold down long<br />
bonds because of a change in monetary policy of point 75 of a per cent<br />
in the United States, and driven up yields in their fright that in the<br />
hands of these great thinkers that we will have an appropriate dividend<br />
for a lower budget deficit at the expense of half a million Australians<br />
and their livelihood, then we won't be making that calculation. And<br />
that's why I answered yes.<br />
Q: Ross Peake from the Canberra Times, Prime Minister. I was speaking<br />
to a manger of a CES Branch this morning, who incidentally really likes<br />
the W ' hite Package, but the discussion raised two questions. How will<br />
you deliver on your guarantee of a job for the long term unemployed in<br />
a small town where unemployment is already high? And secondly,<br />
how confident are you that you can change the mindset that employers<br />
seem to have against hiring the long term unemployed?<br />
PM: Well, that is part of the challenge, I think, that faces the whole country,<br />
that the Government can't do this alone, we have made this very clear<br />
in the Paper. That is, that this has to be done by everybody, there has<br />
to be a premium by all of us on the notion that we are better and<br />
stronger if all of us have opportunities of work and enjoying Australian<br />
prosperity. Now, you can take the other view. You can take the view<br />
that the British manager took: " we won't give them an hourly rate,<br />
because we won't get the productivity". You can drive the wage race<br />
down so you have got essentially a heap of working poor people. I<br />
mean, one of the things that President Clinton said to me in Blake<br />
Island going out, on the back of a vessel, I remember well he said,<br />
"' one of the things I want to remedy in this country is the fact that the<br />
American working poor haven't had a real wage increase in 15 years."<br />
Now, that's what has happened in America. You have got a huge body<br />
of poor people. And I don't believe that we can make that decision.<br />
Therefore, it means that we all have to regard full employment, that<br />
much of it as we can garner from these changes, from economic </p>
<p>growth, as an objective for us all. And it means if the Government sets<br />
up programs that actually provide case management and training<br />
where necessary, or a job subsidy, employers should at least take The<br />
opportunity of taking peo~ ple up and giving them a go. And they will<br />
find, I think, that with the retention rates we have been able to secure<br />
with many labour market programs has a high success rate. And given<br />
the fact that a lot of labour market programs now are actually managed<br />
through a fairly rigid system, a fairly rigid system, a much more closely<br />
arranged and targeted system, a person-to-person case manage<br />
system should mean that the matching between the person and the<br />
employer, and the attitude of the person should be better. So,<br />
therefore the retention rates and success rates in jobs of long term<br />
unemployed people should be higher. If that happens employers may<br />
change their mind about the value of taking unemployed people. As<br />
well as that the subsidies are quite high, for someone unemployed<br />
three years it is $ 260.00 for the first 13 weeks, it drops down<br />
substantially after that. But it is still a substantial benefit. And for<br />
$ 230.00 for people unemployed 12 months or more. So, there is, I<br />
think, a value in that, and of course with a training wage we have got<br />
the prospect of employers taking on young people for training at below<br />
award rates because there is some structured on-the-job training. All<br />
this, I think, leads to good employer and employee relations that<br />
generally lead to on-going employment. So, that's where I think the<br />
relationship will be. In country towns there will always be a problem<br />
where there is a dearth of jobs, but one of the things we have in the<br />
White Paper is a new opportunities program where we might be able to<br />
fund some of these payments to community organisations who engage<br />
young people and unemployed people in community work. Now, there<br />
is a bit of additionality in jobs in the paper, essentially, it is not about<br />
additionality, it is about streaming the long term unemployed back into<br />
the mainstream labour market.<br />
Q: Laura Tingle, from the Australian, Prime Minister. You said in your<br />
speech yesterday, and also today in your comments, that in this<br />
recovery the compliment to skill formation in the labour market is not<br />
going to come from migration but it is coming from training our own<br />
people. I was wondering given the unemployment crisis, and the fact<br />
that it is going to take a long time to resolve, what the Governments<br />
parameters are on establishing a migration program in the medium<br />
term?<br />
PM: Well, we will be, as you may know, Laura, this time each year we<br />
announce a migration target for the year. That follows a process of<br />
extensive consiitations vWhich we have with the States, with employer<br />
organisations, with community groups and this process has been<br />
undertaken by my colleague, Nick Bolkus, and he will be reporting to<br />
Cabinet shortly with his recommendation for this year's intake. But it<br />
needs to be juxtaposed against the view that the migration program<br />
was cut from, I think, a high of about 147 thousand to just over </p>
<p>thousand a couple of years ago. And the emphasis there, a greater<br />
emphasis on family reunion, and therefore, the notion that people will<br />
have come here and set themselves up here, and being housed here<br />
ready to participate in the recovery and meet skills shortages at<br />
various points in the economy, is one that I don't think that we ought to<br />
substantially rely upon. That is not to say there isn't some additional<br />
skills and some complimentary skills coming through, there is. But<br />
principally we are going to have to rely upon the natural growth of the<br />
workforce and how could you do that and at the same time ignore 360<br />
thousand people who have been unemployed for 12 months or more.<br />
Let alone those who have been unemployed for less than 12 months.<br />
So, this is why we believe that this is an economically efficient thing to<br />
do. This is a micro-economic reform of great substance. That's the<br />
point, this is a micro-economic reform of great substance, and if we<br />
want to see the natural rate of unemployment, the NAIRU, the natural<br />
rate of unemployment, with a sustainable low rate of inflation at the<br />
lowest level possible, then we need to engage these people back into<br />
the workforce.<br />
Q: Fran Kelly, ABC Radio, Prime Minister. One of the big promises, and<br />
one you have mentioned here again today is the one to one case<br />
management of half a million people as part of this White Paper. That<br />
has got to mean at least 2000 people involved in administering and<br />
giving out the case management, those people currently aren't there.<br />
Where are you going to find them? And is this going to turn out to be<br />
an overly ambitious promise that can't be fulfilled?<br />
PM: I don't think so. I think, though, it has a lot of ambition, that I would<br />
never deny. But the question is, is it appropriately ambitious and I<br />
think it is. The challenge will be for us to get the systems in place to<br />
make the policy work and work well. And that's why I think it is an<br />
important feature of the paper that the Government has said, that not<br />
withstanding a substantial addition of resources to the CES and a<br />
compliment to its capacities and training, that it will seek to develop,<br />
and put incentives to develop, a private market for case management.<br />
And we will see a whole series of companies and institutions set up. It<br />
is very possible for instance, take the Metal Trades Industry<br />
Association which yesterday issued a very complimentary press<br />
statement about the White Paper. It is conceivable in capital and<br />
provincial cities, that an organisation like the MTIA could be a case<br />
manager, particularly for people in its industry, or other industries, the<br />
hotels and tourism industry, for instance, could be another. I mean, I<br />
think, one of the things we might be able to get from this is not simply<br />
devices and organisations to case manage those who are at risk of<br />
being long term unemployed or unemployed, but we'll actually develop<br />
a better labour market where employers know how to responsively, in a<br />
way where there is a quick and accurate response, go to a case<br />
management body, be it the CES or a private one, and go there with<br />
confidence for their future labour market needs, the future needs of the </p>
<p>business. I would hope a better matching of these things should be<br />
possible, and this is particularly so with computerisation, ADP<br />
equipment more generally available in the economy then say in ten or<br />
twenty years ago. And bearing in mind, I think, the CES places only<br />
about 18 per cent of people in employment, most people find their own<br />
job through newspaper or their own individual efforts, or networking.<br />
And if we can improve that networking and get better matching we can<br />
end up with a really important change from this.<br />
Q: Nikki Savva, from the Herald Sun, Mr Keating. Can you give an<br />
assurance now that the extra spending in the White Paper will not be<br />
funded by increases in spending on new taxes or by increasing<br />
existing taxes?<br />
PM: That's the sort of question that disc jockeys normally ask me, or<br />
reformed disc jockey's, out of print journo's I expect more sophisticated<br />
questions. And the answer is no. I am not in the business of giving<br />
guarantees on those sorts of things. I mean it is a week to the Budget<br />
and that's when, I think, all will be revealed.<br />
Q: Kim Sweetman, from the Courier Mail, Prime Minster. The regional<br />
development plan virtually leaves provincial areas to drag themselves<br />
up by their bootstraps. While areas like Cairns, which was cited as an<br />
example, have managed to develop themselves due to long term<br />
planning, what real hope can you give to the 12 per cent of Australians<br />
which are living in areas which are already in decline?<br />
PM: Well there seems to be a very clear contradiction in your question.<br />
You are saying the people of Cairns under their own leadership have<br />
made it, but you are not going to let other groups under their own<br />
leadership make it, that's the very essence. I mean the message of<br />
the Kelty Report, and the Mckinsey Report that after a vast survey, and<br />
in the case of the Kelty task force, a most comprehensive visit to the<br />
reg ions of this country and discussions of quality, and also the Industry<br />
Commission report the one key finding was given that regions with<br />
leadership cohesion, a sense of unity of purpose between local<br />
government, municipal bodies, shire organisations, business<br />
organisations, trade unions and other community organisations, that<br />
regions which have a clear ambition for themselves and work<br />
cooperatively invariably do better than those who don't. And so what<br />
they found was a lot of the investment in these regions didn't come<br />
from outside, it wasn't floating investment, it was investment generated<br />
form within the region. And this I think is quite a revelation. Because<br />
the notion is you have got to have someone jump in from outside and<br />
do something they weren't formerly doing, but most of the investment<br />
actually came from the region itself. So, what we have done in the<br />
White Paper in response to the recommendations of Bill Kelty's<br />
taskforce and the various other reports was to say, well look, where<br />
there is the establishment of regional economic development </p>
<p>organisations as he recommended, READOs, we will fund those and<br />
we will let people get into a position where they can actually put<br />
together some cogent plans for their region. As well as that we will do<br />
some other things for them. We will actually help them with some<br />
financial devices to fund capital formation and infrastructure that may<br />
be necessary in particular locations. And we had a very substantial<br />
change to the tax treatment of infrastructure bonds. We are now<br />
giving a 33 per cent tax rebate on infrastructure bonds, where formally<br />
these might not have been attractive to low taxed tax payers, such as<br />
super funds which are taxed at a rate of 15 per cent or less. And the<br />
same with pool development funds, we have changed the tax treatment<br />
of those from 25 per cent to 15 per cent in the hope that high marginal<br />
rate tax payers can through the mechanism of the PDF fund some<br />
equity and capital into some of these regions. Now, I think what you<br />
will see in regions is increasingly people will pool their own savings in<br />
regions and they will invest them in regions because funds<br />
management is sophisticating all the time across the economy. You<br />
have got in some regions of Australia very large collections of retired<br />
aged people who have got lump sums to invest and what have you.<br />
Many of them are investing in capital city organisations. They could<br />
have invested in regional organisations, and, I think, as a<br />
consequence of that we can see regions starting to get their act<br />
together, know what they should do and be helped. We have also got<br />
there a capital fund, not a large one, but one that can, I think, make<br />
clear that for really good capital works that will provide a big regional<br />
dividend, that is important in a regional sense, the Commonwealth can<br />
play a role there with either seed funds or a more substantial role. I<br />
think that is the answer, so when we look at Cairns we have got to say,<br />
why is the region of Cairns successful? By and large because it has<br />
got a community comrmitted to a common set of objectives, and I think<br />
getting those objectives together is the way to do it. But the notion of<br />
pulling them up by their bootstraps, left to their own devices, the<br />
flipside of that remark means the Commonwealth should be simply<br />
going along with a very large cheque trying to rebuild these regions<br />
and that is not possible if the regions themselves don't understand<br />
what they can do best, how they can do it together. And where we can<br />
play a role is helping them do that. Helping them conceive their plans<br />
and execute them sensibly.<br />
Q: Malcolm Farr from the Telegraph Mirror, Prime Minster. What will be<br />
the major occupational groupings of the one million jobs the White<br />
Paper says will be created between now and the end of the century?<br />
And what will be the growth areas in vocational training to accompany<br />
that?<br />
PM: Well, I think that the general answer to that, Malcolm, would be that<br />
per cent of our product comes from the service side of the economy.<br />
While we have doubled manufacturing productioh in the last ten years,<br />
and tripled manufacturing exports, productivity in manufacturing has </p>
<p>probably demonstrated that those involved, the number of people<br />
involved in manufacturing has, if not grown, fallen. But our output is<br />
greater and our product innovation is better. Now there is a potential, I<br />
think, with small and medium-sized enterprises to employ more people<br />
in manufacturing, and that is one of the hopes I have and why I think<br />
vocational education is going to be a very important complement to<br />
tert1iry ~ skis formation. But again, if you look at the service sector of<br />
Australia, it's changing all the time, it's far more sophisticated than it<br />
was five years ago. And we have got services which are now<br />
internationally traded like tourism. We are now earning $ 9 billion a<br />
year from tourism, we were earning virtually nothing, there was a<br />
tourism deficit in the early 1980s, and we have been closing that at<br />
great speed. So I think that you are going to see it across the<br />
economy. But remember this, that we had enormous job growth in the<br />
1980s, between 1983 and 1989-90 the economy grew on average at<br />
per cent or around that. What we're saying is that at that speed or<br />
even slightly more around 5 per cent, ought to be a possibility in a<br />
much freer economy than the one that we inherited over a decade ago,<br />
where now a lot of micro-economic and structural reform has made it<br />
far more flexible. In that context therefore, the growth in employment<br />
which we saw in those years two million jobs, should be capable of<br />
being replicated at that kind of rate through the balance of this century.<br />
Therefore, I don't have a problem with the notion that in aggregate this<br />
can be done. What we need to do, I think, is to make sure that we<br />
accept the notion that there are not very many unskilled jobs for young<br />
people, that 15 to 19 should be a period of vocational preparation. In<br />
this White Paper we are actually reaching into Years 11 and 12 to give<br />
kids work experience and to set them up vocationally while at school<br />
as well as expanding mightily by 700 million over four years TAFE and<br />
seeing the provision of a private training market in vocational<br />
education beyond TAFE where we have a much closer fix by business<br />
and industry on the training needs of the particular institutions and<br />
where business and industry take a very close and high interest in<br />
training themselves.<br />
This is going to mean, I think, that vocational preparation and<br />
education is going to rise phoenix like I believe and hope, from what<br />
was basically a section of Australian education largely forgotten and sit<br />
beside the universities as a real complement to Australian education<br />
and skills.<br />
Q: Michael Millet, Sydney Morning Herald. Prime Minister, how important<br />
is the training wage and ACTU acceptance of it in the overall success<br />
of the White Paper agenda and a somewhat different question are<br />
there any circumstances in which the Government would be prepared<br />
to revise its deficit reduction program? </p>
<p>PM: Let me go to the second one first. People are saying to us you need a<br />
lower Budget deficit, there is always someone out there bidding the<br />
numbers down and at the same time they'll tell you investment is not<br />
quite as strong as it ought to be. Well, if investment is not quite as<br />
strong as it ought to be, we don't need the savings complement from<br />
an earlier reduction in the deficit. The rate of withdrawal of the<br />
stimulus and the cushioning which the natural stabilisers had in the<br />
turn around of the Budget deficit from a surplus of $ 8 billion to a deficit<br />
of $ 14 a $ 22 or $ 23 billion turn around meant the Australian economy<br />
was saved a lot of pain and grief even beyond that which it<br />
experienced in the course of the recession.<br />
What we found about the recession was, it was long rather than deep<br />
in terms of the loss to GDP, but it had very large effects in<br />
employment. Whether that was through labour hoarding in the 1980s I<br />
don't know. So, therefore, the notion that we should be just the<br />
lowest deficit is the best deficit belongs simply to the mind of those<br />
who have been preaching this stuff for years. You know, putting a<br />
monkey on the Governments back for no particular virtue than simply<br />
the supposed economic virtue of the lowest possible number.<br />
Therefore, if the economy performs more strongly the revenue yield<br />
will be greater, the natural shift in the Budget balance will become<br />
apparent. The key point is that the cyclical changes the Government<br />
introduced in ' One Nation' and I notice some person on television last<br />
night talking about how the general policy had failed, yet the economy<br />
is growing at 4 per cent and maybe even faster. You have got to say,<br />
what do you mean it failed? It succeeded, absolutely and yet the<br />
stimulus of ' One Nation' has been withdrawn, it was a temporary<br />
stimulus. So, if you look at the underlying level of the outlays and the receipts,<br />
have they been in some way changed on a discretionary basis by the<br />
Government in some massive way which affects the budget balance?<br />
they haven't. If anyone says ' what about the tax cuts?' My reply would<br />
be without those the real incidence of tax would have risen. Therefore,<br />
the budget balance as you see it and its return to surplus which is now<br />
going to be accomplished in this period is something which we've been<br />
able to do because of the great fiscal consolidation of the 1980s.<br />
Because Australia had a surplus it was able to open up the deficit and<br />
cushion the effect of the recession upon the economy. Similarly, now<br />
the economy is growing it will come back and it will come back<br />
sensibly. But everyone who says that in an economy of $ 400 billion<br />
odd of GDP and a budget of $ 110 billion or there abouts, look, $ 1<br />
million is going to make or break the whole show, we say what kind of<br />
vernier dial to you have? What kind of enhanced calibrations to you<br />
possess because there is no doubt that the Wallahs of the financial<br />
markets have no such vernier dials and no such calibrations.<br />
That is why I believe that the Government in these things is correct. </p>
<p>The training wage is important because, for a start, we are trying to get<br />
up the-canc-pTof a national training award or a national training<br />
decision with one rate. So instead of having a multiplicity of rates<br />
across various industries that we've had we end up with one rate which<br />
has a discount on the award rate for on-the-job training, not simply a<br />
low rate. I notice the Liberals the other day out talking about this thing<br />
of theirs called Jobtrain. They were talking about massive discounts<br />
on award wages without any need for training. Theirs was simply the<br />
word they used for pushing wages down. But there they were at the<br />
front door the other day saying, " we thought of this first" imagine them<br />
thinking of anything novel first. Novel let alone first. I suppose there is<br />
a tautology there, if its novel it must be first. Anyway, there it is.<br />
Therefore, it can be an important thing for young people and for<br />
unemployed people for an employer to say look, we won't be giving the<br />
award wage, but the discount will be a sensible one and we'll make<br />
that up by on-the-job training. Because for many employers the onthe-<br />
job training is the kind they really want. They get somebody that<br />
comes to their place or factory, they teach them something and they<br />
become a real value to them. They build a real relationship. That, I<br />
think, is the value of the training wage.<br />
Q: Mark Riley, Sydney Morning Herald. If our focus is going to be on full<br />
employment, could you share with us your definition of full employment<br />
in per centage terms and secondly, the best case scenarios seem to<br />
be that we are going to be stuck with unemployment of 500,000 at the<br />
turn of the century. To what extent would you and your party accept<br />
responsibility for that figure?<br />
PM: We'll accept responsibility for the number, but if we were the<br />
Government and I think we will be, that is, if we were able to get<br />
unemployment down to around 5 per cent which roughly equates to<br />
half a million people where now we have got a million people out of<br />
work, the way I see things half a million out of work is much better than<br />
a million out of work. But understand this point, to get to that one<br />
would have to create well over a million jobs because you are not just<br />
talking about half a million off the current one million, you've got to<br />
take all the new entrants to the labour force up between now and then.<br />
I don't know whether you understand this point. If you think about it<br />
you know you are not dealing with just a million. You've got roughly a<br />
million people there and then you've got the addition to the work force<br />
in the period. So, if you're getting to half a million, you've got to have<br />
well over a million.<br />
You are saying, would we take responsibility for that? Absolutely.<br />
Q: ( inaudible) </p>
<p>PM: Well, that is difficult. What is structural full employment these days in<br />
an economy in a massive transition? In the United States they think<br />
it's around 6 per cent. The aim of this White Paper though is to get<br />
down what's called NAIRU-the natural unemployment rate consistent<br />
with stable low inflation. That is, if we have labour market programs<br />
this sophisticated, if we have flexibility in the labour market coming<br />
from changes in the industrial relations laws, if we have enterprise<br />
flexibility in enterprise bargaining, if we have productivity diminishing<br />
costs therefore, with a combination of these things and low inflation<br />
generally sensible outcomes on wages productivity, profits et cetera, it<br />
should be possible to lower whatever otherwise one would believe<br />
would be the unemployment rate with stable rates of inflation. Now, I<br />
don't know what that is. When I say that let me complete the sentence;<br />
I don't know what it is other than to say it is certainly not zero, but we<br />
would certainly be within close proximity of making a fine judgement<br />
about it were we to have unemployment at 5 per cent by the end of the<br />
century. I think that is the important point.<br />
Q: Tony Vermeer, AAP. Prime Minister, the relative air of peace between<br />
the Right and the Left seems to have ended in a big way in NSW and<br />
Victoria recently. You plan to privatise airports, that appears to be<br />
grist for the mill for more destabilisation between the factions. Are you<br />
headed for a big stoush at the ALP national conference?<br />
PM: I don't think so. The thing is, one of the great structural changes for<br />
Australia in the last eleven years was that the major party capable of<br />
forming a government in its own right has reformed its views, changed<br />
the way it has operated, become a party of government and led a<br />
process of major, massive national reform. For any nation this is a<br />
major advance. When you see major parties going to seed in Western<br />
Europe and the United States and other places like North America, this<br />
is a major change. The Labor party has proven it is the vehicle of<br />
social and economic change in Auitralia and it has proven it changes<br />
itself on the way through it. Now, at every point along the way,<br />
whether it was foreign bank entry or whether it was the sale of Qantas,<br />
you'll always have these debates. I regard those as fairly healthy and<br />
we've always worked our way through them. The thing is the Labor<br />
party can change and adapt. What the Coal ition has shown is they<br />
can't. Every reference of their they talk about rebuilding by going<br />
back to Menzies. They talk about the future by going back to Menzies<br />
and we are told reliably Menzies didn't vote for them in the last two<br />
elections of his life. I don't think he voted for us either, but we wouldn't<br />
want his vote.<br />
Therefore, I think, that the public being quite wise about all of this,<br />
looking past the static of the daily media reporting to the points of<br />
value, say this is good, there's the Labor party taking on another thing<br />
and they listen for what the debate is about and if they form a<br />
judgement that say an airport can be run efficiently as a private sector </p>
<p>organisation, perhaps even more efficiently, they say a good thing has<br />
been done here. And if it requires a debate so be it.<br />
Q: Randal Markey, The West Australia. Prime Minister, earlier this week<br />
you told Caucus when the time comes for the next election you will<br />
" punch out the Coalition's lights". Given that the two WA Green<br />
Senators said last night that they will have problems voting for the<br />
legislative based parts of your White Paper and the Opposition is<br />
toying with the idea of voting against parts of it, although it hasn't<br />
specified what it will do, could rejection of any part of the White Paper<br />
provide you with the double dissolution trigger to ' punch to Coalition's<br />
lights out'?<br />
PM: One of the things that would restrain me and that is, if I punch their<br />
lights out, I'd break your heart anyway and that would displease me no<br />
end. The fact is that, let's see what the Senate does. It is always<br />
talking about these days, it is always getting minor officials to defend it<br />
and telling us how representative it is, this is something for which the<br />
Government went to an election, it is something I made clear in the<br />
course of the campaign we wouldn't leave the unemployed behind.<br />
John Hewson said if you reached back to pick them up they'll pull the<br />
rest of us down. I believe that faced with the structure, order, sense<br />
and decency of this policy, the Senate will have no recourse but to<br />
pass it.<br />
Q: Geoff Barker, The Melbourne Age. Prime Minister, you said yesterday<br />
that the decade of Labor Government made Australia one of the most<br />
sophisticated social democracies in the world and I note that Professor<br />
John Neville of the University of New South Wales has published<br />
research showing that the number of Australians living below the<br />
Henderson poverty line over the 1 980s has increased from 9 to 13 per<br />
cent and that general income distribution has become distinctly more<br />
unequal with the rich doing much the best. How does that research<br />
square with your view that Australia has become one of the most<br />
sophisticated social democracies in the world?<br />
PM: I think Ross Gittins answered this quite well in an article the other day<br />
saying that the poor have become much less poorer even if some of<br />
the wealthy have become wealthier. As a consequence, if one looks at<br />
the transfer payments which we now have well, a number of things,<br />
the support for low paid people in the wage system, the direction of the<br />
tax cuts for nearly ten years to their benefit, the reduction in the bottom<br />
rates of tax and the lift in the tax free threshold, the Family Allowance<br />
and the additional family payment formerly the Family Allowance<br />
Supplement all of these things and support for, I'm just trying to<br />
remember the expression, but in the late 1980s to the early 1990s we<br />
had a complement to the wages of unskilled low paid people, mainly<br />
women in the retail and clothing industry, and these things, I think,<br />
have changes as with the advent of Medicare and the social wage in </p>
<p>general, changed the treatment of the poor in this country. You'll<br />
always have critics from the Left and from the Right, but I don't think<br />
any serious person believes with the targeted safety net we have in<br />
place today and there is more of it in this White Paper. Here we are in<br />
a very marked reform again taking the joint income testing of an<br />
unemployed couple and separating it down the middle and paying half<br />
the married rate to one partner and half to the other and then income<br />
testing one and where the others income is not affected, as it was<br />
under the joint income tests, not affected until that unemployed person<br />
has substantially more income. In fact $ 230 of more income before $ 1<br />
is lost under the new taper of the spouses unemployment benefit or<br />
parenting allowance another milestone, major change.<br />
Let me say Geoffrey, I was very disappointed with The Age this<br />
morning. Because, frankly the Sydney Morning Herald's coverage and<br />
the Australian coverage beat The Age into the ground. The Age is<br />
always going around saying it is part of the Melbourne social<br />
laboratory it is interested in social and economic issues; your lead<br />
story was reporting financial market whinges. Mark Baker had one<br />
which was peripheral and not to the point and you really had to get<br />
back into the body of the paper to find out what the Government was<br />
actually doing. There was a little box on the front page which was<br />
indecipherable. Now, where is The Age when we need it? Where is<br />
The Age when great social reforms are about and where its former<br />
championing of these things doesn't seem to matter that much these<br />
days. At least Geoffrey your carrying on the fight and good on you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
