<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8696</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSPORT TO THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP, DOORSTOP CANBERRA 18 OCTOBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008696.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 19. Oct. 92 11: 11 No. 003 P. 01/ 0!<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINis-rER, TIHE HION P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, CANBERRA, 18 OCTOBER 1992<br />
fi&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM; I just want to make a couple of comments about a few things Dr Hewson has said<br />
and done over the weekend. HeI told us in the Alfred Dcakin lecture earlier in the<br />
weck that policies of leaders should have a human touch and should be more<br />
warmi-hearted. Well he was totally cold-hearted in his put down of the Australian<br />
tourism industry on the weekend. That industry, which I think 14; now the largest<br />
employer of Australians or certainly will become, particularly of young<br />
Australians in the 1990s, and is really doing more that its share of any sector to<br />
add to growth and to exports of services, that sector has asked that under a. OST it<br />
be relieved. Not only did Dr Hewson say he wouldn't relieve them, but he has<br />
actually upbraided them, he has hopped into them for daring suggest that they<br />
should have relief. It is as if they have to apologise for even existing.<br />
Now, Dr Ifewson's proposals provide no relief to these people. Payroll tax relief<br />
will not go to any tourism operator who has a payroll of less than about half a<br />
million dollars. So they'll wear the OST, it will actually put a hole right through<br />
the industry, and there will be no relief for them, and to an industry which is really<br />
making a huge contribution to Australia and is going to make a bigger contribution<br />
in the future. Because you can't get a machine to make a bed, you can't gct a<br />
machine to clean up someone's bathroom, you can't get a machine to serve a meal.<br />
Thiis is a very-1abour-intensive industry, it's one of the service industries we are<br />
going to rely upon in the ' 90s, and he is going to kick a hole right in it with the<br />
goods and services tax. And Mr Jull, his tourism spokcsman, recognises and<br />
understands that. But not only does he not recognise it but he has hopped into<br />
them for daring suggest that they need relief.<br />
J: The tourism industry will be helped by the industrial relations chaniges the<br />
Opposition is putting forward when penalty rates are abolished.<br />
PM: No. Under the Sheraton Hotels agreement already concluded, penalty rates have<br />
all been rolled into a weekly rate. Thcrc's no thing, nothing In flexibility, that can't </p>
<p>TEL: 19. Oct .92 11 : 11 No .003 P .02/ 05<br />
2<br />
now be done under Section 37 agreements. What Dr Hewson and Mr Howard<br />
want to do is to actually cut the wages of Australians. They want flexibility<br />
downwards, they dont want flexibility up, they don't want flexibility sideways.<br />
Anything they want to do by way of hours, working time, working week, are all<br />
now iii all these hundreds of varied agreements which are being made and have<br />
been made over thc last 6 months, and quite historic ones in the case of Sheraton<br />
Hotels. So, don't believe any of Dr Hewson's rhetoric about tourism and industrial<br />
relations, the truth of thc matter is they just want to cut people's pay. And as I<br />
demonstrated during the week, in an American survey of pay rates Australians arc<br />
way down the scale. We're already hugely competitive, what does he want to hop<br />
into Australians' pay for?<br />
J. The Opposition Leader says that Fightback will quadruple the number of tourists<br />
coming here by thc end of the decade. Given that, why do you think he'd be<br />
insane enough to want to damage an industry as important as tourism to Australia?<br />
Surely what he says is based on fact.<br />
PM: No, I think the potential of the tourism industry is huge. It was the one great new<br />
industry created by the freedoms of the 1980s introduced by this Government.<br />
And its going to grow very strongly in the ' 90s, and particularly in the region, and<br />
also not just inbound tourism but domestic tourism. But a heavy tax on every<br />
service provided by it accommodation, meals, all sorts of scrvices will knock it<br />
down and slow its progress back. So the fact is, the industry is entitled to say were<br />
actually doing well and we're not going to get virtually any substantial relief from<br />
payroll tax or anything else, leave us alone. And he has got into them for being<br />
selfish.<br />
1: Does that indicate, Prime Minister, inbound tourists face some sort of value added<br />
tax in most competitive destinations anyway?<br />
PM: But it's also a fact that we're running a current account deficit, arnd one of the<br />
things we have going for us is a trade in international services tourism, financial<br />
services, education services, et cetera, and tourism has grown like Topsy in the<br />
1980s and has the potential to keep on going. People have got to understand this:<br />
the GST is half as big as Australia's income tax. At $ 27 billion theGST raise<br />
more than half the income tax. It's not just a mere bagatelle, it's a massive impost<br />
on the nation and on any industry, and this industry, which is competitive, and<br />
does has a lot to offer. One thing it has to offer is the potential to employ labour.<br />
When productivity is reducing the number of people employed in factories,<br />
tourism is giving us a real potential to employ people to take up labour and to set<br />
this industry back as this would do, I think enormously, is a terrible pity. But not<br />
only that, for them to ask for relief and then be shunned in the way that hc shunned<br />
them on the weekend and then chastised them as being selfish) means it's just<br />
nothing but inflexibility and cold-hearted responses from him. </p>
<p>TEL: 19. Oct. 92 11: 11 No. 003 P. 03/ 05<br />
3<br />
J: He's just being consistent, isn't he? He's not going to give them anything he is not<br />
givinp any othcr industry.<br />
pM: The fact is, to be consistent, this industry is not consistently growing, it is<br />
exponentially growing. If we want industries which are going to actually make a<br />
bigger than average difference to the way in which we perform, you've got to give<br />
them somc room.<br />
J: If he zero rated inbound tourists you'd have say a tourist couple in a hotel room<br />
paying a great deal less than an Australian couple in the next room. Isn't there<br />
some inequity in that?<br />
PM: I think there is, but the best thing he can do is relieve the whole industry. See, the<br />
truth is a tax of this dimension will seize the Australian economy. A tax which is<br />
equal to over half the income tax will seize the Australian economy. And his great<br />
rationale for it is that it will relieve payroll tax. In fact it is four or five times a<br />
larger tax on labour than payroll tax is. And in collecting equal -to-over-half the<br />
income tax, it's too great a burden an inflationary and coernptive burden on the<br />
Australian economy at this time. It's a luxury Australia can't afford.<br />
J: Prime Minister, given there is an inequity on inbound tourists having a cheaper<br />
deal in Australia, then isn't that a justification for what Dr Hewson is saying?<br />
PM: Look, there's no justification for penalising, an industry which is now competitive<br />
and growing like steam. None. It's a bad tax, the whole idea, and it's particularly<br />
bad on high labour content industries like tourism.<br />
J Jeff Kennett this morning said that he'd like to talk to you and you hadn't spoken to<br />
you yet, and he said that the worst thing Labor had done federally was not to go far<br />
enough with industrial relations reform, have you any response to that?<br />
PM: We've changed the nature of Australia in the ' 80s. It's now an externally-oriented<br />
competitive country. We're now clocking up bc-st practice awards with<br />
international bench-mnarking with companies. Because of the huge changes in<br />
industrial relations we've got an inflation rate of 11/ 2 per cent. So I don't think<br />
there's any validity in Mr Kennett's claims at all. And as far as I'm concerned I'm<br />
quite happy to see him. If he wants to discuss Victoria's troubles he'll be treated as<br />
fairly and as decently and as openly as every othcr Premier is.<br />
J Well does Mr Kennett have any other option than that he conceded hc was going<br />
to do today, that is to raise taxes substantially?<br />
PM: Well, that's a matter for him. But Victorians should take note that the Liberal<br />
Party of Australia is a high tax party. Whether it's the State Liberal Party sticking<br />
up taxes as Mr Kennett is, or Dr Hewson putting on a OST, they believe in higher<br />
taxation. Whereas what Labor has done is produce one of the smallest public </p>
<p>TEL: 19. Uct. 92 11: 11 No. 003 P. 04/ 05<br />
4<br />
sectors in the world and onc of the lowest rates of tax to GDP of any OECD<br />
country. in fact we're the second lowest in the whole of thc 27 countries of the<br />
OECD.<br />
J: What do you make of Mr Hewson's comments on Mr Can in New South Wales?<br />
PM: To be honest I was flabbergasted by that remark, that in some way he tried to Score<br />
off the fact that Bob Carr had no children. And what we see here creeping into the<br />
debate he said you've got to be suspicious of a guy that doesn't like kids. Well I<br />
can tell you this, Bob Canr has climbed all over my children from the time they<br />
were babies, and I think he's bringing in the worst of American politics. It's onc<br />
thing to have people criticising us in the way we fight the issues out in Parliament<br />
House, but at least they're issues. But this sort of stuff, and I should imagine that<br />
Dr Hcwson, who has had his own family affairs paraded in the public debate,<br />
would have been grateful for the fact that not one person in the Labor Party, not<br />
one, on the Labor side of politics made a comment about them. Not one, He said<br />
that Mr Carr wasn't as full-blooded as John Fahey because he doesn't have<br />
children. Well I don't think Ben Chifley had any trouble being a full-blooded<br />
Australian, and he didn't have any children. I think Dr l-ewson should withdraw<br />
this renmark, apologise for it and never repeat it.<br />
I, Mr Keating, speaking of issues, do you think that after the release of the<br />
Coalition's IR policy that IR will be the biggest political battleground up till the<br />
next election?<br />
PM: It will be two. It will be the GST arnd industrial relations. But remember this,<br />
we've now got industrial disputes at their lowest since we've been keeping records;<br />
we've got an inflation rate of under 2 per cent, which you can only havc a with a<br />
labour and wages system which is working; we've got all sorts of inventive,<br />
ingenious and productive enterprise agreements, flexibly being written between<br />
unions and employers across the country; we've got now one of the better labour<br />
market systems in the world and it's growing and improving every year. But to<br />
give it the cold, hard treatment of saying that awards arc finished, that people lose<br />
holiday pay, maternity leave, rates of pay and other things, and that they can sign<br />
up under a contract but only contest it in a court with their own legal<br />
representation will see Australians' wages cut dramatically from what are already,<br />
by world standards, competitive and low levelled. So industrial relations is<br />
obviously going to be an area of great difference between the Government and the<br />
Coalition, but I suppose most things are a great difference now between thc<br />
Government and the Coalition.<br />
J: khe fact is workers in Ncw Zealand havcn'I bceii chopped off at the knees, have<br />
they?<br />
PM: But they are being chopped off now. The rates of pay for New Zealanders now are<br />
now declining sharply, people are losing conditions and living standards are </p>
<p>T1E9L: . Oct. 92 11: 11 No. 003 P. 05/ 05<br />
sitarting to decline. And we don't need to do it here. Weve got an inflation. rate of.<br />
1 1/ 2 per cent, wc've got a profit share which is already reasonably good and will<br />
go quite high the moment there's any, real volume going on the to the bottom line<br />
of Australian corporate accounts. That is, when their overheads arc covered all<br />
their extra volume is just simply cop, it goes straight to the bottomn line of profits.<br />
So we're about to sce, as the economy really gets up a head of steam, the profit<br />
share go to very high level, and why anyone would want to go ripping Australian<br />
pay rates around and knocking ordinary people around in pay I've got no idea, and<br />
at the samne time while they knock Medicare over and everything else.<br />
J: Speaking of..<br />
PM: OK, I think I'll just leave it at that. T'hanks. I know You're very enthusiastic,<br />
Anmanda ( Buckley), it's that break it's done you the world of good!<br />
ends TEL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
