<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17118</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Attorney-General Premier of Queensland Flood grants for small businesses and primary producers 9 March 2010</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd and Premier Anna Bligh today announced joint Commonwealth-State funded grants to help small businesses and primary producers affected by recent flooding in Queensland.</p>
<p>Today's announcement will see small businesses and primary producers receive grants for clean up and recovery. Tier 1 grants will be available for up to $5,000 and Tier 2 grants will be up to $20,000.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said his thoughts were with the people of Queensland's south- west who were going through a very tough time.</p>
<p>"The Australian Government stands ready to assist the people of Queensland to recover from this very serious natural disaster," Mr Rudd said.</p>
<p>"This announcement today comes on top of the range of funding and assistance measures the Australian Government has already provided over the last week.</p>
<p>"This additional assistance is designed to minimise the economic impact on severely affected communities by providing short term targeted assistance, so businesses can continue trading as soon as possible."</p>
<p>Premier Bligh said small business owners and farmers would struggle to recover from this severe flooding event.</p>
<p>"Significant damage has occurred to small businesses in the majority of the communities in flood affected south west Queensland," Ms Bligh said.</p>
<p>"There will be extensive livestock and crop losses and damage to fencing, watering points, irrigation and other infrastructure on many rural properties.</p>
<p>"This grant funding is available to all eligible primary producers and small business owners who have suffered damage to their business."</p>
<p>The grants are being provided for the local government areas where the greatest impact has occurred. To date these areas include Balonne, Barcoo, Blackall-Tambo, Bulloo, Diamantina, Maranoa, Murweh, Paroo, Quilpie and Western Downs</p>
<p>The last time this grants program was activated in Queensland was during the 2009 monsoonal flooding and Tropical Cyclones Charlotte and Ellie.</p>
<p>These grants are in addition to concessional loans and freight subsidies for small businesses and primary producers which have already been activated for these local government areas.</p>
<p>The Australian and Queensland Governments are providing prompt and targeted assistance to help local communities recover from Queensland's biggest flooding event on record.</p>
<p>Last week the Premier announced the Premiers Flood Appeal and pledged $500,000 from the Queensland Government.</p>
<p>Joint State and Commonwealth Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA) have been activated for 59 local government areas.</p>
<p>Under the NDRRA, councils will be able to access funding from the Australian and Queensland Governments to assist with the cost of restoring essential public assets as well as the cost of counter disaster operations.</p>
<p>Disaster relief funding arrangements have also been activated for people experiencing personal hardship in a number of local government areas.</p>
<p>These funding arrangements consist of:</p>
<p>     * Emergent Assistance Payment - up to $170 per person and $780 per family.</p>
<p>     * Means tested - Essential Household Contents Grant - up to $1,660 for individuals and $4,980 for couples or families.</p>
<p>     * Means tested - Repairs to Dwellings / Structural Assistance Grant - up to $10,250 for individuals and $13,800 for couples or families.</p>
<p>The Minister for Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs has also activated the Australian Government Disaster Recovery Payment in a number of local government areas in south-west Queensland where individuals and households where significantly impacted. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
