<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2805</transcript-id>
    <title>TUESDAY 30 JANUARY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002805.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRAC,<br />
TUESDAY 30 JANUARY 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Thanks ladies and gentlemen: First the Cabinet<br />
decisions. We have sent for legislative drafting, four<br />
schemes of tax avoidance which the Treasurer, Mr. Crean,<br />
announced that we would be wanting to prevent from now on.<br />
The purchase of company shells for tax avoidance purposes,<br />
income tax concessions for capital subscriptions to mining<br />
companies, income tax deductions for life insurance<br />
premiums and payments to superannuation funds and avoidance<br />
of tax through Norfolk Island. Mr. Crean will give you<br />
the full details on any of those four if you have not got<br />
them. Broadcasting of Parliamentary proceedings. The<br />
present Act doesn't extend to the territories, i. e. in<br />
case of defamation or possible defamation so we have resolved<br />
to amend the Act to cover that situation.<br />
Export of merino rams and semen. We are taking<br />
steps to hold a referendum of the persons affected by any<br />
lifting of the ban.<br />
Amendments to the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
Act. There again, quite extensive amendments to the<br />
present Act were approved for drafting of amending<br />
legislation. Mr. Cameron would have a press conference<br />
on these tomorrow if you wish. </p>
<p>A proposal for dental therapists and social<br />
workers. Mr. Beazley can give you the explanation but in<br />
brief they are these:<br />
That the State Grants Advanced Education Act be<br />
amended as soon as practicable to provide supplementary<br />
grants for approximately $ 715,000 this year for training<br />
up to 55 additional dental therapists and $ 40,000 this<br />
year to establish a post-graduate course for social workers<br />
commencing next year.<br />
That there be an immediate announcement that the<br />
Government will provide additional capital and recurrent<br />
funds to enable colleges of advanced education to double<br />
the number of places available for new dental therapy students<br />
this year. C. A. E. scholarship,,, will be available subject<br />
to the usual conditions for the enlarged student entry,<br />
and the Government will provide additional funds this year<br />
to enable the Tasmanian College of Advanced Education to<br />
establish a post-graduate course for social workers<br />
commencing in 1974. That fills out the proposals that have<br />
already been announced for getting more trained men and<br />
women to undertake pre-school education and social work<br />
and dental therapy.<br />
Then there was some decisions of Cabinet committees<br />
which were ratified.<br />
The Townsville International Airport terms of<br />
reference. The Inquiry into the Australian Post Office.<br />
The three Commissioners they will sit as Royal Commissioners<br />
will be Sir James Vernon, Mr. Bernard<br />
James Callinan, the senior partner of Gutteridge Haskins<br />
and Davey, the engineers, and Mr. J. J. Kennedy, a Chartered<br />
Accountant of Brisbane. .3/ e </p>
<p>A fresh reference to the Public Works Committee<br />
of the Palmerston Highway in the Northern Territory and<br />
the general lines of the new conditions on which the<br />
Commonwealth will make money available to the States for<br />
housing purposes next financial year and the following<br />
years. A decision on Lake Pedder perhaps I should read<br />
the full text. The Minister for the Environment and<br />
Conservation is to be asked to advise the Cabinet on the<br />
establishment of appropriate machinery to determine the<br />
Australian Government's role with respect to the<br />
environment in relation to past or future development<br />
projects both in the States and in the territories. The<br />
projects the committee had in mind are those which have<br />
deleteriously affected or can so affect the environment.<br />
The projects specifically mentioned in this context were<br />
in addition to Lake Pedder, Cluther in New South Wales,<br />
Black Mbuntain in the Australian Capital Territory and the<br />
Alligator River in the Northern Territory.<br />
P. M. Are there any questions?<br />
Q. Prime Minister, two weeks ago you said that<br />
Vietnam was the only area of dispute between Australia<br />
and the United States. In view of the information which<br />
I presume you and Mr. Barnard now have, can you say whether<br />
you are in full agreement with the type and role of U. S.<br />
installations in Australia?<br />
P. M. There's no more information I have to give you<br />
on that matter.<br />
Q. Can you say whether you have made any further<br />
studies?<br />
P. M. No. 4/. </p>
<p>Q. Sir, on the same subject, can you tell us if<br />
you have any information on the types of signals going<br />
between Australia and Washington, in particular the role<br />
of the Defence Department. Is there anything there in which<br />
you feel you are perhaps under-informed or which you would<br />
consider it would be important for you to know. I'm thinking<br />
particularly of defence information which, there have been<br />
a lot of rumours over the last few weeks, is being put by<br />
members of the Department and by members of organisations<br />
in the department without direct reference to the<br />
Government to either you or Mr. Barnard?<br />
P. M. I don't understand the purport of your question.<br />
You mention rumours. I don't know what rumours you're<br />
referring to.<br />
Q. They are rumours that there are signals being<br />
sent between Canberra and Washington which have not been<br />
referred to either you or Mr. Barnard?<br />
P. M. I think there'd be hundreds of such signals being<br />
sent every day to various posts. It's quite obvious that<br />
ministers can't see the text of every signal that is<br />
received or transmitted. I have no knowledge of any signals<br />
which have been sent which wouldn't be completely in<br />
accordance with Government policy.<br />
Q. Are you totally satisfied with the information<br />
you've been getting from the Defence Department and from<br />
the various security organisations about communications<br />
between Canberra and Washington?<br />
P. M. Whenever I've asked for any information in the<br />
security field, I've been satisfied with the answer I was<br />
given. Mr. Barnard has never expressed any doubts as to<br />
the information he was given by his Department. My own<br />
Department of Foreign Affairs I'm certain that it is<br />
e </p>
<p>carrying out the Government's policy promptly and effectively.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, the Premiers of Victoria and South<br />
Australia have called for a Premiers' Conference in February.<br />
Have you considered this and, if so, what is your answer?<br />
P. M. I don't think they have formally asked for a<br />
Premiers' Conference.<br />
Q. You've received no formal request?<br />
P. M. There has been a letter from each of them but<br />
it's not a formal request. I would point out that the<br />
Government acted very promptly much more promptly than<br />
had been the case as far as I can remember in assisting<br />
the States all the States with grants for employmentgiving<br />
works. The assistance which has been given at<br />
Premiers' Conferences which have been often held in<br />
February was in fact granted as the result of direct<br />
negotiations between the Treasurer and sometimes myself<br />
and the State Premiers or Treasurers in every case before<br />
the end of the year.<br />
Q. Sir, how do you feel about a Premiers' Conference<br />
in February?<br />
P. M. I don't see the need for one.<br />
Q. Are you in favour in principle of maki-ng public<br />
the membership of inter-departmental committees?<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
Q. Will you make public the membership of the<br />
inter-departmental committee which is proposed by Dr. Cairns<br />
and Mr. Crean into the question of export incentives.<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
Q. If and when set up. </p>
<p>P. M. Yes.<br />
Q. Will you make public the report of that committee?<br />
P. M. It has been set up and I'll give you the<br />
information. Q. The report of that committee will be made public?<br />
P. M. I didn't say that. The membership I can give<br />
you now*<br />
Q. The third question was: will the report of that<br />
committee be made public?<br />
P. M. I don't remember ever having given an undertaking<br />
of that character.<br />
Q. I hadn't suggested that you had.<br />
P. M. Well, probably not.<br />
P. M. There is an inter-departmental committee to<br />
consider the general question of export credit composed of<br />
the Departments of Overseas Trade, Secondary Industry,<br />
Treasury, Reserve Bank and Export Payments Insurance<br />
Corporation. There is an inter-departmental committee to<br />
deal with adjustment assistance for secondary industry<br />
composed of Treasury, Overseas Trade and Secondary Industry.<br />
There is a third inter-departmental committee dealing with<br />
the question of export incentives composed of Treasury and<br />
Secondary Industry.<br />
Q. Mr. Whitlam, while you didn't commit yourself<br />
to making inter-departmental committee reports public,<br />
you, on a number of occasions asked in Parliament would<br />
they be made public, and it was just in going through<br />
today I noticed for example, in respect to the superannuation o o </p>
<p>report superannuation I seem to remember you asked the<br />
inter-departmental committee report to be made public and<br />
so there was an inferential support of this idea; and<br />
while also looking at that I noticed the available report<br />
itself was never made public despite the fact that you<br />
asked for it. Could you tell us when all these documents<br />
which you requested be made public will be made public?<br />
P. M. The general position is that they are tied in<br />
with the question of making public documents before an<br />
earlier government, and the practice has been hitherto<br />
that the documents which have been before a preceding<br />
government are not made public without the consent of the<br />
head of the party or parties which composed that previous<br />
government. I wouldn't depart from that practice without<br />
very serious consideration but I have not, at this stage,<br />
asked the heads of the Liberal Party and the Country Party<br />
whether they would mind any such documents being published.<br />
The whole thrust of my questions and statements on these<br />
subjects in earlier Parliaments was that the late<br />
Government used to hide behind the fact that an interdepartmental<br />
committee had been set up to look into certain<br />
subjects and one could never find out One couldn't<br />
for the last two years, find out what Departments were on<br />
these inter-departmental committees and when they had<br />
reported. Mr. Gorton used to make available the names<br />
of the inter-departmental committees and the Departments<br />
which sat on them and somewhere about the beginning of 1971<br />
he changed his policy and in that respect Mr. McMahon did<br />
not change a Gorton policy. So you've asked me who sits<br />
on these inter-departmental committees I've given you.<br />
If you later ask me if the inter-departmental committees<br />
have reported I expect I would tell you if they had.<br />
Q. Do you have a closed mind to the proposition of<br />
giving us inter-departmental committee reports? .8/ o </p>
<p>P. M. No, I haven't got a closed mind about it, but<br />
in these matters it is the Ministers who have to take the<br />
responsibility and I believe we will tell you the procedure<br />
by which we are arriving at our decisions. We'll not<br />
fob you off by refusing to tell you who are on these<br />
inter-departmental committees or when they have reported.<br />
Q. Will you be asking the heads of the Liberal and<br />
Country Parties whether they mind these documents being<br />
made public?<br />
P. M. I may, I mean one subject which is under<br />
consideration of course is the Moreshead Committee Report.<br />
Q. Sir, on the same subject, you say you think<br />
you should inquire of the preceding government whether a<br />
report should be made public?<br />
P. M. No, whether Cabinet documents should be made<br />
public, and these have all, we find, all these Committee<br />
Reports have been attached to Cabinet documents.<br />
Q. Well, Sir, during the election campaign you made<br />
quite a lot out of the Bureau of Transport Economics<br />
Report, You don't see any inconsistency in what you're<br />
telling us now with what you did during the campaign?<br />
P. M. No, well there are two matters there one I think<br />
was the sleepers, you know, the railway sleepers, the concrete<br />
or the hardwood you know what the Government's policy is<br />
there. It is calling for tenders for the most economic<br />
form of sleeper. The other one was about the B. T. E's<br />
reports on urban transport and I think I've written to<br />
all the Premiers on those reports on the investigations<br />
which the B. T. E. made into urban transport, and I'm not<br />
sure if I've written to the Tasmanian Premier because<br />
Tasmania was not covered in the original report. Melbourne 9/. </p>
<p>was not adequately covered because the Victorian<br />
Government hadn't given sufficient information. Some of<br />
the other States you remember hadn't given any information<br />
on underground railways, so I've obeen in correspondence,<br />
I think, with all the Premiers on that B. T. E. report on<br />
urban transport.<br />
Q. The Australian Proprietary Sugarmillers' Association<br />
said today that they had no objection to a public inquiry<br />
into the home price of sugar when next they apply for a<br />
variation in the price presumably upwards. Would you<br />
have any objection in principle to these State industry<br />
and Commonwealth talks on the home price of sugar being<br />
held in public in future?<br />
P. M. I'd want to discuss this with my Minister. I've<br />
not considered it.<br />
Q. Mr. Whitlam, a week ago, Senator Wriedt after<br />
conferring with you announced that he had approved the<br />
export of 30 Merino rams to China. Could you tell us<br />
the procedures by which this decision was arrived at. It<br />
seemed to many who wrote about it that the decision was<br />
inconsistent with Labor policy. Could you explain that<br />
and could you explain if an exception was made in that<br />
case purely to be nice to the Chinese?<br />
P. M. This was the only application that had been received<br />
by the present Government. It had no bearing on it that<br />
the destination was China. It's the only application for<br />
an export licence which the Government had received. We<br />
found that the deal has not been concluded and, accordingly,<br />
it is possible for us to have a referendum on the subject<br />
as the Party Platform prescribes.<br />
Q. On that particular subject, Sir </p>
<p>P. M. I think there are some other people that<br />
haven't asked a question.<br />
Q. I was going to ask you about the same question.<br />
P. M. Would you announce your name because people will<br />
understand why you take an interest in rural matters?<br />
Q. Richard Farmer: Do I take it from that answer<br />
that the rams will now not go to China?<br />
P. M. That will depend on the result of the referendum.<br />
Q. But Sir, what was announced last week is not now<br />
applicable. Is that right?<br />
P. M. No. Because the deal had not in fact been<br />
concluded it has not been concluded.<br />
Q. As a supplementary, who will take part in the<br />
referendum?<br />
P. M. That's been worked out.<br />
this for next Tuesday's Cabinet. We'll have a paper on<br />
Q. You can't give us any idea of whether it will<br />
be just graziers or<br />
P. M.<br />
affected. No, I can't. The Party Policy says the persons<br />
Q. On the supplementary to the supplementary would<br />
we be correct in drawing<br />
P. M. Max, you haven't asked a question.<br />
Q. It's not another supplementary, Sir. It's on<br />
another subject. Lord Carrington's visit at the end of<br />
the week which you and Mr. Barnard and other Ministers will<br />
see him / 11. </p>
<p>P. M. Yes.<br />
J-066I take it that you will reaffirm to him as<br />
tie p~ robably already knows that we will withdraw our<br />
infantry battalion group from Singaporeso<br />
P. M. We will not replace them at the end of their term<br />
of duty.<br />
Q. However I understand that several hundred, perhaps<br />
up to 500 or 600 Australian soldiers will remain in<br />
logistic support at the signal in Singapore. Has this been<br />
made clear too?<br />
P. M. Well I haven't spoken to Lord Carrington about<br />
this but of course it'll be made clear. I would imagine<br />
he's quite he knows what we've said on this..<br />
WJ. Why I asked was I think it was generally inferred<br />
that the whole 1300 or nearly the whole 1300 would be<br />
coming home. It now appears that perhaps only about half<br />
P. M. That would be an inaccurate inference.<br />
Q. Now finally could you indicate the other matters<br />
other than ANZAC and Defence matters that you may be<br />
discussing with Lord Carrington?<br />
P. M. I'm happy to discuss with Lord Carrington any<br />
matter which he thinks the British Government would like<br />
to discuss with me. There's no agenda. Lord Carrington<br />
knows Australia well and Mr. Barnard and I, I think, can<br />
claim to know him well because we knew him when he was<br />
British High Commissioner here in the late fifties and we<br />
always see him when we are in London.<br />
Q. But apart from what he might want to put to you,<br />
have you got anything specific to put to him apart from<br />
the Defence side? 12/. </p>
<p>12.<br />
P. M. I think -there'll be quite a wide ranging discussion.<br />
I'll have some hours with him and some of my other<br />
collieagues will be also in the talks for part of the time<br />
so I think there'll be quite a wide range of matters of<br />
mnutual interest. There is no agenda. Lord Carrington<br />
is a very easy person with whom to have a discussion.<br />
ve Sir, on the subject of Lord Carrington, will you<br />
be open to argument to change your mind on any subject<br />
which you raise?<br />
P. M. Of course, I always am.<br />
Q. But with Lord Carrington?<br />
P. M. Of course. And he's one of the most persuasive<br />
of men.<br />
Q. That's what I meant.<br />
P. M. Lord Carrington is not just another Lord. He<br />
is a very important member of the British Government and<br />
of the Conservative Party.<br />
Q. You've said Sir, he knows Australia well. fie<br />
knows Australian politics well, too, Sir?<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
W. He will therefore have some firm intentions.<br />
Will you be prepared to hear his arguments in view of that?<br />
P. M. Of course. Noblesse oblige.<br />
That's for Agence France Press.<br />
Q. Sir, on Merino rams. Can I ask why the decision...<br />
P. M. You gentlemen are taking a great interest in them..<br />
13/. </p>
<p>13.<br />
Q. Can I ask you why the matter wasn't referred<br />
initially to Cabinet instead of allowing Senator Wriedt<br />
to make a decision which was apparently in conflict with<br />
ALP policy?<br />
P. M. It was a matter which we hadn't got round to<br />
discussing. No one really was expecting an application<br />
on this subject. The next auctions were thought to be I<br />
think next June.<br />
Q. Mr. Whitlam, I thought the next auctions were<br />
on February 6 in Dubbo.<br />
P. M. Well, there are going to some in March, I now<br />
learn.<br />
Q. Just to return to this point, I know that<br />
Merinos aren't very important<br />
P. M. I wouldn't have thought so.<br />
Q. We're in the novel situation trying to work out<br />
procedures with the new Labor Government. It always struck<br />
us that it was part of the Labor Party philosophy that the<br />
opinions the conference decision were binding. The<br />
conference decision is quite unequivocal in this area<br />
P. M. That's right.<br />
Q. And both yourself and Mr. Wriedt in consultation<br />
have decided to override the conference decision. Is<br />
that correct?<br />
P. M. No.<br />
Q. Well it would seem to be, Sir, that the statement<br />
put out last week by Senator Wriedt under his name flew<br />
in the face of the conference advice. 14/. </p>
<p>14.<br />
P. M. We now find that it is possible that since the<br />
deal has not been made that we can go ahead with a<br />
referendum.<br />
Q. Was there any suggestion that the deal would have<br />
been made within a day or two before the Cabinet meeting?<br />
P. M. It could have been made, it was thought, last<br />
week. But in fact it's now found that it was not. The<br />
deal has not been concluded.<br />
Q. If I could sheepishly ask another question<br />
about sheep Sir, did Senator Wriedt confer with you on<br />
this subject can you confirm that? Were there any<br />
complaints after the decision was announced complaints<br />
from unions or anyone else that this flew in the face<br />
of Labor Policy, and can you explain to us why you were<br />
apparently prepared to breach Labor policy until you found<br />
that the deal hadn't gone through?<br />
P. M. There have been no complaints as far as I know<br />
from unions or anybody else on this subject. This is<br />
scarcely a matter of as great interest as it was four<br />
years or even one year ago.<br />
Q. Sir, on the question of a wider topic the<br />
uniform building code: There seems as though there'll be<br />
some State opposition to the introduction of a uniform<br />
building code. Have you any thoughts at this stage on how<br />
the Federal Government will persuade the State Governments<br />
to agree to the adoption of that policy that you pledged<br />
before the election?<br />
P. M. You are being very obscure. What State opposition<br />
do you expect? </p>
<p>Q. Melbourne and Queensland, Sir.<br />
P. M. Mr. Dickey has changed his mind in the past<br />
in fact in the last couple of weeks. In Queensland the<br />
question scarcely arises because there is a single building<br />
code throughout the Brisbane City Council area. If there<br />
was a single building code throughout the Melbourne and<br />
the Sydney Metropolitan areas the average house in those<br />
areas would cost $ 800 less.<br />
Q. But in the Queensland country areas, Sir, there<br />
are I think 134 different building codes required by the<br />
1ocal government authorities.<br />
P. M. The mischief doesn't occur in Queensland. Where<br />
the expense arises is where builders, architects, surveyors,<br />
tradesmen in general have to operate in an area where<br />
there are several conflicting codes. In Queensland, local<br />
government areas in general are larger than in the other<br />
States; and accordingly one does not have the waste of<br />
money in Queensland that one has in all the other States.<br />
The ordinary builder, surveyor, tradesman operating in any<br />
Queensland provincial city operates in the terms of a single<br />
building code. This is one reason why houses in general<br />
in Queensland cost less than in any of the other States.<br />
Q. In view of Mr. Dickey's statement, Sir, I<br />
wondered if you could give us an indication of how far<br />
you're prepared to support the Housing Minister in his<br />
endeavours to carry out policy pledges in the housing area<br />
with the States?<br />
P. M. I'm prepared to support Mr. Johnson, the Minister<br />
for Housing, completely in this area. I welcome the<br />
opportunity to point out that it's been known for years<br />
the Jennings family have proclaimed it for many years past<br />
that the average home costs now $ 800 more than it needs .16/. </p>
<p>16.<br />
to cost because there are so many conflicting building<br />
codes in the largest Australian cities; and these<br />
building codes depend not only on local government requirements,<br />
they also depend and in Queensland they can partly depend<br />
on this on the varying requirements of the lending<br />
authorities. The Commonwealth, under the Constitution,<br />
can have a very great influence on standardising the<br />
codes accepted by the lending institutions. The Constitution<br />
gives the Commonwealth Parliament power to legislate with<br />
respect to banking and insurance. The Commonwealth also<br />
of course makes most of the Government funds available for<br />
housing by way of Housing Commission and War Service Homes<br />
finance. Incidentally, the War Service Homes Act will be<br />
renamed Defence Services Homes Act because it will now of<br />
course be available to people in the Armed Services in<br />
general not just to those that have had active service<br />
overseas.<br />
Q. Sir, in the light of the continuing relatively<br />
high unemployment figures, is the Government restricting<br />
the growth the increased growth in the Public Service<br />
to the 3 per cent limit laid down by the previous Government?<br />
P. M. That still stands. At this stage it's not been<br />
considered by the new Government.<br />
Q. Can I ask a further one Sir: In view of the<br />
number of new Departments that have been established, will<br />
this not place a strain upon the existing if this limitation<br />
is continued?<br />
P. M. No. There can be savings in some areas such as<br />
Immigration and Labour and National Service.<br />
P. M. Gentlemen, I think this is understood. Anyone<br />
who hasn't yet asked a question gets one before those that<br />
have already had one get a second 17/. </p>
<p>17.<br />
Q. Can you tell me, Sir, in the light of the meeting<br />
soon in the field of Trade with New Zealand and also the<br />
meetings that have gone on this week in New Zealand<br />
between Australia and New Zealand and Canadian Dairy Boards,<br />
will we be likely to see co-operation between Australian<br />
and New Zealand on world markets including the Australian<br />
home market?<br />
P. M. This will all be discussed by the New Zealand<br />
Minister for Trade and Dr. Cairns, Mr. Freyer, and the<br />
Minister for Overseas Trade, Dr. Cairns, when they meet o<br />
It's quite soon isn't it?<br />
P. M. I can't see you in this distress Mr. Hawke,<br />
will you ask your third question?<br />
Q. There was a question that wasn't answered the<br />
last time. At the time Senator Wriedt and yourself made<br />
the decision about the export of Merinos, I take it that<br />
it wasn't known whether the Chinese deal would come into<br />
operation. Is it to be taken then that the decision to<br />
fly in the face of Labor Conference policy<br />
P. M. I won't have you saying that. There's no flying<br />
in the face of Labor policy by me or anybody else.<br />
Q. Well, is the fact that there was no flying in<br />
the face of Labor Party policies simply dependent on the<br />
fact that the deal didn't go through before the referendum?<br />
P. M. The decision today has been made in the light<br />
of the fact that we find that we can take a referendum<br />
or that we believe that we'll be able to hold a referendum.<br />
Q. Over the weekend the Leader of the Opposition<br />
advertised two positions on his staff which seemed to be<br />
considerably higher salary than that being paid 18/. </p>
<p>18,<br />
P. M. Yes, they did.<br />
Q. Has that been approved by the Government these<br />
salaries, and has it been approved by the Government, the<br />
Leader of the Opposition and other members including the<br />
Leader of the Country Party and the Deputy Leader of the<br />
Country Party have their staff arrangements been approved?<br />
P. M. Mr. Snedden was told that he could have two<br />
Private Secretaries as his predecessor had. He was not<br />
told what the salary would be. The salary appropriate<br />
for the positions will depend on the calibre of the<br />
persons attracted to them. On that, the Public Service<br />
Board's advice will be sought as it has been on all<br />
Ministerial staff appointments as regards salary.<br />
Q. Could I add something supplementary to that. If<br />
he was to advertise for a man at a salary of $ 20,000 a<br />
year and if you could get a man appropriate for that<br />
salary, does that mean that it would be approved?<br />
P. M. I would want to take the Public Service Board's<br />
advice. I don't fix salaries.<br />
Q. Sir, could you outline the proposed changes in<br />
the Arbitration system which Mr. Cameron is to develop<br />
tomorrow and specifically do they affect the penal<br />
clauses?<br />
P. M. I said earlier that if you want an explanation<br />
of these Mr. Cameron is willing to have a press conference<br />
tomorrow. Let him deal with it as a whole.<br />
Q. Sir, you said last weekend regional co-operation<br />
would be a cornerstone in Australia's foreign policy.<br />
Does that mean a significant increase in foreign aid to<br />
South-East Asia?<br />
P. M. Yes. 19/. </p>
<p>190<br />
2. Could you tell me whether Senator Wriedt got the<br />
approval or contacted any of his ministerial colleagues<br />
before he made his announcement last week?<br />
P. M. He spoke to me.<br />
Q. Did he have your approval?<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
Q. Sir, in view of the fact that there's been<br />
precious little evidence so far that any of the benefits<br />
of up-valuation will be passed on to the consumers in the<br />
form of lower prices, has the Government got any active<br />
policy in mind to ensure that the importers and manufacturers<br />
who take advantage of the up-valuation on the import side<br />
will pass the advantages on to the consumer?<br />
P. M. The Prices Justification Tribunal will cover that<br />
situation. Q. Sir, going back to your earlier remarks about<br />
secrecy, will it be possible for members of the public to<br />
look at papers presented to Ministers which involved the<br />
exercise of ministerial discretion and, in particular,<br />
would it be possible to look at those where the Treasurer<br />
decides whether there should be an inquiry into a takeover<br />
by a foreign company and specifically could I look at<br />
the ones involving the takeover of the Australian Equitable<br />
Insurance Company Limited by Samuel?<br />
P. M. I wouldn't think so. I guess that you're<br />
referring to the fact that our High Commissioner in<br />
Britain had an interest in the Company being taken over.<br />
Is that it? e. </p>
<p>Q. That was one thing that intrigued me, but..<br />
P. M. Yes, but I hope you don't think I'm too<br />
suspicious if I think that was the motivation of your<br />
question. Q No, not at all, Sir.<br />
P. M. There is a High Commissioner United Kingdom<br />
Act which lays down very strict provisions as to a ny<br />
shareholdings or directorates enjoyed by the High<br />
Commissioner. They are the most stringent conditions<br />
in any Federal or State Constitution or Statute as far<br />
as I know. Mr. Armstrong complied with them completely.<br />
Gentlemen, I would have thought that I might have been<br />
asked something about Sir William Dargie. I think<br />
we've exhausted our time and if you don't mind I want<br />
to get in something on this: Sir William Dargie wrote<br />
to me on 27 December. He got an acknowledgement on<br />
January from Dr. Wilenski. I wrote to him soon<br />
after the date doesn't appear on my copy. I wrote<br />
to him on 23 of January about the new Council for the<br />
Arts, and he acknowledged that letter on 25 January.<br />
In view of this chronology, I can't understand some of<br />
the press reports which are attributed to him. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
