<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7287</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ASIAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION OF AUSTRALIA CANBERRA - 11 FEBURUARY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/02/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007287.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ASIAN STUDIES ASSOCIATION OF AUSTRALIA<br />
CANBERRA -11 FEBRUARY 1988<br />
I am pleased that your annual conference this year includes<br />
the word Bicentennial in its title.<br />
Because this conference has an important contribution to<br />
make to the national celebrations and reappraisals which<br />
the Bicentenary has sparked.<br />
One of the more important lessons to be learned by all<br />
Australians during this Bicentennial year is the lesson of<br />
the benefits which flow from our cultural diversity.<br />
That diversity is one of our greatest national endowments.<br />
And the creation of a community in which all of us,<br />
regardless of our ethnic origin, share a commitment to the<br />
future of Australia, is one of our greatest national<br />
achievements. It is a rare achievement among the nations of<br />
the world and one which my Government is committed to<br />
nurturing. The Bicentenary commemorates the European settlement of<br />
Australia a settlement by people drawn initially from the<br />
British Isles.<br />
For most of the subsequent two hundred years, the influence<br />
of Britain and Ireland on our national institutions, and our<br />
national psyche, has been profound. It has been a bequest<br />
of which we can be proud.<br />
But it is important to recall, and not just at a gathering<br />
of this nature, the non-European contacts with Australia,<br />
which in some cases predate 1788 and which in many cases<br />
have formed powerful, if minority, elements of the<br />
Australian identity since then.<br />
I'm referring to the links forged with Australia over the<br />
years by Asian people:<br />
the Eastern Indonesians who gathered trepang on our<br />
north west shores for export to China; the thousands of<br />
Chinese who joined the gold rush; the Japanese pearl<br />
fishermen in Broome; and so on. 004372 </p>
<p>It was not until relatively recently that the majority of<br />
Australians came to appreciate the importance of their<br />
geographical proximity to Asia.<br />
Pearl Harbour and the fall of Singapore and the attacks on<br />
Darwin and other Australian cities, forced on us<br />
dramatically, the reality of our place in Asia.<br />
Since 1942, we have seen the end of our reliance upon<br />
Britain and a reorientation of our foreign policy and<br />
defence concerns to the Asian-Pacific region.<br />
We have witnessed the decline of European colonialism in our<br />
region and we have supported the independence aspirations of<br />
countries in our region. I might mention here the Chifley<br />
Labor Government's support for the Indonesian independence<br />
movement in 1945 and the Whitlam Government's grant of<br />
independence to Papua New Guinea.<br />
we have experienced the contraction of our British and<br />
European markets, and the expansion of the Japanese, east<br />
and south-east Asian markets.<br />
We have overcome our prejudices and done away with the White<br />
Australia policy, opening the way for the truly<br />
multicultural society of today in which our dynamism and<br />
cultural richness is owed in part to new arrivals from Asia.<br />
Today we find ourselves in a region containing a great part<br />
of the world's population; producing a great part of the<br />
world's GNP; embracing a great number of the religious and<br />
cultural traditions of the world; holding some of the<br />
world's largest armies; encompassing some of the principal<br />
exponents of free market capitalism and some of the<br />
principal interpreters of Marxism-Leninism; and containing<br />
some of the world's fastest-growing economies.<br />
Economically, the region encompasses the dynamo of Japan,<br />
the emerging power of the NICs, the newly industrialised<br />
countries, and the enormous potential of China.<br />
As I said last year in Singapore, when I had the honor of<br />
delivering the Singapore Lecture the single most enduring<br />
important event of our time is the emergence of China from<br />
its period of isolation.<br />
From Australia's point of view, the prospects are that<br />
greater enmeshment of our respective economies through, for<br />
example, joint ventures in mining and manufacturing projects<br />
in China and in Australia, will offer both sides enormous<br />
mutual benefit.<br />
While there are still societies which have failed to take<br />
advantage of the region's overall prosperity and whose<br />
people still live in poverty and hunger, in the region as a*<br />
whole trade and investment opportunities have abounded over<br />
the last quarter century. 004373 </p>
<p>The Western Pacific Asian economies share of world trade<br />
rose from just over 14% in 1971 to almost 22% by 1986. This<br />
year despite a slowing of average world economic growth to<br />
an estimated regional growth has remained at an<br />
average level of However China, Hong Kong, Singapore<br />
and Taiwan did even better than that, achieving growth rates<br />
of over 8% for the year.<br />
It is no exaggeration to say that as we enter our third<br />
century one of the most important and testing challenges<br />
this country faces is the challenge of finding our true<br />
place in Asia of recognising that our self-interest lies<br />
in our becoming an integral part of our region, a full<br />
participant in regional efforts towards peace and security,<br />
and an economic partner co-ordinating our economic skills<br />
and specialisations with those of Asia to the consequent<br />
prosperity of all.<br />
The assertion that Australia's future lies in Asia has<br />
become a commonplace of Australian political and commercial<br />
dialogue. But we are still learning to come to grips with the<br />
practical implications the challenges and opportunities<br />
of that assertion.<br />
It is obvious that at times we have drawn the wrong<br />
conclusions from the evidence of our geographical proximity<br />
to Asia.<br />
The tragedy of our Vietnam involvement demonstrated how<br />
costly was the predisposition of the Australian Government<br />
of the day to project onto the international screen the<br />
narrow concerns of its domestic political prejudices.<br />
But it is undeniable that there has been change gradual,<br />
painstaking but real change which has brought the<br />
Australian economy into closer alignment with that of our<br />
Asian neighbours.<br />
Despite the protectionist cast of post-war policies in<br />
Australia, there were enlightened and far sighted policies,<br />
thanks in particular to Sir John Crawford, which ensured<br />
that after the bitterness of war Australia could conduct<br />
constructive relations with Japan based on trade. The<br />
result was that when our traditional European markets closed<br />
in the 1960s, Australia was able in their place to develop<br />
the new and critically important export market of Japan.<br />
I am proud that my Government has been able to continue and<br />
dramatically expand that process of adjustment. We have<br />
taken on, as the essential task of our period in government,<br />
the long overdue process of economic reconstruction which<br />
will allow Australians increasingly to take advantage of the<br />
opportunities which our proximity to Asia provides.<br />
Asia will continue to demand substantial supplies of our<br />
primary commodities for decades to come. 004374 </p>
<p>4.<br />
But in addition, as the wealth of Asia increases and as the<br />
exchange rate pressures of industrial success begin to force<br />
the most rapidly growing exporters to restructure, Asia will<br />
also increasingly demand processed raw materials,<br />
manufactures and services.<br />
Australia's economic reconstruction is designed to put us in<br />
a good position to meet that demand just as in earlier<br />
times we geared up to supply burgeoning demand for raw<br />
materials. The changes which are occurring are far reaching.<br />
At their heart is the massive improvement in our<br />
international competitiveness brought about by the<br />
depreciation of the Australian dollar coupled with<br />
appropriate domestic policy adjustments.<br />
That improvement is particularly marked compared with the<br />
traditional manufacturing nations of Europe and the USA.<br />
It is also especially marked in the case of Japan, against<br />
which our real exchange rate has fallen by about 40 per<br />
cent, bestowing a substantial lift in competitiveness.<br />
However, it needs also to be appreciated that the<br />
improvement is much less dramatic compared to many of the<br />
other major exporters of Asia such as Korea, partly because<br />
of the exchange rate management regimes which have been<br />
adopted in those countries.<br />
But even in these cases, the reality is that the longer some<br />
of these countries continue to run large current account<br />
surpluses, the more likely it is that their exchange rates<br />
will remain under pressure to rise. This suggests that<br />
Australia's emerging competitiveness window will not close<br />
quickly so long as we control domestic costs.<br />
And that is the second element of our reconstruction<br />
strategy. This element is not just about wages though<br />
wages moderation has recently been and will remain an<br />
outstanding feature of the Australian economic scene.<br />
It is also about continuity of supply, the winding back of<br />
industrial disputes to what are historically low levels, and<br />
a determined effort to lift productivity. Australian<br />
workers and managements have shown a willingness to look<br />
hard at past practices to ensure that today we take the<br />
steps necessary to underwrite the steady improvement of our<br />
living standards by competing in non-traditional export<br />
markets. Indeed the growth in Australia's export awareness has also<br />
been critical to Australia's economic reconstruction.<br />
The high protective barriers erected around Australia in the<br />
post war decades had dulled the senses of our manufacturers.<br />
It encouraged domestically-oriented sales strategies and lax<br />
attitudes to quality and innovation. 004375 </p>
<p>But that is changing. Our economic policy has begun to<br />
dismantle the artificial props of protection and regulation<br />
which in the past have cosseted our industries. we have<br />
begun to replace them with regimes which not only encourage<br />
firms to compete but which provide a sufficiently flexible<br />
economy to allow the ensuing structural transformations to<br />
occur.<br />
One of my most gratifying duties as Prime minister is to<br />
visit many small and medium sized companies around<br />
Australia. I find time and again that companies which previously had<br />
never even considered exporting are now not only thinking<br />
about it but positively seeking out market niches for<br />
themselves and succeeding.<br />
one particularly pleasing statistic is that exports of<br />
Australian produced manufactures to Korea have grown by 154<br />
per cent in the two years to 1986-87.<br />
The latest estimates show that Research and Development<br />
expenditure in 1986-87 was 65 per cent higher than two years<br />
before, laying a solid basis for future growth and<br />
innovation. In addition our services sector, especially our tourist<br />
industry, is expanding rapidly.<br />
Yet for all of our progress, Australia's task of economic<br />
reconstruction is far from complete.<br />
Accordingly, as we have made clear, we entered our third<br />
term in office with a further agenda of reform in the<br />
micro-economy: a program of change in specific industries<br />
and institutions designed to complement and strengthen the<br />
continuing program of macro-economic reform.<br />
It is a substantial agenda one that my Government is<br />
committed to implementing.<br />
One of the most important elements of micro reform is in the<br />
field of education. We seek a number of goals, most<br />
significantly increased numbers of students completing<br />
secondary school; an enlarged capacity of our universities<br />
and other research institutions to focus their attention on<br />
productive and relevant research; and better application of<br />
our language skills to the task of improving our trading<br />
position. But the reform of attitudes of those in business has still a<br />
way to go.<br />
Too many of our entrepreneurs are prone to identify first<br />
the market opportunities available in the US and Europe and<br />
to pay less attention than they might to those emerging in<br />
the less familiar and, for many, untried markets of our<br />
region. 004376 </p>
<p>6.<br />
The key to overcoming such deficiencies lies in knowledgeknowledge<br />
of Asian business practices, knowledge of<br />
political and legal systems, knowledge of emerging economic<br />
conditions and knowledge of the key Asian languages.<br />
Let me remind you that of Australia's ten largest export<br />
markets last year, six were non-English speaking countries.<br />
Five are in Asia: Japan, China, South Korea,. Hong Kong and<br />
Taiwan. Moreover, our ten fastest growing major markets<br />
over the last four years have all been non-English speaking<br />
countries. Threeof them are in Asia: China, Hong Kong and<br />
India.<br />
Maintaining and improving-our language skills would<br />
undoubtedly improve the ability of our businesses to compete<br />
in these markets as well as foster a more enlightened<br />
understanding of the societies with which we trade.<br />
Indeed, it is recognition of the importance of languages and<br />
cultural understanding in developing our export and<br />
hospitality industries that has led the Government to<br />
emphasis the economic significance of our multicultural<br />
policies.<br />
Australia's communications with non-English speaking nations<br />
should be more often a dialogue of equals. It is not in our<br />
best interests to rely so heavily on our partners' English<br />
speaking abilities or the capacity of someone to provide<br />
an interpreter.<br />
My Government is already addressing the issue of expanding<br />
Australia's linguistic capacities.<br />
Nearly two years ago, while I was making an official visit<br />
to Japan, the Australian Government announced its decision<br />
to establish an Asian Studies Council.<br />
This Council was given the mission of strengthening Asian<br />
studies at every level of the Australian education system<br />
and helping Australian industry become better integrated<br />
with economic developments in the region.<br />
Last March, I announced the Government's endorsement of a<br />
National Policy on Languages. We have allocated full year<br />
funding of $ 28 million for 1988-89 to begin implementing<br />
this policy.<br />
The Asian Studies Council will be funded to undertake<br />
surveys on curriculum needs and teacher supply in schools,<br />
and to research demand for Asian related skills in industry.<br />
An inquiry into the teaching of Asian languages and Asian<br />
studies in higher education is also to be undertaken.<br />
The information gathered will be used in the development of<br />
a national secondary schools curriculum for Asian languages<br />
and Asian studies together with appropriate teaching<br />
materials. 004377 </p>
<p>7.<br />
More recently the Council, under the able chairmanship of DrI<br />
Stephen Fitzgerald, has produced a report on a national<br />
strategy for the study of Asia in Australia.<br />
I am not in a position to comment in detail on how the<br />
Government will respond to the report since it has not yet<br />
been formally received by the Government and has not<br />
received any Cabinet consideration.<br />
But I believe some comments to this audience would be<br />
appropriate. The Asian Studies Council has found that scarcely any<br />
Australian in a position of leadership in business,<br />
government, education or the media has a command of an Asian<br />
language.<br />
The Council adds that of all students presenting for<br />
Matriculation, only two per cent take an Asian language, and<br />
a significant number of these are native speakers.<br />
we are deluding ourselves if we think that state of affairs<br />
will allow us to compete to our full potential in Asian<br />
markets, or to negotiate successfully with Asian partners,<br />
or to extend hospitality sufficiently to Asian tourists, or<br />
to break down permanently the cultural barriers with our<br />
Asian neighbours.<br />
The report sets out a general objective of making the<br />
Australian population ' Asia-literate' by the year 2000. It<br />
seeks widespread command of Asian languages in the<br />
Australian community and a more integrated and thorough<br />
study of Asia in our schools and tertiary institutions. It<br />
advocates a more ' Asia literate' conduct of Australian<br />
business, government and cultural relations with Asia.<br />
These are ambitious goals. But I believe they are worth<br />
working for. Achieving them will require extensive business<br />
involvement as well as a commitment by government. At base,<br />
they require a change in attitude by the Australian people<br />
themselves. There are, I am happy to say, signs that business is<br />
beginning to face this challenge. A survey of key decision<br />
makers taken last year showed that overwhelmingly Australian<br />
employers want to see a much stronger emphasis on Asian<br />
languages, a greater emphasis on the study of Asia, at both<br />
school and tertiary levels, and programs on Asia given a<br />
much higher priority in tertiary courses in business<br />
studies, economics and management, in engineering, science<br />
and the technologies, and courses leading to employment in<br />
the tourist industry.<br />
some major employers have already recognised the importance<br />
of skills and are beginning to adjust recruitment and<br />
training practices Qantas, for example, is taking a<br />
leading role with its International Communications Skills<br />
Improvement Program. 004378 </p>
<p>For its part, the Government has taken the initiative by<br />
putting in train the implementation of the National Policy<br />
on Languages.<br />
The Asian Studies Council, in conjunction with the Office of<br />
Multicultural Affairs and the National Accreditation<br />
Authority for Translators and Interpreters, is also<br />
contributing to this process by co-sponsoring a conference<br />
later this year on " Languages for a Competitive Australia".<br />
The term ' Asian' is in itself a shorthand term used for<br />
convenience. The reality of the term covers a myriad of<br />
cultures and languages: they defy instant comprehension let<br />
alone mastery. We are talking about long-term planning not<br />
short-term interim measures. Even so, this government has<br />
provided the greatest stim~ ulus to the teaching of ' Asian'<br />
language, ever undertaken in Australia.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Let me close by stressing the role which you must play in<br />
improving our nation's capacity to understand Asia and to<br />
compete successfully with it.<br />
Most of you are Asia experts. Many of you have spent a<br />
lifetime studying Asia. Some of you stand at the pinnacle<br />
of your profession in the breadth of your knowledge and<br />
scale of your mastery of Asian issues.<br />
If we as Australians are to bring Asia more fully into our<br />
intellectual universe, we rely on you to help us and to<br />
share your expertise, to the maximum extent possible, with<br />
us. That way we will find ourselves not only meeting the<br />
economic challenges we face in Asia but also coming to a<br />
deeper understanding of our neighbours and ultimately, I<br />
believe, of ourselves. 004379 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
