<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3254</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTIONS - 13 MAY 1974 - THE POLICY SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA - HON EG WHITLAM QC MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003254_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ELECTIONS 13 MiAY 1974<br />
THE POLICY SPFCl<br />
THF' PRIM~ E MINISTER OF AUSTRbALIA6<br />
HON. E. G. TV71ITLAM, -P<br />
9 . BIArKTO' TN,,<br />
29 APRIL. 1974<br />
A IT. S t. A"<br />
INDExeo Co~ y.<br />
Jjj. . A U 8 r I I A I I A 6q </p>
<p>Men and Women of Australia,<br />
Just 17 months ago, I stood here, and from this<br />
place and from this city I asked you to choose for Australia<br />
a new team, a new program, a new drive for equality of<br />
opportunities. You gave us a clear mandate to go ahead with<br />
our program for the next 3 years. For 17 months we have<br />
driven ourselves to carry out you;: mandate, to carry out the<br />
program I placed before you. Now the government you elected<br />
for 3 years has been interrupted in mid-career. Our program<br />
has been brought to a halt in mid-stream.<br />
Everything we promised, everything we have achieved,<br />
everything you expected of us your expressed hopes for<br />
yourselves, your families, your nation all this is suddenly Lt=<br />
threatened. It is threatened by the actions of the men you oco<br />
I rejected a mere 17 months ago.. It is threatened by the actions<br />
of men elected to the Senate not in 1972, but in 1967 and 1970.<br />
It is threatened by men who refused to stand by the umpire's<br />
verdict your verdict to give , s a chance, to give you a<br />
chance, to give Australia a new chance.<br />
These men who have falsified democracy now ask<br />
you to turn back. Turn back to what? Think again how it n<br />
was when you elected us in ! 972. Unemployment was at its " 4 A<br />
worst for 10 years. Our rate of gr: owth was one of the<br />
world's worst a paltry 20. The Australian dollar was<br />
grossly undervalued. Foreign money was. flooding in to buy<br />
up Australian resources and Australian industries on the chieap.<br />
Accelerating numbers of nigrants w/ ere leaving in disillusion.<br />
Australia was still deeply involved in the war in Viet Nam.<br />
Our whole foreign policy was based on hostility to China. We<br />
were running an army on the cheap by conscripting young men.<br />
There were young men in prison foe their conscience.<br />
Australia was a. d2ep3y divided nation. Our young people were<br />
becoming alienated frorr. the mainstream of Australian society.<br />
S The disrespect in which our nation.-al leadership the Liberals<br />
were held at home had spread to cidre~ ect for Australia abroad.<br />
Think again, indeed!<br />
Mark today's contrast. The Australian economy i<br />
one of the most buoyant and vigorous in the world.<br />
Full employTmnt has been restored. Business<br />
activity is at its highest for a decade, company profits are<br />
at record levels and business expectations are at an all time<br />
high. Through our economic policies and our social security<br />
program, Australia's prosperity i3 becoming more fairly shared<br />
than ever before. Abroad, Australia has never stood so tall. We have<br />
buried old animosities. We dare-hold in new respect by old<br />
friends and allies. Never in her history has Australia been<br />
more secure. </p>
<p>2<br />
We have ended national division, national<br />
disunity by ending our involvement in Viet Nam, and ending<br />
conscription. We have opened up new and expanding markets for As,<br />
our farm products. By placing family reunion for migrants above mere f'e<br />
recruiting, we have stopped the rmigrant drift. t<br />
For the first time Australia has a government<br />
determined to promote Australian ownership and control of<br />
Australian industries and resources. 0 N( 446 ' IR<br />
O-^ N&amp; oub<br />
For the first time fcr a generation Australia has<br />
a government dedicated to equal opportunity for all its<br />
citizens. We have more than doubled spending on schools. d JLu-cJG<br />
We have abolished fees at universities, colIee 3 of zaivanced<br />
education and going one better than oar pledge at technical<br />
schools. For the first time Australia has a government<br />
determined to make the conditions of life more equal for all<br />
Australians, wherever they live in Australia.<br />
For the first time Australia has a government WQ A<br />
seriously concerned to give equality of opportunity to women.<br />
For the first time Australia has a national<br />
government involving itself directly in the affairs of. our<br />
cities. For the first time Australia has a government ready an<br />
to give local government direct access to the national finances.<br />
For the first time Australia has a nrational<br />
government prepared to co-operate in renewing our decaying<br />
urban transport systems. 27<br />
For the first time Australia has a national<br />
government determined to fulfil its con: stitutional obligationAa1<br />
towards the aboriginals L<br />
For the first time Australia has a government<br />
determined to preserve, protect and enhance Australia's<br />
national estate our natural and historical inheritance,<br />
what we keep from our past, what we transmit to the future.<br />
For the first time Australia Las a national<br />
government which recognises the significance of the arts and<br />
artists in our society. Our support for the arts has<br />
released an unparallelled burst-of creativity in this nation. N. ox </p>
<p>These achievements are just some of the fruits of<br />
programs based on expert advice. . Je sought and obtained the Ow
co-operation of the most highly qualified Australian men and<br />
women to enquire into and to report upon basic requirements<br />
in Australia's social and economic structures. Tnese reports 5a4<br />
are public. The work of these enquiries and commissions is<br />
the basis of a continuing, coherent. comprehensive program.<br />
The new initiatives 1 announce tonight are the new dimensions<br />
and expanded fruits of this work.<br />
This premature election means that these fruits<br />
are being denied the Australian people. It has meant deferring<br />
our entire legislative program. ' Oe have this legislation<br />
ready to go; it is crucial legislation, and we have it ready.<br />
We ask you to send us back to get on with the business your<br />
business. In the Parliament that has been dissolved four<br />
referendum bills had been twice rejected by the Senate. Under<br />
the Constitution the Governor-General is submitting each of<br />
them to the electors. Six other bills had been twice rejected<br />
by the Senate. That is why under the Constitution the<br />
Governor-General has dissolved both Houses of Parliament.<br />
The Senate had also rejected nine other bills.<br />
Some of them had been introdiuced a" second time. When the<br />
Parliament was dissolved 24 bills were waiting to be passed.<br />
The government will reintroduce all these rejected and<br />
pending bills in the new Parliament. Also,* 107 new bills<br />
have been already drafted and are awaiting introduction in<br />
the new Parliament; a further 104 bills are being drafted on<br />
the government's instructions.<br />
I Our programs the programs you endorsed in 1972<br />
had been developed over the previous si; x , ears. They were<br />
published policies; they were debated in public; they were<br />
scrutinized in Parliament. Time and time again as an<br />
Opposition, we put positive proposals up for debate in<br />
Parliament. By contrast our opponents have never since put<br />
up a single proposal for examination by eitier Parliament or<br />
the public. When they forced tnis election, none of us knew<br />
anything of what they proposed. All we knew was what they<br />
opposed. And that's really all we know now.<br />
In defence of their wealthy friends and vested t<br />
interests, they rejected the democratic principle of equal<br />
electorates; they blocked attempts to democratise and modernise<br />
the trade union movement; they denied representation in the<br />
Senate to the people of the inorthern Territory and the<br />
Australian Capital Territory; they sought ' L deny to local<br />
government direct access to national revenues and borrowings;<br />
they preserved for foreign mining iaterests the right to<br />
exploit our of f-shore resources. -They preserved the inequity,<br />
inefficiency and injustice of an anti{ uated healtA scheme.<br />
They have prevented one million of our fellow-citizens from<br />
having any protection against hospital and medical charges. </p>
<p>4<br />
By shelving the Trade Practices Bill they left<br />
the door open to monopolies and big corporations to fix<br />
prices, organise cartels and exploit the Australian customer.<br />
By shelving the Ausralian ndustry Development Corporation<br />
Bill they blocked the most effective instrument for ensuring<br />
Australian control of our industries and developing new<br />
industries. They left the door open to foreign takeovers and<br />
foreign exploitation of the Australian economy. Yet you had<br />
given us a clear mandate for every one of these proposals they<br />
have opposed and obstructed.<br />
These are the men who forced a premature election.<br />
Now they are asking you to make a judgement affecting your<br />
lives, your families and their welfare, your nation's future<br />
for the next three years on the basis of policies cooked up in<br />
the last three weeks. When they destroyed my government's<br />
power to govern they had no more idea of what their policies<br />
would be than you did. All they knew is that they were out AW<br />
S to destroy the Whitlam Government. The Leader of the g<br />
Opposition in the Senate admitted on the night of the<br />
dissolution of Parliament " T'e embarked on a course some<br />
12 months ago to bring about a House of Representatives<br />
election". In the five weeks that the Senate sat this year<br />
votes were taken on 43 occasions. The three opposition<br />
parties combined to defeat the government on 42 of those<br />
occasions. They had made the parliament unworkable.<br />
What a spectacle This must present to the world<br />
a world where everywhere democracy is under challenge. In<br />
no other country in the world could an Upper louse, elected<br />
3 years ago ' and 6 years ago, use an outdated majority, a<br />
chance majority, to bring down the government elected by the<br />
people only one and one-third years ag.<br />
SAnd in Australia this had never been before<br />
attempted by the Senate. Until our opponents lost office,<br />
after 23 years, it had never even been threatened in the<br />
Australian Parliament. One result of their actions is that for only the<br />
third time in Australia's history, we are to have an election<br />
for the whole Senate as well as the House of Representatives.<br />
In addition, you will be asked to support referen. um proposals<br />
to make the Australian democracy more equitable and more<br />
efficient. REFERENDUMS The last occasion on which you voted for the whole F&amp; W<br />
of the Senate and the House of Representatives was 1951. The<br />
first referendum proposal is desicn-i: to avoid the situation<br />
after 1951. Barely two years aftr the 1951 double dissolution<br />
there had to be an election for h&amp; af the Senate ' and then a year<br />
later a separate House of Representatives election. It is<br />
quite wrong to suggest that the present dissolution of both<br />
Houses of itself synchronises future elections for them. 4 </p>
<p>It does nothing-. of the sr. The-ehiections for the two Houses<br />
will remain out of kilter' unless you accept our referendum<br />
proposal. Australia has too -many elections. Since 1963 we<br />
have had a national election every, 1j years. That is not<br />
good for Australia. It does not make for good government or<br />
for a healthy Parliament.<br />
* Australia needs a period of stable government.<br />
Australia needs a period of stable lecadership. we enter upon<br />
a timne of difficult deci; sions. Such-decisions can * be taken'<br />
* only by a united governme-at1 a united ' leadership, a united -Party,*<br />
a united nation. Anid ou-r government alone offers such unity,<br />
-Such leadership. We need a Parliament which re'fects the will of the<br />
W people as fully and accurately as pom3ible. Our referen'dum<br />
proposals are designed to achieve this.<br />
-Our proposal to synchro-iise elections fo h-Senate<br />
and House of Representatives was reccmmended as far back as-<br />
1958t ye. a1part Contitution Review Committee establishd<br />
under Sir Robert 21enzies in 195G. The second proposa. is to--<br />
allow the Constitucion to be c-Ilt_ red if a m~ ijority of all the<br />
electors in Australia approve anC ilsd a majority of the<br />
electors in not less than one-half of th,! States; this<br />
proposal was also recomaended by the Ct-onstitution Review<br />
Comiteein 1958. The third proposal is that after July 1976<br />
there should be equal electorates in the Uois!_: of Representatives<br />
and in every State Douse of Parliament; thle inethod has been<br />
perfected for the. U. S. Congress and State legislatures by the<br />
U. S. Supreme Corurt over the lz. t 10( years; in Australia'it will<br />
be applied by the High Court. The Sen~ ate o-pposed your having<br />
a vote on any of these issues, eve, th-ose recommended as far back<br />
as 1958. But where tha Senate tcerejects referendum proposals,<br />
the Constitution gives you, peopl. e, the right to vote on<br />
them regardless of the Scnates re-Jection-.---<br />
* It is not i thoui-s. gpifi canc3 that our opponents<br />
-used their -nui-ibe-Ls in the Senate' ock your chance of<br />
having your say as -electo,-s on pronoSals to make Australia<br />
a more stable deniocracY anid a more. iaqial democracy. Despite<br />
their obstruction, you will1, at referendumns on the same day<br />
as the elections, be able to. hav -_, our say.<br />
Iknow that thesc matters require your thought and:<br />
your time if you are to make a reasonable judgement. I ask you<br />
again as I asked you two weeks ago, give close thought to<br />
them and five minutes of your-time for the future of Australia<br />
on the 18 N. ay. </p>
<p>THE ECONOMY Ue Australians all now face together one of the<br />
great historic challenges of our time; to make democracy<br />
work; to make the parliamentary system work; and make it<br />
work better. We share this challenge with most other<br />
parliamentary democracies. Equally, with them, with all<br />
major trading nations, with all mixed economies, we share the<br />
problem of inflation. We are all seeking ways by which the<br />
expectations, the wishes, the aspirations, the hopes of every<br />
member of the community can be reconciled with freedom, good<br />
order, security, stability. There is no simple answer, no<br />
one answer, no easy cure. But if a solution is to be found<br />
or even attempted, we need a strong, courageous, united<br />
Sleadership. We need at the same time, a national leadership<br />
passionately concerned about the preservation of the democratic<br />
system and a leadership compassionately concerned to protect<br />
the weaker members of the community. I suggest to you that<br />
our government, since you elected it only 17 months ago, has<br />
Sshown such dedication and has shown its capacity for firm and<br />
courageous decisions decisions which were sometimes<br />
initially unpopular, opposed by powerful interests, but which<br />
have proved their correctness and which have proved the<br />
doomsayers wrong. World events and the policies of -our predecessors<br />
inevitably meant a higher rate of inflation in 1973 than in<br />
1972. We have acted firmly to moderate these pressures.<br />
s And these policies are beginning to work inflation<br />
has slowed. All our efforts to curb inflation have been opposed<br />
or obstructed by our opponents. Where we took administrative<br />
action, they criticised. Where we took legislative action,<br />
they obstructed. Where we sought more powers from you by<br />
way of referendum, they opposed. Uhere we have sought<br />
co-operation with the States, governments of the same political<br />
persuasion as our opponents have failed to pass the necessary<br />
legislation. SA1dministratively, we cut tariffs by 25% to. reduce<br />
the price of imports without damaging Australian industries.<br />
We have twice revalued the Australian dollar reflecting its<br />
true status as one of the world's strongest currencies.<br />
By legislation, we have tried to promote competition.<br />
As long ago as 1963 the present Chief Justice Sir Garfield<br />
Barwick pointed to the need to outlaw collusion between<br />
corporations in fixing prices above their genuinely competitive<br />
level. Last September we introduced legislation to do just that.<br />
Our opponents in the Senate combined-' three times, not just to<br />
oppose this legislation, but to prevent it from even being<br />
debated. 6 </p>
<p>7<br />
Only the Labor State of South Australia has<br />
cod-operated in setting up land commissions to stop the spiral<br />
in residential land prices. The average price for a home<br />
site in Adelaide is $ 5,000 and has begun to stabilise. The<br />
average price in Sydney is $ 18,500 and is still rising.<br />
Not content with obstructing our efforts, our<br />
opponents in their election promises now propose economic.<br />
vandalism. Their policies mean soaking the average<br />
Australian wage and salary earner. They mean cutting back<br />
on opportunities for creative employment. They mean the same<br />
sort of unemployment Mr Snedden as Treasurer created two years<br />
ago. They mean the same rise in indirect taxes which they<br />
imposed when in government they pretended to reduce income tax<br />
in 1970. They mean disrupting our program for help to all<br />
Australian schools. Their policies mean that once again, as<br />
happened so often in the long life of the previous government,<br />
O Australian children year after year will be set back in<br />
their opportunities. When ' ir Snedden speaks of cutting back<br />
on government spending he means cutting back on schools, on<br />
health, on social security. They are the only fields where<br />
meaningful cutbacks can be made. lhy should the children of<br />
Australia, the migrants, the old, the handicapped, the sick,<br />
the retarded, the aborigines, the disadvantaged groups pay<br />
the price for r Snedden's economic fantasies? Let our<br />
opponents say clearly, honestly, unequivocally, that their<br />
weapons in the fight against inflation in Australia are. to be<br />
the children of Australia, the aged of Australia, the<br />
handicapped of Australia, the aborigines of Australia, the<br />
disadvantaged people in our Australian community. For that<br />
is what their policies mean. These are the consequences, the<br />
undoubted consequences of their rag bag of proposals.<br />
Forget their half--bahed proposals and look at the<br />
performance their performance of obstruction in Opposition,<br />
Stheir performance of mismanagement in government.<br />
You will recall how for a disestrous week before<br />
Christmas 1971 the then coalitioc* 9-g-.'-rnment nearly fell<br />
a'part about the internatioual v. 1iue of the Australian dollar.<br />
The Leader of the Country Party the man who wants to be<br />
Treasurer, the man whose remedy fcr inflation is to double the<br />
price of oil threatened to ., ilk out of the government<br />
unless he got his way. And get his disastrous way he did.<br />
Their division as much as their actual decision to devalue did<br />
great harm to Australia in those days. Australia cannot afford<br />
a repetition yet nri. thiig is m'ore certain, than that the<br />
return of our opponents to government would mean deep,<br />
unbridgeable and continuing division and damage on the matter<br />
of the value of the Australian dollar. Division on such a<br />
matter means undermining the strength of the Australian dollar<br />
u </p>
<p>8<br />
Following the decision in 1971, this nation was flooded with<br />
millions of dollars of unwanted foreign capital, capital which<br />
sought to buy Australia up on the cheap. You must not allow<br />
it to happen again.<br />
This vast infusion of foreign money was one of the<br />
root cauces of the inflationary problem which we have faced<br />
ever since we came into government. The men who created<br />
that problem now ask you to give them back the government.<br />
The same men created the major economic prohierm much more<br />
than an economic problem a social and huxian problem which<br />
we first had to face when we came into government. It was<br />
the problem of unemployment. The Budget of 1971 created<br />
Australia's worst unemployment for 10 years. The man who<br />
made that Budget, the Treasurer who presided over that<br />
unemployment, is the present Leader of the Opposition. We<br />
promised to restore full employment. We have restored it.<br />
Every comparable country in the world shares the problem of<br />
inflation. Ile are distinct from all those countries in this:<br />
that in Australia alone, there is._ no unemployment; in<br />
Australia alone, unemployment and inflation do not march side<br />
by side. Our opponents by their divisions,, by their decisions,<br />
started the new round of inflation in Australia. Yet<br />
simultaneously, they created unemployment. And these are the<br />
men who ask you to give them control over your economic-affairs.<br />
V.. </p>
<p>9<br />
TAXATION The new prosperity our policies have created, the<br />
restoration of full employment we have achieved, the rise in<br />
wages and salaries has brought new problems, in particular for<br />
the lower and middle wage and salary earners. It has created<br />
a whole new range of problems and new inequities in the field of<br />
personal taxdtion. In Septenber 1972 our predecessors appointed members<br />
of a Committee under the chairmanship of Ir. Justice Asprey to<br />
inquire into the structure and operation of the present<br />
Commonwealth taxation system and to formulate proposals for<br />
improving the system by making changes in it, abolishing any<br />
existing form of taxation or introducing new forms of taxation.<br />
The Committee was to have regard to the effects of the present<br />
system upon the social, economic and business organisation of<br />
the community and upon the economic and business organisation<br />
Sof the community and upon the economic and efficient use of the<br />
resources of Australia and to the desirability of a fair<br />
distribution of the burden of taxation and of a system of<br />
collection which not unduly complex and did not involve the<br />
public or the administration in undue difficulty, inconvenience<br />
or expense. The Treasurer, Crean, an:-I have had discussions<br />
with the Asprey Committee, which will make a report to us by<br />
I June. Its recommendations will therefore be taken into account<br />
in this year's Budg et, when we shall be giving urgent consieeration<br />
to the restructuring of the taxation system.'<br />
In my Policy Speech in I! ovember 1972 I promised that<br />
we would expand the terms of reference of the Asprey Committee<br />
to include State and Local Government taxation systems and<br />
Scollection methods. The Premiers of South Australia, Western<br />
Australia and Tasmania agreed to coopel. te but the responses of<br />
the other Premiers made it impossible for the Committee to carry<br />
out the expanded inquiry.<br />
Last month, however,. at a Constitutional Convention<br />
standing committee which I chaired, it was decided that Commonwealth<br />
and State officers should confer and report on the<br />
respective occupancy by the Commonwealth, State and Local<br />
Governments of the fields of income taxation, excise dutie2 And<br />
sales tax, vehicle and fuel taxes, death duties and land and<br />
property taxes. ' e shall be consulting fully with the States<br />
on those items of shared taxation, such as death duties, on<br />
which our officers are to report.<br />
The Treasurer has already announced in Parliament that<br />
the estate duty law is to be amended to e-tablish a Board of Relief<br />
to hear applications for release from liability for duty in cases<br />
of serious hardship. Such a Board has proved its worth in the<br />
case of income tax. The estate duty board will be empowered to<br />
release an estate from all or part of the duty payable where<br />
ayment would impose serious hardsh; ip on a beneficiary or<br />
beneficiaries and where relief granted would be for the benefit<br />
of beneficiaries so affected. </p>
<p>10<br />
One aspect of estate duty is particularly unjust<br />
the taxation of the matrimonial home. This practice constitutep<br />
a failure to recognise the role wo; ien play in our society. The<br />
person who looks after the home and the family contributes as<br />
much to the economic value of the family home as the person who<br />
goes to work. In estates in which the matrimonial home or an<br />
interest therein passes to the widow or widower of the deceased<br />
the value of the deceased's interest, up to a limit of $ 35,000,<br />
shall be excluded from the dutiable value of the estate; the<br />
prooortion of the value exempted from duty will be reduced by<br />
2% for every $ 1,000 above this limit.<br />
This is one of the very few completely new undertakings<br />
in this policy speech. It will cost only about $ 10 million<br />
per year but will ensure that no widow or widower will have<br />
to sell the family home in order to meet federal estate duty.<br />
The present income tax law allows concessional<br />
deductions for dependants to Australian resident taxpayers only<br />
where the dependants are themselves resident in Australia. In<br />
Sthe case of a migrant who comes to Australia intending to bring<br />
his wife and children out to this country as soon as he has made<br />
Sa home for them, a period of 5 years is regarded as a reasonable<br />
time for the wife and children to join the migrant in Australia.<br />
If he maintains the family during this period income tax<br />
Sdeductions for the dependants are allowable to him.<br />
However, migrants who . are maintaining dependent<br />
relatives overseas with no view to bringing them to Australia,<br />
or who may be prevented from bringing them to Australia by<br />
restrictive emigration policies in force in some countries, are<br />
unable to qualify for a tax deduction for dependants. It is my<br />
Government's intention to extend the provisions of the income<br />
tax laws governing dependants' deductions so as to entitle people<br />
in these situations to the taxation advantages availale already<br />
to all of us maintaining dependent relatives who reside in<br />
Australia.<br />
SCUSTOMER PROTECTION The Australian Government has already taken<br />
important measures to protect the -safety and economic interests<br />
of customers. They include the 25% tariff cut and decisions<br />
to. ensure cheaper colour television sets and radios. 7iTen<br />
passed, the Trade Practices Bill will make safety stanrlrds<br />
mandatory, and will require specified information to be disclosed<br />
when specified goods an1 services are offered for sale.<br />
Collusive price-fixing by corporations , ill he prohibited and<br />
the protection of customers will be promoted through the<br />
encouragement of a competitive climate in industry. Last year<br />
we established the Interim Commission on Consumer Standards,<br />
which has recommended that a permanent body.. succeed it.<br />
We will establish a Bureau of Customer Protection.<br />
The Bureau will ensure that consumer interests are properly<br />
consulted and represented in all aspects of governmental<br />
activity on consumer protection. </p>
<p>.11<br />
The PILu~ trali-in Coveri::. ent la~ hor9 tories twi 1 he<br />
or inntJ~ LeLoward:: pro-luct T0i1 : tfwr esults Of suoch tests<br />
b ie. e t u1 l. c.<br />
MlEW STRUCTURES The greatest burden on the Australian economy,<br />
the b~ iggest drag on our nr~ timnl prwosperity is the inefficient,<br />
costly structures iLnheritted frcii L1.0 p&amp; SL. The great thieme of<br />
our legislative program th~ e program now disrupted and deferred<br />
by this premature electir) has ber; en one oi: refLorm and<br />
renovation. Wie rccognise-d from i-he heginninq that thf.! ref'orms<br />
vie wiere sceeking for Austra] izon socie ty -for a more -ju! st and<br />
humane Australian society would be possible only through<br />
reforms in the structure of tha government itself.<br />
9 The accumulated dcadwocd of inefficiency of our<br />
urban sprawl, uncoordinated local government bodies, too many<br />
trade unions, obsolete communic at ions, archaic public transport<br />
systems, lack of hospitals; where most people now live, our land<br />
* use and abuse, the duplication of es. sentiail scervices because of<br />
a misinterpretation of the true mcnaningy of fedUeralism, an<br />
education system which until latyear never took adequate<br />
* account of needs it is all these archaisms, anachronisms, and<br />
inefficiencies which generation after generation, have built<br />
into the Australian economy such-. high costs for such poor returns.<br />
And this is precisely what we. hacvb attempted to reform and<br />
restructure institutions and system,. s whose ine ffici~ erncy or<br />
antiquity impose a tremendous buirden on th'c Australian economy<br />
and the Australian Society.<br />
The onsitution~ i~ a~ s~ " There shall bie ah<br />
Inter-State Ccmrission". One2 of the first acts of the Menzies<br />
Government in 1950 -was to repeal the act establishing the<br />
Conssion pqc . oenmn n9-1: 21. o The<br />
Government will re-estabis omsso h _ yhea r.<br />
Vle hav'e completely * ccmoulelJle thoe epartmental<br />
* structure of the Australian Governmcm! t. To qive2 organisational<br />
thrust to our new priorities we -hfivo created new; depa--rtmncnts<br />
Mlinerals and Energy, Urban and Regional Davelopnient, Ahoriginal<br />
Affairs, Environment and Con serva tici and Horthern Devalopi nent.<br />
We have remodelled and reinviqrritc'd othw-r departments and! ltave<br />
amalgamated and are amalgamcat~ ln; st'L! 3. others. Vie Ihave, a rnoct,<br />
efficient administration. Even r,. or e: important, the national<br />
government is now equippe( 3 involve itsel-i-in new important<br />
and urgent fields. In 1972 1 said:<br />
'" We shall need the help and seek the helrh of the<br />
best Australians. W'e shiall rely of course on<br />
Australia's gireat Publ) Iic Service. tic shiall seek<br />
and wielcome. ad ice arid co,--operatormbyn<br />
the confines Canb , Xra':. </p>
<p>12<br />
To promote further the efficiency of the Australian Puh-Ii qervice<br />
w; e shall establish a R~ oyal Cornnision. It will b; e headed by one<br />
of PAustralia's most dTstin uished and experienced former public<br />
servants a great servant of the Australian people Dr. H-. C.<br />
Coombs. I have already announced, our acceptance of the<br />
recommenda tions of Sir James \ lernon's I1: oyid Coi-miission on the<br />
Post Office -that tl'ut Post Office __ snould-be I-: ndeyeuident of the<br />
control of the Publ--i; cService Board. an. that a separate<br />
Australian Postal Coiymiru~ iov' nd Au: tralianTeleco nunications<br />
C ORnissron ( incor--Lc-rat iriq the 07ex seas icmuriain<br />
Commtission) should be established. 1e( shill follow the same<br />
principle in the transpurt fielld for the Australian<br />
National RaiJlwa s, our: airportKri &amp; tcve' q oprations and,<br />
~~ Lti wththe respective Statas, the Mewcastle dockY ardl andI.<br />
We have armred the admi nistrative machine with new<br />
capabiliti's -and new organs to c-a1 with the increasingly<br />
complex and difficult problem's ofL planning tor the needs of -a<br />
growing iridustrizl soci ety. Srme ofL -% he new~ bodies were given<br />
permanent statutory form, slich as th-&amp; schools Commission, the<br />
Social welfare Commission, T. he Isat and flea3. th Services<br />
Commission, the Prices Jus t. fijat. ion Tribunal and the Pipeline<br />
Authority; others ha-d tileir statutory charter utterly<br />
transformed such as tho Grants Ccmn; si: on, the Cities CoMlission<br />
and the Industries Ass; istance C ommission.-<br />
Obviously, our newC Ldeirart-mc-n* Cs, statutory authorities,<br />
the comnssions and enr~ uirij. es aL'Aisj. nci the Government and the<br />
Pavlii-nenrt cannot oper: ate wvjti-iout staff, without advice, vlithout<br />
qualified men and wvomen. Of crsthat costs money not a<br />
cent too much, not a cent too soon. Yet for the sake of paltry<br />
* short-teinA saving~ s, at th,-e pri. ce nf ). osing the timne and talents<br />
of men and women who hav cr' te1rqcuctdy--<br />
judges, academics, sta te pulcservants and businessm-ten, our<br />
opponents propose -to thaiottlei These nmew activitieS; they . itend<br />
to cut off the source of : 2xper t an(! pulic advice so essential to<br />
any planningj for tLhr-. effoctivO,-ef , ficidm-t, mo! 3t humane andi least<br />
exp:) nsive ways of decaling wit', A ustralia' s accumulated soCial an~ d<br />
ecoinomic problems for the re-st of this centCury. . The fact is that<br />
wie have to spend a little plan a lot now, in 1974 ife<br />
are to build a decent, humane, efficient society for the<br />
generations to come.<br />
so we have begun 1Lasic andA quite massive reorganisation<br />
of the s~ tructuLre-S wii-ch oerensUse. in<br />
hustralia to carr:' out tic pol's ule This w. e propose<br />
to continue to do. -In some 2: e/ Jrota YIy eCf'ucatioin, ' i&gt;<br />
able to act immciatelyvf o-her fields, , e nad to ; q-ait for<br />
moreD information and moze e; perL so weimmediiately sr-t<br />
_ L~ ut getti-. g th-at advice ai-d, *. r. cru? ti-nc the ex). rts. I'II othc,:<br />
fields, like health I , ot conrt btuL.~<br />
Dat in all f ields and all levelIs, t. he wor'k goes on. It mnust ixit<br />
Ibe interru. pted. It must not be disrupted. I utnth<br />
dlestroyed. </p>
<p>F. UCATI O1.1 The vdluc of the work of our new Comnmissi~ ons ancl<br />
Committees of Enquiry have been great and continuingi. e<br />
arnel. Cormmtltee on * Schools, now instituted as the ' Schools<br />
Cormais Aon, has transformed the outlook for Australian<br />
education. We have* almost doubled Au-stralian G over nmnt fqlr'.<br />
on education. That money has beens distributed Z1CCo1! din-. J to<br />
needs of all schools. Ile have assum&amp; ed full financial reop-: n0--<br />
bility for tertiary education. Vle have. abolished fees for<br />
tertiary and technical education. For the first-time qeare<br />
giving assistance to teachers' colleges and pre-schcol teachers'<br />
colleqecs on the saine basis as univer. si ties andl colle-,; es of<br />
* advanced education. We are giving much more generous allowancens<br />
to studE-nts and have more than trebled the nu.: iber of teaching<br />
scholarships. The parents of Australia well know -and history<br />
* will record that the greatest single achievement of our<br />
* W Government in its first year was to change the face of education<br />
in Australia, and to change the basic attitudles, of the Australian<br />
people towards education. If we had achieved nothing else, iwe<br />
would be remembered for this-that we buried once and for all<br />
the futile and divisive debrate over so-called " State rights" and<br />
" State aid" for s; chools. T. e not only freed vast amounts of money<br />
f or schools; we freed the whole deboate on'education so that froill<br />
now on, parents, teachers, and educcational authorities can engage<br />
rationally in discussion about what is really best for our schools<br />
what is truly best for our chilcdr. n.<br />
Of course, many reforms st.' 1 remain to be made<br />
within the Australian education system. The Schools Commission<br />
is already conducting a study of those -_ rours not receiving full<br />
Wbenefits their schooling.-the culturally dis~ advantaged<br />
* child, the linguistically disadvantaged, the emotionally or<br />
intellectually aisadvantaged. The greatest inequiity in the<br />
* systcem ' how: ever, as the Karmel Cormm-ittee itself remarked, is its<br />
bias ajainst girls: the fact that so few girls as compared to<br />
boys sit for their final sc'-iooP &amp;; rWAS or continue into the<br />
technical trades or enter the brofes:; ions. This is one. th~ e<br />
major reasons w~ hy women are concentyr-ted in the less wjell paid<br />
Jobs in our society. I have as3-ed the Commission to study the<br />
causes of this situation and recomn. nd remedies.<br />
1have drafted a bill to establish a C-urriculum<br />
Deve) opment Centre. </p>
<p>CHILD CARE The advice of the qualified and the concerned m~ en<br />
and women now being made available through our commissions and<br />
enquiries enables the Government to imlpleMent its broad vision<br />
of the nature and purpose of education in a modern society.<br />
Tile want not only to provide wider opportunities for education.<br />
for a lifetime, we want to provide opportunities for a life-ti!. i-e<br />
of education. Such opportunicties must be made available if<br />
Australians are to be able to lead full and happy lives<br />
rewarding to themselves and to the cOmmunity. In a society<br />
undergoing such rapid change a~ s ours, the plain fact is that a<br />
majority of people will changeterocptonmr hnoc<br />
in their lives. Rcdundancy Is no longer the lot of manually<br />
skilled workers alone. Few occupations are going to be left<br />
untouched by the technological revolution.<br />
In the next Parliament our big initiatives in<br />
education will concern the care and education of pre-school<br />
children, technical training, and adult retraining. The<br />
foundations of our initiatives rest on work done by the<br />
Social 11elfare Commission, the Pre-Schools Committee, * the<br />
J'angan Committee on Techni cal and Farther Education arid the<br />
Cochrane Committee on Adult Training and Re-Training.<br />
There are at Dresent about 1.3 million children<br />
of pre-school age. For more than one in four of these children,<br />
there is no parent at hoi-me during wvorking hours. of these only<br />
one in every 10 attends a chill care centre. A child in<br />
Canberra has twice as gjood a chance Lf attending a pre-school<br />
as a child in Victoria and four times as good a chance as a<br />
child in Nlew -South OaJes. least 15,000 children aire left<br />
totally unattendedi] durincj the day. Thousands more are left to<br />
the care of brothers or sisters. Furthermiore, for too many of<br />
our primary school childran there is , here to go outside of<br />
school hours or during vacations. Too rf; any children begin<br />
school with educational, cul tural. or psychological disadvantages.<br />
The Government's Droqran for these children ) reflepcts<br />
the recommenEtiers of the PeSho mitewhosceorot<br />
was tabled last December, the Social 7elfarc conmmssion,_ Lpi; h<br />
was established by ain act atVoHvaesidn iber, ar) d thr<br />
Priorities Reviewz Staff. The. roiq ran will aa e"" elop<br />
of services__ includingi the development of famnily dIay cr<br />
diay centres, preschools, T~ tyL. O uis, outside of school care,<br />
Li,, irqenc ard occasional care, todi-iers qrourns and _ y-tin<br />
po4-ols. Pro-. ision will. he imi-Ade fo tof: care by relativl-S,<br />
or hhors TheH scen! ill be diese and f lexib-le<br />
troe cogn Ise d if fe r ent nie cd s o f dI f ' k: c-rent communities.<br />
To encouragje the creatiiion of child care csnntres in<br />
indrustry, ". 1es~ ai remove t1' e' Innr wt ip. Lrrcomc-Tax Act<br />
w; hich' 1inipEdes the( tax dieduct-ibITity ofsedn--_ cm~ ne<br />
on child care. </p>
<p>15<br />
Ve envisage that 50-0,000) children will benefit by<br />
1.977 and that by 1930 all Australian children will have access to<br />
local centres designed to take care of their educational, health,<br />
psychological and other needs. All children, not just the<br />
4 year-olds, whether cared for in their own home or in full,<br />
part-time or occasional care, will have access to free pre-school<br />
education. Child care servi. ces wil~ l be subs idi sned ith parents<br />
contributinq to the cost aeoc~ oto their me~ ns, the inain<br />
thrust of th~ e prograt in tFhefirst yer being to assist<br />
disadvantaged children, it is esLimatedI that the cost of thi~ s<br />
program in the first year a program of vision and imagination<br />
based on a compassionate understandi -ng of the needs of the child,<br />
the parent and the community will $ 130 milli-on.<br />
We are determined that technical education shall<br />
cease to be the Cinderella of Australian educationl. The reports<br />
* of the Kangan and Cochrane Commiittees will provide an effective<br />
and expert basis for hold new initiatives to allow technical<br />
skills to find their proper and honoured place in a changing<br />
society. These proposals represcnt a major attack on social<br />
inequality. We have drafted a bil~ l for a Technical and Further<br />
Education Comm37ssion. In March last yea r my Government appointed a special<br />
manpowaer commission to study manpower policies abroad. Ne now.<br />
Ppos1 e to am-lalciamatce all existincj5 -r iining chemnes into one new<br />
National Emplo~~. 1ymernt arid Training ]? rocramu . wl oki<br />
W s -6o-aoain-vi-t no movement and employer<br />
organisations to identcify immaediate needs and to make long-term<br />
projectioris of labour needs to meet the future demands of industry.<br />
Ve will offer relocation assistance to those who find themselves<br />
in regions or industries affected bjy economic, structural or<br />
technological change. In the provi-sion of its training<br />
facilit-ies, will give priority to persons affected by<br />
changes in tariff policiesz anid th-ose m-ade ri-dundant by technological<br />
change. N. E. A. T. will trinn ooron5p~ o rtunities for<br />
all persons without discrimination on grounds of race or sex. </p>
<p>16<br />
Our retraining program will help ensure that our<br />
present unprecedented growth in enployincrit opportunities cal).<br />
be met and maintained. Increased productivity and our groving prosperity<br />
depend upon our ability to make full use of the whole of our<br />
available manpower.<br />
STIdJCTUILAL CIX\. CFE<br />
The Government realises that, in times of rapid<br />
tectinological change a mechaninm is nceded to promote and<br />
make easier the movoment of employees from one occupation to<br />
another, from one industry to another, from one region to<br />
W another. Accrdinqlv, the Governnent has decided to<br />
introduce structural adlIustArnent assistarice to inci'viduals<br />
WattY* ! fLVoyers. Indlivi~ duals, including~ sma~ l owners ant<br />
rur i pro" W -C-3, s advecrselyrnj~~~ i~ l, structural ch? n r~ qo<br />
3 1. C 0 1 f J, 1) 1e f q(-Ji(' ICC U MC) Mi 1,17.1i ' t-enance paRyment s,<br />
raininq assistance and rc ocati7onq f rms<br />
will be eliqi. ble f o r consultancy/ qua.-! antees<br />
This scheme will improve the Xusitralian economy<br />
in the interests of the consumer and will provide industry<br />
with a better resource base and pattern of skills.<br />
L </p>
<p>.17<br />
1iAIGTANTS We recognise the outstanding contribution migra-, nts<br />
have made to our productk-ive capacity. Our primary conc(! rn,<br />
8h ow'tvleever.-s, ai. ns d rocti titzheenisr. ecotlneo mhaicv e vhaleueq ibunta vthgeoiro hsadpip-n s ohsl<br />
migrants ovrercclflie the disadvantage inseparable fromn life in a<br />
new country. The number of social workers and welfare officers<br />
x. orkf.': ng amongst migrants has been more than doubled. Sonic 1,500<br />
special teachers 1vv'been employed in schools at 3atnrr<br />
Government cost to give special tuition in ~ ni. hto 60,000<br />
miqra-i1t ebldien, twice the number receiving it under our<br />
predecessors. Provision has also be: en made f.-r emergency<br />
classroom acc.. mmodation, For a. ilts-the numnber of specialised<br />
courses intensive or accelerated courses, courses in industry,<br />
3courses for women arid arrangemwents for onie-two-one tuition in<br />
migrants' own homes has been developed or expanded,<br />
Mligrants have responded and have demnonstrated a<br />
new111 interest in ident.' fyling wit'. Austr:* lia. The number who<br />
Whave beco-ye 72xUStrali. ay--iti011inS 1973 has increased by 48%<br />
over-1972, ind the nun. bter returiining to their countries of<br />
okigin has declined for the first timie in 9 vears.<br />
* SOICIAL SECURlITY For too long Australia has demeaned herself and<br />
mlli. ons ol. our followi-citize.. ns by the idea that those unable<br />
to work, or to engage with full vigor in the xw. ork and leisure<br />
Sof a vig.:-rous community deserved charity but lost their right<br />
Wto self-respect and dignity.<br />
' 1e inherited a system of social welfare based almost<br />
entirely on the% concert of cash payments. We inherited a system<br />
* whereby society accepted that it had fulflilled it~ r. oh~ ligat. ions<br />
Wto the disa-dvantacjcd sections of the comnmunity onece it h<br />
settled upon the leval of cash payments JFor tho! se dotoeid to be<br />
in need. It was an easy way to fob off our coillectiv conscience.<br />
It was a systefa which took litt-le ' real account oif true : ei<br />
It was a systeia which did nothing at all. to provide its<br />
beneficiaries o; victims -with a chance for dignity, a chance<br />
for rehabilitation, a chance for taking a real place in the<br />
living community. The Social W4elfare Commission has been established to<br />
help the Government set goals for social welfare and to allow<br />
the community to help determine these goals. The public reports<br />
of the Corai: is ion serve as a standlard by which the comt:, unity<br />
can judge the Government's decisions and performance.<br />
Certainly cash payments for all classes of pensions<br />
and welfare benefits have been sign-ificantly increased. </p>
<p>Since taking office, we have increasedi age and invalid<br />
pensions by 30% a significantly greater increase than the rise<br />
in average weekly earnings or prices.<br />
We have introduced a number of new benefits and<br />
improved a number of exci.-ting oiien. Ne introduced the Supporting<br />
:', others Benefit and the Or-phans Pension. We abolished the<br />
discrimination of classes of widowys all widowis nowr receive the<br />
same amnount. We, have increased the grants arid liberalised the<br />
conditions for Aged Personr' Homes, th! 2 Home Care program and<br />
Rehabilitation allowances.<br />
Ile have proceeded to abolish the means test according<br />
to our promised scheO~ ula.<br />
My G~ overnment's ovar-riding concern, however, has<br />
been to overhaul th: entire system so that Australia s-hall be,<br />
as once she was, as she ceased to be in the coalition years, a<br />
pioneer and a l. eader.<br />
The TAustrAlian Assistance Plan has been established<br />
to expand and enh,, ance, co-ordiix atte yet diversi f-y the activities<br />
of welfare agencies, official anu' ; clunt~. ry alike. The Plan<br />
places emphasis on th? neec'. for huirnr contact, counsel and<br />
compassion as an adlition to cash payments. Funds on a costsharing<br />
basis with ilocaJ. gover-. n-Rent; and voluntary agencies havre<br />
beeni made availabla In 3.5 regions ohbt. A trl.<br />
In 3.9' 5 the A'ustrcalian Gcvormmnt % ill-make funds<br />
available und( J the Plan tovcy ejo. n u<br />
NATIONAL COMPENSATIOM lie are ( ieter-. nin, 2d to place the security, the welfare<br />
of those who suffer incapacity th; rough z:. cciden;-or sickness on<br />
a sure and certair, ba:-is on t-he basis of confidence and freedom<br />
from f inanc ial. a:' ix ety for tlhenms2 vc-s zand their famil ies.<br />
Australians should not havie ton l. vc ini d1oubt or anricty lest<br />
irnjury or sic] WC5Ss reduce oet! ~ eW hmw~ i ant to reduce<br />
hardships imrpose_; by on(-of the great fi. ctors -for i~ nc. aliy -in<br />
society irnequality of 2uck. Accor0. inaly, in arhl: 7<br />
we established the National Rehabil itat ion and Compnr: satio2<br />
Committee under the chairmanshi of-rl justice 7, ooahouse of th e<br />
N~ ew Zealand Court of Apa. In rubi: uary its teram of reference<br />
were extended to cov, the sick as wcll as the iLnjuired. It is<br />
excpected to report zL the end of June.<br />
N-y Government has dec . Ae-! d to irntroduvo a procjral to<br />
help meet the im. aterial neeas anrl. vdtise the dignity o-1 homcL! Es<br />
men -and wometi. </p>
<p>Ca ita). r rants will be made available . q-or a<br />
three-ear period to vo untary agecies, local anr~. a-i2r<br />
authlor . tief; for cts such a~ s ngtsetrhses<br />
daycetre a sapncYdTe ~ TTis c-and centres.<br />
This is a program devised in response to a ic.<br />
neglected need; it will be of benefit to the young as well as<br />
the old. It will be of benefit to any person in inediat e , Cdt:;<br />
to the permanently homeless, to the desierted or disturbed womThAiL<br />
and her children, to the aboriginal or teenager in want or distr(-: s<br />
to the battered woman or the battered child, to the singjlepan<br />
in short, to anyone without support or an income.<br />
NUHRSfING HOMES In keeping with the governmenit's commitment to proteuti! ng<br />
arnd improving the position of tho sick arid the aged, the qoveriient<br />
will suzattlyincrease benefAits paid to nursi. nq Fm din<br />
to taKe iento account the increased COScs incurred. by nursi ncy huces.<br />
In addition, an altcrinativc form of financial<br />
assistance wl'YFFe of fered * to rTTeii cht. errriI~ ri~<br />
I) T2I ne thje&amp; I* eIciIIpc) eot rUatxnqr<br />
of these homes reclarding this arrangcment which will enale these<br />
homes to improve still furtCher their stanidardis and facilities.<br />
The ! Ainister for Social Security, Hr. Hfayden, wi) ll<br />
announce the details of the proposals and other welfare mfuasure.:<br />
in the goverpment's welfare pol icy speech in Djoeibourne C~ n<br />
W~ ednesday.<br />
HIEAVY i The government is determin, -d to fulfil its<br />
constitutional responsibility ' for providin~ g ho!: pitcil b : rierfit anid<br />
medical and dental services anid to give all Aistralians. access<br />
to high quality health care at reasonclble ccest.<br />
Our proposal for universal health iirisurance pat<br />
you and strongly supported by you in the elections of 1969 and<br />
1970 as well as 1972, was twice rejected 1, y the Sei*, ate. It wz:. S<br />
among the measures on which the Gove rno.~ Generzal grantced t he--<br />
double dissolution. it will therefore he one of the first<br />
measures brouoht before eho alam~ t. i r tiLU<br />
one mlfon_ Austraflans -are st1 l , otctaeqda iast hosoital<br />
and medi. cal c-harges.<br />
We will extend iuedial eefits Lo ; ovei: 1, hwJtat ions<br />
with op tome t F~ sts. </p>
<p>We propose to restore free hospital treatment established<br />
by the last Labor Government in 1947 and abandoned by the 1ienzies<br />
Government in 1952. ! tJe shall offer to share . with the States half<br />
the cost of making_ hospital treatim: ent free in sitandard wards.<br />
Furthcr, the national. qov'ernment is ite r epred<br />
to build, staf f and operateflhospita  li areas and regions now<br />
inadequateLy served. ' ie havc alreadly approached the States.<br />
We have offered to provide half the cost of building<br />
and operating a new General Hospital in Launceston and wholly<br />
build and operate a new womien'I s hos-pital in Hobart.<br />
Ile have offered to construct and operate teaching<br />
Wextensions at the Rloyal Newcastle Hospital without cos-t to<br />
the U. S. W. Gov'ernment. In the last Budget we set aside $ 4 million to proceed<br />
Swith the building of a teaching hospital at 1W. estmead,<br />
WThough this project has bee(-n planned by th State governr1, c-nt<br />
for silz years, that government has i. nformoed us that they are un1able<br />
to spend the mnoney' we have provided. our offer still stands.'<br />
The money is there. It is up to the State government to<br />
use it. Ile shall press on withm the establishment of commuunity<br />
health centre~ s, Te ihate and<br />
loaloverninents. The Australian school Dental Scheme will be expanded<br />
to cover all rilnary scoo lddrnb<br />
We shall institute a dornici liary dental servefo<br />
thed tosev 7 OO Ooplhe~<br />
a cost of 600,0OO anmmual. y<br />
Ile shall reconstitute thie Commonwealth Seerm<br />
Laboratories and estc hTFa Phaxin, it~ a3d. C, iii ion to -es arch<br />
.( and w holeo; ale di-1gs th u~. feslnsrcmkJ) 0_ a<br />
bythe Vernon floyal Com! wissio F~ or the Ps fie<br />
CITIES In all. these matters in education, social security,<br />
health we have had these great objective.;: to reduce inequality,<br />
to promote equality of opportunity, to make the system itself<br />
rmo re efficient and equitable. 7, J1 ther~ ain 3 aire comnbined in<br />
the biggest new effort my cjo'i-evnt has mido_-in our qreat cities,<br />
in our growing centres all around AUStralicz. At last Australia<br />
has a national governmclnt reparc-d to i nvolv e it-, sel f i~ n the<br />
* affairs of the places where m~ ost. Au ~ txraliant liVe: our citieS<br />
and our centres. </p>
<p>21<br />
We have recognised, as I said in 1972, that " a<br />
national government which cuts itself off from responsibility<br />
for the nation's cities is cutting itself off from the nation's<br />
real. life". In its direct involvement in cities the Australian<br />
Government has entered the mainstream of Australian life. That<br />
new involvement has been central not onl. y to the affairs of<br />
the great majority of Australian people; it is central to our<br />
relations with State government and local government, Pie not<br />
only want to remould, modernise, revitalise our cities; we want<br />
to remould, revitalise, rnodernise the relations between the<br />
three levels of government national, state, local. tl. have<br />
involved the national governmen~ t in matters w . hich previously<br />
were left to the States or not done at all. If they were left<br />
to the States,* they were too often done inadequately, or not<br />
done at all. If left to local government,. they were too often<br />
done inadequately, finaaced unfairly or not done at all.<br />
0 In this field we have had some examples of splendid<br />
co-operation with the States yet equally we have met some of the<br />
worst obstruction f rom the States.<br />
The Albury/ Uodoiga agreemennt. to create Australia's<br />
first large centre away from the seaboard since the found.' ing of<br />
Canberra has been a splendid example * of co-operation. . Je have<br />
also made agreements with the States for new growth cent)-es,<br />
finarice for sewerage and grants for urban transport. It would<br />
have been unheard of until 1972 that an Australian national<br />
governinent should involve itself di rectly ip regional development,<br />
s-ei\: eracge, urban.-trcunsport. Because previous national governments<br />
even with all their atonopo ly over the really big and gro..,; ing<br />
sources of revenue, w-, ould not involve themselves, nothing effective<br />
* was ever done about c~ ecentralisation; our great cities had the<br />
largest unsewered areas of any comparable cities in the world;<br />
and our urban transport systems were app&gt;-:, a ching breakdown. Of<br />
c~.~: cit hats been impossible in so short a time to reverse<br />
the trendis rc-. salting from decades of neglect. But we have made<br />
a J nnn; a rtbainic<br />
LOCAL GOVERNIMENT Yet crucial to making a good continuationi andl a gcod<br />
culmination of these efforts i~ s the role of local goveroi. cnt'.<br />
And it must 1be sai. 1 tChat our efforts to raise the status of<br />
local govern~ ment and to give local government direct access to<br />
th1 nation's finances have met with scant co-operation from<br />
state governments. Ie huave sought to wake local government a genuine<br />
vlrtrtner in f~ ha ; stc T li. rvi c. '~ ll1: the<br />
Gtants Cou.~~, a~ llot; 1.-. Cal j0-v'-L'r1JTIent bodies to make<br />
submissions and t allow the Cormission to ma ke recommrendations<br />
on the amounts of ri,. nay needed to rek-1tce inequalitjes between<br />
regions and within States.-as traditionally it used. to do as<br />
between the States,. </p>
<p>-22-<br />
The role we assign to local governmenit is the real<br />
answer to charges of centralismn. Under a variety of programs<br />
we'have provided local governm-ient with the funds to undertake a<br />
range o activiti-es previously inadequately carried out or<br />
totally neglected. The Auistralian Assistance Plan, the programs<br />
for community health, area imp--rovemnent-, the national estate,<br />
the arts, tourism and recreation a d aborigines all these<br />
provide funds for commrnunity activities to be orqanised by local<br />
government. We deliberately have made and shall make local<br />
government a vehicle for our lcgislation on aged persons' homes<br />
and hostels, sheltered employment, han-dicapped children, mea ls<br />
on wheels, home care and nursing, nursing homies and homeless men<br />
and woi-men. These are all activities which cannot be close],,. y<br />
regulated from the centre and are best planned and implemented<br />
by local government workingq with local communities. They justify<br />
assistance fromn the nation'Is finances but not increases in rates.<br />
W~ e insisted on local, gover-nment representation' at<br />
the Convention on the Constitution in September last year~. We<br />
made local government representation a condition of part iciJ-pation<br />
by the national government.<br />
0At that Convention I put the case for local govevnment<br />
representation on the Loan Council.. The States' Premiers then,<br />
and at a special Premiers' Conference in Octolber, turned down<br />
our proposal that local governiment should have a voice vid a vote<br />
in the Loan Counzcil. Tie forhreferendum now boc": ore you will take the<br />
next crucial step in raising the status of local governriepnt. It<br />
wil. l enable the national government to make grants direct: to<br />
local yoenetbodies, if they wish, zand to borrow m,-oney on<br />
* their behalf, if they wish. Only if this is done can local<br />
governmtent acquire reasonable access to '' le nation's finances.<br />
Only if this is done can local governmenz carry out, the increasing<br />
responsibilities and bear the increasing . h-urdcer-s vyhich federal<br />
and state governments alike iimrpose upocn it and which the p.-eople<br />
* need. Only if this is done can inequality between regions be<br />
reduced. It remains true, as I said in 1972, that more anid more<br />
the standard of life of the Australian citizen depends not<br />
so much on how much hie earns but % Z1tre he lives.<br />
URB3AN TRANSPORT We are providing $ 31 million this year to the state<br />
governments for urban public transporL.-improvement. We are<br />
proosinqt2p1ovide another 141 mil lion to coi : pet FrIc~ ts<br />
CUoimn 1N. 9ths Y. Half the morie y haF, been allocate-d for the<br />
tion of new railway rolling st~ ock, buses andtr: s<br />
Other mcjor proje( cts loeing assistecd include<br />
quadruplicatioii of the railway line lhcatween Granville and Penrith,<br />
construction of a number of acdditioi... 1 tracks in N'elbourne to </p>
<p>-23<br />
relieve congestion and increase the capacity for express services<br />
operating to outer suburban area!-, and electrification of urban<br />
rail links in Brishane andl Adelaide.<br />
From as far back as 1907 each mainland taegove~ rnment<br />
has from time to time-consented to Che Commonw,. ealth Government<br />
constructing or extending railways in its state; these railway's<br />
have always been country lines and have usually involvedC State<br />
expenditure. Last February my g-overnime,' int sought. the M. S. 14.<br />
government ' s consent to construct a railway in the metropdolitan<br />
area, to be constructed and operated without cost to the N. S. U1.<br />
govern-iient. The railway system we scek to construct will radiate<br />
from )? arramatt1-a to Hoxton Park, Castle Hill andf through Carlingford<br />
to Epping. It will allow the i~ ntr. oduction of the best contempnorary<br />
* Signalling practices and carriage sets.<br />
I have told the Premier -that we wish to Provide funds<br />
in the ne." zt uqe heeimc: Lntof-E; ntrC tioi and -the<br />
0ECo rol I~' stoCK<br />
1131 S 1.1G Wrec ogise too that wher-n Australians live is le: s<br />
and* leS a Matter Of truly f ree choicee, but a matter of the<br />
availability and price of resideiAial land. I regret to say that<br />
here agaitn, in our Ce2forts~ to hoJ. d down the pi-ic-e of lizntd, we havke<br />
mnet State goverrnm'ent obstruction. Frum-, the -timue we tooK office<br />
1; e hAve been negotiating with the States to es. tablich land<br />
. friCnogretmsi ssi ons to clear and develop lanei at new centres or On the<br />
of existingl cities. The Commrvissions, by selling<br />
buildingj blocks at'a fair pri~ ce, twov! ld help dampen spiralling<br />
land costs. They would alslo be a key to better town planning. In<br />
the larst B~ udget we allocated $~ 60 million to be spent over two<br />
years by the land coaaissions. Only one State the Labor State<br />
* of South AustL-ralia has so far pa-ssed. the necessary lecjisl&amp; a'ion.<br />
The foL-mer Labor Administration in !( estern Aii7tralia pass!, ed the<br />
legislation in the Legislative Asseinbly, only to have it rejected<br />
in the Upper House.<br />
lie have found the housing problem one of the most<br />
difficult of all our inheritances fromn the previous government.<br />
During the two year: s prior to Deceniber 1972, there was a miassive<br />
growth in money supply within Aust-ralia and vast sums were<br />
channelled to the housing industry for private dwellig<br />
con struct ion. The result of this was that the housinrl industry<br />
became grossly over-extended, long delays occurred in the supply<br />
of materials and labour to building sites, construction times<br />
were greatly extended and excessive cost risQs became the order<br />
of the day. Public housing-proqrairs-for which thle government<br />
provided a record assistance of $ 21l8.65 million in .1973/ 74 were<br />
not being fulfilled because of the demand for resources in private<br />
housing and other building construction. </p>
<p>-24<br />
While maintainInc all our efforts to-rc. over from the<br />
position we inherited, We pro, ) oso fur~ ther nieasures; to reduce<br />
housing costs and the burden of ;' igfor a house.<br />
A major proc id al-uadcy, r am3; en Launched to produce<br />
a uniform housinq code and '. cmmwdp.-cacticcs for dwellinig units<br />
of various types ranging. from hiJh' te med11WL andi low density<br />
housing. This is aime at_ sip aynnd rational ising inany<br />
of the unnecessarily complex and non--st. Drila~ rj ic, ms; whiich ad~ d<br />
unduly to housing costs, and x-Aich do not conL) ibutc! to thle<br />
quality of living.<br />
HOUSE INTSURANCE The government Jis determine6 to civc home--owners the<br />
opporuun3. ty to insure their propcrties, for lower prcinium,-s and<br />
against natural s T ~. 1Jh JVq( 1C<br />
introduced on I f[ chr)) uiary u s ' VIi' iA r21-osr, L<br />
favourable than those se t hOy i SUJ1: c2]: t t111: h1 t: 1k DI.,, XG:<br />
Service HIomejs i u~~ eshiv . r : evrIg~* A<br />
wider ccover than oi-. hcr inuiors ~ c<br />
have come to realisc.<br />
AccordIn-nly Lhc tjvny. n: I isn Au'. itral IJ trz<br />
Gove-rnmient InsuranL: j~ 2 f. e<br />
forms of insV raflc(* hIlcA'm 2, ii~ i'<br />
UI.;-diJS tjcs; e1 oCe) r fo:-no,:~ t~ IIe:<br />
TiFn1RS i I : J Tofc<br />
P~ e will heltp new-,. hiome bye to rearrane their<br />
mortaq( e repmon-._ 1111Tcsrcr andI the( IinisLer fo): Housing<br />
willrhave early dicussicons \/ il: h the mrajor ) c: n3. ing institutions<br />
* mono rttghaigse mpaatltmerc. n t3 Osuor itnhha-te nyt-o'uonnri c is tom hc.; I~ rn. easw lr , arrangcpmayc erliet sso fat<br />
a time when the cderiands5 on their . iJncoPme arc-1igche-t. nI hrc. 1in<br />
to pay more later i~ n life whea .' h) iy are-be. ter able tc) ov<br />
higjher repayments. We are thoroughly aware of the burden interest rates<br />
impose on those buying their cown home, particularly-young married<br />
couples. Ife are determineC. to cEac t-hat burden for those in<br />
in my _ 972 policy spehT unoertook that until<br />
i~ anteer et cn h~ edued a ~ hor would introdue<br />
a scherie of tax deduc-:_. bility for hom-. e i; Itc-' c! i-. s payments. All<br />
ta) payers -wh! ose act~ oal incon or belo-7 wilil be entitled<br />
to dedu~ ct 10 0 of thi r intclsc i e AVMinctS. r'iwi vercentaqle<br />
JJEtoti interest nam2t 7V74hiutYS will e reduced<br />
Py 1% for evei5 100 of ic;: in e o of , Gco. r1hat c-~<br />
as I announced 4i. n rebruacry 19.74 is 6ue to no into &amp; f: t . i. n*<br />
of T fh. The legiTs4a Lion hasJ T The~ d schemed </p>
<p>II<br />
will provide direct tax relief inot&amp;-only for now hiome buyers, but<br />
also for nearly all those %-whc arc: at present paying~ off their<br />
homes. ENVIRONJIIENT Increasing. 1 lh.' z rntoisWvce come to see the relation<br />
between thleir oti'ri hornres h i thr: i.* i ', 70MniLi. ens an<br />
the Whtol;. AuStrillian retn . tt h. 7 j r! q(.' nei:! tion of<br />
Australian.; to tt ( eoest" h:. e 3:. 1c n Yrwls<br />
bex-, weefl oro. wth aidpe3v: i nof tL-he-fliu:~ rmc~ t<br />
govextr-~ 1~ 1~~ ri~~ r~ nt.~ 1A C! I--st CAI, 1) d2d.<br />
to cnsiirL iiha t. crov. th andr jr iC?] Yr: ce nut boiiqhl a t the price<br />
of the dl(,.; ruct. or of thuntio'~ n~ tur-al. and hi!; to'zical<br />
inhe): i4-ZnCc . ICW-h( e, jCv thlat. The polluter must riot future<br />
generations of Aus-k-raJlians.<br />
One of my fir3st-actionsE vat-to* confer with the P r crm i es<br />
of N. S2-7. Vi". ctoria and S: outh st;&gt; ialja on thu fEunctions of the<br />
River Iurray Conw. is-, ion, which have been virtuially un: hanqjed for<br />
years an~ d which are now LuAeJnd2ua to sa feguard the<br />
urban and rural. u~ ers of aqlcreaiate' st1 waterway/.<br />
!, le have Cbt r nictf1Protection Pill<br />
yprovidinqc fon vilo. m1;" I1-~ i il<br />
on them."' I have r po:. e. 1t t1' c yli oH enLr 1 I<br />
impact statents ce. -ilr ;; r<br />
Tr i a,, Z 770. e e5 r ch; t Eli-I<br />
-r 31 o 1~ uI Ti7r'o~<br />
T 1: r to hePm3r5that joint<br />
invo. lvinq X003 -1-s Iit6o 77  QJ CA: G~ 0<br />
Corrmittee. on Inciuir-" The Con-. titu'Lton c ivos the Australizin<br />
Government power 4to corit:-ol th-. ey~ port of goods and, in particular,<br />
the export of innerals and t:': imicr. It cai, requi-re that ith<br />
satisfied that the exp) oitcitio of mincra or t.~ c eor~ S<br />
or the manner or -zxterit of tliat e-. ploi1: ation, w! ill. not adversely<br />
affect the environment hcfor-. QV1. iriq(. a toeseeLc port." Otr<br />
. gp\ ernmcflnt will. excrci~ . bs j'mo roqjulaYrly arnd effectively<br />
on the basi. s ot ski:. ilrd and . in~ herc., dnt ilvice.<br />
' Je have drafteOd a National Parks andl 1 Jilcdlife-<br />
Conservation Billi. It wi). l eea. ih~ ilationil Park: s and<br />
Wildlife Commission " 71 Y'iTQhC: JCT e, on a 1<br />
parks, includin such arts a ffuhe ret rr r ( 6<br />
tieJntral, Austral. an71Tre -thcxut' La AA ps an( e<br />
vacatd dncfenc in s ie y i ian Po P1% i-T i<br />
The Governmrnnt ':. rethexotof i tiruts of<br />
kangaroos and relat-d ,;. ecjps. It hi 6ti-' I~ l ii I~ 1th<br />
internM-. i-, il . X4TL7omil1Aty as: Ote t; e irport-ance<br />
of wildlifie cozii.: rvat. 6on. aro . o inccatc : othe i~~: es thlat . it iS.<br />
not siit i., fied with t. 1 l of itni -armniiy in their. approacb. t<br />
conservation pro: 7ram3 for krA:~ s </p>
<p>26-<br />
FORE~ IGN CONTROL OF RESOU31CES<br />
The national estate belongs to all Australians.<br />
We have accepted the responsibility of the national government<br />
to help protect it arid preserve i~ t for the benefit of all<br />
Australians. Equally, we have accepted our responsibility<br />
to protect Australia's resources ' S thtIecfrh utain<br />
will have a greater share in the control and ownership of<br />
their own resources. We have tried to stop the gre at Australian<br />
sell-out. We have tried to help Australians buy Australia<br />
back. In these aims we have met unrelenting obstruction from<br />
our opponents. For years the Australian Labor Party advanced<br />
the idea of the Australian Industr,-y Dc velopment Corp~ oration<br />
Sand in 1972 undertook to expaiid iLs activi-ties: to enable it to<br />
3join aith Aun'L-ralian arnd foreilgr companie-s in the discovery,<br />
development and proces sinq of Austral ian resources. Eight mon ths<br />
ago we introc2uced the legislation; the Senate stalled it.<br />
Con. 1 anion legislation for the National Investment Fund had tlhe<br />
* Same fate. Through this fund wo intend to holp ord~ inary<br />
Australians invest in the devc,.' pwm nt of thei~ r own re,-_ source~ s<br />
and industries instead of subuidising to the tune of millions,<br />
foreign investors and nmulti-n~ itional corporations. T' e F.<br />
will raise f unds by oprtn<br />
for the g&amp; Yc_, q-( iCp ublic andl by LferiiL3-v erjtC: n investi~ ent<br />
bonds to both~ irivate and i~ Lt* inl: n~ ios<br />
Further, the Senate twice re-jected the Pe-trol and<br />
.1inrals Authority Iill. Th1is is designed-as our basic<br />
instrument for ensurinig dcveloprrent of our energy and mineral<br />
Sresources and to maximise thec ownership and control. of th. CEse<br />
W resources by 1' Australians. It was another of th~ e me,_ aSures'-on<br />
which the Governor-General yranted the double dissolution<br />
and it also will be Yrmtbyebfoocrhet the new Parliament.<br />
Our opponents pattern. of resistance to measures<br />
Wdesigned to promote Australian ownership forms part of a<br />
pattern of encouragement of foreign ownership they set when<br />
in Government. The great sell-out occurred when they formed the<br />
Government. They are still the apologiists for forcei-. n ownorship.<br />
Their return to office w~ ould agJain olpen iw. ide the door. As a'<br />
result of thieir policies, 68 of our cnerm' resources are<br />
controlled overseas. just how wide our opPonients opened t ' he door<br />
is now being revealed. T * he Departrent of H'inerali; and Energy<br />
set up by this Government has now received a thoroughly<br />
documented and impartial report on the mining industry<br />
the Fitzgerald Report. </p>
<p>-27<br />
Ausralansnow know for the first time the exteat to wich they<br />
have been suL-sidisirig mining invustors.. riainly foreic ncorporations.<br />
The profit on their operations for the las.-t 6 years<br />
was $ 2,000,000,000. Our prodoccs-lori3 developed a syste m of<br />
taxation concess~ ions so generous to these struggling corporations<br />
that the Australian taxpayer gave*' 3100,0 in subsidi-es and<br />
concessions. But the comcpanies paid only $ 28361-in tax. es an-d<br />
royalties, $ 55 m~ illion less.<br />
We have been paying to be TThie~ oti<br />
Fitzgrald orwc lJ tfe sti tr tiriq poAit fcnr L. formutlation<br />
C~ fpoicusai med at m: 1Li; qtn-e" r tAur~ i to ziu~ trali a of her<br />
natural en.] o,; 1xlat or-mineral and ec-kerj wealth.<br />
__ We will. conitinue to pursue v wih vrigour the surveillance<br />
Vof all foreign takce-over pro~ posals for shares or: assets of<br />
exitin Zutralian compaies. kWe have. estcablisheC[: u' e ine<br />
of new foreign invostmervt proposal1s for wn c"" h e eiiceC1lLC<br />
approval i~ s reci~ red. We haveq n~ It' I a c~ t* f1O LO<br />
certain industries Austr3 3 i iiIiL: U. i<br />
institution. s s; o -"-ere is 1itt 1c! advad. ' t;': 3Ce J1in CJ Jowiflcy C3itoDCJ<br />
institutions to Lbe cstablisicd inte. rcists. This is<br />
parti. cula:': ly thie case in the 2je). d of int-urarnce. In the iareza<br />
of m~ neals we have, indicatedC clearly that it . is our ob-i cctive<br />
to reduce the extent of foreign owner-ship a~ nd con trol and<br />
to rnaxiu. se Ausit-ra~ lian contCrol), parjjticujjnr. y of onerq'~' resources9p<br />
FurthurmoreC we haestpp d thec I-u of Autr~ l~ nland,<br />
andexhage onro. ppro~ ial for foreig inCaIl~ v~~ ni<br />
estate. hzas been Iimrited.<br />
T he G vrieie tn t' ii 1 wa . I<br />
ii.( 1 3 il -e 1)*-Th-' afli.-<br />
p. 1ocgsS of fo),-e ion andne'c: v<br />
CC8: fl ng proC: 5~ i un C e o-oi.~ r ci. o, L OF tftlh 1:<br />
will e c 1 to dCVeP Io' p0 r f'hI'f " k 0l1~ kii i. iiflI:<br />
areas oft c;: port fxrc~~ I J~ w<br />
i L. 11C-f 0 ( yJ d) utLTlhe<br />
world ehcccjv rit.~ td4CA:! hd<br />
* thie resources policies of the t iw G<: lln..="" h=""></:>
met that test triunphant). y. We have no int,-nti on % fia1.:: ocver<br />
to use our possession of vast res: Luarces to 9g:. ng up against<br />
* the resource users. I e stand ready to join with oth-, r nations<br />
in search of solutions. ue recog-nise the interdcpeiidcnce of<br />
our economy and our prosperity withi our great trading partners,<br />
particularly Japan, Northern Amrica anc! Surope, We are,<br />
however, determined that our resources command a fair price<br />
in world markets, This we arei achieving. Througn export controls<br />
and . discussions with exo~:;. h'Oirrei: h--. obtained higher<br />
returns for exporters. </p>
<p>For the first time an Australiai cjovernuiont has U'sed its authority<br />
to reinforce the bargaining power of Australian exporters. We<br />
shall not sell our re.-Dources on; thec clieap.<br />
Australi~ a has emerged az: s one of the world's ene7rgy<br />
rich countries. . chave,; mn~ murm dc4; pen] Ence on imports of<br />
heavy crude oil and we have been amo. ingj the countries least<br />
affected by escalating crude oil prices overseas.<br />
To obtain advice on hoe this situation can lbest be<br />
used for the continuing bc,-nefit of aill !' ustralians the<br />
governmtent has set up a Royal. Corcimssion under r~ r. Justice Collin.-s<br />
to enq. uire into all a-spects of petroleum products, refining arnd<br />
pricing. Further, we ap-proved lastC year the creation of a<br />
Pipeline Authoarity to provide for the transmission of natural<br />
gas by an interstate pipeline ' stein. Thce f irstsag h<br />
National Pipeli-nc Sys tem -Jill link Sydlnuy to the Gidgealpa fields.<br />
It lst iatlyproposed th-at the pipe) line will continue to<br />
Palm Valley. Inv~ w of t'lce cj-i. ical onerrm-s) horta( je in<br />
Weten st~ ia aTZjo int ormw~ ithS! aL study is uinder way~<br />
tov al~ Letho feas ibil1it,' nf pipel-3ine l ink hn-_ twecri Palo, Valley,<br />
R z 1 c r-* i Pert. 1-and3 the 11Ftura1_ q3U-c~ ds on the ortl--cst<br />
The Australian ( Jovternman t is working closely with<br />
the Wecstern Piustralian Governmant on a studly of a ma. jor industrial<br />
complex in the Pilbara baseC. on the utiliza-tion of the ' abundant<br />
suppli -s of natural gas, iron ore and salt in the reolon.<br />
The rellort wiJlprovde the aS: fi or decision on our f-uture<br />
r1o. e dveo~ : iLol. tij-e iIt will. bo reLaay in June.<br />
P RrIiA RY INDUSTRIES<br />
SAustralia' s future as an ex-porte-r rests increasingly<br />
upon o-ur newly discovered imincrcii. re! zourccs. The farm sector,<br />
however, rem-iains and will. long remiain fundamentally important<br />
to our trade, fundamentially impurtant to Australia's pr-osperity.<br />
My colleague, Senator 17riedt, the Mlinister for<br />
Primary Industry, will c. lelivcr the governlment's rural policy<br />
speech in Coulburn on .' ed: nesdl-y. 1l.-t me, however, outline the<br />
Government's general. approach and record.<br />
Eost Australian farmers this year have enjoyed<br />
unexampled prosperity. The avrac jrit income of Australia' s<br />
190,000 rural holdings this year is about 000. Tne average<br />
for the previou5 6 years was less than $ 6,000. Our policies<br />
have contributed in no small measure. In particular, we have<br />
sought aid! to farmers to take the hetadvantage of present<br />
favourable conditions to obtain new mnarkets. We want to encourage<br />
industries whicha have solid, l-png Lerm prosi: ects of selling their<br />
products at a good return to the farimer. </p>
<p>-29<br />
To this end, we have viqoroiirlv expanded existing<br />
mnarkets and opcncd newi one(-s.<br />
The Tr-ad'e agreemenmt withA Pe~ cISh IO~ Cof China<br />
is onl~ y th-e most and novel. exoam'. 1e. lk. tlhii li term'Is Of<br />
this Aqireement iih-i:. a ocrter coitract kavec . n 1.1nre<br />
f or the supply of Aust; ra-lian vheat and sugar to Ch in a. Tt -is Ibeyond<br />
question thiat the q'efrnl-inent Co,* China '. 111 honou-ar a~ ou~ Jya<br />
agreement, noe-c-s . oliiica. a: oscmltL~. e ~ d<br />
re). ajons Our prko: N.. ot: ecrcg I., f. n o' the Pjo ~~~ ulc~ asww<br />
iadis-putably a signific nt -7ator: in th2 wrt) v Vd 3, U<br />
ri~ rt with whic,' .) oth f; Ades negotl. aze h f&amp; e2c~'~~<br />
In addi-tion, t're P . us':, alianG overnment has roached a<br />
new levl1 of 111&amp; rstr. dJrcj : n trz'.&amp; o w%.. th Japc'-7n, thv Pacif~ ic region,<br />
eastern Europe andI the S;; vict-Union.<br />
We have Is2i30 Acts fo,-r the rtcco and<br />
Sreconstruction of prixi-iry industry i~ n genera.. aind for S; nCh S)) ciU<br />
industries as wool; Wfl(: at meatr eggs in-m-, honey ap  ' les andper<br />
ile have drafted 16 bfiil~ ls~ nitrogeioow; fci-ti.. z<br />
subsidiEs and v.]; e( at stabi lizatiion and~ For thc! sugar.,~. yx~<br />
* pig-' farming, wool, canned fiiP.&amp;. ts and a'canc! pear i. nustries.<br />
Although our vineat; tiJ.~&amp; n. plajn was edre ru:.<br />
by the itsr3~ lhaa. h;* nwbripJlacod<br />
in jeopardzy by the new llo-tarn. Am; tC-ra. ian ocrme.<br />
pro~ uer Miy coverninent-ocd~ ie or~ tns of priimiary<br />
cmpajnlvs -1) bout h-' cji-i tcIDf.~ y re. ducing tariffs<br />
by 25% across the Bouard weshall. savu prirr. a-y produicers att least<br />
$ 100 million this fina: nriaj. yors:.<br />
The Tarii~ f Poare, oas i~ e succ-eeded h't~ he X( nelstrj-cr<br />
A~ ssistancecormsox on i ash J re<br />
Si~ r John Craw-S'ord. A'thouiq! i thi e L3Ax ta0 t. ric ULrst<br />
tailoe enale1. s ( gToJvun nat to) 5. ud m: ia v~:<br />
on assistance fo0--i~ x tto oni a bq. r1asis, the<br />
COuntry Party in Doouhs es~ ilgei s: S the * ijiil es--ta. blishing<br />
it. I havo ale a s! C&amp; ithz-. OQ co. x rc,. or-t<br />
prom~ oti On and rae hand riuct r on cbl23 ~ c; x<br />
OaL : y and qoi d-' uKiningj2PU and toi~ d~ r~&gt; i~~. a<br />
;&gt;, lanxis f -: rm rs.<br />
The(,, governiment is awaj. ti nrj rc:; ort Afrom a o ite<br />
o ~ hchE~~ h7 Ca; fod saISo nb) or. tep~ . p<br />
Tlmrdc. kiri andl Doci-, D'; I'Arml~ s </p>
<p>FLOOD__ ITiIC." TIOW<br />
Tha recent d-isastrous floods in. Queens land have! amply<br />
deoions t rated the nec~ d for a positive, co--ordinated nationali<br />
approachi to f lood mitigation. jer. onally invited the Premr<br />
of ) ue-: n. s land X suDi-. tit__ a S Ltie-wide panoji floo-d Iiticration<br />
as tlie basis cii Con-3: lcerat ion for Austra'li'an G~'-: r. tassistance.<br />
We rooethat anve.-A fl. c-itiqaion schemofi fov<br />
1Livsoir : ' s shoul. d b! e__ d ta co-or. crc&amp; i'v&amp; ly'b_~ e the<br />
Aiir. a-ralian, Sta La ar local coverwY : nS as jv.' 1<br />
in.-the case of Nov. () Lltll WaJ'tles.<br />
I contr.;-: 2t tl-ii. cc)--operativc appro:, thnis national<br />
ap) tocCh wqit. the attitude of the present Leader of thc Country<br />
Party jhc n 1) told tL--he_ 11ou sro of eprezc~ n tz. tives on 1,16 May 19), 6 3<br />
' Th-problem of flood miticiat-_ oni rcst-~ s.-paarely on State<br />
( Govc:: rments The. pres Co*., monvealt~ h R~ id 7. ads Act expi-res at<br />
the end of Junec. TeBureau of Poads-impa-e a report to assist<br />
the goverrnmunt in consi4dering final-1 * ci-al ass-Istance to the States<br />
for the ensuing pc~ r-: Lod. TjiC Pliniste-r for Trai-spozt tznled 1te<br />
reot last DocevIber. Discussions have since enhedwt<br />
the State-s and also0, -for ' Che firct tLi-c, Lut ina accordance with<br />
the* t, Bureau' s recommecndation, vy., Ath Local -o'. rwn autNioriti-s.<br />
These diacussmons will be r'? sumed af~ tcli the e:~ ections.<br />
ivleanwhile t!) e qovernment has ~ eiddthat it will<br />
itself Pre.!. ' n the con ~ tru. ctio ofLa a na Li. onaLI roal<br />
systa in t: Iiose areas \ wichi iiwth7 ow Cnt. J. i t.. i fn<br />
repniiiies., ti 1Vr12ft'~ ~ Qrrpni)~<br />
the whole Cost of Ol trOitjigl anl d ii tainlncf the i. ncxa.<br />
road -hne. L ~ eaia~ 7r<br />
-inter ests ofl S~"<br />
SccC nriuy a ncw; 4 -1cuic diviLdedhqwc needls t te Y' vc<br />
t nc GItJ'~ L( oal) bn ai. d irok pTsis inc : 1OU'<br />
j'. mu t a': dBatlo and-~ comng cl.. ose t1o Ccanburra it will recuce<br />
L:.. roa.-d () istanc. e bctwcen Sycin-y and i ~ 1o, u r ie by 70 miles.<br />
The~~ m ~ twii Ico lq inL h ic ,. tzte and local govurnment<br />
authoritio. s on the prcise-, routo. </p>
<p>S&gt; eccnc'lv, the ooverroentc aill1 take epos. iit<br />
for the whole cost-ofotot 4&amp; i1 ilrsqui~ c<br />
These__~~~ ucflihe-nrte rcroads ( ovecrthenext three \' ears<br />
_ poo-m~ ioli yc'lln and 23 ilo<br />
on the, FIItzroy r s iq-! rdia ro . tj in Ues toW71Z ra ri d<br />
oteu a oianng mines to i; naodr. u ~ ca roc i~ s<br />
. to mjocr sea and air termi).-als.<br />
Thirdljy, we shall make special povA. son fur roads<br />
between Canberra and nej. crhhcur incJto in 1lew r-; OuItlh W-ales<br />
and betwccn. thez-Northiern Tr. tr&gt; cIthe~ tl-re surrouing<br />
SEA TRAIISPORT We have appointed Mr. M' 1lCOlr SuM2! ie r the former<br />
secretary of the Department of Tran.,: port, cas a Royal Coi-, if'iisioer<br />
to inq1uire into the M1arit.-Ie TIndustry. Ei~ s wilcl~ t e h<br />
foundation of a coiqlete x-oderni:.; ation of the laws cover. ig our:<br />
ports and our coastal and overseas trade.<br />
Vie are particul~ arly awarc-. of the burden placed on<br />
the Tasm,, aniai ecorio! my and on Tasnaiinm by their r-elijance on sea<br />
transpurt. Wle have aryoiritLcd Nimio a membe10r ofJ--the<br />
Grants Co zua5sion as a N~ o al Con,,: i ri o inc-uir into the<br />
impact of freijht ILL-cS, oCAI~ a~ arinecn<br />
THlE i-10! 1.-FORCE' Here then is a picture of tlre nat ion -rich in<br />
resources, and through our policies, ( lett. in,-j ricber; rich in its<br />
ability to develop those re,!( Jnrc('!: i. AnL Hirow( our lO . i c:<br />
getting richer, a n-I t iou. i i r in iaJ'i: ri*. UjJ-t-JIIj h. Iomj<br />
resou,. rces at home anhd abroa, v jAii uo OA Cik  fcj t1 i'il<br />
to th; tre tnm n io~ n 1, c c o1 . cie s,<br />
oettintj rircher Yet we rcco i-ec [ H At IL-1ebasic AnIst) v'Ilian<br />
resource, the to ( Il r 1jFj jov.. a m ii; j~ arj 1 o : i<br />
the Austral~ ian % workof rce, aS Skillcd EIS ally in theC liO. Cld, a<br />
hardiwo,, rki. nq as any in the world. TIhis workforce is overwhelingly<br />
and increasingly coimposed o~ f employuees. 1'] o0re than ever before<br />
and tLhe trend wX. continiuc the more skilled a pers. on is,<br />
the more likcly it is thlat hie will be an eirployee.<br />
For the first time the submnissions before e<br />
Australian Conciliation and Arbitration Coriu-ission hiavero been<br />
positive and corist. ructive. As soon as we ' were. elected we<br />
reoperied the eq. ual pay. case and our submiasion was suCCCS. Sful.<br />
31 </p>
<p>32<br />
In tha 1974 National " laye Case, we argued that the<br />
miniimum wage sli,) ulj 11j e-: tenoed worlen anCm the automatic Viage<br />
adjustmcnts to compensate for risina, prices snould be reintrodiuced.<br />
There are complli-ng . in,,, iu::; t-L-rial, social2 and rworal arguments for<br />
the eoual treatment xwo . er. n thc aorkforce. Further all women<br />
whether in the w" orkfoicc or not, will knowa the need arnd the just"-ice<br />
of automatic adjustim. ent..; to wages a-very t. 1hree mtonths. If accep~ ted<br />
by trio Comdsslon these aUtonwti. C Z. Cj LIEt:,' ntS woxuld remove the<br />
cause of miany inOU2; trial dlispu te: r' and would protect the fam., ily<br />
budget against the effects of infJ.-tion.<br />
The vast itajo::-ity of A'u-sL': liz-n oi-iJpoyees are membcrs<br />
of unions employee a-ociationF*.. Th,:',. fey to industrial<br />
efficiency is efficient cmlw) loyee organisattiecn. Our opponents<br />
have obstructed our efforts to ; o. rieand denocrat.-Lse<br />
Australian trade unions. There are too m~ lany. unions in Australia,<br />
We have souiht to recluce the number--of uyilon: 7. There are too miany<br />
needlo~ ss strik es in Austrcilaa w-, e have sought to reraova the<br />
causes nueelss striik" cs. In tocefforts we have been opposed<br />
by our opponent: s in the her PZrliamnnt and have met with no<br />
co-oper. atioll fror~ thjei Cc ujde~. ate 41-n Ch tts<br />
RestlJonsaibie leadeorship of both unions and iindustry<br />
strongly supporLts a reductiLon in t-he, nuntber of unions and of<br />
demarcaion disputes et.: nrivalj un1, ionS. Our lcg Kt" ation to<br />
help union amalgamation has beeni tiwice reject'ed by the Senate.<br />
In February J., 7,690 the Inri'utrial. Court pointed to the<br />
u r gent need for tae Austr-. Iian.. ' ew South t~~, Queen~ sla. nd,<br />
South Austr-aliari aid Weten Wstralian Parliarrents to remedy<br />
the problewms creatcd by corflictiing atnd unrx:--ordinat~ ed federal<br />
and Srtt c Ir partic-alar this situation has<br />
caused. Jndustr-iai trf throac1-co~ metition fo union membership<br />
within the saina 4indu : rv. Ul have. ;: cted u*,: q. cnt-lv on this riatter<br />
whjlich the Industrial Cutsaicl war~ gent years ago'.<br />
Ile have repeat,, dOly as-ke thle Stat-2s to ce-p aewith us in<br />
co-ordiniatincjgisai Only SQcutli Austr'aJJid has cd-<br />
We have iwet with 20o rosponse in pa.: tizular f rein Nlew South Wales,<br />
the StLate whe.!: e: the pro) Je~ is : 1' cxst acute, most urgenit.<br />
It is not my : ov. rhoweverl, to dwell or) matters<br />
where we have b-eern fairustra&amp; Led, ciAtlir by thei-Seniate ox the States.<br />
For the real story of the . a: t . seventcan inonthr, has-been one of<br />
Coninunq Q ~ izie chievemenL. It has been a story of nc-O)<br />
initiatives carried throughl, of ncov.? baginningso, of new co-operattion<br />
at all levels: tc the gr~ tand enduring1; W ac1.' antagc of tha people<br />
of raiion Outitnhhiss be o see that' n~ o Australian,<br />
nobody % who ]. ivos in Austr-alia and cjs to caZ st his J-oL with<br />
us, shoulci be eXc]. uded frmn the famiily of thc! nation. ive have<br />
s ought to unite the nation and all wiio live in it. </p>
<p>33<br />
4ce have soucjht to 3( d Pp; Ortufli. tJes mforeC &amp;%; u21L.<br />
to . O '~ UIt2o 10r&amp;; I ' ve SuC." ai i' ., Zae Ca 1-Iien rt C~ f<br />
3.. e or all Our ouo,) 0C. -Je iiL.\' Q sougit. o ; pV. r n i. 2<br />
for all citJ!. zoos th : L thrw fatiun nicgj) iL no ]. o,-Vcj 6Jqjin u<br />
the i.: xistenfcc am. us 0o: tac g. rosse-: ine~ mualij, the<br />
grouser diszadvantages, the ~ osrdiscriination.<br />
In my p.. olicy specch in 1972 T said tha! L "~ All of us<br />
as Australians are diminiihod whilIe the Abor iginec; a: dcrnio<br />
tbjei r rightful. i1: lace in this nation" Doccmbiibr ). 972 h uh<br />
d. a ill t} V: l.; J g~ u of Abor. iginal ut. 1an<br />
ma Ku: by Sh. eful b'rutality, pi . tt. on egl:, ct. andCL contcernot.<br />
We i. o not claK h: t ou,, r C LL h.) e e whoi. Y SCC. ' otul.*<br />
33uL we m.~ n. w c. ourfc We vei atb ver*' le; t OlYC<br />
a d o) to0 1.) Deupi. ~ ta d~' Aa i-a iuich h.! is ' 0een achi evA: and theroad<br />
f~ or t: 1e, kut. Ire daily clc. arer. For the -first timo<br />
S aborioiria x'oLces h" avoe 1-een hoard and iheedcd. From now on the. 1re<br />
will t1nxvT! local comvmunity councils cnd at tho national level<br />
througa the U i o:.( inal boisin close touch w-. ith<br />
Aborig * inal orJn,, on zand int--rcs ts width authority to s,* peak for thcr-;'<br />
and to work in tchei~ r Myn ~ eg~ cs-) vornmae{ t, o,, e of its f-I-St.<br />
acts, decidocd thiat I rgnsin. t Northern Terri. ry sh ) uli<br />
gratedrigh,_ s-to thcui r traditiun3i* lands&gt; wmrL oc tIc-~ A<br />
esltablished. and ap-poinced Mr. Justice EI. A. kloodlward to advise us<br />
on ho-v logi E-, I t ive uthnrity could best bct given to -that<br />
) Lt. T. I[ oei ~ th; , a not Yeth~<br />
cC: h'eI r2 Sns:. -7o t c) o vir 1I2I? Ii : ii c, nw ~ J; 3 3 to<br />
oftiiciolehve fully acce:: tcd the ovtcrW-, ciI! 1.-p i i-structi4on<br />
of t -Li. gi~ vonY in the reir~ Ou~ fl~ ito<br />
&amp;. cc~. pt rnct.. ona. I i~ feopnr ~ Abc( A. iln.. 4 V. 51110h<br />
zroAu'c.. 1i. n 3az -liamcnzt I , as oasscud, 1 the ncoudr<br />
complecmonta . eil. to to giv6d 0Tiffct to pOPl<br />
q:(-WttY. nI2V$ a ; bn rr ., ched in ~ in: e<br />
a, States:_ cl e 1' id1 0 a<br />
: oreached-c on~ -the trcansfe~ r of rc!-; poa-. sibii. ity for Ao~ iia<br />
is fx-o~,' he Queens . Slid Governm&amp; . t to the Australiean-<br />
Goverrnent., . wtheo pes cii : L deimnded 7 ya. na-o.<br />
I e int4-. cend( to c: 1. iminate the remniantf3 Of discriminatory Queens. le. nd<br />
l~~ a. cs1li jainst Aborigines and : TJlanders, a hope declared<br />
y) r4. m MnCiister Gort-on.<br />
Au~ t. c r looiwiii s neri-itled to free legal aidl<br />
from the Aboriginal Legal Servicos % we establisheOd.. </p>
<p>.34,<br />
THE,~ L-AIJI tie have soucT lt, however, to riqlecm 0, jd<br />
within the reach of all .' wu: traliaiis. arc concerned to<br />
protect arnd enhan: e tlhie: ricjhts of z2. l AuStralians. r-Je<br />
are determined to give realj moaning -, to the concept of<br />
equality before thle Law.<br />
The Australian 1. egal AieJ Sarvice has been<br />
established to ensurce ready and equnal access to the Com:' tCs<br />
to give every Ausc'Lralian ezrnual protection bofore thz! Law.<br />
The service is already funct--onincj in all State capitals and<br />
in Canberra and ] aii. Ofii. ces will Joe ened in rec~ i-inai<br />
centres throughout Australi iL n the nex~-t 3<br />
The refusal of Suppl~ y the Senate has delayed<br />
* our legislation to estcah1ish an I'ustralian ombudsman and<br />
Adninistx-ative AFpeals Tiribiiunal.<br />
Pe wanrt to simrplify the law and it~ lecss<br />
expensive, Wea'e-atbis~' d: I., aw ~ for Cct: Lmssion an~ d<br />
* have set-up a Le, isLa1i-ve Drafting~ 2: ns! 7t-itU. L Co ran<br />
in the d3rafting~ of' -, implcr an( larr-and therefo0re(<br />
better law IW e . sI a I Ie cj' is 1at e I.-o 0, en-1 t 1io ': uhl ic<br />
F, r v ant the ma) x3muzn sib-' fredmto ercisce the civil<br />
and p-olica riq'hts e~ oe yOE~~ 1L~ S<br />
VWe wjill proc,, edl with ou r iPre cidoti 6f In form~ at ion<br />
A~ ct. The rcefCrCIOdUMnpooa be fore you are e i-jneci<br />
to protect and enhance 1-ttuos r eassa ~. iocaIy. F, 1<br />
* true eqiiality ofj r-epr esent: a. i-oA in ow: r'laetaypoess<br />
As a further prote: cticrn arjainrst pervers'-wn of<br />
these processes, we -noose for th-e riisclosure of<br />
the sour1ce's of full"!-n asF; ino to<br />
The Cokrcrnftion: wAJ rpin:. Iudc i r<br />
flto-.) m! l-thorls 7cJeindcisimZ) Orn ad'-; e,-Se) yi cLJ3<br />
. ti~ zenrs or lie w-. ill re-introdunce our Qci 21, tt on fe the<br />
Sn oc'r ior Cour~ j-c-iustro ljia, a pr~ pco2Q., laulicheK. hI,<br />
; ir Garfield 1. r in lIW-: i96, clev 2 oj by the present<br />
Tea( der of the O~ o.~ r~ as 1\ trc-~ e~ a d introducerd<br />
i,. ontli ago. </p>
<p>The '\ ur-tral. i. an Coverninent is con\ vjnc-d tha t the<br />
High Court of Australia mnust: hc-comcl th-e final court in all<br />
ma tters pertaininig to Australiai andi to the legal. riqhts afld<br />
obligations of its citizens. Inrocec-. : A4--h our<br />
legslaion to abolish otePiv orc~<br />
SIle have pa., sed three jAfllS concern: fyq onqera 2 arld<br />
life insurance. Pe have 71rafted leg islat ion on novi intawaricc<br />
companPi. s and on the upervision of ins-urancre bro! kers.<br />
have twice introduce6 but not yet M.. 3se( 1 tho Finzancial<br />
Corporations Bill. Ile would nave alre~ ady introduce.( 1<br />
legislation for the controi of the securiie_ industry 1. ut<br />
for the constant dlefeorment of a report front thel 1elect,<br />
Comnmittee on Securities and ). xchanqe whiich the ~* ntesot<br />
up over 4 years ago. Ne shall. introduce a. lat iona 1. Con. n) nie S<br />
Act iwhich vyill ecj h . oriy-rr . cpePS' 0El 11uht by<br />
Lier owerr;, Yt~ since thhe late 1950' s hut aelnow. ler190ed<br />
to be un " tta -hkable through sep'Arate. acLs of the S'tate-s<br />
Vle have dJrafted 1).. jEc; slaton to ta! l.' Ian e : thikand<br />
J'und,. merntal to our whole hc OS1) andI fundamcnt. cal<br />
to our programs is the idea of a . xouzAw. tralian national<br />
sp. nt a heal thy prido ancl corifidI~ e c ow~: vs,<br />
our country's promisc in our capacity to 1. i 1t the-stan-' ords<br />
of our people andl help our less foj.-tur. 1: Le I. 0curi t<br />
fuler andl hetter-life.<br />
Sp ri. dec, arid toT o ehnel~ alrpg ec ult hteiv arOteco pla. e richol :) i~. 2i i~ cn-ur if( j forn fl1ic: i~ ounai; il<br />
fulfilmenL e have qiYn higl\, pr4-im)-ty to tliaecc11qIe<br />
of the: 7 arts, hiaa v rcC r t5 Lu1 14et r. l~ ( ounci. for<br />
the Arts, andI prcvirle2 5Q1 ( foi[ lintr art s iri our firl; t.<br />
Judcjet more ttntwi cce ou iven) hby our prdc.-ccs sors.<br />
W CdLe. hut-. no L y(' et. r s cJi. I fo:-<br />
)? otes*;__ are1the Chairman of the Aus-_ tralJian S. chools<br />
ccirriission. It is not jus t the artists themsefl5IVOFS who will<br />
benef it. Our purpose is I* o mal~ e the arts more accessible<br />
to e-ve---y Auctralian, -to let ever,. y mian and ' woman share in<br />
their challenge and enchantment and in the richer and fuller<br />
life they can 1bring. </p>
<p>36.<br />
In the past 17 m,, onths we have encouraged a<br />
greater participation of Australian creative and performing<br />
tal. ent in radio, television and! cinema production.<br />
Nlever before have there been s~ uch opportunities<br />
for Austral~ ian artists. T7e are firmly cornu ritted to<br />
miaininqa hos oportunities and increasing thewt still<br />
f urther. Xn our niext three vears tin we il<br />
prov~ ie at v-J. cost, aa daitionaEDo network<br />
w: rraihavowrcev<br />
a-n g3. C AYs~ eL e will introduoce V11 radio for high quad.  ty<br />
U'UPbac at~~ than Oni the iv ento~ lvacepted heawnd<br />
The pub!. ic iiw~ iuiry whAich we estabis41hc2 cajlcuiated that this<br />
wouw. d cost an extra $ 2250 It would have been ; anoth--r<br />
Fill. The pr.-evious coverninrii-Elso turncA a lideye to tChe<br />
tecnial o~ sib2 ~: esOf new AMY ra~ dio stations. Additional<br />
radio  Jxequcncies w-. ill enable us to exp-And the comciuJa1<br />
oerv' 3ccr;, cr-twbl; ish educational. and fora'i'n language<br />
statio,-ts and uiall-e spf-cialpro' i o ~ 1rt mnoritJy cgroupf;.<br />
W'e slijA. l introdiuCe colour tColevL5Lon in A'utrali~ a<br />
on 1 llm. rch epr ev: tLOU' goC rmub~ ie<br />
~ FsEiW~' ThY:~ ato inquje Ii the Cost Of colour<br />
* tel. evision receivers. On-. of the first. steos I ' Cook after<br />
Ibeco: minc Prilme ilirisr; Ll was to refer the10 ill-uP" ter to the<br />
Tariff ) 2adfol inq~ uiry. E'ecauee~ of action talre. 1 by my<br />
goeri~ ntto datc, colour television rc. ceives in Australia<br />
will1 be availaWle to thce public-at a xmuchi ciicaocr price than<br />
~ ould have been the had. Jh inquiry not brZ! en held.<br />
We hal; e etl. hdthe Filmn and T ol r i S o 1<br />
School anJ we ILicrodhice Tcq-.( JSiL. Y u~ rteA~ rl<br />
ara nlv s the Austi~ xalian I; oniC. L'rthe Au,,-traliari<br />
Na t: 01n1 a-~ CU andJ Col ct) i. onr3 th AutT 1' ii an i111.<br />
CO'MS iCon, -L o 11. i: s ru : onht Aieic inCT<br />
a ndTT-t-1l--Fc-ou) 1-nty.<br />
In short, as far a qovernmnts can act in<br />
terms of money and iiiachiner, , e v re creal~ inq the conditions<br />
for a renascence of Australian creativity. </p>
<p>-37.<br />
-f V3T:' RNA'T TniJ7t%, ITT O MS<br />
: lore than ever before Austral. ians ar1c en-tit * lCe<br />
to feel Lorit'l in theiAr nation. T~ oe have never beec( n liel-0 in<br />
higcher respect abroad. ore than ever beforc Austk-ralians<br />
arc, eititCledl to feel confid6enit. I have said much ahout: our<br />
resources. In the final analysis our r: icbest resource, an<br />
irreplaceablie one, is our naitionial rei,-u t* at. ion). Tha t<br />
reputation has never been higher. Ir have saiA muc-h about<br />
providing security for all. our citizens. In its wiclest<br />
sense this country has ne-ver 1-) en more secure. A u s tr a'( iL now<br />
has bas.-ica).]. y a bi. partisax forei. gn Policy, not b~ ecause of<br />
any change o-f heart or miric1 on the partk-of our opponerits, b ut<br />
bracause we; as a' governmont recoyrnisc~ d and acted ur) ofl the"<br />
rea.-lities of worl affairs and above all t he realities of our<br />
regi~ on. Our op ' poneni11-s hav\, e just cuh: up witk-h reality.<br />
* The feairc, the shih-b) oleths on which they trziae for a<br />
generat:;. on have. been sw-erpt aw! ay. Try as they ight wish as<br />
they magih. our o-f;-onents cannot return to the Dast'.<br />
It is beccause iw. e rcgic1the realities of<br />
* our tines t'hat orforeign policy has )-een so succes! sfl<br />
Wand our defence policy so relevant. e approa--ch the<br />
managementl-of def-ence matter-cs on the basis thi. tL the<br />
interna:: tional situt~ tion and the-atfairs of the region Ere in<br />
the process of rapidt clh ; nqe. Tie saw that defe', nce policy and<br />
foreiLgn policy hdto b~ e b-rought into line wi'jth these changjes,<br />
into lina with tliese reatlities. Ile saw-v how. fax-both deifcrnce<br />
and foreign po: licy had beco-me basedl on p-ast concept~ s iand~ eeep<br />
rtisconcc -tions of thec proesent.<br />
In 1.972 -1 undertook to loadt( this country to her<br />
rightful proud ancd securce pl. ace in th-e w-. orld. IA--can be<br />
w proud of our repu kation can ccoi. n* :. dciint of our sccur'it.<br />
V-e have set a nevy course fo. x-Australia v'ay from<br />
interventionism, towards tr--* uc interlnationali sin. This i s the<br />
most genu;. neiy interinational govern-ment lustra J. ia has ever<br />
O had. VTh have placedl our relations-hips with the United<br />
S tates and the United Ringdom on tho basis of mature<br />
partne rr; h) ip1. ' ec have reneg9ot-iated the aqr-ceint for -the<br />
L-te States flaval Communication St~ ation ilto rth v-est Cape.<br />
The agreement sjigned by our opponent. s: vas a denial of<br />
Austral. ia's rights. The new agreevient asserts and establishesF<br />
them. ha;: ve-wid'. ened our ho-rizons, sought anti, achieved<br />
growing co-operation with t~ te count: ries of the Cornmnwe,( alth<br />
and with the nations round. the In ian and south Pacifi. c<br />
Oceans. </p>
<p>17e have: Irouciht co-operation and frin:. 1ship with<br />
Japan, our greatest trading partner, to a new~ l-vel.<br />
Followinq an agreem.--ent in principle between Prime ' Iinister<br />
Toy last Octobe.-r, We'i c1e into a treal-y of ricileWShi<br />
theTra of Fjs~ er<br />
Ue have sought to 1. realh Oown ideological constraints<br />
which had for so long; oLbstructeO! meaningful relationships with<br />
countries such as China, Past Germiany aylo Uar1 Viet!~~ L<br />
Wc have sought to remove any taint of racism from<br />
our national and ite: rnatioja. nolicies.<br />
Pe havo co--opera'tel c. Lo. sely with the Government and<br />
H~ ouse of Assemibly of Papua P ew Gluinea as our neighbour moves<br />
* towards independlence bDy Dccemher this year.<br />
TlJe hwave forgued and intiriate links with the<br />
countries of'. A. S. V". A. rlI. TnrI. 0neSIa-, the Philippines, ~ a~ a<br />
Thai lan!. e-n6 1i-lrrh ave acce-pt-ed their inv ita tio. n<br />
to co-operatec with A. S i Qfl devt-lorv ' ot ts.<br />
With the agreceme: nt of all1 it-s nieibers, we have<br />
secured the remodellinrg o; . E A PC<br />
Ue haove-, taken f irm moarures for disarmlaltent and<br />
against the develo; rf cnt and pr: ol zf-ra ticr of nuc lear waos<br />
Pe have ratif-ied the nuclear non-prolifera. tion treaLy and<br />
the Sea.-led Arms Cont--: ol Treaty. Ile have protosted ar1a jis t<br />
C h i ne se t es ts IWe niali used every availab?. o, leqal. an.-.<br />
* politica). channel to persuade F-rance to desist from its<br />
atmospheric polluinlon ixn our h em) ni S I crr<br />
VWe have actively suipported the obrjectives of the<br />
zoofpne ae ad nutrality in South Fna; t Asia and the<br />
Indian Ocean z~ ne of peaco. Pe haye madle pol-.' rrful<br />
W reprOsentat4io3ns in T,*' ashi~ nq1: c-n an. ocwto p! r suacle the-m<br />
to exorcis8' restrai~ nt annI not to ma]:. ehe Indian Ocecmi yet<br />
another scene for great, pownr rivalry.<br />
Wehave introlue3 1, ul: vetpa~. lciQtn<br />
to eaals nAsi] inPvio'n: L; It:~ c] nY' in<br />
order to . lii-v h! a ruaii-. our a ir) ) Yoq rain, arvO -move.<br />
tctdh0{~-I Zton a 1 ta3-cq ei, wih C, we~ hav, aci; eptc d, o( 7 </p>
<p>39.<br />
Dr, T-PNCE W'. e have encouraged and supotd the-, ' Jetente<br />
betwoen the great po',, Yers-. 1,, e have tal-en aclvantag of the more<br />
hopeful ou-L. ook in our region to _ reorjanisc: Australia's<br />
defence forces. To giv,, e a tarigible and pcactical basis to<br />
our defence relations wi1.. th ot-hcr countri. es we have ebredon<br />
an expanded progia of exercises w, it h our neighbours and.<br />
traitional allies. In June, the l? rqest peacc-timei exerCise<br />
ever held in Australi-a will be helrd in Queenslanrd involving<br />
over 8,000 servicemeri fromn Australia, P1ew Zealanrl, the U~ nited<br />
States and Gj: eat Britain.<br />
The Deputy Prime ! JnistCer, iny . closest colleague<br />
downn the yca:,_ s, T1r Lance Parn;; rd, has provocd the most<br />
const.-ructivc. and effective, ministerial, hea( 2 of the, dlefence<br />
forces in Aut: la'ahistory. T-je has ayialgaal-. cd the IDcfa~ ncce<br />
JDeparytvtent and the 3 Service tert ( is reo;~ n~ din the<br />
report, of the-iqorsho-ad Coitmit-Cee wshi. ch our predE. cc,. ssors<br />
sup-pressr-2 -oz 15 yeaors. HeI has-underta):,' n to es1to;*&amp; jish the.<br />
co:,-bined Au.-tralian Defence Frce Academ~;-y. The scvices are<br />
being~ equipped to pleay a gjreater role in case of c1neracricies<br />
and natural disasters. He has presenter'. to the Parliame-nnt a chiarter<br />
for the Citizen Military Force s, -a newv cdisciplinary code o<br />
the forces a nenw p2: ocurcenert p~~~ mfor taW,' s : cna ie<br />
aOrcraft and destrors. ( Our p) Xo5cft. ta-nkzs %,, ere orclerci y h<br />
last Lab-or Governmient a quartern of a century ago.)<br />
fie has ap.-po~ nted. a military ombudsman.<br />
F~ e has instiituted. the-regul ar ; rceviev, of: sn. vitce Pay and<br />
allowances and a comprell-ronsive andl coiworoeni, ibl a Defence<br />
Forces Retirement ar(! Docath 11( new~ itc schcme. Pie has co-o-: 1: inated<br />
the passaae of 17 measures 31-alin( T With 3-0_ repatriOat: io31, taxa-Ftion,<br />
eduication and acco-mmodati'on bene fits for sorviceiztfn and the<br />
draftIing of 9 more such measures.<br />
In short, we have.-ila) ycd steidily and firmly<br />
towards our aimi that Auta:.* salhave theC cfence-. forces<br />
she needs -finely e-quipperl, higjhly professi. onal, high mobile<br />
and highly respected. </p>
<p>rV<br />
Here then i. s a record of achieve-ment, of purpose,<br />
yet it-is a record of a governrnent w.. hich has heen in office<br />
a mere 17 months. It is a record -6f a government which came<br />
into oiflfice after 23 unhrol! en Years of Dower hecld by our<br />
~ o~ o~ ns~ 23 years or decay and neglect. It i~ s a record of<br />
a govcrrni.. ent whicl-had hva, -o overcoiie unparaliclled<br />
o b st *-, ti: ion i n . a S c n a 4-Q i n i) ic h I JLt wa s in a i,, noc) r it Y. ThiS<br />
was our legacy inl 1972 23 yearis of* our opoets'iStZ1, e~ s<br />
and a hostiAle Sen,-ate. rl-e havre lived with the part and wer have<br />
ovc _ rcc-. nea thec-past, the record shiow-s it.<br />
11ow our opponernt,,: propose._ a return to the past,<br />
* the attitucles aneA policies of . the past whiich you so firmly<br />
rejecteO only 17 imonths agjo. tlhere hoe no ~ mistake abrout<br />
the truLe na-'. ture o: E thes tii-. n-s and olicies. In the, oast<br />
17 months our oppo. nents ha-ve siiown no repentancc,, they h'ave.<br />
done ) o On ev r mAjor issue ilow a) s always, they<br />
* come cOown on the side of prvl~. Th-e who7Lle thrust their<br />
policies . ceiflis theC retenL-ion o-c priviloge
priv-41l':. io. ThiLs has been tl-e t x runningJ through the~ ir<br />
pattern o-C'f obStruction and o-Pporsition. They resistO. to the<br />
ele-enth hour our proposals ~ oqivo 1mosti mone'.,, to the -oSt<br />
nee-dy sc] ools. The \ 7 havo ohbst--_ ct-ed "-at every tu" rn our la r<br />
to give health covor tCo th-: milliii unlprotectec! Australians..<br />
OQl : every cccas:! on tILhey have s~ prung to the dlefence of we'illthy<br />
interest-. who fear-that ouir ofo~ sto retain the greater<br />
haeof Iuiztralia; n control ov'er our resources may inconvenience<br />
tbc-m1. They hay--opposedt our every effort to have qreate-r<br />
c'ualil-in parli~. lcentary re~~ eiaini uta.<br />
The last elect~ ion was oezscritiaJ. ly about the<br />
pro-motk-ion of op,? tuin itict-: of ;: urr c, i -* XorJt-un itie 3 ane-d morla<br />
eC'ual opportunities, all~ i Austra1.1* 0r1S. n the past .17<br />
onths that effort has been carrica on with zcst, deter-ii,, iation<br />
and Ispucciceecs s sccs of course the tiimeF hasbe<br />
short, the back~ log of 23 years so groat The question now<br />
is % whether that work1-shall go on.-.--The quostion iS whether the<br />
great opporitunItie. s this nation* offero -shall ba more and m.. ore<br />
equally sha-red, whether prfvilege halbe deeper and ezeeper<br />
entrenched. This lawhat you have to1c lecide.<br />
W~ hen they makeo thieir jue~ geii,: ent I to the basic<br />
intelligence and idealism of t! 7 Australian people. I rely on<br />
it, and I -rely upon it with confidenno-a. in all my fafforts to<br />
reform and revital. ise Australia, in my efforts to reform<br />
and revitaliSe the Australian Lalo. P. artv, 1 have relied upon<br />
that: inteolligencia and t,-ha't Lres Andi voru havje never Let<br />
me down. T look to the imen cJ. 7, ustrali-' who bel,-ieve in a fair<br />
go not. just a fair go for an elected' g overnmnent, hut a fair<br />
go for all those of their fel. low citizens to whi . Cur policies<br />
have brought a new hope, a ne' chan ce for a Odecent life. I<br />
look to the women of Australia, who .'-ell ifnow what our program, </p>
<p>has-alre-ady meant for the future, welfare of our children, of<br />
our aged, our sick, oxr f~ look,.-to the idealism<br />
of that vast new constitucency of irura anl women over the acjTe<br />
of 18 now voting for thc first tiri~ e. It ip, al-ove all their<br />
f; uture at stake. 1' or the outco.-me o this clectio must go<br />
t ar to de!: ocrmine the sort of Austcal ia they will be living in<br />
for the rest of their lives.<br />
Bere is the recordl. !! ere is the:. promise of the<br />
fulfilment of the pi-ogram!; w have begun with such vigor and<br />
determiation with dcaicaticn. que, tion is whetCher<br />
the action of our opponents last month was only a temporary<br />
interruption to thosre progrc~ ms or the-i-r dlestri. ction. It is<br />
nonsenfse to believe that oppunlants w'oul. d accept and apply<br />
our prcjms and policies w, h ich they resisf. ed and. deriJded for<br />
* 23 yas rel. ory--Austrahians?-it is a tima for decision,<br />
and I put thc. e quetionsj to ' iou.<br />
Are you for e. fcU. i go, not just a fair go 
an elected Govornwm: nt, but a fargo for our program to w-ork?<br />
Are you for giving us a chaince to make them work?<br />
Are youi for Pixst--aliris haiga fair opplortunilty<br />
to have a fai-r share in conti. L. and1 ownership of theirJ. 3 own<br />
resources? Are you In favour of giving every Austral1-ian chlildi,<br />
whatever his parents i~ iani ocj ~ cd a ifair start, an equal<br />
start in life? Av~ e yo. u : E-01. h du. wa have given to our<br />
children, to the O-pcndLrt, tho cli. ,; z! dvantaqge-d in our community?<br />
S Aro y'ou foi: thic :, iore docent the more humane,<br />
the more toie: caP:, thc :~ int : ooe'coi ety wic have been<br />
trying to build1 in thie last J. 7 im. onths?<br />
A ro: t 1, e A u str, 1i a n p-cofIe-to allowed to rear)<br />
the full harvest, 11 of ouor pro'jrams?<br />
I don't1 be). imive the. Autralian people areL(-going<br />
to turn h-ac. 1 don't belie4. ve they'r going to turn their backs<br />
on the promis-. of the future.<br />
I d. on' t bohl ove thg ecoing to throw wimy the<br />
new opjortuwA.' S -11C newJ hiopes, -! ic new iitiozial fpirit ar-A<br />
national self-r. se. </p>
<p>r 42.<br />
I ( Ion't -elie7e they wjia :. 1 a &gt;-ar Of the<br />
tactics, the bl;: tart opportmn. i sm of ouw opponents.<br />
I don't believe for a :-icren t th. Cy arr-AhCit<br />
do wlh! at they , ave refused to do in all our histcry<br />
a strncg, united cqover: frent, i tqovnrnmnent wilJ. l a clear program,<br />
a proven record, a great record, and hand this country over to<br />
a Odiscreitied, di. sunited, ( iiscarded coalition of fru-ltration<br />
and futility, without policies, without unity, without<br />
leader,. jhip. And t1at is the real choice on the 18 tva,,,.<br />
Therofore I looj: lith ronfidence to a great vrote<br />
of affirmation on the R 1ay a migyhty votc of ye yes I-o<br />
our xeferenCitui prop -sals yes to tu return of o-r gjovernment<br />
t" e fut!. Iv,, a bright confidant, prCoud, secure future </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
