<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6235</transcript-id>
    <title>BURDEKIN DAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006235.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMEE: MINSTR<br />
BURDEKIN DAM<br />
I give an unequivocal commitment on behalf of the Federal<br />
Government to total continuity of funding for construction<br />
of the Burdekin Dam.<br />
There have been promises to build the Burdekin Dam virtually<br />
continuously since the Second World War.<br />
I am proud it is only the Federal Labor Government that has<br />
matched its promises with action.<br />
The $ 13 million we will spend on the Dam this financial year<br />
will enable construction of the main Dam Wall to commence at<br />
last. The Chifley Government's Snowy Mountains Scheme was an<br />
historic recognition of the significance to Austra. Lia of<br />
major developmental works.<br />
The Snowy Scheme became a cornerstone of post-war<br />
reconstruction.<br />
The early completion of the Burdekin Dam will confirm the<br />
Federal Labor Government's role in fulfilling the historic<br />
needs of Australians a Government pursuing coherent,<br />
confident, robust policies for national davelopment.<br />
The demeaning and destructive comments about the dam by the<br />
Deputy Opposition Leader, Mr Howard, are an indictment of<br />
the Coalition.<br />
For example, The Age of 19 August quotes Mr Howard as<br />
saying: I wouldn't have regarded the Burdekin Dam as any more<br />
sacrosanct than other areas. I'd have put it into<br />
hotch-potch with some of the other things".<br />
The last thing the people of North Queensland need is for a<br />
cloud to be cast over this great national development<br />
project.<br />
With a Federal Budget of over $ 50 billion, it is amazing<br />
that Mr Howard has singled out the Burdekin Dam as the one<br />
project to be consigned to the scrap heap.<br />
The people of North Queensland have waited 30 years for the<br />
Burdekin Dam. Isn't that long enough even for Mir HIoward?,<br />
Even more disturbing is the absolute silence on Mr Howard's<br />
remarks by the Opposition Leader, Mr Peacock, and the Leader<br />
of the National Party, Mr Anthony. </p>
<p>In the face of their apparent disinterest or worse there is<br />
no doubt Mr Howard would get his way as Treasurer under a<br />
Liberal-National Government although on the Opposition's<br />
current performance such a Government is a long way off.<br />
There is an interesting paral. lel between the Burdekin dam<br />
and the history of the Tennessee Valley Authority in the<br />
United States.<br />
The Tennessee Valley Authorifry was dogged by interference,<br />
was vilified in Congress, was abandoned by two American<br />
Presidents, was hindered at every turn for 20 years.<br />
Australia's 20 year wait indeed 30 year wait is over<br />
at least while I have any say in the matter.<br />
A great: deal. of the credit for our final decision to proceed<br />
with the Burdekin Dam must go to the forceful and persuasive<br />
representations of the Stat,: Opposition Leader, Keith<br />
Wright. He has been a great advocate for North Queensland to his<br />
Federal Government colleagues and will continue to be as<br />
Premier., I have noted Keith Wright's commitment on behalf of the<br />
State Labor Party to the building of a water pipeline from<br />
the Burdekin Dam to Townsville on the basis of one-third<br />
funding from each of the Federal, State and Local<br />
Governments. I look forward to discussing this proposal with Keith Wright<br />
when he is Premier.<br />
Tenders for the mass concrete gravity wall of the Burdekin<br />
Dam closed on September 20. Eleven tenders have been<br />
received. I understand the range and quality of these tenders has been<br />
very favourable. There should be little difficulty in<br />
selecting an appropriate tender. Accordingly, I urge the<br />
Queensland Government to quickly come forward with a<br />
recommended tender for the Federal Government's<br />
consideration and approval.<br />
We want the construction of the Burdekii Dam to proceed as<br />
quickly as practicable and will work hard for its completion<br />
by 1988.<br />
Townsv il1le<br />
9 October 1983 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
