<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4860</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT LUNCHEON FOR PRESIDENT SCHEEL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/10/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004860.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
UTALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 24 OCTOBER 1978<br />
ADDRES S<br />
AT<br />
LUNCHEON FOR PRESIDENT SCHEEL<br />
It is a great pleasure to welcome you Sir, to Australia.<br />
This is the first occasion on which we have been visited<br />
by a President of the Federal Republic of Germany. It is<br />
an important milestone in the relationship between our two<br />
nations. Mr President, we welcome you not only because of the significance<br />
of your position, but also because your deep sense of commitment<br />
and strength of purpose have put you in the front rank of today's<br />
European statesmen.<br />
In the course of your political career, you have shown a<br />
willingness to chart new courses, and since your assumption<br />
of the Presidency you have maintained a lively and critical<br />
interest in domestic and world affairs.<br />
Your visit to Australia demonstrates the breadth of your<br />
interests and your acute awareness of changing trends.<br />
As I believe you said, before you departed on this visit,<br />
looking at Australia from the German perspective " The political<br />
economic and strategic significance of Australia, and of the<br />
whole South Pacific Region, is rapidly increasing... ( Thus) it<br />
is a good thing to intensify our exchange of views and our<br />
co-operation with Australia."<br />
We, for our part, have watched with admiration Germany's<br />
development as one of the world's great and most stable<br />
democracies. The economic miracle of the Federal Republic<br />
has been spoken of so often that the very real truth contained<br />
in that phrase is sometimes overlooked.<br />
The economic restoration of your country to the first rank of<br />
the industrial world is a great tribute to the German people<br />
and a reminder that seemingly insuperable problems can be<br />
overcome by dedication, determination and a willingness to<br />
work. / Z </p>
<p>-2<br />
Just as important is-the Republic's record of democratic<br />
constitutional innovation and the strength of its commitment<br />
to the democratic process and the rule of law.<br />
Mr President, there is considerable common ground between us.<br />
our countries have a commitment to democratic values and<br />
institutions. We have economic and strategic interests in<br />
common, and similar approaches to the major problems of the<br />
day. Australia and Germany are far from one another, but your<br />
visit underscores the fact that distance has not obscured<br />
the very real interests we share.<br />
Economically, politically and not least strategically, Germany,<br />
Australia and the world's other democracies are inter-dependent.<br />
The democracies are not just similar political systems,<br />
isolated and scattered at random across the globe, or merely<br />
inter-dependent in just a narrow sense.<br />
The democracies constitute what is in reality a community,<br />
drawing sustenance and encouragement from one another,<br />
recognising that our values, our national security and our<br />
prosperity must be safeguarded on a global basis.<br />
To maintain their strength the democracies must not only<br />
recognise the nature of their inter-dependence, but also<br />
continue to make economic progress.<br />
Unfortunately in the last few years we have all encountered<br />
economic problems of varying degrees. Australia and the<br />
Federal Republic of Germany have had much in common in our<br />
approaches to these problems.<br />
We in Australia have long respected the steadfast manner in<br />
which the German Federal Government a government which I<br />
should point out is on the other side of the political fence<br />
from my own has consistently pursued policies directed at<br />
reducing and controlling inflation.<br />
Those policies have, of course, been based on the need to<br />
exercise fiscal and monetary restraint a lesson which I<br />
know you in Germany learned from your bitter experience with<br />
the disastrous social and economic effects of high inflation.<br />
Germany's progress in controlling inflation has now enabled<br />
you to take action to expand demand, thereby improving the<br />
outlook for world trade. There is an important lesson here,<br />
but because time and patience are required it is not a message<br />
which has instant popular appeal, and we should seek ways of<br />
getting it better understood.<br />
Mr President, we have heard that of the many records you<br />
have set, some have even reached the German hit parade.<br />
Perhaps, with your fine singing voice, if you were to record<br />
a popular song on this subject, the message might be better<br />
spread. It wouldn't have the lilt of " High on the Yellow Wagon",<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
and I'm not sure exactly how the lyrics would . but the<br />
message could be based on the recent speech by Emile Van Lennep,<br />
a speech which might just as easily have come from Helmit Schmidt.<br />
In that speech, Secretary General Van Lennep pointed out that<br />
" unacceptably high rates of inflation remain the fundamental<br />
obstacle to getting back to full employment." It is a message<br />
that calls for a steady application of policies over the medium<br />
term. That is the strategy which your government has pursued, and it<br />
is the strategy my Government is also determined to maintain.<br />
There is, however, one respect in which the policies of all<br />
members of the European Community bear re-examination. My<br />
Government believes that the common agricultural policy of the<br />
Economic Community is unreasonably excluding many producers<br />
from the European market.<br />
We believe this threatens the further development of world<br />
trade, and is against the economic interests of the members<br />
of the E. C.<br />
It is not that we fail to understand the problems confronting<br />
the European Community or are preoccupied with our own concerns.<br />
Against the background of many years of international conflict<br />
we endorse the importance of the broad political and economic<br />
objectives of the European Community.<br />
What we find difficult to understand is that Europe should<br />
apparently overlook the great dangers that could flow if it<br />
should now fail to adopt more outward looking trade policies.<br />
Of course, Mr President, we do distinguish between the policy<br />
attitudes of the Republic in this matter and those which I<br />
characterised as the policies of " Europe".<br />
We know that Germany has argued its points of view in the counsels<br />
of Europe and at economic summits. We should be delighted if<br />
these views achieved greater success in those interminable<br />
counsels in Brussels.<br />
Mr President, we welcome the increasing role that Germany is<br />
playing in diplomacy and global matters in general, because<br />
there are major issues facing the international community.<br />
Not the least of these involve trade and the international<br />
economy. It is of the utmost importance that powerful trading blocs such<br />
as the European Community recognise that trade decisions made<br />
in Europe reverberate around the world, that they have political<br />
and strategic consequences which could endure far beyond their<br />
shorter-run economic impact.<br />
The recognition of this is one reason why, as we understand it,<br />
the Federal Republic has argued for an outward looking trading<br />
policy for reduced barriers to trade, an end to increased ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
protectionism, and a recxgniticn of the importance of shared<br />
political, economic and strategic interests.<br />
Mr President, although your visit is a comparatively short one,<br />
I am sure that it will give you the opportunity to gain an<br />
appreciation of Australia.<br />
I extend to you and your distinguished colleagues a very warm<br />
welcome and my very best wishes for a successful and enjoyable<br />
visit. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
