<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3738</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, 13 MAY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003738.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1W EMBARGO 7.30 P<br />
NATIONAL BROADCAST A<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
13 MAY 1975<br />
I would like to report to you on the valuable and wide-ranging<br />
discussions I have been having overseas during the Parliamentary<br />
recess. With the Special Minister of State and senior officials<br />
of the Australian Government, I have been attending the Meeting<br />
of Commnonwealth Heads of Government in Kingston, Jamaica. On<br />
the way to Jamaica we visited Peru the first visit by an<br />
Australian Prime Minister to a South American country. And on<br />
the way home I had talks in Washington with President Ford,<br />
Vice-President Rockefeller, Secretary of State Kissinger and<br />
senior members of the United States Congress. So in the space<br />
of a fortnight there have been opportunities for Australia to<br />
exchange views with leaders from every part of the world to<br />
establish new friendships and build on old ones.<br />
0There h as'never been a time when events in the world have<br />
moved so swiftly or suddenly as they have during the past two<br />
years. The extraordinary changes in our own region the recent<br />
decisive events in Indo-China were of course very much in our<br />
minds; but that's only a part of the story, part of the pattern<br />
of change and upheaval in recent years. Since the Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government met in Ottowa in 1973 there have been farreaching<br />
developments in Africa, in Cyprus, in the Middle East;<br />
the western nations have grappled with inflation and unemployment;<br />
the gap between the developing and the developed nations has<br />
grown wider. So this is very much a time when national leaders<br />
must get together to discuss their problems in an atmosphere<br />
of frankness and intimacy.<br />
I know there is a tendency in some quarters to disparage the<br />
Commonwealth as a debating society, or as the vestige of a<br />
bygone empire. I don't share those views for a moment. Here<br />
we have an organisation that brings together heads of Government-<br />
Presidents and Prime Ministers or their representatives from<br />
34 nations representing a quarter of the world's people, nations<br />
of every kind, rich and poor, consumers and producers, agricultural<br />
and industrial, developed and developing, and from every part of<br />
the world.<br />
There is an obvious value in this diversity, but there is an<br />
equal value in the shared traditions of the Commonwealth partners.<br />
The very fact that all our discussions are in English gives an<br />
ease and familiarity to our meetings that cannot be valued too<br />
highly. It's not so long ago that many member nations were a<br />
little cynical and indifferent about the Commonwealth and<br />
some States were reluctant to join it. There is no sign of<br />
such attitudes today. At the next meeting, for example, Papua<br />
New Guinea will take her seat as an independent nation; and in<br />
the years ahead other newly independent countries of the South<br />
Pacific will be admitted to Commonwealth membership. So year </p>
<p>2.<br />
by year the Commonwealth gains in numbers, gains in strength,<br />
and I believe, gains in wisdom, experience, and prestige.<br />
The -truly remarkable thing about our discussions in Jamaica<br />
was the readiness of every nation to get down to essential<br />
issues and the striking measure of agreement we reached. You<br />
will remember that Commonwealth conferences in the past were<br />
often occasions for squabbling and grandstanding. There were<br />
endless confrontations between the nations of the old white<br />
Commonwealth and the newly independent states of Asia and<br />
Africa. There was nothing of that sort in Jamaica. On the<br />
particular issues of racism and de-colonisation, for example,<br />
there was complete agreement. Every nation confirmed its<br />
total support for the African people of Southern Rhodesia-<br />
Zimbabwe in their struggle for independence on the basis<br />
of majority rule. Every nation reaffirmed the need for the<br />
Indian Ocean to remain an area of peace and stability and<br />
expressed concern about military bases in the region and<br />
when we remember that something like half the member nations<br />
0 of the Commonwealth are island, coastal or hinterland states<br />
of the Indian Ocean that is not perhaps surprising. Again,<br />
every nation supported the-need for international assistance<br />
in the rehabilitation and reconstruction of Indo-China. Every<br />
nation expressed concern at the continued testing and proliferation<br />
of nuclear weapons and reaffirmed the need for a comprehensive<br />
ban on all nuclear weapons tests.<br />
Every nation supported the withdrawal of foreign armed forces.<br />
from Cyprus. I was particularly gratified, on the Cyprus<br />
0 question, that Australia was accepted as a member of a committee<br />
of eight Commonwealth nations which will seek ways of restoring<br />
the independence and territorial integrity of Cyprus on the<br />
basis of United Nations resolutions.<br />
On all these issues I was able to put Australia's views, and<br />
in every case the outcome was deeply satisfying not just<br />
because the resolutions of the conference happen to-coincide<br />
with my own Government's foreign policies, but because they<br />
represent the views of so many different states, and were<br />
reached without rancour, without dissension, in an atmosphere<br />
of extraordinary goodwill.<br />
There was one problem in Jamaica that stood out above all othersthe<br />
need to find a new and equitable international economic<br />
order. All of us recognised that many, if not most, of the<br />
world's problems really come down to a single basic issuehow<br />
best to distribute the world's resources, how best to<br />
reduce the disparities between the rich and poor nations,<br />
between the haves and the have-nots in the world. </p>
<p>3.<br />
In tackling that question the most difficult challenge<br />
facing mankind I believe we were tackling the root cause<br />
-of tension and conflict in the world. of course it would be<br />
rash to pretend that we found the answers, but we did find<br />
a remarkable readiness on every side among the rich industrial<br />
nations as well as the poorer ones to seek the answers.<br />
Everyone agreed on the range and complexity of the issues<br />
involved. Everyone agreed that trade, not aid, is the real<br />
answer to the needs of the developing countries. We agreed<br />
to set up a group of experts who will draw up, for consideration<br />
by Commonwealth Governments, a comprehensive and inter-related<br />
program of practical measures to help close the gap between the<br />
rich and poor countries.<br />
In Washington I was able to give some account of our discussions<br />
to President Ford, as well as hear his own views on current<br />
problems, both-in America and the world at large. In the<br />
wake of the recent events in Indo-China, the President assured<br />
me of America's firm and continuing commitment to her allies<br />
in our region and in other parts of the world. Yet welcome<br />
as these assurances were, they are not the sole basis for my<br />
confidence in Australia's--future, in Australia's security, or<br />
in Australia's place in the world. Everywhere I went in my<br />
talks in Peru, where we have forged a new and valuable link<br />
with a Pacific nation, in my talks in Jamaica with Commonwealth<br />
leaders, in my talks'in Washington I found both great goodwill<br />
for Australia and a calm, steady belief in the strength of our<br />
common institutions, in our friendships and our alliances, in<br />
the ability of nations to overcome their difficulties with<br />
rational programs and united efforts. Nowhere in my talks with<br />
world leaders did I find any disposition to panic, to lose faith,<br />
to lose heart, to lose nerve. The United States, in particular,<br />
having come through her great domestic and international agonies,<br />
will be better placed now to build on her true strengths and<br />
profit by past experience. I said as much in Washington; and<br />
I pledged that Australia would be a ready and willing partner<br />
of the United States in her efforts to build a more rational<br />
world order and tackle the great problems of the developing world.<br />
We still have to beat some problems at home, but they are no<br />
different in kind from those of other comparable countries.<br />
Where we in Australia are truly fortunate is in our strengths<br />
the undoub~ ed strength of our friendships, the rare abundance<br />
of our resources, the tested spirit and steadiness of our people,<br />
the goodwill we enjoy in every part of the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
