<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7009</transcript-id>
    <title>ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF REGIONAL DAILIES DUBBO - 30 SEPTEMBER 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/09/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007009.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARG03DO UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF REGIONAL DAILIES<br />
DUBBO 30 SEPTEMBER 1986<br />
Chairman, Directors, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
First, let me thank you for the invitation to Hazel and me<br />
to be with you tonight at this celebration to mark the<br />
Anniverrsary of the Regional Dailies Association of<br />
Au Stcr Ii a.<br />
This is not, of course, my first involvement in one of the<br />
Association's annual conferences, having previously been<br />
with you during my ACTU days and again two years ago at your<br />
meeting in Canberra.<br />
I assumo, by the way, that there is no particular<br />
significance intended in the zoological surroundings tonight<br />
either that you regard your industry as an endangered<br />
specieG or that I should regard this captive audience as<br />
fairf cjm<br />
of course the relationship between politicians and the media<br />
is as close as it is uneasy. There are cynics on both<br />
sides. Samuel Butler once said that the most important service<br />
rendered by the press is that of educating people to<br />
approach printed matter with distrust.<br />
Whereas the American journalist Frank Simonds replied, there<br />
is but one way for a newspaperman to look at a politician,<br />
and that is down.<br />
Seriously, however, it is a pleasure to be here tonight,<br />
away from Canberra and the State capitals, and in the<br />
company of professional newspaper people who are in close<br />
touch with the ordinary men and women of Australia. </p>
<p>In a continent as large and with such a scattered population<br />
as Australia, the regional dailies serve a vital role. Your<br />
papers do much more than just offer a news service. They<br />
foster a sense of community and identity.<br />
At last count t he 36 member papers of the Regional Dailies<br />
Association, I am to'd, had a combined circulation of well<br />
over half a million, with a readership of around 2 million.<br />
Aside from promoting co-operation between its members, the<br />
Regional Dailies Association has an important industrial<br />
relations role, as well as sponsoring research and promoting<br />
the industry.<br />
It is a measure of the group's effectiveness that the<br />
Association remains strong and viable some 50 years after<br />
its establishr~ ent. This is a credit to the leadership of<br />
the organisation.<br />
The strength of the regional dailies is based on the<br />
provincial ci. t.. es and towns of Australia. Although<br />
Australia is regarded as one of the most urbanised countries<br />
on earth, this overlooks the fact that almost one in three<br />
Australiano lives outside the capital cities.-<br />
only a small percentage of these non-metropolitan<br />
Australians live on the land, in the sense of being farmers<br />
or residents of very small country towns. Most of them~ live<br />
in large provincial towns and cities of the kind represented.<br />
by your newspaperz places like Burnie, Ballarat, Bathurst,<br />
and Bundaberg.<br />
Although the garm crisis and Australia's related balance of<br />
payments difficulties have recently focused ouch attention<br />
on provincial Australia, the fact is that for well over a<br />
decade now irdeed, since its inception at the turn of the<br />
century the Australian Labor Party has had strong regional<br />
roots and policies.<br />
In the early 1970s the ALP was the first major political<br />
party to articulate a coherent policy of regional<br />
development. flany of those innovative programs were<br />
suspended in the years following 1975. But the philosophy<br />
remained part of Labor's thinking.<br />
The principle of popular participation of grassroots<br />
democracy, if you like has always been one of the<br />
distinguishing characteristics of ALP philosophy. Those of<br />
you who follow the Labor Party's vigorous internal debates<br />
would be aware that in practice this democratic spirit is at<br />
times overproof. I </p>
<p>Ii 3<br />
This participation principle has become, and remains, a<br />
touchstone of governmental practice in the 1980s. When I<br />
launched the Labor Government's re-election platform, I<br />
said: " The needs of the four and a half million people who<br />
live and work outside the major cities are at the<br />
forefront of our Government's concerns. We recognise<br />
that distance in this vast country can create problems<br />
for country people and as we implement our policies<br />
during our second term in the fields of health,<br />
education, transport and communications, the special<br />
needs of country people will have a high priority."<br />
These priorities have become enshrined in the platform and<br />
principles of the Australian Labor Party. They are<br />
reflected in the ALP Platform of 1986 which, among other<br />
things, calls for a national recognition of employment and<br />
unemploymnent imbalances. Here in Dubbo, for instance, the<br />
unemploycnent rate ( 12 per cent) is higher than the rural<br />
average (, 10.3 per cent). And the proportion of Aboriginal<br />
people in the ranks of the unemployed ( 12 per cent) is<br />
double their share of the population ( 6 per cent).<br />
The 1986 ALP platform acknowledges three inter-dependent<br />
aims that are central to the principles of efficiency and<br />
equity, namely:<br />
facilitating economic growth in areas possessing natural<br />
development potential and comparative advantage,<br />
assisting the adjustment of urban and regional<br />
commiunities to the stresses and opportunities associated<br />
with change, and<br />
promoting equity and access in the regional provision of<br />
social facilities and services.<br />
As a party and as a Government we appreciate that in order<br />
to give effect to these aims we need to fashion policies<br />
that: are tailored to the specific circumstances of regions,<br />
involve local communities in their design and<br />
implementation, are adaptive to change, and<br />
are consistent with agreements between the Government,<br />
trade unions and the private sector on strategies for<br />
development. </p>
<p>When I articulated the priorities of the second Hawke Labor<br />
Government, X. said that we would aspire to, and be judged<br />
by, our commitment to a more equitable society.<br />
more precisely, we recognise the restricted access of many<br />
country people to a range of community facilities and<br />
services. we had in mind such areas as education, training,<br />
retraining, transport, health, housing, children's services,<br />
communications, and the delivery of benefits and welfare<br />
services. in the area of-telecommunications, to take a topical<br />
example, the Government's policy of uniform charges for<br />
similar services a policy of far-reaching social and<br />
economic benefit to the less densely populated areas of the<br />
country is made possible through a system of cross<br />
subsidies. Some half a billion dollars a year in such<br />
subsidies is directed towards Telecom's 1.5 million rural<br />
consumers. In the Labor Party Platform we undertake to give attention<br />
to the speci: f" ic characteristics of rural and isolated areas,<br />
to seek to overcome disadvantages in access to community<br />
services, and to develop specialist institutions and<br />
programs where required.<br />
These are grand aspirations, fine words, but they are not<br />
hollow phrases. To translate them into reality requir the<br />
practice as i-iell as the spirit of co-operative endeavour.<br />
As I said in the John Curtin Memorial Lecture, exactly three<br />
years ago th: s week, with the election of Labor Governments<br />
throughout Australia, " it should now be possible to devise a<br />
pattern of relationships, in a spirit of co-operation and<br />
consultation, which is most attuned to the circumstances of<br />
our time a set of relationships which more effectively<br />
matches the capacities and responsibilities of the<br />
respective levels of Governments ( including local<br />
Government) than we have ever known in Australia."<br />
You might rightly ask, how has this commitment been<br />
translated into tangible expression for the one-in-three<br />
Australians who live in non-metropolitan Australia.<br />
I am pleased, in fact proud, to say that the runs are on the<br />
board. Financial assistance 1to local Government was increased by<br />
more than 50 per cent during the first three years of Labor<br />
Government. This reflects a recognition of local Government<br />
as an important provider of services.<br />
The 1986-87 Budget saw the allocation of $ 586 million in<br />
Commonwealth general purpose funding to local Government<br />
authorities throughout Australia. </p>
<p>7' This was the first allocation under the new Local Government<br />
( Financial Assistance) Act.<br />
Under these arrangements the level of funding in real terms<br />
is guaranteed fo ' r the next 2 years, combined with greater<br />
emphasis or. assistance to disadvantaged councils a further<br />
tangible expression of equity in practice, of restraint with<br />
equity. These untied grants represent only part ( slightly more than<br />
half) of Commonwealth assistance to local Government<br />
authoritleG. They do not include earmarked grants for<br />
Communityr Employment Projects, for roadworks, for country<br />
town water supplies, and so forth.<br />
Nor do theyj reflect the heightened recognition of local<br />
Government in the counsels of our federal system, such as<br />
the prio: ity accorded local government in the economic and<br />
tax summits and in the Economic Planning Advisory Council.<br />
To some extent, however, it is misleading to treat regional<br />
Australia as a coherent unit, universally different from<br />
metropolitan Australia. Ballarat is as different from<br />
Bundaberg as is Perth from Sydney.<br />
This diversity is as much a strength as it is a challenge,<br />
helping us to survive and benefit from the swings and<br />
distortions in the product markets that influence the<br />
national well-being.<br />
Regional economies need to establish a wider range of<br />
activitiac in order to insulate themselves from fluctuations<br />
in certain markets. This is already happening in many of<br />
our regional centres.<br />
using the natural advantages of cheaper land, large open<br />
spaces, a relatively stable labour supply, a less stressful<br />
lifestyle, often first class education, welfare and cultural<br />
facilities and unique local resources, regional centres have<br />
obvious advantages in attracting specific industries away<br />
from metropolitan areas.<br />
Tourism is one area in which many regional centres have<br />
undertaken substantial development. Stimulated by the<br />
depreciation of the Australian dollar, tourism has continued<br />
to grow at more than 10 per cent p. a. since 1984 when the<br />
number of tourists visiting Australia, and the number of<br />
Australians choosing to holiday at home, first exceeded one<br />
million. This trend is accelerating.<br />
When I visited Cairns recently it was very apparent that<br />
tourism development was providing the city with an economic<br />
alternative in the difficult times being experienced by the<br />
local sugar industry. </p>
<p>Here, too, in Dubbo and the central west generally there is<br />
evidence of the community diversifying its economic base.<br />
In place of an almost total dependence on agriculture, we<br />
now see light manufacturing industry and a growing tourism<br />
industry, inicluding such outstanding attractions as the<br />
Western Plains Zoo.<br />
In order to promote the development of robust, diversified<br />
regional economies the Commonwealth and the States are<br />
collaborating on the Country Centres Project, a pilot scheme<br />
operating in eleven country areas. Working in conjunction<br />
with the local community and private sector interests, its<br />
purpose is to develop local self-help strategies based on<br />
realistic economic and community development opportunities.<br />
Such initiatives have assumed increased importance and<br />
urgency as the historical rural base of many provincial<br />
cities has been eroded. I hardly need remind you that world<br />
prices for most of Australia's major agricultural and<br />
mineral products have plummeted to despairingly low levels.<br />
In the case ol' agricultural commodities a large part of the<br />
reason is to be found in the excess production artificially<br />
stimulated by the subsidising practices of Euirope and the<br />
United States.<br />
The price-de-rcssing effects of these absurd policies has<br />
contributed to a 20 per cent decline in the export income of<br />
our farming conmunity. In my visits to towns like<br />
Canowindra, ' Ao , ee and Cowra, I have witnessed the human<br />
dimension of this Crisis.<br />
Because agriculture constitutes 40 per cent of Australia's<br />
total exporto, however, the consequences are felt not just<br />
in rural Austz-alia, but in the metropolitan areas as well,<br />
These reduced returns are slicing $ 6000 million off our<br />
national incoms. The nation has had to tighten its belt as<br />
a result.<br />
we have responded to the changed international environment<br />
with a number of strategies. We have attacked the most<br />
important caluse of the problem the agricultural<br />
subsidising practices of Europe and the US not only<br />
through bilate -al representations, but also through the<br />
multilateral system, the General Agreement on Tariffs and<br />
Trade ( the GATT).<br />
The minister for Trade, John Dawkins, recently organised the<br />
fair trader alliance, a group of 14 like-minded, efficient<br />
agricultural producing countries that had suffered from the<br />
policies of the major trading nations. </p>
<p>7<br />
Less than a fortnight ago, at the historic GATT ministerial<br />
meeting held to launch a new round of multilateral trade<br />
negotiations, Australia and the new alliance enjoyed an<br />
astonishing victory we overcame formidable EEC resistance<br />
in having the problems of agricultural trade and subsidies<br />
effectively included in the negotiating agenda for the new<br />
round.<br />
This is the first time that the GATT has addressed itself to<br />
agriculture. The recent sale of heavily subsidised wheat by the EEC to<br />
the Soviet Union underlines the importance of getting<br />
meaningful multilateral trade negotiations underway as soon<br />
as possible, now that the new round has been launched.-<br />
Although fundamental and absolutely necessary, this<br />
multilateral strategy is a long-term one. Therefore it is<br />
being supported by a range of domestic initiatives aimed at<br />
providing imnmediate assistance to the rural sector.<br />
If we cannot increase world prices in the short term, we<br />
certainly can reduce costs through productivity and<br />
efficiency gains in our rural industries. Recent decisions<br />
concerning the diesel fuel rebate for primary producers,<br />
fertiliser rubsidies, and bounty instead of tariff<br />
assistance : or farm machinery, have all reduced the cost of<br />
farm inputs.<br />
In the case of the hard-pressed Queensland sugar industry we<br />
have sought to raise productivity by encouraging the removal<br />
of various restrictive regulations imposed under State<br />
legislation. This could reduce industry costs by some $ 130<br />
million. on the broader rural front, in the face of declining world<br />
prices, we have sought to increase Australia's m~ arket share.<br />
This year has seen several new initiatives, including the<br />
start of a four year program of marketing innovations for<br />
the meat industry; a $ 10 million market promotion program<br />
for the horticultural industry; and $ 25 million over<br />
years to develop innovative marketing methods for<br />
agriculture generally.<br />
our efforts have not been confined to the farm sector. The<br />
minerals industry is an important part of provincial<br />
Australia, It also supplies 40 per cent of our export<br />
income. it too is suffering the price-depressing effect of<br />
oversupply and new technologies.<br />
The Governiment for its part has sought to ease the<br />
regulatory burden on mineral exports. By easing controls on<br />
the export of coal. and crude oil, alumina and bauxite, we<br />
have increased the capacity of mineral exporters to respond<br />
flexibly in what has become an intensely competitive<br />
international ma rket. </p>
<p>All these rural initiatives would be of only limited<br />
benefit, however, if they were not complemented by a sound<br />
general economic strategy that is, a coherent set of<br />
economic policies directed towards addressing Australia's<br />
externally induced economic difficulties. Such a strategy<br />
is firmly in place.'<br />
As a result of the very difficult decisions of the last<br />
Budget, the Government has been able to reduce substantially<br />
its borrowing requirement in the coming year. This will<br />
feed through ultimately to lower interest rates and easier<br />
finance in the private sector.<br />
On the wages front we have signalled the fundamental<br />
importance of further restraint. We will do whatever is<br />
necessary in order to maintain Australia's newfound<br />
competitiveness and to control inflation.<br />
Both the Budget and wages policy will contribute to the<br />
easing of the burden currently borne by regional Australia.<br />
I was heartened, Mr Chairman, to read the editorial in your<br />
own paper, the Bundaberg News-M4ail, following the Budget.<br />
As you said,<br />
" The federal Government has lived up to its promise and<br />
given Australia the tough. Budget it feels will lead us<br />
out of tho economic quagmire it looks good and<br />
hopefully will work towards bolstering the economy."<br />
Mr Chairman, regional dailies like the Bundaberg News-Mail<br />
play an important role in the economic life of provincial<br />
communities. They assist in the promotion and success of business in the<br />
local area, often providing local business with information<br />
that is more focused and relevant to regional needs. News<br />
of local stock markets or the results of agricultural<br />
research relevant to the area are often most effectively<br />
conveyed through regional media.<br />
When I say media, however, I also encompass regional<br />
television ( as wiell as radio, of course). As a Government<br />
we are committed to offering a better level of services to<br />
regional areas, a level of service comparable to that<br />
enjoyed in the cities.<br />
Already through the ALISSAT satellite, some remote areas are<br />
receiving ABC television for the first time. A more<br />
far-reaching expression of that principle will be the<br />
equalisation of commercial television services. This<br />
involves the most significant change to the production and<br />
distribution of television in this country in the 30 year<br />
history of the industry. </p>
<p>Before the end of this decade even by 1988 in many cases<br />
most country television viewers will have access to second<br />
and third commercial channels.<br />
our decision on equalisation favours fair competition<br />
between stations, and thus a better deal for consumers.<br />
I know it has been said that equalisation will lead to a<br />
loss of local programming and identity, with the spectre of<br />
regional trtations becoming mere slaves to the networks.<br />
We do not ihare that view.<br />
There are two guarantees. First, there are the regulatory<br />
provisions of the Australian Broadcasting Tribunal<br />
concerning local content.<br />
The second and, in my view, greater guarantee is the<br />
established and legitimate demand for local news and<br />
programming. Those stations that express and identify with<br />
the interests of the local community will. be better able to<br />
resist their new competitors and hold their viewers.<br />
Indeed, what we could see is an even stronger local flavour<br />
in regional television. Some stations may gain more than<br />
others, but people living in non-metropolitan Australia will<br />
benefit nost of all.<br />
After all, somewhat similar circumstances have not deprived<br />
regional radio or newspapers of their local identity.<br />
Indeed, as each of you would well know, it is the<br />
cultivation and expression of a regional perspective that<br />
underpinn your viability and popularity. Without such a<br />
strong scnse of local identity you would not be here tonight<br />
celebrating the 50th anniversary of your Association.<br />
once again, I thank you for the opportunity to be here<br />
tonight, to enjoy this occasion with you, and to share a few<br />
thoughts with you.<br />
our country faces difficult economic circumstances imposed<br />
on us from, outside. The Government is very conscious of the<br />
fact that nowhere is this more clearly felt than in regional<br />
Australia. I can assure you, however, that we are on the right track in<br />
solving the underlying problems.<br />
But sound policies alone are not enough. The period ahead<br />
requires an active spirit of co-operation and restraint by<br />
all parties. It is not a time for confrontation or<br />
divisiveness. </p>
<p>I believe that, by helping bridge the gap between<br />
metropolitan and provincial Australia, the regional press<br />
can contribute much to fashioning that necessary mood of<br />
shared endeavour and a determination to succeed.<br />
I congratulate the Regional Dailies Association on the<br />
achievement of your 50th anniversary and wish you well for<br />
the future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
