<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8333</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech at &#039;Grains 2000&#039; Conference, Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/09/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008333.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>10 September 1991</p>
<p>Mr Chairman, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>The year 2000 is just a handful of harvests away. But before then, long before then, we must have achieved fair access to world markets, free of the wastefulness of the and American subsidy systems.</p>
<p>A system which perpetuates this colossal waste of resources, which penalises the most efficient farmers in the world Australian farmers cannot, must not and will not be allowed to stand indefinitely. </p>
<p>That is why I welcome the opportunity to open this<br />Conference which is important to the future of your industry - and this country.</p>
<p>While the grains industry is experiencing very diff~ icult<br />trading conditions at present, our focus must continue to be<br />fixed firmly on the future of the industry. What ktind of<br />industry do we want in the year 2000.</p>
<p>Farmers have always had to live with changing conditionsever<br />since grain was first domesticated just 4000 years<br />ago. We should never forget that it was this great<br />scientific and social breakthrough the evolution of grass<br />into grain that marked the beginning of civilization as we<br />know it.</p>
<p>The discovery of farming meant our ancestors had to stop<br />being hunter-gatherers and settle down in one spot to plant,<br />to grow and to harvest. They had to work out a way to trade.<br />to communicate, to record and tally their crops, to innovate<br />and invent new techniques and implements.</p>
<p>Farmers have acquired something of a conservative<br />reputation. In many case~ s that is a justified reputation<br />especially in Europe but I think if you look fairly at<br />the record you will see that on the basis of new techniques<br />and technology, the application of the latest scientific<br />knowledge, farmers have been at the forefront of change.</p>
<p>Nowhere is this more true than in Australia, and nowhere in<br />Australia is it more true than here in Canberra.</p>
<p>William Farrer pioneered scientific wheat breeding on his<br />property Lambrigg here in the ACT for 20 years until his<br />death in 1906 without, it must be said, a great deal of<br />recognition at the time. But we know now that without<br />Farrer's work the wheat industry would not have successfully<br />adapted to Australian conditions.</p>
<p>There have been other pioneers of course, in other paddocks - but the point is that Australian innovation and Australian<br />perseverance and Australian capacity to change has got us to<br />where we are today.</p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>Australia has the world's most efficient, least protected<br />and most outward looking farmers.</p>
<p>Australia is the ninth largest producer and fourth largest<br />wheat exporting nation in the world.</p>
<p>In 1991-92 ABARE forecasts agricultural commodity exports of<br />S12.9 billion, little above 1990-91, but around 10t down on<br />the years immediately prior to that.</p>
<p>The Australian grains industry is crucial to this<br />performance</p>
<p>In 1991-92, it is estimated that grains and oilseeds will<br />contribute 18% of the value of total farm production and<br />of the value of total farm exports, which is 6.5% of the<br />total value of all ccmmodity exports.</p>
<p>In forecasts to be released today, ABARE estimates that<br />production of wheat will decline by 26% in 1991/ 92 to around<br />11.3 million tonnes. The 1991-92 crop is estimated to be<br />24% lower than the 103-season average of 14.9 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Wheat prices have been dropping in real terms since 1988-89.<br />and last year. prices received by wheat farmers dropped by<br />around 33% on the previous year alone. As a consequence,<br />the average area sown in 1991-92 is forecast to be only 8<br />million hectares a far cry from the boom year in 1983-84<br />when 12.9 million hectares were sown. While wheat prospects<br />are projected to pick up from last year's slump in line with<br />moderate price rises, real prices are nevertheless projected<br />to remain low by historical standards for some time. </p>
<p>Looking at the bottom line. the farm cash operating aurplus<br />for wheat and other crop farms, whilst still remaining much<br />higher than the average broadacre farm, is nevertheless<br />expected to decline by 27% in 1991-92 to S38,800. We know<br />that this is biting deep in many rural communities.</p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>It is against that background, that I would like to address<br />the long term future of the industry. Because despite the<br />present short term difficulties, I believe there are many<br />reasons to be optimistic about the outlook f or the industry.</p>
<p>There are five key principles which will underpin the long<br />term success of our agricultural industries trade,<br />efficiency, competitiveness, equity and environment.</p>
<p>Strategies in these areas cover the rural sector f rom the<br />farm environment, through the farm gate to the contiumer<br />from the soil to the supermarket shelf. Let me address each<br />in turn.</p>
<p>TRADE</p>
<p>Mr Chairman</p>
<p>There is no doubt that a successful conclusion of the Uruguay Round is the most important single factor for the future of the grains industry.</p>
<p>Indeed, no international economic issue is more pressing<br />than the future of the Uruguay Round. However, time is<br />running out. Nine months have passed since the failure of<br />the Ministerial meeting in Brussels last December.</p>
<p>We remain resolutely comitted to the need for a balanced<br />outcome in the Uruguay Round. No one can afford an<br />arrangement that perpetuates the present gross waste of the<br />world's scarce resources. The Common Agricultural Policy<br />( CAP) of the EC, the American Export Enhancement Program<br />( EEP), and, on a lesser scale, the import restrictions in<br />Japan, Korea and other countries, all add up to ain<br />intolerable situation for Australian primary producers.</p>
<p>As measured by the OECD, total trade distorting subsidies and transfers rose to $ A385 billion in 1990.</p>
<p>This represents almost thirty times Australia's forecast agricultural exports for 1991-92.</p>
<p>The EC is the main culprit with payments worth about SA171 billion; in the US such payments total SA95 billion; and in Japan SA76 billion, mainly to its rice industry.</p>
<p>In the late 1970s, the EC was a major importer of grains. Now it is one of the world's largest exporters, with ashare of the international wheat market.<br /> </p>
<p>ABARE has estimated that the cost to our farmers as a result<br />of the price depressing effect of the EEP was between $ 125<br />million and S175 million in 1990-91.</p>
<p>At the same time, however, ABARE estimates that the coat to<br />our wheat and grains producers as a result of the EC's level<br />of grain industry protection was S695 million in 1990-91, of<br />which S430 million was in wheat.</p>
<p>So it is the EC with whom we have most at issue. It is the<br />Common Agricultural Policy which has turned a major grain<br />importer into a major distorter of the grain market.</p>
<p>The CAP's impact is less exposed to the public view, but the<br />cost to Australia is more than four times greater than the<br />EEP.</p>
<p>And it will receive the exposure it deserves when Dr Blewett<br />leads a bipartisan mission to Brussels in early October.<br />Mr Chairman.</p>
<p>Last March. Dr Blewett led a bipartisan delegation to<br />Washington. This visit and the subsequent officials level<br />consultations represented a constructive though modest start<br />to a complex consultative process, to minimise the impact<br />the EEP has on Australia.</p>
<p>The results have not been as precise or as positive as you.<br />or 1, would like. But they represent an opportunity which<br />we cannot ignore and which we will not ignore.</p>
<p>Mr Chairman.</p>
<p>Australia, as chairman of the Cairns Group, will continue to<br />push in the negotiations for agreement on a comprehensive<br />agricultural reform package. it must include substantial<br />reductions in agricultural support including domestic<br />support, border protection and export subsidies and<br />provide enhanced rules and disciplines to bring agriculture<br />fully into the GATT system.</p>
<p>The overwhelming responsibility for a successful conclusion<br />to the Uruguay Round rests: with the Europeans.</p>
<p>As I wrote to the leaders of the G7 Summit before the London<br />Summit in July, the key to the future of world trade is<br />GATT; the key to GATT is the Uruguay Round; the key to the<br />Uruguay Round is agriculture; and the key to agriculture is<br />reform of the European Community's agricultural protection<br />policies.</p>
<p>A successful Uruguay Round will not see the end overnight<br />of agricultural support, or export subsidies, but it will be<br />the start of an historic aind sustained process of<br />liberalisation. </p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>I am aware that there have been some calls from within the grains industry for Australia to join the subsidy war.</p>
<p>The argument essentially goes that if you can't beat themn.<br />Joinl them. It is a seductive argument, particularly when<br />times are tough. But It is one which we must emphatically<br />reject. A subsidy war is a war we cannot win. And by joining it we<br />would lose the last chance of stopping the subsidy madness<br />once and for all.</p>
<p>Our subsidies would no doubt be met by retaliatory action.<br />We are a small trading nation and we export over 701 of our<br />agricultural product. Retaliatory action would devastate<br />our farm sector.</p>
<p>Furthermore, a subsidy program would undermine the<br />credibility of the Cairns Group and thereby significantly<br />lesson the chances of a successful conclusion to the Uruguay<br />Round. The key to our prominent role in the Uruguay Round<br />is that we are a fair trader. That fact has given us<br />immense credibility credibility that we must cherish.</p>
<p>As a small trading nation, our prospects are inextricably<br />linked with the world economy and growth in world trade. We<br />must continue to play a leading role in promoting a fairer<br />trading system.</p>
<p>That is why we did not introduce a guaranteed minimum price<br />for wheat. That is why we will not be joining the subsidy<br />war. That is why we have instead targetted assistance to<br />those farmers in need during the current rural downturn.</p>
<p>Ladies and Gentlemen,</p>
<p>We cannot, and do not, rely solely on the Uruguay Round.<br />In 1989 1 initiated discussions with our regional neighbours<br />that gave rise to the Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation<br />( APEC) process.</p>
<p>An important pert of the work being undertaken is regional<br />trade liberalisation.</p>
<p>At the next ministerial meeting in Seoul in November, the<br />three Chinas Hong Kong, Chinese Taipei and The Peoples'<br />Republic of China will be formally joining the APEC<br />process. I n 1990, existing APEC participants and the three Chinese<br />economies accounted for almost $ 900 million worth, or 40 per<br />cent of our wheat exports, and $ 240 million worth, or 54 per<br />cent, of our barley exports.</p>
<p>The work to liberalise trado barriers beyond GATT, to<br />develop trade under APEC is; going to be long term but we<br />must pursue them now to ensure that the benefits to us in<br />the future are not lost today.</p>
<p>in addition, we can and wil. l be able to use the standing<br />Australia has with some of the key players in the Uruguay<br />Round to influence its outco~ me and to consider where the<br />future may take bodies such as APEC.</p>
<p>President Bush will be visiting Australia in December at a<br />time of momentous change in international relations. The<br />focus of this visit will be much wider than agricultural<br />issues. Nevertheless, the President will, I know, want to<br />learn more about issues of interest to the Australian<br />agricultural community. I hope that we can constructively<br />give him that opportunity.</p>
<p>The Uruguay Round will, hopefully, be reaching a high-point<br />of activity and, if it is not, we will be able to put our<br />ideas for breaking the impasse direct to a leader who will<br />have great influence in fav. our of reform.</p>
<p>EFFICIENCY</p>
<p>Mr Chairman</p>
<p>Underlying the principle of efficiency is the recognition of<br />the complete interdependence of the whole economy, and the<br />interdependence of the world trading system.</p>
<p>In order to remain internationally competitive we must have<br />the right macro-economic fundamentals in place, and we must<br />continue vigorously to pursue micro-economic reform.</p>
<p>The March Industry Statement accelerated the process of<br />unprecedented tariff reforms, and introduced structural<br />reforms designed to improve the efficiency of primary<br />industries in the context of a more general package to speed<br />our industrial reconstruction. We also advanced taxation<br />reform, notably the simplification of depreciation<br />provisions; and the widening of sales tax exemptions all<br />of which will benefit farmers.</p>
<p>The commitments undertaken through the Special Premiers'<br />Conference process are also fundamental to micro-economic<br />reform.</p>
<p>The July Special Premiers' Conference agreed to establish<br />the National Pail Corporaition, the National Road Transport<br />Commission, the Electricity Grid Management Council, and to<br />business deregulation which will sweep away the stupidity of<br />having six sets of regulations around our nation. These are<br />all major reforms fundameantal to building a competitive<br />Australia. </p>
<p>The -Government recognises that land transport costs form a<br />significant part of the costs of producing and marketing<br />grains.</p>
<p>The Government agrees with the industry Commission's draft<br />recommendation that State Governments eliminate, without<br />delay, restrictions of bulk commodities to particular modes<br />of transport. The Commonwealth considers that the<br />reservation of particular commodities to rail to be<br />undesirable, and has deregulated the transport of grains<br />purchased by the Australian Wheat Board in South Australia.</p>
<p>I know that some in rural and remote communities fear that<br />the road transport reforms agreed to at the July Special<br />Premiersl Conference will be to their detriment.</p>
<p>Research is being undertaken by the Bureau of Transport an4<br />Communications Economics and by ABARE and preliminary<br />indications are that Primary industry will not be unduly<br />disadvantaged by the new charges which constitute a very<br />small proportion of the total costs of operating a vehicle.<br />For example, the Bureau has found that for Darwin consumers<br />a typical example of a community dependent on road<br />transport the cost of the reforms would be less than<br />cents a week, at worst. The nonsense that has been put<br />forward in this area about damage to rural communities is<br />now exposed for what it is. Yes, we will recover costs from<br />road users, so we can provide better roads. No, consumers<br />will not suffer.</p>
<p>The grain industry was the first to benefit from the<br />Government's waterfront reform program. Manning reductions<br />of between 50 and 80% are leading to considerable<br />productivity gains and ongoing cost savings calculated by<br />the Wheat Board as annual savings for the industry of at<br />least $ 10 million for wheat and other bulk grain industries.</p>
<p>COMPETITIVENESS</p>
<p>Mr Chairman</p>
<p>One of the fundamental building blocks to building a<br />competitive Australia are the microeconomic reforms I have<br />just mentioned. But being competitive means more than that.<br />It also means being flexible and sensitive to the changing<br />nature of dynamic markets. we must develop and produce<br />products that are wanted. we can't assume that traditional<br />markets will stay the same forever, or that new markets<br />necessarily will want the same basic products we have always<br />provided.</p>
<p>A simple example of this are the changes occurring in demand<br />for hard wheat and high quality, higher protein wheat, as<br />well as alternative grains.</p>
<p>If Australia is to reach its true potential in the next<br />century it will have to be at the forefront of research,<br />development, and application of new technologies. So too<br />will we need to become more export oriented in value added<br />downstream processing. Food processing is Australia's<br />largest manufacturing activity, accounting for around 20% of<br />total manufacturing sales.</p>
<p>At present, however, the export market is seen primarily as<br />a convenient means of disposing of surplus product. Each<br />year, tens of billions of dollars in value is added overseas<br />to Australian food commodity exports.</p>
<p>We have a market of some 2 billion people on our Asia-<br />Pacific doorstep, but far too little has been made of our<br />natural advantage of strong public research infrastructure;<br />access to high quality, unpolluted, competitively priced raw<br />materials; and a skilled and highly-educated workforce.</p>
<p>EOUITY</p>
<p>Mr Chairman</p>
<p>For rural Australia, social justice means effective support<br />of farmers and their families in times of crisis, improving<br />the access and relevance of education and training programs,<br />enhancing business skills and opportunities, and building<br />strong and diverse regional economies able to withstand the<br />ups and downs of the commodity cycle.</p>
<p>What equity does not mean is the adoption of untargetted<br />assistance measures which will distort markets by offering<br />industry-wide subsidies, or which subsidise farmers who do<br />not need assistance.</p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>I am very conscious of the difficulties being faced by Rural<br />Australia and that in 1990-91, about half of farm families<br />had taxable income of less than S10,000.</p>
<p>The Rural Adjustmnt Scheme, the Countrylink program, the<br />Income Equalisation Scheme, and our package of rural<br />education access programs are some of the services this<br />Government is providing to rural Australians.</p>
<p>In April we announced a major rural assistance package. The<br />most important measure in that package was the increase in<br />funding for the Rural Adju. ntment Scheme by almost S100<br />million to S160 million in 1991/ 92 an increase of over<br />150%. An ex gratia payment of up to $ 35.1 million has been<br />allocated for the grains industry to cover losses incurred<br />as a result of the United N4ations sanctions against Iraq. </p>
<p>Ini addition to that allocation. more than S280 million has<br />been paid by taxpayers under EFIC National Insurance Cover<br />in relation to Iraqi debt to the wheat board. Payments by<br />the end of 1992 wnder this insurance cover may reach S500<br />million. I said at the time that the burden of sanctions in<br />this area would be shared. It has been.</p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>The Budget announced changes to the eligibility rules for<br />family payments to rural Australians.</p>
<p>The new rules involve changes to the assets testing<br />requirements for the Family Allowance and Family Allowance<br />Supplement components of the new Family Payment. The rules<br />recognise the particular circumstances of farm families who<br />are, as we say, asset rich but cash poor.</p>
<p>Despite the introduction of an assets test on the family<br />allowance at $ 600,000, for two years from 1 January 1992.<br />families will continue to receive the Family Allowance<br />component of the Family Payment regardless of the value of<br />their assets if current income is less than the basic rate<br />of Social Security benefit S13,078 plus $ 624 per child<br />and liquid personal assets are less than $ 10,000 in the case<br />of a couple.</p>
<p>From the same date, families meeting the above tests and<br />with net business assets up to the value of S600,000 will<br />became eligible to receive the equivalent of the pre!; ent<br />Family Allowance Supplement.</p>
<p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
<p>Mr Chairman,</p>
<p>A fundamental goal of the Government is to ensure that our<br />primary production is ecologically sound and environmentally<br />sustainable for the long term. The health of the economy<br />depends on the vitality of the land itself. Land<br />degradation costs our economy an estimated S600 million a<br />year in lost agricultural production alone. This is roughly<br />equivalent to 20 per cent of the value of our grain exports<br />last year. Individual producers and the nation, cannot<br />afford to sustain these losses.</p>
<p>The Government has made an unprecedented commitment to<br />overcoming this country's land degradation problems. It Is<br />our responsibility to farm in an environmentally sustainable<br />manner to safeguard our prosperity for future generations.</p>
<p>This is the Decade of Landcore, and we are providing $ 320<br />million for land care and related tree planting and remnant<br />vegetation preservation programs. At the same time, we have<br />changed tax deductability rules to encourage primary<br />producers to spend more on correcting environmental<br />problems. The cooperation between the National Farmers'<br />Federation and the Australian Conservation Foundation on the<br />development of policies to Vrevent land degradation has been<br />particularly important in the battle against one of our<br />major environmental and economic problems.</p>
<p>CONCLUSION</p>
<p>Mr Chairman, the grains industry has a proud past which has made it one of Australia's mrost Important and innovative exporters; it faces a turbulent present over which neither you nor the Government has 811 the control we would like.<br />But once we have accomplished this round of reforms. the grain industry has a future more secure than any in the past or than you presently experience.</p>
<p>I say that with confidence tLecause at the end of the day the world's most efficient and most innovative farmers will harvest their reward. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
