<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1780</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: EXPORT INCENTIVES - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN. GORTON.</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001780_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: ixOL B, P. M. No. 21/ 16<br />
EXPORT INCENTIVES<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Gorton, today outlined a<br />
number of changes which the Government has decided to make in<br />
the two export incentive schemes which have been in operation<br />
since 1961. " In the light vf the facts beñ forc it", said the<br />
Prime Minister, " the Government is convinced that as a result<br />
of the proposed changes these schemes will offer better and<br />
more effective incentives to encourage the continued growth<br />
of Australian exports".<br />
" During the review of the schemes undertaken by the<br />
Government we received many suggestions fr'om Ind~ ividual<br />
e" lxIpn otrhteisrs reagnad rde xIp owrto uoldr gpaanyi sasptieocnisa" l, trMi7b uteo r to thceo nwtiohruke do. f'<br />
the Export Development Council and the Australian Manufacturers'<br />
Export Council, both of whom had made detailed submissions<br />
which had been of great assistance to the Government".<br />
The Prime Minister pointed out that, under the<br />
proposed arrangements, rebates of payroll tax would continue<br />
to be allowed in respect of increases in export sales and<br />
income tax concessions would be available for eligible<br />
expenditure incurred in promoting exports. However,<br />
significant changes were proposed for both schemes.<br />
Payroll Tax Rebates Scheme<br />
So far as the Payroll Tax Rebate Scheme was concerned<br />
the major change proposed was the introduction of a new and<br />
simplified formula relating rebate entitlements only to increases<br />
in export sales. The new formula will provide that the<br />
entitlement to a rebate of payroll tax would amount to 10.5%<br />
of the increase in exports. The increase in exports will be<br />
calculated by deducting from the current year's exports the<br />
average annual exports in a base period. The percentage factor<br />
of 10.5% used in the formula will be reviewed from time to time.<br />
The present base period will be replaced by a three<br />
year period which moves forward each year but remains five years<br />
behind the year of export. For example, in 1968/ 69, the first<br />
year of operation of the new scheme, the base period will be<br />
the three years 1960/ 51 to 1962/ 63. In the next year, 1969/ 70<br />
the base period will be the three years 1961/ 62 to 1963/ 64.<br />
Special provision will be made for phasing in new exporters.<br />
Mi. r. Gorton explained that this five year " lag" to<br />
the base period was designed to reduce the impact of switching<br />
from the previous fixed base of 1958/ 59, 1959/ 60. He said that<br />
under the proposed scheme most exporters would have a greater<br />
incentive to increase their exports than under the former<br />
scheme. 12 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The Prime Minister added that a criticism levelled<br />
at the present scheme was that many exporters achieved export<br />
results which would entitle them-to greater benefits if the<br />
rebate were not limited to the amount of the payroll tax that<br />
they paid in that year. The new scheme would include a new<br />
provision which will allow exporters to carry forward for up<br />
to three years some of their " excess". In addition it was<br />
proposed to continue the export certificate systemn under<br />
modified conditions which should make the system more attractive<br />
to both exporters and their suppliers of components or materials.<br />
The scope of the scheme would be extended by the<br />
inclusion in the definition of export sales of certain items<br />
not included under the existing scheme.<br />
Special arrangements would also be made to assist<br />
exporters whose rebate entitlements were found to be materially<br />
affected by the devaluation of foreigyn currencies lat6 last<br />
year. The scheme would be directed to encouraging the<br />
export of manufactures and primary products, where the need<br />
for incentives is greatest. Exports of petroleum, petroleum<br />
products, minerals, mineral concentrates and alumina will not<br />
participate in the new payroll tax scheme.<br />
Market Development Allowance<br />
The main change to the Export Market Development<br />
Allowance will be the allowance of a rebate of income tax of<br />
42.5 cents in the in respect of eligible promotional expendituire<br />
instead of an additional deduction from income. In the case of<br />
a public company for example, the effective rate of benefit<br />
would be increased from an equivalent of an income tax rebate<br />
of about 37.5 cents in the S under the old scheme to a rebate<br />
of 42.5 cents under the new scheme. The scope of the schemea<br />
would also be extended to cover several classes of expenditure<br />
not at present eli~ gible.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Acting Minister for<br />
Trade and Industry, Mr. Anthony, would be issuing a mocrsL<br />
detailed statement of the proposed changes in the two ince3ntives.<br />
He emphasised, however, that a comprehensive explanation of<br />
the two incentives could not be made until the Treasurer,<br />
Mr. McMahon, introduced the legislation into Parliament.<br />
He concluded by saying that both schemes would come<br />
into effect from 1st July, 1968, and would continue to operate<br />
for a period of 5 years from that date. The current incentives<br />
expire on 30th June, 1968.<br />
CANBERRA 14th February, 1968. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
