<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7090</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER EMF SYMPOSIM DAVOS- 29 JANUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007090.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
g3FM4 2 02: 25 5. ISPTM RICOHAX 2 Z4595 P. 2<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY.*<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
EAF SYMPOSIUM<br />
DAVOS 29 JANUARY 1987<br />
FOR SOME YEARS NOW YOU HAVE BEEN KIND ENOUGj TO INVITE ME TO<br />
JOIN" YOU HERE IN DAVOS-IT WOULD 9E EASY T( SAY THAT ITHAS<br />
NOT BEEN PHYSICALLY POSSIBLE TO ACCEPT YOUR INVITATION<br />
BEFORE THIS BUT IT WOULD BE UNTRUEWHILE<br />
THE TYRANNY OF DISTANCE HAS FOR US IN AUSTRALIA BEEN<br />
DIMINISHED BY THE MARVELS OF MODERN TRANSPORT, ONE. DOES'NOT<br />
LIGHTLY CROSS THE WORLD MERELY FOR THE PROSPECT OF CONGENIAL<br />
COMPANY OR SALUBRIOUS SURROUNDINGS AFTER ALL WE ARE NOT IN<br />
OUR COUNTRY ENTIRELY WITHOUT THESE ATTRACTIONS* PARTICULARLY<br />
AT THIS TIME OF THE YEAR.<br />
BUT TWO RELATED CONSIDERATIONS LED ME TO AGREE, WITH<br />
PLEASUREa TO OPEN THIS 1987 SYMPoSIUM.<br />
FIRST, THE STATURE OF DAVOS HAS BEEN GROWING. THIS REFLECTS<br />
THE GREAT CREDIT YOU DESERVE FOR YEAR AFTER YEAR ASSEMBLING<br />
IN THIS FRANK AND INFORMAL ATMOSPHERE SEVERAL HUNDRED OF THE<br />
WORLD S LEADERS IN FINANCE, TRADE, INVESTMENT AND<br />
GOVERNMENT-PUT IN THE SIMPLEST OF LANGUAGE, THIS IS BEING<br />
INCREASINGLY RECOGNISED AS A BODY OF CONSIDERABLE CLOUTSECOND,<br />
THERE IS A RISING SENSE OF FRUSTRATION FELT BY THE<br />
PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA AND MANY OTHER NATIONS ABOUT WHAT CAN,<br />
WITHOUT EXAGGERATION, BE DESCRIBED AS THE DISINTEORATION OF<br />
THE GLOBAL ECONOMIC SYSTEM AND THE THREAT TO WORLD SECURITY<br />
THAT THIS tS FUELLINGSO<br />
I COME HERE TO GIVE VOICE TO THAT SENSE OF FRUSTRATIONI<br />
COME TO MAKE SOME SPECIFIC, RELEVANT AND PRACTICABLE<br />
PROPOSALS. AND I COME WITH THE CONVICTION THAT I DO SO iN A<br />
FORUM COMPOSED OF PEOPLENOT SATISFIED MERELY TO EXCHANGE<br />
VIEWS, IDENTIFY PROBLEMS AND THEN TO CONTINUE ON THEIR WAY<br />
AS BEFORE. </p>
<p>I I<br />
I 3I 29 ' 87 OZI6 V&amp;. ST PM<br />
I COME<br />
ON ALL<br />
TO ACT<br />
WAY OF RICOHFRX 2 24565<br />
T: s.<br />
2 g, P. 3<br />
Jr<br />
WITH A CONVICTION THAT YOU RECOGNISE A RESPONSIBILITY<br />
OF US AT THIS CONFERENCE, IN OUR VARYING CAPACITIES,<br />
DECISIVELY TO REMOVE THE OBSTACLES STANDING IN THE<br />
A" DURABLE ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL REVIVAL'<br />
LADIES: AND GENTLEMEN:<br />
I SPEA( TO YOU THIS EVENING AS A PRACTISING POLITICIAN. THE<br />
PRIORI | ES OF THE TASKS I FACE MAKE IT AN UNACCEPTABLE<br />
LUXURY MERELY TO ENGAGE IN SPECULATION ON THE PROBLEMS<br />
CONFRONTING US.<br />
INSTEAD, MY BASIC CONCERN IS TO OUTLINE SOME OF THE MEASURES<br />
BY WHICH WE CAN MAKE IMMEDIATE PROGRESS TOWARDS THIS GOAL OF<br />
POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC REVIVAL.<br />
HOWEVER, ALLOW ME, BY WAY OF NECESSARY BACKGROUND, TO<br />
ESTABLISH THE CONTEXT FOR THESE PROPOSALSTHE<br />
STARK ECONOMIC PROBLEMS FACING THE WORLD ARE FAMILIAR TO<br />
THIS AUDIENCE-WE LIVE IN AN ERA OF UNCERTAINTY WITH<br />
TROUBLING WORLD-WIDE DEVELOPMENTS IN DEBT ACCUMULATION,<br />
CURRENT ACCOUNT IMBALANCES, INTEREST RATES AND UNEMPLOYMENT.<br />
BENEATH THESE PROBLEMS LIE DEEPER COMPLEXITIES. MANY OF THE<br />
PREMISES OF THE POST-WAR DECADES ARE ERODING OR HAVE<br />
VANISHED ENTIRELY WITHOUT BEING REPLACED BY NEW PRINCIPLES<br />
UPON WHICH TO BASE THE RESOLUTION OF OUR DIFFICULTIESTo<br />
UNDERTAKE EFFECTIVELY THE SHAPING OF THESE NEW PRINCIPLES<br />
WE SHOULD APPRECIATE HOW THESE PREMISES OF THE POST-WAR<br />
DECADE WERE THEMSELVES SHAPED. -I<br />
I.. 4 j </p>
<p>JAN 29 ' 87 02: 27 AF* ST PM RICOHfRX 2 245965 P. 4<br />
3,<br />
IF WE ARE TO LEARN ANYTHING FROM PRE-WAR HISTORY IT MUST BE<br />
THAT THE GLOBAL CONFLICT OF WORLD WAR 2 WAS IN LARGE MEASURE<br />
THE PRODUCT OF THE FAILURE OF POLITICAL LEADERSHIP TO RECOGNISE<br />
AND ADJUST. TO THE COLLAPSE OF ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN AND<br />
WITHIN NATIONS. ONE OF THE MORE REMARKABLE MINDS OF THIS CENTURY<br />
JOHN MAYNARD KEYNES HAD HOISTED THE EARLY WARNING SIGNALS. 0<br />
FIRtS T IN HIS oECONOMIC CONSEQUENCES OF THE PEACE" ( 1919) AND<br />
LATER IN THE ' GENERAL THEORY OF MONEY, EMPLOYMENT AND INTEREST"<br />
( 1935-36).<br />
IN THE AFTERMATH OF THE CONFLICT-WHICH KEYNES HAD FORESEEN, THE<br />
WORLD SHOWED THAT IT HAD LEARNED CONSIDERABLY FROM THOSE MISTAKES.<br />
WITHIN NATIONS, THE IMPORTANCE OF, AND MECHANISMS FOR MAINTAINING,<br />
ADEQUATE AGGREGATE DEMAND WERE BETTER APPRECIATED AND APPLIED.<br />
As BETWEEN NATIONS, THE VICTORS NOW, FAR FROM IMPOSING GREATER<br />
REPARATIONS UPON THE VANQUISHED, SET ABOUT ASSISTING THE<br />
RESTORATION OF THEIR ECONOMIES WITH THE REMARKABLE SUCCESS TO<br />
WHICH Wt ARE ALL WITNESS; AND MECHANISMS WERE ESTABLISHED FOR THE<br />
BETTER CONDUCT OF INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIPS,<br />
AS A RESULT, IN THE DECADES AFTER THE SECOND WORLD WAR, CHAOS<br />
AND BEGGAR-MY-NEIGHBOUR POLICIEC GAVE WAY TO MULTILATERALISM<br />
WHICH PRODUCED GROWTH AND PROSPERITY#<br />
BUT, IN TURN, THAT WORLD HAS GONE. THE CLEAR ECONOMIC LEADERSHIP<br />
PROVIDED BY THE US HAS DISSIPATED. RELENTLESS TECHNOLOGICAL<br />
CHANGE AND THE EVOLUTION OF THE INFORMATION SOCIETY HAVE RENDERED<br />
MANY OF OUR EXISTING INSTITUTIONS AND ATTITUDES OUT OF DATE. A<br />
SIMPLE FAITH IN THE KEYNESIAN PANACEA IS NO LONGER ADEQUATE NOR,<br />
FOR THAT MATTER, MIGHT I SAY IS THERE SALVATION IN THE NOW MUCH<br />
MORE MUTED DOCTRINES OF MONETARISM,<br />
AS DECISION MAKERS FACE4 WITH THE RESPONSIBILITY OF MANAGING THESE.<br />
CHALLENGES, WE MUST BE PREPARED TO RELINQUISH WHATEVER SUPERSEDED<br />
ASSUMPTIONS AND INHERITED IDEOLOGIES IMPEDE OUR TASK OF LEADERSHIP<br />
IN THE FINAL YEARS OF THE TWENTIETH CENTURY.<br />
71' </p>
<p>JPi2917 M22R9IACTO W-AX<br />
IN THEIR PLACE, WE MUST ACCEPT AS A BASIS FOR ALL OUR<br />
DECISIONS-THE NO0W INDISPUTABLE TRUTH OF OUR TIME -OUR<br />
COMPLETE INTERDEPENDENCE-WE MUST AVOID ANYTHING RESEMBLING<br />
A RETURN TO THE ECONOMIC INSANITIES OF PRE-1939. FOR LET ME<br />
EMPVIASISE* THIS POINT. I HAVE SAID THE WORLD PAID A HEAVY<br />
PRICE IN WORLD WAR 2 FOR ITS INCAPACITY TO READ AND RESOLVE<br />
THE EMERGING ECONOMIC AUTARKY OF THE 20' S AND 30' s<br />
HORRENDOUS AS THAT PRICE WAS, IT WOULD BE AS NOTHING<br />
COMPARED TO THE CONSEQUENCES OF CONFLICT IN THIS NUCLEAR<br />
AIDE. THIS COMPLETE INTERDEPENDENCE MEANS, AS THE DEBT CRISIS AND<br />
THE COMMODITY PRICE SLUMP DEMONSTRATE, THAT THE POVERTY OR<br />
PROSPERITY OF INDIVIDUAL NATIONS ARE QUESTIONS THAT CONCERN<br />
US ALLIT<br />
MEANS THAT NATIONS WHICH SEEK TO ACHIEVE DOMESTIC<br />
POLITICAL GOALS THROUGH DISTORTING THE INTERNATIONAL TRADING<br />
FRAMEWORK ARE DELUDING THEMSELVES WHILE THEY ARE HURTING<br />
OTHERSFROM THIS ' IT FOLLOWS THAT SUCCESSFUL LEADERSHIP WILL REQUIRE<br />
TWO CLOSELY RELATED COMMITMENTSFIRST.<br />
GOVERNMENTS MUST SHOW THEIR WILLINGNESS TO<br />
RESTRUCTURE THEIR OWN ECONOMIES, WITH DEVELOPED COUNTRIES<br />
LEADING THE WAY.<br />
WE MUST ALL ACCEPT THE LESSON THAT GOOD DOMESTIC POLICY AND<br />
GOOD INTERNATIONAL POLICY ARE INSEPARABLE-IF WE CANNOT<br />
PERSUADE OUR DOMESTIC CQJ4STITUENCIES TO ACCEPT CHANGEINDEED,<br />
IF WE ALLOW TtIEM TO ISOLATE AND INSULATE THEMSELVES<br />
FROM IT AND ENCOURAGE ITHEM TO RESIST AND RETARD DOMESTIC<br />
STRUCTURAL ADJUSTM4ENT -WE HAVE FAILED NOT ONLY THEN BUT THE<br />
ReST OF THE WORLDcl 2 tj </p>
<p>No. 062 733693 29,01,87 12: 09 P. 06<br />
JAN 29 ' 87 02,30 RUST PM RICOfAX 2 245965 P. 6<br />
IN THIS RESPECT I ASK YOU TO OBSERVE WITH ME ONE OF THE MORE<br />
INCONGRUOUS AND CERTAINLY LESS ATTRACTIVE FEATURES OF THE<br />
PRESENT WORLD ECONOMIC LANDSCAPE. REFER TO THE CONSTANT<br />
LECTURING TO THE DEBTOR NATIONS OF THE DEVELOPING WORLD ON<br />
THE NEED TO EXERCISE THE HARSH DISCIPLINES OF RATIONAL ND<br />
RELEVANT ECONOMIC POLICIES AND THIS BY MAJOR ECONOMIC<br />
POWERS WHO AT THE SAME TIME THEMSELVES ESCHEW THE<br />
STRINGENCIES RELEVANT BOTH TO THEIR OWN CIRCUMSTANCES. AND TO<br />
THE VERY CONDITION OF THOSE WHOM THEY LECTURE*<br />
OUR SECOND COMMITMENT MUST BE TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF FREE AND<br />
FAIR INTERNATIONAL TRADEFOR<br />
RESTRICTIONS ON TRADE TODAY STAND OUT AS MAJOR OBSTACLES<br />
TO RENEWED PROSPERITYPROTECTIONISM IS SPREADING LIKE A PLAGUE-QUOTAS, VOLUNTARY<br />
RESTRAINTS, DOMESTIC PRICE SUPPORT SCHEMES AND CONTRIVED<br />
QUALITY STANDARDS HAVE SUPPLEMENTED TRADITIONAL TARIFFS TO<br />
FORM BARRIERS TO TRADE IN A STAGGERING RANGE OF<br />
MANUFACTURES, FARM PRODUCTS AND SERVICESo<br />
WE MUST BE ABLE TO TRADE OUR WAY OUT OF OUR PROBLEMSo AND TO<br />
DO THIS WE NEED, AS A BASIC AND URGENTLY REQUIRED CONDITIONo<br />
A MARKET'PLACE FREE OF THE DISTORTING INFLUENCE OF<br />
UNNECESSARY GOVERNMENT INTERVENTIONNOWHERE<br />
IS THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THESE COMMITMENTS CLOSER<br />
NOR THE NEED FOR ACTION GREATER. THAN IN THE TRADE IN<br />
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS, WHICH CAN FAIRLY BE SAID TO BE IN ITS<br />
DEEPEST CRISIS SINCE THE GREAT DEPRESSIONSHORTSIGHTED<br />
LRICULTURAL PROTECTIONISM HAS ALLOWED INDEED<br />
ENCOURAGED FARMERS IN SOME COUNTRIES TO IGNORE THE NORMAL<br />
MARKET SIGNALS OF OVERSUPPLY FOR THEIR PRODUCTS, SUCH AS<br />
FALLING INTERNATIONAL PRICES AND EXCESSIVE OVERSTOCKING-</p>
<p>062 33' 2 0 1 7 1 2: 10 F .07<br />
JSW: 29 ' 87 02132 RUST PMRICOHF-X 2 Z4565 P. 7 i~ k<br />
AS A RESULT THEIR FARMS ARE LIKE MACHINES OUT OF CONTROL,<br />
CHURNING OUT GLUT ON GLUT OF WHEAT AND BEEF, BUTTER AND MILK,<br />
SUGAR AND-RICE. SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE DECADE, INTERNATIONAL<br />
WHEAT PRICES HAVE FALLEN BY NEARLY HALF, SUGAR PRICES BY MORE<br />
THAN TWO THIRDS YET STILL THEY ARE PRODUCED, AND STILL THE<br />
PROTECTIONISM HAS FOSTERED SOME TRULY LUDICROU ANOMALIES,<br />
BUDGETARY ASSISTANCE IN BOTH THE EC AND THE USIIS DIRECTED TO<br />
FARMERS WHO IN MANY CASES ARE WEALTHIER THAN THE AVERAGE INCOME<br />
EARNER WHOSE TAXES PROVIDE THAT SUPPORT. SOME EC DAIRY FARMERS<br />
PAY MORE TO IMPORT FEED FOR THEIR COWS THAN THEY COULD HAVE<br />
RECEIVED ON THE WORLD MARKET FOR THE MILK PRODUCED FROM IT.<br />
JAPANESE RICE PRODUCTION IS SO HANDSOMELY REWARDED THAT PART<br />
OF THE ANNUAL OVERSUPPLY HAS BEEN SOLD AT HUGE LOSSES AS ANIMAL<br />
FEED. FARM SUPPORT PROGRAMS FOR 1986/ 87 ARE ESTIMATED AT $ US23 BILLION<br />
IN THE EC AND $ US26 BILLION IN THE US WHILE JAPAN IN 1985<br />
SPENT MORE THAN $ US10 BILLION,<br />
IN ADDITION TO THESE DIRECT BUDGETARY COSTS, HIGHER DOMESTIC<br />
PRICES MEAN THE CONSUMERS IN EACH SOCIETY ARE PAYING BILLIONS OF<br />
DOLLARS MORE EACH YEAR TO KEEP FARMERS ON THE LAND.<br />
THE TOTAL SUBSIDIES ARE HUGE. AS JUST ONE INDICATION, DAIRY<br />
FARMERS IN EUROPE RECEIVE AROUND $ 400 A COW. THAT MAY SOUND<br />
AN EXTRAVAGANT SUM AND IT IS. BUT IT IS MODEST COMPARED TO<br />
AMERICAN SUBSIDIES WHICH AMOUNT TO SOME $ 835 FOR EVERY DAIRY COW IN<br />
THE UNITED STATES.<br />
BUT DESPITE IT ALL, AND'THIS IS THE MOST DAMNING INDICTMENT OF<br />
PROTECTIONISM, IT JUST ISN'T WORKING NOR COULD IT EVER HAVE DONE<br />
SO. THE INCOMES OF PROTECTED FARMERS HAVE NOT RECOVERED AND FARM<br />
BANKRUPTCIES ARE CONTINUING. ' C<br />
No </p>
<p>* JPr4 29 D87 02133 ALUST F11 RICOWfRX 2 Z45V65 P. 6a<br />
7.<br />
BECAUSIE OF THE MISALLOCATION OF RESOURCES AflD RESULTANT<br />
HIGHER COST AND PRICE STRUCTURES, THE ECONOMIC, GROWTH RATES<br />
OF EUROPE ARE LOWER AND THE DOLE QUEUES AT LEAST A MILLION<br />
PERSONS LONGER.<br />
AT T. HE SAME TIME, IT IS HURTING THE. REST OF THE WORLD. LESS<br />
DEVELOPED COUNTRIES ARE HURT BY B~ IN% EXCLUDED FROM THE<br />
WORLD AGRICULTURAL MARKET. FREE RADE IN FARM PRODUCTS<br />
WOULD ALLOW DEBTOR NATIONS TO EARN SUFFICIENT FOREIGN<br />
EXCHANGE TO MORE THAN DISCHARGE THEIR INTEREST COMMITMENTSMiORE<br />
IMPORTANT, THEY WOULD BE ON THEIR WAY TO DEVELOPMENT<br />
THROUGH TRADE* NOT JUST AIDLADIES<br />
AND GENTLE~ MEN,<br />
WE KNOW THIS PROBLEM IS NOT PURELY AN ECONOMIC ONE# TO BE<br />
CURED PURELY BY ECONOMIC MEASURESFOR<br />
THE ISSUES AND VALUES AT STAKE ARE ESSENTIALLY POLITICAL<br />
ONES THE LIVING STANDARDS OF OUR PEOPLE' AND THE<br />
COMMITMENTS I HAVE URGED THE PURSUIT OF STRUCTURAL<br />
ADJUSTMENT AT HOME AND THE CREATION OF AN ANTI-PROTECTIONIST<br />
ETHOS ABROAD ARE ESSENTIALLY POLITICAL ONES TOO, REQUIRING<br />
THE bALANCING OF THE OFTEN CONFLICTING DEMANDS OF FARMERS,<br />
CONSUMERS, TAXPAYERS, CONSERVATIONISTS AND OTHERSIN<br />
THE SEARCH FOR THESE POLITICAL SOLUTIONS, I BELIEVE THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN VOICE HAS CREDIBILITYOUR<br />
CREDIBILITY DERIVES NOT FROM THE FACT THAT AUSTRALIAN<br />
FARMERS# PERHAPS THE MOST EFFICIENT AND LEAST PROTECTED IN<br />
THE WORLD, HAVE BECOME TAlE INNOCENT VICTIMS OF THE CYCLE OF<br />
PROTECTIONISM BY THE WORLD'S RICHEST COUNTRIES THOUGH THAT<br />
CERTAINLY FUELS OUR FRUSTRATIONS'<br />
OUR CRiDIBILtTY ARISES FROM4 THE FACT THAT WE IN AUSTRALIA<br />
HAVE LEARNT TH4E LESSON THAT MANY OF OUR TRADING PARTNERS<br />
SEEM SLOW TO GRASP-OR RELUCTANT TO APPLY -THAT SIMPLY<br />
STATED LESSON OF OUR WORLD-WIDE MUTUAL INTERDEPENDENCE-</p>
<p>No. 062 733693 29,01,87 12: 11 P. 09<br />
JFI 29 ' 67 02134 AUST PM RICOHFAX 2 24965 P. 9<br />
8.<br />
AS A MEMBER OF THE ASIA-PACIFIC REGION, THE MOST DYNAMIC AND<br />
FASTEST GROWING PART OF THE WORLD ECONOMY, AUSTRALIA HAS HAD<br />
NO CHOICE-BUT TO LEARN THAT LESSONSIMPLY<br />
TO SURVIVE AS A R LEVANT, MODERN ECONOMY AND SOCIETY<br />
IN XHIS DYNAMIC REGION, IUSTRALIA COULD NOT CLOSE ITSELF OFF<br />
BEHIND ARTIFICIAL AND AR( HAIC BARR. ERSAS<br />
ANYONE WHO HAS SOME ACQUAINTANCE WITH THE RECORD OF MY<br />
GOVERNMENT FOR THE PAST FOUR YEARS'WILL KNOW. WE HAVE SHOWN<br />
OUR WILLINGNESS TO MEET THE TWO COMMITMENTS I MENTIONED<br />
EARLIER-WE ARE RESTRUCTURING OUR DOMESTIC ECONOMY, AND WE<br />
ARE OPENING OURSELVES UP TO FREE AND FAIR INTERNATIONAL<br />
TRADE WE ARE PHASING DOWN PROTECTION OF OUR MANUFACTURING SECTOR<br />
AND AS A RESULT OUR CAR MANUFACTURERS AND TEXTILES, CLOTHING<br />
AND FOOTWEAR MAKERS ARE FACING STEADY REDUCTIONS IN<br />
ASSISTANCE. SIMILARLY THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO REDUCE<br />
TARIFFS ON CHEMICALS AND PLASTICS TO RATES MORE IN LINE WITH<br />
OTHER OECD COUNTRIES. THE STEEL AND HEAVY ENGINEERING<br />
INDUSTRIES, WHICH HAVE NOT IN THE PAST BEEN HIGHLY<br />
PROTECTED, ARE NOW BEING REVITALISED THROUGH SECTORAL PLANS<br />
WHICH WILL ENCOURAGE THEM TO LOOK OUTWARD TO COMPETE IN THE<br />
WORLD S MARKETSø<br />
IT IS TRUE THAT SOME AREAS OF AUSTRALIAN PRODUCTION CONTINUE<br />
TO RECEIVE HIGH, ALBEIT DECLINING, BARRIER PROTECTION-IT<br />
IS NOT TRUE HOWEVER, DESPITE THE FREQUENT MISREPRESENTATIONS<br />
TO THE CONTRARY. THAT THESE MEASURES CAN BE PLACED IN THE<br />
SAME CATEGORY AS THE NON TARIFF PROTECTION PROVIDED TO<br />
AGRICULTURAL AND IN SOME-" CASES INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTION, IN<br />
EUROPE, NORTH AMERICA AND JAPAN. </p>
<p>tito . c6, 2 _ I6 2 j 12: 12 F.<br />
3 2g9 o a" JS3T PM RIC10HFAX 2 245965 P. 10<br />
LET ME EXPLAIN THE KEY DIFFERENCES. AUSTRALIA'S BARRIER<br />
PROTECTION IS GENERALLY EXTENDED BY WAY OF TARIFFS. THIS Is<br />
A TRANSPFARENT FORK OF ASSISTANCE. IT ALLOWS SIGNIFICANT<br />
MARKET ACCESS TO IMPORTS-IT IS NOT PROJECTED BEYOND OUR<br />
BORDERS-IT IS NOT RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CREATION OF MASSIVE<br />
$ U4LUSPj ODUCT ION.<br />
NOR DOES IT WEAKEN OUR TRADING PARTNERS' ACCESS TO<br />
TRADITIONAL MARKETS THROUGH DUMPING AND OTHER EXPORT<br />
SUBSIDISATION SUCH AS WE SEE WITH* THE CURRENT TRADE WAR.<br />
FINALLY, AUSTRALIA IS COMMITTED TO THE STEADY REDUCTION OF<br />
PROTECTIONISM OVER THE NEXT DECADE.<br />
AS A PRACTISING POLITICIAN LET ME TELL YOU THERE iS NOT MUCH<br />
SHORT-TERM POPULARITY TO BE GAINED IN TELLING WORKERS THEY<br />
MUST ACCEPT REAL WAGE CUTS AND CHANGE LONG-STANDING,<br />
COMFORTABLE BUT OUTMODED WORK PRACTICES, OR IN TELLING<br />
ELDERLY PENSIONERS THEY MUST ACCEPT A DELAY IN THE RECEIPT<br />
OF THEIR PENSIONS, OR IN TELLING AN OWNER OF A BUSINESS OR<br />
PURCHASER OF A NEW HOME THAT THEY SHOULD PAY HIGHER INTEREST<br />
RATES THAN THEY MIHT HAVE EXPECTEDBUT<br />
THE HARD DECISIONS YIELD LONG-TERM BENEFITS A MORE<br />
RESILIENT AND COMPETITIVE ECONOMY AND A HIGHER STANDARD OF<br />
LIVING. OUR SUCCESS IN THE TASK OF STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT HAS RELIED<br />
ON THE WAY WE HAVE GONE ABOUT THE TASK* I HAVE A LONG-HELD<br />
CONVICTION THAT PROGRESS TOWARDS FAIRNESS AND PROSPERITY CAN<br />
ONLY BE ACHIEVED THROUGH CO-OPERATION RATHER THAN<br />
CONFRONTATION-IN PLANNING OUR REFORMS, MY GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
SOUGHT THE VIEWS OF ALL THOSE AFFECTED AND AIMED AT BUILDING<br />
A COMMUNITY CONSENSUS AS THE BASIS FOR OUR DECISIONS* </p>
<p>No. 06 33 3 12: 13 P. 11<br />
JAN 29 ' 87 02: 37 AUST PMRICOH* F -2 245% 5<br />
IF I COULD PUT THIS PERHAPS IN EVEN MORE DIRECT TERMS. I<br />
HAVE OPERATED ON THE BASIS THAT IN THE SWEEP OF HISTORY THE<br />
HORSE. CALLED ' MORAL IMPERATIVE* HAS, UNFORTUNATELY, USUALLY<br />
BEEN A POOR-PERFORMER. THE ONE CALLED * SELF INTEREST" IS A<br />
SUPERIOR CONVEYANCE BECAUSE IT IS ALWAYS TRYING. THE SECRET<br />
OF SUCCESSFUL POLICY ACHIEVEMENT 16 TO MAKE THE RELEVANT<br />
CONSTITUENCIES UNDERSTAND THAT ENLIGHTENED SELF INTEREST<br />
ME NS UNDERSTANDING THE INTERESTS OF, AND CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
CO-OPERATION WITH, EACH OTHER.<br />
IT IS A FORMULA WHICH COULD WELL-BE -APPLIED TO THE<br />
RESOLUTION OF OUR AGRICULTURAL TRADE PROBLEMS, AS THIS WILL<br />
REQUIRE PATIENT NEGOTIATIONS AND A REALISTIC IF YOU LIKE,<br />
A SELF-INTERESTED UNDERSTANDING OF THE BENEFITS TO BE<br />
GAINED FROM ENDING THE TRADE WAR.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN:<br />
A MAJOR STEP TOWARDS RESOLVING THE PROBLEM OF AGRICULTURAL<br />
PROTECTION WAS TAKEN WITH THE RECENT DECISION TO LAUNCH THE<br />
URUGUAY ROUND OF MULTILATERAL TRADE NEGOTIATIONS, WITH<br />
AGRICULTURE SERIOUSLY ON THE AGENDA FOR THE FIRST TIME.<br />
l<br />
THIS NEW ROUND PROVIDES A TIMELY OPPORTUNITY TO RESTORE<br />
CONFIDENCE IN THE MULTILATERAL SYSTEM AND PROVIDES SCOPE FOR<br />
A RETURN TO FREER TRADE TO THE BENEFIT OF ALL COUNTRIES.<br />
AUSTRALIA WAS EAGER TO BE AT THE VANGUARD OF THIS REFORM<br />
MOVEMENT. WE CONVENED A MEETING IN CAIRNS OF REPRESENTATIVES OF<br />
FOURTEEN FAIR TRADING NATIONS IN AGRICULTURE. THIS CAIRNS<br />
GROUP PROVED TO BE AN EFIECTIVE ALLIANCE AT PUNTA DEL ESTE<br />
LAST SEPTEMBER. P. 11 I<br />
ii<br />
I-OLP Y<br />
s. </p>
<p>N'<br />
JTAN 29 187 eZ 38 RUST PM I i4 I-IRICOHFAX<br />
Z Z4565 I<br />
WE ARE FULLY COMMITTED TO MAKING THE MTN ROUND A SUCCESS.<br />
To DEMOt _ LRATE AUSTRALIA'S COMMITMENT, I AM PREPARED TO<br />
STATE NOW THAT WE ARE WILLING TO NEGOTIATE THE BINDING OF<br />
TARIFF LEVELS IN ALL SECTORS OF AUSTRALIA'$ TARIFF REGIMETHIS<br />
Is A. SIGNIFICANT COMMITMENT, GIVEN THAT REVIOUS<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS HAVE BOUNDONLY A VERYLOW PORTION OF<br />
ITS TARIFF.<br />
SFRONG MOTIVATION AND COMMITMENT 1 REQUIRED OF ALL THE<br />
PARTICIPATING COUNTRIES IF THE NEW MTN ROUND 18 SUCCESSFULLY<br />
To LIBERALISE WORLD TRADE. THE NEW ROUND MUST BE ALLOWED TO<br />
PROCEED FREE OF FUTILE DELAYS, AND NOT GET SIDE-TRACKED BY<br />
PERIPHERAL OR TECHNICAL ISSUES. SOME PARTICIPANTS WILL<br />
HAVE TO CONTEMPLATE OPENING UP PREVIOUSLY STRONGLY PROTECTED<br />
SECTORSBUT, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, WITH ALL THE COMMITMENT IN THE<br />
WORLD, THE MTN ROUND WILL STILL SPAN GGVGRAL YEARS-MY<br />
CONCERN 1$ THAT MANY COUNTRIES CANIT AFFORD THE LUXURY OF<br />
WAITING TO SEE WHAT THE NEW ROUND BRINGS.<br />
INDEED, IF PRICE CUTTING BETWEEN THE US AND THE EUROPEAN<br />
COMMUNITY CONTINUES AT ITS CURRENT FRANTIC PACE, THE TOTAL<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADE FRAMEWORK MAY BE UNDERMINED BEFORE THE<br />
NEW MTN ROUND ACHIEVES ANY RESULTS.<br />
SO THIS EVENING I WANT TO EXPLAIN HOW WE CAN START MAKING<br />
PROGRESS IMMEDIATELY.<br />
BECAUSE OF THE IMPORTANCE AUSTRALIA ATTACHES TO THIS ISSUE,<br />
I WANT TO SPEND A LITTLE TIME OUTLINING TO YOU THE STEPS I<br />
BELIEVE CAN AND SHOULD BE TAKEN TO ACHIEVE THIS-( A MORE<br />
DETAILED STATEMENT AMPLIFYING THIS PROPOSAL 1S BEING<br />
CIRCULATED-) MI </p>
<p>V<br />
JAN 29 ' 87 02: 39 AUST PM RICOI--( 2 245% 5 P. 13<br />
12-<br />
CENTRAL TO T1tE AUSTRALIAN PROPOSAL IS THE OBSERVATION THAT<br />
THE CORRUPTION OF WORLD AGRICULTURAL TRADE is BEING CAUSED<br />
BY GOVERNMENTS RAISING THE PRICES THEIR FARMERS RECEIVE<br />
ABOVE PREVAILING WORLD PRICES, RESULTING IN A SUBSIDY TO<br />
UNECONOMIC PRODUCTION. THIS PRICE ADJUSTMENT GAP PROVIDES<br />
A CLEAR PICTURE OF THE ALMOST UNBLIEVABLE AMOUNT OF<br />
PROTECTION PROVIDED TO SOME PRODUdTS,<br />
THE DOMESTIC PRICE OF EC WHEAT IS DOUBLE THAT OF WORLD PRICES,<br />
FOR BUTTER IT IS AROUND TWO AND A HALF TIMES WORLD PRICES, FOR<br />
EC AND US SUGAR IT IS AROUND THREE TIMES WORLD PRICES, AND FOR<br />
RICE THE JAPANESE PRICE IS SOME EIGHT TIMES WORLD PRICES.<br />
[ F WE ARE TO RESTORE SOME SANITY INTO THE WORLD AGRICULTURAL<br />
MARKET WE MUST SEE WORLD MARKET PRICES BETTER REFLECTED IN<br />
DOMESTIC MARKET PRICES. AN ABRUPT CLOSURE OF THIS PRICE GAP<br />
IS NOT POSSIBLE. BUT A MOVEMENT IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION IS<br />
NEEDED OUR CENTRAL OBJECTIVE SHOULD BE TO AGREE ON WAYS TO FREEZE<br />
THE LEVEL OF SUBSIDIES AND TO REDUCE THE PRICE ADJUSTMENT GAP<br />
FOR ALL AGRICULTURAL COMMODITIES,<br />
THIS IS CONSISTENT WITH THE TOKYO SUMMIT CALL FOR ADJUSTMENT<br />
MEASURES IN AGRICULTURE AND THE OBJECTIVES ADOPTED AT PUNTA<br />
DEL ESTE,<br />
WE HAVE DISCUSSED OUR FREEZE, OR CEASEFIRE, PROPOSAL WITH<br />
OFFICIALS OF THE US AND THE EC. BELIEVE BOTH AGREE IN<br />
PRINCIPLE WITH THE NOTION. THEY ARE EACH TOTALLY AWARE OF THE<br />
FUTILITY OF THEIR TRADE WAR AND OF ITS CONSEQUENCES FOR THEIR<br />
TREASURIES,<br />
WITH A FREEZE IN PLACE, THE GAP COULD BE CLOSED BY A COMBINATION<br />
OF MEASURES AIMED AT SIMULTANEOUSLY REDUCING<br />
INTERNAL ADMINISTERED PRICES AND FACILITATING AN INCREASE IN<br />
INTERNATIONAL PRICES BY REDUCING SUPPLIES, </p>
<p>P. 1<br />
Z9170: 4 TP<br />
A RELATED MEASURE MUST BE THE ORDERLY DISPOSAL OF THE<br />
EXISTING HUGE STOCKS SO THEY CAN BE PROGRESSIVELY RELEASED<br />
ACCORDING TO AN INTERNATIONALLY AGREED APPROACH WHILE<br />
CAUSING MINIMUM DISRUPTION TO THE MARKETIRECOGNISE<br />
THAt ALL [ HIS WiILL NOT BE ACHIEVED WITHOUT<br />
TRANAITION DIFFICULTIES. WHERE NECESSARY, FARM INCOMES WILL<br />
HAVE TO BE SUPPORTED BY A ' RANGE OF SUPPLEMENTARY ADJUSTMENT<br />
MEASURESBUT THIS SHOULD NOT 8E PURSUED BY COUNTERPRODUCTIVE MEASURES<br />
WHI1CH LINK THE LEVEL OF SUPPORT TO THE AMOUNT PRODUCED.<br />
AN OPPORTUNITY TO FURTHER THESE OBJECTIVES IS PROVIDED BY A<br />
SERIES OF IMPORTANT MEETINGS TO BE HELD OVER THE FIRST SIX<br />
MONTHS OF THIS YEAR, INCLUDING THE WHEAT EXPORTERS MEETING<br />
NEXT MONTH, THE GATT TRADE MINISTERS MEETING IN MARCH, THE<br />
OECD MINISTERIAL COUNCIL MEETING IN MAY AND THE UN WORLD<br />
FOOD COUNCIL AND ECONOMIC SUMMIT IN JUNE.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN:<br />
THE OPPORTUNITY FOR SUBSTANTIAL REFORM IN AGRICULTURAL TRADE<br />
IS AT HANDIF:<br />
THE MAJOR PLAYERS SUCCEED IN REACHING A CONSENSUS<br />
BELIEVE OTHiER COUNTRIES WILL FOLLOW SUIT.<br />
AND IF WE SUCCEED NOW, SUCCESS AT GATT WILL SURELY FOLLOW.<br />
BUT If WE FAIL, WE RUN THE RISK OF TOTAL COLLAPSE OF THlE<br />
INTERNATIONAL TRADING 6YSTjM.<br />
INDEED, WE RUN THE RISK OF EVER MORE SUBSTANTIAL DAMAGE THAN<br />
THAT-</p>
<p>1 F I<br />
-C r~ r1E<br />
14. RIOOHAX 2 Z45% 5<br />
THE-REALITY, AS I HAVE ADUMBRATED EARLIER, IS THAT THE<br />
PROBLEM OF PROTECTIONISM GOES TO THE HEART NOT JUST OF OUR<br />
ECONOMIC WELL-BEING BUT OF OUR FUNDAMENTAL POLITICAL<br />
RELATIONSHIPS-IT CONTAINS THE SEEDS OF TURMOIL. As<br />
LEADERS WE MUST PREVENT THE GERMINATION OF THESE. DEADLY<br />
SEEDS.<br />
THIS is UNDERLINED FORCEFULLY IF WE AGAIN CONSIDER THE<br />
PROBLEM IN THE LONGER HISTORICAL SWEEP. IN THE FIRST<br />
POST-WAR DECADES, THE PRINCIPAL ECONOMIC DEBATE CENTRED ON<br />
THE IDEOLOGICAL CONTEST BETWEEN EAST AND WEST. IN THE<br />
1970' s, WE FOCUSED OUR ATTENTION AS WELL ON THE NORTH-SOUTH<br />
PROBLEMSNEITHER OF THESE BIG IssuEs IS RESOLVED. YET IN THE 1980' s<br />
THE DEVELOPED DEMOCRATIC NATIONS OF THE WEST AND THE NORTH<br />
NOW FIND OURSELVES PREOCCUPIED WITH A DEBILITATING DISPUTE<br />
AMONG. OURSELVES IN PARTICULAR, AMONG THOSE NATIONS WHICH<br />
THROUGHOUT THE POST-WAR ERA HAVE PROVIDED THE BEDROCK OF OUR<br />
POLITICAL CO-OPERATION AND ECONOMIC LEADERSHIPAM<br />
NOT PREDICTING THAT THE TRADE TENSIONS WILL LEAD TO THE<br />
COLLAPSE OVERNIGHT OF CORDIAL POLITICAL RELATIONSHIPS IN THE<br />
WEST-OUR DEEP HISTORICAL, DEMOCRATIC AND STRATEGIC LINKS<br />
ARE ALL FAIRLY DURABLE COMMODITIES AND ARE CAPABLE OF<br />
ENDURING A HIGH DEGREE OF DISAGREEMENT ON ECONOMIC ISSUES.<br />
BUT WE MUST BE ALIVE TO THE PLAUSIBLE THESIS THAT COMMERCIAL<br />
TENSIONS, IF ALLOWED TO FESTER, WILL OVER TIME ERODE WESTERN<br />
POLITICAL AND SECURITY RELATIONSHIPS TO THE POINT WHERE THEY<br />
EVENTUALLY LOSE THEIR DAY-TO-DAY VITALITY-WE COULD BE LEFT<br />
WITH FORM, BUT LITTLE SUBSTANCE.<br />
THAT'THE PROCESS MIGHT BE GRADUAL AND SUBTLE, RATHER THAN<br />
SUDDEN AND DRAMATIC, WOULD MAKE IT NO LESS PERNICIOUS AND<br />
ITS ULTIMATE CONSEQUENCES NO LESS DAMAGING.<br />
1.41-1 </p>
<p>No. 062 733693 29,, 87 12: 18 P. 16<br />
JAN 29 0-0. 43 A. PM RICOAX 2* 24596<br />
MY COUNTRY 18 PART OF THE WESTERN ALLIANCE AS A MATTER NOT<br />
ONLY OF TREATY OBLIGATION BUT OF HARD STRATEGIC ASSESSMENT<br />
THAT WESTERN STRENGTH AND UNITY OF PURPOSE ARt ESSENTIAL.<br />
AND YET IN AUSTRALIA WE HAVE HAD A TASTE OF THE WAY IN WHICH<br />
PROTECTINISM BY OUR FRIENDS CAN PROVOKE PUBLIC ANGER AND<br />
LEAD TO HE QUESTIONING OF ALLIANCE CONNECTIONS HITHERTO<br />
CONSIDERE ALMOST SACROSANCT.<br />
INDEEDi OUR CAPACITY TO PLAY A ROLE IN ADVANCING THE<br />
INTERESTS OF THE WEST CAN ONLY BE. LESSENED IF OUR ECONOMY IS<br />
WEAKENED BY THE SHORT-SIGHTED PURSUIT OF PROTECTIONISM BY<br />
OUR WESTERN ALLIES.<br />
IF THE REACTION Or AUSTRALIANS TO AMERICAN OR EUROPEAN<br />
AGRICULTURAL EXPORT POLICIES IS ANYTHING TO O BY, THE<br />
FRUSTRATION AND RESENTMENT BUILDING UP AmONG AMERICANS,<br />
EUROPEANS AND JAPANESE ABOUT THE TRADING PRACTICES OF EACH<br />
TOWARDS THE OTHER MUST BE TRULY CORROSIVE OF LONG TERM<br />
WESTERN COHESION.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN:<br />
I OPENED MY REMARKS THIS EVENING BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE HIGH<br />
CALIBRE OF THIS DAVOS GATHERING. You HAVE AN EQUALLY<br />
SUBSTANTIAL OBLIGATION TO DISCHARGE.<br />
IT IS MY HOPE THAT IN THE DAYS AHEAD YOU WILL CONSIDER THE<br />
PROPOSALS I HAVE OUTLINED IN THE INTERESTS OF A FAIR AND<br />
OPEN INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ENVIRONMENT IN WHICH TRADE CAN<br />
FLOURISH AND IN WHICH THE QUALITY OF RELATIONS BETWEEN<br />
COUNTRIES CA" BE ENHANCEDIf<br />
LEADERSHIP IN THE TREND OF IDEAS AND OF POLICIES CANNOT<br />
COME FROM PEOPLE SUCH AS YOU, THEN I DO NOT KNOW TO WHOM<br />
ELSE WE CAN LOOK POR THE VITAL COLLECTIVE ENTERPRISE WHICH<br />
LIES ANC$ j OF Us-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
