<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5690</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/11/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005690.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PMIM MNHNST-R<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, NOVEMBER 15 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK.<br />
The Commonwealth Government took the decision to proceed without<br />
further delay towards proclamation of the Cairns section of<br />
the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park after about two years of<br />
' discussion and negotiation with the Queensland government<br />
about the boundaries. We felt that it was time for decisions<br />
to be made and I had indicated earlier in the year that the<br />
Commonwealth's patience was not inexhaustible.<br />
The proclamation of the Cairns section will open the way<br />
to the development of management and zoning arrangements by<br />
the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority, and I hope<br />
Queenslanders will be very much involved in the planning of<br />
these arrangements. In developing this plan, the Authority<br />
will be seeking public subsmissions, and a draft will be<br />
published in due course for further public comment. The management<br />
and zoning arrangements will be designed to protect the Reef,<br />
and as with the Capricornia section, there will be perfectly<br />
satisfactory provision for recreation, shipping, touring,<br />
commercial and amateur fishing and other activities.<br />
The proclamation of the Cairns section will be a further<br />
significant step in the strategy of progressive proclamation<br />
of the various sections of the whole Great Barrier Reef Marine<br />
Park. Since 1975, the whole of the Reef has been protected by<br />
the Commonwealth Government under the Great Barrier Reef Marine<br />
Park Act. The strategy of proclamation by sections provides scope<br />
for effective and realistic planning, and enables the Authority<br />
to take account of the special requirements of each particular<br />
section of an enormous marine park area.<br />
The planning itself takes time eighteen months to two years<br />
in the case of the Capricornia section and the further delays<br />
caused by this part of the whole process makes it even more<br />
important that the decision to proclaim the Cairns section<br />
should be taken now.<br />
The selection of the boundaries of the Cairns section of the<br />
marine park has been made only after the most careful consideration<br />
of alternatives by the Government and by the Great Barrier<br />
Reef Marine Park Authority. The only point at issue was whether<br />
the western boundary along the 550 kilometre coastline should be the ic<br />
water mark on the mainrand or a line some distance off the coast.<br />
And in th2 event, the actual area in dispute affects only 30" of<br />
that 550 kilometre coastline. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
The Commonwealth Government has taken the view that this<br />
boundary would go . out five kilometres from the coast for<br />
about two thirds of its length, but that th-e low water mark<br />
on the mainland must form the boundary where features of<br />
ecological significance are involved, and some of these areas<br />
which need protection right up to the low water mark are<br />
adjacent to land areas that Queensland has itself designated<br />
as national park. Among the ecological features included<br />
will be the sea grass beds north of Cape Flattery, which are<br />
an important habitat for Dugong an internationally<br />
recognisedendangered species, and high quality reefs fringing<br />
the mainland and islands. The marine park concept and the way<br />
it is being implemented will ensure the conservation, of the . Ree<br />
ecosystem. The decision that has been made is a reasonable one, and it<br />
takes account of all the interests and issues involved. It is<br />
decision which deserved the support of the whole community<br />
and the concern for the Reef which all Australians share will<br />
now be best served if all parties work together to get the righL<br />
management arrangements into operation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
