<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2130</transcript-id>
    <title>TALK GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, OVER ABC NETWORK ON FRIDAY 7 OCTOBER</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/10/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002130.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
0. E MBARGO: 7. 15 p. m. RADIO TALK NO. 3<br />
19 69 FEDERAL ELECTION<br />
TALK GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. JOHN GORTON, OVER ABC NETWORK<br />
ON FRIDAY 17 OCTOBER<br />
In my previous talk to you, I dealt with the lack of<br />
policy of the ALP in matters of defence and of foreign affairs. Also<br />
I spoke of how I believed their policy of running out of our overseas<br />
obligations and then cutting our own defence forces imperilled<br />
Australia's future security and, indeed, made it quite possible that<br />
the existence of Australia as an independent nation might, in the years<br />
ahead, well be threatened by these policies.<br />
And so, naturally, they have in their policy speech no<br />
provision for increasing Australia's defences at all. Rather, as<br />
would be expected, do they have a proposal to cut Australia's Army<br />
by one-third by abolishing National Service Training, and this we<br />
will not do. And also they have a proposal to deny the Air Force<br />
that strike aircraft which the Air Force and all our military advisers<br />
say Australia's defence needs. So they have no policy in those<br />
directions. But when you examine the propositions put before you,<br />
they don't have policies in other directions either. There arc no<br />
policies for development which have been put before you by the Labor<br />
Party. We, on the other hand, have put specific proposals.<br />
We have proposed to build railways in South Australia.<br />
We propose to establish an Institute of Marine Science so we can<br />
learn about the Barrier Reef and help to protect it. We propose to<br />
take Australia into the atomic age by establishing an atomic plant<br />
at Jervis Bay. We propose to help the film industry in Australia so<br />
that our talent can be employed, so that the pictures we make can be<br />
exported and so that people overseas can see what the real Australia<br />
is like. These are some of the specific proposals that we have put.<br />
There are no such specific proposals to counter them from the<br />
Opposition. Further, we have in what we have said, made it clear<br />
that we realise that the State Governments will in the years ahead as<br />
our revenue rises, need more and more revenue themselves so that<br />
they can, as their population grows, provide the schools, the roads,<br />
the hospitals, the other services they now give. e. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
There is no indication whatsoever in the speeches of<br />
the Opposition that they realise there will be this need. No indication<br />
whatsoever. All there is is an indication that they will bypass the<br />
States; that they will in education, for example, set up a Commission<br />
to examine ten thousand schools and assess the needs of each. Whereas<br />
we are already working and have been for months been working with<br />
the States not to bypass them, but with each State Education Department<br />
to assess, so that they could assess, the needs of their own schwls.<br />
This surely is a better way to do it.<br />
Then we have in one field only these large promises<br />
in welfare large promises, very costly promises, promises which<br />
will lead to inflation and yet promises which Dr. Cairns, one of the<br />
economists in the Labor Party, has already said may be so costly that<br />
they won't be able to be carried out. It is not surprising he should<br />
say that because in the Opposition, no matter what the Leader wants<br />
to do, he is told what to do by an outside body.<br />
Let me give you one example of that. In Bendigo nct<br />
long ago, the Leader of the Opposition went to the people saying,<br />
" My policy is to make a grant for education. I will give half to State<br />
schools; half to independent schools. Elect my candidate". And a<br />
few scant weeks later he had to change that under dictation.<br />
You cannot rely on what a Parliamentary party, dictated<br />
to by an outside body, will do no matter whatever they may promise<br />
to do. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
