<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11549</transcript-id>
    <title>Awards for Clever People in Agribusiness</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce In-Market Experience Scholarships worth $90,000 to three innovative agribusiness people as part of the Commonwealth's New Industries Development Programme (NIDP).</p>
<p>The three winners are Rick Martin of Australian Cartilage Company, Cootamundra, NSW; Stephen Jeffers of Phoolbari Park Nurseries, Palmwoods, Queensland; and Simone Tully of OBE Beef Pty Limited, Cunnamulla, Queensland.</p>
<p>These awards recognise the efforts of Australians who are opening up new markets through their ingenuity and skill. They highlight the Government's commitment to revitalising regional Australia.</p>
<p>For Australian agribusiness to be competitive we need to continue to build the pool of agribusiness managers with commercial experience in developing new products, services and technologies for new markets. I know these recipients will maximise the opportunities that come with this Scholarship.</p>
<p>The awards will provide opportunities on three key fronts - practical hands-on experience to agribusiness entrepreneurs in better understanding their markets; financial assistance to upgrade skills and knowledge to do their job with greater confidence, and most importantly, they will encourage the ingenuity of Australians who are making things happen.</p>
<p>Rick Martin, General Manager, Australian Cartilage Company, Cootamundra, NSW will further his commitment to establishing Liquid Cartilage, a neutriceutical to aid in the treatment of cancer and arthritis in global markets.</p>
<p>Stephen Jeffers, Manager, Phoolbari Park Nurseries, Palmwoods Queensland will look at the production of commercially grown Australian native cut foliage to supply the highly valued domestic and export floristry markets.</p>
<p>Simone Tully, Company Secretary and Business Manager, OBE Beef Pty Limited, Cunnamulla, Queensland will use the scholarship to assist her in research and development of a new organic supply chain for the marketing of certified organic beef products, attend an Executive Development Program for Primary Producers and to complete a Graduate Certificate In Business Administration.</p>
<p>This Scholarship announcement comes only two weeks after almost $750,00 was awarded to agribusiness enterprises under the New Industries Development Programme's Pilot Commercialisation Projects (PCP).</p>
<p>This funding will assist agribusinesses to reach the full commercialisation stage of a new product, services or technology. A total of 16 PCP projects have now been funded with expected benefits over the medium term in the vicinity of $280 million dollars and the creation of some 475 jobs.</p>
<p>1 September 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
