<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1495</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW ZEALAND TOUR 1967 - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT AT FAIRBAIRN AIRPORT, CANBERRA ON HIS RETURN FROM NEW ZEALAND - 8TH FEBRUARY 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001495.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NEW ZEALAND TOUR 1967<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. HAROLD HOLT AT FAIRBAIRN AIRPORT, CANBERRA<br />
ON HIS RETURN FROM NEW ZEALAND 8TH FEBRUA* YW-1967<br />
MR. HOLT: Well, I am very glad to be back home, and the first thing I want<br />
to say is how saddened I have been to learn of this tragic business in<br />
Tasmania. VWhen I got the news this morning, I sent a message off<br />
immediately to Mr. Reece and then tried to contact him by telephone, but<br />
he was, I gather, on the mainland at the time, and I talked to Mr. Fagan.<br />
I told him that in my message to Mr. Reecel hadasked'if there was<br />
anything more that the Commonwealth Government could be doing to be of<br />
help, and when I spoke to him on the ' phone I suggested if there was<br />
anything he could think of, to contact my colleague, the Deputy Prime<br />
Minister. I gather Mr. McEwen himself had been active in the matter and<br />
that Mr. Howson had been appointed as a liaison Minister f-r-) m the<br />
Commonwealth Government. I asked Mr. Fagan whether our own Service<br />
people had been able to help in any way and he said they had been extremely<br />
helpful on the day of the fire, and at that stage, he felt it was under<br />
control. As to the rest of the detail, I have only been able to pick up a<br />
little bit along the way. I told Mr. Fagan to contact me If he could around<br />
about seven tonight. I expected to be in then. He may have tried to do<br />
so. If not, I will be trying to get in touch with him from the Lodge.<br />
Q. Wil l you go down yourself and have a look at it do you think<br />
you will get an opportunity?<br />
PM: Well, I am willing enough It is a question of whether I could<br />
serve any valuable purpose by doing so. There are busy days ahead here,<br />
but of course if it was of any usefulness and help, I would be glad to do so.<br />
Q. Have you any comment on the result of the Labor leadership<br />
contest<br />
PM:-Well, I heard the news on the plane of Mr. Whitlam's election.<br />
I sent him a message telling him I had just learnt of his election, offered<br />
my congratulations and expressed the hope that he would have a long tenure<br />
of that office, as Leader of the Opposition. The election of Mr. Barnard<br />
revealed, I think, how deep and strong the divisions remained inside the<br />
Labor Party. There have been changes of personalities, but the problems<br />
which confronted the Labor Party before the election remain with the sole<br />
exception that there has been a change of personalities. As for myself<br />
and my Government, we shall continue to strive to command the public<br />
support which currently holds us there.<br />
Q. I didn't understand what you meant about the divisions....<br />
That was the vote between Barnard and Cairns you are referring to?<br />
PM: I am not wishing to discount Mr. Barnard's abilities, but I<br />
think most observers, most objective observers, would have considered<br />
that there were several Members of the Labor Party who on Parliamentary<br />
form would have had a claim on the vote rather more strongly than Mr.<br />
Barnard, but it is not for me / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Q. Are you aware of the fact that Senator Willesee has been replaced<br />
in the Senat<br />
PM: No, I was not aware of that.<br />
Interjection: By Senator Murphy.<br />
P M. Yes, well, again I thirk that confirms the point I was trying to<br />
make that this after Senator Vlillesee had been so shortly in office that he<br />
should be rejected again reveals, I think, the divisions which exist, and the<br />
currents which are swirling around the personalities. Howeier, we have<br />
our problems; they -have theirs. We shall do our best to remain a Government<br />
and no doubt they will do their best to displace us.<br />
Q. Gould we ask you something, Sir, about -your New Zealand trip.<br />
From what has come back, you have been most reluctant to discuss economic<br />
issues. You made a big point of the fact that you were not ove r there<br />
specifically for that and that Mr. McEwen was going over afterwards.<br />
I was just wondering whether you could tell us whether there were any specific<br />
points of difficulty raised with you from official sources because there were<br />
a number of private criticisms of the operation of the trade agreement.<br />
PM: Well there weren't all that many private criticisms. There<br />
was the criticism expressed by Mr. Stock the Chairman of the Chamber<br />
of Commerce. On the other hand, I was given the most cordial welcome<br />
and reception by the Chamber of Commerce at Christchurch which was<br />
attended by representatives of the Chambers of Commerce of all other parts<br />
of the South Island. It was one of the agreeable surprises of the tour. I<br />
had been asked to meet the Christchurch Chamber of Commerce. I went<br />
along expecting to find twenty or thirty people of industry and commerce<br />
around the table and having a discussion with them. Instead of that, it was<br />
a very crowded and quite convivial gathering of estimable people from all<br />
over the South Island. They told me in the 179 years which we had<br />
celebrated just a few days before, I was the first Prime Minister to have<br />
ever visited the South Island. There were these comments of Mr. Stock<br />
as well as one or two editorials in the Press which came to my notice.<br />
I think some of my critics here in Australia would have been rather surprised<br />
to learn that in New Zealand some people think we are so smart that we<br />
in some way are able to score advantages over the New Zealanders. The<br />
point of substance, of course, is our hope that this agreement will work to<br />
the mutual advantage of both. countries. Australia has much to gain from a<br />
developing, prospering, strengthening New Zealand, as indeed they have<br />
from a strengthening, prospering Australia, and I said there that this<br />
agreement which, after all, is only about twelve months' old, could hardly<br />
have been said to have given full expression to its elements in so short a<br />
space of time, and particularly following a year in which Australia had been<br />
contending with the effects of very serious drought in two of our principal<br />
States that if this agreement in the longer haul was not working out to the<br />
saisfaction of one side or the other, then I was sure that the parties to<br />
it would approach it in a constructive and helpful spirit. I am sure that is<br />
the spi nit my colleague will carry with him to New Zealand when he goes<br />
there. I may say that in talking to members of the Government, I didn't<br />
find this same degree of concern expressed. The question of forest<br />
products is an important one with them, and I shall be mentioning that to<br />
Mr. McEwen, although I didn't discuss it in any detail with the Government<br />
there. The Deputy Prime Minister did tell me that the aspect which they<br />
regarded as of topical importance was this question of forest products.<br />
Altogether I may say, that the Prime Minister of New Zealand and myself / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( Mr. Holt Contd.)<br />
both felt we had derived great value from the visit and our two Governments<br />
and two countries. He has exchanged with me, even on the aircraft, the<br />
most cordial of messages. We were able to spend a lot of time together<br />
covering a wide range of subject matters in a most direct and intimate<br />
fashion. I did give to the press representatives who were accompanying<br />
me ap indication of several of the subject matters we discussed. It<br />
wasn't by any means an exhaustive list, but it ranged over a wide area both<br />
of domestic matters and of international matters of mutual interest. The<br />
overwhelming impression I bring back from New Zealand is the friendliness,<br />
warmth and goodwill towards Australia and towards, if I may say so, its<br />
Prime Minister. It struck all of us that there were quite spontaneous<br />
expressions of this wherever we went and I didn't see a sour face or hear<br />
a sour voice in the whole of my journeyings. On the contrary, people went<br />
out of their way to come and see us in what is not a demonstrative country,<br />
a little less demonstrative even than this undemonstrative country of<br />
Australia.<br />
Q. Did you arrange any further mutual visits wh-ile you were there?<br />
PM: I made it clear and public that there was an open invitation to<br />
Mr. Holyoake to come here with Mms. Holyoake whenever he would find it<br />
convenient to do so and I have suggested to him that such is the relationship<br />
between our two countries we should encourage more frequent visits by<br />
Ministers on -natters of mutual interest or even of particular concern to<br />
one country or the other and that we should not regard these as the kind of<br />
formal visit which occurs from other countries to Australia. In point of<br />
fact, it is no further indeed it is a good deal shorter from Canberra to<br />
W7ellington or Christchurch than it is from Canberra to Perth, and there is<br />
every good reason why Ministers from his Government should fly in and<br />
do a few days of business here and fly out again, and the same with my<br />
Ministers if that can be of advantage to us. I mentioned at the Parliamentary<br />
Luncheon given to me or rather the Government Luncheon given<br />
to me in the Parliament Buildings that we had already provided opportunities<br />
for our own Members of Parliament to visit New Zealand as one of the<br />
perquisites of off ice. Whether there will be reciprocity on that score remains<br />
to be seen, but I may say Mr. Holyoake and his Cabinet greeted very warmly<br />
my proposal about Anzac scholarships and immediately indicated that they<br />
wished to have a reciprocal arrangement going, and we will see how this<br />
works out. If it is as useful as I would expect k to be and successful as<br />
Iwould hope it to be, then we can enlarge on that if we both think that is<br />
desirable as time goes on.<br />
Q. Do you see any possibility of a move to help New Zealand in its<br />
balance of payments difficulties?<br />
PM: Well, no requests were put to me. We did give some assistance,<br />
as you may remember, not so long ago, but T gather that the Prime Minister<br />
and his colleagues are looking at these matters now in their Cabinet<br />
discussions.<br />
Q. Sir, have you had a preliminary report, or a final report yet,<br />
on this incident in Viet Nam in which the Australians were killed.<br />
PM: No, I did receive an expression of sympathy and regret from<br />
Mr. Holyoake as soon as he knew of the matter. It wasn't easy to get details<br />
at first, and I contacted Australia, of course, as soon as I had some word<br />
of the incident and was later supplied with the text of the two statements<br />
made by the respective Ministers for Defence in each country and I made<br />
a short comment myself while in New Zealand, which was appreciated by / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
( Mr. Holt contd.<br />
them. I spole on the ' phone again to Mr. Holyoake this morning and the<br />
first thing he said to me was another expression of his profound regret at<br />
what had occurred. He referred to the skill and efficiency for which the<br />
New Zealand artillery are noted. But both Ministers the Minister for<br />
Defence in New Zealand and ours have indicated that a full investigation is<br />
going forward into the incident and I don't think I can help you any further<br />
on it at this point.<br />
Q. Sir, is there likely to be a common approach between Australia<br />
and New Zealand to the possible entry of Britain into the Common Market?<br />
PM: Well, I don't think we have yet reached the stage where we know<br />
precisely what sort of timing or conditions would apply to a British entry.<br />
Both Australia and New Zealand have made it clear in the past that their<br />
industries could be affected New Zealand's, perhap4 more seriously<br />
than our own by British entry. The United Kingdom Government has<br />
maintained at all times that it would have regard to Commonwealth<br />
interests in any such approach, and there have been assurances given<br />
from various quarters that the special position of New Zealand would be<br />
safeguarded. Whether this would extend beyond a transitional phase has<br />
yet to be seen. We didn't go Into that matter in any detail or, indeed,<br />
discuss it more than superficially, because our two experts on this are<br />
Mr. McEwen and Mr. Marshall. They will be meeting again very<br />
shortly.<br />
Q. Could you just elaborate on that balance of payments question,<br />
Mr. Holt. You said there was no request for assistance at this stage<br />
but the Prime Minister and his colleagues were looking into the problem<br />
now. This doesn't rule out the possibility of an approach from New Zealand<br />
at this stage?<br />
PM: Well, I am not in a posi tion to anticipate what action the New<br />
Zealand Government may take. There are various ways in which a country<br />
seeks to redress a balance of payments problem, and no doubt these are<br />
being examined by them at the present time.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
