<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8743</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP LAUNCH OF TERRY AULICHS BOOK &quot; THE RIVERS END&quot; 26 NOVEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008743.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF TIlE PRIME MINISTER, TIlE lION P J KEATING, MP<br />
. AUNCI I OF TERRY AULICH'S BOOK " TIlE RIVER'S END"<br />
26 NOVEMBER 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well thank you very much I am quite happy to be associated on this occasion with<br />
Kerr publishing and most particularly with my friend and colleague, Terry Aulich.<br />
On this very novel occasion for the Parliament because we believe that this is the<br />
first novel written by a meniher of Parliament since Federation, which makes it<br />
something of an event.<br />
You have got to say one thing about the Labor Party we can breed all the<br />
varieties -we arc the entrepreneurs, the adventurers, the romantics of Australian<br />
politics. And in that high tradition we have produced Brother Aulich. He has<br />
brought to the public a very hiteresting novel. It is interesting because it is about<br />
something which is not quite a contemporary issue, but it is not that long ago that<br />
it was, a decade ago. The issue of the Franklin River and its possible damming,<br />
something which divided our national life which caused the fall of a Government<br />
in Tasmania. The first time that a Government actually took on an cnvironment<br />
issue in this country and of course changed Tasmania for cver, I won't say for ever,<br />
that is too big a claim, at least for the monient. But certainly from the quieter days<br />
of Tasmanian life, things changed when the Franklin and the Gordon-below-<br />
Franklin debate was on.<br />
The interesting thing about this is as described this book, not simply as fiction but<br />
as faction. Half fact, fiction, or fact rolled with fiction, or fiction rolled with fact.<br />
And Terry paints quite interesting pen sketches of some of the players, including<br />
Doug Lowe, then Premier, who Terry in the past used to describe to me as the sort<br />
of boy-ncxt-door type that every mother loved and that every mother wished her<br />
daughter to marry. Well that was a prctty big wrap for Doug, but it didn't do him<br />
much good politically when the crunch came.<br />
œ O/ TO'd 2-O'ON Z,: SI Z6" AON' 9 </p>
<p>2<br />
He lived through this period tumultuously. Of course, one has to know Tasmanian<br />
politics to understand just how tightly fought it is, within that H-are Clarke system<br />
and those multiple-member constituencies. People of thc same party campaign<br />
against one another, so it is all hamlet and village-political machination, inighting<br />
and thc rest. And I had much experience of this when I used to come to<br />
Tasmania as the Shadow Minister for Tasmania in the then Opposition in the<br />
1970s, and Terry was the person who used to take me around the State. Terry<br />
always had a good automobile under him and wc used to he likes the good<br />
things in life Terry and we dashed up and down Tasmania; Fingal, up the top,<br />
and one day Fight down thc full length of the State to two or three things, we were<br />
stopping at all these villages we will just stop in here, two drinks, be seen at the<br />
pub, say hello, out we go, back in the car and off again. He had this sort of death<br />
defying -struggle with the dreaded Michael Policy, who he shared a place with in<br />
the same constituency and it was the fox eyeing off the fox and how one would<br />
gamner support within this constituency. Now you can just imagine an issue like<br />
the Franklin River dropped into the middle of this minutia of political<br />
manoeuvrings that went on, and of course it was really something which was<br />
cathartic to the political system.<br />
What's nice about this book is that Tcrry has writtcn about it in a way that only<br />
somebody as involved as he was could write about it. Someone who actually<br />
knew about it, knew about all those little internecine battles, all those little<br />
jealousies, past rebukes never to be forgotten, all that sort of stuff. And he has it<br />
here woven into a story which I think tells a very nice tale about a big Australian<br />
national issue. That's a very good thing to do and of course it is a most<br />
unpretentious book, and that is in keeping with Terry himself who is certainly not<br />
a pretentious person. He is good humoured and he does like a laugh and he has<br />
that mocking style and all the time I have ever known hinm he has always sent up<br />
all the personalities around hinm and has never taken the whole thing all that<br />
seriously. Now that comes through, which is a very good way to be, a very good<br />
way to be, particularly in public life, and that comecs through in the book, and I<br />
mean there are just some very nice sort of this could only be written by an<br />
Australian as, " Sinbad was a born victim, he had a certain style which didn't go<br />
unnoticed." " There was a sudden intake of breath, a cross between a honk and a<br />
snort", it goes on, " she's a bit on the skittish side and that right fetlock is still<br />
troubling her", or, " you are seeing a lot of that McMillan bird" ( bird is an old word<br />
now in Australia) but " Kerry Wade said plonking his burai on my desk". I mean it<br />
is not reallIy James Joyce, but nor is it obl ique and distended l ike Patrick Wh ite.<br />
So, this is very readable and while it may not be knocking on thc door for a Booker<br />
prize, it's ccrtainly a very nicc piece of writing about Australia and the Australia<br />
that we all know.<br />
It is interesting that Terry has, it's one of a trilogy of books, he has two others<br />
completed and in the course of publication, and it's again quite interesting that<br />
somebody who has been involved in public life as much as he has has been able<br />
still to turn his mind to a subject like this and get himself published and have two<br />
œ O/ ZOdJ _ OON ZZ: GT Z 6AON* 9Z ' 113J1 </p>
<p>other bo~ ks at the ready as well. So, I think this is going to be a joy for many of<br />
us. particularly in political system and journalists, to read. Terry has had a bent for<br />
prose with poetry and writing over the years and I think that many of us who are<br />
ourselves victims of the systemn of politics will find this a really good read.<br />
So Terry, congratulations on putting it together, it is a very rcadablc book, it spins<br />
a very nice tale, it paints tremendous pcn portraits of the characters, Patrick<br />
[ Cennedy reads Ilike a refugee from the NSW Labor Party, but I[ don't know whcthcr<br />
that is true, and he certainly found his way around Tasmania. Congratulations<br />
again, Terry, I hope the book succeeds, it deserves to, it occupies a unique place in<br />
the history of this place and the fact that you are the first as we understand it, the<br />
first MP to have published a novel and not just one but three. Congratulations to<br />
McMillan an Australia publishing company for publishing it. Goad luck to all<br />
concerned. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
