<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7357</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/07/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007357.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 15 JULY 1988<br />
Monday 18 July is the 70th birthday of Nelson M~ andela.<br />
Tragically, as with so many of his other birthdays, he will<br />
be celebrating it in gaol.<br />
I would like to use the occasion to appeal once again to the<br />
South African Government to release unconditionally Mandela<br />
and the numerous other political prisoners who have been<br />
gaoled for their opposition to apartheid.<br />
The release of the prisoners would be an important gesture<br />
of goodwill by the South African Government and could have a<br />
role in laying the basis for negotiations leading to the<br />
peaceful abolition of apartheid and the establishment in<br />
South Africa of a just society.<br />
The situation in South Africa is tragic and will not endure<br />
indefinitely. It is in the interest of South'Africa and the<br />
world that it be resolved peacefully. Bold action by the<br />
South African Government, such as the release of<br />
Nelson Mandela, will be necessary to achieve this and would<br />
be applauded by Australia and other members of the<br />
international community.<br />
I have sent the following message to Nelson Mandela himself:<br />
" on the occasion of your 70th birthday please accept my<br />
personal best wishes and those of the Australian<br />
Government and people.<br />
In 1985, you described your period of imprisonment as<br />
" long, lonely, wasted years". In terms of their impact<br />
on world views about your people's suffering, however,<br />
your long, lonely years have not been wasted.<br />
Your years in gaol are a constant reminder to us of the<br />
abhorrent impact of apartheid, not only on you,<br />
personally, but also on the many lesser known people,<br />
including children, who continue to be gaoled and to<br />
suffer daily under that system. It is a tremendous<br />
tribute to you that, after so many years in gaol, you<br />
are still regarded by South African blacks as the symbol<br />
of their struggle for freedom.<br />
Your courage in withstanding the privation of the prison<br />
system and your determination to maintain your<br />
commitment to the freedom of your people, even at the<br />
expense of your own freedom, have been an inspiration<br />
not only in South Africa but to people throughout the<br />
world. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Your refusal to become embittered and your consistent<br />
willingness to negotiate with all parties the possible<br />
future of a free, democratic, non-racial South Africa<br />
are characteristics greatly admired here in Australia.<br />
The Australian Government is deeply concerned over the<br />
continuing polarisation of politics within South Africa,<br />
the banning of political groups, the constraints on free<br />
trade union activity, the muzzling of the press, and the<br />
detention of so many whose only offence is their<br />
courageous determination to strive for a better future<br />
for their people.<br />
As a first step towards achieving the political and<br />
social reconciliation that this will require, Australia,<br />
along with other members of the international community,<br />
has long been calling for the release of all political<br />
prisoners. That message was central to the Nassau<br />
Accord on Southern Africa, agreed by Commonwealth<br />
leaders in 1985 and was given the highest importance by<br />
the Eminent Persons Group.<br />
We will continue to call on the South African Government<br />
to release you unconditionally. Such action would be<br />
seen by the world as an act of hope and as a measure of<br />
the readiness of the South African authorities to take<br />
the necessary first steps away from confrontation and<br />
violence. For our part, Australia and Australians will continue to<br />
do what we can to impress on the South African<br />
Government the need to enter negotiations to put an end<br />
to apartheid. I was pleased to be able to talk about<br />
these and other matters with ANC President, Oliver<br />
Tambo, when he visited Australia in 1987.<br />
It is my sincere hope that you will be able to take part<br />
in such negotiations and to see the beginnings of real<br />
movement towards the goal for which you have worked so<br />
hard and given up so much.<br />
My support and sympathy go out to you and to the family<br />
and friends who you have been isolated for so long. I<br />
can assure you that many of us in Australia will be<br />
thinking of you and of the other political prisoners in<br />
South Africa on the day of your birthday." 369<br />
w-lize &gt;' 777711 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
