<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6662</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Report</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006662.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The ACTU sought information from Treasury and the EPAC<br />
Secretariat on a number of tax reform options, and<br />
with the agreement of the ACTU that information is made<br />
available to Summit participants.<br />
I </p>
<p>2<br />
Introduction<br />
This paper provides a preliminary analysis of the broad<br />
distributional erfects of a series of taxation options<br />
formulated by the ACTU. The analysis has been<br />
undertaken at the ACTU's request. The options<br />
considered include Approaches B and C of the draft<br />
White Paper Reform of the Australian Tax System,<br />
together with particular proposals' put forward by the<br />
ACTU.<br />
2. Methodology Distributional results have been obtained with the aid<br />
of the STATAX facility developed at the. Office of<br />
EPAC. STATAX is designed to provide a statistic called<br />
" cash gain" for households of a chosen type and within<br />
each of a series of weekly income ranges. The cash<br />
gain is simply the number of dollars per week<br />
households of the chosen type, within the given income<br />
range, would be better off ( or worse off if the cash<br />
gain figure is negative) on average if a particular<br />
proposed package of changes in taxation and benefit<br />
arrangements were to be introduced.<br />
The basic data used by STATAX is the individual<br />
household record file from the full-year 1984 Household<br />
Expenditure Survey ( HES) conducted by the Australian<br />
Bureau of Statistics ( for details see ABS, .1iM<br />
House-hold Expenditure Survey. Australia Preliminary,<br />
6529.0). Although HES was not designed to support an<br />
income-expenditure analysis of the STATAX type, it is<br />
the only official data source available which provides<br />
integrated up-to-date information on the details of the<br />
incomes and expenditures of a broadly representative<br />
sample of Australian households. The heavy reliance of<br />
STATAX on HES brings with it data problems which have<br />
been discussed widely in reports by the Australian<br />
Statistician, in the White Paper ( see Appendix 22-A)<br />
and in the media.<br />
In developing The STATAX methodology the Office of EPAC<br />
has explicitly recognised the deficiencies of the HES<br />
data for these purposes. These have been dealt with by<br />
implementing a set of corrections to the HES data, the<br />
effect of which is to calibrate incomes by major<br />
source, and expenditures by broad commodity group, to<br />
coincide in aggregate with the corresponding National<br />
Accounts aggregates. Full details of the basis for<br />
these corrections are provided in EPAC Papee' 85/ 3.<br />
( Note, however, that the particular correction factors<br />
provided there were preliminary, being based on only 6<br />
month data from HES and earlier National Accounts<br />
information current ones are available on request.) </p>
<p>While it is believed that these corrections have<br />
dramatically reduced the biases implicit in the raw lIES<br />
data, it is important to recognise that all such<br />
adjustments carry with them implicit distributional<br />
assumptions. It must also be recognised that the<br />
chances remain high of significant errors in any<br />
analyses based on HES data which link the income and<br />
expenditure information from the survey as explicitly<br />
as does STATAX.<br />
No data source exists that would permit an entirely<br />
accurate estimation of the detailed distributional<br />
effects of the types of radical tax changes in the<br />
options considered here. At best the results presented<br />
here, and others of their kind, can provide a broad<br />
picture of the distributional effects of changes in<br />
taxation and benefit arrangements. Nevertheless, the<br />
Office is satisfied that the STATAX methodology does<br />
reliably provide such broad distributional information.<br />
STATAX calls on the results of the TAXIO model,<br />
developed by the Treasury, to obtain the effects of<br />
changes in the Wholesale Sales Tax on the prices of<br />
commodities at the factory gate. The TAXIO model is<br />
also used to provide estimates of revenues derived from<br />
consumption taxes applied to commodities and services<br />
outside private final consumption expenditure taxes<br />
on business inputs and on investment goods for<br />
instance. This reflects the fact that STATAX itself is<br />
concerned primarily with private final consumption<br />
expenditure, as reflected in the expenditures of<br />
individual households.<br />
Estimates of the distributional impact of<br />
base-broadening measures have been formed in a manner<br />
consistent with that used in the White Paper ( Sections<br />
22A. 15 to 22A. 32), although the White Paper methodology<br />
has been modified to reflect the household orientation<br />
of the STATAX facility. ( White Paper estimates were<br />
based on individuals.) Consistent with the White Paper,<br />
the methodology used here includes an assumption that,<br />
at higher income levels, some of the incidence of the<br />
tax on fringe benefits will be shifted back to the<br />
employee.<br />
The estimates of revenue yields from the imposition of<br />
a BBCT, of the cost to revenue of modifications to or<br />
elimination of the WST, of the cost to revenue of<br />
compensation measures and of the revenue yield from the<br />
existing personal income tax schedule are consistent<br />
with estimates published in the White Paper and in the<br />
1984-85 Budget Papers.<br />
A separate paper prepared by the Treasury in-response<br />
to the ACTU request provides details of the revenue<br />
yields and CPI effects of a range of options. ( Note<br />
however that the numbering of the * ACTU options in the </p>
<p>Treasury paper does not correspond to that used in this<br />
paper)<br />
Full details of the STATAX methodology are provided in<br />
EPAC Paper 85/ 3, Quantifviniz the Distributional Effects<br />
of Alternative Tax Options A report of Proxress,<br />
March 1985. That paper considers in some detail<br />
limitations of the HES data and of the STATAX<br />
methodology. This paper should be read in conjunction<br />
with that discussion to put the distributional results<br />
in their proper context.<br />
It is important to recognise that the results provided<br />
below from the STATAX facility do not make any<br />
provision for behavioural responses to the proposed tax<br />
changes. Thus the possibility that consumers may<br />
change their expenditure patterns, that work effort may<br />
change or that the balance between consumption and<br />
saving may alter is ignored. Such responses may well<br />
be significant but the objective of the present<br />
analysis ( in keeping with that of the White Paper and<br />
other analyses available to date) is to concentrate on<br />
the immediate impact of the changes.<br />
3. Overview and Interpretation of the Results<br />
Two household types have been chosen for analysis at<br />
this stage. In line with figures presented in the White<br />
Paper, these are households whose principal source of<br />
income is wages and salaries, and households whose<br />
principal source of income is the age or wife pension.<br />
In most cases, a table is provided which presents, for<br />
each of several income ranges, estimates of:<br />
the change in the commodity tax applicable to<br />
expenditures by households in that income range;<br />
the change in the personal income tax payable;<br />
the additional personal income tax payable<br />
resulting from measures intended to broaden the<br />
income tax base;<br />
Examples of base-broadening measures include<br />
taxing non-cash fringe benefits, taxing<br />
capital gains and eliminating negative<br />
gearing of rental property investments. Such<br />
base-broadening measures form the basis for<br />
Approach A of the White Paper-,<br />
the compensation payable as the result of<br />
increased pensions or improvements to other<br />
government benefits;<br />
the cash gain.<br />
Positive entries in the tables indicate an amount by<br />
which households in the given income range would be </p>
<p>better off in cash terms, negative entries an amount by<br />
which they would be worse off. Summing the entries<br />
across a particular row of the table for commodity tax<br />
change ( CT change), personal income tax change arising<br />
from new tax scales ( PIT change), personal income tax<br />
change arising from base-broadening measures ( PIT BB),<br />
compensation payments ( compensation) gives, for<br />
households on average in that income range, the cash<br />
gain arising from the proposed package of changes in<br />
commodity taxation, personal income taxation and<br />
government benefit arrangements. All figures in the<br />
tables are expressed in 1984-85 dollars per week.<br />
Consider the seon row of Table 2 for illustrative<br />
purposes. Table 2 provides results for the impact of<br />
the White Paper Approach C on households whose<br />
principal source of income ( this will not generally be<br />
the only source of income to such households, of<br />
course) is wages and salaries. The second row relates<br />
to such households ; whose 1984-85 incomefell in the<br />
range $ 301 to $ 350 per week. The results show that, on<br />
average, these households will<br />
pay an extra $ 19.86 per week as the result of the<br />
impact of the BBCT included in Approach C on their<br />
expenditures on commodities and services<br />
receive a personal income tax cut of $ 20.60 per<br />
week incur additional income tax of $ 0.07 per week as<br />
the result of the impact of base-broadening<br />
measures included in Approach C on their personal<br />
income tax liability<br />
receive compensation in the form of higher<br />
government benefit payments to the tune of $ 2.67<br />
per week.<br />
The net result of these changes is that the cash gain<br />
for households of this type in the $ 301-$ 350 per we * ek<br />
income range is $ 3.33 per week. That is the estimate<br />
of the amount by which such households would be made<br />
better off by Approach C.<br />
In interpreting the estimates provided in the tables,<br />
it is important to recognise that all the figures<br />
provided are group averages. That is, they provide an<br />
estimate which applies on average within the specified<br />
income range and for households of the specified type.<br />
Such aggregation is necessary in view of quite<br />
significant variation within income classes. Equally,<br />
however, it is important not to lose sight of.. this<br />
underlying variation. In particular, household<br />
structures will impact significantly on the access to<br />
and need for compensation within lower income groups,<br />
while the impact of base-broadening measures will vary<br />
sharply amongst higher income earners reflecting </p>
<p>individual household access to and exploitation of the<br />
underlying income sources and taxation avoidance<br />
measures. In the case of the 3 specific ACTU Options, the precise<br />
details of the compensation packages including income<br />
tax Cuts, have not yet been finalised ( being depenaent<br />
on further analysis Of the runs so far conducted).<br />
These tables do not therefore include figures relating<br />
to changed income tax scales and compensation. The<br />
last column " preliminary net gains' refers only to the<br />
impact of the changes to indirect taxes and base<br />
broadening.<br />
4. Results 4.1 White Paper ApproachC<br />
Tables 1 and 2 provide estimates of the distributional<br />
impact on age-wife pensioner households and wage and<br />
salary earner households respectively of the White<br />
Paper approach C options.<br />
Over4ll, pensioner households are estimated to be $ 4.80<br />
per week better off if Approach C were to be<br />
implemented, while the corresponding cash gain estimate<br />
for all wage and salary earner households is $ 6.25.*<br />
There is relatively little distributional variation for<br />
pensioner households, with those in the $ 121-$ 150 per<br />
week income range experiencing the largest estimated<br />
cash gain ($ 6.37 per week) while the least ($ 2.36 per<br />
week) is experienced by those in the $ 181-$ 210 per week<br />
income range.<br />
The distributional pattern of cash gains over pensioner<br />
households is influenced to a considerable degree by<br />
household composi * tion effects and by the age structure<br />
of households. ( These factors underlie the variation in<br />
expenditure patterns over income ranges.) Since<br />
pensioner households are in receipt of relatively low<br />
levels of taxable income, they do not benefit to any<br />
great degree from the shift to the Approach C income<br />
tax schedule. Similarly, the incomes Of these<br />
households are too low for base-broadening measures to<br />
have any impact upon them as a group. Consequently,<br />
their cash gains are dominated by compensation payments<br />
offsetting the increased Cost Of thei'r expendituros<br />
arising from the imposition of the BBCT.<br />
A more varied distributional pattern is evident for<br />
wage and salary earner households under Apprpoach C.<br />
Cash gains rise steadily from $ 2.43 per week for such<br />
households * in the $ 271-$ 300 per week income range to<br />
$ 12.74 per week-for the $ 741-$ 930 per week range. This<br />
mainly reflects the interaction of the increased<br />
outlays on expenditure with the benefits of the reduced<br />
income tax payments, compensation being relatively </p>
<p>7',<br />
unimportant for all but the lowest income groups<br />
amongst these households. Base-broadening measures<br />
begin to bite significantly above the $ 741-$ 930 per<br />
week income range. The effect is for the estimated<br />
cash gain to fall away rapidly above this level of<br />
income, with wage and salary earner households on<br />
average experiencing a cash loss of $ 314.86 per week in<br />
the over $ 1250 per week income range. As noted<br />
earlier. this reflects the fact that high income<br />
households tend to have the greatest access to income<br />
sources affected by base-broadening measures.<br />
4.2 White Paper Approach 8<br />
Estimates of the distributional impact. of the White<br />
Paper Approach B are shown for age-wife pensioner<br />
households in Table 3. and for wage and salary earner<br />
households in Table, 4. For both household types, the<br />
overall impact of the proposals, as measured by the.<br />
cash gain, is much smaller than for Approach C.<br />
In the case of pensioner households, the variation in<br />
the impact on particular income ranges is similar to<br />
that evident in the case of Approach C. Aside from the<br />
highest income households, however, wage and salary<br />
earner households show much less variation in cash gain<br />
over income range under Approach B than was evident for<br />
Approach C. This occurs because, with a much lower<br />
rate BBCT, after allowing for the removal of the WST,<br />
relatively little revenue is available to provide for<br />
income tax cuts. The benefits of the new income tax<br />
schedule being significantly smaller, the general<br />
effect is to compress the variation in cash gain over<br />
income ranges. For the highest income ranges, the<br />
income tax benefits are not sufficient to offset the<br />
impact of base-broadening measures to a significant<br />
degree. As a result, these groups suffer cash losses,<br />
the magnitude of which ($ 59.90 per week) is quite large<br />
for the top income range.<br />
4j, 3 ACTU Options I to3<br />
The remaining options considered are not as fully<br />
specified as those ' examined above, in that no change to<br />
the personal income tax schedules or in the rates of<br />
government benefits is proposed. Consequently,<br />
estimates are provided only of the impact of proposed<br />
consumption taxes and base-broadening measures. In<br />
each case. the base-broadening measures included are<br />
the same as those of the White Paper approaches.<br />
ACTU Option 1 involves the elimination of ' the-WST, the<br />
imposition of a 5 ' per cent BBCT on the same base as in<br />
the White Paper. together with base-broadening<br />
measures. Estimates of the distributional impact of<br />
this option are shown in Tables .5 and 6 for age-wife<br />
pensioner households and for wage and salary earner<br />
households respectively. The main noteworthy feature </p>
<p>of these results is the extent to which the<br />
distributional pattern which emerges is dominated by<br />
the impact or the base-broadening measures.<br />
ACTU Option 2, results for which are provided in Tables<br />
7 and 8, involves the elimination of the WST, the<br />
imposition of a 7 per cent BBCT on the White Paper<br />
base, the imposition of a 12 per cent UST on selected<br />
(" luxury") items predominantly those currently<br />
subject to WST at 32 per cent, together with motor<br />
vehicles and parts and the base-broadening measures.<br />
ACTU Option 3 involves a restructuring of the WST to a<br />
uniform rate of 5 per cent, with the imposition of a<br />
per cent BBCT on the White Paper base and<br />
base-broadening measures. Results for this option are<br />
provided in Tables 9 and<br />
41.4 Exemptions<br />
Tables 11 and 12 provide estimates of the<br />
distributional impact of two types of exemptions from<br />
the base for the BBCT.-The tables show, for th~ e<br />
specified household type and for each of the income<br />
ranges, the amount per week) by which the cash gain<br />
shown in Tables 1 or 2, as is appropriate, would be<br />
increased by the specified exemption.<br />
In the first case, all food is exempted from the BBCT,<br />
while in the second the exempt commodities are food,<br />
clothing, electricity and gas.<br />
Exempting food from the BBCT base clearly benefits<br />
higher income households more in dollar terms than<br />
lower income households. ( See pages 119-121 of the<br />
White Paper for a discussion of the general issue of<br />
exemptions.) Exempting clothing, electricity and gas in addition to<br />
food provides a similar, though accentua * ted<br />
distributional picture by comparison with the exemption<br />
of food only. However, examination of the ratio of the<br />
columns for the two exemption types reveals the strong<br />
regressive element of the wider set of exemptions<br />
relative to that of food only. For the lowest wage and<br />
salary income range, this ratio is about 1.69. In<br />
general, the ratio rises progressively with income to<br />
2.17 for the highest income range. * The implication is<br />
that the wider set of exemptions confers a cash benefit<br />
which is greater than that for the exemption of food<br />
only by a factor of 1.69 for the lowest income<br />
households. For the highest income households the,<br />
wider set of exemptions confers a benefit 2.117 times<br />
greater than that for food only. In this sense, the<br />
wider set of exemptions confers a benefit that rises<br />
sharply with increasing income.. </p>
<p>Concluding Remarks<br />
The paper has provided preliminary estimates Of the<br />
distributional impact of a range of alternative tax<br />
packages put forward for analysis by the ACTU. The<br />
options encompassed by the tested packages are far from<br />
comprehensive but should usefully provide an overall<br />
feel for the distributional Consequences Of tax-benefit<br />
change. The results also serve to illustrate the<br />
capabilities of,, the STATAX facility developed by the<br />
Office of EPAC and may therefore assist the ACTU in<br />
formulating requests to the Office for further work.<br />
Results have been obtained to date only for two main<br />
household types age-wife pensioner and wage and<br />
salary earner households. The STATAX facility has the<br />
capability to provide results for a range of other<br />
household types, some of which may well be of interest.<br />
It must be emphasised that the figures provided here<br />
are estimates and' no more than that. Considerable<br />
uncertainty is attached to them as with any estimates.<br />
No data source is available which will provide a more<br />
reliable assessment of the distributional impact of the<br />
major taxation-changes currently under consideration.<br />
Nevertheless, the estimates presented here should not<br />
be regarded as providing more than a broad picture of<br />
the distributional impact of tax change proposals.<br />
Office of EPAC<br />
June, 1985 </p>
<p>TABLE I<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Option C Age-wife Pensioners<br />
By Household Income Class<br />
Income Range $ pw CT change $ pu PIT change $ pw PIT BB $ pw Cornp pu Cash Gain $ pw<br />
0-120 -8.28 0.95 0.00 9.79 2.46<br />
121-150 -9.81 6.21 0.00 9.96 6.37<br />
151-180 -12.55 3.47 0.00 13.56 4.48<br />
181-210 -14.57 0.96 0.00 15.97 2.36<br />
211-210 -15.00 3.99 0.00 16.88 5.87<br />
Total -11.98 3.64 0.00 13.14 4.80<br />
TABLE 2<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Option C for Wage and Salary Earners<br />
By household income class<br />
Income CT PIT PIT Compensation Cash<br />
Range change change BB Gain<br />
Spy pw $ pw $ pw $ pw tpw<br />
271-300 -18.54 16.53 0.00 4.44 2.43<br />
301-350 -19.86 20.60 -0.07 2.67 3.33<br />
351-425 -22.54 24.47 -0.21 3.22 4.95<br />
426-510 -25.34 29.07 -0.43 3.91 7.20<br />
511-615 -28.08 35.00 -0.80 3.30 9.42<br />
616-7.40 -29.54 41 .80 -3.45 3.02 11.83<br />
741-930 -35.91 51.61 -6.14 3.17 12.74<br />
931-1250 -42.44 67.07 -18.76 3.38 9.25<br />
&gt; 1250 -54.38 97.65 -81.77 3.64 -34.86<br />
Total -30.09 40.48 -7.57 3.43 6.25<br />
Option C as in the White Paper.<br />
CT: net commodity taxes ( BBCT, wholesale, and<br />
excise). PIT: Personal income tax on current base.<br />
PIT BB: Personal tax on additional income from base<br />
broadening.<br />
Notes: </p>
<p>Income Range py TABLE 3<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Option B Ago-Wife Pensioners<br />
By household income class<br />
CT PIT PIT Compensation<br />
change change BB<br />
$ pw $ py $ pypy Cah Gain pw<br />
0-120 -2.58 0.93 0.00 2.12 0.417<br />
121-150 -2.90 3.441 0.00 2.14 2.68<br />
151-180 -2.941 1.31 0.00 2.97 1.341<br />
181-210 -41.241 0.418 0.00 3.417 -0.29<br />
211-2410 -41.00 2.87 0.00 3.67 2.541<br />
Total -3.30 2.05 0.00D 2.841 1.59<br />
TABLE 11<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Option B Wage and Salary Earners<br />
By household income class<br />
Income CT PIT PIT Compensation Cash<br />
Range change change BB Gain<br />
spy $ pw * pw Spy Spy Spy<br />
271-300 -11.55 5.50 0.00 1.19 2.141<br />
301-350 -5.07 6.65 -0.08 0.93 2.413<br />
351-1125 -5.51 7.91 -0.22 1.12 3.27<br />
426-510 -6.00 11.00 -0.116 1.25. 5.79<br />
511-615 -6.119 11.15 -0.85 1.10 7.91<br />
616-7110 -5.90 15.82 -3.66 1.01 7.27<br />
7411-930 -7.67 20.15 -6.50 0.99 6.97<br />
931-1250 -8.77 26.72 -19.86 1.05 -0.86<br />
&gt; 1250 -10.86 36.55 -86.58 0.98 -59.90<br />
Total -6.66 15.110 -8.02 1.06 1.78<br />
Notes: Option B as in White Paper<br />
CT: net commodity taxes ( BBCT, wholesale, and<br />
excise). PIT: Personal income tax on current base.<br />
PIT BB: Personal tax on additional income from base<br />
broadening. </p>
<p>TABLE<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
ACTU Option 1 for Age-wife Pensioners<br />
Current Income Tax Scale<br />
By household income class<br />
CT' PIT<br />
change BB<br />
$ pw $ pw Preliminary<br />
Net Gain<br />
$ pw<br />
0-120 -1.95 0.00 -1.95<br />
121-150 -1.83 0.00 -1.83<br />
151-180 -1.67 0.00 -1.67<br />
181-210 -2.93 0.00 -2.93<br />
211-240 -2.74 0.00 -2.74<br />
Total -2.. 21 0.00 -2.21<br />
TABLE 6<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
ACTU 1 Wage Salary with Current income tax scales<br />
By household income class<br />
CT PIT<br />
change BB<br />
$ pw $ pw Preliminary Net Gain<br />
$ pw<br />
271-300 -0.48 0.00 -0.48<br />
301-350 -0.99 -0.07 -1.06<br />
351-425 -1.20 -0.21 -1.41<br />
426-510 -0.97 -0.43 -1.40<br />
511-615 -1.22 -0.80 -2.02<br />
616-740 0.39 -3.45 -3.06<br />
741-930 -0.57 -6.14 -6.71<br />
931-1250 0.15 -18.76 -18.61<br />
&gt; 1250 -0.99 -8.1.77 -82.76<br />
Total -0.68 0.00 -7.57 0.00 -8.25<br />
Notes: ACTU Option 1 involves no change in the personal<br />
income tax schedule; broadening of the income tax<br />
base ( no impact estimated for pensioners); 5% BBCT;<br />
and no wholesale sales tax.<br />
CT: net commodity taxes ( BBCT, wholesale, and<br />
excise). PIT: Personal income tax on current base.<br />
PIT BB: Personal tax on additional income from base<br />
broadening.<br />
Income Range $ pw<br />
Income Range $ pw </p>
<p>TABLE 7<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
ACT, 2 with current Income Tax for Age-wife Pensioners<br />
By Household Income Class<br />
CT PIT<br />
change BB<br />
$ pw $ pw Preliminary<br />
Net Gain<br />
$ pw<br />
0-120 -4.05 0.00 -4.05<br />
121-150 -4.82 0.00 -4.82<br />
151-180 -5.99 0.00 -5.99<br />
181-210 -7.17 0.00 -7.17<br />
211-240 -7.40 0.00 -7.40<br />
Total -5.86 0.00 -5.86<br />
TABLE 8<br />
Preliminary Anal-ysis of Tax Options<br />
ACTU 2 for Wage Salary Earners with Current Tax Scales<br />
CT PIT<br />
change BB<br />
$ pw $ pw<br />
-7.92<br />
-8.68<br />
-9.55<br />
-10.79<br />
-11.75<br />
-12.22<br />
-15.30<br />
-18.27<br />
-22.77 0.00<br />
-0.07<br />
-0.21<br />
-0.43<br />
-0.80<br />
-3.45<br />
-6.14<br />
-18.76<br />
-81.77 Preliminary Net Gain<br />
$ pw<br />
-7.92<br />
-8.75<br />
-9.76<br />
-11.22<br />
-12.55<br />
-15.67<br />
-21.44<br />
-37.03<br />
-104.54<br />
Total -12.76 -7.57 -20.33<br />
ACTU Option 2 involves no change in the personal<br />
income tax schedule; broadening of the income tax<br />
( no impact estimated for pensioners); 7% BBCT; 12%<br />
wholesale sales tax on selected items.<br />
CT: net commodity taxes ( BBCT, wholesale, and<br />
excise). PIT: Personal income tax on current base.<br />
PIT BB: Personal tax on additional income from base<br />
broadening.<br />
Income Range $ pw<br />
Income Range $ pw<br />
271-300<br />
301-350<br />
351-425<br />
426-510<br />
511-615<br />
616-740<br />
741-930<br />
931-1250<br />
&gt; 1250<br />
Notes: </p>
<p>TABLE 9<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
ACTU 3 Age-Vito Pensioners with Current income tax scales<br />
CT PIT<br />
change BB<br />
Spw Spw Preliminary Net Gain<br />
$ pw<br />
0-120 -6.25 0.00 -6.25<br />
121-150 -7.51 0.00 -7.51<br />
151-180 -9.53 0.00 -9.53<br />
181-210 -11.26 0.00 -11.26<br />
211-240 -13.06 0.00 -13.06<br />
Total -9.17 0.00 -9.17<br />
TABLE<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
ACTU 3 W&amp; S Current income tax scales<br />
Income CT PIT Preliminary<br />
Range change BB Net Gain<br />
$ pw $ pw $ pw # pw<br />
271-300 -11.92 0.00 -11.92<br />
301-350 -14.01 -0.07 -14.08<br />
351-425 -15.96 -0.21 -16.17<br />
426-510 -18.00 -0.43 -18.43<br />
511-615 -20.12 -0.80 -20.92<br />
616-740 -20.49 -3.45 -23.94<br />
741-930 -24.83 -6.14 -30.97<br />
931-1250 -34.50 -18.76 -53.26<br />
&gt; 1250 -30.10 -81.77 -111.87<br />
Total -12.27 -7.57 -19.84<br />
Notes: ACTU 3 involves a 10% BBCT and a 5% wholesale sale<br />
tax CT: net commodity taxes ( BBCT, wholesale, and<br />
excise). PIT: Personal income tax on current base.<br />
PIT BB: Personal tax on additional income from base<br />
broadening.<br />
Income Range $ pw </p>
<p>TABLE. 11<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Effects of Different Exemption Struotures under<br />
Age-Wife Pensioners<br />
Cash Gain by Household Income Class<br />
Gain From.<br />
Food Exemption Gain from<br />
Food/ Clothing/ Utilities<br />
Exemption<br />
0-120 2.61 3.91 1.50<br />
121-150 2.53 3.95 1.56<br />
151-180 3.87 6.415 1.67<br />
181-210 4.53 6.941 1.53<br />
211-2410 1.93 7.741 1.57<br />
Total 3.66 5.76 1.57<br />
TABLE 12<br />
Preliminary Analysis of Tax Options<br />
Effects of Different Exemption Structures under Option C<br />
Wage and Salary Earners<br />
Cash Gain by Household Income Class<br />
Income Gain from Gain from Ratio of<br />
Range Food Exemption Food/ Clothing/ Utilities the two<br />
Exemption Gains<br />
271-300 41.53 7.66 1.69<br />
301-350 41.641 7.61 1.641<br />
351-4125 5.411 8.90 1<br />
1126-510 5.86 10.08 1.72.<br />
511-615 6.30 10.85 1.72<br />
6 16-74o0 6.30 11.13 1.77<br />
7411-930 7.211 141.31 1.85<br />
931-1250 8.19 16.16 1.97<br />
&gt; 1250 9.01 .19.52 2.17<br />
Total 6.410 ' 11.65 1.82<br />
Notes: These figures relate solely to the exemption of the items<br />
specified; as such they would involve significant revenue cost<br />
unless accompanied by other revenue items. Figures are<br />
presented simply to indicate the incidence of the tax on these<br />
items as background to consideration of the possibility of<br />
exempting them from the base.<br />
Income<br />
Range Option C<br />
Ratio of<br />
the two<br />
Gains </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
