<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6700</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE ALP POST-BUDGET BREAKFAST, MELBOURNE, 21 AUGUST 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006700.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Check against<br />
DeliveryJj) AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER TO THE ALP POST-BUDGET BREAKFAST<br />
MELBOURNE 21 AUGUST 1985<br />
LAST NIGHT PAUL KEATING DELIVERED OUR THIRD BUDGET.<br />
LIKE OUR FIRST TWO BUDGETS, IT IS A BUDGET FOR JOBS AND<br />
GROWTH JOBS FOR TODAY AND JOBS FOR THE LONG TERM,<br />
IT IS A BUDGET WITH A CLEAR DIRECTION, CONSISTENT WITH<br />
OUR OVERALL ECONOMIC STRATEGY,<br />
ANn IT IR A RIInFT nF RFFRM IN PAPTWIII AP PFFAM nA<br />
OUR PROGRAMS IOR YUUNG PEOPLE SO AS 10 ADDRESS THL MAJOR<br />
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL ISSUE OF OUR TIME-YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
AND DISILLUSIONMENT#<br />
BUT, THIS IS AN HISTORIC BUDGET IN ANOTHER QUITE FUNDAMENTAL<br />
SENSE. THIS BUDGET HANDSOMELY FULFILS THE STRINGENT TRILOGY<br />
OF FISCAL COMMITMENTS MADE IN THE LAST ELECTION CAMPAIGN.<br />
COMMITMENTS WHICH NO OTHER GOVERNMENT HAS EVER HAD THE<br />
CONFIDENCE TO MAKEj COMMITMENTS WHICH THE SCEPTICS SAID<br />
COULD NOT BE FULFILLED. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
IN PLEDGING THAT WE WOULD NOT INCREASE TAX REVENUE, AND<br />
WOULD REDUCE SPENDING AND THE DEFICIT, IN PROPORTION TO<br />
GDP, WE SET OURSELVES CONDITIONS WHICH HAVE ONLY BEEN MET<br />
TWICE BEFORE IN THE PAST QUARTER CENTUR~ Y BUT WE MET THEM.<br />
IN ADDING TO THESE COMMITMENTS THE FURTHER UNDERTAKING TO<br />
REDUCE THE DEFICIT IN MONEY TERMS FOR 1985-86, WE SET<br />
OURSELVES CONDITIONS WHICH HAD NOT BEEN MET FOR SIXTEEN<br />
YEARS BUT WE MET THEM@<br />
IT IS WORTH RECALLING THE RATIONALE FOR THAT UNPRECEDENTED<br />
SET OF COMMITMENTS AND THE ECONOMIC POLICY CONTEXT IN WHICH<br />
THEY ARE SET.<br />
CAST YOUR MIND BACK TO THE EARLY MONTHS OF 1983.<br />
AUSTRALIA HAD ENDURED SEVEN LONG YEARS OF LIBERAL RULE,<br />
RULE BASED ON CONFRONTATION AND DIVISION WHICH REAPED A<br />
DEBILITATING WAGE-PRICE SPIRAL AND ECONOMIC STAGNATION.<br />
RULE WHICH EARNED FOR JOHN HOWARD * THE DUBIOUS HONOUR OF BEING<br />
THE ONLY TREASURER IN AUSTRALIA'S HISTORY TO* PRESIDE OVER<br />
BOTH DOUBLE-DIGIT INFLATION AND DOUBLE-DIGIT UNEMPLOYMENT.<br />
THEIR APPROACH SHARPLY ESCALATED REAL UNIT LABOUR COSTS AND<br />
DROVE THE PROFIT SHARE, IN THE SECOND HALF OF 1982, DOWN TO<br />
A RECORD LOW OF LESS THAN 12 PER CENT. s60/ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THEIR APPROACH DESTROYED OUR INTERNATIONAL COMPETITIVENESS@<br />
IT REAPED A WHIRLWIND OF INDUSTRIAL D[ SLOCATION AND<br />
DISHARMONY. AS THEY STROVE TO FIGHT INFLATION WITHOUT AN INCOMES POLICY<br />
BY HOLDING THE EXCHANGE RATE ARTIFICIALLY HIGH, THEY WENT<br />
CLOSE TO BREAKING THE BACK OF OUR GREAT MANUFACTURING,<br />
MINING AND RURAL INDUSTRIES.<br />
OVER THE 7 YEARS OF LIBERAL RULE, NON-FARM GDP AVERAGED<br />
GROWTH OF ONLY 2.4 PERCENT PER ANNUM. EMPLOYM'ENT CREPT UP<br />
AT AN AVERAGE RATE WELL BELOW THE GROWTH IN THE LABOUR FORCE<br />
AS A RESULT, UNEMPLOYMENT ROSE INEXORABLY, IN EARLY 1983,<br />
MOST COMMENTATORS THOUGHT THAT THERE WAS LITTLE PROSPECT OF<br />
ACHIEVING SUSTAINED GROWTH AT A PACE FAST ENOUGH TO STOP<br />
TIIE RISE OF UNEMPLOYMENT, LET ALONE TO REDUCE THE DOLE QUEUES,<br />
WE PROMISED IN 1983 TO SEEK RECONCILIATION AND CONSENSUSTO<br />
GET AUSTRALIANS WORKING TOGETHER AGAIN,<br />
WE BROUGHT To GOVERNMENT AN. ECONOMIC POLICY BASED ON. THE<br />
ACCORD, PROGRESSIVELY LESS STIMULATORY FISCAL POLICY, AND<br />
RESPONSIBLE MONETARY POLICY. ISI/ 14 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
WE SET OURSELVES SEVERAL INTER-RELATED GOALS: TO CREATE<br />
HALF A MILLION JOBS IN OUR FIRST THREE YEARS; TO REDUCE<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLAT ION SIMULTANEOUSLY; PERMANENTLY<br />
TO IMPROVE OUR LONG-TERM GROWTH PERFORMANCE BY<br />
CORRECTING STRUCTURAL WEAKNESSES; AND PROGRESSIVELY TO<br />
ACHIEVE A MORE JUST, MORE EQUITABLE SOCIETY.<br />
OUR APPROACH -AND IN PARTICULAR THE EMPHASIS WHICH WE<br />
PLACED ON PRICES AND INCOMES POLICY WAS FRAMED IN<br />
RECOGNITION OF THE ENVIRONMENT WITHIN WHI CH ANY AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE TO WORK.<br />
AND I BELIEVE THAT AUSTRALIANS CAN BE PROUD OIF THE FACI<br />
THAT, TOGETHER, WE HAVE MADE SO MUCH PROGRESS TOWARDS<br />
ACHIEVING THESE GOALS.<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS EXPERIENCED ONE OF THE STRONGEST RECOVERIES<br />
OF ALL THE OECD COUNTRIES ALREADY 10 PER CENT GROWTH IN<br />
TWO YEARS.<br />
AND WE ARE LOOKING TO A FURTHER FIVE PER CENT REAL NON-FARM<br />
GROWTH IN 1586-FIVE PER CENT GROWTH IN AUSTRALIA WHILE<br />
THE OECD IS ONLY EXPECTING ABOUT 3 PER CENT FOR THE WORLD'iS<br />
MAJOR INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES.<br />
THE STRONG GROWTH HAS BEEN THE KEY TO THE 4110,000 NEW JOBS<br />
THAT HAVE BEEN CREATED IN AUSTRALIA SINCE THE NATIONAL<br />
ECONOMIC SUMMIT CONFERENCE IN4 APRIL, 1983. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
IN THIS BUDGET WE HAVE REDUCED THE GROWTH OF REAL OUTLAYS<br />
TO 1.3 PERCENT, THE LOWEST IN 6 YEARS. AND EVEN MORE<br />
IMPRESSIVELY, THIS BUDGET HAS THE LOWEST NOMINAL GROWTH<br />
OF OUTLAYS SINCE 1968-69..<br />
WITH NO INCREASE IN TAX REVENUES AS A PROPORTION OF GDP<br />
WE HAVE, IN THIS BUDGET, REDUCED THE DEFICIT TO<br />
$ 4.9 BILLION A CUT OF $ 1.8 BILLION.<br />
THIS YEAR'S DEFICIT REPRESENTS 2 .1 PERCENT OF GDJP,<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY LESS THAN HALF THE PROSPECTIVE RATIO THAT<br />
WE INHERITED EARLY IN 1983.<br />
AS A RESULT THE GROSS BOND SALES TO THE PRIVATE SECTOR<br />
THIS YEAR ARE EXPECTED TO AMOUNT TO ONLY $ 5 BILLION,<br />
COMiAflED TO $ 7.6 DILL-ION LACT V&amp; An. AND TWAT S5 DILLIONI<br />
INCLUDES $ 3 BILLION OF REFINANCING OF MATURING SECURITIES.<br />
IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE CUTBACK IN STATE AUTHORITIES' BORROWING<br />
PROGRAMS NEGOTIATED WITH THE PREMIERS IN MAY, THIS BUDGET<br />
WILL PERMIT A SHARP REDUCTION IN THE GROSS PUBLIC SECTOR<br />
BORROWING REQUIREMENT IN 1985-860<br />
SUCH A REDUCTION WILL HELP TO REDUCE PRESSURES ON REAL INTEREST<br />
RATES FROM THIS SOURCE AND HELP TO BRING MONETARY AND FISCAL<br />
POLICY INTO BETTER BALANCE.<br />
THIS REDUCTION WILL HELP TO UNDERPIN DOMESTIC INVESTMENT<br />
AND CREDIT-SENSITIVE CONSUMPTION EXPENDITURES AND CONTRIBUTE<br />
TO A FIRM BASIS FOR ON-GOING ECONOMIC. GROWTH. </p>
<p>WE HAVE CREATED 70,000 MORE JOBS SINCE THE SUMMITr THAN<br />
THE FRASER GOVERNMENT MANAGED. IN 7 YEARS. OUR THREE<br />
YEAR TARGET OF 500,000 IS NOW COMFORTABLY WITHIN REACH,<br />
AND THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE, WHICH HAS ALREADY FALLEN BY<br />
2 PERCENTAGE POINTS, IS EXPECTED TO FALL FURTHER THIS YEAR<br />
To 7-1/ 2 OR, AT WORST, 8 PER CENT.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME, EVEN THOUGH THERE HAS BEEN SOME PICK UP<br />
RECENTLY IN RESPONSE TO DEPRECIATION, THE ANNUAL INCREASE IN<br />
PRICES IN THE PAST YEAR WAS THE LOWEST SINCE 1970-71.<br />
INDUSTRIAL DISPUTATION IS AT ITS LOWEST FOR ONE AND A HALF<br />
DECADES, BUSINESS PROFITABILITY HAS BEEN RESTORED. REAL<br />
UNIT LABOUR COSTS HAVE BEEN REDUCED TO LEVELS LAST SEEN IN<br />
THE EARLY<br />
WE RECOGNISE THAT, WHILE FISCAL PUMP PRIMING WAS APPROPRIATE<br />
WHILE ECONOMIC ACTIVITY IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR WAS WEAK, IT<br />
IS NO LONGER NECESSARY OR APPROPRIATE FOR THE PUBLIC SECTOR<br />
TO SHOULDER SO MUCH RESPONSIBIL. ITY.<br />
CONSISTENT WITH OUR FISCAL TRILOGY WE HAVE,-IN THIS BUDGET,<br />
REDUCED THE SHARE OF COMMONWEALTH OUTLAYS IN GDP BY A FULL<br />
PERCENTAGE POINT, AS THE MAY MEASURES AMPLY DEMONSTRATE,<br />
THIS IS THE RESULT OF RIGOROUS EXPENDITURE PRUNING AND FIRM<br />
CONTROL OVER NEW PROGRAMS, a. 16 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
LET ME SAY A LITTLE MORE ABOUT THE STRENGTH OF RECOVERY<br />
IN 1985-86o AND THE FACTORS WHICH WILL SHAPE OUR GROWTH<br />
PROSPECTS BEYOND THAT.<br />
A PLEASING FEATURE OF THE ECONOMIC OUTCOME IN 1984-85 WAS<br />
THE CONSISTENT GROWTH IN PRIVATE SECTOR ACTIVITY ACHIEVED<br />
THROUGH THE COURSE OF THE YEAR.<br />
REAL PRIVATE CONSUMPTION EXPENDITURE GREW AT AN ANNUAL RATE<br />
OF 5.5 PER CENT IN THE SECOND HALF OF 19841-5, UP FROM<br />
3.7 PER CENT IN THE FIRST HALF. BUSINESS INVESTMENT GREW<br />
STEADILY AT AN ANNUAL RATE OF 4I PER CENT.<br />
MOST PLEASING OF ALL WAS THE HUGE PRIVATE SECTOR CONTRIBUTION<br />
TO EMPLOYMENT GROWTH.<br />
SOME 90 PER CENT OF THE GROWTH IN EMPLOYMENT WHICH OCCURRED<br />
IN THE YEAR TO THE MARCH QUARTER ( THE LATEST FOR WHICH THE<br />
DISAGGREGATED DATE ARE AVAILABLE) WAS PRIVATE SECTOR EMPLOYMENT,<br />
1985-86 IS FORECAST TO BE ANOTH4ER BUOYANT YEAR FOR THE<br />
PRIVATE SECTOR, UNDERPINNED BY SOLID GROWTH IN PRIVATE<br />
CONSUMPTION AND FASTER GROWTH IN BUSINESS INVESTMENT.<br />
PARTLY REFLECTING THE STRENGTH OF SALES, THE OFFICIAL<br />
FORECASTS ASSUME THAT BUSINESS INVENTORIES DO NOT MAKE MUCH<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO GROWTH IN 1985-86. BUT STOCKS ARE NOW VERY<br />
LOW RELATIVE TO SALES, IN HISTORICAL TERMS, AND THERE IS A<br />
CHANCE THAT WE WILL DO BETTER THAN THE FORECASTS ON THIS POINT. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
A SIGNIFICANT FACTOR IN THE OUTLOOK FOR 1985-86 AND<br />
BEYOND IS THE RECENT DEPRECIATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN DOLLAR,<br />
WE,. AS A COMMUNITYA HAVE A REAL CHANCE TO MAKE A DECISIVE<br />
BREAK WIT11 THE CONSEQUENCES OF PAST POOR COMPETITIVENESS&amp;<br />
OUR MANUFACTURING INDUSTRIES NOW HAVE A REAL CHANCE<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY TO INCREASE THEIR SHARES OF DOMESTIC DEMAND.<br />
AND OUR MANUFACTURING, RURALo MINING AND SERVICE INDUSTRIES<br />
NOW ARE WELL PLACED TO DO MUCH BETTER ON EXPORT MARKETS.<br />
IHAVE SUGGESTED BEFORE THAT WE COULD CREATE 100,000 NEW<br />
JOBS FOR AUSTRALIANS IF WE RETAIN AND UTILISE OUR NEWLY<br />
STRENGTHENED COMPETITIVENESS.<br />
BUT THE SAME INCREASES IN THE PRICES OF IMPORTED GOODS WHICH<br />
HAVE ALREADY STRENGTHENED THE COMPETITIVENESS OF DOMESTIC<br />
PRODUCERS ARE RAISING CONSUMER PRICES. IF THESE INCREASES<br />
FLOW RIGHT THROUGH TO ALL OUR COSTS WE WILL HAVE LOST OUR<br />
ADVANTAGE. FOR THIS REASON THE GOVERNMENT. WILL BE ARGUING FOR DISCOUNTING<br />
OF THE CPI FOR THE PRICE EFFECTS OF DEPRECIATION<br />
AT THE NEXT TWO NATIONAL WAGE HEARINGS.<br />
WE WILL BE MEETING EMPLOYERS AND UNIONS BEFORE THE NEXT CASE.<br />
TO DISCUSS THE GOVERNMENT IS APPROACH. AS THE TREASURER<br />
INDICATED LAST NIGHT, WE WILL BE EXPLORING WITH THE ACTJ,<br />
WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF TH4E ACCORD, MEANS BY WHICH ANY 6Ul./ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
TEMPORARY LOSS IN REAL INCOME CAN BE FULLY RESTORED, OVER<br />
TIME, WITHOUT DAMAGING THE ECONOMY6<br />
AS A FURTHER INDICATION OF THE SCALE OF BENEFITS WHICH CAN<br />
BE ACHIEVED IF ONLY THE REAL DEPRECIATION CAN BE PRESERVED,,<br />
THE OECD HAS ESTIMATED THAT NET EXPORTS COULD CONTRIBUTE<br />
1.41 PERCENTAGE POINTS TO GROWTH IN 1985-860 THE BUDGET<br />
FORECASTS INCORPORATE A SLIGHTLY MORE CONSERVATIVE ESTIMATE<br />
OF ONE AND A QUARTER POINTS,<br />
BUT BASED ON PAST EXPERIENCE THE CONTRIBUTION COULD TURN OUT<br />
TO BE HIGHER THAN THAT.<br />
AND WHILE CIRCUMSTANCES MAY VARY, ACROSS INDUSTRIES, MUCH<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN MANUFACTURING CERTAINLY HAS THE CAPACITY TO<br />
RESPOND TO THE BUSINESS OPPORTUNITIES WHICH ARE EMERGING,<br />
BUT WHETHER THOSE OPPORTUNITIES WILL BE PRESENT IN 1986-87<br />
AND BEYOND WILL DEPEND VERY MUCH ON HOW SUCCESSFUL WE ARE AT<br />
CONTAINING INFLATIONARY PRESSURES IN THE AFTERMATH OF<br />
DEPRECIATION.<br />
Tiic BUDGFT rSTIMATES OF OUTLAYS AND REVENUE ASSUME CONTINUED<br />
FULL INDEXATION 01-WAbhS TO im1IAi 1 </p>
<p>IF INSTEAD AND AS WE WOULD HOPE THE CONCILIATION AND<br />
ARBITRATION COMMISSION IS PERSUADED TO TAKE ACCOUNT OF THE<br />
EFFECTS OF DEPRECIATION, THE BUDGET DEFICIT WOULD BE SOME<br />
$ 350M HIGHER.<br />
IN A SPEECH TO THE ECONOMIC SOCIETY IN SYDNEY A COUPLE OF<br />
WEEKS AGO, I DESCRIBED HOW OUR MONETARY POLICY IS FIRMLY<br />
DIRECTED TO SUPPORTING STRONG GROWTH BUT NOT ANY RESURGENCE<br />
OF INFLATION. OUR APPROACH TO MONETARY POLICY WAS REAFFIRMED<br />
LAST NIGHT IN THlE BUDGET.<br />
IN ADDITION TO STRENGTHENING THE FOUNDATIONS OF ECONOMIC<br />
GROWTH, OUR THIRD BUDGET, LIKE ITS TWO PREDECESSORS, IS<br />
A BUDGET OF REFORM IN AN EVEN WIDER SENSE.<br />
WE HAVE FOCUSED STRONGLY ON THE MAJOR ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL<br />
CONCERN OF OUR TIME THE POSITION OF YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
As I SAID IN MY ADDRESS ON SUNDAY NIGHT, WE MUST NURTURE<br />
THE TALENTS OF YOUNG AUSTRALIANS. THEIR ENTHUSIASM,<br />
THEIR BRAINS, THEIR VISION CAN LIFT THIS COUNTRY TO THE<br />
FRONT LINE OF THE WORLD'IS INDUSTRIAL POWERS$<br />
BUT SO OFTEN WHEN WE HAVE SPOKEN TO YOUNG PEOPLE WE HAVE DETECTED<br />
A SENSE OF FRUSTRATION AND ANGER BECAUSE A DISTURBING NUMBER<br />
FEEL THAT THEY HAVE NOT BEEN GIVEN A CHANCE. I. I. I 11 </p>
<p>1.-<br />
IN THIS BUDGET my GOVERNMENT HAS GIVEN EFFECT TO A<br />
CO-ORDINATED STRATEGY TO GIVE YOUNG PEOPLE THAT CHANCEESPECIALLY<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE FROM FINANCIALLY POOR OR<br />
OTHERWI SE DISADVANTAGED BACKGROUNDS&amp;<br />
A BETTER TRAINED WORKFORCE MEANS A WORKFORCE WHICH IS MORE<br />
FLEXIBLE AND BETTER ABLE TO RESPOND TO THE CHALLENGES<br />
WHICH LIE AHEAD OF US.<br />
WITH THIS IN MIND WE HAVE REVITALISED ARRANGEMENTS FOR<br />
YOUTH INCOME SUPPORT AND PUT IN PLACE AN IMAGINATIVE NEW<br />
APPROACH TO YOUTH TRAINING PROGRAMS AN APPROACH MODELLED<br />
CLOSELY ON THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE KIRBY REPORT,<br />
INVOLVING A MIX OF BOTH ON AND OFF-THE-JOB STRUCTURED<br />
TRAINING AND EDUCATION.<br />
WE WILL BE DEVOTING SUBSTANTIAL ADDITIONAL BUDGETARY RESOURCES<br />
TO THIS TASK. RESOURCES TO PROVIDE AN ADEQUATE LEVEL OF<br />
INCOME SUPPORT; TO PROVIDE 20,500 ADDITIONAL TERTIARY PLACES<br />
OVER THE CURRENT TRIENNIUM; TO SPONSOR TRAINING PLACES<br />
IN THE PUBLIC SECTOR;-AND TO ENSURE THE SUCCESS OF<br />
TRAINEESHIPS IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR.<br />
WE HAVE GIVEN THE LEAD. BUT TO REACH ITS FULL POTENTIAL OUR<br />
SCHEME REQUIRES THE CO-OPERATION OF ALL PARTIES EMPLOYERS,<br />
UNIONS, EDUCATORS AND YOUNG PEOPLE THEMSELVES TO TURN THAT<br />
INITIAL ENTHUSIASM INTO REAL TRAINEESHIPS AND REAL JOBS. </p>
<p>-12<br />
IASK ALL AUSTRALIANS YOUNG AND NOT SO YOUNG ALIKETO<br />
CAREFULLY CONSIDER THE CHALLENGE WHICH OUR PROPOSALS<br />
INVOLVE, WE NEED YOUR WHOLEHEARTED SUPPORT. BUT WITH<br />
YOUR WHOLEHEARTED SUPPORT WE CAN ENSURE A NEW DEAL FOR<br />
THE COMING GENERATIONS OF AUSTRALIANS.<br />
OF COURSE THIS BUDGET HAS NOT NEGLECTED OTHER AREAS OF<br />
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL REFORM.<br />
THERE IS GREATLY EXPANDED SUPPORT FOR RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT<br />
WITHIN THE MOTOR VEHICLE PLAN,<br />
THERE ARE SUBSTANTIAL INITIATIVES TO EASE THE BURDEN ON<br />
FARMERS IN THEIR TIME OF CRISIS. THESE INCLUDE THE COMPLETE<br />
REMOVAL OF THE EXCISE ON FUEL FOR ELIGIBLE PRIMARY PRODUCERS<br />
AND THE REPLACEMENT OF THE TARIFF ON GRAIN HARVESTERS BY<br />
BOUNTIES ON LOCAL PRODUCTION.<br />
WE HAVE BUILT UPON THE SUBSIANIIAL KtAL 1MPHUVE'IENT3 114<br />
BENEFITS PROVIDED IN PREVIOUS BUDGETS TO PROVIDE MORE<br />
ADEQUATELY FOR OUR MOST NEEDY FELLOW AUSTRALIANS.*<br />
IN PARTICULAR, WE HAVE INTRODUCED A SUPPLEMENTARY PAYMENT OF<br />
PER WEEK FOR LONG TERM UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFICIARIES WHO RENT<br />
PRIVATELY AND WE HAVE FURTHER INCREASED THE ADDITIONAL BENEFITS<br />
PAID TO CERTAIN LOW INCOME FAMILIES WITH CHILDREN. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
THE BUDGET THEREFORE INCORPORATES A CONSISTENT, MEASURED<br />
APPROACH DESIGNED TO PRODUCE A MORE HIGHLY SKILLED, MORE<br />
EFFICIENT AND MORE EQUITABLE AUSTRALIA. AND IT DOES SO<br />
WHILE ALSO SUBSTANTIALLY WINDING BACK THE BUDGET DEFICIT.<br />
BUT LET US BE CLEAR. THIS GREAT FISCAL FEAT IN 1985-86<br />
IS NOT THE OUTCOME OF ANY FISCAL SLEIGHT OF HAND.<br />
THERE IS NO INCREASE IN THE TAX BURDEN. THERE IS NO<br />
ARTIFICIAL FUNDING OF DEFICITS BY WHOLESALE SELLING OF<br />
PROFITABLE ENTERPRISES, AS OUR OPPONENTS WOULD HAVE US DO.<br />
THIS FISCAL OUTCOME HAS BEEN ACHIEVED AFTER A HARD SLOG TO<br />
PRUNE WASTE AND UNNECESSARY EXPENDITURES DATING BACK TO<br />
CHANGES IN PROCEDURES THAT WE INTRODUCED ALMOST A YEAR AGO;<br />
A HARD SLOG TO REORDER PROGRAMS TO TARGET THEM MOST CLOSELY<br />
ON NEED; AND TO CONTAIN NEW PROGRAMS TO THOSE WHICH ARE<br />
ESSENTIAL TO SATISFY THE PRESSING NEEDS OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
IT IS A BUDGET FOR THE FUTURE NOT ONLY BECAUSE IT DELIVERS<br />
THE RIGHT MIX BETWEEN MONETARY AND FISCAL POLICY; NOT ONLY<br />
BECAUSE IT WINDS BACK THE DEGREE OF FISCAL STIMULUS AT A TIME<br />
WHEN THE PRIVATE SECTOR IS SET TO EXPAND STRONGLY! BUT ALSO<br />
BECAUSE IT PUTS IN PLACE MEASURED STRUCTURAL REFORMS DESIGNED<br />
TO RAISE SKILL LEVELS AND PURSUE SOCIAL JUSTICE. 1 </p>
<p>-14-<br />
ABOVE ALL, IT IS A BUDGET TO UNDERWRITE A THIRD YEAR OF<br />
STRONG GROWTH<br />
, A THIRD YEAR OF GROWTH WHICH FURTHER DEFIES<br />
AND, I TRUST, SHALL DEFEAT THE PESSIMISM ABOUT<br />
GROWTH THAT DESCENDED UPON AUSTRALIA IN THE<br />
MID-SE VENTI ES.<br />
A THIRD YEAR OF GROWTH FOR AUSTRALIANS TO<br />
LEARN AGAIN THE HUGE REWARDS FOR ALL AUSTRALIANS,<br />
TO BE WON BY COMMUNITY CO-OPERATION WITHIN A<br />
WELL-CRAFTED STRATEGY FOR NATIONAL RECOVERY<br />
AND RECONSTRUCTION,<br />
1SAID AT THE BEGINNING THAT THE FULFILMENT OF THE TRILOGY<br />
ACHIEVED IN THIS BUDGET ITSELF JUSTIFIES PAUL KEATING'S<br />
DESCRIPTION OF His BUDGET LAST NIGHT AS HISTORIC<br />
BUT TIIERE IS MUCH MORE TO IT THAN THAT.<br />
IPROFOUNDLY BELIEVE-THAT IF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE -AND<br />
IN PARTICULAR, AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS AND AUSTRALIAN TRADE<br />
UNIONS RESPOND TO THE OPPORTUNITIES THIS BUDGET OFFERS,<br />
THEN THE 1985-86 BUDGET CAN BE A WATERSHED IN OUR HISTORY. </p>
<p>AND I SAY THAT FOR THIS REASON:<br />
FOR TOO LONG, THE BUDGET-MAKING PROCESS IN AUSTRALIA<br />
LACKED CONSISTENCY,-PURPOSE, AND DIRECTION. UNTIL 1983,<br />
BUDGET AFTER BUDGET FAILED TO PROVIDE ANY COHERENT<br />
FRAMEWORK WITHIN WHICH BUSINESS COULD PLAN OR IN WHICH<br />
THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT COULD FULFIL ITS RESPONSIBILITIES<br />
OR IN WHICH THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE COULD SEE<br />
WITH CONFIDENCE THE FUTURE DIRECTIONS OF AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL POLICY,<br />
THIS BUDGET, EVEN MORE THAN ITS TWO IMMEDIATE PREDECESSORS,<br />
AND CERTAINLY IN A WAY NEVER ATTEMPTED IN THE BUDGETS<br />
OF THE SIXTIES AND SEVENTIES, DOES ESTABLISH THAT FRAMEWORK<br />
-A FRAMEWORK OF CONFIDENCE AND CONSISTFNCYO OF<br />
DIRECTION AND PURPOSE THAT WILL SERVE AND STRENGTHEN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY AND THE AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY NOT MERELY<br />
THIS FINANCIAL YEAR, BUT FOR MANY YEARS TO COME.<br />
THIS WILL BE AN HISTORIC ACHIEVEMENT. THIS IS AN<br />
HISTORIC BUDGET. 0I* </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
