<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10368</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES - 2UE RADIO</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010368.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3 0 M ay 19 9 7-TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES 2UE RADIO<br />
E O E<br />
JONES: Prime Minister good morning.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Good morning Alan.<br />
JONES: You offered a personal apology at the National Reconciliation Convention. Your critics seems to say that's<br />
not enough.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I thoug~ ht it was. I meant every word of what I said. Alan, I have read this report. There are some<br />
horrific stories in it and it's quite plain that a lot of people were affected very badly and continue to be<br />
affected and ithat can't be denied or ignored. It's also true, as you said, that the practises were meant, at the<br />
time, to be doing the right thing. They were thought at the time to be benefiting the people involved. And<br />
there is no doubt that in many cases, however wrong we now see the taking of the children away from their<br />
own natural homes, that in many cases those people received a very happy home life and a very, very happy<br />
upbringing. In many cases they didn't. But sadly, even as we talk, there are children in Australia and children<br />
all around the world who are having a happy home upbringing and others who are having a very unhappy and<br />
neglected one and that is a sad fact of human behaviour. But my view was that this generation can't be held<br />
accountable for the mistakes of past generations. I did make a very strong and unambiguous expression of<br />
my own sorrow and distress at what had happened and I meant that. I meant every word of it. I didn't tend<br />
to what is called an official apology. One of the things you've got to bear in mind is that we have received<br />
legal advice to the effect that an unqualified apology delivered on behalf of the Government and the people<br />
could have quite significant legal implications.<br />
JONES: In other words, that could be construed as an admission of wrong doing...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh yes.<br />
JONES: and therefore action...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Give rise to compensation claims and the like. Now, we got that legal advice in writing from the Chief<br />
General Council of the Attorney-General's Department. And that is a factor that I ask Australians who think<br />
that I should have gone further to bear in mind. I have an obligation to them given that we take the view that<br />
cash, monetary compensation is not appropriate in this situation. And having taken that decision and made<br />
that submission to the commission, I have an obligation to the Australian taxpayer to avoid using words that<br />
could give rise inaudible... compensation claims. Now, it's easy when you're in Opposition, it's easy when<br />
you're outside the loop of responsibility to call on the run for all sorts of apologies and statements. We will<br />
give a very considered and sympathetic response and sensible response to this commission... . report. We'll do<br />
it in a measured way. We'll take our time, but not a lot of time to do so. And there are many things in the<br />
report which I'm sure that we'll be able to respond to in a positive and helpful way and we'll want to do that.<br />
But we do hold a strong view about compensation and we've stated that and we've expressed our sorrow for </p>
<p>what happened. But as for a formal apology it does have the difficulty about being an admission of liability,<br />
of giving rise to a stronger legal claim that I've referred to and that is the reason why this week I have<br />
stopped short of doing . is one of the reasons why I've stopped short of doing it.<br />
JONES: The convention the Reconciliation Convention began last Monday and you made your speech there. I'm Just<br />
wondering for the benefit of listeners who've heard a lot of rhetoric and a lot of emotion and a lot of anger,<br />
how widely circulated has this report been? How many people at that convention would have read the<br />
report? How many people actually commenting upon now and advising you or criticising you for what you<br />
should or shouldn't do would have actually had access to the report?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that's very, very hard to tell. I think at the convention itself, probably not a large number would have<br />
had access to the report....<br />
JONES: So in other words they're calling upon you, are they, to do things without actually knowing...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well many of them, many of them would, although to be fair to them there had been extensive press briefing a<br />
few days earlier of the contents of the report and there had been some of the case histories in the report<br />
published widely in newspapers.<br />
JONES: Should that have happened prior to it being tabled in the Parliament?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, but it wouldn't be, Alan, the report that's been released before its been tabled in Parliament. But<br />
certainly that, technically speaking, shouldn't have happened. But the thrust of the report, the themes of the<br />
report were pretty widely known, although perhaps the detail of it and certainly no opportunity to scrutinise<br />
the detail of it would have occurred before that conference.<br />
JONES: Well do we have any documentation 1 mean, if we just take a figure of $ 100,000 and he apparently, Sir<br />
Ronald Wilson's, got 535 cases and I don't think we need to go on about how tragic it is that people are<br />
abused in any walk of life, indigenous or otherwise. But is there any documentation about those Aborigines,<br />
indigenous Australians, living today who've been educated and cared for under that kind of regime who may<br />
not have been with us if they hadn't been removed from the dangers of their childhood environment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I can't give a precise answer to that. I can tell you that in relation to some of the case histories I read in the<br />
report the individuals involved acknowledged that they had received good support and good education, they<br />
have been well looked after. Although, then going on to say that despite that, they felt a separation from their<br />
own culture, from their own families and so forth. But certainly the emphasis of the report is on the tragic<br />
side of it. Now, if you're asking me is there a fair and full documentation of the good things that occurred in<br />
the context of the overall practice, I'm not aware of that. But I don't I'm not in a position to pass<br />
judgement about how comprehensive the report in acknowledging that in some cases people did receive very<br />
good education, very good care. I mean, there is no doubt that in some cases the children involved did enjoy<br />
and receive the benefit of an upbringing and an education and of support...<br />
JONES: That was to their benefit.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: </p>
<p>But equally ( inaudible) is a report document say, well, you know, all of this was fine, but, I was separated<br />
from my family and that was very, very heavy negative in my early years and it remains so.<br />
JONES: But you would be aware, wouldn't you, of the stigma 25, 30, 35 years ago of pregnancy, teenage pregnancy,<br />
of having children out of wedlock and daughters of Catholic unmarried girls were taken from them at birth<br />
without the mother even seeing the child?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I am aware of that and the point I'm not going to go in to whether you know, going to start talking about<br />
those practices on your programme or indeed any other one. The point I simply make with that illustration is<br />
that once you start going down the path of trying, through the compensation system, to make amends for<br />
what you believe to have been wrong practices in the past, you open up a pandora's box where does it end?<br />
If you were going to pay compensation in relation to the stolen children then are you going to have people<br />
who at birth were taken from their natural mothers now claiming that that was a breach of their human rights<br />
and that therefore they are entitled to compensation despite the fact that their mothers may have been at a<br />
very young age and may have wanted them to be adopted, or in some cases not wanting them to be adopted.<br />
But it was simply the practice of the time because it was thought to be in the best interests of the child that it<br />
not be left in the care of somebody who clearly was unable at that time to care for the child. Now, this is the<br />
difficulty of imposing backwards the standards and attitudes and today...<br />
JONES: And it is also a difficulty, as Prime Minister, is it not, to try and make decisions in the interests of all<br />
Australians? How much has that been a factor in what you've tried to do?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it is. I mean, I take the view that the best thing we can do to repair the hurt of Aboriginal people who<br />
today continue to carry the scars of having been taken away from their families and continue to be affected by<br />
it, the best thing we can do is to help them now to build a better tomorrow. I would have thought if we<br />
understand that it happened, but if we say to them, how can we help to address your genuine disadvantage? I<br />
mean, those that aren't disadvantaged well, they don't need any more assistance than the rest of us. But<br />
those who are, and there are many Aboriginal people in Australia who don't need any special assistance and<br />
who are not asking for any special assistance. They're saying, look I've, you know, I've succeeded, I'm part<br />
of the Australian community, I'm proud of my heritage and my culture but I'm not asking for any special<br />
help. JONES: Well, one other dimension of this debate which hasn't been -and I raise this with you, because it's quite<br />
separate from this notion of taking the children away because in the interest of their safety and help they were<br />
going to be better off I read where AO Neville, a Chief Protector in Western Australia from 1915 to 1940<br />
so he was the bloke legally in control of Aboriginal children argued in 1937, and I quote what he said.-' the<br />
pure blooded Aboriginal was not a quick breeder, on the other hand the half cast was' his solution ' our<br />
solution is to separate one from the other and let the Aboriginal race die out'. Now, was there a policy really<br />
to that would be of some concern to us all that there were active and legally sanctioned decisions taken to<br />
really exterminate the Aborigines?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I can only conclude from a statement like that, and I've read statements of that type, I can only<br />
conclude that that was the view of some people at the time. I don't believe the totality of the report is as<br />
severe as that but certainly there were at that time and it continued up to the 1970s in the minds of some<br />
people a view about the unworthiness of Aboriginal people. And you still get it in today's society and I have<br />
to say these are the sorts of attitudes that can be very, very genuinely hurtful and quite distressing in relation...<br />
JONES: </p>
<p>Absolutely. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I mean, anybody who talks about, you know, inferiority of race, anybody who talks about the lowliness of<br />
people in the social spectrum, I mean, that is intensely offensive and totally unacceptable.<br />
JONES:<br />
Repugnant. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Absolutely repugnant to all of us.<br />
JONES: Just on the legal side and one final question on that. Native title requires a traditional connection with the<br />
land. Have children who were stolen been denied the benefits conferred on others by the native tittle<br />
legislation? PRIME MIN][ STER:<br />
Well, I can't answer that question yet. One of the reasons I can't answer it is that the existing Native Title<br />
Act is so obscure. We know from the Mabo decision that there has to have been a continuous connection<br />
with the land in order for native title to be established. A question of whether a child removed from his or her<br />
family has thereby been denied the continuity of physical connection could come back and make a native title<br />
claim is something which, at this stage, I can't answer. Some of the lawyers very steeped in this area might<br />
be able to do so. I guess it's one of those questions which throws up the almost never ending difficulty and<br />
complexity of the Native Title Act which, of course as you know, we are very keen to amend with our<br />
Point Plan which not only deals with the Wik decision and delivers certainty and stability to pastoralists in the<br />
mining industry but it also protects the Mabo principles of native title and provides a more efficient system<br />
and I hope prevents some of the more extraordinary ambit claims that have been made under the act over<br />
recent times.<br />
JONES: Just one thing before you go. Last night you talked about tax. Are you aware that there's a tremendous push<br />
in America through the presidency for a debits tax and given that the Treasury have figures that there are<br />
$ 200 billion of withdrawals from financial institutions every day, a one half a per cent tax on that would net<br />
about $ 250 billion a year, $ 65 billion more than you actually need you could pay of your debt in the term of<br />
one Parliament and there'll be no tax, no tax returns needed, no file numbers, no deeming, no nothing. Is<br />
that likely to get on the table for debate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Alan, once you start a debate on tax reform anything can get on the table.<br />
JONES: Well you've started the debate.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I've certainly started the debate. I mean, there are some distributional problems with that sort of tax if I<br />
remember rightly from some work I had done about 15 years ago. It sounds simple on the surface but it can<br />
have some sort of very awkward distribution, particularly with multiples...<br />
JONES: Well thank you for your time, we've got to go to the news. Appreciate your time.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Thanks Alan. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
