<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5228</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/01/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005228.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 9 January 1980<br />
The Government today considered a report from the Foreign-<br />
Minister concerning the latest events in ! ran and more specifically<br />
the Russian invasion of Afghanistan.<br />
The Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister have already condemned<br />
the invas-ion of Afghanistan as totally without justification;<br />
as a violation of everything the United Nations stands for; and as<br />
a mode of behaviour which will make normal relationships between<br />
nations totally impossible.<br />
Soviet explanations of the invasion have been rejected by the<br />
Government. The Government, along with many others, is conscious that its<br />
actions and decisions must. be directed to the securing of<br />
circumstances where this kind of behaviour will not be repeated.<br />
The Russians have invaded Afghanistan. Now, collectively,<br />
the world needs to demonstrate that the price of that invasion is<br />
much higher than the Soviet envisaged and higher than they would<br />
be prepared to contemplate on future occasions.<br />
made it plain thi4S morning that it is not just a question ofwanting<br />
the Russians out of Afghanistan but est&amp; E. bi-ishinq . g -e<br />
I. Wh hi<br />
It is against that background that the Soviet Union needs to<br />
understand that the price of its actions in Afqjhranistan will hr!<br />
heavy one indeed.<br />
There are inevitable limitations to the we!. iq( h L Lhal. a niation of<br />
14 million people can put into the scales. NeverLhecL'. S WC hi. vCe<br />
taken a number of decisions on a broad front which are designe-d<br />
to demonstrate concern and to register the strongest possible<br />
opposition to the Soviet Union's actions.<br />
Some days ago the Government made an offer to the United States to<br />
consult with them concerning greater Australian involvement in<br />
patrolling and surveillance of the Indian Ocean. Much needs to be<br />
determined and options considered, but-thiis could involve Australian<br />
participation with United States forces, or a greater independent<br />
effort by Australia to survey larger areas of the Indian Ocean. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The United States has reciprocated warmly to that suggestion.<br />
It is not one made merely against the short term position that we are<br />
now confronting. It is one made against the background of changed<br />
strategic circumstances which will involve greater co-operation<br />
between Australia and her friends and allies.<br />
Australia will support United States action in relation to<br />
wheat sales to the Soviet Union. We will not pick up any<br />
of the short fall created by that decision and will urge other<br />
wheat exporting nations to take a similar view. Consistent with<br />
United States actions normal sales to the Soviet Union will not<br />
be affected.<br />
We will be putting to the United States at a meeting being<br />
held in Washington on Saturday that the 17 millinji tonner,;<br />
shortfall resulting from President Carter's decision, should<br />
be handled in such a way that the international market in<br />
wheat is not prejudiced.<br />
Any discussions or arrangements or agreements over fisheries<br />
matters are indefinitely suspended. This has particular<br />
application for two projects: a joint feasibility fishing<br />
venture on the North West Shelf off the Western Australian coast;<br />
and a feasibility fishing project involving jack mackerel in<br />
waters adjacent to Tasmania.<br />
Any approvals previously given in relation to these fisheries<br />
projects are withdrawn.<br />
USSR Liner Shipping services at present operate to and from<br />
Australia in conference trades ( Australia to Europe Shipping<br />
Conference) and in non-conference trad,, s ( Aiustr; ilia to Eucope,<br />
and the triangular service East Asia/ Japan, USA arid AuLra]. ii).<br />
Russian bulk shipping also carries primary produce bought by<br />
Russia from Australia.<br />
These shipping operations and other facil. itie; provided by<br />
Aust-&gt;-alia are currently being revielird.<br />
There will be no further approvals for scier--. ic<br />
vessels to visit our ports.<br />
The visit of the Soviet Fisheries Delegation in February will.<br />
not be permitted into Australia.<br />
We will not meet the Soviet request to station Aeroflot<br />
personnel in Australia to facilitate the Russian Airline's<br />
services going through Australia to other countries.<br />
In addition we are not prepared to consider their requests for<br />
direct Soviet/ Aus-tralia air flights.<br />
Scientific collaboration with the Soviet Union is indefinitel. y<br />
suspended.<br />
Official talks and visits between Australia arn( t-he. Sovi(. t<br />
Union are also indefinitely suspended. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
New programs under the Cultural Program will not be entered into.<br />
A number of countries have made statements concerning the Olympic<br />
Games. Many, including Australia, would prefer, as a result of<br />
recent events, that the Games were not being held in Moscow.<br />
The Games are, however, an international event not a Russian<br />
event and should be seen in that context.<br />
Any decision on this matter is therefore of a different kind<br />
to decisions affecting bilateral relationships between Australia<br />
and Russia. The Government will, therefore, be closely examining<br />
these wider aspects and assessing the views of a number of<br />
other countries.<br />
In addition to these measures, the Government will be embarking<br />
on a wide range of consultations with other countries.<br />
What has happened in Afghanistan has demonstrated that the fears<br />
and concerns expressed in my Statement on Foreign Policy in 1976,<br />
and repeated on other occasions by the Foreign Minister have<br />
been only too realistic. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
