<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8876</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP INTERVIEW WITH 4 CORNERS, ABC TV SYDNEY 31 MAY 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/05/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008876.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
tn A PRIME MINISTER1<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH 4 CORNERS, ABC TV<br />
SYDNEY 31 MAY 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
AO: Mr Keating has agreed tonight to his first substantive Interview since the<br />
election. and Prime Minister, welcome.<br />
PM: Good Andrew, nice to be here.<br />
AO: When you won power, Immediately afterwards you , urged your Ministers to<br />
stop and think, to do nothing for a while, to take stock, almost like sending<br />
them Into retreat, I suppose, for a while. Oid you actually need to meditate<br />
on just what you wanted to do with this personal mandate over the next<br />
three years?<br />
PM: I think so. I think it is the right time for a Government after an election to<br />
think about the future and think about the circumstances in this election,<br />
some of the longer run issues. The issues which will be Important in<br />
twenty or thirty years from now.<br />
AO: But the point is you haven't really had that much time, I suppose, to think<br />
about that of late. I mean, the last couple of years have been all<br />
consuming, haven't they? First you had to get rid of Hawke, then you had<br />
to stop Hewson, all the time and energy, I suppose, was used in getting<br />
there. Was It a bit like suddenly arriving and having to stop and ask<br />
yourself, oh ok, now I am here what do I really want to do?<br />
PM: No, because last year. In 1992, the principal endeavour of the Government<br />
was to get the economy growing again, but since the election I think the<br />
Government has decided to think about long run Issues, to set its sails,<br />
and to take the wind shifts wherever they are, not to react to them. There<br />
is always this notion, you made this point about being Invisible, that's code </p>
<p>2<br />
for saying that we should appear at press conferences answering wind<br />
shifts. Well I think it is Important for Governments to think about things,<br />
set their sails, arnd go to them, Since the election we have had on our<br />
plate setting the principles for the fulfilment of the High Court decision on<br />
native title under Mabo, thinking about the future structure of APEC arid<br />
trade which I gave a long and important speech on in New Zealand a<br />
week or two ago, and the other issues you mentioned.<br />
AG: Well we will come to all those Issues.<br />
PM: Setting up the republic and getting a thoughtful structure, to have a proper<br />
debate about the republic. Looking at the long-term unemployed.<br />
AG: For the moment can we stick with the long -term unemployed because the<br />
economy and unemployment, and solutions to that, was a major issue at<br />
the election arnd yet here we are just straight after the election and now<br />
you appoint a committee to look at the issue of long-term unemployment<br />
to find a solution, which they will be sitting on until the end of this year, I<br />
think?<br />
PM: I think so, yes. Because I think we have a chance to do something novel<br />
In Australia, I am quite sure very few comparable countries will attempt to<br />
do as we are already doing and can do. That Is, we already have In place<br />
substantial labor market programs to get people work experience and<br />
training and get them back to work.<br />
AG: But you appreciate the people are cynical about yet another committee?<br />
PM: I know, but again It's not a matter of a committee, I don't think, Andrew.<br />
The fact is we are in a new phenomenon. That is, that we have got a high<br />
proportion of middle age people, of those unemployed who are middle<br />
aged, we set to work on dealing with youth unemployment last year and It<br />
made some substantial inroads Into that. But I think what we don't want to<br />
see In this country Is people marginalised. In Britain, for instance, you<br />
have got very high prices of labour, high labour rates, yet 3 million people<br />
are out of work, And you say to yourself, well how could there be high<br />
rates of labour with so many people out of work? And the answer Is<br />
because they are sidelined, they are just no longer taken to the<br />
employment equation. I don't want to see that happen In Australia.<br />
AO: So what do you want to come out of this committee, what do you hope it<br />
will come up with, what options?<br />
PM: Well ways In which we can get people, longer term people back Into work<br />
expenence and back into work, and to study the post-war patterns of<br />
employment In Australia and In other countres and to try and take lessons<br />
from that experience. ( I D -4 i U U I </p>
<p>AO: You do want to get them back Into work, though, do you? Because you<br />
did raise an Interesting question the other day when you said, should<br />
everyone who wants to work be entitled to a job. I mean, are you<br />
seriously suggesting that our society can now afford to abandon that<br />
fundemental principle, that right?<br />
PM: Well, it's a matter of whether the notion of full employment Is zero<br />
unemployment, and whether in an economy where there's a lot of flux a<br />
big shift In its structure where people are going to be trained and retrained<br />
whether In that sort of an economy you're not going to have a<br />
proportion of people who are unemployed, Now, you've got another<br />
problem as well and that Is, the problem of the older unemployed, eldedy,<br />
oider people.<br />
AO: Yes, you're now saying that perhaps one solution to that is to bring forward<br />
ihe pension for these older people. Now, I'm sure that's aimed In part, at<br />
least, so they can avoid the humiliation of having to go out looking for<br />
non-existent work, but a lot of people will see it as pensioning off the<br />
unemployed?<br />
PM: Well, we've already made a decision in the election to set up as we have<br />
already we're already doing legislation a provisional aged pension for<br />
people over 60, because It Is somewhat unreal for someone to be<br />
requiring somebodiy who Is 60 to subject themselves to the work test<br />
AO: to start again?<br />
PM: and when they can't get work, But it's an option for them, they don't<br />
have to write themselves down as on provisional aged pension.<br />
AC: But you're thinking of bringing it down to 55, aren't you?<br />
PM: Not necessarily, no. I don't think this is not pre-judging this committee's<br />
work I don't think that's much of an option. I think what you've got to do<br />
Is get more economic growth, find more jobs, train more people and get<br />
the velocity of people through the pool of unemployment up and give them<br />
work experience. About 80% of those who are long-term unemployed<br />
now, find work, those who find work 80% of them have had some<br />
contact with the labour market program these are the programs of the<br />
Commonwealth which touch about 500,000 people a year and about<br />
of those who are long-term unemployed find themselves keeping<br />
their lob and have had some contact with the labour market programs. So<br />
it's a matter of seeing what we can do with this problem.<br />
AO: One thing a lot of people would suggest you could do straightaway, Is cut<br />
the tax cuts that you have in mind. Now, let me mention to you Professor<br />
Bob Gregory who Is on this unemployment committee that you're looking<br />
at, who says that we've really got to be prepared to pay a lot of money for<br />
these people over 45 who can't find work to support them the community </p>
<p>4<br />
has to be prepared to do something about that. And like many other<br />
people, he's suggesting and same of them Inside your own Government<br />
you'd have to concede are questioning these tax cuts. They're saying<br />
bluntly: look, if you're going to do something about these long-term<br />
unemployed, surely we have to abandon tax cuts for well-paid people?<br />
PM: Let me just make this point on thejA~ cyts. If the country is to make a<br />
commitment to the long-term unemployed, It's got to be a commitment<br />
from more than just the Government it's also got to be a commitment<br />
from the whole community and that includes, of course, business. So the<br />
notion that people should be laying people off as simply efficiency<br />
changes, to find that businesses are not running often as well as they<br />
were and that the moment there Is strong pick-up In demand they'll have<br />
to be re-hired may not be a policy which is advantageous in the end of<br />
business. So If there's going to be a compact in the nation about<br />
committing Itself to higher levels of employment, It's got to extend beyond<br />
the Government.<br />
AO: Indeed, but surely business is simply doing what the Government said?<br />
You've urged them to get leaner and meaner they've done that and<br />
now it's going to be very difficult to turn them around, isn't it? They've<br />
discovered they can do very nicely with fewer people, they just had record<br />
profit?<br />
PM: Until they have a surge In demand, and it might be that they've lost a lot of<br />
skills that they'll pay dearly for to have them returned. So it's not<br />
necessarily the best policy that Is, In corporate terms to be seeing the<br />
unemployment queue rise because often the company demand is not<br />
the problem, it's just simply to get more efficient and they get more<br />
profitable.<br />
AO: Okay, If I could get back to those tax cuts, though. Isn't it almost immoral,<br />
Isn't there something almost immoral about having $ 8 billion that you're<br />
about to hand out In tax cuts to well paid people, when you've got one<br />
million people unemployed those long queues you've just referred to?<br />
PM: I don't think somebody on $ 20,000 a year Is a high paid person.<br />
AO: But up to $ 20,000 they get nothing out of it.<br />
PM: The tax rate at the moment, the marginal rate for somebody on two-thirds<br />
of average weekly earnings, that's $ 20,000, is 38% it's too high. It's just<br />
too high. That's what the tax cuts are there for, they are basically to deal<br />
with that group between $ 20,000 and about $ 45,000. Now I don't regard<br />
those people as wealthy.<br />
AO: Well compared to people without work, they are? </p>
<p>I LL 1 JTU 1 l 1<br />
PM: But the point 13 this: the notion Is we can't afford the tax cuts because of<br />
what, Government debt?<br />
AO: Yes, because you have a huge deficit, which you acknowledge yourself<br />
you wart to get down dramatically.<br />
P M. Yes, I know, but again look at it in the context of any other parameter<br />
we've got just about one of the lowest Government debts to GDP net<br />
debt to GDP In the world. Australlas net debt to GDP Is 12%<br />
Government debt to GDP I'll draw the numbers because I think It's<br />
Important to get this over. France's is 27% of GDP, the United Kingdom's<br />
is 30.3%, Spain's Is 33%, the United States' Is 34.7%, Canada's Is 49%<br />
and ours Is 12%.<br />
AO: But If we're going to make International comparisons, we're not that<br />
heavily taxed are we?<br />
PM: No, but let me make this point. The point is the Government can afford, in<br />
these cicumstances, to run these deficits because our debt to GDP is<br />
quite low. Remember this, where we're not being given credit Is In the<br />
1980s, we ran very large surpluses and we banked them that's why the<br />
debt is now low. We're saying now is the right time to be using that low<br />
debt to GDP in the right circumstances In the economy. Now people say<br />
to me: well, President Clinton Is pulling down fiscal policy in the US so<br />
should you. But the American..<br />
AO: putting up taxes.<br />
PM: The American's In the 80s had an awful fiscal policy, they never had a<br />
surplus, they were massively In deficit right through the 80s. We were<br />
massively In surplus, so therefore our debt to GDP, net debt, is low.<br />
Fiscal policy has to come back towards balance in the medium ternm, but<br />
not in the short-term. The reason the deficit for the coming year is going<br />
to be higher than this year, the starting point<br />
AO: $ 18 billion Instead of $ 16 billion?<br />
PM: because the economy Is just not growing as quickly and receipts are not<br />
coming in. If the economy, therefore, is not growing as quickly.<br />
Investment per se Is not growing as quickly. If we're not going to have a<br />
draw on savings, what's the point of bringing the deficit back earlier?<br />
What is the urgency? The key point is to bring it back in the medium term,<br />
which is what we'll do.<br />
AO: Well, you said you want to get it back to 1% of GDP in 1996/ 97?<br />
PM. That's right. </p>
<p>6<br />
AO: That's a lot of money, $ 13 billon, from your starting point coming up this<br />
year?<br />
PM: Yes, but that's years away, and as the economy responds so too will<br />
receipts, and the Government will do Its normal housekeeping job on the<br />
outlays. The key point is: a measure of any Governments, if you like good<br />
health, In Its Budget Is the level of Its outlays. The outays have risen<br />
because of the cycle of spending we've had to deal with the recession and<br />
its aftermath. As the cycle turns down so too will the outlays our outlays<br />
will be back to one of the lowest In the OECD so the rest of it is an<br />
equation with the receipts. That is, where does the economy go and<br />
what's the receipts harvest.<br />
AO: Well, if we needed any evidence of whether the economy Is still in trouble,<br />
surely today's trade figures and the resulting dollar dive must have had<br />
you worried?<br />
PM: Yes, but again, you've got 1986 commodity prices. Remember this, the<br />
world is basically in recession the United States is growing modestly,<br />
Japan's In recession, Germany is barely out of re cession so too is the<br />
case with Britain and as a result commodity prices are now back to 1986<br />
levels.<br />
AO: It's all true but, with respect, Isn't there always a reason, an excuse as to<br />
why things aren't coming good the way you thought they would?<br />
PM: By any other measure, exports have been growing strongly over the<br />
decade, the qualitative change in exports Is to elaborately transformed<br />
manufactures away from rural and mining products and at any rate I<br />
think it's a little bit too early to be making judge ments about the trends in<br />
the Current Account and the Balance of Payments.<br />
AO: But you were In despair when you felt the need to talk about a ' banana<br />
republic'. We're now within 0.1 of that all-time low, aren't we, on our<br />
currency against the basket of currencies?<br />
PM: Oh yes, but in the meantime we've been comparatively high and<br />
sometimes exceptionally high which has worried us too. The market can<br />
get awfully bullish once things start to turn around. So this a commoditydriven<br />
currency, It's less though today, I think, although I don't think the<br />
market thinks that. The change in composition of our exports to<br />
manufacturers away from primary products, will mean that over time we'll<br />
become less of a commodity-driven currency. But we still are a<br />
commodity-driven currency and when commodities are down, the rate will<br />
be down.<br />
AO: Do you sometimes feel like a little balsa raft just being buffeted by all sorts<br />
of things? Do you feel you have control of the economy? </p>
<p>PMV: I don't think any one person, Individual or Government can have control of<br />
the ecpnIoM-y, but our economy Is growing at the moment about 2.5% to<br />
2,5% to 2 34%<br />
AO: which Is not enough to even make an inroad into unemployment, is it?<br />
PM: Well, It would ordinarily have been the problem Is we've got people<br />
laying people off as you mentioned earlier to be productive. So we've got<br />
the growth bul it's productivity-laden instead of em ployment-laden. If<br />
you're talking about the 80' s it would have been<br />
AO: if it's not one thing, It's another, Isn't it?<br />
PM: That's right. These things are not preordained, but nor Is there any point In<br />
throwing your hands up and saying: well, this Is shocking, It's not running<br />
according to as we wish.<br />
AO: Sure, but the money market Is starting to worry. Isn't it? It Is starting to<br />
show a lack of faith? There has been a number of projections made since<br />
the 1987 crash and a lot of them just don't seem to come good. Where<br />
are these gang-busting trade performances, the avalanche of investment?<br />
They're just not there.<br />
PM: Well they are there and they are gradually happening. I'm sure you'll get<br />
onto McArthur River and the Aboriginal Issue that's another $ 300 million<br />
Investment that's going to happen. There has been quite a number of<br />
those. But the key point is that manufactured exports have risen threefold<br />
since the early 80s, manufacturing production has doubled, the fastest<br />
growing component of our exports is elaborately transformed<br />
manufactures, but while a great part of the basket of our exports is in base<br />
metals and in agriculture when those prices are down In an International<br />
recession so too, probably, will be the Australian dollar. But as the<br />
International recession passes and things start to grow and the demand for<br />
commodities rise, so too, will the Australian dollar.<br />
AO: As it passes, we've just heard more slow-growth from the Americans?<br />
PMV: A low dollar also presents enormous competitive opportunities for<br />
exporters. It means your products in world terms are very much cheaper<br />
and very much more competitive.<br />
AO: And you've got big hopes of getting into Asia. You made a big play about<br />
that while you were In New Zealand, didn't you? What exactly do you<br />
hope to achieve?<br />
PMV: Well, it~ s where the fastest growth and income is in the world, it's in the<br />
Asia/ Pacific, and if we can find ourselves integrated there, if we can<br />
develop the Asia/ Pacific Into an open trading area, then Australia's<br />
opportunities for income and employment growth will be enhanced. </p>
<p>AO: Don't we have a rather awkward situation at the moment, part of which we<br />
alluded to a moment ago, that Australian companies are becoming leaner<br />
and meaner, they're making these good profits but Instead of Investing<br />
them here, they're off investing them In Asia, especially souther China,<br />
and creating jobs there?<br />
PM: Some are but these things find their right balances, and one of the<br />
balances built Into the system Is dividend Imputation, so if companies pay<br />
tax to a foreign treasury they don't get a credit for their dividends here. So<br />
a lot of companies will find the balance between domestic investment and<br />
abroad, but In that investment allowance the development allowance we<br />
established in the One Nation project, which has registered $ 130 billion of<br />
projects which are now starting to roll If just a proportion of them come to<br />
fruition, the economy will be moving, In investment terms, quite nicely.<br />
AO: What are the hopes of a decent trade zone in Asia?<br />
PM: This Is what we're trying to do with APEC now improve its trade<br />
liberalising agenda and we've established an eminent persons group to<br />
kick that process along. Neville Wran is representing Australia on that<br />
group and its report will be ready for the Seattle meeting of the APEC<br />
Ministers In the United States in November. What we Intend to do with<br />
that is try and establish a framework for further trade liberalisation and<br />
hopefully beyond that, harmonisation of tax policies, foreign Investment<br />
policies, packaging, food standards all the things that will make the<br />
velocity of trade greater In the Asia/ Pacific area. There's already<br />
tremendous growth in these economies, you mentioned China, apart from<br />
the established ones like Japan and less so Korea and the rest of the<br />
Tigers and the ASEAN countries, there's already a lot of growth there if<br />
they are more open, they're more liberal economies, there's a greater<br />
opportunity for all of them and for us. And that's why we're working so<br />
hard on these trade policies, on APEC and of course beyond all that the<br />
Uraguay round of the GATT which would set a much stronger background<br />
and framework for freer trade<br />
AO: While our companies are going into Asia, Malcom Fraser has expressed<br />
some concern about foreign firms coming here and buying us out. I<br />
suspect he expressed a fear that a lot of Australians have when he<br />
wondered aloud the other night whether therell be anything left for his<br />
grandchildren to own. Do you recognise that as an emotional concern for a<br />
lot of Australians?<br />
PM: Yes, but again I think what will happen with these businesses they'll be<br />
developed as export businesses into ASIA from the platform of Australia,<br />
by and large. And this can only be good for us In the long term. Now, a lot<br />
of these concers have been expressed about property in the past<br />
weve now seen high prices payed in the eighties for properties, we've<br />
seen particularly Japanese companies selling that property down now for </p>
<p>much lower prices. I mean, they can't carry it away I think there are a lot<br />
of phobias about this and the other thing Is If you're running a current<br />
account deficit and It's got to be funded It will be funded with debt or with<br />
equity.<br />
AO: That's what I was going to ask you I mean there Is a perception that you<br />
are a bit soft on foreign takeovers but in a sense you're In that bind aren't<br />
you, of needing the Income for it, needing the proceeds from takeovers?<br />
PM: Well today's current account for the month $ 1700 million has got to<br />
be funded. It will be funded by debt or by equity and equity means buying<br />
positions In the Australian commerce. Now, this Is not the place to be<br />
arguing with Malcolm Fraser but if Malcolm was really worried about that<br />
he wouldn't have let the seventies go by and drop our trading guard so we<br />
start to develop large levels of debt, bad current account Imbalances by<br />
relying on commodities and letting our manufacturing sector fail to pieces.<br />
I mean, we dropped our guard in the late sixties, seventies and early<br />
eighties and we've payed the piper since. And part of that is foreign equity.<br />
AO: But you're urging constantly more Independence for Australia. It's almost<br />
the battle hymn of your republic I suppose. Rather than attacking the<br />
Monarchy some would say, shouldn't we be tackling more seriously our<br />
dependence on foreign money. I mean, our foreign debt has burgeoned In<br />
recent years, hasn't it, from, I think, it's 32% of GOP up to 43%?<br />
PM: Well, that can only be done in two ways. Lifting our domestic savings and<br />
lifting our own import replacement and exporting capacity and those things<br />
are happening, the latter In particuiar I'm not sure whether you saw the<br />
McKinsey study of 700 smaller exporting companies bt their rate of<br />
growth is phenomenal, 14 percent compound a year. Our problem on our<br />
trade front which Is the generator of our debt, the so-called net income<br />
deficit, Interest payments on the old debt, is about two percent of GDP it's<br />
about eight or nine billion. We've got an eight or nine billion dollar trade<br />
problem to deal with and as we deal with it the debt starts to stabilise. It<br />
can only be dealt with by a high level of Australian savings so we're not<br />
calling on overseas savings and overseas debt and a better productive<br />
base in this country meaning more investments, more exports, more<br />
Import replacement. And all of those things are going on.<br />
AO: Despite all our economic woes you've Indicated that you've spent most of<br />
the time since the election concentrating on Mabo you've signalled that<br />
you obviously want to achieve a major breakthrough in that understanding<br />
with the Aboriginal people. What exactly do you want to achieve there?<br />
PM: Well I think the High Court decision does present a tremendous<br />
opportunity. its the opportunity of evening Australia up, of giving the<br />
Aboriginal people what they've always believed was theirs. And that's a<br />
legal title to the land that was always theirs. And while the High Court has<br />
made this decision to facilitate the decision, a whole set of principles have </p>
<p>got to be developed whereby we give expression now what the High<br />
Court has said Is there Is a native title In the common law which has<br />
existed since settlement In 1788, discovered only In June 1992, but<br />
existed from that time.<br />
AO: What exactly does that mean, do you think, for the Aboriginal people?<br />
PM: I think what it means is that they have a claim on land in this country<br />
which can be facilitated other than by resort to statutory land rights. In<br />
other words instead of the Parliaments of Australia conferring on them a<br />
land right something the community of Australia, via the parliaments,<br />
gives them its something which has more Innate dignity. It's theirs of<br />
right.<br />
AO: Well they're now fearing that In fact the parliaments of Australia are taking<br />
it away from them. I mean given the fine sentiments that have been<br />
expressed about trying to reach this understanding, the reconciliation with<br />
A boriginal peopLe, McArthur River must have come as a surprise to them.<br />
PM: Well I don't think so but I'll come to that In a moment. What we've got to<br />
do is set up a system whereby we establish who has native title, and then<br />
upon having established It, where procedural fairness and compensation<br />
are paid for any use which may be put to that land, subject to that title.<br />
Now hearing claims for native title across Australia will be a test of our<br />
capacity to develop systems because it really means that there Is In<br />
common law a title to land for the Aboriginal people of this country who<br />
can establish an association with it. So Its going to really test our maturity<br />
as a country to see this into place.<br />
AO: You can understand the confusion and the cynicism though can't you,<br />
especially among Aboriginal people. I mean they think, iook the Labor<br />
Government has been in there ten years now, we haven't realy got<br />
anywhere with land rights at all, nothings happened, It's only happening<br />
now because the High Court has put us In a bit of a pickle, put you in a bit<br />
of a pickle, with the Mabo decision. And it's the first real test that comes<br />
along, McArthur River. Well, they go down again, the miners interests are<br />
put first, and they're not even consulted.<br />
PM: It's not really like that. The Aboriginal people themselves made clear to us<br />
that they are prepared to validate titles issued after 1975. Now, the<br />
problem with McArthur River was, there was a project to begin, it needed<br />
the title validated. The Northern Territory Government sald it wouldn't<br />
revive the title. In other words, the title was extinguished. It Issued a<br />
mining right and extinguished forever and always the title. We'e said as<br />
a Commonwealth Govemnment, we reserve the right in the future to revive<br />
that title, after the mining Is complete, so that native title won't be lost.<br />
AO: Will that have to go to a State Tribunal, which has been flagged, or not? </p>
<p>PM: No. Well, that legislation now lays on the table and before its passage<br />
there's an opportunity for the Aboriginal community to negotiate just terms<br />
about the use of that land. And I got a letter from the Northern Land<br />
Council today. which made that point clear.<br />
AO: We did too. They didn't sound too happy in the letter.<br />
PM: No, It says this negotiatons regarding compensation and a just terms<br />
agreement should, as each of the parties has recently stated, continue a<br />
pace pending the passage of the Bill. So, In other words, they've got a<br />
chance to negotiate just terms. We're protecting under our caveat, the<br />
revival of the title, but what we are doing, Is In the Northern Territory<br />
passing the law, validating the title, which means the project proceeds.<br />
Now, Andrew, were the project not to proceed, you could Imagine the<br />
noise which would be around. People would be saying, well, here's Mabo<br />
at its first blush a $ 300 million project hits the fence. You'd have the worst<br />
elements of conservative interests In this country up there blaggarding the<br />
Mabo decision and all it stands for. So, what we're doing, Is doing no<br />
more than the Aboriginal community offered us, that Is, the validation of<br />
these titles, protecting its revival, allowing a discussion about just terms,<br />
getting it off the stocks so It doesn't complicate the broader Mabo<br />
principles.<br />
AO: Well, that maybe what you're doing, but what they're saying, of course, is<br />
it's the other way round. Look, a $ 300 million project comes along and<br />
suddenly these proclaimed rights of ours go out the window,<br />
PM: Again, It depends how the media responds to this. When Coronation Hill<br />
was on, they said this Is terrible.<br />
AO: Is this the pay back for Coronation Hill?<br />
PM: No, the Government has taken a political approach. It should have taken<br />
an analytical approach. When the Government takes an analytical<br />
approach on McArthur River, they say you should have taken a political<br />
approach. I mea n, you can't do It right, In fact, In terms of Aboriginal<br />
Interests In this country, In terms of getting acceptance of a set of<br />
principles for establishing native title and dealing with native title, McArthur<br />
River threatened the prospects of that happening needlessly, In the event<br />
that it failed. So, validating the leases, protecting the revival of the title,<br />
and giving the Aboriginal community time to negotiate lust terms, in my<br />
view, treats Aboriginal interests appropriately, and properly, but<br />
Importantly, lets get on with the ma~ n discussion about Mabo and not<br />
having it sidetracked by a project not proceeding.<br />
AO: It's effectively an emergency that blew up before you could sort everything<br />
out, But how many more McArthur Rivers might there be before it Is<br />
sorted out? </p>
<p>12<br />
PM: Well, they'll be some I suppose. But as I Said, this will test.,<br />
AO: And all be treated the same way?<br />
PM: No, because once the principles are in place, then what'll happen Is, they'll<br />
negotiate. A proponent will negotiate with the Aboriginal community and<br />
they'll arrive at terms for mining through procedural fairness. There will be<br />
a procedure procedural fairness as required under the Racial<br />
Discrimination Act, and there'll be compensation. But by then, there will<br />
be a structure in place. The problem at the moment Is, there is no<br />
structure In place. And were we to let McArthur River fall, the people<br />
opposed to Aboriginal Interests in this country, would have banged the<br />
drum so loudly that I'm quite sure upon reflection, the Aborinal<br />
community would have said we would have been better dispensing with<br />
this one properly.<br />
AO: The-Republ. Lc another drum that you've been banging. Is it a certainty<br />
for the Year 2000, or have you still got a lot of wori
PM: I think there's a lot of work to do with it. But I think the procedure we've<br />
set up for a Committee to look at options for a competent change to a<br />
republic, so at least we all know what we're speaking of. I mean, the<br />
problem at the moment is, It doesn't matter who you are as a<br />
commentator, there are no pieces of paper about what constitutes a<br />
change to a republic of any variety. The point of the Committee headed<br />
by Mr Turnbull is to produce those models, so that at least we'll know what<br />
models we're working in, and people can say, well, a change of this varety<br />
I can support, a change of that variety I couldn't support. And In this first<br />
Instance, at least we'll start to track the course. After that, of course, it's a<br />
matter of whether we have constitutional conventions, Involve the States<br />
and other parties.<br />
AO: Can it happen without the support of the Liberals?<br />
PM; I Well, I prefer that it didn't.<br />
AO: But could it happen without that?<br />
PM: It could happen, but I think it would be better if the Liberals recognise the<br />
fact that their involvement In this process can lead to a more harmonious<br />
and competent change.<br />
AO: So how can you get them across the line? How can you get people like<br />
John Howard and Jeff Kennett to see It your way?<br />
PMV: Well, I think a lot of people In the Liberal Party do.<br />
AO: But those two don't. </p>
<p>" 4I -U I<br />
13<br />
PMV: I know, that's true. And I have said to them that we will give the Uberal<br />
Party time to come to an opinion about this, and that we don't necessarily<br />
want to have only our name on the makers label. That we're quite happy<br />
to have theires there too. But I think the first phase Is Important, and<br />
people can see what is involved in a quite minimal change to the<br />
Constitution.<br />
AO: Can you resist the temptation though Paul Keating the great politician<br />
can he resist the temptation to use this to divide the Liberals, to keep<br />
dividing the Liberals, rather than going for the unity which would certainly<br />
make it a lot easier to work?<br />
PM: Well, I'm Interested in the change rather than worrying about the Liberal<br />
Party. There are plenty of other issues we can deal with the Liberal Party<br />
on.<br />
AO: But how can you convince them of the bona fides then?<br />
PM: Well, I think that just by our actions. That is, I've Invited a fairly broad<br />
committee, a number of people on the conservative side of politics or the<br />
community are on that committee. And once the models are established<br />
I'm quite sure there will be an Informed debate about what constitutes a<br />
minimal change, whether they think there should be change to the reserve<br />
powers, what's the mode of election, should the Head of State be<br />
nominated by the Government, should they be endorsed by the<br />
Parliament, should it have a fixed term. All of these Issues will be<br />
debated, and we can come up what the community thinks is a reasonable<br />
change.<br />
AO: Mr Keating, you'd be very conscious of the television series coming up<br />
next week on Labor in Power, In which you and a number of your<br />
colleagues have been extremely frank, perhaps, on the premise that you<br />
might not have won the election that we've just had.<br />
PM: No, no,<br />
AO: Are you worried they've been too frank?<br />
PM: No. Look, this notion that we've been frank because we might not have<br />
won the election.<br />
AO: Well, why have you been so frank?<br />
PMV: This has been talked up by Phillip Chubb, and good on him, the Producer<br />
of the series. Look, anything I've said In this program I would have been<br />
happy to say win, lose or draw. And I noticed on the weekend In the<br />
Sydney Morning Herald, Alan Ramsey amongst others, had an article on<br />
this, and he's got quotes from these Interviews, and the notion that what </p>
<p>have we got here. V/ ha it Is, is big boys and big girls behaving like they<br />
are.<br />
AO: But hang on. You'e got the Deputy Prime Minister, your current Deputy<br />
Prime Minister, Brian Howe, using words about you like betrayal. And<br />
Robert Rays statlng quote * constantly carping al every meeting and<br />
every sczial c~ casion. Constantly bagging Hawke, Constantly leakin to<br />
the Pres Gallery, trolling upstairs with the latest story to hurt Hawke.<br />
That Is destabilis-ation of the worst and most disloyal kind." He's one of<br />
your Senior Ministers.<br />
PM: I think he was referrg there I haven't seen the series but I think you'll<br />
find he is referring there notionally to my supporters.<br />
AO: We think you.<br />
PM: Well, I don't know. It may be me, but I don't know. But I think Robert is<br />
happy tucked away back there In the Government. I mean, we're back<br />
there, that's all thzt matters. But the idea that it's being told as it is, Is<br />
shocking. I mean, really.<br />
AO: Well, it is unusually frank. As you say, you would have said it anyway<br />
because you're the Leader, but some of these people are looking for jobs<br />
from you, looking for your favour.<br />
PM: Look, again, It's back In history, And I think what does motivate most<br />
people in public life is what they have on their plate right at the moment,<br />
and their aspiralions for change. And this Cabinet has I think a very<br />
healthy approach in that respect. I think a lot of this stuff just slips into the<br />
past.<br />
AO: Well, it does go to an Issue at stake at the moment. It's come up a lot<br />
since the election anyway. And that Is, your style of Leadership, which Is<br />
certainly very different from the consensus style of. Mr Hawke' You are,<br />
suppose, much dominating, much more interventionist, power centred on<br />
what's already been dubbed the oval office, and that you've promoted<br />
really only your supporlers In the Ministry. Are you really Interested in<br />
putting an incredibly firm grip on this Government, it's you and that's it?<br />
PM: I don't think that's a fair description Andrew. I mean, some of this come~ s<br />
from the Press Galery. But look, I took the opportunity with this election<br />
to try and re-make the Ministry. And the younger and newer people who<br />
have joined it will give the Labor Government a new lease on life that it<br />
might not have otherwise had.<br />
AO: There's some merit In that, but It also will require your stronger hand of<br />
guidance, won't it? </p>
<p>PM: Welt, I think that energy that you get from now members joining the<br />
Minr" and Cablnet, and paicuariy, yourgar newer members, Is te sort<br />
of energy I think a Government needs. And I cho-se those people on their<br />
abiltes. And I think they're already showing their ability. But as far as<br />
consultation go-as, I can only say to you that I think the Cabinet process<br />
since December 1991 has been a very happy one. The meeting talks<br />
Issues through. Now, since the elecdon we've got a committee proess<br />
Into place, so some of the issues go off to committees and they come<br />
back to the Cabinet and the debate is truncated, so there is less<br />
discussion. But the whole process Is a pretty fiendly and discursive one.<br />
AO: But again, if I can go back to that Labor In Power series. Gareth Evans I<br />
think it was made the point in that, that under the Hawke style the best<br />
was drawn out of the Ministers, because they were expected to contribute<br />
a lot to this consensus style of Government. That perhaps you will be<br />
sitting on top of Ministers much more?<br />
PM: No. My attitude is, you let Ministers make their own pace provided the<br />
generaJ direction is one where the whole Government Is heading. That Is,<br />
provided the direction Is one which is basically not ultra vires of the policy.<br />
I don't think it's healthy for Prime Ministers to be trying to run the detail of<br />
portfolios. I don't think you should do that. But by the same token, it is<br />
Important in meetings, at the right time, for the Prime Minister to have a<br />
view, But I don't think I tend to choke off debate by putting a view. I tend<br />
to let people have their say.<br />
AO: You don't brook opposition lightly tugh, do you? Can I put it to you, that<br />
you have a habit of really crushing quite ruthlessly opposition at times? I<br />
mean, Kim Beazicy Is said to have never fully recovered from the<br />
-savaging you gave him during the telecommunications debate, And even<br />
you have acknowledged on this program, when we were talng about<br />
Labor In Power, that you went too far.<br />
PM: Well, I think In terms of the poilcy I was correct.<br />
AO: But you lost.<br />
PM: But I lost It, But we did in the end, all of us, cobble together nevertheless<br />
a good policy.<br />
AC: Is there a problem though when you do think you're correct that it's very<br />
hard to shake you from It? That you have this fixation about staying the<br />
course, not losing your nerve?<br />
PM: Because the place never had a break in nearly a quarter of a century. I<br />
mean, the place was Inhabited with politicians who wouldn't stay to<br />
anything. it was just a flim flarn place run by the bureaucracy for most of<br />
the post-war years. The reason it has now made the change to a different </p>
<p>culture, a different sort of society, Is because It's had Ministers who've<br />
meant what they were doing.<br />
AO: Yes, but I'm talng about you and your colleagues, your Ministerial<br />
colleagues, who you will take on and stand up to eye to eye and that's it. I<br />
mean, If you really decide to go for something nothing wiil move you?<br />
PM: Yes, it does, arguments move me. If a Minister is doing a good job, and<br />
he's got a good case, that's fine. I think the notion that I've got a very<br />
Interventionist style In the Cabinet is wrong. And this is a view that floats<br />
around the place perhaps from the hectic days of the 80s. I let Ministers<br />
talk, but in the end, we do bring it to a conclusion. I don't believe in<br />
aimless meetings where I sit mum trying to let a consensus develop for<br />
fear of showing my hand, That I reject as a style of leadership.<br />
AO: Perhaps we're talking about two Paul Keating's? Perhaps, there are two<br />
Paul Keatings? One who is a cynical..<br />
PM: I'm much softer than you think.<br />
AO: There are two sides to this Keating coin I suggest to you. One is the<br />
cynical powerbroker who will resort to just about anything and force his<br />
way through. The other is, at times quite sensitive in some of the<br />
speeches you've made. I'm sure at times even charming, and quite highly<br />
focussed, and desperately trying to think ahead, no doubt about that. But<br />
can you understand, why people find it very hard to get a fix on you? That<br />
they're rather divided over your merits as well, because there are the-se<br />
two people. Which one Is right?<br />
PM: Yes, well, I'm a mixture of things. I am, by and large, I think, nice to<br />
people. I try and draw the best from them, and I stick with them often, or I<br />
help them. Now occasionally, you'li get to the point where you're going to<br />
have a difference of view, and so I'll exercise a view then. I did when I<br />
was Treasurer, and I do as Prime Minister. But this is not in this Cabinet,<br />
a very heavily Interventionist style by me, and I think Ministers would think<br />
that. But these sort of myths spring around. Now, I'm not saying that I'm<br />
some sort of wishy washy sort of character that doesn't have a view. Of<br />
course I have a view. But again, so do Ministers. And I think Ministers<br />
ought to be you choose Ministers, you give them a job, and you let them<br />
go and do it, by and large. And they'll come and ask you, do you think this<br />
Is right, or do you think we should do that, and that's fine, I'll give them a<br />
view. But by and large I let them run. But If it gets to a point where It Is a<br />
problem with direction you've got to have a say, and that's the Prime<br />
Minister's lob.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
