<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2546</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;A CURRENT AFFAIR&#039; - INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON, CH MP, ON CHANNEL 9 TELEVISION NETWORK - 8 MARCH 1972 - INTERVIEWER: MICHAEL SCHILDBERGER</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002546.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
" A CURRENT AFFAIR"<br />
Interview given by the Prime Minister, the Rt Hon.<br />
William McMahon, CH, MP, on Channel 9 television<br />
network 8 MARCH 1972<br />
Interviewer Michael Schildberger<br />
Q. Good morning, Prime Minister. Firstly, * congratulations<br />
on one year in office.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
Q. Have you found being Prime Minister very different<br />
from the way you expected?<br />
PM: Yes I have. It has been far more unpredictable,<br />
and I believe, far more difficult than. I expected it to be.<br />
But you learn to live with it and that is what I have to do.<br />
Q. In what ways more difficult?<br />
PM: Because you are always on the job. You can't ease<br />
up for a moment.... . over the weekends, the holidays, when you<br />
come back to The Lodge, when you go to bed at night, the<br />
problems are still with you. You have to try and solve them.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, twek~ e months ago when you became<br />
Leader, there were-considerable divis-ions in the Party.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Q. Now it appears from the Outside that there also<br />
divisions, perhaps even worse.<br />
PM: No, I differ with you about " ev en worse".<br />
I don't think that's a proper way to put it. In fact it is<br />
not. Butcf course ybu will find differences of opinion within<br />
a Party like mine where you have got people of a very high<br />
order of intelligence, people of great vigour and independence<br />
of mind, and they want to express their' views and you can' t<br />
object to them doing it. But on the whole, I think, we are<br />
much better off than we were a year ago.<br />
Q. Does it concern you, though, that there are these<br />
* possible divisions and that the public hears about them? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, it concerns me, bu~ t I don't think it can be<br />
stopped, and I think the public are wise enough to realise<br />
that in a big Party like ours, with a large number of people<br />
of the kind I've mentioned, I think they understand, because<br />
they understand Australian political life.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, now that you are heading. for another<br />
day's work, what-is foremost in your mind at the moment?<br />
PM: Well, we have a Party meeting this morning, and the<br />
House meets this afternoon. And there are half a dozen motions<br />
on the business paper of the Party, and I am thinking about<br />
those at the moment. The most important of them is that we<br />
will be considering some industrial legislation relating to<br />
the civil service today. That is important and we will give<br />
notice of a bill in the House this afternoon or tonight.<br />
Q. Do you keep thinking about China, the economy". the<br />
doctors at the moment?<br />
PM: Yes, I must think of the lot of them. For the time<br />
being I will eliminate China. because I insisted that the<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs takes over responsibility for the<br />
China problem. The others I will have to watch carefully<br />
myself, particularly the doctors.<br />
Q. Back to your own Party at the moment, PM, do you<br />
feel there is any feeling of despair among Parliamentarians<br />
about the recent poll result?<br />
PM: I think there is disappointment, yes. But not despair.<br />
I don't think you could go that far, and in any event, I<br />
believe when the next unemployment figures come out and<br />
I think they will be pretty good then I think you will<br />
see a change of mind, because you can get affected by momentary<br />
influences.<br />
Q. You have often been criticised for not making enough<br />
decisions<br />
PM: No, I don't. What I would like to have done is for<br />
a record of all the decisions we have made over the last year<br />
* to be published, and I am sure when they are published the<br />
public themselves and they are the judges wnild come to the<br />
concli~ sion E has been a remarkably good performance over the<br />
period of a year, and a more remarkably good performance when </p>
<p>you realise the difficulties we have had to face.<br />
They are pretty good and I am proud of them.<br />
Q. There are many who say, particularly Labor supporters,<br />
but even strong Liberal supporters, that perhaps it<br />
would be time for a change of Government, that you have<br />
had a pretty good innings. Could you agree with this?<br />
PM: No, I don't because what the people must remember,<br />
and I believe what ever person asking questions must<br />
remember, is that the Labor Party don't know where they<br />
are going. If you look at.-the major issues, do they<br />
know where they are going on induatrial lawlessness?<br />
Mr Whitlam says, yes, they would impose fines he is<br />
overruled' by his own Party. Do they know where they<br />
are going on the problem of inflation? No, Mr Whitlam<br />
says they won't, have general pricecontrol. HisoParty<br />
overrules him. Do they know where they are going on<br />
defence, and our wish in the Liberal Party/ Country<br />
Party to be able to play our part in the defence of<br />
South-East Asia? No, they would abolish National<br />
Service and destroy our defence system and withdraw<br />
troops from Singapore/ Malaysia. So a very wide spectrum<br />
they are guilty of both evasion, and-1; I believe, of deceit.<br />
But with us, our policies are positive, we've made them<br />
kn~ own and we will keep on emphasising them. So I believe<br />
it would be disastrous for this country. If I could<br />
put one other aspect to you, if you look at all the<br />
promises they are making, it must be obvious they couldn't<br />
be fulfilled without even worse inflation thah-, we have<br />
got today and without punishing the Australian people.<br />
Q. Do you worry about the pressures of the DLP and the<br />
Country ' Party?<br />
PM: I don't think there are many pressures from the<br />
Country Party. In fact 1.'. am sure it is exaggerated.<br />
And in truth I get on very well with Doug Anthony and with<br />
the rest of the Country Party members of Cabinet. So far<br />
as the DLP is concerned, until the moment, they have been<br />
very good friends of min'e, and the only great difficulty<br />
I have had with them is over the amalgamation. What must </p>
<p>What must be remembered is that we must make the decisions<br />
and we make them in the nation's interest, and if we think<br />
we are right, then of course for the moment we have to<br />
disagree with them, and we have done so on this occasion.<br />
But gerEally speaking, I think I could say that I am on<br />
very good terms-wikk certainly with Vince Gair, Mr Gair,<br />
and also with Jabk Kane.<br />
Q. When you arrive at work, now, Mr Prime Minister, do<br />
you worry about the crises that you might face today?<br />
PM: No, you can't worry about them because you have got<br />
to be-reading the papers and reading the minutes you get<br />
from the Department and signing the letters, and you haven't<br />
got enough time to worry.<br />
Q. Prime Minister do you feel and I don't mean to~ be<br />
nasty with this question that Mr Gorton is still looking<br />
over your shoulder?<br />
PM: I don't give it very much thought. You have got so<br />
much to do in this business-of being a Prime Minister,<br />
so many difficult decisions to make that you have to<br />
concentrate on the business of Government and try and<br />
forget the personalities. So I don't give that muich!<br />
thought, I have to confess.<br />
Q. Do you think Mr Gorton has become somewhatcf a<br />
folk hero now to the public?<br />
PM: I don't know about being a folk hero, and in fact<br />
I won't comment on him at all. I believe that it is better<br />
to keep personalities out of these problems and get on with<br />
the business of government and that is exactly what I intend<br />
to do.'<br />
Q. Prime Miniister, on that subject, what do you believe has<br />
been yotr great achievement during the first twelve months?<br />
PM: I-think there have been a number. The first one that.<br />
I had to face was the problem of the Premiers and Commonwealth/<br />
State relationships. That was a pretty difficult problem<br />
and I believe we have solved it. And if I could put it to<br />
you this way as frankly as I ' can, had it not been for the </p>
<p>BHP issue on price rises, the last Premiers' Conference<br />
would have been a triumph, the only one I can remember.<br />
Secondly, overseas we had to repair a few bridges between<br />
the United States and ourselves and I am sure we have done it.<br />
Third, we had the problem of trying to control industrial<br />
lawlessness, and I think this is one of the major issues<br />
that will face the people at the next election. Ihave said<br />
to you that today we will be giving notice of a bill that<br />
I think will indicate clearly where we stand., But on such<br />
matters, other matters as education, as immigration and<br />
a dozen and one other, if we.-can only get our message to the<br />
public, I am sure they will realise that we have done a<br />
tremendous amount in a year and we have done it und~ r<br />
difficult conditions.<br />
Any failures?<br />
Yes, of course there have been. Nbt so much failures but<br />
we haven't been able to achieve all our purposes. It is<br />
best to admit that and to admit it clearly. But on the whole,<br />
and pretty substantially our way, what we have done has been<br />
in the interests of the nation,<br />
You must have a particular goal for the next twe-lve<br />
months? Yes, first of all-to get economicconditions running<br />
along well so thiat we can cut unemployment down to an<br />
acceptable number, so ~ aat we can give people reaso ! n to<br />
believe that they have confidence in the future and we can<br />
do all those things in health and in education and in -public<br />
works and services of the kind they want and they should<br />
get, and if we can control inflation and get control of<br />
industrial lawlessness, we will ensure they do get it.<br />
Prime Minister, do you have any fears for th2 next twelve<br />
month Not fears, exactly, no. I believe our main problem is<br />
of communication with the people, and if we can go on the<br />
way we have been going on and putting up the performances and<br />
* getting them recognised, then I believe the people will have<br />
their confidence restored an~ d they will have complete<br />
confidence in the Liberal/ Country Party and make certain<br />
we win the next election.<br />
Th ank you very much indeed, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: PM: PM: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
