<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11395</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          ADDRESS AT BOOK LAUNCH          &amp;quot;THE MENZIES LECTURES 1978-1998&amp;quot;          PARLIAMENT HOUSE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.................</p>
<p>  Thank you very much David for those very warm words of introduction. To</p>
<p>   Alan Gregory who has provided magnificent leadership to the Menzies Trust</p>
<p>   over so many years, and particularly do I welcome Denis Napthine, the newly</p>
<p>   elected Leader of the Opposition here in Victoria.</p>
<p>  The predecessor of mine as Prime Minister and Leader of the Liberal Party,</p>
<p>   Sir Robert Menzies, and I shared a number of common experiences separated</p>
<p>   by many years and one of them, of course, was a long period in opposition.</p>
<p>   I hope that that is not your lot in life but there will be a period in Opposition.</p>
<p>   It's a period which is immensely challenging. It's a period that comes the</p>
<p>   way of most people who spend any length of time in public life. I mean,</p>
<p>   you could be lucky like somebody say Graham Richardson, for example, who</p>
<p>   was never in opposition. You can waltz into parliament and be there for</p>
<p>   a short period of time and then go out having never experienced the challenges</p>
<p>   of opposition. But if you are to have a full political existence your predecessor</p>
<p>   had challenging years in opposition and came to be, in my view, one of the</p>
<p>   great Premiers that Australia has seen, certainly in the period after World</p>
<p>   War II.</p>
<p>  So to you, Denis, I wish you well. You will have the total cooperation and</p>
<p>   understanding of your federal parliamentary colleagues. We will work together</p>
<p>   with you to provide a strong alternative to the new Government here in Victoria.</p>
<p>  I want to welcome so many of you as old friends, as supporters, as fellow</p>
<p>   Liberals, as members of the National Party, and I am delighted to acknowledge</p>
<p>   the presence of my old Cabinet colleague, Peter Nixon. We shared many experiences</p>
<p>   together in the Fraser/Anthony Government between 1975 and 1983. And I also</p>
<p>   acknowledge with gratitude the presence of so many members of the Menzies</p>
<p>   family.</p>
<p>  This is quite a pleasure for me because I remember the first experience</p>
<p>   I had I delivering a Menzies lecture in the circumstances described by Alan</p>
<p>   Gregory back in 1980 when I was Treasurer in the Fraser Government. And</p>
<p>   again I had the privilege in 1996 not long after our victory in that year</p>
<p>   as Prime Minister to again deliver the lecture.</p>
<p>  This Trust, of course, has its genesis at Monash University when in 1976</p>
<p>   members of the Monash University Liberal Club under the leadership of Michael</p>
<p>   Kroger resolved that they would create the Menzies Trust in the image of</p>
<p>   the Deakin Trust of the Melbourne University Club.</p>
<p>  Heather Henderson recalls how her father was approached to lend his name</p>
<p>   to the Trust which he so readily did. And so it was established and it had</p>
<p>   great names in the Victorian Liberal cause - Alan Gregory, Stan Guilfoyle,</p>
<p>   Andrew Peacock and Sir Billy Snedden. The meeting was set up with Sir Robert</p>
<p>   to meet members of the club executive. It was to have been held in June</p>
<p>   in 1978 but unfortunately Sir Robert died several months before then and</p>
<p>   the meeting could not take place.</p>
<p>  Alan Gregory records the intense interest of Dame Pattie while she was alive</p>
<p>   and of Heather Henderson in the activities of the Trust and I remember being</p>
<p>   honoured by Heather's presence when I delivered the lecture in 1996. And</p>
<p>   as patron of the Australian Liberal Students Federation it's always a special</p>
<p>   pleasure for me to be associated with any event that brings into focus the</p>
<p>   contribution of Liberal students to political thought and political debate</p>
<p>   in Australia. And I am very pleased that the Government I lead, and David</p>
<p>   Kemp in particular as Education Minister, has pushed for fulfilment, so</p>
<p>   far frustrated by the Senate I might say, of our commitment for genuine</p>
<p>   Liberal freedom in relation to membership of student unions. And it was</p>
<p>   from the activities of the members of the Monash University Liberal club</p>
<p>   and many other Liberal clubs around Australia that our policy on those issues</p>
<p>   was devised.</p>
<p>  The lectures presented in this book are a kaleidoscope of Liberal and conservative</p>
<p>   thought over the years. I use those two words very deliberately because</p>
<p>   one of the special characteristics of the Liberal Party of Australia is</p>
<p>   that it has, unlike some other centre right parties around the world, it</p>
<p>   has been the trustee of both the Liberal and the conservative traditions</p>
<p>   in Australia. And the pluralism of the Liberal Party on many things reflects</p>
<p>   that joint trusteeship. We are not an exclusively conservative party nor</p>
<p>   are we an exclusively small "l" Liberal Party, we are a combination</p>
<p>   of the two. And it's an important obligation of any Liberal Party leader</p>
<p>   to reflect and to respect that tradition.</p>
<p>  There are many favourite stories, of course, recounted of Sir Robert in</p>
<p>   this book of lectures. There is the one attributed to Geoffrey Blainey,</p>
<p>   who after Menzies had won the federal election in 1949 Sir Robert was approached</p>
<p>   by a young journalist who said "please sir, now that you have won will</p>
<p>   you be answerable to the vested interest that supports you?" To which</p>
<p>   Sir Robert gave the classic reply "Young man, please leave my wife</p>
<p>   out of this debate."</p>
<p>  Alan Gregory quotes those wonderful words of the late Sir Paul Hasluck which</p>
<p>   many of us heard at that magnificent function he organised at the Southern</p>
<p>   Cross Hotel in 1989 to honour the 90th birthday of Dame Pattie</p>
<p>   Menzies. And Sir Paul said "the Menzies post-war years stand as a great</p>
<p>   period in Australian history. Australia had stability. Australia had a sound</p>
<p>   base for reorganisation. There was regularity, high standards and the utmost</p>
<p>   probity in all aspects of government. Australia stood with dignity and growing</p>
<p>   respect in a reconstructed world. Our economy was managed with care. To</p>
<p>   use a phrase of the period, we walked the knife-edge of inflation without</p>
<p>   losing balance. We kept a high level of employment. We guarded the overseas</p>
<p>   balances. Great care was taken over all appointments to public office and</p>
<p>   scrupulous control of government expenditures. In Menzies' years in Australia</p>
<p>   tradition was respected and progress was soundly based."</p>
<p>  In his 1985 lecture David Kemp recorded that when Sir Robert left office</p>
<p>   unemployment was under two per cent, inflation was almost non-existent and</p>
<p>   a person on average earnings paid about 16 per cent of his income in tax</p>
<p>   at a top marginal rate of 27.</p>
<p>  I reflected on my own impression of Menzies in my 1996 lecture when I said</p>
<p>   "Menzies political genius lay in that basic affinity with the aspirations</p>
<p>   of the Australian people. He understood the priority they placed on jobs,</p>
<p>   on raising living standards, on home ownership, on high economic growth,</p>
<p>   on a sense of national unity and on opportunities for their children that</p>
<p>   were greater than they themselves had experienced. And he developed priorities</p>
<p>   in national policy making and a role for national government that enabled</p>
<p>   those aspirations to be achieved."</p>
<p>  It is appropriate, as Alan said, that we should gather here in this beautiful</p>
<p>   Parliament building in Melbourne to launch this book because it was here</p>
<p>   in this building in this Parliament that RG Menzies began his political</p>
<p>   career. And it will be appropriately in this building that the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   Parliament will return in May of 2001 as one of the great events of the</p>
<p>   Centenary of Federation to sit after having re-enacted as best we can the</p>
<p>   inauguration of the Commonwealth Parliament in the Exhibition building to</p>
<p>   then sit here in ordinary session and to honour the magnificent achievement</p>
<p>   of 100 years of the Australian Federation in an event that I believe will</p>
<p>   in a very symbolic way unite all of the Australian people across the political</p>
<p>   divide and irrespective of their beliefs and attitudes on other issues.</p>
<p>  At Prahran Town Hall Menzies delivered his first political speech in 1926.</p>
<p>   He was accompanied by his uncle Sydney Sampson and he turned to his uncle</p>
<p>   after the speech and asked how he went to which the reply was "My dear</p>
<p>   boy, as an argument to the High Court of Australia it was admirable; as</p>
<p>   an address to the electors, it was hopeless. The art of political advocacy</p>
<p>   is the art of judicious and varied repetition." I have never heard</p>
<p>   that suggested before. "Until you learn to repeat yourself with skill</p>
<p>   you will never make a good politician." I will not make any comment</p>
<p>   on that.</p>
<p>  But the lecturers over the last twenty years have represented, as I said,</p>
<p>   a tremendous kaleidoscope not only of thought but of personalities that</p>
<p>   have richly contributed to the intellectual and the intellectual leadership</p>
<p>   of Australia.</p>
<p>  Great defenders of our institutions and our systems that have made us strong.</p>
<p>   They have included Sir Garfield Barwick, Sir Harry Gibbs, Dame Leonie Kramer,</p>
<p>   Sir Paul Hasluck, Geoffrey Blainey, Sir Zelman Cowen, Allan Martin, Don</p>
<p>   Argus, Hugh Morgan, Peter Costello, David Kemp, Jeff Kennett as well as</p>
<p>   successive Liberal Party leaders.</p>
<p>  The speech, of course, that stands out in the minds of many was that delivered</p>
<p>   by Margaret Thatcher in 1981. I might say it was delivered where it</p>
<p>   was always meant to be delivered at the university in circumstances of great</p>
<p>   difficulty. The university administration, as Ron Wilson describes, was</p>
<p>   less than enthusiastic about the visit and on a number of occasions urged</p>
<p>   the Trust and the Club to hold the lecture off the campus. The Hall committee</p>
<p>   refused to accommodate requests for a large lecture hall as a venue. The</p>
<p>   matter was only resolved when the Vice Chancellor rang the club president</p>
<p>   at home to advise that due to the intervention of Malcolm Fraser as Prime</p>
<p>   Minister the Blackwood Hall had suddenly become available. A sad footnote</p>
<p>   to that particular visit was that a letter of thanks delivered on behalf</p>
<p>   of Margaret Thatcher by her then parliamentary secretary, Ian Gow, proceeded</p>
<p>   by only a few days his murder by the Irish Republican Army.</p>
<p>  Ladies and gentlemen, today is an occasion to honour the contribution, not</p>
<p>   only of Sir Robert Menzies to the life of our nation but also to honour</p>
<p>   the importance within our community of keeping alive the spirit of ideas</p>
<p>   and the spirit of political debate. It has to be said that we on our side</p>
<p>   of politics, if I can use the broad collective, have not always been as</p>
<p>   successful as we might have been in defending and postulating the intellectual</p>
<p>   and philosophical basis of our beliefs. It is not only important to win</p>
<p>   elections, it is also important to win arguments and if you can win both</p>
<p>   elections and arguments then you have been truly successful.</p>
<p>  Menzies was the greatest election winner that Australia has ever seen. He</p>
<p>   was also of course a great winner of arguments and a great advocate in his</p>
<p>   cause. You were never in any doubt as to where he stood on an issue. He</p>
<p>   was not one for temperising, he was not one for mincing words, he was not</p>
<p>   one for deferring to fashionable views of what ought to occur if those views</p>
<p>   coincided with what he perceived to be the national interest. He was a man,</p>
<p>   in my view, who quite correctly believed that on some issues you should</p>
<p>   be willing to argue for fundamental change and on other issues you should</p>
<p>   be willing to stand by something that continued to work and continued to</p>
<p>   work in the national interest. It is an approach that guides and instructs</p>
<p>   me in my attitude to public issues in Australia at present. I respect the</p>
<p>   plural tradition of the Liberal Party. I respect the fact that the Liberal</p>
<p>   Party has always regarded itself as a defender of free thought and individual</p>
<p>   conscience.</p>
<p>  For that reason and because this is essentially a gathering of people who</p>
<p>   could loosely be described as being broadly supportive of the Liberal Party</p>
<p>   in the Australian political milieu I have refrained from making any explicit</p>
<p>   reference to matters that are the subject of political debate in Australia</p>
<p>   at the present time because the Liberal Party, quite correctly in my view,</p>
<p>   is affording to its parliamentary members the privilege of a free or open</p>
<p>   vote on that issue and I think that is the right and correct thing for us</p>
<p>   to do. Can I say two other things. And that is that in Sir Paul's great</p>
<p>   address to Dame Pattie's 90th anniversary.90th birthday</p>
<p>   party celebration 10 years ago he spoke of the stability and strength of</p>
<p>   Australia during the Menzies years and he spoke of the regard in which Australia</p>
<p>   was held at that time.</p>
<p>  Although the circumstances now are very different and Australia is a very</p>
<p>   different country now from what it was in those days and to draw slavish</p>
<p>   comparisons between the two would be an immense error, there is nonetheless</p>
<p>   a resonance in those words when you look at the condition of Australia at</p>
<p>   the present time. We have not had such strong economic conditions in this</p>
<p>   country at any time, in my belief, than we have now since World War II.</p>
<p>   It is also fair to say that in recent times Australia has demonstrated to</p>
<p>   the rest of the world with a clarity and speed, her capacity to display</p>
<p>   strong leadership on foreign affairs and defence issues within the Asian</p>
<p>   Pacific region. The regard in which Australia is held not only in the region</p>
<p>   but around the world because of the action we took in relation to East Timor,</p>
<p>   an action that respected the long term importance of a close relationship</p>
<p>   between Australia and Indonesia but nonetheless also respected the importance</p>
<p>   of standing up for what was right and what was in the Australian national</p>
<p>   interest.</p>
<p>  And that action has won for Australia enormous respect. It has demonstrated</p>
<p>   our capacity to act strongly and independently and with a sense of not only</p>
<p>   the national interest but also a sense of what is right within the Australian</p>
<p>   community and within the region and I believe that Australia's standing</p>
<p>   as a consequence of that is immeasurably greater than would have been the</p>
<p>   case if we had fumbled and passed over an opportunity to display such tremendous</p>
<p>   leadership.</p>
<p>  I am delighted that this launch today coincides with the second volume of</p>
<p>   Alan Martin's biography which I will read as well with intense interest.</p>
<p>   I read the first instalment of that biography some years ago as many in</p>
<p>   this audience would have and I was struck by the, I think, the intellectual</p>
<p>   rigour, the accuracy and the historical perspectives of it and I look forward</p>
<p>   to the second volume.</p>
<p>  I remember the phrase that was used by Sir Robert after his deposing by</p>
<p>   his own party in 1940 and he described how he was going to go away and bleed</p>
<p>   a while. And he did, he bled a while but he recovered from the experience</p>
<p>   and he returned with very great strengths and an enhanced capacity and went</p>
<p>   on to become Australia's longest serving and greatest Prime Minister.</p>
<p>  This volume and those who have contributed to it I thank them, I honour</p>
<p>   their contribution to political and intellectual thought in Australia I</p>
<p>   have great pleasure in launching it and finally Alan could I pay a very</p>
<p>   special tribute to you for the enormous leadership that you have shown in</p>
<p>   this enterprise. You have been the driving force behind the Trust, you have</p>
<p>   kept it alive you have gathered support, you have won the respect of all</p>
<p>   of us and today's gathering is a very special tribute to you as well as</p>
<p>   to the memory of Australia's greatest Prime Minister. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
