<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19033</transcript-id>
    <title>Vietnamese New Year Festival Opening Ceremony</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/02/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Fairfield Showground, Sydney</p>
<p>In 1977, a small wooden vessel threaded its way through the Gulf of Thailand and the waters to our north before finding landfall near Darwin.</p>
<p>The boat's cargo:</p>
<p> * 	Thirty one people in search of a better life.</p>
<p>The boat's name:</p>
<p> * 	“Tu Do”... Freedom.</p>
<p>Friends, this land tells us many stories.</p>
<p>From the world's oldest living culture to those who came on the first wooden boats of the First Fleet, to today's newest migrants coming from war-torn Africa.</p>
<p>But perhaps one of the most remarkable is the story of the Vietnamese.</p>
<p>Vietnamese migration was particularly challenging for us because it was the first broad-scale migration from Asia since the gold rush.</p>
<p>I don't want to minimise the challenges you sometimes faced.</p>
<p>But overwhelmingly, Australians opened their doors and opened their hearts.</p>
<p>Now, 38 years after the first Vietnamese came to Australia, this community is seeing its pioneers grow old.</p>
<p>Its children succeed and prosper in all aspects of national life.</p>
<p>Its grandchildren speak in broad Aussie accents.</p>
<p>But one thing that does not change is Tet.</p>
<p>A time for visiting loved ones, honouring ancestors and giving gifts.</p>
<p>A time to forget the worries of the year just past and to embrace the possibilities of the year ahead. </p>
<p>A time to remember your old homeland from the safety and prosperity of the new.</p>
<p>Friends, you came from a sad and difficult past.</p>
<p>And sought a place to build a new and brighter future.</p>
<p>You looked out across those seas to a land under the Southern Cross.</p>
<p>A place that celebrated freedom in its laws and intuitions in the same way you treasured freedom in your hearts.</p>
<p>Friends, so many Vietnamese refugees came to these shores with only the clothes on their backs.</p>
<p>Yet you did not come empty-handed.</p>
<p>You came with hope to this land of new beginnings.</p>
<p>Hope, ambition and high expectations that honoured the welcome offered by your new home.</p>
<p>You matched opportunity with effort.</p>
<p>Citizenship with commitment.</p>
<p>Acceptance with goodwill.</p>
<p>So four decades since the journey began, we are here as civic leaders to share this festival and to say: thank you.</p>
<p>We enriched by your culture.</p>
<p>Strengthened by your hard work.</p>
<p>And blessed by your faith in the nation you chose and made your own.</p>
<p>Happy New Year!</p>
<p>May the Year of the Snake bring happiness and prosperity to you and all those you love.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
