<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3654</transcript-id>
    <title>OIL AND URANIUM EXPLORATION - GOVERNMENT GUIDELINES</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003654.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER Press Statement No. 468<br />
12 March 1975<br />
OIL AND URANIUM EXPLORATION<br />
GOVERNMENT GUIDELINES<br />
The Government reaffirms that it seeks Australian<br />
participation in oil exploration, but has decided that<br />
foreign companies undertaking oil exploration in<br />
Australia need not necessarily seek Australian participation<br />
at the initial or ' grass roots' level of their exploration<br />
activities i. e. up to the detailed proving stage, but that<br />
in exploitation and development beyond these stages, the<br />
Australian Government expects such companies to offer<br />
Australian interests, private and public, every reasonable<br />
opportunity as is practicable for participation in these<br />
projects. The Government reaffirms that the development<br />
of any oil * discoveries, as for minerals generally, will<br />
be subject to approval by the Government in accordance<br />
with the guidelines published by the Prime Minister<br />
on 3 November 1974.<br />
The Government makes clear too, that search<br />
f or uranium in the Northern Territory will be done only<br />
by the Atomic Energy Commission. Export licences will<br />
not be issued where there is exploration with foreign<br />
participation arranged after 31 October 1974. The<br />
Australian Atomic Energy Commission will be the only<br />
exporter of uranium wherever found.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T.. </p>
<p>GUIDELINES FORl r'Ow* H N WILITTrY PARTWI'TPATrON IN<br />
AND) ( ONTI1efl ( W ; II: ti irqirN [ FNiI WoI ZY<br />
i n s ; i i I i -in I t oret' i<br />
' ihli Governmiient' s baicC i i s PtCo cnsuiie Lli Awn: t rali i'<br />
minera rii'I osourcu arou doleIopil inI suich a w. Iy as to 1br i i loii IiiIII<br />
WwwuiLtsL to the AustralIianu pcVo. if t his. obu~ ict-i I . in to Ao<br />
I ' Ji! vt: d, ultimate( nfiluE ini ia t y~ lo t LiiAIIlora ioni, dvl c t t<br />
ona~ ia, whlet her Austraia n or Foriqn-owodd, eng( aged~ it)<br />
unpIorLi dtl) tr. lV v ' opmontF or pri n) i() i. in, muustCLCofio rui wi th the<br />
nalt inal interes't. The Covoiuuioii will. use all of itPs pnorh,<br />
InirInq i ts export and e: xcIh nq contrvol J) 0wnr s, to achie ve<br />
Y[ ho G; overnmienit des ires;, as; ai ma jor oh]( c t. iye tQ promo Ie<br />
Australianli eq. uit y An and contriol of itCs resource~ s and iridust ries,<br />
aniii iiid) iilUL Australian ownershI i p compa-tibal o xii t Atralia' 5 longjtermi<br />
cap it al requirements adi Ms neeicds for access t-o markets,<br />
ManVdfced technology anid kflo\ I-iow The Coveruuwunt recoqn uses,<br />
hou'vor that many of the i iuort2 in P exis tinhj unterpr isuengri~ dod<br />
in t he dev'elopmentC of Aus t ral i~ esourrc es are under fore ign<br />
eofui L ~' ontrol. For this reason, the promotion of Aus tralIian<br />
oqu. ity in and contlt. of our cohnurces and industries must be:<br />
v icoal~ an a longer-term Objent i<br />
( iii) Rloles for the Public anud Pri vat-e Sectors.<br />
The Government . recoqnisos that private participation in<br />
explorat i. on and development " Q1i cont inue to On essential. A<br />
MMiU liuivma l of activity will he achijeved onl y if there i. q<br />
AIpMa, r tioiiipda tpi orniv abtoet h ebnyt erppurbilsiecs . b o ITLhise Gsouvcehr nmaenn tt hbere cPoMgAn aizrde s tahlseo' T~ aa<br />
part1i cipatLion by conupan Les w il b. e dopoenit, on the prlopect of it<br />
PC? tiu iiOi capit al hip loyed ui ilis1. comnhl( urate with the h igh<br />
rinsnos iCt. 1iiCs involved.<br />
Q v) xr lora t ion<br />
The Government seeks Australian participation in mineral<br />
expl1oration. it bolieves lho wever t hat becauge of the r isk!;<br />
inVivd and Australia ' s Ilii itad capital resourices it in mo11c e<br />
a op. vt ant to secure a htiq1h doqvcoo oh~ Auatraioc n equity part ici pation<br />
ant: h n production sta96. The ' level opnient of aay mineral discoveries;<br />
1willo, f course, he subject t o npprov" l by the Government in<br />
aWCcd rdancL w. ith these quidel i. ns<br />
Prorossinq<br />
The Government's objectivo is the maximui level of mineral.<br />
proce:. snc cons is tent withi thle rati onal use Wt Australia's re:. Ourcos. </p>
<p>' i'Iit t int*( lni*( I al I ma jo) r inerai<br />
-ol ai ly 4ikiV-' TI1t ! po i. of C() it. dC L uil I be<br />
" oIL Hii t o' Vo fo rkril n( l: I~ a I qy ' ah) o I1Wt t~ i~ I rI It t) er( I f~* r'h<br />
L I i I ( 0oVt Jim( I ~ i I IH i i i i iiit I t o1i n imi w i Ihi in 1 h " i<br />
I; renponsili i Li V ho 1T reauiL onl Vo ret'tj q owtiors i i1)<br />
,1i on riallcilij ( t.,) poc t It 1L, i i i a; L er V it l) u Env! rotliont and<br />
k. k uitti, v, tLL i onf onl en1v] i oliie a1 I: s1, andt 1 I iv Al i n Is Lt! r f or U rl iii<br />
i I Oihil Deveoment-ioi. bant and reqf Vaal asp; ect s. Thki WIi I1<br />
-wi h. Governmentt in oitnut ing that ntaxit oum benelfi L acc~ rue<br />
io Ulto0~ it 0 ]. lOat tr VeCof). I an at: w hio le. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
