<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>272</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES  </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000272.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
kdr. Presidegnt, ladies and jsntle<br />
It is no moe form of words for me to say that I am<br />
delighted to be here,, because this is a very exciting oaasiozi<br />
It is a wry exciting act of raith and of ina.; inution.<br />
We ure accustomed, In Australia,, to think or ourselves as<br />
lukiing an almost painfully now country. I daresay that some of<br />
As here today have thought what a contwast there would be between<br />
this bohoolt so far ans It has gpoet and . Vsminmter School In<br />
London. Juif we have enough imagination to tiarn our eyos backc<br />
Into history we will roeulise thatpafter all that Zciool had a<br />
3egmS9g wAn Westminster itself had a bekning, It in one of<br />
t~ ie things that I like thinking about when I's in ; London, that at<br />
V-A very tim when . iotmixistor 14ll was beind built, the Ureat<br />
.[ al of Auflana Rufus* there were fields and furm -iun~ d it.<br />
aid when the Abbey sprang Into existence, the vhi4 shining Aauay,<br />
as it was at that time, thero were fields ja4 frm~ s around it.<br />
mdc need every now and then to have an act of faith in<br />
order to lift ourselves above the ordinary comam round. I don't<br />
know whether any of you, or many of you, have had the opportunity<br />
of seeing the great EUl Cathedral In the esstern provinces of<br />
Sagland a nagnificent cathedral rising out of a villip, built<br />
at a time when there were a fey v; ljaes and a feow farms scattered<br />
around. What a tremondous act of inazination ind faith.<br />
Therefore I as delightedo not only to be here, on such an<br />
occasion, but I an particularly Interested in the name that hasn<br />
aeon chosen. 4ec aum 1 am a poeut believor in the contirnuity of<br />
good traditionst a sense of continuity , a sense that we are not<br />
hera today and gone tomorrow, a sense Ufat we are part of' an<br />
izmotal procession of huna'i beings. This is the Me~ At : ning, i<br />
iellove, in the national character.<br />
And there at Jestuinster, whose fn you have taken what<br />
doe ones, I even today? The at~ hall of iluliam Rufus built In<br />
the -% velfth oentury, still sta g, q rimed with smake an two<br />
occasions in its history, stll thor. the ! al in which Clarles<br />
i was tried; the UIll outside whichoday looki;-.&amp; Into<br />
Parllaaent Place,, stands tine atuo of 0liver Cromwell; h Hall<br />
out of which opened the doors into little, rooms in which the whole<br />
of the Suglish Comoon Law was developed,, the agat uiediaeval<br />
Oourts of the tLing's iJench and of the Common kleas and of the<br />
444hequor, This Is, of all plaoes In our omunity of n&amp; ationsO the<br />
most fascin~ iting and the most historic. And just over tin road,<br />
sao to speak, the coeat Abey with all that It contains of Jt'itish<br />
~ Ii story. How this 1L think Is something that I. hope every boy<br />
who ames here viM aw to understand. I would li1e to think that<br />
the full. significance or what has happened and is ! zppening, in<br />
Jestainater becaine known. We are so acmastaned today to having<br />
0,, rlianents. 3a people think that we have too many. I<br />
oocauionially share that fae, p but only in a momentary way. The<br />
rirst Parliament that ever atq sat in Iestminster " all, The model<br />
PAirliament sat in iesttiinstor lall. And today, If You wish to &amp; V<br />
In or ambers wish to 4o in to the '" Ouse of Commons one of their<br />
main avenues of approach is Viraigh eaistr ; a1l. it at Il<br />
remains the great source of all our parliament.-Ary Instituztions,,<br />
and of all the Or~ t institutions of Vie Comoi Uiv, Vlwru in no<br />
Ar" Of -ff : TIE IjIM13= 8 rw las </p>
<p>place to compare with it* And thwrerores, Oa I Wa to the boys,<br />
there is no name to vapare vith it. Ths s it m.&amp; nificent and<br />
i &amp; inative decision.<br />
air, one other thing that iL vuuld like to say is this.<br />
It Is no easy matter to create a School; it is no easy matter to<br />
say, " Well, we must start; we viii jet our first b ilding.<br />
Jomeday we will. jst our seoondand our third and our fbifth. And<br />
in due course the jrounds of the school will Wo developed and we<br />
will have all those thins. that So with a ; twat ~ co1" It must<br />
rather try the patience for people who are no longer jromgto be<br />
able to postpone to their childrtsn the satist ct o hat te<br />
would have loved to have had themselves In seeing th, thing<br />
ecupleted. And yet, what I want to remind them of is this: that<br />
this In not just creating scow gounds, or creating saw buildings.<br />
Zhis Is creating a sc~ ool which, so t-at it is properly understood<br />
and properly aapported, will be tort for hundreds of yamrs, and<br />
wi1l itself boooe the spiritual 2uther of oths.-scaiools in other<br />
places. There have been very great cluanges in the world of<br />
education. If we p back to the middle apss when higher education<br />
was scholastic# vas conducted against a basis almost entirelyof<br />
rellion, whten It was considered t~ w , erqiisite of ticue who<br />
were destined Zor the Churoh, when It involved almo3t monasntic<br />
excl-aliau frus the world when it dealt entirely with classical<br />
knoledp, we find one ; Mn of * ducation, a-d one : or X'iich I have<br />
myself a protbubd respect. jkat nov the wheel has t Lraed, Today<br />
higher eduo~ tion is taking place not In the upe of nediaeval<br />
scholastiim but in the age of science and tachnology, in which<br />
man Is actully beginning to burst fromtbe surface of th. earth in<br />
Is exploration and aroh for krnoidedjs9<br />
sIo the whole matter has changed. It seems to As to have<br />
somthinig of ugency rather than omethinj of reflection. It is a<br />
search for something new, rat&amp; eWr thian the study of something old*<br />
Sat the choice Is not quite so gim. as thiat, bocause it<br />
still remains tnie that there is no higher education -wort.-the<br />
namne unless It embraces not only the knowledge of physical<br />
science but the knowledge of mankind# the knowled,; e, of the<br />
huiltest a broad sweep of education, a broad and balanced<br />
training. And that Is somthing that we aivays have to keep In<br />
mind so that we won1t be, tempted as so mmmy people are, to adopt<br />
as our p~ al fr education a Ozpa~ an conception of physical<br />
knvowledeo Nov t ~ st is a Church School. This in one of those,<br />
schoo~ ls standing vividly and ondwringly for that most Important<br />
ooneeption ofeducation over the whole field a belief not only<br />
that we stould have humane letters as well as science but that we<br />
should have chmracter as well as knowledge. A the ! un* 4ticn of<br />
this school is to producoe character, not a lot of clever son with<br />
destructive mind with no conception of tawir obligations to<br />
tVair ,, O* Uow men, and no conception of their duty to ! aod but<br />
people of character, of a high morality, trained with a tackpgounl<br />
of reliioni able to understand right through their lives t-At<br />
It Is a Q0 thing to be intell1jent, it is a jood thing L ' beb<br />
successful It is a pyod thing to be able to do thi~ s, or this, or<br />
this. 8, but thatIt is a better thin&amp; to be u ine man# abetter<br />
rilh time those e ternal t~ uths whicoh make all the dif ference<br />
between a great man and a little ons. </p>
<p>And so, ; ir, I am delighted to be here. i an so'z'<br />
that I am not as young as I use to be boouase if I yoie as young<br />
as I smostiaws tool wbfl I am under &amp; titok, I would tool confident<br />
of cocing baak here in 4O yers' tin* to have &amp; L look over it,<br />
. Ut I don thlflk t at I can) look " orward to t: mat. Mh0so boys<br />
will look forwar'd to it* And I would like then to ta 14isselwes<br />
trig pioneers of this school, the tirt bqys who will over boome<br />
txo ' old boys" of Oestainster. I would like tb= to feel that<br />
they are helping to start a truditioc in one sense but in<br />
another sense to * ry an the Jmat tradition whiA is eaplified<br />
in the Church schools of this aountty, and in partioular, to feel<br />
proud of the fact that their shool has a nuse which associates<br />
It in the mind, and in the heart with the areat entre of all<br />
those things ian Parliament to the Iay which have marked our<br />
race and whioh have been among our rat oontributions to<br />
man In'd" ow, -Ar-having said that I exprese my ploasu'e and<br />
Vie pleasure of my wif at beinj here and I shall now, I think,<br />
if I have understood my instuctions aoetzatey, step smartly<br />
the President told ae " stop wartly three cricket pitt lengths<br />
to the left and 1 h! je that in the course of doine, so I won't<br />
pull a musole. ( Applause) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
