<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23133</transcript-id>
    <title>A fairer funding agreement for schools </title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/12/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Following negotiations with Queensland, Western Australia and the Northern Territory the Government has secured a national agreement on school funding.</p>
<p>The Coalition is committed to ensuring a fairer funding arrangement for schools nationally, whether a deal was signed with the former Labor government or not.</p>
<p>We will restore the $1.2 billion funding cut by Labor – bringing total additional school funding over the next four years to $2.8 billion – ensuring no State or Territory misses out.</p>
<p>We will implement a funding model that is national, fair and needs based while getting rid of the prescriptive command and control features that removed authority for schools from States, Territories and the non-government sector.</p>
<p>Labor left school funding in a mess. The hurried agreements signed in the dying days of the Labor government meant some States secured funding, while others missed out completely.</p>
<p>The Coalition Government is delivering what Labor failed to – a national agreement on school funding that ensures parents, principals and students, regardless of where they live, have funding certainty.</p>
<p>The Government will also honour funding promised to non-government representative bodies for four years including $55 million to Catholic Education Commissions and $110 million to the Association of Independent Schools.</p>
<p>The Government is keeping its commitments on school funding and delivering more funding over the next four years than promised by Labor.</p>
<p>2 December 2013</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
