<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8756</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE PERTH 7 DECEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008756.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME NITNISTTEq THE HON P J KE-ATING, M7P<br />
PRESS CON FERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE. PERTH<br />
7 DECEMBER 1992<br />
IF&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM III just give a brief overview of the meeting. We'rc nom, about two thirds the way<br />
through the Council of Australian ivennunents' agenda, and there have been many<br />
positive outcomes and Ill refer to those in a moment. On the protocols, on the<br />
crvlronnient, forests, rnicro econornd.; rerorm of electricity and gas, Asian language<br />
development and a few others I'll mention inore comprehensively in a moment,<br />
We had a lona and 01gorous discussion on industrial relations where there was not<br />
agreement between the Comnmonweath and particulaly the State of' Victori a, and<br />
where I said that the Commonwealth was determined to trve the workforce Of<br />
Victona choice. a matter the LiberalS often refer to it t~ hoice as to whethcr<br />
they wish to accept the opportunity of enhanced access to the coverage under the<br />
federal jurisdiction for awards, an option they would lose when State awardi<br />
tvirminate in March of nex~ t year.<br />
I argued to Mr Kenriett and to Mr Stockdale and others-and you miaht have seen<br />
those charts about the factor shares betwe~ en wages and profits, that already at this<br />
stage of the cycle the profit share -is at the level of the golden mncan of the 1960s,<br />
and of coursc with any volume In the economy, any volume ubvc overheads wil<br />
certainly just produce a hi~ her level of profits on the bottom line ul'cornpanies<br />
which will tale the profit share above the ' 60s experience. And urcourse, the<br />
concomitant wage share is at the 1 960s levels, levels where we all believed were<br />
such as they would promote Investment aind allow the econorny to develop. My<br />
question then was what are you asking for' Are you sayinlg that the profit share<br />
is not hi~ h enough at this stage, in absolute 1evels or at this stage of' the cycle, that<br />
the w3Ae share should be lower'? To which of course I had no replies Because<br />
there isn't a reply Wagcs in Australia are competitive Willh Countries with Whom </p>
<p>we trade, and their unit labour costs are nearly 10 Me cent below wherc thcy wet.<br />
a decade ago.<br />
So I bild Mr Kennett that the Commonwealth would be legislating to extend<br />
Section tI I of the Australian Industrial Relations Arbitration Commission powers<br />
ror coverage for those employecs or groups of employees in Victoria who sought<br />
such coverage. who exercised the choice and who sou~ h such coverage. We'rq<br />
nol imposing coverage, we're leaving the opportunity there for people to make a<br />
choice as to whether they want coverage.<br />
Secondly, that in relation to the adopion of legislation under the ratified ILO<br />
ggrecmrefts, I again reaffrrmed the Commnon wealth's willingness to consult with<br />
states about the detail of that legislation. Need I say, these are for two of these<br />
treaties, treaties which were ratified some timc agu with the agreement of the<br />
States This is for thin~ s such as minimumn rates and equal pay, and it Is putting<br />
into legislation the adoption of the content of the ULO ratifications which arc<br />
Interniationally agreed minima agreed by thc employer, employee, and govcniment<br />
representatives in the ITO. subsequently 4gtcvd by Australian States. subsequenitly<br />
rautied to which we are Si'in clTect. Hardly a basis for Objection And of course,<br />
what point could anybody argue that they don't agree with the principle of equal<br />
pay for equal work. Or in the later to be ustified termination of employment<br />
convention, that there people will have, a$ ain legislated international nimaU<br />
under that convention, but about whcth we've agreed to consult, and consult we<br />
will. We've established today a mechanism chaired by Peter Cook fur that<br />
i; Qnsultation, as he i3 the appropriate M~ inister<br />
So, we take the view, and I miade this point, that Australia in the last decade has<br />
adopted a much more consensus, cooperative model in industrial relations, we<br />
have adN-ance4 in tvi tn ur the change in our conomy materially since that<br />
adoption, that there can be no complaint about the rac. to; sharts in the economy<br />
beween wages and profit% and the 11Otion that we should drive wages down to<br />
peas~ ant levels, or sonmething approaching it, is not what is holding the economy.<br />
What has slowed growth in the economy is lack or demand, not the price of<br />
labour. And it is demand which is now pickint; up, we've had 2. 1 per cenit growth<br />
over four quarters, a lot of that demand has come from the public sectut wlikl, is 4<br />
result of the Comm~ onwealth stimulus, and Australia is growing now faster than<br />
ally ur iiie countries; of the Or--CD area.<br />
So. on industridl reldtions I hNA-you could say we've agreed to disagree, but<br />
around the basii of the Commonwealth Cove; ruient giving Victorian employees a<br />
choice as to whether they want to go on single employer contracts with recourse<br />
only to the common law, or whetherT thty opt rot choosing the enihanced access for<br />
the federal jurisdiction of the Australiwi Industrial Relations Commni3sion. </p>
<p>In relation to the other ar eas, in the protocols we've established it basis and rules<br />
for the proper Wnictioninl of the Council of Australian Governutents and the<br />
Ministerial Councils, and we've also decidcd to review the number of Ministerial<br />
Councils which are now 48 to more closely align them~ with thc structure of the<br />
Federal Giovernmrent's administrative arrungement3 order a~ 3s g uidt to the Sort Of<br />
model we might have.<br />
On the environment, we have agreed with the Stutcs on ESD and ( 3roenhouse<br />
straegies. This is quite an historic agreement involving work of environentalists<br />
and indust ry, and is a sound basis for further decisioms. 1 think the main flavour of<br />
that is we now have a decision-makcing framework for better land use planning<br />
across the country which we've nevci-had in this nation before,<br />
In forests. we adopted a forest strategy which provides a sound b&amp; 43i for fUture<br />
planning and more confidence for the forest industries. In rduis to water, a<br />
primary national resource, we've adopted certain principles and sought a report on<br />
better pricing, transferability of water rights and the use ofwvater. And in other<br />
mnicro-economic related reformi areas, in electricity we4 have reaffrrned our decision<br />
in May to separate power generation from distribution, making the point that<br />
separate accountin$ is not enough. that we actually want a separation of<br />
deneration and distributioni assets. In gas. where we are working towards the<br />
objective of a free and fair trade in gas in the country. and setting up a report to<br />
achieve it. And also adopting a proposal for enhanced Asian language<br />
, development in the Austaliwi education system.<br />
That is the progress to date. That's about, I'd say, 60 per cent through our agenda<br />
of the Council of Australian Governments, and my coulleague die Treasurer John<br />
Dawkins will share the Loan Council Meeting to follow this aflernon..<br />
J Prime Nfinister, aren't some of the States. including the Labor Statc of Quensland.<br />
concerned about your legislation. while it's directed specifically at VictV1ria, 111ay<br />
have unintended consequences on places like NSW and Queensland, which already<br />
have a number ofenterprise agreements which are outside the State award system"'<br />
WM No, but they have the status of awaids, just as in the Commonwealth arca an<br />
enterprise agreement has the status of an award. Even thougih it may be jointly<br />
entered anid agreed by an employer and employee or a reprewentative uternploym. s<br />
and is no longer the subject of scrutiny by the Cummrnssion still enjoys the status of<br />
an award. There is still an arbitral structure, That's why, while it is national<br />
legislation, the trigger will be the absence of an arbitral structure. That's why<br />
Queensland doesn't have a worry in that respect. In relatiuji to soine of theA other<br />
matters, that is the equal pay, terminations ct cetera, we've agreed to let them me<br />
the detail of the bill, and that's why it's flne </p>
<p>get any support fromn any of the States today f'or your ILO conventions now,<br />
have you?<br />
PM: Yes, absolutely.<br />
J. States antendments<br />
PM. No, no there's no States amendments. Labor States were arguing the casc with me<br />
aganst the conservative Sovernments rtpi-esented about the nature of the Viqtorian<br />
reforms, so-called<br />
3 But they've all evpresscd tconcem.<br />
P M. They've said they'd like to be party to tbe consultations. I'm very happy to reaffirm<br />
that, and we've set a structure up But I've made it very clear that the tArst and<br />
principal change is the extension of enhanced acCCss for employccs for coycrasc by<br />
the Australian Industrial Relations Cornmnission,. which does not rely on the<br />
ce'dI affairs power.<br />
J. You 3aid you'd consult on that, but you'rc also soing to rush it through the sy1stemn<br />
by Chrictma~ s<br />
PM-No, we Aill Rush through are yuui words We will consult. full stop. And then,<br />
I hope. expeditiously put it through.<br />
I. So doesi that mean it's not likely to go through before Christimas'.<br />
Pm. rm not sure whether we cmhi di lift sonie of it beflore Christmas. but if we can and<br />
we can comsult, we'll put it through. Certainly the cqual pay, and the minimums.<br />
which have already been ratifitd, Lct me state the point a&amp; air, these ar'e 11.0<br />
conventions already ratified with the agretrrments or the States. and they aze for<br />
internationally agreed minima. Who is Suing to tvgue in this country? What are<br />
the Liberals goinS to stand up and say, they don't agree with equal pay, they don't<br />
agree with somebody doing the mirnt woik being paid equaUy?<br />
I Can you just clarit that Mr Keatin'g, you're goin to put through the arbitration<br />
amendments befbire Christmas if you can, and you may put through the JLO<br />
cotvention amendmients as well if it's possible to do thai berbir Clu ssitas?<br />
PM. Ifit's Possible, except the third element, the separations have to be ratified first<br />
3 So the ones that are ratified you would try to get through before Christmar=)<br />
PM' -if it's pus~ ble. and with consultation, </p>
<p>J. Well in this case, this task force that's been se. t up. Mr Keating, are you SoinS to<br />
move bcforc thait reports" Wouldn't that rcpuit to another Premniers' Conferen"?~<br />
PM No, it's not a task force at all. It's a working group, at workin&amp; party bet-ween the<br />
Commonwealth chaired by Peter Cook, our industrial relations Minister, and<br />
whoever the States wish to nomninate.<br />
I: The States would be putfint3 on officials in positioris?<br />
PM: No, I think Ministers, probably, or officials or both.<br />
J_ So this dotsn't report back to a Premiers' Confetrence?<br />
PM-No.<br />
3. And you can't see this delaying the introduction of that second draft ofilegislation<br />
at all"<br />
PM: No. thcre are two possible delays in it. One, that we can't get the draflinS<br />
completed and introduced in time, and therc's something in the Consultation<br />
which causes us to redraft or do somcthing else. In other words, it's a<br />
reaffirmation of what wc've already said But can I just say that as a1re sult of our<br />
legislation. today in VIctoria the power strike. I understand. is not going ahead.<br />
Again. it makes the point, the Liberals are always talking about choice yet they<br />
object to Victorian employees. instead of the gun-at-the-head policy of take the<br />
contract or take the sack, ofwhich of'courst there is no choice, we're actually<br />
saying you can choose, if you wish, to be covered by the federal Australian<br />
Industrial Relations Commilssion. Now, I don't think Mr Kennett can argue a point<br />
of frusiration here ofthis legislation If there's a free choice ror the comnmunity of<br />
Victoria<br />
J: Mr KeatinS. Mr rahey hai just maid that this is basically Soing to.. miany Urf the<br />
States... tax on employmentcosts"<br />
M Laura, can I just ansv~ er that point straight away. I have agreed as Treasurti to<br />
miany additions to Ilic 6lobdl limnits to States, tu pay redundancies, to cut the size of<br />
llitli wurkrotixc and make their GBEs more efficient. None of us Is entitled to<br />
short-change eniployes ivin tedunawtes on whiiJz they believ~ e always existed,<br />
and it's n~ ot a % alid ease to be saying that it's a cost to the States which they can<br />
tiiove by just soagely, without consultation. removing a right which someone<br />
formerly enjoyed.<br />
J But they're not just talking about redundancy, Mir Keating. they're saying if you<br />
establish a national framework for all particularly in the area of teachers. there<br />
will be another efrect in the setting of wages, and the States will lose control. </p>
<p>PM. But that' 3 Ot udse now A larbv proportion of State employevs " c covcrod by<br />
federal awards now. And that's nothing to do with this Government, it's just the<br />
way the Arbitration Conumission has developed over timne. A substantial<br />
pruportivii of' State employe" are covered by federal awards. Pic fact is, the<br />
Liberals had no reply to the ractu: share point. that the profit sharc is already hi~ h.<br />
very high rbi this stage of the cycle. that the wage share is competitive with any<br />
country we wish to compare ourselves with. that the levels are ones which<br />
Snitcd high levels of investment in the Australian economy in years gone by.<br />
and that thc whole point of their policy is basically to cut people's income.<br />
J: I thought Mr Kennett's point was, when you said that, was that basically the only<br />
thing, that was rising was unemploy-ment.<br />
PM. it wasn't his point at all They hid no come-back to the essenitial point. that their<br />
policy is basically a red-neck, small business group generated policy which they<br />
had dropped on the people of Victoria without consultation, in Parliasnentary<br />
shtin~ s in the dead of night, without any consultation with the national<br />
Government which has a mandate ror a cooperative policy, which it's introduced<br />
now for over a decade, which is producing high levels of productivity, which has<br />
arranged in an aggregate way the factor shares to generate high levels of<br />
investment in thV101O, Mild Will qgaif III Ol:' 9O0i. flu CAMISUltatkili Uut Urtle Mlug,<br />
rtt policy which basically weks to Scnerate more activity by Cutting people's4<br />
wages. Now. ' wc rcjvt that We Av the wage levels itt this country aic adcqualt<br />
to promote the investment we need. But the problem has been demand not labour<br />
C03 id tNS is basically a red-neck agenda which the Commonwealth will never<br />
accept. I can't set how the Liberals, always so keen to talk about chice, wle<br />
afraid of Victorian employees makin* a choice of their own volition to exercise the<br />
enhani, ed opportunity of coverage undcr thc federal award systwm.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
