<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2974</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, SUNDAY 22 JULY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/07/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002974.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 7.15 P. M,<br />
NATIONAL BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
MR. E. G. WHITLAM, SUND) AY 22 JULY 1973<br />
On Tuesday I shall be flying to North America, primarily<br />
to attend the meeting of the 32 Commonwealth Heads of Government in<br />
Ottawa,. Before leaving I want to explain to you the reasons for the<br />
Government's historic decision which I announced this week with my<br />
colleague, Cairns to make an immediate reduction of 25 per cent<br />
in all tariffs on goods imported into Australia. I want to tell you<br />
also of the Government's policies on a matter that concerns us all<br />
the world-wide problem of inflation.<br />
First, our tariff cuts. Our purpose is simply to allow<br />
imported goods to come into Australia more cheaply and in greater<br />
quantities. This means that a whole range of imported products will<br />
cost less to the Australian consumer. It means keener, healthier<br />
competition for Australian industries producing similar goods.. This<br />
in turn will encourage those industries to bring down their prices<br />
as well. So that is our aim: cheaper imports, more goods for people<br />
to buy, more competition, lower prices. There are five million<br />
wage and salary earners in Australia. They, and their families, are<br />
the people who have suffered most from rising prices. They are the<br />
people who will benefit first, and most directly, from our decision.<br />
When my Government came to office just over seven months ago,<br />
inflation was runnin~ g at its highest level for 20 years. I mention<br />
that, not in an attempt to shufL" fle off responsibility onto our<br />
predecessors, but to remind you that inflation is, and always has<br />
been, a problem for all political partiesw And$ as you know, it is<br />
a problem for nearly all the major western industrial nations.<br />
Including our friends in Britain, the United States and Japan They<br />
knows as we do,, that there is no one quick or easy solution. For<br />
example, it is not constitutionally possible for the Australian<br />
Government to introduce a prices freeze in peacetime, although the<br />
State governments could,. It is not constitutionally possible in<br />
peacetime for the Australian and State governments, singly or<br />
together, to freeze all wages.,<br />
In other ways dontt forget our economy is in a sound<br />
and remarkably robust condition,. We have, for a start, eliminated the<br />
serious unemployment which faced us when we came to office. Demand<br />
for labour is high. Business is booming. Consumer spending is<br />
running at very high levels. Our overseas reserves are immensely<br />
strong that indeed is one of the causes of our inflation problem,<br />
although to our current advantage, the reserves make it possible for<br />
us to pay easily for more imports., In most respectss, we have never<br />
been more prosperous than we are now. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
None of us, however, can remain indifferent to the<br />
inflationary pressures that are pushing up prices. Inflation is<br />
harmful to every Australian. It is harmful to pensioners and those<br />
on fixed incomes: it is harmful to those with savings. It is<br />
harmful if I may take a selfish example to my own Government,<br />
because it makes it more difficult for us to implement, as promptly<br />
as we would wish, the great social reforms in housing, education,<br />
health, transport and the cities, to which we are pledged. When<br />
people talk glibly about cutting Government expenditure, they mean<br />
that we should be content to do little or nothing about the very<br />
things you elected us to do.<br />
For all those reasons we have taken action without delay<br />
to reduce inflationary pressures. I might say that my colleagues<br />
and I have been deeply encouraged by the reception our measures<br />
this week have met from most sections of the community. The<br />
business community, the leaders of the trade union movement, have<br />
both shown themselves sympathetic and understanding and where it<br />
may create difficulties for them, forebearing in the face of the<br />
difficult decision we have taken. We are confident that we can<br />
count on their co-operation to implement our policies successfully.<br />
Of course we are well aware that our tariff reforms can<br />
entail hazards for some Australians. We know they are bound to<br />
affect production and employment in certain industries. That is why<br />
we have set up a tribunal which will be able to hear immediatelyappeals<br />
from any organisation representative of employers and<br />
employees who may be seriously affected. We are equally determined<br />
to protect the jobs and livelihoods of Australian workers. My<br />
Government did not restore full employment in this country merely<br />
to take it away again even from a section of workers. Any person<br />
who may lose his job as a result of our changes will be entitled to<br />
receive, as special readjustment assistance, a weekly amount equal<br />
to his average wage in the previous six months until he obtains<br />
alternative employment. If necessary we will offer to retrain him<br />
in a new, perhaps better, occupation. We have provided $ 25 million<br />
to pay for the assistance which may be necessary as a result of our<br />
tariff reforms. Above all, you may be sure that we shall remain<br />
flexible and co-operate i~ n carrying out these reforms.<br />
In our attack on inflation, success depends on the<br />
co-operation of the whole community. One way we can all co-operate<br />
is by being more vigilant about price movements. Here is a way<br />
that every housewife, every consumer can help. If you know of<br />
cases where tariff cuts are not passed on to the consumers tell<br />
us about them, or tell your member of Parliament. The Government<br />
will ensure that consumers get the benefit of our tariff reduction.<br />
Remember, this is not the only measure we have taken to<br />
attack inflation. The revaluation of the dollar last December was<br />
a first step: the establishment of the Prices Justification Tribunal,<br />
which will come into operation in 10 days time, was another. I am<br />
confident that all these measures will allow us to keep inflationary<br />
tendencies under control, to safeguard the prosperity which<br />
Australians now enjoy, and to lay the foundations for the great<br />
social reforms we are determined to carry out for the benefit of<br />
all Australians. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
