<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8539</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP, PRIME MINISTER&#039;S NSW BRANCH ALP STATE CONFERENCE SYDNEY TOWN HALL SATURDAY, 6 JUNE 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008539.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 3uri ji i: 111C4<br />
SPEECH DY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MON P. J. KCEATING MP,<br />
PRIME MINISTER' S NSW BRANCH ALP STATE CONFERENCE<br />
SYDNEY TOWN HALL<br />
SATURDAY, 6 JUNE 1992<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
In this next year, if we are bold, if we are astute, arnd<br />
if we are united, we can retain government.<br />
If we retain governmnent, we can do many of the things<br />
which, in the last one hundred years, the men and women<br />
of Labor have dreamed of doing.<br />
Which Australians have dreamed of doing.<br />
We can come out of the recession stronger and more<br />
independent more truly one nation.<br />
We can make the Australian community strong and cohesive.<br />
We can inspire a sense of common national purpose.<br />
We can ingrain more deeply in our society that<br />
characteristic of all good societies the degree to<br />
which we care for our fellow Australians.<br />
We can make it the model of individual opportunity and<br />
social security which it should be -and which in the<br />
eyes of the world it was, in the first decade of this<br />
century. We can re-kindle an Australian democratic spirit.<br />
We can set those goals.<br />
And so long as I am Prime Minister they will be pursued.<br />
We will go for them.<br />
And we will achieve them. </p>
<p>TEL: u c C) 4 F. C<br />
2<br />
We'll do it by building on our strengths, and I mean much<br />
more than our economic strengths.<br />
I mean our care for this place and our fellow<br />
Australian. I mean our traditions, our strong social f abric, our<br />
democratic spirit.<br />
I mean our willingness to embrace change.<br />
I mean harnessing the energy and aspirations of all<br />
Australians by extending opportunity and encouraging in<br />
all Australians an intelligent belief in the nation and<br />
its national values.<br />
We will do best if we do all these things.<br />
Our economic strengths, of course, will continue to be<br />
crucial. And we can say that, for all the problems along the way,<br />
and even despite the recession, we hAve laid the basis of<br />
a stronger economy.<br />
A manifestly more competitive and robust economy and a<br />
much more internationally integrated economy.<br />
That is one reason we can do it economically speaking,<br />
we have given ourselves a chance in the world, and thus<br />
given the next generation of Australians a chance.<br />
We have great strengths and should not forget them: we<br />
are rich in resources, we have things the world wants to<br />
buy, in our'unequalled natural environment we have things<br />
which they want to see; we are making great strides in<br />
manufacturing and services.<br />
We shouldn't forget how dramatic the changes have been<br />
manufacturing and services now earn more export revenue<br />
then raw materials and agriculture. it was unthinkable<br />
ten years ago.<br />
We have more than doubled our secondary school retention<br />
rates. We have created the equivalent of twelve<br />
universities. We have quadrupled our child care.<br />
We have developed levels of social security with few<br />
parallels in the world.<br />
Under Labor we won't lose them we will build on them.<br />
We have learnt things we had never heard of in the 1970s.<br />
Like how to run a tourist industry from the ground up. </p>
<p>TEL: Ju. 2 10 : 10 No 004 F 0'<br />
3<br />
Like how to work to a cooperative ethic rather than an<br />
adversarial one.<br />
We are a nation capable of change.<br />
Remember we have gone in the space of a generation from<br />
being a country notorious for Insularity and xenophobia<br />
to a country which earns the admiration of the region and<br />
the world for the tolerance and openness manifest in<br />
* ultioulturalism.<br />
Similarly we have learned come economic truths:<br />
we've learned that we must be less dependent on<br />
commodities. we've learned about the historic opportunity that<br />
exists for us, the historic necessity of our<br />
economic integration with Asia and the Pacific.<br />
we've learned terms we had never heard of in the<br />
1970s: like value-adding and downstream processingterms<br />
which describe economic imperatives. Things<br />
we must do.<br />
We are in 1992 what we most certainly were not in 1982-<br />
one of the more economically literate countries of the<br />
world. These things our economic and social base, our capacity<br />
for change, or willingness to change -give me great<br />
confidence in our future.<br />
Our opponents are weak.<br />
The Coalition is a coalition in name only. It papers<br />
over large cracks in some very old and mouldy plaster.<br />
Admittedly there's some new plaster there these days but<br />
most of it's as flaky as the old stuff.<br />
Fightback. is a sterile document informed by a<br />
reactionary ideology whose principle characteristic is a<br />
loathing of ordinary people.<br />
It was built on the discredited and generally repugnant<br />
philosophy of the New R~ ight.<br />
Fightback is a throwback to the late seventies. it's an<br />
anachronism in the nineties. Like the dodo or the<br />
Hindenburg. It won't survive.<br />
They stuck an exclamation mark on the end of it in an<br />
attempt to give it life but if you take it away it<br />
turns up its toes.<br />
Our opponents have no heart. Their Australia would have<br />
no soul. </p>
<p>TEL: ~~ 6. Jun .2 i. 0l: F.<br />
4<br />
These days in Parliament they sit in their desks, like<br />
schoolchildren, with bunting beside them to prove that<br />
they are Australian.<br />
Because they think that you can win in politics by<br />
resisting history rather than making it, because they<br />
think that the people of Australia have no more spirit or<br />
faith than they have, they send me letters saying what an<br />
abomination I am because I think we should not have the<br />
flag of another country on ours.<br />
They gather In Town Halls to sing God Save the Queen, and<br />
tell each other that Australia must not change, must not<br />
grow towards its separate destiny.<br />
They spin tales about the idle pleasures of the past<br />
the Menzoid Golden Age, when the country dozed, and the<br />
best minds left along with the minerals and wool, and the<br />
world largely passed us by.<br />
They always want to go back. While the people of<br />
Australia, with hope in their hearts, march bravely<br />
towards the future, John Howard gallops about urging them<br />
to retreat to the rear.<br />
Back to the fifties, he shouts. Back to the dead end<br />
jobs. Back to the massive inefficiencies. Back to the<br />
quarries. Back to the sheep's back. Back to Britain.<br />
John Howard leads the national reverse thrust.<br />
But the rest, including his Leader, have engaged the same<br />
gear. Back they go.<br />
They are regressive by nature.<br />
Anid nothing is so regressive as Fightback.<br />
Fightback, as Ralph Willis put it, is socially regressive<br />
and economically perverse.<br />
Fightback is not a policy. it is an excuse for a tax.<br />
A tax that we will re-ignite Australian inflation.<br />
just as we get inflation out of the system the Tories<br />
want to put something in the region of 6 percentage<br />
points back into it.<br />
out the vandalism doesn't stop there.<br />
After a decade of unprecedented peace and cooperation in<br />
industrial relations they want to back to the jungle.<br />
And in a society with one of the most sophisticated and<br />
effective social security systems in the world, the </p>
<p>-TEL: I '* ur n~ 110 Nc i C'' 1J4 P 1DS<br />
Tories want to introduce measures characteristic of<br />
societies in decay.<br />
they will push Medicare towards the American system<br />
which offers care to only 80 per cent of the<br />
population end at 50 per cent greater cost. They'll<br />
cut the rebate from 85% 75t and they'll abolish<br />
bulk billing except for those on benefits.<br />
the unemployed are to be knocked off benefits after<br />
nine months.<br />
the waiting for sickness and unemployment benefits<br />
will be increased from one week to three.<br />
the job placement services of the CES will be<br />
contracted out. Effectively CES will be abolished.<br />
they ' 1l throw 40,000 people off supporting parents'<br />
benefit by cutting off the pension when the youngest<br />
child reaches 12, not sixcteen.<br />
they'll make migrants wait two years before they can<br />
claim benefits of any kind.<br />
Everyone will be a winner under Fightback, the propaganda<br />
says. if you want to send your kids, or yourself, to<br />
university It will cost you an estimated $ 24,000 for<br />
an arts degree up to $ 150,000 for medicine.<br />
families with Income levels about $ 7000 under the<br />
present limits will lose the Family Allowance.<br />
That's 100,000 families.<br />
they'll cut $ 10 million from legal aid. The<br />
cumulative effect of funding cuts and the GST will<br />
mean more than fourteen thousand cases will not be<br />
funded by legal aid. Those cases of course will<br />
involve the most vulnerable In the community.<br />
Fightback compounds injustice.<br />
they'll cut overseas aid by nearly 16 per cent in<br />
real terms, making Australia number 14 of the OECD's<br />
18 donor countries. Emergency refugee programs will<br />
be slashed by more than half.<br />
they will abolish the Youth Bureau and the Youth<br />
Access Centres which provide information and advice<br />
to more than 200,000 young people each year, and<br />
which a recent evaluation shows are successful in<br />
delivering employment, education and training.<br />
despite the findings of the Royal Commission on<br />
Black Deaths in Custody that a substantial increase<br />
in funding was necessary, and despite the feelings<br />
of all decent Australians that this must be the </p>
<p>TE6 Juri .92 1C: 1C No .004 F . C<br />
6<br />
decade when we end the national disgrace, the Tories<br />
will cut $ 90 million from outlays on Aboriginal<br />
programs.<br />
Yet they say, everyone's a winner under Fightback.<br />
Under Labor, working women have made significant steps<br />
towards achieving parity with men. We have legislated to<br />
protect women against discrimination in the workplace,<br />
and our affirmative action policies are encouraging<br />
employers to promote women to a wider range of Jobs.<br />
Under our equal pay strategy the gap between men's and<br />
women's earnings has narrowed to from 33 per cent to 17<br />
per cent.<br />
Our National Agenda for Women reaches out to women of all<br />
ages and vocations, including women in the home.<br />
We are committed to constantly evaluating our overall<br />
policies to ensure fair and equitable treatment of women.<br />
There is still a lot to do, but we are proud of our<br />
record and you will see us build upon it.<br />
But the struggle to improve the status of women in<br />
Australia would end with Fightback.<br />
the Affirmative Action Agency, the Equal Pay Unit<br />
and the Work and Family Unit will be abolished.<br />
the Human Rights and Equal opportunity Commission<br />
which includes the Sex Discrimination Commissioner<br />
will have its expenditure cut by an unspecified<br />
amount. the public sector will be cut back, privatised,<br />
abolished, contracted out or " rationalised" in the<br />
areas where women work in service delivery areas<br />
like nursing and caring. And in clerical, cleaning<br />
and catering services.<br />
Dut everyone, they insist, is a winner under Fightback.<br />
Fightback will unpick the social fabric. It expresses<br />
that sentiment of selfishness that loathing of the<br />
unfortunate and vulnerable which characterised the<br />
regimes of Reagan and Thatcher.<br />
In Australia it was resisted in the market-driven years<br />
of the eighties. We held it of f.<br />
It would be tragic if now It were to take hold In the<br />
form of a Hewson governments<br />
it is repugnant to Labor. And we will fight it to<br />
extinction. </p>
<p>TEL 7<br />
The Treasury analysis of Fightback under which everyone<br />
is supposedly a winner shows that 70 per cent of wage<br />
and salary earning households will be worse off under a<br />
Howson government.<br />
It shows that 60 per cent of farm and self-employed<br />
person households will be worse off.<br />
I haven't yet mentioned the consumption Tax. The jewel In<br />
the crown of Fightback.<br />
Treasury estimates that food would rise by 8.9 per cent.<br />
Clothing by 11.2 per cent.<br />
Electricity by 10.7 per cent<br />
Health services by 22.6 per cent<br />
Newspapers and magazines 10.5 per cent.<br />
Urban public transport 6.6 per cent<br />
Post and telephone 8.1 per cent.<br />
A Ferrari will cost $ 15,000 legs.<br />
Everyone's a winner, Dr Hewson reckons, under Fightback.<br />
Like smell business. Consider the remarks from Mr<br />
Cedric Stanford, a leading British authority on<br />
value added taxes. He did a detailed study of the<br />
costs to business and found<br />
The compliance costs of the small firm were 260<br />
times those of the largest firms. Where small firms<br />
are competing in the some market with large firms",<br />
he found, " they are being put under a state-created<br />
disadvantage."<br />
Indeed, he found that " compliance costs.. became a factor<br />
in helping to push small firms out of particular<br />
markets". Or take the comments of a New Zealander, Mr John Marine,<br />
in the January issue of Australian Small Business and<br />
investing. He gave Australian small business people an<br />
explicit warning based on experience about, the GST.<br />
your personal stress level will rise sharply.<br />
Sunday at the beach will be a thing of the past.<br />
You should consider how you will cope when you lose<br />
one day a week to OST, whether your business will<br />
survive and what you are going to do about it."<br />
To small business GST stands for a Great Shrinking of<br />
Time but what Is time to a man in a Ferrar17 TELj: u6n .92 11-t: i F''. YJ </p>
<p>TEL: Ln; r~ I cn1 o'.: 4 4 F<br />
Everyone, Dr Hewson says, Is a winner with Fightback.<br />
But not if you happen to be at the vulnerable end of the<br />
labour market.<br />
Perhaps the most insidious and potentially the most<br />
devastating aspect of Dr Hewsonus program is his<br />
Industrial Relations policy.<br />
Nothing reflects so well the right wing ideology at the<br />
Core of Fightback. Nothing is so perfect an expression<br />
of their contempt for the weak.<br />
Industrial relations policy is the policy which most<br />
generally defines the relationships between one<br />
Australian and another.<br />
We have seen In the last ten years that relationship<br />
reach a new level of intelligent cooperation.<br />
In Burnie we are seeing the Tories'I idea of how<br />
Australians should relate to each other.<br />
Their industrial relations policy is a policy of social<br />
intimidation. There is only one thing to be gained from the dispute in<br />
Burnie it has exposed the philosophy of John Howson<br />
and John Howard, and it has given Australians a glimpse<br />
of what life would be like under a conservative<br />
government. The gains which flowed from the development of an ethos<br />
of cooperative workplace reform, the spirit which has<br />
seen disputation fall by 60 per cent in a decade, the<br />
increase in productivity experienced by companies where<br />
agreements have been negotiated with unions and<br />
management, the inflation gains brought about by the<br />
Accor all these gains will be killed stone dead.<br />
The Opposition plans an assault not just on the unions<br />
and the principles of unionism they plan an assault on<br />
the principle of the Umpire, of social and industrial<br />
justice.<br />
They want to drive Australian workers on to contracts<br />
where they will then be exposed to what John Howard is<br />
calling a " floor wage"<br />
The " floor wage", John Howard says will be somewhere<br />
between the dole and the existing minimum award.<br />
Now they introduced an Employment Contracts Act in New<br />
Zealand last year it is the same Idea.<br />
It's Hewson and Howard's safety net. Australian workers<br />
especially the most vulnerable, including women,<br />
migrants, the unskilled these workers should know that </p>
<p>TEL: U Tr<br />
9<br />
the " floor wage" in New Zealand has been set at AS175.0<br />
a week, or A$ 9153.00 per annum.<br />
For employees under 20 years of age there is na minimum.<br />
There are many questions which should be put to Mr Howard<br />
and Dr Hewson about their industrial relations policy and<br />
over the next six months we will be putting them.<br />
For instance: How will you prevent workers being forced out of the<br />
protection of the award stream by an employer who<br />
wants to put the employee on a contract?<br />
How will scrupulous employers compete with the<br />
unfair advantage that is offered by Dr Rawson to<br />
uinscrupulous employers?<br />
With no more National Wage Cases, how will workers<br />
in weak bargaining positions ever get a wage rise?<br />
If industrial disputes are to be dealt with under<br />
common law instead of the Industrial Relations<br />
Commission, how will ordinary workers have the time<br />
and the resources to take their employers to court?<br />
How long will it take the courts to hear the cases?<br />
N ow will the Hewson and Howard model of industrial<br />
relations protect living standards?<br />
How will It make everyone a winner?<br />
We should ask these questions. All Australians should<br />
ask them and I believe they should ask themselves if<br />
this policy is the hallmark of a civilised society?<br />
Does it express our values and goals? Is it a social<br />
advance to drive the weak down?<br />
Is Burni our industrial and social model for Australia?<br />
For John Hewson and John Howard It is.<br />
As John Howard said himself, on 23 May, the right being<br />
exercised by APPM " is basic to the new industrial<br />
relations system the Liberal and National Parties will<br />
bring to Australia after the next election"<br />
I say, like hell they will.<br />
I said Fightback will unpick the social fabric. It will.<br />
The Tories you know are very big on values and traditions<br />
they're big on holding on to what is there. Like the<br />
Union Jack and their interpretation of our history. </p>
<p>ILL-L<br />
They get very cranky if we say they don' t have a mortgage<br />
on our history any more than they have a mortgage on our<br />
future.<br />
The truth is that their blueprint for the future<br />
Constitute$ the most savage attack on our traditions we<br />
have ever seen.<br />
Xt attacks the tradition of fairness anid equity.<br />
It attacks the tradition of progress towards civilized<br />
social goals.<br />
It attacks the tradition of care for the underprivileged<br />
and vulnerable for protecting the weak against the<br />
strong. These traditions are built in to our society -they shape<br />
the way we think, the way we go about our lives.<br />
In large part they derive from the last decade of the<br />
last century from the rise of the Labor movement and<br />
the emergence of a new national spirit.<br />
But they were values shared by liberals by non Labor<br />
Australians. They were widalm shared.<br />
They are not shared by today's anti-Labor forces.<br />
Don't let them tell you that this government is hostile<br />
to tradition, or that it's re-writing the past.<br />
It's the future we're concerned with and we're building<br />
it on the best of Australian traditions.<br />
We are determined to equip Australia for the next<br />
century. To do that we have to make bold policy decisions. We<br />
have to be willing to meet the challenges head on.<br />
As I said at the beginning, we are building on solid<br />
foundations laid down in the last decade of Labor<br />
government. And as I said, we are also building on the foundations of<br />
our best traditions our best sympathies.<br />
our social goals are equitable ones. Our aim is fairness<br />
as well as strength.<br />
The strength will not only come from economic policy, it<br />
will not only be measured by economic success.<br />
Our national spirit, the degree to which we identify as<br />
Australians and declare our first loyalty to Australia<br />
wherever in the world we have come from; the degree of<br />
care for each other as Australians; the degree to which </p>
<p>TEL: IC t. -1U I I V J I I L'<br />
we are prepared to take a national view and pursue<br />
national goals all these will give us strength.<br />
And in the coming years we will measure our success by<br />
how truly we can say that we are One Nation.<br />
The Tories don't understand this. WJe will have to teach<br />
them. We'll teach them by the sorts of bold Initiatives we took<br />
this week by our example.<br />
Revolutioniuing the airline industry is a major Labor<br />
breakthrough it has profound implications for the<br />
tourist Industry, and therefore profound long term<br />
Implications for our economy and employment.<br />
Introducing Pay-TV on the basis that we have, getting<br />
optimal outcomes from the new and available technologies,<br />
was a milestone in the transfer of information technology<br />
to Australians.<br />
The decision we made this week will be the key to what<br />
Australians will be viewing in their homes, businesses<br />
and schools, and how they will be commuunicating with each<br />
other over the next quarter century.<br />
we also gave the ABC an historic opportunity to break<br />
from its national free-to-air charter into the almost<br />
limitless realm of sophisticated information transfer.<br />
Getting TAFE into the high quality, high status shape<br />
that it should be will be a profound reform, with<br />
profound benefits to our economy and society for<br />
generations to come.<br />
Extending occupational superannuation to all is a<br />
fundamental reform, an imperative if we are to achieve<br />
our goals of better incomes for the retired aged and<br />
greater national savings.<br />
Infrastructure spending on rail, road, airports, ports,<br />
electricity is essential, not only to recovery and to<br />
employment in the short term, but to the long term health<br />
of the economy. It's essential to our keeping up with the<br />
world. Moving, as we have this week, to develop strategies for<br />
youth training and employment in conjunction with our<br />
TAFE reforms and our existing labour market programs, is<br />
essential if our young people are to have the<br />
opportunities they deserve.<br />
Our goal is to involve business, unions and the wider<br />
community in creating a national response a national<br />
effort. </p>
<p>TE L: . u3rn .92 1C 11.1 No0 . C' 4 F 1I<br />
12<br />
These initiatives must be taken if we want young<br />
Australians to believe in this country and it is no<br />
exaggeration to say that, without that belief, we will<br />
never be the nation that we can and should be.<br />
We are doing the things Labor governments must do.<br />
The Tories never do them. They'll never understand.<br />
What you will hear from them are the sounds of scare<br />
campaigns. And smear campaigns.<br />
They will call urn traitors for wanting unequivocal<br />
symbols of our nationhood just as they so often called<br />
u~ s traitors during the Cold War.<br />
They'll grub around looking for dirt like they have been<br />
doing for the past few weeks just as they have so of ten<br />
done in the past.<br />
They'll rush outside and shout " anarchy" and " mayhem" and<br />
accuse US of not having respect and they will go around<br />
the homes of elderly Australians with bizarre, vicious<br />
and entirely inappropriate propaganda they knocked of f<br />
from the Republican Party of the United States.<br />
Propaganda which was fomented in the prejudice sheeted<br />
homes to black America and in the gun culture of that<br />
country. Propaganda whose use here constitutes a dramatic lapse In<br />
standards of political behaviour, and, I believe, a<br />
serious misjudgement. of Australian values.<br />
Yet this is just a variation on the things that they have<br />
always done.<br />
But they will fail.<br />
They will go on being what they are spoilers.<br />
And we will go on being what we are builders.<br />
And we will win. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
