<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8263</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008263.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 2 March, 1991<br />
I have decided that the Minister for Trade and Overseas<br />
Development, Dr Blewett, will lead a bipartisan mission to the<br />
United States. </p>
<p>The mission will meet representatives of both the US Congress<br />
and the US Administration to convey Australia's grave concern<br />
about the damage being done to our farmers by the Export<br />
Enhancem~ ent Program ( EEP). </p>
<p>The mission was suggested by the Leader of the National Party in<br />
response to the escalating trade subsidies war between the EC<br />
and the United States. I have today written to the Leader of<br />
the Opposition, seeking his nominees for the mission. </p>
<p>Congressional consideration of the EEP for 1991 is imminent<br />
possibly as early as 11 March 1991; therefore, the bipartisan<br />
inission needs to visit the United States next week. </p>
<p>Of course, the principal offender in corrupting international<br />
agricultural trade has been the European Community. But the US<br />
response to these policies through the EEP is causing our<br />
farmers increasing hardship. </p>
<p>The mission will convey our concerns to the US about the<br />
damaging side-effects of EEP, and, at the very least, seek to<br />
moderate its impact on Australia and our farmers. </p>
<p>Obviously, it is imrportant for us to continue to make our strong<br />
representations to the Europeans who started the trade war, and<br />
whose export subsidies are double those of the US. </p>
<p>Australia, through our leadership of the Cairns Group, has been<br />
at the forefront in the Uruguay Round negotiations in imploring<br />
the Europeans to engage in meaningful reform of agricultural<br />
trade. In this recard, the restart of negotiations in the<br />
Uruguay Round is encouraging. </p>
<p>The Europeans are now engaged in an internal process of reform<br />
of the Common Agricultural Policy. As soon as the time is<br />
right, we will send a similar delegation to Europe, although<br />
this is likely to te some months away. </p>
<p>TIhe mission, which will leave on Wednesday, will comprise<br />
Dr Blewett; Mr BriEn Courtice, MP, Chairman of the Country<br />
Taskforce; a Shadowr Minister and Opposition backbencher; and Mr<br />
John Allwright, PrE: Sident of the Natiotial Farmers Federationl. I </p>
<p>Self-reliance means the capacity to defend yourself, if ever<br />
that is necessary. And in this sense, these vessels are the<br />
most modern and capable conventionally-powered submarines in<br />
the world. Based on the west coast of Australia they will<br />
substantially increase our capacity to defend our shores.<br />
But defence self-reliance means much more than this. Any<br />
country which aspires to defence self-reliance must be<br />
capable not only of operating the necessary defence<br />
equipment on which its security depends but also of<br />
constructing and maintaining it.<br />
In this sense too, these submarines are a proof of our selfreliance.<br />
It is Australian skill, ingenuity and sheer hard<br />
work which is making this project the success it is. More<br />
than seventy cents; of each dollar to be spent on the<br />
platform work on these submarines are to be spent in<br />
Australia. Sub-contracts for over $ 1 billion have already<br />
been let in Australia with another $ 900 million of work<br />
being performed by Australian Submarine Corporation.<br />
So the project refutes the view that too often pervades<br />
Australianb thinking that if something is technologically<br />
demanding then we should buy it from overseas.<br />
I would like to pay tribute to Dr Williams and the people of<br />
the Australian Submarine Corporation, to Rear Admiral Hughes<br />
and his project team, and to the entire workforce, whose<br />
combined efforts have brought us to this point of laying the<br />
keel of Farncoinb. You are right on budget, and right on<br />
schedule. The success has relied too on the support and<br />
encouragement of the South Australian Government, and others<br />
around the country who believed in the ability of Australian<br />
industry to construct submarines in this country.<br />
This project then represents change and it represents the<br />
future. But in ore respect, however, it stands for the<br />
traditions of the past. The names of these vessels have<br />
been selected to commemorate sailors of the Royal Australian<br />
Navy who embody the finest traditLions of service ond<br />
dedication. Admiral Harold Farncomb, in war and in peace,<br />
stood for and advanced these traditions and he is justly<br />
honoured today.<br />
Finally, I would like to take this opportunity to pay<br />
tribute to the Chief of Naval Staff Vice Admiral Mike<br />
Hudson. Today marks his last formal ceremony before<br />
retiring . at the endof. next week, after a Naval career<br />
spanning nearly forty fuur years. Hie has been the longest<br />
serving Chief of Naval Staff since Vice Admiral Collins who<br />
retired in 1955.<br />
in the past six years he has provided dynamic leadership in<br />
the development of standards and directions which I believe<br />
the Navy will value for many years to come. </p>
<p>He has served with great distinction in ships and<br />
establishments of the Royal Australian Navy with an<br />
outstanding devotion to this country and his profession.<br />
I would now like to invite him, and Mrs Farncomb, to help<br />
lay the keel for this new submarine.<br />
54 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
