<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18806</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech for Equal Futures Partnership Launch</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>New York City, USA</p>
<p>I am honoured to announce Australia's founding membership of the Equal Futures Partnership.</p>
<p>I am delighted to do so in the company of Secretary Clinton.</p>
<p>Hillary  -  you have done so much to inspire women and girls all around the world.</p>
<p>We stand taller  -  and walk freer  -  because of your work and your example.</p>
<p>Two years ago President Obama committed the United States to new steps to break down economic and political barriers which separate women and girls from their full human potential.</p>
<p>And he called on the nations of the world to join this effort.</p>
<p>From that commitment, the Equal Futures Partnership was born.</p>
<p>As Australia's first female Prime Minister, I am delighted to commit my nation to three domestic initiatives under the Equal Futures Partnership.</p>
<p>First, we're working to strengthen the pipeline of female talent in traditionally male-dominated industries.</p>
<p>It's great to have women Secretaries of State and Prime Ministers. But let's have more women engineers and truck drivers as well.</p>
<p>Second, we're committed to achieving a minimum of forty per cent of women on Australian Government boards by 2015  -  up from 35 per cent today.</p>
<p>Our progress so far is commendable.  But near enough is not good enough.</p>
<p>We're also creating a National Centre of Excellence to Reduce Violence Against Women.</p>
<p>The Centre will lead a national research agenda to support policies and programs to reduce violence against women.</p>
<p>No woman should live with violence or the fear of violence.</p>
<p>It is always and utterly unacceptable.</p>
<p>And I'm proud to say that Australia recently announced our A$320 million commitment to gender equality in our region: Pacific Women Shaping Pacific Development.</p>
<p>In Australia, in the Pacific, in every corner of the world  -  all women are created equal.</p>
<p>This is the moral heart of our Partnership: </p>
<p>Women and girls must have futures equal to those of their brothers and fathers.</p>
<p>That is what our work must achieve.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
