<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5760</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE DINNER OF THE ASSOCIAZIONE LIBERALE ITALIANA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005760.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
! EM~ BARGO: 9,40 PM<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 26 FEBRUARY J982<br />
SPEECH AT THE DINNER OF THE ASSOCIAZIONE LIBERAJE ITALIANA<br />
Through a s-oirit of free enterprise, Australia has developed<br />
into one of the world's strongest and most dynamic economies.<br />
With a population of just over 8 million in 1949, which has now<br />
S grown to 15 million, we have developed into a vibrant,<br />
concerned and diverse society marked by freedom and widespread<br />
opportunity. over this period living standards have doubled and our whole<br />
way of life has been uplifted. Now as always, Victoria<br />
is at the forefront of Australia's economic and social<br />
development. There is a long history of development in Victoria,<br />
and the level of Victorian achievement is often taken for granted.<br />
Under successive Liberal Governments, Victorians have marshalled<br />
the resources of their State to generate the highest average<br />
household income and to achieve the highest rate of home<br />
ownership of any State. The average home in Melbourne costs<br />
$ 20,000 less than in Sydney. Victorians can be proud of the<br />
achievement s of their state, and should recognise the progress<br />
which they have exp6rienced.<br />
Victoria leads Australia in developing and utilising its<br />
energy resources. Over 90% of Australia's oil production is in<br />
Victoria arid three quarters of Australia's demonstrated<br />
recoverable reserves of crude oil, condensate and LPG are in<br />
Victoria. Half of Australia's natural gas production is<br />
in Victoria. Victoria has successfully developed its huge<br />
brown coal deposits for its electricity needs. A third of<br />
Australia's spending on production, exploration and development<br />
of petroleum occurs in Victoria. We live in an era where theeconomic<br />
use of and supply of energy resources is of<br />
paramount importance, and successive Liberal governments have<br />
ensured that Victoria's needs are met and maintained.<br />
It is significant for Victoria's prosperity that two thirds<br />
of Australia's largest companies are headquartered in Victoria,<br />
and two thirds of Australia's leading resource development companies<br />
are headquartered in Melbourne. Two of Australia's three leading<br />
private trading banks are Melbourne based. Victorian Liberal.<br />
Governments have worked to maintain Melbourne's position as the<br />
financial capital of Australia. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
In the three years to January, over 70,000 new jobs were created<br />
in Victoria and Victoria's unemployment rate in January<br />
1982 was the lowest of any state. Victoria is amajor manufacturing<br />
state. One third of Australia's employees in manufacturing work<br />
are in Victoria. Victoria is Australia's leading producer<br />
Of passenger motor vehicles, and a major force in the<br />
engineering, chemicals, textiles, food processing, paper<br />
and rubber industries. Victoria is the leading state for<br />
research and development in business enterprise. Victoria<br />
is also a leading primary production state and growing,<br />
In the last 5 years the value of rural output grew faster<br />
in Victoria than any other State.<br />
In education Victoria enjoys above state average spendinig for<br />
school students, and has better student-teacher ratios than<br />
the Australian average. In tertiary education, Victoria is<br />
the equal highest state in terms of the participation rate<br />
in Universities and Colleges of Advanced Education.<br />
The advantages which Victoria offers are immeWiately clear,<br />
both as a place in which to live and as a place in which<br />
to invest. The facts speak for themselves.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
