<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6518</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, ABC TV (NORTHERN TERRITORY) PROGRAM: TERRITORY TRACKS, MONDAY 22 OCTOBER 1984, HOSTED BY RUTH DEXTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006518.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
' TRANSCRIPT ABC TV ( NORTHERN TERRITORY) PROGRAM: TERRITORY TRACKS<br />
MONDAY OCTOBER 22 1984 HOSTED BY RUTH DEXTER<br />
Well last week also saw the visit of the Prime Minist~ er, Bob Hawke, to<br />
strike the first major blow In the Labor Party's election campaign in<br />
the Northern Territory. Geoff Adlide reports;<br />
GA: A bulldozer clearing the way for a Labor victory in the Territory<br />
at least that's the hope of its driver, Prime Minister Bob Hawke. The<br />
Prime Minister spent the first day of his national ciampaign here-in the<br />
Territory on the hustings in support of Labor Member, John Reeves. Not<br />
surprisingly he was selling his Government by displaying some of the benefits<br />
to the Territory since Labor camne to power. Namely, the $ 90 million upgrading<br />
of the Darwin Airport and the several hundred million dollar Tindal Air<br />
Force Base. This Is Bob Hawke's second visit in less than a year. Last<br />
time he was here to campaign for the Territory elections, In which the<br />
Labor Party was devastated. Many of the issues are still much the same,<br />
with uranium, land rights and the like, so how does he believe he'll turn<br />
the tide of' Labor Party fortunes.<br />
BH: All our research shows that the people of the Territory have a different<br />
perspective than they bring to bear on a Northern Territory election than<br />
what they do when they talk about Federal elections. We're encouraged<br />
by the indication that the people of the Territory firstly recognise what<br />
we've done for Australia* secondly particularly recognise the fact that<br />
we've put in about $ 1.8 billion In our two budgets to the future of the<br />
Territory. We've given about a 12% increase in tax repayment money to<br />
the Territory as compared with about 6% to the states,, and thirdly, they<br />
recognise the great job that John Reeves has done in prodding us. As<br />
a member of the Government he can do that.. And I think all t ~ ese things<br />
will go In our favour.<br />
GA: But Mr Everingham is a tough opponent. </p>
<p>EHt Oh yes, of course I can see that he'll be a tough opponent. I mean,<br />
I'm a relaist In politics, he's well known, but I also recognise the great<br />
job that John Reeves has done for the Territory and I believe that the<br />
Territorlans will be sensible about that. We're not now talking about<br />
Mr Sveringhan, the Chief Minister, but we're talking about someone to<br />
be in Canberra either as a member og Government, returned to power as<br />
Mr Everingham says it will be, someone to be there directly and intimately<br />
involved in that, or someone over there on the Opposition,<br />
GA: If' Mr Everingham does win, will the Territory suffer, or will the<br />
Government be less responsive to the Territory's needs?<br />
BH: You see, it's not a question of I think my s; ort of attitude to<br />
life is well known. I'm not a vindictive person, I don't operate like<br />
that, but it's just a fact of life that if you've got a person that's<br />
a member of your party, part of the whole process, and in the nature of<br />
things he can just wander in to see you, because he is your own party,<br />
and he can wander into ministers' offices, he's an intimate colleague<br />
of them. That person has got, just in the nature of things, a much greater<br />
capacity to get the view accross than someone in the Opposition. It's<br />
true whether we're in Government or the other people are in Government<br />
that members from seats and areas of the Government have a better access<br />
to and capacity to Influence their own Government than they have if they<br />
are in Opposition just as a fact of life.<br />
RDt Geoff Adlide talking to Prime Minister, Bob Hawke.<br />
-ends<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
