<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2769</transcript-id>
    <title>A SPECIAL COMMITTEE OF FEDERAL MINISTER WILL INVESTIGATE THE POSSIBILITY OF ESTABLISHING AN INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT AT TOWNSVILLE.</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002769.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS A special committee of Federal Ministers will investigate<br />
the possibility of establishing an international airport at<br />
Townsville. This was announced today by the Minister for Tourism and<br />
Recreation ( Mr. Frank Stewart).<br />
Such an airport would be expected to boost the tourist<br />
potential of the entire region, Stewart said.<br />
It would also continue to be used by the RAAF as a joint<br />
military-civil vpnturP.<br />
" The committee will carefully study the location and also<br />
the physical requirements for an airport, the anticipated needs<br />
of international airlines and the environmental, urban and regional<br />
development aspects," he said.<br />
" We will also look at the operational and economic factors<br />
which would speed up the tourist development of Northern Australia<br />
in general and the Great Barrier Reef area in particular."<br />
Mr. Stewart said the Prime Minister ( Mr. Gough hitlam) in<br />
his policy spcech had bcon s-pecific about thce Govcrniuiicnt's<br />
intentions to declare the Great Barricr Rcef a National Park.<br />
This would follou the expectcC early passage of the<br />
Territorial Sea and Continental Shelf Bill.<br />
Such a move :.' ould neccs: itate the e; tablishment of an<br />
international airoort at Townsvillc.<br />
Chairman of the sp,, ecial Cbinet Coiiitte is<br />
Mr. Frank Stevwart.<br />
Other meribcrs are Dr. Rex Patterson, Iinister for<br />
Northern Development, Senator Reginald Dishop, linister for<br />
Repatriation and inister assisting the -inister for Defence,<br />
1r. Tom Uren, . inister for Urban anC Regional Development,<br />
H. r. Charlooes Jones,. inister for Transport and i: inister for Civil<br />
Aviation and Dr. Moss Cass, Minister for the Mnvironrment and<br />
Conservation. The committee held its first meeting last night, shortly<br />
after the full Cabinet ncmeeting.<br />
Mr. Stewart said the pro) osed new Tov. nsville airport would<br />
cut travelling time for overeoas touristo and %: ould also eliminate<br />
many of the inconveniences aLsociated with changing aircraft. / 2 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
