<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16498</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview - Port Hedland, Western Australia    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/04/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST: Are you disappointed that this has happened again in Thailand, this instability is (inaudible) very important meetings (inaudible)?</p>
<p>PM: Well the East Asian Summit brings together heads of government from right across our region  -  from Japan, from Korea, from China, right across South East Asia. So this is disappointing for all heads of government. There's important business to discuss on the future of the regional economy given the impact of the global economic recession. And we'll have to of course reconvene this meeting at a later time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It's been cancelled twice now effectively, what confidence would you have for democracy in Thailand if they cannot hold this sort of meeting?</p>
<p>PM: Obviously there are deep problems in Thai domestic politics at present. I think all friends of Thailand want to see a return to political normality in the Kingdom of Thailand. It's going to be important for the future for that to occur and we all urge all parties to adhere to peaceful, democratic means to return Thai politics to normal.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Just about Fiji as well, you talked about-</p>
<p>PM: One other thing on Thailand if I might say this. All Australians in, either in Thailand at present or contemplating travel to Thailand, should consult carefully the Australian Government's travel advisory. It's important that Australians remain closely in touch with the most recent details about their safety and security within Thailand as well.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: There's no evidence that tourists are being targeted in Thailand though are they?</p>
<p>PM: I would just urge all Australians to consult the travel advisory, which urges people to apply appropriate caution in their movements within Thailand and in making decisions to travel there.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: And Fiji, talking about instability in the region, you must be deeply disappointed with what's gone on in there in the last few days?</p>
<p>PM: Australia condemns unequivocally this action by the military ruler of Fiji to turn this great country Fiji into virtually, a military dictatorship, with the suspension of freedom of the press and actions which undermine prosperity for the ordinary people of Fiji.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
