<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10246</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES, RADIO 2UE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010246.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
19 February 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH ALAN JONES, RADIO 2UE<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
JONES: There is absolute amazement in the community today and from people ringing my<br />
programme here about what happened at the Prime Minister's electorate office at<br />
Gladesville yesterday. These people taped an effigy of Mr Howard over the portrait of<br />
the Queen. They scrawled beneath it, Her Majesty, Queen John Howard. They<br />
ordered pizzas, drank beer, made phone calls, climbed in through the roof of his office<br />
and crawled under a glass petition. These are Greenies, protesting at a Government<br />
decision. The Government decision is irrelevant. It wouldn't matter what it was<br />
about. They spent three hours chaining themselves to desks and chairs, calls were<br />
made to New Zealand in an attempt to contact Mr Howard by these hooligans and<br />
louts but Mr Howard was already back in Canberra. Someone shouted out, does<br />
anyone have friends in Africa, presumably because, we can make a free call if we want,<br />
and what we can't understand as a public is that the police eventually got there at 2<br />
o'clock but the reports today suggest that Mr Howard's senior staff told the police to<br />
do nothing and allowed the protesters to occupy the office until closing time.<br />
Prime Minister Howard is on the line. Prime Minister, good morning.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
How are you Alan?<br />
JONES: Not too badly. What do you make of all this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Congratulations on your ratings performance. </p>
<p>JONES: Thank you. What do you make of all this, Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I didn't know much about it, quite frankly. I was told that the office had been<br />
occupied. I was tied up at a Cabinet meeting all day and I was given only the scantiest<br />
details of it. I obviously will have a chat to my staff about it. My only, my immediate<br />
concern yesterday when I was told about it was as to whether my electoral staff who<br />
are very working and conscientious, whether they were okay and I was assured by my<br />
people in Canberra that they were and that the matter was being discussed with the<br />
police. I didn't know how many or when the police had arrived and as I think my staff<br />
may have indicated to your staff this morning, my own personal knowledge of the<br />
details of it but it simply didn't go beyond that. As you understand I was tied up in a<br />
Cabinet meeting all day and..<br />
JONES: Let me tell you about the public concerns?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Just a moment, Alan. Things like this have happened before, not perhaps as well<br />
publicised, as widely publicised as this but from time to time people do sort of move<br />
into electorate offices. It's happened to the former Government. I think it happened<br />
once to Mr Keating's office in Bankstown. I guess the point I'd like to make is that I<br />
think it gives the broader conservation movement in Australia a poor name because<br />
most people who are worried about Australia's environment and want to conserve<br />
things in this country do so in a totally sort of lawful and democratic fashion and I just<br />
make the further point that the decision against which they were protesting and I think<br />
it is important that this be made, the decision against which these people were<br />
protesting was a decision of the Government which has been upheld by the Federal<br />
Court of Australia. It was not only a politically correct decision in the proper sense of<br />
that term but also a legally valid and a legally justified decision and one that balanced<br />
the interests of the environment with a desire on the part of the Government to see<br />
some jobs created in small business in North Queensland, and I don't think the<br />
environmental movement gets a particularly good name from something like this.<br />
JONES: Well it sure as hell get's an appalling name but I just come back to the point, and you<br />
seem very relaxed about it..<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, well I never believe in sort of over reacting or indeed underreacting to things like<br />
this and.. </p>
<p>JONES: No. Well might I suggest you might be under reacting because let me tell you what<br />
many people are saying today. A call was made to you in New Zealand, so these<br />
people obviously didn't know where you were. They've got that much wrong. You<br />
could well have been in the electorate office. Forget they were environmental people.<br />
They've come in through the roof They've crawled under a glass petition. I mean, if<br />
they are going to come at that, go to those lengths, what's to ' say-hat the Prime<br />
Minister of Australia, forget it's John Howard, is not at risk. What is the level of<br />
security in relation to the Prime Minister that his electorate office can be invaded<br />
through the roof by an indiscriminate mob?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well can I say, Alan, that whether anybody regards it as an underreaction or whatever,<br />
I never feel insecure in Australia. Now you may think I'm foolish. I have a security<br />
detail but I never feel insecure.<br />
JONES: No, one of your greatest assets is you want to be part of the people, yes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I mean, you know, some people may regard that as a foolhardy expression of opinion<br />
but I have, I don't feel insecure. From time to time there are demos at meetings I<br />
address. That's part of the process and it goes with the territory and bear in mind..<br />
JONES: But you don't come through the roof, do you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No but I mean the fact is I wasn't there. Look, Alan,<br />
JONES: Should your staff have told the police to do nothing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look I'm not even going to try and answer that because I haven't spoken at length to<br />
my staff about the incident. That's not because I'm disinterested. It's because I had<br />
an eight hour Cabinet meeting yesterday and I had an engagement last night and my<br />
senior staff in Canberra, in whom I have total confidence, briefed me about the<br />
incident. I inquired about the safety and well being of my own staff in the electorate<br />
office. And I will get a further report about the matter today. But I'm simply not </p>
<p>going to hypothesise about what should or shouldn't have been done. I will get a<br />
report about it and I will ask, I will then assess what I've been told.<br />
JONES: If I could just ask you one finally thing in a total relaxed mood in which you'd never,<br />
ever feel threatened would you be at all worried that someone could get in through<br />
the roof of your house or your electoral office or the Lodge or anywhere, get in<br />
through the roof?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well Alan, those things don't really enter my head. I think if you go into this business<br />
and you start worrying about those things I mean, I worry... I1 mean the only people I<br />
worry about in this game is I mean, I have an interest obviously in the comfort of my<br />
family and the comfort of my staff. But I mean I'm a realist but I also take the view<br />
that the Australian people, even those that can't stand me politically and you know<br />
there are...<br />
JONES: Just a couple.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, there are probably more than a couple, but I mean that's the nature of..<br />
JONES: Rumour has it you don't have to go onto the second hand Prime Minister.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I don't know about that. I wouldn't quite... you've got to keep in touch. But<br />
look, I am not somebody who gets worked up about securities. I have a security<br />
detail. It is sensible and they are with me and they do a very good job. And I always<br />
get a bit concerned if the people around me, sort of get the backwash.<br />
JONES: But you would want this behaviour to be prosecuted. As a leader this can't happen to<br />
other people, can it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I mean, I have a very strong view that the question of prosecutions and so forth is a<br />
matter for the police even when it involves my office and my staff and so forth. That is<br />
a matter for the law enforcement authorities. I have pretty traditional views about the<br />
role of police. I respect their role. You know, they cop a lot of criticism and I'm </p>
<p>never in to making gratuitous comments about the police, whether the State police or<br />
the Federal police. I think it's a pretty difficult job in our society and I have a lot of<br />
sympathy look, all I can say is the law in this should take its course. There should be<br />
no special case made of this. Equally it should not be treated any more, you know, be<br />
treated less seriously than any other case. But it's not for me. In relation to this I'm a<br />
citizen and it's for the police to take decisions about this matter. And I don't intend to<br />
use my office and my position to bring about any particular result. I will find out what<br />
happened. I'll just say again that the environmental movement should not be judged by<br />
the behaviour of these people. There are a lot of very decent, dedicated<br />
environmentalists in Australia even though they disagree with some of our policies,<br />
they accept and respect the lawful process of Australia.<br />
JONES: 1 don't want to be nitpicking here, I'm just concerned, I suppose, for the many people<br />
out there in suburban Australia who worry that the notion of invasion and interference<br />
with other peoples property is becoming much more pressing in their lives than has<br />
been in the past.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That in a sense is a different matter.<br />
JONES: Well I've just to ask you this question, you see, and you may not answer it but...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
concern. I mean, I can understand people who aren't involved in public life. I mean,<br />
you've got to accept that there is a certain interruption in privacy which doesn't occur<br />
if people aren't in public life and...<br />
JONES: But it's public property. It's someone else's property. I would have thought...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look Alan, I'm trying to sort of get the balance right in this...<br />
JONES: Well, I just want I'm not arguing with you either I just want to raise one question<br />
and I'll let you go. The one question is this, if someone out there enters someone<br />
else's property which is not there's, illegally, you call for the police and you expect the<br />
police to do their job. My concern when I heard about this was that your staff told<br />
them to do nothing until it was closing time. Do you think and you may not want to </p>
<p>answer this, but I'm just saying if you could get an answer that the law may have<br />
been stopped from doing its job by your staff?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh look, I'm not even going to try and answer that Alan. I mean, I don't know<br />
whether that report is accurate in every detail. I've really, I've just got to talk to my<br />
staff and find out precisely what happened.<br />
JONES: Okay, we'll let you go and thank you for taking the call.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's all right Alan. Always a pleasure to talk to you.<br />
JONES: Okay, thanks Prime Minister.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
