<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12250</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT BY THE QUEEN AND THE DUKE OF EDINBURGH</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I am pleased to announce that the Centenary of Federation celebrations will provide a special focus for The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh during their visit to Australia in October.<br />
The Royal couple will arrive in Australia on 3 October 2001 for the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Brisbane and will also visit Canberra, Adelaide and a number of regional centres in Queensland and South Australia.  They will depart Australia from Adelaide on 12 October 2001.<br />
They will attend a number of Centenary of Federation events including a visit to Roma, Queensland, where The Queen will open the Big Rig Oil and Gas Museum, a Centenary of Federation project which marks the birthplace of Australia's oil and gas industry.<br />
The Duke of Edinburgh will be the Reviewing Officer at the Centenary of Federation International Naval Review on Sydney Harbour and will also visit the home of one of the federation's founding fathers, the Hon Charles Kingston, in Adelaide.<br />
The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh will also visit North Queensland where The Queen will launch a new aircraft for the Royal Flying Doctor Service in Cairns.<br />
In South Australia, The Queen will visit the Barossa Valley and open an aged care facility at Tanunda.  The Duke of Edinburgh will inspect seafood industry operations at Ceduna and visit Port Lincoln.<br />
The programme has been organised so that The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh can meet many Australians in both formal and informal settings, and in regional areas as well as cities.<br />
I am sure The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh will be welcomed wherever they go in Australia with the warmth and hospitality for which Australians are renowned.<br />
Further details of their programme will be released separately by the governments of Queensland and South Australia as they have overall responsibility for the activities occurring within their states.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
