<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2935</transcript-id>
    <title>SOLIDARITY WITH THE COLONIAL PEOPLES OF AFRICA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002935.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 87 25 May 1973<br />
SOLTDARITY ' IT T-HE COLONIAL PEOPLE' OF AFRICA<br />
The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr Whitlam, said today that t}' e Australian neople and Government<br />
supnorted the inalienable right to self-determination and<br />
independence of the peoples of Namibia, Zimbabwe and Portuguese<br />
territories in Africa.<br />
In a statement on the occasion of Africa Liberation<br />
Day ( today, 25 May), Mr Whitlam said that this support was<br />
clearly manifested in the actions of the present Government.<br />
Africa Liberation Day marks the beginning of the inaugural<br />
Week of Solidarity with the Colonial Peoples of South Africa and<br />
Guinea ( BISSAU) Fighting for Freedom, Independence and Equal<br />
Rights. The United Nations General Assembly, at its 27th<br />
session in 1972, instituted the Week of Solidarity which will<br />
be held annually. Mr Whitlam said that the present Government's actions<br />
of supnort had included changes in Australia's voting on African<br />
issues at the 27th session of the United Nations General Assembly,<br />
financial 3Unnort of the United Nations funds established to / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
further the educational and other aspirations of the peoples of<br />
Southern Africa, wholehearted co-operation with the efforts of<br />
the international community to bring to an end the illegal Smith<br />
regime in Zimbabwe through sanctions and other measures, and the<br />
exclusion from Australia of South African sporting teams selected<br />
on a racial basis.<br />
The Prime Minister recalled that Africa Liberation Day<br />
this year marked the tenth anniversary of the signing in Addis<br />
Ababa of the Charter of the Organisation of African Unity. The<br />
O. A. U. had resolved on 25 May 1963 that that day would be observe*<br />
as Africa Liberation Day.<br />
Mr Whitlam said he had already conveyed to the Organisation<br />
the congratulations and good wishes of the Government and people<br />
of Australia on the occasion of the tenth anniversary of the O. A. U<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
