<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9068</transcript-id>
    <title>
      </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009068.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NINE NETWORK AUSTRALIA LIMITED<br />
A. C. N. 009 071 167<br />
SUITE 114 PRESS GALLERY PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
CANBERRA A. C. T. 2600 AUSTRALIA<br />
TELEPHONE: ( 06) 273 3300 FACSIMILE: ( 06) 273 3097<br />
WIN TV SUNDAY 0940 05.12.93<br />
Subject: INV Prime Minister Paul Keating<br />
Compere ( Jim Waley):<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: As we've already heard, the Malaysian Government line<br />
seems to be hardening in the row over Paul Keating's<br />
choice of words to describe Prime Minister Mahathir.<br />
A letter from Mr Keating, explaining he meant no<br />
offence, has been rejected as not conciliatory and now<br />
there are reports that the Malaysian Cabinet will<br />
consider downgrading the relationship with Australia.<br />
This latest threat was made public last night after<br />
Sunday's Political Editor, Laurie Oakes, recorded this<br />
interview in Canberra with Prime Minister Keating.<br />
Prime Minister, the first issue I wanted to talk about,<br />
obviously; is Malaysia. Dr Mahathir has rejected your<br />
letter. What's your response?<br />
Oh, I don't know that he rejected the letter. I think he<br />
just said that it was not as conciliatory as he expected it.<br />
But the one clear message in it is I mean, it's an<br />
honest, frank letter but the one clear message in it is that<br />
what I said was not calculated to offend him, and that's<br />
true. So, therefore no offence was intended and I hope </p>
<p>he accepts therefore that none was taken.<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: Well, he said last night that it did give offence. Do you<br />
regret that, even though you didn't intend it, do you<br />
regret that he took offence?<br />
Well, if my remarks were not intended to offend him<br />
and he has taken offence at it, well naturally one would<br />
regret that. But they were said in the context which, at<br />
the time, made it fairly clear that there were some issues<br />
of difference between us and I've always got to argue,<br />
and will of course, for Australia's policy positions.<br />
Have you done all you can now or will you try and<br />
make contact again?<br />
No, I think what I have done is very reasonable. That<br />
is, I've written to him, putting in some sort of context<br />
I mean, there is not much point in writing letters saying<br />
' Dear Prime Minister, under the tail plane in the Boeing<br />
747, I had this to say', and not provide any cofitext, and<br />
I've put some context-there but made clear that the<br />
remarks were not designed to offend. The remarks were<br />
made to say ' look, this is not my matter'. That is<br />
whether Dr Mahathir attends APEC meetings or decides,<br />
as he put it, to thumb his nose at people, is for him.<br />
That was the point of the remark.<br />
Although you obviously didn't apologise in this letter, is </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: it fair to say that you're sorry that he's offended?<br />
Laurie, look I've made it quite clear. I represent<br />
Australia's national interest. We have interests, I was<br />
asked by journalists and I've been asked persistently for<br />
months about Dr Mahathir's attending of these meetings.<br />
On the day I was asked, what prompted the question was<br />
his remark saying that his policy was to thumb his nose<br />
to people and that was his best way of being noticed. It<br />
was in that context I said ' please don't ask me about<br />
Dr Mahathir. It's not my matter and that APEC's larger<br />
than any one of us, including those who seek to thumb<br />
their nose at people.' That's what I was really saying.<br />
It was not, I don't think, offensive or calculated to<br />
offend. Now, that's what I have told Dr Mahathir quite<br />
clearly but look, we want to put a line under the<br />
relationship, Laurie and get on with it. Now, I've got<br />
Senator Cook and Senator Ray going there this week. I<br />
mean, it's very tangible evidence on our part. We want<br />
to keep the relationship going and on a good footing. I<br />
think there are substantial opportunities in the economic<br />
developments between Australia and Malaysia. This has<br />
always been our view and, you know, we want to try<br />
and maintain that kind of momentum.<br />
Dr Hewson says that you should now pick up the phone<br />
and talk to Dr Mahathir personally. Is there any point<br />
in that? </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Well, I don't think so. I think I've said what I wanted<br />
to say but, you know, one the Federal Opposition<br />
saying in the first instance they could understand my<br />
remarks and then, as late as yesterday, Dr Hewson was<br />
running around saying I should get on the phone and do<br />
this and do that. Well, I mean, they should make their<br />
mind up what they meant. I mean, I'm sure their first<br />
response was right. That was that they could understand<br />
my remarks and Australia does have a position of<br />
substance on these various issues between Australia and<br />
Malaysia and I've put those. But again, hopefully in the<br />
context of a good ongoing relationship.<br />
Since you've been Prime Minister, you've stressed the<br />
need for Australia to engage more heavily in Asia.<br />
Now, how does this row affect that?<br />
Well, I mean, I don't think it does. I mean, we have<br />
had spats with Malaysia before on other issues, or more<br />
particularly, Malaysia's had spats with us on other<br />
issues. I have a very good relationship with-President<br />
Sohato, I've a very good relationship with Prime<br />
Minister Go Chok Chong(?), I've an equally good<br />
relationship with President Kim Yung Sam(?) and I<br />
would like such a relationship with Prime Minister<br />
Mahathir but he's got to want it to. Malaysia's got to<br />
want to have a relationship with Australia of the kind<br />
Australia's prepared to have with it. </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes: If the worst happens and there are more sanctions, more<br />
retaliation from the Malaysian side, does Australia have<br />
any way of hitting back? I mean, could we engage in a<br />
fit for tat fight with them on this level?<br />
Well, I don't think we would like to. That's the point.<br />
We would prefer a constructive relationship to continue.<br />
But what about those 5 power arrangements? I mean, is<br />
that something that we could pull out of if we took<br />
offence? Well, I mean, defence agreements are fairly solemn<br />
things and, of course, they exist because countries<br />
regard each other's sovereignty as important enough to<br />
defend and that means keeping core relationships going.<br />
Now, I think everybody in that arrangement, including<br />
Malaysia, understands the importance of keeping the<br />
relationships going. Australia certainly does.<br />
But if there's a freeze on the Malaysian side, r mean, is<br />
there any point in having a defence relationship like<br />
that? Well, I think this is premature to be talking about this,<br />
Laurie. Well, the reason I raise it is that when we had the last<br />
spat you mentioned in ' 91 over the Embassy television </p>
<p>Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: -series, Gareth Evans did make some recommendations<br />
about this to the then Prime Minister. Bob Hawke took<br />
a different view and he decided instead to apologise, but<br />
presumably that kind of recommendation is still there for<br />
you to look at.<br />
Well, I'm not aware of that, to be honest. Thank you<br />
for the research.<br />
But you haven't looked at that yourself this time.<br />
No. What would the Malaysians have to do to prompt you to<br />
go that far? I mean, if they were to start defecting<br />
Australian businesses, disadvantaging say the company<br />
that's bidding for the patrol boat contract, you couldn't<br />
sit back and just cop it, could you?<br />
Well, I don't think it's going to help our relationship for<br />
me to even canvas those issues. I mean, I'm faking the<br />
presumption-Malaysia wants a good cooperative<br />
relationship with Australia, as certainly as we want with<br />
it. But again, as I said earlier, Malaysia does have to<br />
want that. In the end, we can't whistle up or in some<br />
way develop the spirit of a great relationship if one party<br />
doesn't want that. Now, I mean, our bona fides in this<br />
are that our two very senior ministers are going there<br />
this week to maintain that relationship and I think really </p>
<p>we've got to see where it goes from there.<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: Do you wish you hadn't used the word recalcitrant?<br />
Well, Dr Mahathir said that morning that he thought the<br />
best policy was to thumb to use his words thumb his<br />
nose at people to be noticed. The word recalcitrant was<br />
a sort of shorthand way of tailking about the odd person<br />
out or odd people out. As he had himself described<br />
himself that way, I didn't think it was particularly doing<br />
anything other than simply identifying that kind of<br />
attitude. The reason I asked for this interview was to look to the<br />
future in our last program for the year. So, I guess I'd<br />
better move on to that. Can I ask you, do you think that<br />
at last the economic and political cycles are coming<br />
together for your government?<br />
Well, I think that's true but I think, more particularly,<br />
the economic cycle's coming together for the country. I<br />
mean, we are growing now at three and a quarter<br />
percent, we're growing as fast as any other OECD<br />
country, there's a fair bit of, there's a nice mix in some<br />
of that a bit of investment, private consumption, a bit<br />
of government spending but all in all, it's going quite<br />
well. We're seeing job vacancies improving quite<br />
sharply, job ads and we saw 70,000 employment<br />
growths in the last 2 months. So, I think we can say </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: with some confidence, the economy is now looking<br />
much better.<br />
And what about the Japanese situation? I mean, how<br />
worried are you that the problems they have could drag<br />
Australia back?<br />
Well, I think it's certainly delaying their recovery.<br />
Japan's still running a structural budget surplus. I can't,<br />
with all due respects to Japan, see a lot of sense in a<br />
country which has got a recessing running a structural<br />
budget surplus. Now, there may be some indications<br />
that the government of Japan is going to change its<br />
policy there. That would help. But there's no doubt<br />
these very big changes in asset values would be very<br />
inhibiting of growth and activity in investment. That<br />
can't be good for us, Laurie, but again, given the spread<br />
of our the elements of our growth and where it's<br />
coming, I think we can maintain the kind of growth<br />
rates we've got at the moment and do better.<br />
You've been preoccupied since the election by Mabo.<br />
That's, every other way, served one way or the other. I<br />
mean, what's your priority for ' 94? What's your main<br />
focus? Well, I think we're coming into ' 94 with the following<br />
things in place the economy growing, we will have<br />
received the report on full employment by the 15th of </p>
<p>December. On the 16th of December, Bill Kelty will<br />
present the Regional Development Task Force report..<br />
We'll be focussing on those two things in the run up to<br />
the budget which will now be an earlier budget and that<br />
kind of focus, I think, coupled with other changes which<br />
the government will be looking at over the course of the<br />
year, including say in health, means that we're going to<br />
have a fairly full domestic agenda, following as it has<br />
already upon a very successful conclusion of<br />
negotiations in respect of industrial relations. I hope by<br />
then a successful conclusion of the Mabo debate in<br />
legislation, the development of APEC as a structure for<br />
Australian investment and trade to grow within.<br />
So, we're moving on a broad front but I think next year<br />
we'll get back onto those domestic issues and hopefully<br />
that will occupy a large part of the debate.<br />
Laurie Oakes: Prime Minister, we'll pause for a break. We'll be back<br />
in a moment.<br />
Prime Minister, the task force on unemployment's due<br />
to report, I think on the 15th of December. Do you<br />
expect any sort of left field options from them, anything<br />
radical?<br />
Paul Keating: Well, I think that the whole tenor of the report in<br />
western world terms will be reasonably radical. I mean,<br />
I think we can pride ourselves on being quite innovative </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: in social policy with things like the family allowance<br />
supplement-and those other income support mechanisms<br />
over time. I think we have the opportunity here to be<br />
doing something innovative again. There is no doubt<br />
that there is a problem and a reasonably long term one<br />
with the long term unemployed and we have to address<br />
it otherwise it'll be a long term problem and so it was<br />
an important part of our election policy, that as I said<br />
we wouldn't leave the unemployed behind and that's<br />
why the Government will be considering it very<br />
carefully and acting on it as quickly as possible.<br />
In the budget...<br />
In the budget and of course it'll be an early budget<br />
which means we'll be acting on it fairly early.<br />
You're prepared to spend money on it?<br />
Well, I think so. But again, that's got to be money well<br />
spent. That is that the proposal has got to be thought<br />
about, thought in the structure of our current policies in<br />
respect of the labour market so that when we spend<br />
money, we spend it effectively.<br />
The ACTU talks about spending $ 3 billion. Is that the<br />
sort of ball park you've got in mind?<br />
No, I haven't got any in mind at this stage, Laurie. I </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: think it is very important for us actually to see the<br />
colour of the report, to see what's actually<br />
recommended. But does that sound unrealistic?<br />
Sounds on the high side to me, for some of the<br />
objectives that have been spoken of.<br />
The ACTU, of course, like ACOSS and a large slab of<br />
the Caucus, says it should be paid for, part of it should<br />
be paid for with a jobs levy. Now, what do you think<br />
about that? Your Treasurer doesn't like it.<br />
Well, no, I think John has made a remark about it but it<br />
is an option, of course. It's a relatively short term<br />
response to what would otherwise be a long term<br />
problem. How we'll raise the revenue or how we will<br />
deal with outlays are matters for the ERG and the<br />
Budget Cabinet to consider. But the jobs levy is<br />
obviously an option and we'll consider that because it<br />
may well be that the report actually recommends it.<br />
The employers, of course, say that the jobs levy will<br />
cost jobs and there seems to be some backing from<br />
economists for that.<br />
Well, I think that that's like saying that the<br />
Commonwealth revenue, wherever it might be, if it's </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: high it'll cost jobs, if it's lower it won't. I mean, this is<br />
the lowest taxed country in the western world. I mean,<br />
this is the point I think the Australian business<br />
community have got to understand. This is the lowest<br />
taxed country in the western world and the profit share<br />
in GDP, the profit share in the economy now, is back to<br />
the highs of the late ' 80s. So, I don't think there's any<br />
real case for saying the Commonwealth shouldn't be<br />
spending money on the long term unemployed.<br />
So you don't have an in principle objection to the jobs<br />
levy idea?<br />
I don't have an in principle objection but I don't, I've<br />
never embraced levies in the past when we've spoken of<br />
them and when I was Treasurer, for what I thought at<br />
the time were good reasons. So, I'd like to see what is<br />
recommended, look at our budgetary options and then<br />
see what we can do within the, if you like, the normal<br />
parameters of budget making.<br />
Now, is your plan for next year all economic or have<br />
you got some sort of cultural program as well?<br />
Well, we've got, we've had this review of cultural<br />
policy being undertaken. That will be announced next<br />
year. I think the whole there has been a see change in<br />
Australia, Laurie. There's no doubt the culture has<br />
changed from the ' 80s culture, the ' 70s culture of </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: protection. Australia's now an open trading economy,<br />
we've got the GATT backdrop hopefully underpinning a<br />
greater growth in trade around the world, we've got<br />
APEC as well but we are now very, very competitive<br />
with a competitive exchange rate mechanism, low<br />
inflation, low interest rates. It's all there for us. We've<br />
got a good education system which is feeding through<br />
into our industrial base and into product innovation and<br />
research and development.<br />
How's that related to culture?<br />
I think one has to look at all of that in terms of a total<br />
culture. That is, Australians have got to know, have got<br />
to feel proud about themselves, they've got to feel proud<br />
about the change they've made in the last 10 years and<br />
we go to the world as ourselves, as a totality. In other<br />
words, you just can't market a bit of R D here or a<br />
particular service there. You go as Australians who<br />
have made an important change competently to deal with<br />
the rest of the world. So, I think the whole culture<br />
matters. I -think art matters, culture matters. You know<br />
my views about the republic. I think the earlier<br />
Australia represents itself in these matters, the better.<br />
So, what you're talking about is creating some sort of<br />
national spirit but can governments do that?<br />
Well, I think a lot of that's happening already. It's a </p>
<p>combination of the Government's ' 80s policies changes<br />
and the early ' 90s policy changes and the willingness on<br />
the part of the Australian public to actually make an<br />
important change for their own long term economic and<br />
social benefit. It's a totality and I think we're a long<br />
way down the road to that totality but I do see it all as<br />
one thing. I don't think just the economic bit and then<br />
there's the sort of social bit and it's got to be a total, a<br />
total view of Australia.<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: We're almost out of time but could I ask you about the<br />
political bit? You're now facing a couple of hielections,<br />
probably 3. It's a bad time for you to face a<br />
hi-election, isn't it, with the Government on the nose,<br />
basically? I don't think that's true, Laurie. I don't think the<br />
Liberals have any standing, basically. John Hewson<br />
hasn't come up with a policy change since the election.<br />
But they're miles ahead in the polis. I mean; these hielections<br />
must show a big anti-government swing:<br />
Well, hi-elections traditionally do, hut look, all of this<br />
will come back to the field. If you ask people seriously<br />
whether the Opposition amounts to an alternative<br />
government, I don't think the answer to that's in the<br />
affirmative. John Hewson's been the classic<br />
Oppositionist, opportunist since the election. . He's </p>
<p>Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating: nothing like the figure he said he would be someone<br />
removed from public life, trying to do the right thing in<br />
policy. That's all gone and even last week he said<br />
basically he was readopting the essence of Fightback.<br />
So, I don't think in leadership or policy terms I can't<br />
remember one policy that they've articulated since<br />
March 1993 that matters. Not one policy.<br />
But if that's the case, why are you so far behind in the<br />
polls? I mean, is it because of the things you refer to as<br />
dust in the cracks of history? Are people offended by<br />
things like your style?<br />
In political terms, we had a bad budget and it's taken us<br />
a lot to in political terms. In economic terms, it was a<br />
very good budget for us. It's taken us a while to<br />
recover from that. We have had the distraction of all<br />
these other issues and<br />
What about your so-called imperial style?<br />
Well, I think people will make their judgement about<br />
that. In the end, I think people ' make their judgement<br />
without the big issues. You know, in a couple of weeks<br />
where we concluded the budget, wrapped up a deal on<br />
Mabo, attended a meeting of APEC of which we had a<br />
large part in the architecture there of, and are now about<br />
to consider long term unemployment and regional<br />
development, for that not to be recognised I mean, I've </p>
<p>been here a long time and so have you. There was<br />
more change this year than there was in 10 years of<br />
Coalition governments. I mean, I remember my own<br />
government and the Gorton Government and the whole<br />
government. I mean, they didn't do these sorts of<br />
things. So, I think it's pretty unfair to have that, you know,<br />
important classic work you know, really large changes<br />
in any way diminished by basically silly issues.<br />
Laurie Oakes:<br />
Paul Keating:<br />
Compere: Prime Minister, we thank you.<br />
Thank you, Laurie.<br />
The Prime Minister with Laurie Oakes.<br />
ENDS Agency Report For private research and not to be disseminated. Every effort made to ensure accuracy for the benefit of our clients but<br />
no legal or other responsibility is taken for errors or omissions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
