<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3257</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO GOVERNMENT PROCUREMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003257.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARLIAMENTARt1 O<br />
4&gt; usTAA<br />
PRIME MINISTER 13 May 1974<br />
COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY INTO GOVERNMENT PROCUREMENT<br />
The Prime Minister announced today that the Chairman of the<br />
I SCccooomntcmtil, tu steiheoa nd so fw rainIdtn tqeurnie rcytoo m mienantddov aitsGieoo vnehsri. nm m eofnT th et hPePr roicCmuoerm emmMieitnnttie, se t'esSr i rm arjeWocaralltleer d<br />
that in announcing the establishment of the Committee in<br />
November 1973, it was foreshadowed that the Committee's<br />
report would form the basis of a review, by Ministers, of<br />
procurement policy. This review, he said, would be carried<br />
out as soon as possible after receipt of the Committee's<br />
full report which was expected shortly.<br />
The Prime Minister said that Sir Walter had advised him that<br />
the Committee's major conclusion was that the procurement<br />
function as a whole had been seriously neglected, and was not<br />
serving the Australian Government or its suppliers, as'<br />
effectively as it should. Sir Walter said the Committee<br />
recommended that, in order to upgrade the procurement function<br />
to a degree commensurate with its importance to both government<br />
I baen d esitnadbusltirsyh, e d aans Auas tcreantlriaaln Gpourvcehranmseinngt aPuutrhcohraistiyn g toC obmmeission<br />
responsible for the co-ordination of policy, and in the course<br />
of time, for the purchase of goods and services for all<br />
departments with the possible exception of certain specialised<br />
functions.<br />
The Committee sees two major advantages from the creation of<br />
an Australian Government Purchasing Commission. First, it<br />
considers that such a Commission should make possible greater<br />
efficiency and streamlining in the whole process of Government<br />
procurement, as it saw obvious gains to be achieved in terms<br />
of economy and efficiency of operations. Secondly, the<br />
Committee considers the Commission could be expected to develop<br />
an expertise and experience which would allow it to purchase<br />
more effectively for the various Government departments for<br />
which it would act as agent. It was thought that the Commission<br />
should achieve the traditional objective of Government<br />
purchasing, the " best value for money", more effectively than<br />
the present system.<br />
The Committee also recommended that, as soon as possible, the<br />
proposed Commission should initiate a thorough overhaul of the<br />
principles, rules and regulations governing the procurement<br />
function. In the meantime, the Committee would make a number<br />
of detailed recommbndations designed to improve the situation<br />
immediately. In particular it would recommend that the </p>
<p>SGovernment overhaul its forward planning for procurement, so<br />
that suppliers will have a better knowledge of what is required.<br />
The Prime Minister said he had also been advised that the<br />
Committee would be suggesting ways in which Government purchasing<br />
may be used to further other policy aims considered desirable<br />
by the Government. The Committee has concluded that in various<br />
ways and in varying degrees Government purchasing can be used to<br />
help to achieve some policy objectives; in the field of product<br />
standards and testing; in the following of a labour employment<br />
code; the employment of women; the employment of aborigines;<br />
promoting regional development; furthering technological progress;<br />
requiring pollution control; encouraging industrial efficiency;<br />
setting standards in the field of motor vehicle safety; and<br />
in influencing a desirable structure of industrial development<br />
in line with Government policy and community needs.<br />
The Committee's report will also suggest means by which<br />
Government purchasing can be used to further the policy of<br />
encouraging a higher level of Australian ownership and control<br />
of industry. Q<br />
The Prime Minister said he wished to place on record the<br />
Government's appreciation of the valuable work done by the<br />
Committee. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
