<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23608</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit by the Prime Minister of Japan</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister of Japan, HE Mr Shinzo Abe, will make an official visit to Australia from 7-10 July as a guest of the Australian Government.</p>
<p>It will be the first bilateral visit to Australia by a Japanese Prime Minister since 2002.</p>
<p>Australia and Japan share a strong friendship based on common values, growing commercial and people-to-people links and shared interests.</p>
<p>We are both committed to the peace, stability and prosperity of the Asia-Pacific region.</p>
<p>We owe much of our economic prosperity over the last 50 years to our bilateral trade and investment following the signature of the Commerce Agreement in 1957.</p>
<p>Japan is Australia’s second-largest trading partner with two-way trade worth almost $70 billion in 2012-13 and Australia is a significant supplier of energy and resources to Japan.</p>
<p>Japan is a pilot country for the New Colombo Plan, which I launched during my visit to Japan in April. More than 140 Australian students are taking part in the first round of the Plan in Japan.</p>
<p>During his visit, Prime Minister Abe will address a joint sitting of the Houses of Parliament, meet senior Cabinet Ministers and sign the Japan-Australia Economic Partnership Agreement.</p>
<p>Mr Abe will also travel to the Pilbara and Perth. His visit to Australia, accompanied by a senior business delegation, will further strengthen our special relationship and build on the outcomes of our recent meetings in Japan.</p>
<p>I look forward to welcoming Prime Minister Abe to Australia and witnessing his historic address to Parliament.</p>
<p>30 June 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
