<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>571</transcript-id>
    <title>W.A. COVENTION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY AT SOUTH PERTH CIVIC CENTRE 30TH JULY, 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000571_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
W. A. CONVENTION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY<br />
AT SOUTH PERTH CIVIC CENTRE<br />
JOTH JULY,-1962<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. Premier and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I have really had quite a good day here. I<br />
first of all went to have a talk with Mr. Brand one of<br />
the great Premiers in the history of Australia ? Applause),<br />
then I recorded a television appearance, and those of you<br />
who haven't been through that misery, won't understand what<br />
a misery it is ( Laughter) and that, ltm told will be on at<br />
otclock tonight. Enough, no doubt, to undo whatever good<br />
I may do tonight ( Laughter).<br />
This afternoon, I went to the opening of a new<br />
building; I went on strict conditions that this was my<br />
afternoon off no speechmaking, but after I had arrived<br />
there, I began to detect in the mind and the voice of the<br />
Chairman a sort of hint that, with a little encouragement,<br />
he would ask me to speak and I was resolutely determined not<br />
to speak. Even a chattering fello.-w like myself needs t-Ime<br />
off occasionally ( hear, hear), and just as we were reaching<br />
the danger point His Excellency the Governor had spoken,<br />
the Chairman of the Company had spoken, the Premier was in<br />
midstream a note came into me that I was wanted on the<br />
telephone, At first I thought this was the effort of a<br />
zealous officer of mine ( because I have one or two who might<br />
be so described), but when I went out it turned out that it<br />
was the Prime Minister of New Zealand who wanted to have a<br />
little natter to mel and I said " My dear Keith, I can't tell<br />
you how glad I am to hear you. Laughter) When we have<br />
discussed our business letts keep it going for a little<br />
while" and we did. And so I was saved. ( Laughter)<br />
Now, I said just then something about your Premier.<br />
I'd like to say this. I know that there is a by-election.<br />
There are always by-elections. There will be one for Kooyong<br />
one of these days. ( Laughter) By-elections are terrible<br />
things but on this by-election at Bunbury much will turn for<br />
this State because to lose this by-election, would involve<br />
the Premier of Western Australia in the most tremendous<br />
political problem and I repeat what I said to you, we are all<br />
very much inclined, and particularly in our own country, to<br />
disregard the local product. " Oh, yes, he's quite good."<br />
" Oh yes, he's not bad." " Oh yes I knew him at school." It<br />
is a pity that Australians go outside their own bailiwick so<br />
frequently to be recognised. Every time your Premier comes<br />
to Canberra to a Loan Council Meeting, to a Premiers'<br />
Conference I find myself saying to my colleagues " Isn't this<br />
man absolutely first-class." I have never in my long experience<br />
of office the longest outside South Australia ( Laughter) of<br />
any man in Australia known a man to establish, time by time,<br />
year by year, such repute and authority among the Premiers as<br />
your Premier has. ( App), ause)<br />
And, therefore Mr. Chairman, whatever comes or<br />
goes'on the great issues that we discuss otherwise, I hope<br />
that everybody in the Liberal Party in this State will do<br />
whatever he can, directly or indirectly, sparing no effort to<br />
see that the Brand Government continues to exist and to serve<br />
this State, And, indeed, why shouldn't it? I almost give<br />
up guessing, I've been a long time now too long -in this<br />
c e* &amp; e a/ 2 </p>
<p>busiessand I never cease to marvel at how disposed people<br />
are to say 11Oh yes, whatever is good we must take for<br />
granted. Let us concentrate our minds on what we want, not<br />
on what we have or what we have achieved."' This is a very<br />
human falling. It is just as much as to say, " W1ell, Father<br />
Christmas hasn't been here this year. He came along last<br />
year rather handsomely." But when I look back over even the<br />
last ' twelve months, and remember what has been done by Dave<br />
Brand's Government and by my own in utter collaboration for<br />
the development of this State, I marvel that anybody could<br />
vote against him,<br />
In fact, I will tell you a story about that. I<br />
have a couple of sons who treat me with reasonable respect,<br />
and I have a daughter who treats me with more than respect,<br />
and before she was married, she travelled. around Ausuralia<br />
with me on one of tl'ese grr'at campaigns, you know my wife,<br />
my daughter and myself. We got back to Melbourne the night<br />
before the poll and my daughter leaned against the mantelpiece<br />
in the hotel sittingroom. and looked at me and said, " You know,<br />
Dad, I don't understa. id how anybody could vote against you."<br />
( laughter) I said, " Well, of course, darling, it's very nice<br />
of you to put it that h. ay, but I'll. settle for fifty percent,,<br />
plus one." ( Laughter) I want rather better than that for Mr. Brand,<br />
14oulC. you all think about it, would you all work on it?<br />
Because, really, it would be one of the ironies of political<br />
history to have a Government that has done and is doing more<br />
for this State than any other Government in its history, to<br />
be put in any position of embarrassment over a by-election,<br />
So it's your job. Everyone of you, directly or indirectly,<br />
Now, Sir, I thought I would like to talk to you<br />
as the Fede ral leader, about national policy, particularly<br />
internal national policy. There are quite a few people to be<br />
found who will say to you you know you have met a few of them;<br />
have perhaps said it yourselves " Oh yes. The Liberal Party<br />
stood for something. it has done great work, but what does it<br />
stand for now. It can't live on the past." Now, this is<br />
something that every political party that has had success must<br />
face up to " What do you stand for now. Are you living on<br />
the past?" It is just wlhen you have been in office for long<br />
enoutog hve a reat record of positive results that your<br />
opponents will be heard to say, " Yes, well., that's all right,<br />
but what are they doing next year or the year after or the<br />
year after," Then, with great gaiety, they begin to let<br />
their imaginations loose on what they would do,<br />
I notice that my friend and opponent, the Leader<br />
of the Opposition, has been in the Northern Territory. Dear<br />
me, what he's going to do ' or the Northern Territory after the<br />
next election exceeds all the expectations of his prospective<br />
Treasurer0 ( Laughter) But hevs announcing it0He doesn't<br />
realise, of course, that in my own Cabinet, we have a Minister<br />
who represents or administers the Northern Territory. That's<br />
Paul Hasluck, And iJ. f I were to give you a ball to ball<br />
description of how Paul Hasluck tr* ies to get the extra<br />
œ C100 000, the extra half million, the extra million out of us<br />
for he Northern Territory, you would be Jfascinated as listeners,<br />
and shocked as taxpayers. ( Laughter) And Paul knows all<br />
about it. Nobody has ever understood better the problems of<br />
the Territories than hoe does, but it's so easy, when a Government<br />
has been in office for a long time, for its opponents to say,<br />
" Oh, well, thais is what we'tll do, and so on,," 0904066OS / 3 </p>
<p>And, therefore, I thought I'd like to say something<br />
to you tonight about Liberalism as a living force.<br />
After all, as everybody knows, I had romething to do with<br />
the establishment of the Liberal Party in Australia and<br />
something to do with writing its first platform, and writing<br />
its constitution, and something, I hope, to do with subsequent<br />
achievements in the political world, I dontt regard<br />
Liberalism as a fading force, I think we've run our trial<br />
courses and that we are now at the beginning of the next<br />
great chapter of achievement. But if we are, then we must<br />
know, positively, what we stand for, Don't suppose that I<br />
am going to make you a policy speech about half crowns, oi<br />
five shillings or things, I want to know what it is we stand<br />
for, what we believe in, what makes you come here, what makes<br />
me come here, what makes the whole movement of Liberalism n<br />
Australia a powerful force6 So let's ask ourselv-es what our<br />
objectives are not yet achieved; far from it.<br />
i think that above althings we want to build in<br />
Australia a balanced and strong and progressive and civilised<br />
nation in which advances are shared by all sections of the<br />
people, Now you may say that's platitudinous, Perhaps it is.<br />
There are many great passages in English that are platitudinous<br />
and that, if you like, is a platitudeo But let's look at it.<br />
A balanced nation. That is, a nation in which primary industry<br />
and secondary industry and tertiary industry live side by side<br />
and achieve a common, national purpose, And the moment you<br />
say that you stand for a balanced nation, you are saying that<br />
whatever is done there must be progress, productivity,<br />
advancement for the man on the land, for the man in the factory,<br />
for the man on the truck or the railway train. This is a<br />
balanced community strong, progressive. I'll say something<br />
more about that in a moments<br />
And civilisedo There is a tremendous amount of<br />
talk engaged in about economic problems; there is a great<br />
amount of discussion about how much more money A gets or B<br />
gets or C gets, 4We could easily become man fr many woman<br />
for woman, the richest country in the Southern Hemisphere,<br />
cut it won't matter very much unless we can say that we are<br />
the most civilised country in the Southern Hemisphere,<br />
Civilised because we understand the unselfish duties of<br />
citizenship; civilised because we have come to understand<br />
the importance of tho human being, the dignity of the human<br />
being, the dignity of labour, the responsibility of riches,<br />
These are the tests of civilisation, and our great task is<br />
to produce a civilised nationo<br />
The only supplement I would like to make to that<br />
is that in our time, certainly in mirn there have been many<br />
furious attempts made to build up class warfare in Australia.<br />
We hear a lot about class distinctions. All the reactionary<br />
forces in the country, and I refer particularly to the<br />
socialists and the communists who are, of all people, the<br />
most reactionary, always like to talk about class distinction,<br />
the class war, in the classical phrases of the Communist Party<br />
that you so well remember.<br />
But I have, all my political life, believed that<br />
there is one single, very g: reat, class distinction in Australia.<br />
I insist on it. It's the distinction between people who work<br />
and people who donet; between people who contribute to human<br />
society and people who merely want to benefit from human<br />
society, This is an enormous distinction; and if in the<br />
language of the old Communist Manifesto, the phrase is,<br />
" Workers of the world unite you have nothing to lose but<br />
your chains," I say, " Yes. Worhkers of the world uniteo<br />
That's what the Liberal Party believes ino" ( Applause) e0 0 0 a3 0 9 t </p>
<p>Iow Sir, the next thing that L want to say to<br />
you is this. Here we are, we are a young nation, not<br />
unknown around the world, sometimes credited with being<br />
aggressive, sometimes accused of being noisy, but not unknown<br />
around the world, and I am happy to say, in all material<br />
quarters, respected around the world,, What we are engaged<br />
in doing, what we must continue to be engaged in doing is t<br />
build this young nation into a strong ans splendid heritage<br />
and that cantt be achieved by people who acquire habits of<br />
dependence. A Slight yawn " Wlhy doesn~ t the Government<br />
( whatever that ieans) do something about it." You can't<br />
build up an independent nation on a foundation of dependent<br />
people. The spirit of independence, this fire that burns<br />
in the veins of an independent nation must burn in the veins<br />
of the individual, We cannot succumb to the ideas of our<br />
opponents which, roughly, are that whatever good is to be<br />
done must be done by the L-ystical being the Government.<br />
This is, a matter for the individual; this is a matter which<br />
calls for a spirit of adventure, a desire to contribute.<br />
You know, it is a cant phrase, Sir, a cant phrase to talk<br />
about private enterprise and every now and then, I will hear<br />
people say, " Oh, of course, your Government is not as much<br />
in favour of private enterprise as it ought to Not<br />
infrequently when I hear somebody .3ay that, I come to discover<br />
what he means, What he means is that his particular private<br />
enterprise ought to be the nursling of the Government. He<br />
doesn't want private enterprise really; he doesn't want<br />
competition really; he wants to be protected from all the<br />
winds that blow, In other words, that particular private<br />
enterpriser has lost the spirit of adventure.<br />
Have we? This is the crucial question for the<br />
people of Australia, because our whole history has been a<br />
history of adveonture sailing wherever ships could sail.<br />
This island continent came out of the mists it was<br />
developed by people who had the spirit of aiventure. it<br />
has been found by people who had the spirit of adventure,<br />
Wherever you go in Australia, you see all the memorials<br />
not cairns of store, but the memorials in farms and stahions<br />
and factories to the people who had the spirit of adventure.<br />
And without that spirit of adventure, Australia can't become<br />
by the turn of the century the great and powerful and respected<br />
country to whose noises I would hope to listen from the grave.<br />
It's the spirit of adventure and it is our task as<br />
Liberals to foster it, not to foster the spirit of leaning<br />
on governments but to say thiat if private enterprise means<br />
what we think it means, it must be prepared to accept risks,<br />
take chances, go forward.<br />
Now, Sir, all that is by way of preliminary. I<br />
just want to elaborate that a little tonight by saying something<br />
t'Vo you about what, in material terms, might be regarded as<br />
our problems. And the first of them is to increase the population<br />
of this country, I think that when at the and of 19&amp;+ 9 we<br />
came back into office, full of adventure, full of hope? full<br />
of' thought, the population of Australia was about 7_ 2 million<br />
and, 9 today it's 1bJ million. There are three million more<br />
people in kustralia than when I went and took my oath of<br />
office at Government House only a few years ago. And we<br />
must do this. We know, do~ t we, what a pressure there is<br />
co 00000 </p>
<p>in the world great populations in Asia, China itself, which<br />
may very well have by the turn of the ' entury, a thousand<br />
million people " suckled in a creed outworn", if you like,<br />
still perhaps under the authority of Communism a thousand<br />
millions. If we, in Australia are to enjoy and defend our<br />
heritage, we can't afford to have 10i or 11 million people<br />
at the turn of the century. We must have our 25 or 30 or<br />
whatever it may be,, And this means that we must do whatever<br />
we can in this country to maintain the flow of immigrarts<br />
and that's not as easy as it looks, because you have fluctuations<br />
in the economy from time to time and there will always<br />
be people to be heard to say, " Well, you must cut down on<br />
Immigration or you must abolish immigra-t'ion,." We irust have<br />
people coming into Australia or we will oerish,<br />
I know about the proble.-. is of ipmigratior, not all<br />
about themi but I know a good deal about them and the<br />
pressures they make on resources and the impact that they<br />
make on the general problems of inflation in the country,<br />
but I am a convinced believer in imnmigration, because I<br />
believe that unless we can go on as we have been going on<br />
in Australia, increasing our population by importation and.<br />
by natural increase inside our own country by about 2 a<br />
year, thun we are going to be in a position in ten years'<br />
time, in fifteen years' time in which thie onlooking world<br />
will not tolerate our ownership of our trusts.<br />
That means, you know, that-. occasionally we ought to<br />
think about our grandchildren; not as rather nice little<br />
creatures, or naughty little creatures or dampening little<br />
creatures you know, all grandparents will understand what<br />
I mean ( Laughter), We musn't think of them entirely in<br />
that sense; we must think of them as those who, as the men<br />
and women of their -ace, will be standing responsible for<br />
Australia in their day, and there can't be too many of them.<br />
Therefore, to build up the population is a great and primary<br />
task. But you canft build up the population, Sir, in that<br />
handsome fashion and, at the same time, ignore the responsibility<br />
of providing proper employmaent for the people who live<br />
hero. Not only proper employment of human beings, though<br />
that is of supreme importance, but proper employment of the<br />
material resources of the nation. And, therefore, our<br />
second great task is to maintain full employment of manpower<br />
and material resources.<br />
Now so far, I suppose everybod~ y would say to me,<br />
" Yes, that~ s quite right. No difficulty in agreeing -to<br />
those things. Why labour them? They are two riat-ters;<br />
they are commonplace." Yes, I suppose they are I hope<br />
they are. But side by side with these matters we have, and<br />
particularly as a Government a profound responsibility to<br />
restrain the destruction of the currency, -to restrain inflation,<br />
to maintain economic stability. Now, the moment I come to<br />
that point because all the pressures of the first two<br />
propositions tend in the direction of inflation the moment<br />
i say, " But, at the same time, we must restrain inflation,"<br />
and I mention the word " stability" somaebody is bound to say,<br />
" Oh, IYes, there you are, you see. That's what's wrong with<br />
this Govirnment. It believes in stagnation." There is not<br />
much evidence, is there, in the last eleven years of the<br />
stagnation that we have produced? Not much. But today, they<br />
say, " Stability? Wel'l, that means Stagnation." oe, ./ 6 </p>
<p>Now, I'll come back to that because this is crucial<br />
to my argument, We have had for the last eighteen months,<br />
pursuant to policies for which we have, or some of us,<br />
been roundly abused, we have had, in Australia, for eighteen<br />
months, complete stability in the consumer price level.<br />
How many people really worry about inflation? I do,<br />
There must be a lot of people here tonight who do, who<br />
know that if their incomes are fixed by any method. at alJ.,<br />
then to have the value running out of their fixed income<br />
is a cruel, heartless tax on them. Of course, people of<br />
responsibility don't w" nt inflation. Gamblers do, becauce<br />
they can chase the market, But do you? Do you want<br />
inflation? It isn't stagnation o The fact is that for the last eightEen<br />
months we have had a steady level of prices-for the lasu<br />
eighteen months in consequence, we have had the most marvellous<br />
flow of capital into Australia for investment. " Here is a<br />
country that is stable, here is a country that is not afraid<br />
to take the measures designed to check inflation." I have<br />
had these things said to me abroad by some of the shrewdest<br />
financial people in the world who inspire their clients to<br />
put their money into Australia,, They say, " You've got a<br />
government there that isn't afriad to take steps to restrain<br />
inflation, to produce stability in the currency. And when<br />
somebody says to me stability means stagnation, all I want<br />
to say is that this is an utter abuse of language, I was<br />
thinking of it this afternoon when I went to the opening of<br />
this big building in the city, If somebody had said, " Oh,<br />
this building is no good because the foundations are stable,"<br />
everybody would have laughed. They would have said, " Well,<br />
that's today's funny story." It might have got into a gossip<br />
column, for all I know. ( Laughter)<br />
These are equally important a building in the city<br />
of Perth and the building of this nation, the building of the<br />
mansions in which we want our grandchildren to live,<br />
Stability and strength, In case somebody wants to tell<br />
you once more that your Government in the Commonwealth has<br />
confused stability with stagnation, I would like to remind<br />
you that in this very period in which we are accused of this<br />
negative, stagnant attitude towards public affairs, we have,<br />
in conjunction with State Governments, accepted a share of<br />
responsibility, and a very large share for probably the<br />
greatest developmental programme in the history of Australia,<br />
( Applause) Speaking in Perth, I wontt take you on a tour of<br />
the horizon to all the other States, though I very well<br />
could. I will just talk about your own, here. In this<br />
period of stagnancy, what has happened.? We have agreed,<br />
and put in hand, ana it is now being pursued with great<br />
vigour, a standard gauge railway line from Kalgoorlie to<br />
Kwianna; we have agreed upon the development, organised<br />
by your own Government, of a great iron and stool industry,<br />
We look around us and we see bauxite, alumina; we look<br />
further up, and we see the most remarkable developments of<br />
iron ore, with pert development, with roads in the Northe<br />
Look, Dave Brand could give you a much fuller account of it<br />
than I could, but he would be the first to say that my own<br />
stagnant Government has played along on these matters with<br />
immense vigour and the result is that whatever comes or goes,<br />
the State of West Australia is at the very beginning of its<br />
greatest period of development in its historyo ( Hear, hear)<br />
( Applause) o 0ooo . oo / 7 </p>
<p>I wonder if I might without wearying you tell you<br />
a little private recollection of mine, When I was first<br />
Prime Minister, which is beyond the memory, I hope, of some<br />
of you who are here tonight, one of my Ministers was Herbert<br />
Collett a West Australian Senator and a great man, a<br />
splendid person, and I was chatting with him one night and<br />
I said, " Herbert, were you born in the West?" He was then<br />
fairly venerable, about the same age as I am now. ( Laughter)<br />
This is a long time ago, I said, " Were you born in che West?"<br />
and he said, " No my family went there when I was about seven<br />
or eight." And I said " What was the population of the ! Jest<br />
then?" He said, ' 36,000 people."<br />
Somebody said this afternoon, no doubt with that<br />
truthfulness that characterises West Australians, tbat the<br />
population now is about three-quarters of a millioi. Think<br />
of it, At the very time that he and I were speaking, the<br />
population was over half a million from 36,000 to over<br />
half a million and this seemed to me to be the most phenomenal<br />
development that you could imagine in a community, I want to<br />
say to you, it's nothing to what is going to happen in the<br />
next fifteen or twenty years. You may say to me, " Well,<br />
fifteen or twenty years, old boy, you won't be here." Neither<br />
I will be, that's quite true, I am happy to say ( Laughter) but<br />
it is going to be true, it is going to be true, and I do hope<br />
that all Liberals throughout this period will keep on emphasising<br />
that it is because we want this kind of thing to be true<br />
that we believe that we serve the best interests of the people<br />
of Australia. The people who talk about stagnation in a period of<br />
the greatest fertility in development in Australian history<br />
are preferring a slogan to the truth and I beg of you to<br />
answer them,<br />
Now there is one other matter that I want to mention<br />
to you. If we are to have a large migration programme, if<br />
we are to build up our population, if we are to have the<br />
fullest employment of our resources, of men and materials,<br />
if we are to have the greatest outlook on the development of<br />
the resources of the nation, then there are one cr two other<br />
things that we must have, and one of them is a growing<br />
manufacture because, with all the good will in the world,<br />
any man on the land will agree that the rural industries are<br />
not going to atcract migrants. As they become more and<br />
more mechanised, as they become more and more improved<br />
scientifically in productivity, the chances are all against<br />
them being able to absorb thousands of new citizens. I<br />
understand that. That is true. Therefore, if we are to<br />
bring into Australia large numbers of imrmigrants we must<br />
look at the manufacturing industries and at the tertiary<br />
industries to help us to fulfil the condition of full employment.<br />
Now that is a very simple conception. It is true,<br />
we believe in it, We stand for ito But it contains onn<br />
great danger. We must guard against ito If we are going to<br />
develop our manufacturing industries as we must, and as we<br />
should, if we are going to encourage them as we must and we<br />
should, to export some of their products to the rest of the<br />
world, we must never lose sight of the fact that today and<br />
for many years to come, the primary industries of Australia<br />
provide the backbone of our export income and therefore<br />
provide a good deal of those imports upon which manufacturing<br />
in Australia will depend, ( Applause) 000o..../ 8 </p>
<p>8.<br />
Therefore, Sir, every time I think about this matter,<br />
every time I speak about this matter as a Liberal and a<br />
leader of the Liberal Party, I keep reminding myself and<br />
those who are good enough to listen to me, that whatever<br />
we do we must do a great deal to develop these other<br />
industries, vastly important for full employment, and<br />
therefore to population growth and therefore to national<br />
strength and national security, The argument is unanswerable.<br />
Whatever we do about that, we must remember that the costs<br />
of production in the rural industries are more important<br />
than perhaps they are in any others. Because if you have<br />
a local industry and its costs go up well, it has its<br />
local list of customers and if their wages go up they can<br />
pay the increased price. It's rather a sort of homely<br />
affair, But the woolgrower gets what the world will pay<br />
him. The wheatgrower, subject to certain limitations, will<br />
get what the world vill -ay him. The grower of meat also<br />
you can run the whole gamut of primary industry. The<br />
essential thing from their point of view is that they should<br />
not be costed out of their market.<br />
And how are we to achieve that? This is where the<br />
Liberal Party has a great task, a great task. How are we<br />
to achieve that? We are not going to achieve it by crying<br />
down manufacturing because I think without an increase in<br />
manufacture in Australia, steadily growing, year by year,<br />
our population will not grow year by year. We are not going<br />
to do it by fine words, we are not going to do it by taking<br />
the world by the throat and telling the world that it ought<br />
to pay more for what we grow. We have to do it by attacking<br />
the problem of rural costs, and in order to do that, we<br />
encounter not just some simple problem of subsidy but a<br />
basic problem of bringing to the service of the man on the<br />
land, whether he is a grazier, a sheep man, a cattle man<br />
or a wheatfarmer or a dairyfarmer or whatever it may be, the<br />
latest results of scientific researcho We must have more<br />
scientific research, we must build up the activities of<br />
people like C. S. I. R. O and so on and above all things, we<br />
must get a common understanding between Commonwealth and<br />
States that the results of research must go in the quickest<br />
possible time to the man on the land. They must travel<br />
from the laboratory to the farm much more rapidly than<br />
they ever have before. And if they do, we will find the<br />
most remarkable results.<br />
I am not one of those statistical fellows who come<br />
around with reams of figures because, although they are<br />
fascinating, I've often found that nobody listens to them,<br />
and therefore I am not imposing them on you. But I will<br />
safely say this, in the broad, that one of the great features<br />
of the last few years in Australia has been the increased<br />
productivity of rural industries, not arising from increased<br />
employment because, on the whole there may have been a<br />
fall in employment but increased productivity, increased<br />
efficiency. And here is a point of time at which governmonts<br />
and private enterprise can meet together.<br />
I still have a few friends and I like to see them<br />
who are on the land ( Laughter) who are sheep men or whatever<br />
it may be. I am always fascinated to find that at a time<br />
when our opponents like to represent the sheep man, for<br />
example, as a rather idle fellow who goes down to the<br />
Melbourne Cup you know and buys a bottle of indifferent<br />
champagne and all that kind of nonsense, I an fascinated<br />
to find that I never encounter one of then on his own<br />
property who isn't at some pains to tell me how much he has<br />
0o0e o / 9 </p>
<p>9.<br />
been able to build up the weight of fleece in his flocks,<br />
how delighted he is to know how he his been able to increase<br />
the carrying capacity of his land by the improvement of<br />
pastures these are men who believe in enterprise, They're<br />
men who know that while they don't mind earning some money;<br />
of course, who does they know that their own country in<br />
which they have a considerable stake will depend on The<br />
skill, the scientific effort that they put into the problems<br />
of production, Now, Si, this is not merely a matter for tLemo<br />
This is where we come in, Tonight, standing here I can<br />
see an old friend of mine the distinguished Minister for<br />
Agric-iu. tw. e in the State of Victoria,, He has been over<br />
here on a conference. He knows, I donst need to persuade<br />
him, and all his colleagues around Auscralia know, that this<br />
is one of the great proLlems to have more and more<br />
scientific efforto ( Between you and me, and I wouldn't like<br />
to have it quoted against me, I grudge all. this stuff vp in<br />
the air). I want more and more scientific effort in<br />
increasing the productivity of the land, the capacity of<br />
Australia to sustain a cost level by making it spread over<br />
a far greater area of production,,<br />
This is our great hope. This is the great tasko<br />
I dontthink our opponents have ever thought of ito To<br />
them, costs are nothing, There is nothing in costs to<br />
them that can't be made up by an extra tariff or by an<br />
extra subsidy or something, or an extra tax, But for<br />
Liberalism, which believes in Australia, for Liberalism<br />
which knows that it is on the productivity of our o. n<br />
country and our capacity to sell what we produce to the<br />
rest of the world that tie whole of our economic future<br />
depends, this is a different problemo Keep down the<br />
costs of rural industries, increase the efficiency,<br />
increase extension services, do all these things, so that<br />
we may extend our secondary industries increase our<br />
population and come, in twenty years' time, to a state<br />
of affairs in which somebody will look around and say,<br />
" This is wonderful, the population of this country is<br />
twenty odd million, the position in this country is that<br />
we still maintain our position as remarkable exporters to<br />
the rest of the world, we still retain our position of<br />
being a country in which the man on the land can survive<br />
and grow and prosper and maintain our position as being,<br />
perhaps, the greatest manufacturing and export manufacturing<br />
country in the Southern Hemisphere" This is a good dream,<br />
isn't it? And it is not merely a dream, it can be made to<br />
come true, It can be made to come true if we, as Liberals,<br />
do not allow ourselves to be beguiled by silly people who<br />
tell us that Liberalism has Pecome stagnant, that it's all<br />
over, that it is about time to give the other boys a go,<br />
These pseudo-Liberals who whistle in your ear some of them<br />
from very well-appointed offices, forget about them. You<br />
don't suppose do you, for a moment, that we would be<br />
exercising such miserable talents as we have in the service<br />
of this country as Liberals unless we had something to<br />
believe in? Not to make too fine a point of it, I have<br />
been Prime Minister, in my second manifestation now, for<br />
twelve and a half years, You don't suppose, do you that<br />
I had some fascinated interest in creating a record? I<br />
would like, very much, to have a little private life, Most<br />
of you have I have none. But I am here, I hope you're<br />
here, because I believe in things, on behalf of my country<br />
and am determined to do every last thing that I have in<br />
me to achieve themo </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
