<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3628</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL WOMEN&#039;S YEAR GRANTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003628.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 456<br />
February, 1975<br />
INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S YEAR GRANTS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today<br />
grants and assistance totalling $ 305,300.00 for special<br />
activities during, International Women's Year. This is the<br />
second of a series of grants and represents a total commitment<br />
so far of-over a half a million dollars ($ 538,800.00).<br />
He stated that he had approved the grants on the<br />
advice of the Australian National Advisory Committee for<br />
International Women's Year. This Committee which was established<br />
in September 1974, has the general responsibility for<br />
developing themes and programmes for the Year which will be<br />
of benefit to all women in Australia.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that the grants were part of an<br />
overall program for International Women's Year and reflect the<br />
Government's determination to make the Year one of substantial<br />
progress for women in Australia. The Prime Minister said that<br />
he had been pleased with the response to the Year of both the<br />
Premiers of South Australia and Victoria and also of many 11<br />
local government organisations.<br />
As well as involving the community and individuals<br />
in activities for the Year the Government had embarked on an<br />
extensive program throughout all. Australian Government Departments<br />
which aimed at reassessing their existing activities in<br />
light of the aims of-the Year.<br />
As part of this program the Australian Post Office<br />
would be issuing a stamp to mark International Women's Day on<br />
March 8, a National Conference on Women and Health would be<br />
held in Brisbane in August, a special edition of Education News<br />
with special emphasis on women would be prepared, and an<br />
International Seminar on Women as Victims in Crime will be<br />
held in Canberra in April. Australia w-7ould also host a United<br />
Nations Inter-regional Seminar on Women, the Arts and the Media<br />
the communication of attitudes. e *. 2<br />
11,1,( L
</p><p>The Prime Minister said that many other<br />
submissions were presently under consideration by the<br />
National Advisory Committee and by various Government<br />
Departments. He expected to be able to announce further q~<br />
grants-shortly.<br />
NOTE FOR PRESS<br />
A detailed description of projects available from the<br />
Prime Minister's Press Office. Contact officers for<br />
further information: Shirley Castley 49 6489, John<br />
Gavin 47 0839. </p>
<p>Attachment to 456<br />
INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S YEAR<br />
PROJECTS FUNDED<br />
Submissions EDUCATION SSt. Michael's Collegiate School ( Tas.)<br />
SNSW Teachers' Federation<br />
Carole Ferrier, University of Queensland<br />
SSpecial edition of " Education News"<br />
SUniversity of Adelaide, Department of<br />
Adult Education 874<br />
12,000 1,682<br />
up to 6,160<br />
3,250<br />
CREATIVITY Adele Cohen Readings ( W 4,775<br />
The Women's Film Festival 75 ( N. S. W.) guarantee35,000<br />
Royal South Australian Society of Arts Inc. 3,850<br />
Albury Symphony Orchestra ( Vic.) 300<br />
Ewing Gallery.( Vic.) 6,000<br />
SAdelaide Festival Centre Trust 1,000<br />
North Shore Symphony Orchestra 500<br />
HEALTH AND WELFARE<br />
Conference on women's health ( Qld) 22,500<br />
The Wayside Chapel, Kings Cross 3,000<br />
SN. S. W. Council for the Ageing 5,500<br />
t I . IA </p>
<p>Viole. nce<br />
* The WcLmoC-n ' cIs cc,* saV i ct0 ri r<br />
Cout-Wn1.22L Is assCzc'. aln, r~<br />
tano-e n jg_:. C Gro ( t7c<br />
* pannln t7-ithoumlt Partners ( Asst )<br />
WORT, Cotrefo'r tlrban Pcscrnrch and Action ( Vic.) C<br />
Women Lawyor: s Association<br />
tational Council. Of Wromen, Towsvil ( 03Ac)<br />
* As-ral. ian Lonn). t'evin I<br />
W* OAclian roPoso', r~ a: r<br />
P-nPh, v-n Co1llege of Advancec1 Edca-lcotin ( Vic)<br />
n'C-na Woalomn's Day oite<br />
uOnonan Asoco'ation' of tUniversi. ty t-c-meri<br />
C x? r inq~ n. AgnJnT st lIO al Pp 0( r sc etnYt1 .) I<br />
* The Cotntxv Wom." enls Association Vi~ co'Ia:'' I-<br />
* Seventecent'h M'ational Confa,-ro2nce%<br />
* The National. Council of IWomen o. i~ oi<br />
joyce St-evens<br />
* National Council -of Wammen of Lanncoton ( Tas)<br />
ancl 1I! . Itc'n ( VICO~<br />
* The Co~ T': cz-. cn s Assnciat!. on 0* f N' 09~ t1.<br />
77-7.. 7. tS .0,2160 ' 4,000 000<br />
6,000 C000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
