<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6590</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER ON &#039;SUNDAY&#039;, 17 FEBRUARY 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006590.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSTRAL
PRIME MAINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER ON " SUNDAY" 17 February 1985<br />
E. O. E. -PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: On the MX missile decision, the decision to help the<br />
Americans test it, was that the wrong decision and was it a<br />
decision taken the wrong way.<br />
PM: Let me say this it was a decision taken in good faith for<br />
what appeared to myself and Mr Hayden and the then Minister for<br />
Defence, Mr Scholes, for good reason. And then in respect of the<br />
second part of your question was it taken in the wrong way we<br />
have a Security Committee arrangement which must obviously operate<br />
in certain sensitive areas. It was quite clear that not all<br />
decisions in this sort of area are capable of being taken through<br />
the full Committee and Cabinet processes. Now coming up to the<br />
present time, when we were confronted with a situation that the<br />
reaction to that decision, not merely within my Party or on the<br />
Left of my Party, it was an across spectrum reaction,-and as far<br />
as I can ascertain a pretty broad reaction in the community, then<br />
I had to make the judgement as to whether two continuing<br />
fundamental issues of importance to Australia were jeopardised.<br />
One, is the continuing alliance relationship with the United<br />
States and what goes with that that's the joint hosting of<br />
facilities and the availability of ports for their visits on the<br />
one hand, and on the other hand the integrity, the capacfty, of my<br />
Government to pursue its policies in the disarmament field. I was<br />
not going to have either of those two things prejudiced. And it<br />
seems as though they would have been, so we made the decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: So there was a misjudgement initially?<br />
PM: Well the judgement at the time it was made, as I say, seemed<br />
to the Ministers concerned, including myself, to be on balance the<br />
appropriate one. In the circumstances that emerged there were<br />
over-riding considerations of more importance because the<br />
continuing importance of the alliance relationship with the United<br />
States and what it entailed in regard to the bases, which are<br />
important for the strategic deterrence program and verification,<br />
it was important that that continuing situation not be prejudiced.<br />
The MX test was a one-off passing thing. That was a continuing<br />
matter of importance. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke on Friday a seniorc State Department official<br />
was reported as saying that Australia was in danger of catching<br />
nuclear allergy, or the anti-nuclear allergy, and that the antinuclear<br />
movement could make you less secure in your pro-American<br />
stance. Do you think his fear is justified?<br />
PM: No. One of the problems in this whole area is statements<br />
being made by certain officials, certain people in positions of<br />
low authority, they like to speak with purported authority. And<br />
I'm not diverted by those things. I've made it quite clear, and<br />
most importantly on my return the Cabinet unanimously endorsed my<br />
position, that the United States/ Australian alliance remains<br />
central and unshaken. Now that's understood by me, it's<br />
understood and accepted by my Cabinet and I guess not<br />
unimportantly it's understood and accepted and welcomed by the<br />
President and the administration of the United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you believe this was an unauthorised statement.<br />
Do you have some information to that effect.<br />
PM: When you have these statements by State officials, State<br />
Department officials or Defence Department officials, I mean they<br />
do it because they want to express a personal attitude often. You<br />
know from your appearances in the United States, your reading of<br />
United States material, that there are differences and strong<br />
differences of opinion not only between Departments but within<br />
Departments. So because one person in one Department says<br />
something you're not entitled to draw any conclusion about that as<br />
an official United States position.<br />
JOURNALIST: One alliance that concerns us that is badly shaken is<br />
that between New Zealand and the United States, clearly, Now if<br />
as seems likely the United States cuts off high level military<br />
intelligence to New Zealand what position does that put us in. Do<br />
we have to quarantine the intelligence we get from America and not<br />
make it available to New Zealand or do we cut New Zealand off as<br />
well. PM: Let me make one preliminary comment and then go to your<br />
specific question. You say that the relationship between New<br />
Zealand and the United States is badly damaged. But I think it's<br />
proper, Robert, to have this position clear. It was put to me by<br />
both President Reagan and by Secretary of State, George Shultz,<br />
that they still regard New Zealand as a friend. And it's<br />
important to say that. They are upset, naturally, by the decision<br />
in regard to the non-accessibility of ports to their ships. But I<br />
believe that the United States is not going to pursue a policy of<br />
massive retribution in respect of the military arrangements<br />
between them. Obviously changes have taken place and in a sense<br />
will continue to take place. But they are not going to fracture<br />
the relationship. And, indeed, it's our decision of the United<br />
States and Australia they we won't take any steps to abrogate<br />
the Treaty, to remove the Treaty. So that the Treaty will remain<br />
there in place. The United States and* Australia will maintain </p>
<p>PM cont : their full relationships in the hope that there can be<br />
a resumption at some subsequent stage of the full tni-lateral<br />
relationship. Now going to your specific question, Robert, about<br />
intelligence. This was discussed by me with the United States.<br />
They have not made a decision as to what they intend to do in the<br />
sharing of intelligence information. Because you'll appreciate,<br />
there's a two-way flow. It's not simply intelligence provided by<br />
United States sources, but New Zealand has a capacity for<br />
collecting information also. Now I'm simply saying that there has<br />
been no decision made. That is a decision for the United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: But would you hope to see a continuation of the<br />
intelligence flow?<br />
PM: Between<br />
JOURNALIST: The U. S. and New Zealand.<br />
PM: Well I think it's not right for me to say that, that's<br />
something really for the United States and New Zealand. Overall I<br />
certainly want to see the highest level of the relationship<br />
maintained if possible in these circumstance between the United<br />
States and New Zealand. So at this stage we don't have to make a<br />
decision as to a residual decision by Australia in regard ', to<br />
information received from the United States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you feel that Mr Lange, by his action, has sold<br />
out his country's interests in rupturing ANZUS in the way he has.<br />
PM: I wouldn't make such a statement as that. I have, from the<br />
very beginning, despite misinterpretation and some deliberate<br />
misinterpretation of my letter of 10 January, I have at.. no stage<br />
sought to intrude into the internal affairs of New Zealand. Let<br />
me make it clear, and it's important that Australians understand<br />
this, there is a longstanding, deep, firm relationship between<br />
Australia and New Zealand. And that has not been fractured, as<br />
indeed President Reagan has gone out of his way to say that they<br />
still regard New Zealand as a friend. What is important is that<br />
New Zealand and Australia retain their relationship in the<br />
military co-operation field, because we live and have<br />
responsibility in an area of the world which has some tendency to<br />
increase instability we know the developments in New Caledonia.<br />
Now it is obviously good sense in those circumstances without on<br />
my part wanting to overstate developments and potential<br />
developments in New Caledonia but it makes good sense that<br />
Australia and New Zealand maintain our military co-operation. We<br />
will. ( COMMERCIAL BREAK)<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, turning to what is coming up this week,<br />
Cabinet meets on Tuesday and the Indians are restless. How do you<br />
respond to the proposal that will go to the Caucus meeting that<br />
Caucus views should be included in Cabinet submissions and </p>
<p>JOURNALIST cont wouldn't that be a breach of the rule of<br />
Cabinet government?<br />
PM: The Kirribilli Committee has been meeting for some time. I<br />
have indicated it has my full support to examine ways in which<br />
there can be an improvement in liaison between the members of the<br />
Caucus, Ministers and Cabinet. All I have expressed a firm view<br />
about and against, if you like, is one suggestion that was made<br />
about chairmen of Caucus committees sitting in on Cabinet<br />
considerations or Cabinet committee considerations. That is not<br />
on but I am quite open really, Michelle, about any other methods.<br />
This is not something as a reaction to recent events. I have been<br />
conscious of the concern that backbench members of Parliament must<br />
have. It must be very frustrating and anything that is going to<br />
improve the communication and the flow-through and the interchange<br />
of ideas, I am not only relaxed about. I am in favour of it.<br />
JOURNALIST: But you are balancing two matters here, aren't you.<br />
Your reputation you have had unprecedented support in the<br />
business community for a Labor Prime Minister and that has been<br />
based to a large extent on the impression that you are in command,<br />
that unlike Mr Whitlam, you have command of Caucus, and especially<br />
of the Left Wing. Yet now you are having to accommodate more to<br />
Caucus opinion and I think that that is going to diminish-, your<br />
reputation with the business community.<br />
PM: You are setting up alternatives that are not real<br />
alternatives. I don't think it is right to talk about command. I<br />
mean, right from day one I just can't say, here we are, here is a<br />
position. I have got no-one to think about. I have never<br />
operated like that. Never. Previously before I was in the<br />
Parliament that is not my style. I talk and discuss... But I<br />
think there has been a perception on the part of the business<br />
community a correct perception that the principles, the<br />
policies, which I and Mr Keating originally took the initiative<br />
in, if you like, have been accepted. That is the correct<br />
perception. Any fight that Mr Keating and I had at the beginning<br />
about getting a line ' adopted is over. That has been adopted. No<br />
government, I suggest, in post-war Australian history which has<br />
now imposed upon itself a more stringent apparatus and framework<br />
for decision-making in regard to the economy, than we have. And<br />
that has been accepted by the Caucus and by the Cabinet. Now to<br />
the extent that we are now talking about ways in which there may<br />
be better flows through from Caucus. I don't see the business<br />
community as being concerned about that. They know that the<br />
framework which has produced record economic growth, record job<br />
creation, a halving of the inflation rate, a 30% increase in<br />
housing commencements, a reduction in interest rates, an admired<br />
economy they know that those policies are in place and will<br />
continue and the fact that we are going to be having a look at<br />
more discussion processes is of no concern to them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well just on that, the thing that they would want to<br />
see is a re-affirmation of the trilogy the promise not to </p>
<p>JOURNALIST cont increase the burden of debt spending and<br />
taxation.<br />
PM: Well if I can take the Sabbath as an occasion for reaffirmation<br />
of the trilogy I am more than prepared to do so. I<br />
hereby re-affirm the trilogy on Sunday 17th, is it, of February.<br />
JOURNALIST: And on the Sunday program.<br />
PM: And on the Sunday program. What could be more appropriate.<br />
But let me not joke. That is important and the business community<br />
knows, and the Australian people know, that there will be no<br />
increase in the deficit either as a proportion of GDP, and in fact<br />
there will be a reduction in monetary terms. Secondly, that<br />
there will be no increase in tax as a proportion of GDP. And<br />
importantly, the third and necessarily consequential element in<br />
the trilogy, there will be no increase in the levels of government<br />
expenditure beyond the rate of economic growth. Now those are<br />
fundamental and important and re-affirmed.<br />
JOURNALIST: But that is going to require a tough attitude on<br />
spending, isn't it. It is going to be a tougher Budget for you<br />
this Budget than last Budget.<br />
PM: Yes, but when you say tough, let's get the economic and<br />
political realities right. What does toughness mean if what you<br />
are doing is going to produce a better Australia for all<br />
Australians in the immediate and in the longer term, that you're<br />
going to create the foundations of solid, strong non-inflationary<br />
growth, what's toughness about that. It is adopting sensible<br />
measures now to ensure that all the people of Australia are going<br />
to be better off. That's sensible.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's tough in the sense that you'll have to overrule<br />
Ministers who want to spend money or not impose things like<br />
universal<br />
PM: The important thing is that they, and the Caucus, have<br />
accepted this necess ary discipline. Now in the process itL is true<br />
that some things that some Ministers and that I would like in a<br />
world where you had no constraints of reality well, it can't be<br />
done. But our responsibility which we have accepted more<br />
responsibly and more effectively than any other government in<br />
post-war history is that we recognise the things that have to be<br />
done. We have done them and we have produced the results. We<br />
will continue to do it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, can I turn to another very pressing<br />
problem that is confronting the Government at the moment. An<br />
important part of your public service is on strike, which is<br />
making things difficult for economic management and very centrally<br />
is being seen as a threat to the Accord. How seriously do you<br />
take that particular threat? And what sort of other pressures do<br />
you see on the Accord in the next twelve months? </p>
<p>PM: I am not overwhelmed by the current dispute in the public<br />
service. I am not pleased by it, but I have total confidence in<br />
my Minister, Ralph Willis, who has reported to the Cabinet and the<br />
Cabinet is giving him support. And the support is for this<br />
position. And let everyone understand it. When we went before<br />
the Commission when the anomalies case was there we indicated that<br />
an increase of the order of 2% would be justified. That remains<br />
our position. We are prepared to help to facilitate a return for<br />
the Commission for a hearing of that claim, but we would be<br />
supporting no more than that and our support for the case being<br />
re-opened would be on two conditions that all bans would be<br />
lifted, and that there be an undertaking to abide by the decision<br />
of the Commission. Now that is clear and non-negotiable.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well what do you say to the union leaders. Are they<br />
unable to understand the importance of the Accord to the economic<br />
recovery?<br />
PM: Well, they believe that within the principles of the Accord<br />
anjd the wage fixing principles at the anomalies provision, as they<br />
argue it, justify more than we put. Now they are entitled to<br />
believe that and try and argue it, but as far as we are concerned<br />
there are not going to be increases of any significance outside<br />
the Commission and outside the principles. And we are not-going<br />
to bend on this. This is not a matter of toughness or being mean<br />
in regard to our own employees. The very centrepiece of the<br />
outstanding success of the Australian economic performance has<br />
been adherance to the principles of the Accord. We have got a<br />
situation now where that has brought manifest improvements. These<br />
people in the public service should understand, as should aJll<br />
people in employment, that their major responsibility is to assist<br />
to create conditions which are going to create more jobs for more<br />
people. And all of us who are in the fortunate position of having<br />
employment, and secure employment particularly no-one has got<br />
more secure employment thant the public servants they have got<br />
to understand that the greater good of the greater number is what<br />
is important. And that is what my Government is going to insist<br />
upon.<br />
JOURNALIST: On another matter connected with the Accord, what is<br />
your present position on the productivity claim. Last year you<br />
suggested that maybe that should be a1elayed.<br />
PM: No, to be precise, Michelle, what we said and this is all<br />
that we said is that we would hold our position, our<br />
consideration of our position until we got into 1985 at the time<br />
that the claim was being developed and lodged-to finally<br />
formulate our position. Now my answer to your question is mne<br />
line with the previous answer I have just given. That we will be<br />
discussing the matter with the ACTU and we will be discussing it<br />
with the employers too. And by the time we go to the Commission<br />
it will be putting a position which we believe is most consistent<br />
with the maintenance of conditions most likely to facilitate<br />
strong non-inflationary growth. Now that may very well be a </p>
<p>PM cont position of not supporting any increase in money wage<br />
terms, but there may be some accommodation, sensible<br />
accommodation, in the area of superannuation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does it depend on how the unions behave in matters<br />
like the public service strike?<br />
PM: No, let me make it clear that in this national wage case<br />
* that is coming up now as distinct from the productivity case later<br />
on, I don't support and the Government won't support, a<br />
proposition of punishing everyone else because of the attitude of<br />
the public servants. I mean, the logical thing would be that if<br />
the public servants have not come back into the mainstream and are<br />
still conducting their dispute, well they could not expect to get<br />
the flow on from the national wage case.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, another issue that we must question<br />
you about, although I know that there is some sensitivity on what<br />
you can say, is the chronic weakness of the Australian dollar<br />
which has been, for the past week or so in condition that some<br />
people in the market describe as free fall. Now there is a very<br />
serious trade deficit opening up which now seems to be bigger than<br />
we thought. Isn't it time for the Government to reconsider its<br />
hands off policy and to consider supporting the Australiag dollar<br />
in the markets?<br />
PM: I appreciate the way in which you opened your question,<br />
Robert. It is difficult and improper for a Prime Minister to make<br />
comments in an area which could affect the level and value of ourcurrency.<br />
So within those constraints, which I am glad you<br />
recognise, let me say these things which I think are relevant.<br />
There has been, as you say, a significant fall. It is ot<br />
something that has got to be looked at as all bad. Indeed, as you<br />
appreciate, there are many advantageous features of a fall in the<br />
value of our dollar vis a vis the United States dollar in<br />
particular and some of our other trading partners to a lesser<br />
extent. And that means that it is better for our exporters and it<br />
makes the position of our own import competing industries slightly<br />
better. So don't let's look at it as all negative. It is<br />
certainly not. The second point I make is this that it does<br />
seem to reflect some transient features. No-one can weight them,<br />
but certainly the non-collection of very substantial reve~ nues, as<br />
a result of the public service dispute has had a lot of money<br />
slopping around in the market. That has had some sort of an<br />
impact. And I would have to say that perhaps the events of the<br />
last week when there was that misunderstanding, if you like, and I<br />
think over-dramatisation of what was happening internationally as<br />
far as Australia was concerned may'have had some passing adverse<br />
impact. My own view, Robert, is that the fall that has taken<br />
place will not continue substantially. There will be a settling<br />
down and in those circumstances the Government believes that the<br />
decision which it took to free up the exchange rate and which has<br />
had manifest benefits for Australia is not something which we<br />
should be precipitately intervening in so that people would start </p>
<p>to have doubts about our adherance to that position. I don't want<br />
to say more at this stage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Government event of perhaps most<br />
interest to the public this year is the July tax summit. Mr<br />
Keating in the last week or so has given notice that he will go<br />
out into the party forums and argue the case very strongly for a<br />
shift towards greater reliance on indirect tax. Do you feel as<br />
strongly as he does about that?<br />
PM: Yes I do. And it is very interesting, Michelle, to see the<br />
shift that is taking place. I notice I mean a lot of my Caucus<br />
colleagues are not totally reluctant to express their view<br />
publicly I notice that Dr Theophanous of the left is reported as<br />
saying he understands the need for it. It is also interesting to<br />
see a number of other quarters where there was opposition that<br />
there is an acceptance of it. Look, the position is very simple<br />
and straightforward. We have got in this country a position where<br />
our marginal tax rates are too high and they are biting in too<br />
early. They are disincentives and people rightly feel that they<br />
have got too high a burden of direct personal tax. So for obvious<br />
reasons of personal hardships, incentives, economic efficiency, we<br />
have got to bring those rates down and bring them down<br />
substantially. Now, everyone has agreed on that. Everyone can<br />
nod their head and say, very wise, Mr Hawke, very proper, very<br />
accurate, hear hear. We have got to understand then, if we want<br />
basically as a community to have government providing the same<br />
level of services in defen'ce, in education, in health, in roads,<br />
in all those services which must necessarily be provided for the<br />
community by the community as a whole via governmenL, then if we<br />
are not going to have the income via personal tax to do that, and<br />
there is a substantial cut in revenue, then if people want the<br />
same level of services basically then there has got to be an<br />
alternative. Now it seems to us that there, therefore, has to be<br />
a substantial increase in indirect taxation. The third point I<br />
make is that it is true that relatively speaking recourse to<br />
indirect tax as compared to direct tax will be regressive. It<br />
will tend to hurt those on the lower income levels more. So we<br />
must, if we do these things, Robert, we must in fact have<br />
compensating mechanisms to ensure that we offset that impact.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, thanks for that answer. We have<br />
time only for one last question. What have you had to say to<br />
Susan Ryan?<br />
PM: I said, good-day, Susan. I don't believe that it is<br />
appropriate that I should say on public programs like this what<br />
passes between myself and my Ministers. And I don't intend to do<br />
it. Let me say this, however, that Susan was one of those who, in<br />
the Cabinet on Tuesday unanimously supported my report which, as<br />
you know, referred to the centrality of the maintenance of the<br />
Australian-American alliance and the ANZUS relationship. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: So everything is smooth there?<br />
PM: obviously must be.<br />
JOURNALIST: morning. Prime Minister, thanks very much for joining us this<br />
PM: It has been my pleasure Robert and Michelle. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
