<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5826</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF CONNELLAN AIRPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005826.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Af; DELI___ t_<br />
JJ) AIUSTRALIA<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 6 JUNE 1982<br />
OPENING OF CONNELLAN AIRPORT<br />
It really is I think a very great occasion and there could not<br />
be a more f itting way to honour somebody who has done a great<br />
deal for the Northern Territory and a great deal for Australia<br />
over most of his lifetime. Eddie Connellan is probably<br />
best known obviously for his contribution to aviation in the<br />
Northern Territory. Maybe not so many people know that he<br />
has also been in the forefront of pastoral activities,<br />
water conservation and disease control in:-the Territory, always<br />
looking to doing things better than they were done in the past,<br />
and contributing not only to his own operation, to the broader<br />
knowledge of how to do things in this part of the world.<br />
Tamie and I are delighted that it has been possible to be<br />
here and to come here on this occasion and particularly so<br />
because the Airport has been named in a way that honours the<br />
work that Eddie Connellan has done. through the decades.<br />
It was the relationship between Eddie Connellan and another<br />
great Australian going back to the pre-war years that as I<br />
understand itILle ad to it all. I understand that John McEwan<br />
in 1938 or 1939 said to Eddie on one occasion why don't you<br />
establish an airline and provide some services to people that might<br />
otherwise have them. If my researchers are correct,<br />
that is where a large part of it began. Air services were<br />
established, airports developed, places for airfields picked<br />
out and at the peak the service went to about 130 or more<br />
locations right around the Northern Territory.<br />
It is worth roting that in the earlier years the mail carried<br />
was a much larger part, much heavier in weight than freight.<br />
I was trying to point out that the need for communications<br />
between people was obviously very great because the weight of<br />
mail carried in the early days was greater than the freight<br />
carried. That obviously tells its own story and the need<br />
for communications between people who lived in the QMerritory<br />
and who had their links and their families maybe outside<br />
the Territory. o. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
I think again you would all know that now we are getting to the<br />
stage where we are seeking to establish a communication system<br />
where all people in Australia will have the same kind of<br />
communication as those who live in Melbourne or Sydney and<br />
when the new satellite is established we believe that that<br />
will be so. That is the mark 6f time and the changes in<br />
technology that make that kind of thing possible. The<br />
original serviLces provided by Eddie Connellan and his team<br />
provided something that was much needed in many remote parts<br />
of the Northern Territory.<br />
This cairn behind me is I understand it, the propellor from<br />
the first de Havilland toilfly to Ayers Rock. That a gain<br />
has its own story to tell in terms of aviation and in terms<br />
of the history of the Northern Territory.<br />
Paul Everinghamn with the kind of vision that he has brought to<br />
the Government of the Northern Territory since independence<br />
is obviously banking on a growth in tourism. He has been<br />
prepared to back his belief with dollars and the Northern<br />
Territory Government is spending large sums in helping to<br />
promote tourism and this I~ s obviously a large part of it<br />
right here and the Yulara Village that you are going to<br />
be visiting a little later on this morning. The number<br />
of people coming to the Territory, the dollars they are<br />
spending-is growing as each year passes. A large part of<br />
them come fromr overseas and with the many unique features<br />
of the Northern Territory in Ayers Rock, the Olgas, Kakadu<br />
National Park, there are sites of great and enormous value<br />
to all Territorians and indeed to people wherever they may<br />
be. It will be one of the vital and growing industries<br />
in the Northern Territory, I have not the slightest doubt<br />
at all.<br />
In passing, I think it is worth making the point that the kind<br />
of adavances that have occurred in the Territory over the<br />
last four years at the next election I am going to try<br />
and get Paul to give me a plug too just would not have come<br />
if an administration had remained centred on Canberra. You<br />
need people with a faith and belief in their own part of the<br />
world,-prepared to go out and back that with their time and<br />
with energy and with their vision. That is very much<br />
what has happened. You have only got to look i at the changes<br />
around Alice Springs, the changes across the Territory since<br />
independence, since self-government to know that there.* is., a<br />
new life, a new hope and a new faith compared to the days,<br />
when however well they did it, Ministers and public servants<br />
from Canberra seemed to determine everything that happened<br />
in the Territory.<br />
If the Federal Government has done anything for the Northern<br />
Territory, the most important thing it has done, has been<br />
to say well you look after your own affairs, ' we will work in<br />
partnership and do what we can to help, but we believe you can </p>
<p>-3-<br />
do much better because it is your futures that you are governingi,<br />
your futures that you are determining. We believe that you<br />
can do much better than we ever could. In a sense the<br />
unleashing of the talents and the initiative of the Territorians<br />
in terms of their own government has been an enormous advance<br />
for the Territory.<br />
Eddie I would like to thank you for everything that you have<br />
done for aviation in the Northern Territory. It has been<br />
an enormous contribution and indelibly written in the<br />
history of the Territory and the histgry of aviation in<br />
Austi~ alia. There are some parts of that history that might<br />
not be all that is in the records of the Department of Civil<br />
Aviation. I have here an authentic minute which was signed<br />
on 4 December 1957 by Shane Paltridge and Don Anderson and<br />
one or two others. Some parts of it said well I have never<br />
tried to put a swifty over the Department of Civil Aviation<br />
and Eddie has signed it, that's right at the bottom and<br />
witnessed by a number of people. I guess it is true. The<br />
word try is the word that was wrong because whatever Eddie<br />
did, he did not just try to do, he succeeded in doing and<br />
I think he was probably ahead of the Departmen't of Civil<br />
Aviation at every step of the way. He might never have<br />
tried, but that has got an implication of failure and Eddie<br />
never failed.<br />
There was anc-ther minute involving the late George Taylor<br />
who many people here would remember, with his association<br />
with Eddie and whatever and there was a meeting discussing<br />
Connellan Airways and what was going to happen in the<br />
future. George Taylor thought he would get it off to<br />
a bright start by saying, I hope those who don't like me<br />
using the language, will forgive me, but this is in the<br />
record so I have got to be accurate, aren't you the fat<br />
little bugger I scrubbed at Pearce a fews years ago?<br />
That happened. to be Shane Paltridge who was failed 15 years<br />
before by George Taylor of Pearce Elementary Flying<br />
School. How Shane Paltridge ever wanted to do anything<br />
for Connella. Airways after that, I just don't know. That<br />
might be just one more area where Eddie stayed one or<br />
two steps ahetad of the ministers and the departments and<br />
no matter howr hard the ministers and departments, tried, ; I am surce<br />
they were never able to catch up.<br />
As a result cof it all, and as a small part of the total<br />
fabric, there is this great airport, great terminal building<br />
which is going to stand as a permanent and fitting reminder<br />
of the work that Eddie Connellan has done for the Northern<br />
Territory. I have very grreat pleasure indeed in declaring Connellan Airport<br />
of ficially open.<br />
I am sorry I forgot to say something that I should have.<br />
Some time ago, always looking to the future and always looking<br />
to the need to keep adequate services. to the remoter areas that.<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
could not necessarily afford to do so by themselves. Eddie<br />
Connellan approached the Federal Govnernment to see if we<br />
would give tax deductibility to a special airways trust that<br />
would help to provide and support services to some of the<br />
remoter parts of the Territory which might not otherwise<br />
be able to sustain services under normal commercial conditions.<br />
We have provided tax deductibility for that trust. I don't<br />
know if Eddie has got somebody around here with a receipt.<br />
book, but donations are tax deductible. I believe again<br />
it shows the kind of concern that Eddie has for providing<br />
services to p1eople in the Northern T4rritory and I am glad<br />
that the Federal Government has been able to co-operate.<br />
This is a very unique arrangement. I don't think any other<br />
arrangement of the same kind has been given the privilege of<br />
tax deductibility and if it wasn't for the persuasive powers<br />
of Eddie Connellan and of his reputation, I am quite sure<br />
it would nothave succeeded. oOo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
