<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8349</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE HONOURABLE R J L HAWKE AC MP PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA  AT A BANQUET IN HIS HONOUR IN HARARE 23 OCTOBER 1991 - BRISBANE</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008349.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVU EMBAGOE .1 4N. Lf<br />
SPEECH BYt THE HONOURABLE R J L HAWKE AC MP<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA<br />
AT A BANIQUE IN HIS HONOUR IN HARARE,<br />
23 OCTOBER 1991-ZIMBABWE<br />
Your Excellency President Robert Mugabe<br />
The First Lady Amal. MIugabe<br />
Honourable Vice-President,<br />
Honourable Ministers,<br />
Your Excellencies,<br />
Your Worship the Metyor of Harare,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemon,<br />
Yesterday nearly all Commonwealth Heads of Government were<br />
still here in Harare for one of the most successful and<br />
constructive meetings of the Commonwealth I have attended.<br />
The success of thits CHOGM is due in no small part to the<br />
wonderful hospitality extended by you Mr President, and the<br />
Government and people of Zimbabwe. That is the public side of<br />
CHOGH. But may I also say that success is also dependent on what<br />
happens in the privacy of the Executive sessions and here<br />
your expert chairmanship did much to create the conditions<br />
where a very diverne group or Heads of Government could work<br />
constructively and harmoniously together.<br />
It says something, Hr President, of your capacity for work<br />
that, rather than t: aking it easy atter the massive<br />
responsibilities 01! hosting CHOGN, you invited me to undertake<br />
a separate bilateral visit.<br />
I believe our time together also says something for the<br />
particular relationship that has developed between Australia<br />
and Zimbabwe since 1980 and of the seeds of that relationship<br />
during your strugg] Le for independence.<br />
On a personal note, may I say, Robert and Sally, how much<br />
Hazel and I have enjoyed our time in Zimbabwe, especially the<br />
many private moments in which you have shared with us some of<br />
the unique experiences of your lives, We now appreciate a<br />
little better what the long years of strugq14 for the<br />
independence of Zimbabwe have meant to you. 2499 </p>
<p>2.<br />
Mr President<br />
Our two nations may be at opposite ends of the A-to-Z alphabet<br />
of the Commonwealth, but we also have much in common, much<br />
that we are working for together in the forums of the world,<br />
including the Commonwealth.<br />
Some parts of Zimbabwe even look like Australia.<br />
I have been struck by the success our eucalyptus trees have<br />
found here in Zimbabwe, with some 200 species of Australian<br />
gum-t roes and wattles flourishing here under the Seeds of<br />
Australia project.<br />
Travelling around the cattle country of Zimbabwe, the<br />
extensive, eucalypt plantings remind me of many parts of our<br />
cattle country in Northern Australia.<br />
This is a reminder that we are both countries of the Southern<br />
Hemisphere, sharing the same tropical latitudes and climate,<br />
and sharing some of the same industries mining, agriculture,<br />
and tourism.<br />
Like Zimbabwe, Australia has great natural wonders and an<br />
abundance of unusual wildlife that in our case, millions of<br />
people will travel thousands of kilometre. to see. we have an<br />
economic interest, as well as a national duty to take<br />
seriously the environmental consequences of this increasingly<br />
vital industry.<br />
Mr President<br />
Australia was privileged to have played a part in Zimbabwe's<br />
triumphant emergence to nationhood, through that crucial<br />
meet~ ing of the Commonwealth Heads of Government in Lusaka just<br />
twelve years ago. Australian troops and electoral observers<br />
wera here under Commonwealth auspices in the vital preelection<br />
period in 1980.<br />
It is only twelve years since the people of Zimbabwe were<br />
engaged in a bitter but successful struggle for freedom and<br />
equality in the land you have lived in for mare than a<br />
thousand years.<br />
It is just over eleven years since you achieved independence.<br />
That is not a long time in which to reconstruct a country.<br />
It is a remarkable tribute to the atmosphere of unity and<br />
teiim-work which your leadership, Mr President has provided<br />
that so much has been achieved.<br />
Zimbabwe is characterised by a cheerfulness and optimism not<br />
pressent everywhere in Africa. The struggle to become<br />
independent has energised the people of Zimbabwe and given<br />
them purpose.<br />
There is no more telling example of the spirit of the people<br />
of Zimbabwe than the resurgence, the renaissance, of the arts<br />
2500 </p>
<p>especially stone carving. I have made * a few modest but heavy<br />
purchases which will stand as permanent reminders of our<br />
visit. Mr President<br />
Australia has always had a very close relationship with<br />
Zimbabwe. Since the early days of Zimcord, when many young Australians<br />
came to assist with that expansion of the education system<br />
which has been one of the signal achievements of your<br />
government, Australia has continued to provide practical help<br />
to Zimbabwe.<br />
Lately, our contribution has focussed on staffing, training<br />
and commodities assistance, as well as support for the grassroots<br />
development work. undertaken here with the support of<br />
Australian non-governmental organisations and volunteers.<br />
Today T had the moving experience of seeing the contribution<br />
that can be made to the welfare of men, women and children by<br />
things as simple, but as important, as water supply and health<br />
care. I am proud of Australia's role in that project and I<br />
congratulate World Viesion for their enthusiastic and creative<br />
management of this important project.<br />
our trade and investment links have been expanding steadily,<br />
if from a relatively low base, with a healthy and broad-based<br />
flow in both directions. Australian companies have already<br />
identified and shown a strong commitment to significant<br />
projects such as Hartley Platinum.<br />
Australians and Zimbabweans enjoy many of the same things.<br />
Sport is one obvious example.<br />
For golfers like myself, your courses certainly provide<br />
something unique in the way of hazards. in Australia you might<br />
run into the occasional kangaroo, but they are not quite in<br />
the same league as a troop of baboons, or a herd of buffalo,<br />
as I had the pleasure of experiencing at Elephant Hills last<br />
weekend. Y'our cricketers gave curs a run for their money last month,<br />
and although your Rugby Union team had a disappointing World<br />
Cup, it will learn from the international experience.<br />
A~ nd Zimbabwean soccer seems to be on the verge of an<br />
international breakthrough. Many experts believe the future of<br />
soccer is in Africa. I look forward to the day when Zimbabwe<br />
will make an impact on a future World Cup similar to the one<br />
Cameroon made in 1990.<br />
Frequent international competition is the only way for<br />
national sports to prcogress. 2501 </p>
<p>Ono or the useful by-products in this region of the gradual<br />
re--admission of South Africa to international sport will be<br />
increased competition in all the sports our two countries<br />
play. Mr President<br />
Zimubabwe emerged to independence in a manner which has etched<br />
itself indelibly on the consciousness of Australians, and of<br />
the world. It was an inspiring event not only for itself,<br />
but for the hope it gave for the eventual achievement of a<br />
Just solution to the uniquely abhorrent and intractable system<br />
of institutionalised racism, oppression and exploitation in<br />
South Africa.<br />
Our two countries have co-operated actively in the collective<br />
effort to speed the passing of apartheid, particularly in the<br />
Commonwealth where our respective Foreign Ministers have<br />
worked closely together in the Committee of Foreign Ministers<br />
on Southern Africa.<br />
All of us now hold firm the hope that the changes underway in<br />
South Africa, stimulated by the action of the Commonwealth<br />
this week, will lead rapidly to a democratic constitution and<br />
tkae enfranchisement of all South Africans, and the removal-of<br />
the injustice and disadvantage ingrained in South African<br />
society by decades of apartheid.<br />
at you know, we are providing practical assistance to<br />
representative organisations and groups, including the ANC, to<br />
upport that work.<br />
May I also express the hope, Mr President, that the<br />
inauguration of a democratic government so long awaited there<br />
will be characterised by the same spirit of reconciliation and<br />
forgiveness that you gave Zimbabwe in those climactic hours<br />
after your first stunning election victory.<br />
The challenges of the last decade of the twentieth century,<br />
and those in the beginning of the twenty first century will be<br />
very different than those of the recent past. The world has<br />
changed utterly in the last two years. Trading nations like<br />
Zimbabwe and Australia have to face up not only to a new world<br />
order in politics, but also to a new world order in economics.<br />
Where once, perhaps, both our countries might have been able<br />
to rely on old friends to buy our products, these days we know<br />
no-one owes us a living.<br />
We discussed today our respective plans to restructure and<br />
reinvigorate our economies. Your economic structural<br />
adjustment plan is a bold and imaginative reflection here in<br />
2; imbabwe of the world-wide trend towards recognition of the<br />
role of markets in sound economic managenent and raising<br />
standards of living. I congratulate you on the plan, and wish<br />
i. t every success.<br />
Vie have also discussed today, as we did at CHOG4 itself, the<br />
vital links between economic development, good government,<br />
2502 </p>
<p>democratic institutions and respect for human rights. The<br />
importance of those links was affirmed in the Harare<br />
Commonwealth Declaration, and has been reflected in the<br />
extraordinary events we have witnessed in many parts of the<br />
world over the past two years.<br />
Those events have shown how more and more people around the<br />
world are coming to recognise that the universal aspirations<br />
to freedom, dignity, security and prosperity can best be<br />
satisfied through pluralistic democratic institutions and<br />
market economies.<br />
We have been particularly glad to see this growing realisation<br />
in Africa, where command economics and undemocratic politics<br />
have in so many cases until recently blighted the bright hopes<br />
of independence.<br />
of course every naticn must develop its own political and<br />
economic structures t~ o meet its particular circumstances. It<br />
is not the Commonwealth way to seek to impose our views on<br />
fellow-members. But it is the Commonwealth way to recognise<br />
and reflect on the enduring ideals we share, which were-set<br />
out so well in the Singapore Declaration twenty years ago, and<br />
re-affirmed here in Harare, and to encourage and assist fellow<br />
members to find ways to meet those ideals more closely in<br />
their particular circumstances.<br />
For all these reasons I an delighted that at the historic<br />
conference which you have hosted and chaired over the past<br />
week, Mr President, the Commonwealth has dedicated itself to<br />
help its members taket practical steps towards building the<br />
institutions of good government.<br />
I had a practical example of the role the Commonwealth can<br />
play today, when I had lunch with the President of the<br />
Australian Senate, Sornator Kerry Sibraa, who is travelling to<br />
Zambia with other Auntralian and Commonwealth Parliamentarians<br />
to observe the multi-party elections being hold there next<br />
week. I wish his tesam, and the people of Zambia, well for<br />
their election.<br />
I am sure that the courage and foresight which you have shown<br />
in developing and implementing your economic structural<br />
adjustment program for Zimbabwe will also provide a strong<br />
impetus for strengtheaning the democratic institutions which we<br />
believe are, amongst other things, the natural and essential<br />
complement to market-based economic institutions. In talking<br />
about these vital isaiues in our long and warm discussion this<br />
afternoon, I was heartened by your strong recognition of the<br />
appropriateness of multi-party democracy in Zimbabwe.<br />
Mr President<br />
The emergence of a democratic South Africa will have a<br />
profound effect on regional relations. I believe that in the<br />
medium term it can be a source of economic dynamism, but it<br />
will not be smooth sailing. 2503' </p>
<p>Australia Bees Zimbabwe as a lynch-pin in the emergence of a<br />
new dispensation in this whole region a region which has<br />
suffered so much but which has such enormous potential.<br />
We look to Zimbabwe to give a lead in providing talent, energy<br />
and creative solutions for the new challenges facing you and<br />
your neighbours in the next decades.<br />
Your land, your manufacturing capacity, and the talent and<br />
energies of your people are rich endowments which can help to<br />
carry not only Zimbabwe but this whole region of Southern<br />
Africa to a prosperous and peaceful future.<br />
Mr President, as free and independent nations we natural ly and<br />
necessarily make our way in the regions within which we live.<br />
We have in recent years devoted much thought and work to<br />
regional issues, such as the processes of Asian-Pacific<br />
Economic Cooperation, or APEC.<br />
In tile light of concerns sometimes expressed by commentators<br />
in this part of the world, I want to make it very clear that<br />
APEC is not and will not become a trading bloc. On the<br />
contrary, it is committed to promoting free trade both within<br />
the region and between the region and other parts of the<br />
world. After all, we too are a country of the South. As a commodity<br />
exporter and in other ways, Australia shares direct interests<br />
with tihe countries of the developing world, our position on<br />
international trade and our initiative in promoting the Cairns<br />
Group of agricultural exporting countries fully bears this<br />
out. The dramatic and rapid changes of recent years make us<br />
question the assumptions of the past.<br />
I therefore welcome the new focus being proposed for the Non-<br />
Alig'ned Movement, of which Zimbabwe is a distinguished former<br />
Chairman and which is now led by one of our nearest neighbours<br />
and most important regional partners, Indonesia. I should<br />
also' like to express Australia's deep respect and appreciation<br />
for the far-sighted role played by Zimbabwe as a member of the<br />
Security Council, and as its President in February, at a time<br />
when the world was faced with a major threat to international<br />
security in tense and unprecedented circumstances.<br />
The new world order, whether we like it or not, is now being<br />
forged in the crucible of breath-takingly rapid change. None<br />
of us can afford to be locked into old and obstructive ways of<br />
thinking, or to limit ourselves solely to regional concerns.<br />
We inust not be spectators: we must decide where to put our<br />
weiflht, Blight as it all too often may seem, on the<br />
international scales.<br />
Australia looks forward to working with Zimbabwe, an old and<br />
trusted friend, in the effort to ensure that the new world<br />
2504 </p>
<p>order is one that fulfils the long-term needs and aspirations<br />
of our peoples.<br />
As part of that proceis it is imperative that the statements<br />
of Commonwealth principles be translated into the lives and<br />
experience of our peoples.<br />
Mr President, I look forward to the continuing development of<br />
an even closer and more mutually beneficial bilateral<br />
relationship between Australia and Zimbabwe.<br />
May I in conclusion ask you all to join me in a toast to good<br />
health and happiness of President Mugabe and First Lady Mrs<br />
Mugabe and to the peace, prosperity and happiness of Zimbabwe<br />
and all its people. 2505<br />
lq </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
