<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9784</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH PETER COUCHMAN, RADIO 3LO MELBOURNE 5 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009784.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PETER COUCHMAN, RADIO 3L0 MELBOURNE<br />
OCTOBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PC: Good morning, Prime Minister. Good to have you joining us.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
PC: We have been discussing the erosion of support for the Labor<br />
Government from the so-called ' true believer's' and people have been<br />
advancing reasons for it. Why do you think the true believers are<br />
deserting you?<br />
SPM: I don't think they are. Just take the not the opinion polls, but the<br />
real polls in 1990 Labor's primary vote was 39 per cent of the<br />
national vote. In 1993 it was 45 per cent. So we picked up 6 per cent<br />
of the national vote in primary votes between 1990 and 1993 and, I<br />
think, if you take an electorate like my own, I think I got 72 per cent of<br />
the primary vote and previously I have never had over about 65 or 66<br />
per cent. So, in 1993 we had probably the biggest Labor vote in a<br />
decade. I just don't think that this thing is really happening and to the<br />
extent that it is, the mosaic is changing. We have picked up a lot of<br />
people in the middle ground that we never had 10 years ago.<br />
PC: All right, so you are losing some but you are gaining some you think?<br />
PM: We have to be because we have won five elections.<br />
PC: Let me just put to you some of the things that people have told me<br />
this morning while we have been discussing it. They feel betrayed<br />
because as Jennie George pointed out in an interview she did the<br />
other day, the people in the lower pay scales have borne the full<br />
brunt of economic restructuring that has gone on. They just haven't<br />
seen any return for it yet, or they feel that they haven't seen any<br />
return for it. </p>
<p>PM: What has happened, we've now had fairly strong real wage growth<br />
for many years and in the 1980s where we had wage restraint in the<br />
middle 1 980s to recover our competitiveness, we gave compensation<br />
by way of tax cuts. This was a huge tax cut program that went on<br />
from 1984/ 85 right through until 1993 and by cutting government<br />
spending as we did, when I became Treasurer back in 1983 we had<br />
government spending at 30.5 per cent of GDP and by 1990 it was<br />
down to 23.5 per cent. So, it was down about six to seven<br />
percentage points. That is about today, $ 30,000 million a year,<br />
billion a year and because of that we are able to give those huge tax<br />
cuts. Those tax cuts and the transfer payments, such as the Family<br />
Allowance Supplement which we pay to low income families, all of<br />
that has pulled them right up from where they were. For instance, a<br />
decade ago the bottom tax rate was 30 per cent, it is now 20 per cent.<br />
The tax free threshold was $ 4500 it is now $ 5460 from memory.<br />
PC: The trouble is, they don't feel any better off and there are two factors<br />
here, I think, they feel as if they have been thrown a few morsels and<br />
then the better-offs the haves as opposed to the have notes have<br />
been getting huge salary increases.<br />
PM: Yes, but there was a lot of that in the 1980s, Peter, for a few people<br />
up the top end, but I think a lot of that has disappeared, too. Look,<br />
these are the real numbers household disposable income, and<br />
household disposable income per capita. Now, per capita measures<br />
wages, salaries, supplements and pension payments, and household<br />
disposable income per capita per person has risen by 21 per cent in<br />
real terms since 1983. Household disposal income per household<br />
has risen by 40 per cent. They are the best measures.<br />
You won't find anything like that in the United State. You won't find it<br />
in most parts of western Europe. It is very strong real growth. Partly<br />
the reason for that is, of course, th6 huge employment. We have had<br />
two million job growth since the early 1980s. We have had about 26<br />
or 27 per cent employment growth, which is about 2 to 3 times the<br />
OECD average. And because more people in households are in<br />
work, household income has risen.<br />
PC: Yes, but you see people are earning less than $ 30,000 a year. Look<br />
at a story like the one that was published in the Australian yesterday,<br />
some of the senior executives in one of the Government's own<br />
corporation, the Australian Industry Development Corporation, have<br />
got the most huge salary increases, I mean millions of dollars a year<br />
going to seven or eight executives in that corporation. They just see<br />
the Government speaking with fork tongues on something like this.<br />
PM: This is a body which we have thought of privatising and selling.<br />
Essentially an investment bank like the AIDC is really only a<br />
collection or a collation of its top staff. I mean, it is basically as I said,<br />
you know, computers and office dividers and bits and pieces, but the </p>
<p>business is really the people in it. Now, to keep those people, you<br />
keep them against the competition in the market place. But, again,<br />
that is decided by the AIDC board. But the things I have been<br />
interested in, Peter, and the things Jenny George is interested in, is<br />
for instance the Family Allowance Supplement. You take someone<br />
on $ 18,000 who has got two or three kids 18 base rate. That would<br />
have taken them to roughly about $ 25,000 a year. Now there is no<br />
way that someone on that income could negotiate in a workplace a<br />
sort of 6-7 thousand a year wage increase. Now I have got John<br />
Howard running around in fact he is following me around Melbourne<br />
at the moment, I was just over at 3AW, me and my shadow I said to<br />
him, if I give you my itinerary will it help. But anyway, I don't know<br />
whether he will burst in on us in a minute.<br />
PC: He hasn't rung us up though..<br />
PM: He might come in with his smiling countenance in a moment.<br />
Anyway, the point is what he is about, is basically cutting this out.<br />
You see, he is out there talking about battlers. I mean, the cynicism<br />
of it is he's opposed every wage increase bar one since 1978, and<br />
when we introduced FAS, the Family Allowance Supplement, now<br />
called Additional Family Payment, they were opposed to it. They<br />
have been opposed to all of these benefits which we have paid to low<br />
income families. Now when he talks but doesn't show us the list of<br />
his policies which include cuts in government spending to get rid of<br />
they say " waste and duplication". But it really isn't waste and<br />
duplication, it's cuts in payments to families. It's cuts in payments to<br />
schools. The same sort of things that Jeff Kennett has done here in<br />
Victoria, but on a grander scale nationally. What we have done in<br />
Australia there is a disparity in incomes, Peter, it has happened<br />
world wide.<br />
PC: So you acknowledge this.<br />
PM: Absolutely.<br />
PC: The gaps between the haves and the have-nots has widened.<br />
PM: This is now an international country and the wage spectrum reflects<br />
that which exists in a lot of other countries. The chief executive<br />
officers, etc. But what we have done, unlike the United States, unlike<br />
Britain, unlike the Thatcher's Britain which John Howard would seek<br />
to emulate, or Ronald Reagan's America, we have brought the bottom<br />
two deciles at least of income deciles, two groups, up immeasurably<br />
so that yes the gap has widened but nothing like the way it would<br />
have widened. So if you inject into that heaps of employment growth<br />
so that a couple more people in the household are at work or the wife<br />
has a job and formerly wouldn't have, because there is massive<br />
participation now by women in the workforce, all of that I think means<br />
that we wiill keep the Australian family. together by keeping the place </p>
<p>more financially, economically cohesive. That is with employment<br />
and a goad social wage. That means, the likes of the Family<br />
Allowance Supplements. That means the safety net for wage<br />
increases which Mr Howard wants to do in. It means Medicare. It<br />
means all of those things that really buttress a family. Now, you will<br />
still have people say as they have said to you, Peter, well okay we<br />
still feel as though some of it has passed us by, and I can emphathise<br />
with that, but nothing like it would have. I mean, I don't know whether<br />
you noticed the US labour secretary, Robert Reich, the US Minister<br />
for Labour, about 3 months ago said well in America we have had<br />
heaps of employment growth but we have had real wages falling for<br />
16 consecutive years. In the United States, 70 per cent of the<br />
incremental wealth of the last decade has gone to 3 per cent of the<br />
population and the people at the bottom, they are really at the bottom'.<br />
This is not true in Australia. The values of this government and the<br />
values of holding this society together, I mean, Working Nation<br />
looking after the long term unemployment, One Nation getting the<br />
place started again, and those big social questions, occupational<br />
superannuation for the workforce these are all about making<br />
Australia different and better.<br />
PC: Oh yeah, I think you are right. I think anyone who goes to the United<br />
States comes back saying you are infinitely better off here if you are<br />
disadvantaged than you are there. But your problem, politically, is<br />
that John Howard is reminding people of just why they are finding it<br />
tough in Australia. He pointed out last night, for instance, that the<br />
cost of servicing an average mortgage in Australia has jumped from<br />
$ 651 in 1983 to $ 974 in 1995 and that is in real terms. Now that is a<br />
hell of a lot of money out of people's pockets if they are earning less<br />
than $ 30,000 a year.<br />
PM: Again, I would have to look at those numbers to know whether they<br />
are right. But partly that will be explained, some of it will be explained<br />
that house prices have risen. I mean, many people will say to you<br />
oh I feel better about things because I bought a house for $ 120,000<br />
and it is now worth $ 300,000. Well the new buyer who ii coming in to<br />
buy the $ 300,000 house is going to have a higher level of<br />
repayments than that person who bought it 10 years earlier. So that<br />
is the sort of meaningless comparison, but if you look at the interest<br />
rates we have got now, Peter. And here is John Howard crying<br />
crocodile tears about the repayments but he has opposed every wage<br />
increase. You see he says this " oh isn't it shocking that you are<br />
paying this on your mortgage", in other words, your household<br />
income has been diminished but " by the way I do oppose your wage<br />
increases" you know, you have got to say are you-. for real, really. I<br />
mean, are you out there crying crocodile tears about peoples'<br />
disposable income but you have opposed formally every wage<br />
increase bar one in 20 years. Now, before I opened up the banking<br />
system in the 80s, when you went to get a mortgage you would get<br />
maybe $ 30,000 at 13 1/ 2 per cent then the next $ 20,000 would be at </p>
<p>the overdraft rate which would then be 15 or 15 1/ 2, and then the next<br />
$ 20,000 would be at 18 per cent. They used to call them cocktails<br />
because the banks couldn't lend on a consolidated mortgage. So<br />
your average interest rate, God knows what it was then, it was around<br />
or 16 per cent. What is it now 10 and it is all in one lump. So<br />
you can actually go in and say well look, I want a mortgage for the<br />
house and it is in one consolidated mortgage and it is around 10 per<br />
cent and at the same time you can actually say and we want to<br />
actually start by putting, you know, a new fridge in and a garage on<br />
the side and the bank will let you have actually a bit more on the<br />
mortgage at the mortgage rate to do those things. Back in the 80s, in<br />
Howard's Australia, you could get $ 30,000 from a bank, so you had<br />
all these fringe institutions growing up, permanent building societies<br />
remember the growth of the permanent building societies they were<br />
all there because the banks couldn't lend and people had these very<br />
high interest rates. So, if it does comfort people to think that their<br />
house is worth more, they must know that when someone buys it they<br />
are going to have a bigger repayment than they had 10 years earlier<br />
or 20 years earlier. But the question is how much of their income<br />
goes on it. And this is the housing affordability index and housing<br />
affordability is very good now because wages have risen and interest<br />
rates have come down.<br />
PC: Just while we are talking about housing and so on. One of the things<br />
that would have helped you and, I'm sure, heartened you enormously<br />
would have been a cut in interest rates between now and the next<br />
election whenever that happens to be. Now, the latest retail figures<br />
we've got this week seem to indicate that that is not very likely at all.<br />
Were they good news but a disappointment to you politically.<br />
PM: Well, by the same token, the balance of payments for the month was<br />
very good. Two months ago we had everyone going potty about the<br />
thing running at 3 billion for the month and last month it fell to 1 1/ 2<br />
billion, the previous month, 2.2. So, there is a sharp fall. You might<br />
remember, Peter, at the beginning of the year Ralph Willis came out<br />
and said the current account deficit would be 27 billion for the year.<br />
Well there is now going to be, I think, a sharp revision downwards of<br />
that number, which means the economy is behaving in a controlled<br />
way. So we might have seen a strong retail figure for the month but<br />
that doesn't mean to say that the economy is tearing away. I don't<br />
think it is. When the next quarter comes around it will be 17<br />
consecutive quarters of growth, we are in our fifth year of growth now.<br />
We have had 16 consecutive quarters, four years, as of last quarter.<br />
In the next quarter, the one we are in now, when the numbers are<br />
published, it will be the longest growth phase in Australia since the<br />
second world war. The longest continuous growth phase since the<br />
second world war, but not just the longest continuous growth phase,<br />
the longest continuous growth phase with low inflation. We had<br />
some higher growth in the 70s but it was with 10 per cent inflation.<br />
Now we have got strong growth with two to three per cent inflation. </p>
<p>PC: Which must make it puzzling to you that you are not getting support<br />
from not just the true believers, it's the middle class greens, you know<br />
the tree huggers, they are saying to you now we are the enemy and<br />
we are going to bring this government down. A survey of business<br />
leaders the other day I noticed overwhelmingly wanted John Howard<br />
as Prime Minister.<br />
PM: That is not true, though. Look, the public know the polls are a sort of<br />
partial snap shot of opinion and they also know it is a way of sort of<br />
spurring the government on, you know, needling the government. It<br />
is a bit like a by-election, you can sort of have a needle at the<br />
government through the polls. But it is only when we get down to<br />
near the vote that people really start to focus sharply on where their<br />
interest lie. This is just as true in the 1993 election. I was having the<br />
same conversations, to some extent, that I am having with you today,<br />
different issues perhaps, but the same theme, but then of course the<br />
growth was only starting to it would have been around about a year,<br />
it was not as obvious as now. I think that Australians know that this is<br />
a good place to live. We have a chance of creating here, if not the<br />
fairest, one of the fairest societies in the world. This makes your life<br />
much more pleasant and that means a good social wage, decent<br />
wage increases, a safety net, a good medical system, access and<br />
equity in education, long term savings in superannuation and<br />
retirement incomes. All of these things are what it is about low<br />
inflation which really means low interest rates. Before they walk<br />
away from that model and go back to a Liberal Party unprepared for<br />
office. I mean, here is Andrew Robb, the Federal Director of the<br />
Liberal Party, last week going on television saying we have 98 per<br />
cent of our policies finished well why are they keeping them a<br />
secret. Why are they so slick in not showing the public what their<br />
policies are. The answer is they don't think the public will like them.<br />
PC: Well the answer is they want to keep the pressure on you and they<br />
want to make you the focus of public discussion and the public<br />
campaign.<br />
PM: No, they think the public won't like them, they think they will slip them<br />
out to the public in the last week of the election campaign and they<br />
will slip under the wire without really being pinned down. Remember<br />
when Jeff Kennett said about three or four years ago no one will<br />
lose a dollar of income when we come to office and of course that<br />
was completely untrue. Howard will say the same things. He will<br />
start talking about softening his wages policies, don't believe him. He<br />
is going to be cutting into wages as he has always wanted to. Now, I<br />
think, when the public take all of that into account they say what has<br />
this government given us, four continuous years of growth and now<br />
the longest growth phase since the war, low inflation, equity in the<br />
wage system, enterprise bargaining but a safety net, a decent social<br />
security system, income support for families, retirement incomes and </p>
<p>not just that, a view about Australia's identity, about its culture,<br />
threading together the biggest free trade agreement in the world with<br />
APEC which we are part of they say will we walk away from this and<br />
take pot luck with the Liberal Party. I don't think they will do it.<br />
PC: How seriously do you take these threats from the greens. I mean,<br />
they do represent a large slab of the middle class vote don't they.<br />
And if what we are hearing is true, they're pretty disillusioned with<br />
you at the moment especially over forest policy.<br />
PM: I don't think so. I mean, what happened, we have had a few<br />
intemperate remarks by some people in the Wilderness Society<br />
because what we are seeking to do now is the grand-daddy of forest<br />
policy around the world. What this Government, this Labor<br />
Government is seeking to do is to do as no other western government<br />
anywhere has done. We are seeking to put away in representative<br />
reserve systems for forests 15 per cent of the cover which existed<br />
before European settlement in 1788. No other country is trying to<br />
benchmark 15 per cent, they are mostly working on 7 or 8 per cent.<br />
So we have got a most ambitious policy and we now have a draft in<br />
the marketplace for three weeks which is a Commonwealth/ State set<br />
of documents looking at Deferred Forest Areas. So what we are<br />
hoping to get to is what we called Regional Forest Agreements. Let<br />
me not confuse people with the terms, Peter. What a Regional<br />
Forest Agreement is is this, we say look if you want to take logs, that<br />
is native forest logs or regrowth from particular areas, you can only<br />
do so if there is a Regional Forest Agreement. And what a regional<br />
forest agreement will be about is having representative, solid strong<br />
representative species of trees in representative reserve systems.<br />
Once that is in place, they can go taking these things and they can<br />
export their woodchips but only where these deferred forest areas<br />
have been agreed. But before we -get to a regional forest agreement<br />
which takes two to three years to pu6t into place because you have got<br />
to firstly measure and survey the areas, you have got to know what<br />
the species are, you have got to be clear that it truly is a<br />
representative system. We are putting away now what we call<br />
Deferred Forest Areas or OFAs. In these three weeks what we are<br />
agreeing to is what goes away for the next two to three years so we<br />
can have the Regional Forest Agreements later. And what will<br />
happen in this process, you will have the greens pushing for more<br />
and the foresters pushing for less, but what the Commonwealth..<br />
PC: And the Government sandwiched in the middle.<br />
PM: No, the Government will come through the middle with a system<br />
which does justice to our native forests but at the same time tries to<br />
preserve a forest products industry, perhaps not in the form it is in<br />
now, but preserve a forest products industry that can actually work off<br />
either regrowth, planations or parts of the native forest. But it won't<br />
be parts of the native forest which tear away at the integrity of that </p>
<p>reserve system. So if we were not doing something like this, if we just<br />
went on for years just approving woodchip exports like we had last<br />
years debate, and not tried to put this together. You see, what I said<br />
at Christmas last year is if these States don't come to the party, if<br />
Tasmania doesn't sign up and the other States don't sign up here, we<br />
will be cutting woodchip exports by 20 per cent a year to nothing, so<br />
in five years there will be none. So they all said, God we better get<br />
into the game. So they have signed up, Tasmania has signed up<br />
which is the State we needed to be in it, along with Victoria and NSW<br />
and we are now in this sophisticated process that no government like<br />
this is doing anywhere in the world. And I just hope there was a<br />
very good piece in the Australian on the weekend where one<br />
journalist said look I hope the greens understand how important this<br />
process is and what quality it is and how good this is going to be for<br />
Australia and that they are part of it and not removed from it.<br />
PC: Prime Minister, we have got to break for our news now, but thank you<br />
for stopping by this morning and I'm sure we will see you again<br />
between now and the next election, whenever it happens to be.<br />
PM: If you give me a good invitation, Peter, I'm sure I'll turn up.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
