<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19003</transcript-id>
    <title>PM Endorses Nova Peris as NT Senate Candidate</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>Today I have asked the National Executive of the Australian Labor Party to endorse Nova Peris OAM as a candidate for the Senate in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>Australians first came to know Nova as an outstanding Olympic and Commonwealth Games medallist.</p>
<p>Since then, Nova has devoted her career to working with young people and indigenous Australians across the country.</p>
<p>Her passion for health and education makes her the right choice to succeed Senator Trish Crossin.</p>
<p>I look forward to working with Nova as she works hard over the coming months to become the endorsed candidate and ultimately, the first Aboriginal woman to enter the Parliament of Australia.</p>
<p>I pay tribute to Senator Crossin for her extraordinary contribution to the Northern Territory, the Australian Parliament and to her advancement of indigenous Australians.</p>
<p>Trish has been a highly effective, selfless and tireless advocate for the communities she has been proud to represent since 1998.</p>
<p>As a teacher, a unionist representing teachers and lecturers, and as a Parliamentarian, Trish has been a significant contributor to the debates and policy development in our Parliament and particularly the opportunities that education provides for indigenous children and youth.</p>
<p>This is a record that extends back to 1981 when she first arrived in Yirrkala on the Gove Peninsula as a school teacher.</p>
<p>Trish has a long commitment and an outstanding record of service to the questions of constitutional reform and rights for the residents of the Territory and the recognition of indigenous Australians in our constitution.</p>
<p>She has been a true role model for Labor people, unionists, women and all Australians with a sense of social justice.</p>
<p>I thank her for her service and look forward to her continuing contribution to national and Territory life.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
