<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5289</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF CHANNEL 3 NEWS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005289.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER MONDAY 10 MARCH 1980<br />
From the Press Office SUMMARY OF CHANNEL 3 NEWS<br />
The petrol strfieke: 09domestic f lights have been interrupted and delays<br />
occured.. of. up'to five hours .1<br />
As expected the freeze on petrol supplies in Sydney, Newcastle and<br />
Wollongong will remain indefinitely. The countries areas will<br />
escape restrictions for the time being. Mr. Hills says arrangements<br />
are now being made to keep essential services on the road. Publi&amp; f<br />
transport. has:-. at present ' abouti ten . days.-. supplybof fueybut trains<br />
and.--buses have -slightly . less-. ithahthat. 7<br />
Tasmania's Premier Mr. Lowe-: today predicted-major . i3iduitial<br />
disputes and political:: ipheal-for-the:-. 1980sY Mr. Lowe told a<br />
gathering of businessmen in Sydney that inequalities and conflict<br />
in business, such as the reporting of massive profits and rapidly<br />
increasing rate of bankruptcies. He said the challenge of the<br />
for the trade union movement should be a critical self examination<br />
to ensure that unions went into the next century with a new spirit<br />
of rationality. . ool. growtehresm selves voted:-today :: to.-. start-: moving. unsold wool from<br />
woolstores unless. the Storemen and Packers dispute is. settle' in<br />
a few days. The President of the Wool Council of Australia, Mr.<br />
Dick O'Brien said in Canberra a special committee had been formed<br />
to examine ways of moving the wool. ( newsconference reported in<br />
full in Newsvoice).<br />
Mr. Wran today-told. a conference of health and research employees<br />
in Sydney there should be a cooling off period in the NSW petrol<br />
dispute. He thought the tanker drivers strike was unjustified but<br />
at the same time he said section 45D of the Trade Practices Act<br />
dealing with secondary boycotts was a recipe for industrial chaos.<br />
Mr. 4WranLt<br />
Increasingly there is immediate resort to the extreme course.<br />
Employers, particularly, if the employer is the Federal Government,<br />
or a federal agency, are turning to sanctions and penalties, unions<br />
are turning to industrial action as a first resort rather than the<br />
last resort often for quite trifling claims which any decent<br />
industrial advocate or barely competent leadership could get through<br />
by negotiation. Somel: Pplje may think this -proves their: toughness-.<br />
It!. s. more often a demonstration of bankruptcy. of leadership,; . Where ! s<br />
6l. l1t he -so-called. toughness by the: Fraser : Government . and Telecom<br />
gotiafa ar. as.: industrial-sanity in the communications-industry is:,:<br />
concerned: Or where inithe long run -are frequent stoppages going to<br />
get-tha. public -transport-. wor ers except gradually, to throttle.<br />
system on which. their livelihood depends. And where's the common<br />
sense or the faintest chance of establishing common ground or common<br />
purpose in the use* of the civil law to settle industrial disputes.<br />
Only: somehe hellbentjon.. industrial.. confrontation could imagine that<br />
a-fundamental : hard won : principle could suddenly be set aside without<br />
a . disastrous reaction. Equally disastrous is the new philosophy<br />
expressed by Mr. Fraser as recently as last Friday that the wayv to<br />
settle a dispute is to widen it. -On. -Friday Mr.-Fraser-: urged thewool,;.<br />
brokers to:: sack the . non-strikif gembers6 o the Storemen and<br />
Packers Union . in0. the States:-so that:. strike funds would not. be sent<br />
to-V ictoriaadNS-Winik .-aasi sg ood. as anod and yesterday the.<br />
WoolCounci. l took Mr. Fraser athis-word _ The., result. is that a<br />
dispute ' which was possibly-nearing settlement-would almost certainly<br />
2 </p>
<p>be:-prolonged.. with-more and more unions -becoming involved. Is this<br />
toughness T call it madness. But it's a classic illustration of<br />
how far this nation under its present leadership is moving away<br />
from common sense a sharing of common interests, common standards,<br />
common goals and a common purpose.<br />
As the stalemate continues over the American hostages in Teheran<br />
Iran's Revolutionary ' Council.--has met: to discuss the situation.:<br />
A spokesman for the Council said it would make its views known in<br />
a few hours time.<br />
In the seige in the Dominican Republic's Embassy in Colombia there<br />
has been little development. There have been three rounds of talks<br />
but as yet no details have been released.<br />
* Harvesting this years opium.: crop. in-.. rthe' Golden Triangle is about<br />
' to begin'. The opium crop is expected to be smuggled out of<br />
northern Thailand. Peter Moncton reports that all five member<br />
countries of the ASEAN group have stepped up surveillance at border<br />
checkpoints.<br />
Mr. Mugabesays he.' s almost comrpleted fobrming his coalitiongovernment.<br />
He says it will include members . of" Mr. Nkomo's party<br />
and representatives-of the -country's.-white minority. Mr. Mugabe<br />
said there would be one of twowhites in his Cabinet, not, necessarily<br />
members of Mr ". Smith's party. Rhodesian security forces meanwhile<br />
are joining in what is being called Operation Merger with former<br />
Patriotic Front guerrillas.<br />
Papua -New Guinea has : given ' a'consortium of ' Australian,: American -and<br />
West. German companies" the go-ahead to mine the rich. gold and copper<br />
deposit in the country's remote western province. Geoff Robertson<br />
in Melbourne says BHP leads the consortium into a $ 700 million<br />
development.<br />
Mr. Hunt has approved TAA's application to have Apex fares extended<br />
year round.<br />
The National Executive of the -ALP-: isi . expected to consider -a:<br />
compromise proposal:--in. the-row over federal -intervention in the<br />
Queensland Branch when it meets on Friday week. The compromise<br />
was suggested at a meeting in Canberra at the weekend. It allows<br />
for the Administrative Committee of 29, nominated by the National<br />
Executive to be expanded by 10. However Dr. Dennis Murphy says<br />
the increase is unacceptable.<br />
Murphy I don't think it's acceptable-at all. The Interim Administrative<br />
Committee is already ' at 29 which is quite a large committee if<br />
you remember the . Whitlam Cabinet was 27 and it became somewhat<br />
unwieldy. To increase it from 29 to 39 really makes almost a<br />
mass meeting. If you had 39 people then you'd have to get back<br />
to having an inner executive and really we'd be back to the whole<br />
problem that started this off in 1978.<br />
Question Well are you concerned that there is some compromise on the part<br />
of federal leaders?<br />
Murphy Look this is a decision of the National Executive of the Party. </p>
<p>It's not a decision of the federal leaders or of the Federal<br />
President or of the Federal Secretary. Any change in that<br />
National Executive decision would have to be made by the National<br />
Executive itself. And I know several of the National Executive<br />
members who will-be arguing quite strongly against that, myself<br />
included. I'm now a delegate on the National Executive of the<br />
Party. I would certainly be arguing against increase from 29 to<br />
39.<br />
The AMi-todaycalTed-' on:. the'NSWyPrices-. Commission to wind-.: up its'<br />
enquiry.' intoQ-doctors fees. The AMA says the enquiry should be<br />
wound up on the grounds that no evidence has been produced that<br />
doctors' charges were excessive.<br />
The condition of an apprentice jockey injured in a fall at Rose Hill<br />
on Saturday continues to deteriorate.<br />
Cricket: Victoria has retained the Sheffield Shield.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
