<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1190</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF LIBERAL PARTY HEADQUARTERS, CANBERRA - 9TH NOVEMBER, 1965 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001190.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF LIBERAL PARTY HEADQUARTERS,<br />
CANBERRA 9TH NOVEMBER, 1965<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
I would like to say " thank you" to. Phil McBride.<br />
He didn't refer to himself of course, but if you knew Phil<br />
McBride as clzsely as I have known him for many many years,<br />
you would know that he is a very hard man to dodge and the<br />
moment that he decided there ought to be a headquarters<br />
building, it was as good as done. True, he recruited all<br />
these other notable people to whom he has referred, but I know<br />
Phil and I am quite satisfied that but for him, we might not<br />
have achieved the result so soon. Always a difficult man to<br />
contradict. On the many occasions when I have in a small<br />
voice said " Yes, Phil Ientirely agree with you" the has<br />
looked so taken aback that he has usually restate the<br />
proposition ( Laughter) in case I had misunderstood it. He<br />
has drive, and or course he carries with him a reasonable<br />
amount of healthy South Australian bias. That's obvious from<br />
everything we have been told this morning. In fact it<br />
explains why Tom Playford is here this morning, practically<br />
lroking over the estate. ( Laughter)<br />
Now as we have been reminding ourselves in the<br />
last twenty-four hours, this is a national party, a natioral<br />
-arty that was made up originally out of a mass of fragments,<br />
a solid unified national party. Now that itself is a great<br />
achievement. And a national party is a party that has a<br />
national policy, and over these years we'have been able to<br />
provide the country with policies which, open to attack as<br />
hey may be in point of detail, h.' ve in the broad achieved<br />
great results for our country. So we had a national party with<br />
a nationa_ policy and now we have what was lacking1 a true<br />
national headquarters in the national city. This t think is<br />
real landmark in the history of the party, a national<br />
headquarters. You imagine it in the past our national secretariat,<br />
our Federal secretariat has been scattered here and there, part<br />
of it in Sydney, part of it here in Canberra. Now it assembles<br />
here. It conducts its operat-. ons in research, study, in<br />
public relations, in achieving effective close and natural<br />
contact with the Parliamentary party. these things are of<br />
tremendous importance and I want to say on behalf of my<br />
Parliamentary colleagues that we attach importance to the<br />
c:: istence of this buildin and the presence of the Secretariat<br />
because we know that thisowill be a source of knowledge, a<br />
source of wisdom on many thinj, and that the levels of achievement<br />
in Parliament itself will thereby be raised. Now this is<br />
very good. Long distance communications are one thing, and<br />
failing all else they do. But the close daily contact so that<br />
Members know what is going on in the mind of the Secretariat<br />
and the Secretariat, importantly, knows what is going on in the<br />
mind of the Ministers, this is, i think, a tremendously important<br />
matter. Now, I am not a controversial fellow and therefore<br />
I won't buy into an argument about the architecture. I think<br />
it's delightful, but t en I am an old-fashioned reactionary<br />
Tory whe* it comes to architecture, and perhaps on some other<br />
matters for all I know. But it is a lovely building. It has<br />
charm; it reflects, I think, great skill in its architecture<br />
and magnificent achievement in its craftsmanship. The building.....<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
look around this room and you see the most astonishing craftsmanship<br />
which some people had begun to think no longer existed in<br />
a mass production period of time. So I like this building, and<br />
I defy the so-callod modern architects who disagree. All I can<br />
say about some of them is that if they had their way, they have<br />
a ree hand in the great cities of the world over the nex fifty<br />
years, nobody will Know what city he is in because they will all<br />
look the same ( Laughter) and I like to believe in a little<br />
character in a city. Fancy taking away the character of London,<br />
for example, by putting up a series of glasshouses. It gives<br />
me the horrors. And therefore when we were told that we were<br />
to have a building that looked as this one does and didn't look<br />
like a dairy ( Laughter), I was delighted and I still am.<br />
Over there in the corner somewhere I think is, if not<br />
a storied urn, at least an animated bust, I believe. All I can<br />
say because I am not going to anticipate what Sir vVilliam<br />
Anderson will be sayin about it all I can say about it is this<br />
that to the extent that it resembles me it will be a sign and<br />
a warning to those who come after me. ( Laughter) From that<br />
point of view., it will turn out to be a very useful addition to<br />
this room. I am very greatly honoured that this room should have<br />
been named after me, very greatly honoured that I should have<br />
the opportunity of opening the building. I concur in everything<br />
that Sir Philip McBride said. I merely added a few words on<br />
my own account because that seems to be the thing to do. History<br />
will be made in this room. Year after year, decade after<br />
decade, good history will be made in this room. It must be<br />
good, otherwise the new generation will hAve failed to maintain<br />
their vision and I don't believe that they will. Wo are a<br />
pirty with an enormous d-stiny. That is a thing that has to be<br />
remembered a creditabl history. Twenty-one but a great<br />
destiny, a great responsibility, and the existence of this<br />
building and the meeting of the people who will meet in this<br />
building these things will make a contribution I am sure to<br />
our country, our greatly loved country which will be quite<br />
imperishable. Sir, I have great pleasure in declaring the building<br />
open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
