<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1777</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M.NO 20/1960 ADDITIONAL FINANCE FOR THE STATES STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/02/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001777.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
*' 1c ti<br />
FOR PRE~ CS: 20 FEB1968<br />
/ RA P. M. No. 2C/ 1C63<br />
ADDITICNAL FINANCE FOR THE SCTATES<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Gorton, announced today that, in<br />
resp onse to requests from the States, the Commonwealth had agreed to<br />
provide special revenue assistance totalling $ 13 million to be distributed<br />
between the four Statec still being affected by drought. The Commonwealth<br />
had also indicated that it would be prepared to support an increase of<br />
$ 23 million in the approved Loan Council borrowing programmes for Ctate<br />
semi-government authorities. The States would thus have access to<br />
additional funds totalling $ 33 million in 1967-68.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the additional grants this year to<br />
the four drought-affected Ctates would help them at a time when drought<br />
had affected their revenues. Through the procedures of the Grants<br />
Commission, such assistance would also help the budgets of the other two<br />
Statec of V'estern A ustralia and Tasmania. Mr. Corton pointed out that<br />
this assistance was in addition to that being rovided to meet the full cost<br />
of State expenditure on drought relief measures; co far the Commonwealth<br />
had , provided over $ 44 million under these arrangements and by the end<br />
of the current financial year it was expected that the total amount made<br />
available would be in excess of $ 50 million.<br />
The Prime Minister indicated that the special revenue assistance<br />
of $ 13 million, which would take the form of a non-recurring grant, would<br />
be distributed between the four States concerned in proportion to their<br />
chs. res of the 1967-60 financial assistance grants under the grants formula.<br />
These had not yet been finally determined but, on present estimates, would<br />
provide the following amounts:-million<br />
New South V. ales 5.1<br />
Victoria 3.3<br />
Queensland 2.4<br />
South Australia 1.7<br />
13. C<br />
As regards the proposed increase in the Loan Council borrowing<br />
prcgramme for semi-government authorities in 1967-68, the Prime<br />
Minister said that the Commonwealth had offered to support an increase<br />
of $ 20 million notwithstanding the large increase from $ 268 million to<br />
$ 311 million approved at the June 1967 Loan Council meeting. Conditions<br />
in the loan market ap. eared to make it possible to raise additional<br />
amounts in the current financial year and, in these circumstances, the<br />
Commonwealth had agreed that advantage could be teken of this situation<br />
to enable State authorities to seek loan funds to carry out additional / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
programmes of work which could include such important areas as<br />
electricity, water and cewerage and roads. The Commonwealth had<br />
advised the States that as this additional borrowing authority had a<br />
special character deriving from conditions in the current financial year,<br />
the Commonwealth would not wish it to be taken ac forming part of the<br />
bacis on which the cemi-government borrowing programmes for 196C-69<br />
would be determined. The . tates had agreed to the proposed increase.<br />
The Frime Minister went on to say that the Treasurer, as<br />
Chairman of the Loan Council, had obtained the approval of the Loan<br />
Council to the additional borrowing allocation of million being<br />
distributed as follows:-million<br />
New South ales 6.36<br />
Victoria 7.15<br />
Queensland 3.97<br />
South Australia 1. C<br />
V/ estern Australia 82<br />
Tasmania G. 64<br />
C1: Meb3 RR<br />
9th February, 1968. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
