<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15156</transcript-id>
    <title>Coalition Government: Eleven Years of Achievement</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Today marks the eleventh anniversary of the election of the  Coalition Government.</p>
<p>Australia  today is a more prosperous, optimistic and outward-looking nation than it was  on March 2, 1996. We are more confident about who we are and what we stand for.</p>
<p>Since the election of the Coalition Government, the Australian  economy has grown by 40 per cent into a $1 trillion powerhouse, a model economy  and the envy of the developed world.</p>
<p>The attached figures show how Australia has progressed over the  past 11 years and underlines the improvement in the quality of life of  Australian families.</p>
<p>Australians are reaping the benefits of the Coalition's economic  management, with official figures revealing since 1996 Australians: </p>
<p>   * doubled household net wealth.</p>
<p> * pay $16 billion a year less tax;</p>
<p> * outlay five per cent less on average in mortgage interest  rates;</p>
<p> * have seen their real wages increase by 17.9 per cent,  compared to a fall in real wages under Labor; and</p>
<p> * enjoy far greater opportunities to find a job, with  more than two million jobs created.</p>
<p>My Government has also introduced major social reforms, including  strengthening of the health system through the support for Medicare and private  health insurance, entrenching the principle of mutual responsibility through  such programs as Work-for-the-Dole and beneficial changes to family law through  the introduction of Family Relationship Centres.</p>
<p>The Government's economic management and reforms and the commitment  and effort of Australian workers has delivered a national economy in far better  shape than in 1996:</p>
<p>   * </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
