<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>836</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, ON TELEVISION NETWORK TCN, GTV, QTQ, NWS, TVW AND TVT ON SUNDAY, 20TH OCTOBER 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000836.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
63/ 137<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIM~ E MINISTER THE RT.<br />
HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, ON IELEVISION<br />
NETWORK TCN, GTV, QTQ NWIS TVW AND TVT<br />
ON SUNDAY) 20TH 6CTOBE'R, 1963<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
This is not a policy speech. That, no doubt is<br />
a pleasure to come. What I want to doain this occasion Is to<br />
answer a question which is being fairly widely put as to why<br />
we are to have an election now when the Parliament, theoretically,<br />
has another twelve months to go. I want to answer that<br />
by reminding you of a few things.<br />
Before the last election that was in December,<br />
1961 my Government had a majority of something over<br />
When the last election finished we had a period for about<br />
six or seven days in which noboly quite knew who had won,<br />
It looked at one stage as if the vote would be 61 all and,<br />
of course, that would have meant, inevitably, another election<br />
almost immediately. Well, then, when finally the counts were<br />
completed, it turned out we had 62-60 and by the time a Speaker<br />
had been elected, that meant 61-60 on the floor of the House<br />
a majority of one. A majority of one in a House of 122 I<br />
think it might properly be said, was a pretty narrow ma3ority,<br />
It couldn't be narrower,<br />
And I think that at that time but you can think<br />
for yourselves and remember for yourselves raost people thought<br />
we would be out in a matter of months. The Opposition<br />
certainly thought so because when Parliament met, for the first<br />
time after the election, in February in 1962, the Opposition<br />
at once launched a No-Confidence motion which was defeated<br />
by one vote. Since then as you know because I have mentioned<br />
it publicly we have ha3four other No-Confidence motions,<br />
all designed, no doubt, to bring about the defeat of the<br />
Government. And we have survived mostly by a majority of<br />
one. Now, right through this period it's getting near<br />
two years now we have had to live on the very edge of a<br />
political precipice. Two of my supporters, staying away from<br />
a division, not hearing the division bell or being otherwise<br />
engaged could mean the defeat of the Government; one member<br />
on the 65overnment side feeling very strongly about something,<br />
crossing the floor of the House and the Opposition wins and<br />
the Government is defeated. This is an eminently unsatisfactory<br />
way of conducting the business of the country.<br />
At that time, of course, the Opposition wanted an<br />
election and let me remind you that at all times that would<br />
have been an election for the lower House, not for the Senate,<br />
because under the constitutional arrangements, there can't be<br />
a Senate election before July of 1964+, and therefore had the<br />
Opposition succeeded in any one of these repeated atlacks,<br />
there would have been an election for the lower House only and<br />
we would not have been hearing all this nonsense about the<br />
extravagant waste of money involved in a single House election.<br />
That, after all was what the Opposition wanted. They can<br />
scarcely complain now that they have got it. Well why have<br />
they gone cold on this election? Why is it that people who<br />
wanted to have one so frequently have now taken up an attitude<br />
of protest about having one. Well, the answer is quite simple, </p>
<p>-2<br />
They were quite certain early in 1962 that if they<br />
could force an election they would win it, I'm a bit inclined<br />
to think they were right because our popularity if I may say<br />
so had fallen very considerably and the 1961 election was<br />
followed by a period of time in which I wouldn't have rated our<br />
chances very high, But of course, today the position is quite<br />
different. The Opposition knows that an election is not likely<br />
to be a successful one for it; knows that the position of the<br />
Government has strengthened; that there is an increasing<br />
realisation in the country of the prosperity that we see around<br />
us, a prosperity which bears out the policy of the Government<br />
for stability and for growth because we have had both in full<br />
measure and therefore the Opposition now finds that it is a<br />
wicked thing to have an election. Well we are going to have<br />
one and you will be the people who will determine whether it is<br />
wicked or not. You will be the people who will decide whether<br />
you want this precarious situation to go on with a Government<br />
devoting quite a bit of its time to preserving itself to<br />
discussions with the Whip, to finding whether the full numbers<br />
are present. All these things take a lot of time and I regard<br />
my duty to you as one to use my time and the time of my<br />
Ministers in attonding to the serious problems of the Government<br />
of the nation. Now why is it, I wonder, that the Opposition has<br />
this fear, apari from what they know about public opinion.<br />
Why do they now fear an election? I think the answer to that<br />
is quite simple, First of all, last year they were talking<br />
vociferously about unemploymenz, whipping up the unemployment<br />
issue magnifying whatever unemployment existed. Today they<br />
know that this has practically disappeared, They know, indeed,<br />
as well as I do and as well as you do that it won't be very long<br />
now before it will become increasingly difficult to find employees<br />
for jobs. We are almost at the point where there are more jobs<br />
than there are people looking for them. And the result is<br />
that the eager cries about unemployment have now faded away and<br />
anyhow -you wouldn't be very much impressed by them if they were<br />
resumed, would you?<br />
In the second place, they know quite well that<br />
people are more conscious than they ever were before that the<br />
issue is not so much between the Government and the Opposition<br />
in Parliament as it is between the Government and those who<br />
control the Opposition in Parliament the thirty-six men, most<br />
of whom you have never heard of who sit on the interstate body<br />
of the Labour Party which lays Aown ironclad rules as to what<br />
policy they are to pursue. That is something that is very well<br />
worth remembering. We have had quite a few instances of it,<br />
haventt we, in the last twelve months*<br />
Again, the Labour Party knows that on matters of<br />
foreign policy, matters of our relationship with the United States<br />
of America a very vital relationship because America is our<br />
ally in this part of the world that on all these problems of<br />
defence on which they now profess to be having second thoughts,<br />
on all of these matters they are extremely vulnerable, and they<br />
are vulnerable because they are ambiguous. Do you know what side<br />
they are on in these matters? You take a simple illustration:<br />
Do they really believe in Malaysia? Just up to our North, lying<br />
there in the path of southward Communist aggression, the<br />
expanding and aggressive activities of China; do you know what<br />
their attitude is? Do they really believe in Malaysia? Do they<br />
believe in it sufficiently to support it? Would they be willing<br />
to carry out the undertaking thiat I have given publicly that if<br />
Malaysia is attacked, then we will join with Great Britain in<br />
helping to defend her? Is that something on which you feel you </p>
<p>-3<br />
clearly understand what they have in mind? Because I don't.<br />
I know they've said, " We support the concept of Malaysia." Yes,<br />
well, that's right. I may support the concept of a neutral<br />
Sweden. I may support all sorts of concepts around the world,<br />
but the real problem is what are we going to do about it.'<br />
That's the thing, and that is where you are entitled to ask<br />
any any Government where it stands and what it will do. Well,<br />
of course, the reason for the ambiguity that they suffer from<br />
is quite clear. You just remember that it's only a little while<br />
ago that their outside authorities told them that their policy<br />
was to withdraw Australian troops from Malaya, to say nothing of<br />
Malaysia, They have now gone through the form of abandoning<br />
that, so it said, and yet the President of the A. L. P. only the<br />
other day went on public record as saying that that was still<br />
their policy that Malaysians didn't want Australians in and<br />
Australians Aidn't want to be there.<br />
Now, nobody talks lightheartedly about the possibilities<br />
of hostilities but, believe me this country needs over the<br />
next three years a Government that knouswhere it stand-~ that<br />
can speak with authority and can act with authority onlahalf<br />
of Australia. Other countrie3 are entitled to know where we<br />
stand and what we mean to do, and that's fair enough. Therefore,<br />
we must have an election. No Government with a precarious<br />
majority of one can speak with power and authority for our<br />
nation in all these difficult matters that now surround us. And<br />
therefore there's an election. You will decide it. All I can<br />
say is and this is, I think, a rather magnanimous statement<br />
for a politician to make if you are going to put us out well<br />
see that our opponents, whoever they may be and however they<br />
may be controlled, get a real majority and can speak for<br />
Australia and if you are going to save us in office, if you are<br />
going to affirm your belief that we are the most competent<br />
people to speak for Australia in these matters then give us<br />
a decent majority. Let us be able to speak with a plain voice.<br />
You see, the overriding interest in all this matter is the<br />
welfare of Australiao If the electors you, and all your<br />
friends will have that consideration in mind to the exclusion<br />
of all others, then the election will be admirably justified<br />
and if I may say so, I think the result might well turn out<br />
to te pretty satisfactory for you, and of course in a small way,<br />
for me, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
