<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1601</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO US, CANADA &amp; U.K. - MONTREAL, CANADA - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT IN MONTREAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001601.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2 4 JUL 1967<br />
VISIT TO US, Cl: W. U. K. WIBRAW<br />
MOTrW. L, C ' DA<br />
*' RESS COFFERECE JIVEI jy THE RIME IISTER, MI.<br />
IH{ iOLD HOLT Ii MONTT;. L 6TH JUND, 1967.<br />
May I je seated? I think this will work better if I<br />
do, Ladies and gentlemen, I first thank Sir V: lston Hancock for<br />
introducing me to the press of Zxno. I do-; int to sn-y ho,. re tly<br />
my own country has annreciated the opportunity of Jeing represented<br />
at Expo, and ho.; proud I am, as the head of the Government, having<br />
had an opportunity of seeing . ustr lin's Pavilion and having hid.<br />
in opportunity of seoin. tho various exhibits, the lay-out and the<br />
eneral construction, that we should have a Pavilion which I believe<br />
ittingly expresses our national sentiment and some of the more<br />
prominent features of our national life. Perha-s, before saying<br />
a little more in detail about that I should acknowledge the<br />
tremendous satisfaction I have felt in what I have seen of Expo<br />
67 generally. It is fitting at a time when man is demonstrating again<br />
only too tragically thAt he can destroy the things that he has<br />
built to find here in this Exposition a demonstration that man<br />
can also innovate and construct and take vision for the future.<br />
It has been something of an inspiration, certainly a tonic in these<br />
sombre days, to have had the opportunity to see Exno 67 in being,<br />
to have gone over some of the Iavilions that of Canada of Cuebec<br />
of Great Iritain in addition to that of my own country Australia<br />
and I am sure that the inspiration and stimulus that has come to<br />
me from the visits to the other Pavilions would be repeated if<br />
only one could have wandered and studied more intensively throughout<br />
this Exposition. My wife said it has almost a spiritual quality<br />
about it. ell, I don't know whether it is spiritual or whether<br />
it has its own mystic, out certainly there is a snirit about Expo<br />
67 which is encouraging, stimulating and even inspiring. One thing<br />
which has imnressed us is that it does not seek to be, so far as we<br />
can gather, a sort of money-making enterprise.<br />
I have an impression of our own Pavilion with me of a<br />
well-constructed, even imainatively conceived Pavilion, with a<br />
quiet restful dignity about it which answers the various phases<br />
of Australian life which are reproduced I think, so arrestingly<br />
in the Pavilion. I would like to take this puolic opportunity of<br />
con ratulating any of the architects and tiose who were concerned<br />
with the interior decor and Sir Valston Hancock and his staff for<br />
helping to make the Australian Pavilion the success which I believe,<br />
the figures of attendance demonstrate it to be. You may have already<br />
been told that the anticipated attendance has been multiplied about<br />
fourfold over the period of the Exposition, and this is at the one<br />
time not only a mark of the success of Expo 67 itself but a mark<br />
also of the attraction which the Australian " avilion hAs held for<br />
those who have visited the Exposition.<br />
So my congratulations on oehalf of my Government and people<br />
to all who had a hand in the Australian contribution. Just as<br />
fittingly one's congratulations must : o to Mrr. Duuy and all<br />
associated with him, and to the city o Montreal for having had the<br />
courage and the enterprise to take those amoitious projects, and<br />
to make such a successful achievement of it. tell, that is all.<br />
I wish to say thank you, Ladies and Gentlemen. If there is any<br />
query which I can conveniently cope with, I shall do my best. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Mr. Prime Minister you said in Ottawa, yesterday, that<br />
you envisage a reater role for Canada in Asia, in the po icy<br />
making in Asia. I wonder just what you mean by this? And why<br />
you would see Canada in such a role?<br />
P. M. i', ell, I will de. tl first with the situation as I see it,<br />
and I am projecting my mind not into the short term but into a<br />
much longer period ahead. Jy the end of this century the nopulation<br />
of both Canada and A'ustra. lia should have doubled. already ve have<br />
a significance in international trade and, I believe, in international<br />
affairs out of all proportion to our numbers.<br />
I can't say what the gross national nroduct is of Canada.<br />
I know it is a go d deal higher than that of my own country. Dut,<br />
just to illustrate what I me-in from the situation as I know it.<br />
India has 42 times our population but only double the value of<br />
our gross national nroduct. Indonesia, our nearest neighbour<br />
to the Iorth of Australia, has nine times our ponulation but<br />
only one third of the value of our . ros national nroduct.<br />
ith two countries such as . ustralia and Canada which already have<br />
had a long association through the Commonwealth of Nations and,<br />
with less frequent meetings, inside the Cononwealth and with<br />
a community of interest in other directions in international trade,<br />
in a progressing world of peace I believe that it is important we<br />
should be closer together and get to know each other more closely<br />
than we have been accustomed to do through our occasional meetings<br />
in London. ; e should be encouraging more of our people to visit<br />
each other's country now. '. hat has this to do Twith the Pacific?<br />
You ha-pen to have not only a burgeonin economy but a Pacific<br />
border and an outlook ; estward from 3ritish Columbia and indeed<br />
from the whole nation.<br />
I am sure, your own leader indeed the Prime Minister has<br />
publicly recognized, that where in the past most of the orientation<br />
from Canada has been towards the iorth Atlantic or Korth America,<br />
in the years ahead they have to an increasing degree ( not supplanting<br />
of course the interest you have in these areas I have mentioned), but<br />
to an increasing degree growing trade interest, perhaps a growing<br />
political interest in the affairs of the Pacific. ' ie have a vision<br />
in Australia of a growing Asia, growing in economic, social and<br />
political strength uhere communism can ; e urought in check as it<br />
has in so many of the countries of Asia.<br />
trade with. ei shiaav e osr eethne recmoaurnktaroielse Eeacsotn omoif c Sgurezo wthhas. mo! vMye do wnf rocmo untry's<br />
in 1950 to 40% at this time. Japan just to name one country<br />
trading with us, has surnamsed the inited Kingdom as the biggest<br />
purchaser of Australian goods, and I think Canadians are sufficiently<br />
keen traders. Once they find that this has been going on in an<br />
area to which they look from their ;. estern borders, they will not<br />
be slow to ta. ke up the opportunity which will come their way out there<br />
in a growing Asian economy.<br />
Q. 1Mr. Prime Minister, is Austrtlia and Canada to have a<br />
continuing policy of immigr'ation?<br />
P. M. '. ell, when you say continuing, it has never really had an<br />
all-white policy of immigration. There has always been room inside<br />
the Australian lmmigration policy for the admi. sion of people of<br />
known European races for specified purposes. I find a good deal<br />
of misunderstanding, particularly in this part of the world, far<br />
more misunderstanding than one finds in the countries of Asia<br />
themselves. In fact it might interest you to know that in all my<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
visits to the countries of Asia I have never Jeen asked a question<br />
on that immigration policy by the representative of any asian<br />
jovernment because I know in their own visits to Australia no<br />
discrimination is shown against them.<br />
There are at the present time 12,000 students from Asia<br />
in our colleges and in our universities. Since the Second orld<br />
ar more than 50, v000 neole from thee countries have come to Australia,<br />
who had not oeen eligi4bl to enter Australia under the regulation<br />
or rule of immigration which previously applied. . any thousands<br />
of them have taken out full naturalizatiohas australian citizens;<br />
many Asian men and women ma: rry in Australia and immediately take<br />
ustralian citizenship a5 a matter virtually of right. The children,<br />
of course, are australian citizens, out the peoDle of Asia would not<br />
want us to * ive encouragement to those who .0 through the universities<br />
and the colleges, to stay in rermanent residence in Australia. They<br />
want them to ; o back and help them in the development of their own<br />
country. Youfind slokesmen-for tynical Asian countries such as<br />
Tunku bdul . aman of Malaysis, puulicly amending policy, recognizing<br />
the value of a secure sta'ble and r l:. vely homogeneous . ustralia<br />
for the other countries of the region.<br />
C. Mr. Prime iinister, how does your . overnment view the<br />
events of the past 48 hours in the Middle East?<br />
P. M. ' ell we have made official statements on this matter. My<br />
colleague the Denuty Prime Minister, Mr. J. McEwen, with whom I<br />
was in contact, nut out an official statement from the Government<br />
yesterday. * e of course, in company with most of the other people<br />
around the world, deplore those tragic events, and hope that an<br />
effective action can . je speedily taken which will bring an end to<br />
the fighting. , e would hope that this could ue achieved under the auspices<br />
of the United Nations, and I myself would feel that all the major<br />
powers as far as I can discover, are anxious to see the fighting<br />
brou hi to an end, This could be a test of the effectiveness of<br />
the Security Council, : articularlv the permanent members of the<br />
Security Council, and of the United Nations in dealing with a<br />
situa tion in which all the senior members of the Security Council<br />
wish to see the fighting brought to an end.<br />
My own country, of course, has only a relatively insignificant<br />
Dart to play in these events, but we have a reat interest, first in<br />
the cause of peace because peace to us enables us to go on with the<br />
task of development of a great continent, and because peace is<br />
precious in itself. But we also have, as one of the twelve top<br />
trading nations of the world an interest in seeing that the<br />
international waterways are kept free for trade sr. the traffic<br />
of the peaceful and free world. So we are concerned on these<br />
counts to see an early restoration of peaceful conditions in the<br />
area. Q. Sir, if the U. U. force should have to be recruited to<br />
keep the peace there, would Australia particiTate?<br />
P. M. ; ell, you have raised an hypothetical question, and it<br />
is not customary to state Government' policies on hvnothetic. l issues.<br />
But Australia is a rood member of the-United Natiohs. , e have<br />
constantly supported it. ' e supported the action which was taken<br />
in Korea as United Nations action. e have financially supported / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
peace keeping efforts in various directions. ' 7e have policemen in<br />
Cyprus at this moment as part of the United Nations grip there.<br />
ut I mention that as evidence of our record of loyalty to the<br />
United Nations support of foreign decisicns. But I am not committing<br />
my country in : dvance in any course of action until I know what is<br />
proposed to it.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, especially in view of your reference<br />
to Australia's importance as a trading power, and in view of what<br />
happened in the Suez Canal namely tuat the Canal has been closed so<br />
we Rear at least would ou agree with Foreign Secretary Jrown<br />
of the United Kingdom that that is an illegal act, or would you say<br />
in any case it's an act which will seriously jeopardize Australia's<br />
interests? P. M. ell, what I would like to know first before I make any<br />
definite comments would be the facts of the situation As I ha<br />
the news item this morning, the claim has been made th-t the Canal<br />
was closed in order to keen it secure and to protect it against bombing<br />
which could ue dama. in both to the shipping and to the Canal as a<br />
waterway. Now if that were so one might take a different view of<br />
events th. n if it i,: ere simply closed in order to prevent free movement<br />
of shipping, so I would not wish to indicate an attitude of mind<br />
without being fully in possession of the facts that I haven't at the<br />
present time. Thank you. -A </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
