<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16871</transcript-id>
    <title>Challenging Australia&#039;s young people for fresh ideas. Joint media release with the Minister for Youth, Kate Ellis   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd and Minister for Youth Kate Ellis today launched a new national competition to stimulate fresh ideas about how young people can connect with their communities.</p>
<p>The annual Prime Minister's Australian Youth Forum Challenge will start next year.</p>
<p>Young Australians will be asked to propose projects that get young people engaged in their community and actively addressing local needs. The ideas will need to be sustainable and to link in with wider support, organisations and local businesses.</p>
<p>A panel of young people, youth workers and industry experts will shortlist the best ideas, with the Prime Minster and Minister Ellis choosing the ultimate winners.</p>
<p>Winners will be eligible for up to $15 000 to put their ideas into action.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Challenge supports the Government's vision for all young people to grow up safe, healthy, happy and resilient.</p>
<p>Entrants will be encouraged to put forward ideas that give young people the skills and experience they need to learn, work, engage in community life and be a part of decision-making that affects them.</p>
<p>This announcement comes as Prime Minister Rudd and Minister Ellis today launched the National Conversation - a nationwide discussion with young people as part of the creation of the National Strategy for Young Australians.</p>
<p>The Office for Youth will call for proposals for the Prime Minister's AYF Challenge in early 2010.</p>
<p>More information can be found at <a href="http://www.youth.gov.au/ayf">www.youth.gov.au/ayf</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
