<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8840</transcript-id>
    <title>SOME FACTS THAT DR HEWSON DOESN&#039;T WANT YOU TO KNOW</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008840.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS<br />
SENATOR PETER COOK<br />
HOWARDS WAY THE<br />
John Howard admitted on ABC's AM this morning that he is<br />
prepared to ride roughshod over workers covered by State,,<br />
awards by using the Corporations power of the Constitton.<br />
State awards cover 57.3% of the Queensland workforCe 48.8% in<br />
NSW, 47.8% in SA, 57.3% in WA and 45.6% in Tasman~ ia.<br />
Being covered by a State award offers no security for workers<br />
in these States. Il<br />
All these workers are under threat by' 4he John Howard system<br />
of individual work contracts.<br />
Some 40% of workers in Victoria hve had their awards<br />
abolished already under JeffzKennett. This experience will<br />
spread across the nation if" 3ohn Howard is in control.<br />
If the States don't agreie to accept his policy, Mr Howard<br />
admitted this morning/-that the Opposition is prepared to act<br />
without the co-oper tion of the States to implement his<br />
policy. He said:<br />
" even if e had to act unilaterally in defiance of the<br />
States; ( our legislation) would reach about 70% of<br />
priva sector employees in Australia."<br />
Mr Howar s admission came in the face of criticism of the<br />
Opposit on's industrial relations policy by Sir Richard Kirby,<br />
forme head of the Industrial Relations Commission who<br />
con d h Opstion's policy as a recipe for the<br />
exp oitation of workers.<br />
Sir Richard on ABC's AM this morning said:<br />
" Let's assume for the moment that the employer, a<br />
particular employer, relying on the fact that there are<br />
thousands of people, million people out of employment,<br />
could say I'm leaving those provisions out and if you<br />
don't sign the contract you're sacked because I can get<br />
many out those million people to come in and take your<br />
place.... That I think would be a very deplorable<br />
thing."<br />
Contact: Don Mackay 06 27732043/ 93 11 March 1993<br />
" 7 1 A ( I a<br />
-4<br />
tZ, 7, PRIME MINJISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MIP<br />
SOME FAiCTS THAT DR HEWSON DOESN'T WANT YOU TO KNOW<br />
' MTe economy grew by 2 1/ 2 per ccnt over the past year, the highest in the OECD.<br />
n growth is set to accelerate and sec. unemployment decline. Consensus Economics, a<br />
London-based firm that surveys prominent economists around the world, predicts that the<br />
Australian economy will grow by 3.2 per cent this year and 3.7 per cent in 1994. Access<br />
Economics forecast growth of 4% in 1993-94 under existing policies. They forecast the<br />
unemploymient rate to fall to 10% next year and down to around 8% within three years.<br />
* There are increasing signs that growth is accelerating. Retail trade is up. private investment<br />
grew strongly in the December quarter. Building commencements are 15% higher than a year<br />
earlier.<br />
* Moreover, there are increasing signs that the labour-marke is set to expand. ABS, ANZ, CES<br />
and DEFT vacancies are all increasing, some quite quickly. Overtime is up. The DEFT<br />
leading indicator of employment again rose strongly in January. Unemployment tends to lag<br />
these indicators and thus will improve in the next few months.<br />
* In addition, conditions are right for a strong, sustained lift in investment and jobs.<br />
* Inflation over the past year is 0.3% the lowest in the world.<br />
Interest rates have fallen by over 12% and are now at their lowest levels for two decades.<br />
Productivity has increased by almost 3% over the past year.<br />
Our international competitiveness has improved by 25% since 1983.<br />
There are now 735 enterprise agreements covering almost 1/ 3 of all employees under federal<br />
awards.<br />
* Industrial disputes have fallen by 60% undcr the Labor govemnment and now are below the<br />
OECD average, a feat never achievcd under past Liberal governments. </p>
<p>Australia has the third lowest ratio of tax revenue to GDP among all OECD countries, down<br />
from sixth lowest in 1985.<br />
We have one of the lowes -t Government debt levels in the world. Our gross government debt<br />
as a ratio of GDP is below chat of every other OECD country, and is less than half chat of the<br />
G7 major economies and the OECD average.<br />
ving standards, as measured by real household disposable income, have risen by 28.3%<br />
since the March quarter 1983.<br />
* Australia's foreign-debt is entirely due to the private sector, State Governments and<br />
Government Business Enterprises. The Commonwealth Government has borrowed S18<br />
billion overseas but has more than $ 20 billion in foreign reserve assets in other words, we<br />
are a net lender to the rest of the world.<br />
The Research Effort<br />
As a nation we are devoting many more~ tcsources to research and development. Australian<br />
businesses have more than doubled their research and development over the past decade in<br />
real terms.<br />
The Government has increased its funding by 39% and is encouraging a further change in<br />
culture through measures such as the 150% tax concession and the funding of the 52<br />
cooperative research centres. with 10 more in prospect.<br />
As a result. over the past decade we've had the fastest growth in the OECD in both business<br />
research and development expenditure and external patent applications.<br />
tndustr and ExoRts<br />
* Australian export occupy about one third of the world fast ferry market. Government will<br />
extend the shipbuilding bounty whilst the Coalition will end it.<br />
* Cochlear holds nearly 90% of the world's bionic ear implant market.<br />
* Uncle Toby's is the number one name in health food snacks in Singapore.<br />
* We're exporting over Si 1.2 billion in cars and automotive components. Australian firms<br />
supply catalytic converters for Rover in the UKC, leather seating upholstery to BMW and<br />
springs to Mercedes Benz cars. An Australian firm is designing, developing and<br />
manufacturing instrument clusters for Mercedes.<br />
* Exports of IT and Telecommunications equipment are around $ 2 billion. Digital Equipment<br />
Corporation is exporting S240 million and $ 72 million into research and development.<br />
* Exports of pharmaceuticals have risen from almost zero from five years ago to over $ 1/ 2<br />
billion this year and probably S2 billion bi' the end of the decade. ( Peter Roberts, APR<br />
11/ 3/ 1993)<br />
7142 * in aerospace, Lockhart and Preston are winning major contracts for overseas airports.<br />
* Transfield and SN{ EC have landed a S1 billion contract to build and operate a hydro-electric<br />
power station in Laos.<br />
* Quality and productivity performance of Australian industry have improved dramatically in<br />
the last four years. Australian cars have reduced the number of faults per vehicle by 40% anc<br />
many now rival the best in the world. A 1992 survey of Japanese manufacturing investment<br />
in Australia concluded that " within these companies... the concept of quality control has<br />
begun to take root firmly in the minds of factory workers.'<br />
* Of 29 Japanese firms surveyed on their operations in Australia. only one rated labour force<br />
problems as its most important problem in 1992. This compares with eight of 26 Japanese<br />
manufacturing firms in 1988 saying that labour force problems were their major problem.<br />
Stimnml Rfor<br />
* Productivity has more than doubled on the waterfront.<br />
* Crews on Australian ships have been reduced from 28 to below 21, and will fall to 16 over thnext<br />
stage of the reform process.<br />
* A record of over 18 million passengers flew in Australia in 1992 as a result of airfares falling<br />
in nominal terms over the past three years.<br />
Education * In 1982, only three out of every 10 young people finished high school; now. 8 in 10 do.<br />
* The chances now that any young person will finish school and go onto university are Q=<br />
. hizber than when the Liberals were last in office.<br />
* There are actually fewer young people unemployed now than in 1983 110,000 compared<br />
with 158,000. Most young people are in education or training. This is the right response to<br />
the increase in skill level required for entry to employment.<br />
* Under Labor, the number of Australian students attending university has increased by 211,00(<br />
to 530,000. This increase is equivalent to 20 new universities.<br />
* Australia now has one of the world's highest rates of university graduation for young people.<br />
Vocational Training<br />
* Labor has undertaken a fundamental reform of vocational education and training, and<br />
established the Australian National Training Authority, with increased funding of $ 720<br />
million.<br />
* There are 73,100 more TAFE places in 1993 than in 1991. </p>
<p>* Labor has provided special incentives for employers to recruit and train apprentices and<br />
trainees apprentice intakes increased by 54% in the December quarter of 1992, over 8,100<br />
commencements. Trainee intakes have increased by 146% over the 7 months since June<br />
1992 compared with the same period a year before.<br />
LAbour market promrris<br />
* There were 170,000 job vacancies notified to the CES, in the December quarter of 1992, the<br />
highest for any quarter since March 1990.<br />
* 136,000 people were placed in jobs by the CES in the December quarter 1992, the highest<br />
number placed since the June quarter of 1990.-<br />
* Seasonally adjusted CES job vacancies and placements in the month of December 1992 were<br />
the highest for any month since June 1990<br />
upward trends in both indicators have been established for 12 months.<br />
* Job placements for the long-term unemployed rose substantially in the December quarter of<br />
1992 up 175% on the same period in 1991;<br />
37,000 long-term unemployed people were placed in jobs.<br />
* T'here has been a turnaround in the success of labour market programs<br />
in December 1992 the percentage of people in labour market programs who found<br />
a job or entered further education or training was the highest since December 1990<br />
44% of people who participated in a labour market program in 1992 gained<br />
employment or went on to further education.<br />
11 MARCH 1993<br />
CANBERRA<br />
7144 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
