<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7056</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007056.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA B DECEMBER 1986<br />
The Government will tomorrow be recommending to the<br />
Governor-General in Council the appointment of the new Chief<br />
Justice of the High Court to succeed Sir Harry Gibbs and two<br />
other appointments as Justices of the High Court.<br />
The new Chief Justice is to be Sir Anthony Mason, at present<br />
a Justice of the High Court. The other appointees are Mr<br />
Justice John Toohey of the Federal Court of Australia,<br />
Perth, and Ms Mary Gaudron QC, Solicitor-General for New<br />
South Wales, who will be the first woman appointed to the<br />
High Court.<br />
Sir Anthony Mason was appointed to the High Court in 1972<br />
after serving as Judge of the NSW Court of Appeal from 1969<br />
to 1972. Prior to that he was Solicitor-General for the<br />
Commonwealth from 1964 to 1969. Sir Anthony Mason is the<br />
senior Justice on the High Court after Sir Harry Gibbs.<br />
Mr Justice Toohey was appointed to the Federal Court in<br />
Perth in 1977. He is also a Judge of the Supreme Court of<br />
the Northern Territory. He was an Aboriginal Land<br />
Commissioner in the Northern Territory from 1977 to 1982,<br />
and before his appointment to the bench he served in the<br />
Aboriginal Legal Service of Western Australia.<br />
Ms Mary Gaudron has been Solicitor-General for New South<br />
Wales since 1981. She was the first woman appointed to that<br />
position. She was a Deputy President of the Commonwealth<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission from 1974 to 1979,<br />
and Chair of the NSW Legal Services Commission from 1979 to<br />
1980. Her practice as Solicitor-General has included a<br />
number of appearances before the High Court of Australia in<br />
major constitutional and other cases.<br />
The appointments are to take effect on Friday, 6 February<br />
next, the day immediately following on the retirement of the<br />
present Chief Justice, Sir Harry Gibbs. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
