<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7657</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HYDE PAR HOTEL, LONDON, 23 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007657.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRlANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HYDE PARK HOTEL, LONDON, 23<br />
JUNE 1989<br />
E &amp; O0E -PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke have you achieved anything so far on<br />
this trip?<br />
PH: well reading the Press, reading our Australian Press,<br />
you'd doubt it but of course as usual you are wrong. We've<br />
achieved a lot, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: What?<br />
PH: We have achieved I think an enormous increase in<br />
interest in Australia within the business community. T base<br />
that on the fact that I was able to move around yesterday<br />
amongst a lot of business leaders and there is no doubt that<br />
this was rnot a conference yesterday that you often have ok<br />
you meet today, say nice things and exchange platitudes then<br />
off you go and forget it. I mean there is a reality and a<br />
constructiveness, a nitty grittiness about not only the<br />
formal conference sessions but behind the scenes which I<br />
think is going to mean two things an increase in British<br />
investment and joint enterprise interest in Australia and<br />
from the Australian point of view I think an increased<br />
awareness of the opportunities for activities here in Britain<br />
and from Britain as a spring board into the 320 million<br />
market of the post ' 92 Europe. So I think that's very<br />
important. In the area of the political discussions with Mrs<br />
Thatcher we I think were able to get common ground of a<br />
number of issues while still maintaining areas where we are<br />
not at one. We are not at one on the issue of the Antarctic<br />
obviously, but I think I was able to get into the mind of Mrs<br />
Thatcher the reality of our position, what we're about, and<br />
that doesn't mean in any sense that I've made the decision<br />
that I think she's going to change her mind in the near<br />
future. But I think we've established in the mind of Mrs<br />
Thatcher and those around her an understanding of what we're<br />
about and that's a plus. We had a very interesting<br />
discussion for instance on the South Pacific nuclear free<br />
zone and I'm certain that in that area that there is a<br />
clearer understanding of the compatibility of that Treaty </p>
<p>-2-<br />
( PM cont) with the alliance relationships and obligations<br />
that we have and of the very strong case there is for the<br />
adherence to the protocols of that Treaty by Britain in that<br />
such adherence would strengthen the attitude of the Pacific<br />
island nation states towards our general view of the world<br />
and they see a position perhaps somewhat simplistically.<br />
They see the position where the Soviet Union and China have<br />
adhered to the protocols. The rest of the nations haven't<br />
and I think that I have been able to show to Mrs Thatcher and<br />
those around her that this area is one of less stability.<br />
This region is one of less stability than it was in the<br />
beginning of the ' 80s and it is to our interest to have a<br />
greater degree of understanding by these island nations of<br />
our position and that adherence to the protocols would assist<br />
that. Now let me make it clear. I'm not saying again that I<br />
think that Britain is tomorrow going to adhere to the<br />
0 parnodt oac oslesr iobuust cIo dnos ibdeelriaetvieon thofa t outrh e pcohsaintcieosn hoafs thbaeten happening<br />
increased. ITf you look at the question of China I think we<br />
are essentially at one on what we see as the appropriate<br />
approach there. I think there is an acceptance by the<br />
British of the sort of position I outlined and that is and I<br />
repeat it, we are not at length because you know it, but<br />
firstly we have to be unequivocal in our condemnation of<br />
what's happened and of the brutal repression and executions<br />
that are going on and also see if we can adopt a position<br />
which-will ensure as far as possible a continuation of. the<br />
processes of economic reform. Now we understand, I<br />
understand, I'm sure Mrs Thatcher does, that that's a very,<br />
very difficult line that you have to walk and r don't pretend<br />
it's going to be easy but I'm sure that in the interests of<br />
the people of China, the ordinary people of China and the<br />
Interests of the region, that that's the sort of thing we<br />
have to do. so that was a very, very useful discussion.<br />
We've also had useful discussions about the developments in<br />
Sdisarmament processes between the Super Powers and what'* s<br />
Wgoing here in Europe. We've certainly been given a clear<br />
understanding of the perceptions of the British in that area.<br />
Now obviously that doesn'It cover everything. I've been with<br />
you before about the detailed range of issues we've covered.<br />
But I think it is the case that the general relationship<br />
between Britain and Australia is now on a very, very much<br />
more substantial footing. I mean I think you will have<br />
noticed if you had the opportunity of talking to industrial<br />
leaders, political leaders here that the visit has gone very,<br />
very well. There has been a very good reception to the sorts<br />
of things I've had to say both in the speech I made at<br />
Mansion House and in the discussions that we've had. There's<br />
a pretty tough assessment on both sides, understanding<br />
that there are points of difference between us but<br />
understanding that there is a hell of a lot that we can do </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( PM. cont) together to advance the interests of our<br />
individual countries and importantly the interests of the<br />
fundamental values that we share.<br />
JOURNALIST: Looking forward to Washington, are you throwing<br />
in the towel on the EEP?<br />
PM: It's not a question of throwing in the towel. What<br />
you've got to do in your negotiations with any country and<br />
including the United States if you're going to properly<br />
represent the interests of your own, is to make sure that you<br />
do put clearly to the country you're visiting the areas of<br />
concern that you have, including where there are differences<br />
of opinion or differences of interpretation, IVll do that.<br />
I'm not going to allow, as I said just before I left<br />
Australia, I'm not going to allow the issue of the EEP to<br />
dominate the visit or to mar the possibilities of advancing<br />
our interests, our regional interests and global interests,<br />
by just allowing that to dominate the discussions. There are<br />
differences of estimate on this issue, we'll talk about<br />
those. I think the important point to make is that at the<br />
present time and in the immediate future because of the<br />
lessening of world wheat stocks and the movement in prices<br />
in the period immediately ahead, Australia is not going to be<br />
adversely effected to the extent it has been in the past and<br />
that gives us in a sense coincidentally an opportunity to<br />
work with the United States in the period leading to the end<br />
of the Uruguay Round negotiations because we are totally at<br />
one the United States and ourselves in saying that<br />
subsidies, agricultural subsidies, projected over into the<br />
export area are against the interests of the world trading<br />
system. They are committed with us to changing that<br />
position. so the negotiation period takes us up to the end<br />
of 1990 and in that period I don't believe that the EEP is<br />
going to have the sort or adverse effect it has had in the<br />
past. So what we ought to be doing is stating the<br />
differences we have to the extent that they exist about past<br />
impact but using this period where we're not going to be<br />
W significantly adversely effected, to use that period where we<br />
are at one to try and get a position under the negotiating<br />
round of the Uruguay processes the GATT processes to try<br />
and reach agreement to have an elimination of these<br />
processes. That's how immediate and long term permanent<br />
interests are going to be best served.<br />
JOURNALIST: My final question. Could you comment on the<br />
cruel Ablett hoax that's been played on Senator Button? </p>
<p>PM: it has been a matter of extreme sadness for me to see<br />
how this otherwise dynamic, ideas driven Minister of mine has<br />
been reduced sadly to rnot a tearful figure other people<br />
have a monopoly on that sort of position but sadness of the<br />
dimension which I find impossible to convey. But in the end<br />
one realises that he is a man of enormous fortitude, hidden<br />
strength and he is going to survive. I mean I can assure all<br />
our supporters in Australia who I know would be very, very<br />
worried about whether he was just going to throw in the towel<br />
as it were or the whole bloody bed linen, I mean he is not.<br />
Hie's exhibiting great strength but as you would know from the<br />
way he's conducted himself in the internal affairs of the<br />
Labor Party over the years, he's a man who has a very, very<br />
long memory and I would suggest any who've been associated<br />
with this vile as he sees it decision should watch their<br />
backs because the Little General is a man as I say of long<br />
memory and as you will appreciate a capacity to change the<br />
course of events.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
