<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3911</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S CHANNEL 7 BROADCAST - BRISBANE, 4 OCTOBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003911.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIE N] INISTER' S Q{ ANNiJ -7 BRADCAST BRISaANE, 4 CC FOBER 1975<br />
Last week I told you how the Federal and<br />
Liberal leaders had boycotted the Australian Constitutional<br />
Convention in M* elbourne, and on the opening day had held<br />
a press conference on the other side of the road to<br />
release a policy on federalism. Over the last week,<br />
people have come to realise that this policy on federalism<br />
is really a policy on taxation; it is a proposal to<br />
abandon the system of uniform taxation and to introduce<br />
a system of double taxation, of unequal taxes throughout<br />
Australia. It's a proposal to abandon the system of<br />
uniform taxation which was supported by all other<br />
Prime Ministers,. Labor, Chifley, Liberal, Menzies, Holt,<br />
Gorton and McMahon, never criticised by the Liberals<br />
when they were in office, and to go back to the old<br />
pre-war system where there was the Federal income tax<br />
and on top of that a different State income tax in every<br />
State. Now this would be the end of indexation. How<br />
could you index seven different taxes? It would be the<br />
end of the great tax reform which my Government has<br />
introduced in this year's Budget; this great reform which<br />
means that every taxpayer gets a smaller tax bill and<br />
where everybody gets rebates of equal value in the dollar,<br />
whatever his income. The comparison is made with Canada,<br />
and Canada shows what would happen in Australia if we<br />
went back to this double system of taxation. In Canada,<br />
the provinces with the biggest population and the richest<br />
resources pay the smallest provincial income tax;-<br />
on the other hand, the provinces with the smallest<br />
population and witLh the poorest resources, they pay the<br />
highest provincial income tax, and that's what used to<br />
hanpen in Australia; it's what would happen again.<br />
Now ' no wonder that the Liberals are very<br />
up-enthusiastic about it this week. The Premier of<br />
New South Wales, Mr Lewis, has said that no one really<br />
knows what the scheme is all about. The Liberal leader<br />
in Queensland, the Treasurer, Sir Gordon Chalk, has<br />
expressed his reservations about it. A Liberal M. P.<br />
from Queensland, Mr Kevin Cairns, is quite rightly<br />
worried that the scheme would dissadvantage the smaller<br />
States. To quote him: " All Australians with a sense<br />
of equity would ask: Who pays and who gets the benefits?"<br />
Mr Gorton, the for-mer Liberal Prime Minister, points out<br />
that every taxpayer would receive a demand varying in each<br />
State the tax over and above what they would pay in<br />
Federal taxation. And Senator Steele Hall, the last<br />
Liberal Premier off South Australia, has denounced the scheme.<br />
Now not only is this Liberal policy on federalism<br />
a proposal to have double taxation and unequal income<br />
taxation in Australia, it also involves fragmenting the<br />
initiatives my Gcverninent has taken to help local government.<br />
The amount of local government revenues coming from the<br />
Federal Government nas risen during my Government's term<br />
of, office from half of one percent to over six percent.<br />
And these grants are made on the recoimmendations of a<br />
Grants Comassion, an expert body under a Supreme Court IV, </p>
<p>Judge. The Liberals would break up the whole of this scheiie.<br />
They would continue a Federal rants cominission; on top<br />
of that they'd have six separate State grants commissions.<br />
This would be bureaucracy run mad. Now after further<br />
consideration of only one week, Libe-ral confusion on<br />
the subject, I've no doubt that the Australian people<br />
will not tolerate a Liberal policy on federalism which<br />
is really, in blunt terms, a policy to introduce double<br />
taxation in Australia; to have varying State taxes.-<br />
only Canberra would have the one tax, they're the only<br />
people who'd benefit from it and to abandon Federal<br />
assistance for local government. The public will not<br />
tolerate double taxation, unequal taxes, neglected<br />
local government. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
