<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3140</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER;S PRESS CONFERENCE, BANGKOK, I FEBRUARY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003140_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
DEPARTTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWA1G. CABLEGRAM<br />
IN S6 1.15903<br />
FR OM TOD 01.2.74... 2345 LT<br />
AUSTRALIAN EMBASSY TOR 02.2.74... 0501 LT<br />
EA NG KOK 535 UNCLASSIFIED<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE9 BANGKOK, I FEBRUARY 1974.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN:<br />
I HAVE OFTEN SEEN THE PRESS IN NIGHTCLUBS BEFORE BUT THIS IS THE<br />
FIRST TIME I HAVE GIVEN THEM A CONFERENCE IN ONE.<br />
I HAVE HAD SOME HOURS NOW IN CONVERSATIONS WITH YOUR PRIME<br />
MINISTER LAST NIGHT AT THE RECEPTION AND AT THE DINNER AND<br />
ENTERTAINMENT9 AND THIS MORNING WITH HIS AND MY OFFICIALS AT<br />
GOVERNMENT HOUSE.<br />
WE WERE AFLE TO DISCUSS A VERY GREAT NUMBER OF MATTERS IN A MOST<br />
R: NDLY AND FRANK FASHION.<br />
THE LAST TIME WE HAD BEEN TOGETHER WAS IN THIS CITY NINE YEARS<br />
AGO AT A MEETING OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMISSION OF JURISTS.<br />
HE MADE SOME AUSTRALIAN FRIENDS AT THAT TIME IN THE LEGAL AND<br />
ACADEMIC SPHERES WHICH HAVE GIVEN HIM A VERY GREAT INTEREST IN<br />
AUSTRAL IA.<br />
I HAD LOOKED FORWARD VERY MUCH TO MEETING HIM BECAUSE HIS NAME<br />
IS GREATLY HONOURED RIGHT ROUND THE WORLD SINCE HE GOT SUCH OBVIOUS<br />
PUBLIC AND ROYAL APPROVAL ON 14 OCTOBER.<br />
THE RELATIONS BETWEEN THE THAI GOVERNMENJ_ AND THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT, I AM SURE, ON A PERSONAL LEVEL9 AT THE TOP LEVEL, WILL<br />
EE VERY HAPPY AND FRUITFUL INDEED.<br />
THERE ARE TWO PARTICULAR MATERRS WHICH I MIGHT MENTION TO YOU AT<br />
THIS STAGE.<br />
THERE IS THE PROSPECT, IN THE QUITE NEAR FUTURE, OF A CULTURAL<br />
AGREEMENT BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES AND ALSO A TRADE AGREEMENT<br />
RTWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES.<br />
I HAVE MENTIONED THE PRIME MINISTER'S INTEREST IN AUSTRALIA IN<br />
ACADEMIC AND LEGAL MATTERS.<br />
HE IS NATURALLY9 THEREFORE9 VERY MUCH DISPOSED PERSONALLY TOWARDS<br />
A CULTURAL AGREEMENT BETWEEN US.<br />
THE AGREEMENT WILL COVER, AMONG OTHER THINGS9 THE PROVISION OF<br />
FACILITIES BY EACH COUNTRY IN THE OTHER COUNTRY FOR THE CITIZENS OF<br />
EACH TO LEARN THE LANGUAGE OF THE OTHER.<br />
THERE WILL ALSO BE ARRANGEMENTS9 WE EXPECT, FOR EXCHANGING MEN<br />
AND WOMEN OUTSTANDING IN SUCH FIELDS AS MUSIC, RADIO, TELEVISION9<br />
FILMS9 ARTISTIC EXCHANGES AND ALSO IN SPORTING MATTERS.<br />
IN REGARD TO THE TRADE AGREEMENT, OUR OFFICIALS ARE NOW PURSUING<br />
THIS MATTER AT THE OFFICIAL LEVEL.<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER SHOWED HIMSELF VERY MUCH AWARE OF THE<br />
I,' ITIATIVES MY. GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN IN RECENT MONTHS AND IN FACT<br />
U ' 0 THE VERY EVE OF MY DEPARTURE FROM AUSTRALIA, IN PROMOTING<br />
M-' iY'ERS OF TRADE AND, WHERE DESIRED, INVESTMENT, ? RODUCTION OF<br />
TARIFFS OVERALL BY AUSTRALIA, REDUCTION FURTHER BY AUSTRALIA ON<br />
TARIFFS, ON GOODS COMING FROM DEVELOPING COUNTRIES, PROMOTING THE<br />
TRADE COMMISSIONER SERVICE IN THAILAND, THE MAKING AVAILABLE OF<br />
. ACILITIES IN TRADE BY AUSTRALIAN OFFICIALSO<br />
I MENTIONED SOME OF THESE MATTERS IN MY SPEECH AT LUNCH TIME.<br />
. o o 2 </p>
<p>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INVVARD CLEGRAM I. 15903<br />
ASI( LMAE DIES AND GENTLEMEN, ARE THERE ANY QUESTIONS YOU WOULD LIKE TO<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN JOURNALISTS HAVE BEEN AROUND WITH ME AND WILL<br />
CONTINUE TO BE AROUND WITH ME, BUT THIS IS THE FIRST OPPORTUNITY I<br />
KAVE EVER HAD FOR A PRESS CONFERENCE AT THE HANDS OF THAI<br />
JOURNALISTS, OR INTERNATIONAL PRESS STATIONED IN BANGKOK, SO CAN THEY<br />
SrART. IT WOULD HELP ME IF YOU WERE TO LET ME KNOW YOUR NAMES WHICH I<br />
MIGHT NOT CATCH IMMEDIATELY AND YOUR JOURNALS WHICH I HOPE I WOULD.<br />
PRIME MINISTER9 YOU HAVE MADE SEVERAL STATEMENTS ABOUT THE<br />
AMERICAN BASES IN THAILAND.<br />
COULD YOU CLARIFY YOUR POSITION ABOUT IT?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
MORE SIGNIFICANTLY STILL I BELIEVE IS THE FACT THAT THE ROLE OF<br />
THE BASES HAS CHANGED.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT AND BEFORE IT BECAME THE GOVERNMENT, MY PARTY,<br />
HAD HAD VERY GREAT QUALMS ABOUT, NOT ONLY QUALMS9 THE STRONGEST<br />
O3JECTION TO BOMBING BY THE UNITED STATES AIRFORCE.<br />
A GREAT DEAL OF THIS BOMBING TOOK PLACE FROM BASES IN THAILAND.<br />
I FIRST BECAME AWARE OF THIS WHEN I VISITED UDOM IN JUNE OR<br />
J1LY 1965o<br />
AT TH4AT TIME, THERE WAS A FLIGHT OF AUSTRALIAN AIRFORCE FIGHTERS<br />
SATIONED AT UDOM.<br />
AT THAT TIME, I SAW THE RELATIVELY SMALL BEGINNINGS OF THE UNITED<br />
STATES BOMBING OVER NORTH VIETNAM.<br />
MY PARTY HAS ALWAYS HAD THE STRONGEST OBJECTION TO AMERICAN<br />
BOMBING. IT THOUGHT THAT MILITARILY IT WAS INEFFECTIVE.<br />
MORALLY, IT WAS MONSTROUS.<br />
S ' WE REGRETTED THAT THAI AIR BASES WERE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.<br />
THEY NO LONGER ARE AND I AM SATISFIED THERE COULD BE NO<br />
RESUMPTION OF AMERICAN BOMBING IN THIS PART OF THE WORLD.<br />
THERE IS A NEW SITUATION THEREFORE.<br />
Q. COULD YOU PLEASE TELL US WHAT USE AUSTRALIA NOW SEES IN SEATO?<br />
( UNCLEAR)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
WE HAVE NO OBJECTION TO THE MANILA TREATY.<br />
I WISH PEOPLE WOULD READ THE PREAMBLE TO THE MANILA TREATY.<br />
IT EXPRESSES VIEWS AND PRINCIPLES WHICH WERE AND STILL ARE<br />
VALID. SUCH MATTERS AS ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AND SOCIAL JUSTICE.<br />
THE MANILA TREATY IS SOUNDTHE<br />
SEATO -ORGANISATION EMPHASISED AN ASPECT WHICH NO LONGER IS<br />
REL EV A NT.<br />
.0.3 </p>
<p>DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWARD CAK3LEUGRAM 1. 15903<br />
SEATO AROSE OUT OF THE DULLES POLICY OF MILITARY CONTAINMENT OF<br />
THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA.<br />
THAT DOCTRINE LONG CEASED TO HAVE ANY VALIDITY.<br />
IT WAS -JVEN THE COUP DE GRACE BY DR KISSINGER AND THEN PRESIDENT<br />
NIXON VISIT ING THE CAPITAL OF CHINA.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT CAME TO OFFICE AND THE NEW ZEALAND GOVERNMENT9 AT<br />
THE SAME TIME, RESOLVED TO DISMANTLE THE RESIDUAL ELEMENTS OF THAT<br />
DOCTRINE AS EMBODIED IN SEATO.<br />
WE SPENT SOME MONTHS IN CONSULTING WITH THE SURVIVING MEMBERS OF<br />
THE MANILA TREATY ON THIS ISSUE AND THE RESULT WAS THE NEW<br />
ARRANGEMENTS WHICH WERE MADE IN NEW YORK BETWEEN THE VARIOUS FOREIGN<br />
MINISTERS LAST SEPTEMBER.<br />
NY GOVERNMENT IS CONTENT WITH THE NEW ARRANGEMENTS.<br />
I THINK THEY HAVE BEEN FULLY CONSUMMATED WITHIN THE LAST WEEK.<br />
I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU ABOUT THE THAI STUDENTS THAT ARE GOING TO<br />
AUSTRALIA AND HAVE TO HAVE A TEST IN ENGLISH BECUASE THAI IS NOT<br />
%-ALAYSIAN OR INDONESIAN THEY HAVE TO SPEAK ENGLISH MORE THAN THEIR<br />
Q'JN LANGUAGE9 SO A THAI FINDS IT VERY DIFFICULT TO SPEAK THE ENGLISH<br />
LA ; G UA G E<br />
ALSO9 WHAT IS THE POSITION ABOUT DISCRIMINATION OF A LOT OF THAI<br />
WO. IEN MARRIED TO MEN IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THEY FIND IT A BIT DIFFICULT TO LIVE AMONG THE ' AUSTRALIANS.<br />
HOW WOULD YOU HELP THEM WITH THESE THINGS?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
THERE ARE TWO MATTERS WHICH THE LADY RAISES.<br />
THE SECOND ONE I HAVE NO COMMENT TO OFFER.<br />
I HAVE NO IMPRESSION WHATEVER THAT WHERE A THAI CITIZEN HAS<br />
MARRIED AN AUSTRALIAN CITIZEN THAT THEY HAVE NOT BEEN HAPPY WHETHER<br />
THE' WERE LIVING IN AUSTRALIA OR IN THAILAND.<br />
THERE ARE MANY MARRIAGES OF WHICH I AM AWARE AND THEY HAVE ALL<br />
EZEN VERY HAPPY MARRIAGES.<br />
I WOULD NOT THINK THERE IS ANY DIFFICULTY IN EITHER COUNTRY FOR<br />
THE PARTNERS IN SUCH MARRIAGES.<br />
THE OTHER MATTER ABOUT THE USE OF9 OR THE FAMILIARITY WITH<br />
ENGLISH FOR STUDENTS AT AUSTRALIAN UNIVERSITIES IS A MATTER OF WHICH<br />
I HAVE ONLY BECOME AWARE OF IN THE LAST 24 HOURS.<br />
I HAVE DISCUSSED IT WITH OUR AMBASSADOR HERE AND I HAVE DISCUSSED<br />
IT WITH MR. BEAZLEY9 OUR MINISTER FOR EDUCATION WHO HAS FOR THE<br />
LAST FEW DAYS BEEN ATTENDING SEAMEO9 THE MINISTERIAL MEETING OF<br />
MINISTERS OF EDUCATION IN SOUTH-EAST ASIA WHERE WE AND NEW ZEALAND<br />
WERE ADMITTED FOR THE FIRST TIME AS ASSOCIATE MEMBERS.<br />
SO MR. BEAZLEY IS AWARE OF THIS SITUATION ALSO.<br />
NEXT WEEK9 MR0 GRASSBY9 MY MINISTER FOR IMMIGRATION9 WILL BE<br />
VISI1' ING BANGKOK AND THE AMBASSADOR WILL DISCUSS THIS MATTER WITH<br />
HI l0 S09 I CAN ASSURE YOU THAT MY MINISTER FOR EDUCATION9 MY MINISTER<br />
FOR IMMIGRATION AND 19 MYSELF ARE NOW AWARE OF THIS MATTER9 AND FOR<br />
MYSELF9IT IS ONLY NOW THAT I HAVE BECOME AWARE OF IT.<br />
.00 4 </p>
<p>I) I_ 1ARTMIENT F01F OREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
NWARD CABLEGRAM<br />
4-I. 15903<br />
PERHAPS I CAN HELP IF I MAKE A FEW GENERAL OBSERVATIONS ABOUT IT.<br />
IN ALL EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS IN AUSTRALIA, ENGLISH IS THE ONLY<br />
LANGUAGE OF INSTRUCTION.<br />
AND, AT THE UNIVERSITIES IT IS OBVIOUSLY NECESSARY TO HAVE A<br />
THOROUGH COMMAND OF ENGLISH IF ONE IS TO PROFIT FROM ANY OF THE<br />
COUR SE S.<br />
WE HAVE ABOUT 10,000 STUDENTS FROM OVERSEAS AT AUSTRALIAN<br />
UNIVERSITIES. ABOUT 8,500 OF THESE OVERSEAS UNIVERSITY STUDENTS IN AUSTRALIA<br />
COME FROM HONG KONG OR FROM SINGAPORE OR FROM MALAYSIA AN' IN EACH<br />
CASE NEARLY ALL OF THEM ARE PERSONS OF ETHNIC CHINESE ORIGIN.<br />
IN EACH CASE, HONG KONG, SINGAPORE9 MALAYSIA, THEY ARE<br />
THOROUGHLY FAMILIAR WITH THE USE OF ENGLISH.<br />
AT THIS STAGE9 SECONDARY EDUCATION AND TECHNICAL SECONDARY<br />
EDUCATION SUCH AS PROFESSIONAL AND SCIENTIFIC COURSES AS DISTINCT<br />
FRO1" CULTURAL COURSES AND HELD IN ENGLISHo<br />
ACCORDINGLY, STUDENTS FROM THOSE COUNTRIES ARE ABLE TO<br />
FARTICIPATE IN LECTURES AND SEMINARS AND COURSES AT AUSTRALIAN<br />
UNIVERSITIES WITHOUT ANY DIFFICULTY WHATEVER.<br />
IT IS OBVIOUSLY AND REGRETTABLY MUCH MORE DIFFICULT FOR STUDENTS<br />
erPOM OTHER COUNTRIES9 WHICH DON'T PRIMARILY USE ENGLISH9 TO<br />
FARTICIPATE IN THOSE LECTURES AND SEMINARS AND COURSES.<br />
IT MIGHT NOT MATTER SO MUCH, SAY, IN THE CASE OF INDONESIA<br />
FECAUSE IT IS RARE FOR INDONESIANS TO UNDERGO EDUCATIONAL COURSES<br />
CVERSEAS BEFORE THEY ALREADY HAVE ONE UNIVERSITY DEEREEtuAjND RS<br />
[ 1, LE OFPOICY9 THE INDONESIAN GOVERNMENT ENCOURA DETS T<br />
iHEIR FIRST DEGREE IN INDONESIA AND MAYBE DISCOURAGES THEM<br />
FROM COURSES BEFORE THE UNIVERSITY DEGREE.<br />
THE OTHER ASEAN COUNTRY, THE PHILIPPINES, HASNT LOOKED VERY MUCH<br />
TO AUSTRALIA FOR ADVANCED EDUCATION BUT TO THE UNITED STATES.<br />
I THEREFORE HAVE BECOME AWARE OF THIS PARTICULAR PROBLEM AS<br />
REGARDS THAILAND.<br />
THERE ARE TWO PARTICULAR FEATURES ABOUT THAI EDUCATION WHICH<br />
WOULD DISTINGUISH IT FROM SOME OTHER COUNTRIES IN RESPECT TO OVERSEAS<br />
SF UD IES.<br />
THE FIRST IS THAT THAI STUDENTS WHO HAVE GOT OVERSEAS<br />
QUALIFICATIONS OVERWHELMINGLY GO HOME AFTER THEY HAVE ACQUIRED THOSE<br />
QUAL IFICAT IONS.<br />
THERE IS, THEREFORE, NOT THE DIFFICULTY WHICH IS SOMETIMES<br />
ENCOUNTERED IN RESPECT TO STUDENTS WHO COME FOR UNIVERSITY DEGREES IN<br />
AUSTRALIA OF THEIR NOT WANTING TO GO BACK TO THEIR OWN COUNTRY.<br />
THERE HAS BEEN SOME MISUNDERSTANDING OR EVEN ILL-FELLING BETWEEN<br />
AUSTRALIA AND SINGAPORE ON THIS ISSUE.<br />
SINGAPORE HAS COMPLAINED OF A '' BRAIN DRAIN''.<br />
NOW THIS WOULD NOT APPLY IN THAILAND.<br />
AT LEAST go PER CENT, I AM TOLDO OF THE THAIS WHO OBTAIN OVERSEAS<br />
CUALIFICATIONS GO BACK TO THArLANDø<br />
THAILAND HAS THE VERY GREAT ADVANTAGE OF HAVING HAD9 FOR CENTURIES,<br />
INDEPENDENCE AND IDENTITY.<br />
THE STUDENTS ARE PRIMARILY PATRIOTS WANTING TO GO HOME TO SERVE<br />
TAEIR FELLOW CITIZENS.<br />
0 C </p>
<p>DEPARTMENT'I OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM I. 15903<br />
THE OTHER QUITE UNUSUAL FEATURE ABOUT THAI STUDENTS OUTSIDE THEIR<br />
COUNTRY IS THAT THEY GO AT A MUCH YOUNGER AGE.<br />
SO MANY THAI STUDENTS ARE ENCOURAGED BY THEIR FAMILIES TO GO TO<br />
SCHOOL IN OTHER COUNTRIES, NOT JUST TO GO TO UNIVERSITIES. OR COLLEGES<br />
BUT TO GO TO SCHOOL.<br />
ONE OF THE OBJECTIVES IS TO OBTAIN A WORKING FAMILIARITY WITH<br />
ENGLISH OR OTHER LANGUAGES WHILE THEY ARE STILL YOUNG AND ADAPTABLE.<br />
THERE ARE NOT SO MANY SECONDARY STUDENTS FROM THAILAND IN<br />
AUSTRALIA. THERE HAVE BEEN SOME HUNDREDS, THERE ARE STILL SOi\ E HUNDREDS,<br />
THERE ALWAYS WILL BE I HOPE A VERY GREAT NUMBER OF THAI STUDENTSo<br />
WE WILL HAVE TO LOOK AT THIS ASPECT OF HAVING SECONDARY COURSES<br />
FOR THAI STUDENTS.<br />
NOW THERE ARE SOME TECHNICAL MATTERS ABOUT THE APPLICATION OF<br />
THIS TEST WHICH I WILL HAVE TO LOOK INTO OR WHICH MY MINISTERS WILL<br />
HAVE TO LOOK INTO WHEN THEY GO BACK TO AUSTRALIA.<br />
WE ARE A FEDERAL SYSTEM IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THIS YEAR, THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS ACCEPTED THE COMPLETE<br />
FI . i. CIALR ESPONSIBILITY FOR EVERY UNIVERSITY AND COLLEGE IN<br />
ALL THESE UNIVERSITIES AND COLLEGES HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED<br />
UNDER STATE LAWS, AND IT IS NOT POSSIBLE FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT<br />
TO LAY DOWN THE EDUCATIONAL STANDARDS, TESTS AND SO ON, WHICH APPLY<br />
IN THESE UNIVERSITIES.<br />
WE CAN PERHAPS LEAN ON THEM OR TO USE A TERM THAT I ONCE USED IN<br />
ANOTHER CONNECTION, WE CAN NUDGE THEM, BUT WE CANNOT CONTROL THEMo<br />
IT IS A MATTER WHERE WE CAN USE OUR INFLUENCESo<br />
I AM GLAD YOU RAISED THIS MATTER, I MUST CONFESS I WAS NOT AWARE<br />
OF IT UNTIL I SET OUT ON THIS JOURNEY.<br />
IT IS A MATTER WHERE MY GOVERNMENT WOULD NOT WANT TO SEE THAT<br />
THERE WAS ANY DISADVANTAGE FOR THAI STUDENTS AS AGAINST ANY OTHER<br />
OJERSEAS STUDENTS IN AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS OR UNIVERSITIES.<br />
Qo<br />
THERE HAS BEEN AN INCREASE IN COMMUNIST ACTIVITIES IN NORTH-EAST<br />
'-AILAND IN THE PAST TWO OR THREE MONTHS.<br />
WITH REGARD TO YOUR REMARKS TODAY, I WONDER IF YOU WOULD COMMENT<br />
ON THIS ON THE INCREASE OF COMMUNIST ACTIVITIES IN NORTH-EASTERN<br />
THAILAND? WHAT YOU HAVE LEARNED FROM THE PRIME MINISTER OF THAILAND?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I HAVEN'T DISCUSSED THIS MATTER.<br />
I HAVEN'T RAISED THIS MATTER AND IT HASN'T BEEN RAISED WITH ME,<br />
WE HAVE BEEN LESS THAN A DAY HERE, BUT AT THIS STAGE I HAVE NOT<br />
BEEN INVOLVED IN ANY DISCUSSIONS ON THIS ISSUE.<br />
HAS OUR GOVERNMENT REQUESTED YOU TO ACT AS A MEDIATOR BETWEEN US<br />
AND THE REPUBLIC OF VIETNAM?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
NO.<br />
oo 6 </p>
<p>DPI'A\ RTMFENT 1OFFO REIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWA1RD CABLEGRAM I. 15905<br />
Qo COULD YOU TELL US THE MEANING OF YOUR TRIP TO SOUTH-EAST ASIA<br />
ESPECIALLY IN RELATION TO THE ASEAN NATIONS?<br />
HOW IS AUSTRALIA GCING TO MAKE BETTER RELATIONS WITH ASEAN<br />
TIONS? PRIME MINISTER<br />
I SUPPOSE I CAN GIVE YOU AN ILLUSTRATION FROM THE MATTER THAT<br />
THE LADY NEXT BUT ONE TO YOU RAISED.<br />
S THIS QUESTION OF THE FAMILIARITY WITH ENGLISH WHICH IS REQUIRED<br />
EFORE STUDENTS ARE ADMITTED TO OUR INSTITUTIONS OF HIGHER LEARNING.<br />
THAT WOULD BE A MATTER WHICH I CAN PROMOTE AS A RESULT OF<br />
VISITING ONE OF THE ASEAN NATIONS.<br />
THERE WERE SEVERAL MATTERS IN THE TRADE FIELD WHICH AROSE DURING<br />
MY VISIT TO MALAYSIA.<br />
'-lERE ARE MATTERS AS I MENTIONED IN THE CULTURAL AND TRADE<br />
AGRETMENT FIELD WHICH HAVE COME UP IN THIS VISIT TO THAILAND.<br />
AUSTRALIA'S RELATIONS WITH ALL THE ASEAN NATIONS ARE GOOD.<br />
THEY ARE NOW TAKING PLACE ON A COLLECTIVE BASE ALSO.<br />
IT WAS A COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO9 WASN'T IT, 9 THAT AUSTRALIA WAS<br />
INVITED TO CONFER WITH THE SECRETARY-GENERAL OF ASEAN COLLECTIVELY<br />
ON ASEAN PROJECTS SO WHILE OUR BILATERAL RELATIONS WITH EVERY ASEAN<br />
MNTION HAVE ALWAYS BEEN GOOD, WE ARE NOW DEVELOPING COLLECTIVE<br />
RLATIONS WITH ASEAN NATIONS.<br />
IT WAS ENCOURAGING FOR ME, ON THIS VISIT9 TO HEAR DIRECTLY FROM<br />
PROFESSOR SANYA HOW MUCH THE THAI GOVERNMENT SUPPORTS THE PRINCIPLE<br />
WN:-CH ASEAN ADOPTED ON THE INITIATIVE OF MALAYSIA FOR A ZONE OF PEACE<br />
' PODOMAN D NEUTRALITY IN THE ASEAN AREA GUARANTEED BY THE GREAT<br />
THERE HAVE BEEN SOME SUGGESTIONS THAT THIS WAS A MATTER UPON<br />
VHICH MALAYSIA WAS MORE INTENT THAN THE OTHER ASEAN MEMBERS.<br />
T IS QUITE CLEAR TO ME NOW THAT THAILAND IS ALSO NO LESS INTENT<br />
ON I SO A OSIT LIKE THIS ENABLES ME DIRECTLY AND PROMPTLY TO ACT<br />
ON MATTERS WHICH CONCERN ASEAN NATIONS.<br />
I THINK THIS IS THE GREAT ADVANTAGE OF A VISIT LIKE THIS TO FOUR<br />
OF THEM WHICH I AM MAKING9 AND TO TWO OF THEIR. IMMEDIATE NEIGHBOURS<br />
WHOM THEY WOULD LIKE TO ENROL IN ASEAN.<br />
Qo<br />
ALTHOUGH YOU HAVE STATED PUBLICLY THAT IT WAS NOT WITHIN YOUR<br />
COUNTRY'S INTEREST TO JOIN ASEAN AND THAT YOU LOOK FORWARD TO A<br />
LAPRGER GROUPING9 NAMELY ASEAN9 MY QUESTION IS WHAT HAS BEEN THE<br />
ETiCRT ON THE PART OF YOUR GOVERNMENT IN TRYING TO ESTABLISH A LINK<br />
P2: ATSHE AN, OR CAN WE EXPECT PERHAPS ON A TOKEN BASIS AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
LINK WITH ASEAN IN THE NEAR FUTURE?<br />
YOU WANT AN ASIAN FORUM SPANNING COUNTRIES IN THE PACIFIC TO<br />
INCLUDE ALSO JAPAN AND CHINA BUT WHAT ARE THE CHANCES THAT JAPAN AND<br />
CHINA UON'T DOMINATE IT JAPAN ECONOMICALLY AND CHINA POLITICALLY?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
AUSTRALIAN HASN'T BEEN ASKED TO JOIN ASEAN BY ANY OF ITS MEMBERS<br />
AND AUSTRALIA HASN'T ASKED TO JO, AS..<br />
* a o7 </p>
<p>RTNI'INT OF' FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWARD CABLE GRAM 1. 15903<br />
I WOULD EXPECT THAT THE ASEAN MEMBERS WOULD PROBABLY BELIEVE AND<br />
AUSTRALIA WOULD ACKNOWLEDGE THE FACT THAT THERE ARE9 AT THIS STAGE9<br />
TW'JO DISPARITIES ECONOMICALLY BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND EACH OF THE ASEAN<br />
COUNTRIES OF SUCH SIZE THAT IT WOULD DISTORT THE GENERAL CONCEPT OF<br />
ASEA N.<br />
WE ARE VERY HAPPY AT THE PROGRESS THAT ASEAN HAS MADE BECAUSE IT<br />
IS A NATURAL ASSOCIATION OF CONTIGUOUS NATIONS.<br />
IT IS RELEVANT INCREASINGLY ANTD IT IS GROWING IN COHESION ALL<br />
THE TIME. IT IS SATISFACTORY FOR ASEAN AND ALSO FOR AUSTRALIA THAT WE HAVE<br />
BEEN ASKED TO CONSULT AS I JUST SAID ON ASEAN PROJECTS9 PROJECTS<br />
WHICH ARE PUT UP ON A COLLECTIVE BASIS OR PROJECTS WHICH MIGHT AFFECT<br />
MORE THAN ONE ASEAN COUNTRY.<br />
NOW9 THOSE ARE FRUITFUL ASSOCIATIONS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND<br />
ASEA N.<br />
THERE IS NO NEED TO MAKE THEM MORE FORMAL BY JOINING THE BODY.<br />
ALL THE ASEAN ' ATIONS HAVE HAD ASSOCIATIONS AT ONE TIME OR<br />
ANOTHER WITH REGIONAl.. ORGANISATIONS.<br />
THERE WAS ASA9 THERE WAS MAPHILIND09 THERE WAS SEATO, THERE WAS<br />
ASPAC. ASEAN IS THE ONLY ONE TO WHICH ALL THE PRESENT FIVE MEMBERS HAVE<br />
BEEN ABLE TO ADHERE.<br />
IT IS THE ONLY ONE WHICH HAS A GROWING FUTURE AHEAD OF IT.<br />
THE WHO IDEA OF REGIONAL CO-OPERATION HAS HAD A LOT OF ATTENTION<br />
IN EACH OF THE ASEAN MEMBERS UP TILL NOW9 BUT ASEAN IS THE ONLY ONE<br />
THAT REALLY HAS MOMENTUM.<br />
NOW YOU MENTION THE POSSIBILITY OF DOMINANCE ECONOMICALLY9<br />
PCLITICALLY I DON'T KNOW WHAT OTHER WAY, IF THERE WAS A WIDER<br />
ASSOCIATION IN SAY THE WESTERN PACIFIC OR IN SOUTH-EAST ASIA.<br />
THIS CAN ALWAYS HAPPEN IN ANY ASSOCIATION.<br />
I'LL GIVE AN INSTANCE OF AN ASSOCIATION THE FIRST ONE TO WHICH<br />
AUSTRALIA BELONGS THE COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS9 THE BRITISH<br />
COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS AS SOME PEOPLE MIGHT CALL IT.<br />
NOW IT MIGHT BE THOUGHT THAT IN AN ORGANISATION OF ABOUT 34<br />
RATIONS WHICH VARY IN SIZE FROM INDIA WITH HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF<br />
POPU_ ATION, TO OTHERS WHICH HAVE LESS THAN ONE MILLION POPULATION9<br />
', HERE WOULD BE TOO MUCH DISPARITY THAT ONE NATION WOULD DOMINATE<br />
ANOTHER, THAT COUNTRIES WHICH HAVE A VERY LARGE INCOME PER HEAD OF<br />
PCPLLATION LIKE BRITAIN AND CANADA OR AUSTRALIA OR NEW ZEALAND OR<br />
SIAGAPORE WOULD BE ABLE TO DOMINATE COUNTRIES WHICH HAD A SMALLER<br />
ItjCOME PER HEAD OF POPULATION,<br />
IT DOESN'T HAPPEN.<br />
IT IS VALUABLE FOR ALL OF THEM TO GET TOGETHER AND SEE WHAT THEY,<br />
HAVE IN COMMON.<br />
NOBODY THESE DAYS TALKS OF LEAVING THE COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS.<br />
EVERY COLONY9 ON BECOMING INDEPENDENT9 WANTS TO JOIN IT.<br />
EVERY COUNTRY THAT BECOMES INDEPENDENT WHICH HAS BEEN RULED BY<br />
SRITAIN OR THESE IS ONE THAT H:' S BEEN RULED BY AUSTRALIAq PAPUA NEW<br />
GUINEA9 AS SOON AS THEY ARE IXD3EPENDENT THEY WANT TO JOIN THE UNITE<br />
NATIONS AND THE COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS.<br />
08 </p>
<p>D1I',.\ RTILNF 01: FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
INWARD CAISLEGaAM 1. 15903<br />
THEY ARE NOT WORRIED ABOUT DOMINATION.<br />
THESE ARE NOT SUCH FORMAL BODIES.<br />
THERE MIGHT BE SOME SUCH MISGIVINGS IN THE ORGANISATION OF<br />
AMERICAN STATES WHERE, ON SOME ISSUES, SUCH AS CUBA9 IT MIGHT BE<br />
THOUGHT THE UNITED STATES WANTED TO LEAN TOO HEAVILY ON THE OTHER<br />
CEM B E R S.<br />
IT MIGHT BE SAID SO IN THE ORGANISATION OF AFRICAN UNITY WHERE<br />
YOU CAN GET VERY LARGE STATES, VERY RICH STATES9 LIKE NIGERIA, BUT<br />
THEY DON'T TRY TO DOMINATE AND THEY ARE NOT RESENTED.<br />
THERE ARE NO ALLEGATIONS THAT THEY ARE DOMINATING.<br />
I DON'T BELIEVE THAT ONE OUGHT TO BE NEGATIVE IN THESE RESPECTS0<br />
IT IS ONLY BY REGULARLY AND INFORMALLY CONSULTING THAT WE REALLY<br />
GT TO UNDERSTAND EACH OTHER.<br />
IF WE HAVE BILATERAL VISITS, EVEN SUCH FAIRLY RELAXED ONES SUCH<br />
AS THE ONE I AM ENGAGED IN AT THE MOMENT9 IT STILL LIMITS THE<br />
OPPORTUNITIES THAT ONE WOULD LIKE TO HAVE BECAUSE YOU JUST CAN'T<br />
MAKE VISITS AS OFTEN AS YOU WOULD LIKE.<br />
BUT YOU CAN ALL PUT TIME ASIDE, ALL FOREIGN MINISTERS, OR HEADS<br />
OF GOVERNMENT, CAN PUT TIME ASIDE ONCE EVERY YEAR OR TWO YEARS TO GET<br />
TOGETHER IN BODIES SUCH AS THE COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS0<br />
AND9 I THINK THAT IN DUE COURSE WHEN, FOR INSTANCE9 THERE IS THE<br />
ZONE OF PEACE9 FREEDOM AND NEUTRALITY, THIS WOULD MAKE A WIDER<br />
ASSOCIATION VERY MUCH EASIER.<br />
THERE ARE SOME OTHER SUCH ASPECTS SUCH AS THE DIFFERENCE IN<br />
ATTTUDE TOWARDS CHINA.<br />
EVERYBODY HAS TO RECOGNISE EITHER TAIPEI OR PEKING AS BEING THE<br />
SAT OF GOVERNMENT OF CHINA.<br />
NOBODY, BUT NOBODY, CAN RECOGNISE BOTH GOVERNMENTS.<br />
EACH GOVERNMENT INSISTS THAT YOU RECOGNISE IT AND DISREGARD THE<br />
OTHERO NOW9 WE HAVE MADE OUR DECISION IN THIS MATTER9 BUT WE DON'T<br />
C'ERLOOK THE FACT THAT IT IS MORE DIFFICULT FOR OTHER NATIONS WHICH<br />
MAY HAVE A LONGER HISTORICAL INVOLVEMENT.<br />
0. REGARDING CHINA.<br />
ONE OF THE IMAGES OF AUSTRALIA/ THAI DIPLOMACY WAS IN A STATEMENT<br />
YOU MADE LAST YEAR SAYING THAT THAILAND SHOULD RECOGNISE MAINLAND<br />
CHI NA. DO YOU SEE ANY CHANGE IN THAI DIPLOMACY ON THIS?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I DON'T REMEMBER EVER MAKING A STATEMENT THAT THAILAND9<br />
INDIVIDUALLY9 SHOULD RECOGNISE CHINA BY WHICH I WOULD REGARD<br />
IT AS INEVITABLE THAT SOONER OR LATER ALL THE ASEAN NATIONS SHOULD<br />
AVE NORMAL DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH PEKING AS THE SEAT OF THE<br />
GOVERNMENT OF CHINA.<br />
I WOULD THINK THAT IS iNEVITABLEO<br />
I DON'T THINK ANYBODY WOULD DISPUTE THAT IT IS INEVITABLE BUT IT<br />
IS NOT FOR ME TO MAKE THE DECISION0<br />
AFTER ALL, ASEAN IS NOT IN AGREEMENT AMONG ITS OWN MEMBERS ON TH$<br />
ISSUE0 INDONESIA HAS NEVER SAID THAT GENERALISSIMO CHIANG KAI-SHEK WAS<br />
THE PRESIDENT OF CHINAø<br />
9 </p>
<p>DE1.' ART.\ lE\ T F01F OREIGN \ FFAIRS<br />
iNWARD CAB LEGRAM 1. 15903<br />
TWO OTHER ASEAN NATIONS STILL SAY THAT HE IS.<br />
TtOO OTHERS HAVE NEVER SAID WHO WAS THE PRESIDENT OF CHINA.<br />
SO, IT SHOULDN'T BE NECESSARY TO POINT OUT THAT WE ARE IN A<br />
COMPLETELY NEW BALL GAME SINCE THE 1TH OF OCTOBER.<br />
EVEN BEFORE THAT DATE, THERE WERE CONTACTS BETWEEN BANGKOK AND<br />
PEKING. THEY HAVE CONTINUED.<br />
I BELIEVE THAT THEY ARE LIKELY TO PROVE PRODUCTIVE BUT CAN SEE<br />
T-ERE ARE MORE DIFFICULTIES IN REGARD TO RELATIONS BETWEEN BANGKOK<br />
AND PEKING THAN THERE ARE IN RELATIONS BETlWEEN CANBERRA AND PEKING.<br />
ALL THAT WE HAD TO DO IN CANBERRA WAS TO SAY WHAT I SAID IN MY<br />
PROGRAM FOR THE ELECTIONS 14 MONTHS AGO9 THAT WE WOULD MOVE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S EMBASSY FROM TAIPEI TO PEKING.<br />
WE HAD AN AMBASSADOR TO CHINA,<br />
WE ACCREDITED HIM TO PRESIDENT CHIANG KAI-SHEK.<br />
UHEN WE CAME IN9 WE DISCONTINUED THAT ACCREDITATION.<br />
WE SOUGHT AND WE QUICKLY GAINED ACCREDITATION TO THE CHINESE<br />
CDVERNMENT IN PEKING.<br />
iT WAS RELATIVELY EASY FOR US.<br />
WE ARE MORE DISTANT AND OUR ASSOCIATION IS SIMPLER.<br />
Qo<br />
WHAT IS YOUR ATTITUDE TOWARDS THE SOVIET PRESENCE IN THE INDIAN<br />
CCEANq AND IF YOU HAVE CONSIDERED IT, HOW DO YOU EXPECT TO HANDLE IT?<br />
BRIT-SAID THE DAY BEFORE YESTERDAY THAT CONFRONTATION BETWEEN<br />
THE SUPER POWERS IN THE INDIAN OCEAN HAS TO COME9 THAT CEYLON'S AND<br />
INDIA'S ATTITUDE OF A PEACEFUL INDIAN OCEAN IS UNREALISTIC..( UNCLEAR)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SWELLq I WON"? COMMENT ON WHAT THE LADY HAD TO SAY.<br />
WE ARE ON THE INDIAN OCEAN IN AUSTRALIA AS WELL AS ON THE<br />
PACIFIC OCEAN.<br />
I HAVE NOT LOOKED AT THIS MATTER ON THIS VISIT.<br />
I HAVE NO COMMENTS I WANT TO MAKE ON THIS VISIT9 BUT I DO NOT<br />
WANT TO SPEAK IN THESE MATTERS IN TERMS OF THREATS AND SO ON.<br />
THE FACT IS THAT SOME NATIONS HAVE QUITE LARGE NAVIES0<br />
AS THE LAW OF THE SEA STANDS AT THE MOMENT9 THEY CAN SAIL THE<br />
HIGH SEAS.<br />
I WOULD NOT LIKE THE INDIAN OCEAN TO BECOME A SCENE OF<br />
CONFRONTATION AS SAY THE MEDITERRANEAN HAS.<br />
I BELIEVE WE WOULD HAVE THE SUPPORT OF MOST OF THE COUNTRIES IN<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS9 SO MANY OF WHICH LIE WITHIN AND AROUND<br />
THE INDIAN OCEAN.<br />
JUST AS THE AUSTRALIAN GOVER: MENT HAS POSITIVELY SUPPORTED THE<br />
ASEAN INITIATIVE FOR A ZONE OF '; EACEq FREEDOM AND NEUTRALITY9 SO TOO<br />
T" F AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS POSITIVELY SUPPORTED THE SRI LANKAl'<br />
FROPOSAL FOR A NEUTRAL INDIAN OCEAN5 AND AUSTRALIA IS A MEMBER OF<br />
THE COMMITTEE WHICH THE UNITED NATIONS HAS SET UP TO PROMOTE THAT<br />
CO NCE PT.<br />
o. o00 </p>
<p>1) 1 JA RTMr\ E NT 0 F FOR E IG N A FF1A IR S<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM 1. 15903<br />
A/ PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOREIGN MINISTER<br />
FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
MT'N AND DEPT DEFENCE<br />
TREASURER AND TREASURY<br />
J. 1. 0.<br />
A. I S.<br />
MED IA<br />
AID OFFICE<br />
O. JE%-AS TRADE<br />
E CC K3 A Y INDUSTRY<br />
FEM9S PRESS SECRETARY<br />
RF1 A ND C<br />
Fm S N </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
