<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6256</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO National Aboriginal Employment and Development Committee</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006256.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRWIE MINISTER<br />I1 N' V ' mix 3 1<br />The attached speech will be delivered by Mr Basil Atkinson,<br />Chairman of the National Aboriginal Employment and Development<br />Committee to the NAEDC Seminar in Canberra on behalf of<br />the Prime Minister today.<br />EMBARGOED UNTIL 3.30 P. M.</p>
<p>PRiMIE MINISTER<br />I am pleased to participate in this seminar which<br />has been organised by the National Aboriginal Employment and<br />Development Committee to highlight the need for greater<br />numbers of Aborigines to he employed in Commonwealth<br />statutory authorities and departments.<br />My Government is committed to increasing the<br />numbers of Aboriginal people in Commonwea th (; Government<br />employment to a point at least equal to their representation<br />in the community a level generally believed to be between<br />1 and 2 per cent.<br />Numbers, however, are not in themselves enough.<br />Aboriginal people should be at a sufficiently<br />influential level to be able to play a significant part in<br />Aboriginal self-management.<br />Accordingly an Affirmiative Action strat-gy in<br />Commonwealth Government employment i s now being deveoloped.<br />We should be appalled at the continuLng high<br />unemployment rate amongst Aboriginal people this Is<br />estimated to be in excess of 50 per cent.<br />My Government is actively working to try and<br />alleviate the situation.<br />Aboriginal employment in the Australian Public<br />Service today is not as good as it should be, buL is<br />improving. At 1 Orc t c bor 108? 2 here-wor., 804 A!, or i q i n; l tn f* tI<br />in the APS repres( nting only 0.53 per cenL CLl -l-im1 e<br />staff. This is an increase of 13.4 per cent over the<br />previous year.</p>
<p>The figures from the survey of Aboriginal staff<br />conducted in October 1983 are not yet available but chere<br />are indications that the situation is continuing to change<br />for the better. Already this year 261 Aborigines have been placed<br />by the Public Service Board in permanent employment in the<br />APS. In addition there are currently 430 Aborigines who<br />I. v hr-eoi empnio ly l uindir lho' Tria inini for Ahor i( inal;<br />Program in APS.<br />In the next few months at least 200 Aboriginal<br />people are expected to receive jobs in the APS under the<br />Commonwealth Component of the Community Employment Program<br />CEP. If present recruitment trends continue the<br />proportion of Aboriginal staff in the APS, excluding those<br />in temporary training positions, is expected to approach<br />1 per cent by the end of 1984.<br />Although recruitment targets may easily be met<br />overall employment figures will not increase at the same<br />rate unless attention is paid to the induction and training<br />of new recruits to prevent high resignation rates.<br />Neither will the numbers of Aboriginal people in<br />decision making positions increase at a satisfactory rate<br />unless properly structured career development programs are<br />introduced for Aboriginal staff.<br />Over the years the Board, with the support of<br />relevant departments and authorities, has sought to address<br />these aspects. Let me briefly review a number of these<br />initiatives. I Equal Employment Opportunity Officers<br />In 1978 a program to implement a National<br />Employment Strategy for Aboriginals in the Australian Public<br />Service was established.<br />Early next year my Government plans to introduce an<br />Affirmative Action Srategy.<br />Departments ind authlorit i on who have not already<br />.7one so should designate an officer to be responsible for<br />developing and implementing these programs for Aborigines.</p>
<p>2 Aborigin, 1 Services Program<br />The Clerk ( Aboriginal Services) Program was<br />introduced by the Public Service Board in 1981 to meet the<br />Service's continuing demand for staff with a knowledge and<br />understanding of Aboriginal people.<br />At present the Board is undertaking a major<br />nationwide recruitment drive for the 1984 Aboriginal<br />Services intake. Ofticers from the Board have beein visiting<br />departments seeking vacancies for the program.<br />I am told that departments are being very helpful<br />and the Board expects to receive in excess of 200 vacancies<br />for 1984. I urge those departments which have not already<br />offered opportunities to this program to do so.<br />The Board is particularly interested in receiving<br />vacancies from country and isolated offices in areas of high<br />Aboriginal inemployment.<br />All departments however can participate in the<br />program whether or not they provide services directly to<br />Aboriginal communities.<br />3. Lateral Recruitment<br />In previous years the Board has asked departments<br />to identify positions where an ability to communicate with<br />Aborigines or a knowledge and understanding of Aboriginal<br />culture and communities is sean as necessary for the<br />efficient performance of dut: is.<br />The Board has introduced a number of initiatives to<br />try and increase the Aboriginal occupancy rate of these<br />po. i tions. It is now discussing with departments the<br />possibility of running regular nation-wide recruitment<br />programs for identified positions.<br />This should provide a pool of suitable applicants<br />for a number of middle level vacancies.<br />Revised guidciinec are being prepared to assist in<br />lhoe soe oct: n t appl icI ann .; nr i ( ot. i ied posi. tion"; pay ing<br />parti cu] ir al: tenLion i, the wiglhti n of the selection<br />criteria in these positions.<br />The revised guidelies will be issued early in<br />1984.</p>
<p>4. T'nmporarary and Exempt Fmploymen-<br />The employme:) t. of Ahoriginal-, in-temporary arid<br />exempt positions requires particular attention.<br />I would urge all departments employing exempt staff<br />to. ensure that vacancies are made known to Aboriginal people<br />and that Aboriginal applicants a~ re given full con!-; ideration.<br />The Gove rrnimen t wonldt like to 3; ee the numbie r of<br />Ab r i qi naL1 poop l onuipp yodi t 1! x ompti Po l1 i onl" in t1h. 1 at<br />1 ea! 3t double thie 1982 . iguteo tho ond of 1984.<br />Vocational Training<br />The training function is crucial to long--term<br />success. During the five years Auglust 1978 to September<br />1983, 2,295 Aboriginal people have received vocational<br />training in the APS to prepare themn to compete for<br />employment in both the public and private sectors.<br />[ live hunidred of theE; e traines; ( 363 per cent)<br />entered employment at, or shortly after the conclusion of<br />their training periods 161 per cent oL' these were pla ed in<br />APS employment. Additional trainees found emnployment in the next<br />few months in both the private and publ ic sectors.<br />Tra in ing programns ro date have been primarily<br />oriented L* towharaIsi ic on-th,-j ob experienc-e for uinemnployed<br />Aborigines who lacked skii] 3 anid work experience.<br />I n a( 16i t io n to t his 5a se l evel t ra in i. ng, ot he r<br />c h eine:; ha1: 1v e a I so ca tL rk 2d 1: o r A ho r.-i i nes!--wh ) i a-1 rea71( 1y pOS SoS 3<br />skills or who have had somte experience in the workforce and<br />who re-quire enhancemnent or broaden in'j of thiese skills.<br />Opportunities for thos; e requiring enhancement of<br />exisiting skills have however been limnited.<br />Moro opportuLnities -, houl: d he provided for skill<br />enhancement, pirttcularly Cor: Aborigjinal people already<br />employed in Ab: ariginal organisations and enterprises.<br />As well1 add itional procedures for. moni toring of the<br />p ro r o s: 3 of the tra irn.-s Io enrure tha) t-thiy amo receiving<br />u nood qualiAty and CatI I-toot I n r! iin -jg a to nuu(! dccl<br />Guildeties to be cela-asod by the Board earl! in the<br />new year should receive the particular attention off<br />departments and author] ities.</p>
<p>6. The Commonwealth EmploymentPr. gqram<br />The Commonwealth component oft the Commun it y<br />Employment Progra the CEP is prov idirm-ng a uscful chanlnel<br />by which Commonwealth Departments and author ities can employ<br />Abor ig ines. In the next few months at least 200 Aborigines will<br />be employod in departments on CEP projects.<br />Tn i-on a pr xi0 O1y 30 Aho r ifint:: v/ i111 he<br />employed in authoritie! s.<br />A major aim of the CEP is to ensure that women<br />receive an equal share of the jobs created.<br />I am encouraged, therefore, to see that departme nts<br />have not only provided jobs for Aboriginal women but that<br />many of these will result in bonefit to lxborig inal womnin<br />generally. For example 59 aboriginal women are being engaged.,<br />to consult with Aboriginal communities about the necclIs and!<br />views of Aborig inal women on a wido rarige of<br />Information gathered by these C17P participants will<br />be referred to the Government by Lhe T isk F. urc on<br />Aboriginal women, which was set up in my department in July.<br />T uirge Departments and authorities to join in this<br />very worthwhile program and to pay particulur attention to<br />the developm-ient of projects which will offer om,) loymn,-nt for<br />Ahor ig inal pueople.<br />7. Study-haf; edDevelopment Programs<br />-T11a Bo ard has int ro r] uce-i two btat Sd p 0e1-m<br />to assirst the(-caree--r development ol Abor ig ilmal. '; tafE<br />ier e the Ahorigin-il Unejc-at ,~ tudy Award-'<br />Scheme, and the Ahor iginal APS Staff Sponsorsh ip~ Pru-g ran.<br />I know that several ol the Commonwealth author ities<br />vwitLi Aborig inal staff have expressed keeninestnthe<br />two programs;. 1 Would encourage authorities--generally to develop<br />their own stuidy-base7d dieve'loprm , tt programs as a positiva rCi<br />effectivye mecans of -iss ist inq t ho1; rerd vol oo-) M': nt-( F th1eir<br />Abo r C 1 11)</p>
<p>8. Training of Recruits<br />There is a widle variation in the extent. to which<br />departments carry out their responsibility for deivelopment<br />of their Aboriginal Services recruits.<br />The Board is now developin-g i moce struictured<br />objectives baSed trainincl program for Aboriginal Service<br />recruits. Departments will. be responsible fr rgii thce<br />progjr~ in of:, rolti onp1icmiL , Iriniw o:;: t!' mde;<br />and counsellIing agreed Lor ealch OL Lthe il recruit., t<br />Emphasis will be placed hi the Board on<br />co-ordination of effort anid the co-operative pool ingj of<br />training resources in the regions.<br />9. Management Development Initiatives<br />The Board's Equal Employment Opportunity Bure-au has<br />taken steps to review the Board's prog ram,, find enhance the<br />extent and effectiveness of the Board's monitoring of the<br />status of Aborigines in the APS.<br />Already it is apparent that, in Fhierarchical<br />system like the APS, what is really important is getting<br />Aborigines into the senior levels in increasing numbers, on<br />mer it. The focus must go beyond enhanc ing recrui tment<br />opportunities to a commitment by dopartments and authorities<br />not merely the Board to keep developiLng their Aboriginal<br />staff and provide fair opportunity for thein th rougiho ut the ir<br />careers. The Board will shortly he rons-ierinrq a noimhor of<br />Proposals for !; orv ice-wide spca. nis. r.; Cf-. i( J'c( to ine.: t<br />those needs not met by existing recruitment and development<br />programs for Aborigines.<br />These proposals i: iclude:<br />development of a Service-wide Middleo Managnment<br />Program for Aborigines aimed at rapidly icesn<br />the number of aborigines at mideand<br />management level.<br />development of a Pnrsonal Development Br i-g ing<br />Program luMnEd at a; utnqAhori' i ; 1,1 officers -it<br />onwer Th i rd F) i v j ii I ~ v I: i o d p o h<br />skil1l-, anid ' Knowledge needed t-o sticce!: S! f111ly opet<br />for promotion or for S'ervic'-., ide development<br />programs.</p>
<p>Affirmative Action<br />As I mentioned at the outset, my Governnmnt is<br />committed to an Affirmative Action strategy for Aborigines.<br />Affirmative Action is a systematic approach to the<br />identification and elimination of the institutional barriers<br />that disadvantaged groups encounter in employment.<br />An Affirmative Action program is a planned, results<br />orientated, management prog . r: in dos; i([ ned t achieve Equal.<br />E: 111 oyimen t Oppor tun i t y.<br />There are two popular misconceptions about<br />Affirmative Action.<br />Firstly that it is inconsistent with a system of<br />selection and promotion based on merit and secondly that it<br />involves the use of rigid quotas.<br />Dr Peter Wilenski, the new Chairman of the Public<br />Service Board, put these issues in perspective when he said:<br />" In Government services where the merit principle<br />applies Affirmative Action con.; i! st( ent with that.<br />principle. Indeed, Affirmative Action can be a<br />means of making competition more open, that is, of<br />implementing the merit principle. By introducing<br />social equity, the element which should be<br />fundamental to competition, Affirmative Action<br />removes the effect that characteristics such as<br />sex, race, national origin and physical handicap<br />can have on the assessment of merit. Affirmative<br />Action can provide a much broader range of<br />efficient applicants to be considered in<br />selection".<br />AC i rmative Action dloes not involve 1. th us; of<br />quotas fixed numbers or percentages which must be attained<br />or which cannot be exceeded regardless of the numbers of<br />qualified applicants available.<br />The setting of numerical goals and targets, is,<br />however, an essential part of affirmative action.<br />Goals and targets included in Affirmative Action<br />Programs are an expression of the expected outcome of the<br />merit system in conjunction with the programs undertaken to<br />remove discrimination and ensure equality of opportunity.<br />The admini istrative ar ranl -ments for the<br />introduction of affirmative action in Commonwealth<br />Government employment are currently under consideration in<br />the Task Force on Public Service Matters.</p>
<p>I expect my colleague, Mr , ohn Dawkins, to be able<br />i: o announce details of this new progran to all Permanent<br />Heads early in the new year.<br />I would like to conclude by thanking you all for<br />the interest in this area.<br />1 cannot emphasize too strongly how important it is<br />that you caerfully address how best to increase employment<br />and training opportunities . or Aboriginal people in your<br />depar tmonts anid authoriio..<br />This deserves your priority attention.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
