<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8883</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP OPENING REMARKS, PRESS CONFERENCE, COUNCIL OF AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS MEETING, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, MELBOURNE, 9 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008883.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL:<br />
AA PRIME MINISTER<br />
"" SCRIPT or TEZ VKa KXWSTZi, Tm RON P. Jr. K mW<br />
OPIMG RDMRS, PMSS CO PEPNCB, cCO= NIL OF AISTMNLAT<br />
GOVEMO S NUT=*, PARLZIMSM HOUSE, WLBOMMIE, 9 JU2<br />
1993<br />
3603 PROOF COPY<br />
I thought I would give you just a few preliminary remarks<br />
and then take some questions.<br />
As you know the Council of Australian Governments in its<br />
second meeting has met now for two days with a fairly<br />
extensive agenda which has ranged over a number of<br />
issuesj, the main one being the response to the High<br />
Court's decision in the Mabo case and then other microeconomic<br />
issues which are covered in the Communique which<br />
lists a fairly extensive range of issues which we<br />
considered later this morning and into the early<br />
afternoon, after we concluded the discussion on Mabo.<br />
I am happy to take questions about those things. Let me<br />
just say a few things now about the Mabo decision and<br />
take questions from you.<br />
There was not unanimous agreement to the package proposed<br />
by the Commonwealth and the package which we had<br />
discussed through yesterday with the States, if you like<br />
the amended proposals.<br />
I am disappointed with this# but by the same token what<br />
must emerge from this is a comprehensive response to the<br />
Mabo decision. What we had at the meeting was<br />
undercurrents of the view that there was only a grudging<br />
recognition of the High Court's historic decision and a<br />
tendency to view Mabo not just as a problem requiring<br />
bnly a minimalist solution as just a problem requiring<br />
only a minimal solution. There wasn't a preparedness on<br />
the part of some of the Premiers to give effect to the<br />
principles of the Mabo decision; that is to set up the<br />
T9. Jun. 93 17: 15 No. 030 P. 01/ 03 </p>
<p>TEL: 9. Jun. 93 17: 15 No. 030 P. 02/ 03<br />
2<br />
mechanisms to hear and dispense native title that is<br />
the principal core matter that we should have mechanisms,<br />
tribunals, set up under a framework of Commonwealth<br />
-guidelines to operate in the states under State<br />
legislation to hear and award native title. The Premiers<br />
would not agree to this, in particular Premiers Kennett<br />
and Court, would not agree to this and as a consequence<br />
we were unable to advance the mechanics of a response to<br />
the High Court decision..<br />
There a num-er of other issuss which I'm sure you will<br />
ask me about and I will be quite happy to respond to you<br />
On. Towards the end of the day, the end of discussions later<br />
this morning Premier Kennett and others tried to pull<br />
together %, text which they wanted me to accept which of<br />
course paid no zecognition to the problem at hand at all.<br />
And the point I made to them is that the COAG the<br />
Council of Australian Governments is an executive body<br />
charged with an executive function and they are requiring<br />
of the Commonwealth that we execute an executive act to<br />
validate titles back to 1975 and pcovide compensation<br />
that they would execute no executive act what so ever to<br />
give affect to the Mabo decision. In the text that<br />
Premier Kennett wrote just before I indicated to them<br />
that it was not acceptable to me or the Commonwealth<br />
government, the first point was to accept the High Court<br />
judgement in Mabo that there is native title. So they<br />
are suggesting to me as Prime Minister of the<br />
Commonwealth that we should take away trom the meeting as<br />
some sort of concession from them that they accept the<br />
High Court judgement in Mabo because they were disputing<br />
the fact that the High Court can make law and I said to<br />
them, what do you want me to say, that you accept that<br />
the High Court judgement in Mabo, there is native title.<br />
Well, you have to accept it, the Court said it, there is<br />
no appeal from the Court's decisi. on, there is no privy<br />
council, It is an absolute position.<br />
The second part of their text was that the Commonwealth<br />
should then validate all the leases and provide<br />
compensation, but the third part and this is the point I<br />
tested them on, was that in their text they should<br />
establish procedures to hear and resolve issues raised by<br />
claims for native title and I had said to them well, hear<br />
and resolve claims for native title. No, they said no,<br />
we won't have any text which says will hear and resolve<br />
claims for native title. We'll have text which says only<br />
we will hear and resolve issues raised by claims for<br />
native title. So I said let me get this straight, you<br />
want to the tommonwealth to validate all these leases, </p>
<p>TEL: bW36 .03/ 03<br />
3<br />
pay all the compensationof eighteen years of leases<br />
across the country and you want me to say, to say of to<br />
me that you will accept the High Court decision in<br />
respect of Mabo and that you will only establish<br />
procedures to hear issues, you won't give primary effect<br />
to establishing the mechanisms of hearing and awarding<br />
native title.<br />
I know they have told some of you that we wanted to go<br />
beyond Mabo. Well, we see the Mabo decision as an<br />
opportunity to deal with policy towards Aboriginals In<br />
terms of the reconciliation process and there are issues<br />
there which I am happy to talk to you about.<br />
But the core thing was that they wouldn't agree to the<br />
primary ijsue end that was setting up a system of<br />
tribunals to ' heara nd award native title and not would<br />
they ac-cept the principle of where ever practicable to<br />
protect native title from extinguishment. We said there<br />
is no problem about title co-existing so why say to an<br />
Aboriginal person who may have a native title that there<br />
is a mining grant been issued which may take ten years,<br />
why extinguish that persona title when in ten years time<br />
the mining is finished. Why shouldn't the title revive<br />
after the ten years? Why can't there be co-existence of<br />
title and a revival of the title when the mining is<br />
finished. No, they wouldn't accept the principle of nonextinguishment<br />
of native title.<br />
So in the end they wouldn't give effect to the proposals<br />
which the Commonwealth put up. The Commonwealth<br />
addressed all this in a discussion paper and a 33 point<br />
document. Premier Court told me he had spent four months<br />
with legal advice on this, all Premiers told me that they<br />
had had extensive legal advice, they had our document and<br />
the 33 point plan and yet they said they couldn't agree<br />
to what were nine paragraphs of text encapsulating the<br />
core points. So I said in that case the Commonwealth, if<br />
there is no package, the Commonwealth will not be part of<br />
any partial arrangement or partial solution and that the<br />
Commonwealth would have to reconsider its position as too<br />
would the States.<br />
I am happy to take your questions.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
