<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9514</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP RECEIPT OF SUBMISSION FROM THE COUNCIL FOR ABORIGINAL RECONCILIATION, MURAL HALL, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA FRIDAY, 17 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009514.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-0D<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
RECEIPT OF SUBMISSION FROM THE COUNCIL FOR ABORIGINAL<br />
RECONCILIATION, MURAL HALL, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
FRIDAY, 17 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
I am very pleased to be able to receive this today. I thought it was important<br />
when we were negotiating, and I use the word negotiating, with the Aboriginal<br />
community over the Native Title legislation that in terms of the social justice<br />
response to the High Court decision, that there was a process of adequate<br />
consultation with Aboriginal communities around this country and that no one<br />
group or one self-appointed group was sought to or seen to represent their<br />
views or their interests and the extensive process of consultation which has<br />
followed in the Report going forward by the Council for Aboriginal<br />
Reconciliation I think does justice to that wish that there was to be a<br />
widespread consultation and that this document truly represented the views<br />
of, the representative views of, a majority of Aboriginal people. I'm sure this it<br />
adequately does.<br />
And it is true, as Ian Viner said in his introduction, this Report is passed on<br />
today by Patrick Dodson to me representing the Government on the day after<br />
this historic decision again by the High Court confirming a constitutional basis<br />
of the Commonwealth Parliament's Native Title legislation. This is, I think, an<br />
important milestone in the struggle for legitimate rights for Aboriginal<br />
Australians. I think that in the time since I first spoke to the Reconciliation Council three<br />
years ago, just after I became Prime Minister, I said that I thought we ought to<br />
get on and get some results. And that the best way of providing or meeting<br />
some genuine aspiration for a reconciliation was on the basis of the fairmindedness<br />
of the Australian community, that if they see some practical<br />
things happening, some results happening, and they think they're rational,<br />
they will support it. I have always believed this is a most conscientious<br />
community in a most conscientious electorate. And that you can as a<br />
Government or as any group go to them, talk to them, appeal to them, reason<br />
with them and they will listen to you. But they're looking for tangible results.<br />
In that sense there is something solid about them which goes past any </p>
<p>2<br />
perceived notions of difficulty, whether it be in the economic or the social field<br />
or whether it be in terms of relations with our indigenous community.<br />
Now, as a consequence of that I made clear then at that meeting that this<br />
would be the intention of the Government I was privileged to lead. And at the<br />
so-called Redfern Speech in Redfern Park at the end of 1992, 1 made clear<br />
again that the Government would be seeking to make, first of ali to<br />
acknowledge, and I think it is very important that as Head of Government I<br />
acknowledged in a very public way, the wrongs done during the period of<br />
European settlement to our indigenes and said that reparations need to be<br />
made including of course giving expression to the notion that there was title<br />
and prior ownership of the land to that of European settlement.<br />
Now, I believe that that Redfern Speech and the results which have flowed<br />
from them Mabo, the Native Title legislation and now the Land Fund are<br />
results for which I think Australians have felt good about and I think it has<br />
reduced rancour and it has reduced racism. Because rather than it just being<br />
a skittish debate that never seems to go anywhere, all of a sudden there are<br />
tangible milestones where people understand that something good has been<br />
done and something just has been done and that the community has been<br />
able to reflect upon it and believe in it and feel good about.<br />
So, I think by these results, we have actually reduced any propensity not to<br />
recognise the rights of indigenous peoples and it has reduced what most of<br />
us in this room would call racism in Australia. Now this is a good thing and it<br />
has come as the Reconciliation Council was given a nigh on impossible task<br />
to simply, through the fact that it was a representative body sought to by its<br />
work and by its deeds and by its expressions, preach the gospel of<br />
reconciliation with practical results. It was too big a task without some help<br />
and I think the help needed to come by the Government and the Parliament<br />
taking its responsibilities onwards to do these things.<br />
So I think results are the key words, not pap and nonsense. And if there is<br />
one thing about this debate that I reflect upon, it is that there is no place for<br />
bleeding hearts in it. You know if the Aboriginal community, every time they<br />
see somebody with a bleeding heart, they ought to say thank you but just<br />
please move to the side. It's because of that sort of attitude that it has taken<br />
so long to get this far and it is why now, I think, we have got to continue in the<br />
way we are going.<br />
Now Pat ( Dodson) talked about a policy based on rights not welfare and I<br />
concur in that and we have got to establish what those rights are but of<br />
course we have made some very important headway in that principal right<br />
which, of course, is the right to land and the moral strength of the inherent<br />
right. Whether the Native Title Act applies in only a limited way to those who can<br />
still establish a limited connection with the land is so or otherwise, its force is<br />
that it is an inherent right. That it has quality about it far above a statute<br />
right. But with the Land Fund, where people have been dispossessed of the </p>
<p>land, the Land Fund gives them the capacity and we know in this country<br />
essentially Australia, particularly in areas where Aboriginal people are still<br />
living a traditional lifestyle, or are still able to live a traditional lifestyle, or live<br />
particularly remote from the urban areas, Australia's a patchwork quilt of<br />
pastoral leases and where it's not pastoral leases of freehold title.<br />
The Land Fund allows the purchase of those titles and it means that with the<br />
inherent right coming from the Native Title legislation and the right to<br />
purchase coming under the Land Fund, the satisfaction of Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander people being able to get access, get themselves<br />
access to land, becomes, I think, the significant issue of empowerment that<br />
Pat Dodson spoke about a few moments ago. Because we understand that<br />
there can never be justice for Aboriginal people while they live on the margins<br />
of the cities, or they live congregated in former mission stations around the<br />
country or areas we call Aboriginal communities. They have to, I believe,<br />
have that access to land.<br />
Now, I'm very pleased about the fact that we've got a lot of bipartisanship in<br />
this from people who have always had their heart in the right place with<br />
Aboriginal people; Ian Viner is one and I'm glad to see him in this capacity<br />
today, and he refers to our period in public life in the past on opposite sides<br />
of the house, and Fred Chaney who has taken a role with the Native Title<br />
Tribunal. These are good people and they are after good things. But, we<br />
have to be vigilant about this matter because Richard Court has made clear<br />
yesterday that even after the knock out decision seven to nothing of the<br />
High Court, he is going to fight the matter politically.<br />
I was disappointed that John Howard said today the decision confirms a<br />
significant shift of power to the Federal Government on matters previously<br />
within the direct authority of the states This is not a States/ Commonwealth<br />
matter. It is a matter about our indigenous community and it is very clear that<br />
the community of Australia wanted the Federal parliament to have this<br />
authority in indigenous affairs with the carriage of the referendum in 1967.<br />
There is always this discussion about the rights of the States. It is because<br />
this Government believes the States have prerogatives in land management<br />
and have the capacity to manage land, given they have the records and the<br />
data base and the systems that we have under the Native Title legislation<br />
giving them the right to establish their own tribunals. They just have to be<br />
consistent with the Native Title Act and then it is theirs. There is no dispute<br />
about this. There is no reasonable dispute about this.<br />
But, I will tell you this. Beware of the whispered word ' workable', because<br />
this is now the pass word of the die-hards. Not procedural because I get<br />
asked about Justice French saying ' look, there is this procedure and that<br />
procedure' and, of course, the Judge sitting atop of this tribunal is able to<br />
recommend to the Government that this procedure or that procedure be dealt<br />
with, but procedure is one thing, ' workable' is a word that goes to the<br />
structure of the Bill. So, when Richard Court talks about workable, he means<br />
a change to the structure. He doesn't mean a Western Australian tribunal set </p>
<p>up under a Western Australian act of Parliament consistent with a<br />
Commonwealth law, he means something else.<br />
Now, when John Howard said today, I notice The Age said ' Howard softens<br />
line on Mabo' by referring to he won't repeal the Act he says, but he<br />
wants to make it ' workable'. Workable. Just like the Land Fund. He said he<br />
would pass it but when he got to government he would amend it to make it, of<br />
course, workable.<br />
I just say this, that there has been great milestones made here and this has to<br />
be a bipartisan matter between those who believe in justice for Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander people, that is historic justice and future justice<br />
historic justice and future justice and let's be clear about what we have in<br />
front of us and the results we have and let's go on and not brook any<br />
opposition to the structure of these historic pieces of legislation on some<br />
prejudicial basis that black people shouldn't have title to land. That they<br />
should have only minimum statutory rights and that the whole notion and the<br />
continent where they were possessed of it or had associations with it, they<br />
had the title to it before European settlement is to be put to one side and they<br />
get just minimum rights under statute as proposed in the Western Australian<br />
Act. Now that, we are not having a bar of and I think we have got to press on and<br />
make sure the country understands the difference between procedural<br />
change and procedural improvement and as I say the whispered word<br />
' workable' because workable means burrowing in to overturn progress and to<br />
put these things down.<br />
Let me say something about Aboriginal health and other issues of welfare<br />
which, amongst other things, are included in this Report. I think that as with<br />
all intractable problems it will be dealt with by taking it piece at a time. There<br />
is no big ticket, magical solution, we are not going to get a large Australian<br />
consulting organisation or a major international firm and let them a contract to<br />
repair the lifestyles and living conditions of Aboriginal people, it can't be<br />
done. I was in Hopevale as you may know a couple of weeks ago in<br />
Queensland, Cape York, what struck me about that was that the Cape York<br />
Health Council came into being in recognition of the fact that there won't be<br />
improvements in the health of Aboriginal people unless the Aboriginal people<br />
themselves are committed to the improvements and are part of the solution.<br />
It is another form of empowerment and I think that is right and I think we have<br />
now got to do practical things to make that work. For instance, Aboriginal<br />
people in these parts of the country don't have Medicare cards, completely<br />
unsustainable. They have a right to go to a GP and be treated, but you know<br />
in these places there are no GPs. There are partly no GPs because there<br />
are no cards, there is no booty and there are no pharmacies so there are no<br />
pharmaceuticals. But then we all know there is no point in pharmaceuticals<br />
and drugs if, in fact, we have still got 15 people living in a house with a<br />
transmission of diseases or inadequate sewerage or if there is an acute<br />
problem that there is no air strip to land on for a doctor to give help. </p>
<p>So, these are things that we have got to do, but we must bring the States into<br />
this and local government because this is a tripartite thing. The<br />
Commonwealth whatever it wants to do doesn't build arterial roads in remote<br />
places. It doesn't build municipal roads. And we have to work with the States<br />
to make sure that roads go to Aboriginal communities, that we actually<br />
encourage out stations and we find that when people move on out stations<br />
their morale improves, their state of mind improves, their health improves<br />
which only proves a point the more we move back, the more closer we get<br />
to the natural order of things the better.<br />
These are all things that I think we can do and the same with things like<br />
sewerage, but you know this to be true, if there is a sub division on the<br />
outskirts of Canberra the first thing that will go out there is a road and the<br />
second thing will be the sewerage line and the water supply. This is not true<br />
of Aboriginal people because the States have not done it and when ATSIC<br />
has got the funding they have said it is all over to you, you got the lot and, of<br />
course, it can't do it. So it has to be a tripartite arrangement and something<br />
we go at and perhaps we start trying to prioritise the areas that need help<br />
rapidly and start doing it, again, with results. So people say ' well, there is<br />
something happening here and it is good.'<br />
So, the land matters as we know because the titles matter and then, I think,<br />
we move on these other problems but let's not be starry eyed or dewy eyed<br />
about it, let's get out there and do it. That is what it means and I think that is<br />
what this Report is about, but there is hope in this Report. There wouldn't<br />
have been three years ago, this could not have been produced three years<br />
ago because I don't think the back drop existed within the Australian<br />
community. To receive such a report, it could be produced but would it have<br />
meant anything? One wonders, but I think it means something now.<br />
So, I am quite bullish about the prospects of us being able to deliver justice,<br />
that we can think about social justice in response to the High Court decision<br />
in harmony with the decisions that have been taken in respect of land and<br />
that we can produce results that, I think, all Australians can feel proud of.<br />
The extensive consultation has meant something, that it has come together<br />
under the stewardship and leadership of the Council for Aboriginal<br />
Reconciliation, that it has substance and it has meaning, I am delighted to<br />
receive it on behalf of the Government and we now think about how we<br />
respond to it, it won't all be done obviously quickly, it won't be done as a<br />
package all of it but like this intractable problem of 200 years in the making<br />
we will hop into it with substantial fervour to try to see that justice is done, as I<br />
say future justice and not just historic justice.<br />
Thank you very much for the Report. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
