<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20580</transcript-id>
    <title>Commonwealth Ombudsman   </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce the appointment by the Governor-General of Professor John McMillan as Commonwealth Ombudsman for a term of five years commencing on 17 March 2003.</p>
<p> Professor McMillan is a distinguished academic with extensive knowledge and experience in administrative law. He holds the Alumni Chair in Administrative Law at the Australian National University and was a founding member of the Australian Institute of Administrative Law.</p>
<p> I am confident that he brings outstanding skills and experience to the office of Commonwealth Ombudsman.</p>
<p>A copy of Professor McMillan's curriculum vitae is attached.</p>
<p>I would also like to acknowledge once again the contribution of the outgoing Ombudsman Mr Ron McLeod AM on his retirement after nearly 45 years of distinguished service to the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>CURRICULUM VITAE</p>
<p>  NAME:</p>
<p>John Denison McMILLAN</p>
<p>DATE OF BIRTH:</p>
<p>17 September 1949</p>
<p>NATIONALITY:</p>
<p>Australian</p>
<p>EDUCATIONAL  QUALIFICATIONS:</p>
<p>Bachelor of Arts (ANU, 1970)</p>
<p>  Bachelor of Laws H2A (ANU, 1972)</p>
<p>PRESENT POSITION:</p>
<p>Professor, holding the Alumni Chair in Administrative Law at the Australian National University</p>
<p>RELEVANT PAST  EXPERIENCE:</p>
<p>1995-2002 Member, Centre for International and Public Law</p>
<p> Since 1997 Consultant to the Clayton Utz Government Services Group</p>
<p>1995-1997 Deputy Dean (Students), Law Faculty, ANU Responsible for many aspects of student administration</p>
<p>Founding member and later President of the Australian Institute of Administrative Law (AIAL)</p>
<p>1983-2000 Lecturer/Senior Lecturer/Reader in Law</p>
<p>1982-1983 Visiting Fellow, Australian Graduate School of Management</p>
<p>1979-1980 Principal Investigation Officer in the Office of the Commonwealth Ombudsman</p>
<p>Author of articles and legal opinions about the role of the Ombudsman</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
