<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8145</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF ILLAWARRA REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT SRATEGY WOLLONGONG, 27 SEPTEMBER 19900</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/09/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008145.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY FMRAR( orD UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF ILLAWARRA REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT STRATEGY<br />
WOLLONGONG, 27 SEPTEMBER 1990<br />
Nearly two years have passed since the Illawarra community<br />
started the ball rolling on what has turned out to be a<br />
great reassertion of the confidence, strength and optimism<br />
that characterise this region.<br />
In October 1988, on a visit to Wollongong, I was given a<br />
document that outlined a new plan for getting the Illawarra<br />
back on track.<br />
You called for three things: the convening of a Regional<br />
Economic Summit, the formation of a Regional Consultative<br />
Council, and the development of a regional economic action<br />
plan. At the time, that might have seemed an ambitious proposal.<br />
But today we are celebrating the fact that, with the launch<br />
of this report, you have achieved each of those three goals<br />
you outlined to me two years ago.<br />
The regional summit was held last July and from the<br />
reports I received from the five Ministers of my Government<br />
who attended, it was a path-breaking success.<br />
Out of that Summit came the establishment of a Consultative<br />
Council that would develop an economic strategy for the<br />
Illawarra. It was my pleasure to appoint Stephen Martin as<br />
its Chairnin, end to see that the Federal Government could<br />
" r. vide the financial resources to fund the Council's work.<br />
This report is the product of the Council's work, and I can<br />
tell you at the outsct that it is a very welcome report,<br />
both becaucR of the obvious effort that has gone into<br />
preparing it and because of the breadth of community support<br />
that exists for it. iI </p>
<p>2.<br />
I want especially to thank Stephen Martin for his tireless<br />
efforts in bringing this project to fruition; in many ways<br />
his work has been a classic example of what a local member<br />
can do for his constituents through hard work, imagination<br />
and leadership.<br />
I am not here just to pat people on the back for a job well<br />
done. But before I turn to the substance of the report, I<br />
want first to underline the significance of what you have<br />
done here.<br />
The fundamental problem facing the Illawarra is its<br />
dependence on a narrow range of industries, particularly<br />
coal and steel. You don't need me to remind you of the<br />
difficulties the region as a whole faced when those two<br />
industries were hit hard in the early 1980s.<br />
In this dependence on a narrow range of industries, and in<br />
your consequent vulnerability to economic fluctuations, you<br />
embodied many of the economic difficulties experienced by<br />
Australia as a whole.<br />
As a nation, we have for too long relied for our prosperity<br />
on doing a few things well a few relatively easy things<br />
such as shearing sheep or digging up minerals while<br />
neglecting the harder job of building a diverse and<br />
competitive economy.<br />
It's been the principal tasks of my Government to try and<br />
shake Australia out of those old complacent habits; to make<br />
us more efficient and more cooperative in our economic<br />
practices; and to encourage Australians to be more creative<br />
and energetic in looking for new industries and new products<br />
that we can sell on the increasingly competitive markets of<br />
the world.<br />
And just as the Illawarra region embodied many of the<br />
economic problems faced by Australia, so you embody as<br />
this report shows our hopes as a nation for a more<br />
cooperative, diverse and productive future.<br />
The way in which employers and trade unions cooperated with<br />
the Federal Government to put the steel industry back on its<br />
feet was an eloquent proof of that. The steel plan simply<br />
could not have succeeded without the commitment of each<br />
party to work together in the interests of ensuring the<br />
region, and the nation, retained a competitive and<br />
productive steel industry.<br />
The results are on the board: increasing exports,<br />
strengthening productivity, and a dramatically improved<br />
industrial relations scene. Here at Port Kembla, hours lost<br />
through industrial disputes last year were just over five<br />
per cent of the levels of 1981 a dramatic turnaround by<br />
any standards. I </p>
<p>I 4. 3.<br />
So it's crystal clear that there is a new spirit at large in<br />
the Illawarra a new commitment to work together as a<br />
community so that the vast potential of the region can be<br />
fulfilled. That's what makes this report such a welcome achievement,<br />
and that is why it provides such a firm foundation for the<br />
future of -the region.<br />
As you recognise in this report, manufacturing will always<br />
be importanrt for the Illawarra, and there is a number of new<br />
industries such as marine engineering that could be natural<br />
complements to the strong base that has already been<br />
established. Some improvements could also be made to your<br />
transport infrastructure to sustain such developments.<br />
Perhaps even more exciting are the prospects outside<br />
manufacturing the new opportunities for employment and<br />
growth in tourism, finance, retailing and high-tech industry<br />
such as telecommunications.<br />
Of critical importance to this is the expansion of the<br />
educational and skills base of the local economy.<br />
The University of Wollongong is now the second-largest<br />
employer in the Illawarra. The Commonwealth has increased<br />
its funding for the University by 150 per cent in real terms<br />
since 1983. But equally significant for the future has been<br />
the way ina which the university itself has embarked on<br />
cooperative projects with industry that have generated<br />
significan~ t new revenues the turnover from cooperative<br />
research programs has grown from $ 300,000 in 1985 to<br />
$ 14 million this financial year.<br />
These changes have not by themselves solved the problems the<br />
Illawarra faces. But they do help diversify the local<br />
economy and so make it better able to cope with fluctuations<br />
and better able to offer satisfying jobs to the people of<br />
the Illawarra. They help the region, and the nation,<br />
generate new exports to earn new income abroad. And they<br />
help us build not just a lucky country but a clever country<br />
that can stay ahead of the constantly changing game in those<br />
critical activities of scientific research and development.<br />
I don't pretend that I can give you an answer today to all<br />
the issues you raise in this report. I'm not here to<br />
announce new financial commitments on the requests made in<br />
this report. I can commit, and I do commit, my Government<br />
to look carefully at all the proposals made here and to<br />
provide a detailed responsa to it as soon as we can. </p>
<p>4.<br />
I notice in particular the report's emphasis on the need for<br />
better cooperation between different levels of government,<br />
since efforts to develop an effective regional approach have<br />
been hampered by a degree of duplication and lack of<br />
coordination. As you know, I am initiating a major effort,<br />
with the State Premiers, to improve the efficiency of our<br />
Federal system, and I will be chairing a Special Premiers'<br />
Conference at the end of October to address this very issue.<br />
In this regard, I make the point that many of the projects<br />
suggested in your report would stand a much better chance of<br />
attracting Commonwealth funding under current programs if<br />
the State Government were to raise the priority it places on<br />
tackling the problems of the Illawarra.<br />
I can only echo Stephen Martin's words: this is not a<br />
wish-list report; it is a hard-headed and sensible set of<br />
achievable solutions to the problems faced by the region.<br />
I congratulate you on this report and I give you my<br />
commitment to continue working with you to ensure the best<br />
possible future for the Illawarra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
