<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8912</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, REPORT OF THE MINING COMMITTEE OF THE COUNCIL FOR ABORGINAL RECONCILIATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008912.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 1. Jul. 93 11: 18 No. 003 P. 01/ 02<br />
PRIME MINISTER 178/<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PR[ ME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. ] KEATINGj XIP<br />
REPORT OF THE MIN~ ING COMM1TIEE OF THE COUNCIL FOR<br />
ABORIGINAL RECONCILIATION<br />
I welcome the report, Exploring for Common Ground, presented to me today by the<br />
Mining Committee of the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation.<br />
In February last year, I invited the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation to appoint a<br />
committee to seek improvements in consultations, mediation arnd the resolution of<br />
disputes between mining firms and Aboriginal people.<br />
Across much of the mining industry, an intelligent awareness of Aboriginal cultures has<br />
developed, and Aboriginal people have increasingly shown that they are prepared to<br />
assist the industry in developing the resources in which all of us, as Australians, have<br />
an interest.<br />
It has been assumed by many people and still is, in far too many cases that the<br />
interests of indigenous people and mining companies must conflict.<br />
Where there is recognition and respect for the rights of others, their interests can coexist<br />
to the benefit of all concerned.<br />
Examples such as the agreement between North Flinders Mines and Sons of Gwalia on<br />
the one hand and the Central Land Council on the other in regard to gold midning in the<br />
Tanami Desert, and the more recent agreements on the Mt Todd mine demonstrate<br />
that a wiingness on both sides to negotiate can result in mutually beneficial<br />
arrangements. This report challenges some of the assumptions which remain about the relationships<br />
between miners and Aboriginal people, identifying common ground as well as<br />
remaining areas ordifference.<br />
Some of its recomrmend at ions, such as ways of improving communications between the<br />
parties and negotiating access to land, are directed to companies and to organisations<br />
which represent Aboriginal communitics. I hope both will consider the<br />
recommendations and act upon themn.<br />
Other recommendations, touching on Aboriginal education, employment and heritage<br />
protection, will be considered by the Commonwealth Government as soon as possible. </p>
<p>TEL: 1. Jul. 9311: 18 No-. OO3 P. 02/ UZ<br />
I thank the Chairman of the Committee, Mr Robert Champion do Crespigny, and the<br />
committee members Mr Archie Barton, Ms Jennie George and Mr Wenten Rubwita<br />
for their efforts and congratulate the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation and the<br />
greater part of the mining industry on the way they have approached this important<br />
aspect of reconcilation.<br />
I amr also pleased to announce today that the Government will be offering a public<br />
award to a company operating in the mining or resources area in Australia which best<br />
demonstrates a commitment to constructively addressing Aboriginal and Torres Strait<br />
Islander issues.<br />
This will be a non-cash award, offered this year and open to companies which<br />
nominate themselves or which are nominated by Aboriginal cocimunity groups.<br />
The proposed Joint Council on Aboriginal Land and Mining would be a most<br />
appropriate body to co-ordinate this award.<br />
I believe this award will reinforce the impact of the report I have received today by<br />
focussing attention on the many positive elements of the relationship between<br />
Aboriginal people and mining companies which the report identifies.<br />
CANBERRA, JULY 1, 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
