<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>724</transcript-id>
    <title>PUBLIC MEETING AT FESTIVAL HALL BRISBANE ON  23RD APRIL,  1963  SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THR RT HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000724_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PUBLIC MEETING AT FESTIVAL HALL BRISBANE<br />
ON RDAPRIL, 196.<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt, Hon, Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mr. Hulme and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
The acoustics in this hall are not half as good<br />
as the audience because I have been sitting behind my friend,<br />
the Chairman, and I didn't hear a word that he said but I did<br />
hear a few glancing references to " Pig-iron" so that I knew<br />
my old friends, the Commos, were hereo ( Applause)<br />
Now, I just want to offer one piece of advice to<br />
all of you in the audience if you want to register into my<br />
ear, you must not all talk at once, Do you mind? Just take<br />
it in turn and then I might hear you2 and, of course, I would<br />
love to hear you. I would enjoy tha a Already I have heard<br />
enough to be able to congratulate my friend Mr, Nicklin, on<br />
his assured victory at the next election, ( Applause) because<br />
when our opponents scream, they're in trouble, Now, don't<br />
destroy your voice. Don't become too hoarse too quickly or<br />
for that matter, too donkey too quickly. You please yourself.<br />
Now, I'll explain to you, my dear fellow, that there is an<br />
echo in this hall which makes it impossible for me to understand<br />
what you are saying. Therefore, you are wasting your time.<br />
But I want to say something tonight about matters which concern<br />
my Government, the Commonwealth, and the nation of Australia.<br />
Somebody over hjro says " You are not a Government." ihen he has<br />
been Prime Minister by the election of the people as long as<br />
I have, I invite him to get up and tell us, ( Applause)<br />
Now, first of all, ladies and gentlemen, I just<br />
want to say something to you, in spite of all this, about what<br />
has happened in Australia in my own time, what has happened in<br />
Australia since you've had the Commonwealth Government you now<br />
have the Commonwealth Government, I beg you to remember, which<br />
has been voted for by the people of Australia six times. Six<br />
times, ( Applause) Sir, the Labour Party. I can speak freely about<br />
the Labour Party, can't I, because you're not a Labour man ( to<br />
interjector); I can tell that, The Labour Party is very fond<br />
nowadays of getting up and saying, sometimes with one voice, and<br />
sometimes with 36, that Australia has really gone to the dogs<br />
we are in a state of acute misery in Australia and, of course,<br />
particularly in Queenslando They are willing to say that because<br />
they have hopes in Queensland; rather sketchy hopes but still<br />
hopes. I wonder if I might remind the Labour Party that it<br />
really contributed mighty little to the development of this<br />
State, in fact discouraged investment in this State. I'd<br />
like to remind them and if you can listen as well as roar,<br />
you might consider those figures.<br />
The tobacco industry is a great Queensland industry<br />
and a growing one and, no doubt in spite of your poverty, my<br />
dear boy ( to interjector), you are a great customer of the<br />
tobacco industry, ( Applause) When the Labour Government was in<br />
office the Commonwealth Labour Government they managed to<br />
screw themselves to the point of requiring that 2-per cent of<br />
cigarette tobacco should be Australian-grown. Today, under my<br />
Government, and in current terms with the great assistance of<br />
my colleague down here the Minister for Primary Industry the<br />
percentage is not it is 40 per cent. ( Applause) And in<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
the result, up at Mareeba and Dimboola, œ 3M worth of tobacco<br />
is being grown. Tobacco which was an unwanted rather doubted<br />
industry in Australia has become a major industry,<br />
What else has happened? Up in the north of<br />
Queensland, we have been seeing a new era of development<br />
which is of supreme importance to Australia the great<br />
bauxite deposits, the great uranium discoveries. I don't<br />
remember that the Labour Party had anything to do with these<br />
matters, The great sugar industry ( Interjector " What<br />
about the worker?' Yes, he says, " What about the worker?"<br />
that is an almost Edwardian expression: " What about the worker?"<br />
( Applause) It's absolutely wonderful " What about the worker?"<br />
Well, I'll tell him. I suppose that what he calls the worker,<br />
the employed man or woman, in this State has some interest in<br />
the fact that whereas when we came into office, the great sugar<br />
industry in Queensland exported half a million tons of sugar<br />
I'm not talking about money, I'm talking about quantity and<br />
what is it today? A million and a quarter tons or more ( Applause).<br />
Well, now, my colleague sends me a signal to say I am underestimating<br />
it. All I know is that it has practically quadrupled<br />
over the term of office of the present Government.<br />
I wonder if I might make a delicate reference to<br />
the great subject of pig-iron. Pig-iron and ingot steel these<br />
are two of the great pointers in industrial production in<br />
Australia and since we have been in office the production of<br />
these two commodities has trebled today. 1 11 explain to some<br />
of you boys what I mean by trebled three times as much today<br />
( Applause) as there were when your boys were in officeo<br />
Sir, I don't need to go through all these things.<br />
Wevve had the most tremendous development in this country, New<br />
industries every year. I was reminded this morning if I may<br />
refer to the subject of coal, that when the Labour Party was in<br />
up to 1949 for eight years ( to interjector " That's right<br />
Happy DaysS) we were importing coalo We were so happy thaz<br />
we had blackouts and power shortages and we, Australia, were<br />
importing coal from India and from South Africa and paying<br />
through the nose for it, Today, under a non-Labour Government,<br />
Australia is exporting coal as well as using far moro coal<br />
internally than she ever did before0 ( Applause) And some of<br />
your friends, my boy, ought to be pleased about it, because up<br />
at Gladstone, there are a few good, sound unionists who have<br />
jobs in the handling of coal for export, who wouldn't have had<br />
them at all but for what has happened over the last ten years.<br />
Now, Sir, in this rather gay and friendly atmosphre,<br />
I am not going to occupy your time by quoting a lot of statistics<br />
and therefore, well, I know I wouldn't waste statistics on<br />
you ( Laughter, Applause) but I want to turn to another matter<br />
which I am sure will infuriate some of the exports around the<br />
room, We have had in Canberra, ( I suppose you can mostly<br />
hear me, can you?) in che last three weeks two motions of " No<br />
Confidence" by this powerful Opposition that we have at Canberra,<br />
They came along and breathed deep the night air at the Kurrajong<br />
Hotel or wherever it was what was it, the other one, the<br />
Wellington Hotel or something; they came along reinforced by<br />
a vote of 19 to 17, which would have been 18 all and therefore<br />
negative, but for a statesmanlike act by the Queenslander well,<br />
now, I would have thought you would have applauded that.<br />
ee aeea/ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
They came along and they had two goes at us. I have never<br />
enjoyed two debates more, I have never felt so convinced that<br />
a Labour Party is on the way out ( Applause) ( Boos) Now, ladies<br />
and gentlemen, if you dontt mind me engaging in a little bit<br />
of autobiography, I have been a Leader of the Opposition myself<br />
and I know what it means and I know that an Opposition Leader<br />
must occasionally move a vote of " No Confidence", It keeps the<br />
boys together. It takes their minds off their troubles, and<br />
we have had two, and the first of them seemed to have something<br />
to do with international affairs and, as a matter of fact we<br />
didn't assume an attitude of defence, we went on to the attack<br />
and if ever an Opposition moving a " No Confidence" motion was<br />
thrashed to its feet appropriate expression in this hall it<br />
was the Labour Party on that censure motionø Their trouble was<br />
that they know that Australia, whatever else it may think about<br />
this or that, is quite determined to be free and secure in future.<br />
Therefore, we decided that we would find out where the Labour<br />
Party stood on these matters, and what did we get? What did we<br />
get? We got, first of all, this extraordinary attitude that<br />
they have about the signalling station in the North West of<br />
West Australia. ( Interjector " What will it I' 11 tell<br />
you what it will do, and believe me, Sir, if you understand what<br />
I say to you now, don't waggle your finger at me if you<br />
understand what I am saying to you, you will be better informed<br />
than any of your cobbers in the Opposition because they have<br />
never succeeded in understanding ito The Americans, the United<br />
States of America, they are our allieso Do we all realise that?<br />
( Applause) They are our allies, We and New Zealand ( to interjector<br />
Well don't you like them to be allies?) Really what<br />
have we come to? We and New Zealand are their allies in tho<br />
ANZUS pact, just as we are also associated with them in the<br />
South East Asia Treaty Organization, I wonder if anybody would<br />
like to report that on a reference to the United States being<br />
our ally, a few cheapjacks in this audience counted them out.<br />
Is that the Queensland view? Is that the view that you want to<br />
That's right ( voices counting out). That's exactly what<br />
I expected. Yes, take a good picture, boys. They'll get all<br />
the publicity, This is the usual thing. Wonderful. They ought<br />
to get the Stalin Medal with a bit of luck. ( Cheers and Applause)<br />
You know the interesting thing about those lads? They stand up<br />
straight, but they can't think straight, ( Cheers, Applause).<br />
Now ladies and gentlemen, what is the purpose of this<br />
signalling station? I would like to tell you. The purpose of<br />
it is to enable communications to occur between the United States<br />
and United States naval forces in the Indian Ocean and the South<br />
West Pacific. They have these facilities.... ( More counting<br />
out by interjectors) By Jove, this is the first time that I ever<br />
heard that the Pope was a Communist. ( Applause) Really, you<br />
boys would make anybody laugh, Well trained, no doubt well paid,<br />
Get a picture of them. That's the object of the exercise. All<br />
over the press tomorrow, " The Pope calls for peace." All I am<br />
saying is that if we want peace for ourselves in Australia, if<br />
we want security for ourselves in Australia, it's time we woke<br />
up to the fact that in this part of the world, the friendship,<br />
the generosity the power of the United States is essential to<br />
us. ( Applause PUhy does the Labour Party object to this<br />
signalling station? Well, I confess I am wrong because by a<br />
majority of 19 to 17, they decided they were in favour of the<br />
signalling station, provided that if a war occurred, and the<br />
signalling station was therefore needed, it couldn't be used<br />
000 00 0/ 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
except by the permission of the government of the day in other<br />
words: " Yes America, spend œ 50M or œ 60M or œ 70M, put up this<br />
signalling station and when the day comes that you need it, we<br />
give you notice that if there's a Labour Government in Australia,<br />
you won't be allowed to use it at all." ( Boos) If anything<br />
has been made crystal clear, it's that.<br />
Now, I wonder why the Labour Party has this extraordinary<br />
view. Is it anti-American? ( To interjector Well,<br />
I am very glad to have your answer, Sir, that it is not anti-<br />
American) Does it believe that in the event of a great<br />
conflagration in the world, Australia can defend herself without<br />
friends or without allies? Does the Labour Party believe that<br />
because nobody else does. The simple fact is that if we expect<br />
the United States to do things for us, we must be prepared to<br />
do things for the United States, ( Applause) ( Interjector<br />
" What about Great Britain?" Not so powerful as she once was but<br />
with tremendous significance in the old world. We expect Great<br />
Britain to do things for us, We are prepared to do things for<br />
her, The whole curse that has come upon the Labour Party<br />
is that it has become isolationist in the last few years. It<br />
wants to pretend that if it puts its head in a bag and looks<br />
in the other direction inside the bag nothing will happen and<br />
we will be left alone. And if we wanz any further proof of that,<br />
we have only to look at the fantastic proposal of the Labour<br />
Party that the whole Southern Hemisphere should be a nuclearfree<br />
zone. ( Yells and cheers from interjoctors) Of course this<br />
is what they are cheering. The whole Southern Hemisphere is to<br />
become a nuclear-free zoneo What about the Northern Hemisphere?<br />
They haven't said anything about that. Let's stick to the<br />
point. The Labour Party has agreed that the whole Southern<br />
Hemisphere is not to have, store, manufacture or receive or use<br />
any nuclear weapons and that goes for the whole area of the<br />
world south of the Equator, It goes for South Sumatra, but it<br />
doesn't go for North Sumatra. It goes for Indonesia and for<br />
New Guinea and Australia but it doesn't go for Thailand; it<br />
doesn't go for Burma, it doesn't go for North Viet Nam, it<br />
doesn't go for Communist China. And therefore, we have this<br />
extraordinary proposition being put up: We, in the Southern<br />
Hemisphere will say nobody can bring a nuclear weapon to our<br />
defence south of the Equator, but north of the Equator, the<br />
only aggressors in the world, the Communist powers, can make<br />
use of them to their hearts' content, and if the time comes<br />
( more jeering and yelling). These boys, of course, are great<br />
exponents of free speech. We notice that. They are delighted<br />
to have somebody express his mind and to give them provocation.<br />
I would express my mind about them with even more delight. But,<br />
anyhow, I am going back to my topic.<br />
My topic is that this policy is one in which you<br />
confine nuclear weapons to north of the Equator and you leave<br />
the countries south of the Equator defenceless against them.<br />
Absolutely defenceless against them. ( Interjector " Rubbish")<br />
You say " Ribbish", but let me put this to you. Lot me put this<br />
to you. The United States, I hope you will concede is our<br />
ally, and the United States is significant to us and the United<br />
States has naval forces in the Indian Ocean, including, of<br />
course, naval vessels, either carriers or submarines or aircraft,<br />
which carry nuclear weapons and it may well be in the event of<br />
a great war that the capacity of the Western powers to attack<br />
the Communist stronghold by nuclear weapons will depend upon<br />
their control of the Indian Ocean, their capacity to use the<br />
* 0 a O </p>
<p>Indian Ocean for those purposes. But according to the Australian<br />
Labour Party, they are not to be allowed to use the Indian Ocean,<br />
except North of the Equator, they are not to be allowed to bring<br />
their vessels into the Indian Ocean if they are armed with<br />
nuclear weapons, unless they bring them through the Straits<br />
of Malacca where they can be closed overnight and counted every<br />
day, in any event, or bring them through the Suez Canal. Now,<br />
I ask you, ladies and gentlemen do you want the United States<br />
to think we are a lot of half-wits? Do you want them to suppose<br />
that we are bogus in our attitude of friendship with them, of<br />
alliance with them, because the best way to do that is to vote<br />
into office a Labour Government with the views that I have been<br />
putting and I venture to say that our alliances in a useful<br />
sense with the United States will come to an end,<br />
Now I am talking about this matter because I don't<br />
want anybody to be under any misapprehension. I am very familiar<br />
with the views of various people around the world. ( Jeering<br />
slow clapping, shouting and yelling) Isn't it wonderful? This<br />
shows that they are on the wane because the moment the Labour<br />
Party becomes overwhelmed by its Communist friends and they all<br />
start preventing people from listening, that's the end of it.<br />
( Cheers and applause) Thank you, ladies and gentlemen. I<br />
want to say to you you won't have any doubt of the truth of<br />
this, though they do: The majority of the people of Australia<br />
are decent people, ( Applause) which distinguishes them sharply<br />
from some of these. Decent people. And what's more, they are<br />
not only decent people but they are sensible people and they<br />
know that the future of this country is tremendously involved<br />
in us maintining our contacts, our alliances with the great<br />
free powers of the world. ( Applause)<br />
Sir, I was very interested to discover what the<br />
Labour Party's policy was on these matters and indeed I took<br />
the opportunity of pointing out, in the course of the debate,<br />
how many of the front-bench Labour men and I presume they<br />
were expressing the views of the 36, the 36 faceless men who<br />
run the Labour Party several of them were at great pains to<br />
say, " What's Malaya got to do with us, Wny should we have<br />
forces in Malaya? Why should we worry about what happens in<br />
relation to Malaysia? Why should we worry about anything<br />
except what happens inside Australia?" Now that's the Labour<br />
Party's policy, Di-me, my distinguished opponent is, I believe,<br />
speaking in Brisbane somewhere tonight you know, the Member<br />
for East Sydney. ( Yells and cheers) Well give him a cheer.<br />
You're exactly his type. Give him a cheer. And I am told<br />
he's here. Do you remember when he invented a story about the<br />
Brisbane Line ( shouts and yells) Yes, invented a story about<br />
the Brisbane Line and went before a Royal Commissioner and<br />
pleaded privilege and said, " I can't give evidence; I have<br />
parliamentary privilege." You must, some of you, remember this,<br />
All I can say is, that if this business of the Labour Party, if<br />
their policy to warn off the Americans, to control them at the<br />
North-West Cape to ban any nuclear rovision in the Southern<br />
Hemisphere, if this succeeds, it won't be the Brisbane Line<br />
that they will be up to, it will be the Hobart Line or the South<br />
Pole Line, ( Applause) Now, Sir, that is all I need to say<br />
about that matter, There are a lot of people in this hall<br />
tonight and a lot of people listening in who really understand<br />
that it is the first duty of a Government to attend to the<br />
security of the nation, that the security the safety of the<br />
people is the supreme law, They know that, and therefore they<br />
will be in a good position to judge the worthlessness of these<br />
evasive, isolationist policies on the part of Labour, </p>
<p>6<br />
Well, now I just turn to another matter, because<br />
we have had two " No Confidence" motions. I don't know how<br />
many more we'll have.... ( Interjector " You'll get one<br />
now") I welcome them, ny dear boy. I welcome themo But,<br />
my dear fellow, didn't you listen in? Didn't you listen in<br />
to the debate? Didn't you realise that the Labour Party was<br />
thrashed on both, not only in the division, but in the<br />
House? Come, core, you must do yourself justice. But the<br />
second " No Confidence" notion had to do with television and<br />
it was a very interesting one. Very interesting. It is<br />
quite true that the Leader of the Opposition fell into the<br />
error of making some outrageous charges of corruption and<br />
dishonesty against people who were not involved and that I<br />
find it very difficult to forgive. But at any rate, what did<br />
happen was that the Labour Party explained its policy on<br />
television. How? ( Shouts and jeers) Well in your case,<br />
put it under the control of the Comintern. I understand<br />
that. But to nationalise all television.<br />
Now letts understand what this is: Every country<br />
television station run by a local company, aery city television<br />
station run by a company to be closed down; either at the<br />
end of its current licence if they are being respectable,<br />
or closed up with or without compensation, so that when we<br />
turn on the television at night we will be privileged to<br />
look at the one station run by the Government. Now that's<br />
their policy. And, having stated that policy repeatedly, they<br />
then began to support it by the rather villainous argument<br />
that I referred to,<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemeno this is something worth<br />
thinking about, This television is something new in<br />
Australia. It has boon introduced in our own tine, not in<br />
a hurry and it has now been going and spreading and extending<br />
for a few years. Does anybody in Australia wish to have a<br />
Government monopoly of television? ( Interjector " What<br />
about private enterprise?") Jell, exactly, you talk about<br />
private enterprise. He's in favour of private enterprise<br />
now. ( Laughter) He's in a confused state of mind, I think,<br />
my friend down there. He wants private onterprisoe What I<br />
am saying to this great audience is Do you want to have a<br />
Government monopoly on television? ( Interjector " Yes")<br />
Good. He has ambitions to be in the Government. ( Laughter)<br />
A government monopoly in television, a government monopoly<br />
in broadcasting sane sort of thing is that what we want?<br />
A few rather feeble yessos. I imagine if I an any judge of<br />
an audience that 90 per cent. of the people here tonight<br />
don't want to have a government monopoly of television,<br />
( Sustained applause) If they don't they had better take<br />
a little more care how they vote at the next election than<br />
some of them did at the last.<br />
Now, ]. et's face up to it because here is a<br />
Labour Party, publicly and solidly pledged, and repeating<br />
it in the House to nationalise television, to wipe out<br />
commerecial broadcasting over here he says, as if he is<br />
talking to himself " Liars" ( Lnughter) If I thought you<br />
could read, I would advise you to read the Hansard because<br />
we went to great pains to have this established in the House,<br />
and it is established beyond the slightest chance of contradiction.<br />
And the Labour Party? Well, it's in a funny state.<br />
It's a messed-up Party. It really is. I am almost sorry<br />
for it at tines. ( Laughter) ( Applause) It is just muddledup,<br />
the Labour Party, They sit down and they say, " Well, </p>
<p>-7-<br />
we ought to do this." For example, I think this is rather<br />
amusing. There was a television licence to be issued in<br />
Melbourne and one of the applicants had two directors representing<br />
the Labour Party ( Interjection inaudible.) Oh, no. The<br />
two directors representing the Labour Party. And they had one<br />
or two extraordinarily well-to-do capitalistic types sitting<br />
on the Board and they made their application, but it turned out,<br />
when the House was meeting to discuss this matter, they didn't<br />
believe in private enterprise even with Labour directors, they<br />
must have their monopoly. And, finally, the Broadcasting Control<br />
Board recommended, in the case of Victoria, the application by<br />
Mr, Ansett's group. Oh, this was very, very unhappy. After<br />
all, the Board recommended it and the 3oard recommended it<br />
unanimously, and after all, one of the directors of the Ansett<br />
group is a well-known Labour candidate in Victoria Sir George<br />
Jones not likely to be a supporter of mine or of ours. But<br />
the Board recommended the Ansett group and we said, " Very well.<br />
We accept the recommendation."<br />
SNow that, I would have thought, would have ended it,<br />
because Parliament established this Board, Parliament passed<br />
the law. Under the law passed by Parliament, there is a Broadcasting<br />
Control Board; the Board is an independent body and<br />
every application for a licence has to be referred to it and<br />
people come along eight or nine of them in each case, and<br />
spend thousands ol pounds on presenting their case to the<br />
Board and the Board makes a report, and we accepted the Board's<br />
report, I wonder what the Labour Party would have done.<br />
( Interjector " Don't worry about the Labour Party") I'm not<br />
worried about the Labour Party. I am only talking about the<br />
Labour Party because I think there might be a few noodles left<br />
who want to vote for them, ( Cheers, applause) Suppose Labour<br />
had been in office, what would they have done about it? Would<br />
they have rejected the report of the Board? Would they have<br />
selected a few of their own friends? ( Sustained slow clapping)<br />
There you are, you have got the answer. They would have given<br />
a slow clap. That's it and while everybody was saying what<br />
dumbbells these are, the Labour Party, no doubt, would have<br />
either given the licence to one of its friends, or would have<br />
said, " The whole thing is cancelled; we are going to have<br />
a complete Government monopoly of television" because that is<br />
its policy. Now ladies and gentlemen, I have spoken to you<br />
about those matters because I think they are modern, they are<br />
quite contemporary. We have thrashed them out in the House, and<br />
I don't propose at this stage to occupy your time any longer,<br />
but I do take the opportunity of saying that there has been<br />
no great Party in the history of Australia ever to have won an<br />
election by larrikin tactics. No great Party. ( Applause)<br />
All I can do is to express my deep sympathy to my Labour<br />
opponents for some of the curious characters who allegedly<br />
support them on the fringe. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
