<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7998</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 3 APRIL 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007998.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
0<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 3 APRIL<br />
1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Good afternoon. A few comments to start with and<br />
0 tthhee n elIe cwteilocno. m e Yyoouu r maqyu ehsatvieo nsn. o ticFeidr stt haotf tihne thoeu tcpoemrei odof<br />
since last Saturday week I haven't been bouncing around<br />
the place making great claims about victory and so on. I<br />
have had my head down and engaged in the serious business<br />
of getting ready for the fourth Hawke Labor Government.<br />
However, I should say about the outcome of the election<br />
first of all that I am indebted to the people of<br />
Australia for the confidence that they have once again<br />
reposed in me and my colleagues. I was often asked<br />
during the election what my view was as to the likely<br />
outcome and I think many of you will recall perhaps that<br />
I said, almost adnauseam, that I was confident, without<br />
being cocky or complacent, and I want to say that having<br />
achieved victory I am now neither cocky nor complacent, I<br />
am grateful that we have been given the opportunity once<br />
again of serving the people of Australia. I think I<br />
discharged during the campaign the obligations that I<br />
felt I had to set out to the Australian people the<br />
vision, and the plans and the concepts that we had for<br />
0 the future. And I can give the people of Australia the<br />
commitment that what was promised during the campaign<br />
will be delivered. Now as I say I have been engaged in<br />
the process of drawing up the Ministry for this fourth<br />
term and I attempted in this period to use the authority<br />
that I believes rests with me to secure a direction that<br />
I thought was appropriate. That is I understand that<br />
there must be, in the formulation of a Ministry within<br />
the Labor Party, some taking into account of the group<br />
within the Party. And it would-be-futile to try and<br />
avoid that fact. But I was determined that those<br />
considerations would not monopolise in any way the<br />
outcome of the Ministry. I also understand that there<br />
must be some taking into account of state and regional<br />
considerations. Again that can't be an exclusive matter<br />
but neither can it be totally ignored and I want to<br />
express my appreciation to the Caucus and the groups<br />
within the Caucus for the way in which, generally<br />
speaking, they took account of my wishes in this regard.<br />
I believe in the outcome, as a result of the co-operation </p>
<p>2.<br />
that I have received, that I have been able to establish<br />
in this fourth Hawke Ministry one which has a great deal<br />
of vibrant new talent and one which I have been able, in<br />
the allocation of portfolios, to place in a way in which<br />
I believe will ensure that in this fourth term there will<br />
be the delivery of relevant and imaginative constructive<br />
government. And as I say I thank the Caucus for the way<br />
in which I have received their co-operation. There is no<br />
addition to the Ministry but I have appointed four<br />
Parliamentary Secretaries whose duties will be as<br />
outlined in the accompanying statement to assist their<br />
portfolio Ministers in the area of correspondence,<br />
assistance with departmental papers, the making of<br />
inquiries on behalf of Ministers, representing Ministers<br />
at official engagements, meeting with delegations and<br />
clients, maintaining liaison with other members of<br />
Parliament, and generally acting in a way which will be<br />
of assistance. And this will be a way in which, at<br />
minimal cost, another group of people are able to gain<br />
experience. One feature of the decisions that I have<br />
made that I would also particularly draw to your<br />
attention is the fact that I have asked Senator Collins,<br />
in addition to his portfolio duties, to be the Minister<br />
Assisting me on issues concerning northern Australia. It<br />
is very interesting if you look at a map of Australia now<br />
you will see that the whole of the north of Australia has<br />
put its trust in Labor. Western Australia, the Northern<br />
Territory, Kennedy, Leichhardt at the very north, and<br />
ones below that. So it is appropriate both in terms of<br />
the intrinsic importance of northern Australia and the<br />
fact that northern Australia has put its confidence in<br />
us, that Senator Collins is particularly well informed on<br />
the needs, the opportunities and the challenges of<br />
northern Australia should be advising me in this way.<br />
Finally, before I make myself available for your<br />
questions, I would put on record here, as I did in the<br />
Caucus, my gratitude to those who have served as<br />
Ministers but who will not be in that capacity in the<br />
fourth Hawke Ministry. There are eight departures. Four<br />
who are retirees and four who have been compulsorily<br />
retired. In regard to those eight, and they are Senators<br />
Walsh and Reynolds, and in the Reps, Holding and Morris<br />
and West and Duncan and Jones, and very importantly of<br />
course, my dear friend, Lionel Bowen. To those eight I<br />
place on record my thanks and the thanks of my Party for<br />
the service which they rendered.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke have you.. and Mr Keating got the<br />
guts to continue to tackle Australia's economic problems?<br />
PM: Just before I answer that question I also meant to<br />
say, and I take this opportunity of saying it, that it is<br />
for me, a matter of very great satisfaction that my<br />
friend and colleague Paul Keating was unanimously elected<br />
Deputy Prime Minister. It is an honour which he has<br />
thoroughly earned, and thoroughly deserves, and I look<br />
forward to working in a sense of an even closer<br />
relationship, if that is possible, with Paul in his dual </p>
<p>3.<br />
capacity as Deputy Prime Minister and Treasurer. Now the<br />
question was have we got the guts to make the tough<br />
decisions. I believe the answer is yes. We have in the<br />
past, I believe, made the tough decisions. The best<br />
evidence of that I suppose is the nature of the campaign<br />
that was run against us. They say look at what you have<br />
done to Australia. That was our opponents cry. Of<br />
course it was a very slick, superficial analysis but it<br />
was referring to the fact that we had been prepared to<br />
make tough decisions. And I think on our record, to the<br />
extent that tough decisions are necessary, they will be<br />
taken. But let me finally make this point. That while I<br />
believe there will be tough decisions to be taken in the<br />
next three years, we also believe that it is going to be<br />
a very good period for Australia because of the sorts of<br />
things that I was talking about in the campaign. And<br />
also because in fact that some of the tough decisions<br />
have been taken in the past. What we are now going into<br />
the nineties with is an Australia in which more<br />
Australians are employed, better trained, and with better<br />
equipment. We have in that the foundation for growth and<br />
for greater competitive capacity.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why did Senator Walsh have his doubts about<br />
that? PM: Well I think my friend Peter sets particular<br />
standards, has expectations which are not always either<br />
necessarily economically correct or politically sound.<br />
But having said that let me say in respect of Peter Walsh<br />
that I think that Peter Walsh has been a person who has<br />
made an enormous contribution to the achievements of my<br />
Government in the past seven years. And despite the fact<br />
that he has expressed some reservations don't upset me.<br />
I want to place on record my sense of obligation to him<br />
for the contribution he has made. I think that he would<br />
be the first to admit that he tends by nature to be the<br />
resident pessimist. And he is entitled to be such. But<br />
I don't share the pessimism which he has expressed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Who is going to be the resident pessimist<br />
now? PM: Well I guess he is around for a while, isn't he.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what do you think Senator Walsh is<br />
w6' rried about with the power of the environmental lobby.<br />
How.. will you. balance the. environment and how much<br />
of a debt do you owe the environment lobby<br />
PM: Well I think that any democratic government anywhere<br />
in the world today that is going to be one of the classic<br />
challenges of Government. How you balance the legitimate<br />
concerns for the environment and the need for growth.<br />
And I will just say one or two things about that. I said<br />
during the campaign, and I don't want to say it at great<br />
lengths because all of you would have heard me say it<br />
before, that it is the fact that on the one hand we had </p>
<p>record economic growth, record employment growth, during<br />
the seven years of my government, and at the same time we<br />
have achieved in the area of the environment the<br />
situation where the World Heritage Bureau has said, that<br />
no government has done more to advance world heritage<br />
values than has Australia. So I can talk about this not<br />
in nebulous terms of balance but saying, well look at the<br />
records. Record growth and a record achievement in<br />
regard to world heritage values. And that hasn't been<br />
easy. I mean it is all very well for people to sit down<br />
in the comfort of their analyst armchairs and deliver<br />
their opinions but to make those decisions at times is<br />
very very difficult. And I think I can look Australia in<br />
the eye and say, well look at the record, I think we have<br />
done it fairly well. Now I don't pretend that in the<br />
next three years that it is always going to be easy. But<br />
I can say that we will approach these issues on the basis<br />
of knowing that we have got to strike the right balance.<br />
Now having said that let me make a raw concrete<br />
observation that I think that I was going to have to<br />
build upon what I have already done in this area in terms<br />
of process. Let me remind you of what that process has<br />
involved to this point. At the end of last year I called<br />
meetings of groups from farmers and miners and so on as<br />
well as the environmentalists and put before them the<br />
concept of sustainable development and undertook that we<br />
would have prepared a working paper on that concept which<br />
would then be brought back to the groups. And then, on<br />
the basis of agreement, we hoped that we could get, we<br />
would then take that concept into a whole range of areas<br />
of rural industry, manufacturing industry, mining,<br />
tourism and so on, and having got hopefully an agreed<br />
concept then try and work through the implications of<br />
that in these areas. Now those processes are going to<br />
continue. But what I also had in mind is that I will, I<br />
think, be recommending to my colleagues that probably we<br />
should establish a subcommittee of the Structural<br />
Adjustment Committee which, for want of a better title at<br />
this stage, would perhaps be called the Sustainable<br />
Development Committee of the Structural Adjustment<br />
Committee, so that I would have the input of the relevant<br />
departments, environment, primary industry, DITAC,<br />
without being exhaustive about it, so that in this way,<br />
both through what I have done and now trying to get the<br />
concept of sustainable development formulated and with a<br />
process within the government, enable us better to deal<br />
with these issues so that there will be a total framework<br />
we can.. reduce adhocery as much as possible. Now these<br />
are concrete ways in which I think I can answer your<br />
question. And finally, I think there is a part of your<br />
question, how much do I feel that we owe to the<br />
environmental forces. A very considerable amount. It is<br />
not possible at this stage, I mean all the analysis<br />
hasn't been undertaken, but I would find it very<br />
surprising if both directly and in terms of influence<br />
upon the votes to the Democrats and so on, I would be<br />
very surprised if indeed there hadn't been a significant<br />
influence in the number of seats. I am grateful for that </p>
<p>support. I think it was earned by the decisions that we<br />
have made in the past and I will be conscious of the<br />
representations of that area in the future but we will<br />
not be their captive.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Walsh over the economic effect<br />
of immigration. Have you got any comment on that?<br />
PM: Yes, there is a view in Australia, and it's<br />
interesting how it spans the political spectrum, David,<br />
from extreme left right through to extreme right when you<br />
think about it's get the Rainbow Alliance strange<br />
group of people who would be either reduced immigration<br />
people or zero immigration. Now I'm not, by philosophic<br />
disposition, a low immigration person. I believe that we<br />
have basically got the, the balance right. We have to, I<br />
think, always have as a fundamental criterion the<br />
economic capacity of Australia to absorb migrants. And I<br />
think that the figure that we've been running at, at<br />
about 140,000 net a year is about right according to that<br />
criterion and I'm aware of the fact that some people want<br />
to argue that immigration at that level, or some say at<br />
any level, imposes unacceptable economic strains. I<br />
believe that that is an inadequate economic analysis<br />
because I believe that you've got to look at the other<br />
side of the coin and point to the pluses of immigration.<br />
The point is getting the balance right in economic terms<br />
and I think, David, we've basically at about this level<br />
got it right at this stage. I would hope that as we go<br />
on that we may be able to look at higher levels of<br />
immigration. That would be my propensity rather than<br />
lower, but-economic<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: just a minute the economic criteria is<br />
important. The final point I make is this, that one<br />
thing that will be a constant, hoee, inn the<br />
immigration area, as far as I am concerned and this<br />
Government is concerned, that we will never in any<br />
circumstances allow the, the race card to be played. And<br />
I must say that this campaign was unfortunately marked by<br />
the use of that card. It happened in 1984, it happened<br />
in the Parliament in 1988, it surfaced again in this<br />
election and indeed I, it's probably can be argued that<br />
there's one member of this Parliament, the Member for<br />
DaCwe, who can owe his election to the fact that he<br />
distributed in the last weeks of. the campaign a letter,<br />
blatantly racist in its appeal and deliberately false. A<br />
letter to the electors of Lowe that they would have<br />
80,000 Japanese living on their doorstep under the Multi<br />
Function Polis, or 80 percent 80 percent of the<br />
people that would be there. Why people who profess to<br />
have principles resort to these sorts of tactics, I, I<br />
just don't know. They have not sense of responsibility<br />
to the future of this country. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Well the issues outlined by Senator Walsh<br />
had nothing to do with it<br />
PM: No, no, of course not. I mean, let me make quite<br />
clear, David, in any of the comments I made about race<br />
that had nothing to do with Walsh's comments. The first<br />
part of my response where I was talking about economic<br />
matters, were relevant to what Peter had said. There was<br />
no suggestion in what I'm saying that he was going to<br />
those issues.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you that any way to deal with the<br />
economic aspects of the issue to be raised?<br />
PM: Well<br />
JOURNALIST: The impact on savings and on<br />
PM: I'm simply saying that our judgements have been to<br />
this point that the, I mean, we haven't lightly reached<br />
our judgements about the immigration levels. They have<br />
been reached on the basis of what is economically<br />
appropriate. Now I'm saying I think they've been<br />
economically appropriate to this point, I wouldn't want<br />
to see them lowered.<br />
JOURNALIST: raised by Senator Walsh, he gave a very<br />
bleak picture of the Australian economy, saying that time<br />
was running out for Australia and that it was urgent to<br />
address the problems over the next couple of years. Do<br />
you think that he, that he exaggerated the extent of our<br />
problems? PM: I think he somewhat exaggerated them, yes. But<br />
that is a, a, I suppose, a legitimate technique of the<br />
Cassandras. If they have a feeling of concern, I suppose<br />
if you want to make colleagues and the community think<br />
about economic issues it's a reasonably valid technique<br />
to write the message large. I think he's written it too<br />
large, but having said that, having said that as I did<br />
during the campaign, we haven't got easy street coming<br />
up, we have not got easy street coming up. I think we've<br />
got the prospect of very good streets, of great avenues<br />
opening up, but they're not going to happen just by<br />
assuming, as Australia too often has tended to assume in<br />
the past, that she'll be right mate. What we have<br />
diamonstrated to this point is that you need tough<br />
decisionsboth in the.. macro. economic and the micro<br />
economic field. And as I said to the Caucus in my<br />
address this morning, there will be tough macro economic<br />
and micro economic decisions required and to the extent<br />
that they are required, they will be taken. But what I<br />
am saying is that I think we've got a great deal of<br />
evidence which I think Peter has not sufficiently paid<br />
attention to. We've got a great deal of evidence of<br />
very, very significant improvement taking place in<br />
Australia's competitive position. After all you can't<br />
have a massive increase in the number of people employed, </p>
<p>you can't have a massive increase in the education of<br />
your people and the training of your people and you can't<br />
have all that happening with the massive re-equipment of<br />
your economy and not in fact be seeing good things<br />
happening. I mean, I saw them during the campaign. I<br />
went around Australia and I saw an Australia which is<br />
becoming more competitive. For instance, I think there<br />
would be some of you here who would have been with me<br />
when we went to that Pacific Dunlop tyre truck factory<br />
in, in Melbourne and there you had both management and<br />
unions proudly talking about the fact that together<br />
they'd been to the United States for twelve months, had<br />
brought back what they'd learnt there and now we ' re<br />
establishing there, in Melbourne, the best state of the<br />
art plant in the world. Now those things are happening.<br />
Now they haven't happened by accident, they've happened<br />
because we'ye created the environment for it. But we<br />
can't be complacent about that. We've got to continue to<br />
do it. We will.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister on macro and micro economic<br />
reform PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: What specific macro and micro economic<br />
reforms then would be your priority issues<br />
PM: Read the speech of the 22 February, Geoff.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Walsh wants fiscal policy<br />
tightened. Now is that something which you'd be planning<br />
during the next few months or as far as you ' re concerned,<br />
is fiscal policy on hold?<br />
PM: No, fiscal policy is never on hold and, see, I have<br />
to say to you people so frequently when you ask me<br />
questions like that look at the record. I mean, we<br />
have not in seven years been a Government which has said<br />
of any arm of policy, it's on hold. I mean, how can you<br />
you take the area of fiscal policy where you produced a<br />
situation where you've had a 7.1 percent turnaround,<br />
billion in terms of reduction of Commonwealth outlays,<br />
four successive years of real reductions in outlay. I<br />
mean, what possible intellectual basis have you got then<br />
for talking about putting things on hold. What we do,<br />
we've done each year, we've looked at the three arms<br />
of policy wages policy, we sit-down, we say there you<br />
are, we'll work it out, we come to an arrangement with<br />
the trade union movement and say there you wage and<br />
salary earners and you employers now know for the next<br />
period what your incomes and costs are going to be. In<br />
regard to fiscal policy, both at the time of, of May<br />
statements or April statements and the Budget we<br />
undertake the task of seeing what is necessary in the<br />
area of fiscal policy. And in the area of monetary<br />
policy no-one can say that we haven't been active in that<br />
area. I mean, I've just been through a campaign where </p>
<p>the impact of monetary policy decisions was the number<br />
one issue. Now, now, Paul, in other words what we will<br />
be doing this year will be the same. We will be, as we<br />
approach the Budget, we will be looking at what the<br />
appropriate fiscal settings should be. Not resting on<br />
any laurels.<br />
JOURNALIST: tough decisions already been taken, so<br />
that there is room for a little bit of easing<br />
PM: Well, I think the right<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: No, I think the right answer is this, that you won't<br />
be able to expect the same degree of fiscal cutting in<br />
the future as you've had in the past. I mean, there is<br />
a, you don't get into some exponential or even arithmetic<br />
series in this sort of thing because when you've made big<br />
cuts as you have in a whole range of areas, you are<br />
getting rid of more fat and getting closer to the bone.<br />
So I don't think there's anyone with any knowledge of the<br />
economy and the social structure of this country who<br />
sensibly believes that you can go on in the same measure<br />
as the past. That doesn't mean, however, that savings<br />
are over. I mean, just look at the most recent<br />
experience. I mean, here we are just into April and<br />
already in this year we've shown what we can do. This<br />
was what distinguished me from my opponent in this last<br />
election. What we did first was to get the savings, the<br />
new savings, then on the basis of getting the new<br />
savings, made our new commitments. So there are still<br />
things that will be looked at and but it would be<br />
unreal to think that you're going to have the same sort<br />
of availability of expenditure cutting that you've had in<br />
the past.<br />
JOURNALIST: A Party Committee A Party Committee has<br />
been meeting for two years discussing privatisation. Is<br />
that one area where you want to move more quickly?<br />
PM: I'll be interested in getting their, their report.<br />
JOURNALIST: When do you expect that?<br />
PM: I don't know. In the last week when I've been<br />
e faged in these matters I haven't really been on the<br />
phone. ringing up about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, we'll see. I mean it depends on what' s in<br />
their report. But it's not a matter about which I feel<br />
nervous at all, Peter.<br />
JOURNALIST: But if micro economic reform </p>
<p>PM: Just, just let me make this in the area of micro<br />
economic reform, may I say, I don't think that the<br />
question of whether the airlines are sold or not is by<br />
any means, by any means, the most important area of micro<br />
economic reform. It's not irrelevant, not saying it's<br />
irrelevant, but let me make it clear to you I don't think<br />
it's by any means the most important.<br />
JOURNALIST: Parliamentary Secretaries look a bit<br />
like over-manning while we're on the subject?<br />
PM: No I don't think they look like over-manning.<br />
There's been in the history of federation, in the history<br />
of federation, a fairly, you know, continuous use of<br />
them. And you can go back and a long, long way back and<br />
I've had people do that for me and they've pointed out<br />
that in one form or another they've been used for a long<br />
period during federation. They were used in the ' 70s by<br />
the McMahon Government and then formalised by the Fraser<br />
Government with the legislation in 1980 and they<br />
appointed a number of them. They have a situation where<br />
there's obviously no possibility of saying that this was<br />
a factional accommodation thing, I mean, the factions<br />
have made their adjustments and that's evident in the<br />
list you've got before you. But I, I think there is a<br />
case for them. I don't think it's the sort of thing that<br />
you want to have great numbers of and some people might<br />
have liked more. I don't think there is a case for great<br />
numbers, but I think I've got the balance right there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is Bob McMullan's appointment a token<br />
gesture? PM: No, you ask Bob McMullan. He certainly doesn't<br />
regard it as such.<br />
JOURNALIST: why didn't<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: Why did Kelly get a Ministry and he didn't?<br />
PM: Well, you've got a situation where there are<br />
positions, 30 positions and within that 30 there wasn't a<br />
place for, at this stage, for Bob McMullan.<br />
JOURNALIST: reflection on his talent?<br />
PM: No reflection on his talent at all, nor does he<br />
regard it as such.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, going back to Senator Walsh's<br />
remarks, were you surprised that yesterday he referred<br />
people approvingly to John Stone's critique of the 1988<br />
Budget, do you think he is totally wrong and what's your </p>
<p>PM: Yes, I had a, I had a private meeting with Peter<br />
yesterday and as I think you know now from seven years, I<br />
don't talk about private meetings in any detail, but I<br />
don't think Peter will mind if I say this. That during<br />
that private meeting he referred me to this, this speech,<br />
as I understand it was September 1988. 1 asked was it in<br />
the Parliament, he said no it was outside the Parliament<br />
so you can see we talked about it<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you get a copy?<br />
PM: No, just a minute, just a minute. Don't get so<br />
excited, Michelle, just wait. And I said to him that I<br />
didn't necessarily regard Senator Stone I was going to<br />
say the late, that's improper but the ex-Senator Stone<br />
as a great authority on matters economic. And I reminded<br />
Peter of the fact, fact which are burnt indelibly into my<br />
memory of Stone in his earlier capacity, or incapacity,<br />
whatever, which way you want to look at it, Secretary of<br />
the Treasury. In that capacity when we had the<br />
discussion in the Cabinet room about the floating of the<br />
dollar. And Senator Stone was vehement, vitriolic in his<br />
opposition to the floating of the, of the dollar and had<br />
the view if we did it the dollar would go through the<br />
roof. Now and that we would learn to regard this as<br />
one of the great mistakes to be equated with the<br />
percent tariff cut in the Whitlam Government period, that<br />
we would come to regret that like Whitlam came to regret<br />
that. I reminded Peter of this and said with that sort<br />
of background, Peter, don't be surprised if I don't have<br />
the faith that you may have in John Stone and his<br />
analysis. Having said that I said I'm not therefore<br />
saying that everything he may have said in this paper is<br />
necessarily erroneous. I'm simply saying that on my<br />
experience I have no reason to regard the pronouncements<br />
and the analysis of one John Stone as of any great<br />
significance. JOURNALIST: Did the environment groups express any<br />
concern to you about Graham Richardson's move from that<br />
portfolio? PM: They had hoped that Graham was going to stay in the<br />
portfolio so there's no state secret about that. That<br />
view had been conveyed to me. But I think the next thing<br />
to say is that they do understand and accept, albeit<br />
reluctantly, Graham's reasons for leaving that portfolio.<br />
I believethatin the.. appointment-of Ros Kelly they will<br />
have someone who will be very, very understanding of<br />
their position consistent with the overall<br />
responsibilities that she has.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you offer the job to Kerin?<br />
PM: I discussed the matter with him, Michelle, because I<br />
must say I was fascinated as no doubt all of you were<br />
by the suggestion that both the ACF and the Wilderness<br />
Society made that if they couldn't have Richardson they'd </p>
<p>11.<br />
like Kerin. I was fascinated by that, as he was, and we<br />
did have a bit of a yarn about it. But you see Kerin has<br />
the problem of the talents, I mean he has a remarkable<br />
talent as Minister for Primary Industry, without any<br />
question the best Minister for Primary Industry that this<br />
country's ever had, to use the bucolic analogy, no-one's<br />
ever come within a bulls roar of him and is likely to.<br />
He is just very valuable in that area and it's an area in<br />
which he wants to stay.<br />
JOURNALIST: So was it a rebuff to the environmental<br />
groups to appoint Ros Kelly?<br />
PM: No, not a rebuff. They would've liked Richardson,<br />
he wasn't available and in their thinking they expressed<br />
this desire for John Kerin. John Kerin's not available.<br />
I've given them a very good Minister.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you try to persuade Senator Walsh to<br />
stay and if so did you offer him any change of portfolio?<br />
PM: I think that part of the discussion I had with<br />
Senator Walsh is appropriately between me and Senator<br />
Walsh. JOURNALIST: During the election campaign, Prime<br />
Minister, you made some predictions about interest rates.<br />
In view of the emerging international and domestic<br />
pressures now on rates do you care to make any further<br />
predictions? PM: The predictions I made have been fulfilled. That is<br />
that if we won as we have that the Treasurer would be<br />
talking immediately with the Reserve Bank that he has<br />
done. He's had discussions with the Governor of the<br />
Reserve Bank. The board of the Reserve Bank is meeting<br />
today. After their meeting the Treasurer will be talking<br />
again with the Governor. It would be presumptuous for me<br />
to speculate on what the outcome of that will be other<br />
than to say that it is a matter of record that we did<br />
what we said we would do and that is, through the<br />
Treasurer, conveyed our view to the Reserve Bank that the<br />
conditions were there for a fall in rates. Now as to<br />
what that will be, we'll see.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you think the appointment<br />
ofrR alph Willis as the Minister for Finance will send the<br />
right-message-about the determination of your Government<br />
to handle the tough issues in your next term?<br />
PM: As far as messages go out, I don't think there's<br />
just one appointment. I think that the reaction of the<br />
markets as of the media and anyone who looks at it<br />
will be that this is a remarkable Ministry. It's a very,<br />
very well constructed and talented and fresh blooded<br />
Ministry. I think the markets, to the extent that they<br />
look at it, will be very encouraged by the determination </p>
<p>that the Prime Minister has shown and the cooperation<br />
he's received in shaping an appropriate Ministry.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was Senator Ray at one stage led to believe<br />
he would get the Finance portfolio?<br />
PM: No, not by me or as I understand by anyone.<br />
JOURNALIST: What are you expecting from Dr Hewson and Mr<br />
Reith?<br />
PM: What am I expecting from Dr Hewson and Mr Reith?<br />
Well JOURNALIST: the answer?<br />
PM: Well the answer is Liberal, they are both Liberals.<br />
It's a bit early to say and seriously I don't want to be<br />
ungenerous about this. I mean, I am, I don't want to be<br />
ungenerous about it. Clearly Professor Hewson brings to<br />
the position a good knowledge of economics even if he<br />
gets his ideas wrong. I mean he knows what economics is<br />
about. He's literate in it and understands things even<br />
if some of his answers are wrong. It'll be very<br />
interesting, for instance, I tried to get your interest<br />
during the campaign on a couple of points, to get the<br />
question up to Professor Hewson and I'll give him the<br />
opportunity. Just to show how generous and charitable I<br />
am, I give him notice now. I'm going to try and find out<br />
from Dr Hewson why it is that as a Professor of Economics<br />
in 1987 he had a very firm and unqualified view that<br />
there should be a capital gains tax but when he became a<br />
captive Liberal politician he changed his mind. I mean,<br />
this is one of the things that's going to be interesting<br />
to see with Dr Hewson as Leader of the Opposition how to<br />
what extent he may bend his economic beliefs to what he<br />
regards as the imperatives of Liberal politics. But I<br />
think that Dr Hewson brings positive qualities to the<br />
position. I would say this finally in regard to Dr<br />
Hewson and then I'll have something to say about Mr Reith<br />
in a moment, but I'd say this finally about Dr Hewson.<br />
However closely I will be watching Dr Hewson it will not<br />
equal in the intensity of scrutiny that of those behind<br />
him and alongside him. It will be very interesting to<br />
see the reaction of those opposite. We'll be very<br />
modulated in our reaction. Now Mr Reith, well now here's<br />
aifascinating one isn't it, Mr Reith. He made his<br />
reputation on the-~ basis of going out and defeating our<br />
proposals for a referendum. Four year terms, our<br />
proposals, and now part of the Reith proposal for a<br />
better Australia is what? Four year Parliamentary terms.<br />
He's got a certain amount of elasticity which was to me<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be having another go on that<br />
question in this term of office on constitutional reform,<br />
Mr Hawke? For example, </p>
<p>13.<br />
PM: I must say that one is tempted at the first meeting<br />
of the Cabinet to put a bill through for a four year or<br />
five year or a ten year term immediately. I think having<br />
had this election I'd have a fair chance of satisfying<br />
the dual constitutional requirements of an overall<br />
majority and a majority of States.<br />
JOURNALIST: So will you<br />
PM: I said I'm tempted, and I'm..<br />
JOURNALIST: On the question of constitutional reform,<br />
will you be having another crack at it in this term of<br />
office? PM: Look, I am very pessimistic about constitutional<br />
reform, not really about the people of Australia as such,<br />
but I'm pessimistic about the vision of the Tories in<br />
this country. I mean, it is to me still almost<br />
impossible to understand how any responsible party in<br />
this country without going to all of the four points<br />
where I can if you want to go through the four of them.<br />
But you just take the obvious one's, the one's I've just<br />
talked about four year term. Take the proposal that<br />
there should be entrenched into the constitution a<br />
provision that if any citizen were in a situation where a<br />
government had compulsorily required his or her property,<br />
they were entitled, as a constitutionally entrenched<br />
provision, to fair compensation. But the Tories of this<br />
country opposed that, as they did the four year terms and<br />
the freedom of religion and entrenching in the<br />
constitution the rights of local government. By any<br />
objective assessment, the interests of Australia into the<br />
future would be well served by each of those proposals<br />
being passed but these people have no capacity, no<br />
capacity for looking at the real interests of the<br />
Australian people. They are political opportunists par<br />
excellence. They knew that each one of those proposals<br />
which their leaders had in fact supported in one way or<br />
another within their own party and within their own<br />
constituencies, but when it came to the question of<br />
supporting them politically, they were not prepared to<br />
because they regarded it as politically opportune to<br />
inflict a blow upon the Labor Party, little caring that<br />
the blow was really inflicted upon Australia. That's<br />
wbhpt makes me depressed about constitutional reform. The<br />
incapacity of the conservatives of this country to have<br />
any vision and commitment to the future of this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: What about national powers over prices and<br />
incomes as a possible subject for constitutional reform,<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: That doesn't fascinate me very much, David.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, given that an alleged rumour<br />
PM: One of them. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Given that an alleged rumour has received<br />
national circulation if not national credence-<br />
PM: Now what's this one?<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you briefly, essentially briefly, give<br />
us a report on the condition of your health generally and<br />
your prostate gland in particular?<br />
PM: Well I think it's for you to judge. I mean, if we<br />
had a in general I'll come to the prostate gland in<br />
particular in a minute. Perhaps you're not in a position<br />
to judge about that and I don't intend to give you the<br />
opportunity of becoming more familiar<br />
JOURNALIST: Perhaps I should ask Hazel.<br />
PM: Will you deal with your colleague, will you deal<br />
with your colleague. But, I mean, I think in answer to<br />
the general question about the state of my health, I<br />
mean, I submit myself to you. I went through a pretty<br />
vigorous campaign, I think I held up well, I felt that I<br />
did and I think I look OK now. My general health is<br />
excellent. As to the state of my prostate, at this stage<br />
I'll leave that as between my doctor and myself.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, just back on the election<br />
campaign, the Labor Party's vote fell to a very low level<br />
Why do you think that it was and do you think<br />
there's a need for some sort of internal review process<br />
to look at-the reasons for that happening<br />
PM: Within the Party?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM: Oh no. What we always do, Geoff, after an election<br />
is we have a detailed analysis provided to us by the<br />
Secretariat. And may I just parenthetically say what a<br />
brilliant job I think Bob Hogg and the Secretariat and<br />
the Party did in this campaign, I think they did a<br />
brilliant job. The post-script of that brilliant effort<br />
will be, I think, a very detailed analysis provided to us<br />
and we will sensibly and responsibly analyse that report<br />
that we get. If out of that there are lessons to be<br />
l-~ arned, you can be assured that we'll learn them and<br />
that we'll apply them. Going to-your question more<br />
broadly, it's a question as you know that was asked many<br />
times in the campaign and I'm not saying it critically<br />
because you are talking about the future, what will we<br />
learn from. But going to the point generally about the<br />
lowered primary vote, I think it was a combination of two<br />
factors perhaps more than that but two essentially.<br />
One that I referred to during the campaign that I think<br />
that in this country as around the world, there is a<br />
heightened and a significantly heightened interest in the<br />
environment. I mean anyone who's analysing politics and </p>
<p>doesn't understand that, you know, shouldn't be in the<br />
game. And that was true in this country. Now we<br />
understood that, we understood that and in an intelligent<br />
way, I believe, throughout the campaign and then<br />
particularly in the last week, we said to people well<br />
alright we weren't critical of them, we didn't abuse them<br />
for wanting to vote for others particularly on that<br />
ground. We said what you've got to realise is that when<br />
you wake up on the 25th either Hawke or Peacock you've<br />
got as Prime Minister and what they stand for in regard<br />
to environmental matters and what their record is. So I<br />
wasn't terribly phased about that phenomenon because it<br />
is a global phenomenon. I think we intelligently reacted<br />
to it, not just in the election but that we have been<br />
ahead of the game in a very large extent from 1983.<br />
We've understood that these things are important, we've<br />
made the right decisions, not to attract a vote but<br />
because there is a great commitment within the Labor<br />
Party certainly under my leadership to discharge the<br />
obligations we have on these matters. So our vote went<br />
down in part because people are now so concerned about<br />
that, they wanted to register their commitment to these<br />
issues by a primary vote in that area. I think that's<br />
one reason. Now I don't ignore, Geoff, the other factor<br />
that there is some disillusionment with my Government and<br />
people were hurt by high interest rates, they didn't like<br />
it and they protested in that. But they also, as I said<br />
to many of many of you in one to one conversations, I<br />
said I have faith in the intelligence of the Australian<br />
electorate. I said it to meetings of you as a whole and<br />
I talked to you individually. I've said all along that I<br />
have great-faith in the ultimate intelligence of the<br />
Australian electorate. What they did say, well alright<br />
we don't, you know we're not too keen about you, we'll<br />
not give you the vote, the primary vote we had before.<br />
But they looked at the alternative, Geoff, there is no<br />
way that they were going to be voting for them. In what<br />
mattered in the end, we got the of preferred votes.<br />
Look, we'll just have three more.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you see the significant vote for<br />
parties as now being a permanent feature of the political<br />
landscape or do you think it will<br />
PM: Oh no, I don't think it's necessarily a permanent<br />
feature, Glenn. I mean just let me take one part of the<br />
answer I gave to Geoff that if we get the economy going<br />
in a wayI. hiope it will and_ we,_ at.. this stage of the<br />
electoral cycle, are able to go up with not that<br />
oppressive burden of high interest rates that we had to<br />
have and a more congenial economic environment then I<br />
think we'll get many more primary votes for that reason.<br />
So I don't think you can say it's a permanent feature but<br />
I do say this, that I can't see the interest in the<br />
environment significantly diminishing. OK, there's just<br />
one here and one up there. </p>
<p>16.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just going back to your earlier statement on<br />
micro economic reform and the question Geoff asked. Will<br />
you mean then that the statements released during the<br />
election campaign on micro economic reform was going to<br />
be the blueprint for change and that you weren' t<br />
envisaging any further<br />
PM: Well you remember the statement, you read it? I<br />
mean it was a very comprehensive statement which covered<br />
areas.<br />
JOURNALIST: But a lot of the measures have been<br />
announced previously. I was just<br />
PM: Oh no, no, no, no, no. If you look through that you<br />
will see in each of the 10 areas nominations of areas<br />
that had to be addressed in the fourth term and I mean I<br />
wasn't trying to give a flippant answer to you, Geoff. I<br />
mean, it's all there and it wasn't you know, said for fun<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible<br />
PM: Just a minute. It's not a debate between you and<br />
me. I'm answering a question. In that area as in the<br />
Ballarat speech before, the Ballarat speech was delivered<br />
on. Now some people say not at the rate that some of<br />
them would've liked. But I simply assert, as I've said,<br />
before, at a faster rate than ever before but I'm not<br />
resting on those laurels and what the 22nd I think it<br />
was the 22 February speech was about was saying well here<br />
are the 10-areas of micro economic reform in which we're<br />
going to operate and I think you can see by the<br />
composition of my Ministry and the sort of people that<br />
are there, that I'm very serious about that. Now there<br />
was one up here.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, said at the weekend that of<br />
the big challenges for the Labor Party in the next three<br />
years was support of the greens into the Party<br />
How important do you see that challenge and do you think<br />
it can be achieved? The second point he made in a<br />
personal capacity was that the Government should look at<br />
managerial salaries seemingly high in some areas. Is<br />
that something that could see you<br />
PDT: Well I'm in favour of getting as many people into<br />
the-Labor.. Party as possible who-. are . consistent with the<br />
basic philosophy of the Labor Party -and it's legitimate<br />
to talk about the greens and so on -but let's not get<br />
into a mind set where we think that's the only issue. I<br />
mean, I go back to the answer I gave before that we've<br />
got to get the appropriate balance. But for those people<br />
in the community who have a real involvement in the<br />
commitment to environmental matters, I think this<br />
election should show that in the end the Democrats and<br />
the greens, they are not going to form governments, not<br />
in the foreseeable-future and not in my life or beyond </p>
<p>17.<br />
that. Governments are going to be formed by either the<br />
Labor Party or the conservatives, whether they be 2 or i,<br />
whether they finally marry. Therefore I think a lot of<br />
people with interests in environmental matters would<br />
perhaps see that it makes sense to get into the Labor<br />
Party and express their point of view. Last one, Paul.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you see any merit in the idea of a postelection<br />
May Statement or would prefer to wait until the<br />
Budget for the bulk of the economic initiatives after the<br />
election? PM: I would think that it's a Budget matter, Paul.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
