<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9583</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, RADIO 6WF, 15 MAY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009583.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, RADIO 6WF, 15 MAY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
RE: Did you enjoy the football?<br />
PM: There was some very great football played there. I mean I have seen<br />
better games in the sense closer games, but I don't think I have seen<br />
better football. I thought that some of the playing by the Eagles and<br />
the Dockers was just spectacular.<br />
RE: The Dockers are noted for being bold which I suppose gives you a bit<br />
of a thought in terms of your political strategy, but the thing to notice<br />
that your team, Collingwood, is the one the Eagles have had the most<br />
difficulty with in recent years because they seem to be a hard tackling<br />
side. So there is hope yet Paul.<br />
PM: Well the old Collingwood they need a good, old Collingwood forever,<br />
as they say. They know how to play the game. But they have had a<br />
run of bad luck recently. Of course, they got up on the weekend and<br />
they will be playing at Victoria Park.<br />
RE: That's right, they play the Dockers at Victoria Park next weekend.<br />
PM: They play the Dockers at Victoria Park next weekend and that will be a<br />
tough match because Collingwood on its home ground is a hard side to<br />
beat. So I wish the Dockers well there.<br />
RE: And it has really turned out to be a good stadium now hasn't it?<br />
PM: The stadium looks terrific. We put that up under the One Nation<br />
program trying to, at the time, get the economy started and get some<br />
construction moving because normally the Commonwealth is not in the<br />
business of funding $ 8 million into a football stadium, but we did on<br />
this occasion and I think it was a lucky stroke for the Western<br />
Australian Football Club and we were delighted to be able to play a </p>
<p>role in developing the stadium because now that the game is a<br />
transcontinental game, a national game, I think it is important,<br />
particularly as you have got the Eagles and the Dockers playing<br />
against one another here, to have a stadium that takes 40,000 or<br />
50,000 people.<br />
RE: That is our view too.<br />
PM: And I think also the ground looked like a bowling green. It looked<br />
fantastic. Apparently they took 1 1/ 2 metres of earth out of it, drained<br />
it, and it will be a really great spot for the AFL and for really<br />
competitive games here in the west.<br />
RE: Well, certainly, off to a good start. Now on the question off to a good<br />
start. The Budget is interesting, but what's been taking the minds of a<br />
number of people in the last day or two is the question of election<br />
speculation. Of course, that is reported today in the press. Are you<br />
going to have an early election?<br />
PM: Well I have never been in favour of an early election and John Hewson<br />
was saying, last year, that we were going to have an early election.<br />
Alexander Downer said we were going to have an early election and<br />
we are still here. There has been no early election because they are<br />
too hard to win, Ron, without giving the time away.<br />
RE: So they are too hard to win so you<br />
PM: The pressure and cost of winning a national election in Australia, have<br />
an election 15 or 16 months after you won the last one, which is what<br />
John Hewson was proposing we have and Alexander Downer, was ( a)<br />
wasting the mandate and the public say hang on we elected you for<br />
a term, you better get in there and do your best.<br />
RE: It must be tempting though with interest rates good news on the<br />
weekend, the unemployment figures, the Budget reasonably well<br />
received.<br />
PM: People are starting to see now that John Howard has made no<br />
substantial policy. He has no substantial policy thought. He has made<br />
no substantial policy changes or announced anything of substance in a<br />
substantial way. That is now becoming apparent. He ran around with<br />
a cynical little line about five minutes of sunshine. We have grown for<br />
3 1/ 2 years now and the Treasury are saying we will grow for 3 more in<br />
their forecasts. You can see, from 1983-1998/ 99, which is 15 years,<br />
we will have grown all the time, bar 18 months. And really grown. We<br />
averaged about 4 1/ 2 per cent through the 80s, where Europe is doing<br />
1, Japan is doing 1/ 2 per cent. We are doing 4 1/ 2 per cent. And this<br />
year we are doing 3 3/ 4. </p>
<p>RE: He is now attacking your credibility and saying you can't be believed in<br />
what you say.<br />
PM: The principal commitment I made at the election was about<br />
employment. The whole election was about unemployment and<br />
employment and you might remember me saying on election night<br />
Ron, we wouldn't leave the unemployed behind, we'd put an arm out<br />
and pull them up behind us. And what was our principal commitment?<br />
500,000 jobs in 3 years. We are at 650,000 already. In 2 1/ 4 years<br />
we are at 650,000. We actually reached 500,000 jobs in two-thirds of<br />
the time. That was our principal commitment. Then to the long term<br />
unemployed, the people unemployed 12 months or more, who ran the<br />
risk of becoming an underclass, this year because of Working Nation<br />
and our labour market programs, we have seen 102,000 of them go<br />
back into work, which is a phenomenal figure. You look at the 80s, we<br />
would have got maybe 10,000 in this period of long term unemployed<br />
people back to work. This year we got 100,000. So not only have we<br />
kept our principal commitment, but at the same time we haven't the<br />
long term unemployed behind. That was the principal thing and there<br />
were all the other specific election commitments, the generalised Child<br />
Care Rebate introduced, the Home Child Care Allowance introduced<br />
and now, of course, we have seen the Parenting Allowance, it will be<br />
introduced soon, and the one we have just recently announced the<br />
Maternity Allowance.<br />
RE: The Opposition is also saying that 12 years is long enough it is time for<br />
a change. That must be fairly hard to counter.<br />
PM: Well I don't think it is hard to counter. Ron, this Budget is so fresh, it<br />
could have been delivered in 1983 from the Cabinet then. I mean what<br />
Ralph Willis and Kim Beazley and my colleagues in the ERC have<br />
been able to do on this occasion, and the whole Government indeed, I<br />
mean look at what this Budget has got. It has got a massive return to<br />
surplus, but more than that it has got the biggest and most<br />
comprehensive savings plan the nation has ever had, laid in the<br />
middle of it, is superannuation.<br />
RE: It must worry you a bit though that the question of superannuation,<br />
what we have seen already is that the funds can get in and rip into the<br />
contributors in terms of charges. You must have some worries about<br />
the management of funds and whether or not they are going to be<br />
secure in the future because it hasn't all been plain sailing on<br />
superannuation.<br />
PM: The funds had a loss on the long bond market this year, but they did<br />
all around the world because long bond yields went up and therefore<br />
the bond prices came down. They took losses. But you have to look<br />
at the longer run. The point though, at issue, was the question you<br />
asked me about the Government. Now here is John Howard, he had </p>
<p>a chance on Thursday night last to respond to the Budget on national<br />
television. Not one policy thought did he put down. You see, what has<br />
the Government given the public since the election? A strong<br />
economy, huge employment growth, low inflation and now we have<br />
taken all that pressure off interest rates. You see, Ron, what people<br />
need to realise about the Budget is last year we had what is called a<br />
bond selling program, you know the Commonwealth Bonds, we sold<br />
$ 21,000,000,000 worth of bonds. This year we will be selling<br />
$ 6,000,000,000. There is a $ 15,000,000,000 reduction in the bond<br />
selling program. That means that there is less Commonwealth paper<br />
out there. The price, if it rises, if the price goes up, the yield or the<br />
interest rate drops. That is why long bonds, 10 year bonds, dropped<br />
by 1 percentage point in the last 10 days and that pressure having<br />
been taken, the banks then responded by dropping their variable<br />
mortgage rates for housing. So here is the Government, which has got<br />
an economy back into life through things like One Nation, the football<br />
stadium, all these areas got it there with 2 to 3 percentage points in<br />
inflation, not 10 as John Howard left us. We have had the biggest fall<br />
in unemployment, since we have been keeping the records, in the last<br />
12 months. We have had 650,000 jobs since the election. And you<br />
look at the vitality and the verve and the spring in it and say how would<br />
that come from John Howard who has got no policy clues and look at<br />
his front bench. He has got Tim Fischer who is economically illiterate.<br />
Costello who is like a crow on a fence, picking the eyes out of anything<br />
that is good, carking along about any positive thing that comes along.<br />
And, Alexander Downer who is a professional failure. That is his front<br />
bench.<br />
RE: They are revitalising. If we look at the events of the weekend, Brendan<br />
Nelson coming in, he might add some new light to their front bench.<br />
PM: Revitalising. Well, have a look at what has happened over here.<br />
Rocher has been tipped out, Filing has been tipped out, Connolly was<br />
their superannuation spokesman he has been tipped out. So<br />
somebody, Nelson, who was in the Labor Party for 17 years, he<br />
resigned because the Labor Party wasn't socialist enough. Look the<br />
Liberal Party is like a club, you join at the door. You know some of<br />
those business clubs that you see you join at the door. I mean you can<br />
join at the door. Say here am I, 1 am Brendan Nelson, you have been<br />
in the Party before. No, no, no. His principal backer is Bruce<br />
Shepherd who is not in the Liberal Party and so the Liberals are so<br />
moribund, they are so had it that they have given the safest seat in<br />
Australia, Bradfield one of their safest seats to an opportunist.<br />
RE: So you are not threatened by him?<br />
PM: We had all this with Bronwyn Bishop. And we had it with John<br />
Hewson. John Hewson bounded in as a sort of a Bent Street Sydney<br />
economist into the Liberal Party. He was going to show us a thing or </p>
<p>two. Out the door. Where is he? He is back in Bent Street or<br />
somewhere else. Then it was Bronwyn Bishop. You know an old<br />
friend of mine said to me years ago, he said " Paul, I tell you this, never<br />
worry about the sky rockets of politics. At first a shower of sparks, but<br />
a dead stick falls to earth." And this guy is a shower of sparks and a<br />
dead stick if I ever saw one.<br />
RE: Now, you created some sparks earlier this year with your exchange<br />
with Kerry Packer. In hindsight do you wish that you hadn't had that<br />
exchange?<br />
PM: Well, Kerry is a professional bully.<br />
RE: You don't think he would say that of you?<br />
PM: I am not going to be pushed around by Kerry. Kerry is a fellow that<br />
has a lot of good qualities. I mean I have known him a long time and I<br />
counted myself as a friend of Kerry's not a close friend or one I see<br />
regularly or anything like that, but somebody who I have liked over the<br />
years and I have been disappointed by his attitude. But that is all I<br />
can say about it. I don't wish him any ill.<br />
RE: The Medicare levy is an aspect of the Budget that you had to change,<br />
you had to increase. There is a real problem in the world, that is the<br />
increase in medical costs, in pharmaceutical costs. Can you see that<br />
you are going to cap the Medicare levy or is it going to be one of those<br />
taxing measures that you will have to keep looking at depending on<br />
medical costs.<br />
PM: Well you see in this Budget, Ron, we lifted the Medicare levy by 0.1<br />
from 1.4 to 1.5 and that was basically because the Medicare levy<br />
proceeds have fallen from providing 30 per cent of the cost of<br />
Medicare, to 24 per cent of it. See the levy only brings in 24 per cent<br />
of the cost of the system. By putting that 0.1 on, we took it back to 27<br />
per cent of the cost of the system. So we are not even back to the sort<br />
of level that the Medicare levy formerly provided that was 30 per cent.<br />
Now, why is this happening? Well, the answer is because the health<br />
system is improving in its quality. Diagnostic imaging, pathology, all<br />
these referral services of much higher quality than we had when you<br />
and I were young men or boys, now there is much better diagnosis and<br />
imaging et cetera and surgical procedures. So, the cost of the system<br />
is rising then the aim, I think, always in the national health scheme like<br />
this is to have that tension between quality service, fee for service,<br />
private practice and price. Now, by and large we have kept Medicare,<br />
the total cost, running at around eight per cent of the size of the<br />
economy; eight per cent of GDP. The American system is running at<br />
16 per cent which is really now unaffordable for them. </p>
<p>So, we are all the time trying to keep the cost down and by and large<br />
we have succeeded, but I don't have to tell you anything Ron or your<br />
listeners to know that if you have let's say a serious ailment of some<br />
kind these days, the likelihood is that you are going to be referred on<br />
for further diagnosis which wouldn't have happened 20 years ago or<br />
wouldn't have happened as frequently as prevalently. That means<br />
higher costs and it is also the same with pharmaceuticals, a very large<br />
part of the health scheme is in pharmaceuticals, the drugs are now<br />
very effective, but they are also very expensive. Some can be $ 60 a<br />
pop or $ 100 a pop which we are providing for $ 2.50, particularly to<br />
aged people.<br />
RE: On the weekend President Clinton attacked the Japanese for their<br />
intransigence on trade matters. He said that they really weren't<br />
coming to the party on questions of tariffs. What is your feeling about<br />
that in terms of the Japanese because we have made a great play<br />
about opening our economy and we have, in fact, been the good<br />
performers here. The Japanese, if you talk to people anecdotally, will<br />
say they get up to all sorts of goings, are you in President Clinton's<br />
court on this?<br />
PM: Well, you mentioned opening our economy, we have really opened our<br />
economy up. We started reducing tariffs in 1988 and they will be at<br />
five per cent by 1997, that is two years time. It is one of the reasons<br />
why Western Australia, for instance, is growing so rapidly. National<br />
economic policy is savoured. This Labor Government's economic<br />
policy is savoured in terms of change, the two big primary exporting<br />
states of Western Australia and Queensland because by taking the<br />
tariff monkey off the back of Western Australia and Queensland they<br />
have both grown and that is why now the growth is here so strongly in<br />
Western Australia. So, tariff reductions work, you do it in your own<br />
best interests. But, the Japanese have made somewhat of a mistake<br />
by becoming very heavy savers, but not running the savings down their<br />
own standard of living. Their levels of housing and the quality of their<br />
housing is, by our standards, poor. The quality of their sewerage<br />
system is poor. Their transport system the same and if Japan were to<br />
lift its domestic demand and improve the life styles of Japanese<br />
people, then there would be an automatic sucking in of imports which<br />
would then ease the trade problem. But, it is a case of save, save,<br />
save, save, save, and yet not spend on a higher standard of living<br />
while in the case of the American community it is a case of spend,<br />
spend, spend, spend and not save. So, what is underlying this<br />
argument is a savings balance problem. The Japanese are very big<br />
savers and the American's aren't.<br />
RE: And, we are a bit more like the Americans if you look at our current<br />
account deficit. </p>
<p>PM: That is why we have introduced this great change in the Budget with<br />
superannuation. You see, our current account deficit problem is two<br />
per cent of GDP, it is about $ 10,000 billion, GOP this year is $ 500<br />
billion, that is the total economy, two per cent of it is about $ 10,000<br />
billion, that is the problem that we have for the year. In the Budget we<br />
have done two things to deal with that. We have taken the Budget<br />
from deficit to surplus with a turn around of around three to four per<br />
cent of GDP and by buying the tax cuts into superannuation accounts<br />
and getting employees to contribute to it, we will build on top of the<br />
nine per cent we already have there to 15 per cent. So, every person<br />
in Australia will have a 15 per cent mature superannuation<br />
contribution. What this will do is two things. It will add four per cent of<br />
GOP to savings so if we have got four per cent from the Budget and<br />
four per cent from superannuation that is eight per cent, but the<br />
problem we have in the current account is two per cent. So, we have<br />
got an eight percentage points fix for a two percentage point problem.<br />
If that four per cent happens in 2020, if we take the year 2000 as a<br />
benchmark, we add two percentage points from superannuation and<br />
let's say three to four from the Budget. So what we did last Tuesday<br />
night in the Budget is put a six percentage point saving change in for a<br />
two percentage point current account problem.'<br />
Now, that is why this Government has given Australia the sort of<br />
leadership it needs in these things. It is hasn't happened in America.<br />
They don't have such a policy in America. Americans are not saving<br />
while the Japanese are and we will be able to fuel our growth and<br />
prosperity in employment through investment because we will have the<br />
savings to pay for it where many countries like Australia won't. That is<br />
why I say, Governments like this come along only very rarely to do<br />
these sorts of things and it is the point you asked me earlier about<br />
people taking the Liberal party free of policies, without policies, I<br />
mean, who is going to walk away from a savings change of this quality<br />
which is going to underwrite Australia's future and not only that,<br />
underwrite our incomes. What it means is someone on average<br />
weekly earnings $ 33,000 will, at the end of their working life, have a<br />
pension or an income of $ 30,000.<br />
RE: Provided we can secure the funds, the superannuation funds and then<br />
managed properly, I mean, that still must be a worry for you.<br />
PM: That is a challenge I think. I think we are now building a very big<br />
system of savings, we now have to build a superannuation<br />
management system as good as our savings themselves. I think we<br />
can do that, I mean, they have had a rough time in the last year with<br />
the long term bonds because that was a world wide problem, but by<br />
and large their savings performance has been pretty good. Anyway,<br />
on the Treasury's estimates we have got very moderate savings<br />
returns in there, compound returns. </p>
<p>RE: Can I just close on a couple of matters. Senator Noel Crichton-Browne<br />
was subject to attacks upon his private life and he made those feelings<br />
known in the Senate last week. How do you feel about this move into<br />
the private lives of public figures?<br />
PM: Well, I have no time for it what so ever. I have been in Parliament for<br />
26 years and I have never ever supported, much less been involved in,<br />
attacking someone's private life. I mean, I think it is the last card in the<br />
pack. There are enough things to talk about, there are enough..<br />
differentiation points in policy without going to these private attacks.<br />
So, I don't see any value in that and, I think, it is a very bad<br />
development in Australian politics.<br />
RE: Does it worry you that with the Royal Commission announced by<br />
Premier Richard Court that the timing of that Royal Commission is<br />
about October and if the findings, in relation to Carmen Lawrence,<br />
were adverse, that would make it difficult for you in terms of election<br />
timing and also given Carmen's significant role in the Federal<br />
Government.<br />
PM: I have made my position clear about that in the past, even if it is found<br />
against Carmen Lawrence, so what? I mean, it is a political matter.<br />
The thing is there is no question here about any serious illegality or<br />
misappropriation or maladministration of public duties, this is really<br />
about an inquiry into what was going on politically in the former<br />
Cabinet. It is like me saying well look, we will have a public inquiry<br />
today into the Asia dairy scandal of the former Coalition government<br />
and we will get Malcolm Fraser and John Howard and Ian Sinclair and<br />
Peter Nixon, we'll get them over there and say ' what really happened<br />
then? What did you say to him that night you met before the Cabinet<br />
meeting?' It is a nonsense. So even if the thing " found against<br />
Carmen" it doesn't matter a tinkers cuss. It is just, in a sense, an<br />
inappropriate inquiry into not public administration or illegality or<br />
maladministration of any kind, it is an inquiry into the politics of<br />
Cabinet discussions.<br />
RE: Did you get to talk to Richard Court, the Premier, at the football<br />
yesterday?<br />
PM: I did, yes.<br />
RE: What was the exchange like?<br />
PM: Good, but not about this. I mean, if he had got onto this I would have<br />
told him exactly what I thought of it. He was talking about some other<br />
issues that affect the economy and the state in general, we had a<br />
discussion about the native title and some of those problems. I mean,<br />
I keep a dialogue with him and we can progress matters. But, things<br />
would be helped if he wasn't, I mean look, can I just say this, there is a </p>
<p>sort of a snakiness and nastiness about it all. He was the Premier who<br />
defeated Carmen Lawrence, but there is not grace in victory with him.<br />
He has not only defeated her at an election and she has gone off to<br />
make a career in public life, he has now got to run an inquiry into what<br />
was going on inside her Cabinet. I mean, it is very bad behaviour and<br />
it does nothing for the place. It does nothing for getting along with life<br />
and dealing with the public, the real public is its problems and I think<br />
that is why Hendy Cowan and Colin Barnett and others have made<br />
their views known about this, they are not very happy with it.<br />
RE: Well, Paul it is good to have you here in Perth. The weather is<br />
beautiful, the economy is moving and it is good to have you visit.<br />
PM: It couldn't be nicer, Ron. I had a lovely day yesterday, as I said, the<br />
grounds at Subiaco look like a bowling green, it was great football and<br />
I have had a very pleasant couple of days. Thank you very much.<br />
RE: Thanks for joining us today.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
