<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6395</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, OPENING OF THE CSIRO CLAYTON LABORATORY, MELBOURNE, 18 MAY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006395.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED AGAINST DELIVERY CHiECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
AT 4.00 P. M. AUST R A 1
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF THE CSIRO CLAYTON LABORATORY<br />
MELBOURNE 18 MAY 1984<br />
I am most grateful for the consideration shown by Dr Wild<br />
and members of the CSIRO Executive in deferring the opening<br />
of these laboratories to afford me the opportunity of<br />
participation today.<br />
I know all connected with the Divisions of Chemical and Wood<br />
Technology, and Mathematics and Statistics, will find these<br />
new facilities a considerable improvement over those<br />
available at the former premises in South Melbourne.<br />
When facilities for other CSIRO Divisions are completed on<br />
this site, the entire complex will have the capacity to<br />
become a world class centre for technological research. By<br />
its very location, providing as it does for close<br />
interaction with the adjacent university and with industry,<br />
it has a natural advantage.<br />
The work being carried out by the new division of Chemical<br />
and Wood Technology is of particular significance. It is a<br />
clear demonstration of commercially relevant research. Such<br />
research is vital to Australia's future prosperity.<br />
Much of the Chemical and Wood Technology Division's work is<br />
carried out in conjunction with Australian industry. Indeed<br />
the Division already has a number of industrial developments<br />
to its credit. Importantly these achievements include<br />
exan~ ples of how high technology research can provide for the<br />
need for both advanced product and improved process.<br />
Notable recent activities include:<br />
Development with Repco of a process for converting<br />
small diameter logs into structural wood product<br />
called " scr imber" l<br />
Successful scale-up of the " Sirofloc" water<br />
clarification process with a commercial plant now<br />
in operation at Bell Ba'y, Tasmania.<br />
Investigation into ways of substituting wood fibre<br />
for asbestos in re-inforced cement products. </p>
<p>The new laboratories will enable the Division to pursue even<br />
more actively its industrially rel-ated research. A feature<br />
of the building itself is the large process bays provided<br />
for the scaling-up of research from the laboratory stage to<br />
pilot plant operation. This will allow demonstration of<br />
many of the new ideas generated by research staff for<br />
industry. The ultimate test of success for most CSIRO research is its<br />
likely benefit to the Australian industry and-community.<br />
Research and Development R and D should not be ends in<br />
themselves. They must become economically productive either<br />
directly or indirectly. They should be linked to a-range of<br />
other considerations, including quality control and<br />
marketing. In this regard I am pleased to see that one of<br />
the manufacturing industry research topics to which C7SIRO is<br />
giving highest priority is that of using advanced<br />
technologies for process and quality control. This<br />
correctly recognises the fundamental importance of achieving<br />
high quality if Australia is to improve its industrial<br />
competitiveness. There can be no doubt that successful industrial application<br />
has not been generally characteristic of Australia's broad<br />
research effort. While we compare favourably with other<br />
countries in terms of basic research we are in the top<br />
eight in OECD we are well behind in turning these research<br />
results into new industrial opportunities.<br />
We are failing to turn R and D into dollars. We are giving<br />
too much emphacis to the 11R" and too often neglecting the<br />
11D1 dimension of it all.<br />
Greater effort should therefore be made to capitalise on ou:<br />
indigenous research.<br />
It is important that commercialisation of CSIRO development! s<br />
be carried out wherever possible by Australian firms, since<br />
this not only maximises CSIRO's assistance to Australian<br />
industry, but also maximises the return to the community on<br />
its investment in CSIRO.<br />
This '* does not mean, however, that all Australian research<br />
should be reserved for exploitation by Australian industry.<br />
That would go against the principle of the free exchange of<br />
ideas. As a nation which has had the capac-ity to produce<br />
four Nobel Prizewinners the same number as Japan with<br />
eight times our population we must shoulder our<br />
responsibility. But if Australian research is taken up<br />
overseas, as it will be in some cases, there should be<br />
provision for some of the benefits of commercial<br />
exploitation to be returned to Australia by way of joint<br />
ventures or royalties. </p>
<p>I would also suggest ( and here I am repeating a theme I have<br />
taken up elsewhere) that it is vital that support for<br />
research be directed deliberately to the best research<br />
workers. This should apply as much within CSIRO as<br />
elsewhere. If Australia is to maintain its lead, or indeed survive, in<br />
a wide range of national endeavours, whether they be pure<br />
science or new technology for industry, then we shall-have<br />
to identify the best and most forward-looking-research<br />
workers, and ensure that their excellence and enterprise are<br />
properly supported.<br />
Quality and opportunity should be our key criteria for<br />
support. To the extent they are, results will flow back to<br />
the nation as a whole, in advancement of scientific<br />
knowledge, and a vigorous economy based on technologically<br />
aware and up-to-date industries.<br />
Obvious as this might seem, the plain Fact of the matter is<br />
that we as a nation have a long way to go to achieve a<br />
vigorous economy based on technologically aware and<br />
up-to-date industries industries working arm in arm with<br />
our research establishment. What we nE. ed is a situation<br />
where our research community and industry meet together,*<br />
talk together, plan together and work together. This shouli<br />
be a priority objective for all concerned.<br />
In this regard the results of several recent surveys are<br />
disturbing. They reveal that many Australian executives are<br />
confused about the application of new technology. A high<br />
percentage of those interviewed in one survey saw foreign<br />
competitors as more technologically advanced and making<br />
better use of technology. Notwithstanding this, more than<br />
two thirds still professed themselves satisfied with the way<br />
research and development was being carried out within their<br />
own organisat ions.<br />
No-one in Australia can take comfort from these findings<br />
whatever inconsistencies there may be between the attitudes<br />
expressed. One factor at work clearly is a complacency born of the<br />
inwa'rd-looking nature of some areas of our economy.<br />
Government willingness in the past to shelter areas of<br />
industry, and thus lessening the edge of competition, may<br />
have made industry, and top executives in particular,<br />
indifferent to new technologies.<br />
Certainly this complacency cannot continue if we are to<br />
compete with countries whose industries are making greater<br />
efforts than ourselves to utilise new productivity raising<br />
technologies. </p>
<p>4.<br />
The'adoption of new technologies to revitalise existing<br />
industry and promote the development of new industries is<br />
crucial to the maintenance and improvement of the living<br />
standards of the Australian people. The success with which<br />
we do so will also have an important bearing on the extent<br />
to which we ultimately get to grips with unacceptably high<br />
levels of unemployment.<br />
The Australian Labor Government, with its commitment to<br />
consolidating the economic recovery which is now under way,<br />
and its interest in establishing a sound basis for<br />
Australia's long-term economic development, wants a close<br />
nexus to be forged between science and technology and<br />
industry development.<br />
This emphasis on practical research and development does nol:<br />
deny in any way the importance of basic research. What the<br />
Government seeks is a balance between pure and applied<br />
research. As a nation with fewer financial resources than<br />
many of our international competitors, it is essential that<br />
we make the best use of our scientific resources.<br />
We can accept that, as a small country in terms of<br />
population, we cannot match the research and development<br />
capacity of overseas establishments in some particular areas<br />
of specialisation. In such cases it may be advantageous to<br />
monitor their output and purchase the relevant rights. With<br />
suitable modification to Australian conditions, it may be<br />
profitable to do so.<br />
But there will be cases where, if we focus our attention and<br />
exert our will and enterprise, we can lead the world. Vie<br />
should not shrink from doing so. Interscan, in which Dr<br />
Wild had such a direct hand, is a clear instance of the<br />
possibilities which exist. The Siding Spring Telescope<br />
which I had the privilege to open the cother day, would be<br />
another example.<br />
My more general concern, however, is that development of<br />
Australia's capacity in the field of science and technology<br />
be seen as an integral part of our efforts to build viable,<br />
internationally competitive, Australian industries.<br />
The discussion paper on a n ational technology strategy<br />
recently released by my colleague, Barry Jones, and debated<br />
in Parliament only last week, is an important contribution<br />
to the process of developing an active and coherent approach<br />
to technology issues and their relevance for the growth of<br />
Australian industry. </p>
<p>As Sir Gustav Nossal said earlier this week of this draft<br />
strategy: is important because it identifies both the<br />
essential role of science and technology in long-term<br />
economic health and the serious quantatitive and<br />
attitudinal deficiencies in Australia that limit the<br />
contribution which our science sector can make".<br />
That paper set out five national priorities as matters for<br />
debate: 1. Raising Australia's skill base;<br />
2. Bridging the gap between research and industry;<br />
3. Moving towards high value added goods and services;<br />
4. Creating stronger and more appropriate economic<br />
structures which will provide goods which can be placed<br />
on a world market; and<br />
Overcoming the problems of overspecialised regional<br />
economies such as in coal, steel and heavy manufacturing<br />
industries.<br />
I think it very important that this statement of priorities<br />
be submitted to the closest scrutiny. On the basis of a<br />
constructively critical dialogue around the issues involved,<br />
the development of a relevant, well-co-ordinated policy<br />
approach in this important area should become possible.<br />
In the meantime, the Government has already introduced a<br />
number of positive measures to overcome the problems it sees<br />
in the area. The Government has given particular priority<br />
to the stimulation of the level of industrial research<br />
development activity through the provision of financial<br />
incentives and support for new technologies<br />
In 1983/ 84, substantially increased funds were<br />
provided for science and technology research under<br />
the Australian Research Grants Scheme and for<br />
Marine Science and Technology programs;<br />
A national Biotechnology Scheme has been<br />
established; Additional funds were provided for public interest<br />
projects for industrial development and for the<br />
establishment of innovation centres;<br />
New research associations have been formed to<br />
encourage co-operative industry research<br />
development, </p>
<p>w 6.<br />
Government purchasing policy has been strengthened<br />
and offsets policies are being reviewed to see how<br />
these areas of Government activity can best be<br />
co-ordinated with our approach to science and<br />
techology; and<br />
We have introduced the National Research<br />
Fellowships Scheme to provide individuals and<br />
research teams with opportunities to undertake<br />
research of national significance, with a view to<br />
strengthening Australia's development capacity.<br />
The Government has also supported the establishment of<br />
Sirotech to take developments pioneered by the CSIRO to<br />
commercial application. It is particularly pleasing to note<br />
that universities and research institutions have also<br />
adopted this approach by setting up commercial ventures to<br />
market their own research findings.<br />
The Government is, as well, offering substantial taxation<br />
benefits to promote the development of a venture capital<br />
C market in Australia. We aim to reduce the risk in taking up<br />
new technologies and to help small business to exploit<br />
available market oportunities. This should help businessmen<br />
to take Australian, or overseas technological breakthrou-ghs,<br />
and turn them into profitable business ventures.<br />
All these measures, in one way or another, are designed to<br />
close the gap between research and product development; to<br />
accelerate the rate of technology transfer into new products<br />
and processes.<br />
But there still needs to be much greater dialogue between<br />
industry and scientists and we need to look closely at<br />
mechanisms to facilitate this.<br />
Australian scientists themselves should examine their role<br />
and be alert to opportunities to transfer technology from<br />
laboratories, universities and research institutions to<br />
businesses in Australia.<br />
At the same time, decision makers in the business community,<br />
whose attitudes to new technology are so critical, could<br />
usef'ully reassess their individual R and D efforts, to<br />
ensure that they are making an optimal contribution to the<br />
long-term strength of their enterprises.<br />
We have the research capabilities, the creativity and<br />
managerial talent to meet the challenge.<br />
The official opening of this new laboratory, with its<br />
excellent facilities, will I hope, provide renewed impetus<br />
to CSIRO's research and technology transfer activities and<br />
mark the beginning of a new era in sciEntific research and<br />
industry collaboration. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
