<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11697</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            AT THE NATIONAL LAUNCH INDIGENOUS NATIONAL            LITERACY AND NUMERACY STRATEGY, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much to Dr Kemp, Mr Scott, the Chairman of the Corporation,</p>
<p> to Jimmy Little and the other ambassadors for the strategy, ladies and</p>
<p> gentlemen. And may I also acknowledge the Daruk people, the traditional</p>
<p> owners of this land and pay respect to their very rich culture as part</p>
<p> of the indigenous community of Australia.</p>
<p>Today is a moment to announce and to launch a strategy which is very</p>
<p> much an exercise in practical reconciliation. It is a strategy that addresses</p>
<p> an area of demonstrated and unarguable disadvantage for the indigenous</p>
<p> within the Australian population. The right to a decent education as the</p>
<p> right to a decent health system and opportunities of gainful employment</p>
<p> are those fundamental birthrights that we ought to take for granted for</p>
<p> all Australians. The sad fact however is that within the broader Australian</p>
<p> community, there are many people who leave the school system unable to</p>
<p> properly read or write or to add or subtract. And the handicap that that</p>
<p> represents for them as they go through life is immense. And the burden,</p>
<p> both psychological and also in practical terms, is considerable and it's</p>
<p> something that is with them all the days of their life. I think it is</p>
<p> very important that we see the problem of literacy and numeracy as being</p>
<p> a community problem and a community challenge as well as it having a very</p>
<p> special dimension and being a special difficulty so far as indigenous</p>
<p> Australians are concerned.</p>
<p>Today is a very positive day because you have governments and communities</p>
<p> coming together in a spirit of good will and working together to address</p>
<p> in a very practical way a significant problem. And I want Jimmy, to acknowledge</p>
<p> the warmth and the generosity and the inspirational character of the remarks</p>
<p> that you addressed at the commencement of today's gathering. It was</p>
<p> a simple moving statement of a person's love of his country, his</p>
<p> deep respect for his indigenous culture and his desire to work with everybody</p>
<p> of goodwill within the Australian community to overcome areas of disadvantage.</p>
<p>It is a sad fact that Aboriginal children are only half as likely as</p>
<p> other children within our community to complete secondary school. And</p>
<p> although indigenous retention rates have quadrupled since the 1970s, they</p>
<p> are still only half those of the rest of the community.</p>
<p>But I think it is important whilst acknowledging that continuing disadvantage</p>
<p> and important to see today's announcement in the context of addressing</p>
<p> that disadvantage, it's important also to recall the fact that progress</p>
<p> is being made. Too often in this broader debate, we only hear what has</p>
<p> not been accomplished and the challenges that lie ahead and we hear very</p>
<p> little about some of the progress. Undoubtedly not enough that has been</p>
<p> made under successive governments let me say in a number of important</p>
<p> areas. And let me mention some of them. The proportion of indigenous adults</p>
<p> who've never attended school has fallen from a level of 14% in the</p>
<p> 1970s to 3% today. The proportion of indigenous children who complete</p>
<p> secondary schooling has increased fourfold since the 1970s. The proportion</p>
<p> of indigenous people with post secondary school qualifications has doubled</p>
<p> in the last ten years and indigenous higher education enrolments have</p>
<p> tripled over the same period. And specifically in the area of training,</p>
<p> the number of indigenous students in higher education has risen from under</p>
<p> 7,000 in 1996, to over 8,000 in 1999. Ten years ago, there were an estimated</p>
<p> 15,000 indigenous students involved in vocational education and training.</p>
<p> And by 1998, that number had risen to nearly 45,000 students. In 1994-95,</p>
<p> a bare five or six years ago, there were only 817 indigenous traineeship</p>
<p> commencements. By 1997-98 that number had grown to a record of 5,200.</p>
<p>Now I mention these things not to weave any particular story with statistics,</p>
<p> but rather to make the point that there is hope that if a commitment and</p>
<p> an investment of time and resources is made, progress can be achieved.</p>
<p> And it is very important in the ongoing debate about reconciliation, the</p>
<p> ongoing debate about addressing demonstrated areas of indigenous disadvantage</p>
<p> that we recognise the scale of the challenge ahead of us as well as recognising</p>
<p> that with the implementation of the right programs significant progress</p>
<p> has been made and continues to be made.</p>
<p>And why I very enthusiastically responded to David Kemp's invitation</p>
<p> to come here today and to formally launch this $27 million strategy was</p>
<p> because I saw it very much in the context of what I've just described.</p>
<p> I see it as a practical way of addressing disadvantage and that has been</p>
<p> something the Government has sought, not always successfully but always</p>
<p> with goodwill and good intentions, the Government has sought to do over</p>
<p> the last four years, to put an emphasis on those areas that mean that</p>
<p> the indigenous within the Australian population as a group remain the</p>
<p> most significantly disadvantaged. That is an unarguable fact whatever</p>
<p> the views of the rest of the community may be. And it is our responsibility</p>
<p> and it is particularly my responsibility as the Prime Minister to address</p>
<p> that. And today's program which goes to the heart as David has said,</p>
<p> of disadvantage. He records some of the problems. The lack of attendance.</p>
<p> Part of the program is to encourage a greater effort on the part of parents</p>
<p> to ensure that their children attend school. It acknowledges the significantly</p>
<p> high rate of deafness and hearing impairment of children, and as somebody</p>
<p> who himself in his very young days had a significant hearing impairment</p>
<p> that was first discovered through a routine health check at the government</p>
<p> school that I attended here in Sydney, I am very conscious of the value</p>
<p> of that kind of approach and that kind of program to young indigenous</p>
<p> people who suffer that same disability.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I am very happy to launch this strategy. I see</p>
<p> it taking its place along side the commitments that the Government and</p>
<p> State governments around Australia, and let me say that in so many of</p>
<p> these areas it is our desire to work closely with governments of both</p>
<p> political persuasions in order to solve problems which are our common</p>
<p> challenge and our common responsibility. You can't implement a literacy</p>
<p> and numeracy strategy be it for the population generally, or for the indigenous</p>
<p> within our population, you can't implement it effectively unless</p>
<p> you have the cooperation of the State government. And I'm delighted,</p>
<p> I haven't spotted him yet through the gloom that is the function</p>
<p> of television lights, but he's on the list. I'm very pleased</p>
<p> to acknowledge the presence of Dr Ken Boston, the Director General of</p>
<p> Education here in New South Wales, as well as the representatives of many</p>
<p> other educational organisations both government and independent, and also</p>
<p> the leaders of parent groups from schools within the western suburbs of</p>
<p> Sydney.</p>
<p>I would also like to particularly thank Mark Patterson, the Executive</p>
<p> Director of the Australian Chamber of Commerce and Industry because this</p>
<p> is a partnership. Dare I say it it's an expression of the social</p>
<p> coalition where you have the government, you have business, you have the</p>
<p> volunteer sector of our community, and you have individuals working together</p>
<p> trying to uplift people, providing them with the tools so that they can</p>
<p> have a better life. We will never remove disadvantage within the indigenous</p>
<p> of Australia unless we address the depravation they suffer in areas of</p>
<p> education, and health and employment. They are to me fundamental to the</p>
<p> process of reconciliation. That is not to say that reconciliation doesn't</p>
<p> have a spiritual component. Of course it does. It is a multidimensional</p>
<p> concept and different people see it in different ways. But a fundamental</p>
<p> element of it is to address these areas of disadvantage. And I see today's</p>
<p> strategy which represents a firm commitment of resources from the federal</p>
<p> government, as well as a commitment to better direct existing resources</p>
<p> going towards indigenous programs, I see it as a very important element</p>
<p> in the reconciliation process and a very practical gesture towards addressing</p>
<p> the disadvantaged.</p>
<p>I think all of us share to the full the values expressed in Jimmy's</p>
<p> very inspirational introductory speech. He brought together I think feelings</p>
<p> that we all have  a desire not to forget the past or to misunderstand</p>
<p> what was involved in the past, but a recognition that if we work together</p>
<p> in goodwill we can build a better and a fairer future. You can't</p>
<p> build a better and a fairer future if people don't have the fundamental</p>
<p> educational tools to share in that future. And attacking deficiencies</p>
<p> in literacy and numeracy either within the population generally and most</p>
<p> particularly within the indigenous population is a very important element.</p>
<p> I thank you very warmly and particularly the corporation for having us</p>
<p> here today. And I've enjoyed the opportunity of hearing something</p>
<p> of your programs, and of meeting those that who being assisted. And I</p>
<p> thank you very sincerely for that and I have very great pleasure in launching</p>
<p> the strategy. I know it will be a success. I thank the ambassadors for</p>
<p> being here today, and in advance for the role that they will play in the</p>
<p> very successful implementation of what is in every sense of the word a</p>
<p> gesture of practical reconciliation amongst all Australians. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
