<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3304</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA TUESDAY 18 JUNE 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003304.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA,<br />
TUESDAY 18 JUNE 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Ladies and gentlemen, you know that the applications<br />
to the Chief Australian Electoral Officer, for recounts in Queensland<br />
and Western Australia have been rejected. The count is already complete<br />
also in Tasmania and South Australia. The count is not finished yet in<br />
either New South Wales or Victoria. It appears unlikely that the results<br />
will be so close as to justify a recount in either of those States.<br />
Accordingly, I think that we can go ahead on the assumption that the<br />
Parliament will meet on Tuesday 9 July. It will be opened by the<br />
Governor-General, Sir Paul Hasluck. He will leave Canberra the<br />
following day and the Governor-General designate, Sir John Kerr will<br />
arrive later that day and then on Thursday, Sir John Kerr, we expect,<br />
will be sworn in in front of the two Houses which with him constitute<br />
the Parliament. I should also like to tell you that the Australian<br />
Government has received confirmation that the Chinese Government<br />
exploded a nuclear weapon device in the atmosphere over its territory<br />
yesterday. We understand that the Chinese explosion was somewhat less<br />
than a megaton in size, and that it appears to have occurred at Lop Nor<br />
at about 4 p. m. yesterday. It is a matter of deep concern to the<br />
Australian Government that the Chinese Government has conducted a<br />
further nuclear test which is likely to lead to the deposit of radio<br />
active fallout not only within its own territory but over a wide<br />
area including, in the longer term, Australia.<br />
Since the establishment of diplomatic relations with<br />
China in December 1972, the Australian Government has made known to<br />
Chinese leaders its opposition to Chinese nuclear weapon tests on a<br />
number of occasions. On 10 April last year the Government made a<br />
formal protest to the Chinese Government expressing Australia's strong<br />
opposition to the conduct of nuclear weapons tests and reaffirmed the<br />
Australian Government's view that atmospheric nuclear weapons testing<br />
is contrary to international law; during his visit to China in May<br />
last year, Dr. Cairns re-stated-the.. Australian position to Premier<br />
Chou En-lai; I issued a statement ex pressing deep concern following<br />
the last Chinese nuclear test on 27 June last year; and soon afterwards<br />
formal notes of protest-were delivered both to the Chinese Foreign Ministry<br />
in Peking and the Chinese Embassy in Canberra. Most recently, I<br />
vigorously re-stated the Australian position during my meeting with<br />
Chairman Mao Tse-Tung on 2 November.<br />
Since China does not accept the jurisdiction of the<br />
International Court of Justice and is nota party to the 1928 General Act<br />
for the Pacific Settlement of International Disputes, it is not feasible<br />
for Australia to initiate proceedings against China in the Court.<br />
Nevertheless, the Australian Government considers that the Chinese<br />
Government, as well as the French Government, has a clear obligation<br />
towards the international community to prevent the dangers of<br />
environmental pollution. The present Australian Government has<br />
consistently opposed nuclear weapon testing by all countries and will<br />
continue to work vigorously for a complete cessation of such testing. / 12 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Are there any questions that you would like to ask?<br />
QUESTION: In the last few weeks there have been a number of nuclear<br />
explosions; the Indians, the French, the Chinese. And there has also<br />
been President Nixon's decision to give nuclear assistance to both<br />
Israel and Egypt. Now you Sir, have only made a comment on the French<br />
tests and today on the Chinese tests; no comment has come on the<br />
Indian tests or President Nixon's decision. Have you any comment on<br />
those two?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Senator Willesee the Foreign Minister, has previously<br />
made statements, I think on two occasions, about the Indian testing.<br />
The Indian testing of course was claimed to be for peaceful purposes<br />
and it was underground. The Chinese and the French testing have been<br />
in the atmosphere. We have no details of the offers which President<br />
Nixon has made to Egypt and Israel in the nuclear energy field.<br />
We would hope that these offers like all transfers of nuclear technology<br />
equipment or materials, will be carried out under the most stringent<br />
safeguards. QUESTION: Have you formally protested to Russia or China over the<br />
nuclear testing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Arrangements are in hand in this matter with respect<br />
to France and China. Russia and the United States have not tested and<br />
Britain has not tested in the atmosphere for over ten years.<br />
QUESTION: Does this mean that Mr. Renouf, for instance, will seek<br />
to see the Chinese and French Ambassadors?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I have got no more to say on this at the moment.<br />
I am not going to have those other foreign offices reading about<br />
matters in the newspapers before any contact has been established<br />
between them and our representatives.<br />
QUESTION: Do you remain satisfied with the effect of the credit<br />
restrictions on the building and housing industries; are you<br />
concerned that too severe an impact is being made by the shortage of<br />
finance in this area?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The reduced liquidity in general has of course had an<br />
effect on the construction industry. It was intended to have an effect<br />
on the construction industry. It is regrettable that most of the State<br />
Governments have not acted where they could in these matters. It is only<br />
because of the action that the federal Government has taken within the<br />
constitutional powers available to it that there has been a reduction<br />
in the cost of land for instance. And there has been some reduction<br />
in the respective commercial construction of buildings. It ought to be<br />
possible for people to get housing land more cheaply. It ought to be<br />
possible for them to build houses more cheaply. It appears that each<br />
,-of those things will come about. our regret is that that we have had to<br />
-, rely entirely in most cases, right along the eastern seaboarid, on<br />
federal initiatives in this regard; the States have been utterly inert.<br />
In Victoria in fact the State Government has used Australian Government<br />
housing funds to give a boost to land inflation Sunbury and Melton. </p>
<p>-3<br />
QUESTION: Do you agree with Premier Dunstan's claim that your<br />
treatment, financial treatment, of the States and your economic policies<br />
are contrary to Labor policy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I don't agree with it. Of course I don't. I don't<br />
depart from Labor policy in any respect. I carry it out.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Wran is reported this morning as saying that Mr. Dunstan<br />
jumped the gun in making his comments before next week's discussions on<br />
consumer tax. Do you agree that he jumped the gun in making that statement?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I don't comment in terms like this.<br />
QUESTION: On dealing with the States, Mr. Ejelke-Petersen took time off<br />
on Friday on radio and television to accuse you of trying to smash the<br />
States. Is that a valid criticism?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, as far as I could tell from the newspaper reports<br />
of Mr. Bjelke-Petersen's telecast and broadcast, and I went to the authentic<br />
organ in these respects, the Brisbane Courier Mail, he regurgitated at the<br />
expense of the Queensland taxpayers and therefore at the expense of the<br />
Australian taxpayers in general, the thesis which he developed at inordinate<br />
length at the Premiers Conference. You heard him say it. You notice that<br />
not a single other representative supported him. Sir Gordon Chalk, the<br />
other representative from Queensland at the Premiers Conference exhibited<br />
notable irritation when he was not showing boredom at what Mr. Ejelke-<br />
Petersen had to say. The interesting part of Mr. Bjelke-Petersen ' s<br />
thesis I thought was that he was suggesting that my Government should<br />
do what the Chifley Government had done in the late 19401s. I would be<br />
very happy to do so, he didn't acknowledge however, that there were in<br />
the aftermath of the war, in the last few months of the war, options<br />
available to the Australian Government which are not available to the<br />
Australian Government in peacetime. He was suggesting for instance that<br />
we should subsidise products which featured in the Consumer Price Index.<br />
The Chifley Government did do that. That is true. The Chifley Government<br />
was also able to restrain the overall position as regards prices and<br />
incomes for some months. Mr. Ejelke-Petersen was wishing that the<br />
Australian Government of today should do what the Australian Government<br />
was able to do at the conclusion and in the aftermath of the war.<br />
It was an interesting position in one way, but it didn't grab the interest<br />
of anybody else at the Premiers Conference.<br />
QUESTION: In 1969 you advocated a new federal system which was based<br />
on a House of Representatives for international and nation-wide matters,<br />
an assembly for each of the bigger States, and separate regional<br />
assemblies for areas outside the cities. Could I ask whether you are<br />
still in favour of such a proposal and would you comment on the<br />
practicalities of it being implemented?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I commented on the practicalities at the time. I believe<br />
I said that if we were making arrangements for our continent today that<br />
what you say is what we would try to achieve. I didn't say that I thought<br />
it was practicable now. But nevertheless I think there is some use in<br />
looking at the overall geographic and economic situation where possible.<br />
The State boundaries were not set by Australian politicians. They were<br />
set by British public servants in the middle of last century or earlier.<br />
Local government boundaries were set mostly by State politicians about<br />
years ago. Now nobody really looking at the best way to govern<br />
Australia in the circumstances which have developed where settlement<br />
has taken place, where resources have been discovered would suggest that<br />
0/ </p>
<p>our State boundaries are ideal. In fact very few people would say that<br />
they had very much relevance. Again I think most people would realise<br />
particularly looking at the way settlement has changed in the last<br />
quarter of a century, that local government boundaries haven't<br />
got very much relevance. Nevertheless, while I think it is fair<br />
enough looking at some of these things with fresh eyes, I am not<br />
suggesting that these things are immediately practicable.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Dunstan said over the weekend that he believed that it<br />
was essential for the Labor Party to decide at its federal conference<br />
that the federal Government should give a fixed percentage of income<br />
tax back to the States. Could you tell us your views on this matter<br />
and do you agree with that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't agree with that. I don't remember any reports<br />
that Mr. Dunstan has said that. I remember Mr. Snedden saying it.<br />
But I don't agree with it. The reason is that Australia is very variable<br />
in its taxability. If the States were to raise through their own income<br />
taxes on individuals and companies, the amount of money which they receive<br />
from the Australian Government by way of revenue assistance now, we would<br />
have the situation where income tax rates in Victoria would ye very much<br />
lower than they are. In the other four States they would be very much<br />
higher. our position in Australia is quite different from say the<br />
position in the United States. In the United States you will find<br />
east and west, New York, California, north and south, Illinois and Texas;<br />
states of comparable population and economic power. In Australia we do<br />
not have that situation. None of us can expect to see that situation.<br />
And in those circumstances in Australia it is necessary to have income<br />
tax on individuals and on companiesraised by the one government. And<br />
that must be the Australian Government. There is no question that that<br />
is the Australian Labor Party's attitude. It has been for over 30 years.<br />
It was thrashed out between Prime Minister Curtin and the Premiers,<br />
particularly Premier McKell, back in 1942. And it is quite clear in the<br />
ALP's platform that there should be an Australian Government monopoly in<br />
the raising of income tax. And that is not a matter on which there is a<br />
division of opinion until three months ago, between the Labor Party on<br />
one side, and the Liberal/ Country Parties on the other side. It is the<br />
principle on which Sir Robert Menzies and his successors all acted.<br />
It is quite idle to suggest we ever could in Australia have a situation<br />
where income tax of a certain percentage went to the States. It would<br />
not be fair to the States; because they need a variable degree of<br />
assistance in their revenues and that is what happened. My Government<br />
has refined the process of specifying to an increased degree the amount<br />
of assistance, the nature of assistance which the Australian Government<br />
will give to the State Governments. The State Governments have the<br />
responsibility in a great number of fields where the Australian Government<br />
wishes to see government services upgraded. The only way to get those<br />
government services upgraded we believe, is to specify how the money will<br />
be spent. South Australia has been much more co-operative in this field<br />
than the other States. It has come to an agreement with the Australian<br />
Government in all the relevant fields, urban public transport, sewerage,<br />
land commissions, regional development Monarto where the Australian<br />
Government has responsibility if a State Government-gives it authority<br />
as in the construction of railways there to. We have made a very great<br />
commitment over $ 80 million to connect Adelaide to the rest of<br />
the Australian railway system; also another $ 80 million to have an<br />
all-weather railway from that system in South Australia to the Northern<br />
Territory. It is a very clear example of where a flat rate assistance<br />
to the States doesn't help the States who need it most. </p>
<p>QUESTION: During the election campaign you mentioned, you foreshadowed,<br />
various amendments to the Prices Justification Act. And Mr. Crean also<br />
said that he thought it might be sensible to have a second tribunal<br />
simply to look at the question of retail price rises. I just wondered<br />
in your consideration of the amendments to the Act, do you now favour<br />
expanding the resources of the existing tribunal to cope with retail<br />
prices or whether in fact, to introduce a second tribunal?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It will be some months before anything can be done<br />
along these lines. The resources of the Tribunal are being expanded as<br />
quickly as it can digest those additional resources. The Tribunal does in<br />
fact deal with some retail matters already because of all the largest<br />
retail companies in Australia that fall within its pervue.<br />
QUESTION: On the tax question Mr. Whitlam, would the Commonwealth<br />
Government be prepared to collect State consumer taxes on behalf of<br />
the States as it now does for payroll taxes for the States?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This matter was raised at the Premiers Conference, and<br />
I said we will consider any suggestions you make but there is no<br />
commitment in this regard. You will remember that the Tasmanian<br />
Government imposed a tax on tobacco, the people who sold tobacco products,<br />
and this was challenged in the High Court by the Australian Government.<br />
It was supported by most if not all of the State Governments.<br />
And in constitutional terms it was upheld but the particular technique<br />
of raising it was rejected by the High Court. There was some reference<br />
to this at the Premiers Conference; the general question of consumer<br />
taxes; and I said that we would be prepared to discuss any proposition<br />
they put up. They are in fact discussing it, the States are, their<br />
officials with our officials, they wanted our officials to be there also,<br />
on Thursday in Melbourne. But there is no commitment to raise it.<br />
But obviously we are ready to co-operate with them in discussing any of<br />
these matters.<br />
QUESTION: They seemed to be under the impression when they left the<br />
Premiers Conference that there was a commitment.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is certainly a commitment if you like to discuss<br />
any proposition they put up.<br />
OQUESTION: Do you accept the role of Dr. Cairns, as described for<br />
himself as Deputy Prime Minister, as something of an overall co-ordinator<br />
of economic policy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't remember this description but it certainly<br />
would be expected, I expect, that Dr. Cairns would take a great interest<br />
in economic policy. Of course he should, and he has.<br />
QUESTION: Do you support the view by Dr. Cairns that the introductiQn<br />
of colour television should be deferred as an anti-inflationary measure?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think this is quite an arguable proposition. But we<br />
discussed this over a year ago and we all thought then that it was too.<br />
l. ate to thin it out. Too many investments have been made to delay it. / 16 </p>
<p>QUESTION: Could I ask the same question about Dr. Cairns comment on<br />
the metric conversion, whether it should be delayed or suspended?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well you ought to ask Mr. Morrison about this. It is<br />
already in many respects far advanced. I think I might be able to give<br />
you some percentages of what has been done already there. Primary<br />
Industry is 75% metricised now, and will be wholly so in 1976.<br />
About 70% of the cost of converting the steel industry has already been<br />
expended, in the transport industry, freight rates are completely converted.<br />
And taking into account the conversion of road signs, which is to take<br />
effect on 1 July, more than 90% of the total outlay has been expended.<br />
Over 70% of the new road signs have already been constructed. Metrication<br />
of the building and construction industry is well advanced. Of all<br />
public works projects for this coming year, 64% is to metric design.<br />
Now there may be fields other to those where it would be possible or<br />
advantageous to defer or thin out metrication.<br />
QUESTION: Were you disappointed to hear Mr. Dunstan who has so long<br />
been a supporter of yours, publicly attack you over your attitude to<br />
the States at the ALP meeting in South Australia?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I wasn't disappointed, I wans't surprised. I am used to<br />
Premiers making such statements this year, in past years, whether they are<br />
Labor or Liberal or Country Party in one notable instance; or whether the<br />
person in my position is Labor or Liberal; but never I trust,<br />
Country Party! If I was in Mr. Dunstan's position, I might speak as he<br />
has if he was in my position, I am certain that he would speak and act<br />
as I have. The only difference between Mr. Dunstan and the other Premiers<br />
is that he is a more effective speaker. The only th--na tiiat I volunteer<br />
in this respect is ' 1h: t I wouldn't like local government to believe that<br />
the attitude of the Australian Government, the Labor Government, or the<br />
Labor Party in general accords to the views that Mr. Dunstan has expressed<br />
about local government in his State. The role of local government in<br />
Australia varies very greatly from State to State. In Queensland for<br />
instance, local government is responsible to a much larger extent for<br />
expenditure of the total public expenditure, national, state, local<br />
government, than any of the other States. In South Australia I believe<br />
it is responsible for a very small percentage of the total governmental<br />
expenditure. The Labor Party has had at successive federal conferences<br />
the supreme policy making body of the party, emphasised the increasing<br />
responsibility of local government. And to take one specific instance<br />
which Mr. Dunstan mentioned, the platform states that the administrative<br />
arrangements should be altered to include on the Loan Council a<br />
representative that is chosen by local government and semi-government<br />
authorities in each State. I tried to do that last September, to<br />
alter the financial agreement under which the Loan Council operates,<br />
by having a representative chosen by the council of an alderman in each<br />
State sitting on the Loan Council beside the representative of the State<br />
Government and the representative of the Australian Government.<br />
My efforts failed. I was trying to carry out the ALP's policy in that<br />
respect. But we have done a very great deal for local government and<br />
we intend to do more. It is because the State Government have in some<br />
cases downgraded or ignored, or outsted local government, that we find<br />
so mnay of the growing centres of Australian population badly serviced.<br />
For instance it was unconscionable that the Sydney Water Board or<br />
the Melbourne Metropolitan Board of Works should be so denied proper<br />
financial resources. It is for that reason that we have madedeliberate<br />
efforts to enable them to carry out their functions. And there is no doubt<br />
that the Australian people responded to that effort. In that local<br />
government referendum for instance, it was carried in New South Wales<br />
and it was close to being carried in Victoria. It wasn't close to being<br />
carried in the smaller States. </p>
<p>7.<br />
But in the large States it is realised that the proper facilities for<br />
communities depends on local government getting a fairer share, having a<br />
fairer go. I think you all should have a copy of that book we produced<br />
last month, Australian Government Assistance to Local Government projects,<br />
I commend it to you. You will'see the range of programs which we<br />
have, the number of federal Departments which are involved and the way<br />
that local government can get assistance from them.<br />
QUESTION: In an interstate commission, which you propose to re-establish,<br />
will you widen its powers to use it to control prices of goods travelling<br />
interstate, using it as an anti-inflationary vehicle?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That is a very good idea. I will take it a-board.<br />
There may easily be such a constitutional power available to the<br />
Australian Government if and when it sets up the interstate commission.<br />
You will remember that the Commission, the Constitution says that there<br />
shall be an interstate commission. The Chifley Government set up one in<br />
1912 I think, and then the members were appointed for 7 years and their<br />
terms expired in 1919. No new members were ever appointed. Then the<br />
Menzies Government in 1950 being a new broom, abolished the Act.<br />
Now Mr. Snedden I was interested to see, asked a question in the last<br />
Parliament about re-establishing it and I gave him an answer, it was<br />
on the last day, it appeared in the weekly hansard, that we propose to<br />
set it up immediately after the double dissolution. Those were prophetic<br />
words, I am confirmed in my intention. Mr. Jones has been working on it<br />
for some time. I will get the Attorney-General's Department to look into<br />
your proposal. I think it is a very good one, excellent one. The number<br />
of goods which go interstate is not great, but they are significant of<br />
course, this is what South Australia has found. It has been unable to<br />
although it has price justification procedures, it hasn't been able to<br />
apply them to goods coming interstate. And New South Wales and Victoria<br />
don't have such procedures and therefore their manufacturers or<br />
retailers can exploit the smaller States which do have those procedures. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
