<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8944</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE HON PJ KEATING MP VISIT OF THE PRESIDENT OF GERMANY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008944.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 95/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
VISIT OF THE PRESIDENT OF GERMANY<br />
I am pleased to announce that the President of the Federal Republic of<br />
Germany, His Excellency Mr Richard von Weizsticker, will make a State visit<br />
to Australia from 3 to 9 September 1993 at the invitation' of the Governor-<br />
General. While in Australia President von WeizsAcker will be visiting Melbourne,<br />
Adelaide, Canberra, Sydney and Cairns. I will meet President von Weizsaicker<br />
in Canberra on Monday 6 September.<br />
President von Weizsacker's visit to Australia will be the first by the President of<br />
a reunified Germany. His visit underlines the dramatic changes in international<br />
affairs in rccent times, including the ongoing process of European union.<br />
Australia's relationship with Germany is substantial. In 1992, Germany was<br />
Australia's eighth largest trading partner. Australian exports to Germany were<br />
worth $ 1.1 billion and imports from Germany $ 3.2 billion.' Germany is also a<br />
significant source of investment for Australia, with capital stock of $ 6.4 billion<br />
invested here. Around 1 15,000 Australians were born in Germany and, at the<br />
1986 census, over 230,000 claimed German ancestry.<br />
I warmly welcome President von Weizsacker to Australia, and look forward to<br />
discussing with him a range of issues including Australian-German relations<br />
and the outlook for European economic integration.<br />
CANBERRA 24 August 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
