<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4596</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT COMMONWEALTH/STATE REVIEW OF THE ORD RIVER IRRIGATION AREA, 15 DECEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004596.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
V 4J~ AUSTRALIA ~ g-<br />
PRIME MINISTER.<br />
FOR PRESS 15 DECEMBER 1977<br />
JOINT COMMONWEALTH/ STATE RVEWOF THE ORD RIVER IRRIGATION AREA<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Frasez and the Premier of Western Australia,<br />
Sir Charles Court, today announced further details of the joint<br />
Commonwealth/ State review which is to be established to report<br />
to both Governments on the future development of the Ord River<br />
Irrigation Area.<br />
Following discussions between the Prime Minister and the Premier,<br />
agreement has been reached onthe composition of the body to<br />
undertake the review and the terms of reference for the study.<br />
The review body is to be comprised of five members, including anind<br />
ependent ' chairman,.. two -officers of the Commonwealth Government<br />
and two State Government officers.<br />
The Chairman will be Sir Norman Young who is Chairman of<br />
Elder Smith Goldsborough Mort! Ltd., Australia's largest pastoral<br />
house. The Prime Minister. and Premier said that the terms of reference<br />
stressed the need to look at the medium to long-term and involved<br />
an assessment-of the'total benefits and costs to the nation<br />
of various development strategies f or the area.<br />
An assessment would also be made of the desirable future direction<br />
of research and the possible ' roles of the Commonwealth and State<br />
Governments. The review will involve extensive discussions in the region and<br />
with other interested parties, Subsmissions will be invited.<br />
The body will commence its task ea rly in the new year and it<br />
is expected that the review will be completed within six months<br />
of its establishment. I<br />
The full terms of reference for the review are attached. </p>
<p>REVIEW OF THE FUTURE PROSPECTS OF THE<br />
ORD RIVER IRRIGATION AREA ( ORIA)<br />
THE REVIEW IS TO<br />
1. Assess and report on the total benefits and costs<br />
to the nation of:<br />
Ci) Development in the ORIA to datel and<br />
( ii) Further potential development having regard<br />
to future world needs for food, fibre and<br />
energy in the medium and longer term.<br />
2. Include consideration of the following matters:<br />
Technical, economic and environmental research<br />
to date;<br />
S ( ii) Commercial prospects for commodities which may<br />
be produced in the region;<br />
( iii) Infrastructure requirements and costs;<br />
( iv) Where relevant, the impact of development on:<br />
activities adjacent to the area<br />
the-Aborigina-1-. ommunity~<br />
the environment;<br />
( vi Special-disabilities in the-region;<br />
( vi) Possible future directions of research, including.<br />
the involvement of and<br />
( vii) The future implementation of the Western Australian<br />
Agreement ( Ord River Irrigation} Act 1968.<br />
3. Report also on possible roles of the Commonwealth and<br />
Western Australian Governments in any future development. I. r </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
