<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8375</transcript-id>
    <title>FIRST KEATING CABINET MEETING- ECONOMIC STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008375.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 31/<br />
FIRST KEATING CABINET MEETING ECONOMIC STATEMENT<br />
The Keating Cabinet met for the first time today to begin<br />
work on an Economic Statement to speed the recovery and job<br />
growth. The Prime Mi~ nister told Cabinet the Statement would detail a<br />
plan to deliver a much-needed boost in confidence to<br />
business anti the wider community.<br />
It would contain specific measures to encourage investment<br />
and provide greater certainty in business planning as well<br />
as measures for industrial development and work on major<br />
infrastructure projects.<br />
The Prime Minister stressed that the community was looking<br />
to the Government for leadership and that the Statement<br />
would providle that leadership and articulate a clear,<br />
practical plan to get Australia growing again.<br />
He told Cabinet a major task facing the new Government was<br />
to get out cf Canberra to listen to business and community<br />
leaders.<br />
This would involve the Prime Minister and senior economic<br />
Ministers meeting with small and large business, unions and<br />
community leaders during the next few weeks to hear their<br />
ideas for recovery.<br />
As an initial step the Prime Minister, the Treasurer, the<br />
Minister for Finance and the Minister for Industry,<br />
Technology and Commerce would meet key business and union<br />
leaders from. different States in Melbourne and Sydney over<br />
the next two weeks.<br />
The PM and Ministers would also be in touch with State<br />
Premiers and Territory Chief Ministers as work developed.<br />
The Treasurer, Mr Dawkins, reported to Cabinet on current<br />
economic conditions and said the most up-to-date information<br />
from Treasury confirmed the view expressed by the Prime<br />
Minister over the past few months that the economy has been<br />
weaker than official data suggested at the time.<br />
Mr Keating said the timing of the Statement was yet to be<br />
decided but he expected to deliver it in the Parliament in<br />
late February or early March.<br />
7 January 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
