<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11338</transcript-id>
    <title>17 March 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT IRISH AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE                 ST PATRICK&amp;#146;S DAY BREAKFAST, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Mr President, to Ms Sile de Valera, your</p>
<p> grace Bishop Stewart, Pat McNamara, Ivan Deveson the Lord Mayor of</p>
<p> Melbourne, the other many distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>I really do regard it as quite a privilege and a pleasure to have</p>
<p> the opportunity of saying a few words on this St Patrick's Day</p>
<p> 1999. It is really understating the history of this country and it's</p>
<p> misunderstanding the temper and the mood and the passions of the Australian</p>
<p> people to see the Irish contribution as merely being one of yet another</p>
<p> immigrant group.</p>
<p>Of all the many tributaries that have shaped the mighty river which</p>
<p> is the modern Australia none in a sense has been more distinctive</p>
<p> and more important than the contribution of the Irish to this country.</p>
<p> The Irish inheritance is part of the modern Australian identity. It</p>
<p> has brought many things to Australia, it has contributed in many distinctive</p>
<p> ways. It is impossible, for example, to hear the sort of music that</p>
<p> we have heard this morning and not realise the enormous contribution</p>
<p> that is made to shaping music in this country. It is impossible to</p>
<p> think of the footballing passion of this city, for example, without</p>
<p> acknowledging its Irish ancestry in part. And I say that as a rather</p>
<p> devoted rugby follower myself it is impossible to think of what the</p>
<p> shape of Australian politics would be like without understanding the</p>
<p> Irish contribution, and I'll come to that in a moment.</p>
<p>And one of the captivating, indeed endearing, things about being an</p>
<p> Australian in 1999 is that as we approach the Centenary of the Federation</p>
<p> of our nation all of us are reflecting more and more on what made</p>
<p> us as we are today. And all of us are coming together in celebrating</p>
<p> our history and part of that celebration, a massive part of it, must,</p>
<p> of course, be to acknowledge the Irish contribution. You have heard</p>
<p> it all before some 35 to 40 per cent of Australians claim an Irish</p>
<p> ancestry and do it proudly. In my own case, my maternal great grandmother</p>
<p> was born in County Westmeath and my paternal great grandfather was</p>
<p> born in Portadown in County Armagh. A fairly familiar pattern of so</p>
<p> many Australians.</p>
<p>And the Irish have really been part of the Australian story now for</p>
<p> more than 200 years. And they have become, and their culture, their</p>
<p> attitudes, their passions, their way of life has become inseparably</p>
<p> part of the Australian way of life. When Mary McAleese, the Irish</p>
<p> President, was in Australia early this year the only person, I said</p>
<p> at her welcome luncheon, that had the capacity to interrupt an Australian</p>
<p> election campaign which she did late in September of last year. She</p>
<p> spoke of the natural affinity that exists between our two countries.</p>
<p>But, of course, when we think of Ireland and we think of Australia</p>
<p> we don't only think of it nostalgically and romantically we also,</p>
<p> and historically, we also think of it of course in contemporary terms.</p>
<p> And today Ireland is a modern thriving successful economy. It is indeed</p>
<p> an economy with probably the fastest economic growth in the European</p>
<p> Union. It is an economy that has been transformed over the last 20</p>
<p> years. It has defied the critics. I first visited Ireland in 1977,</p>
<p> I went as an Australian Minister for special trade negotiations. I</p>
<p> was trying to get a better trade deal for Australian produce in what</p>
<p> was then the European common market and I got pretty lean pickings</p>
<p> just about everywhere I went to every capital. And at that time the</p>
<p> Irish economy was really struggling. And I remember talking to the</p>
<p> then Prime Minister, I think it was Mr Lynch, about some of the challenges</p>
<p> of the Irish economy. But since then things have changed and have</p>
<p> changed enormously and I am delighted as I know all Australians who</p>
<p> have an affection for Ireland and the Irish contribution to this country's</p>
<p> history and current day being I am delighted that the incredible success</p>
<p> that the Irish economy has achieved in recent times.</p>
<p>We honour, as Australians, the contribution of the Irish to the history</p>
<p> of this country. We recognise that it has not always been an experience</p>
<p> free of discrimination and intolerance. Like all societies through</p>
<p> the 20th Century we went through our experiences of the</p>
<p> divisions of sectarianism within our community. And for more than</p>
<p> 100 years the Irish in Australia who were overwhelmingly catholic</p>
<p> have suffered the discrimination of being forced to pay for the education</p>
<p> of their children in their faith. And I am very proud, of course,</p>
<p> that that well known member of the Melbourne Scotts and self declared</p>
<p> humble Presbyterian, Robert Menzies, more than anybody else brought</p>
<p> to an end that discrimination.</p>
<p>And now Australia probably has a system of openness and tolerance</p>
<p> and freedom of choice in relation to the education of its children</p>
<p> second to none anywhere in the world. And we have all moved on from</p>
<p> that and we all hope as the Minister said that the fragile peace process,</p>
<p> and it is fragile, we were reminded again only this morning our television</p>
<p> bulletins that the mad men and women on both sides of the argument</p>
<p> are still to be found and those people are to be shunned and the example</p>
<p> of those two great Nobel Prize winners, John Hume and David Trimble</p>
<p> are to be very much admired and respected. And I know that all Australians</p>
<p> who have any affinity for Ireland and their Irish associations will</p>
<p> join in prayers and hopes for a successful fruition of the Good Friday</p>
<p> agreement.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, it is a great privilege to be the Prime Minister</p>
<p> of this country. It is a great privilege for me to acknowledge the</p>
<p> immense Irish contribution to our nation, we wouldn't be what</p>
<p> we are today. I can't conceive of Australian politics having</p>
<p> been anything remotely resembling what it has been over the last 40</p>
<p> or 50 years without the Irish contribution. For so long, of course,</p>
<p> the Irish contribution to Australian politics was seen as overwhelmingly</p>
<p> belonging to the Australian Labor Party for obvious historical reasons.</p>
<p>The Liberal Party that I joined in 1957 when I left school in Sydney</p>
<p> didn't boast an enormous number of people of Irish Catholic descent.</p>
<p> But I can say that over that 40 or 50 years that has changed and I</p>
<p> can say to all of you that there is an adequate supply of Faheys and</p>
<p> Heffernans and Herrons and McNamaras and indeed the list can go on</p>
<p> of people of Irish descent bringing their passion, their particular</p>
<p> view, to the lifeblood and to the existence of our political party.</p>
<p> It is a wonderful occasion, I salute the Irish contribution to our</p>
<p> nation it wouldn't be what it is today without it. And I hope</p>
<p> all of you have a marvellously enjoyable St Patrick's Day. Thank</p>
<p> you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
