<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4837</transcript-id>
    <title>GRANT TO WORLD WILDLIFE FUND AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004837.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 27 SEPTEMBER, 1978<br />
GRANT TO WORLD WILDLIFE FUND AUSTRALIA<br />
The Commonwealth Government has allocated $ 50,000 in the<br />
1978/ 79 Budget for World Wildlife Fund Australia, following<br />
its active support to the setting up of thfp Fund in Australia.<br />
The World Wildlife Fund is a well respected international<br />
organisation established in 1961. Its headquarters are in<br />
Switzerland and 27 countries have independent national<br />
organisations. By the end of 1977 the Fund had disbursed<br />
over $ 30 million for some 1,800 projects in 131 countries.<br />
World Wildlife Fund Australia was incorporated in New South<br />
Wales under the Companies Act on 29 June 1978 as a company<br />
limited by guarantee and not having a share capital.<br />
Its aim is to raise money and support for the preservation of<br />
the natural heritage, particularly threatened habitat and<br />
wildlife species.<br />
Although the Fund's secretariat is based in Sydney, its<br />
operation is being developed on an Australia-wide basis.<br />
A Conservation Program Committee has been established<br />
comprised of a number of leading scientists and conservationists<br />
chosen on a multi-discipline basis from universities,<br />
government and the community. It will be responsible for<br />
selecting projects for financing from submissions made by<br />
conservation groups, governments and other agencies.<br />
It is anticipated that the Fund will work in cooperation<br />
with other conservation organisations. In this way these<br />
organisations could be involved in additional projects.<br />
The majority of funds raised by World Wildlife Fund Australia<br />
will be allocated to Australian projects. Some funds may<br />
be allocated to projects located in the neighbouring South<br />
Pacific countries.<br />
It is extremely satisfying that the business community has<br />
already given considerable support to the World Wildlife<br />
Fund Australia. The World Wildlife Fund Australia is<br />
indeed fortunate to have obtained the services of so<br />
emminent an Australian businessman as Sir Noel Foley, C. B. E.<br />
as the President.' 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
