<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8693</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSPORT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, ADDRESS TO THE BARCALDINE COMMUNITY, BARCALDINE 10 OCTOBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008693.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THlE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
ADDRESS TO T1IE BARCALDINE COM M UNITY, BARCA LDINE,<br />
OCT~ OBER 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you very much Rob ( hulls), Lancc ( Norman), Pat (.) and Rob's wife<br />
Petrina and ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It's a great honour to be here and thank you very much for so many of you coming<br />
out to see us, on this I'm sure another Queensland sunny day. My daughters are<br />
telling me now I've got a bald patch up here I've got to watch and I should have had<br />
the sun tan cream on it; I'm warming up for the Sydney summer. It is lovely to be<br />
In such nice weather, but more particularly in nice company and thc nice company<br />
being those of you who kept flying the flag of the L abor Party and the spirit of<br />
Labor and thc spirit of Australia so known to be connected with the town of<br />
Barealdine and the famous Tree Of Know. ledge under which the Labor Party Was<br />
formed a century ago.<br />
It is an interesting conjunction of events that in this decade, the last in this century,<br />
that a century ago, in probably our worst drought and worst depression, the Labor<br />
Party was formed and we went through that great time, that great spirit in<br />
Australia, when Australia federated and became a nation. And that great spirit of<br />
experimentation continued right until the First World War. And now a century<br />
later, in what is not a general drought but one near by here, and a rcession we arc<br />
now moving from, we are contemplating that spirit of Australia again because we<br />
lost that sense of social experimentation which came in the 1890s and in the first<br />
fifteen or so years of this century. And the problem was it was snuffed out at </p>
<p>G9allipoli when all the conservative forces of this country took what was a very<br />
radical thing, the contribution of the young men and women of Australia to the<br />
First World War,-and wrapped themselves conservatively and all their conservative<br />
mores around it.<br />
And then, of course, we had the ' 20s, a period of economic expansion, the ' 30s with<br />
the depression. the ' 40s with the war and thcn, under Menzies in those years, the<br />
and ' 60s, we again kept focusing back on other countrics rather than our own.<br />
So we lost that sense of nation, that sense of experimcritation, that spirit of<br />
Australia which was kindled here a century ago.<br />
That spirit has, I think, returned and there's now a greater sense of national identity<br />
than there was at any time since just before the First World War. Anrd that_ has<br />
been recovered, I think, across the countryside; people are much more clear about<br />
their identity as Australians and Australia as a country is more clear about its<br />
identity in the world as a nation.<br />
The Labor Party has always been called upon to lead that national spirit and one<br />
wonders today if we hadn't federated a hundred ycars ago would we fcderatc in this<br />
decade. Given all the various rivalries between the States and thc Commonwealth<br />
I don't know.<br />
But yesterday we had another indication, I think, that that spirit is around. We<br />
decided in June this year to form a National TrainingAuthority that's to take the<br />
TAFE system and turn it into a nati-onal ratherthan a state-s-ystem and yesterday<br />
the deision was made to put the headquarters of the national body in Brisbane.<br />
So, for almost the first time, Brisbane has picked up a national authority in the<br />
State of Queensland and that spirit of co-operation which will produce for<br />
Australian kids a vocational cducation system to sit beside the universitics is<br />
perhaps a glimpse of that great spirit that obtained in the 1 890s in this country and<br />
in this part of Australia.<br />
So the spirit of Australia, the spirit of Labor owes a great deal to Barcaldine, but<br />
the Labor Party still carries the spirit on and in this century, in the latter half of it,<br />
we've had to remake Australia in Labor's image. That is, try and take it from a<br />
closed country to an open, robust country again one that is prepared to look at<br />
some social experimentation like a century ago but this time go out to the world<br />
in trade. And we have done this in the 1980s. We've made the great cultural shift<br />
out, Instead of staying with'the cultural shift in which we had through all the post<br />
war years. This is the first year that we'll export more manufactured goods than<br />
rural exports or mining exports. Because the problem was, though the great rural<br />
industries and mining industries have been such strong things for Australia, they </p>
<p>weren't able to pay for our imports as long ago as 1980 over a dccade ago. So we<br />
had to start developing our goods and our services, but you can't develop goods and<br />
services, you can't develop sophisticated things, without developing the most<br />
valuable resource and that's our young people our children.<br />
When we came to office only three children in ten completed secondary school;<br />
this year that's over seven in ten, and in five years' time we think it will be nine in<br />
ten. And then we created enough places for 40 per cent of them to go onto<br />
universities. But there was always a hole: those who couldn't get into university.<br />
And we're now filling that by developing a proper vocational education system<br />
under that so that wc end up with a trained workforce that can develop<br />
sophisticated products and not only that add value to our rural product-, so instead<br />
of selling beef and wool in an unprocessed way, wc start adding value to it and<br />
selling it to those markets that really matter. That's what really is going to add<br />
income to Australia, add benefits to the country and put a stable base in<br />
employment right across the country.<br />
These are the things which we've done, but as well as that we'vc picked up all the<br />
social aspects of the people, the views of the peoplc who have met here a century<br />
ago. And while there was drought here a century ago, now we have drought relief<br />
courtesy of a Labor Government.<br />
Where they were talking about unemployment a century ago in that depression,<br />
we've got unemployment benefits. Now Dr Hewson, our Tory friend, wants to cut<br />
them out after nine months) but we've got them there, we've increased them<br />
through the 1980s and we've got a decent social security _ system. sitting there for<br />
Australians courtesy of the fact that a Labor Party was formed -so long ago. And it<br />
means now that access to health through Medicare, access to education, support for<br />
the aged in retirement, a new scheme of support for the aged with occupational<br />
superannuation for those who will be retiring in some years hcncechild care, as<br />
well as all those aged care things, all that support in the education system, that<br />
great social wage has come from a Labor Government that knows to keep Australia<br />
strong, you'vc got to keep Australia together. And the notion that the rich should<br />
prosper and they'll flick some crumbs off the table and the rest of the public pick<br />
that up, is not our view of the world.<br />
We say all Australians should come along together. So we want to build a strong<br />
industrial base, but not just growing wheat and wool or even raising beef, but to<br />
add value,-to make sophisticated products, to get into services like tourism as we<br />
see tourism changing the whole of thc state of Queensland, an industry that<br />
developed entirely under a Labor Government in the past ten years. And that trade </p>
<p>4<br />
in international services, whether they be tourism or medical services or financial<br />
services or health services, have all come from a Labor Government.<br />
The funny thing is, it has taken a Labor Government to give Australia an open<br />
market econom~ y. In that great struggle between capital and labour here a century<br />
ago, capital won, but capital has been tamed since so that now it works with labour<br />
to make Australia stronger. We are working together. And now the great phalanx<br />
of enterprise agreements across Australia, where unions and employees and<br />
managers and businesses are sitting down making novel changes for productivity<br />
and higher wages, is part of the growing up and maturing of Australia, part of the<br />
maturing of Labor and the country.<br />
There's always been a to-ing and fro-ing in this century between the notion of<br />
private interest and private reward being the key to everything and government<br />
intervention being the key to everything. We saw the robber baron capitalists of<br />
the United States and Britain in the 19th century believing that private interest and<br />
private reward was everything, and yet we saw the communist parties of Europe, of<br />
Russia, and some of the other socialist parties, believing that government<br />
intervention was everything.<br />
In the Labor Party we've had neither one of those things. We've always had that<br />
nice happy mix, that fair mix of saying not everything is going to be solved by<br />
private reward or looking after yourself and it's not all going to be solved by the<br />
government sector getting too big so let's render unto Caesar thc things that are<br />
Caesar's, but let's get that nice balance in there.<br />
We think we've got that balance in there, that is the rights of the individual, the<br />
freedom to achieve, but at the same time this concept of nation and community.<br />
And that's what I think our friend Dr I-ewson has forgotten. He's trying to tell us<br />
basically that greed is good, if you go out and achieve for yourself that's all that<br />
matters, but God help you itf you are not an achiever, God help you if you are not<br />
on the top of the heap because in that sort of a world you get left behind. We heard<br />
John Howard speaking at the Press Club during the week about industrial relations,<br />
he wants to deprcss Australian working conditions. So it's the same old stuff. As I<br />
said during thc week, Howard could have made the speech in Lancashire in 1895<br />
and I'm quite sure the people arguing for capital could have made it here in<br />
Barcaldine in 1890 or 1891. It's the same old argument, put by the same sort of<br />
people, but wve're not having a bar of it. We're saying all Australia comes along<br />
together, let's grow together prosperously, lct's rekindle the spirit of Australia that<br />
came with the federation in the 1890s and let's do it with the spirit of Labor which<br />
came from Barcaldine in 1891. </p>
<p>Let's make the spirit of Labor in the 1990s as relevant as it was in the 1890s and<br />
let's show as we did a century ago that Australia leads the world in social<br />
experimentation and social change and economic change with it-We can do it<br />
again, in fact we arc doing it again and while the recession has been a real problem<br />
for us and brought a lot of suffering to people as we get out of it into a recovery, a<br />
strong recovery, the basic breadth and depth of the country will mean that we've<br />
got those balances right and that spirit and hope which the Labor Party has always<br />
been able to provide will be there again in the last decade of this century.<br />
To the people of Barcaldine can I say not only thank you for seeing Rob and me<br />
here today, but thanks for keeping the faith, thank you for keeping the spirit and the<br />
hope of Labor which has for nearly all of this century been the hope of Australia,<br />
And a century later say that your loyalty has brought back that economic and social<br />
change, that economic and social experimentation which this town and my Party<br />
started a century ago.<br />
T'hank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
