<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>95</transcript-id>
    <title>MOUNT ISA RAILWAY - ARTICLE BY THE PRIME MINISTER (MR MENZIES)</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Article</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000095_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STRICT EMBARGO FOR FRIDAY MORNING'S PAPERS.<br />
MOUNT ISA RAILWAY.<br />
ARTICLE BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( MR. MENZIES).<br />
I have gathered from practiially all of my Queensland<br />
Commonwealth Parliamentary colleagues, and also from some<br />
communications I have personally received, that there is a great<br />
deal of propaganda current in Queensland to the effect that the<br />
Commonwealth Government. has'not-made genuine efforts to secure<br />
the financing of the new rehabilitated railway; that, on the<br />
contrary, it has impeded the project; and that it has no proper<br />
interest in the development of Northern Queensland.<br />
The Queensland Government is familiar with the faets,<br />
and therefore cannot be held responsible for this propaganda.<br />
My Government has no quarrel with the Queensland Government on<br />
these matters, our interests are-completely in common, and we<br />
share a great enthusiasm for this great mining and railways<br />
enterprise. To avoid foolish controversies, and to put the record<br />
straight, I have written this statement, which is designed to be<br />
objective and clear, and as brief as is practicable.<br />
As I. have had more to do with the negotiations than any<br />
other Commonwealth Minister, most of what I have to say will have<br />
my own first-hand authority.<br />
What I will call " the project", which includes a'dramatic<br />
development of the mining output of Mt. Isa so as to make it one<br />
o. f the greate. st mines in the world, with large consequential<br />
additions to Australia's internal activity and export income, and<br />
a vastly improved railway link between Mt. Isa and the East Coast,.<br />
began to be discussed some years ago. The then Queensland<br />
Government sought a report from a. great firm of American railways<br />
consultants, Ford, Bacon and Davis. In what is still regarded as<br />
an authoritative examination, these engineers made it clear that<br />
should the company develop its daily produetion, to 14,400 -tons.<br />
( and more so should this be increased to 19,000 tons), the<br />
projected cost of the railway (œ 29m) could be comfortably amortized,<br />
over a period of 20 years, by the resultant freight revenues from.<br />
Mt. Isa. </p>
<p>2.<br />
The company clearly would be undertaking a vast capital<br />
expenditure on the mine. From the point of view of-Government,<br />
the question was how to raise the œ 29m. for the railway and its<br />
associated expenditure.<br />
When Mr. Nicklin became Premier, he promptly investigated<br />
the matter, in close collaboration with Mr. Hiley, his<br />
Treasurer. He took the matter up with us before and at the<br />
Loan Council Meeting in June 1958. His proposal was that the<br />
Queensland Government should, out of its own resources during<br />
the period of construction, find k7m., and that œ E22m. should be<br />
borrowed abroad. We thought that a World Bank borrowing would<br />
have a triple benefit; one was that it would add to our capital<br />
resources for the carrying out of a great work; the second was<br />
that it would improve Australia's overseas balances; the third<br />
was that it would not impair ordinary borrowing for the States'<br />
works programmes. It was, however, necessary to secure Loan Council<br />
approval for a borrowing by the Commonwealth in the specific<br />
interest of one State. We undertook to do everything in our<br />
power to secure this approval, and it was in fact given.<br />
The proposal which the Premier formulated for purposes<br />
of the Loan Council, was that Queensland envisaged entering<br />
into a contractual agreement with the Mt. Isa Company, whereby<br />
the Queensland Government would agree to rehabilitate the<br />
railway between Mt. Isa and Collinsville by June 1963 to the<br />
standard proposed by the expert consultants, Messrs. Ford<br />
Bacon and Davis; and the company would agree to guarantee<br />
sufficient earnings on the carriage of inwards and outwards<br />
traffic to Mt. Isa, to meet the cost each year to Queensland<br />
of rehabilitating the line within a period of, say,<br />
years from 1st July, 1963. It will at once be seen that, at<br />
that time, the proposal was that the company wouild amortize<br />
the total cost.<br />
We thought the proposal had great merit, and<br />
believed that it would commend itself to the World Bank as<br />
a borrowing for a specific and self-liquidating developmental<br />
proj ect. </p>
<p>3.<br />
From that day to t his, filv persuaded as I am of the<br />
great value of the project, nobody has worked harder to bring<br />
it off, But, quite early, in the subsequent negotiations, it<br />
transpired that the Company was not prepared to guarantee the full.<br />
amortisation, I am not criticising the company; it formed its<br />
own business judgment. But the change did present diffio'ilties in<br />
securing the money from the World Bank. That bank is one of<br />
Reconstruction and Development. It does not lend money simply for<br />
the purpose of getting interest on it and securing a repaym ent of<br />
the principal. Its prime function is to finane2, some economic<br />
development which will, so to speak, pay for itself. In the case<br />
of applications for loans relating to specific projects, the World<br />
Bank has made a practice of requiring a complete guarantee from the<br />
principal user.<br />
After preliminary exchanges with the bank, which it is<br />
unnecessary to particularise, we had a three-cornered. conference<br />
at Canberra, in which I pointed out that I did not think there was<br />
any real chance of a World Bank loan unless there was a freight<br />
contract between the Queensland Government, which had a proper<br />
interest in securing the wonomic success of the new line, and the<br />
company, which had much to gain by a long-term freight contract in<br />
respect of a railway adequate for the ultimate expansion of the<br />
mine. Our discussions lasted until 3 o'clock in the morning, and<br />
ended with a broad and no doubt tentative agreement by the company<br />
to guarantee ( on various conditions) a substantial proportion of<br />
the amortisation, of the order of about 70 per cent, which we<br />
thought would provide a basis for negotiation with the bank.<br />
Upon subsequent reflection, the company did not feel able<br />
to confirm this. Alternative proposals were considered, but for<br />
various reasons, they later came to nothing<br />
Just before I went off on my recent journey to America<br />
and Europe, we had a further conference at Canberra. Queensland<br />
Ministers had with them a revised draft agreement. We once more<br />
discussed the possibilities of a World Bank loan. Having once<br />
more explained the bak' method of approach, and the purposes </p>
<p>I<br />
for which it had been . stablished, I was asked whether, as I had<br />
had great personal experience with the barnk in the securing of<br />
earlier loans, I would be willing to take the matter up in<br />
Washington with the F'eFidont of the Bank, Ir. Eugene Black, with<br />
i<br />
whom I was known to be on close and friendly terms. I replied that<br />
I would be willing to do so, though unless thee was some very<br />
material change I was by no means sanguine of success. In effect,<br />
I said: " The bank will consider that this business is primarily<br />
a matter between the Queensland Government and the Mt. Isa<br />
Company. The bank has made it clear that it wants a freight<br />
contract between the company and the CGovernment of such a kind as<br />
will make a very expensively re-consZructed line not a liability<br />
to the Queensland Government, but an asset. They vill want to<br />
strengthen the position of Queensland at the samle time -as they<br />
facilitate this enormous mining development."<br />
That was a perfectly fair: statement, not of our<br />
requirements our function was lo become the borrower from the<br />
bank and to re-lend to Queensland but of the requirements, as we<br />
understood them, of the bank.<br />
We had a good deal more discussion, which I need not<br />
rehearse, about the desirability of including in'any freight<br />
contract adequate provisions to protect the company in the event of<br />
such events as a partial collapse of the mine, or some Government<br />
action, or war. But, in the broad, we agreed that a suitable<br />
freight contract would be necessary if we were to do business<br />
with the bank. I went to Washington and saw Mr. Black and some of his<br />
top men. Knowing that no loan could be actually secured in a day<br />
or two, I set out to establish, if I could, the essential<br />
pre-conditions of a useful negotiation. First, was the bank<br />
genuinely interested in the Mt. Isa project? Did it see it, as I<br />
saw it, as something of immense importance both for the development<br />
of Queensland and. for the improvement of export earnings? </p>
<p>The answer to that was. unhesitating: " You can take it<br />
that thi' bank would be pleased to be ' associated with this project.<br />
But of course we have our own standards and practices." " Anyhow,"<br />
I said, " you are keen?" Mr. Black said, ' Yes."<br />
We then discussed the fact that the Australiar Government<br />
would be the borrower. It was once more made clear as I had<br />
tried to make clear at Canberra that the proposal did not turn<br />
upon our credit-worthiness, which the bank regarded as unquestionable,<br />
but upon the freight arrangements which could be made between<br />
the Queensland Government and the Mt. Isa Company.<br />
" Well,"' I said, " I think it would be useful though they<br />
are not the direct borrowers if I could get the Queensland<br />
Government to send their Treasurer, Mr. Hiley, to Washingtong and<br />
the company to send Mr. Fisher. Would you and your officers be<br />
Prepared to have discussions with them iif they cane over?" He<br />
said " Yes." I then said, " Before I do anything about this, I want tO<br />
know one more thing. The bank has heretofore said that it<br />
requires a 100 per cent amortisation guarantee from the principal<br />
user, the company. Is that inflexible?"<br />
After discussion, th2 answer was " No. We are prepared to<br />
negotiate on a basis of less than 100 per cent, because we think<br />
this a valuable project.<br />
I then dictated. in the presence of the bank's representatives,<br />
the relevant passage of a cable to my colleagues at<br />
Canberra on these two points. The bank agreed. I think it<br />
necessary to set this out, because, although thereafter I made no<br />
statement at all on the subject of the loan, it has been, I gather,<br />
freely said by so: ne people in Queensland that I " oversold" the<br />
prospects of a loan.<br />
Mr. H-iley and Mr. Fisher in fac. t went to Washington and<br />
had negotiatifons first with Mr. Black and then with officials<br />
which were in fact terminated by Mr. Hiley on the ground that he<br />
felt no adequate progress was being made. This was naturally a<br />
matter for Mr. Hiley's own judgment, and I have no right or desire<br />
to criticise it. I did, however, redeive in London a ltter from </p>
<p>Mr. Black in which he said he was sorry that the negotiations had<br />
terminated. ( Mr. Black was himself in Toronto when the talks<br />
ended.) He repeated that the bank was very interested. He pointed<br />
out, quite accurately, as I subsequently learned, what -the<br />
differences were, and added " I didn't think any of them were<br />
insoluble." On my return to Australia I was shown the documents, which<br />
included, by courtesy of the Queensland Government, reports which<br />
Mr. Hiley had made to Mr. Nicklin during the discussions. In these<br />
I read that the company, through Mr. Fisher, had at Washington<br />
offered, on certain conditions, to guarantee 70 per cent of the<br />
0amortisation of the cost of the railway.<br />
As this seemed to me, with my knowledge of the bank, to<br />
provide a basis for a further loan negotiation, but as the<br />
Commonwealth Treasury officer who had attended the Washington talks<br />
had expressed doubts as to whether such an offer had been made in<br />
terms ( this being, of course, a matter of interpreting the language<br />
used), I decided to invite Mr. Nicklin, Mr. Hiley and Mr. Fisher,<br />
once more to come to Canberra.<br />
This they most willingly did. The conference began with<br />
* a short statement by me on my own talks at Washington, followed by a<br />
question from me about the company's preparedness to gua~ rantee 70 per<br />
* cent. Mr. Fisher at once rejected any such idea. Speaking to<br />
Mr. Hiley, he said, in substance, " I have never guaranteed 70 per<br />
cent. What I said was that we were prepared to accept aL surcharge<br />
on the freight rates to build up a fund of E5m. which could be drawn<br />
upon if, in any year, the amount of freight was insufficient, and<br />
that that might, over a period of 20 years, produce 70 iper cent of<br />
the total amortisation." In answer to a question by me, Mr. Fisher<br />
agreed that if for any reason the volume of freight fell for some<br />
time, the 10 per cent surcharged freight rates might not; produce<br />
anything like 70 per cent of the amortisation figure.<br />
As, in a matter so complex, there was clear room for<br />
misunderstanding, and as the 10 per cent surcharge proposal had,<br />
I learned, been rejected at Washington, I was proceeding to ask </p>
<p>some more questions about it, when Mr. Fisher said: TeFeling jundersome<br />
pressure, X advanced the 10 per cent surcharge proposal at<br />
Washington, but it is now withdrawn." Well, I said, " What offer<br />
are you making?"; to which Mr. Fisher replied, " None. The company<br />
will guarantee nothing in respect of the railway rehabilitation.<br />
Why should we? We are mining people. We will develop the mine.<br />
The Government can develop the railway. That is its business,<br />
not ours." This statement was subsequently repeated several times,<br />
after which I made the obvious remfark that, in the absence of any<br />
guarantee from the ompany, all talk about a borrowing from the<br />
bank fell to the ground, and that we could forget about it. This<br />
conclusion was accepted around the table.<br />
I. am. not . auirrelling with the company or Mr. Fisher, who<br />
are admirably competent to decide their own business, or wthie<br />
Queensland Government., which had pursued this matter with great<br />
activity and zeal.<br />
But I have stated the bare essentials of the negotiations,<br />
because it clearly appears that a proposal which began at the time<br />
of the Loan Council mecting of 1958 as one which involved-a oorapiln1tguarantee<br />
by the compan:, ended with a decision by the company to<br />
give no guarantee at all,<br />
Clearly, therefcre, the failure to secure a World Bank<br />
loan arose from circumstances over which the Commonwealth<br />
Government had no control, and for which we can in no sense be<br />
fairly blamed. Mr. Nicklin and Mr. iiley, I am sure, agree with this.<br />
Before our last conference ended, Mr. Hiley opened up the<br />
possibilities of a borrowing from some other source or sources. I<br />
am in close correspondence with Xr. Nicklin about this matter.<br />
All that need be said at this stage is that the Queensland<br />
Government and my own are both actLve and co-operative, since we are<br />
both-enthusiastic about the project, and will do all that we can to<br />
see it complobted as a whole, in the. Lnters-ts-tof-bcLth-ine-ral-and---<br />
pastoral development in Northern Queensland.<br />
CANBERRA,<br />
August, 1959. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
