<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5396</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN LIBERAL PARTY STATE COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005396.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRliVIE MIN I TEM 6 Jul 1980<br />
ADDRESS TO THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN<br />
LIBERAL PARTY STATE COUNCIL<br />
We meet at this State Council in challenging but poLcntially<br />
rewarding times. Conditions in many overseas countries are<br />
extraordinarily difficult. The accumulated effects of inadequate<br />
economic policies; the steep and recurring increases in the<br />
price'of crude oil; these have contributed to reduced productivity<br />
and lower growth rates in many countLies in the industrialised<br />
world. Because Australians have read in recent days about recession<br />
in the United States; because they have read of the inflation<br />
rate in Britain of over because they have read of the<br />
United States and British economies actually declining this<br />
year as production falls; they may be tempted to express concern<br />
about our own future.<br />
But despite the difficulties that are being experienced overseas,<br />
I want to put it to you that there are very sound and well based<br />
reasons for having confidence in our future. Indeed, we are<br />
uniquely placed to meet the challenges of the 80s and to share<br />
significantly in its rewards.<br />
The eventful and exciting week that I have just spent in<br />
Western Australia, confirms the spirit of confidence that: exists<br />
in Australia about our prospects for the future. A new sense<br />
of purpose is emerging in our national way of life; an enthusiasm<br />
about our capacity as a nation; and a faith in, and a commitment<br />
to, our future.<br />
This faith is based, not on rhetorLc or political sctacement,<br />
but on economic reality. Under Labor. Australia's inflation<br />
rate had soared to 5 percentage points above the OECD average.<br />
Today it is below this average and the margin in tavour<br />
of Australia hls been growing on the basis of published statistics.<br />
The latest available inflation figures show Australia's inflation<br />
rate at 10.5%; less than half that of the UK; and significantly<br />
below the USA rate of nearly 15%. Indeed, over the last year,<br />
accentuated by the pressures of oil. prices and oE some commodity<br />
prices, inflation in Australia i. ncreased by a little over 2%,<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
much less than the increases in the United Kingdom, the USA,<br />
Japan, Germany and France, where the average rate of increase<br />
for all these countries was over But this is only one-measure<br />
of Australia's improvement. We have reduced the Commonwealth<br />
deficit; our industries are now competitive; manufactured<br />
exports are up; and our balance of payments position is sound.<br />
Overseas capital is being increasingly attracted to Australia<br />
for major development of and investment in, Australia's<br />
resources. We have access to markets in Asia and the Pacific<br />
which can boast some of the fastest growing economies in the<br />
world. Because of our geographical position, we are closer<br />
to these markets. And that makes us a more attractive source<br />
of supply.<br />
But there are other opportunities for Australia as a result<br />
of increases in the price of oil. Such increases have raised<br />
the transport cost of bulk commodities. This will contribute<br />
to Australia being increasingly seen as a country where our<br />
natural resources and our vast coal-based energy reserves<br />
are brought together in an expanding programme of raw material<br />
processing. This is a decade which offers new horizons in investment and<br />
development. A recent report in the Australian Financial Review<br />
made explicit the confidence of British investors in the Australian<br />
economy; a confidence which they were reported as having said they could<br />
not gain elsewhere; a confidence which in the words of the report, " was<br />
conditional upon the continuation of a Liberal Government."<br />
These investors proclaimed Australia as a country featuring<br />
a well managed economy, stable government and good prospects<br />
for the future. We have come a long way since 1975 when<br />
investment in Australia had ground to a halt. But the kind of<br />
success we enjoy has not happened by accident. It is aproduct<br />
of our general economic policy; our opposition to inflation<br />
and our incentives to investment; all these have'lent impetus<br />
to private sector activity.<br />
The Government is determined that a national programme of<br />
resource development should take place efficiently, in such<br />
a way that Australia will be a low cost producer in decades<br />
to come. The oil crisis of 1973/ 74 had underlined the potential<br />
disruption and instability that can be caused to Western<br />
economies too much dependent upon Middle East oil; and this<br />
has been re-emphasised by the oil crisis of-the last 18 months.<br />
While these crises have posed problems for all countries, including<br />
Australia, they also offer opportunities for us that we are<br />
determined to take. As a result of co-operation with State<br />
governments and private industry, we are now embarked on a<br />
great programme of national development. This has ' required new<br />
initiatives from government. In the past, much of our national<br />
development has depended upon getting long term export contracts<br />
for iron ore, for coal and for other major resources. Of course<br />
that will continue and'the demand for coal will increase as<br />
a result of the dramatic increases in the price of oil.<br />
4 / 3<br />
L </p>
<p>3-<br />
But because of the changes in the world energy situation, Australi.<br />
has a unique opportunity to bring together our natural resources<br />
and our capacity to produce, by world standards, relatively<br />
cheap power. But for this to happen, new initiatives are being<br />
required of governments in order to increase their capacity<br />
for electricity generation. To make sure they respond adequately<br />
to the challenges of the new decade; to make sure that Australia.,<br />
through private enterprise, is capable of taking advantage<br />
of the great opportunities before us; the Commonwealth convened<br />
an historic Loan Council meeting in 1978,<br />
At this meeting, agreement was reached with the States for<br />
a special additional borrowing programme to provide necessary<br />
facilities and alternative sources of energy for Australia's<br />
programme of national development. Since then, special borrowing<br />
authority has been given for just over $ 4,700 million of projects.<br />
$ 1,200 million of this is for projects directly associated<br />
with resource development. Almost $ 3,000 million has been<br />
approved to increase Australia's electricity generating capacity.<br />
Over 20% of all borrowing approvals over $ 1 billion is<br />
for projects in Western Australia. And over 50% of the special<br />
borrowings for resource projects is earmarked for W. A.<br />
If we are going to plan adequately for our future, we must<br />
have better and more efficient transport, espec. ially in a country<br />
as large as Australia. Therefore, we are planning to upgrade<br />
and electrify significant railway lines in Australia.<br />
Through all these programmes the Commonwealth, in conjunction<br />
with the States, will be assisting private investment worth<br />
many times that which the governments themselves will be undertaking<br />
The development being supported by government is necessary for<br />
the industrial strength and vitality of this nation. It is<br />
necessary for attracting continuing investment from within<br />
Australia and overseas. Published figures bear witness to the<br />
extent of this investment.<br />
In my election speech in 1977, I announced to the Australian<br />
people that " Australia is ready to go with 6,000 million dollars<br />
of development". I indicated then that " in the coming . three<br />
years we can look to other vast developments".<br />
This trend has gained momentum. In the two years after 1977,<br />
more than 6,400 million dollars of investment actually took<br />
place. But now many more great projects are coming on line.<br />
In the latest survey of the Department of Industry and Commerce,<br />
the total value of Australian mining and manufacturing projects,<br />
at the committed or final feasibility stage, had risen fro:, i<br />
just over $ 16 billion Last October to almost $ 29 billion in<br />
May this year.<br />
Of the total projected investment, more than $ 19 billion is<br />
in mining ventures; $ 9 billion in manufacturing. And Western<br />
Australia, with less than 9% of the population, holds about<br />
of the total investment reported in the survey more than<br />
8 billion dollars. </p>
<p>4<br />
There is not the slighest doubt that with a well run economy<br />
in this country; with the high cost of transporting raw<br />
materials overseas; with the availability of natural<br />
resources and cheaper supplies of energy, there is going<br />
to be more processing of our raw materials in Australia.<br />
This is already happening in the aluminium industry where<br />
there is over $ 4 billion cf new investment right around<br />
the country. Australia is experiencing an upsurge of<br />
investment in basic resources that will keep our economy<br />
expanding through the decade to come.<br />
It is fair enough to ask what this upsurge means to the<br />
average Australian; what all this resource development means<br />
to an Australian family wanting a decent education for its<br />
children and a secure future for them in this country.<br />
It if fair enough for this question to be asked by those<br />
who believe that this is the best country in the world<br />
in which to bring up a family.<br />
The answer is straightforward. A aation can only consume<br />
what it produces. If a family spends more than it earns,<br />
trouble lies ahead. So it is with a nation. A nation cannot<br />
consume what it doesn't work for. If we want improved<br />
standards of living; if we want improved education, health<br />
and welfare programmes; the kind of roads which your Premier<br />
fights so avidly to achieve; all of these can only be<br />
provided from the wealth earned by the people of this nation.<br />
Ther . is no particular value in resource development for<br />
its own sake. Its merit lies in the jobs that it provides<br />
for Australians; and in the opportunities that it makes<br />
available to individuals and to our community to share in<br />
a high standard of living as a result of sustainable<br />
economic growth.<br />
The level of economic activity currently underway in<br />
Australia demonstrates a new respect for Australia and a<br />
new confidence in our future. This activity is broad based,<br />
shared by our great rural industries. Because the government<br />
has been able to secure better markets for our rural exports<br />
Australian farms are entitled to be optimistic abou their<br />
long term future.<br />
Prices [ or sheep, for wool, cattle, wheat, suga and for<br />
other smaller but important rural industrics arc reasonable<br />
It is not often that this happens at the oie i<br />
Manufacturing industry -is also doing much better. Last year<br />
manufacturing exports increased by nearly<br />
Australia is on the go. OL~ r policies are designed to enable<br />
all Australians to save and be independent; to. manage their<br />
own affairs; to make decisions about their families; and </p>
<p>to secure their own future:. through the rewards from their<br />
own efforts. In this sense, Liberal policies are policies<br />
of opportunity. But they are also policies of concern for<br />
those who-are disadvantaged and in need of more particular<br />
help. In these last four years, while practising strlngent<br />
government restraint, our welfare commitment has not been<br />
compromised. Care for the aged is an important concern of<br />
the whole cornmunitf, as it is of governments.<br />
In significant measures to secure this, the Government has<br />
replaced the complex means test for aged pensions with a<br />
fairer and more easily undertandable income test. We have<br />
approved the building of over 500 new self-contained hostel<br />
and nursing home projects and have already determined that<br />
this programme will continue for the next three years.<br />
These initiatives have been complemented by our concern<br />
for the family.<br />
We have introduced family allowances designed to help low<br />
income families. By July the first this year, the spouse<br />
rebate had increased from $ 400 to $ 800 during our term of<br />
office. The sole parent rebate has arisen from $ 200 to $ 559.<br />
Since we came to office, we have extended the supporting<br />
parent's benefit to include supporting fathers.<br />
This represents pioneering assistance to single income<br />
earners. In our first budget, we introduced triennium funding<br />
to enable organisations to provide more certain and<br />
effective help for handicapped persons.<br />
Over the last three years, the funds that we have<br />
made available through this programme have increased<br />
by almost 80% in real terms, over the levels that<br />
operated in the last three Labor years. Further<br />
sums for capital and recurrent expenditure have<br />
already been approved by the government for the next<br />
three years and these will ensure continued expansion<br />
of services for disabled people.<br />
These services include the provision of training<br />
centres and sheltered workshops Eor handicapped adults;<br />
day training centres for handicapped children;<br />
activity therapy centres; and residential facilities<br />
for people who need special accommodation to enable<br />
them to engage in normal outside employment. With<br />
these facilities, disadvantaged people are able to<br />
demonstrate to themselves and to their own families<br />
and communities that they have skiLls; and that,<br />
with these skills, they can cQntribute usefully to<br />
society and to their own self-esteoe. Beyond thi. s,<br />
we increased the handi capfed clii. dren's allowance<br />
by 50% soon ifter we came to office. / 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
At that time, it was only paid to the severely handicapped. In<br />
1977, we widened the eligibility for the allowance<br />
to include substantially handicapped children whose<br />
family income is low. We have widened the eligibility<br />
criteria for rehabilitation assistance. The result is that, in<br />
the year ended June 1979, a record number of people was<br />
accepted for rehabilitation. And in 1978, we recognised the<br />
special needs of handicapped students when we extended the<br />
allowance to cover students over 16 and under 25 who are not in<br />
receipt of an invaLid pension.<br />
These are significant achievements. As politicians and as a<br />
party, we have sold ourselves short on our policies of concern,<br />
and our achievements that have resulted from them. These<br />
achievements have not been adequately recognised, yet they<br />
represent a massive commitment to the needy people of the<br />
Australian community. Not only do our achievements demonstrate<br />
that we are better economic managers than our political<br />
opponents, but also they represent a record of concern for the<br />
disadvantaged in realistic and practical terms that will stand<br />
the test of time. It is because of these achievements; it is<br />
because of our policies of opportunity and concern that we are<br />
entitled to feel-optimistic about Australia's future.<br />
But we need to understand that the competitive gains<br />
we have made have been hard won. We also need to<br />
understand that gains so painstakingly made can be<br />
easily eliminated by irresponsible behaviour and irresponsible<br />
policies. There are two things that could destroy Australia's<br />
future. First, the strike action of left wing, extremist and<br />
often Communist led unions which dislocates significant<br />
industries and could place in jeopardy our economic<br />
recovery. And secondly, the kind of policies that<br />
our political opponents, increasingly subservient to<br />
the left wing, would put into effect if they ever<br />
again won the confidence of the Australian people.<br />
Only last year, strikes in the Pilbara region resulted in a<br />
loss of iron ore exports of more than $ 100 million. Over<br />
one-quarter of a million man days were lost.<br />
At a time when our industries have achieved a competitive edge<br />
in terms of cost atid price, we caniot afford to sacrifice these<br />
gains by developing a reputation unrcLi. able suppliLers.<br />
ReaL success lies inri Front of us in a dilT icult worl. d, Long<br />
as we do not defeat ourselves. The ComFonealth and thi. State<br />
have both legislated to strenthen our industrial laws. ' fhe<br />
Trade Practices Act now applies to secondary boycotts. Yet<br />
resolutions of the ALP. conference in Adelaide last year,<br />
binding on every member of the ALP, show how little the Labor<br />
Party understands the-need for this. / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
For at that conference the Labor Party committed themselves<br />
to the: " Rights of unions to regulate their own<br />
affairs.. . free from government and judicial<br />
interference".<br />
Labor is also committed to:<br />
".. repeal. all penalties for strikes against<br />
decisions of the ( Arbitration) Commission<br />
or a c-onciliation committee..."<br />
They are further committed to prohibit,<br />
clauses in awards or agreements<br />
( which prevent) the right of-workers to<br />
resort to industrial action".<br />
And in case that doesn't cover every union which wants<br />
to do as it likes, the Labor Party has further committed<br />
themselves to guaranteeing the,<br />
". immunity of unions and their members...<br />
in. . furtherance of a. Labor dispute".<br />
Such immunity is not available to any Australian citizen<br />
or to any corporation. But i~ f by supporting such policies,<br />
the Labor Party want to commit themselves to perpetual<br />
opposition, who are we to complain. The Australian<br />
electorate will never support a political party which<br />
seeks to place the union movement, large and powerful<br />
as it is, above the law. Yet, at its conference last<br />
year, the ALP endorsed a deal between Mr Hayden and<br />
the Socialist left which made sure that future ALP<br />
economic policy would be dominated by the trade union<br />
movement. It was later revealed that this policy was written<br />
by Mr Hayden and the Amalgamated Metal Workers and<br />
Shipwrights' Union; the union with the most left wing<br />
and irresponsible leadership in the country. / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
It was a policy which Mr. Hawke called " a gutless sellout<br />
to the Left". It was this socialist left that Mr. Hawke<br />
later described as a ' canker' within the ALP; a canker which<br />
now claims Mr. Hayden as its captive.<br />
We are entitled to ask whether such an extreme movement,<br />
is not bent on undermining Australia's economy<br />
and doing grievous damage to the fabric of our free society.<br />
As a measure of the control exercised by the left wing<br />
within the ALP and the ACTU, we are now in the midst of<br />
the selfishness and stupidity of the 35-hour week campaign.<br />
It is a campaign that can only lead to more unemployment;<br />
to higher prices; and fewer goods being sold here and<br />
overseas. Already, Alcoa have indicated that they will<br />
shut down the Pinjarra plant. And if the 35-hour week<br />
campaign were to succeed, many other businesses will be<br />
damaged and many more people will be unemployed. Regrettably,<br />
it is a campaign supported by resolutions of last year's<br />
ALP conference and ACTU congress.<br />
On this issue, the whole Australian community must make it<br />
perfectly plain that to avoid damage and disruption to<br />
Australia's economic recovery, the campaign for a<br />
week must-be defeated with all of the vigour we can command.<br />
If the Labor Party is serious about economic growth which<br />
alone can lead to more employment, let it abandon now, by<br />
example and by direction, selfish and irresponsible claims<br />
to shorter working hours. Let it condemn the level of<br />
disputation provoked by militant left wing union leadership<br />
in pursuit of unreasonable demands. Mr. Hayden once said<br />
that he would condemn irresponsible union action, but he's<br />
not yet found an irresponsible union act to condemn'<br />
It is no wonder a journalist in the Melbourne Age only<br />
recently was prompted to remark that: some aspects<br />
of Labor policy as presented by senior spokesmen are<br />
remarkably-similar to those of one or other of the<br />
Australian communist groupings".<br />
Indeed, in relation to the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan,<br />
while the Labor Party have verbally condemned the Soviet<br />
Union, they have sought to frustrate all actions designed<br />
to demonstrate effective international opoosition to<br />
Soviet expansion. The Australian coLmnunity is entitled<br />
to ask why.<br />
It is very hard to name another major poli.-: ical party<br />
that has taken tho same isolaLed attitude; an attitude<br />
that has, to our repugnance, put Australia alone alongside<br />
comm. unist Laos and communist Vietnam itt our part of the<br />
world. / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
Why does Mr. Hayden try to suggest that President Carter<br />
is reacting to the invasion of Afghanistan for domestic<br />
political reasons? It is totally of~ fensive to a major<br />
dEfence ally and traditional friend. Does he suggest that<br />
Margaret Thatcher, who has just won an election, is taking<br />
her stand for domestic political reasons? Or Pierre Trudeau,<br />
who announced the same policy just after his eleccion. * Or<br />
Mr. Muldoon and Mr. Rowling, the Labor leader in. New Zealandhave<br />
they taken their stand for political reasons?<br />
Mr. Hayden's capacity to deny Aust-ralia's true interest<br />
and to offend our traditional friends is as great as that<br />
of his predecessor.<br />
In my statement of 19 February this year to-the Parliament,<br />
I said that in the light of Soviet actions in Afghanistan,<br />
there existed an urgent requirement for independent nations<br />
to demonstrate to the USSR in a convincing fashion, and beyond<br />
any doubt, that the will and resolve to meet new challenges<br />
exist. The main burden of-doing this must inevitably fall<br />
on the USA. But it is essential that Australia, along with<br />
other allies, provide as much support as possible. The<br />
cohesiveness of independent nations around the world can<br />
have a profound influence on the behaviour of the USSR.<br />
With the invasion of Afghanistan, the Indian Ocean has<br />
assumed a greater strategic significance.<br />
Because of the difficulties of the world situation, the<br />
Government has announced a greater allocation of resources<br />
to defence. Under the five-year programrme, there will be<br />
an average increase in defence expenditure of per annum.<br />
in real terms. This is indicative of the Government's resolve.<br />
There are direct implications for Western Australia in this<br />
develo'ment. We are expanding the facilities at Cockburn<br />
Sound. Our ships are base-ported there now; by 1983, when<br />
facilities are established in' the area, they will be homeported<br />
in Cockburn Sound.<br />
We have discussed the use of these facilities with the U. S.;<br />
and have offered them the use of Cockburn Sound, if they<br />
so wish, for significant units of their fEleet. The Learmonth<br />
Air Base is to be expanded and imo-roved; to f ill the gap<br />
between Learmonch and Darwin, a major _ RAAF base is being<br />
established at Derby, at a cost of nearly $ 50 million.<br />
An amphibious training area will be established in Western<br />
Australia where our forces, and those of our allies, will<br />
be able to exercise. </p>
<p>10<br />
We have made a number of other major decisions on defence.<br />
We have ordered a fourth FFG guided missile frigate and<br />
new tactical fighters will be ourchased.' All the Orion<br />
surveillance aircraft will be equipped to carry the harpoon<br />
anti-shipping missile. At a cost o'f around $ 80 million, a<br />
second underway replenishment ship will, be built to enable<br />
our combat units to stay at sea for long and extended periods.<br />
We will order additional Patrol boats t o be built at Cairns.<br />
And we know we will have the support of the whole community<br />
in expanding the Army Reserve to 30,000 by the middle of<br />
next year.<br />
Our defence programme takes full account of our paramount<br />
responsibility to all Australians. This responsibility<br />
increases with our recognition that, in a difficult world<br />
order, we have much to be thankful for. Our strong-and<br />
competitive economy has recharged our national capaci ty;<br />
confirmed our success as a government. Sometime later this<br />
year, as a Government, and all of us as Liberals, will be<br />
judged before the court of the Australian people.* Once<br />
the result of the election was clear on 13 December, 1975,<br />
I made it plain that the purpose of my Government would be<br />
to govern fairly and responsibly for all the people of<br />
Australia. I believe we have discharged that responsibility<br />
honourably and with a sense of purpose.<br />
Now another election lies before us; of great importance,<br />
especially for those of us with a deep faith and conviction<br />
about the future of Australia; with an idea and a new ideal<br />
of what we want Australia to become. What happens to<br />
Australia matters very much.<br />
We have a particular philosophy in which individual men<br />
aind women are paramount; a philosophy which recognises<br />
that. the end of government is -not power or authority, but<br />
the service of people,-their freedom and their dignity;<br />
their self-esteem and their capacity to lead rewarding lives.<br />
Your support in the weeks and months ahead is enormously<br />
important in the task of securing Australia's future.<br />
Your understanding, of our policies, Your knowled 4ge of<br />
the difficult decisions; your advocacy and your defence<br />
of those policies and decisions all these are vital<br />
elements to our continued success.<br />
The Western Australian Division has always, been vigorous and<br />
hard working, and I thank you fur all your support over t. me<br />
past years.<br />
But elections that lie ahead of us are always more<br />
important than elections already won. Every election needs<br />
to be fought hard with all the strength at our command, and<br />
I know the full force of this Division will be directed to<br />
that purpose. ./ 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
Australia has an unparalleled future.<br />
As Liberals, we have a great responsibility, and a great<br />
challenge to see that what we achieve today, improves<br />
for our children the quality of the life they will lead.<br />
Let us accept that challenge and pursue it single-mindedly;<br />
with energy, commitment and success.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
