<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8625</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, BEST PRACTICE DEMONSTRATION PROGRAM SGERATON TOWERS, MELBOURNE 24 SUGUAT 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008625.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
/ 74<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THZ PRIME~ MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATINGt MP<br />
BEST PRACTICZ DEMONSTRATION PROORAH<br />
SHERATON TOWERS, MELBOURNE 24 AUGUST1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: 046 would say that when we have a wall attended mid<br />
morning meeting where award for best practice, with<br />
benchmarking against the world's boat, It is sometbing<br />
which Australian business is pleasad to be in. Because<br />
if there is, I think, any demonstration of the maturity<br />
and coming of age of the now Australian economy, it is<br />
gatherings ouch as this and evonts such as this.<br />
It wasn't that many years ago when worse practice was<br />
rewarded. if you are actually slick at getting into<br />
Canberra, twisting Its arm up its back, getting more<br />
border protection, 8 bit more Bubsidies, bounties, if<br />
you are in the worse preatice program you're regarded as<br />
one of the good slick people around town. Well now of<br />
course those people are discredited and they left us an<br />
industrial museum and it has fallen to the lot of the<br />
new managers of Australia to give us something better.<br />
One of the interesting thi~ ngs in all this is that when<br />
comoanies -do well in Australia and they reach the<br />
lgCal end point of their market share, where they are<br />
only squabbling over half per cents and costing<br />
themselves a lot to do it, the obvious thing to do is to<br />
go and do what you do well somewhere else, go and grab<br />
someone's market share, but not where you are running<br />
against the outer edges of your own possibilities in 8<br />
domestic market like Australia. This has happened of<br />
course, when we removed exchange controls that whole<br />
sort of pent-up, propensity, buoyancy, willingness on<br />
the part of Australian business to get out there and<br />
find other markets where they could do well occurred.<br />
And of course our overeas investment went from about $ 4<br />
billion in 1983 to around $ 65 to $ 70 billion today,<br />
which is * a very large proportion of our international<br />
debt. And It is through the operation of these<br />
companies abroad that people and companies are importing<br />
best practice back into Australia from the international<br />
companies which they bought and operated around the<br />
world. And so, you have got companies automatically<br />
banch-marking between themselves and their foraign<br />
:-31 </p>
<p>subsidiary as to the sort of practice which is being<br />
undertaken, and the of fioiency levels which are the<br />
standards of those businesses, and of course making both<br />
the better for having been together by doing the things<br />
that Australia does best abroad anid doing some of the<br />
things which are done beet abroad and having them<br />
brought back into Australia.<br />
I mean it is all part of growing up. It is all part of<br />
getting out of the cort of crazy restrigtions we had<br />
upon us where you couldn't invest -abroad without some<br />
clerk in the Reserve bank giving you a tick, and of<br />
course most people never bothered. or in the sort of<br />
regulated economy we had, where there was really not the<br />
prem~ ium on eff ici-ency because of people drawing down the<br />
economic red from protection and the other natural<br />
protections which come from the non-traded goods sector<br />
of the economy.<br />
We have decided that we want to be in the leading edge<br />
of the world and not in the rear edge. And that means<br />
that we have to smarten ourselves up acroas the board<br />
with our investment, our research and technology, our<br />
Industrial relations practices, our work practices, our<br />
management practices, our best practices. And so the<br />
beat practice program is, as John said, I think a novel<br />
way, a way in which we require companies who are<br />
involved in it to demonstrate to other companies what<br />
they have been able to do. So it is not just something<br />
in which they have excelled privately, and it remains a<br />
private matter for them, but where they are tharing with<br />
others their success, and their innovation, and their<br />
ingenuity and their willingness to make Australia better<br />
and smarter.<br />
This is, I think, a good program and therefore, it's<br />
part of the fact that to become an international<br />
economic society one hag got to do all these comipl. ex<br />
things. They are not going to be done with single<br />
policies, big bangs or consumption taxes or anything<br />
also, they are going to be done the hard way. That is,<br />
reforming industrial relations quletly, slowly,<br />
sensibly, your management practicP, the way the<br />
business operates, getting down costs, all the things<br />
that go, all the smart things, the complex things which<br />
go into that word efficiency and productivity.<br />
We are going to be 4 more productive country, we are<br />
already. But that word in itaelf implies fewer people<br />
producing a given level of output. And if we don't want<br />
a permanent pool of unemployment in this country we have<br />
got to continue to expand output, so that we take more<br />
people up for that given level of employment to each<br />
unit of output and that means the whole climate has got<br />
to be one which is cast towards beat practice and where<br />
all the bits and pieces ofjjnvestmen, be it the<br />
inflation rate, the interest rate, the taxc eystem, : 131 </p>
<p>depreciation, wages, profits. The rest has got to flow<br />
naturally, as it has.<br />
We have come long way already, in the early 1990e<br />
there were very few manufacturing businesses which one<br />
could speak of as being world claas busineesee. This is<br />
not true today. Fortunately, the success of the whole<br />
change, thet is the whole change, the external<br />
orientation of Australia has changed all that. And the<br />
Government itself likes to think it is pretty good ot<br />
best practice to. We benchmark ourselvee against other<br />
Governments around the world. We are, bar a decimal<br />
point, the lowest taxed Country in the OECD. Japan is<br />
below us by a decimal point. We have got one of the<br />
lowest level of outlays to GDP of the OECD countries,<br />
our public sectOr is one of smallest yet it delve<br />
services of a very high standard. So, in terms of the<br />
macro measures best practice this Government has taken,<br />
beat practice on international Government scale on, as<br />
seriously as I know many of you have on a commercial<br />
scale. And we are continuing to make tremiendous changes<br />
in the sort of regulatory regimes for which we ore<br />
responsible, which will help invest practice to in<br />
things like aviation, telecommunications, where we are<br />
awfully good In the world league, banking and finance,<br />
and in things like industrial relations, enterprise<br />
bargaining, where we have really presided now over a<br />
revolution in wage fixation in the last decade, where we<br />
have seen more wage flexibility than perhaps any<br />
comparable country, where the profit share in high, and<br />
whether inflation unit labour costs are low, where<br />
inflation is low, and now we are having this big shift<br />
to enterprise agreements, enterprise bargaining, where<br />
we have now got twice as many people in Australia<br />
working under enterprise agreements, as for instance,<br />
there are in New Zealand under employment contracts,<br />
which we hear so much about, there are twice * s many<br />
Australians working under enterprise agreements all<br />
ready, and just last week Peter Cook and I have opened<br />
discussions with the ACTU in a wa @ e effj. where now 2/ 3<br />
to 3/ 4 of all Australians will have their wages adjusted<br />
under enterprise bargaining and not under a centralised<br />
wacqe fixina system, not under a national wage ease.<br />
These are all I think significant things in this whole<br />
quest for best practice and the same with training, retraining,<br />
skilling, and we saw recently at the youth<br />
meeting the announcement I was able to make of an<br />
agreement with the Commonwealth and the States to put<br />
together a new national vocational education system. I<br />
mean it won't be too many years before we are up there<br />
with best practices, as we already nra, with best<br />
practice in relation to the tertiary sector, the<br />
proportion of our kids going into tertiary institutionfs.<br />
So, whether it be in shipping where we have achieved<br />
crew levels comparable with other OECD countries, or in<br />
the waterfront where we have Just doubled productivity,<br />
0O/ 0" d 800ON' 2: 9T Z6'" nuBp7 : 131 </p>
<p>or In electricity where we ate now starting to create a<br />
market for the first time by separating power generation<br />
from distribution, or in railways where we are<br />
developing a flew national freight highway, rail highway,<br />
under an enterprise agreement. Again, where best<br />
practica is going to be the focus. So, we have taken it<br />
on and of course no more particularly than in the public<br />
service, Peter ( Cook),, started nagotitationB a week or<br />
two ago with the Public Service Union in relation to an<br />
enterprise agreem~ ent, industrial agreement, enterprise<br />
bargaining in the public service where we are seeking to<br />
yield productivity gains, further productivity gains<br />
from our own employees, in our own service. Just as you<br />
are, those of you In the beat practice program in your<br />
own companies.<br />
So, this is in a sense this day isn't just another<br />
manifestation, but an important manilfestation, of people<br />
reaching for those high points, those pinnacles of<br />
achievement which must be the norm for an economy in a<br />
country that wants to do wel. l, that wants to employ its<br />
people, want@ to have rising living standards, not<br />
declining living standards, risling wages not declining<br />
wages, rising profits not declining profits, all these<br />
things one must do and we all know one must do to be in<br />
the international league, and climb that international<br />
league table of efficiency. So, I congratulate all<br />
those associated with the program, from John Down who<br />
has chaired it, and to those companies who have been<br />
Interested enough to apply, and who have signed the<br />
contractual arrangements with the Commonwealth to<br />
demonatrate their best practice and who have received<br />
Commonwealth financial assistance In so doing. But are<br />
whom, on nearly all occasions, the companies themselves<br />
spent much greater level of funding then that which is<br />
paid to them by the Commonwealth.<br />
I congratulate you, all of you, for being in it, for<br />
trying. This Is what Australia must be about. This is<br />
how the clever country becomes more clever, how we<br />
become a smart sooiety doing the clever things well.<br />
Thank you very much.<br />
t7n./ t7rflA AOON2gi9 7--n-z: 73 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
