<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23167</transcript-id>
    <title>Delivering on our commitment to upgrade Victoria&#039;s Great Ocean Road</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/12/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>In line with the Coalition’s election commitment to upgrade Victoria’s iconic Great Ocean Road, today I announce that Anglesea will be one of the first locations to benefit from this combined $50 million State and Federal government contribution.</p>
<p>“The Anglesea community will benefit from these works which will improve the road surface from the Anglesea River Bridge through to the Tonge Street intersection,” the Prime Minister said.</p>
<p>“This project is one of the first to help improve the 240 kilometre Great Ocean Road, making it safer for everyone - local residents and visitors alike."</p>
<p>“Building the infrastructure of the future – such as upgrading the Great Ocean Road – is part of the Government’s plan to build a stronger Australia," the Prime Minister said.</p>
<p>“We will deliver the infrastructure that our nation needs so that people spend less time in traffic jams and more time with their families, businesses can get their goods and services to market faster, and our export and tourism industries can be more competitive."</p>
<p>“This is another example of the Federal and State governments working together to improve vital infrastructure across Victoria,” the Prime Minister said.</p>
<p>Victorian Minister for Roads and local member for Polwarth, Terry Mulder, said both governments understand that the Great Ocean Road needs ongoing maintenance to ensure the attraction lasts well into the future.</p>
<p>“We want to make sure that future generations will continue to visit this nationally historic attraction, and that they have an improved experience to what we enjoy today,” Mr Mulder said.</p>
<p>“Anglesea is where the Great Ocean Road meets the coast for the first time with many lookouts for people to take advantage of the beautiful forest and coastal scenery.”</p>
<p>“This location has been constantly pounded by traffic travelling through Anglesea as one of the first key towns along the Great Ocean Road. It is also a wetter area due to its close proximity to the ocean and the Anglesea River, which has degraded the road surface,” Mr Mulder said.</p>
<p>Federal Member for Corangamite, Sarah Henderson welcomed the funding announcement.</p>
<p> “Up to 16,000 vehicles can pass through Anglesea in the peak holiday season and more will be encouraged when the road provides a safer, smooth and more even road surface for everyone,” Ms Henderson said.</p>
<p>“Through community displays and consultation, we are listening to the community living on and using the road.  We asked for input into our planned maintenance activities and have heard some great ideas about how we can preserve the Great Ocean Road into the future,” Ms Henderson said.</p>
<p>Other projects recently announced include upgrades to sections of road in Lorne and Allansford, which will improve conditions for all road users.</p>
<p>The total estimated cost of these works in Anglesea is $1.8 million.</p>
<p>Work on the Anglesea improvements will begin in 2014.</p>
<p>16 December 2013</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
