<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2303</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;FOUR CORNERS&#039; - TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR JOHN GORTON ON ABC TV NETWORK - INTERVIEWER: MIKE WILLESEE - RECORDED ON 2 OCTOBER FOR SCREENING ON 3 OCTOBER 1970</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002303_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 6. 30 p. m. Saturday, 3 October 1970<br />
" FOUR CCIRNERS"<br />
TELEVISION I\ TERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
KROT OTNO B VEWO<br />
Interviewer : Mike Willesee<br />
Recorded on 2 October for screenin~ g on 3 October 1970<br />
We open our programme this week in Canberra, and it's been quite a<br />
hectic week in the National Capital. The controversy wie might loosely term " law<br />
and order" reached a peak with an Opposition motion ofZ No Confidence in the' : ri.-. ne<br />
Minister; Sir Henry Bolte stepped in and trumped that with a $ 9 million gesture of<br />
defiance towards the Commonwealth, and the Prime Minister rounded off the week<br />
with the announcement of the Senate election date November 21 which is sever,<br />
weeks away or perhaps I should say almost rounded off the week, because in fact<br />
the Pria1Te Minister is here to do that now.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, could I start talking to you on this issue of law and<br />
order, and I stress it's a loose covering term. Now you have foreshadowed<br />
some new legislation, but you have shown reluctance to use existing regulat ions.<br />
Now are you going to apply the law to those young men who have failed to<br />
answer the call-up? If so, could I ask you when't<br />
PM Well, yes, we are going to apply the law to young men who have failed<br />
to answer the call-up and, indeed, have already begun to do so. Th-ere was<br />
a case in Adelaide last week, if I remember rightly, and other ones will be<br />
coming along as the wheels of the law grind and I don't grind them. The<br />
Attorney-General and others do. But you spoke of something called " lawi and<br />
order" which has become a journalistic kind of a headline. What I have always<br />
said we needed to do was to protect the civil rights of the majority and that<br />
is the way I prefer to put it.<br />
Q. I am going to come on to that specifically in a moment, Prime Minister.<br />
On the point of prosecuting those people who failed to answer the call-uro, would<br />
I be right in understanding there may be some 103 such prosecutions in the<br />
pipeline?<br />
PM I think less than that. I haven't got the figures in my mind. The<br />
Minister for Labour and National Service or the Attorney-General would have<br />
but my recollection is rather considerably less than that.<br />
Q. And would they be imminent enough to see them before the Senate<br />
elect ion.?<br />
PM I believe they would follow the ordinary course of the application o! the<br />
law. We would not be hastening them nor delaying them. a 0 2 </p>
<p>Q. In the norml procedure of time, would you expect they would come up<br />
before the ' 3enate election?<br />
PM I am sure some will. One has.<br />
Q. So we could see some more young men in gaol because of this prior to<br />
the Senate election' 7<br />
PM That would depend on the Courts' consideration.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, the other point where you have shown some reluctance<br />
to prosecute is in those who are inciting others to break the National Service<br />
Act which is, or could be a breach of the Crimes Act. Do you intend to take<br />
action in that area?<br />
PM This is a different area. I think we had a ijress conference once at<br />
which you were present at which this matter was raised. And the Attorney-<br />
General later traversed that particular ground, indicating that he had in<br />
those kinds of case to be quite sure that he would be on proper legal grounds,<br />
and provable legal grounds and he also had to take into account the whole<br />
of the public interest. On the one question you asked me first, I can give you<br />
a specific answer. On the second one, I can only refer you to w'hat the<br />
Attorney-General has already said.<br />
Q. Coming on to this point which you described as offending the civil rights<br />
of people-. Now, firstly, do you want new legislation because of any increase<br />
in the incidence of such off ences?<br />
PM I think we do. We are limited in the area that our own legislation can<br />
cover because the States cover quite an area of it. What we have got to do in<br />
this field is to properly allow dissent to be held and expressed and at the<br />
same time protect the people who aren't interested or mixed up in that from<br />
being annoyed or having their own rights interfered with by that dissent.<br />
Q. The point I was making there was the incidence of such offences. Now,<br />
you want to legislate further because of a rising incidence of such offences?<br />
PM I think to prevent a rising incidence. We have had, as you ' know,<br />
incidents where people have invaded the Labour and National Service C~ ffice,<br />
torn up the records, intimidated the civil servan~ ts working . behind the counter<br />
and poured ox blood or something on the floor. We have had incidents where<br />
people have invaded the office of the Minister for National Service and<br />
locked him in. We have had incidents where people have invaded Mr Bury' s<br />
office. The incidents are there. They weren't there before. I think there<br />
are insufficient penalties to prevent that kind of offence. 9 e </p>
<p>Q. Looking through some of th-. various -: tatutes, both State and Con-onwealth,<br />
it seemed to me there were quite a few acts which covered such<br />
violations or apparent violations.<br />
PM Well, I don't think they do myself, and the Attorney-General doeSn't<br />
think they do either. Now let's put it this way. If, in fact, you are wro-ngIa<br />
in your legal assumptions and you are not a legal man<br />
Q. Quite right.<br />
PM and the Acts don't cover them, then the Attorney-General would be<br />
right in seeking to see they were covered I think.<br />
Q. Yes, but I am specifically asking you on this point because you have<br />
spearheaded this campaign. Now, just for a cou-ple of examples I don't<br />
wiant to go reaching into the statutes too long, but on the point o! going into<br />
Commonwealth offices, Ministers' offices, there is a Section 20, of the<br />
Commonwealth Crimes Act which specifies that " any person who wilfully<br />
and unlawfully destroys or damages any property whether real or personal"<br />
. two years' imprisotument.<br />
PM Yes, that's right. Now, you would not wish to have two years'<br />
imprisonment.... you are asking me now to try and translate the law anvd<br />
I am not a legal man. I can only take the legal advice that is given to me.<br />
This I think is something which requires a jury trial and, from memory,<br />
two years is the penalty this is from memory. Now what we would want<br />
to do would be to make a greater penalty than exists at the moment for<br />
trespass or for preventing people from using roadways for preventing<br />
citizens from using roadways, and see that it was a penalty which was<br />
sufficiently severe to stop it.<br />
Q. But even on that, there is a Police Offences Act which covers unaut~ iorised<br />
demonstrations and people who don't go away when they are told to are liable<br />
to up to three months and,: or $ 100. This wculd -3eem to be adequate'<br />
PM Have you ever heard of people being fined more than $ 2 or $ 5 or<br />
something of that kind for sitting on roadways arid preventing people fromn<br />
using them, or for unauthorised entry?<br />
Q. But, really, Prime Minister they are different charges such as<br />
vagrancy, and Police Offences Act covering riotous behaviour I'm talking<br />
specifically about the Crimes<br />
PM Well, really, what you are saying now to me is this, that in your<br />
opinion you thinik there are enough laws already to cover the kind of offfence<br />
of which I have spoken * 1s ; 4 </p>
<p>Q. No, I am saying there appear z) be enough laws to questionñ it.<br />
PM Well you are saying that you think there appear to be enough laws to<br />
question it. I am saying that the legal advice that I have is that it would be<br />
necessary to bring in an Act to provide penalties for the sort of offence,-of<br />
which I have spoken, and it -would also be very necessary in bringing in that<br />
Act to see that one didn't take away the right of people to dissent or to<br />
congregate to dissent. Now, it ought to be perfectly easy to arrange that<br />
people can congregate for dissent but that they can do it without interfcering<br />
with other people's rights, without letting off stinkc bombs in post officer, for<br />
example.<br />
Q. P rime Minister, why do you make this move now rather than some time in<br />
the past say twio years ago?<br />
PM I think the incidence of these incidents has been increasing, but you may<br />
remember that two years ago I did indicate then that I fe I t some moves along<br />
these lines were necessary.<br />
Q. You now say they are increasing. Ycu said earlier that you didn't k11now<br />
that they were increasing<br />
PMA Oh, now wait a moment.. . You are now going back to two years<br />
Q. No, no, no. I am talking about earlier in the irt erview when I as'.-ed you<br />
if the rising incidence....<br />
PM I know you did but you said.... rising incidence since when"' Since last<br />
week or something? I think that since two years ago there has been an 1increase<br />
in this kind of activity.<br />
Q. Do you have any evidence of any increase s'f<br />
PM Well, just recently I suppose we had the refusal of some Moratorium<br />
marchers in Sydney to obey the instructions of the police. That's a State<br />
matter. We have the invasion of Mr Hughes' ownn home.<br />
Q. You are talking about specif ic things, and in 1967 and 196C...<br />
PM I though that you wanted me to talk about specif ic things.<br />
Q. The point is that we have had these things happening for four or five<br />
years. Now you say there is a rising incidence, and I asked you if there was<br />
evidence of this. S </p>
<p>PM And I thought I was answering you because in the last few weeks I have given<br />
you two instances of two things which have happened.<br />
Q. Couldn't we go back to the visit of President Johnson or Marshal 7Ly and<br />
say, well, there were certain things happening then. Is there an overall increase<br />
i numbers, for instance?<br />
PM I can only tell you you don't have to believe it, you obviously don't; but I<br />
can only tell you that I believe there has been an increase in there kinds of<br />
incidents. Now, let us suppose there hasn't been<br />
PM Well let us suppose there hasn't been. Would that mean tha'-t you still didn't<br />
need a law to pr event them?<br />
Q. No, the point I was questioning you on, Prime Minister, was whether there<br />
was evidence cf any increase. You now say it is an observation on your part<br />
that there has been. an increase.<br />
PM This is right.<br />
Q. I think the overall criticism that your opponents direct towards you on<br />
this is that it is olitical. Now what do you say to that criticism"<br />
PM I say that it is not political. I say that if Parliaments are going to function<br />
properly, then they are going to make laws after they have been elected and that<br />
those laws should only be changed if a government is changed or if a government,<br />
through Constitutional methods, decides to change them that they shlould<br />
not be altered by people seeking to bring pressure outside of the ? arliament on<br />
individuals by attacking their privacy, on the public by interferinga with their<br />
use of public facilities, on the Government by taking over the streets. Th1is<br />
obviously must be stopped, or else you could get to a situation such as Thappened<br />
in Germany where, under the guise of dissent, H1-itler's Brownshirts took over<br />
the streets and terrorised people they didn't likl-e or who disagreed with the~ ri<br />
and eventually overthrew the government. Now, I would think most people of<br />
Australia of eithe r political party would agree w~ ith what I have just said.<br />
0. 1 think your opponents might say this is why it could be political because<br />
you judge popular support for such a move.<br />
PM Our opponents by which I presume you mean the Labor Party'.. 0 0 a / 6 </p>
<p>Q. Well. . the Labor Party<br />
PM The Labor Party would say I am being political in what I have just said<br />
because I think that most people would support it. Well, the onldy answier I<br />
can give to that is that I believe in it so strongly that I believe it should be<br />
attempted to be done if a minority of people sup-ported it. It could always be<br />
changed by Constitutional means if the Labor Party wanted to, if they had the<br />
chance.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, I would like to move to Vietnam and a good linkiing point<br />
seems to be conscientious objection. Ncw, of course, you agree a man has a<br />
right to follow his conscience if he objects to a war, and have legislated accordingly-<br />
And you would agree, I am sure, there are some circumstances where a soldier<br />
must follow his conscience rather than an order. Do you agree with that'-<br />
PM You are going to sort of talk about Nuremberg trials if you are going to<br />
bring in Nuremberg triat stuff we could go on for a long, long time, and one would<br />
have to say, yes, there must be instances where according to what was laid<br />
down at the Nuremberg trials, a soldier can't excuse himself because he has been<br />
given an order to do something......<br />
Q. Yes, well, My Lai would be I don't vwant to labour that point. " What I<br />
am trying to set up is that on these two points, there is room for conscientious<br />
objection.<br />
PM There is room for conscientious objection to bearing arms at all. As you<br />
say, we have legislated for that in two ways. ' We have legislated to enable a<br />
man to claim conscientious objection to bearing arms and to come before a<br />
court, and we have subsequently extended that to say that if he doesn't do it,<br />
we are prepared to do it on his behalf. Now, there is then a ques-tion of whether<br />
a man should have a conscientious objection to a particular war. I do;.' t believe<br />
that he should. I believe if he has no objections to bearing arms then the question<br />
of saying, " Well, I won't fight in Malaysia. I wion't fight in Germany. I won't<br />
fight in Vietnam<br />
Q. Well they are not saying that, in fact. Th-ey are saying Vietnam.<br />
PM If that is admitted, it must be admitted for any theatre that anybody says<br />
they have conscientious objections about.<br />
Q. All right. Well how can you feel so strongly about this point when.-it is a<br />
matter of conscionce?<br />
PM Because there is no conscientious objection to bearing arms -or to fighting<br />
or to war. This then is merely a matter of judgment, or alleged to be a matter<br />
of judgment as to bearing arms in a particular theatre of war. But, of course,<br />
as you know, we have also legislated to prevent anybody really being faced with<br />
that dilemma. if they genuinely have it. 9 / 7 </p>
<p>Q. You are referring to the CMF?<br />
PM I am referring to the opportunity people have to join the CMF.<br />
Q. But don' t you invite young men to gamble when you provide this lottery?<br />
PM You say young have all young men got this conscientious<br />
objection? I don' t think we are inviting young men to gamble at all. I think<br />
all we are saying to them is, " Look, if you have conscientious objections to<br />
bearing arms, there is a way in which you can have that tested. If you think<br />
you are going to be called up and you feel you will have conscientious objecziua iiow<br />
tOVietnam, maybe tomorrow to Malaysia, OK, join the CMF and then you won' t<br />
have to have those conscientious worries.<br />
Q. Don' t you think it' s reasonable that a young man, not wanting to go to<br />
Vietnam and not wanting to go into the CMF which takes up a lot of time, might<br />
look at that lottery and say " I've got six chances out of seven of avoiding it".<br />
PM You used the words " not wanting" which is quite different from a genuine<br />
conscientious objection.<br />
Q. Well I didn' t give any reason why he might not want to. We are talking<br />
about conscientious objection.<br />
PM But you said some youing man not wanting If he is not wanting to do<br />
it, and that is as far as it goes, then it is up to him, isn' t it to judge his<br />
chances. If he has got a really, genuine, deep conscientious objection to it,<br />
then he has an opportunity to avoid a confrontation and getting into difficulty.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, I wonder if this might not prove to be an academic<br />
argument. I wonder whether you intend to send any more conscripts to<br />
Vietnam?<br />
PM What do you mean?<br />
Q. Do you intend to send any more conscripts to Vietnam?<br />
PM At the moment, the situation in Vietnam is that one of our battalions<br />
is being withdrawn. It is coming back and some supporting troops. You<br />
are asking me what will happen regarding the two battalions that remain there<br />
after this one is withdrawn. I can' t give you an answer to that because it<br />
depends upon the progress of the Vietnamisation and the capacity of the<br />
Vietnamese to look after themselves. But if you are saying will we replace<br />
the other battalions that are up there when they in turn come to be withdrawn,<br />
you are asking me to make a guess as to what situation will have arisen up<br />
there and how strongly the Vietnamese will be able to look after themselves. / 8 </p>
<p>Q. It's conceivable then that no riiore conscripts may go to Vietnarn'i<br />
PM You said that and I didn't.<br />
Q. But you don't disagree with that?<br />
PM How could I disagree with that? Supposing the Paris peace talks were<br />
successful, and -aeace started tomorrow"' Let's conceive that. Then, of course,<br />
no more troops of any kind would go to Vietnam, but you are ask.-ing me to say<br />
what is going to happen in the future when nobody can tell you what is gofing to<br />
happen in the future.<br />
Q. You foreshadowed the withdrawal of the Eighth Battalion six months ahead.<br />
PM Yes, we foreshadowed it when the Americans foreshadowed their own. We<br />
joined in that withdrawal. I haven't seen any other similar foreshadowing because<br />
uf Vietnamisatio-n. But let's turn it round the other way. You must conceive<br />
there will be more conscripts going to Vietnam?<br />
Q. You say I must conceive there will be<br />
PM. Well if I must concede that I can conceive there won't be, you muct<br />
concede that you will conceive that there will be. You are talking about soomething<br />
we don't know in the future.<br />
Q. Well, I think we could make a simple point that there is a real chance<br />
that no more conscripts may go to Vietnam?<br />
PM I wouldn't miake that simple point at all.<br />
Q. Would you like to be optimistic about that i<br />
PM I wouldn't make that simple point at all. 1 Simply cannot tell you vfhat is<br />
going to develop in Vietnam. All I know is that we would like to have our troops<br />
all of them cut of Vietnam as soon as our objective was achieved, and thet<br />
is of allowing the South Vietnamese to be strong enough to look after themselves.<br />
Now, when that will happen I can't tell you.<br />
Q. Well, let's talk about something happier, -Prime Minister. Mcrney, for<br />
instance. Do you think Sir Henry Bolte has been..., do you thirnk:-he acted<br />
responsibly with this move on the payroll tax the $ 9 million?<br />
PM Well he didn't let me know that he was going to do it at any stage. I don't<br />
want to say whether he acted responsibly or irresponsibly. I don't know what<br />
was in his mind. But all I can is that it was quite a surprise since at tiie last<br />
Premiers' Conference, all the offers that the Commonwealth made to the<br />
States which increased very, very considerably the benefits to the States 0 / 9 </p>
<p>were made on the condition that the 3tates did pay payroll tax. I-lw, Sir Henry<br />
Bolte didn't agree to that, which means there was no agreement either as to him<br />
paying payroll tax or as to us to paying any of the offers that were made. The<br />
other States did agree.<br />
Q. This whole area of Federal/ State financial relationships seems to be in<br />
pretty poor shape at the moment. Now, can you patch up the problems or do<br />
you think it requires a rebuilding job?<br />
PM I am interested to hear you say it seems to be in pretty poor shape at the<br />
moment. I have got some figures here on this which show that the States are going<br />
to get $ 291 million more this year than last year through various fields. This is<br />
a very great percentage increase in their funds, deliberately done by us to<br />
enable them the better to finance their schools and hospitals and the other<br />
responsibilities they have.<br />
Q. But don't you think this Bolte move would indicate it is in poor shape. You<br />
ate calling a special meeting next week.....<br />
PM Oh no. I am not calling a special meeting next week on the Bolte move.<br />
Q. On Federal/ State financial relations?<br />
PM No, I am not calling it on Federal/ State financial relatiorships.<br />
Q. Could you tell us what the meeting is?<br />
PM It is to consider the receipts tax and the areas in receipts tax rnon-exiz.; e<br />
areas and excise areas....<br />
Q. Wouldn't this add to my argument?<br />
PM I don't think so.<br />
Q. Receipts tax is part of Federal/ State financial relations?<br />
PM. Sure. But the fact that there is such a meeting to find out how best the<br />
Federal Government can help the States and in what areas the States can help<br />
themselves, would, I should have thought, indicate that the relations were<br />
working fairly well and fairly smoothly.<br />
Q. I am surprised that you should say that because particularly as you had<br />
to back down before the Senate on the receipts tax. </p>
<p>PM Well, that' s right, but has that got anything to do with the fact<br />
that we are having a meeting to find out how best in co-operation we can<br />
overcome that difficulty?<br />
Q. I thought it would have a lot to do with my earlier question that<br />
Federal/ State financial relationships were in some sort of a mess.<br />
PM just because a Senate votes against a proposition which we bring in<br />
at the request of the States again showing co-operation in order to help<br />
the States, again showing co-operation, doesn' t, I think, show that Federal/<br />
State financial relationships are in a mess.<br />
Q. Isn' t that a dangerous argument because an argument could be made out<br />
to show cause for a double dissolution when a government is not able to put<br />
its measures through the Senate. But you have said, " We 11, we were doing<br />
this on behalf of the States". Couldn' t you take that to the point, that<br />
argument of saying perhaps at the next Budget, " Well the Commonwealth<br />
is happy but the States need more money, so we are going to lift taxes for<br />
the States?"<br />
PM No, this was a specific measure, the receipts tax one, and you are<br />
seeking to translate a specific measure which came into being as a result<br />
of an unexpected High Court judgment in a particular field, you are seeking<br />
to translate that into the whole field.<br />
Of course, if the Commonwealth brought in a taxation<br />
Budget of some particular kind, and the Senate went to the unusual lengths<br />
most unusual and I think, improper lengths, of disallowing it that would<br />
create a very serious situation. But they would need to disallow the Budget.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, I have judged time badly. I would like to skip through<br />
a few more things fairly quickly. Talking about the Budget, the last Budget<br />
you described as possibly being one of the great Budgets, despite the fact<br />
that you introduced more indirect taxation which is generally regarded as<br />
being an inequitable tax. / 11 </p>
<p>PM Well we will see what the fut're says about it, but it was a Budget which<br />
did a number of things. One was to greatly increase the amount of fina:-ce<br />
available to the States to the extent that a third of our entire Budget is going<br />
to finance the States and more than a third of the increase in expenditure.....<br />
this to pick up the problems which the States had been indicating, or to<br />
help to pick them up. It reduced direct taxation in a meaningful way. You<br />
can argue whether it should have been less on $ 10, 000, but throughout the<br />
range it reduced it in a meaningful way which was the promise we had made.<br />
It introduced indirect taxation which, if I may take issue with you, is not<br />
generally regarded as an inequitable tax. Indeed, you will find that nearly<br />
all countries in Europe, for example, are moving towards indirect and away<br />
from direct taxation, and the last Labor Chancellor of the British Government<br />
made a very strong speech showing that indirect taxation was not inequitable<br />
when that Labor Government moved towards more dependence on it.<br />
Q. Now just one other point that intrigued me out of that.... you said at the<br />
time that if people wanted to drink more wine and drive cars and smoke, that<br />
was their business and they could pay the extra taxes because cf it. But I<br />
wonder by what principle you tax moderate people more lightly than you tax<br />
the people who want to drink and smoke and drive?<br />
PM I think the principle I would advance would be this.... that there is a<br />
certain amount of money left in people's pockets after they have paid direct<br />
taxation, after they have paid their income tax. That is the same for all<br />
people at a given level of income. Now what they do with that money is their<br />
own choice. They can save it all if that is what they wish. They can spend<br />
whatever part of it they wish to spend on cigarettes or on wine, and this is<br />
a choice that they ha ve as to how they use the money that is eft in their<br />
pockets after direct taxation. And one of the tenets of Liberal philosohy is<br />
that people should have a right of choice rather than be told by an overriding<br />
government everything they have got to do.<br />
Q. Don't you think people have exercised that choice as to the general way<br />
in which they will lead their lives and the people who drink and smoke will<br />
continue to, even with this extra imposition?<br />
PM If they do, that is their decision.<br />
Q. Haven't you discriminated against them because of their way of living?<br />
PM No. We have given them a right of choice.<br />
Q. Prime Minister to close. You have got the Senate election coming up.<br />
How confident are you about the election?<br />
PM Oh, I am never confident about elections, either confident that one will<br />
win them easily or that one will lose them. I think people that talk about<br />
elections before they are held are always rather silly. </p>
<p>Q. Let me ask one more question on this. Do you think it matters more<br />
how you go vis-a-vis Mr. Whitlam or do you think it really matters as to<br />
the seats and the votes and the general counting of the election?<br />
PM As far as the wellbeing of the Australian people goes, L think what<br />
really counts is how the Liberal Party goes as against the Labor Party.<br />
Not me as against Mr. Whitlam or the other factors you mention. What I<br />
feel is that the people of Australia will see a continuance of advancement and<br />
a continuance of improvement under the Liberal Party that they won' t under<br />
the Labor Party, forgetting me and forgetting Whitlam.<br />
Q. Do you think the Press and the public might see it in terms of<br />
Gorton versus Whitlam?<br />
PM I don' t know what they will do, but you asked me what I thought was<br />
the really important thing, and I think the really important thing is that<br />
Australia should continue with the type of Government which has given it<br />
such great advances for the last twenty years.<br />
Q. You don' t think the minor exchange of seats which might come out<br />
of it is going to matter very much?<br />
PM I wouldn' t think so. I think that mathematically in any case there<br />
will be a very marginal exchange of seats.<br />
Prime Minister, thanks very much for talking with Four Corncrs. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
