<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21122</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Victoria  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You have some questions, have you?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well, Mr Howard, the Newspoll – does it vindicate your decision to crackdown on the pollies'; super?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, look, I don';t want to get too excited about one poll.  It illustrates something I';ve said all along and that is the next election is going to be very close and all elections in Australia are very close, except those few where there';s a tidal wave for change.  I don';t find that.  And I think the next election will be very close and tough for us but we';ll see how it works out.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, Mark Latham says he supports Pine Gap, but not the missile defence system…</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, well, he';s very confused. I mean, Mr Downer put it very well this morning and it';s been pointed out, of course, that Pine Gap will be part of the system that supports the missile defence system.  I can';t understand how anybody can oppose at least looking at the missile defence system because it';s something that could years ahead protect Australia against a missile attack.  Now, why would any Australian be against that?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard on that point – Mr Latham has in the past questioned the strength of our alliance with America.  Do you think it';s somewhat hypocritical that he';s touring facilities like Pine Gap?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I think it';s important he know about them.  He might learn something.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does this announcement today suggest you and Mr Latham are like-minded on the issue of early intervention for dysfunctional families?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we have been doing this for some time and the money that I announced today is a continuation of existing programmes.  So, if he supports that, well that';s good.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How different is it from his proposal for guidance classes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don';t really know exactly what he means. I mean, one of his problems is that he touches something then dances off to something else without actually saying what he means.  Now, anyway, look, you go and ask him what he means.  I';ve announced today support for a very important programme in this part of Melbourne, ongoing support. And I';ve outlined my philosophy and people are aware of that.  Families that are doing the right thing and getting on very well, they don';t want governments and Members of Parliament telling them how to bring up their children.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You';ve dangled the $445 million freeway carrot again this morning…</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Dangled the carrot?  Now, I';ve renewed our commitment.  We will keep our promise on Scoresby.  It is now up to Mr Bracks to keep his promise on Scoresby.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How important do you think anti-toll strategy to…?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, I don';t get into what';s important about a strategy. I';m just saying to the people of Melbourne – we will keep our word on Scoresby.  Mr Bracks should do the same.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Victorian farmers have said they';re going to put up a massive fight if New Zealand apples and pears are allowed into the state.  Are you prepared for any sort of backlash that might come out of that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there is a period of 60 days, I think, perhaps it';s 90, where people can lodge objections and if there is any proper scientific basis for those objections, then we will have a very careful look because if I could be satisfied that there were proper scientific basis, then obviously we would have a different view.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>… day period falls right in the middle of harvest season, it';s an 800 page document, do they… is that enough…?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I';m sorry, could you say that again. I was…</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>That 60 days they have falls right in the middle of harvest period, it';s an 800 page document.  Does that give them enough time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I think it';s quite a reasonable period of time, yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>… been given a bollocking by the Press Gallery, perhaps you could do a George W Bush, not read the newspapers and just rely on those around you…</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I';ve always got to keep an eye on you Raphael!</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What about the Press Gallery?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I really think you are, you know, all of you, you';ve got to keep an eagle eye on you.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>… that you';ve been treated unfairly over the past couple of weeks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don';t think I';m being treated unfairly.  I have no complaints to make.  I loves ya';s all and I';ll, you know, be very very happy to, sort of, continue my warm generous discourse with all of you…</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] you saying that you';ve received a bollocking.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that';s alright.  I was making an observation.  But I don';t think I';ve been treated unfairly at all, Alison.  I think in the long sweep of human affairs, I can';t really complain about my treatment by the media.  That doesn';t mean to say they';re always right.  They';re often wrong.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, you spoke inside about how harmonious a society like Australia is.  How do you account therefore the violence that we saw in Redfern just a couple of weeks ago?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but that is not typical of Australia.  It is a particular part of Australia with a particular set of challenges and it';s a very tragic thing what happened in Redfern, the death of any young boy, no matter what the circumstances.  It';s just awful, somebody';s life is cut off at that age – that is very tragic.  But that doesn';t justify the wholesale assault on the police.  There';s no evidence that I';ve seen that implicates the police.  I think the police of this country do a fantastic job, but I think the first responsibility of people in authority, whether it';s federal or a state level is to defend the role of the police.  That doesn';t mean to say police are perfect, they have a rotten job in those circumstances and I have a lot of sympathy for the police and I can understand the pressure they';re under.  And you cannot have a situation where there are different law enforcement standards applied in one part of the country to another – that';s the one thing I would say.  Now, whether that is the case in Redfern, I don';t have enough direct knowledge, nor enough direct responsibility to say so.  But the reality is that law and order depends for its respect on an even application and that means everybody should be entitled to the same protection, but equally those who break the law should expect the same measure of response from the police.  And I';ve got to say that I';m sympathetic to the police';s position, very much so.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think there are a lot of things that will help Mr Barresi.  I think his superb work as a local member, the strong policies of the Government and the fact that we are committed to providing a freeway, a Scoresby Freeway, not a Scoresby tollway.  Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
