<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18</transcript-id>
    <title>THE COMMONWEALTH BANK AND THE PEOPLE SPEECH BYT THE  RT HON. R.G MENZIES, P.C, K.C IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1945</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000018_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Commonwealth Bank<br />
and the People.<br />
Speech by the<br />
Rt. Hon. R. G. MENZIES, K. C.<br />
In the House of Representatives,<br />
Canberra.<br />
I<br />
K&gt; Reprinted from " H-ansar~ d,"<br />
21st March, 1945. </p>
<p>C COMMONWEALTH BANK BILL 14<br />
SECOND READING SPEECH<br />
by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr. Menzies)<br />
This bill, and the Banking Bill, introduced by the Treasurer ( Mr.<br />
Chifley) some days ago, represent, in total, probably the most important<br />
domestic measures that will be introduced to this Parliament<br />
during its currency. They are extremely important, from the point of<br />
K view of their supporters, as well as of their opponents. I have given<br />
a good deal of serious thought to the way in which I should address<br />
myself to them. I do not propose to endeavour to discuss both of<br />
them to-night, but I do propose to address my remarks to the Commonwealth<br />
Bank Bill, the first of the two, and the one that is now<br />
before the Chair. It would be possible to discuss these matters, which<br />
have a broad and obvious political significance, in, perhaps, a broad<br />
political fashion. From some points of view, that might be a good<br />
idea. But the bill itself is full, not only of matters which have a broad<br />
political significance, but also of matters which, on the face of them,<br />
are technical; and if I refer to-night to technical considerations, with<br />
Ca ll the tentativeness of an amateur in such matters, it will be simply<br />
because T believe that in some of the technical considerations some<br />
of the more important aspects of the bill may be found concealed.<br />
The measure professes, on the face of it-and, indeed, was so<br />
explained by the Treasurer-to be one that is enlightened and proCasgr,<br />
e ssive, and designed to give increased security to the people, where-<br />
in fact, carefully analysed-and I propose to-night to submit it to<br />
analysis-it is reactionary and unsound, and will increase the insecurity<br />
of the people. As explained by the Treasurer, it professes<br />
to strengthen the central bank. I shall have occasion later to refer to<br />
an observation by the right honorable gentleman on that point. In<br />
reality, it weakens the central bank. It offers to protect the currency<br />
-indeed, its sister bill says sc in terms-but in reality it runs a good<br />
chance of destroying the currency. In saying that, I do not say that<br />
the effects of this legislation will be seen immediately, or very drastically.<br />
I have a shrewd notion that when these bills have reached the<br />
statute-book, it will be remembered that elections are to be held in<br />
eighteen months' time, and there will be a good deal of " soft pedalling"<br />
by some of the advocates of the measures until'those elections<br />
have passed.<br />
2) </p>
<p>How Will This Affect the People?<br />
As a good deal of reference will necessarily be made in the course<br />
of my own remarks, and in this debate, to the trading banks as a part<br />
of the banking structure, I wish to make it clear right away-and I<br />
can say this for every honorable member on this side of the Housethat<br />
I regard the pecuniary interests of the banks and their shareholders<br />
as of minor importance in this matter. The most vital<br />
element in the trading bank structure, I remind honorable members,<br />
is to be found in the depositors in those banks, and the paramount<br />
interest in the consideration of banking is the welfare of the Australian<br />
people as a whole. Therefore, every banking proposal, such as(<br />
the one that is now before the Chair, must be tested by asking not<br />
how it will affect bankers but how it will affect the people.<br />
This bill is an amending, re-enacting and consolidating bill. The<br />
Treasurer has adopted the course that is convenient to all of us, of<br />
embodying the existing law, so far as it is unchanged, in the bill that<br />
is before the House, so that we -: my have the whole picture before us. C<br />
But our attention will be directed primarily, not to the old but to the<br />
new provisions of the banking law. Looking at the bill I have found<br />
-and I daresay it will agree with the judgment of others-that there<br />
are six principal new provisions. The first is the suggested strengthening<br />
of the central banking function of the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
The second is the abolition of the Board of Directors of the Commonwealth<br />
Bank and the substitution of one-man control. The<br />
third is the subordination of that one man-the Governor of the bank<br />
-to the ' government of the day. The fourth is the establishment of<br />
active competition with the trading banks in general banking business.<br />
The fifth is the abolition of Board control of the note issue.<br />
The sixth is the abolition of the currency reserve. There are other<br />
matters ; n the bill. If time permits-which I begin to doubt-I shall<br />
say something about one other aspect before I sit down. In broad<br />
principle, however, those are the six major matters with which the<br />
bill proposes to deal by way of new provisions. I propose, for convenience<br />
and clarity, to take them in that order. So, I take the firstthe<br />
suggested strengthening of the central banking function of the<br />
Commonwealth Bank. If we are to understand that quite clearly, itC<br />
will be necessary to refer-very briefly, of course-to some historical<br />
matter; because these problems are not to be judged except against<br />
the background of the experience wve have had in Australia. Every<br />
honorable member will agree with that. At the present time we have<br />
in Australia, broadly speaking-and I omit some private, semibanking<br />
institutions, such as pastoral companies-banks of three types,<br />
namely, the trading banks, the savings banks, and the Commonwealth<br />
Bank., The trading banks were established very early in the history<br />
of this country on the branch banking system.<br />
Mr. LAZZARINI.-They crashed fairly early, too.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-In 1893 they encountered some difficulties, but </p>
<p>iot, I am bound to say, as many as they would have encountered had<br />
: he honorable gentleman been in charge of them.<br />
Mr. LAZZARIM.-They had to appeal to the Government to assist<br />
n their rehabilitation. Distributing Risks and Interests<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-The advantage of the branch banking system,<br />
Ls everybody except my friend the Minister for Works will plainly<br />
~ ealise, is that it distributes risks and interests, and is utterly distinct<br />
rom that system of individual banks which was so closely associated<br />
vrith the bank crashes in the United States of America. It is true that<br />
n 1893 there was a bank crisis, following upon the breaking of a<br />
and boom, and that some banks got into difficulties from which a<br />
iumber of them never emerged. But the crisis of 1893 taught some<br />
essons; and it has to be said for the trading banks of Australia that<br />
hey learned their lessons and. can claim to have had a solid record<br />
: ver since. They are not beyond criticism. There are criticisms<br />
vhich may be made of them, as, indeed, there are criticisms which<br />
nay be made of us. But ever since 1893 the trading banks have coninued<br />
to provide, without any question as to their solvency a daily<br />
ervice to more and more people in Australia, until to-day, I suppose,<br />
hey provide a daily service for something over 1,000,000 people in<br />
his country; and they have done so-and it is well, in justice to them,<br />
hat this should be stated-at an uncommonly low rate of profit. In<br />
he report of the Royal Commission on the Monetary and Banking<br />
; ystems-a royal commission, I remind the House, that was assisted<br />
iy one of its members in the person of the present Treasurer of the<br />
, ommonwealth-my friend the Treasurer said in a special personal<br />
nemorandumn that the profits of the trading banks should not exceed<br />
. n amount equal to 5 per cent. of shareholders' funds or 8 per cent.<br />
fthadiaks onishaehlers' fundles amouernte, in 1943to, ft .6e<br />
fhrai als wnhic h ders' henles Them erntage of proitof th6er<br />
ent., and not since 1930 have those banks earned profits as high as<br />
he rate suggested by my friend the Treasurer in the report of the<br />
oyal Commission.<br />
The next kind of bank that we have in Australia is the Savings<br />
lank. It has a long history. Except for the failure of the New South<br />
Vales Government Savings Bank, that history is untarnished by<br />
efault or failure. We can go right back to Campbell's Bank in 1819<br />
) r the history of savings banks in Australia, and except for the one<br />
-istance to which I have referred, we shall find it an unbroken history<br />
f improvement and increasing strength. We now have a chain of<br />
avings banks all over Australia.<br />
The third kind of bank is the Commonwealth Bank. Because a<br />
reat deal of " poppycock" is talked about the origin of the Commonrealth<br />
Bank and what it was designed to do, it is well that we should<br />
e reminded of its origin. The Commonwealth Bank Act of 1911,<br />
rhich established it, set up the Commonwealth Bank primarily as a<br />
ompetitive trading bank. The note issue was not controlled by it,<br />
3 </p>
<p>but continued to be controlled by the Treasurer. At that time, most of<br />
the supporters of the Commonwealth Bank quite plainly had not in<br />
their minds any notion of establishing the Commonwealth Bank as a<br />
central bank, but directed their attention to it as an instrument of competitive<br />
trading. But whatever many of its supporters may have<br />
thought, the then Prime Minister, Mr. Fisher, indicated that he was<br />
looking towards two things. One was, that the bank should ultimately<br />
become a bank of banks-that is, the lender of last resort-and the<br />
other was that the control of the bank should be entirely non-political.<br />
In the course of his notable speech at that time, he said-<br />
While the bank may deal in land securities and other security, it<br />
will in time grow to be rather a bank dealing in ordinary bills of exchange<br />
and liquid securities. It will ultimately become a bank of banks, rather<br />
than a mere money-lending institution.<br />
Later a Governor was appointed as the controller of the bank-the<br />
late Sir Denison Miller. Shortly after he became governor, he an-(<br />
nounced in an interview to the press that he wanted the bank to become<br />
like the Bank of England, and be able to stand behind the other<br />
banks in a crisis. There we have two statements, one by the founder<br />
of the bank in the political sense, and the other by the first governor<br />
of the bank, clearly indicating that each of them was looking in the<br />
long run towards the development of the Commonwealth Bank, not as<br />
a mere competitor in the market of the other banks, but as a future<br />
central bank for Australia. This was in line, of course, with the decision<br />
of the Brisbane conference of the Labour Party in 1908, a conference<br />
back to which we must go to find the foundations of the<br />
Commonwealth Bank, because that conference passed resolutions, and<br />
one of them, it is interesting to recall, was that the bank should be<br />
conducted absolutely free from political control.<br />
Control of the Credit Structure<br />
The early reference to the Commonwealth Bank as being a bank<br />
of banks, or a bankers' bank, were, of course, correct. A central<br />
bank is a bankers' bank in the sense that it is the bank of last resort.<br />
It is the controller of the credit structure of the trading banks, and<br />
the bank in which the trading banks keep most of their cash. I refer<br />
to that fact largely for the purpose of pointing out that the tendency<br />
has developed in later years, particularly on the hustings, of saying<br />
that the Commonwealth Bank must be converted from being a bankers'<br />
bank into being a people's bank.<br />
Mr. CALWELL.-Hear hear.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I hear it being echoed most ignorantly from<br />
the Government benches. There is no antithesis between a bankers'<br />
bank and a people's bank. A strong central bank, that is, a bank<br />
which has power to exercise by whatever weapons may be appropriate<br />
some authority in the field of credit expansion and credit contraction, </p>
<p>As only to serve the interests of the people. So I line myself<br />
igside the pioneers of this bank in saying-<br />
Mr. LAZZARINI.-What a beauty!<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-It did not occur to me that any of the honorable<br />
tlemen opposite were the pioneers of the bank. All that I am<br />
scious of, when reading this bill, is that they are setting out to<br />
its destroyers. As I do not wish to be associated with the de-<br />
' yers, I line myself with the constructors.<br />
During the first world war, the Commonwealth Bank, which had<br />
: been established, had rapid growth. It had intense experience<br />
he financing of government, but nobody would suggest that it was<br />
Lny sense equipped to be a central bank for Australia. At that<br />
a it had not the necessary technique for the task. In some respects<br />
ad not the necessary power. There was a good deal of confusion<br />
hought, which has not yet entirely disappeared, about the respecfunctions<br />
of the central and the trading banks. That is not to<br />
wondered at, because central banking is a very modern art, and,<br />
he degree that it is a science, a very modern science. It is as well<br />
* ecall that fact to mind, when one hears discussion on what the<br />
nmonwealth Bank and the trading banks should or should not have<br />
e during the last depression. I point out that in 1929-30, when<br />
depression commenced, there were very few central banks in<br />
world, and very little was known about central banking functions.<br />
: he United States of America major reforms of the federal reserve<br />
: em occurred in 1935, as the result of depression experience. The<br />
; erve Bank of India was created in 1934. In New Zealand, the<br />
-rve bank was established in 1933. Canada's central bank came<br />
ife in 1935, and the Central Bank of Argentina also began business<br />
hat year. When we have those dates in mind we shall be forcibly<br />
iinded that it was as the iesult of the depression that the minds oi<br />
ughtful men became directed to how far we could strengthen the<br />
ier to control credit and to the efficiency of controlling credit in<br />
it modern communities. Much thought was directed to the prob-<br />
, and it would be odd, indeed, if, as the result of that, and the<br />
erience in those various countries, we were not immeasurably<br />
: er equipped to deal with the credit problem to-day than we were<br />
.929-30. I ask the House to remember that until central banking<br />
; well established, individual trading banks followed their own<br />
rse in credit control, and, as there was no machinery for making<br />
tcourse cohesive, it stands to reason that varying policies were<br />
sued and that difficulties would arise. At that time the Commonilth<br />
Bank was in no sense adequately equipped for central bankand<br />
many countries were still groping towards this technique.<br />
marvel is, not that mistakes were made during the world depresi,<br />
but that more mistakes were not made, and that recovery in<br />
3tralia came as quickly as it did.<br />
In 1920 the control of the note issue was transferred to a board.<br />
to that time it had been controlled by the Treasurer, but in that </p>
<p>year it was transferred to a board, the chairman of which was the<br />
governor of the bank, ex officio. In 1924, the first legislative proposal<br />
designed to establish central banking in Australia was presented<br />
to this Parliament by the right honorable member for Cowper ( Sir<br />
Earle Page).<br />
Mr. CALWELL.-He sabotaged the Commonwealth Bank. f<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-The Minister may use harsh expressions, but<br />
the bill then introduced, and the speech then made, represented the<br />
first large, scientific and intelligent attempt in this country to estab-f<br />
lish central banking. In the bill which was sponsored by the right<br />
honorable member for Cowper, a board of directors was substituted(<br />
for one-man control and comprehensive central banking powers, in-1<br />
cluding the control of the note issue, were conferred upon the bank.<br />
From that date we may begin to trace out, not all at once, because f<br />
the progress was slow, the development of real central banking in<br />
this country.<br />
I now ask myself, and also invite honorable members to ask,(<br />
what should be the chief functions and powers of a central bank in<br />
this country. The chief function, as I understand it-and I speak with<br />
all the diffidence of a layman on these matters-is the regulation of I<br />
the volume of credit, including currency. That regulation is de-r<br />
signed to achieve, among other things, three results. The first is t<br />
the stabilisation of the internal or domestic value of the currency, I<br />
which is not merely a matter of stabilising things as items in accounts, r<br />
but stabilising the purchasing power of the people's money, the s<br />
people's savings, the people's future money. It is, therefore, a task C<br />
of the first magnitude. The second result is the stabilisation of the c<br />
external value of money, naturally through the exchanges. The third<br />
result is the reduction or elimination of sharp variations in the general t<br />
level of employment and trade activity. If one were asked for a<br />
broad statement of the objectives of a central bank, I believe that f.<br />
would not be an unfair summary. To achieve those results the f.<br />
central hank must be in a position-and I want to emphasise and reemphasise<br />
this throughout my speech-of real strength and real c<br />
authority. The central bank is not to be simply a servant of some<br />
passing movement. It is to be in a position of real strength and real<br />
authority. It is not only to he in a position to control the total volume<br />
of credit, and so affect the entire economy of the nation, but it also<br />
becomes the custodian, as it is in Australia, of the nation's cash reserves,<br />
and the nation's chief monetary adviser. If I may, I emphasise t<br />
the reference to the nation's chief monetary adviser. The adviser to t<br />
any government or to any community should be detached, objective i<br />
and utterly above the storm, because on the skill, honesty and dis-f<br />
interestedness of his advice a great deal will depend. The considera-b.<br />
tion of these things will show that a central bank, adequately equipped I<br />
with brains, scientific knowledge and experience, must be in a position i<br />
to lead banking thought and banking practice. So much for the t<br />
objectives of the central bank. ti </p>
<p>Methods of Controlling Credit<br />
We then inquire what instruments the bank can use in order to<br />
eve those objectives, and on that problem it would be idle to<br />
: end that there is unanimity, because central banking is, as I have<br />
, a modern art and science, and there is still room for ample difnce<br />
cf opinion about the value or significance of this instrument<br />
hat; but there is fairly common agreement at least that the foling<br />
are appropriate central banking powers: I am not now rei<br />
ng in particular to Australia, but to countries in general. Those<br />
, ers are the control of the note issue, as in Australia; the control<br />
he exchanges, which the central bank has de facto; the discountand<br />
rediscounting of trade bills; the bank rate; open market<br />
ations; lending to the Government, and the holding of deposits<br />
ai the trading banks. In Great Britain there is an enormous<br />
t-term bill market. Each of these is a method by which the<br />
ral bank can hope to influence and, in suitable cases, -control, the<br />
ine of credit in the country. All we have to do is to watch the<br />
ing and selling of securities on the open market by the central<br />
c to see that it is of their essence that the central bank should<br />
n a highly liquid condition. Let us consider an example of open<br />
ket operations by a central bank. It desires to put more cash into<br />
general banking system so that advances may be made on a more<br />
-al basis. In other words, it desires to initiate an inflationary<br />
ement, to apply a stimulus to trading operations, so it buys<br />
rities in the market, and puts cash into circulation. On another<br />
sion it may believe that a boom is developing, and that credit<br />
it to be restricted. It then sells securities for cash and takes<br />
cash out of the trading system. In order to do that kind of<br />
g a central bank must kceep its assets in a highly liquid condi-<br />
. A trading bank which kept 90 per cent. of its assets in liquid<br />
iwould not be much of a success as a trading bank. It would<br />
down on its job, but a central bank which, in normal circumces<br />
failed to keep its assets 90 per cent. liquid would be in danger<br />
iiing in its duty as a central bank. I mention that merely to<br />
trate a fundamental difference between central banking with its<br />
itive, delicate methods of controlling credit, and the output and<br />
-w of cash, and a trading bank which establishes more or less<br />
lanent relations with its customers over a term of years.<br />
[ believe that the effective weapons of a central bank in Ausi<br />
would be these-and I am not stating them in order of merit:<br />
) ank rate, open market operations, government finance, the leadand<br />
advising of the trading banks, and the taking of deposits<br />
the trading banks. The taking of deposits from the trading<br />
s represents one of the real departures in this bill from the<br />
lation of 1924. Of all those operations I believe that the most<br />
) rtant, having regard to the financial circumstances of Ausi,<br />
is leadership by the Commonwealth Bank in a truly co-operabanking<br />
system, in which the Commonwealth Bank and the </p>
<p>trading banks, accepting a joint responsibility, shall stabilise credit<br />
and trade. All those functions may now be exercised by the Commonwealth<br />
Bank under the existing law, though special legislation<br />
on the subject of deposits may be needed after the National Security<br />
Regulations have ceased to operate. I point out, however, that the<br />
National Security Regulations have not ceased to operate. This<br />
legislation, in so far as it deals with deposits, is anticipating by a long<br />
time the termination of the National Security Regulations. This is<br />
essentially a piece of post-war legislation which will not begin to<br />
operate until after the war, and the termination of the National<br />
Security Regulations. Why it should be brought on at this stage I'<br />
am at a loss to understand. If the National Security Regulations<br />
cease to operate, and Parliament then decides, or if it decides now<br />
in anticipation of such an occurrence, that deposits by trading banks<br />
with the central bank are to continue to be compulsory, whether fixed<br />
or variable, then no doubt legislation is, or will be, required.<br />
I turn at once to that problem because, as I have said, all the<br />
other proper functions of a central bank may already be exercised by.<br />
the Commonwealth Bank under the powers it now possesses. The<br />
real point of departure in this bill is the provision that the trading<br />
banks shall continue to make deposits with the central bank, that<br />
those deposits will continue to be frozen as against the trading banks,<br />
and that, by varying the amount of the cash deposits required from<br />
the trading banks, the total volume of credit may be increased or<br />
reduced. Problem of Variable Deposits<br />
The problem of variable deposits is an extremely difficult and<br />
important one. For my part I have had the greatest difficulty in<br />
completely clarifying my own mind on this intensely teasing subject.<br />
The Royal Commission on Banking recommended in paragraph 589<br />
of its report as follows:<br />
The Commonwealth Parliament should legislate to provide that the<br />
Commonwealth Bank Board, with the consent of the Treasurer, may require<br />
every trading bank to keep with the Commonwealth Bank a deposit(<br />
of an amount not less than a percentage, specified in the requisition, of<br />
the liability of that bank to its depositors in Australia.<br />
That is very much in line with the practice established by one or two<br />
central banks in 1934 and 1935. The next recommendation of the<br />
Banking Commission is as follows:<br />
Each trading bank should be required to keep on deposit the same<br />
percentage. The board should have power at its discretion to vary the<br />
percentage from time to time within the limit fixed by the consent of the<br />
Treasurer.<br />
The making of deposits by trading banks with the central bank may<br />
serve several purposes. Thirty or forty years ago, the central bank<br />
in the United States of America took dleposits from the trading banks </p>
<p>manily for the protection of the customers of the trading banks.<br />
tat is not significant now, although it was then. When that is the<br />
rpose in view, the matter has no real relation to central banking.<br />
is really ancillary to trading banking in the ordinary way, and parularly<br />
in the American way. Again, the making of deposits with<br />
central bank might mean very little more than the provision of<br />
! ap funds for the central bank, the deposits also representing the<br />
freserves of the trading banks, other than till money. That was<br />
-purpose for which deposits were made to the central bank in<br />
istralia before the war. The trading banks normally kept their<br />
; h reserves, other than till money, in the Commonwealth Bank. It<br />
d nothing to do with the control of credit. They were free deposits<br />
iich could be withdrawn at will. They formed part of the cash of<br />
! trading banks, and, therefore, were not related to central banking<br />
ntrol. The third system is that in which deposits are taken by the central<br />
nk from the trading banks as part and parcel of a scheme conously<br />
designed to regulate credit. The central bank asks for larger<br />
smaller deposits according as it desires to decrease or increase the<br />
3h holdings of the trading banks, the idea being that if the central<br />
nk takes, say, 15,000,000 from a trading bank, and puts it on fixed<br />
posit with itself, that amount no longer forms part of the trading<br />
3h of the trading bank, which must, therefore, decrease its advances.<br />
ius, the increasing or decreasing of fixed deposits by the trading<br />
nks with the central bank may determine the total amount of cash<br />
ailable to the trading banks, and so govern the amount of credit<br />
ailable. If the control of credit is the dominant purpose of requiring desits<br />
by the trading banks, th~ ere seems to be no escape from the<br />
stem of variable deposits, because it is of the essence * of such a<br />
ieme that the deposits should be adjusted up or down according to<br />
credit policy of the central bank. The question then arises, is<br />
ch a system of variable deposits a better method of achieving credit<br />
ntrol than that employed by the Bank of England, which is still<br />
greatest and most successful central bank. It has a remarkable<br />
-ord, and is the oldest central bank in existence. It has developed<br />
. mendous skill over the years, and to this moment it exercises no<br />
rnpulsory control whatever in its central banking functions. It<br />
erates entirely in co-operation with the trading banks, and it uses<br />
incipally, as it can in London, the method of the bank rate and open<br />
irket operations. Thus, we have to ask ourselves whether the<br />
stem of variable deposits by the trading banks with the central<br />
nk is likely to be more effective than the methods employed in<br />
) ndon. As to that, I do not believe that any man is qualified to<br />
; e a dogmatic reply. I do not believe that any one-not even the<br />
eatest authorities in the world--can say whether this use of variable<br />
posits is a scientifically accurate way to control credit. It is experi-<br />
! ntal, and I shall watch its operation with the greatest interest. </p>
<p>Let us understand that it really is experimental. Let us c<br />
understand that it is a crude method, which might produce i<br />
unexpected results, including the harshest kind of deflation. If the L<br />
central bank can take by compulsion a large part of the cash reserves 1<br />
of a trading bank and freeze them, the trading bank may be forced f<br />
to adopt very harsh methods in order to increase the volume of its L:<br />
liquid assets. If we are to have variable deposits-and this is at the<br />
heart of whatever reform is contained in the bill-will it be achieved<br />
best by some curt compulsion by the Commonwealth Bank without<br />
any kind of consultation with the trading banks, or by close and<br />
friendly co-operation between the central bank and the trading banks,<br />
with the former in a position of acknowledged leadership? We should<br />
think carefully before we introduce methods of authority and cornpulsion<br />
when we have never fully tried out the method of co-operation<br />
and of leadership which has achieved such amazing results in Great<br />
Briti. CALWELL.-Some day the Bank of England will be improved.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-That may be, but not by the Minister for Information<br />
( Mr. Calwell).<br />
Mr. CALwELL.-It will be done by a Labour Government in<br />
Great Britain.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-That may happen, because in that country they<br />
might get a good Labour Government. Even at the risk of being<br />
tedious, in order to complete my picture I mention that up to 1924,<br />
when legislation was introduced by the right honorable member for<br />
Cowper ( Sir Earle Page), the then Treasurer, most of the trading<br />
banks held relatively small balances at the Commonwealth Bank, but<br />
after the Act of 1924 was passed, all the trading banks in Australia<br />
have held increasing balances at the Commonwealth Bank. In 1928<br />
the Commonwealth Bank asked the trading banks to keep their reserves<br />
with it, and ever since 1930 the deposits by the trading banks<br />
with the Commonwealth Bank have formed the chief part of their<br />
cash in Australia. Up to that phase, the making of those deposits<br />
had no relation whatever to credit control; it was done primarily for<br />
the convenience of the trading banks. Incidentally, it was a replenishment<br />
of funds and a source of profit to the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
I come now to the war period-a period which we should have in<br />
close memory-because it provides a contrast between the two<br />
methods of approach. Towards the end of 1941 the right honorable<br />
member for Darling Downs ( Mr. Fadden), who was then Prime<br />
Minister, obtained from the trading banks an undertaking which he<br />
read to this House and was recorded in Hansard at the time of the<br />
presentation of the budget in 1941.<br />
Mr. CQNELAN.-The trading banks made an offer.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I do not suppose that even the honorable<br />
member for Griffith ( Mr. Conelan) assumes that the arrangement<br />
came out of the air. He might at least assume that it was the out-</p>
<p>e of a great number of discussions between the then Prime Minand<br />
the Treasurer, the Commonwealth Bank, and the trading<br />
cs. It is well that we should remind ourselves of the terms of that<br />
! rtaking before we talk too crudely about compulsion, and there-<br />
I shall read the terms of the undertaking given by the trading<br />
cs-The trading banks have no intention and no desire to make excess<br />
its arising from war conditions.<br />
As a war-time measure and with the object of ensuring that addis<br />
to their funds owing to war conditions will not be used to make<br />
! ss profits or to expand advances in any way contrary to the National<br />
restsuse to ask honorable members to compare that with the bill upon<br />
-h they will soon have to vote-<br />
, agree to place all surplus investable funds accruing in their hands on<br />
) sit with the Commonwealth Bank as special war-time deposits, and<br />
. e to the Commonwealth Bank making appropriate variations in the<br />
of interest thereon to ensure that no excess war-time profits arise.<br />
To achieve the objects set out above, the trading banks give the foling<br />
firm undertaking:-<br />
They will not make new advances or grant increases in existing<br />
ances except in accordance with the policy laid down by the Common-<br />
Ith Bank from time to time and to ensure conformity therewith will<br />
ply to the Commonwealth Bank a monthly analysis of new and insed<br />
advances in a form approved by the Commonwealth Bank.<br />
Before purchasing or subscribing to Government or semierment<br />
loans, the trading banks will obtain the concurrence of the<br />
imonwealth Bank.<br />
The trading banks will make available by way of deposit with the<br />
imonwealth Bank all surplus investable funds accruing in their bands,<br />
all funds over and above those necessary to enable the bank to meet<br />
overdraft requirements of the public in accordance with the advance<br />
cy laid down by the Commonwealth Bank, and those funds necessary<br />
the protection of their depositors. The deposits will be made at such<br />
rates of interest as will avoid the trading banks making excess profits<br />
of war conditions. These rates will be fixed by the Commonwealth<br />
Ik from time to time.<br />
They will advise the Commonwealth Bank periodically what<br />
is become available as above, and the Commonwealth Bank will decide<br />
total amount of deposits required from the trading banks from time<br />
; ime. Such deposits will be made in a special war-time deposit account,<br />
will be for a term of six months. They will be renewed as they<br />
; ure unless, in the opinion of the Commonwealth Bank, they are neces-<br />
7 to the trading banks for purposes mentioned in paragraph ( 3)<br />
Bof. They agree to supply the Commonwealth Bank with such certifi-<br />
! s from the Commonwealth Commissioner of Taxation as will enable<br />
tbank to satisfy itself that the undertaking herein regarding, profits<br />
Peing observed. </p>
<p>Protection for Depositors? b<br />
I point out that no opportunity was given for that voluntary scheme tj<br />
to work; compulsion was at cnce brought in by the present Govern-a<br />
ment. In the bill I find no reference whatever to any power in the t<br />
banks to make advances on overdrafts in accordance with the central i<br />
bank's policy, nor do I find any reference whatever to the protection<br />
of the depositors with the trading banks. I mention these matters b<br />
at this stage because it is so easy to treat the volume of war-timea<br />
deposits in banks as being the property of the banks. Those depositsa<br />
are not the property of the banks; they are liabilities of the banks. 0r<br />
If the depositors who own the rights to those moneys want to drawr b<br />
their moneys, it seems curious that the bank should answer with an c.<br />
emphatic " No; we have no liability to you in this matter. Your de-C<br />
posits have been frozen by the Commonwealth Bank." I ask the ti<br />
Treasurer to consider seriously whether there should not be some pro-tF<br />
vision to give protection to the depositors of the banks, who, after E<br />
all, are the owners, in the broad sense, of the moneys that they have S<br />
deposited with the banks. I ask him to do that, notwithstanding that<br />
the Government has the numbers to carry this bill. The War-time I<br />
Banking Control Regulations threw the undertaking to which I have gn<br />
referred overboard, and set up a compulsory system. As the result of nI<br />
those regulations the funds lodged in ' the special account by the t<br />
trading banks became frozen funds; the banks could not use them or<br />
withdraw them without the permission of the Treasurer. t<br />
Mr. FADDEN.-Except to use them as treasury-bills, which they n<br />
did. g<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-There are no instances of the interest of deposi-t<br />
tors being specially considered. E<br />
Mr. CURTIN.-The deposits of the trading banks with the central b<br />
bank would be liabilities of the trading banks to their depositors. N<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-That is what I have been pointing out, and IF<br />
am glad that the right honorable gentleman agrees with me. These f<br />
moneys are liabilities of the trading banks to their depositors. I re-b<br />
mind the House that when a bank has liabilities to its depositors thel g<br />
depositors have an old-fashioned prejudice in regard to the discharge<br />
of these liabilities when the time for discharge arises. A bank has anI<br />
interest, on behalf of its depositors, in having some flexibility and in<br />
not having its funds frozen; but under these war-time regulations, I1<br />
special accounts and frozen deposits have reached a total of r<br />
1230,000,000, according to the Treasurer's statement. This bill, to-b<br />
gether with the Banking Bill, which also is before the Parliament, s<br />
proposes to make permanent a system which was designed for purely tl<br />
emergency purposes. There is no time limit in the new bill; appar-B<br />
ently, the scheme of compulsory deposits in these special accounts is r<br />
to go on in perpetuity. Clause 18 requires every bank to establish17<br />
with the Commonwealth Bank a special account; clause 19 transfers to<br />
the special account of each bank the amount to the credit of that r( </p>
<p>' s special account under the regulations; clause 20 provides that<br />
' rading banks shall each month lodge in the special account such<br />
unts as the Commonwealth Bank directs. The fund may be added<br />
* om month to month, according to the direction of the Commnonth<br />
Bank. The amount to be directed has a limit placed upon it:<br />
interesting to discover what that limit is. The amount is not to<br />
uch that the amount to the credit of the bank's special account,<br />
making the new lodgment, exceeds the sum of the original<br />
unt transferred, plus any increase of the bank's assets after the<br />
ation of this new law. The nett effect of this is that the trading<br />
-s are to be confined to their pre-war assets position. Under the<br />
lations they were confined to their pre-war assets position, bee<br />
any increase of their assets was treated as arising from warfinance,<br />
and for the avoidance of secondary inflation, it was said<br />
war-time credits must be passed over to the Commonwealth<br />
and rightly so. Under this new, permanent system, there they<br />
1; and any increase may be called upon by way of further<br />
ment in the special account. The curious thing is that, while the<br />
will confine the trading banks to their pre-war position, the<br />
ral banking department of the Commonwealth Bank will have<br />
uch restriction placed on it; it is to run free. We are told that<br />
is to be competition, and by that I assume that fair competition<br />
tended; yet the first competition that we see provided in this<br />
lation is that no trading bank may expand beyond its 1939 posi-<br />
; every increase of the volume of business arising from the deds<br />
of the business community for banking accommodation must<br />
: the trading division of the Commonwealth Bank. That seems<br />
e a queer form of fair competition. The Commonwealth Bank<br />
which is now before the Chair, professes to attach a safeguard<br />
provision in clause 21-<br />
The Special Accounts established by banks under Division 3 of<br />
IL. of the Banking Act 1945, and the accounts established by banks<br />
; he purposes of section fifty-two of the Banking Act 1945, shall not<br />
ept in the General Banking Division.<br />
' lause 21 says that these special accounts are not to be kept in the<br />
ral banking division. Well, I have had a look at this clause, and<br />
rite other honorable gentlemen to have a look at it, and I do not<br />
-ss to know what it means, if it does mean anything. The<br />
surer was optimistic enough to tell us that that meant that the<br />
! y in this general account cannot be used in the general banking<br />
iess. I find no such language in the clause. It says that the<br />
al accounts shall not be kept in the general banking division, but<br />
is no provision that they shall not be used in the Rural Credits<br />
ich, the Mortgage Bank Department or the Industrial Departand,<br />
as I hope to point out later, the Industrial Division itself<br />
! sents about as bold a piece of concealment as this bill contains.<br />
-e is the alleged safeguard! It is much more apparent than~ it is<br />
The whole thing on this point is a striking example of the </p>
<p>Government's desire to perpetuate in Australia, long after the emergencies<br />
have passed, what has been epigrammatically styled " the servile<br />
state," and the particular weapon here is the weapon of slow<br />
strangulation of the private banking system in favour of a publicly<br />
owned and politically controlled banking system.<br />
Direct Control by Politicians"<br />
It is abundantly clear-at least I hope it will be-that the true<br />
function of the central bank in a system in which there are also<br />
trading banks can never be satisfactorily performed in an atmosphere<br />
of hostility. If any one supposes that in an atmosphere of hostility<br />
in which the private banks and the central bank are at arn's length<br />
any good purpose for Australia can be achieved I beg him to forget it.<br />
We can get good results for this country only by utmost co-operation<br />
and understanding. Therefore every endeavour should be made to<br />
produce understanding, and there should be as little insistence as<br />
possible on the weapon of coercion. But, if there is to be coercion<br />
and if it is really in the minds of the framers of this hill that the<br />
trading bank deposits with the central bank should be used as a flexible<br />
means of regulating credit, it is quite clear that the political, and,<br />
therefore, fluctuating control of the central bank is utterly destructive<br />
of the whole scheme. I say by way of warning to my honorable<br />
friends on the other side that, though they may think that political<br />
control of this bank is a fine thing when they are in office, they will<br />
not always be in office. In fact, they will not be in office very long,<br />
and I venture to believe that when they, or those who are left of them,<br />
are sitting on the left-hand side of the Chair in this chamber, they<br />
will curse the day when they made the central bank a mere fluttering<br />
political instrument.<br />
G overnnment members dissenting.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I see. They rely on us doing the right thing<br />
so that for a few years they may do the wrong thing. I always thought<br />
that that was their point of view.<br />
Mr. CALwELL.-The right honorable gentleman is our best frozen<br />
itsset. Mr. MENZIES.-I notice that the Minister for Information<br />
seems a little worried about me. All that means, and perhaps it can<br />
be summed up in this way, that we need in Australia-and I think,<br />
or, at least, hope that we can all agree on this, world experience proves<br />
it-a strong, well-equipped central bank. The Treasurer said so in a<br />
passage which is such a masterpiece of irony that I beg leave to repeat<br />
it. It is one of those things which the people will not willingly let<br />
die when they hear about it. He said-<br />
The Central Banking functions and powers of the Commonw. ealth<br />
Bank are strengthened so as to ensure that the broad lines of its monetary<br />
and financial policy will be in harmony with the economic policy of the<br />
Government and in the interests of the people of Australia. A 9 </p>
<p>compliment my honorable friend on that. He says that we are to<br />
-engthen the central bank by making it our servant, by taking it<br />
. t of its non-political atmosphere and making it obey the political<br />
. iim of the moment. Strength in the central bank is essential beuse<br />
the end of the central bank is to produce stability. Weakness<br />
s never produced stability. Strength will. Except to mere specu-<br />
: ors the stability of the currency does matter. If that needs proof,<br />
ery budget presented by the Treasurer has said so. Without<br />
isonable stability of the currency there can be no incentive to save<br />
) ney, there can be no reliance placed on social security, the deferred<br />
y or gratuities of fighting men become a mere gamble, life insurances<br />
come chancey, and general trade, which is an essential element of<br />
neral prosperity, becomes a mere matter of gambling in futures.<br />
ie stability of the currency is of first-class importance to the ordinary<br />
m and women of this country and a strong, independent central<br />
nk is of first-class importance to a stabilised currency.<br />
Mr. SPENDER.-We may see the honorable member for Werriwa<br />
dr. Lazzarini) made Treasurer any day, too.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-We may indeed! From now on, if this bill<br />
Duld be passed, all the delicate adjustments that have to be made<br />
a central bank charged with this great responsibility will be under<br />
Sdirect control of the Treasurer of the day, whoever he may be,<br />
d he, in his turn, will be under the direct control of politicians like<br />
rselves, and I venture to say with a great respect to all honorable<br />
. mbers, including myself, that we have not the skill, experience or<br />
. ormation necessary for this task. Yet we shall control the<br />
' easurer and the Treasurer will control the bank. I go now to -a<br />
Drt and pleasing task. I intend to quote a passage from an estabhed<br />
authority who will be listened to with great respect by members<br />
the Government. That authority is Professor D. B. Copland,<br />
lose earlier sins appear to have been forgiven. In 1931, my disguished<br />
and able friend wrote a book, What Have the Banks Done!<br />
which he said-<br />
In the controversies that have taken place in the past eighteen<br />
) nths there is sufficient evidence that political control of the currency<br />
Puld destroy confidence, and abolish reasonable checks to the issue of<br />
. dit. We can therefore only reap the benefits of a liberal banking<br />
licy if the control of the currency be free from political interference.<br />
iope that most of the members of the House will agree with that.<br />
when this bill has gone through, what will be the position of a<br />
bour Treasurer who goes to meet his party and to whom his party<br />
is, as I believe it has said on more than one occasion, " We want<br />
5,000,000 for this, that or the other thing." I noticed the other day<br />
Lt my honorable friend the Treasurer, when confronted with such a<br />
-nand, made an impassioned answer-at least, it appeared to be<br />
passioned, in the unofficial press versions-in which he pointed out<br />
tat the taxation was and what the obligations were for the future,<br />
I said, in effect, as any good tory might have said, " I cannot afford </p>
<p>it. You cannot have But I wonder what the position will be<br />
when he goes before caucus after this bill has become law and receives<br />
a demand for f20,000,000. Tempted to say, " I cannot afford<br />
it," he will have them reply, " Of course you can. You are now in<br />
charge of the Commonwealth Bank. You can direct it. You are in<br />
charge of the note issue.<br />
Mr. FADDEN.-" And the sky is the limit."<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Yes,' '" and the sky is the limit. We have abolished<br />
the reserve. There is no restriction on the note issue."<br />
Mr. HARRISON.-The right honorable gentleman is putting ideas<br />
into their heads.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I do not have to put ideas into the head of the<br />
Minister for Works ( Mr. Lazzarini) because that is his style of<br />
finance. That is the very kind of finance that he believes in. If ever<br />
there were something that' put us on the slippery path to real continental<br />
inflation it would be that kind of thing. That is all I desire to<br />
say on the proposal to " strengthen" the central bank.<br />
Advantages of a Board<br />
The second proposal is for the abolition of the Bank Board, and<br />
that, of course, receives griat applause. Yet honorable members<br />
know there are great and obvious advantages to the country in having<br />
a system of controlling the central bank by a board of directors or a<br />
board of governors. Every other country has clearly seen those advantages.<br />
I do not know of any democratic country which has oneman<br />
control of the central bank. The great advantages of a board<br />
are the bringing together of a diversity of experience, the added<br />
judgment produced by frank discussion by competent men, the added<br />
strength involved in joint responsibility, and the publicity which a<br />
board of directors strongly adhering to a view can secure for that<br />
view in the event of great conflict of opinion on a central banking<br />
problem. Under this bill the governor, one man, will conduct<br />
no less than eight institutions; central banking, general<br />
banking, the note issue, the Rural Credits Department,<br />
the Mortgage Bank Department, the Industrial Finance Department,<br />
housing loans, and the Commonwealth Savings Bank.<br />
My only disappointment is that there were not seven instead<br />
of eight, because I should then have been reminded of one of Wordsworth's<br />
poems. When one of those institutions had gone under this<br />
strange system they would say, " One of us in the churchyard lies,<br />
but, master, we are seven." It is interesting to recall that in 1930, a<br />
time when a Labour Government was formerly in office, the then<br />
Treasurer, Mr. Theodore, brought in a bill to establish a reserve<br />
bank, and provided that it was to be controlled by a board consisting<br />
of a governor, two deputy governors, the secretary to the Treasury,<br />
and five other directors, " who are or had been actively engaged in </p>
<p>-iculture, commerce, finance, industry or labour." It is also intering<br />
to recall that the royal commission, so far from reporting in<br />
* our of the abolition of the Bank Board, reported in favour of conuing<br />
the Bank Board. True, the royal commission recommended<br />
Lt the governor should be chairman of the hoard; and the Treasurer<br />
[ I remember that although he was not lacking in courage when he<br />
nted to dissent he did not dissent from that recommendation. At<br />
Lt time he had no quarrel with the board; to-day he proposes to<br />
Mlish it.<br />
Mr. CURTi-.-Why did the Theodore bill fail to pass?<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I feel no occasion to go into that. Does the<br />
* ht honorable gentleman suppose that it failed to pass because it<br />
wvided for a board of directors; because unless he believes that<br />
, s the reason why it failed to pass his interjection is a mere inter-<br />
Dtion? I know perfectly well that the right honorable gentleman<br />
iuld be delighted if I talked about some other bill, because he will<br />
d this bill difficult to defend at the bar of public opinion.<br />
The third provision in this bill is quite bluntly for the<br />
litical control of the governor and, therefore, of the bank.<br />
ause 9 provides that the bank must give effect to govern-<br />
2nt policy, but honorable members will observe that the<br />
) rd " policy" is not defined. It may apply to matters great or<br />
iall, and, therefore, it is quite clear that the clause provides for com-<br />
-te political control. Everything is policy, and, therefore, on everyng<br />
the Treasurer may give a direction to the governor.<br />
An " Advisory Council"<br />
Clause 28 sets up an advisory council. It is a purely advisory<br />
uncil. I do not want to rake over the ashes of old controversies;<br />
. t it is a purely advisory council, and it consists, mark you, of three<br />
bordinates of the governor in the bank's service, and two Treasury<br />
icers. Such a body cannot be described as in any sense independent,<br />
d, quite clearly, it is mere window-dressing thrown into the bill to<br />
ike it appear that there is some form of check or authoritative con-<br />
Itation. SIR EARLE PAGE-Why does not the governor have a vote in it?<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I take that to be almost a humorous addendum.<br />
he governor has no vote, but, after all, he will not be bound by any<br />
: cision of the advisory council, and as the other members will be<br />
ider him, the advisory council does not rate very high. In addition,<br />
is interesting to note that most of the senior officers of this bank<br />
ill be politically appointed, namely, the governor and the deputy<br />
) vernor. the secretary of the Treasury, the additional Treasury re-<br />
-esentative on the advisory council, the general manager of the<br />
Ldustrial Finance Department, the chairman of the Promotions<br />
ppeal Board, and so on. The Minister for Information ( Mr. Calwell) </p>
<p>interjected that the royal commission had recommended a method<br />
which is substantially adopted in clause 9.<br />
Mr. CALWELL.-And for which the honorable member for New<br />
England voted.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-The royal commission recommended that there<br />
should be a method of this kind for reconciling differences not between<br />
the Government and the governor, but between the Government<br />
and a board of directors. There we have a very essential difference.<br />
After all, one man, himself dependent for appointment on<br />
the government of the day, is not in a strong position to resist or<br />
argue about the instruction of a Treasurer or a government; but a<br />
board of directors, consisting of people who are in every other respect<br />
independent of the Government, is in a far better position to say, " We<br />
think this is wrong. We object to it. We are prepared to argue<br />
about it, and, if necessary, to tell the people and Parliament about it."<br />
There is a vital distinction between the recommendation of the royal<br />
commission and what appears in the bill. But I go further and say<br />
that what appears in the royal commission's report is itself open to<br />
very grave question. I am not prepared to accept a state of affairs in<br />
which the Executive, of its own force, is able to override a central<br />
bank on matters of great moment. After all, all matters arising will<br />
be great or small. If they be small the Government should not he<br />
interfering in the control, and if they be large matters Parliament<br />
should attend to them. It is high time that the authority of Parliament<br />
was restored. If there is any major conflict between the central<br />
bank and the Government, then Parliament should be invited by appropriate<br />
means to deal with the matter.<br />
" Competition" with the Trading Banks<br />
The fourth matter is competition with the trading banks. I suppose<br />
that we shall be told that competition between the Commonwealth<br />
Bank in its trading capacity and the trading banks is perfectly fair.<br />
It cannot be fair. The Commonwealth Bank will pay no land tax<br />
or income tax, and it can face losses with equanimity. But, in any<br />
event, competition between the trading banks and a bank whose<br />
primary function is that of a central bank is quite inconsistent with<br />
the atmosphere of wise leadership and co-operation which ought to<br />
exist in a banking system. The royal commission, in paragraph 585<br />
of its report, deals with that matter. In view of the lateness of the<br />
hour, I shall not read that paragraph. but the commission, in a sentence,<br />
said-<br />
One way in which this conformity<br />
( that is conformity between the Commonwealth Bank and the<br />
trading banks-)<br />
can be achieved is by co-operation. This requires wise leadership on the th( int dr;<br />
* bo an wi on<br />
Q th, TI tr, ca. it an de pe w<br />
' C cx ta B is </p>
<p>of the Commonwealth Bank and its acceptance by the trading<br />
ise leadership! Acceptance of co-operation !-when with all<br />
extra weights to be carried by the trading banks, the Governsays<br />
that its own central bank is in one of its departments to go<br />
ctive competition with them. There is another point to which I<br />
the attention of the Treasurer. The same man will be controlling<br />
banks. The same governor is responsible for the central bank<br />
he Commonwealth trading bank. To use a fashionable phrase,<br />
sort of a " split personality" will this one man need if he is at<br />
nd the same time to control the central bank and a trading bank,<br />
terests of which must on many occasions be completely opposed?<br />
vhole essence of the central bank is that it may have to control<br />
ig banks. It may decide to sell securities and so reduce their<br />
or buy securities and increase their cash. In the circumstances<br />
, ht be to the interest of the trading bank to hold more cash, but<br />
ity to the economic system to hold less. That, after all, is the<br />
ess of a central bank, to reconcile the interests of trading banks<br />
heir duty to this country; and this unhappy man will have to<br />
e that conflict, which can be resolved only by a strong inde-<br />
-nt central bank.<br />
CALWELL.-And his decision will be the same each time.<br />
MENZIES.-He will need to be a super-man if he can, with<br />
action to every one, occupy two such inconsistent positions at<br />
Line time. The royal commission made a recommendation on this<br />
and that recommendat~ on, on the face of it, is contrary to the<br />
I have been putting. The commission, in paragraph 577 of its<br />
t, states-<br />
WVaer e of opiniion that the use of its trading-bank activities ais an<br />
ict to central bank policy is in keeping with its central bank<br />
ions and is te be approved.<br />
* ut if we go back to paragraph 156 of the commission's report<br />
iall there find explained in much mrjre detail what the commishad<br />
in mind. What it had in mind was the using of its trading<br />
powers as an additional mearis of controlling the volume of<br />
t, not as a mere competitor in the market for business, but by<br />
g business a3 it came along in order to help the Commonwealth<br />
: to perform its central bank function. All that is explained in<br />
3graph 156 af the commission's report.<br />
' he fifth proposal is the abolition of Board control of the note<br />
, and as the hair goes with the hide I do not need to waste time<br />
iis point. ' Ine note issue is now to be controlled by the governor<br />
e bank, and, through clause 9 of the bill, by the Treasurer, and<br />
igh the Treasurer by the caucus, or party, mceting of the day;<br />
if we care to go further back still we might find other people<br />
ig autboricy in the matter. </p>
<p>Currency at the Mercy of Politics<br />
That brings me to the sixth of the proposals to which I have referred,<br />
namely, the abolition of the currency reserve. Here is another<br />
interesting example of how the Government has accepted that portion<br />
of the royal commission's recommendation which suits it, and has<br />
ignored, or discarded, the rest; because the royal commission recommended<br />
the abolition of the currency reserve and the substitution of a<br />
note issue limited by law to a fixed maximum, subject to the right of<br />
the bank to exceed the maximum by a stated amount with the consentof<br />
the Treasurer. What does the Government do? It ignores the<br />
safeguard, the proposition that there should be a fixed maximum, with<br />
limited flexibility, in the note issue, and seizes eagerly upon the proposition<br />
that the currency reserve should be abolished, the effect of<br />
that being this: It is hard to conceive that any issue between the<br />
governor and the Treasurer on the note issue would not be a matter 4<br />
of policy. It would be hard for my friend the Treasurer to think up<br />
a case in which a difference of that kind would not be a difference .3i<br />
policy; and, therefore, this bill places under the political control of the<br />
Treasurer the note issue of the country, and utterly and unconditionally<br />
abolishes all reserves behind that currency. For a long time we<br />
had a currency reserve of 25 per cent. gold, which was later modified<br />
to 25 per cent, gold or English sterling. That is how it stands to-day.<br />
When this bill has been passed no reserve requirement will be provided.<br />
There is nothing whatever on to which any person protecting<br />
the currency can seize as a means of defence. Every Treasurer will<br />
he utterly and literally defenceless in the presence of those who, in<br />
some ignorant clamour, desire to have the note issue expanded for the<br />
purpose of meeting somne passing whim or political demand.<br />
I now desire to discuss very briefly what reazons there are, or(<br />
were, for the provision of a currency reserve, because this is a<br />
profoundly important matter for Australia. As I see it, there are two<br />
principal reasons to which I am disposed to attach weight. The first<br />
of them is a psychological reason. The abolition of all reserve provisions,<br />
when coupled with untrammelled political control of the currency,<br />
might very well produce the most far-reaching results. The<br />
psychological factor in currency matters is not to be ignored. In<br />
Australia we have had painful experience of the effet which a deepseated<br />
public psychology can have on the currency, and on the whole<br />
economic position. I recall having read in a book by D. H. Robertson.<br />
the Cambridge economist, a story which illustrated the psychological<br />
factor in the matter of gold. A goldmine manager in South Africa<br />
had a glass eye, and it was a very ferocious glass eye. as artificial eyes<br />
sometimes are, and it produced, or helped to produce, great discipline<br />
in the mine, so that pilfering and speculation decreased when he was<br />
in the vicinity. Before he went on leave he made a practice of taking<br />
out the artificial eye. and placing it in a prominent place in his office. </p>
<p>he natives, who were employed in the mine, felt that his eye was<br />
ill on them, and they continued to behave until one day one of them<br />
id enough wit to place an empty cigarette tin over the glass eye so<br />
at he could not be seen, and henceforth a good time was had by all<br />
the manager's absence.<br />
Mr. LAZZARINI.-That is only a story.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Yes, it is only a story. I do not suppose that<br />
even happened. But then the Minister would, by an Act of Parliaent,<br />
abolish not only all sound banking practice-or at least he<br />
: sires to-but also public psychology. He will not succeed in doing<br />
I venture to say that whether it is soundly based in financial<br />
eory or not, there is a great psychological value for any nation in a<br />
. cked paper currency.<br />
Mr. FADDEN.-Of course there is.<br />
Mr. LAZZARINI.-It was the cigarette tin that " did it."<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-It must have happened before the war, when<br />
npty cigarette tins were still available. The second reason is not<br />
; ychological, but purely practical, and it is mentioned by that very<br />
 illiant and progressive writer and thinker, the economist, J. M.<br />
eynes, in Treatise on Money. I can quote J. M. Keynes in any<br />
, mpany on these matters, because if any economist has influenced<br />
odern economic thought, it is he.<br />
Mr. POLLARD.-That is why he was made a director of the Bank<br />
England. Mr. MENZIES.-Yes, and the honorable member will be interted<br />
to know that as a director of the Bank of England, he does not<br />
id himself sitting side by side with a director appointed by the<br />
overnment. He sits on a board of governors, entirely independent<br />
political control, and the bank enjoys no authority of a kind that<br />
e Government proposes, in this bill, to grant to the Commonwealth<br />
ink. Mr. LAZZARINI.-J. M. Keynes has turned a few economic somerults.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-If the Minister persists in interjecting, I shall<br />
obliged to call him " Chatterini." J. M. Keynes wrote-<br />
What is the object of a gold reserve? Partly to provide liquid reurces<br />
for use in ultimate emergencies partly for merely psycholoical<br />
reasons to promote confidence.<br />
eynes then explained the " ultimate emergency," by saying that-<br />
The reserve is mainly to meet short-period fluctuations in the interitional<br />
balance of indebtedness or, as it used to be called, " the external<br />
. ain." To cope with these factors, he sees virtue in the fixing of " a<br />
inimum absolute figure for the gold reserve and a maximum absote<br />
figure for the note circulation, both these figures being subject </p>
<p>to reasonable revision from time to time, and so chosen as to allow a<br />
wise discretion to the central bank in its day-to-day and year-to-year t<br />
policies." When he speaks of gold, he includes foreign currency; l:<br />
and speaking from our point of view here, he would include English<br />
sterling with gold when applying the principles to which he had re-a<br />
ferred. But this bill ignores all factors both psychological and prac-I<br />
tical. It does not profess to say that there shall be a maximum to c<br />
the note issue or that we shall have a minimum holding of gold or a<br />
English sterling. It ignores, apparently, the very important fact that s<br />
this country's solvency depends primarily on its avoidance of default C<br />
abroad, and, therefore, reserves to meet the external drain are of , t<br />
first importance. It simply says, without qualification, that there shall<br />
be no reserve of any kind, and the result is that it passes over an unlimited,<br />
unconditional control over the note issue to the central bank<br />
which, for the first time as a central bank, is to be plunged into the<br />
vortex of p~ olitics and day-to-day political direction and control. t<br />
Nationalisation of Industry<br />
Earlier 1 indicated that I should like to say a few words about a seventh<br />
matter, and that is the industrial finance proposals contained in<br />
this bill, because the more one looks at them, the more one finds how<br />
very significant and far-reaching they are. The industrial finance<br />
department is created by Part X. of the bill, beginning with clause 91.<br />
It is to perform-functions, which are not defined, but which, one<br />
gathers from the Treasurer's speech, will have something to do with<br />
industrial development in Australia, whether by government or bys<br />
private enterprise. But when we come to see what its powers andS<br />
resources are, we shall find somnething which to me is as astonishing t<br />
as anything I have ever seen in a bill of this kind. Clause 95 pro-'<br />
vides t<br />
The bank shall have, and may exercise through the industrial finance<br />
department, such powers as are necessary for the exercise of the functions<br />
of the industrial finance department under the last preceding section<br />
and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing may, through the,<br />
industrial finance department lend money; and purchase or other-r<br />
wise acquire shares and securities and sell or otherwise dispose of shares<br />
and securities so purchased or acquired.<br />
Therefore, this new department will be able to lend money and<br />
buy and sell shares. It seemns to be admirably equipped, for example,<br />
to deal with the problem of the nationalisation of the interstate airlines,<br />
or with the nationalisation of anything else which the Govern-f<br />
ment may seek to draw into its net. ' the powers, as the House will<br />
see, are as near as possible unlimited. I turn now to clause 97 toa<br />
discover what financial resources will be available. Briefly, I find<br />
that there is no limit to the financial resources which may be placed r<br />
at the disposal of this new department. Clause 97 provides that the r<br />
Treasurer may make advances to the bank for the purposes of thea </p>
<p>istrial finance department of such amounts and subject to such<br />
is and conditions as are agreed upon by the Treasurer and the<br />
c. That is as broad as it is long. The Treasurer may make ad-<br />
-es to the bank, and clause 98 provides that the bank may make<br />
inces to the industrial finance department, " at no time to exceed<br />
00,000." In order to get away from this rather petty conception<br />
noney, clause 98 provides also that the savings bank may make<br />
inces to the bank for use in the industrial finance department of<br />
amounts and subject to such terms and conditions as the governor<br />
rmines. This is the first time in the history of Australia when<br />
admirable conservatism of the savings banks which have, by law<br />
by practice, confined their investments to government securities<br />
ie past-<br />
M~ r. ABBOTT.-And the land.<br />
~ Ar. MENZIES.-That is so. This is the first time that they have<br />
been told or directed, because that is what it amounts to, that<br />
r money shall be invested in an industrial finance department, the<br />
ness of which will be to lend money on any or no security, and to<br />
and sell shares.<br />
SIR FREDERICK STEWART.-I am reminded of the purchase o~ f<br />
adcasting Station 2HD Newcastle.<br />
Monetary Policy and Future Problems<br />
q4r. MENZIES.-That seems to be a matter of the greatest pos-<br />
. gravity, and if one can discern in this particular department posities<br />
of that kind. I believe that when we have an abundance of<br />
to exam-ine all the minute details of the bill, we shall find that this<br />
ot the only example of utterly unsound methods being grafted on<br />
nstitutions which have stood the test of time, not because they<br />
2gamnbling institutions, but because they were secure institutions.<br />
Ishould like to put it to honorable members and to the people in<br />
! ral in Australia, that we are in grave danger of misunderstanding<br />
ingerously misunderstanding-this whole problem of monetary<br />
rm. The depression with all the wretchedness and suffering that<br />
-ought, the curious reluctance of the trading banks to inform the<br />
ic mind on matters of currency, a reluctance that I have never<br />
iable to understand, and the somewhat tentative position occupied<br />
he Commonwealth Bank for a number of years-all those things<br />
! been emphasised by the apparent phenomenon of war-time<br />
. ice, and they have conspired to -induce in the minds of many<br />
) le a belief that monetary reform, as such, is the be all and end<br />
, f economic reconstruction, and that irrespective of hard work, iniity<br />
and the encouragement of enterprise and thrift, full employt<br />
can be provided without difficulty by central bank action. I do<br />
say that honorable members entertain such a belief, but they know<br />
vell as I do that thousands of people in Australia have come to </p>
<p>entertain it. Some of our economists in this country are by no means<br />
free from blame for this extraordinarily loose and dangerous approach.<br />
Therefore, it is necessary for us to remind ourselves of the<br />
fact that a liberal monetary policy-that is, a policy which is intelligent<br />
and far-seeking and which aims at the full utilisation of our re-<br />
Fsources, human and material--cannot really solve the problem of<br />
production and inequitable distribution.<br />
Mr. McLEOD.-Or want in the midst of plenty.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Yes. It cannot do it. I referred a few minutes<br />
ago to the Cambridge economist, D. H. Robertson, and I should like<br />
to quote a very pregnant passage from his book on " Money"<br />
The real economic evils of s ociety-in adequate production and inequitable<br />
distribution-lie too deep for any purely monetary ointment t~ o<br />
cure. An unwise monetary policy can wreak unmerited hardship and<br />
engender unnecessary confusion and waste; not even a wise one can turn<br />
a world which is unjust and poor into a world which is rich and just.<br />
The mending of the road over which the produce passes to market is no(<br />
substitute for the digging and dunging of the fields themselves. No<br />
tinkering with counters will take us-very far towards the discovery of an<br />
industrial system which shall supply both adequate incentives to those<br />
who venture and plan, and peace of mind to those who sweat and endure.<br />
I believe that is the truth and the whole truth of this matter, and<br />
that we should do well to bear it in mind.<br />
A certain sceptism has arisen in Australia in the public mind-I do<br />
not wonder at it-about opposition to bills. Members of the public<br />
have seen bills opposed in Parliament in the past, and after elections<br />
have taken place, they have seen all too frequently these bills left on<br />
the statute-book unamended and untouched. Therefore, on behalf of<br />
my colleagues and myself, I desire to make quite clear to the House<br />
and to the people that if we on this side of the chamber are returned<br />
to office in the future, we shall take prompt steps to restore board<br />
control to the Commonwealth Bank, with political independence for<br />
the Commonwealth Bank functions, and a complete restoration of<br />
parliamentary authority on this matter, and that in every other respect<br />
we shall hold ourselves obliged instantly to review the working<br />
of this legislation with the object of bringing it into line with what we<br />
believe to be the stable re quirements of the people. I make that statement<br />
publicly, here and now, because it will be well that when the<br />
people of Australia come to pass judgment upon this matter, they<br />
should know exactly what is the issue, and where we all stand upon it.<br />
19-47 Jeffeott St., Melb. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
