<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41352</transcript-id>
    <title>Macquarie Park Interchange a win for commuters</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/11/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Faster and smoother transitions between buses, trains and taxis will become a reality for commuters in the Macquarie Park precinct after the Turnbull and Berejiklian governments agreed to build a major new interchange.</p>
<p>The state-of-the art interchange will make commuting to and from the state’s second biggest business district easier for more than 20,000 transport customers who travel through the precinct each day. </p>
<p>The $100 million investment will ensure the construction of a new bus interchange connecting Macquarie University and Macquarie Centre, improving access to transport options.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull said the joint project would streamline the commuting experience for transport customers and reduce congestion on local roads. </p>
<p>“This interchange is a game-changer for peak-hour commuters who travel to and from Macquarie Park every day. It will provide faster, safer and easier transitions between various transport options,” he said.</p>
<p>“John Alexander has campaigned tirelessly for better transport services for his community. We are delivering the transport infrastructure to ensure Sydney residents spend more time at home with their family and less time commuting.’’</p>
<p>NSW Premier Gladys Berejiklian said the interchange would make a massive difference to the 20,000 public transport customers who travel to and from the precinct each day.</p>
<p>“Macquarie Park is a critical driver of economic growth in NSW, and it is important we deliver the best public transport possible to the tens of thousands of people who live, work and study in the area,” Ms Berejiklian said.</p>
<p>“This funding will allow us to not only fast track the project, but also choose a design with the best outcomes for urban amenity.”</p>
<p>NSW Minister for Transport and Infrastructure Andrew Constance said the funding towards a new interchange would support the NSW Government’s work in improving local transport and the construction of the Sydney Metro mega-project, which opens in 2019.</p>
<p>“We have been doing our homework in preparing a strategic business case for the transport priorities of Macquarie Park, this important injection of funding from the federal government will allow us to fast track a better interchange for our customers,” Mr Constance said.</p>
<p>Liberal candidate for Bennelong John Alexander said the interchange would improve traffic flow around Macquarie Centre and Macquarie University, and reduce congestion for local motorists.</p>
<p>“This interchange is a huge win for people of Bennelong. It will reduce congestion on our local roads and make it easier for commuters to travel from A to B,’’ he said.</p>
<p>Work will begin immediately on a business case that will determine the final design and whether parts of the interchange should be built underground.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
