<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11010</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP AND                   GENERAL BARRY MCCAFFREY                   (DIRECTOR, OFFICE OF NATIONAL DRUG POLICY)                   JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE                 WILLARD INTER-CONTINENTAL HOTEL, WASHINGTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.........</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, the General and I have just had a very valuable meeting. I've</p>
<p> extended an invitation to him to visit Australia. Nobody has a greater</p>
<p> overall focus on the drug issue in the United States than does he.</p>
<p> I therefore think his views on the issue would be very interesting</p>
<p> in Australia. We've talked about the various policy approaches in</p>
<p> our two countries and there's a great similarity of approach. He has</p>
<p> a particular but it's not obviously the limit of his interest, particular</p>
<p> interest in effective campaigns against drugs in sport. The discussion</p>
<p> I've had with him has reinforced in my own mind that we have the right</p>
<p> balance in Australia in seeing the drug problem is not being in any</p>
<p> way sold or mitigated by throwing up one's hands and giving up the</p>
<p> fight.</p>
<p>Legalisation is not the path to dealing with the problem that the</p>
<p> balance between education, effective interception and enforcement</p>
<p> and adequate investment in treatment. I was interested in what he</p>
<p> told me about Drug Courts in the United States, which is very similar</p>
<p> to the diversion policy that's being adopted in Australia and now</p>
<p> being implemented in cooperation with the State Governments. So I've</p>
<p> particularly welcomed the discussion that we've had General and I</p>
<p> certainly would welcome your visiting our country at some time that's</p>
<p> convenient to you because this is a world wide challenge and there's</p>
<p> a lot that we can learn from each other.</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Mr Prime Minister. I must add that I've been</p>
<p> trying to get to Australia for some 50 some odd years now.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll do something about that.</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>Who said something can't come out of these conferences? Let me first</p>
<p> of all thank you for the chance to share with the Prime Minister our</p>
<p> own thinking on our National Drug Control Strategy and you know these</p>
<p> ideas are not revolutionary, they're commonsense. We have based them</p>
<p> on some hard work by really three people in the US Government: Janet</p>
<p> Reno our Attorney General, Donna Shalala our Health and Human Services</p>
<p> Secretary and Dick Riley the Education Secretary and that's really</p>
<p> the heart and soul of what we are doing. We're trying to keep young</p>
<p> people off drugs until they're 18. We've got another 4 million Americans</p>
<p> that are chronically addicted. It's a huge problem - 5 per cent and</p>
<p> a half of the population but it's really the heart and soul of a lot</p>
<p> of the damage in America. The criminal justice system, the welfare</p>
<p> system, the health system. We're trying to effectively pull together</p>
<p> treatment and these other social systems and finally I told the Prime</p>
<p> Minister I was very impressed by his own delegation at Lausanne, Switzerland</p>
<p> during the International Olympic Committee. You know the central part</p>
<p> of what we're doing is trying to prevent chronic drug abuse but there's</p>
<p> this huge opportunity we have, the world community, to prevent what</p>
<p> is increasingly going on around the world which literally hundreds</p>
<p> of thousands of young people believe that to compete and win in national</p>
<p> or international competition you have to get involved in chemical</p>
<p> engineering of the human body. With disastrous results as we saw in</p>
<p> East Germany with steroid use, well now it's well beyond that. Artificial</p>
<p> testosterone, blood packing, just a tremendous challenge. And these</p>
<p> drugs are available over the internet whether you're in Uganda, Australia,</p>
<p> the United States so many of us went to Lausanne to the IOC to demand</p>
<p> reform, to ask for an independent testing agency for testing 365 days</p>
<p> a year to save samples so that future technology could unravel cheating.</p>
<p> And we want to do this not just to make sure that the record of the</p>
<p> top 100 swimmers on the face of the earth is ethically sound, we want</p>
<p> to do it because they're models for the human spirit and I think Australians</p>
<p> are better organised on this whole issue that almost anybody I've</p>
<p> listened to. There's a tremendous amount of interest and here in the</p>
<p> United States how can we guarantee both in Sydney and Salt Lake City</p>
<p> international competition that's based on raw human talent and spirit.</p>
<p> And so I've accepted the Prime Minister's invitation to go and learn</p>
<p> more about their own approaches to this.</p>
<p>I might add it's an approach that obviously can't be based simply</p>
<p> on interdiction, like the world is awash in heroin. I told the Prime</p>
<p> Minister we probably have 800,000 Americans using heroin out of 270</p>
<p> million of us, but they do incredible damage. We think they use 11</p>
<p> metric tonnes of heroin and we're reasonably sure the world produces</p>
<p> 360 metric tonnes. So the world communities got a problem and the</p>
<p> damage it's done and meanwhile it's worse than it is and I would argue</p>
<p> in the United States and Australia where the world owes a global effort</p>
<p> to confront this situation.</p>
<p>So again, Mr Prime Minister, thanks for your leadership and I look</p>
<p> forward to a visit in November.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>A couple of quick questions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you canvass any new issues, any new strategies that could be employed</p>
<p> in either country on heroin in particular?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think it's fair to say that we agreed that one or two strategies</p>
<p> that are in the air in Australia are not desirable such as heroin</p>
<p> shooting galleries. Neither of us thought there was any merit in going</p>
<p> down that path.</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>I might add to that if you'd permit me. One of the things we are most</p>
<p> proud of, we have finally gotten a decent level of investment in our</p>
<p> National Institute of Drug Abuse, Dr Alan Leshner, and his colleagues.</p>
<p> About 600 some odd people. They are doing some absolutely breathtaking</p>
<p> research to deal with the consequences of drug abuse and its prevention.</p>
<p> But the last thing any of us believe one should do is give one of</p>
<p> these suffering creatures a heroin addict who is somebody's baby to</p>
<p> leave them with the addiction. Now, it would be like pouring alcohol</p>
<p> into an alcoholic. Drug treatment and therapeutic intervention can</p>
<p> work. We have got good studies that show you can take a tremendous</p>
<p> number of these people and break this behaviour. And that's what would</p>
<p> seem to me we owe the chronic drug abuser.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In the same recent edition of the Washington Post that published</p>
<p> your very articulate article strongly opposing the legalising of drugs</p>
<p> like marijuana, it was reported in another story, the same edition,</p>
<p> that the US Army is now allowing the use of peyote for religious purposes</p>
<p> provided that none of the native American church soldiers who use</p>
<p> peyote are allowed to handle nuclear weapons. Now, I have.</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>That piece is very encouraging.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you believe peyote using US soldiers should be allowed to use other</p>
<p> weapons like sting missiles or stealth bombers and should they be</p>
<p> allowed to participate in the Olympics and that's a first part?</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>Now, that's a question I rush to avoid. I don't know what to make</p>
<p> of all this. I mean, to be honest I shouldn't comment on a policy</p>
<p> I haven't studied. On the surface it looks goofy, it got wrapped up,</p>
<p> I am sure, in some very detailed legal issues that are based on Constitutional</p>
<p> principles. We absolutely do not believe that.we are so proud we are</p>
<p> having a drug-free armed forces, we don't want them using psychoactive</p>
<p> substances, we don't want them smoking cigarettes and we don't want</p>
<p> them abusing alcohol. And that's really the only useful [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sorry, I have only got a limited amount of time. I apologise but I</p>
<p> have got to go and make a phone call in a minute.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>I am sorry, I have a question that doesn't have anything to do with</p>
<p> drugs but instead with the PNG. I have learned that you have been</p>
<p> discussing with IMF and World Bank regarding PNG and I am just wondering</p>
<p> that the, you know, that a country that was the first..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Where are you from, what's your..</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Oh, I am sorry. My name is Mark [Inaudible], I am with the Economic</p>
<p> Daily News Taiwan. Australia was the first country in Pacific Asia</p>
<p> to warn the, you know, Chinese missile exercise in '96 and now it</p>
<p> is the country that first.the country to warn that the PNG's decision</p>
<p> to establish diplomatic relations with Taiwan will bring insecurity</p>
<p> to that area. That [inaudible] a strong protest from Taiwan. I am</p>
<p> just wondering that, can you share some of the discussions with IMF</p>
<p> and the World Bank on PNG's economic situation? And also your relationship</p>
<p> to Taiwan?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Most of our discussion was about the internal situation in Papua New</p>
<p> Guinea. I don't know that I want to get in, at this gathering, into</p>
<p> a detailed discussion of that issue. I made some comments reaffirming</p>
<p> what is a longstanding Australian Government policy in relation to</p>
<p> recognition and the maintenance of a one China policy and also the</p>
<p> reaffirmed, the value we place on our longstanding and very good commercial</p>
<p> relationship with Taiwan.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you satisfied, Mr Howard, that President Clinton and his advisers</p>
<p> are sufficiently alert to the dangers of the situation unfolding in</p>
<p> East Timor and what would you like to see them do?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think it's fair to say that our discussion today we spent</p>
<p> more time, apart probably from the issue of lamb, we spent more time</p>
<p> talking about Indonesia and East Timor than any other issue. And I</p>
<p> know that they are very engaged in what is happening in East Timor.</p>
<p> I offered some views about what I believed was happening in Indonesia</p>
<p> proper. I have expressed my views on that before and the views I have</p>
<p> expressed publicly on that are consistent with the views that I expressed</p>
<p> privately to the President. And I thought as a result of our discussion</p>
<p> today he and the other senior members of the administration who were</p>
<p> present had a very detailed idea of what I and the Australian Government</p>
<p> thought about what was happening in Indonesia, what needed to be the</p>
<p> response of other countries and what was happening in East Timor.</p>
<p> Both of us were very seized of the need to remind the Indonesian Government</p>
<p> constantly of international attitudes towards their handling of the</p>
<p> situation in East Timor. One more question and then I really do have</p>
<p> to go and take a phone call.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Could I ask General McCaffrey. In Australia quite a lot of money and</p>
<p> effort is already going into drug education and research and other</p>
<p> aspects of trying to counter the drug problem. Do you have any ideas</p>
<p> about what further can be done that might cause some sort of breakthrough</p>
<p> on this front?</p>
<p>McCAFFREY:</p>
<p>Well, of course in November I'd be very keen on learning more about</p>
<p> what the Australians are doing in their existing programmes and their</p>
<p> own thinking. We have an array of approaches we are taking. That is</p>
<p> the heart and soul. The central component of the National Drugs Strategy</p>
<p> is a reduction of drug abuse to include alcohol and nicotine by American</p>
<p> adolescents. So that's a central piece of what we are doing and there</p>
<p> is a series of programmes and education, health and human services</p>
<p> designed to minimise that. And they all begin with parents, homeroom</p>
<p> teachers, coaches, pediatricians. It's community level action. And</p>
<p> we are starting to see a pay-off. We are finally seeing the beginning</p>
<p> of the turning of the curve we believe. We have got to stay at it</p>
<p> for 10 years.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look, I really must go, I have got to make a phone call.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Just on the lamb.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am lambed out. We have dealt with lamb at some length. I mean, my</p>
<p> view is well known, it has not changed, it's adamant but I don't know</p>
<p> that I can add anything.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you preparing a retaliation against the United States?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what form do you think that should take?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] focussed here on alcohol and tobacco with children. Should</p>
<p> that be something that Australia can..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we do it now. In fact Australia has probably been more successful</p>
<p> than any country in the world in reducing tobacco use. We still have</p>
<p> a long way to go. And it is part of it. I mean, one of the things</p>
<p> I have always found perplexing is that some of the people who are</p>
<p> the staunchest supporters of discouraging people from using tobacco</p>
<p> are amongst those who believe that you go in the other direction in</p>
<p> relation to marijuana and other drugs and I find that puzzling. Anyway,</p>
<p> I really, I must go.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
