<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6768</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENT OF MALCOLM FRASER TO COMMONWEALTH GROUP ON SOUTH AFRICA</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/10/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006768.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 28 OCTOBER 1985<br />
The Commonwealth Accord on Southern Africa, concluded at<br />
Nassau last week, included as one of its important elements<br />
a decision to establish a small group of eminent<br />
Commonwealth persons to encourage a process of dialogue and<br />
reform.-in South Africa.<br />
Mr Malcolm Fraser has accepted the Government's request to<br />
serve as a member of the group.<br />
The central objective to which I and other Commonwealth<br />
leaders addressed ourselves at Nassau was to see an<br />
effective process of change and reform begun in South<br />
Africa. The core elements of Australia's approach to the Meeting<br />
were a two-pronged strategy of a package of measures of<br />
pressure, for implementation against a timetable of action,<br />
and mechanisms for dialogue. Those elements were accepted<br />
by other leaders and are embodied in the Accord.<br />
The measures agreed on by the Commonwealth against South<br />
Africa build effectively on the steps that have been taken<br />
in recent weeks by the international community notably the<br />
United States, the European Community, and other countries<br />
including Australia.<br />
It was not our purpose at Nassau to impose sanctions<br />
measures for their own sake. we all recognised the<br />
desirability of the Commonwealth playing its own<br />
constructive role to develop proposals to assist the<br />
peaceful transition of South Africa to a non-racial society<br />
based on universal adult suffrage.<br />
Commonwealth leaders acknowledged that it was for the people<br />
of South Africa themselves to work out the details of their<br />
own political and constitutional future. We realised that<br />
it would not be appropriate for the Commonwealth to be<br />
intrusive or prescriptive. </p>
<p>Nevertheless, at a time when some of the major elements of<br />
South Africa society have begun to talk to each other across<br />
the apartheid barrier in the face of hostility from the<br />
South African Government, I and other leaders felt that the<br />
Commonwealth could facilitate the process of dialogue.<br />
This was the basis of Australia's initiative to form the<br />
group of eminent persons, independent individuals not<br />
currently active in politics, which was endorsed by the Meeting.<br />
I am very pleased that Mr Fraser will be a member of the<br />
group. He is an Australian whose credentials on South<br />
Africa are highly regarded by African leaders and I am<br />
confident that he will make a valuable contribution.<br />
His nomination will be communicated to the Governments of<br />
Zambia, the Bahamas, India, the United Kingdom and Zimbabwe,<br />
as well as to the Commonwealth Secretary General, who along<br />
with Australia, are responsible for determining the group's<br />
composition and mandate. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
