<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7687</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF STATEMENT OF THE ENVIRONMENT WENTWORTH, NSW 20 JULY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007687.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF STATEMENT ON THE ENVIRONMENT<br />
WENTWORTH, NSW<br />
JULY 1989<br />
This morning's journey through three States, culminating in<br />
this launch at Wentworth, symbolises two realities about our<br />
environment. It shows in a graphic way that the degradation<br />
of our environment is not simply a local problem, nor a<br />
problem for one State or another, nor for the Commonwealth<br />
alone. Rather, the damage being done to our environment is<br />
a problem for all of us and not just governments but all<br />
of us individually and together.<br />
The second reality is that the solutions just as we have<br />
witnessed with the land rehabilitation programs in this<br />
region are to be found through co-operation at all levels<br />
of government and by community groups who care for the land,<br />
who want to repair our damaged environment.<br />
That is why I am delighted with the broad cross-section of<br />
institutions and groups represented here today Federal<br />
Ministers, State Premiers and Ministers, local Members of<br />
Parliament, local government representatives, the remarkable<br />
alliance between the National Farmers' Federation and the<br />
Australian Conservation Foundation, the Murray-Darling Basin<br />
Commission, the churches, community groups but most<br />
importantly in a sense, the schoolchildren, our future.<br />
It is to the future, to our children, that the. statement I<br />
am launching today is dedicated. Through the measures<br />
announced in the statement and through the co-operation of<br />
all Australians, we seek an ecologically sustainable future.<br />
That simply means we have borrowed from our children part of<br />
their natural heritage and the time has come to repay the<br />
debt. Environmental problems today, more than ever, are global.<br />
In just over 200 years since the Industrial Revolution,<br />
human activity has significantly increased the earth's<br />
temperature, threatening the onset of the greenhouse effect.<br />
Huge areas of the world's tree cover have been destroyed and<br />
we are obliterating thousands of living species. we have<br />
polluted the world's oceans, seas and rivers, degraded the<br />
earth's soils, damaged the fragile Arctic and Antarctic<br />
environments. </p>
<p>We have even managed to punch a hole through the ozone<br />
layer. It would have taken all our scientific ingenuity to<br />
do that deliberately, but it has taken no effort at all to<br />
pull off that spectacular accident.<br />
Australia is one of the most fortunate countries, escaping<br />
some of the world's greatest environmental traumas acid<br />
rain, persistent eye-watering smog, the disasters at<br />
Chernobyl and Bhopal, the blight caused by population<br />
pressures.<br />
We have many magnificent environmental treasures the Great<br />
Barrier Reef, the Queensland rainforests, the Tasmanian<br />
forests, Kakadu National Park.<br />
And we have many proven successes in protecting the<br />
environment. The Franklin runs free. Our World Heritage sites are a<br />
source of national pride. Greenhouse research is being<br />
funded. We are, with industry, phasing out ozone-depleting<br />
chlorofluorocarbons.<br />
But we have our environmental problems, and many of them are<br />
serious. With today's statement the Federal Government is<br />
providing new impetus and new directions in tackling those<br />
problems. And we're asking the community to join us in these efforts,<br />
for it is only by working together that we will restore and<br />
improve our environment.<br />
I'm not going to outline all the initiatives we're launching<br />
today. They are explained in detail in the statement. But<br />
I will concentrate briefly on some of the key ones.<br />
None of Australia's environmental problems is more serious<br />
than the soil degradation in this region and over nearly<br />
two-thirds of our continent's arable land.<br />
Accordingly, we are declaring next year the Year of Landcare<br />
it will be the first year in a Decade of Landcare that<br />
will provide as never before a focus for protecting the most<br />
fundamental ingredient both of our natural environment and<br />
of our agricultural prosperity our soil.<br />
Today I am committing $ 320 million to a package of measures<br />
to apply over the Year and the Decade of Landcare.<br />
And I express here my gratitude to Rick Farley of the NFF<br />
and Phillip Toyne of the ACF. They're two organisations one<br />
would probably not immediately imagine forming an alliance<br />
but it is an indication of the importance of this issue, and<br />
an inspiring demonstration of the way forward that they used<br />
their imagination and commitment to develop proposals and<br />
put them constructively to Government. Their work has been<br />
an invaluable contribution to the creation of this new<br />
program. </p>
<p>3.<br />
To address the special problems in this region, the<br />
Commonwealth will provide up to $ 18 million over the next<br />
two years to the Murray-Darling Basin Commission so that it<br />
can begin to implement the Natural Resources management<br />
Strategy for the Basin. my colleague, Senator Cook, will<br />
have more to say about this in a moment.<br />
A key ingredient in the treatment of many soil degradation<br />
problems is the growing of trees.<br />
Trees will help slow the greenhouse effect; they provide<br />
habitat for endangered species; they form magnificent<br />
wilderness areas and complete forest ecosystems; they ease<br />
the burden on our virgin native forests as a source of<br />
commercial timber.<br />
We need more trees.<br />
I am pleased to say, therefore, that after this launch Hazel<br />
who is patron of Greenin-g Australia will plant the first<br />
of One Billion Trees to be planted over the coming decade.<br />
This is an ambitious program aimed at re-greening at least<br />
parts of Australia, at restoring some of the 50 per cent of<br />
tree cover removed in 200 years of European settlement in<br />
this ancient continent.<br />
One Billion Trees is very much a community program and I'd<br />
like you and schoolchildren throughout Australia, through<br />
your teachers, to plant trees and most importantly, to look<br />
after them to make sure they grow.<br />
We must, too, save those important remnants of native<br />
vegetation on our farming lands. To this end I am<br />
announcing a Save the Bush remnant vegetation program. This<br />
has been inspired by the pioneering work of South Australia<br />
and I pay tribute to John Bannon for showing a lead which my<br />
Government, and I hope, the other State Governments, will<br />
pick up.<br />
of course, Australia needs a healthy, viable forest<br />
industry. That viability must increasingly be based on<br />
plantation development, to ease the burden on our virgin<br />
native forests. The Government's National Afforestation<br />
Program will be applied to this task and our forest<br />
strategy will be informed by the work of the newly<br />
established Resource Assessment Commission.<br />
Meanwhile, Commonwealth Ministers will be arranging trials<br />
on the use of recycled and unbleached paper in their<br />
Departments. The Government is removing the 20 per cent<br />
sales tax on a range of recycled paper products.<br />
The roll call of Australian animals and plants that have<br />
been wiped out in the last two hundred years is long at<br />
least 18 species of mammals and 100 species of flowering<br />
plants. Another 40 species of mammals are in danger of </p>
<p>extinction and 3,300 plants species are rare or endangered.<br />
We must strive to save them and so the Government has<br />
decided to allocate $ 2m for each of the first two years of a<br />
year Endangered Species Program.<br />
Although we're out in the bush today, the nation's<br />
environmental concerns do not end at the urban fringe.<br />
Pollution in our cities, preservation of our urban cultural<br />
heritage, the environmental strains caused by often<br />
haphazard coastal development all of these are the subject<br />
of new Federal Government measures detailed in the<br />
Statement.<br />
The Commonwealth also wants to advance with the States the<br />
development of agreed national minimum environmental<br />
standards, addressing matters affecting air, water and noise<br />
quality. I've said the environment is a global problem, and I can<br />
assure you Australia's concern for the environment doesn't<br />
end at our shores.<br />
We will be taking the lead in developing international<br />
conventions on greenhouse gas emissions and on biological<br />
diversity.<br />
Australia will do everything in its power to ensure<br />
Antarctica remains free from mining.<br />
We will be seeking a global ban on the barbarous practice of<br />
driftnet fishing which indiscriminately kills dolphins,<br />
seals and small whales.<br />
And we will be urging faster international action on the<br />
phasing out of CFCs.<br />
Consistent with these international efforts, Australia will<br />
be developing a national strategy on greenhouse emissions<br />
and we are accelerating the phase-out of CFCs nearly all<br />
CFC use will be phased out within five years. I have put<br />
greenhouse issues on the agenda for the first meeting of my<br />
Science Council.<br />
To give Australia a stronger and a clearer voice on global<br />
environmental issues such as Antarctica, and the greenhouse<br />
and ozone problems and to have a strong, consistent<br />
capacity to be represented in the increasing rounds of<br />
international negotiations and range of forums that will<br />
characterise our involvement in these issues the<br />
Government has decided to appoint a special Ambassador for<br />
the Environment. I am delighted to tell you that Sir Ninian<br />
Stephen has agreed to be Australia's first Ambassador for<br />
the Environment. I am sure everyone will agree that no-one<br />
could better discharge this important role for Australia. </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
When the earth is spoiled, humanity and all living things<br />
are diminished. We have taken too much from the earth and<br />
given back too little. It's time to say enough is enough.<br />
Today's announcements won't solve everything. But with the<br />
right mix of political commitment and community support we<br />
can ensure that our country is simply the best in the world.<br />
This is our country, our future. I give my commitment to<br />
you, kids, that my generation will hand on to you a better<br />
country, a brighter future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
