<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3268</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER - BANKSTOWN MEETING, 15 MAY 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003268.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEiENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
BAliKSTOWN MEETING. 15 , AY,-1974<br />
Su_ PnBPFR ASKIN HAS SHOWN A RECKLESS AND<br />
IRRESPONSIBLE INDIFFERENCE TO THE NEEDS OF NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
AND THE OPPORTUNITIES HELD OUT TO HIM BY THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT FOR FRUITFUL CO-OPERATION,<br />
0 THIS GREAT DEFENDER OF fDERALISM, THIS SELF-STYLED<br />
APOSTLE OF COMMONWEALTH-STATE CO-OPERATION, HAS REJECTED<br />
0@ NEARLY EVERY. INITIATIVE FOR CO-OPERATION PUT FORWARD BY THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DURING THE PAST 17 MONTHS.<br />
HIS DOCTRINAIRE OBSESSION WITH STATE RIGHTS HAS COST<br />
THE PEOPLE OF NEW SOUTH WALES DEARLY.<br />
IT HAS SET BACK BY MONTHS PERHAPS YEARS THEIR<br />
PROSPECTS FOR BETTER URBAN TRANSPORT; FOR YOUTH CENTRES, FOR<br />
HEALTH SERVICES, FOR REASONABLE LAND PRICES,<br />
TIME AND AGAIN ~ ROBERT ASKIN HAS REFUSED EVEN<br />
TO ACKNOWLEDGE OFFERS FROM THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT OF<br />
HELP AND CO-OPERATION, MONTHS HAVE PASSED WITHOUT A REPLY<br />
TO OUR LETTERS. c N* </p>
<p>-2-<br />
YET THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS TREATED SIR ROBERT<br />
ASKIN AND THE NEW SOUTH !' ALES GOVERNMENT WITH UNPARALLELED<br />
GENEROSITY, OUR PAYMENTS TO NEW SOUTH WALES HAVE INCREASED<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY IN EVERY AREA.<br />
OUR TOTAL SPECIFIC PURPOSE PAYMENTS TO NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES ARE ESTIMATED AT $ 540,265,000 THIS FINANCIAL YEAR.<br />
INDER MR. SNEDDEN'S. LAST BUDGET THESE PAYMENTS TOTALLED<br />
$ 294,562,000 FOR 1972/ 73.<br />
OUR TOTAL SPECIFIC CAPITAL GRANTS WILL GO UP FROM<br />
$ 160,793,000 TO AN ESTIMATED $ 332.. 062,000.,<br />
OUR GENERAL REVENUE GRANTS WILL GO UP FROM $ 537,000,000<br />
TO AN ESTIMATED $ 581,000,. 000.<br />
OUR TOTAL PAYMENTS OF ALL KINDS WILL'GO UP'FROM<br />
$ 831,000,000 TOAN E TIMATED $ 1 121,00,000,<br />
LET ME GIVE SOME SPECIFIC EXAMPLES, CAva </p>
<p>IN SPECIFIC PURPOSE CAPITAL PAY'MWEINLTS, THE LAST<br />
SNEDDEN BUDGET GAVE $ 10,522,000 FOR UNIVERSITIES; WE WILL t<br />
GIVE $ 17,676,000. THE LIBERALS GAVE $ 10,637,000 FOR SCHOOLS,<br />
WE WILL GIVE $ 32,029,009, THE LIBERALS GAVE $ 107,000 FOR<br />
SENIOR CITIZEN CENTRES; WE WILL GIVE $ 310, n009, THE LIBERALS<br />
GAVE $ 3,500,000 FOR HOUSING; WE WILL GIVE $ 86,000,00, THE<br />
LIBERALS GAVE $ 2,821,000 FOR ABORIGINAL ADVANCEMENT' WE<br />
WILL GIVE $ 3,715,000, THE LIBERALS GAVE $ 8,590,000 FOR THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH AID ROADS PROGRAM; WE WILL GIVE $ 98,270 00,<br />
IN SPECIFIC PURPOSE REVENUE PAYMENTS, THE LIBERALS<br />
GAVE $ 32,155,000 FOR UNIVERSITIES: WE WILL GIVE $ 79,437,000,<br />
THE LIBERALS GAVE NOTHING FOR TECHNICAL TRAINING: WE WILL<br />
SGIVE $ 5,801,000, THE LIBERALS GAVE $ 15,046,000 FOR SCHOOLS;<br />
WE WILL GIVE $ 34,053,000. THE LIBERALS GAVE NOTHING FOR<br />
PRE-SCHOOLS. WE WILL GIVE $ 1,390,090. THE LIBERALS GAVE<br />
NOTHING FOR URBAN IMPROVEMENT; WE HAVE GIVEN $ 5,066 099 FOR THE<br />
WESTERN SECTOR OF SYDNEY ALONE, </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I HAVE TO ADMIT THERE IS ONE AREA WHERE OUR PAYMENTS<br />
HAVE FALLEN DRASTICALLY. THAT IS IN UNEMPLOYMENT RELIEF.<br />
THE LAST LIBERAL GOVERNAENT GAVE NEW SOUTH WALES<br />
$ 37,220,000 FOR UNEMPLOYMENT RELIEF. OUR ESTIMATED TOTAL'FOR<br />
THIS FINANCIAL YEAR IS $ 4,530,000, I ' U<br />
' 4_ 6 LAND COMMISSION SIR ROBERT ASKIN HAS SHOWN UTTER CONTEMPT-FOR THE<br />
HARDSHIPS SUFFERED BY YOUNG HOMESEEKERS IN HIS STATE, .1E HAS<br />
DONE. NOTHING TO CHECK THE SOARING COST OF LAND IN NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES. LAND COSTS IN SYDNEY ARE THE HIGHEST IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE AVERAGE PRICE OF A BLOCK OF LAND IS $ 18,500. THE NEW<br />
SOUTH WALES GOVERNMENT HAS REFUSED TO USE ITS POWERS TO CHECK<br />
THE LAND SPIRAL, DESPITE THE FACT THAT IN HIS 1970 ELECTION<br />
CAMPAIGN SIR ROBERT PROMISED ACTION ON PRICES, INCLUDING A<br />
ROYAL COMMISSION. HE HAS DONE NOTHING TO HONOUR THAT PROMISE,<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S POLICY IS TO ESTABLISH<br />
LAND COMMISSIONS IN EACH STATE TO BUY UP TRACTS OF RESIDENTIAL<br />
LAND AND SELL THEM AT FAIR'PRICES TO HOMESEEKERS.<br />
LOOK AT THE SORRY RECORD OF DELAY AND OBSTRUCTION<br />
BY THE ASKIN GOVERNMENT, </p>
<p>I WROTE TO THE PREMIER ON 27 DECEMBER 1972 OUTLINING<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S LAND PROPOSALS AND ASKING FOR<br />
EARLY MEETINGS. THE PREMIER WROTE ON 15 FEBRUARY NOMINATING<br />
OFFICIALS FOR DISCUSSIONS.<br />
I WE INFORMED SIR ROBERT ON 21 AUGUST 1973 OF THE<br />
S AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S INITIAL OFFER OF $ 30 MILLION TO THE<br />
STATES FOR 1973/ 74 FOR LAND COMMISSION PURPOSES. NOTHING<br />
HAS BEEN RECEIVED FROM THE PREMIER APART FROM A FORMAL<br />
ACKNOWLEDGEMENT DATED 30 AUGUST 1973.<br />
NEW SOUTH WALES WAS TO GET $ 10.5 MILLION IN 1973/ 74<br />
O WITH A SIMILAR AMOUNT IN 1974/ 75 FOR COMMITMENTS ENTERED INTO<br />
IN 1973/ 74.<br />
URBAN PUBLIC TRANSPORT<br />
WE HAVE OFFERED NEW SOUTH WALES GRANTS TOTALLING<br />
$ 28.6 MILLION FOR URBAN PUBLIC TRANSPORT PROJECTS COMMENCED<br />
IN 1973/ 74. OF THIS TOTAL, $ 12.6 MILLION WAS TO BE PROVIDED<br />
IN 1973/ 74 AND THE REMAINDER OVER THE NEXT FOUR FINANCIAL<br />
YEARS, THE DRAFT. AGREEMENT WAS SENT TO THE PREMIER ON<br />
MARCH 1974 E IS STILL ARGUING<br />
ABOUT MODIFICATIONS TO THE AGREEMENT. -y I </p>
<p>-6-<br />
YET THE PREMIERS OF WESTERN AUSTRALIA AND SOUTH<br />
AUSTRALIA HAVE ALREADY SIGNED THE AGREEMENT. THEY SIGNED<br />
IT ON 28 MARCH 1974. I SIGNED THE AGREEMENT ON 29 MARCH,<br />
GROWTH CENTRES I WROTE TO THE PREMIER ON 21 AUGUST 1973 OFFERING C<br />
MILLION IN 1973/ 74 FOR HOLSWORTHY/ CAMPBELLTOWN, BATHURST/<br />
ORANGE AND GOSFORD/ WYONG, I WROTE AGAIN ON 11 SEPTEMBER<br />
PROPOSING AN EARLY MEETING OF MINISTERS,<br />
THE PREMIER REPLIED ON 19 NOVEMBER ASKING FOR AN<br />
INDICATION, IN ADVANCE OF ANY SUCH MEETINGS, OF THE LIKELY<br />
TERMS OF AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT ASSISTANCE.<br />
DETAILED PROPOSALS WERE SUBMITTED TO THE PREMIER<br />
ON 12 FEBRUARY 1974. THIS WAS ACKNOWLEDGED BY THE PREMIER<br />
ON 22 FEBRUARY BUT THERE HAS BEEN NO FURTHER CORRESPONDENCE,<br />
QUEANBEYAN BRIDGE.<br />
ON 25 FEBRUARY I WROTE TO SIR ROBERT OFFERING THAT<br />
THE NATIONAL CAPITAL DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION SHARE THE COSTS<br />
OF CONSTRUCTING A NEW BRIDGE OVER THE RAILWAY LINE AT<br />
QUEANBEYAN AS PART OF A FOUR LANE DIVIDED ROAD LINK BETWEEN<br />
CANBERRA AND QUEANBEYAN, WITH THE NEW SOUTH WALES DEPARTMENT<br />
OF MAIN ROADS AND THE STATE RAILWAYS, THIS LETTER, AND A<br />
-rrr nATIl 10n APRIL, HAVE RECEIVED FORMAL<br />
I </p>
<p>-7-<br />
HOSPITALS WE ALLOCATED MILLION TO NEW SOUTH WALES FOR<br />
CONSTRUCTION OF A NEW TEACHING HOSPITAL AT WESTMEAD,<br />
THIS MONEY HAS NEVER BEEN USED.<br />
ON 7 DECEMBER LAST SIR ROBERT ASKIN WROTE TO ME<br />
REQUESTING THAT $ 500,000 OF THE ALLOCATION OF $ 4 MILLION<br />
TO THE WESTMEAD PROJECT BE DIRECTED TOWARDS THE CONSTRUCTION<br />
OF A 104-BED WARD AT THE LIVERPOOL DISTRICTHoSPITAL IN 1973/ 74<br />
AND THAT A FURTHER CONTRIBUTIO N BE MADE TOWARDS THE EXPENDITURE<br />
OF $ 1.5 MILLION IN 1974/ 75 WHICH WILL BE REQUIRED TO COMPLETE<br />
THE WARD BLOCK. ON 28 FEBRUARY I REPLIED TO THE PREMIER AGREEING<br />
TO THE ALLOCATION OF THE $ 500,000 BUT STATING THAT THE QUESTION<br />
OF FURTHER SUPPORT FOR USE IN 1974/ 75 WOULD BE EXAMINED AGAIN<br />
AFTER CONSIDERATION OF THE REPORT BY THE HOSPITALS AND HEALTH<br />
SERVICES COMMISSION. THE LETTER SOUGHT THAT THE WARD BLOCK<br />
DISPLAY SOME ACKNOWLEDGEMENT OF THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT'S<br />
CONTRIBUTION AND THAT IT BE REPRESENTED ON THE BOARD OF<br />
LIVERPOOL DISTRICT HOSPITAL. IT WAS LEFT TO THE MINISTER FOR<br />
HEALTH, DR. EVERINGHAM, TO TAKE THESE MATTERS UP WITH THE<br />
MINI TER FOR HEALTH, N NEW SOUTH WALES. DR. EVERINGHAM WROTE TO<br />
THE NEW SOUTH WALES mINISTER FOR EALTH IN MARCH REPEATING<br />
THE CONDITIONS OF THE OFFER OF $ 500,000 FOR LIVERPOOL. No FORMAL<br />
REPLY HAS BEEN RECEIVED FROM THE NEW SOUTH WALES GOVERNMENT TO<br />
DATE. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
