<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10824</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER             THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP             AND THE QUEENSLAND PREMIER             THE HON ROB BORBIDGE MLA           BRISBANE LIGHT RAIL - FEDERATION FUND PROJECT</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/03/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister John Howard today announced that the Commonwealth Government</p>
<p> would commit $65 million from its Federation Fund to the construction</p>
<p> of a light rail network in Brisbane.</p>
<p>Mr Howard's pledge came during the official opening of the Briztram</p>
<p> Project Office at South Brisbane, where Premier Rob Borbidge and Deputy</p>
<p> Premier and Treasurer Joan Sheldon were on hand to welcome the news.</p>
<p>The Brisbane Light Rail Project was nominated as the Queensland Government's</p>
<p> first priority for assistance from the Federation Fund.</p>
<p>This project is expected to cost around $210 million in total and</p>
<p> will create an estimated 3,000 jobs in its construction phase, with</p>
<p> a further 150 jobs created from the ongoing operation of the system.</p>
<p>This $65 million support is subject to acceptance by the Queensland</p>
<p> government of a private sector tender to build and operate the network.</p>
<p>The Queensland government has an ambitious plan - that by the Centenary</p>
<p> of Federation in 2001 Brisbane will have a modern, advanced technology</p>
<p> light rail network that will be able to carry more than 40,000 passengers</p>
<p> each day.</p>
<p>This plan was developed by the State Government in conjunction with</p>
<p> the 18 local governments in the region and the community mindful of</p>
<p> the need to meet the high population growth in South East Queensland,</p>
<p> and the associated growth in travel demand.</p>
<p>"The Brisbane Light Rail Project to provide Brisbane with a world-class</p>
<p> integrated transport system is a visionary project for the new millennium",</p>
<p> Mr Howard said.</p>
<p>"Not only will it provide a more convenient system for distributing</p>
<p> people around the inner city Brisbane area, but, the system also has</p>
<p> the potential to benefit tourism, urban renewal and the environment."</p>
<p>Premier Borbidge said the state-of-the-art, light-rail system would</p>
<p> pump new life into Brisbane's inner-city suburbs and would be</p>
<p> a tangible sign of the city's progress into the new millennium.</p>
<p>"The State Government's dream has been for a world-class</p>
<p> transport system for a world-class city."</p>
<p>"I sincerely thank the Prime Minister and look forward to inviting</p>
<p> him back to officially launch the very first Briztram in 2001,"</p>
<p> Mr Borbidge said.</p>
<p>Deputy Premier and Treasurer Joan Sheldon said this exciting new Coalition</p>
<p> project signalled a tram-driven renaissance for the city of Brisbane.</p>
<p>"I predict this tram system will become as much a symbol of Brisbane</p>
<p> as the famous cable cars of San Francisco."</p>
<p>Mr Borbidge said a light rail option was clearly set out in the Integrated</p>
<p> Regional Transport Plan for South East Queensland and would be consistent</p>
<p> with overall transport planning.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
