<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23691</transcript-id>
    <title>Forrest Review of Indigenous Training and Employment</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/08/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Government welcomes Mr Andrew Forrest’s Review of Indigenous Training and Employment Programmes.</p>
<p>Mr Forrest is a remarkable Australian with a unique vision and an impressive track record in supporting indigenous businesses and creating jobs for indigenous Australians.</p>
<p>We thank him for investing so much of his own time and energy in the preparation of this comprehensive report. The report sets ambitious objectives to improve indigenous employment outcomes and ensure that we tackle disadvantage, wherever it occurs in Australia.</p>
<p>A six week consultation period will allow the community and interested stakeholders to provide feedback on the broad direction of the report.</p>
<p>Getting more people into work is one of the Government’s highest priorities in Indigenous Affairs, along with ensuring children attend school every day and that communities are safe.</p>
<p>Employment gives people the ability to control their own futures, independent of government, and is critical to closing the gap in life outcomes for indigenous people.</p>
<p>The gap between employment outcomes for indigenous and non-indigenous Australians is alarming and it continues to grow despite the best efforts of Government, communities and businesses.</p>
<p>To close the gap by 2018, we need another 188,000 indigenous people in jobs – more than double the current 178,000 indigenous people already employed.  The Government will carefully consider the report’s recommendations and feedback during the consultation period.</p>
<p>We thank Mr Forrest and his team for their hard work in supporting the preparation of this report to Government.</p>
<p>The report is available on <a href="http://indigenousjobsandtrainingreview.dpmc.gov.au/">http://indigenousjobsandtrainingreview.dpmc.gov.au/</a>.</p>
<p>1 August 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
