<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11197</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview, Melbourne </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>violence in East Timor</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>6 September 1999</p>
<p><i>Subject: violence in East Timor</i></p>
<p>E&amp;OE……………………………………………………………………………………….</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>How concerned are you about what’s happening in East Timor?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well I’m very concerned. I made some views of my….my views and that of the Government made known this morning, and the situation has really got much worse in the last 48 hours. It remains overwhelmingly the responsibility of the Indonesian Government and the Indonesian security forces to restore order. That plainly hasn’t happened. The people of East Timor have voted in favour of independence and they are entitled to have their wishes respected. But it’s quite desperately urgent that the army and the police do their job and stop the violence that is occurring.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>How urgent is the need for an international peacekeeping force in there Mr Howard?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Well the urgent need Louise is for the violence to stop and the quickest way the violence can stop is for the Indonesian police and the Indonesian army to do their job now.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>If they haven’t done their job up till now, why do you think they will now?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>I’m not suggesting that I’m the least bit happy with the present situation. I’m making the obvious point that until the Indonesian Government agrees to foreign forces going into East Timor, that can’t occur except in circumstances of an invasion. And I just think people should understand that and not make simplistic calls.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>You suggested withdrawing IMF funding possibly…..</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>No I didn’t. What I said was that everything is on the table.</p>
<p><b>JOURNALIST:</b></p>
<p>And that’s on the table?</p>
<p><b>PRIME MINISTER:</b></p>
<p>Everything is on the table. Thank you.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
