<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>845</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 87/1963 - AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY COUNCIL - APPOINTMENTS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/10/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000845.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. Noo 8211963<br />
AUST11ALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY COUNCIL o<br />
Statement by the Prime-Minister, the Rt, Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister announced in Canberra today the<br />
names of members who have been appointed to serve on the<br />
Council of' the Australian National University, In accordance<br />
with the Australian National University Act appointments are<br />
for a period of three years. The Act provides that twelve<br />
members may be appointed to the Council by the Governor-General,<br />
Those appointed are<br />
Mr. Norman Cowper, CBE, Chairman, Angus and Robertson Ltd.<br />
of Sydney.<br />
Mr. John Evens, CBE, Commonwealth Parliamentary Draftsman,<br />
of Canberra.<br />
Mr, Warwick Fairfax, Chairman of John Fairfax Ltd.<br />
of Sydney.<br />
Mr. Herbert Goodes, CIE, Secretary of the Department of<br />
Social Services, of Melbourne<br />
Mr. Brian Hone, Headmaster, Church of England Grammar<br />
School, Melbourne,<br />
Mr. Peter Lawler, First Assistant Secretary, Prime<br />
Minister's Department, Canberra.<br />
Mr. Warren McDonald, CBE Chairman, Commonwealth Banking<br />
6orporation, of Canberra,<br />
Mr. Charles McGrath, Chairman and Managing Director of<br />
Aepco Ltd., of Melbourne<br />
Professor. Alexander Mitchell Deputy Vice-Chancellor of<br />
the &amp;~ iversity of Sydney,<br />
Sir Frank Richardson, Chairman and Managinf Director of<br />
Cox Bros, ( Au st.) td., Melbourne.<br />
Mr. Arthur Shakespeare, Managing Editor, " Canberra Times".<br />
Sir Frederick White, Chairman, Commonwealth Scientific<br />
and Industrial Research Organisation, of Canberra.<br />
CANBERRA, 31st October, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
