<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8598</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AND THE MINISTER FOR LAND TRANSPORT, THE HON BOB BROWN MP. TWO BILLION DOLLARS FOR AUSTRALIA&#039;S ROADS WILL EMPLOY 50 000 PEOPLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008598.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
joint statement by the Prime Minister, the<br />
Hon P J Keating MP and -the Minister for Land<br />
Transport, the Hon Bob Brown MP.<br />
TWO BILLION DOLLARS FOR AUSTRALIA'S<br />
ROADS WILL EMPLOY 50 000 PEOPLE<br />
Funding from the Federal Government's One Nation spending pa ckage for Australia's<br />
roads began to flow today. The $ 600 millon out-lay will generate 15 ooR<br />
The additional funding from One Nation will boost total Federal Government spending<br />
on land transport this financial year to $ 2 billion. The program will prrieemployment<br />
for 50 000 people.<br />
Overall, the Commonwealth will spend about $ 6 million a day on Australian roads in<br />
1992-93.<br />
To emphasise the effects of the package on regional Australia, details of the spending<br />
were unveiled in Gladstone today by the Prime Minister, Paul Keating and Federal Land<br />
Transport Minister, Bob Brown.<br />
Mr Keating and Mr Brown said the Commonwealth roads spending, including the One<br />
Nation money would be targeted at rural areas and roads carrying primary produce,<br />
minerals and components for manufacturing to ports and railheads. In the cities, priority<br />
would be given to ring roads, -routes carrying commercial traffic, access to ports and<br />
roads serving freight distribution centres.<br />
" The Commonwealth will contribute S39 million to the joint government upgrading of the<br />
Pacific Highway in New South Wales, while $ 138 million has been set aside for-works<br />
on two new National Hhwy links-from Adelaide to Sydney and from Melbourne to<br />
Brisbane. This will increase the length of the National Highway to more than<br />
18 400 km.<br />
' More than $ 370 million of the total will be spent on a maintenance program for the<br />
National Highway System linking all state capitals and major provincial centrs. 835 </p>
<p>2-<br />
This essential maintenance will provide work to road gangs in widely dispersed regions<br />
throughout the counuy. Additional employment opportunities will be created', Mr<br />
Keating and Mr Brown said.<br />
They said the land transport spending was directed at meeting the needs of the transport<br />
industry and at increasing Australia's international competivenss through improved<br />
roads and reduced travelling times.<br />
' Because transport accounts for about seven per cent of the total value of goods and<br />
services in Australia today, even small gains in road transport efficiency will be reflected<br />
directly in a more dynamic economy', they said.<br />
' The importance of achieving these savings is underscored by the fact that the Federal<br />
Government will spend more than $ 6 billion on road and rail infrastructure<br />
improvements during the next few years'.<br />
Mr Keating and Mr Brown said the $ 2 billion allocation for 1992-93 represented the<br />
largest ever annual land transport budget ever committed by a Federal Government in the<br />
post-war era.<br />
' The program was fully costed and has been taken into account when framing the Budget<br />
estimates. Normally, the Federal land transport budget is not known until the Budget is<br />
brought down.<br />
' By revealing the extent of the roads program spending now, states, territories and<br />
councils will be able to proceed confidently with large projects that would otherwise<br />
have remained on the back-burner until after the Budget in August', Mr Keating and Mr<br />
Brown said.<br />
The package approved today does not include One Nation spending on rail.<br />
Mr Keating is expected to announce details of Federal funding for a national rail network<br />
soon. Gladstone July 30, 1992<br />
FEDERAL LAND TRANSPORT PROGRAM, 1992-93: STATE ALLOCATIONS<br />
NSW VIC OLD WA SA TAS NT ACT<br />
$ 574m $ 345ri $ 374m $ 161m $ 107m $ 56.3m $ 46m $ 2.6m<br />
( Excludes $ 350 millon pai as Financk AssisanceO Grants to councis and to Soe and<br />
Ternitory Governments for spending on local roads.)<br />
836 </p>
<p>FEDERAL GOVERNMENT LAND TRANSPORT<br />
PROGRAM AND ONE NATION SPENDING<br />
1992-93<br />
S5$ 46.2m<br />
S1 $ 373.7m<br />
$ 161.2m $ 106.6m I 5737m<br />
Excludes grants to councils and States<br />
for local roads 0 s $ 345.2<br />
c s$ 56.3m </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
