<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9506</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP OPENING OF AUSTRALIAN STAND AT CEBIT&#039;95 HANOVER - 8 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009506.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 8. Mar. 95 15: 32 No. 021 P. 01/ 05<br />
"* EMBARGOED UNTIL 6.3Opm<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, TXI! WON P J KIATING, MP<br />
OPENIN43 OF AIJSTRAUAN STAND AT<br />
HANOVIR 8 MARCH 1995<br />
It Is a Pleasure to be in Hanover opening this Australian stand at CeBIT'<br />
it Is also a source of pride which I trust Is shared by all the Australian<br />
companies represnted here.<br />
We are sharing tha exhibition with sorme of th'e world's best companies, in<br />
some of % he word's most competitive Industflex.<br />
It Is a signal honour that Australls has been chosen as tis year's Partner<br />
Country for CeaIDT, and Aumtrlia's information technology and<br />
telecommunicationa companies have responded with unprecedented<br />
enthusiasm to the opportunity this fair presents to show Germany, Europe<br />
4nd the world what the Australian inidustry has achieved.<br />
One of the problems faced by Australian manufacturers and service<br />
lidustries In marketing themselves abroad Is the absence of intemationally<br />
recognised Australian brand names.<br />
Our companies are doing remarkable things in information technology and<br />
communications, but their achievemeant. often go unrmarked and<br />
anonymous. Often they are masked by fth names of the overseas<br />
companies with which they are connected.<br />
Theo fact Is Australia does not live In the internallonal mnind as a famously<br />
technological society. We do not have companieS which fly the flag In, the<br />
way that aI Siemens file&amp; It for G~ erm~ any, or Phillips for The Netherlands or<br />
Microsoft for th~ e United States,<br />
I have no doubt that Australian companies of thiS kind wvill soon emerge.<br />
Teistra, to ofler one example, Is becoming a well known Australian brand In<br />
Asia. Intellect, a CaBIT veteran which sells advanced point of s8la wW<br />
smaert card technology, Is nlow a multinational firml opststing in Scanldinavia<br />
and elsewhere in Europe. </p>
<p>TEL: 8. Mar. 95 15: 32 No. 021 P. 02/ 05<br />
2<br />
It will take time, but the l1'" Pott'rt thing is to ruC40gnis that the Process has<br />
begun. and that the emergence of Such companies will signify not only their<br />
Individtial succss but another Step in~ the transuformation of AsIjstai.<br />
The presence of 170 Australian companies at CeB3IT was unimaginable lust a<br />
few years ago. It demonstrate* how much the enivironment has changed In<br />
Australia, how much it has adapted to the changed International<br />
environment. CoSIT' 96 will change it that much more. For your companies and for<br />
Austraiae It has, I believe, an historic dimonsion.<br />
It Is not too much to say that you carry the future in your hands. Not alone,<br />
of course: those traditional sectors of the Australian economy which have<br />
served us so well down the years will continue to underpin our economic<br />
success, at least So long as they continue to moderrilsa end adapt to<br />
tachnologloui and globl change. So too will other now and sophisticated<br />
elemnents of our manufacturing Indus" r.<br />
But no other inidustry carries such reel and symbolic importance as the one<br />
In which your companies are working. And no Industry serves all other<br />
Industries, or isuso fundamntal to their fitur success, as your Industry Is.<br />
It Is * iso true to say that more trian any other sector of the economy,<br />
Information technology and communications will define the sort of society<br />
we become In the 21 at century.<br />
On your success, and on how we Austrlan governments apply the now<br />
technology, subsiantally depends th achievement of our national<br />
ambitions, Your work fits our strategy.<br />
We need an Innovative, competitive modam manufacturing Industry. You<br />
are providing us with one.<br />
We need an export-oriented economy initegrated with our region and Mhe<br />
world, You are helping us to build It.<br />
We need to re-vitalise our regions. Your industry can help us do It.<br />
We need to overcome the distances wnicm separate people and * Ommunities<br />
from each other and Australia from the world. T1hat Is what you are about<br />
TEL 8. Mar. 95 15: 39 No. 021 P. 02/ 05 </p>
<p>TEL: 8. Mar.~ 5 15: 32 No. 021 P. 03/ OS<br />
3<br />
Yo make Australia competitive and to expand the realm of opportunity for<br />
Australian$ now and In the future, we need comorehenalve and elfecove<br />
vocational education and training. Your industry will play a crucial role.<br />
Information technology arnd communicationsl isa baslc and defining element<br />
In our economic and social ambitions -a world competve economy<br />
underpinning an egalltarian. inclusive society.<br />
It 13 an Industry with vast potential for good. It can make us a more<br />
productive nation, make all sectofu of our economy mnote efficient, inettase<br />
our exports. It Can deliver better health and other social services.<br />
To quota just three examples of this potential: among the companies<br />
represented hare are some like Mincom. which has developed sophisticated<br />
systems for managing capital Intsnsive industris Including mining,<br />
mnanufactuing and defence: and Rosemt Laboratories who have developed<br />
Bralle computers, optical character reading machines that road to the blind;<br />
anid Earth Resources Mapping. whose spectacular graphics packages for<br />
visualisirig and analysin~ g Satellite piCTUres of the earth for applications like<br />
mineral exploration, mapping end city planning, have set Il world standard.<br />
Yet we shouldn't forget the moat fundamental foct about these new<br />
technologies I mean the fact that properly applied, they can make all our<br />
lives easier.<br />
They 9o directly to the most commonplace and essential of our activities.<br />
This is emiphatically not " bay* with toys" teochnalogy. it is technology to<br />
make shopping easier, banking simpler, Teaching more effective, transport<br />
" for, our public service more efficient. It can give Us better h* Spitals and<br />
health services. It can enlarge our experience of the arts, open new<br />
channels of creativity, deliver now and better realms of entertainment.<br />
It has profoundly democratic possibilities.<br />
Yet none of these benefits are inevtabtle. They will not happen by<br />
themselves. They won't happen In Australia and they won't happen In the<br />
world unless we decide ftat tey should happen and re-iolve to find the best<br />
ways to rmake them happen.<br />
Recenty I heard &amp; bow% a startling fact which I think we igowla uaefully beer<br />
In mind when we talk about communilcation's end informaTion technology: It<br />
Is that half the worlds population has never made a telephone call.<br />
We will fall ourselves and future generations If we allow the new technology<br />
to compound the difference which nlow exists between developed and<br />
developing counules if we allow Information technology and<br />
communications to be as unfairly distributed as the world's other resources.<br />
TEL 8. Mar. 95 15: 32 NO. 021 P. 03/ 05 </p>
<p>TEL: 8. Mar. 95 15: 32 No. 021 P. 04/ 05<br />
4<br />
And what is true of t-16 glaol application of th flaw tochnQlolO$ Is true In<br />
different degrees lor Australia. We need a strategy which wIIl ensure that<br />
the great potential of IT and T Is realised In the Interests of out democratic<br />
end social goals.<br />
I think I can may with some certainty that Australia has considered more fully<br />
then most countries 4ll the Implications regulatory, technical and social of<br />
the information society.<br />
Last weak I launched 8 major report Commissionled by the Goverme~ nt Into<br />
the provision of broadband services. The repo't lay* the groundwork for the<br />
Government to be a leadingeodge user of the new technology. Our objective<br />
Is not just to Improve the way we perform the existing functions of<br />
Government but, much more broadly, to re-engineer Its work to deliver in<br />
completely new and more effective ways services ranging from health inl<br />
remote areas to the kinds of entertainment we &amp; so every night In our<br />
suburban homes.<br />
Many of you will also be aware that lost year we dlivered two major<br />
statements: the first on employment, the second on AuMalln cultural<br />
development. Both expressly took account of the new technologies. Both<br />
wer* designed to stimulate and give democratic and socIall direction to the<br />
IT Indus" r.<br />
Australia may not yet be well known tar Its technological Innovation and<br />
excellence, we may not yet have that Siemens. or Sony or Microsoft, but<br />
the companies represented here at CeSIT may reasonably think of<br />
themselves as being leaders sm~ ng those who are establishing such a<br />
reputation for us.<br />
These 170 companies collectively carry one message to the 700,000 people<br />
who are expected to visit this exhibition: It is that Ausuala knows the way<br />
the world is going end will not be left behind.<br />
Let me then congratulate thorn far their enterpriso and wisti them good luck<br />
In their ventures.<br />
Lot me also congratulate all those who worked so hasrd to put this together,<br />
of AWTRADEao Dieter La Crn. e end his teem.<br />
As I hove said so many times in the 082t, Ausualla's future is very much<br />
tied to our close engagement with the economies of the Asia-Pacifc, not<br />
least with our export to themn of Information technology and<br />
tolecommuncstiofls. For that reason I want to welcome In paricular the<br />
rmembers of business delegations who have Come here from Ousngzhau and<br />
Japan especially to meet with Australian exhibitors. </p>
<p>TEL: 8. Mar. 95 15: 32 No. 021 P. 05/ 0O<br />
I also want to say how pleased I am that Australian State GOovemments re<br />
giving this exhibition their full support; and thet the Premier of Queensland.<br />
Wayne Goes, Deputy Premier Cowan from Westemrn Australla and Minister<br />
Gude from Victoria have all made the effort to be here today.<br />
And finally let me thank our German hets, whose generosity and hospitality<br />
have made this visAt so rewarding and enjoyable partcularly the people of<br />
Hanover. Since European settlement In 1788 Australiana have always known Hanover<br />
as the place from which the British and, therefore, the Australian<br />
monarchy came. When that connection passes., as I am sure It soon must,<br />
this new link may well remain the link formed between Australea and<br />
Hanover by this most 21st century event,<br />
It is now my pleasure to officially open tills Australian exhlbtt at </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
