<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3867</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, OPENING ADDRESS TO CONFERENCE OF THE CENTRE FOR RESEARCH ON FEDERAL FINANCIAL RELATIONS, AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY, 27 AUGUST 1975 - THE NEW FEDERALISM: A REVIEW OF LABOR&#039;S PROGRAMS AND POLICIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003867.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
OPENING ADDRESS TO CONFERENCE OF THE CENTRE FOR RESEARCH ON<br />
FEDERAL FINANCIAL RELATIONS, AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY<br />
27 August 1975<br />
THE NEW FEDERALISM:<br />
A REVIEW OF LABOR'S PROGRAMS AND POLICIES<br />
The title given to this Conference itself illustrates<br />
a basic characteristic of Australian federalism and the<br />
approach which Australians have usually taken towards their<br />
federal system. The general title is: " Making Federalism<br />
Work Towards a More Efficient, Equitable and Responsive<br />
Federal System". We Australians have always tended towards<br />
a pragmatic and practical approach without concerning ourselves<br />
overmuch with deep questionings about the philosophical nature<br />
and purposes of federalism. Significantly this conference<br />
does not ask the question, what is Australian federalism?<br />
It asks, is federalism working, or can it be made to work better?<br />
One might draw a contrast with America. A similar<br />
conference in the United States would, in all probability,<br />
be as concerned with first principles about the nature and<br />
purpose of the American Constitution as about its practical<br />
operation. For a variety of reasons, the Americans have<br />
always tended to be more reverential towards their Constitution<br />
than Australians, though curiously, much more ready to amend it.<br />
whatever one's opinion about the excellence of the<br />
Australian Constitution, one would not, I think, readily<br />
apply to it Gladstone's description of the American Constitution<br />
as " the most majestic single work ever struck off by the<br />
brain of man". However high our regard for our own founding<br />
fathers, it lies this side of idolatry.<br />
The practical and political preoccupations of our<br />
Constitution-makers at the conventions of the 1890' s still<br />
dominate our approach today. We are still preoccupied with<br />
practical and political questions of how to make the Federal<br />
system work. In particular, we have been concerned almost exclusively<br />
with financial relations, as the name of the Australian National<br />
University Centre for Research on Federal Financial Relations<br />
itself bears out. Up to 1972 this question was invariably<br />
referred to as Commonwealth/ State financial relations and usually<br />
meant Commonwealth versus State financial relations. To the<br />
extent that Australian federalism has been limited to the<br />
concept of Commonwealth/ State financial relations the debate has<br />
tended to be cast in terms of confrontation between the States<br />
and Canberra.' This has occurred whatever the Party affiliation<br />
of the State Premiers, whatever the ideological stance of<br />
the Prime Minister of the day a conservative federalist<br />
like Menzies, a conservative centralist like Gorton, or a<br />
reform regionalist like the present incumbent. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
My first involvement with this Centre when its<br />
establishment was proposed by Mr McMahon in 1972 was to urge<br />
successfully that local government should be included within<br />
its research charter. One hopes that the continuing work of<br />
this Centre and conferences like this may help broaden the<br />
debate and lift it beyond the slogans of centralism versus<br />
States' rights. I believe they are concepts which little<br />
accord with the needs or ideas of the Australian people and are<br />
even less in accord with the reality of what the Australian<br />
Government is trying to achieve.<br />
I accepted the suggestion that the them of my own<br />
address should be: " The new Federalism: A Review of Labor's<br />
Programs and Policies". I thought that appropriate not<br />
least because I used this expression towards a new<br />
federalism in the last major address I made on this general<br />
subject within this University to the Academy of Social Sciencc<br />
at the Australian National University Seminar on Intergovernmenti,<br />
Relations on 8 November 1971. 1 meant then and mean now nothing<br />
especially grandiose about the term. I do not pretend to<br />
have invented a new philosophy of government. My Federalist<br />
Papers, if ever honoured by publication by the A. N. U. are<br />
not intended to be a new testament to replace Hamilton,<br />
Madison and Jay.<br />
I was concerned then as I am now that our institution.,<br />
and administrative system should provide a proper balance<br />
b etween finances and functions, that each of our three levels<br />
of government should be able to carry out the functions which<br />
it is best able to perform. As I said here in November 1971:<br />
" Each of our three levels of government has functions<br />
which it is best able to perform. The key to<br />
effective performance is not domination but<br />
consultation, not centralisation but co-ordination.<br />
An Australian Schools Commission would no more<br />
deprive the States of their schools, nor an<br />
Australian Hospitals Commission deprive the States<br />
of their hospitals, than the present Universities<br />
Commission has deprived them of their universities.<br />
Failing such commissions I see no way of determining<br />
the objective priorities for those Commonwealth<br />
grants without which neither schools nor hospitals<br />
can improve. Again, we will not return power to<br />
the people simply by concentrating assistance on<br />
the existing States. A meaningful devolution of<br />
power will be effected in this country only when<br />
we provide local authorities with the means and<br />
incefttives to associate freely on the basis of<br />
shared urban and regional interests. The new<br />
federalism will rest on a national framework for<br />
the establishment of investment priorities and a<br />
regional framework for participation in all those<br />
decisions which most directly determine the quality<br />
of our lives." ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
You will see that that statement addressed itself<br />
to the three criteria implied in the theme of this conference<br />
as the benchmarks by which we may measure how well federalism<br />
is working first more efficient, secondly more equitable<br />
and thirdly more responsive. But there is a question within<br />
the question posed in each case. More efficient, yes but<br />
for what purpose? It is possible to create a system which<br />
may be quite efficient for the administrators but not very<br />
efficient in the delivery of the benefits it is designed to<br />
give. More equitable for whom? It is possible to make<br />
arrangements which are seen as equitable as between the levels<br />
of government concerned in those arrangements but which impose<br />
continuing inequalities as between States and regions.<br />
More responsive to whom? It may be possible to have a<br />
national government which seems to respond readily to demands<br />
and pressures from State Premiers but which is not really<br />
responsive to the needs or wishes of the people.<br />
oversimplified concepts such as centralism or States'<br />
rights, particularly if they are thought of as mutually<br />
hostile, mutually exclusive concepts, would have very little<br />
to do with the promotion of efficiency, equity or responsiveness.<br />
And of course it is a gross oversimplification to depict the<br />
actions of the present Australian Government in centralist<br />
terms. It is a grotesque caricature to depict the program of<br />
the Australian Government in centralist terms.<br />
It is not perhaps sufficiently recognised how much<br />
the program I set out on behalf of the Australian Labor Party<br />
in 1972 was about federalism. Indeed in its totality, in<br />
terms of the initiatives and innovations proposed and the<br />
means by which they were to be implemented, the policy<br />
speech of 1972 could well justify the description of being a<br />
document for a new federalism.<br />
It is true that these programs specified new initiatives<br />
and called for vigorous action by the national Government.<br />
The programs assert the principle that unless the national<br />
Government becomes involved in a major function or costly servicE<br />
that function or service will either not be financed fairly<br />
or not financed adequately or not financed at all. it should<br />
be equally recognised that those national initiatives and<br />
actions required co-operation with the States and the involvement<br />
of the States and local government. Action, reform, involvement<br />
by the national Government are not necessarily centralism.<br />
The program of 1972 was not framed by doctrinaire centralists.<br />
It was not framed as a statement of centralism. Nor, significant<br />
was it interpreted as such when it was presented and argued<br />
not, to the best of my recollection, by those who criticised it,<br />
and certainly not by those who supported it. It was never<br />
depicted in those terms. / 14 </p>
<p>For example, there would be no Australian newspaper<br />
more apt to detect the centralist heresy than the Sydney<br />
Morning Herald. As the thinking behind the Labor Party's<br />
program for national involvement developed and matured, so did<br />
the views of the Sydney Morning Herald. I raised some eyebrows<br />
and some horse laughs when I first urged national assistance<br />
for sewerage works. On 24 October 1969, the eve of that year's<br />
House of Representatives elections, the Sydney Morning Herald<br />
had climaxed its editorial campaign against the A. L. P. with a<br />
crunch line on I quote " Mr Whitlam's dizzy vision of<br />
Canberra deciding the correct line of a sewer in Bankstown."<br />
By 23 January 1970 it was saying surely the Commonwealth<br />
Government will heed the plea of the Premier, Mr Askin for<br />
special assistance on such a basic problem as additional funds<br />
for the Water Board's sewage treatment plans". On 6 August 1970,<br />
it again gave the Water Board's sewerage backlogs as " surely<br />
an unanswerable instance of the need for the Commonwealth to<br />
accept greater responsibility for urban requirements."<br />
On 26 December 1970: " If problems such as pollution are not<br />
to grow much worse, governments, and especially the Commonwealth<br />
Government, must show a deeper appreciation of city needs".<br />
On 7 April 1971: " More than 500,000 homes in the Sydney<br />
metropolitan area are still unsewered. These basic problems<br />
can be overcome only by a reappraisal of priorities at the<br />
Federal level." I've never seen such intelligent, fair-minded,<br />
responsible, judicious editorials in the Sydney Morning Herald<br />
until last week's Budget!<br />
At the heart of the program for national involvement<br />
lay a view about modern, more contemporary, more rational<br />
relations between the three levels of government and more modern,<br />
more contemporary, more rational arrangements for the financing<br />
and discharge of functions which modern communities now require<br />
their elected representatives to fulfil.<br />
Just how much our program was a statement about<br />
tederalism a partnership between the three levels of<br />
government is evident by recalling very briefly its key<br />
proposals. The Schools Commission was designed to examine and<br />
determine the needs of students in government and non-government,<br />
primary, secondary, and technical schools. Quite apart from<br />
the objective of making vastly more money available for education,<br />
w e intended the Commission to -help the States with the greatest<br />
burden upon their Budgets schools.<br />
The Pre-School Commission was designed to enable the<br />
children in the-States to enjoy at least equal opportunities<br />
for pre-school care and education then enjoyed only by children<br />
in Canberra, where the Commonwealth could not escape responsibilit<br />
The abolition of fees at tertiary institutions and the<br />
assumption by the Commonwealth of full responsibility for<br />
financing tertiary education fulfilled an agreement made by all<br />
the Labor leaders, federal and State, in 1967. </p>
<p>So similarly did our undertaking to make the full range<br />
of Commonwealth assistance available for buildings and<br />
equipment for staff and students at all teacher colleges.<br />
The proposal for a Hospitals Commission meant that the<br />
States would be helped with what was then the heaviest burden<br />
on t1-ir budgets after education.<br />
The program for urban and regional development represente.<br />
an altogether new approach to the idea of national involvement<br />
in the places where most Australians live. It envisaged an<br />
altogether new approach in the relations between the three levels<br />
of government. The specific proposals included the creation<br />
of land commissions, a new Commonwealth/ State housing agreement,<br />
a national sewerage plan and national aid for urban transport.<br />
We proposed to require the Grants Commission to promote equality<br />
between regions as it had formerly promoted equality between<br />
the States. We undertook to accept the offers as they then<br />
were of the New South Wales and Victorian Premiers as they th.<br />
were for the transfer of their State railways systems and to<br />
accept such an offer from any other State.<br />
We undertook to revive the Inter-State Commission to<br />
enable it to achieve the purpose envisaged by the Constitution<br />
of ending the centralism fostered by the State Governments<br />
within their borders through their transport systems. We<br />
undertook co-operation with the States in supporting the<br />
, regional development plans they had already announced. We<br />
undertook assistance to the States and to local commurities for<br />
the preservation of the national estate.<br />
In order to make local government a genuine partner<br />
in the federal system we undertook to make direct representation<br />
of local government a condition of the Australian Government's<br />
participation in the Constitutional Convention pr9posed for 1973.-<br />
Further, we proposed anzamennmntofthe-Financial Agreefl<br />
to give semi-and local government authoriti-. a voice and a<br />
vote at the Loan Council.<br />
It is impossible to say which parts of the program<br />
presented in 1972 were most important in shezr terms of winning<br />
the necessary votes to change the balance of political power.<br />
Certainly, issues like conscription and Vietnam-were charged<br />
with more emotion. But the ongoing issues, the ones that had to<br />
be developed most thoroughly, to be explained most frequently,<br />
to be expatiated upon at greatest length and in greatest detail<br />
were those that come under the three broad headings of education,<br />
health and urban and regional development schools, hospitals,<br />
cities. They might not always have raised the loudest cheers,<br />
but they certainly sustained the longest interest. They may not<br />
have been gut issues, but they were the guts of the program.<br />
And the great relevance of this basic political fact in my<br />
present context is that these programs had to be defined within<br />
a reasoned framework of national-state-local relations, financial,<br />
functional and administrative. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
They had to be relevant and shown to be relevant to the<br />
systems within which they would update the Australian federal<br />
system. The program for schools, hospitals and cities would<br />
never have made sense had it been conceived just as an exercise<br />
in centralism; it would never have been endorsed if it had<br />
been perceived as such.<br />
It is important to remember that the essence of these<br />
programs is not just increases in government spending. We<br />
sought new techniques, not new taxes. we sought to improve<br />
the machinery by which Australians govern themselves, not<br />
just to outlay more of their money on national programs which<br />
might hold electoral appeal for them.<br />
The program was, particularly in its earliest stages<br />
of implementation, admittedly expensive. It was avowedly<br />
expansive. We sought to do two things. We sought to catch<br />
up a backlog over a whole range of social matters created by<br />
twenty-three years of conservative government and we sought<br />
to make a breakthrough over a whole range of national issues<br />
to make Australian government more efficient, more equitable,<br />
more responsive. We make no apologies for being an activist Government.<br />
But there is nothing necessarily centralist or anti-Federalist<br />
about action by the national government. More action by<br />
Canberra need not be equated with more power for Canberra.<br />
National involvement in the planning and financing is not<br />
incompatible with co-operative planning. Rather it is essential<br />
to successful co-operative planning under the Australian<br />
system. This holds true even in cases where the very greatest<br />
of new outlays have been involved. In what sense can it be<br />
rationally argued that the vastly increased sums made available<br />
to the State Education Departments and the non-government<br />
schools through the Schools Commission is a victory for<br />
centralism? Who could now dismantle the Schools Commission in<br />
the name of State rights? Again in what sense can it be<br />
rationally argued that the redundancy of the private health<br />
bureaucracies through Medibank is a triumph for the central<br />
bureaucracy? But the long rearguard action by four of the StateE<br />
against Medibank was presumably fought on just that ground.<br />
I can best illustrate the approach of the Australian<br />
Government by referring to the actions we took at the three<br />
Premiers' Conferences of 1973, 1974 and 1975.<br />
At the 1973 Premiers' Conference I put the view that in<br />
the fields of welfare housing and tertiary education, Australian<br />
Government spending had grown so much in the 30 years since<br />
the Commonwealth first became involved that the Australian<br />
Government should now accept full financial responsibility<br />
for them. The States accepted the view; the Australian<br />
Government now accepts that responsibility. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
At the 1974 Premiers' Conference we adopted a new roads<br />
program. I put the view that there was no hope of our having<br />
satisfactory inter-State highways under the existing<br />
arrangements and that acting under Section 51( i) of the<br />
Constitution the Australian Government was prepared to accept<br />
not just 80 per cent of the financial burden, but 100 per cent.<br />
At the 1975 Premiers' Conference I stressed that the<br />
Australian Government was not prepared to carry the States'<br />
deficit where it is growing most rapidly on railways and<br />
hospitals other than on the basis of the agreement which<br />
we had already achieved with South Australia. That is, we<br />
are prepared to acquire the State railways and to share<br />
hospital costs fifty-fifty.<br />
In other words, at these three conferences, we have<br />
shown our readiness to adopt a constructive approach to the<br />
financial problems of the States. It seems to me ludicrous<br />
to suggest that the provision of basic physical services like<br />
inter-State roads and railways should be submerged in debate<br />
over questions of political power or political rights. In<br />
other federal systems such matters are planned on a national<br />
basis. I must emphasise, however, that our approach to the<br />
States' financial problems has by no means been limited to<br />
a willingness to accept responsibility for some of their more<br />
burdensome and costly services. We have not only freed them<br />
of some of their burdens, but have given them the financial<br />
means towards greater freedom in pursuing their own pi: poses.<br />
There has been a very large increase in general purpose funds,<br />
even given the constraints all governments are now under.<br />
The figures are instructive: improved financial<br />
assistance grants to the States, accepted at the June Premiers'<br />
Conference, will provide a total of about $ 3,185 million in<br />
1975/ 76, an increase of $ 811 million or 34.2 per cent over<br />
the grants paid in 1974/ 75. The States are free to determine<br />
how these funds are spent. The increase of 34.2 per cent is<br />
very significantly greater than the increase in total Australian<br />
Government outlays estimated at 22.9 per cent.<br />
There is the additional freedom which Medibank funding<br />
will provide to the States in 1975/ 76 relief of the order<br />
of $ 300 million. The Australian Government has undertaken that<br />
such relief will not be the subject of " offsets" to general<br />
revenue grants. Unconditional funds available to the States<br />
will thus be very significantly increased.<br />
The Budget itself reflects an important change of<br />
emphasis in our future approach. In the first two years of<br />
office we relied heavily on grants under Section 96 of the<br />
Constitution to break through in key areas which had been badly<br />
neglected by our predecessors. Under Section 96 we involved<br />
the national Government directly in new initiatives at the<br />
local level. In the new Budget we have increased emphasis on<br />
untied grants to the States through general revenue assistance<br />
and to local government through the Grants Commission. / 8 </p>
<p>-8-<br />
The June Premiers' Conference was also notable for a<br />
significant-move towards co-operative planning with the<br />
States. Premiers' Conferences themselves are obviously unable<br />
to act effectively to co-ordinate policies and determine<br />
priorities. Before the June Conference Australian Government<br />
officials conferred with State officials on the development<br />
of co-operative planning. Those discussions were taken further<br />
at the Premiers' Conference itself and the Premiers agreed<br />
that the officers should develop more specific proposals and<br />
report back to us.<br />
As I told the Premiers:<br />
" The Australian Government will be seeking in<br />
the longer term a more rational and co-ordinated<br />
system of assessing needs, setting priorities and<br />
allocating resources in the public sector one<br />
based on co-operation between Governments. it<br />
may take years to develop a new approach of the<br />
kind we have in mind, of the kind discussed among<br />
our officials. But we believe a start should be<br />
made now."<br />
We have already taken steps towards co-operative<br />
planning, for example in the fields of transport, health<br />
and urban development.<br />
Transport systems should be planned on an integrated<br />
basis, the right balance needs to be struck between land, sea<br />
and air transport so that the resulting total system satisfies<br />
our nation's needs and priorities.<br />
The Transport Advisory Council has become the major<br />
forum for discussion and consultation on the problems of<br />
public transport services and main railway lines and is now<br />
concerned also with road matters. Moreover, the Australian<br />
Government has recently taken the initiative in bringing<br />
aviation matters before the Council.<br />
In the health field, two major new programs have been<br />
developed by the Hospitals and Health Services Commission in<br />
close co-operation with the States the Community Health<br />
Program and the Hospitals Development Program.<br />
In the latter case, formal provision has been made<br />
for co-operative planning the hospitals buildings program<br />
for each State is considered jointly and formally by equal<br />
numbers of Australian and State Government officers who<br />
recommend to'their respective Governments the total program<br />
of hospital development within the particular State.<br />
In the case of the community health program, there is<br />
a process of consultation, somewhat short of co-operative<br />
planning, which recognises that individual health services<br />
must be seen as part of an integrated and co-ordinated system. </p>
<p>There is growing support for the development of a<br />
regional approach to the planning of health services. New<br />
South Wales has formally regionalised its health services<br />
planning and administration, and other States are examining<br />
such an approach.<br />
It is hoped that as regional planning and administration<br />
of health services are developed-the Australian and State<br />
Governments will be able to divest themselves of unnecessary<br />
detail and devote their energies to co-operative planning<br />
and evaluation at the broad level, while responding to and<br />
promoting detailed planning and administrative responsibility<br />
at the regional level.<br />
There has been considerable progress recently in the<br />
development of co-operative planning arrangements in the field<br />
of urban development.<br />
Perhaps the most complete example is the arrangements<br />
for Ministerial Councils to oversee the development of each<br />
of the designated growth centres. These Ministerial Councils<br />
require the State and Australian Ministers working jointly to<br />
determine the overall development strategy for each growth<br />
centre-and the forward financial plan associated with that<br />
strategy on a rolling basis five years ahead.<br />
The Australian Government's intentions for co-operative<br />
planning are that it be a process by which national priorities<br />
are identified and harmonised with the priorities of other<br />
levels of governments; by which CO&gt;-ordinated forward planning<br />
i's developed in pursuit of agreed ' priorities and by which functior<br />
and finances of the Australian, State and local gover~ nents<br />
are better balanced.<br />
In February this year I announced the establishment<br />
of a small committee of Ministers to be concerned primarily<br />
with the Australian Government's relations with the States.<br />
The Ministers are the Treasurer, the Minister for Social Security,<br />
the, Minister for Urban and Regional Development, and myself.<br />
This Committee is also undertaking examination of programs of<br />
direct assistance to regions, to local government and to local<br />
communities. This Australian Government has stressed a regional<br />
approach to planning and decision-making.<br />
Agreement has been reached with all States on the<br />
regional borders used for Grants Commission purposes. In most<br />
cases. these boundaries have been defined by the States<br />
themselves. Our purpose in developing a regional policy, in<br />
identifying logical regions and hopefully, contributing to<br />
the growth of a sense of regional identity among Australian<br />
communities, is not to out-flank the States or to replace local<br />
government. But it is a fact that there are a wide range of<br />
community programs and services which are most efficiently and<br />
equitably planned, co-ordinated and delivered at a level<br />
intermediary to those of State and local governments. There are<br />
many examples electricityj reticulation, water and sewerage,<br />
hospitals, libraries, some forms of public transport and some<br />
welfare services. </p>
<p>The Australian Government has been encouraged by<br />
the degree of acceptance of the concept of regionalism by local<br />
government and the widespread recognition that regionalism<br />
is not a threat but rather a stimulus to local government.<br />
For our part, we see regionalism as crucial to our efforts to<br />
make local government a genuine partner in the federal system.<br />
The work of the Grants Commission has been the most important<br />
step to that end that we have so far achieved. Following<br />
the Governments acceptance of the Commission's Second Report<br />
million will be provided without conditions this year<br />
a 42 per cent increase on last year. Despite our efforts<br />
at the 1973 Constitutional Convention and at a special<br />
Premiers' Conference in October 1973 and at the May 1974<br />
referendum, we have not yet been able to fulfil our promise<br />
of 1972 and our hope of 1974 to give local government a voice<br />
and a vote in the Loan Council and reasonable direct access<br />
to the nation's finances.<br />
Central to our concepts of regionalism are devolution<br />
of decision-making and public participation at the regional<br />
and local levels to give the people a say in matters<br />
affecting them directly. The Coombs Royal Commission is<br />
examining the regionalisation of Australian Government<br />
administration with the aim of improving the delivery of<br />
government services to the citizen and of giving the citizen<br />
easier access to the array of services provided by different<br />
levels of government.<br />
At the Constitutional Convention on 3 September 1973<br />
I put it that regionalism was a logical and necessar-extension<br />
of the federal system. I said:<br />
" Why did we create this Federation? The answer<br />
is partly to alleviate inequalities between<br />
regions, between colonies. Why did we accept<br />
the Financial Agreement of 1928? The answer<br />
is to alleviate inequalities between the States.<br />
Why did we establish the Grants Commission? To<br />
reduce even further inequalities between the States.<br />
Much of the object of our history, the thrust of<br />
our traditions, a deep part of the purpose of our<br />
being one nation, is to alleviate inequalities. The<br />
task now is to alleviate inequalities between regions;<br />
our new regions, our new pattern of development know<br />
little of the borders and boundaries established in<br />
Whitehall last century."<br />
It is ironic indeed that some of the Constitution's<br />
clearest intentions and the clearest intentions of the<br />
Constitution-makers in the 1890' s are still so strongly resisteC~<br />
in the 1970' s.<br />
A striking example is the resistance to the reconstitut'<br />
of the Inter-State Commission. Section 101 requires the<br />
appointment of the Commission . The section reads:<br />
" 1101. There shall be an inter-State Commission,<br />
with such powers of adjudication and administration<br />
as the Parliament deems necessary for the execution<br />
and maintenance, within the Commonwealth, of the<br />
provisions of this Constitution relating to trade<br />
and commerce, and of all laws made thereunder." </p>
<p>-11-<br />
The Joint Committee on Constitutional Review, to<br />
which I was appointed in 1956, unanimously recommended in 1959<br />
the reconstitution of the Commission. It was, as I mentioned<br />
earlier, one of the undertakings I gave in 1972 and repeated<br />
in 1974. I don't recall in all those years any suggestion<br />
that the Commission or the proposal to reconstitute it was in<br />
any way sinister. Yet our intention and more our positive<br />
undertaking to re-establish the Commission has been stalled<br />
in the Senate and you may have noticed some of the denuciations.<br />
For example, the New South Wales Minister for Federal<br />
Affairs, Mr Hewitt was reported on 26 August in Tuesday's<br />
Sydney Morning Herald as saying:<br />
" The bill is more in keeping with the practices<br />
of Nazi Germany than a federal democracy such<br />
as Australia".<br />
The-fact is that the Commission would do the job<br />
intended by the Constitution to help solve the problems,<br />
particularly transport problems, inherent in a federal system,<br />
inherent in the continental nature of Australia herself.<br />
There are the current examples of Bass Strait freight rates,<br />
Victorian transport costs to the Riverina and the cancellation<br />
of shipping services operated by Associated Steamships<br />
from Fremantle to the eastern States. As I wrote on this last<br />
matter to the Premier of Western Australia, Sir Charles Court,<br />
on 13 August: " The Australian. Government's intention to<br />
re-establish the Inter-State Commission, which<br />
has been delayed by the Opposition in the<br />
Senate, is designed to examine and seek solutions<br />
to problems of this nature involving competing<br />
modes of transport. In the absence of legislation<br />
re-constituting the Commission, Government<br />
intervention in matters of this kind is beyond<br />
power under the Constitution." m<br />
To sum up the approach of the Australian Labor GovernmE<br />
to the federal system:<br />
the national Government has involved itself<br />
directly in financing and planning of a wide<br />
range of new functions, particularly where<br />
national involvement is crucial to the<br />
achievement of equality of opportunity and<br />
equality of services,<br />
in its relations with the States, the national<br />
Government has accepted or is willing to accept<br />
financial responsibility for services, the<br />
provision of which has hitherto imposed the<br />
heaviest burdens on State budgets. Yet at the<br />
same time we have increased general purpose<br />
grants at a significantly increased level. / 12 </p>
<p>-12-<br />
* We have embarked upon co-operative planning<br />
at both the Ministerial and official level<br />
on a continuing basis in those areas where<br />
national and State responsibilities overlap<br />
or dovetail.<br />
* We have developed a regional policy to provide<br />
community services which cannot be as well<br />
provided by any of the existing levels of<br />
government acting alone.<br />
* Local government is becoming a genuine partner<br />
in the federal system and is securing direct<br />
access to the nation's financial resources.<br />
In contemporary Australia, the questions about<br />
structures, systems and powers the sort of concern expressed<br />
in the old slogans about centralism or States' rights are<br />
more likely to be the preoccupation of politicians, public<br />
officials, the press and, perhaps, academics, rather than<br />
the general public. The people's concern will not be so much<br />
who performs a function, but how well it is performed in<br />
terms of their needs and wishes and hopes.<br />
The program of the Australian Labor Party, as developed<br />
in Opposition, as implemented in Government, has been very<br />
much about an attempt to bring our federal system and our<br />
federal machinery up to date, at least to a degree already<br />
achieved by comparable federal systems, particularly those<br />
of Canada, West Germany and the United States.<br />
For more than a generation, the old approach to the<br />
Australian federal system the buck-passing of responsibility<br />
between governments, the crude confrontation at the annual<br />
charade of the Premiers' Conference exploited the federal<br />
system at the expense of the Australian people. The limitations<br />
of the Constitution were used by all governments of all<br />
parties Federal and State as an alibi. Canberra exploited<br />
the system to justify indifference; the States used it to<br />
justify inertia. I might say in passing, that Liberal<br />
Premiers sometimes think that I am abrasive about their<br />
unwillingness to come to terms with new realities; let me<br />
say at least that I am even sharper with any Labor leader<br />
or State branch who uses the alibi of the federal system to<br />
justify their failure to develop policies either relevant to<br />
that system or particularly relevant to the needs of the people<br />
of their States.<br />
Be that as it may, the fact is that for a generation and<br />
more, other federal systems were attempting to move ahead, to<br />
grapple with the new problems created by the New Society these<br />
highly urban, highly mobile, highly technological civilisations.<br />
We lagged behind.<br />
In very many important respects urban development,<br />
transport, health, welfare, education our program was developed<br />
and designed to match these new realities and to match what was<br />
already being done in modern comparable federal systems. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
It is interesting some may say ironic that just<br />
when the Australian Government and the Australian system began<br />
to catch up in terms of what had been done abroad in Federal<br />
systems long ago, the results achieved in other systems should<br />
come under a new and searching and critical scrutiny, indeed<br />
a fundamental reappraisal. The new concern is whether the<br />
objectives sought by the range of new federal programs are<br />
actually being met. Are they delivering the goods to the<br />
people they are designed to benefit? Are the expectations raise,-,<br />
by the promise fulfilled in the reality? Have they produced<br />
benefits proportionate to their cost? Have they created<br />
welfare or merely a welfare bureaucracy? These are proper<br />
questions already being asked, particularly in the United<br />
States. We should certainly be asking them here about our<br />
own programs. I should be the last to suggest that--there are<br />
no lessons to be learnt from overseas experience, from the<br />
experience of comparable federal systems, except those that<br />
were to be learnt up to December 1972.<br />
It is further interesting to note that, in the<br />
United States, the new questioning about the efficiency,<br />
equity and responsiveness of federal programs comes especially<br />
from concerned liberals, from Democrats, from the heirs of<br />
the New Deal and the authors of the Great Society.<br />
But this new scrutiny would miss its mark if it mistook<br />
failures in specific methods for failures of ideals and objectives.<br />
It would be a travesty and a tragedy it trie onjectives<br />
of welfare, of equality, of civil liberties, were to<br />
be discredited simply because of flaws in the means by which<br />
governments, here or abroad, were attempting to achieve them.<br />
Knowing how quickly we imitate trends of discussion<br />
in the United States, I think it very likely that it will<br />
become fashionable here quite soon to decry and deride and<br />
strive to discredit the great post-War effort towards<br />
collective and community social welfare and social equality<br />
made in the United States, as well as in Europe, in Britain<br />
and in Australia herself.<br />
From those who seek to enshrine inequality, there is<br />
going to be a great deal of talk about " enforced equality".<br />
Such arguments will miss the point entirely. President Johnson<br />
proclaimed the Great Society. The ends which were sought have<br />
not been achieved. The expectations aroused have not been met.<br />
All sorts of reasons are given and there is truth in them.<br />
But if the vision splendid has dimmed, let us remember that<br />
beyond the actual shortcomings of the programs, in both<br />
conception and execution there was a fundamental contradiction<br />
which lies at the root of the failure of the Great Society.<br />
The contradiction was that even the United States, for all its<br />
unparalleldd wealth and power, could finance both the Great<br />
Society and the war in Indo-China without damage to herself<br />
and all of us. And just as that fallacy is at the root of the<br />
failure of the vision of the Great Society, it is at the root<br />
of half the economic problems we all face today. Let us bear<br />
that in mind, before we pass judgement on the success or failure<br />
of federal government-sponsored welfare programs, either in<br />
the United States or in Australia. / 14 </p>
<p>-14-<br />
Nonetheless, the scrutiny of such programs must be<br />
undertaken are they efficient, are they equitable, are they<br />
really responding to the needs and wishes of the people.<br />
That scrutiny is being undertaken by this Government. The<br />
Budget itself was part of that process as the Treasurer<br />
put it: " A time to pause and take stock, a time to<br />
consolidate".<br />
We want a continuing scrutiny to go on in co-operation with<br />
the other Australian governments at all levels at the<br />
federal, State and local levels, at the political and<br />
administrative levels.<br />
I believe the record of the past two and a half years<br />
justifies the assertion that the Australian Government has<br />
tried to inject a new life into the Australian federal system<br />
and a new meaning into Australian federalism.<br />
It has not been done through any mindless, centralist<br />
doctrine, but by a genuine effort to build more modern,<br />
efficient machinery at all levels of government. It has<br />
been a genuine, creative, constructive, co-operative effort<br />
to make Australian federalism more efficient, more equitable<br />
and, above all, more responsive to the people of Australia<br />
wherever they live. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
