<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>540</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR THE PRESS: 26TH JUNE, 1962 - WEST NEW GUINEA - STATEMENT BY TEH PRIME MINISTER, RIGHT HONOURABLE R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/06/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000540.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR THE PRESS WEST NEW .3UINEA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister-, Rig. ht Honorable R. G. Menzies<br />
Cabinet has given consideration to recent developments in West<br />
New Guinea. We have in particular been concerned at the latest news of<br />
the dropping of Indonesian troops in and around Merauke.<br />
With every natural desire to live on terms of friendliness<br />
with Indonesia, we find it necessary to point out two things.<br />
Oi ne is that this warlike action is quite inconsistent with the<br />
Otatements publicly and repeatedly made to us, that Indonesia would not<br />
pursue its territorial claim to West New Guinea by force-of arms.<br />
SThe other is that the negotiations recently begun in the<br />
presence of Mr. Bunker after initiating action by the acting Secretary-<br />
General of the United Nations, have yet to be resumed and concluded. We<br />
find it impossible to understand why the processes of peaceful negotiation<br />
should be interrupted and impaired by military aggression...<br />
Wo would like to say, ince more, that we df. siro and will respect<br />
peaceful sftttlement arising fr-' m such negotiation; that active<br />
hostilities can achieve nothing but unnecessary bitterness; and that<br />
peace in this part of the w-rld is important, not only to the nations<br />
mmediately concerned but to the whole future of South East Asia and the<br />
outh West Pacific.<br />
It is also important for the future authority of the United<br />
Nations that international territorial differences should be settled<br />
without either the threat or the use of armed force.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
