<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5022</transcript-id>
    <title>1979 VICTORIAN ELECTION CAMPAIGN OPENING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005022.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
_ A U STRAIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA-17 APRIL 1979<br />
1979 VICTORIAN ELECTION CAMPAIGN OPENING<br />
We are eighteen days away from a crucial election, an election<br />
which will decide the future of this State, an election<br />
which is vital for Victoria. We want a government committed<br />
to Liberalism. We want a government committed to free<br />
enterprise. We want a government committed to the right of<br />
people to achieve their own goals in their own way. We<br />
want a Hamer government.<br />
Dick Hamer is vital for Victoria. Just look at the alternative.<br />
Does Victoria want a socialist government? Does Victoria want<br />
a government in the grip of the extreme left wing? Victoria<br />
needs the philosophy, the policies, the people, that only the<br />
Liberal Party can provide.<br />
Only Dick Hamer and the Liberals will take Victoria confidently<br />
into the 1980' s, with a humane and progressive government.<br />
The economic record of the Hamer government speaks for itself.<br />
It's kept Victoria prosperous. It's kept Victoria in the forefront<br />
of Australia's economic activity. But Victoria's successes have<br />
not just been in the economic area. The Victorian Liberals have<br />
demonstrated their commitment to improving the quality of<br />
life in this State, to improving health and education, to<br />
conserving the environment and our historical and cultural<br />
heritage, our great buildings and historic sites, to providing<br />
a new deal for our ethnic communities, and working with the<br />
Commonwealth to make the Galbally Report a total success; to<br />
protecting the civil rights of individuals. Those are just<br />
some of the achievements made by the Liberal Government.<br />
But what of the future? Under a Liberal Government, Victoria's<br />
future is one of progressive reform and continued economic<br />
prosperity. It's because of industry's confidence in the Liberal<br />
approach of the Commonwealth and the State Government that so<br />
many new major projects are planned for Victoria. There's<br />
ICI's $ 500 million petrochemical pl-ant at Point Wilson,<br />
GMH's $ 210 million engine plant based in Victoria, ALCOA's<br />
$ 350 million aluminium smelter, and the massive expenditure<br />
which Esso-BHP will make in Bass Strait. </p>
<p>2<br />
Would Labor get any of these projects underway? No. Labor<br />
says it's " moderate", but Labor always says it's " moderate"<br />
at election time. We saw how Mr. Whitlam's Labor Party pretended<br />
to be moderate in the run up to the 1972 elect1ii. And we saw<br />
how quickly they cast aside their cloak of respectability. Labor<br />
stopped development dead in its tracks. In three years income<br />
tax more than doubled from $ 4 billion to over $ 9 billion. In one<br />
year alone, income tax grew by 40 percent. Our income tax<br />
reforms have saved taxpayers $ 3 billion a year. In three<br />
years under Labor, government expenditure soared from<br />
billion to nearly $ 22 billion. In one year alone outlays<br />
grew by 46 percent.<br />
We have reduced the rate of growth of government expenditure<br />
to 7.7 percent. Under Labor unemployment rocketed, rising<br />
by nearly 200,000 in one year. Labor created unemployment<br />
in Australia. The Whitlam. Labor government which set this<br />
record said it was " moderate".<br />
We saw Mr. Wran's Labor Party preach responsibility when it had<br />
a majority of only one. We are now seeing Mr. Wran, with a<br />
clear majority, paying off his debts to the left wing. He took<br />
the power workers' demand for a 37 1/ 2 hour week out of the<br />
hands of the Industrial Commission to give it to them on a<br />
Parliamentary platter, as an entree to a 35 hour week.<br />
But we must be fair. At least the left wing in New South Wales<br />
had to wait until after the election to be paid off. In<br />
Victoria, the left wing has already won.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition, Mr. Wilkes, has said that he will<br />
ignore the Arbitration Commission, and give wage increases to<br />
Latrobe Valley power workers, regardless of the decision by<br />
the full bench of the Commission.<br />
It's official Labor Party policy to remove all present legal<br />
restraint on industrial disputes conducted by trade unions.<br />
Labor wants to put unions above the law. Would Labor protect<br />
the people of Victoria against union militants? No. Is there<br />
a guarantee that Newport would go ahead under Labor? No.<br />
The union leadership knows that Labor's posturing on Newport is<br />
only political expediency. As the Secretary of the Electrical<br />
Trades Union said on the 27th of March: " Frank Wilkes is<br />
prepared to make statements for political expediency.., the<br />
Parliamentary wing of the Labor Party had changed its stance<br />
( on Newport) three times since 1971..."<br />
The Labor Party would try to buy industrial peace by caving in<br />
to every union demand. It's prepared to appease the unions by<br />
bankrupting the enterprises that provide the jobs for<br />
Victorians, by promoting inflation which would harm the weak<br />
and the poor most of all. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
The left wing goes quiet just before election time, but just<br />
a few months ago, they showed their strength. They defeated<br />
a motion condemning infringements of human rights in the<br />
Soviet Union. There couldn't be any such infringements because<br />
the Soviet government said so. The left wing also defeated<br />
a moton which tried to water down Labor's commitment to<br />
nationalise industry. The left wing wasn't having any of that.<br />
They insisted that the commitment to total nationalisation<br />
remain in its pristine form the same form that it had<br />
in 1921. What a way to step into the future.<br />
The Labor Party is ready to leap with verve and gust back into<br />
the 1920' s. While Labor is looking backwards, the Liberals are<br />
ready for the challenges of the 1980' s. We are now moving into<br />
a new period of economic recovery. Inflation has been reduced.<br />
Australian businesses are once again competitive. Investment<br />
has increased dramatically. Exports are rising, and business<br />
confidence has returned. There are heartening signs of<br />
improvement on the employment front. For the first time in<br />
five years, civilian employment, seasonally adjusted, have<br />
risen for each of the last seven months. Overtime and<br />
vacancies seasonally adjusted, are also improving.<br />
For Victorians to benefit from this recovery, we need a State<br />
government which is prepared to co-operate with the Commonwealth<br />
government's policies, not undermine them.<br />
The Labor Party would turn back the clock. It would destroy the<br />
advances already made in Victoria. It would damage the future of<br />
this State. Only under the Liberals who have provided stability<br />
and good sense in government for almost a quarter of a century<br />
will Victoria continue to build on its achievements.<br />
When it really comes right down to it, that's what this<br />
election is about. Do we want a Liberal government, committed<br />
to people, to people's creativity, to people's needs, to<br />
people's interests? Or, do we want a Labor Party committed<br />
to the destructive dogma of socialism, a Party that has time<br />
and time again been rejected by the people of Victoria?<br />
The Liberal Party has governed Victoria well, providing stability<br />
and prosperity. I have no doubt that the Liberal Party will<br />
lead Victoria into the 1980' s.<br />
But we can't just sit back. We all have to go out and tell people<br />
about what the Liberal Party believes in, what the Party has<br />
achieved, about the Liberal vision for Victoria's future.<br />
It's been this vision, it's been our capacity to govern well, and<br />
the dedication of those committed to the Liberal way of life,<br />
that has given us victory after victory in Victoria. We are<br />
doing it again because the Liberals and Dick Hamer are vital<br />
for Victoria. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
