<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6654</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH ITA BUTTROSE, 2KY, 24 JUNE 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006654.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2%<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E. O. E PROOF ONLY<br />
INTERVIEW WITH ITA BUTTROSE, 2KY 24 JUNE 1985<br />
BUTTROSE: Good morning Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Good morning Ita how are you?<br />
BUTTROSE: I'm alright.<br />
PM: Good.<br />
BUTTROSE: I may be a new girl at 2KY but I think you're<br />
copping a lot of flack. Tax must be a bit of a detestable<br />
word for you at the moment.<br />
PM: Yzs well before we go onto that Ita, congratulat-' ns<br />
on your new appointment and the best of luck to you and the<br />
Station. BUTTROSE: Thanks very much.<br />
PM: Ita yes well as you say its very much in the news.<br />
But I want to make this point that I found as I've been going<br />
around Australia, I was over in South Australia yesterday and<br />
talked to a luncheon of about five hundred people, when you<br />
get to the people and talk to them and are able to listen to<br />
what they've got to say, respond to them, there is a very<br />
positive response. So I think there is a difference between<br />
the people themselves, once you can actually talk to them,<br />
and some of their leaders are a little bit timid, should I say-.<br />
BUTTROSE: Prime Minister did you expect that it would be such<br />
a tough selling job?<br />
PM: Yes I thought it would be fairly tough Ita. Because<br />
when you talk about tax you're talking about something that's<br />
very close to everybody. And they tend, naturally enough, I<br />
don't complain about it, to look at it in a very direct personal<br />
sense. They see somdthing that they think might hurt them.<br />
That tends to dominate their thinking. There's a bit of an<br />
incapacity to look at the package as a whole. And in fact<br />
the preferred Option that the Government is putting up would<br />
make virtually everyone, except the tax avoiders, better off.<br />
BUTTROSE: Well there are a lot of tax avoiders in Australia<br />
we know that. That's why I personally believe the system<br />
needs an overhaul. Because when you've got a system where<br />
everybody's trying to avoid paying tax, regardless of where<br />
you happen to be in income levels, you're right. You've </p>
<p>got the cash Society, and then you've got your business people<br />
with all their perks and lurks. There has to be something wrong<br />
when we've got a system that makes everybody want to avoid tax.<br />
PM: Well that's right. And that's one of the reasons<br />
why the preferred Option that we put forward, I think, has so<br />
much merit that it means that at least in respect of their<br />
consumption that people who may be avoiding tax elsewhere<br />
will be paying a contribution to the common revenue. The<br />
central question, Ita, is whether the compensation packages<br />
that are contained in the preferred Option are adequate to<br />
look after the needs of the lower income people and those<br />
on social welfare benefits. So they won't be disadvantaged<br />
by the increase in prices associated with<br />
BUTTROSE: The general consensus, if I can use one of your<br />
words, sir, is that a lot of Australians think that they won't<br />
be looked after well enough. Earlier this morning we took<br />
a call from a gentleman called Bill, whose on an average income<br />
of $ 350, and he says that he doesn't have any money left after<br />
$ 350, after he's paid his tax and everything else. And that<br />
if he has to pay 12h% on a lot of consumer items, he's just<br />
not going to be able to afford that. Now what would you say<br />
to somebody like that?<br />
PM: Wt:: 11 the answer to Bill of course is that as part<br />
of the package he'll have a lot more in his pay packet. Because<br />
the rates of tax will be slashed enormously. I mean for instance<br />
the person in the annual income range of $ 19,500 to $ 28,000 who<br />
now pays 46 cents in the dollar in tax would have that slashed to<br />
cents in the dollar. So Bill would have that much more in<br />
his kick, if I can use that phrase, because he would be paying<br />
less direct tax and he would have more than enough there to pay<br />
the increased costs of goods associated with the consumption<br />
tax.<br />
BUTTROSE: The Federal President of the Labor Party, Neville<br />
Wran, last week came if we can just have a look at some of<br />
the critics of the scheme so far Neville Wran said that he<br />
was against the consumption tax on food. Now when the<br />
Federal President of the Labor Party comes out and makes a<br />
statement like that that must be a bit of a blow to you.<br />
PM: That's not what he said the next day. I mean<br />
when he thought about it a bit....<br />
BUTTROSE: I felt someone probably muscled him.<br />
PM: Oh no. You can't do that to Neville. No he's<br />
had the opportunity of looking at more detail. And naturally<br />
enough I respect. Neville's, if you like, instinctive reaction.<br />
We're all against a tax on food if that's all there is because<br />
we know that it will hurt the lower income people, the needy,<br />
much more. But that's why we're putting two billion dollars<br />
worth of compensation packages, Ita, into the whole proposal<br />
which we believe will offset those disadvantages. But at the </p>
<p>Summit we're going to listen to what everyone' s got to say.<br />
If it can be shown that those compensation packages are not<br />
adequate, and more needs to be done well then of couz: se the<br />
Government will listen to that.<br />
BUTTROSE: Well you said last night, you said yesterday speaking<br />
on the weekend, if there is a better way we will do it. Yet<br />
m Paul Keating has been quoted as saying that everything is<br />
non-negotiable. But are you saying, therefore, that if you<br />
feel after the Summit that perhaps the consumption tax on food<br />
is incorrect you will change your mind?<br />
PM: We've said all along, Paul and myself and the<br />
Government, that we are going into the Summit not with our<br />
minds closed, we're going to listen to what people have got<br />
to say. Now if it could be shown, and it certainly hasn't been<br />
to this point Ita, But let's say that it could be shown, that<br />
there were some new calculations, which indicated that the<br />
compensation package wasn't good enough, and the people, the<br />
lower income levels were going to be hurt in a way which we<br />
can't see that they are, then<br />
of course we'd take that into account.<br />
BUTTROSE: And change your mind?<br />
PM: Cliange your mind as to the way you had to go about it.<br />
I mean I still believe, without question, that an approach ' wiich<br />
involves the consumption tax is necessary if we're going to ensure<br />
that everyone in the community makes a contribution to the<br />
general revenue. But it may be, I mean I just say this hypothetically<br />
it may be that it can be shown that the way we've approached<br />
it doesn't sufficiently take account of some areas which need<br />
further compensation. And I say to the people of Australia,<br />
through your programme Ita, that we are not a Government which<br />
is about trying to hurt people. We want to make them better off<br />
and politically you'd be stupid to deliberately do something<br />
which is going to hurt people. So of course we're going to<br />
listen. And if can be shown that there's some, things that<br />
haven't been sufficiently taken into account then they will be.<br />
BUTTROSE: What about the ACTU, Prime Minister. Now to my<br />
mind they seem to be acting like a separate Government. Almost<br />
like a superior Senate. Mr Creanyhas been quoted as saying<br />
" we will consider our policy and if we so choose nothing will<br />
go on". I wonder do you every remind the ACTU that the<br />
-Government was elected by the-people?<br />
PM: Oh yes, and I understand that you may have that<br />
reaction. But let me-say this, that the ACTU know that we'll<br />
be making the decisions. It makes good sense, however for a<br />
government to be talking, not only to the ACTU, but the<br />
business community. That's what we've done since we've been<br />
in office. Because if you're going to get a system to work<br />
as well and efficiently as possible, then its best go get as<br />
much co-operation as you can from the major sectors of the<br />
community. So of course we'll talk to them. They won't<br />
be making up our minds for us though. </p>
<p>BUTTRQSE: People are very concerned and the polls, well the<br />
polls are not as good as they might be, but I guess you've<br />
been in, well in the Trade Union movement and in politics<br />
long enough to know that polls come and go. But there are<br />
a lot of them, the first I've heard in a long time sir, that<br />
Labor could lose office over this tax. If you look at the<br />
history of the Labor Party it seems to me that the Labor<br />
Party is never beaten at the polls they tend to lose at<br />
the polls because they slip, and I wonder how concerned are<br />
you that there may be a monumental split in the Labor Party<br />
over the tax issue.<br />
PM: Well let me take the points in succession that you<br />
made about the polls generally. And the last poll showed that<br />
we would have won on the distribution of DPemocrats preferences.<br />
And given the troubles that we've had in preparing for the<br />
tax paper and also the Expenditure Review Committee and the<br />
constraints we had to impose there, I think that's not a bad<br />
position. But coming to the position of the Labor Party itself,<br />
you're quite right Ita, in saying that there are obviously<br />
divisions within the Labor Party on this issue. The conferences<br />
generally have not been terribly supportive of the Government' s<br />
preferred package. But we will listen to what they've got to<br />
say but that's not going to be absolutely determinative of<br />
our position. We are elected to govern, to make the decisions<br />
which we thin. 7k are necessary in the best interests of the<br />
country. We will take into account those observations of<br />
the Party conferences as we will of everything that's said<br />
by representative organisations. And we will have the job<br />
after the Summit, Ita, of trying to see whether what's<br />
happened satisfies the Ninth Principle of some broad general<br />
community support for the approach that we're talking about.<br />
BUTTROSE: This weekend there was a Summit talking about yet<br />
another area of concern. There was a Women's Summit in<br />
Canberra, and they now say a taxation plan would be unfair to<br />
women. sending a deputation to see you. Have you<br />
caught up with that report yet.<br />
PM: I saw the report in this morning's paper, yes.<br />
Well of course a number of women's organisations will be<br />
represented at the Summit, Ita. Again we'l11 listen to what<br />
they've got to say. Let me put it this way, that I think the<br />
women of Australia have got to understand that the most<br />
regressive aspect of any system of taxation is avoidance and<br />
evasion. And the only way that you're going to be able to<br />
get at a lot of avoiders and evaders is through a consumption<br />
tax. Now, if the wom~ en's g'roups have got some details that<br />
they want to put to us which they think prove the inadequacy<br />
of the compensation package, of course we'll look at them. And<br />
we'll subject those observations to very rigorous testing.<br />
But there's a lot of difference between prejudice and fact you<br />
know. BUTTROSE: Yes I know that, but there are a lot facts being,<br />
are you saying that the Women's Summit was prejudiced? </p>
<p>PM: No I'm saying, no I'm not casting aspersions againsft<br />
the women that were there. I'm simply saying that a lot of<br />
people start off with a prejudice, and may I say an. understandable<br />
prejudice, against the consumption tax. They say, correctly,<br />
th-at a consumption tax is regressive, because the very low<br />
income people have to pay a much higher proportion of their<br />
income on those goods that are subject to a consumption tax,<br />
and do people like yourself and myself who are on a higher<br />
income. So there is a natural prejudice against that. But then<br />
what you've got to do is do the detail work of analysing the<br />
compensation package and saying now the compensatio~ n package<br />
which is directed to looking after the people at the low income.<br />
level, the social welfare beneficiaries, does that two<br />
billion dollars of compensation in fact overcome that<br />
disadvantage. So its no good just parading prejudices against<br />
consumption taxes you've got to engage in the tough intellectual<br />
exercise. The hard work. of examining the details of the<br />
package. Now that's what I say, if they've done their hard<br />
work, and they can demonstrate factually that the package<br />
doesn't adequately compensate, then of course we'll look at<br />
that and act accordingly. I don't that they've done that.<br />
BUTTROSE: Well clearly its going to be the Summit to end all<br />
Summits I think this one.<br />
PM: No I disagree with that entirely. People have saidL<br />
if you had your time over again you wouldn't have it. Well that's<br />
wrong i would. I believe that what we've done as a Government<br />
has been the right thing to do. We've accepted the challenge<br />
of analysing the present system, in a way that it has never been<br />
analysed before. We put that before the people, and we say now<br />
here are various avenues which we as a society can move down<br />
to get a better, fairer more efficient tax-system. Now, we will<br />
then expose ourselves to the community and say well look tell us<br />
what you think. And I'm sure that out of that process we are<br />
much more likely to get a tax system which is acceptable and<br />
workable. Not only have no regrets about the Summit, the more<br />
that its going ahead the more I'm sure its the right thing to do.<br />
BUTTROSE: I suppose in a sense Andrew Peacock could be regarded<br />
as a strength.<br />
PM: As a what?<br />
BUTTROSE He could be regarded as a strength. Because I don't<br />
see much opposition coming forward from the Liberal Party.<br />
And this morning Andrew Peacock said, if I can quote, " Hawke is<br />
a man who no longer has a clear blueprint, and a schedule<br />
for his programmes. A man who has lost any common purpose, if<br />
he had one, in terms of leading his Party, and has therefore<br />
lost authority in the leadership of his Party."<br />
PM: Well no-one takes any notice of Mr Peacock. * But let<br />
me, and I regard him as an irrelevancy of course, but let me<br />
make some observations in regard to what he said. The reason<br />
that we are in this position of having a Tax Summit is because </p>
<p>the Party of which he was a leading member has been in control<br />
for thirty cf the last thirty-five years as the Government of<br />
this country, and the fact that we have a tax system which is<br />
recognised as the worst in the western world is a reliection<br />
upon the lack of vision, principle, authority of the<br />
Governments of which he was a part. Governments in which<br />
I might say he was conspicuous by the absence of his contribution<br />
to any areas of economic thinking at all. Now, that's the first<br />
point. This Government under my leadership has the responsibility<br />
of fixing up the mess that we've inherited from thirty years<br />
of Peacock type governments. And the second point I make, is<br />
this, that Commissioner Costigan in 1981, in his report to<br />
Mr Peacock's Government, the Government of which he was a member,<br />
Commissioner Costigan said that in the last five years, that<br />
is from ' 76 to ' 81, the fastest growing industry in Australia<br />
was the tax avoidance and evasion industry. In other words,<br />
under the Government of which Mr Peacock was a prominent member,<br />
they allowed the ordinary tax payers of Australia to be bulked<br />
of billions and billions of dollars because they allowed the<br />
tax avoiders and evaders to get away with blue murder at the<br />
expense of the ordinary people of Australia. No wonder he won't<br />
come to the Summit he couldn't come with clean hands. He would<br />
be laughed out of court. So if you're going to have people<br />
judging the credibility of political leaders in the area of<br />
tax, Mr Peacock doesn't even get to the starting line.*<br />
BUTTROSE: Prime Minister I know we're coming to the end of the<br />
time, that you have to return to Cabinet, but just very quickly<br />
I'd just like to ask your reaction to the Builders Labourers<br />
Federation, well the long running campaign iI about to undertake<br />
to free Norm Gallagher.<br />
PM: The processes of the law have been properly followed.<br />
I agree with the position of Premier John Cain.<br />
BUTTROSE: Do you think that the Builders who were involved<br />
in the case should have been dealt with more severely as<br />
some BLF supporters are saying.<br />
PM: Well I'm not here to interfere with the processes<br />
of the law. I mean one can have -tviews about apparently different<br />
standards. All I'm saying is that I agree with the position of<br />
Premier Cain. The processes of the law have been followed,<br />
oind there should not be interference by Government in those<br />
processes. BUTTROSE: Thank you very much for talking with us this morning.<br />
PM: TMh. a nk you Itta and all the best. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
