<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5664</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE ACT DIVISION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005664.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8: 30PM -7<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVZ i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 12 OCTOBER 1981<br />
ADDRESS TO THE A. C. T. DIVISION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY<br />
This is the first time I have spoken to the ACT Division<br />
since the death of John Knight and I want to pay tribute again<br />
to his contribution to this Division, and the development<br />
and identity of Canberra itself. His successor in the Senate,<br />
Margaret Reid, is obviously going to make her own very significant<br />
contribution, and I am only sorry that it had to be in this<br />
way that Margaret came to join the Parliamentary Party. I<br />
want to say a few things tonight about developments and prospects<br />
here in Canberra and then turn to some of the differences<br />
between our Party and Labor.<br />
It is almost exactly a year since the last election, and it<br />
is vastly important that the community should recognise the<br />
disastrous and di vsive impact that a Labor Government would<br />
have on prosperity and stability. Let me start here with<br />
Canberra, where there is apparently no Labor policy whatever,<br />
because the Shadow Minister has managed his Shadow portfolio<br />
in such a shadowy way that he has hardly asked a question<br />
or put out a public statement about the ACT. What sort of<br />
enthusiasm is this for the welfare of the people of Canberra?<br />
It is in fact a very simple example of the Labor Party's typical<br />
refusal to accept the responsibility which a democratic systen<br />
requires of politicians, and it is symptomatic of something that<br />
was so evident in the Whitlam years, that a Labor Government<br />
will never accept the discipline of governing in the interests<br />
of'all, because no Labor Government can ever submerge the<br />
inherently sectional interests of the Labor Party itself.<br />
We must never let this country forget the inherent weakness of<br />
Labor not only in its socialistic approach to policy-making,<br />
not only in the factionalism and left-wing union domination<br />
that always divides the Labor Party internally, but in Labor's<br />
refusal to accept the obligation of the national Government to<br />
govern in the interests of the whole nation,<br />
of every Australian and every Australian family, not just<br />
those who vote for it, not just those who provide financial<br />
support for it, not just those in ideological sympathy with it,<br />
and not just those who control the votes in caucus.. Labor<br />
abdicates responsibility for many parts of society as the attitude<br />
of the Shadow Minister for the ACT so plainly reveals. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
By contrast, Michael Hodgman as Minister is obviously extremely'<br />
effective and dedicated in his concern for the interests of<br />
Canberra. Canberra is a great national capital, and I strongly<br />
support Michael's campaign to promote the widest appreciation<br />
that Canberra belongs to all Australians. We want a<br />
substantial impetus to tourism, and the Minister and the<br />
Government have been active in several wider initiatives<br />
as well in connection with Canberra achieving a stronger<br />
private sector.<br />
The new Parliament House has captured the imagination not<br />
just of Canberra but of the whole of Australia and even<br />
the Labor Senator for the ACT concedes that Canberra's building<br />
industry will be better as a result of this year's Budget.<br />
The future is good, the opportunities for investment are there.<br />
Private enterprise is joining in a partnership which is making<br />
Canberra one of the finest national capitals in the world.<br />
The forty odd world leaders at the Commonwealth meeting<br />
recognised the fine quality of Canberra as Australia's capital,<br />
and the weekend retreat here was successful in terms of<br />
the. enjoyment and friendliness experienced by our visitors as<br />
well as in the productive results of the discussions.<br />
Turning now to national policy, I want to say something about<br />
economic management and industrial relations, because these<br />
vital areas highlight the differences between our approaches<br />
to government.<br />
First of all I want to make a few comments about the economy,<br />
and the link between economic Dmanagement and taxation policy.<br />
The Liberal policy of encouraging private enterprise as the<br />
best way to achieve higher living standards and more jobs is now<br />
recognised here and around the world as extraordinarily<br />
successful. Inflation has been kept below world<br />
levels. 237,000 new jobs were created by private enterprise<br />
in the two years to June. The latest unemployment statistics,<br />
while showing a seasonal fluctuation, were the lowest<br />
September rate for four years, and unemployment among young<br />
people is down on last year. Only one thing can undermine<br />
the Australian economy, the scandalous disregard of many of<br />
the most powerful unions for those out of work, and their<br />
attempt to steal all the benefits of growth for their own<br />
members who have jobs. Look at the $ 33 a week maximum<br />
increase which storemen and packers in Victoria<br />
gained last week through industrial pressure, and the<br />
massive claims being made by metal industry workers,<br />
builders labourers, building tradesmen, meat workers and others.<br />
Unreasonable wage claims will undoubtedly prevent employers<br />
taking on new employees, and can only push up unemployment<br />
at a time when the rest of the community recognises the need<br />
to support policies aimed at real job creation. We must keep<br />
our costs down so that we can sell more Australian made goods<br />
here and overseas. That is the way to generate more jobs and<br />
better living standards for all Australians. </p>
<p>3<br />
The campaign of job destruction by militant unions now getting<br />
under way is very bad news for Australia's young people.<br />
The failure of the Labor Party to stand up and speak out<br />
against this campaign, and in favour of the national interest,<br />
represents by what is not said an endorsement of irresponsible<br />
union behaviour. Excessive wage demands and strikes are just<br />
as damaging to the community, and reflect exactly the same<br />
Santi-social rejection of obligations to the community, as do<br />
those . tax-avoidance schemes which John Howard has fought against<br />
so effectively, and with such grudging support from Labor.<br />
I am advised that the new Section 260 is getting rid of tax<br />
avoidance, and that the anti-social tax avoidance industry which<br />
Labor did nothing-about whatever, is now shrinking back.<br />
Not one intitiative taken by the union movement at its recent<br />
congress did anything which would help create more jobs for<br />
the unemployed, and the Labor Party as usual prefers not to<br />
criticise the powerful unions which control it. At the<br />
recent ACTU Conference at a time when we as a government had such<br />
an effective and practical consultation process actually in<br />
operation with the ACTU, we had the spectacle of the Parliamentary<br />
Labor Party and its leader pleading for a special sort of<br />
understanding and trust with the union movement, trying to get<br />
the so-called " social contract" and getting no joy whatever<br />
out the of the union movement. I want to take a moment to<br />
lay the ghostof any suggestion that a special deal between the<br />
Labor Party and the unions could be regarded as a social contract<br />
for whatever else the social contract may have been in the minds<br />
of philosophers it was never a sectional idea that took no<br />
account of the views or interests of three quarters of the<br />
population, and no traditional philosopher was ever foolish<br />
enough to imagine that. the social contract could be anything<br />
but a fiction.<br />
Labor has learnt nothing about economic management since 1975.<br />
It is because Labor has learnt nothing that Australia must not<br />
forget w. hat the Whitlam years and the Hayden economic policy<br />
disasters w. ere like. Private sector employment was<br />
actually falling in 1975 and the trend towards more and more<br />
entrenched unemployment, for which Labor was primarily<br />
responsible, has taken years to around. Business investr. ent<br />
fell, foreign investment fell by two-thirds in two years, and<br />
resource development virtually ceased altogether. Home<br />
ownership was lower in 19.76 than in 1971.<br />
The records were in inflation, which reached almost 18% over<br />
one year, in' the absurd wage rises which did so much to<br />
entrench unemployment, such as the increase of 38% in Federal<br />
. aardw ages in the year to March 1975, and in industrial unrest,<br />
with 6.2 million working days lost in 1974, compared with<br />
3.3 million in 1980. I do not believe that anyone realised<br />
at the time the full extent of the damage to Australia's<br />
economy when we came to power in 1975. ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
The damage certainly took years longer to retrieve and reverse<br />
* than we anticipated. For example, the 1975 Budget deficit of-<br />
$ 2.8 billion ran out to $ 3.6 billion in-spite of the expenditure<br />
cuts, amounting to hundreds of millions of dollars, which we<br />
made immediately on assuming office.<br />
Let me add that at that Labor rate, this year's deficit would<br />
be almost $ 7.5 billion, instead of which the Budget has<br />
virtually eliminated the deficit altogether, but Australians<br />
are even no%-experiencing in a significant way indeed the<br />
damaging consequences' of labor's mismanagement, because the<br />
loans that had to be raised to fund those deficits still<br />
need to be rolled over and renewed, and so they continue to<br />
exert pressure on capital markets, on interest rates and on the<br />
availability of funds for home buyers, farmers-and small<br />
business. In a number of areas, our policies have taken years to bear<br />
fruit, for in economic policy as in so many other spheres<br />
there are long lead times, and in a number of areas it is<br />
only in the last year or* two that the outcomes have started<br />
to reflect the full benefits of sound economic management.<br />
Last year, for exanile, average weekly earnings increased<br />
by more than 4 in real terms. That gain is -reflected in an<br />
increase off $ 2.7 billion, after tax, in the real<br />
disposable income of: households throughout Australia, and<br />
since 1973/ 79, average ' Weekly earnings have increased in<br />
real termns by almost $ 10. Our policies have as their<br />
principal objectives increasing the ability of the economy<br />
to pay higher real wages through economnic growth and reducing<br />
the burde:-n of taxat1ion.<br />
Let me sa7: so: mething about the sales tax increases in the<br />
Budget, because it is important to understand the underlying<br />
objectives 3f getting rid of the deficit, of reduced pressure<br />
on interest rates, of a better balance in the * tax mix, and of<br />
an enhanced potential for personal income tax reductions.<br />
The Govermment regards these objectives as having overriding<br />
importance, precisely because we in the Liberal Party are<br />
dedicated to reducing the burden of taxation and costly<br />
government. And Mr Hayden's very different attitude on the<br />
tax issue, the fact that he is, as he was once incautious<br />
enough to say, a ' high tax man', is clear enough if we look<br />
at what he actually had to say in his speech in connection<br />
with his opposition to these sales tax increases. Because<br />
we do not find him saying that he would have foregone the<br />
increase to government revenue, we find him saying that he<br />
would have instituted an entirely new kind of tax.<br />
It is also worth looking back to what Mr Hayden said on<br />
a previous occasion when the Government did something in the<br />
sales tax area, and I am referring to the 1978 reduction from<br />
27 %* to 15% in sales tax on passenger motor v * ehicles, because<br />
on that occasion the Leader of the opposition, while supporting<br />
this and favouring some other revenue reductions, said he would<br />
have imposed two entirely new kinds oE tax instead, one of thom<br />
a capital gains tax. </p>
<p>Let there be no doubt in anyone's mind that it is the<br />
Opposition which favours a high tax burden on the people<br />
-and the productive enterprises of this country, because<br />
they are the big spending party in Australia. If we had<br />
continued to spend as much as Labor did of each dollar<br />
produced in Australia, Commonwealth spending in this<br />
year's Budget would be $ 3.7 billion higher than it is.<br />
Our expenditure restraint has been impressive by any standards<br />
especially in view of the increased demands placed on the<br />
Budget by Defence requirements and the needs of an ageing<br />
population, for the average real growth in outlays of just<br />
over 1% between 1975-76 and this year not only compares very<br />
well with the Labor average of over 10%, but it also stands<br />
in stark contrast to the comparable figures of nearly 3%<br />
for West Germany, about 5% for the United States, and over<br />
for Jaran, countries which have themselves been trying<br />
to restrain government spending.<br />
Not only does Mr Hayden want his new tax, but he still<br />
wants to keep on making the future pay for the Government<br />
U spending schemes of yesterday and today. He still favours<br />
deficit financing and the ' mild domestic deficit' which he<br />
came out supporting in his speech on the Budget must mean<br />
an overall Budget deficit of around $ 2 billion this year,<br />
and this just highlighzs once again that Labor has learnt<br />
none of the lessons which were so plain to see during its<br />
earlier ceriod of eccnomic mismanagement.<br />
This $ 2 billion deficit would mean more government loans,<br />
more pressure on capital markets and-interest rates, and<br />
extra comzezition. for people looking for home loans. It is<br />
important to realise all borrowings, both government and<br />
private, ultimately come from the same pool of funds and<br />
that the funds borrowed to fund a $ 2 billion Labor deficit<br />
could be translated into 70,000 or 80,000 home loans.<br />
I wonder if i have got a minute to say something about CHOGM<br />
not only because of its importance in the whole pattern of<br />
international negotiations in search of a more stable and<br />
prosperous world, and not only because the success of CHOGM<br />
would again display in the clearest way the absurd and<br />
disgraceful attitude of the present Labor leadership to<br />
Australia's place in the world and our responsibilities<br />
to other nations, but rather because so many of our visitors<br />
said such good things about Australia, and I think we are<br />
entitled topride ourselves on the fact that our self-confidence<br />
as a nation has been so widely noticed by so many of the<br />
distinguised overseas leaders who attended the Commonwealth<br />
meeting. Pierre Trudeau in fact went so far as to say that the twentieth<br />
century can be said to belong to Australia, " because this country,<br />
with its tremendous economic potential, with its exciting<br />
technological and natural resources, with its intense and<br />
vibrant culture, seems to be very much part of the definition<br />
and formulation of the twentieth century as it's meant to be". / 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
I have picked out Trudeau's particular words, but lots of other<br />
leaders and journalists said very similar things. And<br />
these words are right. They are right about Australia, and<br />
about the Liberal Party's attitude to Australia. But<br />
nobody would have said those words in 1975, under Labor,<br />
and we must make sure that Labor does not have the opportunity<br />
to destroy their truth again. oOo---<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
