<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20896</transcript-id>
    <title>Health Care Reform  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/08/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I attach an outline paper I circulated to premiers and chief ministers regarding a process for health care reform.</p>
<p>I assured premiers and chief ministers that all seven areas of reform raised in a paper circulated by them would be included.</p>
<p>I also assured premiers and chief ministers that any agreed reforms could be implemented before the expiry of the five-year Agreements.</p>
<p>Despite this, the premiers and chief ministers, led by Mr Carr, walked out of the meeting.</p>
<p>  29 August 2003</p>
<p>  __________________________________________</p>
<p>Health Reform Review</p>
<p>   The Australian Government suggested that COAG agree to commission a review over the next two years into the health system.  The purpose of this review would be:</p>
<p>- to ensure optimum efficiency and effectiveness of health service delivery for all Australians;   - to ensure best use of the funding that all jurisdictions put into health; and  - to identify barriers to  seamless service delivery for patients and recommend options to address them.</p>
<p> The review,  would be conducted within the following context:</p>
<p>- That states and territories sign the Australian Health Care Agreements for the next 5 years;   - That the principles of Medicare be maintained including access to free treatment as a public patient in a public hospital, payment of a Medicare rebate at 85% of the scheduled fee for a visit to a GP and subsidised pharmaceuticals under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme;  - That the 30% Private Health Insurance Rebate will be maintained;  - That there will be financial accountability and transparency for both Commonwealth and state and territory governments in respect of public hospital funding, as outlined in the Australian Health Care Agreements.</p>
<p>Terms of reference and details of review would be agreed by COAG out of session within two months.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
