<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10366</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN STANLEY - RADIO 2UE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010366.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
29 May 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN STANLEY RADIO 2UE<br />
E O E<br />
STANLEY:<br />
Mr Howard, good afternoon.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Good afternoon John.<br />
STANLEY: Tell me first of all, this task force, what will it aim to achieve?<br />
STANLEY: It was a recommendation to me by Maurie Rudd and the delegation of steel workers, really to be<br />
made up of community representatives to advise me directly on some of the social as well as<br />
economic implications with a greater emphasis on the social of what is occurring in Newcastle. It<br />
was at very useful meeting. I didn't make any foolish promises that I wasn't able, I wouldn't be<br />
able to deliver. I will go to Newcastle, probably at the end of June or early in July. A number of<br />
my Ministers have already been there and we are of course matching the 10 million that the<br />
NSWA Government has made available. I guess one of the most interesting things that Mr Rudd<br />
said to me was that the steel workers of Newcastle and their families were not interested in this<br />
issue becoming a political slanging match. I think that's right. I am not going to spend the next<br />
few months berating the former Government for the situation and I think what the people of<br />
Newcastle are interested in is practical assistance not false expectations. I can't wave a magic<br />
wandI but they did put a number of ideas to me and I have undertaken to examine all of those<br />
ideas to try and get some further information and to come back to them.<br />
Newcastle is in a sense a metaphor for some of the problems we face in Australia as we go<br />
through this restructuring phase and the impact of the globalised world economy and the<br />
difficulties of areas of manufacturing industry and we have to work through what solutions we<br />
can find and I am very conscious of the social as well as the economic implications of what is<br />
happening in Newcastle and indeed what is happening around Australia in other industrial areas.<br />
STANLEY: So do you believe in globalising our economy and restructuring our economy we've actually gone<br />
too Par, that we've actually gone ahead of some of our trading partners?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
John, I don't think you have any alternative. We are a people of 18 million and if we are to<br />
sur\, ive, we have to trade, we have to sell, we have to find buyers for our products, we have to<br />
expose ourselves to competitive forces. We have to do it in a clever, intelligent way and whoever<br />
is in power in New South Wales or in Canberra is dealing with certain forces that we have to take<br />
account of Now there is always a balance to be struck and it's no good just sort of uttering<br />
phrases like industry policy and so forth without having a clear idea what you mean by that.<br />
Obviously, if you run the economy well and you have low inflation and falling interest rates you </p>
<p>encourage investment. We've had some very good investment figures over the past few days and<br />
many features of the Australian economy are very strong.<br />
STANLEY: Isn't there a perception abroad though that we've stripped away protection from our Industries<br />
and it s no longer a level playing field, that many of our competitors still have their tariffs up<br />
much higher than ours and that we're allowing people with much lower wage rates to flood the<br />
country with cheap products that are competing with those that we're making?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's the sort of statement that is sort of half right and half wrong. It is true that there are some<br />
countries whose wage levels are so low that we can't in wage terms compete with them. That's<br />
right. On the other hand, there are a lot of benefits of opening up our economy. We have been<br />
able to sell things into Asian markets that we wouldn't have dreamt of selling before. I mean, you<br />
have had industries like the dairy industry that has lost all its protection yet has now booming<br />
exports in a situation that people wouldn't have dreamt of ten years ago. I mean, I can remember<br />
as a member of the Fraser Government the dairy industry seemed to be in intensive care the whole<br />
time ihat we were in Government for seven years, yet now, without protection and without the<br />
suppo~ rt of old subsidised policies it's now quite a strong industry and we've had some market<br />
access successes in relation to other products. Manufactured exports are the fastest growing side<br />
of export markets so it's a mixed picture, John.<br />
STANLEY: Yes I chose the word carefully, I said there was a perception abroad and I just wonder if..<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Easy, I mean, it's a very understandable perception because it's an attractively simple proposition<br />
to say, protect everything, you save jobs, you keep Australian industry. Now obviously we<br />
shouldn't be foolish about it. Obviously we shouldn't try and be world leaders in cutting<br />
protection. We should be world leaders in being competitive. We should be demanding that other<br />
countries match what we do and that is a perfectly legitimate thing to do. We will face in the next<br />
little while a decision on the motor vehicle industry. We will have to make a decision in the next<br />
little while what we're going to do with the Productivity Commission report. Now that will<br />
require a fine balance and...<br />
STANLEY: Now you met some of your own backbenchers today, didn't you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We had a party meeting and it was a very good meeting and I invited people to express their<br />
views on this issue and there's a wide spectrum of views as you might understand. People who<br />
represent rural electorates traditionally don't like protection for manufacturing industry because<br />
the cost of it is borne by their constituents and Australian farmers are the least subsidised, least<br />
protected, most efficient farmers in the world and therefore they say, well if we have to survive in<br />
global markets then we don't like paying the cost of somebody else's protection. Equally,<br />
members representing Adelaide electorates and industrial electorates and of course having such a<br />
big back bench now, we represent most of the country and we're not just a party of sort of<br />
traditional conservative areas in rural Australia so it is a very, very difficult debate. It's not one<br />
that will be solved by simple slogans from Pauline Hanson, Simon Crean or indeed anybody else. </p>
<p>STANLEY:<br />
But I would have thought at the moment politically you've got her, you've got the Labor Party,<br />
the Democrats, everyone lined up against you in terms of what does seem to be politically a rise in<br />
protection of sentiment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well what we have to do is sensibly work through each situation. I mean, it is no good giving<br />
away something unless you get something in return. Also you have to recognise that some<br />
industries, no matter how much you protect them, can't survive. Now, I'm not talking about the<br />
steel industry, quite the contrary, I can't imagine this country without a strong viable steel<br />
industry and equally I can't imagine Australia without a strong viable manufacturing industry.<br />
STANLEY: So on ihe proposal to further reduce protection for the car industry you've still got an open mind?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, wie are very, you know, much looking at that thing at the moment and I don't want to<br />
disclose my thinking but can I say this, that I'll be influenced by determination to preserve a<br />
strong Australian motor manufacturing industry and I'll be very conscious of the employment<br />
situation in South Australia and I am working towards getting a policy position on that which is<br />
sensible for the whole country but also takes those two things into account. Now, people will<br />
judge the quality of that decision when it comes out.<br />
STANLEY: When wvill we get that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh, it will be fairly soon I don't want to tie myself down in the next, sort of, couple of<br />
weeks quite soon...<br />
STANLEY: I know you're juggling a few balls at the moment. Can I just ask you about cross-media<br />
ownership laws. There's a proposal reported for newspapers . or for television proprietors in the<br />
larger cities to be able to own one newspaper. Can you confirm that that's being looked at?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
A whole lot of things including that is being looked at, a whole lot of things. But some of the<br />
reports in the paper this morning were hairy but others were a little closer to the mark in terms of<br />
option. It is still something that is being talked through and talked through very carefully.<br />
There's a view that we have high levels of foreign ownership. There's also a view about<br />
diversity. One argument is that you should have a bit more diversity of ownership in the<br />
newspaper area. But we are still considering a series of options but it is something that is being<br />
debated inside the Government, not only in the Cabinet but also in the backbench committee.<br />
Media policy always involves a fair amount of debate and always generates a great deal of<br />
interest. STANLEY: Yeah, I'm just interested in the foreign ownership aspects. I think I've heard you say before you<br />
didn't think you'd entertain any increase in foreign ownership. Are you now a bit more flexible in<br />
allowing perhaps.. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, [ don't want to pre-emptive as to what we might do. I mean, obviously there are quite<br />
high levels of foreign ownership and the aggregate level of foreign ownership in the media is<br />
something that everybody would want to keep an eye on. But we are looking at a range of<br />
options. STANLEY:<br />
But with the possibility of increasing 15% to 25% foreign ownership<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't want to either confirm or deny that.<br />
STANLEY: Okay. Can I just ask you just one other thing. There is a suggestion this morning, and certainly<br />
the events in the Senate, don't all go well for your 10 Point Plan on Wik would you consider a<br />
double dissolution on that issue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh look, I'm hoping that the Senate will support the plan, I really do. Because it's the only way<br />
out of this awful dilemma. I mean, we can't leave the Native Title Act as it is. With the best will<br />
in the world towards the Aboriginal community, and I really do mean that, the Wik decision went<br />
far beyond what anybody expected, even the Aborigines. They didn't expect the High Court<br />
would say that pastoral leases and native title might co-exist.<br />
STANLEY: You wouldn't relish fighting an election on it though would you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't want to, sort of, pre-empt what we're going to do. I mean, I hope your question is<br />
hypothetical. I want to resolve this issue by getting our legislation accepted but equally I can't<br />
have it hacked around by the Senate so that it becomes unworkable. Now, I don't want to start<br />
talking about what might happen if it's knocked back. I still hope to persuade the Labor Party to<br />
see the sense of supporting our 10 points. I mean, the Labor Party must think very hard about<br />
this and put aside emotional arguments and just think very hard what is the sense in the Labor<br />
Party blocking something that will end some of the uncertainty. I mean, we have rejected blanket<br />
extinguishment. I mean, you saw me got to Longreach in Queensland and argue the merits and<br />
resist some of the pressure that was being put on me on blanket extinguishment and I've said no<br />
to that. And equally I have to say with the best will in the world to the Aboriginal community<br />
that the 10 Point Plan preserves all of the principles of native title. It does represent less than<br />
what they got from the High Court in Wik. I don't make any bones about that. But I think and I<br />
believe the community thinks that Wik went too far and you've got to pull the pendulum back and<br />
that really is what the 10 Point Plan does.<br />
STANLEY: Just on the Stolen Generation Report I think you're going to have a formal response in about a<br />
month is there still a possibility that you'll consider the recommendation there for a more formal<br />
apology? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look John, our situation is that we have said we're not supportive of compensation and may I<br />
make the point that the Labor Party, when it was in power, chose to fight the case in the High </p>
<p>Court claiming compensation in relation to children who'd been removed in the Northern<br />
Territory the so-called Kruger case and all of the facts of that would have been known to the<br />
government of the day. We're going to look at all of the recommendations and we're going to<br />
give a considered response.<br />
STANLEY:<br />
Just on the formal apology part though, is that still a possibility?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, look, there are... we're looking at all of the recommendations. We've made it very, very<br />
clear that we're not supportive of compensation and in that sense we're exactly the same as what<br />
the Labor Party was when it was in government. I don't really want to go any further.<br />
STANLEY:<br />
Okay. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I noted incidentally that Sir Ronald Wilson, the Chairman of the Human Rights Commission, said<br />
today that he understood that it was a very big report and that the Government had to give a<br />
considered response. It is a very difficult issue. I have read very large sections of that report and<br />
it is gripping. It's very depressing. It's very disturbing reading. On the other hand, as I've said,<br />
the notion that our generation should begin to accept legal liability and liability for the deeds of<br />
earlier generations, particularly if they were sanctioned by law, opens us up into a whole<br />
new... well, I mean, where does it end? Do you start getting people who are in adoption situations<br />
bringing claims for breaches of their human rights? I mean, there has to come a time when you've<br />
got to focus on the future and the best way that we can help people who were affected by those<br />
things is to help them now and into the future. And there are a lot of recommendations in the<br />
report which are directed towards and I would imagine that in those areas...<br />
STANLEY: I think we're out of time Mr Howard. I appreciate your time. Thank you very much.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Okay. j </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
