<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40765</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Netanyahu’s visit to Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am looking forward, with Lucy, to welcoming the Prime Minister of Israel, Benjamin Netanyahu, and his wife, Mrs Sara Netanyahu, to Australia.</p>
<p>This is a historic visit - the first by an Israeli Prime Minister - and it demonstrates the strength of our relationship and its importance to both countries.</p>
<p>The friendship between Israel and Australia dates back to the establishment of Israel in 1948. It is anchored in our shared values, commitment to democracy and mutual interest in a rules-based international system and an open, global economy.</p>
<p>Later this year we will jointly commemorate the 100th anniversary of the Battle of Beersheba, a foundation stone of the relationship.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister’s visit is an opportunity to not only reflect on our shared past, but to invigorate and further deepen the relationship for the benefit of our people. We will discuss expanding cooperation in cyber-security, innovation and science, agritech, energy and resources, and the environment.</p>
<p>During the visit, our countries will sign an agreement on Technological Innovation and Research and Development, providing a framework for our scientists, engineers and businesses to create the jobs and industries of the future. We will also sign an agreement on Air Services, expanding our commercial and people-to-people links.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Netanyahu and Mrs Netanyahu will spend 22-25 February in Australia. They will be accompanied by a delegation of business leaders from Israel. I look forward to working with them to further strengthen ties between our countries.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
