<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7434</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007434.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 16 NOVEMBER 1988<br />
I am very pleased to announce that the President of Greece,<br />
His Excellency Christo Sartzetakis, will make a State visit<br />
to Australia in our Bicentennial year. He will be in<br />
Australia from 22-28 November 1988 and will visit the<br />
Australian Capital Territory, Victoria and New South Wales.<br />
I welcome this visit by President Sartzetakis as an<br />
opportunity to strengthen, the already close and friendly<br />
relations which exist between the peoples of Australia and<br />
Greece. This relationship is founded on a common commitment<br />
to democracy, shared historical experiences in time of war,<br />
and strong community and personal ties between our two<br />
countries. The Greek community has become one of the<br />
largest and most active ethnic communities in Australia and<br />
Greek Australians have made invaluable contributions to the<br />
development of our flourishing multicultural society, across<br />
the full range of Australian economic, political and<br />
cultural life.<br />
The President's visit will also serve to celebrate the<br />
magnificent contribution of Greek Australians to Australia's<br />
Bicentenary. A highlight of his visit will occur on 24<br />
November when the President opens the Exhibition of<br />
Macedonian Antiquities in Melbourne. This exhibition the<br />
largest of its sort ever to leave Greece is the valued<br />
gift of the Greek Government to Australia and I look forward<br />
to being in Melbourne to attend its opening.<br />
While in Canberra, President Sartzetakis and his wife will<br />
stay at Government House as guests of their Excellencies the<br />
Governor-General and Lady Stephen. He will meet the<br />
Premiers and Governors of New South Wales and Victoria when<br />
he visits those States as well as meeting members of the<br />
Greek community. The President will be accompanied-during<br />
his visit by the Greek minister in charge of International<br />
organisations, Mr Christos Marcopoulos, and the Greek<br />
minister for Macedonia and Thrace, Mr Stylianos-Angelos<br />
Papathemelis.' 3487 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
