<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2595</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY DINNER - DEAKIN ELECTORATE, VIC - 15 MAY 1972 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002595.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBAR-O 8.00 p. m. 1S/ 5/ 72 CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
LIBERAL PARTY DINNER<br />
DEAKIN ELECTORATE , Vic. M4AY 1972<br />
Spee ch by the Prime Minister, The Rt Hon.<br />
William M~ ctahon, M. P.<br />
Mr President, J-! r Alain Jarman, Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
Thank you for comning along tonight and for gi'ing me the<br />
chance to talk to you for a few minut~ es, and to join forces with my<br />
colleague, Alan Jarman, in getting the Liberal message across to the<br />
people in this election year.<br />
We depend Qfl you to heln us do that. You are closest to<br />
the voting public and therefore in a good position to " sell" the<br />
Government's policies, and also give us in Canberra a " feedback" on<br />
what people are thinking.<br />
I see the Labor Party has got a haberdiasher slogan called-<br />
" It's Time" Well, true enough it is time time for the mask to<br />
be ripped off Labor pretensions and policies. Time for Liberals to<br />
be out in the market place telling the Australian pEiple what they<br />
have been doing as the major party in Government in the last twelve<br />
months or'so. If we all get down to this task and press on with it,<br />
enthusiastically and energetically, then later in the year I have no<br />
doubt it will be the Labor Party " for whom the bell tolls" 9<br />
I am confident that the policies we are putting forward are<br />
honest, open for all to see, and in the best interests of the people<br />
of Australia. Now, Mr President, the-: re is one theme that I want to<br />
give some time to tonight, because it is importanit to all Liberals,<br />
important to the Government as the voice of the people, and imrnortant<br />
to the people themselves as individuals in a free society. I refer<br />
to " freedom within the law' in our community.<br />
Most Australians are " fed up to the back teeth" with disorderly<br />
demonstrations like those in Melbourne and other cities last<br />
week. This isn't freedom of sneech and of assembly two ideals<br />
Liberals hold dear. Those disorderly demonstrati. ons involve unbridled<br />
licence by the few illegal in therrselves but dangerous to all. It<br />
is anarchy by a militant, subversive few who inflame thoughtless<br />
people and are encouraged too much by some sections of the L~ abor Party.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>Last week's events were more than just another demonstration<br />
that got out of hand. They were a symntod of a sickness in some parts of<br />
our society which left wing elements and Labor politicians are promoting.<br />
Naturally, I was delighted to see Henry Boltetaking a firm stand about<br />
these events. As Liberals we have a duty to take our stand in support<br />
of the law. Demonstrations in Melbourne were once promoted only by the<br />
hard-core communists and a few fellow= travellers, but in the last year<br />
or two the left-wing unions and Labor noliticians have added their weight.<br />
This, now, is exploding into a serious challenge to the authority of the law<br />
keener-+* h ~ viice-and the authority of Covernments-Gommonwealth and State<br />
The clearest demonstration of this occurred during the recent Springboks<br />
Tour when the A. C. T. U. President and certain Labor Politicians openly<br />
inspired mass disruption. There was no industrial motive for their actions.<br />
Indeed there was no really genuine nolitical . motive. It was attemoted.<br />
anarchy for anarchy's sake.<br />
We in the Liberal Party stand for the freedom of the individual<br />
and for free enterprise. We believe it is the duty of the Government to<br />
exercise the authority within the law I repeat within the law vested<br />
in it by the Australian people.<br />
That is why, for example, we have taken action against draft<br />
dodgers We believe Australian citizens have the right to go about<br />
their business. In Melbourne, or Blackburn or anywhere else in Australia<br />
without being interfered with by dangerous demonstrations. Ordinary<br />
decent people, the great majority of Australians have every right to<br />
expect their Government to act in their interests.<br />
I want to put this matter in perspective. I am sure that the<br />
majority of people like my Government, respect absolutely the right of<br />
dissenters to dissent, and the right of demonstrators to demonstate.<br />
But it must be within the Law We support South Vietnam. Our soldiers<br />
fought there with great courage. We are still helping with training<br />
even though our troops are home. We support the latest action by the<br />
United States. Why? because it is honourable and right, and because<br />
we are opposed to aggression. Yet what do we see on the other side of<br />
the political fence?<br />
Support for North Vietnam has been given by the Labor Party<br />
here in this state. Support for an aggressor, ecposed for all to see.<br />
No longer can the Labor Party talk nonsense about the war being an<br />
internal rebellion or civil war and therefore nobody's business.<br />
Let's look at another exaxple of the false and dangerous values<br />
of our opponents. They have declared themselves against compulsory<br />
National Service. We, the Liberals are for it because there is no other<br />
way of keeping our armed forces up to the strength required to meet our<br />
defence obligations to the Australian people. The Labor Party has always<br />
said it would scrap National Service. That would be mark you a<br />
political not a defence decision. But in the last day or two they have<br />
started to talk with two voices and adopt two standards. Perhaps they<br />
wouldn't scrap it right away. Or perhaps they would. Who knows? And<br />
perhaps they wouldn't pull out of the five-power defence arrangements in<br />
Singapore-Malaysia; Or perhaps they would. They have always said so<br />
until recently! Well, who knows? / 3 </p>
<p>I mention these matters because these are at the heart<br />
of the demonstrations which have been bringing chaos to the streets<br />
of our capital cities. The Australian people must judge for<br />
themselves, the degree to whichi demonstration and violence would<br />
grow worse with a Labor Government looking with a benevolent eye on<br />
the law-breakers the draft resisters the violent demonstators<br />
and the aggressors against friendly countries.<br />
My Government wants to minimise the divisions within the<br />
Australian community not to enlarge and inflame them. We want the<br />
Australian people to know we stand for respect for the Law. In the<br />
face of the challenge that is so clearly aimed at the Government by<br />
militants and some Labor-inspired agitators.<br />
We have had economic difficulties as a major preoccupation<br />
in this past year. We have been quick to react to changing condition.<br />
In the months ahead I am confident we will make steady, solid progress<br />
which will prove to be the justification of everything we have done<br />
in the past year. I ask you to join me now in nreparing apd working<br />
for a handsome election win. You have your part to play in securing<br />
that victory. Let us do it together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
