<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9768</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 27 SEPTEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009768.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
17<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 27 SEPTEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well, we have seen Mr Howard, the old Mr Howard. It took a while for<br />
us to take the layers of new political clothes from him, but there he is<br />
just as he always was: without ideas and without principle. He is now<br />
going to strike down, if he can, the largest change to the micro<br />
economy in the State of NSW and, for tourism and air transport, the<br />
largest change in Australia in the last 20 years, the third runway in<br />
Sydney. This is the runway that he enjoined this Government to build<br />
for years and for years. This is the runway he said was not being built<br />
because of political cynicism on the part of members of the Labor<br />
Party in seats around Sydney airport. It has now been built, he now<br />
wants to cut its capacity dramatically by again opening the cross wind<br />
east-west runway which would mean a dramatic increase in the risk<br />
factor of aircraft intersecting a downwind runway and at the same time<br />
dramatically cutting the capacity of the airport. This would have flow<br />
on effects to Melbourne and Brisbane and the whole east coast grid of<br />
airline connections.<br />
It means that all of his rhetoric about micro economic reform which we<br />
have had ad nauseam, how he will be the tough guy, that will hop into<br />
the waterfront, he is the tough guy that is going to hop into the unions,<br />
he is the tough guy that is going to hop into the seafarers. When it<br />
comes to one micro economic change, and a big one, he starts to<br />
backslide on years of statements by himself for a handful of votes in<br />
his own seat of Bennelong. We hear these headland speeches, as the<br />
Minister for Transport said in the House this morning, the only.<br />
headland he is interested in is the one between Lane Cove and<br />
Woolwich the one that worries him about his three per cent margin in<br />
the seat of Bennelong.<br />
So, here he is saying I am the new John Howard, I have been<br />
airbrushed, my old past has been airbrushed away, I am a new person<br />
but when it comes to the first test, even as Opposition Leader, I don't<br />
think I can pass it, I don't think I can support the Government in a<br />
policy I have supported for years.<br />
To add insult to injury, bad enough that he puts asunder this micro<br />
economic reform, he wants to stamp his foot and abuse his powers in </p>
<p>the Senate by tugging away at $ 2 billion of the budget by pulling the<br />
Kingsford-Smith airport sale out of the sale of the FAC airports. As the<br />
Minister for Transport made clear yesterday, there is no way that<br />
people are bid for the other smaller investments until the big one<br />
Kingsford-Smith and Badgery's Creek are settled first.<br />
So, if Mr Howard refuses passage of the Bill before Christmas, it<br />
means that the budget will miss out on a $ 2 billion change, $ 2 billion<br />
which has produced the surplus and it will be all at the hands of John<br />
Howard. I hope the business community are looking at all this because it is no<br />
accident that he left the likes of me and other ministers to do all the<br />
dirty work of the 1980s that he left behind. He wanted to float the<br />
Australian dollar, but he never got around to it. He wanted to<br />
deregulate the banking system, but he never got around to it. He<br />
wanted to free up the labour market, but he never got around to it. He<br />
wanted to remove the tariff wall, but he never got around to it. He<br />
wanted to improve the micro economy, but he never got around to it.<br />
And now, when we have got around to it and got around to it on this<br />
important feature of aviation he says " No, I'm not having it, I want the<br />
cross wind runway open", and even though he knows it will cut the<br />
traffic volumes by nearly half, he says, " that is all right providing I am<br />
safer in the seat of Bennelong."<br />
This guy is not fit to be Prime Minister. He is not fit to lead a major<br />
party and you don't need my claims about that, you have got it right in<br />
front of your eyes over night.<br />
J: You mentioned the business community, what about the local<br />
community which feels that your government has created an<br />
intolerable situation for them in their daily lives?<br />
PM: We have got now the largest noise abatement program anywhere in<br />
the world. What we are seeking to do is to immunise those areas from<br />
the airport noise. But, as Mr Howard's own the Mayor of Hunters<br />
Hill said rather eloquently yesterday, if they were to put light aircraft<br />
even on the tail end of the east west runway they will take them out of<br />
the main parallel runways which will only then fill up with larger wide<br />
bodied aircraft which will only compound their noise.<br />
PM: The other thing is the Government has made, I think, very important<br />
changes now, all the aircraft do take off from the end of the seaward<br />
runway, if they are taking off to the north. And by the time they get<br />
over Hunters Hill and these other places, they have got 3000 or 4000<br />
feet under them, and this has made a very great difference.<br />
J: People are still very angry, though, do you accept that this is a<br />
dangerous political issue for you, and that John Howard could be just<br />
playing smart politics here? </p>
<p>PM: Well, if you think that tugging away at the largest micro-economic<br />
change, destroying the largest micro-economic in Civil Aviation in the<br />
last quarter century, and knocking $ 2 billion out of the Budget is smart<br />
politics, I don't.<br />
J: Is it a dangerous....<br />
PM: lI think it is a dangerous issue for him so dangerous, I think, it has<br />
really painted him as he really is. I mean, Howard in policy terms has<br />
never amounted to a row of beans. I know that, because I have had to<br />
do amongst others most of the work in areas he had former<br />
responsibility. And what he is showing you again is that no matter how<br />
much he has been air-brushed by Andrew Robb and the Liberal Party,<br />
and how much the Liberal Party want to make him over as a New Age<br />
person, he is the same tired, old character cynical character that he<br />
always was.<br />
J: Do you accept that this issue is hurting you, electorally?<br />
PM: No. I think the Government Governments that do things the nation<br />
needs are generally rewarded. The nation needed this change, and<br />
the Government put it into place.<br />
J: Prime Minister, you say he has been air-brushed, too, on IR what is<br />
your IR message to workers for the election?<br />
PM: My IR message is that we're now in the lowest level of industrial<br />
disputes since we have been keeping the records they are one-sixth<br />
of what they were in the late 80s, we have had a fair wages system<br />
which has made Australia competitive, but given Australia high<br />
employment and fair wage outcomes, and all the protection's that<br />
working people can only get under the award system. We have given<br />
them flexibility with protection, and this will go under a Coalition<br />
Government.<br />
J: What about wages? Will they cut wages?<br />
PM: The Coalition the result of their policies will be substantial cuts in<br />
wages for Australians as they lose, without compensation, penalty<br />
rates, overtime and other elements of the wage package. Because<br />
there will be no guarantee and when pressed, Mr Reith, their<br />
spokesman, always falls back on the same expression: " We will be<br />
keeping Federal awards". But, that's not a choice that is going to be<br />
made available to the 1.7 million people a year who either join the<br />
workforce for the first time, or change their jobs. 43% of Australians<br />
changed their jobs in the last 3 years. That means that 43% of<br />
Australians will have no award protection under a Coalition<br />
Government.<br />
J: But workers still see executive salary increases going through the roof<br />
all the Government does is criticise them, what do you intend to do<br />
about that? </p>
<p>4<br />
PM: The Government does criticise them, and executives who take these<br />
decisions know they they induce a problem in their own companies<br />
under an enterprise bargaining system. All of this is noticed by the<br />
workforce. But executive salaries are not set in any Industrial tribunal,<br />
and therefore, the Government has no option to appeal them when<br />
these remunerative packages are set.<br />
J: Prime Minister, the temperature seems to be picking up around the<br />
place are we still looking at a poll next year?<br />
PM: That has always been my intention to stretch the Parliament out, to<br />
give the public the value they like from them.<br />
J: It still is, Prime Minister?<br />
PM: It is, indeed. And, you know, we have had... when a very high hurdle<br />
was set for the Government with the Budget, and the Government<br />
jumped it a surplus Budget without all these mooted increases in<br />
income tax and the rest instead of saying good jump, generally it was<br />
said [ that we were] " clearing the decks for an election". When the<br />
Government introduced Accord Mark VIII, pinning the inflation rate to<br />
it was said " clearing the decks for the election". When the<br />
republic framework came down, it was said " clearing the decks for the<br />
election". That was months ago, and there has been no election.<br />
What the Government is going to do here, is keep on governing, and<br />
one thing is very clear the more time we give John Howard, the more<br />
obvious we make our view known, and that is that he stands for<br />
nothing, and he represents nothing but cynicism and low principle.<br />
J: Mr Keating, there is a poll out today on Carmen Lawrence a 2-1<br />
majority now of people who think that the Carmen Lawrence affair is a<br />
witchhunt do you think that issue is now over as a political problem<br />
for the Government?<br />
PM: I think it's over in respect of any damage that it is likely to be doing to<br />
Carmen Lawrence, and because what matters to her matters to us, it<br />
means that, I think, most Australians think the process has been unfair.<br />
J: Is it true, Prime Minister, that you will be doing big hit policy<br />
statements?<br />
PM: No. But I'm always considering policy statements.<br />
ends. 1-:-1<br />
il'o iilaL. : ui-b </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
