<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8683</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP MCARTHUR RIVER PROJECT MOVES AHEAD</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008683.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT FROM THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
MCARTHUR RIVER PROJECT MOVES AHEAD<br />
. Mount 1I9a Mines' ( MIM) and its joint venturers' decision to<br />
sei7 cooidinated board level approval for the huge<br />
McArthur River Zinc ProJect was today welcomed by the Prime<br />
MiniterMr Keating.<br />
The Prime Minister's comments coincided with the<br />
introduction into the Northern Territory House of Assembly<br />
of the McArthur River Project Agreement Ratification Act.<br />
This Act will provide a legislative basis for the Franchise<br />
Agreement negotiated between HIM and the Northern Territory<br />
Government. Introduction of the Act represents a milestone for the<br />
McArthur River Project as all government requirements f or<br />
i-ts commencement have now been fulfilled.<br />
First discovered in 1955, the McArthur River<br />
Zinc/ Lead/ Silver Deposit is one of the world's largest, yet<br />
most remote mineral reserves. Its development will involve<br />
capital expenditure of $ 290 million and at today's zinc<br />
prices will generate annual export earnings for Australia of<br />
$ 230 million.<br />
Associated infrastructure development will provide a fillip<br />
to the neighbouring township of Borroloola while a<br />
Commonwealth Government training and employment strategy<br />
will aim to ensure that local aboriginals benefit from new<br />
job opportunities.<br />
The mine's prospects were enhanced by initiatives announced<br />
in the February " One'Nation" Statement. It is the first<br />
major project to benefit from the " fast tracking"<br />
arrangements announced in One Nation and will be one of the<br />
first to receive the Federal Government's 10 per cent<br />
special development allowance. </p>
<p>Under the One Nation Facilitation Arrangements Commonwealth<br />
environment an oeg netietapoaswere obtained a<br />
mere six months after MIM's initial approach to the<br />
Government, through the Parliamentary Secretary to the Prime<br />
Minister.<br />
Obtaining all approvals for the project so quickly would not<br />
have been possible without the total coordination of.<br />
Commonwealth and Territory processes. It is testimony to<br />
what intergovernment collaboration on projects of substance,<br />
projects of real benefit to Australia, can achieve.<br />
Indeed McArthur River has the potential to become a model of<br />
cooperation under the One Nation framework.<br />
There has been cooperation between governments on all<br />
environmental and related approvals, cooperation between<br />
governments and the project proponents, and cooperation<br />
between an Australian company, MIM, and its foreign joint<br />
venture partners in developing Australia's resources and<br />
infrastructure. The foreign joint venturers, Nippon Mining, Mitsubishi<br />
materials Corporation, Mitsui and Co and Marubeni hold<br />
interests totalling 28 per cent in the feasibility study and<br />
have options to acquire the same levels of participation in<br />
the project.<br />
The involvement in the project of these four Japanese mining<br />
giants represents a significant vote of confidence in<br />
Australia's future, and builds upon MIM's earlier commitment<br />
to participate in the development of a new zinc smelter in<br />
Japan. It represents another expansion of the mutually beneficial<br />
economic relationship Australia and Japan have developed in<br />
the post war period, a relationship I sought to further<br />
encourage with my recent visit.<br />
CANBERRA 1 October 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
