<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10231</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP ADDRESS AT NATIONAL ANGLICAN CONFERENCE EXPLORING OUR FUTURE: AUSTRALIA IN THE FAMILY OF NATIONS ANU, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010231.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 8 February 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS AT NATIONAL ANGLICAN CONFERENCE<br />
Exploring out Future: Australia in the Family of Nadtis<br />
ANU, CANBERRA<br />
OE<br />
To Archbishop Rayner, the Primate of the Anglican Church in Australia; Archbishop<br />
Harry Goodhew, the Archbishop of Sydney; to Kim Beazley, the Leader of the<br />
Opposition; ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It's quite a privilege for me to be here this morning and I want first of all to<br />
congratulate the Anglican Church in organising, what I understand to be, your first<br />
national conference. it is, if I may say so, a very sensible and forward looking move to<br />
focus the thoughts and the activities and the energies of the members of the Church on<br />
the Church's role in Australian society in the late 1990s and also to throw forward to<br />
the next millennium.<br />
The coming of a new millennium is focusing the minds of many organisations and many<br />
groups of people within Australia. I suspect that the year 2001 will be a catalyst in<br />
many ways as Australians together look towards the next century and the next<br />
millennium. And I emphasise that word together because it is important as the Primate<br />
said in his introductory remarks, that we endeavour a5 far as possible as Australians to<br />
focus on those things that unite us and bind us together rather than those things that<br />
may push us apart, Powerfiil, legitimate, partisan debate is a necessary and healthy<br />
part of the activity not only of a nation in its political dimension but also within the<br />
Churches in their spiritual and other dimensions.<br />
I also want, as Prime Minister of Australia -and I know speaking on behalf of a vast<br />
cross-section of the Australian community to express my gratitude and the gratitude<br />
of the nation for the contribution that the Anglican Church and indeed the other<br />
Christian Churches make to the life and the times of our society. And that gratitude is<br />
expressed not only in relation to the spiritual contribution that is made to the nation<br />
Faxom 08/ 02/ 97 11: 53 PS: 1 </p>
<p>Fax from~ 08/ 62/ 97 11: 53 Pg: 2<br />
and to the lives and the families within the nation, but also to the massive social and<br />
compassionate contribution that the Churches make to Australian society.<br />
Too often I think in modem times that role is forgotten and overlooked. The flaws are<br />
trivialised and emphasised. The massive ongoing compassionate contribution made by<br />
the Churches and their various agencies is greatly overlooked.<br />
Australia would be a Poorer, meaner, less hospitable, less compassionate society were<br />
it not for organisations like Anglicare, the society of St Vincent de Paul, the Salvation<br />
Army, the Wesley Mission, the Brotherhood of St Lawrence, and the list is very long<br />
and very impressive. And the contribution that those organisations make and the<br />
people within those organisations, many of whom I guess will be here or represented<br />
here today, is something that ought not to go unrernarked. Because one of the<br />
distinctive Australian traditions of which I am immensely proud, and of which all of us<br />
should be immensely proud, is that great tradition of voluntarism. And that great<br />
tradition of voluntarism is very powerfully expressed in the life and the work of the<br />
various Christian Churches.<br />
And I want to take the opportunity as the leader of the Government of Australia to<br />
record my thanks. Too often on occasions such as this thanks are not recorded and<br />
acknowledgment is not given and respect is not paid for the massive contribution that<br />
is made quite selflessly to those in our community who are less fortunate.<br />
I've been invited to share a few thoughts with you today about the role of Australia in<br />
the family of nations. I don't want to particularly address that in a political or in an<br />
economic dimension although those dimensions are immensely important and it is<br />
simply not real life to address many of the challenges that face Australia without giving<br />
pride of place to those two particular dimensions.<br />
Hut when I think of Australia's role in the family of nations I think of what the rest of<br />
the world sees of Australia and sees what Australia represents. And in trying to<br />
project Australia forward as part of the family of nations I think not just of our<br />
economic achievements, not just of our economic strengths and our political stances,<br />
but I also think of the values for which Australia stands. I think of those values that<br />
we have in common with many nations around the world.<br />
I am reminded that Australia is one of only eight nations that has been continuously<br />
democratic for the whole of the 20th century. Many nations of course lost their<br />
democracy and their freedom in the 20th century through no fault of their own. But it<br />
is no mean achievement that Australia is one of only eight nations that has retained<br />
democracy throughout the entire 20th century.<br />
Anid we share many values in common with other nations. The shared entitlement of<br />
all people to self dignity and self fujlfilment. The relevance of a common humanity.<br />
The common search for peace, and a liberal I don't mean that in a political sense but<br />
in a generic sense commitment to the worth of all people as individuals.<br />
When I think of Australia's projection to the world I think that we must see that the<br />
strength of any nation or any community does not rest alone in the strength of its </p>
<p>Fax from economy or in the wealth of its individuals. But it does rest very much in the moral<br />
strengths and the importance of values within the community.<br />
I think also when we project to the rest of the world we ought to place emphasis on<br />
those characteristics of our which are distinctively Australian are home grown and<br />
have been imported from nowhere. The emphasis we place on rnateship, on<br />
adaptability, on down to earth practicality, vitality, concern for the underdog, straight<br />
forwardness, the spirit of constructive defiance against the odds so magnificently<br />
demonstrated right at the moment in Queensland in the area in and around Charleville.<br />
I think also of the importance that we give to promoting fairness and decency and a<br />
quality of opportunity in our national life. I think sensibly we are a fuindamnentally quite<br />
sceptical people when it comes to the operations and the limits of government.<br />
Scepticism may of course present particular challenges to the evangelising and<br />
theological role of the Church, but within a nation it can be a great strength because it<br />
can protect the people against the inducements and the blandishments of charlatans and<br />
can provide a very powerful barrier to protect against the excessive concentration of<br />
power. Government should also be limited, have a limited but strategic role. Its goals ought to<br />
be to facilitate unity, security, choice and opportunity and to give help to the<br />
disadvantaged. I think also of the importance as a nation that we attach to the central role of family life<br />
within our community and the importance that public policy makers should place upon<br />
the role of the family within our society.<br />
We have also of course a very strong commitment as a society to an effective social<br />
security safety net. Many elements of that safety net have enjoyed bi-partisan support<br />
across the political divide within Australia for many years.<br />
I think also of our capacity to project to the rest of the world an impression of<br />
tolerance and acceptance of diversity of culture, diversity of ethnicity and of diversity<br />
of view. It remains the fact that Australia, particularly in the last 20 or 30 years, has<br />
had a profoundly honoured place amongst the nations in its willingness to accept<br />
people from the four corners of the earth. It'ought to be a matter of immense pride<br />
that this country in the late 1970s received on a per capita basis more refiugees from<br />
war torn LIdo-China than any other nation in the world.<br />
There is strong bi-pai-tisan support for a non-discriminatory immigration policy. There<br />
remains legitimate room for vigorous debate on the level of the migrant intake. But<br />
that that intake will occur on grounds that are completely oblivious to race ethnicity<br />
and country of origin remains a hi-partisan constant in Australian politics.<br />
We would also, in projecting to the world, be a nation that is willing to face both the<br />
benefits and the burdens of our history. To recognise that we as a nation have<br />
achieved many things together. To recognise that there have been blemishes and stains<br />
in our past. Far8xo / m82 / 97 11: 53 PS: 3 </p>
<p>Fax from Our attempts to achieve genuine forward looking reconciliation between all Australians<br />
and most particularly between Australians of a non-Aboriginal and Torres Strait<br />
Islander descent and the original inhabitants of this country remains a major challenge<br />
for the Australian community. But I say that optimistically, I say that positively, I say<br />
that deliberately using the expression forward looking. In my view the true path to<br />
reconciliation lies in removing current disadvantage and working together for a<br />
brighter shared future.<br />
The Primate mentioned the discussions that are now going on between my<br />
Government and various sections of the community regarding the appropriate response<br />
to the decision of the High Court in the Wik case, It is a profoundly difficult issue and<br />
a effective resolution of it will require of all those involved an understanding and a<br />
willingness to appreciate the others point of view. There is no monopoly of<br />
righteousness, there is no monopoly of wisdom on this particular issue enjoyed by one<br />
particular section of the Australian community.<br />
I have made it clear that in my own handling of the matter only two things are, as it<br />
were, untouchable. The first of those are the basic principles which underlaid the<br />
decision of the High Court of Australia in the original Mabo case. In other words the<br />
concept of Native Title which was a new concept to Australian law created by the<br />
decision of the High Court in the Mabo case. And the other, of course, is the belief<br />
that absolutely nothing need be done in the wake of the High Court's decision in the<br />
Wik case because that decision did alter quite fiindamentally the original basis on<br />
which the Native Title Act had been framed.<br />
I am approaching that issue with complete openness and good will towards those<br />
involved. I am already well into consultations. Further consultations I hope involve all<br />
of the interested parties at a national level will take place within the next couple of<br />
weeks. And out of that we will be able to see whether any common ground can be<br />
achieved.<br />
But it is important on issues such as that as the Primate said, that time be taken to<br />
reach a just decision and a decision and an outcome that gives to all Australians a sense<br />
of predicability, a sense of fairness and a sense of security. So when I think of the<br />
projection of my country and our country to the rest of the world I think of the<br />
projection of its values and its belief. I think of the projection of its capacity to solve<br />
in a compassionate, fair and descent manner the internal challenges that it faces. I<br />
think the willingness of people to put aside their partisan differences and unite to<br />
achieve such things as national gun laws sent a very powerful message to the rest of<br />
the world that here was a group of people faced with a particular challenge that were<br />
prepared to put aside their differences and they were prepared quite determinately to<br />
move away from going down one path that would, in my view, have led to greater<br />
sadness and greater destruction within our community and quite determinately go<br />
down another path wihich I believe over time will produce a more positive and a more<br />
benign outcome.<br />
When we project to the rest of the world we should never be reluctant to project those<br />
particular characteristics of us as Australians which have always marked us out from<br />
the rest of the world. In an age of globalisation and internationalisation a delicate<br />
Faxfro'~ 08/ 116: 25/ 39 7 Pg: 4 </p>
<p>I Fax from balance must always be struck between universal fraternity amongst the nations but<br />
also retaining those features and those characteristics which enable those from other<br />
countries to instantly recognise that we come from a country called Australia. And<br />
those traditional characteristics and values which we have nurtured and developed and<br />
added to and moulded and changed over the years are part of the enduring and very<br />
endearing Australian story.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen I thank you again for the privilege of addressing you this<br />
morning. I congratulate the Anglican Church on its sense of vision and perspective in<br />
putting together this national conference. I have a sense of great optimism and hope<br />
about the future of Australia. I have a sense of optimism and hope about the capacity<br />
for those forces within our community working towards positive outcomes in the<br />
defence and the promotion of values within our society. I have a positive and very<br />
optimistic view about their capacity to influence the affairs of the nation.<br />
I respect and value the views of the Churches expressed on so many issues. I don't<br />
always agree with them. I don't always quite know who is speaking on occasions for<br />
the Church or for some. But can I assure all of you as representatives of the Anglican<br />
Church as I did recently in a discussion with Cardinal Clancy speaking on behalf of the<br />
Catholic Church to me about certain matters, as I would to the leaders and the<br />
representatives of any of the Christian Churches or other religious communities in<br />
Australia, that my Government will always listen carefully to what you have to say.<br />
We won't as I said, always be able to agree with it. We will expect that on occasions<br />
you will be critical of us as you will be critical of other political movements. But the<br />
important thing is that you have a valued role iitihe wider activities of the Australian<br />
community, a role that I respect and a role that I will always deal with very openly and<br />
very forthrightly.<br />
Thank you for having me and I hope you have an immensely successful and rewarding<br />
conference. ends Farxom 08/ 02/ 97 11: 53 Pg: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
