<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11388</transcript-id>
    <title>26 May 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT CENTENARY OF FEDERATION                 BUSINESS LEADERS&#039; DINNER                 THE GREAT HALL, PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much Mary. To my colleague, Kim Beazley, my other</p>
<p> ministerial and parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Can I say how delighted I am to share in a very bipartisan way this</p>
<p> very special occasion which really is the first major event of a long</p>
<p> series of events planned by the Council of the Centenary of Federation.</p>
<p> It is, as Kim said, a celebration of a great achievement.</p>
<p>No doubt all of you over past years, and certainly in recent years,</p>
<p> would have had conversations about that marvellous phenomenon we find</p>
<p> amongst the young of Australia of a rediscovered interest in the great</p>
<p> deeds of our war heroes. The stories emerged again at the last Anzac</p>
<p> Day of the growing crowds of young people at Gallipoli and the growing</p>
<p> crowds of young people at Anzac Day celebrations.</p>
<p>Now, in part that is a demonstration of a realisation on the part</p>
<p> of the young in Australia, of the debt they owe to those who fought</p>
<p> to defend this country. But I think it is also resonant of a wider</p>
<p> development in our community and that is a growing interest in, a</p>
<p> greater curiosity about, and a growing appreciation of what this country</p>
<p> has achieved and indeed how successful it has been over the last 100</p>
<p> years.</p>
<p>It is a fact that you could count on the fingers of both hands the</p>
<p> number of nations that have been continuously democratic throughout</p>
<p> the entirety of the 20th Century and Australia of course</p>
<p> is one of those. It is true, as Kim Beazley pointed out, that this</p>
<p> nation pioneered many democratic forms and democratic practices and</p>
<p> democratic traditions years ahead of when they were tried in other</p>
<p> nations. It is also true that as we contemplate the next century,</p>
<p> as we contemplate 100 years as the Commonwealth of Australia that</p>
<p> we do as a community occupy what I frequently described as a special</p>
<p> intersection or a unique place.</p>
<p>Here we are in the Asian-Pacific region, a nation that has very deep</p>
<p> roots but certainly not exclusive roots in Western Europe and being</p>
<p> in many ways, but not exclusively again, a projection of western civilisation.</p>
<p> We share the great democratic traditions that we hold dear in common</p>
<p> with our friends in North America. But here we are in the Asian-Pacific</p>
<p> region and our society is very greatly enriched by the hundreds of</p>
<p> thousands of Australians of Asian descent who are adding such vitality</p>
<p> and zest to many parts of Australia. And it gives to us because of</p>
<p> that particular heritage, that mixed heritage, it does give to us</p>
<p> a special capacity over the next century to build a society and to</p>
<p> make a contribution that is unique. It is special and it is quite</p>
<p> unlike any other society on earth.</p>
<p>That, of course, throws on us an enormous responsibility because opportunity</p>
<p> carries responsibility. And as we contemplate the celebration of the</p>
<p> Centenary of Federation I think we can do so in a tremendous sense</p>
<p> of optimism. There is within all Australians a great competitive streak.</p>
<p> Our political system is competitive, it is adversarial and Australians</p>
<p> understand that and it is part of the process both in politics and</p>
<p> business to be competitive. But I think there's also another streak</p>
<p> within the Australian community and that is a deep desire on occasions</p>
<p> which are of national significance. A deep desire to see unity within</p>
<p> the Australian community, to see both sides of politics come together,</p>
<p> to put aside differences about other issues, to see all sections of</p>
<p> the Australian community recognise the special privilege it is to</p>
<p> be an Australian and to live in Australia.</p>
<p>Tonight is particularly an occasion for me, as Mr Beazley has done,</p>
<p> to honour the contribution of the businessmen and women of this country.</p>
<p> To honour those who laboured long and hard in the early years of Federation</p>
<p> when, of course, Australia at the turn of the century by many measures</p>
<p> had the highest living standard in the world. To remember those who</p>
<p> kept the entrepreneurial spirit going during the years of the great</p>
<p> depression and the difficult years through both world wars. To particularly</p>
<p> honour those business men and women who came with the great waves</p>
<p> of migration after World War II, many of whom are here tonight and</p>
<p> whose exploits and deeds and contribution in the business community</p>
<p> of Australia are very well and clearly understood and respected.</p>
<p>So I do thank the business community of Australia for coming here</p>
<p> tonight. I do ask, as Peter McGauran has done and as Kim Beazley has</p>
<p> done, I do ask you to get behind this great celebration, this reflection,</p>
<p> this opportunity to be nourished by the Australian achievement and</p>
<p> the Australian experience. To honour those that have made this country</p>
<p> so strong and free and, of course, to contemplate with a great sense</p>
<p> of optimism and hope the years that lay ahead of us.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I thank you for being here tonight. It is an</p>
<p> honour to host this occasion. It is important that I do so in the</p>
<p> presence of the leader of the Opposition because it is an occasion</p>
<p> that reminds us of one enduring reality of Australian life and that</p>
<p> is that things that unite us as Australians are infinitely greater</p>
<p> and more enduring than those that divide us. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
