<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18318</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech to South Australia Proclamation Day Ceremony, Adelaide</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/12/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Can I say to the crowd assembled here  -  I love this time of year.</p>
<p>I love it because it means I get to come home to South Australia. I get to come home and spend some time with family and friends, a very precious thing to do.</p>
<p>But I've also made it part of my annual calendar, as I come home to South Australia, to attend here, for Proclamation Day.</p>
<p>Such an important time of reflection on the history of this great state.</p>
<p>A time when we look back and a time when we look forward.</p>
<p>And friends, when we do look back, when we remember the Proclamation of South Australia, I think we see it as a day of endings and a day of beginnings.</p>
<p>For the traditional owners, it was the end of a way of life that they had treasured for centuries.</p>
<p>For the settlers it was a final closing of the door on old skies and old friends.</p>
<p>For both, it was a new beginning.</p>
<p>Full of risk.</p>
<p>But full of promise too.</p>
<p>The Proclamation tells us that they set out to create nothing less than a “great and free colony."</p>
<p>As the Premier and Mayor have detailed in their speeches, the founders succeeded and they succeeded in abundance.</p>
<p>Those nine ships of our own “first fleet” didn't just bring settlers and cargo.</p>
<p>They brought the best of our human values:</p>
<p>Optimism.</p>
<p>Faith in the future.</p>
<p>And willingness to unite great ambition with relentless hard work.</p>
<p>As Australia's first female Prime Minister, I was delighted to be reminded that there were 78 women in that fleet.</p>
<p>A woman, one of them a historian, who told us that they believed themselves to be“a worthy sisterhood.”</p>
<p>We rightly celebrate our founding fathers like Hindmarsh and Gouger; Torrens and Light.</p>
<p>Let's celebrate too those unnamed founding mothers and sisters too  -  because there would have been no South Australia without them.</p>
<p>If we have achieved good things, and we have, it's only because they achieved even better things in circumstances unimaginably harder than our own.</p>
<p>Friends, there is perhaps another clue to this State's success in the cargo of those ships: the state's first printing press.</p>
<p>Yes, they brought a printing press because they intended us to be a people of reason and learning - a free people in a new land; liberated from the poverty and the ignorance of the old.</p>
<p>175 years later, their achievements stands  -  and it stands strong </p>
<p>They created South Australia out of hardship and sacrifice.</p>
<p>And no community has ever been made of better materials.</p>
<p>And so on this day of gratitude and homecoming, we make our own proclamation:</p>
<p>That we will honour their great deeds with great deeds of our own.</p>
<p>Proud of the past and unafraid of our future.</p>
<p>Always ready to make those founding hopes our own.</p>
<p>Thank you for welcoming me on Proclamation Day.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
