<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4628</transcript-id>
    <title>CHOGRM COMMUNIQUE PRESS CONFERENCE, 16 FEBRUARY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004628.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
Regional Meeting<br />
SAustralia 1978 16 February, 1978.<br />
CHOGRM CO. IKNIOUE PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
Introductory remarks by the Australian Prime Minister,<br />
Mr. Fraser, at a joint press conference with the<br />
Commonwealth Secretary-General, Kr. Rampha, at the<br />
Hilton Hotel on 16 February, 1978, </p>
<p>Secretary-General, ladies and gentlemen, I hope you have-had<br />
time to read the commuinique that was agreed this afternoon by the<br />
conference. I believe that the comnmuniq~ ue does contain new and.<br />
promising decisions and that the discussions we have had over this<br />
last week btheeadlsatBowraltol very real significance for<br />
all the countries that have been represented throughout this week,<br />
The raceting has proved valuable. It has proved worthwhile and I think<br />
that is demonstrated very clearly by the attitude of all countries to<br />
the reeting, to the results, and by the determination that after the<br />
next full Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting we have already<br />
agreed to schedule a further meeting of this regional group. India<br />
has very kindly offered to host that particular meeting*<br />
I believe that the discussions we have had and the continuing<br />
negotiations and consultations that will take place together with<br />
further meetings will lead to a better understanding of our common<br />
hopes and aspirationss a better understanding of each other's problems<br />
and difficulties. Quite clearly the meeting has demonstrated that there<br />
is a determin~ ation to act together to advance our common cau. se in a<br />
number of directions,<br />
The exchange of views throughout the meeting has been always<br />
good humoured but it has been thoughtful, creative and sincere, That in<br />
itself has contributed enormously to the success of the meeting as a<br />
whole. There are common area interests which have all been well<br />
considered as well as wider world problems that impinge~ his particular<br />
areas In a number of areas firm decisions have been made and these<br />
are drawn together in the last page of the comriinique. ln paragraph 44<br />
you will see that there is to be a consultative group on trade;<br />
Australia will be responsible for convening that group. Trade there<br />
is to be interpreted in the broadest sense because when officials meet<br />
they will involve themselves not only with trade as such but with.<br />
corrzrnnicationss transport and with any matter that might enable trade<br />
within the region to be expanded. From the body of the document you will<br />
see that the region is not only concerned with increasing trade-between<br />
all the members of the region but also concerned at the 11U discussions<br />
and nego tiations that will take place that there should be some positive<br />
result and that commodities should not be pushed aside, should not be<br />
ignored in those major international discussions and all governments<br />
have recognised the need for progress to be made in that particular<br />
directi on. An imaginative proposal put forward by India has led or will<br />
lead to the establishment of a consultative group on energy. I think<br />
we can all understand how important that can be and I believe will be,<br />
The groups will be serviced jointly by India and by Australia. It is<br />
in this area where cocmon interests between the largest of us all and<br />
some of the smallest of us who are here that I think become apparent in<br />
a very tangible sense, For instance, the problem~ s of -getting the chleapest<br />
and most appropriate form of energy at the village . level in India has<br />
many similarities with the problems of providing energy for the Island<br />
States of the Pacific. That demonstrates in plain and practic-1 terrm-s </p>
<p>-2<br />
how there can be a real similarity of interest between large nations and<br />
small. Working groups will be established. One is to be led by Singapore,,<br />
another by Malaysia on aspects of terrorism and drugs so that we may<br />
all examine those present mechanisms of cooperation which take place through<br />
international forums and to see also whether other aspects need to be<br />
pursued more vigorously by cooperation between us.<br />
A proposal which has been put to the Secretary-General for<br />
examination and report by the Secretariat to see what services the Common..<br />
wealth as a Commonwealth might be able to better provide to small states<br />
is I believe a very useful one. Small states in the Pacific not only have<br />
the problems of distance and problems of development on a more acute scale<br />
than many other developing nations but they also have problems of adequate<br />
representation in international forums. That in itself can be a very<br />
expensive business to a small State and in the number of arenas in which ai<br />
nation needs to have its interests protected it is sometimes very difficult<br />
for the very sm-all States to achieve that. So there will be a number of<br />
aspects that the Secretariat will be examining and I am certain that they<br />
will be followed forward with uigour.<br />
I have already mentioned that it is intended that the next meeting<br />
should be held at Delhi in 1980. 1 am sure that all countries represented<br />
here will look forward to that,<br />
Other matters which are of importance were discussion in relation<br />
to the Common Fund. Australia's position, which I explained a day or two<br />
ago has been noted. The group has lent support to the Secretary-General's<br />
proposal that there should be a M1inisterial m~ eting of Commorm; ealth<br />
countries to discuss the technical working report established as a result of<br />
the June meeting last year, because the main negotiating conference in<br />
relation to the Cor-4non Fund takes place in April of this year. So I hope<br />
that the commonwealth group can get together before that time. I also hope<br />
that the initiative of this meeting together with the position taken by<br />
Australia might help lead to a constructive breakthrough in negotiations<br />
which have been deadlocked over the last few months because we believe<br />
it is of importance that progress be made in relation to the Common Fund,<br />
I would like to publicly thank the Heads of Governments and the<br />
delegations of all those who have visited with us during the course of this<br />
last week. I think everyone has wholeheartedly contributed to achieving<br />
a very constructive result out of a very useful few days' discussions,<br />
I would like to ask the Secretary-General to say whatever he would<br />
like to say and then it would be over to you for questions. </p>
<p>Comm-ionwealth Heads of Government<br />
Regional Meeting<br />
Australia 1978 16 February, 1973o<br />
_ CHORM COKI13NIUE PRSS CONFERENCE<br />
Introductory remarks by the Commonwealth Secretary-General<br />
N~ Shridath Ramphal, at a joint press conference with the<br />
Agetralian Pritw_ Minister, Mr Malcolm Fraser, at the Hilton<br />
Hotel on 16 February, 1978. </p>
<p>MR. RAYIPHAL: Thank you Prime Minister.<br />
There isn't a groat deal. I wish to add. I believe that<br />
the meeting itself has vindicated the highest hopes we could<br />
possibly have had for it. When Mr'. Fraser mooted the idea of<br />
a regional gathering of this kind at the Summit which is what<br />
is important about a meeting of this kind, that it takes place<br />
at the Summit when he mooted this in London last year it was<br />
obviously a point of departure in the ways in which we use the<br />
facilities of Commonwealth dialogue and consultation. As is<br />
natural on an occasion of that kind -there is uncertainty, there<br />
is doubt, there is wonder, there is an appreciation of the<br />
potential of the occasion and it is only its practical out-turn<br />
that reveals and justifies it.<br />
What has happened here in Sydney in the last four or five<br />
days has, I think, in every sense fully justified the faith tha~ t<br />
was put in it; not just by the members of this part of the<br />
Commonwealth but by all Commonwealth leaders when they welcomed<br />
these proposals last June. I think the great significance is<br />
that it has happened. The leadership of a very important segment<br />
of the world, about a third of the world has been brought together<br />
at the highest level for the first time in human history and<br />
that's a very important factor. It has been brought together not<br />
just because of geography and economics, but brought together<br />
because the leaders of the countries have been willing to use the<br />
Commonwealth connexion to bring it together. That in itself speaks<br />
volumes for their own confidence in that connex~ ion and they have<br />
gone out of their way in the communiques as you will see to state<br />
that very clearly.<br />
We have bridged, I believe, here in Sydney some very<br />
important gaps that have existed in relations in this part of the<br />
world and nothing is more significant about the occasion than the<br />
human relationships that have been established, the personal contacts<br />
that have been made between Presidents and Prime Ministers<br />
and the effect this is going to have on relations between countries<br />
in this part of the world hereafter, and on relations between this<br />
part of the world and the rest of the world.<br />
So what has happened here is of enormous significance.<br />
Mr. Fraser has already identified some of those practical issues<br />
on which decisions have been reached. They have not just been<br />
general accords. We have been able to develop the processes of<br />
follow-up action. We know precisely who will be doing w* hat and<br />
what line of direction this will take and that's an important part<br />
of the development. On the economic issues, I -think this meeting can prove to<br />
have made an important advance in the international dialogue that<br />
is taking place. The recommendations that have come out of * the<br />
meeting in relation to the Common Fund, and the Common Fund you<br />
must remember is at the very heart of the international dialogue<br />
between north and south, provide the best chance for international<br />
concensus that has existed for a long time. ' It will, I am sure,<br />
give heart to many people in many couhtries, developed and developing,<br />
that there . still exists possibilities of finding a way<br />
towards agreement on the Common Fund. / 1)<br />
1 L2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Australia's very important decisions in relation to the<br />
fund, which are in keepingr with the positions that the Prime<br />
Minister developed at the London meeting itself, when he launched<br />
initiative for the report on the Common Fund, those positions are<br />
going to be of great significance in a regional context and in an<br />
international context. I can only reiterate the hope he has<br />
expressed that other countries, countries in group B, developed.<br />
countries, would follow this lead that has been given down the<br />
path to concensus, and the developing countries would themselves<br />
be responsive to it and match that kind of initiative with a<br />
readiness on their own part to find the way of accommodation.<br />
If we can have begun to develop this here in a regional<br />
Commonwealth context, if we can carry it forward into wider<br />
Commonwealth context, there is no reason why we can't help to<br />
achieve the global concensus that is so important. I'd like<br />
finally just to add my own sense of satisfaction with the conclusions<br />
that have been reached about the need for us to find new and<br />
enlightened and effective ways of helping the small states within<br />
the Commonwealth. Many are here on your doorstep in Australia.<br />
There are others scattered around the Commonwealth. We have all<br />
helped to bring them to independence. They are facing very great<br />
difficulties in a world that is not kind to small and isolated<br />
communities. That this important group of 12 within the Commonwealth<br />
should have recognised collective responsibility to help<br />
them and to have invited me to put forward proposals for a wider<br />
Commonwealth concensus on the way we help them is a very significant<br />
advance here and something that I think will have enormous importanc~ e<br />
to the future of relations in this part of the world where so many<br />
of these states exist and will be coming to independence in the next<br />
few months. THE PRIME MINISTER: Thank you very much. I think it is<br />
over to you. </p>
<p>Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
Regional Meeting<br />
Mstralia 1978 16 February, 1978.<br />
CHO4 COM1UNIUE CONFE RENCE<br />
tions and inwe _ a during the joint press confrence<br />
by the Australian Prime Xinister, Mr. Fraser, and the<br />
Secretary-Gceneral, Mr. Ramphal, at the Hilton Hotel on<br />
16 February, 1978, </p>
<p>Q: In relation to parao 34 your Department of Productivity is sending<br />
an overseas mission on textiles around the Pacific region with<br />
the aim of increasing Australia's productivity. I am asking now<br />
how this will halp trade access as far as the countries in the<br />
region are concerned and to Australia and alsot in fact,<br />
how can this not only protect but give encouragement to Australia's<br />
industry, textiles industry, help the regionalisation effort...<br />
Mr, Fraser: I think this proposal in para. 34 needs looking at in its total<br />
context, The purpose of officials meeting will be to encourage<br />
the totalality of trade within the region. It is not, and not<br />
intended, to be just a mechanism in which everyone exports more<br />
to Australia but trade betw;. een other members of the region is also<br />
important and between all the members of the region and countries<br />
outside. There are a number of matters that officials will be able<br />
to report on which will be very significant,<br />
I believe it is coming to be understood that imports from developing<br />
countries have been increasing at. the rate of 40% a year for a<br />
number of years. No matter what the initial base may be~ at that.<br />
kind of accumulation the base starts to become quite large, n<br />
addition of course* you have the per capita imports of very<br />
sensitive items that come into Australia which I think are greater<br />
than for any other developed country, certainly greater than for<br />
any other group of countries for which 1 have seen figures.<br />
Para. 34 does recognise the importance of a number of matters that<br />
are interrelated. The importance of markets outside for the<br />
countries of the region, mrarkets outside which are very often<br />
barred to countries of the region because of non-tariff barriers*<br />
I think sometimes in the past there has been too much attention<br />
merely on the Australian market when after all that is a market<br />
of only 14 million people. Whatever you do about protection or<br />
don't do about protection in Australia a market of 14 million<br />
people just can't solve the trading problems of the whole region<br />
or of South East Asia. The capacity just isn't there. So para., 34<br />
needs to be looked at in the wider context of a general promotion<br />
of trade and a general breaking down of barriers which move against<br />
the interests of all countries of the region. It also needs to be<br />
looked at against the background of the changing movements of trade<br />
over recent years where access to Australia by countries of theregion<br />
and other developing countries has increased verygreatly.,<br />
I don' t think anyone has ever suggested that Australia should not<br />
have any textile industry and that is certainly not the governmnt's<br />
position but there might have been some implication of that in the<br />
question,<br />
Q: Can the Secretary-Ceneral tell us the obviously somewhat fine<br />
distinction between a consultative group and a working group?<br />
S-G: Yes, we see the consultative group as being somewhat more of an<br />
institution having a indeterminate future, an important part of<br />
the mechanism of cooper-ation between the countries of the region.<br />
We see thc working group very much in the nature of an ad hoc<br />
group whose future will be determiined by the character of its work. </p>
<p>Q: Prime Ministers to what extent do you think the impact of the<br />
conference has suffered from the bombing that preceded it?<br />
1-1r, Fraser: I believe that as a resulL of that particular tragic happening<br />
all Heads of Governme~ nt devoted themselves to the work of the<br />
conference with a greater commitment, a greater sense of purpose<br />
because they weren't going to allow an incident of that kind to<br />
divert them iLrom the major and important purposes for which they<br />
had come here. So if there had been an impact, I think it was<br />
to enhance the quality of the discussions and the final outcome.<br />
Q: Prime Minister it is now four days since that explosion, You<br />
have been getting reports from police and security people. Can<br />
you tell us what progress has been made in the investigation?<br />
If as seems to us very little progress has been made, what<br />
problems have been encountered? Does the whole episode show up<br />
deficiencies in Australia's police and security services and<br />
finally are you concerned that the explosion could damage<br />
Australia's chance of hosting the 1981 CHOGRM?<br />
Mr, Fraser: As to last part, not at all, and as to the rest, could I<br />
suggest that we concentrate on questions in relation to the<br />
communique and the substance of that communique first. I would<br />
be very happy to answer any other questions at a later point but<br />
rather than having questions jump backwards and forwards from one<br />
subject to another, I think it would be better if we just make<br />
that distinction.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, in para. 32 you referred to developed countries<br />
at th-e meting. Which do you identify as the developed countries<br />
that were at this meeting?<br />
Hr,, Fraser: Australia and New Zealand would be the developed countries at<br />
the meeting. I don't know, other countries might want to classify<br />
themselves but I think that is fair enough.<br />
Q: In your section on energy the question of atomic energy as an<br />
alternative seems not to be mentioned. Why is that, and is that<br />
a factor in the considerations that the committee will give?<br />
Mr. Fraser: 1 don't think it is -ruled out but the main thrust of what tie<br />
were talking about was not at that level. That sort of energy<br />
is more for the great metropolis and for great industries with<br />
large energy requirements. One of the things that we did have<br />
very mu. ch in our mind was the energy requirements of the howe use<br />
and the village industry use which is of quite a different-character.<br />
It is there that I indicated a similarity of interests between<br />
India, for example, and some very small States. But the termns of<br />
reference of that particular consultative group I don't think are.<br />
going to be restricted. On the needs for village purposes there<br />
was a background paper which Australia had prepared. That,<br />
together with the major Indian paper, will be referred to the<br />
group but at least in the Jinitial stage I think we are all looking<br />
to the rather different purposes than that to which nuclear energ~ y<br />
for peaceful purposes would be applied, </p>
<p>Q. Sir, section 25 on protectionism by industrialised countries<br />
was this aimed at Australia and New Zealand?<br />
Mr. Fraser: I didn't notice anything that was aimed at Australia and New<br />
Zealand and I think if you read Section 25 Heads of Government<br />
expressed their concern over rising protectionism of industrialised<br />
countries against manufactured goods wfiich countries in the region<br />
were well equipped to supply. Well Australia joins in that<br />
expression of conern, You will note that it goes on especially<br />
also to point also to the damaging effects of non-tariff and other<br />
barriers in trade and agricultural products which are of major<br />
importance to regional countries, a matter which Australia has been<br />
emphasising for somne considerable time. Through this paper there<br />
are a number of references to that particular aspect; and that<br />
means of trying to overcome those non-tariff barriers in trade<br />
and commodities which aff~ ect all the countries of this particular<br />
region, I think, virtually all, anyway, is really within the<br />
ter-as of reference of the consultative group on trade. There are<br />
expressions in the document about the importance of getting a<br />
breakthrough in this area at the major trade and negotiations<br />
taking place later this year, It is also recognised in this<br />
paper that those particular barriers on Australia's exports,<br />
to take our example f or a momen't, very much inhibit our capacity<br />
to provide a market for other industrialised goods in the region<br />
because those barriers limit the extent to which we can export<br />
those thing's we can do best and cheapest that therefore weakens.<br />
the Australian economy. So there are a number of things interrelated<br />
here. I believe that we were discussing in proper terms objectives<br />
that we would all want to pursue. We also know that if we are to<br />
advance our common causes to the best possible extent that there is<br />
a need to take account of the particular views, the particular<br />
concerns, the particular problems of all member countries. I think<br />
that has been a characteristic of the Commonwealth as a whole and<br />
it was certainly a characteristic of this particular meeting.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, in para. 41 on the special problems of sinall States,<br />
there doesn't seem to be any reference to the proposed unilateral<br />
declaration for 200 mile fishing zones or how on earth the smaller<br />
States are going to police those fishing zones. Was any consideration<br />
given to this? </p>
<p>MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
S. G.<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
SJ. G. That wasn't discussed at any great length. One might<br />
well ask how a number of other countries are going to<br />
police those zones too because if you really take a<br />
map and mark in that 200 mile zone for all countries<br />
in the world it does create a very great problem indeed.<br />
You will know for our own part the top level IDO has<br />
been instructed to report to the Australian Government<br />
on the problems involved in surveillance and what's<br />
needed in relation to it and report promptly. You. are<br />
quite right to point to an area which does create very<br />
real problems but I don't think anyone could possibly<br />
suggest that there is going to be 24 hour surveillance<br />
over all of those areas. The cost of that would be<br />
astronomical and beyond the capacity of all of us.<br />
I was wondering why that was omitted in the communique,<br />
no reference to the fishing zone?<br />
The Foreign Minister reminds me that the South Pacific<br />
forum is looking at this Particular matter, but it<br />
wasn't a matter that was discussed at great length in<br />
these discussions. There is no inhibition on it being<br />
raised. I don't think you should look on this as an omission.<br />
There were a number of issues, a number of matters which<br />
are regarded as being of vital interest to the small<br />
countries, this was one of them. There were others, for<br />
example, in relation to the international negotiations<br />
there, the multi-national trade negotiations in GEneva,<br />
the resumption of the negotiations on the second LOMOG<br />
convention which affect the interests of many countries<br />
here. They have not been enumerated but they are very<br />
much a part of the concerns and you will notice a ref erence<br />
to the need to help them, to meet their vital.<br />
interests and pursue them.<br />
In other words the Secretary-General has an unlimited<br />
charter in proposing what he thinks ought to be done.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, para. 44, I notice that the country<br />
co-ordinating the consultative group on trade is one<br />
that doesn't want changes, the country co-ordinating<br />
the working group on terrorism won't send back plane<br />
hijackers to Vietnam and the country co-ordinating the<br />
working group on illicit drugs believes in whipping<br />
people for possession of a bit of " pot". How were those<br />
countries chosen and why?<br />
I think there was a general concensus that those<br />
countries would be appropriate and would do the job.<br />
And I think the definition of the countries implicit<br />
in the question is not necessarily a completely accurate<br />
one.<br />
Might I with more detachment say that the classifications<br />
you apply to those countries would not have been ones<br />
that would have been genri, 7ally accepted at he conference. </p>
<p>MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER: We do not for example,* regard Australia as a country<br />
that in international trade is unwilling to face the<br />
realities of change. In fact we believe that many<br />
of the policies that the Australian Government have<br />
become to initiate point in the direction of a willingness<br />
to approach in a systematic and constructive way<br />
the opening up of new avenues of change.<br />
As to para. 27: Sir, the brief and surprisingly mild<br />
reference to the EEC hardly reflects the Australian<br />
position. Were you not able to prevail on the other<br />
Heads of Government the need for a stronger stand<br />
against EEC trade barriers?<br />
I think -there are a number of references, you mentioned<br />
para. 27. I think the language is thoroughly appropriate<br />
for a communique from 12 Heads of Government.<br />
Para. 25 contains an implied reference which is pretty<br />
plain. Para. 26 certainly does. I think para. 27 does<br />
also and 34.-" riecognising the access to major markets<br />
in the European community, North America and Japan were<br />
critical to the well-being of world trade. They also<br />
agreed that the consultative group would examine ways<br />
and means of persuading those major trading blocks to<br />
break down non-tariff barriers, which inhibited so many<br />
of the natural and economic exports from the region".<br />
I would hardly have thought that you could have got a<br />
more precise or explicit reference to a problem which<br />
concerns all of us and one which Australia has mentioned<br />
on a number of occasions.<br />
Mr. Prime Minister, when do you expect some concrete<br />
proposals and concrete decisions to emerge from the two<br />
consultative groups and the two working groups?<br />
I think it is too early to say at this point. But; for<br />
our part, and I'm sure for the other countries concerned<br />
the matters will be approached with energy and commitment.<br />
Some of the problems that the groups will be looking at<br />
are obviously difficult and some of them are not capable<br />
of any early solution. But let me only say that no time<br />
is going to be lost.<br />
Do you expect some action before the next Regional. Heads<br />
of Government meeting?<br />
Oh, in two years time, good heavens yes, yes. It doesn't<br />
wait for them to report back and there are other means<br />
of communication also which I hope, very much, will be<br />
employed. No, please, let nobody think that just because<br />
a meeting has been determined in two years time in Delhi<br />
that the reporting back happens then; long, long before<br />
-that, or I.' ll be very disappointed.<br />
Prime Minis-ter, in relation to the question that was<br />
asked orn the EE~ C, do you feel that Australia's position<br />
has now been strengthened, its bargaining sition has<br />
been strengthened, in -ro'a" Cion to the abso-ate trade<br />
barriers that the issues impose and you've criticised?<br />
MR. FRASER: I think., _ ft ov', Ly Ausl-.' a) ial's positi-on, T </p>
<p>MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER: commodity producers have had their positions<br />
strengthened because there are other aspects of this<br />
that also need to be taken into account I think and<br />
understood. Under the LOME convention, for examnie,<br />
there are many people who believe that the developing<br />
countries of Africa and the Carribean gain some<br />
advantage in relation to that and some not insignificant<br />
advantage, but that the developing countries of<br />
the Indian sub-continent, South East Asia and the<br />
Pacific, while may be technically designed to be<br />
accommodated within that convention, were not gaining<br />
a great deal from it. That might be another aspect in<br />
a sense but it is related to the problem which has<br />
concerned us. The more discussion there is in world<br />
forums about the way the present policies of the EEC<br />
inhibit trade generally and prevent many countries from<br />
doing that which they can do best and most naturally.<br />
All countries are thereby strengthened in efforts to<br />
get a more rational result.<br />
Q. 39. The communique mentions down the bottom to<br />
examine the possibilities for further regional<br />
co-operation. What are those possibilities?<br />
Well this will come forward as a result of a working<br />
group. That's what it will be charged with doing.<br />
There are a number of international organisations and<br />
arrangements now in relation to these matters. Are<br />
these being pursued as vigorously as they should be?<br />
Are there additional measures that ought to be applied<br />
by all of us or by some of us which aren't embraced<br />
under present international arrangements? Again, there<br />
are no particular restrictions on what the working<br />
group might examine and recommend in relation to this.<br />
This subject of illicit drug trafficking. It is something<br />
that concerns us all. I am wondering why<br />
Indonesia was not invited to this conference in the<br />
first place?<br />
It was restricted to members of the Commonwealth and<br />
that is the only reason.<br />
Para. 13 on the Indian Ocean I am wondering what<br />
sort of practical steps you would like to see taken<br />
for the implementation of the declaration of the<br />
Indian Ocean as a ZOP.<br />
One practical step would be a successful conclusion<br />
of negotiations between the Soviet Union and the United<br />
States but which at the same time recognised and protected<br />
the rights of all states in and around the Indian<br />
Ocean. That is one step that could be taken..<br />
Not specifically on the text of . the communique but on<br />
the balance in it, are you happy and do you think there<br />
is a general satisfJ" action of the extent to which the<br />
meeting was able to identify specifically r-: gionally<br />
interests as opposed to world interests whi.-, h occupy<br />
the greater part of the ' Lext? </p>
<p>MR. FRASER: I don't know that world interests really cover a<br />
greater part of the text because you've got a<br />
situation where there are many world issues which<br />
obviously have a very great impact on this particular<br />
region. The Common Fund discussions, that is<br />
a world matter, but nobody can say it is not a<br />
matter of great interest to the region. The meeting<br />
took a view on it and has proposed one or two<br />
matters which might help to break an impasse, We<br />
hope so. Therefore, in a number of areas the world<br />
issues flow over very much into the regional issues.<br />
I think that the balance of the document is not a<br />
bad one. We have addressed ourselves to very specific<br />
regional problems such as the question of small states<br />
in the Pacific. That again, if you like, has got<br />
world overtones because there are small states outside<br />
the Pacific that have, to a significant extent, the<br />
same problems. So you just can't look for rigid lines<br />
of demarcation. The conversations and discussion were<br />
very much related to the particular problems and<br />
interests of the countries that were represented. </p>
<p>D1R. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER: Prime Minister, para. 11 takes 66 words to dispose<br />
of the subject of terrorism. In view of the bombing<br />
outrage on Sunday night, would it not have been<br />
entirely proper to give more weight to the subject<br />
of terrorism in this communique?<br />
I hope people are not going to judge the merit of<br />
what is done or not done by the number of words used<br />
to express a view or to state an objective and a conclusion.<br />
The meeting quite quickly came to the view<br />
that the conclusion that appears in the document and<br />
the working group relating to it was what they wanted<br />
and that it was the appropriate thing to do. With<br />
all the kindness of the world to a good friend, I<br />
really do believe that to measure quality by length<br />
is not necessarily the best way of doing it. Column<br />
inches. I was speaking in media terms.<br />
There is a reference here to ASEAN, in para. 8 and 9<br />
Mr. Prime Minister. Would you foresee in the future,<br />
if not a state of competition, then an overlapping<br />
between ASEAN and this conference as a continuous<br />
event. Certainly not competition, no. I think that what<br />
happens in this particular discussion contributes to<br />
the worth of other forums in which countries participate.<br />
Let me give one or two examples. Very useful<br />
work is undertaken in the Pacific Forum and the<br />
countries in the Pacific Forum are strongly represented<br />
at this meeting. But they were thus able to have their<br />
views known and heard amongst a wider group of countries<br />
that are not often at normally not at that Pacific<br />
Forum. I think the fact they were here was one of the<br />
reasons why we have discussed and come to the conclusions<br />
we have had about the problems of small States. That<br />
would not have occurred if the Pacific Forum countries<br />
met only in the Pacific Forum and not in the wider<br />
community. Quite obviously, the Commonwealth as a whole in many of<br />
its discussions overlapped matters that are discussed<br />
in the United Nationa. But I believe the Commonwealth<br />
connection, the Commonwealth influence enables individual<br />
countries to play a more constructive role in the United<br />
Nations than if they weren't members of the Commonwealth.<br />
I would believe that is one of the reasons why many<br />
diverse countries from many parts of the world feel<br />
strongly about the Commonwealth and the Commonwealth tie.<br />
Coming back more directly to your particular question,<br />
I see the work of this group as advancing the general<br />
interests of the whole area and of the region of the<br />
countries represented. Strengthening tthose countries,<br />
I would believe, is going to strengthen ASEAN. I<br />
certainly don'~ t see any degree of competition. Australia<br />
supports ASEAN very strongly and wishes that Association<br />
every success. It is a very important one and I think </p>
<p>MR. FRASER: it has achieved noteable results, I believe it will<br />
continue to do so. I am quite sure it would be the<br />
view of the 12 countries represented here during the<br />
course of this week to inake quite sure that nothing<br />
it did cut across the purposes or view of ASEAN.<br />
Mr. Fraser, as a producing country, where does<br />
Australia stand with relationship to the philosophies<br />
of the new economic order and the north-south dialogue?<br />
I think you have got to look at that by looking at<br />
Australia's attitude on the Common Fund which I have.<br />
expressed quite clearly and plainly. We do believe<br />
in commodity arrangements, international commodity<br />
arrangements. We have participated in them on many<br />
occasions. We have tried to nudge developed countries<br />
that might sometimes have been reluctant to undertake<br />
sugar agreements or wheat agreements to do so.<br />
How do we nudge ourselves?<br />
MR. FRASER: In relation to what?<br />
To that.<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
S). G.<br />
S. G. I think thatq. we are ahead of the B group of countries.<br />
We are hoping that as a result of the initiatives<br />
Australia has t-aken and as a result of discussions<br />
that I hope will take place at the Ministerial level<br />
in relation to the Commonwealth's technical working<br />
group report on the Common Fund that when the negotiating<br />
conference resumes in April or May that it might<br />
get nearer to agreement than it was when it broke up<br />
last November.<br />
There is no problem with Australia's philosophy in<br />
its relationship and support of these particular<br />
matters. Mr. Prime MinistL-er, may I add to that the role of the<br />
media in translating to the public an understanding of<br />
the aspirations of the international community in<br />
relation to the new international economic order and<br />
what iz in it for Australia. That will be an enormous<br />
help to all that the government is trying to do at its<br />
level.<br />
May we ask the Secretary-General if he perceived a<br />
Sydney spirit and if so, how would he define it?<br />
A Sydney spirit? You know, we talked about the spirit<br />
of Ottawa and we talked about the concord of Kingston.<br />
If , it isn't. too hackneyed I think really the best<br />
presentation is for us to think in terms of the Bridge<br />
of Sydney.<br />
Prime Minister-, are a set number-of millio', going to<br />
bc 11ocated in th-2 budget for the nex-, t tw.: years of<br />
research or are they goinlg to have unlimited access to<br />
our funds? .4 </p>
<p>MR.* FRASER: Who?<br />
Q: For all this research we are apparently going to<br />
finance in the second last paragraph. " Most of the<br />
Secretariat's work..." 1 in section 44.<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
S. G.<br />
MR. FRASER: That's Secretariat work. That is follow up work<br />
which will be undertaken by the Secretariat. I<br />
would have thought the finance involved in that<br />
would be relatively modest. It needs to be understood<br />
if you are talking about energy that we already<br />
spend a good deal on energy research. We have made<br />
arrangements so that there will be greater funds and<br />
a levy on coal, for example, for additional coal<br />
research. I have no doubt that India spends a good<br />
deal on energy research. We have co-operative programmnes<br />
with the Victorian Government and the German<br />
Government in relation to coal liquification, I would<br />
imagine that it would be up to this consultative group<br />
on energy to do its own work. I would imagine, however,<br />
that a good deal of its early work would be to pull all<br />
the related knowledge that we have, not only Australia<br />
and Indi~ a but from other parts of the world together to<br />
see what is relevant to the countries of the region.<br />
If additional research or a changed orientation of<br />
research is necessary, then that certainly will be<br />
proposed. But I don't think you need be concerned that<br />
as a result of these decisions there is suddently a<br />
large or unlimited call on Australian or any other<br />
exchequer. There isn't.<br />
This is essentially work of co-ordination, trying to<br />
ensure that if I can follow through the Bridge of e<br />
Sydney isn't just an edifice structure that is erecte<br />
but in fact that we use it.<br />
Your expressions earlier in the conference of pessimism<br />
on the world economy and disappointment in US budgetary<br />
policies were widely reported and some sections of the<br />
press criticised. How did you want them to be understood<br />
or interpreted?<br />
Precisely in the terms in which I used the terms. If<br />
a plain meaning of the language could be used rather<br />
than looking for some hidden interpretation sometimes<br />
there would be a better understanding on that score.<br />
The words speak for themselves. I have not seen all<br />
the interpretations, so I can't judge that. But I<br />
think it is an odd circumstance that you sometimes get<br />
a position in Australia where people say you have got<br />
to be independent, you mustn't just quietly accept<br />
what other people of great powers say and then if<br />
something is said that in the m~ ildest and most friendly<br />
terms offers a ooint of view that is different from<br />
that of one -of the major powers, there is immediately<br />
criticism of it. " Yo should-n't have done that"<br />
impliedly meaning that it might give off en,; e. I am<br />
quite cer. tain t.-hat what was said would not give<br />
offence. 34 arm , ilso qui--te certain that there are oc-cas--</p>
<p>MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER: ions when Australia does need to Speak her view<br />
aloud. Australia will do so but I hope always it<br />
can be regarded that we do so in proper and reasonable<br />
terms.<br />
Prime Minister, given the urgency of the drug problem,<br />
what priority would you like to see the working<br />
committee on drugs give to addressing that particular<br />
situation. Indeed, would you not like to see them<br />
report back withi~ n some specific time span rather -than<br />
the rather vague terms set out in the communique?<br />
When you do something like this involving a number of<br />
countries, I think you have got to leave the matter<br />
reasonably broad because you are not quite sure where<br />
the examination will go or where it will need to go.<br />
I am quite certain that the people concerned won't<br />
waste any time in getting down to their examination<br />
and report. But it is not always easy at the outset<br />
to define the size of the. task.<br />
In para. 39 You said " They welcomed efforts to suppress<br />
the traffic". Can you tell me what efforts you believe<br />
are being made already?<br />
In general terms but quite plainly national governments<br />
have efforts in their own boundaries and in their own<br />
countries to suppress traffic. You will have noted in<br />
Australia in recent time some very considerable hauls<br />
of drugs that had been imported.<br />
Is-it your view that any countries in the regions are<br />
not carrying out those efforts to the best of their<br />
ability? I think there is a general recognition that this is<br />
an important problem. We all need to examine what we<br />
are doing and what we are doing in relation to international<br />
arrangements to make quite certain that<br />
nothing that ought to be done is left undone. I<br />
believe that is a very proper examination for governments<br />
to undertake. Again I would hope that it is<br />
possible for countries to get together to undertake<br />
that kind of examination without suggestions that one<br />
particular country is not doing everything it ought.<br />
People have approached this with a feeling of goodwill,<br />
recognising it as a major national and international<br />
problem. Prime Minister, it has been four days since the bomb<br />
explosion outside this building, you have been getting<br />
police and security reports. Can you tell us what;<br />
progress has been made in the investigation. If, as<br />
seems to us, very little progress has been made, canyou<br />
tell us what the problems are, and what is being<br />
done to overcome them, and hasil't the whole episode<br />
shown up a deficiency in our police and security<br />
services? </p>
<p>MIR. FRASER:<br />
MR. FRASER: I think that the first parts of those questions<br />
relate to the nature of any investigations that<br />
are being under-taken by those professionally<br />
charged with that kind of investigation. I<br />
haven't got particular information about that.<br />
If I had, I don't think it would be proper to do<br />
it because giving information about examinations<br />
of that kind could well prejudice further examninations.<br />
Quite clearly, I think, as a result of what has<br />
happened we need to review the circumstances of<br />
the past week. We had gone to very significant<br />
lengths between the state authorities and the<br />
commonwealth authorities to make sure that the<br />
liaison arrangements were good. I believe they<br />
were and are. We did in relation to this meeting<br />
undertake more stringent security arrangements than<br />
Australia had in her history. Due to the tragedy<br />
that occurred, those arrangements were immediately<br />
reviewed and additional measures put in train. On<br />
all future occasions Australia has to recognise and<br />
understand that these things can happen here because<br />
they have.<br />
Therefore with major international conferences, we<br />
clearly need to plan in relation to maximum security.<br />
There will be consultations in the future between the<br />
States and the Commonwealth. I had indicated on an<br />
earlier occasion that I would be approaching the<br />
States in-relation to consultations about formal<br />
agreements between State special branches and ASIO.<br />
I now believe that those discussions ought to take<br />
into account the physical arrangements again to make<br />
sure that they are as good as we can make them between<br />
State police forces and the Commonwealth's own instrumentalities.<br />
The Executive order which authorised the use of the<br />
Defence Force declared that this order shall continue<br />
in force until revoked. Can you given an assurance<br />
that that order will be revoked once the last visiting<br />
Head of Government leaves Australia, and if not when<br />
will it be revoked?<br />
The requisition which was related to a couple of days<br />
at Bowral has already been cancelled. The Foreign<br />
Minister cancelled that at 2 o'clock today. I would<br />
expect it won't be very long before the Executive<br />
Council authority is also cancelled.<br />
I I I </p>
<p>Mr. Fraser:<br />
Mr. Fraser: Sir* if I could just follow my question. Are we right in<br />
interpreting what you said as meaning that you still have no<br />
idea who planted that bomb?<br />
No. I don't know.<br />
Do the police have any clues? Are they following any<br />
particular line?<br />
I haven't had a full briefing about all the avenues being<br />
persued by the police at the present time. One thing I<br />
would be convinced about is that the authorities would be<br />
using every avenue available to them to find who or what<br />
organisation put the bomb outside this hotel. When they<br />
have matters to report I am quite certain they will,<br />
On the same subject, very briefly, are you now planning for<br />
possible emergencies when Parliament sits or in local VIP<br />
context in view of that bomb explosion? u<br />
Mr, Fraser: There is very plainly a need to<br />
inside Parliament House itself.<br />
of Parliament House I think you look at security arrangements<br />
From your own knowledge<br />
would understand that.<br />
Mr, Fraser:<br />
Mr. Fraser: Mr. Prime Ministerp this is the first time the armed forces<br />
have been used to protect the civil authority. Could I ask<br />
you whether you believe this means that in future the-armed<br />
forces should receive a special type of new training which<br />
might equip them more for this particular purpose?<br />
Using the broad term, aid for the civil power, has always<br />
potentially been one of the Army's responsibilities because<br />
the law and it is not a new law has always allowed for it.<br />
The Army people were well equipped for the task-which wasentnusted<br />
to them over the last couple of days. This was<br />
basically making sure that a reasonably long stretch of road<br />
was going to be secure, the bridges and culvets were secure,<br />
that bombs couldn't have been planted under a culvet and<br />
detonated. I am quite certain that the Armny is well equipped<br />
for that,<br />
You spoke earlier of the question of liaison. Do you think<br />
in this case security suffered because of liaison and because<br />
divided responsibility and in future will there be one authority<br />
in charge?<br />
In Australia, because of the Commonwealth state relationship,<br />
because of different constitutional responsibilities, we have<br />
the circumstance in which things have to be done by liaison.<br />
One of the things which I am sure Neville Wran and myself<br />
would want to examine, is to make sure that liaison and the<br />
mechanisms to govern any particular situation are as best<br />
devised as possibly can be. You can'tf get away from the fact<br />
that the states have their own police forces the Comm nealth </p>
<p>Mr. Fraser: again has its own instrumentalities and in emergencies such<br />
as the kind which we had earlier this week there is an<br />
absolute necessity for them to co-operate. I believe they do.<br />
I would likeg incidentally, to pay a tribute to Neville Wran<br />
for the full support that he and the instruments of the<br />
state government have given this conference. When the initial<br />
news of the bomb outrage came through I rang him and told him<br />
of the incident. He was down here very quickly* and again<br />
early the following morning. He had made it very plain that<br />
his attitude was the same as mine that we must both co-operate<br />
to make sure that maximum security was provided for the<br />
conference in the Hilton Hotel and for the movement to Bowral<br />
and for our guests while they were at Bowral, I believe that<br />
the co-operation between the State and the Commormiealth in<br />
relation to that has been good. I am quite sure that his own<br />
attitude significantly contributed to it,<br />
Mr. Fraser, does the Commonwealth plan to send any police<br />
officers overseas to study anti-terrorism tactics?<br />
There is training, in relation to that undertaken in Australia.<br />
If it was believed that officers needed to go overseas, well<br />
then I am sure that would be done. I think you must appreciate<br />
that government determines that certain things need to be done,<br />
certain objectives attained, There is a trust in those<br />
responsible for the carrying out of that instruction and decisions<br />
that they will do it in a way that's constructive, adequate<br />
and proper,<br />
Sir, is<br />
why was<br />
who had<br />
Mr. Fraser:<br />
Mr. Fraser: that training available to State police and if so,<br />
a state policeman placed in charge of security here<br />
not undergone such training?<br />
I was answering the question in relation to a different matter,<br />
that is the question of international terrorism, which is of<br />
specific Commonwealth responsibility. It was under that<br />
particular responsibility that the call-out was in fact authorised,<br />
It could equally well have been authorised by and Neville Wran<br />
had indicated that either course was satisfactory so far as hie<br />
is concerned as aid to the civil power. But in all the<br />
circumstances it was felt that the course that was taken was<br />
the better one. That is the particular responsibility of the<br />
Commonwealth's and the training that is encompassed-is by the.<br />
Commonwealth. I have indicated that there will be an examination<br />
as a result of this of the co-operative arrangements that exist<br />
between the states and the Commonwealth. I am quite certain<br />
that Heville Wran and myself will both want that. We will1 want<br />
to satisfy ourselves that our own people are doing everything<br />
possible and everything necessary in the light of the somewhat<br />
different circuw~ tances into which that event took Australia.<br />
What has been the total cost of the conference and the security<br />
that has gone into it?<br />
The conference estimates earlier given,* to me were round about<br />
half a million but I wouldn't be surprised if it is noticeably </p>
<p>above that figure. But let me also say thats in terms of<br />
the cost to the Commonwealth and the result, I believe<br />
that it is very well worth while. Every cent, has given<br />
its value in terms of the resul~ ts of the conference. I<br />
haven't got estimates of the costs of the security operation<br />
but$ again, I believe that it would have been the general<br />
wish of the overwhelming majority of Australians to make<br />
sure that we did everything that we could to ensure the<br />
security of the conference of its members and of the<br />
delegations. After the bomb explosion quite plainly if<br />
' there was a doubt about whether a particular thing ought<br />
to be done or not the decision was made to do it, if it<br />
was an additional security item,<br />
S* G9: Before we respond to the Prime Minister for Fiji I think<br />
I would be lacking in my candor with you if I didn't say<br />
just two things on this question, without in any way<br />
presuming to interfere in the ' domestic aspects of it. The<br />
first is that, particularly for those heads of government<br />
and their Ministers, people like myself who live and work<br />
in an international environment, we are very conscious<br />
all the time that events of this kind happen, not because<br />
of deficiencies in security arrangements, but despite them.<br />
There was an overwhelming feeling on the part of all the<br />
heads of government who were here that immense precautions<br />
had been taken and a great deal of care had been lavished on<br />
adequacy of security arrangements. I think it is fair to say<br />
that no head of government, and you all have access to them<br />
and you will know of your own conversations with them how<br />
real this is, that at no stage in this meeting in their<br />
stay in Australia has any head of governmient or any senior<br />
official or Minister of government felt a sense of insecurity,<br />
whether we were here in Sydney or in Bowral, everyone felt<br />
that everything possible was being done and that you were<br />
in a happy and friendly land which like all other countries<br />
in the world are prone from time to time to acts of mradness<br />
and lunacy which we have got to live with.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, do the heads of government feel that the<br />
bombing may not have occurred if the Indian Prime Minister<br />
was not here and if the conferences is ended why are many<br />
heads of government staying in the country for days?<br />
Mr, Fraser: They have different interests in Australia and I am delighted<br />
that they are staying here to pursue those interests. One of<br />
things which I am sure has been conveyed to them is that I<br />
hope that they will be able to enjoy some time in Australia<br />
and not merely be here for the strict time of the conference.<br />
One president I don't know the individual movements and when<br />
each head of government is moving out at least one has<br />
relatives in Australia, as I think you know, and others have<br />
interests here. One I know wishes to visit a particular<br />
fanming enterpriFe because it is not unrelated to an enterprise<br />
that I think he wants to see introduced into his own country*<br />
1, I </p>
<p>I am delighted that heads of governm~ ent, those that can,<br />
are staying here a little longer and now that the conference<br />
is over don't feel im~ pelled to move out of Australia forthwith.<br />
Thank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
