<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6332</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HEALTH AND RESEARCH EMPLOYEES&#039; ASSOCIATION, SYDNEY, 5 MARCH 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006332.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Q~ sNz Y4A; A<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
HEALTH AND RESEARCH EMPLOYEES' ASSOCIATION<br />
SYDNEY., 5 MARCH 198LI<br />
MR CHAIRMAN, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN,<br />
IAM VERY PLEASED TO HAVE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO AD) DRESS YOUR<br />
AS SOCI AT IONTODAY<br />
IS THE FIRST ANNIVERSARY OF THE PRESENT LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENT'S ELECTION TO OFFICEAMONG<br />
THE MANY ACHIEVEMENTS OF THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN THE<br />
INTRODUCTION OF MEDICAREWITH<br />
THIS HISTORIC INITIATIVE ALL AUSTRALIANS NOW HAVE A<br />
NEW, SIMPLER AND FAIRER HEALTH INS! JRANCE SYSTEMYOUR<br />
ASSOCIATION ANID ITS MEMBERS ARE PARTICULARLY WELL<br />
PLACED TO APPRECIATE THE ADVANTAGES THIS BRINGS FOR THE<br />
COMMUNITY GENERALLY-QUITE APART FROM IMPROVED COMMNUNITY<br />
HEALTH STANDARDS, OTHER CONCRETE ADVANTAGES INCLUDE THE<br />
ELIMINATIOJ4~ OF MANY COMPLEX BILLING PROCEDURES THAT HAD<br />
PREVIOUSLY DIVERTED VALUABLE RESOURCES FROM IMPORTANT<br />
SERVICE ACTIVITIES INTO UNNECESSARY ADM1NISTRATIVF AND /* 1 </p>
<p>SUPPORT ACTIVITIES. UNDER MEDICARE THOSE SAME RESOURCES<br />
WILL BE USED TO PROVIDE BETTER HEALTH SERVICES FOR ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS. THERE ARE FUNDAMENTAL AND COMPELLING REASONS WHY THE<br />
INTRODUCTION OF MEDICARE HAS BEEN CLOSE TO THE TOP OF THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S AGENDAIT<br />
WAS TOTALLY UNACCEPTABLE THAT NEARLY 2 MILLION<br />
AUSTRALIANS WERE FOR SEVERAL YEARS WITHOUT PRIVATE INSURANCE<br />
OR THE COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT'S COVER PROVIDED TO<br />
PENSIONERS, UNEMPLOYED AND LOW INCOME EARNERS. MANY OF THE<br />
TWO MILLION WERE SIMPLY ' JNABLE TO AFFORD THE COST OF PRIVATE<br />
INSURANCE-IRONICALLY THEY AT THE SAME TIME FACED POTENTIAL<br />
FINANCIAL RUIN IN THE EVENT OF MAJOR ILLNESSTHE<br />
LABOR GOVERNMENT WAS ELECTED, AMONG OTHER THINGS, TO<br />
REDRESS THIS SITUATION-WITH MEDICARE AUSTRALIANS NOW HAVE<br />
A STABLE SYSTEM WHICH PROVIDES EVERYONE WITH COVER AT A FAIR<br />
COSTUNDER THE PREVIOUS ARRANGEMENTS THERE WAS SOME PROVISION * FOR<br />
LOW INCOME PENSIONERS AND FAMILIES TO RECEIVE FREE CAREBUT<br />
THE INCOM4E TEST ON THESE BENEFITS WAS TOO RESTRICTIVE;<br />
MANY FAMILIES WITH INCOMES JUST A LITTLE OVER THE CUT-OFF<br />
POINT SIMPLY COULD NOT AFFORD THE $ 13 MINIMUM PER WEEK WHICH </p>
<p>WAS THE COST OF BASIC COVER. FAMILIES WITH INCOMES AS LOW<br />
AS $ 200 PER WEEK FAILED TO QUALIFY FOR THE CONCESSIONA'-<br />
ARRANGEMENTS. IF PRE\ VIOUS HEALTH SCHEMES HAD CONTINUED, rHE<br />
COST OF FAMILY COVER IN FEBRUARY 1984 WOULD CERTAINLY HAVE<br />
BEEN GREAT ER THAN $ 15 PER WEEK.<br />
MEDICARE ENSURES THAT NO AUSTRALIAN NEED NOW FEAR THAT<br />
TREATMENT OF SICKNESS WILL HAVE CRIPPLING FINANCIAL<br />
CONSEQUENCES. ALL AUSTRALIANS ARE GUARANTEED -AS A BASIC<br />
RIGH T PROTECTION AGAINST THE FINANCIAL IMPACT OF ESSENTIAL<br />
MEDICAL AND HOSPITAL TREATMENTALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS ARE CONTRIBUTING TO0 THE COST OF MEDICARE<br />
ACCORDING TO THEIR CAPACITY TO PAY. IMPORTANTLY A MAJORITY<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN FAMILIES ARE NOW PAYING LESS FOR HEALTH COVER<br />
UNDER MEDICARE.<br />
A VITAL REASON FOR MOVING TO REFORM THE HEALTH INSURANCE<br />
SYSTEM IS T0 CURB THE INCREASE IN COSTS OF HEALTH CARE,<br />
WHETHER THES-E COSI'S ARE BORNE BY THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE OR<br />
BY INDIVIDUAL PATIENTSTHE<br />
UPWARD TREND IN COSTS NEEDS TO BE RECOGNISED. HEALTH<br />
COSTS AS A PERCENTAGE OF AUSTRALIA'S NATrONAL PRODUCT<br />
INCREASED SUBSTANTIALLY DURING THE 1970' s -RISING FROM OVER<br />
5.7 PER CENT To 8.00 PER CENT OF GDP IN THE PERIOD-</p>
<p>MANY FACTORS WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR TfHIS; SOME OF THESE WERE<br />
SOCIAl-LY DESIRABLE ANT) NECESSARY FOR EXAMPLE THE EQUAL PAY<br />
DECISION OF 1973; OTHER ELEMENTS, SUCH AS THOSE INVOLVING<br />
MEDICAL FRAUD AND OVERSERVICING, WERE A HEAVY DRAIN ON THE<br />
PUBLIC PURSE-WHAT IS CLEAR IS THAT GOVERNMENTS MUST TAKE<br />
VIGOROUS AND EFFECTIVE ACTION TO CONTAIN INCREASING MEDICAL<br />
SERVICE COSTS TO THE EXTENT POSSIBLEMEDICARE<br />
THROUGH A SINGLE NATIONAL ORGANISATION, AIMS TO<br />
BRING NEEDED EFFICIENCIES AND ECONOMIES TO THE<br />
ADMINISTRATION OF THE NATIONAL HEALTH SYSTEMTHE<br />
INTRODUCTION OF MEDICARE HAS BEEN ACC: OMPANIED' BY THE<br />
ESTABLISHMENT OF ONE OF THE LARGEST AND MOST MODERN COMPUTER<br />
NETWORKS IN THE WORLD. THIS SYSTEM WILL ENSURE THAT THE<br />
STANDARD OF ADMINISTRATIVE BACKUP AND SUPPORT IS SECOND TO<br />
N ON EIT<br />
. WILL ALSO PROVIDE-THE MEANS TO DETECT QUICKLY ATTEMPTS TO<br />
ABUSE MEDICARE-WHILE ONLY A SMALL MINORITY OF DOCTORS ARE<br />
INVOLVED IN QUESTIONABLE PRACTICES, SUCH A CAPACITY IS<br />
NEEDED-INDEED WE HAVE JUDGED IT RECESSARY TO EXTEND THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S ABILITY TO INVESTIGATE AND DEAL WITH ABUSES<br />
WHERE THEY EXIST IF RISING COSTS ARE TO B. E EFFECTIVELY<br />
CONTA INED-</p>
<p>WIDER APPLICATION OF BULK BILLING BY DOCTORS SHOULD ALSO<br />
LEAD TO REDUCED COSTS. BULK BILLING, APART FROM BEING MORE<br />
COt'VENIENT AND ZHEAPER TO THE PATIENT, LOWERS ADMINISTRATIVE<br />
COSTS FOR BOTH THE DOCTORS AND THE GOVERNMENT. THE<br />
PROPORTION OF MEDICAL CLAIMS THAT ARE BULK-BILLED IS<br />
EXPECTED TO INCREASE WITHIN 3 MONTHS FROM ABOUT 30 PER CENT,<br />
WHICH REFLECTS THE NUMBER OF PENSIONER PATIENTS, TO ABOUT<br />
PER CENT. THE GOVERNMENT IS PLEASED THAT VIRTUALLY ALL<br />
DOCTORS HAVE CONTINUED THEIR PRACTICE OF BULK BILLING<br />
PENSIONERS AND THE DISADVANTAGED IN OUR COMMUNITY, AND THAT<br />
AN INCREASING NUMBER ARE EXTENDING THIS TO ALL PATIENTS.<br />
BULK BILLING SHOULD BECOME THE NORM CERTAINLY THIS IS WHAT<br />
THE GOVERNMENT INTENDS.<br />
WE ARE ALSO COMMITED TO CONTAINING COSTS ON. THE HOSPITAL<br />
SIDE OF AUSTRALIA'S HEALTH BUDGET. UNLIKE THE HOSPITAL<br />
FUNDING ARRANGEMENTS UNDER MEDIBANK AND IN THE EARLY FRASER<br />
YEARS, WE WILL NOT BE SHARING THE COSTS OF STATE HOSPITAL<br />
SYSTEMS ON A DOLLAR FOR DOLLAR BASIS. THE OPEN-ENDED<br />
COMMITMENT INVOLVED IN THAT SYSTEM CONSII) E : ABLY REDUCED THE<br />
INCENTIVES FOR STATE GOVERNMENTS TO CONTAIN THE COSTS OF<br />
THEIR HOSPITAL SYSTEMS.<br />
WE ARE INSTEAD PROVIDING A GREATER LEVEL OF ASSISTANCE TO<br />
THE STATES FOR THEIR HOSPITALS, BUT ON A RESPONSIBLE BASIS<br />
WHICH ESTABLISHES AT THE BEGINNING OF THE YEAR THEIR LEVEL </p>
<p>OF COMMONWEALTH FUNDS. THiIS ENABLES STATE HOSPITALS TO<br />
BUDGET ACCORDINGLY AND REPRESENTS A REAL INCENTIVE TO THEM<br />
TO CONTAIN COSTS.<br />
AN IMPORTANT PART OF THE HOSPITAL ARRANGEMENTS ARE SPELT OUT<br />
IN THE MEDICARE AGREEMENTS WITH THE STATES, ALL OF WHICH ARE<br />
NOW SIGNED, SEALED AND DELIVERED-QUEENSLAND SHOWED SOME<br />
RELUCTANCE. THERE WJAS A TEMPTATION TO BUY OUR WAY OUT OF<br />
ARGUMENT IN THIS AREA -NEEDLESS TO SAY I DO NOT GIVE IN TO<br />
SUCH TEMPTATIONSWHAT WE HAVE AGREED WITH QUEENSLAND, TO ENSURE THAT IT IS<br />
EQUITABLY TREATED, IS TO. ASK THE GRANTS COMMISSION TO GIVE<br />
SPECIAL CONSIDERATION TO THE IMPACT OF THE MEDICARE GRANTS<br />
ON QUEENSLAND'S FINANCIAL POSITION, AND TO RECOMMEND ANY<br />
NECESSARY ADJUSTMENTS IN THE TAX SHARING AND IDENTIFIED<br />
HEALTH GRANTS-HAVE ASSURED THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT<br />
THAT THE COMMONWEALTH WILL RESPOND ON THE BASIS OF PROMPT<br />
AND FULL CONSIDERATION OF THE-GRANTS COMMISSION'S<br />
RECOMMENDATI-ONS ON THIS MATTERANOTHER<br />
INSTANCE OF THE COST CONTMiNMENT STRATEGY BEING<br />
PURSUED BY THE GOVERNMENT IS THE CHANGES WE ARE MAKING TO<br />
PRIVATE PRACTICE RIGHTS FOR DIAGNOSITC SPECIALISTS IN PUBLIC<br />
HOSPITALS.-AM REFERRING HERE TO THE RIGHT OF SALARIED AND<br />
VISITING DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS TO TREAT' THEIR PRIVATE </p>
<p>PATIENTS WITHIN PUBLIC HOSPTIALS, USIN4G HOSPITAL EQUIPMENT<br />
AND FACILITIES, AND CHARGING THOSE PATIENTS ON A FEE FOR<br />
SERVICE BASIS. THESE PRIVATE PRACTICE RIGHTS DO NOT AFFECT<br />
THE TREATMENT OF PUBLIC PATIENTS; NOR DO THEY AFFECT THE<br />
RIGHTS OF DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS TO TREAT PATIENTS OUTSIDE<br />
PUBLIC HOSPITALS.<br />
RECOGNISE THAT PRIVATE PRACTICE RIGHTS ARE ESSENTIAL IF WE<br />
ARE TO CONTINUE TO ATTRACT THE HIGHEST QUALITY MEDICAL STAFF<br />
TO OUR PUBLIC HOSPITALS. BUT FOR SOME YEARS, CONCERN HAS<br />
BEEN EXPRESSED BY COMMONWEALTH AND STATE HEALTH MINISTERS,<br />
AND BY THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENTIS JAMISON REPORT INTO<br />
HOSPITALS, ABOUT THESE RIGHTS OF PRIVATE PRACTICE.<br />
SEVERAL REPORTS TO GOVERNMENT HAVE HIGHLIGHTED QUITE<br />
UNSATISFACTORY FEATURES OF CURRENT PRIVATE PRACTICE<br />
ARRANGEMENTS, SOME VISITING DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS HAVE<br />
BEEN DRAWING INORDINATELY HIGH INOMCES FROM THE PUBLIC<br />
HOSPITAL SYSTEM APPROXIMATELY A QUARTER OF A MILLION<br />
DOLLARS NET IN SOME KNOWN CASES. IN SOME STATES SALARIED<br />
DIAGNOSTICIANS HAVE ALSO BEEN EARNING MORE FROM PRIVATE WORK<br />
THAN THROUGH THEIR SALARIED PUBLIC" WORK.<br />
As A RESULT, LATE LAST YEAR, DR BLEWETT PROPOSED NEW<br />
ARRANGEMENTS AIMED AT INCREASING THE PUBLIC ACCOUNTABILITY<br />
OF DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS AND REDUCING THE INCENTIVES TO </p>
<p>8.<br />
REQUEST AND PERFORM DIAGNOSTIC TESTS. THESE ARRANGMENTS<br />
WOULD HAVE ENSURED, FIRST, THAT HOSPITALS CHARGE THE<br />
SPECIALISTS FOR THE USE OF EQUIPMENT AND OTHER FACILITIES;<br />
SECOND, THAT HOSPITALS, RATHER THAN THE DOCTORS, WOULD BILL<br />
PATIENTS; THIRD, THAT REASONABLE RESTRAINTS WOULD BE PLACED<br />
ON THE INCOMES DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS COULD EARN; AND<br />
FINALLY THAT THE DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS WOULD CHARGE NO MORE<br />
THAN THE SCHEDULE FEE.<br />
THE OUTCOME OF THE NEGOTIATIONS WHICH FOLLOWED BETWEEN DR<br />
BLEWETT AND THE AMA WAS A VERY SUBSTANTIAL COMPROMISE ON THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S PART. WE AGREED THAT THE QUESTION OF LIMITS ON<br />
THE INCOMES OF DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS WOULD BE REFERRED TO A<br />
REPRESENTATIVE INQUIRY THE PENNINGTON INQUIRY. WE<br />
ACKNOWLEDGED THAT WHAT WAS INVOLVED WENT TO SENSITIVE AND<br />
IMPORTANT ISSUES; WE DID NOT WANT TO DRIVE SPECIALISTS,<br />
ESPECIALLY SALARIED SPECIALISTS, OUT OF THE PUBLIC HOSPITAL<br />
SYSTEM. WE HAD EXPECTED THAT, AS A RESULT OF OUR COMPROMISE, THE<br />
SPECIALISTS WOULD AGREE TO INTERIM CONTRACTS WHICH WOULD<br />
COVER THE OTHER ASPECTS OF THE PROPOSED ARRANGEMENTS.<br />
HOWEVER, AS YOU WOULD ALL KNOW, SOME ELEMENTS OF THE MEDICAL<br />
PROFESSION HAVE NOW OBJECTED TO OUR INSISTENCE THAT<br />
DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTSI CHARGES IN PUBLIC HOSPITALS BE<br />
LIMITED TO THE SCHEDULE FEE-</p>
<p>ONE OF THE PROBLEMS WE HAVE FACED IN THIS PROCESS IS THAT<br />
THE AMA HAS BEEN HAPPY TO OBTAIN CONCESSIONS FROM THE<br />
GOVERNMENT, BUT HAS THEN BEEN UNABLE TO RESPOND WITH BINDING<br />
COMMITMENTS FROM THE MEDICAL PROFESSIONTHIS<br />
NEGOTIATION CANJNOT ALL BE ONE WAY. THE GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
BEEN PREPARED TO DEMONSTRATE CONSIDERABLE FLEXIBILITY IN THE<br />
INTERESTS OF SECURING AGREEMENT. ANY AGREEMENT, HOWEVER,<br />
REQUIRES TWO TO TANGO" It; THE GOVERNMENT AND THE COMMUNITY AT<br />
LARGE COULD QUITE LEGITIMATELY HAVE EXPECTED A LESS<br />
UNCOMPROMISING AND RIGID STAN4D FROM THE DOCTORS, IF ONLY OUT<br />
OF RECOGNITION OF PATIENTS IINTERESTS. THERE ARE, HOWEVER,<br />
LIMITS TO THE GOVERNMENT'S FLEXIBILITY-IT HAS A<br />
RESPONSIBILITY OT SECURE IMPORTANT NATIONAL INTERESTS-ONE<br />
SUCH INTEREST IS THE CONTAINMENT OF RISING HEALTH COSTSHENCE<br />
OUR INSISTENCE THAT DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS, WHO HAVE<br />
SUCH PRIVILEGED ACCESS TO PUBLIC FACILITIES, SHOULD CHARGE<br />
NO MORE THAN THE SCHEDULE FEE.<br />
LAST WEEK BOTH DR BLEWETT AND THE FOUR STATE LABOR<br />
GOVERNMENTS INITIATED ACTION TO ENSURE TrHAT rHE SCHEDULE FEE<br />
IS CHARGED FOR DIAGNOSTIC SERVICES IN PUBLIC HOSPTIALS. IN<br />
THIS WAY THESE LABOR GOVERNM~ ENTS ARE SEEKING TO ENSURE THAT<br />
THE PEOPLE IN THEIR STATES CAN RECEIV'E TIE MEDICARE BENEFITS<br />
TO WHICH THEY ARE ENTITLED-WE WERE NOT PREPARED TO ALLOW<br />
THE DISPUTE WITH THE DIAGNOSTICIANS TO REACH A STAGE WHERE </p>
<p>THE PUBLIC WOULD BE INCONVENIENCED THROUGH THE REFUSAL OF<br />
MEDICARE BENEFITS TO PPTIENTS WHOSE SPECIALISTS HAD NOT<br />
SIGNED AN AGREEMENT TO CHARGE THE SCHEDULE FEE. IN<br />
QUEENSLAND AND TASMANIA, RIGHTS OF PRIVATE PRACTICE<br />
ARRANGEMENTS ARE VERY LIMITED; THERE WE WILL REQUIRE<br />
DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS TO AGREE IN WRITING TO CHARGE THE<br />
SCHEDULE FEE.<br />
THERE HAS BEEN A LOT OF NONSENSE TALKED ABOUT THE MINISTER<br />
FOR HEALTH HAVING SOME ABSOLUTE POWER TO SET THESE FEES. ON<br />
THE CONTRARY, THE FEES SET OUT IN iHE MEDICAL BENEFITS<br />
SCHEDULE ARE NOT DETERMINED BY THE MINISTER OR BY THE<br />
GOVERNMENT, BUT BY AN INDEPENDENT TRIBUNAL TO WH! ICH BOTH THE<br />
GOVERNMENT AND THE MEDICAL PROFESSION MAKE SUBMISSIONS. THE<br />
CURRENT TRIBUNAL HEARING IS BEING CHAIRED BY THE DEPUTY<br />
PRESIDENT OF rHE ARBITRATION COMMISSION, MR JUSTICE<br />
MCKENZIE.<br />
WE-MUST GET THIS DISPUTE INTO PERSPECTIVE. THE GREAT<br />
MAJORITY OF DIAGNOSTIC SPECIALISTS ALREADY CHARGE NO MORE<br />
THAN THE SCHEDULE FEE. AND MANY ALREADY HAVE CONTRACTS WITH<br />
STATE HSOPITAL SYSTEMS WHICH LIMIT' THEIR CHARGES TO THAT<br />
SCHEDULE FEE. THOSE WHO ARE HOLDING OUT AGAINST THE NEW<br />
ARRANGEMENTS ARE DOING SO, AT LEAST IN MANY CASES, FOR<br />
NARROW AND SELFISH REASONS-</p>
<p>LET ME STREES THAT THIS GOVERNMENT HAS NO INTENTION OF<br />
NATIONALISING HEALTH CARE IN THIS COUNTRY. WHILE WE ARE<br />
COMM ITTED TO CURB ING GROWTH I N COS TS AND ENSUR ING THE<br />
EFFICIENCY OF THE OVERALL SYSTEM, THERE IS NO PLAN TO END<br />
PRIVATE P RACTJCE. WE REGARD PRIVATE PRACTICE AS A<br />
FUNDAMENTAL AND ESSENTIAL PART OF OUR HEALTH CARE SYSTEMANOTHER<br />
IMPORTANT PART OF my GOVERNMENT'S AIM TO SECURE<br />
RATIONALISATION OF HEALTH CARE EXPENDITURES, IS THE NEW<br />
SYSTEM OF PRIVATE HOSPITAL SUBSIDIESTHE<br />
CHANGES WE HAVE MADE WERE LONG OVERDUEPRIVATE<br />
HOSPITALS ARE A VERY DIVERSE RANGE OF INSTITUTIONSAT<br />
ONE EXTREME ARE THE MAJOR SURGICAL HOSPITALS, MOSTLY RUN<br />
BY RELIGIOUS OR CHARITABLE ORGANISATIONS, WHICH PROVIDE A<br />
LEVEL OF CARE AND SERVICES COMPARABLE WITH THAT IN THE MAJOR<br />
PUBLIC HOSPITALS. AT THE OTHER EXTREME ARE MANY SMALLER<br />
INSTITUTIONS, WHICH ARE IN EF-FECT NO MORE THAN NURSING<br />
HOMES. DESPITE THIE DIFFERENCE IN COST STRUCTURES BETWEEN<br />
THESE TWO EXTREMES, THE SAME INSURANCE BENEFITS AND<br />
COMMONWEALTH SUBSIDIES USED TO BE-' PAID TO0 BOTH-MANY<br />
PRIVATE HOSPITALS CAPITALISED ON THIS SITUATION, SOME DREW<br />
INORDINATELY HIGH PROFITS FROM THE SYSTEM. OTHERS WERE ABLE<br />
TO CONTINUE OPERATING WHEN THEY WERE NOT OTHERWISE<br />
ECONOMI1CALLY VIABLE-THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT, WHILE </p>
<p>12.<br />
DEDICATED TO SECURING EFFICIENCY IN THE PUBLIC HOSPITAL<br />
SYSTEM, DID NOTHING TO ADDRESS THIS OBVIOUSLY ANOMALOUS<br />
S ITUAT IONTHE<br />
NEW SYSTEM OF CATEGORISATION OF PRIVATE HOSPITALS SEEKS<br />
TO ENSURE THAT BENEFITS AND BED SUBSIDIES; WILL BE FAR MORE<br />
CLOSELY RELATED TO THE LEVEL OF SERVICE AND THE COST<br />
STRUCTURE OF SPECIFIC HOSPITALS.<br />
WHILE CONVINCED OF THE FAIR AND EQUITABLE CHARACTER OF THE<br />
CATEGORISATION PRINCIPLE, THE GOVERNMENT IS AWARE THAT ITS<br />
DETAILED APPLICATION WILL REQUIRE SOME FINE-TUNING.<br />
ALREADY WE ARE AWARE THAT SOME OF THE CATEGORISATION RULES<br />
NEED TO BE MORE GENEROUS. WE HAVE DECIDED ALSO THAT IT IS<br />
NECESSARY TO GIVE THE MINISTER FOR HEALTH A WIDER<br />
DISRETIONARY POWER TO UPGRADE INDIVIDUAL HOSPITALS-ON THE<br />
BASIS OF EVIDENCE ALREADY AVAILABLE WE INTEND IMMEDIATELY TO<br />
UPGRADE 14 HOSPITALS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA FROM CATEGORY 3 TO<br />
CATEGORY 2, AND AS A RESULT, TO INCREASE THE BENEFITS<br />
PAYABLE FOR PATIENTS IN THESE HOSPITALS 1BY $ 30 A DAY.<br />
SEVERAL OTHER CASES ARE UNDER CLOSS CONSIDERATION.<br />
IN RELATION TO PSYCHIATRIC PRIVATE HOSPITALS I CAN GIVE A<br />
CLEAR UNDERrAKING THAT THE BETTER OF THESE INSTITUTIONS WILL<br />
BE UPGRADED AS SOON AS THE PRIVATE HOSPITAL INDUSTRY AND THE </p>
<p>13.<br />
MINISTER FOR HEALTH CAN DEVELOP SUITABLE PRINCIPLES FOR<br />
DETERMINING WHICH INSTITUTIONS PROVIDE HIGHER LEVELS OF<br />
CARE. FINALLY, LET ME SAY THAT ANY PRIVATE HOSPITAL WHICH CAN<br />
OBJECTIVELY PROVE THAT, GIVEN REASONABLE OCCUPANCY LEVELS,<br />
IT CANNOT OPERATE ON THE EXISTING BENEFITS WILL BE GIVEN<br />
SYMPATHETIC CONSIDERATION FOR RECATEGORISING. IN THIS WE<br />
PRESUME THE HOSPITAL WILL BE PREPARED TO MAKE A FULL AND<br />
HONEST DISCLOSURE OF ITS OPERATING COSTS. THE GOVERNMENT<br />
OBVIOUSLY CANNOT BE EXPECTED TO BE SYMPATHETIC TO SITUATIONS<br />
IN WHICH SOME HOSPITALS SIMPLY " CRY POOR" BECAUSE PREVIOUS<br />
SUBSTANTIAL PROFITS ARE NOW BEING REDUCED TO REASONABLE<br />
LEVELS. I BELIEVE THE INTRODUCTION OF MEDICARE REPRESENTS A<br />
SIGNIFICANT ' ACHIEVEMENT OF OUR FIRST YEAR IN OFFICE. IT HAS<br />
BEEN AN EVENTFUL AND PRODUCTIVE YEAR.<br />
THE RAPID INTRODUCTION OF MEDICARE AND ITS ACCEPTANCE BY<br />
MOST AUSTRALIANS ARE DEMONSTRATED BY THE FACT THAT OVER 7.3<br />
MILLION MEDICARE CARDS HAVE BEEN I-SSUED, COVERING OVER 14<br />
MILLION PEOPLE OR WELL OVER 90 PER CENT OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
POPULATION. THIS IS A TRULY REMARKABLE ACHIEVEMENT WHEN YOU<br />
CONSIDER THAT REGISTRATION IS VOLUNTARY AND THAT IT HAS ONLY<br />
BEEN 32 MONTHS SINCE OUR ADVERTISING CAMPAIGN COMMENCED-</p>
<p>14l.<br />
BUT UNFORTUNATELY, IT IS OFTEN THE FEARS AND THE PROBLEMS<br />
WHICH CAPTURE THE HEADLINES. THERE IS USUALLY TOO LITTLE<br />
CREDIT FOR THOSE WORKING HARD BEHIND THE SCENES.<br />
IT IS A TRIBUTE TO THE MINISTER OF HEALTH, DR NEAL BLEWETT,'<br />
AND TO THE OFFICERS OF His DEPARTMENT AND THE HEALTH<br />
INSURANCE COMMISSION THAT IN JUST ON4E YEAR THEY HAVE<br />
TRANSFORMED MEDICARE FROM NOTHING MORE THAN A POLICY<br />
DOCUMENT TO THE SIMPLE, EQUITABLE, EFFICIENT AND UNIVERSAL<br />
HEALTH SCHEME WE NOW HAVE IN OPERATION. THIS IS A MAJOR<br />
ACHIEVEMENT. THE GOVERNMENT FOR ITS PART IS MORE THAN EVER<br />
CONVINCED OF THE ADVANTAGES MEDICARE IS BRING. ING TO EACH AND<br />
EVERY AUSTRALIAN-WE SHALL CERTAINLY NOT BE DEFLECTED FROM<br />
THE TASK OF CONSOLIDATING AND REINFORCING THOSE ADVANTAGESAFTER<br />
ALL, AS I KNOW YOU WOULD ALL AGREE, MEDICARE AS WE<br />
HAVE DEVELOPED IT PROVIDES AN EXCELLENT MODEL FOR AUSTRALIAN<br />
HEALTH COVER WELL INTO THE 21ST CENTURY-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
