<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7198</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007198.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR IJ1UELDYI A12908 7<br />
Attached io co :' zospondence the Pimeii1 Minister Is sending to<br />
partieGi involvod in the coal industries dispute. 0002%) 3<br />
FOR MEDIA </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANeERRA<br />
Mr R. riarshai.<br />
Chairman Austr1. a11l. i aHno l~ Cionclg sAssociation<br />
GPO Box 1423<br />
RISBALZ 07D 4000<br />
Dear or narohall<br />
I am deeply concerned about developments in the coal<br />
industry end propose to accept the suggestion that I convene<br />
a national tripartite conference to consider a long term<br />
strategy fo: the coal industry.<br />
It is , y hope to convene such a meeting of all the parties<br />
next weel and that we can move constructively to find<br />
sufficient common ground on a strategy to enhance tho<br />
viability of the industry and to avoid a widespread coal<br />
strike. I have made it clear that the Government is<br />
prepared to consider establishing a National Coal Authority<br />
with a central role in the implementation of that strategy.<br />
However that does not extend to vesting that Authority with<br />
direct marketing functions on the model of the various<br />
agricultural commodity boards.<br />
I would aedd that it is difficult to see how such a meeting<br />
could bo successful next week if over the intervening period<br />
there is a further escalation of industrial tension.<br />
Accordingly I ask that all companies refrain from further<br />
retrenchnents until that meeting has been held and its<br />
result-become clear. I have written in similar terms to<br />
the Coal Mining Unions National Liaison Committee asking<br />
that there also be no further industrial action in this<br />
period. A copy of that letter is attached.<br />
Yours s. ncerely<br />
R. J. L. Hawke O0O02, </p>
<p>Jf. PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
Mr J. Maitland<br />
Chairman Coal Mining Unions National<br />
Liaicon Comaittee<br />
3rd Floor<br />
377 Suscoc Street<br />
SYDNEY NSU 2000<br />
Dear Mr Maitland<br />
I am deeply concerned about developments in the coal<br />
industry cnd propose to accept the suggestion that I convene<br />
a nationaL tripartite conference to consider a long term<br />
strategy for the coal industry.<br />
I fully und* rstand your concern about the need to enhance<br />
the viability of the industry and to maintain employment<br />
wherever practicable. While the industry's problems are<br />
complex, ny Government is committed to develop a strategy<br />
that fully involves all parties to help ensure the long term<br />
viability of the industry.<br />
The Government is willing to consider establishing a<br />
National Coal Authority to play a central role in the<br />
implementation of that strategy. We are prepared to listen<br />
to argumant on any subject at the tripatite conference.<br />
However I want it to be clear that the Government believes<br />
that the coal industry would not be assisted if such an<br />
Authority were to be vested with direct marketing functions,<br />
including on the model of the various agricultural commodity<br />
board, as has been suggested.<br />
As you will appreciate, I am in the process of setting up<br />
the rinistry and I am unable to convene a tripartite meeting<br />
this wee:, I propose, however, together with the new<br />
Minister for Primary Industries and Energy, to call a<br />
meeting of Net South Wales and Queensland Government<br />
representatives, the coal unions and the Australian Coal<br />
Association towards the end of next week. 000294 </p>
<p>2<br />
It is my hope that the meeting can move constructively to<br />
find sufficient common ground to avoid a widespread coal<br />
strike. Howevor it is difficult to see how such a meeting<br />
could be oucces3ful next week if over the intervening period<br />
there ic a widoopread strike. Accordingly I ask that all<br />
relevant unions refrain from further industrial action until<br />
that meeting has been held and its results become clear. I<br />
am writing in uimilar terms to the Australian Coal<br />
Association cohing that there also be no further<br />
retrenchments in this period.<br />
I have sent a copy of this letter to Mr Unsworth, the<br />
Premier of Queeonsland, and Mr Marshall of the Australian<br />
Coal Association.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
R. J. L. Hawho 000295 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
