<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10697</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW WITH DAVE HARRISON                RADIO 4TO, TOWNSVILLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/08/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.............................................................................................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It's the biggest tax reform ever, certainly since World War</p>
<p>   II and on the hustings, if I can use that term, the old snake-oil</p>
<p>   charmer himself, the Prime Minister, John Howard to sell his tax</p>
<p>   reform package which includes a 10% GST. As we call it Mr Howard</p>
<p>   a great spot Townsville. Would you agree with that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is a great spot. I went for a walk this morning and it's</p>
<p>   a great spot.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On the new refurbished Strand to be completed shortly with some</p>
<p>   of your money.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's always plenty of Commonwealth money. Peter Lindsay</p>
<p>   here is always makes certain that there is a steady stream of Commonwealth</p>
<p>   money coming to Townsville.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Now, I've got to ask the question: are you a thrill seeker</p>
<p>   putting out a tax reform package when people say tax that's</p>
<p>   more money we have to pay?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, actually this plan will collect less tax than is being collected</p>
<p>   at the present time, so the first thing that should be said about</p>
<p>   it as far as the level of tax is concerned there'll be lower</p>
<p>   tax collections under this plan than at the moment. The country</p>
<p>   needs tax reform everybody knows that, deep down everybody knows</p>
<p>   that we can't go on forever with the present system and what</p>
<p>   we are putting forward is not just a lazy tax cut  I mean</p>
<p>   anybody can offer a lazy tax cut and say look here's a few</p>
<p>   dollars. We're doing more than that, we're offering dollars,</p>
<p>   but we're also offering generational change and reform for</p>
<p>   the long term benefit for the country. And the thing that I want</p>
<p>   most known about this plan is that it is good for Australia because</p>
<p>   it will reduce the cost of producing goods and services in Australia</p>
<p>   by about $10,000 million a year, it will boost our exports by reducing</p>
<p>   the cost of producing them, and all of that has to be good for the</p>
<p>   whole Australian economy so it's in the name of the entire</p>
<p>   Australian economy, more than one individual group, that I ask the</p>
<p>   Australian public to support this plan.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay now ten indirect taxes will go</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Gone completely. The wholesale sales tax ...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But who watches that? Who monitors to make sure it ...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will be a condition of the introduction of the GST that they</p>
<p>   all go. I mean the wholesale sales tax will be abolished by the</p>
<p>   Federal Government, in full without deduction in total, and we'll</p>
<p>   be saying to the States who will get the full proceeds of the GST</p>
<p>   revenue, you can't get that money unless you get rid of your</p>
<p>   bank account debits taxes, those that have them, and financial institutions</p>
<p>   duty, your stamp duty on shares, stamp duty on business conveyances,</p>
<p>   stamp duty on bills of exchange, stamp duty on cheques, promissory</p>
<p>   notes, a whole list of things and the best thing of all, of course</p>
<p>   for regional Australia, for the bush, is that we are going to make</p>
<p>   fuel much cheaper by reducing the fuel excise on heavy trucks and</p>
<p>   rail from 43 cents a litre to 18 cents a litre. Now you know how</p>
<p>   big Australia is, you know how far Townsville is from other parts</p>
<p>   of Queensland and other parts of Australia, and the greatest single</p>
<p>   thing that you can do reduce costs in regional Australia is to cut</p>
<p>   the price of fuel. And by reducing the excise on diesel from 43</p>
<p>   cents a litre to 18 cents a litre, that's a huge boost to the</p>
<p>   bush.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Now the Labor Party incidentally is against that. Their environment</p>
<p>   spokesman said it would be bad for the environment so he's</p>
<p>   against cheaper diesel for the bush.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On the subject of the Labor Party you've flushed them out</p>
<p>   though haven't you because they've got to respond to this?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well of course they have to respond and I think the Australian</p>
<p>   public will want to know...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So we're going to go to an election on tax?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>....whether all the Labor Party offers is a lazy tax cut or</p>
<p>   do they have a real plan for Australia's future?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But given the Labour Party's performance it doesn't become</p>
<p>   L-A-W, does it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it will. I mean, I bet now Mr Beazley will do what Mr Keating</p>
<p>   did it in 1993. When we had a plan in 1993 what Mr Keating and Mr</p>
<p>   Beazley did was to say we won't have a GST, we won't reform</p>
<p>   the system, we'll offer you a tax cut. What did they do? They</p>
<p>   got into office on the strength of that, they immediately took away</p>
<p>   the tax cut and they increased every single indirect tax they could</p>
<p>   put their hands on. The 20% went to 22, the 10% went to 12%, 30%</p>
<p>   went to 32%. Now left with the existing system they will be forced</p>
<p>   to do that again if they win the next election. The only way you</p>
<p>   can avoid putting up existing indirect taxes is to change the system.</p>
<p>   It's either higher indirect taxes off the back of the wholesale</p>
<p>   tax system we now have, or it's the GST. That's the choice</p>
<p>   in the indirect area, you don't have another choice because</p>
<p>   the Government has got to get some revenue from somewhere and the</p>
<p>   indirect tax base is eroding the whole time. I mean this idea that</p>
<p>   the GST is going to hurt the welfare sector couldn't be more</p>
<p>   wrong because unless you protect the indirect tax base you won't</p>
<p>   have the resources to help the welfare sector. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On that subject ACOSS deliver their final verdict on the tax reform</p>
<p>   package this morning in Canberra. Now they've been very guarded,</p>
<p>   do you think they'll give it the thumbs up or will they say</p>
<p>   there needs to be some change?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know, but I understand that they're going</p>
<p>   to be critical of a couple of things, they're going to raise</p>
<p>   questions about the calculations that we have made.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Tax on food?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll come to the tax on food in a minute. But as far as the</p>
<p>   calculations are concerned they've been made by the Federal</p>
<p>   Treasury, they've got the best economic modelling capacity</p>
<p>   in Australia and we in fact said to ACOSS if you have any concerns</p>
<p>   or questions about the modelling, we're prepared to talk to</p>
<p>   you and make the Treasury people available to explain the basis</p>
<p>   of it and to respond to your queries. Well, they haven't taken</p>
<p>   that up so we're a little surprised if they are concerned about</p>
<p>   the calculations that they wouldn't come and talk to us about</p>
<p>   it. </p>
<p>Now the question of food. People say it's tough on the poor</p>
<p>   to include a GST on food. I'd say a number of things about</p>
<p>   that. If you leave food out of the GST there is a solid argument</p>
<p>   that says that that will advantage the rich as much, if not more,</p>
<p>   than the poor and the reason for that is that if you leave food</p>
<p>   out you have to go the full bit. You can't just say we won't</p>
<p>   include fresh food in the GST. What do you do about restaurants?</p>
<p>   What do you do about McDonald's? I mean if you say that food</p>
<p>   is exempt from the GST are we going to exempt McDonald's or</p>
<p>   are you going to put it in? If you exempt McDonald's are you</p>
<p>   going to exempt other restaurants? If you exempt other restaurants</p>
<p>   it means that very well-off people who spend a fortune dining out</p>
<p>   don't pay any GST. Now is that fair to the poor? Of course</p>
<p>   it's not fair to the poor. In Canada you have the ridiculous</p>
<p>   situation where they're arguing over whether a pie in a supermarket</p>
<p>   should be GST free, but a pie heated in a takeaway food shop is</p>
<p>   free of GST. I mean what's the equity of the commonsense in</p>
<p>   that? So the only way that you can only really fairly deal with</p>
<p>   this thing it to put all of it in and have a lower rate of indirect</p>
<p>   tax. I mean the trade-off is a broad base with everything in and</p>
<p>   a lower rate, or a lot of things out but a much higher rate. I mean,</p>
<p>   which we have at the present time. I mean, a lot of people don't</p>
<p>   understand they go into, they pay 12% tax on things like flavoured</p>
<p>   milk and biscuits. You can pay 22% on soaps and detergents, you</p>
<p>   can pay 32% on televisions and videos. I mean that's what we're</p>
<p>   paying at the present time. Now under our system you get rid of</p>
<p>   all of that and you replace it with a single rate 10%. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Would it be fair to say though that people concerned and confused</p>
<p>   about will it stay at 10%. Is that justified - that scare-mongering</p>
<p>   out there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well all I can say is this, that it will be legislated at 10% and</p>
<p>   the law will provide that can't be altered unless you have</p>
<p>   the unanimous agreement of every State and Territory Government,</p>
<p>   the Commonwealth Government and both Houses of Parliament. And I've</p>
<p>   been in politics 24 years and I can tell you those eight Governments</p>
<p>   have never agreed on one thing, let alone on something like this.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Now, if you think there's a better mechanism than that, knowing</p>
<p>   Australian politics, tell me what it is.</p>
<p>QUESTIONS </p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Good morning Mr Howard.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes Les, good morning.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>A couple of simple questions. I'm a pensioner. You're</p>
<p>   going to get a lot of trouble with this I think. I'd like to</p>
<p>   know  medications, prescriptions...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>GST free.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>As you know, all people that are fairly old are being sick people,</p>
<p>   getting sick people. Now we will have to pay this. Now is there</p>
<p>   going to be any rise, or anything whatsoever in our prescriptions</p>
<p>   in going to the chemist?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, your prescription drugs you just raised are GST free,</p>
<p>   and on top of that your pension will be permanently 1.5% above any</p>
<p>   increase in the cost of living as a result of these changes, and</p>
<p>   we've put that 1.5% there as an extra buffer. So whatever the</p>
<p>   price impact is, and we calculate it to be 1.9% across the board</p>
<p>   you will always have this buffer of 1.5%. </p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>But listen, Mr Howard, what does this stand for? I'm talking..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm just telling you what the facts are. I mean you will</p>
<p>   have your view and you're entitled as an Australian.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>It's not a matter of view I just want you to listen to this</p>
<p>   just for a moment.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I answered your question.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>I happened to see the lady on 6o Minutes' talking</p>
<p>   to you the other night, the lady pensioner herself. I'm not</p>
<p>   talking about pensioners that have some money in the bank.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I understand that.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>I'm talking of us people that have all these things to pay</p>
<p>   on improving your health. I myself am getting $162 a week and so</p>
<p>   is my wife. Is it going to affect that money or how much more money</p>
<p>   would I get then.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you'll get a 4% increase up front on the 1st</p>
<p>   of July in the year 2000.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>What would 4% be on $162.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well [inaudible] calculations, we'll do it.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Well there's I'd like to say to you, I hope you don't</p>
<p>   get upset.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you can say anything you like, it's a free country. But</p>
<p>   could I just answer, I'm sorry but you did ask me question</p>
<p>   and I hadn't finished answering it. You get 4% and then the</p>
<p>   guarantee is that whatever the CPI impact of the changes are, and</p>
<p>   we calculate them to be 1.9%, you will always be 1.5% guaranteed</p>
<p>   above that CPI increase.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>I see.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>So that is how it works.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Well okay. That other lady the other night, as I say, on television,</p>
<p>   she was going to explain to you about going into a supermarket and</p>
<p>   the prices, now I worked in a supermarket, I've just retired</p>
<p>   after 20 years, and everything that lady said is true. You people</p>
<p>   and Mr Costello and all you sitting up there, none of you know what's</p>
<p>   going on in supermarkets. Youse want to get around, get into a supermarket</p>
<p>   instead of getting into the mall today, and have a look at the prices.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sir, I'm very interested, andI'd just like you to stay</p>
<p>   for this. You say you worked in a supermarket?</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>I did work in a supermarket.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I believe you. Sir I'm not disbelieving you. So you'll</p>
<p>   therefore know that 20% of the cost of everything that lands on</p>
<p>   a supermarket shelf, particularly in a distant area like Townsville,</p>
<p>   is made up of transport costs.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>We realise, yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And do you realise that the sector that gets the biggest single</p>
<p>   price cost reductions under this package is the transport sector,</p>
<p>   because of the reductions in fuel excise? And it's because</p>
<p>   of those reduced transport costs that the price of many articles</p>
<p>   on supermarket shelves will fall and that the increases in relation</p>
<p>   to others will be a lot less than 10%. And that is why you ought</p>
<p>   to believe me when I say that the across the board increase is only</p>
<p>   just under 2% rather than 10%.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Well what I was trying to stress to you Mr Howard, you just made</p>
<p>   a statement. All right that is true possibly. But I'm going</p>
<p>   to ask you again, I repeat...</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Hang on Les...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think you've done well. You asked me one, I asked you one</p>
<p>   and I think we're square.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay, we've got to move on. Thanks for your call. Bye bye.</p>
<p>   Wayne, hello.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Yes good morning Mr Howard.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Good morning Wayne.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>How are you today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm all right thanks, nice to be in North Queensland.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>It's a beautiful place isn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's a fantastic place and it will be even better under this</p>
<p>   tax plan because transport costs will be a lot cheaper.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Well fingers crossed, yes. One question: I was listening to an</p>
<p>   article on the radio the other day regarding the cost of a bottle</p>
<p>   of wine. Now wine has a 22% sales tax I understand.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well actually the...I think the wholesale sales tax on wine is</p>
<p>   41%. It's a special rate. Anyway we're changing all of</p>
<p>   that. Anyway go ahead, I'm sorry.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Okay. Those wholesale taxes are going away aren't they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They are going away but they're being replaced by a wine equalisation</p>
<p>   tax. The effect of this is essentially that the standard 4 litre</p>
<p>   cask will go up by about the normal CPI rise of 1.9 and in relation</p>
<p>   to medium and higher price bottles the increase will be slightly</p>
<p>   more. But generally speaking what we've done is in line with</p>
<p>   what the wine industry has put to us. The price of ordinary beer</p>
<p>   on a per stubby, per unit basis will simply rise by the CPI adjustment</p>
<p>   and the price of light beer will fall a little. And what happens</p>
<p>   to whisky, it remains the same. It's already heavily taxed.</p>
<p>   And that's essentially it on alcohol.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Getting back to the bottle of wine, now the wholesale or the indirect</p>
<p>   taxes are coming off, the 10% tax is going on, the GST, so by rights</p>
<p>   that should make a bottle of wine cheaper than what it is now.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, well, we took the view that if you are having a situation where</p>
<p>   there were some price adjustments in relation to other items it</p>
<p>   wasn't justifiable to reduce the price of wine. Wine is already</p>
<p>   particularly, cask wine in Australia is cheap, very cheap by world</p>
<p>   standards. The great boon to the wine industry out of this of course</p>
<p>   is that there exports will be GST free and that is a huge boost</p>
<p>   to the Australian wine industry.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Okay Wayne, have to leave it there. Thanks for your call, bye bye.</p>
<p>   Graham good morning.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Good morning Mr Howard, how are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm very well Graham.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Welcome to northern Queensland. I've got two quick questions.</p>
<p>   If I was a primary producer and I was selling my items to the wholesaler,</p>
<p>   would there be a 10% GST on that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yep, he gets it back.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Sorry.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He gets it back.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>He gets it back. And what about when the wholesaler sells it to...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there's another one but he then gets it back too. I</p>
<p>   mean the way a GST works is that it is imposed at every point in</p>
<p>   the chain. But all the intermediates get it back and it's borne</p>
<p>   at the point of consumption.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>So in other words, what it boils down to it's just on the</p>
<p>   retail price of the food.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's right. It's borne at the point of consumption,</p>
<p>   that's right. And you see that's the great virtue of it.</p>
<p>   For a farmer or anybody else in business you will now get all of</p>
<p>   your inputs tax free. Where as now, even people who have special</p>
<p>   exemptions from the wholesale sales tax, there is a manufacturers</p>
<p>   exemption, but even those people, they pay wholesale sales tax on</p>
<p>   some items but don't enjoy the exemption. I mean a typical</p>
<p>   example is a computer. There aren't many businesses now that</p>
<p>   don't have computers and I think there's a 22% wholesale</p>
<p>   sales tax on computers. You don't get that back now, but under</p>
<p>   this system you'll pay only 10% and you'll get it back....</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Oh yeah, well that sounds...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>...because it's a business input. And when you go and buy</p>
<p>   petrol, forget about, even apart from the diesel arrangement, if</p>
<p>   you need petrol to run your business, and most businesses need petrol,</p>
<p>   it will be 7 cents a litre cheaper because what we're doing</p>
<p>   with petrol is that we're reducing the excise on petrol to</p>
<p>   the extent necessary to allow in the 10% GST and that equals a 7</p>
<p>   cent reduction per....7 cents every litre reduction in excise</p>
<p>   and you get the whole of that back because the GST is fully rebatable.</p>
<p>   So that means that every litre of petrol used in business is 7 cents</p>
<p>   cheaper.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>So what about the average man on the street, he still pays the</p>
<p>   same?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>His price, the ordinary motorist will not pay any more for petrol</p>
<p>   but of course they won't get that reduction. They won't</p>
<p>   pay any more though. They won't pay any more. It won't</p>
<p>   go up. The price at the pump will be the same and he'll have</p>
<p>   a tax cut. So in relation to petrol his way ahead, and the businessman</p>
<p>   is even further ahead because he gets the seven cents a litre cheaper</p>
<p>   because it's a business input but he also gets the tax cut,</p>
<p>   unless he's, you know, cheating or something.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Thanks for your call Graham, bye bye. Ross good morning.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>Yes good morning Mr Howard, how are you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm very well.</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
<p>That's good. Just a quick question for you: now I earn $30,000</p>
<p>   a year and according to an advertisement in the Sunday Mail last</p>
<p>   week I get a $7.30 increase. Now what I've done is I've</p>
<p>   gone over the last two grocery lists and allowing a 10%...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Do you have any dependants?</p>
<p>CALLER::</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
