<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16358</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Doorstop Interview  Hobart   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PM: Can I say it's great to be here in Tasmania in the lead up to Australia Day. So much of our nation's early history, early settled history is here in this great state. And one of the great things about Tasmania and its economy is how grounded it is, in our national tourism industry. All industries are doing it tough at present with the global financial crisis. Many Australians have been holidaying at home, that is good. But when we look at this state and what it has to offer in terms of richness, of historical tourism sites, as well as the beautiful natural heritage of Tasmania, there's so much on offer.</p>
<p>It's been good to see here this morning at the Museum of Tasmania and the Art Gallery, there plans for future expansion. I'm sure that will go through the decision making processes with the Government in Hobart and in Canberra. But these are the sorts of projects which governments over time need to get behind. You know why? It's good for the economy in terms of building things. It's good for the economy in terms of tourism. And it's good for Australia because it preserves and enhances our heritage.</p>
<p>The other thing I say is this. Being in Tasmania with the Premier and with our local members, underlines the importance of every level of government pulling together and responding to the challenge of the global financial crisis. And this is a challenge as I said before which applies to governments national, governments states, governments local. Through the COAG agreements we've sought to provide additional investment through the states, for teachers, for nurses, and for other workforce needs in critical services. With local government we had a local government summit in Canberra recently, and provided additional resources there. But as I indicated in my remarks just before, this is the beginning. We've got a lot more to do. And the challenges here and for anyone losing their job here in Tasmania are as real for the government that I lead, as anyone else across the country. We are all in this together.</p>
<p>Over to you folks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Can we get your reaction please to some controversial comments by a Melbourne Islamic cleric about rape and domestic violence?</p>
<p>PM: I just looked at the text of these. The quotes as I see them are along the lines of how can a person rape his wife, then in relation to violence the quote is, first of all advise them that is your wives, you beat them, but this is the last resort. These are the reported remarks that come from this particular Islamic cleric. Could I say that these remarks have no place in modern Australia at all, at all. I would call upon this Islamic cleric to publicly apologise and repudiate his remarks. Under no circumstances is sexual violence permissible or acceptable in Australia. Under no circumstances. Under no circumstances are other forms of violence, physical violence towards women, acceptable in Australia. Nor are they acceptable in my view to mainstream Muslim teaching. So I say to this Islamic cleric, Australia will not tolerate these sort of remarks. They don't belong in modern Australia. And he should stand up, repudiate them, and apologise.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: The question of jobs is front and centre for the nation in 2009 as it had been in 2008, in the Government's preparations. Any job loss anywhere is important. It's not just the fact of someone losing their job, it's the human person and their dignity and the impact on their family which lies behind that as well. So what can you do about it?</p>
<p>Three things. One, government through its own investments taking the place to the greatest extent possible of a private sector in retreat, and that is why we've announced $36 billion worth of measures in recent months. And through those measures to create tens of thousands of jobs through these efforts of government, that's the first thing.</p>
<p>The second thing is to help business still retain and invest in their own employees, that's why before Christmas I announced also that we would through our $4.6 billion stimulus package, invest not just in roads, not just in rail, not just in universities, not just in TAFE, but also one to two billion dollars of that representing a temporary investment allowance of ten per cent to businesses, to help them with their bottom line, to help them in turn maintain employment.</p>
<p>The third thing is this, for those who lose their jobs, the government and the community to do everything physically possible to support them, everything physically possible. So I've said before on jobs, I intend to be upfront and direct with the Australian people. This is a huge challenge for all of us, we're all in this together, and we have a strategy for dealing with the challenge. It's going to be tough, it's going to be hard, and it's not going to be perfect. There's a huge world out there which is washing over Australia, but our strategy and our course of action is clear.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Just on the pulp mill, the Labor member for Bass, Jodie Campbell has refused to say about whether or not to support the Gunns pulp. Why do voters have a right to know where she stands in the issue and bring it such a controversial issue in her electorate?</p>
<p>PM: What all of our members support is the proper process being engaged in by Minister Garrett. He's operating under the law. And the law says that this pulp mill has to go through a whole range of environmental approvals under Commonwealth law. Mr Garrett's made clear those elements of the approval process which he has supported, and those where he says further work needs to be done. That's the process Government members support. That's the process the Government supports because our responsibility is to get the balance absolute right, and we intend to do so.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Gunns Ltd have suggested that the Commonwealth might like to pay to upgrade the treatment of their (inaudible), the tertiary standard to something that Peter has spoken about. Can you rule that out or is it something you might consider?</p>
<p>PM: What I want to see is the completion of the approval process. And what the Minister determines independently, this is his independent decision under Commonwealth statute on the question of the impact of any proposed pulp mill on associated marine areas. That's what the law says. Let's see where the regulatory decision lands first.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, on the whaling issue, the Sea Shepherd left Hobart yesterday for more direct action. Japan's repeated its possibility of withdrawing from the International Whaling Commission. What possibility or what progress do you see in diplomatic dialogue with Japan on this?</p>
<p>PM: Minister Garrett through his partners in the IWC, is engaged in a lengthy process concerning the future of so-called scientific whaling. Minister Garrett initiated a review process along these lines at the last meeting of the IWC. My most recent advice is that review process will reach its conclusion sometime around about the middle of this year. It is within that framework that Australia, together with other countries is directly engaging the Government of Japan. We will wait and watch carefully what the outcome of that is, because our policy has not changed one bit. We are engaged however in a process of diplomacy to see with our friends in Tokyo, where we can work our way through this. That's what's underway right now.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: So dependent upon that PM, you would consider legal action (inaudible).</p>
<p>PM: What I'm saying is that diplomacy is a varied and wondrous beast. And that we will see what it produces between now and mid-year.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: (inaudible)</p>
<p>PM: You know, when it comes to the emissions trading scheme, the Carbon Pollution Reduction Scheme. The Carbon Pollution Reduction Scheme sought to get the balance right in taking a responsible course of action against the need to act on climate change and a long term threat of water shortages across so many parts of Australia, and it's a consequence. And the on the other hand, the real impact of the current global economic crisis. These are both real challenges. Responsible governments can't afford to walk away from either. You've actually got to rise to the challenge with both.</p>
<p>I believe we've got the balance right. If you look at the adjustment packages that we have built in for the electricity supply industry and for the emissions intensive trade expose sector of the economy and for households, we believe we've got this balance right and it's one part of a necessary global agreement. And let me say one other thing. In adjusting for the future the lower carbon world, there are enormous economic opportunities which lie in investment, in renewable energy, in carbon capture and storage, as well as energy efficiency. President Obama has been speaking about these things in recent times. I believe President Obama is absolutely right and I thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
