<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41328</transcript-id>
    <title>Final Report of Royal Commission into the Protection and Detention of Children in the Northern Territory</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government today welcomes the final report of the Royal Commission into the Protection and Detention of Children in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth acted swiftly to establish this Royal Commission in July 2016, following concerns over the treatment of children at the Don Dale Youth Detention Centre.</p>
<p>While most of the recommendations of this Royal Commission are matters for the Northern Territory, the Australian Government will now carefully consider those findings directed to the Commonwealth. Importantly, many of the recommendations have wider implications for all jurisdictions.</p>
<p>The Australian Government thanks the Commissioners, the Hon Margaret White AO and Mick Gooda, as well as their staff, for their work over the past 16 months. We also acknowledge the individuals, expert witnesses, government and non-government representatives who came forward to give evidence.</p>
<p>The Government particularly recognises the courage of the children and young people, their families and communities who have shared their views, experiences and personal stories that have been so critical to informing the Royal Commission’s findings.</p>
<p>This is a serious report and the Government is committed to ensuring it carefully, comprehensively and appropriately responds to the substantial work of the Commission.</p>
<p>The Royal Commission’s final report is available on the Royal Commission's website.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
