<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22630</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Tim Cox 936 ABC Radio, Hobart </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What I've been told is essentially publicly known, the loss of property, the continued threat, the change in the wind which, of course, altered the course of things yesterday, with the renewed concern. It's one of those situations where the public is entitled to know everything that's known by the authorities because it can affect their safety. The workers, the men and women in the fire authorities, not only in Tasmania but all around the country, have been amazing and I just want to go there to tell the communities that their fellow Australians are thinking of them and supporting them and they admire the people who are defending their lives and their properties.</p>
<p>COX:</p>
<p>We learnt a lot about that Australian spirit that you talk about at times like this. Is it an interesting exercise for you as Prime Minister to meet the men and women that are actually in the front line fighting these fires?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's always inspiring because they just drop everything and get stuck into it and it's an amazing reaction, it happens all around the country. It's uniformly impressive, that's all I can say. It never ceases to amaze me that over the years as Prime Minister I've visited a lot of these places and they're all a bit different but there's one thing that's in common and that is the indomitable spirit of people and also the willingness of their fellow Australians to risk life and limb, as is so often the case, to save their properties, and that is just terrific, and it's something we ought to be very proud of. People have come from all around Australia on occasions to help, and I know if help is needed all around, both in Tasmania and in the other places, then that will happen.</p>
<p>COX:</p>
<p>Now, what level have you been asked for assistance at this stage, either by Premier Paul Lennon or the local mayor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've spoken to the Tasmanian Premier, I rang him yesterday morning, before he went to the area and said if there's anything extra you want from the Commonwealth Government, you've got it and he said well thanks very much for that. There are a range of standing arrangements whereby we provide on request at an officials level, extra defence equipment, there are financial arrangements whereby if natural disasters go beyond a certain level, the Commonwealth picks up most of the tab, and they're pretty mature, well-established arrangements that work quite well. On occasions like this, governments stick together. I've spoken to Mr Bracks as well and I've given him the same indication. I look forward to seeing the mayor today and I've been in touch with Senator Barnett and I hope Dick Adams, the local member, is also there today so I can say hello to him. Everybody pitches in on occasions like this, we work together for the common outcome.</p>
<p>COX:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, I'm not sure how appropriate it would be for the type of fires they're fighting here on the east coast, but I know in Victoria, there's some talk that they'll be looking to bring in fire fighters from overseas. Often, of course, we send our fire fighters overseas, particularly to North America, but does the Commonwealth assistance extend to bringing in fire fighters from abroad should the need arise?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, we are prepared to look at anything where it's appropriate that we help. I've indicated that to Mr Bracks and Mr Lennon, obviously if there is a need to bring people in from America or elsewhere, well that will happen, and whatever we have to do as part of the process, we will.</p>
<p>COX:</p>
<p> Prime Minister, I thank you for your time this morning, look forward to seeing you in St Helens later in the day.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you, bye bye.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
