<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6923</transcript-id>
    <title>BANQUET HOSTED BY GOVERNOR OF SICHUAN IN CHENGDU  </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006923.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
BANQUET HOSTED BY GOVERNOR OF SICHUAN IN CHENGDU<br />
WEDNESDAY 21 MAY 1986<br />
RETURN TOAST SPEECH BY-PRIME-MIN-ISTER.<br />
GOVERNOR JIANG<br />
DISTINGUISHED GUESTS<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN<br />
TONIGHT WE ARE IN THE CENTRE OF CHINA. I AM GLAD THAT ON<br />
MY PRESENT VISIT I HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXPERIENCE<br />
CHINA'S DIVERSITY AT FIRST HAND. I AM PARTICULARLY GLAD<br />
TO HAVE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO VISIT SICHUAN, CHINA'S MOST<br />
POPULOUS REGION AND ONE OF ITS MOST SIGNIFICANT.<br />
ITS SIGNIFICANCE FOR ME IS HEIGHTENED BY MY KNOWLEDGE THAT<br />
SICHUAN IS THE " OLD HOME" OF MY DEAR FRIENDS: GENERAL<br />
SECRETARY Hu YAOBANG, WHO I AM HONOURED COULD MEET ME HERE<br />
TODAY, AND MY HOST IN CHINA, PREMIER ZHAO ZIYANG.<br />
SICHUAN IS ALSO, OF COURSE, WELL KNOWN AS THE " OLD HOME"<br />
OF THE AGRICULTURAL REFORMS OF THE LATE 1970s WHICH SIGNALLED<br />
A NEW PHASE IN CHINA'S DEVELOPMENT, THE CONCEPTS OF<br />
IRESPONSIBILITY / IAND " tTO EACH ACCORDING TO HIS WORK 11.<br />
DEVELOPED HERE IN SICHUAN, HAVE HAD A PROFOUND EFFECT ON<br />
THE MODE AND VOLUME OF CHINA'S PRODUCTION. ONE IS IMPRESSED<br />
BY THE BOLDNESS WITH WHICH A NEW PHILOSOPHY OF INCENTIVES<br />
AND REWARDS FOR WORK WAS PIONEERED HERE, CONSISTENT WITH<br />
SOCIALIST PRINCIPLES BUT EXPRESSING THOSE PRINCIPLES IN NEW<br />
TERMS. </p>
<p>SUCH BOLDNESS HAS APPARENTLY PAID OFF, SICHUAN, DESPITE<br />
ITS HUGE POPULATION, IS NOW, I UNDERSTAND, AN EXPORTER OF<br />
FOOD. IT CAN NOW AFFORD TO INVEST IN RESEARCH AND<br />
TECHNOLOGY SO AS TO ENSURE THE CONTINUED DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
ITS AGRICULTURAL BASE. SUCH BOLDNESS,-OF COURSE, BRINGS<br />
ITS OWN RESPONSIBILITIES AS PEOPLE WILL CONTINUE TO LOOK<br />
TO SICHUAN, AS THE HOME OF REFORM, FOR NEW DEVELOPMENTS,<br />
WHEN WE THINK ABOUT SICHUAN WE THINK ABOUT AGRICULTURE',<br />
BUT TODAY I HAVE DISCOVERED SICHUAN IS DIVERSIFYING.<br />
AT THE XINXING FACTORY TOD) AY I WAS PRO UD'TO SEE AN<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMPANY INVOLVED IN PIONEERING A HIGH TECHNOLOGY<br />
PROJECT HERE. THIS PROJECT IS AN EXCELLENT EXAMPLE OF THE<br />
COOPERATION THAT EXISTS AND SHOULD CONTINUE TO BE PROMOTED<br />
BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES. SKILL AND ENTHUSIASM HAVE<br />
COMBINED TO GET A FINE PROJECT OFF THE GROUND. I AM<br />
GRATIFIED THAT THE PROJECT IS WAY AHEAD OF SCHEDULE AND<br />
THAT I COULD SEE IT TODAY SO NEAR TO COMPLETION., AM PROUD<br />
TO SEE THAT AN AUSTRALIAN COMPANY HAS PROVIDED THE SKILL<br />
AND TRAINING TO ESTABLISH THE PROJECT.,<br />
TODAY I 1 ' C KABLE TO ANNOUNCE<br />
THAT AUSTRALIA IS TO BE LOANED TWO PANDAS AS CHINA'S<br />
CONTRIBUTION To AUSTRALIA'S BICENTENNIAL CELEBRATIONS, </p>
<p>.00 3.<br />
ILOOK FORWARD VERY MUCH TO THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXAMINE<br />
SOMETHING OF SICHUAN ' S AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTION AT FIRST<br />
HAND TOMORROW AND TO HAVE LOCAL METHODS EXPLAINED TO ME<br />
BY SUCH DISTINGUISHED HOSTS.<br />
IKNOW NOW FROM EXPERIENCE THAT SICHUAN IS NOT JUST ABOUT<br />
AGRICULTURE AND AGRICULTURAL REFORM, IT IS ALSO ABOUT<br />
DIVERSIFICATION AND THE CHALLENGE THAT DIVERSIFICATION<br />
BRINGS. I AM PROUD TO SEE AUSTRALIANS INVOLVED IN THE<br />
DIVERSIFICATION OF THE SICHUAN ECONOMY. I HOPE THAT<br />
AUSTRALIANS CONTINUE TO COME TO SICHUAN AND THAT SICHUAN<br />
CONTINUES TO DIVERSIFY.<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN I PROPOSE A TOAST TO THE HEALTH OF<br />
GOVERNOR JIANG( AND OF GENERAL SECRETARY Hu J) TO THE HEALTH<br />
OF ALL DISTINGUISHED GUESTS HERE TONIGHT AND TO THE FRIENDLY<br />
RELATIONS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND THE PROVINCE OF SICHUAN.<br />
GAN BEI! </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
