<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3455</transcript-id>
    <title>REFERENCE TO THE TEXTILES AUTHORITY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003455.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 370<br />
November 1974<br />
REFERENCE TO THE TEXTILES AUTHORITY<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, announced today that<br />
he had sent a reference to the Textiles Authority within the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission covering a wide range of men's,<br />
women's, children's and infants' clothing, hosiery and gloves.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that this action was being taken as a result of<br />
high and rising levels of imports and an apparent total<br />
availability of such goods on the Australian market substantially<br />
in excess of previous levels.<br />
The reference seeks the advice of the Authority on<br />
whether action should be taken in terms of the GATT Textiles<br />
Arrangement, to which Australia acceded earlier this year, to<br />
restrain imports into Australia. The Authority has also been<br />
asked that if it is found that restraint measures are necessary<br />
and that measures which may be recommended in accordance with<br />
the GATT Textiles Arrangement are unlikely to overcome the<br />
market disruption, what other measures, if any, should be taken<br />
to overcome the disruption. The Authority has been requested<br />
to report within 45 days in relation to certain shirts and<br />
pyjamas and within 75 days in respect of the remainder of the<br />
goods covered by the reference.<br />
The Prime Minister emphasised that the questions of<br />
whether it would be necessary to have negotiations on the goods<br />
in question with exporting countries or take other action would<br />
have to await examination of the recommendations of the Textiles<br />
Authority. Mr. Whitlam said that, altP~ ough it is not clear to the<br />
Government at this stage that action on all goods covered by<br />
this latest reference is necessary, he considered it important<br />
that the Government be able to take the initiative in having<br />
investigations undertaken so that action can be taken promptly<br />
if found necessary. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Prime Minister invited manufacturers and other<br />
interested parties to start preparing submissions now to the<br />
Authority, which would announce arrangements for publichearings<br />
shortly. The Prime Minister also pointed out that should<br />
the need for action emerge from the report of the Textiles<br />
Authority, goods ordered overseas but not cleared for home<br />
consumption at the date of announcement of any action would<br />
be subject to the terms of the action. Importers should<br />
therefore exercise caution in placing orders overseas and in<br />
entering into financial commitments on such orders as it may<br />
not be possible to give special consideration to outstanding<br />
commitments should action be recommended by the Textiles<br />
Authority. CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
