<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6162</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE NATIONAL CRIMES CONFERENCE, 28 JULY 1983, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006162.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A, A~. jS~ 4. A-4-4. V œ S4.<br />
FOR MEDIA 28 July 1983<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF NATIONAL CRIMES CONFERENCE<br />
28 JULY 1983,-CANBERRA<br />
MAY I FIRST WELCOME ALL PRESENT TODAY AND THANK YOU<br />
FOR YOUR ATTENDA NCE. SOM~ E HAVE TRAVELLED CONSIDERABLE<br />
DISTANCES TO BE HERE AND TO ADD YOUR COUNSEL TO OUR<br />
DELIBERATIONS. FOR THE PARTICIPATION OF ALL WE ARE DEEPLY<br />
GRATEFULWE MEET TODAY BECAUSE OF OUR SHARED CONCERN ABO-UT<br />
THE EFFECTS OF ORGANISED CRIME ON THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITYWE<br />
MEET IN RESPONSE TO THE GROWING ANXIETY THROUGHOUT THE<br />
COMMU. JITY ON THIS MATTER AS A RESULT OF THE FINDINGS OF<br />
NUMEROUS ROYAL COMMISSION'S AND OTHER ENQUIRIES-WE MEET NOT<br />
ONLY TO GIVE EXPRESSION TO THAT CONCERN, BUT TO HELP CHART A<br />
COURSE TO ENABLE US, AS A NATION, TO ERADICATE THE CANCER OF<br />
ORGANISED CRIME.<br />
THE DELIBERATIONS OF THIS CONFERENCE SHOULD, I<br />
BELIEVE, BE DIRECTED TOWARDS THE ACHIEVEMENT OF TWO<br />
OBJECTIVES -THE STREN'GTHENING OF LAW ENF ORCEMENT AND THE<br />
MAINTENANCE OF CIVIL LIBERTIES. FOR AUSTRALIA -AND<br />
EMPHATICALLY, FOR my GOVERNMENT.-THESE OBJECTIVES ARE OF<br />
EQUAL IMPORTANCE-WE MUST NEVER ALLOW IT -ro BE ASSUMED THAT<br />
THE TWO ARE INCOMPATIBLE. IN A FREE SOCIETY, VIGILANCE<br />
AGAINST CRIME AND VIGILANCE AGAINST ENCROACHMENT UPON THE<br />
RIGHTS AND FREEDOM OF THE INDIVIDUAL MUST GO HAND IN HAND.<br />
7 717 </p>
<p>2.<br />
THEREFORE, I SUGGEST THE PRIMARY TASK OVER THE NEXT<br />
TWO DAYS IS TO SEEK TO BALANCE TWO LEGITIMATE REQUIREMENTS<br />
OF OUR SOCIETY: THE NEED FOR ACTION TO COMBAT NEW FORMS OF<br />
CRIME, PARTICULARLY ORGANISED CRIME, AND THE NEED TO ENSURE<br />
THAT ACTION TAKEN IN THIS DIRECTION DOES NOT JEOPARDISE<br />
INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS AND LIBERTIESPERHAPS<br />
AT THE OUTSET, THE MOST HELPFUL THING WOULD<br />
BE FOR ME TO DECLARE my GOVERNMENT'S ATTITUDE TO THE<br />
QUESTION OF A NATIONAL CRIMES COMMISSION. LET ME SAY THAT<br />
OUR PRESENT DISPOSITION IS TO SUPPORT THE ESTABLISHMENT OF<br />
SUCH A COMMISSION AND TO SEE IT OPERATING FROM JANUARY 198' 4<br />
AS A NATURAL AND CONTINUING SUCCESSOR TO THE COSTIGAN ROYAL<br />
COMMISSION. HOWEVER, WE ARE NOT COMMITTED TO IMPLEMENTING<br />
THE FRASER GOVERNMENT'S NATIONAL CRIMES COMMISSION ACT 1982<br />
IN IIS PRESENT FORM-AND I WANT TO MAKE IT VERY CLEAR THAT<br />
WE HAVE MADE NO FINAL DECISION ABOUT ANY OF THE MATTERS TO<br />
BE CONSIDERED BY THIS CONFERENCEIT<br />
FOLLOWS FROM THAT THAT WE REGARD THIS CONFERENCE<br />
AS A GENUINE CONSULTATIVE EXERCISE-WE ARE EAGER TO HEAR<br />
ALL POINTS OF VIEW AND TO TAKE THEM UNDER FULL<br />
CONSIDERATION. EQUALLY AS WITH ALL MATTERS OF HIGH-POLICY<br />
-THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT DOES NOT RETREAT FROM ITS<br />
ULTIMATE RESPONSIBILITY TO MAKE DECISIONS-<br />
9. n'JTPM4! ' rjvv" q </p>
<p>3.<br />
A NUMBER OF ISSUES IN RELATION TO THE ESTABLISHMENT<br />
OF A NATIONAL CRIMES COMMISSION HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED IN THE<br />
G3REEN PAPER THAT WAS SENT TO YOU EARLIER AND, DURING THE<br />
COURSE OF THE CONFERENCE, YOU WILL BE ASKED TO CONSIDER EACH.<br />
OF THESE ISSUES OR BATCHES OF ISSUES IN DUE COURSE. AGAIN,<br />
ISHOULD LIKE TO EMPHASISE THAT*, WHEN THE CONFERENCE. PASSES.<br />
FROM ONE ISSUE OR BATCH OF ISSUES TO ANOTHER, IT IS NOT TO<br />
BE INFERRED THAT THE CONFERENCE HAS MADE A DECISION ONE WAY<br />
OR THE OTHER ON THE MATTER LAST DISCUSSEDWITH<br />
A VIEW TO ASSISTING YOU IN YOUR DELIBERATIONS,<br />
MAY I OBSERVE THAT IT IS NOT JUST A MATTER OF BEING " FOR" OR<br />
it GIS'tACIE OMSIO; EEYHN<br />
AGAINST"~ AIRMEESEECD DM ISO; EENNYWWAHAN<br />
KIND OF CRIMES COMMISSION AND HOW THAT COMMISSION WILL<br />
OPERATE. IT SEEMS TO ME THREE DISTINCT LEVELS OF QUESTIONS<br />
NEED TO BE ASKED AND ANSWERED:<br />
FIRST, IS THE PROBLEM OF ORGANISED AND<br />
SOPHISTICATED CRIME SUCH THAT SOME FURTHER AND<br />
BETTER INVESTIGATORY MACHINERY THAN WE HAVE AT<br />
PRESENT IS NEEDED TO COPE WITH IT?<br />
SECONDLY, IF THE ANSWER IS " YES", IS THE CONCEPT OF<br />
THE STANDING CRIMES COMMISSION PREFERABLE TO<br />
ALTERNATIVE APPROACHES,-INCLUDING IN PARTICULAR<br />
I </p>
<p>UPGRADING THE POWERS AND CAPACITY OF THE POLICE,<br />
AND CONTINUING AD Hoc ROYAL COMMISSIONS AND<br />
ENQUIRIESTHIRDLY, IF A NATIONAL CRIMES COMMI. SSION IS THE<br />
PREFERRED ALTERNATIVE, WHAT SHOULD THE PRECISE<br />
FUNCTIONS, POWERS AND COMPOSITION OF THAT<br />
COMMISSION BE?<br />
AS TO THE FIRST TWO OF THESE QUESTIONS THE<br />
THRESHOLD QUESTIONS THE GOVERNMENT IS INCLINED TO SAY<br />
" IYES" It, BUT AGAIN I STRESS THAT NO FINAL DECISIONS HAVE BEEN<br />
TAKEN IN THIS AREA-WE ARE OPEN TO MODIFYING OUR POSITION<br />
IN THE LIGHT OF THE VIEWS EXPRESSED IN THIS CONFERENCE.<br />
AS TO THE THIRD QUESTION ABOUT THE POWERS AND<br />
COMPOSITION OF A COMMISSION THE GOVERNMENT WOULD BE<br />
GREATLY ASSISTED IN REACHING DECISIONS ON THESE MATTERS BY<br />
THE VIEWS* EXPRESSED AT THIS CONFERENCE.<br />
IT SEEMS TO US THAT ON THIS THIRD QUESTIONFUNCTIONS,<br />
POWERS AND COMPOSITION OF A NATIONAL CRIMES<br />
COMMISSION TWO PARTICULARLY CONTENTIOUS ISSUES ARISETHE<br />
FIRST AND UNDOUBTEDLY THE MOST CONTENTIOUS<br />
SINGLE QUESTION ABOUT A CRIMES COMMISSION IS WHAT SHOULD BE<br />
ITS PRINCIPAL ROLE-IS IT TO IDENTIFY AND EXPOSE ORGANISED </p>
<p>AND SOPHISTICATED CRIME; OR IS IT TO PACKAGE OR HELP PACKAGE<br />
THE KIND OF ADMISSABLE EVIDENCE THAT WILL LEAD TO CRIMINAL<br />
CONVICTIONSTHERE IS. ONE SCHOOL OF THOUGHT THAT THE CRIMES<br />
COMMISSION SHOULD DIRECT ITS ACTIVITIES TO THE GATHERING AN* D<br />
ANALYSIS OF CRIMINAL INTELLIGENCE SO THAT IT CAN IDENTIFY TO<br />
THE ORDINARY LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES PERSONS SUSPECTED OF<br />
CRIMINAL OFFENCES, PARTICULARLY MEMBERS OF CRIMINAL<br />
A ORGANIZATIONS, THEIR ASSOCIATES AND CRIMINAL ACTIVITIESTHESE<br />
AGENCIES WOULD HAVE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF PREPARING<br />
THE BRIEF TO PROSECUTE AND TAKING PROSECUTION ACTION. FOR<br />
THE COMMISSION TO UNDERTAKE SUCH A ROLE, WOULD BE, IT IS<br />
SUGGESTED, TO SUPPLANT THE POLICE FORCEONE<br />
EXAMPLE OF A COMMISSION WHICH HAS OPERATED<br />
SUCCESSFULLY ON THESE LINES IS THE COSTIGAN ROYAL<br />
COMMISSION. FROM A COMMONWEALTH REVENUE VIEWPOINT, THAT<br />
COMMISSION APPEARS TO HAVE PAID ITS WAY.<br />
THERE IS HOWEVER A CONTrRARY VIEW, NAMELY THAT THE<br />
CRIMES COMMISSION SHOULD-GO BEYOND MERELY IDENTIFYING<br />
OFFENCES AND SHOULD ASSEMBLE EVIDENCE WITH A VIEW TO ; THE<br />
PROSECUTION OF OFFENDERS.<br />
IF THIS APPROACH IS ADOPTED, THE-COMMISSION WOULD<br />
NOT BE EXPECTED TO ASSEMBLE ALL THE EVIDENCE REQUIRED FOR </p>
<p>6.<br />
THE PROSECUTION BRIEF IN THE PARTICULAR CASE AND OF COURSE<br />
THE COMMISSION WOULD NOT NEED TO GET INVOLVED ITSELF IN<br />
PURSUING PROSECUTIONS OF EVERY OFFENDER THAT THE COMMISSION<br />
COMES ACROSS-IT WOULD BE EXPECTED TO EXERCISE THIS ROLE<br />
ONLY IN A SMALL PROPORTION OF THE TOTAL NUMB-ER OF CRIMINAL<br />
INVESTIGATION CASES, AND THAT THE COMMISSION WOULD CONSULT<br />
THE DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC PROSECUTIONS, SOON TO BE ESTABLISHED,<br />
IN THE CHOICE OF CASES IN WHICH THE COMMISSION WERE TO<br />
EXERCISE THIS ROLECOMMONWEALTH AND STATE GOVERNMENTS IN THE PAST HAVE<br />
SOMETIMES BEEN FACED WITH RECEIVING REPORTS FROM ROYAL<br />
COMMISSIONS SUGGESTING THAT IDENTIFIED PERSONS HAVE BEEN<br />
GUILTY OF VARIOUS OFFENCES BUT FINDING SUBSEQUENTLY THAT THE<br />
EVIDENCE PROVIDED BY THE COMMISSION IS INSUFFICIENT OR<br />
INADE. QUATE FOR SUCCESSFUL PROSECUTIONS-THE VIEW IS PUT<br />
THAT GOOD GOVERNMENT AND PUBLIC CONFIDENCE IN THE<br />
ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE ARE NOT SATISFIED BY MERELY<br />
IDENTIFYING OR NAMING OF PERSONS IN REPORTS OF A COMMISSION<br />
IF THIS ACTION IS NOT FOLLOWED BY THE CONVICTION AND<br />
PUNISHMENT OF THESE PERSONS. THE PROBLEM OF LAW ENFORCEMENT<br />
BODIES IS FREQUENTLY NOT JUST THE IDENTIFICATION OF<br />
SUSPECTED OFFENDERS BUT RATHER THE OBTAINING OF SUFFICIENT<br />
EVIDENCE TO ENSURE THEIR CONVICTION.<br />
YOU WILL NO DOUBT WISH TO GIVE CAREFUL AND DETAILED<br />
CO. NSIDERATION TO THIS DIFFICULT AND IMPORTANT ISSUE. </p>
<p>K 7.<br />
THE SECOND CONTENTIOUS ISSUE IS WHETHER THE EXCUSE<br />
OF SELF-INCRIMINATION SHOULD BE AVAILABLE TO A WITNESS<br />
QUESTIONED BY THE CRIMES COMMISSION. THIS ISSUE APPEARS TO<br />
BE CLOSELY RELATED TO THE QUESTION JUST MENTIONED WHETHER<br />
THE ROLE OF THE COMMISSION SHOULD EXTEND TO THE ASSEMBLING<br />
OF EVIDENCE FOR THE PROSECUTION.<br />
THE EXCUSE IS NOT AVAILABLE TO WITNESSES BEFORE A<br />
ROYAL COMMISSION BUT ITS ABSENCE IS BALANCED BY PROVISIONS<br />
TO MAKE A WITNESS IS ANSWERS INADMISSIBLE AGAINST HIM EXCEPT<br />
IN A PROSECUTION FOR PERJURY. THE JUSTIFICATION FOR THIS<br />
BALANCE OF PROVISIONS IS THAT THE FUNCTION OF A ROYAL<br />
COMMISSION FOCUSSES ON ASCERTAINING THE FULL FACTS OF A,<br />
PARTICULAR MATTER AND NOT ON THE PARTICULAR OBJECTIVE OF<br />
ASSEMBLING EVIDENCE FOR PROSECUTIONS.<br />
HOWEVER, IF THE ROLE OF THE CRIMES COMMISSION IS TO<br />
EXTEND TO ASSEMBLING OF EVIDENCE FOR THE PROSECUTION, QUITE<br />
DIFFERENT CONSIDERATIONS APPLYTHE<br />
INTENTION WOULD THEN BE THAT THE EVIDENCE<br />
GIVEN BY A WITNESS WOULD BE AVAILABLE FOR USE IN SUBSEQUENT<br />
P ROCEEDINGS WHETHER AGAINST HIM OR SOME OTHER PERSON. THAT<br />
BEING SO, LONG ACCEPTED PRINCIPLES APPEAR TO REQUIRE THAT<br />
THE EXCUSE OF SELF-INCRIMINATION SHOULD BE AVAILABLE TO THE<br />
WITNESS-</p>
<p>8.<br />
WHETHER THE EXCUSE OF SELF-INCRIMINATION SHOULD<br />
APPLY TO DOCUMENTS IS ONE MATTER ON WHICH THERE APPEAR TO BE<br />
PARTICULARLY STRONG DIFFERENCES OF OPINION-ON THE ONE HAND<br />
IS THE VIEW THAT PURSUIT OF DOCUMENTARY EVIDENCE SHOULD BE A<br />
VITAL PART OF THE CRIMES COMMISSION'S ACTIVITIES-ON THE<br />
OTHER, IS THE VIEW THAT IT WOULD BE INCOMPATIBLE WITH THE<br />
COMMISSION'S ROLE OF ASSEMBLING EVIDENCE FOR PROSECUTION FOR<br />
A WITNESS TO BE DEPRIVED OF THIS EXCUSEAS<br />
A RESULT OF AMENDMENTS MADE TO THE NATIONAL<br />
CRIMES COMMISSON ACT DURING THE COURSE OF ITS PASSAGE<br />
THROUGH PARLIAMENT, THE EXCUSE UNDER THE ACT IS CONFINED TO<br />
NATURAL PERSONSHOWEVER, BEFORE DEVOTING TOO MUCH TIME, ENERGY AND<br />
EMOTLON TO THIS PARTICULAR ISSUE, IT MIGHT BE WISE, I<br />
SUGGEST,, TO EXAMINE WHETHER APPLICATION OF THE EXCUSE TO<br />
PRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS BY NATURAL PERSONS WILL HAVE ANY<br />
REAL PRACTICAL EFFECTTHESE ARE'NOT OF COURSE THE ONLY CONTENTIOUS<br />
ISSUES. THERE ARE QUITE A NUMBER OF OTHER ISSUES THAT ARE<br />
TO SOME DEGREE CONTENTIOUS; TO MENTION SOME, THE WIDTH OF<br />
THE COMMISSION'S JURISDICTON, WHETHER THE COMMISSION SHOULD<br />
IDENTIFY SUSPECTED OFFENDERS IN ITS PUBLIC REPORTS,<br />
ACCOUNTABILITY OF THE COMMISSION, WHETHER THE COMMISSION<br />
SHOULD OR SHOULD NOT BE HEADED BY A JUDGE AND THE ROLE OF<br />
THE STATES AND THE NORTHERN TERRITORY. A 7 k_" </p>
<p>9.<br />
AS TO THIS LAST MENTIONED ISSUE, CLEARLY THE MOST<br />
SATISFACTORY ARRANGEMENT SO FAR AS LAW ENFORCEMENT * GENERALLY<br />
IN AUSTRALIA IS CONCERNED IS TO HAVE FULL PARTICIPATION BY<br />
THE STATES AND THE NORTHERN TERRITORY IN THE WORKING OF THE<br />
CRIMES COMMISSIONSHOULD THE STATES WISH TO PARTICIPATE IN THE<br />
COMMISSION, THE EXISTING ACT PROVIDES FOR TWO POSSIBLE WAYS<br />
BY WHICH THIS CAN BE DONE.<br />
FIRST, THE COMMISION CAN BE EMPOWERED BY A STATE<br />
LAW TO EXERCISE FUNCTIONS IN RELATION TO BREACHES OF STATE<br />
LAWS CORRESPONDING TO THOSE IT WILL EXERCISE UNDER THE ACT<br />
IN RELATION TO BREACHES OF COMMONWEALTH LAWSSECOND,<br />
A STATE GOVERNOR OR MINISTER CAN CONFER,<br />
WITH THE CONSENT OF THE COMMONWEALTH ATTORNEY-GENERAL,<br />
PARTICULAR FUNCTIONS OR POWERS ON A MEMBER OR MEMBERS OF THE<br />
COMMISSION. THUS, IF THE COMMONWEALTH ATTORNEY-GENERAL<br />
CONSENTS, A STATE GOVERNMENT WOULD APPOINT ONE OR MORE<br />
MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL CRIMES COMMISSION As ROYAL<br />
COMMISSIONERS FOR STATE PURPOSES AND THESE PERSONS COULD<br />
EXERCISE STATE FUNCTIONS CONJOINTLY WITH THEIR COMMONWEALTH<br />
FUNCTIONS BUT, SO FAR AS STATE FUNCTIONS WERE CONCERNED,$<br />
WITHIN THE LIMITS SPECIFIED BY THE STATE. </p>
<p>My GOVERNMENT HOPES THAT STATE GOVERNMENTS WILL<br />
FULLY PARTICIPATE IN THE* WORKINGS OF THE CRIMES COMMISSIONTO<br />
THIS END, WE ARE KEEN TO DISCUSS WITH STATE GOVERNMENTS<br />
WAYS AND MEANS BY WHICH THIS MAY BE DONE-IF ANY INTERESTED.<br />
PARTIES WISH TO ADVANCE DURING THE COURSE OF THE CONFERENCE<br />
WAYS AND MEANS OF FACILITATING STATE PARTICIPATION THEY<br />
SHOULD BY ALL MEANS DO SO AND THEIR SUGGESTIONS WILL BE VERY<br />
CAREFULLY CONSIDEREDWE SHOULD NOT THINK THAT A CRIMES COMMISSION WILL<br />
BE A PANACEA FOR ORGANIZED CRIME. ESTABLISHMENT OF A CRIMES<br />
COMMISSION WOULD ONLY BE ONE PART, ALTHOUGH A VERY IMPORTANT<br />
PART, OF A PACKAGE SO FAR AS THE FIGHT AGAINST ORGANIZED.<br />
CRIME IS CONCERNED-<br />
. GOVERNMENTS NEED TO ADDRESS THIS FIGHT AT ALL<br />
LEVELS RANGING FROM REVIEWING AND UP-GRADING POLICE<br />
RESOURCES TO MODERNIZING THE CRIMINAL LAW AND THE PROCEDURES<br />
OF THE COURTS TO MINIMIZE DELAYS IN THE BRINGING OF<br />
OFFENDERS TO JUSTICE. IN REVIEWING THE LAW WE NEED TO BE<br />
CONSCIOUS OF THE NEED TO REMOVE FROM THE STATUTE BOOK ANY<br />
OFFENCES THAT THE COMMUNITY NO LONGER CONSIDERS<br />
REPREHENSIBLETHE OBJECTIVE OF ALL OF US GATHERED HERE AT THIS<br />
CONFERENCE IS THE PROTECTION OF AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY FROM<br />
HARMFUL DEVELOPMENTS IN CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES, WHICH RECOGNISE </p>
<p>NO BOUNDARIES, STATE OR NATIONAL. THERE IS A PUBLIC<br />
EXPECTATION THAT THIS CONFERENCE WILL ACHIEVE SIGNIFICANT<br />
RESULTS IN CLEARING THE GROUND FOR EFFECTIVE ACTION IN THIS<br />
REGARD AND WE MUST TRY TO ENSURE THAT THOSE EXPECTATIONS ARE<br />
NOT DISAPPOINTEDWHILE AGREEMENT IN EVERY DETAIL CANNOT REASONABLY<br />
BE EXPECTED IN YOUR DELIBERATIONS, AND WHILE TODAY IS NOT AN<br />
OCCASION NOR THIS CONFERENCE A FORUM APPROPRIATE FOR FORMAL<br />
DECISION-MAKING, I HOPE AND TRUST THAT, BEARING THE ULTIMATE<br />
OBJECTIVE IN MIND, NONETHELESS, A CONSIDERABLE MEASURE OF<br />
CONSENSUS WILL EMERGE HERE AS TO THE ACTIONS THAT NEED TO BE<br />
TAKEN BY ALL AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS. AIDED BY THAT COUNISEL,<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS WILL, I BELIEVE, BE GREATLY ASSISTED<br />
IN REACHING THEIR DECISIONS AS TO ACTION TO BE TAKEN TO<br />
FIGHT THE INSIDIOUS GROWTH OF ORGANIZED CRIME IN OUR<br />
COUNTRY-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
