<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10888</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO THE NEW SOUTH WALES DIVISION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY&amp;#146;S                 CORPORATE DINNER                SYDNEY TOWN HALL</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/12/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Kerry, to Tony Staley, Michael Osborne, Michael Yabsley, to my numerous</p>
<p> State and federal parliamentary colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>There's something about addressing a gathering from the stage</p>
<p> of the Sydney Town Hall that tickles my political fancy. This particular</p>
<p> stage is normally known as the stage from which conferences of the</p>
<p> New South Wales Labor Party are addressed. And over the years many</p>
<p> a rowdy gathering has taken place in this Town Hall but it doesn't</p>
<p> belong to the Labor Party it belongs to the people of Sydney. I really</p>
<p> am delighted that the division has chosen this venue for tonight's</p>
<p> gathering. And can I start by thanking Kerry for her very kind words</p>
<p> of introduction and can I also wish her well and commit myself and</p>
<p> my federal parliamentary colleagues in New South Wales in doing everything</p>
<p> in our power to secure her election as the next Premier of New South</p>
<p> Wales and the defeat of the Carr Government.</p>
<p>It won't be easy but it is eminently achievable and the Carr</p>
<p> Government is an eminently beatable Government if you can describe</p>
<p> governments in that fashion. You have our goodwill, our good wishes</p>
<p> and both from a personal and a political point of view I am very committed</p>
<p> to doing everything I can to bring about the result we all want on</p>
<p> the 27th of March next year.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, tonight is a marvellous moment on which to reflect</p>
<p> on a remarkable year. Parliament got up last night and right at the</p>
<p> end we secured the support of the two Independents thus passing into</p>
<p> law the Private Health Insurance Rebate legislation which was one</p>
<p> of the key elements of our taxation policy. It's the first downpayment</p>
<p> on the introduction of the Coalition's taxation plan and once</p>
<p> again this country has a non means tested fully available private</p>
<p> health insurance rebate which, when the new tax system comes into</p>
<p> operation, will mean that 81 per cent of Australians have full tax</p>
<p> deductibility of their private health insurance premiums. We have</p>
<p> had a remarkable year and the greatest thing to me about the election</p>
<p> result on the 3rd of October is that it demonstrated that</p>
<p> there is a reward in politics and there is a reward in public life</p>
<p> for actually asking the community to support fundamental change and</p>
<p> fundamental reform.</p>
<p>All of my political life I have seen politics about bringing about</p>
<p> change for the better and for the improvement of the community. I</p>
<p> don't believe in change for its own sake. I have often said that</p>
<p> the art of statecraft in the modern age is to preserve those practices</p>
<p> from the past that continue to serve the nation well whilst at the</p>
<p> same time being willing to challenge and discard those practices that</p>
<p> no longer serve the country well. And we had an opportunity in this</p>
<p> election campaign to lay out a very important economic road map for</p>
<p> Australia in the area of taxation. And the truth is that as many in</p>
<p> this room will know because in different ways you have been intimately</p>
<p> involved in and associated with the operation of the Australian economy</p>
<p> and the interface between that economy and the Government of Australia</p>
<p> for many years. You all know that our taxation system has been crying</p>
<p> aloud for reform for two decades.</p>
<p>I came into Parliament, as Kerry reminded you, in 1974. A year later</p>
<p> we had the Aspry Report named after a very prominent judge at the</p>
<p> time of the New South Wales full court. And that report tabled in</p>
<p> 1975, 23 years ago, recommended the introduction of a broad-based</p>
<p> indirect tax, in other words, a GST. And year after year the issue</p>
<p> would come up and people would solemnly say: yes, we have got to get</p>
<p> around to it. And the former Coalition Government looked at it on</p>
<p> a couple of occasions and discarded it. To his credit my predecessor</p>
<p> as Prime Minister Paul Keating advocated it in 1985 only to be torpedoed</p>
<p> by the trade union movement then led, let me remind you, by Simon</p>
<p> Crean who is now the Deputy Leader of the Federal Opposition and Bill</p>
<p> Kelty and a rather wishy-washy Prime Minister on that subject at the</p>
<p> time, Bob Hawke. Then John Hewson tried to his credit and very bravely</p>
<p> in 1993 to advocate it. And it was defeated then by a ferocious fear</p>
<p> campaign led by my predecessor.</p>
<p>It may have been clever politics, it may have given them a great afterglow</p>
<p> on the night of the election in 1993 but it wasn't serving the</p>
<p> national interest. And I have never forgotten the conversation I had</p>
<p> with Mr Keating in his office in 1985 when I was the Deputy Leader</p>
<p> of the Opposition and Shadow Treasurer and I went into his office</p>
<p> and I'd arranged to get a copy of the white paper on taxation</p>
<p> reform and we discussed between us the need for that reform even though</p>
<p> we were on opposite sides of politics. And he said that he thought</p>
<p> it was something that had to be done for the long-term interests of</p>
<p> Australia.</p>
<p>Now, I believed that then and so did he. He, of course, had a different</p>
<p> view when he was Prime Minister in 1993 and more is the pity as far</p>
<p> as the national interest was concerned at that time. But we have needed</p>
<p> this reform for two decades. So many of the other things that we needed</p>
<p> to change in this country so far as the economy and the business community</p>
<p> are concerned have been attended to. We have deregulated our financial</p>
<p> system, we have relaxed the tariff barriers, we have embraced sensible</p>
<p> policies of privatisation, we have embraced sensible competition policies.</p>
<p> All of those things have made the Australian economy stronger and</p>
<p> more competitive.</p>
<p>And can I tell you that the best thing and the thing that has given</p>
<p> me the greatest sense of pride and satisfaction over the last 12 months</p>
<p> was the experience that I had in Kuala Lumpur only a few weeks ago</p>
<p> at the APEC meeting. To feel and to know that Australia had won a</p>
<p> new respect in our region. For two reasons, because we had a strong</p>
<p> domestic economy and we were recognised as having got our own economic</p>
<p> house in order. And also because of that strength we had been able</p>
<p> to offer assistance. We have been able to be true regional mates to</p>
<p> countries such as Indonesia and Korea and Thailand that needed our</p>
<p> assistance. And one sensed that there was a recognition that Australia</p>
<p> was performing well. And by any measure as I said to the Parliament</p>
<p> yesterday in the last Question Time, Australians go to Christmas 1998</p>
<p> with our economy in a stronger more healthy condition than it has</p>
<p> been at any time since the late 1960s.</p>
<p>We do have a very strong level of economic growth, we have historically</p>
<p> low levels of inflation, we have a budget strongly in surplus turned</p>
<p> around to that condition in only two-and-a-half years, we have strong</p>
<p> levels of business investment. But most importantly of all, I think,</p>
<p> we have a situation where the business community and those responsible</p>
<p> for the future economic growth of this country believe that we have</p>
<p> a Government that is committed to taking whatever decisions are needed</p>
<p> in the long-term national interests of Australia. And that is the</p>
<p> message that came out of the result on the 3rd of October.</p>
<p>It was a risk. There were many people who told me you were crazy to</p>
<p> go to an election introducing...proposing the introduction of a</p>
<p> new taxation system. And in a sense, we were defying conventional</p>
<p> wisdom in doing so. But when you look at it in another respect there</p>
<p> was really no other way of doing it given the history of attempts</p>
<p> previously to reform the Australian taxation system. I couldn't</p>
<p> have gone to the election on the 3rd of October saying</p>
<p> I am not going to reform the taxation system when I knew in my heart</p>
<p> that reform was necessary. What was the point of being in a position</p>
<p> of power and authority unless you are prepared to use it in the national</p>
<p> interests? I have had all the jobs in politics. I have been Opposition</p>
<p> Leader, I have been Treasurer, I have been a senior Minister, I have</p>
<p> been out of favour, I have been back in favour, I have been Prime</p>
<p> Minister. But really you go into public life to do positive things</p>
<p> and to do - to bring about change. You don't go into public life</p>
<p> to occupy office and to enjoy power for its own sake. There is nothing</p>
<p> in the end to be derived from that. So, in a way, although it was</p>
<p> difficult, it was also, in another sense, a fairly simple choice.</p>
<p> The only way we could ever get this great reform embraced was to confront</p>
<p> the Australian community with it in an election campaign. Risked all</p>
<p> and having won it, know that we enjoyed the ultimate moral authority</p>
<p> to implement it. And we had a Federal Executive meeting in Canberra</p>
<p> today and one of the young Liberal representatives said during the</p>
<p> meeting, the thing that he enjoyed most about the last election campaign</p>
<p> was that he could stare any of his political opponents in the eye</p>
<p> and feel that we had the moral high ground in that campaign because</p>
<p> we were arguing for something that everybody, Labor and Liberal alike,</p>
<p> knew deep down was necessary for the long-term economic benefit of</p>
<p> Australia. So I feel pretty happy about the outcome of the election</p>
<p> and I think all of the party supporters had every reason to feel very</p>
<p> pleased about the outcome.</p>
<p>And it's not just the area of taxation reform over the last year</p>
<p> that we can draw some pride from but there have been a number of other</p>
<p> major events over the last year that, as time has gone by, have worked</p>
<p> even more to the credit of the Government than appeared at the time.</p>
<p> And one of those, of course, was the very traumatic circumstance of</p>
<p> the, I believe, increasingly successful attempt in April of this year</p>
<p> to reform the Australian waterfront. At the time we ran into a lot</p>
<p> of criticism. A number of court decisions didn't quite go in</p>
<p> the way anticipated but that is the nature of a nation that lives</p>
<p> under the rule of law. And I make no further comment about those decisions.</p>
<p> But that wasn't easy. And I want to pay tribute here tonight</p>
<p> to the courage that was displayed on that occasion by Chris Corrigan,</p>
<p> the head of Patricks. And I also want to pay tribute to the tenacity</p>
<p> and strength of my Minister for Industrial Relations, Peter Reith,</p>
<p> who endured all of the intimidation and all of the pressure and all</p>
<p> of the personal strain and stress that goes with a senior Minister</p>
<p> who is in the eye of an industrial storm of that character. And as</p>
<p> the weeks and then months have gone by we are now starting to get</p>
<p> a productivity dividend, not so much here in Sydney but that will</p>
<p> ultimately come because once you start getting efficiency gains in</p>
<p> other parts of the country inevitably it will flow through to the</p>
<p> other ports in the country. The Australian waterfront will never be</p>
<p> the same again. There have been fundamental changes and reforms. And</p>
<p> that was something that, for decades, Australians also knew had to</p>
<p> be tackled, something had to be done about it.</p>
<p>We were able, over the last year, to resolve that incredibly difficult</p>
<p> native title issue. And I don't think there was a person of goodwill</p>
<p> in this country who wanted the Wik legislation to be an issue in the</p>
<p> last election campaign. I never did and I don't think Liberals</p>
<p> of goodwill and decency wanted it to be either. But we weren't</p>
<p> prepared to surrender what we regarded as important conditions of</p>
<p> an honourable settlement and we needed to maintain the commitment</p>
<p> that we made to the different sections of the Australian community</p>
<p> in 1997.</p>
<p>We achieved a remarkably good outcome just a year ago, almost to the</p>
<p> day, at the climate change convention in Kyoto. And, of course, we</p>
<p> were able, in May of this year, to bring down a budget which a year</p>
<p> ahead of time had turned a deficit of $10.5 billion inherited in March</p>
<p> of 1996 into a very comfortable surplus. And I want to pay tribute</p>
<p> to the tremendous commitment of Peter Costello as the Treasurer and</p>
<p> Deputy Leader of the Party to the economic stewardship of Australia</p>
<p> over the last two-and-three-quarter years.</p>
<p>I think on the broader scale we have been able, in the last year in</p>
<p> particular, to finally but nonetheless significantly rebalance Australia's</p>
<p> foreign relationships. There was nothing fundamentally wrong with</p>
<p> many of the foreign policy directions of the former government. There</p>
<p> were questions of emphasis and there were nuances about it which I</p>
<p> didn't think were suitable for Australia's longer term interests.</p>
<p> I had the sense, when I became Prime Minister, that this country was</p>
<p> rather an anxious outsider to the Asian Pacific region knocking on</p>
<p> the door seeking admission. I felt that we had to move away from an</p>
<p> Asia only' policy to an Asia first' policy recognising</p>
<p> that our prime area of commitment and interest, both economically</p>
<p> and politically and strategically, had to be the Asian Pacific region</p>
<p> but also knowing that we had long-term interests with other parts</p>
<p> of the world.</p>
<p>And over the last year I've spoken a lot of the special intersection</p>
<p> that I believe Australia occupies. We are quite unique. We are a projection</p>
<p> of western civilisation in this part of the world. We have very deep</p>
<p> and special links with the nations of North America and we share so</p>
<p> much in common with them culturally and politically. But here we are</p>
<p> in the Asian Pacific region with a vibrant population of Australians</p>
<p> of Asian descent, increasing the relevance of Australia to the Asian</p>
<p> Pacific area by the many people-to-people links that that produces.</p>
<p> And you don't have many countries in the world that have such</p>
<p> a conjunction of that history, geography, shared political values,</p>
<p> economic circumstance and so forth. And I can't think of a time</p>
<p> in Australia's recent history where we are a more attractive</p>
<p> magnet as an investment haven in this part of the world.</p>
<p>Given everything that has happened in the Asian Pacific region over</p>
<p> the last couple of years, isn't it good that Australia has the</p>
<p> following characteristics? We have a stable political system. We have</p>
<p> a strong economy. We have a deregulated financial system. We have</p>
<p> a stable and prudentially regulated banking system. We have a strong</p>
<p> and internationally respected legal system and we speak the English</p>
<p> language. I can't think of a more fortunate conjunction. When</p>
<p> you add all of those things together, if we can't make this country</p>
<p> one of the great financial centres of the world over the next few</p>
<p> years then we're not trying hard enough. And it really is, very</p>
<p> specifically, and I talk generally about Australia as a financial</p>
<p> centre, but I know that there are many people in this city who have</p>
<p> a very strong and understandably deep commitment to achieving that</p>
<p> goal.</p>
<p>So we have a lot to be not smug about or not complacent about but</p>
<p> we are entitled as a political party and we are entitled as a government</p>
<p> and a group of men and women who have worked together over a number</p>
<p> of years to achieve our political goal, we are entitled to achieve</p>
<p> as we come to the end of this year, we are entitled to feel that we</p>
<p> have achieved a great deal. We have turned on its head some of the</p>
<p> conventional wisdom about Australian politics. The last election campaign</p>
<p> destroyed the mythology of the ascendancy of the Labor Party, particularly</p>
<p> here in New South Wales when it came to marginal seat campaigning.</p>
<p> And I want to thank Remo and his colleagues for the tremendous work</p>
<p> they did in holding so many marginal seats here in New South Wales.</p>
<p> It played a very, very major role in securing our re-election on the</p>
<p> 3rd of October.</p>
<p>I want to thank all of you for the tremendous loyalty and support</p>
<p> that you've given me. There are many people in this room tonight</p>
<p> who've been political friends of mine the whole time that I've</p>
<p> been in Parliament. And many of you have counted me as a friend when</p>
<p> I haven't had the job that I've got at the present time</p>
<p> and when perhaps I sort of hadn't had very influential jobs at</p>
<p> all in politics and I remember that and I appreciate that very, very</p>
<p> deeply. I really do. But I can't tell you what a sense of satisfaction</p>
<p> and pleasure that it gives me to be able to say and to be able to</p>
<p> reflect and to know it is true that we have won re-election on the</p>
<p> strength of what we have put to the Australian public and not off</p>
<p> the back of 13 years of accumulating hostility to a former government</p>
<p> and accumulating desire to bring about a change of government. And</p>
<p> the mandate that we received on the 3rd of October in many</p>
<p> ways was more emphatic than the mandate we received in March of 1996</p>
<p> because it was achieved in more difficult circumstances. And the fact</p>
<p> that by voting for us in October of this year the Australian people</p>
<p> were voting for difficult but, nonetheless, necessary fundamental</p>
<p> change, means that the Australian people properly led, with a proposition</p>
<p> adequately explained, with the benefits for average Australians fully</p>
<p> spelt out, with the essential fairness of the proposition evident</p>
<p> from the beginning, that the Australian people will embrace necessary</p>
<p> change. And that gives me a source of tremendous hope and tremendous</p>
<p> optimism, not only about taxation reform but about other things as</p>
<p> well.</p>
<p>We are going to have our difficulties with the Senate, we're</p>
<p> going to have our arguments, but the greatest thing we have going</p>
<p> for us is that the people voted for the programme that we are now</p>
<p> trying to implement. Imagine the difficulty of trying to get through</p>
<p> the Senate something you'd kept from the Australian people at</p>
<p> the previous election. And every time I have an argument with the</p>
<p> Senate about something that we put up at the previous election they</p>
<p> are in a defensive position, the Labor Party and the Democrats, and</p>
<p> we are in a position of occupying the political and moral high ground.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much for tonight. It touches</p>
<p> Janette and I very deeply that you've all come along tonight.</p>
<p> We do feel that it's been a great year for the Liberal Party.</p>
<p> We don't forget the fact that there are many people in Australia</p>
<p> who will not be sharing as bountiful a Christmas as, I guess, most</p>
<p> of us will share and none of us should ever forget that. There is</p>
<p> still a lot that remains to be done in terms of bridging some of the</p>
<p> gaps between the well-off and the not so well-off within our community.</p>
<p> And it remains as one of the challenges of the kind of society that</p>
<p> we want Australia to remain and perhaps, in a sense, even more to</p>
<p> become.</p>
<p>But let us not pass up the opportunity as Liberals and as Liberal</p>
<p> supporters of reflecting on a remarkable year of achievement. The</p>
<p> Australian economy is in great shape. That is significantly due to</p>
<p> the decisions that the Government has taken over the last two-and-a-half</p>
<p> years and it is significantly due to the sense of direction that the</p>
<p> Government has given to the business community and to the Australian</p>
<p> people over that period of time. I thank the business community of</p>
<p> Sydney for its support for the Liberal Party. I know it has been generous.</p>
<p> I thank the Liberal Party organisation here in New South Wales for</p>
<p> its support. I wish all of you a merry Christmas. I hope that 1999</p>
<p> is even better for the Australian people and that the dreams and the</p>
<p> goals that we have for our country and for our families are fully</p>
<p> realised.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
