<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5910</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL CAMPAIGN AGAINST DRINK DRIVING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005910.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
9ClI LJz-%<br />
A U STRAIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 19 SEPTEMBER 1982<br />
NATIONAL CAMPAIGN AGAINST DRINK DRIVING<br />
I have written today to the State Premiers and the. Chief<br />
Minister of the Northern Territory sceking their co-operation<br />
in'a natL-ional media campaign against drink drivinag.<br />
There is growing concern in the community about the<br />
appallingly high number of deaths and injuries occurring<br />
daily on our roads. This concern : Ls shared by -the<br />
Commonwealth. Every effort should be made to reduce trauma and distress<br />
in Australian families and the very high costs associated<br />
with the road toll. A major problem appears to be driver<br />
behaviour and drink driving in particular. Evidence suggests<br />
that drink driving contributes to about 50% of road deaths<br />
and 30%. of injuries.<br />
The Commonwealth has therefore decided to provide $ 0.5 million<br />
as part of a national co-operative effort towards the campaign.<br />
The contribution will be on the basis of a dollar for dol. lar,<br />
matching contribution from the States and the Northern Territory.<br />
This will provide a government sponsored campaign of million.<br />
Industry stands to benefit from this campaign through<br />
reduced losses of output and productivity so it is hoped<br />
that the private sector will also contribute to the campaign.<br />
While details are yet to be finalised, it is envisaged that<br />
the campaign will commence later this year and extend through<br />
the Christmas/ New Year holiday period.<br />
I strongly recommend that the States and Northern Territory<br />
Governments join with the Commonwealth to make this<br />
worthwhile campaign a truly nation-wide co-operative effort. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
