<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7871</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HYATT REGENCY, ADELAIDE, 24 JANUARY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/01/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007871.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
MWASCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERECE, HYAI? W* mCYP ADBL&amp; ZDE<br />
24 JXANURY 1990<br />
2-6 O3jr PROOF -ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: What do you say to mr xeating predicting an<br />
early Kay election this morning? Is he right in doing<br />
that? PH*. Be's got a fair chance in being right.<br />
JOURNALIST: Only a fair chance?<br />
PX: Ne's got a fair chance of being right. I mean I<br />
love Adelaide and I'd love to use this occasion to make a<br />
very important announcement and I an not going to.<br />
JOURNALIST: H~ ave you made the decision?<br />
PKE: Not yet.<br />
JOLRNALIST: sentenced James Savage to death.* Will<br />
the Government be doing anyting about that or do you<br />
have any comment to make?<br />
PNI You, I do have a coment to make. I notice that zY<br />
friend and colleague Lionel Bowen# the Deputy Prim<br />
Minister and Attorney General, ham issued a statement<br />
which reflects the position of the Government and that is<br />
that we deeply regret that the judge has rejected the<br />
ecoidation of the Jury but as Lionel has said this<br />
matter has still a long way to go through the American<br />
legal system. We've provided $ 50,000 already to enable a<br />
number of witnesses, to go to the United Stt. To<br />
explain essentially the tragic ciroumetanoes of this<br />
matter and talking about the tragic circumstances of this<br />
man who has been found guilty and of course we don't<br />
overlook the nature of the crime but you do have to<br />
undrstndthat he was a young man up-acoead from his<br />
natural environment,, from hi. parents, put into a<br />
situation out of which developed this tragedy and we hope<br />
that through the futher processes that are available<br />
account will be taken at the appropriate level of the<br />
American judicial system of those Wccitances. So that<br />
justice can be properly qualified with mercy. </p>
<p>Porter: mr seatinrfvusNyfr neetode<br />
that rule out AprilifvusMyfra 1cim o<br />
PH: No, I make the decision.<br />
Reporter: What about interest rates Uir Hawke* how moon<br />
before they an coae down?<br />
PR: As Paul ating said rightly-yestarday will<br />
happen now is that the first stop has been taken and how<br />
the banks vill mowe now in the area of other interest<br />
rates including mortgage rates wiii be a matter for<br />
decis ion by then and the pressures and the considerations<br />
won't be identical for each of the banks ut we believe<br />
that we have acted responsibly, there vas-same presure<br />
upon us to ease monetary policy earlier than this but we<br />
Were rat prepared to do that until we were confident that<br />
there was a slowing down in the economy which we regarded<br />
as necesary to meet the fundamental external challenges<br />
confronting this country. We think this position has been<br />
reached and now the conditions are in place for the<br />
easing of monetary policy which has been undertaken now<br />
when that will be reflected in mortgage rates will be a<br />
matter for the banks.<br />
Reporter: Will there be further adjuatmentass, this was<br />
an initial adjustment, is there a program of adjustments<br />
in mind now?<br />
111: There is a program in mind,, but an Paul rightly<br />
described it,, it van a limited initial move now that<br />
carries its own implications.<br />
Reporter: If there is an easing of mortgage rates, will<br />
that be a trade off in any wage negotiations later this<br />
yeSar. PM: No not a trade off, quite clearly in negotiations<br />
that we will be having with the trade unions, and let so<br />
also say with the employers,, when we talk about wage<br />
negotians it is not just with trade, unions, we talk<br />
with emloyers as well.* I think it is quite clear that<br />
they should see the desirability of having an outcome<br />
fzrl the wage negotiations which of itself will be<br />
oopzsive to a further easing in monetary policy and<br />
Wwloslywe would want to see that.<br />
Reporter: reaction a 1.5% drop in the dollar?<br />
PR: go not worried about that at all.* We the float of<br />
the dollar and when you have changes in the price of<br />
mey within our country then that create* a change in<br />
-relativities that will obviously have mom reflection in<br />
the exchange rate that was to be expected.<br />
Reporters The polls are suggesting that Janine Haines may<br />
be able to take Kin ton from the Labor Party, what are<br />
You feelings an a. Does it concern you? </p>
<p>p31: no I want to see all my sitting members returned I<br />
believe that Gordon Dilney nas done an ezoellent job of<br />
representing the electors Of Kingston-I think that they<br />
will appreciate that their interests will be better<br />
served by having someone in the aovernment wbo can<br />
directly represent then and I make those ObSSVtiofls<br />
without making any personal detraction Of senator Haines.<br />
I mean : E an not here to attack her. I an simply saying<br />
that it makes sense. I would beleive for the electors Of<br />
singston to ensure that they are Continued to be<br />
represented by a person who has proven hi. capacity to<br />
represent them effectively*<br />
Reporter: Are you confident that Post election interest<br />
rates will stay down?<br />
. MI: Yes. * we have . not at any stage played with any element<br />
of our economic policy, whether it in wages policy,<br />
fiscal policy or monetary policy in electoral terms. * I<br />
meon we have been in Government nov for nearly 7 years<br />
and we are entitled to be judged on the consistency of<br />
policy making and the results of it. There have been<br />
times when electoral or political considerations would've<br />
pushed us in the judgement of analysts in a<br />
particular way but we didn't go that way because we<br />
didn't think it would be responsible. We have therefore<br />
in this case waited to ease monetary policy until we<br />
believed it was appropriate in economic term to do it.<br />
We've made that judgement and we think those conditions<br />
will continue.<br />
JOURNALIST?: Mr Hawks, to what extent has the reduction<br />
or likely reduction in interest rates led you to believe<br />
that May would be the best possible election date?<br />
FN: It has had no connection. I've not made my decision<br />
as to when the election will be. it always had to be by<br />
abot mid May and am I've made it clear all the way along<br />
as I did in response to a question just previously, we<br />
make our economic decisions in termn of what the economic<br />
interest of the nation demand and that's how we've acted.<br />
There wert some who would have liked us on political<br />
grounds to ease monetary policy earlier because their<br />
argument way if you do it earlier then it'll be reflected<br />
mowe qickly into mortgage rates and that would be good<br />
polticlly But we made the judgement that it wasn't<br />
appropriate in economic term to do it earlier. I think<br />
that the Autralian electorate has shown over recent<br />
years an increasing sophistication of judgement in these<br />
matters. I don't think they would've taken kindly to a<br />
decision by me and the Goenet to bring monetary<br />
policy of f earlier than it was appropr iate to do so. I<br />
think they will make the judgement that veve made the<br />
right decision in economic to= m. I hope that taking all<br />
those things into account we' 11 get the approval of the<br />
electorate. I think we will. </p>
<p>JOUNIALST: t<br />
mest likely Are you saying Mr Hawke,, that May seem the<br />
date now?<br />
PK: I haven't said that. YOU SemM to be w* aing to get<br />
me to say it. I haven't said it. Z've said I haven't<br />
mad. my mind up yet.<br />
JOURMULST: A fair bet?<br />
PSum yWoaulrl diet'csis iyoonu. r money you're betting with,, mate. You<br />
im~ xALLM: But Ir Keating favours it wad he is Part of<br />
the teamn.<br />
PUt I an" e the decisions. I listen to what a numer of<br />
my colleagues certainly including what Paul has to say.<br />
-But in the and an in 1987, in the quietness of The Lodge<br />
or my office in Parliament Nouse ii * mke the decision.<br />
I'm not dictatorial in these matters. I like to hear the<br />
views of my colleagues and I will take aboard the<br />
thinking, of paul and other.. But in the end 1I'll make<br />
the decision that I think's appropriate.<br />
JOURNALSIT: mr Hawke, the domestic airfare price hike.<br />
Imn't that a bit rough on the public considering we were<br />
promised a better system after the polite disp: U?<br />
PHE: Yes, but just get it exactly right because the ABC I<br />
might may last night got it wrong. Hy sateIments and<br />
you look up all the transcripts and you' 11 see it quite<br />
precisely this is what I said and what 1I'll say again.<br />
I said that after the airlines recoup the losses from the<br />
dispute that was inflicted upon them by the pilots, after<br />
they reoup the loeses we will have an airline fare<br />
structure lover than it would otherwise have been because<br />
ot the enormous pilot productivity increases that arise<br />
out of what happened in 1989. Now they were my<br />
sa ts and what in fact has happa is peisely in<br />
line with that. The Independent Nf ares Tribual has<br />
not agreed to the full amount that the airlines asked to<br />
recoup their losses but it recognised that they had<br />
suffered very significant loses. They've granted an<br />
increase to help them meet those loss. But it is true<br />
and indisputedly true what I said before i that as a<br />
result of the enormous increase in pilot productivity<br />
that nov exists with very,, very many less pilots being<br />
eployed that from that factor alone airfare structure<br />
will be lover than it otherwise would've been.<br />
JOURNALIST: hike in July So do you expect there'll be aother price<br />
when they review it again?<br />
FU: I don't know, but all I<br />
right, that you are going to<br />
airfare structure than there<br />
with the airlines employingi<br />
of pilots. Now how long it~ know is that what I said is<br />
have a basis for a lower<br />
would otherwise have been<br />
k significantly lesser number<br />
till take for them to recoup<br />
0 </p>
<p>their losses, I can't sake that judgement,, I don'It<br />
assess. But there is no argument with anyone in the<br />
airline industry about the accuracy of what I've said on<br />
this matter. Xr Hawke, the Morgan Gallup Poll puts Labor<br />
slightly ahead today. Basing of monetary policy surely<br />
Must give you some confidence going into an election<br />
SO" e.<br />
PM2 Well, I think you'll recall what I've said about<br />
polls consistently. When we've been in front before I<br />
haven't exhilerated about it or gloated and when I've<br />
been behind I certainly haven't been despondent. If you<br />
look at what I've had to say to political journalists<br />
over the years, thereto one phrase that I've consistently<br />
said to them in my charitable attempt to be educative in<br />
these Matters. I've maid get your timescales, right. Then<br />
when you're on a high, a real high, don't think that<br />
that's necessarily normal. When you're down a bit, don't<br />
think that thatVs normal. Be intelligent about Your<br />
MSs n of the Australian electorate. They have<br />
become more and more sophisticated I think during the<br />
eighties. Its of course happy that we're in front. I<br />
meon it would be silly for me to say otherwise. I'm<br />
happy we're in front but I1m, rnot cooky about it. I<br />
Understand that we've got a very significant job in front<br />
of us to ecplain to the Australian electorate why the<br />
sensible decision whenever I call the election would be<br />
for them to return us.* Now I ' m not cokyo complacent<br />
about that but I do believe we can win.<br />
JOURNALIST: in your speech inside you talked about what<br />
you term the inevitability of confrontation industrial<br />
confrontation under a coalition governmet. Do YOU<br />
then regret being what most people regarded as the prime<br />
architect of confrontation in the pilots dispute?<br />
IN: Of course you'-re totally wrong in yoaw premise.<br />
Nast people don't regard as as being the prim architect<br />
of conrotaion<br />
JOUNAIT: assessment of what the obser vers were<br />
saying at the time# Prime Minister.<br />
PH: At the time. But some of thm were saying at the<br />
time and they were wrong as they so often are. An I<br />
say as in answer to your previous questions, it's good to<br />
get your timescale here and remember see we're now in<br />
January of 1990 remember that in February of lastea<br />
the Pilots Federation produced their docmints in : hl: h<br />
they said theme thing.: we are going to take on our<br />
employers, the Government,~ the ACMr and the Arbitration<br />
comission. We are not prepared, they said, to abide by<br />
the guidelines. We're going to take then on. It that<br />
means a prolonged NIP non incom period be prepared<br />
for it, they said, because we are going to fight<br />
everyone.* We're going to take the vwhole system 0Cm. They </p>
<p>6<br />
were very, very keen to do that then, they vere canf ident<br />
ina their view of history that they could take on the<br />
Australian community and get a 30% wage increase. NOV<br />
they were the people who took that position.<br />
JOWUNLIST: exercise in conciliation,, wsTt it.<br />
Ml: my friend, I'a not here an you so often want to do,<br />
to have a debate. ' s here to answer a question so let<br />
as finish. I said after they put that they woe going to<br />
destroy the wage fixing system and have a 30% increase,<br />
remember a 30% increase on a average wage of $ 60,000, the<br />
increase that they wanted was maze than the average<br />
income of ordinary Australians, I said as Prim Ninister<br />
of this country that as far an I was -WnWifr Iteh ey<br />
persisted with that position I would fight it. I would<br />
not allow Australia to be destroyed by the pilots. So I<br />
was not the initiator but 7. wasn the defender and quite<br />
clearly ma 1' ve said before, these people picked the<br />
fight, they were warned not to, they picked a fight,<br />
they've lost. I regret the trouble they've caused to<br />
everyone but the system has been an it sha'ldve beeo,<br />
defended. JOURNALIT: Mr Keating has been saying consistently that<br />
there would be no easing in monetary policy until there<br />
were clear and unamiuu signs of a slow damn in the<br />
economy. What are those signs as you now see them?<br />
PHO2 Well let me give you the aggregates and then the<br />
individual components. If you look at domestic demandl<br />
the s ituaation you' 1ve had is this; going through the Masrch<br />
quarter, the JUne quarter and the September quarter of<br />
the national accounts, in the March quarter last year<br />
there was a 3.7% growth in domestic demand. in the June<br />
quarter they had dropped to 0.6% and in the September<br />
quarter the the mast recent figures available -that<br />
had dropped to a flat figure. Those aggrgtei~<br />
have been concerned by the individual onen<br />
regard to e~ loyment which has shown a significant<br />
slawing down in growth and by housing and by the surveys<br />
that have been down at business. When you add those<br />
things together the national aggregates and the national<br />
acounts which-show the movements from 0.* 6 down to<br />
twro, take the individual components that I referred to<br />
and put then all together, its Judgement of the Reserve<br />
Bank and of the Government that the conditions have been<br />
endst </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
