<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18733</transcript-id>
    <title>COAG to review counter-terrorism legislation</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/08/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>Prime Minister Julia Gillard today announced the start of the COAG Review of Counter-Terrorism Legislation.</p>
<p>The Review will examine the Commonwealth, State and Territory counter-terrorism legislation that was introduced in 2005 after the London terrorist bombings. </p>
<p>It will look at control orders, preventative detention and certain emergency stop, question and search powers held by police.</p>
<p>Terrorism is an ever-present threat and the review of our laws is important to ensure that our laws remain necessary and provide effective powers for our police and security agencies.</p>
<p>The Hon. Anthony Whealy QC, who recently retired from the NSW Court of Appeal, will chair the COAG Review. </p>
<p>The other members of the Review Committee are:</p>
<p>•           Judge David Jones AM, retired Victorian County Court judge•           Mr Richard Bingham, South Australian Ombudsman•           Commander Justine Saunders, Australian Federal Police•           Assistant Commissioner Mike Condon, Queensland Police•           Mr Graeme Davidson, Office of the Commonwealth Director of Public Prosecutions</p>
<p>The Review Committee will provide a written report to COAG within six months.</p>
<p>The Independent National Security Legislation Monitor, which was established in 2010, also reviews Commonwealth counter-terrorism and national security laws.</p>
<p>While the Monitor's role is separate, the Review Committee will liaise with the Monitor, Mr Bret Walker SC, on this review.</p>
<p>The review has no relationship to the Parliamentary Joint Committee on Intelligence and Security's examination of potential national security reforms.</p>
<p>More information on the details of the Review, including the legislation the Review will cover and opportunities for public consultation can be found at <a href="http://www.coagctreview.gov.au">www.coagctreview.gov.au</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
