<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10227</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP SIGNING OF REGIONAL FOREST AGREEMENT (RFA) WITH PREMIER JEFF KENNETT MLA, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010227.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
3 February 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
SIGNING OF REGIONAL FOREST AGREEMENT ( RFA)<br />
WITH PREMIER JEFF KENNETT MLA, MELBOURNE<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Good morning ladies and gentlemen. The purpose of this news conference is for the<br />
Premier and myself along with the Victorian Minister responsible, Mrs Tehan, to<br />
announce that the Commonwealth Government and the Victorian Government have<br />
reached agreement and as testified by the Premier and I signing that agreement in a<br />
moment, the first of the Regional Forest Agreements covering the East Gippsland area<br />
of Victoria. This is the trail blazer of forest agreements around Australia.<br />
It is a win-win agreement. It is a win for jobs in regional Australia. It will generate<br />
investment of $ 150 million in the industry and the creation of 400 additional jobs, at<br />
least, in the industry. it is also a win for the preservation of environmental values<br />
because the nationally agreed criteria under the agreement have been reached or<br />
exceeded. And I want to thank the Victorian Government and particularly I want to<br />
compliment the two Ministers directly responsible at a Victorian and Commonwealth<br />
level that's Mrs Tehan, on behalf of the Victorian Government, and Senator Robert<br />
Hill on behalf of the Federal Government.<br />
This agreement is an example of how if you sit down in good faith and with good will<br />
you can negotiate resource security preserving environmental values. This agreement<br />
will endure for 20 years. There's provision for reviews every five years. The great<br />
thing it does is that it delivers predicability and security. It will enable people to plan,<br />
but that planning will take place in the knowledge that environmental values have been<br />
protected. So I'm delighted that the agreement has been reached and I'm delighted<br />
that I have the opportunity with the Premier of announcing that agreement today and<br />
both of us signing it on behalf of our respective governments. </p>
<p>QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS<br />
QUESTION: ( Inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
( tape break) precise break up and in a sense having entered into an agreement that<br />
protects environmental values, the important thing is that jobs in the industry generally<br />
are being created. One of the very important things we've got to understand about<br />
regional Australia is that regional Australia needs predictability and certainty and<br />
there's nothing better for regional Australian than the knowledge that you can invest in<br />
safety and that the ground rules are not going to be changed. For years and years<br />
we've had uncertainty and unpredictability in the timber industry. There's been this<br />
constant tension and tug-of-war. There was some nationally agreed criteria laid down<br />
which are world class as far as the preservation of conservation values are concerned<br />
and this agreement marries all of those things and that's why it's so good and people<br />
can now go out and invest. Small businesses, which are really the heart of much of the<br />
timber industry in regional Australia and regional Victoria, will hail this agreement and<br />
so they should because it gives them protection, predictability and certainty and that's<br />
what small business wants in Australia. And if you can give them that they'll generate<br />
the jobs that will make a contribution to reducing our unemployment level.<br />
QUESTION: ( Inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Backlash? Well, there shouldn't be because this meets the nationally agreed criteria. I<br />
mean, if we had torn up the criteria, if we had sort of ignored the conservation values,<br />
then they'd be entitled to complain. But the benchmarks that were laid down some<br />
years ago, they have been observed.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, having promoted your Wetlands Policy yesterday ( inaudible)<br />
KENNETT: I think that's a different issue. It has nothing to do with this at all.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No it hasn't. That will be considered in a proper basis as we do all issues that affect<br />
the environment. </p>
<p>r QUESTION: ( Inaudible)<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I would say to the other States this is a trail blazer, this is a model and I would<br />
hope it will be copied all over Australia, not in every particular because... but the<br />
cooperative elements of it. If you can have a win-win in other parts of Australia, if you<br />
can get regional jobs created in other parts of Australia and conservation values<br />
protected then you've got a very good deal.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
