<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4121</transcript-id>
    <title>TRADE UNION TALKS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/05/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004121.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4AUSTRALIA.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS MAY 18, 1976<br />
TRADE UNION TALKS<br />
Talks are to be held with the Trade Union Movement on<br />
June 7,11 and 12 following the return of Mr Hawke from<br />
the I. L. O. Conference in Geneva and before the departure<br />
of the Prime Minister to Japan and China.<br />
I will be spending a significant amount of time at the<br />
Conference. It will be attended by senior Ministers<br />
among them the Minister for Employment and Industrial<br />
Relations, the Treasurer, and other specialist Ministers<br />
such as the Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs,<br />
and the Minister for Industry and Commerce.<br />
W e will be prepared to discuss with Mr Hawke whether there<br />
are particular areas where he would like Government<br />
expertise to be made available to the Trade Union Movement.<br />
At the Conference the Government will lay fully on the table<br />
the advice available on the economy from the Treasury,<br />
the Reserve Bank and other Departments so there can be the<br />
fullest possible understanding of the state of Australia.<br />
It will be open at the Conference for discussion to take<br />
place on options, possibilities, and opportunities.<br />
For the Government, I am glad that Mr Hawke and the A. C. T. U.<br />
have responded to the request by the Minister for Employment<br />
and Industrial Relations as a result of my statement last night.<br />
This may be a beginning but it is an indication that diverse<br />
groups can recognise a common cause and work for that cause.<br />
I have had a number of conversations with Mr Hawke and so<br />
has the Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations.<br />
These conversations have been cooperative and constructive.<br />
We are about to embark on equivalent talks with employers.<br />
The President of the A. C. T. U. made a request to us concerning<br />
industrial legislation. We indicated that we would not<br />
proclaim that legislation although we would wish it to go<br />
through Parliament. / 2 </p>
<p>Wewould also be prepared to listen to views the union<br />
movement may express and we would do that without prejudice.<br />
The talks which Mr Street has already held with the unions<br />
concerning secret ballot legislation had already<br />
resulted in modification to that legislation.<br />
By the time these talks take place union delegates will have<br />
had the opportunity to examine these modifications<br />
in detail.<br />
I have given a complete guarantee that the Government will<br />
examine the views put forward by the union delegates in<br />
good faith.<br />
I also emphasise that the Government is committed to the<br />
principal of secret ballot legislation. S<br />
000oo00000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
