<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18331</transcript-id>
    <title>Helping Australians just say no to cyber-bullying</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/01/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The Gillard Labor Government today launched a new website to tackle cyberbullying and help more young people stay safe online.</p>
<p>The Easy Guide to Socialising Online website has been developed in partnership with industry and young people to help parents, children and educators combat cyberbullying and inappropriate content online.</p>
<p>The Easy Guide website is part of the Government's $125.8 million Cybersafety Plan and has been developed following advice from the Government's Youth Advisory Group on Cybersafety.</p>
<p>The new website provides cybersafety information for 26 social networking sites, search engines and online games, and gives step by step instructions on how to report cyberbullying, abuse and inappropriate content on these sites.</p>
<p>It also provides clear information for parents, educators and young people on how to adjust safety and privacy settings on websites as well as tips on how to stay safe when using any social media site.</p>
<p>Members of the Government's Consultative Working Group on Cybersafety (CWG), including Facebook, Google, Microsoft, NineMSN, Yahoo!7 and the Interactive Games and Entertainment Association worked closely with the Government to develop the Easy Guide website.</p>
<p>Cyberbullying is a serious matter which is why the Government has listened to young people and produced the new guide to staying safe online.</p>
<p>The Government's Cybersafety Plan involves a number of important initiatives including the Easy Guide to combat online risks to children.</p>
<p>The Cybersmart website <a href="http://www.cybersmart.gov.aulaunched">www.cybersmart.gov.aulaunched</a> two years ago, has received well over a million visits and provides access to KidsHelpline for confidential online counselling.</p>
<p>It also provides access to the Government's Cybersafety Help Button which is a ‘one stop shop' for practical information and tips on how to deal with cyberbullying, unwanted contact and offensive or illegal content.</p>
<p>Since its launch 12 months ago, the Help Button has been downloaded on more than 300,000 computers across Australia.</p>
<p>The Cybersafety Help Button can be downloaded at <a href="http://www.dbcde.gov.au/helpbutton">www.dbcde.gov.au/helpbutton</a>.</p>
<p>The new Easy Guide website address is <a href="http://www.dbcde.gov.au/easyguideand">www.dbcde.gov.au/easyguideand</a> it can also be accessed via the Cybersafety Help Button.</p>
<p>For further tips on cybersecurity and safety are available at <a href="http://www.staysmartonline.gov.au">www.staysmartonline.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
