<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10193</transcript-id>
    <title>MEDIA TRANSCRIPT PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP, PRESS CONFERENCE - PARLIAMENT HOUSE 13 DECEMBER 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010193.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96 http:// www. nia-gov~ a pressreI/ 131296. htmi<br />
MEDIA TRANSCRIPT<br />
Prime Minister the Hon. John Howard MP, PRESS C kMN EPARLIAMENT<br />
HOUSE<br />
13 December 1996<br />
E&amp; OE Good morning ladies and gentlemen. I don't have anything specific to announce this<br />
morning but I thought it would not be appropriate to end the year, political year here in<br />
Canberra, without one more full-scale press conference.<br />
I did want to make one or two very brief points at the commencement of the press<br />
conference in relation to some of the economic developments of the past couple of weeks.<br />
I think it is important to see those developments, particularly the falls in interest rates, as<br />
being part of a pattern whereby you do eventually get not only a good news story but also<br />
good economic news as a result of the right policies having been followed or the right<br />
developments having occurred in the economy. It's important to remember that the falls in<br />
interest rates are, at least in part I think in large part due to the fact that we now have<br />
very low inflation in Australia and that low inflation has been contributed to by wage<br />
restraint. And I again take the opportunity of thanking the working men and women of<br />
Australia for the wage restraints that they have evidenced over the past several years<br />
and I quite deliberately say the past several years and not just and only the last nine<br />
months and it is important to see the contribution that that has made.<br />
And it's also important to see the contribution that the fiscal consolidation process the<br />
reduction in the budget deficit in the budget brought down in August the contribution<br />
that has made. And the point out of all of this is that there is good news at the end of the<br />
process. And it's important that the material rewards of good policy are both understood<br />
by and explained to the Australian community. And there can be no disputing the material<br />
value of cuts in interest rates and there can be no disputing the boost that that represents<br />
to thle household disposable income of the great bulk of Australian families, particularly<br />
those who are paying off a home.<br />
I guess the other point that I wanted to make is that that connection, those linkages, just<br />
as the linkages between the benefits of changes in levels of protection and the benefits of<br />
trade liberalisation, also need to be spelt out very clearly to the community. And there is<br />
an obligation on governments and there's an obligation on those who talk about and write<br />
about politics and about political and economic developments to constantly make those<br />
linkages so that we are not talking in the abstract about thle desirability of particular policy<br />
changes, and that policy goals are not seen as ends in themselves but rather as means to<br />
achieving material benefits and higher living standards for the Australian people. So when<br />
I talk about the desirability of budget deficits being lower, I have in mind lower interest<br />
rates, when I argue for wage restraint, I have in mind lower interest rates because of the<br />
' feed on' effect of wage restraint on inflation rates. And when we argue for trade<br />
liberalisation, we are taking about job generation and job creation. And there is a constant<br />
obligation on people in the political process and in the levels of government to make<br />
those linkages. Are there any questions?<br />
QUESTION:<br />
I of 161 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 72 6 </p>
<p>. PM Press Conference ment H-ouse, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagva. rerI1326tm<br />
Mr Howard, you mentioned in your speech to Parliament the other day that you had<br />
several goals for next year the environment, infrastructure, getting investment going<br />
can you give us some more details about what you actually have in mind within those<br />
three headings and also tell us a bit more about your Project Facilitator?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, the Project Facilitator will be somebody who's had experience in business. He or she<br />
will be filling a debate and consultancy position on my staff establishment. I have several<br />
people in mind. I haven't decided on anybody yet. There's a number of people I want to<br />
talk to and I hope to make an announcement in the early part of next year early in the<br />
New Year. The main purpose that this individual will pursue will quite literally be to push<br />
aside any roadblocks and to achieve, in the shortest period of time, Government<br />
approvals that are needed for major projects and able to have a fairly loose definition of a<br />
major project. We don't want to hamstring ourselves by having artificially high thresholds<br />
so far as major projects are concerned. I think there is somebody needed to fulfil this role.<br />
That's not to say the approval process is too slow at the present time. I think it can always<br />
be made faster. This will not, I should stress, be some kind of hunting license to push<br />
aside proper environmental or other concerns. But getting major projects going in<br />
Australia, not only for the value they have in themselves but also the downstream benefits<br />
they have for small business, is a very, very important part of the architecture of<br />
investment in this country and a very, very important goal to be pursued.<br />
You asked me about some of the other things. If you ask me about next year, I think it's<br />
fair to say that next year will be very much about continuing to implement our agenda. I<br />
mean, we have quite a lot on the calender already. We have the detail response to the<br />
Charlie Bell Report on small business deregulation by the middle of February. And when<br />
that comes down I think I will be able to say to the small business community, when you<br />
add in thle benefits to the unfair dismissal laws going, the industrial relations reforms, the<br />
capital gains tax changes which really are a very, very significant liberalisation of the tax<br />
regime for small business and that won't start until the first of July next year when you<br />
add all of those things in together we'll be able to tell a very strong and active story in the<br />
small business area. We'll have the Wallis Inquiry in March; we'll have a focus on<br />
superannuation and savings policy in the budget; there is getting in to train the process of<br />
selling one third of Telstra;-establishing the Natural Heritage Trust; there'll be further<br />
building on the Supermarket to Asia initiative and there is the need to keep up the<br />
pressure on microeconomic reform; Native Title reform will be back on the agenda<br />
because that will need to be debated again and a decision made by the Senate next year;<br />
there will be debate, obviously, on our proposals in relation to responses on the Head of<br />
State issue, and there'll be a few surprises as always happens in politics and it's always a<br />
pity to spoil surprises by speculating as to what they might be. But there is a very active<br />
agenda already being drawn up for next year. I'll be having a lengthy Cabinet meeting in<br />
Sydney on Monday and Tuesday next week to not only wrap up the year but also to<br />
throw ahead into the New Year and to talk about some of these issues and also to talk<br />
about some others.<br />
QUESTION: The other day you mentioned that you thought that large spending cuts were not needed<br />
in the budget next year. Could you elaborate more precisely on your position on<br />
spending?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: 2 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 1<br />
http:// www. nla. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
2 of 16 </p>
<p>. PiU Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. resl/ 326tm<br />
Well, I don't want to pre-empt what's going to be in thle budget process, which<br />
incidentally will start fairly early in the New Year, because the budget's in May.<br />
QUESTION: When does it actually start?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It starts, heaven forbid, in February. So we'll all need a bit of a holiday.<br />
QUESTION: Did you just say...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I'm not going to say any more than what I said the other day, I'm really not. The<br />
point I sought to make the other day is that we'd laid down in the budget $ 4 billion, about<br />
$ 4 billion, this year building to $ 7.2 billion over a two year period leading to, in year<br />
three, to an underlying balance. Now, that remains thle parameter and that remains the<br />
goal. There'll be a mid-year review which will be released in January by the Treasurer<br />
which will give us a clue as to how that's all going. I still don't know the final outcome in<br />
relation to somne legislation in the Senate. I understand we had some success last night in<br />
relation to the R&amp; D measures. So we're doing reasonably well, but we've lost a bit and<br />
we could lose some more, I hope we don't. I'm not going to get into further figures. I'm<br />
just going to say that, again, that we stay with parameter and the goal that was laid down<br />
in the budget.<br />
QUESTION: Any new spending would have to be offset.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
People will have a new spending proposal a new policy proposal. The normal thing<br />
would be to seek offsetting savings. But I really am not going to go into any more<br />
speculate... we have a goal that was laid down very clearly in the budget that remains the<br />
goal and the parameter and we think it represented a significant achievement that level<br />
of fiscal consolidation and we're very keen to preserve those achievements and those<br />
gains.<br />
QUESTION: How quickly do you see the benefits of the industrial relations changes and the fiscal<br />
consolidation flowing through to small business and employment?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, the first thing that's got to happen is that they've got to come into operation. I<br />
mean, I actually read a story somewhere the other day perhaps it was a report of<br />
somebody's comment that the industrial relations reforms had failed. I mean, they 3 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 1<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. html<br />
3 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96 http:// www. nla. gov. a pressreI/ I31296. htm<br />
haven't even come into operation. They don't start until the first of January. Now, they<br />
will take time. And I think it is very important and I take the opportunity of saying this<br />
in relation to unemployment but that is going to take time and I went to some lengths<br />
yesterday not to exaggerate the good news out of yesterday's figures. I acknowledged<br />
that and I'll say it again that it's always unwise to put too much emphasis on one<br />
months' figures. I was pleased that it was the best figure since July and I was pleased that<br />
you'd had two months of employment growth. And psychologically coming the day after<br />
the interest rate cut it certainly injected a note of confidence. And I endorse that<br />
confidence but I also enter the caveat that it's a long, hard road on unemployment and<br />
you'll need a whole lot of things over a period of time working in a way that gives you<br />
maximum impact and maximum success. You need the IR changes to work their way<br />
through, and they do provide a lot more flexibility; you need the benefits of lower interest<br />
rates to work their way through into higher growth; you need the benefits of trade<br />
liberalisation to work their way through into more jobs and more exports; you need<br />
microeconornic changes, freeing up supply bottlenecks. I've said always that the two<br />
things that are most needed to get lower unemployment are higher growth and<br />
microeconomic reform, removal of the supply bottlenecks, particularly but not only in<br />
industrial relations.<br />
Now all of these thing will take time and I don't want to pretend to you or to the<br />
Australian people that they won't take time and there's no merit in sort of proclaiming<br />
premnature and illusory victories in any of these areas. It's unwise and it devalues the<br />
process and it causes disappointment if and when things go in another direction.<br />
JOURNALIST: So taking up some of your points on inflation in terms of your introductory comments, as<br />
you are aware, JEFG met this week. I think it started a meeting on Monday, and the early<br />
indications are that JEFG has decided to revise down the budget forecast for the<br />
underlying inflation rate and the headline inflation rate. Would you confirm that and<br />
would you like to...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No I won't confirm anything. I haven't got JEFG's report yet and I'm not going to confirm speculation.<br />
JOURNALIST: If JEFG has in fact revised down its inflation forecast, what would you see as the<br />
implications for...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I don't answer hypothetical questions.<br />
JOURNALIST: How quickly would you see the business community actually adopting the industrial<br />
relations, the Australian workplace agreements, enterprise bargaining?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the indications I have are that they wili, particularly in the small and medium sized end of the<br />
4 of 164 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 2 </p>
<p>. PMVPr ess Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. rsre132. tm<br />
show, adopt them very quickly, very quickly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Before the election you made it clear that you would be very disappointed if youth unemployment<br />
didn't come down significantly. How confident, is that the number one priority for the next year and<br />
how confident are you that you will see significant results in the next twelve months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Michael, the best thing I can do is to see that all of the arms of Government policy and decision<br />
making are directed towards trying to reduce unemployment, commit my Government to work very<br />
hard to do that, push as hard as I can to get policies which are going to have a beneficial effect on<br />
unemployment in place and working and as you know, I make the point again that some of the specific<br />
policies that we have brought in to help reduce unemployment haven't really been allowed to operate<br />
yet. Now the IR changes will come in on the first of January. I mean, the unfair dismissal law against<br />
which we so properly railed for so long is still there right at the moment as I speak. It won't be until<br />
the first of January that the Brereton law will finally be swept away. The changes in relation to capital<br />
gains tax will begin to bit on the first of July. I think they will, when they are widely understood in the<br />
small business community, they will bring about a very significant shift in investment flows into small<br />
business. I mean, you've got a situation where up to $ 5 million in value, this is you can sell one<br />
business and buy another up to $ 5 million and they can be completely dissimilar businesses without<br />
incurring any liability for capital gains tax. Now that's a very significant change in the investment<br />
climate and the risk taking climate for small business.<br />
Now these are still to bite. ' Now I'm not complaining about that because we set the first of<br />
July next year as the commencement date in the election policy but I am trying to explain<br />
in mentioning those starting dates that a lot of these things are yet to bite and therefore<br />
for me to start trying to put dates and figures on when the beneficial effects of those<br />
things biting, I just can't do that but I really want the community to understand that there<br />
is a time lag involved in these things and I accept that and that's one of the reasons why I<br />
am not making exaggerated claims about what may have occurred yesterday. I mean, I am<br />
very pleased about what occurred yesterday and if the drop in unemployment and the rise<br />
in employment brings more confidence and helps consumer confidence, that's a terrific<br />
thing but I just want to react to it accurately and sensibly.<br />
JOURNALIST: What specific work has the Cabinet Employment Committee done so far in relation to the employment<br />
issue? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, we've begun to look at microeconomic changes that can have a beneficial impact and we've<br />
commissioned a study on a number of other issues that bear on levels of employment, or might bear on<br />
levels of employment. I don't for reasons of, proper reasons of confidentiality that you will understand,<br />
I don't want to elaborate any further. It's a committee that, we've also looked at aspects of the new<br />
approach to labour market programns and the new approach to the employment market. We've spent<br />
quite a bit of time examining those. I don't really at this stage Geoff, want to go into any more detail<br />
for reasons of confidentiality.<br />
JOURNALIST: 5 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 2<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
of 16 </p>
<p>. PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htpfwwnagva. rerl/ 3126tm<br />
By emphasising the lag time in relation to the effects of policies coming in, are you indirectly saying to<br />
us well, hold your judgement on our performance ooi the employment front, and if so, could you give<br />
us a time frame in your own mind when you think it's going to be fair for the Australian people to<br />
make an assessment as to whether your policies are working or otherwise, on the jobs front?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The Australian people will decide when and how they judge us and it's not for me or for you to sort of<br />
lay down when the Australian people will make a judgement about us. That is for them and it's<br />
uniquely within their gift to do that and I'm not going to say well, Australian people, by such and such<br />
a date and not before then, you can make a judgement on uIS. I mean, that would be presumptuous. I<br />
am not going to do that. I am not trying to overemphasise it. I am trying to talk factually and<br />
accurately. I think it's very important at this stage in our economic development that we do that and I<br />
think it's also very important to remind people that in an area as crucial as industrial relations, the law<br />
only commences on the first of January next year. I mean, a lot will happen in the first half of next<br />
year. You will have the start of the industrial relations law. You will have one billion dollars of family<br />
tax initiatives. Family tax cuts comne into operation at the beginning of January. You will have the<br />
Government's response to the small business deregulation taskforce, you will have the receipt of the<br />
Wallis Inquiry. All I am endeavouring to do is react in an informed, balanced fashion. I think the<br />
economnic steps that we have taken over the last nine months have been excellent and I am very<br />
pleased about the developments on the interest rate front. I am very pleased about the development on<br />
the employment front. I am not trying to gear back expectations. Equally, I want the expectations to<br />
be realistic and I want people to understand that you can't make a judgement on the effectiveness on a<br />
law within a few months of its operation, let alone before it's even begun to operate. So I think it is<br />
important that those sequences be emphasised.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the issue of race, yesterday the Social Justice Commissioner laid the blame largely at your feet for<br />
the, he's quoting you, now insidious rise in racism. Do you acknowledge that racism continues to be a<br />
problem and what can you do next year to try and put a lid on it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I thought Mr Dodson's remarks were inaccurate and quite intemperate. They didn't really do his<br />
own cause a great deal of justice. I'd point out that yesterday I had a brief but very constructive<br />
meeting with the new board of ATSIC. I had previously had a discussion with the new Chairman of<br />
ATSIC, Gatjil Djerrkura. There seemed to me to be a willingness on the part of the new board and the<br />
new Chairman to work in a very positive way and think about the future in this area rather than the<br />
immediate past and 1 welcome that. I welcome that very warmly and I can only repeat what I said in<br />
the Parliament yesterday, that we are very committed and genuinely committed to the process of<br />
reconciliation. I do want to in 1997 demonstrate very clearly that although I will do things in<br />
Aboriginal affairs somewhat differently from the previous Government and the previous Prime<br />
Minister, my personal commitment to doing something to improve the disadvantage of the Aboriginal<br />
people is no less than his but I will do it differently.<br />
JOURNALIST: When will you go and visit Aboriginal communities?<br />
PRIME MVINISTER:<br />
I have had some discussions already with some people regarding that including the 6 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 2<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
6 of 16 </p>
<p>. PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagva. resl/ 326tm<br />
Chairman of the Council for Aboriginal Reconciliation and when I amn in a position to<br />
indicate when I will be doing that, I will let you know, but I have spent some time over<br />
the past few months constructing the broad outline of my diary for next year and it will<br />
involve a great deal of travel around Australia. But I don't want to visit Aboriginal<br />
communities in settlements in any kind of tokenistic sense but I do want to visit them.<br />
Like all Australians who in their upbringing have not had much contact with Aboriginal<br />
people, and I guess like many others 1 didn't, I have a lot to learn and understand about<br />
their culture but I will be approaching that on a basis of goodwill, recognising that I bring<br />
some different perspectives and a different way of doing things and I think part of the<br />
difficulty that has occurred in the past in this area is that some people have been reluctant<br />
to accept that when you have a new Government, even though the commitment to<br />
achieving the end result may be no less, because the way of doing it is different, resistance<br />
builds up and I think we can put a lot of that behind us.<br />
I think the changes that we have made in relation to the ATS1C board are good. I<br />
welcome all of the new members to that board and congratulate those that have been<br />
re-elected and I think we can work in a very constructive fashion but I don't pretend that<br />
it will be argument or debate fl-ee and neither it should because it's a difficult area and I<br />
don't have instant solutions to things like deaths in custody. I mean, that's a problem that's<br />
bedevilled Liberal and Labor Governments at a state and federal level for a long time and<br />
it's the product, as I said in Parliament yesterday, it's a product of the social disadvantage<br />
and disintegration of Aboriginal communities. It's a product of the high incarceration rate.<br />
Because there are more Aboriginals in custody than other Australians inevitably the<br />
number of deaths in custody is higher although I understand it's still broadly the case that<br />
the rate is no different, but there's just such a sharply higher proportion of the Aboriginal<br />
community in custody.<br />
Now that is a very difficult issue to respond to. You can't just simply say well, we won't<br />
have any more custodial responses. It's not quite as simple as that. That's not to say you<br />
couldn't work out in relation to some levels of activity alternatives to custodial sentences.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Dodson was particular critical of your response to the Larrakia claim over public land<br />
in Darwin, saying you were criticising them for the mere exercise of their legal rights.<br />
Does he have a point?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No I don't, look he's entitled in a free society to say what he chooses and I'm not going to<br />
overreact to that. I mean, I think the whole cast of the remnarks was intemperate and over<br />
the top. There are weaknesses in the Native Title legislation. We're endeavouring to<br />
remedy those but we won't do anything that violates the fundamental principles of that<br />
legislation or indeed the Mabo decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: With the benefits of hindsight, do you think the Government could have handled the<br />
communication in this new approach in the Aboriginal Affairs area earlier. Do you think<br />
that some mistakes were made by the Government that you've now put behind you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: 7 f 1601/ 1117:/ 0907: 33<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
7 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. resI1326tm<br />
Well, no I mean, look in a finite sense all Government's make errors and we've made some<br />
and we'll make some in the future. I think in a sense some of this shaking out process was<br />
inevitable because we are just doing things somewhat differently and we do have a<br />
different emphasis. The emphasis on economic independence that Senator Herron spoke<br />
of in his address at the university a few weeks ago which has been picked up by the new<br />
Chairman, that is different firomn that of the former Government. I mean, they will comb<br />
through and find a bit in the speech that says ' economic independence' but it really wasn't<br />
the emphasis of their approach. So I don't think we made any major mistakes I don't. I<br />
think John Herron has done a great job. I know lhe has been criticised by a number of<br />
people in this room. I always was publicly and privately very supportive of him because I<br />
knew in him I had a person whose instincts were absolutely... they were well placed, his<br />
motives were correct and he had great personal application to the job and a great deal of<br />
personal compassion and commitment to trying to do something practical to remedy<br />
disadvantage. Now, people will comb over a criticise different ways of doing it, but I<br />
think as time has gone by the wisdom of his approach and the Government's approach is<br />
winning wider acceptance. Now, I don't want to put it any higher than that because this is<br />
a difficult area and I understand that and it requires comnmunication not only to the<br />
Aboriginal community but to the rest of the Australian community. Because you can<br />
never underestimate the immense damage that was done within the wider Australian<br />
community to the cause of accepting the need to continue to do special things to help thle<br />
Aboriginal community by things like the Hindmarsh Bridge. I mean that is something that<br />
just was the most massive turn-off to the rest of Australia and it was one of the I think<br />
the most ignoble features of the former Government's handling of policy in this area.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the issue more generally of race though, the Hanson race issue, are you happy or do<br />
you think that racism continues to be a problem more generally in the community, and<br />
what will you do about it in 1997?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I don't believe that Australia is a racist country. I think I've been asked this before<br />
but..<br />
JOURNALIST: inaudible.... . you'd have to concede..<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, there are racists in Australia, of course there are. There are racists in every country.<br />
As the Far Eastern Economic review pointed out in its editorial that was reproduced in<br />
the Sydney Morning Herald a few days ago, Australia compares rather favourably with<br />
many other countries in this area. That's a point that was made by President Clinton.<br />
Look, I will continue to publicly repudiate racism. I will continue to put the views that I<br />
did during the debate on the motion in the parliament, I'll continue to express the sort of<br />
view that I did yesterday in response to the question asked of me by Clyde Holding about<br />
the activities of the Larouche organisation. But I have to say in the context of this that it<br />
is very important that we don't Sound apologetic to thle rest of the world on the issue of<br />
racism because our credentials are very creditable indeed, they are far ahead of most and<br />
they are certainly not things that we should be defensive or apologetic about, whilst 8 f 1601/ 1117:/ 0907: 33<br />
http:// www. nla. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. html<br />
8 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagva. psrI/ 326tm<br />
acknowledging as I frequently have, that there are dark stains on our history of which the<br />
treatment of the Aborigines is obviously the most prominent.<br />
JOURNALIST: You said at the beginning of the year immediately after the election that you wanted<br />
Australia to be more relaxed and comfortable. How far progressed do you think that is?<br />
Has there been a change in societies attitudes?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It's sort of become by design or whatever my label. I actually used it in the context of an<br />
attitude that we should have towards, an attitude of confidence as to what sort of people<br />
we were and what we had achieved and how we were regarded by the rest of the world.<br />
That was the context in which I used it, although I am quite happy if people give it a<br />
wider application. I don't underestimate the amount of stress and the difficulties in<br />
adjustment in so many walks of life, so many ways of life has imposed on the Australian<br />
community, and I think in understanding that we have asked a lot of our fellow<br />
Australians over recent years, we've asked them to accept a lot of change and we have to<br />
ask them to accept more change in the future, if we are to secure some of the economic<br />
beach heads that we want and it is very important that you do a number of things. It is<br />
very important that you don't use overdramatic or exaggerated language in either claiming<br />
things or declaiming things. I think it is very important that you where possible<br />
understand the level of, I suppose, concern and anxiety there may be in the community<br />
about the incidence of change and I think part of the process is to feel self-confident as a<br />
people and as a nation and not be constantly told that we have to apologise to the rest of<br />
the world or apologise excessively for what may have gone before us.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you succeeded though do you believe....<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That is something for other people to judge. I can't make that judgment. I talk to the<br />
Australian people a lot, I spend a great deal of time meeting people and I'll spend even<br />
more time meeting people next year because it will be a time in which I travel around the<br />
country a great deal. I have a sense in which I'm succeeding from those exchanges but<br />
that ultimately is not for m-e to judge. It would be impertinent of me to even try.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the point of more change, Mr Howard, you just mentioned. Does the record of the<br />
Senate over the last few months give you confidence and greater ambitions about what<br />
you would like to do in this current term of the parliament try to achieve more than you<br />
sort of originally foreshadowed or that you originally thought you could achieve.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I'm very pleased that Senators Harradine and Colston supported our Telstra<br />
legislation and have supported other legislation and I was very pleased at the negotiation<br />
between the Democrats and I don't want to in my thanks forget to thank the Democrats<br />
for supporting our industrial relations legislation. I think it is very important that that be 9 f 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 4<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
9 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. rere1326tm<br />
said. I'm encouraged by what's happened over the past few months but we have an agenda<br />
and we are going to continue to push for that agenda and I mean, when I talked about<br />
surprises I don't want you to get sort of too imaginative about that, but there'll be a few<br />
surprises.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, how high on the agenda is the question of trying to reform the waterfront?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh that's a very important part of micro-economic reform which is...<br />
JOURNALIST: And when will we see a push on that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, it is an issue that is being discussed by me with the relevant Ministers and it will<br />
continue to be discussed over the next little while.<br />
JOURNALIST: But what about action?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, discussion normally precedes the action. Or action normally follows discussion.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could you be more precise about when...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I won't be more precise than that.<br />
JOURNALIST: In relation to the issue of the pace of reform. There are many people in the business<br />
community either publicly or privately who contrast your style with that of Peter<br />
Costello's. They describe Peter Costello's approach to reform as capital R revolution and<br />
your's as capital E evolution. How do you respond to those sorts of comments. Do you<br />
think they are unfair and do you see that there is a risk of a possible split between Mr<br />
Costello and yourself over the next two years on the pace of reform?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No.<br />
JOURNALIST: l~ t 1601/ 1117: 0/ 90: 73 4<br />
http:// www. nla. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htpfwwnagva. resl/ 326tm<br />
On the republic. As Prime Minister, have you changed your view about the inevitability of<br />
becoming an Australian republic?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm trying to remember precisely all the various formulations that I've used in the past. I<br />
mean, Geoff, my view is as follows. I do think the present system works very well. I don't<br />
think it is going to make any material difference if we change and we have to be very<br />
careful if we were to change that what we changed to is as stable and as coherent as the<br />
system we have at the present time. I've also acknowledged, and it is a fact that the<br />
attitude of the Australian community towards the constitutional monarchy is quite<br />
different now from what it was 30 or 40 years ago. It is quite different, and there is with<br />
the passage of time an acceleration of that process. But I've also I suppose invoked the<br />
Benjamin Franklin injunction that the only two things in life that are inevitable are death<br />
and taxation and I have a Burkeian view of life that you don't change institutions unless<br />
they are demonstrated to have failed. But I think the process of changed attitude<br />
continues, so if that means, I mean, in theory nothing is inevitable, in practice obviously it<br />
more likely now than what it would have been thought to have be the case 10 or 20 years<br />
ago. But then, because it is a bit of anl unpredictable thing, I remind myself of a<br />
conversation 1 had with the Canadian Minister for Consumer Affairs in Ottawa in 1977,<br />
which is over 19 years ago. It was my first visit as a Minister and we had a luncheon and<br />
we had a toast at the luncheon to the Queen of Canada and hie turned around to me and<br />
he said ' well, you know, we probably will have to pretty soon here change this system<br />
because it really does need changing'. Now that was 19 years ago. In fact, the Republican<br />
push in Canada was stronger in the 1970s than it is in the 1990s. Now there are<br />
countervailing influences. Some people argue that the proximity to the United States is a<br />
reason why it works in a subtle way to reinforce links with countries other than the<br />
United States. Now I just throw that in but, look, in the end there will be a vote on this<br />
and people will make a decision. I've been very open about my own view. I was open<br />
about it before the election, I'm open about it now. I'm not trying to stall the process but<br />
I'm not going to be stampeded into a handling of the process that is less than the best you<br />
can have. It's not like an election, you can't keep revisiting constitutional change. I mean,<br />
if we changed to a republic we're not going to have another vote in three years time as to<br />
whether we'll change back. So that's perhaps picking up a comment that was made in the<br />
SM. I-editorial to the effect that elections, you'd have elections that are decided by narrow<br />
margins. I think something like a profound constitutional change is different than that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will people be ready to vote on this by the Year 2000 in your view?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What at a referendum? My feeling at the moment is that, I mean, I would be surprised if<br />
I think I've said this before I'd be surprised if there were the kind of momentum for a<br />
unifying change by the Year 2000. But I mean, I may be wrong. These things change as<br />
time goes by. I mean, there was obviously quite a shift in public opinion in Australia on<br />
this issue between, sort of, late 80s and the early 90s and sometimes these things they go<br />
in, not fits and starts, but you have a lot of activity and a shift and then it slows down for<br />
a while and then it spurts up again.<br />
JOURNALIST: 11 of 1601/ 1117: 0/ 907: 3 5<br />
hnp:// www. nla. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
11 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagva. pesI/ 326tm<br />
You're still committed to the plebiscite before the next election though aren't you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I've never said that. What I've said in relation to votes is that the Australian people<br />
will have a vote on this issue before the turn of the century. I don't recall having said, if I<br />
did it was a mistake and rendition of the policy, I don't recall having said that there would<br />
be a plebiscite before the next election.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you'll see the plebiscite as meeting your commitment in terms of the electorate having<br />
a vote on the issue before the turn of the century?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What I'm saying, John, is that the people will have a vote on this. I'm not going to, once<br />
again, get into hypothetical questions. We are considering all of the options right at the<br />
moment and I said a few days ago that I'd make a considered statement about it in the<br />
new year. Now I'm not going to get into any further sharp responses on the policy. Geoff<br />
Kitney invited me to, sort of, think in more general terms about it which I've done which<br />
is quite a different thing. Look, we are handling it, we're going to produce a process that<br />
will enable, which will make all but the unreasonable feel that they are completely<br />
involved in it and there'll be a vote. I'm not going to stall it or shove it under the carpet<br />
but equally I'm not going to be stampeded into laying down an agenda which is less than<br />
ideal. I have the very strongest view that if we are to change it should be in circumstances<br />
that unites the Australian community and not in circumstances that divide us.<br />
JOURNALIST: If you're talking about the plebiscite beyond this term than that's no longer a commitment<br />
to ensure the people have a vote. Because you can give no commitments beyond this<br />
term.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That will be covered when I make a statement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you agree with Mr Fischer's comments from last Friday that he'd prefer to see you<br />
opening the Olympics rather than the Queen?<br />
PRI[ ME MINISTER:<br />
I didn't know he'd said that. Any way...<br />
JOURNALIST: Well how do you feel about...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: 12 of 16011/ 11: 70/ 09: 375<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
12 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. rerI132. tm<br />
Well look, how do I feel about the opening of the Olympic Games? I think, look, I seem<br />
to remember saying some three or four years ago when I was certainly not Prime Minister<br />
and certainly not Leader of the Opposition that I thought there was a good case for the<br />
Prime Minister of the day opening the games. I think that's part of the discussion that's<br />
going on at the present time. I'm not hankering to do it. We'll just see what emerges. I'm<br />
certainly not hankering to do it.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the gun issue, were you satisfied the gun buy back scheme has been a success?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I understand that as of last Friday, or is it today, there are 228,000 fewer weapons in<br />
Australia than there were 12 months ago which is a remarkable achievement. I've even<br />
got a pen here which I was given the other day by the Chief Minister of the Australian<br />
Capital Territory which is made out of gun stock by the Richmond Foundation here in<br />
Canberra which includes quite a number of people who, sort of, had some troubled<br />
background. I suppose it's a modern example of beating swords into plough shears. I<br />
mean, it's just an example of, I suppose in a peacefully symbolic way, of what has<br />
happened.<br />
JOURNALIST: But even though people are handing their guns in they're also buying legal guns.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I can only tell you what the figures are and that's a net figure.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, you talked about Mr Herron's performance this year. A number of other<br />
Ministers have been criticised, Kim Beazley suggested you should sack Alexander<br />
Downer.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I won't be.<br />
JOURNALIST: How likely is there, what's the likelihood of any sort of reshuffle in the next 12 months?<br />
PIME MINISTER:<br />
I have not intention of having a reshuffle. You will understand that I'm not going to, just<br />
as I'm not going to grade relationships with countries, I'm not going to start grading<br />
ministerial performances. I'll talk generally and say that I am very well satisfied with the<br />
way my Ministry has performed and I don't have any plans for a reshuffle.<br />
JOURNALIST: 13 of 16011/ 11: 70/ 09: 375<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. html<br />
13 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. pesI/ 326tm<br />
Mr Howard, in your preview of next year you didn't make any reference to the COAG<br />
process. Are you concerned that the COAG process has run off the rails and has lost<br />
momentum and do you have an plan to try and reinvigorate it and try and break through<br />
what now seems to be a very complex bureaucratic web that's wrapped around it and<br />
ground it to a halt?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I didn't mention it that's true that doesn't mean to say I've lost interest in it. I would<br />
point out, of course, that one of the things that we are trying to do in these areas it that<br />
where you can actually achieve something such as the Victorian IR hand over you<br />
certainly go ahead and try and do it. The Commonwealth State area is littered with grand<br />
speeches and heroic declarations the big changes that have been achieved in this area<br />
have really been achieved through a pragmatic seizing of an opportunity, going through<br />
an opening when it suddenly presents itself and I'm going to continue to do that. I think<br />
you can probably achieve some packages, if I can use that expression, in this<br />
Commonwealth State area in a less grandly announced fashion than...<br />
JOURNALIST: So you're saying the COAG process has got problems then?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, the COAG process is always going to be a fairly tortuous one, always, and the<br />
meeting that we intended to have a few weeks ago was aborted at the last moment<br />
because of the Western Australian election but I do intend to reconvene that meeting in<br />
the first half of next year...<br />
JOURNALIST: Sounds like you don't have high expectations?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well no, I'm not saying I don't have I'm trying to get the expectations at a realistic level.<br />
I watched what happened with Bob Hawke's new Federalism. That had the support of<br />
Nick Greiner, the Liberal Premier of New South Wales, I seem to think to recall it was<br />
sunk by my immediate predecessor in the Office of the Prime Minister.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Howard, in terms of some of the State Premiers they've been pushing for tax reform<br />
which in mnany quarters has taken as code for GST. Do you think there's a risk that some<br />
of those Premiers are pushing the tax reform issue so strongly that it will end up being<br />
counterproductive and forcing you to knock GST on the head forever?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't think anything my State Premiers do is counterproductive.<br />
JOURNALIST: 14 of 16011/ 11: 70/ 09: 376<br />
hftp:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. html<br />
14 of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. resI/ 326tl<br />
Mr Howard, just on foreign investment. Do you see this as something that the public,<br />
weighing up the benefits and the concerns of foreign investment that the public are<br />
confubsed about, do you see it as an issue that's going to bubble along next year and how<br />
easy is it to explain given how motive the issue is the values that follow it to the public?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
There's always been an ambivalent view and an unsympathetic view in general in the<br />
community about foreign investment. I probably have it too, I mean, I would rather<br />
everything be own by Australians I would. In an emotional sense I think Australian<br />
ownership beats the ownership of anybody. But we don't have that luxury. We need the<br />
savings of foreigners because we don't generate enough of our own and if we want the<br />
living standard we now enjoy, even a higher one, we're going to have to for a long, long<br />
time into the future take foreign investment. So it's an argument that has to be constantly<br />
put and I will, I have over a long period of time, put that argument I put it again the<br />
other day in thle Parliament and I'll continue to put it. Now it's not necessarily a popular<br />
view. I mean, out there people would, and I understand it when they see great brand<br />
names disappearing I understand all of that, but it just emphasises the need to ( tape turn<br />
over)... position. I think I'll take one more.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I ask you about the Western Australian election. Would you have a message for West<br />
Australians.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the message I would have for Western Australia is Richard Court, overwhelmingly,<br />
deserves to be re-elected but they've had a very weird distribution and nobody in Western<br />
Australia should go into the polling booth tomorrow thinking they have the luxury of a<br />
protest vote because it's otherwise you could have a strange outcome. I think it's very<br />
important that that be understood. But I wish Richard well. We have a close working<br />
relationship. He deserves to be re-elected. He's run a very good government and I hope<br />
he wins and wins handsomely.<br />
JOURNALIST: On Telstra there's been some confidence that you could do better than $ 8 billion or could<br />
get as high as $ 10 billion. If you do better than the $ 8 billion will that go to the budget<br />
bottom line or..<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh well that's a hypothetical question. I don't know how well we'll do. I mean, we may<br />
do, I mean, $ 8 billion was a realistic estimate but we haven't really got into thinking about<br />
it, we're just working on the basis that we'll get around about $ 8 billion and $ 7 billion will<br />
go into retiring debt and the rest into the Natural Heritage Trust. We haven't really<br />
thought about the possibility of any more. But I certainly, I suppose I'd say I have quite<br />
an interest in further debt retirement but it's quite hypothetical at this stage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister can I ask on Telstra you know that you've got the sale secured. Will you 15 of 16011/ 11: 70/ 09: 736<br />
http:// www. nia. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
of 16 </p>
<p>PM Press Conference ment House, 13.12.96htp/ wwnagv.. resI/ 126tm<br />
wait for the sale to go ahead before putting the funds into the Natural Heritage Trust or<br />
will the environment fund<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
1 think in relation to some of those funds I would have to go away and check I don't want<br />
to give the wrong answer. I think we have already announced there's some money that,<br />
once the legislation had gone through, that we were going to put in but I better take a<br />
rain cheque on that. Thank you very much and Merry Christmas.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will you be announcing Cabinet decisions next week?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it depends what decisions we take. We could be making some announcements, I<br />
mean, I wouldn't all of you come to Sydney. You're always welcome but I don't think,<br />
look, I don't have any surprises next week. But we may have a few announcements out of<br />
it. Thank you and Merry Christmas.<br />
Return to Media Transcripts<br />
Last aa1, udutt1e7d D ecemnber 1996 16 of 1601/ 1117: 0/ 907: 3 7<br />
http:// www. nla. gov. a pressrel/ 131296. htmi<br />
16 of 16 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
