<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22811</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview at the Freedom House, DMZ, Panmunjon</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Doorstop</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Visit to DMZ</p>
<p>E&amp;OE  …………………………………………………………………………………</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What were your thoughts when you went in . . . </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It’s still very relevant today, it’s still being acted out, played out and I think that’s fascinating.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How long do you think it will be before you go across the border into North Korea yourself – given that Australia’s now recognizing it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it could come quicker than we would have imagined a few years ago.  I think it’s a tremendous breakthrough and I think President Kim Dae-jung deserves an enormous amount of praise from the rest of the world for what he’s done.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Would you go to North Korea yourself?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>If it were appropriate to do so, yes.  Once you establish diplomatic relations with a country of course.  But it’s something where Korea has taken the lead on, I will take my cue from Kim Dae-jung.  But we support what he’s doing.  What he’s doing is very forward looking, very courageous and I am greatly encouraged by the fact that he’s going to have a Summit meeting.  Australia supports that with diplomatic recognition, along with other countries and I think it’s a huge breakthrough.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It’s your first visit to the DMZ, what were your impressions of standing in that room – you had North Korean guards looking in at you.  It must have been a strange feeling.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, as I said it’s a bit of history but it’s also unfinished history.  It was, it reminded me of forty years ago what I remember, but I am also reminded that unlike visiting a battlesite of World War I or II or Vietnam War, there is still an issue to be resolved.  It’s still a part of current political current political events and that gives it a character which is different to just visiting a battle site of a former war.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you want to come here personally, did you make the request to come here, or were you invited?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, it was obviously a possibility once I was coming to Seoul and I said yes very enthusiastically.</p>
<p>Thank you</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
