<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7798</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER WELCOME DINNER FOR DELEGATES TO THE MINISTERIAL MEETINF ON ASIA PACIFIC ECONOMIC COOPERATION CANBERRA -5 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007798.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
WELCOME DINNER FR DELEGATES<br />
TO THE MINISTERIAL MEETING ON<br />
ASIA PACIFIC ECONOMIC COOPERATION<br />
CANBERRA 5 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
Distinguished guests,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
Just nine months ago, I had the pleasure of making an<br />
official visit to the Republic of Korea a visit that took<br />
me from near the southernmost point of the Asia Pacific<br />
region to near its northernmost point.<br />
The Australia-Korea relationship is just one of the economic<br />
success stories of the region.<br />
over the nearly three decades from 1960, trade between<br />
Australia and Korea has grown one thousand fold, at a<br />
compound annual rate of 28 percent from $ 3.5 million to<br />
billion and shows no signs of slowing.<br />
Similar stories can be told by any of the economies<br />
throughout the region of their growing trade with each<br />
other, and with the rest of the world.<br />
Larger regional GNPs, stronger regional investment figures,<br />
higher standards, of living all bear witness to the<br />
dynamism, the energy, the exuberant growth, that are the<br />
striking characteristics of the economies of the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
The 9 per cent of world output contributed by the Western<br />
Pacific in 1967 has doubled to 18 per cent; including North<br />
America, our region produces some 44 per cent of global<br />
output. Since 1980, more goods have been traded across the Pacific<br />
than across the Atlantic. 298-5<br />
AV AWoh" </p>
<p>It was with all this in mind all these pointers to the<br />
Pacific Century that I undertook my visit to Seoul, and I<br />
took with me a proposal designed to build on these<br />
achievements; a proposal that I believed was useful, timely<br />
and directly relevant to the mutual interest of all the<br />
economies of the region: a proposal for closer regional<br />
economic cooperation.<br />
At the conclusion of my visit there I * made a speech in which<br />
I articulated my belief that the time had come for us as a<br />
region substantially to increase our efforts towards<br />
building regional cooperation, and seriously to investigate<br />
what areas it might focus on and what forms it might take.<br />
The months that followed that speech made it clear that I<br />
was far from alone in my belief as to the value and<br />
timeliness of a new look at regional cooperation.<br />
In my own talks with President Roh Tae Woo and later on that<br />
same tour with Prime Minister Chatichai of Thailand; in my<br />
subsequent talks and correspondence with other Heads of<br />
Government in the region; and in the rounds of consultations<br />
between Australian officials and their counterparts<br />
throughout the region, it became clear that a substantial<br />
body of-support existed for a ministerial-level meeting at<br />
which the whole region could explore ways of improving our<br />
economic cooperation.<br />
So when I express my heartiest welcome to our guests todayto<br />
Ministers and senior officials from Brunei, Canada,<br />
Indonesia, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, New Zealand, the<br />
Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and the United States of<br />
America I do so, first, with a deep sense of personal<br />
satisfaction. But much more importantly, I do so with a sense that we are<br />
participants in an unprecedented, vital experiment in<br />
international consultation we have made an historic<br />
breakthrough where previous efforts,' for different-reasons,<br />
had failed.<br />
This is the first time the region has met, as a region, to<br />
discuss the economic future of the region.<br />
By coming together at this time we are expressing both the,'-<br />
dynamism of our-. region, and tangibly demonstrating our<br />
commitment to see what more we can do to enhance our<br />
prosperity, to the benefit of those * hundreds of millions of<br />
people whom we represent and whose interests we seek to<br />
advance. We are, if you like, expressing our regional<br />
self-confidence; making a statement that for all our<br />
diversity we share a capacity and a determination to create<br />
a region of economic excellence.<br />
2986 </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Asia Pacific economic cooperation is, of course, * an idea<br />
with a history.<br />
Proposals for some sort of regional economic forum have been<br />
emerging since the 1960s, and were achieved in part but<br />
without the involvement of governments in any leading role<br />
with the constructive formation in 1980 of the Pacific<br />
Economic Cooperation Conference.<br />
With the benefit of hindsight, we can clearly understand why<br />
the early attempts failed to mature fully.<br />
The relatively benign global economy of the 1960b and early<br />
1970s diminished the apparent need for regional cooperation.<br />
The long period of post-war growth in the major economies<br />
had still not come to an end and the GATT framework was,<br />
with global tariff cuts, successfully delivering real<br />
benefits to the region.<br />
At the same time, regional economic linkages, though<br />
strengthening, were still relatively weak. The western<br />
Pacific economy was based heavily on a simple vertical<br />
division of labour fuelled by Japan's demand for<br />
agricultural products and raw materials and its capacity,<br />
along with the US, to supply manufacturing products to the<br />
region.<br />
Overhanging all this, of course, were global political<br />
tensions and damaging regional conflict that pushed issues<br />
of economic management out of the limelight.<br />
So it is not surprising that the idea of strengthened<br />
cooperation remained an obscure vision. It was simply too<br />
early. But today, we are no longer the simple, vertically<br />
integrated, region of the 1960s, but one of spreading<br />
prosperity and of more sophisticated interdependence.<br />
Intra-regional trade has continued to grow; a more complex<br />
division of labour is emerging, with increasing<br />
manufacturing, investment, tourism and technology; economic<br />
management has been sound and flexible; and, not least, the<br />
hard working human resources of the region our people<br />
have continued to acquire new skills, and new purchasing<br />
powers. Some regional economies of course still face daunting tasks<br />
of development Indo China comes immediately to mind. But<br />
no observer could conclude other than that there have been<br />
in this region, overall, some of the most rapid improvements<br />
in living standards in the history of mankind. </p>
<p>That is why there has been a resurgence of the regional<br />
cooperation idea a renewed determination to see what can<br />
be done to sustain and enhance that amazing transformation<br />
and a growing feeling that our level of economic dynamism<br />
and interdependence will make such an effort worthwhile.<br />
It was against this background that I made my proposal<br />
with a conviction that the idea of closer, more effective,<br />
regional cooperation is an idea whose time has come.<br />
Let me add this. Some of the earlier thinking about Asia<br />
Pacific cooperation was confused by a mistaken belief that<br />
we should or could move towards some kind of Pacific trading<br />
bloc. Then, as now, such an idea was an impractical one that<br />
failed to take into account the diversity of the region's<br />
economic development.<br />
More seriously still, such an outcome would be a foolish<br />
one, in that it would run counter to the reg~ ion's absolutely<br />
compelling interest in the maintenance of a strong and open<br />
multilateral trading system. It is on such a system that the<br />
region's economic prosperity has been built, and continues<br />
to rely.<br />
indeed, one of the reasons why the time for regional<br />
economic cooperation has at last arrived is because of the<br />
important new challenges that have emerged to threaten the<br />
multilateral trading system.<br />
We all know of the critical issues at stake in the current<br />
Uruguay Round of trade talks.<br />
One of the primary benefits that I originally envisaged<br />
springing from more effective cooperation was the<br />
opportunity to protect that system and to enhance the<br />
practices of fair trade.<br />
So let it be clearly understood that we do not meet here<br />
today with any hidden agenda to create some form of Pacific<br />
trading bloc.<br />
Our commitment is to open, multilateral trade. our united<br />
resolve is that thee world eco ' nomy should not fragment into<br />
defensive trading blocs. Our very prosperity depends on it.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I referred earlier to the view that we are entering or have<br />
already entered, the so-called Pacific Century. It's a fine<br />
notion but I have always thought it wrong to assume we<br />
could sit down complacently and expect the fruits of Pacific<br />
prosperity to fall into our laps.<br />
2% 988 </p>
<p>The Asia Pacific region can sustain its economic dynamism<br />
during the coming decades. But whether it will depends on<br />
whether we anticipate the opportunities and the problems of<br />
what will, without doubt, be a challenging, even a<br />
difficult, global and regional environment.<br />
Let me briefly and broadly enumerate these forthcoming<br />
challenges. First, there is the challenge of ensuring that the<br />
growing economic significance of the Asia Pacific region<br />
will be adequately reflected i. n international economic<br />
forums including, as I have said, in efforts to<br />
protect the multilateral trading system.<br />
Second, there is the challenge of reducing impediments<br />
to trade within the region and of identifying hitherto<br />
untapped opportunites.<br />
this highlights the need for flexibility and<br />
structural adjustment. As industrialisation<br />
continues to spread, the need for adjustment will<br />
be felt not only in the older industrial centres,<br />
but increasingly in the dynamic economies of our<br />
own region. Yet barriers and inflexibilities<br />
persist within our region and we all know the<br />
strength of sectional interests that resist change<br />
for essentially short-sighted reasons.<br />
Third, there is the challenge of accelerating<br />
technological change. The declining importance of<br />
unskilled labour; further positive emphasis on education<br />
and training; the rise of automation; the demands for<br />
custom-made goods and services; the growth of leisure<br />
and tourism; the undeniable necessity to achieve growth<br />
that is environmentally sustainable all these forces<br />
will change the pattern of comparative advantage in the<br />
region. Fourth, ther e is the challenge of ensuring continued<br />
rapid growth is facilitated, and not obstructed, by<br />
available infrastructure.<br />
Fifth, there is the challenge of change in the<br />
international economic environment in which we will<br />
operate. substantial current account imbalances between<br />
major economies, the indebtedness of developing<br />
countries, and the particular problems of primary<br />
commodity exporters are likely to remain with us<br />
for some time.<br />
Sixth, and related to all the foregoing, there is the<br />
further challenge over the next decade of integrating<br />
the socialist countries into the international economic<br />
order. 2981) </p>
<p>we are witnessing massive and welcome changes<br />
within the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. Within<br />
our own region, it is in the interests of us all to<br />
maintain a trading environment in which the<br />
People's Republic of China can participate<br />
increasingly productively to our mutual benefit.<br />
In posing these challenges, I don't seek to determine a<br />
precise work program for regional cooperation. That will, I<br />
hope, emerge from your discussions over the next couple of<br />
days. But I do want to point to the breadth of potential issues<br />
that need to be discussed and the substantial and relevant<br />
benefits that can flow from such discussion.<br />
Because in confronting all these challenges in the eventful<br />
decades ahead, we would do well to strengthen our individual<br />
and collective capacity for analysis and policy formulation;<br />
to share essential information; to compare experiences; to<br />
weigh short-term costs and long-term benefits; to reinforce<br />
each other's political will where necessary all this so as<br />
to achieve sensible economic policy decisions that reflect<br />
and advance our common interests.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Let me state once more, here, what Australia has made clear<br />
from the start: this meeting has on its agenda only issues<br />
of economic cooperation not politics.<br />
In particular, we don't seek with this meeting to impinge on<br />
the enormous contribution that has been made over the years<br />
to regional political cooperation and consultation by ASEAN.<br />
But having made that quite clear, I want to draw attention<br />
to a broader reality the fundamental relationship between<br />
sound economic and political management.<br />
In a very real fashion, economic cooperation and good sense<br />
are the handmaidens of peace and security.<br />
whatever progress we can achieve here in the field of<br />
economic cooperation can only serve to support the work, and<br />
help to achieve-the goals, in the political field, of groups<br />
such as ASEAN.<br />
By the same token, economic irrationality and the practices<br />
and attitudes of economic autarky inevitably put peace and<br />
security at risk. We need look no further than the 1920s and<br />
the 1930s to be taught that lesson of history.<br />
So it is, I believe, with a sombre responsibility that we<br />
embark today on a process of profound importance to our<br />
region and to the world.<br />
2990~ f </p>
<p>Let me briefly refer to two more specific questions that<br />
will need to be resolved as we begin to build regional<br />
consultation. One issue for further reflection is whether, when and how to<br />
broaden participation so that-the process can draw in all<br />
those economies within, or with close links with, the<br />
region. In the short term we will need to think through the issues<br />
related to the potential participation of the People's<br />
Republic of China, and the economies of Hong Kong and<br />
Taiwan. In the longer term, we will also need to remain open in<br />
principle to helping others forge stronger economic linkages<br />
with the dynamic economies represented at this meeting.<br />
A second issue is to do with our recognition that improved<br />
economic cooperation in our region is a long-term investment<br />
in our shared future prosperity.<br />
We won't be able, at this initial exploratory meeting at<br />
Canberra, to discuss and solve all the challenges that this<br />
long-term investment'will require.<br />
we will need to come together again, and I am pleased that<br />
ASEAN the outstandingly successful institution of regional<br />
cooperation and the Republic of Korea one of the most<br />
dynamic economies in the region have offered to host a<br />
second and third meeting of this group.<br />
But if these consultations are to be truly effective, we<br />
will need to back them up with effective sharing of<br />
information, and sharp strategic thinking to identify and<br />
study relevant policy questions.<br />
Now that we've embarked on this endeavour, I don't want to<br />
see the spirit that has brought us together simply wither<br />
away for lack of a mead~ s of keeping the momentum going.<br />
By the same token, none of us, least of all me, wants to see<br />
this meeting result in the creation of a vast, expensive or<br />
cumbersome bureaucracy, or the duplication of existing<br />
organisations that are already performing an effective role.<br />
Neither outcome could be seen as a productive step towards<br />
the goal we have come together to explore.<br />
My own preference would be to harness as soon as practicable<br />
a small, high-calibre group of officials, seconded from our<br />
governments, that could prepare the groundwork for<br />
forthcoming meetings and follow up on issues that have been<br />
identified at previous meetings, drawing also on available<br />
analytical resources in the region. 29.1 </p>
<p>I recognise of course that others may have different<br />
proposals and I certainly don't make my suggestion in any<br />
way to impose it as the only suitable outcome.<br />
But I do believe that, in the short term, some effective<br />
mechanism is needed to carry forward our efforts and<br />
intentions for the future; and I look forward to hearing the<br />
views of the meeting on this.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Australia is proud to host this historic meeting, which I do<br />
not doubt will carry the message of the cooperative<br />
commitment of our countries throughout the region and indeed<br />
the world.<br />
The meeting will also carry a message a vital message to<br />
my fellow Australians a message I have repeatedly<br />
emphasised for nearly seven years as Prime Minister. The<br />
message is that the transformation underway in the Asia<br />
Pacific region is of critical importance to the way we go<br />
about life in this country and to the expecta'tions<br />
Australians can entertain for the future.<br />
With our historical roots in Europe, and our reputation<br />
let me concede it was sometimes in decades past a<br />
well-earned reputation for economic and cultural<br />
insularity, Australia has not been seen by some in the<br />
region as an integral part of the region. Indeed sometimes<br />
Australians haven't seen themselves in that light either.<br />
But those days are gone gone forever. Increasingly our<br />
domestic attitudes and certainly, at the level of my<br />
Government, our domestic and foreign policy making<br />
recognise the truth that our future is thoroughly interwoven<br />
with that of the Asia Pacific region.<br />
This is not the place to discuss the sweeping economic<br />
reforms underway in this country and I do not propose to<br />
do so. But I say this: none of us is immune from the need<br />
for economic flexibility and structural adjustment, and<br />
Australia's own commitment to reform our determination to<br />
achieve greater enmeshment with our region shows we<br />
recognise that as a fundamental fact of life.<br />
Certainly, with 8 of our top 10 export markets last year<br />
being in the Asia Pacific, we are as good an example of<br />
regional interdependence as any economy in this region.<br />
So this is certainly one of the most important international<br />
meetings Australia has ever hosted important in the range<br />
and seniority of our guests and important, indeed vital, in<br />
the issues to be discussed over the next two days.<br />
If Asia Pacific economic cooperation is to bear fruit, we<br />
will need to be flexible, imaginative, and outwatd-looking. </p>
<p>9.<br />
if we succeed in this respect, I believe we will have<br />
succeeded in making an historic contribution to sustaining<br />
our remarkable record of Asia Pacific growth well into the<br />
next century.<br />
I thank you for your attendance and I wish you well in your<br />
work, which I believe can be of enduring benefit to each of<br />
our economies and for all the peoples of our region. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
