<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15</transcript-id>
    <title>DIGEST OF DECISIONS AND ANNOUNCEMENTS AND IMPORTANT SPEECHES BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY - NO.137 </title>
    <prime-minister>Chifley, Ben</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19450713 - 19491219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1948</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000015_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENWV<br />
DIGEST OF DECISIONS<br />
AND ANNOUNCEMENTS<br />
IMPORTANT SPEECHES<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
( THE RIGHT HON. J. B. CHIFLEY).<br />
No. 137.<br />
PERIOD IST JULY, 1948, TO 21s'r AUGUST. 194S.<br />
L P. Jansrmos. Ckmennnwealh Gomenmml Pi w.<br />
( Printed in Auitra[ 6.)<br />
4738.<br />
I </p>
<p>SERVICE PAY RATES.<br />
PERMANENT FORCES--RETIREMENT SCHEME.<br />
On 1st July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) announced that<br />
the Defence Forces Retirement Benefits Board would comprise-<br />
Messrs. H. C. Newman ( Treasury), F. X. Hassett ( Naval Board). W. M.<br />
Anderson ( Military Board). J. E. Hewitt ( Air Board).<br />
( For earlier references, please see Nos. 134, page 6; 135, page<br />
REPATRIATION-TEACHING.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to authorize the Repatriation Commission<br />
to extend its functions for the establishment of courses of training cr<br />
other measures to serve the necessities of treatment. The commission<br />
will be authorized to-<br />
Make available facilities for post-graduate and under-graduate teaching and<br />
. studies in medicine in all the aspects which the teaching autlhorities ( univer-<br />
-ities and the like) consider are covered by the types of patient under treatment<br />
a nid the facilities available at the commission's medical institutions.<br />
1 EEstablish courses of training in the nursing of tulerculous. diseases for the<br />
certificate in Victoria or any other State which nmay later inaugurate such an<br />
. additional nursing qualification.<br />
Establish courses of training in the nursing of psycliatric dicleses.<br />
Afford training and instruction in physiotherapy, occupational therapy,<br />
medical and psychiatric social studies, clinical psychology. radiological and<br />
pathological technique. THE GOVERNMENT.<br />
ACTING MINISTERS.<br />
On 3rd July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Attorney-General ( Dr. Evatt) will be Acting Prime Minister<br />
and the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman) will be<br />
. cting Treasurer during my absence overseas."<br />
On 21st July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt) is leaving Australia<br />
on the first stage of his journey overseas on 22nd July, 1948. I will act<br />
as Minister for External Affairs and the Minister for Health and<br />
Social Services ( Senator McKenna) will act as Attorney-General as<br />
from 23rd July and for the period of Dr. Evatt's absence abroad."<br />
PEACE.<br />
GERMANY-BERLIN POSITION.<br />
On 6th July, 1948, the Minister for External Affairs ( Dr. Evatt)<br />
said that following the cutting off by the Soviet authorities of all surface<br />
methods of-supplying Allied occupation forces and the German population<br />
in the three western sectors of Berlin, the British, United States<br />
and French Governments, in their determined employment of emergency<br />
supply measures, were protecting their undoubted juridical rights.<br />
4738.-2. </p>
<p>The presence of occupation forces in Berlin was clearly authorize'd<br />
by the agreement of 1944 nominating Berlin as the centre of Allied<br />
control of Germany and setting up machinery for Allied government<br />
of the city. The agreement had been subsequently amended to provide<br />
for the participation of France and had been made public in joint<br />
four-power statements issued with the declaration on the surrender of<br />
Germany, on 5th June, 1945. The agreement became operative before<br />
the Potsdam Agreement, so that the Soviet contention that the western<br />
powers have brought four-power control to an end by violating thr.<br />
Potsdam Agreement was clearly inadmissible. In the interests of world<br />
peace, it was hoped that all outstanding matters affecting Berlin would<br />
soon be discussed between the western powers and the Soviet Union,<br />
but no permanent easing of tension could result unless the Soviet Union<br />
recognized clearly and unequivocally the undoubted occupation rights of<br />
the western Allies. These had been hardly won in the common struggle<br />
against Hitler and could not be set aside or nullified by unilateral acts.<br />
On llth July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-<br />
It is unthinkable that the western Allies should do other than hold<br />
on in Berlin. There is no question that Australia supports the westerii<br />
Allies." On 18th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
I went to Berlin to gather some real background information of the<br />
position. The British Foreign Secretary ( Mr. Bevin) thought it<br />
highly desirable for me to get the atmosphere of the position and to<br />
talk to German trade union and political leaders.<br />
" I have nothing more to say on the Berlin position than what I<br />
said when I was there-that for the western powers to take any other<br />
stand was unthinkable."<br />
GERMANY-BERLIN POSITION, AIR LIFT.<br />
On 2nd August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to offer to the British Government the<br />
use of ten Douglas Dakota aircraft to assist in the air lift to Berlin, if<br />
required. If the offer is accepted, the ' planes will be flown by Royal Australian<br />
Air Force crews to Britain, where the uses to which the aircraft<br />
are put will be determined by the British authorities."<br />
ITALY-TREATY, RATIFICATION.<br />
On 12th July, 1948, Dr. Evatt announced that the Australian instrunment<br />
of ratification of the peace treaty with Italy had been deposited<br />
on 9th July, 1948, and the state of war between Australia and Italy had<br />
ended as from that day. At Berlin. </p>
<p>ROUMANIA, BULGARIA, HUNGARY, FINLAND-TREATIES,<br />
RATIFICATION.<br />
On 13th July, 1948, Dr. Evatt said that the Australian instruments<br />
of ratification of the peace treaties with Roumania, Bulgaria, Hungary<br />
and Finland had been deposited on 10th July, 1948, and the state of war<br />
between Australia and those countries had ended as from that day.<br />
JAPAN-MINISTER'S STATEMENT, JULY, 1948.<br />
On 22nd July, 1948, Dr. Evatt said-<br />
It is becoming evident that peace and stability in the Pacific and<br />
in Asia will be attainable only so far as there is peace and stability in<br />
Europe. The problem is not regional, it is global. The situation in<br />
Berlin and Europe generally, where there is an acute dispute between<br />
Russia on the one hand and the western democracies on the other, must<br />
have a direct effect in delaying any peace settlement with Japan.<br />
Australia's concern in the European situation is direct and vital.<br />
Certainly no peace will endure unless it is based on justice and<br />
reached by free agreement in accordance with the principles of the<br />
United Nations Charter. The next meeting of the United Nations may<br />
well become a turning point in world history. I am hopeful that the<br />
Assembly will bring public opinion to bear on both political and<br />
economic aspects of international disputes and so contribute to the<br />
prevention of a third world war."<br />
EXTERNAL TERRITORIES.<br />
PAPUA-NEW GUINEA-COPRA.<br />
On 7th July, 1948, the Minister for External Territories ( Mr.<br />
Ward) announced that the Australian New Guinea Production Control<br />
Board would relinquish control of marketing the Territory of Papua-<br />
New Guinea production of copra. The present rate of production of<br />
copra, over 40,000 tons a year, was about two-thirds of the potential<br />
output of the remaining coconut plantations and groves of the territory<br />
and negotiations were in course with traders in the territory to secure<br />
an orderly changeover of marketing activities under a system of export<br />
licences. The board, which was established during the war to secure<br />
from the territories the maximum possible produciton of copra and<br />
other tropical produce, would then wind up its affairs.<br />
BRITISH COMMONWEALTH OF NATIONS.<br />
CO-OPERATION-PROPOSED SECRETARIAT.<br />
On 8th July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-<br />
" Suggestions have been made for the establishment of a British<br />
Commonwealth of Nations Secretariat hut there is no evidence at present<br />
of anything of a concrete character."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 98, page 46; No. 114, page 3.)<br />
At London. </p>
<p>6<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S BROADCAST.<br />
On 12th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley broadcast over the British Broadcasting<br />
Corporation and Australian Broadcasting Commission networks.<br />
Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Good evening. I speak to-night to the people of Great Britain, to<br />
my own people in Australia and to listeners in the Pacific and North<br />
American areas.<br />
We live in difficult times, the world is suffering an uneasy peace.<br />
I have just returned from Berlin where I went so that I might get a<br />
first-hand picture of a very difficult position. Economic and political<br />
problems of a character never before encountered in our history have<br />
to be faced daily. There is little respite from them. But we are a<br />
sturdy race. Our Comnionwealth is composed of very determined<br />
people. If I needed any reminder of that fact, I have only to look at<br />
what the people of Britain have suffered and are suffering and what<br />
they are doing to lift themselves up towards a happier way of life.<br />
During the past week I have had the opportunity of talking with<br />
the British Prime Minister ( Mr. Attlee) and a number of his Ministers.<br />
It is natural that the British people are wondering what will be the<br />
outcome of the talks, while my own people at home will be interested to<br />
know what tasks lie ahead of them. My mission here at London,<br />
primarily, was economic. But I have also had more than one talk<br />
with the Foreign Minister ( Mr. Bevin) from whom I have obtained a<br />
very full picture of the world scene. I aim having talks with the<br />
Minister of Defence and with the Service Ministers.<br />
Perhaps I can best sum up my objective in coming to London<br />
in a sentence: I want to obtain, and to give, a clear understanding of<br />
the economic difficulties that confront the people of Britain and Au.-<br />
tralia. We want to determine, as well as circumstances will permit,<br />
our joint policies for the future.<br />
" I say to my own people that the path is not easy, that the going<br />
is hard and will continue to be hard. Sir Stafford Cripps said last<br />
week that Britain was running into debt on her overseas trade to the<br />
tune of more than a million pounds for every working day. Australians<br />
know that our future is linked with Britain, not only hy ties of rnee<br />
and kinship, but because of hard, practical reasons.<br />
Tl'hre is a bond of gratitude between Britain and Australia<br />
because of the gallant part played by Britain in the war and in the<br />
post-war struggle to re-establish herself, and, at the same time, to assist<br />
others. The next three years may very well be the most crucial in the<br />
history of the British peoples. The key to the situation lies in production<br />
and I say to every Australian that hard work is not only a national<br />
duty but a stern responsibility if we are all to survive.<br />
" I am not being alarmist. I have the advantage of knowing not<br />
some of the facts, but all the facts. I have talked with the best brains<br />
in Britain; men who devote day and night to the task.<br />
I </p>
<p>The Australian people have had imposed on them severe restrictions<br />
in order that the use of dollars should be reduced. The Australian<br />
Government realizes that, without substantial imports of capital<br />
equipment from America, the progress of the country's development<br />
will be seriously delayed. Nevertheless, the Australian Government<br />
is prepared to take appropriate action in the future; however strong<br />
it may be. I also add, in view of incorrect reports, that I did not<br />
coime to Britain to demand more dollars. My mission has been aimed<br />
at obtaining the fullest information so that economic policy, particularly<br />
as it affects dollars, can be laid down with reasonable certainty<br />
and that the efforts of the United Kingdom and Australia can be<br />
properly co-ordinated.<br />
To the British people, I say that I believe that much can be done<br />
in Australia to expand production of beef, dairy products and wheat.<br />
We lhav good seasonal prospects in Australia and it is hoped, for<br />
example, that lamb production this year will be 10,000,000 above an<br />
average year.<br />
" I know that numbers of people in England, Scotland, Ireland<br />
: n d Wales are interested in going to Australia. The fullest understanding<br />
exists between the British and Australian Governments on<br />
this matter and to those who feel that delays are endless, I point out<br />
that, first, the ships have to be available, and, secondly, we have to<br />
pursue vigorously, which we are doing, a housing construction proegrnmin'<br />
Time is the arresting factor.<br />
It has been my privilege and pleasure auring my stay to meet Their<br />
Ma. jesties and the Princess Margaret and I have assured them, on<br />
behlilf of the people of Australia, of the warmest welcome when they<br />
visit us next year.<br />
Let : ijc. in saying good-night to you, tell you that the Australian<br />
people are constantly thinking of you. Our servicemen fought alongside<br />
you in two wars. We are standing by you now in fighting for<br />
economic stability. That may be, as I have said, a long fight, and<br />
each obstacle must be faced with the same courage that the people of<br />
Britain have shown in the last ten years. It will he our privilege, and,<br />
ind', d, oui' duty. to help in every way we can."<br />
On 25th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley broadcast over some commercial<br />
stations-Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Good evening. As you know, I have just returned from a mission<br />
to London. My objective was primarily to discuss economic problems<br />
of mutual interest to the British and Australian Governments, but I<br />
also dealt with a number of other matters. All told, I attended two<br />
meetings of the British Cabinet and also talked with eleven members<br />
of the British Government-and with some of the Ministers I talked<br />
more than once.<br />
In addition, I visited Berlin, where I spent some hours with<br />
British, American, French and Australian authorities so that I might<br />
obtain first-hand information and be able to gauge the atmosphere<br />
4738.-3. </p>
<p>of the situation in the German capital. While there, I also talked<br />
with German trade union leaders and with members of the German<br />
civil administration in Berlin. Berlin presents a sad picture of the<br />
devastation of war. I have previously visited some of the worst war<br />
devastated cities, such as Hiroshima, Yokahama, Tokio, Manila and<br />
Rangoon. But, excepting Hiroshima, which was completely destroyed<br />
by the atomic bomb, I have not seen anything like the destruction in<br />
Berlin. Masses of bricks and rubble, gutted buildings, now mark this<br />
once beautiful city. It is a grim warning of the tragic consequences<br />
of war. On my way to London, and also on my way back, I talked with<br />
the British Commissioner-General at Malaya ( Mr. Malcoln<br />
Macdonald) and with the British Governor of Singapore ( Sir Franklin<br />
Gimson). I obtained from Mr. Macdonald a full background picture<br />
of the position in Singapore and Malaya.<br />
As the result of my talks at London, I can say that there is<br />
the fullest understanding between the British and .\ ustralian Governments<br />
on the economic matters that affect our common and national<br />
interests. Of course, we are in constant touch with each other by<br />
cable and often by radio-telephone. I told the British pcople, on<br />
your behalf and on behalf of all Australians, that it would be our<br />
privilege, indeed our duty, to help them in every way possible. I was<br />
glad to sec that, despite great economic difficulties, London and itpeople<br />
looked brighter than when I visited there in 1946. The gaping<br />
holes made by the doodle bugs" and V2' s have been patched up.<br />
The people are better dressed. There are more things in the shop<br />
windows. British production is steadily increasing and their courage<br />
is an example to the world.<br />
While at London, I also said, and I give you a further reminder<br />
now, that the road ahead for the British peoples everywhere and,<br />
indeed, for nearly all the non-dollar countries, is going to be long<br />
and hard. I don't want anybody to think, because I have said that,<br />
that the British Commonwealth is not going to come tlrou: gh. It is<br />
going to be a tough fight, but I have not any doubts that we shall<br />
pull through. I feel confident that with the growing strength of the<br />
Dominions. the British Commonwealth can be made stronger than<br />
ever. One of the keys to the problem is increased production. The<br />
Macquarie electorate contains centres of both primary and secondary<br />
production. On the industrial side, there are places such as Lithgow,<br />
Portland and St. Mary's. Primary production of a varied nature is<br />
to be found in almost every part of Macquarie. Australia is pledged<br />
to assist Britain in every way possible and increased production is<br />
necessary to fulfil that pledge. In addition, our own welfare, the<br />
expansion and development of our country, are both wrapped up in<br />
our own capacity to do better. </p>
<p>" Work-hard work-overtime, where necessary, must be undertaken<br />
as part of our national duty. We want to develop and build<br />
a greater Australia for our children. Further, our strategic position<br />
is not what it was. This is a shrinking world and Australia cannot<br />
feel immune just because, geographically, she is situated down under<br />
in the Southern Hemisphere. We have to build and maintain a strong<br />
Australia and, I repeat, hard work is the only way to achieve that.<br />
We owe that not only to our own people but to our Allies and, particularly,<br />
the United Kingdom. Let me illustrate to you how the<br />
world has shrunk. In fourteen and a half days, I covered just on<br />
28,000 miles by air. In other words, I travelled about 2,000 miles<br />
every day and did eight days work as well. I stopped at or passed<br />
over about a dozen different countries.<br />
" There is no such thing to-day as the Far East. In fact, Asia<br />
and Europe have been brought almost as close to us as New Zealand.<br />
An island that is 450 miles away from Darwin and was just a spot<br />
on the map could very easily become of intense interest to Australia.<br />
I want Australians to realize that they must think and act as Australians.<br />
They must think and act in terms of the nation. Economic<br />
wevlfare, security and a contented future are all wrapped up in what<br />
we do as individuals and as a community.<br />
In your homes to-night, you are safe and secure. Your families<br />
rue around you. You are assured of full employment. You have<br />
boundless opportunities ahead of you. By contrast, I have seen places<br />
and talked with people in the grip of misery and hardship, indeed,<br />
with no future at all. Uneasy countries, worried peoples are to be<br />
found everywhere. The devastating hand of war has caused<br />
unbelievable material damage and worked shocking havoc in people's<br />
minds. The heritage that has come to us, the great chance for the<br />
future must not be frittered away. I ask the people of Macquarie, as<br />
I ask all Australians, to stand together for the national good and for<br />
their own good." TARIFF.<br />
WESTERN CUSTOMS UNION.<br />
On 8th July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-<br />
The matter of the Western Customs Union would have to be a<br />
subject for discussion between Britain and the Dominions if it cut<br />
across Imperial preference in any way.<br />
Australia has assumed that no finality will be reached on the<br />
Western Customs Union without consultation with the Dominions.<br />
There has been no intimation yet by the British Government that it<br />
will be specially discussed with the Dominion Governments."<br />
At London. </p>
<p>MIGRATION.<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY-BRITISH MIGRANTS.<br />
On Sth July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-<br />
have had discussions with the Minister for British Commonwealth<br />
Relations ( Mr. Noel-Baker) and further discussions will be<br />
held later. We have dealt with migration generally rather than any<br />
specific plans-matters such as ships and related problems. Many<br />
physical difficulties are in the way of mass migration and a lot of<br />
study and thought will be necessary and I do not think that mass<br />
migration is physically possible in the near future. I am satisfied<br />
that the British Government has been very co-operative in regard<br />
to shipping. There have been discussions regarding the transfer of some<br />
British industries to Australia but the tendency has been for British<br />
firms to establish branches in Australia or to expand existing branches-<br />
That has been going on fairly rapidly because of the sound Australian<br />
economy; the market in Australia; and the fact that Australia is a<br />
foctil point of development of eastern trade."<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 111, page 44; No. 122, page 16;<br />
No. 123, page<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY-PRIME MINISTER'S STATEMENT.<br />
On 1Sth July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said:-<br />
I had long discussions at London with the Minister for British<br />
Commonwealth Relations ( Mr. Noel-Baker) and the Minister for<br />
Transport ( Mr. Barnes). Despite the shipping shortage, I hope that<br />
the rate of migration will be stepped up very considerably for British<br />
migrants, displaced persons in Europe and Italians. At Berlin, I<br />
discussed with the United States authorities the possibility of securing<br />
additional displaced persons for Australia."<br />
GOVERNMENT POLICY-MINERS.<br />
On 19th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said:-<br />
The British Government is endeavouring to use Polish niners.<br />
They are used in Wales. Difficulties are being encountered in<br />
Yorkshire. At the moment, trained Polish miners are not available<br />
for Australia but some Italian miners might be available. The matter<br />
would have to be discussed with the Australian Coal and Shale<br />
Employees Federation. One of the difficulties is knowledge of the<br />
English language and it would be necessary to teach them the rules<br />
and regulations of working." At London. </p>
<p>BRITAIN.<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-DOLLAR IMPORTS, PRIME<br />
MINISTER'S STATEMENT.<br />
On 8th July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said*-<br />
" My mission to London is mainly on matters of economic interesis<br />
common to both British and Australian Governments. I hope that, as a<br />
result of the mission, the common bond between us will be strengthened<br />
in the best interests of . both Governments. Cables cannot fully cover<br />
the ground that can be covered by talks.<br />
Australia forms part of the dollar pool. It has been almost always<br />
a drawer on the dollar pool. We have been striving to cut d! own<br />
expenditure in many fields. The judgment as to what constitutes<br />
essentiality in dollar expenditure causes controversy but Australia feels<br />
that she must not draw any more dollars than are essential.<br />
" In 1948-49, Australia anticipates making very substantiail ri. luetions<br />
in dollar expenditure and in the amount to be purchased from the<br />
British Treasury. The precise programme is difficult until revenue<br />
from Australian exports are knowin-an example being the revenue<br />
from Australian wool sold in the United States. Time often alters<br />
early figures. Further, rising prices often alter quantities."<br />
On 18th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley -aid-<br />
I make it clear that I did not go to London to beg for dollars. The<br />
main objective of the visit was to find out how best we can co-ordinate<br />
the policies of the two governments having regard to the shortage of<br />
dollars; how Australia can share in the availability of goods from<br />
Britain, previously obtained from the United States and other hard<br />
currency areas; and to discuss a long-range policy regarding dollar..<br />
" The European recovery programme provides only for Britain's<br />
dollar deficit and not for the Dominions' dollar deficits. It is doubtful<br />
if the European recovery programme makes full provision for the dollar<br />
deficits of Britain. One of Britain's problems is the increasing price<br />
of dollar imports. Although production is increasing-and increasing<br />
splendidly in some industries-some of the increased dollar earnings are<br />
offset by rising prices in America. As British leaders have said,<br />
increased production is one of the keys of the problem. It is also<br />
necessary in Australia if Australia's economic welfare is to assist in<br />
giving increased help to Britain-particularly in foodstuffs. I have<br />
not given thought to means of increasing production but the working<br />
of overtime is essential.<br />
" It is no use disguising the fact that a long hard road is ahead<br />
because of the difficulty in getting dollar goods. It would be very foolish<br />
to think that either Britain or Australia can solve that as a . hortterm<br />
problem. At T. ondn. </p>
<p>The only solution to the present disequilibrium in dollars will<br />
be for the United States and other dollar countries to buy something<br />
equivalent in value to what they sell. That course seems unlikely so<br />
the sterling area countries must do the best they can with the dollars<br />
available. We have to face the inevitable by doing the best we can in<br />
the years ahead on the dollars available and in the meantime to<br />
produce our utmost.<br />
The Australian Government must be prepared to examine all<br />
avenues of trade to see how dollars can be saved. There is a complete<br />
understanding with the British Government as to the precise position<br />
and how best Australia can render assistance to Britain. The Australian<br />
Government has already planned reductions in dollar expeiditure."<br />
On 19th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" The Australian Government is trying to divert imports into tho<br />
sterling area and the latest figures are-<br />
In May, 1947, 27 per cent. were from Britain, and in May, 1947, this had<br />
increased to 53 per cent. Imports from the total sterling area at the same<br />
dates were 44 per cent. and 66 per cent. respectively. Imports from the dollar<br />
area on the samine dates were 39 per cent. and 13 per cent. Total imports for<br />
the same dates were œ 23,000,000 ( Australian) and œ 31.000,000 ( Australian)<br />
respectively. " It is hoped to get dollar imports down still lower but there i:<br />
always the problem of ever-rising prices in the United States."<br />
FINANCIAL POLICY-STERLING, APPRECIATION.<br />
On 19th August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" I was aware that consideration was being given by the New<br />
Zealand Government to this matter* and the Commonwealth Government<br />
had also been giving consideration to it. But I have no official<br />
intimation from the New Zealand Government of the contemplated<br />
action. It is not the intention, in the present circumstances, as<br />
indicated by me in the House of Representatives on 26th February,<br />
1948, to appreciate the Australian<br />
( For earlier reference, please see No. 133, page 11.)<br />
PRIMARY INDUSTRIES.<br />
EXPORTS TO BRITAIN-PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
STATEMENT, JULY, 1948.<br />
On Sth July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) saidf-<br />
" Australian exports to Britain depend largely on seasonal conditions.<br />
. Australia anticipates being able to increase exports this<br />
seaso n. ( For earlier reference, please see No. 114, page 24.)<br />
To ni. priciato lie New Z.: il: iinl œ 1 I o piirlly wvitli ' terliig.<br />
t At Londmi. </p>
<p>AGRICULTUI{ AL MACHINERY-TRACTORS. CONTROL<br />
REVOKED.<br />
On 29th July, 1948, the Minister for Agriculture ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
announced that control over the distribution of tractors to agricultural<br />
nu. rs would cease on 31st July, 1948.<br />
EXPORTS-1947-48 FIGURES.<br />
On l1th August, 1948, Mr. Pollard said that exports in 1947-4S<br />
showed heavy increases in many exported commodities over 1946-47,<br />
and in some cases had regained the volume of exports in 1938-39.<br />
Combined exports of dairy products ( butter, cheese and processed milk)<br />
were higher than pre-war. Other products which were exported in<br />
greater quantities were hares and rabbits, bacon and hams, preserved<br />
meat in tins, fruit in liquid, jams and jellies. Eggs and egg products,<br />
poultry, oats and barley were much higher than pre-war. Those in<br />
which there was a minor downward trend were sausage casings, citrus,<br />
vleat and flour. Those in which there was a substantial decline over<br />
1938-39 were beef, lamb, mutton, apples and sugar. Comparative<br />
figures were-Ye; irs.<br />
Unit of<br />
Quantity. 1938-39. 1946-47. 1947-48.<br />
Butter ' 000 lb. 229,543 133,642 185,122<br />
Cheese 35,924 53,662 51,163<br />
Meats-Bacon and hams 1,739 6,649 5,531<br />
Preserved by cold process-<br />
Beef 271,964 180,339 230,504<br />
Lamb 158,333 112,095 103,280<br />
Mutton 28,156 52,208 19,396<br />
Pork 30,716 18,705 3,720<br />
Rabbits and hares ' 000 pairs 3,995 5,385 12,671<br />
Preserved in tins ' 000 lb. 14,896 119,713 94,320<br />
Sausage casings cwt. 23,099 17,714 17,595<br />
Milk and cream ' 000 lb. 19,107 105,959 97,785<br />
Fruits, dried-<br />
Currants .53,219 12,558 22,551<br />
Raisins 110,992 78,957 70,308<br />
Fruits, fresh-<br />
Apples Cental 2,111,139 387,458 1,408,507<br />
Citrus 274,229 167,910 273,849<br />
Fruits, preserved in liquid ' 000 lb. 81,478 71,689 84,973<br />
Wheat ' 000 bus. 63,129 12,176 60,454<br />
Flour ( wheaten) ' 000 cntl. 14,501 15,302 15,942<br />
Jams and fruit jellies ' 000 lb. 13,872 65,434 58,877<br />
Sugar ( cane) ton 443,021 117,379 100,460<br />
PETROL SUPPLIES.<br />
RATIONING-CONTINUANCE.<br />
On Sth July, 1948, the Minister for Shipping and Fuel ( Senator<br />
.' thley) said that a meeting of the Cabinet Sub-committee on Fuel had<br />
beun held that day to consider the report of the Director of Rationing </p>
<p>( Mr. Cumming) regarding the operation and administrative methods<br />
of petrol rationing in Australia. The sub-committee decided to recomment<br />
that either by legislation or by continuance of existing Defence<br />
( Transitional) Act Regulations, power be taken to continue petrol<br />
rationing until 31st December, 1949. The sub-committee had decided<br />
that there would be no immediate reduction in petrol rations, but that<br />
all State Liquid Fuel Boards would, in conjunction with the existin. g<br />
review now being undertaken of licences in the business/ pleasure group<br />
( classes 3 to review a number of important proposals in regard to<br />
the administration of the petrol rationing plan. Further severe restrictions<br />
in petrol consumption could be avoided only by petrol nser.<br />
co-operating to the utmost in effecting all practical economies.<br />
LITERARY CENSORSHIP BOARD.<br />
MEMBERS APPOINTED.<br />
On Sth July, 1943, the Minister for Trade and Customs ( Senator<br />
Courtice) announced that the Literary Censorship Board would<br />
comprise-Professor L. H. Allen, chairman, Professor J. F. M. Haydon and Mr. K.<br />
Binns, with Sir Robert Garran as Appeal Censor.<br />
AUSTRALIAN MILITARY FORCES.<br />
SALVAGE SERVICE-CESSATION.<br />
On 9th July, 1948, the Minister for the Army ( Mr. Chambers) said<br />
that the Australian Army Salvage Service had ceased to exist as from<br />
1st July, 1948. Commands and military districts would continue in the<br />
peace-time army to exercise the functions performed previously by the<br />
service. Although the service sold more than œ 5,000,000 worth of<br />
recovered materials, that represented only a fraction of the vast quantity<br />
which it recovered. AUSTRALIAN BROADCASTING ACT.<br />
TELEVISION.<br />
On 12th July, 1948, the Postmaster-General ( Senator Cameron)<br />
-aid that tenders would be called for two television transmitters for<br />
installation on an experimental basis at Sydney and Melbourne and,<br />
alternatively, for six transmitters for trial purposes in each State<br />
capital city, in addition to sets for receiving the experimental programmes.<br />
When tenders were received they would he considered Iy<br />
the Cabinet sub-commi'ttee on Broadcasting which would report io<br />
Cabinet. ( For earlier references, please see No. 136, page 37.) </p>
<p>WHEAT STABILIZATION SCHEME.<br />
CONFERENCE WITH STATES-DECISION.<br />
On 12th July, 1948, tie Minister for Commerce and Agriculture<br />
( Mr. Pollard) said that a conference that day with the State Ministers<br />
for Agriculture had resulted in the following decisions:-<br />
The Commonwealth Government shall guarantee a price of 6s. 3d. a hushel<br />
f. o. r. ports bulk basis for wheat grown and delivered by wheat-growers.<br />
The guaranteed price shall vary according to an index of production costs for<br />
each season starting with the 1948-49 crop.<br />
The guarantee shall apply to the wheat crop marketed through approved<br />
organizations for the period up to the end of the 1952-53 season.<br />
Approved organizations shall be the Australian Wheat Board and those<br />
organizations which are empowered by the State Parliaments with authority to<br />
receive wheat and to market it as the agents of the Australian Wheat Board.<br />
The Commonwealth shall ensure the guaranteed price in respect of the<br />
export from any one season's crop, provided that this guarantee shall not apply<br />
to the quantity of export in excess of 100,000,000 bushels.<br />
A stabilization fund shall be established by means of a tax on wheat<br />
exported to meet the guaranteed price above mentioned.<br />
The tax shall apply when the export price is higher than the guaranteed<br />
price, and shall be 50 per cent. of the difference between the two but shall not<br />
exceed 2s. 2d. a bushel.<br />
The tax slall apply to the 1947-48 and later wheat cropl.<br />
No refunds of tax from the fund shall he made ( except for the Il945-46<br />
and 1946-47, amounts already approved) except after consideration at sonim<br />
future date. The Commonwealth agrees that it will not hold an excessive<br />
amount in the fund, and it will consider a refund of tax to the oldest contributing<br />
pool whenever the financial prospects of the fund justify it.<br />
The State Ministers agree to recommend to their governments the pas; age iif<br />
legislation necessary to ensure-<br />
The home-consuinption price equal to the guaranteed price.<br />
The authorizing of an approved organization to receive from whe: Atgrowers<br />
all wheat voluntarily delivered for sale as part of an Australia. i<br />
pool.<br />
That legislative authority exists in each State to empower the direction<br />
of wheat by the Australian Wheat Board at any time to an approved<br />
organization as defined above.<br />
The regulation of wheat-growing on marginal areas which have been<br />
reconstructed under the plans approved for the elimination of uneconomic<br />
wheat areas, and the establishment of a commiittee to advise<br />
in cases where action to regulate wheat-growing on marginal areas<br />
is necessary.<br />
The conference agrees, subject to acceptance by the respective State governments-<br />
That States, where they desire to do so, will constitute State whe. it<br />
boards composed of a majority of growers' rlpresentatives elected ly<br />
a ballot conducted by the State.<br />
I That each State board will nominate growers' repreentatives who . re<br />
growers to the central authority in accordance with the present gri er<br />
representation on the Australian Wheat Board.<br />
That it will be optional for any State board to act cither in an advisory<br />
or an administrative capacity as decided by the State concerned.<br />
Where a State Government does not desire to create a State Wheat Boari.<br />
the machinery of the central authority ( the Australian Wheat Boardl)<br />
is to function.<br />
Where no State hoard is created, growers' relpresentativcs to the<br />
Australian Wheat Board will be elected by a: ballot . f growers conducted<br />
by the State.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 128, page 19; No. 129, page 35; No. 136,<br />
page 34.) </p>
<p>SOUTH-EAST ASIA.<br />
MALAYA-PRIME MINISTER'S STATMENT.<br />
On 18th July, 1043. the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
I cannot say I am very happy about the position in Singapore and<br />
Malaya. I had long discussions on my way to London and again on<br />
17th July, 1948, with the British Commissioner-General ( Mr.<br />
MoDonald). He is in the best position to judge and believes that the<br />
situation can be brought under control satisfactorily."<br />
MALAYA-EXPORT OF ARMS.<br />
On 19th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The export of arms and war material from Australia to Malaya<br />
are matters that have not come before the Government for consideration.<br />
I do not recall any request by the late Sir Edward Gent. There is a<br />
long standing embargo on the sale of arms to anybody or any country."<br />
On 21st July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The Customs Act provides for a prohibition on the export of arms,<br />
ammunition, explosives, military and naval stores. From the inauguration<br />
of the Commonwealth, there has been an export prohibition in<br />
one form or another on goods in this category. The existing prohibition,<br />
which came into operation in 1935, provides that none of these<br />
goods may be exported without the consent in writing of the Minister<br />
for Customs.<br />
" Following the outbreak of disorder in Malaya recently, numbers<br />
of applications have been received by the Customs Department for permits<br />
to export automatic pistols and revolvers and ammunition therefor<br />
to individual persons and individual companies in Malaya for the selfprotection<br />
of themselves or of their employees. Applications have been<br />
made also for permits to export small bulk shipments through commercial<br />
houses. These applications have been granted subject to the following<br />
conditions:-<br />
That, from the perusal of the order and related documents, the Collector<br />
of Custonie at the port of export is satisfied as to the hona-fides of the case.<br />
That the goods are covered by an import licence issued by the police<br />
authorities in Malaya.<br />
That the goods are consigined to the Chief Police Officer in the district in<br />
which the consignee resides.<br />
No applications have been received for the exportation to Malaya<br />
of any machine, guns or sub-machine guns.<br />
As regards provisions of light machine guns or military equipment,<br />
no request has been made by the British Government for the supply of<br />
these weapons to Malaya. The Australian Army authorities already<br />
hold in custody 100 Sten guns which the British War Office has asked<br />
the Australian Government to dispose of as surplus equipment on its<br />
behalf. Should the British Government cancel this request and ask to<br />
have these guns delivered, they will be delivered as early as possible.<br />
If a request is received through the British Government for supply from<br />
Australian stores of similar equipment, to assist in the preservation of </p>
<p>17<br />
law and order in the area, the request will be referred to Cabinet at its<br />
meeting on 2nd August, in view of Cabinet's previous decision that no<br />
export of military equipment was to be permitted. Should Cabinet<br />
decide to vary this view and supply equipment, in response to such a<br />
request, this will also be delivered."<br />
On 30th July, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
The British Government, at the request of the Government of the<br />
Federation of Malaya, has asked for the early delivery of the 100 Sten<br />
guns belonging to them and held in Australia and has also asked<br />
whether the Australian Government would be ready to supply certain<br />
other automatic weapons, ammunition and equipment, which are required<br />
for the maintenance of law and order in Malaya, and which<br />
may be available here.<br />
In accordance with the statement I made on 21st July, 1948, the<br />
100 Sten guns, with ammunition, were despatched by air yesterday<br />
nnd should be delivered at Singapore later to-day for onward transit<br />
to the Malayan authorities, together with a few other items of equipment<br />
required for testing purposes.<br />
" The question of the supply of weapons and equipment from Australian<br />
stocks will, in accordance with my statement of 21st July, 1948,<br />
bf, considered by Cabinet at its meeting on 2nd August, 1948. Meanwhile,<br />
the extent to which the item. required may be available here is<br />
being urgently examined."<br />
On 2nd August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that, where a request has been, or will be,<br />
made by the British Government for arms and equipment for use by<br />
the Government of the Malayan Union, these will be made available<br />
from Australian supplies within the reasonable limits of their<br />
a vailability." INDUSTRIAL.<br />
INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS-PROPOSED CONFERENCE.<br />
On 20th July, 1948, the Minister for Labour ( Mr. Holloway) said--<br />
" I would be in favour of the Prime Minister calling a conference<br />
of employees and employers to discuss how . best to get a greater volume<br />
of production of essential goods. If a basis for an all-party conference<br />
cannot be reached, I am in favour of the Prime Minister calling a<br />
conference of union delegates for a discussion, with the same object<br />
in view." On 1lth August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" I have conferred to-day with the Minister for Labour ( Mr.<br />
Holloway), the President ( Mr. P. J. Clarey), the Secretary ( Mr. A. E.<br />
Monk), the Assistant Secretary ( Mr. R. R. Broadby) and Mr. C. Crofts<br />
of the Australian Council of Trade Unions on the need for greater<br />
production. A conference of trades unions will be convened at a later<br />
date. Dtails of the conference will be arranged by Mr. Holloway in<br />
conjunction with the A. C. T. U." </p>
<p>SOCIAL SECURITY.<br />
PHYSICALLY HANDICAPPED PERSONS.<br />
On 21st July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" To take full advantage of the knowledge and experience of<br />
existing staffs in extending the Government's plans for the rehabilitation<br />
of physically handicapped persons, it has been decided that the plan will,<br />
for the time being, be administered by the Department of Post-war<br />
Reconstruction. Legislation will be introduced to amend the Social Services Consolidation<br />
Act to vest the responsibility for the development of the<br />
scheme for rehabilitation of disabled members of the community in<br />
the Director-General of Social Services.<br />
The scheme will extend to invalid pensioners or claimants for thi<br />
invalid pension and those receiving or claiming unemployment or sickness<br />
benefits who would become unemployable unless rehabilitation<br />
assistance is provided.<br />
" The Department of Social Services has already established a<br />
rehabilitation centre in each State except Tasmania, where facilities cf<br />
the Red Cross Society are u. ed.<br />
" Staff employed by the Department of Social Services on this work<br />
is almost wholly temporary, but the Department of Post-war Recolstruction,<br />
responsible for the rehabilitation of many thousands of<br />
ex-servicemen, has a considerable number of permanent officers on it::<br />
. taff. These officers are still required for this work. It is recognized.<br />
however, that the work of post-war reconstruction will gradually declin..<br />
and that many of the permanent staff of that department trained in<br />
rehabilitation work might appropriately be transferred to the Department<br />
of Social Services. The Minister for Post-war Reconstruction<br />
( Mr. Dedman) and the Minister for Social Services ( Senator<br />
McKenna) have decided that-<br />
The Department of Social Servirc e lhall coiitinue ti he relpiniible ftinr tii<br />
civilian rehabilitation plan.<br />
Temporarily the Depirtnlc': t of I.' ot-war Recon-truction will tnke , v. cr. athe<br />
agent for the Depart enicito f Sociail Services. tlhe dtl nii tistitor n . f i l<br />
rehabilitation scheme.<br />
" The Department of Social Services will proceed with the cstal,-<br />
lishment and appointment of its permanent staff for the rehabilitationl<br />
plan but will, in the meantime, second the personnel so appointed tii<br />
the Department of Post-war Reconstruction."<br />
TUBERCULOSIS-CABINET DECISION.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
Cabinet to-day approved of a plan of control in regard to tuberculosis<br />
along lines already discussed with State Ministers of Health on<br />
29th June, 1948, for conclusion with the States at the forthcomilng<br />
conference of Commonwealth and State Ministers on 23rd Auguzt." </p>
<p>COMMONWEALTH LOANS.<br />
FLOTATION COSTS.<br />
On 28th July, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
During the war years and since, Commonwealth loan raisings have<br />
been conducted with remarkable economy and compare more than<br />
favorably with other countries. After provision is made for all charges<br />
-including advertising, brokerage, bank expenses and the Commonwealth<br />
Loani. Organization-the cost does not exceed 5s. per cent. This<br />
cost is less than one-third of the cost rate regarded as appropriate in<br />
some overseas countries.<br />
" From the war-time peak of 360 in all States, the Commonwealth<br />
Loans Organization staff has been reduced to 130. The remaining staff<br />
is regarded as essential. It provides a nucleus of highly-trained persons<br />
whose services are fully employed on loan subscription, conversions and<br />
national savings campaigns.<br />
The Sixth Security Loan, opening on 8th September, 194S, is an<br />
iin'portant operation. Apart from œ 15,000,000 of new money, an appeal<br />
will be made to 300,000 holders of œ 85,000,000 of Commonwealth<br />
securities maturing in September-October, 194S, to convert into the<br />
new loan.<br />
" Visits to homes by the organization's representatives have been part<br />
of normal activities for a considerable period. This advice card sent<br />
to householders is necessary because, with money involved, precautions<br />
ar1 necessary to protect both Commonwealth and public. This work is<br />
done under strict supervision."<br />
HEALTH AND YOUTH WELFARE.<br />
INTERNATIONAL YOUTH CONFERENCE.<br />
On 28th July, 1948, the Minister for Health ( Senator McKenna)<br />
announced that the Australian delegation to attend the International<br />
Youth Conference at London in August, 1948, would comprise-<br />
Miss Lyra Taylor, in charge of professional social work and research<br />
activities in the Department of Social Services; the co-director of national<br />
fitness in the Department of Health ( Miss Kathleen Gordon) the Rev. G.<br />
Malloy of the Church of England Youth Department; the national secretary of<br />
the Young Christian Workers' Movement ( Mr. F. McCann) and Mr. A. S.<br />
Livingstone, of the department of social studies at Melbourne University.<br />
Major aspects of discussion at the conference would be-<br />
Preparation for work, including training and vocational guidance; legislation<br />
specifically affecting young people in work ( urban and rural) the status of<br />
young people in work; the position of women and girls and the family in relation<br />
to work social security; the influence of mass media ( press, films and radio)<br />
on young people; commercial provision for leisure ( including commercially<br />
sponsored holiday camps and compulsory holidays for employees of business<br />
undertakings): travel, holidays and interchange; the contributions of the<br />
voluntary organizations to leisure, in age groups under and over eighteen:<br />
cultural life and developments in relation to work and leisure. </p>
<p>NATIONAL HEALTH COUNCIL-APPOINTMENTS.<br />
On 28th July, 1948, Senator McKenna announced the appointment<br />
to the National Health and Medical Research Council of a representative<br />
of the Australian Dental Association, and of an obstetrician<br />
representing the Australian Regional Council of the Royal College of<br />
Obstetricians and Gynaecologists. GOITROUS AREAS.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet to-day approved of the supply free of charge to State<br />
governments, municipalities and other approved public authorities of<br />
tablets containing potassium iodide for the prevention of endemic<br />
goitre. Reports of school medical officers have revealed the main<br />
goitrous areas in Australia as follows:-<br />
Nmv SOUTH WALES.-Hunter and Manning valleys ( excluding Newcastle),<br />
25,000 children; norther tablelands, 10,000; portion of central tablelands,<br />
10,000; southern tablelands. 8,000; portion of non-metropolitan section of<br />
Cumberland, 2,500; total, 55.500.<br />
VICTORIA.-Gippslaind, 21: 000 children: portion of central Victoria, 5.000:<br />
total 26,000.<br />
QUEENSLAND.-Cairns Hinterland and Toowoomba valley., 3,500 children.<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALLA.-Adelaide Hills, 5,000 children.<br />
WESTERN AUSTRALIA.-C. Leenwin Hinterland ( strongly suspect. n( t proven).<br />
1.000 children.<br />
TAsMANLA.-Derwent Valley, HH Valllleey, , King Valley, North Midland. na,,<br />
portion of Midland, 25,000 children.<br />
TOTAL.-116,00. INDUSTRIAL HYGIENE AND MEDICINE.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
" A Division of Industrial Hygiene in the Commonwealth Health<br />
Department, first established in 1924, was abolished in 1932 and since<br />
then Health Department medical officers working part time on this<br />
subject have given advice on industrial problems.<br />
" Cabinet decided to-day to establish a strong unit in industrial<br />
medicine at the School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine at<br />
Sydney University. The unit will include a senior medical industrial<br />
hygienist, with a team of workers including a chemist and a physicist.<br />
The duties of the unit will be-<br />
To act as a training school for medical men and others needed to carry out<br />
investigations into industrial hazards and problems of industrial hygiene.<br />
To advise the Government on all problems relating to diseases in industry.<br />
As a research unit to initiate industrial hygiene field investigations into the<br />
cause, nature and extent of industrial health hazards.<br />
REPARATIONS.<br />
SCIENTIFIC PERSONNEL.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" The Minister for Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman) advised<br />
Cabinet to-day of a further report by the Employment of Scientific and<br />
Technical Enemy Aliens Committee. The report recommended that a<br />
further 48 German scientists and technicians be brought to Australia for<br />
employment." </p>
<p>i1<br />
RECONSTRUCTION.<br />
SECONDARY INDUSTRIES-DIVISION OF INDUSTRIAL<br />
DEVELOPMENT.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day that the Division of Industrial Development<br />
of the Department of Post-war Reconstruction be established on a<br />
permanent instead of its present temporary basis. The functions of the<br />
Division will be-<br />
To encourage and advance industrial development necessary for Commonwealth<br />
responsibilities.<br />
To exercise Commnonwealth responsibilities in respect of the national policy<br />
lif decentralization of secondary industries.<br />
Generally to lromote efficiency in industry, and in particular to study technical,<br />
production and managerial problems.<br />
To encourage and assist in the discmination and the application of new<br />
knowledge and new methods.<br />
To undertake for publication continuing tlidies of the structt cr and operation<br />
of Australian imanufactering industries."<br />
EXTERNAL COMMUNICATIONS.<br />
TELE-COMMUNICATIONS COMMISSION-APPOINTMENT.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
Cabinet decided to-day to re-appoint Mr. G. U. J. Gowans as<br />
imember of the Overseas Tele-communications Commission ( Aust.) for<br />
three years from 23rd August, 1948. Mr. Gowans was appointed a<br />
member of the Commission from 25th January, 1947, in place of J. V.<br />
Barry. K. C." FIGHTING FORCES.<br />
COMMONWEALTH RECONSTRUCTION TRAINING<br />
SCHEME-CLOSING DATE.<br />
On 3rd August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
When the Government decided that there should be no general<br />
extension for the closing date for the receipt of applications under the<br />
Commonwealth Reconstruction Training Scheme beyond 30th June,<br />
1947, provision was made whereby, under special training plans approved<br />
by. the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction ( Mr. Dedman), applications<br />
could be received after that date.<br />
Cabinet to-day approved of action taken by Mr. Dedman under<br />
the following special plans:-<br />
No. 1. War-caused Disabled Personi.-Applications may continue to be<br />
accepted, subject to review in June, 1948.<br />
No. 2. War Widows.-Applications may continue to be accepted, subject to<br />
review in June, 1948.<br />
No. 3. Part-time Training.-Date for acceptance of appllications extended t,<br />
June, 1948, in respect of the following classes of persons enrolled in the<br />
scheme as at 30th June, 1947, and to twelve months after date of enrolment in<br />
the scheme in cases where enrolment occurs after 30th June, 1947:-<br />
Full-time trainee ( including a trainee in subsidized employment) applying<br />
to take a part-time course concurrently with his full-time course.<br />
Part-time trainee applying to take another part-time eunr-e concurrently<br />
with the first part-time course. </p>
<p>FullI-tine rin ce ( pro fesjollaj OF or cational a PP lying to take at prt<br />
tin,,, couirse at the end of his full-time courbe.<br />
P art-timen trai ne. applying to take additional jair t-tt i course, liin<br />
tioin j~ ction of at course not costing the full<br />
No. 4. Teacher Training.-Dgate for acceptance of apjlications extended to<br />
3Oth JTune, 1948.<br />
No. 5. Trainiu if Nath-es in the Territory of P~ apua-New G. uinea.-Dattc for<br />
twcvptanct! A) aLpiipf 1LtionS extended to 31st Decemiber, 1948.<br />
No. 6. Trainin-of ' Jorres; Strait Islanders-Date for-accelitance ( if applicatiouue<br />
extend~ ed to 30th June. 1948.<br />
No. 7. N ursinA Trainin..-Date for acceptance of ap-plicationls extendled to<br />
June, 194S.<br />
" Cabinet also applroved of the continued operation of special plans-<br />
Nos. 1. 2 and 3. with a further review in Juine, 1949."<br />
WAR SERVICE MORATORIUM-CONTINUANCE.<br />
On 10th August, 1948, the acting Attorncy-General ( Senator<br />
2% cKenna) announced that amendmcnts would be made to National<br />
Security ( War Service Moratorium) Regulations to afford ex-servicemen<br />
the saic protection under State landlord and tenanit legislation<br />
asj they7 lid undi~ er Commonwealth regulations.<br />
( For earlier references. please see No. 128, page 20; No 135, page 34.)<br />
WHEAT POOLS PAYMENTS.<br />
10 POOL--FIFTH ADVANCE.<br />
On : 3rd August. 194S, thle Minister for Coinmcee ( Mr. Pollard)<br />
9nnoi~ uceu a fifthi advance of 54d. a bushel for wheat in No. 10 pool-<br />
' The advanee \\-ould hring paYments to 7s. Sid. a bushlel.<br />
-No. 11 POOL-THIRD ADVANCE.<br />
On 3rd August, 194S, Mivr. Pollard announced a third advance ( if 1<br />
ii bushel for w~ beat in No. 11 poo01. The advance would bring payments<br />
to Ss. 6d.: less freight, for builk wheat a bushel and 9s., less freight, for-<br />
EXTERNAL AFFAIRS.<br />
DIPLOMATIC CADETS.<br />
On 6th August, 1948, the acting Minister for-External Affairs ( Mr..<br />
Chifle y) said that applications had been invited for diplomuatic cadets<br />
tol commence trainling at Canberra University College in 1949.<br />
AID ROADS AND WORKS ACT.<br />
PETROL TAX, GRANT FOR ROADS.<br />
On 6th August. 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
" Representationis have been received from many sources that the<br />
whbole of the -proceeeds of taxation on petrol or a greater portion shiould<br />
be made available for roads purposes. </p>
<p>" The petrol tax is not imposed solely for this purpose and although<br />
for many years substantial roads grants have been made to the States,<br />
the major portion of this tax has been required to meet the expenditure<br />
of the Commonwealth for general purposes and in particular, the heavy<br />
commitments for war and post-war purposes. The tax is primarily a<br />
revenue impost, in common with those imposed on many other item;,<br />
such as beer, tobacco and matches.<br />
" About 90 per cent. of the petrol consumed in Australia for civil<br />
purposes is used for commercial and industrial purposes. To a great<br />
extent the cost is passed on to the general community in traisportatioa<br />
and delivery charges.<br />
Since the greater portion of the tax is not finally borne by the<br />
users of petrol but by the general community, it is inappropriate to<br />
contend that the whole of the proceeds should be usecd for roads<br />
purposes. Since the war the petrol tax has been reduced by Id. a gallon.<br />
As in the case of other forms of taxation, consideration is given to tile<br />
possibility of effecting reductions as the financial commitments of the<br />
Commonwealth permit.<br />
The whole question of Commonwealth assistance for roads received<br />
very full consideration when the Commonwealth Aid Roads and Works<br />
Act was ' passed in May, 1947. This legislation provides for the payment<br />
to State Governments over a period of three years of considerably<br />
increased amounts and one of its features is that it provides for ai<br />
special payment of œ 1,000,000 a year for the maintenance and construction<br />
of roads, other than main highways, through sparsely settled<br />
areas, timber country and rural areas. These payments are made in the<br />
first instance to State governments, since it is not the policy of the<br />
Commonwealth to give direct financial aid to local government bodies.<br />
Including the sum of œ 500,000 for expenditure by the Commonwealth<br />
on strategic roads and roads for access to Commonwealth properties,<br />
the amount so made available for roads purposes during 1947-48<br />
was œ 6,300,000, compared with œ 4,800,000 in 1946-47. The question<br />
of the adequacy of the present grant is being kept under notice by the<br />
Government. It was inevitable that the war-time diversion of practically Australia's<br />
total economic resources should result in some deterioration i,<br />
the condition of many roads. The question of restoration and improvc.-<br />
ment is not, however, solely one of finance. As a result of the suspension<br />
of many forms of ordinary economic activity during the war, resources<br />
of materials and man-power in Australia to-day are insufficient to me-t<br />
all requirements. If a greater sum were to be spent on roads, it is<br />
obvious that there would be a reduction in the allocation of labour and<br />
materials to other types of economic activity and apart from purely<br />
financial considerations, the expenditure of money on roads must be<br />
viewed in that light." </p>
<p>NATIONAL UNIVERSITY.<br />
INTERIM COUNCIL-APPOINTMENTS.<br />
On 10th August, 1948, the Minister for Post-war Reconstruction<br />
( Mr. Dedruan) announced appointments to the interim council of the<br />
Australian National University as follows-<br />
The Prujie-'-, or of Bacteriology at Sydney University ( Profes,. or H. WVard).<br />
the Professor of Botany at Adelaide University ( Professor J. G. Wood), the<br />
Professor of Physics at Melbourne University ( Professor L. H. Martin).<br />
Original members wvere Professor R. C. Mills ( chairman), Sir John Medley,<br />
Sir Robert Garran. Sir Frederic Eggleston. Sir David Rivett, Professor R. D.<br />
Wright, Profe, or Eric Ashiby. Dr. H. C. Coomibs. Mr. C. S. Daley. Mr. IT. J.<br />
Goode-, and tlic Vice-Chiancellor.<br />
( For earlier references, please see No. 118, page 26; No. 130, page 41.)<br />
BANKING CONTROL.<br />
LEGISLATION-NATIONALIZATION, HIGH COURT CASE.<br />
JUDGMENT.<br />
On 11th August, 194S, the Prime MNiinister ( Mr. Chiflev) . said-<br />
" The matter'; is one upon which the Acting Attorney-Generat<br />
( Senator McN~ Kennia) will report to the Government."<br />
The judgment olt the High C'ourt in the foiliowiiig eases:<br />
BANK 41F' NENV SU'iH NVALEIS ANI' OTRgli r. THE (. MM0ONVEALTH OF'<br />
AUSTRAL. IA AN[; OTIIFTlS.<br />
Doclare that the followiing pr-ovisions of th, Baniking Act 1947 tire invalid-Part<br />
IV.. Division 2. xiit sita r is, it rein tes ti. the volo Iita ry acquisition of shiares<br />
andi without prejudice to the question whether section 14 Is valid In relation<br />
thereto: Part IV.. r) jvisoii 3. s. etins 24. 25. L7 to 45 inclusive, 46, 59 and 60.<br />
Orderthat the defendant the TIrtasurer a ld anly Minister of the defendmir tihe<br />
Commonwealth of Australia or a~ ny mnember of the Executive Counicil for<br />
the timie being acti or purporting to act for or on behalf of the<br />
Treasurer of t ( imnionweiiiti of Australia be restrained from<br />
ptublishing or causing or permitting to bo published any notice pursuant<br />
to sob-section of Section 13 of the Banking Act 1947:<br />
( b) i that the defendant Hugh Trai~ il Arniltaig and every other person for the<br />
time being entitled by law or purporting to exercise thle powers of the<br />
Governor of the Commonwealth Ban], of AXustralia be restrainctd from<br />
appointing or purporting to oippoiiit tiny person it tdirector of any ot the<br />
plaintiff complautes:<br />
tc) that the defendant the Treasurer and ainy Minister of the defendant the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia or ainy member of the Executive Council for<br />
the time being acting or purporting to act for or on behalf of the<br />
Treasurer of the Commonwvealth of Australia be restrained from iving<br />
or cauosinig or permitting to be given anly notice pursuafnt to sub-section<br />
of Section 22 of the Ilonkftig Act 1947;<br />
0i1t ha tt t tie defendant the Coniio pael ti ( if A us tralia Its iticers anid servants.<br />
be restramined froin requiring any of the plaintiff comnlies it, take tiny<br />
action piursuan~ t to sob-sectionl of Section 24 of tile Balling Act 1947;<br />
thait the defendant the Trensurer ilnu tiny Minister of the defendant the<br />
Commonwealth of Auqtralia or any member of tile Executive Council for<br />
the time being acting or purporting to act for or on behalf of the<br />
Treasurer the (' omunowealti of Australia be restrainedl froim<br />
pubhiishing or causing or perii ig to be published in the Coinin icicth~<br />
Gazette tiny notice p~ ursuant to simiisection of Section 46 of the<br />
Btinking Acet 1947: andl<br />
thiat thle dlefendanit Hugh ' rral .% rAmtj ag' a m1ue si' ry other personi for the<br />
tinue being enititled by law or purporimig to exercise the powers of the<br />
Governor of the Commonwealth Biank of Australia be restrained from.<br />
inuthiorizliug any son to ict un der Sect jion 59 if the Ban king Irfe 194..<br />
Defendanits to pay costs of plajinjtiff icledin. g reserved costs, If any. </p>
<p>TUE BANK OF AUSTRIIAASA otiluts r. THE COIIAIONWEALTH OF<br />
AUSTRALIA AslD OTIMRiS.<br />
Declare that tile following privisionts of the Bantking Act 11) 47 ate invalid:<br />
Sections 24, 25, 3-7 to 45 ittcltt. ti'e, 46. 59 and 60.<br />
Orderthat te. deteaitnt the ' Treasurer and aiiy Mliniste~ r of the defendant rthe<br />
Cionimonwealtlt of Australia or any member of the Executive Counteill<br />
for rthe time being atcting or purporting to act for or on behalf of the<br />
Tgretisurer of the Commonwealth of Australia be restrained front giving<br />
or causing or permtittinig to he given any notice pursuant to sub-sectitit<br />
if Section 22 of the ltankittg Act 1947<br />
that tite defetdatt tite Conmtmtweailtit Btink of Australia its officers aitd<br />
. aervtitts te restritinedi frontt reqluiring tiny of the plaintiff compttnies to<br />
take tinty action pursoatin to sub-seeton of Section 24 of tio'<br />
IBlinking Aict 1947:<br />
that tite defendanot lime ' frea., urer and ty ' Minister of the defendatnt inlie<br />
Coinitntwitnilth of Anstrtt or any nmenmber of the Executive Ciouacii tor<br />
the tinte belting acting or punrportinmg to act for or on behtalf of tite<br />
Tretasurer oft the Coinmonwetaith of Austrttlia he restrained front<br />
publishing tor causing or permitting to be published In the Cornaioitincalth<br />
Gazette tttt niotie" piursnuant to sub-section of Section 4C0 of ite(<br />
Jtainkiig .4ct 1947 ; and<br />
( 4r) that tite tleti'tdont ught ' roii Aratitage tttd every other pirson for tit'<br />
tinit' bitilun ititled bylaitiw-iflurportinz to exercise the powers tit<br />
tit,-Uovi-ninon of rthe Coimtiomtwealtht Hank of Australia be restralied fromt<br />
itiutitorizimig tiny persont to tict. under Section 59 of the Baniking Arct 19147.<br />
Defeiidants to pay costs of plaititiffs iticluding reserved costs. it any.<br />
THE STATE OF VICTORIA ANtD ANtiijnina I. TEE COMMONWEAtLTH OF<br />
AUSTRALIA AND OTHEiRS.<br />
THlE STATE OF1 SOUTH . AUS'ITRALIA ANti ANOTHIER r. THE COMMONWEALTH I) F1<br />
AUSTRtALIA ANti OTHERniS.<br />
THE STATE OF WESTERN AUSTRtALI. A Axn ANoriIEI r. TI-I COMMONWEAI. TII<br />
OF AUSTRALIA AND' OTHieiS.<br />
Judgment itI the sanie ti'ris as it Baniik of New Southi Wit les and outhters.<br />
Lu themn G. J.:<br />
In these tive ttctionts. the validity of the Rttikity A1ct 1947 hits beemn cii~ tiin-g-.-<br />
In my opinion, the followvimtg sectionms of the Act tire ivitlid:<br />
sectioii 14 reititing to the trantsfer by tlte Cutointweultlt Bank ( if shlt. tre<br />
Sections 17 to 20 relating to the ttiking over anil comitrotl of tih' Australitan Ranks.<br />
Sections 23 and 24 reiatinig to the acquisition ( if the Assvts of thie Banks.<br />
Iii my opinion declaraztionts should lie itae accirhingly tillthe liiitpriiiit'i<br />
iitjumictionts gramited.<br />
Rich~ J. aind Williaim* Js. ( deilivered by Rtichi)<br />
We would give Judgmieiit to the plaintiffs in all tiv'e tictitons. Iti the atitoit by tii"<br />
private banks incorportited IIt Australia antI the Sttttes Of Victoria-Sooth Atistratlli<br />
tiud lWistern Australia, we dlecitire thtat Seetiiins 13, 14. 17-21 iiiclosilvi, 22. sub-sectiiins<br />
S ( bF) ttid 24. 56,. 59 amid 60l. titid Parts 6 tand 7 of ite( Banking : Act 1947 tire vi iii<br />
In the actioni by the three private banks incorporated itt the Uniited Kingdom, l e<br />
declare Sections 22. sub-section, S tinid 24. 25, 59 tind 60 andii Parts C, : and 7<br />
( if tite aict : ire void tidt ton isequen tila1 r-lief shoiuid hi' gin it ted.<br />
, Stai'ke J. ( deliviered by Dixotn)<br />
His Honour says time followinig iinivisons of the Itainking Acit 11447 tire invailid<br />
Part 4, Division 2, exciept Iiisiifar tis the aicquisition tit shiares by agreenient is<br />
Pac rotn c4e, rnDeidv. isioin 3 Iq wvholly it ' ald~.<br />
l'. trt 4, D~ ivision 4. taihkinig tii iiess if uatis. hs inivailid iexceplt itiaaf; r<br />
as by agreemntt.<br />
P'art 6 Is wvlolv iIiv atlid.<br />
Pitrt 7 ha wvhollv invalid.<br />
P'art S inoperative.<br />
I,' art 9 Is inoperaitve, esci-pi itisofar is. rite-proivisiiiis ithereto nity Ill, ttliiii<br />
tioa ctiuisitionis by aigreeiteni. atimil li tinty icise' Siectioiis 59). 60i toil 62 a<br />
invalid.<br />
Diecla rationts shtuttd Iitami lua d zieorngly.<br />
Dixon J.:<br />
I1 i ift 11o piioin thtait Setiunt 172 i r the Itit. 11-lt 11947 tit'i ii omli-wilt,<br />
Seciott 5,1 ( 311 of tlii ( onslititutiim aiid are. void. Sirlit 13 ctimuritut givii a<br />
pturptose. himdi'iutihu-nt ori I ituta provisitis. Sectioiis 41, 42. 43. 44 unit diet w'ith<br />
Sectitin 75 ( 3 4 of rite Comistitrut Iion. wvith thle risulit thaiit l1iit I; fttlls. i ; oil ilt t itt,<br />
tourthier ri'sulit altat. excilit fur Sectitti 12, Divisioni 2 of 1' ttrt 4 itnid Sectiiins 24 at xIi<br />
46 tire in validi. Sui-si-etiomis 4-8 itt Siection tire ciiiitrnii toi Sect] iii 92 indi are-<br />
. lfTientani ' rTe futlluihig p ru'isiiit uif tih' Rantintumg Act ; ire invailid:<br />
Secticits 17.20 Inclusive.<br />
S etin 24. mili-sectioit S. </p>
<p>LEGISLATION-NATIONALIZATION. II ll( ('; OU1T<br />
JUDGMENT, APPEAL.<br />
On 13th August, 1948, Mr. Chifley said-<br />
I have consulted all members of Cabinet on the High ( ou: l's<br />
judgment in the Banking case and a decision has been reached to seek<br />
an appeal to the Privy Council at the earliest possible date.<br />
direct attention to some aspects of the court's decision which it is<br />
desirable should be made clear to the public. A majority of the court<br />
has held that certain parts of the 1947 Act conflict with Section 92<br />
of the Constitution, which guarantees interstate free trade. That,<br />
however, is a matter on which there has been sharp division of opinion<br />
among the justices of the court, In the Chief Justice's opinion, the<br />
Act was fully within the principles relating to Section 92 established by<br />
the Privy Council.<br />
Apart from Section 92, the fundamental question is the scope of<br />
the National Parliament's power to make laws with respect to banking.<br />
On that point, a majority of the court substantially upheld the major<br />
contentions put forward for the Commonwealth by the Attorney-General<br />
( Dr. Evatt) and rejected the narrow. interpretation contended for by<br />
the private banks.<br />
The majority of the court also decisively rejected the special<br />
contentions put forward by the three plaintiff States.<br />
I am advised that the judgments of the Chief Justice and Mr.<br />
Justice McTiernan show that a few amendments in non-vital provisions<br />
would have enabled those justices to uphold the Act in all respects.<br />
Copies of the High Court judgments are being despatched to Dr.<br />
Evatt in London and will reach him early next week. I have arranged<br />
for the Solicitor-General ( Professor K. H. Bailey) to go to London<br />
as soon as possible for consultation with Dr. Evatt.'<br />
COAL INDUSTRY.<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT TO COALFIELDS.<br />
On 12th August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Minister for Shipping and Fuel (. Senator Ashley) and representatives<br />
of the Joint Coal Board will accompany me on a visit to<br />
Cessnock and Kurri Kurri on Sunday, 5th September, 1948. It is<br />
proposed that I address members of the Australian Coal and Shall<br />
Employeve' Federation at those places."<br />
NATIONAL DEBT.<br />
NATIONAL DEBT COMMISSION-ANNUAL MEETING.<br />
On 19th August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said that<br />
the National Debt Commission had met that day when the annual report<br />
of transactions for the year ended 30th June, 1948, was presented, and<br />
consideration given to the application of sinking fund moneys accruing<br />
diiring 194S-49. </p>
<p>Receipts of the sinking fund for 1947-48 were œ 27,659,000. Receipts<br />
for 1948-49 were estimated at œ 28,785,000 being œ 18,592,000 on account<br />
of the Connuonwealth and œ 10,193,000 on account of the States. Of<br />
the latter amount, œ 1,851,000 would be provided from Commonwealth<br />
revenue. Total contributions estimated to be available for the redemption<br />
of the d,. bt of each State were-<br />
New South Wales, œ 4,000,000; Victoria, œ 2,034,000: Queensland, œ 1,475,000;<br />
South Australia, œ 1.254,000; Western Australia, œ 1,092,000; Tasmania, œ 338,000;<br />
ttal œ 10.193,000.<br />
The receipts totalling œ 28,785,000 were directed by the commission<br />
to be applied in the various markets in which Commonwealth and State<br />
securities were held-Australia, London and New York. The commission<br />
used its funds for the redemption of Commonwealth and State<br />
securities either by repurchase of securities on the market, or by redemption<br />
at maturity.<br />
The large sums applied in repurchases on Stock Exchanges ensured<br />
a regular market for security holders. When securities were acquired<br />
by the commission, either by repurchase or redemption, they were canrc'lled<br />
and the public debt reduced accordingly.<br />
Members of the commission were-<br />
The Couionwealth Trea-urer ( Mr. Chifey), chairman, the' Chief Justice<br />
( Sir Jolhn Lathami), the Governor of the Commonwealth Bank ( Mr. H. T.<br />
Armitagc), the acting-secretary of the Treasury ( Mr. G. P. N. Watt), the<br />
Solicitor-General ( Professnr K. H. Bailey) and Mr. A. T. Smithers, representati\<br />
ve . f tlwi States. GOLD MINING.<br />
ASSISTANCE.<br />
On 20th August, 1948, the Prime Minister ( Mr. Chifley) said-<br />
The Commonwealth has agreed to provide a measure of assistance<br />
to three gold-mining companies in the Kalgoorlie area and to review<br />
the case of another Kalgoorlie mine when the financial results of its<br />
operations during 1948 are available. The request of a mine in the<br />
Cue district for assistance is still under consideration.<br />
The Commonwealth's agreement to provide this assistance, follows<br />
an application which was made by fifteen mines, through the Western<br />
Australia Chamber of Mines, to the Minister for the Interior ( Mr.<br />
Johnson). The Chamber claimed that a number of the mines would<br />
he forced to close as the present price of gold did not allow a sufficient<br />
margin to meet the rising costs. It was pointed out that the closing<br />
cf these mines would have a serious effect on the economy of Western<br />
Anctralia and might result in the abandonment of certain townships.<br />
Financial and technical investigations were made into the position<br />
of each mine. These investigations showed that a general form of<br />
assistance is not warranted. Many mines are still capable of paying<br />
good dividends even though rising costs are reducing the level of profits </p>
<p>to which the mines have been accustomed. A few of the mines included<br />
in the application are only salvage propositions, and Commonwealth<br />
assistance would not be justified under such circumstances.<br />
The mines wvhich it has been decided to aid during the current<br />
year have been informed of the termis of assistance, and the position of<br />
the indust ry in Western Australia will be reviewed early next year.<br />
Most mines are experiencing difficulty in maintaining production rate<br />
because of labour shortages."<br />
By Authority: L. F. JOHNSTON, Commuronwealth Governmzient Printer, Canberra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
