<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5671</transcript-id>
    <title>THE JOHN LAWS SHOW, RADIO 2UE, SYDNEY, 20 OCTOBER 1981, INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RT HON MALCOLM FRASER CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005671.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
pXTE:<br />
* SUBJ EC. 7 i~ 77<br />
TiHE~ JOHN LAWS SHOW, RADIO 2UY, SYDNEY<br />
20th October 3081<br />
INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MIINISTtR OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
TBE RT. HON. MALCOLM FRASER, CHI, 14P.<br />
Five or six years ago 1. believed that overseas countries<br />
would -get. their own economies right. much quicker. I<br />
believed that they'd get InIlation down, I believ'ed their<br />
economics would start growing and that. world trade would<br />
start growing and that that therefore wvould assist,<br />
Australia because we are very much ' an export country.<br />
I suppose ubout three or four years ago I came to the<br />
view thbat major world economies weren't going to get<br />
fixed quickly and that. whatevere wve did we would have<br />
t~ o do on our own account and that's really been the basis<br />
of policy ever since.<br />
LAWS: Mr. HIayde-n Is not the sort. of fellow Who would make th~ at.<br />
kind of statem-ent without some sort of foundation. I<br />
don't really think that Bill ) ayden'is an alarmist. as<br />
such. I don't know whether you agree or not but one<br />
would think that he had some basis for making t-hat.<br />
statement.. What might that basis. b) e?<br />
PM4<br />
CLAWS: TIM: 1 don't reall1y think he's got. abasisfor It beca ' use I f<br />
you really look at what he has said over the Years,<br />
you know, he has predicted changes In the value of the<br />
dollar, he hats predicted difficult circumstances In t-be<br />
economy, he has predicted, If my recollection is,<br />
correct,* 12 or 13 or 14 percent rates of Inflation, and<br />
thbose predict-ions have Invariably proved to be very wrong.<br />
Don't you think that a statement that. we are facing t-be<br />
worst credit squeeze in 20 years Is rather an alarmiststatement?<br />
Yes It is and I think it'sntboroughly Irresponsible<br />
statement and you know, I doubt if, 1-his might be a harsh<br />
thing to say, but I doubt if he really believes, it<br />
himself.<br />
LAWS: Yes. I don't. know that it is harsh. I think if I made<br />
the sane sort of statement on radio I'd probably have<br />
another trip to the Tribunal. It seems extraordinary..<br />
* that he can make that. sort of statement if there's no':.<br />
foundation for it.<br />
PM: WellI I don'I-think there is any foundation for it at all<br />
because one ol' the things that we've tried to do over<br />
the last five or six years is t~ o manage the economy and<br />
to manage the banking system In ways which h[ ave avoided<br />
w~ hat in the' old days you'd call a credit. squeeze.<br />
And we" Ve been able to succeed in that. I ca n' see<br />
why we shouldn't succeed in the future in precisely the<br />
same way.<br />
YAM: 1j2C) </p>
<p>Page 2<br />
LAWS: Ok. President Reagan, as you say, admits that Americia<br />
is in a recession he calls it. Is that going to have<br />
an effect on us?<br />
PM: When the American economy is Tn difficulty it has an<br />
effect on the whole world and they buy less from overseas,<br />
they buy less from Japan. Commodity prices therefore<br />
tend to fall and this is precisely what's happened over<br />
recent months. It's not only-the Unile-d Stales' economy,<br />
the British economy, the French economy, the Italians,<br />
the German economy which was known, for a number of<br />
years, as the economic miracle.<br />
LAWS: That's right. We looked to it for guidance.<br />
PM: They've taken a very severe battering.<br />
LAWS: Yes they have.<br />
PM: And, you know, when this happens amongst the major<br />
western economies around the-.. orld i.' s bound to affect<br />
commodity prices and, you know, this in a sense is the<br />
main thing affecting our own Balance of Payments.<br />
PM: Yes. I'm asking you to loQk.._ B bit into the future<br />
which is probably not possible, but a calculated guess,<br />
what's the situation going to be like, in your mind,<br />
six months irom now?<br />
LAWS: Well I suppose in -office you learn not to make the same<br />
mistake twice and predicting too definitely what might<br />
be the circumstance has proved to be embarrassing in<br />
past years so I don" t want to put an albatross around<br />
my own neck by being too precise. I think the world<br />
economy is going to stay difficult and that means some<br />
difficulty through, you know, commodity prices but<br />
also believe that Australia is very well and strongly<br />
placed to deal with whatever c-rcumstin-ces might arise.<br />
We are better placed. We do have a sounder economy than<br />
most industrial countries overseas and therefore whatever.<br />
happens in other places, we ought to be able to get through<br />
better and I believe we will;<br />
LAWS: OK. Could I ask you to go this Jar. Do you think it<br />
will be worse or better in six months?<br />
PM: This economy has been growing. The Budget estimates are<br />
that. this economy will grow through this year. I haven't<br />
seen any evidence that. would suggest, you know, that<br />
those Budget estimates, and -they are-not cynical estimates,<br />
they are put down by Treasury on the basis of their<br />
projections.<br />
LAWS: Yes.<br />
PM: I haven't seen any evidence that suggests that. those<br />
estimates of growth in this economy are off track. </p>
<p>Page 3<br />
o the situation sbouldn't worsen,<br />
PM: -I don't believe so.<br />
LAWS: ON~. AThut.' s going to happen over this sales tax question<br />
In the Senate? what.' s the Constitutional posit-ion<br />
ithe legislation-continues to be blocked by the Senate?<br />
Ithat happens then?<br />
SLAWS: A second rejection, on all the ) egal advice that I've<br />
been given from the Attorney-General and quotitig<br />
autlhorities going back for forty years, does constitute<br />
a rejef,-tIon. Now I. wIll be Interesting t~ o see if, In<br />
spite of the letters thbey've signed, the Demiocrats will<br />
In fact. reject thc measures. It. wIll also be Interesting<br />
to see, in spite of everything the Labor Party hoa said<br />
about blocking Supply and Money B1116, whether they are<br />
prepared t~ o participate in ft rejection because that is<br />
totailly against their pbilosophy in terms of the. use<br />
of the powers ol thbe Senate.<br />
' 1Jat's right.<br />
We've always said$ on our part, that if the situation was<br />
serious enough that. those Senate powers are there and<br />
could be uised but the Labor Party As not. trying t~ o say<br />
t. hat.-there's t-hat kind of serious situation. They are<br />
just tmking a totally expedient and in view ol' their<br />
past attitudes, as I would believe totally hypocritical<br />
" ttitudes, if they, you know, tAke an action which does<br />
constitute a rejection of the measures.<br />
LAWS: Ok. Now I-or the people who don't understand it<br />
Const-itutionally, aDd. I'n -one of them, would that. then<br />
Aprov'Ide grounds for a double dissolution?<br />
N0. M For a double dissolution yould'have to have a<br />
rejection ' twice _ spread out over a -three month preiod but<br />
1 -think a lot -of * wat er has flowed tinder the bridge over the next<br />
Ye ; ew ee) s and. whi). e ere. determied to. get , the mneasures:<br />
hruhad eieewe wil get th. e measureas thrig<br />
1don', t' tb Ink; w6' wt talk o f double, -dis solutioxis'gol ng'<br />
oround thbe place because.<br />
LAWS: Well you-, vouldn't want . one anyway,. -would you?<br />
PM: : I ' m quite sure . hat the people' fit. ime Want uB to<br />
eton with the business. of governing.. That's<br />
pcslywat -we Intend to do.<br />
LAWS: It'd just be a nuisance wouldn't it. : It wouid just waste<br />
more * time and w~ ore money.-<br />
PM: *. It would be 6 diversion and It would be unnecessary aad..<br />
we are going to get , on with the business of VovernIng.-</p>
<p>Page 4<br />
* LAXS: Aire You ever going to consider backing off on sales<br />
tax on items like building materials apt) I footwear if<br />
you do find yourselves In a corner?<br />
PM: Look, I believe we'll get. the. se mensures throiugh the<br />
8~ nteI reailly do.<br />
LAW~ S: You're that confident?<br />
I ' M: Yes.<br />
LAWS: M~ any people are saying that those particular ones, and<br />
I remember mentioned them t~ o you the day Filter the<br />
B~ udget, the building material on, I thought that. Was a<br />
bit tough for young people At's tough enough trying t~ o<br />
buy a house now anyway without that additional sales<br />
-tax on those materials. B~ ut that.' s the only one I<br />
questioned actually.<br />
0AW1: Well I can understand your reasons for that but<br />
again, we wanted to take an-Initial step or a modest<br />
step might be'a better way of putting it, t~ o broaden<br />
-the Indirect tax base and to put uis In an enhnced<br />
position for income tax reductions at, a later point. and<br />
also I think It.' s worth noting that while the additional<br />
tax is collec * ted and this year a very few bundred<br />
additional million dollars,* the real Increase In average<br />
. eurnings'last year* put 2.7 billion dollars Into tbe<br />
pockets of Australian families and thbat was after<br />
tax and I think t. hat does put it.. into., you know, a little<br />
bit of perspective. There waS.' a very big Increase In<br />
-real earnings last year for, wost. Australian families and<br />
. the additional sales tax Is-a very . small part of t~ hat.<br />
I do recogDise the ' difficulty of people'starting'Out and<br />
trying to meet home. interest, repayments but the real way<br />
to solve'that problem Is to'try'and collect policiesthat<br />
will ' r'e duce pressure oninhterest'rIates find get<br />
-t~ o the source of the difficulty.<br />
The new arms dealb '$ 2,000 million, thatt's the biggest.<br />
In Australia's history. Obviously you feel it's&amp;<br />
necessary. Wby--is it necessary?<br />
PH: Australia-has got -to have It's own Independent defence<br />
capacity. and . by the' standards of many countrI es we spend.<br />
* a mhodest. amount on Def once.*: It Is a little less thban 3.<br />
percent of , eyerything we produce although present. projections<br />
WA l1 bulId it. up to that. and i t' n A * mal I f orce, smallI<br />
in numbers, and that.' s one o f the reasons why you need<br />
mjo dern, highly sophist-icated and harder hitting equipment-<br />
7whether it. s$ for the Airforce, thbe Army or the Navy and-*.<br />
.1 suppose In F slense you uke up for. l ack of numbers<br />
j itR sure. that your own people:# re very well1'<br />
eqlpedindeedi -We ' N" e taksen ak-very long while tormak6<br />
w'tbi9-decisioniakd -fle eilbIBdga atiat~"..<br />
-~ jater today ' About it. and hink that ~ our own..: Airfofte<br />
andp r~ efoencnee lhav realy~ o through. the whole<br />
process -with ebnormous care'.'--It is'a~ vastl) y. eXpensive<br />
decision but -thrt-i1s. spread,-obverpa -considerable period. </p>
<p>P'age<br />
It's a sum that has been allowed for in forward Detence<br />
* planning for a number of years, ItIs j~ ot, you Unow,<br />
In addition to, the current basis and whatever, It's<br />
allowed In the program and I'm very glad that. we have In<br />
fact got to a position to be able t~ o make a decision.<br />
LAW~ S:. Are you.* getting any grizzles from the Opposition about It?<br />
TIM: Aircraft sn'lesmen I suppose are very, you know, thbey press<br />
their views very, v'ery strongly indeed but what we need<br />
to ( 10 in these circumstances is to rely on thbe expertise<br />
iind the advice In our owl) defence establishments and thbe<br />
airlorce because they really have built up a very great<br />
capacity aniJcIt's worth noting that in buying new<br />
Eircraft the purchases of the Australian aircraft. has<br />
quite a relevance t~ o other purchases In different places<br />
around the world. They'know the expertise of the Royal<br />
Australian Airforce and there are other places where they<br />
watch that and say, you know, what's the decisions those<br />
D ~~ hatevAer ustralian-pse oaprlee msaayk infrgo. m tShoe wlhoastienvge r cttehderI grizzles Pthrein kand<br />
W we just need t~ o stick, well I ' m sure we just need to<br />
stick withi our own advice on these particular matters.<br />
LAWS: Yes, well your own advice obviously says you should be<br />
buying themn IcDonel -Doug) as F38.<br />
PH: Well that'Is what Jim Killen Is going to be saying. You<br />
know.-be's going to be saying one. way or the other<br />
l1ater on in the day although newspapers ' this morning all<br />
seem to have their * particular view but. you'll have to wait<br />
' till1 Jim Killen speaks to see whether tbe newspapers have<br />
jumped. the rIght way or the wrong way.*<br />
-AS; Y'eIts. w ould appear that General Dynamics aren'<br />
g oing to take It lyi~ ng on. I was reading thbe paper<br />
c-rgrlier t * is ' morning,,, In the. Aust-ralian t-hey have a large<br />
* advertisement giving us a number of good reasons why w<br />
o boul-d buy the P16 as' opposed to the<br />
wi: Whoever, let. me put It that. way because I'mn not going<br />
t~ o pre-emnpt tbe Defence Minister, Whoever is the loser<br />
in this contest will be very well advised to take it.<br />
with good grace. They really would. Because once a<br />
obvernmet. has made a -decision for an aircraft<br />
c.:, orporation and a multi-national company to try and whip<br />
-: up pressure against that. decision is-not behavIng In a<br />
-particularly decent way. It's not behaving In a way that<br />
would win any respect whatsoever-and I ' ye got to say<br />
that 1. don't appre: iate and have not responded to . the<br />
last minute press~ ure. of' whi ch some ' members of major<br />
corporations have sought to put. on me.<br />
LAWS: Yes wvell they've certilanly put the pressure on, haven't<br />
they? </p>
<p>Page 6<br />
PM-: Ifell they've sought to and I haven't responded to It<br />
and. I don't, Intend to0 In any sense. But _ you know,' that<br />
Wind of pressure is something that Governments should<br />
% yellh. ave In mind when they are making purchases in the<br />
future b) ecause It's for Government. to make the decision<br />
bnd if the corporation happens to lose out well then so<br />
be It. They've lost that one and they should accept it.<br />
LAWS: Yes but you know the nature of the Am~ erican saletsman<br />
ks well as J do. They are hotshots when it comes to<br />
selling find they really stop at. nothing ( 10 they?<br />
1114 Well I-think that's probably true but maybe. they'll ' think<br />
twice i1f they only learn thbat that In getting their<br />
corpora-tion a very. you know, once t. e aeIeiini<br />
whichever. way R decision goes, if. the losing contender<br />
then tries to continue to pressure . and-all the rest the<br />
only result of that will be to damage. the name and the<br />
reputation of that corporation In this country, with<br />
t-he-Government., wvith-, the Airforce and w* ith the Australian<br />
J) ubl Ac.<br />
LAIWS: Did you have a look at the editorial in the hustralian<br />
this morning by any chance our davzling sti<br />
perlormance. I would think you'd be aware of the figures.-<br />
Thbe Australian * shipping Industry' has lost somne $ 600<br />
mil Ion through strikes In the past three months.<br />
P) 4, The'. Astralian shpigindustry,, and the strikes involved<br />
inl it$ for a variety' of reasons, the records an appalling<br />
one,-<br />
LAUS: Yes It really is, : We ' re responsible for 53.45 percent<br />
of t-he tot'a'l st rikes onthe world waterfronts and'our<br />
closest challenger I$ Sween' That.' comes In with 312.<br />
percent and, Britain Is copping such criticism these days,,':<br />
isa in third place with 8 percent and we're leading wt<br />
5345. I t'snot good Is .1t?<br />
:-elIf the figure'i right, well whatever thbe figures right,<br />
our record on the waterfrolnt Is not good but, you know,<br />
th'ere has been ft variety of. reasons; There was'a marine<br />
engineers di spute, they have been condtinuing Problems<br />
wlt h coal loaders in Nlew South Wales.-and one. of the.<br />
tregedies is that. while otit overall:. trike xecord " As<br />
about the same.* as the United States alhubIthink<br />
we make much more. of a fuss of it. tan they do, a large<br />
Part of It is in sensitive.. areas which are evident and-..<br />
obvious to our trading partners. In the resource'Andusti-ies,.<br />
on the waterfront. In shipping, and thieref ore*, -you, know,<br />
overall our. position Is the same as m6any other. countries<br />
and it. isa more ' obvIous and -that.' s not -good. Itsbad' 7<br />
for Australia'~ s reputat-ion and, you k~ now, therels one<br />
vecry simple message that f wi sh we could g'et tbrought<br />
. trade union. leaders and, it they could only sbow some<br />
concern fur people. who are out, of. work and show-greater<br />
concern for Itustrlala's trading reputation find whether<br />
-it's in terms of . demanding Increased. wages or Improved...-.<br />
conditions or -just.* sheer' di sruption'. if they could haive in<br />
mind that every time they undertake that kind of activity </p>
<p>Page 7<br />
t hey are making it. harder to reduce the number of people..<br />
w-% ho are, In fact,* out of work.<br />
LAWS: Do you think tbey% really care?<br />
PU11: I think a n~ umber of them don't care..<br />
LAWS: I'm Quite sure they don't..<br />
PM: A lot o1 them wouldn't care ifthey'thougbt. about It,<br />
But then translating'theory. into action is quite ftnother<br />
matter,<br />
LO1S: I mean even tbose who are totally In sympathy with the<br />
labour movement must really shrug thbeir shoulders when<br />
they bear figures like that, I mean we must really<br />
wonerwhether the Australian maritime unions care<br />
whether thbeir f ellow countrymen prosper or whether they<br />
don't prosper.<br />
9P*..,. some union leadership Just doesn'* t care at all. They<br />
cttotally selfishly and their own Immcediate interests<br />
Is fill that they ' cin see but again the " union is made<br />
up of a generality of Australia ' ns and Australian * families<br />
and if they' and their families or wives If wives were<br />
allowed toc have a vote on strikes<br />
LAWS: The situation would be very different. wouldn't<br />
yPM: I thinkc the situation would be vastly different.<br />
LAWS., Yes It sure would. lell thbank you very much for your time,<br />
It's been good to talk to you. We've covered a bit. of<br />
-ground there., Ie won't talk about the leadership. It<br />
seems to have died down,<br />
IM:."~ lthnkt~ ees ojav fied down butan yay. ev-en if i<br />
LA8 OR, Well Int lb f area We111 talk to you<br />
very soon. . Thank6 . very mu. h . fo r your., time, Prime Minister,<br />
To: PH IME 14JdIUBTER' 8 PRIESS OFIFCE<br />
' ROM: FID118 OFFICE,' 8D~ 1Y </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
