<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9906</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP QUESTION AND ANSWER SESSION FOLLOWING THE SINGAPORE LECTURE - &quot;AUSTRALIA, ASIA AND THE NEW REGIONALISM&quot;, SINGAPORE, 17 JANUARY 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009906.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
QUESTION A ND ANSWER SESSION FOLLOWING THE SINGAPORE<br />
LECTURE " AUSTRALIA, ASIA AND THE NEW REGIONALISM",<br />
SINGAPORE, 17 JANUARY 1996<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Q: Mr Keating, my question is in two parts. First, Australia has spent a<br />
great deal of time and effort on multilateral security initiatives.<br />
What has prompted the sudden desire to engage in bilateral security<br />
arrangements with Indonesia? On that note, considering Indonesia's<br />
traditional reluctance to sign security treaties, what in your opinion has<br />
motivated Indonesia to accede to the Austral ia-Indonesia Agreement<br />
on Maintaining Security?<br />
PM: I don't think it is accurate to describe Australia's interests in security<br />
arrangements as simply multilateral.* In fact, its c~ rntral security<br />
arrangement has been bilateral and that is, of course, the<br />
ANZUS Treaty between Australia and the United States. We have had<br />
other mulilateral treaties and have them. The Five Power Defence<br />
Arrangements, of course, in this context springs immediately to mind.<br />
But the Five Power Defence Arrangements themselves reflect, in part,<br />
the history of the confrontation period and now the years have gone<br />
by, ASEAN has come, regional cooperation in South East Asia is now<br />
the norm, and yet Australia was a party to and remains a party to and<br />
has affirmed this very day, its commitment to the Five Power Defence<br />
Arrangements. Yet the period of confrontation brought many<br />
suspicions to Australia about Indonesian intentions as they brought<br />
those same suspicions, very obviously, to Singapore and Malaysia.<br />
As a consequence, the relationship which Australia had with Indonesia<br />
from its founding in 1946, where we were the first country to recognise<br />
its independence, who took a leading role in the United Nations in ' its<br />
independence, and who claimed proudly some very direct and<br />
influential association in the birth of its independence, this confidence<br />
and friendship was muted over the years as a result of events in the </p>
<p>1 960s and because of Timor and other things in more modem times.<br />
Yet the event of greatest positive strategic significance to Australia in<br />
the post-war years was the election of President Soeharto's new order<br />
government. So it seemed to me and to my government that we should make clear<br />
that we regard the government of Indonesia and Indonesia as an<br />
influence of positive strategic significance to Australia and that we do<br />
not hold Indonesia in suspicion, that we accept its statements that it<br />
has no territorial ambitions in conflict with Australia and I am sure<br />
President Soeharto accepts my declaration that we have no territorial<br />
ambitions towards Indonesia.<br />
Therefore, we are neighbours locked together by geography and,<br />
in some respects, by a very happy history surrounding the birth of their<br />
country. And we thought the time was right to make that declaration to<br />
declare our friendship, to banish forever any lingering suspicions and<br />
I believe the best way of doing that was to say that we share a<br />
common regional perspective and that we share a common<br />
perspective on matters of security and that we should engage one<br />
another on that subject. These are all the elements of the treaty.<br />
The second part of your question was, why did Indonesia agree to the<br />
treaty when it has a history of non-alignment? I think it is for this<br />
reason that Indonesia does regard Australia in a friendly way, that<br />
making such an arrangement, or declaring such an arrangement,<br />
between countries in friendship, doesn't offend any non-aligned<br />
principle, and there was also the whole issue of the * rength of our<br />
position Australia is an island continent, as I remarked vin my address.<br />
We are in the fortunate position of sharing a border with no one.<br />
We are the only nation on earth with a continent to ourselves and our<br />
nearest neighbour is a nation of 200 million and I believe the largest<br />
archipelago in the world.<br />
There are very large strategic issues to be considered always in that<br />
kind of geographic environment. So I think on the basis of friendship<br />
of a common view, of the things we are doing bilaterally and<br />
multilaterally, and also in juxtaposition to the Five Power Defence<br />
Arrangements it gave the region more solidity and more security and<br />
more confidence for Australia to make this arrangement with Indonesia<br />
and I believe Indonesia thought that too.<br />
Q: I would like to ask Mr Keating two very simple questions. One, you<br />
make constant reference to the region. As Australia's Prime Minister,<br />
what is the geographical boundary of this region you are referring to.<br />
Two, you are a very strong advocate and, of course, initiator of APEC.<br />
Yet, in your lecture on regionalism, you are singularly silent on the<br />
EAEC Dr Mahathir's proposal as well as on the Indian Ocean<br />
Association. In the case of the EAEC, I understand many Australians </p>
<p>are adversary. But in the case of the Indian Ocean Association,<br />
I understand that many Australians are strong advocates. Could<br />
I have your views please, thank you?<br />
PM: Well, I think, there will be all sorts of definitions of the region.<br />
I mentioned in my speech my Foreign Ministers definition, which is the<br />
East Asia hemisphere. That is that slice of the orange which takes you<br />
down through East Asia and through Australasia. But while that may<br />
describe the' East Asia hemisphere, or perhaps you could call it, too,<br />
the Pacific Rim depending on how large a slice you take. One thing<br />
we are all clear about, I think, and that is that it is good for us to have<br />
the largest economy and the largest liberal democracy in the world<br />
economically and strategically engaged in East Asia and that is the<br />
United States. And the United States strategic protection of Japan and<br />
Korea, which is embodied in their treaties, remains more convincing to<br />
everyone in the region if it is underpinned by a higher level of United<br />
States economic engagement.<br />
This is, perhaps, the distinguishing feature between the EAEC<br />
proposal and APEC. And it is also the fact that the United States<br />
represents the largest market for the greater number of the developing<br />
countries of East Asia. So it is the largest market and it is the largest<br />
strategic power and the largest strategic influence.<br />
So APEC, as distinct from East Asia, includes of course the United<br />
States which has a boundary on the Pacific Ocean. So it is a<br />
trans-Pacific body and, I think, that is the distinguishing feature<br />
between the two.<br />
As for the Indian Ocean, I think some good may come from some<br />
clarity about common interests in -Indian Ocean trade patterns and<br />
trading trends, or even trading facilities. But I don't see the<br />
Indian Ocean as being part of APEC or the APEC region, which is<br />
distinguished by the coincidence of its trade sinews and its strategic<br />
alliances. The Indian Ocean is altogether different.<br />
Q: Mr Prime Minister, this security treaty that Australia has signed with<br />
Indonesia is it a bilateral confidence building expression, or is it a<br />
concrete defence arrangement whereby if Indonesia feels threatened<br />
in the matter of the Spratley Islands Australia will have to respond to<br />
this challenge?<br />
PM: You should be writing for an Australian newspaper. No, it is not a<br />
security pact. It is a treaty about maintaining security and adverse<br />
challenges to what we perceive to be our mutual security. And those<br />
challenges may be military, but more likely not and therefore we would<br />
discuss with one another how we would respond to those challenges.<br />
They could be environmental, they could be in all manner of fields.<br />
But the fact of the matter is that it is above everything else a </p>
<p>declaration of the trust between us, in a statement that we do see<br />
ourselves having a common strategic outlook and common strategic<br />
interests, and that we are prepared to consult and discuss them<br />
whenever they are challenged. That is what it is.<br />
Q: Mr Keating, could you please give a definitive definition of APEC's<br />
commitment to open regionalism? Does this mean that APEC would<br />
extend its free trade obligations to others on a reciprocal basis, on a<br />
unilateral MFN basis, does it mean the simultaneous lowering of its<br />
barriers to its non-members as it lowers its barriers to its members?<br />
PM: Well you might recall I said in my address that one of the rules should<br />
be that we don't close the Asia-Pacific area off, that we don't get<br />
complacent about it, that we are not smug about it were we to keep it<br />
growing, and that we should engage with the rest of the world and<br />
I extol the virtues of the WTO and the multilateral trading<br />
arrangements that came from the Uruguay Round. That is the position<br />
I hold fairly firmly.<br />
The other thing is that Australia did some substantial economic<br />
modelling on APEC to examine who received the greater benefits and<br />
the berfefits total, we believe, up to the region of US$ 1 trillion of<br />
additional wealth from the APEC reforms. That is the Australian and<br />
Korean economies together in additional value and, obviously, some<br />
countries will secure more of that trillion of benefit than others.<br />
But one thing that the study did reveal is that there is a very minimal<br />
free rider effect from countries outside the Asia-Pacific.<br />
In other words, the notion that the European Union, for instance, would<br />
in some way be a free rider on the reforms in APEC were not really<br />
borne out by the study, which only reinforces in my mind the view that<br />
the issue of whether APEC is a preferential or MFN area is really not<br />
much of an issue at all. And, even if we were to make it a preferential<br />
area, and under the GATT rules it was a free trade area, each<br />
individual country could independently decide whether it wanted to<br />
extend the preference anyway.<br />
I think more likely we will all decide that we do want it to be an open<br />
system. But, of course, this is a matter of debate in the United States<br />
and I think if the United States is convinced that there is no free rider<br />
effect, but a much more harmonious world effect, they would probably<br />
share the view that I would take and I suspect your Prime Minister<br />
takes about where we see APEC and free arrangements in the<br />
Pacific going.<br />
Q: It is quite clear that economically and geopolitically Australia is part of<br />
Asia. Yet, historically and culturally it has been affiliated with the<br />
Anglo-Saxon world. To what extent do you see this as a hindrance or<br />
a handicap on your efforts at integrating within Asia? </p>
<p>PM: I don't see it as a hindrance or a handicap. The point I made in the<br />
speech is Australia is unique. I mean Australia is unique in many<br />
ways. For a start I mean as a nation, let me repeat the point, we share<br />
a border with nobody. The continent is old it is geologically old.<br />
Australia is a very old place. Evidenced, in part, by the fact that the<br />
indigenous civilisation had been there for 40,000 years.<br />
The important thing for Australians of European origin, or Asian origin,<br />
is that they understand that it is imperative that to become part of the<br />
region, let's call it that rather than Asia the region it has to come to<br />
terms, first, with its own indigenes, so that we are at peace with<br />
ourselves, that we move together, forward, as a nation, and that the<br />
tolerance and diversity I mentioned in the text is the defining quality<br />
that marks out the Australian nation as a unique nation.<br />
If it is unique, therefore, why would it want to be Asian. I mean it would<br />
have a crisis of confidence if it wanted to be anything other than what it<br />
is. And whatever else Australia has, it has no crisis of confidence.<br />
What we want to be is part of the region. We don't want to be Asian,<br />
though'of course over half of our intake in migration now comes from<br />
Asia and the culture of Asia is having a very large impact within<br />
Australia and upon Australia. But the fact that 75 per cent of our<br />
exports go to the Asia-Pacific area, already I think underlines that we<br />
are integrated with the region and that is what we want to be.<br />
As I said, it would be foolish for us to describe ourselves as Asians<br />
because we are not./<br />
Whether we are part of Asia, or the Asia-Pacific, is a debating point.<br />
Whether we are part of the East Asian hemisphere, or that slice of the<br />
orange, is another debating point. But we are not European, as I said,<br />
we are not African we are Australians and I believe we can play not<br />
just an active role in this region, but a very constructive and supportive<br />
role which will enhance the quality of life for people in the region<br />
Asian people in the region as well as people who have come from<br />
Europe.<br />
Q: Mr Prime Minister, sir, you have made it very clear that Australia is<br />
not Asian, but you have also told us that you are in the " others"<br />
category and it's a bit difficult to be one country in a single category.<br />
I would like to invite your comments on a possible grouping, which is<br />
not Asian, but Oceania, which could include New Zealand and the<br />
other islands around Australia and New Zealand and the region. I<br />
would like to invite your comments, on this as a possible grouping,<br />
and with the Chairman's indulgence, a related question what are<br />
your comments on an Asia Oceania community? </p>
<p>PM: Well, I'm not sure I am the one to decipher or divine the ways of the<br />
United Nations, in that mirror-maze and mish-mash of interests, who<br />
am I to say what grouping we should belong to. But let me make this<br />
point it doesn't overly exercise our mind. We are engaged with the<br />
region, and we're playing that role, I think, conscientiously, because<br />
we are here, we live here and we want to be with our neighbours.<br />
Our principal focus is with our neighbours, and it seems incongruous<br />
to us, that we are with Europeans and others, but I can assure you<br />
that we are not wandering around saying where are we? Because, it<br />
is no burden to inherit a continent, and when they were giving them<br />
out, not too many people got one. And when you got one, you don't<br />
wonder about it, you just be grateful for it.<br />
Q: My question is about human rights how do you see, Mr Keating, the<br />
role of regional organisations, and particularly APEC which is the one<br />
regional organisation Australia is part of, in promoting dialogue about<br />
human rights? What we mean by human rights, I guess, is another<br />
question.<br />
PM: Well, I think it is another question for many people. I made the point<br />
in the* speech that Australia is one of the oldest democracies in the<br />
world~ You know, we had universal suffrage, secret ballots, before<br />
the United Kingdom for instance. Egalitarianism and equity have<br />
mattered in our country, and the rights of individuals have mattered.<br />
And I think the reason for Australian tolerance of a very multicultural<br />
population, or the degree of tolerance within that population, comes<br />
from the deep sense of democracy which Australia has. That sense<br />
of democracy gives everybody a lot of intellectua) -space, and<br />
therefore, human rights, and the liberties, and all the issues of the<br />
social contract have always been in our mind, and they always will<br />
be. But that's not to say that we can impose our values on others, but<br />
we know and we invariably, whenever we think human rights have<br />
been violated, we say so. And when they are perpetually or<br />
consistently violated, we keep on saying so. But I think we know the<br />
dialogue of the answer, and that economic growth and prosperity<br />
generally will liberate many societies or individuals oppressed in<br />
this way. And it is impossible to grow economies and societies<br />
without growing their politics as well it's not possible to liberate<br />
them, and yet constrain liberty, freedom and the mind. So, in the<br />
quest for economic growth and prosperity, these things have been<br />
great liberalising forces in breaking down ideology and lifting<br />
opportunities, and with it one hopes a premium on human rights<br />
and good values. These are the things we have been supporting, as<br />
well as forthrightly putting a view whenever we think those human<br />
rights are violated.<br />
But I am often asked is the Australian sense of democracy and liberty<br />
a handicap in dealing with Asia, and I never believe that it is,<br />
because I think Australia can contribute a lot to the region. It is a </p>
<p>very democratic state, and people's liberties are very obviously clear,<br />
and taking that sort of inheritance, and tradition, to the region, I think<br />
must be a good thing.<br />
Q: Recently, the Prime Minister's of Thailand and Vietnam met in Hanoi<br />
and they said that a way to keep peace in the region is to have the<br />
region of South-East Asia is to have a defence alliance in the<br />
region. May we have your views regarding what are Australia's views<br />
towards such a proposal? And whether Australia will participate if<br />
such a proposal is endorsed by the whole region?<br />
PM: Well, I think I didn't know of this, but you have informed me this has<br />
happened. But let me say that I think that a commitment to security<br />
and respect for the affairs of others is a good thing a web of<br />
declarations saying so is, I think, a good thing. And if you look at just<br />
the discussion we have had in these last few minutes, about this<br />
declaration between Australia and Indonesia. The affirmation today<br />
between our two Governments here, about our arrangements. The<br />
discussions I have just-had with Prime Minister Mahathir around<br />
some of the same subjects, with his country a member of the Five<br />
Power Defence Arrangements. I mean, that constitutes something of<br />
a welS. And whether the web moves through Thailand and Indo-<br />
China, I guess is a matter for those countries. The main thing is, I<br />
think, that none of this should be discerned as in any way a policy<br />
either seeking to contain China, or needing to. Because as I made<br />
clear in my remarks, I don't believe China is an expansionist power<br />
it is a country focussed on its internal development, and we should be<br />
doing everything to fully engage it, and to co operativey, bring it into<br />
the world. That's the way to respond to China.<br />
But again, China, or Vietnam, or Thailand, or Indonesia, or Australia,<br />
or Singapore are entitled to make prudent arrangements, or to have<br />
prudent structures, that have an eye to their security. And I think the<br />
security of one's people is the first duty of any government. So, I<br />
don't have any problem with this at all, and this general commitment<br />
to a stable situation and respect for others is the kind of healthiness I<br />
think we have always wanted to see.<br />
Q: Mr Prime Minister, in your talk this afternoon you touched briefly on<br />
China, but one issue that you have missed out is the China Taiwan<br />
relationship. Now, I have two questions, if you don't mind Mr<br />
Chairman?<br />
C: Well, keep them short.<br />
Q: Okay. First question is Mr Prime Minister what is your position on<br />
this issue, and second question is, in the likelihood of a flare-up<br />
across the Taiwan Straits, and as Australia becomes an increasingly </p>
<p>significant player in the Asia-Pacific region, what do you think the role<br />
of Australia would be?<br />
PM: Well, Taiwan is a competent economy a highly developed,<br />
competent economy, as is Hong Kong. One of the points I made<br />
earlier about APEC is, I mentioned this point about flexibility within<br />
regional structures, in the context of inflexibility in the bi-polarity of<br />
global arrangements. Remember I made the point about Afghanistan<br />
and Angola? how they were dressed up as being regional issues, they<br />
were really global ones. They were sub-sumed into the global<br />
discussion the bi-polarity that existed in the Cold War. What we are<br />
seeing in regional arrangements here, say, with ASEAN, with APEC<br />
and particularly you can see it in APEC is that you have got China<br />
sitting there with Hong Kong and Taiwan represented there. So there<br />
is, indeed the point I was making is there is flexibility. You can get<br />
flexibility into regional arrangements you mightn't be able to get into<br />
global arrangements. Now, Taiwan operates as a competent,<br />
effective economy, but we accept China's view about Taiwan's status.<br />
We also accept the fact that China is going to have a number.. there<br />
are going to be a number of Chinese economies Hong Kong will<br />
remain one, Taiwan will remain one, and there will be parts of China<br />
growing at different rates than other parts, and we may see<br />
discernible parts of China be more prosperous than others I think<br />
we are already seeing that. In other words, the development of subregional<br />
economies in China. Now, I don't have any problem with<br />
that, but I do have a problem with Taiwan having, say, government<br />
status head of government, leadership level within APEC. So, our<br />
position on this is pretty clear it has always been clear,<br />
Q: Prime Minister Keating, despite any number of treaties that countries<br />
may have, either unilateral, bilateral or multilateral, it's only when<br />
push comes to shove effectively, when there is war that the<br />
commitment to these treaties is tested out. But particularly at that<br />
time, it seems to be the world security council that has a bigger say in<br />
things than anyone else. What in your view Mr Keating, rather, what<br />
is your view, of the present constitution of the present world security<br />
council, and how if at all could it be changed to better serve the<br />
interests of everyone concerned?<br />
PM: Well, reform in the United Nations is a very big subject and there are<br />
people more specialist and more have more specialist views about it<br />
than I. Indeed, my Foreign Minister has written a book on it. So, I am<br />
not game to say too much about it other than repeat what I said in my<br />
remarks. When the second largest economy and the third largest<br />
economy in the world are not part of the governing structure of security<br />
we have an immature structure. It is 50 years now since the war in the<br />
Pacific and the war in Europe and the time has come, I think, for Japan<br />
and Germany to take their proper place in these forums. I think that<br />
would do much to improve the security council. As to its broader </p>
<p>charter I don't know. At this point, I think, you could say that for<br />
whatever reason the United Nations has not garnered, not drawn to it,<br />
not drawn down the national authorities one might have expected it to<br />
have been able to draw down when the Berlin Wall came down in the<br />
post Cold War period. This hasn't happened.<br />
That is why I believe that a far superior way of dealing with problems is<br />
to eliminate them at their source. One of the ways we are doing that<br />
here is we are co-operating together. I talked about the sense of<br />
fellow feeling and good will at APEC meetings when the Leaders sit<br />
down. The chemistry of the meetings is quite interesting. There are<br />
18 leaders without officials and they all now know one another well.<br />
They have bilateral meetings, they have occasional casual meetings,<br />
they have a good feeling together and they know they are co-operating<br />
in a bigger undertaking in opening up their economies and lifting<br />
prosperity. This is a much better way of dealing with problems than<br />
relying on some structure within the United Nations, no matter how<br />
modem or how adaptive it might be.<br />
Q: Mr Prime Minister, I am curious as to what you consider to be a priority<br />
in as far as the progressive equation of Australia goes risk<br />
management or opportunity seizing and I am curious as to how you<br />
feel your recent relations in the region may have helped one cause<br />
or the other?<br />
PM: I think that the primary one is opportunity seizing as you put it. The<br />
way to keep east Asia growing is to keep it properly resourced. It<br />
won't keep properly resourced unless the avenues, of resource<br />
availability are open and the impediments are taken away. Be it tariffs<br />
or non-tariff barriers or other traditional policies. These are the things,<br />
I think, the efficient commitment of resources of the region to our<br />
respective economies is the way to best guarantee that the east Asia<br />
growth phase continues. That is what, essentially, APEC, is about. It<br />
is essentially what a lot of Australian foreign policy is about, it is a lot<br />
of what our bilateral relations are about. How we create better trade<br />
and investment opportunities, how we create a climate of confidence<br />
and in doing that how the region then prospers. In a prospering region<br />
these questions about risk management become much less important.<br />
Compare your own country or Malaysia with 30 years ago. Look at the<br />
attendant risks then and now and what has been the intervening<br />
influence. It has been economic growth. But, you.. won't get economic<br />
growth, many countries don't have resources or adequate resources or<br />
they don't have skills or they don't have other things. What I am trying<br />
to do, what I think your Prime Minister is trying to do, I think what all of<br />
us in the region are trying to do is open the flows, to let the flows<br />
happen naturally and to keep the growth phase continuing. And in that<br />
way, we all seize the opportunities and the emphasis on risks then<br />
become very greatly diminished. </p>
<p>Q: Mr Keating, you mentioned earlier your opinion as to who should be<br />
the new members of the Security Council of the United Nations. Now,<br />
this debate on the increased membership of the United Nations has<br />
been going on for years and years. The problem is the cost, there are<br />
far too many members in the United Nations and each continent is<br />
advancing their own members. Now, don't you think it would be better<br />
to have an agreed criteria, of course, the important word is agreed and<br />
that would be a problem of course, an agreed criteria on which<br />
members could be appointed.<br />
PM: The United Nations exists on the principle of universality, I think. And<br />
it was the great attempt in the post war years to develop a new order of<br />
collective security and that had to be representative of the growth of<br />
nations. As people threw off their colonial yoke and took their<br />
independent status, obviously the numbers within the United Nations<br />
have grown. I don't think that is what has made it ineffective. Any<br />
argument about its effectiveness was probably overshadowed by the<br />
influence of the cold war and the bi-polarity of those two powerful<br />
nations the United States and the Soviet Union. That is not to say<br />
there isn't a place for a healthy debate about the future shape of the<br />
United Pations or how it can work effectively. All I am saying is that<br />
the second and third largest economic power should certainly be in the<br />
business of the Security Council. What I am not saying here is what<br />
the design of some of these instruments should be. What I am saying<br />
is that regional arrangements and regional solutions are going to be<br />
more important and can be very effective. I made the point in this<br />
region, the arrangements are between developing and developed<br />
countries. There is no hierarchy. If you look at ouj -multi-lateral<br />
bodies, be it ASEAN or APEC, there is no hierarchy. The developing<br />
countries, indeed look at the Bogor Declaration that came from one of<br />
the largest developing countries in the area.<br />
So, regional bodies can do good and effective things and I think where<br />
many regional problems in the past have been glossed over or<br />
papered over by the bi-polarity which has existed, the tensions are<br />
now coming to the fore and they are best, I think, dealt with regionally.<br />
If they spill over, they may spill over to the UN, but I think there are<br />
other solutions to the world's problems, other than the UN, despite the<br />
fact that the UN remains a very useful body.<br />
Q: Mr Keating, I would like to ask you about exchange rates, they have<br />
not been mentioned at all this afternoon.<br />
PM: You are a punter are you?<br />
Q: A number of impediments have been offered that might stand in the<br />
way of further APEC, Pacific Rim or whatever developments in the next<br />
or even 30 years. European experience suggests that when a<br />
number of other problems have been cleared out of the way, currency </p>
<p>then starts to rise towards the top of the list as being something which<br />
simply stays in the way. Do you feel we might see any kind of<br />
developments on currency harmonisation in this region over the next<br />
or 15 years and perhaps if we do see a regional unit I might dare to<br />
suggest a name for it, the regional unit of course would be called<br />
' ARU'.<br />
PM: [ tape turn] what will happen in these things, but I doubt very much<br />
that any of this would ever be in a position of being able to design<br />
something which provides so-called stability to exchange rates. I<br />
mean, since the days of fixed exchange rates broke down in the 1970s<br />
and we have not got a very large flux of international markets and<br />
flows of funds and where each countries characteristics are different<br />
and where they are assessed differently and where their levels of<br />
wealth and prosperity are different, of course, the value of their<br />
currency will reflect that. And in the reflection of it, it will adjust the<br />
parameters within the economy as well as with the outside of it. So, I<br />
am not one for managed exchange rates. I don't believe in them. All<br />
that happened in the Plaza-Accords which we often heard about in the<br />
1980s was a lucky break at the end of a long period when a correction<br />
was ovbrdue. If. the Plaza Accord partners today sought to do what<br />
they d6~ then, I think, the markets would trample on them. So, if you<br />
run a good country with good policies you can always stand in the<br />
market place and get a fair price on your currency. It might be a bit<br />
overdone some days and a bit underdone on another, but by and<br />
large, the fundamentals will come out and, I think, tricky management<br />
by central bankers trying to pick the rate has been the cause of much<br />
of the world's problems in the post war years. It is a ha~ it-we have all<br />
kicked and, I think, it should stay kicked.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, earlier on you mentioned recently the significant<br />
increase of Asian migrants into Australia. It has been well documented<br />
that this has caused some problem and some Australians have been<br />
rather upset about this trend. Does this worry your government and<br />
will you please comment on what is your government going to do about<br />
that.<br />
PM: I don't want to correct your assumptions in any strident way, but let me<br />
assure you there is very little tension or adverse comment in Australia<br />
about the make up of the migration intake. Half of it now is from Asia<br />
and the settlement of people in Australia is as harmonious now as it<br />
was five years ago or ten years ago or earlier. In fact, I think it is more<br />
harmonious now than perhaps it has ever been. Australia is singularly<br />
devoid of racial problems, be it around Asians or Muslims or any other<br />
categories of persons. By and large it is not an issue there. The issue<br />
in Australia, if there is an issue, is just on a population basis, how large<br />
the migration program should be, not what its composition is. So, I am<br />
very happy to report to you that what may be perceived, perhaps in<br />
some places, maybe here in Singapore, that there is some resentment </p>
<p>if that is the implication of your question about a high proportion of<br />
Asians in the intake, that is not so. I represent a constituency which<br />
has a very cosmopolitan makeup and I have a very good feel of these<br />
issues in Australia. I can assure you that there is almost complete<br />
equanimity about the character of the cosmopolitan makeup of the<br />
country. I think people are very happy with Asian migration to<br />
Australia. It has brought wealth, business experience, diversity,<br />
strength. I think, if there is perhaps one phrase that I could borrow<br />
from that, it'is that many Australians feel that in diversity there is<br />
strength and vitality and interest and that it is no longer really an issue<br />
for us. To manage our country or our society in some exclusive way to<br />
Asia, it is not on and it hasn't been on for 25 years.<br />
ends<br />
CI i L I. i~ i </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
