<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8718</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP LAUNCH OF THE EVALUATION OF ACCESS AND EQUITY REPORT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 10 NOVEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008718.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ. KEATING, MP<br />
LAUNCH OF THE EVALUATION OF ACCESS AND EQUITY' REPORT<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 10 NOVEMBER 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you Neil ( Edwards), Gerry ( Hand), Robert ( Tickncr), other distinguished<br />
guests, ladies and gcntlemen. I am delighted to launch this excellent evaluation of<br />
the Commonwealth's Access and Equity Strategy and the new access and equity<br />
regime. A week or so ago I spoke of extending the -multicxultural agenda to take advantage<br />
of Australia's huge national economic asset rcpresented by our linguistic and<br />
cultural diversity, our so-callcd productive diversity. It is true that while for many<br />
years we have been very proud of ourselves about the way in which we have<br />
created something new in Australia, something dirferent to other countries in the<br />
world, we have settled quite divcrse communities into oiic nation. There is as well<br />
as the great social achievement of that, a very clearly emerging and strong<br />
economic bcrnefit, and that is the capacity to do things around the world by virtue<br />
of the fact that we have a very strong multicultural community in this country. Our<br />
skills, our linguistic skills and our cultural diversity, mean that whencer Australia,<br />
which is now an open trading economy, seeks to approach particular markets or<br />
sections of particular markets there are people in this country familiar with those<br />
markets, those places, those customs, those morays, those languages. We can take<br />
advantage of our productive diversity and build again further on our multicultural<br />
achievement. As far as the Government is concerned, I said a week or so ago that wc are<br />
continuing to build on the firm foundation of multicultural policies based on<br />
assuring accss and equity to programs regardless of ethnic origin. Of course all of </p>
<p>us who are interested in this room know that without fair access to programs we<br />
can't expect all Australians to be able to contribute their best.<br />
The new regime I'm launching today shows our determination to strengthen access<br />
and equity. I must say that whilc we may be talking in these ternms access and<br />
equity I am delighted to see that just a wcck ago we had the American President<br />
elect speaking in their national debate in these terms about access and cquity so<br />
that the people of that country can share in its wealth, have access to what the<br />
United States offers and have equity in terms of the approaches people can take to<br />
it and expect from it.<br />
We have been developing these themes over all of the 1980s, and what I can say<br />
for this Government is in the early part of the 1980s we were standing against the<br />
wind in terms of the prevailing northern hemisphere ideological breeze; that was,<br />
all that mattered was private initiative and private reward. But now where the<br />
breeze has changed and the wind has warmed up, one finds that Australia's view<br />
about such things as fairness and equity in society and programs oftgovernment<br />
which govern for cverybody and seek to help everybody equitably arc becoming<br />
the voguc world wide. So all the more reason and all the more appropriate that we<br />
should be evaluating what we are doing oursclvcs and strengthening our<br />
determination to do things equitably and to demonstrate full access.<br />
The new regime will demonstratc our firm belief that the programs must be fully<br />
available to all Australians regardless of language, race, culture and religion. The<br />
evaluation shows that there has been real progress, but a lot more can be done.<br />
This Government has endorsed the evaluation's recommendations and expects that<br />
all Government agencies will implement them with vigour. The new regime will<br />
be practical and participatory, it will address the real barriers and make sure that<br />
Commonwealth agencies do reach out to all Australians.<br />
These are not just programs in name, but they are programs in reality that actually<br />
do what we say they will do. The agencies of the C-ommonwealth, many of you<br />
here today who administer them, are fervently taking the view that they will reach<br />
to where they are designed to reach and that they'll meet their program objectives.<br />
It gives me very great pleasure to launch both the evaluation and the new regime<br />
and now my colleagues Gerry Hand and Robert Ticker will address you about the<br />
details. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
