<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7088</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER HEBREW UNIVERSITY, JERUSALEM 28 JANUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007088.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
HEBREW UNIVERSITY, JERUSALEM<br />
28 JANUARY 1987<br />
To BE GRANTED THE DEGREE OF DOCTORATE OF PHILOSOPHY HONORIS<br />
CAUSA--BY-T-I-S-GREAT-UN. IVER. SLTY IS__ NE OF THE HIGHEST HONOURS<br />
ISRAEL CAN OFFER, AND I FEEL DEEPLY HUMBLED BY YOUR GENEROSITY.<br />
I i-S NOW NEAR LY SEVENTY -YEARS-SI NCE-THE-UN IVERSI TY-S-TWEVEFOUNDATION<br />
STONES, REPRESENTING THE TWELVE TRIBES OF ISRAEL,<br />
WERE LAID HERE AT MT SCOPUS, SIGNALLING THE START OF THE GREAT<br />
ACADEMIC VENTURE OF HEBREW UNIVERSITY.<br />
BACK IN 1918, THE STATE OF ISRAEL WAS STILL A DREAM, SO THE<br />
DECISION TO LAY THOSE FOUNDATION STONES AND ESTABLISH A<br />
UNIVERSITY FOR THE JEWISH PEOPLE REQUIRED FORESIGHT, PERSISTENCE<br />
AND COURAGE.<br />
IT DOUBTLESS HAD ITS CRITICS THOSE WHO FELT THAT, IN 1918, WITH<br />
SO MUCH ELSE STILL TO DO, A UNIVERSITY WAS NOT NEEDED.<br />
BUT AT THAT FOUNDATION CEREMONY NEARLY SEVEN DECADES AGO,<br />
DR CHAIM WEIZMANN WHO WAS TO BECOME THE FIRST PRESIDENT OF<br />
THE-STATE OF ISRAEL, EXPLAINED WHY . HE BELIEVED-HEBREW UNIVERSITY<br />
WAS SUCH AN IMPORTANT PRIORITY FOR THE TIME. S </p>
<p>" IT IS TRUE THAT GREAT SOCIAL AND POLITICAL PROBLEMS<br />
STILL FACE US AND DEMAND THEIR SOLUTION FROM US",<br />
DR WEIZMANN SAID.<br />
" WE JEWS KNOW, HOWEVER, THAT WHEN OUR MIND IS GIVEN FULL<br />
PLAY, WHEN WE HAVE A CENTRE FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
J-EWI-SH-CONSC-I-OU SNESS--THEN-CG-NC-ID EN-TALLY-WE-ATTAI-N-----<br />
THE FULFILLMENT OF OUR MATERIAL NEEDS".<br />
DR-IEIZMANNSS' WORDS IMPLIED A SYMBIOSIS EXISTED BETWEEN THIS<br />
INSTITUTION AND THE WHOLE JEWISH PEOPLE. AND LOOKING BACK<br />
OVER THE LONG AND SUCCESSFUL HISTORY OF THE UNIVERSITY WHO CAN<br />
GAINSAY HIS VISION?<br />
THE GROWTH OF HEBREW UNIVERSITY HAS INDEED EXEMPLIFIED MUCH<br />
THAT IS SO GREAT AND MUCH THAT IS SO TRAGIC ABOUT THE STRUGGLE<br />
AND ACHIEVEMENT OF JEWS IN CREATING THE STATE OF ISRAEL.<br />
THROUGH MANY DIFFICULTIES, THAT YOU KNOW BETTER THAN I,<br />
HEBREW UNIVERSITY HAS SURVIVED AND PROSPERED LIKE ISRAEL<br />
ITSELF. YOU ARE INDEED, IN DR WEIZMANN'S WORDS, A " CENTRE FOR<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF JEWISH CONSCIOUSNESS", AND YOUR ACADEMIC<br />
STRENGTHS, RANGING ACROSS THE SPECTRUM OF THE SCIENCES, THE<br />
PROFESSIONS AND THE HUMANITIES, ARE MAKING AN INVALUABLE<br />
-CONTRIBUTION TO THE UNDERSTANDING-AND-GROWTH-OF -THE-ISRAELI--COMMUN. IT W7 W </p>
<p>BUT YOU ARE MORE THAN THAT TOO. HEBREW UNIVERSITY IS NOT<br />
JUST AN ISRAELI UNIVERSITY BUT, INCREASINGLY. ONE WITH A<br />
PERSPECTIVE ON THE WHOLE MIDDLE EASTERN REGION.<br />
A STRIKING FEATURE OF YOUR SUCCESS HAS BEEN THAT YOU ARE NOT<br />
ONLY GUIDING THE INTELLECTUAL DEVELOPMENT OF ISRAEL BUT<br />
ALS-ENGAGING IN THE EXCHARGE OF-I-DEAS-WI-TH-ACADEMICS<br />
THROUGHOUT THE REGION AND INDEED, THROUGH THE WORLD.<br />
YOUR SYLLABUS COVERS NOT JUST JEWISH STUDIES BUT MIDDLE<br />
EASTERN STUDIES AS A WHOLE, AND YOUR INTELLECTUAL BREADTH<br />
IS MATCHED BY THE DIVERSITY OF YOUR STUDENT BODY.<br />
IT IS A PARTICULAR SOURCE OF PRIDE TO ME AS THE PRIME MINISTEROF<br />
AUSTRALIA THAT AUSTRALIANS HAVE BEEN SO CLOSELY LINKED WITH<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF THIS INSTITUTION.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN FRIENDS OF THE HEBREW UNIVERSITY WAS ESTABLISHED<br />
IN 1936, ONLY EIGHT YEARS AFTER THE FIRST STUDENTS WERE<br />
ADMITTED TO THE UNIVERSITY$<br />
ITS NOTABLE ACHIEVEMENTS INCLUDE THE BLANKFIELD POLITICAL<br />
SCIENCE BUILDING, THE TWO SIR ZELMAN COWEN FUNDS FOR ACADEMIC<br />
EXCHANGES, THE AUSTRALIA HOUSE DORMITORY AN DI AM. DELIGHTED . O<br />
SAY, THE BOB HAWKE MEDICAL RESEARCH ENDOWMENT WHICH WAS<br />
ESTABLISHED IN 1977. </p>
<p>THE GOLDA MEIR FELLOWSHIP FUND, A SCHEME WHICH HONOURS A GREAT<br />
LABOR LEADER AND A GREAT WOMAN, HAS BEEN HEAVILY SUPPORTED BY<br />
AUSTRALIAN CONTRIBUTORS AND ONE AUSTRALIAN HAS ALREADY WON A<br />
FELLOWSHIP. I HAD THE PLEASURE OF INAUGURATING THE GOLDA MEIR FUND<br />
IN AUSTRALIA LAST YEAR.<br />
FOUR AUSTRALIAN ACADEMICS ARE CURRENTLY TEACHERS AT THIS<br />
UNLVERS. LTYAND A-NUMBER--OF-YOUNG-AUSTRALIANS--1-4CLUD-ING-A--------<br />
GROUP OF NURSES, IS STUDYING HERE. AT THE SAME TIME, THREE<br />
OF YOUR TEACHING STAFF ARE ON STUDY LEAVE IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
THREE AUSTRALIANS ARE GOVERNORS OF THE UNIVERSITY BEREL GINGES,<br />
ISADOR MAGID AND ISRAEL BLANKFIELD, AND, AS IF THIS LIST WERE<br />
NOT ENOUGH, SiR ZELMAN COWAN, THE DISTINGUISHED AUSTRALIAN<br />
LAWYER, AND OUR FORMER GOVERNOR-GENERAL, IS AN ACADEMIC<br />
GOVERNOR OF-THE UNIVERSITY. SIR ZELMAN, WHO IS NOW PROVOST<br />
OF ORIEL COLLEGE AT OXFORD, WAS BEFORE TODAY THE ONLY<br />
AUSTRALIAN HONOURED BY YOU AS RECIPIENT OF AN HONORARY<br />
DOCTORATE, THAT LIST OF AUSTRALIAN CONTRIBUTIONS TO AND BENEFICIARIES<br />
OF THIS UNIVERSITY IS EXTENSIVE AND IMPRESSIVE. BUT ON<br />
REFLECTION IT APPEARS ENTIRELY REASONABLE THAT WE AS A NATION<br />
SHOULD BE SO CLOSE TO YOU.<br />
FOR THE AUSTRALIAN JEWISH COMMUNITY HAS. A _ R. ICH_ AND.-GLITIERING<br />
INTELLECTUAL LIFE. SINCE THE EUROPEAN SETTLEMENT OF AUSTRALIA<br />
BEGAN NEARLY TWO CENTURIES AGO, IN 1788, JEWISH ACADEMICS,<br />
WRITERS, ARTISTS AND COMPOSERS HAVE BEEN AT THE FOREFRONT OF OUR<br />
NATIONAL ENDEAVOUR. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIA HAS CALLED UPON JEWS TO BE HEAD OF ITS ARMED FORCES,<br />
HEAD OF ITS JUDICIARY AND, TWICE, HEAD OF STATE.<br />
BUT TODAY I CANNOT LET PASS THE OPPORTUNITY TO NAME ONE MAN<br />
WHOSE INTELLECTUAL BRILLIANCE AND UNQUENCHABLE INTEGRITY<br />
EPITOMISES THE LASTING JEWISH IMPACT ON AUSTRALIAN LIFE.<br />
JUL-US-STNEjjURIST, TEACHER, PUBLICIST, INTERNATIONALIST,<br />
WAS A MAN WHOM I NOT ONLY-RESPECTED -AS--AN-INTELLECTUAL<br />
HAD THE HONOUR TO KNOW AND LOVE AS A FRIEND.<br />
JULIUS STONE DIED IN SEPTEMBER 1984 AT THE AGE OF 77 BUT<br />
HIS ACHIEVEMENTS SURVIVE BOTH IN HIS WRITTEN WORK AND IN THE<br />
WISDOM HE PASSED ON TO HIS STUDENTS,<br />
THERE ARE SOMESPECIAL LINKS BETWEEN JULIUS STONE AND THIS<br />
UNIVERSITY WHICH I WANT TO MENTION, -JULIUS WAS AN ACADEMIC<br />
DIRECTOR AND HEAD OF YOUR TRUMAN CENTRE FOR'THE ADVANCEMENT OF<br />
PEACE, AND THERE IS AN ENDOWMENT TO ESTABLISHWT'THIS UNIVERSITY<br />
A JULIUS AND RECA STONE SCHOLARSHIP HERE, WHICH WOULD CERTAINLY<br />
BE A FITTING MEMORIAL. IT IS A PARTICULAR JOY TO MENTION<br />
TOO, THAT JULIUS' SON MICHAEL IS YOUR PROFESSOR OF ARMENIAN<br />
STUDIES, So THE BONDS WHICH LINK AUSTRALIA TO THIS CAMPUS ARE STRONG<br />
AND GROWING STRONGER, </p>
<p>fRST AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER TO VISIT ISRAEL I AM<br />
HAT YOU CHOSE ME AS THE RECIPIENT OF AN HONORARY<br />
E PARTICULARLY AS YOU HAD ALREADY AWARDED ME AN<br />
HONORARY FELLOWSHIP OF THE UNIVERSITY IN FEBRUARY 1978 WHEN 1<br />
WAS PRESIDENT OF THE AUSTRALIAN COUNCIL OF TRADE UNIONS.<br />
THIS IS NOT OF COURSE THE FIRST TIME I HAVE MADE THE JOURNEY TO<br />
TH-I-S-C-OUNTRY.--BUT-W-I-TH-EV-ERY-V-S-I-T-I AM-IMPRE-SS-ED-ANEW-BY--<br />
IT, ENTHUSED BY YOUR ENTHUSIASM, STUNNED BY YOUR RESILENCE AND<br />
MOVED BY YOUR STRUGGLE.<br />
MY RESPONSE WAS, IN PART, THE HUMAN RESPONSE TO THE<br />
GREAT DRAMA OF THE FOUNDATION AND GROWTH OF ISRAEL ON THE<br />
ASHES OF THE HOLOCAUST.<br />
BUT I WAS IMPRESSED TOO FOR A NUMBER OF. SPECIFICALLY AUSTRALIAN<br />
REASONS.<br />
AS A MEMBER OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY,-I COULD NOT-FAIL TO<br />
BE IMPRESSED BY THE ELECTORAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE SUCCESS OF<br />
YOUR LABOR PARTY. WHEN I FIRST VISITED ISRAEL, IN 1971, LABOR<br />
HAD BEEN IN POWER HERE FOR MORE THAN IqENTY YEARS ABOUT THE<br />
SAME NUMBER OF YEARS AS WE IN AUSTRALIA HAD ENDURED OF CONSERVATIVE<br />
RULE. As A TRADE UNION LEADER,-I -COULD NOT-. FAIL TO ADMIRE--THE-ISRAELITRADE<br />
UNION MOVEMENT, WITH ITS TOTAL COMMITMENT TO THE ISRAELI<br />
PEOPLE, AND ITS THOROUGH ACCEPTANCE BY THEM. </p>
<p>CERTAINLY, AS LEADER OF AN AUSTRALIAN TRADE UNION MOVEMENT<br />
WHICH WAS AT THE TIME NOT ONLY EXCLUDED FROM THE FORUMS OF<br />
DECISION MAKING BUT NOT INFREQUENTLY VILIFIED BY THE<br />
GOVERNMENT OF THE DAY, THE HISTADRUT MADE A LASTING IMPRESSION<br />
ON ME.<br />
As A SOCIAL DEMOCRAT VISITING ISRAEL IN 1971, I COULD NOT FAIL<br />
TO RESPECT THE SUCCESSFUL WAY IN WHICH YOU HAD INCARNATED<br />
THE VISION OF DAVID BEN GURION OF A-WORKIN G-CLASS BUILDING -ITS<br />
OWN-NATION BY DI-INT--OF-I-TS-OWN PHYSICAL_. AND_ INTELLECTUAL.<br />
BUT TO DISCOVER THESE THINGS ABOUT ISRAELI POLITICS AND TRADE UNIONS<br />
WAS TO CONFRONT AN EVEN MORE FUNDAMENTAL INSPIRATION OF YOUR<br />
CIVIC LIFE: ISRAEL IS A DEMOCRACY, PROUDLY AND INCESSANTLY ENGAGED<br />
IN DEMOCRATIC DISPUTATION ABOUT EVERY ASPECT OF NATIONAL POLICY.<br />
YOUR KNESSET WHICH I VISITED YESTERDAY, IS ONE OF THE GREAT<br />
DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS.<br />
YOUR PRESS IS AS UNFETTERED AS ANY IN THE WORLD.<br />
AND YOUR SOCIETY IS AS RESILIENT AS ANY IN ACCOMMODATING THE<br />
FREQUENTLY UNCOMFORTABLE QUESTIONS WHICH A FREE PRESS MUST ASK.<br />
THESE ARE FEATURES OF YOUR LIFE WHICH YOU HAVE NEVER SURRENDERED,<br />
EVEN IN THE DARKEST MOMENTS WHEN YOUR VERY SURVIVAL WAS AT RISK. </p>
<p>W.<br />
I SAY ALL OF THIS TO UNDERLINE WHAT MUST ALREADY BE APPARENT<br />
TO YOU: I RESPECT THIS COUNTRY AND FEEL CONSTANTLY<br />
REFRESHED AND CHALLENGED BY IT.<br />
BUT I DON'T WANT MY PRAISE TO BE MISUNDERSTOOD. I DO NOT WANT<br />
TO BREED COMPLACENCY ABOUT YOUR VIGOROUS AND EGALITARIAN<br />
DEMOC-RAC-Y -NOR--FOR-THAT-MAT-TER--DO--4-WANT--N-RA-S1-NG-T4I SUNIVERSITY<br />
TO SUGGEST THAT ACADEMIC EXCELLENCE DOES NOT NEED<br />
TO BE CONSTANTLY AND VIGILANTLY PROTECTED.<br />
I DO NOT WNAT MY THEME TODAY TO BE THAT OF PANGLOSS: THAT<br />
EVERYTHING IN ISRAEL IS " FOR THE BEST IN THE BEST OF ALL POSSIBLE<br />
WORLDS", IT IS FINE TO RECALL THE GREAT EARLY DAYS OF YOUR NATION, AND<br />
TO REFLECT ON THE GLORIOUS PRINCIPLES ON WHICH IT WAS FOUNDED.<br />
BUT IT IS NECESSARY TOO, I THINK TO-TAKE THE MEASURE OF-THE<br />
CHANGES WHICH SEPARATE THOSE EARLY DAYS FROM THIS DIFFERENT<br />
WORLD IN 1987.<br />
THE OLD GENERATION OF PIONEERS HAS, SADLY, LARGELY PASSED ON.<br />
ISRAEL IS CHANGING AND MATURING AND IS CONFRONTING TROUBLING<br />
AND PROFOUND ISSUES OF WHICH THOSE PIONEERS KNEW LITTLE OR NOTHING.<br />
LET ME NAME A FEW OF THOSE ISSUES. </p>
<p>HOW WILL ISRAEL SOLVE THE GREAT ISSUES OF POLITICAL PRINCIPLE<br />
AND HUMAN RIGHTS, NOT TO MENTION THE DEMOGRAPHIC PRESSURES,<br />
ENTAILED IN ITS ROLE AS ADMINISTRATOR OF OCCUPIED TERRITORIES?<br />
WHAT CAN ISRAEL DO TO ENSURE THAT OVERSEAS JEWS SEEKING<br />
EMIGRATION HERE SUCH AS SOVIET JEWS CAN IN FACT REACH THEIR<br />
PROMISED LAND?<br />
How CAN ISRAEL BEST BUILD ON THE SUCCESS -OF -THE-CAMP-DAVID<br />
AGREEMENT TO ENSURE PEACE _ WITH ALL-_ ITS ARABNEIGHBOURSWITHIN<br />
SECURE BOUNDARIES?<br />
How CAN GOVERNMENT AND POLITICAL PARTIES CONTINUE TO REPRESENT<br />
THE PEOPLE AND EFFICIENTLY MANAGE THE STATE?<br />
THESE ARE NOT EASY QUESTIONS, BUT I-RAISE-THEM AS A-FRIEND WHO ISFULLY<br />
AWARE THAT AUSTRALIANS WOULD HAVE DIFFICULTY PROVIDING<br />
SUITABLE ANSWERS TO COMPARABLE QUEST-IONS POSED ABOUT THEIR<br />
SOCIETY.<br />
BUT THE QUESTIONS MUST BE ASKED, AND THEY CANNOT BE IGNORED.<br />
HAVING HAD THE TEMERITY TO RAISE THESE-ISSUES WITH YOU IN SUCH . OUTLINE<br />
FASHION, FORGIVE ME NOW IF I HAVE THE PRESUMPTION EQUALLY BRIEFLY<br />
TO SUGGEST WHERE ANSWERS MAY LIE. -FOR I FIRMLY BELIEVE THAT<br />
SATISFACTORY ANSWERS CAN AND WILL BE FOUND. </p>
<p>THE ANSWERS I BELIEVE LIE HERE, DEEP IN THE ROOTS OF THAT<br />
JEWISH CONSCIOUSNESS OF WHICH DR WEIZMANN SPOKE.<br />
THE RESOLUTION OF THESE ISSUES IS A TASK WHICH FIRST, WILL<br />
REQUIRE THE PATIENT AND STEADY APPLICATION BOTH OF THE KIND<br />
OF VISION WHICH LED TO THE FOUNDATION OF THIS UNIVERSITY, AND<br />
OF THE INTELLECTUAL PRBII-G-AND-PROITYCWTHAS-1ADE-IT A<br />
GREAT -UNIVERSITYSECONDLY, ON A MORE GENERAL PLANE, I BELIEVE THE ANSWERS TO THE<br />
PROBLEMS OF TODAY'S ISRAEL LIE IN KEEPING ALIVE AND APPLYING<br />
ANEW THE PRINCIPLES ON WHICH THE STATE WAS ORIGINALLY FOUNDED.<br />
THESE PRINCIPLES EGALITARIANISM, THE DIGNITY OF LABOR, DEVOTION<br />
TO A JEWISH HOMELAND, AND UNDURINGLY DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT<br />
PROVIDE A SOUND PATH FROM YOUR PAST._ TO. YOUR FUTURE,<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN<br />
IN LOOKING BACK TO THE ROOTS OF THIS UNIVERSITY AND THIS<br />
NATION, ONE CANNOT FAIL TO ENCOUNTER THE GIGANTIC PRESENCE OF<br />
ALBERT EINSTEIN.<br />
EINSTEIN OF. COURSE WAS CLOSELY CONNECTED WITH THE EARLY-DAYS OF<br />
HEBREW UNIVERSITY. ALONG WITH SIGMUND FREUD, MARTIN BAbER,<br />
CHAIM WEIZMANN AND OTHERS HE WAS A MEMBER OFTHE FIRST BOARDOF<br />
GOVERNORS.<br />
ONE WONDERS, IN PASSING, WHAT BRILLIANT CONVERSATIONS THOSE<br />
DISTINGUISHED GENTLEMENT MIGHT HAVE HAD AT THEIR BOARD MEETINGS! </p>
<p>EINSTEIN HAD A CLEAR VISION OF THE ROLE OF THE UNIVERSITY IN<br />
THE WORLD AND I CAN DO NO BETTER TODAY THAN TO CONCLUDE WITH<br />
HIS WORDS. FOR I BELIEVE HE WOULD HAVE BEEN IN NO DOUBT ABOUT<br />
THE INSPIRATION PROVIDED BY THESE PRINCIPLES ON WHICH THE<br />
ISRAELI STATE WAS FOUNDED.<br />
" ISHOULD LIKE TO EXPRESSTHHOEINENSAD<br />
" THAT-TEACHER-S---AND STUDENTS-WILL ALWAYS PRESERVE THE<br />
CONSCIOUSNESS THAT THEY SERVE THEIR PEOPLE BEST WHEN<br />
THEY MAINTAIN ITS UNION WITH HUMANITY AND WITH THE<br />
HIGHEST HUMAN VALUES.<br />
" IN THE COURSE OF TIME THIS INSTITUTION WILL DEMONSTRATE<br />
WITH THE GREATEST CLEARNESS THE ACHIEVEMENTS OF WHICH<br />
THE JEWISH SPIRIT I-S CAPABLE".<br />
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN<br />
THEY WERE PROPHETIC WORDS. THROUGH-YOUR EFFORTS THEY ARE<br />
BEING FULFILLED EVERY DAY.<br />
THANK YOU </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
