<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21772</transcript-id>
    <title>Taskforce on Biofuels  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/05/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce today the appointment of a taskforce to examine the latest scientific evidence on the impacts of ethanol and other biofuel use on human health, environmental outcomes and automotive operations.</p>
<p>On this basis, and taking into account the most recent economic analyses of fuel supply in Australia, the Taskforce will assess the costs and benefits of biofuel production.</p>
<p>The Taskforce will examine:</p>
<p> the findings of the December 2003 CSIRO/ABARE/BTRE desktop study into the appropriateness of a 350 million litre biofuels target;</p>
<p> the findings of the DEH study into the impacts of E10 and E20 on automotive operation;</p>
<p> other international and Australian scientific research on the health and environmental impacts of supplementing fossil fuels with oxygenates such as ethanol and other biofuel blends;</p>
<p> the economic and scientific bases upon which decisions have been made to support ethanol and other biofuel production in North America, Europe and other countries.</p>
<p>The Taskforce will comprise Dr Conall O'Connell, Deputy Secretary, Department of Environment and Heritage; Dr David Brockway, Chief, Division of Energy Technology, CSIRO; Dr John Keniry, Chairman Ridley Corporation Limited; and Mr Max Gillard, Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, Toyota Technical Centre, Asia Pacific Australia.</p>
<p>The Taskforce will report to the Government by the end of July 2005.</p>
<p> It will be supported by a small whole-of-government secretariat based in the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
