<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11571</transcript-id>
    <title>ROYAL VISIT 2000</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh will</p>
<p> visit a number of rural and regional centres as well as Sydney, Canberra,</p>
<p> Melbourne, Hobart and Perth during their forthcoming visit to Australia.</p>
<p>The Royal couple will arrive in Australia on Friday 17 March 2000. Their</p>
<p> visit will commence with a ceremonial welcome at the Opera House, Sydney</p>
<p> on Monday 20 March and conclude in Perth on Saturday 1 April 2000.</p>
<p>Their programme has been arranged so that The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh</p>
<p> can meet people in remote areas of Australia as well as in the cities,</p>
<p> and to enable them to see the many and varied contributions that people</p>
<p> from all walks of life make to the nation.</p>
<p>The Queen and The Duke of Edinburgh will visit Bourke, Ballarat, Launceston,</p>
<p> Busselton, Alice Springs and Wagga Wagga (The Duke of Edinburgh only).</p>
<p>The programme will include a tour of the Sydney Olympic site, a demonstration</p>
<p> by volunteer bush firefighters, visits to an aboriginal community radio</p>
<p> station and the Immigration Museum, a meeting with INTERFET Commander</p>
<p> Major General Peter Cosgrove, a talk with students on the School of the</p>
<p> Air and the chance to see first hand the work of Australian medical researchers.</p>
<p>Further details of their programme will be released separately by the</p>
<p> governments of the States and Territories to be visited as they have overall</p>
<p> responsibility for the activities occurring within their States.</p>
<p>23 February, 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
