<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8742</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING AUSTRALIA - UNITED STATES TRADE AND INVESTMENT FRAMEWORK ARRANGEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008742.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
T9E: L5: 5 No. 60.0. N69o 2 P. 01/ 01<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AUSTRALIA-UNITED STATES TRADE AND INVESTMENT FRAMEWORK<br />
ARRANGEMENT I am pleased to announce that Australia and the United States have concluded negotiations<br />
on a Trade and Investment Framework Arrangcmenu, an initiative which arose during the<br />
visit of President Bush in January.<br />
The Airrangement will provide a valuable framework for regular high-level consultations<br />
with thc United States on trade and investment issues. These includeS _ xpsurtb sidies and<br />
imp~ ort barriers which affect some of our exports to the United States such as beef, sugar,<br />
dairy products anid steel.<br />
Australia and the United States have a very substantial economic relatio nsh-i p The<br />
combined value of the investment stock cach country has i he other is o-ver $ 85 billion.<br />
For Australia, the United States is our largest source of imports ( worth around $ 12 billion<br />
In 1991) and our second largest export market ( worth over $ 5 billion in 1991). For the<br />
United States, Australia is both a significant market for goods and services and an<br />
Important destination for investment.<br />
Through its consultative provisions, the Arrangement will help strengthen the open and<br />
non-discriminatory trade and investment environment which both countries support.<br />
Conclusion of the Arrangement is consistent with the Government's policy to pursue<br />
actively all opportunities to advance Australia's trade interests consistent with Australia's<br />
firm commitment to the GAIT mnultilatcral trading system and our support for the Asia<br />
Pacific Economic Cooperation ( APEC) roccss as an essential mechanism for promoting<br />
trade liberalisation in the Asia-Pacific region. Some other APEC countries. have<br />
concluded similar agreements With the United States.<br />
The Government welcomes the Tradc and Investment Framcwork Arrangement and looks<br />
forward to even closer relations with the United States on matters of trade and investment.<br />
CANBERRA 26 November 1992 TEL 26. Nov. 92 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
