<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9476</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP POW CEREMONY, AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL, 14 FEBRUARY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009476.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
POW CEREMONY, AUSTRALIAN WAR MEMORIAL, 14 FEBRUARY 1995<br />
I am honoured to speak to you today at this commemorative service for<br />
Australian Prisoners of War.<br />
This year we are commemorating the 50th anniversary of the end of World War<br />
II. In Europe they are commemorating the liberation of their countries from<br />
occupation and tyranny; the end of a war which took the lives of millions and<br />
wrought devastation on a scale unequalled in history.<br />
They are celebrating freedom and honouring the dead including those 6 million<br />
Jews who died in the Holocaust.<br />
Because many thousands of Australians fought in Europe and the Middle East,<br />
we in Australia are sharing in this commemoration.<br />
We are also commemorating the end of the war in Asia and the Pacific, which<br />
was no less a fight for freedom over tyranny, and the price in death and suffering<br />
was just as high.<br />
It was also, for a time, a fight to save Australia.<br />
In all, more than 27,000 Australians died in the Second World War. Their<br />
sacrifice, like those who have died in every war, will never be forgotten.<br />
We pledge this as Australians.<br />
Here at the Australian War Memorial and at memorials in communities<br />
throughout Australia we remember those who made the supreme sacrifice.<br />
They are also remembered at memorials overseas. </p>
<p>In the past three years I have visited some of them in Britain and France, New<br />
Guinea and in Thailand.<br />
In Thailand last year, at Kanchanaburi. I attended a service for the Australians<br />
who diedi as Prisonprs of War on the Rpijrmp-Th qi land Railwav. Their story is<br />
legendary.<br />
Thirty thousand Australians were POWs in various parts of the world. It is they<br />
who we are honouring today: the Australians who died in captivity.<br />
We are paying tribute to the Australians whose desire to serve their country and<br />
the cause of freedom led them to leave their country and / ose their freedom.<br />
Their privations were profound.<br />
To remember the sacrifice of our POWs today we need to imagine not just the<br />
physical suffering they endured, but the psychological suffering the terrible<br />
loneliness and the sense of loss, the homesickness and the helplessness they<br />
had to live with.<br />
And we need to ask ourselves what gave them the faith and courage they<br />
needed to live with the adversity and fight off the despair.<br />
How did they keep hope alive?<br />
We know from accounts like those of Barney Roberts and Weary Dunlop, and<br />
from what Max Jagger has said this morning, that paramount among the<br />
sustaining values of Australian POWs were those indefinable bonds between<br />
them which we call mateship.<br />
Today we should remember the basis on which those bonds are built the love<br />
of freedom and fairness, the pragmatism, resourcefulness and perseverance and<br />
above all the love of this place. The love of Australia.<br />
They are sustaining values for this generation too.<br />
Perhaps, then, we should bring two messages to this commemoration.<br />
One is the message of faith and courage, the victory over adversity which can<br />
teach us and inspire us now.<br />
The other is that we should never forget the evil that was done in these prison<br />
camps. </p>
<p>3<br />
The outrage we feel about what was done on the Burma-Thailand Railway or on<br />
the Sandakan Death March should never fade.<br />
Our children should know about these things.<br />
We must not forget.<br />
Yet, as the life of Weary Dunlop tells us, we must allow the wounds to heal.<br />
If Australians sacrificed their lives and freedom so that we could be free, we owe<br />
it both to their memory and our children to see that Australia is kept free of old<br />
hatreds and bitterness.<br />
Today, and throughout this year, these are the messages I think we should<br />
convey we honour the sacrifice of that heroic generation and we give meaning<br />
to it by making real their hopes for us and those who follow. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
