<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>179</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL LIBRARY</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000179.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NATIONAL LI3RARY<br />
The Government has reached a numbeir of conclusions upon the<br />
future of the National Library, about which I should like to<br />
inform the House.<br />
As Honourable Members will know, the National Library has<br />
grown directly from the Library of the Commonwealth Parliament.<br />
The P rliamentary Library Committee under the leadership of the<br />
President of the Senate and the Speaker has been the main source<br />
of advice in the Parliamentary and National Libraries, and I<br />
should like to acknowledge the value of its work over the years.<br />
The advice of the present Committee and of its Chairman, Sir<br />
Alister McMullin, has been most helpful to the Governent in<br />
considering the future of the National Library.<br />
It has been clear for some time that the Nitional Library<br />
has outgrowin the scope of the Parliamentary Library and has<br />
become a rese. irch and reference institution with nation-wide<br />
responsibilities. It is generally recognised that a different<br />
form of control has become desirable.<br />
In 1956, therefore, the Government set up a Committee with<br />
Sir George Paton, the Vice Chancellor of the Oniversity of<br />
Melbourne, as Chairman to study the matter. The Committee<br />
included three members of the Parliament representing all parties<br />
and both Houses. The report of the Committee was tabled in<br />
Parliament and we are all greatly indebted to the Committee for<br />
its work. Last year, the Govei-nment set up an Interdepartmental<br />
Committee to advise on the detailed measures which were necessory<br />
to make effective the main reconmendations of the Paton Committee.<br />
This Committee worked last year in the closest association with<br />
the Presiding Officers and the Parliamentary Library Committee.<br />
The Government's conslusions can be suTimarised as follows:<br />
1. There should be a Parliamentary Library and a National<br />
Library of Australia, each to be a separate institution.<br />
2. The Parliamentary Library should be controlled, as it is<br />
now, by the Presiding Officers of Parliament with the<br />
advice of a Joint Committee of Members of both Houses. </p>
<p>2.<br />
3. The National Library wotuld be controlled by a small Council.<br />
The Council would be given substantial reponsibility<br />
for th~ e control and development of the National Library,<br />
with Ministerial responsibility limited, so far as<br />
possible, to such matters as the review of annual expenditure<br />
and the appointm~ ent of members of the Council.<br />
The present Division of the Library concerned with the<br />
records and archives of thte Commonwealth Government<br />
should become a separate agency of the Government, within<br />
an appropriate Department, under the direct control of a<br />
Minister.<br />
T~ he Government intends that thnere should be the closest<br />
co-operation between the Parliamentary and the National Libraries<br />
in order to avoid overlapping wherever possible and to ensure<br />
economies in administration. This co-operation, will, of course,<br />
be especially close in the ealy stages because we do not have,<br />
as yet, a building to house the National Library adequately. The<br />
Government has agreed that design and planning work for a new<br />
National Library Building should begin, Naturally, the timing<br />
of construction -dill have to be considered in relation to requirom~<br />
nts f~ or other public works.<br />
The Parliamentary Library -, 1ill have its own stock of books,<br />
puriodicals, newspapers and so on for the use of Members of<br />
Parliament. It will have access to the resources of the National<br />
Library by arrangement between the Parliaiientary Library CoMMitt~ e<br />
and the Council of the National Library an arrangement which<br />
will strengthen the reference and reading services available to<br />
Parliament itself.<br />
The Government has given special attention to the future<br />
of Government archives and has reached the conclusion that<br />
Government archives should be under Government control as they<br />
are essentially a collection of the Government's own confidential<br />
papers, records and files, many of which for a number of reasons<br />
should not be made public at least until a certain period of time<br />
has ela. psed. This is the normal practice in countries overseas.<br />
The Government proposes to take early action to give effect<br />
to the conclusions it has reached. The first step will be to<br />
appoint a Na-ional Library Council and its Chairman on an interim<br />
basis. </p>
<p>I should perhaps emphasise that wie are not in essence establishing<br />
new institutions but are rather introducing new<br />
methods of control and divisions of responsibilities which are<br />
more suitable for the present needs and ihich are similar to<br />
those operating in many countries in the British Commonwealth<br />
and olsewhere. I am confident that the Government's legislation which, it<br />
is hoped, will be brought down in the next session of Parliament,<br />
will command a large measure of support, both in this Parliament<br />
and the Australian cmmunity.<br />
CNII BE RAI<br />
4th may, 1960. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
