<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10792</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                PRESS CONFERENCE                PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, I have called this news conference with the</p>
<p> Minister, Mr Somlyay, and the Chief Minister of the Northern Territory,</p>
<p> Shane Stone, to announce the formation of a $10 million Katherine</p>
<p> region redevelopment programme. A third of that will be contributed</p>
<p> by the Federal Government, a third by the Northern Territory Government</p>
<p> and the other third will be sought from the community. Tax deductibility</p>
<p> for contributions will be available. The money from both the Federal</p>
<p> and Territorial Governments is available forthwith and the fund is</p>
<p> in operation as from this afternoon.</p>
<p>So far the Federal Government has contributed through the natural</p>
<p> disaster relief arrangements $31 million to the Katherine region.</p>
<p> The Northern Territory Government has contributed $11 million. I would</p>
<p> also like to pay particular tribute to the co-operative and generous</p>
<p> response of the banks to requests made by the people of Katherine</p>
<p> and by the two Governments. In a variety of ways the banks have been</p>
<p> particularly helpful and understanding and I would like on behalf</p>
<p> of the Commonwealth Government to record my appreciation for the contribution</p>
<p> that the banks have made in this very difficult situation.</p>
<p>I once again record with some pleasure the cooperative manner in which</p>
<p> the community has pulled together in this particularly distressing</p>
<p> situation. The role of the Australian Defence Forces deserves unstinted</p>
<p> praise. The men and women of the Defence Force, both the Army and</p>
<p> the Air Force, have worked in very difficult situations and they have</p>
<p> demonstrated again the intense public spirited character of the Australian</p>
<p> Defence Forces. All of the emergency services have worked well. And</p>
<p> I also want to record the appreciation of my Government to the work</p>
<p> of the Northern Territory Police and also, may I say, the excellent</p>
<p> working relationship between my Government and the government of the</p>
<p> Northern Territory. The Chief Minister and I have not only been in</p>
<p> regular contact about this disaster from the moment it happened but</p>
<p> at other levels and with the cooperation of Alex Somlyay, the Minister</p>
<p> responsible, it has been a very cooperative effort.</p>
<p>It has been a very serious flood and the damage is long-lasting. And</p>
<p> the size of the contribution by the Federal Government, both under</p>
<p> the Natural Disaster Relief arrangements and under some special measures,</p>
<p> the size of that response is entirely appropriate and the sort of</p>
<p> response that a generous Federal Government and a generous nation</p>
<p> is willing to make.</p>
<p>I commend to all Australians contributions to the Red Cross Appeal</p>
<p> which are tax deductible. There have already been some very significant</p>
<p> corporate contributions to that appeal and I hope that they are matched</p>
<p> by others throughout the Australian community.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you believe that $10 million will be enough?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When you add to the $10 million the $31 million and of course there</p>
<p> is no cap on that, in the sense that there are fundamental arrangements</p>
<p> that come into operation, we think that represents a very generous</p>
<p> response, obviously we keep it under review. In a situation like this</p>
<p> somebody in my position is loathed to say that a particular figure</p>
<p> is enough. On the other hand nobody should underestimate the scale</p>
<p> of the contribution.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, will any of this money go directly to individuals or will</p>
<p> it be used for general rebuilding?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will be discretional. In other words, under the Natural Disaster</p>
<p> Relief arrangements certain money goes to individuals and then the</p>
<p> $10 million can be used in a discretionary fashion. So the answer</p>
<p> is it could, yes.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So the funds won't be used necessarily for particular infrastructure</p>
<p> projects, Mr Howard?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it could be a combination Laura. We don't want to limit</p>
<p> ourselves. We want to have a flexible approach.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, should Justice Callinan have stood aside on the Hindmarsh</p>
<p> Island Bridge case?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is quite inappropriate for me, the Leader of the Opposition or</p>
<p> indeed anybody else to comment on that. It involves a matter before</p>
<p> the High Court, the hearing has commenced. It is quite wrong of anybody</p>
<p> in holding public office to make comment on that. It was his decision,</p>
<p> it is a matter for him and his brother and sister judges on the court</p>
<p> and it should be left at that.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you concerned that lawyers are now considering asking the full</p>
<p> bench to decide whether he should be able to make a judgement?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't have a comment because it is not proper.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley argues that you create the perceptions of bias?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley is not behaving according to the high standards that are</p>
<p> expected of Opposition Leaders in these matters. He knows that it</p>
<p> is wrong of him to be weighing into this. The court has commenced</p>
<p> hearing something - the status of a judge. The way in which those</p>
<p> proceedings are conducted is not something on which Mr Beazley should</p>
<p> comment, nor is it something on which I should comment.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, is it possible that if there is a free vote on the republican</p>
<p> convention, that if the matter came to a referendum, the Government</p>
<p> wouldn't actually have a formal position, one way or another,</p>
<p> in a referendum campaign?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Let us deal with things sequentially. We are in the middle of a very</p>
<p> interesting convention and if, as I hope, a clear view emerges from</p>
<p> the convention in accordance with the undertaking I gave before the</p>
<p> last election and repeated on Monday, that will be put to the Australian</p>
<p> people. The question of how the Government handles the matter, and</p>
<p> different views and so-forth, is something which will be apparent</p>
<p> at the time of the referendum but you should look carefully at what</p>
<p> I said in my speech. The speech represented a clear and unambiguous</p>
<p> statement of how the Government would handle the matter and where</p>
<p> I stood on the issue.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>If the clear view does emerge will you support it in a referendum</p>
<p> campaign?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am not going to talk about the attitude I am taking in the referendum</p>
<p> campaign until that is upon us.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, what steps will the Australian Government take to</p>
<p> offset the US push into Indonesia that you talked about at your press</p>
<p> conference earlier this week?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are still assessing that we are gathering evidence of the behaviour</p>
<p> of the Americans, about which I complained yesterday, and when we</p>
<p> have that we will consider what our response ought to be. What I wanted</p>
<p> to do yesterday was to flag the concern of my Government about what</p>
<p> had happened.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Might the WTO be an avenue for the...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't rule anything out. The Americans have not been reluctant</p>
<p> to take us to the World Trade Organisation. The Americans played hard-ball</p>
<p> over Howe Leather and the Australian Government's first responsibility</p>
<p> is to protect the interests of Australian jobs and Australian exporters.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, has the Government come to view yet on whether it</p>
<p> believes that the GSM programmes conform to WTO rules or they don't</p>
<p> conform?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>If the what, I am sorry?</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>The US Trade credit support programmes, the loans, does the Federal</p>
<p> Government believe that they are illegal or legal under the WTO rules?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What, the ones we are proposing?</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>No, the ones that the US Government is actually offering now?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh well, that is something that we are assessing at the present time.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You can't say whether they are legal or illegal as yet?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am not going to pre-empt an examination that's only just</p>
<p> started.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, do you think, given the history of failure of constitutional</p>
<p> reform in this country, that a referendum for a republic can succeed</p>
<p> unless the Prime Minister lends his weight to the yes case?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Can I just make it clear, I gave an answer on that generic issue a</p>
<p> few moments ago and I am not going to be persuaded to give a different</p>
<p> answer.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well Mr Stone, do you have a view about that, I mean, can a case...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have a view about a lot of things but I am telling you that our</p>
<p> position on the referendum will be made known when the referendum</p>
<p> is upon us but you should look at it against the background of what</p>
<p> I said in my speech.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>I read your speech very carefully and it was a good speech but you</p>
<p> didn't rule out supporting the McGarvie model.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Rule out supporting, no, well I don't think you did read it.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You didn't rule out supporting the...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, you didn't read it. At the Convention, yeah, you clearly</p>
<p> didn't read it or you went to the wrong school...</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you saying you don't support the McGarvie model?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am saying that of the alternatives to the status quo that McGarvie</p>
<p> is the best.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You didn't rule that out did you? Rule out support for that?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I think it does. Go and read it. Look my position at the Convention</p>
<p> is very simple and that is that I support the status quo for the reasons</p>
<p> I explained in my speech. But, of the alternatives on offer, McGarvie</p>
<p> is better than the other two. It is the least worst option.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Doesn't that rule out any possible support for a referendum?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister will you also be accepting an invitation to attend</p>
<p> a meeting in Washington to discuss Asia?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When is the meeting taking place?</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>US Treasury has just said that they have sent out the invitations</p>
<p> to countries...</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I haven't got the invitation yet. Sounds like a letter</p>
<p> addressed to the Prime Minister from the Leader of the Opposition.</p>
<p> It gets to the press before it gets to the Prime Minister.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, do you believe the Hindmarsh Island Bridge Case could have</p>
<p> a bearing on the Wik Legislation, have an impact on your Wik Legislation?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't want to say anything about the Hindmarsh Bridge Case. It has</p>
<p> started before the High Court and I am not going to say anything about</p>
<p> it, in any colour shape or form. None what-so-ever.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
