<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6310</transcript-id>
    <title>FOLLOWING IS TRANSCRIPT OF PM&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT THE ROYAL HOTEL, OSAKA AT 2.45PM ON 3 FEBRUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/02/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006310.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOLLOWING IS TRANSCRIPT OF PM'S PRESS CONFERENCE AT THE ROYAL<br />
HOTEL, OSAKA AT 2.45 PM ON 3 FEBRUARY 1984.<br />
E AND 0 E PROOF-ONLY<br />
PM: THANK YOU LADIES AND GENTLEMENT FOR YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE.<br />
I WILL SAY A VERY BRIEF FEW WORDS IN OPENING AND THEN MAKE MYSELF<br />
AVAILABLE FOR QUESTIONING. THIS IS MY FIRST VISIT.<br />
TO THE KANSAI AND I REGARD IT AS IMPORTANT BECAUSE OF THE<br />
LONG HISTORICAL LINKS BETWEEN THIS AREA AND AUSTRALIA. THE<br />
TWO CONDITIONS FOR STRENGTHENING ECONOMIC RELATIONS BETWEEN<br />
OUR TWO COUNTRIES ARE FIRSTLY THAT OUR OWN ECONOMIES BE GROWING<br />
AND SECONDLY, THAT BETWEEN US WE RECOGNISE THE CHANGING STRUCTURES<br />
OF THOSE TWO ECONOMIES AND SEE THAT WE CAN ADJUST APPROPRIATELY<br />
TO GAIN MUTUAL ADVANTAGE FROM THOSE CHANGES. AND ON THOSE TWO<br />
POINTS I'M PLEASED TO REPORT TO YOU AS I DID IN MY MEETING BEFORE<br />
LUNCH WITH BUSINESS REPRESENTATIVES FAVOURABLE DEVELOPMENTS.<br />
FIRSTLY, IN REGARD TO OUR OWN ECONOMY IN AUSTRALIA WE HAVE THE<br />
IN THIS LAST YEAR TURNED AROUND FROM A POSITION OF RECESSION<br />
TO SIGNIFICANT GROWTH. WE EXPECT OUR ECONOMY TO GROW THROUGH<br />
1983/ 84 IN THE NON-FARM AREA OF GDP BY SOMETHING LIKE 6%<br />
AND WE ARE CONFIDENT THAT WILL CONTINUE BEYOND 1984. SECONDLYi IN<br />
RESPECT OF THE CHANGING STRUCTURE OF OUR ECONOMY THERE HAVE BEEN<br />
DEVELOPMENTS IN MY VISIT I ERE WHICH INDICATE A PREPAREDNESS<br />
ON THE PART OF OUR TWO-GOVERNMENTS TO MEET THOSE CHANGES. I REFER<br />
FIRSTLY TO THE AGREEMENT BY THE JAPANESE GOVERNMENT TO SEND AN<br />
IMPORT EXPANSION MISSION TO AUSTRALIA AS THEY HAVE TO THE UNITED<br />
STATES AND THE EEC. SECONDLY. THE INVITATION THAT THEY HAVE<br />
EXTENDED TO ME TO SEND A HIGH LEVEL AUSTRALIAN MISSION TO JAPAN<br />
FOR THE PURPOSE OF EXAnNfING NEW EXPORT OPPORTUNITIES IN JAPAN.<br />
SO THESE TWO FUNDAMENTAL CONDITIONS OF GROWTH AND A PREPAREDNESS<br />
TO ADJUST TO NEW AND CHANGING ECONOMIC STRUCTURES ARE BEING<br />
MET ON THIS BASIS, I HOPE, THAT THE ALREADY STRONG RELATIONSHIPS<br />
BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES WITH THIS AREA IN PARTICULAR<br />
28WILL DEVELOP EVEN MORE STRONGLY INTO THE FUTURE.<br />
JOURNALIST: WELL YOU REFERRED TO YOUR INTENTION TO STRENGTHEN THE<br />
LINK PARTICULARLY WITH THE KANSAI ECONOMY. IN SPECIFIC TERMS<br />
IN WHAT AREA ARE YOU GOING TO STRENGTHEN THAT TIE SETWEEN YOUR<br />
COUNTRY AND THE KANSAI AREA?<br />
PM: WELL I SAIfi THAT THERE ARE TWO WAYS IN WHICH WE WANT<br />
TO CONFIRM AND STRENGTHEN THE ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP. AND WHAT<br />
I SAY GENERALLY TO JAPAN APPLIES TO THE KANSAI AREA. FIRST WE HAVE<br />
HAD DISCUSSIONS WITH LEADERS OF GOVERNMENT AND INDUSTRY TO ENSURE<br />
I-HAT AUSTRALIA MAINTAINS ITS HARE IN THE TRADITIONAL AREAS OF<br />
SUPPLY WHICH, COURSE INCLUDES MINERAL PRODUCTS AND PRIMARY<br />
PRO UCTS PARTICULARLY BEEF. THAT THERE HAS BEEN PER14APS 4 FEAR<br />
rHAT WE WOULD LOSE SOME OF THE SHARE IN THAT AREA EITHER<br />
3ECAUSE OF POLICIES DIVERSI; ICATION WHICH! WERE NOT ALWAYS MADE<br />
URENL y COMMERCIAL GROUNDS AND ALSO RELATED -0 THAT ! S A RESUT </p>
<p>OF BILATERAL NEGOTIATIONS UNDERTAKEN BY JAPAN WITH OTHER<br />
COUNTRIES IN WHICH OUR INTERESTS MAY HAVE BEEN PREJUDICED. AND SO<br />
I HAVE SECURED, I BELIEVE, IN THE DISCUSSIONS WITH MR NAKASONE<br />
AND OTHERS AN UNDERSTANDING THAT PROVIDED THAT AUSTRALIA REMAINS<br />
A COMPETITIVE AND RELIABLE SUPPLIER WHICH WE WILL THEN THE<br />
SHARE THAT AUSTRALIA'S ENJOYED IN THESE TRADITIONAL MARKETS WILL.<br />
BE MAINTAINED. SO THAT'S, IF YOU LIKE, THE STEPS THAT WE-VE<br />
TAKEN BE MAINTAINED. SO THAT'S, IF YOU LIKE, THE STEPS THAT WE'VE<br />
TAKEN IN REGARD TO OUR EXISTING MAJOR AREAS OF TRADING RELATIONSHIPS.<br />
BUT SECONDLY, WE HAVE BEEN CONCERNED TO RECOGNISE THAT THE<br />
PROJECTIONS MADE IN THE PREVIOUS YEARS ABOUT THE SORTS OF LEVELS<br />
OF EXPORT OF OUR RAW MATERIALS ARE IN THE PROCESS OF BEING REVISED<br />
BECAUSE OF THE CHANGE IN THE ECONOMIC STRUCTURE OF JAPAN. THEREFORE,<br />
WE ARE LOOKING AS TO HOW WE CAN IN FACT EXPORT MORE IN THE AREA OF<br />
MANUFACTURED GOODS AND OF SERVICES TO JAPAN. AND IT'S PRECISELY<br />
IN THOSE AREAS THAT THE ARRANGEMENTS WE HAVE COME TO IN REGARD<br />
TO THE IMPORT EXPANSION TEAMS FROM JAPAN INTO OUR COUNTRY AND THE<br />
MISSION TO JAPAN FROM AUSTRALIAN ARE RELEVANT. IM MAY ALSO<br />
MENTION THAT WE HAVE HIRED TWO JAPANESE CONSULTANCY FIRMS TO ASSIST<br />
US IN THE EXAMINATION OF THESE AREAS. SO WHILE I CAN'T BE<br />
PRECISE IN REGARD TO THE AREAS OF MANUFACTURED GOOD AND SERVICES,<br />
BECAUSE WHAT WE'LL BE ABLE TO DO IN THAT AREA WILL IN FACT COME OUT<br />
OF THESE EXAMINATIONS WE'RE UNDERTAKING, WE DO BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE<br />
THE CAPACITY IN AUSTRALIA TO PROVIDE PARTICULAR AREAS OF MANUFACTURED<br />
GOODS AND SERVICES AS PART OF THE JAPANESE MARKET. AND LET ME<br />
SAY THAT THE OTHER SIDE OF THE COIN IN THAT IS THAT OF COURSE IN<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF SOME OF OUR AREAS OF MANUFACTURING CAPACITY<br />
WE WILL BE LOOKING TO JAPANESE INVESTMENT TO HELP US DEVELOP<br />
THOSE AREAS. WE HAVE ALREADY BEEN ABLE TO POINT TO SOME AREAS<br />
OF MANUFACTURED GOODS AND SERVICES IN JAPAN BEING SUCCESSFUL.<br />
WHAT WE MUST DO NOW IS TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE CHANGES IN JOB<br />
NEEDS APPROACH THE JAPANESE APPROACH WHICH IS OPENING UP<br />
SECTORS OF THE MANUFACTURING MARKET HERE. WE BELIEVE THAT WE<br />
HAVE THE CAPACITY TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THAT.<br />
CAN I JUST BRIEFLY MAKE THIS POINT IF ONE KNEW ALL THE PRECISE<br />
ANSERS TO THE QUESTION ONE WOULDN'T NEED TO HAVE THESE IMPORT<br />
EXPANSION MISSIONS IN AUSTRALIA OR A BUSINESS MISSION FROM AUSTRA; IA<br />
TO JAPAN OR TO EMPLOY 7ESE CONSULTANCY FIRMS. BUT I DO MAKE THIS<br />
POINT THAT I BELIEVE THAT ONE AREA WHICH IS OBVIOUSLY OPEN FOR<br />
SIGNIFICANT EXPANSION IS IN PROCESSED FOODSTUFFS. WE ARE OBVIOUSLY<br />
WELL PLACED TO MANUFACTURE IN THAT AREA AND WITH THE RISING STANDARDS<br />
OF LIVING IN JAPAN IT SHOULD BE VERY RECEPTIVE MARKET FOR MANY<br />
OF OUR PRODUCTS IN THAT AREA. I USE THAT AS AN EXAMPLE.<br />
JOURNALIST: YOU INDICATED YOUR INTENTION TO INVITE MORE INVESTMENT<br />
IN MANUFACTURING SECTORS IN AUSTRALIA. DOES EPAC HAVE ANY<br />
DISCUSSIONS ON THE WOULD BE POLICIES AS TO THE INTRODUCTION OF<br />
INVESTMENT FROM FOREIGN COUNTRIES.<br />
PM: THE BASIC RESPONSIBILITY OF EPAC IS TO CONCERN ITSELF WITH<br />
MEDIUM TO LONGER TERM ECONOMIC GROWTH PATHS FOR AUSTRALIA. CLEARLY<br />
AS PART OF THE THINKING OF EPAC AS TO WHERE AUSTRALIA SHOULD MOVE<br />
TO MAXIMISE ITS GROWTH POTENTIAL, YES iT WILL BE CONCERNED AMONGST<br />
A WIDE RANGE OF ISSUES WITH THE QUESTION OF THE PLACE FOR FOREIGN<br />
INVESTMENT IN THAT GROWHT. BUT ' HAT WILL BE IN TERIS OP THE LONGER<br />
TERM PLANNING MECHANISMS IN THE FUNCTIONAL SENSE OF MAKING DECISION'<br />
ABOUT PARTICULAR INVESTMENT PROPOSALS, FOREIGN<br />
INVESTMENT PROPSALS. EPAC HAS NO ROLE IN THAT. THAT IS SOMETHING<br />
WHICH IS WITHIN THE PERVIEW OF THE NECHANISM THATWE HAVE I\ 0LACE<br />
THAT IS THE FOREIGN INVESTMENT REVIEW </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: PRIME MINISTER ONE OF THE DECISIONS YOUR GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL BE FACING FAIRLY SOON CONCERNS THE LEVELS OF PROTECTION AND<br />
ASSISTANCE TO THE AUSTRALIAN CAR INDUSTRY. COULD YOU TELL US<br />
HOW CONFIDENT YOU FEEL THAT WE CAN USE THE APPROACH YOU'VE OUTLINED<br />
HERE IN TOKYO TO INCREASE BOTH THE EFFICIENCY OF THE INDUSTRY AND<br />
ALSO LOWER PROTECTION BARRIERS WHEN THE GOVERNMENT MAKES THESE<br />
DECISIONS. PM: I CAN'T ANSWER THAT QUESTION AT THIS POINT. AS YOU KNOW<br />
THE FIRST STAGE OF THE PROCESS OF REVIEWING WHAT IS TO OCCUR AFTER<br />
THE EXPIRY OF THE PLAN WHICH IS OPERATING UP UNTIL THE END OF THIS<br />
YEAR HAS ALREADY BEEN UNDERTAKEN. SENATOR BUTTON SET UP THE<br />
COMMITTEE OF THE INTERESTED ELEMENTS IN THE INDUSTRY TO REVIEW<br />
THE POSITION AND MAKE SUGGESTIONS TO THE GOVERNMENT. THAT HAS<br />
NOT RESULTED IN ANY COMMON POSITION BEING PUT FROM THE PARTS OF * rHE<br />
GOVERNMENT CONSIDERING WHAT IS APPROPRIATE-FOR THE FUTURE. AND<br />
I CAN'T PRE-EMPT THE DISCUSSIONS WHICH ARE TAKING PLACE WITHIN THE<br />
REVELANT DEPARTMENTS OF GOVERNMENT. BU I WILL SAY THIS, THAT I<br />
WILL BE EXPECTING THAT WHAT WE DO IN RESPECT OF THE MOTOR VEHICLE<br />
MANUFACTURING COMPONENT INDUSTRY AND WHICH WILL COME NTO EFFECT<br />
IN 1985 WILL REFLECT BASICALLY THE THRUST THAT I HAVE BEEN ALLUDING<br />
TO RECENTLY AND MORE PARTICULARLY IN THE SPEECH THAT I MADE TODAY<br />
BY THE RELEVANT DEPARTMENTS. AND I HAVE TO ADMIT THAT THAT<br />
CONSIDERATION HAS NOT BEEN GREATLY ASSISTED BY THE CONSIDERATIONS;<br />
OF THE INDUSTRYt BY THE INDUSTRY ITSELF.<br />
JOURNALIST: I HAVE A QUESTION CONCERNING A KOALA BEAR. THE CITY<br />
OF OSAKA AS WELL AS THE CITY OF NAGOYA HAS BEEN REQUESTING ABOUT<br />
RECEIVING KOALA BEARS. WE UNDERSTAND THAT AT THE DINNER MEETING<br />
WITH THE PRIME MINISTER NAKASONE YOU MENTIONED SEVERAL KOALA BEARS<br />
TO BE BROUGHT INTO JAPAN: WHEN YOU MENTIONED SEVERAL KAOLA BEARS<br />
DID YOU INCLUDE THOSE TO BE SENT TO THE CITY OF OSAKA AND IS IT<br />
POSSIBLE FOR THE CITY OF OSAKA TO GET KOALA BEARS, AND IF IT''<br />
POSSIBLE, WHEN?<br />
PM: HERE IS A CLEAR AREA FOR SIGNIFICANT EXPAN4SION IN TRADING<br />
OPPORTUNITIES. I HAVE4' T MET ANYTHING SINCE I'VE BEEN IN JAPAN<br />
FOR WHICH THERE IS A GREATER DEMAND THAN KOALAS. SO WE W-ILL<br />
DO OUR BEST TO SATISFY THAT DEMAND AND. I BELIEVE THAT ACCORDING<br />
TO MY KOALA BEAR ADVISERS THAT THERE IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO SPEND<br />
KOALAS TO A NUMBER OF ZOOS AND I'M GIVEN TO UNDERSTAND THAT<br />
OSAKA IS VERY HIGH ON THE LIST OF PRIORITIES. AND IF I COULD USE<br />
A PHRASE WHICH HAS COME TO HAVE SOME CURRENCY IN RECENT<br />
MONTHS IN AUSTRALIA I THINK THAT WE WILL SEE KOALAS IN PLACE<br />
IF NOT IN GUM TREES IN OSAKA BEFORE THE END OF THIS YEAR.<br />
COULD I ADD THAT I HAVE IN MY MINISTRY A MINISTER WHO HAS A<br />
PARTICULAR RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE PROMOTION OF THE KOALA BEAR.<br />
NR BROWN, AND HE HAS TO MAKE UP TO THE KA-ALA BEAR BECAUSE HE<br />
WAS NOT COUITE AS FRIENDLY AS HE MIGHT HAVE BEEN IN HIS DESCRIPTION!<br />
OF THIS BEAUTIFUL CREATURE IN THE PAST AND I MAY SEE IF I CAN<br />
ARRANGE TO SEND HIM HERE WITH THE FIRST KOALA BEAR JUST TO PROVE<br />
THAT HE HAS MADE HIS PEACE WITH THE KOALA BEAR.<br />
JoURNALIST: MR HA-Wl-\ E YOU EMIPHASISED' IN YOUR SPEECH TO-DAY THAT<br />
THE WHOLE COMMUNITY STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT<br />
IN PREVIOUS TIMES SPECIFIC PROGRAMS To HELP THOSE EFFECTED<br />
BY STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENTS. DO YOU HAVE ANY SDECIFIC IDEAS ABO..-UT<br />
HOW WE CAN CHANGE OVER </p>
<p>PM: YES, I DO HAVE A NUMBER OF IDEAS ABOUT THIS. I'LL JUST GO TO<br />
THEM VERY BRIEFLY BUT I PREFACE WHAT I HAVE TO SAY BY<br />
REMAINDING YOU THAT AS I SAID IN THE SPEECH Ii TOGETHER WITH<br />
NEIL CURRIE, AS A MEMBER OF THE CRAWFORD COMMITTEE WHICH MET<br />
IN 1978/ 79 AND YOU WILL RECALL FROM YOUR EXTENSIVE READING OF<br />
THAT WELL REMEMBERED REPORT THAT WE ADDRESSED OURSELVES VERY<br />
SPECIFICALLY TO THIS QUESTION IN THAT REPORT. AND THE SORTS<br />
OF THINGS THAT I WOULD SAY IN ANSWER TO YOUR QUESTION NOW REALLY<br />
OF THINGS THAT I WOULD SAY IN ANSWER TO YOUR QUESTION NOW REALLY<br />
ARE A REFLECTION OF WHAT WE SAID THEN. LET ME PICK UP BRIEFLY<br />
SOME OF THE THINGS THAT WE SAID. THE FIRST THING THAT WE SAID<br />
IS THAT THE BEST FORM OF ASSISTANCE THAT CAN BE PROVIDED TO<br />
PEOPLE LIKELY TO BE EFFECTED BY CHANGE, IS THAT THE INDUSTRY AND<br />
THE FIRM ITSELF SHOULD IN ADVANCE OF CHANGE CONSULT WITH THOSE<br />
WHO ARE LIKELY TO BE EFFECTED, SO THAT THEY ARE NOT FACED SUDDENLY<br />
WITHOUT THE OPPORTUNITY THEMSELVES AND THE COMMUNITY OF<br />
ASSISTING THEM TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF TRAINING AND RETRAINING<br />
OR RE-LOCATION SCHEMES. SO PRIOR CONSULTATION WITHIN THE<br />
WORKFORCE LIKELY TO BE EFFECTED IS AN IMPORTANT ELEMENT.<br />
SECONDLY, WE SAID THAT FIRMS THEMSELVES SHOULD UNDERTAKE<br />
PROCESSES CONTINOUSLY OF TRAINING AND RETRAINING FOR CHANGE.<br />
THIRDLY. WE INDICATED THAT GOVERNMENTS SHOULD GIVE EMPHASIS<br />
IN THEIR TOTAL EDUCATION PROGRAM TO ADULT TRAINING AND RETRAINING,<br />
AND EMPHASIS WHICH HASN'T BEEN PARTICULARLY APPARENT IN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN EDUCATION SYSTEM IN THE PST. SO THAT PEOPLE WHO HAVE LEFT<br />
THE FORMAL EDUCATION SYSTEM IN THE PAST. SO THAT PEOPLE WHO HAVE<br />
LEFT THE FORMAL EDUCATION SYSTEM AND HAVE GONE INTO THE WORKFORCE ARE<br />
GOING TO HAVE AVAILABLE TO THEM THE OPPORTUNITY TO RE-EQUIP<br />
THEMSELVES FOR NEW POSSIBLE AVENUES OF EMPLOYMENT. THE NEXT THING<br />
THAT I WOULD SAY IS THAT WE NEED TO HAVE PROVISIONS FOR POSSIBLE<br />
RE-LOCATION ASSISTANCE IF PEOPLE MAY HAVE TO MOVE FROM ONE AREA TO<br />
ANOTHER. THAT BURDEN SHOULDN'T BE BORNE BY THEM ALONE. THOSE ARE,<br />
IF YOU LIKE, SOME OF THE MORE OBVIOUS FEATURES OF WHAT WE NEED TO DO.<br />
AND THE BROAD THINGS WE HAVE ALREADY STRARTED9 AS YOU KNOW, TO MAKE<br />
DECISIONS WITH REGARD TO THE PROVISION OF VENTURE CAPITAL IN<br />
AUSTRALIA AND ADDITIONAL ASSISTANCE FOR RESEARCH AND DEVELOMENT. THE<br />
POINT OF THESE THINGS IS TO HAVE GOVERNMENTS PROVIDING ASSISTANCE FOR<br />
THE CREATION OF LIKELY NEW INDUSTRIES. WE CANT SIMPLY SIT BACK AND<br />
SAY WELL, THIS PARTICULAR INDUSTRY IS BECOMING LESS RELEVANT YOU<br />
ARE ACTIVELY TAKING STEPS TO TRY AND EITHER BUILD UP EXISTING<br />
INDUSTRIES OR CREATE NEW ONES. SO WITHOUT BEING EXHAUSTIVE THOSE ARE<br />
SOME OF THE THINGS THAT WILL NEED TO BE CONSIDERED BY MY GOVERNMENT<br />
AND TO BE DISCUSSED BY THE COMMUNITY. WE HAVE, AS YOU CAN SEE,<br />
ALREADY MADE SOME DECISIONS WHICH ARE RELEVANT IN THIS DIRECTION.<br />
NOW THE PACE AT WHICH WE CAN GO AS A COMMUNITY TO MAKE THE FURTHER<br />
SORTS OF CHANGES TO WHICH I HAVE ALLUDED WILL DEPEND UPON THE EXTENT<br />
OF CONSULTATIONS WITH INDUSTRY, THE UNIONS AND WITHIN GOVERNMENT.<br />
AND ITS THAT PROCESS WHICH WE WILL BE URGENTLY UNDERTAKING.<br />
JOURNALIST: PRIME MINISTER AS YOU SAID EARLIER THE AUSTRALIAN/ JAPAN<br />
RELATIONSHIP HAS BEEN VERY STRONG AND AS YOU JUST SAID YOU ARE<br />
GOING TO FURTHER STRENGTHEN OUR RELATIONSHIP. I THINK IN THIS<br />
REGARD IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THE PEOPLE OF BOTH NATIONS TO KNO<br />
EACH OTHER. SO WITH REGARD TO THE CULTRAL ASPECTS OF RELATIONSHIFS<br />
IN CULTURAL TERMS OF COURSE AUSTRALIANS, I THINK, SOME EXCHANGEE<br />
HAVE TAKEN PLACE, FOR EXAMPLE-AT PRIVATE LEVELS FOR EXAMPLE<br />
SOIE UNVIERSITIES ARE EXCHANGING FACULTY MEMBERS OR STUDENTS.<br />
WELL ON THE PART OF YOUR GOVERNMENT [ O YOU HAVE ANY SPECIFIC<br />
IDEA OR POLICY TO PROMOTE THE CULTURAL EXCHANGE BETWEEN THE<br />
IWO COUNTRIES. </p>
<p>PM: YES, IT IS PART OF OUR OVERALL THINKING ABOUT HOW TO<br />
STRENGTHEN RELATIONS BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES. YOU REFERRED TO<br />
EXCHANGES AT THE ACADEMIC LEVEL THEY ARE TAKING PLACE. I<br />
THINK ONE OF THE BASIC THINGS THAT WE HAVE TO LOOK AT IN ADDRESSING<br />
THAT QUESTION IS THE ACTUAL PROVISIONS FOR PHYSICALLY MOVING PEOPLE<br />
BETWEEN JAPAN AND AUSTRALIA AND I MUST SAY THAT THERE HAVE BEEN SOME<br />
SUGGESTIONS THAT THE SERVICES PROVIDED BY OUR TWO AIRLINES<br />
MAY NOT ALWAYS HAVE AS ADEQUATE AS THEY MIGHT BE. AN I<br />
KNOW THERE HAVE BEEN DISCUSSIONS GOING ON BETWEEN OUR GOVERNMENT<br />
AND OUR AIRLINES AS TO HOW WE MAY BE ABLE TO IMPROVE THE<br />
FACILITIES FOR TRAVELLING, QANTAS AND JAPAN AIRLINES. AND I WOULD<br />
CERTAINLY HOPE THAT WE MAY BE ABLE TO MAKE EASIER TRAVEL BETWEEN<br />
THESE TWO COUNTRIES. NOW AS TO SPECIFIC ASPECTS OF THE STRENGTHENING<br />
OF CULTURAL RELATIONSHIPS, I HAVEN'T MYSELF COME WITH ANY<br />
PROPOSALS, BUT I CAN SAY THIS TO YOU, THAT ANY SUGGESTION<br />
THAT MAY BE FORTHCOMING FROM RELEVANT ORGANISATIONS IN JAPAN FOR<br />
INCREASING THE LEVEL OF CULTURAL EXCHANGE WOULD BE ELOMED<br />
BY US. AND IN TURN MY GOVERNMENT WOULD WISH TO SEE ANY<br />
EXTENSION OF ACTIVITY FROM AUSTRALIA COMING TO YOUR COUNTRY.<br />
WE BELIEVE VERY SIRONGLY, AS I'VE SAID BEFORE, GOVERNMENTS<br />
uaN DO SO MUCH IN PROVIDING A BASIC FRAMEWORK FOR IMPROVING RELAIIONS<br />
BEIWEEN uUR IWO CUOUNIRIES. OBVIOUSL CHOSE SORTS OF THINGS<br />
NEED TO BE FLESHED OU T BY THE ACTIVITY OF THE PEOPLE. WE<br />
ARE PROUD IN AUSTRALIA OF THE DIVERSITY OF CULTURAL ACHIEVEMENTS<br />
WHICH WE PRESENT WE HAVE EXPORTED MANY OF THOSE TO MANY PARTS<br />
OF THE WORLD. AN THEY RANGE FROM DANCE, THEATRE, BALLET AND<br />
FILM, WITHOUT BEING EXHAUSTIVE. WE ARE PROUD OF WHAT WE CAN SHOW<br />
TO THE REST OF THE WORLD IN THE AREA OF CULTURAL ACHIEVEMENT AND<br />
WE WOULD WISH. TO SHARE THESE WITH YOUR COUNTRY AND IN RETURN TO<br />
RECEIVE IN AUSTRALIA THE MANY DIVERSE MANIFESTATIONS OF YOUR RICH<br />
CULTURAL TRADITIONS. I REPEAT AND EMPHASISE THAT ANY SPECIFIC<br />
PROPOSALS THAT THERE MAY BE WITHIN JAPAN TO STRENGTHEN SUCH<br />
RELATIONSHIPS WE WOULD WELCOME.<br />
PM: BEFORE WE FINISH THIS SESSION I DO NEED TO CLARIFY ONE<br />
MATTER. IF WE GO FROM CULTURE BACK TO KOALAS. IT HAS BEEN<br />
POINTED OUT TO ME AND LWAS UNCERTAIN IN THIS REGARD AND IT<br />
APPROPRIATE THAT IT BE CORRECTED, THAT THE ZOO FACILITIES HRE<br />
OSAKA, AS I UNDERSTAND IT, HAVE NOT BEEN PREPARED AT THIS POINT TO<br />
RECEIVE THIS DELICATE CREATURE. AN I SAY SERIOUSLY THAT IS IS A<br />
DELICATE CREATURE. YOU JUST CAN'T SEND A KOALA NYWHERE.<br />
AND THERE ARE OTHER ZOOS, AND I THINK PARTICULARLY NAGOYA, WHICH<br />
HAVE MADE MUCH MORE EXTENSIVE PREPARATIONS<br />
FOR RECIEIVING THE KOALA. SO YOU WILL APPRECIATE THE IMPORTANCE<br />
WHICH WE ATTACH TO THIS UNIQUE ANIMAL AND WE ARE NOT GOING TO<br />
BE PREPARED TO EXPOSE IT TO ENVIRONMENTS WITHIN WHICH WE THINK<br />
IT WILL NOT BE ABLE SECURELY TO FLOURSIH. AND SO IT IS THE CASE<br />
THAT WHEN WE DO SEND A KOALA TO JPAN THAT IT FIRST GO TO THOSE<br />
ZOOS WHICH HAVE DONE THE MOST WORK IN PREPARATION TO ENSURE THE<br />
SAFETY, NOT MERELY THE SAFETY BUT THE ENVIRONMENTAL SECURITV,<br />
OF THE KOALA. AND AS I UNDERSTAND IT NAGOYA IS THE ZOO WHICH HAS<br />
AT THIS STAGE BEST PREPARED AND BEST PLACED. SO IF OSAKA<br />
HAS WANT TO SHARE OUR NATIONAL TREASURE IN THIS REGARD<br />
IT WILL HAVE TO MAKE ADE( CUAI'E PREPARATIONS TO RECEIVE THE KOALA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
