<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6030</transcript-id>
    <title>LABOR&#039;S ABDICATION: GOVERNMENT BY THE UNIONS FOR THE UNIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006030.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 8.00PM<br />
FOR MEDIA 20 FEBRUARY, 1983<br />
LABOR'S ABDICATION GOVERNMENT BY THE UNIONS FOR THE UNIONS<br />
Finally we have Labor's real policy speech. Last week<br />
speech at the Opera House just gave us Labor's starting<br />
price of $ 2750 million.<br />
Labor's so-called prices and incomes policy, set out in the<br />
Statement of Accord by the Australian Labor Party and the<br />
Australian Council of Trade Unions regarding Economic Policy,<br />
dated February 1983, is in every sense a blueprint for union<br />
government. It means government by the unions for the unions.<br />
Union Veto<br />
This 324 page document dots the I's and crosses the T's on<br />
the greatest ever attempted sell-out to left-wing union<br />
control of the national government and economy.<br />
From the moment Mr Hawke signs this blueprint he becomes the<br />
puppet leader of a Labor Party subject to union veto in<br />
respect of virtually every significant decision of national<br />
government. This is made totally plain by the statement " the policies<br />
detailed in this document are agreed between the parties<br />
rather than imposed by the government". 6)<br />
The document not only makes it plain that the policies it<br />
covers are agreed between the parties, but that modifications<br />
to those policies must also be agreed or else the compact is<br />
broken. That gives the union militants the right of veto across a<br />
broad range of government policy. They would have a veto over<br />
laws to regulate union behaviour ( pp 15-16), levels of protection<br />
20), the number of migrants 23), even over assistance<br />
to non-achieving students in primary schools 29). This<br />
would paralyse democratic government and transfer power from<br />
Parliament to the Gallaghers, Carmichaels and Halfpernny's of<br />
this world. </p>
<p>In one stroke ti-is dockiment has given the ecoIiiununist~ s and<br />
fellow travellers rrore than they could ever have got fromi<br />
the ballot box. ' Phis document has giv ' en them real political<br />
power but without any pUhlic accountability.<br />
Now we know why M~ r flawke is so 1; een about his Economic Smni<br />
He wants to lift the ACTU to parity. with the national qovcinm( neTt<br />
and give it equivalent power.<br />
WAGES SRTUPID1TY<br />
Once again Labor and the u. nion leaders have xejected the need<br />
for wage restraint; once again they have shown callous<br />
disregard for the interests of the unemployedi. Their w'age<br />
propcosals are economic madness.<br />
The document states categorically that systern of full<br />
cost of living adjustments will be strongly supported in<br />
tripartite consul tation~ s and before inaus trial tribunals".<br />
9) The words " will be supported" obviously mean by the<br />
Labor Party and tlie unions. A Labor Government would be<br />
the adviocate of the traoe unions in industrial tribuntals.<br />
Th ere would be no one to argue the case for all Australians.<br />
Their approach to wages would set in concrete Australia's<br />
excessive labour costs and ouor lack of international<br />
competitiveness. Their approach to wages would cost<br />
Australians ten$ of thousands of jobs. l' 1I&gt; Dolart said<br />
last January don' t wanit to sour d cynical abou). t this<br />
and I'm definitely norjt trying to, but _ Nhile ' hreare*<br />
of workers uncmployed, . there Are 90% itl. c-rploynient."<br />
In the battle for survival against adverse economic conditions,<br />
employers would be faced by the corRbined weight of unionsand<br />
Government, not only in the wage tribunals but also in<br />
negotiations about over award payments. " Where over award<br />
payments exist the Government will support the maintenance<br />
of those levels in real termrs Simll businessmen<br />
would be bankrupted; big businesn would be crippled.<br />
Ioflationi would be institutional ised and tinerployment would<br />
be a permanent fact of life for vast nurabers of Austra-ianfs-.<br />
There is abSOlutely TLO way that Australia's manufacturing<br />
inatustry, already unpompetiti\' e after last year's wage<br />
explosion, could survive full wage inaexation.<br />
On top of all that, the disastrous thrust for shorter working<br />
houirs would be supported by a Labor Government. " Bargaining<br />
based upon achieving increased procluctivity via changer. in<br />
work: practices or procedures as a means of redu4ci ng hours<br />
at negligible cost increases, will continue to be<br />
supported </p>
<p>Everyone knows that shorter hours mean higher costs; everyone<br />
knows that the drive for shorter hours has contributed<br />
materially to Australia's current economic difficulties.<br />
Labor and the union leaders either refuse to learn the lessons<br />
of our recent past, or simply do not care, This would<br />
institutionalize the wage-price, spiral and worsen unemployment.<br />
TAXATION A Labor Government's taxation pol'icy would be subject to<br />
control by militant union leaders.<br />
This document outlines precisely what a Labor Government would<br />
be required to do.<br />
_ s well as a general desire for lower income tax, the unions<br />
have also directed that Labor should endeavour to reduce<br />
the relative incidence of indirect taxation. 12)<br />
Labor has already offered massive spending increases. Cutting<br />
both direct and indirect taxes as well would bankrupt Australia.<br />
It is economic lunacy.<br />
The madness doesn't stop there, A Labor Government couldn't<br />
change taxation rates at any time without the permission of<br />
union Teaders,<br />
Furthermore, the document says that a Labor Government,<br />
in conjunction with the trade union movement, will<br />
annually review the tax scale so that the tax burden will not rise<br />
automatically with inflation". ( p. 11/ 12) and it also states<br />
that the Government would discuss any " general rise in<br />
taxation" with the unions -efore " seeking to give effect to ( p. 13<br />
Clearly again, the unions would control the tax policy of a<br />
tabor -Go-vernment.<br />
By regulating the incomes of unincorporated enterprises<br />
10), that is the self-employed, shopkeepers, builders<br />
and tradesmun, the Labor Party and unions will strike at<br />
the heart of incentive and enterprise. In their determination<br />
to increase the powers of the unions over the economy, Labor and<br />
the unions would destroy the self-employed and small business<br />
people who are not -uqionised and never want to be.<br />
MASSIVE INTERVENTION AND SURVEILLANCE<br />
Trade-union involvement is to be enforced in every aspect<br />
of economic advice, economic planning and detailed<br />
economic control of every sector of activity. The only<br />
group who is to be immone from intervention and immune<br />
from the law are the trade union leaders themselves. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
The document says that " comprehensive" and " closely ponitored"<br />
interventionist policies are neccessary to achieve the desircd level<br />
of gz-vth, with a * planinirtq rr~:~ vtism to assist " the tvansition of the<br />
e-OrIOfnY -into -a Planned framework". ( pp 17-18)<br />
The lives and incom~ es of " shopkeeqpers, self-emnployed builders<br />
aind tradesmen etc. 4, are-to be subject to a whole new riaige<br />
of government controls.<br />
Business enterprise is to he suppressed, with bureaucratic<br />
control andl government int : vention ta~ ing over from the mnarke~ tplace<br />
at every level. No one will escape from the largest companies<br />
to the smallest corner shop or Luilding sub-con tractor. Suibjec t<br />
to the permission of union leadcrs at every turn, a Labor Government<br />
bound by this dloclupent Would embark on a program of massive<br />
interv. ention and surveillance to convert Australia into a<br />
planned socialist economy for the benefit of the powerful unions.<br />
All sectors of inclustry, both public and private, are to<br />
he integrated 18), and there is to be wide-ranging<br />
regulation of manufacturing activity., There will be a<br />
pricing authority operating under legislative criteria<br />
" designed to ensure that enterprises do ) iot earn profit<br />
beyond levels necessary for the maintenance and expansion<br />
of the enterprise..." And the States would be asked<br />
to use their*. kinlimited constitutional powe. r" t~ o assist<br />
in "... regilating prices charged by important sections of<br />
the non-corporate area". 11).<br />
CONCLUSION Wage increases, hours reductions, extensive * intervention<br />
and regulation, massive spending, both direct and indirect<br />
tax cuts, and huge Budget deficits: that's what this<br />
document promises the union leadership. What it promises<br />
the people of* Australia is higher inflation, higher interest<br />
rates, no investment, no growth anid no jobs. Economic<br />
insanity is the only way to desordlhe it Bankruptcy can be<br />
its only result.<br />
The document lays down that the role of Government shall<br />
be " accommodatin'g and supportive" 7) Accomiodating<br />
and supportive to whom Obviously the militant trade<br />
union leadership._______<br />
The Australian community, and ordinary rank and file trade<br />
unions are ignored. Mr Hawke has not only given the<br />
unions. everything. they could have possibly wanted in wage<br />
adjustments, in Government support for wage madness, but<br />
on top of that chiaritable gesture he has handed to* the<br />
union -leadership the specific written power of veto over<br />
Government decision-making.. </p>
<p>Now we kriow why he said there was no prices and irngomi S<br />
policy in Britain. The British Labor Party never offered<br />
this total and absolute abdication.<br />
Mr Joel Barnett, the Labor Government's Chief Secretary<br />
to the Treasury, had this to say about the British social<br />
contract: we went much further in the way we co-operated<br />
under the terms of the qLuaJntly titled Social<br />
Contract, supposedly cnshrining a ncwrelaUio3] ship<br />
between g overnrment and unio~ is. To my mind, the<br />
only give and take in the contract was that the<br />
Government gave and the unions took".<br />
' IWe were, after all, stil1 in the middle of the<br />
disastrous ' Social Contract' it may have helped<br />
to secure our election victory but it did nothing<br />
to prevent some would argue it ensured the 27%<br />
growth in earnings ( in 1974)".<br />
What Mr Hawke is trying to sell to Australians would have<br />
far more damaging consequences.<br />
Mr Hawke's real policy speech, to be signed and sealed<br />
tomorrow, does not seek a mandate to govern for all<br />
Australians. It seeks a mandate to hand over the r<br />
Australia to the powerful unions.<br />
There is no way in the world Australians will have a<br />
bar of that kind of Government. -ooo00ooo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
