<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4549</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH REGIONAL MEETING - MELBOURNE, FEBRUARY 1978, 18 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004549.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
(-7<br />
F 77/ 263<br />
, Jij AUSI AL I( A J1,<br />
FOR PRESS 18 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
COMMONWEALTH REGIONAL. MEETING.. MELBOURNE,. FEBRUARY 1978<br />
A meeting of Commonwealth regional Heads of Government,' which<br />
was an Australian initiative at the Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government meeting in London, is to take place in Melbourne<br />
early next year.<br />
Present planning is proceeding on the basis of a meeting in<br />
Melbourne next February.<br />
Invitations have been extended to the Heads of Government of<br />
eleven regional Commonwealth countries Bangladesh, Fiji, India,<br />
Malaysia, Nauru, New Zealand, Papua New Guinea, Singapore,<br />
Sri Lanka, Tonga and Western Samoa.<br />
The agenda for the meeting will consist of international and<br />
Commonwealth matters of interest to the region, and is expected<br />
to include, subject to consultations with the Goverinments<br />
concerned, regional economic and functional co-operation,<br />
international economic issues and regional political trends.<br />
The agenda will be discussed in detail at an officials' meeting<br />
in London next month, and will then be submitted to the participating<br />
Heads of Government for approval.<br />
The communique issued after the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
meeting in London in June endorsed the concept of informal<br />
regional consultative arrangements among Commonwealth countries.<br />
The matter was one on which I spoke in London suggesting that<br />
informal consultations among regional leaders would have a<br />
number of advantages. I am pleased at the progress-~ made in<br />
recent weeks.<br />
The Commonwealth Secretary General, Mr. Ramphal, has been<br />
encouraging in his reaction to a regional meting, and has<br />
accepted an invitation. to attend.<br />
In London, the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting saw<br />
regional consultation as enhancing co-operation on matters of<br />
Commonwealth interest and furthering collective Commonwealth<br />
objectives. The Australian initiative for a' Commonwealth regional<br />
meeting has been taken in this spirit. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
