<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7031</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OECD SCIENCE CONFERENCE CANBERRA - 11 NOVEMBER  1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/11/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007031.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OECD SCIENCE CONFERENCE<br />
CANBERRA 11 NOVEMBER 1986<br />
Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
On behalf of the Australian Government I extend a warm<br />
welcome to all of the participants in this conference and,<br />
in particular, to the many distinguished visitors from<br />
overseas. Nothing could be more fitting than that the first<br />
major OECD conference to be held in this country should be<br />
on " Policies and Directions for Science and Research".<br />
Australian industries, academic institutions and governments<br />
in recent years have united on the urgency of increased and<br />
more productive effort in science and technology research<br />
and development. Just a few weeks ago I opened an important<br />
conference convened by major companies and the<br />
vice-chancellors of our universities focusing on precisely<br />
this critical issue.<br />
In many ways few countries are more directly and acutely<br />
aware of the need to meet this challenge. We live, after<br />
all, in the Asia-Pacific basin, the fastest developing<br />
economic region in the world. On our doorstep are many of<br />
the countries which have most impressively harnessed science<br />
and technology in the service of economic growth and<br />
development. If this were not sufficient incentive we have in Barry<br />
Jones, our Minister for Science, a passionate and energetic<br />
advocate of the importance of science and research for this<br />
nation's future. A recognised authority in his own right on<br />
this topic, I thank Barry for opening this conference this<br />
morning. I I </p>
<p>When I referred to the broad coalition of commitment that<br />
exists in Australia on this issue I was speaking from<br />
personal experience. one of this Government's early acts<br />
was to convene a conference on technology. From the very<br />
start we have included discussion of, and action on, the<br />
role of science and technology in our plans to revitalise<br />
Australia's economic performance.<br />
Clearly, we are in step with our fellow OECD members in the<br />
significance we attach to this issue, as it was at the 1982<br />
heads of State meeting in Versailles that science and<br />
technology was first placed on the agenda.<br />
I understand this conference will contribute to the proposed<br />
OECD Ministerial level meeting of the Committee for<br />
Scientific and Technological Policy next year. As joint<br />
sponsor, Australia is proud to be facilitating attempts by<br />
OECD Governments to enhance the role that science and<br />
technology can play in encouraging economic advancement.<br />
I would now like to take a little time outlining the role of<br />
science and research in Australia's economy and the measures<br />
the Government is taking to encourage greater effort in<br />
these areas.<br />
Australia has traditionally relied for its standard of<br />
living on a rich endowment of natural resources. From this<br />
base we have developed internationally competitive and<br />
highly successful agricultural, mining and energy based<br />
industries. importantly, the development of these<br />
industries has relied on science and technology.<br />
Agriculture, for example, benefited from the early<br />
improvements in shipping transport and refrigeration<br />
technology which gave Australia access to rapidly growing<br />
world markets. Equally importantly the efficiency of our<br />
agriculture relied, and still does, on a high quality<br />
science and research base. Appropriately that base has been<br />
provided largely in the public sector but has been closely<br />
attuned to user requirements.<br />
More recently the Government has moved on several fronts to<br />
improve the resources available for rural research and<br />
development. Technological innovation is an essential<br />
element in maintaining and improving international<br />
competitiveness in rural industries. Our commodity<br />
exporters, in general, have had to be highly innovative to<br />
remain competitive in the world markets in which they have<br />
predominantly operated.<br />
But this traditional reliance on commodity exports has left<br />
us vulnerable and exposed to the recent major slump in the<br />
international prices of primary commodities. In the face of<br />
depressed mineral commodity markets and heavily distoring<br />
agricultural trading practices of the EEC and the US, we<br />
cannot expect a substantial turnaround in our terms of trade<br />
in the near future. Australia can now starkly see the need<br />
to restructure our economy with particular emphasis on </p>
<p>diversifying our export portfolio into manufacturing and<br />
services. of course science and technology will play a<br />
leading role in this restructuring.<br />
At a time when manufactures and services have led the growth<br />
in world trade Australia has not been part of that<br />
development. As a resul * t our share in world trade has<br />
fallen sharply, from 12th world ranking in 1973 to 23rd by<br />
1983.<br />
These res~ ults have forced the increasing acceptance here<br />
that manufacturing must become more outward looking. I am<br />
pleased to say from first hand experience that there is<br />
increasing evidence that industry is alive to the<br />
possibilities now open to Australia. Last week I opened an<br />
exciting building program for a local pharmaceutical company<br />
that is aiming to sell 80 per cent of its products on<br />
international markets.<br />
Plainly the most desirable new course for our manufacturers<br />
would be the one which applies science and technology most<br />
effectively to the production of innovative goods and<br />
services. Proving this point is the fact that the<br />
technology intensive products, headed by the electronics<br />
industry, computers and scientific equipment have been the<br />
fastest growing components of world trade in manufactures.<br />
At present Australia devotes about one per cent of its GDP<br />
to research and development a disappointingly low figure<br />
compared with the leading OECD countries. Not only large<br />
economies like the U. S. and Japan but also countries with<br />
more comparably sized economies such as Sweden and the<br />
Netherlands devote figures approaching around 3 per cent.<br />
Much of our research effort is in basic research rather than<br />
market driven research undertaken by industry. more to the<br />
point, while the overall level of public sector investment<br />
in research and development has been broadly comparable with<br />
that in most OECD countries, expenditure by the private<br />
sector compares most unfavourably, especially in<br />
manufacturing. Averaging about 0.2 per cent of GDP it falls<br />
way behind the figure of 0.9 per cent for leading comparable<br />
medium sized OECD countries. Therefore it is no surprise<br />
that our industrial products have often lacked the<br />
competitive edge that comes from industrial research and<br />
development. The substantial depreciation of the Australian dollar has<br />
boosted the price competitiveness of Australian industry.<br />
We must take advantage of this but we cannot rely on price<br />
alone as a basis for sustained competitiveness in the longer<br />
term. There will always be countries with cost structures which we<br />
neither should nor could emulate. These countries will<br />
always be able to make many products more cheaply than we<br />
can, so our competitiveness must be bolstered by enhancing<br />
the non-pr~ ce attributes of the goods and services we<br />
produce. </p>
<p>innovation enhances competitiveness in areas such as product<br />
quality, lower rates of defects and better product<br />
performance. The key to the product and process development<br />
necessary for sustainable long term competitiveness<br />
therefore is innovation based on locally performed research<br />
and development.<br />
Innovation requires firms to undertake research and<br />
development particularly applied research and product<br />
development closely linked with opportunities in the market.<br />
Having given you a brief and frank outline of the state of<br />
Australian industrial R&amp; D, I would like now to outline the<br />
course this Government has mapped to get the best return for<br />
our country from our wealth of human resources.<br />
Our strategy is, put simply, to provide incentives to<br />
increased private sector R&amp; D activity while maintaining the<br />
overall level and improving the effectiveness of public<br />
sector investment in R&amp; D.<br />
overseas studies of innovation policy show governments can<br />
act to complement the innovatory endeavours of technically<br />
progressive managers in industry by creating a national<br />
environment conducive to innovation. in the final analysis,<br />
however, these studies show that much depends upon the<br />
abilities of industrial managers.<br />
Private sector R&amp; D activity shares many of the<br />
characteristics of private sector investment generally. R&amp; D<br />
expenditure tends to be undertaken by firms and industries<br />
in response to profit opportunities. significantly in this<br />
context the Government has first and fundamentally restored<br />
the conditions for business profitability. By improving the<br />
overall investment climate we have improved the demand for<br />
innovation, including through industrial R&amp; D.<br />
we have also acted to provide direct incentives for<br />
innovation. These include a 150% tax concession for<br />
expenditure by the private sector on research and<br />
development, a complementary R&amp; D grants scheme, a tax<br />
incentive for private sector venture capital investment as a<br />
complement to financial market deregulation, changes to<br />
government purchasing and offsets arrangements designed to<br />
give higher priority to technology and industrial<br />
development, and strengthening of support provided through<br />
Austrade for high technology exporters.<br />
The tax incentive for R&amp; D puts the decision on what R&amp; D is<br />
to be conducted squarely in the hands of business. In this<br />
way it provides for the most effective linkage between<br />
market pull and technology push. importantly, it provides a<br />
major incentive for the many foreign owned companies<br />
operating in Australia to locate more of their R&amp; D activity<br />
here and to develop this country as a base for export<br />
activity. </p>
<p>it also provides an incentive for industry to establish<br />
closer links with public sector research particularly in the<br />
early years as industry scales up its own research<br />
capability. There are encouraging early signs of progress<br />
in all these respects.<br />
So far nearly 1700 companies have registered for the tax<br />
incentive and report an overall increase of about 40% in<br />
real terms in their R&amp; D expenditure in 1985/ 86, the first<br />
year of the scheme's operation.<br />
In their recent report on Australia's Science and Technology<br />
policies the OECD Examiners favoured tax based incentives<br />
over grants as a means of stimulating R&amp; D. At the same time<br />
the examiners noted that tax-based schemes do little to help<br />
small companies still struggling to become profitable.<br />
The scheme of Grants for Industry Research and Development<br />
( GIRD) introduced as a complement to the tax scheme is<br />
directed at just such companies and particularly those which<br />
can demonstirate potential improved competitiveness and<br />
export earnings.<br />
Another feature of the grants scheme is that it provides<br />
specific assistance for nominated technologies of<br />
fundamental importance to industrial competitiveness and<br />
with a widespread impact across many sectors of industry.<br />
Biotechnology is the first area to be identified in this<br />
scheme. Consideration is being given to further nominations<br />
such as new materials and microelectronics information<br />
technology. The biotechnology scheme has established vital connections<br />
between scientists in public sector research organisations<br />
and companiies which can commercialise a research<br />
achievement. A good example is the collaboration between<br />
CSIRO's Division of Tropical Animal Science and the company<br />
Biotechno"' ogy Australia. The project aims to develop a<br />
vaccine against cattle tick, based on synthesis of the<br />
tick's antigen by recombinant DNA procedures in<br />
micro-organisms.<br />
Overall therefore, the Government has, and is continuing to,<br />
provide a major stimulus to private sector R&amp; D activity. As<br />
I have indicated there are signs already that the private<br />
sector is responding. But we still have a way to go before<br />
we can be sure that we have attained the levels of<br />
innovative activity that can sustain long term<br />
competitiveness in world markets.<br />
As business increasingly accepts the need for innovation, it<br />
will also become more aware of the substantial assets<br />
available to it in public sector research and of the need to<br />
draw on this resource to assist its own product development<br />
work. of course this does not mean that the public sector<br />
should become directly involved in product development. But<br />
it does call for a wide variety of interactions between<br />
public and private research. </p>
<p>In Australia we already have underway a broad review of<br />
public sector investment in research and development. A<br />
principal concern in this review is to ensure that the<br />
substantial investment in public sector research contributes<br />
to our fundamental objective of enhancing innovation and<br />
competitiveness in industry.<br />
Among the measures already taken as part of the review have<br />
been the setting of new directions for the Commonwealth<br />
Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation ( CSIRO)<br />
our major Government research organisation. The review of<br />
CSIRO was prompted, in part, by a growing perception that<br />
some sections of CSIRO were paying insufficient attention to<br />
the real needs of industry and the community. As a result<br />
of the review we have accepted a series of recommendations<br />
designed to change the general ethos of the organisation.<br />
In the future, the emphasis is to be on applicationsoriented<br />
research and the strengthening of links at all<br />
levels between the organisation and the users of its<br />
research results.<br />
The largest component of public sector involvement in<br />
research in Australia is in the higher education system.<br />
The Government will shortly be taking decisions on future<br />
directions in higher education research based on the ASTEC<br />
review which is nearing completion.<br />
The challenge facing universities is to ensure that the most<br />
effective use is made of their funds. We have now seen a<br />
decade in which general or recurrent funding for<br />
universities research has remained about constant in real<br />
terms. During this period the growth in university research<br />
funds has come through more specialised funding schemes<br />
which are allocated competitively.<br />
These include the National Energy Research Development and<br />
Demonstration Program, the Australian Biotechnology Scheme,<br />
the Marine Sciences and Technologies Grants Scheme, the<br />
program for promotion of excellence in research which has<br />
led to the establishment of special research centres, and<br />
the key centre for teaching and research.<br />
These funds represent important supplements to the<br />
underlying levels of funding. But institutions have been<br />
slow to move towards more competitive internal funding<br />
arrangements which would allocate recurrent resources more<br />
selectively to the best and most productive researchers. In<br />
establishing suitable mechanisms university administrators<br />
could well look to practices in other OECD countries and to<br />
the practices of other major research performers in<br />
Au st rali a.<br />
Such developments do not, to my mind, impinge upon academic<br />
freedom. There is no basic conflict between excellence in<br />
research and the relevance of that research to national<br />
goals. The Government and the higher education institutions<br />
have a common purpose in seeking the best and most effective<br />
research from the funds which are available. </p>
<p>We do have encouraging evidence of closer links between<br />
university and industry.<br />
I have mentioned the recent inaugural forum meeting between<br />
the chief executives of universities represented by the<br />
Australian Vice Chancellors' Committee ( AVCC) and of<br />
business represented by the Business Council of Australia<br />
( BCA). Recent initiatives by the Minister for Education,<br />
including the establishment of an industry reference group,<br />
are designed to further facilitate this important<br />
interaction.<br />
An example of a program funded by the Government to promote<br />
collaboration between industry and tertiary education<br />
institutions is the Teaching Company Scheme. Under the<br />
scheme a research project of industrial relevance conducted<br />
in a firm is jointly supervised by the firm and university.<br />
The scheme is valuable for technology transfer and in<br />
particular for allowing industry to tap the skills of highly<br />
specialised personnel in ways which would not otherwise have<br />
been possible. it is expected that one hundred such<br />
projects will be funded next year.<br />
obviously the Government believes there is a strong case for<br />
a level of public funding of research and development in<br />
Australia which is at least comparable to that of the better<br />
performing medium-sized OECD countries.<br />
Because of the introduction of the tax concession and the<br />
need for continuing budget restraint, it is unrealistic to<br />
expect major additional funds to be allocated to public<br />
sector research organisations. The challenge for publicly<br />
funded institutions is to use the resources already<br />
available to them in as flexible a manner as possible.<br />
Necessarily I have dealt largely with the economic<br />
implications of the policies and directions for science and<br />
research. But that should not be taken as the only measure<br />
of the esteem Australians have for-individual skills and<br />
prestige of our scientific community. The manifest<br />
commitment to excellence shines through in so much of the<br />
work that is undertaken in their probing of the frontiers of<br />
human knowledge and experience. Australians have shown the<br />
ability to undertake research and development initiatives<br />
equal to any in the world.<br />
Of course there is an international as well as a domestic<br />
dimension to our interests in science. Australia has a long<br />
and proud tradition of international co-operation in<br />
scientific endeavours. Australia was, to take one topical<br />
example, a founding member of the United Nations Committee<br />
on the Peaceful Uses of Outer Space.<br />
Those involved in scientific research have a special<br />
responsibility and capacity to contribute to peace and<br />
security. In the Australian context, science and research<br />
have a particularly important contribution to make in </p>
<p>enhancing our capacity for defence self-reliance and in<br />
facilitating the conditions necessary for effective arms<br />
control. Australia's size, small populati ' on and physical environment<br />
create special challenges and opportunities for defence<br />
science and research, particularly in the areas of<br />
surveillance communications and integration of weapons<br />
systems. These challenges are being met by Australians and<br />
particularly by the Defence Science and Technology<br />
Organisation ( DSTO). The indigenous development of the<br />
technologies associated with the over-the-horizon radar,<br />
sensor equipment, anti-submarine warfare, electronic<br />
warfare, and command, control and communications systems<br />
have all played an important role in addressing the<br />
challenges posed by Australia's geographic and strategic<br />
circumstances. Through this kind of research as well as through the<br />
integration of weapons systems appropriate to Australia's<br />
circumstances, science and research are making an important<br />
contribution to the maintenance of an effective Australian<br />
Defence Force and thereby enhancing our national security as<br />
well as the prospects for peace and stability in our region.<br />
Scientific research can also actively promote peace through<br />
its contribution to effective arms control and disarmament<br />
measures. Two cases have particular relevance to Australia.<br />
Seismological monitoring is important in the detection of<br />
nuclear explosions and a major component of a verification<br />
system for any comprehensive nuclear test ban, which<br />
Australia is actively promoting, will be an adequate<br />
seismographic network. With the opening of the Australian<br />
Seismographic Centre in Canberra in September this year,<br />
Australia is uniquely placed to make an important<br />
contribution in this area.<br />
Scientific research expertise can also contribute to<br />
international efforts aimed at eliminating chemical and<br />
biological weapons. Through our diplomatic activity and the<br />
expertise of the DSTO, Australia has been a leader in this<br />
area and has contributed to United Nations initiatives to<br />
control and eliminate such weapons.<br />
These examples serve to illustrate a more fundamental point.<br />
It is a tragedy that man devotes immeasurably more resources<br />
to scientific research for his own destruction than to work<br />
directed to the betterment of the human condition.<br />
As the world anxiously watches the current efforts of the<br />
superpowers to move towards arms control agreements, we may<br />
reflect on the appalling waste of money and ingenuity which<br />
has gone into the build-up of their nuclear arsenals.<br />
A conference such as this provides a rare opportunity for<br />
men and women of the scientific community to search for<br />
opportunities to reduce this shocking imbalance for the<br />
benefit of all mankind. </p>
<p>9.<br />
Many of these issues I have mentioned are on the agenda for<br />
your conference. This suggests that OECD governments are<br />
confronting common problems as they attempt to develop<br />
policies and directions for science and research. We<br />
welcome the opportunity to benefit from the combined<br />
experience of the distinguished delegates gathered here from<br />
many OECD countries.<br />
I wish you well in your deliberations.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
