<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5223</transcript-id>
    <title>AFGHANISTAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005223.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JJ ATST~ I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY 31 DECEMBER 17<br />
AFGHAN ISTAN<br />
The Soviet Ambassador today called on the Prime Minister at<br />
Nareen. He did so on instructions from his Government.<br />
The main purpose of the Ambassador's call was to give an official<br />
explanation of the Soviet Union's military intervention in<br />
Afghanistan. The Ambassador said there had been an appeal to his<br />
Government for help, and that help had been granted.<br />
The Prime Minister told the Ambassador that his explanation was<br />
noted, but that it was not acceptable; that there were no valid<br />
grounds for Soviet military involvement in Afghanistan; and that<br />
while the previous Afghanistan Government had been a brutal one,<br />
whatever might hav1. e occurred in Afghanistan during the last two<br />
years did not justify or provide any reason to condone the Soviet<br />
invasion. The Prime Minister drew attention to the fact that the Soviet<br />
military action in Afghanistan was similar to that taken by the<br />
Soviet Union in Hungary and Czechoslovakia. What they have done<br />
in Afghanistan should be condemned by freedom-loving people<br />
around the world.<br />
The Australian Government-and people could not accept that there<br />
should be military interference by one power in the affairs of a<br />
neighbouring state. It was morally wrong and totally contrary to<br />
the accepted norms of international society. In this particular<br />
case. it could only have a destabilising effect on an area which<br />
alradyhad more than its fair share of problems. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister said that Soviet actions in Afghanistan stood<br />
in marked contrast to the restraint shown by the United States in<br />
Iran. He called on the Soviet Union, as a responsible member of<br />
the international community, to condemn the taking of hostages.<br />
The Soviet Union should exert its undoubted influence in<br />
achieving a return to normal relationships.<br />
The Prime Minister said that Australia had only yesterday made<br />
its position on the Iranian situation very plain in the<br />
Security Council Debate. The opportunity would be there for<br />
the Soviet Union to do likewise. 000---<br />
; r<br />
r t<br />
i r t' r..<br />
i. t </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
