<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2111</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH THE RT HON. J.G GORTON, M.P ON OVERSEAS INVESTEMENT IN AUSTRALIA ( MINISTERIAL STATEMENT)</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/09/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002111.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRILUA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
The Rt Hon. J. G. GORTON, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
OVERSEAS INVESTMENT IN AUSTRAIA<br />
( Ministerial Statement)<br />
[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 16 September 1969]<br />
Mr GORTON ( Higgins-Prime Minister)<br />
by leave The importance to<br />
Australia of a strong and continuing inflow<br />
* of overseas capital has never been ques-<br />
'. tioned by my Government. During the years<br />
-after the end of World War II, the accumulated<br />
total of private overseas investment<br />
ini Austral) ia has been about $ 7,000m. With-<br />
6 tha. ' investment, ' it would have been<br />
impossible for us to develop as quickly as<br />
history demands we must. Our immigration<br />
programme would have been restricted.<br />
Import replacement and a, growing independence<br />
of many overseas commodities would<br />
have been curtailed. And we would not have<br />
grown the industrial muscles which we need.<br />
This overseas flow of investment has<br />
developed resources which were previously<br />
not utilised. It has contributed to the sustained<br />
growth in our export income, and<br />
it has raised the general level of efficiency<br />
and therefore of real incomes in many<br />
sectors of the economy. It confers great<br />
benefits on us and it is essential that it should<br />
continue. It is, however, also true that overseas<br />
capital does not come to Australia<br />
merely because of a wish to confer these<br />
advantages on us. Basically it comes here<br />
because we are a politically stable country,<br />
because there are great opportunities for<br />
new development here, and because there<br />
are good opportunities for profit, and for<br />
growth as the nation grows.<br />
Naturally, at a time when great new<br />
possibilities are opening up in this country<br />
22179/ 69 we wish to see Australians get as good an<br />
opportunity as possible, within the limits of<br />
their resources and capacities for saving,<br />
for participation in these developments and<br />
growth and profits. This is not an attitude<br />
that can or should be carried to'the point<br />
of discouraging people from abroad who<br />
are willing to bring here their money and<br />
their energies and their know-how. But it<br />
is an attitude on the part of the Australian<br />
community which overseas interests have to<br />
recognise. To a very large extent they<br />
already recognise and are prepared to<br />
accept it. And many of them indeed, in<br />
indreasing numbers, have seen that it is an<br />
attitude which is basically helpful to them<br />
and can be turned, in a co-operative spirit,<br />
to their and our good account.<br />
As we see it, the central aim of policy<br />
must be to provide, on terms which are fair<br />
as between overseas investors and the Australian<br />
people, the conditions under which<br />
investment will be attracted here. Those<br />
conditions should be such that overseas<br />
enterprises can operate securely and<br />
effectively, making the greatest contribution<br />
they can to our development at a fair<br />
return to themselves. And above all, conditions<br />
under which they can work ' in<br />
harmony, on even terms, and so far as<br />
practicable on a joint basis and in close<br />
collaboration with Australian enterprises.<br />
We do not believe that we can or should<br />
seek to legislate, in such a complex field. </p>
<p>But we reiterate our wishes and have little brevity I will refer to those amounts as<br />
doubt that overseas companies of repute the increase in funds employed.<br />
A h -iL<br />
will Lnote and reiponJ LU Uose wl es.<br />
Mr Uren-They have not in 20 years.<br />
Mr GORTON-Yes. They are doing it<br />
more and more. The Government has, as<br />
its general objective, the encouragement of<br />
Australian participation in and partnership<br />
with, overseas enterprises. And in speaking<br />
of partnership I place emphasis upon the<br />
offer of equity participation to Australians<br />
by overseas ventures. As encouragement<br />
towards this end we have recently completed<br />
a review of the restraints imposed on<br />
overseas companies seeking to raise fixed<br />
interest borrowings in Australia-or the<br />
borrowing guidelines as they have come to<br />
be known. These guidelines . apply onlyto.<br />
proposed fixed interest borrowings, not to<br />
the raising of share capital in Australia for<br />
the purpose of financing operations by<br />
enterprises incorporated here.<br />
' At present overseas interests proposing<br />
any form of borrowing within Australia are<br />
requested to consult the Reserve Bank and<br />
Australian lending institutions are requested<br />
to satisfy themselves that overseas interestsor<br />
companies in which more than 25% of<br />
the shares are held by overseas interestshave<br />
received approvals from the Reserve<br />
' Bank covering any proposed borrowings.<br />
This will continue. Generally speaking companies<br />
will be allowed reasonable access to<br />
Australian borrowings for financing normal<br />
requirements of working capital, bridging<br />
finance, and continuing carry-on requirenients.<br />
Further, in accordance with the<br />
Government's general policy of ensuring<br />
that every effort is made to increase exports<br />
of Australian goods, ready approval will be<br />
given to borrowings for the specific purpose<br />
of financing export transactions.<br />
In calculating the new local borrowings<br />
that will be approved to finance fixed assets<br />
Sin future, the base will be the local borrowings<br />
approved as acceptable as at 30th<br />
June 1969 under the existing guidelines.<br />
Companies that are now regarded as having<br />
been established in Australia for a period<br />
of' 4 years or longer will be allowed to<br />
borrow up to 10% of any increase subsequent<br />
to June 1969 in the total of shareholders'<br />
funds, other funds from overseas<br />
sources, and. local borrowings excluding<br />
those to finance increases in working capital<br />
: or to finance exports. For the sake of Companies wholly overseas-owned and<br />
established in Australia for periods of less<br />
than 4 years will be allowed local borrowings<br />
of up to 21% of the increase in funds<br />
employed for each year that they have been<br />
, established. Such companies will hence-<br />
, forth have a new base and a new percentage<br />
applied each year until they have been<br />
established here 4 years. From that time<br />
onwards they will be allowed local borrowings<br />
of up to 10% of subsequent increases<br />
in funds employed. For companies in<br />
which Australians have a share of the<br />
equity, additional borrowings to those set<br />
out above will be allowed. The extent of<br />
the additional borrowings will be determined<br />
by the share of the total equity in<br />
the company held by Australians.<br />
.: To meet, requirements of funds additional<br />
' to the proceeds of new share issues and the<br />
local borrowings in accordance with the<br />
preceding paragraphs, a company will be<br />
., allowed to raise in Australia a proportion<br />
of its total new borrowings which will<br />
accord with. the proportion of shares in<br />
the company held by Australians. Australian<br />
equity will be weighted on a four<br />
for three basis so that the proportion for a<br />
. company with 30% Australian equity will<br />
be 40%. If for special reasons overseas<br />
loan funds to match local borrowings can-<br />
: not be arranged, access to local borrowings<br />
will nevertheless be increased to take<br />
account of the extent of the Australian<br />
equity. In the application of this aspect of the<br />
guidelines, the Reserve Bank will take into<br />
account,; for purposes of calculating the extent<br />
of Australian equity, offers to Australians<br />
of new or increased equity ( other<br />
than through convertible notes) which have<br />
not been taken up but which are considered<br />
to have been genuine and reasonable offers<br />
of . local equity participation in the company.<br />
If new or increased Australian equity<br />
, is offered bona fide through the issue of<br />
convertible notes, the Reserve Bank will<br />
take into account in calculating the extent<br />
of. Australian equity one-half the future<br />
increase in Australian equity that would<br />
result if the notes were converted.<br />
' It should be mentioned here that<br />
approval will not normally be granted for </p>
<p>borrowings that would facilitate the remittance<br />
of funds abroad. Consistently, moreover,<br />
with the longstanding exchange control<br />
policy of requiring overseas interests<br />
taking over enterprises in Australia to bring<br />
in cash to the full extent of the purchase<br />
price, approval will not normally be given<br />
to borrowings intended to finance a takeover.<br />
Overseas interests seeking exchange<br />
control for a takeover are reminded<br />
that on completion, the changed<br />
ownership of the enterprise taken over will<br />
necessitate discussions with the Reseive<br />
Bank of the extent of local borrowings by<br />
the enterprise as a whole.<br />
I move on to discuss convertible notes.<br />
During , the developmental stages of many<br />
major projects there are either no earnings,<br />
or no surplus earnings available for distribuition<br />
to shareholders. This, of course, discourages<br />
would-be investors who need a<br />
return on their capital at once and limits<br />
the amount of share capital which those<br />
promoting the venture can raise. Therefore<br />
the alternative of fixed interest borrowings,<br />
with a guarantee of income, has had more<br />
attraction to many lenders as well as; to<br />
those seeking to borrow. For the borrower<br />
believes that by offering immediate return<br />
on the investment as income he will increase<br />
the likelihood of borrowing successfully. He<br />
also knows that the interest he must pay on<br />
fixed interest borrowings is cumulatively<br />
deductible for income tax purposes, thus<br />
substantially reducing the effective cost of<br />
his borrowings.<br />
As a step towards attaining our goal of<br />
increasing Australian equity participation in<br />
Australian development, we sought means<br />
of-diverting these fixed interest borrowings<br />
into borrowings'with-' a chance of equity<br />
participation. It was foi this reason that the<br />
Treasurer /( Mr McMahon) announced in<br />
his Budget Speech our proposal to amend<br />
the Income'Tax Law in order to restore<br />
deductibility of interest for income tax purposes<br />
on convertible company securities.<br />
Before 1960 interest on all convertible securities<br />
was deductible; but it became evident<br />
that convertible notes were being widely<br />
substituted for equity issues and that, in<br />
the majority of cases, the plain purpose of<br />
this substitution was tax avoidance. So to<br />
protect the revenue, deduction of interest<br />
on all convertible securities was disallowed. We do not intend to go back to a pre-<br />
1960 situation. We shall minimise the scope<br />
for tax avoidance and will lay down conditions<br />
to which convertible securities must<br />
conform if they are to qualify for deductibility<br />
of interest. These conditions are:<br />
1. The lender or noteholder, and not the<br />
issuing company, has the option to<br />
convert;<br />
2. The noteholder's right to exercise the<br />
option is not deferred longer than 24<br />
months after the date of issue of<br />
the security;<br />
3. The convertible note has a currency<br />
of not less than 7 nor more than<br />
years but the company may make the<br />
terminal date for the exercise of the<br />
option as much as, but not more than,<br />
12 months earlier than the maturity<br />
date of the note;<br />
4. The terms and conditions of the issue<br />
are fixed and not subject to any variation<br />
throughout the period of their<br />
S currency; and<br />
5. The conversion price for shares is not<br />
less than 90% of their market price<br />
when the convertible securities are<br />
issued, qr par, whichever is greater.<br />
We believe that these conditions will have<br />
. a twofold advantage. They will give companies<br />
adequate scope for using convertible<br />
securities to their best advantage in business<br />
financing and they will offer to Australian<br />
investors a new opportunity to participate<br />
in the equities of overseas-initiated<br />
ventures in Australia, especially those in the<br />
extractive industries. If such ventures issue<br />
* convertible notes to finance development or<br />
expansion, Australians who take up these<br />
securities will have an assured rate of income<br />
during the developmental period of<br />
the project with the option to acquire equity,<br />
and thus share in the growth of the business.<br />
The opportunity that convertible notes opens<br />
up for wider participation by Australians<br />
in the ownership of such overseas-initiated<br />
ventures has been a major consideration in<br />
the decision we have taken to restore tax<br />
deductibility of interest on such convertible<br />
notes. In so seeking to widen opportunities for<br />
Australian participation in ownership we<br />
have sought to ensure that the opportunities<br />
would be real and not merely nominal and<br />
that they will not be too long delayed. We<br />
think that the option to -convert to shares-</p>
<p>should remain open long enough for the<br />
company to have established itself and for<br />
its shares to have value enough for noteholders<br />
to take them rather than opt for<br />
repayment of their loan in cash. It is in<br />
order to provide adequate time for development<br />
and profitability that we propose that<br />
convertible notes should have a currency of<br />
at least 7 years and that the option to<br />
convert should not terminate earlier than<br />
12 months before the maturity date of the<br />
note. We also believe that 10 years will<br />
for all practical purposes be long enough<br />
for convertible notes to remain outstanding.<br />
Certainly, if the development or expansion<br />
of an overseas-initiated venture is to lead to<br />
an issue of equity to Australians, it is<br />
reasonable to expect this to be resolved<br />
within a period not longer than 10 years.<br />
Convertible issues proposed to be issued by<br />
companies in which more than 25% of<br />
the shares are held by overseas interests<br />
will be subject to examination by the<br />
Reserve Bank to determine that the terms<br />
of issue are . reasonable and genuine.<br />
COMPANY TAKEOVERS<br />
The question of Australian participation<br />
in Australian development is not confined to<br />
expressing a strong Government desire for<br />
joint ventures, -or to encouraging the offer<br />
of equity to Australian shareholders through<br />
borrowing guidelines. The question of protection<br />
of Australian companies against<br />
overseas takeovers also arises. . The Government<br />
has given special consideration to this<br />
question of takeovers in general, whether<br />
such takeovers are by overseas or by other<br />
Australian companies.<br />
We have been especially concerned to<br />
prevent the use of takeover methods which<br />
are unfair -to a company's shareholders as<br />
a body. I refer to such practices as the<br />
large-scale purchase of shares through<br />
nominees, to first come first served offers<br />
and similar manoeuvres. These problems<br />
were. reported on. by the Company Law<br />
Advisory Committee and in March of this<br />
year the Standing Committee of Attorneys-<br />
General agreed to adopt the report in<br />
principle. * As the Attorney-General informed the<br />
House on 20th May the Commonwealth<br />
Government has considered that report and<br />
has decided to amend the companies Ordinances.,<br />
of, the, Australian. Capital Territory. and Northern Territory to give effect to the<br />
Advisory Committee's recommendations,<br />
namely: Disclosure<br />
A person having a beneficial interest of<br />
10% or more in the voting capital of a<br />
company listed on an Australian stock<br />
exchange will be required to give notice of<br />
that interest to the company. The company<br />
will be required to enter this information in<br />
a special register which will be available<br />
for public inspection. The new provisions<br />
are to apply to, but without discrimination<br />
against, persons resident, or companies<br />
incorporated, outside the jurisdiction, as<br />
well as to persons or corporations within<br />
the jurisdiction of this Government. The<br />
-proposed provisions are generally in line<br />
' with the existing law in the United Kingdom<br />
and the United States but, in view<br />
of. enforcement difficulties,. are to be<br />
accompanied by certain sanctions not provided<br />
in those countries. A registered holder<br />
who is aware that he holds on behalf of a<br />
non-resident will be required to furnish to<br />
that. person information as to the requirements<br />
of the legislation.<br />
THE TAKEOVER CODE<br />
A. The code will be made applicable to<br />
offers by natural persons.<br />
An invitation to make an offer-as,<br />
for example, in first come first served<br />
invitations will be treated as if it were<br />
an offer.<br />
C. The criterion for application of the<br />
code will be 15% of the voting power,<br />
instead of one-third as at present.<br />
D. An offerer who increases the price<br />
offered in respect of some shareholders<br />
will be obliged to pay the<br />
increased price to those who have<br />
already accepted.<br />
E. Provision will be made to prevent a<br />
bid for less than the provided limit<br />
of 15% of shares being used to<br />
acquire shares in excess of that limit.<br />
F. -It will be an offence for a person to<br />
make a takeover offer, or to give<br />
notice of intention to do so without<br />
having any reasonable or probable<br />
grounds of expectation of being able<br />
to provide the consideration for the<br />
offer or proposed offer. </p>
<p>G. All aspects of a takeover will be<br />
governed by the law of the State or<br />
Territory in which the offeree company<br />
was incorporated.<br />
It will be noted that the report does not<br />
recommend the prohibition of first come<br />
first served offers as such but the Eggleston<br />
Committee -reported that these . changes will<br />
ensure that this kind of offer will not escape<br />
the control applicable to other kinds of<br />
takeover offers.<br />
There were additional proposals from the<br />
Associated Stock Exchanges and although<br />
these were not covered by the Committee<br />
because it considered they were outside its<br />
terms of reference, they will be incorporated<br />
in the companies ordinances of the Australian<br />
Capital Territory and the Northern<br />
Territory. 1. One of the amendments will provide<br />
that any amendment to the articles of<br />
association restricting voting rights<br />
shall require the affirmative vote of<br />
not less than 51% in value of the<br />
shareholders of the class of shares<br />
affected. A similar requirement<br />
already exists in the listing requirements<br />
of the Australian Associated<br />
Stock Exchanges. The present position<br />
under the uniform Companies Act is<br />
that any amendment of the articles<br />
of association of a company requires<br />
a special resolution, which in turn,<br />
requires a three-fourth's majority of<br />
members of the company voting in<br />
person or by proxy.<br />
The proposed provision will be in<br />
the nature of an additional requirement,<br />
which will recognise the<br />
significance of a restriction on voting<br />
rights. Shareholders who do not vote<br />
affirmatively for a restriction-including<br />
those who do not vote at<br />
all-will, in effect, be treated as<br />
opposed to the restriction.<br />
2. The other additional, amendment<br />
relates to the notice of intention that<br />
must be given before a takeover is<br />
made. The present position is that this<br />
notice must be given not earlier than<br />
28 days, and not later than 14 days,<br />
before the offer is made. The amendment<br />
will require the notice to be<br />
given not earlier than 42 days and<br />
not later than 28 days. The additional notice provided for by the amendment<br />
will allow an offeree corporation a<br />
better opportunity of considering the<br />
terms of the offer and of taking steps,<br />
if it so desires, to amend its articles of<br />
association to restrict voting rights<br />
attached to shares held by overseas<br />
interests.<br />
I turn now to takeovers which, irrespective<br />
of the method used, may be judged<br />
contrary to the national interest. In the past<br />
theGovernment has acted to preserve<br />
Australian ownership and control of enterprises<br />
which for special reasons of national<br />
interest or importance could not be permitted<br />
to' pass into foreign hands.<br />
For many years we have opposed the<br />
entry of overseas banks into the local<br />
industry. And . inth e areas of television and<br />
radio broadcasting the acquisition of control<br />
by foreign interests has been excluded by<br />
statute. Further statutory control is not at<br />
present contemplated and we do not believe<br />
that it is possible now to define further<br />
classes or fields of enterprise which we<br />
believe should not, in the national interest,<br />
pass to overseas ownership.<br />
However whilst our general experience<br />
over the years has shown that almost all<br />
overseas investment in Australia accords<br />
with our country's interests it has also shown<br />
that there remains a need for the Government<br />
to be ready to guard against the<br />
transfer from Australian control of established<br />
companies in particular areas of<br />
activity. For example some few years ago<br />
there were thought to be attempts by overseas<br />
investors to take over an important<br />
and long-established Australian mining company,<br />
while more recently it was believed<br />
that there was an attempt to take over<br />
one of the principal Australian life assurance<br />
organisations, which would have carried<br />
with it the right to determine the<br />
investment policy of assets totalling some<br />
$ 700m of Australians' savings.<br />
Although we expect the need to arise<br />
only on rare occasions as a Government<br />
we reserve the right to do all in our power<br />
to prevent particular takeovers when, in the<br />
circumstances of the case, we would consider<br />
it to be bad in the national interest.<br />
The strengthening of the takeover code<br />
through amendment of the Uniform Companies<br />
Act should ensure not only that takeover.<br />
proposals proceed in a fair and open </p>
<p>manner, but also that the Government will<br />
have more time to intervene, or express a<br />
Government view, if it considers the<br />
national interest calls for it.<br />
Peroration<br />
To sum up, Mr Speaker, we seek to encourage<br />
the flow of overseas capital into<br />
this country. We seek-to make it crystal<br />
clear that we look with favour on joint<br />
enterprise and . on the offer of Australian<br />
equity in new ventures-and that we will<br />
' be disturbed where the opportunity for Australian<br />
participation is not given. We seek<br />
to encourage the growth of Australian<br />
equity by offering more access to the fixed<br />
interest borrowing as Australian equity in a<br />
company increases. We seek to protect<br />
companies against unfair methods of takeover<br />
and to reserve to ourselves the right<br />
to. intervene in such takeovers when we<br />
consider it is in the national interest, and<br />
we seek the acceptance of the basic principles.<br />
of a code of good corporate behaviour.<br />
Such a code was adopted by the<br />
Canadian Government three years ago. Speaking of overseas companies, and paraphrasing<br />
the language to our -own environment,<br />
I think there are three essentials for<br />
which we look as a nation:<br />
1. A high. degree of Australian autonomy,<br />
with Australian citizens participating<br />
on the boards of directors<br />
and in the management of companies;<br />
2. The objective of a financial stucture<br />
, which provides opportunity for equity<br />
participation by Australians;<br />
3. A sensitivity to the reasonable<br />
national -aspirations of Australia<br />
vhic6 whilst somewhat indefinable in<br />
detail are known quite well by all<br />
those in this House and by anybody<br />
who is at all sensitive to these aspirations,<br />
' and who as a company has<br />
intentions of investing in -this ration.<br />
By the means outlined in this speech we<br />
believe that we will, without interfering<br />
with the flow of capital we need so badly,<br />
offer considerable encouragement to greater<br />
Australian, equity participation and that,<br />
Sir, is the objective. of this Government<br />
and, I believe, of most of the citizens of<br />
this country.<br />
Priuteil for the Government of the Commonwealth by W. 0. MURRAY at tho<br />
. Government Printing Office, Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
