<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17300</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Sinking of the South Korean Navy Corvette &#039;Cheonan&#039;   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australia condemns North Korea for the sinking of the South Korean Navy corvette Cheonan on 26 March with the loss of 46 lives.</p>
<p>The South Korean Ministry of National Defense today issued a statement setting out the results of the investigation of the Joint Civilian-Military Investigation Group (JIG) into the causes of the sinking of the Cheonan.</p>
<p>The key findings of the investigation are deeply disturbing. The JIG gathered conclusive evidence that the Cheonan was sunk by a torpedo manufactured in North Korea, fragments of which were found on the sea floor at the site of the incident.</p>
<p>This hostile and unprovoked act represents a flagrant violation by North Korea of the United Nations (UN) Charter and the 1953 Korean Armistice Agreement.</p>
<p>The international community cannot let this act pass without an appropriate response. The Australian Government is working closely with South Korea and other partners on how to respond, including action in the UN Security Council.</p>
<p>I spoke by phone with the President of the Republic of Korea, H.E. Lee Myung-bak, today to reiterate my sincere condolences at this tragic incident, underline Australia's solidarity with South Korea, emphasise Australia's condemnation of North Korea's deplorable act and confer on appropriate responses.</p>
<p>The Australian Government was pleased to contribute five specialist and intelligence personnel from the Royal Australian Navy to support the Korean-led investigation, at the request of the South Korean Government. The United States, the United Kingdom, Sweden and Canada also contributed to the investigation.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
