<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11065</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   TELEVISION INTERVIEW                 INSIGHT &amp;#150; VIVIAN SCHENKER</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, welcome to our first Insight of the year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Nice to be here.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Can we talk first about the preamble to the Constitution. Are you</p>
<p> convinced that you can find a form of words that will be acceptable</p>
<p> to the majority of Australians?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I am Vivian. I'm very keen to try and I think I can.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Have you consulted many Aboriginal leaders? I mean there are people</p>
<p> like Ms Dodson who are already threatening to campaign against. Won't</p>
<p> most Aboriginal people want more than you're prepared to say?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think some of them will and, let's be frank, some of them will</p>
<p> never be satisfied unless we provide words that are in turn unacceptable</p>
<p> to the majority of the rest of the country. So the idea that you can</p>
<p> get everybody in the Aboriginal community in favour of it is just</p>
<p> unrealistic. I will be releasing for public comment the draft that</p>
<p> we have in mind. Once the Government's decided on what it wants</p>
<p> I'll be sending it to the Leader of the Opposition seeking his</p>
<p> comments. And I'll be making it publicly available so leaders</p>
<p> of the Aboriginal community and others can make a comment. But you</p>
<p> can go on, you know, you can go on talking and talking about these</p>
<p> sorts of things forever and this is a great opportunity to put something,</p>
<p> along with the republic proposal, and let's face it, if we put</p>
<p> it off this time it could be years before we approach.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Mr Beazley said this morning that if you get it right you advance</p>
<p> the course of reconciliation but if you get it wrong you set it back</p>
<p> immeasurably. I mean [inaudible] would be disastrous to the course</p>
<p> of reconciliation if the preamble gets knocked back couldn't</p>
<p> it? Or if there a divisive public debate about it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes but there shouldn't be a divisive public debate simply because</p>
<p> some in the community would like it to go further. That to me is an</p>
<p> artificially generated divisive public debate. I mean the simple question</p>
<p> has got to be asked of people who would like to go further. Okay you</p>
<p> might want to further but are you really saying what we are putting</p>
<p> up is objectionable? I mean people who want to go further than say</p>
<p> occupation by the indigenous people can hardly say that at least acknowledging</p>
<p> occupation is objectionable.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>No but presumably the argument's the same as it is by the direct</p>
<p> election.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No no.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>.....now then you've got no chance of getting change further....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well what the direct election the republicans are saying is that they</p>
<p> would rather the status quo than a Parliamentary election where as</p>
<p> in relation to the preamble it could hardly be better to say: no mention</p>
<p> of the indigenous people at all is preferable to a mention that you</p>
<p> think falls short of what you would desirably want. I think they are</p>
<p> quite different things. But can I suggest that people actually wait</p>
<p> and see because they may in fact find what we put forward acceptable.</p>
<p> Some people won't and I accept that but you've got to play</p>
<p> the test or reasonableness and I'm a reasonable man and I hope</p>
<p> people will see it as reasonable.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>The Opposition have also accused you of hubris in wanting to write</p>
<p> it all by yourself. Why do you want to write it all by yourself?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm not going to write it all by myself. Of course I'm</p>
<p> not. I said yesterday I'd be consulting other people. I mean,</p>
<p> dear me, the Opposition Leader should listen to what I say. I didn't</p>
<p> say that at all.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Okay. Before we leave the republic and the preamble can I just ask</p>
<p> you, I know there's been pressure from within Coalition and also</p>
<p> certainly from the Ethnic Communities Council to get a mention of</p>
<p> cultural development in there. Are you at least leaning that way?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well once again, people just wait and see. I know what makes up Australia</p>
<p> and what makes up Australia is quite a mixture of people. You have</p>
<p> indigenous people, you have people whose ancestors came predominantly</p>
<p> from Britain and Ireland in the 19th century and the 20th</p>
<p> century. You have that great wave of post war migration.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>[inaudible] encouraging for those who want cultural....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well well, I want to sort of do the right thing by all Australians.</p>
<p> I don't want people to feel as though we don't appreciate</p>
<p> the lovely character of Australia. But if we....</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>[inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No no no, just wait and see. I just want, want something that people</p>
<p> feel comfortable with, but equally you can't have something that's</p>
<p> too long and if you get into a situation where you're sort of</p>
<p> ticking off each sort of little pressure the whole thing becomes quite</p>
<p> meaningless because we are Australians before we are anything else.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Okay. Can we turn no to the big issue in Parliament today, [inaudible]</p>
<p> Industrial Relations? When you first came to government you promised</p>
<p> that no Australian worker would be worse off under any new system</p>
<p> that you introduced. Are you now saying that that promise is limited</p>
<p> to existing workers and doesn't hold to someone starting a job</p>
<p> for the first time?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No no, I'm not.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>There hasn't been a change?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no. What I said in 1996, and it remains our policy, is that anybody</p>
<p> that goes into an Australian workplace agreement will not be worse</p>
<p> off than they would otherwise be under the relevant award. That's</p>
<p> our policy. That's been our policy since 1996. It was repeated</p>
<p> in 1998 and it remains our policy now. And I, in fact, made it very</p>
<p> clear in the response to Mr Reith that any new directions we developed</p>
<p> had to honour our commitments. So let me make it pluperfect clear,</p>
<p> that commitment remains.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>But when you say any existing worker, that's not significant</p>
<p> in any way.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, no.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>You mean any workers, past, present or future.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm saying any worker under a workplace agreement, past,</p>
<p> present or future.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Okay. Mr Reith's ideas for further industrial reform are not</p>
<p> yet policy, as you rightly said, but are you in broad agreement with</p>
<p> his suggestion that if the Senate does block the initiative when they</p>
<p> come you should push for reform of the Upper House?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, we don't have a government position on that. I'm</p>
<p> not going to get into a discussion about what might happen. Look,</p>
<p> I applaud the fact that less than a month after I made him Employment</p>
<p> Minister he's writing to me with 20 pages of new ideas. I mean,</p>
<p> that is what we want. I mean, that is terrific. I think it shows that</p>
<p> he's a Minister committed to reform. And we have a plan, we have</p>
<p> a set of proposals and when you go through them some we'll adopt</p>
<p> and some we'll throw out. And the culling process will be against</p>
<p> the background of those election commitments about workplace agreements.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>When will we know what you've got in mind...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, that will evolve over a period of time. I mean, this is a menu</p>
<p> for the whole term. I mean, that's what you do at the beginning,</p>
<p> you get a new Minister, you get a new bloke in a job and within a</p>
<p> month he's writing to you saying, look, let's do this. That's</p>
<p> terrific.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Okay.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's how a government ought to work.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>The most pressing problem the Coalition has with the Senate at the</p>
<p> moment anyway  that's all for the future, industrial relations,</p>
<p> at the moment you've got problems with the GST. How would you</p>
<p> rate your chances of getting the tax package through the Senate before</p>
<p> the end of June.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I remain hopeful. Obviously I won't know until the 30th</p>
<p> of June. The Senate will, by then, have had plenty of time to examine</p>
<p> the package. And I say again that the Australian people voted for</p>
<p> us knowing that that's what we wanted to do. And you couldn't</p>
<p> have had a stronger mandate, if the word mandate means anything, and</p>
<p> I hope the Senate will ultimately heed the wishes of the Australian</p>
<p> people. And we'll continue to work and argue and persuade as</p>
<p> best we can but I won't know until the 30th of June</p>
<p> but I remain hopeful.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>If you don't know, in fact, until the 30th of June</p>
<p> and they do hold out and they won't pass it before then, would</p>
<p> you consider a quick double dissolution election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, Vivian, we've just had an election. Do you remember?</p>
<p> I think the last interview you and I had was during the dying days</p>
<p> of the campaign.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>I remember.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Vivian, look, you know, I'm not going to get into speculation...</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Are you ruling it out?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, I'm not even contemplating what we might be doing post</p>
<p> failure to get it through by the 30th of June. I have an</p>
<p> optimistic frame of mind. I mean, I'm in the business of trying</p>
<p> to persuade those in the Senate who've got the balance of power</p>
<p> to support the Government's plan. I'm not contemplating</p>
<p> other things.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Is Senator Harradine the most likely avenue to get it passed at the</p>
<p> moment?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Senator Harradine is obviously an important person and Senator</p>
<p> Harradine is somebody who keeps his counsel and I respect him for</p>
<p> that and I've always found him a reasonable man. I know that</p>
<p> there are certain things he will never support and other things he</p>
<p> might be persuaded to support. And I'm not going to try and verbal</p>
<p> Senator Harradine. I'm not giong to try and suggest  he</p>
<p> will decide what he's going to do in the fullness of time and</p>
<p> I wouldn't presume to predict what he might do. That's a</p>
<p> matter for him.</p>
<p>SCHENKER:</p>
<p>Okay, Prime Minister, we're going to have to leave it there.</p>
<p> Thank you very much.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It was a great pleasure.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
