<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3858</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, FOR THE OPENING OF THE 18TH BIENNIAL CONFERENCE OF THE LIBRARY ASSOCIATION OF AUSTRALIA, MELBOURNE, 24 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003858.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE HRilf 1EfINIiSTERT<br />
TUE HON, E. G. WHITLAN,<br />
FOR THE ONEThING OF THE 18THl BIENNIAL CONFEREINCE<br />
OF THE LIBRARY ASSOCIATIo~ OF AUISTRALIA<br />
H1E L3 OUIN~ E. 24 AUGUST 1975<br />
ICONGRATUL ATE . THE ORGAN ISERS OF THIS CONFERENJCE O N<br />
BRI-NGING TOGET,-]"-HER SUCH A R EP RE SETAT I~ A ND. D IST INGUISHED<br />
* GATHERING OF LIB3RARIAiNS, ADM' N1STRATORS AIND AL L T HOSE CONCERN'ED<br />
W IT H T iiE 2/ LOPMENTf OF LIBRARIES IN LlUS RA L IA, THE_ SIZE AND<br />
SCOPAES SOCr" IT TY, O U% HCEF RV IGOUNRC P OFA R-EY OUER0V IDENCFES IN0C F THE NS TRETNH'\ EG THP U-OBFL IC'( O'SUR<br />
F TE OLEr Or: IRAV IN A FREE SOCIETY,<br />
I P3i-YEAPS THERE HAS B EN A MIARKED CHANGE IN<br />
CTFH E 1ZEDUi. T2VV3 LrCG I CH PEDCE PTIO TO 0OFP R'OyIVHAIDTE , A LII1NBE RAN RO Y LOSNHGOEURL. D THBEIN KA N" OD F-W LHIABTR ASRO RIETS<br />
AS CQLt rCER3 j5O OOKS, ITI O OUUHTHE t'IATERIAL'<br />
O1R1 C S OF A L T D THAT COUNT 7IMPORTANT AS. THESE. ARE<br />
BU: TH Ci 0UR ESARE USED AND HOGW T HE Y ARE M1ADE AVAILABLE<br />
TO0 THOS E lWHO2-N' ED THEi', THE LIBRARY' S FUNCTION IS TO PROV/ IDE<br />
INFO, A-f I' TB'ARIAN IS FUNCTIONI IS TO ORGANISE THAT<br />
INFORNATIGN AND ENSURE" THAT EVERYONE HAS ACCESS TO IT, </p>
<p>IHOPE THIS WI LL NOT SOUND TOO ELITIST A V/ I EWf ORA<br />
T HE M E TOO R EMOT E FIROM YOUR P RLES ENT P R EOCC UP AT I OINS TH E<br />
FREEDC; TO DtE iGNORANT MlAY WELL BE -AS PRECIOUS AS* THE RIGHT<br />
TO N~ r4. DO3THOWEVER, IF LIBRARIANS WOULD ACCEPT THAT.<br />
CCE R A' 0h NOT. IMPLY MAKE THE POINT THAT WHEREA<br />
O3, CSRE A FUNCTION OF LITERACY.', THEY ARE RIGHTLY<br />
S . A 3 A FU iC T nIN IF LI1B E RT Y. NOTICED THAT IN YOUR. SUBMISSION<br />
TO THE C OMI 4T T F: G F UIRY INTO PUBLIC LIBRARIES AN INQUIRY<br />
ISHt-: AL DEAL 111T! H L'TER YOU QUOTED SOME WORDS OF ONE OF MY<br />
FO3. ADVITSSEL LSY., L YOR OF COURSE, THE DISCIPLES QUOTE THE<br />
:~ SERBUTIN HISCAS IQUOTE THE DISCIPLE JIM SPIGELMAN<br />
u 1972 AT 5O) TH SUMIMER SCHOOL. OF FEASRLA<br />
NS TlTU TE 0OF P OL TIL S C I ENC E<br />
" REE-CM~ OF INFORIMATION IS AS VITAL TO DEMOCRACY<br />
AS FREEDOM OF SPEECH, YET THE ORFHA EER<br />
ATTRACTED THE SAME DEGREE OF ATTENTION OR<br />
E. M'OTIOPN AS THE LATTER," .1/ 3 S 0<br />
THESE FUNCTIONS ARE BASIC TO ANY CONCEPT OF T-RUE<br />
D EOCAY LBARE THAT ARE FREE, OPEN AND ACCESSIBLEAE<br />
JUST MUCH BASTIONS OF FREEDOM AS UNIVERSITIES OR<br />
PARLIAMENTS. FREEDOM OF SPEECH IS A PRECIOUS FREEDOM, BUT<br />
IT HAS A i U1CH HIGHER VALUE,, A MUCH RICHER SIGNIFICANCE, VIHEN<br />
FREEDOil OF INFORMATION GOES WITH IT. EVERYONE HAS TfHE RIGHT<br />
TO AN ILL-INFORM" ED1 OPINION, BUT ONLY THROUGH ACCESS TO<br />
INFORMATION CAIN THE FIR EEDO0M TO EXPRESS OPINIONS HAVE GENUINE<br />
VALUE, ONLY' THROUGH ACCESS TO liNFORMATION C AN FREEDOM OF<br />
C D C f' -0 D H V D1 I % A N rT N1 A T) CM r ' D A T r Q C zTV </p>
<p>IT IS ONLY LATELY THAT GOVERIiIENTS HAl~ VE COME<br />
TO RECOGNISE THE FORCE OF THIS ARGUMIENT3 MENT1INl 1f<br />
HERE BECAUSE IT IS RELEVANT INOT ONLY TO0 THE WORK OF YOUR<br />
PROFESSION BUT TO ONE OFr TIHE BASIC POLICIES OF NiY<br />
Go0V EE isi'l 1rT. THE RE I S NO0 PART OF OURI) PHILOSOPHY; NlO<br />
PHRASE IN THE CURRENT POLITICAL VOCABULARY, SO POORLY<br />
UNDERSTOOD AS " OPEN GoVERMEii", IT IS REGULARLY QUOTED<br />
BACK TO ' E BY JOURNALISTS 14E.. E MINISTERS REFUSE<br />
TO ANSWER A QUESTION AT A PRESS CONFEER-JCE OR REFUSE<br />
TO DIVULGE THE DETAILS OF A CABINET DECISION. I SUPPOSE<br />
IT CAN BE ARGUED THAT IN AN iD, E' AL SOCIETY THERE W4OULD<br />
BE NO SECRETS OF ANY KIND. FOR ALL THE PROGRESS WIE<br />
H AV. E M ADE SI iC E D EC EM 3ER 1972; 1 CONFESS THFAT THE IDEAL<br />
SOCTY A ETT ATTA INED, SO WE SHALL HAVE TO<br />
~. CETsoMECi= TALT I N PUBLIC AFFAIRS, By<br />
QE G HOW EVER, WE INTEND SOME: THING DEEPER<br />
A iD MNORE IllDPORTANT THAN CON" TEM?"', OR'AiNE'-OUS DISCLOSUREl";<br />
MEAN TIE WIDE . ST_ POSSIBLE ACCESS TO REPORTS, TO<br />
STATI1STICS, TO DC*% Jo=., TS, TO THE RESULTS OF OFFICIAL<br />
CUlU TRIESJ TO FACTS, TO RECORDS OF EVERY KIND, WE PlEAN<br />
SOMEITHING NO R E PEi OUS GOVE~ rNME'l\ lNTS FREQUENTLY AVOIDED<br />
RESPONSI3I1LITY FOR CERTAIN THINGS BY SAYING THEY WERE<br />
3. A T E PMA T TCERD\ S INEVITABLY THIS IMAT1HAT VERY<br />
LI TTLE EXPERT PUBLI C SERV/ ICE ADVICE OR INFORMATOWA<br />
AV. AILA8LE ON THESE SUBJECTS TO THE NATIONAL GOVERNIMENT.<br />
BY BRINGING TOGETHER THE BEST TALENTS IN THESE AREAS.,<br />
B_ 3Y OPEN'IN,\ G U. P THE WIDEST RA NG E OF AD'/ ICE. 1 AND BY MAKING<br />
THAT ADVICE AVAILABLE TO ALL. WE HAVE VASTLY WIDENED<br />
THE VOLUME OF PUBLIC INFORtMATION, LIBRARIES AND<br />
LIBRARIANS HAVE HELPED IN THAT PROCESS, ~ i S I . dll </p>
<p>3A.<br />
OPEN GO-VERNMENTS t" EANS FREEDOM 0O: INFORMATION. AS<br />
SURELY AS THE PARLIAMENT ENSHRINES., DEFENDS AND<br />
MAINTAINS THE-FREEDOM OF SPEECH.) THE LIBRARY ENSHRINES,<br />
D EFE N DS AND 11A IN TA. NS T HE FREDOM 0OFINFORMATION1 </p>
<p>IN MlY POLICY SPEECH INf, 197 2 1 DEF-INi-D LABOR'S BASIC<br />
O3J'ECTIVES IN THESE TERMS<br />
TO PROMOTE EQUALITY i<br />
TO INVOLVE-THE PEOPLE OF IN THE DECISIONMAKING<br />
PROCESSES<br />
TO LIBERATE THE TALENTS AND UPLIFT THE HORI1ZONS<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE<br />
QUITE CLEARLY THE FULFILMENT OF THESE OBJECTIVES.<br />
DEPNDSON THE CULTIV'[' ATION OFr A ORE AWARE A" ND BETTERIOME<br />
ELETORTEII~ MLR PPOTUNTIS IN EDUCATION ARE A LONG-TR<br />
A\ SPE-CT OF ' THIS PROCESS, IN TH E SHORT TERM IT IS CLEAR THAT.<br />
BETTE'R LIRrY AND ' INFORMATION SERVICES, PROPERLY ORGAN ISED<br />
; DEQUATEL Y F; ED CN RAISE THE-LEVELS OF-KfNO!' llEDGc<br />
~ IC ANiDL r-SOP H ISTICATION IN SOCIETY, IF PEOPLE ARE<br />
TO 4 E I' LV. L) iU' T&gt; CISION-MAKING PROCESS THEY MUST KiNOWi<br />
L~ 4 ~ CTSIONSARE ANDu HOW POLITICAL ISSUES CAN B3E JUDGED,<br />
LI RE S M-ItU T IN THIS PROCESS, AN INFORMED COMMUNITY<br />
ETTER EQU IPPED TO PARTICIPATE IN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS#<br />
T " ILE RA. E~~ TAI EIITS ANT) UPLIFT THE HORIZOS O H<br />
T AN PEO PLE iT S ES SE NT IAL THA T PLE BE AWARE OF. THE*<br />
T~ ORU1II~, THE PO'NS3! 3ILITJES FOR B0ETTERMENT AND PEFOP " MJ<br />
THE FAIITYOF CHNETHAT COMES FROM A GRASP OF CURRENT<br />
A. FAIRS I. N'FOROMED AND ENRICHED BY A KNO' 4' _ EDGE OF HISTORY, HERE<br />
AGA"% il THE LIBRARY, AS TiHE PRIMARY SOURCE OF INFORMATION, HAS A<br />
CENTPAL ROLE TO PLAY, </p>
<p>FORp A RIEFORMING GoVElINiNENT THEREAi OBSVIOUS<br />
DEFICITENC! VS IN THE LIB3RARY SERVICES POVIDED IN AUSTRALIA,,<br />
THEIil hSoT-OBIOUS DEFICI ENCY LIES IN THEC" IN'EQUALITY OF THEIR<br />
STANDARDS, STANDARDS VARY SIGNIFICANTLY FROM STATE TO STATE<br />
ANDW TI SFA1ES AND WITHIN CITIES, IAM THINKING PARTICULARLY(<br />
HERE OF PUBLIC. LIBRARIES.. WITH NOTABLE EXCEPTIONS PUBLIC.<br />
LIBRARY STANDARDS IN AUSTRALIA ARE LOWER THAN THOSE I1N MAM4Y<br />
OTHER OUTESOF COMPARATIVE ', iEALTH, PUBLIC LIBRARIES R<br />
THE BASIC RESPONSIBSILITY OF LOCAjL GO'IERN IENT AUTHORITIES0<br />
WHC = EC:-' TIVE ASSISTANCE FROM STATE GOVERNMENTS, GENERALLY<br />
SP EAKI fG THAT ASSI1STAN*) CE HAS BENINADEQUATE, LOCAL. AUTHORITIES<br />
HAVE THEIR---T-o 001 4N F INANCI AL PROBE) 13 r-ND THIE RESOURCES ALLOCATED 0<br />
TO DUBLC Ll DRAR ZS HAVE USUALLY HAD A LOW PRITORITY,<br />
ACY.~ D~ ThT HESSTOA TES THE SCALE OF: ASSITACE: TO<br />
_ l ' TD RE C A 3LEi NARKEDLY INCREASED INi RECENT YEARS.,<br />
BU YS CLEr A R&gt; A S7-rRIES OF A" THOR1TATIVE RE P ORT S OVER<br />
YEARS~ A OVERALL STANDARDS IN PUBLIC: LIBRARIES<br />
AR U TOO LO4, CETAINLY THE TASK OF PROVIDING EFFICIENT<br />
? U3L LLI 3DR' SE S i MUCH MOPC) E DIFFICULT IN THINLY<br />
." ATED RURAL AESTHAN IT IS IN COiMlPACT CENTRES OF<br />
9LTI~ oiIN ClUES IANTO) W ! 4S. THERE IS NO REASON WHY THE<br />
CITIZCEF NS~ SOULiS D~ HAVE ACICESS TO BETTER LIBRA! t<br />
S ER V CE S 6G EATFER F EE iDC' 1 OF I IFO0R AT 1IN' THFIANI T HE CITIZENS<br />
oi ECHUCttfA oR GrEELOCNG. </p>
<p>ONlE OF THE GOV/ ERNMENT'S CENTRAL AMBITIONS HAS BEEN<br />
TO REDRESS I NEQUALIT IES BETWEEN REG IONS, BETWEEN CITY DWELLERS<br />
AND RESIDENTS OF COUNTRY TOWNS, 11WEB 3ELIEVE THAT A PERSON'S~<br />
STANDARD OF LIVING SHOULD NOT DEPEND ON WRE HE LIVES Of!<br />
IS OBLIGED TO LIVE: WE HAVE TAKEN A NUMiBER OF STEPS TO<br />
ALLEVIATE THE FINANCIAL POSITION OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES AND PROVIDE MORE ADEQUATE AND UNIFORM PUBLIC<br />
LIBRARY AND INFORMATION SERVICES. FOR EXAMPLE, W/ E HAVE.<br />
AMENDED THE GRANTS COMMISSION LEGISLATION TO ENABLE THE<br />
COINMISSION TO RCOMN;. END-GRANTS TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT 0444<br />
T 2AT'~ LREDRESS SREGIONAL INEQUALITIES IN THE SAMiWAY THAT<br />
* INEQUALITIES 2ETWEEN STATES HAVE BEEN ALLEVIATED. LAST'<br />
FINANCIA'' L YEA $ 56 i'lILLION W/ AS ALLOCATED TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
Bouvs; IN i975-76 ALMOST $ 80 MILLION WILL BE GRANTED<br />
7 ZZE GRANTS S-V. ULD DO MUCH TO IMPROVE LOCAL LIBRARIES:<br />
I~ * ADITIO 1, 7HROUGH THE DEPARTMENT OF URBAN AND REGIONAL<br />
DEVELOPMENT, THE GOVERMMENT IS DIRECTLY ASSISTING' SOME<br />
LOCAL AUTHORITIES IN THE PROVIJSION OF LIBRARY SERVICES. </p>
<p>InM, A. RC H THIS YEAR I ANN-OUNCED THE APPOIN.\ TMENT<br />
OF A WIIDE-RANGING COMMl" 1ITTEE OF INQUWIRY INTO PUBLIC LIBRARIES.<br />
IN AUSTRA LI A. [ HERE HAS BEE. N A FULL NT ENCOURAGING RESPONSIE<br />
TO THIS iNQUIRuuY THE CONITTEEJ UNDER THE CHAIRMAiNSHIP OF<br />
. LA.<br />
HIP. R HORTON, HAS ALREADY HELD 13PUBLIC HEARINGS IN THE<br />
STATE CAPITALS, CANBERRA AND DARWIN AND 11' MOIRE HEARINGS IN<br />
REGONL CNTES. IT HAS RECEIVE~ D SOME 350 WRITTEN SUBMISSIONS,<br />
INCLUDING AN4 EXTENSIV/ E AND VALUABLE SUBM" ISSION FROjM YOUR OW4N<br />
ASSOCIATION, WHTWE. ARE SEEKING ARE NOT JUST MORE BOOKS OR<br />
BETTER BUILDINGS BUT A COMPIREHEINSIVE NAT IONAL I NFORII<br />
POLICY, THi.: E IS A L N-TERiMy il D TO C-ORDINATE ANDj.<br />
RATIONALISE ALL L IB R ARY SERVICES, THE RE I S SOI'ME IRONY I N THE<br />
F A CT T HAT C H LD REN OFTEN HAVE A" CCESS TO BETTER LIBRARY SERVICES<br />
* r:~ THEIR PAREllNTS. IN ANY ARE'S THE ONLY LIBRARIES OP ANY*<br />
DID ARE THOSE IN SCHOliOLS. I SOM AEAS THERE I S INOT E VEIN<br />
A S.-Li" OI_ LIBRA" IRY WfiORTHYi OF THE COINSIDERABLE<br />
AUSTlRALliA_. N GOVERNMENT ASSISTANCE H,-AS GOIN'E TO SCHOOL AND<br />
TERTIAIRY EDUCATIONAL LIBRARIES BU. LT VERY LITTLE TO PUBLIC<br />
L 1BRA R I ES C LE-A RL Y THERE IS A NEED TO CO-O1RDINATE THE FUNDING<br />
OF SCHOO-3L A111 ' 3 i~ i:' AL LIB-2RARY SEDVICES 11,1 TlHE PE-ST RESULTS ARE'<br />
To PPE ACHIEVED, AGAIN, THE WORK OF CATALOGUlING LliBRARY<br />
MlATER IAL., COMPI LIN.' G B IBLI OGRAPH IES AND REFERENCE SYSTEMS,'-is<br />
FREQUEINTLY DUI-PLICATED IN MIANY LIBRARIESI THERE IS A NEED TO<br />
EXAMINE 1WHETHER A CENTRAL CATALOGUING AND IN1DEXING SERVICE IS'<br />
cEOFR IIN8 TEEAE THE SORT OF QUESTIONS THAT NUST BE<br />
ANSWERED IN EVALUATING THE EFFrECTI'/ ENESS OF PUBLIC LIBRARIES3<br />
AND DETERMINING THE B'EST M" IETHOD OF FUNDING THEM, </p>
<p>_ 78-* ISHOUL D MENTION A FURTHER INITIATIVE INi THE<br />
DIEVELOPMEN-r OF" A NATIOiNAL INFORH1ATION SERVICE, EARLY LAST<br />
YEAR rH~ E GOVEiRNMEiNT APIPOINTED AN INTER-DEPART'MENTAL COMMITTEE<br />
TO CONSIDER THE ESTABLISHMENT OF AN AUSTRALIAN LIBRARY BASED<br />
INFORMATION SERVICES THIS AROSE FROM A PROPOSAL MADE BY ' THE<br />
NATIONAL LIBRARY. IN THE BUDGET SPEECH LAST YEAR THE THEN<br />
TREASURER ANNOUNCED AN ALLOCATIO'N OF-MORE THAN $ 1MILLION<br />
FOR A FEASI3ALITY. STUDY INTO THE ESALSHETOFSC<br />
S ERIIC E A STAND ING I NTER-DEPARTMENTAL CO" M I TTEE HAS BEEN<br />
A PPOINTED TO SUPERVISE THE SE STUDI ES, ITS INQUIRIES ARE<br />
PROCEEDING. ~ ONE EXAiMIN ES THE RECORD OF TH Is GOVERNMENT ONE_<br />
WILL SEE A BiROAD AND COSSETTEE-AN EMPHASIS ON THE<br />
S F&gt; RED OF ICATOON WIDER ACrCE SS TO INFORMATION), AND<br />
W IT HIN THIS CONTEXNT), A GIENERAL CULTIVATION OF LITERACY AND<br />
C ULT UR E. DO NOT P. REI-TEND, 4. THAT EV/ ERYTHINIG IN THIS AREA<br />
BEARS DIRECTLY CN TWHE WOR. K OF LIBRARIANS) BUT OUR SUPPORT<br />
FOR LIBRARIES -A SUPPORT SPECIFICALLY PROCLAIMED IN MY<br />
POLICY SPE EC H IN, 1,97 2 IS-P ART OF THIS PROCESS. [ HERE IS.)<br />
FFO R EX A MP A CLEAR LINK TO BE SEENl BETWEEN OUR CONCERN FOR<br />
THE MEDIA AND CUP, CONCERN FOR FREEDOM OtF INFORMATIO'N. a89/ </p>
<p>IEVIDENCE OUR INITIAT IVES IN ACCCESS RADIO AND ETHN IC RADIO<br />
STATIONS, INi OUR EXPANSION OF EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES AT<br />
ALL LEVELS, IN THPE PRIMACY WE GIVE? TO PARLIAM~ ENT AS THE<br />
HIHST FOGRUPI OF OPEN POLITICAL DEPBATEJ NTH STBISMN<br />
OFITE AUSTRALIA CONCIL WITH ITS LITERATURE BOARD<br />
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ENCOURAGEMT o F /-USTRALIAN W'RITING,<br />
IN OUR SUPPORT FOR AUTHORS THROUGH THME GRANTING OF A PUBLIC<br />
LEIND ING RI GHT, IN THE LIBERALISATION OF CIENSORSHIP, IN OURGENERIFAL<br />
FUlP DIN.' G OF THE ARTS IOUCONCERNl FOR THE<br />
PRESERVATION OF NATIONAL ARCHIVES AND THE NATIONAL ESTATE-,<br />
ISUG-GEST TH7A 1T THRO0U GH AL TH'E SE POLICY INITIATIVES THERE<br />
RUNS A CONSI STEN T THR" AD OF ENL IGHTENMENT, IT IS CERTAINLY<br />
M'Y HOPE THA. T GOV/ ERMMEN-TS OF WVHATEVER POLITICAL COLOUR WILL<br />
BE JUDGED AS. &gt; IUCHL BY TEIlR PO L ICrIES I N THESE AREAS AS BY<br />
THI PCITs 7\ -': IrCE PRACTICAL-A-ND CONIVEflTIONAL-FIEL DS,<br />
IT1 HR HA U C-PAiMN T TH HIGHEST V'ALUES OF<br />
D -RACY AjND CIVIIZATION IS REVEALED, las/ lu hf </p>
<p>10<br />
THE FUTURE OF YOUR PROFESSION IS FULL OF PROMISE<br />
OF CHANGE AND INNOVATION. MODERN COMPUTER TECHNOLOGY AND<br />
METHODS OF DATA PROCESSING OFFER REMARKABLE OPPORTUNITIES<br />
FOR MORE EFFICIENT LIBRARY AND INFORMATION SERVICES,<br />
THERE IS A MUCH GREATER AWARENESS AMONG GOVERNMENTS AND<br />
AMONG THE PUBLIC OF THE IMPORTANCE OF THE LIBRARY IN<br />
BROADENING OUR KNOWLEDGE, ELEVATING OUR STANDARDS OF TASTE<br />
AND CULTURE AND SAFEGUARDING OUR DEMOCRATIC VALUES, THE<br />
LIBRARY ASSOCIATION OF AUSTRALIA HAS A GREAT ROLE TO PLAY<br />
IN FURTHERING THIS PROCESS, IN IMPROVING THE STATUS OF<br />
YOUR PROFESSION, IN PROMOTING, ESTABLISHING AND IMPROVING<br />
LIBRARY SERVICES IN SHORT, IN FULFILLING THE NOBLE<br />
OBJECTIVES OF YOUR CHARTER. w </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
