<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10299</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP ADDRESS AT THE OFFICIAL OPENING OF THE GARVAN INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH&#039;S NEW BUILDING GARVAN INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/04/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010299.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
7 April 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS AT THE OFFICIAL OPENING OF THE GARVAN INSTITUTE OF<br />
MEDICAL RESEARCH'S NEW BUILDING<br />
GARVAN INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL RESEARCH, SYDNEY<br />
E O E<br />
Well thank you very much Professor Shine, to the Premier of New South Wales, Mr<br />
Bob Carr, your Eminence, to Peter Wills, the Chairman, to Sister Cunliffe, to the other<br />
very distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
That was a very warm and touching introduction. I could perhaps complete the<br />
historical record to say that that particular branch of the Howard family to which the<br />
Duke of Norfolk belongs stoically defied through the centuries the English reparation<br />
presided over or inaugurated by Henry VIII. So there's a very, very strong and very,<br />
very interesting link.<br />
But ladies and gentlemen it's a particular delight for me to be here today. My first<br />
contact with the Garvan Institute was when I was Federal Treasurer I can't imagine<br />
why. But I was visited by, I think it was a trio a pretty formidable trio of<br />
Jim de Minks, Charles Curran and the late Keith Cousins who was a very active<br />
member of the Garvan Institute. And they sat in my then Martin Place office in the old<br />
Commonwealth Bank building and explained the work of the Institute and spoke of the<br />
need for ongoing government support at both a State and a Federal level. And over<br />
the years the role of the Garvan Institute has grown enormously and it has taken its<br />
place alongside a number of other very eminent research institutes all around Australia.<br />
When you think of medical research, I don't think it's an Australian exaggeration to<br />
say that given the size of our population our country has done remarkably well.<br />
Because names like the John Curtin School, the Walter and Eliza, the Howard Florey<br />
Institute, the Garvan Institute here in Sydney, all of them have won, over the years,<br />
worldwide fame and worldwide respect. And on a per capita basis, this country has<br />
done remarkably well. We do have world class medical research. We have world class<br />
medical practitioners. And the cutting edge of medical research here in Australia is<br />
something of which all Australians can be inordinately proud.<br />
The Garvan is part of, what I might call, an enclave of compassion and medical<br />
research in the city of Sydney. It's part of the St Vincent's campus which is an area of </p>
<p>Sydney over the years which has brought unparalleled support and compassion and<br />
care to hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of people irrespective of their<br />
background, irrespective of their views on life. The obligation of all of those that have<br />
worked in that campus have been the relief of suffering and the care of fellow human<br />
beings. And the medical research element of it, of which the Garvan Institute<br />
represents, is of course a very crucial component. And even if you are a mere laymen<br />
in matters relating to medical research and medical technology, which I certainly am,<br />
you can't be other than quite excited at the research, the gene research, which is<br />
occurring at the present time and the almost limitless opportunities that it provides for<br />
rolling back some of the great challenges of disease which have afflicted mankind<br />
through the century.<br />
Can I echo the thanks that have been expressed by Mr Wills and by Professor Shine in<br />
recognising the corporate contributions of so many people. And as I look around this<br />
room I can see people who individually and through the corporate organisations that<br />
they direct that have been in the forefront of philanthropic effort in Australia, not only<br />
in medical research, but today we are thanking them for their contribution to medical<br />
research. It's fashionable for some to criticise the apparent obsession of the corporate<br />
sector with the bottom line and with modern theories of economic rationalism and<br />
hard-hearted, bean-counting approaches to economic management. When I look<br />
around this room I can certainly see one or two people who are believers in<br />
appropriate philosophies of economic restraint and economic commonsense. But they<br />
are simultaneously very generous Australians who've put their hands deeply in their<br />
own pockets and have seen to it that the companies they run-have also supported great<br />
organisations such as the Garvan.<br />
I'm delighted to say that in the last budget, despite cutbacks in other areas, the Federal<br />
Government increased expenditure on medical research. And I can assure you,<br />
without pre-empting the particularities of what might be contained in the May budget,<br />
we certainly won't be reversing that decision in the coming budget.<br />
Medical research is something that should always receive the enthusiastic support of<br />
governments. And I acknowledge the contribution of predecessor Labor governments<br />
in this area. This is a bipartisan effort. The Commonwealth Government has been<br />
very pleased to join the New South Wales Government in making a significant<br />
contribution to the $ 46 million cost of establishing this institute in its current form.<br />
And national health and medical research council funding in the current financial year is<br />
something in the order of $ 160 million.<br />
It is something that's very precious to all of us. It touches the quality of our lives. It<br />
will touch the quality of the lives of our families. It will touch the quality of the lives<br />
of our children of generations to come. It's an important national treasure, medical<br />
research. It's something of which all Australians should be proud. And the Garvan<br />
Institute is the finest example of it here in the city of Sydney. I congratulate all of<br />
those that are associated with it. I particularly acknowledge the dedicated commitment<br />
of the Sisters of Charity and of the enormous support that their inspirational work has<br />
drawn from people of all faiths and, indeed, of no faiths in the city of Sydney over long<br />
years of dedication to the relief of human suffering. And I'm delighted to join the<br />
Premier of New South Wales at the opening of this fine new building. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
