<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>364</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 48/1961 - EXTENSION OF THE PERIOD OF OPERATION OF THE 1956/1961 SUGAR AGREEMENT - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000364.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. 48/ 1 1<br />
EXTETSION OF THE PERIOD OF OP: ERATION OF THE<br />
j-1 56/ f96.1 SUGAR AGREEI'MENT__<br />
Statement by the Prm e " Minister the Rt. HonMenzies<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Menzies, announced today that<br />
the Commonwealth Government and the Queensland Government had<br />
agreed to extend until 31st May, 1962, the period of operation of<br />
the 1956/ 61 Sugar Agreement, which would otherwise have expired<br />
on 31st August, 1961.<br />
Mr. Menzies said that his Government had decided last<br />
year that an examination of the sugar industry should be carried<br />
out before steps were taken to enter into a new sugar agreement<br />
with the Queensland Government when the 1956/ 61 Agreement expired.<br />
Accordingly the Sugar Enquiry Committee, under the C. airmanship<br />
of Mr. M. E. McCarthy, was appointed to investigate the<br />
circumstances of the sugar and fruit industries and their<br />
relationship. The Committee had been asked to furnish its report<br />
if possible not later than May 1961, but owing to the wide scope<br />
of the investigation and some unexpected difficulties the<br />
Committee had been unable to complete its leport in the time<br />
proposed. Mr. Menzies said that since the current Agreemennt was<br />
due to expire on 31st August and the Committee's report was still<br />
not available the Commonwealth Government and the Queensland<br />
Government had decided that the existing Agrooment rould need to<br />
be extended for the further period necessary to enable full<br />
consideration of the report, the framing of a now formal<br />
Agrouemnt mutually acceptable to both Governments and the<br />
introduction of the necessary legislation.<br />
CANBERRA,<br />
1st September, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
