<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5425</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE METAL TRADES INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION OF AUSTRALIA, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005425.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L'S gmz rii~-<br />
TRALIA '' 7<br />
~ Zj K N.,<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, 25 AUGUST,<br />
ADDRESS TO THE METAL TRADES INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION OF AUSTPALIA<br />
SYUNEY<br />
I am pleased to be able to address this distinguished gathering<br />
of manufacturers. Economic debate at present is dominated by<br />
the Budget brought down last week. Today I will try to put<br />
that Budget in context, in terms both of the present economric<br />
outlook and of the Government's persistent anti-inflationary<br />
strategy. But what needs to be said at the outset is that Australia is<br />
on the verge of what could be one of the most exciting eras<br />
of economic develop-ment in its history. As a result, we are<br />
facing prospects different both in kind and magnitude from<br />
anything experienced in recent years: prospects, on the one<br />
hand., of potential growth and increasing living standards for<br />
all. Australians, and, on the other hand, of problems and<br />
difficulbies in ensuring that potential is achieved. But th._ n
as has been said, life wasn't meant to be easy.<br />
On present prospects, the growth capacity of our economy for<br />
the 80s is going to be stretched increasingly to its limits.<br />
This will demand firm and forward looking policies from<br />
Government to make sure that inflationary pressures are contained<br />
and sustainable growth continues.<br />
Australia suffered a series of major shocks during Labor's period<br />
in office, which fundamentally distorted the workings of the<br />
economy. As a nation, we have paid dearly for the wild and<br />
reckless policies of that period: in terms of a lower growth<br />
in national output and, hence, in our standard of living, as<br />
well as in much higher unemployment.<br />
One of the reasons wages escalated under the previous Labor<br />
administration was that the then Government encouraged unions<br />
and tribunals to seek excessive wage increases. Indeed, the<br />
Commionwealth Public Service was used as a pacesetter in wage<br />
determination. And the with organic links to the union<br />
movement, was not in a position to withstand union pressure, even<br />
if it had been interested in doing so.<br />
Over the last weeks, there has been some talk of a social contCract.<br />
Of course, the unions reject it because such a contract would<br />
diminish their future freedom of action. The so-called " agreement"<br />
between the A. L. P. and the unions was not a contract at all.<br />
For the unions are still determined to get as much as they can from<br />
the Arbitration Commission, and as much as they can on top of<br />
that from employers. / 2<br />
b&gt;&gt; AU S </p>
<p>2-<br />
But in addition, A. L. P. policy, which grants immunity to<br />
unions from penalties for strike action, would effectively<br />
place the union movement above the law. Such an approach<br />
would open the door to the kind of wage escalation that<br />
occurred in the mid-70s. And the consequences of that would<br />
be obvious to everyone here.<br />
Mr. Hayden has demonstrated that he wants union p eace at any<br />
price; but the price will inevitably be paid by all Australians.<br />
The A. L. P./ union document merely creates expectations that the<br />
Labor Party will comply with union demands. It was such a policy<br />
on owages, agreed to by the last conference, and binding<br />
on all members of the IPart-, that Mr. Wran calloc&amp; " a hotclh po"-. ch",<br />
and 14r. Hawke called " a gutless sell-out to the left". And as<br />
one of the major newspaper editorials reminds us this morning,<br />
Mr. Hawke let it be known " that he felt that he had been ' sold out'<br />
and that Mr. Hayden could not be trusted".<br />
Bill Hayden says he has a " special relationship with the trade<br />
union movement". That is true, he has like the special<br />
relationship that exists between a ventriloquist and his doll<br />
a slight twist from the left wrist and Bill's head nods up<br />
and down. / 3 </p>
<p>it has taken time to reduce the distortions created by Labor<br />
and beogin to restore the conditions in which the private sector<br />
can ex~ pand with confidence. But five yerars of concie-ntCratC. ed and<br />
persistent effort is now bcinnina to pay off. Let there be no<br />
mistake: even today, our inflation rate gives us no grounds for<br />
complaceflcy, but it has improved in absolute terms, having been<br />
reduced from around 17 Der cent in 1975 to just ovr 10 per cent<br />
als iapt~ rea iv t e tezs ' Lr om n e a rly<br />
~ canageocits -astr than O. E. C. D. a7. verage in 1973, -to<br />
3 percentage Points slow, er than that averag, during the past<br />
J. 1, z 0 n n in Au str-ali. ' S jt z r jht Jofln; C0 L. i V : L<br />
a subject with which everyone in this audience is fam-iliar.<br />
Last year, when roost O. E. C. D. coun-tries had higher, external<br />
tr'e deficits, Australia's was sn-arply reducedc. T'hat ex_ ternal<br />
lrmoroverment has allow,-ed the Governm,-ent to brincr the exp~ anded1<br />
official overseas borrow-. ing program-Me to a successfLul coclusion.<br />
But, mo-re importantly1,, to both this audience and the count-ry as<br />
a w., hole, the improved international competitiv\. eness of Australian<br />
industry is now permitting increased exports over a wide range.<br />
This is reflected in the figures.<br />
The value of our exports last year rose by 33 per cent, and the<br />
value of rural exports rose by ove--r 40 per cent. But the<br />
increase in Australia' s internatienal competitiv . eness " has also<br />
Ov -e r me~ l, 1a s: t<br />
yeasexports of maru Factures are estimated to r'iva: crare<br />
in real terms by no less than 23 per cent, showinc auite clearly'<br />
that Australian manufacturing indcustry can comete successfully<br />
against international comiipetition.<br />
This expansion has not been confEined to the processing of our<br />
natural resources, important thoug: h that is. The value of<br />
eXports of machinery and transport equipment, for example, rose<br />
by over 50 per cent in the last two years. In sho-rt, the most<br />
effec-tive export incentive Provided by the Governrmant'has been<br />
the imnorovement in international competitiveness 1-1ich our policies<br />
have brought about. That improve--nnt is also contributing<br />
imoortantly -to the upsurge in inr. 7atent in Australian industry,<br />
including investment from overseas.<br />
Last Lotfd rr-cn i. er. rlL n Juta. a entuorise~ s<br />
waso ver $ 2,500 million, more than $ 500 million flagne r t-nan for<br />
thle sameL1 Period a year b) efore, and almost double thle level ofL<br />
two years ago. But the benefits of' reducing inflation are not<br />
limited inmprovement in international comrpeLt2. JtJ-veness. A l oweTPr<br />
rate off inflation, anrd particularly inflation of waeCosts, is<br />
central to improving profitability.<br />
There is a need for such imp rove -rent, and -the esitimated 16 per<br />
cent increase in companies' opercau" nq surplus in 1979-80 is<br />
w e ICo) me, 0-. I t I s n1o ncidence th a t improved pro f -iab ility hnas<br />
gone hand in hand with both high. er employment and an, upsuroe in<br />
expected inve-_ stment. A1 </p>
<p>4<br />
Those who deride higher profits would do well to remember<br />
that without profits there can, in the end, be no jobs. In July<br />
this year, on figures released at noon today, 212,000 more people<br />
were . in employment than was the case a year ago. And this is a<br />
record increase over a twelve month period. And prospects are<br />
good for a further rise in employment this year.<br />
That will come partly from investment in the major resource-<br />
, ased projects now. in tra-in, including their call upon other<br />
Australian industries for supplies of materials and equipment<br />
and not least the industries chiefly represented here today.<br />
Fut the prospective inves'ment surge is not confined to resource<br />
eviopn en t projects.<br />
The statistician's recent survey of expectations of business<br />
fixed investment in 1980-81 suggests strong growth, in real<br />
terms, more or less across the board, with nearly every section<br />
of manufacturing and tertiary industry expecting a strong<br />
investment rise as, of course, does the mining industry. This<br />
is consistent with the very strong outlook for investment<br />
reflected in other surveys of investment intentions that are less<br />
specific as to timing, but which in a more diffused way indicate<br />
that the expected strong increase in investment in 1980-81 is<br />
likely to be only the beginning of what we must now call the<br />
decade of development.<br />
But we must not jeopardise our chances. We must not fritter<br />
away our opportunities through the illusion of ' quick-fixes'<br />
offered by irresponsible policies. The realisation of our<br />
te: nticl1 as a nation is dependen, upon continuing fir. fisc. l<br />
d monetary policies. And without appropriate resistance to<br />
growing pressures for excessive increases in hourly wages, this<br />
potential could be squandered. For it is not additions to money<br />
wages, but increases in the nation's productive capacity that<br />
allow us to raise living standards in any continuing sense.<br />
So far as the immediate outlook is concerned, it is not merely<br />
investment that is on the rise. Looking at the economy as a<br />
whole, there is a major contrast with last year, when, particularly<br />
in the first half, external trade contributed most to the improved<br />
level of activity.<br />
This year, domestic demand is set to provide most of our growth,<br />
which the Treasury predicts, will be somewhat faster than in<br />
1979-80, making it the third year in a row when growth in real<br />
noi-farm-cut-ou has improved. All this is coming at a. time of<br />
liitle or no grow. th in the O. E. C. D. area as a whole, and iwhen<br />
two. of the major industrialised economies of the world, the U. S. A.<br />
and Britain, are in the grip of recession and when most other<br />
Western economies are seriously flagging.<br />
Why is it that, in these difficult times, with the exception of<br />
the motor vehicle industry, the Australian economy is experiencing<br />
a strengthening in business activity, more or less across the<br />
board? I put it to you that Government policies provide much of<br />
the answer. </p>
<p>The consistent application of respon sible policies has reduced<br />
Lne unce rtain ty attached -to pvaedecis ion-makinc and<br />
i7-2rovac-: i sicinificantly the underlying conditions in hihthe<br />
Drivate sector operaltes. We recognised the need for-. su:: h Policies<br />
ficveers ago-This is no--a beginninc to be recognised world wido.<br />
The economic survey of Aus-tralia, published by the O. E. C. D. last<br />
ncnh, 3O~ L~ r-, Ut+ t1hat,<br />
Mmahcai g ement of the Alustralian economym has re-ained<br />
broadly1 unchang~ ed since late 19715, when the authorilties<br />
cmnzdon a scayplcyL: ec hih hog<br />
cc muvncthe imbalance2s impedirie a ret. no<br />
su s L i i~ Thti: or: ary go. tovr tne t-arimu "<br />
The O. E. C. D. went on: to say that the,<br />
of coIoeitveF is no-i much higher anC; re -al<br />
uni t labour costL-s slightly lowe-cr than in 1975, and these<br />
condi -tions seem-i to be reflected in the recent strengtheningr<br />
ofr mi-nuafacturin; outnut investment and epo enovrthe<br />
lasc. 18 months or so".<br />
A key element in our policies has been the restrairt on public<br />
sec or siuending, and on public sector calls on financial markets,*<br />
e:<. erci="" sed="" th="" rougrh="" the="" cornmonwea="" lt="">-Budge.<br />
Beteen1975-76 and last year, Com onwelth Budget outlay-, were<br />
: v'm ~ b3o0 cnt ) F 1 P. to about 2 3e c<br />
7 frm ner&gt;: 5 pe r cent of t~ o unO~<br />
2 prcent. The Bud,' get presented-' Last Tuesday is framed arou-nd<br />
a frersignificant reduct'ion in-the total budget defEicit to<br />
a i t tlIe a,-re r 1 p er ce nt o f G . D a nd t.: o a Po0i nt Er e t he-a<br />
deficit on domestic transactions ill be eliminated in the curr-~ nt<br />
financi al year.<br />
This conrfirms the ability of the GCovernmen-t to back: its economic<br />
; Drescriiutions with action. We ara-paying our way again. zh is<br />
respresents a signi-ficant achievem-ent in fiscal responsibilit.-y.<br />
Low~ er bu)--dget deficits are a g oal w. 7hich is embraced almost4<br />
uniformly by the govern-ments of in-dustrialised count-ries. B utfew<br />
count'Cries havi. e achieved as much in this respec-t as Australia.<br />
Of cuecentral to achievina this is the ex: 7 ICise of re--stra-in-t<br />
-Dn C, C-tse1 ou~ l~: at<br />
m es* ra :ñ crcngrowtr<br />
h of over 3 per ccnt in non-farm product,. demonstra-Linr<br />
cierlv, to those w,. ho still need2 any such demonstration -ta<br />
the economny is quite capable of gaining . strength , ithout a soc)-<br />
called stim-, ulus' from t'he Public sector.<br />
Of cour our political opponents still pursue the discredite~ d<br />
line of arguing f~ or rapid ex:-pansion of the public sector-Un<br />
until last week, they were commodtted to $ 2,000 mllion in fiv<br />
areas of ex-penditure alone, and thI-is figure does nottk intco<br />
ac-coun-t 1more than 250 other unco:; te2d e::, Penditu-re p~ rogjramm-, es;. </.></p>
<p>6<br />
But then Mr. Hayden went on the ABC programme, and made a<br />
further commitment to raise pensions to 25 per cent of average<br />
weekly earnings. Even though pensions, as a proportion of average<br />
weekly earninas are now almost the highest they have ever been,<br />
the c mmitn tn by Mr. Hayden to lift them to 25 per cent of<br />
average weekly earnings would cost as much as $ 500 million. And<br />
the further commitment, which he gave, to raise them in the longterm<br />
to 30 per cent of average weekly earnings would represent,<br />
a furtiher cost of more than $ 1,400 million. This is lv a<br />
recycling of past Labor failures.<br />
Labor spending proposals could only be funded through massive<br />
increases in taxation, and Labor have already threatened us<br />
with that; or a massive increase in the size of the deficit.<br />
And we can only judge them by their record. In the year to<br />
March 1975, award wages for males rose by almost 35% and for<br />
females bv over 40% increases that would normally take many<br />
years to earn through increased productivity. In one year,<br />
under Labor, Commonwealth Budget outlays rose by 46%; an increase<br />
which exceeds the total increase in Commonwealth Budget outlays<br />
of the first four Liberal Budgets. It takes a long time to pay<br />
off debts, but we have managed to balance the Budget on the<br />
domestic side. In today's conditions, reducing the demands made<br />
by the public sector is essential to the growth of the economy<br />
as a whole. It is because of this growth that the Government has<br />
been able to increase its assistance to business, and meet its<br />
commitment to those in the community who, through no fault of<br />
their own, need our help.<br />
The challenges of the 80s will call for new responses from the<br />
business community. That is why this Budget provides for: a<br />
loading to existing depreciation rates, an increase of<br />
in-the funds for the export expansion and market development<br />
programmes, an increase of 55% in funds available for industrial<br />
research and development; which includes an increase of over<br />
i1 co-encement grants which ,7iil encourage small and<br />
medium-sized firms to develop a research capability.<br />
A major initiative, designed not just to assist small business<br />
but for the benefit of all self-employed, is the new tax concession<br />
for superannuation. It applies to the self-employed, and to any<br />
employee who is not covered by a superannuation scheme funded<br />
by an employer. And contributions up to a limit of $ 1200 will be<br />
deductible from assessable income. / 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
New initiatives in last week's Budget reflect the concern of the<br />
Government for the paradox of high youth unemployment co-existing<br />
with the growing shortage of skilled labour. Because of this,<br />
we announced in December 1979 a five year, $ 250 million<br />
school-to-work transition programme, in conjunction with the<br />
States. The Budget provides a 22% increase in funds for<br />
apprenticeship and emplo-ment training programmes, and we have<br />
also introduced a tapered income test for unemployment benefits<br />
in order to provide more incentive for unemployed_ people to<br />
part-time work.<br />
The Biu-. t's initiatives under the Comionwealth Mapower, Traini. n<br />
and Youth Support Programmes mean that by th end of this<br />
financial year, about 800,000 people will hae been assisted, since<br />
we came to office, through the range of Government schemes.<br />
Regrettably, many of the young people for whom these programmes<br />
exist are products of an education system which, for too long,<br />
has plc too -mucehm -h asis on academic cualities. It has<br />
ignored the needs of those whose talens lie in different<br />
vocational directions, especially those requiring trade training<br />
and manual skills. It is essentially the responsibility of<br />
Au stra. lian schools develop the cualities and talents of all<br />
Australi an stud. ent; to find som. ething that each student can do<br />
'. weli, with enthsi a m.<br />
I doubt very much whether many of our schools are meeting that<br />
standard now. To the extent that they are not, I -regard the school<br />
system as failing many thousands of young Australians. I think<br />
w. cg-gt a b c. r: result fro:.~ our sc: hoo! inof<br />
saying, ' these young people have failed in school', we put it<br />
correctly that school. has failed these young Australians because<br />
it has not found something that each can do well something to<br />
give each of them a satisfying and rewarding life when they leave<br />
school. The Government is dedicated to minimising the difficulties faced<br />
by yo'ung people in seeking employment. And, . in this and other<br />
areas, the Budget provides significant reforms to assist those in<br />
need. These include, an increase in the handicapped child's allowance,<br />
which will provide improved assistance to 27,000 handicapped<br />
children; a national employment strategy for the handicapped.<br />
In our first Budget, we introduced triennial funding to eligible<br />
organisations to provide more certain and effective help for<br />
handicapped persons. In the last three years, the funds that we have<br />
made available through this programme have increased by almost<br />
in real terms, over the levels that operated in the three<br />
Labor years.<br />
Other initiatives in this Budget provide for an increase in the<br />
allowance for dependent children of pensioners and beneficiaries,<br />
which will assist 560,000 children, the removal of the six month<br />
waiting period for supporting parent's benefit, an increase in<br />
the mother's/ guardian's allowance which will benefit about 190,000<br />
single parent families, and the extension of the right to<br />
pensioner health benefits to eligible sickness beneficiaries. / 8 </p>
<p>8<br />
These initiatives demonstrate that the hard decisions require,.<br />
in the last four years, to secure sustainable economic growth<br />
have not compromised our commitment to the disadvantaged. But this<br />
commitment can only be maintained in an economic environment in which<br />
the private sector is encouraged to expand. That is why the<br />
Government is concerned to see that this expansion is not frustrated<br />
by inappropriate wage structures. This is especially so because<br />
the wage tribunals have continued to hand down decisions<br />
inconsistent with the needs of the economy, as well' as harmful<br />
to the needs of those who are seeking jobs.<br />
Through the wage indexation process, and the continued spread<br />
of so-called " w. ork value" determinations, wage tribunals have<br />
brought us to the point where accel. erating wage inflation begins<br />
to constitute a major threat to the economy. In resisting these,<br />
wage inflation pressures, the Government is playing its part,<br />
and will continue to do so. But employers also have an important<br />
responsibility to resist such pressures.<br />
I therefore wholeheartedly endorse the IN. T. I. A's campaiqn<br />
against the NMetal Industries Unions' destructive claim. rfor<br />
a 35-hour week. The metal industries have already suffered<br />
sharply increased labour costs as a result of the " work value"<br />
round and two sizeable national wage increases in January and<br />
July this year; decisions which have added more than 14 per<br />
cent to the award rates of pay in these industries in the space<br />
or ins_: ie~ rt<br />
A reduction in the standard working week to 35 hours would . add<br />
to hourly rates o-f nay and raise abour cots still frt-r.<br />
Even Mr. Hayden ear i. er in the yeer ocveas the nrc 0. Ir 2<br />
-w-Ce B 3ut iuicLO soon revursed this spar: o.<br />
responsibility, and Mr. Hayden supported the proposal in<br />
a-he proponents of the shorter working week are dishonestly<br />
aradi: i. n it as an unemployment relief scheme. It is nlablI<br />
nonsense to say that a -measure which would raise labour cost-s<br />
would reduce unemployment. On the contrary, by undearminingc the<br />
profitability and international competitiveness of industry, it<br />
would put more people out of wor?, and I am tempted to assert<br />
that this. is indeed an objective of some of its morc pro:.. inent<br />
advocates, who are much more interested in fosteringc disruption<br />
in our econofmy anrd our society than in working for the good of<br />
those they purport to represent.<br />
Ausbtrai has entered a decade which has a potentia:. for economic<br />
deveorment unparalleled in ou-history. Th2e d . lomen that<br />
is in prospect-demonstrates the faith the private sector has in<br />
the future of the Australian economy. That faith depends, to a<br />
large degree, on the belief that we will continue to implement<br />
our economic strategy. And beating inflation is still the key<br />
to that strategy.<br />
The Government will not allow a small and disaffected minority<br />
to de: troy our prospects.. The 1980-81 Budget, in association<br />
w: i. th an appropriate monetary policy, and with the co-operation of<br />
the vast majority of Australians, employers and employees, is<br />
directed to ensuring that those prospects are realised. Against<br />
that background, I commend it to you.<br />
000----</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
