<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9805</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J KEATING MP ADDRESS TO ALP DINNER, GREEK CLUB, BRISBANE 20 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009805.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
ADDRESS TO ALP DINNER, GREEK CLUB, BRISBANE,<br />
OCTOBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you very much indeed. Thanks very much Bob Gibbs ( QLD Party<br />
President), Wayne and Roisin, members from the State Cabinet, my Deputy<br />
Kim Beazley, members of our Federal Cabinet, Lord Mayor Jim and Mary,<br />
Mike Kaiser and Maree and friends one and all.<br />
Well, it is always good to be back at the Greek Club, always a marvellous<br />
audience, always a marvellous Labor audience and it should be because<br />
Queensland is a Labor State. I am particularly proud to be here with Wayne.<br />
I was here with him three years ago when we did and said all those things<br />
then at the start of that election and I am delighted to see his Government<br />
back in office because you can see what a difference it makes in Western<br />
Australia this week what a difference a Labor government makes. I thank<br />
him for his uplifting speech and for the uplifting sentiments.<br />
This is a Labor State. We lost it for a very-long period of time until he won it<br />
back and we always remember, of course, that the Labor Party was born in<br />
Queensland and every time I come here I am reminded what a remarkable<br />
Party it is, more than 100 years old and it has seen the transformation of the<br />
country, seen all the history, made a large part of it and has gone on adapting<br />
itself and adapting Australia. One hundred years later our Party is still useful<br />
to Australia, still cutting the mustard, still making the way, still puffing our<br />
stamp upon this country and we are stronger now than we have ever been<br />
and we will win the next election.<br />
We will win the next election because Australians will not want to squander<br />
all the hard work of this last decade. They won't want to make the<br />
commitments they have made to build a new modem, efficient, outward<br />
looking country and squander it. They will always choose to go forward.<br />
Australians always choose to go forward, they will never go back. I don't<br />
think Queenslanders are any different than their fellow Australians. They<br />
have always cherished in this State our best traditions, the best traditions of<br />
Australia and, of course, many of our best traditions began here. They will </p>
<p>stay true to the course and if we have faith in Queenslanders, they will have<br />
faith in us and I think that we can show them that we have delivered.<br />
At the last election our most solemn pledge and our most solemn promise<br />
was to restore the economy back to growth and to get unemployment down.<br />
Remember at the time I said we wouldn't leave the unemployed behind and<br />
we have done these things. When the quarter we are living in, this current<br />
quarter of the year, when the figures for the quarter come out it will show that<br />
we have had 17 consecutive quarters of growth. Four full years and the first<br />
quarter of our fifth year and those 17 consecutive quarters will make it the<br />
longest growth phase since World War 11 670,000 jobs since the election,<br />
we made a target of half a million, they said it will never be achieved, it's just<br />
a bit of banter, never be achieved! We got to 500,000 jobs in two thirds of<br />
the time in two years and we are now at 670,000 since the election. While<br />
we have done that of course, we have consolidated low inflation. Not only<br />
have we broken the back of inflation as no other government was able to do<br />
after it struck Australia, but we have got it around now running at 2.5 to 3 per<br />
cent. Remember about two months ago all the foreboding from the Liberal party<br />
when the current account deficit came out at $ 3 billion for the month. They<br />
went on about our debt, how we were ruined and then the following month it<br />
was $ 2.2 billion and last month it was $ 1.5 billion, last month we were at half<br />
of what it was two months earlier and now we are starting to see the current<br />
account trending down. So, if you look at where we are I don't think we have<br />
been anything like this in 12 years. In fact, the Governor of the Reserve<br />
Bank made that point in today's press 4 per cent growth, 4 per cent<br />
employment growth, 2-3 per cent inflation, the current account deficit trending<br />
down and exports booming. While we have done all that we have got the<br />
budget back into surplus, we have dramatically expanded superannuation so<br />
that all of us will have a better standard of living in retirement. Everyone by<br />
the year 2002 which is not far away, just seven years away will have<br />
per cent minimum being put away for everybody to improve their income in<br />
retirement while producing at the same time a massive pool of retirement<br />
savings to help the country ease its savings path, to call upon for investment,<br />
to give us a stronger economy and a stronger income for all of us into the<br />
future. And to anneal these achievements while we have been doing that, we<br />
have strengthened our identity and our culture. We have righted the wrong<br />
of terra nullius with our indigenes. We have given them back that part of the<br />
remaining land that was always theirs. We have built a relationship of quality<br />
and trust with the countries of the region which, I think, is without precedent<br />
and we threaded together while we have been doing all that the most<br />
ambitious free trade undertaking in the world APEC and at the same time<br />
layed down the blue print for an Australian republic.<br />
We have done all these things in three years, in less than three years.<br />
Within one Parliament. We have made Australia a country that we can be<br />
proud of and, I think, we have made it one of the fairest countries in the world<br />
and that is what the Labor government, after all, is all about. It is about<br />
fairness. It is about equity. It is about imagination. It is about belief. It is ' A<br />
A~ I~ </p>
<p>about faith. Faith in our fellow Australians, compassion for their lot in life and<br />
belief in Australia. But now at the brink of a new century we can't go back.<br />
We can't go back to the inequality. We can't go back to our past<br />
uncompetitiveness. We can't go back to the conflict, to our continental<br />
insularity, to the monoculture, to the denial of truth about our indigenes, to<br />
the monarchy. We can't go back to the old Australia. We can't go back to<br />
John Howard's Australia.<br />
We can't go back to the man who describes himself as the most conservative<br />
leader the conservative parties have ever had. To the man who a week ago<br />
told us Asia was a threat. To a man that told us when he was leader that<br />
Australians need to avoid being fooled by Gorbechov and Perestroika. Who<br />
railed vociferously against the economic sanctions against South Africa and<br />
condemned our government's anti apartheid policy as mistaken and who<br />
opposed the government's south pacific nuclear free zone initiative. We can't<br />
go back to that person and to those things.<br />
Imagine if John Howard had been managing Australia over the last twelve<br />
years. There would have been no accord, no awards, no Medicare, no safety<br />
net, no superannuation, no Daintree, no Gordon Below Franklin, no leap into<br />
Asia and no progress towards a republic. In other words, we would be a<br />
completely different kind of Australia, a right wing regressive backwater of a<br />
country that would be unrecognisable from the country that we have today.<br />
We have seen him in the last week with industrial relations. John Howard is<br />
always talking about support for families. He says he is in favour of families.<br />
He is in favour of families but not in favour of family support. He is in favour<br />
of families but not in favour of awards. He is in favour of families but he is not<br />
in favour of overtime rates. He is in favour of families but he is not in favour<br />
of penalty rates. He is in favour of families but he is not in favour of annual<br />
leave loadings. He basically believes as the Western Australian government<br />
does, that he can cut across the rights of society, he can break the social<br />
contract, he can do things which rob Australians of their sense of democracy<br />
and their rights. He can do things to say that Australians can't withdraw their<br />
labour, that they must keep their heads down, they have to work for the offer<br />
that they have been given, that we take them back to where they were more<br />
than a century ago in the 1890s. These are the things that he believes in.<br />
But this week was, I think, quite revealing about the Liberal party. It is<br />
haunted you know by its past. It is a bit like a haunted house. The echoes<br />
come out of the walls, the old policies the old individual wage contracts or<br />
the old disasters like Vietnam you see, he wouldn't see Do Muoi here five or<br />
six weeks ago. He wouldn't meet the paramount leader of Vietnam, but the<br />
US Secretary of State met him two days later. He was good enough for<br />
Warren Christopher but not good enough for John Howard.<br />
They are haunted and it keeps bubbling out. In just one week we have had<br />
Mr Andrews the Parliamentary Secretary to Mr Costello the Shadow<br />
Treasurer talking about the need for a GST. We have had Bronwyn Bishop<br />
giving us her treatise on families and children. She said ' I think it is an </p>
<p>important principle that when you bring children into the world you have to<br />
remain responsible for them and that it is not the tax payers responsibility to<br />
pick up the remnants of a family when it breaks up.' She is a real charmer<br />
isn't she? She is a real sweetie, Bronwyn.<br />
Then we had Costello, of course, today with his state income taxes. They, of<br />
course, won't show us their policies. Andrew Robb says they are 98 per cent<br />
prepared, but he won't let the public see them. Supposedly to keep them<br />
from me, but somebody on the inside on one of the consultancies who are<br />
working with them, gave the story to the BRW Business Review Weekly<br />
published today, saying that basically they want income taxes for the States<br />
so the States can put their rates up as they see fit. So you would have a<br />
different rate in Queensland to NSW to Victoria et cetera. In other words,<br />
they would fracture the country and break it up.<br />
Then you have got, of course, Mr Fischer. Did you see him on Lateline the<br />
other night? That was a -stunning performance wasn't it? Kerry O'Brien said<br />
to him ' well, you would have to concede that it does on the face of it give<br />
ammunition to the Government's claims that the Coalition is a policy free<br />
zone?' He said ' but we do have policies, policies of substance, policies in the<br />
pipeline, policies some aspects of which have already been announced. On<br />
the small front but important, the reintroduction of the black spots road<br />
program.' This is one of our programs. It happens to be an important one,<br />
but you would hardly say it was the rationale, as the principle policy focus of<br />
a deputy prime minister talking about the policy framework for a new<br />
government. Of course, John Howard said it would dribble out. I made some illusion to Mr<br />
Newman from that Mad magazine years ago, but it wasn't appreciated. But, it<br />
is dribbling out and as it is, it is not doing him any good. I mean, we have<br />
seen just in the last week his GST out from Andrews, Bronwyn Bishop giving<br />
us her view on children and the support of children I don't think the Pope is<br />
on her side. Mr Costello with state income taxes and then, of course, I had<br />
little Johnny at 8: 00am Monday morning. Now, I don't listen to I used to<br />
be an ' AM' junkie until 1983 and I gave it up. I broke the habit. But my<br />
colleague Don Russell is coming back from the US to support us and I<br />
thought he would be on ' AM' so I turned it on.. And heard them say we<br />
have got a blockade in Western Australia and we will cross live in the<br />
Canberra studio to the Leader of the Opposition. So, I thought oh here he is<br />
like the cat who swallowed the cream. Sitting up there about to lay into this<br />
strike which Premier Court and he have basically conjured up, lay it on us as<br />
if it is our responsibility. Sure enough, first sentence, and he has now got this<br />
Menzian tone of voice, he says ' I think it is a disgraceful thing in a country like<br />
this when a Prime Minister will allow the blockade of a State'. Now, I don't<br />
know whether he has been schooled in this, but this is now the way he is.<br />
It is a long time since I phoned in, I wouldn't even know what the number was.<br />
So I got onto Greg Turnbull and said ' you had better get me that ' AM'<br />
producer because I want to get into this and I had the flu, I was as crook as<br />
Rookwood I can tell you. Anyway I staggered to the telephone, in the dark, </p>
<p>and I got on there but I got the drift after a while because they put me through<br />
to the sound box so I had the debate coming over. Of course, it didn't take<br />
me long to hit the themes. The main theme was if John Howard was Prime<br />
Minister this is how it would be every week that he was Prime Minister.<br />
Well, it was only in the evening that we saw the film footage of his reaction. I<br />
don't know whether you saw it, but it was one of the classics of Australian<br />
politics. He took the earphones off and then banged them back on and<br />
banged his glasses off and then put them back on straight again and banged<br />
himself again, then said ' turn him off, turn him off and I thought God! he has<br />
got St Vitus dance. He is doing an Inspector Clouseau impersonation here.<br />
Now, it is little wonder he is hearing voices. There is little wonder there is<br />
echoes from the haunted house because as we squeeze him, as we squeeze<br />
the tube and a bit comes out, every bit that comes out always leaves us<br />
plenty of room to get into it because they have no policy structure and they<br />
have no discipline.<br />
And it is the same team, the same old team that was there at the last election.<br />
Sixteen of the nineteen are the same ones who put Fightback together. The<br />
new ones are simply replicates. Bronwyn Bishop being one of them.<br />
He said this recently, he said this on radio. He was on with Jeremy Cordeux<br />
in South Australia:-' the major issue will be what Mr Howard, industrial<br />
relations do you think or what?' And Howard says with all of the<br />
seriousness he could summon ' no, I think the major issue will be essentially<br />
whether or not it really isn't time that a new group of people were given the<br />
leadership of this country.' Not that you deserve it. Not that you have got an<br />
agenda for change. Not that you can lead the nation. Just that a new group<br />
can come in and give us the leadership of this country. You know, like the<br />
new Minister for Trade Mr Fischer, the new Deputy Prime Minister, our black<br />
spots specialist. Or the new Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Downer. Now,<br />
there's a fresh face. Or the new Minister for Industrial Relations Mr Reith, he<br />
is real new. Or that happiest one of them all that new Minister for<br />
Employment, Mr Kemp. He is always such a happy fellow. Or the New<br />
Minister for Privatisation, Senator Bishop. Or Mr New himself, the member<br />
for Bennelong. Or the new Treasurer, of course, Mr Costello.<br />
There never was a new group quite as old as this one. Never was thinking so<br />
stale. Now, you can take recycling so far, but this is taking it to absurd<br />
lengths. You have got to say when you look at some of the other people like,<br />
and I always forget his name, that young monarchist, Abbott. Yes, the mad<br />
Abbott. You have got to say of the Liberal Party where do they find these<br />
junior monarchists to lead Australia into the 21st century? Do they look<br />
around for them or do they just spring up naturally? Where do they find these<br />
relatively young men and women with the social and political ideas of a<br />
century ago. I mean you have got to look pretty hard.<br />
The fact is, this is what we face. This is the same group that put Fightback<br />
together. I said the other day they have had the sort of Paulian conversion<br />
on the road to Damascus. I mean, 16 of the 19 of them wanted to throw the </p>
<p>unemployed off unemployment benefits after nine months. They wanted to<br />
set up a GST. They wanted to make young Australians pay full fees at<br />
university. They wanted to abolish Medicare. But now, they are into ' me<br />
tooism'. They are in all the things the Government believes. You say<br />
Medicare, ' no we're for that'. You know, expansion of opportunity in schools,<br />
no. we're for that.' Awards, ' no we're for that.' So, well God! if that is the<br />
case why don't you let the authors of the policy. If we are the authors of the<br />
policy why don't let us do the governing? ' No' they say ' it's time for a new<br />
group to run Australia'. Time for a new group to run Australia. In other<br />
words, it is on a rotational basis. You know, they have had five turns and<br />
now it is our turn. I mean, you know how it works inside the Liberal Party.<br />
Howard used to go around saying Andrew has had two turns and I want two<br />
turns and he got two turns. He got two turns and now he thinks, he says ' now<br />
they have had five turns it is our turn. It is a new group and it is our time to<br />
run Australia.' Well, righto, ok, good luck to you Johnny but we are not going<br />
to make it easy mate.<br />
I'll tell you what is wrong with the Liberal Party, they don't believe in the<br />
country. [ Sound system breaks] Hello someone has knocked us off. There<br />
must be a Tory on the staff. Get their names! It has got to be a Lib.<br />
We may laugh at these characters, but the thing about the Liberal Party is<br />
they have got one fundamentally bad trait and that is they don't believe in<br />
Australia, in what we have become, and the have no faith in Australians.<br />
That is their problem. I have often said and I have used this term that<br />
Manning Clark used to use. He said there are only two kinds of Australians<br />
the enlargers and the punishers and the straighteners the enlargers are the<br />
ones who always believed in something better, having faith in people,<br />
believing they could do something better themselves and having faith we<br />
could do greater things together enlarging Australia, making it bigger and<br />
making it better. That class of Australians and the others were the punishers<br />
and the straighteners. Those who said be happy with your place in life, get<br />
your head down, know your place, get your nose to the grindstone. I mean,<br />
you could see it in Western Australia last week. You know, you want to have<br />
a strike? Give us seven days notice. Want to have a strike? Go and tell<br />
your employer first. If you try to get under the federal awards we will actually<br />
deregister your union. You know, take the offer, get your nose down, don't<br />
complain. This is their view, they would never have faith in the people, in the<br />
institutions we have built, in the country we have become.<br />
It is as if Australia has passed John Howard by. His defence speech of a<br />
week ago could have been given by Harold Holt. No nonsense, no joking, it<br />
could have been given by Harold Holt. It wasn't security in Asia, as we are<br />
saying but security from Asia. Nothing has changed. The same industrial<br />
relations policies, the same general approach. No real pride in the<br />
institutions we have built. The Accord which is a model of co-operation in the<br />
country and the economy, the lowest level of industrial disputes since 1940<br />
working days lost per 1000 compared to 690 working days lost per 1000<br />
when Howard was in office. A model of co-operation, low inflation, high<br />
productivity. </p>
<p>I was out at a workplace today with Michael Lavarch and the people there<br />
were saying ' look, the first enterprise bargain, it took us a while to work out<br />
what to do with it. The second one we actually got something out of it, we<br />
have got higher pay, better hours.' One fellow said ' I'm home more often than<br />
I've ever been these days getting to know my wife again' and ' a real spirit of<br />
co-operation' he said. ' When we get to the third enterprise agreement we will<br />
really know how to do it better', so the Manager said ' yes.' That whole cooperative<br />
spirit is there. No, they want none of that. No faith in people to do<br />
the right thing. No faith in the bigger view. No co-operative model. No view<br />
that we should basically keep these egalitarian concepts of Australia that it is<br />
a good thing that we don't have an underclass here. You saw the American<br />
Labour Secretary Robert Reich, no less a person than the US Secretary of<br />
Labour saying that in the US ' we have had enormous employment growth, but<br />
unfortunately we have had falling real wages for 16 years. We have got an<br />
army of working poor.' And you can see the divisions in that society with the<br />
O. J Simpson trial. You can see the tensions there. You can see it in<br />
Washington during this week. You can see what happens when you don't<br />
have the commitment to one another. You don't have that sense of<br />
compassion. You don't have that sense of consensus. You don't have that<br />
co-operative spirit.<br />
We have got it because we believe in people. We trust them, we've asked<br />
them to be in it with us, to make it a new economy. An efficient place, but a<br />
caring place and we have done it. But they have none of these<br />
understandings and they don't believe in people. John Alston said it another<br />
way recently in Canberra. He said ' there is only two kinds of Australians' he<br />
said ' lovers and the others' and we know what to think of the others don't we?<br />
I said at the Labor Conference in Sydney a week or so ago, we are going to<br />
make this election a referendum on ideas. A referendum on who has the<br />
ideas for Australia. Who are the people that can lead it into the 21 st century,<br />
who can lead Australia into Asia, who can find us an organic place for<br />
ourselves in the region. Who can find us peace at home with our indigenes.<br />
A society which feels together and at one truly one nation one that has a<br />
focus on growth and on jobs and on co-operation and on fairness and on the<br />
environment and on the big things that we believe in our identity, the<br />
republic and the things that have made this a great country. The things that<br />
have made us unique as a culture and unique as a society and as a people.<br />
This is the agenda of Labor. The big agenda. The big ideas. The big ideas<br />
of the nation. The big ideas of our sovereignty being fully expressed by an<br />
Australian head of state. Of taking us into Asia and being part of it. Of<br />
threading together a great free trade agreement around the Pacific rim, with<br />
APEC. Of coming to terms with our indigenes. To say we can't ever make<br />
the leap to these old societies in Asia without settling these things at home<br />
first. I mean, these are the things that follow. It is not just mean spirited<br />
budget making or penny pinching or trying to cut the lowest paid people<br />
down, to cut people under $ 22,000 or $ 25,000 down. What an objective in<br />
l ife to try to do that. </p>
<p>I believe this, that the election will be a referendum on ideas. That it will be<br />
about who has had the faith in the country. Who has adapted and been able<br />
to change it. Who has been able to make it better. Who has been able to<br />
make it fairer and more decent and to be able to say as the Reserve Bank<br />
Governor said today, in all the years he had been in economic policy making,<br />
he had never seen the Australian economy quite as strong as it is now.<br />
John Howard can slip around, he can try to hide his policies, he can try to<br />
keep it under wraps until those last couple of weeks before a poll, but in the<br />
end I don't think the Australian people will reward him. I think the sands are<br />
running against him already and one thing about the Liberal Party, there is no<br />
sentimentality in it. Once your use by date is past you are for it. He is the<br />
third choice after all in this Parliament and he knows that.<br />
So, I can say this, I look forward to this election and so do my colleagues.<br />
We go into it with tremendous fervour, great faith in what we have been able<br />
to do and faith that we can do more with the Australian people. But we know<br />
this, we are democrats and we know that all power comes from the people<br />
and that we need their support to keep on going. It is not just elected<br />
governments, you need that constant support to put the mandates into place.<br />
We need their confidence and we need their encouragement. And we will go<br />
back to them and say three years ago you wanted us to restart the economy,<br />
we have done it. Three years ago we made a commitment to do the hardest<br />
thing, to get unemployment down and employment up, we have got<br />
employment up and we have still got it growing. We have done these things<br />
that we made our commitments to you to do and we want you to assess us<br />
but assess us fairly against the other party that has not done the hard yards,<br />
that has not done the policy thinking, that has not done the work, that hasn't<br />
come together, but after all this that they can't at this point just simply reel off<br />
some dreary policies without basically having faith in the place and believing<br />
in the place because our Party has the change. It was formed in Queensland<br />
100 years ago, as I said in the beginning, 100 years later it is still useful. We<br />
have adapted Australia. We have adapted ourselves and we have adapted<br />
Australia and we have made a model of social democracy, which I think now,<br />
is unique in the western world. We have got an efficient economy grafted<br />
onto a compassionate social wage and, I think, Australians are going to think<br />
very hard before they put that asunder, before they put their mark against it.<br />
I can assure you that we will be going into this election with great confidence.<br />
And we will be putting those big views, the big views about where we see<br />
Australia and where we see it going. And I know that visiting a school today,<br />
all those young people joining the rolls, they have got no doubt about which<br />
way the direction in this country, which way that direction should be. It<br />
should be for the things we value the republic, the environment, faith in<br />
ourselves, opportunity, the right to a job these are the things which I think<br />
they hold dear. They are not about to take a trip down the time tunnel to the<br />
Liberal Party. </p>
<p>Perhaps I can conclude on this point by saying how much I have appreciated<br />
the Party in Queensland, bringing us together the Cabinet today here in<br />
Brisbane. For the Lord Mayor for having us at the Town Hall which is a<br />
singular pleasure. But to be here in the presence of Wayne Goss and his<br />
Cabinet as the Labor family together. Because the thing about the Labor<br />
Party is it is united. We are together. There is no fracture in our views, there<br />
is no great divide in the Labor Party on social policy or foreign policy or<br />
economic policy. There are changes at the edges, there are shades of<br />
opinion, but there is no great divide. We have never been as united as this<br />
and as well as that we have got the industrial movement with us. We are a<br />
united force. I don't think, as I said earlier, the Labor Party has ever been<br />
stronger. But this is the State in which it was formed, in Queensland, and to<br />
be here with 1200 of you with such bonhomie and buoyancy, with our State<br />
Cabinet colleagues and with Wayne, it gives me a lot of pride and a lot of<br />
pleasure. We will need your strength to carry it through. But don't believe for<br />
a moment that we can't win well and win here in Queensland. We can. And<br />
if we have faith in Queenslanders they will return the faith to us. The one<br />
thing I pledge is to work for their support. To work with our State colleagues<br />
for their support. To work as a united party and when we have that mandate<br />
to work hard to put it into place and the great catalogue of things we have<br />
been able to achieve in these three years, we will be able to do again in the<br />
next three as we come down to the end of the century, as we make that leap<br />
into the 21st century and put the indelible stamp of Labor proudly across the<br />
face of Australia.<br />
Thank you very much indeed.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
