<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16972</transcript-id>
    <title>National Security College    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australia's first National Security College will be established, providing world class education and training in national security policy issues.</p>
<p>The College will be a joint venture between the Australian Government and the Australian National University.</p>
<p>The College will provide executive development programs for senior national security officials and provide access to ANU teaching and research programs, with the aim of better preparing national security personnel for the increasingly complex challenges they face.</p>
<p>The creation of the National Security College follows the success of a pilot executive development course, overseen this year by the National Security Adviser, Mr Duncan Lewis.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister also announced the appointment of Mr Michael L'Estrange AO as the founding Executive Director of the National Security College.</p>
<p>Mr L'Estrange has served governments of both sides of the political divide for many years with distinction.</p>
<p>His most recent appointments include Secretary of the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, High Commissioner to London and Cabinet Secretary. Mr L'Estrange is a Rhodes scholar and has a distinguished academic record. He has over many years made a major contribution to public policy development, particularly in international policy and national security policy. The ANU has determined that Mr L'Estrange's position as Executive Director of the College will see him appointed as a professor of the University.</p>
<p>Mr L'Estrange's wide public service experience, linked with professorial standing, will place him and the University in a very good position to establish the College and deliver the high level of executive development essential for the national security community.</p>
<p>Mr L'Estrange's first tasks will include developing the detailed business model for the College, and building on the early course development work of the pilot executive development program conducted this year.</p>
<p>The College will have a board consisting of membership drawn equally from among senior government officials and University nominees.</p>
<p>The first chairman of the board will be the National Security Adviser, Duncan Lewis.</p>
<p>The College will be a critical element in preparing Australia's future national security leadership, and safeguarding our national security.</p>
<p>A safe and secure Australia is the Government's first priority, and the National Security College will play a key role in ensuring this.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
