<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7141</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF COMMENTS, PARLIAMENT HOUSE FRIDAY 27 MARCH 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007141.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF COMMENTS, PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
FRIDAY 27 MARCH 1987<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: John Howard says you'd be the biggest phoney<br />
ever if you call an early election.<br />
PM: John Howard talking about people being phonies. Honest<br />
John! Really, what we're seeing is the disintegration not<br />
only of the Liberal Party, but the disintegration of the<br />
person of John Howard. He is totally lacking in any<br />
principle. This exercise on the legislation, the equal<br />
opportunity legislation, would have to go down as the<br />
greatest piece of hypocrisy and deception. Everyone knows,<br />
every single person in this Parliament House knows that the<br />
reason John Howard changed the position of the Opposition<br />
from support for the legislation to opposition was to kowtow<br />
to the National Party. This is the man who just days before<br />
was saying what is fundamentally important to me is the<br />
integrity, the principle of the Liberal Party, that we are<br />
not dictated to by anyone else. And what has he done? He's<br />
allowed his position of principle on the legislation to be<br />
changed, to be dictated to by his concerns about the<br />
reaction of the National Party. Any comments by Mr Howard<br />
about me are simply an attempt to divert attention from the<br />
fact that we've witnessed in this last day possibly the<br />
greatest act of political hypocrisy and dishonesty by any<br />
political leader in the history of this country.<br />
ends do </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
