<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5586</transcript-id>
    <title>ANNUAL DINNER OF THE AUSTRALIAN LIBERAL STUDENT&#039;S FEDERATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005586.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
__ EMBARGO: 9.30PM<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY II<br />
i . PRIME-ME INISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAYMAY 15 981...<br />
MELBOURNE<br />
ANNUAL DINNER OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN LIBERAL STUDENTS' FEDERATION<br />
For more than a century, the Socialists have thought that<br />
history is on their side. Their view has been that nothing<br />
-" can-, top -ocialism-from-coming-in the end. . This9doctrine.--'<br />
is one of historical inevitability, a comforting doctrine<br />
to some kinds of people, and one that has assumed several<br />
fonrms.<br />
In Australia, the doctrine has, in the mainb assumed a<br />
comparatively non-ideological form, namely, that each<br />
Sodralistic policy put in place by a Labor government will<br />
-remain in place even after the electors have thrown Labor<br />
out of office at the next election. There has been a belief<br />
that-succeeding Liberal governments will not remove, but<br />
live with established Socialistic policies. So no matter how<br />
infrequently Labor holds office, Socialism is inevitable<br />
in the end by a silw _ proce-sof accretion.<br />
This version of historical inevitability portrays the<br />
advance of Socialism not as an irrestible swelling tide,<br />
but a sort-of slTow shuffle. There is little. idealism in.<br />
it, but it has at least been something for the Socialists<br />
in this country to cling to,<br />
From the time the Liberal Government came to office after<br />
the 1975 election, we-made it plain that we did -not regard<br />
existing Socialistic tyPe policies as sacrosanct. We expressed<br />
our clear determination-to-re-establish a more Liberal<br />
and more limited and less arrogant role for government in<br />
Australia. We have done this because we believe that if<br />
Australia is to meet the cfalteges-of--th-M ighties-and<br />
beyond, we cannot afford to sit back and accept unsatisfactory<br />
and inefficient arrangements which cause more problems than<br />
they solve, and whose costs outweigh-the-benefits.<br />
Never has our direction been made plainer than in our recent<br />
decisions arising out of the Review of Commonwealth Functions<br />
and in relation to hospital and medical arrangements in<br />
this country, and in the recent Premiers' Conference. There<br />
are major benefits which will flow to all Australians from<br />
a more realistic view of whart-government-can do. </p>
<p>2<br />
In announcing the Governiment's decisions arisin 4from the<br />
Review of Commonwealth Functions I' said that theyp were a<br />
Smajor contribution to.-the historic turnaround -tVA the_-,<br />
political oppo e~ uht:.<br />
this turnaround was impossible. This is why so many Of<br />
them, were -outraged. , One-of -thenm in -fact rose APi 3c<br />
the liaPaf nt-,-wi I was only halfway thr A -the-*<br />
-onerch. and confi aed-,. limself unable to sit t1l-j'e an<br />
it also-helpi expla" ui: ihy 6iirpool-itical opponeiiwereso<br />
confused in their immediate response. The Leader:, f the<br />
Oppsiton taredby-accusing us of dsatigte<br />
puicSeotor, -yet 1later-on-iw-tte same-spee. h1cu~ ks a,, e<br />
Government: of spending-' too much. The leaders of -tthe-<br />
-* Labor Party cannot make, up their minds whether hey.-<br />
should denounce our approach arid ur__ potiaiesa a--<br />
dismantling of government# or. whether they should-try<br />
to gain popular support for themselves by accus-i-ng us of<br />
not having gone. far enough.<br />
-Our turnaround is a move away from big government; away<br />
government ' that Labor gave this country between 11972-75., when<br />
the number of Commonwealth employees rose by 52,000<br />
( June 1.972 June 1975). We have brought itkA_~~ yjOO. QL. 0<br />
and the RCr will bring it down a further 16,000 or 17,000.<br />
under L~ abor the Governmen't's claims on the nationl's<br />
earnings rose from under 24% of GDP in 1972-73 to more than<br />
In 1975-76. We have cut this c17he~ Ta<br />
and we have further to go.<br />
We -don't--nt bi-g--govemment,--nor do the Austral-ian people.<br />
Only Labor wants it. And let me stress that big goverment<br />
is not caring government. It makes unemployment inevitable<br />
by undermkning pxL~ ateernterprisg, and it fosters inflation<br />
-and--cons equen t-ly sociiA-divisiveness, with so~ arj'g_ taxes......<br />
and large deficits.<br />
Limited governulefftWasafae-greater capacity to improve<br />
* care for those who need assist * ance. B~ y strengthening the<br />
eonomy, limited govetb1ment provides a foundation for.-<br />
generous ss&amp; eocu-ar i-ty_&amp; rranqaements. Those in lieed<br />
benefit-from more ef ficient government.. Over tbg-period<br />
of this Government, age pensions have reached higher levels<br />
in relation to average weekly earnings than at any time<br />
* in the last 25 years. And you will' 1 be aware-TTYat p edi-ttns**--<br />
have been made in income security payments as a result of<br />
the RCF~.<br />
A Liberal government does care about people, and the Liberal<br />
approach is based on the view that society has immense resources<br />
Sfor achiieving what people want-without the need for<br />
counterproductive intrusion by governments. These resources<br />
are the talents, the skills and the knowledge which people<br />
possess. Big government cramps these resources. </p>
<p>Centralieationan bk-A; governent neuze held ouk; 1in1n<br />
: prospects for the.-Cause of freedom' and civilii iion, for<br />
ihitittiVd-and4 crdaeivity; -df" for the promotionmof tose--.<br />
values which lead to the advancement of mankind. The<br />
advance~ ment 0f. * mankifiQ&amp; c omes -! w-amet Ty Mf Wevo~ itr..<br />
-effot-f individal'iwithin. the-framework of-ivility<br />
~ a P--_ thw.-rkXIe~ of:: 1aW. which governments -helpp, i W i.~<br />
~. is hman beings whor make-history, and in this process,. historY does w-*<br />
mtaakkee nsoid eas!. s uznIp twioafriist twoW iscahy sutoig gyeosutn gth avte ort) hee ._ fukptgure ei clqi4e&amp; sr,.<br />
: 7ouits'Ide himan conitol.' Sicdh-&amp; 9bumptions. would i unqworthy......<br />
of your own capacities and of the responBi-bili'ties which<br />
-youiwereto the , gensr&amp; tlions which WUTTfollowY~ oiu ,*<br />
It is often-said. that'-the West has faced a crisis in recent<br />
decades. I doubt that crisis propertiens.-were ever-reached..<br />
but -there certainly have been considerable uncertaintie~ i<br />
of both will and belief.' From the late fifties, through<br />
to the meid seventies, the West fail~ adto perceive the need<br />
for new policies, and by the time it did wake up..<br />
unemployment and inflation were both high and becoming<br />
entrenched. In those years, the distinction between caring<br />
government and big government was n5tTaT cle-atTf1 Jy asit<br />
should have been. The distinction between a protective<br />
-role for government and the omnipresence of government was<br />
Th6t-as clear as it should have been 42eople--thught--that-~-<br />
governments -were entitled to spend almost without. limit,<br />
and it was falsely imnagin~ ed that government money would<br />
__ avle human problems.<br />
The tradition of freedom -which says that the way to solve<br />
these problems, Is to encourage people to use their sk~ ills,<br />
tARnts and imaginations was subordinated to a reliance<br />
on government. Hardly anyone now fails to recognise that<br />
government had õ kdwii'too much. " Our policies reassert that<br />
fr-eedom not paternalism and bureaucracy is the path<br />
to the way of life that most people want.<br />
Let me give a simple, but compelling, example of how<br />
freedom helps to solve social problems.. u-r--polici-ea-fise---<br />
that if government creates the right conditions for people<br />
to use their know16edqde, and express their own wants in themarketplace,<br />
the inevitable result is the-opening-U-pOf--<br />
n~ ew opportunities for others, including job opportunities,<br />
As a result, almost a quarter of a million additional jobs<br />
camne into existence in the two years to last December in the__<br />
private sector and the rate of unemployment is n~ wif ailing.<br />
In April it was the lowest rate for four-years. This<br />
achievement far exceeds what could have been achieved<br />
with government make -work-s cheme s which-a-malways7-tl e<br />
first resort of the Socialists and which could only have<br />
been paid for by higher taxes anyway. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
T heidJwayof Ifreedom-4; l-.&amp;, t6 I k ni-1<br />
.1 -j6b! 3s&gt; Taid lbwer-tasio.-. r~ ea~: the f<br />
definition, the retreat of oppression arnd injustice. BY<br />
'---axe. thei sourcesa of-ne-ppreasin-f. nqwj n u_; fte. 4d~ oi.<br />
1ewopportunit~ es_. fox.-asubtle diecrimination * rh.<br />
The-:. retreat of'' monolUit1cSocialism-in;, pqlan d-: ZWya--the__<br />
ff ragi lity of' a systeyxwwh ich--uppreses thUf V antrfe<br />
-~ values of the. people Freedom may pot end. prejudice and<br />
_ Ihtoerance -in, prtid'atitudes but-, it--depries-the-;..<br />
,.-. sz-pte JvdIL-e4 i -th-e lin tdi-fart-the-dami e rin 9 of= gU cant--<br />
opportunities to grow strong.-<br />
In implementing policies which express our faith in freedom,<br />
* we -believe we ak6-bdiiijtrue-to the traditioniswil-hwe av<br />
built in the West, the most humane -and creative societies that<br />
the world has ever knowqn. The thread running through all<br />
ou k pjidfiiie9 -is -that~ i-dividalss houl&amp; lie able O make7-<br />
decisions for themselves. This is why this government is<br />
so fd is-i~ ely coiritted. to the protection of theF-t-axpayers,-<br />
for freedom requir-e.-that individuals have their -ownl<br />
spending power, and that governments must justify the cl~ ims<br />
they make on taxpayers..<br />
The Revijew of Government Functions has a particular<br />
-relevance in this connection, for the decisions arising<br />
from that review amount to.. the most comprehen sive practical<br />
expression of this kind-of c6mmitment to freedam-ñ ch<br />
has emerged from any m~ odern Australian government.<br />
-There were -three -categjories of decisions. The~ fikstqqpcerned<br />
with moving over to private enterprise functions which itwill<br />
handle better * than governments, the second with passing<br />
back to the States functions which they can handle more<br />
appropriately, and thus -avoiding waste and dupliaTtif,-.<br />
and the third with rationalising some of the commonwealth's<br />
own activities.<br />
I mention here particularly the abolition of the Prices<br />
Justifi . cation Tr ibuinal ffie'f reeing up of the airlines&gt;<br />
and the establishment of TAA as a public company; the offering<br />
zale of a * number-of-gorvernment enterprises to private_...<br />
enteprie; the reductions in industry assistane h<br />
abolition of dual control over public hospitals, anid the<br />
* new health arrangements based on voluntary private-ihl-uanceTthe<br />
introduction of a loans scheme for tertiary stu-dents<br />
from the beginning of 1982; the maJor reductions in the<br />
size of theCeemonweal-th bti-r aucracy; and a joint<br />
Parliamentary standing committee to review the performance,<br />
role, f unctions and continued need for all statuatory bodies. </p>
<p>-4<br />
The, way, of. -f reedomvleds.-tW, I-gher ecnmcgowt. Mx.<br />
*-rjobandlower. taikes...' And, bicause the freedom-1' I -am: ta'lking.,<br />
defipition the retreat of oppression and injustice. BY<br />
zC -fldbtrast j excezssi-vd zp e; x* nism and interferivg.: regulatton.<br />
ave-th-e sourcea' of ' n-e o~ ainLaw in~ natice'-. nd of.-<br />
~ new ,. opportumriewzt f or-subtle irjnatin.' c<br />
_ r. ttdre at of . onli-thi-. Sbeialism in . Polard. hos 0.9W<br />
fragility of a -yatem-whlct -suppr'essres1th-freeffom-and thi,<br />
values of the -people-.-Freedom. may not end-prejudice, and<br />
**--intole ran ce ' in ' pfiVataF-tttude s but ' it -deprives the<br />
preijudiced, the<br />
opportunities to grow strong.<br />
In implementing policies which! expresra-lfaithin-reedon..-.<br />
we believe we are being true to the traditions which we have<br />
built in the West.. the most humane and creative societies that<br />
the world has ever known. The thread running through all<br />
our-Volicl-edis that' indtvtdilals AVrofld-be M! Ls . omAke<br />
decisions for themselves. This is why this government is<br />
so decisively committed to the protection of the taxpayers,<br />
for freedom requires that individoaJs&amp; hava-tUOi-r own-.<br />
spending power, and that'governments must justify the claims<br />
they make on taxpayers.<br />
The Review of Government Functions has a priua<br />
relevance in this connection, for-the decisions arising<br />
from that. reviOew amount to the most cornprehen. 51vo practical<br />
expression of this hind of-eu itmert-ta freedom-which<br />
has emerged from any modern Australian government.<br />
There were three categories.-of decisions. Tbha... ik-st concerned<br />
with moving over to private enterprise functions which it<br />
will handle better than governents, the second with passing<br />
back to the States functions which they can handle more<br />
-appropri ately, iand thus-avoidi ng ' wast-e and iTuirI1-iation,<br />
and the third with rationalising some of the Commonwealth's<br />
own activities.<br />
I mention here -particularly the abolition of the Prices<br />
Justification Tribunai ' the freeing up of the airline6s<br />
and the egtablishment, of TMA as a public company; the offeri-ng<br />
for sale of a nuniber of goverament enterprises to private<br />
enterprise; the reductions in industry assistance; the<br />
abolition of dual control over public hospitals, and the<br />
ffiw-hea'flhrarange ments based on voluntary private insurance;<br />
the introduction of a loans scheme for tertiary students<br />
from the beginning of 1982; the major red uctions in the<br />
-4ñ 4e of-4e-ommonwe lth bureaucracy; and a joint<br />
Parliamentary standing commi~ ttee to review the performance,<br />
role, functions and continued need for all statuatory bodies.<br />
.1 </p>
<p>s-determnb* nv O -t4lOW<br />
( iot" PhVas y eli eve. ' this is ; th &amp; Ay rgal<br />
and iOUlt4e4.<br />
want it to be.. our turnabout from high taxes anid iniflation,.<br />
-44-bgh unempldymenprqvides;<br />
' morefrbmi'ur ecricdftI dWtY And that establikhesthe,,<br />
LA~ñ coti~ ti~ ~ i ie' gbterai~ os C o&gt; n e<br />
to enjoy and look forward to.<br />
L -Otilk. turnabbuhd also -eg1h'=. hade<br />
means givingade rngh~ ta-<br />
Au~ tibAlian federal -ytem. One of our conoerns4ft to-* avoid'-<br />
thew atle ahd duplicilTfon regsltiig. from over-z6TrlatOh....<br />
byillh theF S dV4t&amp;&amp;' i diiibility' for fufotioo-Wh1 hareprei<br />
n il tefg Q<br />
What point is there in the Commonweal~ th funding a curripuluhl<br />
develo~ pmenit centre of -its own wheny thi-s merely ov~ r-laps-with<br />
work-being! done by the States? Or what point is there in<br />
the Commonwealth bureaucracy being involved with the running<br />
of piilie hospi'tals w in th-e States are both cboistitutionally<br />
responsible and very well able indeed to run public hospitats?<br />
There have been some differences of view about -the precise<br />
financial contribution which the Commonwealth BhOUld ' make to<br />
hospitals. But I have no doubt that a year or two down<br />
_ the track when these differences will seem like ancient___<br />
history, the States will value their independent capacity V<br />
to them.<br />
Over recent decades, and especially from 1972-15', the general<br />
*~ qdwtrofgove rnment -It-Au stralia was made worsee. by-an<br />
increasing centralism in Canberra. ideal lyfeedfra im.<br />
should operate to limit government. But in terms of power,<br />
the Commonwealth Government was the beneficiary of the<br />
centaliatin ad te-r of government in Australia. 4-<br />
Eve * n Sir Robert Menzie~ s, looking back f rom his r-etireme-nt,<br />
made the observation that while it was easy in theory to<br />
-favour limited power for the om nwata larger amount<br />
of ' pbwer Iinade3i. tC ~ ii<br />
of course, in a situation in which selfish'and divisive<br />
groups are extremely powerful, a weak Commonwelth Government<br />
would be a poor protector of individual rights and of the<br />
public interest. So what the Commonwealth needs is that<br />
measure of power which will enable it to discharge its<br />
own proper respan-sibil-it-ie----) ithtr-more nor less and<br />
this Governmenit will seek to retain no power in., excess of<br />
that.<br />
Labor has sometimes argued that government is relatively, small<br />
* and restrained in Australia, by comparison with ' other countries.<br />
International comparisons are always difficult because of<br />
inins titutt~ iwT and -I-ways of compiling statistics.<br />
Nor is there any obvious magic about the average or typical<br />
size of the public sector in other industrial countries. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
ITw ectbk iab ' ibV filsrbnrevraM % frelation toGP--than: tha VfWM-.<br />
' United States* the united kingan Germay,. th etrl -ra~ t<br />
the lsize of their iiblic sectors. T: " e<br />
And it<br />
ispartiularly interesting that of . the majorOC<br />
GD 1T'hose e0o-ni'c conditions-would yo -prefer'<br />
. Au6stralia to* hA&amp; thote-of bg. qfger sedi---United'<br />
IFingdom and Uited'ttates 6rci those of mierpe<br />
Japan? TW&amp; fo" i ea~ on re~ gniionin the Weat of the<br />
need for a turnaround is plain to see. Not only does<br />
limited government fnean more effective and -less intrusive.<br />
governmfent, it also means higher economicrowth,_ higher<br />
real incomes, more job lower taxes, more nfluenceto<br />
ordinary* Jieople'a's usersasid consumers, anrd a greater,<br />
adaptability in our society to change.<br />
There are also very real advantages in freeing resources<br />
and opening opportunities for current priorities. We are<br />
no longer so locked into programes an4-zztiviti-C.-Wihich<br />
once had an importance they no longer have. We can<br />
devote -resources much more-adequateoly'to areas we believe<br />
are of major current importance.<br />
Let me mention energy research as an example. A re-location<br />
existing resources. -in the Australian Atomic Energy<br />
Comi~ jion -Research Establishment and in the -C* SIRQ will<br />
e&amp; na~ le the Government-to establish. a new institute of<br />
energy-and earth resources in the CSIRO.<br />
The establishment of this institute is a recognition<br />
of the higli. p~ ri6-ty the Government believes must be given<br />
to endxgy research.-These -decisions, will consolidate<br />
Australia's pres~ ent nuclear regearch establishment into<br />
a f irst class nuclear science and technology research<br />
organfisation and establ-ish a first class non-nuclear<br />
research Organisation.<br />
The rezources transferred to CSIRO will enable expansion<br />
of research in such areas as fossil fuels, mi1nng of energy<br />
re-sources,. alternative f uels and renewable energy andenergy.<br />
-conserv-ation.<br />
Because limited government compels greater awareness of<br />
priorities, it is more effective goverrnment and government<br />
better geared to enable Australia to take up the challengeB<br />
and opportunities before us. We pioneered more limited_<br />
government through the second half of the 1.970s. It has<br />
been a hard path calling for a degree of determination,<br />
and for a sustained resistance to demands for government<br />
spending but other countries are now trying to follow us.<br />
~ Ji C-. I. -I<br />
A<br />
' 1<br />
I<br />
-J ~ Ji<br />
j </p>
<p>* LUberalism stnsas a srnti-ig<br />
-message--to th, wor ms, -eu~ ta4~ Itfe<br />
3z~ e ef~ rt~ s... r~&amp; t~ eiPL of 4ndividua1 humani&amp; na<br />
three Olu~ irce f rogresal a message -whichzifakes.. T*~<br />
-~ ftee'~ oi pre -einenta message which insists % lat<br />
-' People shod Eb. treateda ither 7t; B:~-<br />
patient-An*' the hanft of -goveirnment, but-~ ds amic...<br />
" responsible and.-adult.<br />
This* is--the esserif'ral messagre 6! the fre6 sooleties o the.<br />
wo idn our time.:., J'Modern Australian Liberalism stands.<br />
at the f oref ront as W: a p . ra6caj example of th~ zbenefits.-<br />
of the Liberal way of life. ours is the message of optimism.<br />
It is the only message worth entertaining.-<br />
, M i Stergtfisae. bcauei starts with human<br />
beings as they are, withi their capabilitfies wl atheir<br />
aspirations,--and because it recognises that the<br />
only way to achie~ ve huma~ n aspirations is through the free<br />
operation of hutantalents and abilittes.<br />
-00__<br />
IA </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
