<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17837</transcript-id>
    <title>Tribute to Claude Choules - Last known First World War Veteran</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/05/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Minister for Veterans' Affairs, Warren Snowdon today expressed their sorrow at the passing of Claude Choules, the last known veteran to have served in the First World War.</p>
<p>Mr Choules was also the last known Royal Navy veteran of the First World War.</p>
<p>Mr Choules passed away today at his residence in Perth, Western Australia.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said his passing marks the end of a significant chapter in world history.</p>
<p>Mr Choules was the last known link to those who served in the Great War.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said Mr Choules and his generation made a sacrifice for our freedom and liberty that we will never forget.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister also said we must now, more than ever, ensure that the contribution of those who fought in the First World War is never forgotten.</p>
<p>On behalf of all Australians, the Prime Minister and Minister Snowdon send their condolences to Mr Choules' family.</p>
<p>Minister Snowdon said with Mr Choules' passing, we strengthen our commitment to honour the service and sacrifice of all who served in the world wars.</p>
<p>Mr Choules made an outstanding contribution to Australia's and our Allies' wartime efforts.</p>
<p>Mr Choules was the last man known to have served in both world wars, serving the United Kingdom in the First World War and Australia in the Second World War.</p>
<p>His service history spanned more than 40 years, demonstrating his unwavering dedication and commitment to defending the United Kingdom and Australia.</p>
<p>Note: The family of Mr Choules have requested privacy at this time. Mr Choules' biography and images are available at <a href="http://www.dva.gov.au/media">www.dva.gov.au/media</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
