<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8322</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008322.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 23 AUGUST 1991<br />
The dramatic collapse of the conservative coup in the Soviet<br />
Union has brought into sharp focus the tragic situation in<br />
Yugoslavia. I am appalled by the violence, destruction and<br />
loss of life which is occurring there. The events in the<br />
Soviet Union must surely be a salutary lesson for those who<br />
are seeking to impose their will on others and to those-who<br />
seek to use violence to resolve political problems. The<br />
times have changed. People's aspirations to freedom and<br />
democracy cannot be thwarted by force, and those aspirations<br />
will be strongly supported by the international community.<br />
The peoples of Croatia and Slovenia have freely and<br />
democratically expressed their desire for independence.<br />
Their aspirations must be satisfied in a just, peaceful and<br />
democratic manner. For our part, Australia will be among<br />
the first countries to recognise Croatia and Slovenia when<br />
they satisfy the attributes of statehood.<br />
The latest peace plan, which was agreed earlier this week by<br />
the Yugoslav Federal Presidency and the leaders of the six<br />
republics, appears to be yet another expression of good<br />
intent which is not being backed up by the necessary action.<br />
I urge all the parties involved to summon the necessary<br />
political will to implement a cease-fire and bring an<br />
immediate halt to the bloodshed.<br />
We fully support the Europeans in their efforts to mediate<br />
in this crisis, and hope that they will not be discouraged<br />
by recent set-backs. We believe the European Community has<br />
the best chance of negotiating a settlement.<br />
On my own behalf and that of the Government, I extend my<br />
deepest sympathy to those who are suffering as a result of<br />
the violence in Yugoslavia. I appreciate and respect the<br />
restraint and understanding being demonstrated by the<br />
communities in Australia which are affected by this tragic<br />
situation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
