<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>339</transcript-id>
    <title>PUBLIC MEETING AT BURNIE ON 4TH JULY 1961 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000339_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
61/ 040<br />
PUBLIC MEETING AT BURNIE<br />
on 4th July, 1Q61<br />
Speech by the Prime iinister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
Mr. Warden, parliamentary colleagues and ladies and gentlemen:<br />
I won't need to tell you that the hero of that story<br />
that the garden told you was my old friend Sam Bird, whom I missed<br />
very much indeed when I called at the " seat of the great" this<br />
afternoon to see the 1arden himself. I said " Tell me, was Sam<br />
warden of Burnie for 20 years, or was it 25?" They took me and<br />
showed me a photograph which seemed to show that he was warden<br />
only for 9 years. I don't believe it, I don't believe it. And<br />
Mr. Bruce, as he then was, wouldn't have believed it either,<br />
because he and Sam had this little interlude that you heard about.<br />
Now I am in a sort of dubious position tonight: I'm<br />
not here on an election campaign; I rather like to get around the<br />
4 country from time to time Vwhen there is not an election on. They<br />
are having one in Victoria but it's not mine it's a State<br />
election. No doubt, if all goes well, somewhere towards the<br />
Fcderal election I will be around, as usual, in Burnie,<br />
Sappreciating the beautiful draughts that flow up the streets from<br />
i the sea ( Laughter) and having a good reception, or a bad one, as<br />
the case may be. But on this occasion I thought it might be<br />
useful not to make a contentious speech to you, but to say<br />
something to you about what is going on overseas, and here; and I<br />
know that what goes on here has a very particular interest for all<br />
of us. In the last 12 years I have had a good deal to do,<br />
rightly or wrongly, with Australian foreign policy; and a good<br />
deal to do, rightly or wrongly, with some of the leaders of the<br />
great nations in Che world. They are nations with whom we do have<br />
Ssome influence that's the remarkable thing to me. . e are a<br />
small country, 10 or 11 million people, hew could we have any<br />
influence with great countries with 180, or 200, or 400 millions?<br />
But the fact is that we do.<br />
' 9io have some influence because we go to some pains to<br />
undurstand what the problems of the world are, and are willing, on<br />
suitable occasions, to tell our friends what our opinions are, and<br />
what our suggestions are. It would be very easy for us to nurse<br />
ourselves, comfortably, into a belief that the only problems we<br />
have are those that we see at our front door. We have, I venture<br />
to say, Sir, very nuch greater problems in the world at large.<br />
Because the first problem for Australia is to remain a free, safe<br />
country, able to work out its own future.<br />
( To an inturjector: I know that you are delighted to<br />
think that there aru s. me unemployed there have been mighty few<br />
during my torn of office, righty few during my term of office. Of<br />
all the periods of Australian history that you can select the<br />
period of my own Government has eon the highest record of<br />
employment. ( Applause) I know there are sono people who,<br />
professionally want to whip up the agony and make things worse,<br />
instead of better. But I happen to be talking to you about<br />
something that is Luch mnro important than you, my friend, or than<br />
me, and that is the peace of the world, the peace of the world.)<br />
I was saying something about a matter that ay<br />
interjector ought to understand, the peace of the world and how<br />
it affects Australia. Australia has fjund itself engaged in<br />
two wars in our lifotirco. It is troeendously important that we, </p>
<p>as an intelligent and self-respecting people, should do our best<br />
to contribute to the maintaining of the peace and security of the<br />
free world.<br />
( Interjections) Now, ladies and gentlemen I'm accustomed to this kind<br />
of thing but I just want to point out to you that the world,<br />
today, is eJez'y bit as uneasy as it has been at any time in the<br />
last 10 years. Je talk about the cold war as if it . rere something<br />
frozen. The cold jar goes on because the Communist powers want it<br />
to go on; the cold war goes on because by threat and pressure,<br />
by blackmail, by violence where necessary, they keep the free<br />
nations of the world all agog, all anxious, all more or loss<br />
standing to arms. This is the tragedy of the decade. And before<br />
this year is out we will have discovered whether all this is<br />
bluff, whether bluffs have to be called. Bacause before this<br />
calendar year is out we will know whether Khrushchev's talk about<br />
Berlin is merely talk; or whether he means war about Berlin, war<br />
about East Germany. These are tremendously important matters for<br />
us to be thinking about.<br />
. c have in south-cast Asia, practically next doer to us,<br />
problems now bubbling up in the country called Laos, and liable to<br />
bubble up in other countries on its perimeter. They greatly<br />
concern us. Because if the Communist nations of the : orld can<br />
take over an Asian country whose only ambition it is to live<br />
quietly within its own boundaries, if they can take over a<br />
country like Laos where do they stop? They have already taken<br />
North Viot-Nam which is part of ihat we used to call, many years<br />
ago, French Indo-China. South Viet-Nam is exposed to daily acts<br />
of revolution and violence within her own boundaries. Thailand,<br />
which we used to call Siam, is there with a long land frontier<br />
with Laos. And if Laos goes, Thailand will find<br />
perhaps, more difficult to stand. If South Viet-Nam is exposed to<br />
attack then we have a problem which concerns every nation which is<br />
involved in the South East Asian Treaty, what we call SEATO Great<br />
Britain, France, the United States of America, Australia, Now<br />
Zealand, Pakistan, Thailand, the Philippines. Here you have a<br />
group of countries who, between thomsalvos, have entered into<br />
Treaty obligations which, or the performance of which, alone<br />
stands between us and aggressive Communism in Asia.<br />
When people want me to put an order of importance on to<br />
things I am quite prepared to say that the most important thing in<br />
our national life is that we should not pass into the Communist<br />
orbit in this world. That is the imperative thing for which<br />
Australia rust stand, and for which every honest political party<br />
in Australia must stand. At this very moment there is a<br />
Conference at Geneva about Lior, with much manoeuvring going on.<br />
I haven't the slightest doubt myself that the Soviet Union are<br />
playing for time because they believe the more tie that is<br />
occupied in discussion at Geneva, the more opportunities will<br />
their Communist supporters have to put themselves into a position<br />
to take over the entire country.<br />
. e cannot be uninterested in these matters. The very<br />
reason why we exist in SEATO, the very reason why we hope under all<br />
circumstances to keep American interest in South-east Asia, which<br />
I am glad to say is great and powerful, the very reason for it is<br />
that if the forward surge of Communism in South-East Asia continues<br />
uninhibited, then before we are very much older we can look out<br />
across our northern seas and contemplate a Communist world as our<br />
nearest neighbour. Now, Sir, having said just so little, or so much as that,<br />
about the international position which is, of course, very grave,<br />
which will require cool heads and firm minds, firm judgments, and </p>
<p>.3.<br />
firm actions, I want to turn to the position of our own country<br />
because it happens that after a period of 10 years which nobody<br />
will deny has been a period of the greatest prosperity this<br />
country has over enjoyed ( Applause) ( Interjections)<br />
No responsible person I'll amend my statement no<br />
responsible person could denly that in the last 10 years we have<br />
had the most remarkable period of growth in the history of this<br />
country. I am surprised that anybody should deny it in Burnie<br />
which itself is a--magnificent example of the growth that has gone<br />
on during the last 10 years.<br />
Right through this period we have attracted enormous<br />
capital investments into Australia, we have seen the most<br />
phenomenal industrial growth, we have seen the development of<br />
national resources on the grand scale, we have been increasing<br />
our population by natural increase and by immigration at a rate<br />
even higher than that in Japan; and, in the result we have a<br />
country so strong, so respected so worthy of credit in the<br />
world, so full of busily engages people that we, today, represent<br />
in the other countries of the world, the most attractive field of<br />
investment that they know.<br />
Now this is worth considering. I know there are people<br />
who just take a superficial view, you know what I noan, about<br />
these things. ( Interjections) But I wonder, I wonder if my<br />
friend will know what I mean if I say that there is one rather<br />
good way of testing the prospects of the development of a young<br />
nation like ours. First of all l'e--us ackuiowvdgo I hopo wo<br />
all will that 10 million people, 1 O( million people, eanst, out<br />
of their own savings produce all the capital that is required to<br />
develop a continent the size of the United States of America.<br />
That is pretty obvious isn't it? Therefore if we are going to<br />
develop our resources, if we are going to have great water supply<br />
schemes, great power schemes, and great mineral developments, then<br />
we must be able to look to the rest of the world for some of the<br />
capital at least, that is required for these purposes. If the<br />
people In the rest of the world are not prepared to trust us with<br />
their money, then we are going to be handicapped, we are going to<br />
be tied down to a lower rate of progress. I want to say this to<br />
you that if, over these last 10 years, the investors of the world,<br />
the citizens of other countries, had not been willing to invest<br />
money in Australia we couldn't have had the immigration programme<br />
that we have had, we couldn't have had the same increase in the<br />
standard of living, and we couldn't have had the same high level<br />
of employment. Now that is perfectly plain English. And I will<br />
demonstrate it to you.<br />
About 10 years ago we had a look at the accounts of<br />
money coming into Australia to be invested, not in Government, but<br />
in ordinary business activity In Australia, and it amounted to<br />
something a little under œ lO00m. That was a lot, a great sun of<br />
money to have coming in. Last year it was over œ 300m. And in<br />
the current financial year, in spite of the fact that iv-, who<br />
have worked so hard to develop prosperity in Australia, are<br />
supposed now to be busy destroying it, the amount coming into<br />
Australia from oversoas is higher than it was in the previous<br />
' ycar, It has reached an all-time record. ( Interjections)<br />
( Well if I may put it not in roubles, madam but in<br />
Australian ( Applause) well over œ 300m. Australian ana in anybody's<br />
language that seems to me to be quite a bit of money)<br />
What happens with it? It develops industry. You go<br />
around Australia and look at some of the great industries which<br />
give employment to t'liusands and thousands of A,' ustralians and you<br />
will be surprised how frequently that its an industry7 the<br />
financial prevision for which has come fron. outside L~ stralia. </p>
<p>Does anybody complain about that? Is anybody prepared to say to<br />
those people, " Don't bring your money here; we don't need you".<br />
I remember making a speech at the last election in a<br />
great factory, financed by AIerican capital and my opponent<br />
incautiously, the previous day, said that they objected to this<br />
importation of capital, that we were pawning ourselves to the<br />
overseas money lenders a very attractive phrase. But I said it<br />
was simple to test. I said to these thousands of non, " You know,<br />
you're engaged in earning a good living, a steady living, in a<br />
good job with prospects, in this business which is entirely<br />
financed from outside Australia. Are you in favour of cutting off<br />
the supply of finance? Are you in favour of telling people in<br />
Canada, people in the United States of America, they are not to<br />
invest their money in Australia?"<br />
I apologise to you for talking so long about so<br />
elementary a matter. But I began it and I end that particular<br />
thing by pointing out to you that the people who have control of<br />
investable funds outside Australia are not to be treated as fools;<br />
they are pretty shrewd people. They are just as shrewd as the<br />
average financial critic in a newspaper in Australia, just as<br />
shrewd. And while a local man wastes his time occasionally by<br />
saying " We are confronting nothing but disaster", which is utter<br />
drivel, the fellow outside, the shrewd man, who has money to<br />
invest, and money to lose, wrho has to back his judgment with his<br />
investment, finds us rore attractive this year than he ever did<br />
before. Now I ask you to make a mental note that.<br />
And now perhaps you will allow me to put one or two<br />
questions to myself, then answer then myself. I find that is a<br />
rather convenient arrangement.<br />
( Interjections) ( Well madam I an sorry to disappoint you but I like<br />
putting questions to myself because I find them intelligible)<br />
( Laughter, applause)<br />
The first question I want to put is this: Why should<br />
the Government of Australia, having presided over these<br />
remarkable developments, suddenly go mad and decide to tear down<br />
the whole building that they have been working to construct for<br />
or 11 years? Last year, 1960, the prosperity in this couhtry<br />
converted itself into a great inflationary boon and I have yet to<br />
read any expert, so-cilled, in any organ of opinion, who denies<br />
the existence of the boon, an inflationary boom. Costs were<br />
rising, prices were rising, there was a great shortage of labour,<br />
with far more jobs than there were men to hold them, or women to<br />
hold then, a great shortage of labour, prices rising, costs<br />
rising. The effect of that kind of thing is two-fold.<br />
First of all it meant the most tremendous demand for<br />
imports. Whenever people feel well-off, whenever overtio is<br />
high, whenever wages are much higher than the award rates, whenever<br />
there is a shortage of labour, whenever people are fooling<br />
good and prosperous, then you will have, always in the experience<br />
of any country like our own, a tromendous demand for imports;<br />
because the local production can't satisfy the demand. The<br />
result was that imports were flowing into Australia under<br />
circunstances which were lowering our overseas reserves so<br />
vital to our solvency month by month. At the same time, of<br />
course, inflation was inflicting grievous injury on people who<br />
can't chase the market, but who live on fixed incomes. Whether<br />
they are people on salaries, or fixed waess, whether they are<br />
people on pensions or social benefits, whether they are people on </p>
<p>superannuation, it is they who are on fixed incomes who suffer<br />
murderously through inflation. Thereforo social justice required<br />
that we should quell this beoi, and international solvency<br />
required that we should quell this boon.<br />
Now, Sir, it must be at somebody's expense, I'n sure you<br />
realise that. I'm sure that you are not so naive as to believe<br />
that you can que'. l arn infla'ti: nary boor and not touch anybody. Of<br />
course you have to touch sor.: body. The greatest complaint that<br />
have come as a result of our neasures have not cone from people on<br />
fixed incomels, have not come from employed people; but have come<br />
from others. But you must hit and hurt somebody if you are going<br />
to get rid of an inflationary boon.<br />
( TI-_ erjection) ( My dear sir the worker is the least affected by this,<br />
and will profit most by the success of our policy. All right, I<br />
know you don't agroe with no, you've registered your pointo<br />
( Interjections) If I belonged to your Party, Sir, and had no<br />
outlook on the problems of the country, I would pray for more and<br />
more inflation every month, because that is your only stock-intrade.)<br />
I have a great responsibility in this matter. It is, of<br />
course, deplorable that you should have to enco: unter any degree of<br />
uhcuployment in Australia. But it is much better to encounter<br />
some, by strong measures, and get back to full. employment at the<br />
quickest possible moment, than it would be to sit quietly by and<br />
allow the boon to go on and burst. If it were allowed to go on,<br />
and burst, then I want to tell you that unemployment in Australia<br />
wouldn't be measured by thousands, it would be measured by<br />
quarters of millions. You can't afford to trifle with a great<br />
serious economic problem like an inflationary boon.<br />
( Interjection) ( You know I marvel at the vanity of some of you chaps.<br />
You sit there and you chatter the same little bits over and over<br />
again; I'm sure you have &amp; ot them written down on a piece of<br />
paper. I remember two or three chaps like this years ago at a<br />
meeting of . ine and they kept saying the most pungent things, but<br />
unfortunately when they left at the end of the meeting they left<br />
their printed bits of paper behind them. And I read then.)<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, lot re ask, " What would have<br />
happened if we hadn't taken these counter-inflationary measures?"<br />
Would it just have settled itself, quietly, with no assistance by<br />
anybody? If we had lot the boon run on and said, " No, we're<br />
afiaid to touch it, it will hurt somebody and it will make us<br />
unpopular" as if unpopularity ought to trouble responsible<br />
people suppose we had just stood by and said, " No, we will do<br />
nothing about it', the boom would have run on, costs would have<br />
risen, prices would have risen. And in the result two things would<br />
have happened to this country of ours that I want you all to think<br />
about. The first of them is that our primary industries in<br />
Australia, which are our life blood in international trade, which<br />
provide over 900 of the whole of the export income of Australia,<br />
would have been put at great risk. What a fantasy it would have<br />
been if, following the popular course, we had sat down and said<br />
" We are not doing anything", and the price of wool had not been<br />
adequate to cover the cost of producing wool in Australia, then I<br />
want to tell you that this country would be bankrupt in every<br />
international sense of the word.<br />
L </p>
<p>ai~ no,' or :' ofo-Vx y Governuent, going tO see<br />
that fha pp'r. ! le must na-. intain s wd on thao Dlcr. lants of<br />
cost, for the sake of o) ur exr-. ort :. Indus trios, whfichi hav a D<br />
battle today in the mw'iikct-s of the uorld, and rmay ia ve an even<br />
-r. tr b-~ l in the fWu o mch _ 1e ,; 3eneing upon 7 lat : 7aspi<br />
Europo. If. ru are gto ' aold those cxcports of ouors and hos<br />
gr~ at inhcabsuiZ~ rai rd anin or1<br />
a. w~ cen'vru u. j~ st.: J aining a it a<br />
_ 1 t b( , i nn; t with.<br />
Novw a is one reason, I ; iljust 6ive y. Du one more,<br />
II 1ustral-Ja we Lc,.-c 7,. x sta'a Govornnen-;: s and a Cumrab<br />
Gmre'm( 1_ 1mnT. o; ret t1no'e have eonormous 1publJ c works to<br />
I. o 11; I dozli,: 1t--_ Llr KIjey wfo-st ieney on thorn-. I ' nave no<br />
c! Ltl; cisr of the orlspogare of the Stlatfes of . ustUral~ ia, or<br />
of the Counonwal. th-14ll I know is thnat thLa avoi~ n'a go citizen in<br />
his ow. n dList;-ict v.-nts thy::-to 1o nc rot less. ndwhat are<br />
thaose public works? Theoe are not frippori-es. When StLA:-, e<br />
Government, for example, bil--ds a sc!, ool, sciaools, it is<br />
building sonothing, vital to the prog ross of theo Sta,, te; whe; n it<br />
r. mokes roads it is doing Sorl~ inE vital to tho expansio) n of<br />
enterporise and of coim1e-rco-, when we spend money year by year,<br />
large am~ ounts of it on the Snewy, we :, re doing soi: eth-inEg vital for<br />
tho provision of poor in factoriejs inVictoiii and Now ot<br />
1+ 1 C, and for ir2? igation in the who I broad ; ep of thle<br />
You look at any of these public wiori ho-using,<br />
sch.-ools, roa-ds, transport, water supply, irrigto. p~ ower, all<br />
thiose rnatters tha.-t I have been rafoniing<br />
( Interj ection) My friend down hcere and I are on the saine wave length<br />
at last ( Laughter) He said " Not enough" il. I think I agree.<br />
But thjro wouldnMt be as m~ uch se-,-) nt o. n it teDda-y if we<br />
haC. an inflationary boon.-. May I toll y-u w-hy? Because tho money<br />
that the St~ itos spend on p,,, blic works, on kid tlh Itm es I<br />
ho,_ ve rentioned, COCeS, non -ally, fronm theo LoanA Ha: koet. Tae States<br />
don't use their ordinary r,_ venuo to provide capitol go0ods, capital<br />
se-rvices, capital building-, S and works, but Loan nroney. The Lean<br />
Market in A1ustralia improves when you don't hiaver inflation<br />
boc. ctuLuo peo&gt; 1havo more c+ nfidonce) in a fixed interest investment.<br />
The Loan Market drics up when you haave an infj. ationary boor) 1'<br />
because people say " The value of r-iy mioney is runnig away ai th<br />
tii-e. Uhet is the point in taking? out a 5'-yoar Bond, or a<br />
3ond?" A1nd, Sir, what has huplec-Led in fa,, ct, is that m-, y<br />
Government, as thei first GoDvernment. Jn -! srla over to do it,<br />
has every yea-r, supplemrl-. e d heLcatn Mar-ket mn behalf 3f the<br />
Staze Governments. WIe 1iovec. madeI the diffcer ence botween what<br />
the lenders of money w% ould give the G-ov-ior. enIC.!, uthat was<br />
needed for the vrorks pregrarme.<br />
( Interjection) Ladlies and ~ lto t7u. sm ng et away f1-rm this. He<br />
doesn't understand what I talkin6 about. But do, yrou do.<br />
The fact is tha-t unlesS you can -get rid of an in'fia-tinary boom<br />
theo prospects of aorr:) wiigir cq for Public works will -dir:ñ iJnish<br />
year by year. N-ow,, nnybo'iy can understand that. A1nd under thec<br />
system that we have had thais wuld riean tha,. t the Cmowat<br />
itself wmuld find thrat groater mnd sreate r proportiuin ) f the<br />
rioney for State work". s out of its Budget. And what heappons -then<br />
is that the taxpayer of AustraiJe and that is probably every<br />
grown-up person here to) ni gh and a lot nore has to find the<br />
extra m. oney out of revenue fir tha,, t year. </p>
<p>Does it strike you as reasonable that the taxpayers of<br />
1961 should have to find, in cash, out of their annual o rnings<br />
for that year the whole capital cost of works which will be<br />
enjoyed by their children? I don't think so. I think it is a<br />
fair thing that the burdens of these i. naters should be spread.<br />
But the point that I want you to have in mind is that unless you<br />
can got rid of inflationary boons, unless you can produce stability<br />
in our econo. iy, then the ; works progranmes are going to represent,<br />
overy year, increasing burdens on taxes and taxes will be steadily<br />
increased year by year.<br />
Now I'n not a theoretical econonist; I've been<br />
entrusted by the people of ny country with these matters for a<br />
long time, longer than anybody else ever was, and I've got to know<br />
something about then. I'm not talking theory; I'n talking hard,<br />
practical experionce on these matters.<br />
Now, Sir, those are two illustrations of the enorous<br />
practical inportance of dealing rwith an inflationary boon and<br />
dealing with it strongly, firmly, not being afraid of a little<br />
unpopularity over it.<br />
You ray think, you know, that we are unpopular. I've<br />
boon pretty unpopular with some regularity all through my life;<br />
and I'm still here. And I don't mind being unpopular in a good<br />
cause. Now, how have these policies of ours been rworking out?<br />
Have we had the discnfort, have we had this tenporary phase of<br />
some unemploynent not a great figure, but an undesirable figure<br />
of course, a miserable figure from the point of view of the people<br />
who are out of a job bave we had these results for nothing? Has<br />
the policy produced positive results? Has it produced results so<br />
positive that we can look forard to a period in the near future<br />
in which evorything will get back on to its normal tracks, and we<br />
will be going about our affairs in the ordinary way? I think the<br />
answer to that is " Yes".<br />
There are two or three matters that this policy of ours<br />
was ained at. The first was to protect our overseas balances,<br />
money built up overseas in order to pay for imports as they cone<br />
in. The first thing was to protect those from running away. The<br />
fact is that the policy has been so effective that at Juno<br />
just the other day, the diminution of the balances that we had<br />
feared back in November had not happened, because of the policies<br />
and the neasures taken. I an happy to say that at the end of<br />
June ( Interjection: Do we ha. ve to nport things? Can't vwe produce our<br />
own? ( Well, unfortunately we can't)<br />
( Intorjection: Why?)<br />
( If you think that by a stroke even of your pen you<br />
could produce in . ustralia tomncrrow œ 1 00Om. worth of goods now<br />
imported, then you are the greatest optinist I over know in ny<br />
life). I have no apologies to make about the developc-. nt of<br />
Australian rmanufacturing during our torr of office. It has boon<br />
phenomenal. I know that sonething is made, occasionally, of some<br />
enterprise that has increased' i. ts o nloynont year by year by year<br />
over the last 8 or 9 years, not being able to increase it this<br />
tine, or even to reduce it a little. This is sinply one of those </p>
<p>8.<br />
things that happens in any economy. But the point that I an<br />
getting at is that the balance of payments position in Australia<br />
has been arrested in the nost dranatic fashion by the stops taken<br />
by us. It was only today, as I was coning across to Tasmania,<br />
that I was able to read in a loading article in the Financial<br />
Tines of London, applauding what had boon done in Australia, and<br />
this remarkable result.<br />
What about land speculation? Did you like it? Did you<br />
think it was a helpful thing? Did any serious married couple of<br />
people in this hall, thinking about a house, not worry about the<br />
prices that were being run-up for a block of land to put a house<br />
on? The land speculation boon in Australia, in all its various<br />
forms, was becoming a social menace. That boon has finished.<br />
There are all sorts of other things: the activities in<br />
the hire purchase field, adn irable up to a point, were reaching<br />
such dimensions that people were acquiring liabilities on household<br />
goods which they would not be able to discharge if there were<br />
one breath of adversity in the family earnings. All this has been<br />
quietoned down; brought back to a reasonable level. We are not<br />
looking for a low-level of activity; we are looking for a high<br />
steady level of activity. Therefore when I talk about quelling<br />
the boon I talk about bringing matters back to that level at which<br />
money, in other words incomno wages, salaries, whatever they nay<br />
be, will maintain some steadiness of value, and enable people to<br />
plan their future with some security.<br />
Finally, I just want to say this to you: these are all<br />
natters worth thinking about. They are matters, I agree, worth<br />
explaining on behalf of the Governeont from time to time; but,<br />
above all, I do want you to believe this simple truth, that 20 nen<br />
don't go mad, all at the same tine, suddenly. If anybody had<br />
talked, 12 months ago, about our policy we wouldn't have heard any<br />
of these criticisms. People wo. uld have said, " Oh, things are going<br />
along; in fact they are booming along. Everything in the garden<br />
is lovely". And for 10 years, with one or two interludes in which<br />
we have had to take stringent measures and they haven't been<br />
extraordinarily popular at the time for all this period of time,<br />
' 49, 59~ ' 5 8, you have voted for us. I don't think<br />
many people have regretted that they did. I just want you to<br />
understand that if we, in a few matters, take steps which you don't<br />
like very much, or which may hurt somebody hero or there, we are<br />
not taking then for fun.<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, I have talked long enough for<br />
my good, if not for yours. I just want to say that I ua<br />
delighted to be hero t. night, i really dicn't intend to become<br />
involved in a political argumecnt; I thought I might have saved<br />
that until the next election. But as my friend over there seemed<br />
to believe that the next election won't be much good to me,<br />
perhaps I was right to take the opportunity of talking about it<br />
now. ( Applause)<br />
l, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
