<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9342</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA 31 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009342.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
31 AUGUST 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I'll make this brief. Mr Downerhas gone out of his way to.. has gone<br />
out in 1987 and associif-d himself with an organisation which is the<br />
most notoriously racist and anti-Semitic in the country. In 1987 it<br />
would have been impossible for any active person in politics not to<br />
have known that he was addressing the League of Rights. Particularly<br />
when all his colleagues knew about themaiid-had already in the<br />
Hansard record and elsewhere reacted angrily to them. Sitting as he<br />
was, I understand, next to Eric Butler and Jeremy Lee the person who<br />
had escorted David Irving, a man who denies the Holocaust, around<br />
the country. In speaking at a meeting organised by avowed racists<br />
and anti-Semites, he has failed every principle of his political duty.<br />
And by his failure today to explain his actions, he's failed again.<br />
I can tell you I've never seen a leader of the Opposition in the House<br />
display so little courage as Mr Downer did today being protected by<br />
the likes of Wilson Tuckey, and Peter Reith and the leader of the<br />
national party, when he stood up and made a personal explanation, or<br />
ducking out of back doors from journalists after indicating that he<br />
would in fact gave them an interview. When John Hewson said to<br />
Alexander Downer, when he rang him and said that he was going to<br />
run for the leadership of the Opposition, he said " You don't have what<br />
it takes, Alexander", and the truth is he was dead right.<br />
J: Do you think Mr Downer should resign, Mr Keating?...( inaudible)...<br />
PM: Well, he has failed I think, the principle of political duty and he has<br />
failed to explain his circumstances at the time. I mean, this is a<br />
notorious organisation. When you look at some of the remarks which<br />
have been made by... in April 1988, by Senator Peter Baume: " There<br />
can be no doubt that the League of Rights espouses values </p>
<p>inconsistent with the Liberal-Democratic traditions to which so many of<br />
us are committed. It's not surprising, indeed, it's almost inevitable that<br />
serious political leaders should find the League of Rights message to<br />
be anathema to them.", and it goes on with others. Senator Boswell:<br />
" The League's public face is for God, Queen and country, and support<br />
for States rights, free enterprise, the Constitution, the family farm and<br />
small businesses. It's only natural that many decent men and women<br />
are attracted to these objectives which are laudable and noble.<br />
However, the more extreme side of the League is introduced<br />
insidiously by degrees through its extensive network of organisations."<br />
Now, if you are a member of Parliament, and you are an aspiring party<br />
leader, you shouldn't be one of the gullible men and women who are<br />
attracted to the objectives and yet not understand what the<br />
organisation is.<br />
J: So do you condemn with equal vigour the support from members of<br />
your own party, like Graeme Campbell, for right wing groups?<br />
PM: Graeme Campbell is not the leader of the Labor Party. That's the<br />
difference.<br />
J: But he is an ALP politician and he did address a League of Rights<br />
meeting, will you seek to have him expelled?<br />
PM: No. And I don't endorse his political views either... r his social views.<br />
J: But do you condemn his views?<br />
PM: Well, some I do. But most, of course, are consistent with the Labor<br />
Party's objectives.<br />
J: Do you really think that Alexander Downer has anti-Semitic views?<br />
PM: Well, it's hard to explain that he has addressed a League of Rights<br />
meeting. In the late eighties, the League of Rights was an active<br />
organisation. I mean, any of us you in journalism, or any of us in<br />
politics at that time knew this to be so. It shows very, at best,<br />
exceptionally bad judgement to be in their company.<br />
J: Is the crime that he addressed the meeting, or that he won't own up to<br />
it?<br />
PM: Both. I think he shouldn't have addressed the meeting, and he<br />
should've today said he did and what the circumstances are,<br />
instead of ducking and weaving, and cowardly hiding behind people in<br />
the House of Representatives when it was raised. And, of course,<br />
having it defended in the Senate. What he should have done was<br />
come out and said so said what the circumstances were, and at least<br />
given the country some explanation of his position. </p>
<p>3<br />
J: Have you, in your long political career, addressed or shared a platform<br />
at a party or group of people, that you didn't share those views later<br />
on? Perhaps you were embarrassed about later on?<br />
PM: Not that I can remember. Not the League of Rights. You won't find me<br />
with the League of Rights.<br />
J: Have you seen the video, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: No, I haven't.... which video?<br />
J: The one of this event?<br />
PM: No, I haven't seen it, no.<br />
J: What of his explanation that he thought he was addressing a Christian<br />
Youth Rally at the time?<br />
PM: Well, Senator Boswell says this... that it goes through the established<br />
fronts; " The most established front organisation would be the Institute<br />
for Economic Democracy, Ladies in Line Against Communism, the<br />
Christian Institute for Individual Freedom, the Australian Heritage<br />
Society, and the Conservative Speakers Club". I mean, you've got to<br />
be either incompetent, or a fool to turn up to a show like this and not<br />
know what it is. And if you are that, you shouldn't be the leader of the<br />
Opposition. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
