<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9465</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE, COMMONWEALTH GOVT OFFICES, SYDNEY 27 JANUARY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009465.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, COMMONWEALTH GOVT OFFICES, SYDNEY<br />
27 JANUARY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Let me just say a couple of things about it on December 22nd last<br />
year I made a statement about forest policy, and I said at the time that<br />
the Government would implement a program calculated to preserve<br />
the forests of high conservation significance and environmental<br />
significance, and that the Government would undertake a rescheduling<br />
study to establish which of those areas or coupes as they are called<br />
actually fall in that category. Now that study was undertaken through<br />
the Christmas period, with the Department of the Environment<br />
conducted by the Minister for the Environment, Sports and Territories,<br />
and he along with the Minister for Resources have met and<br />
discussed these various coupes and judged it As a consequence, I<br />
can announce today that the Commonwealth has identified 509 such<br />
areas or coupes and will do everything in its power to ensure their<br />
protection pending more detailed assessment of their values. In other<br />
words, we are setting aside 509 coupes for study. Of these, about<br />
roughly half 222 in fact are in the register of the National Estate,<br />
and the others are part of wilderness regrowth and part of the<br />
conservation area forests. Our policy is to protect these areas until<br />
their values are properly assessed as part of a national reserve system<br />
through a regional forest agreement. You will recall in the National<br />
Forest Policy Statement, the aim is to get away form coupe-by-coupe<br />
assessments, and to go to Regional Forest Agreements whereby we<br />
have got a comprehensive and adequate reserve system, so we don't<br />
have to say well is this category of wilderness trees adequately<br />
represented in the reserve? That would be the case if an RFA<br />
between the Commonwealth, the States and the industry were in fact<br />
constructed. But what we will be doing is putting aside these coupes fo e </p>
<p>until their values are assessed in the context of Regional Forest Policy<br />
Agreements. You may know that since I made that announcement, the Federal<br />
Court made a decision about licences, and the validity of their issue<br />
which has created some uncertainty as to their validity. So the<br />
Commonwealth is saying to these companies that they can consider<br />
their position, and I know that they are many of them unhappy about<br />
the uncertainty which that decision has brought, and the offer that the<br />
Commonwealth makes to them is that we will re-issue their licences in<br />
the event that they give up the licence that was issued before<br />
Christmas. And in the event that they do, we will very quickly re-issue<br />
licences which comply with that Federal Court decision. Now can I just<br />
say in that context, that the Minister for Resources though agreeing<br />
to licences before Christmas didn't write to companies about areas<br />
reserved for his decision in respect of areas of old growth conservation<br />
values. He will be writing to companies in terms of the 509 coupes<br />
and the companies can make a decision as to whether in fact overall<br />
they are advantaged by actually giving up their licence, and then<br />
seeking a new one from the Commonwealth.<br />
I think the key point in all of this is that the Government's goal is to put<br />
into place over the next 5 years a program to adequately protect old<br />
growth wilderness and other high conservation value forests in a<br />
national reserve system, in a system of Regional Forest Agreements.<br />
And to ensure that a high value-added wood products industry can<br />
operate sustainably. In other words, we have an industry primarily<br />
based on plantations and regrowth forests that is the aim. And the<br />
Government is prepared in that context to look at the impact of<br />
these decisions, how we can best advance the regional forests in the<br />
National Forest Policy Statement of Regional Forest Agreements, to<br />
move towards that kind of forest products industry and that kind of<br />
conservation policy. And we will be meeting with the industry, with the<br />
trade unions, with the conservation movement to see how best that<br />
can be done, and what sort of package should be put into place to<br />
encourage those things to happen.<br />
Now I said before Christmas that we will be reducing the overall<br />
volumes, and I'm not sure the significance of that was picked up in the<br />
brouhaha at the time. But it would mean that areas which were part of<br />
Regional Forest Agreements would get first chop at the tonnage, and<br />
those that were not part of the Regional Forest Agreements those<br />
that in fact that basically decided not either add value or to put into<br />
place a comprehensive reserve system would be at the back end of<br />
any priority on that tonnage. For many years, we have been speaking<br />
of phasing out the raw woodchippping and moving towards higher<br />
value-adding. The Government in getting the National Forest Policy<br />
Statement together has the framework in place to do that with the<br />
concept of the Regional Forest Agreement. But it needed the screws </p>
<p>turned on it to make it work, and that screw was turned when I<br />
announced the volumes were coming down.<br />
So by and large, I think that this decision when I say the decision, it is<br />
the judgements that both Ministers have brought here, the Minister for<br />
the Environment and the Minister for Resources are good and<br />
balanced judgements and in the best interests of the country and in<br />
terms of the conservation of important stands of trees, and the longrun<br />
interests of the industry for certainty and for the future in terms of<br />
sustainability are best served by measures of this kind. I am happy to<br />
take questions.<br />
J: Prime Minister, what portion of the licences do you expect to<br />
automatically re-issue, and for those that don't get those licences<br />
automatically re-issued, will there be any form of compensation?<br />
PM: There is no question of compensation. Understand this the point I<br />
made earlier the Minister for resources never wrote to the companies<br />
not to this point saying which coupes would be reserved or set<br />
aside for study, which is a right he enjoys. That is in terms of the<br />
existing licenses. But the companies would themselves probably<br />
believe that the certainty is a key matter for them. I can't tell you how<br />
many of them will actually give back if you like, or give up, their<br />
licences, but I should imagine the need will be for certainty.<br />
J: Prime Minister, given what you have said in the past... inaudible what<br />
is the process by which you protect these areas?<br />
PM: The Commonwealth will not be agreeing to the exporting of woodchips<br />
from those coupes. But this gets back to the central point that I made<br />
in December I mean you have all been around for the Christmas<br />
break, you have probably all driven through if not all of you, then<br />
some of you will have driven through parts of NSW and Victoria you<br />
never see a Commonwealth forest. They are State forests. This is a<br />
State-run industry the Commonwealth gets in there only on strings<br />
and mirrors through the export powers, and the saw-log industry we<br />
have essentially no control over, other than to try and urge the States<br />
to be party to Regional Forest Agreements, so they have got to make<br />
judgements themselves about where they might and try and make<br />
volumes for companies in the event that product can't be exported<br />
from these coupes. Now sensibly, they should do that. If they say " Oh<br />
well, we can't find the volumes", it means the whole notion of<br />
sustainability was a ruse in the first place, so I think they will they will<br />
get to it and try to make this work.<br />
J: If they can't find the volumes, then you will accept compensation<br />
requests?<br />
PM: No. There is no requirement for compensation here. The<br />
Commonwealth has a right to decide in the national interest what </p>
<p>product can be exported, and in what terms. It in no way is agreeing to<br />
these decisions before Christmas, made clear its preferences that is<br />
why I said that Mr Beddall didn't write to companies at that time,<br />
reserving the right to write to them after the re-scheduling study.<br />
J: Do you still have confidence in Minister Beddall?<br />
PM: Look, this is a difficult issue a very difficult issue. As always, we<br />
have got the environment there riding the Commonwealth, but not<br />
riding the States. And the pressure point comes, as I say, round the<br />
incidental power the Commonwealth government has over exports.<br />
And the Ministers will take positions in terms of their portfolio interests,<br />
and at the same time we did last year, make a key decision on the<br />
Minister Ros Kelly to have the Minister for the Environment to have a<br />
right and a power in here. Now, at the time the environment movement<br />
dismissed that as pap. This year, of course, it is all-important, though<br />
of course she received no credit for it. Now, we were trying to develop<br />
a process where we can sensibly consider export licences reasonably,<br />
and the conservation values of particular coupes. But it will always be<br />
difficult, and I hope we can get that process better. But it is much<br />
better if we have Regional Forest Agreements where we are not going<br />
coupe-by-coupe, where we have in fact areas where we look at<br />
adequate reserve systems so this coupe issue doesn't come up.<br />
J: Prime Minister, given that the Environment Minister was ignored,<br />
doesn't that prove that the process was pap?<br />
PM: The Environment Minister I don't think was ignored, it was just a matter<br />
of whether in the advice which the Minister for Resources received, he<br />
was able to adequately discern what the priorities were in that advice,<br />
and at any rate, both public opinion and opinion within the Government<br />
within the Caucus and the Cabinet has made very clear the areas of<br />
high conservation value are important in national terms, and I think he<br />
has certainly accepted that message.<br />
J: So you won't be taking Gough Whitlam's advice?<br />
PM: I didn't hear... I mean Gough has advice for many people that is not a<br />
bit I heard, actually.<br />
J: Isn't it arguable that Minister Beddall has completely botched this<br />
process?<br />
PM: I like to think that if a good thing happens here and I think this is a<br />
good thing happening here I like the notion of Ministers sorting out<br />
the way they make decisions and coming to the right conclusions. I<br />
mean, I think it is healthy.<br />
J: Regardless of processes and how the processes might have been? </p>
<p>PM: It is like you lot doing mea culpas for any stories you got wrong -I<br />
mean, you wouldn't consider it.<br />
J: Do you think that this statement will satisfy the Democrats in terms of<br />
the.. inaudible....<br />
PM: I think so. Let's call a spade a spade in this if there had been 200 or<br />
230 coupes reserved here before Christmas, the environment<br />
movement would have thought they kicked a tremendous goal. As it<br />
is, there are 509, and they are all important areas....<br />
J: inaudible<br />
PM: . and this is a very significant decision.<br />
J: Already this morning I am getting calls from....<br />
PM: Who are you and where are you from?<br />
J: James Woodforde from the Sydney Morning Herald. Already this<br />
morning we are getting calls from environmentalists and industry<br />
saying that this compromise will solve nothing that<br />
PM: You don't say? You shock me you have really slayed me.<br />
J: They are arguing that this is just a compromise.. . there is no basis for<br />
it?<br />
PM: Well, see what the serious people say.<br />
J: Prime Minister, in Caucus on Monday ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, the Caucus is master of its own destiny always, and part of the<br />
democracy of the Labor Party is that people have got a right to put a<br />
view, but I think that most people in the Caucus will think that this is a<br />
very fair and balanced outcome.<br />
J: Prime Minister you have mentioned that you will invite the companies<br />
to give back their licences and you will re-issue the bulk of them have<br />
you got any idea on how swiftly that can be done?<br />
PM: I think reasonably quickly. Now that this work has taken place, and<br />
that we are in a position to know which coupes have these values, so I<br />
think the answer to that is very quickly.<br />
J: Prime Minister, do you.. inaudible do you think perhaps you<br />
should be more involved in the processes of these decisions?<br />
PM: There are matters of law here, and so as that Federal Court decision<br />
very adequately shows Ministers who make judgements and issue </p>
<p>licences must do so conscientiously to have conducted the work<br />
themselves and come to the judgements. And that I have implicitly<br />
understood, and that is why in the context of this process because we<br />
are dealing overall with about 3,500 coupes it is very difficult for<br />
either the Prime Minister or the Cabinet to be sitting there looking at<br />
little purple or green dots, or red dots various others and saying we will<br />
have half a dozen of those and, and 6 of those and 12 of those -I<br />
mean, in the end it requires Departmental effort here to go through a<br />
system of evaluation and after all, for a whole lot of values about<br />
forests which are not in the Commonwealth charter there is no<br />
Commonwealth Department of Forestry we do not run forests.<br />
J: How exactly do you propose to protect these 509 coupes, given that<br />
there are already licences issued allowing them to log?<br />
PM: I made it clear to you Mr Beddall has not yet written in terms of those<br />
reservations he is able to enter into those licences, and he is obviously<br />
being guided by the study and is concurring in its outcome.<br />
J: Isn't this a slap in the face for Senator Faulkner I mean there is still<br />
less than half of the areas that he put forward as being those requiring<br />
protection?<br />
PM: I know that Senator Faulkner is very happy with this outcome. And he<br />
is for the reason that I said earlier that if in the first instance it had<br />
been 200 250 reservations coupes this would have been general<br />
regarded as a good decision. I think that at this number and at these<br />
values, I think he is well pleased with the study.<br />
J: Would it be better to be a decision made by the entire Cabinet and will<br />
that be the case in 1996?<br />
PM: Probably not, and for the reasons I just said. I think it is very difficult to<br />
get into it although we have in the past but it is very it is not to say<br />
that the Cabinet can't do it, but it is very tedious and onerous because<br />
Ministers then have to.. the whole Cabinet has to be up to speed on<br />
the values of particular areas across the Commonwealth, particularly<br />
down the East Coast, and trying to inject themselves into some<br />
judgements about values in forests which we, of course, have no<br />
responsibility for.<br />
J: It is a fair guess, I'd suggest, that NSW, Victoria and Tasmania<br />
Governments will not be enamoured?<br />
PM: I don't know that would be true.<br />
J: Do you believe Mr Beddall is conscientious about this decision, Prime<br />
Minister? </p>
<p>PM: I am announcing on behalf of him and Senator Faulkner this is their<br />
joint decision, Of course he is conscientious about it.<br />
J: Did he follow all the proper steps do everything that he was<br />
supposed to have done?<br />
PM: Well, the Federal Court took a view that environmental values should<br />
have counted more heavily in the decision, but the Commonwealth is<br />
still yet to take a view about that decision.<br />
J: Prime Minister, can I ask some crude political stuff now?<br />
PM: If you want to be crude Laurie, sure.<br />
J: I was wondering how you feel about having your new opponent?<br />
PM: It's 3 in 10 months for me. And for the Liberal Party of course, John<br />
Howard will be their third preference John Hewson, they passed over<br />
Howard for Hewson, they passed over Howard for Downer, and they<br />
are taking him because they have got nobody else.<br />
J: It has been suggested this morning that you are relishing the prospect<br />
of the contest?<br />
PM: The thing to do is forget all the hyperbole about triple-bypasses and<br />
relishing the contest go and ask him about this decision. Start tough<br />
with him, and ask him about some policy ask him what he thinks<br />
about these 509 coupes, and whether he supports them. Because<br />
what you might find is that you will get a repeat of what he had to say<br />
in the 1987 election for what it's worth, he said he would leave<br />
decisions to State governments, the Queensland rainforest nominated<br />
for World Heritage listing would only be listed if the Bjelke-Peterson<br />
government approved it, he would hand over Kakadu and Uluru to the<br />
Northern Territory Government, and he would abolish the Department<br />
of the Environment. So go along and ask him let's leave the political<br />
theory out because none of us are too strong on that, are we? So, just<br />
ask him what he thinks of this it's not a bad starting point I would<br />
have thought.<br />
J: inaudible<br />
PM: Well, I think that Mr Howard was a failure as Treasurer, and a failure<br />
as an Opposition Leader. He left an inward looking, moribund, lowprofit,<br />
low-employment, high inflation economy behind, and as<br />
Opposition Leader, he had no clear policy of change for the country,<br />
and the one he did fell apart at Box Hill in Victoria.<br />
J: Prime Minister, Senator Bolkus has raised the Asian immigration<br />
( inaudible)... . are you going to put you shoulder to the wheel on that </p>
<p>kind of attack on Mr Howard, or do you think those sort of devices<br />
PM: You mean reminding Mr Howard of what he said is an attack on him<br />
is that what you are saying?<br />
J: Well, I think it is.<br />
PM: I know you are close to him Glenn, but you shouldn't be that close.<br />
J: Well, he has made an attempt to move away from those remarks he<br />
has apologised for them....<br />
PM: And for years he said he wouldn't change his position on this John<br />
Howard hasn't changed his position. When he tells you that he didn't<br />
mean it, all I say is don't believe him. Of course he meant it.<br />
J: So that is going to be an issue?<br />
PM: It will rank with the great constellation of issues out there.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
