<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2828</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINSTER ADRESSES INDONESIAN PARLIAMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002828.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AF-A-S<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 42. 22 Febr~ uary 1971<br />
PRIfBMI r! rFi Arm2. m3mTw) Il A PA IAr. TANT<br />
Fol~ lowing is the text of an addreos by the Prine Minister<br />
and Minister for Foreign Afffair Mr kWhitlam, to the Dowan<br />
Peri-. alciinn ) P,. kYat TRenxiblik Tndoncoia ( Ind-o7nc~ tia Parliament) in<br />
O Jakarta today. The speech was delivered at about 1600 hours<br />
Canberra time. I am ro-Loundly moved by th-e honnur yo) u ' have dlone me,<br />
and through me, m-y Government and nation in inviting me to address<br />
you. When a little over t.! o months . ao I became Prime<br />
tirU'istpr, as leader of th-e majority party in the Australian<br />
* Parliament, I placed a visit to Indones-: ia at tu e vnry ' he~ d of<br />
my nriorities. I was highily gratified by -the warmth o. f President<br />
Soeharto's invitation. I and those travelling with me members<br />
of my family, my stiff, and my officials hnave been deeply<br />
touched by hosnite-lity and pr-nerosity with, which we hnave all<br />
been treated. This visit comes at a !-ime of great cl&gt; ange of grea. t<br />
change in ry own nation and of great c'. arge in our region. I want<br />
to em-ha! sise, h'-) wevf-r, at -the ouLtse-t, thnat my visit syrbolisec<br />
continuity a5 well as change. 12 </p>
<p>. In June last year my prcdoceosor as Prime Minister of<br />
Australia, the Rkt. Hon. William McMahon, visited Jakarta and<br />
xrde, sed this ass-c-bl1y. On Petu. L~ i to Au~ siralia he ti h<br />
pcople of Australia, as I shall tell them, of the friendship<br />
which the -oeopole and rvirernment n. f T~ dnzahad extended to himi<br />
and through him, to Australia. Mr Mc~ abon was able to report<br />
that at the official level, his discussions had fuirther advanced<br />
co-osoeratuiton betw; ceri our tk~ ro countric,,.<br />
Tbere w~ kas and is no partioan kdisot iIn y utyo<br />
this mratter. Thbe cr11a ngae o f G o vePr n ie n Iias iade no cl-ange in<br />
Australia's desire for the closest co-operation with the Government<br />
and people of Indonesia.<br />
I know that that wish is shared by the Indonesian<br />
Government and neople. Austra-li* an-Indone,,,' Iin friendship is a,<br />
constant factor in a charging region and a changiLng w. orld.<br />
The new Australian Government has macle many sigrificant<br />
changes in Australia's international relations, It would have been<br />
strange indeed had it Inot been so, for my Government was elected<br />
by the people of Australia with a mandate for ch. n, or -,-an. PeS<br />
at home and abroad. You will -ecall that m~ y T~ arty e Autralian<br />
Labor Party had been out'of office for 23 years, InhAvi: ng lost<br />
power before Indonesia finally won her great struggle for<br />
independence. -I-</p>
<p>As an example of the changes that have taken place,<br />
I cite the record of Australia's voting in the United Nations<br />
General Assembly. In the 1971 General Assembly, Australia<br />
voted against three resolutions on Southern Africa and three<br />
others concerning the Indian Ocean, apartheid and selfdetermination<br />
all of which Indonesia supoorted. But in the<br />
1972 General Assembly, immediately after my Government took<br />
office, Australia voted affirmatively with Indonesia on each<br />
of those resolutions. On all important iissues of race,<br />
decolonisation and self-determination, our voting now accords<br />
with Indonesia's. On the day that I was sworn in as Prime Minister<br />
of Australia I made this statement to our people, which sums<br />
up the general approach of my Government. I said that I<br />
wanted " An Australia which will enjoy a growing standing<br />
as a distinctive, tolerant, co-operative and well<br />
regarded nation not only in the Asian and Pacific<br />
region, but in the world at large."<br />
I will return later to the role of middle powers in<br />
the world at large. Let me say something first about our<br />
relations with our neighbours and our region. In the distant<br />
past Australia tended to ignore South-East Asia. Generations<br />
ago, we were still largely a European outpost, a part of the<br />
old British Emnire, with our loyalties and nreoccupations in<br />
Europe alone. In the oast 20 years we moved to an opposite<br />
extreme. / 4 </p>
<p>Influenced by such events as the Chinese revolution<br />
and the war in Indo-China, we became oreoccupied, even obsessed,<br />
with South-East Asia as a new Australian frontier, even a frnntline<br />
for our security. This led us into military involvements<br />
and military pacts that are no longer relevant to the contemporary<br />
needs of Australia or the region in which we live.<br />
In the wake of a Vict-Nam settlement, it is my hope<br />
that we will see South-East Asia in a calmer, more constructive<br />
perspective. We -want our attitude to be based less on irrational<br />
fears for our security, and directed more to peaceful political<br />
initiatives for the welfare and nrogress of our neighbours.<br />
My Government believes that it has a responsibility<br />
to take a generous oart in any international effort for the<br />
social and economic rehabilitation of Indo-China. There are<br />
several reasons why such resnonsibility devolves on us.<br />
Australia was one of the belligerents, although my<br />
Government has withdrawn all its forces from Viet-Nam and ended<br />
its military involvement. Over and above that, we are the<br />
richest member of the community of nations in the South-East<br />
Asian region, with a strong interest in the welfare of our<br />
neig-bours. We believe that the problems that you and other<br />
nations of the region face now are human and social problems,<br />
nroblems that are common to all mankind. How best to raise<br />
your stndards of living: how to bring literacy, cultural and </p>
<p>educational opnortunities to your people: how to control the<br />
growth of population and the environmental problems it will<br />
bring in its wake as your cities become more industrialised:<br />
how best to make use of the foreign aid resources at your<br />
disoosal to overcome poverty and disease. It is in these<br />
areas that my country is most anxious to help. We note the<br />
measures you are now taking to achieve population control.<br />
We would welcome, if your Government desires it, a long-term<br />
study of the whole rnncept of foprain aid to determine how<br />
best to apply it to urgent human and social needs. 2<br />
Last month I visited N-w Zealand where a new Labor<br />
Government has also been elected. The New Zealand Prime<br />
Minister, Mr Kirk, and I expressed our intention of working with<br />
our Asian and Pacific neighbours in making adjustments to<br />
existing arrangements and. seeking new forms of co-operation.<br />
We see great merit in an organisation genuinely representative<br />
of the region, without ideological overtones, conceived as an<br />
initiative to help free the region of the great power rivalries<br />
which have bedevilled its progress for so long, and which would<br />
be designed to insulate the region against ideological<br />
interference from the great nowers. I must emnhasise that<br />
such an objective is one which would take time and careful<br />
consultation with all of our neighbours.<br />
There is one very great change about to occur in<br />
our region of very special imoortance and interest to Indonesi2.<br />
and Australia equally. Indonesia and Australia at nre: e" t ./ 9 </p>
<p>a common border the border between Indonesia and Papua New<br />
Guinea. Before long that will no longer be true. Indonesia<br />
will share that border with an independent nation, the nation<br />
of Papua New Guinea.<br />
I have just visited Papua New Guinea to explain my<br />
Government's plans to the Deople there. What I have tried to<br />
put to them is that a decision about independence is not just<br />
a decision on behalf of Papua New Guinea. It is also a decision<br />
on behalf of Australia. It involves in a very real sense<br />
S-Australia's vision of herself in the world. To put it nlainly,<br />
Australia is not willing any longer to rule a colony.<br />
We regard it as unacceptable that Australia, of all<br />
countrie:, should be one of the world'-s last colonial powers.<br />
It would be incredible if the Australian Labor Party, which, in<br />
its last Government, wholeheartedly supported the cause of<br />
Indonesian independence, were to accept willingly a colonial<br />
D role for herself in the 1970s.<br />
SIt is not only a question of our responsibilities to<br />
the neople of Papua New Guinea, it is not only a question of<br />
our clear responsibilities under the United Nations Charter,<br />
it is a question of our responsibilities to ourselves.<br />
We are determined that we shall be true to ourselves<br />
and divest Australia of the colonial taint. This in no way<br />
means that we are going to wash our hands of our responsibilities<br />
towards the people of Panua New Guinea. We freely ana gladlY / 7 </p>
<p>accept that for many, many years to come, Papua New Guinea '. ill<br />
need continuing and substantial assistnnce from Australia. She<br />
shall have it and this again is a policy which would not be<br />
changed even if there were a change i the Gover4; mcnt of Australia.<br />
But our true role is as a friend and neighbour, not as a ruler.<br />
I believe that Indonesia can also play a valuable part<br />
as Papua New Guinea's friend and nearest neighbour. I hope the<br />
Seopl. of Papua New Guinea will look to Indonesia as an example<br />
of how neoples of different cultures and customs, of different<br />
Slanguages, of different religions, at widely different stages<br />
of deve. orment spread over a vast, divided and difficult terrain,<br />
Scan come together, live together , nd grow together as one great<br />
nation. If I might sum up the general lines that my Government<br />
will follow, I should like to quote a brief nassame, I wrote<br />
18 months ago when in Opnosition, for a book outlining for th,<br />
0 Peoole of Australia, the lines a Labor Government, if they<br />
elected one, would pursue. I wrote then:<br />
" Essentially, a nation's foreign nolicy depends upon<br />
a balance between commitment and Dower. Australia's first and I<br />
fundamencal commitment is to. our own national security. This is<br />
a commitment quite commensurate with our power and our re: source;.<br />
Our second commitment is to a secure, united and friendly<br />
Papua New Guinea. This too is well wit'in our nower. Our lack<br />
of wisdom and foresight, rather than any lack of nower and influere,<br />
is our real danger in this case. / 8 </p>
<p>Our third commitment is to achieving friendly relations 3<br />
with our nearest and largest neighbour, Indonesia.<br />
Our fourth commitment is more general, because in this<br />
context our power becomes more generalised it is our commitment<br />
to the peace and prosperity of the immediate region. Clearly<br />
our ambitions and aspirations on this level run beyond our actual<br />
power. Even so, we are far more influential than mere numbers<br />
would suggest Our fifth commi tmient is to our own renutation: our<br />
power in this case lies in our will, not our resources. This<br />
taint of racism must be removed if w. e are to be a good neighbour<br />
in our region." These are the five great pillars on which my Government<br />
proposes to establish its international relations. But it is<br />
not merely to ourselves, or even simply to our own region, that.<br />
our ultimate commitment lies. Our ultimate interests lie in<br />
helping to nreserve stable and peaceful relations between the<br />
great powers. In military and industrial terms, Australia<br />
and Indonesia can both perhaps be described as middle powers.<br />
We have a common interest in seeing th.'. it stable balance is<br />
maintained between the great nowers China, the Soviet Union,<br />
Janan, the United States on whose decisions the peace of the<br />
world will principally derend. As middle Dowers, we can both be<br />
active in working for peace and understanding in the world at<br />
large. It is in this broader context that I see the need for a<br />
fresh and indenendent policy for Australia in international rel-"" </p>
<p>It is in this context that I see great new opportunities for<br />
co-operation with Indonesia.<br />
Once more let me express my deep gratitude for the manner<br />
in whici you and the Government and people of Indonesia have<br />
received me. I am glad to have the opportunity so early in the<br />
life of my Government to reaffirm the existing links between our<br />
two countries and to forge new and stronger ones.<br />
Living as we both do in a region which is in many ways<br />
the world's most turbulent and economically deprived, we cannot<br />
ignore the very great difficulties and complexities which lie<br />
ahead, for us and for our neighbours. Yet, even so, it is<br />
S impossible not to hold real hope for the future, even while<br />
acknowledging the dangers.<br />
There is a very real prospect that there will be no<br />
major international conflict in our neighbourhood in the foreseeable<br />
future. The region has seen 30 very dark and troubled years. It<br />
would be naive to believe that we are now entering a period of<br />
profound peace. But at least we may look forward to a period of<br />
S comparative oeace uneasy, fragile, imperfect nerhaps, but if<br />
we have the will and determination, it will be enough to allow us<br />
to create the conditions in our rgiJon by which we can reduce the<br />
scourges of ooverty, starvation and suffering. In that war a<br />
war that is really worth waging I profoundly believe our two<br />
great countries will cement a deep and enduring, an unbreakable<br />
nartnership. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
