<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5588</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005588.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 17 MAY 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
A fortnight ago the Commonwealth met with State Premiers in<br />
Canberra for the first Premiers' Conference and Loan. Council<br />
Meeting in 1981.<br />
Tonight I would like to step aside from the predictable bickering<br />
that surrounds such conferences and talk to you about the real<br />
issues involved. They are fundamental issues about the role<br />
of government in a free society about cutting back on bloated<br />
bureaucracy; about streamlining and modernising government and<br />
making it more efficient for the eighties and beyond; about<br />
reducing the burden of taxation, and about whether you are free<br />
to spend your earnings as you choose, or only as government<br />
chooses.<br />
Not so many years ago, governments were under the impression that<br />
they would be popular if they spent money freely; that votes<br />
could be bought. It was that philosophy which raised government<br />
spending-from-3-1cents--in--every-dollar--produced-in Australia<br />
in 1972/ 73 to 37 cents only two years later in 1974/ 75.<br />
It is a matter of history that the sharp increase in government:<br />
spending was not paid f or at that time., But we have paid heavil~ y<br />
since-through inflation and unemployment triggered by the big<br />
budget deficits of those days.<br />
We have been obliged to take tough action to bring the deficit<br />
under control.-The Government has had to borrow massive amounts<br />
to pay for these deficits and these borrowings increasingly<br />
run the risk of depriving private enterprise of the funds it<br />
needs to increase job opportunities. We have to hold back<br />
government spending--. so-that-. private enterprise. can-continue<br />
to grow and take advantage of the magnificent opportunities.<br />
Australia now affords..<br />
Fortunately, there is now a change blowing through the AustraliLan<br />
community. People are realising that governments which spend<br />
money willy-nilly are using resources that wo ' uld otherwise be<br />
available to familil-s and to businesses to spend in the ways<br />
they themselves want. They are realising that governments that<br />
want to spend more money, first have to take it from the people<br />
of Australia in taxes, or borrow it in a way which holds back<br />
job-creating developments.<br />
On every side we are being told " there is too much government,<br />
too much regulation", " taxes are too high", " give us tax relief".<br />
A responsible government cannot reduce taxes unless it first<br />
cuts its spending. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
That was one of the reasons for the recent Review of Commonwealth<br />
Functions which identified ways of eventually saving $ 560 million<br />
a year in Commonwealth outlays and pruning 16,000. or so public service<br />
places..<br />
At the Premiers' Conference we carried the process a stage further<br />
by imposing restraints on the tax sharing funds paid by the<br />
Commonwealth to the States. It is not generally realised that<br />
State and Local governments spend just over half of all the<br />
money spent by governments in Australia. But at the same time,<br />
they raise less than one fifth of all the taxes. The Commonwealth<br />
raises the rest. The States keep up their spending only with<br />
the help of massive payments from the Commonwealth. In fact,<br />
about half the funds the States spend are raised by the Commonw * ealth.<br />
To put it simply, the Commonwealth collects the taxes and the<br />
States spend them. This means that if there are to be tax cuts<br />
all levels of government, State as well as Commonwealth, have<br />
to rein in their spending. The question now is whether the<br />
States will take the lead from the Commonwealth and cut<br />
their spending. I hope they will.<br />
Make no mistake, the States have done very well out of the<br />
Commonwealth in the past.. Under the existing agreement, the<br />
States' general revenue funds the monies the States can spend<br />
as they please rose at an average rate of 5.57% per year<br />
( even after inflation is taken into account) in the four<br />
years to 1979/ 80. Total Commonwealth budget spending grew by<br />
under per annum in real terms over the same period.<br />
Wihthsagreement about to come to an end;, we told the States<br />
in no uncertain terms that it was much too generous. The<br />
Commonwealth simply could not afford to go on treating the<br />
States better than it is treating itself. What we are doing<br />
now is asking them to bear a small decline, in real terms, in<br />
their tax sharing funds; they will still increase by 9% in money<br />
terms. Thereafter they will receive a share of total Commonwealth<br />
tax revenues.<br />
Under this new arrangement, the States will fare no better and no<br />
worse than the Commonwealth itself. They will be insulated<br />
from changes in the relative importance of the different sorts<br />
of tax. If past experience is any guide, their revenue will be<br />
more stable than if they were linked only to personal incometax<br />
receipts where is the injustice in-that?<br />
It almost seemed as if the Commonwealth went into the Premiers'<br />
Conference as the sole representative of the Australian taxpayer.<br />
In our view the taxpayer is already carrying too heavy a burden<br />
and the time has come to protect the taxpayer against the<br />
ever-growing demands of government. We succeeded in our aim<br />
at the Premiers' Conference.*<br />
We have put the brakes on the uncontrolled public spending<br />
spree. Without that, there would be no hope of genuine tax<br />
relief in the forseeable future. o000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
