<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9317</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J KEATING MP LAUNCH OF THE OPEN LEARNING AGENCY OF AUSTRALIA&#039;S INTERNATIONAL TELEVISION PRODUCTION &quot;THE GLOBAL ECONOMY&quot;,PARLIAMENT HOUSE,CANBERRA,16 AUGUST 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009317.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
LAUNCH OF THE OPEN LEARNING AGENCY OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
INTERNATIONAL TELEVISION PRODUCTION " THE GLOBAL<br />
ECONOMY", PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 16 AUGUST 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you very much indeed Tony ( Pritchard), as Executive Director of Open<br />
Learning, Professor Logan, Vice-Chancellor of Monash and David Hill,<br />
Managing Director of the ABC and other distinguished representatives of the<br />
Embassies that Tony has mentioned and other people who have been<br />
dramatically involved with the Open Learning Initiative and ladies and<br />
gentlemen. Well this, of course, is not the only launch today. But, I'll bet pounds to<br />
peanuts this one has a longer term influence on Australia than the other one.<br />
And, particularly as we are now, I think, as a country so well placed to<br />
understand what multi media combinations can do, what telecommunications<br />
technology is capable of, to understand that in these instruments we have a<br />
device, which fashioned properly, can extend particularly educational<br />
learning opportunities to thousands, indeed millions, of people who wouldn't<br />
otherwise have had these opportunities available to them.<br />
Australia is, I think, at the forefront of technology change in the western<br />
world, particularly in the OECD area, and in my notes there is a reference to<br />
the fact that of a survey done recently of many countries in the region, the<br />
survey showed that Australians felt more comfortable with technological<br />
change than was the case with many of the communities in our region. A<br />
chart in the Far Eastern Economic Review last week showed that Australia<br />
was.-tbe.... ority-regional. country comfortable with the rate of technological<br />
change. By contrast, the people of South Korea, Taiwan, the Philippines,<br />
Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Hong Kong, Thailand and Japan all thought<br />
the rate of technological change was too fast.<br />
I think this is a very encouraging statistic and, I think, it is particularly as we<br />
are now starting to learn about broad banded services and convergence and<br />
that in not so many years from now we'll work, learn, shop, play and </p>
<p>communicate in ways most of us can't today imagine. We've already<br />
developed and are developing networks in Australia and, of course, anyone<br />
who goes to automatic teller machines knows that that is so. And, in its<br />
myriad forms the information highway has found its way into Australian<br />
schools and universities already, into libraries and hospitals, into government<br />
departments like DEET, into local governments, and as a consequence, we<br />
are really starting to understand its spread and its opportunity.<br />
It is for that reason, with some substantial pleasure that I established, last<br />
year, the Broad Band Services Expert Group headed by Brian Johns whose<br />
interim report I have now just received. It is a very good report. I think<br />
everybody who wants a window into the future should read it. It is an exciting<br />
report and one which for all the challenges it presents, should give us<br />
confidence that Australia can be at the forefront of change in the global<br />
economy and the information highway, because of the fact that we have<br />
natural skills in content, in software, just as today we are launching the<br />
telecourse " Global Economy". That kind of software product is the sort of<br />
thing that Australians are capable of and the information highway is going to<br />
be very much about content. The debate now is principally about hardware<br />
and whether the cable is going to be rolled out here or there or how many<br />
channels can be put on it, but it is essentially about content and we are a<br />
content strong country and education has been one of our greatest strengths<br />
and one of our primary strengths and it's a matter of exceeding pleasure to<br />
me that our educational institutions are right into the information highway and<br />
the opportunities to advance learning via these particular technologies.<br />
So, it is against that background I am very pleased to be here today to launch<br />
the " Global Economy" and it is, I think, a great example of the quality<br />
intellectual merit and international co-operation rolled into one. Let me at this<br />
point congratulate the three major Australian players in the enterprise. The<br />
ABC whose staff made this co-production with their United States, Swedish<br />
and Dutch partners such a success. Monash University and in particular<br />
Professor Richard Snape and his colleagues for their distinguished academic<br />
contribution and Open Learning for showing that co-operative endeavour and<br />
higher education can produce material equal to any in the world.<br />
So, " Global Economy" I think we can say, is a truly global product produced,<br />
in the main, by Australians and it will earn export dollars for Australia and<br />
more than that it will present to the world the face of Australia in the 1 990s. A<br />
country with a global perspective and a pervasive belief in learning and<br />
innovation. Tony. -Pr4thard-said-An -This-introductory -remarks that the " Global Economy"<br />
and, in a sense, the distance learning movement are heralds of the future.<br />
And, when Peter Baldwin first approached me in 1992 about Open Learning<br />
and the Open Learning Initiative I thought there was a great opportunity here<br />
to establish a facility whereby we could encourage students who may have<br />
not qualified for matriculation, who may not for any number of reasons been<br />
able to go on to university at a particular time, that we could by the Open<br />
Learning Initiative develop curricula where students could join it and, that is, </p>
<p>anyone could enrol in a course regardless of their background, prior<br />
experience or educational qualifications and having then succeeded in<br />
picking up units in the course, if they wish, stream themselves back into<br />
mainstream campus activities. In other words, they get a second go, a<br />
second shot at education.<br />
You see how the Government is thinking in these terms. First of all the high<br />
participation rates in schools, the additional places in tertiary institutions,<br />
then spreading open learning beyond that as a catchment for people who<br />
may have dropped out of the system and then building beside the universities<br />
the TAFE system so that in vocational education there could also be career<br />
opportunities mapped out. Tomorrow we are speaking about that very thing,<br />
that is, how students in Years 11 and 12 can start to take on units in TAFE, to<br />
start streaming themselves and get TAFE accreditation for their longer run<br />
education. So, there is an exciting panoply of options there and a large part of that, I<br />
think, apart from just the primary strengths of the participation and the higher<br />
commitment to places in tertiary institutions in this country, I think, that the<br />
Open Learning Initiative and Open Learning has a tremendous potential and<br />
particularly for students who don't, because of parental circumstances or<br />
geographical circumstances, can't find it easy for themselves to get<br />
themselves into mainstream tertiary education or tertiary institutions.<br />
Now, the White Paper on employment and growth Working Nation was<br />
also at pains to stress Australia's future depends on ideas, skills and<br />
knowledge of the workforce. And, if we are to be a high value added export<br />
oriented economy, we need to continually upgrade our skills and we will also<br />
need to find new and more effective ways of developing skills into the future.<br />
In all of this, I think, it is incumbent upon us to take responsibility for our own<br />
learning and this is where, I think, distance learning again comes through<br />
with flying colours. Through distance learning programs such as Open<br />
Learning anyone interested can learn about economics through productions<br />
such as this one or learn a language, gain skills in statistics and marketing or<br />
learn more about our own history.<br />
One of distant learning's great strengths is that it can help break down the<br />
artificial barriers between various education and training sectors. It is going<br />
to take a lot of the, if you like, formality and structure out of our educational<br />
structures and institutions. Just as businesses are increasingly making use<br />
of outsourcing and telecommuting, Open Learning is increasingly utilising<br />
information technologies and telecommunication advances to expand<br />
educationraI--services in-the -home and"-, he office. Distance learning<br />
techniques have also important applications for entry level training, for youth<br />
education as I made a point a moment ago, and for the training market in<br />
general. I was very pleased to see the ABC's rivals at SBS offering<br />
vocational oriented training in diverse fields such as health, education and<br />
journalistic ethics. I could make a little contribution to that software package<br />
myself, maybe that's something I can do later. </p>
<p>Not surprisingly, Open Learning's flexibility and strong client focus, I mean, I<br />
think these words are important flexibility and strong client focus pose<br />
challenge for our more traditional educational institutions. I think that is why,<br />
I mean, I'm not just simply mouthing words here saying, I think, that is why it<br />
is exceedingly encouraging that the main stream institutions are interested in<br />
this challenge. The challenge being posed for flexibility and a stronger client<br />
focus away from formal structures. Students can now study at times which<br />
suit them and they can study in various settings. It doesn't matter if you are<br />
from a rural area or you want to study specialist subjects not taught nearby or<br />
have disabilities that prevent easy access to classroom study Open<br />
Learning comes to you. And, the fact that of course it lets anybody enrol,<br />
makes quality education more accessible to the many groups in society not<br />
well served by traditional forms of education and it gives access to Australia's<br />
best institutions, lecturers and tutors.<br />
Open Learning is inclusive accessible learning, but we want to make it even<br />
more accessible and that is why the second stage of the Government's Open<br />
Learning Initiative is the new Electronic Support Service. This service will<br />
enable students to communicate with tutors and other students through<br />
electronic mail to search library catalogues and to access course and<br />
administrative information.<br />
Eventually, the service will enable educational institutions and industry to<br />
access national and international education and training programs for use in<br />
workplace training. We can already see that with programs such as Internet<br />
where people are already accessing Internet and drawing quite a lot of data<br />
out of it for particular areas of educational research.<br />
Access points will be established in community based centres around<br />
Australia to ensure that all students have access to the service. I mean, I just<br />
think this is a terribly exciting thing that a student can go to a point in a<br />
suburb and then have this communication with a tutor or the institution in the<br />
broad. By putting Australian education and training onto the information super<br />
highways it will put more education and training at the fingertips of more<br />
Australians. And, of course, I think we all know that our future as a country is<br />
going to be more and more in areas of added value, of education, of change,<br />
of continual retraining and, of course, in flexibility and less formalisation in<br />
the way education is delivered.<br />
So, it is about equipping our children with the education, skills and<br />
infrastructure-that-wi l-allowthem-to create a future for themselves. It is about<br />
building a future that is more secure. So, perhaps let me conclude by saying<br />
how gratifying it is that the concept of Open Learning is gaining widespread<br />
acceptance. Its educational advantages are quickly being recognised, but it<br />
doesn't surprise me as I have said many times in recent years, this country is<br />
profoundly capable of change for the better and the embrace of change in<br />
Australia in the last decade or so has, I think, been profound and why should<br />
we not think that we can meet the challenge of the revolution in information </p>
<p>and in technology when we so successfully have met the challenge of the<br />
global economy? When we are successfully meeting the challenge of the<br />
region. When we have learned that there is nothing to fear and so much to<br />
gain from having the courage to embrace change and the wit to manage it.<br />
So much to lose by retreating from it.<br />
But, providing such a practical and positive answer to these rhetorical<br />
questions, I thank the Open Learning Agency of Australia and all the other<br />
people associated with this production. It is a marvellous, again,<br />
collaborative initiative by the educational institutions, by the ABC, it continues<br />
to demonstrate it's changing its role in this country, by the Government, and<br />
of course, here particularly with collaboration with other production units<br />
abroad and we certainly applaud that kind of collaboration.<br />
Let me congratulate all involved, particularly the three people represented<br />
here on the rostrum for getting out there and catching the wave that is now<br />
with us that lets Australians say that the information highway is a great<br />
opportunity for Australia, that we are strong in education and we are strong<br />
on software and that we will master this technology and be first amongst<br />
equals in getting out there on the highway with the sort of products as we've<br />
seen today. But in doing that, make sure that that highway starts at home<br />
and that the first wave of people to benefit from it are Australians who can<br />
take up thes opportunities that formalised structures in the past have denied<br />
them. Congratulations to one and all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
