<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9164</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP THE HON ALAN GRIFFITHS - INQUIRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009164.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
12,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
THE HON ALAN GRIFFITHS INQUIRY<br />
When I announced Mr Griffiths' resignation from the ministry on 22 January I<br />
said that I intended granting his request for an independent inquiry to<br />
determine whether his conduct had met appropriate standards of ministerial<br />
behaviour. I also said I had informed Mr Griffiths that I would advise Caucus<br />
not to fill the vacancy caused by his resignation until after the investigation<br />
was concluded.<br />
I now understand that the Director of Public Prosecutions ( DPP) has<br />
approved the laying of criminal charges arising from the Australian Federal<br />
Police investigation into matters upon which Mr Griffiths had provided<br />
information to the AFP. The police investigation found no evidence of<br />
criminal offences by Mr Griffiths, and accordingly no charge has been laid<br />
against him.<br />
The Attorney-General's Department has advised that until court action in<br />
relation to charges which have been laid is complete it would be<br />
inappropriate for a government-appointed inquiry into Mr Griffiths' conduct to<br />
proceed if it would hamper the defence by a person of any charges pending<br />
in the courts. I am advised that, even if this were not the case the DPP would<br />
be concerned if persons who were witnesses in a pending criminal case were<br />
also being asked to give evidence about the same issues to an administrative<br />
inquiry. I am of course concerned at the delay implied by this advice, particularly<br />
because I am aware that Mr Griffiths is anxious to have these matters<br />
disposed of and his future resolved as soon as possible. In the<br />
circumstances, however, I have decided that while the independent inquiry<br />
can now begin it should restrict itself, until relevant criminal cases are<br />
concluded, to matters which can be investigated without hampering any<br />
person's defence or taking evidence from potential witnesses in those cases. </p>
<p>The terms of reference of the inquiry are as follows:<br />
Whether the conduct of the Hon Alan Griffiths in relation to the matters<br />
leading to his resignation from the ministry was in accordance with<br />
appropriate standards of behaviour for a person holding office as minister<br />
and a member of parliament and, in particular:<br />
whether there was any conflict between his private interests and the<br />
performance of his public duties and;<br />
whether he authorised or condoned any inappropriate, improper or illegal<br />
activity by any of his staff in relation to the conduct of his private interests.<br />
The inquiry is entitled to adopt any findings made by other official inquiries if<br />
it appears sensible to do so. In case other matters arise which appear to<br />
bear on Mr Griffiths' fitness to hold ministerial office, but which do not fall<br />
strictly within the above terms of reference, the inquiry will have discretion to<br />
inquire or not, depending upon its judgment of the relevance, seriousness<br />
and substance of such matters.<br />
The inquiry will be conducted by Mr Michael Codd, AC, who has wide<br />
experience in and knowledge of issues related to ministerial conduct and<br />
propriety. Mr Codd was Secretary of the Department of Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations from 1981 to 1983, Chairman of the Industries Assistance<br />
Commission from 1983 to 1985 and then became Secretary of the<br />
Department of Community Services, before being appointed Secretary of the<br />
Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet in 1986.<br />
I am attaching a copy of a letter I have today sent Mr Griffiths informing him<br />
of the inquiry. Also attached is a copy of my letter to Mr Codd.<br />
CANBERRA 23 MARCH 1994 </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
2 3 MAR 1994<br />
The Hon Alan Griffiths, MP'<br />
Member for Maribyrnong<br />
Parliament House<br />
CANBERRA ACT 2600<br />
Dear Alan,<br />
I am writing to you to confirm our discussions concerning the inquiry into the<br />
circumstances leading to your resignation from the ministry.<br />
As I indicated to you, the situation is such that the inquiry will not be able to proceed<br />
as quickly as we both initially had hoped.<br />
In the light of this I appreciate your willingness to accept that it is now necessary for<br />
the proper functioning of the Government to proceed to fill the ministerial vacancy<br />
which had previously been held open pending the outcome of the inquiry.<br />
Once the inquiry is complete and if its findings, as you expect, are that your conduct<br />
was not such as to call into question your fitness for ministerial office, it is my intention<br />
to facilitate your return to the ministry at the earliest opportunity.<br />
P J KEAT' </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBERRA<br />
2 3 MAR 1994~<br />
Mr Michael H Codd, AC<br />
RMB Monaro Highway<br />
WILLIAkMSDALE NSW 2620<br />
Dear Mr Codd<br />
I am writing to request you to inquire into and report on whether the conduct of the<br />
Hon Alan Griffiths in relation to the matters leading to his resignation from the<br />
ministry was in accordance with appropriate standards of behaviour for a person<br />
holding office as a minister and a member of parliament and, in particular:<br />
Whether there was any conflict between his private interests and the performance<br />
of his public duties<br />
Whether he authorised or condoned any inappropriate, improper or illegal activity<br />
by any of his staff in relation to the conduct of his private interests<br />
In inquiring into the above matters, you are entitled to adopt any findings made by<br />
other official inquiries if it appears sensible to do so. In case other matters arise which<br />
appear to bear on Mr Griffiths's fitness to hold ministerial office, but which do not fall<br />
strictly within the above terms of reference, you will have discretion to inquire or not,<br />
depending upon your judgment of the relevance, seriousness and substance of such<br />
matters. The Attorney-General's Department has advised that until court actions in relation to<br />
criminal charges are complete it would be inappropriate for a governmient-appointed<br />
inquiry into Mr Griffiths's conduct to proceed if it would hamper the defence by a<br />
person of any such charges. I am advised that, even if this were not the case the DPP<br />
would be concerned if persons who were witnesses in a pending criminal case were<br />
also being asked to give evidence about the same issues to an administrative inquiry.<br />
I am of course concerned at the delay implied by this advice, particularly because I am<br />
aware that Mr Griffiths is anxious to have these matters disposed of and his future<br />
resolved as soon as possible. In the circumstances, however, I have decided that while<br />
your inquiry can begin you should restrict yourself initially to matters which can be<br />
investigated without hampering any person's defence or taking evidence from potential<br />
witnesses in those cases. </p>
<p>You will not have any special powers of compulsion in relation to the giving of<br />
evidence or the production of documents, but you will have access to official records<br />
in the relevant agencies of the Commonwealth. Your inquiry should be conducted in<br />
an inquisitorial rather than adversarial manner. It would be appropriate for you to<br />
invite submissions from parties who may have information that would be useful to the<br />
inquiry.<br />
You will have access to legal resources, including the legal resources of the Attorney-<br />
General's Department. Mr Rose, the Secretary of the Department, is available to<br />
discuss with you the precise nature of the assistance you may require, for example in<br />
relation to the conduct of interviews.<br />
Persons interviewed in the course of the inquiry should be permitted if they so desire,<br />
to have their legal representatives present during such interviews, with the right to<br />
make submissions on their behalf should they so wish. The government will consider<br />
any applications that may be made to it for financial assistance for such legal<br />
representation by persons centrally involved.<br />
You may also wish to consider the desirability before finalising your report, of<br />
affording affected individuals the opportunity of responding to any adverse<br />
conclusions you may have reached.<br />
I am attaching a copy of a media release in which I have outlined the above matters. I<br />
would be grateful if you could begin the inquiry as soon as possible, subject to the<br />
limitations I have indicated above, and provide me with your report within three<br />
months of completion of the prosecution actions involving people associated with<br />
these matters.<br />
PJ KEATING I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
