<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1915</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 80/1968 - VISIT OF THE PRESIDENT OF KOREA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/09/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001915.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 80/ 1968<br />
VIS IT OF THE PRESIDENT OF KOREA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
President Park Chung He6 of the Republic of Korea, and<br />
Madame Park, accompanied by an Off icial Suite of 15, including three<br />
Cabinet Ministers, will make a State Visit to Australia from 16 to 19<br />
September. The President and his wife and party are scheduled to<br />
arrive at R. A. A. F. Base, Fairbairn at 10. 00 a. mi on 16 September<br />
and will be given a 21-gun salute. They will be welcomed by the<br />
Governor-General, Lord Casey and The Lady Casey and by myself and<br />
my wife. The President will leave for Sydney on the morning of<br />
18 September and will depart for New Zealand the following day.<br />
Australia and the Republic of Korea enjoy cordial relations<br />
and share many mutual interests. President and Madame Park will be<br />
welcome visitors to Australia.<br />
PROGRAMMF, FOR CANBERRA<br />
Monday 16 September<br />
Morning: President and Madame Park arrive at R. A. A. F. Base, Fairbairn<br />
and after a ceremonial welcome leave for the Hotel Canberra-Rex<br />
where they will stay. After a formal call by the Prime Minister<br />
and Mrs. Gorton, the President and Madame Park will leave for<br />
Government House where they will be received by the Governor-<br />
General and The Lady Casey. Later they will meet Heads of<br />
Diplomatic Missions and their wives and then proceed to the<br />
residence of the Ambassador of Korea for Lunch.<br />
Afternoon: No official engagements.<br />
Evening: The President and Madame Park will attend Dinner at Government<br />
House. Tuesday 17 September<br />
Morning: The President visits the Australian War Memorial and lays a wreath<br />
on the Stone of Remembrance.<br />
Madame Park inspects the Marymead Children's Centre.<br />
The President visits Parliament House for discussions with the<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet Ministers, after which he will be<br />
the guest of the Government at luncheon.<br />
Madame Park will be the guest of Mrs. Gorton for lunch at The Lodge. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Afternoon: Evening: The Leader of the Federal Opposition, Mr. Gough Whitlam,<br />
will call on the President.<br />
Dinner given by the President and Madame Park.<br />
Wednesday 18 September<br />
Morning: The President and Madame Park leave for Sydney.<br />
Please Note: Details of President Park's programme in Sydney will be<br />
given by the New South Wales Premier's Department.<br />
CANBERRA 12 September 1968 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
