<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7456</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, YOUTH ACCESS CENTRE, LIVERPOOL - 17 JANUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007456.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, YOUTH ACCESS CENTRE,<br />
LIVERPOOL 17 JANUARY 1989<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you feel about that reception you got<br />
today? PM: The reception from the people inside was marvellous.<br />
I take no notice of those outside.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think you're going to be stuck with<br />
it through the election campaign though?<br />
PM: Well it doesn't worry me if I am. I mean that's<br />
reflecting upon the people who in the Australian<br />
vernacular what's happened, those people picked a fight,<br />
they lost it and they're behaving very badly. Now that's<br />
how it's perceived by the Australian people. I take no<br />
notice of that performance at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: They say the fight's not over.<br />
PM: Well it may not be for them.<br />
JOURNALIST: It sounds like you're speaking as if the<br />
pilot issue is still a vote winner perhaps for the Hawke<br />
O Government. PM: I'm not thinking of it as a vote winner or a vote<br />
loser. It's a non-event. It is a non-event. I mean I<br />
take no notice of it whatsoever. If they want to<br />
dissipate their energies like this well that's up to<br />
them. It's a democratic country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you pleased by the poll the Herald<br />
printed this morning?<br />
PM: Well yes but I don't get carried away by polls. The<br />
honest thing obviously to say is any politician prefers<br />
to be in front in the polls. I mean you'd be silly to<br />
deny that<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible) </p>
<p>PM: Just let me finish. So I'm happy that we're in<br />
front on that. But I don't get carried away by it. I<br />
have been confident without being complacent all along.<br />
I think that the as I was saying here today in opening<br />
this Youth Access Centre with Peter Duncan that the<br />
people going to be carried away by platitudes that<br />
come from the conservatives about their concern with<br />
families. They had their chance. They had seven years<br />
in office and they just threw the kids of the families<br />
onto the unemployment scrapheap. They denied them<br />
education. They denied them training. What we've been<br />
doing is providing them with jobs, providing them with<br />
education, providing them with training the real things<br />
that the young people of this country need. And we're<br />
going to keep on doing that and will keep on doing it. I<br />
just am confident that the people will make the<br />
appropriate judgement on the facts.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your response to Mr Howard's policy<br />
yesterday? PM: Mr Howard's policy? I'm not aware of Mr Howard's.<br />
There's been a palace coup again has there? A palace<br />
coup. There was no policy yesterday. I mean put<br />
that out months ago. Nothing new.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you tell us the outcome of yesterday's<br />
talks on the logging issue?<br />
PM: No, what I did was to have talks with Mr Kerin and<br />
Senator Cook and Senator Richardson. And on the basis of<br />
those talks Senator Cook went and had discussions with Mr<br />
Causley. Those were preliminary discussions. They are<br />
still going on. I hope that out of those discussions<br />
we'll get a sensible and agreed outcome which means that<br />
we can get a proper balance between the responsibility<br />
that both governments have for protecting the environment<br />
and also trying to ensure that the employment<br />
opportunities are maintained. I think that the<br />
discussions that were held yesterday, those preliminary<br />
discussions, may lead us to that position. I hope so.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, back on the opinion poll. It did<br />
show an erosion, or a potential erosion of seats for the<br />
Labor Party in Victoria. Are you worried about the union<br />
dispute going on down there that that could exaccerbate<br />
that? PM: I would hope it wouldn't go on. I mean obviously<br />
again the honest answer is to say that a continuation of<br />
that dispute couldn't be helpful. But I believe that it<br />
will be resolved fairly quickly from what I've been told.<br />
I </p>
<p>-3-<br />
JOURNALIST: The Liberals have been getting quite a lot<br />
of coverage recently. Do you feel as though they've got<br />
a head start in the campaign?<br />
PM: No. Well that's a judgement that they will have to<br />
make. It doesn't seem to be doing them very much good.<br />
But they'll make their judgements about how they conduct<br />
themselves and their timing. I'll make my judgement<br />
about how I conduct myself and what our pace and pattern<br />
of campaigning is. That's the way it should be.<br />
JOURNALIST: If the Papua New Guinean Government asks Mr<br />
Beazley for military assistance while he's over there, do<br />
you think Australia should be giving it?<br />
PM: That's a hypothetical question isn't it? Let me say<br />
this, that we are very concerned with the developments in<br />
Bougainville. My Ministers who will be up there will<br />
have the opportunity of getting the latest rundown from<br />
my friend the Prime Minister, Rabble Namaliu, and they<br />
will be coming back to report to me on those discussions<br />
they have up there. We will make our judgements about<br />
what ought to happen as far as Australia is concerned.<br />
But Australia is not going to be I can assure you<br />
involved in a military sense with personnel up there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is Badgery's Creek going ahead as an<br />
international airport?<br />
PM: Well the decisions have been made about the<br />
international airport needs of Australia in general and<br />
NSW in particular. You know that we've made the decision<br />
in regard to the third runway. The inquiries are going<br />
on there. We said at the time that there would be a<br />
development at Badgery's Creek subsequently. That<br />
remains the case.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think many pilots reside in Liverpool<br />
Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: It doesn't look like it. The people of Liverpool<br />
clear and precise judgement about what they thought<br />
of their performance. I won't use the language that the<br />
local residents used to me about them but it was very<br />
uncomplimentary. ends<br />
I I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
