<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2587</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA - PRESIDENT NIXON&#039;S DECISIONS ON VIETNAM - 9 MAY 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/05/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002587.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CH. MP, IN THE HOUSE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA<br />
PRESIDENT NIXON'S DECISIONS ON VIETNAM<br />
9 MAY, 1972<br />
I refer to the important decisions which President Nixon<br />
has been obliged to take in the present very serious situation in<br />
Vietnam. These decisions were taker because of the blatant invasion<br />
of South Vietnam by the North Vietnamese, supported by outside<br />
Governments. Not only has there been this invasion of South Vietnam<br />
across the Demilitarized Zone, but the North Vietnamese forces have<br />
been carrying on offensive military operations in Laos and the Khmer<br />
Republic for a period of years.<br />
The Australian Government strongly condemns North Vietnam and<br />
its associates. It is they who must take the complete moral<br />
responsibility for these actions.<br />
The United States has made with full Australian supportevery<br />
effort to bring about a negotiated settlement of the present<br />
conflict. These efforts have met with an absolute refusal by North<br />
Vietnam to negotiate seriously. The United States has also tried to<br />
de-escalate the fighting by progressively withdrawing its forces from<br />
Vietnam. The response from Hanoi has been the launching of a<br />
long and carefully planned invasion.<br />
The Australian Government understands and supports the<br />
decisions which the President has fel-t compelled to take.<br />
in our view, the United States had done everything in its<br />
power t'' o ensure a negotiated settlement and to maintain the independen,<br />
of South Vietnam and not to abandon the people of that country. The<br />
present decisions by the United States reflect its determination to<br />
stand by its international obligations and alliances. The United<br />
States must also avoid endangering the lives of its own forces in<br />
Vietnam. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
