<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1137</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M.NO. 58/1965  INDEPENDENCE OF SOUTH VIET NAM STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/07/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001137.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. m. No. 58/ 196~<br />
INDEPEN~ DENCE OF SOUTH VIET N4AM<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menz&amp; s<br />
The Australian Government was informed by the<br />
United States Government of the further decisions now announced<br />
in Washington by the President for the defence of South Viet Nam.<br />
The Government has in fact been in continuing touch with<br />
Washington about the course of United States policy, and I have<br />
already conveyed to Presjcbnt Johnson o1ir support for these<br />
further efforts by the United States to preserve the independence<br />
of South Viet Nam. I have also assured him of Australia's<br />
continuing assistance in the defence of South Viet Nam.<br />
The armed forces of South Viet Nam, the population<br />
centres in the rural areas and the col. mtry's installations and<br />
transport and communications systems are currently under<br />
heavy military pressure and attack from the Viet Cong. At<br />
the same time, the Viet Cong, in pursuing their campaign of<br />
insurgency and guerrilla warfare, are strengthened and<br />
supported by the supply of men and equipment from North Viet<br />
Nam on a substantial scale. The South Vietnamese Armed Forces<br />
are maintaining their courageous efforts to counter these tactics<br />
but it is clear that additional assistance from outside is<br />
necessary. We support also the steady purpose of the United<br />
States to pursue every political and diplomatic effprt to<br />
open the way for international discussion. de earnestly<br />
hope that these further evidences of United States' resolve<br />
will help convince those now seeking to overthrow by force<br />
the Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam that they<br />
cannot succeed and that there will be an end to the senseless<br />
violence and bloodshed opening the way for a peaceful solution<br />
in Viet Nam.<br />
MELBOURNE, 29th July, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
