<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7796</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, ARGYLE WOOLSHED, THE ROCKS 3 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007796.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTERj<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, ARGYLE WOOLSHED, THE HOCKS,<br />
3 NOVEMBER 1989<br />
ZE&amp; O0E-PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the Greiner Government's industrial<br />
package, do you see that as undermining the accord?<br />
PM: well it's based on a totally different philosophy to<br />
the accord and I guess the best thing in politics is not<br />
just to have an ideological harangue about you know, mine's<br />
better than yours, but to look at the record. I simply say<br />
that under the accord these things have happened. Firstly,<br />
we've reduced industrial disputation by 60%. We've had a<br />
rate of job creation which is five times faster than under<br />
the previous policy, which is a reflection of the Greiner<br />
type policy. So that difference is remarkable. we've<br />
created jobs five times faster than the conservatives did,<br />
we're creating jobs more than twice as fast as the rest of<br />
the world, we've increased our competitive position. After<br />
all, it's not surprising because if you have a policy which<br />
is based upon the concept of trying to get employees and<br />
employers to see their shared interests and work<br />
accordingly, it's much more likely to work than one which is<br />
essentially confrontationist in its concept. so I'm<br />
prepared to rest on the record in these matters.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you and Graham Richardson have had<br />
some big wins in terms of the environment vote recently.<br />
Hag John Kerin undone all that in the last week?<br />
PM: No. Let me take the premise of your question and then<br />
answer the question. it's not a point of saying that Bob<br />
Hawke and Graham Richardson have had big wins on the<br />
environment. I mean the winners out of the decisions that<br />
we've taken are Australians. They are the one's that have<br />
won. if you look at those decisions without being<br />
exhaustive about them, putting onto the world heritage list<br />
of the forests in Tasmania, the rainforests in northern<br />
Queensland, Kakadu, if you look at all those things they are<br />
not wins for Richardson or Hawke, what's it really meant is<br />
that our kids today and the kids of the next generations are<br />
being guaranteed by those decisions the opportunity of<br />
enjoying the marvels of our environment and not only our<br />
kids but for the people of the world because we are a world<br />
which is increasingly one where peple move between<br />
countries. So the winners are the future generations. Now<br />
coming to the point about john Kerin, it would obviously be<br />
dishonest of me if I were to say, ' oh, that doesn't make any<br />
difference'. It was a bit unfortunate in the expression<br />
because that would give some sort of impression of some </p>
<p>-2-<br />
( PM cont) basic division in the Government, there isn't.<br />
What you ' ve got to understand is that one of the things that<br />
gets under John Kerin's goat a bit is the sort of thing<br />
we're witnessing at the moment. But there is a sort of<br />
extremism amongst some elements of the conservation movement<br />
and that rather upsets John Kerin. Let Me say this about<br />
Kerin, I know him well, he is a man who is very much<br />
concerned with the environment, he is somewhat concerned<br />
that according to his perceptions some people in the<br />
conservation movement and perhaps some people in the Labor<br />
movement weren't looking, as he saw it, at all the<br />
considerations which must go into a decision, economic<br />
considerations as well as environmental. So the fact that<br />
John expressed things the way he did has probably upset a<br />
few people. But I've had a long yarn wit h John last night<br />
and it was a very cordial yarn and I think that we'll have<br />
no difficulty in maintaining a position of unity and commity<br />
within the Government. Just to conclude what has been a<br />
fairly long answer, but it's an Important question, I've<br />
said in the Parliament this; that I have always regarded the<br />
argument that development on the one hand, environment on<br />
the other, as being necessarily opposed to one another is<br />
not the right way of looking at it. Look at our record,<br />
we've done two things. one, we've had a rate of economic<br />
growth which is twice as fast as it was before, we've<br />
created jobs more than twice as fast as the rest of the<br />
world. So on the development side, we've shown what can<br />
happen. But at the same time as that we have the world<br />
Heritage Bureau coming out and saying that no government has<br />
done more to advance world heritage values than this<br />
government. so you can do both and that's what the secret<br />
of government is in this important area, to listen to the<br />
debate, to allow people to express their views and their<br />
concerns and in the end make the decisions which are going<br />
to give you ecologically sustainable development.<br />
JOURNALIST: breaking one of the basic principles of<br />
Cabinet, though?<br />
PM1: No, Mr Kerin has accepted and does accept the decisions<br />
of Cabinet and he made that clear publicly and he said that<br />
he believes that his position has been misrepresented in. the<br />
media, I'm not blaming the media about that, but he believes<br />
that they haven't got the balance correctly in their<br />
reporting of what he said. He accepts the cabinet<br />
decisions, there's no question about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you tell him then to stop talking about mr<br />
Richardson? FM%: No, I didn't need to say that. He said that he felt<br />
that held made the points he wanted to make and he's not<br />
going to be saying anything more.<br />
JOURNALIST: What your Government's performance in the<br />
Parliament this week? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: Well let me say this, and I'm not avoiding that<br />
question, i can assure you. we've been in government now<br />
for nearly seven years. Everyone knows that for virtually<br />
the whole of that period we've dominated in the Parliament,<br />
we've dominated the political agenda. Now that's not a<br />
proud Prime Minister saying it, that is common knowledge.<br />
Now it is the case that we've had a less than glorious week<br />
and the fact that we have predominated for nearly seven<br />
years has made that sort of aberration the more obvious.<br />
Now we could've done very much better-' this week, all of us,<br />
and I include myself in that. We all could've done very<br />
much better. But let me say this; I'm in one sense not<br />
unhappy because it will show me, it will show my ministers<br />
that we have to be on our toes all the time, We can't take<br />
for granted a permanent ineptitude on the part of the<br />
Opposition. it is a terminal condition for them, they are<br />
basically driven by internal hatred and divisions. As Mr<br />
Howard has said at the beginning of this week, Howard and<br />
Peacock can't trust one another. That's symtematic of their<br />
divisions. But we can't just as a government assume that<br />
these fundamental hatreds and distrusts are going to be<br />
reflected in an easy path for us. So we didn't have a great<br />
week but I can tell you what, we'll murder them in the<br />
months ahead.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you worried about what the polls say?<br />
PM: Now again# it would be quite dishonest if I were to say<br />
I don't look at the polls or watch them closely, I do. I<br />
would prefer to be in a position of being a little bit<br />
better off in the polls at the moment. But I remind you of<br />
1986, we were in the polls in a much worse position then<br />
than we are now and I tell you what, you watch us between<br />
now and where the election date is concerned. we're in the<br />
Spring Carnival period when everyone's interested in racing<br />
and punting and I'll tell you what, I'll tell you who to<br />
have your money on, mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you worried about your backbmnchers<br />
comments though?<br />
PM: Now am I worried about the backbenchers comments? what<br />
I am a little bit worried about is the standard of<br />
journalism. Now I may say that the Gallery in Canberra's a<br />
little bit upset about that performance. What you do is you<br />
ring up a number of people, you get one to make a comment<br />
and you make a headline out of that about Hawke being a<br />
liability. Well I tell you what, you do a check of my<br />
backbenc hers<br />
JOURNALIST: As a member of the Gallery-<br />
PM: And a very fine member too.<br />
JOURNALIST: You're too kind. What about the Howe-Keating<br />
stuff? </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM: The Howe-Keating stuff?<br />
JOURNALIST: On the possibility of a<br />
PMt Sure. OK well I'll try to make this as brief as<br />
possible. The question about the comment that was reported<br />
by Brianl Howe earlier in the week about the possibility of a<br />
wage/ tax trade off, I said in the Parliament yesterday that<br />
if you look at the period we've been in government, what<br />
we've done is to have as the basis of economic policy making<br />
an effect ive wages policy. An effective wages policy<br />
involves consultations with the trade union movement. The<br />
essential feature of that has been that the trade union<br />
movement has been prepared to exercise restraint in their<br />
money wage claims on the basis that the Government will<br />
increase and improve the social wage so that that is a<br />
compensation for excessive money wage increases. Now that's<br />
been essentially what's been done and at the appropriate<br />
time within each year we've sat down and talked with the<br />
trade union movement on that basis and that's produced the<br />
sort of results that I've been talking about. Remember<br />
them, a rate of economic growth, twice as fast under us as<br />
under the conservatives in their seven years. A rate of<br />
employment creation five times as fast and 60% reduction in<br />
industrial disputes. Now what will happen as we go into<br />
1990 is that again we will sit down with the trade union<br />
movement and discuss the wages outcome for the following<br />
period and what actions by government are most likely to<br />
ensure a restrained wages outcome and benefits for the<br />
Australian community as a whole. We'll have those<br />
discussions at the appropriate time.<br />
JOURNALIST: Maintaining the high standard of Sydney<br />
journalists, can I ask you a question about this campaign?<br />
How seriously can something like this turn around<br />
Australia's current account problem?<br />
PH: It can make a contribution. As I said in there, I try<br />
to be absolutely honest about it, it's impossible to measure<br />
with precision the impact but the sorts of things that you<br />
can look 17 million people and if every purchaser in the<br />
course of a year makes a deci ' sion which involves say in the<br />
course of a year some $ 300 for an Australian product rather<br />
than the imported product, it adds up to billions of<br />
dollars. That was the point I wasitrying to make at the<br />
end, I do really hope that Australians will say, ' well here<br />
is something which I can do'. this government making<br />
decision. But I as an individual can make a decision which<br />
is going to help Australia's external position. it can be<br />
very important.<br />
JOURNALIST: backbenchers last night, Mr Hawke,<br />
concerned about some of the recent Government decisions. </p>
<p>P14; No, it's not true that I had a delegation of<br />
backbenchers last night concerned about Government<br />
decisions. What I did yesterday at one stage was to talk<br />
to some backbenchers at my invitation about the way we were<br />
going on dealing with the pharmacy issue. I hop e, i f I may<br />
say so, in respect of that that the Pharmacy Guild will see<br />
our proposal as a responsible arnd constructive one. It<br />
represents a very significant addition to the position which<br />
was left at the outcome of the Pharmacy Tribunal. it offers<br />
some $ 60M~ to pharmacists which is not only relevant in money<br />
terms, income terms, but also recognising as it should be<br />
recognised, the im~ ortance to the community of their<br />
professional standing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I have just a quick reaction to the<br />
Americans? PM: These are the talks I had with the United States<br />
Secretary of State Baker and United States Secretary of<br />
Defense Cheney. They were very useful talks, I mean that's<br />
not just a cliche, we talked for about an hour and a half.<br />
I had the benefit of listening to their exposition about<br />
developments within the Soviet Union, the Eastern Bloc,<br />
China, we exchanged views which covered almost the globe, I<br />
think you can say Again, what emerged from that is the<br />
strength, the underlyinrg strength of the relationship<br />
between our two countries. They've been kind enough to say<br />
in recent times that the relationship between our two<br />
countries has never been stronger, and that was reflected<br />
this morning. It doesn't mean that on every issue that we<br />
have exactly identical views. But our relationship is so<br />
strong that where there are some differences of emphasis<br />
we're able to express them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you raise the question of the Americans<br />
retaining 21 of their stockpile of chemical weapons after<br />
a convention?<br />
PM: That is a particular matter which is going to be<br />
discussed in the talks today and tomorrow between Gareth<br />
Evans and Secretary of State Baker. see, we only had an<br />
hour and a half this morning and we were talking about<br />
developments between the superpowers in their own relations,<br />
the developments in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe,<br />
China, Southern Africa, the Philippines, New Guinea. Just<br />
to mention some of the things we discussed, I mean you just<br />
can't go to every issue but that will be on the agenda.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think they'll come around on the<br />
Antarctic? PM: Again, that will be an issue that's going to be talked<br />
about. Oust let me briefly say this about the Antarctic; I<br />
think it simply cannot be disputed that the distance we've<br />
travelled in just the last few months is truly phenomenal.<br />
when I said just a few months ago that Australia was going<br />
to launch the initiative to establish a wilderness reserve </p>
<p>-6-<br />
( FM cont) in the Antarctic and that we would refuse to sign<br />
the minerals convention, I think it would be fair to say<br />
that there is a scepticism, cynicism, and pessimism amongst<br />
the rest of the community They said; ' well what's<br />
Australia doing?' No w what's happened since then? Firstly<br />
and most importantly, we have a foundationally strong<br />
relationship between Australia and France. we have an<br />
identity of position which we were able to advance at the<br />
Paris meeting, we now have the support of a wide range of<br />
countries and without being exhaustive about it, it includes<br />
India, Belguim, a number of countries and many of them<br />
indicating their support for the idea. This is so great<br />
that at the meeting in Paris that was held at the same time<br />
as we were in Kuala Lumpur at CHOGM, there was an agreement<br />
reached there at the Paris meeting of the Antarctic<br />
consultative group to have a special meeting next year at<br />
which the Australia proposal will be considered in detail.<br />
So we've gone a long way. Now the United States at this<br />
point is not supportive at the administration level. But<br />
it's important to note that Senator Gore has tabled a<br />
resolution which is supportive of our position and I think<br />
the great strength that we have is that with each passing<br />
month world opinion, including of course within the United<br />
States, is going to become more and more supportive of the<br />
Australian position.<br />
JOURNALIST; Mr Hfawke, on a lighter note what do you think<br />
of your singing Treasurer?<br />
PM: I didn't see it but I'm told he put on a superb<br />
performance in the Bert Newton Show and I think I'll<br />
recommend to him that he does it once a month.<br />
JOURNALSIT: Are you going to take it up?<br />
PM: Well I have always taken the view that I've got a<br />
fairly good vote winning capacity but if I had to name one<br />
thing that would guarantee a loss of votes it would be if I<br />
were to exhibit my singing prowess. I have a passionate<br />
love of music, an ear for it, but somewhere in the creation<br />
process the Almighty forget to give me a sense of tune and I<br />
don't sing very well.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, with the sponsorship for the<br />
campaign, do you think that there's more room for Australian<br />
manufacturers to get behind the campaign and perhaps chip in<br />
some money for it?<br />
PM: You can always do a bit better in terms of support from<br />
manufacturers but I think that there has to this point been<br />
very considerable support, not Just financially but when you<br />
have sixteen hundred manufacturers getting in behind it and<br />
sixteen hundred manufacturers covering some 30,000<br />
products, that's very good. I mean you don't have </p>
<p>-7-<br />
( PM cont) awareness of the campaign unless there's been a<br />
great degree of cooperation from manufacturers as well. So<br />
sure, I would like them to do more, that would be good. But<br />
the important thing for government is that governments not<br />
walk away from it and this is where we have a fundamental<br />
disagreement with the Opposition. The Opposition say they<br />
would eliminate government funding for this great campaign<br />
and we're not, we're going to keep government support and we<br />
hope that the manufacturing industry will come in<br />
financially as well.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
