<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1476</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA DAY LUNCHEON, ROYALE BALLROOM, MELBOURNE - 26TH JANUARY 1967 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001476.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIA DAY LUNCHEON<br />
ROYALE BALLROOM, LELBOURNE 26TH JANXUARY, 1967.<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT<br />
MR. HOLT:<br />
Mr. Chairman Your Excellencies Lady Delacombe Distinguished<br />
guests, and this includes my Parliamentary and Ministerial<br />
Colleagues and Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
First, Sir Norman I must congratulate you, and I do so<br />
on behalf of the Commonwealth Government, for the work that you<br />
and your colleagues are doing to bring a wider and deeper<br />
observarce of this National Birthday of ours and it must be<br />
very gratifying to you to look around at this room today and<br />
see how the initiatives which you and those with you have set<br />
in motion some years ago are now producing this wider recognition.<br />
In this part of Australia by the stimulus you have given, I<br />
believe, about Australia generally certainly in my own experience<br />
and this is perhaps not merel a product of any particular initiative<br />
of any organisation, but of the degree of progress and development<br />
and maturity that is going on inside Australia itself there is<br />
this deepening awareness of the significance of our National<br />
Birthday and the growing desire to recognise it and participate<br />
in it. The other thing which I feel you must be congratulated<br />
upon is the enterprise you have shown in making each year a<br />
selection of the man or woman who in your judgment is the Australian<br />
of the Year. I make no complaint that Parliamentarians are<br />
disbarred from this very fitting recognition. Ve get our recognition<br />
in other ways usually a three yearly interval, either favourable<br />
or unfavourable, and we get enough of the limelight anyhow, but<br />
it has been truly said that a great nation is a nation which<br />
produces great people. It doesn't have to be a large nation, or<br />
a powerful nation if it produces great people it is a great nation,<br />
and we have confidence and pride in the quality of the Australian<br />
people, and we do well to recognise those Australians who have<br />
shown such distinction in the year under review that they have<br />
earned the accolade of their fellow Austrilians and have been<br />
honoured with this proud title. You have chosen well, you have<br />
spread your choices through various fields of activity of interest<br />
and importance to us and this year's selection is well up to the<br />
high standard of your earlier selection and I offer my personal<br />
congratulations to hr. Brabham as I did when he secured the World<br />
Championship. I want to say thank you on behalf of us ill, that includes<br />
my Government and your organisation and all assembled here, indeed<br />
all to whom his warm thoughtful, generous words will come. Thanks<br />
from us all to Mr. iAelan for th. it remarkably eloquent address to<br />
us. I felt that we could not have expressed for Australia and to<br />
Australia more admirably the thin-s that we are feeling at this<br />
time, and how appropriate it is that these words should come from<br />
the representative in this city of our great Pacific partner nd<br />
ally, the United States of America.<br />
has seen ouIr satyw o tchoatu ntardiveiss edblryo ugbhetc aculsoes etrh e tyoegaert hetrh att hhaans evjeurs t beclfoosreed<br />
in their history. The tangible evidence of this is that at four<br />
separate sets Qf meetings the Heads of Jovernment of our two<br />
countries came together for our common purposes. Never before in<br />
the history of our two countries have the Heads of those Governments / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
met so often and for such common purposes as was the object of<br />
our discussions, twice in Washington, at Manila and here in<br />
Australia in the course of the year which has just closed-and<br />
that is significant, I believe, of what is occurring in this<br />
area of the world.<br />
It is of course, no accident or coincidence that these<br />
meetings should have taken place with such frequency because we,<br />
with the United States, have so much in common in this area of<br />
the world and indeed in the world at large; our common principles<br />
of democratic freedom, our adherence to principles of social justice,<br />
of a prospering world at peace, is the goal to which we constantly<br />
aspire, our common determination to play such part as we can in<br />
improving the lot of those people who live with us in the Pacific<br />
and Asian region*<br />
These are things which have held us closer together our<br />
comradeship in the issue of Vietnam, where such a massive effort<br />
has been put forward and so much sacrifice by the people of the<br />
United States in initiative which is vital to us and indeed important<br />
to the free world as a whole.<br />
You spoke, Mr. Whelan, of the influence which this small<br />
country, small in terms of population can exert and those were not<br />
fullsome or overly flattering words, because we recognise that this<br />
is a fact of modern history so far as our own country is concerned<br />
in this area of the world and various factors have combined to<br />
produce this. I discovered in my first few days of office that<br />
both President Johnson and Prime Minister Wilson were inviting<br />
me to maintain with them the same close, intimate correspondence<br />
which had been developed between them by my predecessor Sir<br />
Robert Menzies, and this surely was an indication that this small<br />
country has a voice which is valued and respected. Some times,<br />
people say, we are going American in my boyhood I used to hear<br />
people say that we used to cling to the skirts of Downing Street;<br />
we are not going American or for that matter going English we<br />
are going Australian; we are -oing Australian. That is why the<br />
Heads of these great JovernmenIs respect our views they want<br />
independent views and frank views from a friend and from an ally<br />
and that is what they received from us. I can assure you<br />
communication is frequent. It is helpful, informative sincere<br />
between us all and if helps us in the common purposes to which<br />
we aspire. And so, as this becomes more widely known around<br />
Asia and indeed throughout the world Australia s influence and prestige<br />
develops. Then we have had the task in this vast continent not<br />
always favoured by climate nor seasons nor fertility of the soil,<br />
of building one of the affluent societies of the world and you<br />
have referred to our standard of living our high standard of<br />
living. This impresses our neighbours in this area of the world,<br />
who themselves have problems of development. They seek advice<br />
technical assistance and help of various kinds from us. They<br />
don't do so with any feeling that in that way they are demeaning<br />
themselves. We have from their point of view no great power<br />
aspirations. We have no colonial past to embitter the relationship<br />
between us. And we are a frank and friendly people whom generally<br />
speaking, they find they can like. This too, helps to bulld our<br />
influence and the bridges of friendship that we can create in Asia<br />
are bridges which help us all. I could give you one short<br />
illustration. Cambodia is a country which at the present time is<br />
not supporting our policies, indeed it has no diplomatic relations<br />
with the United States of America. And so in Cambodia Australia<br />
represents the United States' interests, and in South Vietnam<br />
Australia represents the interea. ta of Cambodia. Now this is an<br />
example of the kind of thing I have in mind when I say this<br />
country can be of value and is recognised as having that value by<br />
our friends in this region of the world.<br />
It is only in comparatively recent years that we have<br />
built up our capacity for these things. In the foundation of our<br />
Federation in 1901 there was a place for a Department of External<br />
Affairs in the seven States then created. But it seemed to have </p>
<p>-3-<br />
so little to do and there was so little interest in its activities<br />
that it was abolished in 1916 and it wasn't until 1955 that we<br />
re-established a Department of External Affairs. It was in 1946<br />
that we set up our first Mission to the United Nations in New<br />
York. But since that time in the 20 years that have elapsed<br />
there has been a -rowth of the establishment of the Department<br />
from 410 personnel to 1,570 personnel. Where there were then 19<br />
posts abroad representing Australia, that is in 1946, today there<br />
are 54 and the largest number of any section of the world in which<br />
these are found is the area of Asia and South East Asia, where we<br />
have 19 posts, 18 in Europe, 7 in North and South America, 7 in<br />
Africa and 3 in the South Facific. In addition, of course, we have<br />
built up our trade posts, our immigration posts and other means of<br />
carrying Australian interests out into other countries. But you<br />
will gather that this is of comparatively recent origin. My<br />
Parliamentary colleagues will know that it wasn't so very long ago<br />
that a debate on External Affairs in our House would attract very<br />
little interest or attention. Now it is the most eagerly sought<br />
after for participation by Members of the Parliament.<br />
You spoke, Mr. Whelan, of the standards we have built<br />
up and this again illustrates how Australia can have an influence out<br />
of all proportion to its numbers. If you look at the situation in<br />
India-and I don't say this in respect of either of the two<br />
countries I mentioned in any reflection on what they are doing for<br />
themselves, we know quite clearly the problems which exist in these<br />
countries but India is a country with a population 42 times that<br />
of Australia and it has just doubled the value of gross national<br />
products of Australia. Indonesia, which has nine times the population<br />
of Australia, has a value of gross national product one third of<br />
that of Australia; and you will see that the reference made by<br />
Dr. i" helan in carrying on some remarks of mine that we have ranked<br />
among the top ten or twelve tr. iding nations of the world. This has<br />
revealed that our country, small in numbers, nevertheless has an<br />
impact both in influence and in its economic strength, its trading<br />
capacity out of all proportion to the population of our people.<br />
So we can, I believe, on this our National Birthday,<br />
feel that we are favoured people, that we have achievements behind us<br />
to which we can look with pride, yet, as the proposer of the toast<br />
so eloquently stressed, there are brighter horizons ahead for us.<br />
. e share that judgment and confidence, Mr. Whelan, we Australians<br />
believe that our tomorrows will be the greatest days of Australian<br />
history. Jiven a world of peace we cannot only expand our own<br />
country's capacity, build our population, improve our standards<br />
but make a growing contribution to the welfare of those around us.<br />
So, with that bright prospect before our eyes, with a vision<br />
of a greater Australia greater in influence, greater in strength<br />
greater in security and prosperity wve can today in all certainty<br />
say it is a happy birthday for Australia and may there be many<br />
happy returns ahead. Thank you again. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
