<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15968</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Statement with Prime Minister Yasuo Fukuda of Japan and Prime Minister Kevin Rudd, on Comprehensive Strategic, Security and Economic Partnership  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/06/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
     * On 12 June 2008, Prime Minister Yasuo Fukuda of Japan and Prime Minister Kevin Rudd of Australia met in Tokyo to reaffirm the particular importance of the relationship between Japan and Australia, and confirmed their commitment to strengthen further the comprehensive strategic, security and economic partnership between Japan and Australia.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers shared the view that the relationship was based on a long history of cooperation, trade and investment links of enduring significance to both countries, a growing strategic relationship reflecting shared strategic interests and democratic values, and close people-to-people links. They expressed their determination to strengthen these important pillars of the relationship and explore new areas of cooperation.</p>
<p>     * In this context, the two Prime Ministers called on the next Japan-Australia Conference to present forward-looking recommendations for future Japan-Australia relations.</p>
<p>Security Cooperation</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers reaffirmed their commitment to promote bilateral security cooperation through the implementation of the Joint Declaration on Security Cooperation and its Action Plan, including updating the Memorandum on Defence Exchange and holding the Customs Cooperation Meeting. This also covers continuing enhancement of defence exchanges including unit-to-unit exchanges through aircraft visits such as P-3Cs and ship visits. The two Prime Ministers also reaffirmed their commitment to work together to contribute to peace and stability in the Asia-Pacific region and beyond.</p>
<p>     * In this context, the two Prime Ministers welcomed steady implementation of the Action Plan, and reaffirmed the importance of reviewing the status of bilateral security cooperation and examining further ways to enhance cooperation with a view to reviewing the Action Plan.</p>
<p>     * The Japanese side welcomed Australia's proposal to host the next Japan-Australia Joint Foreign and Defence Ministerial Consultations (“two-plus-two”) in Canberra in early November. The two Prime Ministers confirmed their commitment to hold the talks this year and to coordinate further to realise the proposal.</p>
<p>     * Noting that Japan and Australia both maintained alliance relationships with the United States, the two Prime Ministers emphasised the strategic value of promoting bilateral security and defence cooperation between Japan and Australia.</p>
<p>     * Underlining the importance of continuing presence and engagement of the United States in the region, the two Prime Ministers shared the view that strengthened bilateral cooperation would contribute to the enhancement of trilateral cooperation among Japan, Australia and the United States, such as through security and defence cooperation in the trilateral senior officials' meeting.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers confirmed their commitment to enhance dialogue and cooperation on a trilateral basis with the United States. The two Prime Ministers shared the view that the third ministerial meeting of the Trilateral Strategic Dialogue (TSD) to be held in late June would give greater momentum to furthering trilateral engagement in a practical manner including through disaster relief cooperation. In this context, the Japanese side welcomed Australia's offer to host a first meeting of TSD disaster relief experts.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers renewed their commitment to tackle the proliferation of the weapons of mass destruction and their means of delivery. The two Prime Ministers welcomed the fifth anniversary of the Proliferation Security Initiative (PSI) and expressed their determination to continue cooperation in the effective implementation of the PSI and its outreach activities.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers stressed the need to enhance regional capacities to provide disaster relief, including through the APEC Task Force for Emergency Preparedness (TFEP), and welcomed the World Food Program's plan to establish a regional disaster simulation facility. In this context, the Australian side noted Japan's intention to consider creating a network among disaster relief organisations already existing in Asia which would complement the work of other regional mechanisms. The Japanese side took note of Australia's intention to conduct a feasibility study on improving regional disaster relief mechanisms and to consult Japan closely on this.</p>
<p>Economic Relations</p>
<p>     * Reaffirming the importance and the high degree of complementarity of the economic relationship, the two Prime Ministers expressed their determination to further strengthen the economic relationship between the two leading economies. The Australian side noted the significant role Japanese investment had played in the development of the Australian economy.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers shared the view that the Economic Partnership Agreement (EPA) / Free Trade Agreement (FTA) would provide a good opportunity to strengthen and deepen the economic relationship. The two Prime Ministers affirmed their commitment to working towards a comprehensive and mutually beneficial agreement. The two Prime Ministers stressed the importance of a flexible and constructive approach in negotiations to achieve such outcomes, bearing in mind the sensitivities of both sides.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers reaffirmed the importance of stable supply of food and energy and mineral resources from Australia to Japan, noting that both countries benefit from such reliable supply. They confirmed their commitment to examine this issue in the context of the EPA/FTA.</p>
<p>     * Recognising that services trade was a relatively underdeveloped part of the bilateral trade relationship which needed to be enhanced, the two Prime Ministers shared the view that efforts to link the two services sectors should be strengthened.</p>
<p>     * The Australian side welcomed Japan's “Invitation Programme for Future Business Counterparts from Australia,” under the Japan-East Asia Network of Exchange for Students and Youth (JENESYS) programme that aims to build stronger business links between the two countries.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers decided to encourage the financial regulatory authorities in both countries to broaden the scope of their cooperation, including a regular dialogue between them to share experiences in financial services, with regulatory authorities involving business and other sectors as and when necessary.</p>
<p>Climate Change</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers affirmed their commitment to cooperate on climate change and reduce greenhouse gas emissions, acknowledging the close bilateral engagement occurring between the two countries through the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC), particularly in the ‘Umbrella Group', the Asia Pacific Partnership on Clean Development and Climate (APP), APEC and the East Asia Summit.</p>
<p>     * The Japanese Prime Minister welcomed the ratification of the Kyoto Protocol by Australia. The Australian Prime Minister welcomed the close co-operation with Japan in advancing the climate change agenda, stressing the importance of Japan's leadership as the G8 Chair of this year.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers expressed their resolve to work to establish, by the end of 2009, an effective international climate change framework in which all major economies participate in a responsible manner through the negotiations under the UNFCCC process.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers emphasised that while developed countries should continue to take the lead, all major economies should make meaningful contributions in accordance with their responsibilities and capabilities.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers underlined the need to reach a positive outcome at the G8 Hokkaido Toyako Summit in July to accelerate negotiations in the framework of the United Nations. The two Prime Ministers confirmed their commitment to working with others in the Major Economies process on a shared vision for a long term global emissions reduction goal and other important elements.</p>
<p>     * The Australian side highly appreciated the contribution of Japan's “Cool Earth Promotion Programme” as an important input to address the challenge of global climate change. The two Prime Ministers saw that the sectoral approach is useful for encouraging global sector specific actions. They also saw the bottom-up sectoral approach, which can complement economy-wide targets, as a useful tool for identifying technically possible mitigation potentials. The two Prime Ministers looked forward to continuing to work cooperatively on this and many other issues.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers reiterated their support for cooperative private-public sector work to share best practices and improve energy efficiency in the APP. They shared the view that such cooperation between developed and developing countries needs to be further enhanced.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers welcomed the launch of the Callide A project, the world's first demonstration of oxy-fuel combustion with CO2 storage and shared the view that the project would make a significant contribution to the development of technology that captures greenhouse gas emissions from coal-fired power stations. As a flagship APP project it is a good example of how Japanese and Australian industry and researchers are working together to develop practical solutions to address climate change.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers stressed the need to develop innovative technologies and to shift to a low carbon society in order to achieve long-term emissions reduction. The two Prime Ministers concurred on the importance of sharing technology roadmaps in partnership with the International Energy Agency (IEA), and of establishing a framework for international cooperation. They also expressed their support for the outcome of the G8 Environment Ministers Meeting regarding an international research network of institutions involved in research on low-carbon societies.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers recognised that Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Degradation (REDD) is critical. Therefore, the two Prime Ministers welcomed that relevant agencies of both sides would continue to cooperate in developing integrated forest and carbon monitoring systems towards a Global Carbon Monitoring System (GCMS) to underpin REDD policies. Cooperation will include a collaborative research alliance of Australia's CSIRO, the Cooperative Research Centre for Spatial Information, Japan's National Institute of Environmental Studies and Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency.</p>
<p>     * Noting that forests play a key role in conserving biodiversity and mitigating climate change, the two Prime Ministers decided to continue to work together to achieve sustainable forest management and combating illegal logging in the Asia-Pacific region.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers expressed their commitment to cooperate in assisting developing countries including Pacific Island countries in their effort toward adaptation to climate change. In this context, the two Prime Ministers expressed support for the co-benefits approach which addresses both development and climate change issues at the same time.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers welcomed progress towards the establishment of the new Climate Investment Funds at the World Bank.</p>
<p>Science and Technology</p>
<p>     * Recognising the two countries' strengths as world-class centres of research, the two Prime Ministers directed relevant ministries and agencies to take a fresh look at existing science and technology cooperation with a view to identifying new areas of mutual interests. They also encouraged closer collaboration between Japanese and Australian researchers, especially among young researchers. They welcomed the twentieth anniversary of Questacon.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers underlined the importance of generating the interest of the younger generation in science and technology and expressed their intent to build cooperation in this area including through student exchanges.</p>
<p>     * The Japanese side welcomed Australia's interest in participating in the Integrated Ocean Drilling Program (IODP).</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers recognised the important role of continued cooperation in scientific research in the Antarctic to support the understanding of the global impacts of climate change and confirmed their commitment to further enhanced cooperation in this area.</p>
<p>Pacific Islands</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers reaffirmed their commitment towards the Pacific Island countries in supporting their efforts to promote peace and prosperity. The Australian side welcomed Japan's intention to strengthen its efforts as “Peace Fostering Nation” in the region. The Japanese side welcomed the 6 March Port Moresby Declaration outlining Australia's approach to cooperation with the Pacific Island countries.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers expressed their intention to enhance dialogue and cooperation not only bilaterally but also with other major players in the region such as the United States and New Zealand. The two Prime Ministers affirmed that they would closely cooperate toward the Fifth Japan-Pacific Islands Forum Summit Meeting (PALM 5).</p>
<p>Energy and Mineral Resources Security</p>
<p>     * Recognising the strategic importance and highly complementary nature of the trade and investment relationship in energy and minerals resources such as iron ore, coal, liquefied natural gas (LNG) and uranium, the two Prime Ministers underlined the importance of stable and secure supply of energy and minerals resources. They noted the efforts of Australian Federal and State Governments to enhance infrastructure in support of energy and minerals exports.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers noted with great concern the escalation in oil prices. They also noted the importance of increased investment in energy and resources projects for sustaining global economic growth and combating high oil prices. They confirmed the need to address these issues in a cooperative manner in relevant international forums such as the IEA.</p>
<p>World Food Security</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers stressed the importance of world food security. They noted with strong concerns the trend of high prices of food, particularly in light of its acute impact on developing countries' efforts to overcome poverty and to reach the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs). They confirmed the need to tackle this issue in a cooperative manner in line with the outcomes of relevant international fora including the FAO High-Level Conference on World Food Security in Rome.</p>
<p>East Asia Summit (EAS)</p>
<p>     * In order to realise long-term stability and prosperity in East Asia, the two Prime Ministers reaffirmed their commitment to the development of the East Asia Summit (EAS) by promoting specific cooperation in such areas as energy security, finance, the environment, disaster management, climate change, education and youth exchange, based upon the principle of openness and universally shared values.</p>
<p>Regional Economic Integration</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers also welcomed initiatives for regional economic integration including the Track Two study on the Comprehensive Economic Partnership in East Asia (CEPEA), the establishment of the Economic Research Institute for ASEAN and East Asia (ERIA), initiatives on regional financial cooperation and the APEC initiatives for strengthening regional economic integration including the examination of the options and prospects for a Free Trade Area of the Asia-Pacific (FTAAP) as a long-term prospect.</p>
<p>APEC</p>
<p>     * Noting that Japan and Australia had been formative in the development of Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC), the two Prime Ministers affirmed their shared commitment to strengthening APEC as one of the primary regional institutions and noted the contribution APEC could make to regional economic integration.</p>
<p>Future of Asia Pacific Region</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers underlined the importance of continuing regional discussions on the future of the Asia Pacific region to explore ways to better respond to common challenges in the region, referring to Prime Minister Fukuda's Initiative for the future of the Asia Pacific as well as Prime Minister Rudd's proposal to exchange views on a future vision of the region including regional architecture.</p>
<p>WTO</p>
<p>     * Recognising the benefits of cooperating on economic issues in multilateral fora, the two Prime Ministers affirmed their strong intent to seek a conclusion to the WTO negotiations within this year and stressed the importance of achieving an ambitious, balanced and comprehensive outcome. They stressed that a successful outcome would be vital to the global economy, the international trading system, and the needs of developing countries.</p>
<p>Intellectual Property Rights</p>
<p>     * Emphasising the importance of intellectual property rights in this knowledge-based world economy, the two Prime Ministers affirmed their cooperation in intellectual property related issues, including on international efforts to harmonise substantive patent law. Recognising the need to combat counterfeiting and piracy, the two Prime Ministers also confirmed their commitment to work together towards early conclusion of negotiations for an Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement (ACTA), with a view to establishing a new standard of intellectual property protection.</p>
<p>Disarmament and Non-Proliferation</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers renewed their determination to strengthen the international disarmament and nuclear non-proliferation regime. The two Prime Ministers reaffirmed that they would continue to closely cooperate with each other with a view to achieving a successful outcome of the 2010 NPT Review Conference including through launching a bilateral initiative for high-level expert dialogue on nuclear disarmament and non-proliferation. In this context, the Japanese side welcomed the idea of establishing an international commission on nuclear non-proliferation and disarmament proposed by Prime Minister Rudd on 9 June in Kyoto.</p>
<p>     * The two Prime Ministers stressed the importance of cooperating in the field of denuclearization of the Russian Federation, including the dismantlement of decommissioned nuclear submarines in the Russian Far East.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
