<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>355</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA AND THE COMMON MARKET STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RIGHT HONOURABLE R.G MENZIES C.H.Q.C.M.P  IN THE HOUSE OF PRESENTATIVES  WEDNESDAY 16TH AUGUST, 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000355_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIA AND THE COMMON MARKET<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE RIGHT HONOURABLE R. G. MENZIES,<br />
in the<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
WEDNESDAY, 16th AUGUST, 1961 </p>
<p>STATEMENT* BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES)<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
WEDNESDAY, 16th AUGUST, 1961<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THE COMMON MARKET<br />
The decision of the Government of Great Britain to negotiate<br />
for admission to the European Economic Community is one of enormous political,<br />
economic and historic importance for Great Britain herself, for Europe, for<br />
the Commonwealth in general and Australia in particular, and for the world.<br />
It is therefore essential that, at this first opportunity after the<br />
visit of the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations ( Mr. Duncan Sandys)<br />
and after Mr. Macmillan's announcement in the House of Commons. I should, on<br />
behalf of the Australian Government, set out in this Parliament the nature of<br />
the action proposed or taken, and of the issues involved.<br />
But before I do that, there are some matters of history to be<br />
recorded. Not long after the War, movements began for strengthening<br />
Western Europe, economically and politically, against new threats to freedom<br />
and progress. These took a particular practical form when, in 1950, the<br />
European Coal and Steel community was promoted by M. Schumann of France.<br />
This was a marked success, and paved the way for the later development of the<br />
Common Market. In 1957 the Atomic Energy Community, known as " EURATOM", was set<br />
up. Concurrently, on March 25th 1957 the Treaty of Rome was signed,<br />
establishing the European Economic Community, sometimes known as " the Common<br />
Market" or " The Six". The parties to the Treaty were France, Germany, Italy,<br />
Belgium, the Netherlands and Luxembourg. While this Treaty was being negotiated,<br />
Great Britain made her first decision, which was not to participate. At that<br />
time, she felt that, although she approved of the idea of European unity, she<br />
could not go in as a party because of her Commonwealth commitments, her own<br />
system of protecting British agriculture and ( as I have always supposed)<br />
because she did not choose to accept any abatement of her own sovereignty.<br />
But she still took active steps. Her second decision was to<br />
propose an Industrial Free Trade Area for the whole of Western Europe,<br />
including The Six. This proposal would have met the agricultural and ( for<br />
the greater part) the Commonwealth considerations which had previously </p>
<p>deterred her. But " The Six" did not favour the proposals, and they failed.<br />
A third decision was then taken. Great Britain formed the<br />
European Free Trade Association with Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Austria,<br />
Portugal and Switzerland. This group became known, and I shall refer to it,<br />
as The Seven. Subsequently, attempts were made to bring about an association<br />
between The Seven and The Six but without success.<br />
I mention these matters of history because they will remind us that<br />
the decision now taken is the fourth, and that as it involves detailed negotiations<br />
with The Six on items some of which concern Australia very greatly, we<br />
have now reached a period in which we must all clarify our attitudes on<br />
identifiable matters of great practical moment.<br />
It is now necessary to turn to the Treaty of Rome itself, to<br />
discover the broad structure and mutual obligations of the economic community<br />
which Great Britain will now negotiate to enter.<br />
The preamble to the Treaty stated that the signatories were<br />
" determined to establish the foundations of an ever-closer union among<br />
European peoples." Under the Treaty, the " Common Market" will be progressively<br />
established during a transitional period of somewhere between ten and fifteen<br />
years. This involves the progressive elimination of Customs duties<br />
and quantitative restrictions on trade between member States, and the establishment<br />
of a common external tariff.<br />
There is to be a common agricultural policy, providing for such<br />
matters as increased production and organised marketing. Subject to the<br />
negotiations, which will be put in hand, probably by about October, 1961,<br />
The Six were due to meet before the end of this year to work out the agric-<br />
Sultural policy. This is clearly one reason for the decision by Great Britain<br />
at this time. She will, having regard to the Commonwealth position, need<br />
to negotiate on agricultural matters before the final policy of The Six<br />
has been settled. There is to be free movement of workers between the Member States.<br />
Nationals may freely ( whether individuals or companies) establish themselves<br />
in the territory of another Member State.<br />
There are to be set up common provisions for conditions of trade<br />
within the Common Market, co-ordination of economic policies, and the<br />
harmonisation of social policies. One of the express purposes of Article 118<br />
is to promote close collaboration between Member States in the Social field,<br />
particularly in employment, labour legislation and working conditions,<br />
training, and social security. </p>
<p>The Treaty further provides for the establishment of a European<br />
Investment Bank. Institutions are provided for; an Assembly of 142, a Council of<br />
six, an Executive Commission of nine, and a Court of Justice to deal with the<br />
interpretation and enforcement of the Treaty.<br />
Under Article 237, any European nation may apply for full membership<br />
in which case the agreement must be made by the unanimous act of the<br />
existing members at present The Six.<br />
Under Article 238 a nation may become an Associate Member, as<br />
Greece recently has; but it is understood that such a course is not favoured in<br />
the case of a substantially developed manufacturing nation.<br />
The Treaty is, by Article 240, concluded " for an unlimited period".<br />
There is no provision for withdrawal, at the option of the member concerned.<br />
It would therefore appear that a Member can withdraw only with the consent of<br />
all the others; the decision being in effect an amendment to the Treaty.<br />
Any amendments to the Treaty will require ratification by all<br />
Member States. Clearly, this is a formidable and far-reaching organism, of<br />
profound economic significance, and with political objectives to which I<br />
shall refer later. I will first endeavour, with as much brevity as possible, to<br />
explain the nature of the economic interests involved in a negotiation by<br />
Great Britain for membership.<br />
Great Britain herself has, of course, enormous interests at stake.<br />
Her decision to negotiate could not have been easy, and we may be sure that it<br />
has been arrived at in the light of her immense experience and ripe judgment.<br />
It would not be for us to substitute some opinion of our own, even if we had<br />
formed one. For we are in no position to assess the elements in the British<br />
economy, or the economic arguments this way and that concerning the effect<br />
upon her of an achieved membership. We have, of course, a lively interest in<br />
the accuracy of her final decision, for we want to see a powerful and<br />
prosperous Great Britain, for the good of Australia in all aspects of our national<br />
and international life and for the good of the whole free world.<br />
She herself, as Mr. Sandys was careful to explain to us in the<br />
course of our frank and helpful exchanges, is impressed by the competitive<br />
advantages for her own exports and necessary trade balances which she<br />
believes would derive from free access to a " Home Market" of over 250,000,000<br />
people. This is a larger population than that of the whose own large<br />
internal free trade home market with free access to enormous supplies of power<br />
and materials, has given her great strength in the markets of the world. </p>
<p>On the other hand, of course, Great Britain's entry into a<br />
European free trade area will mean that her own industries will meet the full<br />
blast of European competition, including that from countries like Germany<br />
which has a longer working week, a less extensive system of social services,<br />
and a high proportion of modern plant erected since the War-time destruction.<br />
It is said that such competition will lead to greater efficiency, and no doubt,<br />
given sufficient time, it will. In any case this aspect of the matter has<br />
beyond question been fully weighed and considered. We ourselves see great<br />
scope for an increase, by increased efficiency, in the Commonwealth Market.<br />
Commonwealth countries to-day take 42/ of British exports, while The Six<br />
take 14.5%. While Great Britain clearly hopes that, as a member of the<br />
Common Market, she will increase her exports to Europe which would be a<br />
great thing for her economy we simply direct attention to the undoubted fact<br />
that her Commonwealth market must continue and grow if her overall strength<br />
is to increase. But the Commonwealth market cannot grow if any conditions of<br />
European membership inflict material damage upon the export earnings of<br />
Commonwealth countries. That, of course, is the great matter to which we<br />
will direct a close and studied attention before and during the negotiations,<br />
until the final decision is taken.<br />
There is another aspect of this great matter. We have throughout<br />
felt that the Common Market, as it now stands, whatever effect it might<br />
have on any individual country, would tend to increase the total prosperity<br />
and purchasing power of The Six, and that Australia, among others, might hope to<br />
find a growing market in Europe. As I will show later, we have for some time<br />
been actively seeking to develop that market. Undoubtedly, the European<br />
Economic Community has been succeeding. The economic recovery of France in<br />
recent years has contributed to this. Trade exchanges between them have<br />
increased 5/ o since the Treaty of Rome. They have accumulated massive<br />
international reserves.<br />
Yet the prospect of Australian benefit from this improvement will<br />
depend very importantly upon the internal policies adopted by the Common<br />
Market Countries in relation to their own agriculture. If, and there have<br />
been suggestions of it, agricultural protectionism prevails, the entry of<br />
foodstuffs, from e. g. Australia, will become more difficult. The pricing<br />
policy adopted by the E. E. C. for its agricultural products will largely<br />
determine the size of the European market for imported agricultural products<br />
and the extent to which surpluses in given European countries can be exported,<br />
Price stabilisation at the high levels now current in some Member States will<br />
tend to increase production in the Community area. Under the encouragement<br />
of high domestic prices, France is already developing an export surplus in<br />
wheat. These matters will be dealt with by my colleague, the Minister for<br />
Trade. It is sufficient for me to say that the advantages or disadvantages<br />
to Australia, economically speaking, from the success of the Common Market will<br />
be largely determined by policies worked out in Europe. </p>
<p>It is difficult to assess the prospects:' For example, wool<br />
is to enjoy free entry under the common external tariff. But it does not<br />
automatically follow that European economic growth will correspondin gly<br />
increase the demand for wool. We hope that it will, but the fact is that<br />
although industrial production in The Six has been rising rapidly since 1957,<br />
there has so far been no increase in thd volume of our exports of wool to<br />
these countries. Our most definable interest arises in relation to our exports<br />
to Great Britain; wheat, meat, dairy products, base metals, sugar, dried fruits,<br />
fresh fruit and processed fruits. These constitute the great bulk of our<br />
current exports to Great Britain of 1198m. Stg. They enjoy a preferred entry<br />
into the British market, while meat and sugar are the subjects of special<br />
long-term agreements. ' In exldhange. for-these preftences, Gi-eat'Britafin<br />
enjoys preferential rates in our Customs Tariff and currenly ' exports goods to<br />
the value of œ 259m. Stg. to Australia.<br />
0 Clearly, this mutual preferential structure comes into the arena<br />
of Great Britain's negotiations with The Six. Should the other members of the<br />
European Free Trade Association decide also to apply for membership 6f the<br />
Common Market ( which seems probable) there will be further important problems<br />
to be decided. If, to take a good example, Denmark acceded, and Great Britain<br />
acceded without securing a special position for Australian dairy products, the<br />
preference now enjoyed by Australia inGreat. Britain would be reversed into<br />
a preferentialt becauee duty free, entry for the Danish products.<br />
I will not, In this general survey, go into the details of our<br />
exports which are involved. But I think it most desirable that I should point<br />
out to all the negotiators that if they want ( as I am sure they do) a strong and<br />
growing Australia, they must recognise the peculiar Australian significance of<br />
the relevant industries.<br />
The development and populating of the North of Australia, from the<br />
WKimberleys in Western Australia through the Northern Territory to North<br />
Queensland depends primarily on beef cattle, minerals and sugar. The British<br />
market has been of commanding importance in all three. Wheat stands next<br />
to wool as our export staple; the welfare of at least two states is bound<br />
up in its success. The intensive settlement in the irrigated areas of the<br />
Murray and Murrumbidgee regions has been built up on dried vine fruits,<br />
processed fruits, and the production of fat lambs. Not one of these industries<br />
could exist on its present scale without large exports. In the case of dried<br />
fruits and fat lambs, the British market is vital; for processed fruit it<br />
is important. Our great mineral resources, in relation to which great expansion<br />
is in sight, tend to be found in areas remote from the industrial cities<br />
and the agricultural areas. They come, when developed, to sustain large<br />
communities whose very existence depends upon a growing export for the products. </p>
<p>of the mines, refineries and smelters.<br />
It follows from all this, and I take leave to emphasise this<br />
point, that severe blows to our export primary industries would fall with<br />
particular severity upon particular areas,. industries, and people. The<br />
impact would not be more or less evenly distributed over the whole nation, but<br />
would be concentrated and therefore more damaging.<br />
We cannot as yet anticipAte the result of the negotiations.<br />
We can, I think, reasonably assume that Great Britain will not accede<br />
to the Treaty of Rome unconditionally. Such an accession would bring to an<br />
end the Commonwealth Preferential System which has endured for many years.<br />
It would be highly damaging to Australia, and could be disastrous to our<br />
neighbour and friend, New Zealand. As the preferential system operates both<br />
ways, it could mean the end of B. P. T. rates in our Tariff schedules.<br />
On the other hand, it may be too much to hope at this stage that<br />
Great Britain will be allowed ( by the necessary unanimous agreement of The<br />
Six) to maintain the Commonwealth Preferential System completely unimpaired.<br />
Some compromise will no doubt be sought. We shall, of course,<br />
battle for the best possible arrangements for the protection of our traditional<br />
and legitimate interests.<br />
We cannot doubt that Great Britain will be on our side in that<br />
battle. We also have good friends in Europe, and can be assured of their<br />
understanding. I have already said something about some of the exports which<br />
are our special concern and need not repeat it. But we are not unaware of<br />
the suggestions, already being made in some quarters', that the emergence in<br />
practical form of the Common Market issue has suddenly made the Australian<br />
Government aware of the need to develop new and deversified markets.<br />
The suggestions are quite unfounded, as I shall quite easily<br />
Wshow. The matter has not arisen with the suddenness which recent<br />
publicity may suggest. We have for some time known that~ attempts would be<br />
made to bring The Seven and The Six together. I myself had some general<br />
talk about this with both Chancellor Adenauer and President de Gaulle in<br />
1959. But no detailed proposals were ever put to or considered by us because<br />
first, it was the specified object of Great Britain to keep agriculture<br />
out of any negotiations, thus preserving our own and British interests, and<br />
second, it was made clear that before any negotiations were decided upon,<br />
we would be effectively consulted.<br />
In London, immediately after the last Prime Minister's Conference<br />
I proposed ( and the proposal was accepted) that our officials should go into<br />
preliminary conference in London, so that, " getting down to brass tacks"<br />
we could identify the points of difficulty and try to find common methods of<br />
approach. </p>
<p>This Conference preceded the visit of Mr. Sandys; a visit which<br />
produced, for the first time on the political level, a specific exchange<br />
of v. ews. Meanwhile much official study has been made in the relevant<br />
departments. The matter has, therefore, not come suddenly out of a blue sky.<br />
From Australia's point of view, neither time nor ground has been lost.<br />
Indeed, we have been active for years in strengthening and diversifying<br />
our exports to whatever markets we could find.<br />
When, in January 1956, I announced the creation of the Department<br />
of Trade, I pointed out that it would direct its major attention to the<br />
stimulation of trade. It has, with the backing of the Cabinet, acted vigorously<br />
in this field. It has continued to intensify the Trade drive through the efficient<br />
and widely appreciated Trade Commissioner Service.<br />
In 1949 there were 17 posts in 12 countries. In 1961-2 there will<br />
be 37 posts in 28 countries. Since 1949 we have opened posts in Karachi,<br />
Rome, Trinidad, Bonn, Montreal, Salisbury, Auckland, Manila, Christchurch,<br />
New Delhi, Kuala Lumpur, Bangkok, Stockholm, Chicago, Ottawa, Nairobi, Accra<br />
and Beirut with plans already announced for opening in Lima, Caracas and<br />
Teheran. The Trade publicity vote has increased from œ E16,000 in 1949<br />
to œ. 1,000,000.<br />
0 InJul y 1956 we established the Export Payments Insurance<br />
Corporation. On June 30th, 1961. current policies were valued at œ E26 m.<br />
the export transactions covered being spread over 120 countries, mainly in<br />
Asia and the Middle East.<br />
Since 1954 we have organised 13 major trade or survey missions, and<br />
have co-operated with industry associations in the organisation and despatch<br />
of two trade ships. Another trade ship is planned for the Persian Gulf<br />
in the new Year and trade missions to the Middle East, Pacific Islands, and<br />
South America will be organised during 1961-1962.<br />
There were three passages in the communique issued at the end of<br />
our talks with Mr. Sandys which deserve special mention.<br />
The first showed that the Australian government took a view of<br />
the impact of Great Britain's membership of the Common Market upon Commonwealth<br />
Relations different from that of Great Britain.<br />
The second showed that we refrained from giving approval to the<br />
opening of negotiations. </p>
<p>The third made it clear that we wished to take an active part in<br />
the negotiations affecting our special interests.<br />
These statements have been interpreted by some as indicating a<br />
spirit of hostility in our discussions, or at least a lack of a co-operative<br />
Commonwealth approach. I want to make it clear that our discussions were<br />
conducted on a proper Commonwealth level; our common interests never forgotten,<br />
but our particular interests zealously expounded and upheld.<br />
I should perhaps repeat our general attitude, for the benefit of<br />
the people of Great Britain as well as our own.<br />
We want whatever decisions are finally taken to bring added<br />
strength to Great Britain, for her own sake, for our sake, and for the sake<br />
of the world. For we are both British and Commonwealth.<br />
But our first duty is to protect what we believe to be the proper<br />
interests of Australia, whose future development will be a considerable factor<br />
in Commonwealth strength, and will in particular produce economic advantages<br />
for Great Britain herself. We do not doubt that this is understood and accepted<br />
by Great Britain. There is therefore much common ground upon which to<br />
stand. But the problems will not be solved by saying that we have common<br />
objectives. The real issues will be those of method. Some long-accepted<br />
ideas may need to be modified; there will be conflicts of opinion; the<br />
advocacy of lawful interests may produce high and intense argument. But<br />
such matters are in the British tradition. We need not fear them, nor<br />
pretend that they do not exist.<br />
The decision that will ultimately be taken by Great Britain, to<br />
enter on the negotiated terms or to stay out, will be the most momentous peace<br />
time decision in living memory. Upon its wisdom and success probably the<br />
future of the free world and most certainly the future of our own family of<br />
nations will turn.<br />
It follows that Australia will bring to her own negotiations with<br />
Great Britain and, as we venture to hope, with The Six, not only the most<br />
powerfully presented exposition and defence of her own interests, for her own<br />
future is our special care and responsibility, but also a strong and wide sense<br />
of common responsibility. It will have been observed that Great Britain has put The Six<br />
on notice of these complexities. She has informed them that Great Britain must<br />
take account of the special Commonwealth relationship as well as the<br />
essential interests of British agriculture and of the other members of the<br />
European Free TradeAssociation. </p>
<p>THE BROAD POLI T ICAL I SSUES<br />
We believe that the entry of Great Britain into the European<br />
Economic Community would have far-reaching political implications. As we<br />
see it at present, we believe that it would mean a substantial departure<br />
from, or even an abandonment of, the traditional British policy of the<br />
Balance of Power, a policy which basically represented a form of isolationism,<br />
of freedom from what I 4nay call standing or permanent obligations. True, as<br />
Mr. Macmillan pointed out in the House of Commons on August 2n4t " in every<br />
period when the world has been in danger of tyrants or aggression, Britain<br />
has abandoned isolationism". Nevertheless, I pointed out that a decision to<br />
enter the European Economic Community expressed to be a permanent body, and<br />
with political " overtones" of the clearest kind, would represent the<br />
abandonment of the old position and the acceptance of permanent European<br />
involvements. I ' thought' th'at Mr. Macmillan accepted this when he said, in the<br />
same speech, that while European federation should be rejected, a confederation<br />
of European nations was an acceptable concept with which Great Britain could<br />
associate willingly and whole heartedly.<br />
The distinction between the organic distribution of sovereignty<br />
which exists in a Federation and the looser association of a Confederation is one<br />
which I was at pains to make in our discussions with Mr. Sandys. But even a<br />
confederation involves mutual political obligations of a continuing kind.<br />
A few days after we had been pointing this out in the Canberra<br />
talks, the Heads of State of The Six issued a communique, dated July 18th,<br />
which gave special point to the argument. The Communique stated that the<br />
Heads of State and Governments were convinced that only a United Europe is<br />
in a position, allied with the United States and other free peoples, to meet<br />
the common dangers of the free world; that they were determined to develop<br />
their political co-operation with the aim of European unification; and that<br />
for this purpose they proposed to have regular meetings in order to bring their<br />
policy into line and reach agreed views.<br />
Of course, we need not suppose that European unification is just<br />
around the corner. National histories and prides and characteristics are not<br />
so easily set aside. But it does seem clear that, as the Rome Treaty's<br />
economic provisions become effective, there must be a closer co-ordination, if<br />
not actual integration, of political policies. For where there is a common<br />
economic system established and made enforceable by law, the journey to<br />
confederation or even federation is half completed. Common domestic policies<br />
will cry aloupI for common external policies to protect them.<br />
If Great Britain joins, and other West European nations with her,<br />
and Europe becomes, step by step, a great power ( or a cohesive agglomeration<br />
of power) Great Britain will become, we would hope and expect a most important<br />
integer in that power. But she will, ex hvpothesi, cease to be completely </p>
<p>independent in relation to European affairs.<br />
This is why the decision which she must make after the proposed<br />
negotiations, is so politically momentous.<br />
We do not doubt the strength of the ' broad political considerations<br />
which lie behind the decision to negotiate. Some of them clearly are:-<br />
the importance of the cohesion of free Europe<br />
as an area of resistance to Communist threat and aggression;<br />
the fear that the perpetuation of economic rivalries and<br />
differences in Europe: will mean political rivalries and<br />
differences, and so weaken the joint will and capacity to<br />
resist the Communist threat;<br />
the importance of influencing that area from within,<br />
if it needs such influence, to maintain po$ itive and<br />
outward looking policies which will be non-neutralist in<br />
character; the belief that Great Britain, as an influential member of<br />
the European Community, will bring added strength to<br />
British Commonwealth consultations.<br />
I have stated these matters so that it may not be said that we<br />
have failed to see the arguments on the great issues, and have adopted a small<br />
and unimaginative view.<br />
We understand, and freely acknowledge, that if true European<br />
unity can, in spite of the history of the past hundred years, be brought about,<br />
the prospects of world peace will grow brighter. But, as a senior Commonwealth<br />
country, we have felt bound to say that we do not think that the Commonwealth<br />
as a political organism would be strengthened. Great Britain, as the<br />
centre of the Commonwealth, has in the past spoken for herself at Commonwealth<br />
Conferences. After entering the new Europe, with its common policies and<br />
institutions and rules, she could no longer speak with detachment. The<br />
Treaty of Rome cannot be approbated and reprobated at the same time.<br />
Nor could a growing interest, and, more than interest, involvement in Europe,,<br />
be calculated to leave completely untouched the present British position in and<br />
around Asia and Africa.<br />
It is for these reasons that we have publicly expressed our grave<br />
doubts of the continuance unimpaired of the Commonwealth to which we are deeply<br />
attached, with which we have stood in peace and war, and the existence of<br />
which still means much to civilisation. </p>
<p>We may be wrong on this matter. We sincerely hope that events may<br />
prove us wrong. But, as much is being said about the impact of any accession<br />
to the Treaty of Rome on the Commonwealth in its present form, we think it proper<br />
to express our own view.<br />
In the long run, of course, the stern facts of contemporary history<br />
may require some abatament of the special Commonwealth relation. in favour<br />
of a powerful European unity: we do not as yet know. But it would be<br />
a mistake to pretend that there was no change when in fact there had been a<br />
great one. We have not based our opinion upon any narrow ground of the<br />
importance of absolute sovereignty. All international pacts, from the<br />
United Nations to N. A. T. O. and S. E. A. T. O. involve the exercise of sovereignty<br />
to limit, by free choice, liberty of individual action. But neitl~ er U. N.<br />
nor N. A. T. O. nor S. E. A. T. O. is a super-state. Parties to the agreement may<br />
leave as they think fit, in the exercise of the very sovereignty by which they<br />
joi'ned. The Treaty of Rome., as I have pointed out, is different.<br />
There must be unanimous agreement for the joining and the leaving. Complete<br />
independence of action no longer exists.<br />
We pronounce no dogma. We do not seek to turn back the great<br />
tides of international affairs. We do not say that the British view of the<br />
effect upon the Commonwealth of a decision by Great Britain to go into<br />
Europe is demonstrably wrong. In the present state of the world, with<br />
bullying and bluster our daily diet, it may be that the Commonwealth must<br />
once more change, for the common good.<br />
Even a cursory examination of the Treaty of Rome and its<br />
proposals will indicate, as I have briefly indicated before, the immense variety<br />
and complexity of the matters to be negotiated. The decision as to whether<br />
we should participate directly in those negotiations which affect our special<br />
interests does not depend on Great Britain, but on the willingness of The Six<br />
to permit it. We are, however, confident that Great Britain will do her<br />
best to bring it about. So far as we can judge at present, the actual<br />
negotiations, once begun in, say, October, will last for at least six months.<br />
They will need to be proceded by close exchanges between Great Britain and the<br />
other Commonwealth countries, some time next month. If these preliminary<br />
talks are to prove valuable in a fairly short time, our representatives will<br />
need the best possible briefing from this end. For this purpose, we have<br />
established a special Committee of Cabinet, to sit-frequently and to be<br />
available at short notice, working in conjunction with senior officials and<br />
expert advisers. Important decisions will need to be made at this end, not<br />
only before but during the course of the negotiations themselves. For the<br />
problems confronting our export industries are so great that every last<br />
detailed care must be taken to solve them in a way which protects, and indeed<br />
enlarges, our national,. developmental, and trading future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
