<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15531</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian National Rugby Academy</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am very pleased to announce that the Australian Government will provide the Australian Rugby Union (ARU) with a $25 million capital contribution towards the establishment of the Australian National Rugby Academy (ANRA) at Ballymore in Brisbane.</p>
<p>The ANRA will be integral to the continued development and success of Australian rugby.  The ANRA will provide state of the art facilities for the ARU to develop and prepare its elite and emerging players, coaches and referees.  The centralised facilities will include field skills training, gymnasium, pool and support infrastructure such as accommodation, medical and meeting facilities. The ANRA will also become a centre for excellence for the Asia-Pacific, providing assistance for fledgling rugby bodies in the region.</p>
<p>While Australia's immediate focus is on regaining the World Cup in France later this year, the establishment of the ANRA will ensure that the Wallabies are well positioned to retain their place as one of the top rugby nations in the world.</p>
<p>Ballymore, the spiritual home of rugby in Queensland, is the ideal site for the ANRA with its central location and the availability of land offering significant advantages.</p>
<p>Australian Government funding is contingent on the ARU meeting recurrent costs and the Queensland Government providing the ARU with appropriate secure tenure arrangements at Ballymore.</p>
<p>Rugby is played in over 120 countries throughout the world and is a game rich in history, traditions, camaraderie and community involvement. Its popularity in Australia continues to grow, with grassroots participation increasing by 9.5 per cent in 2006 to just under 194,000.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
