<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5126</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT ON LUSAKA CHOGM</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005126.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 23 AUGUST 1979<br />
STATEMENT TO PARLIAENT ON LUSAKA CHOG. M<br />
I sek lea. ve to report to this House on the Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Mecting held in Lusaka from 1 August<br />
to 7 August.<br />
There can be no legitimate doubt in anyone's mind that this<br />
was a critical conference in the history of the Commonwealth.<br />
The way things turned out should not cause us to forget that.<br />
Before the event responsible and reasonable people were<br />
expressing serious concern as to whether the Commonwealth<br />
would survive the conference. There was talk of a break-up.<br />
This was r. ot altogether idle talk. Had the conference gone<br />
badly, the institution would have been seriously maimed and<br />
could have been destroyed. As it happened the conference<br />
did not go badly, it went extremely well, and far from<br />
breaking uo, the ComonJealth has emerged a stronger, iore<br />
vital and ore cohesive body.<br />
io-one who has followed events in Lusaka and certainly<br />
no-one who was present there can doubt that the Commonwealth<br />
is an institution which has rele vance, and a distinctive<br />
function to perform, in the contemporary world.<br />
It has sometimes been asserted and even oftener been implied<br />
that this is a romantic and exaggerated view, that the<br />
talking-shop, a dealer in myths and illusions. I believe<br />
it is now clear that it is those who hold this view who are<br />
the real romantics pessimistic romantics who refuse to<br />
come to terms with a changing world and the changing forms<br />
of influence and power.<br />
The old Commonwealth could never have achieved what was achieved<br />
at Lusaka. For at this conference, the Commonwealth took on<br />
one of the most serious and sensitive issues in international<br />
affairs today, an issue which has resiste d p ongd efforts<br />
made by major powers, acting alone, to find a solution.<br />
In a matter of days, real and substantial progress was made.<br />
It seems perverse, therefore, to persist in the defeatist and<br />
negative view that thit ins itution does not have the potential<br />
continuing valble annd constructive role in world affairs.<br />
of influence and power.<br />
for a continuing valuable and~ constructive role in world a~: airs.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
The issue I refer to is, of course, the future of Zimbrabwe.<br />
As anticipated, this issue was inevitably the central<br />
preoccupation of the conference. It was approached with a<br />
minimum of polemics, and with a detecrmination to find a<br />
fair settlement acceptable to all parties.<br />
In my response to President Kaunda's opening speech on the<br />
first day I appealed, as I have done on previous occasions,<br />
for a spirt of principled moderation and compromise which<br />
would make it possible to bridge different positions.<br />
In the event that spirit turned out to be the distinguishing mark<br />
of the conference. It was the spirit of Lusaka.<br />
That it was so was due, in particular, to the attitude<br />
of three of the participants: our host President Kaunda;<br />
President Nyerere of Tanzania; and the British Prime Minister,<br />
Mrs. Thatcher.<br />
I would like to take this opportunity to express my personal<br />
admiration for the courage and vision of these three leaders.<br />
In a situation where there were pressures on each to be<br />
intransigent, to ask others to yield while remaining inflexible<br />
themselves, all three rejected that path and chose the one<br />
leading to genuine accommodation. It is greatly to their<br />
credit and represented statesmanship of a high order.<br />
The ritish Prime Minister, for her part, reaffirmed the<br />
unqualified co'-mitment of her Government to the goal of genuine<br />
black majority rule in Rhodesia. Much more importantly,<br />
in her speech of 3 August, she recognised the validity of<br />
the criticisms, made of the present constitution, of the<br />
blcking power s enjoyed by the white minority, and of the<br />
power vested in the various Service Commissions, which<br />
together make it impossible for the Government of Bishop Muzorewa<br />
to have adequate control over the country's affairs.<br />
So long as these criticisms could be made. of the Constitution<br />
one could not assert that genuine black majority rule exists<br />
in Rhodesia. Such powers, which have not been included in<br />
any constitution resulting from a legal transference of power<br />
by Britain, deny Government powers which are fundamental to<br />
a democracy or indeed to any responsible Government.<br />
A Government which cannot control appointments in key areas,<br />
or the activities of its armed forces, is not master of<br />
its own house.<br />
Mrs. Thatcher also accepted the responsibility of the British<br />
Government to bring the country to legal independence on<br />
a basis which the Commonwealth and the international community<br />
as a whole will find acceptable. She undertook to present<br />
proposals as quickly as possible to all the parties.<br />
The leaders of the front line states show. ed an equally<br />
admirable willingness to approach the issue constructively.<br />
In his speech on the Zimbabwe debate, President Nyerere<br />
recognised that an advance had been made in recent months. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
while rejectinc~ the vanlidity of CXLtlr ons t. itiolnal<br />
Lramowt hich allL white minrjr it-, to con'tr ol the<br />
levers of powder, hie acccoted tolat a 6~ e,' o~ rdL. tui<br />
was riot inconnpatible with special provisionz for the w'il-tc<br />
minority in the form of reserved " cLseverou of<br />
proportion to the numbc) rs involved". eO recocgnised t~ hat<br />
a ceasc-fire a precondition for free and Cair eluctions.<br />
Beyond -this, President Kaunda and President Nv" erere, showe.-d<br />
a re--traiit and patience, and3 a confiCdence in the<br />
British which were an cstilelement in creacing<br />
the trust neceSsary for aurement and prcgress. They were not<br />
in th-e bu_-sz" ness of conf] rontat ion and ooint-scoring.<br />
Let m2 sa-y. son. ething about the nart A,, ust-ralia played in the<br />
ne,-oaiation' of" t-he Zim,: babw,. e iSsue. in therz periJoQ leadinig up<br />
to the conference anC dur-inu it, we hadc extensive contacts<br />
both direct-ly and by letter wi4th the principal parties.<br />
S'hort ly bef-o re the cor-Pez-ence I had talks w-. ith 1,11s. Thatcher<br />
here in Cbraand in-z,-edi ate1y be-fo-re going to Lusaka I<br />
visited N-ige-ri-a-a key African state to talk with<br />
General-Ob-asanjo, the leaderl of': the eealmilitary government.<br />
The FCorei. n %' in4 ster had separate talk s %-with the British<br />
an, rsentatives of the -duzorel., a Government and<br />
suseuen&gt;.' ithleaders of' the Tanzanian and Kenyan<br />
Dur i.-g Ccn-erence of course, we had extensive discussions<br />
vit-l all thne narties iresent the;-Patriotic Front.<br />
In all these talk' s we exoressed' the view,. that,, whatever else,<br />
the Arlelections had b'roken a Jlog-j ar and created conditions<br />
for ri-oveii. nt. 7,1e maintained that further consti tutional<br />
chances in the direction of greater A-fricanisation were<br />
essential.<br />
Wie emphasised that a precondition for a successful,<br />
settlement w,, as that it should b) e acceptable to a significantLl<br />
number of African states. IWVe stressed the need to bring<br />
the wvar to an end.<br />
The invitation to give the first response to President Kauna's<br />
opening ad" dress gave me teopportLunity to put Australia's<br />
vie-is to the conference very early. I stressed the neod to<br />
bear in mind the positive elements of agreement which existed<br />
among those present, the fact that we essentially agreed on<br />
ends and differed only on means.<br />
I stressed also that recent events had created an opportunity<br />
for advance by introdlucing a new element of flexibility and<br />
movement. And, as I have said, I made as strong a plea as<br />
I could'for moderation and comoroinise.<br />
During the weekend of 4-5 Auciust, and following the openln;<br />
of the debate on the Rhodesia issue on Friday, 3 Augus: t,<br />
a small consulting group of si&gt; X Headcs of Governrment was set<br />
up to try to reach an agreeme-n. ./ 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
Australia was a member of that group. The group reached<br />
agreement and drew. up a coTmmunilcue on Southern Africa, which<br />
was subsequently accepted by other H-eads of Government.'<br />
The communique made nine points: The Heads of Government<br />
-confirmed that they were wholly committed to genuine<br />
black majority rule for the people of Zimbabwe;<br />
-recognised, in this context, that the internal<br />
settlement constitution is defective in certain important<br />
aspects; fullyaccepted that it is the Constitutional responsibility<br />
of the British Government to grant legal independence to<br />
Zimbabwe on the basis of majority rule;<br />
recognised that the search for a lasting settlement must<br />
involve all parties to the conflict;<br />
were deeply conscious of the urgent need to achieve such<br />
a settlement and bring peace to the people of Zimbabwe<br />
and their neighbours;<br />
acceped that independence on the basis of majority<br />
rule recuires the adoption of a democratic constitution<br />
including appropriate safeguards for minorities;<br />
-ackn7owledged that the government formed under such<br />
inSadne oendence constitution must be chosen through<br />
free and fair elections, properly supervised under<br />
British Government authority, and with Commonwealth<br />
observers; welcomed the British Government's indication that an<br />
appropriate procedure for advancing towards these<br />
objectives would be for them to call a Constitutional<br />
conference to which all parties would be invited; and<br />
-consequently, accepted that it must be a major objective<br />
to bring about a cessation of hostilities, and an end<br />
to sanction,; as part of the process of implerent-: i. on<br />
of a lasting settlement.<br />
These nine points do not amount to a settlement of the Zimbabwe<br />
situation. Neither the Muzoreua government nor the Patriotic<br />
Front ZANU and ZAPU were parties to the discussion, and a<br />
settlement will require their agreement.<br />
Much hard work and delicate negotiating remains to be done.<br />
But the significance of what has been achieved is enormous.<br />
To appreciate this it is necessary to contemplate what the<br />
position would ncr. be, had there been a failure tp reach<br />
agreement. Both Southern Africa and the Commonwealth would be<br />
facing bleak prospects. The momentum for change would have<br />
been lost.<br />
As it is, a very formidable and-diverse body of opinion has<br />
been mobilised and unified, in favour of a particular process<br />
of settlement. Given its nature, that body of opinion will.<br />
require a serious response both from Salisbury and from the<br />
Patriotic Front. </p>
<p>Before the con-furence, the-opJinliozi pre-_ vai lod in each of thc-se<br />
cencres that time wsoilTei side, -LThaL tl-ecy could afforcl<br />
to wa-iti and to resist IIth iew ,-ill 1De Kf F -c Ul t : f or them~<br />
to inaintai. n that view now... It is verO)' erat ht for the<br />
f ir st t ime i n P.,; 1nNY ye ar s thIie ii itiLa. t iv e hIi b c2e. n 5; eed b y th<br />
forces of mdrto and -, caceful set'tlement arnd that-has buecn<br />
done withlin the -frameworlk of the C mowatthat often<br />
derided' Ir-stiti. tionr which continues Lo confoundA its critics<br />
by pr'pirg its f nle1vance.<br />
The si etrce that is onv\ isaged can bring p aacn r<br />
a1 : ia to take t plar'. i n the commu, n it, of nations.<br />
It ale.: o-nine cma,, jority rule, for a return Lo lec. g ality<br />
for o" zettchnea x-: hi) te r,,, nori-' y, and' -or the ending of<br />
wa r a. S: ntions. If achieved6, it will be acceptuble to<br />
leadi. A" 4r icar: states, it will r=-move a fLester-ing sore w-. hich<br />
has t) j _-eat--en e in fcc Southern' Pfri ca it-h both the poison<br />
of ra ial w. 1ar a-cd great pow,, er conf lict.<br />
Therelis nc cuarantee thla these things aill happen, that the<br />
proces. s w,-ill s~ ce. Bu U T eli that the-re are reasonable<br />
prospecas a: o: r-cess. I bz. lieve_ th,-is for t-iwo reasons, first<br />
bDecau'Se thne z~ sOf seteetit envisages arc-essentially<br />
right in thmevsIn that th~ y afc bas. e-d on the principles<br />
that, thLerI. o imbab11We all the. people have therih<br />
to chooe \ nc shell1-govern them'~, and that the olovernxmerit so<br />
elected3 shul-ave reail controloe the aff--L: airs of the countr1<br />
Seco-c--I beie -the chnc es o7 success are good because<br />
such astlmr is in Terati-ns1 self: interest of_ the partizes<br />
c on c c I s thne o nI . a y i n w,: h ic h th suff--e r ing-a nd0<br />
blood shed end~ ured! by the people of Zimbab%. e can be ended.<br />
If the settle-en does i-ot succec'u, the prospect is for an<br />
intensification of: the -war,' a cgrea ter resort to Communist<br />
arms, and greater turmoul,. for th hole of Southern Africa.<br />
As far as the -whit-e ccounity of: tChat country is cond erned,<br />
it can hope for-a stable and peace-ful e&gt; istecnce, only as part<br />
of a m t-rca aeuns o c iec. Conti_ 4nu_, inc! warfJare will<br />
lead its ndaous. -i! gato Tihe PaL-iotic 1? roiit<br />
can hope to " articipate in the governing of the country<br />
on the bhasis of such asete n.<br />
The Front-line states have an interest in ending the state of<br />
war which fEorces them to accept sacrifices and threatens to<br />
involve them directly in other-peon) le's conflicts. Britain<br />
has an in-terest in ending a situation -which has perhaps caused<br />
it more international embarrassmient than any other over the<br />
last decade.<br />
The international community at large can only benefrit fmoml<br />
removing a potential source of confLlagration and great power<br />
rivalry. Australia, as a member of the in-: ernational<br />
community shares this concern for peace and stability in<br />
Southern Africa, and, as a member -ofL the Ccommc-onealth, vwe<br />
have a conce-rn with preserving its intecriy, and -with the<br />
Commonwealth proving itself as a constructive and relevant<br />
institution. G </p>
<p>T1he LusakLa confcrc-. nc. e has set a pi-occ,: ss in train. Vch a cJ~~<br />
international body could ha'., e achieved this? It is Our'Sr~~<br />
hope that thc i-rocro'o is conbL. Irnucd to a successfu" Ll cn~ i<br />
If th-e Rhodesia issue occupiedC the centre of the stage Lt..<br />
conference, it certainly did no-t monopolise attention. A Co:.<br />
deal else was done besides, and for the information ofAnonourabl<br />
e I table the final co-mmu-nique.<br />
Ons. of7 t*-e aor initiatives w%-as in the econom-, ic field, whr<br />
Al: zzrzalia 3--=-osed a omonethgroup of e.
c c, -: DrC 2e ns study of factors restraining growth. We put<br />
tih: nrcposal owrdin t-he cntext ofL th1 hitoi cLn<br />
that h-ev 0nolded the world's e-conomily ove-r the past few,, 6ecaclos.<br />
In the qua ftcr-1 cen tury a fte r the Secona Wor ld 1-ar). the world'<br />
e&gt;: perieiaced-a period of unprecedeonted econo-Mic growth. The<br />
GDre~ art~~ 10o rloe ytewr ad created a huge<br />
pent-cUo dem-and for consume-. r ODS. That, together w ith i) c<br />
!-k--rsh--ll -Plan, the widesure~ ad adoption of Keynesian policies<br />
and the raziD'C int4-1-0 juI-io of new technology, led to a<br />
sustai-ned usvrg in economic ai-. owth ar&amp; i real income in thc-<br />
Oevelc-. ing countries as w,. ell1 as in the industrialised world.<br />
In thCz-e z the mnaterial conditions of the mass of pol<br />
in Wet-oieiswstransformed. utthe very success:.<br />
of that Pr1ocess me.-ant that by,, the mid-196% ' s concdlitions wr<br />
enn~ a ngadby the ear-. ly 1970 ' s the consumj-er boom was cl(-Ear~ y<br />
.1c cown.<br />
At thn e sam: Te -time, there emerged increasin~ g impediments to<br />
enterpri se and investment. Higch inflation was becoming beilt<br />
into0 the major e-conomies; uthrmoves to protection were<br />
bu-greater restraints to trade. Governmeonts condi-tioned<br />
to belevinq that Keynesian rolicieOs were the answer to all<br />
problems Stubbornly continued to pursue-those policies, e~ ispite<br />
the ons! Et of in-flation, encourag7ed by electorates increasi-ngly<br />
accustomec to believing that governments could provide for) i all<br />
needs.<br />
The extraordinary grow., th of the period came to be taken for<br />
granted. Increasingly, unrealistic demands were made on I<br />
economies, particularly by -tradie union movements which calme to<br />
exercise unprecedentecd power, and it became fashionable to<br />
decry growth and to place impediments in its path.<br />
An increasingly formiaabJle system-i of statutory road blocks<br />
wer -plceidn the way of developmn-n ivsment. Very<br />
demanding environmental laws, harsh trade practicecs legislation,<br />
prices justification regulations, and thedeelpmntan<br />
investment policies pursued by many countries have actecd as<br />
impediments to economic growth. Mlany investmfient opportunities<br />
which had been highly attractive twenty years ago now beca-, e<br />
uneconomic. The result of all t-his is that in. recant years the growvth in<br />
world trade has fallen to half of wha-t it Was in previo-us<br />
decades, from eight percent to four pecn. A further con, Z.<br />
to growth is slow rates of do'iclop-mcnt iJr a numnber of e'lcin<br />
countries. </p>
<p>Australia' s exporien-Coe\ J the, n'uwlv InIdC ~ 1LI S i-. inc ciaY<br />
hac: i; shown us th,. t. as Sloon as Lhey L-o._ 1X1f: eCono110i. cal 1, tr (: Cr<br />
both ways gr v:\ er% rapid ly Dur;' 197h 0 howecr<br />
it a. s d o f a c thechlne anc; o P!) or tu I of grca Lur t~<br />
with ne%, ly inutil. sn countries Many, ma-or dvc e u ions:<br />
beccuno fe,-arfuil anmd turned to qrcaLer protectionism..<br />
We ~ ee~ av~ e~ of this i~ n the $ 25 billion , ipent by Iesteril<br />
an&amp; 4s~~ Oio tni. c reon. wage anci cxpDa rt Sulba-idies the use of<br />
voi:~ c;' retr<. tagithsents="" dndt="" the="" conorla:="" o="" of=""></.>
: s ard sS Tj~ j 5 is no'. onl1yj, s el1fish and wri. ong,<br />
t lCol_ ih 6n sh o rt si g ht-ed eonmo Jics fo-0r the growth-j of<br />
rkltinea oi econtr coul' well. be oneI of the keCys<br />
to rL i c rate of n po\:: n beinng e-_ xpr lenced by<br />
We r!) iva nations in the last q: re ofc the Lwenticeth<br />
It 1 la-tocat the conditions whc cncrated and! f ue-lled tWl<br />
grea c'rcw=,-th in th'ie last cqua-rter ce~ ntury have n o. 1ircl<br />
disc oe rcent assessm-z-, ents by interna-tional orcganisza.! iors<br />
for fl-h c terin outlook are -For acontinuation of sJlo! -rowth<br />
or eve a-'-hrdterioration ijn growth prospocLs.<br />
At 7 : c ofe Goe-rnt -! ocn-' sed a continuation of<br />
slo-w. c~ rc'c t1 n the global econoi-iy% wo-uld. fu_, rther damage tht~ E:<br />
pros-p-0; cs c-7 increasing livinrg standards in bo-th developed. and<br />
d e loe) In 7 counmtries, and could have a Q v7erse effects i~ n their<br />
Po_ a s; cial structur-es.<br />
Theya~ z th-at there oudbe cons iderableI advant-ace in a<br />
oa-.,-idrnotCmrowat exp-2rts that ~ focusses on thez<br />
constra-nt's to ecnmcgr-owth andl structural change. in develope,), id<br />
arid developingi nat'iOns, and ideontifisr. iicmaue<br />
necessary to reduce these -cons traintS.<br />
The grou-_ p is to report in time to assist Corunoniwealt-gcovTernrnc,,., ts<br />
in their preparation for the specizl session of the' U. N. Generjal<br />
Assembly in 1930, and the Govern-ment. has indicated to the<br />
CcOlCo . s u is txerobieio ava-ilab) le to serve on the group.<br />
I believe that Australia h as already set an exarrn. lE! in some areas<br />
of the way thiat constraints on growth can be broken down. 1* Wheca ve<br />
reac* ec inflation, and w-, e -, ill maintain our strong antk-i--in1fla : ionary<br />
policy. We have increasedl company prof itability, imp-i. oved.<br />
Australia's co: r,--titive position, andi strengjtheneid the dollar.<br />
Under our foreicjn investmeont policy admrinis-tered by the Foreig.-n<br />
Investment ReCview Board, last ye/ ar's priva-te foreign investmerib'L<br />
was the highest sinice 1971-72, andl in the June quarter, $ 1.4 billion<br />
prospcctive exponditure was approved.<br />
All these help to redluce itho impediments to o-ur natoa deeopet<br />
but there are miny other barric-rs to grow,, th withinl the global<br />
omy I hope that the reporr il addresq itself to these<br />
cons Lraintsf and recoa-j-end practical policios that can be pursu; a* c<br />
in order to promote grokw. th of the -jorld economy. </p>
<p>. rhe, discussion of the Aus tralineoi inii c i-ve an<br />
imiadc i l~: Heads of Lr-lsejtha toero~~ in crL'r i c<br />
aLahnned-o-thpberoorlbd. lienmesiss , wea ndf aca e, ilinc.: L11o0 0 ia. Eus iloisnt eonf -racnad. liJusr:,-, iLms a ti a tnl. c<br />
The eyes of the w,-orld were on the Cor:,, i cncalt h a t Lu s Eaka.<br />
Tt facC, hjj-c~ tCst. It plassed' thaL tc'st a-' d in doin-so<br />
prov---m-that it-ha; s the capaciL~ y to makec a Fma-jorcoribio<br />
in intrntin-=-affairs throuch',-the res-t ofti cetir'<br />
Onc c-the rslsof -hthLppun. sdain'a is that -the<br />
me be s of h Cc:-m coTnw.; ea11thI illJ. 1 sh1a rec a nc-cor i-J. de, 2ric e a -IC~<br />
as su-r anc,--I wh-i we ca-7n CoII,--vel a ciee, adC 1 amsr<br />
that k'-.: Stre1a-ans will warm-welcom the fact. th~ at the ncet<br />
Conr~:~ cthiledsof Government conference waill be held in<br />
thlis cou--ntry. o 0 1) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
