<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5064</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/06/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005064.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
RLEJjXAUSTL<br />
A, ' I<br />
PRIME MVINISTE~ R<br />
FOR MEDIA 10 JUNE 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Australians today, perhaps more than ever before, care about<br />
the physical shape and face of our land. Australia is fortunate<br />
in still possessing a range of wilderness areas which contain<br />
frag~ ile and complex environments.<br />
Australia, too, is the last sanctuary on earth for many natural<br />
species. In a real sense we are the custodians of their<br />
survival. We want to preserve and protect our natural<br />
heritage. We kn:. iow that no person, no organisation, no Government Department<br />
can ever rebuild an island, renew a forest or a swamp or<br />
reSurrect an extinct species. No decree of Government can<br />
turn back the clock and save a lost species or a lost wilderness.<br />
That is why a Federal Government has a national obligation<br />
to make decisions on any issue that affects our heritage.<br />
This is a responsibility that your Govern-ment has accepted.<br />
Australia's record of action in the protection of the<br />
environment has given our nation a growing international<br />
reputation. A few days ago, Sir Peter Scott, Chairman of the<br />
World Wildlife Fund said " Australia has made a tremendous<br />
contribution to world conservation Australia has shown the way".<br />
During the week ! asked the Minister for Science and the Environment<br />
to look at the question of banning the imports of products<br />
from endangered animals listed under an international convention.<br />
Australia should not import products from species that are<br />
thrreatened with extinction. Why should we give this kind of<br />
tacit approval to the killing of endangered species.<br />
Accrdna1-', I have' asked the Minister to look particularly<br />
closedv at irnoorts of hides, skins and furs included in this<br />
internatilonal convention.-<br />
Also, this week I announced that there would be no further<br />
exploration for oil in the region of the Great Barrier Reef until<br />
the results of both short and long term research are known.<br />
We accepted the recommendation of the Chairman of the Royal<br />
Commission on this question. I gave a categoric and absolute<br />
guarantee that the Government would not permit any drilling on<br />
the Reef, or any drilling or mining which could damage the Reef.<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Government has asked the Australian Marine Science and<br />
Technologies Advisory Committee to recommend a program<br />
of research. We will be considering that recommendation<br />
in the Budget context.<br />
The Great Barrier Reef is a unique part of our natural<br />
heritage. We have acted to protect it.<br />
These decisions follow earlier action by this Government to<br />
ban whaling and to ban the import of whale products fromn January 1981.<br />
We are using the International Whaling Commission to argue<br />
strongly that our policy be followed by other countries.<br />
The Government has appointed Professor Ovington, Director of<br />
the National Parks and Wildlife Service, as the Australian<br />
Commissioner to the International Whaling Commission.<br />
Professor Ovington will lead the Australian delegation to the<br />
31st Annual Meeting of the International Whaling Commission<br />
in London next month. As a distinguished scientist and<br />
conservationist, he will advise the Australian Government on the<br />
conservation of whales.<br />
In April we Proclaimed the Kakadu National Park, one of.-the world's<br />
tru-1I1 great national Parks. The Act under which the Park has<br />
been established makes sure that traditional land owners are<br />
fully consulted in its management.<br />
In 1976 we moved to stop effectively mining on Fraser Island,<br />
tsis world's largest sand island. The issue here was simple.<br />
Were we prepared to watch mining proceed on a unique and<br />
fragIrile stretch of earth. The answer was a categoric no.<br />
The Government has acted to support the establishment of -the<br />
World Wildlife Fund in Australia. Australia also plays a<br />
leading role in worldwi'de moves to protect endangered species<br />
and migratory birds.<br />
My own concern for the environment and for conservation goes<br />
back many years. I can recall as a backbencher in the late 1950s<br />
expressing concern in the Government Party Room that the<br />
Princess Alexandra Parrot was in danger of extinction. Because<br />
of its beauty, this Parrot was highly prized by overseas<br />
aviarists. I was ' determined that this repulsive trade in birds<br />
sh11cuid s to: D. Subsequently I was pleased to learn in about<br />
Nov\ ember 1959 that the then Minister for Customs, Senator Henty,<br />
had convinced Cabinet that the export of not only the Princess<br />
Alexandra Parrot, but of all native birds, should be banned.<br />
C~ nsrvaton a tht_ tie assoehqgof a dirty word.<br />
It was not a popular issue, but that ban was a start.<br />
From it, the conservation movement went from strength to strength.<br />
It now commands, as it should, great popular support.<br />
Today the Government is playing its part to the fullest extent<br />
in protecting Australia's environment. We have a record of action<br />
to conserve our unique heritage. Wle are meeting the on-going<br />
challenge of protecting what can never be replaced. We will<br />
not falter in that task. 00 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
