<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8082</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR THE PRIME MINISTER OF MALTA THE HON EDWARD FENECH-ADAMI CANBERRA - 15 AUGUST 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/08/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008082.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON FOR THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF MALTA<br />
THE HON EDWARD FENECH-ADAMI<br />
CANBERRA 15 AUGUST 1990<br />
Prime Minister and Mrs Fenech-Adami,<br />
Dr Galea and Mrs Galea,<br />
Distinguished guests,<br />
Parliamentary colleagues,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
Earlier this year I travelled to Turkey with sixty<br />
World War I veterans to commemorate the 75th anniversary of<br />
the ANZAC landing at Gallipoli.<br />
For Australians, the heroic achievements and the selfless<br />
sacrifice of the ANZACs in the ill-fated Gallipoli campaign<br />
are immortal. For a young nation full of reckless valour<br />
and comradeship Gallipoli was a bloody initiation into the<br />
world arena.<br />
It is a little known fact that serving beside Australian<br />
troops at Gallipoli, and sharing their sacrifices, were<br />
volunteers from Malta. The barges which brought the diggers<br />
to Anzac Cove were Maltese built. Once on shore, our<br />
soldiers were sustained by supplies provided, in part, from<br />
Malta. And not least in importance for twenty thousand<br />
Australian troops wounded at Gallipoli and elsewhere during<br />
World War I, Malta, ' the Nurse of the Mediterranean', was a<br />
safe haven of rest and healing.<br />
The bravery of the Maltese people during the privations and<br />
terror of World War Two is also renowned not least by the<br />
Australian troops who served there or who visited there in<br />
transit to the Aegean and North Africa.<br />
All these efforts mean the Maltese people deserve, and hold,<br />
a special place in the hearts of Australians. Such bonds,<br />
forged in wartime, have been strengthened in peace. And you<br />
will excuse me, I am sure, if I give one uplifting<br />
demonstration of that statement.<br />
993(; </p>
<p>In 1946, a young Maltese girl began tending the graves in<br />
Malta of Australian airmen killed in the Second World War.<br />
moved by the sacrifice of the Australians, she also began<br />
organising wreath-laying ceremonies, single-handedly<br />
honouring the ANZAC spirit. For forty four years,<br />
Margot Bonello has continued in these quiet endeavours, not<br />
for profit or gain, but in simple recognition of the dignity<br />
of life. Earlier this year, Margot Bonello's work was<br />
recognised formally by the Australian people when she was<br />
made an honorary Member of the Order of Australia. Her<br />
story symbolises, poignantly and eloquently, the links of<br />
history and of friendship which bind Australia and Malta so<br />
closely together.<br />
Physically, of course, Australia and Malta are distant and<br />
dissimilar countries.<br />
Malta, in the heart of the Mediterranean, would fit some 200<br />
times into our state of Tasmania. The size of your island<br />
nation has inhibited your growth, while the vastness of our<br />
island continent has created different problems and<br />
opportunities. Natural resources have been our way of life<br />
for decades, while your people are remarkable for their<br />
achievements in a land without rivers, lakes or forests.<br />
What ties Australia and Malta together is not proximity or<br />
similarity, but the links of kinship and history that Margot<br />
Bonello symbolises links which your visit, Mr Prime<br />
Minister, will broaden and strengthen further.<br />
Your visit, of course, is only the most recent episode in a<br />
long tradition of movement of people between Malta and<br />
Australia. It is a tradition that dates back to the earliest days of<br />
European settlement of Australia. Our common heritage as<br />
British colonial outposts has studded our history with many<br />
bright figures -such as Count Bologna Strickland later<br />
Lord Strickland -born in Valletta in 1861, appointed Chief<br />
Secretary of Malta and then, in the first two decades of<br />
this century, Governor of Tasmania, Governor of Western<br />
Australia, and Governor of New South Wales, before returning<br />
to Malta where he became Prime Minister.<br />
Not the least of his achievements while he was in Australia<br />
was as a vocal and effective advocate of Maltese emigration<br />
to Australia. The steady growth of the Maltese community in<br />
Australia was such that in 1931 my predecessor as Prime<br />
Minister, Jim Scullin, attended Maltese National Day<br />
celebrations in Melbourne.<br />
Melbourne today has more Maltese residents than can be found<br />
in any city in Malta. Indeed, from the Mt Lyell copper<br />
mines on Tasmania's west coast, to the sugarcane fields of<br />
Northern Queensland, Maltese people have settled every<br />
corner of this country and they have done so, in<br />
particular, since World War Two. They have accepted the<br />
challenge that a new life brings and, through vigour and<br />
persistence, carved out new and productive lives as proud<br />
and committed Australians. </p>
<p>3.<br />
You begin to realise just how substantial that contribution<br />
has been when everyday Australian names reveal their Maltese<br />
ancestry. Darren Gauci the " Golden Hands" of horseracing one of<br />
Australia's premier jockeys.<br />
Jeff Fenech the triple world champion boxer a working<br />
class kid from Marrickville who has become one of our best<br />
known sporting heroes by taking on the best fighters the<br />
world could offer and beating them all.<br />
Joe Camilleri -a well known singer-songwriter.<br />
Mario Fenech -the captain of the South Sydney Rugby League<br />
Club and a fierce competitor on the field.<br />
Through the Catholic Church many Maltese Australians have<br />
made valuable contributions to the social advancement of the<br />
Maltese community here and to the broader Australian<br />
society. And I am particularly pleased to record that the trade union<br />
movement and the Australian Labor Party have repeatedly<br />
benefited from the dedication and commitment of many members<br />
of the Maltese Australian community.<br />
So I pay unstinting tribute on this occasion to the<br />
commitment and the great contribution made to Australia by<br />
its Maltese community. We are proud of them and you too, Mr<br />
Prime Minister, have reason to be proud of them.<br />
Of course, such achievements come as no surprise. The<br />
courage and determination which has characterised Malta in<br />
war and in peace are evident still in her Australian<br />
children. It is evident too in the way the modern Malta is taking a<br />
role in international issues which concern us all. The<br />
active and constructive role you are playing in<br />
international environmental issues attracts our<br />
congratulations and admiration.<br />
The discussion that you initiated at the United Nations on<br />
global climate change has led to close attention being given<br />
to the issue through forums such as the Intergovernmental<br />
Panel on Climate Change.<br />
Your foresight will, I am sure, lead to increased<br />
collaboration between us as we meet the environmental<br />
challenges that the coming years will bring.<br />
At the same time the Commonwealth will remain important for<br />
us both as a major forum for us to exchange views.<br />
1) 98 </p>
<p>4.<br />
Malta has also played a memorable supporting role in the<br />
dramatic evolution of closer relations between the two<br />
superpowers that we have witnessed in recent years. The<br />
first talks between Presidents Bush and Gorbachev took place<br />
at sea off Malta though I recall that your weather almost<br />
succeeded in consigning the two leaders to the same fate as<br />
that other, earlier, distinguished visitor to Malta St<br />
Paul, shipwrecked in<br />
Mr Prime Minister,<br />
At this time we are seeing many momentous events: tyranny<br />
replaced by popular rule, suspicion replaced by trust, the<br />
accumulation of weapons replaced by disarmament, and<br />
international discord replaced by dialogue. Notwithstanding<br />
our concern at current developments in the Gulf, these<br />
developments give us great hope for the future.<br />
Malta and Australia have not stood idly by during these<br />
dramatic transformations, but have played our parts, and<br />
continue to do so, in the interests of creating a more<br />
peaceful and prosperous world. In applauding that, and in<br />
celebrating the enduring people-to-people links between our<br />
two countries, let me say that you are a very welcome<br />
visitor among us. On behalf of all Australians I wish you a<br />
productive visit and a safe journey home. 999;<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
