<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5004</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER: TALK-BACK, RADIO STATION 2KA, PENRITH, NSW</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005004.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 30 MRCH 1979<br />
PRIME MINISTER: TALK-BACK, RADIO STATION 2KA, PENRITH, NSIV<br />
Question: It's my pleasure to welcome to the studio the Prime Minister of<br />
Australia, Mr. Malcolm Fraser. Mr. Fraser, we would like to thank<br />
you for particularly making yourself accessible to the people<br />
of the Western suburbs and the Blue Mountains in an open-line<br />
situation. Prime Minister:<br />
I'm very happy to be here, thank you.<br />
Quetion:<br />
We probably both agree, actually, that these same people know<br />
which issues are crucial to them and so I am not going to talk<br />
with you about politics. We will be taking a first caller in<br />
just a couple of minutes. I wonder if you would mind satisfying<br />
a great curiosity for us it's something that many people wonder<br />
about and probably when little boys are born there would be very<br />
few of them that got through to the age of 6 months when Mum or<br />
Dad or somebody in the family didn't say " one day he will be<br />
the Prime Minister of Australia'" and although they may say it in<br />
jest at the time, it's obvious that to * be Prime Minister does<br />
epitomise success. What of the experience,-the personal experience,<br />
of being Prime Minister would you be prepared to share with us?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think the important thing about the job, or the most rewarding<br />
in any sort of personal sense, is when things go right and<br />
policies are effective and that results in a better life for a<br />
large number of Australians. Obviously, there are difficulties<br />
difficulties with any job there are exciting times and there are<br />
times when it is just plain hard work. The part that I regret<br />
most I think about this particular job is the fact that you have<br />
to make very positive efforts to try and shut yourself away with<br />
your family occasionally.. It's very hard to get any sort of<br />
family privacy of a kind which most families in Australia have<br />
and believe is their right. If we ' went off for a holiday<br />
somewhere together there would probably be some cameras following<br />
and wanting to take pictures of the Fraser family at play.<br />
Question: Before you became Prime Minister, when you were thinking perhaps<br />
in terms as many politicians no doubt do did you find the<br />
concept somewhat awesome?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think the concept is slightly awesome. But you don't really<br />
think ' that's where I want to get, that's what I want to do<br />
as a politician'. I didn't. The only objective I had, in a sense,<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
was to do whatever job I had at the time as well as I could<br />
and whether that was representing my own electorate, which is<br />
the important first duty of any politician to respond to the<br />
needs and requirements, the concerns of his own people. To this<br />
day I still have a very large electoral correspondence. When<br />
you are a Minister alright, you've got a job so you just<br />
do that particular job as well as you can. I think if people<br />
are trying to plan, say ' look, I'm going to be in a certain<br />
position, I've got to get somewhere else' then you never are<br />
content with what you are in fact doing.<br />
Question: Does the pressure of being in such a pivot of public expectation,<br />
public attention and things like this, does it change your<br />
outlook on life. The pressures, the public image, the things<br />
that people expect you to measure up to does it bring immense<br />
pressure on you as a person?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
The thing that brings pressure is just the plain amount of work<br />
because there is a great deal and a lot has to be delegated to<br />
other people, to other Ministers. But there are always<br />
requirements on a Prime Minister and you never know when some sort<br />
of emergency might arise which nobody hears anything about but<br />
it is just one of those things that a Prime Minister has to deal<br />
with. That can land you in with several hours additional work<br />
where you have to give attention to it with other other Ministers,<br />
on top of what was already a reasonably full day. That sort of<br />
thing is always happening. You have to learn to pace yourself,<br />
know what you can do, know what you can't,. in terms of physical<br />
endurance and I think that's important because I have seen people<br />
in the Parliament just do too much. You go on doing too much<br />
for too long and you end up by not being able to do anything at<br />
all. That's not much help to you, your family, your Parliament<br />
or your constituents.<br />
Question: Probably not a speciality, of politicians. Probably 20 or 30 years<br />
ago it was much more easy for the public to differentiate between<br />
the philosophies and the principles of the major parties. These<br />
days it is not uncommon at all to overhear people in conversation<br />
saying ' well, it doesn't really matter to me very much who is in<br />
power because there isn't m -uch difference between the two'. It is<br />
often said in fact that the Liberal-Country Coalition has become<br />
more left and the Labor Party has gone more towards the middle<br />
themselves. Could you tell us in fairly simple, concise terms<br />
what the Liberal Party is all about? 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Yes. People have often said that Parties move in one direction,<br />
Parties move in another. I think the essential differences<br />
between the two Parties are really just the same as they ever were.<br />
Thc Liberal Party is all. about trying to create circumstanccs<br />
in society where men and women can go about their own lives in<br />
their own way and work out their own future; can plan for that<br />
future with confidence; make their plans for their children;<br />
and where individuality, I think, is encouraged to the maximum.<br />
The things that Government has to do certainly we want to<br />
and do in termis of welfare and programmes for disadvantaged people<br />
but we don't try and prescribe remedies for great groups of<br />
people. That's something that they themselves ought to seek and<br />
find for themselves.<br />
Question: Do you assume that basically, when you say people as individuals,<br />
do you assume that they all have equal opportunity to take<br />
advantage of whatever environment they are in, whatever is offered<br />
to them by the Government at the time?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well it depends what the programme might be. We've got many<br />
programmes which are in a sense designed for specific groups of<br />
people and which other people can't qualify for. Aborigines<br />
are eligible for a whole host of programmes which help with<br />
education, which aren't available to white people. In some parts<br />
of Australia that creates a problem. So there is not, in a sense,<br />
equal opportunity there. An Aboriginal stockman, a white stockman,<br />
on the same property in Western Queensland, being paid the same<br />
wage, but the Aborigine gets a very hefty subsidy if his kids<br />
are going to school. The white stockman doesn't. So these things<br />
can work in many different ways.<br />
Question: Could we possibly get back to basic principles for a second then.<br />
You've described what you feel to be the basic principles of the<br />
Liberal Party. How would you compare that with what the Labor<br />
Party is about?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think the Labor Party is much more inclined to prescribe<br />
solutions, because I think they have much more a view that they<br />
from Canberra can determine what is best for people. We basically<br />
reject that view. We believe that people ought to make their own<br />
minds up, make their own decisions and whether it is let me<br />
an example-support for local Government. We just say here is<br />
the support, you decide how you want to spend it. The Labor Party<br />
is much more inclined to say " here is the support and this is<br />
the way you must spend it". I think that has a different philosophy.<br />
To the maximum extent Governments need to trust people to look<br />
after their own affairs and make their own decisions and if<br />
necessary, their own mistakes. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Question: I think perhaps, in any case, you accidently mentioned the<br />
magic word and that was " local Government" and probably on that<br />
note, it is time to take our first call.<br />
CALLER: I'm very glad I don't have your degree of stress or your lack<br />
of privacy. I don't envy you those problems.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Oh well, it's voluntary, it's not compulsory.<br />
CALLER: I would like to compliment you on your efforts to keep inflation<br />
down. Our business is more-secure and it is keeping more people<br />
in work because of it. But I don't feel the same way about the<br />
Federal Government's efforts in health care. We have a national<br />
health bill, if I remember correctly, of something like $ 7 billion<br />
a year.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Health and welfare together would be something of that order.<br />
Don't tie me to the exact figures, but health and welfare, together...<br />
CALLER: A colossal...<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
is a colossal sum, it really is.<br />
CALLER: I know how concerned the Government has been and we have a deficit<br />
of $ 3000 million, $ 3 billion.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
About that, yes.<br />
CALLER: There seems to be a clear line of thought that if something can<br />
be done with the nation's health costs we may improve the<br />
nation's total financial situation very considerably. When we<br />
look at the health situation, heart disease and cancer are<br />
virtually at epidemic proportions. Half the population of<br />
the St. Mary's area are chronically ill, according to a Government<br />
survey with bad backs, nervous trouble, heart disease and high<br />
blood pressure and much of the medical research now that's coming<br />
out is pointing to lifestyle as being involved with health. Over<br />
and over again we find that diet, and particularly lifestyle,<br />
are being connected with health problems. Right now, you are<br />
only 18 kilometres from H-opewood Health Centre, Wallacia, where </p>
<p>CALLER: ( continued)<br />
there is 18 years experience, which is more than any other<br />
place in the country, of a lifestyle approach to health.<br />
The methods here have in fact been observed scientifically,<br />
or the same methods elsewhere have been observed, and yet in<br />
Australia there has been no interest whatsoever at Government<br />
level that I am aware of, taken of this type of approach to<br />
health which is so readily available to be looked at.<br />
What I would like to ask, when is the Government going to do<br />
something positive about looking at lifestyle and preventive<br />
medicine. Prime Minister:<br />
I think the points you make are very real one s they are very<br />
valid ones. The community health programmes that are operating<br />
reasonably well in-some parts of the country but more particularly<br />
in those areas where there wasn't an adequate general practitioner<br />
service are trying to do something about preventive medicine<br />
prepared to accept it if you say not enough but there is a much<br />
greater awareness. I would like to, if I could, maybe you could<br />
give it to the station get the address of the Health Centre that<br />
you are talking about so I could find out more about precisely<br />
what you are doing. I agree that lifestyle, diet and the way<br />
people live, the temper of modern society and the pace of modern<br />
activity, does have an effect on people. Nervous tensions and<br />
all the rest can arise out of these things.<br />
CALLER:<br />
May I quote two examples. One was a guest at Hopewood who went<br />
back to his heart specialist in Melbourne and he-wrote me a letter<br />
and said his heart specialist wanted more details did medical<br />
tests on the gentleman's return and found that cholestoral levels<br />
and blood pressure and the condition of his heart was so much<br />
improved that the specialist words and apparently he is a<br />
leading specialist were that there be more such centres and they<br />
should have Government support. This is really what I am putting<br />
to you.<br />
CALLER: I want to speak to the Prime Minister about my son. Mrs. lEllenyss.<br />
from Penrith. Mr. Fraser, excuse mie calling you Mr. Fraser<br />
the policy was unite the family.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Yes of course we do.<br />
CALLER: I have applied twice for my son in India and both times the<br />
thing has been turned down. / 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
How old is your son?<br />
CALLER: He is working in the Forest Department, lie is 44.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
In India?<br />
CALLER:<br />
Yes. He has worked in the Forest Department.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
How long have you been out here?<br />
CALLER: I'm 18 months here. My son has been here from 173 with<br />
two months staying the eldest boy he has been here from<br />
' 73 and my daughter has been from 1970 she is living in<br />
St. Mary's.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
What other relatives do you have in India?<br />
CALLER: I've got only two sons.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Two more sons in India?<br />
CALLER:<br />
Yes. Prime Minister:<br />
Are they married?<br />
CALLER: Yes. . We are trying for'-is the youngest and he has three<br />
boys and one girl. His eldest is 8 years.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
At the present moment,-when there is more unemployment than<br />
we want to see in Australia, there are limits on the total<br />
immigration programme and under that, therefore, we have<br />
priorities for certain categories of family reunion, especially<br />
dependents, and also people who have job skills where the skills<br />
are in short supply in Australia. But, without making any<br />
commitment what the outcome will be, again, if I can get your<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
name and address I will be prepared to follow that up to<br />
see if there is any way in which your son does come within<br />
the guidelines as they are at the moment.<br />
CALLER: I'd like to ask you why, in a time of high unemployment and<br />
when our neighbouring countries are having major skirmishes<br />
on our back door, why doesn't the Government reintroduce<br />
compulsory national service for all 18 year olds, for a<br />
period of say, 6 months?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
That is a possibility. It would be a very expensive possibility.<br />
When you look a~ t the straight out defence requirements, what<br />
we basically judge as one of the main priorities at the moment<br />
is to get as large a share of the defence vote as possible<br />
into modern and more efficient capital equipment armanents<br />
for the services. A few years ago we were spending less than<br />
five percent on replacement equipment and that is just not<br />
enough. Your equipment wears out. Now we've got it up to<br />
about 13 or 14 percent, but we still believe it needs to be<br />
increased more. Now that means the manpower numbers have been<br />
rising a bit but not all that much, and it also means keeping a<br />
tight rein on the current running costs. It would be possible<br />
to put everyone from the age group into national service<br />
for say six months. It would cost a great deal. There are say<br />
200,000 young people in an age group, and if-they are going to<br />
be in for six months that is, I suppose, 100,000 at a time.<br />
The Army would need to be very substantially expanded for<br />
training and other purposes. This is a very contentious<br />
subject because there are a lot of people who believe as you<br />
do that that kind of service would be very good for many<br />
Australians. There are others who oppose it quite bitterly<br />
as something which they oppose, which they think if authoritarian.<br />
CALLER: I just feel that the money we are putting out in the dole with<br />
these young fellows would be both themselves and our country<br />
would be a lot better off. They would reap a lot of discipline,<br />
which they need, to hold employment.<br />
CALLER: From time to time the subject of compulsory, or elected,<br />
voluntary retirement of public servants at age 55, both male<br />
and female, arises. Is this in fact likely to become a reality?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Not compulsory retirement at 55. We do have legislation which<br />
will be presented to the Parliament shortly and that legislation<br />
will make voluntary retirement at 55 a possibility at a slightly<br />
reduced retirement pension, superannuation, but also in some<br />
cases there would be the possibility of management initiating<br />
retirement at the same age. But if it is management initiated<br />
the superaniiuation penalty for going out earlier is not the<br />
same as one would expect. Now, this is something that applies / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
to the Commonwealth Public Service. There has been a great<br />
deal of discussion with the Public Service unions about it<br />
over the last couple of years.<br />
CALLER: If it does say, become a reality with Federal Public Servants,*<br />
would it then become a matter of the State decision, or a flow-on<br />
from the Federal Public Service?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
If it was going to apply to State Public Servants that would<br />
be a State decision, not a decision for us.<br />
CALLER: In the present unemployment situation, I would certainly endorse<br />
such a move, on a voluntary choice basis. I feel for it to<br />
be any other way it would only just more or less shift the social<br />
disadvantage from one age group to another.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think you can really compulsorily retire people at that<br />
sort of age. A lot of people want to work beyond the normal<br />
retiring age because they feel fit and that's what they like<br />
doing. It is, in a sense, rather cruel to tell people they<br />
can't work anymore. Also, of course, you've got to look at the<br />
other side the, in part, cost to the community because it is<br />
not always understood that for every thousand taxpayers ten<br />
years ago there were about 160 pensioners.. Now -for that<br />
same thousand taxpayers there are about 270 pensioners, all<br />
getting pensions at a much higher level. That's one of the<br />
reasons why taxes are so high.<br />
CALLER: In the new divorce law that was brought in by the previous<br />
Government, there are many areas that have fallen down badly.<br />
Because there is no fault, many innocent people and children have<br />
been put out of their homes. Others who were fortunate to<br />
keep the family home have to foreg6 maintenance and others<br />
have to sell their homes when the youngest child is 18. In a lot<br />
of cases these people can't re-marry because of the ramifications<br />
arising from these court decisions arid'I would like to know if<br />
the Government intends doing anything to rectify the situation<br />
in that area?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think this is a matter where there are many very divided<br />
opinions. I personally believe, as I think you do from your<br />
question, that the family is a very important and integral part<br />
of the community and community life. The changes in this area<br />
have generally not been regarded as ones for party political<br />
debate. They have been regarded as ones in which individual<br />
members of Parliament, by and large, make up their own minds. </p>
<p>9-<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
That being so, it is not so mnuch a matter for one particular<br />
political party to introduce changes because Members vote on<br />
these matters as their own conscience determines.<br />
CALLER: I would like to know why I have to pay provisional<br />
tax when I'm not working for myself.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
How are you getting paid. What sort of provisional tax<br />
is generally for self-employed.<br />
CALLER: Working on the piece-work wages. Like on piece work. Say,<br />
if I wanted to go onto sub-contract and I wanted to go on<br />
sub-contract,, why should I have to pay provisional. tax?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, you are not having tax taken out of your wages every<br />
week on the pay as your earn basis.<br />
CALLER:<br />
Don't you actually have to pay double there -like more or<br />
less the double the amount you are paid.-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
If you are not paying on a weekly basis, as you earn, as you go,<br />
everyone who is not doing that pays provisional tax. That<br />
doesn't any more than really try and put the provisional<br />
taxpayers in the same position as those who pay as they earn<br />
because they pay later. You pay when the financial year is<br />
mostly ended and you are paying, in a sense, for the year before.<br />
Provisional tax is only designed to put people on the same<br />
basis as those who pay on a weekly basis. I think that's fair<br />
enough really. I am a provisional taxpayer myself.<br />
CALLER: I would like to know when the Department of Defence will recognise<br />
the shiftworker in the Forces, for instance, my husband has<br />
been in the Army for 16 years and ten years he has spent working<br />
as a shift worker working approximately 80 hours per week and<br />
receives only about $ 2.50 per hour. To me this doesn't seem fair<br />
and in relation to a fellow who works 8 to 4 and five days a week,<br />
weekends off and etc. and etc.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
What's his job in defence?<br />
CALLER: He is a military policeman and I just feel that--I have written </p>
<p>10<br />
CALLER: ( continued)<br />
to the Department of Defence, Mr. Killen, and I would like<br />
to know if I write to the Department of course there are<br />
repercussions on my husband. They find out at work and<br />
you know.. . c gets extra duty and etc.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
When I was Minister to Army an awful lot of people used to<br />
write to me. They really did about a whole host of things.<br />
I would have known more about the details of this when I<br />
was Army Minister, or Defence Minister, and then we established<br />
a committee of inquiry into the pay and conditions of service<br />
of Armed Serviceman and that inquiry reported and was accepted.<br />
Since then there is a I'm not sure of the exact words but<br />
it is an Armed Forces pay tribunal and they determine the<br />
rates of pay and conditions for members of the Armed Forces.<br />
Without going and getting some advice I wouldn't know if the<br />
particular matter that you are talking about has been before<br />
the tribunal or is going to be referred to the tribunal.<br />
But to satisfy myself when I get back to Canberra I'll ask<br />
and find out.<br />
CALLER: I think it's only in general that the pays and-conditions are<br />
done. In this particular unit, I won't mention it, I will write<br />
to you if you would rather and put all the details in the<br />
letter, but their shift is on average 80 hours per week at<br />
work. That is quite a few nights and quite a few weekends and<br />
they get nothing extra for this. They can't get their meals<br />
there.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think you could write to me about that and<br />
CALLER:<br />
Will something be done about it if I do write to you?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well I can at least look into it, but refer to this conversation<br />
to make quite sure that the letter gets to me, because something<br />
between 2,000 and 3,000 letters a week come into my office.<br />
I quite obviously can't read them all-directly., they have * to<br />
be opened and sorted by other people. Just refer to this<br />
conversation and say that I have said to make sure the letter<br />
lands on my desk.<br />
CALLER: Back in 1976, Mr. Fraser, Dillinghams and Murphyores were stopped<br />
from mining and exporting mineral sands from Fraser Island.<br />
When the Dilligham Murphyores group claimed $ 23 million in<br />
compensation, you replied with a take it or leave it offer of<br />
a mere $ 4 million ex gratia. Now this has become a multi-million<br />
dollar dispute of international significance to the Australian<br />
mining industry. Why don't you refer this dispute to arbitration<br />
/ 11 </p>
<p>11<br />
CALLER: ( continued)<br />
the advice that you frequently recommend to striking trade<br />
unionists? Prime Minister:<br />
There are a number of reasons. That particular company was<br />
going ahead and mining. They knew that there was a Commonwealth<br />
appointed environmental inquiry. It was a well-based inquiry<br />
and it recommended that mining cease on Fraser Island, which<br />
I suppose there is no need to take it it's Fraser Island<br />
and I'm Fraser but it's got nothing to do with me: Some people<br />
have said in the past that it has so I just make the point.<br />
At the time I think Dillinghams had basically lost their contracts.<br />
They were in a court case, either with a customer or with a<br />
partner, I'm not sure which, and we decided that mining should<br />
cease, following the advice of the environmental inquiry.<br />
The legal advice to the Commonwealth was that there was no<br />
legal liability at all, but we did offer compensation to another<br />
company that was mining, and to Dillinghams, and also to a number<br />
of smaller contractors who were operating I think all of whom<br />
have accepted it. The other company mining in the area<br />
accepted the offer. The offer we made was $ 4 million, after tax,<br />
which something between $ 7 million and $ 8 million before tax.<br />
It was quite a substantial offer. In the United States, for<br />
example, there is no compensation, as I am advised, for costs<br />
put on companies, or problems caused for companies, by<br />
environmental legislation that's what my American friends<br />
tell me. Of course, if Dillinghams, which is a large and<br />
big multinational company, didn't like the offer, they have<br />
always been able to take us to the High Court. That's available<br />
to them. If other companies feel that they have been wronged<br />
by Government or by whatever, that redress is there.<br />
Dillinghams haven't availed themselves of that redress. What they<br />
have done is to try and conduct a press campaign. They have<br />
tried to get support from other people in the industrial and<br />
financial circles, especially overseas. I don't think that's<br />
the right way of going about it. Let me only say when I have<br />
been in the United States and Dillinghams is an American<br />
multinational corporation that whether it has been in New York<br />
or Washington, there has been no financial support from other<br />
corporations or bankers or institutions for their cause, knowing<br />
the facts. John-Howard,, the Treasurer, was over there just a<br />
short while ago and I don't think anyone mentioned the matter<br />
to him. Basically, we have made an offer that we think is a<br />
very fair one $ 4 million after tax, between $ 7 million and<br />
$ 8 million before tax is the equivalent and the other companies<br />
have accepted the offers made on the same basis. Dillingham's<br />
haven't. At any time they could have taken us to the High<br />
Court if they wanted to.<br />
CALLER: I would like to ask two questions if I may. Firstly, the<br />
Telecom charges for the outer Western areas, which includes<br />
Windsor and Penrith and Campelltown these areas you would be<br />
aware of. The previous Minister promised us that these areas<br />
would be included in the metropolitan zone before the next election.<br />
We realised that Mr. Staley is handling this in the best way that<br />
he possible can, but can you tell us what progress has been<br />
made in this issue? </p>
<p>12<br />
P~ rime Minister:<br />
Yes 1 can and there has been more delay than I would have liked<br />
and certainly more delay than Reg Gillard would have like on<br />
this particular issue. When that earlier statement was made<br />
by the former Minister, I think he was thinking of those areas<br />
only and then tying them in with the metropolitan area.<br />
Then when we and Telecom camne to look at this, we felt that there<br />
ought to be a total inquiry into local call access that it<br />
really in a sense isn't fair to all Australia just to make the<br />
decision for one part of Australia which is fairly close to<br />
the metropolitan area of Sydney. There has been an examination<br />
by Telecom of local call access over the whole country and the<br />
last advice I had was that that report ought to be available<br />
for examination by the Minister about the end of March. We are<br />
past the end of March. I haven't actually been told that the<br />
Report is available, but if we haven't got it-now it is certainly<br />
imminent. I know quite well that Mr. Gillard is not going to<br />
let the Minister or me forget the iact and he will be pressing<br />
for decision as soon as we can.<br />
CALLER: That's good news.<br />
CALLER: What are your views on school fees in Government schools?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
What sort of fees? Fees for general tuition or fees for<br />
special things?<br />
CALLER: Fees for buying equipment and whatever the school feels<br />
is necessary for a quality education.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think it's fair enough if parents make some contribution to<br />
make sure that the education their children is as good as it can<br />
possibly be. An involvement by the community, by parents and<br />
the school, the life and well-being of the school I think is a good<br />
thing. It's not something that should be shut and isolated and<br />
apart from the rest of the community. A financial contribution<br />
can be part of that. Let me also say that schools are much better<br />
funded than they have ever been in the history of Australia and<br />
the equipment in schools is much more than it has ever been.<br />
I was in a primary school sometime ago, and I'm not going to say<br />
where, but even for the five and six year olds it was full of<br />
electronic equipment which was fairly expensive. I must say I<br />
came away with the feeling that more importance was being placed<br />
on equipment and not enough on the quality of teaching. The<br />
most important thing in a school really, is a good teacher. / 13 </p>
<p>13<br />
CALLER: I believe legally, we can't insist that their parents pay<br />
fees, is that right?<br />
Prime Minister:.<br />
I would doubt it. The State might try and make it compulsory<br />
because these schools are run by the State. I wouldn't have<br />
thought it could be made compulsory.<br />
CALLER: It's just that we feel that with the non-Government schools<br />
getting aid, using Government funds, they can insist on fees,<br />
but we who are getting less of the Government's finance, cannot<br />
insist that these fees be paid.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
For Government schools they are totally funded by Government<br />
and the non-Government schools get some support but in terms<br />
of the money spent on non-Government schools,. taxpayers funds,<br />
it's much much smaller than the amount that's spent on<br />
Government schools. In many of the non-Government schools the<br />
resources available to teachers and therefore to the pupils<br />
is much much less than it is in Government schools. There has<br />
been a tremendous improvement in equipment and building of<br />
Government schools over, I suppose, the last fifteen years.<br />
It's real ' ly a transformed scene from what it was certainly<br />
when I went to school.<br />
CALLER: On a recent talk-back programme you stated that were it your<br />
decision, it would not be possible for unions to be heard before<br />
the Arbitration Court whilst they remain on strike. Would you<br />
explain what the Government would need to do to bring this<br />
about; by legislation or even referendum?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm not too sure that we would have the legislative power to do<br />
this and the Arbitration Commission, as you know,<br />
CALLER: It's independent, yes<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
has got a great deal of independence and it should have<br />
independence. Countries that do have the legal power to impose<br />
wages on people have never been able to do it very successfully<br />
and by and large decisions have to have the support of both<br />
sides. In earlier times the Arbitration Commission itself would<br />
not hear cases if there was a strike involved or if there were<br />
bans involved they would say " look, we will hear the case<br />
as soon as work is proceeding normally". ./ 14 </p>
<p>-14<br />
CALLER:<br />
That's as it should be.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
1 think it's as it should be.<br />
CALLER: There would be a great support for that and if the Government<br />
could get around to it, even if it meant having a referendum,<br />
it should be done.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
This is one of the things that we are looking at at the moment<br />
and as I think you also know, I said it wasn't in a talk-back<br />
it was in answer to a question in the Parliament that in<br />
relation to a situation such as in the Postal. Commission or<br />
Telecom where when there is an industrial claim people say<br />
" 1well we have some bans and limitations to give teeth to our<br />
claim",. well<br />
CALLER:.<br />
That makes it difficult.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
It not only makes it difficult, but if people aren't doing the<br />
work which they are paid for, we believe they shouldn't be paid<br />
or that they should be stood down.<br />
CALLER: Quite right.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
We are agreeing with each other. But I think there is a very<br />
real community interest and the community is always the silent<br />
third party in any industrial dispute. It's time that, I think,<br />
those that are involved in disputes not only thought of the<br />
community but said " look, let's give arbitration a go, let's<br />
trust the umpire for a change and s'ee what the umpire can do<br />
without industrial muscle, without bans and limitations, or strikes",<br />
because we would be a much, much better country if they would.<br />
only accept that.-<br />
CALLER: My name is Mrs. Bligh from Hazelbrook. Mr. Fraser, can you<br />
enlighten me on the following situation please? My son is 18 years<br />
old. He had a good education, but when he left college he was<br />
unable to get employment like many other boys. Ile qualified<br />
for the NEAT scheme, sponsored by your Government, and was selected<br />
to do a computer training course. Hie did this and 15 months<br />
ago he got his diploma as computer programmer. His lecturer<br />
said hie was really brilliant in this field. Despite the face<br />
that he has a diploma for this, also vocational guidance put him<br />
in the top 5 percent of the intelligence bracket, he has </p>
<p>15<br />
CALLER: ( continued)<br />
absolutely been unable to get any sort of employment in this<br />
field at all, because the magic word seems to be experience.<br />
Because lie hasn't got 6-12 months experience in commercial<br />
work he had six months on site training I might mention<br />
and his applications have been rejected. Now with all the<br />
Governmont departments going computerized, surely there should<br />
be a moral obligation to give some opportunity to the young<br />
people to get employment in Government departments. I even<br />
believe the Commonwealth Department doesn't even recognise<br />
that a ( inaud) course, which your Government paid for can<br />
I mention the place where he trained?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Yes. CALLER: From the ACIC that's the Advisory Computer Information Centrethey<br />
don't even recognise it when he has been down to get an<br />
interview. I was just wondering why . does such an anomoly<br />
exist and can you suggest any way of overcoming it please?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think the best thing would be if, maybe you could ring-up<br />
this station and give your son' s name and address, the details<br />
of what you have just told me over the airwaves, and I'll look<br />
into it and see what I can do.<br />
CALLER:<br />
Thank you very much indeed, I would greatly appreciate that<br />
because he is really brilliant in this work.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
You make sure you ring this station what is your name?<br />
CALLER: Bligh my son's name is Martin.<br />
CALLER: I think earlier you spoke to a lady regarding superannuation.<br />
In particular I think at that time you were talking about compulsory<br />
retirement. My question to you relates to the western area in<br />
particular where we have a terrible lot of people in the low-income<br />
area, and superannuation in fact represents quite an attractive<br />
proposition for them in terms of 5 percent contribution by them<br />
and 5 percent empl6yer. Later on I think it is a fact of life<br />
that later on they will be caught with a fixed income which is<br />
subject to inflationary spiral and as a result the superannuation<br />
is a think which helps them later in life in terms of subsidising<br />
their income. My question to you then is, have you considered<br />
a national superannuation scheme. If not, why not? And if you<br />
have,, is it the study you have started? ./ 16 </p>
<p>16<br />
Prime Minister;<br />
Oh yes, the study has started. There have expert reports on<br />
these particular matters. There have in the past generally<br />
been, I suppose, two major difficulties in the introduction of<br />
a national superannuation scheme which, like you, I believe is<br />
good in theory, if only w,. e could get it in: one, the cost,<br />
which would be very great it would be a significant increase<br />
in taxes paid by all taxpayers and two, the problem of covering<br />
the self-employed person is also one of some significance.<br />
There are some examinations still going on about this particular<br />
matter but there are very real difficulties.<br />
CALLER: Naturally, with a scheme such as this, you wo-uld expect some<br />
form of contribution by the people themselves. Would you see<br />
a superannuation fund of this nature taking the place of say<br />
pensions and that?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I suppose that could be one of the options, but there would be<br />
substantial additional costs. You might still have a position<br />
of some people who through life, for one reason or another,<br />
didn't qualify for a superannuation pension. But it is a complex<br />
matter and one which I don't think any Government, no-Australian<br />
Government,, has so far been able to see its way through.<br />
CALLER: I think you said that a study has been either started or nearing<br />
completion. When is the completion date for that study? Could<br />
you tell me?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
There are studies that have been completed but they've been<br />
examined within Government departments over recent times but they<br />
haven't yet got in front of the Government itself.<br />
CALLER:<br />
And up to that stage we can expect some sort of public disclosure<br />
of those studies the results?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Of the results, yes, certainly.<br />
CALLER: Do you intend proceeding with the voluntary youth community<br />
service scheme?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm sorry, do we intend to what? / 17 </p>
<p>17<br />
CALLER:<br />
Do you intend to carry out the voluntary youth community<br />
support scheme service scheme.<br />
Prime Mini ster:<br />
You are talking about the newv proposal that Mr. Viner announced,<br />
you are not talking about the CYS schemes, community youth<br />
support schemes, are you?<br />
CALLER: I'm talking about VYC the Voluntary Youth Community Service<br />
Scheme. Prime Minister:<br />
There are two programmes that in a sense fit that category.<br />
There is the community youth support schemes which are commonly<br />
known as the CYS schemes and they are funded in a number of<br />
communities. Ian Viner, as the Minister for Employment and<br />
Youth Affairs, is now looking to see whether we can't get a<br />
wider voluntary scheme involving the community. He has been<br />
having, over the last two or three months, extensive discussions<br />
with a number of people and community groups and he will be<br />
reporting to the Government as a result of those examinations.<br />
I certainly hope that it will be possible to introduce some<br />
programmes which will give more opportunitie s to young people<br />
who are not employed.<br />
CALLER: I'm concerned about the defence of Australia. I believe that<br />
we are only paying about 2 1/ 2 percent of the national income<br />
on defence whereas China and Russia are up around 20 percent<br />
and America I believe is about 7 1/ 2 percent. What's the good<br />
of having a good country that we've got, if we can't defend it?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
We have got quite effective defence forces and we shouldn't<br />
forget that. We've got some very good and very advanced equipments<br />
in the three services, and over the last there years we've been<br />
trying to get a larger share of the, defence vote, which itself<br />
has been increasing, into the purchase of more modern equipment<br />
which is very important for a defence force which inevitably<br />
because of the number of people in Australia, will remain small<br />
in size. Now Mr. Killen in this last week made a statement in<br />
the Parliament which indicated that we've already made decisions<br />
that involve a greater rate of increase in defence spending<br />
than we had in mind at the time of the last Budget. So that<br />
will lead to some greater degree of expansion and we are<br />
increasing the proportion of the vote spent on new equipment.<br />
I think your percentages aren't quite right. The Soviet Union<br />
spends about 12% to 13%, which is certainly very high.<br />
The Americans, you were right about 6% or 7% I don't know<br />
the Chinese percentage. The armaments that would concern us<br />
most of course would be the buildup of Soviet arms because it<br />
./ 18 </p>
<p>18-<br />
Prime Miniister:( continued)<br />
is so substantial, with naval forces that can reach anywhere.<br />
It is not just an Australian concern. All the western European<br />
Governments have expressed concern in exactly the same terms.<br />
But Australia ( inaudible) by herself, with 14 million people,<br />
is never going to be able to have a defence force that could<br />
stand against the might of a major power or a super power.<br />
Thercifure, we have a system,, of alliances the ANZUS Treat)'<br />
with the United States. That doesn't take away from us the<br />
responsibility of what we can and should and must on our<br />
own account. I agree with you, we do need substantial and<br />
significant defence forces.<br />
CALLER:<br />
Mr. Fraser. This is not a very important thing, I suppose,<br />
but why has the country changed to metrics?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
We changed to metrics I sometimes, with the fuss that has<br />
gone on wonder whether I did the right thing, but years ag o<br />
I had the original submission to Cabinet suggesting the change<br />
to metrics. I didn't carry it at the time. The next Minister<br />
for Education and Science did.<br />
CALLER:<br />
You didn't do it though?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I brought in a submission to Cabinet and it got defeated, but.<br />
my successor was more successful. He brought in another submission<br />
and was successful. The reasons is a simple one. Most of our<br />
markets overseas, the countries from whom ' we are buying equipment,<br />
and to whom we are selling things, operate. on the metric system.<br />
Now, if we want our manufacturers to well, it helps if they<br />
are producing in metrics because then it goes to a country where<br />
metric is the standard measurement and it makes it easier. Take a<br />
mechanic in a garage where he is operating on cars. If all the<br />
cars are metric he needs one set of spanners which does everything,<br />
but if hie's got British standards and American fine and metrics<br />
and I think there are some other measurements as well SAE then<br />
he needs a different set of spanners for the lot and it becomes<br />
inefficient and more expensive. Now, I know there are some things<br />
about metrics that people don't like. If you are used to buying<br />
a pound of beef, you want to be able to go on buying a pound of<br />
beef. You don't necessarily want to have to buy a kilo of beef if<br />
you are not sure what thiat -is.<br />
CALLER: I still don't.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm not either, I can promise you. I don't know what a kilometre<br />
is. I know what a mile is. The kids are all being taught<br />
metrics at school. / 19 </p>
<p>19<br />
CALLER: Not very well, sir.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, miay be not as wvell, but they are unot being taught feet<br />
and inches at all. So, through the passage of time, everyone<br />
will, I suppose, be more used to metrics and you and I won't<br />
be here with our memories of the older system. We are looking<br />
at some aspects of the compulsory elements which seem to be<br />
around at the moment which suggest that is wrong for somebody<br />
to sell you a pound of beef or a pound of bread or however<br />
bread is measured, because that just seems to me to be quite<br />
unnecessary. That aspect is being looked at.<br />
CALLER: I want to speak to you about the state of the nation and I<br />
am referring to the Income Tax Assessment Act No. 1, 1979.<br />
This hits out unintentionally on a wide range of legitimate<br />
business dealings which have nothing to do with tax avoidance.<br />
The Act defines tax avoidance so widely that even paying wages<br />
could be called a tax scheme. What I wanted to ask you was that<br />
would Parliament reconsider having another look at this amendment<br />
act, considering income tax, because it affects every business<br />
house in Australia.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Two things; I don't carry the precise memoi-y and details<br />
of the particular part of the Act that you are concerned about<br />
in your mind, so I would be grateful if you could do what<br />
other people have done on this programme and ring in to the<br />
station. Give me your details, your name and address and I will<br />
look at the details for you. We don't want positions that put<br />
unreal or unnecessary difficulties in the way of business.<br />
But at the same time we have been very very concerned about<br />
tax avoidance which has become a massive industry. I believe<br />
that some elements of the legal and accounting profession are<br />
really not acting in the best interests of the -reputation of<br />
their professions in promoting schemes which have cost taxpayers<br />
over the years hundreds of millions of dollars. That means<br />
everyone, to make up for<br />
CALLER: I know that the Government was very concerned over the current<br />
scheme and..<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
That's the sort of thing that can cost hundreds of millions of<br />
dollars and as a result of that everyone pays higher taxes because<br />
you lose out from a few wh...<br />
CALLER: But this particular piece of legislation is pretty dangerous<br />
in the fact that the law should be clear enough to create an </p>
<p>CALLER: ( continued)<br />
atmosphere of certainty in which busincss can operated, but<br />
this piece of legislation is so wide that it reminds me of<br />
when I was in the forces, under Section 39A of the<br />
( Interrupted by comrpere of show)<br />
CALLER: I would like to ask your opinion on what you intend to do<br />
about abuses of the current unemployment schemes,, such as<br />
the NEAT scheme in particular.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Do you have particular abuses in mind?<br />
CALLER: Yes I do. The NEAT scheme runs for a poriod of about 17 weeks<br />
and I know of several instances where people have been employed<br />
for those 17 weeks under the thought that they are going to get<br />
a job at the end of that time, but at the end of that time they<br />
have just been given the sack.<br />
Prime Minister;<br />
Under the NEAT scheme and under the that's training on the<br />
job? CALLER:<br />
That's right.<br />
Prime Minister;<br />
If there are employers who have become known to the Department<br />
for taking people under the NEAT scheme or under the Special<br />
Youth Employment Training Scheme, which is designed to help<br />
young people with some training for the same purpose but over<br />
a shorter geriod, if we find people who are just taking them<br />
for the period that is subsidised and then don't keep them on<br />
in employment, well then they just wouldn't be eligible for<br />
more people in the future wider the programmes.<br />
CALLER: liable for any sort of prosecutions?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think they are liable for prosecution but they wouldn't<br />
be eligible for anyone else under the programmes. Our only<br />
problem is to identify the employers who do that.<br />
CALLER: Who can we report these employers to, because I do know of some<br />
who~~ hav dneit </p>
<p>-21<br />
Prime Minister;<br />
You could report to Reg Cillard, you could report it to the<br />
Department the Commonwealth Employment Service.<br />
CALLER: There have been many questions lately about taxing company<br />
profits and this money then being taxed as income for<br />
individuals. There have also been many questions about foreign<br />
equity of companies and repatriation of large profits overseas.<br />
Why can't a tax policy be introduced along these lines<br />
say a company is 50 percent foreign-owned and makes $ 100 million<br />
profit. The $ 50 million going to Australians would not be<br />
taxed at the company level. The money that leaves the country<br />
would be taxed along the following lines: a flat rate because<br />
it is foreign-owned; extra on a progressive-scale of tax based<br />
on the amount repatriated and finally a surcharge for the<br />
profitability of the company on the amount invested. This would<br />
encourage Australians to buy shares in local companies and help<br />
increase local equity. The Government would benefit because people<br />
would take risks, employ people, with a resulting increase in<br />
demand for goods and services and give the economy a general shot<br />
in the arm. Multiply ( inaudible) would then take effect. The<br />
balance of payments problems wvould ease up<br />
Wouldn't this benefit the economy generally?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I , think these are complex matters but one of the things that<br />
we do believe we need to do and that is to tax all companies<br />
on a fair and equitable basis; the same sorts of rules for<br />
all whether they are Australian or foreign companies.<br />
000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
