<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4387</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT ON GOVERNMENT-ACTU-ACSPA DISCUSSIONS - 5 MAY 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004387.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 5 MAY 1977<br />
JOINT STATEMENT ON GOVERNNENT-ACTU-ACSPA DISCUSSIONS<br />
A useful exchange of views occurred on the 1977/ 78 Budget.<br />
There was discussion on the changed emphasis of the NEAT<br />
Programme with its stress on inpiant training and the<br />
contribution which the new Craft Scheme had made. While<br />
the unions acknowledge the improvements which had occurred,<br />
nevertheless they expressed some reservations about particular<br />
aspects of the operation of the * schemes and they will be<br />
submitting a paper on these matters.<br />
There was agreement on the desirability of tri-partite<br />
discussions involving the Minister for Employment and Industrial<br />
Relations and other Ministers where necessary on the development<br />
of manpower policies. It was envisaged that subject to<br />
consultation with the employers such discussions would occur as<br />
soon as the necessary preparatory work on all sides could be<br />
undertaken. Officials would be meeting to work out the agenda<br />
and it was accepted that substantive papers would need to be<br />
prepared by all parties.<br />
The ACTU referred to the legislation which the Government has<br />
already introduced bearing on the industrial relations area and<br />
there was agreement to continue these discussions at the<br />
meeting already arranged between the Minister for Employment and<br />
Industrial Relations and the peak Councils in Melbourne on<br />
Wednesday next, the 11th May. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
