<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4889</transcript-id>
    <title>ITALIAN COMMUNITY OF COORDINATION BALL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004889.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F78/ 235<br />
jA U S IALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 10 NOVEMBER 1978<br />
ITALIAN COMMITTEE OF CO-ORDINATION BALL<br />
The Italian Community is a very significant and much<br />
respected part of the Australian community. It was not<br />
always so significant. At Federation, about 95% of<br />
immigrant Australians were of British descent only some<br />
5,000 people out of 3.7 million were of Italian descent.<br />
That's about 1/ 8th of one pericent of the population!<br />
Australia today, with our very large and important Italian<br />
community, is far richer in diversity. Our customs, our<br />
traditions, our lifestyles have benefitted enormously from<br />
your influence.<br />
I know you are proud to be Australians, and equally proud<br />
of your own distinctive and rich culture. It needs to be<br />
said that Australian society is not weakened, it is strengthened<br />
by diversity. One can love Australia, and participate-fully<br />
in Australian life and at the same time preserve one's<br />
cultural heritage.<br />
I am particularly pleased to see Frank Galbally here tonight.<br />
As many of you would know, he has been three times decorated<br />
by the Italian Government for his services to the Italian<br />
community in Australia. He recently chaired a review of the<br />
services available to migrants upon their arrival in Australia.<br />
His review recommended a new deal for migrants and the<br />
Government, even in -these times of economic restraint, decided<br />
to adopt his recommendations.<br />
We are setting up sixteen centres which will give English<br />
orientation courses for new migrants; we are spending an additional<br />
million teaching English to migrant children; we are stepping<br />
up English classes for adult migrants; we are extending the<br />
Government's telephone interpreter service; we are going to<br />
establish a new Institute of multi-Cultural Affairs; and more<br />
funds are to be given to ethnic associations to employ their<br />
own welfare workers, health workers and people skilled in<br />
assisting children and the aged. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
This last initiative will be of direct benefit to many of<br />
the 40 Italian clubs represented here tonight. The Italian<br />
Community is noted for the strength of its community<br />
organisations. You have established a network of institutions<br />
sustaining your community, and I applaud your desire to be<br />
self-supporting, without undue reliance on government.<br />
For all these expenditures and programmes to be truly effective,<br />
the Government believes it is of crucial importance that ethnic<br />
communities themselves be closely involved in their implementation.<br />
Those senior officials who have been given the task of<br />
co-ordinating the new programmes are at the present time<br />
actively consulting a variety of ethnic and voluntary agencies.<br />
Australia has long offered to people of all nations freedom<br />
of opportunity to achieve and create, freedom to rise to the<br />
top of their professions and occupations. Over the last three<br />
years, the Government has been striving to restore Australia's<br />
capacities to offer people such freedom of opportunity. We have<br />
been striving to restore the economy, to give people renewed<br />
incentive and fair reward for achievement.<br />
This has been a difficult period we have faced tough decisions<br />
and we have made them.<br />
Australia is now on the threshold of a new era of growth and<br />
prosperity. We can realise the promise which the next decade<br />
holds for us if, through a partnership of Government and<br />
people, we can work effectively together, having confidence in<br />
our capacity and faith in Australia's future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
