<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22611</transcript-id>
    <title>Endeavour Scholarship Award Winners For 2007  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/11/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I was pleased today to present next year's Endeavour Malaysia Awards, Endeavour Postgraduate Awards and Endeavour Malaysia Research Fellowships to a number of outstanding Malaysian scholars.</p>
<p>The scholarships will strengthen educational ties between Australia and Malaysia, and help us to further enhance our long-term bilateral relationship through the cultural and academic exchange of knowledge.</p>
<p>Of the 13 winners for 2007, four were awarded Endeavour Postgraduate Awards worth $195,000 each, five received the Endeavour Malaysia Award worth $50,000 each and four received the Endeavour Malaysia Research Fellowship worth $25,000 each.</p>
<p>The Endeavour Program aims to strengthen education links between Australia and the Asia-Pacific region by supporting high-achieving students and professionals in their fields of study and research.  The Program also awards scholarships to Australians to study or conduct research in the Asia-Pacific region.  In 2007, two Australians will undertake study in Malaysia.</p>
<p>The Endeavour Program is part of the Australian Government's larger Australian Scholarships initiative worth $1.4 billion.  The initiative aims to build enduring people-to-people links within the Asia-Pacific region through the exchange of knowledge and the sharing of ideas.</p>
<p>The selection of Endeavour award winners followed a competitive and merit-based process, with eligible applications being assessed by panels of academics and professionals.</p>
<p> I was pleased that the Minister of Higher Education Malaysia YB Dato' Mustapa bin Mohamed was able to attend the awards ceremony.  This is a clear reflection of the value of the education relationship shared between Australia and Malaysia.</p>
<p>  Malaysian Endeavour Awards scholarship winners</p>
<p>Mr Hean Leng Ang - Endeavour Postgraduate Award</p>
<p>Ms Nasreen Badruddin - Endeavour Postgraduate Award</p>
<p>Miss Li Laine Ooi - Endeavour Postgraduate Award</p>
<p>Miss Guak-Kim Tan - Endeavour Postgraduate Award</p>
<p>Mr Keith Leong Yu Keen - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Mr Weikong Pang - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Miss Mangalam Sankupellay - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Dr Heok Yit Tan - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Mrs Yusmarhaini Yusof - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Dr Anna Abdullah - Endeavour Malaysia Award</p>
<p>Ms Lay Wah Lee - Endeavour Malaysia Research Fellowship</p>
<p>Ms Seok-Hoon Quah - Endeavour Malaysia Research Fellowship</p>
<p>Mr Adnan Zulkiple - Endeavour Malaysia Research Fellowship</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
