<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12753</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER    THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            DOORSTOP INTERVIEW, SYDNEY                </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/08/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Cricket tour.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What does this decision mean for Australian cricket?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I am very understanding of the decision that';s been taken, regrettable though it is. It was always up to the Board to decide whether the tour should go ahead.  As is known the Pakistani President telephoned me about this several weeks ago. I know how much the tour meant to Pakistan but I ask them to understand that the safety of the players was the paramount consideration of the Board. I hope that at some time in the not too distant future circumstances alter so that an Australian team can go to Pakistan. It';s a great test playing nation and I hope that alternative arrangements can be made for the test series to take place somewhere else. And I know from my discussion with the Chairman of the Cricket Board, Bob Merriman, that the ACB is willing to find an alternative and will try very hard to compensate for this necessary decision. I did know of it in advance and I communicated with the Pakistani President in advance of the Board';s announcement this afternoon.  It's regrettable but understandable.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think the Australian players will be disappointed [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think they will understand that it was apparent from remarks made by both Steve Waugh and Mark Waugh that there was an understandable concern. It';s difficult there and the situation is complicated by the fact that Pakistan has taken a very strong stand in the war against terrorism, and I feel for the Pakistan cricket authorities and for their Government because of that. But they will understand in the end the Board';s responsibility is for the safety of the players and I don';t think particularly in the light of recent events, they had any alternative other than to take the decision they have.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you be looking at the wider issue of the safety of Australians in Pakistan?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we';re already doing that. The Department of Foreign Affairs has issued quite a deal of advice and we';ll continue to follow that very, very closely.</p>
<p>   [ends] </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
