<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4337</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME  MINISTER WHEN TABLING THE REPORT OF THE STUDY GROUP ON YOUTH AFFAIRS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004337.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER WHEN TABLING THE REPORT OF<br />
THE STUDY GROUP ON YOUTH AFFAIRS<br />
Mr. Speaker, I table a report from tChe Study<br />
Group on Youth Affairs and seek leave to make an accompanying<br />
statement. In October 1976, my Government established a study<br />
group to examine services to youth and matters of co-ordination<br />
and communication. In particular, the study group was directed to<br />
repo~ rt on proposals that the Government should consider establishment:<br />
of a youth bureau and a youth advisory panel.<br />
The decision to establish the study group reflected<br />
the Government's concern with youth, and the adequacy of services<br />
for youth. During the course of its investigations the study<br />
group met with and received submissions from representatives of<br />
Commonwealth, State and Local Governments, voluntary organisations,<br />
youith workers and-young people.<br />
The study group concluded that young people warranted<br />
consideration as a group with special needs by Governments and<br />
other organisations. It suggested that there are a number of trends<br />
which affect youth in complex ways and deserve more careful<br />
attention. These include smaller families, higher female work<br />
force participation rates, longer periods of formal education,<br />
the employment market's emphasis on accreditation, the increased<br />
affluence of many members of the community, and changing life<br />
styles. The study group saw an urgent need for improving<br />
the machinery for co-ordinating and developing youth policy<br />
and co-ordinating the delivery of services to youth.<br />
It believes that in the future greater emphasis<br />
should be placed on meeting the particular needs of youth in<br />
general community programs, rather than developing more specific<br />
youth programs and services.<br />
The study group believes that there are important<br />
long term social and economic trends which have significant<br />
implications for young people and for the appropriateness of<br />
Government programs and services provided to them. </p>
<p>.1 -2-<br />
These trends and their implications need to be<br />
assessed more effectively. There should be improved co-ordination<br />
and consultation between Commonwealth departments and bet~ ter<br />
communication and consultation with young people.<br />
Mr. Speaker, the Government has noted the rep ort<br />
and has taken a decision to establish an office-of youth<br />
affaiLrs within the Department of Environment, Housing anti<br />
Community Development. The office will have direct access to the Minister<br />
on matters of youth policy and its functions will be to seek<br />
greater co-ordination and consultation between Commonwealth<br />
departments in relation to Commonwealth Government programs<br />
and p~ roposals affecting youth. To seek qreater co-ordination<br />
and consultation with State Governments, Local Governments<br />
and non-Government agencies in relation to Commonwealth<br />
progrcams or proposals affecting youth. To build up a research<br />
and information capacity to complement and increase the<br />
effectiveness of similar activities in functional departments.<br />
Advise on youth needs to assist those designing specific<br />
and g4eneral programs and services, and build up a channel for<br />
better communication with youth.<br />
The Government has also decided to establish a<br />
standing task group on youth affairs, comprising senior officials<br />
of relevant departments and including a representative of the new<br />
office of Youth Affairs.<br />
This task group will operate within the Cabinet<br />
committee system to ensure proper departmental consultation in<br />
the development of new policy proposals or proposed changes<br />
to existing programs which bear significantly on Government<br />
services to youth. It will provide a link between the office, other<br />
departments, and to Ministers.<br />
The concerns raised by young people through the office<br />
of Youth Affairs will be more readily brought under full<br />
consideration. The Government has asked the Minister for Environment,<br />
Housing and Community Development to investigate further the<br />
question of a youth advisory council or panel and report to it<br />
after the office has been operating some 6 12 months.<br />
It is essential that the new office be staffed in<br />
part by young persons, or others with special experience and<br />
skills, drawn from outside the service.<br />
Accordingly, the aim will be to seek an appropriate<br />
balance between career Public Service appointments, and staff<br />
engaged on a short-term basis from outside the service having<br />
regard to the particular requirements of the office. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Mr. Speaker, I believe that the Government's<br />
establishment of the Office of Youth Affairs and the<br />
standing task group demonstrates its resolve to keep<br />
in close touch with youth needs and issues and to see that<br />
its own programs serve young people more effectively.<br />
I table the report of the study group.<br />
Copies have been placed in the Parliamentary Library<br />
and I have arranged for copies to be sent to Honourable Members<br />
when more copies are printed. </p>
<p>[Date confirmed]    </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
