<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3465</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE NEW MELBOURNE HOTEL, SOUTH BRISBANE, SUNDAY 17 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003465.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY TIE PRIME MINISTER, THE IION. E. G. WIITLAM, Q. C. M. P.,<br />
AT THE NEW IMELBOURNE HOTEL, SOUTH BRISUANE,<br />
SUNDAY 17 NOVEMBER 1974<br />
WHEN I UNDERTOOK THIS CAMPAIGN IN SUPPORT OF<br />
PERC TUCKER AND HIS COLLEAGUES I MADE IT CLEAR THAT I WOULD<br />
BE FIGHTING THE ELECTION PRIMARILY ON STATE ISSUES. I CAME<br />
TO ENDORSE PERC TUCKER'S VIGOROUS AND COMPREHENSIVE POLICIES<br />
FOR SOLVING THE PROBLEMS OF QUEENSLAND AND PROMOTING ITS<br />
DEVELOPMENT. I WANT TO SEE THIS RICH, IIVERSE, EXCITING<br />
STATE MOVE FORWARD CONFIDENTLY* WITI THE REST OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
I WANT TO SEE ITS RESOURCES DEVELOPED SPEEDILY AND<br />
EFFICIENTLY, ITS PRODUCTS SOLD AIBOAD AT THE BEST POSSIBLE<br />
PRICES, ITS ENORMOUS A( RICULTURAL AND INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL<br />
DEVELu " D FI , j THE IENEFIT OF ALL ITS CITIZENS, ITS CITIES<br />
I'LANNED TO THE BEST ADVANTAGE, ITS TRANSPORT SYSTEMS<br />
INPROVED, AND ITS PEOPLE PROVIDED WITH TIE BEST EDUCATION,<br />
THE I3EST HEALTH SERVICES, TIHE BEST HOUSING AND THE HIGIIEST<br />
S'TANDARD OF LIVING TIIAT A MODERN INDUSTRIAL SOCIETY CAN<br />
AVi,, iD. IN MY CONCERN AND AFFECTION FOR QUEIENSLAND, IN NY<br />
KNOWLji, OF YOUR STATE AND MY LONG-STANDING ASSOCIATION<br />
WITH IT, I Y'IELD TO NO ONE NOT EVEN MR BJELKE-PETERSEN<br />
OR SIR GORDON CHALK.<br />
I CAME HERE WITI NO GRUDGE AGAINST YOUR PREMIEIR,<br />
AND FOR ALL OUR DISAGREEMENTS, I BEAR NO LASTING ANIMOSITY<br />
TOWARDS HIS GOVERNMENT. I HAVE DONE NY BEST TO WORK VITH<br />
IIIl FOR THEI GOOD OF THIS STATE. IF I POINT TO FAILINGS IN<br />
HIS GOVERNMENT'S PERFORMANCE I KNOW YOU WILL UNDERSTAND I<br />
HAVE NO DESIRE TO BUCKET QUEENSLAND OR ITS CITIZENS. </p>
<p>L i o<br />
l J" i<br />
-2-<br />
IF IT ERE POSSIBLE TO CONDUCT THIS CAMPAIGN WITHOUT<br />
RECRIMINATION OR BITTERNESS I WOULD GLADLY DO SO. I AM<br />
IAPPY FOR THE FACTS TO SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES. TODAY I SHALL<br />
CONFINE MYSELF TO SOME SIMPLE FACTS. THEY ARE MORE<br />
ELOQUENT THAN ALL TIE SLOGANS AND CATCIICRIES WE HAVE<br />
IEARD FROM THE PREMIER AND HIS SUPPORTERS.<br />
I ASK THE PEOPLE OF QUEENSLAND TO CONSIDER THE<br />
TRUTH ABOUT THEIR STATE, TO LOOK AT THE FACTS CALMLY AND<br />
THIOUGHTFULLY, TO FACE UP TO THEIR IMPLICATIONS.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN TALKS ABOUT INFLATION AND RISING PRICES.<br />
THE FACT IS THAT IN QUEENSLAND PRICES ARE RISING FASTER<br />
TIAN ANYWHERE ELSE IN AUSTRALIA. THAT IS NO ACCIDENT.<br />
IT CAN BE TRACED TO TIE POLICIES AND ATTITUDES OF THE STATE<br />
GOVERNMENT, AND I SHALL RETURN TO THAT IN A MOMENT.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN TALKS ABOUT UNEMPLOYMENT. AGAIN, THE<br />
FACT IS THAT IN QUEENSLAND UNEMPLOYMENT HAS RISEN FASTER<br />
OVER TIE PAST YEAR THAN ANYWIIEIE ELSE BY "' AR IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN OFFERS NO SOLUTIONS; HE CERTAINLY OFFERS<br />
NO COMFORT TO THE UNEMPLOYED. HIS SOLE REACTION IS TO<br />
IDEPRIVE TIEM OF STATE UNEMIPLOYMENT BENEFITS AND SEEK<br />
SCAPEGOATS IN CANBERRA.<br />
AS THE LEADER OF THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT I ACCEPT<br />
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ECONOMIC MANAGEMENT OF THIS COUNTRY. </p>
<p>I DON'T SHUFFLE OFF THAT RESPONSIBILITY ON TO MR BJELKE-PETERSEN.'<br />
AT THE SANE TIME MR BJELKE-PETERSEN CANNOT SHUFFLE OFF HIS<br />
OWN RESPONSIBILITIES ON TO NE. HE KNOWS, AS WE ALL KNOW, THAT<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT AND INFLATION ARE NOW AT CRITICAL LEVELS THROUGHOUT<br />
THE WORLD AND THAT FOR THE FIRST TIME EVERYWHERE, TO AN<br />
UNPRECEDENTED DEGREE, THESE TWO PROBLEMS ARE OCCURRING<br />
SIMULTANEOUSLY.' MY OWN GOVERNMENT HAS USED EVERY WEAPON AT<br />
ITS DISPOSAL, EVERY CONSTITUTIONAL POWER IT POSSESSES, IN THE<br />
BATTLE AGAINST INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT. WE WILL NOT LET UP<br />
IN THAT BATTLE. TIIE FURTHER ECONOMIC MEASURES I ANNOUNCED TIIS<br />
WEcEK IN PARLIAMENT WILL BOOST BUSINESS CONFIDENCE, SAFEGUARD<br />
JOBS AND LAY THE FOUNDATION FOR CO-OPERATION AND RESTRAINT IN<br />
DEALING WITH INFLATIONARY PRESISURES. WHAT HAS MR BJELKE-PETERSEN<br />
DONE? HE HAS DONE NOTHING. HE CAMPAIGNED AGAINST OUR REFERENDUM<br />
TO SEEK GREATER POWERS IN THE FIGHT AGAINST INFLATION. HE<br />
REFUSES TO USE. THE POWERS HE ALREADY FOSSESSES.<br />
LOOK AT TIE CONTRAST WITH OTHER STATES. IN<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA, WHERE THERE IS A LABOR GOVERNMENT, THE STATE<br />
HAS USED ITS POWERS EFFECTIVELY TO CHECK THE LAND PRICE SPIRAL.<br />
THIS IS SOMETHING EVERY STATE CAN DO. IF THE QUEENSLAND<br />
GOVERNMENT CO-OPERATED WITH US IN SETTING Ui A LAND COMMISSION,<br />
AS THE THREE LIBERAL STATES ARE DOING, WE COULD REDUCE THE<br />
PRICE OF LAND FOR THE HOME BUYER. IF THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT<br />
ALLOWED THE AUSTRALIAN -NATIONAL LINE TO OPERATE BETWEEN QUEENSLAND<br />
PORTS IT COULD CUT SHIPPING FREIGHTS. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
IF HE CO-OPERATED WITH OUR PLAN TO REDUCE ELECTRICITY COSTS<br />
IN QUEENSLAND WE COULD CHECK PRICE RISES OVER A VAST<br />
RANGE OF GOODS. HE REFUSES TO WORK EFFECTIVELY WITH<br />
OFFICIALS FROM OTHER STATES IN FORMULATING ANTI-INFLATIONARY<br />
POLICIES. THERE IS A LIMIT TO WHAT ANY GOVERNMENT CAN<br />
DO TO CHECK PRICES IN A WORLD-WIDE INFLATIONARY SITUATION,<br />
BUT MR BJELKE-PETERSEN I REPEAT DOES NOTHING.<br />
LET ME DEAL WITH SOME PARTICULAR ISSUES.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN TALKS ABOUT TRANSPORT. THE SAD FACT<br />
IS THAT BRISBANE HAS THE WORST, THE MOST DELAPIDATED<br />
URBAN TRANSPORT SYSTEM IN AUSTRALIA. MY GOVERNMENT WANTS<br />
TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT. WE HAVE OFFERED ALMOST<br />
MILLION OVER THE NEXT FOUR YEARS TO ELECTRIFY YOUR<br />
SUL I'BAN-RAILWAYS AND UPGRADE BRISBANE TRANSPORT SERVICES<br />
GENERALLY. NO NATIONAL GOVERNMENT HAS EVER MADE FREE<br />
GRANTS FOR URBAN TRANSPORT BEFORE. PERC TUCKER'S GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL WORK VITH US IN IMPLEMENTING THESE PLANS.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN'S GOVERNMENT WAITED A LONG TIME BEFORE<br />
ACCEPTING OUR PROPOSALS. AS FAR BACK AS 1957 HIS PARTY<br />
SC.:'. PED. THE PREVIOUS LABOR GOVERNMENT'S PLANS FOR<br />
ELECTRIFICkTION. THEY HAVE DONE NOTHING SINCE. IT IS AS<br />
SIMPLE AS THAT. MR BJELKE-PETERSEN TALKS ABOUT TIE DIFFICULTIES<br />
OF HOUSING. THE FACT IS AGAIN THAT QUEENSLAND'S RECORD<br />
IN WELFARE HOUSING IS TIE WORST IN AUSTRALIA. THEY HAVE<br />
DONE LESS THAN ANYONE FOR TIE PEOPLE MOST IN NEED OF HOUSING,<br />
AND EVEN LESS THAN LABOR DID IN QUEENSLAND IN ITS LAST YEAR<br />
IN OFFICE IN 1956-57. IN THAT YEAR LABOR BIJILT 1900 HOUSING<br />
CONMISSION HOMES. </p>
<p>LAST YEAR TILE I3JELKCE-PETERSEN GOVERNMENT BUILT 1460, YET<br />
HAD ALMOST' $ 12 MILLION UNSPENT IN IIOUSING. FUNDS FROM<br />
CANI3LRRAv DESPITE A 40 PER CENT INCREASE IN POPULATION<br />
SINCE LABOR WAS IN POWER.<br />
bllt BJELK] E-PETERSEN TALKS ABOUT THE MEANNESS AND<br />
WICKNEDNESS OF CANBERRA* TIM, FACT IS THAT QUEENSLAND<br />
HLAS RECEIVED MORE 1IlA'l) CASH FROM THE PRESENT NATIONAL LABOR<br />
GOVERMENT THAN IT HAS RECEIVED FROMI ANY PREVIOUS * GOVERNMENT<br />
IN HISTORY. NO AMOUNT OF HEDGING OR QUALIFICATION, NO<br />
TALK OF RESTRICTIONS OR STRINGS OR TILE VALUE OF MONEY,<br />
CAN ALTER TILE FACT THAT WE IIAVI BE-EN OVERWHELMINGLY<br />
GENEROUS. IN THLE LAST FINANCIAL YEAH OUR TOTAL PAYMENTS<br />
TO QUEENSLAND TOTALLED $ 739 MILLION. NOT ONLY DOES<br />
QUEENSLAND GET MUCH, MUCH MORE THAN z1IE DID FROM THlE<br />
LIW11-UALS IN CANBERRA; SHE GETS CONSID) ERABLY PMORE PER HEAD<br />
OF 1PO14' JL % TION THAN OTHER STATES ( JET NOW. QUEENSLAND<br />
RECEIVED MORE THAN 3382 PER HEAD) OF POPULATION IN 1973-74<br />
COMPARIED WITII .1343 P'ER HEAD) IN AVEL.* AGE PAYNENTS TO ALL<br />
STATES. LAST YE,' AR OUR GRANTS FOR'PilIMARY AND SECONDARY<br />
EDUC. ATION WERE UP 145 PER CENT ON THlE YEAR BEFORE, TER'ITIARY<br />
EDUCATION WAS UP 165 PER CENT, TECHNICAL EDUCATION 110 PER<br />
CENT, lve, 77ARE HOUSING 20 PER CENT, A13011IGINAL A]) VANCEIIENT<br />
NEAHLY 30 PER'I CENT. HEIALTHI AND WELFARE, ROADS AND URBAN<br />
AND HEGIONAL DEVELOPMENT IN QUEENSLAND ARE. ALL GETTING<br />
RECORD) AMOUNTS FROM MY GOVERNMENT. e* 1 6 </p>
<p>SO MUCH FOR THE HARSH TREATMENT OF QUEENSLAND BY<br />
THE SOCIALISTS IN CANBERRA. W-HAT OF OUR ATTITUDE TO QUEENSLAND'S<br />
. DEVELOPMENT? YOU HAVE SEEN HOV MR BJELKE-PETERSEN ' REFUSES TO<br />
CO-OPERATE WITH US IN MAKING TOWNSVILLE A REGIONAL GROWTH<br />
CENTRE.-ONE OF THE GREAT FUTURE CITIES OF AUSTRALIA, COMPARABLE<br />
IN SIZE AND IMPORTANCE WITH THE BEST PLANNED CITIES IN THE WORLD.<br />
I HAVE GIVEN MANY INSTANCES IN THIS CAMPAIGN OF HIS FAILURE TO<br />
CO-OPERATE WITH US IN INITIATIVES FOR THE PROGRESS AND ADVANCEMENT<br />
OF YOUR STATE. IN THE PAST TWO YEARS QUEENSLAND HAS MISSED OUT<br />
ON AT LEAST $ 50 MILLION IN FUNDS FROM MY GOVERNMENT BECAUSE OF<br />
THE ATTITUDE OF THE PREMIER. THAT IS THE COST OF MR BJELKEPETEROEN'S<br />
OBSTINACY. THE FACT IS AGAIN UNPALATADLE THAT.<br />
NO STATE IS MORE IN NEED OF BALANCED DEVELOPMENT THAN QUEENSLAND.,<br />
THE DRIFT FROM COUNTRY TOWNS TO* THE CITIES IN THIS STATE HAS<br />
REACHED A RATE UNPARALLELED IN QUEENSLAND'S HISTORY.<br />
MR BJELKE-PETERSEN REGARDS THIS TREND AS LESS IMPORTANT THAN<br />
HIS DISLIKE OF THE ELECTED NATIONAL GOVERNMENT.<br />
FINALLY, MR BJELKE-PETERSEN TALKS OF THE THREAT TO<br />
DEMOCRACY IN THIS STATE FROM MY GOVERNMENT IN CANBERRA. IN<br />
' ONE REMARKABLE PHIIRA3E HE TRIED TO PERSUADE YOU THAT THIS ELECTION<br />
WILL DETERMINE WHETHER QUEENSLAND " CONTINu S TO EXIST". WHAT<br />
IS THE REAL THREAT TO DEMOCRACY IN QUEENSLAND? THE RIGGING<br />
OF ELECTORAL, BOUNDARIES IN THIS STATE IS NOT A THREAT BUT A<br />
FACT OF LIFE. YOU KNOW THE STORY. IT IS A SHAMEFUL ONE.<br />
LAIO0R WON MORE VOTES IN THE 1972 ELECTIONS THAN THE LIBERALS<br />
AND THE COUNTRY PARTY BUT WON FEWER SEATS THAN EITHER OF THEM.<br />
A PREMIER WHO HOLDS OFFICE WITH 19 PER CENT OF THE VOTE IS<br />
HAIRDLY QUALIFIED TO LECTURE ABOUT THREATS TO DEMOCRACY. / 7. </p>
<p>MY GOVERNMENT HAS DONE MUCH FOR QUEENSLAND AND HAS<br />
OFFERED TO DO MUCH MORE. WITHOUT CO-OPERATION FROM YOUR<br />
GOVERNMENT WE CANNOT ACHIEVE OUR GOALS FOR THE PEOPLE OF<br />
THIS STATE. I HAVE SHOWN YOU THAT THE PROBLEMS YOU FACE ARE<br />
IN MANY CASES WORSE THAN THEY ARE IN THE REST OF AUSTRALIA,<br />
AND THAT YOUR DIFFICULTIES ARE INCREASED BY TIHE NEGLECT, THE<br />
COMPLACENCY, THE PIG-HEADEDNESS OF YOUR STATE GOVERNMENT.<br />
IT IS A GOVERNMENT WHOSE ATTITUDES ARE REJECTED BY<br />
EVERY OTHER STATE GOVERNMENT IN AUSTRALIA INCLUDING THE<br />
LIBERAL STATES OF NEW SOUTH WALES, VICTORIA AND WESTERN AUSTRALIA.<br />
IT IS A GOVERNMENT THAT CLINGS TO OFFICE BY A<br />
FLAGRANTLY UNDEMOCRATIC VOTING SYSTEM.<br />
IT IS A GOVERNMENT THAT WANTONLY FORFEITS $ 50 MILLION<br />
FOR DEVELOPMENT PURPOSES.<br />
IT IS A GOVERNMENT WHOSE RECORD IN MANY FIELDS IS<br />
THE WORST IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
IT IS A GOVERNMENT THAT TOLERATES THE STEEPEST RATE<br />
OF PRICE INCREASES AND THE STEEPEST RISE IN UNEPLOYMENT OF<br />
ANY ST-TE. IT IS A GOVERNMENT THAT REFUSES TO DISCUSS, TO TALK,<br />
TO NEGOTIATE, TO CO-OPERATE. </p>
<p>I TAKE NO PLEASURIE FROM THIS SORRY RECORD. I SUSPECT<br />
THAT IT ALARMS AND DISILLUSIONS MANY OTHER AUSTRALIANS AND<br />
MANY FRIENDS OF OUR COUNTRY ABROAD. I HOPE QUEENSLANDERS WILL<br />
FACE THESE FACTS. ON 7 DECEMBER THEY HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
VOTE FOR A CHANGE OF DIRECTION AND A CHANGE OF HEART. IT WILL<br />
BE A CLEAR CHOICE A CHOICE BETWEEN CO-OPERATION OR CONTINUING<br />
CONFRONTATION, A CHOICE BETWEEN PROGRESS OR CONTINUING<br />
BACKWARDNESS, A CHOICE BETWEEN RATIONALITY OR DOGMATISM, A<br />
CHOICE BETWEEN GOODWILL AND GOOD SENSE OR A CONTINUATION OF<br />
ONE MAN'S HATREDS AND OBSESSIONS, A CHOICE BETWEEN MATURITY AND<br />
ENLIGITENMENT OR THE FORCES OF EXTREMISM AND MALEVOLENCE. FOR<br />
THOSE WITH QUEENSLAND'S BEST INTERESTS AT HEART, FOR THOSE WHO<br />
RESPECT THE ENERGY AND IDEALISM OF HER PEOPLE, IT SHOULD NOT<br />
BE A DIFFICULT CHOICE TO MAKE. I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
