<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41570</transcript-id>
    <title>Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting and European Leaders’ meetings</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/04/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>This week I will travel to London to attend the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting (CHOGM) and then continue onto Europe to meet with leaders in Germany, Belgium and France.</p>
<p>This trip comes at a crucial time. Chemical weapons attacks in Syria and on the streets of England have sparked a strong and united response from Australia and our allies.</p>
<p>Alongside Prime Minister Theresa May, I will explore ways to further strengthen our cooperation on intelligence and security.</p>
<p>We will discuss ongoing threats from terrorism, foreign interference and malicious cyber actors, as well as uncertainty in the Korean Peninsula.</p>
<p>At CHOGM, I look forward to discussing how the Commonwealth can contribute to a fairer, more sustainable, secure and prosperous future. We will reinforce the global rules-based order and strengthen the resilience of our near neighbours in the Pacific.</p>
<p>I will then travel to Berlin to meet with Chancellor Angela Merkel, President Frank-Walter Steinmeier and key members of the German business community where I will advocate the strategic and economic benefits of an Australia – EU free trade agreement.</p>
<p>I believe in free trade because free trade creates jobs. That is the message I will be taking to Europe, as we fight for more opportunities for Australian exporters.</p>
<p>The economic and security relationship between Germany and Australia is strong – particularly in our defence industries. Just last month, I announced a $5.2 billion contract with German firm Rheinmetall to manufacture combat reconnaissance vehicles for the Australian Defence Force. This contract is an important part of Australia’s defence modernisation program.</p>
<p>In Brussels, I look forward to meeting with NATO Secretary General Jens Stoltenberg and the President of the European Commission Jean-Claude Juncker to discuss our security and trade relationships, including the Australia – EU free trade agreement, and Australia’s contribution to NATO operations in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>My visit will conclude in Villers-Bretonneux, where French Prime Minister Édouard Philippe and I will officially open the Sir John Monash Centre, a new museum honouring those Australians who served on the Western Front during the First World War. While in Villers-Bretonneux, I will also attend the Anzac Day dawn service commemorating one hundred years since Australian units bravely led a counter attack to successfully defend the village.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
