<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17434</transcript-id>
    <title>Get ready now for Australia&#039;s Paid Parental Leave scheme</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/10/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Education</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Parents and employers should get ready to benefit from the introduction of Australia's first Paid Parental Leave scheme on 1 January next year.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister, Julia Gillard, and the Minister for Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs, Jenny Macklin, today called on Australian businesses to register with Centrelink to provide Government-funded parental leave to their employees.</p>
<p>Already 158 employers have registered with Centrelink, including Holden and Bank of Queensland.</p>
<p>The Government has also made it easier for expectant parents to plan for their baby's arrival by opening applications for Paid Parental Leave three months before their baby's due date.</p>
<p>Applications opened on 1 October and in the first week 129 families applied, including 23 on the opening day of applications.</p>
<p>The Government today also launched an information campaign to make sure that families and employers are ready for the 1 January start date.</p>
<p>The information campaign will reach expectant parents in doctors' surgeries, at work, in their living rooms, online and in Centrelink and Medicare offices around the country.</p>
<p>The Australian Government's scheme will provide eligible working parents of babies born or adopted from 1 January next year with parental leave pay for up to 18 weeks at the minimum wage (currently $570 a week before tax).</p>
<p>The Australian Government's Paid Parental Leave scheme will help employers retain skilled staff and boost workforce participation.</p>
<p>To help women remain connected to their workplace when they take time off to have a baby, the Gillard Government's scheme ensures employers provide Government-funded parental leave payments to their long-term employees.</p>
<p>Parental Leave Pay should be delivered as a workplace entitlement, just like sick leave or any other form of leave.</p>
<p>Parents can find out more by visiting <a href="http://www.familyassist.gov.au">www.familyassist.gov.au</a> or calling 13 61 50.</p>
<p>Employers can find out more, including how to register to provide the Government-funded parental leave from 1 January next year by contacting the Centrelink Business Hotline on 13 11 58 or visiting <a href="http://www.centrelink.gov.au">www.centrelink.gov.au</a>.</p>
<p>Australia's first Paid Parental Leave Scheme will give families more options than ever before to balance work and family, and will help boost the economy by encouraging workforce participation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
