<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2657</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 3 AUGUST 1972 - OIL INDUSTRY DISPUTE - INTERVIEWER: PAUL LYNCH</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/08/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002657.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MACQUARIE NETWORR WEEKLY PROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE P. T. HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CIT, s1P. 3 AUGUST 1972<br />
OIL INDUSTRY DISPUTE<br />
Interviewer: Paul Lynch<br />
Q. Prime Minister, the oil strike is now officially<br />
over. I think the first thing we would like to know from<br />
you is where does the Government go from here?<br />
PM: I have already given the Presiding Officers of the<br />
House and of the Senate advice that because the strike is<br />
over it is not necessary to call Parliament together.<br />
Q. it has been suggested over the last week or two<br />
that perhaps the Government did not do the very best job<br />
it could do to settle this strike, that your Government<br />
could have done something more positive. How would you<br />
answer these suggestions?<br />
PM: I deny that. You first of all have to ask yourself<br />
what power we have under the Australian Constitution.<br />
And the simple fact is that we have only one power, and<br />
that is arbitration and conciliation, and that is in the<br />
hands of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission.<br />
When it appeared as though the Commission might have failed,<br />
I resorted to the only alternative that was available to<br />
us to prepare emergency legislation as Ir Chifley had to<br />
do in 1949, and I had to do in the case of the Stevedoring<br />
Industry in 1956. Consequently, I gave instructions for<br />
this emergency legislation to be prepared and I made<br />
arrangements, too, to call the House, that is the Parliament,<br />
together in order that the legislation could be put on the<br />
statute books. This was done in the interests of the<br />
community. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Q. This amergency legislation w~ a2 popared for possible<br />
use tomorrow morning. Now by that i would assumne that it<br />
is all reody whenever you need it from now on?<br />
PM4: Yes, it will be.<br />
0. Can you enact it without there being an emergency in<br />
the first place? In other words, can you add it to your<br />
armoury of laws to help out, or must you wait for the<br />
emergency before you can pass the law?<br />
P! A: We could make it permanent legislation and therefore<br />
it would not be necessary to introduce it as an emergency<br />
measurc. But usually this is regarded as an affront to the<br />
trade union movement, and for that reason, we p~ refer to<br />
handle it on an emergency basis.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, thera have been very strong suggestions..<br />
. Mr 14hitlam particularly on this programme last Monday<br />
night suggested that there has bacn collusion between your<br />
Government and particularly the foreign-owned oil companies<br />
in this country. The suggestion is that your Government,<br />
as part of its attempt to curb inflation has tried to fOrce<br />
the oil companies to refuse to negotiate with the unionists.<br />
What do you ay to that?<br />
PM: That is false, even dishonest. There has been no<br />
colluginn. in fact, 1 have remained separated from this.<br />
I have believed it was a matter for arbitration itself.<br />
So I can't ag~ ree with them,~ and Mr Hawke himself last night<br />
on television had to say that he couldn't prove there was<br />
collnsion, but he thought because of a combilnation of<br />
circumstances there might have bean. He answered for me<br />
the accusation made by Mr ; Thitlam. I say emphatically<br />
and I would say it over and over again there was none.<br />
But I would have to go a stage further. We were acting in<br />
the public interest, we were acting in accordance with our<br />
donstitutional power, and we were determined that we would<br />
do all in our power, first to end the strike, and secondly,<br />
to prevent too much unemp~ loyment and too much damage to the<br />
Australian people and to the Australian economy.<br />
Q. Apart from forming this emergency legislation, have<br />
you learnt anvthi ng in terms of ossible constitutional<br />
change or have you in retrospect decided that there was<br />
something else your Government could have done in the last<br />
two weeks which wasn't done?<br />
PM: I am what they call a federalist and consequently<br />
I have never been what could be regarded as a very strong<br />
believer in drastic changes to the Constitution. But I<br />
have learnt, not only as Minister for Labour and National<br />
Service but now as Prime Minister that there is one change<br />
to the Constitution that must be made in time, and that is to<br />
give the Commonwealth power to legislate in respect of<br />
industrial disputes when they are of a national character.<br />
And I believe the oil dispute and the failure in the transport<br />
industry is a clear indication that this is a national<br />
problem and that the Commonwealth Parliament should have the<br />
cGunstitutional power to legislate. / 3 </p>
<p>Q. And 1.-: oking back over thczf? last t isturbcd<br />
do you think thz-re is canything the Govcrnment<br />
could hIave c&amp; hn that it didn't do?<br />
PM: I don't think oi_ Th only action we could have<br />
t: aketrn was to call the Parlia-: mcnt toq.: Ather and to introduce<br />
ome rgcncy leagislatic-in to dt-; al with the kind of problem<br />
that emerqca' as ~ a result of the strike. We did that, and<br />
im ort: ! ntly, has to be remembcered that from theC moment<br />
I announced th1-at we wr rprdtro recall Parliament,<br />
so'. too, did all the other activities commence, As for<br />
example, ' 4r justice M~ oore then docided that he would make<br />
reccartuendations to the -t-q7o partCies for a resolution of<br />
the dispute and to got tChe men back to work. So, too, did<br />
you find other members of the trzde union movement,<br />
particularly leaders of tho trade union, and in one case,<br />
a Leade~ r in the Tracs Hall Council in Sydney, T,;, ere prepared<br />
to make recor'xcncdtions to theic Australian Council of Trade<br />
Unions that thev should let the men gn back to work. In<br />
other words, T believe that our action was the beginning<br />
of a process, and that process ended today when the men<br />
decided overwhelmingly to go back tro wc-ir% and to accept<br />
arbitration. Thanli-you very nuch Prime ' tinistcr. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
