<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9040</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP TO THE WORLD AFFAIRS COUNCIL ORANGE COUNTY CALIFORNIA, 17 NOVEMBER 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009040.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ADDRESS BY THE AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON P J KEATING MP TO THE WORLD AFFAIRS COUNCIL ORANGE COUNTY,<br />
CALIFORNIA, 17 NOVEMBER 1993<br />
" PRESENT AT THE CREATION OF TE<br />
ASIA-PACIFIC ECONOMIC COMMUNITY"<br />
I am in Orange County taking advantage of your kind invitation to<br />
me to speak because I am on my way to Seattle to attend a meeting<br />
about which I can tell you little.<br />
Mostly, when political leaders meet, our officials and diplomats<br />
f rom the best of motives are anxious that the soil is well tilled<br />
and the crop planted and fertilised and the political leaders are<br />
allowed near only when the harvest is ripe for picking.<br />
This time, President Clinton has organised a break-out.<br />
Leaders of the APEC economies will be left in a room for a day,<br />
without of ficial s, to discuss with each other visions for their own<br />
countries and for the region into the 21st century.<br />
I'm sure you are by now beginning to become familiar with the<br />
acronym APEC, the organisation just four year. old, which brings<br />
together the nations of North America and the Western Pacific.<br />
It includes all six ASEAN countries in South East Asia, Australia<br />
and New Zealand, China, Korea, Japan, Hong Kong, Taiwan, the United<br />
States and Canada. Mexico and Papua New Guinea are now expected to<br />
join.<br />
This leaders, meeting in Seattle is a remarkable event you will<br />
forgive me if I use the word " unprecedented" once or twice today.<br />
The people gathered, representing the most dynamic region in the<br />
world, have never met as a group before. Indeed, until a couple of<br />
years ago the idea of such a meeting would have been inconceivable.<br />
It has all happened with extraordinary speed. Yet not before time.<br />
One hundred years ago a US Secretary of State was proclaiming " the<br />
Mediterranean is the ocean of the past; the Atlantic is the ocean<br />
of the present and the Pacific is the ocean of the future."<br />
At the turn of the 21st century, I think we can surely say that the<br />
Pacific's time has arrived. For it is beyond question that the<br />
Asia-Pacific economy is, as a recent analysis. concludes, " the<br />
dominating fact of modern economic geography, the most striking<br />
event in the economic history of the 21st century".<br />
So when President Clinton proposed an informal APEC leaders meeting<br />
to be held in Seattle, I was delighted.<br />
3216~ </p>
<p>It was a sign of the freshness of approach and willingness to<br />
embrace a now vision which has characterised President Clinton's<br />
agenda. it was a sign which Australia and other countries in the western<br />
Pacific welcomed, of a new commitment to engage with the region<br />
with which the United States does more than half its trade, and<br />
where it will always have vital security interests.<br />
So while it is very difficult to predict what will emerge from the<br />
Seattle meeting, I am confident that we will look back on it as one<br />
of the defining moments in the remarkable history of the<br />
Asia-Pacific.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I have called this speech " Present at the Creation of the<br />
Asia-Pacific Economic Community", but the title begs the question<br />
of what a commuunity is.<br />
Are we talking about an uppercase " C"-style Community, like the<br />
familiar European one, complete with an uppercase " E"-style<br />
Eurobureaucracy, and aggressive protectionism against the rest of<br />
the world?<br />
Let me make it quite clear that I, for one, an not.<br />
But I am talking about something more than a random collection of<br />
countries which trade with one another to their mutual benefit.<br />
A community and I am now using a lowercase HC" is marked by the<br />
comprehension of common, and enduring, interests.<br />
Among the most important of those interests is the maintenance and<br />
improvement of the economic conditions which lead to shared<br />
prosperity. A community is marked not necessarily by a monoculture, as<br />
Australians and Americans accustomed to diversity readily<br />
understand, but by a sympathetic understanding of cultural<br />
differences. And, I might say, by an awareness that in cultural<br />
diversity there is immense dynamism.<br />
A community is marked by a shared history and a history in which<br />
points of contact and common endeavour are of greater interest than<br />
the threads of isolated achievement.<br />
And above all, perhaps, a community is distinguished by a shared<br />
sense of possibility, shared goals, a shared sense of. the future.<br />
That is what APEC can help do. It can develop something like this<br />
in the diverse Asia-Pacific region.<br />
And, in fact, in the economic area at least an Asia-Pacific 3217 </p>
<p>I3-<br />
community has already emerged -unplanned, unstructured and<br />
unheralded. In Seattle we will meet in a context which for the first time<br />
obliges us to think about common problem and opportunities, and<br />
how we may work together to underpin the extraordinary success of<br />
the Asia-Pacific economic community.<br />
This economic community is not something governments have brought<br />
about by a process of formal agreement like the EEC, NAFTA or our<br />
own agreement with our neighbour, New Zealand, the CER.<br />
It is already happening spontaneously, based on a market which for<br />
a decade has grown more rapidly than any other in the world, and<br />
which is likely to continue to grow at twice the rats of Europe.<br />
The two sides of the Pacific now form an integrated market of two<br />
billion people, accounting for half the world's production and<br />
nearly half the world's trade.<br />
The economies of North America and the Western Pacific are actually<br />
more closely integrated, without a regional trade agreement, than<br />
are the economies of Europe or North America, with a regional trade<br />
agreement.<br />
That is, the APEC economies as a group have a higher proportion of<br />
trade with each other than do the members of the EC or the members<br />
of NAFTA.<br />
Overall, the share of total exports of the APEC group to other<br />
members of the group is 66 per cent.<br />
In the EC, the comparable share is 61 per cent. In NAMT it is 42<br />
per cent.<br />
The European Community was created as a means of integrating the<br />
economies of Europe, lowering tariffs and increasing trade.<br />
By contrast the Asia-Pacific economic community is already highly<br />
integrated, already successful, and already benefiting from four<br />
decades of worldwide reductions in tariff protection.<br />
Yet as the recent report of the APEC Eminent Persons Group pointed<br />
out, 20 of the 24 members of the OECD increased their trade<br />
protection during the 1980s. And after seven years of difficult<br />
and often disheartening negotiations, the conclusion of the Uruguay<br />
Round is less than a month away and there is still no assurance<br />
whatever that we will get a worthwhile result. For the<br />
increasingly open economies of our region, there is no higher<br />
economic priority than an open and expanding world trading system.<br />
Our weekend meeting is an occasion to ponder the significance and<br />
the implications of what has already begun and what we can imagine<br />
it to be.<br />
3218 </p>
<p>I have no doubt that there are many things we can do as a group to<br />
increase trade and prosperity and to help private business make the<br />
most of the region'sa opportunities.<br />
And I am sure that Americans arm thinking along these lines too.<br />
As the Clinton administration says, if the US is to go about<br />
expanding its trade, increasing its competitiveness, renewing its<br />
global economic force, the Asia-Pacific region is the logical place<br />
to look.<br />
Californians are already well aware of the importance 0ñ f the<br />
western Pacific it is the market for a little under half of your<br />
state's exports.<br />
Since the mid eighties the trend rate of growth of US exports to<br />
the Western Pacific has been three times the rate of growth of<br />
Western Pacific exports to the United States.<br />
In less than a decade the portion of US exports which go to East<br />
Asia has risen towards one third.<br />
Not only is the Western Pacific market growing faster than others<br />
for you it is also buying a higher proportion of the most<br />
sophisticated US exports.<br />
Today US exports of elaborately transformed manufactures to the<br />
Western Pacific total over $ 230 billion, and they continue to grow<br />
rapidly. Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
This process of growth in the Western Pacific market has some very<br />
interesting characteristics.<br />
We see, for example, great changes in the structure of production<br />
in the region; labour intensive manufacturing industries which<br />
first went to Japan, moved to Korea and Taiwan, then to Hong Kong<br />
and Singapore, and are now moving to Malaysia and Indonesia and<br />
Thailand and the Philippines and on to the awakening industrial<br />
giant of China.<br />
As those industries leave countries with rising labour costs,<br />
others move in capital intensive high tech industries or<br />
knowledge intensive industries as we see now in Japan, and in Hong<br />
Kong, Taiwan, Singapore and Korea, as well as in the United States,<br />
Canada and Australia.<br />
The result is rapidly rising living standards through the whole<br />
region, which in turn changes the structure of demand and of<br />
consumption. Incomes and wages in Japan may now be as high as they are in the<br />
United States, and higher than in Australia. 3219 </p>
<p>Income per head in Hong Kong and Singapore is higher than it in in<br />
Ireland, and as high in Taiwan as in Greece and Portugal. Wage<br />
rates in manufacturing are higher in Taiwan and Korea than they are<br />
In Portugal, and higher in Hong Kong than in Mexico. Indonesia now<br />
has a middle class larger than the entire populations of some small<br />
wealthy countries.<br />
None of this has involved sacrificing the openness and<br />
international isation of the regional economies, or the trend to<br />
more and more liberalised markets.<br />
China's most rapidly growing businesses, for example, are almost<br />
always in the private economy.<br />
Malaysia, Indonesia and Thailand have all been growing rapidly in<br />
recent years because they have liberalised investment rules, and<br />
begun to deregulate their economies.<br />
We are familiar with similar stories in Korea and Hong Kong and<br />
Japan. By any standard this growth is impressive. And we are still in the<br />
early stages of the region's development.<br />
China is still only at the beginning of a transition that could<br />
well make it the world's second biggest economy sometime early in<br />
the new century.<br />
Indonesia, with its 190 million people, vast resources, stable<br />
government and enlightened economic policies has enormous<br />
potential. And the countries already achieving middle incomes, like Korea and<br />
Singapore, will within a very few years be joining the rich<br />
countries. Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
As I have indicated, the region presents great challenges and great<br />
possibilities. A reasonable estimate of what Western Pacific economies will need<br />
to spend over the next decade in ports, roads, bridges and<br />
utilities to support their continuing development is at least one<br />
trillion US dollars.<br />
McKinsey and Company tell us that the additional power capacity<br />
required in Asia by the year 2000 is more than 350 gigawatts, with<br />
a capital cost for generation alone exceeding $ U3400 billion. And<br />
there are similar requirements in hydrocarbons.<br />
Development on this scale will have a dramatic impact on the<br />
regional environment. So we will have to use the advances of<br />
technology and science to minimise the adverse environmental<br />
3220 </p>
<p>consequences of rising material living standards.<br />
If these are the challenges, the opportunities are there to build<br />
the roads and ports and pipelines; to devise and implement the<br />
technologies for a cleaner environment; to seize the opportunities<br />
for trade and investment.<br />
And while many of the responses will be local or national, they<br />
will be much more effective if we aiso have a well-designed<br />
regional organisation able to help governments remove impediments.<br />
APEC can be that organisation.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
As I said earlier, the growth that has taken place in the APEc<br />
community has been spontaneous growth.<br />
It has had no regional safety net of understandings and agreed<br />
processes spread beneath it, no mechanism for encouraging<br />
agreement, or for facilitating trade growth by removing<br />
impediments.<br />
The more sceptical business people among you may say that, given<br />
the growth that has taken place, we obviously don't need a<br />
framework for the region. But I am convinced that as time goes by<br />
this will be less and less true.<br />
It is already the case that the trade problems between North<br />
America and the Western Pacific could sometimes benefit from a<br />
discussions among all the parties, * rather than bilateral<br />
discussions between the United States and the individual countries<br />
of East Asia.<br />
We can benefit, too, from the adoption of common or compatible<br />
product and occupational standards, simpler and more uniform<br />
customs procedures.<br />
Earlier this year I proposed an agenda of discussions along these<br />
lines.<br />
Agreement on rules like these would facilitate trade and economic<br />
integration. Some of these discussions are already taking place among APEC<br />
officials, and part of the purpose of the Leaders, Meeting is to<br />
give them more political weight.<br />
Most of the work being undertaken in APEC is not being successfully<br />
done in other international institutions like the GATT. And while<br />
it doesn't discriminate against countries outside our group, the<br />
benefit will be mostly within. They are what I call " GATT-plus"<br />
initiatives. The area of product and industry standards Is particularly 3221. </p>
<p>important. A feaw weeks ago I convened a meeting of business people in our<br />
cabinet room to discuss APEC and what business hoped could be<br />
achieved within it. And one of the things we talked about was the<br />
impediments to exports caused by different product requirements and<br />
standards in the f if teen nations of APEC.<br />
In many product areas where large sellers and buyers have long-term<br />
relationships, standards and product descriptions are not a<br />
problem. But in other areas especially in manufactured food exports, in<br />
pharmaceuticals and in telecommunications conflicting standards<br />
and requirements are a significant difficulty.<br />
One manufacturer told us that the standards requirements in<br />
different markets added 5 to 10 per cent to the initial costs of<br />
entering an export market.<br />
The whole-problem is made worse because even where we have similar<br />
standards, one country's standards authority often doesn't accept<br />
the testing results of another's, and the same test has to be<br />
replicated right through the region. There is not much sense in<br />
that. Standards are also relevant in the finance industry, which I<br />
believe will be one of the great growth markets in the region as<br />
increasing wealth creates the demand for sophisticated funds<br />
management. Here the problem is not so much too many standards, as<br />
not enough.<br />
We need to have clearer legal and administrative structures so that<br />
funds can be reliably and prudently managed. Australia is eager to<br />
play a part, through our legal firms and particularly through the<br />
expertise of our Securities commission.<br />
Another area we could look at is standards and descriptions in the<br />
increasingly internationalised education market. I am told for<br />
example that we do not have reliable common descriptions of courses<br />
and standards in vocational education in the region a shortcoming<br />
we ought to be able to remedy.<br />
These are issues on which we can engage and produce results. We<br />
don't pretend that harmonisation of standards will be easy, or that<br />
once achieved it will revolutionise regional trade and welfare.<br />
But it will get us talking, and if we are successful it will make<br />
a discernible difference.<br />
Economic research commissioned recently by the Australian Trade<br />
Minister, Peter Cook, suggests that the value of removing<br />
impediments like conflicting standards in the Asia-Pacific region<br />
may be just as great as in Western Europe.<br />
3222 </p>
<p>f<br />
The reforms summarised in Europe 92 were over time expected to<br />
yield an increase in European GDP of around 3 per cent.<br />
Our research suggests that a program of standards harmouisation in<br />
APEC would yield at least MtJ400 billion boost to regional output<br />
an increase bigger than the annual output of all but tour of the<br />
fifteen APEC economies.<br />
I am convinced that everything that APEC does wiil be done stronger<br />
and more effectively it it draws regional business into its work<br />
I think we should have business people on our standards committee.<br />
for example, and energy committees and customs committees and so<br />
on. The private sector has created the Asia-Pacific economic community,<br />
and private business is best placed to know the impediments which<br />
governments should remove.<br />
There may veil be other things we can do in coming years.<br />
There is little doubt, for example, that some of the energy needs<br />
of the western Pacific could be most efficiently met through a<br />
network of natural gas pipelines that, in the most ambitious form,<br />
might extend from the north west of Australia to Japan. But no<br />
such network could be imagined, let alone built, without a very<br />
high degree of cooperation among governments in the region.<br />
The same goes for connecting up the separate power generation and<br />
transmission systems of the Western Pacific another logical and<br />
efficient solution to energy problems, but one which would need a<br />
degree of cooperation between governments which we are only likely<br />
to develop through APEC.<br />
At some point we may wish to talk about a regional steel agreement,<br />
or a regional electronics agreement or a regional food agreement or<br />
a regional services agreement.<br />
But on these major trade issues the consensus within the group is<br />
that we should await the outcome of the Uruguay Round of GATT and<br />
then see what is left over which could be usefully advanced on a<br />
regional basis.<br />
If the Uruguay Round fails or the outcome is completely<br />
unsatisfactory, perhaps we might think about some kind of regional<br />
round which picks up the Geneva agenda and attempts to do for the<br />
Asia-Pacific, for half of the world economy, what the GATT will<br />
have failed to do for the whole world economy.<br />
Some ideas on these issues were presented by the APEC Eminent<br />
Persons Group report chaired by Washington economist Fred Bergstel.<br />
In the longer term, the Eminent Persons Group report calls for free<br />
trade in the region a goal to which Australia heartily<br />
subscribes. But just how to get there and by what time is a 3223 </p>
<p>subject which in my view it is too early to determine.<br />
What really matters now is that f or the f irst time the governments<br />
of these rapidly integrating economies are talking about comisn<br />
problems and about their relationship to each other.<br />
Secretary Bentsen has proposed regular meetings of APEC Finance<br />
Ministers. I think that is a good idea. Although our economies<br />
are different in scale and historical experience, the problem we<br />
are facing are increasingly similar. Each of us has much to learn<br />
from each other.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
As I said at the beginning, for Australia's part, we are already<br />
committed to the Asia-Pacific region. During the last decade we<br />
have internationalised our economy through financial deregulation<br />
and tariff cuts.<br />
Since we began the reforms we have seen our exports trebled, and<br />
increase as a proportion of GNP from 13 per cent to 20 per cent.<br />
We have seen manufacturing exports rapidly increase, so that they<br />
are now consistently stronger than the rural exports for which we<br />
are still better known.<br />
And we have seen the proportion of our exports to East Asia<br />
increase from under half of the total towards two third@.<br />
Australia now sends more of its exports to Asia than does Japan.<br />
For us, there is no turning back just as I believe that for the<br />
United States there is now no turning back.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
The impact APEC can have goes well beyond its economic potential.<br />
AFEC's development will have a lasting -strategic impact on the<br />
Asia-Pacific region.<br />
I do not mean by this that APEC itself has or should develop a<br />
political or security dimension. other forums exist to fill those<br />
roles. But I have no doubt that APEC has the potential to change quite<br />
wfuonrdlda meinnttaelrlayc tt hew iwthay eianc hw hiocthh ert hea ncdo unthter iedse gorfe et hitos pwarhtic ho f thtehye<br />
understand each other's interests. And that, I am convinced, will<br />
have consequences well beyond the economic field.<br />
The process will be quicker and deeper if, as I hope, this first<br />
meeting in Seattle leads to a regular pattern of informal leaders'<br />
meetings, with all the opportunities that would open up for closer<br />
personal contact and understanding among the leaders of the APEC<br />
3224 </p>
<p>economies. By bringing the United States and Japan the world's two largest<br />
economies and the emergi. ng giant of China into a framework of<br />
multilateral economic cooperation, APEC will provide all the<br />
countries of Asia and the Pacific with the reassurance-that during<br />
a period of profound change in the world, this region will continue<br />
to be characterised by interdependence and engagement.<br />
Half a century ago a distinguished group of Americans around<br />
President Truman were present at the creation of the post war order<br />
an order based on superpower rivalry between the Soviet Union and<br />
the United States, on the creation of a united Western Europe, and<br />
the rebuilding of Japan and Germany as prosperous, free countries.<br />
Today I believe we are present at the creation of quite another<br />
configuration in world af fairs one which succeeds the cold war,<br />
which is directed to increasing welfare through economic<br />
prosperity, the Asia-Pacific economic community.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
