<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24825</transcript-id>
    <title>Delivering the Northern Connector</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth and South Australian Governments are investing $985 million to build the Northern <span style="line-height: 1.6em;">Connector project as part of our shared plan to deliver a fully upgraded North-South Corridor in a decade.</span></p>
<p>The Northern Connector will involve construction of a new six lane 15.5 kilometre road linking the <span style="line-height: 1.6em;">Northern Expressway with the South Road Superway and Port River Expressway, saving up to seven </span><span style="line-height: 1.6em;">minutes on travel time and avoiding six sets of traffic lights.</span></p>
<p>This world-class project will support on average 480 jobs a year during construction and unlock the <span style="line-height: 1.6em;">economic capacity of South Australia’s transport network.</span></p>
<p>With more than half of Adelaide’s freight task located to the north and west of Adelaide, the Northern Connector will significantly reduce heavy vehicle travel times and lower operating costs for the transport </p>
<p>This strategic freight route from northern South Australia to Port Adelaide will ensure our primary producers can get their products to market more effectively and at less cost, meaning more opportunities to grow their business and create jobs.</p>
<p>More than 52,000 vehicles are expected to use the Northern Connector on weekdays and the more efficient movement of freight and commuters along the North-South Corridor will drive economic growth and boost productivity in South Australia.</p>
<p>With planning works already well progressed, early works will commence in January next year, with major construction on the Northern Connector expected to commence by May 2016 and be completed by the end of 2019.</p>
<p>This game-changing project, along with our other major infrastructure investments like the Torrens Road to River Torrens and Darlington Upgrade projects will drive economic growth and help build a stronger South Australia.</p>
<p>A fully upgraded North South Corridor is also at the heart of revitalising Adelaide to stimulate urban renewal, strengthen local communities and create economic growth.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Government is now investing a record $2.9 billion to build game-changing infrastructure in South Australia which will support thousands of new jobs during construction.</p>
<p>This is the single largest investment of any Commonwealth Government in South Australian infrastructure.</p>
<p>The Northern Connector is funded on an 80:20 basis with the Commonwealth Government providing $788 million and the South Australian Government $197 million.</p>
<p>Both governments will continue to work together in consultation with industry on developing new innovative road pricing reforms for South Australia including the possible introduction of heavy-vehicle network</p>
<p>More information about the Northern Connector Project can be found at – <a href="http://www.infrastructure.sa.gov.au/nsc/northern_connector">www.infrastructure.sa.gov.au/nsc/northern_connector</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
