<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9290</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR 25 JULY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/07/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009290.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 22.6 . Jul .994<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RAY MARTIN, A CURRENT AFFAIR<br />
JULY 1994<br />
RM: Prime Minister, thanks for your time.<br />
PM-: Good, Ray.<br />
RM: Now the UN Commander said today of Rwanda, said today, that had<br />
countries like Australia responded more quickly there would be<br />
hundreds and thousands of people alive there. How do you respond to<br />
that?<br />
PM: Well, we were one of the first countries to respond. We put our first<br />
funds in there in April, that's now some months ago, and I think, and of<br />
course, we've been preparing for a substantial commitment to the UN<br />
Force which is about clearing the way for the refugees to go home.<br />
You see, the best way of deafling with a refugee problemh, Ray, is to get<br />
people to actually go back to their houses, and their villages. They<br />
won't do that unless there is a stable scene there, so we've been<br />
preparing to make the major commitment we made today there, and as<br />
well as that, as you know today we've made a major commitment to the<br />
humanitarian aid. Now, I had a cable in last Friday, in fact I'll read it to<br />
you it's directly from AI1DA-B that's Australian aid abroad officer<br />
said: " The situation in Goma has deteriorated since my visit there on<br />
Wednesday", and he said, " what is clear is that Goma is apocalyptic".<br />
Now that came in on Saturday. So, we've had a deterioration here, a<br />
very speedy one, unforseen really, in the last few days and what we've<br />
now decided to do is bring our commitment up to $ 1lOm in all, which is,<br />
which will be if not the largest, just about the largest, of all the financial<br />
commitments, and then we are sending two Hercules with water<br />
filtration equipment, and re-hydration equipmept, rehydration kits for<br />
8: 09 No. 001 P. 01/ 04 </p>
<p>TEL: 26. JuI. 94 8: 09 No. 001<br />
2<br />
people, and food aid and medical supplies, as well as the big force of<br />
over 300.<br />
RM: So this equipment is going into the camps, as against going into<br />
Kigali?<br />
PM: Going into the camps. Now, Kgli is where our officers will be with the<br />
5,500 strong UN Force. That's basically about letting the refugees<br />
come home. See, they're too afraid to go home, and that's why they're<br />
stuck in these camps with all of this destruction and death and<br />
disease.<br />
RM: What about those people, such as CARE and so on, who say that<br />
these people are too sick to travel Wfi~ t need is to prop them up<br />
for some months before we do anything back in Kigali?<br />
PM: Well, some will travel Ray, and some would need to be propped up. I<br />
think what we need to do is do both, and what we're trying to do is<br />
respond to both challenges along the term one of getting the people<br />
back into Rwanda, which is now made somewhat more likely and<br />
easier by the fact that the Patriotic Front there now controls the country<br />
and there isn't a war still raging so it's possible to resettle people<br />
and then, to get as much support as we possibly can in food aid and<br />
medical supplies onto the people, on a humanitarian basis, in the<br />
border camps.<br />
RM: Well, PM, if we accept that what you've done, that what the<br />
Government has done is very generous, would you agree though that<br />
for whatever reason we were pretty late in moving?<br />
PM: No, well, I think..<br />
RM: The western world..<br />
PM: we sent over an observer team about a month ago to see whether<br />
the UN plan was feasible. See, Ray, we can't put Australian troops in<br />
a position of jeopardy, and there had to be a feasible scheme by the<br />
UN that worked. We went basically to case that out, to see whether<br />
that would happen, whether it was feasible. In the meantime, the<br />
Patriotic Front has actually succeeded, so the temperature within<br />
Rwanda politically has dropped and militarily has dropped. Our<br />
judgement is now that the plan can succeed and we are committing<br />
over 300 people. I don't think we could have done it any earlier.<br />
RM. But do you accept what the UN Commander says, that had we been<br />
able to, for whatever reason, had we been able to get in earlier, the<br />
western countries, we may have saved hundreds and thousands of<br />
lives? </p>
<p>EL: 26. Jul. 94 8: 09 No. 001 P. 03/ 04<br />
3<br />
PMV: That could well be possible, but, I think, nobody foresaw the build up<br />
on the borders the number of people leaving the country, that have<br />
built up on the borders and, I think, it is to that we are now<br />
responding.<br />
RM:. Mr Keating, you have got a small family as lots of us have a young<br />
family. I mean, what do you say to them as they sit and watch<br />
television each night. How do you explain to your eight year old<br />
daughter that we can't just go in and feed them?<br />
PM: Well, I think, my family probably the same with your own Ray, they sit<br />
there very quiet when they see this, very quiet very sad and quiet.<br />
They know there is a bad thing going on here. I mean, I think, you<br />
know, some of that scenery over the weekend made me very<br />
determined, that I know Australians feel compassionate about these<br />
sorts of events and I wanted the Government today to respond to that<br />
compassion. I wanted us to be able to say well, we're there and we're<br />
doing our very best. Now, we have some influence, we have some<br />
financial power and some organisational ability and we are going to<br />
use it. So, the answer is my family's reaction, Ray, which was, you<br />
know, a sad one and one saying that, well, there is a certain<br />
helplessness about us in the face of this. I mean, the Government is<br />
not helpless and we've made, I think, the appropriate steps today to try<br />
and do our part as Australians.<br />
RM: I'd like to personalise that a little further. Obviously, if you sit there<br />
with your daughters and your son and your wife, do they say hang on<br />
dad, this Is terrible, this unforgivable, we've got to do something?<br />
PM: Well, the reports over the weekend, I mean, I was only with them<br />
probably on one occasion where the news reports came in which<br />
showed the big helicopter pictures of the people there and the close<br />
ups and there was just the, sort of, I think, quiet and latent expressions<br />
of sadness. I think they were overcome by the pictures. Annita and I<br />
were talking about it saying how dreadful this scene is and how we<br />
ought to be getting something cracking there as quickly as possible.<br />
RM: You've suggested that they impacted on you so much that while you<br />
would have come in anyway for the Cabinet decision today, that it<br />
made you more determined to actually make a serious effort than you<br />
were?<br />
PMV: Well, I think, more determined to be effective. More determined to<br />
make sure our presence was being felt. I mean, I think I know how<br />
Australians think about this. They would see this group of people in<br />
this desperate position with their loved ones dying around them and in<br />
their arms. Our sense of democracy and support for one another<br />
doesn't countenance those sorts of things. So", I wanted our response<br />
TEL: </p>
<p>TEL: 26. Jul. 94 8: 09 No. 001 P. 04/ 04<br />
4<br />
today to be one the Australian people thought was both appropriate<br />
and they felt proud about.<br />
RM: Alright, but the $ 10 million figure, which is a very significant figure in<br />
world terms, would that have been as high as it is had you not been<br />
affected over the weekend?<br />
PM: Probably not, Ray. Probably not.<br />
RM: Why is it, it seems, that, every time in this wealthy world of ours, this<br />
world of plenty, it is always an African catastrophe? It always seems<br />
to if it is not the Sudan, it's Somalia, if it's not Somalia, it's<br />
Ethiopia, now it's Rwanda. Why is that? What do you say to your<br />
children?<br />
PM: Well, I think it is about politics and it is about prospects for growth.<br />
There are enormous pockets of poverty and deprivation in Asia. But,<br />
the Asian economies are at least growing and gradually income<br />
standards are rising. This is not true in parts of the African continent.<br />
RM: If perceptions is what we deal in, it seems easier, somehow, to forget<br />
black Africans when they die, than white people?<br />
PM: Well, I think what Australians are saying today, certainly what I am<br />
saying and what the Government is saying and, I'm sure, all<br />
Australians are saying this should not be so. That, when there is a<br />
human tragedy, those of us who are able to respond should, no matter<br />
where it is.<br />
RM: It seems, as well, you know, people saying that where there is oil at<br />
stake, for example, the West responds far more quickly than when it is<br />
just, simply, black Africans dying?<br />
PM: Well, that, I think, is probably true. But, it is not right and it is events<br />
like these which test those sorts of attitudes.<br />
RM. Alright, we thank you for your time.<br />
PMV: Thank you, Ray.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
