<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9493</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP VISIT TO GERMANY AND THE NETHERLANDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009493.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 12/ 95<br />
E M B A R G 0 E D: 1700 Sunday 26 February 1995<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
VISIT TO GERMANY AND THE NETHERLANDS<br />
I will pay official visits to Germany and the Netherlands from 6 to 15 March<br />
1995. During a stop-over in Singapore on 5 March I will hold talks with<br />
Prime Minister Goh Chok Tong. I will take the opportunity of my presence in<br />
Europe to travel to Copenhagen on 12 March to speak at the United Nations<br />
World Social Summit.<br />
My visit to Germany will be the first by an Australian Prime Minister since<br />
re-unification in 1990, one of the central events in a period of profound<br />
change in Europe and the world.<br />
Germany is the world's third-largest economy and the biggest country in the<br />
European Union. It has an important and growing international role. It is<br />
Australia's ninth-largest trading partner, with bilateral merchandise trade<br />
worth $ 4.76 billion in 1993/ 94, and our seventh-largest source of foreign<br />
investment. Our relationship with Germany is very important economically and politically<br />
for Australia, but I believe it has not yet matched its potential. Both countries<br />
have changed greatly in recent years and I hope my visit will help to give the<br />
relationship a new direction.<br />
I am looking forward to discussions with Chancellor Kohl, President Herzog<br />
and senior ministers of the German Government as well as the state premiers<br />
of Lower Saxony and Brandenburg and the Governing Mayorof Berlin.<br />
An important element in my program in Germany will be my participation in<br />
the opening of CeBIT, the world's largest information technology and<br />
telecommunications exhibition in Hanover on 7 March.<br />
I am very pleased Australia has been chosen as this year's partner country at<br />
CeBIT, an honour given to only one country at each exhibition. More than<br />
150 Australian suppliers of information technology and telecommunications </p>
<p>software and equipment will be represented. This is an unprecedented<br />
opportunity for Australia and Australian manufacturers to demonstrate to an<br />
international as well as a European audience our capabilities as a supplier of<br />
world-class high technology and services.<br />
I will have further discussions with senior German business people and<br />
financial leaders in Berlin.<br />
In this fiftieth year since the end of the Second World War, I will also lay a<br />
wreath on the graves of Australian servicemen who are buried at the<br />
Commonwealth war cemetery in Berlin.<br />
In Potsdam, I will launch a new Australian Studies Centre at the University of<br />
Potsdam. This multi-disciplinary centre, which will work closely with German<br />
and Australian business and industry, will assist our objective of making<br />
Australia and Australian capabilities more widely understood in Germany.<br />
I will visit the Netherlands for official discussions on 13 March at the invitation<br />
of Prime Minister Kok. I will have talks with the Prime Minister and his senior<br />
Ministerial colleagues and I will meet senior Dutch business leaders. I will<br />
also pay a courtesy call on Her Majesty Queen Beatrix, who visited Australia<br />
in 1988.<br />
Australia has an old and important economic relationship with the<br />
Netherlands. It is the sixth-largest foreign investor in Australia and our<br />
18th ranking trading partner. In addition to our traditionally robust exports of<br />
primary products, Australia's exports of manufactures to the Netherlands are<br />
growing strongly. We also share a wide range of international interests.<br />
In both Germany and the Netherlands, I will be emphasising Australia's<br />
potential as a commercial partner and as a regional trading base for<br />
European firms wanting to enter the Asian market.<br />
I will visit Copenhagen on 12 March to speak at the United Nations<br />
World Summit for Social Development. Australia has been involved heavily<br />
in the preparations for this meeting, which a large number of Heads of State<br />
and Heads of Government will attend.<br />
I expect my discussions with Prime Minister Goh, which follow his very<br />
successful visit to Australia in September last year and further talks we had at<br />
the APEC leaders' meeting in Bogor, to focus on the wide range of regional<br />
and bilateral issues, including APEC, on which Australia and Singapore are<br />
co-operating very closely.<br />
CANBERRA<br />
26 February 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
