<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4835</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S INTERVIEW WITH SYDNEY JOURNALISTS, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004835.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
7T/<br />
IIW 25 SEPTEMBER 1978<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S INTERVIE WIH SYDNEY JOURNALISV; SYDNEY<br />
QUESTION<br />
What did you think of the Centrie-( Youth Job Centre,. Sydney)<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think it is a very good centre. Quite plainly a number of young peo.<br />
are coming in and finding jobs and I think the success rate is<br />
quite a reasonable one. There is obviously hope for improvement.<br />
QUESTION Do you think there is a need for more centres like this?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
This is something that the Government will be reviewing.<br />
It is a relatively new development, as you know, t-4tat has comein<br />
over the last year they have centres of this kind in<br />
virtually each capital city. Tony Street will be surveying the<br />
effectiveness of these kinds of offices I know; all the reports<br />
that I have had so far have been enthusiastic.-When I was<br />
having lunch down here I thought I would stop in and have<br />
a look for myself.<br />
QUESTION Was it merely a PR exercise for the Government or do you think<br />
you could give the young people some advice, and perhaps promote<br />
the Centre?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
It is not a question of a public relations exercise-It is a<br />
ma-tter of coming down and seeing for yourself what happens.<br />
Just in exactly the same way I was in one of the classes for what<br />
is called the Experimental Programme for Unemployed Youth.<br />
These are kids who have virtually never had a chance in their<br />
-lives, who are not well motivated and have no idea really what<br />
they want to do. The kids in this office did know what they<br />
wanted to do, did know what sorts of jobs they wanted to go for.<br />
Quite a number hadn't been out of work long they might have<br />
left a job lastE-Ffiday or whatever. In the other programmes,<br />
to see people being given a bit of enthusiasm, having a concern<br />
and interest in the future, maybe for the first time in their lives,<br />
I think is quite an exciting experience. The EPUI scheme,<br />
as it is called, is generally helping people whoT have never had<br />
a chance, coming from broken families, difficulty families maybe<br />
the teachers in the classes are the first people who have<br />
ever shown any interest in their future and well-being.<br />
QUESTION Did you discern any one thing from the Centre? I I </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER<br />
I don't think any one thing. I have discussed these Centres, and<br />
the workings of the Centres with Tony Street on a number of<br />
occasions and I have an impression which is very much the same<br />
as his and that is that the people going into this Centre are<br />
better motivated and in mant cases, I think, bettcr educatel<br />
than some of the young unemployed. Therefore, they have more<br />
chance of getting jobs and keeping jobs.<br />
QUESTION<br />
Have you revised your opinion of some of the young people being<br />
dole bludgers?<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think we all know that there are some young people who want<br />
jobs and find it difficult to get them. We also know that there<br />
are some people-who abuse the system. I have never had an<br />
omnibus opinion of any group. It is perfectly plain that in<br />
Australia at the moment there are a significant number of young<br />
people who haven't got a job and who would like to work and<br />
contribute-to-society.<br />
QUESTION<br />
How do you attract people who are less educated to these Centres.<br />
You mentioned that they were better educated...<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
I think these are but the normal Commonwealth Employment Service<br />
offices provide the general service. This office, and others<br />
like it in the other capital cities, provide a very particular<br />
service to young people. We all kow that there has been a special<br />
problem in that area. A number of the training schemes are<br />
designed especially to help people up to 25. One of the<br />
intiatives we took last year was to establish offices of this<br />
kind. From all appearances I think it has been a great success.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
