<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>472</transcript-id>
    <title>8TH DIVISION ASSOCIATION&#039;S ANNUAL SINGAPORE DINNER, SYDNEY 16TH FEBRUARY 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000472.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
8TH D11I310fi 630OCIAT12gla gi4aL J; iApgR&amp; DIN~ t huaa<br />
16th Fera 1962<br />
USnmeeh bZ the kZimWMinsterO te ! iL. Rk. t Mnl<br />
sirs I am very greatly honoured and very riatterad by your<br />
invitation to be here. I'm afraid tldat 1 haves been something of a<br />
nuisance over this matter because at first a date vas fixed your<br />
date, the 15th and then it turned out by the inscrutable wisdom of<br />
the electors ( Laughter) that certain things had to be done and I<br />
needed to have a conference of the Premiers, and so I had to put you<br />
to the sreat inconvenieance of altering, for this purpose, yesterday<br />
for today. 3ut all of you notable izarriors will undei stand that I<br />
eculdn't be here last night because, like tne apostle, I was<br />
" fighting wild beasts at Sp~ eus". Laughter$ applause)<br />
And even when we had rinished the Conference of Premiers<br />
this morning rather unexpectedly from my point of view because<br />
there dere a few Items st1u1 efst I pointed to the most important<br />
remaining one at five past one today and said, mNov I have a<br />
Conference this afternoon with the First Sea Lord of England" -who is<br />
visiting us on matters that are quite germane to your experiences<br />
" and I must be lown in Sydney to . ight, I have an Important ongageowt,<br />
so could vie meet at 2 o'clock*. Then, you know, remarkably enough,<br />
it tuned out that on* Iremier had to catch a plane at twop another one,<br />
had to catch a plane at 2.30 because,, you know,, when you ha-ve the money<br />
in the beg Y u don't hang around ( Laughter) You might be robbed,<br />
( Laughter) And I gave my celebrated imitation of a man to whom time<br />
was no object so long as It finished by four o'clock. In the result<br />
at ten past on e had concluded all our businessl ( Laughter) And<br />
went home and packed my bag and cam back to the office and tried to<br />
clean up some of the accuulations of le,; Itimat* business over the last<br />
two days, and then say the First Sea Lord, and then case down hers.<br />
Tomorrow morning I go back I's happy to tell you that I've made no<br />
appointment tomorrow until noon ( Laughter) and that, It'a happy to say,<br />
will not be with any 1' remier who wants money. ( Laughter)<br />
Sat tonight first of all I deeply approciate the honour you<br />
have done me In inviting me to ame I know of no trualific ition tVat<br />
I have to be here. -3ut in the second place Iviant to tell you how much<br />
I1 have enjoyed being here so far because e have heard two<br />
speeches which, to so, were very moving speeches by Dr. Fisher and by<br />
the famous and celebrated Gen. Gordon Jeto lpplause)<br />
Sir, the one concession that I must make be ' or* I say a few<br />
things that may matter a little more Is thist that having sat in<br />
conrerence with the Premiers and the Treasurers and with Treasa&amp; ry<br />
officials, viearing one suit all the week a~ nd -, ligrather baggy in<br />
it, as you might 1zuaginet I brought down a freshly pressed suit with<br />
ms and when I dent over and put It on tonight I found t . at the pockets<br />
4~ o 9 rull of papers. I thought " Now how odd. Zhat jaupers have I?"<br />
And all of a sudden ihen I looked at them I roalised that this must<br />
have been the coat I was wearing on polling night, ( Laughter) because<br />
the first piece of aper showed what at 10.30 was my 2.. stimate of the<br />
rnumor of seats I was losing; and at Ul o'clock I crossed that out<br />
and added a flow names to it; by midnight 1 had no more saats to add.<br />
It -was obviously a season of prayer 4nd faating. ( Laughter) And I<br />
thought " Now that's very intert-3ting" because this has all remirdled Me<br />
of what It is like to be on the verge of dereat -and perhap.,; that is<br />
something to r member on a night like this.<br />
I hope, you will allow me to say without making any invidious<br />
distinctions, how delighted I was when I arrived at this Tiotel tonight<br />
to be received by that great and pood marie Charles '-nderson. ( Applause) </p>
<p>I am, as you know, the last man to engage in party politics. ( Laughter)<br />
This is completely foreign to my nature. But I am told remotely that<br />
you have an election on in New South Wales not mine, tut somebody<br />
else's. I hope that without trespassing in the arena of party polities<br />
you will allow an to say that I don't understand how any electorate<br />
that had the honour to be represented by Charles Anderson should foigo<br />
it at a General Election. However, whatever happens to me, he'll be<br />
back. ( Applause) Now, Sir, General Bennett has tonight referred to a number<br />
of histori events all of which I know I can confirm. I thought<br />
perhaps I might just say this to you about them and I want to develop<br />
this because I want to demonstrate to you, if I can, how what appeared<br />
to be defeat has turned out to be of the most enormous significance to<br />
Australia. At the very end of 1940 we had a report by the military<br />
experts on the position in Singapore and in Malaya and it was so<br />
disturbing that that was the very reason why, at the end of 1940<br />
having a shrewd idea that I wouldn't remain in office too long alter I<br />
got back because my majority was even sketchier than it is at this<br />
moment, I went off to snland, The prime purpose of the Journey was<br />
to see whether we couldn t strengthen the defensive position in<br />
Singapore in relation to Malaya and the Far East because there was an<br />
enormous deficiency of aircraft and there was a great weakness in<br />
landward de ence. There was a naval base there were all sorts of<br />
provisions of that kind for sea warfare, Lt there was a tremendous<br />
deficiency, particularly in aircraft. I don't think I've mentioned<br />
this before but if I grow old enough and silly enough to write any<br />
memoirs I will have to state in some detail that the prime obJet of<br />
that journey was to secure air defence, particularly by fighter<br />
aircraft, in and around Singapore and Malaya.<br />
Of course, at that tine, it turned out to be impossible.<br />
It's easy to forget these things, but at that time, when I vas in<br />
England in early 1941 there was no second front except the fronts<br />
that the British were fighting on with their Commonwealth allies<br />
America was neutral, the Middle East presented a dreadful problem, we<br />
had all the problems of getting things through the Mediterranean, and<br />
in the result you couldn't succeed in getting modern aircraft, or even<br />
sub-odern aircraft, for the Far East. All t at they had were needed<br />
in the battle for the old country, or for the battles that were being<br />
organised in the Middle East.<br />
The result was, as we all know that when the Japanese came<br />
in and at that time, frankly, I thought they would, that was why this<br />
expedition was taken on there was such a deficiency in air cover that<br />
their tactics on the land and by the sea succeeded. dell this was a<br />
tremendous tragedy, I don't blame anybody for it. I think that as the<br />
facts then stood it was an unavoidable one,<br />
But I don't think we ought to stop there. I don't think we<br />
ought to say that this is just the final history of the event. If,<br />
Sir, on the 15th February of every year you Just celebrated a defeat,<br />
this would be a depressing event. But I don't believe it myself,<br />
because 1 want to give you two, or three, outstanding reasons why the<br />
efforts and the sacrifices and the suffeings of the Division, and of<br />
the Air Force attached to them and of the Navy which served so<br />
heroically in the defence as the Japanese came down, are immortal<br />
events, and -hy I believe that they have not been thrown away.<br />
The first reason that I ive you is one that has been<br />
referred to by General Bennett himself. I have never been able to<br />
understand why anybody, at any time, doubted his courage.( Applause)<br />
He had shown his courage far too frequently to be ancused by other<br />
people, and lesser people, of a lack of it. This is too silly. He's<br />
long since forgotten it. I refer to it only to assure his that people<br />
like myself have never, never entertained such nonsensical ideas. </p>
<p>3.<br />
Irememier -I fasn't the ?. rime Ministers I had been relieved of that<br />
post by a discrimna~ ting group of people,, before theso events -sitting,<br />
as an Opposition mamm) er 0or the Advisory lar C uncil when he produoed<br />
his training manual on jungle darfare and I can cofr everything<br />
that he says about it* This became of supreme Importance in the Nov<br />
Guinea and the Islands campaigns, and ias a tremendois contribution to<br />
ultimate victory. B3ut may I go oeyond that? You have all been reading lately<br />
about the proposals that -ure on foot for ai greater Malaysia Malaya$<br />
plus jingapore, plus North 13ro PlU3 Ja. rawaic plus Jruei -those<br />
proposal3 promoted by the Tunku A1dU1 Rahmans our zrecit and friendly<br />
leader of Malaya to establish on this crescent a realfter Malaya which<br />
would represent a friendly group of nations closely integrated with<br />
each other, 3tanding betvaen us, peoaphically, &amp; nd more than<br />
georaphicaily, and the Communist throat coming down from Asia. This<br />
is a ramarkable coniception,<br />
And why ha-! it been promoted by halaya as a friendly power,<br />
as a membe.-of the Commonealth? AW has It been promoted with the<br />
whole of those ideas in mind? It has been promoted be~ cause behind you<br />
you lert in Malaya an undying stmnsa of comradeships of mzutual help,<br />
of admiration. has only to go to Maiaya today, as I've had to<br />
myself ) nee or C. dtce, to realize how high the tocksof Australis and<br />
of Australians are in that country. ! md 1 vouldit have you underestimatLe<br />
for one moment the significance of that in these great moves<br />
that are now occurring to iestablish a1 greater Malaysia which under no<br />
circumnstances would tolerate becoming Cotrsiluit but wvbichs inl the<br />
broad sweep is on our side, and on the s2. de of the free iorld.<br />
Nov I ask you to remember that ladies and 4entlemen. This<br />
is fro~ c the point of view of a pra.-tising working politician, who has<br />
had saae responsibility for the affairs o! his country. This is a<br />
great thought that joa ought always to have in your winds. It must<br />
have been God knows that people like myself can't und-. stand it it<br />
xust have been a bitter inoiat to r the point avlaodleda<br />
defeat. 3ut to ackcnowledge defeat for the time and to go for the rest<br />
of your lives thinking that that das the ~ iial defeat, would be the<br />
greatest tru&amp; gedy of all. And I be&amp; of you, throw it out of your minds,<br />
Because all those events have left their indlible mark on our friends<br />
in these countries, and, I believe., on the fiature of 33outh-2. ast Asia.<br />
1ir, that is my ateonj to * atim~ te the . mpset 11 these<br />
things on the minds of the leaders and member3 of these countries in<br />
south-east A-sia.<br />
fiat I now iunt jou tocoo~ e buiCA. Wu .) ar oen coia., try. .4e are<br />
not al-ays as interested in foreign -ffT4irs ais do might be; though<br />
rather more than we 4erea T-4 we are more itareated ia :~ rign.<br />
affairs than we 4ere it is lar~ ely baoxaase 4e ti.. ve as a nation, become<br />
conscious of the signifcan~ ce ) f -; outli-.3L: the signiilicanoe of<br />
these countries lying close to us with the throat lyingo behiLnd them.<br />
This is one of the Treat reasons Arhy A~ us~ ralla has be.-omo more<br />
conscious of foreign affairs, more onscio-is in 1jarticular, of South'-<br />
. ast : 45jaf affairs than It ver wjas ov oreo<br />
In the result . ihat has hapened? ,, tie Lf Vae early' things<br />
that my own deplorable ;-vrnent did to ao one of tlli , rToaoters<br />
of the South-.: Ast Asia Treaty )~ rganisation; and todai J-, t Is<br />
something of enormous significinco to ere h; rAre a<br />
def'ensive origanisation of mutual help,, of Iatual un4' rAtarndi'je of<br />
mutual economic asisistance, vwth esnbracet nqt ; rmly ; rua~ t Zr-taln and<br />
the U. nited 3tates and France and Australia and Ned Zealand, but also<br />
' sian countries Pakistan, and Thailan~ d, oral the k K lipjpines. This,<br />
is a unique organisation. So long as it exists, so long as all its<br />
members stand up to it, , re have, in this corner of the world, a<br />
de ' n17e -i harlis! 1 i 1-4ich we cm-n17. oe our most tremendous reliance.<br />
Lt Is a rgional agreement in a reg; Ion bout which few pe~ ople thought,<br />
and friw people cared, only 20 years ago, </p>
<p>h~ ow If it is true$ as I &gt; eiiev* it to be, that today we are<br />
deeplyr concerned in this area that today qof are deeply concerned to<br />
see that we take our part in this great joint organisationt that this<br />
is something that anab1e-is to hold up our hevads In the company of our<br />
great anid pwrful friends like t he United Kin gdom and the United States<br />
then I wan t say., Sir, to you, tonigtst and to all your aembers, that<br />
what wan done by our forces, apparently so umaucoessfUlly, ap ontly<br />
ending In some form of disaster, has in fact boen one o' the great<br />
things to bring the Australian mind to understand how important this<br />
g; reat soutfi.. last sian .) rpnisation is. ( Applause)<br />
in other words, AIrq you can go through two periods on these<br />
matteres you can go through a feeling in 4hich emotions are highi anid<br />
sentiments are high; you can become accustomed, If I may just mention<br />
a row names at random to think with pride of peopl&amp; like Albert Coates<br />
and " Weary* Dunlop aund the miracles that they performed; you can think<br />
of Charles Anderson; you can think of' Clordon Bannett up thera with very<br />
little knoledge alroady acquired, until the e-'; ents, happened and they<br />
had to oe lea; neA by hard practice, fou can think of all these things,<br />
and there is a high rfeeling about Lhem, there is R deep emotion about<br />
tiem. I share them; you share t hem. jut In t he long rian, in the eye<br />
of history it becomes nec.-ssarylp after a while, to say " das all this<br />
wasted?" " Did all this comie and 4o and be forgotten exoept in a few<br />
warm hearts anda few ! ively memories?" " Or were these awents events<br />
whiich actually altered trw course of' history in this part of the<br />
world?' It is because I believe that they did alter the course of<br />
history in this part oi the . torld it is because IL believe what I have<br />
been saying to you about our relation to South-East of Asia, to our<br />
groat allies to whom I have referred it is because I believe that that<br />
I also believe that your annual cel9? v~ tion is niot to be reearded so<br />
much as a melancholy 0eet In which people look beck wiith sorrow<br />
though of course we do -but as an event from which you look forward<br />
with pride and with a realisation that these were great things, done<br />
fur Austraia, arid, as I firmly believe, dlone for the world.<br />
61r, I don't want to detain you any longer, It would have<br />
been sufficient, from my point of view', to come down perhaps,, and to<br />
say, and say trulyt Lhat I think It is a tre . endoux compliment on your<br />
part to Invite me to be here. I would have hated to miss being here,<br />
zsut above and beyond that It has given an opportunity to mo what you<br />
might call the more or less precarious head of the Governmient -to tell<br />
you something whuich perhaps only7 a an who ims 2rime Minister around<br />
that time and who is now, by the Mc~ wcy of i~ rovldv. noe, ' rlme Minister<br />
again some 17 years after It all ended can sre in proper retrospect,<br />
and who could tell you what I have toll you tonight. I believe It;<br />
1 mean it; and I hop* you vil accept it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
