<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21323</transcript-id>
    <title>Doorstop Interview Canberra </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What are the main points you'll be making tonight on the terrorism speech (inaudible)?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'll be making the point that at this critical moment in Iraq's history where a new democratic future is being challenged by immoral terrorism; it's the worst possible time to be sending the worst possible signal to the worst possible people about pulling out support and withdrawing moral support as well as real support for the Iraqi people.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Would your speech tonight be dealing with regional terror issues?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'll be warning that a defeat for the coalition in Iraq will greatly hearten and embolden terrorists in our part of the world.  What people have got to understand is that irrespective of the views about whether we should have gone there in the first place, terrorists see Iraq as the frontline in the international struggle against countries like Australia and our friends in our region and if the coalition fails in Iraq, if the terrorists win in Iraq, they will also win and organisations like Jemaah Islamiyah with all its reach in the Asian Pacific region will also win.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you saying that  Labor's policies will  encourage further terrorism?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Labor's policies will encourage the terrorists to think that if they persist they can gain ground.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In general, is it time that the focus on terrorism and anti-terrorism is brought back to our region?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it's a world-wide struggle, obviously what occurs in our region is of great importance to Australia but what occurs in other parts of the world influences what happens in our region.  A win for the terrorists in Iraq will embolden and lead to the recruitment of more terrorists in our part of the world.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Should Senator Hill have asked for a copy of the Amnesty report on the treatment of prisoners in Iraq last year?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think Senator Hill has handled himself appropriately and he has my total confidence and support.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
