<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7473</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, HOTEL SHILLA, XONEA 30 JANUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007473.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME-MI NISTER<br />
fTANSCIPT OF Pu~ ss q. OMPFENCEr HOTEL SKfILLA r XOkEA<br />
JANUARY 1989<br />
u~ o E -PRooF ONLY<br />
JOURNALiST: Trhere ' s so much emphasis beten on business and<br />
00111aferce. Now did those talks go last night with the<br />
business leaders that you met here? What chance does<br />
AusBtral~ ia have of getting into the act?<br />
L'-14: A very signiricant chance indeed. Thero was, I think,<br />
aim) lqst ail the businesswen with whomn I spoke, thore wras<br />
considerable optimism 1. an~ ing fromi our agricultural, rural<br />
products like beef, there s ~ a considerable deqrse of optimism<br />
in re~ gard to beef, and our mineral products, iron ore atnd<br />
c~ oal., in both those aseas, optimism. Goinq through to<br />
manufactured products, the solar heatinq peopie there who runi<br />
a contract for the Olympic village have now told me last<br />
niqht , that they are in receipt oi another big contract which<br />
gives-thoin considerable optimism for the future. So vie * have<br />
this Pisential combination of businessmen who are imaginative<br />
andjyressive in an acceptable way, who are out there finding<br />
niches i. n the sense of manufactured goods and in terms of<br />
'. asic maiterials, providing substance for the development of<br />
the )( oroan economy. So we have the businessmen dointg that<br />
anid on our si~ de a Government at the political level, and the<br />
bureaucratic level doing everything we can t6 create the<br />
enviuonnent in which Australian businessman are going to be<br />
able to get the benefit and the Australian economy is going<br />
to qet the benefit of the stronq qrowth in the Koreai<br />
econow~ y. Also there've been discussions between the<br />
UF LPresident and mayself already today about anooureqing Xoreai<br />
investment in Australia. So all together I'm very pleased<br />
about the environment that exists betweenuu a t the political<br />
lQee. I'm certainly indebted to the Australian bunihessmen<br />
who are go'ing out and doing what they need to do, that is<br />
fkndinq markets for an increasingly diversified range of<br />
Australian products.<br />
JO) URNALIST: Do you think the Korean government is moving<br />
fact enough in terms of cutting its tariff levels and quota<br />
rest r. ct lons?<br />
VN4: There have been significant reductions but they've been<br />
comewhxat specific. You stll-have the situatiLon where. there<br />
are specialk taxes and regulations in certain areas which make<br />
acoess difficult. Those things I'll be talking about in some<br />
more detail this afternoon when I have the meoting with the<br />
range of oconomic mirilatars. May I say on this, one<br />
devel~ opmient that cameo out of my meeting with the President<br />
this morning and thatL is that you know that he established </p>
<p>2<br />
PM ( cent) the Presidential Commission on Economic<br />
Restructuring and that is addressing the issues of<br />
liberalization and increasing access. I invited through the<br />
President the members of the Commission to come to Australia.<br />
1 thought that would be a good idea. May I say I'm very<br />
pleased to say that the President accepted that with pleasure<br />
and indicated that he'll request--the members of that<br />
Commission to come to Australia. So that will give us a'very<br />
specific opportunity of discussing these issues directly with<br />
those who'll be making the recommendations as to what should<br />
be happening here in Korea.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you received a satisfactory explanation for<br />
the bungle that led to your delayed departure yesterday?<br />
PM: Do you know what? I'm that much more interested and got<br />
my priorities that much more sorted out than some people that<br />
haven't given it another thought. I'm sure that some of my<br />
bureaucrats have though.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Button said yesterday that this region<br />
needed to band together more to combat the strength of other<br />
trading blocks. How do you see that happening?<br />
PM: i've already had some discussions with the President<br />
this morning. I would rather address that in a little bit<br />
more detail tomorrow if you don't mind because I'm going to<br />
be referring to the issue in an address I'm going to be<br />
making tomorrow here. I can say that I've had some<br />
discussions, some very constructive discussions with the<br />
President on that point. But I'll have a little bit more to<br />
say about that tomorrow.<br />
JOURNALIST:. That involves a formal proposal?<br />
PM: Tomorrow.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you discuss North Korea today?<br />
PM: Yes, I had long discussions with the President about<br />
that and I think it's fair to say that the President takes<br />
the view that there are pleasing signs of the opportunities<br />
for closer relations but that this is something which is<br />
going to require a lot of patience and time. There's a lot<br />
of accumulated doubts, grievances, suspicions and the<br />
important thing however is that this President, this.<br />
administration is commited to the process of increasing<br />
dialogue and cooperation and coexistence with the North.<br />
When he was with me in Canberra he said that he would welcome<br />
Australian initiatives of opening up their relations with the<br />
North. We have done that since I met with him in November<br />
and I was able to report. to him on those initiatives that<br />
we've taken both in North Korea and in some discussions that<br />
took place in China. We of course kept the government here<br />
informed of those developments at all times and we've<br />
indicated that we'll continue to do that, keep them informed. </p>
<p>3<br />
PM ( oont) Of course in our discussions with the North there<br />
will be a conditionality about it and that in that to the<br />
extent that we want to help to open up the relationship with<br />
the North, the speed with which we can do that will in some<br />
sense obviously be a function of the way in which the North<br />
is cooperating with the South in facilitating the discussions<br />
for resolving the impasse that has existed for oo long<br />
between them.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
