<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5531</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES COMMEMORATING COMMONWEALTH DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005531.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A~ 1<br />
PRIME MINISTERFor<br />
Media THURSDAY 5 MARCH 1981<br />
SPEECH TO THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
COM14EMORATIING COMMONWTEALTH DAY<br />
Members will recall that a decision has been made by the<br />
members of the Commonwealth to set aside the second Monday<br />
in March each year as a day on which the purpose and<br />
achievements of the Commonwealth would be duly marked. As<br />
this is the last sitting day before this year's Commonwealth<br />
Day I would like to take this opportunity to make a brief<br />
statement to that end.<br />
This year's Commonwealth Day is especially noteworthy for<br />
Australia in two respects. First, it marks the<br />
anniversary of the Statute of Westminstar, an Act of the<br />
British = arliament which gave birth to the Commonwealth.<br />
Second, this year Australia will host the. Commonwealth Heads<br />
of Government Meeting for the first time.<br />
To an exceptional extent the history of the Commonwealth has<br />
been one of gradual., evolution, marked by continuity and subtle<br />
modifications rather than abrupt change. But if there is one<br />
event which constitutes a decisive step in that evolution,<br />
it is surely the passing of the statute of Westminster in 193: 1.<br />
That event marked the decisive transition from empire to.<br />
Commonwealth. By establishing the principles of autonomy, equality and<br />
free association among members, it created the conditions for<br />
the Commonwealth to grow, diversify and establish a distinctive<br />
role in an era . of far-reaching changes. Thus as decolonisation<br />
proceeded with great rapidity, most of the newly independent<br />
countries found it natural and advantageous to become<br />
members of it. A leading Australian authority on the<br />
Commonwealth ( Professor Bruce Miller) has referred to the<br />
Statute as " a masterpeice of ambiguity", and no doubt in legal<br />
and constitutional terms it was that. But politically it<br />
pointed clearly in one direction. The time when discussion<br />
of the Commonwealth tended to be clouded by rather dubious<br />
metaphysics and the search for the definition of an essence<br />
is long since past. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
