<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12889</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks folloiwng Election of Remarks Following Election as Chairman, International Democratic Union -  Marriott Hotel, Washington DC</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/06/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...........</p>
<p>Thank you very much Mr Chairman. May I first express my thanks to all of you for the confidence that you';ve placed in me. I will do my best to discharge the common values and aspirations of this organisation and in the time that I am Chairman, do everything that I can to advance the cause of political parties around the world based on the beliefs that the individual is more important than the state; based on a belief that competitive capitalism more likely delivers rising national incomes for nations; and that the role of the family within our society remains absolutely paramount.</p>
<p>I would like to join you, Mr Chairman, in thanking our American friends and particularly the Republican National Committee for the courtesies extended to us in characteristic American friendliness. Can I also congratulate you Mr Chairman on the tremendous work that you';ve done as Chairman over the past three years. You';ve worked very hard, you';ve brought about many reforms, and the chairmanship that you graciously pass to me today is of an organisation that is in infinitely better shape as a result of your efforts and I';d like everybody to thank you very warmly for that.</p>
<p>And in that spirit I would like, as I understand is the customary right of the incoming Chairman, to nominate you, the Right Honourable William Hague as the Vice Chairman, and I know that we will work together very closely over the next three years.</p>
<p>Finally, can I say that I hope at some time during my chairmanship it will be possible for Australia to extend hospitality to a gathering of the IDU. We have done so in the past, and I hope the opportunity arises over the next three years.</p>
<p>May I conclude by echoing the sentiment you expressed Mr Chairman, and that is that we meet at a time of considerable success for the view of life that politically speaking that brings us here together here in Washington. And we also meet at a time when a reaffirmation of our close relationship with the people of the United States is more than ever appropriate. I thank you Mr Chairman, and most importantly I thank all of you for the honour you have paid to me and very importantly, to my country, Australia.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
