<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6448</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, FORUM PRESS CONFERENCE, 12NOON, 27 AUGUST 1984, FUNAFUTI</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006448.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PF 2 MMEE MINISTER<br />
. TscrkP FORUM C NO' UGUST 1984.1<br />
FUNAFUTI PRIME MINISTER: Well ladies and gentlemen, the Forum having<br />
quickly disposed of certain procedural matters went first to<br />
the decolonisation issue which, of course, specifically involves<br />
developments in New Caledonia. Without identifying contributions<br />
individually I would attempt to spell out and sum up for you<br />
the nature of the discussion. And I would preface that by saying<br />
that we concluded the discussion just prior to lunch when I<br />
introcuced the nuclear free zone concept. I'll come to that in<br />
a r--ant. No resolution was passed on this matter of New<br />
Caledonia, but that will come to be reflected in the final<br />
communique. I think these tbings can be said as reflecting<br />
general views in the Forum discussions. Firstly there was, as<br />
of course will be no surprise to you, a unanimous view as to the<br />
desirability of independence for New Caledonia. _ But I think what<br />
should be stressed is that while in some quarters there has<br />
been a tendency to stress the question of indepence for the<br />
Kanaks it was the very general view that what we're talking<br />
about is independence for New Caledonians. There was reference<br />
to the multi-ethnicity of the population and that all people there<br />
including, of course, the Kanaks-have the right to independence.<br />
Within that view there was again I think a fairly general<br />
attitude that there should be an acceleration of the move by<br />
the French. We were talking about, as you know, a referendum<br />
date of 1989 and without there being a resolution on this a<br />
number of speakers felt that there should be an attempt to be<br />
thinking of perhaps as early as 1986 for a referendum in these<br />
terms.. There was a ceneral recognition I believe of the<br />
progress that has been made under the 1K-tterand Government since<br />
its accession to power in 1981. Indeed, I think there is an<br />
acceptance generally of the integrity of the French Government<br />
in its attempts to come to a peaceable resolution of this issue.<br />
There was reference to some of those particular developments and<br />
I refer not merely to the passage of the statute recently in the<br />
French Parliament, but earlier to the plan for legislation which<br />
was instituted by decree from France in 1982. And that was<br />
subsequent to the visit to France by a Forum delegation headed<br />
by Prime Minister Ratu Mara of Fiji. On the specific question<br />
of the suggestion that there should be a move to support<br />
reinscription of the issue of New Caledonia on the agenda of<br />
the Committee of 24 of the United Nations I think it is fair<br />
to say that there was a general, not unanimous, but a general<br />
view that reinscription on the agenda of the Committee of 24<br />
would not be helpful to the aspirations of New Caledonia for<br />
independence which, as I say, the Forum unanimously supported<br />
that as such reinscription itself would not add anything but<br />
properly considered may in fact create more difficulties within<br />
France, where after all the decisions of substance have to be made.<br />
And there has to be a consciousness of the fact that there are<br />
elections in France in 1986 and that is relevant for the present<br />
Government and indeed looking at the political continuum in France<br />
there is the judgement generally made, I think, by Forum members<br />
that the decisions taken now by us in respect of how we would<br />
attempt to press or not. to press for reinscription on the </p>
<p>P. M. cont...: Committee of 24 would be relevant to that internal<br />
French context. A final point I'd make in regard to-the discussions<br />
Sis this, and I think its a very important one, that there are<br />
suggestions from the independence frcnt'or at least elements<br />
of it that this is a critical point for the iorum as to their<br />
attitude and that if in fact we were not to take-a particular<br />
position, for instance in regard to inscription, that this coul. d<br />
be regarded as providing a situation, or creating-a situation,'<br />
where they would-no longer be able to look to the Forum and would<br />
have to look outside the region. Now very'specifically some of us<br />
referred to. that issue and we made it. qlear that one.. of.. the.<br />
great advantages of our region, the forum region, is that the<br />
processes of force, armed revolution and . terrorism have been<br />
c;.. t. ic tly absent from the way in which affairs have evolved in<br />
this country. And I think there was a fairly general agreement<br />
with the attitude expressed by some of us that the evidence<br />
that exists of some embryonic move by elements of the Independence<br />
Front to seek support from quarters which advocate the processes<br />
of terrorism should be condemned. So ladies and gentlemen I think<br />
that that essentially covers ithe essence of the discussion and<br />
I believe that those views will come to be reflected in the<br />
final communique.<br />
I introduced in the last stage of this session the next item<br />
on the agenda which is the nuclear free zone and in a brief<br />
introduction I made the points that Australia welcomed the<br />
developments that had taken place since the Canberra meeting<br />
in 1983 that there had been discussions bilaterally between<br />
countries in the Forum, the basis of a draft set of proposals.<br />
I indicated that different countries gave perhaps different<br />
emphasis to different aspects of this. issue. For some the<br />
question of the testing of nuclear devices in our region was<br />
the most important. For others the question of the possible<br />
dumping of nuclear waste products assumed perhaps more importance<br />
than other aspects. For some the more general question of trying<br />
to prevent the proliferation of nuclear weaponry was another<br />
matter. But I indicated that there did seem to be an emerging<br />
consensus that we in this region should try and move to a position<br />
of some ' sort of nuclear free zone concept. I pointed out that<br />
there are particular matters, technical matters, that need to be<br />
addressed in some detail. Without being exhaustive, that includes<br />
the question for instance of the geographical limits of the zone,<br />
it includes the question of at what stage would we as a Forum<br />
wish to take the matter'into other international forums in general<br />
of the nuclear weapons states in particular. And so I stressed that<br />
in Australia's judgement what we needed to do was to have this<br />
. general discussion now and address these matters in a productive<br />
working group. I also made the point which I think is of particular1<br />
relevance at this time to say that from the moment when I<br />
introduced the concept last year it had been an intrinsic part<br />
of Australia's proposal that the question of the visit or. non-visit<br />
to the ports of members of nuclear-armed or nuclear-powered ships<br />
had always been seen from the outset and was built into our<br />
proposals that that was a matter for decision by individual<br />
countries of the Forum. I've made that clear in Canberra. I<br />
reiterated it today and that that right of individual countries<br />
was, of course, not only consistent v'ith but important to the<br />
concept of a nuclear free zone. I made the observation fhata fron </p>
<p>P. M. cant Australia's point of: view, because of our alliance<br />
relationship with the Unitedl State!;, Australia had made the<br />
judgement that such visits would be per-mitted to Australia.<br />
But in saying that again re-emphasised that this was a matter<br />
for decision by particular states.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen that is the end of the report that I would<br />
" ma-ke t cu,<br />
JOURNALIST: Just a point of clarification on decolonicationyou<br />
didn't mention French Polynesia, did that come into it at all..<br />
No it didn't come into the discussion at all this morning.<br />
TAhl. t doesn't mean that it may not be picked up later. But it<br />
w~ n~ 2 2 ~'~ dto this morning. Except let me say this that one<br />
6peaker did make the general point, but really in addressing<br />
himself to New Caledonia, that there was no further reason for<br />
a French Presence in the area.<br />
JOURNALIST: You say there's no resolution to bring forward<br />
the referendum date to 19856. What were the arguments that.<br />
Were-there arguments that that was too soon.<br />
-No there were not specific arguments against. it'and<br />
think that in the communique you will see reference to, you'Ill<br />
certainly I believe, see reference to the desire of the Forum<br />
countries for a bringing forward of the date. There may be<br />
reference to 1986 but'I think you'll see there'll be a view<br />
put that we are all saying to the French that it is evident that<br />
very considerable tensions are building up. You've got the<br />
decision of the Independence Front to boycott the up-coming<br />
elections, to withdraw co-operation. There is evidence that the<br />
situation is deteriorating and it's in that context that we<br />
are sa ying that the French should try move more quickly towards<br />
the concept of a referendum embracing the independence of<br />
New Caledonia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister was there specific mention of<br />
elements of the Independence Front approaching Libya.<br />
Yes there was<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it that that you condemned.<br />
Oh it was certai'nly condemned by those ' of us who referred<br />
to it and, of course, its not exclusive that's the evidence<br />
of that approach at present, but the concept of buying outside<br />
* the region and making an appeal to the force of arms and the<br />
terrorist technique to be introduced was something which I think<br />
was very generally deplored.<br />
JOURNALIST: What you are saying, Mr Hawke, is that you wiant<br />
by the French Government before the next election.<br />
L </p>
<p>j e eIt Pa1 V; 4. 43 n<br />
ll the next Parliame. ntary electicn, of course, is 198;.<br />
It's a five year term. The Presidential election is a seven<br />
year term, so it's 1988. But really the concept of mentioning<br />
a date was not specifically related to the date of the elections<br />
in France. There was a view expressed that under the Mittorand<br />
Government there had been progress, some perhaps thought it could<br />
have been faster, but there has been identifiable progress<br />
And there was a vie' that' nthing should be done'which would<br />
complicate the capacity of the French Government to move tocwards<br />
independence. But let me say there was also the view expressed<br />
that even should there be a change of Government that there was<br />
a more general attitude beyond this Government in France to<br />
recognise the aspirations of the people of New Caledonia. But<br />
I repeat the concept of bringing forward a date was not specifically<br />
to: the timing of elections in France.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you among those who believed that the date<br />
should be brought forward.<br />
Yes, I believe that if it's possible it should be brought<br />
forward because we recognise the building up of tension. But<br />
speaking of myself I am one who has consistently said, following<br />
my discussions with President Mitterand in Paris last year, that<br />
I do recognise the integrity of the Government of France on this<br />
issue. They have, as I've put it, no political or economic<br />
imperatives to remain there any longer than is necessary. But*<br />
they do have a recognition of the very large and potentially<br />
explosive difficulties that exist there because of the composition<br />
of the population and the quite dispirate training of the elements<br />
of the population the Kanaks are lacking in physical and armed(?)<br />
resources, that's one thing. But in terms of professional and<br />
technical training because of h generation of inadequate approach<br />
by previous French. administrations there is at this stage a<br />
relative lack of trained people amongst the Kanaks and the<br />
French Government is conscious of all these elements.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were there any discussion of any possible<br />
initiative that the Forum could take to persuade France to<br />
move faster on the timetable for the referendum.<br />
These elements were alluded to by various speakers.<br />
One, while I think as I've said, there was a general view against<br />
the concept of reinscription and the Committee of 24, I think<br />
acceptance that in their speeches to the United Nations General<br />
Assembly that Forum members could make the point about the need<br />
for acceleration. Secondly, that individual members of the Forum<br />
in their relations with and their bilateral relations with France<br />
-should press the view. And thirdly, I would expect the communique<br />
will probably be again an attempt by the Forum as a Forum to press<br />
the view upon France.<br />
JOUP-NALIST: Will there be any mention last year's decision to<br />
ask France to invite a Ministerial group to visit New Caledonia. </p>
<p>7..<br />
Well we didn't specifically adadress ourselves to that, but<br />
it's possible that we iray make that attempt: again.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did the New Zealand Prime Minister make any attempt<br />
to explain New Zealand's position on the visits of nuclear ships.<br />
. No. because,, as I. pointed out, -it arcige -just' -in: the ast<br />
few minutes. I merely made the introduction and after my<br />
introduction we closed the session.<br />
JOURNALIST: Vrno put the proposal for reinscription.<br />
Oh well that's in the paper that's been circulated by<br />
Vanuatu and it was advanced by the spokesman for Vanuatu. He<br />
wiai cr-i. Lely unsupported.<br />
JOURNALIST: Who was supportive.<br />
Well I've made the point that I don't want to go to<br />
individual points although it was appropriate to respond that<br />
way to Mr Steketee because in fact that was a matter of knowledge<br />
that they had distributed that paper.<br />
JOURNALIST: What was the flavour of the debates. Was there<br />
sharp differences or differences of emphasis or how would you<br />
characterise it?<br />
No difference8 of emphasis. It was a very Pacific<br />
discussion. JOURNALIST: Does the lack of a resolution, Mr Hawke, reflect<br />
It reflects the fact that there won't be any communique<br />
until-' the end and I would believe that on all the issues that<br />
we discussed, it's unlikely that there be specific resolutions<br />
emerging until the end. That may not be the case but that's<br />
the way I put it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is the-debate then, Sir, finished on the nuclear<br />
issue an6 also on New Caledonia.<br />
No, for the third time I repeat that in the last few<br />
minutes before the conclusion of the session I introduced the<br />
nuclear issue. That means by definition that the debate hasn't<br />
started. I<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect the debate on the nuclear issue to be<br />
. a long one. What's your reaction to how the island delegates will<br />
guage the Australian proposal.<br />
Well by definition there hasn't been any opportunity In<br />
the forrm-al meetings to get the response. But my impression from<br />
w~ hat has happened up to this stage is that there is a growing<br />
support for the concept.<br />
JOUR-NALIST: Were there any other countries who were mentioned<br />
as possible sources of outside assistance to New Caledonia.<br />
Libya was the only one that got a guernsey. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: ? ri: 2 Minster you said at you'r press confZrence<br />
yesterday that the zone proposal, Australia's zone prcpocal,<br />
would be consistent with your treaty obligations. And in 1975<br />
Mr Whitlam seemed to think that it wouldn't'be consistent, or<br />
at least New Zealand's proposal then, wouldn't be consistent<br />
with our treaty obligations. I'r just wondering what's changed,.<br />
I don't want to make too much of the point; But there's<br />
a great deal of difference in 1984 between the Governments that<br />
are operating and in times past. We deal with the issues now<br />
in terms of our assessment of the present. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
