<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4133</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 27 MAY 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004133_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
100<br />
PRME uAIVNISTE<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 27 May 1976<br />
This is basically an opportunity to enable you to ask<br />
questions of myself or Mr Hunt or Mr Ellicott, on the law<br />
of this particular matter..<br />
The Government was advised, as I indicated in the Parliament<br />
this morning, in a joint opinion, that indicated that<br />
continued payments to the States for the purposes of the<br />
hospital. agreements would not be valid because the agreements<br />
had not been drawn up in conformity with. the Act that<br />
had been passed through the Federal Parliament. And this<br />
concerns-us, because quite obviously the Commonwealth needs<br />
to meet its obligations, there is an understand to pay half,<br />
under the present arrangements of the costs of running the<br />
major hospitals in the States, and we're advised that because<br />
of the joint opinion that has been provided by the Attorney<br />
and-the Solicitor-General, that the Auditor-General would not<br />
authorise continuing payments under the present legislation.<br />
So at the moment, special legislation is being drafted which<br />
will cover: the situation until the 30 September, and in the<br />
intervening Athe Minister with his colleagues, as I indicated<br />
this morning, will be having discussions with the States about<br />
continuing and on-going arrangements that would be within the<br />
law. This is really only repeating what I said in question<br />
time:-this morning, but I want to emphasise, that no<br />
arrangements in relation to patients of any kind will be altered<br />
by this situation that has been revealed, this inadequacy in<br />
the law. I want to give the strongest possible assurance-that<br />
nobody need be concerned about these particular matters. The<br />
rights and interests of patients under Medibank will be protected,<br />
and the emergency that we'll be. introducing will make quite<br />
erOain of that. I can't give the full details of chac legislation<br />
at'the moment, because it's still being drafted:-there are<br />
a covple of aspects of it that need sorting out.-but the<br />
Attorney and the appropriate Departments and the Treasury are<br />
looking at those particular matters. But it's likely that it<br />
will be done on the basis, as I . indicated again this morning,<br />
of working out the sort of total payment that would go to<br />
each State-in these areas over the next few months, and providing<br />
legislation for that bulk sum to go to the States, for the<br />
purposes required. / 2 i I<br />
I I I<br />
i I<br />
j t </p>
<p>, STION: Prime Minister, you said in Parliament this morning that<br />
the Attorney-General's department advised the department<br />
of Socip. l Security last year that some of the hosoital.<br />
agreements weren't in compliance with the Act. Why is it<br />
that nothing was done until now about the acts<br />
if you suspected, or someone suspected that they weren't<br />
in compliance?<br />
LD. MINISTER: I think you'd have to ask other people that. The<br />
dates of the letter were in April, and there was an exchange<br />
of letters involving April and May of 1975 a different<br />
administration w.. as in power and it's a question as to whether<br />
or not Ministers were aware of the situation. This situation<br />
came to our knowledge yesterday or the day before within<br />
the last couple of days. But we had not been advised of it<br />
before then. I'm advised, but. I can't vouch for it, you<br />
could ask the people concerned, that the previous Government<br />
was aware of this situation., ut you also need to understand<br />
that the legislation had been part of the double dissolution<br />
procedures,-sdi ~ ny amendments to the legislation after it<br />
had gone through the double dissolution procedures and the<br />
Joint House would have enabled the Senate to be in the position<br />
of blocking the legislation and the previous administration<br />
might not have wanted to run that risk, and therefore decided<br />
Sto do nothing about it. Now, I make no allegation about that<br />
at all.. I've been given conflicting advice about whether<br />
any Ministers in the previous administration knew of this<br />
or whether they didn't. But departments were certainly aware<br />
of it and there was an interchange of correspondence between<br />
departmental officials in relation to it.<br />
JESTION: Prime Minister, why has it taken so long to be brought to<br />
your Pttention.? Are you saying there's been some degree<br />
of inefficiency with regards to your ( inaudible) advisers?<br />
LIMOINISTER: I make no criticism of that. at all. I quite specifically<br />
asked the Attorney-General to look at these particular agrPements<br />
as I indicated in the Parliament, because of one or two<br />
statements that had been made by one or two States in relation<br />
to the hospitals agreements. And so I said look at the provisions<br />
of the agreements and see what powers lie in the hands of the<br />
States, what powers lie in the hands of the Commonwealth, and<br />
this was the result the Attorney came forward with-<br />
IESTION: Prime Minister, what will be the effect on the States. Will<br />
money at all stop flowing.<br />
IME MINISTER: No, the emergency legislation is going to cover the<br />
period until the 30 September so that money will continue to flow.<br />
So that hospitals will be protected, but above all so that<br />
patients will. be protected, and that's what were concerned<br />
about, preminently,. and absolutely. We're going to make<br />
quite certain of that. What is needed is for the Minister<br />
for Health and his counterparts, properly advised by law<br />
officers to get together with the States to sort out the<br />
situation that's developed. But this is a matter between<br />
Governments, hospitals, are going to be protected, and patients<br />
are going to be protected. One of the reasons I wanted<br />
to respond to the recuests for further information in these<br />
particular matters was to give a complete and absolute guarantee<br />
in relation to those n-tters. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Sir,-, when did you ask the Attorney-General to look. at<br />
these agreements?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:' Two days ago.<br />
QUESTION: And what were the specific matters that prompted you to<br />
do this?<br />
PRIME MINSTER: They'd been some rather strange statements by a<br />
Minister in New South Wales, and they'd been statements<br />
by one or two other people also about the matters, a; fd<br />
Swas those matters that prompted me to ask the Attorney<br />
to look at the agreements?<br />
QUESTION-And it only took them two days, the Attorney-General's<br />
department, and the Solicitor-General's department. to come<br />
uo with this?<br />
PRIL MINISTER: ' They went straight to the law, straight to the agreements,<br />
and demonstrated that lawyers can act swiftly uhen there's<br />
P need to.<br />
QU ION. Sir:-. are you going to release to us the advice upon which<br />
you've made this decision, the advice of the Solicitor-General<br />
and Attorney-Gereral.?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: At this stage not, but I would be intending that a<br />
copy of the joint opinion should go to the Premiers concerned.<br />
And I think at this stage the decision to send a copy of<br />
that joint opinion to them is the appropriate and oroper course..<br />
QUESTION: Thy w-on't you release it to us?<br />
PR. MINISTER: I think at this stage the appropriate thing is for<br />
a cooy . to go to-the Premiers who are intimately involved.<br />
It after all involves an agreement between Governments.<br />
We've been given a certain opinion in strong terms, and<br />
as to any future decision, well, at the moment, let me leave<br />
0 that open. But certainly it should go to the Premiers<br />
inthe first instance.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, you said you had had conflicting advice about<br />
whether the Labor Ministers knew about this conflict in the Act<br />
but you're saying that you feel that some Labor Ministers<br />
a dikdn ow?<br />
JRIME MINISTER: I would find it very difficult for them not to know,<br />
but. I make no allegation about it. I don't know.<br />
ø] QUESTION: Mr Fraser, will you be raising this specifically with Premier<br />
Wran in a few minutes time?<br />
RIME MINISTER: I'd imagine that he'd want to talk about it, yes.<br />
UESTION: Can I ask Mr Ellicott where this conflict arises, what is the<br />
N legal point? 1<br />
_ II~ </p>
<p>-IR ELLICOTT: Well section 30 of the Act requires that any agreement<br />
that's. entered into should be substantially in accordance<br />
with the heads of agrement. And those heads of agreement<br />
are set out in the schedules of the Act. Well, fairly<br />
clearly, when you look at the agreement and ask the question<br />
whether it's substantially in accordance with the heads<br />
of agreement, the answer is no. And I refer there to<br />
head of agreement No. 3.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Fraser, now that this situation has arisen, and I notice<br />
that any emergency legislation will take only until<br />
October 1, the new arrangements for Medibank, would you<br />
expect to be: in a much more powerful position now in seeking<br />
increased hospital charges in States.<br />
? RIME MINISTER: I think we're in a very strong position in relation<br />
to that anyway. Because what the Minister's proposing, what's<br />
the Government's accepted and fully supports, and what our<br />
Parties support, is that there'd be no change in standard ward<br />
treatment which is the basic Medibank approach and standard<br />
of health care. But then there are people, in . many different<br />
categories who wish to insure either for intermediate<br />
or private ward treatement and there are still 60 or<br />
of people covered for that-throughout the Australian community.<br />
Now,. the question of. increasing in public hospitals the<br />
intermediate and private ward charges would have the result<br />
of lessening the subsidies to those who wish to. pay something<br />
else to upgrade their. bed treatment, and to enable their own<br />
doctor to follow them into the hospital. And we felt<br />
that there was no real justification on those who were<br />
content with Medi1ank treatment, paying the levy, or on lower<br />
incomes,, not paying the levy at all and the general run<br />
of. taxpayers to provide additional subsidies to those seeking<br />
intermediate or private ward treatment. Now I do believe<br />
in some of the cor ents, been a real measure of misunderstanding<br />
C in relation to this particular matter I think when the<br />
Minister speaks with state Ministers, and when the matter<br />
is properly understand, the logic of what we're proposing<br />
will stand in its own right.<br />
) UESTION: Prime Minster, that doesn't answer Mr Howard's question.<br />
Does the new situation give you a stronger position to argue<br />
with the States?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I suppose I'd have to say yes.<br />
! UESTION: Prime Minister, can you give us some idea of what amounts<br />
of money are involved here?<br />
' RIME MINISTER: I wouldn't know, the Minister might know but you see<br />
there are two questions there is also a view as to whether<br />
Q past payments are valid, but otherwise you've got a question<br />
of part of May, June, July, August, September. So you've<br />
got several months of the year they'd be very considerable<br />
sums...<br />
P: INISTER: About $ 60 million a month. </p>
<p>QUESTTQN: Will . this legislation seek to make it retrospective.<br />
back to'July 1, when Medibank started, in fact all the payments.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:. No, the emergency legislation we'll be bringing<br />
through will be providing for continued payments from now,<br />
until-the 30 September. Other matters will be resting upon<br />
negotiation and discussions between the Minister and his<br />
State counterpart.<br />
QUESTICN: So there is the chance that some of the States will owe.<br />
the Comonwealth money, if it's considered that those payments<br />
have been invalid?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I suppose in technical terms you could put it that<br />
way, but you know,. one might judge the reality of that sort<br />
of situation.<br />
QU~ TION-: Sir, disregarding how much the former Minister may have<br />
Lknow or not have known, are you surprised at all that whoever<br />
gave that opinion to the Social Security Department in April<br />
didn't give you that advice?<br />
P-I E MINISTER: Earlier...?<br />
QUESTION: Earlier.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: But this advice was offered in April of last year<br />
I don't know if he's in the same position or not, I really don't.<br />
Our own particular examiniation of Medibank had n't come<br />
across-this particular point because I don't think that<br />
it had occured to ary person in the Government and I doubt<br />
if it had -occured to anyone in the Medibank Review Committee<br />
that there was any conflict between the actual agremeents<br />
ardthe law as it had been passed.-<br />
QUESTION:.: But did the Review Coummittee investigate these legal points?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would have doubted it I don't think it would have<br />
occured to anyone that there was a conflict, until these<br />
specific questions were raised, as I indicated two days ago.<br />
QUESTION: Is it fair to say that the invalidity would have never come<br />
to light had you not undertaken a review of Medibank?<br />
IRIME MINISTER: I think it probably would have come to light, at some<br />
stage, nobody could say when, but invalidities of this kind,<br />
I would have thought, would have a way of surfacing in one<br />
form or another. I think it's much better-that it's surfaced<br />
now rather than much later?<br />
QUESTION: Do you think it would be a fruitful exercise to ask the<br />
Attorney-General and the Solicitor-General to take a look<br />
at some of the other legislation that's been tabled<br />
in the past three years?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well it might well be a fruitful exercise and the specific<br />
agreements with the states that have been encompassed in a number </p>
<p>6.<br />
of matters, are in fact, under examiniation as a result<br />
of this, for that very purpose.<br />
' QUESTION: Since you found this flaw...?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, since this instance?<br />
QUESTION: That means all other agreements?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There were a number of formal agreements signed,<br />
and if there are illegalities with them, if they're<br />
not in conformity with the law, I think we need to know<br />
a bout it, so that the matter can be properly rectified.<br />
QUESTION: Mr Nixon raised the question of the South Australian<br />
Railway ( inaudible). Are we to take it that you're<br />
examining all agreements made...<br />
E MINISTRR. Well the major agreements will be under examiniation<br />
yes, we don't want tc be surprised by this sort of situation<br />
in some other arena?<br />
ISTION: It may also mean that you can't get out of some of them?<br />
? RIME MINISTER: It depends on the nature of the agreement.<br />
1) x </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
