<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2628</transcript-id>
    <title>FOURTH NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF THE INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS SYDNEY NSW - 21 JUNE 1972 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002628.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SAUSTRALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOURTH NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF THE INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS<br />
SYDNEY, N. S. W. 21 JUNE 1972<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. William McMahon,<br />
CH, MP.<br />
Mr Chairman, Gentlemen It is a pleasure to be the guest of the Institute tonight,<br />
to have the opportunity of talking to so many distinguished visitors,<br />
and to such a representative gathering of leaders of Australian<br />
business and industry.<br />
I would have liked to have sp. okn to you in a freewheeling<br />
fashion about the recent visit I have made overseas, because not only<br />
was it a memorable one for me, but I do believe in the presence of<br />
some of those people whose Governments were good enough to look after<br />
me whilst I was away that they did show their great liking for<br />
this country and and spoke of what they saw to be the wonderful<br />
prospects in front of us.<br />
But I think you can take it for granted that wherever<br />
I went they showed a disosition to look to Austraa for assistance,<br />
they looked to Australia for comradeship and for friendship and they<br />
had implicit trust in the belief that this country will, in their<br />
time of need, come to their help and come to their assistance.<br />
So for that reason, I wanted to speak to you in the<br />
presence of so many : istinguished guests, and say something to you.<br />
Instead not in a freewheeling. because as Prime Minister that is<br />
impossible under certain circumstances and so therefore I will<br />
keep pretty closely to a text I have already prepared.<br />
I think most of you will know that I have been visiting<br />
three of our near neighbours in South-East Asia first of all<br />
Djakarta, then Singapore and later on Kuala Lumpur. Naturally<br />
the events of that journey are very much in my mind, particularly<br />
as I have here on my left-hand side a colleague whom I have learnt<br />
to respect and who I think is just as interested in not only the<br />
South Pacific countries but also in the countries to the countries<br />
to the North, and who realises that the our destinies of New<br />
Zealand and ourselves our greatest friend is New Zealand<br />
and these other countries are inextricably bound up and that their<br />
destinies will inevitably affect what happens in our own countries.<br />
And, too, it was an appropriate time for me to be there<br />
because only recently President Nixon had completed his visits to<br />
Peking and to Moscow. Also, there is no doubt at all of the changes<br />
that are occurring, economically, socially and politically not only<br />
in the countries that I visited but indeed in the whole of South<br />
East Asia and the Western Pacific as well. </p>
<p>2<br />
Japan and I say this, Mr Saito in your presence<br />
as you know, has emerged as a very great power and I think in the not<br />
too distant future, you will see its political influence ex pnding,<br />
and particularly will see a greater attempt at rapprochement with<br />
its nearest and big nighbour immediately to the West.<br />
Britain, of course, will be going into the Common<br />
Market quite soon and that must have an impact on us of the size and<br />
of the duration that for the moment we cannot foretell.<br />
And, of course, there are also problems of our own<br />
stability and growth. rhu QOD<br />
These all give us, I believe, a very significant role to<br />
play in the South East Asian and Pacific region. I hope therefore<br />
you will bear with me if I mention some points of importance as they<br />
affect Australia and our relations with our Asian friends. And then<br />
I would like to refer more particularly to trade and investment<br />
and in truth, this is exactly what I want to speak to you about tonight.<br />
I went to Indonesia, Singapore and Malaysia as Prime<br />
Minister of Australia because our relationships there have a direct<br />
bearing on our defence and security arrangements and on our economic<br />
activities. I had no domestic arguments to export, and I think this<br />
is one of the reasons that wherever I went and it was learnt that I<br />
was not going to engage in political activities whilst I was overseas,<br />
that we were able to talk so frankly and so freely together while our<br />
relationships not only improved but I doubt whether they could have<br />
been very much better.<br />
I wanted simply to do what I could to strengthen our<br />
friendships and increase our understandings on these vital matters,<br />
and I believe the mission did exactly that. This came across very<br />
strongly in my talks with the Heads of Government in the three countries,<br />
with their administrations, and I believe with the people themselves.<br />
Because you do get an impression and I speak of only<br />
one capital and that was Djakarta.... it was unbelievable for a person<br />
like myself who hadn't been a Prime Minister for very long, to drive<br />
through throngs of children, probably as many as twenty or thirty<br />
thousand, they knowing you are Australian and ready to cheer for the<br />
fact that you have come from this wonderful country of ours.<br />
The official and private talks just could not have been<br />
freer and friendlier, nor more outspoken or have taken us more into<br />
their confidence. Wherever we went, the press, radio and television<br />
gave us a fair go, and I can impress that upon you.<br />
I had what I felt was a good meeting of minds with<br />
President Soeharto of Indonesia, Pr we Minister Lee Kuan Yew of<br />
Singapore and Prime Minister Tun Razak of Malaysia. They, too and I </p>
<p>64 i1<br />
3<br />
can confirm this they expressed appreciation of what we were<br />
doing and of our great interest in their countries. They wanted<br />
that interest to develop and they kept impressing on me their<br />
desirability that Australian businessmen should go there and should<br />
take part in the development of their own companies and of the<br />
companies to which they were going.<br />
I believe that te visit has helped to strengthen the<br />
security of Australia and generally opened up new prospects for<br />
closer relationships in the future in all manner of ways. It was a<br />
most encouraging and stimulating experience for me and all the members<br />
of my party. There was between Indonesia and us a complete<br />
understanding of how each is contributing to better security and<br />
to better prospects for economic growth in South-East Asia. We<br />
are co-operating very closely.<br />
In Singapore and Malaysia we again found a complete<br />
accord at the highest levels and in their own words, there were<br />
no issues between us because we are of the same mind. And that,<br />
too, was a worthwhile contribution to our own security and the<br />
security of the region.<br />
0 Now, Mr Chairman, may I elaborate a little on my<br />
discussions in South-East Asia on trade and investment. I had a<br />
senior member of the Department of Trade and Industry with me, and<br />
we had most constructive discussions in all three countries we<br />
visited. They ranged over a wide area finance and banking,<br />
trade and development, aid, particularly economic aid and defence<br />
aid as well. And what struck me most in all these discussions was<br />
the differences that there were in the various stages of development.<br />
What they are concerned to do in each of the countries is to create<br />
new employment opportunities for their people. This means they seek<br />
to raise living standards progressively in the years ahead.<br />
Unfortunately, and I say this with deep feeling, their<br />
resources of investment capital and foreign exchange particularly<br />
in Indonesia and Malaysia are far too limited, and they look to<br />
us, not only for support, but understanding as well.<br />
Increasingly, they regard Australia as a growing market<br />
for their exports and as a source of capital funds. Trade between<br />
the countries in thn region has been growing over recent years and<br />
undoubtedly will continue to expand in the future. t<br />
Many Australian firms have already taken advantage of<br />
the special incentives provided by these countries for foreign<br />
investment and have established operations in the South-East Asian<br />
area. I believe that Australia has reached a stage in its economic<br />
development which allows us to adopt a much more liberal attitude<br />
towards overseas investment by Australian firms. This was the<br />
subject of a statement by my colleague, the Treasurer, in the<br />
Parliament in February. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
At that time, Mr Snedden said<br />
" Direct investment accompanied by exports of technical<br />
know-how and managerial skills which give the Australian<br />
enterprise a role in the conduct of an overseas venture,<br />
is an important means by which Australia can contribute<br />
to development and growth of other countries. This is<br />
particularly true of countries in the Pacific and South-<br />
East Asian region."<br />
I fully endorse his view. And I can assure you from<br />
my personal contacts how much Australian investment is welcomed<br />
in the region. In Indonesia, I unveiled the foundation stone for a<br />
new factory which will produce glass containers, probably between<br />
to 25 per cent of their total requirements. The major partner<br />
was an Australian company, Australian Consolidated Industries.<br />
And if I can say this, one of the disappointing moments<br />
I had going through Djakarta was to see branch banking systems of<br />
the great American banks such as Chase Manhattan and First National<br />
City and banks from the Continent and other olaces. But to my<br />
surprise, even to my anguish, I found there wasn't a single<br />
Australian branch bank there. Butnow we are moving to<br />
establish representative banks, and Indonesia has closed off the<br />
prospect of further branch bankincg systems being estabished there.<br />
In Singapore, I visited a very successful Australian<br />
factory Besley Pike at the Jurong Industrial Estate.<br />
These factories are tangible examples of the role of<br />
private Australian capital in the economic development of the area.<br />
Arrangements have already bceen put in hand which I<br />
believe will lead to even better trade relations and economic<br />
co-operation. The Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Trade<br />
and Industry, Doug Anthony, will visit Indonesia early in July for<br />
important trade talks including the review of our bilateral trade<br />
agreement. Similarly, we have advised the Malaysian authorities<br />
of our readiness to review our trade agreement with that country<br />
when they are ready to do so. In both cases, the reviews would be<br />
aimed at ensuring that the trade agreements reflect the current<br />
nature of our trading relationships and cater for the high level of<br />
interest in trade with, and investment in, Indonesia and Malaysia. </p>
<p>5<br />
I have also said that we are prepared to consider<br />
additions to the list of itcms already covered by our system of<br />
tariff preferences for developing countries.<br />
Itis now generally recognised that it is essential to<br />
establish a closer relationship between our respective business<br />
leaders. An Austraian/ Indonesian Business Co-operation Committee<br />
has already been established. It is very encouraging to note the<br />
large number of senior Australian businessmen who have joined together<br />
to promote this organisation.<br />
I have suggested, in conversation with iTn Razak, that a<br />
similar arrangement be made with Malaysia, and I hope that Australian<br />
businessmen will become interested in it. When I raised this question<br />
with the Malaysian Finance Minister, he mentioned they were so<br />
anxious to get our investment and the possibility of getting a far<br />
greater degree of investment there, that they would use their Capital<br />
Dsvelopment Council as the vehicle for developing links with<br />
Australian manufacturers, And whilst I am not in a position where I would be able<br />
tc commit either the Malaysian Government or the Capital Investment<br />
Council itself, I do believe that if Australian business interests<br />
were prepared to have discussions with that Investment Council or<br />
the management of that Investment Council, they would see they are<br />
willing to provide incentives for investment opportunities there.<br />
The private sector advisory panel of the Council might, as<br />
Tun Razak and the Minister for finance thought, be an appropriate<br />
mechanism by which you could, if you wished to, make contact and try<br />
and ensure that that contact was successful.<br />
Now, gentlemen: it is one thing for governments to<br />
express a desire for closer economic relationships. However, at<br />
the end of the day, the ultimate decisions on individual investment<br />
projects or commercial transactions must be taken by the businessmen<br />
themselves. The main purpose of these Committees will be to enable<br />
business leaders in our respective countries to meet and review<br />
problems and prospects relating to mutual trade and investment.<br />
There were a number of other matters raised in the course<br />
of our discussions. These will be pursued further through normal<br />
diplomatic channels. </p>
<p>6<br />
I am wholly satisfied of the scope and need for greater<br />
Australian participation in economic development in South-East<br />
Asia. I think I can assure you that there is sincere goodwill<br />
towards Australia and also that the regard for individual Australians<br />
is very high. I have, too, taken this problem up with both the Treasury<br />
itself and the Reserve Bank and we will shortly be as we have<br />
recently produced a paper on international investment we will<br />
very shortly be putting down a paper in the House that will deal<br />
with this problem of investment by Australians overseas.<br />
Now, Mr Chairman, these activities, of course, have to be<br />
locked at in the context of our overall trade and investment<br />
position, and I will conclude with some general observations about<br />
that. In all external economic transactions, the balance of<br />
payments is maintaining a very strong position with record performances<br />
developing in a number of areas in the current year. In the first<br />
nine months of 1971/ 72; exports rose more than $ 403 million above<br />
S the level in the corresponding neriod of 1970/ 71. The more recent<br />
figuces for May indicate that this trend has been accelerating.<br />
For 1971/ 72 as a whole, exports could well be about $ 4,800 million.<br />
I remember when I was Treasurer and we got to a figure<br />
of somewhere about $ 2,400 million, we thought it was an occasion<br />
for celebration, Now this was achieved despite some slowdown in the growth<br />
of exports of mining products ( turning to Mr Saito)... I won't<br />
continue because he knows the answer and you know the answer too.<br />
I believe myself it is only a temporary slowdown in our exports to<br />
one of the great countries to our north.<br />
Firmer prices overseas for a number of rural products have<br />
led to a substantial growth of rural exports, and exports of<br />
S manufacturers have grown very rapidly this year. In contrast,<br />
imports, reflecting the slower rate of growth in the level of domestic<br />
activity, have risen much less than exports.<br />
In consequence, the balance of trade surplus ie currently<br />
running at more than double the level at this time last year, and<br />
looks like achieving a record level around $ 100 million for 1971/ 72.<br />
On the invisibles transactions, the net deficit has continued to<br />
increase, but at a slower rate than in recent years. This improvement,<br />
combined with the arger trade surplus, has made a significant reduction<br />
in the current account deficit, which may be less than $ 400 million<br />
in 1971/ 72 as a whole. This is the smallest current account deficit<br />
for almost a decade. / 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
If I can go back a little, I can well remember in the<br />
time of the Menzies Government, when we used to think of having<br />
current account deficits not of $ 400 million but we would talk<br />
of them in the thousands and probably the two thousands.<br />
So what it does indicate to me is the ability of the<br />
Australian, not only to produce, but to got out and sell, and to<br />
get out and compete and to win in international company.<br />
But I believe when I read of recent exploits of the<br />
Broken Hill Pty. Co. Ltd., in winning the contracts it did in the<br />
Eurcpean markets, again it confirmed my belief in the Australian<br />
manufacturer and the Australian producer, and their ability to do<br />
the job when they have the opportunity and the will to do so.<br />
We have also had a very strong increase in caoital inflow.<br />
This brings with it certain problems which we are examining. The<br />
overall balance of payments outcome in 1971/ 72 will thus be one of<br />
substantial surplus, perhaps of the order of $ 1,500 million. This<br />
surplus on external account places us well to meet the various<br />
challenges and uncertainties which lie ahead.<br />
In particular, the international monetary situation,<br />
although it has settled down in recent months from the turmoil of the<br />
second half of 1971, still has some way to go before we can have<br />
Scomplete confidence in its viability. Discussions on possible long<br />
term changes in the system could begin later this year.<br />
If I can now say this. In some of the visits we have<br />
had in recent weeks, particularly by Governor Connally, and some<br />
of the talks I have had with my colleagues, as for example, with<br />
my colleagues, the New Zealanders, have all indicated to me how<br />
desirable it is that the sooner we can come to grips with this<br />
problem of foreign exchanges to try and get them more stable, the<br />
better it will be for us. And I do hope, Mr Prime Minister, and<br />
I express this in your presence, that you will be thinking of<br />
entering the OECD and Working Party No. 3, and when that happens,<br />
if there has to be a group of 20, that you will join with us in<br />
seeing that multilateral exchanges and multilateral trade are for<br />
the benefit of our two countries.<br />
So discussions on possible long-term changes in the<br />
system will go on and I hope we can start very soon. As well,<br />
a very important round of multilateral trade negotiations is scheduled<br />
to begin in 1973, equivalent to the Kennedy Round negotiations which<br />
are so beneficial to world trade. On the domestic front a review of<br />
the tariff is in progress.<br />
These developments in the monetary and trade fields could<br />
have important implications for our external economic position.<br />
I / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
In the shorter term, the Government h * as in recent<br />
months acted to stimulate the level of demand and economic<br />
activity. Nevertheless, on present indications we can expect the<br />
balance of payments to continuc in strong surplus in 1972/ 73.<br />
These large and continuing balance of payments surpluses<br />
can bring their own problems, just6 as balance of payments deficits<br />
can. The Government will therefore be watching closely developments<br />
on the external account in the months ahead.<br />
If I can just make an interpolation to what I have<br />
just said, fortunately for us now as the development of the work<br />
of the Government Statistician, and the private and Commonwealth<br />
banking system, we can now identify in a way that we have never<br />
been able to do not only the source but the first use of the funds<br />
that are coming to Australia. And this I can to you, . the<br />
very largest proportion of the money that is coming in is for<br />
direct investment, and is therefore making its contribution to the<br />
growth and development of this community.<br />
I am confident, therefore, that by maintaining the<br />
flexibility which has been a characteristic of our economic<br />
management, we can deal with new situations as they arise, and<br />
justify the confidence which I believe is now beginning to flow<br />
quite strongly from the business community.<br />
Our neighbours in South-East Asia made it clear to me<br />
that they regard Australia as a country making a considerable<br />
contribution to stability in the region. We must continue to<br />
justify that confidence by our performance at home and by our<br />
readiness to explore new prospects abroad.<br />
I hope everyone of you as a businessman here will<br />
have the opportunity to visit each of the countries I visited.<br />
You will get a reception of a kind that you will find unexpected<br />
but generous and warm. But above all things I believe that if<br />
you do go, end you go with enthusiasm, you will find that not only<br />
can you do much to get expansion of trade on behalf of your<br />
own companies, but also you will be able to make your contribution<br />
to inter-country development prospects, inter-country trade<br />
developments, and by this means, you can make the four of us<br />
much more wealthy, and our prospects much brighter that I gather,<br />
Sir Robert, was conveyed to you by some of the speakers this<br />
morning, and later on this afternoon.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
