<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3877</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER FOR THE GERMAN-AUSTRIAN CLUB JAHRESBALL, CABRAMATTA, 6 SEPTEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003877.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER FOR THE GERMAN-AUSTRIAN<br />
CLUB JAHRESBALL, CABRAMATTA, 6 SEPTEMBER 1975<br />
1. I AM DELIGHTED TO BE WITH YOU HERE TONIGHT WITH<br />
MY WIFE, BACK IN MY OWN ELECTORATE, BACK AT THE GERMAN<br />
AUSTRIAN CLUB FOR THE TENTH ANNIVERSARY YEAR OF YOUR CLUB<br />
BUILDING. I WAS PROUD TO BE INVITED TO LAY THE FOUNDATION<br />
STONE BACK IN 1965, WHEN I WAS THE DEPUTYLEADER OF THE<br />
OPPOSITION AS WELL AS YOUR LOCAL MEMBER. I THOUGHT THEN<br />
THAT YOU SHOWED GREAT FAITH, GREAT POLITICAL ACUMEN,<br />
I. KNEW THAT YOU COULDN'T BE ACCUSED OF PLAYING REALPOLITIK,<br />
BECAUSE A DEPUTY LEADER OF AN OPPOSITION CAN BE AS FAR<br />
AWAY FROM LEADERSHIP AS THE LEADER OF AN OPPOSITION IS<br />
FROM LEADING THE COUNTRY. BUT I LIKE TO THINK THAT SOME<br />
OF YOU BACK IN 1965 BELIEVED THAT IN YEARS TO COME,<br />
GOUGH WHITLAM MIGHT RETURN AS PRIME MINISTER, AND I DID, IN 1972.<br />
2. IT WASN'T SO APPARENT IN MARCH 1965, WHEN I LAID<br />
THE FOUNDATION STONE, THAT 1965 WAS TO BECOME A WATERSHED<br />
IN GERMANY'S MODERN POLITICAL HISTORY. IN SEPTEMBER THAT<br />
YEAR, 1965, JUST TEN YEARS AGO THIS MONTH, A MAN CALLED<br />
WILLI BRANDT WAS ELECTED TO THE BUNDESTAG. BUT ALTHOUGH<br />
HE WAS CHAIRMAN OF THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATS, HE CHOSE NOT TO<br />
TAKE HIS SEAT IMMEDIATELY BECAUSE HE WANTED TO REMAIN AS<br />
GOVERNING BURGERMEISTER OF WEST BERLIN. ER WAR BERLINER,<br />
TO RECALL THAT GREAT PHRASE OF JOHN F. KENNEDY. I HAVE NO<br />
DOUBT THAT YOU ALL KNOW OF MY OWN GREAT ADMIRATION FOR<br />
WILLI BRANDT. I WAS ONCE ASKED TO NOMINATE THE GREAT WORLD<br />
LEADERS AND STATESMEN OF OUR TIME. a/ 2 </p>
<p>-2]<br />
IHAD NO HESITATION IN NOMINATING WILLI BRANDT; I HAVE NO<br />
HESITATION IN NOMINATING WILLI BRANDT. MY INVITATION TO<br />
HIM TO VISIT THIS COUNTRY STANDS, WHATEVER HIS POLITICAL<br />
FORTUNES. AND AS IT HAPPENS HE IS NOW AGAIN CHAIRMAN OF THE<br />
SOCIAL DEMOCRATS, JUST AS HE WAS IN 1965.<br />
3. BUT ANOTHER EVENT OF GREAT GERMAN POLITICAL SIGNIFICANCE<br />
WAS TO HAPPEN BY THE END OF 1965, AND I DON'T MEAN THE<br />
OPENING OF YOUR CLUBHOUSE BY THE AUSTRIAN CONSUL GENERAL,<br />
THEN AND NOW PROFESSOR FELSER.<br />
IREFER TO THE RESIGNATION, ON CHRISTMAS DAY 1965,<br />
OF KONRAD ADENDUER AS HEAD OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATICUNION,<br />
A POSITION HE HAD HELD SINCE 1946. HE WAS TWO WEEKS OFF<br />
BIRTHDAY. CHRISTMAS DAY 1965 MARKED THE END OF AN<br />
ERA IN GERMANY.<br />
4. BUT THE LAST DECADE HAS SEEN UNIMAGINED CHANGES IN THE<br />
WORLD, NOT JUST IN GERMANY. THE POST-WAR LEADERS WERE<br />
ALREADY CHANGING IN 1965; SOME INDEED HAD ALREADY GONE.<br />
HOW MANY OF THE WORLD'S LEADERS AND STATESMEN WHO WERE IN<br />
POWER IN 1965 ARE STILL THERE TODAY? THINK OF CHARLES DE GAULLE*<br />
LYNDON JOHNSON, SUKARNO, Ho CHI MINH.-U THANTo<br />
EVEN OF COURSE SIR ROBERT MENZIES. IT IS SOBERING TO CONTEMPLATE.-<br />
BUT WE CAN ALL TAKE HEART FROM THE FACT THAT THE AGELESS<br />
MARLENE DIETRICH ! S STILL WITH US, AND MOREOVER, WITH US IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, TONIGHT, " FALLING IN LOVE AGAIN" </p>
<p>-3-<br />
OF COURSE, I HAVEN'T HEARD HER SING ADVANCE AUSTRALIA<br />
FAIR YET, BUT I RECALL BEING QUITE ENCHANTED, MANY YEARS AGO,<br />
ON HEARING THE VIENNA Boys CHOIR SINGING VALZING MATILDA AND<br />
GOD SAVE YOUR GRACIOUS QUEEN$ IN THESE DAYS OF FREQUENT<br />
REFUGEE CRISES IT IS WORTH RECALLING THAT AUSTRALIA BENEFITED<br />
IMMEASURABLY BY TAKING CARE OF AN EARLIER TOURING VIENNA<br />
Boys CHOIR, STRANDED HERE AS A RESULT OF THE WAR.<br />
BUT TO RETURN TO ANTHEMS, I MUST TELL YOU OF THE THRILL MY<br />
WIFE AND IFELT WHEN WE ARRIVED IN KO-LN IN JANUARY THIS<br />
YEAR, TO BE GREETED BY A SUPERBLY STIRRING RENDITION OF<br />
BOTH THE AUSTRALIAN AND GERMAN NATIONAL ANTHEMS.<br />
6. WE HAD ONLY TWO DAYS IN GERMANY DURING OUR EUROPEAN<br />
VISIT, BUT VERY FULL AND PRODUCTIVE DAYS THEY WERE, IN<br />
BONN, K6LN AND HAMBURG. RECALLING THE OUTSTANDING CONTRIBUTION<br />
MADE TO AUSTRALIA'S DEVELOPMENT BY MANY THOUSANDS OF GERMAN<br />
SETTLERS AND THEIR DESCENDANTS, IT IS HARD TO BELIEVE THAT<br />
MY VISIT To GERMANY WAS ONLY THE SECOND BY AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
PRIME MINISTER. THE PREVIOUS VISIT HAD BEEN BY SIR ROBERT<br />
C MENZIES 16 YEARS EARLIER. IBELIEVED IT WAS HIGH TIME TO<br />
RECTIFY THAT STATE OF AFFAIRS. Now, MORE THAN EVER, WE NEED<br />
TO RECOGNISE THE IMPORTANCE, THE VALUE OF OUR LINKS WITH<br />
EUROPE. 7. WHILE'I WAS IN GERMANY;' I NOT ONLY HAD THE PLEASURE OF<br />
MEETING FORMALLY WITH THE CHANCELLOR HELMUT SCHMIDT, AND<br />
WITH THE PRESIDENT, HERR SCHEEL, IN BONN, BUT I ALSO HAD<br />
INFORMAL AND VERY FRUITFUL DI-SCUSSIONS WITH THE PRESIDENT<br />
OF THE FEDERATION OF GERMANY INDUSTRY ( THE [ N K6' LNI<br />
a 14 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
IN EACH CASE I WAS ABLE TO REMIND MY HOSTS OF THE GREAT<br />
CONTRIBUTION MADE By GERMAN'Y MIGRANTS To AUSTRALIA, AND OF<br />
THE FLOURISHING CLUBS YOU HAVE ESTABLISHED TO KEEP ALIVE<br />
CUSTOMS AND TRADITIONS OF WHICH YOU ARE JUSTLY PROUD.<br />
8. IN MAY WE RECEIVED A GERMAN TRADE AND INVESTMENT MISSION<br />
LED By HERR GRUENER, PARLIAMENTARY STATE SECRETARY, AND<br />
INCLUDING SENIOR GOVERNMENT OFFICERS AND REPRESENTATIVES<br />
OF PRIVATE INDUSTRY. THIS VISIT AROSE DIRECTLY FROM THE<br />
SUGGESTION MADE BY THE GERMAN FOREIGN MINISTER, HERR GENSCHER<br />
DURING MY VISIT, THAT SUCH A VISIT WOULD BE ESPECIALLY<br />
VALUABLE IN PROVIDING A COMPREHENSIVE UNDERSTANDING OF)<br />
AUSTRALIA'S FOREIGN INVESTMENT POLICY. I READILY AGREED.<br />
IN NOVEMBER WE WILL HAVE THE PLEASURE OF THE COMPANY OF<br />
PARLIAMENTARY UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, HERR MOERSCH WHO<br />
WILL BE VISITING AUSTRALIA AS PART OF A TOUR OF SOUTH EAST<br />
ASIA DESIGNED TO PUT HIM IN TOUCH WITH THE LATEST POST<br />
VIETNAM DEVELOPMENTS IN OUR REGION, ONE THING WHICH WILL<br />
BE OF OBVIOUS INTEREST IS THE PROGRESS MADE BY PAPUA NEW<br />
GUINEA, WHICH BECOMES INDEPENDENT ON 16 SEPTEMBER. SINCE<br />
NEW GUINEA WAS ONCE A GERMAN MANDATED TERRITORY, AND SINCE<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS HAD THE MOST RECENT TRUSTEEESHIP TASK, OUR<br />
INTEREST IS MUTUAL,<br />
ANOTHER VERY IMPORTANT VISITOR SCHEDULED TO COME TO<br />
AUSTRALIA IN FEBRUARY OR MARCH NEXT YEAR IS THE MAYOR OF<br />
WEST BERLIN, HERR KLAUS SCH'UTZ... As I MENTIONED BEFORE THERE<br />
IS A STANDING INVITATION TO -ONE OF HIS PREDECESSORS, WILLI<br />
BRANDT, JUST AS THERE IS FOR CHANCELLOR SCHMIDT AND<br />
FOREIGN MINISTER GENSCHER. s v </p>
<p>9, FIND IT GRATIFYING THAT TOP LEVEL VISITS OF THIS<br />
NATURE BETWEEN OUR COUNTRIES ARE BECOMING THE RULE RATHER<br />
. THAN THE EXCEPTION, IT IS ONLY PROPER THAT THERE SHOULD BE<br />
MORE REGULAR CONTACT BETWEEN THE LEADERS AND THE PEOPLE OF<br />
GERMANY AND AUSTRIA AND AUSTRALIA. CERTAINLY MANY MORE<br />
AUSTRALIANS ARE TRAVELLING To GERMANY AND AUSTRIA THAN WAS<br />
THE CASE TEN YEARS AGO, NOT LEAST BECAUSE INCREASING NUMBERS<br />
OF AUSTRALIANS ARE WANTING TO SEEK THE SNOW RATHER THAN THE<br />
SUNSHINE DURING THE AUSTRALIAN SUMMER MONTHS.<br />
AND TOURISTS COMING TO AND TRAVELLING ROUND AUSTRALIA<br />
CAN BE IN NO DOUBT AS TO THE CULTURAL CONTRIBUTION MADE BY<br />
AUSTRIAN AND GERMAN SETTLERS IN AUSTRALIA, THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN DEPARTMENT OF TOURISM AND RECREATION PRODUCES A<br />
PUBLICATION, N~ OW IN ITS SECOND EDITION, CALLED " AUSTRALIAA<br />
LAND OF THINGS To THIS DEALS WITH THE ATTRACTIONS,<br />
SCENIC, CULTURAL, CULINARY, SPORTING AND RECREATIONAL OF<br />
EACH STATE IN TURN. IT ALSO LISTS THE FESTIVALS WHICH TAKE<br />
PLACE IN OUR MAIN CITIES. THERE AREN'T THAT MANY, AS IT<br />
HAPPENS, BUT THERE IS ALWAYS EITHER AN OKTOBERFEST OR A<br />
SCHUTZENFEST, FROM DARWIN TO SYDNEY. FROM HAHNDORF TO HOBART.<br />
AND WHENEVER I POSSIBLY CAN, I MAKE IT MY BUSINESS TO PROCURE<br />
AN INVITATION WHICH IS VERY EASY -AND TO ATTEND -WHICH<br />
IS OFTEN QUITE HARD.<br />
NOW THIS YEAR I HAVE BEEN INVITED TO BOTH BRISBANE'S<br />
OKTOBERFEST, AND TO YOUR OKTOBERFEST. AND SINCE THIS YEAR<br />
YOUR OKTOBERFEST, OUR OKTOBEFkFEST, IS COMING-HOME To FAIRFIELDAFTER<br />
BEING HELD IN ANOTHER PLACE YOU WILL KNOW WHICH<br />
OKTOBERFEST I WILL ATTEND. I'LL TRY TO GET To BRISBANE AS<br />
WELL, BUT I HAVE A FIRM ENGAGEMENT TO Al [ END OUR OKTOBERFEST </p>
<p>-6-<br />
ON 4j OCTOBER, AND I LOOK FORWARD VERY MUCH TO SEEING YOU<br />
ALL AGAIN FOR THAT ANNUAL FESTIVAL, HAVE THE FONDEST<br />
MEMORIES OF THE MANY O. KTOBERFESTS I HAVE ATTENDED OVER<br />
THE YEARS., AM SURE THIS WILL BE NO EXCEPTION,<br />
11 IPAY TRIBUTE TO EVERYONE CONNECTED WITH THIS EVENING'S<br />
JAHRESBALL, AS WELL AS THE OKTOBERFEST, AND TO ALL THOSE OF<br />
GERMAN AND AUSTRIAN DESCENT WHO HAVE DONE SO MUCH TO MAKE<br />
AUSTRALIA A MORE DIVERSE, A MORE STIMULATING, A MORE ENJOYABLE<br />
PLACE TO LIVE. AT THE LAST CENSUS IN 1971, THERE WERE 23,941<br />
PEOPLE IN' AUSTRALIA WHO WERE BORN IN AUSTRIA AND 110,811<br />
WHO WERE BORN IN GERMANY. THIS COMPARES WITH 1902 FROM<br />
AUSTRIA AND 38,352 FROM GERMANY WHO WERE HERE IN 1901, THE<br />
YEAR OF FEDERATION.<br />
' THEY AND THEIR DESCENDANTS HAVE GIVEN SO MUCH OF<br />
THEMSELVES AND OF THEIR HERITAGE TO EACH OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
STATES AND TERRITORIES IN THE YEARS SINCE FEDERATION,<br />
THAT AUSTRALIA SHOULD BE, AND IS GRATEFUL TO THEM. YOU CAN<br />
BE SURE THAT I STRESSED THIS ON MY VISIT To GERMANY EARLIER<br />
THIS YEAR. THANK YOU FOR WHAT YOU HAVE ALL DONE FOR MY<br />
HEIMATLAND, AND THANK YOU FOR MAKING ME SO WELCOME HERE AND<br />
IN GERMAN AND AUSTRIAN COMMUNITIES THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>CURRENT PENSION/ BENEFITS<br />
PAID TO PEOPLE RESIDING IN<br />
AUSTRIA AND GERLMANY<br />
Social Welfare Branch<br />
3 September 1975<br />
Pension/ Benefit N. S. W. Total Australian Total<br />
Austria W. Germanv Austria W. Germany<br />
Age 13 23 33 105<br />
Invalid 6 5 14 16<br />
Wives 2 1 4 8<br />
Widows 0 4 3 22<br />
Supporting Mothers 0 1 1 2<br />
Total 21 34 55 153 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
