<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5041</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/05/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005041.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 6 MAY 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
This week I will be leaving for a brief visit to the<br />
Philippines, where the 5th Session of the United Nations<br />
Conference on Trade and Development is beginning.<br />
I was pleased to accept the long-standing invitation from<br />
President MarTcos to visit his couintry.<br />
Australia and the Philippines have a warm relationship.<br />
Apart from cultural and tourist links, trade between us is<br />
growing fast, with total two-way trade now nearing $ 200 million.<br />
The Philippines is also an important member of the ASEAN group<br />
of nations, and our ties with ASEAN continue to develop year<br />
by year.<br />
The UNCTAD session is an important one. It will focus attention<br />
on international trade-problems and this is an issue of vital<br />
concern not only to developing countries, but to the general<br />
world community.<br />
Australia of course is a developed country, but as a major<br />
trading nation we understand the very real problems of the<br />
developing world. These problems have been well chronicled.<br />
There is a need to free up world trade to reduce<br />
protectionism and to seek to open up new markets. The<br />
need is in human terms. In some developing countries average<br />
annual incomes are no more than $ 200 while less than one in<br />
five adults are literate.<br />
Between the various developing countries themselves, there is<br />
a wide divergence of living standards. Many African and Latin<br />
American-Caribbean countries are not as well off as<br />
developing countries in the Asian region. This of course is<br />
due to many factors, but in part reflects on the effectiveness<br />
of economic policies carried out by developing countries<br />
in the Asian region, and in particular their tackling of<br />
inflation. It is a simple fact of life that the livelihood and well-being<br />
of millions of families in developing countries depends so<br />
much on access for their products in markets of the world. They<br />
a * re at the whim. of strongly fluctuating commodity prices.<br />
Over the years, unstable prices and restricted access have hit<br />
developing countries. Australia knows this from our own<br />
experience. Of course, for purchasing countries, boom-and-bust<br />
markets have caused sudden and massive swings in prices<br />
contributing to inflation and inflationary expectations.<br />
It is therefore in the global interest that there be stable,<br />
soundly-based commodity trade. 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Australia earnestly believes that a viable and well-managed<br />
Common Fund, which countries in thc international community<br />
have worked on for some years, can help achieve this<br />
goal. In a very real sense, we have been the catalyst in<br />
bringing the developed and developing world closer together<br />
on thi's fundamental issue.<br />
The importance of face-to-face discussions in forums like<br />
UINCTA) can never be stressed too much. It is crucial that<br />
in a world facing so many fundamental economic and trade<br />
problems that leaders have the opportunity to listen personally<br />
to each other's views. Clearly, there has to be more<br />
communication between world leaders. Written communication<br />
between Governments is necessary and unavoidable, but it can<br />
never replace personal contact, for getting to the<br />
nub of problems.<br />
While in Manila, I will be having extensive discussions also<br />
with the recently elected Prime Minister of Japan, Mr. Ohira.<br />
Japan has invited Australia to present our views on<br />
international trade and economic issues prior to the important<br />
Tokyo Economic Summit. It is an invitation we welcome<br />
and appreciate.. Among other meetings I will also talk with<br />
Mr. Ramphal, Secretary-General of the Commonwealth Secretariat,<br />
on the forthcoming Commonwealth -leads of Government meeting in<br />
Lusaka and on matters such as the Common Fund.<br />
Countries much larger and more powerful than Australia<br />
recognize our unique position and our special experience.<br />
We are a developed country with close links with developing<br />
countries. We are a significant trader with expertise in<br />
marketing of commodities like sugar, wheat and wool.<br />
While we recognize the limits of our influence, we must continue<br />
to take an active part in discussions and negotiations on<br />
w~ orld economic issues. My meetings this week in Manila<br />
demonstrate again the Government's strong desire to continue<br />
as a responsible member of the international economic community.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
