<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3162</transcript-id>
    <title>APPOINTMENTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003162.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Press Statement No. 189<br />
18 February 1974<br />
APPOINTMENTS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, today announced the following<br />
appointments, which were approved by the Executive Council:-<br />
Mr. T. K. Critchley has been appointed High Commissioner<br />
of Papua New Guinea from 29 March. Mr. Critchley has been<br />
Australian Ambassador to Thailand since 1969. He was<br />
High Commissioner to Malaysia in 1957/ 65, and Senior<br />
External Affairs representative in London in 1966/ 69.<br />
Mr. Critchley, 58, will replace Mr. L. W. Johnson, who<br />
will be recommended to the Executive Council for appointment<br />
as head of the Australian Development Assistaiice Agency.<br />
Mr. V. E. Jennings has been appointed a part-time member<br />
of the C. S. I. R. O. Executive. Mr. Jennings, who is Managing<br />
Director of A. V. Jennings Industries ( Australia) Pty. Ltd.,<br />
will take up his appointment from 26 March.<br />
The appointment is for three years. He replaces<br />
Sir Henry Somerset, who is retiring.<br />
Mr. C. H. Webb has been appointed Administrator of<br />
hrstmas Island. Mr. Webb, a former will take<br />
up his appointment, which is for one year, on 15 March.<br />
He replaces Mr. F. S. Evatt.<br />
Two appointments have also been made to the Commonwealth<br />
Banking Corporation Board. Both appointments are for<br />
five years. Professor L. F. Crisp and Mr. J. J. Kennedy.<br />
Professor Crisp has been Professor of Political' Science<br />
at the Australian National University since 1950.<br />
He was Director-General of Post-War Reconstruction in<br />
1949/ 50. Mr. Kennedy, a Brisbane Accountant is<br />
proprietor of a chain of electrical retail stores.<br />
He was been appointed as a member of the Post Office<br />
Commission of Inquiry in February 1973.<br />
Professor Crisp and Mr. Kennedy will replace Sir Reginald<br />
Groom and Mr. R. J. Baxter, whose terms of office have<br />
expired.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T._ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
