<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17508</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech to the St Vincent&#039;s Institute Luncheon</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Health</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Langman Hotel, Melbourne </p>
<p>Thank you for your warm welcome - and a big "thank you" to the Australian Children's Choir for their outstanding performance here today.</p>
<p>We're here today because Sue Alberti has chosen to do something very special with an auction win from last year.</p>
<p>She could have sat down with five friends and enjoyed a luncheon with me.</p>
<p>Instead, she has transformed it into an opportunity to do good for the whole community, and that is so typical of Sue and her legendary generosity.</p>
<p>Today we launch an appeal that is very close to Sue's heart, and in doing so we remember her daughter Danielle with great affection and respect.</p>
<p>Danielle's passing is a reminder that we must fight hard for life and never, ever give up hope.</p>
<p>Friends,</p>
<p>We will honour Danielle's memory best by doing all we can to manage and defeat diabetes because diabetes is an insidious disease that we under-estimate at our peril.</p>
<p>It is not just a matter of insulin injections or monitoring your sugar levels.</p>
<p>It is a difficult condition to control with sufferers often battling multiple health problems.</p>
<p>For many, it can lead to the loss of limbs and even loss of life.</p>
<p>And like all chronic diseases, it requires constant management, placing a huge toll on patients and their families.</p>
<p>In short, diabetes is a serious condition that merits a serious response.</p>
<p>These points are not lost on me or on the Government.</p>
<p>That is why, from the first of July next year, we will invest more than $30 million to pilot Coordinated Care for Diabetes.</p>
<p>This program recognises the complexities of diabetes and will identify the most effective methods of care for those living with the disease.</p>
<p>This work will be undertaken through the Diabetes Advisory Group which includes Diabetes Australia and the Australian Medical Association and I understand the Diabetes Advisory Group are, in fact, meeting today.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the Coordinated Care pilot program, current arrangements for diabetes will continue with more than $2.7 billion invested in diabetes care over the next four years.</p>
<p>Of course, the Government is committed to a broader and long overdue reform of the entire health system.</p>
<p>And I want to share some of the key points today because your presence here shows a special commitment to the future of our health system.</p>
<p>The first thing about the future is that it can't be the same as the past.</p>
<p>The old model of block funding to the States and Territories cannot be sustained.</p>
<p>We need a system that delivers measurable results in return for the taxpayers' dollar.</p>
<p>A system that responds to community needs at the local level.</p>
<p>A system that delivers more early intervention and prevention so hospitals are a last resort not a first response.</p>
<p>Above all, we need the system to be financially sustainable into the future.</p>
<p>That is the purpose of the reforms we have agreed with all the States and Territories bar Western Australia.</p>
<p>Remember the Federal Government's health reforms have two interlocking purposes that every State and Territory needs to keep in mind.</p>
<p>First, by taking on 60 per cent of hospital costs and 100 per cent of community and aged care, the Commonwealth assumes the lion's share of rising health costs into the future.</p>
<p>That growing burden, which would have bankrupted the state treasuries by mid century, now shifts to the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>That means an increasing level of support, starting with at least?$15.6 billion in additional growth funding between now and 2020 above what the States and Territories would otherwise have received.</p>
<p>Yes, the Commonwealth is retaining a share of GST to increase its share of hospitals funding from less than 40 per cent to a permanent 60 per cent.</p>
<p>But the simple reality of this exercise is this:</p>
<p>- the amount of GST we will retain is worth substantially less than the amount we will give back to each state's hospital system.</p>
<p>And as hospital costs grow so quickly, that gap will only widen?over time.</p>
<p>Second, by taking the majority funder role, the Commonwealth will no longer have an incentive to cost-shift into the hospital system because we would only be cost-shifting onto ourselves.</p>
<p>That means we will look for the best way to treat patients - for example in community and aged care settings - rather than using hospitals as a lazy fallback option.</p>
<p>Taken together, our reforms are the biggest change to the nation's health system since Medicare.</p>
<p>It is the best deal the States and Territories will see in a generation.</p>
<p>Friends,</p>
<p>The health system is about working within the bounds of the known and the familiar using remedies that are proven to work and succeed.</p>
<p>But when we look to the future, we look for cures and treatments that exist only in the minds of our researchers.</p>
<p>Capturing those ideas and putting them into practice is exactly what our great research institutes like St Vincent's exist to do.</p>
<p>You and your sister institutions are writing the next chapter of medical science.</p>
<p>You are rehearsing the future that our children and grandchildren will inherit.</p>
<p>We may not recognise the names of those who devote their lives to research but their work resonates far beyond the laboratory walls.</p>
<p>That is why this year the Australian Government is backing them with $700 million in medical research funding, $430 million for research infrastructure.</p>
<p>I know your institution has its own ambitions with the planned Aikenhead Centre for Medical Discovery at Fitzroy and I understand Greg Sword in his capacity as Chair of St Vincent's has recently put a business case for this centre to the Government.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the great work of St Vincent's continues:</p>
<p>- on heart and bone diseases, cancer, Hepatitis, HIV/AIDS, Alzheimer's,</p>
<p>- and, of course, diabetes treatment which is such a special area of interest for us gathered here today.</p>
<p>I'm told that your islet transplant program has now resulted in four patients becoming independent of insulin a huge improvement in their dignity and quality of life.</p>
<p>I met one of those patients, Margaret Harrigan and we are honoured to have her here with us today.</p>
<p>Margaret's story is a great example of the fact that medical research changes lives.</p>
<p>And it points to a remarkable century of discovery that lies ahead.</p>
<p>But not all breakthroughs belong in the future.</p>
<p>There is something we can achieve right here and now; and that is to advance our understanding of childhood diabetes.</p>
<p>Today I am proud to launch the St Vincent's Institute Childhood Diabetes Appeal because as a society, we need to know more about Type 1 diabetes.</p>
<p>For a disease so prevalent, there is still so much more we have to learn.</p>
<p>What is happening in the immune system of people at risk of the disease?</p>
<p>How can we treat Type 1 diabetes without the use of needles?</p>
<p>The money raised through this Appeal will help unlock answers to these very fundamental questions.</p>
<p>Answers that, if achieved, will change the lives of thousands of Australian children.</p>
<p>Needless to say, if you are feeling a surge of the festive spirit, then give generously.</p>
<p>And I extend that invitation to our friends in the wider corporate world as well.</p>
<p>After all, that's why Sue has gathered us here today; to make a difference.</p>
<p>So dig deep and give the gift of hope to those kids living with the challenge of diabetes.</p>
<p>With special thanks to Sue Alberti, I officially launch the St Vincent's Institute Childhood Diabetes Appeal.</p>
<p>May the spirit of goodwill that has brought us here today sustain and inspire us in the year ahead.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
