<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9518</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RANALD MCDONALD, RADIO 3LO, 21 MARCH 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009518.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Ctio)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RANALD MCDONALD, RADIO 3L0, 21 MARCH 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
RM: . and on the line now is the Prime Minister Paul Keating. Good<br />
morning to you Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Good morning Ranald, how are you there?<br />
RM: Just back from your trip to the meeting . well, the international<br />
meeting on poverty, but you also went to a number of other countries<br />
on the way. Just a quick question about your trip and the way that you<br />
kept in touch with what was happening on the local scene were you<br />
in any way perhaps, did you feel that you needed to take your<br />
points and land your punches from overseas that you couldn't wait<br />
until you came back?<br />
PM: It was just that the travelling media roadshow feel that if they don't<br />
have a domestic story running at the same time, somehow they are<br />
dis-enfranchised from reporting news. I think that's more the problem.<br />
RM: One of the comments you made which of course did make headlines<br />
related to the appointment of the next Governor-General under the<br />
Presidency, and also the question of whether we should follow the<br />
German example I am just wondering whether you now have had<br />
second thoughts about the way that the Governor-General should be<br />
appointed whether you will go along with the suggestion I think Barry<br />
Jones feels is a good idea?<br />
PM: -Well, lam-saying this Ranald if people-want me to essentially give up<br />
the exclusive right to recommend to the Queen the appointment of the<br />
next Governor-General, I am happy to give it up. But it's in the context<br />
of an appointment of an Australian person as the Head of State, that<br />
is, to a republic. And that's why I believe... . more than ever, you go to<br />
these countries in Europe and what have you, Australia is now so well<br />
regarded not only in the Asia Pacific, but also in Europe as a<br />
country. One of the points, for instance, that I made to Chancellor </p>
<p>Helmut Kohl was that you know this notion of the European Monetary<br />
Union of the Maastricht Treaty and the so-called convergence criteria<br />
for countries joining in a single currency in Europe? The only two<br />
countries in the world this year that meet the criteria are Germany and<br />
Australia. Now, we're not in Europe, and we don't want to join it, but<br />
we are the only other OECD country that could. So Australia's<br />
stanaing in Europe in Asia is very, very high indeed, ana to say " just<br />
by the way, we are borrowing the monarchy of another country". See,<br />
when I turn up to see the German Chancellor, normally when<br />
Australian Prime Ministers have been through, they have had a little<br />
chat with the British Foreign Secretary, and the Germans say " well,<br />
here comes not simply Britain across the Channel, but some chip off<br />
the block". I'm saying well forget all that that's all past. This is now<br />
well and truly a country with an independent identity, culture and by<br />
the way, we are thinking now of moving to an Australian republic with<br />
an Australian Head of State, very similar to yours where you have a<br />
Head of State, but you also have a Parliamentary Government.<br />
RM: Just as though talking about Bill Hayden's retirement which is coming<br />
up pretty soon do you therefore feel that it would be appropriate to at<br />
least run a test and have an appointed or elected by the two houses<br />
together the Senate and the House of Representatives in other<br />
words, that you don't select him?<br />
PM: I notice... . my very clear view of all this is the people are suggesting -I<br />
notice Jeff Kennett I think he was suggesting on your program last<br />
week, saying " well, this is not a bad idea", and I said " well look, when<br />
Jeffrey decides that we will have a republic, then I will take his<br />
suggestion seriously", and then he said " oh, it's outrageous raising<br />
these matters overseas". This is the character that has gone across to<br />
Greece and made an absolute meal out of trying to invest himself with<br />
some support with the Greek community of Melbourne by trying to take<br />
on a foreign policy issue in Greece, as a State Premier. He has then<br />
got the front to say to me that I shouldn't raise, with the German<br />
President, the fact that we are considering a republic ourselves, and in<br />
that Republic in that structure we are thinking of these options,<br />
including the appointment of the Head of State by both Houses of<br />
Parliament, or in other ways.<br />
RM: Of course, the other matter that you did discuss while you were<br />
overseas was the Packer deal, and just where that was is that going<br />
to continue? Is that debate between yourself and Kerry Packer going<br />
to follow on, or do you think that should be left?<br />
PM: I think we will just leave that and see what happens here. The thing is,<br />
it will be not me condemning John Howard it will be John Howard<br />
doing it himself . the position is this: I believe in media plurality. I<br />
believe there should be a separation on the ownership of these great<br />
media assets, and John Howard doesn't. So time will tell the proof of<br />
the pudding of this will be in the eating. </p>
<p>RM: Well of course, the question is whether a deal was done, and I think<br />
your own President Barry Jones said perhaps you put two and two<br />
together and did it logically and then drew a conclusion rather than<br />
actually having evidence that a deal was done do you have<br />
evidence?<br />
PM: It's just like any front page story in the Melbourne Age, or the Sydney<br />
Morning Herald you say to the journalists " what proof have you got of<br />
that?", and the journalist says " well, I have got plenty of proof of that"<br />
and you say " well, give it to me" and they say " oooh we are not<br />
revealing our sources". You know....<br />
RM: You're not revealing you sources?<br />
PM: On these things, don't worry about Barry's view on this. The key view<br />
on this is my own, and we do have media plurality for instance, we<br />
have got now an independent radio industry we never had 10 years<br />
ago, we have got television ownership which is now not associated<br />
with newspapers, as is mostly the case with radio. We have now got<br />
distinct rumours of private ownership diverse ownership of the<br />
media, which I think is a good thing for Australia.<br />
RM: Can I just move to your call for higher growth, and the discussions<br />
about Australia's recovering economy overseas how can we achieve<br />
higher growth without blowing out our current account?<br />
PM: It depends the economy is now slowing from the 6% growth we had in<br />
the September quarter of last year, because I think that was for us<br />
unsustainable. But we don't want to go back my point was in a<br />
European context I was really saying to a European audience where<br />
European economies grow by 1.5% saying get yourself locked<br />
into the Asia Pacific where the general growth is higher, and where in<br />
Australia in the 1980s we averaged 4% and at the moment we are<br />
growing somewhere between 5% That's the context of my<br />
remarks.<br />
RM: Can you put a figure on it though what's the figure we ought to look to<br />
as a satisfactory growth for the next decade perhaps, coming out of<br />
our recession?<br />
PM: We have got to grow at something like 4-4.5% to keep unemployment<br />
coming down. And that seems to me to be a social and an economic<br />
imperative to keep unemployment coming down. Now, part of the<br />
European problem, of course, they have nothing like the employment<br />
to growth translation that we in Australia get. If we have 3-4%<br />
economic growth, we get 3-4% employment growth, whereas if they<br />
have 3-4% economic growth in Europe, they might get 1 employment<br />
growth. So, we are getting a much better translation, and that's why at<br />
the moment we have had in the last year, 3.75% employment growth. </p>
<p>And when we had 590,000 job growth since the election which is<br />
phenomenal.<br />
RM: Well, what John Howard has just said on another station, can you<br />
guarantee that there won't be an interest rate hike soon after the or<br />
immediately after the NSW election? Is there going to be an interest<br />
rate increase?<br />
PM: This is one of those other shabby he said this in the 1980s after an<br />
election then, that the Reserve Bank had connived with the<br />
Government to hold interest rates down during the State election this<br />
is in 1987. And Bob Johnson the then Governor said of John<br />
Howard he rebuked him at a private lunch and said of him " relations<br />
with this Government" he said in his departing speech, " with the Labor<br />
Government, have been entirely proper, but one has to be an insider<br />
to know that this was not always so', this is a reference of course to<br />
Howard when he was Treasurer. So, after Mr Howard's disgraceful<br />
performance in the House of Representatives, being party to the<br />
asking of a question he knew was intended to mislead the House of<br />
Representatives by Mr McLachlan...<br />
RM: About Hindmarsh?<br />
PM: He admitted on John Laws' program last week that he was at the<br />
tactics meeting that he sat down with Ian McLachlan, that he agreed<br />
that Ian McLachlan should ask a question which had no truth in it, that<br />
had no integrity to it, which said that the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs,<br />
Robert Tickner, had photocopied and disseminated information that<br />
was the charge in the question when in fact, they both knew it was<br />
them. I mean, if I did a thing like that Ranald, you would never hear<br />
the end of it it would be on for weeks, months, months and months.<br />
Here is John Howard caught red-handed caught red-handed at a<br />
sort of smart little tactics meeting throwing a question around which<br />
had not a shred of integrity to it, and of course, now he wants to forget<br />
that it happened McLachlan has resigned. And the question we say<br />
is " if McLachlan resigned because he asked a question he knew to be<br />
misleading in the House of Representatives, why too shouldn't John<br />
Howard do the same, given the fact that he authorised the question to<br />
be asked?".<br />
RM: There is a certain irony, isn't there, John Howard is down here in<br />
Melbourne for most of this week and you have not exactly played any<br />
significant role, I would have thought, in the NSW elections both of<br />
you come from NSW, both of you come from Sydney why have you<br />
not actually weighed into the state election up there?<br />
PM: I was on the John Laws program this morning, which is basically a<br />
NSW based radio program, and I discussed a number of issues in<br />
NSW. Could I just say the problem with NSW is that the Government<br />
here is dead on its feet we are having a sort of pretend election, that </p>
<p>once we can sort through the election, the thing will come back to life.<br />
I mean there is more Ministers fallen out of this Government.. . you<br />
know there is this question about the film studio. In the Cultural<br />
Statement, I got Rupert Murdoch to agree to do up to three feature<br />
films in Australia, and he wanted to do them in Sydney. John Fahey<br />
can't even get the studio built he can't even give him the space to get<br />
the studio built to start off an international feature film industry through<br />
Fox in Australia.<br />
RM: Might it come down here to Melbourne, as Jeff Kennett said?<br />
PM: Jeffrey is out there touting for business I know he has got the Grand<br />
Prix, and he's got Lloyd Webber. I1 mean, you wonder these days<br />
whether State Government is show business or what it is.<br />
RM: Looking at the NSW election it is interesting, surely, if you say that<br />
the budget, sorry the Government is dead on its feet, that on the<br />
opinion polls, they look as if at least they are slightly ahead, and may<br />
have a sporting chance of remaining in power do you think they will?<br />
PM: Last time the polls showed the same, and Bob Carr came within a seat<br />
or so of winning, and I think he has got a better opportunity on this<br />
occasion. But there is that fellow Pickard, the former Solicitor-General,<br />
there was Packard, there is Terry Griffiths there is that many<br />
Ministers and MP's Smiles who have fallen out of that Government.<br />
It is staggering along nothing happens in NSW, I can assure you.<br />
The only thing that happens are basically Government projects there<br />
is no substantial private projects occurring there, and it is also as if we<br />
are saying " ooooh, let's not talk about that let's see what they can do<br />
later". Well, what they will do is they will fall in a heap, I think. This is<br />
a Government which is, basically, the quicker it gets put down, the<br />
better.<br />
RM: All right. You are talking about a tired State Government what about<br />
Federal Government you have been in power for 12 years I know<br />
you have only been Prime Minister for a few of those, but as a<br />
Government, would you say that how would you reject a suggestion<br />
that you have had a long time in power, and perhaps you are tired as a<br />
Federal Government?<br />
PM: Have a look at the last three weeks look at us, look at the Coalition.<br />
The week I was away, John Howard's antics his principal trick was<br />
throwing dishonest questions in the House of Representatives. The<br />
week before that when I was there, he was asking me about<br />
supposedly dishonest how-to-vote tickets proposed by the Labor Party<br />
in the local Canberra election, which was not dishonest at all. In the<br />
same period, we have had in that same week I had him cave in and<br />
pass the Aboriginal Land Fund Bill a social and cultural milestone in<br />
Australia. Last week, we had 7 0 the High Court supporting the<br />
Native Title Legislation, also the week before that we had 91,000 job </p>
<p>growth for the month. So, if you are looking at substance and quality<br />
and change the thing about Howard is you can't get him into the stalls<br />
on any major issue until the field has jumped, Ranald, and when he is<br />
in there, he goes in backwards.<br />
RM: As an alternative Prime Minister, you reckon you have got his<br />
measure, do you?<br />
PM: The thing is, look, the key-point about Howard is that he is no different<br />
than he was in the 1980s, and it won't be me who says it it will come<br />
out of his own mouth. You could see that in the House of<br />
Representatives two weeks ago when he did this stunt with<br />
McLachlan, you could see it the previous week when he was trying the<br />
stuff on me. There is no policy substance all of the changes.... I can<br />
walk around Europe with the German Chancellor regarding Australia<br />
as one of the countries which has really made great changes in the<br />
last decade, we can walk into APEC which we have had a large part<br />
in creating and have the same view of ourselves right throughout<br />
South-East Asia, we have got an international standing that we have<br />
never had, we have got 170 countries at CeBIT the technology fair in<br />
Germany -we have got great social and identity changes in Australia<br />
and this has come from the Labor Government, and it is still<br />
happening. What has come from Howard think of one national<br />
initiative you associate with John Howard just one.<br />
RM: All right. I'll have to leave it on that note, but many thanks for talking to<br />
me.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
RM: Thank you Paul Keating, Prime Minister of Australia.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
