<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6282</transcript-id>
    <title>FROM THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, MR LIONEL BOWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006282.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FFROM TH'II ACTING YPPIME MINISTER, MR LIONEL BOWEN<br />
WEDNESD) AY,_ 23RD NOVEMBER 1983 FOR MEDIA<br />
The. Tasmanian Premier, Mr Gray -has created a false impression<br />
ov ; er the fundincG of $ 5.3 millio.-n w,. orth of imrproVEments in the<br />
South-West and West Coast of the Statc-.<br />
Mr Gray, through the Tasmanian news media, has suggested that<br />
thre State Government is irijec,-.. nJ theo fu:. 1. i into~ the , rea.<br />
In fact, the $ 5.3 million allccatcd in the Federal Budqet<br />
1! Ldn-r the interim financial cremtwihsar.<br />
wrote to the Premi. er on Tueosday, ta: ~ k iv. i1-f inal<br />
appuroval for the project-, suhL.ñ.: t mec for fundinrg undOer [. m1(<br />
acrreemen t by the Tasm-ianiJan Government.<br />
The $ 1.7 million for the Queens town sewutrage upgradinn3 ad<br />
been approved in theo interim financial pack. q.. e but thec<br />
Commonwealth had agreed to increa-. th-e ~ i~ nto 2 million<br />
, A~ tr thec State had submittc-0 revi,-sed ost. ma, t .<br />
The $ 3.2 million. for tourist facilities, as p-irt of S, 5 million<br />
so approved under the interir . nni4ap. eft<br />
The people of Tasmania should be aware that he $ 5.3 million is<br />
not extra money, but funds already approved.<br />
The only new development Is thaT_ specific projects for which<br />
ii: would be used, have now been agreed upon.<br />
1I: should be made clear tha'-the $ 5.3 million Commonwealth<br />
iniLiated, and the projects Commonwealth fiinded.<br />
The State Government is rcq' ir(; d oni. tr, sugcrest projcC S ' or<br />
approval.<br />
A copy of the letter which was srnt-to Mlr Gray' on~ Tues.-ay is<br />
attached. </p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINI õ TER.<br />
TIhc flhn Rlin~<br />
HOBiART TVAS 7000<br />
Mdear Promier<br />
I refer to your lettVers 1133 O-tober and 10 November inj<br />
which you out fcor-wiird1, in rjoncto the Commonweal1th'is<br />
I-feC f 2 il ion in 98 1anBI $ S3m million in 1984/ 85,<br />
a number of propo ; als ior thc, i'eelopm,:' it of tourist<br />
facik tries in the South We: Jt.<br />
In considerinite., p: oposals he Commonwealth has taken<br />
a broad vi -' tho developme. n t I. requirements of the<br />
West Coast area agjains: t hu background of the expected<br />
increase in tourist. interest following the accession of<br />
a si~ gnificant area~ to Lhe. World Heritage List. On this<br />
basis, and SUbje-c. Lo) t ti follouwing cxceptions and<br />
observations, we have decided to agree to your proposals.<br />
First, we note that two of the projects put forward in<br />
your second letter lie within the World Heritage Area.<br />
These are the Cynthia Bay CL.: ke St Clair) jetty and boat<br />
ramp, and Lhe Cradle Mountain power scheme. In view of<br />
the Commonwealth's rosoonsioililties relating to protection<br />
of the Area it will be necessary, before considering these..,<br />
projects further, to have more detailed informnation on them<br />
in order that their impact on thio natural environment cdan<br />
be assessed. I Suggest that to this end the Minister for<br />
Home Affairs and Environment, the Hon. Barry Cohen, be.<br />
in touch with his Tasmanian counterpart, the Hon. Geoff<br />
Pra rsallI.<br />
In relation to Strahan port development we take it t~<br />
the assistance to bc provided will be additiirhal -4. o ths'<br />
which your Government has alreadly put n train. I refer<br />
iere to the 5 year developmental plan for tbe-State<br />
fishing industry, announced in t~ e Siatn idudgett, whichl,<br />
included $ 108,000 ; n 1983/ 84 for a port: plan,. new sltpW4l<br />
: radle, and amnnitien '.-Aock at Strafian. On th~ e Strahg1o~<br />
water supply csrewtr;-, ge proposal We. propose ' to'' opernte bt'<br />
the baisis of the-. lo~ wer I igure of $-980, 000. / 2 </p>
<p>I' I<br />
I ' I<br />
I If<br />
I; I urn now to your letter of 22 September Poncer~~ g-<br />
Queenstown sewerage, project in whicn you reg red tQo<br />
increase in estimated costs from hqiS1 .7mmi If .4nof~<br />
by the Commonwealth to some rrillion, an4 ' stges141<br />
that 25 man years of employment . woi~ d be morq. appropk<br />
t,'-an the 30 ' man years envisaged ir," thq Cornmoqy$ palthf.<br />
proposal. While the comments I h4X4 made.. abpyQ , are J:<br />
to hisproject also, we are preppr d to cptteXy.<br />
in the light, of the particular circum~ st. ancog. of this-R.<br />
and on the basiis that they aire,. to': b trcat. eid's f inal -r<br />
entimates. ./ 3 t<br />
I have noted your Comments abour the preliminary'. atVX,,,<br />
of the proposals anti the difficulties of determifin. g. r* i'<br />
amount of employment Lhit . il1 be created. WhilejiI)&amp;,<br />
understand this di f ficuity, I tl~ irk i t is irnportant*. t . iq<br />
recognise that the Commonweail thIs principal objective, li<br />
providing financial ' issistalc Lindel the Interimh Finaflc. al<br />
Aqicement for tourism . rnd othtur nhort--. erm projects s<br />
to alleviate employment disrupt.) on arising from termination<br />
of the GordorI-helow-Frarkl in project. In this regard'<br />
your Government has botn ofiored wide .1iscretion in the<br />
selection of tourism projects to be funded under the<br />
Agreement, subject only to satisfying the overall employment<br />
target of 110 inan-yeair.<br />
in accepting your initial toui-; t pro) j c t proposals, the<br />
Commonwealth has boon motivated by a desire to get action<br />
in hand to improve the tourist potential of the South West<br />
as quickly as poss; ible. To this end we are thus agreeing<br />
to certain pro. posals for example, the acquisition of the<br />
Imperial Hlotel at Queonstown which in themselves will<br />
have no or little dire-ct employment implications.<br />
While. some degree of flex Ibility is appropriate in<br />
_ valuating the employment-creating potential of individual<br />
? rojects, I believe that, having regard to the Commonwealth<br />
overall obje-ctives and resnonsibilitie;,' it would not be<br />
appropriate to vary the employment target of 110 man ypa rs<br />
which we envisaged in proposing this two-year program.-, To<br />
,: he extent that some of the a* cvo projects may. fall short.<br />
of constitut'ing jobs a-t the rroquired rate, other projec ts:<br />
the $ 5 million prograro would have to make up the<br />
bal ance.<br />
might also remark that some o: the projects you r-i,-r; C<br />
nominated would, under normal circumstances, be part'~<br />
funded by way of user charge:-of somne form or' ar'othe4<br />
This would be appropri_: ite whorctiieaib euesO~<br />
most of theibenefit of the servi'ces or fclte~ r<br />
These are essential ly management de~ cisions for. Your'~<br />
Covernment ut it would seem to be. in your StateA<br />
test interest to seek appropriate cost recovery if. f4%<br />
4-o other reason than to extend more, widely the benef4ji<br />
to be derivedc from the available f iinds; </p>
<p>The tourism pro) e,* cts and tie Queenstown sewerage project<br />
wili be funded from the: Commonwealth appropriation<br />
which providus for payments to Tasmania in 1983-84 in<br />
relation to thu termination of the Gordon River Power<br />
Development stage IT. Accordingly, it will be necessary<br />
to authoris Lth( expenditure by adding further schedules<br />
to the Interim [ inaricil Agreement and making appropriate<br />
anmertdments to Clnusc 4 of the Agreement. Drafts of the<br />
nec, ssary amendments will be forwarded in the near future.<br />
I look forward to your acceptance of the proposals I have<br />
put in this letter and to the early commencement of the<br />
projects. I propose that officers of our respective Governments<br />
discuss detailed arrangements and, where Ministerial<br />
involvement is dc-sir: ble, that these be between Mr Cohen<br />
and Mr Brown for ' he( Commonwealth and Mr Pearsall.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
LIONEL 8OWEN<br />
Lionel Bowen<br />
' Ily. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
