<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10136</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO 6PR - WITH HOWARD SATTLER</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010136.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from ". LZA<br />
16 October 1996 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
RADIO 6PR WITH HOWARD SATTLER<br />
E O E<br />
SATrLER: Well, how are your nightmares going?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
fifteenth year on radio.<br />
SATrLER: To me? Yes.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Congratulations.<br />
-SATTLER: Thank you for that, you've been around for all of that time in one way or another.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, I have and I'll be around for quite a while to come. I hope we share many more<br />
interviews like this in the years ahead.<br />
SATTLER:<br />
Well, I hope you say that at the end of the interview for your sake at least. But the<br />
code says tell me if I'm wrong I quote one part of it " Ministers are required to<br />
16/ 18/ 96 15: 13 Pg: </p>
<p>Fax from z<br />
divest themselves of all shares and similar interests in any company or business<br />
involved in the area of their portfolio responsibilities". Is that was it says?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes it does.<br />
SATTLER: Given that the industry Minister Moore extended a computer bounty payment scheme<br />
to a company in which the company he holds shares has an 18.2% interest, isn't that a<br />
direct breach of the rules?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No it's not.<br />
SATTLER: Tell me how it isn't.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, he holds shares in an investment company which in turn holds a minority interest<br />
in a large number of companies.<br />
SATTLER:<br />
But doesn't his investment company stand to gain if he makes a decision like that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The rules require divestiture of shareholdings held in companies which are involved<br />
themselves and the company in which he holds shares is not involved in the computer<br />
industry. SATTLER:<br />
It's just investing in it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it's not just investing in it, it is investing in a whole range of companies. It is an<br />
investment company. It is literally no different from somebody who's got a<br />
superannuation policy with the AMP and the AMP has heavy investments in mnines and<br />
buildings and all sorts of economic activities. if you required every person who held a<br />
superannuation policy with the AMP to divest that policy because some decision they<br />
take might affec the mining company which the AMP in turn has an interest... I mean,<br />
there'd be no end to it and you would end up with a situation where people couldn't 2 I<br />
4LLUiC4 JO* C h~ JJ Ji4, l eU 7oc </p>
<p>Fax fromv 16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 3<br />
own anything if they were going to be Ministers of the Crown. What is required by the<br />
guidelines is a divestiture where you have a direct interest by way of a shareholding or<br />
other interest in a company that is directly involved in the area of the Minister's<br />
activity. Now if you apply that guideline to John Moore, the answer is no.<br />
SATTLER: Okay, well let's apply the guideline to the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for<br />
Trade, Tim Fischer. Now did you know that he still held shares in a number of<br />
resource companies while he was a Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, they were declared. You knew too. Everybody knew because he put them on the<br />
public register. But are you saying that, I mean, the logic of that is that the Minister<br />
for Trade can't hold any shares at all because any company listed on the Australian<br />
Stock Exchange is potentially involved in trade. They might be selling something<br />
overseas or they might be selling something in competition to imports from abroad...<br />
SATTLER: Okay but you made the rules.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I know I made the rules, and I'm telling you what they mean. I mean, what is<br />
happening with this issue, now I acknowledge that there were breaches of the rules by<br />
both Brian Gibson and Jim Short. They didn't set out to deceive. They weren't<br />
dishonest, they didn't gain anything.<br />
SATTLER: No, that's not the point is it?<br />
PRIE MINISTER:<br />
Well, I think in terms ofjudging their behaviour it's important. But look, they went<br />
because they were in technical breach of the rules.<br />
SAITLER: Okay, now Tim Fischer apparently still held shares in BlIP when he was in Venezuela<br />
pushing trade with that country on behalf of Australian companies like BHP. Does<br />
that breach the rules?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I mean, what do you expect a trade minister to do, go overseas and dump on B3HP... 3T-. </p>
<p>Fax from 16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 4<br />
SATTLER:<br />
No, far from it, but I'm wondering whether or not he should still retain the shares<br />
under the rules, your rules.<br />
PRIME MNISTER:<br />
Hang on, I mean you either believe that people should own nothing...<br />
SA [ TLER:<br />
Like you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that's right, I mean I don't own anything except my house and a small, some<br />
money in the bank. But I'm not saying that's what should suit everybody. When I<br />
became a Minister twenty years ago I decided not to have any shares because I<br />
couldn't be bothered having the political argumient that was going to arise.<br />
SATILER: Well maybe your colleagues should have thought the same.<br />
PRIM4E NIGSTER:<br />
Yes, but it's a little bit different. If you've owned assets for twenty years and you<br />
suddenly become a minister, it's a bit unreasonably to say you just throw those assets<br />
away. I mean, we've just got to apply a little bit of commonsense to this.<br />
SATTLER: Well maybe so, but Tim Fischer on a Sydney radio station this morning apparently has<br />
said that guidelines were drawn up in haste and must be reviewed. Do you agree with<br />
him? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I didn't hear what he said and I've long since learned in this business...<br />
SATTLER: Well he did say that, I can assure you. All right, I'll ask you, do you believe the<br />
guidelines were drawn up in haste and ought to be reviewed?<br />
PRICME MINISTER:<br />
The guidelines, in fact, consolidate what has been the practice of governments in this<br />
country over the last twenty years. The fact that they were brought together under one </p>
<p>Fax from 16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg:<br />
cover is something that's occurred under my Government. But these guidelines are<br />
not new, they are guidelines that were meant, so I'm told, to apply to the former<br />
government. I mean, the former Finance Minister, Mr Walsh, held shares in<br />
Wesfarmers for example, whilst he was Finance Minister. Can I say I didn't criticise<br />
that then and I don't criticise it now.<br />
SATFLER:<br />
But did he make any decisions at the time that would have benefited Wesfarmers?<br />
PREIE M[ NISTER:<br />
I don't know. Can I say, I'm not suggesting he did. I actually don't think he was in<br />
any way dishonest.<br />
SATrLER: You are, quite clearly, going to stand by John Moore until you and he are both<br />
dragged kicking and screaming from the Chamber, is that right?<br />
PRIME MINISTER.-<br />
Well, I don't think anybody will be dragged kicking and screaming from the chamber.<br />
Look, my position is very simply this, that John Moore has not breached the<br />
guidelines... SATTLER: Has Tim Fischer breached the guidelines?<br />
PRIME MINISTER;<br />
I don't believe Tim Fischer has breached the guidelines. Nobody has pointed to any<br />
conflict of interest in which Tim Fischer has been involved. If it is being argued that<br />
the Minister far Trade can't hold shares in BHP because BHP sells things overseas,<br />
then what you're really saying is that the Minister for Trade can't own shares in<br />
anything... SATTLER:<br />
Prime Minister, I'm not saying it, the rules seems to be saying it.<br />
PRIME MIlNISTER:<br />
No, no, the rules don't say that because the rules say you are allowed, that ministers<br />
are not precluded from having investments on the stock market. </p>
<p>Fax from SATTLER:<br />
All right. What about John Fahey, the Finance Minister, who's allegedly failed to<br />
declare some shareholdings, will you be asking him about that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I have already obtained a letter which has been released to the media which fully<br />
explains that the two shareholdings in which he had no beneficial interest related to a<br />
company in which he was involved in 16 years ago in his legal practice and another<br />
service company associated with his legal practice. And in both cases he signed<br />
transfers of the shares years ago and in both cases the person who took the transfer of<br />
the shares failed to attend to the registration.<br />
STTLER: So he's an innocent victim, is that what you're saying?<br />
PRIE MINISTER:<br />
Well, he's just done nothing wrong and he's not breached the guidelines. I mean, how<br />
can you declare something that you don't believe you own? Answer me that. And that<br />
is Fahey's case. Fahey signed share transfers years ago and naturally when filling out<br />
his form if you've signed a transfer of something and you're asked do you still own it,<br />
you're naturally not going to say ' yes I do' when you've signed a transfer and it's the<br />
responsibility of somebody who receives a transfer of shares to register it.<br />
SAITER: Okay, do you expect any more resignations? Is that it on this issue as far as you're<br />
concerned? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Sorry, I'm going to go back to Fahey because that bloke's name has just been<br />
gratuitously dragged into all of this. He's done nothing wrong. And this just shows<br />
how easy it is to smear people. I mean, John Fahey signed away the ownership of two<br />
shares in which he didn't have a beneficial interest and he'd held them years ago, and<br />
because the people who took the transfer of those shares were negligent in not having<br />
them registered, his name is now being unfairly dragged into this. He told the<br />
journalist of the Financial Review about this last night and the journalist conveniently<br />
didn't bother to print his explanation...<br />
SATTLER: Well, I can't account for them... 16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 6 </p>
<p>Fax from 16/ 18/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 7<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, well I'm not going to have the reputation of my Ministers slandered on any<br />
programme, anywhere in Australia. Look, two men have gone because they were in<br />
technical breach of the guidelines, not because they have done anything dishonest and<br />
now an attempt is being made to sort of smear the whole of my government.<br />
SAflLER:<br />
Well, the Opposition, for the first time since you came into office, is on a roll this<br />
week, you know that.<br />
PIM MINISTER:<br />
Look, the Opposition is having a go. I accept Oppositions do that. I was in<br />
opposition, I used to have a go. I'm not complaining about the fact that the<br />
Opposition is having a go at me. I expect Beazley to have a go at me when he gets on<br />
after me. I accept all ofthat. I don't criticise him for it, that is his job. Butmnyjob is<br />
to defend my colleagues, which I will, against unfair criticism.<br />
SArFLER: All right, but Prime Minister these rules, as they were, showed that your government<br />
was going to be totally open and accountable, and you required very strict guidelines<br />
of your ministers that they and I repeat again, they had to divest themselves of all<br />
shares and similar interest in any company or business involved in their area of<br />
portfolio responsibilities. People looked at that and said, gee, that is open and<br />
accountable government. Now, you're proposing, I think, to dilute those guidelines,<br />
aire you?<br />
PRIME WMIiSTER:<br />
No, I haven't made any decision about dilution yet. What I'm saying is those<br />
guidelines continue to apply. I am looking at whether there is any practical advantage<br />
in developing a system of blind trusts.<br />
SAflLER:<br />
Like the President of the United States is obliged to do.<br />
PRI1ME MINISTER:<br />
If the rules that now operate in Australia had been applied strictly, President Kennedy<br />
could never have been in the Whitehouse and Nelson Rockafeller could never have<br />
been Vice President of the United...<br />
SAflLER: But they're your rules. 7<br />
I. </p>
<p>Fax from : 16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 8<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I understand that. But is there any law of politics that says that if the practical<br />
experience of something suggests it might be improved by change, you don't look at<br />
that change?<br />
SATTLER: No, but do you think now, in retrospect looking at what's happened this week, the<br />
rules are silly and ridiculous?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I don't regard them as silly and ridiculous at all. I think they have worked in<br />
relation to Brian Gibson and Jim Short. They've resulted in two people who haven't<br />
been guilty of any wrong doing, they've been guilty of careless.. if Jim Short had read<br />
the rules he would have got rid of those ANZ Bank shares. I mean, let's not kid<br />
ourselves. If Jim Short had read what was in the guidelines he would never have held<br />
those shares...<br />
SATTLER: So he was naive?<br />
PRIME MINITER:<br />
Well, he was careless in not reading it and he's paid a very high price. Now, that's<br />
accountability isn't it? You're talking to me about accountability..,<br />
SA TMEM<br />
Indeed, about all your Ministers being accountable.<br />
PIM MINISTER:<br />
Exactly. Well Ros Kelly had to be pushed out after months and months of evidence of<br />
her deliberately providing political largesse to her fiends. Carmen Lawrence stayed<br />
there to the bitter end despite the finding of a Royal Commission.<br />
SATTLER: And look how you savaged them.<br />
PRME NMISTER:<br />
Exactly, and I did and I make no apology for having don~ e that and I'm not<br />
complaining about the Opposition attacking me over this issue, they're perfectly<br />
entitled... </p>
<p>16/ 10/ 96 15: 13 Pg: 9<br />
Fax from SA[ TLER:<br />
Prime Minister, no more ministers will go, is that right on this issue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
What I'm say to you is, on the information that has been provided to me none of the<br />
other ministers under attack are in breach of the guidelines.<br />
SATTLER: All right, we will have to leave it there. I do appreciate your time today.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Same to you and happy fifteenth birthday. But I will come back and on many<br />
occasions. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
