<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5683</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO TEH SOUTH AUSTRALIAN STATE COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005683.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1, AUS~~ L L.<br />
PRIME MENISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SATUiRDAY, 7 NOVEMBER 3.981<br />
ADDRESS TO THE SOUTH AUSTRALIAN STATE COUNCIL<br />
I want to talk to you today about the Australia that we know<br />
and love, about our aims for the advancement and development<br />
' of this country, about the kind of lead that Australia needs<br />
and that only the Liberal Party can provide.<br />
I want to'address these themes because I believe that<br />
Australians need a clear perspective of where we are going as<br />
a society, and an equally clear view of th vast difference<br />
between the Liberal vision of the future and the Labor alternative.<br />
We must not overlook or let anyone forget that Labor is the<br />
Party of republican socialism, for socialism and republicanism<br />
were both explicitly espoused by the Labor Party at its<br />
biennial Federal Council Meeting this year. So Labor is the<br />
Party Which would cut us off from our history and our heritage<br />
as well as from our hopes and aspirations because Australians<br />
have alw.. ays abhorred socialism and they will resist socialism<br />
whether Labor tries to introduce it openly or by stealth.<br />
The Liberal appro ach is vastly different for it favours the<br />
way of freedom, it seeks to build up our achievements and make<br />
the most of our history. Liberalism takes the view that people<br />
should have the incentive to succeed in achieving goals which<br />
they set for themselves and which they seek to pursue on their<br />
onw account.<br />
Let me say something first about the fruits of the Liberal<br />
approach in terms of the kind of society we have in Australia,<br />
because it is easy for us to overlook how far we have come in<br />
the last few years, and easy to under-rate the real quality<br />
and significance of the Australian achievement in world terms.<br />
Australia in the 1980' s is one o[ the most \ uibrant and vital<br />
countries in the world in a cultural sense, one of the most<br />
harmonious, free and stable countries in a political sense.<br />
It is one of the best managed and luckiest countries in an<br />
economic sense. It is one of the most concerned and energetic<br />
countries in humanitarian terms, one of the most realistic,<br />
responsible and farsighted countries in the part it plays<br />
in intern at-ional affairs, and it is one of the most self-confident<br />
and friendly countries in term,-of the w-ay in which other<br />
people vie. a us. / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
These are not just my perceptions of Australia in 1981. They<br />
represent . the considered views, expressed in unambiguous terms,<br />
of visitor after visitor, especially during the rec&amp; bnt Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Meeting. I said at the time of that<br />
Meeting that: the world spotlight would b * e turned on Australia<br />
and there can be little doubt that the world was impressed.<br />
And I believe that what impressed people above all was the way<br />
of life that we have built up in this country.<br />
Let me mention some of the comments that our visitors volunteerE~ d<br />
about Australia. * Pierre Trudeau spoke'oh Australia as<br />
" self-possessed and confident about the future believing~<br />
in the future of mankind.".. He also said that " with its<br />
tremendous economic potential, with its exc iting technological<br />
and natural resources, with its intense and vibrant culture,<br />
Australia seems to be very much part of the definition and<br />
formulation of the twentieth century as it's meant to be".<br />
' Robert Mugabe spoke of " the positive and tireless role<br />
Australians have played in world affairs and the outward<br />
policy which Australia has shown consistently, especially towards<br />
the third'world"..<br />
Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia said that before he came to know the<br />
present Australian Government, he " personally did not know<br />
what Australia was, except as a country where there was<br />
indifference to suffering people of the rest Of the world", and<br />
he went on to say that we had brought the countries of the<br />
Comxnonwealth to " an Australia with which we are very proud to<br />
be associated".<br />
Sir Julius Chan spoke warmly of the " fabled Australian<br />
hospitality".<br />
And Sir Dennis Hamilton, a British member of thle Commonwealth<br />
Press Union, said that the thing hie had been struck by, going<br />
round Australia, was " the sense of self-confidence of people<br />
at every possible level, self-confidence in themselves that<br />
they pan tackle any of the immense problems remaining here,<br />
and if more problems come in the world they will help with<br />
those too". And he continued that Australian self-confidence<br />
" is a bit of a refresher and encouragement for some of us who<br />
have come from some of the old countries" 1<br />
Comments like these are representative and typical of. what<br />
people were saying, and there are endless tZrue stories about<br />
the impression that Australian friendliness and kindness made<br />
on our visitors. One Namibian journalist ., as so moved when<br />
a stranger came across to him during dinner and gave him a bottle<br />
of Australian wine that he said h-e would take the wine back<br />
home as a symbolic gift from all Australians to his own people.<br />
Hundreds of the visitors received similar generosity from<br />
friendly Australians, and as a result, hund: reds of people went<br />
back to thcoir own* councries ambassadors f. or Australia. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
We have known for years that Australia is the best country in<br />
the world arid the superiority of the Australian way of life<br />
is even more obvious when you visit most overseas countries<br />
today. * Neither is there anything new about the friendliness<br />
and generosity of Australians. But in terms of the political<br />
history of the 1970' s there is something very satisfying and<br />
significant about the comments on our self-confidence, our<br />
vitality and ou. vr good management, because in 1975, under the<br />
Labor Government, such perceptions of Australian society would<br />
have been utterly impossible.<br />
And while I am on the subject of the dynamism of Australia<br />
today, I want to lay the ghost of: a view which has had currency<br />
with-some people because it ' is sometimes thought ' that ' the<br />
vitality and vibrancy of Australian society and cultur6 as we'<br />
now know it, which contrasts so sharply with the image of a<br />
less exciting society in earlier decades, might have received<br />
its impetus from the Whitlam Government. in fact, the trendy<br />
cultural blossoming which took place in the early seventies<br />
had turned completely sour by 1975 because we all know what a<br />
sense of hopelessness and despondency had come to grip the<br />
whole of Australia by that year.<br />
.1975 was in fact the only year since 1946 when more people left<br />
Australia than came in and what an indictmarit it is of the effects of<br />
Labor policies that withnin three years of , Labor coming to office,<br />
more people were leaving this country than were entering it.<br />
The vitality which we see in Austral~ ian society and culture today<br />
is vastly different in its nature an~ d its inspiration. It is<br />
maore diverse in its expression, more open to a variety of influe nces,<br />
more alive to all the currents which are flowing through AusCra2. ian<br />
life. There is a related point to make about the quality of<br />
Australian life in the eighties by contrast with the early<br />
seventies because while we live in times of great change, most<br />
Australians now feel more secure and confident than a few years<br />
ago about our basic values of freedom, initiative, diversity and<br />
responsibility. The very real doubts of earlier years, and the<br />
uncertainty which gripped the minds of many people about whether<br />
these'values could be sustained have now largely disappeared.<br />
The Value of diversity is being more widely experienced with<br />
every new expression of the multicultural character of our<br />
society, and more widely welcomed as people recognise that<br />
the apparent dullness of Australian society in earlier times<br />
was largely a product of sameness. While people now have a<br />
far better understanding of the contributioh that a diversity<br />
of lifestyles makes to a free and open society there is also,-.,.<br />
I believe, a deeper appreciation of the basic institutions of<br />
Australian society, especially the falmily and a greater<br />
awareness that these institutions are important to the achievement<br />
of progress as well as stability. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
This brings me to the matter of our aims for -the advancement<br />
and development of Australia. In economic terms, Liberal<br />
Governments consistently seek to esta.-blish-the conditions for<br />
expanding employment and increasingT prosperity for the whole<br />
community. Without economic growth, these objectives are<br />
impossible to achieve, and economic growth is fundamentally<br />
dependent on the private sector having the room and the<br />
incentive to expand. Australia has cause to be proud of its<br />
economic achievements in recent years. Nearly 300,000 new<br />
private sector jobs were created in the two years to September.<br />
The unemployment rate throughout this year, on a month by<br />
month basis, has been the lowest for four years. And there is<br />
no doubt whatever that the unempl~ oyment position would be a<br />
great deal better than it is except for the needless'-d6gre~ e of<br />
industrial unrest which has occurred and the absurd wage claims<br />
that are being made.<br />
~ Let me add that I am encouraged by the recent improvement in<br />
the employment position in this state because the turnaround<br />
to a positive increase in employment of over 14,000 in the<br />
year to September puts a far better light on a. situation that<br />
has obviously been a matter of great concern.<br />
I have no doubt that a great deal of the credit for what is now<br />
happening is due to the policies of the present State<br />
Government under the leadership of the Premier, David Tonkin.<br />
It is two years since David Tonkin turned the tables on<br />
Labor in this State. And it is a matter not only for congratulation<br />
but for heartfelt satisfaction that the South Australian<br />
Liberal Government is getting the runs on the board in this<br />
area and that a number of other developments are getting under<br />
way in this State because it often takes years for sound policie-: s<br />
to bear fruit because of the long lead times that are involved.<br />
We would be deluding ourselves in Australia if we thought we<br />
could remain unaffected by the world economic situation, but<br />
we have established an underlying strength in the Australian<br />
economy as evidenced by a number of important indicators.<br />
Inflation is continuing below the OECD average, despite the<br />
greater difficulties which we have in controlling it in a<br />
situation in which our economy is growing while others are<br />
static or even shrinking.<br />
Confidence in the Australian economy is obvious in the widesprea2d<br />
investment in the mining and manufacturing industries that is<br />
now taking place. The latest figures show that retail sales<br />
were up by almost 14% in the year to September and the latestsurvey<br />
indicates that the expectations for private investment<br />
in 1981-82 are 32% higher than at the same time last year.<br />
It is also worth underlining the benefits which the whole<br />
community received from the 4% growth which was achieved last<br />
year in the non--farmsector of the econiomy be--c: ause this crrowth was<br />
translated into a corresponding increase in average weekly earnings<br />
which was reflected, in an aggregate increase in real disposable<br />
household income of $ 2.7 billion after tax. I want to say two<br />
things about this increase. One is that our policies are aimed<br />
precisely at making possible such improvements in thle standards<br />
of living of Australia's families.<br />
I </p>
<p>Let me add to this a general comment about people's attitudes<br />
to Budgets because while the living standards of some people<br />
in the community need to be directly protected through the<br />
BudgetI-, most Australians should be looking to a healthy<br />
economy for real improvements in their living standards.<br />
People should be looking to Budgets as instruments in creating<br />
the conditions in which they will be able to make real<br />
gains through their own activities and as a result of doing things<br />
f or themselves and everyone needs to be aware that Budget<br />
handouts can never match the real gains and increases in living<br />
standards that come from a healthy economy.<br />
The second point to make about last year's $ 2.7 billion increase<br />
in the after-tax real disposable incomes of Australian families<br />
is that increases in incomes must reflect real improvements ini<br />
productivity, therwise they will be ' short-lived and will<br />
undermine the capacity of the economy to grow in the future..<br />
I don't need to say to Liberals that economic success of the<br />
' kind Australia has achieved does not come about by chance.<br />
Good economic management is a discipline which calls for<br />
deliberate and debUhir~ ed policies. And by the same token,<br />
sustained' economic success and prosperity will continue to<br />
depend upon constant attention by the Government to economnic<br />
management. Obviously no Government policy' can be a substitute<br />
for the drive of individual initiative and private enterprise.<br />
But through our sound and responsible economic policy Australia<br />
has been in the forefront in attacking the basic causes of the<br />
economic downturn which plagues so much of the industrialized<br />
world, and our consistent approach has been based on the view<br />
that sustained prosperity requires lower inflation, less<br />
Government spending, less bureaucracy, lower taxes, and a private<br />
sector which can compete efficiently in world markets.<br />
We have stuck to the task with urgency* and purpose<br />
and a landmark in* this year's Budget is the virtual elimination<br />
of the deficit. If we had persist~ ed.: with deficit financing<br />
at the 1975 Hayden Budget rate of almost 5% of GDP this<br />
year's deficit would be almost $ 7.5 billion. We have always<br />
rejected deficit financing because it encourages<br />
expectations that are unreal, it forces our children to pay<br />
for yesterday's Government spending, and with the deficit virtually<br />
eliminated in this year's Budget, we will obviously have an<br />
enhanced potential for tax cuts.<br />
The Government has got rid of the massive Labor deficit partly<br />
by an honest approach to taxation and partly~ by rigorous<br />
restraint on its own spending. We have worked at the problem<br />
from both ends. But expenditure restraint has been the major--<br />
ingredient of our approach to making room for the private sector<br />
growth on which the future prosperity of Australia so fundamentally<br />
depends. In 1975-76, the Commonwealth Government spent over 30. cents of<br />
every dollar that Australia prodluced. in 1981-62, the Com., moneal. Jt]-<br />
Government will bie spend-irw 2 cents less than in 1975-76 of<br />
every dollar produced in Australia. This reduction, which -would<br />
be nearly 3 cents but the extra payday which comes at tw. elve-</p>
<p>6--<br />
year intervals, means that the Government will be spending<br />
billion less* than-i,* f the 1975-76 proportion had, in fact,<br />
continued. If Australia's economy can keep growing, and if at the same<br />
time real growth in Budget outlays can be held down, the<br />
consequences, especially in terms of an enhanced potential<br />
for income tax reductions, and of further reductions in the<br />
cents of each dollar spent by governments, must be obvious to<br />
everyone. The Government's steady progress in reducing<br />
its expenditure requirements has resulted from a resolute and<br />
consistent commitment to the cause of restraint and more limited<br />
Government. In economic management, we need consistency of approach and<br />
at the same time flexibility in the use of policy instruments.<br />
Our aim must be to maintain and build upon Australia's economic<br />
rachievements since the time of federation, while at the same<br />
time increasing our international competitiveness. By achieving..<br />
a proper balance, we can and we will increase prosperity and<br />
at the same time avoid hardship. We have stressed the need<br />
for a strang and growing economy because it is a pre-condition<br />
f or the achievement of so many of our widet aims and objectives,<br />
and fundamental in this wider connection is our determination<br />
to increase the range and availability of opportunities for<br />
all Australian~ s to build for themselves the way of life which<br />
they seek, in a secure and stable environment. / 7 </p>
<p>7<br />
Governments have a critical role in this process of increasing<br />
people's opportunities to build their own lives, not only<br />
through maintaining the conditions of freedom and prosperity<br />
for all, not only through creating the opportunities that<br />
people want and need but also through giving practical<br />
. encouragement and assistance to enable people to grasp the<br />
opportunities they have.<br />
Governments must not exaggerate their role in helping people to<br />
build their own lives because it is too easy to diminish the<br />
incentive for people to use their own initiative in building<br />
their own lives. But governments ca'n'give a very significant lead<br />
to the community through their commitment to the promotion of<br />
a way of life that is more than just a matter of dollars and<br />
cents and the kind of leadership that is required to achieve<br />
this while maintaining the stability, the security, and the<br />
prosperity which are essential components of it, can only<br />
be provided by the Liberal Party.<br />
The future of Australia depends fundamentally on leadership from<br />
the Liberal Party because basic liberal values are the values*<br />
of the vast majority of Australians, because our philosophy of<br />
concern and respect for the individual means that we are<br />
dedicated to the well-being of every member and every part<br />
of society, because our understanding of economic issues means<br />
that our party and our party alone will implement. the policies<br />
Australia needs, and. because Liberalism provided the most realistic<br />
view of the motivations of people and the workings of institutions.<br />
The Liberal Party is the only par-ty which will accept the<br />
obligation to govern in the interests of everyone, of every<br />
person and every family throughout Australia, not just the<br />
people who vote for us or give us their support, not just the<br />
people in ideological sympathy with us.<br />
By contrast, Labor can never submerge the inherently sectional<br />
and divisive interests within the Labor Party itself, so no<br />
Labor government will ever accept the discipline of governing<br />
in the interests of all. The Labor leadership always has to<br />
fall in behind those who control the votes in Caucus and in<br />
the party councils, and, as a result of this, the kind of twisting<br />
and turning which has been so evident in Labor's performance<br />
on the Sinai issue is never far below the surface in Labor's<br />
policy making.<br />
I want to look closely at this particular performance because<br />
it is symptomatic of Labor's incapacity o provide leadership<br />
and of its unfitness to government. Both Mr Hayden and Mr Hawke<br />
are united in their ' opposoition to Australian participatiorT-in<br />
the peace force but their reasons are totally different, equally<br />
wrong, and completely unbelievable.<br />
Mr Hayden says that the Begin Government is the greatest threat<br />
to world peace. But how could the Prime Minister of Israel<br />
possibly be the greatest threat to world peace. It is Pussian<br />
guns, and Russian divisions, which represent that, and it. is<br />
the Soviet Union, not Israel, which has continually obstructed<br />
the peace process in the Middle East. So Mr Hayden's position<br />
is an absurdity, although he did at least try to cast it in terms<br />
of globjl politics. / 8<br />
I </p>
<p>8<br />
Mvr Hawke, the great proponent of' Israel, did not seek to do<br />
that. HeI said he came to his view because of the o'pinion<br />
polls, u to suqggc: t that Mr Hawke would be driven aa<br />
from the actions needed to support the cause of peace by mere<br />
opinion polls is to take too little account of what Mr Hawke<br />
is all about. I can, to use his language, irrefutably prove<br />
it was not the opinion polls that made Nir Hawke' s mind up for<br />
him because at the time Mr Hawke seconded and supported the<br />
Caucus motion opposing participation in the peace force on<br />
27 May, no opinion polls had been taken by any of the major<br />
polling organisations not by Morgan, not by McNair-Anderson,<br />
not by not by the Age Poll.<br />
So Mr Hawke still needs to tell us the real reasons for his<br />
opposition to Australian participation. In fact, of course,<br />
we know the reason, because we know the tactics of the Socialist<br />
Left. The Left Wing of the Labor Party has always been adept<br />
at capturing and breaking their opponents by making them actively<br />
support resolutions they know to be wrong.<br />
Mr Hayden and Mr Hawke, in coming by their conflicting routes<br />
and from their conflicting starting points to. their common view<br />
in relation to Australian participation have surely been<br />
influenced by the interests of the Socialist Left, not by<br />
the interests of Australia.<br />
The case is in fact a classic example of a sectional interest<br />
interfering with the formulation of Labor policy, on a national<br />
issue. How can there be any faith, any conisistency.. in the<br />
foreign policy or leadership of Z party one of whose leaders says<br />
he believes that Mr Begin is the greatest threat to world peace,<br />
and another of whom says he believes that it is proper to fo] low-0<br />
the OPinlion polls in formulating policy on an issue where it: is<br />
plainly the responsibility of leadership to make a decision, to<br />
take a stand, and to carry that view to the people -to seek th. ir<br />
support.<br />
The Government has-acted responsibly, it has made the right<br />
decision for Australia, and its decision will be respected because<br />
of-the way it was made, and because i ts objective is the pursui~ t<br />
of peace. We must never forget that Labor can never provide<br />
the kind of firm and responsible leadership which Liberals rightly<br />
believe in and which the people of Australia rightly require<br />
of their government.<br />
The importance and difficulty of the tasks ahead of us must not<br />
be under-estimated. We live in uncertaini times, not only in<br />
terms of world peace and stability, but also in terms of maintaining<br />
-impetus and progress in Australia itself. But we are on the<br />
right track we shall not stray from that track arnd on that<br />
basis we can be optimistic about the future. Let ine just<br />
say in conclusion that I am delighted to have this opportunity to<br />
be at this State Council meeting and I look f orward to hearing<br />
some of your discussions on the motions before thig meeting anci<br />
to meeting a lot of Liberals through the daiy and at. the dinnerthis<br />
eveningj. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
