<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>692</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 21/1963 - ECONOMIC TALKS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000692_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6 3/ 0<br />
FOR PRESS: ECONOMIC TALKS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister_,_ h Rt Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
During the talks we had recently with representatives<br />
of business, a good many suggestions were put forward. as to ways<br />
in which expansion could be promoted, business confidence<br />
sustained and unemployment further reduced. A numaber of these<br />
suggestions related to matters on which the Government already<br />
had action in view.<br />
As to employment, for example, we had just ahead<br />
of us the Loan Council-meeting at which the works and housing<br />
programmes for this year were to be reviewed. Uhile we wished<br />
to have our discussions with the Premiers before deciding what<br />
the Commonwealth should offer to do, we had already made a very<br />
thorough study of the whole employment situation.<br />
In the event we found that the view put to us by<br />
industry representatives did not differ greatly from our own<br />
assessment nor from the account of things given by most of the<br />
Premiers. In the main, the opinion was that some increase in<br />
expenditure on works and housing could have useful results; it<br />
was generally emphasised, however, that any such expenditure<br />
ought to be channelled as far as possible into localities and<br />
occupations where, for various reasons, employment opportunities<br />
were not coming forward very readily,<br />
That, of course, had been the aim of two of the<br />
chief measures we took last year0 The grant of œ-10 million we<br />
made to the States last February for employment-giving activities<br />
and the subsequent grant of œ C12.5 million in our 1962/ 63 Budget<br />
had just that purpose. Furthermore, the Commonwealth last June<br />
took the initiative in removing any Loan Council limit on the<br />
overall amount that might be borrowed by local authorities<br />
seeking V100,000 or less in any financial year. The grocat value<br />
of this step is that it gives relatively small bodies all over<br />
the country a better chance of obtaining money to spend on works<br />
in their own towns and districts.<br />
It is encouraging now to find that authorities of<br />
that type had been able to borrow, up to the end of January last,<br />
some œ 16.7 million. This is substantially more than they<br />
borrowed in the comparable period of 1961/' 62 and it is, in fact,<br />
al~ most as much as they used to 1b able to borrow in a full twelve<br />
months up to a couple of years ago.<br />
As was announced last week, the Commonwealth agreed<br />
at the Loan Council to an increase of : C5 million in the 1962/ 63<br />
borrowing programmes for Commonwealth/ State works and housing<br />
aind to an increase of œ C6 million in the programmes of semigovernmental<br />
authorities those seeking to borrow more than<br />
œ-100,000 in 1962/ 63.<br />
The Commaonwc2althi also increased the grant for<br />
emioloyment-giving activities by œ C5 million, bringing the total<br />
grant for 1962/ 63 to fœ 17,5~ million. It stipulated thatc expenditures<br />
from the grant should be over and above those from the<br />
State works and housing programmes and should be distributed o. o 9/ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
to areas, like those of the New South Wales coalfields and the<br />
Northern coastal areas of Queensland, where more general<br />
measures are not so likely as elsewhere to give rise to employment.<br />
On housing, the majority of those who took part in<br />
the consultations thought that rather more finance should be<br />
available both for the erection of new homes and the purchase<br />
of existing homes. A good deal was also said about the problem<br />
of the gap between the amount of loan finance people can obtain<br />
and the deposits they are in a position to make when acquiring<br />
a home. These are problems the Government ha3 very much in<br />
mind. They are highly complex matters, It is far from being<br />
a simple question of making more money available for housing<br />
at large; rather, as with unemployment the problem is to ensure<br />
that action is directed to the real centres of difficulty.<br />
We have, in fact, undertaken to make some additional<br />
finance available for housing through established channels. The<br />
decision to increase Loan Council borrowing programmes for works<br />
and housing this year means that the Commonwealth will add œ 2.4<br />
million to the funds available during the next few months u-ider<br />
the Commonwealth/ Stato housing agreement.<br />
Furthermore, the Commonwealth Baxiking Corporation<br />
has now decided to increase the lending limit for the credit<br />
foncier loans of the Comnonwoalth Savings Bank from œ 3Q, 000 to<br />
œ 3900. The Commonwealth Savings Bank being a large-scale<br />
lender for housing this is, of course, an important step.<br />
War Service Homes When the maximum loan under the War Service Homes<br />
Act was increased from œ 2,750 to œ 3,500 in May, 1962, the<br />
objective was to stimulate the home-building industry as well<br />
as to provide more favourable conditions under which eligible<br />
ex-servicemen could obtain homes or carry out essential additions<br />
to their homes. These objectives have been achieved. It is expected<br />
that the number of new homes which will be financed during<br />
1962/ 63 will be some 800 more than was expected at the beginning<br />
of the year. The increase in the maximum loan has greatly<br />
reduced the number of ox-servicemen who have found it necessary<br />
to obtain finance for their homes under a second mortgage.<br />
There has been a heavy demand for loans to provide additional,<br />
essential a cconodation. In order that this increased demand nay continue to<br />
be dealt with under existing arrangements the Government has<br />
decided to provide an additional œ 2,500,060 to be expended this<br />
financial year. The Government's decision will result in an increase<br />
in the appropriation for Xar Service Homes for the year from<br />
œ 3,000,000 to œ 37,500,000.<br />
More generally, and apart from particular matters<br />
like unemploynent and works expenditure and housing finance, / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
it was put to us that there is a need to give the business<br />
community more guidance as to future economic policy so that<br />
forward planning and investment can proceed with all reasonable<br />
confidence. On this view, it may not always be enough to<br />
demonstrate that the economy is currently well situated,<br />
balanced internally and externally and moving forward at a<br />
good rate as it now is, Businessmen hold that if they are<br />
to plan forward securely they need to know, amongst other<br />
things, what the broad trend and content of future economic<br />
policy is likely to be.<br />
The Government understands this viewpoint and is<br />
disposed to meet it as far as it can. Perhaps, at this point<br />
of time, the first thing is to clear away a certain nisapprehension,<br />
There has been comment lately to the effect that<br />
the expansionary measures the Government took last year have<br />
spent themselves and are now having no effect on the economy.<br />
But this is utterly wrong. The Budget for this year continued<br />
all the measures taken earlier the big tax reductions, the<br />
social service increases, the special grants to the States and<br />
it added to then in the shape of large developmental works.<br />
notably in Queensland and Western Australia. Meanwhile, credit<br />
policy has continued to be highly liberal. Nothing of all<br />
that stimulatory action has been withdrawn. It all goes on in<br />
full force. In fact, it is likely that some of the measures<br />
the investment allowance on manufacturing plant for example<br />
are only now starting to exert their full influence. Also,<br />
some of the larger developmental projects have hardly got<br />
properly into their stride as yet,<br />
The chief objectives of Government policy are,<br />
of course, firm and clear full employment, strong and<br />
continuous industrial growth, stable costs and prices, a<br />
balanced external situation and so on. These aims have been<br />
stated again and again and we have spared no effort to make<br />
them really mean something.<br />
But we realise perhaps better than most the need<br />
to keep up the underlying momentum of the economy. As a<br />
dynamic element, probably nothing counts for more than the<br />
migration programme and here again there seems to be a<br />
misapprehension. It is still being said that migration is<br />
lagging. The truth is that immigration is strongly on the<br />
way up and its prospects have rarely looked better than they<br />
do today. Certainly the 1962/ 63 target of 125,000 arrivals<br />
will be exceeded, There has been a tremendous flood of<br />
applications in Great Britain for assisted passages to<br />
Australia. Many of the applicants are skilled people the<br />
key workers upon whom the expansion of our industries depends<br />
so heavily. These skilled workers are being given the highest<br />
priority. Additional shipping and a substantial airlift<br />
have been arranged and it is already clear that the intake<br />
of British migrants in the twelve months ending 30th June<br />
next will be the best for the past ten years. Nothing could<br />
be more likely to impart a renewed drive to the economy or<br />
give assurance of basic expansion in the years ahead of us.<br />
More specifically, the Government has been asked<br />
to give the firmest indications it can as to policy on the<br />
Budget for next year. This, of course, is difficult. We<br />
do not have, and cannot have for some time yet, any precise / 4 </p>
<p>idea as to the probable levels of receipts and expenditures in<br />
1963/ 64+ and, in any case, the Budget is not a thing on which<br />
forward undertakings can readily be given,,<br />
It is, of course, certain that expenditure will<br />
rise substantially neXt year, as it has done in all recent<br />
years if only because of existing commitments which must be<br />
carried on. It is likely also that taxation revenues will<br />
benefit from the strong rise in industrial activity and earnings<br />
that have occurred through 1962/ 63 and we have great confidence<br />
that trends like these will carry on into 1963/ 64+. But there<br />
are, and always will be, elements in the Budget whirch defy<br />
precise or dependable forecasting even at short range. it<br />
would certainly be cut of the question for us to indicate here<br />
and now what particular measures the Budget for next year may<br />
or may not contain, It can be said, however, that we do intend to renew<br />
the legislation which provides for certain export incentives<br />
which would otherwise expire in 1964+. It can be taken for<br />
certain too that the investment allowance on manufacturing plant<br />
will continue to be available, It is of the essence of measures<br />
like these0 undertaken to provide special incentives, that<br />
once established they ought to be carried on long enou-L<br />
produce t heir in~ ended results.<br />
CANBERRA,<br />
February 21, 19630 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
