<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9729</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP MR HOWARD AND THE MARKS ROYAL COMMISSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009729.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL L N U 031<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
MR HOWARD AND THE MARKS ROYAL COMMISSION<br />
Mr Howard today made the extraordinary admission that he and Mr Court<br />
discussed the establishment of the Marks Royal Commission prior to Mr<br />
Court's public announcement that the Royal Commission would proceed.<br />
In his ABC radio interview this morning, Mr Howard refused three times to<br />
answer direct questions as to whether he in fact urged Mr Court to set up<br />
the Royal Commission.<br />
Mr Howard now has the chance to live up to his rhetoric about the need for<br />
absolute truth in politics. He can answer, truthfully and without prevarication<br />
or deceit, the following simple questions:<br />
Did Mr Howard discuss the establishment of the Marks Royal<br />
Commission with Premier Court before its public announcement?<br />
Did anyone acting on Mr Howard's behalf, especially the shadow<br />
attorney-general, discuss the setting up of the Marks Royal<br />
Commission with Premier Court or anyone acting on his behalf?<br />
How many discussions took place, and when and where were they held?<br />
Given the repeated claims by the Liberal Party that there is no political<br />
motive in the establishment of the Royal Commission; and the fact that the<br />
terms of reference relate to matters in the Western Australian Parliament,<br />
why did Mr Howard and/ or his representatives discuss the establishment of<br />
the Royal Commission with Mr Court and/ or his representatives?<br />
Will Mr Howard adopt in his answers to these questions about his<br />
recollections of his discussion with Premier Court, the same standards of<br />
truth and directness that he claims to seek from Dr Lawrence and her<br />
recollections of Parliamentary events leading up to the tabling of the Easton<br />
petition? CANBERRA August 1995 91/ 95 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
