<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3999</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CLUB LUNCHEON - MR MALCOLM FRASER - GUEST SPEAKER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003999.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
V<br />
~ A EXLNSCRIPT IS T. PJ,' E1 1F. 1Oh1 A TiC. iE ii~ J~ TNOT<br />
RtES. ONSIBLE2 FOR AXEPLEORiS OR O. 432IZS<br />
MR. MAIOOZ L : T-LS GUEST Asi<br />
MAX 1-V TthS, CNairman E1ationaa'. Press Club-.<br />
Mr. Fraser has accepted our invitation to addrc-s the C. lub in<br />
the closingZ week of the election campaign with the poll to b) e<br />
held next Saturday. it is tradition that the Club provides this<br />
national forum for Australia's political leaders to sua up their<br />
campaign on the eve of polling day. The L~ abor Party lteader and<br />
former Prime INinister, tbhe Hon. Gough Vthitlam will address the<br />
Club on Wednesday. Mr. Fr-aser first addressed tae club erlier<br />
this year aster he was elected Parliwnentary leader of the Libe-ral:<br />
Party. Today we have a huge audience of about 570, which is a<br />
record for the N~ ational Press Club and one which we expect io<br />
match on Wednesday. Our one regret however is that bccause olf.<br />
space problems in this huge room due to an earlier bonkinge ,, e<br />
have reluctantly had to turn away nearly another 1.00 who vishbed to<br />
attend and might I remind members that there i~ s a club ruling that<br />
demonstrations of -partiality are to be resisted. Mir. T7raser,,<br />
there is no need to summarise your career history which began in<br />
the Federal Parliament in 1955. 1 therefore now.. invite you to<br />
address the Club and following. your address whichi-ohould run up<br />
to an agreed roughly 20 minutes, we have aimecd to allow double that<br />
time for questions which I remind members are restricted to full<br />
and financial members who are working journalists.<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
Mr. President, Excellencies, ladies and goiitlemen, if m~ y reariks<br />
do go slightly beyond the 20 minutes 11= perfectly happy I. o stay<br />
here a little longer so people won't be denied the opportunity<br />
to ask questio. ns. I'd like to start just by zmaking or noting </p>
<p>53/ 2/ 1975 " Press Club Luncheon" 2.<br />
that Mr. Ifnitlarm seems to be fitting in very well into his job<br />
as Opposition Leader. He has already put doin some questions on<br />
notice. If anyone wants to ask those questions verbally I wouldn't<br />
dream of course of trying to rule them out of order.<br />
As we look forward to the last quarter of the 20th century,<br />
Australia faces a difficult and testing time at home and abroad.<br />
At home in the mediate future we are confronted with the kind of<br />
economic crisis many of us believed could never happen here. A<br />
crisis compounded of high and rising unemployment and high.<br />
inflation. A crisis that should never have occurred. Abroad<br />
we're facing a world of uncertainty and inistability. Of great<br />
global problems which will require great ingenuity and goodwill<br />
to solve. Beyond these problems there are the less obvious but<br />
nonetheless vitally important issues that concern the very basis<br />
of our way of life and style of government. It is about thesepr<br />
that I am going to talk today. These issues concern the very<br />
manner in which Australia is to be governed over the next quarter L<br />
of a century and beyond. They concern the relationship of<br />
government to the people and the extent to which people can control<br />
their own lives in a society int. which governments tend to be<br />
increasingly intrusive and demanding. They concern the relationship<br />
between individuals and other institutions in our society,<br />
especially large businesses and large trade unions. We must make<br />
sure that these institutions remain responsive to the needs of the<br />
people within them. And finally among these crucial issues is<br />
the question of whether we as a people can find a renewed faith<br />
* and commitment to our capacity to provide a decent life for every<br />
person while at the same time encouraging the very best that the<br />
Australian people can offer. Australia is changing, the world is<br />
changing. Australians increasingly recognise that the old conflicts<br />
and divisions have less and less meaning. There are manytrade </p>
<p>unionists who ho longer feel cany identification with the Party<br />
of their traditional support. They no longer feel,-for obvious<br />
reasons, that there is any necessary relation between their own<br />
needs and the policies of that Party. income and opportunities<br />
in Australia are more equally distributed than in almost any other<br />
cou-try in the world despite the existence of significant pockets<br />
of disadvantage and real need remaining within our oin community.<br />
The challenges that face us now are new. In many ways they are<br />
exciting. The degree of social and economic equality we have<br />
provides an uncommon chance for Australia.<br />
ArnoldToynbee wrote 12 volumes examining the rise and fall of<br />
societies and civilisations, and he concluded that the<br />
essential factors in a successful response to challenge were the<br />
quality of government and the character of the people. If we face<br />
our problems squarely and do our best to understand them, I'm<br />
confident that we can meet whatever challenges might be in front<br />
of us.<br />
Sir Robert Menzies in his book " The Measure of the Years" laid<br />
down his view of the obligations of an Opposition Party. He said<br />
that an Opposition Party had an obligation to re-think policies,<br />
to look forward, to devise a body of ideas at once sound and<br />
progressive. Opposition must be regarded as a great constructive<br />
period in the life of a Party, properly considered, not a period<br />
in the wilderness, but a period of preparations for the high<br />
responsibilities that you hope will come. We, in the Liberal and<br />
National Country Parties had spent our time in Opposition preparing<br />
one of the most far reaching, exciting and progressive programmes<br />
that we have ever attempted. I'm confident that if the Australian<br />
people approve our policies on December 13 next Saturday, we can<br />
make an effective start on meeting the problems we face.<br />
It will be our objective to bring inflation under control. and get I<br />
8/ 12/ 1975 " Press Club Luncheon" </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 1975 " Press Club Luncheon" 4.<br />
MRFAER COINUES:<br />
unemployment down as rapidly as possible. Establish a style and<br />
framework of government that will lead to effective policy formulation<br />
and decision making. Make government taxation policies more open<br />
and honest. Establish co-operative, not conflicting relations<br />
betwieen the Federal Government and state and local governments<br />
Strengthen the autonomy, responsibility and flexibility of levels<br />
of government closest to the people and reserve the excessive<br />
centralisation of power in the Federal Government. Encourage, and<br />
where necessary, legally eotablish procedures that will make sure<br />
that large business enterprises remain responsive to the needs of<br />
the people who work in them. Similarly we will establish<br />
procedures which ensure that trade unions remain responsive to<br />
the needs of their members and aren't caught up in search of power<br />
for power's sake. We'll ensure that all people, the socially<br />
and economically disadvantaged, as well as the better off, have<br />
maximum freedom of choice, not only in the goods they buy, but<br />
in the educational, welfare and other services as well. As part<br />
of the cnouragement of choice and diversity, strengthen tolerance<br />
and understanding of differing life styles. Australia has moved<br />
beyond the age of narrow anglo saxon conformity and government<br />
must recognise this, and Australia is a better place for having<br />
moved beyond that.<br />
Finally, we'd ensure that all people have opportunities and<br />
encouragement to achieve of their best so that all Australians<br />
can benefit as a result. Only in this way can Australia be a<br />
nation of independent people, confident in their own abilities<br />
to achieve and master their own destinies. Only in this way<br />
can all Australians have that strong foundation of self respect<br />
on which tolerance and genuine and willing co-operation can be<br />
based. </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 1975 " Press Club Luncheon"<br />
11R. FRASER CONTINUES:<br />
If the Australian people approve our approach next Saturday we'll<br />
establish a style of government through which we can give effect<br />
to and develop our policies. One of the first concerns will be to<br />
secure the integrity and professional character of the public<br />
service, free from political appointments. Our system of government<br />
can only work effectively and efficiently with a politically<br />
neutral public service. Legal procedures will be established<br />
uhich will secure the best appointments to this end. These<br />
procedures will be incorporated in the public service Act. These<br />
procedures will ensure that suitable candidates from within the<br />
public service are not passed over, while not precluding appointments<br />
from outside the service. Obviously before legislation<br />
is drafted, advice of the Public Service Board and other senior<br />
people would be sought but broadly the framework we have in mind<br />
would run like this: The Public Service Board for the appointment<br />
of Permanent Heads for example, could put forward a short list<br />
of suitable candidates from within the service. The Board chairman<br />
. would consult with senior permanent heads in preparing that list.<br />
A short list would go to the Minister concerned and to the Prime<br />
Minister. If there are doubts about the suitability of people,<br />
the chairman of the board would be consulted, if additional names<br />
put forward did not dispel the doubts, the vacancies would then be<br />
advertised. But if it is advertised, a high level selection<br />
committee, including the chairman of the board, at least one other<br />
permanent head, would be formed to interview candidates. The<br />
selection committee would list three or more most suitable<br />
candidates in order of preference and that would go to the Minister<br />
and the Prime Minister. The Minister would obviously interview<br />
the candidates that are put forward and in this way proper<br />
procedures will be followed and the integrity of the service<br />
maintained and protected. </p>
<p>Club 6.<br />
8/ 217 PesCu Luncheon"<br />
IR. FRASER CONTIN'UES:<br />
Government would not be precluded from appointing outsiders without<br />
advertisement, outside the procedures, but in such case it<br />
would be understood that succeeding governments could review such<br />
an appointment, in other words, such an appointment would have no<br />
permanency attached to it. These rules would apply to all future<br />
appointments. They would not apply restrosepctively. We would not<br />
alter the rules under which past appointments have been made.<br />
Wie don't believe that one mistake could be rectified, or should be<br />
rectified, by making another,<br />
Under the Liberal, National Country Party Government, the permanent<br />
head of a department would be expected to be the senior adviser<br />
to the MYinister. He'll also be expected to take into account not<br />
only information available from the Department but information<br />
available from the wider Australian community. Outside advice<br />
will be, and ought to be be, actively sought, and in the past this<br />
wasn'-t always done as much as it should be. All groups and sections<br />
of the community must have the right to put their views before the<br />
government but the procedures for offering advice will not be allowed<br />
to be a battlefield of endless conflict of competing advice.<br />
We'll ensure that the protection of public service integrity and<br />
professionalism does notplace a wall between government and the<br />
community because that would be a disaster.<br />
Parliament itself must be revived as the central forum of our<br />
system of Government. If the Liberal National Country Party are<br />
returned on Saturday, major policy announcements will be made in<br />
the Parliament while the Parliament is sitting. As part of our<br />
plan to revive Parliament, our policy of tax indexation of course<br />
will have an important role to play and I think this has been<br />
unnoticed hitherto. One of the most iniquitous effects of inflation<br />
has been that the rapidly rising tax burden of the last few years.<br />
People are paying every year a larger proportion of their incomes </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 1975 " Press Club Luncheont7<br />
T'NRFRASER CONTINUES:.<br />
on taxation, though this has never been specifically autho.-i. sed<br />
by the Parliament. A basic principle a representative government<br />
has been overturned by inflation. Under inflation taxation<br />
increases automatically if Parliament makes no decision. Under<br />
present conditions Parliament has to take an initiative -only if<br />
it wishes to stop the increase in taxation. The protection afforded<br />
to the people by the requirement-that Parliament must approve<br />
increases ini taxation has been almost nullified by inflation.<br />
These unauthorised tax increases have been a major, if not the<br />
O major, factor in the inflationary wage demand and in the<br />
destruction of business profitability and job opportunities.<br />
Our programme of tax indexation will establish the principle of<br />
0 parliamentary control over tax increases if they're to occur.<br />
It will establish once and for all the principle of government<br />
accountability for tax increases. Our tax reforms will not<br />
merely be a major element in economic recovery, they'll make<br />
debate on taxation matters mean what they ought to mean. They'll<br />
bring into the open some of the most important decisions any<br />
government can take. They'll make governments in Australia more<br />
honest. There are a number of other reforms which would significantly<br />
improve the level of performance of parliament and which could<br />
be introduced in the near future. They are reforms because they<br />
affect the procedures of parliament that I believe ought to have<br />
the support of all parties. One of the most valuable reforms of<br />
parliament as an institution would be to improve the scope and<br />
effectiveness of its committee system. An estimates or an<br />
expenditure committee, such as exists in the House of Commons,<br />
would do much to improve parliament's capacity to control<br />
government spending and watch over administration. It would be<br />
a committee sitting throughout the year and examining the principles </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 8.<br />
and procedures adopted by departments in the formation of estimates.<br />
I believe there is also a valuable r-ole for a steering committee<br />
to assist of passage of non controversial legislation. Such a<br />
Committee could decide to direct legislation either to special<br />
purpose committees or to the whole House, depending on the importance<br />
of the matters under review. Such a committee could promote a more<br />
considered debate in an appropriate forum, and I have spelled out<br />
my ideas on these particular matters in much greater detail in the<br />
Parliament itself. It will be one of our principle objectives to<br />
improve the performance of Parliament and so strengthen its<br />
authority and the practical contribution it can make to the<br />
repnil 0 srla A further pre-condition for the effective<br />
operation ofL-the Parliamentary system is a system of cabinet<br />
government which can arrive at co-ordinated government policies.<br />
M~' inisterial initiative is essential, but the Cabinet, a Cabinet<br />
of reasonable size, must ensure that these initiatives form part<br />
of an overall approach to the achievement of national goals. if<br />
the Australian people support us on Saturday, we will immediately<br />
assert the central role of Cabinet in deciding national policy.<br />
on a basis of Cabinet responsibility and accountability we can<br />
establish sound management of Australia's affairs. An effectively<br />
operating Federal Government will provide the foundation to<br />
implement our three year program of economic recovery. Not<br />
merely must a Federal Government be able to develop and implement<br />
those policies effectively, it must also be able to work effectively<br />
with other governments. The Federal Government should facilitate,<br />
not hinder State and Local Governments informing and implementing<br />
the policies appropriate to their own areas. Australia is a<br />
federal country and will remain so. It will remain so for good<br />
reason. Australia has very clear and natural reasons, regions,<br />
largely represented by the States. As in the United States, the<br />
Australian Senate reflects that fact. Indeed the American<br />
founding fathers gave their senate more substantial powers even<br />
than our Senate. Powers which have led America to the State's<br />
House becoming a dominant chamber-Even if we had no States,<br />
it could still be necessary in the interests of effective policy<br />
development and implementation, to formally acknowledge that<br />
policies would have to be acceptable to the great natural regions </p>
<p>8/ 11 2/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 9.<br />
of Australia and not merely to those areas where the great majority<br />
of people live in M~ elbourne and Sydney. The federal structure of<br />
the Australian Government is critically necessary from another<br />
vieiwroin; as well. It is increasingly important that a politically<br />
aware and active population should be able to participate, and<br />
participate effectively in political decisions of importance. As<br />
our society becomes larger and more complex, it is imperative that<br />
local levels of government should be revitalised. Increasing the<br />
centralisation of government power in Canberra is positively<br />
dangerous. The more power is centralised, the less is it subject<br />
to popular influence and popular control. A highly centralised<br />
government, seeking more and more power for itself, is totally<br />
inappropriate to a complex, diverse, changing and well educated.<br />
society. It is totally inappropriate to a country as far flung as<br />
Australia. Instead of central control, there should be improved<br />
procedures for co-ordination and co-operation between levels of<br />
government on matters of common concern. Our reforms to financial<br />
arrangements between Federal, State and Local governments and the<br />
Council for Inter-gov'r-nmental relations, we will es~ tablish, will<br />
do more to achieve these objectives than any reform to the federal<br />
system since federation. These reforms will make it possible for<br />
Local and State governments to plan ahead on a way that has not been<br />
possible in the past. They are part of a broader program to incrdase<br />
the substance and effectiveness of Local Government. Our social<br />
welfare policy for example, in line with the recommendations of the<br />
Henderson Commission of Inquiry into Poverty, places special weight<br />
on the role of Local Government in the co-ordination and provision </p>
<p>~"/ lP2/ r7e5 ss Club Luncheon"' 10<br />
of welfare services at the local level. With such an emphasis,<br />
it should be possible to avoid the impersonality of centrally<br />
provided services and to tailor services to the needs of the local<br />
area. The need to reform our institutions, to ensure that they<br />
are aware of the needs of the individuals, and not merely to the<br />
needs of bureaucracy, applies of course not merely to government.<br />
It applies equally to business and to the trade unions. No<br />
organisation, whether it be a political party, a business or a<br />
union, has ary inherent right to survival. Its justification<br />
is the sertices it provides to individuals. Countries for<br />
example, find their justification in the extent to which they<br />
provide decent jobs, worthwhile goods and services which the<br />
community wants and provide a reasonable return for those who<br />
invest in them. The justification for the existence of<br />
companies is the service they provide the community. Trade<br />
unions find their justification in the extent to which they<br />
improve the condition of their members, consistent with the<br />
interests of the community as a whole. The best companies, the<br />
best trade unions recognise this social obligation, but there are<br />
many in both areas that do not. We must encourage all companies<br />
and trade unions to follow the example of the best. It is<br />
obvious that there is still great scope to improve the quality<br />
of and participation in decisions about working conditions. it<br />
is obvious that there is still a great need to increase the<br />
flexibility with which people can choose their work. The rigid<br />
nine to five working hours . Chstill apply in many business<br />
preclude * many people from working in them. Greater flexibility<br />
of working hours will meet the needs of people and of businesses.<br />
-6/ 12/ 75 </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 11.<br />
There is further a great need to improve the opportunities<br />
for participation by union members in the affairs of their own<br />
anions. Our policies dealing with portability of pensions<br />
and superannuation schemes, increased works consultation on shop<br />
floor matters, our policies on flexible hours, special facilities<br />
for working mothers and for elections in unions and employer<br />
organisations would all make an important contribution to the<br />
achievement of these objectives. The aim of our policies, is to<br />
Sencourage the growth of an Australia which is adaptable, strong<br />
and capable of facing and surmounting challenges. Government<br />
must create the conditions for the development of a vital, dynamic<br />
society. It must also encourage our sense of a common interest<br />
in people. The present economic crisis can only be overcome<br />
if the Government accepts its obligation to point the way if its<br />
policies encourage the co-operation of all Australians. We in the<br />
Liberal and National Country Parties pledge ourselves to work for<br />
that spirit of national co-operation. I believe that the program<br />
on which we are fighting this election provides the basis for that<br />
co-operation. It is a program that seeks to advance the right of<br />
every Australian to freedom, self respect and a real opportunity<br />
to fulfil themselves and their life in their own It is a<br />
program that will help build Australia which can survive in the<br />
uncertain world in which we live. It is a program we are proud to<br />
place before the Australian people for their judgment.<br />
INTERVIEWER:<br />
Thank you Mr Fraser. We now turn to questions from our media<br />
members. I would remind them would they identify themselves and<br />
and their organisations and please keep their questions brief, and<br />
I would stress right here and now that in this-huge room we have </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Lu&amp; ncheon" 12.<br />
1T-AX HAWKINS CONTINUTES:<br />
had in the past and will continue to have and hopefully won't<br />
have in our own club building next year, some hearing problems<br />
of questions. I just ask you to bear with that and wouald ask<br />
our questioners to speak up as loudly as possible. The first<br />
question is Nikky Savva...<br />
NI= K SAVVA:<br />
We supported this Children's Commission when it went through<br />
the power, and one of the things I have not been able to understand<br />
is why it took so long to get the Commission properly established?<br />
IDIR FRASER:<br />
As You know, it was only an interim committee that has been<br />
established. The Commission itself has not been established<br />
and this is one of the matters that I shall be examining, hopefully,<br />
after next Saturday.<br />
STEVE BIRO'JER:<br />
Would you consider you handled the news media well during the<br />
campaign and do you consider you have received more<br />
than favourable treatment from the proprietors?<br />
MIR FRASER:<br />
The first question is one that the media themselves will have<br />
to judge and so far as the other one is concerned, I think the<br />
media can make their own judgments about that. There is a habit<br />
amongst politicians to blame the media where things are going<br />
badly for them.<br />
TONY O'LEARY:<br />
You promised Statehood to the Northern Territory inaudible<br />
with less than half the voting population of the ACTI, will the </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 ",. Press Club Luncheon" 13.<br />
ACT be granted a similar degree of independence if you are elected<br />
on December 13?<br />
MR FRASER:<br />
Our Policy for the Australian Capital Territory does emphasise<br />
the need to have Lmaximum autonomy that is possible, executive<br />
responsibility in the local assembly, but there is one very<br />
significant difference that everyone will recognise between the<br />
Australican Capital Territory and the Northern Territory. For<br />
better or worse, the national capital is also in the Australian<br />
Capital Territory and therefore the relationship between the<br />
Commonwealth Government and the Australian Capital Territory<br />
Assembly will necessarily be different in quality and character<br />
I would think to that between theCornmonwealth Government and the<br />
States. We would need working parties to examine this particular<br />
matter to see how much executive authority can be transferred to the<br />
local Assembly.<br />
PAULI KELLY AUSTRALJIAN:<br />
During the campaign, you have refused under questioning regarding<br />
to two key factors on the M~ edi-bank scheme inaudible Firstly<br />
free treatment in hospital wards, and secondly the 85% refund from<br />
the super health insurance fund offices. Can you tell us in these<br />
circumstances why the public should not think that you are retaining<br />
the name I-edi-bank but destroying the scheme?<br />
MR FRASER:<br />
Because we have said we are going to maintain the scheme and the<br />
answer to that is very simple. I think that was one of Mr.<br />
Whitlam's questions if I can recall it correctly. Oh well, other<br />
people have got a right to know and I said I would not rule any </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club ILuncheoh"' 14.<br />
MYR. FRASER COITTIIE1-JITG:<br />
question out of order. But the scheme has not been operating<br />
long enough for us to get an assessment of it from the States, from<br />
the hospitals from the profession and also from the consuming public.<br />
The patients have a right to be consulted in -these particular matters<br />
and I am not saying that it is easy to assess the reactions of<br />
patients in these particular matters, but the scheme will be continued<br />
as it wa-s introduced until we can assess properly its virtues and<br />
whatever faults might be revealed as a result of experience. Then<br />
public statements would be made about that and everyone would have<br />
an opportunity to express their views in relation to it. . Meanwhile,,<br />
Wthe scheme continues as introduced.<br />
RUJSSELJL SEITON MELBOURiFB AGE:<br />
You are reported in the Canberra Times as saying that rural<br />
concessions should not cost the urban taxpayer. Could you please<br />
explain this?<br />
M4R. FRASER:<br />
I was referring there to support for the wool reserve price scheme<br />
which is loan at.-the modest interest rate charged by the Government<br />
of 11% or Well that is in line with interest rates charged<br />
everywhere and against the security of the clip, farmers pay for the<br />
rate of interest and it is not a charge therefore on the taxpayer.<br />
The Industry Assistance reports for the beef industry, there is a<br />
significant loan element involved in that which also does not involve<br />
a charge on the taxpayer, and they were the elements I was referring<br />
-to.<br />
RUSSELL SKELTON CONTINUING:<br />
Could I just ask a supplementary question? Doesthis mean that </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75" Press~ Club Luncheon" 1<br />
the open rule policy announced by IKrAtoy ilco6utoth<br />
urban taxpayers' money?<br />
K~ R FRA SER:<br />
The increased cost of Holden motor cars and refrigerators and<br />
washing machines and wirelesses and T. V. sets also comes out of<br />
the funds of the average Australian and the philosophical<br />
difference in some instances between a subsidy and a tariff is not<br />
as wide as some people would like to indicate. There are some<br />
areas the super-phosphate bounty, nitrogenous fertiliser bounty,<br />
T. B. and brucellosis eradication campaign which this year would cost<br />
2.4m. Also a recommendation as that was of the Industries<br />
Assistance Commission report, that would be a charge on the taxpayer,<br />
but you asked in the first part of your question what I meant when<br />
I said ' some matters were not' and the major matters especially in<br />
relation to the wool corporation is not a charge on the taxpayer, they<br />
are loan funds against the security of the clip for which many people<br />
would believe a reasonably high rate of interest is paid.<br />
A1UMIREW CLARK: National Times.<br />
You quoted in the Australian of the last few days that you do not<br />
believe that gaoling unionists is an appropriate punishment for<br />
industrial offences. You say ( inaudible) ' Doug McCleland's talk of<br />
fines, de-registration, garnisheeing of union funds and even court<br />
actions are all hot air-and nonsense. However, the Coalition' s<br />
industrial policy in which you play a'leading role says, that for<br />
offenses like strikes you could ( inaudible). Consequences would include<br />
' de-registrationg( ilaudible) or garnishee of funds, fines, exclusiol from<br />
office of employer industrial officers or of office bearers of<br />
organisations ( question unclear) innocent may claim damages for loss<br />
suffered as a result of an unfair industrial practice. Is this still<br />
your policy or not? Are the exclusions ( unclear) aimed at plotting<br />
against trade union officials and does it mean that if a union official<br />
refuses to reveal the whereabouts of his own union bank account, like<br />
in the case of Terry O'Shea, he will be fined for comtempt ( inaudible)<br />
(% his question was extremely difficult to hear)! </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club luncheon" 1<br />
1, R FRASER:<br />
The question would have been more compete if it had indicated<br />
that the answers given in Australia were in relation to questions<br />
which concerned secret ballot legislation and they were restricted<br />
to that. So if there was an implication in the question that it<br />
had covered the whole area of industrial policy, in the question<br />
today I mean, that of course was not true because the original<br />
question was relating to secret ballot legislation. The other<br />
parts of the industrial policy of course sband.<br />
LAURIE WILSON:<br />
Mr Fraser, you have been accused of stone-walling daring this<br />
campaign may we enter into this? Don't you think the people<br />
of Australia have the right to know the answers to this particularly<br />
oni the specific area of your economic policy. I just wonder how<br />
you react to those accusations?<br />
IMR FRASE R:<br />
I am afraid you rather invited this but if it means that a person<br />
must answer every question put in precisely the way the person who<br />
asks it wants to get an answer, well if it means that, my reply to<br />
that is, that is a lot of nonsense. There are some things that<br />
can be said with responsibility and others that cannot. Now in<br />
r'elation to our economic policy for example, I have said quite<br />
plainly that the pace with which we can introduce the reforms,<br />
major reforms will depend upon our success in reigning in the mad<br />
extravagance of Liabor's expenditure. And I have emphasised that<br />
in 72 years of Federation, the Federal Government's budget went to<br />
ten thousand million dollars and in three years of Labor, it went<br />
to twenty two thousand million dol-lars. I do not believe that any<br />
organisation, any company, any business can increase its rate of<br />
expenditure at that rate and not involve a good deal of extravagance </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 17.<br />
and waste, and when we get the detailed reports from departments<br />
and from the treasury, I am sure that that sort of thing will<br />
unfold. So I believe that the Press have had a fair go, so far as<br />
being able to ask me questions are concerned, but they have not always<br />
got precisely the answer they wanted to get. I apologise for that<br />
but the situation is not going to change.<br />
FRED BAILEY: Adelaide Advertiser. &amp; X.-A4.4-<br />
Mr Fraser, you spoke of taxation reforms inaudible. After the<br />
Selections on Saturday, what would be inaudible Labor's tax reform<br />
inaudible to come into effect?<br />
FRASER: be<br />
Well, it comes into effect and there are going to/ a great many<br />
people who will regret it. Mr Lynch has just put out a statement<br />
which indicates, for example, that students are going to be worse<br />
off because apparently students allowances are going to be taxed<br />
and there are copies of his statement I suggest that people get<br />
a look at it'll show that students who get a student's al. lowance<br />
and who under the present circumstances are lucky enough to get<br />
part time employment will be paying significantly more tax.<br />
That is a statement that Mr. Lynch has put out. But I had also<br />
taken a number of examnples in relation to these matters because if<br />
you took somebody in the last taxation years for which these sorts<br />
of figures are available, the 1972-73 year, somebody then on<br />
$ 7,000 per year, with a wife but no dependants, he would have been<br />
paying C901 in tax and under the new scale he would be paying<br />
S970 in tax. If you make an allowance for inflation at 15% o, they<br />
will be paying $ 1338 in tax 16% 11 instead of 12.9% of his income.<br />
A taxpayer with a wife and one child on $ 9,000 per year, would have </p>
<p>8/ 1P2/ 7r5 ess Club Luncheon" 18<br />
MR. F! RASER CONTINUING:<br />
been paying S1399 in tax under the new scale with no inflation<br />
$ 1470 in tax under the new scale with 15% inflation $ D1897 in<br />
tax. A very significant increase indeed. That is a taxpayer with<br />
a wife and one child. There are other examples here that indiCate<br />
the same results and this sheet of paper can be made available to<br />
anyone who wants it. It does indicate that there are some examples<br />
of taxpayers who are going to be very significantly worse off under<br />
the Hayden tax system. It does come into force. It was one, as<br />
part of the caretaker government it was one of the lists of Bills<br />
that went to Proclamation that I think I signed, so it does come into<br />
force. But we willbe immediately wanting to get people to look at<br />
it to review the areas of injustice that we believe are involved in<br />
the Hayden tax scales. The other point that I would like to make<br />
is that, if you take people on fairly average incomes, you will find<br />
that where the Hayden tax sheets that were handed out at the time of<br />
the budget, had three sets of examples-one person with no<br />
deductions, one person with 5% deductions and another with<br />
deductions. The average deductions for the sort of people in the<br />
average income groups are mcre in the region of 12 to 14% l~ or<br />
and I am talking about people on modest incomes not on high incomes.<br />
These people were not even mentioned on those tax sheets that Mr.<br />
Hayden handed out, and when you look to the average deductions that<br />
people did claim, you find that that quite often, puts them in a<br />
worse position on the basis of the figures that I have just given you.<br />
Because these figures were based on the taxpayers having the average<br />
tax deductions for this particular income bracket.<br />
MAX HATK ITNS:<br />
Mr. Fraser, could I just allay the fears of some people who are just<br />
wondering about questions I have on this sheet. At least sixteen or<br />
8/ 12/ 7518. </p>
<p>8"/ P1re2s/ s7 5C lub luncheon" 1<br />
MAUX HAWKINS:<br />
seventeen names for future questions. We a-re getting through<br />
them we have at least half an hour so, just please be patient.<br />
PETER BLAZET4Y: Sunday Observer.<br />
Any Prime Minister should have his health scrutinised to a degree.<br />
Your illness before your policy speech has given rise to concern<br />
about your health. I was wondering if I could ask a two part<br />
question. The first part is if you would confirm that you have<br />
ever sought the seirvices of a psychiatrist? The second part is<br />
it true as is now being rumoured in Melbourne, that you sought the<br />
S services of the P. sychiatrist Ainslie Meers, author of ' Relax Without<br />
Drugs'? Is it true that medical authorities in Melbourne are now<br />
wondering if Malcolm Fraser, Prime Minister might be a health hazard?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
Well, if that was meant as a joke, I think it has fallen slightly<br />
flat! If I am going to answer any question I have to have some<br />
opiinion of the person who asks it!<br />
SANDREW ICRUGER: Melbourne Sun.<br />
Mr Fraser, on 12 November, you asked the Press to be factual<br />
rather than internoretative. Sir, could you help us in this job<br />
by telling us whether you would describe a forty five million dollar<br />
cut back in spending on tertiary education as severe or as non<br />
essential. Is it true that plans are underway by your administration<br />
to cut back this spending by such an amount, and can you give an<br />
assurance that tertiary education spending will not be cut?<br />
8/ 12/ 7519. </p>
<p>-' 7<br />
8/ 12/ 75 " Press Cluab Luncheon"<br />
M. FRASER:<br />
We have already committed ourselves to the recommendations of<br />
the Commission and I think that it woulId be a good idea to remind<br />
people that it was the Labor party that destroyed triennial funding<br />
for universities, colleges of advanced education, schools commission<br />
the Australian Research Grants Commission and the National Health<br />
and Medical Research Council and if people are wanting to ask us<br />
questions about that, why not ask Hr. Whitlam. If I can put<br />
Pa question on notice why did he destroy that basis of triennial<br />
funding? ROSS GIBBONS Sydney Horning Herald.<br />
M~ r Fraser, you have stressed the importance of tax indexation<br />
in the maintenance of wage indexation. You also said that tax<br />
scales won't be fully indexed until 1978. Do you really expect<br />
wage indexation to last another three years?<br />
ER. FRASER:<br />
I would have believed so, yes. At least we have made a<br />
commitment to tax indexation which is much more than 1,1r. Hayden<br />
and 11Wrhit lam have done.<br />
DON WHITINGT01% T: Australian Press Services.<br />
If you are returned to office, will you ensure that the electoral<br />
act prohibits a major party financing an independent candidate<br />
in an election campaign, in return for his preferences?<br />
11R. FRASER:<br />
On two points there is one question on which-writs have been<br />
served and I do not want to make any comment about that. On<br />
another point where writs have not been served, I understand the<br />
Australian Labor Party has financed advertisements for a certain </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 21.<br />
FPSER CONTII-tJING:<br />
Independent, up to $ 200,000. It is a point that certainly could well<br />
be exarined.<br />
TONY WAIKER:<br />
Is it your view that Indonesia has acted properly in relation to<br />
East Timor and a direct question, has Australia protested to Indonesia<br />
over its actions, and if it hasn't, are you planning to lodge a full<br />
* diplomatic protest?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
I have had a number of discussions this morning with Mr. Peacock<br />
and with the Department and with the head of my Department to see if<br />
there are initiatives that Australia can usefully take. Mr. Peacock<br />
made a statement yesterday, but meanwhile, I do not want to add any more<br />
to what I have said.<br />
TOf\ Y ' IALKER:<br />
Mr. Fraser can I ask you something else. Have we protested, are we<br />
going to protest and at the end of the question what is your view<br />
about Indonesia's actions?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
Regret might be regarded as too modest a word, but the use of force<br />
is never a proper way to solve any international problem and I think<br />
that makes my own view completely clear about that. The words that<br />
Mr. Peacock used yesterday may or may not, depending on your own<br />
interpretation, be regarded as a protest. But I do not want to get<br />
into the details of this particular matter because I have been having<br />
discussions with the head of the department of Foreign Affairs and with<br />
the head of my own department to see if there is any action that it </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon"? 22.<br />
1, M. FRASER C0ONTINUING:<br />
might be proper for Australia to take.<br />
LAURIE ]? OWE" R:<br />
At the beginning of this campaign Mr. Fraser, you consistently<br />
refrained to give any costing of your economic plans. Are you<br />
asking people to go to the polls on Saturday, still ignorant of that<br />
costing and its inaudible.<br />
11R. FKUSER:<br />
Not ignorant no, but the costing is going to depend upon the degree<br />
to which we can reign in the extravagance of the previous Labor<br />
Government and we have got to have as a prime objective, overcominig<br />
inflation. It w. e do no overcome inflation, we will not be able to<br />
revive business confidence adequately. We won't create the jobs<br />
and opportunities that ought to be available to Australians. On<br />
this sort of basis, it is not possible therefore, to indicate the<br />
speed with which the proposals will be introduced until we have the<br />
basis of which economies can be made without jeopardising essential<br />
and important programs, which we would all want to see continue.<br />
ROB. CHALI'ThRS:<br />
Mr. Fraser, this might be a question on notice, but on 15 November,<br />
on Four Corners, you forcast that there would be no blow-up in Timor.<br />
' Blow-up' was your word. Why did you s~ o forcast and on what advice?<br />
1,1R. FRASER:<br />
Well, if that is what I did say on Four Corners on that occasion,<br />
obviously it was incorrect, and later events have taken part in it.<br />
EMT RAIUTDALL:<br />
Mr Fraser, Can you tell us why such important policy statements<br />
as business development, equalisation formula and federalism </p>
<p>' 8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 2.3.<br />
IMN RAIMI) ALL CONTINTUING:<br />
policies, and even your specific anti-inflation policy, have not<br />
been introduced in advance of this election, and apparently<br />
once ( inaudible).<br />
MR. FRAS9ER:<br />
Well the anti-inflationary policies have been announced and made<br />
very clear and the change Ln direction that would begin on Sunxday,<br />
is I think, also clear and very clear to the great majority of<br />
Australians. This is one of those efforts really isn't it to put<br />
certain figures, which it is just not practicable and would not be<br />
responsible to do in the present c ircumstances. The major elements<br />
of policy have been announced right around Australia. The question<br />
of eoualisation has been covered in terms of absolute guarantees for<br />
the less popular States with a smaller tax space, not only in terms<br />
of fiscal capacity, but in terms of need, and in that extent our<br />
equalisation provisions will be very much in advance of Canada's,<br />
because in Canada the equalisation only refers to fiscal capacity<br />
and not to need that might result from large area and greater<br />
. distances and sparcer population. So the principles are laid<br />
down, but quite obviously in a matter of that time, which will be<br />
a highly technical one, you are going to need Federal and State official<br />
to sit down and work out the details in a quite precise form. And i<br />
have got no doubt it will take those officials many weeks, if not some<br />
months of work to get to an appropriate formula.. And therefore,<br />
having spelled out the principles, the details is a matter for<br />
officials to be worked out between governments. I think there was<br />
another element of the question Well, urban develonment is<br />
another area again where a number of our policies will help with<br />
urban development. The support for local government is going to </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 24.<br />
M4R. FRASER CONTINUING:<br />
help very much. I would have said that the essential urban<br />
programs that have already been introduced will continue. Indeed,<br />
a number of the programs that were due for signing and in the<br />
capacity of care-taker Government carrying on the policies of the<br />
previous Government, I have not pack-signed them and they continued<br />
with the programs that have put and framed for this particular year.<br />
BILL1 GOUGH: ABC News.<br />
If you leave any formula for the appointment of senior public<br />
servants, and avoid political influence in those appointments,<br />
Shave you seen the appointments of senior public servants only after<br />
interview with the ministry involved as removing your objection to<br />
the politicisation of the Public Service?<br />
11R. FRASER:<br />
Well I think what I said must have been misunderstood. You said<br />
' only after interview with the minister" as though it was the only<br />
essential element in it. Now there are a number of steps and they<br />
re all contained in the speech. The Board to put forward a short<br />
list obviously to discuss that list with the M~ inister and the Prime<br />
Mvinister. If there are doubts, another list. If there are still<br />
doubts advertise the Board advertising. The Chairman of the Board<br />
and other people being on a high level selection committee to put<br />
forward a proposal. Now all of this leaves the initiative for putting<br />
names forth in the hands of the Board and the Public Sergice, and it<br />
is only under the circumstances in which the Minister and the Prime<br />
Minister say no, we do not like any of these names, we are going to<br />
appoint somebody else, alright they can appoint somebody else. But<br />
that particular person would not be regarded as a permanent head in the </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon"<br />
11iR. FRASER CON',. TIMUING:<br />
traditional sense and some incoming government or that same<br />
government for that matter would be under no obligation to maintain<br />
. if we establish proper procedures to make sure that the<br />
Board's advice and the proper approach to selection of people<br />
outside, which involves the Board very much in the procedures, in<br />
every stage of the procedures, then I think we will go a long way to<br />
remove the possibility of some of the political appointments that<br />
have occurred in the past, which I believe are bad for the service<br />
* andought not to occur in the future.<br />
IMIJGO ' 1-cCALUMh:<br />
M1r. Fraser, in your policy speech, you promised not to give our<br />
money to African terrorists. I assume by that you are referring<br />
to the $ 150,000 which was given through UNICEF to women and children<br />
in Zambia who had been affected by war. Dloes this promise, what it<br />
is a specific one of cutting Government spending which you have<br />
Smade mean that in future, humanitarian aid from Australia will only<br />
go to countries with whose governments you yourself feel some<br />
sympathy, if not ( inaudible)?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
There was no understanding, I think, as to where that particular<br />
money actually ended up. My understanding is that there was no<br />
guarantee as to where it ended up and anyway, it was just a straight<br />
statement. We are not going to provide aid to that sort of<br />
organisation or to an organisation that espouses terror as a weapon<br />
of achieving a political objective. Quite apart from that,<br />
Australia has had a record in aid under the Labor Government.' and<br />
under the previous Government which have had regard for the well<br />
being of the people to whom the aid was directed and not necessaril~ y </p>
<p>K 8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club luancheon" 26.<br />
KTR. YtA. SMR CON'TINUUM:<br />
al all to the political colour of the government concerned, and<br />
that philosophy and approach will be continued.<br />
BRIAN TOGKMY:<br />
M4r. Fraser you have made repeated statements that you think<br />
people should have more freedom to decide how they spend their own<br />
money by reducing -the tax burden. In terms of the Bass by-election<br />
you used the slogan ' give the money back to the people who earned<br />
it'. Can we then have aguarantee that in the three year program<br />
to restore the Australian economy, you will not increase tax rates<br />
for personal income tax, for company tax, for indirect tax,, for<br />
levies, for excises or whatever2<br />
M~ R. FRASER:<br />
I think that is another question on notice. Yes or no answers<br />
are not necessarily the sort of answers that I might regard as<br />
Oappropriate. The whole philosophy, and the whole thrust of what<br />
we are saying on our economic policy, is that there needs to be a<br />
change of direction. That more resources need to be placed in the<br />
hands of individuals and of businesses, so that investment can<br />
proceed, so that jobs can be created. We have even got Lionel<br />
Bowen in the paper this morning saying how terrible it was that they<br />
had made all sorts of mistakes, and I think it must be right. I am<br />
not sure, but I think it was the Financial Review that reported it!<br />
I don't suppose you really want me to categorise the mistakesthat<br />
they claimed that they made, but they are all there. The whole<br />
thrust of our policy is that we need to get more resources into<br />
the free enterprise sector, whether it is businesses or individuals,<br />
and the thrust of your question, of course, would run directly<br />
counter to our basic policy objectives. </p>
<p>8/ 3-2/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 27.<br />
BRIANT TOOEY:<br />
Mir. Fraser, I asked you this. You have said the thrust is to<br />
put more resources into the hands of' individuals and companies.<br />
Surely, the thing that flows from that is what is going to happen<br />
to tax rates affecting individuals and companies and surely you<br />
can give an answer as to whether you are likely to increase them<br />
over that period of time.;<br />
TONY THOMIAS Age<br />
4D As a long term matter, would you continue to make aid to rural<br />
industry, dependent on prior reports and recommendation by the<br />
way<br />
Industries Assistance Commission in the same/ as applies to<br />
secondary industry?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
As a generality, yes. I can see some circumrstances -where the<br />
emei'gency provisions of the Industries Assistance Commission<br />
have now worked particularly well, and there are two sides to this<br />
point providing aid and taking aid away and the 25% across<br />
the board which was taking aid away from much of the secondary<br />
industry, was one which led to a great deal of difficulty in the<br />
exporting of tens of thousands of jobs. These matters ought to be<br />
subject to impartial scrutiny and impartial advice. At the same<br />
time, governments have got to make their own decisions in relation<br />
to these matters. If the decisions happened to be contrary to<br />
the advice, the government has got to stand up and explain the<br />
reasons why.<br />
PETER BOWERS: Sydney M~ orning Herald.<br />
Mr. Fraser, have you decided on the size of your Cabinet, and<br />
how many Ministers will it enclose? </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 175 " Press Club Luncheon" t 28.<br />
Nil. I; ASER CONTUiTIING:<br />
The structure of' the Ministry would not be announced until after<br />
Saturday. I think there is a good precedent in relation to that.<br />
I think Mr. Whitlam adopted the same stance some time ago, and he<br />
did set one or two precedents I am prepared to follow. It will be<br />
a much more economic administration than his.<br />
TREVOR CAVANAGH: Daily MiLrror.<br />
Mr. Fraser, would you agree that the devaluation of the Australian<br />
dollar would be inflationary?<br />
MR. FRIISER: I am not going to make any comments on devaluation<br />
0of the Australian dollar. Australia has got substantial reserves.<br />
It is in a strong position and I regret the attempts to revive<br />
public debate which causes public doubts about the strength of<br />
the Australian dollar.<br />
TREVOR CA-VANAGH?<br />
O There have been widespread reports in the Press that a Liberal-<br />
Country Party coalition ( inaudible)<br />
MR. FRASE; R:<br />
This is one of' those areas where people just don't speculate, and<br />
I am not going to blame the source, but the source of' the reports<br />
were not from Liberal or National Country Party sources. Let me<br />
make that quite plain, and I am not going to add to my previous<br />
answer, for the very obvious reasons.<br />
WARWICK BRACKEN: Canberra Times.<br />
11r, Fraser, do you acknowledge any advantages to the tax rebate<br />
system as opposed to the concessional system at all, and if you do,<br />
could you tell us what they are? </p>
<p>7, 8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 29.<br />
DIR. FRASEDR:<br />
I think there are some advantages in both systems, and I have<br />
got an open mind about the way in which the injustices I referred to<br />
in the Hayden scheme should be overcome. There are some clear<br />
advantages in some areas in relation to the rebate system, and I<br />
think we would all know what they are.<br />
TONY HiLL: Melbourne Herald.<br />
Sir, would you accept that the use of the powers of Senate -twice<br />
within eighteen months to block supply and so cause an electicn, has<br />
led to certain instability, uncertainty in Australian political life?<br />
Mr. Whitlam. has given an undertaking that if Labor has the balance of<br />
power in the Senate after next Saturday, that power would not be used<br />
to force a Liberal Government to the elections. Would you be<br />
prepared, if you find yourself in opposition after Saturday, to give<br />
a similar undertaking?<br />
O MRI. FRASER:<br />
Ido not believe it has led to any unstability in the Australian<br />
political scene. That power has been used by upper houses in the<br />
States, and no instability has followed. The power was only used<br />
because of the utter irresponsibility and incompetence of the<br />
Government, and there will always be instability if we have a<br />
government as incompetent and as irresponsible and deceitfu~ l as<br />
the government that preceeded the present one. If I can just keep<br />
the record straight, it is my understanding that I saw a qualification<br />
of those remarkcs of Mir. Whitlam's in the newspapers this morning or<br />
in this morning's reports, saying that he had a certain view but he<br />
did not think he could hold the troops. Now if that is an accurate<br />
report, it is a fairly accurate description of the relationship </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon"<br />
DIR. FRASER CON~ TIN~ UING:<br />
between himself and his Ministry and senior Ministers over the<br />
last two years.<br />
JOHN JOSEPH:<br />
Mr. Fraser, you promised to index tax for companies and individuals<br />
although you refused to say if rates will be increased before you<br />
do index taxes, you promised to pump hundreds of millions of dollars<br />
into business, you promised to increase subsidies inito the riral<br />
sector, you have also promised to balance the budget. Journalists<br />
have been asking you consistently throughout the campaign how you<br />
will achieve this. I want to ask you, have you been advised againS4t<br />
answering questions of details concerning your policies? have you<br />
been told by Yir. Gaul and Mr. Eggleton that Fir. Sneddon got into<br />
trouble for giving detailed answers to questions and is this the<br />
reason for your refusal to answer questions?<br />
O MR. FRASER:<br />
Well, maybe if people read more carefully what had been said in the<br />
nature of the policy speech, they would not need to ask that kind of<br />
question, but the assumptions that underlay the original part of that<br />
question want checking, because some conclusions were made in relation<br />
to the assumptions and part of them which need to be looked at very<br />
carefully in relation to the time frame in which we said it is necessary<br />
to achieve economic recovery. The statement is quite plain. It is<br />
just not possible to indicate the rate at wh-ich the reforms can<br />
be introduced until we can assess accurately on the advice of<br />
departments, the speed with which we can reign in the extravagance Of<br />
the previous Government. And if people doubt the extravagance of the<br />
previous Government, you have only got to go to two figureo which T </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 31.<br />
NR. FRASER CONTINUING:<br />
have already mentioned. Seventy two years of Australian Federaticn<br />
to get to a total budget of Ten thousand million dollars and three<br />
years of Labor more than double it to more than twenty two thousand<br />
million dollars. Now obviously, we have got to go into this matter<br />
very closely and very thoroughly, and we will need the advice of<br />
departments to achieve it.<br />
. JCEI JOSEPH continuing:<br />
Mr. Fraser, is it your intention simply to you make the promises<br />
will you be willing to sacrifice the promises if you are advised that<br />
it is impossible to carry them out?<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
What we said we will do is practical and will be done.<br />
MAX HAWUKINS:<br />
Alan Thornhill and just before you start Alan, we have time for<br />
four more questions after that, that is Brendan Donnelly, Andrew<br />
Potter, Alan Fitzgerald and Laurie Oaks and then we will have to<br />
* close. ALAN THOIUTHILL: Sydney M-orning Herald.<br />
Mr. Fraser, you are the first person to date that I have heard refer<br />
to Mr. Whitlam in the current situation as Leader of the Opposition.<br />
On what parliamentary precedent do you justify this in current<br />
circumstances? MR. FRASER:<br />
He just happens to be Leader of the Opposition that's all.<br />
BRENDAN DOgJELLY: 2CA NEWS </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 1Press Club Luncheon" 32.<br />
BRELNDAN DONINELLY:<br />
Mr. Fraser, would a Liberal-INational Country Party Government<br />
consider introducing a system of tax-reimbursements in the A. C. T.<br />
as applies in the States, and would consideration be given to<br />
putting budgetry planning in the A. C. T. onto a three yearly basis?<br />
U FRASER:<br />
Well budgetry planning for the Commonwealth is basically on<br />
the way the budget is drawn up is in fact on an annual basis,<br />
except as we know for the essential areas. Well, it is on an<br />
annual basis for every area now, but it used to be on a triennial<br />
basis for education and certain research programs. The<br />
relationship with the Assembly in the Australian Capital Territory<br />
and the Federal Government is one that will have to be worked out<br />
with care. Our objective will be to achieve maximum local<br />
autonomy, but because the national capital happens to be placed<br />
in the Australian Capital Territory, it will be a different<br />
S relationship from that which prevails between the Federal<br />
Government and the States and it is now possible at this stage to<br />
define how that relationship will develop, but it will be one that<br />
will develop in a spirit of co-operation and partnership and not<br />
one of direction autocratically being decided by the Federal<br />
Parliament. AINDREW POTTER: ABC.<br />
Mr. Fraser, you said earlier in answer to a question on the<br />
Cabinet that there were one or two precedent which Mr. Whitlam<br />
had set and you are prepared to follow, are you referring to<br />
Mr. Whitlama's practice of setting up an inner Cabinet of one or<br />
two and setting aside the actual portfolios of your own Cabinet? </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Luncheon" 33.<br />
MR. FRASER:<br />
Almost certainly not. The Only precedent that I was referring<br />
to, and my memory might be faulIty and somebody here can correct<br />
me if it was, was that he did not announce the names of his<br />
Ministers or anything of that kind, and I think also the actual.<br />
structure of that Government until after the election day, and<br />
that was the precedent that I was going to follow. That questioni<br />
of there are fifteen Ministers now. I think the question of<br />
the two man junket was one of the worst disasters that Australia<br />
has ever seen.<br />
ALAN FITZGERALD: 2CA<br />
After Saturday, will you be officially leading a Federal<br />
Government, a Commonwealth Government or an Australian Government<br />
and can we look forward to seeing your po-rtrait replacing Mr.<br />
Whitlam's on the walls of government offices? If not, whose<br />
portrait will appear?<br />
MR. FRASER<br />
I'm afraid, whether it is a joy or not, will depend on the<br />
person's political affiliations. Anyway, for those who might<br />
regard it as a joy, I am going to deny it to them. My photograph<br />
will not appear in Commonwealth, Australian or Federal Government<br />
offices, whichever you like to use, nor will Mr. Whitlams. I<br />
would not want people to read some wrong implications into what<br />
I am going to say because I do believe Australia needs a national<br />
song that captures the minds and hearts of all Australians. But<br />
the appropriate portrait in such places is the portrait of the<br />
Queen. </p>
<p>8/ 12/ 75 " Press Club Liuncheon" 34.<br />
LAURIE OAIBS: I1elbourne Sun.<br />
You said earlier -that specif ic details of your arb.-infJlation<br />
policy had been gien all around the country during this campaign.<br />
A few people seem not to have got the message. Peter Sheehan of<br />
the Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic Research said the other<br />
day that if you implemented your policies, inflation would soar to<br />
205. Ken Davidson, one of Australia's most respected economic<br />
writers has said that the only way you can manage the economy properly<br />
is to chasten your promises, and Alan Wood w. ho writes most of the<br />
Sydney Morning Herald's economic leaders, has said that your policy<br />
is a politician's dream but an economic impossibility. Si r, for the<br />
benefit of those three people who have not got. the message and most of<br />
the journalists who have also been covering this campaign, have also<br />
seemed to hiave missed it, will you again repeat for us the specific<br />
details of your anti-inflation policy?<br />
MR. FROSE:<br />
The extent to which we are prepared to go and the details to which I<br />
am prepared to go have already been covered in answers to questions<br />
today and the policy speech is available. There is going to be<br />
rigorous planning to see that there are economies, that extravagances<br />
are cut out and in a budget as large as the Commonwealth budget is,<br />
that can be quite a significant sum. And we start plann ing from<br />
Sunday for the budget next year and the incentives, encouragement to<br />
industry which is essential if there is going to be investment, and if<br />
there are going to be jobs is again something that gets introduced at<br />
a rate which is compatible with the overall objective of restraining<br />
inflation and at the same time will be measured by the rate at which<br />
we can reign in the extravagance of the Labor Government. You kniow,<br />
its a little bit like this is maybe a nasty comment but the question </p>
<p>FI-/ 2<br />
XI<br />
V1* " Press Club Lunchecn,'<br />
MR. FRASER COITTII'JING:<br />
was really very much like the ABC intor-.-i.; the _ 3C on the<br />
current political climate and that so: yetz oCuT, or journalists<br />
interviewing journalists. If I could cr r. J: e one comment which I<br />
saw in I am not quite sure which of th c cnomic professionals used<br />
this comment and I would not want to al-n the two who did not use<br />
it really to say that the Wag-a by-cloec-on has got some relevance<br />
to our economic policy is sheer and ahaolute nonsense.<br />
MAX HAWKINS;<br />
Mr. Fraser, we regret that we have to cloze. You have fulfilled<br />
your obligations to answer over time the questions, as your speech<br />
went slightly over time. It is in the club's interests that we<br />
be impartial and accord equal tiie to all our speakers, particularly<br />
in the political forum and on behalf of our members and their guests,<br />
I want to thankJc you for speaking to us today, and to ask them to show<br />
their appreciation in the usual manner.<br />
8/ 12/ 75 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
