<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3416</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE FEDERAL CONFERENCE OF THE FEDERATED MISCELLANEOUS WORKERS&#039; UNION OF AUSTRALIA, DICKSON HOTEL, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003416.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>93D~<br />SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E. G. WHITLAM, M. P. 1<br />AT THE OPENING OF THE FEDERAL CONFERENCE OF THE FEDERATED<br />MISCELLANEOUS WORKERS' UNION OF AUSTRALIA,<br />DICKSON HOTEL, CANBERRA, 14 OCTOBER 1974<br />I WELCOME THIS OPPORTUNITY, SO SOON AFTER RETURNING<br />To AUSTRALIA, TO COMMENT DIRECTLY ON SOME OF THE BASIC<br />ISSUES WHICH HAVE BEEN DEBATED IN AUSTRALIA IN THE LAST TWO<br />WEEKS. I HAVE OF COURSE BEEN IN CLOSE TOUCH WITH<br />DEVELOPMENTS AD DECISIONS AFFECTING'THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY<br />WHILE TRAVELLING OVERSEAS. IMAKE THAT POINT BECAUSE<br />OUR OPPONENTS AND SOME SECTIONS OF THE PRESS HAVE TRIED<br />TO SPREAD THE IDEA THAT BECAUSE OVER THE LAST TWO WEEKS<br />IHAVE ADDRESSED THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF THE UNITED NATIONS.-<br />HAD DISCUSSIONS WITH THE NEW PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES<br />AND THE RE-ELECTED PRIME MINISTER OF CANADA-AND ATTENDED THE<br />SOUTH PACIFIC CONFERENCE, THE Fiji CENTENNIAL AND THE<br />NORFOLK ISLAND BICENTENNIAL. THEN SOMEHOW I HAVE BEEU OUT<br />OF TOUCH WITH AUSTRALIA AND INDIFFERENT TO DEVELOPMENTS<br />AT HOME. IDO NOT NEED TO LABOUR THE ABSURDITY OF THIS<br />ARGUMENT. IMERELY SAY THAT IN MY ABSENCE MY COLLEAGUES<br />AND I HAVE CONSULTED AND WORKED TOGETHER. ICOMMEND THE ACTIONS<br />THEY HAVE TAKEN, THE DECISIONS WE HAVE TAKEN TOGETHER.-<br />AS A GOVERNMENT, AS A TEAM. mi. / 2</p>
<p>-2-<br />I REAFFIRM MY COMPLETE CONFIDENCE IN THE STABILITY<br />OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, MY COLLEAGUES ACTED DECISIVELY<br />TO DEMONSTRATE THAT OUR FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS SUCH AS BANKS<br />AND BUILDING SOCIETIES ARE SOLID AS A ROCK, I BASE MY<br />CONFIDENCE ON THE FUNDAMENTAL SOUNDNESS OF OUR ECONOMY<br />ON THE STRENGTH OF OUR NATURAL RESOURCES AND THE CONTINUING<br />ECONOMIC PROGRAM OF THE GOVERNMENT, TODAY I SHALL REFER<br />DIRECTLY AND FRANKLY TO THE PROBLEMS WHICH ARE FOUND IN<br />SOME DEGREE IN THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, FIRST, HOWEVER,<br />I UTTERLY REJECT THE WARPED ATTITUDE OF THE OPPOSITION IN<br />SEEKING TO MISREPRESENT AND EXAGGERATE THE PROBLEMS WE<br />FACE, FIDAMENTALLY THE GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAMS IN THE FIELDS<br />OF EDUCATION, HEALTH AND TRANSPORT, AND THE GOVERNMENT'S<br />DETERMINATION TO MAINTAIN EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES, MEAN<br />THAT AUSTRALIANS CAN LOOK FORWARD TO A CONTINUING AND<br />IMPROVING HIGH STANDARD OF LIVING, OUR OPPONENTS, FOR<br />SELFISH POLITICAL REASONS, REJOICE IN CREATING AN ATMOSPHERE<br />OF PANIC, CONFUSION AND RUMOUR-MONGERING, THEY PREACH<br />ABOUT A LACK OF CONFIDENCE, YET NOTHING DOES MORE -TO<br />DESTROY CONFIDENCE THAN THEIR OWN INCESSANT PROPHESIES OF<br />DOOM AND DISASTER, LET US REJECT THESE MERCHANTS OF GLOOM<br />AND THEIR MESSAGE OF DESPAIR, THESE NAGGING AND NEGATIVE<br />MEN HAVE NOTHING TO OFFER US IN OUR PRESENT DIFFICULTIES, / 3</p>
<p>-3-<br />I EXPRESS MY CONCERN NOT MORBID PESSIMISM, BUT<br />A FRANK AND REALISTIC CONCERN ABOUT THE NUMBER OF AUSTRALIANS<br />REGISTERED AS UNEMPLOYED. ON THIS ISSUE I EMPHASISE WITH<br />ALL THE FORCE AT MY COMMAND THAT THE GOVERNMENT REJECTS THE<br />CONSERVATIVE PHILOSOPHY WHICH SAYS THAT MASSIVE<br />UNEMPLOYMENT SHOULD DELIBERATELY BE CREATED AS A DEVICE<br />FOR SLOWING DOWN THE RATE OF INFLATION. IN MANAGING THE<br />ECONOMY THE GOVERNMENT CONTINUES TO PURSUE THE GOAL OF<br />FULL EMPLOYKENT. ALL OF US WHO ARE INVOLVED IN<br />CONSIDERING THESE NATIONAL ISSUES SHOULD ACKNOWLEDGE THAT<br />IT IS NO SIMPLE MATTER, GIVEN INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC<br />FORCES, TO SECURE BOTH FULL EMPLOYMENT AND ALSO A LOW<br />INFLATION RATE. OUR OPPONENTS PRETENDe QUITE DISHONESTLY,<br />AND IN THE FACE OF EXPERIENCE IN OTHER COUNTRIES WITH.<br />ECONOMIES SIMILAR TO OUR OWN, THAT THE LIBERAL PARTY ALONE<br />HAS A MAGIC FORMULA TO ACHIEVE THIS GOAL. MY MEETINGS<br />WITH WORLD LEADERS HAVE SHOWN ME JUST HOW COMPLEX, HOW<br />UNIVERSAL, HOW DIFFICULT THIS PROBLEM is. No ONE HAS<br />FOUND A SOLUTION EXCEPT THE LEADER OF THE OPPOSITLON IN<br />AUSTRALIA, AND MRWII WJINI MdAHON. I AM GLAD TO SEE THAT<br />MR MCMAHON HAS EMERGED AS CHIEF LIBERAL SPOKESMAN ON<br />THE ECONOMY-WITH THE EXCEPTION OF O-IS LEADER HE KNOWS<br />MORE* ABOUT ECONOMIC MISMANAGEMENT THAN ANYONE IN AUSTRALIA.<br />THEIR EXPERIENCE IS UNRIVALLED. THEY ARE THE ARCHITECTS<br />OF THE TWO MOST DISASTROUS BUDGETS IN RECENT HISTORY.<br />BETWEEN THEM THEY CREATED THE CONDITIONS WHICH HAVE LED TO<br />OUR PRESENT INFLATION. YOU DON'T HAVE TO TAKE MY WORD ' FOR<br />IT. I GIVE YOU THIS QUOTATION FROM AN EDITORIAL IN OUR<br />LEADING ECONOMIC JOURNAL, THE " AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW".<br />iss/ 4</p>
<p>L4f r -u /; iA/<br />THIS IS WHAT THE " FINANCIAL REVIEW" HAD TO SAY/ ABOUT<br />THE RECORD OF OUR TWO CHIEF DOOM-SAYERS:<br />" THE MCMAHON GOVERNMENT... FOR ELECTORAL REASONS,<br />PROMOTED A RATE OF MONETARY EXPANSION WHICH WAS<br />TOTALLY UNJUSTIFIABLE IN ITS RAPIDITY AND<br />WHICH, WITH THE ACCOMPANYING RATE OF CAPITAL<br />INFLOW, WAS MAINLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE<br />DEMAND INFLATION OF 1972-73 AND THE INEVITABLE<br />CONSEQUENCE OF THE CURRENT COST INFLATION.<br />THIS IS SOMETHING WHICH HAS BEEN SAID OFTEN<br />ENOUGH BEFORE, BUT WHICH SHOULD NOT BE<br />FORGOTTEN IN THE HEAT OF POLITICAL CONTROVERSY..."<br />IN ITS ECONOMIC POLICY THE GOVERNMENT HAS ALREADY<br />INDICATED ITS DETERMINATION TO TAKE IMMEDIATE AND<br />APPROPRIATE ACTION IN ORDER TO MAINTAIN EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES.<br />THE TREASURER'S STATEMENT, MADE WHEN PRESENTING THE BUDGET,<br />SAID THAT " SHOULD THE NEED ARISE, WE STAND READY DURING<br />THE YEAR TO TAKE ACTION ON THE EXPENDITURE OR REVENUE SIDE<br />OF THE BUDGET TO GIVE A QUICK STIMULUS TO DEMAND AND<br />EMPLOYMENT. CRUCIAL AS THE FIGHT AGAINST INFLATION IS,<br />IT CANNOT BE MADE THE SOLE OBJECTIVE OF GOVERNMENT POLICY.<br />THIS GOVERNMENT IS COMMITTED TO THE PROGRAM OF SOCIAL<br />REFORM TO IMPROVE THE POSITION OF THE LESS PRIVILEGED<br />GROUPS IN OUR SOCIETY AND TO MAINTAIN EMPLOYMENT<br />OPPORTUNITIES." -4-</p>
<p>THE ALTERATION IN THE EXCHANGE RATE WHICH WE<br />MADE ON 25 SEPTEMBER WAS ONE IMPORTANT EXAMPLE OF OUR<br />WILLINGNESS TO BE FLEXIBLE AND RESPOND TO DEVELOPMENTS IN<br />THE ECONOMY. THE GOVERNMENT SHOWED BY THAT ACTION ITS<br />SENSITIVITY TO THE CLIMATE IN WHICH BUSINESS OPERATES.<br />THE NEW EXCHANGE RATE WILL ASSIST IN RESTORING THE GENERAL<br />LEVEL OF BUSINESS ACTIVITY AND IN MAINTAINING<br />EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES. THE EASING OF CREDIT WILL HAVE<br />THE SAME EFFECT. I EMPHASISE OUR UNDERTAKING THAT ANY<br />AVOIDABLE TENDENCY FOR UNEMPLOYMENT TO INCREASE WILL BE<br />CHECKED BY GOVERNMENT ACTION. IN ITS POLICIES TO REDUCE<br />INFLATION AND MAINTAIN EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES, THE<br />GOVERNMENT NEEDS THE ACTIVE COOPERATION OF TRADE UNIONS,<br />EMPLOYERS AND STATE GOVERNMENTS. I BELIEVE THE<br />AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE EXPECT THAT COOPERATION AND WILL BE<br />MAKING THEIR JUDGMENTS ACCORDINGLY.<br />SOME AUSTRALIANS MAY FIND THE CURRENT PUBLIC<br />DEBATE ON IMPORTANT POLICY ISSUES DISTURBING BECAUSE MOST<br />OF US WANT LIFE TO GO ON SMOOTHLY AND WITHOUT ANY PROBLEMS.<br />HOWEVER, SOME OF THE CURRENT DEBATE AND DISCUSSION ON POLICY<br />ISSUES IS NECESSARY BECAUSE OF THE VERY REAL COMPLEXITY OF<br />THE RELATED MATTERS OF COUNTERING INFLATION, MAINTAINING<br />EMPLOYMENT LEVELS, AND CONTINUING THE GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAM.<br />,/ 6</p>
<p>BECAUSE THE POLICIES NEEDED TO COUNTER BOTH<br />INFLATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT ARE COMPLEX IN THEIR RELATIONSHIP<br />TO EACH OTHER THE GOVERNMENT IS USING A NUMBER OF DEVICES<br />TO ACHIEVE ITS ENDS. IN SPEAKING ABOUT MEASURES TO<br />MAINTAIN THE LEVEL OF EMPLOYMENT WE CAN LIST THE<br />FOLLOWING ACTIONS:<br />FIRST, WE HAVE THE REGIONAL EMPLOYMENT DEVELOPMENT<br />SCHEME WHICH IS DESIGNED TO IMPROVE EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES<br />IN CERTAIN GEOGRAPHICAL AREAS WHERE UNEMPLOYMENT EXISTS.<br />THE SCHEME WILL ENCOURAGE LOCAL INITIATIVES IN SUCH AREAS.<br />THE RELEVANT LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITY, FOR EXAMPLE,. WILL<br />BE ENCOURAGED TO SUGGEST SUITABLE LABOUR-INTENSIVE WORK<br />PROGRAMS WHICH WILL HELP BUILD UP PUBLIC FACILITIES-IN<br />THE AREAS CONCERNED.<br />SECONDLY, THE NATIONAL EMPLOYMENT AND TRAINING<br />SYSTEM WILL PROVIDE COMPREHENSIVE TRAINING AND RETRAINING<br />SCHEMES. IN THE DETAILS ALREADY ANNOUNCED THE GOVERNMENT<br />HAS SAID THAT IT WILL GIVE PRIORITY TO THOSE SEEKING<br />RETRAINING BECAUSE OF TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE IN INDUSTRY<br />OR BECAUSE OF GOVERNMENT POLICIES SUCH AS THE ACTION LAST<br />YEAR IN REDUCING TARIFF LEVELS BY 25 PER CENT. THE<br />MINISTER FOR LABOUR IS INTRODUCING THIS TRAINING SYSTEM<br />AS FAST AS POSSIBLE. REMEMBER THAT WE HAVE HAD TO SET UP<br />A COMPREHENSIVE NATIONAL RETRAINING SYSTEM VIRTUALLY<br />FROM NOTHING BECAUSE THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT DID NOTHING<br />IN THIS FIELD IN ITS 23 YEARS OF OFFICE. a/ 7</p>
<p>-7-<br />THIRDLY, ANY PEOPLE WHO LOST THEIR JOBS EITHER<br />DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY BECAUSE OF THE GOVERNMENT'S TARIFF<br />CHANGES CAN BENEFIT FROM A RANGE OF ADJUSTMENT ASSISTANCE<br />MEASURES, FOURTHLY, IN A MORE WIDE-RANGING APPROACH, THE<br />BUDGET SHOWED THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO MAINTAIN<br />EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES THROUGHOUT THE COMMUNITY, I HAVE<br />ALREADY EMPiASISED THAT THE GOVERNMENT STANDS READY TO<br />TAKE FURTHER STEPS TO ENSURE CONTINUED PROGRESS IN<br />BUILDING UP EMPLOYMENT,<br />FIFTHLY, THE CHANGE IN THE EXCHANGE RATE, RECENTLY<br />ANNOUNCED, IS A PARTICULAR MEASURE WHICH WILL HELP TO PROTECT<br />EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES BY IMPROVING THE COMPETITIVE<br />POSITION IN THE AUSTRALIAN MARKET OF INDUSTRIES COMPETING WITH<br />IMPORTS AND THE COMPETITIVE POSITION ON OVERSEAS MARKETS OF<br />AUSTRALIA'S EXPORT INDUSTRIES,<br />IN REAFFIRMING MY CONFIDENCE IN THE LONG-TERM<br />BASIC STRENGTH OF THE ECONOMY I AGAIN DECLARE THAT THE<br />GOVERNMENT CANNOT AND WILL NOT BE DETERRED FROM THE PROGRAM<br />WHICH THE PEOPLE TWICE ELECTED US TO CARRY OUT, WE MUST<br />OVERCOME THE PROBLEM OF OVERCROWDED AND INSUFFICIENTLY<br />STAFFED SCHOOLS A SITUATION INHERITED AFTER A GENERATION<br />OF NEGLECT BY THE LIBERAL PARTY, 1 ,/ 8<br />I</p>
<p>-8-<br />IN AUSTRALIA THE WELL-TO-DO HAVE READY ACCESS TO<br />SOPHISTICATED HEALTH SERVICES WHICH PEOPLE ON MIDDLE AND<br />LOWER INCOMES MAY OFTEN BE DENIED, OUR OPPONENTS ARE<br />COMPLACENT ABOUT SUCH INEQUALITIES IN AUSTRALIAN SOCIETY,<br />THE CONTINUING PROGRAM OF MAJOR REFORM BY THE AUSTRALIAN<br />GOVERNMENT IN THE FIELDS OF EDUCATION, HEALTH, TRANSPORT<br />AND GENERALLY IMPROVING COMMUNITY FACILTIES MEANS THAT<br />GOVERNMENT EXPENDITURES WILL HELP SUSTAIN THE GENERAL<br />LEVEL OF ECONOMIC ACTIVITY, AT A TIME WHEN SOME AREAS IN<br />PRIVATE INDUSTRY ARE PROCEEDING SOMEWHAT CAUTIOUSLY<br />WITH THEIR PLANS FOR DEVELOPMENT AND EXPANSION THIS<br />CONTINUING PROGRAM OF GOVERNMENT ACTION IS OF SPECIAL<br />ADVANTAGE TO THE ECONOMY AS A WHOLE,<br />To KEEP OUR PRESENT DIFFICULTIES IN PERSPECTIVE,<br />IT IS USEFUL TO MAKE SOME COMPARISONS BETWEEN THE AUSTRALIAN<br />EXPERIENCE AND EXPERIENCES IN OTHER COUNTRIES, WE CAN<br />LOOK AT THE RATE OF INFLATION IN THE 24 COUNTRIES WHO ARE<br />MEMBERS OF THE ORGANISATION FOR ECONOMIC COOPERATION AND<br />DEVELOPMENT( OECD), IN 1961-71 THE AVERAGE RATE OF INFLATION<br />IN THESE 24 COUNTRIES WAS 3,7 PER CENT, IN 1972 THE<br />AVERAGE RATE OF INFLATION IN THE OECD COUNTRIES WAS 4.7<br />PER CENT AND IN 1973 IT ROSE TO 7,7 PER CENT, AT THE PRESENT<br />TIMEt TAKING THE YEAR TO AUGUST 1974, THE AVERAGE RATE OF<br />INFLATION IN THE OECD COUNTRIES IS 13.4 PER CENT, THE<br />ANNUAL RATE IN AUSTRALIA AS INDICATED BY THE MOST RECENT<br />QUARTERLY FIGURES IS 14,4 PER CENT,</p>
<p>-9-<br />IN OTHER WORDS, IN 24 COUNTRIES ALL AROUND THE WORLD,<br />INCLUDING ECONOMIES VERY SIMILAR TO AUSTRALIA, THERE HAS<br />BEEN A STRONG TENDENCY FOR THE RATE OF INFLATION TO<br />INCREASE, EVEN THE MOST NEUROTIC OPPONENTS OF THE<br />GOVERNMENT WILL CONCEDE THAT THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />DOES NOT CONTROL THE ECONOMIES OF THE USA,, CANADA, THE<br />UNITED KINGDOM AND THE OTHER MEMBER COUNTRIES OF THE OECD.<br />ALL THAT HAS HAPPENED IS THAT THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY IN<br />ITS CHANGE IN PRICE LEVELS HAS HAD AN EXPERIENCE SIMILAR<br />TO THAT OF MOST OTHER COUNTRIES,<br />LOOKING AT THE QUESTION OF UNEMPLOYMENT IN<br />TERMS OF INTERNATIONAL COMPARISONS IS NOT A SIMPLE MATTER<br />BECAUSE OF THE DIFFERENT DEFINITIONS OF UNEMPLOYMENT IN<br />VARIOUS COUNTRIES, HOWEVER, WE CAN NOTE THAT IN BROAD<br />TERMS WE HAVE IN THE UNITED STATES AND IN CANADA OFFICIAL<br />UNEMPLOYMENT FIGURES WHICH ARE ABOVE FIVE PER CENT COMPARED<br />WITH THE AUSTRALIAN FIGURE FOR SEPTEMBER 1974 OF JUST<br />OVER TWO PER CENT, I AM NOT SAYING THAT WE SHOULD REST<br />EASY MERELY BECAUSE THE ECONOMIES OF THE UNITED STATES AND<br />CANADA ARE SUFFERING FROM AN UNEMPLOYMENT RATE WHICH IS<br />MUCH WORSE THAN OUR OWN.</p>
<p>UNLIKE OUR OPPONENTS WE DO NOT REGARD ANY INCREASE IN<br />UNEMPLOYMENT AS " ACCEPTABLE OR " TOLERABLE" I iEWSPAPERS<br />HAVE RECORDED THE ECONOMIC DIFFICULTIES OF THESE COUNTRIES<br />AND ALSO THE ECONOMIC PROBLEMS FACING BRITAIN. ALL I AM<br />SAYING IS THAT THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, IN WHICH<br />INTERNATIONAL TRADE PLAYS A SIGNIFICANT PARTI IS INEVITABLY<br />AFFECTED BY SOME OF THE ADVERSE FORCES WHICH ARE FOUND<br />IN THE ECONOMIES OF VARIOUS OVERSEAS COUNTRIES,<br />ALL IN ALL WE CAN SAY THAT AUSTRALIANS WHILE<br />TACKLING THEIR OWN ECONOMIC PROBLEMS, SHOULD REMEMBER THAT<br />THEIR STANDARD OF LIVING AND THE GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAM'FOR<br />A BETTER LIFE FOR EVERY FAMILY COMPARE VERY WELLI NOT<br />JUST WITH DEVELOPING COUNTRIES IN OUR REGION, BUT WITH<br />THE STANDARD OF LIVING IN MOST OTHER WESTERN ECONOMIES,<br />THERE IS A SEPARATE AND FUNDAMENTAL ISSUE WHICH<br />OUR OPPONENTS WOULD LIKE TO OBSCURE, IN THEIR CRITICISM<br />OF THE GOVERNMENT THE OPPOSITION IS ASKING THE PUBLIC TO<br />ACCEPT THAT THE PERSONAL INCOME OF THE FAMILY MAN IS ALL<br />THAT MATTERS, AND CAN BE CONSIDERED IN ISOLATION FROM<br />EVERYTHING ELSE THAT HAPPENS TO HIM AND TO HIS FAMILY,<br />AN AUSTRALIAN FAMILY DEPENDS ON ESSENTIAL COMMUNITY SERVICES<br />TO MEET ITS NEEDS, IN ADDITION TO THE NEEDS WHICH IT<br />FULFILS FOR ITSELF FROM ITS OWN DIRECT INCOME, ,/ ii</p>
<p>-11-<br />TAXES PAID BY ORDINARY AUSTRALIANS ARE NOT BEING FED<br />INTO SOME MYSTERIOUS MACHINE IN CANBERRA WHICH IS<br />OPERATED FOR THE SOLE BENEFIT OF THE WHITLAM GOVERNMENT,<br />THE GOVERNMENT HAS NO INCOME OR PURPOSES WHICH ARE<br />SEPARATE FROM THOSE OF THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY,<br />AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS, THROUGH THEIR TAXES, ARE PROVIDING<br />THE FUNDS TO PAY FOR THE ESSENTIAL COMMUNITY SERVICES<br />WHICH ARE NECESSARY IN A MODERN ADVANCING COUNTRY,<br />IN ADDITION TO THE GOVERNMENT'S CONCERN THAT WAGE AND<br />SALARY EARNERS SHOULD CONTINUE TO IMPROVE THEIR TAKE-HOME<br />PAY, THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY HAS DECIDED THAT ESSENTIAL<br />COMMUNITY SERVICES MUST BE PROVIDED AND MUST BE IMPROVED,<br />THE GOVERNMENT REJECTS THE IDEA THAT EVERY CITIZEN SHOULD<br />BE ENTIRELY SELF-CENTRED IN THE WAY HE DISPOSES OF HIS<br />INCOME AND IN HIS RELATIONSHIP TO THE WIDER COMMUNITY,<br />WE REJECT THE NOTION OF " EVERY MAN FOR HIMSELF", BECAUSE<br />THIS ATTITUDE WAS ENCOURAGED BY THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT<br />WE HAVE STILL IN MANY PARTS OF AUSTRALIA NEGLECTED SCHOOLS,<br />INEFFECTIVE HEALTH SERVICES, HOPELESSLY INADEQUATE<br />AND UNCORDINATED SYSTEMS OF PUBLIC TRANSPORT, A HUGH<br />BACKLOG OF UNSEWERED HOUSES AND ALL THE PROBLEMS OF<br />OVERCROWDING IN OUR MAIN CITIES, To ANY REASONABLE PERSON<br />IT MUST BE CLEAR THAT PROVIDING ESSENTIAL COMMUNITY<br />SERVICES IS NOT SOMETHING WHICH CAN BE DONE IN JUST A YEAR<br />OR TWO, PARTICULARLY AFTER 23 YEARS OF COMPLACENT NEGLECT,<br />OUR OPPONENTS WANT THE ORDINARY AUSTRALIAN TO THINK ONLY<br />OF WHAT HE PAYS IN TAXES AND TO NEGLECT THE GIANT STRIDES<br />THAT HAVE BEEN TAKEN BY THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT SINCE<br />BEING ELECTED IN DECEMBER 1972, / 12</p>
<p>-12-<br />THE BUDGET FOR 1974/ 75 ANNOUNCED AN EXPENDITURE<br />ON EDUCATION OF $ 1,535 MILLION, AN INCREASE OF 78 PER CENT<br />ON THE PREVIOUS YEAR, HEALTH EXPENDITURE ROSE BY<br />21 PER CENT IN 1973/ 74 AND ' IS SET TO RISE BY $ 285 MILLION<br />OR 30 PER CENT THIS YEAR, OUR EXPENDITURE ON SOCIAL<br />SECURITY AND WELFARE AMOUNTS TO NEARLY ONE QUARTER OF<br />BUDGET OUTLAYS AND IS EXPECTED TO REACH $ 3,441,5 MILLION<br />THIS YEARI AN INCREASE OF 38,3 PER CENT OVER LAST YEAR,<br />WHICH WAS ITSELF WELL UP ON THE PREVIOUS YEAR, OUTLAYS<br />ON HOUSING ARE SET TO REACH A RECORD $ 401 MILLION THIS<br />YEAR, COMPARED WITH $ 77 MILLION SPENT BY OUR PREDECESSORS<br />IN THEIR LAST YEAR IN OFFICE, EXPENDITURE ON URBAN<br />IMPROVEMENTS AND THE ENVIRONMENT WILL ALMOST REACH<br />$ 400 MILLION, A THREE-FOLD INCREASE ON LAST YEAR AND<br />EIGHT TIMES THE AMOUNT SPENT BY OUR PREDECESSORS IN<br />1972/ 73, WE HAVE ALSO TAKEN IMPORTANT STEPS IN IMPROVING<br />PUBLIC TRANSPORT, WATER SUPPLY AND ELECTRICITY, RETRAINING,<br />REGIONAL EMPLOYMENT AND IN NATIONAL COMPENSATION AND<br />REHABILIATION SCHEMES,<br />WHILE THIS LIST IS OBVIOUSLY NOT AN EXHAUSTIVE<br />STATEMENT I WOULD EMPHASISE THAT THESE PROGRAMS ALL SERVE<br />TO CHANNEL RESOURCES INTO AREAS OF MOST BENEFIT TO LOW<br />AND MIDDLE INCOME GROUPS, / 13</p>
<p>-13-<br />THE CHANGES IN THE PERSONAL INCOME TAX SCALE<br />ANNOUNCED IN THE BUDGET WILL LEAD TO A FURTHER IMPROVEMENT<br />IN THE REAL INCOME AND LIVING CONDITIONS OF WAGE AND<br />SALARY EARNERS, PARTICULARLY THOSE IN LOWER INCOME<br />BRACKETS, TO THE ORDINARY'AUSTRALIAN TAXPAYER, TO THOSE<br />WHO NEED PERSUASION ON THIS ISSUE, I MAKE AN OBVIOUS<br />POINT: THE HEALTH CENTRES, HOSPITALS, SCHOOLS, BETTER<br />TRANSPORT AND ALL THE OTHER ESSENTIAL COMMUNITY SERVICES<br />DO COST LARGE SUMS OF MONEY, THIS IS ALL THE MORE TRUE<br />AS THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT SETS OUT WITH DETERMINATION<br />TO MAKE UP FOR THE HOSTILITY AND NEGLECT WHICH OUR<br />PREDECESSORS SHOWED TOWARDS THESE COMMUNITY SERVICES,<br />WHO WOULD DENY HEALTH CARE AND A GOOD EDUCATION TO THE<br />CHILDREN OF AUSTRALIA? THIS IS A PERFECTLY FAIR QUESTION<br />BECAUSE THIS IS PRECISELY WHAT WOULD BE DENIED TO THE<br />CHILDREN OF AUSTRALIA IF THE FORMER REGIME HAD ITS WAY,<br />ALTHOUGH THEY TRY TO HIDE WHAT THEY ARE REALLY SAYING IT IS<br />NOTHING LESS THAN A PROPOSITION THAT THE AVERAGE AUSTRALIAN<br />FAMILY SHOULD " MAKE DO" AND SHOULD PUT UP WITH CROWDED<br />SCHOOLS, AN OVER-WORKED AND INEFFICIENT HEALTH SYSTEM,<br />CHAOTIC TRANSPORT SYSTEMS, POLLUTION OF THE ENVIRONMENT<br />AND THE OTHER EVILS WHICH FOLLOW IF YOU NEGLECT OUR<br />COMMUNITY SERVICES, I AM SURE MY MESSAGE IS PERFECTLY CLEAR,<br />1 ,/ 14</p>
<p>-14-<br />WHAT THE GOVERNMENT WANTS TO GET ACROSS TO THE PEOPLE<br />IS THIS BASIC IDEA: A DECENT AND IMPROVING STANDARD<br />OF LIVING IS NOT MERELY OBTAINED BY CHASING A HIGHER<br />LEVEL OF PERSONAL INCOME. A DECENT WAY OF LIVING<br />AND CONTINUING IMPROVEMENTS IN THE STANDARD OF LIVING<br />FOR ALL AUSTRALIAN FAMILIES IS ACHIEVED, IN FACT, IN<br />TWO WAYS: BY STEADY IMPROVEMENTS IN THE PURCHASING POWER<br />OF OUR PERSONAL INCOMES AD BY THE USE OF MODERN<br />COMMUNITY SERVICES WHICH MEET THE REAL NEEDS OF THE PEOPLE,<br />IT IS TRUE THAT RAPID PROGRESS IN HEALTH AND<br />EDUCATION AND OTHER AREAS IS MADE MORE DIFFICULT BY CERTAIN<br />CURRENT ECONOMIC PROBLEMS, WHEN, EARLIER IN THIS SPEECH,<br />I ASSESSED THE AUSTRALIAN SITUATION AND MADE SOME<br />REASONABLE INTERNATIONAL COMPARISONS, I WAS IN EFFECT<br />EXPRESSING MY AGREEMENT WITH THE OPENING LINES OF THE<br />RESOLUTION CARRIED BY THE MEETING OF ACTU UNIONS IN<br />SYDNEY ON 24 SEPTEMBER, THE ACTU RESOLUTION SAID THAT<br />" THE TWO PROBLEMS OF INCREASING INFLATION AND RISING<br />UNEMPLOYMENT ARE NOT UNIQUE TO AUSTRALIA". MY GOVERNMENT<br />WAS HEARTENED BY THE FACT THAT THE ACTU CONFERENCE OF<br />UNIONS EXPRESSED " ITS GENERAL SUPPORT FOR THE SOCIAL<br />CONCEPTS AND ECONOMIC STRATEGY CONTAINED IN THE BUDGET<br />IN 1974/ 75", IN RELATION TO WHAT I HAVE SAID ABOUT THE<br />IMPORTANCE OF PROVIDING COMMUNITY SERVICES THE GOVERNMENT<br />ALSO WELCOMES THE ACTU SUPPORT FOR WHAT IT DESCRIBED AS<br />" THE SIGNIFICANTLY INCREASED OUTLAYS UPON EDUCATION.<br />HEALTH, WELFARE AND URBAN AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT</p>
<p>THE ACTU RESOLUTION STATED CERTAIN POLICY GOALS<br />OF THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT, WE DO NOT FIND THE LISTING<br />OF THOSE POLICY AIMS STRANGE OR SOMETHING WHICH NEED CAUSE<br />DISAGREEMENT WITH THE GOVERNMENT, IT IS PART OF THE<br />TRADITION OF THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT THAT IT SHOULD<br />IDENTIFY THE IDEALS AND THE POLICIES WHICH IN THE FUTURE<br />WILL SERVE THE NEEDS OF THEIR MEMBERS,. THESE PROPOSALS<br />AND THE GOVERNMENT'S OWN ECONOMIC POLICY ARE TO BE<br />DISCUSSED AT A MEETING BETWEEN THE ACTU AND THE<br />GOVERNMENT, THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES IN THE PRINCIPLE<br />OF CONSULTATION WITH COMMUNITY ORGANISATIONS AND<br />ON THE SUBJECT OF PAY FIXATION AND ECONOMIC POLICY IT<br />IS RELEVANT FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO HAVE DISCUSSIONS<br />WITH THE ACTU. THE GOVERNMENT IN THE SAME WAY HAS<br />CONSULTED, AND WILL CONTINUE TO CONSULT, WITH<br />EMPLOYER ORGANISATIONS, PRIMARY PRODUCERS AND OTHER<br />BODIES EXPRESSING A WHOLE RANGE OF VIEWS WITHIN THE<br />AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY, / 16</p>
<p>-16-<br />THE DISCUSSIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND TRADE<br />UNION SPOKESMEN WHICH ARE PRINCIPALLY TAKING PLACE UNDER<br />THE CHAIRMANSHIP OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE ARBITRATION<br />COMMISSION, MR JUSTICE MOORE, WILL BE COVERING THE EXACT<br />DETAILS OF WAGE INDEXATION AND OTHER ASPECTS OF PAY FIXATION.<br />HOWEVER, I WANT TO TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO CLEAR UP A<br />COMMON MISUNDERSTANDING ABOUT THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY ON WAGES<br />AND SALARIES. I SPEAK NOW TO ALL OF AUSTRALIA'S WAGE AND<br />SALARY EARNERS-AND I SAY TO THEM THATTHE OBJECT OF THE<br />GOVERNMENT'S POLICY OF RESTRAINT IN THE GROWTH OF WAGES AND<br />OTHER INCOMES IS TO SLOW DOWN THE EXCESSIVE AND SELF-DEFEATING<br />ESCALATION OF MONEY INCOMES. THE GOVERNMENT NEVER INTENDS<br />NOR EXPECTS ANY REDUCTION IN THE PURCHASING POWER OF WAGES.<br />ON THE CONTRARY, THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT A SLOWER GROWTH<br />IN MONEY INCOMES WOULD ENHANCE THE PROSPECTS FOR FASTER GROWTH<br />IN REAL WAGES AND IN LIVING STANDARDS.<br />As I HAVE SAID, PROPOSALS ON PAY FIXATION ARE BEING<br />CONSIDERED BY THE CONFERENCE BEING CHAIRED BY MR JUSTICE MOORE.<br />THE GOVERNMENT IS REPRESENTED IN THAT CONFERENCE AND WILL MAKE<br />A CONSTRUCTIVE CONTRIBUTION TO PROMOTE AGREEMENT BETWEEN ALL<br />THE PARTIES. THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECLARED ITS SUPPORT FOR<br />QUARTERLY COST OF LIVING ADJUSTMENTS, COMMONLY DESCRIBED TODAY<br />AS INDEXATION, IN THE BELIEF THAT SUCH ARRANGEMENTS, AS PART OF<br />A PACKAGE, WILL HELP TO RESTRAIN THE EXCESSIVE GROWTH IN MONEY<br />WAGES TO WHICH I REFERRED WITHOUT DEPRIVING WAGE EARNERS OF THE<br />PROGRESSIVE IMPROVEMENT OF REAL EARNINGS MADE POSSIBLE BY RISING<br />NATIONAL PRODUCTIVITY.</p>
<p>-17-<br />I TURN NOW TO SOME REMARKS WITH PARTICULAR RELEVANCE<br />TO YOUR OWN ORGANISATION, PLEASE LET ME SAY THAT I WELCOME<br />THE OPPORTUNITY TO BE WITH YOU AT THE TIME OF YOUR FEDERAL<br />CONFERENCE, I AM VERY MUCH AWARE OF THE SUPPORT, IN FINANCIAL<br />AND MORAL TERMS, WHICH THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY HAS RECEIVED<br />FROM THE MWU, IN THE YEARS LEADING UP TO OUR WIN IN 1972<br />AND ALSO IN THE PERIOD SINCE THEN,<br />I AM AWARE OF YOUR SUCCESS IN EXTENDING YOUR MEMBERSHIP<br />RULES SO THAT YOUR UNION IS ESTABLISHED IN EFFECT AS BOTH A<br />CRAFT AND AN INDUSTRY ORGANISATION$ YOU HAVE COME A LONG WAY<br />SINCE YOUR ORGANISATION WAS ESTABLISHED IN 1915. You HAVE 13<br />BRANCHES IN ALL AROUND AUSTRALIA AND YOUR UNION HAS ALMOST<br />120 FULL-TIME EMPLOYEES IN THE VARIOUS STATES AND TERRITORIES,<br />YOU HAVE ALREADY ESTABLISHED A REPUTATION AS A MODERN GO-AHEAD<br />TRADE UNION AND THIS IS SHOWN BY YOUR EMPLOYMENT OF 10 RESEARCH<br />OFFICERS, YOUR DIVERSITY IN MEMBERSHIP COVERAGE IS A<br />REFLECTION OF THE FACT THAT YOUR TRADE UNION SERVICES SOME<br />360-AWARDS, DETERMINATIONS AND AGREEMENTS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA.<br />I AM HEARTENED BY THE FACT THAT YOUR UNION, WITH ITS<br />90,000 MEMBERS, HAS ALL ITS BRANCHES AFFILIATED WITH THE<br />AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY, / 18</p>
<p>-18-. I<br />I PAY TRIBUTE TO YOUR SUCCESS IN ENTERING INTO NO<br />FEWER THAN 15 AMALGAMATIONS WITH VARIOUS TRADE UNION BODIES.<br />MY GOVERNMENT HAS SOUGHT TO ENCOURAGE TRADE UNION AMALGAMATION<br />SO THAT DEMARCATION DISPUTES ARE AVOIDED. THERE IS ALSO THE<br />CONSIDERABLE ADVANTAGE FOR EMPLOYEES TO HAVE A LARGE MODERN<br />TRADE UNION WHICH CAN REPRESENT THEM IN AN EXPERT WAY AND<br />WHICH CAN PROVIDE ALL THE SKILLS REQUIRED FOR'THE PROCEDURES<br />OF NEGOTIATION AND ARBITRATION. THE. GOVERNMENT WELCOMES<br />SUPPORT FROM EMPLOYEE ORGANISATIONS SUCH AS YOUR OWN AND FROM<br />MANY OTHER GROUPS IN THE COMMUNITY WHO ARE CONTINUING TO<br />SUPPORT THE PROGRAM OF THE GOVERNMENT.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
