<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5675</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE WORLD HERITAGE COMMITTEE MEETING</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005675.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 10.00 am<br />
j AUSI'ALIA 16<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, OCTOBER 26 1981<br />
OPENING OF THE WORLD HERITAGE COMMITTE MEETINGIt<br />
gives me great pleasure to welcome to Australia the<br />
delegations from the 21 countries which makeup the World<br />
Heritage Committee, and I also welcome the observors who are<br />
attending from a number of other countries.<br />
am advised that some 61 countries have now signed the<br />
World Heritage Convention, and the fact that several countries<br />
have joined in the last few weeks shows that there is growing<br />
acceptance around the world of the aims of the convention.<br />
The doncept of a ' world heritage', which includes both the<br />
cultural and the natural heritage of mankind, and which means<br />
that individual nations will hold sites and properties of<br />
universal value in trust not just for their own peoples, but<br />
for the whole of mankind, is surely a profound expression of<br />
co-operation between people and a willingness to share.<br />
The World Heritage Convention, adopted by UNESCO in 1972, is<br />
an important milestone in the modern history of man's concern<br />
not only for his environment, but also for his cultural roots<br />
and origins. It is impressive that while this is only the<br />
fifth meeting of the World Heritage Committee, there are<br />
already 85 properties and sites listed as measuring up to the<br />
Committee's standards of outstanding universal value.<br />
I hope the World Heritage listing will receive some publicity<br />
in Australia as a result of your meeting here, because our<br />
perspectives as a nation would undoubtedly be broadened through<br />
a wider understanding of these sites and properties.<br />
This particular meeting of the World Heritage Committee has<br />
special significance for Australia, not only because it is<br />
being held here, but also because Australia's first nominations<br />
for the World Heritage list are coming forward, and while these<br />
nominations speak far more strongly for themselves than I<br />
could ever argue for them, I would like to say a word or two<br />
about them, and then to say something about some of our other<br />
environmental and conservation concerns.<br />
One nomination is the Great Barrier Reef. This magnificent maze<br />
of coral banks, reefs and islands, stretching nearly 2,000<br />
kilometres along the coastline of Queensland, has been known<br />
to the world since Captain Cook ran aground there in 1770.<br />
The Capricornia secion of the Great Barrier Reef has already<br />
been established by the Commonwealth Government as a marine<br />
park, and the whole of the reef is fully protected under an<br />
Act of the Comnonwealth Parliament. ,/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
The Commonwealth Government is actively seeking a co-operative<br />
approach with the Queensland government in relation to extending<br />
the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park, and I am sure that this<br />
Committee would appreciate the importance of a co-operative<br />
approach between governments, especially a federal, system, in<br />
matters such as this. But let nobody be in any doubt that the<br />
Great Barrier Reef Marine Park will be progressively extended.<br />
The question is not whether, but when.<br />
The other two Australian nominations before this meeting forthe<br />
world list are the Kakadu National Park in Arnhem Land<br />
and the Willandra Lakes region in western New South Wales.<br />
These great treasures have been unknown to most Australians<br />
until relatively recently, although both have been known to<br />
Aboriginals for thousands of years. It was only eleven years<br />
ago that archaeological discoveries put the Willandra. Lakes<br />
on the world map as an early site indeed in the emergence<br />
,, of modern man, and new discoveries of scientific and cultural<br />
s ignificance, as well as of unrealized and amazing beauty,<br />
are still " being made in the great Kakadu Park.<br />
Even since last year when it was forwarded as a nomination<br />
for the world list, there have been new discoveries of artifacts<br />
which date the origins of human settlement there at thirty<br />
or even possibly forty thousand years ago.<br />
In addition to these three nominations, I am pleased to<br />
foreshadow now that the Australian Government will soon<br />
Sforward the nominations of a magnificent wilderness area<br />
in south-west Tasmania, and also Lord Howe Island, which<br />
is a unique example of a Pacific island eco-system.<br />
The Commonwealth Government has shown in a number of practical<br />
ways its awareness of the need for initiative and action on<br />
matters of c onservation and the environment. This Government<br />
has prohibited sand mining on Fraser Island. We have banned<br />
whaling in Australian waters and put our weight behind banning<br />
whaling completely. We have substantially increased grants<br />
and research in marine scien Ice. We established thc Fox Enquiry<br />
on uranium and have acted on the Report. We have acted on<br />
and encouraged moves towards the preservation of Antarctica,<br />
and the protection of Antarctic seals. We have embarked on<br />
various treaties-and undertakings for the protection of<br />
migratory birds and endangered species, and for nature<br />
conservation in the South Pacific. We were the first party<br />
to the Convention on Wetlands of International Importance.<br />
We have established the Australiana Fund. -And we have<br />
assisted in the establishment of the World Wildlife Fund in<br />
Australia. The World Conservation Strategy was launched in Australia<br />
last year and-the development of Australia's own conservation<br />
strategy is at a very interesting stage. The various sections<br />
of the strategy are already in draft form, and will be discussed<br />
next month. These sections inc] udc agriculture, forestry, and mining,<br />
fisheries, J. ncluding marine resources, manufacturing and processing,<br />
and special purpose areas, including Aboriginal lands, unallocated<br />
Crown Lands, and nature reserves. Tho strategy will then be rewritten<br />
in the licght of these discussions. Then there will be a process of<br />
public comment and discussion next year. This strategy, which is<br />
concerned with the balance of development and conservation, is<br />
expected to be finalised by the end of 1982. </p>
<p>3<br />
The concern of Australia with the environment and with<br />
conservation has a substantial history. The National Trust<br />
Movement, which now has a membership of about 80,000, dates<br />
back to 1945, a number of field naturalists clubs actually<br />
date right back to the early part of this century, and I would<br />
add that the total membership of the various nature conservation<br />
bodies in Australia runs to quarter of a million.<br />
I would like to commend the voluntary conservation and<br />
heritage movement to countries where it is less well-known<br />
because it really is a way of involving vast numbers of<br />
ordinary people in the conservation of their own heritage,<br />
and in a purely Australian context, I would like to take<br />
this opportunity to express the indebtedness of Australia<br />
as a whole to those people who have, over many years,<br />
given significant and effective practical expression to their<br />
concerns for heritage and conservation issues.<br />
D. e spite the youth of this country, we are fortunate to<br />
have inherited one of the oldest systems of national parks in<br />
the world, because the 15,000 hectare Royal National Park<br />
was established in 1879 and some 2,000 hectares in the<br />
Jenolan Caves area was set aside for similar purposes as far<br />
back as about 1866.. Australia is still actively building<br />
up as well as conserving this inheritance.<br />
In the five years to June, the area of national parkland<br />
has more than doubled, to more than 31m. hectares, with<br />
new national parks in every State and territory of Australia.<br />
Many of these parks are quite breath-taking and some of<br />
Australia's national parks are surely of outstanding universal<br />
value. I am sure you will understand that when I speak in such<br />
terms I am not engaging in any special pleading, but simply<br />
stating the facts as they really are, as those of you who<br />
are taking the opportunity to look around Australia after<br />
this meeting'will see in due course.<br />
But in advance of having the chance to look around Australia,<br />
you have a daunting task to undertake, namely, to make a<br />
few decisions about the 40 or so nominations that are before<br />
you for inclusion in the World Heritage List.<br />
The criteria and guidelines which are laid down in your<br />
terms of reference will obviously help in the decision-making<br />
part of your meeting, but in the end you will undoubtedly<br />
have some difficult and potentially far-reaching judgments<br />
to make, and I certainly wish you well in your deliberations.<br />
John Turner said in the " Heritage of Australia" that,<br />
" the more we understand, the more we care, and with caring<br />
comes the instinct to conserve". I believe that most people<br />
geuninely desire to preserve the environment, but it is a<br />
fact of life that in many circumstances, something more than mere<br />
goodwill is required to ensure the protection of the environment.<br />
And while contemporary man has an unrivalled -capacity, through<br />
the application of technology and acquired knowledge, to enhance<br />
his natural surroundings, contemporary man has an equal potential<br />
to disturb or destroy the delicate balance of nature, and the fabric<br />
of human achievement. </p>
<p>-4<br />
Man is part of the natural environment, and while man surely<br />
has the right toutilise the resources of this planet, a critical<br />
question is how best to use these resources to enhance the quality<br />
of human life, and ' avoid unacceptable damage to our physical<br />
and cultural heritage. It is certainly not acceptable for this.<br />
generation to rob the next, or for us to pass on to our children<br />
a less healthy, a less beautiful or a less enriching heritage<br />
than we enjoy ourselves. There seems little doubt that future<br />
generations will share our growing interest in the tangibleevidences<br />
of these roots, and the fruits of human civilization<br />
at large, as well as of particular cultures, and we surely have<br />
a responsibility to do what we can to make sure that more -evidenc-e<br />
rather than less is on record for the future to draw upon.<br />
The production of registers and catalogues is a worthwhile development<br />
of this connection. Obviously no catalogue or register, no mattef<br />
how lavish its production, could measure up to the reality of<br />
the sites -and properties that are represented. But heritage<br />
registers certainly can open up unknown vistas, and I would lik~ e<br />
Ito say something about the recently published, " Heritage of<br />
AUstralia" which is, as I am advised, the first attempt anywhere<br />
to publish a single inventory of the heritage resources of an<br />
entire nation.<br />
This book is as fascinating as it is monumental, although of<br />
course, something like this is no sooner published than people<br />
will-, quite rightly, want to start * bringing forward additional<br />
properties which should be in it but are not. Works such as this,<br />
which make history tangible, help a nation to establish its own<br />
~ identity. They provide points of reference by which a people<br />
can reach a better understanding of itself and its way of life..<br />
There can be little doubt that a World Heritage listing, as it is<br />
more fully developed, will contribute to a better understanding<br />
of human civilization as a whole. The growth of interest and<br />
concern among people throughout the world for heritage issues<br />
is a signifi'cant development in our times.<br />
Obviously this growing interest will be vastly more productive<br />
if it can be given practical direction and effective agreements<br />
such as a World Heritage Convention are plainly significant<br />
achievements in this context.<br />
The identification and protection of heritage resources<br />
is obviously an ongoing process, and for some countries it is<br />
relatively easily accomplished. For others, even where the will.<br />
is present, economic considerations in particular place<br />
discouraging constraints on progress.<br />
The UNESCO publication, " Man and his environment", comments<br />
that " the countries that are wealthiest as far as cultural or<br />
natural heritage are concerned are often among the most handicapped<br />
in the action to preserve and enhance it, ow,, ing to their lack of<br />
qualified staff and of investment capital". And the background<br />
notes to the W.% orld Heritage Convention refer to the need for<br />
some kind of international mechanism to spread the burden more<br />
evenly and it is encollr~ ig] ncl thi-L1 this Committee, through the<br />
World Herit. aye Fund, has been able to0 support efforts in many<br />
countries to protect priceless sites and properties. </p>
<p>This Committee, in co-operation with the nations of the world,<br />
has the task of trying to make sure that universally valuable<br />
sites and properties from all countries, not just the wealthy<br />
and well-provided countries, can find a secure place on the<br />
World Heritage List.<br />
The task is a challenging one. I wish you well in your deliberations<br />
this week and have pleasure in declaring this meeting open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
