<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3075</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, TO OPEN THE AUSTRALIAN HOUSING STANDARDS CONFERENCE, LAKESIDE INTERNATIONAL HOTEL, CANBERRA, MONDAY 19 NOVEMBER 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003075.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
MR, EG. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
TO OPEN THE AUSTRALIAN HOUSING STANDARDS CONFERENCE,<br />
LAKESIDE INTERNATIONAL HOTELL, CANBERRA,<br />
MONDAY 19 NOVEMBER, 10973<br />
THOSE ACQUAINTED WITH MY PERSONAL FOIBLES WILL<br />
KNOW HOW CLOSE TO MY HEART THE SUBJECT OF YOUR CONFERENCE<br />
HAS ALWAYS BEEN. IN THE MORE MUNDANE MATTERS OF<br />
STATESMANSHIP THERE WERE TWO PARTICULAR HOBBY-HORSES<br />
THAT I RODE WITH GREAT ENERGY DURING MY YEARS IN<br />
OPPOSITION. ONE WAS SEWERAGE; THE OTHER WAS UNIFORM<br />
HOUSING STANDARDS. I REGRET TO SAY THAT MANY PEOPLE MADE<br />
LIGHT OF THESE MATTERS. YET BOTH OF THEM WERE CRUCIAL,<br />
IN THEIR DIF17[ 1RFNT WAYS, TO THE BASIC LIVING STANDARDS<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE. THE BUILDING INDUSTRY IS STILL<br />
HAMPERED BY A BEWILDERING VARIETY OF LEGAL CODES AND<br />
STANDARDS. IAM THEREFORE DELIGHTED THAT YOU HAVE ASKED<br />
ME TO OPEN THIS IMPORTANT CONFERENCE.$ TRUST THAT, IN<br />
A SINGULAR AND PERHAPS UNSPECTACULAR WAY, IT WILL PROVE<br />
TO BE ONE OF THE MOST FRUITFUL AND REWARDING INITIATIVES<br />
my GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN$ i / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IS NOT ALONE IN ITS<br />
PERCEPTION OF THE FOLLIES AND DANGERS OF CONFLICTING<br />
STANDARDS AND OUTMODED PRACTICES IN ALL PARTS OF THE<br />
COUNTRY AND ALL AREAS OF THE BUILDING INDUSTRY.<br />
THE STATES HAVE COME GRADUALLY TO RECOGNISE THIS STATE<br />
OF AFFAIRS. THE STERLING WORK THAT HAS RESULTED IN THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN MODEL UNIFORM BUILDING CODE IS PROOF OF THIS,<br />
AND I HOPE THAT CODE WILL SOON BE ADOPTED BY ALL STATES.<br />
A FURTHER PROOF IS THE PRESENCE HERE TODAY OF THE MOST<br />
REPRESENTATIVE GROUP OF PEOPLE IN THE HOUSING INDUSTRY<br />
EVER GATHERED IN AUSTRALIA BUILDERS, ARCHITECTS,<br />
PLANNERS, MATERIALS SUPPLIERS, UNIONISTS, ADMINISTRATORS,<br />
ENGINEERS, SURVEYORS, CONTRACTORS, INSTITUTIONAL LENDERS<br />
AND BUILDING CONTROLLERS. YOUR COLLECTIVE KNOWLEDGE AND<br />
EXPERIENCE OF THE HOME BUILDING INDUSTRY IS UNRIVALLED.<br />
THERE HAVE BEEN HOUSING SEMINARS AND FORUMS BEFORE,<br />
BUT THIS CONFERENCE IS UNIQUE. YOU ARE NOT HERE SIMPLY TO<br />
EXCHANGE VIEWS AND INFORMATION. YOU HAVE A VERY PRACTICAL<br />
TASK BEFORE YOU. I HOPE THIS CONFERENCE WILL SUPERVISE<br />
THE DEVELOPMENT OF NEW STANDARDS FOR HOUSING BASED ON<br />
ORIGINAL RESEARCH; THAT . IT WILL DEVELOP MODERN, READILY<br />
UNDERSTOOD NATIONAL HOME BUILDING REGULATIONS WHICH CAN BE<br />
APPLIED AND ADMINISTERED BY LOCAL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES.<br />
THAT IS YOUR CHALLENGE. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I AM HEARTENED BY THE PRESENCE HERE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
OF THE THREE TIERS OF GOVERNMENT, BECAUSE IT IS THE HOUSING<br />
DEPARTMENTS IN THE STATES AND THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
AUTHORITIES WHOSE FULL CO-OPERATION IS NEEDED. WE MUST<br />
ENSURE THAT ANY NEW HOME BUILDING CODE IS A NATIONAL ONE,<br />
A UNIVERSAL ONE, SO THAT INDUSTRY CAN OPERATE WITH THE<br />
GREATEST EFFICIENCY AND ECONOMY, AND ORDINARY HOME BUYERS<br />
CAN BENEFIT FROM REDUCTIONS' IN COST.<br />
I HAVE REFERRED MANY TIMES TO THE NEED TO REDUCE<br />
HOME BUILDING COSTS, BUT THE UNPALATABLE FACT IS THAT LATELY<br />
WE HAVE SEEN INORDINATE INCREASES RATHER THAN REDUCTIONS.<br />
PERHAPS THAT IS DUE TO OUR HIGH STANDARD OF LIVING AND<br />
ADVANCING EXPECTATIONS. 14E ARE NEVER LIKELY TO SEE CHEAP<br />
LABOUR AND CUT-THROAT COMPETITION AGAIN. WITH THE ADVENT<br />
OF RELATIVELY FULL, AND I HOPE STABLE, EMPLOYMENT, AND THE<br />
ADVANCE OF EDUCATION, THERE WILL BE A PROGRESSIVELY<br />
DECLINING SUPPLY OF ON-SITE LABOUR, OF SEMI-SKILLED MEN<br />
FOR BRICKYARDS AND TIMBER MILLS, ! IE MUST EXPECT A MORE<br />
MECHANIZED ERA IN BUILDING LESS ON-SITE WORK AND MORE<br />
FACTORY WORK IN WHICH GREATER UNIFORMITY AND<br />
RATIONALISATION OF PROCEDURES AND PROCESSES WILL HELP<br />
REDUCE COSTS. I AM TOLD THAT EVERY ONE PER CENT SAVING ( F<br />
COSTS IN THE BUILDING INDUSTRY IS WORTH AT LEAST<br />
MILLION A YEAR. / 4 </p>
<p>I DO NOT HAVE TO TELL BUILDERS AND SUPPLIERS<br />
HOW DIFFERING REGULATIONS AND STANDARDS ADD SIGNIFICANTLY<br />
TO THEIR COSTS. THEY KNOW THIS. IT IS A SUBJECT THAT<br />
YOUR CONFERENCE WILL EXPLORE. IT IS SUFFICIENT FOR ME TO<br />
EMPHASISE THAT SUBSTANTIAL ECONOMIES IN HOME BUILDING CAN<br />
BE ACHIEVED WITH THE KNOWLEDGE AT OUR COMMAND. THE<br />
BENEFITS WILL BE FELT IN THE IMPROVEMENT OF THE QUALITY OF<br />
LIFE FOR THE AUSTRALIAN COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE, AND NOT LEAST<br />
FOR THOSE WITH PARTICULAR NEEDS THE ELDERLY, THE DISABLED,<br />
ABORIGINESAND PEOPLE LIVING IN AREAS OF CLIMATIC EXTREMES.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WHOLEHEARTEDLY SUPPORTS<br />
THE OBJECTIVES OF THIS CONFERENCE. WE HAVE TAKEN THE<br />
INITIATIVE BY ESTABLISHING AN EXPERT TECHNICAL TASK FORCE.<br />
THIS TASK FORCE WILL INCLUDE ARCHITECTS, ENGINEERS,<br />
QUANTITY SURVEYORS AND SOCIOLOGISTS, SUPPORTED BY TECHNICAL<br />
AND ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICERS OF THE NEW COMBINED DEPARTMENT<br />
OF HOUSING AND CONSTRUCTION.<br />
THE MAIN OBJECTIVE OF THE TASK FORCE WILL BE TO<br />
PREPARE A NUMBER OF GENERALLY ACCEPTABLE-MINIMUM REQUIREMENTS<br />
FOR HOME BUILDING IN AUSTRALIA, EXPRESSED AS CLEARLY AND<br />
SIMPLY AS POSSIBLE. LET ME EMPHASISE THAT UNIFORM HOUSING<br />
STANDARDS NEED NOT MEAN UNIFORMITY IN STYLES. EACH AUSTRALIAN<br />
CITY HAS A DISTINCTIVE ARCHITECTURE, AND IT IS CENTRAL TO OUR<br />
PLANS FOR NEW AUSTRALIAN CITIES THAT AUSTRALIANS SHOULD HAVE<br />
AN AUTHENTIC CHOICE OF LOCATIONS AND STYLES. </p>
<p>THE FORMULATION OF SUCH NATIONAL STANDARDS WILL INVOLVE<br />
CLOSE CONSULTATION WITH THE STATES AND OTHER ORGANISATIONS<br />
DIRECTLY CONCERNED. WE ARE LOOKING FOR CONSENSUS: WE<br />
ARE NOT SEEKING TO ACCEPT A LOWEST AGREED DENOMINATOR.<br />
WHERE NECESSARY, THE EXPERTS WILL UNDERTAKE FRESH RESEARCH<br />
SO THAT DECISIONS CAN BE BASED ON SCIENTIFIC FINDINGS.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT INTENDS THAT THE TASK FORCE WILL<br />
PREPARE A SERIES OF SUPPLEMENTARY PUBLICATIONS AFTER<br />
STUDYING CLIMATIC DIFFERENCES, DESIGN AND SITING,<br />
SPATIAL RELATIONSHIPS AND FITMENTS WITHIN DWELLINGS.<br />
THIS CONFERENMF AND ITS EXPERT COMMITTEESWILL PROVIDE<br />
THE GUIDELINES THAT THE TASK FORCE WILL FOLLOW.<br />
AT THE SAME TIME THE HOUSING INDUSTRY WILL BE ABLE TO<br />
REVISE ITS THINKING IN OTHER DIRECTIONS, ESPECIALLY<br />
IN ADOPTING NEW METRIC SIZES. AND REMEMBER ALWAYS THAT<br />
HOUSING STANDARDS ARE NOT NEEDED MERELY TO ENSURE THAT<br />
ONE COMPONENT FITS ANOTHER, BUT THAT MINIMUM STANDARDS<br />
AND QUALITIES PREVAIL.<br />
THE AIJSRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS AN IMPORTANT<br />
RESPONSIBILITY IN BOTH PUBLIC AND PRIVATE HOUSING, WE HAVE<br />
DIRECT RESPONSIBILITY FOR GOVERNMENT HOUSING IN THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
CAPITAL TERRITORY A~ D THC NOSYHERN TERRITORY. IF, HOWEVER,<br />
WE CAN REDUCE THE COST OF HOUsING IN THE STATES BY RESEARCH,<br />
BY DEVELOPMENT AND BY UNIFYING HOME BUILDING REGULATIONS, THE<br />
TAXPAYER'S HOUSING DOLLAR CAN BE MADE TO GO FURTHER IN EACH<br />
STATE'S WELFARE HOUSING PROGRAMS, / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
TO TAKE ONE PRACTICAL EXAMPLE, THERE IS CLEARLY<br />
A NEED FOR UNIFORM HOUSING STANDARDS IN THE DEVELOPMENT<br />
OF ALBIJRY-WODONGA. IMAGINE THE DIFFICULTIES CREATED<br />
AND HIGH COSTS INCURRED IF THE DIFFERENCES IN REGULATORY<br />
REQUIREMENTS WHICH NOW EXIST ON OPPOSITE SIDES OF THE<br />
MURRAY ARE ALLOWED TO CONTINUE. THIS IS TRUE FOR OTHER<br />
POPULATION CENTRES NEAR STATE BORDERS. WE WANT TO ENSURE<br />
THAT A COMPANY PRODUCING COMPONENTS OR FITTINGS IN ToowooMBA<br />
CAN HAVE A NATION-WIDE MARKET AND SELL ITS PRODUCTS IN<br />
PERTH AND LAUNCESTON.<br />
A NATIONAL CONFERENCE SUCH AS THIS CAN TAKE<br />
INITIATIVES TO SECURE TI* IS. WITH CO-OPERATIVE EFFORT<br />
AMONG PEOPLE OF MANY DISCIPLINES, GREAT ABILITIES AND<br />
MUCH EXPERIENCE, I AM SURE THIS CONFERENCE CAN MAKE REAL<br />
PROGRESS IN OVERCOMING THE URGENT PROBLEMS FACING THE HOME<br />
BUIL. DING INDUSTRY. I WISH YOU SUCCESS. IT GIVES ME<br />
GREAT PLEASURE TO DECLARE THIS INAUGURAL MEETING OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN HOUSING STANDARDS CONFERENCE OPEN. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
