<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>506</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, AT OPENING OF T2 POWER STATION, ON 5TH MAY 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/05/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000506.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R..<br />
MENZIES, AT OPENING OF T2 POi. ER STATION, ON<br />
__ MTAHY 162<br />
Sir, colleagues, Your Excellencies, and ladies and gentlemen:<br />
It is only a few days ago that somebody was talking to<br />
me about the great art of speech-making, and in my usual dogmatic<br />
fashion I said to him " Of course the essence of it, old boy, is to<br />
get as close to the audience as you can, so that you are on easy<br />
and even intimate terms with them". And here I am today, feeling<br />
remarkably elevated for the first time since last December.<br />
( Laughter) There is one other thing that I ought to tell you,<br />
. hen I have concluded my few remarks my instructions are to pull<br />
a switch. I see that it has on the switch that it was used by<br />
my wife in opening Tumut 1 and I am therefore very sorry that the<br />
doctor has prohibited her from being with me this afternoon.,<br />
But, I have been warned by Sir William Hudson, who, under the<br />
direction of his wife, manages this enterprise, ( Laughter) that<br />
when the switch is pulled there zrill be a co-tain amount of<br />
mystery go on donm below, and then there will be the most<br />
deafening noise, and I am instructed to warn you all to remain<br />
quietly seated: there will be no occasion for panic because he<br />
assures me that the whole thing has been tested and that it will<br />
worko So that tremendous noise which will occur when I pull that<br />
switch, will of course, be understood by you and will be<br />
gratefully received by me as a substitute for applause.( Laughter)<br />
Now, ladies and gentlemen, this is really, as I don't<br />
need to tell you, a very remarkable enterprisco It has so many<br />
aspects that one could speak for two hours and not deal with all<br />
of them. But this is a very remarkable undertaking, with<br />
various facets some of which are occasionally forgotten. This<br />
enterprise, first of all, began as an imaginative conception, a<br />
conception which was operated, which was put into existence, by<br />
my predecessors; and I always acknowledge the imaginative effort<br />
that they engaged in when they established the Snowy Mountains<br />
Authority. It so happens, by the circumstances of politics,<br />
which do change from time o time that my own Government has had<br />
the opportunity of enabling the taxpayers to find the money to be<br />
spent on it, and in large licks. Senator Spooner, as he admits,<br />
has been the Minister for 11 years, the Minister in whose parish<br />
this comes0 I tell you that his persistent attempts to get more<br />
from the Treasury than he really expected to have excited my warm<br />
admiration. And it is because I have very frequently come doiwr<br />
on his side that he has this high opinion that he has been<br />
expressing to you today. He has been an enthusiast.<br />
But the whole point about this enterprise is that<br />
everybody connected with it is an enthusiast. Sir ! Jilliam Hudson<br />
is a quiet man. In Canberra he seems almost a shy man; it is<br />
very hard to draw him out at all, a most retiring fellow. ho<br />
has ever flogged an enterprise of this kind along in the fashion<br />
in whic' he has done? The moment you meet him and step into a<br />
car and find yourself driving into the domain of the Snowy<br />
Mountains Hydro-lectric Authority he becomes a d7ynamo himself.<br />
He convoys his enthusiasm to whoever may be with him; he conveys<br />
his enthusiasm to a very remarkable team. And my one attempt,<br />
which failed, with my colleague Senator Spooner, was that when he<br />
said that he ywanted me to open this Power Station I said " Well I<br />
look forward to the time when we will have Sir illiam Hudson<br />
open a Power Station". Frankly I think he should have opened<br />
this one. Therefore, as I have had this task put upon me I<br />
esteem it my duty to say not for the first time, that Australia<br />
will never adequately understand the debt that it owes to this<br />
man, and to those who have worked with him. ( Applause) </p>
<p>V* My colleague said something about wives, Wives are very<br />
important: none of us would be here but for wrives. But Lady<br />
Hudson is herself, again, the embodiment of the womn, the wives,<br />
who have contributed to the success of this scheme a very<br />
wonderful success, and a wonderful contribution.<br />
Noj, Sir, there are other aspects of this Snowy<br />
Mountains Scheme. , le think, perhaps, we who live mostly in<br />
cities, think of it perhaps mostly in terms of power, electric<br />
supply and of course it is quite true that it makes a tremendous<br />
contribution to the supply of power in two States. But it is easy<br />
to overlook the fact that in the course of creating power it<br />
provides vast storages of water and facilitates the ultimate<br />
irrigation of many hundreds of thousands of acres of land. ;. nd if<br />
there is one thing that is clear in Australia it is that for the<br />
purpose of diversifying the products of the soil, of attracting<br />
population into rural areas developing export trade on the grand<br />
scale, the spread of irrigation is an imense contribution. I<br />
think I am right in saying, but I speak subject to the correction<br />
of the experts whom I see here, that already in New South Wales<br />
and Victoria something of the order of 3 million acres of land are<br />
under irrigation. This is a tremendous contribution to<br />
Australian peduction, to Australian population to the Australian<br />
future. And this groat Scheme is going to replenish, and add to<br />
those resources, and therefore bring that tremendous piece of<br />
benefit to Australia.<br />
You see the duality of this thing? Power, yes,<br />
primarily for the cities, .? ater, yes, primarily for the ( mtry.<br />
Here you have something that comes in aid of primary industry, of<br />
secondary industry; indead, that comes in aid of the whole<br />
economic development of Australiao<br />
Then, and here I do no more than repeat sor. lthing that<br />
has been well said by my colleague, this enterprise has itself<br />
not only created things, the kind of thing we see today, the next<br />
great step, but it ias also served as a remarkable nursery of<br />
talent. Think of the young engineers, think of all the young<br />
technical people, wuio been working on this enterprise; and<br />
who, in due course, go : t from it and enrich the technical and<br />
engineering life of Aus-alia with the product of the skill some<br />
of which, a good deal of which perhaps, they acquired in and<br />
around these mountains. And our contractors in Australia, some<br />
of whom are now becoming extraordinarily competent and prominent,<br />
have, I venture to say, learned more in a few years about largescale<br />
contracting and engineering works learned more in a few<br />
years by the example of world-famous enterprises, than they might<br />
otherwise have learned in a quarter of a contury,<br />
So that this great Scheme enriches Australia, not only<br />
with power, not only with water, but also with skill and<br />
exp-rienco; and in the doing of all these things it is opening<br />
up a section of Australia which I believe is destined to be one of<br />
the great tourist resorts of the , orld.<br />
Now this means that one must say that it would be<br />
difficult to imagine, and certainly difficult to find, any enterprise<br />
which had so many facets to it as this one has. Therefore<br />
today as I take the mechanical step of pulling a switch, as we<br />
celebrate the establishnent of yet another Power Station in this<br />
great enterprise, let us remember with pride as Australians that<br />
this Scheme was conceived and brought forth, has been carried on,<br />
has been brought step by step towards its a. oLjletion, by people of<br />
this country, and the people of countries friendly to us, anxious<br />
to participate with us, in the development of a great continent.<br />
Sir I believe that this is in its own fashion an<br />
historic event and I thtin that all o' us who are here today so<br />
long as we live will be vuey happy to think that we were resent on<br />
an occasion to mark achievements which do Sc'ri:,' h credit to the<br />
country and so much honour to those who have been primarily<br />
concerned in it. Now hav. ng said that, rememaber my warning, I Wl. l<br />
null the switch. i declare this Stati5n opn, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
