<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16747</transcript-id>
    <title>Unjust conviction of Aung San Suu Kyi and re-establishment of Radio Australia Burmese service Canberra  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/08/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am deeply dismayed by the verdict delivered today on the trial of Aung San Suu Kyi.  She is the symbol of liberty in Burma, and her continued detention represents a new low for the Burmese regime.  The Australian Government is convinced that Aung San Suu Kyi was tried on spurious charges and not granted a fair hearing.</p>
<p>Her conviction removes any prospect that she could participate in Burma's elections, scheduled for 2010.</p>
<p>I join the international community in condemning the conviction and ongoing detention of Aung San Suu Kyi and in calling for her immediate and unconditional release.  It is also critical that the Burmese regime release the more than 2,000 other political prisoners in Burma.</p>
<p>It is time for change in Burma  -  time for the military regime to deliver to the people of Burma the basic right of freedom of political association.  The Australian Government is deeply concerned by the Burmese regime's disregard for the democratic aspirations of its people and its disrespect for their human rights.  We will continue our strong efforts with other members of the international community, including the United Nations, to deliver the change which the Burmese so much deserve.</p>
<p>Australia has strong sanctions against Burma, which it will continue to apply until we see genuine political change.</p>
<p>Aung San Suu Kyi has previously asked that the Radio Australia service to Burma be re-established.  As a gesture of our solidarity with her, and to open a new channel of international contact for the people of Burma, the Australian Government and the Australian Broadcasting Corporation have together agreed to re-establish the Radio Australia service to Burma.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
