<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23450</transcript-id>
    <title>A message from the Prime Minister - Building a strong and prosperous economy</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>In a little over two weeks, the Treasurer will hand down the Budget.</p>
<p>It’s the first Budget for this Government and it is part of our Economic Action Strategy.</p>
<p>It will be a Budget of long-term structural reform and it will be a Budget that keeps our commitments.</p>
<p>The Government will make a range of decisions which are important for Australia's long-term economic strength, because the most fundamental commitment that we gave at the election was to build a strong and prosperous economy for a safe and secure Australia.</p>
<p>In this Budget, we will strengthen the economy so that families have more jobs, lower power bills and overtime more opportunities to get ahead.</p>
<p>The abolition of the carbon tax will save the typical family $550 a year.</p>
<p>The Budget will also deal with Labor’s legacy of debt and deficit, stretching out as far as the eye can see.</p>
<p>Under the previous government, Australia ran up the five largest deficits in our history.  They also left a projected $123 billion in future deficits and $667 billion in accumulated debt.</p>
<p>Already the interest bill on Labor’s debt is more than $10 billion each and every year.  That’s dead money.  Wasted money.  It’s money that could be better used on services and helping families and pensioners to get ahead.</p>
<p>This Government understands that you can’t fix the economy without fixing the Budget.  Equally, we understand that when you strengthen the economy, you strengthen the Budget.</p>
<p>So this Budget will regain control of our nation’s finances – so that all Australians can have confidence in their economic future.</p>
<p>27 April 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
