<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3347</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR.E.G. WHITLAM, Q.C., M.P., TO THE ITALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE - SYDNEY, MONDAY 12 AUGUST 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/08/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003347_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPFCI BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR F. G, WHIHLAP, M. P.,<br />
TO THE ITALIAN CU0rrBER OF COMMERCE -SYDNEY, MONDAY, 12 AUGUST 1974i<br />
THERE ARE FEW COUNtRIES WITH WHIcH AUSTRALIA HAS<br />
HAD LONGER CONTACT THAT IT HAS HAT) WITNi ITALY,, THIS CONTACT.<br />
PROBABLY EXTENDS AS FAR BACK AS CAPTAIN CoOK1'' S VOYAGE To AUSTRALIA<br />
IN 1770, AB3OARUJ THE " ENDEAVOUIR" WAS ANTONIO PONTO, THOUGHT TO<br />
HAVE BEEN A. VENETIArNi THERE WAS AN ITALIAN NAMED TU70 IN THE<br />
FIRST FLEET, THOUGH WE ARE NOT SURE IN WHAT CAPACITY HE CAME<br />
To AuSTRALIAI DURaNG-THE NINETEENTH CENTURY ITALIAN MIGRANTS.<br />
ARRIVFED IN AUSTRALIA IN SMALL BUT GROWING NUMBERS, PARTICULARLY<br />
AFTER THE IMPE7US PRQVfDED BY THE GOLD DISCOVERIES OF THE<br />
2850' S. INDEED THE GOLD RUSH C: AUSED THE INVOLVEMENT OF ONE<br />
ITALIAN IN ONE OF THE MIOST CRUCIAL INCIDENTS IN AnsTRALIAN<br />
HISTORY, RAFFAELLO CARBONI WAS ONE OF THE MINERS' LEADER~ S<br />
AT THE EUREKA STOCKADE IN 185i-<br />
THE ITALIAN MEN AND WOMEN HHO CAME To AUSTRALIA<br />
CONTRIBUTED GREATLYi TO OUR WAY OF LIF'E. WE OWE MUCH 10 THE<br />
ITA. LIAN CANEGROWERS IN NORTH OUENSLAND, TO THE ITALIAN GOLD)<br />
MIlNERS IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA, THE ITALIAN TOBACCO GROWERS IN<br />
SOUTH-WEST OESTERN AUSTRALIA AnD V/ ICTORIA AND THE FRUIT AND<br />
\ E(; ETABLE GROWERS IN THE IRRIG3ATION AREAS OF THE MURRAY AND<br />
PURRUMBIDGEE RIVERS OF NEW SOUTH WAI-ES AND VICTORIA. </p>
<p>2-<br />
THE POST-WAR MIGRATION BOOM LED TO AN EVEN GREATER<br />
INFLUX OF MIGRANTS FROM ITALY. THE ITALIAN COMMUNITY 13<br />
NOW THE BIGGEST OF THE NONt-ENGLIqlH NATIONAL GROUPS IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
FROM 1945 To DECEMBER 1973, 164,863 ITALIANS HAVE BECOME<br />
AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS. THE 1971 CENSUS SHOWED THAT MORE THAN<br />
289,000 AUSTRALIAN RESIDENTS WERE BORN IN ITALY AND IT IS<br />
ESTIMATED THAT FROM 19' 46 TO 1972 MORE THAN 257, OOO of CHILDREN<br />
BORN JN AUSTRALIA HAl) AT LEASI ONE PARENT WHO WAS BORN IN<br />
o ITALY. THIS DRAMATIC INFUSION O'F ITALIANS HAS HAD A GREAT<br />
IMPAC7 ONi AUF3TRALIAN SOCIETY. IT HAS SIGNIFICANTLY CHANGED<br />
OUR WAY OF L114, ESPECIALLY IN OUR CITIES, SUCH PROJECTS AS<br />
THE SNOWY MIOUNTAINS HYDRO-ELLCTR1C SCHEME WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN<br />
rPosSIBI. IF WITHOUT ITALIAN RIGGERS AND ENGINEERS, INCLUDfNG<br />
MIR JIM BA' 1UTTI. THE ITALIAN COMMUNITY HAS HAD A VERY REAL<br />
INFLUENCE IN THE SMALL BUSINESS FIELD AS WELL AS [ N LARGER<br />
ENTERPRISLS, SUCH As TRANSFIFHP CORPORATION, [ rHE BUSINES<br />
CULTURAL AND SOCIAL ACTIVITIES OF THE ONE MILLION AUSTRALIANS<br />
OF ITALIAN BIRTIH, EXTRACTION OR DESCENT HAVE MADE THE ITALIAN<br />
COMMUNITY KA' OST SUCCESSEFULLY I NTECRATED. NATI ONAL GROUP, ON4LY<br />
THE 13f-TIS-K ISLES HAVE MADE A LA4GER CONTRIBUTION ' 10 THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN NATION ANll SOC)[ 1Y, WE HAVE RECU4TLY' RECOGNISEL)<br />
THIS WITH THE APPOINTMENT OF DR-, EVASJO) COSTANZO TO THE-AUSTRALIA<br />
COUNCIL AND MR CLAUDE ALCORSO TO THE UINVERSITIES COMMtISSION.<br />
ITALIANS ARE NOT SIMPLY CONCERNING THEMSELV'ES WITH MIGRANT<br />
MATTERS, BUT 11ITH THE AFFAIRSId OF OUJR WHOLE SOCIETY. </p>
<p>-3<br />
TRADE BETWqEEN ITALY ANDr AuS7RAIA HAS ADDED<br />
SIGNIFICANTLY TO THE CONTAC7 BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES,<br />
ITALY WAS OUR NINTH LARGEST MARKET IN 1972/ 1973. AUSTRALIAN<br />
EXPORTS TO ITALY AMOUNTED TO $ 133 MIlLLION ) N THAT YEAR,<br />
THESE EXPORTS HAVE INCLUDED GREASY WOOL, SHEEP AND LAMB SKINS,<br />
IRON OREo COAL AND PIG [ RON IN TURN AUSTRALIA HAS BENEFITTED<br />
FROM THE IMPORT OF ITALIAN GOODS, PARTICULARLY MACHINERY,<br />
IN THE AREA OF CONSUMER GOODs. AUSTRALIANS H4AVE BEEN ABLE<br />
TO EXPERIEN4CL THE EXCELLENCE OF ITALIAN DESIGN, UNSURPASSED<br />
THROUGHOUT THE WORLDI<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT REMAINS OPTIMISTIC ABOUT<br />
FUTURE TRADE PROSPECTS WITH ITrALY. IAM AWARE, OF COURSE9,<br />
THAT IN MAY THE ITALIAN GOVERNMENT ANNOUNCED A NUMBER OF MEASURES<br />
AIMED AT CORRECTING THE GROSS D[ SEQUIL13RlIUM 11N ' HE ITALIAN<br />
0 ECONOMY. [ HESE MEASURES INCLUDED A PRIOR D) EPOSJTr SYSTEM FOR<br />
IMPORTS WHICH BECAME OPERATIVE ON 7 MlAY AND PRIMARILY AFFECTED<br />
PROCESSED OR MANUFACTURED ITEMS, FORTUNATELY FOR OUR TRADE,<br />
M4ORE THAN TWO-THIRDS OF AUSTRALIAN EXPORTS TO ITALY ARE<br />
EXEMPT FROM THE PRIO. R DEPOSIT SYSTEM, THIS APPLIES PARTICULARLY<br />
TO COAL, RAW WOOL, METAL ORES AND PIG [ RON, AUSTRALIA HAS<br />
MOVED TO ENSURE THAT THERE IS A CONTINUING AND HEALTHY TRADE<br />
BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES, Otq 3 MIAY THE M1INISTER FOR OVERSEAS<br />
TRADE, DR CWkNS, ANNOUNCED THE FORMATION OF THE<br />
ITALO-AuSTRALIAN ' fRADE AD~ viS. ORY COMMITTEE TO PROMOTE THE<br />
DEVELOPMENTr OF COMMERCIAL RELATIONS BE'TWEEN AUSTRALIA AND ITALY,<br />
lHE COMMITTEE WAS FORMED BY A GROUP OF ITALIAN AND AwmTALIAN<br />
BUSINESSMEN ' TO PROMOTE CO-OPERATION AND STREAMLINE<br />
BETWEEN THEC BIJSIIESS COMMUNITIES OF BOJH COUNTRIES, 1. </p>
<p>THERE IS ONE AREA OF POSSIBLE TRADE WHICH I KNOW<br />
IS OF GREAT IMPORTANCE TO ITALY AN) ITALIANS, I REFER TO THE<br />
SALE OF AUSTRALIAN URANIUM SUPPLIES, As MANY OF YOU WOULD<br />
BE AWARE, THE ITALIAN GOVERNMENT INSTRUMENTALITY, ENTE<br />
NAZIONALE IDROCARBURI ( ENI) BEGAN NEGOT] ATIONS IN APRIL 1973<br />
WITH PEKO MINES AND ELCCTROLYTIC ZINC FOR AN INTEREST IN THE<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF THE RANGER URANIUM DEPOSIT. ENI's AGREEMENT<br />
WITH THE RANGER PARTNERS CONTEMPLATED A 10% INTEREST IN THE<br />
0 PROPOSED VENTURE. CLEARLY SUCH AN INTEREST WOULD CREATE<br />
DIFFICULTIES . N VIEN OF THE GOVERNMENTIS OBJECTIVE OF FULL<br />
410 AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP IN URANIUM DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS, I<br />
OUTLINED THE GOVERNMENT' S BROAD APPROACH TO THE SUBJECT WHEN<br />
I SPOKE AT THE AUSTRALIA-JAPAN MIJNISTERIAL COMMITEE MEETING<br />
IN TOKYO ON 29 OCTOBER LAST YEAR, I SAID THIS:<br />
" THERE ARE CERTAIN ) NDUSTRIES WHERE WE REGARD<br />
AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP AND CONTROL OF PARlICULAR IMPORTANCE,<br />
THESE RELATE ESPECIALLY TO SOURCES OF ENERGY WHERE GROWING<br />
WORLD SHOR7AGES AND OTHER FACTORS MAKE THIS ESSENTIAL, URANIUM<br />
IS ONE OF THESE ENERGY SOURCES AND WE HAVE AN OBJECTIVE OF<br />
FULL AUSTRALIAN OWNERSHIP IN DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS INVOLVING<br />
URANIUM 1 1<br />
." WE RECOGNISE, HOWEVER, THAT AUSTRALIA'S RESOURCES<br />
OF CAPITAL AND TECHNOLOGY ARE RELATIVELY LIMITED, THAT THE SIZE<br />
OF THE PROJECTS TO BE UNDERTAKEN IS OFTEN VERY GREAT AND THAT<br />
WE SHALL NEED TO CALL UPON OVERSEAS EXPERTISE, TECHNOLOGY<br />
AND CAPITAL TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE PROPER DEVELOPMENT OF THESE<br />
VITAL ENERGY RESOURCES, [ THUS WHILE WE SEEK TO REQUIRE EQUITY<br />
IN NEW PROJECTS INVOLVING THESE MINERALS TO BE IN<br />
AUSTRALIAN HANDS WE DO LOOK FOR OVERSEAS PARTICI'ATION IN SOME<br />
WAYS: THROUGH ACCESS TO TECHNOLOGY, LOANS AND ESPECIALLY<br />
m y o lA. d i<br />
I </p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT HAS NOTED THAT ENI HAS<br />
STATED THAT, IN CARRYING OUT ITS STATUTORY FUNCTION TO PROCURE<br />
ENERGY RESOURCES FOR ITALY, IT SEEKS TO OPERATE IN A MANNER<br />
CONSISIENT WITH THE POLICIES OF HOST NATIONS, IN TURN tHE<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT RECOGNISES THE IMPORTANCE OF URANIUM<br />
S TO A COUN1RY LIKE ITALY WHICH HAS BEEN SO PROFOUNDLY AFFECTED<br />
BY THE ENERGY CRISIS, WHILL WE MUST SAFEGUARD OUR NATIONAL<br />
INTERESTS WE ACKNOWLEDGE THE HISTORY OF AUSTRALIIA AND ITALY AS<br />
GOOD TRADING PARTINERS, IN KEEPING WITH THAT TRADITION, W/ E WILL<br />
S. NSURE THAT ITALY WILL GET A PROPER PROPORTION OF ALL THE<br />
URAdIUiM WE HAVE TO EXPORT. </p>
<p>THE QUESTION OF THE EXPLOITATION C) F URANIUM RAISES<br />
71H1 BROADER ISSUE OF FOREIGN ' INVESTMENT IN A\ USTRALIA,<br />
I KNOW THERE IS A CONTINUING INTEREST AMONG MANY HERE TODAY<br />
IN THE POSSIBILITY' OF '. JOINT. VENTURES BETWEEN ITALIAN<br />
ENTERPRISES Aim) AuSTRALIAN COMPANIES, IT IS THEREFORE<br />
APPROPIATE TO OUTLJ1NE THE BROAD PRINCIPLES 012CH GUIDE OUR<br />
ATTITUDE TO FOREIGN INVESTMENT, YOU WOULD ALL BE AWARE THAT<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT NO LONGER HAS A WHOLLY UNCRITICAL<br />
ATTITUIDC TO LNV'STMENT FROM OVERSEAS, WE HAVE ADOP-TED A MORE<br />
SELECTIVEF APPROACH TO SUCH ) NVESTMENTrs, WE INTEND TO ENSURE<br />
THAT FOREIGN CAPITAL INFLOWS ARF ASSOCIAIED WITH PRODUICTIVE<br />
INVESTMENT WHICH ADDS TO / IU&amp; TRALIAN HEAL RESOURCES ANT) BRINGS'<br />
US BENEFIT.-THIS DOES NOT MEAN THAT WE HAVE NO WISH TO SEE<br />
1* URTHE9YV RSEAS CAPITAL FLOW ) IqTO A\ USTRA. WIE THINK THAT<br />
SUCH CAPITAL MU'. iT CONTINUE TO PLAY A SIGNIrICANT ROLE,<br />
IN PARINERSHIP WITH hUSTRALIAN CAPITALI N OUR FUTURE ECONOMIC<br />
GROWTH, FOREIGN INVES-TMENT, HOWEVER, MUST NOT CONFLICT WITH<br />
OUR FIRM POLICY OF PROMOTING AUSTRALIAN CONTROL OF AU-S7RALIAN<br />
RESOURNCES AND INDUJSTRIES, N WANT ' To ACHIE VE THE HIGHEST<br />
POSS'IBLE LEV'EL or AUSTRALIAN OWNFRSHIP IN OUR RESOURCES ANT)<br />
INDUSTRILS, BY' THIS WE MEAN WE WANT TO'ACHIEVEF THE HIGHEST<br />
Au-STR
PROJFCTf BY PRO. JECT, THAT ARE. FAIR AND R: EASONABLE TO BOTH PARTIES<br />
AND ARE WITHIN ' Il
WtW-r.. ~ Ot hAA~ 17 46.4d </p>
<p>FOR TOO LONG AUS5ITALIA WAS SEDUCED BY THE QUICK DEAL<br />
AND FAILED TO RESIST THE TEMPTATION FOR EASY PROFIT AT THE<br />
EXPENSE OF OUR LONGER TERM NATIONAL INTERESTS. UNDER OUR<br />
PREDECESSORS 68% OF OUR FNERGY RESOURCES FELL INTO THE HANDS OF<br />
FOREIGN COMPANIES, THis SHOU[ LD NOT HAVE HAPPENED AND, SO F-AR<br />
AS MY GOVERWILNT IS CONCERNED, WILL NOT HAPPEN AGAIN.<br />
14E HAVE SOUGHT TO EXTEND AND STRENGTHEN OUR FOREIGN TAKEOV/ ERS<br />
LEGISLA-TION, THE SENATE., HOWEVER, HASS ODSTRUCTED-1 MUCH OF OUR<br />
I-NDEAVOUR IN THIS FIELD, NEVERTHELESS I ANNOUNCED IN M~ AY THAT<br />
THE GOVERNMENT PROPOSED THREE BASIC EXTENSfONS TO THE FOREIGN<br />
TAKEOVERS LEGISLA<br />
THE MO-ST SERIOUS OMISSION ) N THE PRLSENT ACT' IS THAT<br />
IT APPLIL-s ONLY * TO THE PURCHASE OF SHARES. IT DOES NOT PREVENT<br />
AN OVERSEAS COMPANY BUYING ALL Or PART OF THE ASSETS OF AN<br />
AUSTRA~ IAN COMPANY AS DISTINCT FROM THE SHAREHOLDINGS. THIS<br />
IS A MAJOR LOOPHOLE. THE EFFECT OF BUYING SHARES OR BUYING<br />
ASSETS IS THE SAME. THE SECOND DEFICIENCY IN THE LEGISLATION<br />
IS THAT. iT DOES NOT INCLUDE COMPULSORY NOTIFICATION REQUIREMENTS<br />
FOR FOREIGN COMPANIES PROPOSING TO MAKE SUCH A TAKEOVER OF<br />
ASSETS, WE WILL INCLUDE SUCH PROV'ISIONS, WF PROPOSE A THIRD<br />
AMENDMENT. THE LEGISLATION DOES NOT EXTEND TO COMPANIES ALREADY<br />
UN4DER FOREIGN CONTROL BUT IN % H) Cfl THERE IS A SIGN[ FICANT<br />
11INOR IVl-AUISTRAIJAN I NTIRLsT. ' tHCPRE HAVE BEEiN A WUmBrER OF<br />
OCCASIONS WHEN THE AuSTRALIAN EQUITY IN A VENTURE HAS BEEN<br />
DIMINISHED BY A $ I( ARE ISGUE OR A SHARE SWAP, WE PROPOSE THAT,<br />
ON CERTAIN C'. RiTF~ I\' A, ANY ATTIMI'T TO DIMINISH A SIGNIFICANT<br />
(\ umTALI/' N N1TEREsTr. EVEN ) F IT IS A NON-CONTROLLING INTERESTi<br />
SHOULD EE MADE EXAMINABLE IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE PROCEDURES<br />
DJEVELOPED DY THE FOREiGNq TAKEOVERS COMMITTEE, </p>
<p>CONTROL OF FOREIGN TAK( EOVERS IS ONE ASPECT OF POLICY<br />
DESIGNED TO MAXIMISE AUSTRALIAN OWNFROHIP AND CONTROL, [ HE<br />
GOVERNMENT IN ) TS ADMINISTRATIVE ARRANGEMENTS HAS ESTABL3SHED<br />
. A BROADER SYSTEM OF SURVEJLLIANCE OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT PROPOSAL<br />
NOT INVOLVING DIRECT ACQUISITION OF AIS" TRALIAN BUSIrNESSES,<br />
IANNOUNCED IN MY POLICY SPEECH THAT WE WOULD rORMALISE THESE<br />
ARRANGEMENTS. WE WOULD CSTABL3SH A BROAD gCNEENiNG PROCFSS<br />
WH) CH WOULD COVER BOTH THE FOREIGN TAK~ EOVERS PROCEDURES, AS<br />
* AMENDED, AND NEW DIRECT FOREIGN ) NVESTMENT ANY NEW FOREIGN<br />
COMPANY PROPOSING TO SET UP iN AUS~ iTRALIA FOR THE FIRST TIMEP<br />
OR ANY FOREIGN COMPANY PROPOSING TO EXTEND ITS INVESTMENT INTO<br />
SNEW AREASt WOULD BE REQUIRED TO APPLY To THE TREASURY AND<br />
THE DE'TA1LS OF THE PROPOSFD INVESTMENT WOULD BE REVIEWED,<br />
THE ISCREENING PROCES( SW WILL-ENSURE THAT ANY PROPOSED<br />
[: ORE IGN INVESTMENT WHICH ) S ALLOWED CONFORM$ WITH. AUSTRALIA'S<br />
NATIONAL INTEREST, THE MATTERS WHICH WILL RECEIVE PARTICULAR<br />
AT'IENTiON ARE EXPORT FRANCII{. SE"' l RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT<br />
EXPEND17TURE, LICCENSING OF TECHNOLOGY, PURCHM4,' NG POLICIES AND<br />
TAX AVOIDANCE, OVER A PERIOD OF TIME GUIDELINES IN THESE AREAS<br />
W1ILL BECOME MORE DEF1I4ITE AS OUR FXPERIENCE GROWS, FORLIGN<br />
COMPANIES ALREADY OPLH\ A'rmNG iN AUSjTRALIA WILL BE EXPECTE-D TO<br />
CONFORM WITH THESE GUIDELINES PROGRESSIVELY8 IN THIS WAY WE W! L'<br />
EN4SURE THAT THE FOREIGN ) NVESTMENT THAT HAS ALREADY IBEE14<br />
ALLOWED WILL CONFORM TO THE AuST-RALIAN NATIONAL INTEREST AS<br />
WELL AS ANY NEW FOREIGN INVESTMENT THAT IS ALLOWED, </p>
<p>IN KEEPING W1111 THE INTENTIONS I STATED IN flAYJ<br />
THE GOV'ERNMENT IN JUNE ESTABLISHED A NEW 114TERDEPARIMENTAL R.'<br />
COMMITTEE TO EXAMINE AND PROVIDE ADVICE ON FOREI%'' N INVESTMENT<br />
PROPOSAL&amp; WHICH COME UNDER NCOTICE THROUGH THE EXCHANGE<br />
CONTROL MiECHANISK AND DO NOT INVOLVE THE TAKEOVERS OF AUS TRALI<br />
B U SINIs s cs THE NEW COMM1TL PARALLLLS AND COMPLEMENTS THE<br />
EXISING COMMITTEE ON ' FORE'IGN TAKEOVERS, IT HAS ALSO BEEN<br />
ASKED TO BRING FORWARDl, FOR-THE GOVERNMENT'tS COINSED ñ RATIONt<br />
DJETAILED) PROPOSALS FOR THE SCREEN4ING OF FOREIGN INVESTMENT<br />
ACTIVI1TIES WH) CH DO NOT INVOLVE EXCHANGE CONTA10L APPROVALSFOR<br />
EXAMPLE, INVESTMENT PROP05ALS WH) CH'HOUl. I) BE FINANCED<br />
BY FORLIGN INTERE. STS FROM FUNDS AVAILABLE TO THEM FROM<br />
AUSTRALIAN SOURCES.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT LOOKENG AT FOREIGN INVESTMENT<br />
IN A PURELY NFGATI\' E WAY; IT IS NOT SIMPLY IMPOSING RESTRICTIO<br />
As 1 SAID IN A SPEECH IN PERTH ( IN THE SECOND OF MAY: " THE<br />
0QUESTION IS NOT VIHFTHER'VE PERMIT OVERSEAS CAPITAL TO DO LESS4<br />
THE QUESTION IS WHETHER VIE CAN ENSURE THAT AUSTRALIAN DOES<br />
MORE" IT IS WITH llitS IN MIND T14AT WE HAVE SOUGHT TO EXTEND<br />
7H[ ACTIVITIES OF. THE AUSTRAI1AN ltqDUSTRY DEV'ELOPMENT CORPORATI<br />
IT is FOR THIS REASON T14AT WE HAVE PERSEVFRED WITH ESTABLISHIN<br />
TrHE PETROLEUM ANT) MINERALS AUTHORITfY. IT IS THROUGH THESE<br />
AGINC[ US THAT WE CAN MOBILISE AUSTRAlIA ' S HUMAN AND CAPITAL<br />
RESOURCES TO ENABLE US TO DEVELOP OUR OWN RESOURCES AND<br />
I NDUSTRiLS. SUCH GREAT ITALIAN FlNTERPRISES A\ S ENT&amp; AND THE<br />
IS11TUTO PER LA RhCOISTRUZJ) NE INDUSTRIALE ( I1U) HAVE INDICATELD<br />
HOW CORPORATIONS CAN PLAY A VITAL ROLE IN MODERATE SIZED COUNTT~<br />
WITH LIMITED RESOURCE CAPITAL, </p>
<p>V u<br />
HAVING OUTLINED OUR INTENTIONS IN THIS FIELD,<br />
IREPEAT THAT THE GOVERNMENT 5THll. SEES A PLACE FOR FOREIG6N<br />
INVESTMENT IN AUSTRA~ I-A, WE ARE APPt-YING OUR POLIC'Y IN A<br />
PRAGMATIC WAY AND WE ARE EXAMINIIJING ALL CASES ON THEIR<br />
INDIVIDUAL MLR1TS. WE AIM TO MAKE OUR JUDGEMENTS ' FAKING INTO<br />
ACCOUNT THE FULL CIRCUMSTANCES OF EACH NEW PROJFCT, INCLUDfNG<br />
SUCH FACTORS AS THE SIZE AND LOCATION OF THE PROPOSED PROJECT,<br />
' fH1 USE MADE OF ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY, MARKETING ARR~ ANGEMENTS,<br />
ENVIRONMENTAL ASPECTS, LABOUR RELATIONS AND) ABORIGINAL INTERESTS<br />
THIS W1LL NOT DENY PRODUCTIVE INVESTMENT, IN PARTNERSHIP WITH<br />
(\ U&amp; iTRALIANi CAPITAL, WHICIH1 ADDS TO OUR REAL RESOUR~ CES,<br />
[ IHERE IS THEREFORE EVERY 0, P PORTUN ITY FOR FRUITFUL<br />
ITALIAN 11NVESTMENT 1N AUSTRALIA. WHILE RECOGNISIN4G OUR NEED<br />
TO PROTECT OUR NATIONAL INTCRESTSI ITALIAN ) NVESTORS CAN<br />
BENEFIT FROM AUSTRALIA'S RESOURCES AND INDUSTRIAL OPPORTUNI. T! ES,<br />
A\ USTRALIA IN TURN CAN BENEFIT FROI-ITALIAN TECHNOLOGY AND<br />
CAP I AL. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
