<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8125</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR 13 SEPTEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/09/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008125.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR<br />
13 SEPTEMBER 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
WENDT: Prime Minister, thank you very much for your time<br />
this evening.<br />
PM: Pleasure Jana.<br />
WENDT: You are heading off to Tokyo to try to convince<br />
Olympic Federation members that Melbourne should get<br />
their vote. Are you convinced that a Melbourne Olympics<br />
would be a profitable venture for Australia?<br />
PM: Yes, I believe so. The last two have been and there<br />
has been very very meticulous planning gone into this,<br />
not only at the governmental level but importantly, from<br />
the point of view of the business sector as well.<br />
Melbourne's very well placed to conduct a successful and<br />
profitable Olympic Games.<br />
WENDT: Your former Finance Minister, Peter Walsh, says<br />
that Australia would actually lose money on this. What<br />
do you say to that?<br />
PM: Well Walsh is a professional pessimist. If you look<br />
at the reason he gave, it's contradicted by the facts.<br />
As I said in the Parliament, Peter Walsh never lets a few<br />
facts get in the way of his well-honed prejudices.<br />
WENDT: You say that you are confident in the unions'<br />
ability in Victoria to deliver on all of this. Are you<br />
prepared to go so far as to give a guarantee that any<br />
works that are undertaken would be completed on time for<br />
any Olympics?<br />
PM: Yes indeed, and that's what I'll be saying at the<br />
meeting in Tokyo..<br />
WENDT: I did want to raise with you another persistent<br />
and more senior Labor critic of yours, and that is former<br />
Prime Minister Gough Whitlam. He's criticised you on the<br />
basis of our Gulf commitment, he's criticised you on the<br />
basis of Aboriginal land rights, on privatisation, on<br />
education, on arts spending. It's a long long list. Do<br />
you take any of it on board? </p>
<p>PM: No, I don't. As I said before, when it gets to the<br />
area of economic criticism it's equivalent, as I said, to<br />
getting advice on firefighting from Nero. I would've<br />
thought that the last area that Mr Whitlam would want to<br />
be talking about would be anything that involved<br />
Australia's relations with Iraq. I don't want to develop<br />
that point but anyone who knows anything about the<br />
politics of this country knows exactly what I mean.<br />
WENDT: His track record on that isn't exactly good, is<br />
it? PM: Well you said it Jana.<br />
WENDT: I'd like to move on a bit to our involvement in<br />
the Gulf.<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
0 WENDT: In retrospect, and leaving the principle aside,<br />
do you think that you may have been hasty in committing<br />
us in the way that you did?<br />
PM: Absolutely not. I wouldn't have done one thing<br />
differently. WENDT: Can I get just some of the chronology straight.<br />
Did the United States ask us to commit to the Gulf?<br />
PM: No, I made it quite clear. What happened was that<br />
discussions arose in Washington about the issue of forces<br />
in the Gulf. There was no request from the United States<br />
nor offer from us out of the discussions that went on in<br />
Washington and the discussions that went on here. I came<br />
to the conclusion in discussion with my relevant<br />
Ministers that it was appropriate in terms of Australia's<br />
interests and in terms of Australia's global<br />
responsibilities that we should be part of a<br />
multinational naval force.<br />
WENDT: So there was no formal request from the United<br />
States? PM: No, the issue just came up in discussions about<br />
there were going to be multinational naval forces and in<br />
those discussions the questions arose of, well, Australia<br />
could be there. When it came to me for consideration and<br />
decision, I had absolutely no doubt as to what the right<br />
decision was and neither did my Ministers.<br />
WENDT: There has been a degree of confusion about the<br />
terms of engagement. Today we hear from Senator Ray that<br />
our ships will have to contact him before they fire. How<br />
practically will that work?<br />
PM: How practically will it work? I mean we have modern<br />
and very swift means of communication. That's how it<br />
will work. And may I say that this has been worked out </p>
<p>in full conjunction with and co-operation with and<br />
endorsement of the Royal Australian Navy.<br />
WENDT: But literally, how practically does it work. Is<br />
Senator Ray attached to the phone all day long, or how<br />
does it work?<br />
PM: You know, we live in a modern world with marvels<br />
of communication are there. This is the way it should<br />
happen. It's the way the Navy expects it to happen.<br />
WENDT: Prime Minister, I'd like to move on again, to<br />
China. In the wake of the Tienanmen Square massacre your<br />
Government imposed severe restrictions on Parliamentary<br />
visits to China. Why did you do that?<br />
PM: Because we had to give an immediate indication to<br />
China of the fact that what had occurred was unacceptable<br />
and like the rest of the world we made a range of<br />
decisions to register our protest.<br />
WENDT: Why then give your blessing to the visit of a<br />
Federal Minister, Dr Blewett?<br />
PM: Because as I said at the time, we in Australia, as<br />
indeed in the rest of the world, had to walk the<br />
difficult line, Jana, between continuing to let China<br />
know the unacceptability of their actions but also<br />
keeping open the lines of communication and economic cooperation.<br />
Because what's in the interests of the people<br />
of China, as it is as much in the interests of the people<br />
of the world, is that there be economic co-operation so<br />
that there be the opportunity for the further opening up<br />
of China to the rest of the world. The worst thing that<br />
could happen for the people of China and for those people<br />
in China who want to see change, would be to see the<br />
world cut China off.<br />
WENDT: Gareth Evans conceded that the visit of Gough<br />
Whitlam to China would give the Chinese some comfort.<br />
What do you think was the propaganda value of Dr<br />
Blewett's visit?<br />
PM: I have no doubt, Jana, that in some ways the<br />
leadership in China would try and maximise what value<br />
they could from it. But if you just said, and the other<br />
countries of the world just said well there is a risk<br />
that a visit would be propagandised, then as I say, we'd<br />
just close ourselves off entirely from China. That would<br />
not be in the interests of the people of China.<br />
WENDT: Premier Li Peng has said that the clouds<br />
attempting to isolate China are dispersing. Have we been<br />
partly responsible for conveying that message to the<br />
Chinese? </p>
<p>PM: I can assure you that Dr Blewett was assiduous in<br />
detail in making clear to the leadership of China our<br />
continuing rejection of what happened last year.<br />
WENDT: But Mr Hawke, when Mr Fischer in the Nationals<br />
was to go to China, your Foreign Minister flayed them for<br />
even suggesting it.<br />
PM: Yes, and there is nothing reprehensible about that.<br />
We were in a stage where we had said from the beginning<br />
that the policy towards China would be one of continual<br />
review. We didn't believe it was for the Opposition to<br />
be taking an initiative in the area of foreign affairs<br />
which was inconsistent with what the country, through its<br />
Government, was doing.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, what is the difference? You have a top<br />
level mission going to China.<br />
PM: The Government is the one which sets the policy for<br />
the country in regard to its relations with the rest of<br />
the world. It is appropriate that people and<br />
organisations within a nation should operate within the<br />
framework of the policy set by Government.<br />
WENDT: Isn't it logical though that China would now<br />
assume that our memory of the Tienanimen Square massacre<br />
is fading?<br />
PM: If you read precisely what Dr Blewett had said, and<br />
with a great deal of firmness to the leadership in China,<br />
including may I say a declining on the part of Dr Blewett<br />
to see Li Peng, you would understand that both by word<br />
and by deed there can be no misunderstanding on the part<br />
of the leadership of China about Australia's position in<br />
regard to the events of last year.<br />
WENDT: If they are your Government's feelings, why<br />
reward them on a propaganda level with a visit by a<br />
senior Australian politician?<br />
PM: Well obviously you've got your view Jana. You don't<br />
want to be persuaded by facts and there's nothing more I<br />
can say other than to repeat to you what I've said. You<br />
don't want to accept it but I'll say it again because its<br />
relevant to the question you put again, and that is that<br />
it is in the interests of the people of China, it is in<br />
the interests of the people of China, the people that we<br />
are concerned about and what in your questions I assume<br />
you are concerned about, it is in their interests, and it<br />
is so recognised by others, that the worst thing that you<br />
could do for the people of China, including those who<br />
want change, is that China should be isolated.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, wouldn't it also be logical to conclude<br />
that your own display of emotion on this was just in fact<br />
a display, if this is your attitude now? </p>
<p>PM: That is a despicable and contemptible observation<br />
because you have no reason to believe, and there is no<br />
reason in fact to suggest that my emotions were anything<br />
other than the totally genuine reflection of the<br />
abhorrence that I felt. I find your observation<br />
repugnant in the extreme.<br />
WENDT: And yet you are prepared to hold hands on an<br />
official level with that government now.<br />
PM: I'm not holding hands with that government at an<br />
official level in a way which says anything other than<br />
the repugnance that I felt last year is as deeply felt<br />
now. We continue to say to them that their record on<br />
human rights is unacceptable. As far as our judgement,<br />
and the judgements of others is concerned, that the best<br />
thing that we can do for the people of China in terms of<br />
maximising the chance that they will get a regime and a<br />
practice which recognises human rights more effectively,<br />
is that they are not isolated from the rest of the world.<br />
Those are positions which I've taken in total good faith.<br />
WENDT: Would it be fair for an outsider to say that it<br />
looks like, well, we need them commercially so we'll<br />
jettison our values?<br />
PM: Jana it would be fair for you to say that if you are<br />
absolutely intent upon not accepting the good faith with<br />
which I put my position.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, we'll leave it there. Thank you.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
ends<br />
0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
