<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3096</transcript-id>
    <title>ANNUAL LEAVE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003096.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSiX AIAAg<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 159<br />
December 1973<br />
ANNUAL LEAVE<br />
The Australian Government has decided to introduce<br />
legislation to provide for the payment of an annual leave loading<br />
to all its employees of the Australian Government. I<br />
The legislation which will be introduced to the Parliament<br />
next year will provide for the payment of a loading of an amount<br />
equal to average weekly earnings of all adult male wage and salary<br />
earners as disclosed by the Statistician for the September quarter<br />
immediately preceding the accrual of such leave.<br />
It will apply to leave accruing on or after 1 January 1974.<br />
The legislation will not seek to cover leave accruing in<br />
1973. However, when the various Public Service Unions' claims on<br />
annual leave loadings come before the Arbitrator, the Government will<br />
indicate that it would raise no objections to an interim settlement<br />
in respect of leave accruing on or after 1 January 1973 on the<br />
following basis:<br />
An annual leave loading of 17 per cent of the<br />
employees salary at date of accrual, for the<br />
period of leave accrued at that date, subject<br />
to the total bonus payment not exceeding the<br />
equivalent of the average weekly earnings figure<br />
for the September quarter of the preceding year,<br />
or alternatively, the * shift loading which the<br />
employee would have received had he been on annual<br />
leave if such shift loading exceeds the leave bonus.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
