<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5591</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF ACROD HOUSE, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/05/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005591.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA WEDNESDAY, 20 MAY 1981<br />
OPENING OF ACROD HOUSE, CANBERRA<br />
This is an occasion both for congratulations and for renewed<br />
commitment. This building symbolises a realistic concern for<br />
the well-being of disabled persons within the Australian<br />
community. I have no doubt that this building will be symbolic<br />
of the new hope, and the larger expectations which disabled<br />
persons now have.<br />
And let me say how little I like the term " disabled", which is<br />
a total misnomer for people who are very able indeed in their<br />
various ways. Life now offers a great deal to many people<br />
who, in previous generations, were thought to be at<br />
best-incurable. Too often in the past, and doubtless in some<br />
countries even today, the disabled were ignored, or shut away.<br />
We are now realising more and more that disabled persons<br />
should be treated as-having-essentially-the-same. rights, needs<br />
and aspirations, as other members of our comrmunity. And<br />
indeed, the United Nations Declaration of the Rights of<br />
Disabled Persons is an integral part of the Parliamentary Act<br />
which will govern the operations of our new Human Rights<br />
Commission. Disabled persons shouid be encouraged to develop their capacities<br />
to the fullest extent. Disabled persons should also be<br />
enabled, so far as possible, to live with their families in<br />
the general community. Many disabled people are now able to<br />
live almost completely normal lives, whereas only a very few<br />
years ago, everyone assumed that such people could have none<br />
of the . satisfactions of a normal. life, or an independent life<br />
of their own. But now the whole world recognises that the<br />
potentiality of disabled people has been greatly underestimated,<br />
-and that approaches to rehabilitation have been vastly inadequate.<br />
When I had the privilege last year of launching John Hickman's<br />
book One SteD at a Time, I spoke of the way he coped with<br />
the tasks of everyday living, spending a night away from home,<br />
cooking a meal for himself, emptying the vacuum cleaner,<br />
even hitting Sir Garfield Sobers for six, taking on the<br />
bureaucracy, and occasionally winning. It was miraculous that<br />
he could do these things, but increasingly, we want disabled<br />
persons to be doing them as a matter of course. / 12 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
1981 is the International Year of Disabled Persons. Only a<br />
decade or so ago, the idea of having such a year would have<br />
been unthinkable. We now recognise that disabled persons have<br />
a contribution to make to the life of the world. Remarkable<br />
changes have occurred in community attitudes in a comparatively<br />
short-time. Of course, there is still far to go. But I am<br />
confident that the activities of this year will be a worthwhile<br />
contribution in removing the old ideas and myths. Once it is<br />
accepted that the disabled are full members of the family and<br />
society, then employment opportunities must be extended, to<br />
ensure that the disabled can really participate as full members__-<br />
of society, able to make their own separate contributions.<br />
This will give further substance to the theme chosen by the<br />
United Nations for the International Year of the Disabled<br />
Persons " Full Participation and Equality". And after this<br />
special year, there will be need for consolidation of the<br />
gains that have been made, and an appraisal of further directions<br />
and further gains which need to be pursued in the years ahead.<br />
Nearly every statement of human objectives in nearly every<br />
culture assigns a high value to work as part of the complete<br />
life. Work plays an important role in personal self-fulfillment<br />
and achievement. Productive employment is, therefore, widely<br />
regarded as a crucial component in a rehabilitation programme.<br />
Day after day passing by without the challenge of tasks to be<br />
performed can be depressing indeed. Mr Watts has told us that<br />
it is something like 45 years since the idea of a national<br />
body specifically concerned with disabled persons was first<br />
discussed. Since-that--time--en-ormous-str-ides--have been made.<br />
ACROD House is the culmination of considerable efforts.<br />
It will certainly provide a focal point for the organisation<br />
at the national level of programmes directed to achieve the<br />
full participation and equality of disabled persons in the--<br />
life of the community. The building provides a wonderful<br />
facility. And it is an exemfplar of how architects should<br />
take account of the particular requirements of the disabled.<br />
But of course it cannot substitute for the efforts and the<br />
dedication of those who are concerned to bring about in<br />
increasing measure the full participation and equality to<br />
which I have referred.<br />
This Government has a very strong commitment indeed to the<br />
goals of ACROD. I am very pleased about the Government<br />
contribution for meeting the cost of this building. We are<br />
also proud that over a billion dollars is being spent in<br />
this financial year on programmes for the handicapped and<br />
the disabled, this is more than double the amount of five<br />
years ago, and it is a very considerable increase indeed<br />
in real terms.-It is money well spent. And let me say that<br />
one of the benefits of the policy of financial restraint and<br />
responsibility we have consistently followed is that we have<br />
been able to do more in areas which we regard as of high<br />
priority. Programs for the handicapped and the disabled have<br />
this high priority. For not only are these programmes designed<br />
to help those who have one of the most legitimate claims of all<br />
to make upon the community. </p>
<p>-3<br />
In' addition, our programmes help disabled persons to enjoy<br />
the satisfactions and independence which are essential to the<br />
way of life which we seek for this country, we also seek to<br />
help disabled persons to play a more productive role in. the<br />
community. Our approach is to treat the disabled asindividuals<br />
who can gain acceptance and employment in their<br />
own right, although they may need special training and<br />
support so that they can be employed. Assistance to ACROD<br />
so that it can have its own headquarters, as a focal point<br />
in the national capital, is a tangible bricks and mortar<br />
contribution in the International Year of Disabled Persons.<br />
Our other activities are designed to achieve the longer-term<br />
objectives related to awareness and employment. A key element..<br />
in our approach to help the disabled find satisfying work<br />
is a national employment strategy for the disabled, which was<br />
launched last month. The objective behind the strategy is<br />
to place more disabled persons in employment and training,<br />
and to ensure that they are given an equal opportunity in<br />
the . Labour market. Of course, not all disabled persons can<br />
find work in the open market, and we will continue to support<br />
sheltered workshops as well as rewarding training schemes.<br />
The Commonwealth is also looking at its own buildings to<br />
ensure that they are accessible to the disabled, both as<br />
clients and employees..<br />
I believe that the efforts being made in Australia to make<br />
certain-. that disabled persons are fully involved will enrich<br />
tie_--ife-of our community. All credit to AC. ROD for what it<br />
has done, and all credit to the whole Australian community<br />
for its increasing maturity in recognising the rights of<br />
the disabled. I-ay this building be the means of wider<br />
participation and greater equality in Australia. It gives<br />
me great pleasure to open this building, and to unveil this<br />
plaque. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
