<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9874</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING COUNCIL MEETING</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009874.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 143/ S<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING COUNCIL MEETING<br />
The Prime Minister's Science and Engineering Council ( PMSEC) met today in<br />
Canberra to consider the application of science and technology to managing our<br />
oceans, and developing our plantation forests.<br />
Today's meeting has been valuable to the Government in spelling out the major role<br />
of science and technology in these crucial environmental and resource areas. The<br />
reports, presentations and discussions at today's meeting have given us clear<br />
messages about promoting and using science for sustainable development of some<br />
of our most valuable and promising resource areas. I have asked the Ministers for<br />
Primary Industries and Energy, Industry, Science and Technology, and the<br />
Environment, Sport and Territories, to follow up the key issues emerging from today,<br />
and report on how we can ensure that the best science applied to preserving and<br />
developing the Exclusive Economic Zone and our plantation forests.'<br />
The discussion at today's PMSEC meeting was based on papers and presentations<br />
by independent working groups of scientists and industry leaders.<br />
The paper " Australia's Ocean Age: Science and Technology for Managing our<br />
Ocean Territory" focussed on how science and technology can assist in the effective<br />
management of Australia's marine resources. Australia now has a responsibility<br />
under the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea to further advance<br />
exploration and marine research, so as to sustainably develop, preserve and protect<br />
the marine environment.<br />
The paper and presentation on ' Research and Development Contributing to<br />
Plantation Forestry' examined the substantial and growing contribution which<br />
plantation forests make to our supply of wood products, and the major value-adding<br />
roles of research and development in improving the sustainability and yields of<br />
plantation forests, and in the use of plantation-grown timber. The Council heard of<br />
the close collaboration which has developed between researchers and industry,<br />
leading to the successful application of research to the management, sustainability<br />
and productivity of our forest plantations. </p>
<p>The PMSEC meeting also heard presehntations on the Government's innovation<br />
statement released earlier this week, including the specific projects which will be<br />
funded under the $ 62.4 million Major National Research Facilities program; Science<br />
and Technology in APEC; and Australia's science and engineering base for<br />
information and communications services and technologies.<br />
I also informed the meeting today that the Chief Scientist would become a statutory<br />
office holder within my portfolio. This will build on the current arrangements for<br />
science and technology, and increase the already high profile given to science and<br />
technology by the Government.<br />
The Council ( PMSEC) was created as part of the advisory and coordination<br />
arrangements announced in the May 1989 science and technology policy statement.<br />
It meets twice a year, to provide a major forum for consideration of issues of national<br />
significance in science and technology, with a particular emphasis on the application<br />
of research to economic and social objectives. This provides an opportunity for the<br />
Prime Minister and senior Ministers to discuss issues with leaders of science,<br />
industry, and the major scientific institutions.<br />
CANBERRA 8 DECEMBER, 1995<br />
Further information:<br />
Office of the Chief Scientist:<br />
Dr Guy Verney<br />
ph ( 06) 271 5209<br />
The paper'Australia's Ocean Age: Science and Technology for Managing our Ocean<br />
Territory' is available from:<br />
Office of the Chief Scientist<br />
Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet<br />
National Circuit<br />
BARTON ACT 2600<br />
or from the world wide web at:<br />
http:// www. nla. gov. au/ pmc/ ocs/ ocean. html<br />
or from Australian Government Publishing Service outlets. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
