<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3615</transcript-id>
    <title>URBAN AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT AGREEMENT WITH TASMANIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003615.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J,, AusrHA1.1A<br />
PRIME MINISTER Press Statement No. 451<br />
14 February 1975<br />
URBAN AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT<br />
AGREEMENT WITH TASMANIA<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, and the Tasmanian<br />
Premier, Mr Reece, today signed two agreements relating<br />
to the Australian Government's Urban and Regional<br />
Development program.<br />
The two agreements will provide Tasmania with financial<br />
assistance of more than $ 3 million.<br />
Under the Sewerage Program $ 2,300,000 will be made<br />
available to provide environmentally acceptable sewerage<br />
facilities, and to protect water supplies from pollution.<br />
A contribution of $ 450,000 will go to Hobart to assist in<br />
preventing the discharge of raw sewage into the River Derwent.<br />
The program also covers the treatment of industrial wastes.<br />
Tasmania will receive a total. of $ 895,277 for National<br />
Estate projects for the present financial year. Restoration<br />
work will be carried out on many historic buildings including<br />
St Georges Church, Battery Point ($ 20,000) the Theatre<br />
Royal, Hobart ($ 15,000) and the Courthouse, Town Hall<br />
and Old Goal at Oatlands ($ 20,000).<br />
Conservation studies will be carried out at Longford,<br />
Bothwell, Oatlands and Campbell Town.<br />
one grant will go towards a photogr--phic study of the<br />
wilderness and recreational aspects of tCe South West region,<br />
and another will be for a conservation/ lcndscape study of<br />
the Tasman Valley with particular reference to the woodchip<br />
industry and industrial development in the region.<br />
The Prime Minister said: " The conclusion of these<br />
agreements is evidence of the co-operative endeavours of<br />
our two Governments in promoting sound urban development<br />
and enhancing the environment.<br />
Tasmania has already set a fine example to the rest<br />
of Australia in the preservation of historic buildings.<br />
I look forward to visiting Hobart this weekend and<br />
being able to see for myself the results of restoration work<br />
already carried ? ut inh1e Hobar ctyvaaea seially at<br />
the Theatre Roya lwhic hsJustrecieleaa grant-c<br />
and ivni iitgne CL t( 1CL1HitU ABRR. ACT<br />
and in the village ot Richmond. CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
