<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4778</transcript-id>
    <title>ABC COUNTRY HOUR - COLIN MUNROE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004778.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 16 AUGUST 1978<br />
ABC COUNTRY HOUR COLIN MUNROE<br />
Question: Last night's Budget has been variously described by Mr. Hamer<br />
as severe, by Mr. Hayden as brutal, by Mr. Hawke as<br />
horrendous. How do you see it?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I believe it is a responsible Budget and one that is very<br />
necessary for Australia in 1978 and beyond. We've made<br />
considerable progress in getting inflation down, in getting<br />
stability into wages and the economic structure of this<br />
country. But we all know that inflation is still too high.<br />
Now as a result of this Budget, the Treasury forecastsafter<br />
a rate of inflation of 5 percent, by next June or earlier.<br />
You know that's not a politician's forecast, that the<br />
Treasury forecast. That will put us below the OECD average,<br />
all of the countries, it might only be Germany and Japan<br />
with lower rates of inflation than that and for Australia's<br />
exporters, getting inflation down, keeping it down, is of<br />
enormous importance. I think Australia's farmers will never<br />
forget the year 1974 or so, when farm costs went up 30% in<br />
one year. Now we've stabilised farm costs. Outlook for<br />
farmers of all kinds I think is better than its been for<br />
many years. There is optimism in the bush of a kind I<br />
haven't perceived I don't think I can remember it for<br />
maybe ten or fifteen years and stability in costs is essential<br />
to enable exporters to get the advantage of markets overseas<br />
and of the better prices we are now seeing.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, I take your point, but it has been suggested<br />
that last night's introduction of quite severe indirect<br />
taxes will have the effect of slowing the movement of the<br />
economy. That it will improve much less quickly than you<br />
would perhaps like.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think that's so, because the health financing changes,<br />
together with the reduced sales tax on motor cars, which a<br />
lot of people are forgetting and that's a very substantial<br />
benefit to any purchaser of a car; these two measures will<br />
more than outweigh the CPI effects of the indirect taxes<br />
and taking the Budget as a whole, the total effect on the<br />
Consumer Price Index will be in the right direction. Whatever<br />
the CPI would be in December, the impact of this Budget will<br />
be to reduce it by about half a percent from what it<br />
otherwise have been. So the movement downward in inflation<br />
is reinforced by this particular Budget. / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
Now, if the movement down in inflation is reinforced, I<br />
think that brings us closer to the time when you can get<br />
a more significant movement downwards in interest rates.<br />
So far we have had very significant movements down in<br />
finance company rates, in Government Bond rates. We<br />
haven't seen the real result, we've had a half a percent<br />
result in the home building area the permanent building<br />
society but we haven't seen the result in bank overdraft<br />
rates and I think that's what people are looking for.<br />
Question: It would seem the Budget places greater reliance on the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Commission to keep wages and<br />
indirect taxes out of the CPI. Now what if wages and<br />
salary earners go outside the Conciliation area?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Wage earners, salary earners, in Australia have got two<br />
choices. They can take one of two choices: they can show<br />
greater sense and moderation in their wage and salary<br />
demands, and thus help this nation get more people back<br />
into employment; or they can press for higher wages and<br />
salaries, for themselves, for those in work, at the expense<br />
of those out of work and if they do that I can guarantee<br />
that unemployment will stay high. Against the kinds of<br />
wage demands that we've seen, against the situation in which<br />
wages went up under Labor by 50% over a two-year period,<br />
there is nothing that can be done about unemployment unless<br />
there is moderation in wage demands. I think one of the<br />
great tragedies of the trade union movement is that the<br />
leadership hasn't been prepared to argue for moderation;<br />
argue for a restoration of the profitability of industry<br />
whether its farming or other that's quite essential for<br />
people to be employed.<br />
Question: How much reliance are you placing on overseas investment<br />
to get the Australian economy moving?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think reliance is probably the wrong way of looking at<br />
it. Could I put it this way? If we get the basic underlying<br />
taxes in the Australian economy right, inflation down,<br />
interest rates down, stability in Australia, reasonable<br />
industrial relations, then that's good for investment from<br />
Australians in Australia, internal investment, and that will<br />
occur under those circumstances. Because we are a resource<br />
rich country, we will also attract more than our fair share<br />
of investment from overseas under these circumstances, because<br />
you know with inflation under the world average, this is<br />
going to be good for exporters and it will be good for<br />
investment and both of that is good for jobs. / 13 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Question: 16 cents a gallon on petrol, let alone any other costs<br />
that may be incurred in diesel and in that area. It's<br />
been said by various primary producer organisations this<br />
morning that the effect will be traumatic and its also<br />
been pointed out that perhaps the Treasurer has ignored<br />
that fuel is an essential and not a luxury in rural<br />
Australia. Prime Minister:<br />
It is an essential and its certainly not a luxury in<br />
rural Australia. But at the same time, I am a farmer myself<br />
and I don't do much work, I don't do any work on the far,<br />
but I do look at the balance sheet at the end of each year.<br />
So I do know exactly what part fuel goes to make up costs<br />
of running a property.<br />
Question: 16 cents a gallon, sir, is going to knock around your<br />
balance sheet.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
It will put up the cost of fuel, but I know the proportion<br />
of the total costs fuel is, and it maybe is not as high as<br />
is sometimes stated. But, it's significant, but against<br />
that you've got to look at the benefits that are coming to<br />
the rural community from much lower inflation and as exporters<br />
they benefit from that as they well know, enormously.<br />
Getting interest rates down will much much more compensate<br />
for any additional the rural community as a whole much<br />
much more than compensate for any increases in petrol taxes.<br />
Question:<br />
You talk about help. to primary producers. It has also<br />
been said this morning that is little help to primary<br />
producers in the Budget and that great reliance has been<br />
placed on the weather in fact.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think so, no. The weather is important, and one of<br />
the good things about primary industries at the moment is<br />
that most of Australia is looking forward to better seasons<br />
than we have had for a very long while. But, we've done a<br />
number of things; better access to markets overseas, for<br />
beef, especially in Japan and the United States which is<br />
utterly critical to a large part of rural Australia and<br />
in addition to that with the real prospects of a return to<br />
better incomes, the benefits of tax averaging which is much<br />
much better than anything there before; the benefits of<br />
the income equalisation deposit scheme will start to be of<br />
real benefit to farmers. I think that the income equalisation<br />
deposits have had $ 60 million to $ 70 million invested in them<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
over the time, but with the return to better incomes,<br />
I would expect those deposits to grow greatly.<br />
Question: On the point of IED's and tied in with the Primary<br />
Industry's Bank, there * as no spelling out last night<br />
of interest rate for the Primary Industry Bank and there<br />
has been extreme criticism this morning that TED's should<br />
be used to fund that Bank. It's virtually farmers lending<br />
money to themselves.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
You mean farmers don't want the TED's used?<br />
Question: That's the message I get.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I have had it put the other way around, that farmer<br />
organisations did want TED's used inthe Primary Industry<br />
Bank and that's the view that had been put I think when<br />
farm organisations were discussing these matters in the<br />
Cabinet room with us. So, if they are now saying they<br />
don't want the TED's used, I think that's... . you know it's<br />
not going to restrict any person' s right to withdraw their<br />
IED's under the circumstances and I would have thought it<br />
was a pretty natural development.<br />
Question: Isn't it a fact though, that the Primary Producers would<br />
be lending money to themselves. They put money into the<br />
IED's, they get a certain interest rate, a small one, and<br />
then they borrow back from the Primary Industry Bank<br />
well it's been measured at 11%, what is the interest rate?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
The interest rate is I think around about that sort of<br />
order. But it's the term of the loan which is going to be<br />
the great advantage in the Primary Industry Bank and if you<br />
look at the finance that is available for farmers, its<br />
the terms of repayment that is the most important factor in<br />
the burden on a particular farmer. Now the interest rates<br />
have got to be related to some extent to the general level<br />
of interest rates and as we get interest rates down overall,<br />
obviously the interest rates on Primary Industry Bank loans<br />
would come down as would other bank loans come down. But<br />
I can't understand the argument that TED's have a small<br />
interest rate paid on them and the money is being lent back<br />
at a higher rate of interest. There is a very considerable<br />
tax advantage in TED's which farmers well know and that's<br />
the very precise reason why the interest rate is small. </p>
<p>Prime Minister: ( continued)<br />
The advantage would be inequitable in relation to other<br />
people in Australia if it was getting a commercial rate<br />
of interest in view of the tax advantage.<br />
Question: If I could leave the question of the IED's and the<br />
Primary Industry Bank there and ask-. you whatever happened<br />
to decentralisation?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
The best decentralisation in one sense is profitable<br />
Australian industries; profitable Australian rural industries,<br />
because this means much more to Australian country towns<br />
than anything else. But we did establish last year a<br />
Decentralisation Board and more funds are being provided<br />
to that to encourage enterprises in decentralised centres.<br />
Quite obviously, in this Budget, there are no massive<br />
funds to be put into that particular Board but there is an<br />
increase, it is gearing up, it is starting to make funds<br />
available and its work will be proceeding.<br />
Question: Telecom: Virtually running their own business, does this<br />
mean that the Government has given away any idea of reducing<br />
telephone and communication charges to country people in<br />
Au s t r alia.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No. I think you will note that the off-peak charges were<br />
reduced a short while ago and that is a help. In the country<br />
areas a good deal of business can be done out of hours.<br />
Agents business and this sort of thing and that's the way<br />
its gone for a long period. The Government remains of course<br />
very much involved in policy but I think it needs to be<br />
remembered that while Telecom technically makes a profit.<br />
their capital requirements are so large they still have to<br />
borrow very considerable funds for their total capital program.<br />
Question:<br />
More of your time if I may. You moved in the Budget a possible<br />
reintroduction of the beef export levy, but it will be<br />
held over for a while. Is there a chance there will be a<br />
mini-Budget with that sort of thing introduced in it?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think I would regard that as a mini-Budget. What<br />
we are concerned about is the profitability of the beef<br />
industry and while the prospects look very much better now<br />
than they did twelve months ago or even six months ago, and<br />
everyone knows the reason for this, with the industry running<br />
along normally and profitably its fair enough for some<br />
of these things to be recouped from the industries concerned. 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
When the industry had been hit, we thought well it should<br />
be a charge on the Government, but we didn't want to put<br />
a charge on, at this point, because it is earlier in the<br />
stage of recovery of the beef industry. We wanted to<br />
make quite sure that the recovery trends were confirmed<br />
before moving in that kind of direction.<br />
Question: If the strengths of your Budget, as you see it, don't<br />
take effect, you've mooted that there could be a reduction<br />
in the Public Service and in fact unemployment could<br />
increase. This must-concern you.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Of course unemployment concerns us. But everyone in<br />
Australia has got to understand what causes unemployment,<br />
and Governments can do something about it but Governments<br />
at the same time need the cooperation of other people in<br />
relation to unemployment. If leaders of the trade union<br />
movement are to continue to press for wages running ahead<br />
higher than the Consumer Price Index, the prospects for<br />
getting unemployment down are very much diminished. In<br />
spite of all the arguments we've put to the Arbitration<br />
Commission over the last two years, in the twelve months<br />
to June, average wages increased more than the Consumer<br />
Price Index. Now that doesn't indicate any restraint at<br />
all on the part of the leaders of the trade union movement.<br />
And again, its worth noting that this is something of<br />
very real concern to exporters, farmers, manufacturers,<br />
producers everywhere because its the productive life of the<br />
country which enables the jobs to be provided.<br />
Question:<br />
What do you think you will be able to say when you sit here<br />
next year in August, to the people of rural Australiaat the<br />
end of this 1978-79 Budget year?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think we will be able to say to you, this much does depend<br />
upon forces quite outside my control; you've had a good season,<br />
all the omens are for a good season so lets take that as<br />
read. At the opening of the wool sales the prices were edging up,<br />
so the prospects for wool and for sheep prices remaining good<br />
are very very high. The cattle market is firm and I believe<br />
it will get even better throughout the course of the next<br />
12 months. I know some people haven't been able to sow their<br />
wheat because it has been too wet, but for those that do, the<br />
crops should be good and the price will-be good. So I believe<br />
we will be able to look back and say we've got inflation down<br />
further, significantly further, we are now well belowe the OECD<br />
average. There are only one or two significant countries with<br />
a lower rate of inflation than Australia. We are becoming more<br />
competitive. Our markets overseas are consolidating. You've<br />
had a good year and I'll look forward to the future with a<br />
great degree of confidence. </p>
<p>Question: And does that air of confidence carry through to the<br />
community as a whole.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I believe so and I hope so. And out in rural Australia<br />
I really believe this confidence is already abroad. I<br />
don't know how much you've been out and about over the<br />
last two to three months but there's a tremendous different<br />
atmosphere from six months ago or twelve months ago.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
