<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5051</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005051.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2,<br />
22 MAY 1979<br />
STATEMENT TO PARLIAMENT<br />
During the five days I was away from Australia I had discussions<br />
with Presidents Marcos and Soeharto and Prime Minister Ohira<br />
of Japan, and addressed the UNCTAD meeting in Manila.<br />
This series of discussions was held against the background of<br />
significant changes in the international strategic situation.<br />
There is continuing instability in Africa and parts of the<br />
Middle East. Developments in Iran continue to generate<br />
anxiety regarding oil supplies and about the security of the<br />
north west Indian Ocean area. In Korea, new assessments of the<br />
north's military strength have placed * this at a significantly<br />
higher level than had previously been estimated, and concern<br />
over security in the Korean Peninsula has led to adoption of<br />
a longer time scale for United States ground troop-withdrawals<br />
from the Fepublic of Korea. Hostilities continue in Indo-China<br />
as Vietnam attempts to consolidate its posieion in Kampuchea.<br />
The tensions which led to fighting between China and Vietnam<br />
are still in evidence. A resurgence of fighting would lead to<br />
the danger of wider international involvement.<br />
In this international environment my discussions with<br />
President Marcos and President Soeharto made clear our common<br />
recognition that broadly based co-operation between Australia,<br />
the Philippines and Indonesia and between Australia and<br />
the other members of ASEAN has become all the more<br />
important. We recognise our responsibility to press for<br />
moderation and conciliation in the conduct of international<br />
affairs. The movement toward greater cohesion among ASEAN countries is<br />
of particular importance to Australia' s interests. It provides<br />
mutual support, promotes co-operation, strengthens confidence<br />
and assists forces for stable development. Accordingly, Australia<br />
seeks to strengthen our links with the ASEAN countries.<br />
my talks with President Marcos made manifest that Australia<br />
and the Philippines, as members of the same region with<br />
similar interests and attitudes, have a joint desire and<br />
determination to work together to respond effectively to the<br />
strains and tensions in the international situation.-We both<br />
welcomed the normalisation of relations between Peking and<br />
Washington. It will assist the development of a more effective<br />
U. S. policy in the Pacific and Asia, which had been hampered<br />
by the absence of formal recognition. Jjj AUS f RALIA </p>
<p>-2<br />
Normalisation,* and the conclusion of the friendship treaty<br />
between China and Japan, creates new opportunities for these<br />
countries to play a positive and constructive role in the<br />
Asia/ Pacific region. We expressed the hope that the Soviet<br />
Union would make a similar constructive contribution to the<br />
peacef * ul development of the region a contribution which<br />
would be of particular importance because there are areas in<br />
which the Soviet Union is not without influence.<br />
Australia welcomes the conclusion of agreements between the<br />
Philippines and the United States on military bases. These<br />
agreements are of major importance to the strategic balance<br />
in the western Pacific. By concluding them, the Philippines<br />
has made a major contribution to the stability and security<br />
of that region.<br />
Against the background of a potential world-energy shortage<br />
the Philippine and Australian governments will co-operate<br />
on energy matters. A bilateral nuclear safeguards agreement<br />
has recently been concluded, opening the way for negotiations<br />
for the supply of Australian uranium to the Philippines.<br />
In an exchange of letters between President Marcos and myself,<br />
Australia has undertaken to be a reliable and reasonable<br />
supplier of energy to the Philippines, and to give technical<br />
and other assistance to help the Philippines develop its<br />
own energy potential, including uranium exploration.<br />
With respect to other aid programmes it is noteworthy that<br />
Australia's two largest current aid projects are in the<br />
Philippines. The growing co-operation between Australia and the Philippines<br />
is further reflected in the signature of a double taxation<br />
agreement and the ratification of the trade agreement between<br />
Australia and the Philippines that had for some time been put<br />
aside. The ratification of this agreement comes at a time<br />
when trade with the Philippines has been growing faster than<br />
our trade overall, with Philippine exports to Australia growing<br />
at more than 45 per cent a year. The joint commission, which<br />
will be set up under the terms of the agreement, will pursue<br />
means of furthering our bilateral trade and investment.<br />
President Marcos warmly welcomed Australia's strong support<br />
for ASEAN and the arrangements which Australia is making<br />
to assist the Philippines as a member of ASEAN to take up<br />
market opportunities for exports to Australia.-<br />
The Philippines and Australia have many common concerns and<br />
common interests, a common perception of the challenges that<br />
confront us and that we can work together to surmount.<br />
The recent visit to the Philippines, at President Marcos'<br />
invitation, resulted in the consolidation of a strong and<br />
constructive relationship between our two countries. The<br />
joint communique issued at the conclusion of the visit, which<br />
I table for Honourable Members, reflects the range of matters.<br />
we discussed, and something of the spirit of the meeting. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The visit to the Philippines has contributed to making possible<br />
a relationship with that nation of a kind we have not had before.<br />
I wish to record my thanks to the President, Mrs Marcos, and<br />
members of the Philippines government, for all that they did<br />
to make my visit such a warm and very constructive one.<br />
As Honourable Members will know, UNCTAD V is meeting in Manila<br />
throughout this month. It is a meeting of enormous importance.<br />
It comes at a signficant time, towards'the end of the Tokyo<br />
round of Multi-lateral Trade Negotiations and before the Tokyo<br />
economic summit. It comes at the end of a period of some real<br />
progress on the North/ South Dialogue, particularly on the<br />
Common Fund.<br />
Over the last five years, both developed and developing countries<br />
have come to accept the necessity for compromise--formovement<br />
from the rigid positions they adopted in the past. In this<br />
process, Australia has sought to set an example and has worked<br />
to build consensus. This is reflected in Australia's work to<br />
advance the Common Fund, which has long been a policy of this<br />
Government. At one stage, both developed and developing countries took the<br />
position that the other side had to move first. Australia's<br />
view was that, if such rigid stances were maintained, there<br />
would never be agreement, and that Australia, in the interests<br />
of progress, should take the initiative.<br />
At the 1977 Commonwealth Heads of Government. Meeting in London,<br />
Prime Minister Manley of Jamaica and I1 took the lead in setting<br />
up a Commonwealth technical group to define the realistic<br />
possibilities for a Common Fund, and how this could relate to<br />
an integrated programme for commodities. A negotiating conference<br />
on the Common Fund was held in November 1977. Its results were<br />
disappointing, the outcome was a virtual deadlock which held<br />
out the prospect of continuing frustration and conflict between<br />
the developed and developing countries.<br />
To aid in avoiding this outcome at the Sydney Commonwealth<br />
Heads of Government Regional meeting in February 1978, Australia<br />
took a new and positive position on the Common Fund. In April<br />
1978, the Hon. R. V. Garland, Minister for Special Trade<br />
Representations, represented Australia at a Commonwealth<br />
Ministerial Meeting, called to discuss the report of the<br />
technical group set up at the London Commonwealth Heads of<br />
Government Meeting. This Ministerial Meeting contributed to<br />
a greater -flexibility in the, positionsof the developed and<br />
developing country participants. And, before the November 1978<br />
Common Fund Negotiating Conference, Australia circulated a<br />
paper setting out a suggested model on fundamental aspects of<br />
the Fund, with the aim of encouraging an accommodation between<br />
the two sides. Much of what Australia put forward was adopted<br />
by the Conference. </p>
<p>-4<br />
In addition to Autai's actions in -international forums, the<br />
Foreign Minister and I were active in discussions with the<br />
United States Secretary of State, the Secretary-General of the<br />
Commonwealth, the Secretary-General of UNCTAD, and with others,<br />
in advancing the idea that countries must be prepared to move<br />
if the Common Fund were to become a reality.<br />
The discussion at the December 1978 Heads of Government meeting<br />
in Jamaica was instrumental in helping-to reinforce developed<br />
countries' support for the Common Fund.<br />
The most recent Common Fund negotiating conference, in March 1979,<br />
agreed on the fundamental elements of a Common Fund a position<br />
that, eighteen months ago, few would have thought possible.<br />
Australia made an important contribution to that, but there is<br />
much work to be done before the Common Fund becomes a reality.<br />
UNCTAD must build on the gains that have been made.<br />
At UNCTAD I announced the Government's decision to contribute<br />
to the first window of the Common Fund, which will finance<br />
buffer-stocks of international commodity agreements. Further<br />
negotiation is needed to define the formula for contributions<br />
to the first window.<br />
Australia will also make an effective contribution to the Fund's<br />
second window, which will finance other measures for the stabilisation<br />
of commodity prices, such as adequate research and effective<br />
promotion. It will also be important for commodities where it<br />
is not appropriate to establish a commodity agreement based on<br />
buffer-stocking, for example, a perishable commodity.<br />
Our support for-a second window is firmly based in our own<br />
history. We know from experience that such supports as<br />
research and promotion can be crucial to the success of a<br />
commodity agreement. Australia believes that with respect<br />
to the second window, although contributions are to be<br />
voluntary, it too needs a formula approach which would give<br />
more stability in financing and would do much to guarantee its<br />
success.<br />
Australia will continue to be involved fully in the further<br />
negotiation within UNCTAD, on the Common Fund.<br />
If the Common Fund is to work there need to be international<br />
commodity agreements for certain commodities. Unfortunately<br />
there has been little progress in negotiating commodity agreements<br />
involving both producers and consumers, and consistent with<br />
the principles ? f the common Fund.<br />
Although some progress is being made in relation to rubber,<br />
the International Sugar Agreement is in jeopardy because of<br />
the attitude of the E. E. C. While the U. S. administration is<br />
experiencing difficulties in having the agreement ratified,<br />
. further, some aspects of existing agreements would need to<br />
be re-negotiated to make them acceptable. </p>
<p>Developed countries must join, and agree to participate<br />
financially, in all viable commodity arrangements where they<br />
have a major interest in the trade, otherwise it will be<br />
difficult to see their agreement to the establishment of the<br />
Conmon Fund as other than an empty and rather cynical gesture.<br />
The effective translation of the commitment to a Common Fund<br />
into a reality will contribute to the well-being of developing<br />
and developed nations, but alone this is not enough. The dangers<br />
of inflation and increased protectionism represent major problems<br />
to both the developed and developing nations.<br />
Inflation undermines both confidence in governments and the<br />
confidence of governments. It causes unemployment by reducing<br />
profitability and increasing uncertainty. With inflation, costs<br />
rise, industries are priced out of markets, firms invest less<br />
and employ less creating a national and international unemployment<br />
problem. Inflation leads to disorderly exchange rate conditions<br />
and increases pressure for forms of intervention which inhibit<br />
market forces in general and world trade in particular..<br />
We cannot overlook the conjunction between the increased rates<br />
of inflation since 1973, and the fact that the volume of world<br />
trade grew at only 4 percent per annum between 1973 and 1978<br />
compared with 8 percent over the previous 20 years.<br />
In Europe in particular, new protectionist devices have been<br />
created in recent years. Export subsidies and wage and agricultural<br />
subsidies in the E. E. C. run as high as $ 25 billion each year.<br />
These are just as protectionist as tariffs, quotas or ." voluntary<br />
restraint" arrangements. They deny markets to developing countries<br />
and cause unfair competition for developing countries products<br />
in third markets.<br />
Countries must move to adopt the positive policies advocated<br />
by the O. E. C. D. and allow market forces to work. As my discussions<br />
with the Secretary-General of the Mr Van Lennep, made<br />
clear, the O. E. C. D.' s view is that interventionist policies by<br />
government have the effect of locking labour and capital<br />
into particular industries. The removal or reduction of such<br />
policies would significantly enhance the prospects for<br />
growth in the international economy and international trade.<br />
The Tokyo round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations has put<br />
some brake on the increasing move to protectionism, and that<br />
may be its greatest success. But although there-are individual<br />
negotiations within, the round will be of significant benefit<br />
to Australia, and many of our exporters will have better<br />
assurance of market access than ever beforein their history.<br />
In the world-wide scene, the gains are modest and the impact<br />
is certainly not revolutionary. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
There has been some progress in the reduction of industrial<br />
tariffs but little has been done in relation to non-tariff<br />
barriers, particularly in relation to agriculture. Virtually<br />
nothing has been done in relation to wage subsidies and export<br />
subsidies. Against this background the world must look beyond<br />
the M. T. N. and ensure the continuation ' of effects to liberalise<br />
trade. A lapse into protectionism would deny the basic truth that the<br />
success of the existing system,. a system which has allowed<br />
enormous progress to be made in the recent past, depends<br />
essentially on the growth of mutual trade, and on maintaining<br />
the conditions which allow and encourage that growth.<br />
Nothing would lead to greater bitterness and disillusionment<br />
among developing countries., would do more to strengthen<br />
the case of those who argue for extreme policies. than the<br />
systematic frustration of access to developed country markets.<br />
If the reward for success is to be punishment by means of new<br />
protectionist devices, it will demonstrate that the economic<br />
principles by which the developed~ countries have professed to<br />
live, apply only to those who have arrived and not those who<br />
are on their way. The major developed countries carry a great<br />
burden of responsibility. Thdir management of their own economies<br />
has decisive effects on the international system.<br />
Australia has proposed that UNCTAD should call on these countries<br />
. when tI~ ey meet at-the economic summit in Tokyo to adopt<br />
policies that will bring inflation under control and to resist<br />
the temptation to Burrender to the pressures of protectionism.<br />
Australia is developing a resolution on inflation, protectionism<br />
and structural adjustment and it is expected that this resolution<br />
will be launched at UNCTAD tomorrow. We hope that the resolution<br />
will have a productive effect and will cut across group lines<br />
in UNCTAD.<br />
For Australia's part our record of trade with the developing<br />
nations is a good one. In 1966 Australia introduced the first<br />
system of tariff preferences to assist developing countries.<br />
The Australian system has been'substantially expanded. Some<br />
percent of imports from developing countries now enter<br />
Australia duty free or at a preferential tariff rate. Australia's<br />
imports of industrial products from developing countries have<br />
increased substantially. on a per capita basis, Australia's imports<br />
of manufactured products from developing countries, excluding<br />
petroleum, more than doubled between 1973 and 1977 abetter<br />
performance than that of the United States, the or Japan.<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
In the sensitive textiles, clothing and footwear area, access<br />
to Australia is very high. Australia's imports on textiles,<br />
clothing and footwear from ASEAN countries represent $ A2. l4<br />
per capita compared with 63 cents for the 51 cents<br />
for the E. E. C. and 25 cents for Japan.<br />
If these three areas allowed imports to the same extent as<br />
Australia then ASEAN imports of these products would expand<br />
by $ 1 billion.<br />
The task before UNCTAD is a formidable one. In approaching it,<br />
we will need to display moderation, we will need to display<br />
realism, we will need to display vision, and last, and perhaps<br />
most important, we will need to display the resolution to<br />
face formidable problems and to surmount them.<br />
A useful aspect of the visit to the Philippines was the<br />
opportunity it afforded for discussions with the<br />
Prime Minister of Japan, Mr. Ohira, on important<br />
international economic, political and strategic issues.<br />
This broad based dialogue between Japan and Australia is<br />
something which I believe both countries find useful.<br />
It is a recent development which took shape primarily<br />
following my 1978 talks in Japan with Prime minister Fukuda<br />
when the Australian Government engaged Japan in a broad<br />
discussion rather than focussing on bilateral issues which<br />
important as they are are not the only matters of concern<br />
to our nations.<br />
In discussing the forthcoming Tokyo Summit, we agreed that<br />
the strongest action against inflation is necessary,<br />
especially in view of the link between inflation, world<br />
trading opportunities and the North/ South dialogue.<br />
It was plain from our discussions that Japan and Australia<br />
have common views on many matters including the Common Fund,<br />
co-operation in the peaceful uses of energy and the continuing<br />
importance of the U. S. role in world affairs, and in<br />
particular with respect to the Asia/ Pacific region.<br />
One particular point of interest raised in the course of our<br />
discussions was Mr. Ohira's concept of a Pacific Basin<br />
Community in which there would be closer regional<br />
co-operation amongst Pacific nations. The idea has<br />
considerable potential and merits further discussion and<br />
consultation. At the moment the concept is tentative and<br />
exploratory and requires a great deal of thinking and<br />
consultation, and I have asked the foreign Minister to develop<br />
ideas and approaches to this subject.<br />
The discussions with Mr. Ohira confirmed that Australia and<br />
Japan have close economic relations, a growing political<br />
understanding and shared perceptions about the Asia/ Pacific<br />
region. We now have a broad and mutually accepted<br />
framework for constructive dialogue with Japan across the<br />
range of bilateral and more general issues which can only be<br />
to the advantage of our countries. / 8 </p>
<p>-8-<br />
At the conclusion of the meeting I expressed the hope that<br />
Mr. Ohira would be able to visit Australia at the earliest<br />
possible date. He would certainly receive a warm welcome.<br />
Finally, I turn to my visit to Indonesia. I had earlier<br />
enquired whether President Soeharto would, like Prime Minister<br />
Ohira, be visiting Manila for UNCTAD V, in which case we<br />
could have had an opportunity to meet there. As an<br />
alternative, he suggested having talks on my way back, an<br />
invitation which I very readily accepted because it provided<br />
an opportunity for constructive forward-looking discussions<br />
on a wide range of international, regional and bilateral<br />
matters.<br />
Our talks made it perfectly plain that Australia and<br />
Indonesia recognise that, living together in one part of<br />
the world, we need to work closely together. A strong<br />
relationship between Indonesia and Australia is a<br />
fundamental foreign policy objective of this Government and,<br />
I believe, of President Soeharto's Government also.<br />
The talks confirmed the strength of our relationship and<br />
served further to advance it. They revealed a high degree<br />
of common interest and common understanding on the many<br />
political and economic problems facing the region. There<br />
have in the past been some strains between our two countries.<br />
Those difficulties are now firmly behind us, and we are<br />
determined to look to the future constructively and<br />
realistically.<br />
The President and I reviewed developments at UNCTAD including<br />
the debate on the Common Fund, and the renewed instability<br />
in Indo-China and its implications for the region.<br />
Australia welcomes Indonesia's current efforts to strengthen<br />
its relationship with Papua New Guinea. On the issue of<br />
the Australia/ Indonesia seabed boundary negotiations we were<br />
both hopeful that they will be brought to a speedy conclusion.<br />
Progress has been made in the reunification of Timorese<br />
families and there was agreement that this programme should<br />
be continued as rapidly as possible. The problem of<br />
refugees from Indo-China is a-human problem of vast<br />
proportions which affects all of us. It is a problem which<br />
needs to be tackled at the international level. Indonesia's<br />
co-operation in the Indo-China refugee problem is of<br />
importance in maintaining an orderly intake of refugees into<br />
Australia. Indonesia's continuing help in forestalling<br />
unheralded arrivals of refugees is very much appreciated, for<br />
it is much easier for Australia to take in a significant<br />
number of refugees when this is done in an orderly way and<br />
under proper immnigration procedures. Indonesia' s generous<br />
and constructive proposal to establish an island processing<br />
centre for refugees is welcomed and supported by Australia<br />
and we will be contributing towards the cost of this centre.<br />
The Government urges other nations to make financial<br />
contributions. / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
Finally, we discussed the possiblity of President Soeharto<br />
visiting Australia before too long and the Government looks<br />
forward to offering President Soeharto the hospitality<br />
of this country.<br />
I discussed the new Australian low air fare scheme with<br />
both President Marcos and President Soeharto. We welcomed<br />
the progress made at the recent meeting of Australian and<br />
ASEAN officials in Kuala. Lumpur where as a result of considerable<br />
good will on both sides, agree ment was reached to recommend<br />
to Ministers a package proposal for a settlement.<br />
As General Romulo, the Philippine Minister for Foreign<br />
Affairs said to the UNCTAD delegates, the joint communique<br />
on civil aviation agreed by ASEAN-and Australian officials<br />
at Kuala Lumpur was " an example of the way in which<br />
differences can be reconciled in the spirit of compromise".<br />
The Australian and Philippines Governments are to discuss<br />
arrangements covering routes between Australia, the<br />
Philippines and countries to the North.<br />
Mr. Ohira and 1 agreed that lower air fares between Japan and<br />
Australia are necessary and we urged that the negotiations<br />
that are already underway between JAL and Qantas should be<br />
concluded as quickly as possible.<br />
In conclusion, this brief visit to nearby pountries was a<br />
particularly valuable and effective one. It advanced our<br />
bilateral relations with the Philippines, Japan and Indonesia.<br />
It advanced Australian-ASEAN understanding. It allowed<br />
Australia's views on major international economic issues to<br />
be put at the world forum of UNCTAD V. The visit<br />
allowed a warm and friendly exchange of views between Heads<br />
of Government on a range of issues which can only lead to<br />
better international co-operation and understanding on<br />
world issues and to enduring relationships between the peoples<br />
of our countries, our region and the world. </p>
<p>JOINT COMMUNIQUE<br />
President Marcos and Prime Minister Fraser<br />
Manila, 11 May 1979<br />
At the invitation of His Excellency President<br />
Ferdinand E. Marcos, the Prime Minister of Australia, the<br />
Rt. Hon. Malcolm Fraser, made an official visit to the<br />
Republic of the Philippines from 8 to 11 May 1979.<br />
During the visit the President and the Prime<br />
Minister held extensive discussions on a wide range of<br />
subjects of mutual interest. The talks were held in a<br />
very cordial and friendly atmosphere, reflecting the<br />
important and expanding relationship between the<br />
Philippines and Australia.<br />
Discussion covered three broad areas: regional<br />
and world stability; the international economic situation;<br />
and the bilateral relationship between the Philippines and<br />
Australia. The President and the Prime Minister agreed that<br />
some aspects of the international situation caused<br />
considerable concern, with areas of instability affecting<br />
parts of Africa, the Middle East and Indo-China. In<br />
addition, they noted that international economic difficulties<br />
added significantly to world tensions.<br />
In such circumstances, Australia and the countries<br />
of the ASEAN region had a strong mutual interest in working<br />
closely together to prevent such tensions from impeding<br />
the peaceful progress and development of the region.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister noted the<br />
recent normalization of relations between China and the<br />
United States and the conclusion of the Friendship Treaty<br />
between China and Japan, and agreed that these events<br />
created new opportunities for these countries to play a<br />
positive and constructive role in the Asia/ Pacific region.<br />
They expressed the hope that the Soviet Union would make<br />
a similar constructive contribution.<br />
The two leaders expressed serious concern about<br />
the situation in Indo-China and called for a settlement<br />
of differences among the parties concerned. They agreed<br />
that disputes should be settled by peaceful means, and<br />
without resort to the use of force.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister referred to<br />
the critical importance of the 5th Session of the United<br />
Nations Conference on Trade and Development, currently<br />
being held in Manila. They agreed that its location and<br />
timing made the present conference especially important.<br />
The immediately preceding period had been one of reduced<br />
growth of world trade caused by inflation and leading to the<br />
spread of unemployment and the dangerous increase of<br />
protectionism. </p>
<p>2.<br />
The two leaders recalled the part they and their<br />
governments have played to date in bringing about an agreement<br />
on the basic elements of a Common Fund, and welcomed the<br />
prospects it brings for greater stability in commiodity<br />
prices at levels which are remunerative to producers and<br />
equitable to consumers. They expressed the firm conviction<br />
that the Fund should be established as soon as possible.<br />
They also called, in particular, upon producers<br />
and consumers to proceed to negotiate expeditiousy appropriate<br />
international commodity agreements and arrangements under<br />
the Integrated Programme for Commodities of which the<br />
Common Fund was a key instrument.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister agreed<br />
further that there was a need to look to the future and to<br />
improve on the results of the Multilateral Trade Negotiations.<br />
It was of critical importance to achieve significant<br />
reductions in barriers to world trade. In this context,<br />
they noted that high rates of inflation were a significant<br />
element in the slower growth in volume of international<br />
trade and in market opportunities for all countries,<br />
especially developing ones. They therefore called upon<br />
countries, and in particular the major industralized ones,<br />
to pursue policies to bring inflation under control.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister were pleased<br />
with the contribution that had been made by ASEAN to political<br />
stability and the economic and social development of the<br />
region. The Prime Minister emphasized Australia's strong<br />
commitment to South-East Asia and the whole-hearted support<br />
for ASEAN, which he referred to as an excellent example of<br />
the strength and stability which could be achieved through<br />
regional cooperation. It was a basic element of Australia's<br />
policy to work closely and cooperatively with ASEAN in all<br />
matters. The two leaders discussed the new Australian<br />
low air fare scheme and, in this connection, they welcomed<br />
the progress made in the discussions at the recent meeting<br />
of Aus tral ian and ASEAN of f ic ial s in Kual a Lumpur inc luding<br />
the agreement to recommend to ASEAN and Australian Ministers<br />
a settlement on a package basis.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister agreed to<br />
start discussions on arrangements covering routes between<br />
Australia, the Philippines and countries to the north.<br />
The President and the Prime Minister reviewed<br />
the full range of the bilateral relationship between the<br />
Philippines and Australia and were able to settle a number<br />
of issues, thus clearing the way for the fuller development<br />
of the existing network of bilateral agreements.<br />
W </p>
<p>3.<br />
Referring to the Nuclear Safeguards Agreement<br />
which has just been concluded, the two leaders agreed<br />
that this would be the basis for subsequent arrangements<br />
for the supply of uranium from Australia to the<br />
Philipr-ines. The President and the Prime Minister noted that<br />
while the value of trade between the two countries has<br />
increased considerably, there remains a significant<br />
balance in Australia's favor. In this context, they noted<br />
and the President welcomed the arrangements that the<br />
Australian Government was making to increase market<br />
opportunities for exports to Australia from the Philippines<br />
and other ASEAN countries.<br />
The two leaders welcomed the exchange of letters<br />
of ratificiation which they had authorized to bring into<br />
force the trade agreement between Australia and the<br />
Philippines and agreed that this was a significant<br />
development. The Prime Minister and the President further<br />
welcomed the signing of a double taxation agreement between<br />
the two countries which would help promote greater economic<br />
cooperation. These various agreements, together with the<br />
accompanying strengthening of the political relationship,<br />
reflected the growing warmth and cooperation between the<br />
Philippines and Australia.<br />
The two leaders recognized the considerable<br />
prospects for the substantial growth in tourism between<br />
Australia and the Philippines and agreed to consider early<br />
measures to realize this potential.<br />
The President welcomed the continuing commitment<br />
of the Australian Government to the economic development<br />
of the Philippines through its various aid programs, and<br />
the Prime Minister confirmed that the Australian Government<br />
expected to maintain its aid-allocations to the Philippines.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Australian<br />
Government had studied a recent Philippines request for<br />
assistance in the development of its energy capability,<br />
and confirmed that Australia would provide such assistance.<br />
The President welcomed the Prime Miite' assurance that<br />
Australia intended to be a reliable and reasonable supplier<br />
of energy sources to the Philippines.<br />
The Prime Minister expressed his pleasure and deep<br />
gratitude to the President and Government of the Republic of<br />
the Philippines for their invitation to him to visit Manila,<br />
and for the excellent arrangements and gracious hospitality<br />
that had been offered to his party. The President accepted<br />
an invitation by the Prime Minister to visit Australia at a<br />
mutually convenient time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
