<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19201</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech to Bo&#039;ao Forum for Asia Plenary Session</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
The evolution of this Bo'ao Forum for Asia is a striking symbol of the evolution of our region itself: both of the successes and challenges which have endured and of the new challenges and opportunities which have emerged.</p>
<p>Here two great enduring responsibilities are discussed: continuing Asia's economic growth while achieving human development  -  and maintaining Asia's peaceful regional order while growth changes the strategic balance.</p>
<p>Growth in the region must continue and must strengthen.</p>
<p>The national economies of the region vary widely today, both in their overall degrees of development and in their immediate economic circumstances and prospects for growth. </p>
<p>This Forum reflects just this variety: from developed, knowledge-based economies needing to restart long-term growth  -  to emerging economies managing the challenges of urbanisation  -  and incorporating the firms and international organisations which operate across the whole of Asia.</p>
<p>Through all these varying national contexts, the enduring challenge of economic growth merits an enduring response.</p>
<p>Unlocking the power of well-designed markets to create wealth  -  while harnessing the power of investment in the skills and knowledge of people to spread the benefits to all.</p>
<p>Well-designed markets and well-targeted investment in human capital remain the key to Asia's economic success.We must also understand that continued and strengthened economic growth will keep changing the strategic order of our region.</p>
<p>Militaries are modernizing.  Economic growth will put more pressure on energy, water and food resources. </p>
<p>This does not make major power conflict inevitable  -  all countries in the region share a deep interest in strategic stability  -  but the consequences of conflict are ever more severe for us all.</p>
<p>This is nowhere more clear than on the Korean Peninsula.</p>
<p>There, any aggression is a threat to the interests of every country in the region.</p>
<p>For this reason, I do welcome the growing co-operation of all regional Governments to prevent conflict on the Korean Peninsula and to counter North Korean aggression.</p>
<p>That co-operation is also a sign of what will be needed in future as we face other security challenges.</p>
<p>Asia must be a region of sustainable security in which habits of co-operation are the norm.Peace and prosperity are challenges which endure  -  but since this Forum's inception, new challenges have emerged.</p>
<p>While the climate change debate was a live one in Asia fifteen years ago, then it was a debate about the region's future. </p>
<p>Today, it is a debate about the region's present.</p>
<p>We are living through the effects of carbon pollution and climate change now and we are moving to clean energy sources now.</p>
<p>Today, Australia has a comprehensive approach including record investment in renewable energy and energy efficiency, a price on carbon and emissions trading from 1 July 2015.</p>
<p>Australia has deliberately pursued a market-based response to this pressing environmental challenge.  Many Asian nations are doing the same.</p>
<p>More than one third of the world's clean energy investment in 2012 was in Asia.</p>
<p>Last year Japan introduced its carbon tax. </p>
<p>South Korea's national emissions trading scheme begins in 2015.</p>
<p>Over the three years to 2015, pilot emissions trading schemes will commence in seven Chinese cities and provinces covering 255 million people.</p>
<p>Beijing's emissions trading scheme, which will cover a population of twenty million people, will launch shortly.</p>
<p>That will be a great day for Asia's clean energy future.</p>
<p>So will the commencement of China's national scheme following 2015.</p>
<p>The climate is already changing.  Asia is already acting.</p>
<p>All this will be important to your discussions this weekend.</p>
<p>This Forum reflects change in the region  -  as it reflects the enduring significance of growth and security as matters for us all.</p>
<p>I want to conclude by observing that for Australians, Bo'ao is also a particularly significant symbol of the role we seek to play in the region.</p>
<p>The statesmen of 1998 who presented the idea of this Forum to the Chinese Government were of course, President Ramos and Prime Minister Hosokawa  -  and my friend and predecessor Prime Minister Hawke.</p>
<p>In this, our former Prime Minister took precisely the kind of role Australia seeks to play  -  co-operative and supportive, but more  -  accepting our share in the responsibility of collective leadership which falls to all regional leaders and nations.</p>
<p>This was Australia's approach to our engagement in the region as long ago as 1973: when my predecessor Gough Whitlam became the first Australian Prime Minister to visit China.</p>
<p>This was Australia's role in the origin of this Bo'ao Forum. </p>
<p>This was Australia's role in the founding of APEC and the expansion of the East Asia Summit.</p>
<p>This is Australia's role this week, when I lead the most senior Australian political delegation ever to visit China.</p>
<p>Bo'ao is a vital forum for Asian conversations  -  and we have more to talk about than ever before.</p>
<p>I look forward to the insights which emerge from your discussions. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
