<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10294</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP PRESS CONFERENCE, DIAOYUTAI STATE GUEST HOUSE BEIJING, CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010294.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1 April 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, DIAOYUTAI STATE GUEST HOUSE<br />
BEIJING, CHINA<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
Well ladies and gentlemen we are coming to the end of the visit to China. I want to say that I<br />
believe this visit and the talks that I have held with Chinese leaders have been highly<br />
successful. I have yet to meet the Vice Premier Mr Zhu Rongji and that meeting will take<br />
place later this afternoon and there are one or two other engagements on the programme.<br />
But the discussions that I've had with both the Premier, Li Peng and President Jiang Zemin,<br />
confirm my belief that Australian and China have a very strong and sensible relationship. That<br />
relationship is built on the twin pillars of mutual interest and mutual respect. The great<br />
advantage of this visit has been that I have, for the first time, established a personal contact<br />
with the Premier, Li Peng. I have renewed contact with President Jiang Zemin. We had a<br />
very successful discussion in Manila and we built on that further today.<br />
The economic links between Australia and China have been deepened and broadened as a<br />
consequence of this visit. I have already outlined the decision of the Chinese government to<br />
send a team to Australia within the next few months to conduct a feasibility study regarding<br />
directly reduced iron and the potential if that feasibility study turns out to be positive, the<br />
potential that that offers for an expanded export market for Australia and commensurate<br />
benefits for China. In many respects the Australian and Chinese economic relationship is built<br />
firmly on the complementarity of our economies.<br />
For years Australia has been a reliable supplier of raw materials, of commodities, of things<br />
such as wheat and wool. As I pointed out to the President today, we have been a strong and<br />
reliable supplier of those things on occasions when the political relationship between Australia<br />
and China has not been as good as it is at present.<br />
Having a very senior delegation of business men and women with me has emphasised the<br />
importance of cooperation. It has made the point to our Chinese hosts that the government<br />
and the business community work together when the Australian national interest is involved<br />
and work together in dealings with overseas governments and overseas companies. Those </p>
<p>companies have had excellent opportunities during this visit to renew contacts and to establish<br />
fresh ones. I was delighted to open the Beijing Branch of the ANZ Bank. I was also delighted<br />
to open the seminar being conducted as it happens on the 10th anniversary of the formation of<br />
the Australian Stock Exchange. I made the point there and I repeat it again that the economic<br />
links between Australian and China are not only to be found in the more traditional areas, if I<br />
could put it that way, of international trade such as wool and wheat and manufactures but also<br />
to be found in the service sector. And the presence in China of so many representatives of<br />
major Australian legal firms, the business delegation itself, included the managing partner of<br />
Ernst Young one of the large accounting firms. All of those things drive home the diverse<br />
character of the relationship between Australia and China.<br />
Most of my discussion with President Jiang Zemin was devoted to a sweep of regional and<br />
world affairs. Both of us reaffirmed to each other the importance of the APEC link the<br />
continued commitment of China to opening up her economy and the reaffirmation as the<br />
Chinese leadership has already given in the wake of Deng Xiao Ping's death of the economic<br />
reforms he commenced in 1978 and which have so obviously had their mark all over China. I<br />
made the point to him again as I did to the Premier yesterday that Australia does not see China<br />
as a threat. And that that is a view that Australia has put to other countries.<br />
The three of us have agreed that if you have an effective framework in place then if difficulties<br />
and differences do arise, as inevitably they will in any relationship, particularly between<br />
countries that have different systems and different histories, if you have the right framework in<br />
place than those differences can be effectively managed and dealt with in a way that does not<br />
do any damage to the broader relationship and dealt with in a way that doesn't in any way<br />
prevent the maximisation of the goals that we have in common.<br />
I've renewed my invitations to both the Premier and the President to visit Australia and I also<br />
raised with the President today, and he agreed it would be desirable if Australia and China<br />
renewed or certainly stepped up a notch or two the contacts between Defence Ministers and<br />
between the militaries of our respective countries.<br />
Overall can I say ladies and gentlemen I believe this has been a very valuable visit. We do<br />
have a strong and sensible relationship built on those twin pillars of mutual interest and mutual<br />
respect and I believe that the interests of Australia lie in sensibly and realistically fostering that<br />
relationship. And I think the contacts that have been made both at a government and at a<br />
business level in order to achieve that have been very good and that the visit has been a very<br />
valuable one for the Australian national interest.<br />
Do you have any questions? Mr Milne.<br />
JRNLST: Prime Minister, Glenn Milne from the Seven Network Australia. A Chinese Foreign Ministry<br />
official at there briefing yesterday made the point that Premier Li Peng raised the Australia/ US<br />
security agreement. Could you tell us in what terms he raised it and whether he has any<br />
expectations about how that, that pact should proceed between Australia and the US? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't recall him raising it. It must have been a very brief raising I don't remember it. Paul<br />
JRNLST: Prime Minister, Paul Smith from the Ten Network Australia. The Labor Party, apparently<br />
back home, says that they had a human rights dialogue with China and questioning the need or<br />
why you're instituting another one. Could you tell us why that is different and why it is better<br />
than what Labor had? And on the issue of James Peng, do you accept that China could have<br />
said something other than what it said given that you were asking for his release on<br />
humanitarian grounds?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the Chinese response on James Peng was a serious response as best I could judge it. It's<br />
a difficult issue, I saw it very clearly as my obligation and my role as Prime Minister because<br />
James Peng is an Australian citizen to raise the matter. I'm not going to try and put actions or<br />
words into the mouths of my Chinese hosts. I raised it seriously and it received a serious<br />
response. That matter will continue to be pursued in an appropriate fashion. Mr Peng is<br />
visited regularly by consular people and in different ways the matter will be fuirther pursued. I<br />
think it was correct that it be raised and raised very directly and very openly. I understand the<br />
Chinese response obviously it is one of those matters that has to be dealt with in a sensible<br />
fashion. As far as the Labor Party back home saying things ( tape breaks)<br />
JRNLST: Laura Tingle, from the Age, Prime Minister. Just on a related subject to James Peng you<br />
mentioned yesterday that there was a willingness on Australia's part to discuss a bilateral<br />
arrangement on consular agreements. Previous governments have not been prepared to do<br />
that, partly, as I understand it because they felt it might result in a downgrading of consular<br />
representation in China in areas such as visits to gaols. What ground did you give to the<br />
Chinese yesterday and how do you see the agreement actually being formed?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well what I said was that previously the Chinese Government had pressed Australia to have a<br />
separate agreement and not allow the consular affairs of the two countries to be governed by<br />
the Vienna Convention. And I said that in view of the Chinese desire to have a separate<br />
agreement we would revise our previous position and positively discuss what form that<br />
agreement might take. Now, obviously that doesn't mean to say that we will sign up on any<br />
form of agreement that is proposed to us by the Chinese. We need to negotiate about the<br />
form the agreement would take. We are obviously not going to enter into an agreement that<br />
gives us a less than adequate outcome as far as consular access is concerned. That's quite<br />
basic but it's important to the Chinese and we thought it was one of those things where,<br />
particularly, having regard to the significant number of Australian citizens now, and permanent<br />
residents of Australia, who have Chinese links and Chinese ancestry, that it was reasonable to<br />
alter our view. But obviously it has to be an agreement which is satisfactory to Australia. </p>
<p>JRNLST: Camille Furnell, ABC, firstly on this framework for human rights dialogue given that Li Peng<br />
said that Chinese side said they noted this what hope do you have that there will actually be<br />
some sort of dialogue on human rights in a new framework and also given that you raised<br />
issues of human rights concern, is Australia prepared to help anyone of the forty Chinese<br />
political exiles that are now in Hong Kong who fear that after the hand over that they will find<br />
themselves in Chinese gaols.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, as far as my expectations about the dialogue are concerned I think we have to take it as<br />
it comes. The tenor of the discussion yesterday was very much to the effect that China would<br />
agree, or that China wanted a dialogue on human rights rather than public exchanges. We<br />
specifically proposed that there be a dialogue and I gave some brief outline of the form that it<br />
might take at the press briefing yesterday. And there will be some further discussion<br />
immediately, or in the near future, between Australian officials and Chinese officials about the<br />
form that it will take.<br />
I would hope that the Chinese response will be a serious one and I have no reason to doubt<br />
from what was said yesterday that the commitment to having a dialogue is serious on the part<br />
of China. Equally, I understand that China has different views on human rights issues than<br />
from those held by Australia. I mean, we understand that and I'm not expecting overnight<br />
changes. Equally, I have the view and I went to the meeting yesterday that it was just not<br />
realistic or appropriate for human rights never to be on the agenda in discussions between<br />
Australia and China, but it was important given the overall goals of the relationship to handle<br />
it in a way that allowed for a proper expression of view but also ensured that it was not<br />
something caused unnecessary difficulty in the relationship.<br />
So far as the people in Hong Kong are concerned I think it is a question that I'm not going, in<br />
a sense it is hypothetical at this stage and I think it is more appropriate that we keep that<br />
situation under notice. I did make the point in my discussion yesterday that Australia wanted<br />
conditions of free exchange of information, wanted the preservation of the rights that exist in<br />
Hong Kong at the present and I did receive a general assurance to that effect.<br />
JRNLST: Paul Kelly from the Australian newspaper. Prime Minister in the recent discussions that<br />
you've just held with the President on regional and global affairs was there a discussion of<br />
Australia's relationship with the United States and how that alliance with the United States is<br />
relevant and impinges upon our relationship with China?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No there wasn't. There was a reference to the United States which flowed out of a question I<br />
asked the President about his meeting with Vice President Gore and he spoke very positively<br />
of that meeting and used the metaphor of the " cloud clearing and the rain stopping" which I<br />
thought was an interesting observation. I told the President that when President Clinton had<br />
been in Canberra, in October, he, President Clinton had told me that he wanted a positive </p>
<p>relationship with China and that it was the desire of the United States to fully engage China in<br />
the affairs of the world. Now, it is, of course, for China and the United States to make the<br />
pace of their own relationship. Our position in these matters is well know. We see China's<br />
engagement in the world. We particularly see China's regional engagement. We have an<br />
alliance with the United States born out of a clear headed and independent assessment of our<br />
national interest and that has been our position for a long time and it will always be our<br />
position, but barring a change of circumstances so far as the strategic character of that<br />
relationship is concerned. But, the US-Australia link is not one that has arisen.<br />
JRNLST: Prime Minister, Terry O'Connor, from Australian Associated Press. You said that President<br />
Jiang Zemin had suggested greater links between the military...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
well I actually raised it.<br />
JRNLST: Can you expand a bit on that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, I can't. I simply have in mind that in the past we've had some liaison. I don't want to<br />
over emphasise the significance of it at this stage but it was something that I raised and he<br />
responded very positively and there will be some discussions. I think it will evolve. General<br />
Baker, I think, came to China last year and we're not proposing some sort of, anything<br />
dramatic in this area, but having liaison is a good thing and I raised it and he responded very<br />
positively.<br />
JRNLST: Would you see some greater, or more formal process of discussion between the two sides in<br />
the future on military issues?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I wouldn't foresee it. All I can foresee at the moment is a resumption of liaison. What<br />
flows out of that is something we'll just have to see. But I don't, it was a specific thing that I<br />
raised and he agreed to it, but I don't want it to be seen as some sort of dramatic upgrading of<br />
the links in that area. But, equally there is value and it is, I guess, a positive sign that he<br />
should respond so positively. It has existed, I think, in various forms in the past and it's<br />
obviously a sign of, I hope, more positive times that there is a ready agreement that it should<br />
return. </p>
<p>JRNLST: Michael Millet, Sydney Morning Herald I was just wandering if there was any further<br />
concern expressed today by the Chinese about a possible declaration on human rights?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Today, no<br />
JRNLST: Louise Dodson, Financial Review, Mr Howard. Was the question of access, the question of<br />
wool raised, access to the Chinese market?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Wool in my discussion today, no I don't, that was, I mean it certainly was discussed yesterday<br />
in some detail in relation to the tariff quota. The nature of the discussions today and yesterday<br />
were somewhat different. In a sense, yesterday was a large micro discussion. Today's was<br />
more a macro discussion.<br />
JRNLST: Can I just ask one other question. In yesterday's opening of the meeting with Premier Li<br />
Peng, he described the overall relationship as quite good. Have you any idea why he just<br />
described it as quite good?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Because it is.<br />
JRNLST: But quite, not very. On the whole, he said on the whole it was quite good. Did you see that<br />
as a warm endorsement?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I saw it for what it was. It was his opening words, it was his opening comment through<br />
the words of the translator. Look, this relationship is good, it's positive. Some people would<br />
say it's quite good, some would say it's very good. I would say it, I would describe it in the<br />
terms that I used at the opening of my press conference that I think we have a strong<br />
relationship. It is realistically based and it's based on the twin pillars of mutual interest and<br />
mutual respect. I think it's important in these relationships to avoid needless hyperbole and<br />
it's also important of course to avoid needless agonising over a particular adjective. </p>
<p>JRNLST: Jim Middleton from ABC Television. Prime Minister, just on this question of the defence links<br />
and the upgrading of.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well they're not, I think defence links are too strong an expression. I think it's, they've<br />
agreed to have a yarn.<br />
JRNLST: Well that's exactly what I was going to ask. In responding to your suggestion you said that<br />
the President responded very warmly, did he say specifically they should go ahead, and he<br />
suggested a framework for doing so, did he?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well look, I raised it and he said yes, it's a good idea, it should happen and it will, they will<br />
have a yarn.<br />
JRNLST: Malcolm Farr from the Daily Telegraph. Why didn't you raise the US defence ties, the<br />
Australia/ US link given that there was apprehension about it earlier and that the Chinese have<br />
made clear their discontent?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I thought that would have been in, it may well have sounded somewhat defensive. Why<br />
do you raise something that you are completely comfortable and relaxed about and believe it is<br />
correct and in the Australian national interest unless it is raised by someone else. I mean, the<br />
Australian/ US relationship is not directed at anybody. I've made that very clear. I hope, I am<br />
encouraged to believe that perhaps is understood within the Chinese Government that we do<br />
have bona fides on this issue, that our association with the United States has got nothing to do<br />
with any hostility on our part or on the part of the United States to China. It clearly hasn't.<br />
That's not why we entered into it in 195 1. It's certainly not why we maintained that<br />
relationship now. It represents an expression of an independently refined view by a sovereign<br />
country about its own self interest and I don't feel it necessary going abroad as Prime Minister<br />
of Australia to answer for the decisions that we have made in our own national interest unless<br />
the issue is raised. I think that is altogether striking the wrong note, giving the wrong signal<br />
and sounding altogether too defensive and I don't think that is in Australia's interest.<br />
JRNLST: Louise Maher, Radio 2 UE. Mr Howard, how would you describe the concrete or explain the<br />
concrete benefits of this trip to ordinary Australians beyond what many might think is just<br />
rhetoric about better ties both economically and politically? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the fact that we are able to get another banking license, that we're able to get a feasibility<br />
study that could open up a project, that could earn a half a billion dollars export income for<br />
Australia and 2000 jobs and further sales of LNG in Western Australia, that we have made it<br />
more rather than less likely that China will be part of the World Trade Organisation and that<br />
could carry with it better access for Australian primary products such as wool, now they're<br />
some of the things that I would describe as benefits of this trip.<br />
JRNLST: Fran Kelly, ABC Radio. Just back to human rights briefly, before this trip, very close to you<br />
leaving for China there was a, I think it was a leaked cable, it was described as from Foreign<br />
Affairs, that talked about China saying quite clearly it would be unyielding on the issue of<br />
human rights. Through all your talks today and yesterday and your mention of the framework<br />
and the fact that Premier Li Peng asked Australia not to sign the UN resolution and raised the<br />
issue, wanted reaffirmation of China's sovereignty on Tibet and Taiwan, did you get any sense<br />
that there was any chance of China yielding at any point on human rights?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I am not going to try and respond to a document, leaked or otherwise. I can merely<br />
repeat that I put it to the Premier that inevitably in a relationship such as ours there would be<br />
differences on certain issues, and human rights were one of these issues. I said to him what I<br />
have said publicly both here and in Australia, that we haven't come to hector and lecture and<br />
moralise but we do have views on these issues and I put it to him that the right way of<br />
handling it was within the framework of a dialogue and he seemed receptive to that idea. I<br />
don't want to sort of pre-judge the issue. I don't think that helps. I mean, we will maintain<br />
our position. We have certain attitudes and values and principles as a community, as a nation.<br />
We respect China's right to have hers. There will be differences. They should be managed in a<br />
sensible fashion and I believe that what I put to the Prime Minister fully equips the<br />
commitment of an Australian Prime Minister to the principles and the values of his country but<br />
also recognises the realities and the complexities of dealing with other societies and they're<br />
nations that have their own well defined views on these things that are different from ours. I<br />
don't want to try and judge, be judgemental about the Chinese response beyond what I have<br />
said, and I certainly don't want to use the benchmark of someone else in a document which<br />
has apparently been leaked.<br />
JRNLST: Paul Smith. Prime Minister, in relation to the fact that you're here to size up the Chinese<br />
Government to an extent and no doubt they're doing the same to you, how do you think<br />
they're perceiving you as different from the previous government that managed the<br />
relationship for 13 years or how have you tried to make that point of difference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No I haven't the faintest idea. You'd have to go and ask them. The only thing that I have<br />
accepted as a benchmark on this visit is that at every point I try and advance the national </p>
<p>interest of Australia. I am not really interested in comparisons with Paul Keating or Bob<br />
Hawke or Malcolm Fraser or Gough Whitlam. Others will make those comparisons, perhaps<br />
even some in this room will presume to make those comparisons but I am going to keep a long<br />
way away from those and if you want to know the Chinese attitude, well go and ask them.<br />
That's a matter for them. Look, there's quite a lot of continuity in this relationship. I made<br />
that point at the luncheon yesterday. I made it again this morning at the opening of the ASX<br />
and it doesn't help the interests of Australia for a Prime Minister overseas to needlessly point<br />
out differences and try and claim superiority or superior achievement over his predecessors.<br />
That doesn't advance Australia's interests one iota.<br />
JRNLST: Richard McGregor from The Australian newspaper. Mr Howard, given that the Chinese<br />
official media has been full of, had many articles criticising the US relationship with Australia<br />
or the renewed security alliance, how have you been encouraged to believe, as you told<br />
Malcolm that it's not an issue for the Chinese leaders, that they do believe it's an arrangement<br />
which doesn't affect them if you haven't actually discussed it with them?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the point is that I would have thought that if in a discussion between Leader A and<br />
Leader B, Leader A was really unhappy about something, then Leader A would raise it.<br />
JRNLST: Mr Howard, David Penberthy from The Adelaide Advertiser. Do you have any concerns<br />
about reports from Australia that Independent MIP Graeme Campbell is planning to bring some<br />
kind of Australia First roadshow on a kind of island-hopping tour through the region and, on<br />
your visit to Singapore and particularly in China, have any of the Government officials that<br />
you'ye met with raised last year's so-called race debate with you and asked you to explain<br />
where Australia stands in relation to its role in the Asia Pacific?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It certainly wasn't raised with me. It may have been raised at an official level but I will check<br />
that, I haven't been told of that, no. As for the movements of the Federal Member for<br />
Kalgoorlie, well I suppose that's sort of within the London Convention but you know, people<br />
can go where they like. It's a free country.<br />
JRNLST: Thank you Mr Prime Minister. I am a journalist from Chinese Guangmin Daily. Mr Prime<br />
Minister, as you say now you don't see China as a threat. Can you explain why?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Say why?: Well there are a number of reasons for that. I think what China is endeavouring to<br />
do is undertake an historic economic transformation. 45% of China's GDP is consumed by<br />
trade which is an enormous proportion. It seems to me that the last thing a country that wants </p>
<p>to achieve that historic transformation would do would be to act in a hostile fashion towards<br />
the very countries, that is the countries of the region and many others outside that region that<br />
are crucial and fundamental to economic transformation. China has stated strong positions in<br />
relation to issues such as Taiwan and Tibet and others where they regard it as being important<br />
to China's national interest. My own position and that of the Australian Government in<br />
relation to those two areas as stated yesterday is well known and well understood in Australia.<br />
My assessment is that it is in China's interests to have positive and friendly relations with other<br />
countries and that's the reason that I made the comment I did. I can't put it any more strongly<br />
or any less strongly than that.<br />
JRNLST: Nigel Blunden from the Australian Radio Network. Are you happy that this trip achieved the<br />
appropriate balance or an appropriate balance between human rights concerns and our trade<br />
interests or could you have pushed harder on humanitarian issues?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, as I have said, the only benchmark I'm interested in is the benchmark promoting<br />
Australia's national interest and I believe that I have done that. I have pushed hard with some<br />
success in relation to economic and trade and financial services issues. I have certainly further<br />
improved the person to person dialogue and contact between myself and Chinese leaders. I<br />
am more than satisfied with the access that's been given to me and the members of the<br />
business delegation by Chinese leaders and Chinese officials. I have made clear our own<br />
position in relation to such issues as Mr Peng. I have handled the human rights issue in an<br />
appropriate fashion. I haven't ignored it as some suggested I might but I have raised it in a<br />
fashion that I believe is not going to detract from the positive achievements on other fronts<br />
and will at least be as likely as other approaches adopted by other countries over time to<br />
achieve a positive outcome.<br />
Thank you </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
