<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5446</transcript-id>
    <title>TURNING OF THE SOD CEREMONY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/09/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005446.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4~ ASTRLIA EMBARGO: AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
Pi'IME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 18 SEPTEMBER 1<br />
TURNING OF THE SOD CEREMONY.<br />
Sir Bernard Callinan, distinguished guests, ladies<br />
gentlemen, today's ceremony marks the beginning of r<br />
undertaking. For the construction of a new Parliament House,<br />
involving the skills and labour of very many people over some<br />
seven years, will provide a permanent home for the national<br />
Parliament. It will become a focal point for the nation.<br />
Since 1901, the Federal Parliament has had three homes.<br />
When it was first convened on May 9, 1901, it met in the<br />
exhibition building in Melbourne; and, subsequently, under<br />
an arrangement with the Victorian Government of the day, it<br />
met in the Parliament buildings in Spring Street. In 1927, the<br />
Parliament moved to Canberra. And, on Play 9 of that year,<br />
26 years to the day after the opening of the first Commonwealth<br />
Parliament in Melbourne, Australia's national Parliament met<br />
in the present Parliament House. And that building has setved<br />
the Parliament since.<br />
But as the nation grew, and with it the Parliament and the<br />
demands upon the Parliament, it became increasingly clear that<br />
a new building would, in time, be required. Attention centred<br />
for a long time on the question of an appropriate site for<br />
a new Parliament House. Eventually, the Parliamentdecided that<br />
the new building shou ' ld be located here, on Capital Hill, the<br />
focal point in Walter Burley Griffin's design for the National<br />
Capital. The development of this proj ect has been an exercise in<br />
co-operation between the Parliament and the successive Governments<br />
of the day, with support from all parties. The Parliament<br />
House Construction Authority was set up by statute in 1979 to<br />
undertake and carry out the design and construction of the<br />
new building.<br />
Th , e Authority has worked hand in hand with the Joint Standing<br />
Com~ mittee on the New and Permanent Parliament House. The<br />
Authority conducted a worldwide competition for the design.<br />
A panel of six assessors was appointed under the Chairmanship<br />
of Sir John Overall to advise on the conduct of the competition,<br />
to adjudicate and to select the competition winner. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
on Jun. e 26 this year, the entry submitted by the firm of<br />
Mitchell, Giurgola and Thorp, was announced as the winner<br />
from 329 submitted entries. The nominated architect was'<br />
Australian-born Mr. Richard Thorp. In August, following<br />
close examination of the design by the Government, the<br />
Joint Standing Committee and the Parliament, it was decided<br />
to go ahead with the winning design. The winning entry has<br />
received widespread acclaim. It admirably captures and<br />
complements Burley Griffin's original vision for Canberra.<br />
It makes sure that the new Parliament House will blend with<br />
the natural features of the site. And not least of its<br />
virtues, in my view, is that it complements the present<br />
Parliament House which always enjoys a special place in<br />
the nation's history.<br />
This is a most appropriate occasion to acknowledge and commend<br />
all those who have been associated with the project to date.<br />
The Joint Standing Committee, under the Joint Chairmanship of<br />
Mr. President and Mr. Speaker, played a major part in getting<br />
the project underway and I congratulate it on the work it has<br />
done. The project itself is the responsibility of the Parliament House<br />
Construction Authority ' under the distinguished Chairmanship<br />
of Sir Bernard Callinan. I commend him and the members of the<br />
Authority for the work they have done.<br />
Trhe Government, the Parliament and the Australian people are<br />
indebted to all the groups and individuals who have laid the'<br />
basis for the development of a building which is amongst the<br />
most important in Australia's history. It is the intention<br />
of the Parliameont and of this Government that the buildingJ<br />
should be completed in time to allow for its official opening<br />
and occupation by the Parliament in 1988. For in that year,<br />
Australia will be celebrating the 200th Anniversary of<br />
European settlement in this country. But the opening of this<br />
building will represent much more than the celebration of<br />
an Anniversary. For years to' come it will lie at the heart<br />
of our democracy. it will, I believe, stand to represent the<br />
S excitement, the confidence and the aspirations of all of the<br />
people in this nation as Australia moves into the 21st Century.<br />
It is therefore with great pleasure on behalf of the Parliament,<br />
the people and all. Australians, that I now turn the first sod<br />
to commnence the construction phase of this magnificent project.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
