<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9282</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH SPENCER HOWSON, RADIO 4RK, ROCKHAMPTON, TUESDAY, 19 JULY, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009282.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH SPENCER HOWSON, RADIO 4RK, ROCKHAMPTON,<br />
TUESDAY, 19 JULY, 1994<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
SH: Prime Minister Paul Keating, thanks for coming in.<br />
PM: A pleasure, very good to be here.<br />
SH: Well, welcome to Rockhampton, have you seen our new bull statue,<br />
we now have a fifth statue, did you see it as you arrived?<br />
PM: I did in fact, yes I did. I mean, I'm quite familiar with Rocky, I've been<br />
here many times over the years. It's a lovely city.<br />
SH: -What did you think of the new statue. Did you take any notice of it or<br />
just sort of disappear past you?<br />
PM: No, I just sort of, well, I just noticed it and went on, but it is a, I mean,<br />
it's a very important centre this and it's very nicely situated on the river<br />
and that's a very beguiling place.<br />
SH: You spent time this morning with local Year 12 students. What did you<br />
learn and what did they learn from a discussion like that?<br />
PM: Well, I think there's a great freshness of mind about young people,<br />
there's no humbug about them. They're interested in argument, the<br />
facts, they've got views, they express them. They're not reticent, I find<br />
actually speaking to them they are a tough audience. I mean, they are<br />
very tough, they are very tough judges, hard assessors but, one has<br />
a chance to talk about how I see it. I mean, that's what I'm invited to<br />
do talk about how I see Australia, where it will be in 10 years time,<br />
what the opportunities are and, you know, and I was making the point<br />
I've never seen us so well placed and particularly the lives and the ' life<br />
cycle of young people today in the new Australia, the one that's got </p>
<p>international linkages now it never had, I mean a young person could<br />
today be working in Rockhampton one month, in Shanghai the next,<br />
and then be back into Sydney or Melbourne. You know, we've now<br />
international ised the country so much these very high participation<br />
rates in school are producing a huge body of educated people and<br />
where ever we see an educated nation we see an interesting one.<br />
SH: You say a tough audience. I believe one of the questions was<br />
regarding East Timor, was that the sort of thing that you were<br />
expecting?<br />
PM: No, in fact it wasn't one of the set questions, it was on the outside, but<br />
no, I think, tough in a sense of that they listened for value. I mean they<br />
don't want hypocrisy, they want value.<br />
SH: So, they're very educated when it comes to politics you think?<br />
PM: Well, I think they're doing politics, they're doing economics and they<br />
probably follow current affairs more than say, my generation at the<br />
time did. So, I always give them as good as I can. That is, I try and<br />
tell them things directly because not many people get a chance to talk<br />
to the Prime Minister directly, you know, they get it filtered through the<br />
media in some way, of course, you always have a chance to meet<br />
people both coming and going. They all say things to you and the bits<br />
and pieces, if you're a good listener, the odd little gem sticks with you.<br />
SH: Yes, what do you get out of this sort of thing. I mean, in the last week<br />
we've seen the Premier, Wayne Goss, visiting a school in<br />
Rockhampton and the cynics would probably say that they are turning<br />
18 next year, it means they can vote. Do you get more from it than<br />
that?<br />
PM: It's got nothing to do with that. I mean, we do it for the fact that I think<br />
it is important that regions believe that they are as central to the way<br />
the nation functions as the cities are and the point I've been making up<br />
here is that often, if you look now around the country the areas of<br />
greatest employment growth is actually in the regional areas. It's not<br />
in the cities. Now, there is an absolutely greater number of jobs in the<br />
cities because the cities are bigger, but the employment growth rate is<br />
often higher in regional areas. So, I think it's important for Premiers<br />
and Prime Ministers to come to regional centres and that's why I'm<br />
here. I'm not here because a group of children, students are turning<br />
18 years of age. I think that important as that is, I'm here to say ten<br />
years ago, if I'd been here only half as many students would be there<br />
because only 4 in 10 completed secondary school. This year it is 8 in<br />
It will soon be 9 in<br />
SH: And have you had much chance, you've been in Rockhampton very<br />
briefly today, you got in I believe about 1 1: 00am and it's now just </p>
<p>coming up on 3: 00pm. Have you had much chance to talk to local<br />
interest groups, the conservationists about Shoalwater, the<br />
Cattleman's Union and the drought?<br />
PM: I have. I've just attended a very broadly attended function and quite a<br />
few people asked me about Shoalwater Bay and about the drought. I<br />
mean, you do get a chance if you're in public life to meet people at<br />
functions like this and garner some views and I always try and do that.<br />
I always try and meet as many people as possible. I don't just come<br />
and give a speech then walk away. I try. and stay and meet everybody,<br />
have a talk, see what they want to say and obviously Shoalwater Bay<br />
is quite an issue here now and it deserves to be an issue because it is<br />
one of the loveliest, pristine areas of the coast. I mean, not many<br />
countries even have the option of preserving an area like this.<br />
SH: Shoalwater Bay as you say, has been in the news. We've had the<br />
Environment Minister, Senator Faulkner up here. We've had the<br />
Resources Minister, David Beddall up here. Neither of them are<br />
saying much about what they want. They say that it's to go to Cabinet.<br />
Are you saying any more than that at this stage?<br />
PM: No, but of course, I was the one who established the review,<br />
Committee of Inquiry, and I did so because, I think, an area this large<br />
and with environmental values as important as they seem, deserve to<br />
be considered properly and we've done that. We've now got a set of<br />
recommendations and now the Cabinet will have to weigh that report,<br />
it's recommendations, the environmental values versus the economic<br />
potential.<br />
SH: Do you have a personal view on it at this stage?<br />
PM: Well, I'm not entitled to a personal view about it, but I don't mind<br />
saying that, I think, that Australia's been very well placed being able to<br />
reserve some areas. I supported, as Treasurer, Graham Richardson<br />
when he sought to bring forward the proposals to preserve the<br />
Daintree and to declare it to make a World Heritage declaration.<br />
Essentially that was about money and I was quite happy to be finding<br />
the money for that. Recently, of course, the Commonwealth<br />
government has decided not to build an armaments depot at Jervis<br />
Bay. Jervis Bay which is, sort of, an equivalent sort of area on the<br />
NSW coast has beein now preserved from economic development. So,<br />
I think the Labor government has a very proud record in these things<br />
and Shoalwater Bay is being considered properly. I mean, there is a<br />
thing called due process, I mean, there is an issue here. There has<br />
been an inquiry established. There's been a report. The report now<br />
has to be considered.<br />
SH: How much of that can you do though. The protecting the environment<br />
Jervis Bay you mentioned Shoalwater Bay, the other side of the </p>
<p>argument is, of course, that every time you do that you are losing out<br />
on jobs potential. Is that a hard balance for you to try to achieve?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know that that is true. It's true in some cases, but not<br />
necessarily true in others. If you take, let's say, the Daintree,<br />
something we know something about all of us, there is no doubt now, I<br />
think, that the economic impact of preserving the Daintree has far<br />
outweighed the costs of the loss of forestry activities within the<br />
Daintree. It has become, outside of the reef, the principal focus of Far<br />
North Queensland. Tourist attention has-still; I think, a lot of economic<br />
up side about it. So, it is a moot point about where the economics lie.<br />
SH: All right. On the point of the drought. You have been criticised today<br />
by the Cattleman's' Union for not going out and seeing droughted parts<br />
of Queensland as part of this tour.<br />
PM: Well, I've seen droughted parts of Queensland and I've seen<br />
droughted parts of NSW on plenty of occasions over 25 years of public<br />
life. The issue is not to doubt that the drought is there. Of course it's<br />
there and it's there probably because of climate change effects. What<br />
the Commonwealth Government has said is look, rather than simply<br />
this be part of the natural disaster relief arrangements, disaster means<br />
it is intermittent and unlikely and therefore where it comes it has to<br />
have an arrangement which reflects those kinds of circumstances.<br />
Whereas what we know is with these climate change effects, is it is<br />
much less intermittent than it was, it's becoming a permanent feature<br />
of the Australian landscape in one place or another each year and<br />
therefore, rather than simply dealing with it on a, sort of, natural<br />
disasters basis it's best dealt with as an on-going agricultural<br />
management problem and hence we have included it in the Rural<br />
Adjustment Scheme in the RAS scheme.<br />
Now, what my colleague Senator Bob Collins has said recently is look,<br />
if we think that these drought arrangements are not adequate then we<br />
can review RAS and, I think, he said that today. We can review RAS<br />
and see whether it is working. Now, I think that's the way to go.<br />
SH: All right, on a second point on rural issues, the National Farmers<br />
Federation has been pushing for a commitment from the Federal<br />
Government to make the family farm exempt from Austudy asset<br />
testing which, I believe, was an election promise. So far no<br />
commitment on that though. What's going on with that?<br />
PM: Well, I think, this is a complex matter. We have sought always in<br />
establishing Austudy arrangements to try and overcome the fact that<br />
some people have got quite a lot of capital tied up in farms though not<br />
necessarily a lot of income. So, on an assets basis they could be quite<br />
comfortable. On an income basis this is not so. It is a matter of finding<br />
the balance in these things, I think. </p>
<p>SH: Well, is something going to be done about that?<br />
PM: Well, it is not something which is across my desk at the moment, but<br />
that's not to say I think that the Minister for Education, that is Simon<br />
Crean and his colleague Minister, won't have this as other issues<br />
under, if you like, a permanent watch.<br />
SH: All right, it all sounds very political that. I mean, does this mean that<br />
we are going to get some sort of answer some stage this year or is it<br />
PM: I can't tell you. It's not a Cabinet ranked matter at the moment and I'm<br />
not sure whether we can design an arrangement where simply the<br />
capital values of properties completely, you know, have a very<br />
diminished impact upon the granting of Austudy arrangements. I<br />
mean, Austudy has been extended as you know to Years 11 and 12.<br />
During the period of this Government we have improved Austudy at<br />
home and away from home and the level of the payments are<br />
comparatively generous to what they were when the Government came<br />
to office. It's again, a case of cutting the cloth.<br />
SH: All right, from Queensland to a couple of national issues. The Reserve<br />
Bank has warned today that banks are lending too much money to the<br />
housing sector. Do you share that concern?<br />
PM: It is a matter for the bank to make a judgement about this I think. It has<br />
stewardship of the financial system and it watches the call on the<br />
capital of banks in the devotion of their capital to certain areas of<br />
lending. I think there is also another impact, that is the impact of<br />
housing lending on the economy. It depends where the lending is. If<br />
the lending is in new housing, of course, it adds the supply. If it is<br />
simply bidding up the price of the existing stock of housing well, that's<br />
a horse of another colour. It may be this, I think, that concerns the<br />
Governor and he's the appropriate person to take this up with the<br />
banks.<br />
SH: There has been reports today that the Reserve Bank wants to push for<br />
re-regulation. Do you think that this is all an argument for that?<br />
PM: No, no. I don't think the bank thinks that at all. I mean, heaven forbid<br />
if we were to go back to the time when savings banks couldn't take<br />
deposits over $ 100,000, that banks couldn't accept deposits under<br />
days, all these silly regulations which existed in the past. It has always<br />
amazed me that people have actually even thought about going back<br />
to them. I'm sure the bank has no idea to do those things at all.<br />
SH: What about a compromise. Say, increasing the capital adequacy<br />
requirements from 50 to 60 per cent? </p>
<p>PM: Of banks or on housing lending?<br />
SH: On the housing lending.<br />
PM: Well, it's a matter of really how much at the moment the so-called<br />
risk weights are the amount of capital that a bank would need to<br />
commit to a certain size housing lending book and these weights have<br />
been largely determined by the BIS Convention this is the Bank of<br />
International Settlements Convention. Whether they reflect really<br />
prudential risks in Australia I don't know, but again this is something<br />
for the bank to make, it's something within its charge.<br />
SH: All right, a couple of brief ones more. In the Sydney Morning Herald<br />
this morning a report that the Government is to overhaul family policies<br />
to counter the Opposition's plan to sell itself as the pro-family party. Is<br />
that the reason for the planned overhaul?<br />
PM: No, I mean, the Government has lead on family policies all across the<br />
last decade. I mean, starting with Medicare, universal access of all<br />
Australian families to health protection regardless of income. The<br />
Coalition party the Liberal and National party want to basically give<br />
a free kick to the medical profession and private hospitals, charge what<br />
the market will bear and cover it with gap insurance. We won't be in<br />
that. The Family Allowance Supplement, probably one of the leading<br />
income support systems in the world came from this Government in<br />
1987-88. The child support agency, the generalised child care rebate<br />
which I promised in the last election and which we have now<br />
implemented, the Home Child Care allowance which will paid in<br />
September this year was a commitment by the Government in the last<br />
election. The Coalition will have to run awfully hard to catch the Labor<br />
party on family policy and the reason is, basically, because the Labor<br />
party is a party and a government which is worried about the general<br />
needs of the community. The Coalition is basically an elite<br />
organisation that is interested in people with high incomes.<br />
SH: One of the major components of this new government plan to give<br />
women up to 12 weeks maternity leave at the existing dole rate of $ 140<br />
a week, can you tell us a little bit about that, how would that work?<br />
PM: Well, that is something that we are going to look at in next year's<br />
Budget as a consequence of our on-going discussions with the ACTU<br />
and the Accord. They have been regarding this for a long time as an<br />
important thing, that is, that there is some income protection there for<br />
maternity leave. Now, we are very sympathetic to that. It is all about<br />
means, it is all about being able to do it at the time. But, if you look at<br />
the improvements, the massive improvements to the income of<br />
families, particularly lower income families from the governmenit's<br />
policies, compared to say where they were in 1983, I mean they are<br />
not to be compared. </p>
<p>SH: This idea of giving women the 12 weeks maternity leave, would that be<br />
for all women regardless of whether or not they have children because<br />
there has been some talk that all women should be eligible for it.<br />
PM: We haven't designed it, we said that we will we said to the ACTU<br />
and we announced this at the time, recently, when we had just agreed<br />
to two $ 8 payments for the bottom third of the workforce in these next<br />
two years that we will look at it next year and that will, of course, be<br />
one of the design issues whether it is income tested et cetera.<br />
SH: Would you be interested in looking at some sort of equivalent scheme<br />
for gay families bringing up children?<br />
PM: It has never been proposed.<br />
SH: Well, how do you feel about that yourself the idea?<br />
PM: Well, I've never thought about it to be honest. It's not on the top of my<br />
agenda and may never be.<br />
SH: If someone were to propose it to you<br />
PM: I don't normally just make decisions about these sorts of things. These<br />
are things that we think about in terms of a framework and the big<br />
framework for us is basically looking after families in need.<br />
SH: All right, Prime Minister Keating, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
