<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6642</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006642.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 6 JUNE 1985<br />
The following arrangements have been agreed by the<br />
Minister for Transport, Mr Morris, and myself, to give<br />
effect to the understanding on transport co-operation<br />
with China that I reached with General Secretary Hu<br />
Yaobang during his recent visit.<br />
During his recent visit to Australia, Hu Yaobang<br />
described transport and energy as two major areas of<br />
attention in China's Seventh Five Year Plan.<br />
Australia's transport experience is of particular<br />
relevance to China. Ours is a vast continent with<br />
diverse transport needs and problems. We have developed<br />
special expertise in moving bulk commodities over long<br />
distances, and also have relevant expertise in such<br />
diverse areas as road building, air services, road<br />
transport and cargo handling.<br />
I advised Mr Hu of Australia's willingness and capacity<br />
to co-operate in the review and modernisation of China's<br />
transport infrastructure.<br />
As discussed with Hu Yaobang, Sir Peter Abeles, Managing<br />
Director and Chief Executive of Thomas Nationwide<br />
Transport ( TNT), has agreed that a planned Ansett/ TNT<br />
visit to China will be expanded to include a Government<br />
delegation. Sir Peter Abeles will be leader and Mr Paul Barratt,<br />
Deputy Secretary, Department of Trade, Deputy Leader of<br />
the Transport Mission.<br />
The official mission will be responsible for developing<br />
with the Chinese Government a permanent Government to<br />
Government mechani'sm for promoting long-term<br />
co-operation in transport. Within this mechanism,<br />
opportunities will be developed for a wide range of<br />
Australian private and public sector interests to<br />
co-operate in China's development. </p>
<p>In preparation for the Transport Mission, the Department<br />
of Trade tomorrow, 7 June, will convene a briefing in<br />
Canberra for industry associations in the transport<br />
sector. The briefing will outline the Government's aims<br />
for co-operation with China in the transport sector,<br />
identify possible options to achieve those aims, and<br />
seek industry views.<br />
The initial mission to China will identify particular<br />
transport issues facing China and develop options for<br />
future bilateral co-operation in those areas where<br />
Australia can best assist.<br />
Members of the mission will meet with participants in<br />
the Australian transport sector who are interested in<br />
developing the relationship with China after their<br />
return. The findings of the mission will be put to<br />
Australian industry and a package of initiatives and<br />
plans for future action and further missions will be<br />
developed. The Government's success in maintaining economic growth<br />
and concentrating our efforts on those goods and<br />
services where we have a competitive advantage, have<br />
placed Australia in a useful position to provide<br />
assistance to China. Our experience in comparable<br />
conditions will be of particular benefit.<br />
Australian industry needs to be sensitive to<br />
international opportunities and place emphasis on those<br />
areas where we have superior technology, expertise or a<br />
competitive edge.<br />
The Government's first objective is to co-operate with<br />
China in developing its transport system to support<br />
economic development. Commercial and economic benefits<br />
for Australia will be a pleasing bonus. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
