<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40787</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks at bilateral meeting with His Excellency, Mr Joko Widodo, President of the Republic of Indonesia, Ministers and officials.</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong>Mr President, welcome to Australia, to Sydney.</p>
<p>We had a very, very warm dinner last night at our home. Lucy and I were thrilled to see you and Iriana and of course your Foreign Minister Retno Marsudi. We had a very good dinner, a very good discussion, a very relaxed evening.</p>
<p>We’ve had a very nice walk in the Botanic Gardens this morning and the President and I met lots of Australians who were being very fit. They were running -</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>And we were strolling, walking. All these very athletic people were running past us. And we met a charming young man with an eight-week-old baby. He said that his wife was having a sleep in while he took his baby for a walk in the gardens, so it was very sweet.</p>
<p>But we have got such a strong relationship. It’s a very strong friendship and it gets stronger all the time. We’re working towards the Comprehensive Economic Partnership and great progress there. We’re increasing our trading links and investment, so there’s a lot to discuss.</p>
<p>At every level the Australia – Indonesian relationship gets stronger and stronger. Of course, the bedrock of that is the Lombok Treaty and our absolute respect for, support for, solidarity with Indonesia, its territorial integrity. We give you our full support.</p>
<p>So we’re delighted that you’re here Mr President and we look forward to a good discussion as you continue your visit to Australia.</p>
<p><strong>PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA: </strong>Thank you very much, good morning.</p>
<p>Thank you very much again for the warm welcome extended to me and the entire Indonesian delegation.</p>
<p>I think our wonderful and fruitful discussion last night over dinner has already covered most of the issues.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>And we truly appreciate your aforementioned support for Indonesia’s sovereignty and territorial integrity.</p>
<p>Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
