<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5798</transcript-id>
    <title>RESIGNATION OF MINISTERS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/04/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005798.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-i ,, AUSTRALIA L<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, APRIL 19 1982<br />
RESIGNATION OF MINISTERS<br />
With regret I have accepted the resignations of Mr MacKellar<br />
as Minister for Health and Mr Moore as Minister for Business<br />
and Consumer Affairs. Both ministers tendered their resignations<br />
in view of questions that have arisen about their actions in<br />
respect of customs procedures and having regard to their<br />
acceptance of responsibility for those actions.<br />
Mr MacKellar assures me, and I accept, that in bringing a<br />
colour television set through Customs last October, he had<br />
no intention either to mislead Customs or to evade duty.<br />
He has quite properly accepted responsibility for the<br />
incorrect declaration that was completed in his name.<br />
The outcome! however was that duty was not paid at the time<br />
although subsequently it will be paid and the Minister<br />
therefore appears to be in a preferred position compared with.<br />
other Australians something that ministerial instructions<br />
issued in 1976 sought specifically to avoid.<br />
Mr Moore very properly followed-up the question of the<br />
S tion ctohrer ecetxltye ntc oomfp leetsetda blciusshtionmsg wdheectlhaerra tithoen fiotremm, bbruotu ghntot<br />
in by Mr MacKellar was dutiable or not.<br />
Mr Moore has assured me, and I accept, that his error<br />
in not following up this question was an error honestly made.<br />
This Government has always upheld the fundamental principles<br />
of Ministerial responsibility, and that the appearance and<br />
reality of integrity are indispensible parts of our system<br />
of government. I have insisted, and our Party expects, that<br />
responsibi] lity should be maintained. It is extremely regrettable<br />
that these instances have come into the path of otherwise<br />
outstandingj performances by these two Ministers.<br />
The penalties in public office are high. Both Ministers<br />
accept this and have accordingly volunteered their resignations. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
It is my intention to recommend to His Excellency, the<br />
Governor-General, that the resignations be accepted. I shall<br />
recommend to His Excellency that, for the time being, the<br />
Minister for Employment and Youth Affairs, Mr Brown, be<br />
sworn as Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs and the<br />
Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, Senator Baume, be sworn as<br />
Minister for Health, until such time as permanent arrangements<br />
are made. The appointments will be in addition to their<br />
present portfolios.<br />
This matter will of course be referred to in Parliament<br />
tomorrow. Relevant papers will be available to be tabled. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
