<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11203</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - NHK                TOYKO, JAPAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, what are the likelihood of troops being sent into East</p>
<p> Timor?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it's entirely premature for anybody to be talking about that,</p>
<p> we have a combat readiness. I certainly hope that that won't be necessary.</p>
<p> You must remember of course that troops can only enter a foreign country</p>
<p> in two ways, they only enter by invitation or by invasion and we certainly</p>
<p> have no intention of invading any country, so I think we have to keep</p>
<p> the whole thing in perspective.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Downer seems to think it might be a good thing to do after or during</p>
<p> the transition period, I should say..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I've read what Mr Downer said and I know exactly what he said and</p>
<p> the point I'm making is that Australian troops would only go somewhere</p>
<p> as a result of an invitation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But if they are invited into East Timor, if it did vote for independence,</p>
<p> would the Australian Government be happy to do that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is something that we'll deal with if and when it arrises.</p>
<p> The important thing for a country like Australia to do is to be ready,</p>
<p> which we are, to offer the help that we are through the civilian police,</p>
<p> offer the aid which we are and then deal with each development as</p>
<p> and when it comes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In the meantime what about the safety of the civil police there now</p>
<p> from Australia and other countries, is it time to arm those police</p>
<p> given the unrest?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The constant advice we've had Fran is that arming them would make</p>
<p> them more likely targets. That matter was discussed extensively. I</p>
<p> had the same view as you apparently have and the question implies</p>
<p> but the advice that I had from the Federal Police, from the Head of</p>
<p> the Defence Force and from the Intelligence Services was that past</p>
<p> experience in other countries indicated that if you arm people, even</p>
<p> side arms, they're far more likely to come under attack and we accepted</p>
<p> that advice and we just have to keep the situation under constant</p>
<p> monitoring. It's dangerous, I've never disguised that fact and we</p>
<p> certainly hope they don't come to any harm but the strong advice we</p>
<p> have is that if you arm them you make them more likely targets.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you in your talks last night with Mr Obuchi raise any specific</p>
<p> trade issues, any specific trade problems between the two Nations?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There was what I might call a passing reference to the issues of rice</p>
<p> and tuna, the rice issue has been dealt with in the sense that a decision</p>
<p> was taken by Japan and there are certain other discussions and processes</p>
<p> and our position in relation to tuna is well known. Those issues were</p>
<p> touched upon but they weren't the dominant issues. The dominant trade</p>
<p> issue for Australia and Japan is the upcoming APEC meeting and then</p>
<p> going on from APEC the need to have an effective and comprehensive</p>
<p> round through the world trade organisation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What are the implications for Australian farmers if Japan doesn't</p>
<p> keep its market open?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we obviously want open markets all around the world. We want</p>
<p> an open lamb market in the United States, we want open markets in</p>
<p> Japan. We have done quite well over the last few years in winning</p>
<p> access to markets previously closed. For a nation of 18.5 million</p>
<p> people who has the most efficient farmers in the world, we have a</p>
<p> clear national interest in prizing open markets and when we've prized</p>
<p> them open keeping them open.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard you also discussed China no doubt, how much concern is it</p>
<p> to the two nations that now one member of APEC Papua New Guinea has</p>
<p> recognised Taiwan?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that particular issue was not discussed I don't recall, Mr Downer</p>
<p> has expressed a view on behalf of the Australian Government regarding</p>
<p> it and I agree with what Mr Downer said.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are we coming under pressure from China over this to put pressure</p>
<p> on PNG?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I haven't felt any pressure, I'm not aware of any pressure. We</p>
<p> have a one China policy. We have a good understanding with China.</p>
<p> It doesn't prevent commercial links between Australia and Taiwan but</p>
<p> it does recognise the sovereignty of the Government in Beijing and</p>
<p> we won't in any way depart from that. I want to make that very clear</p>
<p> that we remain very strongly committed to the one China policy. That</p>
<p> has been Australian government policy now for a number of years and</p>
<p> there won't be any departure from it but there is nothing inconsistent</p>
<p> with that in us having strong commercial links with Taiwan.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
