<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9890</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH ANGELA CATTERNS, TRIPLE J, 15 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009890.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
K,.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH ANGELA CATTERNS, TRIPLE J, 15 DECEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
AC: Welcome back to Triple J, Mr Keating.<br />
PM: Thank you, Angela. Good to be here, particularly on this day.<br />
AC: Now, five more transmitters have begun broadcasting the Triple J word<br />
today, with another set to begin on the weekend. What do you think it<br />
is going to mean to the young Australians in these areas?<br />
PM: Well it must be unique, I think, as a national concept. I can't think of<br />
many other countries that have a network so extensive for young<br />
people. You know it was, I think, in 1989 we decided to extend the<br />
network before that it used to be broadcasting in Sydney<br />
we decided to extend it to other States and Territories and to<br />
Newcastle and then by the end of 1990, I think, it reached about<br />
66 per cent of the population. And then you might remember, Angela,<br />
in August of 1993 we announced we would extend Triple J to 44 new<br />
metropolitan centres at a cost of $ 12 million. And today, we are<br />
celebrating the extension to North East Tasmania, Geraldton, Albany,<br />
Mackay in Queensland, the Southern Downs of Queensland, and the<br />
La Trobe Valley of Victoria, and Bega and Cooma in New South<br />
Wales, amongst other places. So, I think, it will now go to all centres<br />
of more than 20,000 people. It will reach about 89 or 90 per cent of<br />
the population. So I can't think of any other country which has such a<br />
network. I think it is a fantastic concept.<br />
AC: Mr Keating, why did you do it? What is the Government's aim in<br />
expanding Triple J like this throughout Australia?<br />
PM: I think to provide a network where young people can listen to music,<br />
where we can expand the whole menu of Australian music, give them a<br />
station or a channel where they can listen to debates which affect<br />
them, that gives them a medium where they feel part of it and included </p>
<p>in it. It is a very inclusive concept Triple J. You know everybody that<br />
has a common interest, whether by age or by inclination, can find<br />
somewhat of a spiritual home in the medium. So I think that is the<br />
reason.<br />
AC: Oh, I am glad you think that.<br />
PM: Well I must think it we put the dollars down for it. You have got to<br />
think it.<br />
AC: And so how committed are you, really, to representing the interests of<br />
young Australians? You know it seems all of a sudden politicians have<br />
realised there is a youth vote.<br />
PM: Oh, I don't think so. I mean I don't think all of a sudden. Let me say,<br />
for my part, I have spent most of my political life making certain that<br />
young people today have more opportunities and a more interesting<br />
life than I had at their age. Not that my life, at their age, wasn't a good<br />
life. But it didn't have the vitality, the interests, the opportunities that,<br />
I think, young people have today. I mean just ten years ago, only three<br />
young people in ten completed secondary school. This year, it is just<br />
under eight in ten and as you know we massively expanded higher<br />
education and vocational education. And look at the<br />
intemnationalisation of the economy now. Look at the opportunities in<br />
Asia. What I found, myself, was working in Sydney for a Government<br />
employer and that is what I had mostly to look forward to. I mean<br />
today somebody can find themselves working for any number of<br />
people, can find themselves working in Asia, or in North America, or in<br />
Europe and be back here, then go somewhere else, or do something<br />
else. So, I think, that education is the great boundary jumper.<br />
Education is the thing that lets people jump the barriers of opportunity<br />
and so my political life has been about believing in the vitality of the<br />
sort of effervescence, the verve, of young Australians. And much of<br />
what I am about is including them and making them feel as though<br />
they are part of the place. I mean everything, in fact, we are doing..<br />
you know this thing we put together in Osaka in Japan, a couple of<br />
weeks ago, with APEC opening all the trade barriers up in the Pacific,<br />
taking all the tariff barriers off Australia, letting the thing breath, letting<br />
people go out there and be part of it. I mean some of these places are<br />
just so exciting.<br />
AC: Mr Keating, you must be pleased with your diplomatic coup today.<br />
The security pact with Indonesia has really surprised us all. Why was<br />
it necessary?<br />
PM: Well we live next to the Indonesians. They are an old society of<br />
190 million people and we have to reach a point of clear<br />
understanding about what our own strategic intentions are towards<br />
each other and we don't want to see any conflict in the area any more.<br />
We saw this in the Second World War and the Korean War and in </p>
<p>Vietnam. So, we have developed a security agreement which is more<br />
than a defence agreement. It is about security. It is about doing<br />
clever things together in the region to secure ourselves so we never<br />
have to see ourselves in conflicts again. And that can extend to the<br />
peace accords in Cambodia which we worked on or the huge<br />
undertaking of APEC, opening up the trade barriers in the Asia-Pacific<br />
or just cooperating in any of the other fields where we believe we can<br />
make it better for Australians and Indonesians. And, where we commit<br />
ourselves to one another in a more formal way than we have ever<br />
done before.<br />
AC: As we know Mr Keating you are a great supporter of self determination<br />
in Aboriginal Australia. Why not in East Timor?<br />
PM: We are not arguing self determination in East Timor. East Timor is a<br />
province of Indonesia and has been since 1975. What we are<br />
concerned about in East Timor is the way in which people live, the<br />
respect for their rights as individuals and we have, as a government,<br />
always made our position clear on this with Indonesia. In fact, I am<br />
sure we have been one of the few countries making our views known<br />
as vociferously as we have and what ever possibilities the people of<br />
Timor have for better lives, lives where they believe all their liberties<br />
are being respected, it is in the context, I believe, of a broader deeper<br />
relationship between Australia and Indonesia. It is not going to be<br />
happening with Australia turning its back on Indonesia. This did<br />
happen from 1975 until about the middle of the 1980s. By and large,<br />
Australia turned its back on Indonesia. It took Timor nowhere and, I<br />
think, this sort of model we produced yesterday is the right framework<br />
to be working in for Timor.<br />
AC: Has 1995 been a good year for you, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: Well, we have got a lot of things done. I mean, good years for me are<br />
about what you can accomplish, what things you are able to do. For a<br />
start we have got this huge regional security agreement with Indonesia<br />
yesterday. Three weeks ago in Osaka we saw the action plan for the<br />
biggest free trade area in the world of which we were massively<br />
involved. We have laid out the blue print for republic. We delivered a<br />
superannuation system to all Australians which will most beneficially<br />
effect young Australians, giving them a decent standard of living in<br />
retirement and a pile of savings to go with it. We think, for this<br />
generation of young Australians, around $ 2 trillion in savings $ 2000<br />
billion in national savings.<br />
I think, we have had an extraordinary year for that generation of<br />
Australians who remember World War 11 with Australia Remembers.<br />
We have convened the Canberra Commission to start the world<br />
thinking seriously about getting rid of nuclear weapons and I am<br />
bringing that group together from around the world in Sydney in<br />
January. </p>
<p>As you know, we have had the economy the most pleasing thing is<br />
that the economy has been growing. We have had now the longest<br />
period of growth since World War 11 17 consecutive quarters of<br />
growth and we have had 730,000 jobs since the last election and we<br />
have got the budget in surplus.<br />
It is hard to have a better year than that. If you are sitting in this job, it<br />
is pretty hard to top that.<br />
AC: How many plane trips do you reckon you have taken 1995?<br />
PM: Oh well, as many as I have to. I am very stingy with my movements. I<br />
try not to move around unless I have to. If I have to go somewhere I<br />
try to do three things at once, rather than make three trips, but even so<br />
I do a lot of travelling.<br />
AC: Are there any personal highs or lows you would care to share with us<br />
Mr Keating?<br />
PM: I think getting the security agreement with Indonesia is a very big high<br />
for me.<br />
AC: It sounds like you have been celebrating long into the night.<br />
PM: I need a cup of tea or a coffee. I need a bit of a hit some where or a<br />
bit later, something else. No, I think, when something is done about<br />
the security of the country, I mean, every Prime Ministers first<br />
occupation must be with security of the country and this goes right<br />
centrally to it. The other high, I think, is APEC. APEC we started<br />
from nothing really, It was a small economic organisation in 1992 and<br />
we built it into the biggest free -trade organisation. Certainly the<br />
biggest free-trade agenda in the world, with the United States, Japan,<br />
China, Indonesia, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Singapore,<br />
Malaysia I mean, it's an enormous body. So, that was getting that<br />
action agenda into place in Osaka was really pleasing for me. And<br />
we have had a lot of other things like, I got this proposal together for<br />
improving our civics education in our institutions. That is, talking<br />
about the workings and the traditions of our democracy, but in<br />
schools, which is going to affect the way people view the whole<br />
institutional basis of the country into the future. And the other thing,<br />
of course, I was very chuffed about was getting a solid framework<br />
down for the republic, and in the months since I did that speech in the<br />
House of Representatives, quite a number of people are now coming<br />
around to saying " Well, on all things considered, the balances in that<br />
speech are pretty right". You know how people reflect on things, you<br />
know, people writing in newspapers and what have you. So, I'm very<br />
happy about that.<br />
AC: Will you be taking a holiday, Mr Keating? </p>
<p>PM: I'm going to have a couple of weeks of I always have two or three<br />
weeks off at Christmas because.<br />
AC: Do you go away?<br />
PM: Well, it's the only time in Australia that the country closes down,<br />
generally shuts up.<br />
AC: Do you go to the beach, or a farm, or stay home?<br />
PM: No. I mostly go to Sydney, because Sydney in summer is fantastic.<br />
You have the Festival of Sydney all the good shows on, half the<br />
traffic, it's not too hot, and I mostly end up somewhere up at Pittwater.<br />
I do a bit of sailing, and I'm doing that this year, too.<br />
AC: Sounds fun.<br />
PM: I mean, just light you know, no-one talking politics or policies,<br />
AC: Turn the phones off. Tell us what a Keating family Christmas is like<br />
does Annita cook?<br />
PM: Well, she has always done, until we have come to the Lodge. But<br />
there, our chef always makes a nice Christmas meal for us. But, the<br />
main thing is the joy we have always had my youngest daughter is<br />
ten Alexandra and of course when we went to the Lodge she was<br />
six, and they were all relatively young. And always, I think, the joy for<br />
us is watching them sort of enjoy the day, and open their presents<br />
and have their friends around. It's that sort of a day a day together.<br />
AC: What do people buy you?<br />
PM: I'm a bit hard to buy for.<br />
AC: I can imagine.<br />
PM: I'm a bit hard to buy for.<br />
AC: Not socks and ties, I presume?<br />
PM: Well, you can get me in with a good Tom Jones CD I'm in the<br />
market for a few more of those.<br />
AC: Right. I can hear him dropping hints.<br />
PM: Yeah. I also... you know I like classical music, and I always look for<br />
some historic violin material.<br />
AC: Really? </p>
<p>PM: People like David Oistrach, or Jascha Heifetz or Nathan Milstein<br />
any of these sort of people. I'm always a sucker for a weepy tune.<br />
AC: Are you?<br />
PM: And the weepiest tunes, of course, come from violins. Or a weepy<br />
song.<br />
AC: Mr Keating big year ahead for you. Do you ever entertain the<br />
though that you might lose the election?<br />
PM: In this game it's all thrills and spills. One hopes for more thrills than<br />
spills, but there are spills around you have got to avoid them if you<br />
can. You can't always.<br />
AC: And so when will we all be voting then?<br />
PM: Well, before next May.<br />
AC: Before next May.<br />
PM: The House of Representatives has to sit three years after it last, first<br />
sat. And it last first sat in this Parliament in May of 1993, so it's three<br />
years to May. Our tradition is to have it a little before the expiration<br />
of that time, and that may be so again. So, it's not far away.<br />
AC: Not far away?<br />
PM: It's not far away. And we're going to have a Christmas without too<br />
much politics, if I can pin Johnny Howard down to a decent Christmas<br />
day, and stop him running around.<br />
AC: What you and him are going to spend it together?<br />
PM: No I don't think we'll be going that. But, I think the public want a<br />
break. They want a break from the hubbub of public life, and all the<br />
buzzes of debate. And this, I think, is the cycle for that break.<br />
AC: So, we'll probably go to the polls around about February some time?<br />
PM: Well, that's what they say here in Parliament House, in the Press<br />
Gallery.<br />
AC: Do they?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
AC: Mr Keating, we appreciate very much you being here with us on this<br />
very exciting day. I don't know if you know, but Triple J at this time </p>
<p>7<br />
every year conducts a poll of the best songs of the year. We call it<br />
the Hottest 100 do you have a favourite song of 1995?<br />
PM: I think that Christine Anu song Party is one of the things my kids<br />
like, and....<br />
AC: Don't forget to tell them to vote in our Hottest 100, your kids.<br />
PM: And I don't mind it myself.<br />
AC: Good on you. Well, I' II play it for you now. Thank you so much for<br />
joining us today Mr Keating Happy Christmas.<br />
PM: Thank you Angela. Thanks for the yarn. Good bye.<br />
AC: Bye.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
