<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4167</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH WELCOMES VICTORIAN MOVE ON DAIRY SUPPORT - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON JD ANTHONY MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004167.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MEDIA RELEASE Commonwealth '. elcomes Victorian<br />
-Moe -n Dairy Support<br />
Statement by the Actin-Prime Minister, the Rt Hon. J. D. Anthony, M. P.<br />
I welcome the decision by the Victorian Government to<br />
-rticipate with the Commonwealth in financing underwriting arrangements<br />
for the dairy industry for the next six months.<br />
This decision, which the Premier, r. Hamer, announced at<br />
s mass meeting of dairy farmers in Melbourne, means that<br />
. ictcria is the first State to indicate its willingness to join with<br />
the Co. mmonwealth in a measure that will ensure s= m scability for the<br />
industry while decisions are made on its long--er= future. I hope the<br />
States will quickly follow Victoria's lead so -hat early<br />
_ ecisions can be made on opening pay rates for the season<br />
starzing on 1st July.<br />
The dairy industry must decide whether it wants to<br />
continue exporting and, if so, how much of its production can be exported<br />
profitably. It will then need to determine the most appropriate<br />
roduction levels.<br />
Then a national policy will have to be developed covering<br />
the industry throughout Australia.<br />
Until this is done, and until governments know what the<br />
industry's policy is, it is unrealistic to ask them to commit large<br />
amounts of money to measures which do nothing to resolve the<br />
industry's basic marketing problems.<br />
If governments knew what it would involve, I have no<br />
doubt they would be ready to work with the industry to devise a floor<br />
price arrangement for export sales, and to help it get the best<br />
possible return from the domestic market.<br />
The States must share with the Commonwealth the cost<br />
of helping the industry.<br />
The States have control of production and marketing<br />
arrangements. Some States have followed policies in thee areas which<br />
a: e contributed significantly to the industry's pre. en difficulties.<br />
It is good to see that, at last, there is to be an<br />
eni 7o the opening up of new dairy farms.<br />
But the wide disparity in returns to producers -f " city<br />
ilk" = nd milk used in the manufacrure of dairy products still exists.<br />
Lack of arrangements giving all producers a fair return has<br />
contributed very much to the present crisis for producers in the<br />
manufacturing sector. </p>
<p>The policls ' nave producea two classes of producsrs<br />
are unfair and ineo~ 3.<br />
Positive E. tms rtst be taken ro change the situation. In<br />
this day and age arrar. e-eets are hardly necessary.<br />
By r~ the in-stry to a certain export level<br />
a guaranteed ar rang eenm r-c the. creation of a one-price<br />
arra-:, entt for dz-c s cry roducts we could arrive<br />
a stable and re,, : czabe income which would allow for the bulk of<br />
irustry to pln : or its future.<br />
une, 1.976 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
