<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1130</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS, RADIO AND TELEVISION CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA - 13TH JULY 1965</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001130.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS. RADIO AND TELEVISION CONFERENCE<br />
GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER. THE RT. HON.<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES, AT PARLIAMENT HOUSE,<br />
CANBERRA 13TH JUJLY, 196-1<br />
PIME MINISTER : I think, gentlemen, I ought to begin by asking you<br />
whether the procedures that I have adopted in the past are satisfactory<br />
to you.<br />
I noticed one complaint somewhere that I had fallen into<br />
the bad habit, I gathered, of starting off by saying something for<br />
myself instead of confining myself to answering questions. Well,<br />
I am pretty sure you will agree that as there might be four or five<br />
topics on which you would be interested today, it would be a great<br />
mistake to have a question on one and then a question on another<br />
so that the whole thing became completely confused. I don't want<br />
to restrict your questions at all but I do think that it might be<br />
more orderly if I said something about the first topic and then<br />
heard your questions on it and then passed on to another it being<br />
open to you, of course, all through, to raise questions that you,<br />
have in your mind to which you think I might give a useful answer.<br />
If that is agreeable, I think I would like to begin by<br />
saying something about the position in Viet~ am and our presence<br />
there and how it has come about. I wouldn't have thought there<br />
was very much doubt about this benause this has been very freely<br />
debated in Parliament over quite a time but perhaps I might help<br />
by summing it up a little,<br />
Some gentlemen who have communicated with me recently seem<br />
to think that I am doing something all by myself that I am involving<br />
Australia in war, that I am helping to escalate that war into<br />
something bigger. Strange Christian sentiments indeed,<br />
Well, of course, I can't plead guilty to that because as<br />
all of those of you who follow these matters know perfectly well7<br />
our attitude towards Viet Nam, the placing of Australian forces in<br />
Viet Nam was not just the decision of one man, it was a Cabinet<br />
decision, announced by me publicly in Parliament on April 29; th and<br />
thereafter debated in the Parliament the better part of two<br />
s ittings. So that the idea that this is a sort of one-man frolic<br />
is absurd. On top of that I think I ought to take the opportunity of<br />
saying that so far as the Government parties are concerned -' both<br />
Government parties every member of both porties entirely supports<br />
the action of the Government in this matter, so that it is rather<br />
foolish to talk about it as a sort of one-man decision,<br />
I am not avoiding my own responsibility the decision of<br />
the Government is entirely in line with my own view and I have never<br />
had any reason to make any apology for it or any qualificatibn or<br />
put any qualification upon it. Not only did we make this decision<br />
and announce it in the Parliament but the President of the Security<br />
Council was informed and the SEATO Council was officially informed by<br />
my colleague. It is perhaps as well to recall that Australian defence is<br />
not a solitary defence, It is a defence which is involved with<br />
certain international treaties under which we have rights and under<br />
which we have obligations. I don't need to mention them to<br />
gentlemen like you who are familiar with them the South East / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Asian Treaty, the ANZUS Pact, our uni-lateral obligation to Malaysia,<br />
publicly stated and debated in this Parliament and in the Press<br />
all of these things are matters which involve us the defence of<br />
New Guinea and Papua which we have accepted as part of the defence<br />
of the mainland of Australia.<br />
We have, as a matter of fact, a considerable variety of<br />
obligations but we are also, I am happy to say, in possession of<br />
a considerable variety of rights. In other words, there is<br />
mutuality about all these agreements and that has much to say to<br />
the safety of our own country.<br />
South Viet Nain happens to be one of the protocol states<br />
under the SEATO Treaty and that means that the obligations under<br />
the SEATO Treaty w~' hich include military obligations, extend to<br />
that country, buz on one condition, of course, and that is that the<br />
government of the country concerned asks us to come in. We don't<br />
go in against the will of the government of South Viet Nain and vie<br />
haven't done so. I~ n the same way, the United States of America<br />
hasn't gone in against the will of the Government of South Viet<br />
Nain but is there by invitation. All this is an expression in<br />
action of the SEATO obligations.<br />
Now I find that there are some people who say, why<br />
should Australia be in South Viet Nam?" 1 It would be quite proper<br />
I think to answer that by saying, " Well, why is the United States<br />
in South Viet Nain?" Her obligations are no greater than ours.<br />
In one sense, her interests may be thought to be somewhat less<br />
immediate than ours, But I notice that those who query Australia's<br />
presence have not been so vocal in querying the presence of the<br />
United States. -ell, why is the United States there? Wvhy are we there?<br />
Obviously to resist armed aggression and subversion the very<br />
thing that SEATO is directed to and the very thing which is<br />
contemplated by the Charter of the United Nations that any<br />
country finding itself under attack is quite entihed to defend<br />
itself and equally entitled to ask its friends to come to its<br />
assistance. And therefore everything that has been done here is<br />
in complete accord not only with the South East Asian Treat' but<br />
also with the Charter of the United Nations.<br />
Now just let me pursue that a little further. Suppose<br />
the United States of America, now building up its forces in South<br />
Viet Nain so that they total, as at present, something of the<br />
order of 60,000 suppose the United States said, " All right, we<br />
will withdraw." This would give great pleasure to the pacifists.<br />
No great pleasure to us in Australia if we value our own state<br />
of security. Suppose they withdrew. Does anybody with his five wits<br />
doubt that before very long Chinese communism., acting through North<br />
Vietnamese communism, would sweep down through South Viet Namn,<br />
would put itself in an early position to control Thailand, to<br />
render the position of Malaya almost intolerable, putting Malaya<br />
between two fires and would therefore in the long run and not<br />
so very long run at that we would find ourselves with aggressive<br />
communism almost on our shores, just across the water.<br />
And it is because of these elementary considerations of<br />
national safety that the SEATO Council when it met and my<br />
colleague, Mr. Hasluck, was there on May 5th of this year<br />
reaffirmed ( I will quote their words) that " defeat of communist<br />
campaign is essential not only to the security of South Viet Nam<br />
but to that of South East Asia as a whole." That is what the<br />
* e ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
SEATO Council had to say and it is very well to keep it in mind.<br />
We are not pursuing some strange warmongering eccentric<br />
activity of ouz. c. urn, We are grown-up people. We have an imnlanse<br />
respcns ' ibility to zhis country and the best way of discharging that<br />
responsibility is to see that with our friends we stand across the<br />
path of aggressive communism.<br />
It is very interesting to notice that this is a view not<br />
peculiar to us. The Foreign Secretary in the present British<br />
Governzment, Mr. Michael Stewart, made a notable speech about this<br />
in the House of Commons at the beginning of April. I wonder if<br />
I might try your patience by quoting just two paragraphs from it.<br />
He observed that after the signing of the Geneva Agreement<br />
in 195W, both parts of Viet Nam both parts, North and South<br />
continued to endeavour to put themselves in order and to make<br />
economic and social progress, He continued and now I use his<br />
words " These possibilities remained open until in 1959<br />
there was a call by the Government of North Viet Nam for an<br />
intensification of the Viet Cong activities in the South and<br />
for full-scale guerrilla warfare against the Government of<br />
South Viet Nam. Not only did the Northern Government call<br />
for that; they then proceeded to help it with more weapons<br />
and military advice, as was made clear by the majority<br />
report of the International Control Commission in 1962.<br />
Faced with that situation, South Viet Nam appealed<br />
to the United States for help, and the United States responded,<br />
but it is important to notice that in 1959, when this pressure<br />
from the North began, and even as late as 1961l, two yeais later,<br />
there were still only 700 members of the United States armed<br />
forces in South Viet Nam. It cannot be claimed that the<br />
action taken by the North was the result of a considerable<br />
United States military presence in the South. The action from<br />
the North preceded the arrival of the United States forces<br />
in any considerable degree in the South."<br />
No9w , it won't be irrelevant for me to add to that that<br />
in 199 the economy of South Viet Nam was beginning to flourish<br />
and the country was developing, at that time, a considerable<br />
stability. I would like to point out also that it is widely<br />
agreed that the Viet Cong th,, s replaced its serious losses because<br />
itI-has hosd t'iam by recruitment from the Nort,% h. Up to thie end<br />
of 1964 thii--t is only the end of last year it was estimated<br />
that 40,000 infiltrators had come down from the North; in 1964<br />
alone, 10,000 came in.<br />
I reported to Parliament on April 29th that there had<br />
occurred the infiltration of a battalion of the North Vietnamese<br />
regular army. Wdell, I needn't go on. That's continuing.<br />
And if we have those facts in mind, here is something........<br />
I am not allowed to call it a war I gather, because somebody<br />
thinks that there is a war only il~ there is a declaration of war.<br />
Strange, remote, academic notion that is, in the modern world.<br />
All I know is that there is fighting going on and the people<br />
involved in it might very well be mistaken enough to think they<br />
w. re engaged in operations of war; as of course they are.<br />
The communists themselves from Hanoi and from Peking<br />
describe this, themselves, as a war of liberation. a 00 / 1 </p>
<p>But we are not allowed to call it a war, which is just<br />
too bad. Well, it is a war of liberation from their point of vievi.<br />
This is the grandiloquent name they give to a series of military<br />
operations which are obviously designed to overthrow the Government<br />
of South Viet Nam, to convert South Viet Nam into a communist<br />
state and to extend the boundaries of communist influence so many<br />
miles, so many iriles, hundreds of miles nearer to us.<br />
Well, I am not going to engage in word-spinning arguments<br />
about phrases that can be used. I think it is quite foolish at a<br />
time like this for people to think that they can solve this great<br />
problem by what I now believe is called an exercise in semantics,<br />
because the facts are not that way.<br />
There is a war going on, and United States forces are<br />
engaged in operations of war defensive war against an<br />
aggressor. And Australian forces are engaged in operations of<br />
war defensive war against aggression, side by side with the<br />
forces of South Viet Nam.<br />
Under those circumstances, our position is just as the<br />
position of the United States is that until the aggressor is<br />
really prepared to negotiate for an effective peace which will<br />
leave South Viet Nam in command of its own affairs, then the<br />
fighting will need to continue.<br />
We are all very conscious of the risks of this business.<br />
There are risks always in these matters. But the very notion that<br />
the contribution to peace is to abandon South Viet Nam and walk<br />
out on them is, I think so fantastic that 95 per cent, of the<br />
people of Australia would find it entirely unacceptable.<br />
Now, we had a look at this matter at the Commonwealth<br />
Conference. There are various views expressed in a Commonwealth<br />
Conference. There are now twenty-one of us I was almost going<br />
to say with twenty-one different views but at least, let us say,<br />
a wide diversity of opinion. And let's face up to it there are<br />
some of the new Commonwealth countries who are opposel to American<br />
action and therefore opposed to what we are doing who lean in the<br />
direction of China. I won't mention their names7 but it is quite<br />
clear that some of them do.<br />
And the Prime Minister of Great Britain said: " Well,<br />
don't let us thrash out our various views pro and con, because we<br />
wil. n~~ e There will be complete opposition between A<br />
and B and between C and D. Could we make an effort to break this<br />
jam by sending a mission from the Commonwealth to Hanoi, to Peking,<br />
to Moscow, to Washington to see whether there is some basis on<br />
which a conference, a peace conference, could be heldT That is<br />
all to discover whether there is some basis on which a conference<br />
may be held." And in the long run, with I think one dissentient, this<br />
was agreed to and the members of the mission were appointed,<br />
It was quite extraordinary to me that one representative<br />
objected to Mr, Wilson being the Chairman of the mission. Whby?<br />
Because Great Britain had and has publicly expressed her support<br />
of what the Americans are doing. Therefore we were told " You,<br />
Great Britain, are committed" but the very remark was maae by a<br />
gentleman who was equally committed by having made a joint<br />
communique with Chou En-Lai upholding China and denouncing<br />
America, and having been brought up in the old school, I still<br />
like words to mean the same kind of thing where they are used. 00 </p>
<p>Of course most people there are committed in the sense<br />
that they had views pro or con. One or two of us were committed<br />
because we had committed forces, but that didn't make our<br />
commitment any clearer. It made it more practical if you like,<br />
but it still remained true that we had taken our stand and we<br />
knew what side we were on, and the mission was appointed,<br />
Well, you know what has happened. It is just as well<br />
to remind some of these people in Australia there are very few<br />
of them of course who think that I stand in the way. I r all<br />
important stand in the way of any peaceful settlement. it is<br />
very interesting to remind them and perhaps to remind the public<br />
that there has been a score of attempts to produce some kind of<br />
settlement, settlement consistent with the freedom of South Viet<br />
Nam, Let us never lose sight of that.<br />
It has been before the United Nations. They sent their<br />
Secretary-General, or they said to him that he might consider<br />
visiting Peking and Hanoi and he got the dusty answer which<br />
everybody else has had ever since: United U~ ations intervention<br />
in the affairs of Indo-China can't be tolerated.<br />
This is the communist reply. " This firm stand of ours"<br />
they went on, " is unshakeable and admits of no exception." 1 Well<br />
then, the co-Chairman of the Geneva Conference tried something.<br />
The seventeen non-aligned nations passed resolutions and sent<br />
them forward and got the same rejection. President Johnson has,<br />
of course, done everything I think that a man could$ in all his<br />
statements, to encourage peace, but the only answer to him was<br />
that it was a swindle, ( These genteel words are used quite<br />
freely a swindle.) The British Government sent my old friend,<br />
Mr. Patrick Gordon Walker, around. He couldn't get through the<br />
door. " Nothing to do with you," they said, The President of<br />
India, he suffered a similar fate. The Americans, not long ago,<br />
tried a temporary suspension of bombing north of the line. This<br />
had no effect whatever. And in the case of the Commonwealth<br />
mission, well, as I don't need to tell you, the answer has been<br />
in the rudest possible terms " Nothing doing. V1e will not<br />
confer. We are the people," they say, " who will not under any<br />
circumstances arrive at any peaceful negotiation unless all-those<br />
people who are engaged in defending South Viet Nam get out.!.<br />
In other words, unless there is surrender, there will be<br />
no negotiation. Strange, strange, bedlamite sort of idea I. t is,<br />
but that is the one that they have put forward.<br />
I remember that at the conference the Prime Ministers'<br />
Conference one of the Prime Ministers, heavily influenced, by<br />
the Chinese, I regret to say objected to the mission because<br />
he said it would be putting China in the dock. I ventured to ask<br />
him why China, if China was a peace-loving country, should feel<br />
put in the dock by being asked to negotiate for peace, That<br />
was a littJe difficult that question, but he still persisted that<br />
this was putting China in the dock, and of course in that sense,<br />
he was right, because although this mission hasn'Z achievedw<br />
anything positive because it hasn't been received, it is perfectly<br />
true that it has made it clear to the world as to where the*'<br />
objection to peac~ e exists and who are the people who are responsible<br />
for carrying on this dreadful operation of war in Viet Nam.<br />
Now I don't know whether there is anything more that I<br />
need to say on that matter in genoral. I should tell you that<br />
the Department of External Affairs has put together a compendium,<br />
suitably indexed, containing the documents relating to Viet Nam<br />
9 a 6 </p>
<p>the first half of this year and I am told that there are<br />
sufficient copies available for each of you to take one away<br />
at the end of the conference. They contain verbatim extracts<br />
from all the statements and documents and reports that are relevant<br />
to this matter. well<br />
QUESTION Can you tell us, Sir, if there is any chance of the<br />
stalemate in Viet Nam ending in the foreseeable future?<br />
P. M. Well, it would take a wiser man than I am to answer that<br />
question, you realise, with any dogmatism, because I had the<br />
great advantage of quite long discussion on this matter with<br />
General Maxwell Taylor in New York and, of course, in London and<br />
elsewhere. The monsoon season is on in Viet Nam and they have a<br />
north-east monsoon and a north-west monsoon and the clouds come<br />
over and the rain comes down and this is ideal hunting time for<br />
guerrillas, Therefore it is to be expected that the Viet Cong<br />
would in this period have some success from time to time. And<br />
they have had some successes. They have also had some failures.<br />
The casualties each day are quite formidable,<br />
But there is a strong feeling of confidence that by the<br />
end of the monsoon season, the progress of the Viet Cong will have<br />
been somewhat disappointing from their point of view and that<br />
this might have its psychological effect on Hanoi.<br />
It is elementary horse sense, I suppose, that as long<br />
as the other fellow thinks he is winning, he is not going to talk<br />
settlement. Well, whether he will still be thinking he is winning<br />
at the end of the monsoon season in the next two or three months,<br />
I dontt know, but I saw no symptom whatever of any doubt, any<br />
weakening of resolution on the part of the United States,<br />
They are increasing the numbers of their forces, t hey<br />
are devoting a tremendous lot of energy to this matter because<br />
they know, as I think most sensible people would agree, that you<br />
dre not going to get a settlement on this matter while you are<br />
being on the face of it pushed around. You will get a<br />
settlement when the other man begins to think that there is~ no<br />
future in it, and therefore we have to make up our minds that we<br />
will go through a very difficult period.<br />
Things may be worse before they are better in fact<br />
I think the President said something to that effect in the last<br />
day or two. But this is no reason for any pessimism; this is<br />
one of the inevitable circumstances of an operation of war<br />
you will notice I didn't say " a war" an operation of war,<br />
conducted under these circumstances of weather and, of course,<br />
with all the advantage that guerrilla forces have of secrecy,<br />
choosing their own time to strike and of sheer terrorism against<br />
the civilian population.<br />
These are trcmendous advantages, but in the long run,<br />
they won't be good enough. You can put me down among the<br />
optimists on this matter,<br />
Q, Mr. Prime Minister, on the political side, some observers<br />
say that some kind of nationalist Viet Nam unified under a<br />
communist r6gime will be preferable to a South East Asia in<br />
flames. Could your Government contemplate a Titoist-type<br />
nationalist communist government at South Viet Nam ostensibly<br />
free of Chinese domination? </p>
<p>7-<br />
P. M. I would contemplate a communist regime in South<br />
Viet Nam with the utmost horror,<br />
Q. Do you think it can be avoided, Sir?<br />
P. M. I do. But only if we stand firm. Only if we refuse<br />
to allow our morale to be whittled away by a lot of<br />
philosophic doubters,<br />
Q0 Sir Robert, there have been reports from Viet Nam<br />
showing that the boots and clothing of members of the First<br />
Battalion have been literally falling apart. Does this<br />
suggest that our troops have been let down by bad planning<br />
and that they were sent to Viet Nam before the Army was ready<br />
to put them into the field properly equipped?<br />
P. m. I have no reason to suppose they weren't sent in a<br />
properly trained and equipped fashion. I read what you have<br />
referred to and no doubt the Minister for the Army, who is<br />
reported to have been there on the spot, will be back and<br />
taking an active interest in these matters,<br />
Q, Were you surprised, Sir, to read these reports?<br />
P. M. Oh I can't say one way or the other about that,<br />
Every time I find myself in the tropics under much more<br />
comfortable circumstances I wonder how your clothing lasts<br />
anyhow. But everything that can be done must be done, that's<br />
quite obvious. There can be no beg pardons or excuses on<br />
this matter. None.<br />
Q, Sir Robert, you referred to the United States<br />
increasing its forces in South Viet Nam. Was there any<br />
suggestion in your discussions with President Johnson that<br />
we might be asked to increase........<br />
P. M. No, none. None either there or anywhere else, I<br />
may tell you it is very well understood that we are in a<br />
rather special position. We have limited resouroes. We<br />
have our obligations that we are performing in Malaysia,<br />
We have forces in Viet Nain. We have our particular obligations<br />
in relation to Papua and New Guinea and, of course,<br />
our own defence. I found no lack of understanding. In<br />
fact, on the whole, there was great appreciation of the fact<br />
that we had rather stretched our resources to do what we did.<br />
Q. Sir, were you given any indication in Washington<br />
of how far the United States might go in terins of commitment<br />
of forces in South Viet Namn?<br />
P. M. Oh no. All I know is that they are increasing. But<br />
you mean to say did they tell me, " Well, we will build' them<br />
up to X thousand"?<br />
Q. Yes, Sir.<br />
P. M. Oh no. They are not so silly as that. That's a<br />
piece of information of interest only to the enemy. They<br />
are not in the habit of doing that.<br />
Q, Apart from commitment of troops to Viet Namn, did<br />
you get the impression that the US administration would<br />
welcome when we could afford to do it an expansion, a<br />
general expansion of our defence base? 3. / 8 </p>
<p>-8<br />
P. M. It was never raised. They are very familiar with the<br />
very sharp expansion that we are now engaging in. I found<br />
them very clearly understanding of that problem.<br />
Q. Sir Robert, have you been informed of the Philippines'<br />
decision which amounts virtually to not sending 2,000 troops<br />
to Viet Nam?<br />
P. M. Well I haven't been informed of this but at the moment<br />
I am not frIghtfully well informed. I have been in bed most<br />
of the time since I got back home.<br />
Q9 Sir Robert, do you think the Malaysian situation and<br />
the Viet Nam horror are part of the same problem?<br />
P. M. All these things, I think, fall into the same pattern.<br />
As I said earlier, if South Viet Nam went and the communlats<br />
came in, well, anybody can imagine the pressures that would<br />
arise, the internal subversions that would be promoted in<br />
Thailand and in Malaya proper, and that would mean that Malaya<br />
proper would find herself once more in the same sort of<br />
trouble as before with the guerrillas in the north and at the<br />
same time defending herself against confrontation on the<br />
Indonesian side. Therefore this is of tremendous importance<br />
to Malaysia and the position and defence of Malaysia,<br />
Q. Sir, if you think there is no doubt about Australia<br />
being at war in Viet Nam, how would you define the Australian<br />
position vis-a-vis Indonesia and Malaysian Borneo?<br />
P. M. In exactly the same way. There are operations of war<br />
going on along the frontier, You know, don't fall into the<br />
error that some of these gentlemen have fallen into of thinking<br />
that we are engaging in a lot of legal technicalities. We<br />
are not. I Make a great distinction. There are operations<br />
of war because fighting is going on and fighting is an<br />
operation of war. What is the use of arguing a lot of stuffwho<br />
has declared war on whom. Some even had the impertinence<br />
to suggest that this has been a frolic of my own. Everything<br />
that we've done has been done by the Government of this<br />
country and with the entire support of all the members of the<br />
political parties who stand behind the Government. I am not<br />
arguing about words, They don't interest me for this<br />
purpose.<br />
Q. Relating to that, Sir, do you think it would clarify<br />
the situation as far as other countries perhaps are concerned<br />
if war were to be declated?<br />
Pam. For us to declare war? For America to declare war?<br />
For North Viet Nam to declare war? It would be an interesting<br />
exercise but purely academic. They would go on fighting in<br />
the same way and in the same places.<br />
Q. Sir, you have often said that the real aggressive<br />
imperialists today are the major communist powers.<br />
P. M, That's right,<br />
Q. Do you think that while this remains true of China,<br />
that the Soviet Union may be moving away from a policy of<br />
aggr~ essive expansionp 0 00 </p>
<p>9-<br />
P. M. I like to think it is. Yes I rather like to think it<br />
is. I think there are material dilferences today between the<br />
Soviet Union approach and the communist Chinese approach,<br />
and I think that the events of the last few years have rather<br />
supported that idea, I think that it is reasonable to hope<br />
one can't be dogmatic but it is reasonable to hope that<br />
peaceful co-existence will become more and more real from the<br />
Soviet Union outwards but of course as I don't need to<br />
tell you, the communist Chinese have an entirely different<br />
view, They regard the Soviet Union as a lot of miserable<br />
revisionists. They are pure Marx-Engels-and-let-the-battlego-<br />
on,<br />
Q. Sir, a few months ago in this room you told us of a<br />
consultation you had in London aimed at getting some order of<br />
priority on strategic situations in our part of the world.<br />
Can you say whether you have made any advance in implementing.....<br />
P. M. I have had discussions on them but they are not of a<br />
kind that I could announce.<br />
Q. What you were saying earlier, Sir Robert, about the<br />
problems of being committed in several areas, do you mean to<br />
say we couldn't send any more troops to Viet Nam?<br />
P. M. I didn't say anything of the kind. I simply said that<br />
the question had not arisen.<br />
Q. Could we send more troops to Viet Nam?<br />
P. M. That's a purely hypothetical question, I am an old<br />
man, as I have been reminded in the last two or three days,<br />
much too old to sit down here and prophesy about the future,<br />
Q. Sir Robert, I will carry on that question. How far<br />
do we go in the situation of Viet Nam? America is a very<br />
very big country, we are a very small country.<br />
P. M. That's right,<br />
Q. We've got to follow the line, but where does the line<br />
draw? Where does it stop? How far do we go?<br />
P. M. Well, we start off by trying to win.<br />
Q* Granted. Where do we go from there?<br />
P. M. Well, let's win first.<br />
Q-Sir Robert, can you comment on a report that Mr, Wilson<br />
has asked for a British bomber base to be set up in Darwin?<br />
P. M. I can't comment on that at all.<br />
QO Did you have any conversation with Mr. Wilson on<br />
strategic bases in Australia in this regard?<br />
P. M. I had some discussions on defence, on common problems<br />
of defence in London but they were private.<br />
Q. In those talks, can you say, Sir, whether the Viet Nam<br />
and the Malaysian positions were regarded as a common problem<br />
in England? 000 00/ 1 0 </p>
<p>10<br />
P. M. I must say that I think that the British Gover'nment,<br />
and indeed I think all parties in Great Britain, are very<br />
conscious of the importance of South East Asia. I think that<br />
this occupies an increasing place in their minds andift their<br />
planning. I have no complaints about that at all,<br />
Q, Do you think the Americans appreciate this, Sir?<br />
P. M. Oh yes very much.<br />
Q. Sir, at Mascot airport on Sunday night you said that<br />
your conversations with the American Presideni coming and<br />
going were of immense value to Australia.<br />
Pam. gIell I hope so.<br />
Q. Can you enlarge on that at all or particularise?<br />
P. M. No, except on the old-fashioned view that our safety<br />
out here, our future the question as to whether we will<br />
have free Press conferences in twenty years' time largely<br />
depends upon how far the United States of America is prepared<br />
to continue to accept responsibility in this part of the<br />
world. I think this is of vast importance. That doesn't mean<br />
that we have to go and bow three times and s~ y " Yas, of<br />
course you're right" but it does mean tLat for us to be on<br />
terms which enable us to talk frankly and in a friendly way<br />
and in a receivable way is of tremendous importance.<br />
Q. This is not new, Sir.<br />
P. M. I know it isn't<br />
Q. You spoke as though it were something special,<br />
P. M. Oh no, I think it is getting better, that's all,<br />
Q. Sir Robert, judging from Press reports that we have<br />
heard from overseas, there seems to be an increasing confidence<br />
amongst the Commonwealth Prime Ministers in the situation in<br />
Malaysia. Could you elaborate on this?<br />
P. M. I think cm the whole the Malaysian section of the<br />
discussion worked out pretty well. You must get rid of the<br />
idea that we are now a monolithic structure in the Commonwealth.<br />
We are not. We exist to debate our disagreements,<br />
primarily, and therefore when one gets a decent amount of<br />
agreement on something that is a good day, and there was a<br />
splendid amount of agreement on Malaysia the right of Malaysia<br />
to defend itself and the right of Malaysia to enjoy our,<br />
support, not necessarily military support which we give: but<br />
support diplomatic, moral, whatever it may be. Yes, I<br />
thought that portion of the discussions came out very woll.<br />
Q. That's judging from the outcome of the previous<br />
conference?<br />
P. M. Yes that's right. I thought this, on the whole, was<br />
rather betier.<br />
Q. Sir Robert, is Australia using its offices to try and<br />
bring the fighting factions within Malaysia together Mr.<br />
Lee Kuan Yew and the Tunku 0 00 0/ 1 1 </p>
<p>11<br />
F~ M. Oh, look we have our diplomatic representatives i14<br />
Kuala Lumpur and in Singapore. They both have the closes<br />
access to the people concerned. I think these differences,<br />
you know, can easily be exaggerated myself. Anyhow it i6<br />
in our interests and in everybody else's interests to see:<br />
them disappear and that is our constant desire.<br />
Q. In your discussions in Britain, Sir, did you get<br />
any indication as to whether Australia as a traditional<br />
and dominant outlet for British capital investment has<br />
any special status under Mr. Wilson's programme to curb<br />
capital outflow?<br />
P. M. I didn't myself engage in discussions on their<br />
financial policy. We just had no time in the complex of<br />
other matters.<br />
Q. Sir, at the beginning you said, " Some gentlemen<br />
have communicated with me recently who seemed to think<br />
that I was the one who was involving Australia in war in<br />
South Viet Nam." Could you enlighten us on that, whether<br />
you have had a large mail bag on this subject?<br />
P. M. No. One letter signed by sixteen people, Kept<br />
me awake all night*<br />
Q9 This is since your correspondence with the bishops?<br />
P. M. Oh yes. But even that consisted of As I said,<br />
my epistle to the bishops made me feel quite like the New'<br />
Testament except that the A1postle didn't ever get a reply<br />
and I did.<br />
Q. You've been quoted here as saying in London at the<br />
last Conference that certain people seem to be under the<br />
influence of communist China? Could you elaborate on<br />
that?<br />
P. m. I think there are distinct symptoms in East Africa,<br />
in particular, of Chinese communist penetration.<br />
QO Does this mean that there is general concern within<br />
the Commonwealth?<br />
Pam* Oh, I wouldntt say it gave rise to general concern.<br />
My views on that problem are not necessarily those of a<br />
majority. I wouldn't know.<br />
Q. Are your views that this will hurt the Commonwealth?<br />
P. M. Assuming that all these countries remain within the<br />
Commonwealth, it would hurt the Commonwealth. Yes,<br />
Q. Do you see a future for the Commonwealth, Sir?<br />
P. M, Well I wish I knew. Look, the whole point about the<br />
Commonwealth is that now there are twenty-one. Twenty-one<br />
Prime Ministers arrive. That means that we meet in a room<br />
at Marlborough House and there are 100 people there. There<br />
is a new fashion that has arisen in the new Commonwealth<br />
andyou boys will be delighted to hear this to engage public<br />
relations officers so that the speech made in private is in<br />
the press before it is delivered sometimes. It's a public<br />
relations exercise very largely, and all this I think is very<br />
puzzling. .0*/ 12 </p>
<p>12<br />
P. M~ tThere are twenty-one Prime Ministers today what,<br />
in a year's time twenty-five; something like that, and<br />
everybody wants io make a speech, except me, and that moans<br />
that if they all have a go at everything, and there are<br />
set speeches made and duly published, the conference will<br />
last a month and nobody will be able to afford the time<br />
to attend it. There's a great problem here in these<br />
growing numbers as to how far we can devise somie<br />
machinery by which you shorten discussions or perhaps work<br />
from committees or groups. I don't know. Some of us gave<br />
a little thought to it in London but without any finality.<br />
There is no doubt about it. It has completely altered the<br />
character of the meeting because now it is a matter of<br />
expressing views, of seeking to get support for some<br />
pressure on somebody else. There is a growing disposition<br />
to want to interfere with or sit in judgment on the<br />
affairs of other individual countries. This is not the<br />
old Commonwealth.<br />
Q, Does this suggest, Sir, that your support of a<br />
Commonwealth Secretariat is waning?<br />
P. M. My support of a Commonwealth Secretariat hasn't<br />
waned. It has always been pretty clearly defined.<br />
That is to say that the Secretariat ought to act as a<br />
Secretariat. It ought to act as a means of facilitating<br />
the exchange of knowledge, of getting papers prepated<br />
so that when people meet they will know what the other<br />
man has in his mind and te prepared to discuss it<br />
intelligently. That's what a Secretariat is for.<br />
There are some who would like to see a Secretariat<br />
which in effect achieved executive action, which could work<br />
out economic plans and discuss the position of this<br />
country or that, what assistance it ought to have and<br />
from whom. And you know, when it gets to that, I think<br />
that will be the end of the penny section. In fact the<br />
penny section is rather a ludicrous reference because as<br />
a rule it is the million pounds section. It depends on<br />
how this works out. The Secretary-General appointed is<br />
well aware of this. I have great hopes that he will<br />
restrain it from too much empire-building, but if it<br />
became too formidable and too much disposed to go in on<br />
a variety of problems, like the Secretariat of the United<br />
Nations which has to I think that there would be great<br />
internal strains in the Commonwealth, considerable<br />
resistances which might not be favourable to its existence.<br />
Q. Sir Robert, do you think that the Secretariat could<br />
usurp the moral leadership role the British Government now<br />
exerts?<br />
P. M. Well if it tried to, that would be the end either<br />
of the Secretariat or of the Commonweaith, the new<br />
Commonwealth.<br />
Q. What steps are being taken to stop this, Sir? How<br />
far did it go in the conference?<br />
P. M. Oh, we had a discussion on this in the conference<br />
itself when we were settling the terms and conditions of<br />
the appointment. 99./ 1o3 </p>
<p>13<br />
Q9 Any time period for the Secretariat? A testing<br />
period, a trial period set for it?<br />
P. M. Well, the first appointment was made for five years<br />
for the Secretary-General. But we discussed this and I<br />
aired my views on the matter and Mr. Pearson of Canada took<br />
the same view and this was finally the received idea in the<br />
ccnfarence that it must have a modest beginning, it must<br />
not try to extend its jurisdiction in a hurry and that its<br />
usefulness will largely depend on how it conducts itself in<br />
the first year or two. But it is a highly experimental thing.<br />
Q. Sir, as a result of your talks with President Johnson,<br />
is there likely to be a greater Budget appropriation for<br />
defence this year than there might otherwise have been?<br />
P. M. Now! Harold.. ( To Mr. Holt) He tells me the book<br />
is closed.<br />
Q. Sir, did you return from London with the name of our<br />
next Governor-General?<br />
P. M. I have nothing to say about that yet. I haventt met<br />
my Cabinet.<br />
Q. Can we expect an imminent announcement, Sir?<br />
P. M. I don't know.<br />
Q. Sir, can you give us your views on the situation of<br />
the United Nations, the contribution towards the deficit<br />
that has been made by some nations about which I believe you<br />
said you reserved your own decision?<br />
P. M. Yes, well the deficit in the United Nations of course<br />
arises from the fact that some of the countries like the<br />
Soviet Union and France and so on, have declinel to pay for<br />
these peace-keeping operations. It went to the Permament<br />
Court. It was decided that they were liable to pay and. there<br />
the question arose as to whether Article 19 ought to be'<br />
enforced. No pay no vote. Good simple rule to which I<br />
subscribed heartily.<br />
Well, in the meantime, they are not paying and the<br />
Assembly has been held up because they don't want to become<br />
involved in this imbroglio. Thle British Government announced<br />
that it would find ten million dollars as a voluntary.<br />
contribution, and Canada offered a voluntary contribution.<br />
I said that we had never been backward in the past in making<br />
voluntary contributions but I did want to discuss with my<br />
colleagues one matter, If the people who are not in<br />
default make up the lag for those who are this year, is<br />
this going to be the rule next year? Does this mean that<br />
you abandon the enforcement of Article 19? Will it be<br />
conducive to getting them to pay up under Article 19 if<br />
they find that other people will pay instead? And I would<br />
like to think about that with my colleagues, not in any<br />
miserable piking spirit because we dontt want to see the<br />
United Nations go broke, but we do want to have some clarity<br />
in our minds as to what it is we are doing. That's all.<br />
QO Do you think the United Nations can survive? of0 0 0 ./ 11+ </p>
<p>P. M, You know, you are developing a fascinating interest<br />
in survival. This is the second question of that kind<br />
you have put to me. I am largely devoted at present to<br />
my own problem of survival.<br />
Q. Talking of that Sir, there are a lot of rumours<br />
around that you are thinking of going out at the end of<br />
this year. Would you comment on that at all?<br />
P. M. Well, any self-respecting man of my age must give<br />
thought to his fuiture and to his duties and I am doing that.<br />
I dontt know what the result will be, but no doubt following<br />
my traditional practice, when I have arrived at a conclusion,<br />
Ifll say it.<br />
Q. Do you think you will arrive at that conclusion<br />
within the next few months, Sir?<br />
P. M. I haver.~ t a clue. Haven't a clue. I thought I<br />
might run a little Gallup poll around here. There was a<br />
Gallup poll wasn't there? I was fascinated to find that<br />
per cent, of my opponents wanted me to retire. The<br />
nicest compliment they've ever paid me.<br />
Well any more, boys, any more?<br />
Q. One question, Sir, if I may. Joan Sutherland. Do<br />
you intend to see her during this<br />
P. M. 1 Oh, look, I don't know. I' love to of course. I<br />
got back two days late to see her opening in Melbourne which<br />
I had been invited to attend. Oh no, I am a Joan Sutherland<br />
fan, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
