<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10854</transcript-id>
    <title>STOLEN CHILDREN&amp;#146;S SUPPORT FUND</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/05/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that public donations to the Stolen Children's</p>
<p> Support Fund are to be made tax-deductible.</p>
<p>The Government will amend the income tax law to allow deductions for</p>
<p> gifts of $2 or more to assist in the counselling, educating and monitoring</p>
<p> of Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders who were removed from their</p>
<p> families.</p>
<p>The Fund's objectives also include the wellbeing of descendants</p>
<p> of children separated from their parents, with particular emphasis</p>
<p> on the recommendations from the National Inquiry into the Separation</p>
<p> of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Children from their Families:</p>
<p> Bringing Them Home report.</p>
<p>After the Fund has satisfied the usual public fund requirements, a</p>
<p> date will be nominated from which gifts will be tax deductible. Legislation</p>
<p> will be introduced as soon as practicable after that time.</p>
<p>The Government has already responded to the Bringing Them Home report</p>
<p> by allocating approximately $63 million on initiatives over four years.</p>
<p> These initiatives are targeted at the Report's major recommendations</p>
<p> to assist in family union. Today's announcement adds another</p>
<p> dimension to that response.</p>
<p>My Government is committed to improving living conditions for indigenous</p>
<p> Australians. We will spend almost $700 million more in real terms</p>
<p> on indigenous-specific programmes during our first four years in office</p>
<p> than was spent in the last four years of the previous Labor Government.</p>
<p>Commonwealth funding for indigenous-specific programmes will increase</p>
<p> from $1.7 billion in 1995-96 to almost $1.9 billion in 1998-99, representing</p>
<p> a real growth of 2.4 per cent.</p>
<p>This funding will be directed towards the Government's priority</p>
<p> areas of health, housing, education and employment to address the</p>
<p> severe socio-economic disadvantage suffered by indigenous Australians.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
