<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18821</transcript-id>
    <title>Online Giants, Entrepreneurs and Innovators to Attend the Prime Minister&#039;s Forum on the Digital Economy</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/10/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Online giants Google, Facebook, PayPal and Microsoft will join leading Australian businesses such as Commonwealth Bank, Australia Post and Virgin Australia at the Prime Minister's Forum on the Digital Economy to be held in Sydney tomorrow.</p>
<p>The Gillard Government has today released the full list of more than 40 attendees for the one-day Forum.</p>
<p>In addition to these major companies, several online start-up businesses including Shoes of Prey, Nicko's Kitchen, and Birdsnest, will attend the Forum to share their success stories.</p>
<p>Attendees from a diverse range of sectors will discuss Australia's role in the growing digital economy, and the significant opportunities this presents for Australian businesses. The rollout of the National Broadband Network will help businesses to capitalise on these opportunities.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister will open the Forum, with sessions to address these key issues:</p>
<p>• The success of innovative digital organisations;• the opportunities and challenges of a digitally enabled world; and• thinking about work in the digitally engaged world.</p>
<p>The Forum will also look at ways to improve Australia's competitiveness and productivity, building on the Government's National Digital Economy Strategy and Productivity Agenda.</p>
<p>The National Digital Economy Strategy has set a goal for Australia to become a leading global digital economy by 2020.</p>
<p>The forum will be held at the University of New South Wales and will be available through live webcast at <a href="http://www.pm.gov.au/digitalforum">http://www.pm.gov.au/digitalforum</a>.</p>
<p>If members of the public want to contribute suggested questions for the Forum on Twitter, they should use the hashtag #pmdigital.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
