<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3230</transcript-id>
    <title>OPPOSITION POLICY SPEECH - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/04/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003230.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER Press Statement 244<br />
April 1974<br />
OPPOSITION POLICY SPEECH -STATEMENT BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Mr. Snedden's policy speech is a document of gross<br />
political irresponsibility a document of desperation and<br />
deception. He produces a host of vague, uncosted, contradictory<br />
promises. They are wildly inflationary promises.<br />
He refuses to provide any estimate of the cost of his<br />
promises. The Australian people are entitled to this information.<br />
He refuses to say clearly and unequivocally what areas<br />
of government spending he would cut in order to reduce inflation.<br />
The Australian people are entitled to this information.<br />
Behind Mr. Snedden's vague and ominous talk of hard<br />
decisions lies a threat to every initiative my Government has<br />
undertaken in education, welfare, transport, the cities.<br />
Mr. Snedden's only definite proposal for curbing inflation<br />
is to call a meeting. Even then he refuses to tell us what he<br />
would propose at such a meeting. He does not say because he does<br />
not know. He deliberately deceives the people when he says the<br />
Labor Government has raised taxes. We have not raised taxes.<br />
The fact is that the average wage earner in 1973 was better off<br />
after taxes than in 1972.<br />
For all Mr. Snedden's scare talk and hysteria, Australians<br />
know that they have never been more prosperous. They have full<br />
employment and high wages. The economy is buoyant. The dollar is<br />
one of the world's strongest currencies. Our trade is booming.<br />
Company profits are at record levels. The latest price figures<br />
show that our policies to control inflation the world-wide problem<br />
of inflation are working. It would be tradgic if the good progress<br />
we have made were to be undone by Mr. Snedden' s reckless and<br />
irresponsible bid for power.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
