<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8256</transcript-id>
    <title>PARLIAMENTARY SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY REFORM 21 FEBRUARY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008256.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAN ELIER EMBARGOED UNTIL DE~ LIVERY<br />
PARLIAMENTARY SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY REFORM<br />
21 FEBRUARY 1991<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
Parliament stands at the centre of our nation's public<br />
affairs. Reform of Parliament is reform of the central<br />
institution of Australian public life. This motion<br />
therefore is of the highest importance, seeking as it does<br />
to help ensure the continuing relevance and efficiency of<br />
this institution and its members. It is a particularly<br />
significant motion given that it comes so soon after the<br />
introduction of the televising of the proceedings of this<br />
House. Let me say al: the outset that I fully endorse the words of<br />
Alan Browning in Houqp of Renresentativpq Practice-: " It is<br />
important that the people know and understand, at least in<br />
broad terms, what the Parliament is, and what it does, how<br />
it works, what happens there and what is said there".<br />
( p 734)<br />
The business of Parliament is indeed best conducted in the<br />
full light of public scrutiny.<br />
Our decision to televise the proceedings of the House of<br />
Representatives has brought Parliament closer to the<br />
Australian people and has made them more fully aware of the<br />
scope and significance of the activities that take place<br />
here. In historical and in contemporary terms, it is highly<br />
appropriate that it should be a Labor Government that<br />
introduced the televising of Parliamentary procedures. It<br />
was, after aLl, a Labor Government that introduced the<br />
broadcasting of Parliamentary proceedings by radio in 1946.<br />
And it has been a recurring theme of this Government that<br />
public access to Parliament should be facilitated and<br />
encouraged wherever possible. </p>
<p>It was this Government that established the Parliamentary<br />
Education Office in 1988 to prepare information about<br />
Parliament for dissemination to schools throughout<br />
Australia. More than 100,000 Australian school students<br />
visit Parliament House each year, and many of them take part<br />
in learning programs in the Parliamentary Education Centre<br />
in this building. In the same vein, it was this Government<br />
that established the Citizenship Visits Program to assist<br />
children from remote schools visit Parliament.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
A complementary theme of the Government's reforms to<br />
Parliament has been our concern that the procedures of this<br />
House be clear, rational and efficient, so as to allow<br />
Members of Parliament to fulfil their responsibilities to<br />
those whom they represent.<br />
This Government has accordingly introduced significant<br />
procedural reforms to enhance the quality of Members'<br />
parliamentary role.<br />
We introduced the Thursday morning debates on private<br />
members' business a popular and successful innovation that<br />
has brought a very considerable range of issues to<br />
Parliament's attention. We revolutionised the sitting hours<br />
of this Chamber to make them more rational and more humane;<br />
they now allow a much better balance to be struck between<br />
members' parliamentary and electorate responsibilities.<br />
I now wish to inform the House that the Government proposes<br />
to introduce another reform to the procedures of this House<br />
that will further widen the scope of Members' parliamentary<br />
role. Following consultation with the Opposition Leader and<br />
the Manager of Opposition Business, and subsequently with<br />
you, Mr Speaker, the Government now proposes, with this<br />
motion, to amend standing orders to allow an Advisory Debate<br />
to be held once or twice each. Parliamentary session.<br />
The purpose of an Advisory Debate will be to allow Members<br />
of the House of Representatives the opportunity to offer<br />
their advice to the Government on significant matters of<br />
public interest before the Government.<br />
I want to see constructive and wide-ranging debates, not<br />
restricted to particular pieces of legislation as is the<br />
case with many debates in this House, nor overshadowed by a<br />
partisan, adversarial atmosphere. The topics of Advisory<br />
Debates will be determined by the Government, since it is<br />
the Government that is seeking Parliament's advice. It is<br />
proposed that the relevant Minister or Ministers will be<br />
present during the debate but that Ministers will not<br />
contribute to the debate except for a brief summation, as<br />
the final speaker. This is to allow Government backbenchers<br />
and the Opposition the maximum opportunity to make their<br />
views known. </p>
<p>It is proposed that an Advisory Debate be held on a<br />
Wednesday; that it commence at 10 am; and that it run up to,<br />
if necessary, but not beyond, the 2 pm commencement of<br />
Question Time. Each speaker should be restricted to<br />
minutes to allow the maximum number of participants in the<br />
debate. The Government is genuine in its desire that the views of<br />
ParliamentariLans on significant issues be made known to it.<br />
I propose that the first Advisory Debate be held on<br />
Wednesday 6 March on the topic of Ecologically Sustainable<br />
Development. I envisage that debate will cover but of course need not<br />
be restricted to topics such as the Ecologically<br />
Sustainable Development working groups that are currently<br />
conducting their inquiries and the role of the Resource<br />
Assessment Commission and its inquiries. I trust Honourable<br />
Members will support this initiative and participate<br />
actively in -the first and subsequent Advisory Debates.<br />
Mr Speaker<br />
Last year the Government raised two other issues of<br />
Parliamentary reform with the Opposition.<br />
The first, dealing with possible changes to Question Time,<br />
failed to eliLcit either support or an alternative proposal<br />
from the Opposition. Consequently, this matter will lapse.<br />
The second, dealing with the possible introduction of<br />
electronic voting, does have the in principle support of<br />
both sides of the House. It may be that the Procedures<br />
Committee will wish to consider which of the range of<br />
options would be most suitable. However, I am advised by<br />
you, Mr Speaker, that a system of electronic voting would<br />
cost between $ 1 million and $ 2 million to install and<br />
perhaps another $ 0.5 million a year to operate. In view of<br />
the likely cost, I do not believe that Parliament should<br />
start down this track at the present time. It is certainly<br />
not a matter to which the Government attaches any immediate<br />
priority. Mr Speaker<br />
The Government will remain open to any further proposals<br />
that may be put that genuinely and constructively seek to<br />
facilitate Members' parliamentary performance. This<br />
proposal for Advisory Debates, coming as it does in the wake<br />
of the decision to televise Parliament, shows our concern to<br />
ensure Parliament remains relevant and accessible to our<br />
masters, the people of Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
