<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9130</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, M.P. COUNCIL OF AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENTS MEETING - HOBART THURSDAY 24 FEBRUARY, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009130.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL5 4 No2 .. 90F04b 1 P. 02/ 04<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF iNTERVI EW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J<br />
KEATING, M. P.<br />
COUNCIL OF AUSTRALTAN GOVERNMENTS MEETING -HOBART<br />
THURSDAY 24 FEBRUARY, 1994<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you think that tomorrow can achieve anything, the<br />
Premiers seem particularly befl. igercnt?<br />
PM; Well, I think that we've had quite a breakthrough in establishing the<br />
Council of Australian G; overrnents ( COAG). It's a departure, a new one, from<br />
the financial arrangements of 60 years longstanding of the Premiers' Conference,<br />
so that we can discuss nion-financial things and we've had quite a lot of success to<br />
date. in just a short time we've established a national authority for vocational<br />
education. We're now working on the national trunk rail system, electricity<br />
power ge~ neration and distribution and now on the agenda for this conference<br />
is the question of competition policy across the country but including, of course,<br />
the state government business enterprise area. So, much has been achieved in a<br />
relatively short time and I think separation of the financial meeting and a<br />
general policy meeting has been a good thing. This is a general policy meeting<br />
and think it has all of the opporturnities that the last meeting has had to push<br />
this agenda-a little further.<br />
J: Well, Sir, what's your response to Mr Court's claimi that you're the worst<br />
thing that's ever happened to federation?<br />
PM: Well, I think the other Premiers don't agree because they've signed<br />
up to a national rail freight corporation, they've signed up to a national training<br />
authority, to power generation. I'm afraid Mr Court is the odd person out in this<br />
view of the role between the Commonwealth and the states. And, simply, the<br />
worst of parochial instincts won't help the people of Western Australia and<br />
that's why other premiers, generally, won't have a bar of that kind of policy.<br />
If the states want compensation for implementing the Hiliner Report are<br />
you prepared to negotiate on that?<br />
TEL 25 Fe b 94 </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Feb. 94 : 3: 54 No. 001 P. 03/ 04<br />
-2.<br />
PM: Well, it Would depend on whether it was compensation of the vAriety<br />
which particularly affected the Commonwealth advantageously. But, if decoding<br />
that message means that the Commonwealth pays for all reform the answer, of<br />
course, is no.<br />
J; What is the Commnonwealth prepared to pay to see the policy<br />
implemented? PM: WelL understand this... ynu've got to just get this right. Here we have<br />
some conservative governments and one which boasts of its conservativeness<br />
Western Austraia and you've got a Labor government, repeat, Labor<br />
govermrent asking them to open themselves up and be competitive in a free<br />
market economy. Now, these are the conservative, so-called market people. Yet,<br />
you've got the irony of a Labor government saying, please be competitive in an<br />
open economy. And they're sayin&amp; oh well, not sure about, not sure about that.<br />
1: Prime Mirnister, NU Court's view is that the West Australian Government<br />
has already implemented many of these sorts of competitive reforms.<br />
PM; Well, if you believe that you'll believe in fairies at the bottomn of the<br />
garden, won't you? Uf he can handle you that easily you're going to be a<br />
pushover. J: If the states, tomorrow, won't agree to any of these competitive changes is<br />
there much point in continuing with these meetings?<br />
PM: Well, that's what we said at the first meeting of COAG and we got the<br />
electricity agenda together and we got the National Training Authority together...<br />
I wouldn't be too gloomy about it if I were you.<br />
s it a-bargaining poit, is it?<br />
PM: Well, I think there's a lot of understiinding for the need to that in some<br />
of the important areas of electricity, water, gas, ports, wharves these are<br />
peculiar things now that the states must be involved that the<br />
Commonwealth can't do these things by itself.<br />
J. inaudible... you've got to have changes to the tax sharing arrangements<br />
or guaranteed. share of incouw tax?<br />
PM: That's a view. That's only a view.<br />
J: Mr Court's eager to talk about the whole future of the makeup of the<br />
Federation, do you think it will get that involved tomorrow?<br />
P-M: What do you mean, are we going to get a history lesson? </p>
<p>TEL: 25. Feb. 94 : 3: 54 No. 001l P. 04/ 04<br />
-3.<br />
J: He's keen to talk~ about the whole future where the Federation is<br />
heading, whether more power should be returned to the states.<br />
PM: It will these have always got their element of bargaining about them<br />
but, in the end, it's pretty hard for conservative premiers who are believing in<br />
market forces to say, " Oh no, we believe in market forces but we don't really.<br />
And here's this Commonwealth Labor Sovernment comning along asking us to<br />
adopt some market forces. Now, we'll only do it if you pay for it."<br />
J: Prime Minister, who won the day in Parliament today?<br />
PM: I thought D~ r I-ewson had all the leadership eggs in his basket and dropped<br />
them all at once. It was a dreadful speech which he took on as a tactic himself, I<br />
think, against the advice of some of his front bench advisers and whe~ n they<br />
realised that he had perform~ ed so poorly they decided to blow the Parliament up<br />
so that the news story was ' uproar in Parliament' instead of ' John Hewson<br />
collapsing' in what ought to have been a relatively easy few debating points for<br />
himn. Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
