<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7767</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SCIENCE COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/10/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007767.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER<br />FOR MEDIA 6 OCTOBER 1989</p>
<p>I am pleased to announce that the first meeting of the Prime Minister's Science Council is being held today.</p>
<p>The membership of the Council is included in your press kits.</p>
<p><strong>Today's Discussions</strong><br />Two topics of considerable importance both to the Government<br />and to the nation are being discussed at today's meeting.<br />They are global climatic change and the issues it raises for<br />Australia, and resources for science and technology and<br />their utilisation.</p>
<p>Also included in your press kits is a paper describing<br />recent developments in government policies for science and<br />technology and significant actions taken since the may<br />statement ' Science and Technology for Australia'.<br />Global Climatic Change Issues for Australia<br />This morning the Council is discussing the scientific<br />evidence for the greenhouse effect and considering the<br />effects of possible changes.<br />Papers to be presented to the Council describe the processes<br />at work in the atmosphere and the ways in which human<br />activity is changing them. Some important points are made in<br />the papers and will be covered in discussion. Although there<br />are considerable uncertainties, the balance of scientific<br />opinion is that climatic warming is very likely in the next<br />few decades. There may be increased climatic variability,<br />which would have important implications for agricultural<br />production. The combination of changes in Australia and<br />elsewhere will present us with a mixture of hazards and<br />opportunities. Since change seems likely, even though we cannot yet predict<br />what form it will take, it is prudent to prepare for its<br />consequences. There is a need to take account of possible<br />rises in sea level in planning the future use of our coasts<br />and littoral regions. As a nation, we make such extensive<br />use of these regions that even small rises in sea level<br />would have important social and economic effects.</p>
<p>Even though we cannot yet predict with certainty the effects<br />of the increase in greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, we do<br />know that climatic change is likely to be disruptive and<br />costly, socially, economically and environmentally. We<br />should, therefore, do all we reasonably can to minimise that<br />change. This means reducing greenhouse gas emissions, a task which<br />will not be easy for any nation.<br />The Government has already done much to prepare its response<br />to the issues to be discussed this morning. Our present<br />position on many of these matters is set out in my statement<br />on the environment ' Our Country, Our Future', which I<br />delivered on 20 July this year.<br />Australia is taking a leading role in international<br />activities. We are participating in the Intergovernmental<br />Panel on Climate Change ( IPCC). We have signed the Hague<br />Declaration on Protection of the Atmosphere. We have<br />introduced measures which more than meet the requirements of<br />the Montreal Protocol on Substances that Deplete the Ozone<br />Layer. We expect significant developments as a result of activities<br />planned for the next few years, including the report of the<br />IPCC at the Second World Climate Conference in 1990 and the<br />United Nations Conference on Environment and Development in<br />1992, which we hope will consider an international<br />convention on climate change.<br />The Government is providing additional funds for greenhouse<br />research in Australia. In addition to activities being<br />conducted as part of ongoing research programs, we have<br />provided $ 5.54 million over two years to complement existing<br />work. Much of this will be spent in CSIRO and the Bureau of<br />Meteorology. The Government has also established a National Greenhouse<br />Advisory Committee to advise on priority areas of research<br />and set objectives for a dedicated research groups scheme<br />which will commence next year. with regard to the important<br />matter of reducing emissions of greenhouse gases I have<br />established a task force to advise the government on the<br />options available to it. Following receipt and evaluation of<br />that advice the Government intends to convene a meeting of<br />relevant interests to discuss options for limiting<br />greenhouse gas emissions.<br />Resources for Science and Technology and their Utilisation<br />There are two messages which emerge strongly from the papers<br />to be discussed this afternoon. We need to make the science<br />and technology infrastructure, comprising research workers,<br />their laboratories and equipment, as strong as possible and<br />we need to link the research activities in our higher<br />education institutions and government laboratories more<br />closely to national needs, and to relevant industry sectors.</p>
<p>The Government can look with some satisfaction at what it<br />has already achieved, while recognising that reform and<br />rebuilding will take time and will require further<br />substantial effort.<br />In the May statement ' Science and Technology for Australia'<br />Minister Jones and I stated the government's commitment to<br />providing an environment which will encourage successful<br />research. It recognised that such research depends on highly<br />motivated and thoughtfully directed effort.<br />In the May statement, we announced additional support for<br />science and technology, amounting to $ 390 million over five<br />years. The measures announced in the May statement are<br />already producing results, as the paper I referred to<br />earlier makes clear.<br />I should like to mention one aspect of progress towards the<br />goals the Government has set for improving Australia's<br />science and technology capacity. This concerns the provision<br />of career structures for research staff in higher education.<br />The Australian Research Council will introduce an integrated<br />package of reforms and innovation to its existing<br />fellowships schemes. It will provide a new system of<br />fellowships that will significantly increase opportunities<br />for career progression of outstanding young researchers.<br />The existing postdoctoral research awards and Queen<br />Elizabeth II fellowships will be supplemented by two new<br />fellowship categories, Research Fellow and Senior Research<br />Fellow. The fellowship system, which currently comprises 128<br />postdoctoral and 28 Queen Elizabeth II fellows, is expected<br />to produce approximately 350 fellowships at its peak in<br />1995.<br />All fellowships in each category will need to be won in open<br />competition. The Postdoctoral Fellowships and the<br />Fellowships can be held only once in each category, while<br />Senior Fellows will be able to compete for further<br />Fellowships at the expiration of their terms.<br />The Minister, Mr Dawkins, has released a detailed statement,<br />which is included in your press kits.<br />The Council will also discuss the commercialisation of<br />Australian research. The authors of the invited papers have<br />noted that our performance in this area has been inadequate.<br />The Government will continue its efforts to improve this<br />situation, but an effective solution will require continued<br />and sustained action by all parts of the community.</p>
<p>I believe that we are moving in the right direction. The<br />restructuring of the Australian economy, which has been a<br />cornerstone of my Government's policies, offers tremendous<br />opportunities to those companies able and willing to take up<br />the challenge of developing and applying new technology to<br />their products and processes.<br />The overall message which emerges from these papers is that<br />science and technology will be even more important in<br />Australia's future than in the past. International<br />competitiveness in all industry sectors will be increasingly<br />dependent on technological innovation and on highly<br />developed skills in management and at all levels in the<br />workforce, of which the science and technology community is<br />a key element. Background to the formation of the Council<br />The formation of the Council was announced in May 1989 in<br />the joint statement ' Science and Technology for Australia',<br />issued by the Minister Assisting for Science and Technology,<br />Mr Jones, and myself.<br />That statement was prepared following reviews of several<br />areas of science and technology policy, including research<br />in higher education and the research responsibilities of the<br />Minister for Primary Industries and Energy, as well as<br />general reviews of Australian science and technology by<br />ASTEC and by a group of officials.<br />The reviews identified a number of issues of general<br />concern, including the adequacy of mechanisms to coordinate<br />and consult on science and technology policy.<br />The Council will be a forum for exchanging views and<br />discussing topics of national interest. It will also be a<br />body which can recommend action by the Government.<br />The Government is strongly represented in the membership of<br />the Council by Ministers with primary responsibility for<br />scientific and technological matters. The Council also<br />contains strong representation from the business community<br />and the science and technology community.<br />The Council will also have links with the Coordination<br />Committee on Science and Technology. This committee, which<br />is chaired by the Chief Scientist, Professor Slatyer, was<br />another part of the measures Minister Jones and I announced<br />in May.<br />Meetings of the Council will be held at least twice a year.<br />The next meeting will be held in about six months and there<br />will be another meeting at about this time next year.</p>
<p>In addition to the core membership of the Council, other<br />people with a particular interest in, or ability to<br />contribute to, the issues under consideration will be<br />invited to attend particular meetings.<br />These people will be drawn from all areas of the community,<br />but will come particularly from those engaged in research<br />and the management of research, and in the application of<br />science and technology to economic and social objectives.<br />Some of these people will be invited to prepare and present<br />papers to the Council. In this way, the Council will be able<br />to draw upon a wide range of resources and benefit from the<br />best expertise available in Australia.<br />The papers will be published after the meetings as a<br />permanent record of proceedings and as useful source of<br />reference material on the issues discussed.<br />Further information: Professor Ralph Slatyer 71 5217 ( w)<br />1728 ( h)</p>
<p>6.<br /><strong>MEMBERSHIP OF THE PRIME MINISTER'S SCIENCE COUNCIL</strong><br />The Prime Minister ( Chair)<br />The Hon Barry Jones, MP  - Minister Assisting for Science and Technology ( Deputy Chair)<br />The Hon Neal Blewett, MP - Minister for Community Services and Health<br />Senator the Hon John Button, - Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce<br />The Hon John Dawkins, MP - Minister for Employment, Education and Training<br />The Hon John Kerin, MP - Minister for Primary Industries and Energy<br />Dr Keith Boardman, FAA, FRS, Chief Executive of CSIRO<br />Professor Ray Martin, AO, FAA - Chairman of the Australian Science and Technology Council<br />A representative of the Australian Council of Trade Unions<br />Professor Brian Anderson, FAA, FRS - Head of the Department of Systems Engineering in the Research School of Physical Sciences at the Australian National University<br />Sir Gustav Nossal, AC FAA, FRS - Director of the Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research</p>
<p>Professor Cheryl Praeger, Professor of Pure Mathematics at the University of Western Australia<br />Sir Peter Abeles, Managing Director of TNT<br />Mr Roger Allen, Managing Director of Computer Power<br />Mr Trevor Eastwood, Managing Director of Wesfarmers<br />Mr John Ralph, AO - Managing Director and Chief Executive of CRA<br />Dr John Stocker, Managing Director of AMRAD<br />Professor Ralph Slatyer, AO, FAA, FRS <br />Chief Scientist ( Executive Officer)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
