<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12242</transcript-id>
    <title>Commonwealth Gives $20 Million for Cancer Research in Queensland </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am delighted to announce that the Government will provide a grant of $20 million to the Queensland Institute of Medical Research (QIMR) and the Leukaemia Foundation for the Comprehensive Cancer Research Centre.</p>
<p>The establishment of this new centre represents a major advance in cancer research and treatment in Queensland and the Asia?Pacific region, with joint funding by the Commonwealth, the Queensland and an overseas philanthropist.</p>
<p>The new centre includes specially designed laboratories, clinical trial suites, patient facilities and storage capacity to enable the placement of a full multidisciplinary scientific and clinical team in one research facility. These facilities will enable high technology biomedical research to be conducted alongside clinical trials of new cell?based therapies.</p>
<p>The design of the new centre is crucially important, as a major limitation for the conduct of cell?based therapies on a larger scale is the availability of custom?designed facilities in which these therapies can be prepared in compliance with TGA regulations. The centre will have a floor specifically designated for the production of cell?based therapies in a secure, contained and clean environment.</p>
<p>The combined expertise of groups within the QIMR and active collaborations with the surrounding hospitals and universities will create a centre of excellence in the Asia?Pacific region in the delivery of cell?based therapies.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth assistance will also contribute to the generation of employment in the construction phase and to longer-term employment in the research sector.</p>
<p>3 April 2001</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
