<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11414</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 TRIBUTE ADDRESS TO SIR JOHN GORTON AT                 LIBERAL PARTY FEDERAL COUNCIL GALA DINNER                 HYATT HOTEL, CANBERRA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Tony Staley, Sir John and Lady Gorton, Shane Stone, the Federal President</p>
<p> elect, Richard Court and John Olsen, the Premiers of Western Australia</p>
<p> and South Australia, Kate Carnell, the Chief Minister of the Australian</p>
<p> Capital Territory, Peter Costello, Deputy Federal Parliamentary Leader,</p>
<p> other colleagues and friends, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>The present member for Higgins and Federal Treasurer has a very good</p>
<p> line in Parliament when he rightly talks about the success that this</p>
<p> Government has had in reducing interest rates. He says that interest</p>
<p> rates haven't been as low in Australia since man first walked</p>
<p> on the moon. Now, of course, when man first walked on the moon the</p>
<p> former member for Higgins, John Grey Gorton, was Prime Minister of</p>
<p> Australia.</p>
<p>And tonight we gather to honour the contribution of John Grey Gorton</p>
<p> to the serve first and foremost of his country. And we saw in that</p>
<p> marvelous little video the great sacrifice and gallantry that he demonstrated.</p>
<p> And we were reminded that this place, a generation ago, was overwhelmingly</p>
<p> filled with men who had gone through that experience on both sides.</p>
<p> Now, of course, a generation or more on, naturally things are different.</p>
<p> But on an occasion like this we reflect on a man who connects us with</p>
<p> those gallant years. We reflect on a man who connects us with a time</p>
<p> that was convulsed by the controversy of the Vietnam War, a time which</p>
<p> in economic terms we are now reminded of because of the great strength</p>
<p> of the Australian economy. I won't dwell on that tonight, that</p>
<p> will come tomorrow. But also a time that connects us with the history</p>
<p> and the heritage of our Party.</p>
<p>And John Gorton was elected to Federal Parliament almost 50 years</p>
<p> ago. When he was Prime Minister of Australia - I reminded myself of</p>
<p> this the other day  I think he was re-elected in 1969 and that</p>
<p> was a year in which Richmond won the VFL flag, Balmain won the JJ</p>
<p> Gilterton Shield that was then the symbol of rugby league supremacy</p>
<p> in Sydney and, of course, Ian Chappell had just become Captain of</p>
<p> the Australian Cricket Team. But it is a wonderful experience, I think,</p>
<p> for a Party and particularly for the younger members of our Party</p>
<p> to be reminded of the contribution of John Gorton to his country.</p>
<p>John Gorton was one of the first politicians, I believe, at the national</p>
<p> political level in Australia to really understand the power of personal</p>
<p> communication on television. It is my belief that John Gorton would</p>
<p> not have won the leadership of the Liberal Party after the tragic</p>
<p> death of Harold Holt in 1967 if he hadn't been able to communicate</p>
<p> so directly and passionately and in such a personal fashion in the</p>
<p> interviews that he conducted on television immediately after Harold</p>
<p> Holt's death.</p>
<p>He also, of course, knew a thing or two about drama when it came to</p>
<p> Party Room ballots. Now, there's a few of who know a thing or</p>
<p> two about drama in Party Room ballots. I've been through a few</p>
<p> of those myself. I've got to say I've never been in a tie.</p>
<p> I either was resoundingly defeated or got drafted but never in a tie.</p>
<p> And it must have been quite an exquisite moment and as I look around</p>
<p> the room and I see some of the former colleagues who are gathered</p>
<p> here. But he played a major role in a number of things that continue</p>
<p> to be very important to the Liberal Party's political base today.</p>
<p>A little remark thing about John Gorton's ministerial career</p>
<p> was that he played a very big role in cementing the changed political</p>
<p> allegiances that followed the Menzies Government embrace of State</p>
<p> aid to independent schools in 1963 and that continue to be an enduringly</p>
<p> important thing in the dynamic of Australian politics.</p>
<p>He was, in every sense of the word, the genuine article as far as</p>
<p> a dinkum Australian was concerned. He was direct. He was laconic.</p>
<p> He had at all times a clear and passionate view of what the Australian</p>
<p> national interest was. He argued like, I guess, all Prime Ministers</p>
<p> do from time to time with the Premiers of the States. He had some</p>
<p> celebrated arguments with Sir Henry Bolte and Sir Robert Askin during</p>
<p> the time of his prime ministership.</p>
<p>On all occasions John Gorton was a man who had a clear eyed view of</p>
<p> the Australian national interest and he was a passionate nationalist</p>
<p> above everything else. And that's not a bad example for any Prime</p>
<p> Minister be it in 1969, 1979 or indeed 1999 because the enduring commitment</p>
<p> to the national interest is something for which I believe he will</p>
<p> be remembered.</p>
<p>I think political parties should treasure their history. I think political</p>
<p> parties should honour their past warriors and their past contributors.</p>
<p> And tonight is an opportunity for us to do that and I'm immensely</p>
<p> proud that I've had the chance, as the current Liberal Prime</p>
<p> Minister of Australia, to honour John Gorton. To have John and Nancy</p>
<p> with us and a number of their former colleagues and former colleagues</p>
<p> of mine who have come here tonight, I think it's a wonderful</p>
<p> opportunity for us to pay tribute to a great Australian, a great leader,</p>
<p> a great Prime Minister, a Liberal to his boot straps and a man whose</p>
<p> contribution to Australia is properly honoured and properly remembered.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
