<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6424</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/07/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006424.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA 13 July 1984<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. Hawke, and the Premier<br />
of Western Australia, Mr. Burke.<br />
The Commonwealth and Western Australian Governments have<br />
agreed on January 1 next year as the date for the handover<br />
to the State of the Army land on Rottnest Island.<br />
The State Government will pay the Commonwealth $ 2.2 million<br />
as a contribution towards the replacement elsewhere of<br />
improvements on the 55.7 hectares of land.<br />
Arrangements for the transfer have been worked out by<br />
Commonwealth and State officials and were announced today by<br />
the Prime Minister, Mr. Bob Hawke, and the Premier of Western<br />
Australia, Njr. Brian Burke.<br />
This follows Mr. Hawke's agreement last September to a request<br />
by Mr. Burke for the return of -the land, ending years of<br />
Commonwealth-State argument about it.<br />
Under the arrangements, the State will make payments of<br />
$ 1.1 million on January 1 and July 1 with vacant possession<br />
on January 1 and the handing over of title on July 1.<br />
The State has been relieved of the responsibility of finding<br />
acceptable replacement facilities for the Army.'<br />
The Commonwealth originally sought $ 2.9 million as the State's<br />
contribution to the replacement of facilities and the State<br />
of fered $ 2 million. The agreed contribution follows<br />
discussions between officials.<br />
Mr. Hawke and Mr. Burke both expressed pleasure that the<br />
arrangements for the transfer had been completed and that thert. e<br />
had been agreement between the Cormnonweallt-h and the State on<br />
the terms of the transfer.<br />
Mr. Hawke said that as someone who had visited the island on<br />
many occasions in the past, he had great affection for Rottnest's<br />
unique charm, lifestyle and environment. He was delighted to<br />
have had the opportunity as Prime Minister to make more of thE!<br />
island available to Western Australia. </p>
<p>Mr. Burke said the handover on January 1 was a day that all<br />
Rottnest lovers had looked forward to for many years.<br />
Like the rest of the island, the land would be placed under<br />
the control of the Rottnest Island Board. No decisions<br />
would be made about its future use until after the review<br />
of public submissions on the interim development plan for<br />
the island. U I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
