<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4348</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH OMBUDSMAN APPOINTED</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/03/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004348.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargoed against delivery / 0<br />
AIS i A A,<br />
FOR PRESS 17 MARCH 1977<br />
CO1DONWEALTH OMBUDSMAN APPOINTED<br />
I an pleased to inform the House that the Government has<br />
appointed Professor J. E. Richardson, Robert Garran Professor<br />
of Law at the Australian National University, to the position<br />
of Commonwealth Ombudsman.<br />
Professor Richardson's appointment will be for a period of<br />
seven years and he will take up his appointment as soon as<br />
arrangements can be made for his release from the University.<br />
The Government is very pleased that Professor RLchardson has<br />
agreed to accept the position of Commonwealth Ombudsman.<br />
Pro'essor Richardson is a distinguished academic of high<br />
Australian and international standing who will bring to this<br />
off: I'ce the qualities and experience which are necessary to<br />
perform this challenging role. He has administ. ative e. nd<br />
public service experience as well as having had a close association<br />
with this Parliament. He was the Legal Secretary to the<br />
Constitution Review Committee of the Parliament from 1956 to<br />
1959. Professor Richardson has been a Professor of Law at the<br />
Australian National University since 1962 and practised. at the<br />
N. S. W. Bar in 1974 and 1975.<br />
As Ombudsman, his task will be to investigate complaints and<br />
to initiate enquiries concerning administrative actions of<br />
departments and prescribed authorities and make reports regarding<br />
those investigations. The establisnent of the Office is<br />
directed towards ensuring that departments and authorities are<br />
responsible, adaptive and sensitive to the needs of citizens.<br />
I am sure that everyone will welcome Professor Richardson's<br />
appcintment as the first holder of the Office of Commonwealth<br />
Ombudsman. My Government believes that Professor Richardson<br />
has the qualities, experience and capacity to successfully<br />
inaugurate and establish the office of the Commonwealth Ombudsman. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
