<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2830</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN/INDONESIAN JOINT COMMUNIQUE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/02/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Communique</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002830.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 43 23 February 1973<br />
AUSTRALIAN/ INDONE9IAN JOINT COMMUNIQUE<br />
The following is the text of the joint communique<br />
S issued at the conclusion of the Prime Minister's discussions<br />
with President Soeharto in Indonesia:<br />
" The Prime Minister of Australia, the Honourable E. G.<br />
Whitlam, visited Indonesia from 20 to 25 February at<br />
the invitation of His Excellency President Soeharto.<br />
Mr hitlam's visit soon after assuming office as Prime<br />
Minister reflected his Government's announced intention to give<br />
priority to the strengthening of Australia's relations with<br />
Indonesia. President Soeharto welcomed Mr Whitlam's visit to<br />
SIndonesia because of the importance he attaches to maintaining<br />
close understanding with the Australian Government. Mr Whitlam<br />
while leader of the Australian Opposition met President Soeharto<br />
several times. His first visit to Indonesia as Prime Minister<br />
of Australia enabled the two Heads of Government to draw on and<br />
consolidate this previous relationship.<br />
President Soeharto and Mr Whitlam value relations of<br />
nersonal confidence. At their wish comprehensive working discussions<br />
were the focal Doint of the visit. The two Heads of Government / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
had lengthy private discussions. Their exchange of views was<br />
wide-ranging and was marked by cordiality, frankness and harmony.<br />
The understanding established between them marked an important<br />
advance in relations between Indonesia and Australia.<br />
Mr Whitlam received courtesy calls by the State<br />
Minister of Economic, Industrial and Financial Affairs, His<br />
Highness Sri Sultan Hamengku Buwon IX, by Foreign Minister Haji<br />
Adam Malik and by the Governor of Jakarta, Lieutenant-general<br />
Kko Ali Sadikin. He attended working meetings with Ministers<br />
and senior officials responsible for economic development and<br />
trade and with the Ministers for Defence and Foreign tAffairs<br />
and senior officers of the Indonesian Armed Forces. Substantive<br />
discussions took place on each of these occasions.<br />
Talks during Mr Whitlam's visit covered matters of<br />
common interest to Australia and Indonesia. These included the<br />
prospects for intensified co-operation in bilateral relations,<br />
the situation and outlook in the Asia/ Pact ,' ic region following<br />
the ceasefire agreement in Viet-Nam, and questions likely to<br />
arise in the United Nations Security Council to which Indonesia<br />
and Australia were both elected at the 27th General Assembly.<br />
Mr Whitlam explained to President Soeharto and his<br />
advisers the direction that his Government is seeking to impart<br />
to Australian foreign policy. He said this was towards a more<br />
independent Australian stance in international affairs firmly based<br />
on national identity, social justice, human rights and peaceful<br />
regional co-oneration, and not onen to suggestions of racism. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
This broad anproach had prompted his Government since coming to<br />
office to take a series of initiatives designed to establish<br />
Australia's standing as a distinctive, tolerant and co-operative<br />
nation in the Asia/ Pacific region and in the world at large.<br />
President Soeharto and Mr Whitlam expressed the hope that<br />
detente among the great powers would improve the prospects for<br />
peace and stability in the South-East Asia region. They welcomed<br />
the conclusion of the ceasefire agreement in Viet-Nam and hoped<br />
that this would lead to the resolution of differences among the<br />
narties in Indo-China by negotiation. Mr Whitlam recognised<br />
Indonesia's participation in the ICCS as a nositive and valuable<br />
contribution towards peace in the South-East Asia region.<br />
President Soeharto explained to Mr Whitlam the develooment<br />
strategy of the new order in Indonesia and its relationship to<br />
foreign nolicy. He said that in accordance with the concept of<br />
national resilience, Indonesia was fully harnessing her resources<br />
for national development and security. He emphasized Indonesia's<br />
wish to have good relations with all countries and the importance<br />
of peace and security for Indonesia's development.<br />
President Soeharto said that, through its good neighbour<br />
policy, the new order in Indonesia had sought oositive and<br />
co-operative relations, esnecially with countries of the region,<br />
to bring about favourable conditions for social and economic<br />
progress. Indonesia attached great importance to regional<br />
co-operation through ASFAN and by means of close bilateral<br />
relations with neighbouring countries. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Mr Whitlam welcomed the progress achieved by ASEAN which<br />
Australia considers a model of successful regional co-operation<br />
in South-East Asia. He said that Australia had followed with<br />
interest th-e initiatives of her A-) 3FNN neighbours to achieve a<br />
zone of peace, freedom and neutrality in South-East Asia.<br />
Australia suppiorted these efforts and would encourage other<br />
countries to do likewise. President Soeharto explained to<br />
Mr Whitlam his Government's arnroach to the idea of a zone of<br />
peace, freedom and neutrality, based upon the strengthening<br />
of national resilience and co-operation among the member countries<br />
of the rerpion so that they maintain effective control of their<br />
destinies. Mr Whitlam discussed with President Soeharto and his<br />
advisers the prospects for progress in regional co-operation in<br />
Asia. Mr Whitlam affirmed that regional co-operation was a keystone<br />
of Australian foreign policy. He looked forward to the eventual<br />
emergence of a comprehensive regional organization, without<br />
ideological overtones, to heln free the Asia/ Pacific area from<br />
great power intervention and rivalries.<br />
Mr Whitlam. said that in canvassing this idea Australia<br />
would consult punctiliously with regional neighbours and would be<br />
sensitive to their ideas and aspirations. His proposals were<br />
preliminary and exploratory. He recognised that new forms of<br />
regional co-operation would not be quiickly or easily achieved.<br />
His ideas were intended to complement ASEAN and were in no way<br />
com~ petitive with, or alternative to it. </p>
<p>President Soeharto welcomed Mr Whitlam's objective of<br />
the evolution of a widely representative Asian regiona<br />
organization. The President agreed that, while such a concent<br />
was unlikely to come about in the short term, he recognised its<br />
potential value in the longer term.<br />
Mr Whitlam addressed a plenary session of the Indonesian<br />
Parliament. He was pleased by this opportunity to strengthen<br />
relations between the representative institutions of Indonesia<br />
and Australia. Mr Whitlam said that he looked forward to a visit<br />
this year to Australia by a delegation representing the leadership<br />
of the Indonesian Parliament.<br />
President Soeharto and Mr Whitlam noted with satisfaction<br />
the progress so far achieved in Australian/ Indonesian co-operation<br />
in the fields of development assistance and defence. They<br />
reviewed several important projects now in course and identified<br />
others to be incorporated in future assistance programmes. They<br />
agreed that both countries would oarticinate in a joint<br />
feasibility study of the develonment potential in the Cilacap<br />
area of Java. During his discussions with President Soeharto,<br />
Mr Whitlam emphasised his Government's commitment to the provision<br />
of expanded development assistance to the developing countries<br />
of the region to assist them to achieve more nrosperous and just<br />
societies. Australia's assistance would continue to be directed<br />
closely to Indonesia's development priorities. President / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
Soeharto expressed anpreciation for past Australian development<br />
assistance and expressed the hope that co-operation between the<br />
two countries in this field would continue to reflect the<br />
increasingly friendly relations between Australia and Indonesia.<br />
The mutual benefits deriving from trade between the two<br />
countries and from Australian investment in Indonesia w. ere<br />
discussed. President Soeharto and Mr Whitlam recognised the<br />
importance of Australian trade and investment contributing to<br />
the economic nrogress of Indonesia and towards the expansion<br />
of Indonesia's export capabilities. Both countries agreed that<br />
consideration might be given by Australian investors to increasing<br />
the local content in their production wherever economically viable.<br />
The Minister of Economic Financial and Industrial Affairs<br />
and the other Economic Ministers outlined Indonesia's economic<br />
problems and the way in which Australia could help. The Prime<br />
Minister undertook to put these matters to immediate and<br />
symnathetic study.<br />
The two leaders agreed to intensify bilateral exchanges<br />
and co-oneration in cultural affairs. They looked forward to<br />
the establishment in Jakarta of the projected Australian cultural<br />
centre. Mr Whitlam said that Australia would welcome the<br />
establishment by Indonesia of a cultural centre in Australia.<br />
Mr Whitlam informed President Soeharto that Australia<br />
would contribute $ A200,000 over five years to the UNESCO Fund<br />
for the restoration o Borobudur. This announcement was warmly<br />
welcomed by the President. / 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
Mr Whitlam informed President Soeharto of his Government's<br />
intention to ratify at an early date the Seabed Boundary Agreements<br />
already negotiated bet",, een Australia and Indonesia. Both<br />
Governments will also ratify as soon as practicable the agreement<br />
relating to the boundary between Indonesia and Papua New Guinea<br />
which was signed at Jakarta on 12 February, 1973, by Mr Malik<br />
on behalf of Indonesia and Mr Somare, the Chief Minister of<br />
Papua New Guinea, on behalf of Australia and Papua New Guinea.<br />
Mr Whitlam and President Soeharto welcomed the rapid<br />
nrogreqs of Papua New Guinea towards indenendence. President<br />
Soeharto affirmed Indonesia's intention to open consular<br />
representation at Port Moresby and looked forward to the develonment<br />
of close and friendly relations between Indonesia and Papua New<br />
Guinea. Mr Whitlam said that Australia was encouraged by the<br />
prosnect of close co-operation betweel. Indonesia and Papua New<br />
Guinea as neighbours sharing a common land boundary.<br />
President Soehrto and Mr Whitlam noted with satisfaction<br />
the broad areas of agreement and nrospects for close co-operation<br />
between Australia and Indonesia in international organizations,<br />
underlined by their concurrent membership of the United Nations<br />
Security Council. They agreed that in future representatives<br />
of both countries in international bodies and conferences would<br />
be instructed to maintnin close consultation and to take into<br />
account mutual interests in all appropriate issues.<br />
At the conclusion of the official talks, the President<br />
of Indonesia and the Australian Prime Minister expressed confidence<br />
that in the years ahead the two countries would work together even / 8 </p>
<p>-8-<br />
more closely and constructively than in the oast.<br />
Before leaving Indonesia the Prime Minister and<br />
Mrs Whitlam exnressed their aprreciation for the warmth and<br />
cordiality that marked both the official and informal functions<br />
during their stay in Indonesia. They said that they would long<br />
remember the hospitality and friendship shown to them by<br />
Indonesians at all levels. They exnressed the hope that President<br />
and Madame Soeharto would make a return visit to Australia at a<br />
convenient future date." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
