<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3835</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO 19 - THE BUDGET - SUNDAY 27 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003835.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO. 19 -THE BUDGET<br />
SUNDAY 27 JULY 1975<br />
On Friday my colleagues and I finished a week of<br />
intensive Cabinet discussions to frame the Budget which the<br />
Treasurer, Bill Hayden, will be bringing down next month.<br />
It wouldn't be proper to tell you what is in the Budget, but<br />
I can tell you something of our general approach to it. I<br />
might mention in passing that our Budget discussions were<br />
more than a little hampered by the farce which the Senate<br />
has enacted in the past two weeks, requiring Ministers to be<br />
on hand for the Opposition's interrogation of public servants*<br />
and others. But those are the Senate's priorities political<br />
inquisitions first, the national Budget second.<br />
It is not exaggeration to say that the coming Budget<br />
will be the most important for Australia for a very long time.<br />
And more preparation and consultation has gone into this<br />
Budget than any before. We've listened to the views of<br />
consumners, of unions, of employers, of farmers' organisations,<br />
of industry a whole host of people in the community. And<br />
P months ago we set up important new procedures to plan and<br />
develop the Budget strategy. A special committee of ministers,<br />
backed by a committee of officials, has worked hard to review<br />
the whole range of government expenditures. So simply: this<br />
will be the most thoroughly prepared and carefully planned<br />
Budget Australia has ever had.<br />
Our first two Budgets in 1973 and 1974 were ones<br />
of heavy Government expenditure. There was a good reason for<br />
that. When we came to office we had the task of redressing<br />
many years of neglect by previous Governments in almost every<br />
field of national life. For 23 years the Liberals had neglected<br />
education, neglected our cities, neglected our country towns,<br />
neglected local government, neglected the urgent needs of<br />
public transport, health, the environment, migrants, women,<br />
Aborigines, pensioners, children. A great many things were crying<br />
out to be done programs and reforms of a fundamental and<br />
long-term nature. After all, the people in two elections in<br />
1972 and 1974 had given us a clear mandate, clear instructions<br />
to get on with the tasks we inherited. So we had to spend<br />
money big money. Things like Medibank, and better schools and<br />
higher pensions don't come cheap, but it would have been utterly<br />
irresponsible for us to ignore the people's demands for such<br />
services. on top of that, there were other heavy unexpected<br />
calls on Government finance such as funds for Darwin and for<br />
flood relief here in Queensland.<br />
While these programs were getting underway a further<br />
need arose for heavy Government expenditure. Last year the<br />
whole western world entered on the worst recession experienced<br />
since the war. Australia has not escaped. In such circumstances<br />
at a time of rising unemployment it was necessary to push<br />
Goverhment expenditure further ahead in order to boost our<br />
economy and keep Australians at work. On the whole that strategy<br />
paid off. The recession in Australia has been a good deal less<br />
severe than it has been in other countries. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Let me illustrate. In the United States, industrial<br />
production during the recession has declined by about 14 per cent<br />
compared with an eight per cent decline in Australia.<br />
Unemployment in the United States has passed the eight per cent<br />
mark. In Australia it is 4.5 per cent. In Japan the decline<br />
in production was of the order of 20 per cent compared with<br />
eight per cent here. So don't get the idea that unemployment<br />
and recession have been confined to Australia; it's been a<br />
world-wide upheaval with world-wide causes.<br />
The point is that the world is nejust beginning to<br />
climb out of the recession. The signs of recovery are appearing<br />
both here and abroad. So we have this difficult problem:<br />
flow much longer should we push ahead with expenditures to combat<br />
unemployment, how much longer should we maintain our high levels<br />
of spending on the great social programs we have started?<br />
Economic questions of this kind have never been more complex<br />
and difficult, because we have to try to look ahead and take4<br />
decisions now whose effects won't be felt for many months to<br />
come. In general we feel that, now that the worst of the<br />
recession is behind us, our priority must be to at-tack inflation.<br />
Inflation is another problem that has bedevilled every western<br />
country. In former years, the standard way to attack inflation4<br />
was to bring about a recession and throw people out of work.<br />
That was thE! method the Liberals used. And of course it no<br />
longer works anywhere in the world. We staunchly resisted that<br />
approach when it was put to us in the Budget discussions last<br />
year. True, unemployment has occurred, but we have managed to<br />
keep it at lower levels than in most other countries. The<br />
question now is: what other approach can we take to hold down<br />
inflationary pressures?<br />
There are two things we can do. One is cut back the<br />
growth of Government qxpenditure. As part of this process, 4<br />
I announced on Monday that we would be putting a strict limit<br />
in the next financial year on the growth of the Australian Public<br />
Service which, incidentally has been growing at a slower rate<br />
than the State public services. In addition we are looking at<br />
ways of reducing Government expenditure in other areas. This4<br />
doesn't mean that we are no longer committed to our national<br />
goals better public facilities, wider opportunities for all<br />
Australians. It means that, having got these programs started,<br />
having set up the machinery to run them, we can now take a breather<br />
and slow down our spending sharply in the interests of the whole<br />
economy. This won't be popular with those who benefit from our<br />
programs and I don't need to tell you that it isn't particularly<br />
palatable to us but it has to be done. And the other thing we<br />
have to do is keep the national wages bill within reasonable<br />
limits. Our economies in expenditure won't be much use in<br />
countering inflation if wages and salaries in both the public<br />
and private sectors are allowed to grow too quickly and push<br />
prices up further. My Government fought a hard battle to persuade<br />
the Arbitration Commission to give wage indexation a fair trial.<br />
Indexation will protect the real living standards of every<br />
employee. It must be given a chance to work. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
I wouldn't be honest with you if I said there were<br />
easy solutions to our economic problems. I can't promise a<br />
popular Budget but I can promise a sound and responsible<br />
Budget if you like, a tough Budget.. In the next twelve<br />
months we are going to need all the help and co-operation we can<br />
get in making the Budget work, in safeguarding our living<br />
standards. I'll have no patience with knockers and whingers.<br />
We must make sure that Australia is one of the first countries<br />
in the world to come through this recession, and to come<br />
through it in good shape, in fighting trim. We can do it.<br />
We cannot afford to fail. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
