<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9910</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP LAUNCH OF OUR NATION SYDNEY, 20 JANUARY 1996</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/01/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009910.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( 7)<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
LAUNCH OF OUR NATION<br />
SYDNEY, 20 JANUARY 1996<br />
* CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY**<br />
Even allowing for this years rel atively awful weather everywhere from here to<br />
Bass Strait and beyond, there are things about Australia in the summer<br />
holidays which never fail to remind us that to live in this country is to be very<br />
fortunate. The long warnm days, the beaches, the barbecues, the family, the friends; the<br />
sport, the arlts, the space it's generally enough to help wind down from the<br />
year gone by and to wind up for the one ahead, even one which contains an<br />
election. You stop reading the papers, give up on the evening news It is a<br />
nag-free environment.<br />
We take the good things pretty much for granted. But sometimes all of a<br />
sudden its hits you, that we are profoundly lucky to have a country as good<br />
as this a continent as big and wonderful, and a society as strong, free,<br />
democratic, rich and unpretentious.<br />
I think it's a time of the year when, in an entirely understated way of course,<br />
we celebrate the country and the pleasure we take in being Australian.<br />
There are even times when I think we should all stop and drink a toast to the<br />
place, to the fact that we are here, and to our fellow Australians.<br />
And just as quickly go back to whatever we were doing or not doing.<br />
This may be an unconscious reflection of a Celtic heritage. The Celts love<br />
toasts. But I don't think it's got much to do with the Irish. It takes a lot less time than<br />
my family have been In Australia to develop a purely Australian form of<br />
sentimentality. We might retain a certain self-conscious pride or interest in.<br />
our ethnic origins, but after a generation or two it is not much more than a<br />
hobby. Yet in an immigrant society the knowledge of where we came from is<br />
knowledge worth having. </p>
<p>Even after several generations of experience has made us incorrigibly<br />
Australian, we old Anglo, Celtic Australians retain a certain affectionate<br />
curiosity about our ancestral seats, and almost certainly reflect a little of the<br />
culture from which we are derived not to say the physical characteristics.<br />
A hundred years ago there were plenty of people in this country who knew<br />
exactly what Henry Lawson meant when he said: " I am Australian. I know no<br />
other land".<br />
And I have met Australians who migrated as children in the 1940s and<br />
who would say exactly the same thing. Even as they eat dolmades and<br />
gefillte fish and tabouli and toad-in-the-hole and tagliatelle.<br />
Eve * n as they practise their traditional religions, observe their traditional<br />
rituals and celebrations and display, in all sorts of nearly imperceptible ways,<br />
their traditional culture and habits of mind.<br />
In other words, we are all to a greater or lesser extent, Immigrants. And we<br />
are all equally Australians. That is the reason for celebrating.<br />
There have been many reasons advanced -for the success of Australia's<br />
Immigrant sodiety. I think most of them are valid and none of them are<br />
sufficient reason to be complacent about it. All of them put together are no<br />
reason to be complacent about it.<br />
There seems to me no doubt that the great physical spaces of Australia al so<br />
create psychological space and this helps the cause of peace in a diverse<br />
society.<br />
And that is also a reason to bear in mind the need to plan our development in<br />
clever ways which use the space and its resources optimally.<br />
Immigration always teaches us things about ourselves.<br />
The old democratic fabric and institutions of this country, and the egalitarian<br />
traditions, have also helped us accommodate the cultural difference. The<br />
Idea of the " fair go" has been a real force in shaping Australia, including<br />
multicultural Australia.<br />
And that is also a reason to insist that all Australians, and especially our<br />
children, know -the-value of the democracy. and the democratic traditions they<br />
have Inherited.<br />
If there Is a third substantial reason for the success of multiculturalism in<br />
Australia, it may be that we have been multicultural since the beginning of<br />
European settlement. The First Fleet was multicultural and every generation<br />
since has lived with significant cultural, religious and political difference not<br />
the least of them of course the difference between the Irish and the English.<br />
And that Is another reason not to be complacent our generations are not the<br />
first to live successfully with diversity, we inherited a lot of our knowledge. </p>
<p>3<br />
If these are three broad reasons for the success of modern multicultural<br />
Australia the fact of our environment, the fact of our democracy, and the fact<br />
of our experience in cultural diversity they tend to suggest that to keep<br />
succeeding we need to keep working and take nothing for granted.<br />
Above all, we should remember what all free immigrants to Australia had in<br />
common and that was the search for a better life. Nothing so effectively<br />
made the cultural differences seem unimportant as the common pursuit of<br />
prosperity and freedom.<br />
It follows that if we want this diverse modern Australia to remain harmonious,<br />
productive and cohesive we have to maintain both the standards of our<br />
democracy and the energy of our economy and our society. Whatever<br />
sophisticated multicultural programs we devise, these are the most important<br />
prerequisites of success.<br />
I think the essential thing to understand about a society like ours an<br />
Immigrant society is that immigration is a two-way street. It involves a<br />
cultural exchange.<br />
When I was'gowing up;, I worked for a while in Pyrmont and I would often go<br />
down and watch the ships from P&amp; O and the Orient Line come in and dock,<br />
loaded with immigrants; families crowded to the rails looking at the city with<br />
who knows what sort of feelings.<br />
And who knows what sorts of feelings were felt by those of us who watched.<br />
But 1 am sure that not all the fear and apprehension were on the other side of<br />
the ship's rail. 1 am sure there was some kind of exchange of feelings. I think<br />
whatever hope they felt was matched by our admiration for their courage in<br />
crossing the world and, perhaps even more admirable, to have come among<br />
US. In retrospect you can see how It was a leap of faith on both sides. That's the<br />
great strength of Australia's post-war Immigration policy. It took courage on<br />
both sides and I believe the experience has given Australia that much more<br />
courage. It gave us many things and I don't think this audience needs me to tell them<br />
what they are,.. But I do think-that-this.-is-a point worth making: when you<br />
open yourself up to the world, when you are brave enough to look cultural<br />
difference in the eye, you learn a great deal. And half of what you learn is<br />
about yourself. And you are made stronger by that and more mature.<br />
That is what I mean by immigration being essentially an exchange. For<br />
everything we have given to the people from 160 countries who have come<br />
here, we have been repaid. For a new start in life, they repaid Australia in<br />
their energy, ideas and ambitions, in their skills and in their culture. But, just<br />
as Importantly, In the greater maturity, self-knowledge and the courage they<br />
have given us. </p>
<p>In the global environment we now find ourselves in, and amid the intense<br />
competition, these qualities have a value for us which is beyond measure.<br />
We can define multiculturallsm In any number of ways. Some people like the<br />
concept but hate the word so much they would like to define it out of<br />
existence. Yet, as I have said before, so long as it is not mistaken for an<br />
ideology or a bureaucracy or a set of rules in political correctness, the word is<br />
a perfectly accurate description of what we are, what we must be and what<br />
we want to be.<br />
I think we should live with the word and enjoy the reality. Above all, we<br />
should recognise that this multicultural ism massively enlarges our democracy<br />
and our democratic traditions, It adds to our freedom as well as to the<br />
richness of our lives.<br />
That Is why we should enshrine the principle of tolerance among our most<br />
basic democratic principles.<br />
And that is why the suggestion made in the statement we are launching<br />
today, that we begin to think of our country in terms of a Multicultural<br />
Compact seeifns to me ' such a good one, Essentially it gives expression to<br />
thb idea of Immigration as an exchange.<br />
The Multicultural Compact states that we share this land with the first<br />
Australians, whose cultures are oldest of all; and that, as a result of<br />
Immigration, we also share a wealth of diverse histories and traditions.<br />
The Compact asks of all Australians, irrespective of background and<br />
generation, that they Invest their main allegiance in Australia; that they<br />
accept the basic structures of Australian society the rule of law, tolerance,<br />
equality of opportunity, parliamentary democracy, freedom of speech and<br />
religion, English as the national language and equality of the sexes and<br />
races; and that they extend to others the same freedoms they claim for<br />
themselves. And the Australian community is asked in exchange: to ensure equality of<br />
access, opportunity and participation, unimpeded by barriers of race,<br />
language or country of birth; to ensure that our institutions reflect and<br />
respond to the diversity of the population; to ensure that the potential<br />
-contribution of-all Australians is recognised, and to provide opportunities for<br />
all Australians to learn both English and another language.<br />
I will be writing to Premiers and Chief Ministers seeking endorsement by all<br />
Australian governments of the principles contained within the Multicultural<br />
Compact. A healthy multicultural society has no need for rules and sanctions. But there<br />
is value In describing the logic by which the country works, and in defining<br />
the minimum standards required in a civil society. </p>
<p>4. And this is the time to begin that process of definition.<br />
Because in the last decade of the twentieth century, for the first time in our<br />
history, we have a real chance to decide our own destiny to pull together all<br />
the strands of Australian identity.<br />
We have dismantled all the barriers which quarantined us from the rest of the<br />
world and we are becoming ever more deeply engaged in our own region.<br />
These are exciting times and we need Australians to engage in them. I<br />
believe this statement will help that process. We have derived immeasurable<br />
benefits from immigration and from the multicultural programs of the last two<br />
decades. These days we tend to think in terms of the economic and cultural<br />
benefits, and there is no question that they are immense.<br />
However, I am inclined to think that the greatest benefits are literally without<br />
measure; and that they go not only to governments, nations and communities<br />
but to every one of us. They make all Australians, whatever their<br />
backgrounds, a little bit richer and a little bit stronger.<br />
In part, Our Nation is a response to the report of the National Multicultural<br />
Advisory Co~ ncil, an&amp;~ I would like to thank the Council for its work in<br />
reviewing the architecture of multicultural Australia.<br />
I want especially to thank Mick Young for his great work as Chair of the<br />
Council. Mick comes from the same ethnic group as myself.<br />
But and I'm sure you will excuse my using the word in this context we are<br />
both thoroughly assimilated.<br />
In his own way Mick Young is proof of the greatness of this democracy: in<br />
not every country is it possible for a shearer to reach the highest rungs of<br />
office; but then not every country produces shearers like Mick.<br />
Mick is stepping down for health reasons; and I hope he will forgive me for<br />
reminding him that everyone in this room wishes him well.<br />
* I must also welcome the new Chair of the National Multicultural Advisory<br />
* CounciyMr Neville Roach,. who is with us today..<br />
I am now delighted to launch Our Nation.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
