<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6940</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PM`S CONFERENCE , CANOWINDRA 31 MAY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006940.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1AtST ALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIP~ T OF PM'S PRESS CONFERENCE, CANOWINDRA 31 MAY 1986<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you think you've won them over today?<br />
PM: It wasn't a question of trying to win them over. I gave<br />
Peter and his colleagues a promise that I would come and visit<br />
them. They asked me to. It was a generous invitation and I'm<br />
fulfilling that undertaking. I wasn't coming here to win votes,<br />
I wasn't coming here to lose them either. I hope that out of<br />
this visit Peter, and the people here, can accept that firstly,<br />
we understand their problems and are serious about trying to<br />
do what we can about them. They may not agree with everything<br />
we're doing, but the first step is that we understand and that<br />
they understand what we're about.<br />
JOURNALIST: D~ oes the rural community have to accept sacrifices<br />
like the rest of us at the moment?<br />
PM: Not like the rest. There may be, in the approaches that<br />
we have to adopt to adjust to this dramatic fall in the terms<br />
of trade, there may be some little further element as far as<br />
the rural coimrunity is concerned. I wouldn't think it is<br />
appropriate that they should be asked to bear as much as anyone<br />
else because they have had an enormous fall in their income as<br />
a result of the terms of trade. When we talk about the terms<br />
of trade decl. ine you are talking about the decline of the income<br />
of farmers.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what were some of the concerns that Mr Ryan<br />
put to you at the meeting this morning?<br />
PM: The indebtedness situation and therefore, the burden of<br />
their payments. They acknowledge that there has been a move<br />
down in the interest rates, but within that situation they<br />
stressed again what appears to be the somewhat differential<br />
treatment of farmers. They don't get the full benefit, of the<br />
decline in rates apparently, and that's something that John<br />
Kerin and I are going to be talking about and seeing whether<br />
there's anything more that can be done in that area. That is<br />
a major burden of their complaint. One can understand it.<br />
One of the sorts of figures that struck me most forceably was<br />
one of the gentlemen, there today, said that his calculation,<br />
I think it was over the last three years, he'd produced for<br />
Australia I think about $ 3 million worth of<br />
RYAN: Two years it was.<br />
PM: I'm sorry, it was two years he'd produced about $ 3 million<br />
of income in wheat exports and was broke. He'd gone broke<br />
in the process. Now that's pretty telling sort of stuff because<br />
Australia as a whole benefits from that export income which his<br />
efforts have generated and you can understand them feeling crook </p>
<p>because if Australia as a whole benefits from those long hours<br />
of labour, and yet he's going backwards. Now you can understand<br />
that. JOURNALIST: Will there that particular issue in<br />
your economic statement?<br />
PM: What on the issue of differential interest burdens?<br />
JOURNALIST: And indebtedness?<br />
PM: I don't think that's necessarily appropriate for that<br />
statement. John and I will be analysing what we've heard<br />
today and there's one or two particular issues where I think<br />
we may be able to do something in initiating possible changes.<br />
Though that's more particularly for rural sector, the general<br />
statement I will be making will be much broader than that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister you've offered nothing new today,<br />
nothing specifically new....<br />
PM: Well you don't know what I've offered.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well you certainly haven't made that public.<br />
PM: No, well I'm saying that you would have to ask Peter and<br />
the others. What I've said is in certain specific areas where<br />
they have raised the problem that this differential treatment<br />
in regard to interest rates. I think there that's something<br />
that we can address our attention to. See if there is some<br />
improvement that can be affected.<br />
JOURNALIST: What are those areas?<br />
PM: Well what I'm saying there is that what they are putting is<br />
that farmers seem to be differentiated against, that is what<br />
they are suggesting, by the banks and they make the observation<br />
that the security of their property is very substantial. There's<br />
no reason why there should be significant differentiation. Now<br />
that seems on its face to be a sound argument. I've undertaken,<br />
together with John Kerin, I'll look at that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think farmers are as badly off as they say<br />
they are?<br />
PM: You can't generalise. When you're talking about 175,000<br />
farmers altogether, around Australia, some relatively aren't<br />
suffering very much. There are others who are going to be<br />
suffering very badly. I think that if you want to generalise<br />
you'vye got to say that farmers are very much worse off now<br />
than they were a few years ago because of this massive<br />
deterioration in the terms of trade. The drop in the price of<br />
wheat over the last two or three years has been 12 per cent.<br />
There's been very significant declines in their prices and they're<br />
still faced with increased costs. So they must be worse off.<br />
Now the extent for each farmer will depend on the degree of<br />
equity he has in his land. Tf he has got a 100 per cent equity<br />
and hasn't got a debt burden well he's going to be, obviously,<br />
in a much different situation to the person who's got very<br />
littl. e ecuity. Also, a lot of them made a move into crop<br />
production in 80/ 81, when the prices were up, and acquired </p>
<p>significant indebtness to get the machinery. It's a heavily<br />
capitalised section of agriculture, wheat and similar crops.<br />
Those who went in heavily then and acquired the machinery<br />
then, they've got particular burdens. So you can't generalise<br />
for all because that will disguise the fact that some are<br />
very much worse off than others. Having said that, clearly,<br />
for Australia as a whole, there has been a massive drop in<br />
rural income.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think that the policies you announce today<br />
could return farming to of the 50' s and the<br />
PM: No of course not and the good sense of the people with whom<br />
I'm speaking know that that's not possible. We're not looking<br />
at that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Ryan you were the man that invited the Prime<br />
Minister down here. Was it worth while?<br />
RYAN: Yes I think that any opportunity to have dialogue with<br />
the Prime Minister of this country and the minister for Primary<br />
Industry has got to be worthwhile. What we were trying to achieve<br />
by this visit today was to get down and talk at grassroots level<br />
at the problems and pain that some people are feeling in<br />
agriculture. I think that we've been able to get that message<br />
across. JOURNALIST: What constructive things came out of it though?<br />
There's been a lot of talking in the past, is there anything<br />
new today?<br />
RYAN: No. I don't believe that there is a lot new at this stage.<br />
We have certainly stressed to the Prime minister that people are<br />
hurting and people are not only hurting, but they're worried and<br />
they're frightened. They're frightened because they don't really<br />
know where their next turn is going to be made and we've tried to<br />
stress that point to the Prime Minister, and given that situation<br />
we've offered a couple of proposals that we believe that they<br />
could look at as a means of alleviating this fear.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does this mean we're unlikely to see you in Canberra<br />
again with your rebel farmers protesting in front of Parliament<br />
House? RYAN: I don't think so. I believe that if need be farmers are<br />
prepared, still, to go to Canberra to make their point. And the<br />
way that we've been doing, I think, has been extremely worthwhile.<br />
I might also point out that we have graduated not only from tryinci<br />
to attract attention to the problem,, but we're also lobbying<br />
the politicians and the Government to try and make sure that<br />
everyone in the Parliament and the Government are informed<br />
on what agriculture is all about: and what are the specific<br />
problems in agriculture. </p>
<p>PM: I'd just like to add to that. As I said to you publicly<br />
and privately, they have o-.' ened up lines of communication. At<br />
no stage did we feel annoyance or aggravation at the fact that<br />
they were exercising a democrat right of protest. I've certainly<br />
appreciated the opportunity out of it of meeting Peter and his<br />
colleagues and I've undertaken that they can meet with our<br />
rural industry committee and out of that there comes a more<br />
formalised process of continuing consultation and that will be<br />
good. I think we both agree with that.<br />
RYAN: We're certainly going to continue with whatever has to<br />
be done. People have put a lot of faith in what we've done and<br />
we've got to make sure they have some hope.<br />
JOURNALIST: You mentioned that area of differential rates. You<br />
mentioned also that there was one other area, can you be specific?<br />
PM: Well I had raised with me specifically the question of the<br />
impact of the fringe benefits tax for employees. I just want to<br />
look at that and get some information about the degree of impact<br />
and Peter knows I've not promised anything on that. I just want<br />
to inform myself on the dimension of it. They are making the<br />
point that if they've got no income they're not paying any tax<br />
otherwise, and yet get hit with this tax. They regard that as<br />
an anomaly and a problem. I certainly want to have a look at<br />
that. They have certainly placed some stress on that.<br />
JOURNALIST: But you are convinced, is there some hope that...<br />
PM: I'm saying as much as I've said there.<br />
JOURNALIST: The European Community has increased its subsidies<br />
on cheese to Australia and the US has encroached further on our<br />
grain markets. Are we making any real impact with those two<br />
main agricultural super powers?<br />
PM: Yes we are making some impact. Clearly, take the United<br />
States first of all, I believe that as a result of my visit to<br />
Washington and discussions with President Reagan we've got<br />
avenues there for ensuring that our case will be put and heard<br />
in the actual implementation of the export enhancement program.<br />
Having said that I'm not being complacent about it because if<br />
you look at some of the recent developments, particularly in<br />
the Middle East with grain sales, there's some cause of concern<br />
there. We have got the avenues open. Mr Kerin will be going<br />
overseas again next month and will be continuing to press our<br />
case in these areas. As far as the Europeans are concerned,<br />
yes we've advanced there. We've got the reaffirmation of the<br />
Agreement as far as an all extension of European<br />
subsidies into our Asian beef markets. I believe that there<br />
is a growing realisation in Europe of the economic absurdity<br />
of $ 70 billion of subsidisation. They know that it's perverting<br />
thei~ r own economies. The fact that at the Tokyo Summit a third<br />
of the time of the economic discussion was spent upon international<br />
trade and agricultural products is some indication of the impact<br />
we've had. We pressed with President Reagan, we've pressed<br />
with Mrs Thatcher and the European Community and Mr Craxi, all<br />
the people who were going to be there, that they just had to<br />
address this issue. And I think that the fact that they had<br />
this historically long time on. these products was some reflection </p>
<p>of our pressures in this regard.<br />
JOURNALIST: One of the industries that is suffering in the west<br />
at the moment is the cotton industry. Did you discuss that<br />
with President Reagan on your last visit?<br />
PM: I've answered that one in Parliament and pointed out that the<br />
provisions of the US Farm Legislation in regard to cotton and rice<br />
were in place before I went to the United States and before these<br />
recent rounds of discussions had been going on. They weren't<br />
able to give us any firm undertakings in that regard. I would<br />
point out that it's not only Australia's concern in the area of<br />
cotton and rice, but Thailand, which is an important strategic<br />
consideration in the United States, they were very much concerned<br />
about the impact upon their rice production. I think the United<br />
States is going to have to look reasonably closely at this. I<br />
think in that area there probably is not the longer term<br />
problem. They say that is going to work out over the next<br />
12 months. There's not the same degree of longer term concern<br />
there as we're entitled to have in regard to the cereal products.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
