<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7129</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF THE AUSTRALIA LOCAL GOVERNMENT CENTRE CANBERRA - 26 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007129.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
USTRAL( 1
FWRME MWNSTER<br />
CHECK AGAINJT DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING W) THE AUSTRALIA LOCAL GOVERNMENT CENTRE<br />
CANBERRA 26 FEBRUARY 1987<br />
Sir Albert Abbott, National President of the Australian<br />
Council of Local Government Associations,<br />
Tomn Uren,<br />
Ladies and Gantlenen<br />
it has boen a long held objective of the Australian Council<br />
of Local Govornment Associations to have its own building in<br />
the National -Capital a bricks and mortar presence in<br />
Canberra which would both assist and highlight the<br />
increasingly prominent role Local Government is playing in<br />
Those who wor-ked to bring this project to fruition saw the<br />
need for Local Government to have a strong voice and a high<br />
profile in Canberra. They saw the need for Local Government<br />
to understand better the decision-making processes at the<br />
Federal level and to be better positioned to participate in<br />
national policy development.<br />
The fulfilner't of that objective has been made possible by<br />
the support of your State Associations, local councils and<br />
individuals. It has been a true co-operative effort and the<br />
result is ai credit to you all.<br />
So it is a pleasure to be here today to open officially this<br />
new Centre.<br />
I had the pleasure last August of presenting in Adelaide the<br />
first National Awards for Innovation an effort by the<br />
Commonwealth and your Council to strengthen Local Government<br />
by promoting and disseminating innovative techniques and<br />
approaches 1-y Local Government associations. </p>
<p>2.<br />
The awards symbolised the current close relationship between<br />
the Federal and Local tiers of government. indeed our<br />
relationship has never been closer than it has been in the<br />
four years since my Government came to office in March 1983.<br />
Your Council, Sir Albert, has played an important role in<br />
building and enhancing that relationship.<br />
We were the first Federal Government to appoint a Minister<br />
for Local Government and in Tom tUren you have had a<br />
formidable champion of your cause at the Commonwealth level.<br />
As well as his continuing efforts to help local government<br />
organisations improve the quality of their services, Tom has<br />
been a strong advocate of the constitutional recognition of<br />
Local Government, which would give formal and long overdue<br />
expression to the reality of Local Government participation<br />
in the Feciezation.<br />
The close : nilationship between Federal and Local Governments<br />
is based not just on the Commonwealth's recognition of your<br />
ability to deliver services and assist people at the grass<br />
roots levels throughout Australia.<br />
It is also firmly anchored in the knowledge that now, more<br />
than ever before, we need co-operation among the various<br />
levels of Government to meet effectively the economic and<br />
social challenges wie face as a nation.<br />
Increasing~ y we need a Local Government sector competent in<br />
the administration of local affairs and the design and<br />
delivery of community programs, as well as one which is<br />
responsivc in meeting broad national goals.<br />
Local Govcrnment is certainly proving its capacity to play a<br />
role in national policy making.<br />
The truth of that assertion is demonstrated by the<br />
contribution made by Local Government representatives at the<br />
National Economic Summit and the Taxation Summit, and by the<br />
continuing and valuable work performed by the Australian<br />
Council of Local Government Associations on the Economic<br />
Planning Advisory Council. we are grateful to you for the<br />
care and the thoughtfulness which typifies your work in<br />
these forumsn.<br />
At the local level, the productive relationship between our<br />
two levels of government takes tangible form in the<br />
thousands of buildings and projects and services we have<br />
created together.<br />
Under the Conmunity Employment Program, we have together<br />
helped many thousands of people, unemployed for long periods<br />
of time, find valuable work and develop new skills while<br />
contributing in a real way to their local community. </p>
<p>3.<br />
Under the Home and Community Care program we have together<br />
provided aged people throughout Australia with improved home<br />
care, in the belief that encouraging people to stay at home<br />
rather than seek institutional care not only provides a<br />
better life for the people themselves but is more economical<br />
for the nation as a whole.<br />
These examples can be multiplied elsewhere thanks to your<br />
contribution to programs for youth, housing, the<br />
environment, local and arterial roads, and the " Buy<br />
Australian" campaign, to mention just a few.<br />
on the central issue of revenues, my Government is committed<br />
to supportingj Local Government through the system of untied<br />
grants. Following the national Inquiry into Local<br />
Government Finance, and our consultation with the States and<br />
your National Council, we were able to improve that program<br />
and to creato the new Local Government Financial Assistance<br />
Act of 1986.<br />
The new act is significant in that it is the first piece of<br />
federal legislation to require Local Government to be<br />
consulted in determining the principles governing the<br />
distribution of funds.<br />
in view of the necessity for budgetary constraints in the<br />
current economic climate, that act provided a good and fair<br />
outcome for L. ocal Gov,, ernment.<br />
I made it clear earlier this week that Australia still faces<br />
considerable economic difficulties which will require all of<br />
us to practise continued restraint.<br />
The Government has decided that a May Expenditure Statement<br />
will be necessa~ ry to ensure that necessary savings can take<br />
effect over the full 1987-88 budgetary year.<br />
I have also put the States on notice that they, too, must<br />
accept further disciplines.<br />
In this current situation, restraint is required not just of<br />
the Commonwealth but of all levels of government for some<br />
time to come.<br />
I want to turn now to one of the key mechanisms we have<br />
developed for coordinating policies towards Local<br />
Government, namely the Local Government Ministers'<br />
Conference. Given the active involvement of your National Council in the<br />
research program sponsored by the conference, it is<br />
appropriate that I publicly launch today the first two<br />
products of that work.<br />
One report concerns the role of Local Government in the<br />
co-ordination and delivery of human services a field of<br />
activity in which Local Government is becoming increasingly<br />
involved. </p>
<p>The other report concerns the role of Local Government in<br />
economic development, drawing attention to the contribution<br />
to business and employment creation which Local Government<br />
is able to make.<br />
Both of these reports warrant serious examination at every<br />
level of Government. Accordingly, I have asked Tom Uren to<br />
consult his Ministerial colleagues and to arrange for the<br />
Office of Local Government to consult with the Australian<br />
Council of Lo,; al Government Associations, and also to seek<br />
responses fron relevant Departments, so that he can report<br />
to me on the implications of these reports for the<br />
Commonwealt: i.<br />
I am also p'. eased to learn that the Local Government<br />
Ministers have now turned their attention to a national<br />
review oE Local Government labour markets. The review is<br />
the first o-its kind, and is a significant initiative<br />
investigating a significant issue.<br />
These various initiatives demonstrate the partnership that<br />
is developing between our spheres of Government. We are<br />
witnessing, I believe, a historic transformation of<br />
inter-governmental relations in Australia.<br />
Now that you have consolidated your presence in Canberra<br />
with this new Centre I believe your involvement and<br />
influence in national administration will grow. So I have<br />
much pleasurc in officially opening the Australian Local<br />
Government Centre. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
