<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9211</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP HOUSE OR REPRESENTATIVES, 4 MAY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009211.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S<br />
PRIME MINMISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER. THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, 4 MAY 1994<br />
WORKING NATION The White Paper On Employment And Growth<br />
This White Paper reflects the collective concern of Australians and their collective<br />
ambition. Their concern for their fellow Australians, their ambition to make this a good<br />
society and a great and successfulI country.<br />
It is a statement about the two imperatives of a decent society compassion and strength.<br />
About the bonds which exist between all Australians and the premrium this country places<br />
on the talent and energy of every individual.<br />
It is about the desire to extend the safety net and basic services which expand equality of<br />
opportunity and go to make a truly civilised society and the ability to pay for them.<br />
This is a White Paper for the times we live in: an era of unprecedented change and equally<br />
unprecedented national opportunity.<br />
It is also an era in which hundreds of thousands of Australians, through no fault of their<br />
own, are bearing the burden of that change and are denied their share of opportunity.<br />
Unemploym~ ent is without question the greatest problem we face. Unemployment saps the<br />
confidence and self-esteem of our fellow Australians which in turn saps the nation's. It<br />
damages the social fabric.<br />
It has profound consequences for our social cohesion.<br />
As we have seen in other countries, ignored and neglected as a social problem, left to a<br />
fate to be decided solely by " market forces", unemployment threatens to create a<br />
permanent underclass.<br />
3! H. 12 </p>
<p>It threatens to create the conditions for social decay.<br />
We are not alone among nations in this it is endemic to the western developed countries.<br />
This government for one is determined to deal with the problem.<br />
I said on election night last year that we will not leave the unemployed behind. And I said<br />
on Australia Day this year that this recovery must be shared by us all. The White Paper I<br />
present to the House today delivers on those two commitments.<br />
But success won't come easily: with this White Paper we caninot say that the battle has<br />
been won, but we can say that it has been joined. And we sincerely hope not just by the<br />
Commonwealth Government. It has to be understood that success here depends upon all<br />
Australians joining the effort.<br />
That means business and trade unions and communities. It means all tiers of Goverrnent.<br />
If we do want to reach the point where we can say that every Australian who wants a job<br />
can have one, it will require a conscious and concerted national effort.<br />
So we don't say that this White Paper will wipe away the problem at a stroke, but we do<br />
say that Australia will not leave people neglected and forgotten.<br />
Through this document Australia says to those who are out of work: we believe you are<br />
entitled to the benefits of recovery and a chance to contribute to it.<br />
I~ f you don't have the appropriate skills, we'll help you get them.<br />
If you are young, we will see that you are trained.<br />
If you have been a long time out of work, we will offer you employment and training, if<br />
that is what you need.<br />
It says we will do all we can to help make you ready for a job.<br />
The means of giving concrete expression to our intentions constitute the most profound<br />
reform of Australia's labour market and social security provisions since World War 1I.<br />
The new provisions are tailored to meet the needs of the unemployed in the modemn<br />
Australian economy. They will serve Australia for many years.<br />
The White Paper is a statement of policy on employment and growth. It takes the view<br />
the incontestable view that economic growth is the key to employment growth.<br />
The evidence is very plainly there in this recovery we have already seen 230,000 new<br />
jobs created in the past twelve months. 93 1:. 3 </p>
<p>In ti<br />
That is why a substantial part of the White Paper addresses itself to the means by which corr.<br />
Australia can achieve higher levels of competitiveness. thos<br />
One of our great goals in these last years of the century must be economic efficiency, and The,<br />
the microeconomic reform and other measures descnibed in this Paper are no less Wh<br />
important than the training, labour market and social security reforms. The<br />
The Government believes that Australia can sustain or improve upon the present rate of wh(<br />
low inflation growth through to the end of the decade. doii the<br />
The period will be characterised by a continuation of the trend towards successful small<br />
and medium size enterprises producing sophisticated manufactures for export. It is<br />
con<br />
It will also see continued growth in sophisticated services. For<br />
Australian business and industry will need to be increasingly flexible, innovative and sub<br />
responsive to customer needs. Cer.<br />
It will need these qualities to succeed in the increasingly competitive markets of the world. woi<br />
As these companies grow, jobs will grow with them. But we know from the experience of The<br />
the eighties that very largely these new jobs will go to new entrants to the labour market une7<br />
and not to the long-term unemployed. une and<br />
As the Green Paper indicated, even with strong economnic growth, without intervention of<br />
the kind we have decided to undertake in this White Paper, by mid-1998 there would still 1ndi<br />
be some 290,000 people in the pool of long-term unemployed. We<br />
This is not only profoundly unfair, it is profoundly inefficient. It is a waste of our greatest unt<br />
resource the talent and energy of our people. To:<br />
Returning the long-term unemployed to the productive process of the nation not only pec<br />
returns them to the income, social interaction and creativity which work provides, it taps lite,<br />
their potential for the good of Australia. pre<br />
As the White Paper says, when we employ these otherwise wasted human resources we It i'<br />
are made stronger. yea<br />
Large numbers of long-term unemployed people demand large outlays on social security Thi<br />
and other assistance. pro<br />
Furthermore, having so many people effectively disqualified from the workforce reduces<br />
the efficiency of the labour market.<br />
59). 14 </p>
<p>In this recovery the complement to skill formation in the labour market is not going to<br />
come from migration. This time it has to come from training our own people, including<br />
those who are presently unemployed.<br />
The details of the Government's policy reforms are spelt out in the second volume of the<br />
White Paper.<br />
The measures l am announcing today will cost S1.7 billion in their first fll year. Those<br />
who may question the cost of these measures should ask themselves what are the costs of<br />
doing nothing. The cost of failing to introduce the major efficiency and equity benefits to<br />
the labour market, industry and the regions that this package describes.<br />
It is important to note that we have been able to accomplish these fundamental reforms<br />
consistent with our target of a deficit of around 1 per cent of GDP by 1996-97.<br />
For the information of Honourable Members, I will concentrate on only the most<br />
substantial of the new measures.<br />
Central to the Government's strategy for getting the long-term unemployed back into<br />
work is the Job Compact.<br />
The Job Compact puts new obligations on both the Government and those receiving<br />
unemployment benefits. The Government will provide to those who have been on<br />
unemployment benefits for eighteen months or more individual case management, trang<br />
and support and the offer of a job for six to twelve months.<br />
Individuals will be expected to take the job or lose their benefits.<br />
We will also introduce measures to identifyr people at risk of becoming long-term<br />
unemployed. Together with those who have been continuously unemployed for twelve months, these<br />
people will be given individual case management including remedial action in such areas as<br />
literacy, numeracy, language and vocational training and access to relevant labour market<br />
programs. It is expected that over half a million people will receive individual case management each<br />
year. This is a radical program, a qualitative change in'the way we approach labour market<br />
problems. 5915 </p>
<p>The objective is to make long-term unemployed people ready for a job, and break forever It " n<br />
the pattern in which the long-term unemployed become steadily more dispirited and advan<br />
unqualified for employment, while employers become steadily less inclined to consider of o0:<br />
them employable. It iso0<br />
In other words, the purpose of the Job Compact is principally to see that a substantial<br />
proportion of the new jobs in the recovery go to long-term unemployed Australians. In the<br />
schoc<br />
A new Training Wage will be introduced to provide employers with extra incentives to for th<br />
hire long-term unemployed workers and invest in their training. 95 pe<br />
aTwhea rtdr awinaingeg wwaillg eb ee ndcisocuoruagnetesd efmorp laocycerresd titoe dp rtoraviindien gtr aainndin tgh ep leamcepsl oiyne trw woi lwl areysc. e ivTeh ea Tuet%<br />
wage subsidy from the Government at a level above what it would be if no training were<br />
involved. This represents a substantial incentive for employers to play their part in the Thet<br />
national effort. no<br />
An in-principle agreement on the Training Wage has been reached with a high-level ACTUJ<br />
committee which will be recommending its adoption to the ACTU Executive. The Seco<br />
Government will also be consulting with employers on the details of the training wage. younE<br />
To deliver case management and job placement services, the Government will radically And f<br />
change the labour market by engaging community and private sector agencies. for ui<br />
the ur<br />
Job seekers will have a choice between these and the CES, with the competition between The p<br />
them regulated and encouraged by a new authority the Employment Service Regulatory<br />
Agency ( ESRA).<br />
The CES will be revitalised to meet the greater responsibilities placed upon it by the Job<br />
Compact and other initiatives.<br />
Additional resources, extra training of staff, external recruitment and improved<br />
information technology will be brought to the operations of the Service.<br />
The emphasis will be on closer relations with employers, greater skills and efficient<br />
delivery through more sophisticated technology and coordination.<br />
For instance, job boards and job cards in CES offices will be replaced with computerised Unde<br />
vacancy systems featuring user-friendly le-cliftology to encourage self-help job searches. Aiistri<br />
the Jc<br />
As the White Paper says, we are never going to return to a world where large numbers of<br />
full-time jobs are available for unskilled young workers. As the keys to a successful Ines<br />
modern economy are skills, ideas and innovation, the keys to employment are education can rr<br />
and training.<br />
~ 591I6 </p>
<p>It cannot be stressed too much in the modemn economy skills are our greatest competitive<br />
advantage. Whether it is in global enterprises or local small businesses, it is on the ability<br />
of our people to add value that our standard of living depends.<br />
It is on skills that every individual's standard of living increasingly depends.<br />
In the past decade, the number of young people completing Year 12 or an initial postschool<br />
qualification has dramatically increased. However we are still below the average<br />
for the ' OECD and well short of the goal that all Australian Governments have set namely<br />
per cent of 19 year olds by 200 1.<br />
The White Paper describes the Government's program for building the skills of young<br />
Australians. T'he three principal elements of new Government policy are: first, the Government aims to<br />
encourage young people to stay in education and training by giving them appropriate<br />
financial support and more relevant courses run jointly by schools and industry.<br />
Second, we will be increasing the number and range of entry level training places for<br />
young people by an estimated 50,000 by 1995-96.<br />
And thirdly, we will be introducing as a major policy change a Youth Training Initiative<br />
for unemployed young people. The key to success is to provide help at an early stage in<br />
the unemployment cycle, which means with the least possible delay after leaving school.<br />
The principal features of the Youth Training Initiative are:<br />
intensive case management, with an initial assessment of skills and knowledge, for<br />
all unemployed people under the age of eighteen<br />
a doubling of the number of labour market and vocational training places for young<br />
people assistance in finding a job, and<br />
reformed income support arrangements to help keep young people in education or<br />
training.<br />
Under the Youth Training Initiative in the clearest possible signal that every young<br />
Australian should be in education, training or employment unemployment benefits or<br />
the Job Search Allowance will be replaced by a Youth Training Allowance.<br />
Investing in skills of Australians, particularly young Australians, is the best investment we<br />
can make. This is recognised well beyond the realms of Government. 59) 17 </p>
<p>Industry is increasingly recognlsing it and increasingly indicating its desire to play a part. In an<br />
We are very well aware of industry's concerns about the relevance of current training and inder<br />
for this reason we are anxious to engage industry in both the design and delivery of child<br />
courses. P The<br />
In future, Australian vocational training will be available through traineeships based in oblic<br />
schools, TAFE, industry and labour market programs and will be available to adults as<br />
well. Ther with<br />
A Training Wage which offers a much simpler alternative to the multiple industry-specific will I<br />
rates currently applying will be available to employers who provide entry-level training. The.<br />
The social safety net was a term first used in the 1 940s by Ben Chilley. He thought of it peop<br />
as the net under a trapeze artist, " to break the fall towards aestitution and sustain a man<br />
and his family while they help him climb the ladder of opportunity again". In thi<br />
worl,<br />
The basic principle of the safety net remains the same and so does the basic necessity in a cons,<br />
decent society to maintain it. But circumstances have changed and so must the way we<br />
design the net. The most fundamental difference is that no longer do families depend on If we<br />
the man alone to bring in the income, at ris.<br />
out c<br />
In general, the present social security system continues to assume that only one member of<br />
a couple, in most cases thie husband, will be actively looking for work while the other will The<br />
be a dependant. new<br />
This ignores the increase in employment for women. It means that unemployed couples If we<br />
have not been encouraged to take advantage of the opportunities in the labour market, our T<br />
flour<br />
Over the last ten years, the gap between income support for a married couple and income<br />
from lower paid jobs has also narrowed and the incentive to find work has been greatly As tldiminished.<br />
Austbuild<br />
In another basic structural reform of our income support system young unemployed<br />
couples without children will need to qualify for unemployment payments in their own Thiret<br />
right and the joint income test for unemployed couples will be abolished. The effect of time!<br />
this will be to encourage both partners to seek work. It also means that many low income Coin<br />
working families will gain extra income support. The<br />
Under the current social security income test, after a modest level of income, for every differ<br />
dollar of income earned, a dollar of income support is lost. From July next year the dollarfor-<br />
dollar taper will be replaced with a 70 cents in the dollar taper which will mean that The<br />
people will always be better off from working because work will always increase their appr(<br />
total income. thenr<br />
59~ ' 18 </p>
<p>In another radical initiative,. a Parenting Allowance will be introduced to provide an<br />
independent source of income for parents in low income families who care for dependant<br />
children under 16 years of age.<br />
The Parenting Allowance will effectively provide a payment for one parent free of any<br />
obligation to seek work.<br />
There will also be a more generous income test for those who wish to combine parenting<br />
with paid work. By any measure. ths is a major reform. The simplest measure is this it<br />
I will mean an extra S59 per week on average for nearly 120,000 low income families.<br />
The Parenting Allowance signals a new approach to income support based on the right of<br />
people to be paid as individuals, rather than as dependent partners.<br />
In this, and in the fact that it constitutes greater recognition of women's role in the<br />
workforce and the growth in part-time and casual employment, the Parenting Allowance is<br />
consistent with the changes to income testing.<br />
If we do not take remedial action, the long-term unemployed and many young Australians<br />
at risk of joining their ranks will be relegated to the margins of our national life and miss<br />
out on the opportunities offered by the present recovery.<br />
The same can be said of many of the regions of Australia. The White Paper presents a<br />
new Commuonwealth approach to regional development.<br />
If we are to make the most of all our national resources, including the skills and energy of<br />
our people, we need to ensure that the regions of Australia are given the opportunity to<br />
flourish that they become partners in Australia's growth.<br />
As the White Paper says, to neglect the regions is to neglect not only a great many<br />
Australians and all that they have to give this country, but to pass up the opportunity to<br />
build a stronger and more diverse economy.<br />
Three reports on regional development have been received by the Government in recent<br />
times the Kelty Taskforce Report, the McKinsey Report and the Report of the Industry<br />
Commission. The principal lessons to be learned are that the regions, though presently enjoying very<br />
different degrees of success, have in common an abundance of energy and commitment.<br />
The Government takes the view, with Kelty and McKinsey, that the most effective<br />
approach for the Commonwealth is to provide strategic assistance of a kind that will help<br />
the regions to make the most of their human and physical resources. 5919 </p>
<p>More often than not, this will require them to integrate their local economies with the The<br />
national and international economy. depi<br />
wor<br />
The White Paper instances some remarkable achievements and some other places where<br />
major obstacles have yet to be overcome. The uneven performance of our regions in large For<br />
part flows from an uneven quality of organisation and leadership. In st<br />
The White Paper details the way in which the Commonwealth Government will support and<br />
the formation and functioning of regional groupings and provide assistance to regions so<br />
that they can develop and implement effective strategic plans, with an emphasis on We<br />
international best practice. the culti<br />
We will also be significantly modifyng the tax treatment of infrastructure bonds and takdig man<br />
other steps to encourage private sector investment in regional Australia. and<br />
We will also provide funds for capital works where it can be demonstrated that their Thei<br />
completion is vital to local economic performance. be a<br />
The White Paper nominates two regional development projects the Government will The,<br />
support which may be taken as models for other regions in Australia. whiu<br />
The Goulburn Valley and the Sunraysia have developed plans for ecologically sustainable, The<br />
highlyi productive, self-funding, irrigated agriculture which will repair the environment and Pol<br />
greatly increase the contribution t~ o GDP the Sunraysia is expected to double output in<br />
the next two decades. The<br />
year<br />
The Government will provide funding for essential capital works projects and support for Ausi<br />
re-structnrng through the Rural Adjustment Scheme. the on i<br />
I will be going to the Sunraysia on Friday to see first hand the proposed projects and meet<br />
with some of the region's leaders. It de<br />
It should be noted also that reforms to the labour market, education and training and The<br />
social security contain provisions for programs which will be specifically tailored to and<br />
regional needs. our then<br />
In addition, some sixty DEET Area Consultative Committees will be created and they will<br />
seek to establish direct links with successful regional development organisations. The Thei<br />
Consultative Commiittees will include employers, local and state government effic<br />
representatives and education and training providers. finaz busii<br />
Just as it is essential that we do not allow the long-term unemployed to become cut off Trai<br />
from the mainstream of society, it is equally important that we take steps to see that<br />
regions of Australia are not left to drift out of the nation's economic and social life. </p>
<p>These reforms and initiatives necessarily depend on continuing economic growth. They<br />
depend on the ability of Australian enterprise to flourish and carve out a future in the<br />
world economy and especially the Asia-Pacific.<br />
For that reason the White Paper contains a statement of the Government's industry policy.<br />
In summary, the thrust of Government policy is towards eiobalisation. competitiveness<br />
and productivity.<br />
We are seeing major success from measures already taken. a dramatic increase in exports.<br />
the rise of dynamic small and medium-sized businesses which have been born of the export'<br />
culture developed in'the last decade " born global" in other words the growth of<br />
manufactured exports to rank now with agriculture and mnining as a proportion of GDP<br />
and the rapid growth in exports of sophisticated manufactures.<br />
There is no question that our policies, including our tariff policy, are enabling Australia to<br />
be a competitive player in the regional and world econiomy.-<br />
There is equally no question that we have no choice but to continue the process of reform<br />
which alone will keep us in the race.<br />
The White Paper contains a broad statement of the principles governing our industry<br />
policy and a number of specific measures consistent with those principles.<br />
The process of microeconomic reform, will continue. A consistent goal of the next few<br />
years must be economic efficiency. The principles of " best practice" which many<br />
Australian companies have adopted, must be adopted by the nation itself. In this, as in all<br />
the measures described in this White Paper, much depends on other tiers of goverrnent,<br />
on trade unions, business, communities, the people of Australia themselves.<br />
It demands a continuation of the great cultural shift which has occurred in the past decade.<br />
The Government sees its proper role as creating a competitive environment for industry<br />
and by strategic intervention, helping to create competitive companies. As the Paper says,<br />
our policy must be to harness the power of markets, while recognising that, left to<br />
themselves, markets will not always give us the best possible results.<br />
There are measures described in this White Paper to remove impediments to business<br />
efficiency, to facilitate exports, to encourage research and development, to make access to<br />
finance for small and medium-sized business easier, to remove regulation and lower<br />
business costs and among the latter, the White Paper announces the suspension of the<br />
Training Guarantee. 5921 </p>
<p>One significant initiative will be the establishment of a body to improve coordination and Just<br />
delivery of government programs for business. The body, to be called Ausindustry, will gove<br />
be within the portfolio of the Minister for Industry, Science and Technol'ogy and ' Ill be the . i<br />
guided by a board comprising people with experience in all aspects of business, from ways<br />
research and development to international trade. This<br />
The establishment of AusIndustry is a direct response to two recent studies by McKinsey<br />
which found that business was often confused about the ranee of services available under Thes<br />
government programs. deca Aust<br />
Our success will also depend on the capacity and willingness of Australians to strike worl<br />
productivity bargains in the nation's workplaces. It WC<br />
The Industial Relations Reform Act introduced last year provides the framework for this we h<br />
process to rapidly proceed. Much now depends on the willingness of employers and once<br />
employees to strike the kinds of bargains which will be mutually rewarding to them, and<br />
rewarding also to Australia's economic future. It WC<br />
the v<br />
We have seen in a very short time a sea-change not just in the shape of the Australian<br />
economy, not just in its orientation and in the way we do business, but in the way we think That<br />
about our business practice. We understand both the need for, and the principles of,<br />
competitiveness. We understand the need for cooperation in the workplace. We It is,<br />
understand the need for ' skills and creativity. We know that we must be a nation which Govc<br />
makes things and sells things in the international markets of the world.<br />
We know these things principally because we know that not to do them will mean to fail<br />
as a nation. It will mean a lower standard of living for this and future generations.<br />
The major reforms announced in this White Paper should be seen in this context.<br />
We do not accept that we can raise the standard of living of Australians by allowing a<br />
large number of people to drift permanently out of the system. We do not accept that we<br />
can afford to waste their potential. Nor do we accept that the only way to maintain our<br />
standard of living is to lower the wages of Australian workers.<br />
The White Paper is underpinned by the belief that Australia must and can be a gjkwage<br />
and a high productivity country.<br />
A hundred years ago, the Australian colonies federated into a nation which numbered<br />
among its watchwords " the social laboratory of the world". The Australia of a hundred<br />
years ago prided itself on advanced social policy.<br />
59 22 </p>
<p>12<br />
id Just fifty years ago, with the White Paper on full employment, another Australian Labor<br />
, I govern. ment codified and consolidated social policies which together formed the basis of<br />
e the Australian social welfare system. That was a document of its times in some essential<br />
ways, a much more modest document than this one.<br />
This White Paper is a document for these times.<br />
er These social programs. together with those introduced in recent years. mean that in this<br />
decade we should take pride in the fact that, faithful to previous generations of<br />
Australians, we have made this one of the most sophisticated social democracies in the<br />
world. It would be no bad thing if, in this decade, we also developed pride in the great changes<br />
Ms we have made to our economy. We should be proud that we now compete in areas we<br />
once thought beyond our capacity.<br />
It would be a very good thing if, at the end of the century, we defined ourselves as one of<br />
the very fair societies in the world and one of the most creative.<br />
tink That is the philosophy which underlies this White Paper.<br />
It is a program for employment and growth. It underlies all the policies of this<br />
Government.<br />
ye 5.923 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
