<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3642</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL WOMEN&#039;S YEAR - 7 MARCH 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003642.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT NO. 462<br />
7 March 1975<br />
INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S YEAR<br />
The Prime Minister will give the opening address at<br />
an International Women's Day reception to be held in Melbourne<br />
tomorrow night.<br />
The function will begin at 7.30 p. m. in the Melbourne<br />
Custom House Ballrocm.<br />
It is in honour of Victorian women pioneers in many<br />
fields of endeavour formerly the province of men.<br />
They include Dr J. Daws, first woman President-elect<br />
of the Ms N. Preston, first woman bus conductor;<br />
Rev. C. Ling,. first woman ordained in Methodist Church and Rev.<br />
M. Thalheiver, first woman ordained in Presbyterian Church;<br />
Ms A. Polis, first woman editor of a suburban newspaper;<br />
Ms K. Polgrase, first woman apprentice motor-mechanic and Ms<br />
K. Perrin, first woman Governor of Fairlea Women's Prison.<br />
A full list of notable Victorian women " firsts" is<br />
available from the P. M.' s Press Office.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. J)&gt; AU ST L A.&amp; </p>
<p>NAES OF FIRSTS<br />
DAY CELEBRATION TO<br />
I<br />
DR. LORNA SISLEY:<br />
( 24-6860)<br />
Dr. J. Dgws<br />
Miss M. Maxwell<br />
Ms. A. Polis<br />
( 419-3037)<br />
Ms. N. Findley<br />
( 58-4659) ( h) MEDI CAL<br />
1st woman to be admitted as a Fello7of the Rojal Australasion<br />
College of Surgeons as a general Surgeon in Victoria.<br />
1st. and only wvoman to be awarded Craig Travelling Scholarship<br />
of Royal Australian College of Surgeons. Only woman member<br />
of Urological Society of Australasia. Now Senior Surgeon of<br />
Queen Victoria Hospital.<br />
1st. woman President-elect Aust. Medical Association<br />
PRESbS ( cannot attend-sending message<br />
1st ' Women's Section Editor Melbourne Herald ( 98 years old -crippled)<br />
Ist. Women Editor Suburban Newspaper ( Melbourne Times)<br />
EDUCATION<br />
1st woman Fullbright Scholarship award in Victoria most likely<br />
Australia, Now Principal Emily McPherson School of Domestic<br />
Economy.<br />
Dr. E. MESSER First Ph. d. Now employed Dept of Labour Librarian.<br />
( 63-0361) 96-5624 ( h)<br />
Ms. K. Grant-Stevenson lsot~. Pincipal Co-od :; condcry School (-o-ing~ rteed High School.)<br />
( 328-1796)<br />
Ms. T. Prior<br />
Ms. Y. Smith<br />
Ms. D. Sonenberg<br />
-r ( 38-5056) ( h)<br />
Ms. M. Tipping<br />
( 24.7133) ( h)<br />
Ms. A. New/ ton<br />
Ms. N. Preston<br />
( 29-6485)<br />
Ms. A. Morton<br />
Ms. N. Ouens<br />
Ms. M. Henderson<br />
Ms. M. Pegan<br />
( 42-4368) ( h) INDUSTRIAL<br />
Shop Steward I. C. I. for 26 years.<br />
1st Claims Officer Butchers Union only one known in Vio.<br />
1st woman Secretary Insurance Staff Association, only one knomw<br />
Vic.<br />
Isyfersonell Officer Cyclone Factory 1950' s<br />
Ist./ v0ce-nPres, then Pres. Royal Historical Society ( Vio.)<br />
1st. Woman Conductor Trams ( prefer no interviews)<br />
1st. \ oman Conductor ( Buses)<br />
1st, woman bus cleaner Fitzroy Depot<br />
Ist, woman timber worker still employed Bruthen Vi.,<br />
1st woman Concrete Technologist<br />
1st woman Overhead Electrical Crane Driver<br />
Ms. G. ', 1fitelaw<br />
( 57-4472)<br />
Ms. K. Polgrase APP R E N T I C ES<br />
1st woman apprentice-gardener Melb. City Council<br />
1st woman apprentice motor mechanic John Oulc' Motors<br />
1st woman apprentice State Electricity Commission ( Morwell)<br />
C HU R C H<br />
CHURCH<br />
SRev. C. Ling st woman to be ordained in Methodist Church ( Buckley Sto Methodist Ch.<br />
Rev. M. Thalheirer 1st woman to be ordained in Presbyterian Church ( The Manse Romsey)<br />
Ms. Ms. G. Brobner<br />
Ms. ( 874-5584) GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENT ( Police)<br />
1st woman to be appointed to C. I. B.<br />
errin ist. omar. Governor ' Fairlea Women's Prison. Foni.; rly Matron<br />
V~ inff^^-<br />
in numerous fields for PRESS RELEASE INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S<br />
BE HELD CUSTOM HOUSE BALLROOM-MARCH 8th, at 7.30 pn.<br />
F<br />
Us. K. P </p>
<p>-2-<br />
NAMES OF 1OMEN FLRSTS PRESS RELEASE TTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S DAY CELEBRATION<br />
CUSTOM HOUSE BALLROOM MARCH 8th 7.30 pm,<br />
Mu. F.,-Eduwards<br />
Ms. C. Ball<br />
( 836-6578)<br />
Ms. I. Lics<br />
Ms. P. Perry<br />
( 36-1565)<br />
Ms. I. Plo\ man<br />
Ms. D. M. Brady<br />
( 93-1631)<br />
Ms. E. M. Tracy<br />
( 29-4926)<br />
Sister Burcholl<br />
( 878-8746)<br />
Ms. Z. D'aprano<br />
( 387-2318)<br />
Ms. M. Doring<br />
( 86-5462)<br />
Cr. N. Barbour<br />
( 90-2000)<br />
Ms. J. Bates<br />
( 81-4612) MI SC ELLANE US<br />
Groat Granduughtor of Miru. E. Davis the first Registrar of Births,<br />
Marriages Deaths in Melbourne offico was in kew. Mrs. Davis<br />
was also in Royal Socioty of St. Georgo.<br />
lot woman to be granted a liquor licence for a grocery business<br />
( although married)<br />
1st wom, n to open a Gent's Hairdressing salon Melb. ( 18 yrs, ago)<br />
1st woman to open a Theatrical Agency still in business,<br />
Woman Cyclist rode Sydney to Melbourne 1938 beat the then<br />
best male cyclist Hubert Opperman on the Razor Back stretch.<br />
1st woman Commercial Traveller employod by large firm.<br />
1st woman in Melbourne to be employed selling radio sets<br />
1932. 1st woman Australian Inland Mission wrote book ' Imamincka' is<br />
now in its 5th edition and translated into Braille-all proceeds<br />
from book goes to ' Homes for the Aged Darwin'.<br />
1st woman in Melbourne to chain hebself tothe ralings at the<br />
Arbitration in protost re their Judgement in equal pay case<br />
Later chained herself to Commonwealth Building in same cause.<br />
1st women Building Student R. M. I. T. Working at present on a<br />
Building site full time necessary to work 2 years on site to<br />
receive Diploma.<br />
24 years as a Councillor<br />
1st woman ' Hansard Writer for Victorian Parliament still<br />
employed. Organisations to be represented<br />
Women's Christian Temperance Union<br />
Housewives Association<br />
League of Women Voters<br />
Girl Guides Association<br />
Women's International League for Peace<br />
Women's Health Collective<br />
Abortion Contraceptive Advisory Centre<br />
Council for Aboriginal Rights<br />
Victorian Council for Aboriginal Island<br />
Victorian Aboriginal Advancement League<br />
Women's Electoral Lobby<br />
National Council of Women<br />
South Melbourne Community Chest<br />
Rape Crisis Centre<br />
Half-way House for Women<br />
Union of Australian Women<br />
Country Women's Association<br />
Women's Centre ( Melbourne)<br />
Unitarian Church C'ttee.<br />
Colinail for Single Mother Child ( as guests)<br />
Unions<br />
Tramway's Union, Butcher's Union<br />
Aust. Metal Workers Union<br />
Postal Workers Union<br />
Freedom Furnishing Trades Union<br />
Liquor Trades Union<br />
Plumber's Union<br />
I Women Clothing Trades Union<br />
Gippsland Trades Labour Council<br />
Australian Railways Union<br />
Miscellaneous Workers Union </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
