<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2434</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIES DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION - ANNUAL MEETING - SYDNEY - 21 JUNE 1971 - SPEECH NOTES FOR THE PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002434.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IZ<br />
AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRIES DEVELOPMENT' 1 ASSOCIATION<br />
ANNUAL MEETING -SYDNEY 21 JUNE 1971<br />
Speech Notes for the Prime Minister<br />
Mr. President, Gentlemen,<br />
I have, Sir, glanced through your annual report with interest ar~ d I recognise<br />
the frank way you have put forward the writer's views.<br />
There are some statements with which L don't altog~ ether agree. There<br />
are others I prefer not to comment on because it is getting too close to Budget time.<br />
And some I am in complete agreement'<br />
I must first confess as a basic assumption that the Government recogn~ ises the<br />
importance of manufacturing industries to the* Australian economy or to put it<br />
another way it is vital to have goods" made in Australia", by Australians, for the<br />
Australian people and for export.<br />
I wo uld like to see private enterprise pushing ever so much more strenuously<br />
its " made in Australia" campaigns.<br />
Your industries are a key segment and a large one in our industrialised<br />
society because of the employment they create,<br />
the domestic and export needs they satisfy and<br />
the growth elements they provide.<br />
Simply because of your remark able diversity you don't have a single image<br />
like our rural industries or a glamorous one like minerals. Yet your diversity is<br />
your strength and it brings in a tremendous range of technical skills and industrial<br />
" know-how". I urge you to give away too much introspecion and not to accept the notion<br />
that you are some kind of a cinderella in our industrialised society. The Government<br />
doesn't think so and is giving close attention to the special interests which are<br />
mentioned in your Report. And I know too, from nersonal discussions, that many of<br />
you don't think this way. On the contrary, you are optimists and rightly proud of your<br />
own industries and your performances.<br />
It is true that, despite our current problems inflation, industrial strife<br />
and the rural crisis our national prosperity has -increased in the past year. And it<br />
might have been greater had there been more voluntary restraints by all parties to the<br />
labour contract. A lot will depend on how industry and organised labour respond to the<br />
call for price and wage restraint from now on and what contribution they make to<br />
industrial stability.<br />
The Government's Aims<br />
I not Mr. President, that A. I. D. A. thinks the country might have done </p>
<p>better in the past year if our national aims had been more clearly defined and more<br />
directly pursued. It is a statement that is easy to make but which I find difficult to sustain. The<br />
Government's aims are clear enough. Let me summarise them in the briefest way I<br />
can. We believe in our national security and that we should take a<br />
responsible place in our geographical region and in world affairs.<br />
We want growth and progress, with a balanced economy. In a<br />
diversified and industrialised society.<br />
We stand for progressive social welfare policies, an educated<br />
people and the right of the individual to the basic freedoms and<br />
a good life.<br />
We stand for minimum interference by Government in the free<br />
workings of private enterprise.<br />
I believe we are pursuing these objectives with vigour. But Governments<br />
must not over-order the affairs of it's citizens and industries.<br />
May I sound a note of caution about too much Government direction and<br />
too much dependence on Government by industry. This would send us all high-stepping<br />
down the socialist road. Believe me, that road does run downhill..<br />
At a time like this, when everybody has to accept some restraints and perhaps<br />
modify some expansion plans it is tempting to agree on the need for sacrifice and then<br />
expect the other fellow to do all the sac riificing.<br />
, The Commonwealth Government accepts its fundamental responsibilities.<br />
The first of these is to make the Federal system work effectively in the interests of<br />
all Australians. It has to give leadership. It also has to accept primary responsibilities<br />
in matters like defence, trade and national economic management.<br />
But it cannot be exclusive in the discharge of those responsibilities. It must<br />
and I believe it does recognise the cardinal importance of co-operation with the<br />
States, and co-operation with business and industry in all its forms.<br />
I have not long come from the Premiers' Conference in Canberra where we<br />
settled on a growth tax. We offered the States pay-roll tax which they accepted, and<br />
made other financial arrangements generally acceptable to them.<br />
Nothing is perfect in an imperfect world, populated, as it is, by human<br />
beings instead of supermen. But we have, I believe, broken with an unhappy spat in<br />
Commonwealth-State financial matters by agreeing on this growth tax which will<br />
give the States more revenue-raising rights directly geared to growth.<br />
I am the first to acknowledge that a final solution to Commonwealth-State<br />
financial relationships may perhaps lie in a review of the Constitution. But let us take<br />
one step at a time through this difficult maze. ./ 3 </p>
<p>And let us remember that many of those who say " change the Constitution"<br />
don't say what changes they want or suggest how the voting public can be persuaded<br />
from their traditional habit of voting " no" when it comes to issues of this kind.<br />
What I am doing is to underline the fact that Constitutional review is a<br />
difficult and lengthy business and wouldn't help us with our immediate problems.<br />
As I have said before I think the long-term outlook for Australia is still<br />
healthy and soundly-based but the current problem of inflation is still pressing<br />
heavily upon us.<br />
I made this clear I think, at the Premiers' Conference last week and I<br />
won't go over the ground again other than to say the need for restraints in both the<br />
public and private sectors and particularly in the public sector continues to be<br />
great. Tariffs The subject I want to talk most about today, is however tariff policy.<br />
Mr. President, your report refers to tariffs and to the statement recently<br />
made in Parliament by my colleague, Mr. Anthony. There are three points on which<br />
I want to comment. They are<br />
Your request for more information about protection.<br />
Your request for a more positive approach in the conduct of<br />
the tariff review.<br />
Your request for a clearer expression of the Government's tariff policy.<br />
I agreed that there is a need for much more -information in some Tariff<br />
Board reports about the effect on individual manufacturers and industries, and<br />
) n the economy as a whole.<br />
I think the demands which your organisation and others in the communityare<br />
making for more information about protection is quite justifiable. That the<br />
demands are now being made is evidence, I think, of a growing awareness in the<br />
nousiness community of the many direct and indirect ef. Lfects of protection.<br />
More and more businessmen are properly asking that decisions by the<br />
Government to change levels of protection should not be made without more knowledge<br />
of their likely effects.<br />
Both the Government and the Tariff Board appreciate the need for more<br />
information about protection. Mr. Anthony took Up this point in his recent statement<br />
on tariff policy, in Parliament. " The Government" he said, " needs as clear advice<br />
as the Tariff Board can give in its reports to enable the Government to reach<br />
judgements on the likely consequences of implementing the Board's recommendations".<br />
The Tariff Board also has said that more information about protection<br />
is essential if it is to do a proper job. I am informed by the Chairman, Mr. Rattigan,<br />
that the Board has already taken steps to get this information. For example </p>
<p>It is about to un~ dertake demand, supply and inter-industry studies<br />
to assist in estimating, how the domestic production of particular<br />
commodities is likely to be effected by changres in their tariffs.<br />
It is assisting in a project being undertaken at Monash University<br />
to study the longer term effects of protection on the economy.<br />
Itis collecting data on the profitability and capital structure of<br />
Australian manufacturing industries to enable it to assess trends<br />
in the financial performance of protected industries.<br />
It has acted to improve the data it gets on imports by increasing<br />
the detail on individual shipments and covering more shipments.<br />
Now facts and statistics cannot be manufactured overnight and the Board's<br />
timetable depends to some extent on the rate at which the data becomes available from<br />
the Statistician. However, the Board has already compiled and published a good deal of<br />
new information about the structure of protection in Australia and it has begun to<br />
recruit the specialised staff needed to complete the job.<br />
I turn now to another aspect of tariff policy, Mr. Chairman. You have<br />
expressed some anxiety about inadequate provision in the Tariff Board's review for<br />
'~ positive action to encourage desirable new industries".<br />
This anxiety is based, I gather, on the idea that the review will deal only<br />
with existing industries and also on the idea that it may result in more decreases than<br />
increases in tariffs. You are worrying unduly.<br />
While I think that a number of very difficult practical problems would arise<br />
if the Government attempted to review industries which did not exist in Australia,<br />
this is not to say that protection can never be afforded products in advance . of their<br />
local manufacture. But I also think it is right that consideration of such a question would be best<br />
made after an intending manufacturer had studied the feasibility of manufacturing in<br />
Australia and was able to provide useful data at the Tariff Board inquiry.<br />
Now Sir, most of the public discussion on the tariff review has been about<br />
what might happen to highly-protected industries. Little has been said about the<br />
Board's declared attitude to industries needing less protection.<br />
I think the phrase " destructive selectivity" as used in your Report doesn't<br />
put the Government's or the Board's attitudes either accurately or fairly.<br />
It should be noted, Mr. President, that the Tariff Board has said in a number<br />
of its annual reports that positive encouragement should be given to manufacturing<br />
industries requiring only low rates or protection. Every industry even the most<br />
highly-protected contains some activities requiring only low rates of protection.<br />
Thus if the review of a highly -pr;-; otect ed industry pro duces some duty<br />
changes which you could regard as negative it should also produce some duty<br />
changes which you could regard as positive. </p>
<p>In fact, of course, the removal of unnecessary protection in those cases<br />
where tariffs are higher than needed to protect local production of the goods concerned<br />
also has quite positive and beneficial effects on the industries which use the goods as<br />
inputs in their own production.<br />
it makes their costs, and the prices of their own outputs, more competitive<br />
without jeopardising the competitive position of the protected inputs producing industry.<br />
I don't think the view will be contested that consequences of this type, which<br />
may be expected to flow from the systematic review, would be viewed as doing anything<br />
else than benefiting not only using industries but the economy as a whole.<br />
I was surprised, Mr. President, at your comment that, even after<br />
Mr. Anthony's recent statement in Parliament, investment decision makers are<br />
' still without a clear expression of Government policy and are confused as to the<br />
circumstances under which tariff protection might be anticipated.'<br />
Investment decision makers must now have a clearer idea of the<br />
Government's tariff policy than they did several years ago before the Government<br />
had indicated its general attitude towards the Tariff Board's proposals, or before<br />
the proposals had even been made.<br />
As you know, the Board has said that it will probably-but not necessarily.-<br />
recommend that activities requiring high r ; ates of protection will be discouraged, and<br />
that those requiring low rates of protection will be encouraged.<br />
It has, furthermore, defined what it means by high and low rates of protection.<br />
Investment decision makers who can estimate the protection which their proposed<br />
activities will require thus have a clearer indication -now than in the past of the<br />
likely attitudes which the Tariff Board will adopt towards those activities.<br />
To give you an even clearer expression of Tariff policy one that will<br />
allow accurate predictions of the amount of protection which particular activities<br />
could expect would involve one of two things<br />
Either the adoption of the B oard's points off reference<br />
as the sole criteria for making tariff changes<br />
OR<br />
( II) The production of an unvarying list of other factors<br />
t o be taken into account, whose relative sig-nif icance<br />
would be fixed for every inquiry.<br />
1. th-ink you will agree that the first alternative is unacceptable.<br />
And for that matter so is the second. I base my comment on what you said<br />
in the A. I. D. A. bulletin of May last year, when you listed the " circumstances to<br />
be reported on by the Tariff Board".<br />
You -then said that your own list was not a total list and that the Tariff<br />
Board should be obliged to examine any " other relevant circumstance not listed". </p>
<p>6.<br />
Succinctly put you want flexibility and so do we. To be completely<br />
definitive or much more precise than we have been would mean being inflexible.<br />
Mr. Pr esident, I have spoken long enough but I thought it proper to let<br />
you know the Government's view on tariffs and to tell you what the Trriff Board<br />
is doing to develop its expertise. I have mentioned a number of points from your<br />
report and I hope I have removed most of your fears.<br />
I f you hadn't taken the line you did with such positive crit icism I would<br />
have had no case to put. But there it is I have put it and I hope what I have, said<br />
is helpful. The Government wants the confidence of its manufacLuring industries.<br />
It knows their value and is anxious that they should continue to prosper. This is<br />
a time when frankness and confidence must go together and this way I believe<br />
lies success. Thank you, Mr. President. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
