<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>526</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, RT. HON. R G MENZIES, ON THE BBC ON 4TH JUNE 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000526.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEXT OF TELEVISION INTERVIEW GITLN BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISITR, RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES, ON<br />
B. B. C. on 4TH JUNE 162<br />
Mr. Robin Day: Mr. Menzies, we've read about your strong reaction on<br />
Saturday to the agreement which was reached in Brussels,<br />
whereby Britain would gradually do away with the<br />
Commonwealth preferences on manufactured goods from<br />
Australia and other Commonwealth countries. Now why were<br />
you so disturbed about an agreement which affects only<br />
about 2 per cent. of Australian exports to the United<br />
Kingdom?<br />
Prime Minister: Well of course the effect of it depends entirely on<br />
how many more agreements there are to come. Because it<br />
will be the cumulative effect of these things which will<br />
be important, in the long run. Now this first one, as<br />
you rightly say bore on a relatively small amount of<br />
trade from Australia, much more of course from Canada.<br />
But when it was announced as an agreement, this at once<br />
provoked in our minds the question that ' Is this the end<br />
of it? t Is this a provisional arrangement? Or are we<br />
being told now that thiat is the agreement?<br />
Mr. Day: Well, the British Government line has been that this<br />
can only be judged, and ought not to be judged except as<br />
a part of a package deal which is not yet complited.<br />
Prime Minister: Well, I've been emphasising to them in my talks since,<br />
that that needs to be made clearer than it was at the<br />
time this particular agreement was announced.<br />
Mr. Day: May I put to you what one Conservative newspaper said<br />
about your statement? It said ' It is a great pity that<br />
Mr. Menzies should make such an outcry over the settlement<br />
on manufactured goods. His Government knows that<br />
its main export interest will be well cared for.' And it<br />
goes on to make this point: The main commodity in<br />
Australian exports is wool, and it is already certain<br />
that there will continue to be free entry of wool into<br />
Britain and Europe.<br />
Prime Minister: Well the writer of that is like a lot of people he<br />
thinks that wool is our only export commodity.<br />
Mr. Day: It didn't say that.<br />
PFinru Minister: No, but he rather implies it, Wool is looked after<br />
wool is safe yes. But we have many many scores of<br />
millions of pounds worth of other co. mmodities, which are<br />
at risk.<br />
Mr. Day: May I ask you about one point in your statement on<br />
Saturday in which you said that this agreement must not<br />
under any circumstances be taken as a pattern for the<br />
type of settlement which might be reached on other<br />
products. Now isn't that rather strong language for one<br />
independent Government to use to another independent<br />
Government?<br />
Prime Minister: Well, I thought it wasn't very strong myself. You<br />
have to remember that these are our exports that are<br />
being dealt with ours these are our preferences that<br />
are being negotiated. Not your preferences into Australia<br />
our pref,; rnces into Great Britain. These are the<br />
ones that are on the counter. JWe have a perfect right<br />
to express our vie-. s.<br />
Mr. Day: Oh, certainly, yes. Jhat was the reaction of the<br />
British Ministers at the weekend to your observations?<br />
Prime Minister: I think they understood rry point of view. </p>
<p>D; bre they angry with you?<br />
Prime Minister: No, oh, no. 7We know oach other very well. We don't<br />
get into that state of mind.<br />
Mr. Day: What safeguards Mr. Menzies<br />
Prime Minister: I may tell you that I M,. y I interrupt you?<br />
Mr. Day: Please go on.<br />
Prime Minister: -We in fact have been, as they know, most co-operative.<br />
We might have said at the very beginning ' Look, we<br />
won't have anything to do with this matter'. But we<br />
didn't do that. le have, through officials and other<br />
channels, put forward constructively, proposals without<br />
which Mr. Heath, as the chief negotiator, wouldn't have<br />
been as far forward as he is now. Of all countries we<br />
have been reasonable on this matter.<br />
Mr. Day: Now what safeguards, Mr. Menzies, are you in fact<br />
demanding for Australia's interests?<br />
Prime Minister: Well, you can't answer that except by answering in<br />
terms of about a hundred different commodities. But<br />
there is one point that we have emphasised though, and<br />
that is that we do not like this transitional period<br />
idea what has been called the precipice by some<br />
people. That was involved, that was included in the<br />
hard manufactures arrangement that has been tentatively<br />
made, as we have by now learnt. But if you were to<br />
reproduce that in respect of dried fruits, canned<br />
fruits, wheat, butter, meat, so that all these<br />
preferential arrangements or their substitutes, went out<br />
by 1970, this would be in the highest degree<br />
unsatisfactory to Australia because we would have a<br />
decline in our production of these things, and our<br />
marketing of them going on steadily over a period of<br />
years. And that is why we sr. id, both Marshall and I,<br />
that rwe didn't want to see this method reproduced down<br />
the line.<br />
Mr. Day: Now may I ask you about some of the alternatives in<br />
this problem, Mr. Menzies? If we join the Common Market,<br />
the United Kin dom stands to get free access to the<br />
Smarkets of Europe; now if we don't, as an alternative<br />
are you prepared to offer us free access to the<br />
Australian market, to take away your tariffs on our goods?<br />
Prime Hinister: But aren't you rather overlooking the fact that we<br />
have been giving you tariff preferences in Australia<br />
since Australia began practically?<br />
Mr. Day: They have been reduced in recent yoers, haven't they?<br />
Prime Minister: But their effectiveness, let me remind you, has been<br />
such that we have over the period of the last twenty<br />
years been. Great Br. tain's biggest customer. In the<br />
last 30 or 40 years we have taken more goods from Great<br />
Britain though we have a population running from five<br />
million at the beginning to ten and a half now, we've<br />
taken more than the United States of America, with 180<br />
million people. And this is, I think, very largely the<br />
result of the preferential tariff position enjoyed by<br />
British goods passing into Australia.<br />
Mr. Day: But if we dont go into the Co_ . maon Market there must<br />
be some alternative trading arrangenoent fur us to gain<br />
benefit from, and this is what critics of your attitude<br />
maintain.<br />
Mr, Day: </p>
<p>Prime Minister: Now look, I want to make it quite clear that whether<br />
Great Britain goes into the Cormon Market or not is a<br />
matter for Great Britain to decide. She knows far more<br />
about her business and her interests on those matters<br />
than I do; or than we do. That's not our point. We<br />
have said: Very well, if you want to go in, that's<br />
your decision, and you will cast up the pluses and the<br />
minuses, fairly enough. We know what the pluses and the<br />
minuses are in the impact on our own trade and we want to<br />
come out of this with as little injury as possible.<br />
Don't imagine for one moment that we expect to come out<br />
of this as a profit, we won't. We will lose something.<br />
But we want our losses to be within reason.<br />
Mr. Day: Many people, Mr. Menzies, see this whole issue as a<br />
choice between the Commonwealth and Uho Common Market.<br />
Do you see it in that simple way?<br />
Prime Minister: Jell, I think that is over-simplifying the problem;<br />
I think the two things overlap; I wouldn't at all be<br />
disposed to be dogmatic on that matter. But just to take<br />
a simple example: if Great Britain goes into the Common<br />
Market, the Cormon Market has an internal free trade, no<br />
internal Customs barriers. Then certain products on<br />
which we now enjoy a preference, will be the subject of<br />
a preference to the European competitor, and we will have<br />
to encounter a tariff barrier. So that our preferences<br />
will be reversed into a preference for one of the<br />
European suppliers. ' cll, this may be the price of<br />
Adniralty, this may be one of those things that must<br />
happen, if you are going into a species of Customs Union.<br />
And we feel the merits of that kind of thing. But we<br />
being of the same race as you are, are always prepared to<br />
have a good look at our own interests on these matters<br />
and protect them.<br />
Mr. Day: Mro Menzies, there has been some criticism in the<br />
press that you have doubtless read about your motives in<br />
making your strong statement the other day. One was that<br />
you had deliberately overstated your case for tactical<br />
reasons in order to with an eye on the harder<br />
bargaining which is to come on wheat and butter and all<br />
these other things<br />
Prime Minister: Well, I'm sorry to be disappointing on this matter,<br />
but you say it was a very strong statement and a<br />
provocative statement<br />
Mr. Day: I didn't call it provocative<br />
PriJae Minister: Before it went out<br />
Mr. Day: I'm not objecting to it<br />
Prime Minister: My only doubt was whether it was too wishy-washy.<br />
Mr. Day: ell would you like to strengthen it now?<br />
Prime Minister: I've never seen anything so built up and so<br />
dramatised it's a perfectly simple statement. We don't<br />
want the rule that's been applied to manufactures, to<br />
hard manufactures to be applied down the line. That's<br />
quite true. They know that. There is nothing in our<br />
statement that hasn't been said a dozen times to the<br />
people conducting the noeotiati-ns.<br />
Mr. Day: There is another criticism made of you which you have<br />
pro) bably also roed, that you made this protest, whether<br />
strong or not, to strengthen your somewhat shaky<br />
political position at home:, where I believe you have a<br />
majority of only one in the lower House of Commons. </p>
<p>Prime Minister:<br />
Mr. Dcy<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Mr. Day<br />
Prirme Minister<br />
Mr. Day:<br />
Pri~ ic Minister<br />
Mr. Day:<br />
Prime Ministeor<br />
r. Day:. many say -tInJt i ha~ ve never felt So comfo_-rtable in<br />
Parliament as I Cid durn 4uh cn itigwt<br />
Lmaj Drity o f Orice.<br />
Can I go onicpe<br />
t1i4nkr I cry-ing roysoif tosleep wjvry night<br />
worrying a-bout ti-n-t thoy-20 quite wrong.<br />
Ym) said before) yo. u lef't Australia tha-t you wre<br />
coming to-1D into tho politic-al iJmpli cations of this<br />
Eur oan quo-stion. Now ono of the th-ings you ineintioned,<br />
whther Brita-in wo,: uld become,, a State, pa-rt of the<br />
Europkean Fe: dcra-tion, what have you f-Jund out about this?<br />
Aro yo. u any clea,? rer?<br />
No, VI' not, but I expect I siaall be before I leave.<br />
I've : lroady ha-d -, no or two discuss.-rL-ns with m: y old<br />
friend, TMr. ir-cillan cmn talk to each other, wvrer<br />
old friends and I'm se_-eing, him agarin next wuekend.<br />
And _ L hope to:_ furnish my -mind a little more fully.<br />
You have sugested that Britain as part of Europe c<br />
ha,, rdly be an independent meombe! r of tVecoonath<br />
those w. 3r your words -, heiin you arrived here. ( Yes)<br />
. vhat effe ct dD yo) u thin!: that is going to hlive on the<br />
wrhole constitutional st1-ructure of the CoiL: ionwoalth and<br />
the Cro in, the q ueen of c:) urse-, being C,: uoen o f<br />
Australia 7. s :, oll as Quee, n of the United K" ingdom? a n<br />
I th-ink-it will teond to i* myself lo-. osen the<br />
structure o) f theo~ nn~ lh but thqe Cojym. onwedLth<br />
structuru, of c". urso, has been fairly well loosened in<br />
rucont years: it's be-come a little less structural and<br />
perhaps a little Drc casinally functional, And when<br />
you discuss it f ccurse, yo-u just -mentioned the ueon,<br />
we are the -, ueonls ] i n and women in Australia, we're<br />
-n. oncirchists; and thore's a c -, rtain quality about the<br />
rei31rti.; nbship bctWuen the imnrchiical countries which<br />
can't be -2, reproducod by a fL. rn of words with other memberS<br />
Do Y,; u thiink, tha12t would be affe~ kcted if the United<br />
Kinf,! rn ro n~ uyp-rt of aEu rop can FedeOration?<br />
Dirminish the sizmifi canco f thec on.<br />
Prime Minister: The longcr thiis, wW1, A tha__ t's true but the-long-er<br />
I live, the less disposed am I t-o -yen-ralizo -, bout the<br />
futuro of the Co: nwat0be cause I don't know, quite<br />
frnnkly. But I do) kn-w this, that t'o the great<br />
Comrenwelthquestion is the re-lations between Graat<br />
Britain and Australia. This is it. I know theiy ( arc<br />
rolo., tio) ns withi othei r vn rsof the Coiunorwalth t. o) o<br />
I dn' udeesir11-ato them~ but when it comes down -to<br />
brass tackEs, to ioe the co) ntiin. uance of theo Commonwalth<br />
is vitally acitdwith thei avoidance of nisunderstanding-<br />
betaeen Great Britain and Australia, and their<br />
workin.,-to gather, Oconom. i cally and p oliti cally.<br />
Mr. Day: Mr Dy: Thyoa. n, uk Mr,. Mnzies. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
