<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5550</transcript-id>
    <title>35-HOUR WEEK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005550.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA' WEDNESDAY, 25 MARCH, 1981<br />
WEEK<br />
Attached is the text of a letter telexed to all State<br />
Premiers and the Chief Minister of the Northern Territory<br />
this afternoon. 000---<br />
K 0: </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CAN BERRA&amp;<br />
My dear Premier, The Commonwealth Government is deeply<br />
concerned about the implications of the present union<br />
campaign for a 35 hour working week. ' I am writing to<br />
propose that the union movement's campaign for shorter<br />
working hours be included on the agenda for the<br />
forthcoming Premiers' Conference.<br />
Our concern has been heightened by the rise of<br />
15.2% in ordinary time earnings in the December quarter<br />
1980 over the corresponding quarter in 1979. This is<br />
substantially above the rate of increase in the cost of<br />
living for the same period and goes far beyond the.<br />
capacity of the economy to pay-higher wages.<br />
The Commonwealth's opposition to the general<br />
introduction of shorter working hours is based on the<br />
severe adverse effects this would have on the Australian<br />
economy and, in particular, labour costs, the<br />
competitiveness of Australian industry, economic<br />
a ctivity and employment.<br />
A reduction of-the working week from 40 to<br />
hours will lea&amp;--to increased overtime, a significant<br />
rise in unit labour costs of over 20% and add billions<br />
of dollars to the national wage bill.<br />
Great opportunities are opening up for the<br />
Australian economy in the 1980' s. It would be a<br />
national tragedy if the. 35. hour week campaign, along<br />
with other s ' er ious inflationary pressures, were allowed<br />
to prevent their realisation.<br />
The Commonwealth will be doing all within its<br />
own power to offer full support for employers in<br />
resisting the union campaign for shorter hours. We will<br />
be taking whatever action is available to us within the<br />
Commonwealth's contractual obligations, the taxation<br />
system, the Government's own employment areas' and before<br />
industrial tribunals. We will be urging major<br />
Australian companies to support firms faced with<br />
industrial difficulties. as a result of the shorter hours<br />
campaign. / 2 </p>
<p>The adoption of a similar'approach by State<br />
and Territory Governments in support of the<br />
Commonwealth's stand would be in the overal-l interests<br />
of the nation. I ask that you join with me and other State<br />
Premier s and the Chief Minister at the forthcoming<br />
Premiers' Conference to consider seriously the action<br />
Governments can take to ensure Australia's economic<br />
prospects for the 1980' s are not jeopardised by the<br />
shorter working hours campaign.<br />
Premiers and the Chief Minister. Yours sincerely,<br />
( Malcolm Fraser) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
