<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11039</transcript-id>
    <title> DOORSTOP INTERVIEW - WATERFRONT PLACE, BRISBANE </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects> Response to Senator Harradine</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, I just called this short conference to</p>
<p>say a few things about the statement that Senator Harradine made in</p>
<p>the Senate this afternoon. Needless to say I'm disappointed that</p>
<p>Senator Harradine has indicated that even with the significant increase</p>
<p>in compensation which the Government proposes to make, he is unable</p>
<p>to support the package.</p>
<p>Let me first of all outline to the Australian people the additional</p>
<p>compensation which I told Senator Harradine yesterday with the Treasurer,</p>
<p>the Government intended to make. Firstly in relation to pensioners</p>
<p>we intend to increase from 4% to 5%, the compensation factor for pensioners</p>
<p>and allowees. We also intend to increase from 25% to 26% the percentage</p>
<p>of male total average weekly earnings linked to the pension. Those</p>
<p>two measures represent a dramatic increase in the level of compensation</p>
<p>available to pensioners in particular, and also in relation to the</p>
<p>5% allowees.</p>
<p>It has been our view that the current proposals are adequate, but</p>
<p>we took account of concerns expressed not only by Senator Harradine,</p>
<p>but by others, that in their view the compensation should be higher.</p>
<p>We didn't believe that those arguments were compelling but we</p>
<p>did believe that there was a capacity to provide more compensation.</p>
<p>Therefore it was resolved by myself and the Treasurer that that additional</p>
<p>compensation should be offered.</p>
<p>We also have resolved that in relation to families, within the existing</p>
<p>family allowance arrangement there is a special loading for families</p>
<p>with four or more children which represents an additional $15 to $16</p>
<p>a fortnight. It's our intention to double that allowance, and</p>
<p>furthermore it will in future operate from the third child onwards,</p>
<p>and not the fourth child onwards as now obtains.</p>
<p>The third alteration relates to self-funded retirees. We intend that</p>
<p>the bonus payable to self-funded retirees should be increased by $500</p>
<p>and that that additional $500 should be payable in the second year</p>
<p>of the package, that is the year 2001-2002. Of equal importance we</p>
<p>intend that the special bonus for self-funded retirees should be available</p>
<p>to self-funded retirees who are aged 55 or over, which represents</p>
<p>a significant liberalisation of the existing arrangements.</p>
<p>Two or three other matters were discussed with Senator Harradine.</p>
<p>The first of those was that we indicated a willingness, and an intention</p>
<p>in fact, three years after the package comes into operation to have</p>
<p>a full inquiry into the adequacy of the compensation and that that</p>
<p>inquiry should be chaired by a person independent of government. We</p>
<p>also indicated, having regard to the concern that Senator Harradine</p>
<p>had expressed regarding</p>
<p>people who he claimed were outside the taxation system and therefore</p>
<p>not eligible for any of the compensation arrangements, that we would</p>
<p>establish a special arrangement in the nature of a relief scheme so</p>
<p>that people who claim to be dis-entitled could establish their disadvantage</p>
<p>and be compensated in accordance with the same compensation principles</p>
<p>applied to people who readily came within the compensation mechanisms</p>
<p>of the package.</p>
<p>It is our view that there are far fewer people in this category, particularly</p>
<p>people deserving of compensation than is the view of Senator Harradine</p>
<p>and others but we are nonetheless quite happy to accept the principle</p>
<p>and to provide a relief scheme in relation to those people.</p>
<p>Two other matters I should mention. In the discussion the Treasurer</p>
<p>alluded to a change in relation to the taxation treatment of credit</p>
<p>unions which the Government quite separately believed ought to be</p>
<p>provided for. That's a matter, of course, unrelated to the principle</p>
<p>matters under debate. And finally, I indicated to Senator Harradine</p>
<p>that the Government would accept in full the changes that he wanted</p>
<p>made in relation to the youth allowance and which were the subject</p>
<p>of some discussion earlier this week. Those changes will have effect</p>
<p>in the forthcoming financial year and, of course, are quite unrelated</p>
<p>and will be quite unrelated to the changes to the taxation package.</p>
<p>I indicated to Senator Harradine that that would be done. The fact</p>
<p>that Senator Harradine has indicated today that he is unwilling to</p>
<p>support the tax package in no way alters the commitment I made to</p>
<p>him yesterday.</p>
<p>I take the opportunity of putting on record that at no stage had I</p>
<p>previously given any undertaking to Senator Harradine about specific</p>
<p>changes in budgets in relation to the youth allowance. What I had</p>
<p>told Senator Harradine, and what I repeat today, is that in the discussions</p>
<p>we had last year I have told Senator Harradine that the Government</p>
<p>would take account of the costs of raising children when it framed</p>
<p>its taxation package. And that undertaking was given in the context</p>
<p>of seeking Senator Harradine's support for the common youth allowance</p>
<p>and the terms of that undertaking were put into the Senate Hansard</p>
<p>on my behalf by Senator Hill. So I just repeat again, at no stage</p>
<p>have I broken undertakings given to Senator Harradine. I reject that</p>
<p>completely. I did give him an undertaking yesterday in relation to</p>
<p>the common youth allowance and that will be honoured in full and I</p>
<p>told him this afternoon when we spoke on the phone that that undertaking</p>
<p>would be honoured in full.</p>
<p>I should also make it plain that what was put to Senator Harradine</p>
<p>yesterday were not private bribes to him. They were changes that the</p>
<p>Government had decided ought to be made and they will be made to the</p>
<p>legislation in the Senate before it is voted on within the next few</p>
<p>weeks. We intend to amend the legislation to give effect to what I</p>
<p>outlined to Senator Harradine yesterday. Our resolve to do that is</p>
<p>unaffected by the speech that Senator Harradine made in the Senate</p>
<p>this afternoon.</p>
<p>I should also say to you that the Government's commitment to taxation</p>
<p>reform remains undiminished. We fought and won an election with this</p>
<p>taxation plan fully disclosed, fully revealed to the Australian people.</p>
<p>We believe we had a mandate to implement it, we believe that if the</p>
<p>Senate votes the legislation down it will be disobeying the wishes</p>
<p>of the Australian people. I can't think of an example in my political</p>
<p>experience where a government has been more explicit, more upfront,</p>
<p>more detailed, more candid, more honest about what it intends to do.</p>
<p>We made full disclosure, we held nothing back. We have listened to</p>
<p>concerns expressed and although we do not believe they are properly</p>
<p>based we have been willing to make very generous and significant changes</p>
<p>which involve the cost of between $1 to $1.5 billion on an annual</p>
<p>basis and, of course, on a three or four year basis a much larger</p>
<p>amount. And given the other demands on the Government's surplus including</p>
<p>debt retirement it represented a very generous but balanced response</p>
<p>to the changes that were sought. It remains an even fairer package</p>
<p>with the amendments that we intend to make. We will put those amendments</p>
<p>and we will invite the Senate to vote on the package as amended. And</p>
<p>those who vote against it will be voting down an even more generous</p>
<p>compensation package.</p>
<p>So, ladies and gentlemen, I want to make it very clear that I have</p>
<p>not changed my commitment to tax reform. In the last 24 hours I have</p>
<p>argued in great detail and with great fervour about the value of tax</p>
<p>reform for Australia's economic future. Nothing has changed now as</p>
<p>a consequence of Senator Harradine's speech. If it was good 24 hours</p>
<p>ago for Australia it remains good today. I have always believed in</p>
<p>fundamental reform of Australia's taxation system and I intend to</p>
<p>continue to pursue it with all the vigour at my disposal.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does that mean taking it to the next Senate after June 30?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll put it up and obviously if it's knocked back we'll put</p>
<p>it up again.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And does that mean a double dissolution....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I am not going to start announcing election dates, we have only</p>
<p>just had one.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But you are prepared to go to a.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what I am prepared to do is do all that I can to get taxation</p>
<p>reform in Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is there someone else you can try and woo apart from Senator Harradine?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll continue to talk to anybody who it seems reasonable that</p>
<p>we talk to. But I'll be talking to the Australian people a lot. And</p>
<p>I'll be saying to the Australian people: we had a seven week campaign</p>
<p>before October of last year. The Government that I lead spelt out</p>
<p>in total detail what I wanted to do. We won that election at some</p>
<p>cost but we won it and if a mandate means anything it means that we</p>
<p>have a right to have that package passed. And those who stand in the</p>
<p>way of that are, in my view, defying the wishes of the Australian</p>
<p>people. And I can't put it any more plainly than that. We need tax</p>
<p>reform. This Government was re-elected on tax reform, this Government</p>
<p>seeks parliamentary passage of tax reform and we'll continue to argue</p>
<p>for tax reform because you go into public life to do things that you</p>
<p>believe are good for the country. I believe taxation reform is good</p>
<p>for Australia and I'll continue to pursue it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] that does sound like double dissolution talk.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, they're your words, they're not mine. I think you should reflect</p>
<p>on that fact. I'm simply saying to you that I don't intend</p>
<p>to give up the fight for tax reform. I intend to continue to pursue</p>
<p>it with all the vigour I have at my disposal.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How much did the extra compensation that you offered to....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's what I mentioned. I said between $1 and $1 billion</p>
<p>a year.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] billions that Mr Costello rejected on Wednesday.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I wouldn't have thought 1 to 1 was billions, but you know.</p>
<p>More than one, less than two.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] heavily involved in negotiations....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Prime Minister is heavily involved in everything.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you get personally in negotiations with Senator Harradine?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of course I had.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you regard this as a personal blow that he's rejected it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't regard it as a personal blow. I am disappointed</p>
<p>for Australia that the task for tax reform is made that much harder,</p>
<p>because the Australian public voted for this. I mean forget my personal</p>
<p>views. What really matters is good policy for Australia's future,</p>
<p>and I have believed in tax reform all the time I've been in Parliament.</p>
<p>I really believe in it. I think I have a responsibility as Prime Minister</p>
<p>to try and bring about change that I believe is good for this country,</p>
<p>even though it's hard, and even though I might be criticised.</p>
<p>But what is the point of holding a great office unless you use it</p>
<p>to the national benefit.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Senator Harradine says that one of the major reasons he's rejected</p>
<p>the GST is that there's no guarantee that compensation won't</p>
<p>be diminished over time. Will you ever be able to convince him that</p>
<p>it won't?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there's no guarantee of anything in this life, except death and taxes of some form as they say. I mean I can't....Senator Harradine can't guarantee that wholesale taxes won't go up under a future Labor government, the taxes on clothing  on't be increased under a future Labor government. He couldn't stop that in 1993.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Are you prepared to offer Senator Harradine anything else to try and win his vote?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I don't know what you mean by anything else. I mean he says quite properly that he doesn't cross trade, and I don't cross trade either. Other decisions that the Government has taken in other non-taxation matters that have been construed as wooing Senator Harradine, I think people have missed the point, that on a number of issues it does happen that my views, and the views of the Government and the views of Senator Harradine coincide.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well is there anything else you can....any way that you can...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You should ask Senator Harradine that not me. I put a proposal to Senator Harradine yesterday along with the Treasurer. And that proposal he acknowledged represented a significant increase in compensation. I mean any of you who studied this will know that it meets the major objection raised by those who were critical of the compensation arrangements. Increasing the MTAWE figure from 25% to 26% is a huge....I think it's a quite significant, even huge change.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So this package is now going to go the Senate.....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It will go to the Senate with these changes in it that's the point.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>They are additional changes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we certainly don't have any others in contemplation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you revisit exempting food?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. No, no, we are not going to exempt food. I have said that all</p>
<p>along and the more compensation you give pensioners the less is the</p>
<p>case for exempting food. And the whole purpose of compensation is</p>
<p>to protect low-income earners in relation to the cost of the essentials</p>
<p>of life. And if you give them more compensation then the case for</p>
<p>exempting food is diminished, it really is. So as of now the case</p>
<p>for exempting food is a lot less then what it was. The case for exempting</p>
<p>food is greatly diminished. It is much less now than what it was 24</p>
<p>hours ago.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Without the GST going through before June 30, is that going to alter</p>
<p>any of your budget predictions?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the budget is in relation to this coming financial year.</p>
<p>(ends)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
