<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>925</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 30/1964 - MESSAGE FROM PRESIDENT JOHNSON</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/05/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Message</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000925.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No, 20/ 1964<br />
MES3AGE FROM P ESID ENT JOHNSON<br />
The Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies, released<br />
in Canberra this afternoon the text of a message wh. ich he had<br />
received from the President of the United States of America.<br />
The President's message is as follows<br />
" Twenty-two years have passed since we<br />
fought the decisive battle of the Coral Sea and it<br />
is deeply reassuring that the enduring bonds of<br />
co-operation and friendship between Australia and<br />
An.. rica remain firm.<br />
The Coral Sea eng ge :-ent in which<br />
Australian and United States Naval units constituted<br />
a single integrated coimmrand, serves to remind friend<br />
and foe alike of the power of free peoples when they<br />
move in concert against aggression.<br />
It is with great pleasure. Mr, Prime<br />
Minister, that I extend to the people'of Australia<br />
on this memorable anniversary the greetings and best<br />
wishes of the people of the United States,"<br />
BACKGROUND NOTE The message was brought to Australia by<br />
General Hamilton H, Howze, Commanding General Eighth US, Army<br />
and Commander-in-Chief United Nations Forces in Korea, who is<br />
visiting Australia for the Australian American Association's<br />
Coral Sea Week Celebrations, General Howze handed it to the<br />
Prime Minister at Sydney airport shortly after his arrival<br />
this afternoon from Korea and before the Prime Minister left<br />
for Canberra.<br />
CANBERRA, 3rd May, 1964. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
