<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8506</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP AND THE TREASURER THE HON J S DAWKINS MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/05/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008506.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AND THE TREASURER THE HON J S DAWKINS MP<br />
JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, MAY 11 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: We thought we would give you a run-down on the meeting<br />
we have just concluded with the Premiers. The first<br />
point I want to make is, there's an agreed communique<br />
and it's now in the course of being published so we'll<br />
have that available for you soon but it was written in<br />
the course of the afternoon as we went through subjects<br />
so there was no pro-forma communique drafted before<br />
hand so that's why it's a bit slow in coming but it<br />
will more than adequately reflect what was discussed at<br />
the meeting.<br />
The first thing I would like to say about the meeting<br />
was that it was a very co-operative one and the<br />
outcomes were, I think, exceedingly good. We in terms<br />
of the broader discussions, we agreed to establish a<br />
Council of Australian Governments to meet at least once<br />
a year on non-financial issues. So where we have the<br />
Financial Premiers Conference to discuss financial<br />
assistance grants, Commonwealth payments to States,<br />
this is about all the other national agenda issues in<br />
the micro economy, education, all the other subjects,<br />
the Commonwealth will be the Chair, the venue will be a<br />
rotating venue around the States where the respective<br />
Premier will be the host, and the Commonwealth and the<br />
States will jointly provide a Secretariat.<br />
The first meeting of this body will decide the protocol<br />
relationship between the Council and the Ministerial<br />
Council, that is the Councils of Ministers of each<br />
particular discipline of the Commonwealth and the<br />
States. So where we now have education ministers and<br />
transport ministers meeting with their counterpart<br />
ministers in what's called Ministerial Councils, the<br />
protocol between those Councils and the Council of<br />
Australian Governments will be decided at the first<br />
meeting. </p>
<p>So it's quite an historic event and, I think, a good<br />
outcome from a succession of meetings discussing<br />
various issues and it will be a useful forum for<br />
debating matters of national moment beyond the<br />
financial discussion. That's not to say that this body<br />
itself can't have a general financial discussion it<br />
can, but by and large the Annual Financial Grants<br />
Arrangements and Loan Council will still be the subject<br />
of the financial meeting.<br />
On the broader topic of federal finances, we've spent<br />
considerable time this morning discussing that subject<br />
and we have agreed to a joint treasury study joint<br />
meaning Commonwealth and State Treasuries to look at<br />
the underlying financial trends in state budgets,<br />
that's on the receipts and the outlays side, and likely<br />
budget balances in the future, the impact from the<br />
recession and the recovery, and to get some idea of how<br />
State budgets will look ahead of the financial meeting<br />
coming up in June.<br />
The States will be deciding this week whether they<br />
require of the Commonwealth a one-year financial<br />
arrangement in 1992-93 or whether-they would prefer to<br />
seek an on-going relationship, financial arrangement,<br />
over say a three year period. It may suit their<br />
purposes to make a one-off arrangement with the<br />
Commonwealth at the financial meeting in June, it may<br />
similarly suit their purposes to make an arrangement<br />
with the Commonwealth over three years because the<br />
Treasurer and I indicated today that we are prepared to<br />
discuss with the States certainty of funding and<br />
questions of adequacy including the prospect of growth<br />
in Financial Assistant Grants and it is with that<br />
background they have now, themselves, withdrawn to<br />
consider their positions as to whether they say to the<br />
Commonwealth we want to now consider a one year<br />
arrangement or a three year arrangement.<br />
The States presented a paper to us of financial trends<br />
and some claims which have been published by some of<br />
you. I think it's fair to say that when we pointed out<br />
that a reference to historical shares, that is to take<br />
Commonwealth payments to the States back to the<br />
proportion of Commonwealth payments which obtained in<br />
the early 1980s would involve an addition of about<br />
billion in the coming year rising to $ 9 billion by<br />
1995-96 which we rejected out of hand and said it was<br />
not possible and reminded them of our own budgetary<br />
position and the fact that we spent the 1980s pulling<br />
the public sector down for national adjustment and<br />
national savings purposes and there was no point now to<br />
try to reverse that to make it easier for State<br />
officials to put their budgets together.<br />
While we said we will examine longer term trends in<br />
State financing we are not accepting of the notion that<br />
we return to some share of payments back in the 1980s. </p>
<p>Certainly we're not the implications of sort of $ 5-9<br />
billion, those sorts of numbers. That was I think<br />
accepted. There were number of other things decided. Mutual<br />
recognition of standards were agreed and the States<br />
agreed that the Commonwealth should fully participate<br />
in the setting of those standards. This was an item<br />
which had been on previous Special Premiers Conference<br />
agendas and has been decided today.<br />
On Technical and Further Education there was an<br />
agreement to resume discussions with a view to<br />
advancing the outcome by the June Financial Premiers<br />
Conference meeting. That is, States at this stage are<br />
not entirely certain of what the dollars and cents of<br />
such an arrangement will mean because some States have<br />
a bigger effort in TAFE, some have a smaller effort and<br />
again, if there's a change to Financial Assistance<br />
Grants, the Grants Commission formula re-allocates<br />
funds on a different basis of distribution than that<br />
which we pay now to TAFE or to that which they spend.<br />
So we agree that we continue discussing this, but we<br />
also said that as John, as Minister for Education, had<br />
discussed with the States some time ago, that if we are<br />
about re-sorting, functions with the States doing<br />
things which they think they can do best and us doing<br />
other things, that in the symmetry of them handling the<br />
compulsory education area, the Commonwealth may handle<br />
Technical and Further Education, vocational education.<br />
But consistent with that would be that the Commonwealth<br />
removed some of the conditions under Specific Purpose<br />
Claimants which we now attach to payments for<br />
education. In other words, what's called in the jargon<br />
the ' tags on the FAGs' that's the Financial<br />
Assistance Grants, the tags we put on them the<br />
requirements of policy which we put on the Financial<br />
Assistance Grants if they were to be removed and we<br />
paid this over to them as Financial Assistance Grants<br />
free of any requirement by us in terms of their<br />
expenditure, meaning that the compulsory area of<br />
education was handled exclusively by them, though with<br />
conversations with us but not legislation,<br />
conversations about general policy that we're<br />
contending and they are considering that a Commonwealth<br />
take over of TAFE funding provides that symmetry. Now<br />
again, we've agreed to continue discussing these issues<br />
and we'll resume discussions on that at official level<br />
soon. There was an emphasis upon the importance of youth and<br />
youth training and TAFE being an important part of that<br />
whole equation. Training young people, those people<br />
who have left school beyond compulsory education who<br />
are not getting tertiary places, and having an<br />
important place for them. </p>
<p>But on the main change, on the Commonwealth assuming<br />
financial responsibility for TAFE, Victoria was<br />
supportive of that, NSW is examining and considering it<br />
in the context of the change I mentioned in relation to<br />
Financial Assistance Grants for compulsory education<br />
and other States are similarly considering their<br />
position, though there is a propensity on the part of<br />
the smaller States to wish to have a joint funding<br />
model. Moving now to electricity generation, which was another<br />
' One Nation' topic we had on the agenda, we did secure<br />
agreement in principle to the separation of power<br />
generation from transmission. This is the key point in<br />
this issue that the providers of power are not the<br />
transmitters of power with a view to establishing an<br />
East-Coast electricity grid, a network which would be<br />
represented by a structure yet to be agreed, upon which<br />
the Grid Management Council will give us advice by the<br />
end of the year. In other words, that the transmission<br />
assets of the East-Coast States would be part of an<br />
East-Coast grid, a body, a corporation, the design and<br />
structure of which we are yet to be advised upon. But<br />
the principle of separation is agreed.<br />
On roads we've agreed to untie $ 350 million of<br />
Financial Assistance Grants of a Specific Purpose<br />
Payment for Roads which were formerly paid for, well<br />
the specific purpose of road funding. We have yet to<br />
agree on how that untieing is distributed because, if<br />
it is distributed by way of Financial Assistance<br />
Grants, the weighting of the distribution is different<br />
to the weighting of the road monies which were formerly<br />
paid under an SPP a Specific Purpose Payment. You<br />
understand, under the equalisation formulas, money is<br />
basically, on the horizontal equalisation, shifted off<br />
to the smaller States, but given the fact that the old<br />
Specific Purpose Payments for roads were concentrated<br />
where the roads were required, more of the money went<br />
to NSW and Victoria under the Specific Purpose Payments<br />
than would go under Financial Assistance Grants. So<br />
naturally, whenever these positions arise there is<br />
always an argy-bargy about which distribution formula.<br />
We are going to have another one of those between now<br />
and the next Premiers Conference.<br />
The other important point was, I think, we had to seek<br />
to agree on the delineation of road funding<br />
responsibilities which is the Commonwealth<br />
Government's and which is the States so that we can<br />
define. Now that the Commonwealth is going to move<br />
$ 350 million out of identifiable roads spending and<br />
give that to the States we want to be clear that we<br />
don't have constituency interest coming back to us to<br />
say, you are now not spending enough on roads. We say,<br />
well hang on, we were spending it, we've just untied<br />
it. It's not shown, so it will be important for us to </p>
<p>get that delineation of what's a Commonwealth function<br />
and a what's a State function clear.<br />
On Aboriginal affairs we endorsed the report of the<br />
AAAC and agreed to, I will just check with John this,<br />
to examine the operation of Section 18 of the Act the<br />
funding powers of ATSIC. The States have had some<br />
difficulty relating to ATSIC as the primary negotiating<br />
point for the expenditure of Commonwealth funds and so<br />
therefore Section 18 of that Act and its financing<br />
function is going to be examined. But the States have<br />
acknowledged that ATSIC is the body they have to deal<br />
with where formerly they were seeking simply a deal<br />
with the Commonwealth.<br />
On rail, several Premiers' expressed satisfaction with<br />
the way things were going in the ' One Nation' rail<br />
program and we are moving to try and negotiate an<br />
enterprise agreement for the National Rail Freight<br />
Corporation but while that's happening, we're in the<br />
process of getting contracts together for the provision<br />
of passing loops, extensions, bridge heightening and<br />
all the other things and Premiers told us that they<br />
were satisfied with progress on that score.<br />
I think that's about it in terms of resume, the<br />
communique will go more expressly to the points but I<br />
think we can conclude by saying that it was a good<br />
meeting and there was an atmosphere of co-operation and<br />
we've now formalised, if you like, this discussion by<br />
the Council of Australian Governments so in the future<br />
there won't be just simply a Financial Premiers<br />
Conference but there will be as well another forum for<br />
national agenda discussions.<br />
I think I will leave it at that and just invite the<br />
Treasurer and see if he wants to add anything to my<br />
remarks in any way.<br />
J: On 1 May the Minister for Finance said that the revenue<br />
collections were moving towards the February budget<br />
deficit target of $ 6.8 billion. What has happened in<br />
the last ten days to so dramatically change that<br />
outlook?<br />
T: Well let's go back a bit further. I mean there was<br />
some suggestion back in January/ February that the<br />
revenue estimates wouldn't hold up. We undertook some<br />
specific enquiries as far as that was concerned and we<br />
were reassured at that time that the revenue estimates<br />
were likely to be sustained during the rest of the<br />
financial year. It wasn't really until the December<br />
quarter National Accounts figures came out in the<br />
middle of March that we began to realise that there may<br />
have been an error in estimation, or the estimations<br />
may not hold up because of the lower growth in earnings<br />
because the higher level of unemployment that then was<br />
anticipated at the time, the fact that you had lower<br />
interest rates. All these things only became a<br />
question after that and that coupled with the actual<br />
experience of collections in, I think, April and May<br />
really revealed the scope or the nature of the<br />
deficiency because it was confined largely to this area<br />
of provisional tax paying individuals, which is of<br />
course based on their 1991 income and what had happened<br />
was that there was an over-estimation of that inc~. e at </p>
<p>T: I think the point is that the deficit, you said that we<br />
were back to where we started. i mean when we started<br />
we had a budget deficit of some 4 per cent of GDP.-<br />
Even with this position it is about 2 1/ 2 per cent of<br />
GDP. So, whilst the numbers, the absolute numbers<br />
might look large when compared back to 1983/ 84 we are<br />
talking about a budget sector which has grown from<br />
about $ 40 billion to nearly $ 100 billion, so it is a<br />
much different equation than we were dealing with back<br />
in 1983/ 84.<br />
the time of the budget. But that wasn't actually<br />
revealed in terms of payments until those provisional<br />
tax payers started actually paying in April and May.<br />
So it was really of recent origin. I was first alerted<br />
to the fact there may be a problem only a matter of a<br />
couple of weeks ago and I indicated that at the time.-<br />
I sent the Tax Commissioner back to confirm his figures<br />
in the context of the May review because we don't give<br />
running commentaries of the revenue side of the budget.<br />
We have a normal process in the context of the May<br />
review. I brought forward the May review, asked for<br />
the revenue figures to be tightened up as much as<br />
possible for the May review and decided that that<br />
should be released in the context of this Premiers'<br />
Conference so that they had an understanding, not only<br />
of our budgetary position this year but also our<br />
prospects for next year as well.<br />
J: You were scathing at the time about those private<br />
estimates which now turn out to have been pretty spot<br />
on, at least in the total. Are you concerned that the<br />
collection of official data or the making of official<br />
estimates is not perhaps what it should be?<br />
T: Well this area which has been the subject of the<br />
greatest volatility has an experience at being<br />
volatile. I mean on this occasion it is down by a<br />
figure of $ 1.8 billion; a year ago it was down by<br />
$ 300 million; the year before by $ 1.1 million; the year<br />
before by $ 1.5 million; the year before by<br />
$ 300 million; but the year before that it was an underestimate<br />
by nearly a billion dollars. So there is a<br />
high degree of volatility in this provisional taxpayer<br />
area. of course, it has been covered up on other<br />
occasions because revenues have increased under other<br />
categories. As far as the Access estimate or<br />
prediction in January, I think, of a $ 9 billion<br />
deficit, they may have got it right but for all the<br />
wrong reasons. The components of their estimates were<br />
wrong, they under-estimated the size of this deficiency<br />
and they wildly over-estimated the size of what they<br />
predicted was going to be a massive deficiency in the<br />
PAYE area. So they got it right by accident.<br />
J: What's the difference Mr Dawkins of getting it wrong<br />
for all the right reasons?<br />
T: Well what do you mean by that? </p>
<p>J: Well you said that Access got it right for all the<br />
wrong reasons.<br />
T: Look there is a world of difference between a budget<br />
deficit blowing out because expenditure is out of<br />
control that is not the case. Expenditure has hardly<br />
contributed to this question at all other than the<br />
planned expenditure that we made in the One Nation<br />
context. This has been a deficiency for all the right<br />
reasons. For the reasons in the way in which the Prime<br />
Minister has described it. We have had lower<br />
inflation, lower earnings growth, lower income from<br />
investments because of lower interest rates and a range<br />
of those kinds of things.-So this is not something<br />
which could have been accurately predicted at the time.<br />
The other point is that the Tax Office' s estimates of<br />
company tax are made on the basis of a private survey<br />
that they make, I think, in June of a particular year,<br />
helping them to estimate for the next year and it just<br />
turns out that survey happened on this occasion to<br />
overstate the company tax collections.<br />
J: Mr Dawkins these ficures were last updated in February,<br />
not so long ago, surely they should be more accurate?<br />
T: At that stage they were all on track and it wasn't<br />
until the later evidence came in, and I am telling you<br />
I actually asked the question before that, I asked that<br />
these matters be confirmed and they were at the time.<br />
It was only when the National Accounts figures camne in<br />
in March and when we had the record of the actual<br />
collections being made in April and May that the<br />
magnitude of this problem became clear.<br />
3: Prime Minister, can you still deliver the One Nation<br />
tax cuts?<br />
PM: Yes. They are solid as they were when they were<br />
published. And again, we will have the Budget back<br />
into surplus in 1995-96.<br />
3: But doesn't that imply that you are going to have some<br />
spending cuts, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: We've, the Treasurer and I, have been involved with<br />
putting together of more budgets just about, certainly<br />
more economic statements, than any other pair of<br />
individuals in the history of the Federation, 17 of<br />
them in fact, and we always have been able to meet our<br />
objectives, and we will again.<br />
J: Does it throw any of the one Nation measures out of<br />
kilter?<br />
PM: No, it just means that the financing task is bigger,<br />
and it means the starting point next year is larger.<br />
But again, there is a lot of volatility in these<br />
revenue estimates, and you can see this in the election<br />
by provisional taxpayers to obviously self-assess<br />
themselves. That will change. </p>
<p>J: But isn't the point about these figures today that<br />
while they might be only just emerging, you are arguing<br />
that their source is from low inflation, what you argue<br />
is that there is a structural change in the economy.<br />
If that's the case, shouldn't we be assuming that<br />
there's not going to be any huge surge again in revenue<br />
if low inflation is locked in?<br />
PM: The revenue will come from growth/ activity profits etc.<br />
Business is now in a position where it is moving to a<br />
mode of higher productivity. The high level of<br />
unemployment is evidence of that. So as soon as there<br />
is a pick up in volumes, the prof its will go straight<br />
on the bottom line. They will all be picked up under<br />
tax collections a year later.<br />
T: Of course with higher levels of employment as well.<br />
PM: With higher levels of employment and activity. But the<br />
initial effects of low inflation are going to be,<br />
obviously, some burden to the budget.<br />
J: Your tax cuts are based on bracket creep, but if<br />
inflation is lower how are you going to fund your tax<br />
cuts?<br />
PM: Well the brackets will be creeping less, won't they?<br />
J: Yes that's right and you'll have less money to pay<br />
back.<br />
PM: And therefore, well we'll see. We've got forecasts in<br />
there. At the moment we've been undershooting those<br />
forecasts with inflation, which is a good thing.<br />
T: Of course the other point to bear in mind is that with<br />
lower inflation you've got the prospect of maybe<br />
growing a little faster.<br />
PM: That is, the confidence effects.<br />
T: Mr Keating, do you reserve the right if those forecasts<br />
turn out to have to be revised to revise the tax cuts?<br />
PM: All governments automatically have a right of<br />
discretion, but we've made our position clear on this.<br />
J: Is that position absolute?<br />
PM: Yes, absolute. Because we have in the past delivered<br />
very large tax cuts over quite long time frames and<br />
they've all been delivered. At every point, the ACTU<br />
has always said the Government has always delivered on<br />
its commitments. Never have we made arrangements which<br />
we backed away from. </p>
<p>J: Mr Keating, in the past you've said it gets harder<br />
every year to keep cutting and there's less and less to<br />
cut. How tough an assignment will it be to actually,<br />
in the past you've been able to cut expenditure, how<br />
tough a task will it be now?<br />
PM: That assumes one has to cut expenditure.<br />
J: Well, didn't you say earlier that you would be looking<br />
at that to reign in the deficit and to deliver the<br />
promised tax cuts?<br />
PM: We'll look at the production of a budget which has got<br />
lots of things to it. We've now got a relatively small<br />
public sector in OECD terms, not withstanding the rise<br />
in unemployment benefits and the outlays coming from<br />
the natural stabiliser in the budget. But invariably<br />
when we put the budget together we've always had a<br />
housekeeping task on outlays, and we probably will<br />
again.<br />
T: And the best way to deal with outlays is to not let<br />
them grow too fast. So what it really means is that<br />
our colleagues might have a dent or two placed in their<br />
new policy proposals.<br />
J: Do you think a $ 10.5 billion deficit is an acceptable<br />
level for next year?<br />
T: Well that's the starting point deficit. This is the<br />
kind of beginning of the budget process. We all have<br />
our discussions about what we think the appropriate<br />
parameters are for the budget and obviously we'll bear<br />
in mind the starting point deficit in that context.<br />
J: What impact is the Government's bond raising program,<br />
now that this deficit figure has appeared, likely to<br />
have on interest rates?<br />
T: Not much I wouldn't have thought, if the response from<br />
the market is anything to go by. The Treasury put out<br />
a statement today talking about, I think, another $ 1.3<br />
billion borrowings in June, and I think we'll wait and<br />
see what the reaction to that is but I think the market<br />
will take it in its stride.<br />
J: All this indicates, despite the spirit of cooperation<br />
today, the States next month clearly cannot expect<br />
anything much in the way growth in real funds, surely.<br />
T: Well interestingly they didn't put in a bid for any<br />
lavish claims. They recognise that, certainly after I<br />
revealed the state of our Budget, they acknowledged the<br />
fact that this was not going to be the year in which </p>
<p>they could get a major correction in what they consider<br />
to be their budgetary circumstances.<br />
J: Someone said it was a role reversal.<br />
PM: Normally they come with a tale of woe, this time they<br />
came to find that there was a change in the<br />
Commonwealth Budget, a deterioration of the<br />
Commonwealth Budget balance, which may have taken some<br />
by surprise.<br />
J: Who said that?<br />
PM: Well I can't remember exactly which one.<br />
J: It was certainly very fortuitous timing, wasn't it<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: There was nothing organised, it was a natural time to..<br />
T: We actually brought it foreword.<br />
PM: Good point.<br />
T: We thought it would have been particularly odd for us<br />
to send the Premiers away from Canberra and then a week<br />
later make this revelation. And that's why I brought<br />
foreword the announcement of this position. Because<br />
they had been making the point frequently and loudly<br />
that their budgets were knocked around by the recession<br />
and ours was not. That's what they said. And it was<br />
important for them to be advised that in fact our<br />
budget is much more knocked around because our budget<br />
is more dependent on income taxes and with fewer people<br />
in the workforce, that affects the revenue, and it also<br />
affects the outlays as you have to pay those people<br />
unemployment benefits. Because ours is the budget that<br />
provides the kind of stabilisers to the economy under<br />
these circumstances.<br />
PM: The States revenue this year is still growing. I think<br />
on average it is about 1.5 per cent. Commonwealth<br />
revenue is declining by about 3.8 per cent.<br />
T: Now more.<br />
PM: Now more.<br />
J: Are you as confident about the growth and investment<br />
forecasts in One Nation as you were two months ago,<br />
particularly for 1992-3?<br />
PM: I think there is a mood change coming from the<br />
consolidation of those low inflation numbers and the<br />
interest rate reduction, which the Treasurer announced </p>
<p>last week, had 1 per cent taking cash rates at 6.5 per<br />
cent is starting to take a substantial effect upon the<br />
outlook for growth activity, investment. We're<br />
starting, I think, to see people really accepting the<br />
fact that inflationary expectations are down, inflation<br />
is down in a trend way and we are going to have lower<br />
interest rates for the foreseeable future. That's an<br />
important part of the investment equation and it is<br />
coming good for Australia.<br />
J: Did the question of the Superannuation Guarantee Levy<br />
come up with the Premiers?<br />
PM: Only in passing.<br />
J: Prime Minister, in the deficit figure today, do your<br />
growth forecasts in One Nation have to be exceeded for<br />
you to meet your timetable of a return to surplus<br />
without spending cuts?<br />
PM: We're talking about 1995-96, we're not talking about<br />
tomorrow morning. We're looking at, obviously, the<br />
economy now moving into a recovery phase on the upswing<br />
and we've, in the past, set ourselves sort of medium<br />
term outcomes for public policy, for fiscal policy, and<br />
I don't really think that, notwithstanding that $ 1.9<br />
nearly $ 2 billion shift, that is an insurmountable<br />
problem for us.<br />
J: Mr Dawkins, can you explain how the Tax Office got its<br />
estimations on the impact of the tax file numbers so<br />
wrong? Is it the case that there is fewer dishonest<br />
people out there, or are they just more clever than the<br />
ATO?<br />
T: I'm not absolutely sure about that. They made some<br />
predictions particularly about interest income and the<br />
effect of having the tax file number as a means of<br />
having a more accurate record of interest income. I<br />
think it was more partially a fact that people probably<br />
anticipated this and made their own arrangements ahead<br />
of the TFN. It was also a fact that interest rate<br />
payments were lower than anticipated. But I can get<br />
you a more detailed response to that if you want one.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you still think the States are basically<br />
irresponsible financial managers?<br />
PM: The States have pulled back on their spending somewhat,<br />
but between the period 1985-6 and 1991-92, that is in<br />
the period when fiscal consolidation became a national<br />
imperative, Commonwealth outlays rose by 5.9 per cent<br />
and State purpose outlays rose by 12.9 per cent. So if<br />
one takes outlays growth as a measurement of restraint,<br />
the Commonwealth's 5.9 per cent real over that period </p>
<p>1985 to 1991-2 is an indication of fairly stringent<br />
levels of restraint. The States did have bigger<br />
spending programs. These in part were camouflaged by<br />
the big pick up in receipts coming off the boom,<br />
particularly in property and stamp duties, that's<br />
declined a bit. But the underlying level of their<br />
outlays and expenditure programs are obviously not as<br />
tight as the Commnonwealth's.<br />
J: Mr Keating, in terms of their confidence as financial<br />
managers, though, given some of the things that have<br />
happened in Victoria and in South Australia, I mean<br />
they're really fundamental problems that need to be<br />
addressed. what sort of things can the Commonwealth<br />
do?<br />
PM: Well they've certainly got problems with management of<br />
financial institutions and PTEs, and I think they're<br />
are obviously now painfully aware of those.<br />
J: But is there some sort of stamp that the Commonwealth<br />
can put on<br />
PM: I don't think so. In the end if you want own the State<br />
Bank the buck stops at the shareholder's door. You can<br />
have all the independent boards you like and you can<br />
have everything else, but in the end you've got to take<br />
an interest in it.<br />
J: Was the position of hospitals discussed?<br />
PM: Only briefly.<br />
J: What about the implementation of the Aboriginal Deaths<br />
in Custody Royal Commission?<br />
PM: Well again they will be responding to that and relating<br />
their response through ATSIC.<br />
T: That was the significance of the endorsement of the<br />
AAAC Agreement that that's the thing that underpins<br />
these mechanisms for the future. So we made progress<br />
on that.<br />
J: So what's the effect of that?<br />
T: It now means we've got a mechanism, a Commonwealth-<br />
State mechanism for dealing with the response to the<br />
Commission' s report.<br />
3: While the Premiers were meeting with you, their<br />
officials were telling the Senate Committee on Super<br />
that they basically rejected what the Federal<br />
Government's been saying about the effect of the SGL on<br />
wages outcomes, on jobs, and on national savings. This </p>
<p>13<br />
SGL looks like it's in a fair bit of trouble with the<br />
Senate. Are you prepared to modify it dramatically or<br />
change the date of its implementation?<br />
T: No. I don't think it is in trouble. I've been having<br />
discussions with the Democrats, they haven't given me<br />
the impression that they're about to reject it. What<br />
would you expect the States to say. I mean, the States<br />
see this as a bit of an inconvenience because it's<br />
going to cost them money. But the alternative is that<br />
they would be up for higher wages costs. The fact of<br />
the matter is that the States have been major<br />
beneficiaries of wage restraint. Wage restraint has<br />
been achieved at a great cost to the Federal budget<br />
through tax cuts, wage-tax trade of fs, and the like.<br />
And this was a point that the Prime Minister made to<br />
them today. So you don't expect them to be throwing<br />
their hats in the air about this arrangement, but it is<br />
basically an arrangement whereby people who don't have<br />
superannuation, or who have very little of it, will get<br />
access to it to improve their prospects in retirement.<br />
J: They're making the basic point which is that the SGL<br />
means that for a lot of people there will be what is<br />
effectively a wage increase on July 1, in terms of the<br />
cost to employers, which would not otherwise flow<br />
through with the economy in the state it's in.<br />
PM: Yes, but the superannuation 3 to 5 to 6 per cent<br />
outcomes are the product of wage restraint from 1985-<br />
1991/ 92. And the years when we've had falling real<br />
levels of wages, the States have been given an enormous<br />
bonus for years in succession. Look at their wage<br />
costs wage costs are 60 per cent of their outlays and<br />
what's average weekly earnings this year? 3.5 per<br />
cent. I mean, they've been the major beneficiaries of<br />
the Accord processes. They can't take all of the<br />
benefits and then say sorry, but the bit at the end of<br />
the section, the superannuation, we're not going to be<br />
paying that. You know.<br />
J: Do you envisage that this new Council is actually going<br />
to be able to make decisions and reach agreements, or<br />
is it just purely as you've put in your Statement for<br />
discussion?<br />
PM: No, if you look at today today is really a precursor<br />
for this, a forerunner for this. It was a decision<br />
we ' ye made today on a whole range of important things<br />
such as mutual recognition of standards, what we're<br />
deciding to do about electricity. It is a very large<br />
principle getting the States to agree,<br />
notwithstanding the presence of electricity<br />
commissions, for the principle of separation of power<br />
generation and transmission assets is a very large one </p>
<p>to get at a meeting like this. I've always said to you<br />
I've thought these Premiers' Conference meetings were<br />
very efficient. And they have been by and large.<br />
Whether they be in the financial guise or in the nonfinancial<br />
guise. And I think this Council could do a<br />
great deal.<br />
J: Mr Keating, in terms of the way you see these<br />
Federal/ State relations going, is there a particular<br />
theme you can point to as to where the reform is going,<br />
I mean through that Council?<br />
PM: All of the areas where national policy, since the time<br />
of Federation there has been a more national outcome.<br />
Be it in terms of the economy, macro-economic policy,<br />
education, roads, the Commonwealth Government has been<br />
involved and there has been a national movement of<br />
policy. Having a place to discuss those things other<br />
than simply Ministerial Councils where it is the<br />
preserve of the respective Minister and not the broader<br />
discussion between States and the Commonwealth, has<br />
been a limited factor. I think to now be in a position<br />
to discuss these issues in the longer haul, that is to<br />
find this sort of delineation between State and<br />
Commonwealth responsibilities and to talk about them in<br />
the broad, so that Premiers in all States at the one<br />
time are all part of the same conversation and know<br />
which way the system is moving, is I think important.<br />
The cooperation in the last few years has been quite<br />
profound and a lot has been achieved. A great deal.<br />
And I think this Council does hold great promise.<br />
Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
