<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7126</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ANNIVERSARY OF THE CENTRAL SYNAGOGUE BONDI JUNCTION, 22 FEBRUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/02/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007126.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J , AUJ LLLA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
ANNIVERSARY OF THE CENTRAL SYNAGOGUE<br />
BONDI JUNCTION, 22 FEBRUARY 1987<br />
Mr Ron Nowman, President of the Central Synagogue,<br />
Rabbie Dr Nisson Schulman,<br />
Professor Graham de Vahi Davies, President of the Jewish<br />
Board of Deputies,<br />
Members of~ the Jewish Board of Deputies,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Thank you for your welcome. You have done Hazel and me a<br />
great honour by inviting us again to this Synagogue, this<br />
time to celebrate with you your 75th anniversary.<br />
We were honoured in 1985, to be present when, Rabbi<br />
Schulman, you became Chief Minister of this, the largest<br />
congregation in Australia.<br />
More than 2000 people belong to the Synagogue today a far<br />
cry from your early days in Dowling Street, where the<br />
Synagogue first held servies in 1912, and then in Grosvenor<br />
Street, where the Synagogue spent more than three decades<br />
from 1922.<br />
In the post-war years the Central Synagogue grew with the<br />
waves of immigration from Europe and it includes among its<br />
members survivors of the Holocaust.<br />
In the 1950s, it became apparent that the Synagogue might<br />
again have to find new premises to cater for its growing<br />
numbers. Thanks to the vision and skills of many people, we<br />
find ourselves today in this fine building celebrating your<br />
anniversary.<br />
The Synagogue has benefited profoundly from the European<br />
learning and tradition your members have brought to us, as<br />
indeed the whole of Australia has benefited from the<br />
contribution made by the Jewish community to our society. </p>
<p>To name a few of the great Australians who have been members<br />
of the Jewish community is to appreciate just how<br />
substantial that contribution has been: Monash, Head of the<br />
Armed Forces; Isaacs, Chief Justice and Governor-General;<br />
Cowen, Governor-General; Stone, jurist and teacher.<br />
Youts is a remarkable and vibrant community and a special<br />
occasion like the 75th anniversary of the nation's largest<br />
congregation is an appropriate and proper time to<br />
acknowledge that fact.<br />
over the last 75 years this Synagogue has seen many<br />
developments in this country and in the history of the<br />
Jewish peopl. Not least among these was the formation and<br />
development of~ the State of Israel.<br />
Australians have every reason to be proud of their<br />
involvement in the events leading up to the creation of<br />
Israel in 1948.<br />
Australian soldiers played a valuable role in the Middle<br />
East in two World Wars.<br />
We are proud to have been able to champion the cause of<br />
Israel in the UN Special Committee on Palestine in 1947,<br />
which led to the UN Partition Resolution and the<br />
establishment of the State of Israel.<br />
I am especially proud that it was H. V. Evatt, Foreign<br />
Minister in an Australian Labor Party government, who was<br />
the General Assembly President when Israel was admitted to<br />
the United Nations. In that forum on many occasions since<br />
then, Australia has been noted for its support for Israel.<br />
my personal interest in Israel was sparked the first time I<br />
set foot there in 1971.<br />
I was impressed by and indeed envied the electoral and<br />
administrative success of the Israel Labor Party, which had<br />
then been in power for over twenty years especially since<br />
at the time the Australian Labor Party had been out of<br />
office for about the same number of years.<br />
I was impressed too by the strength of the Trade Union<br />
Movement, the Histadrut. And as a social democrat, I could<br />
not fail to respect the way in which Israel had incarnated<br />
the vision of David Ben Gurion of a working class building<br />
its own nation through its own physical and intellectual<br />
labour.<br />
What particularly impressed me, however, was the fundamental<br />
fact that Israel was a democracy, a remarkable democracy,<br />
incessantly engaged in democratic disputation about every<br />
aspect of national policy. </p>
<p>The respect which I felt for these aspects of Israeli life<br />
has been fortified on every subsequent visit I made there<br />
and most especially on my most recent visit in late January.<br />
On that occasion I had the honour, having accepted an<br />
invitation from the President of Israel, His Excellency Mr<br />
Chaim Herzog, of becoming the first Australian Prime<br />
M4inister to visit Israel.<br />
I was received with very great generosity by President<br />
Herzog, Pri-. ne Minister Shamnir, Deputy Prime Minister Shimon<br />
Peres and other outstanding personalities such as Abba Eban.<br />
I held talks with them and a large number of Ministers and<br />
leader of che Labor Party and Trade Union. It was a great<br />
pleasure for me to be among old friends.<br />
A personal highlight of the visit to Israel was the gesture<br />
of Hebrew University in Jerusalem in honouring me with the<br />
award of an Honorary Doctorate of Philosophy. I do not need<br />
to remind this gathering of the brilliant intellectual<br />
tradition~ s of that great university.<br />
While in Jerusalem I also had the moving experience of<br />
meeting with mothers and relatives of refuseniks people<br />
who have been prevented, often over many years, from<br />
reuniting with their families who are unable to leave the<br />
Soviet Untion.<br />
One case struck me as particularly unjust: it involves a<br />
woman, Mrs Sofia Landver, who had applied for a visa to<br />
enter the Soviet Union to see her mother who was dying of<br />
cancer. After our meeting, I took steps to have Mrs<br />
Landver's case investigated, and was delighted to hear<br />
that she was granted a visa. Tragically, however the news<br />
came too late her mother died before they could be<br />
reunited.<br />
At least it can be acknowledged that the Soviet authorities<br />
granted Mrs Landver a visa and I understand that two other<br />
relatives of Mrs Landver's mother have since been given exit<br />
visas to leave the Soviet Union.<br />
As I said in Parliament on Tuesday, since coming to office<br />
the Government has taken every available opportunity to<br />
raise its concerns about the plight of the Soviet Jewry. Mr<br />
Hayden, -the Minister for Foreign Affairs, raised the matter<br />
directly with the Soviet authorities in Moscow in 1984. I<br />
think it is well known that I have raised it on occasions<br />
with the Soviet Ambassador. An Australian parliamentary<br />
delegation to the Soviet Union last year again raised the<br />
question with high level authorities. This delegation made<br />
a new appeal for the release of Jewish activists still<br />
imprisoned in the Soviet Union especially, Dr losef Begun<br />
who was in detention for having taught Hebrew in the Soviet<br />
union. </p>
<p>4.<br />
I know that all of us here would have been heartened by the<br />
news after some days of confusion that it has been<br />
confirmed that Dr Begun has been released.<br />
I have made it clear that when the Soviet Foreign Mlinister,<br />
Mr Shevardn. dze, visits Australia next month, I will be<br />
raising with him the question of the treatment of Soviet<br />
Jewry. while I was in the Middle East I1 spent much of my time<br />
discussing v-ith the government leaders the complex issues<br />
underlying the Arab-Israeli dispute.<br />
The fundamental theme that emerged from my talks in all the<br />
countries I visited Jordan and Egypt as well as Israelwas<br />
the desire of all the governments for peace.<br />
This sincere desire was marked not just by a yearning for<br />
the absence of conflict but by a perception that real and<br />
lasting peace will permit economic development, and yield<br />
improvements in the quality of the everyday life of the<br />
peoples of nll nations there.<br />
Nobody should pretend that such an outcome is easy or is<br />
likely to come soon. Indeed my visit took place at a time<br />
when progress towards peace seems to have stalled.<br />
There are nc immediate prospects for a breakthrough. At the<br />
same time I was encouraged by the fact that the commitment<br />
to peace by the nations I visited has not died.<br />
Indeed, I detected a sense of realistic determination to<br />
continue, slovwly but persistently, the search for progress.<br />
Moreover, as I told Parliament this week, I believe there<br />
are ideas and concepts which, if pursued, would offer a way<br />
ahead.<br />
Australia socks no mediating or other role in the Middle<br />
East peace process. However, as I made clear during my<br />
visit, we are willing, if requested, to do all we can to<br />
help bring peace to this divided yet fundamentally<br />
interrelated region. I believe no Australian Government can<br />
or should offer less.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I said at the outset that the 75 years in which this<br />
Synagogue hc. s served the community have witnessed some of<br />
the most momentous events in the history of the Jewish<br />
people. Let uis all hope that we witness another, greater,<br />
chapter: the attainment of real peace in the Middle East<br />
and the consequent improvement in the quality of life for<br />
all the peoples of the region. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
