<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1057</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 16/1965 - ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. JOHN MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/02/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001057.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
65/ 012<br />
FOR PRESS, P. M. No. 16/ 196~<br />
ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Ministers.. the Rt. o4J c~ krp<br />
The Acting Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. John McEwen,<br />
announced tonight that invitations had been extended to<br />
representatives of national organisations to participate in a<br />
further series of economic consultations to be held on 24th<br />
and 25th of February. The Government has had very useful<br />
discussions with representatives of industry and commerce over<br />
the past few years and the present meetings are being arranged<br />
' to enable the Government to get the mos t up-to-date views of<br />
business and other organisations on developments in the Australian<br />
e conomy, A cormittee of Ministers will meet representatives<br />
of a group of national organisations in Canberra on the afternoon<br />
of Wednesday, 24th February. The organisations invited to attend<br />
are Associated Chambers of Commerce of Australia.<br />
Associated Chambers of Manufactures of Australia<br />
National Farmers' Union of Australia<br />
Australian Primary Producers' Union<br />
Australian Woolgrowers' and Graziers' Council<br />
Australian Wool and Meat Producerst Federation<br />
Australian Bankers' Association<br />
Master Builderst Federation of Australia<br />
Federal Chamber of Automotive Industries<br />
Australian Council of Retailers<br />
On the evening of Wednesday, 24th February, Ministers<br />
will have discussions with representatives of the Australian<br />
Council of Trade Unions. At 2.30 P. m. on 25th February, Ministers<br />
will meet representatives of the Manufacturing Industries<br />
Advisory Council, and at 4+ p. m. representatives of the Export<br />
Development Council,<br />
CALNBERRA,<br />
February 7, 1965. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
