<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3283</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA TO SEEK PRESIDENCY OF UN GENERAL ASSEMBLY NEXT YEAR</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003283.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 4 June 1974<br />
Press Statement No. 255<br />
AUSTRALIA TO SEEK PRESIDENCY OF U. N. GENERAL ASSEMBLY NEXT YEAR<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, confirmed today's press<br />
report that in ' March of this year, prior to the general elections,<br />
Australia had begun actively to seek support for the candidature<br />
' of the Foreign Minister, Senator Willesee, for the Presidency of<br />
the General Assembly of the United Nations in 1975.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that, on the assumption that<br />
Senator Willesee would be re-elected to the Ministry and<br />
reappointed as the Foreign Minister, the Government intended to<br />
proceed with his candidature for the Presidency of the Assembly.<br />
Mr Whitlam recalled that Senator Willesee had led the Australian<br />
delegation to the General Assembly session last year, and was<br />
alrea dy well known to many delegation leaders.<br />
Mr Whitlan said that this action underlined the<br />
importance which the Government attached to the United Nations in<br />
its foreign policy and he recalled the constructive contributions<br />
being made by Australia to the work of the United Nations. He noted<br />
that in addition to its energetic support for the peacekeeping,<br />
human rights, decolonisation, and economic and technical activities<br />
of the United Nations, Australia is currently a member of the Security<br />
Council and the Economic and Social Council which are major organs<br />
of the United Nations under the Charter. As President of the<br />
Security Council in October 1973, the Australian Ambassador to<br />
the United Nations, Sir Laurence McIntyre, played an important role<br />
in helping to achieve a ceasef ire resolution in the Middle East.<br />
Australia's current term as a member of the Security Council ends<br />
on 31 December this year.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that the Government was determined to<br />
maintain its forward-looking policies which had been so well received<br />
in the United Nations.<br />
Australia is a member of the Western European and Others<br />
group in the United Nations, and it is the turn of that group to<br />
nominate the candidate for the Presidency of the General Assembly in<br />
1975. In March of this year preliminary soundings were started about<br />
the possibility of the group endorsing Senator Willesee as its<br />
candidate for the Presidency of the General Assembly in 1975.<br />
Consultations with members of the group are continuing. The Prime<br />
Minister recalled that Australia last held the Presidency of the<br />
General Assembly in 1948/ 49 when the late Dr H. V. Evatt was President<br />
of the Third Session of the General Assembly.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
