<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5862</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE 1ST WORLD MERINO CONFERENCE, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/07/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005862.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
j.. i AI.-.<br />
0O * 1% WEDJNESDAY1 14 OULY -82<br />
Std~ OPENING OP TiHE 1ST WrORLsD MOI3NO M rER: N~ LO~~<br />
' I ot1 d*-I C! to congratulatO the Australian: Association of<br />
-qani~ vin the first evr Worl. d<br />
'. onrnc n o lon on Ihehalf of thie Australian<br />
GC6vsrurnernt and paopl-all the o~ vers; eas vjisitor attending this<br />
Pnirec~ 1.~ ldalso like to take fthis opportwity to<br />
apaud_'. eT. 3no breaders for thleir slkill alld parserverance ill<br />
~ p~ o~ ngtrieI~ eii b-reed, ana in adaptingk im 3i to M. eet<br />
thie* 1halen 5. e s faced by the wool induetry over the years.<br />
-CrS -J<br />
Thri 1t'l~ doabt that tile ne-rin~ o is theip inost succassf-u.<br />
-,-her-t-M--ucoes tit s has not com~ e about by chance.<br />
Xit nas b 1 very larcrely ahievt throughI the effort. s of-.-he<br />
breders, tb: hIough a thorough . dr1tandinacndj luvowlerfte of<br />
thr-ough obssayvation and patient seD. 6-ction, helpead<br />
-11-t Ore3 ~ e u t Yasby 6emlopnmtD in o!) ective methods of<br />
mar aqaant and e: xperirnntation.<br />
M~~ irlo3, utfr ao heaviel-f leczces than in earlier yas h<br />
AV~ r~~ 4oolproduction for shecp bas Taore than doubled, to<br />
merillos were f irst brought to<br />
Ai tralia. A nu~ mber of growers are-nc-I wavoracjing 6 or 7 hilos,<br />
-n'~ tsh plernentary feekiinc, some sheep are producing tan<br />
Th woliiiiistry. has haclto face a numbier of challenger&gt; over<br />
t y~ ra. In ths 195 s, tile inidustry as; a wbole suffered zfrom<br />
a 1~ 0ñ confidenlce in~ the face of som,, very real threats a!" I<br />
diffticulties*. + one of the major chiallenges came fromr Bynthatics,<br />
h-ere--n-w -anc glamorou5. All. the doubts alt-outw4th.-.<br />
r wo -j-1: would zurvive, all the old arguments about bled. n<br />
ok'--ears-to overcorie. But the wool industry has, coma-through<br />
stongy, ~ Q! just because notliing can match woo)., b'ut also<br />
pae n' he industry since the 1.950s. The ability to blend<br />
001OXVith t-1tics hav obviously boeen of enormoisly vall. le<br />
~'-a33istanda to the wqool rTvar) 1et, and technical advancaE; such as<br />
Swhich would have seenw ed n thiiikable 30 years ago,<br />
avmofrIorp-p~ u1la r. Lch<br />
t~ hteto the Intcr-nationa). Wool Secretariat and clbser<br />
o h~, ths. Atr q) a Wool Corporation, that the maxl;,' ting of<br />
p~ iiticcated and succe-ssful business.<br />
I </p>
<p>b. _ T2 _ 11-7<br />
Ih f1sta1! r -priernceris, andt i VS14tf preeth wooldp roic~ on for<br />
r ny y-eas anW e rrt r e : i~ O1m1Yoki~ prkam~<br />
wbn--~ yp~-e -ar--f-l-injit ii; good thst e have<br />
Tie a', ble to adopt a ; rall inarease: in the floor price orthc<br />
l9~ 2/ 3. seas-on.<br />
~-~ K~ oor zie~ Schem~ e,__ finan6e( by the gjrowers themmselves,<br />
h~ h~ ta . abillse retu.-ns an'd azlttic same, tiT~ e proved filnaIcially<br />
ucc sul.. As a result of this suiccess, growers have already<br />
r~ eved -sorne refunds on their Xevy paymients. $ 42 million<br />
.1paid bac% to growers last year, anid a furtber payment-of<br />
f contiing sucss of wool ienains very iMportaiit to<br />
at _ ralia, -17o-1980/ 81, for example, -Uhe ex: port value of Merinio<br />
Iloi ve ahned . m-eat is esti:! citeda at over $ 1.5 billion<br />
~ bo.~ t S~ of ths totnl value of our exports The wo uuty~<br />
~ X~ C~ itY. to inodernise and3 ada pt to chanuce, combine' with its<br />
heriation to mnaintain and inrv tandards of production<br />
_? VI'de -groiinds for very real co.-nfi cence in the industry s<br />
-fu tdra*. The fitutrt~-l--1-t clibt-4rirmg ne w challenges to<br />
badi3-n Mar} ketincj, rind changas in consumer demands.<br />
Conhferenccs s~ ich a s thisr can pliay an : itprtant role in<br />
S helpina-. the industry as a whole, and also irm. ividual sheep man,<br />
to,-grasp riew-i6SUep. and cliallengea as they arise. I ami s ure<br />
~ vt ptf4~ teat this Conference will be able to gain from<br />
the ntechatge of irnfoz-mation wihwill take place, ancl fromt<br />
rigaott a ,-tvs-1dmhodsr sv-. of imerino<br />
In other couintrios.<br />
end, thq continued success of. merinios and the wool industry<br />
1 oekac' 2Lbe'aId ( oht~ h~ len greatest challenge of<br />
thftUre will be the b~ reedinij of new andI even more<br />
an 0m:-erxino.-This will particularly so in Autralia<br />
w1 ars it1-ree. t arters of our 136D million sheep are Merinos,<br />
dfld~ aoutlO of the iworla's sheep are Avstralian rrexinos.<br />
-kP -Iiois nartio' 11arly fitting' that ti Conference is<br />
t~ k. Pp-aek arou-nd the time of the one-hundredth Melbourne<br />
~ 2&gt; 7Sh~ pShowi I am sure it w'ill be a fsucce. ss-ful. conference, the<br />
fjst-of inany. in. the _ veara2 lnLae great pleasure<br />
in eclainig the. Conference opan. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
