<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8248</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AUSTRALIAN AND YOUNG AUSTRALIAN OF THE YEAR AWARDS SYDNEY - 26 JANUARY 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008248.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A TAL( IA<br />
CH~ r-AGANSZYLLVRY. EMBARGOED UNTIL DELLIE1Y<br />
SPEECH By THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
AUSTRALIAN AND YOUNG AUSTRALIAN OF THE YEAR AWARDS<br />
SYDNEY 26 JANUARY 1991<br />
With our vantage point here looking out onto Sydney Harbour<br />
it's easy to understand why Australia's lifestyle is envied<br />
throughout the world.<br />
Simply, it reminds us just what a great nation Australia is.<br />
Australia Day is traditionally a day for getting out of<br />
doors: and enjoying the Harbours and beaches and parks and<br />
backyards throughout the nation, and for enjoying the<br />
company of family and friends.<br />
I hope everyone has a chance to do that today.<br />
But it was never intended that Australia Day would merely be<br />
a day for self indulgence or complacency.<br />
It's a day for reflecting on the character of our nation,<br />
and for remembering the debt we owe to our predecessors who<br />
achieved so much and built so much on our behalf and for our<br />
benefit. And especially on Australia Day 1991 do we need to bear in<br />
mind the sacrifices others are making on our behalf.<br />
For t~ he first time in twenty years, Australia Day 1991 sees<br />
Australian defence forces serving overseas, committed to<br />
combat in a difficult and hazardous conflict in the Persian<br />
Gulf.. The 1houghts of all of us today are with those of our fellow<br />
Australians performing this vital task on our behalf. And<br />
let us remember too their families and loved ones who are<br />
waitiLng for them to come home safely. No one can tell<br />
preciLsely when that will be, but as I said in Parliament<br />
this week it will be as soon as possible, when the job is<br />
done. Let's also bear in mind the hardships being experienced by<br />
our embassy staff in the Middle East and by other<br />
Australians living and working in the region. We wish them<br />
all a safe return. </p>
<p>2.<br />
my friends,<br />
Australians have good reason for feeling and expressing<br />
their pride in this our country today.<br />
We have created a free and democratic land a tolerant and<br />
civilised society a close-knit community. Of course we<br />
should be proud of all that. Certainly, our lifestyle is<br />
and remains one that the world envies; we're still a magnet<br />
for tourists and for new settlers from around the world.<br />
But we who have the stewardship of our nation today must<br />
continue to work hard if we are to see these successes-built<br />
on and not frittered away.<br />
The past year was a testing one for the nation and 1991 will<br />
bring its own challenges and difficulties.<br />
But I want all Australians to understand that this nation<br />
can successfully navigate its way through these difficult<br />
times and. that we will do so.<br />
The past year for example has seen a new spirit of cooperation<br />
emerge among the three levels of government, and a<br />
new commitment to building a more effective and efficient<br />
federal system and a more flexible and competitive<br />
p Australian economy.<br />
We have made significant progress. But our governments will<br />
not achieve: this goal alone. It is my hope that this<br />
remaining decade before we celebrate the centenary of the<br />
Australian Commonwealth will be one marked by continued cooperation<br />
at all levels of our community.<br />
We must not, sacrifice the gains made for us nor squander the<br />
opportunities now before us. We have built with the support<br />
of people from around the globe a nation of tolerance,<br />
fairness, innovation and courage. John Newcombd and I are<br />
about to present a number of Australia Day awards to<br />
individual Australians who embody these very qualities<br />
people whom we honour today, our national day, as<br />
Australians; of the Year.<br />
It is my belief too that these very qualities of<br />
tolerance, fairness, innovation and courage -must now carry<br />
us forward to the prosperity and peace which we seek for<br />
ourselves and our children. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
