<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2023</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: U.S. ASTRONAUT TO BE CORAL SEA GUEST OF HONOUR</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/03/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002023.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 32/ 1969<br />
U. S. ASTRONAUT TO BE CORAL SEA GUEST OF HONOUR<br />
The Governments of Australia and the United States<br />
announced today that R. Walter Cunningham, lunar module pilot of<br />
Apollo 7, will be the official guest of honour during the Coral Sea<br />
Commemoration ceremonies to take place in Australia from 3-11<br />
May. Mrs. Cunningham will accompany the astron E'<br />
Their itinerary will include Canberra, Bris ape/ ,7 0~<br />
Adelaide, Melbourne and Sydney. I969<br />
They will visit Australia as the guests of the<br />
Commonwealth Government and the Australian-American<br />
Association. Details of the programme will be announced later.<br />
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE:<br />
Mr. Cunningham was born on 16 March 1932, at<br />
Creston, Iowa. Reared in Venice, California, he received a<br />
Bachelor of Arts Degree in Physics from the University of<br />
California at Los Angeles ( UCLA) in 1960 and a Master of Arts<br />
Degree in Physics in 1961 from that same University.<br />
Cunningham joined the United States Navy in 1951<br />
and entered flight training in 1952. He was assigned to a Marine<br />
squadron in 1953 and remains a Marine reservist.<br />
Prior to his selection as an astronaut, Cunningham<br />
was with the Rand Corporation where he worked as a research<br />
scientist. He performed error analysis and feasibility studies of<br />
defence against submarine -launched ballistic missiles and problems<br />
of the earth's magnetosphere. His later work at UCLA was the<br />
developing, testing, and analysing results of a triaxial search<br />
coil magnetometer which was flown aboard the first NASA Orbiting<br />
Geophysical Observatory satellite.<br />
Cunningham was one of the 14 astronauts selected<br />
by NASA in October 1963.<br />
He is married to the former Lo Ella Irby of Norwalk,<br />
California. The Cunninghams have two children: Brian, born 12<br />
September 1960; and Kimberly born 12 February 1963.<br />
CANBERRA 27 March 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
