<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3067</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE, PEKING</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003067.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
If~ fak AFFAIRS FM S<br />
M/ 166 UATIfE 8 November 1973<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE. PEKING<br />
Below is the transcript of the Prime Minister,<br />
Mr Whitlam's press conference held in Peking, China, on<br />
4 November, 1973.<br />
.4 .1<br />
0 Qi~ PRIME MINISTER: Ladies and gentlemen: You already have the<br />
Joint Press Communique. There is one thing I can add to it.<br />
Following the dinner the Australian delegation gave to the<br />
Premier and the Chinese side last night, there will be discussions<br />
about a Treaty of Nationality between the two governments. There<br />
are two other things I should say about the questions which I will<br />
invite you to put to me. One is, I gather it is the custom of<br />
this country for guests not to purport to state the policies or<br />
views of the host. Secondly, it is the custom not to detail<br />
conversations which the Chairman has with visitors. The subjects<br />
of the conversations have already been given to you. There is<br />
one matter of particular importance which my colleague,<br />
Dr Patterson, could announce to you at this stage.<br />
DR PATTERSON: Mr Prime Minister, ladies and gentlemen: As you<br />
know Mr Crean and I have had discussions with several ministries<br />
over the last few days. And one of the very important and<br />
substantial matters which has been now finalised is that the<br />
Chinese Government has agreed to purchase very large quantities<br />
of sugar from Australia within the provisions of a long-term sugar<br />
agreement with Australia. Quantities involved are in the vicinity<br />
of 300,000 tons of sugar per year. The initial agreement will be<br />
three to five years duration. Details will be the subject of<br />
further discussions between the Australian Sugar Industry and the<br />
China National Cereals Oil and Foodstuffs Import and Export<br />
Corporation and the governments of China and Australia. For<br />
some time the industry in Australia, the sugar industry in<br />
Australia, has been anxious for China to install specialised modern<br />
; 6k </p>
<p>-2-<br />
bulk handling facilities for the importation of sugar large<br />
quantities of sugar and the Chinese Government is making<br />
arrangements to install specialised modern bulk receiving<br />
facilities for raw sugar as well as some other commodities.<br />
Also, the Chinese Government is making arrangements to send a<br />
team of technical people to Australia to study and inspect<br />
Australia's bulk handling facilities which are amongst the most<br />
modern in the world. I might say gentlemen that this agreement<br />
will be of tremendous importance to Australia. lt is the<br />
culmination of a series of discussions which commenced when<br />
Mr Whitlam first came to China in 1971. We have carried it on<br />
carried those discussions on a number of ways since that time<br />
and the sugar industry in Australia through the C. S. R. company<br />
who are the agents have also continued those discussions.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: N'lay I repeat the significance of the concluding<br />
remarks that Dr Patterson made. He inaugurated these discussions<br />
in July 1971. They have come to a successful conclusion on his<br />
return visit. Are there any questions to Mr Crean, Dr Patterson<br />
or me'?<br />
Q. Prime Minister, can I ask Dr Patterson a question?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
Q. Can you place any estimate, any value, on this agreement<br />
with China?<br />
DR PATTERSON: The details, as I mentioned, will be worked out<br />
in discussions between the industry, the two industry<br />
representatives, and the Governments. But, naturally, they will<br />
be related to world prices. World prices at the present time<br />
are $ 150 Australian per ton so it will be, if you take present<br />
world prices, it is a figure somewhere around 850 million per year<br />
over a three to five year period. But it could be, of course,<br />
that long-term negotiations as with the Commonwealth Sugar<br />
Agreement, that the long-term price will be a fair price to both<br />
countries not necessarily a high price. That is it will be a fair<br />
price, a negotiated price, as has been the practice in the<br />
long-term sugar agreement between Australia and the Commonwealth<br />
Sugar Agreement with Britain which, as you know, expires at the </p>
<p>-3-<br />
end of next year.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, may I ask a question? Vie understand, while<br />
cin Peking, you lodged a protest to the Chinese Government about<br />
the nuclear testing in the atmosphere. Can you give us the terms<br />
of that protest and indicate the response of the Chinese Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This subject was raised in the conversation with<br />
Chairman Mao. As I said, details of such conversations are not<br />
disclosed. The approach that the Australian Government has made<br />
on this matter is well known. I reiterated it.<br />
Q. That's with Chairman Mao. What about with the Premier? Does<br />
the same answer apply?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. He was there. The Premier was there in the<br />
talks with the Chairman, as also was the Assistant Foreign Minister.<br />
Q. Was the question raised in the other talks.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, could you be a bit more explicit on the<br />
Treaty of Nationality which you referred to in your opening<br />
remarks? PRIME MINISTER: There is very little more I can say at this<br />
Sstage. It covers the general question of what nationality people<br />
6elong to irrespective of or dependent on their ancestry. And<br />
there has been a confusion up until now about the doctrine of dual<br />
nationality as asserted in respect to persons of Chinese ancestry<br />
Ioverseas. The confusion has been largely due to the fact that<br />
the Kuomintang Government, the Chiang Kai-shek regime always<br />
asserted that persons of Chinese ancestry abroad remained<br />
Chinese citizens. This is not an attitude that the Government<br />
of the People's Republic has ever taken.<br />
Q. The question of the Middle East. Premier Chcu raised this<br />
Oy in private discussion with you. Did he say what he thought of<br />
the Australian attitude of neutrality in the Middle East?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: First question, yes. Second question, no.<br />
We discussed the Middle East question as, I suppose, I can say we<br />
discussed practically every matter anywhere in Asia. We stated </p>
<p>-4-<br />
our respective positions. There was no suggestion by the<br />
Premier that Australia' s attitude should change. I heard his<br />
attitude, he heard mine. It was one of the matters upon which<br />
we differed.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, did you discuss defence and, if so, can<br />
p T you outline to us your own defence projects for the region?<br />
PRIMVE MINISTER: We didn't discuss the question of defence at all.<br />
The other subject, I think, is rather too wide to take up here.<br />
Q. As a result of your talks do you feel there is any role for<br />
SAustralia in helping to improve relations between China and the<br />
five important South-East Asian countries in their relations with<br />
Australia? PRIME MINISTER: I believe the example of the fruitful relations<br />
between China and Australia will be reassuring to the ASEAN<br />
nations. Q. Did Premier Chou repeat the request 1 believe he made to<br />
Overseas Trade Minister, Dr Cairns a request that Australia<br />
might be able to explain to these countries in South-East Asia<br />
which don't at the moment recognise China, explain to them the<br />
Chinese point of view particularly on the question of overseas<br />
Chinese and the nationality question. Did he ask you to pass on<br />
any messages?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. However, I heard his views on all these<br />
matters, so naturally when I discuss any such matters with the<br />
ASEAN countries I would have in my mind the view of the Chinese<br />
Government as I heard it directly from the Premier. But the<br />
Premier certainly didn't seek for Australia a role of apologist<br />
or intermediary in any way. I was very happy to hear his views<br />
on all these matters, and he seemed interested in hearing my<br />
views my government's views on such matters.<br />
Q. Did Premier Chou ask you to explain the Australian position<br />
QO on the Five Power Arrangements?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There wa s scarcel y any mention of -this. It was<br />
mentioned but very briefly. </p>
<p>Q. While you said Premier Chou did not ask you to become an<br />
intermediary link with South-East Asian countries, is it your<br />
intention to try to explain to them the Chinese view or is it just<br />
a matter of if they raise it? Are you going to specifically go<br />
out to try to explain China's position in the ASEA1i countries?<br />
i'RIIEh MINISTER: I have said again and again that the Australian<br />
Government doesn't seek or purport to be an advocate or apologist<br />
for any other government including the Chinese Government. Very<br />
clearly, however, in having discussions with any of the AflEAN<br />
countries, and there will be such discussions in Australia within<br />
the next couple of weeks and there will be in all of them within<br />
three months. In their countries this subject would be<br />
discussed. It would be a pretty empty discussion if such matters<br />
were not discussed. I expect it would be discussed. The<br />
discussion as far as I am concerned will be all the more relevant<br />
in the light of the discussions I have had in Peking.<br />
Q. You will feel. free to pass on Premier Chou's explanation<br />
of the Chinese attitude?<br />
PRINE MNITSTER: I will certainly explain the position as I<br />
understand it. But it is not a question of passing on any<br />
messages or views, that was not sought, and it was not<br />
volunteered. I don't think you would expect it to be sought<br />
or volunteered. The great advantage of talks in depth and at<br />
length that we have been able to have this week is that there has<br />
bc-, en an opportunity of getting a very thorough understanding of<br />
all relevant matters.<br />
Q. ~ eunderstand you have issued an invitation to Premier Chou<br />
Ito come to Australia. L'as there any indication from him whether<br />
e S~ ewould accept?<br />
PRIME MINISTERt: The Premior knows that he would be very welcome<br />
to the Australian people and the Australian Government. I think,<br />
however, one must accept that there are some office bearers in<br />
the world to whom it would be an embarrassment to press an<br />
invitation. A man who is Premier of China or is President of<br />
the United States cannot be expected to accept a fraction of the<br />
t}<br />
S 0 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
invitations that he receives. There are already scores of<br />
invitations on the Premier's plate. Obviously we would be very<br />
happy to receive a visit from him, but it is not really courteous<br />
to press such invitations. There will be, I would expect, quite<br />
regular interchanges of visits between Ministers and officials or<br />
our two governments. The great thing that has been achieved this<br />
week is that a generation of lost contact between our two peoples<br />
has been successfully brought to an end. We can now communicate,<br />
in Australia, in China, between ministers and officials and<br />
people of the two countries without any inhibitions. The lost<br />
generation is now buried.<br />
Q. Did you raise your idea of a regional forum and, if so, what<br />
was the Chinese reaction?~<br />
PRIME MINISTEF: The general idea is welcomed. Clearly, however,<br />
it takes a little time to create such an arrangement or framework<br />
where you still have some confusion about diplomatic relations<br />
between countries in this region of the Western Pacific or<br />
South-East Asia. I notice I have had a few questions but very<br />
few questioners.<br />
Q. Dr Patterson, about the Sugar Agreement. Will the Sugar<br />
Agreement have a cushioning effect on the Australian Sugar<br />
industry at the time of the ending of the Commonwealth Sugar<br />
Agreement? DR PATTERSON: As you know, the British Commonwealth Sugar<br />
Agreement is due to expire at the end of next year. It is the<br />
stated intention of the British Government to phase out the<br />
335,000 long tons which Australia sells to Britain and has sold<br />
for a long number of years. It is hoped that that phasing out<br />
period will be around three years. The effect of the proposed<br />
long-term agreement between China and Australia will naturally<br />
be well received because in the event of the loss of this<br />
British market occurring suddenly then we would be able to phase<br />
in the new or proposed agreement. You can see the significance<br />
of it because it will be bigger than the United States quota<br />
for Australia under the United States Sugar Act and the<br />
C( c<br />
0 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
magnitude of this agreement can be guaged by the fact that the<br />
biggest bilateral or special arrangement between Australia and<br />
any other nation.<br />
Q. Do you regard the Chinese Government's willingness to allow<br />
Chinese nationals to migrate to Australia as a concession?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There were no arrangements hitherto, so we now<br />
have the position where there can now be family reunion with China<br />
as already with many other countries. You remember that this<br />
4D~ matter was raised in the Parliament a fortnight ago by Mr Martin<br />
Nicholls.<br />
oc Q. How do you see the future relations between Australia and<br />
China as a result of this visit?'<br />
Cl PRIME MINISTER: VV'e can now expect that there will be direct and<br />
substantial relations between China and Australia as there should<br />
be between countries of our respective significance in this<br />
region or, indeed, in the world. It has been a very great gap<br />
in the relations of each country that there were no direct<br />
relations between both of them. The fruitful relations between<br />
China and Australia will make for fruitful relations between<br />
China and many other countries in the region and between Australia<br />
and many other countries in the region. It is a good rational<br />
friendly breakthrough.<br />
cQy Q. Could you tell us something about how the results of your<br />
recent visit to Japan last week were appreciated here in China?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The significance of Japan's and Australia's<br />
relations were well appreciated because of the sheer magnitude<br />
of the trade between the two of us. It was understood, I think,<br />
that Australia sold more to Japan than to any other country and<br />
Japan sells more to Australia than to any country other than the<br />
United States. It was accepted, therefore that relations between<br />
Japan and Australia must become very close indeed.<br />
Q. You said that the Middle East was one area of disagreement<br />
between the two governments and nuclear testing was obviously<br />
another. Can you tell us the other areas on which you disagree?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Bangladesh, Korea. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
Q. During your visit here I understand you met Prince Sihanouk,<br />
the head at' the Cambodian Government in exile. Can you tell us<br />
the purpose arnd the outcome of that discussion?<br />
PRIPM MINISTER: While I was in Peking where Prince Sihanouk<br />
Sresides, I welcomed the opportunity to have an exchange of views<br />
with him. He is the acknowledged spokesman of GRUNK and FUNK.<br />
He is the only representative of either who is known to me or to<br />
the ambassador or to Australians in general. It was a valuable<br />
c7~ opportunity to hear at first hand his views on the situation<br />
in his country and in the region.<br />
Q. It doesn't suggest any change in our recognition of the<br />
present Lon Nol Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, as long as the Lon Nol Government is in<br />
possession of the capital of Cambodia and is in the United Nations<br />
the present Australian attitude towards it will continue.<br />
Q. How are we voting in the United Nations?<br />
PRIME MlNISTER: We have been abstaining on the procedural issues.<br />
Q. Will we continue to abstain?<br />
X' PRIME MINISTER: When the question of the seating of the<br />
Government arises wve will vote for that Government with which<br />
we have relations. But we are abstaining on the procedural<br />
matters. We did not oppose the inscription of the item. Our<br />
concern in Cambodia is that the people of Cambodia should have a<br />
government of their wish. W'e will do all we can to put an end to<br />
the hostilities and to deter any supplies from outside. It is the<br />
only part of Indo-China where there has not yet been a ceasefire<br />
or an agreement or an accord. This is all the more deplorable<br />
since, for so many years, from the Geneva accords of 1954 until<br />
the invasion of Cambodia by and from South Viet-nam in March 1970<br />
' Cambodia had enjoyed an undiminished peaceful identity.<br />
Q. Mr Crean, did you have the opportunity of discussing the<br />
world inflationary situation with the Chinese?<br />
MCREAN: Yes. Mline have been more in the nature of watching<br />
briefs during these procedures and the Chinese assure us they </p>
<p>-9-<br />
have not got the problem of inflation, but I think they have got<br />
a lot of problems on their plate that I would not like to have.<br />
Q. Did you discuss the question of territorial waters?<br />
PRITE MINISTER: No, we didn't. This is a matter though that the<br />
officials may well have discussed. It is obviously a matter of<br />
very great interest to our two countries. But the Premier and I<br />
didn't discuss it. I believe the interest which we each have are<br />
well understood at the official level. Our ambassador has had<br />
discussions on this matter already.<br />
We have found this a most pleasant visit indeed and the<br />
ambassador, who is in residence here, and all the Australian<br />
officials have enjoyed very much the co-operation of the<br />
Chinese authorities, I believe our visit has been all the more<br />
pleasant and fruitful because we now have such an eminent<br />
ambassador in residence here,. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
