<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2502</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH OFFER TO TEH STATES OF FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE FOR THE RELIEF OF NON-METROPOLITAN UNEMPLOYMENT - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/12/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002502.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 7/<br />
COMMONWEALTH OFFER TO THE STATES OF FINANCIAL<br />
ASSISTANCE FOR THE RELIEF OF NON-METROPOLITAN<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr William McMahon<br />
The Prime Minister said today that following fruitful<br />
discussions between Commonwealth and State officials, which ' e had<br />
proposed in his letter to the Premiers on 1 December, he hae now<br />
written to the Premiers putting the Government's offer in fi... l form.<br />
The Government's view is that the arrangements which have<br />
been developed for the administration of Commonwealth funds provided<br />
to the States for the relief of unemployment under the schemes of<br />
drought assistance should serve broadly as a model for the scheme now<br />
proposed. In particular, it was envisaged that in the pr%( ent case,<br />
funds would be provided in the form of advances paid monthl. y.<br />
As to the types of work to be undertaken, thie Prime<br />
Minister said that the Gov'rnment sees this as a matter which the States<br />
are well equipped to determine, but recognises a need to enchasise<br />
labour-intensive activities, of as productive a kind as possble.<br />
There are, however, limits to the oronortion of expenditure which could<br />
usefully be devoted to labour costs. Thus, in all the circumstances,<br />
the Government would now be prepared to regard it as appropriate if up<br />
to one-third of the funds provided over the balance of this financial<br />
year was, on average over all the projects undertaken, devoted to<br />
expenditure on other than labour costs.<br />
As to the kind of labour to be employed, the Prime<br />
Minister continued, the Government believes this also to be a matter<br />
for each State to decide in the light of its own particular requirements<br />
and priorities. Iowever, the Government believes that as far<br />
as possible, those employed sh uld have been registered for employment<br />
with the Commonwealth Employment Service, and envisaged that the<br />
Department of Labour and National Ser-ice would be closely associated<br />
with the scheme. The rrime Minister then referred to the question of the<br />
amount and distribution of the funds which the Government is now<br />
offering on a firm basis to the States.<br />
In approaching this question, the Government had<br />
commenced from the figure of $ 2 million a month which, as the Prime<br />
Minister had said in his statement to the House of Representatives, was<br />
the order of cost which the Government had in mind. At the same time, / 2 </p>
<p>in the light of various complexitites associated with the working out<br />
of the detailed application of the scheme, the Government had not had<br />
a closed mind on the matter of the funds to be provided. For example,<br />
the decision to increase the proportion of the total funds which might<br />
be applied to expenditure on other than labour costs was a factor which<br />
had been taken into ,-ount in determining the Government's final<br />
position. Another important consideration in this respect has arisen<br />
out of the consideration of how the total funds should be distributed<br />
between the States. This is, of course, a very complex matter. In<br />
eaching the position finally adopted, the Government had sought to<br />
take into account, as far as possible, the particular problems and<br />
needs of the unemployment situation in the non-metropolitan areas of<br />
each State. While any pattern of distribution arrived at must<br />
ecessarily be open to debate, that now proposed is, in the Government's<br />
iew, the most equitable which could be devised in all the circumstances.<br />
Against that background, the Gover. nment has offered to the<br />
States grants of $ 2.25 million a month, and is willing to apply that<br />
figure as from 1 December last. The total amount of grants payab: le to<br />
all the States during the balance of this financial year woul-. herefore,<br />
bc. $ 15.75 million, distributed as follows millic.<br />
New South ' Tales 6.065<br />
Victoria 3.54;<br />
Queensland 3.15<br />
South Australia 0.. 94:<br />
Western Australia l. lf(<br />
Tasmania 0.865<br />
15.75C<br />
The Government intends that the scheme will :.. j: ct<br />
to review, within six months or so before 30 June 1l972);-i t'. he<br />
light of the then prevailing conditions.<br />
The Prime Minister emphasised that, on the assumption<br />
that it can be put into gear immediately, the Government is prepared to<br />
base the scheme as from 1 December last and, on that basis, the amount<br />
available to each State would be as indicated. He concluded by saying<br />
that, so far as the Government was concerned, the States would be free<br />
to put work in hand immediately.<br />
CANBERRA, 12 December 1971<br />
A 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
