<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8167</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF THE ASIA- AUSTRALIA INSTITUTE SYDNEY 19 OCTOBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008167.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
6.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF THE ASIA-AUSTRALIA INSTITUTE<br />
SYDNEY 19 OCTOBER 1990<br />
Justice Gordon Samuels, Chancellor of the University of<br />
New South Wales<br />
Professor Michael Birt, Vice-Chancellor<br />
Mr Fred Millar, Chairman of the UNSW Foundation<br />
Professor Stephen Fitzgerald<br />
Senator Robert Hill<br />
Ladies Gentlemen<br />
Let me begin this speech about Asia, and about this very<br />
welcome new Asia-Australia Institute, by reflecting first on<br />
developments on the other side of the globe.<br />
Just two weeks ago, the world celebrated the unification of<br />
Germany, and the remaking both of the map of Europe, and,<br />
with it, of the post-war international order.<br />
Earlier this week, we received the news that President<br />
Gorbachev has been awarded the Nobel Peace Prize.<br />
Those remarkable events, which seemed until very recently<br />
unthinkable, impossible, paradoxical even, are dramatic<br />
reminders of how quickly the world is changing.<br />
Australians of course share unreservedly in the celebrations<br />
of these events the emergence of President Gorbachev's<br />
policies of glasnost and perestroika, the dismantling of the<br />
Berlin Wall, the democratisation of much of Eastern Europe,<br />
the fading of rigid ideological divisions, the reduction of<br />
the superpowers' nuclear arsenals, the dramatic draw-down in<br />
conventional forces in Europe. The nightmare of a global<br />
nuclear holocaust is passing and for that we can all be<br />
profoundly thankful.<br />
But no-one, and certainly no-one in Australia, can afford to<br />
be complacent about the international order that is emerging<br />
to replace the rigidities of the Cold War era. </p>
<p>S Saddam Hussein's invasion of Kuwait is a sobering<br />
reminder that large armies and power-hungry governments<br />
can still threaten the common good;<br />
S The struggle to achieve a worthwhile outcome to the<br />
Uruguay Round of trade negotiations is far from over,<br />
and the consequences for Australia and the world at<br />
large of the failure of those negotiations, and a drift<br />
to greater protectionism, or to rigid regional trading<br />
blocs, would be catastrophic;<br />
S We have not reached the point where we can say with<br />
confidence that the international community has the<br />
will decisively to resolve new global issues, notably<br />
the protection of the environment;<br />
S And, of course, old issues ranging from poverty to<br />
abuses of human rights in the world have not<br />
disappeared from the world scene.<br />
So it is important to remember that the world now being<br />
created will not necessarily be a more comfortable one for<br />
Australia. It will certainly be no less competitive. It<br />
will, more than ever, be a world in which Australia has to<br />
work hard to advance our interests, and speak clearly and<br />
forcefully to make our views known.<br />
The task quite fundamentally, will be to ensure, so far as<br />
we can, that the new international order is shaped in ways<br />
which serve Australia's needs and interests.<br />
Of course, Australia is a middle-sized country which has<br />
only limited leverage when dealing with large powers and<br />
with matters remote from our region. But we should never<br />
underestimate the extent to which active and imaginative<br />
Australian policy formulation and diplomacy can influence<br />
the deliberations of the world's councils.<br />
That is why Australia continues to commit heavy resources of<br />
time and effort to the hard, grinding, work of multilateral<br />
diplomacy through the United Nations, of course, which is<br />
undergoing a very heartening revival as an effective<br />
instrument of global will; through forums of disarmament<br />
where we have pressed ahead with the tough but essential<br />
negotiations to ban chemical weapons; through the Antarctic<br />
Treaty where we are working with France to bring about a<br />
total and effective ban on mining there.<br />
And, where no institution has existed in which our interests<br />
in a certain field can be advanced, we have helped fashion<br />
one to meet our specific needs.<br />
We have taken the lead in creating the Cairns Group to take<br />
up the cudgels for liberalised agricultural trade in the<br />
Uruguay Round and of special significance to our immediate<br />
region we have taken the lead in the establishment of a<br />
framework for peace in Cambodia and in the establishment of<br />
the new forum for Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation. </p>
<p>Our success in all these initiatives underlines the<br />
importance to Australia of a stable and peaceful world<br />
order. By the same token, our interests are heavily tied up<br />
with an international system in which blatant breaches of<br />
international law are met by collective action by the<br />
international community as a whole.<br />
This of course was a major reason why my Government decided<br />
to participate in the multinational naval task force in the<br />
Gulf. We were acutely conscious that Iraq's brutal invasion<br />
of Kuwait has provided the first major test a severe test<br />
of the international community's response to aggression in<br />
the post-Cold war period.<br />
So events in Europe, the Middle East, North America and<br />
elsewhere do affect this country's interests in powerful<br />
ways, and my Government has not, and will not, ignore them.<br />
But the area of the world in which Australia will have the<br />
largest interest, and the greatest chance of influencing<br />
outcomes, will be this one the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
There is perhaps no achievement of this Government since<br />
1983 of which I am prouder and none, I am convinced, which<br />
will have a longer-term or more beneficial influence on this<br />
country than the way in which we have worked steadily and<br />
consciously to build up a framework to enmesh Australia more<br />
thoroughly into the Asian region.<br />
And when I chose that word enmesh I meant it. Our policy<br />
concept was not captured by weasel words about developing<br />
relations with the region, enhancing our contacts and so on.<br />
I wanted policy to be driven by a commitment to the most<br />
intimate and irreversible tying of Australia into Asia and<br />
the Pacific.<br />
The reason we have worked so hard to do this is obvious.<br />
The logic of both geography and economics directs Australia<br />
towards the dynamism and vitality of the Asian economies.<br />
The region generates one-third of the world's trade, and<br />
more than half its economic output.<br />
And it contains some of the fastest growing economies in the<br />
world. The success story of Japan and the tigers of Taiwan,<br />
Hong Kong and Singapore are well known. Following in their<br />
wake are the newly-industrialising countries of Southeast<br />
Asia with astounding levels of growth in recent years.<br />
Thailand, for example, has posted consistent annual growth<br />
rates of around 11 per cent; Malaysia and Indonesia have not<br />
been far behind. </p>
<p>Such events challenge Australia in a way, and to an extent,<br />
that we have never been challenged before. So we must make<br />
sure we play a part in the continuing dynamism of the region<br />
a dynamism that is lifting living standards through the<br />
region and that will, ultimately, alter the balance of<br />
economic and political power throughout the globe.<br />
So the policies we have adopted since 1983 have gone far<br />
beyond those weasel words, the simple rhetoric of the past,<br />
to achieve fundamental policy adjustments fundamental<br />
changes to the central areas of our national economic,<br />
social, cultural and educational life.<br />
Several important milestones have marked this process.<br />
First, and most importantly, has been the series of<br />
decisions my Government has taken to make the Australian<br />
economy truly competitive internationally. So long as<br />
Australia remained an isolated economic fortress,<br />
inward-looking and slumbering, we were cut off forever from<br />
full participation in the great shifts going on around us.<br />
So the floating of the Australian dollar, deregulation of<br />
our financial markets, the liberalisation of foreign<br />
investment policy and the reduction of levels of tariff<br />
protection to manufacturing industries by one third, have<br />
all been critical to the process of making Australia more<br />
relevant to Asia, and a closer part of it.<br />
A second important milestone came in 1988, when I<br />
commissioned from Ross Garnaut the report " Australia and the<br />
Northeast Asian Ascendancy" which he delivered to the<br />
Government almost a year ago. I wanted the report to<br />
provide a stimulus for Government and community discussion<br />
about Australia's place in the region, and about how we<br />
might best go about realising our country's almost unbounded<br />
economic potential.<br />
Ross Garnaut's report did just this, providing the most<br />
comprehensive review ever undertaken of Australia's<br />
relations with Northeast Asia, and outlining in great detail<br />
the adjustments required if Australia was truly to become<br />
enmeshed with the region. The Government has already<br />
implemented many of the Garnaut recommendations and is<br />
pressing ahead with a number of others.<br />
A third milestone came, of course, with the Asia-Pacific<br />
Economic Cooperation process that I initiated in Seoul in<br />
January 1989. Since then, several APEC meetings have been<br />
held at ministerial and official level, and a detailed work<br />
program has been adopted to build on the areas of broad<br />
cooperation which have now been identified.<br />
It is undoubtedly true to say that the success of the APEC<br />
process in identifying and advancing the common economic<br />
interests of the countries of our region is now widely<br />
acknowledged. </p>
<p>Australia today is certainly a good example of regional<br />
economic enmneshment.<br />
Eight of Aust~ ralia's top 10 export markets in 1989-90 are in<br />
the Asia-Pac: Lfic region.<br />
APEC members plus the so-called ' three Chinas' the PRC,<br />
Taiwan and Hong Kong take 68 per cent of Australia's<br />
exports and provide 66 per cent of our imports.<br />
This significant economic enmeshment has been matched by<br />
unparalleled efforts to achieve a greater level of cultural<br />
enmeshment. We have sought to raise the level of knowledge<br />
and understanding of Asia in Australia, to reduce what Ross<br />
Garnaut called the sense of " otherness" between Australia<br />
and our regional neighbours.<br />
In 1986 we established the Asian Studies Council, with the<br />
specific mission of strengthening Asian studies at every<br />
level of the Australian education system, and helping<br />
Australian industry become better integrated with economic<br />
development iLn the region.<br />
I note here t: he very important role which the Director of<br />
the Asia-Australia Institute, Dr Stephen Fitzgerald, has<br />
played in the Asian Studies Council, and in the integration<br />
of Asian studies into the broader educational framework in<br />
Australia. The work of the Asian Studies Council is complemented by our<br />
National PoliLcy on Languages and by the establishment of the<br />
Languages Institute of Australia. Together these<br />
initiatives have alerted educators, employers and the<br />
community to the fact that the ability to communicate<br />
linguistically and culturally is crucial to the quality of<br />
Australia's strategic, cultural and economic relations in<br />
the region.<br />
This work is now bearing fruit.<br />
More than ever, Australian children now have opportunities<br />
to learn about the region. The number of Australian<br />
students studying Asian languages has almost doubled over<br />
the past seven years. Over the next three years we aim to<br />
increase by nearly 5,000 the number of places devoted to<br />
Asian languages or Asian studies in our tertiary<br />
institutions, and to give all secondary students access to<br />
the study of an Asian language by the year 2000.<br />
I was particularly pleased, on my recent visit to Tokyo, to<br />
be able to state that there is a higher per capita number of<br />
students learning Japanese at primary, secondary and<br />
tertiary levels in Australia than in any other country<br />
outside Japan. </p>
<p>So taken together, these initiatives have thrust Australia<br />
more fully into the affairs of the Asia Pacific region than<br />
ever before. And as a result, Australia now stands at a<br />
high point of its constructive influence in the region.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
None of this is to say that the relationship between<br />
Australia and Asia is purely the property of the public<br />
sector or to say that fostering the relationship is purely<br />
the Government's responsibility. On the contrary, it simply<br />
can't be if we are to achieve the intimate, broad-ranging<br />
relationship with the region which our policy requires.<br />
In the end, only a changed approach to Asia throughout the<br />
Australian community can deliver the full benefits which<br />
will flow from better understanding of the region, and<br />
enmeshment with it.<br />
This means that all sectors industry, the trade unions,<br />
the media, educational institutions need to transform<br />
their attitudes to Asia.<br />
I must say quite candidly that some sectors have met this<br />
challenge better than others. With a number of<br />
distinguished exceptions some of them represented here<br />
today there are still not enough Australian businesses<br />
prepared to invest in the nurturing of Asian expertise among<br />
their employees, or equipped to take on the Asian market.<br />
There are still not enough Australians willing to make the<br />
effort to learn an Asian language, or to understand an Asian<br />
culture. It is notable, for example, that in 1989-90, Asian<br />
investment in Australia represented almost 21 per cent of<br />
our foreign investment total. But at the same time,<br />
Australian investment in Asia represented only 11 per cent<br />
of our total investment abroad.<br />
In 1989, total merchandise trade with Indonesia, our<br />
immediate neighbour with a market of 180 million people<br />
represented only 1.5 per cent of Australia's total trade.<br />
Only six Australian companies are represented on the ground<br />
in Korea, with its booming market of 50 million.<br />
More than 97 per cent of Australian university and college<br />
graduates still complete their courses without a single unit<br />
focussed on Asia.<br />
That is why I am delighted that the University of New South<br />
Wales has shown the imagination to commit its effort and<br />
resources to establish the Asia-Australia Institute.<br />
I am pleased not just because it will benefit Australia but<br />
because it will also serve the wider needs of the region as<br />
a whole. </p>
<p>4 7.<br />
The Institute's mission to develop an ' Asia consciousness'<br />
among all the countries of our region is an ambitious and<br />
a worthy ideal. The Institute will provide a framework for<br />
the discussion of ideas and for the development of networks<br />
of personal relationships that span Asia.<br />
Let me suggest to you some of the more important questions<br />
that await your consideration questions whose answers can<br />
be elucidated by the Institute and, notably, through the<br />
proposed Asia. Forum that will bring together regional<br />
leaders at the highest levels from inside and outside<br />
government. How can a greater sense of regional identity be<br />
fostered, among the disparate countries of Asia?<br />
What sort of strategic framework do we want to see<br />
emerging in this part of the world?<br />
How can China be encouraged back onto the path of<br />
economic and political liberalisation so that it can<br />
once more resume its full role as a member of the<br />
regional and world community?<br />
As I disecussed in Tokyo recently, what will be Japan's<br />
role as it begins, as it inevitably will, to match its<br />
economic power with new political influence?<br />
Looking beyond a settlement in Cambodia, which this<br />
Government has worked so hard to achieve, how can the<br />
countries of Indo-china be integrated into the dynamic<br />
region around them?<br />
There are no easy answers to any of these questions; but the<br />
University of New South Wales is a particularly appropriate<br />
place to undertake the quest for answers.<br />
The University has a long and distinguished connection with<br />
Asia, including the highest number of students and alumni<br />
from the region of any Australian university. Its<br />
specialist work in Asian languages, its Contemporary Asia<br />
Centre, and its Japanese Economics Management Studies<br />
Centre, are all highly regarded and very relevant to this<br />
exercise. Australia enmeshed with the region, home to a vibrant<br />
multicultural society, and proud of its tradition of free<br />
debate and academic enquiry provides an atmosphere of<br />
unparalleled relevance and stimulation to these efforts.<br />
The Institute's aims are ambitious. That's as it should be.<br />
You have set yourself a job worth doing. You can be assured<br />
of my best wishes as you set out on your task.<br />
I am delighted now to launch the Asia-Australia Institute. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
