<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9592</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP ADDRESS TO THE NATIONAL FARMERS FEDERATION (NFF) ANNUAL CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 17 MAY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009592.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
x'<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
ADDRESS TO THE NATIONAL FARMERS FEDERATION ( NFF) ANNUAL<br />
CONFERENCE, CANBERRA, 17 MAY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
Distinguished members of the conference.<br />
I am very delighted to be able to come, on behalf . of the Government, and<br />
speak to you and to record how appreciative I am, and I think the Government<br />
is, of the fact that you are a body which does look beyond sectional interests<br />
to the broader national policy issues and, as Donald said quite eloquently,<br />
though some of these things are not universally understood in your<br />
constituency, it is nevertheless a matter for you as a body to be able to<br />
articulate them to understand, first of all to put together a comprehensive<br />
approach to policy, to articulate it and to make it relevant to your<br />
constituency. I don't think there is much more a Government could ask of you. But, more<br />
importantly, there is not much more your constituency can ask of you<br />
because we are in a complex world these days. A world of great opportunity,<br />
no doubt, but a complex one and when we talk about agriculture today, we<br />
are talking about all sorts of things not just commodity prices, but<br />
competitiveness and we are talking about best practice and transport and<br />
competition policy and infrastructure and the environment, the global<br />
economy, the US Farm Bill, interest rates, the drought you name it. It is a<br />
very large panoply of issues when one is speaking about rural industry and<br />
its problems and the problems of adjustment.<br />
But I think what is encouraging, certainly to me, has been a willingness on the<br />
part of the rural community, the farm community, to confront these great<br />
economic challenges and recognise the need to make greater changes and I<br />
think one of the strong characteristics of Australia in this last decade or so,<br />
has been not simply a willingness to change, but a willingness to keep it up,<br />
to embrace change and to keep on going and I think that is very important. </p>
<p>A lot of countries are somewhat resistant to change. Their political system<br />
moves away from the prospect of change. As a consequence, their national<br />
economies and societies are not getting the kick along they would otherwise<br />
have if their community was more adaptable to change and more prepared to<br />
listen.<br />
Now I think that in your community, a lot of that has come from leadership, it<br />
has come from the leadership of this body and let me just take this<br />
opportunity to pay a tribute to the leadership of the NFF, in<br />
Donald McGauchie and Rick who is leaving you I know, it will be a great<br />
loss to you because he has played a really useful role in defining the issues<br />
for you as a community, as a constituency and he has had the respect of the<br />
Government and he has been able to relate to us in a way that I think has<br />
been very effective indeed. So no doubt he will be missed.<br />
Could I go on and say that it is probably very unlikely that the NFF and a<br />
Labor Government find themselves as bedfellows, but in quite a number of<br />
issues we have found ourselves in that position. Mainly because this<br />
Government has always been interested in tackling hard issues and trying to<br />
deal with them at source and, I mean, basically we have always been, if you<br />
like, vulnerable to a good argument. If someone has got a good case, we will<br />
listen and if the case is rational and its logical and it has all those others<br />
societal characteristics that make it important, then I think we are always<br />
there to listen and try and make adjustments and quite a few we have had.<br />
We have made a few, of course, in this Budget and I will come to that in a<br />
moment. But I was interested in Donald's speech and a couple of things he said.<br />
He said, talking about the changes, the NFIF has already achieved<br />
considerable success and he mentions the issues which affect in a very large,<br />
and perhaps dramatic way, the whole of the rural sector. The decision to float<br />
the Australian dollar, the deregulation of financial markets, reductions in<br />
protection for all industries and this was always the big bug bear of course.<br />
It was always a matter of great amusement to me in the 1 970s when I came<br />
here. Of course Jack McEwen was still king of the castle round here and<br />
Alan Westerman was still sort of one of the princes of the bureaucracy and<br />
they had this scam running for years that they were going out to<br />
manufacturing industry, doling on protection, while they were out there talking<br />
to the farm community about what a terrible problem it was.<br />
At any rate, we were the ones who finally knocked it over and in what became<br />
obviously, through people like Bert Kelly and others, the identification of the<br />
burden of tariffs on agriculture became very clearly understood in the late<br />
and early 1 980s and by actually getting the tariff wall down, that has made a<br />
very large difference to agriculture.<br />
He mentions progress in the movement away from a centralised wage fixing<br />
system towards enterprise agreements. Broad political recognition of the </p>
<p>need to minimise pressure on interest rates by reweighting policy onto fiscal<br />
policy. He mentions the changes in 45D and E of the Trade Practices Act<br />
and the common law and negotiations of new trade arrangements such as, of<br />
course, Uruguay and APEC.<br />
And then he mentions the achievement of particular farm sector goals above<br />
that, national competition policy but then income equalisation deposits, farm<br />
management bonds, changes to drought assistance, review of the pastoral<br />
industry award etc. Sales tax exemption for direct farm inputs, a better result<br />
than other sectors in Native Title legislation, maintaining the diesel excise<br />
rebate and extensive schools education program etc.<br />
Well, the NFF has been involved in all these issues. But in making the point<br />
about us being strange bedfellows, of course, they were all done by this<br />
Government. All these decisions were taken by this Government.<br />
So we have done a lot of things together and they have been of material<br />
assistance to the farm community and they are the big brush things. You<br />
could imagine how we would be going today at an exchange rate of<br />
cents. And that, you see, getting that core competitiveness up,<br />
Australia today is 40 per cent more competitive than it was in 1983. Not 4 or<br />
14, 40 and that has come about by changes in exchange rate, productivity,<br />
wages etc.<br />
But, the big challenge in the 1 980s, was to turn that big nominal depreciation<br />
of the exchange rate into a real depreciation. I mean any country can have a<br />
competitive depreciation of its exchange rate. We have watched Britain do it<br />
against the European economies now for 20 years, but not anyone can have<br />
a real depreciation, that is washing the price surge out of wages which is<br />
basically what we did under the Accord.<br />
So that core competitiveness which all of the primary export sector now<br />
enjoys, from the exchange rate, happened because of the adjustment to<br />
wages, a terms of trade adjustment for productivity to wages, in the course of<br />
the 1980s. And under those Accords, the fact that we had pulled down fiscal<br />
policy so dramatically, we were able to provide tax cuts and those wage tax<br />
trade-offs of the 1980s, turned that large nominal depreciation of the dollar<br />
into a real depreciation.<br />
That happened, simply, because when I became Treasurer in 1983,<br />
John Howard left me outlays at 30 1/ 2 per cent of GOP an Australian record.<br />
And, as you know, it was a lift in the public sector in the 70s, under the<br />
Whitlam Government and then the Fraser Government that dislocated private<br />
investment and that put a very big call on savings. But by reducing it to<br />
23 1/ 2 per cent of GDP by the late 1980s that is a 7 per cent of GOP<br />
reduction and spending, and in today's dollars that is $ 35 billion we were<br />
able through growth and through revenue and through those outlays changes<br />
to fund a large continuing set of tax cuts and it is only by that way that we<br />
didn't go the way of other countries with a set of competitive depreciations. </p>
<p>So you were competitive for five minutes and you were uncompetitive five<br />
minutes later as wages caught up with prices. And I think that is one of the<br />
very great changes and I am very sympathetic to Bill Kelty and Martin<br />
Ferguson and their ACTU colleagues, when they say we haven't had much<br />
thanks for it, have we? And the answer is, they haven't.<br />
But they did get in there for over a decade and try and manage it down. The<br />
deal always was, of course, that we would compensate them by employment<br />
and in the period between 1983 and now, we have had about 27 per cent<br />
employment growth.<br />
As a consequence, real household disposable income is 40 per cent greater<br />
today than it was in 1983 because there are more people in households in<br />
work. And so that is how that important national economic policy making was<br />
made. The implicit arrangement of wage restraint for growth and employment<br />
growth being the essential element of the Accord and it is by that method that<br />
we have got that competitiveness back.<br />
We are now seeing a much more, but lower tariffs, contestable economy. In<br />
fact, a quite highly contested economy now. So now productivity is coming<br />
out of the pores of the skin of the economy, naturally. In other words, we are<br />
holding inflation down now, naturally. We are not holding it down with a<br />
draconian monetary policy, killing growth and activity. We are holding it<br />
down by the natural productive forces being, if you like, encouraged in the<br />
economy and a change in the productive culture of business.<br />
We have had very large productivity numbers in the last few years, as that<br />
whole productivity surge and cultural change has gone through Australian<br />
industry and it has gone through the farm sector as well.<br />
I remember in the 1 980s, you know Margaret Thatcher was boasting about<br />
and 6 per cent productivity and it was coming by massive lay-offs in British<br />
industry by huge unemployment. But last year we had 4 per cent<br />
productivity with massive lay-ons not massive lay-offs massive lay-ons.<br />
4 per cent employment growth. Still producing 4 per cent productivity, which<br />
is all the world of difference between the policies of this Government and the<br />
policies of the British Conservative Government. So that at the end of the<br />
section, she ended up with massive unemployment, an underclass, a divided<br />
society and, in the end, no structural change to productivity. Whereas what<br />
we are having here, is a long term structural change.<br />
So I think that the way we can, if you like, help the farm community most<br />
beneficially, is through these big brush changes to competitiveness,<br />
exchange rate, wages, inflation, productivity, competition and, of course,<br />
getting proper market access or the best market access we can through areas<br />
like the GATT and, of course, through APEC. </p>
<p>1 attended the OECD meeting in 1986 when we first got agriculture into the<br />
OECD communique and I had a big brawl with Clayton Yeutter and<br />
Malcolm Baidridge and a few other people at the time because this was the<br />
moment of truth if it didn't get into the OECD communique of that year, it<br />
wouldn't get into the G7 summit in Tokyo.<br />
We pushed and shoved and stood the French up and the Europeans up, and<br />
we did squeeze it in with the support of the United States and then as a<br />
consequence of relations we tend to build up over time, the then<br />
Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, who was Reagan's Sherpa at<br />
the summit, got it listed on the G7 agenda for the Uruguay Round and that is<br />
how agriculture got into the Round.<br />
Then we prosecuted that over seven years to get a result which while not all<br />
we were seeking was going to take a lot of the pressure off the kind of<br />
subsidies that we had seen growing and production and export subsidies we<br />
had seen growing in Europe and in North America.<br />
And here we are working together now Bob Collins and Bob McMullan with<br />
you and others on the 1995 Farm Bill to try and again make certain, or ease<br />
the pressure at least, against the Australian farm -sector from these other<br />
sectors who won't expose themselves to the kind of competitive influences<br />
that we have been prepared to expose ourselves, too.<br />
So right through those years, we have learnt together and I think, again,<br />
access remains one of the great issues for Australian agriculture and we have<br />
sought to do our best with it.<br />
Let me say a couple of things about the Budget and perhaps then come back<br />
to some farm specific things.<br />
The Budget, the other night, did respond to a desire and a wish by many<br />
sectors, including your own, for a reweighting of the policy instruments off<br />
monetary policy and on to fiscal policy and we have taken the Budget from a<br />
deficit of over $ 12 billion to a surplus of $ 700 million this year and next year<br />
we are into a surplus of about $ 4 billion and the following year a surplus of<br />
$ 7 billion, in prospect.<br />
What this means is that we have seen a great change in the bond selling<br />
program of the Commonwealth. Last year we sold $ 21 billion worth of bonds<br />
$ 21,000,000,000. This year, as a result of the Budget, that program will be<br />
reduced to $ 6,000,000,000. So, in other words, as a consequence of the<br />
Budget we have diminished the bond selling program by $ 15 billion, which is<br />
a mighty sum and that is why long bond yields fell from over 10 per cent<br />
ten days ago, to under 9 per cent today. And because if there is less paper<br />
around, the paper gets more valuable, the price of it rises and the yield drops,<br />
the interest rate falls and that is what, of course, engendered then further<br />
changes in retail interest rates towards the end of last week. </p>
<p>So we have already had that effect and we have this debate about whether it<br />
is recurrent changes or asset sales, but I thought the man from Moody's not<br />
that I quote them very often said look we are not particularly interested how<br />
it's done, what we want is to know how the bond selling program is going to<br />
be, what is the consequences for that. Well that is pretty clear form now. But<br />
the other point is next year, without any asset sales, we will be in surplus on a<br />
recurrent basis.<br />
Now the changes we made to the recurrent budget are around $ 3 billion this<br />
year and $ 4 1/ 2 billion next year. So we are over 1/ 2 per cent of GOP in<br />
recurrent changes this year and next year we are just under 1 per cent of<br />
GOP, which is a fairly big change.<br />
And the important thing is that the underlying level of outlays drops to<br />
24 per cent of GOP in two years. In other words, in two years time we will be<br />
back to the outlays levels that we had before the Whitlam Government, or<br />
around at the time of the beginning of the Whitlam Government. Back where<br />
we were in fact in the late 80s, which was at 23 1/ 2 per cent of GDP.<br />
Now you know you don't need to be a student of public policy to know since<br />
those years you have seen an enormous change in the services the<br />
Commonwealth provides in education, and in health, and in income support<br />
and yet we are doing it. A much more sophisticated public sector, providing<br />
much greater serves, yet we are doing it for the same outlays to GOP levels<br />
largely and underlying terms as existed before the Whitlam and Fraser<br />
Government's started spending a much higher proportion of GOP on<br />
outlays. Now, this needs to be understood I know a number of you have<br />
said " well, the Government should cut outlays more". Well look, there is<br />
one thing I would say to you, and that is this: I have sat through, now I<br />
have delivered 8 Budgets and 7 May Statements that is 15. We have now<br />
had 13 budgets, 8 May Statements and 3 Prime Ministerial Statements.<br />
That is 24 major budgetary statements, and barring 1 or 2 of those<br />
exercises, I have sat through all the Expenditure Review rounds, across all<br />
of the outlays. Ralph Willis, Brian Howe and myself are the longest serving<br />
officers of the Commonwealth in public spending if you shook the Finance<br />
Department by its toes, or the Treasury by its toes, no-one would drop out<br />
of it who has served in more Expenditure Reviews than the 3 of us. And let<br />
me just say this to you, because one of the things you ask us to do is to<br />
listen and comprehend problems, and we do we listen to what you say,<br />
and we take notice. And even if it doesn't fall on us obviously on the first<br />
moment, we listen and we get the picture. And I want you to listen to this,<br />
and just understand it you cannot cut 2% of GOP from outlays any more.<br />
It is just not possible. You can't cut $ 10,000 million from outlays now. You<br />
can't take the Commonwealth underlying outlays to 22% of GOP it is<br />
impossible, without cutting into pensions.. for instance, one of the first<br />
things that would go would be RAS, straight off the blocks. All of the<br />
industry assistance things would go before income support goes.<br />
Payments to industry the transfer payments, payments to schools which<br />
are holding up these massive participation rates in secondary school, and </p>
<p>into tertiary and vocational education they are all the sorts of things that<br />
will get hit. Because payments to the States we now give them a real<br />
terms per capita guarantee, which in a sense, isolates that area of the<br />
Budget from reductions we have got long-term arrangements with<br />
defence, so you take defence and the States out of there, to get into the<br />
rest of it, you have really got to savage the outlays in a way which would be<br />
unconscionable. Now, the underlying level of these outlays is now roughly 25.4% to 25% of<br />
GDP. Now John Howard, my opponent, is running around saying ' We won't<br />
touch revenue". He claims to want to lead the country, but wants to give up<br />
one instrument of financial management he won't touch revenue " I'll do it<br />
all on outlays". Then he says " we should be cutting outlays" or Costello is<br />
saying for him " by up to $ 10 billion". Well, you can't cut outlays by up to<br />
billion without cutting pensions, income support to the families,<br />
payments to schools or the industry programs, which are important sectors<br />
of industry. That game is up. You can certainly go back through it, and<br />
continue to put pressure on the efficiency of delivery, you can change the<br />
priorities of programs, you can yield savings we have done that with a<br />
savings round this year of $ 1.5 billion. We cut outlays by $ 1.5 billion, but<br />
there is a lot of unavoidable new spending in the Com~ monwealth, and there<br />
are some discretionary policies so that the net changes and outlays were<br />
$ 700 million, but the actual program of cuts was $ 1500 million. So, it was a<br />
very large set of cuts taken by the ERC over 9 weeks, or 10 weeks. So, it's<br />
just not... . you can go beyond it, but you won't have any political authority<br />
no Government in this country would have the political authority to go<br />
beyond it, and when the Coalition tell you they will cut waste and<br />
duplication and they will cut $ 10 billion out of outlays, just don't believe<br />
them. It's just tripe. Nonsense. And take it from somebody who had to sit<br />
through it for 10 weeks a year, for 12 years it just can't be done. And that<br />
is why we say that John Howard has given up economic policy, because<br />
when you give away receipts changes to receipts and you are kidding<br />
everybody you can make major changes in outlays, what you are really<br />
saying is that you are abdicating your role as a financial manager, because<br />
all the weight will then do is shift to interest rates.<br />
Now, that change I have mentioned to you the bond selling program going<br />
down from $ 21 billion to $ 6 billion has taken a lot of the pressure off<br />
interest rates which is one of the things your sector needs, it's one of the<br />
things of value to your sector and we hope that trend we have seen last<br />
week will continue, and that there is a genuine change in sentiment in<br />
financial markets as a consequence of the Budget. The problem we are<br />
trying to meet is not to reduce spending this year it was not about trying to<br />
hold down... . we didn't use the Budget as a demand management tool,<br />
because the 3 monetary adjustments of late last year have basically done<br />
that trick, you might know, that in the year to the September quarter, the<br />
economy was growing at 6.5% a year, and expenditure all spending in the<br />
economy was running at Now you don't have to be an<br />
econometrician to know that if the spending is running at 8.5% and product </p>
<p>is running at 2% is going to be satisfied by imports. And at it<br />
was putting too much stress on the country's productive capacity. So, we<br />
needed to slow it down. So, in the Budget, we are forecasting 3.75% for<br />
GDP, so it's a long way from And those monetary adjustments last<br />
year, were taken at the right time and we made them large adjustments<br />
one percentage points, or 2.5 altogether: 2 of 1 and 1 of 0.5% to<br />
actually get that slowing into place. So we don't need the Budget for an<br />
immediate slowing of the economy what we needed in the Budget is a<br />
medium term change for savings, because our problem is that we have got<br />
a current account deficit which is running about 2% of GDP above the point<br />
where it basically pays for itself. Each year, in the 60s and 70s, we were<br />
running a current account deficit of 2.5% of GOP, but we had capital inflow<br />
equal to 2.5% of GOP. In other words, we were able to afford a current<br />
account deficit of 2.5% of GOP, and not aggregate debt. That changed in<br />
the late 1970s and the early 1980s, when we got so uncompetitive, when<br />
the terms of trade ran against us, when we had a wage explosion, and<br />
double-digit inflation for most of the decade, by that stage the current<br />
account was running it started at 6% of GOP in 1980-81 not the number<br />
you will hear John Howard tell you about, but that's what it was, 6% of GOP<br />
in 1980-81. In other words, the cat was out of the bag then. And we have<br />
been running, on average, at 4.5% since.<br />
So, if 2.5% is sustainable, and the average is 4.5% and that's not<br />
sustainable, the problem is 2 percentage points of GOP. In other words,<br />
our savings have fallen as to around that amount so as not to be able to<br />
accommodate the investment phase we need for employment, growth,<br />
activity. And the reason it fell, I think principally, was double-digit inflation.<br />
Once double-digit inflation came to Australia, it took about a decade to<br />
teach Australians that it wasn't any point putting money in the bank,<br />
because the tax on the nominal interest rate, after double-digit inflation,<br />
was negative reals, so they stopped saving and they started buying flats,<br />
apartments, holiday houses etc. And we inculcated in a generation that<br />
there was no point in saving. It is going to take now, with a much better<br />
and lower inflation performance, some time to change that, so as a<br />
consequence, we have developed a savings pothole, which started from<br />
that period of double-digit inflation a decade or more of double-digit<br />
inflation and what the Budget is about doing is doing that is to try and<br />
overcome that problem. Let me just briefly explain how it happens. In the<br />
Budget and the next couple of years, we will see a turnaround of about 4<br />
percentage points of GOP. And let's say that part of it is cyclical, and part of<br />
it's structural. The other great change we had in the Budget was to extend<br />
superannuation beyond 9% to 15% for every working person, and we have<br />
encouraged people to put 3% of their personal contributions away, which<br />
we will then match with a 3% tax cut equivalent paid into their<br />
superannuation accounts. This will add 6 percentage points of wages to<br />
the 9% under the superannuation guarantee charge. This will take it to<br />
Now, at the moment we have got $ 186 billion in super funds, and the<br />
Treasury estimate that by 2020, we will have $ 2000 billion in super funds </p>
<p>$ 2 trillion, It was $ 40 billion in 1983, it is $ 186 billion now, and they<br />
estimate that it will go to $ 2000 billion..<br />
But that's 2020, and our time horizon is a bit shorter than that, and if we are<br />
looking at the year 2000, the savings and super would be less, but still very<br />
strong. Now, what the Treasury estimate is that by 2020, we will add the<br />
equivalent of 4% of GDP to savings, but they also estimate that by the year<br />
2000, we will add 2 percentage points of GDP. So, lets say that on the<br />
Budget side we have added 4% by the year 2000, on the super side we<br />
have added 4% by 2020, but if we are talking about 2000, we have added<br />
2% on super and 4% on the Budget. In other words, in the Budget of last<br />
Tuesday week, we put in a 6 percentage point fix for a 2 percentage point<br />
problem. Now, let me just say something about the Budget: not all of that is<br />
structural, some of it is cyclical as the economy grows, the cycle changes,<br />
revenue and outlays change, and at any subsequent slowing, that would<br />
affect the cyclical part of the Budget. Well, let's take all of the cyclical<br />
calculation out of it, and call the 4 percentage points of the Budget A<br />
good solid 2% and underlying and super with an underlying 2% gives<br />
you a very solid foundation for 4% savings to GOP to meet a 2% current<br />
account problem. Now, that's why the Budget was important, and that's<br />
why the Government can be relied upon to do a professional job as<br />
always on-the hard problems.<br />
And let me say about super now here's John Howard running around on<br />
Thursday night last saying " we'll put a cap on super we'll put a cap on it<br />
and we'll give tax concession to higher income earners". Well, he gave tax<br />
concessions in the 70s, and by 1983, superannuation coverage was<br />
Today, it's 90%. So, if we go back to tax deductions, what we will see is<br />
superannuation contributions go up to the top end of the income range, and<br />
not the lower and middle income earners where the great bulk of the<br />
community is where the great bulk of the savings must come. So, we take<br />
the view that by starting with a 3% case in 1985-86, and moving it up to<br />
and then getting the superannuation guarantee into place taking it to 9% by<br />
2002, and now adding 6% 3% and 3% from personal contributions and<br />
the tax cuts, we have over a decade, put together a scheme that the<br />
Liberals wouldn't have had the imagination or the wit to even approach,<br />
much less implement. And you think there are some things.. . they don't<br />
have any conversation with the trade union movement, and you can<br />
imagine Peter Costello or John Howard going to say to the workforce of<br />
Australia " please put 15% of your income away as savings", and they would<br />
say " oh, sure we will sure. No problem". Well, of course, they can't do it.<br />
You would think they would have enough sense to say well look, a Labor<br />
government did what we could never do, let's let this one go to the keeper<br />
let's at least lock this away. That's what Mr Connolly was saying a week or<br />
2 ago, and saying in the press yesterday their superannuation<br />
spokesperson who was defeated in Bradfield saying this one we should<br />
let go to the keeper because there is a broad national change here. But<br />
again, the ideology is out saying " oh no, we don't want lower and middle<br />
income earners getting the benefit of the tax concession, so we will cap it </p>
<p>and we will throw tax concessions again to higher paid earners". I mean,<br />
some people never learn.<br />
But, at least, there is here now a really substantial savings change. And<br />
that's going to fund the higher investment we need for more employment,<br />
and a more productive country. And we know, as we go through the<br />
we are going to need more capital investment not less, more because<br />
one of the problems of that 70s double-digit inflation, and the big call on the<br />
public sector, is that it absolutely smashed to pieces the capital stock. And<br />
we didn't have enough capital stock to produce goods and services, and<br />
that's why we had a current account weakness all through the 80s. So we<br />
have got to get the capital stock up that means more investment, that<br />
means more savings to meet it but without those savings, that pressure<br />
for investment will reflect itself in higher interest rates, and you know as<br />
well as any sector, the problem those higher interest rates put on your<br />
particular sector. So, the way to accommodate higher investment, and<br />
higher employment, and reach the Government's target of<br />
unemployment by the year 2000, is through more investment, but we can't<br />
afford more investment if it only puts pressure on interest rates, therefore<br />
we have had to augment savings. So, the Budget was a very important<br />
document, I think, not just for the country, but particularly for the rural<br />
sector, because it does the lay the basis of a very long-term and important<br />
change to savings which we dearly needed and which we now have.<br />
Let me just make one final point about outlays. In the Budget, the ratio of<br />
outlays to GDP will decline by 2.7% over the next couple of years, which is<br />
$ 13 billion to $ 14 billion. In other words, just left to themselves, they are<br />
going to drop away to 24% of GDP. That's $ 13 billion $ 14 billion. But<br />
revenue will increase by only 1 of GOP, so in terms of the structure of the<br />
Budget, outlays are subsiding, and the revenue is only barely picking up.<br />
So, in terms of the quality if you like, the balance between outlays and<br />
revenue in the Budget you have got a $ 13 billion to $ 14 billion change in<br />
the course of happening right at the moment.<br />
Could I just go on and say that we want to be able to with this Budget and<br />
this environment keep the environment up for the health of the rural<br />
sector, this is not withstanding climactic hardships and the rest, and I just<br />
want to say a couple of things about the banks. The banks have been<br />
cutting back a lot of their operations in rural areas in the name of efficiency.<br />
But I think they are being very short-sighted they are failing to see the<br />
potential of Australia's rural industry, which is one of Australia's<br />
comparative advantages, which represents one of Australia's comparative<br />
advantages and the capacity of Australia's farmers to run profitable and<br />
productive concerns. The banks have been cutting overheads, they don't<br />
have the personnel necessary to provide farmers and farming communities<br />
with the service they need. They seem to me to be almost incapable of<br />
intensely managing typical rural loans in the region of $ 50,000 to $ 200,000<br />
they don't seem to be able to get a handle on the management of those<br />
loans at all, so they have taken the next best policy, and that is to basically </p>
<p>back out. I think they need to take a longer term view they do have a very<br />
privileged position in the financial community, and simply just resorting to<br />
housing lending, and moving away from what I call intelligent rural lending,<br />
is I think, a bad trend.<br />
One of the things your President and Rick and I have discussed on occasions<br />
is this question about whole of farm planning which, I think, is important. It<br />
would be far better to get the banks interested in how a farm is managed to<br />
be able to assess the quality of the loans by being able to assess the credit<br />
being extended to farms, if in fact, there is a whole of farm plan. I think we<br />
should be moving more towards this where we have consultants in each<br />
district who are able to go and look at a farm and say what its capacity is,<br />
what the soils are like, what it should be growing, how it should be grazing,<br />
how the. farm should be configured et cetera.<br />
Were that to happen and if whole of farm plans were advanced ahead of, if<br />
you like, primary advances in loans the bank's security would be better and<br />
we would have a far better relationship, a far more conducive relationship<br />
between banks and farms and farmers and graziers.<br />
So, when we look at our possibilities, the Asian markets around was and the<br />
demonstrable ethic for hard work and adaptability which the farm sector has,<br />
then they seem to me to mark themselves out farmers and graziers as<br />
typically the sort of people banks should be lending to rather than cutting<br />
back. So, I am going to take whatever opportunity I can to remind the banks<br />
of their responsibilities here, but let's make their task a little easier by helping<br />
them, if you like develop these relationships which make farm lending easier<br />
rather than harder.<br />
Can I perhaps finish my remarks by just saying, we have established a great<br />
deal of common ground in recent years. We understand that our ambitions<br />
are very much alike. I know from working in the last two years on issues as<br />
diverse as Native Title and Landcare and the drought and regional<br />
development that we can get a lot done together. I think we have become, as<br />
far as the farm and rural communities are concerned, good listeners. We try<br />
and earnestly work our way through the problems and see what we can do in<br />
a systemic way and we will keep that up. As I say, we are working together<br />
now at the moment in the United States on the farm bill and I think it does<br />
show that the view the NIFF has taken, that it is not just simply a sectoral body<br />
which is arguing for sectional interests but taking a broader view of national<br />
interests, have served it particularly well because, I think, while ever it is has<br />
adopted those sorts of policies it has been more relevant, stronger, more<br />
influential and able to get, if you like, sector specific changes into place as<br />
well as the broader, big brush issues.<br />
So, I see enormous potential in our relationship. As hard at times as it has<br />
been and in many places they still are, we have made great progress and I<br />
think the points that Donald made about the drought are right. We are seeing<br />
these rains, but we have seen them before, we've seen the beginning of rains </p>
<p>for winter crops and yet the crops haven't materialised, but this time we have<br />
an infrastructure of policy sitting behind, the problem of the drought and we<br />
ought to be, perhaps, I suppose the term is cautiously optimistic about these<br />
rains. They seem widespread and lets hope they are as good as they look,<br />
but by the same token, let me endorse his remarks by saying let's not let the<br />
pressure off on sustainability and drought management simply because we<br />
have seen some change in seasonal conditions. We have had a major<br />
structural problem here, cyclical problem, but becoming structural because it<br />
is so long with the drought and now is the time to remember that we have<br />
been making progress in drought management and these rains are a<br />
reminder that it is a long term rather than a short term problem.<br />
Can I thank you for having me over. Let me again, conclude my remarks by<br />
commending Rick Farley for the role he has played. I wish him well in the<br />
future. I know he is going to be a hard man to replace, but the organisation<br />
has changed as a consequence of his being there and under the leadership<br />
of people like Donald, I think, the future is yours, it is what we can make of it.<br />
Thank you.<br />
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS SESSION<br />
Q: On the theme of the drought and the fact that we have had some<br />
useful rain in parts of the country and, indeed, some very big parts of<br />
the country and that is very welcome. But, we do seem to have this<br />
persistent problem in some areas and, as I said, those are some of the<br />
areas that have been most badly affected for longest. I think, in the<br />
pleasure that the rain we have had brings to those areas that it comes,<br />
is always the concern by the people in other areas, in the areas that<br />
haven't had it, that they will be forgotten and I think it would be very<br />
much appreciated by those people, Prime Minister, if you could restate<br />
essentially the commitment that you have given in the past that the<br />
relief that they have got through the assistance measures that are will,<br />
indeed, continue until such time as they actually do get back into a<br />
position where seasonal conditions and production returns to some<br />
sort of normality. And secondly, we have actually still got some<br />
exceptional circumstances applications pending and we would like an<br />
assurance that the Government will deal with those as quickly as<br />
possible.<br />
PM: Let me, Donald, say that I am quite happy to say that we had some<br />
exceptional circumstance applications, I think, in Victoria amongst<br />
other places pending and one will need to see with these rains what<br />
the continuing assessment of these regions are. But, from our point of<br />
view we don't regard the drought as being over simply because these<br />
rains have come and that we would like to see these applications<br />
progressed and we will be keeping these policies in place. We have<br />
now got, I think from memory, about 6000 to 7000 and maybe more by<br />
now farm families getting income support. We have seen about 4000<br />
farm businesses received support under RAS and it is the sort of </p>
<p>matrix of policy we have got sitting there now which is something, I<br />
think, that becomes a real advance for the rural community because<br />
now they are there they won't be going away. I mean, us having put<br />
them there, I can't imagine the future if someone is going to basically<br />
say no, the farm assets test is going to be applied regardless of<br />
income in these circumstances. So, I would like to think we have made<br />
a policy advance in some of these areas, but before we cry victory and<br />
walk off the field, let's see what happens with the rains and let's<br />
progress these applications.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, interest rates have a major impact on farm profitability,<br />
some comments made yesterday by the Treasury Secretary Ted Evans<br />
and they have been interpreted by the media to mean that interest<br />
rates may well have peaked. On the other hand, of course, there are a<br />
lot of financial institutions that are providing other advice concerned<br />
about higher inflation and perhaps a rebound in spending. Do you<br />
believe that interest rates, especially those that are driven by Reserve<br />
Bank policy on short term money market rates that have an impact on<br />
business overdrafts and mortgages have peaked?<br />
PM: Let's make these two distinguishing points. -That is, the long bond<br />
rates set in the market without any reference to the Reserve Bank and<br />
it is the long bond rate which has fallen by over a percentage point<br />
and, I think, the large reduction in the bond selling program is probably<br />
responsible for a large part of that. Short end rates are conditioned by<br />
long end perceptions to some extent, but they are also governed by<br />
demand management objectives. One of the points I was making to<br />
you on my feet is that we have succeeded in slowing the economy<br />
down so that now we are forecasting for the coming year three and<br />
three quarters per cent rather than five or six per cent. Therefore, the<br />
policy need of using further monetary adjustments to slow the economy<br />
down seems remote. It would only come back into prospect if, in fact,<br />
growth unexpectedly picked up to unsustainable levels again, but I<br />
can't see it in the current environment.<br />
Plus the change in the Budget balance is fairly substantial and that is<br />
going to reduce quite a bit of public sector demand from the economy.<br />
So, even if for instance, we were only conservatively estimating the<br />
decline in GDP coming from private activity there is one thing certain<br />
about the Budget, there is a further large complement in the reduction<br />
of public demand. Put all that together and Ted Evans' view that the<br />
underlying inflation rate may be a little on the up side in the Budget<br />
estimates and that augurs quite well, I think, for the short run of rates<br />
because, again, you have got always a demand in supply equation<br />
there to be met and by such a very large change in the public sector<br />
call on savings we are going to see a substantial change in that<br />
demand supply equation and that should be good for rates. So, I think,<br />
one of the objectives of the Budget was to take pressure of interest<br />
rates and I think it has done that. </p>
<p>Q: Prime Minister, up until now the. Industrial Relations Accord parties<br />
have been exclusively the Government and the ACTU, given the<br />
importance of progressing further industrial reform for competitive<br />
reasons, what is in your view on the extension of the focus of the<br />
Accord to include parties such as farmers, business, large and small<br />
generally, in interests of progressing further constructive reform?<br />
PM: If you go back over the history of the Accord, it started in 1983 from a<br />
wage share in GDP that was inordinately high and the profit share in<br />
GDP was well below the levels we had experienced in the 1960s and<br />
as a consequence, investment had been sharply curtailed. So, in a<br />
sense it was the ACTU constituency that had to give something away.<br />
They were the people giving it away, the business community were the<br />
people getting it from wages to profits. So, that is why of its essence,<br />
in its original days the Accord was a matter between the trade unions<br />
and the Government because the Government was seeking to redress<br />
that shift in the profit share which had so dislocated investment. Now,<br />
that was true for most of the 1980s. It is less true now because the<br />
profit share is as high as it was in the late 1980s and, I think, now has<br />
no historical precedent. This is the highest levels of profits, national<br />
income to profits, I think, probably ever.<br />
We are seeing a lot of, if you like, informal involvement of the business<br />
organisations. You can see it in the change to enterprise bargaining.<br />
You can see it in the support of the change. You might recall a couple<br />
of years ago the MTIA were most sceptical about a movement to an<br />
enterprise bargaining system because Bert Evans had a long memory<br />
of what had happened with leap frogging in the late 1970s and early<br />
1980s under the concept of comparative wage justice and so was, if<br />
you like, less than confident that business could actually handle the<br />
strengths which the Industrial Relations Act was going to give it. At<br />
any rate, what we are seeing is a very great spread of enterprise<br />
bargains, 65 per cent of all employees covered by federal awards are<br />
now covered by a bargain of some kind or another and we are seeing<br />
some very good bargains being struck and just a week or so ago the<br />
metals' unions and the industry, I can't remember the place, made<br />
what the Metal Trades Industry Association thought was a fairly good<br />
agreement and as we see these, what you call, very good grass roots<br />
agreements continuing to arise, they become industry standards. The<br />
industry starts to get its pecker up and get its confidence, but people<br />
are starting to really pull a lot of productivity out of the changes and<br />
employees also are benefiting.<br />
So, there is, I think, now a fairly conducive, informal involvement by<br />
some of the industry bodies. The hotel sector, for instance, did a land<br />
mark enterprise agreement with federal hotels and, I think, that<br />
therefore the game has opened up. In terms of the Accord proper, of<br />
course, because we have moved away from the centralised wage fixing </p>
<p>system, there is less specificity if you like in the elements of the<br />
Accord, rather broad commitments by the trade unions about<br />
maintaining competition with our trading partners on inflation and<br />
commitments by the Government about support for the safety net<br />
arrangements for those people who can't access enterprise bargaining.<br />
So, the Accord elements are becoming more simple. They are<br />
because the system of wage fixation is less centralised and now more<br />
complex. Now, I think, that it is possible for organisations like the NIFF<br />
and the MTIA and the other business organisations, the Business<br />
Council if they can drop their ideology, to actually be involved and be<br />
relevant in this process as we see the continuing evolutionary change<br />
to the labour market. I think this would be a very good thing, but in any<br />
Accord process, with the government and the unions, there is a<br />
commitment by the trade unions to low inflation, to competitiveness. A<br />
commitment by the government to equity in wage adjustments. If a<br />
business party joins it, there has got to be commitments too, it can't be<br />
in a sense, there is no point in being in it with nothing to contribute and<br />
that is why when we have mooted these things in the past, they have<br />
never come to much because the business community has never<br />
believed it was a principal party to the point where it was actually<br />
giving something away or providing something. That has changed in a<br />
more co-operative environment and maybe the time is arising where<br />
that can be considered. I think we are about to move to another<br />
Accord Mark VIII which will cover the next three years, but I think we<br />
are seeing now, you can see for instance the ACTU's attitude towards<br />
the NIFF or some of the other business organisations, how much the<br />
game has changed, how less confrontational it is, how more<br />
constructive it is and, I think, they would welcome expressions such as<br />
the one you have made.<br />
Q: Prime Minister, when APEC was formed trade was well and truly one of<br />
its prime objectives, Is the reform of agricultural trade still on the<br />
agenda and if it isn't, do you propose to make moves to bring it back<br />
on the agenda because it is extremely important for agriculture in<br />
Australia?<br />
PM: The answer to that is very much in the affirmative and the value of<br />
APEC is that, well you know this expression the north-south dialogue<br />
we used to hear through the 1970s and 1980s, APEC is the first<br />
tangible real expression of that dialogue. When you have got a body<br />
in the pacific rim which are represented by countries such as the<br />
United States and Japan, the first and second largest developed<br />
economies. And then the largest, if you like, developing countries<br />
China, Indonesia, smaller countries like Papua New Guinea so it<br />
really is, in a sense, representing that north-south divide and, of<br />
course, one of the things we argued all the way through the GATT was<br />
that although Australia was a developed country it had a lot of the<br />
trading profile of a developing country because of agriculture and </p>
<p>therefore we put the Cairns Group together and successfully kept it<br />
together for seven years to prosecute that argument. So, I think, there<br />
is a lot of trust in Australia's position as an agricultural producer and<br />
somebody who champions the cause of free markets or open markets<br />
and freer trade in agriculture. That is going to matter in the Asia<br />
Pacific where some of the agricultural nationals will want better access<br />
and it is going to improve the living standards of developed countries<br />
like Japan to actually improve access for agricultural products from<br />
abroad. So, given the fact that the GATT took so long because we are facing<br />
the subsidy problems of the European and the European Common<br />
Market, APEC representing half the worlds production and about half<br />
the worlds population, gives us a chance to do a far more precise and<br />
refined approach to agriculture than we were even able to do with the<br />
Common Agricultural Policy and the GATT. But, we are going to see<br />
changes too and I think the other thing about APEC is that it will bring<br />
on, over time, at least it will encourage a debate about another general<br />
trade round because if half of the world is liberalising its trade, the<br />
other half of the world has got to be thinking about it.<br />
The other thing is, as these Visigrad countries join the European<br />
community, where they have large scale common agriculture, once<br />
those areas have been farmed with modem agricultural machinery and<br />
the agriscience and the understanding of productivity becomes more<br />
entrenched in those countries, the weight of product that is going to be<br />
dumped onto the European financial system is going to be so great, I<br />
think, in the end it will actually dislocate the Common Agricultural<br />
Policy. I think that has been all right to the moment where we have<br />
essentially small, in many countries for instance in France, quite small<br />
farm agriculture, but once you get those broad acres of the Visigrad<br />
countries coming to higher production, I think, the game is going to get<br />
very nasty indeed for European budgets and they may be looking then<br />
for an opportunity to start to see their problems being resolved in a<br />
broader context and that is where I think APEC can be just the ticket.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
