<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9798</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DR DON RUSSELL </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009798.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
111%-5 I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DR DON RUSSELL<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Australian Ambassador to the United<br />
States, Dr Don Russell, is to return to Australia to take up the position of<br />
Principal Adviser on my personal office staff.<br />
Dr Russell has filled the important role of Ambassador to Washington with<br />
great distinction for more than two years. His knowledge and experience of<br />
domestic and international policy issues and his dedication to his country's<br />
interests have lifted Australia's profile in the United States and strengthened<br />
the ties between us.<br />
Of the many issues on which Dr Russell has worked successfully, I want to<br />
thank him in particular for so effectively conveying Australia's views on APEC<br />
and other trade matters to the Clinton Administration.<br />
Naturally, I am pleased that Dr Russell has now agreed to re-join my office<br />
from next month. His experience, knowledge and creativity will be a valuable<br />
addition to the team and indeed to Government policy and Australian public<br />
life. I am also pleased that John Bowan will continue to work with me as Chief of<br />
Staff. Arrangements are in train to appoint a new Ambassador to the United States,<br />
whose name will be announced shortly.<br />
CANBERRA 16 OCTOBER 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
