<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4238</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF ADDRESS GIVEN BY PRIME MINISTER AT THE OPENING OF THE WARRNAMBOOL INSTITUTE OF ADVANCED EDUCATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004238.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 24 SEPTEMBER 1976<br />
TEXT OF ADDRESS GIVEN BY PRINE MINISTER AT THE OPENING OF<br />
THE W4ARRNAMBOOL INSTITUTE OF ADVANCED EDUCATION<br />
It gives me great pleasure to open the first academic building<br />
on the Sherwood Park campus of W. I. A. E.<br />
The building and its extensions will house virtually the whole<br />
college complex its library, student facilities, its lecture<br />
theatre and lecture rooms and staff administration offices.<br />
The Liberal National Country Party Coalition supports the<br />
decentralised provision of post secondary education.<br />
Country students should not be compelled to move to metropolitan<br />
areas to get a post secondary education.<br />
A balance must be maintained between metropolitan and country<br />
education. Educational opportunities should be open to all People.<br />
We must also ensure a rational and coordinated use of our<br />
educational resources.<br />
W. I. A. E. has made significant contributions to the south western<br />
region. It now offers not only degree and diploma courses but<br />
also further educational opportunities to part time and external<br />
students employed in the region.<br />
W. I. A. E. has developed considerably in the past few years.<br />
Total enrolments have climbed from 170 in 1970 to 837 in 1976.<br />
In 1977, it is estimated enrolments will rise to 955.<br />
In this period, funding for the institution has also expanded.<br />
The Commission for Advanced Education in its latest report has<br />
recommended further increases: 1976 recurrent funds $ 1.906 million<br />
1977 recommendation $ 2.054 million.<br />
This is an increase of about which is higher than the average<br />
increase for institutes of advanced education.<br />
In 1976 the capital funds allocated to the institute, were<br />
million..* The Commission's recommendation for 1977-79 is<br />
$ 2.575 million. </p>
<p>2.<br />
This capital programme in particular is evidence of the support<br />
for the continued development of W. I. A. E.<br />
The Commission's financial recommendations for W. I. A. E. should<br />
be considered by Cabinet in the next few weeks.<br />
The Government also has before it a report from officials<br />
on the tertiary education assistance schemes.<br />
As the Treasurer announced in the budget speech, the Government's<br />
decisions on T. E. A. S. will be announced in October and implemented<br />
from the beginning of the 1977 academic year.<br />
I should note in passing that it was the Labor Government which<br />
set the allowances which have been operating through this year.<br />
The Institutes of Advanced Education have a great contribution<br />
to make to the future of' Australian society.<br />
Our society is inevitably on e of change sometimes very rapid<br />
change. Technology is developing rapidly. We are able to<br />
utilise the power of science most effectively.<br />
Concepts of education are changing. There is a vigorous debate<br />
on the purpose of education and its appropriate function in our<br />
society.<br />
Our educational system must adapt to the needs of people for<br />
job mobility, for retraining. It must be appropriate to the<br />
needs of people in the exhilarating new age we are entering.<br />
-As evidence of the importance we place on education, in the<br />
recentbiud1get education was one of the very few areas to receive<br />
a real increase in funds. We also restored triennial funding.<br />
The Government is also, however, acutely aware that there is a<br />
widespread concern about the functioning of our schools and post<br />
secondary institutions.<br />
We have taken the view that an examination of education is now<br />
required. Accordingly, the Government has decided to establish<br />
the most important inquiry into post-secondary education since<br />
the Martin Inquiry over a decade ago.<br />
Having particular regard to current circumstances, this inquiry<br />
will also examine the broader issue of the relationship between<br />
education and employment.<br />
Education needs to equip a person for a satisfying and rewarding<br />
life. One fact of the greatest importance in achieving this<br />
objective is satisfying and rewarding work.<br />
This inquiry will provide a perspective on educational planning<br />
up to the year 2000.<br />
The Committee of Inquiry is being directed to have particular,<br />
regard for the Government's objectives of: widening educational<br />
opportunity; expanding educational and occupational choice;<br />
developing quality and-excellence in all spheres of education and<br />
encouraging community participation in education and training matters.,' / 13 </p>
<p>Education is not only concerned with imparting technical skills.<br />
It needs also to impart a quality of judgement. The great<br />
challenge to educators is to combine the teaching of skills<br />
with that broader understanding.<br />
The development of Australia will depend greatly on the quality<br />
of our educational system and the values our educators impart.<br />
Unless our educational institutions teach tolerance, a sense of<br />
personal responsibility, a respect for others and for their<br />
freedoms, and above all a maturity of judgement and rejection of<br />
dogmatism, it is certain that the great ideal of a socity based<br />
on freedom and human dignity will remain finally beyond our reach.<br />
Education, and the appropriate pattern of the educational system,<br />
will, whatever our views, be one of the major issues facing the<br />
Australian people for the foreseeable future.<br />
00000000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
