<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10618</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER              THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP              ADDRESS AT THE LAUNCH OF THE BOOK              &amp;quot;JOHN HOWARD, PRIME MINISTER&amp;quot;              BY DAVID BARNETT WITH PRU GOWARD              PARLIAMENT HOUSE,</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
 CANBERRA</p>
<p>E&amp;OE.........................................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much David and Pru. To the members of my family</p>
<p>   who are here, my wife Janette, my daughter Melanie, my eldest brother</p>
<p>   Wal and his wife Gwen. To my Parliamentary colleagues, to Mr Sessions</p>
<p>   and members of the Press Gallery, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It is an awkward moment in one's political career to launch</p>
<p>   a biography. You reflect for a moment on what you might or might</p>
<p>   not say, you wonder whether you will be a commentator on the book.</p>
<p>I have reviewed a number of books, I haven't been asked to</p>
<p>   review this one. I reviewed Bob Hawke's book and Graham Richardson's</p>
<p>   book and I have reviewed that marvellous biography of Alan Martin's</p>
<p>   about Sir Robert Menzies. But, of course, I have read this with</p>
<p>   absorption and, of course as David and Pru have pointed out, I spent</p>
<p>   quite a deal of time with them in advising on facts and tracing</p>
<p>   the sequence of events.</p>
<p>It is of course, more than a biography. It is also a chronicle</p>
<p>   of Australian politics over the last, almost quarter of a century.</p>
<p>   And we are constantly reminded of how things change. But when I</p>
<p>   reflect that in 1974 when I was elected to Parliament, I reflect</p>
<p>   upon the Australia of then and the world of then and the Australia</p>
<p>   of today and the world of today, the changes are absolutely mind</p>
<p>   boggling.</p>
<p>Not only have we seen in that quarter of a century the on set of,</p>
<p>   arguably since the industrial revolution, the greatest economic</p>
<p>   transformation brought about by information technology, but we have</p>
<p>   seen the collapse of the most pervasive, authoritarian ideology</p>
<p>   of the 21st Century, that is Soviet communism. We have seen the</p>
<p>   rise, and now the turbulence and the trepidation of the Asia-Pacific</p>
<p>   region as the fastest growing economic area in the world. We have</p>
<p>   also seen a massive transformation of Australian politics.</p>
<p>We are now living in a far less tribal political state that we</p>
<p>   lived in the early 1970s. We have also lived through a period of</p>
<p>   time when elections have been dominated by economic issues. When</p>
<p>   I was cutting my political teeth as a member of the Liberal Party</p>
<p>   organisation and stuffing letterboxes in suburbs like Earlwood and</p>
<p>   Campsie and Dulwich Hill and Hurlstone Park with people like Tom</p>
<p>   Hughes, who became Federal Attorney-General in the Gorton Government</p>
<p>   after the 1969 election, elections used to be fought, as Tony Eggleton</p>
<p>   who is in audience, and there is somebody who shares, as well as</p>
<p>   anybody in this audience, the ups and downs and the successes and</p>
<p>   the triumphs of our side of politics over that period of time, the</p>
<p>   issues that tended to dominate the political scene then were not</p>
<p>   economic issues.</p>
<p>But I can't think of an election since 1974, I would say 1972</p>
<p>   was the last election that was determined overwhelmingly on non-economic</p>
<p>   issues, that was determined on what you might call historical, cultural</p>
<p>   changes issues rather than economic ones. And from 1974 onwards</p>
<p>   it changed and there was, of course, a reason for that, and that</p>
<p>   is the enormous impact of all those economic changes that occurred</p>
<p>   in the 1970s with the floating of the American dollar, the collapse</p>
<p>   of the Bretton-Woods international financial arrangements and the</p>
<p>   OPEC oil increases and all the other domestic changes.</p>
<p>So we are a world away from the political world of Australia that</p>
<p>   I entered in 1974 when Gough Whitlam was Prime Minister and the</p>
<p>   late Bill Snedden was the Leader of the Opposition. When Jim Cope</p>
<p>   was the Speaker for a time to be replaced by Gordon Skulls, who</p>
<p>   I might say in my view, distinguished himself as a Speaker of the</p>
<p>   House of Representatives. I thought that Gordon Skulls was in fact</p>
<p>   a very good Speaker and he had, for a person appointed as a Speaker</p>
<p>   by the Labor Party, an extraordinary difficult moment in controlling</p>
<p>   Parliament on the 11th of November 1975.</p>
<p>To have been present at some of those great and, at times traumatic</p>
<p>   political events. To have lived through the circumstances of 1975.</p>
<p>   To have lived through, as a junior Minister, the early years of</p>
<p>   the Fraser Government. To have been trusted, unexpectedly with the</p>
<p>   responsibilities of Treasurer, as David recounts in the first pages</p>
<p>   of the book. To have suffered the fate of trying to keep pace with</p>
<p>   drinking beer with Malcolm Fraser in the Kirribilli hotel after</p>
<p>   I was sworn in as Prime Minister - and David correctly records that</p>
<p>   I didn't do terribly well out of that, although the press conference</p>
<p>   the next morning wasn't too bad.</p>
<p>To have gone through the difficulties as the years wear on of the</p>
<p>   governments, which inevitably develops tensions. To have gone through,</p>
<p>   in government, a few dark moments. And as I read the book I was</p>
<p>   reminded of some of the internal difficulties. I think one of the</p>
<p>   gut-wrenching experiences that I had was the enormous struggle within</p>
<p>   my own party and within some sections of the broader community regarding</p>
<p>   the very controversial anti-tax avoidance measures that I introduced</p>
<p>   as Treasurer in 1982.</p>
<p>And ironically enough, and David won't mind me saying this,</p>
<p>   David asked me in his afterlife, after he'd left Malcolm Fraser</p>
<p>   as press secretary, in fact as part of his duties in Canberra, was</p>
<p>   vigorously advocating with me, almost on a daily basis, and he did</p>
<p>   the job extremely well to calls of those who objected very violently</p>
<p>   to some of the measures that I was undertaking. I might say, not</p>
<p>   on grounds of the principle of tax avoidance but what he regarded</p>
<p>   as the very controversial and improper methods that the Government</p>
<p>   had adopted in order to recoup to the Australian Treasury the tax</p>
<p>   that had been so wickedly avoided by these people.</p>
<p>That was typical of the sort of exchange that David and I would</p>
<p>   have at that particular time. David, of course, himself has been</p>
<p>   present at all of these events as a commentator and as a journalist.</p>
<p>   And as Malcolm Fraser's press secretary he was with him on</p>
<p>   November 11th 1975 and he joined his staff when Malcolm became Leader</p>
<p>   of the Opposition. And he stayed with Malcolm until after the 1980</p>
<p>   election and he then became a consultant. Then after the defeat</p>
<p>   of the Fraser Government he returned to the Press Gallery. And he</p>
<p>   has witnessed all of those events. I have had a strong personal</p>
<p>   relationship with him but it has never clouded the professionalism</p>
<p>   of the job that he has done as a journalist and as a commentator.</p>
<p>And so to me one of the great values of this book is that it does</p>
<p>   represent, through the experience and circumstances of myself in</p>
<p>   the various roles that I have had during that 23 year period, it</p>
<p>   does represent, as I said, a chronicle of Australian politics and</p>
<p>   the Australian economy over that period of time.</p>
<p>There are many things about political life now which I have mentioned</p>
<p>   which are so different from what they were 23 years ago. I have</p>
<p>   talked about the detribalised character of Australian politics.</p>
<p>   I think also it is fair to say that politics has become even more</p>
<p>   volatile and even more unpredictable now than it was in the 1970s.</p>
<p>If I reflect on my childhood and the political experiences I imbibed</p>
<p>   then, I guess the stability and the predictability at that time</p>
<p>   is the dominant recollection that one has.</p>
<p>And if I look back over the last 18 months can I leave the thought</p>
<p>   with you that, probably the biggest single change that has occurred</p>
<p>   in the last 18 months, even more important than the impressive achievements</p>
<p>   of my Government, of which David was kind enough to draw attention,</p>
<p>   with which I won't too long detain you this morning.</p>
<p>But rather the most important thing that has happened over that</p>
<p>   last 18 months has been, in my view, the very significant change</p>
<p>   in the dynamic of the relationship between Australia and the Asia-Pacific</p>
<p>   region. Not in the sense that I suggest for a moment that our fortunes</p>
<p>   aren't forever committed and our destiny not forever tied</p>
<p>up with the future of that region. But the transformation brought</p>
<p>   about largely, but not entirely, by the economic instability in</p>
<p>   a number of the major economies in the Asia-Pacific region have,</p>
<p>   I think all of both the dynamic and the psychology and also the</p>
<p>   actuality of our relationship with that region.</p>
<p>We are no longer seen as some kind of anxious outsider clamouring</p>
<p>   to be a member of this spectacularly successful club, rather we</p>
<p>   are seen as a strong, reliable, dependable, better run, more successful,</p>
<p>   capable of punching above its weight participant in the Asia-Pacific</p>
<p>   region. And I think as the months go by the psychology of that and</p>
<p>   the way it will impact on Australian politics and the way it will</p>
<p>   reinforce the need for Australia always to be, in a political and</p>
<p>   economic sense, a citizen of the world as well as giving priority</p>
<p>   to our associations with our immediate region. And I think it is,</p>
<p>   without doubt, the single most important change in the dynamic of</p>
<p>   anything that has occurred over this period of time.</p>
<p>One of the satisfying things of political life can genuinely be</p>
<p>   that when you have had a difficult association and you have had</p>
<p>   struggles which have become publicly known, with some individuals,</p>
<p>   that over a period of time that you can become reconciled to each</p>
<p>   other and time and circumstances will alter attitudes. It is no</p>
<p>   secret that Andrew Peacock and I over the years, inside the Liberal</p>
<p>   Party, had the odd disagreement. It is also no secret, I think unfairly</p>
<p>   on occasions, we together were blamed for the assorted ills and</p>
<p>   sins and failures and inadequacies of the Federal Parliamentary</p>
<p>   Liberal Party.</p>
<p>And I must say that I did find an immense personal satisfaction,</p>
<p>   as time went by and particularly after the 1993 election in which,</p>
<p>   almost by accident at first but then over a period of time, both</p>
<p>   of us decided that it was rather stupid, this personal enmity which</p>
<p>   was never quite as big, although some people in this room might</p>
<p>   find it hard to believe given some of the circumstances that occurred,</p>
<p>   that that should go on forever.</p>
<p>And I do say that one of the most pleasing appoints I have made</p>
<p>   as Prime Minister was to initiate Andrew Peacock's appointment</p>
<p>   as Australian Ambassador to Washington. Not only because I felt</p>
<p>   it completed the process of reconciliation between two people who'd</p>
<p>   been competitors in the pursuit of the same cause, but I think it</p>
<p>   also has delivered to this country a magnificent Ambassador in the</p>
<p>   United States of America whose great diplomatic and interpersonal</p>
<p>   skills are very effectively deployed there.</p>
<p>There are many other people in this room that I could talk about.</p>
<p>   I, of course, record unstintingly, indeed fulsomely, my affection</p>
<p>   and gratitude towards my family who have been in their various manifestations,</p>
<p>   commencing with my very devoted and loyal and decent parents who</p>
<p>   gave to me a view of right and wrong as they saw it and as I believed</p>
<p>   in. And they gave to me a sense of country and a sense of effort</p>
<p>   and a sense of personal striving and a sense of humility, I hope,</p>
<p>   although some might doubt that, and a sense of always trying to</p>
<p>   do the right thing by people, for which I have remained grateful</p>
<p>   during my life.</p>
<p>My father died when I was 16 but I have never forgotten his influence</p>
<p>   and I have never forgotten his great decency and his quiet love</p>
<p>   of his country and his commitment to his community and most particularly</p>
<p>   to his family.</p>
<p>My mother was an immensely strong and influential person who fiercely</p>
<p>   protected and promoted the interests of her four sons, of which</p>
<p>   she became immensely proud. She of course didn't live to see</p>
<p>   me become Prime Minister. She did live to see me become Federal</p>
<p>   Treasurer and she died just a few weeks before I was ejected from</p>
<p>   that office by the vote of the Australian people. But I owe both</p>
<p>   of them, now long-dead, a very great debt of gratitude.</p>
<p>To my three older brothers, with whom I have always had a very</p>
<p>   close bond. Wal, my eldest brother, is here today with his wife</p>
<p>   Gwyn, and my next-eldest brother, Stan. Wal was the small businessman</p>
<p>   in the family which followed Dad's pattern and he's now</p>
<p>   very happily retired next to the Leura golf course which is a pleasant</p>
<p>   existence. He's come down here. And Stan, who became a very</p>
<p>   well known corporate lawyer around town and in Sydney, a company</p>
<p>   director. And then of course there's Bob who is quite well</p>
<p>   known on the other side of the political spectrum. Bob and I are</p>
<p>   an interesting sort of commentary on what is the essentially egalitarian,</p>
<p>   and I think likeable character, of Australian politics.</p>
<p>I won't tell that foundry joke again, Janette, but one of</p>
<p>   the things that's always terrific about Australian politics</p>
<p>   is that there is still an accessibility and a capacity to jump across</p>
<p>   a political barrier in Australia that doesn't exist in many</p>
<p>   other countries. Bob was once a member of the Liberal Party but</p>
<p>   he left us, I suspect largely because of the Vietnam war, but not</p>
<p>   entirely because of that, and he's now a very active member</p>
<p>   of the, what he calls the nice left of the Labor Party in New South</p>
<p>   Wales.</p>
<p>Thereby hangs a marvellous story when, was it Les McMahon who used</p>
<p>   to be the Labor Member for Sydney? He was being challenged for preselection</p>
<p>   by Peter Baldwin, and Peter Baldwin as you know was on the left</p>
<p>   and my brother, Bob, was a member of one of the branches in Leichhardt.</p>
<p>   And Les came up to me in the corridor one day and he said, "John,</p>
<p>   do you think you could put in a word in the pre-selection ballot</p>
<p>   with your brother for me"?</p>
<p>I said, "forget it mate, he's barracking for Peter Baldwin".</p>
<p>   And of course, that turned out to be the case. Bob and Baldwin won,</p>
<p>   Les lost but the point of all of that is Bob and I have remained</p>
<p>   good friends and good brothers. When I became Prime Minister I rang</p>
<p>   him up to invite him down to the swearing in because he'd worked</p>
<p>   in a polling booth on Petersham Town Hall all day on election day.</p>
<p>   I said, "you ought to come down to the swearing in". He</p>
<p>   said, "I'll do that". He said, "what's</p>
<p>   the order of proceedings?" I said, "well, the order of</p>
<p>   proceedings is that I get sworn in as Prime Minister and then we</p>
<p>   all go in and I sort of introduce my Ministry to the Governor General,</p>
<p>   and they are all sworn in one in turn". He said, "I tell</p>
<p>   you what, I'll strike a deal with you". He said, "I</p>
<p>   will be there for your swearing in". He said, "we can</p>
<p>   then have a photograph and a cup of tea" but he said, "I</p>
<p>   don't think I could hang around for the rest of your mob".</p>
<p>So I thought that was a very decent compromise but it's never</p>
<p>   fair in those circumstances of course to leave unacknowledged the</p>
<p>   enormous contribution that the two of my brothers who voted Liberal</p>
<p>   and remain very bright and clear-eyed on these matters and have</p>
<p>   been very, very staunch and loyal supporters in every sense of the</p>
<p>   word, of my political aspirations.</p>
<p>And of course, to my three magnificent children with whom, as the</p>
<p>   years went by I have grown ever more fond. I didn't think when</p>
<p>   I was dumped as Leader of the Opposition in 1989 it was all that</p>
<p>   flash but one thing it did do was that at a critical time in the</p>
<p>   ages of my children it meant that I spent a great deal more time</p>
<p>   with them.</p>
<p>One of the great pieces of mythology in bringing up children is</p>
<p>   the belief that it's when they're sort of in their late</p>
<p>   teens that you've got to find more time for them. The fact</p>
<p>   is that by the time they're in their late teens they're</p>
<p>   not particularly interested in you finding a lot more time for them</p>
<p>   and it's really much earlier than that and of course I got</p>
<p>   dumped at a time that neatly coincided with that. Over the years</p>
<p>   they have been very good political advisers, down to my son, Tim.</p>
<p>   When I was talking about the necessity of preparing for the second</p>
<p>   debate against Paul Keating in the last election he said to me,</p>
<p>   "Dad, you've got to do something about those shoulders".</p>
<p>He was referring to the fact that I tended, when I was trying to</p>
<p>   make a point, to do something with my shoulders and keeping that</p>
<p>   in mind, keeping Tim's admonition in mind, I did precisely</p>
<p>   that. I can see Janette is looking at me saying, John, this is going</p>
<p>   on just a little bit too long, and it is but you don't launch</p>
<p>   your own biography every day, do you.</p>
<p>Can I thank David, with assistance from Pru, for their friendship.</p>
<p>   It has been a friendship over a long period of time. David has acute</p>
<p>   and impeccable judgements on most things, although a few things</p>
<p>   where we do disagree rather violently. He has a wealth of political</p>
<p>   experience and understanding and both David and Pru are people who</p>
<p>   understand not only the mechanical side of politics but also the</p>
<p>   human side of politics.</p>
<p>And it's of enormous importance that people with that treasure</p>
<p>   trove of experience have the opportunity of putting it down and</p>
<p>   whether you agree with it or disagree, or reject it or accept it,</p>
<p>   it becomes part of the written history. As we approach the centenary</p>
<p>   of the Federation of Australia we are going to get increasingly</p>
<p>   interested in what's gone before us and I think over the next</p>
<p>   two or three years we are going to have an explosion of interest</p>
<p>   in this country in what we have achieved, particularly over the</p>
<p>   last 100 years.</p>
<p>Of course as we get to the Centenary of Federation, we are getting</p>
<p>   to that moment when there would be so few, if at all, Australians</p>
<p>   left who participated in some of the great events that have shaped</p>
<p>   this century and shaped the first 100 years of the Australian nation.</p>
<p>   It won't be long before there will be nobody left alive who</p>
<p>   served in World War One. There will be diminishing numbers of people</p>
<p>   who experienced the rigours of the Great Depression and as we get</p>
<p>   towards the centenary of our Federation, we are reminded of all</p>
<p>   that experience and all that history. Everything is a</p>
<p>contribution to that so I am very, very grateful to all of you.</p>
<p>   I want to conclude by saying that it's not only a chronicle</p>
<p>   of the 25 years in Australian politics. It's also a chronicle</p>
<p>   of the ins and outs and the successes and the triumphs and the failures</p>
<p>   and the losses of the Liberal Party of Australia.</p>
<p>I joined the Liberal Party of Australia 40 years ago. I owe it</p>
<p>   an enormous debt. I would not have been a Member of Parliament had</p>
<p>   it not been for the Liberal Party. I would not have been leader</p>
<p>   of the Party without that gift from it, and I certainly would not</p>
<p>   have been Prime Minister, and I have a deep love of the Party with</p>
<p>   all its weaknesses and I think it is a great institution. And I</p>
<p>   remain profoundly in its debt as I am in the debt of David and Pru</p>
<p>   for this excellent production.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
