<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11200</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON TIM FISCHER MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH SALLY SARA                 AM PROGRAMME</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/01/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is time the Democrats stopped fudging on these issues and faced</p>
<p> up to their responsibilities on the floor of the Senate when we come</p>
<p> to that critical vote on tax reform later this year.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>Can Jeff Kennett play a useful role as a provocateur in reform debates</p>
<p> like health, and the GST?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm too busy to dwell on the roles of State Premiers. I agree</p>
<p> with his comments that the $300 break through private health insurance</p>
<p> incentive is a great step forward which is being taken up by hundreds</p>
<p> of people already in this first week of January. And that in its own</p>
<p> way is going to further help the hospital and health system right</p>
<p> across Australia.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, there were reports this morning that top public service</p>
<p> chiefs will be receiving a 40% pay rise. If that's true, how</p>
<p> can it be justified?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I note that in one of those reports if they were to get the full rise</p>
<p> indicated they would still be behind those of New South Wales and</p>
<p> Victorian equivalent top public servants. That means Australia is</p>
<p> paying our federal senior public servants, who have to perform to</p>
<p> contracts, less than State governments are paying their senior public</p>
<p> servants. Those same State government public servants who seem to</p>
<p> think nothing of maintaining a credit card system for senior ministers</p>
<p> and senior State public servants, that has been used and abused for</p>
<p> years and ought to have been straightened out by them by now, and</p>
<p> yet they still get more pay. I will defend the federal government</p>
<p> having a remuneration level which will enable us to attract the competent,</p>
<p> cut through administrators we must have in the governance of this</p>
<p> country.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>So if there were a rise of around 40% to take the Commonwealth public</p>
<p> service chiefs up to the level of some of their State counterparts,</p>
<p> that would be justified in principle in your view?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think unfortunately we have no choice in the matter if we are to</p>
<p> have the level of capability and competence and maintain that. The</p>
<p> challenge that is put to these senior federal public servants is quite</p>
<p> onerous and they deserve remuneration.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, on a separate issue, fresh allegations were raised last</p>
<p> night on an SBS television programme of torture and killing of civilians</p>
<p> by Indonesians troops in East Timor. What will Australia do to investigate</p>
<p> these claims?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The federal Government will evaluate any fresh evidence. It's</p>
<p> something that I'll be asking Foreign Affairs and Trade to look</p>
<p> into this day. Obviously there needs to be every effort made to ascertain</p>
<p> the extent of any massacre that occurred last year as opposed to previously</p>
<p> in East Timor and the Australian Government would view that with the</p>
<p> greatest concern.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>The Indonesian Government has denied the claims. Isn't that assurance</p>
<p> good enough for the Australian Government?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm not in a position to answer that right at this time.</p>
<p> I have not seen the detail of the fresh allegations.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>On a separate foreign affairs issue, the United Nations Secretary</p>
<p> General, Kofi Annan, has reportedly raised concerns that UNSCOM may</p>
<p> have helped the United States spy on the Iraqis. Do you have any information</p>
<p> regarding those claims.</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Richard Butler is of course not employed by the Australian Government.</p>
<p> But Richard Butler has fully denied those claims. I make note of that</p>
<p> but I don't comment in detail on matters which relate to security.</p>
<p> But I do note that Butler himself has said there is no truth in those</p>
<p> claims.</p>
<p>SARA:</p>
<p>Could this undermine further though the position of the United States</p>
<p> the fact that these allegations have been raised?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's too early to say that but these are matters which have been</p>
<p> denied by someone who should know after all, and that is head of UNSCOM,</p>
<p> Richard Butler.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
