<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>273</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES, AT THE COMMONWEALTH CLUB, ADELAIDE, ON 13TH FEBRUARY ,1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/02/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000273_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY TIE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
R. G. MENZIES, -AT THE C012, ONtWE LTH CLUB,<br />
ADELAIDE, onI3TH FEBRUARY, 1961<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. Premier and ladies and gentlemen:<br />
That last remark ' You are just as welcome as you were<br />
27 years ago' is one of the greatest masterpieces that I have<br />
ever listened to. Because, you seel 27 years ago it didn't<br />
matter what I did, so far as you were concerned I was acting<br />
Premier of Victoria. ( Laughter) The Chairman conceals the<br />
intervening period except for the time when I came as Leader<br />
of the Opposition. But there are one or two other preliminary<br />
remarks that I would like to make.<br />
First of all, when I was standing out in the lobby<br />
seeing the " great" go by I was delighted to encounter Stanley<br />
Skipper. ( Applause) He looked to me to be almost exactly as he<br />
was whon I first knew him a mere matter of 32 or 33 years ago.<br />
And he said to me " I have been practising at the Bar for<br />
years." ' Jell if he had been a politician I would have said,<br />
" You're a liar!( Laughter) But you don't talk like that to<br />
distinguished lawyers. However I am delighted to know that he<br />
is hereoand fascinated to think that this Club, now so we-. ll<br />
known ail over Australia, was established by him what<br />
years ago? It seems almost unbelievable.<br />
Now you said, Sir, that I must have forgotten what it<br />
was like to be Leader of the Opposition. On the contrary I<br />
remember it very well. And I remember some of the rules for<br />
getting out of Opposition and getting into Government. But I<br />
am keeping them to myself. ( Laughter) Why should I egg on my<br />
friend Mr. Walsh? ( Laughter) Vhy should I give the priceless<br />
secrets of the art of Opposition to my friend, Mr. Calwoll?<br />
Certainly not! Some day I will write a chapter in a book about<br />
it. That will be, I think, rather helpful to whoever is leading<br />
the Opposition then. And who knows who that will be?<br />
Now I know that this is not a political gathering in a<br />
Party sense and I don't propose to make any Party observations.<br />
But I would like to say a little to you about one of our<br />
domestic problems, our national domestic problems, which has an<br />
international flav~ ur; and something about the international<br />
problem itself. Perhaps I might say something about the second first,<br />
because I was reminded of it when the Chairman was introducing<br />
various people and we were applauding then. I have the bad old<br />
habit, if my loft hand is otherwise engaged, of smacking the<br />
table by way of applause. I had to go to the General Assembly<br />
of the United Nations to discover that that is not done any<br />
longer. Because the first time at the General Assembly that<br />
somebody made a speech that I agreed with and that didn't<br />
happen for a couple of days ( Laughter) I beat on the table in<br />
front of me, only to find myself checked by my colleagues who<br />
said, " No, no; no, no. When you smack the table, that's<br />
disapproval. Look at K. and his colleagues along there."<br />
( Laughter) And of course when your disapproval is exceptionally<br />
violent the drill is to take your shoe off and hit the table<br />
with your shoe. ( Laughter)<br />
But I couldn't help thinking at that Assembly what a<br />
strange world it is that we live in twelve or thirteen new<br />
members of the United Nations last year, most of them from<br />
Africa in particular. New nations, the very names of some of<br />
which most of us had never heard. And they are members of the<br />
United Nations. In round figures now a hundred nations in the<br />
United Nations; and people making a play for their support, Ai </p>
<p>particularly our distinguished friend Mr. Khrushchev. Everything<br />
directed to propaganda; to either terrorising people or<br />
persuading people or demonstrating the weakness of the effete<br />
Western powers. It means that we have entered into a phase of<br />
international affairs that is almost infinitely difficult.<br />
We are a little bit inclined ourselves, aren't we<br />
most of us I think are to assume that when a country wins<br />
independence, all you have to do is to say to it, " Very well<br />
now, you just have a Parliament, and elect a Parliament, and<br />
get a Government and everything in the garden is lovely?". It<br />
is quite untrue. Most of the now nations will go through<br />
periods of practical dictatorship before they ever achieve<br />
what we would understand to be a systen of self-government.<br />
You can take the whole of the African countries, with the<br />
possible exception of Nigeria, which has been brought to selfgovernment<br />
by splendid decrees by the British authorities and<br />
which has, incidentally, a magnificent Prime Minister but<br />
with that exception you may take then right across ana you will<br />
find that almost inevitably the head of the Government will do<br />
things that no head of a Government in Australia would dream of<br />
doing except perhaps the Premier of South Australia.<br />
( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />
True, there is a Parliament. But as I said to one of<br />
my distinguished friends from one of these countries only last<br />
year, " Tell re, is your Opposition Leader still in gaol?"<br />
( Laughter) And the answer was, " Yes".<br />
Well these things are slightly different from the<br />
circumstances that we understand. And they mean that there are<br />
a great number of these new countries, particularly in the<br />
north of Africa and the centre of Africa whose constitutional<br />
future, if I may put it in that way, remains uncertain or, at<br />
any rate, experimental. Now this throws a great responsibility<br />
on the rest of us: not to be in too much of a hurry to think<br />
that our system of government is necessarily the right one for<br />
then, but to develop an attitude of sympathy and helpfulness.<br />
I know there are some people who say that " charity<br />
begins at hone" and who have some reluctance about the<br />
substantial suns of money that Australia finds under the<br />
Colombo Plan under various aids of an international kind. I<br />
want to say to you that what has been done before must be vastly<br />
increased in all the Jestern world in the future if we are not<br />
to permit such economic disorder to arise in these countries as<br />
will make them readily responsive to the Communist pressure.<br />
Not long ago the Communists of the Soviet Union and<br />
the Communists of China had a great Conference in Moscow. It<br />
must have been a pretty lively one judging by the echoes that<br />
have reached my own ears, because there are material<br />
differences between them. But in the long run what they appear<br />
to have emerged with was this: " We are not going to seek to<br />
achieve our aim by overt military action because that involves<br />
too great a risk of destruction. But we still will seek to<br />
achieve our aims of Communist propaganda by means of<br />
persuasion, pressure, threat and economic penetration."<br />
You nay take it, that as I talk here today the<br />
economic penetration goes on in all these new countries in<br />
Africa and in all the countries of South-East Asia which stand<br />
between Conrmunist China and ourselves, the pressure goes on.<br />
If this is to be met it will be met not merely by military<br />
means, because the other side exist on internal lines of<br />
cormmunication and are, in a military sense, much more compact<br />
than the . lestorn world can be, but must be net by encouraging </p>
<p>0 3.<br />
nutual understanding, by extending oconorlic and technical<br />
assistance to the very limit of our capacity. If we don't if<br />
we say " What has that got to do with us?" then we will, some<br />
day, we or our sons and daughters, have a very rude awakening.<br />
It used to be said about us in Australia and not so<br />
long ago that we didn't care a hoot about international<br />
affairs; they didn't concern us. There was a certain amount of<br />
truth in that charge. I think we take a vastly greater<br />
anount of interest today in international affairs than we did.<br />
And I hope that is true, because disaster for us won't be the<br />
product of internal events; it could be the product of events<br />
engendered in countries outside Australia altogether.<br />
Therefore we must play our part;<br />
It is one of the tragedies, I think, of modern<br />
thinking that the United States of Aerica which has done out<br />
of its wealth so much to help new countries, so much to help<br />
underdeveloped countries, should have received not many thanks,<br />
a good deal of abuse a good deal of nisunderstanding. And I<br />
warn you, as I warned the General Assembly when I spoke there,<br />
that the great stroke of propaganda that is being engaged in is<br />
an attempt to persuade ordinary men and wonen, particularly in<br />
the uncommitted countries, that the whole argument in the world<br />
is an arguent between . American capitalism and Soviet communism,<br />
with all the rest of us, presumably, just onlookers. This is a<br />
ruinous alternative. It isn't a case of the United States<br />
against the Soviet Union. It is a case of free countries, with<br />
free institutions, against countries with slave institutions<br />
not lAerica versus the Soviet Union, but Communism against all<br />
the rest of us.<br />
I turn away from that subject although those things<br />
cane prominently into mind in looking at the representatives of<br />
99 different nations at the United Nations last November.<br />
Now I want to say something about one of our own<br />
problems which has an international flavour. Every now and<br />
then some Govermnent it happens to be mine at present sets<br />
out to do something about our balance of payments, about the<br />
state of our overseas reserves. And a lot of people very<br />
naturally, I don't blame then at all say " But why couldn't<br />
these things have been fixed up once a year, or once in two<br />
years; why don't we have some steady consistent, unchanging<br />
approach to these matters?". I want to say a word about that.<br />
Why do we have balance of payments problems in<br />
Australia? Why is it that the balance ofpayments problem for<br />
Australia is probably rore acute, more changeable, more subject<br />
to violent fluctuations than is the case in any other country<br />
that I know of? We need to start by understanding this. You<br />
see the great bulk of our exports to the world consists of<br />
primary products wool and wheat and meat and butter and so<br />
on. And the price that we get for these things varies very<br />
sharply. If there is a rise in the price of wool our export<br />
income is up œ 80 million, a œ 100 nillion; everybody is happy.<br />
If the price of wool declines by œ 80 or œ 100 million then<br />
exactly the opposite state of mind is produced. And apart<br />
altogether from the state of mind, you can see the export<br />
income of Australia going up and down, year by year, like a<br />
yo-yo. This is one of the remarkable things that applies to<br />
our export earnings.<br />
But while our export inco. e rises and falls very<br />
sharply our demand for imports doesn't fall very sharply because<br />
the demand for imports depends so much on the internal<br />
purchasing power that we have in the country. And as we have </p>
<p>been going through a quite remarkable boor in Australia the<br />
local purchasing power is high, and so the do-and for imports<br />
is high. In spite of all recent neasures the import bill in<br />
January was considerably higher than the import bill in<br />
December or November or October. ed have an alost insatiable<br />
appetite for imports. When we have bought all that we can buy<br />
here we buy imports. And the result is that you tend to have a<br />
high line on the import side, and a fluctuating line on the<br />
export side. And therefore your reserves go up and down, and<br />
measures have to be taken from tine to time to arrest the fall<br />
lest the fall should become inveterate and involve you in<br />
serious international troubles. In other words most of the<br />
time, internationally speaking, we live beyond our means we<br />
use capital, as a nation, to pay for our purchases on current<br />
account. No business man would do that and no Government<br />
ought to do it. Therefore, constantly Governments I don't<br />
care what Government it may be find themselves compelled to do<br />
something about this marked fluctuation in our balances of<br />
trade. You may say to me, " Well, why doesn't that trouble<br />
other countries?". Let me point out to you that in actual<br />
total figures, not per capit t. Australia is one of the eight<br />
great traing nations of the Wrild. In the first eight! It is<br />
a remarkable thing for a little country of ten million people<br />
in the first eight trading nations in the world. And so<br />
constituted is our economy that our international trade is a<br />
far greater proportion of our total trade than is the case in<br />
the United States of America, or even in the case of Japan<br />
though we think of Japan, don't we, as a formidable and<br />
aggressive international trader. A greater proportion of our<br />
business crosses the seas than is the case in either of these<br />
very great trading nations. And so we are more vulnerable.<br />
If somebody could come along and say, " Well here's a<br />
beautiful notion, the world is going to stabilize the price that<br />
it will pay us for our wool", it would be a marvellous episode<br />
as long as it was stabilized on the right level. If these<br />
things happened, so that our export earnings moved very little<br />
in one direction or the other our position in relation to the<br />
whole of our international trade policy would be much easier,<br />
and our balances of payments would present much smaller<br />
problems. But it happens that in the last seven years the terns<br />
of trade have moved steadily against Australia. If you took the<br />
terms of trade at a sort of parity of 100 in 1953, they are now<br />
The terms of trade have moved more sharply against<br />
Australia than they have against any other country whose figures<br />
are recorded. Now that is not the fault of Australia. It<br />
merely means that our exports are not connranding the same price<br />
and that our imports do comrand a high level of price.<br />
Therefore, translating it into the terms of trade we are in an<br />
adverse position. How this matter ought to be solved in the long run is,<br />
of course, a problem for all of us. How it can be dealt with<br />
in the short run is a problem for all of us.<br />
Talking about the short run first we speak, very<br />
properly, about increasing our exports. That is right. But all<br />
the matters that have been discussed about increasing our<br />
exports are in essential terms long range matters. You don't<br />
suddenly increase your export of manufactured goods over night;<br />
you don't suddenly over night increase the export of beef from<br />
the North; you don't attend to any of these things just like<br />
that, hastily they are long range remedies. But in the short </p>
<p>run any Govornment may have to .10 som-) e very difficult things<br />
because, for the reasons that I have rmeintioned to you you can<br />
begin a year with overseas reserves standing at a hanasorlo<br />
figure like œ C500 millions, and end the financial year with them<br />
standing at œ C250I. This is an enormous fluctuation. This<br />
doesn't occur in a country like Great Britain where the oxpozrts<br />
are manufactured commodities and there is, thereforo, a gr'eater<br />
stability of price and production and sale.<br />
Because this fluctuation there are those who say<br />
and I respect their view very much " Well in order to meet<br />
that, in order to keep your reserves at a stable level, since<br />
you can't control the price of your exports, you can't control<br />
that variable line, you must have a variable line of imports by<br />
having a fluctuating series of physical import restrictions".<br />
Now I wonder what the business community in Australia would<br />
think of that, if you had a system of import controls which<br />
varied roughly with the line of our export income so that it was<br />
here today and gone tomorrow, up next month and down a few<br />
months later. I don't think, you know, that that is practical<br />
politics. You may impose restrictions on imports to give you a<br />
sort of average result for a reasonable period of time but you<br />
really can't have your import level, by Government action,<br />
fluctuating with the same degree of rapidity up and down, as<br />
your export earnin,: s.<br />
This, the~ refore, presents a problem which is not to<br />
be solved over a dining table or between two club arm chairs.<br />
It doesn't possess the noble simplicity that so many of us think<br />
it does. The fact is that doing what we can in Australia to<br />
deal with these abnormal short term variations, we miust<br />
increasingly look for the long term solution. ' Ind the long term<br />
solution is that this country should become an exporter not<br />
only of wool and these , great commodities that we have lived on<br />
internationally, but of manufactured commodities. Aind why we<br />
shouldn't I don't know. It won't happen overnight. I have an<br />
infinite belief in the skill and resourcefulness of<br />
Australians, whether they are employees in a factory or<br />
managers or whatever they may be. And I don't think that we<br />
ought to despair, with all this , reat new A1sian world opening<br />
around us of being able to match the United States of America<br />
or m:-atch the United Kingdom in the production of goods for<br />
expert. The great point about it is this. Many of us here<br />
today remember the depression of the early 30' s. That<br />
depression arose from a variety of circumstances, most of which<br />
were entirely outside Australia. But one of the circuastances<br />
was that the price of our export comm-xodities fell to the<br />
gutter almost overnight. The price of wool you remember it?<br />
It seems fantastic to look back on wool at 6d. or 7d. The<br />
price of wheat dear me, nobody would believe it if they<br />
didn't know about it, and you just told then. as a fable that at<br />
that time the price of wheat was getting down to under a<br />
bushel. The result was that with our export income drying up<br />
we becamie no longer an interesting subject for ovarseas<br />
investment; the capital market dried up and we found ourselves<br />
confronting a tremaendous economic crisis. So tremuendous that,<br />
although we now get a little disturbed if unemployment rises<br />
to three quarters of 1% of the work force, by 1939 as I well<br />
r~ juember we were rather content because unemploynent had been<br />
reduced to 10% not three quarters of These days ought<br />
to be remembered for those reasons. </p>
<p>But the great reason for all this was that<br />
economically we stood on one foot at that time. If our export<br />
income fell down, we didn't have the internal economic<br />
structure of manufacturing, primary, secondary and tertiary<br />
industries to enable us to absorb the shock. That kind of<br />
thing couldn't happen to us today because this is now a<br />
powerful industrial country.<br />
You look back to South Australia before the time<br />
when the Premier and I put our heads tog~ ether to move munitions<br />
establishm-ents into this State and begin a great era of<br />
industrialisation. Why if you go back to 1930-31 in South<br />
AIustralia here was a State dependent entirely on primary<br />
production and therefore liable to all the unprotected shocks<br />
of changes in the world market. But today it is a great<br />
industrial State. Australia is a -rge at industrial country.<br />
And therefore we are able to balance ourselves. What I am<br />
saying to you is that in the long run if we are going to avoid<br />
in future having too frequent changes in the application of<br />
monetary and financial policy we must strive to be in a<br />
position where riot only in dom. estic term:, s we stand on two feetprimary,<br />
secondary but in export terms we stand on two feetprimary<br />
and secondary. When we do there will still be some<br />
fluctuations in our export eairnings, there will still be some<br />
movements in our balance of paynents, of course. But they<br />
will be much miore radual when they are composed of a variety<br />
of elements instead of lipending entirely on one.<br />
Now, Sir, I " cm sorry-I told you, you told me that<br />
I was to finish at five to two and at present I am in that<br />
chastened mood in which I am everybody's humble and obedient<br />
servant. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
