<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3728</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S QUEENSLAND BROADCAST NO 7 - CENTRALISM - SUNDAY 4 MAY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003728.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargo : Sunday_ 5 pm<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S QUEENSLAND BROADCAST No. 7<br />
CENTRALISM<br />
Sunday 4 May 1975<br />
I thought I'd talk to you about a subject that is<br />
dear to the heart of the Queensland Premier Centralism.<br />
Mr. Bjelke-Petersen has a regular obsession with centralism,<br />
as we all know. Whenever he objects to something whether<br />
it's a Labor idea or even something from the anti-Labor sidehe<br />
cries " centralism". I don't mind people having bees in<br />
their bonnet, but I think we're entitled to object when their<br />
obsessions hold back the development of a State or interfere<br />
with Government programs that the people have clearly endorsed.<br />
As far as I can understand, Mr. Bjelke-Petersen means<br />
by " icentralism" anything that the Australian Government tries<br />
to do for the people of Queensland. He used to say Medibank<br />
was centralism, but fortunately his Liberal Party colleagues<br />
in the coalition saw the clear benefits of Medibank for their<br />
State. He said our plans to make Townsville a growth centre<br />
were centralism, that our plans to get down the price of land<br />
were centralism, and he used this catchcry to deny Queenslanders<br />
$ 50 million in Federal funds.<br />
The fact is that the powers of the Australian Government<br />
in relation to the States are defined in the Constitution.<br />
If anyone thinks the National Government is overstepping the<br />
mark they can challenge our action in the High Court. That<br />
is the real defence against any centralist policies. In our<br />
federal system the States, the Commonwealth and Local Government<br />
all have a role to play. And we have to play it according to<br />
the constitutional rules.<br />
I have said that it's not just Labor Policies that<br />
Mr. Bjelke-Petersen regards as centralist. He levelled the<br />
same charge at Mr. Gorton when he was Prime Minister.<br />
Mr. Gorton was convinced that oUi? off-shore mineral resources<br />
were the responsibility of the National Government. He was<br />
quite right. Anything that has to do with mineral exports<br />
or overseas trade is a federal responsibility, and other<br />
countries expect to negotiate with the Australian Government<br />
in these matters rather than particular States. Mr. Gorton<br />
got nowhere in his efforts to assert this very clear principle<br />
and Queensland has continued to resist our own efforts to<br />
legislate on off-shore sovereignty. Mr. Gorton had the<br />
same trouble with the Great Barrier Reef. His attempts to<br />
protect the Reef from oil drilling and other damage met<br />
strong opposition from Mr. Bjelke-Petersen. The centralist<br />
slogan was trotted out again. And it was used when Mr. Gorton<br />
sought better tredtm~ rit for Qd.~ eris" I~ iid's Abdrilirids: </p>
<p>2.<br />
You will remember that the referendum in 1967 -which<br />
was carried overwhelmingly in Queensland gave the Australian<br />
Government clear authority to legislate for the welfare of<br />
Aborigines and, if necessary, to override State laws.<br />
Mr. Gorton sought an end to a number of discriminatory laws<br />
on the statute book in Queensland. Mr. Ejelke-Petersen saw<br />
this as centralism. It is taking a long time to remove<br />
these laws. In the past few weeks my own Government has<br />
introduced legislation in the National Parliament for this<br />
very purpose. One of the great phobias of the Premier concerns<br />
our efforts to make the High Court the final court of appeal<br />
in this country and to end appeals from Australian courts to<br />
the British Privy Council. It was the Holt Government back<br />
in 1967, that stopped appeals to the Privy Council from the<br />
High Court. We think it's time to stop appeals from the<br />
Supreme Courts as well. After all, our Australian High<br />
Court has a reputation second to none throughout the legal<br />
kwortld: oits judgments are everywhere respected. How absurd<br />
have a British Court, sitting in Britain, with judges<br />
appointed in Britain by the British Government, sit in<br />
judgment on Australian courts. Surely it's time surely<br />
we're mature enough to accept that Australians should no<br />
longer litigate their disputes before the Court of another<br />
country. I give you other examples. In his holy war against<br />
centralism, Mr. Bjelke-Petersen has opposed our plan for<br />
an Australian honours system. Never mind that the old<br />
imperial honours are made in the name of an empire that<br />
doesn't exist. Never mind that the Queen herself has<br />
approved the Order of Australia and will confer the awards<br />
herself. Mr. Bjelke-Petersen thinks it's " centralism"<br />
He doesn't want an Australian national anthem either that's<br />
liIcentralist" too despite the fact that a vast majority of<br />
Australians want an anthem of -their own. His silliest idea<br />
of all was to have Her Majesty described as Queen of Queensland.<br />
Imagine if every Canadian province or British county had a<br />
separate monarch a Queen of Ontario, a Queen of Alberta,<br />
a Queen of Lancashire. Where would it end?<br />
It's strange, isn't it, that everything Mr. Bjelke-Petersen<br />
calls centralist" is really pro-Australian, a mark of our true<br />
nationhood and maturity? I wonder what he's really afraid of.<br />
He constantly talks about the meanness and wickedness of<br />
Canberra. The fact is that Queensland has received more in<br />
assistance in hard cash from the present Labor Government<br />
than it has received from any previous Government in history.<br />
No amount of hedging or qualification, no talk of restrictions<br />
or strings or the value of moneXy1 can alter the t?<br />
p~ whxnggr erbust. In t, -I~ t -f4I~ </p>
<p>3.<br />
Not only does Queensland get much, much more than<br />
she did from the Liberals in Canberra; she gets considerably<br />
more per head of population than other States get now.<br />
Queensland received more than $ 382 per head of population<br />
in 1973-74 compared with $ 343 per head in average payments<br />
to all States. Last year our grants for primary and<br />
secondary education were up 145 per cent on the year before,<br />
tertiary education was up 165 per cent, technical education<br />
110 per cent, welfare housing 20 per cent, aboriginal<br />
advancement nearly 30 per cent. Health and welfare, roads<br />
and urban and regional development in Queensland are all<br />
getting record amounts from my Government.<br />
Next time you hear the Premier talk about centralism,<br />
think of those facts of what the Australian Government<br />
has done for Queensland, and the real help we have given<br />
despite the Premier's obstruction. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
