<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8842</transcript-id>
    <title>VICTORY SPEECH</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/03/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008842.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: S P06---<br />
WELL this is the * weetebt victory of All<br />
-this is thes~ weret. This is a victory for<br />
the true believers, the people who in<br />
difficult times. have ke'pt the faith and to<br />
the Austr-4lian people going throucih hard<br />
time. It makebs tileir Ac-t Of faith All that<br />
much greater.<br />
It will be a long time before an<br />
Opposition party' tries to divide this<br />
Country again. 11 w~ ill be is lont time beforc<br />
somebodyv tries~ to put one 970UP Of<br />
Australians over here and another group<br />
over there.<br />
The public of Atustralia are tooo decent<br />
and they awe too consacientious and the.%<br />
are too interested in their country to wear<br />
those sorts of things.<br />
This I think has been very much a<br />
victory of Australian values, because It<br />
was Australian values on the line and the<br />
Liberiii Party wanted to change Austria<br />
from the coup try I is become, a coaperatie,<br />
decent. nice place to live where<br />
people have regard for ovie another.<br />
Anid could I just say that this has been a<br />
hard campaign and I can assure every<br />
member of the public out there, when<br />
they think we don't know In the political<br />
system how tough it is. I can assure you I<br />
can tell you how tough It was in those last<br />
few weeks.<br />
But can I say to you that I wanted to win<br />
iigain, to be there in the 19905 to see<br />
Australia prosper as it will.<br />
The thing is. I said to the Australian<br />
people ~ we've tu-nea the corner'. Can I say<br />
now, after the election, let me repeat it:<br />
we have turned the corner. The growth is<br />
coming through. We will see ourselves as<br />
a sophisticated trading country in Asia<br />
and we've got to do It in a way where<br />
everybody's got a part in it, where<br />
everyone's In It.<br />
There's always cause for concern but<br />
never pessimism and Australia, wherein<br />
for the first time in our history, located in<br />
the region o( the fastest growth in the<br />
world, and we've been set up now, we are<br />
set up now as~ we've never been set up<br />
before to be in It, to exploit. It, to be part of<br />
IIt offers tremendous opportunities for<br />
Autralans and now we have to do it. and<br />
we havi. to do it comspas. sionately.<br />
I give an assurance to the people that<br />
this victory won't go to the heads of the Victory from<br />
true believers<br />
Government of the Labur Party. Well<br />
take~ it seriously, we'll Wike it thankfully,<br />
and well do a great deal with it.<br />
The people of Austraia, have t" en us<br />
on trurt. and we'll return that trust and<br />
we'll care about those people out there,<br />
particularly the unemployed we want to<br />
get them back to work.<br />
If we can't get them back to work<br />
Immredilately. sune as hell we are going<br />
to took after them. We are not going to<br />
leave them in the lurch. We are not going<br />
to leave them In the lurch and we are<br />
going put our hand out and we are going<br />
to pull them up behind u&amp;.<br />
And we are going to move along, this<br />
country is going to move along together.<br />
We have such enormous opportunity. This<br />
world recession is now starting to<br />
dissipate, we've made the break out of It,<br />
This is the text of the victory<br />
speech by the Prime Minister,<br />
Mr Keoting<br />
America's starting to turn, it won't be that<br />
long before the Japanese economy 5tarts<br />
to turn, and hopefully well be away and<br />
running In the 90s in a low inflationary<br />
period of prosperity.<br />
I can assure you the Government will<br />
now be redoubling its efforts to be as good<br />
a government iia you hope and expect we<br />
can be. To be as Conscientious with this<br />
mandate as we possibly Can be. to give It<br />
our every ef fort our every shot, to see<br />
that we recover quickly and we get going<br />
and we put t'his recessionary period<br />
behind us and we Set this country Of<br />
opportunity off and running.<br />
But keeping the opporteuity for<br />
everybody keeping those preat<br />
keeping those great..,. keeping those<br />
great nostrumb of access and equity.<br />
Getting people into the game. The<br />
poliies~ of inclusion. The policies of One Nation. And that's what it,-g ot to be<br />
about. So can I say Again. this is a tremendous<br />
victory. It's a tremendous victory for all<br />
those who have got imagination and faith.<br />
The people who believe in things. who are<br />
not going to let orood beliefs be put aside<br />
for e. sentially miserable ideas to divide<br />
the place up.<br />
I mean. I think the Australian people<br />
have always had such remarkable sense to<br />
spot the value and to cut their way<br />
through It.<br />
Now part of this victory is our part of<br />
it is them spotting what they think were<br />
the dangers In the Liberal Party's policies,<br />
What I hope in that the next election the<br />
victory is 100 per cent due to the good<br />
governiment of Labor.<br />
Now. I'd like to start thanking tiome<br />
people and the first person I'd like to start<br />
with is my wife, Aurtita, who has helped<br />
me right through the campaign. Thank<br />
yout. Arid can I also say, can I give an extras<br />
special note of thanks to the women of<br />
Australia. who voted for us believing in<br />
the policies of this Government.<br />
I want to pay a paticular thanks also to<br />
good on you mate I want to pay at<br />
particular thanks to the architects of this<br />
victory, my personal staff. Don Russell,<br />
Mark Ryab. Don Watson. my press<br />
sertaries and the rest.<br />
And most partcularly to those people In<br />
the Labor Party w-ho've never lost faith,<br />
never iost heart. and are there at the<br />
polling booths to work and to fight for<br />
good things. Thank you. The people who<br />
never give up but always keep on believing<br />
and are always there no matter how heavy<br />
the travails may be. to You I * Ay thank you<br />
very, very much Indeed.<br />
Thank You again and thank you for<br />
believing. But could I most particularly, " nd again<br />
finally, thank the Austrlan people<br />
without whose faith and decency and<br />
commitment to what's fair and what's<br />
reasonable and what is decent in this<br />
coUntr, without thoue conscientious<br />
judgments this victory could not have<br />
been consummated and put together.<br />
Thank YOu.<br />
And I concludle on this. note, to say we<br />
thank you. we appreciate it. we won't let<br />
you down. Thank you.<br />
TE1L6: . Jul. 93 10: 45 No. 001 P. 01 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
