<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3458</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS STATEMENT TO BRISBANE PRESS CONFERENCE - 15 NOVEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003458.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIMEL MINISTER'S PRESS STATEMENT TO DRiSPAi-PRES CONFEP E<br />
NOVUIDER 1974<br />
ISHOULD-EXPLAIN W~ HY I INTEND TO TAKE SUCH AN<br />
ACTIVE ROLE IN THIS CAMJ'PAIGN, IDO SO BECAUSE I HAVE KNOWN<br />
AND ADMIRED PERC TUCKER FOR HANY YEARS, KNOW-Hill! AS A<br />
GREATr OULENSLANDER A1ND A GREAT ALISTRALIA1,1 WHO WILL MAIKE<br />
AN EXCELLENT PREMIER AND STA14D UIP FOR THE INT'RESTS OF THIF,<br />
STATE AS EFFECTIVELY AS DON DUNSTAN STAN~ DS FOR THE INTERESTS'<br />
OF SOUTrH AUSTRALIA OR ERIC iE 2C!: FOR TPOSE OF TAS-MANIA,<br />
IDO N07 EXPECT THAT1 WE WILL ALW. AYS ASREE ON THE APPLICATION<br />
OF ALL POLICIES BUT IDO KNOW TH\ Tq CAM I-ALK' TO FACH<br />
ClH'ER, THAT WE RESPECT LACH OTHER AND iHA~ r WE 111I1L SE ABLE<br />
WORK rOGETHER 114 THlE jINTErfESTS OF 7' HI .), ATE.<br />
IDO NOT COME HIRF. 10 DISCUSS FEDEFPAL<br />
ISSUES&amp; THE ISSUES THAT I MIAL DIlSCUSS~ i 71HIS CAMFV--AIGN<br />
ARE STATE I. SSUES4 DO NOT FLELIEVE 714AT U SL' 3WL<br />
BC FOOLED BY THE PREMIERS TACTIC'OF IN'fR0[ DULCiNG COMPLFELY<br />
IRREVELANT ISSUES JN'A S*[ ATE. ELECTION. 0UEEN-SLANDEr'l':' MUST<br />
DECIDE WHE71HER* THEY WANT A STATE GOVFRNUM NT THAT CAN WO) RK,<br />
EFFECTIVELY WqITH THE PRESENT AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT<br />
CO-OPERATE WVITH IT B~ UT NOT NECESSARILY ALWAYS AGREE WITH<br />
IT. AT PRESpia You HAVE IN OUEE_: NSLAN~ D AS THE PREMIER<br />
H~ AS ALREADY 114DICATED IN4 THIS CAMPAIGN--A GOVERNMENT WHICH<br />
CONTINUES TO OBSTRUC7, WHICH REFUSES TO CO-OPEPATE, W[ HCH<br />
ON SOME OCCASIONS EVEN REFUSES TO DISCUSS HAT1EI: S AIND OIN<br />
OT14ERS FAILS TO FULFIL THE ELEMENTARY C01J R T ESY OF<br />
REPLYIN4G 10 CORRESPONDENCE FROM * IHE Aus$ ThALIA?' OVERMEN </p>
<p>It * b<br />
f<br />
S-2-THE PEOPLE OF OUEENSLAND. MUST DECIDE WHETHER THEY WANT<br />
A CONTINUATrION OF* THIS POLICY OF NON-CO-OPERATION,<br />
OBSTRUCTIOR4 AND INDEED VLICTO. IT IS A* POLICY WHIC; H<br />
I BELI EVE AVREYAFFECTS THE' WELFARE AND DEVELOPMENT<br />
OF THE STATE.. THI s IS' A. STATE ISSUE -NOT A FEDERAL<br />
ISSUE -AND ICOME INTO THIS CAMPAIGN TO SHOW YOU HO1-FAR THE<br />
WELFARE AND DEVELOP'ENT. OF THIS STATE HAVE BEEN IDI<br />
BY THE STAND OF THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT OF* QUEC-hLAND.<br />
THINGS HAVE . COME -TO A SORRY STATE INDEED<br />
WHEN THE PREMIER ' OF THIS GREAT STATE AND THE FRIt?.-MIIIST: p,<br />
OF. THIS -COUNTRY CANNOT EVEN MELO. 1 TO DISCUSS MAiT; 7 R OF<br />
IMPORTANCE BECAUSE TH RME EUES TO DO SO, TH C<br />
PREMIER REFUSE D TO COME TO A PRIVATE* ROUNC-TAPL DlitNER<br />
WITH MYSE2LF A D ALL THE0O HER F IYE PR EM I Ei ', S TO DI SCUS<br />
* THE PROBLEMIS OF INiFLATION, AND IMiAT TE R S C1 ICE RNI G TH E<br />
CONST. ITUT ION. TH E PREMIER SIMPLY IGNORED A LLETTER ( I. IC<br />
IVWROTE TO HI1M VERY EARLY ' IN OUR ( JOVERNUHUUt Pi-OIi<br />
DISCUSSIONS BETWEEN OUR OFFICIALS ON THE GOENET$ PLCES<br />
FOR GROWTH CENTRES AND STABLE LAND PRICES, Auio WHEI IfH<br />
AUSTRAL IAN MINSITER FOR ABORIGINAL. AFFAIRS SOUGH' TO ClO." I<br />
WITH STATE MINISTERS ABOUT THE ' RECOMMENDATIONS. OF A ROYAL.<br />
ComI ss IoN ON ABORIGI NAL. LAND) Ri GHrS, THE 0U E ISL AN D1<br />
MINISTER REFUSED TO EVEN DISCUSS THE MATTER, UNTIL A FEW DAYS'<br />
* AGO, WHEN. I WROTE TO THE PREMIER OFFERING TO ACCEPT<br />
RESP ONSIBILITY FOR THE STATE RAILWAYS AND REMOV0' E THE<br />
FINANCIAL BURDENS THEY IMPOSE ON THE STATE, TEPREMIER<br />
REPLIED NINE MONTHS LATER THAT HE WAS NOT EVEN PREPARED<br />
TO. DISCUSS THE MATTER, AND YET DISCUSSIONS ARE PROCEEDING<br />
ON' A NO COM14ITMENT BASIS WITH OTHER LIBERAL STATE GOVERNMENTS1 </p>
<p>b.<br />
I -3-<br />
TO BE QUITE FRANKI IT SURPRISES 1ME THAT THE<br />
LBERAL-COUNTRY PARTY STATE GOVERNMENT. OF QUEENSLAND FINDS<br />
IDEOLOGICALLY UNACCEPTABLE AND BERATES-IN THE-MOST<br />
VIRULENT TERMS MATTERS WHICH OTHER L! BERAL-COUNTRY PARTY*<br />
STATE GOVERNMENTS* FIND PERFECTLY. ACCLPTAPLE. ' IF THE<br />
OVRMETOF THIS STATE WERE WILLING TO SIGN PRECI* SELY<br />
ri1 W. Mm 44 IE,-CGNT DA/ PpCCi-IL_-7HL= -MC-r T~ A&amp; M A-S _ rH ATWHI1CH<br />
V'VE S. IGNED WITH THE LIBERAL PREMIERS OF NE1' I SOUTH~<br />
WALES AND VICTORIA, THEN THE GROWTHvC ETR N OfSLL EG<br />
VOULD ' BE, A BLE TO PROCEED AS RAPIDLY AS THE GROWTH CENTRE<br />
IS PROCEEDING IN ALBURY-WODONGA. IF THE GOVERNMENT OF<br />
THIS STATE WERE-WILLING TO SIGN THE SAME AGREEIMENTS IN<br />
PRECIS$ ELY -THE SAME TERMS AS' THE L I IERAL GOVERNMENTS IN<br />
NEW. SOUTH WALESp V. ICTORIA AND WESTERi AUSTRALIA, ALL THC<br />
OTHER LIBERAL'COUNTRY' PARTY GOVERNPIENTs IN THIS COUNTRY1<br />
HAVE EXPRESSED A WILLINGNESS TO SIGN OR HAV'E ALREADY<br />
SIGNED OiN LAND COUNCILS, THE14 W'E WOULD BE AB3LE TO ENSURE<br />
THAT HOME PURCHASERS CAN AFFOR. D -THE. PRICE OF LAND,<br />
THESE TWO EXAkMPLES OF THE GOVERNMENT OF THIS STATE REFUSING<br />
TO0 DO IWHAT OTHER* GOVERNMENTS OF THE SAME POLITICAL COLOUR<br />
ARE WILLING TO DO HAVE ALREADY COST QUEENSLAND TENS OF<br />
MILION OFDOLLARS IN FEDERAL GRANTS AND LOANS, M. O<br />
HERE TO ARGUE THE MERITS OF OUR GROWTH CENTRE POLICY OR iD<br />
OUR LAND COMMISSION ' POLICY. THAT IS A MATTER FOR A FE-DERAL."~<br />
ELECTION.-I AM HERE TO SAY THAT QUEENSLANDERS SHOULD NOT<br />
ACCEPT A STATE GOVERNMENT WHICH IS WILLING TO IMPEDE THE<br />
DEVELOPMENT OF THE STATE IN THIS WAY. THAT IS PROPERLY<br />
A. MAT. TER FOR A STATE ELECTION. </p>
<p>c r<br />
T I DO NOT BELIEVE QUEENSLANDERS DESERVE A<br />
GOVERNMENT WHICH, WHATEVER ITS DIFFERENCES OF OPINION<br />
WITH THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, REFUSES TO EVEN ANSWER<br />
LETTERS FROM THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA TO THE<br />
PREMIER OF. QUEENSLAND. SUCH UNANSWERED LETTERS CONCERN<br />
A PROPOSAL TO STUDY THE MEANS OF REDUCING ELECTRICITY Li,~ Ti't<br />
S COSTS IN QUEENSLAND; A PROPOSAL TO ASSESS THE ENVIRONMENTAL<br />
IMPACT. OF.. BEACH SAND MINING; A REQUEST FOR INFORMATION FAC<br />
S ON THE IMPLICATIONS OF AMENDMENTS TO QUEENSLAND LEGISLATION<br />
FOR ABORIGINES; A REQUEST TO THE GOVERNMENT OF QUEENSLAND<br />
FOR THEIR VIEWS ON MY GOERNMmENT'S PROPOSALS CONCERNING<br />
ABORIGINES. WE OFFERED FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE FOR LAND<br />
'. STABILISATION AND GROWTH CENTRES. I 1ROTE IN AUGUST 1973<br />
CONCERNING OUR FI-NANCIAL PROPOSALS FOR THAT YEAR AND AGAINi<br />
IN SEPTEMBER 1974 CONCERNING OUR PROPOSALS ARISING FROM<br />
THE MOST RECENT BUDGET. I HAVE RECEIVED NO REPLY TO THE<br />
FIRST AND THE MOST CURSORY REPLY TO T1E SECOND. AS EARLY<br />
AS DECEMBER 1972, WHEN THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR GOVERNMENT HAD<br />
BEEN IN OFFICE FOR LESS. THAN TWO WEEKS, I WROTE SEEKING THE<br />
AGREEMENT OF THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT FOR THE AUSTRALIAN i<br />
NATIONAL LINE TO OPERATE BETWEEN QUEENSLAND PORTS. IN<br />
SHMAY 1973, THE PREMIER TOLD. ME THAT HE WAS CONSIDERING THE<br />
MATTER. DESPITE SUBSEQUENT LETTERS IN APRIL AND JUNE 1974,<br />
THERE IS NO REPLY.. WROTE SEEKING THE VIEWS OF THE L<br />
QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT ON THE AUSTRALIAN ASSISTANCE PLAN, I<br />
I HAVE RECEIVED NO SUBSTANTIVE REPLY. I WROTE SEEKING THE<br />
VIEWS OF THE GOVERNMENT ON THE PROPOSAL RELATING TO THE<br />
MUTUAL REFERENCE OF POWERS, WHICH WAS BASICALLY AGREED<br />
UPON AT THE MEETING WITH MYSELF AND THE FIVE PREMI-ERS<br />
SWHICH THE QUEENSLAND PREMIER REFUSED TO ATTEND. ' I<br />
7. </p>
<p>* 4K. 7A.<br />
I. T<br />
TRICS-LETR WA SiE TIBUAPRL, O TAIS EANDI . AVEO<br />
CONERETEC WAS HEL O INOELUWRTSIO ND SETPJOONCT<br />
THESE REPORTS TO ALL STATE-PREMIERS FOR THEIR COViAENT<br />
TWO MONTHS. AGO. ONLY THE PR EMI1ER OF OUEENSLAND HAS<br />
FAILED TO REPLY Ilf ANY WAY WHATSOLVERI<br />
THIS IS NOT'TH* E WAY THAT RELATIONS BETniEFI4N<br />
AN AUSTRALIAN AND A STATE GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE CONDUCTED.<br />
WHATEVER THEIR POLITICAL PERSUASI'ONS MAY BE.<br />
.7. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
