<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>501</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES, AT OPENING OF NEW SCIENCE BLOCK AT CANBERRA BOYS&#039; GRAMMA SCHOOL - 19TH APRIL 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/04/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000501.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S3PKKO 3! MIb AM, 4~ MIiJC-4 iiire &amp;, 41 H~ o i* C<br />
MXf-Z aWg WMJ F JWK AT<br />
C. KNAI1h* I 3OL, JOAs1 1 diL.<br />
3Ky lord dishop, Reaib&amp; 3tnrg Mrs Robson and ladies and gentlement<br />
I don't quite know in hAwt capacity I an hero* 1 know that<br />
in a precmrious sense I am bore as Pimn inistur. ( Laughter) I<br />
wou~ ld also have the boys unurstandp so that the Wa treat me with<br />
proper respect, that purely in an honorary capacity I1 am a Doctor of<br />
Selense of the Univrsity of New a; uth iiales. Qtaau degree<br />
less dei~ rvod than that aoe aut still there Is a certain iatisfactim1<br />
to be jot out of life In setting tbhiqyou don't deserve i) eoause In my<br />
experience they are umore than balanced br gettin,, the abuse that you<br />
don't deserve* ( Laughter)<br />
Xov xi'. Robson, I would remind the boys wiho are he~ ro is<br />
not only onected. 9 as be has described, ' With this kigiky<br />
mainrAtIve 1' undq but be Is also himself one of the most a ebaed<br />
headmastors in the history of ' ustralla* ( Applause) do he<br />
understands both sides of the coins knows far mawe about schoolboys<br />
than I do; and far more about the iorkluig of the fund than! I o,<br />
though I appreciate oothe<br />
I was particularly interested, to hear 11r. 1-obsonts<br />
reminiscence about the time he % ras sitting for bAst was then called<br />
; Onior Pulic because he and I ane more or less contemporaries and<br />
he told you ; Lt a tiny fraction of those dho sat for othat you nov<br />
call Leaving were taiting eieoee This Is a very emarkable and<br />
interesting fact. And it is y jInterestin,; indeed* to find V at<br />
In the Johoolsq taking them brosay tca4ay,, .3uh a vast Increase has<br />
occurred in those wh~ o take some aspect or science.<br />
3# At I dant to say this to you because it is vorth recording<br />
it bears on this topic that in spite oft all t a things that have<br />
'-ahpune In recent years In spite of the oznmas expansion in<br />
University activity 4nd In the provision of funds for uriiersitiesp<br />
there la, relatiwelj9 today a smaller poroontape of um4argradutto<br />
ta wng Science -percentage of tie population than there jag 10 years<br />
ago. Xow that in a very rehisrkable raut. 1 c4. L1 It a ramaricable fact<br />
bectase I learnt it only -A ft.-4 days age from the Chairman of the<br />
Universities Commision* Just let me state It quite p~ la inly, that for<br />
say every so aay of the people in Austraiiu thousands ormilllhnasg a<br />
smaller percentage is note ong&amp; aged In the stuij of science in the<br />
Univrsities than we had some 1ears igo.<br />
It is worth asking ourselves whiy this should be so. decoause<br />
-Oen the enorims post-vafr impsat of scientific d, rolopment occurred*<br />
tehon if I may put it quite shortly, science beawe rather the<br />
fashionable, topic of the day# my own fear vus thtwt perhaps we might<br />
Ooocee over-balanoed on ' hat side aAd that the great anrd ' vital studies<br />
of the humanities = L~ ht K1l1 into disrepalr JAu t that was -irong.<br />
This is not so. And when one asks wby thisa Is not so the 4 -sver iag<br />
" OeU in ordinary professional courses ; here is$ under today's<br />
Oirmstanee9 a prospect of Imediately earning a substantial<br />
This in an econasmic sense$ is attractive to students; and attractive<br />
, to treir parents. 4horeas seisnes Is a hard master in tMat sense.<br />
To become, a notable scientist ono' aust be comple~ tely devoted to the<br />
-, ok avo a sonse of mission In the work. AeJll or ejurse it is<br />
' Peopho devotion, and people 41tb a sense or mission * ho keep this<br />
World going. These are the people -who matte-r far more than the people<br />
who own r-turn large Income tax returns.<br />
If do are, to a.. nsider the matoi-ial " kvainomet of lustralia,<br />
or indeed of any other countryg 40 laust ha ve in Min that in this time<br />
In the acrld's history our material -Li1 4q ~ d~ q per4 fi~ rt and<br />
foremost on aco. nce and tectu,. alog ! ng .&amp; ouVnaera<br />
advanometg the -aising of econt" 1o standards. Im not taWIEUM a 0out<br />
the doverlop-eont of other, land porhaps m-ore Important aspects of man* </p>
<p>11at : in esonaaic trms a coutry that ffali oehind In sci _ zce 4nd in<br />
the application of sciene thro,~ technology is goinlg to fall behind<br />
in the race to maintain Its j) oilfftion anid its living standLards and<br />
make headvayq eoonmalls~ y, in the doz'ldo<br />
Now of surn., fortuhately for us tbsre Are man j. ople vho<br />
understand this pez'fsctl' iello The am obo esta~ olished this "' ndg<br />
some of wbis are very close personal riocnds of miae# non of<br />
signifioan'-s in the busin~ ess world* in the ijwodixtive -iorld hami set<br />
to all their oolloapuos in that bwancb of life an examjile of<br />
Inzginutiws Indusa. w~ al statesmaflshipo ImxginatiYe 3e , as1e it<br />
clearly through the : utuz'e years the ernormous Alpxificance of science<br />
Leaching And science toaching In the schools from whience a11 the<br />
universill studonts will ca and statesmanship acause they are<br />
not taking the short viev, och most people dot but the long view<br />
dh must be taken br same and by many If tbe cuumtry Is to go an<br />
and krosper, Now ' 1 &amp; Ae other thi. ng* It Is quite cleat and this<br />
also was iapiicit wu'hst Xr. Rabso had to say that to kroduce,<br />
scientiflo: undrprada-tes, to produie post 6rat42te s : Iaatifio<br />
studocts9 to produce roseareh in sciancelp to produce reople in science<br />
upon wbam our economic fAure dehadst 4 must begin in the gailoolsp<br />
particularly in the later stages 1W baving the best possible eaiiCMet9<br />
the best possible lab*. equipxmto Modemn science CaS , iiWif<br />
beyond ibat we used to rotprd as ft-cionce, thenu I was a boy, it now<br />
Involves In Its higher baaohes partica~ rlyp enormously~ zstly<br />
equipmenLtrau are out of da to, you are out of the race = nless you<br />
can maintain the highest posihie sMa" Adr Of 4qUIjift and these<br />
things oet inney I dare say Heamaster that if yoA had had to<br />
4s end solely on your ovn resources in equping some of these new<br />
U = e ywu do~ id have roand yourself in considt. rable difficulty* It<br />
Is an Imaginative strokes and 1 ag1v* my compliments to the fund upon<br />
It to realis, that you aan't start too soon in devtloping not only a<br />
high level of achieveentg but such an noderstanding of the futnre of<br />
ye~ study that you will produes mor. and note peo ho, will jo on<br />
and not be satisfied to take a first degree9 but va't another onel<br />
not be satisfied until they have made t-il contribution to that<br />
scientifie research rhich the technologists All take up and Vly In<br />
industry abtbher It is kr1nary or secon~ arj to the &amp; riot<br />
&amp; dVaneoMent of AAaralao<br />
So It tisiabig day in tehistory of this icool,<br />
to-. haM AaAmeu that : 6 -as here to p a form a foundation Ston<br />
laying anan earlier oomsion. I haveg for yea-s and years now,<br />
oasionally had myself driven pastg or around this -ichoolo I have,<br />
as any of youa must have sarvelled at the rapidity of Its &amp; ovth.<br />
~ 4be I abrSt COWn to KanLrra in my more res. octable days when I was<br />
ttoasne-General the populaition of anberwm was 6t000 odd anid yo a eou14<br />
walk around the vtie place on Aurday afternoon * ithout mnd*<br />
exhanstion. 10ow It is vottin~ near to 60,000 and the statisticians<br />
tell us t Atit ill be00, O6ku'lf0 " ndItvwill be aquarter of<br />
a million W the end of the century same of the ooys might make a<br />
mental note of Wesu I vaont be bars, aut that is what do A" e told.<br />
And. that is a mere matter of sine. -lot this city : is developing<br />
character and It must develop character as a capital city if the<br />
national Ovovh of ' Australia Is to achieve national tetes and a<br />
conseiouess that do are a nation and not six indepenient o unties*<br />
, so the arovth of Z nborr is her"; and it mrould be a poor arowth If<br />
It erenotforthefact that ye are ombra~ ing in this city<br />
Incrasiglya geatJiversityg great zaboolsq raji&amp; 1j achieving<br />
great trd os n this Schbool may hold, i its be" d uon&amp; ~ Any of<br />
theme ( Cpplauso) i </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
