<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8331</transcript-id>
    <title>State and Territory Winners of 1991 Prime Minister&#039;s Employer of the Year Awards</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/09/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008331.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>9 September 1991</p>
<p><strong>Joint Statement with the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Health, Housing and Community Services, Brian Howe - State and Territory Winners of 1991 Prime Minister's Employer of the Year Awards</strong></p>
<p>Fifteen employers who have led the way in the employment of people with disabilities have had their efforts recognised with their selection as State and Territory winners of the 1991 Prime Minister's Employer of the Year Award.</p>
<p>They are all now eligible for selection as the National Employer of the Year, which will be announced at a reception at Parliament House on 12 September.</p>
<p>Under the Awards, employers are divided into two categories those that employ more than 100 staff, and those that employ less.</p>
<p>The State and Territory winners under the large business category are:</p>
<p>NSW  - BHP Steel Slab and Plate Products Division<br />VIC  - Royal Automobile Club of Victoria<br />QLD  - Palm Lodge Nursing Hone<br />SA  - Walker Australia Pty Ltd<br />WA  - Department of Land Administration<br />TAS  - Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd<br />NT  - Atrium Hotel<br />ACT -, Dickson Motor Vehicle Registry</p>
<p>The award winners under the small business category are:</p>
<p>NSW  - Cooper Tools Pty Ltd<br />VIC  - Bendigo Pottery<br />QLD -  Rayburn Pty Ltd<br />SA  - Regina Lighting Pty Ltd<br />WA  - Dardanup Butchering organisat ion<br />NT - - G RWills PtyLtd<br />ACT  - Instant Office Furniture Pty Ltd<br /> </p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Employer of the Year Awards are designed to encourage employers help disabled Australians. They recognise employers who provide significant work opportunities and support for people with disabilities, many of whom have never worked, or have worked only in sheltered workshops.</p>
<p>Employment on the open labour market gives these people the opportunity to prove themselves as valuable, productive members of the community, and enables them to build confidence and independence.</p>
<p>Invaluable assistance to employers of people with disabilities is provided by Commonwealth Government sponsored employment agencies and regional units of The Commonwealth Rehabilitation Service. Services include on-the-job training and support, and advice on job redesign.</p>
<p>Initiated last year by the Federal Department of Health, Housing and Community Services, the Awards are being sponsored by Australian Airlines, Business Review Weekly and the Australian Chamber of Commerce.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
