<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41236</transcript-id>
    <title>$200 million research boost to improve the lives of Australian patients</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Turnbull Government is investing over $200 million in world-leading medical research projects to improve the lives of patients battling cancers, mental health illnesses and chronic disease.</p>
<p>In addition to this significant investment in medical research, the Turnbull Government is providing $5 million to CanTeen under the Medical Research Future Fund Accelerated Research program to improve access to cutting edge breakthroughs for adolescents and young adults with cancer.</p>
<p>The investment in CanTeen will facilitate new clinical trials into cancer types with the highest death rates for adolescents and young adults.</p>
<p>This builds on our recent commitments of $20 million for the Zero Childhood Cancer initiative, $13 million for clinical trials for rare cancers and rare diseases under the MRFF Lifting Clinical Trials and Registries Capacity program and $5.8 million to Cancer Australia to fight childhood cancers.</p>
<p>The $202 million in funding announced today includes over $40 million for cancer research, including in areas like melanoma research.</p>
<p>Over $29 million will be invested into mental health research, almost $23 million for cardiovascular disease research, $8 million for diabetes research and $5 million for obesity research.</p>
<p>Improving the health of Indigenous Australians is a priority with $15.5 million for new research.</p>
<p>Over $15 million in funding will be targeted at research projects that support Australians who suffer severe injuries.               </p>
<p>A total of 326 research projects will be funded at a cost of more than $197 million under the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC).</p>
<p>And a further 13 Fellowships have been allocated $5.64 million under the $8 million MRFF Next Generation Clinical Researcher Fellowship program, which supports Australia’s new and up and coming research talent.</p>
<p>These grants will increase clinical research capacity in the health and medical research workforce, providing greater opportunities for more breakthroughs.</p>
<p>A full list of grant recipients is available on the NHMRC website: <a href="http://www.nhmrc.gov.au">www.nhmrc.gov.au</a>.</p>
<p>Information on the Medical Research Future Fund and grant recipients can be found at <a href="http://www.health.gov.au/mrff">www.health.gov.au/mrff</a>.</p>
<p><strong>NHMRC FUNDING BY NATIONAL HEALTH PRIORITY AREA</strong></p>
<p>			 </p>
<p><strong>Priority Area</strong></p>
<p align="center"><strong>Commitment</strong></p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Health</p>
<p align="center">$15,598,821</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Arthritis and Osteoporosis</p>
<p align="center">$7,029,520</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Asthma</p>
<p align="center">$2,560,741</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Cancer</p>
<p align="center">$38,249,265</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Cardiovascular Disease</p>
<p align="center">$22,924,959</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Dementia</p>
<p align="center">$4,273,590</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Diabetes</p>
<p align="center">$8,019,687</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Injury</p>
<p align="center">$15,124,672</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Mental Health</p>
<p align="center">$29,110,467</p>
<p>			 </p>
<p>Obesity</p>
<p align="center">$5,026,710</p>
<p>			 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
