<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18951</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia&#039;s Best Female Students To Take Their Research To The World</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>A Queensland researcher developing a new clinical therapy for patients suffering from painful eye disorders has received the inaugural Prime Minister's Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Award.</p>
<p>Queensland University of Technology's Dr Laura Bray will receive up to $118,000 of post-doctoral assistance to perform the research in Dresden, Germany over two years.</p>
<p>The new award, announced as part of Australia's commemoration activities for The Queen's Diamond Jubilee, will allow a high achieving Australian female postgraduate or postdoctoral student to undertake research overseas.</p>
<p>The Award is designed to develop recipients into internationally-aware and skilled future leaders.</p>
<p>The Award will allow Dr Bray to use the world-class facilities at the Leibniz Institute for Polymer Research, in collaboration with the Dresden University of Technology.</p>
<p>Dr Bray's research will help improve outcomes for patients with severe injuries to the surface of their eye, for which there is no current long-term treatment option anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Award will help Dr Bray become a leader in biomedical research in Australia and globally.</p>
<p>Having Australia's best and brightest female postgraduate students and postdoctoral fellows undertake research or study overseas will help develop enduring links between Australia and the host country.</p>
<p>The experience of studying and living overseas also helps Australian students build life-long professional connections and friendships, and develop leadership skills.</p>
<p>Dr Bray will be recognised at the 2013 Prime Minister's Australia Awards Presentation Dinner at the National Gallery of Australia tonight.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Award is an achievement-based scholarship awarded through the merit stream of the Australia Awards  -  the Endeavour Awards.</p>
<p>The Endeavour Awards is the Gillard Government's international, merit-based scholarship program providing life and career changing opportunities for recipients in countries around the world.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
