<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6856</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NATIONAL PRESS CLUB LUNCH, WEDNESDAY 5 MARCH 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911221</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006856.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1, i1Sk~<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NATIONAL PRESS CLUB LUNCH WEDNESDAY 5 MARCH 1986<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
HYWOOD: I want to ask you how long you intend staying Prime<br />
Minister. Do you intend retiring around halfway through the next<br />
Parliament if you win the next election? If so, do you believe<br />
your reluctant Treasurer would be the best person to takeover?<br />
PM: Well my first to the next election and I would hope<br />
that something like three terms I would have been able to put<br />
into policies of this Government the directions in<br />
which this country was going. I've been in public life for a<br />
very long period of time and I hope to have some active and<br />
productive years for more personal pursuits. So I think<br />
something like the order of three terms would be appropriate. As<br />
to the succession, as in most matters with this Government, not<br />
all but most, it's a democratic process. I very rarely seek to<br />
impose my own will absolutely, and without discussion and<br />
certainly in the matter of my successor, the succession, I<br />
wouldn't seek to do it because I know I couldn't any rate.<br />
GRATTAN: Mr Hawke on the third anniversary of your Government<br />
are you disappointed that you have had this week to break the<br />
initial promise on the uniform national land rights legislation<br />
and what do you intend to say to your critics?<br />
PM: Let me, I thought there might be a question on this. So let<br />
me at the outset Michelle put my answers to a very legitimate<br />
question in the context of the record of this Government in<br />
regard to the advance of the aboriginal people in Australia. I'm<br />
proud to say that in this area there has been a more substantial<br />
application of funds than in virtually any other area of<br />
Government policy. The figures are that comparing 82,/ 83 to the<br />
present time, that is the current year 85/ 86, there has been a 73<br />
per cent increase in the funds made available for the advancement<br />
of aboriginal programs. In real terms that's a 44 per cent<br />
increase in funding in this area. And this Government therefore,<br />
has nothing to apologise for in terms of what we have done to<br />
seek to advance the interests of what by any standards is a<br />
severely disadvantaged section of the Australian population.<br />
The fundamental objective of the Government's policy in the area<br />
of land rights has been to achieve secure title for aboriginals<br />
over land with which they have a traditional association. We've<br />
consistently indicated a preference, if that's possible, that<br />
each state should take appropriate action to achieve that<br />
objective. And my Minister to whom I pay unqualified tribute, </p>
<p>Clyde Holding, for the work he's done and the manner in which<br />
he's done it, has through these three years consistently been<br />
having discussions with the aboriginal people, the<br />
representatives, the States, mining interests and others to try<br />
and secure a position in which the advancement of this objective,<br />
that is the obtaining of secure titles for aboriginals over land<br />
with which they have a traditional association, can be achieved<br />
in the most viable and secure way. A way which is going to risk<br />
the least possible creation of an atmosphere in which the<br />
aboriginal people themselves will be disadvantaged. Now<br />
considerable advances have been made in those approaches by my<br />
Minister with the States. In regard to the latest negotiations<br />
that he's had with Western Australia, the position is now, as a<br />
result of those discussions between Mr Holding and the Western<br />
Australian Government, that the Western Australian Government<br />
will provide secure titles to land for aboriginal people living<br />
on reserves in that State and a number of other measures. And<br />
that will, in fact, represent a very significant improvement in<br />
the position of aboriginal people in Western Australia. I also<br />
make the point that in the situation where, as a result of those<br />
sorts of negotiations, the approach to obtaining secure title for<br />
aborigines has been done by the States. We are not going ahead<br />
with that part of what was a more comprehensive approach to<br />
remove the right of veto of aboriginals in the Northern<br />
Territory. We regard it as not appropriate to do that in the<br />
absence of a more national approach. And I also refer to the<br />
fact that we have indicated our intention to bring in a permanent<br />
replacement for the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders<br />
Heritage Interim Protection Act as a further reflection of our<br />
concern to preserve and protect aboriginal culture. Now I say<br />
all that and I make no excuse for the length of the answer<br />
because this is an important question. I guess in some sense one<br />
has to say that it is disappointing that the circumstances in<br />
this country have changed, from 1967 when the people of Australia<br />
overwhelming indicated the desire to have a more centralised<br />
approach on this issue. Attitudes are not the same in 1986 as<br />
thgy were in 1967. We have not therefore, however, retracted<br />
from trying to achieve our objective of obtaining secure title<br />
for Aboriginals because there has been this change in<br />
environment. We have sensibly and effectively tried to work<br />
within that environment and I believe that Clyde Holding is to be<br />
congratulated for the advances that he's made. I am confident<br />
that in the event, as a result of those negotiations that he has<br />
conducted and the decisions that we have made now in this<br />
environment, that the objective, as I say, of obtaining secure<br />
titles for Aboriginals over land, to which they have a<br />
traditional association, has been very significantly advanced.<br />
And I repeat, as I said at the beginning, this aspect of our<br />
approach in regard to the interests of Aboriginal people in this<br />
country has been undertaken within the context of this<br />
historically high level of real increase in funding for<br />
Aboriginal advancement in Australia.<br />
DAVIS: A question on tax avoidance. Is your Government<br />
concerned about the erosion in the corporate tax base involved in<br />
the present wave of takeovers using negatively geared borrowings.<br />
Do you believe it's fair, or efficient that corporate raiders can<br />
negatively gear through their companies, while individuals can't? </p>
<p>PM: Ken, obviously this is an area of concern, not only to you<br />
and I notice the considerable amount of writings you have done on<br />
it. It is properly a matter for concern by us and the Cabinet<br />
has asked that the Treasurer should provide for us a submission<br />
on this subject. we will be getting that submission in the very<br />
near future and we will be considering what action, if any, is<br />
necessary in the light of that submission.<br />
MACCALLJM: Can I ask you a general question on multiculturalism,<br />
which is a subject which I though you might have brought up in<br />
talking about the three years of your Government. It does seem<br />
that there is, in this as in other areas, something of a<br />
community backlash developing. Have you any plans to conduct any<br />
kind of public campaign to stress the advantages of A<br />
multicultural society? And perhaps following up the answer you<br />
gave Michelle Grattan, do you think in hindsight that the changes<br />
in attitudes towards Aboriginal land rights, which you've<br />
mentioned, could have been circumvented if there'd been more<br />
leadership from the Government?<br />
PM: You say in regard to the first part of the question, Mungo,<br />
I can't say that there's been a decision specifically for a<br />
national campaign to highlight what are undoubtedly the very real<br />
advantr. ges that this country has achieved through the fact that<br />
we ha-ve become a truly multicultural society. I would say<br />
howev~ r, that in the specific programs that the Minister is<br />
following, and in the programs that will be part of the<br />
Bicentennial celebrations, emphasis upon the advantages of our<br />
multiculturalism will be very much at the forefront. And let me<br />
say this, that should it become apparent that more needed to be<br />
done than in the areas to which I've referred, we would be<br />
prepared to do it. As to the second part of your question. It's<br />
always easy Mungo, when you're not sitting in the seat of<br />
responsibility to say you should have shaped attitudes in a<br />
different way, and if you'd shaped attitudes in a different way<br />
thqn outcomes would have been different. And I make no<br />
criticisms of those who sit back and perhaps express the wish<br />
that the attitudes of Australian society could have been moulded<br />
in a different way. But I have to say to you, and I say without<br />
any feeling of bitterness, or rancour about the question, it's<br />
certainly a fair question. This society is not an easily<br />
manipuable society and I think that that's a good thing.<br />
Australian society is one which has a record or being prepared to<br />
make up its own mind, it's not easily manipulated by politicians<br />
or by one person and I think that's something for which we should<br />
be considerably grateful. So in a position of power and of<br />
leadership what you've got to try and do is to gradually produce<br />
what you hope will be a more compassionate attitude about issues<br />
of concern. You are, I believe, going to produce a<br />
counterproductive situation if you jump miles in front of where<br />
the populous is at this time. I say without any compunction at<br />
all that I would be happier, personally, if the environment, the<br />
attitudes of Australia in 1986 on the issue about which we were<br />
talking, were more like those of 1967. It does seem to be the<br />
case that a society of 1967, which had experienced a generation<br />
of full employment, whose contemplations were those of certainty<br />
of employment for themselves, certainty of growing living </p>
<p>standards, improving quality of life, that that society had a<br />
greater preparedness for compassion. It does seem to be the case<br />
that in a country and in a world if you like where greater<br />
uncertainty has become the characteristic of life, that that more<br />
obvious preparedness for compassion is somewhat diminished as<br />
compared to readiness of the Australian people to vote and act in<br />
the way they did in 1967. Now all I can say is that we have not<br />
diminished in any way, in our concern for the interests of the<br />
Aboriginal people in this country. I think we have a proud<br />
record on what we have done and within the constraints that exist<br />
today we will try and get a position where the Aboriginal people<br />
do have greater opportunities for secure title the land which<br />
I they have a close association.<br />
STANTON: The planned withnew provisions to cover mining access<br />
toAboriginal land in the Northern Territory to be reviewed two<br />
years after the passage of the amendments. Are you prepared to<br />
give a commitment that aborigines in the Northern Territory will<br />
retain their veto right after that review, or might it be<br />
removed at any time?<br />
PM: I wouldn't believe it would be removed. Let me make the<br />
position quite clear, and I hoped it had been before. when the<br />
Government was developing the concept of its preferred model on a<br />
wider national basis we had not regarded it as appropriate in<br />
that context that there should be this general right of veto<br />
around Australia. And in that context where we had that view we<br />
thought it appropriate to amend the Northern Territory<br />
legislation to bring about a position which was consistent<br />
withthat point of view. We're not then proceeding down the path<br />
of that national model for the reasons which I have tried as<br />
directly and as honestly as I can to put to you. It seemed to us<br />
quite inappropriate, in those circumstances then, to take away a<br />
right in the Northern Territory. What we've done is to propose<br />
that that exercise of the veto shall be amended in a way which<br />
will mean that the veto will have to be exercised at the<br />
beginning. It won't be a situation where we'll say all right we<br />
agree to exploration, but then keep the right of veto as a lever,<br />
and a bargaining position in respect to the rewards, or<br />
compensation you're going to get in the event of actual mining.<br />
Now we believe that this is appropriate. We regard it as fair by<br />
the Aboriginal people themselves and will produce a situation in<br />
the Northern Territory which will properly meet the interests of<br />
both sides, if you want to put it that way. Now the purpose of<br />
the review will be to see how that system works out, but there<br />
would be no reason in my view why you would change the<br />
fundamentals of it.<br />
MALONE: Do you have any idea who leaked the 1986/ 7 Federal<br />
Budget strategy document to the Sydney Morning Herald and when<br />
can we expect a sacking?<br />
PM: No is the answer to the first question and that will no<br />
doubt please many of you because I know you have a vested<br />
interest in the continuity of the leaking process. I don't want<br />
to leave you with the impression that we are in a state of high<br />
anxiety about this issue. I think we're handling it calmly.<br />
Obviously it would be quite dishonest of me to say that I'm not<br />
A </p>
<p>disturbed by the fact of the leak. No government of any<br />
political colour or persuasion likes to see the leaking of a<br />
significant document. I didn't like seeing it. I'm disappointed<br />
that it happened. We're looking at the issue and we're handling<br />
it in our usual competent and cool fashion.<br />
DODD: I refer to your midterm magpie campaign and I'd like to<br />
ask you as most ALP strategists seem to think that the length of<br />
the last election campaign was one of the factors that lead to a<br />
swing against you and basically because it made people bored, do<br />
you believe that launching a campaign midterm will bore people<br />
silly and subsequently you'll get an even more adverse reaction.<br />
And finally can I ask are you going to give a cast iron assurance<br />
that it is in fact a midterm campaign and that you have<br />
absolutely no intention of going to the polls before the end of<br />
next year?<br />
PM: The answer is yes, I'm sure it won't bore them because<br />
there's a very large difference between doing what we're doing in<br />
the sense of sharing our pride with the people of Australia for<br />
our joint achievement in getting 600,000 jobs. I really mean<br />
what I say. I believe that that's been a joint effort and<br />
endeavour of this great Australian nation and I think it's right<br />
that we share pride in it. So it's not the start of anything<br />
like you talk about and yes we won't be having an early election.<br />
I'm fascinated by this speculation about an early election. I<br />
mean I just don't know where it arose, I mean other than from the<br />
obvious fact that people say you must be as cynical as the Libs<br />
because whenever they saw, and it did occasionally arise in the<br />
past that the Labor Party got into a bit of disarray, it had a<br />
few problems, when that happened the Libs used to say wacko<br />
here's a good chance for an election. Now because that was that<br />
was the cynical and consistent attitude of the Conservatives<br />
there seems to be an assumption that I would operate the same<br />
way, because I see an opposition in total disarray, an opposition<br />
of historically proportioned incompetence, it's seems to be<br />
su~. gested that I would do a Malcolm, or a someone else. No sir.<br />
we will go full term. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: ( Niki Savva) Niki Savva of the Melbourne Sun, Prime<br />
Minister. PM: Hey, the headlines are wrong today Niki.<br />
JOURNALIST: Which ones.<br />
PM: The Sun headlines.<br />
JOURNALIST: All of them?<br />
PM: I only saw the one edition and that one was wrong.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, isn't it true that leaks are a fact of<br />
political life and no action you can take will stop them and do<br />
you agree with some Ministers that the latest leak could have<br />
wrecked the Budget processes?<br />
PM: They do seem to be a fact of life so far. I mean I haven't<br />
suffered anything as grievous as whoever that mischievous person<br />
is on the Opposition front bench who leaked the details of that<br />
disastrous meeting that John Howard had with the Business<br />
Council. I mean that was just unbelievable that anyone could do<br />
that. But, yes these sorts of things do seem to be a fact of life<br />
that the odd document seems to leak out. The answer to the second<br />
part of your question is no. It has not wrecked the Budget<br />
process. I mean I wished in a sense I could do a public leak<br />
myself of a document and sort of share with you the beauty of the<br />
letter of the seven because it is a very sensible letter, a very<br />
sensible letter. A letter which recognises explicitly, I mean the<br />
final paragraph, that the decisions that will have to be taken in<br />
the budgetary process will have to be taken within the<br />
appropriate fiscal environment. And having said that and I<br />
recognise that they put their case. That's perfectly natural that<br />
Ministers who have important portfolio responsibilities<br />
particularly in the welfare area, are going to fight as hard as<br />
thqy can to try and see that the things that they regard as<br />
important are going to be protected. I wouldn't respect my<br />
Ministers in those areas if they didn't fight as hard as they<br />
possibly could. Now having said that I, of course, was unhappy<br />
( ii' about the fact that the letter was leaked but I had no problems<br />
about the letter itself at all. Let me make that quite clear, no<br />
problems about the letter. And the Budget processes have started<br />
and we will, as we go now into our fourth Budget, we will be as<br />
successful as we have conspicuously been in our first three<br />
Budgets. That is, we will properly balance the requirements of<br />
responsible macro-economic management to create the conditions<br />
which will be conducive to sustained non-inflationary growth<br />
with, at the same time, protecting the interests of those in the<br />
community most deserving of government assistance. We have been<br />
successful in that. We don't have to come to the Australian<br />
people and say trust us, we'll do it because we have got the runs<br />
on the board. That is the way we have operated successfully to<br />
this point. We will do it again in the preparation of the 1986/ 87<br />
Budget. JOURNALIST: ( David Barnett) David Barnett, Mr Hawke. </p>
<p>PM: Yes David.<br />
JOURNALIST:........ and suggests to you that over the past three<br />
years there has been a movement of transfer of power and<br />
authority to the ACTU which is quite remarkable to such an extent<br />
that a newspaper quite literally suggested that Mr Kelty was now<br />
the most powerful person in the<br />
PM: They used to say that about me while I was President of the<br />
ACTU. I obviously didn't have the same judgment and even moved to<br />
a less powerful position.<br />
JOURNALIST:..... taken up by the opposition leader and I might<br />
suggest there has been a diminution in the authority of the<br />
government and of the Prime Ministership. What prospect do you<br />
think there would be for a coalition government to try and<br />
reverse that process, to try and take back some of the authority,<br />
some of that responsibility that has now moved to the ACTU?<br />
PM: Well, I am not quite sure how you describe an assumption on<br />
a mistaken premise but that's what the question constitutes. The<br />
assumption that the coalition government will be coming back into<br />
power in the foreseeable future is something which I repudiate.<br />
But the premise is mistaken. Now let's be quite clear about this.<br />
Let's get the nonsense and rhetoric out of the way. What I said<br />
to the Australian people in February/ March of 1983 was this, I<br />
said to them look you have now had seven and a half years of one<br />
particular approach to government. That is an approach which<br />
takes the view that working people and their organisations out<br />
there are a hostile camp. They come from another planet almost<br />
and that good government demands confrontation with them. I said,<br />
well just have a look at what it has produced. It has produced<br />
the worst economic crisis in 50 years. The phenomenon of<br />
simultaneous, double digit inflation and unemployment with high<br />
levels of industrial disputation. That's what the approach of<br />
fighting, taking on antagonistically the representatives of<br />
ordinary working men and women has produced. And I didn't pull a<br />
swifty on the people of Australia. I said to them openly there in<br />
1983 now look there is a better way of doing this. I said what we<br />
are going to be about is the first step of national<br />
reconciliation. Now that was not rhetoric. It was about bringing<br />
them together not treating trade unionists and their<br />
organisations or employers and their organisations as enemies but<br />
as important constituents of Australian society and of the<br />
Australian economic process. Now you don't make sense of that<br />
promise by saying alright you have elected me now I am not going<br />
to move to give effect to that promise. No one can say we didn't<br />
do it fairly openly. we had the Summit, we put the Accord there.<br />
The Accord was drawn up during the election campaign openly there<br />
in Melbourne. I saw what it was about, what it promised, the<br />
processes of consultatin not just on economic management but on a<br />
wide range of issues. There it was. what they got was what they<br />
saw. And then we said we will now proceed to create the<br />
mechanisms for fleshing that out. And we created the Economic<br />
Planning Advisory Council. And I can say to you that nothing has<br />
given me greater pride as Prime Minister than to sit down and<br />
chair successive meetings of EPAC where you have had leading<br />
representatives of the business community sitting there, and they </p>
<p>won't mind me saying this, in admiration at the way in which<br />
representatives of the trade union movement have not simply<br />
expressed a point of view about the interests of their own<br />
people. But have responsibly and constructively said these are<br />
the sorts of things including restraints within our campaign<br />
which need to be followed if we are going to try and maximise the<br />
opportunity for growth in this country. I make no apology about<br />
this that I sit down and talk with these people it is what I have<br />
promised and what has come out of it. We have got out of this<br />
process the highest rate of employment growth in the history of<br />
this country, the highest rate of employment growth in any<br />
country in the world. we have got out of it, out of the situation<br />
where we have handed over, in inverted commas, control to the<br />
ACTU, we have got out of it the restoration of the most<br />
competitive position that this country has had for 15 years. We<br />
have got back a restoration of profit levels to the highest<br />
position in 15 years, the reduction of real unit labour costs to<br />
the best position in 15 years. Is that something which is against<br />
the interests of employers, that they are now more competitive<br />
than they have been for 15 years. Is it against their interests<br />
C that as a result of talking with the ACTU and getting their<br />
co-operation with reduced real unit labour costs. We have given<br />
the employers back the capacity for productive investment that<br />
they never had before under the situation of antagonism. I make<br />
no apology for that. There is nothing of which I am more proud.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Peter Bowers) Peter Bowers, Sydney Morning Herald.<br />
Prime Minister, in your 1983 election speech you promised to lift<br />
age pensions to 25% of average weekly earnings in the three year<br />
term of government. In your 1984 election speech you qualified<br />
that undertaking by saying you would try to achieve the<br />
target in the next three years. Now in what you have referred to<br />
in your speech today and I quote " our goals of greater efficiency<br />
and greater equity", what steps do you propose to take in your<br />
next three years to lift age pensions to 25% of average weekly<br />
earnings? PM: Peter, it will remain a continuing objective. We have got<br />
the position, as you know because you are a close student of the<br />
economics of government, we have got a position where we don't<br />
have unlimited capacity to pursue all our social objectives<br />
simultaneously. And what has characterised our approach in the<br />
three years of government, as I think you appreciate, is that we<br />
have sought to target the areas of greatest need and they have<br />
been particularly the situation of single parents with children<br />
and there have been very, very significant increases in outlays<br />
in that and related areas pensioners who are renting and other<br />
areas of signifcant increases in outlays. So you have sought<br />
those areas pensioners who really are in the greatest need and<br />
have given the greatest increases there. I repeat now that as we<br />
go through the next period we will not abandon that objective. We<br />
will seek to obtain it. It will be dependent, the timing of it<br />
will be dependent upon our assessment of the economic capacity of<br />
the community. We don't as a government Hawke, Keating, those<br />
27 people in the ministry, it is not our money it is the<br />
community's. We are agents for the community, we are trying to in<br />
a growing society and one where we are trying to get greater<br />
equity, are trying to take as the first steps for the improvement </p>
<p>three years a very considerable increase in employment. If at<br />
some stage down the track I believe that it is appropriate to set<br />
some sort of figure, it would be done. I don't see any sense in<br />
which it is necessary now. We are not a Party coming in untested<br />
and seeking the endorsement of the Australian people. We are a<br />
government which has now shown its, I think, unrivalled<br />
competence in this area. I don't think a statement of targets is<br />
necessary. JOURNALIST: ( Paul Kelly) Paul Kelly from News Ltd, Mr Hawke. You<br />
said in your speech that the world doesn't owe us a living but<br />
the world is making pretty tough for us at the moment. Our trade<br />
account is declining and this has forced your Government into<br />
imposing a monetary policy which has led to a significant<br />
economic slow down so severe that the Treasury document published<br />
yesterday cast grave doubts on the Government's capacity to<br />
continue with job creation next year. In the light of the<br />
international situation and your statement in your speech that<br />
the Accord is flexible, can you countenance the possibility of a<br />
renegotiated Accord during the course of the year if a lower wage<br />
outcome is necessary in order to ensure that job creation is<br />
maintained? I have got a second question as well.<br />
PM: Well, let me deal with the first one first. I mightn't share<br />
power with the ACTU but I do with madame President. Let me just<br />
quickly make what I think is a relevant point in regard to that<br />
first question, Paul. we renegotiated the Accord and we did it at<br />
a time where there was an enormous amount of cynicism as to<br />
whether the 2% that we negotiated, 2% discount that we negotiated<br />
would be anywhere near adequate for the impact of the<br />
arrangement....... it took from depreciation that had taken place<br />
that would occur through 1985 the price impact. But in fact all<br />
the evidence that we have got now suggests that the 2% that we<br />
negotiated last year, ahead of the event, will virtually exactly<br />
correspond with identifiable inflation impact of the depreciation<br />
during 1985. Now in those circumstances we don't see it as<br />
neceossary to go for further renegotiations. I simply make the<br />
point and it is all that is appropriate to make now that yes, the<br />
Accord is flexible. I don't hypothesise that we are going to have<br />
the emergence of a situation where any further negotiation is<br />
necessary. I simply flag as I have before, there is the<br />
flexibility within the Accord. it is a matter of public record<br />
that we have acknowledged that and the ACTU has. But I am not<br />
saying that on my reading of the situation that I believe it is<br />
necessary, as we see it now, to seek to exercise that<br />
flexibility.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Paul Kelly) The Federal Government is looking at<br />
the proposed Holmes a Court takeover of BHP to make an assessment<br />
as to whether there will be any revenue loss involved in the<br />
takeover and if it hasn't will ensure that it does impart the the<br />
Government's ongoing review of this?<br />
PM: Yes, we have addressed that question, Paul, and as I think<br />
is known we will be meeting this afternoon with representatives<br />
of BHP and tomorrow morning with representatives of Bell. And as<br />
well as what we have already done, in terms of our own<br />
investigation, questions will be directed to the people with whom </p>
<p>we are speaking that will be relevant to that issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Geoff Kitney) Geoff Kitney of the National Times,<br />
Mr Hawke. Just following on from Paul's question about BHP. There<br />
has been a suggestion today that an appropriate way to look at<br />
this question would be through the Steel Industry Authority as<br />
suggested by John MacBean. I wondered if you could offer your<br />
reaction to that?<br />
PM: It was suggested, Geoff, that section 7 of the Act provides<br />
that capacity. Section 7 sets out the obligations of the<br />
Authority to investigate matters affecting the steel industry.<br />
They put that in general terms and then they particularised the<br />
sorts of things that can be looked at. And I think it is arguable<br />
that within the terms of section 7 of the Act that you could ask<br />
for some sort of inquiry there. I accept that it is arguable but<br />
what we have done and I think it is the appropriate course action<br />
is to say well, ultimately the Government has to come to<br />
decisions on these matters and we think it is more appropriate<br />
that we should directly speak with both BHIP and with the<br />
representatives of Bell and Mr Holmes a Court, address ourselves<br />
to these issues but the next point which is directly relevant to<br />
what you have said is that following those discussions I will,<br />
and I have already arranged for us as a group of Ministers to<br />
meet with the Steel Industry Authority's Mr Roberts to discuss<br />
with him the outcome of the discussion that we will have then<br />
held with the representatives of the two groups.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Bill Goff) Bill Goff from AAP, Prime minister.<br />
Change of pace for the last over of the day back to the<br />
Aboriginal land rights question. Both yourself and Mr Foley have<br />
now expressed some satisifaction of the progress made by the<br />
States towards the securing of land tenure....... I have two<br />
questions. Is the preferred model of the Commonwealth now<br />
completely irrelevant or will the Federal Government reconsider<br />
the introduction of national legislation if some or all States<br />
fai~ l to make further progress towards the standards of the<br />
preferred model within a reasonable time?<br />
PM: It is not irrelevant Bill. It contains the statement of the<br />
4..: Government's principles, the desirable objectives in this issue<br />
of trying to get secured title for Aboriginals in regard to land<br />
with which they have a traditional association. That is the<br />
objective and the preferred model sets out considerations which<br />
are relevant to the achievement of that objective. I have stayed<br />
in fairly constant touch with my Minister. on this he reports<br />
regularly to me and I must say that his reporting to me is one of<br />
optimism about the way in which negotiations are going. There is<br />
no doubt that as far as Western Australian is concerned there<br />
will as a result of the agreement that has been reached, which<br />
will go both with the question Bill, of title of the land and<br />
also with the question of improved infrastructure. I mean we have<br />
made a joint commitment now with the intrusion of considerable<br />
funds to provide a significant upgrade of infrastructure within<br />
the areas to which they will get secure title. Now I can only say<br />
that on the reports that Clyde Holding makes to me I believe that<br />
we have grounds for considerable optimism under this approach and<br />
therefore I don't think the question that you put arises. We will </p>
<p>12<br />
positively continue those negotiations and try and have this<br />
co-operative approach with the States because I am certain, I<br />
think there can be very little doubt about this, if you can get<br />
the objectives through co-operation with the States, the<br />
Aboriginal people themselves are going to be able to enjoy the<br />
outcome in a much better environment than in one of<br />
confrontation.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
