<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1165</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS, RADIO AND TELEVISION CONFERENCE ON THE OCCASION OF THE ANNOUNCEMENT OF HIS APPOINTMENT AS LORD WARDEN OF THE CINQUE PORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/10/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001165.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>65/ 129<br />PRESS, RADIO AND TELEVISION CONFERENCE<br />IVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER SIR ROBERT MENZIES<br />T PARLIAMENT HOUSE CANBERRA, ON THURSDAY<br />7TH OCTOBER 1965 AT 3.50 P. M. ON THE OCCASION<br />OF THE ANNOUNCEMENT OF HIS APPOINTMENT AS<br />LORD WARDEN OF THE CINQUE PORTS<br />PRIME MINISTER Sorry I didn't hear the 19 gums.<br />Well, no doubt you will have some uestions but Ithink I ought<br />to begin by mentioning two points that I gather are being dealt<br />with in other places. Somebody appears to have imagined that<br />because I have been given this purely honorary title and office<br />that I am goini off to live in Great'Britain You can forget<br />about it. I live in Australia and I hope I'll die here. So all<br />that kind of rumour has no foundation at all. In the second place,<br />I hope nobody will think I am going to career around Australian<br />waters as an admiral because I am not. This, as you probably<br />know, having looked at it now. is a very ancient style and title.<br />Lord Wairden of the Cinque Ports used to have considerable actual<br />jurisdiction both legal and otherwise. He has none now. His<br />principal duty is. if he can, to go down about once a year for a<br />week or so. is first duty is to attend his installation and after<br />that the people in the ports like to think that he will be down<br />there once a year. Well, I normally fetch up in Great Britain<br />once a year so that is no great inconvenience. He has the right,<br />I believe to reside at Walmer Cstle but as it is uninhabitable,<br />it is a theoretical right rather than anything else. Though,<br />Mr. Wilson when he raised this matter with me in London did indicate<br />that they were investigating the possibility of making some part of<br />it h. bitable, putting in a flat or something of that Kind so that<br />it might be used officially. Well, that's on the knees of the gods.<br />It's fascinating to know that the Lord Warden has the right to<br />Sflotsam, jetsam and lagan.<br />QUESTIONER What is " lagan", Sir?<br />P. M. Lagan is wreckage which lies on the sea floor.<br />Q. Oh, I thought it might be mermaids. ( Laughter)<br />P. M. No, unhappily mermaids are not included in " Fishes Royal"<br />I am entitlea to Fishes Royal. Queer entitlement whales,<br />porpoises and so on. All it means is if a whale gets itself washed<br />up bn the beach at Dover the Lord Warden has the supreme privilege<br />of paying for its removal.<br />Q. When is the installation, Sir?<br />P. M. Oh, that isn't fixed. That will be the next time I am in<br />England, whenever that happens to be.<br />Q. The style of the uniform, if any?<br />P. M. They tell me there is a uniform. I don't My<br />predecessor, Winston Churchill, he was interested in the uniform but<br />I don't think he went down for his weekly visit very much. He was<br />more conspicuous by his absence. But, yes, in terms of uniform the<br />W. rden is a species of admiral, which I imagine is the most nautical<br />thing about him. But it is really a very great personal honour.<br />I feel it in that sense. Lord Willingdon, Lord Reading and<br />Winston Churchill being the three predecessors.<br />Q. Would it suggest that it is a prelude to a peerage?<br />PM. Not the slightest chance. / 2</p>
<p>-2-<br />Q. Have you made any decisiQn on when you'll retire?<br />Oh, come off it. Do you expect me to make a decision<br />this week? I've been expecting one for three months, Sir.<br />Well I'm not even thinking about that. I'll deal with<br />that at what I think is the right time. Yes or No.<br />You did suggest Sir, when you returned from abroad<br />earlier in the rear that you were in fact thinking of it.<br />Are you still t inking of it?<br />PM.: Oh yes, of course and I will continue to think of it.<br />Wouldn't you at my age think of it?<br />When do you think you will be in England again, Sir?<br />P. M. -Vell, I don't know. I don't know.<br />Q. In reference to your age, Sir do you feel the duties<br />of the job are growing such that tAey are testing you<br />physically? You mean my present<br />Q. Ai Prime Minister.<br />P. M. gell, it'z3 not easy. But. look, this problem let's<br />be quite plain about it. This is a matter that I will have<br />to decide one way or the other at the right time, and that<br />time hasn't arisen and as far as I can see, it won't arise for<br />some time to come.<br />Q. Sir, getting back to the position of Lord Warden, are<br />there any privileges that go with this position?<br />P. M. Yes I have the right to flotsam jetsam and lagan and I<br />daresay that what I'll fave to do is to live hoping"<br />would be the wrcng word because it would be inhuman<br />for some decent luxury liner to be cist ashore out of which<br />I might get a few perquisites. There are no privileges.<br />You have the privilege of spending a good deal of money.<br />Q. Do you fly a special flag, Sir, over the castle?<br />P. M. Yes, there is a flag, I believe.<br />Q. Will y~ u use it in Australia?<br />P. M. Oh, I wouldn't think so. None of this has any operation<br />in Australia.<br />Q. Doesn't affect precedence in Australia?<br />P. M. Oh dear no. Oh no.<br />Q. Do you know what the uniform is like, Sir?<br />P. M. I am told that it is based on the uniform of an admiral.<br />Q. A modern or an ancient one?<br />P. M. Oh I haven't a clue. I was under the great impression<br />at the 6oronation time that Winston had on this uniform under<br />the gown of the Garter. That's mere speculation. He enjoyed<br />dressing up. I hate it. / 3</p>
<p>-3-<br />Are you able to tell us, Sir, anything of the method of<br />selecting the Lord Warden?<br />Well, I gather that what happens is this. It's a Royal<br />appointment but the Government 01 the day tenders advice on<br />the matter. Mr. Wilson spoke to me about this towards the<br />end of the last Prime Ministers' Conference and wanted to know<br />whether I would permit him to put my name forward. Well, I<br />said it needed a bit of thouaht. I didn't quite know what it<br />involved, what travel it might commit me to in the future and<br />what expenditure that's not unimportant. And so we had<br />correspondence afterwards and finally I said " yes". I had<br />always said this was a very great honour. I wrote to him<br />finally and said, yes, I would agree to his putting my name<br />forward and he did then. I had reason to believe hat he had<br />discussed it with The Queen before and so the announcement was<br />made. You don't suggest Sir that Mr. Wvilson was trying to<br />help the Australian Latour tarty?<br />P. M I -, Would hate to put it on so low a level as that. Mr.<br />Wilson is a very practical man. I don't think he would<br />commit himself o an impracticable course.<br />Q. Sir Robert, have you any idea why a Labour Prime Minister<br />should su,: est you for the office?<br />-hat's this?<br />Have you any idea why a Labour Prime Minister should<br />suggest you for This office?<br />P. M. No. All I can assume in my :) wn favour is that he thought<br />I was an appropriate person. It wasn't proposed to me as<br />Prime Minister because, after all, one is no a Prime Minister<br />forever, and this appointment runs for life.<br />Do you see any political significance at all in the fact<br />that he nominated you for it, Sir?<br />P. M. I don't. No.<br />Q. Does this carry any special precedence, Sir at Commonwealth<br />Prime Ministers' Conferences?<br />P. M. Oh no. I gather from some of the papers they sent me<br />that I Aave special precedence in the Cinque Ports area. If<br />The Queen is there, I outrank other people. I think that must<br />be great fin, but the question won't arise.<br />Is this installation likely to be this year, Sir?<br />Ycu mean in 1965?<br />Yes.<br />P. M. Oh, no. It will be next year some time.<br />Q. Sir do you think Mr. Wilscn may have considered you a<br />suitable person for this honour because of a possible imminent<br />retirement? I credit Y. Vilson with a great deal of intelligence<br />and therefore he would never entertain so absurd an idea.<br />You boys will chivvy me out of office if you have your way,<br />won't you, but I will make up my own mind in my own time,<br />thank you. / 4</p>
<p>-4-<br />Q. Sir Robert, have you any ideas of what city you will<br />retire to when you do Tinally make the decision.<br />I anticipate Melbourne yes. That's my own, so to<br />speak, home town and there I'll go, I hope.<br />There's a rumour that you have in fact made appraches<br />about buying a house in Melbourne.<br />P. M. Yes, that's quite tre I can confirm that. I have<br />been doing it for the last fifteen years. Once a year my wife<br />and I sa~ y, " Well, it would be rather nice to have a home of<br />our own in our home tywn" and we think of it. You are<br />quite right, so I can t deny that rumour,<br />Q. Would you have actually been looking at any properties<br />in Melbourne in reoent months?<br />Every year I have looked at one or two so far withcut<br />result, but if you should hear of a good one, I'll be<br />grateful.<br />Q. It might be easier to build a new Prime Minister's<br />Lodge here, Sir, as you have been here that lvng.<br />P. M. Oh, I hope not, I hope not. I wouldn't want to be here<br />when the new Prime Minister's lodge was finished. That's a<br />Stime off. That doesn't mean next week.<br />Q. Don't you think in view of the fact that you have been<br />Prime Minister for so long. occupied the Lodge for so long<br />yoa would be the appropriate one to make the decision to build<br />a new Lodge, thereby saving your successor embarrassment?<br />P. M. There are proposals about a new Lodge which I know the<br />National Capital Cbmmission has had in mind because in some<br />ways this is not the perfect answer, the present house. The<br />contribution that I will make to that will be to give them the<br />benefit of my advice and so will my wife, as to what ought<br />to be done in a new rime Minister's house. In other words<br />what deficiencies there are in this one, how they might be<br />improved or removed in another. But that's a mere matter of<br />6cnsultation. I will always be willing to do that, but I don't<br />anticipate living in any oher Prime Minister's Lodge myself<br />than the one I now precariously occupy.<br />Q. Sir Robert do you intend to Co to England before the<br />normal time as AustralianPrime Minister in the winter?<br />P. M. I hope not. Indeed I hope not.<br />Q. There will be no special trip for this?<br />Oh no. No. I have had a few winter trips there and I am<br />not enamoured of them.<br />This suggested retirement before say, May next year, it's<br />just not on?<br />PM. I'm sayin-nothin-about that. I have already said that<br />I will decide hat mater in my own time. Why are you in such<br />a hurry to get rid of me? o</p>
<p>Q. Je are seeking amplification of statements issued in your<br />name. What statement is this?<br />The statement to the effect that normal dutics will take<br />you to the U. K.<br />P. M. Well what's mystericus about that?<br />Q. Well would'hormal duties" be as Australia's Prime<br />Minister, Sir?<br />I didn't say so. I might with reasonable expectation<br />of life hope to be still alive when I am no longer Prime<br />Minister, and if still alive, then I may have some duties<br />or I may impose them myself, which will take me to England.<br />All I am saying is that I would anticipate being able to go<br />there once a year. This is not a job ex officio you know.<br />This is not an appointment as Prime Minister. TAis is an<br />appcintment under my omri name.<br />Q. Sir Robert, do you hope to be the Prime Minister when<br />you accept the new honour formally?<br />P. M. In other words, you want me to make a statement about a<br />matter that I said I am not making a statement about. You<br />are trying in vain. You must restrain your eagerness in<br />spite of your newspaper.<br />Q. On a different subject, Sir, can you give us your<br />reactions or whatever analysis you have made of what could<br />be the effect of recent happenings in Indonesia on Australia?<br />P. M. Oh, no, look the conference was not called for<br />that purpose. I am discussing all that with Mr. Hasluck<br />because I think that we ought to, if we can, if the position<br />has cleared enough, to have a statement made on that on<br />Tuesday in the House, but at present, of course, it is all<br />very obscure. By that time, perhaps, it will be sufficiently<br />clarified to say something useful.<br />Q. Sir, you told us two conferences ago you didn't know<br />whether you were going to lead the Government at the next<br />election. Do you now know whether you will or not?<br />P. M. ' eren't you here when I answered these questions earlier?<br />Q. I was here two conferences ago.<br />P. M. Yes I thought you mi htn't have been here today.<br />Don't tare me for a fool. Y9u can't trick me into making<br />some statement about a matter on which I have already stated<br />ouite clearly that I will deal . ith that in my own time, not<br />in yours. Come on, any more intelligent questions?<br />We'll try, Sir again. Can you tell us if this new<br />appointment could allow you to go to Prime Ministers'<br />Conferences in any other capacity than Prime Minister?<br />Uill it have any Uommonweath significance? e / 6</p>
<p>-6<br />P. M. This appointment has no bearing upon what happens at<br />a Prime Ministers' Conference. This is a purely local matter<br />of great historic interest and continuity. It happens now for<br />the first time to a man outside Great Britain. I$ has no<br />bearing whatever on anything that happens at Prime Ministers'<br />Conferences or otherwise.<br />Q. Sir Robert, if you don't wish to discuss Indonesia at<br />this press conference, will you be holding one soon when we<br />can diScuss it?<br />I don't know. I am going to clarify my own mind with my<br />colleague on what goes on in Tndonesia firsXtw ith a view if<br />we can get some clarification adequate clarification, to<br />saying something to Parliament aoout it.<br />Sir Robert, would you let us go from the Five Ports to<br />the Australian waterfront?<br />P. M. No. No, I won't.<br />Q. Sir there was another announcement in London today from<br />Rhodesia House that IVir. Ian Smith has sent a message to<br />PA.: Gentlemen, I am afraid there has been a misapprehension.<br />I thought this conference was about this little honorific<br />affair of mine, not a general conference.<br />Q. Ie thought it might be a lead-in, Sir.<br />P. M. Did you? No, I'm saying nothing about Rhodesia.<br />I'm just hoping. I'm saying nothing,<br />Q. Sir the ceremony of installation. Does it involve the<br />British Prime Minister?<br />I couldn't tell you. I don't know.<br />Q. Does this take place at one of the Five Ports?<br />P. M. I think it usually occurs at Dover. They have a bi!<br />function of some kind and when that happens you are initTated<br />and when it's over you take off the uniform and hang it up.<br />I think I must buy one and put it in the Parliament House.<br />Mr. Hurst, President of the Press Gallery Sir Robert, just before<br />you go, 3r, on baf of the Press Gallery, in spite of the<br />questions, we would like to congratulate you on this honour.<br />P. M. Thank you very much. Thank you.<br />I I I</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
