<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1648</transcript-id>
    <title>N.S.F CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES ANNUAL DINNER, SYDNEY. N.S.W  30TH AUGUST, 1967  -  MAIN POINTS FROM SPEECH MADE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/08/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001648.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
R Is<br />
CHAMBER OF MANUJFACTURhES<br />
A7-NNUAL DINNER, SYDNEY, N. S. W. L I BR A9<br />
AUGUST, 1967<br />
Main points from speech made by<br />
the Prime Minister, Mr. HaroldiTlolt<br />
Developments since , iorld_'\' ar II<br />
Since the second world war thereo has been a<br />
tremendous surge of development which has completely<br />
transformed the Australian economy.<br />
iiany of you will have little difficulty recalling<br />
the days when it was said " Australia rides on the sheep's<br />
back". There was some important mining activity and an iron<br />
and steel industry. But in the main, manufacturing was still<br />
confined to food processing plus some embryo industries<br />
struggling to penetrate the local market.<br />
There was a time when the tag " imported" appeared<br />
to mean " superior". The pos,_ ibility of exporting manufactured<br />
goods would have been regarded as rather fanciful in those<br />
days. In the two decades since, Australian primary<br />
industry has progressed to a point where it is one of the<br />
most advanced and diversified in the world; it is highly<br />
productive with perhaps the only obvious limit to its<br />
potential being the barriers it meets in marketing its<br />
products overseas. This development has stemm--ed largely from the<br />
application of capital and improved technology a<br />
development in which secondary industry has had a large<br />
and important role to play. Improved machines and<br />
fertilisers combined with the skills of our farmers have<br />
combined to make these adva-nces in primary industry possible.<br />
The massive mineral discoveries of recent yeors<br />
not only offer gi eat new sources of export earnings but they<br />
will provide new sources of power and the prospects for the<br />
development of a great new range of processing and manufacturing<br />
industries. They are also calling for many products of<br />
secondary industry, for mining on the scale envisaged in this<br />
country today is a highly inechanised, capital intensive<br />
operation. Once we got settled down after the immediate<br />
post-war period, Australia's manufacturing industry made<br />
rapid progress. For some, old traditions die hard, but I<br />
think it is fair to say that in this period the old tag<br />
" imported is better" was laid to rest. Dfanufacturing<br />
quietly and efficiently went about the business of supplying<br />
a wide range of domestic needs, and a whole new range of<br />
consumer durable industries appeared to meet the demands<br />
of rapidly improving standards of living which put<br />
refrigerators, washing machines and other appliances into<br />
almost every home and added an ever-growin' stream of<br />
motor cars to the roads.<br />
The Lord lyayor and Yr. Askin might, of course,<br />
have mixed feelings about some of the blessings engendered<br />
by the latter item. I recall here Henry Kaiser's aphorism<br />
" problems are opportunities in work clothes' ( quoted at<br />
the Queensland alumina opening early this month). And all<br />
these things demanded great quantities of the products of </p>
<p>the more basic secondary industries such as iron and steel<br />
and these in turn responded with a tremendous development<br />
and expansion which can be seen so dramatically in the area<br />
from Newcastle to : i', ollongong and at Whyalla.<br />
Australia now has a very wide range of manufacturing<br />
industry with over 60,000 factories employing about 1.3 million<br />
people. This is some 28% of the work force, a proportion which<br />
is higher than that engaged in manufacturing in Canada, France<br />
and Japan and little lower than that in what are truly the<br />
great industrialised nations of the world. For instance, in<br />
the United 63tates the proportion of the work force employed<br />
in manufacturing is 29%.<br />
Dut these bare statistics, important though. they<br />
may be as indicators of industrial progress, do not reflect<br />
the impact that manufacturing industry has had on the lives<br />
and well-being of millions of Australians.<br />
If I may again revert to the immediate post-war<br />
period in the first post-war census, that of 1947 the<br />
Australian population was about 7.6 million, today it stands<br />
at 11.7 million. In those days the wrork force numbered<br />
3.2 million, today it is about 4.7 maillion. But this<br />
accumulation of people and of workers did not come, as it<br />
were, only from our own resources, many came to us from<br />
overseas. Our continuing immigration policy has since<br />
become an absolutely basic factor in the economic life of<br />
Australia. But these new settlers needed jobs and they -wanted<br />
homes and all the things that go with them. IW. anufacturing<br />
has delivered on both sides; it has provided the goods and<br />
the jobs. Some 26% of the work force currently employed in<br />
manufacturing industry are migrants. In the period ' 1947-61<br />
the male wiork,, force employed in manufacturing rose by<br />
270,000 of whom 222,000 or 82% were people who arrived in<br />
Australia since 1947.<br />
Pe rcentage o Jirants of<br />
otl Emplonmnt-in rcent age<br />
Car and ship-building industry 28<br />
Petroleum and coal products 36<br />
Extracting, refining and founding<br />
of metals 33<br />
There is no overall figure for th-e iron and steel<br />
industry, but the employment of migrants is relatively highin<br />
some cases as much as<br />
In the vollongong-Port T,' embla area where there<br />
has been so much manufacturing development, 28,/ of the<br />
popjulation is overseas-born. For these people the development<br />
of industry in Australia is not just a statistic, it is a<br />
vital part of the way of life they have come to emnbrace in<br />
this country. I talked earlier about the importance in this<br />
country of the production of consumer goods and particularly<br />
consumer durables. But we must remember that Australian<br />
industry is not merely concerned with producing washing<br />
machines and T. V. sets, important as these things are in<br />
our standard of living. Australian manufacturing industry<br />
is much more varied and sophisticated than many people<br />
realise. </p>
<p>vle produce items many people associate only with<br />
the most highly developed industrial economies. For example,<br />
radio telephone equipment and transistorised airways beacons<br />
are made here. 4e have developed some unique and complex systems<br />
like the Jindivik pilotless jet, the Ikara anti-submarine<br />
missile and the 1! alkara anti-tank guided weapon, products<br />
which have been produced not only for our own use but for<br />
export to overseas markets including the United Kingdom and<br />
the United States.<br />
In one of the most advanced fields of technology<br />
space exploration we are making a contribution. At ioomera<br />
Australia has one of the largest land rocket ranges in the<br />
world 1,200 miles long over practically uninhabited country.<br />
Currently we are engaged, in conjunction with the United States<br />
and B~ ritain, in investigating problems of re-entry from heights<br />
exceeding 500 miles.<br />
New Opportunities for Trade<br />
If I may re-enter the early post-war period I would<br />
like to say a few words about exports of manufactured goods.<br />
In this field also there has been notable growth flowing from<br />
manufacturing industry. I mentioned a few moments ago some<br />
items which we export to the United States and Britain but<br />
these were only a few of many items which we now manufacture<br />
and export to countries from which wie once imported the same<br />
types of goods. But we cannot rest upon our laurels, we must<br />
continually be on the lookout for new markets for the products<br />
of all types of industry.<br />
4e are all aware of the remarkable development of<br />
our trade with Japan. For the three years prior to the signing<br />
of the Trade Agreement with Japan our exports to Japan averaged<br />
,134m. In 1966-67 we exported goods valued at .588m. to Japan,<br />
an increase of 339% during the period of the , gAr eement.<br />
But the importance and attraction of the Japanese<br />
market should not be allowed to lead us into neglecting other<br />
areas of Asia where trade prospects are bright.<br />
Our exports to other Asian countries last financial<br />
year exceeded .416m. or 13.7%-0 of our reported exports even<br />
though our share of the total market available in Asia was<br />
small. In Malaysia, for instance, wie supplied about of<br />
the market. It is true, of course, that much of the available<br />
market is virtually closed to us because of the nature of the<br />
products required or other economic factors, but there is a<br />
vast, largely untapped market for Australian products in the<br />
Asian area. As economic development in Asia proceeds opportunities<br />
will increasingly arise for alert Australian exporters. Taiwan<br />
is planning an iron and steel industry and Australia will have<br />
an opportunity to supply iron ore. In South Korea, the<br />
extraordinary economic growth there has created a potentially<br />
large market for Australian foodstuffs and materials, machines<br />
and machinery. In some countries such as Vietnam, Cambodia and Laos </p>
<p>trading opportunities may presently seem to be small but if<br />
there can be stable government and peace in the region these<br />
nations will11 progress to a stage wNh: re improved trading<br />
possibilities will arise.<br />
Zconomic rehabilitation in Indonesia would open up<br />
another dimension of trading opportunities.<br />
Tariff Policy lvuch has been written lately about tariffs and<br />
tariff policy and some people have been demanding that the<br />
Government should state just what is its tariff policy.<br />
Some years ago Sir Robert Dlenzies, in his 1962<br />
inaugural John Storey memorial lecture excellently summarised<br />
the Government's position. I would like to quote to you the<br />
relevant parts of his statement on that occasion:-<br />
" The Tariff Board is a purely statutory body, created<br />
by the discretion of P1" arliament and, indeed, subject to<br />
the control of Parliament. In this sense, it is an<br />
instrument of policy and in no sense its master.<br />
It has, however, been recognised by successive governments<br />
that, though what I have said is constitutionally true,<br />
it is important that, for international as well as<br />
domestic purposes, the Tariff Board should possess a<br />
high measure of independence, that the integrity of<br />
its advice should be preserved, and that it should not<br />
be subject to any form of" day-to-day political<br />
instruction.<br />
I accept and maintain these propositions. Yet the Tariff<br />
Board, our principal adviser on import duties, cannot<br />
sensibly be expected to operate in a completely detached<br />
intellectual vacuum. It must have in its mind some<br />
standards or policies by which to teat the cases<br />
presented to it.<br />
For a long time it has acted on the principle that it<br />
should recommend tariff protection only to " economic and<br />
efficient industries'. But that principle was, and is,<br />
itself an expression of Government policy. Of late,<br />
indications have been given on behalf of my own. Government<br />
that the princi-,) e needs extension, and that the Tariff<br />
Board should have in its mind thne national economic policy,<br />
meaning by that the national economic objectivcs, as a<br />
whole There are certain features of national economic policy,<br />
which I do not regard as the subject of party controversy,<br />
which cannot be ignored by any statutory body if the<br />
nation is to achieve a dynamic progress, growing in<br />
resources, population, employment, industry, and<br />
international solvency. For a Tariff Board to ignore<br />
their existence would be to detach its work from the<br />
great stream of Australian development. ' This, I am sure,<br />
it would not wish to do."<br />
The tariff policy of the Government has been clearly<br />
stated for a long time, and I reaffirm it to be that reasonable<br />
and adequate protection will be given to economic and efficient<br />
industry. The Government looks to the Tariff Board for advice<br />
on whether an industry is economic and efficient. On a few<br />
occasions they have been comparatively few the Governmen~ t </p>
<p>has seen fit to say in the terms of reference to the Tariff<br />
Board that its policy is to give assistance to a particular<br />
industry, for example, copper production in remote areas,<br />
crude oil production and production of penicillin. On these<br />
occasions the 3oard is asked to recommend in its published<br />
report its view of the best way to carry out the policy.<br />
But outside of these, tariff protection has been<br />
given to industry only following a finding by the Tariff Board<br />
that the industry is economic and e ffici ent.<br />
The policy does not include, as some peopl? pretend<br />
it does, that every industry that seeks protection shall be<br />
given protection. Industry is given protection if it measures<br />
up as being economic and efficient.<br />
There has been some talk of there being a " high<br />
protection" policy. In truth, our overall level of tariffs<br />
is moderate, and we do not use the quotas and other<br />
administrative devices that so many other countries turn to.<br />
And an important point is that tariff prot~ ction is not given<br />
in excess of that recommended by thc Tariff Board after an<br />
open public inquiry and report. The Government is bound to<br />
this under the U. K.-/ Australia Trade Agreement.<br />
Periodically there are claims that some definition<br />
of the termns " econom-. ic and efficient" should be laid down.<br />
This is a matter that has been carefully considered on a<br />
number of occasions. ? ieteran industry is economic and efficient is a<br />
matter of judgment, and it is a judgment that must take in<br />
all the relevant circumstances of each particular case. There<br />
is a wide range of isaes which can affenct such a judgment and<br />
these can vary in emphasis depending on the circumstancc-s of<br />
each case. The Government, rather than confine the Board to<br />
thc limits of some definition which it may or may not be<br />
possible to lay down, prefers to leave the question to the<br />
independent judgment of the Board, taken in the lighlt of all<br />
the circumstances. Finally, let me turn to the quite baseless charges<br />
sometimes made about political pressure b , ing applied to the<br />
Tariff Board and about its ind~ ependence being undermined. I<br />
take it that the adherents of this line don't build their case<br />
on the few occasions when the Government does not accept the<br />
recommendations of the Board. Afterall, responsibility for<br />
tariff policy and tariff-making rcsts with the Government and<br />
the Government alone. The Tariff Board's role is advisory.<br />
On the same grounds their case could hardly be based<br />
on the Government's desire that the Board should, in offering<br />
its advice, have regard to the general objectives of overall<br />
Government policy. Nor could it rest on the few occasions when<br />
the Government considers it necessary to tell the Board in a<br />
reference that it has a particular line of policy.<br />
The truth is that the ' 2ariff Board has complc: te<br />
independence in conducting its inquiries. It is expected to<br />
exercise its independent judgment in offering advice to the<br />
Government. If the Government wants the Loard to take note of<br />
a particular line of policy it says so in public, in the<br />
reference. I know of no hidden instructions, no secret messages<br />
and no surreptitious pressures. M~ y colleague the Mviriister for<br />
Trade has confirmed this. If the people who harp on that line<br />
believe they have knowledge to the contrary they should bring it<br />
out into the open and it will be investigated and answvered. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
