<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5903</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005903.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
&gt; A US<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 5 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
I don't think any of us now need to be told how serious<br />
the drought is, particularly in the Eastern States. It is<br />
an enormously difficult situation for farmers. Both cattle<br />
and sheep prices are down considerably on last year. Unless<br />
there is substantial rain over the next few weeks, Australia<br />
will face one of the worst rural disasters that it has ever<br />
experienced. Against this background, the Commonwealth has made a number of<br />
substantial decisions. Two of these decisions which are vastly<br />
important will be totally funded by the Commonwealth Government<br />
and other decisions will involve the traditional co-operative<br />
arrangements between the Commonwealth and the States.<br />
The Commonwealth will fund totally a subsidy for farmers on<br />
interest payments exceeding 12% on debts. That means a farmer<br />
will pay the first 12% on his overdraft and if he is in a<br />
drought declared area the Commonwealth will pick up the balance.<br />
However, if a farmer has readily available liquid assets, he<br />
would be expected to use those to help reduce his level of<br />
debt before he would be eligible for interest subsidy.<br />
The Commonwealth will also provide a 50% subsidy on purchases<br />
of fodder for livestock. This decision is very important<br />
because in the period ahead what we have to do is make<br />
sure that basic stock are preserved. Yarding and sales have<br />
increased very greatly in recent weeks but if Australia's<br />
breeding numbers fall significantly, then permanent damage<br />
will be done to the grazing and pastoral industries, and it<br />
would take much longer to recover from the damage of the<br />
drought when finally the drought breaks.<br />
In addition to these two Commonwealth initiatives, the<br />
Commonwealth is to propose significant changes to the core<br />
measures operating under the natural disaster relief arrangements<br />
when Commonwealth and State Agricultural Ministers meet next<br />
week. The Commonwealth funds these core measures on the<br />
basis of $ 3 from the Commonwealth to $ 1 from the States once<br />
the base amount has been provided by the States.<br />
When first implemented, therefore, it should provide no<br />
particular burden on the States. The core measures include<br />
carry-on loans, freight concessions, stock slaughter and<br />
stock disposal subsidies and water subsidies. What we are<br />
proposing is that the core measures not only be expanded,<br />
but that there is a more co-ordinated approach between the<br />
States. With our own intiatives there is no reason why the<br />
States should not accept these additional proposals. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Our proposals include support for local governments in sinking<br />
bores for water supplies for farmers. That is particularly<br />
useful in areas where the farmers run out of water and they<br />
cannot put down a normal farm bore because the cost might be<br />
too great. We hope that the States will accept the cost of<br />
such bores and the manning of such bores as part of the normal<br />
core measures for the purpose of this drought.<br />
We will also be suggesting to the States that the limits on<br />
carry-on loans be raised to $ 40,000 or doubled, whichever<br />
is the greater. In some States it is already up to that level.<br />
But in Victoria, the carry-on loans are only $ 15,000, which<br />
of course is not going to be all that much assistance to farmers<br />
in great and serious difficulty at the present time.<br />
The Commonwealth will also require the money that it makes<br />
available to the States for drought loans be on-lent by<br />
the States at no more than 4% interest. We have been<br />
providing these funds to the States in the past at no<br />
interest and some of them have been charging 5% or There<br />
are proposals to take this up to even 12%. There is no reason<br />
why the States should make a profit on the funds that are<br />
on-lent for these particular purposes.<br />
We will also be suggesting that States should extend the<br />
carry-on loans arrangements for farmers to small. businesses<br />
in rural communities that are affected by drought. This is<br />
already done in Queensland and we would like all States to<br />
follow Queensland's example.<br />
We will be proposing that the subsidy on water cartage be<br />
set at 100% and we will be proposing also to the States that<br />
the freight subsidy on the transport of fodder and livestock<br />
be set at 75% which is the same as the Queensland level at<br />
the moment. In some of the States it is now 60%. In other<br />
States it is<br />
We will be proposing that these six measures should form<br />
part of the normal co-operative arrangements between the<br />
Commonwealth and the. States. The assistance that all these<br />
measures will give the rural sector should be complemented<br />
by recent announcements on US beef imports and on live sheep<br />
exports, both of which will be particularly welcome at this<br />
time of hardship for the farmers.<br />
Sheep farmers will welcome the fact that on 11 September a<br />
ship will berth at Portland to load live sheep for export.<br />
The ACTU and the AMEIU at the Federal and State levels have<br />
agreed to the lifting of bans and restrictions on the export<br />
of live sheep. Beef producers will be heartened by the<br />
assurances given by the Americans that the US will meet its<br />
full commitment to Australia and import from Australia<br />
676.9 million pounds in 1982. There had been recent pressure<br />
in the US from the Cattlemen's Union to restrict beef imports.<br />
As we expected, the US government is maintaining its purchases<br />
under our joint agreement. ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
By pursuing Australia's interests the Government avoided<br />
the situation which occurred under Labor in 1974, when our<br />
beef exports to the US were chopped back considerably,<br />
and we lost all access to the Japanese market.<br />
I am sure that the resumption of live sheep exports from<br />
Portland and the assurances given to our beef producers<br />
by the Americans, as well as the drought relief measures,<br />
will give farmers greater security at this difficult time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
