<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6148</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006148.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA1 JULY 1983<br />
The attached letter was today given to the Tasmanian Premier, Mr Gray.<br />
aAA USTRA, L IA 4 </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER CANBE~ RR A<br />
~ i uLt. 1983<br />
My dear Premier<br />
Now that the High Court has made a decision favourable to<br />
the Commonwealth in relation to South West Tasmania, I am<br />
writing to inform you of measures of assistance that the<br />
Commonwealth is prepared to provide to your Government once<br />
work permanently ceases on the Gordon-below-Franklin project.<br />
The measures proposed take account of the discussions between<br />
yourself and Senator Walsh in Hobart on 22 June, our<br />
discussions in Canberra on 28 June, and subsequent discussions<br />
on detailed matters between officers of our two Governments.<br />
I stress that our pre-eminent concern is, as it has always<br />
been, the welfare of all Tasmanians and especially Tasmanian<br />
workers in relation to the interests of Australia as a whole.<br />
Immediate Employment Aspects I<br />
At this stage the prime concern of both Governments must<br />
undopibtedly be the livelihood of those persons who have been<br />
directly employed on the project. The Commonwealth is<br />
therefore prepared to reimburse the State, for a period of<br />
one month from cessation of work, in respect of payments made<br />
to persons presently engaged in the project area for wages and<br />
other award costs attributable to their continued employment.<br />
Payments to individuals under this element of the Commonwealth's<br />
proposals would of course cease as soon as they had been placed<br />
in alternative employment.<br />
During this period it would be expected that the State would<br />
make best endeavours to arrange alternative employment, and<br />
it would be the Commonwealth's expectation that by the end of<br />
that time most would have been provided with alternative<br />
employment for an initial period at least. Our Governments<br />
would need to review the situation before the month expires.<br />
For contractors currently engaged in the project area, the<br />
Commonwealth would reimburse the State in respect of the<br />
labour costs of contractors on the sam6 basis as proposed for<br />
Hydro Electric Commission employees. As to other expenses<br />
to which contractors may be liable as a result of the stopping<br />
of the project, the Commonwealth acknowledges an obligation<br />
to ensure that contractors are not placed in jeopardy, and<br />
would be prepared to cover relevant unavoidable financial<br />
commitments. The exact nature of any additional assistance<br />
to be provided will need to be considered on a case-by-case<br />
basis in the light of the particular terms of each contract ./ 2 </p>
<p>V7 2.<br />
arid the obligations faced by the contractors. I suggest<br />
that officers of our two Governments get together as a<br />
matter of urgency to work out an overall approach to this<br />
problem and to develop proposals for dealing with individual<br />
cases. I turn now to the question of alternative employment<br />
projects that could be undertaken at short notice. As<br />
Senator Walsh has indicated to you, the Commonwealth would<br />
be willing to accelerate, where appropriate, works in<br />
progress on its own account in Tasmania, and is giving<br />
urgent consideration to further works that might reasonably<br />
be undertaken. Because of lead times it would be a few<br />
months, however, before it would be possible to offer<br />
employment on such projects.<br />
I am informed that a significant part of the workforce<br />
currently engaged on the project is working on the Crotty Road<br />
which was to be the principal access to the Dam site. The<br />
Commonwealth would not wish, of course, to continue construction<br />
of the road for this purpose, and indeed will not b~ e<br />
contemplating any new works in the World Heritage area until<br />
the appropriate studies have been completed and decisions made<br />
about the future management of the area.<br />
I understand, however, that the part of the Crotty Road on<br />
which work is currently proceeding from the Crotty Village<br />
end lies outside the World Heritage area, and that there is<br />
the possibility of developing it for some distance with a<br />
view to the eventual completion of a road to Kelly's Basin.<br />
Given the tourist potential of the South-West region, this<br />
may well prove to be a sound course to follow, but our<br />
Governments would, of course, need to give some detailed<br />
consideration to this matter. For the very immediate future,<br />
however, I suggest that we allow work to continue in order to<br />
maintain the workforce and to keep options open for further<br />
development if that is subsequently agreed.<br />
There will also be employment available for some men to<br />
put other works that have been undertaken in the project area<br />
on a ' care and maintenance' basis in order to minimise<br />
potential adverse environmental effects. In order that<br />
necessary work of this kind can be undertaken within the World<br />
Heritage area, the Minister for Home Affairs and Environment<br />
will be taking the appropriate action under the World Heritage<br />
Properties Conservation Act 1983 as a matter of urgency.<br />
At your meeting with Senator Walsh on 22 June you put forward<br />
a number of possible employment projects, some of which<br />
could be started at short notice, in areas of State and local<br />
government responsibility. I stress that the Commonwealth's<br />
overriding concern for the immediate period ahead is to<br />
ensure that alternative work is found as quickly as possible<br />
for persons previously engaged on the Gordon-below-Franklin<br />
scheme. / 3~ </p>
<p>With this in mind, we could therefore agree to a number<br />
of the proposed projects proceeding forthwith viz the Ring<br />
Ri'ver Railway deviation, Hydro-Electric Commission maintenance<br />
projects, Strahan to Zeehan Road, Zeehan to Lower Pieman Road,<br />
and the Southern Outlet ( Huon Road).<br />
As to the basis on which the Commonwealth would provide funds<br />
for projects the Commonwealth would, of course, wish to be<br />
satisfied that the cost of such projects are reasonable and<br />
does not, for instance, envisage reimbursement of costs that<br />
the State would normally pay in any event. I understand that<br />
our officers have already held preliminary discussions with<br />
regard to costs and have made arrangements for further urgent<br />
detailed work.<br />
I anticipate that the Commonwealth would be in a position to<br />
forward a draft financial agreement to the State, covering<br />
income maintenance payments, payments to contractors and<br />
alternative work projects in the near future. This agreement<br />
would operate on the basis that the State receive regular<br />
and prompt reimbursement of expenditures necessarily incurred<br />
by it under the arrangements agreed between our Governments<br />
and would include the normal information and audit requirements.<br />
Other Matters for Study<br />
You will recall that, in discussing the State's requiest for<br />
reimbursement of the cost of works already undertaken on<br />
the power scheme ( including ancillary projects and preliminary<br />
investitjations), both Senator Walsh and I referred to a number<br />
of considerations that the Commonwealth would need to bear in<br />
mind before coming to a position on appropriate arrangements.<br />
In order that the necessary action can be put in hand, I now<br />
formally ask that the State submit a detailed claim, with<br />
all necessary supporting evidence.<br />
Another matter which you discussed with us was the State's<br />
request for an undertaking from the Commonwealth to meet the<br />
difference between unit power costs produced by an alternative<br />
energy source and the costs that would have been applicable<br />
had the power been generated at the projected Gordon-below-<br />
Franklin power station. It will be necessary as a first step<br />
for the State to develop detailed proposals which can then<br />
be put to study and joint discussion.<br />
Administrative Aspects<br />
I see a need, especially in the early stages, for frequent<br />
discussions between officials of our two Governments on the<br />
outstanding issues I have mentioned and any others that may<br />
arise in respect of the arrangements. To faci-litate and<br />
formalise this process I suggest that we agree to the<br />
establishment of a joint Commonwealth/ State working party.<br />
From the Commonwealth end I would see the composition of this<br />
working party as including officials of the Departments of<br />
the Prime Minister and Cabinet, Resouirces and Energy, Finance<br />
and Employment and Industrial Relations, with other Departments<br />
Co-opted as desirable. / 4 </p>
<p>While both Governments would clearly be equal partners in<br />
such a working party, it would be necessary that one<br />
member be designated as Chairman in order to assist the<br />
prompt and orderly despatch of business. I suggest that the<br />
Chairmanship might lie with the Commonwealth.<br />
As to reporting by the working party to our respective<br />
Governments I would assumre that, where matters are agreed by<br />
officials on both sides, a joint report to us would be<br />
appropriate. Where matters cannot be agreed at working party<br />
level, it would of course be for the officers to seek further<br />
instructions from their respective Governments.<br />
Substantial matters would, of course, continue to be dealt<br />
with at Head of Government or Ministerial level as appropriate.<br />
I would appreciate your early reaction to the proposals I<br />
have put fLorward in this letter.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
R. J. L. Hawke<br />
The Hon. R. T. Gray, MHlA<br />
Premier of Tasmania<br />
HOBART TAS 7000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
