<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7685</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF CONFERENCE WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT, 20 JULY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007685.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEWS WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT,<br />
JULY 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
LYNEHAM: Mr Hawke, thanks for joining us.<br />
HAWKE: Thanks Paul.<br />
LYNEHAM: How much of today was about saving the environment<br />
and how much of it was about winning green votes to save the<br />
Government? PM: All of it was about saving the environment. I believe<br />
that when the election has come, that the people of<br />
Australia as far as they take the environment into account<br />
will give us the marks, not just because of today, but we<br />
have been an environmentally conscious and active government<br />
since day one. We saved the Franklin. If the people<br />
represented by Senator Puplick had been in and had their<br />
way, the Franklin would be dammed. Every nomination that<br />
we've made for the world Heritage List was opposed by the<br />
Puplick crowd, all of them. They have been anti-government,<br />
anti-environment, on every issue. So we will be judged not<br />
as a government which made a statement today on 20 July, but<br />
as a government which has been judged by the international<br />
body advising the World Heritage Commission that's the<br />
International Union for the Conservation of Nature and<br />
natural resources. They have said that no government, no<br />
government in the world has done more to advance<br />
environmental issues under the world Heritage Convention<br />
than the Australian Government.<br />
LYNEHA4: Well Rick Farley in Adelaide. It's all very well<br />
for the farmers to be getting involved now when they've got<br />
a few dolars in their pockets, prices are good. What<br />
happens though if bad times return to the bush?<br />
FARLEY: Well farmers I think, are commited to a land ethic.<br />
I think that's rapidly developing throughout Australia<br />
because even before today's statement, hundreds of Landcare<br />
and voluntary groups have been formed from the Kimberleys<br />
right down to Tasmania.<br />
LYNEHAM: But they bashed the country around a bit in past<br />
generations, haven't they?<br />
FARLEY: Sure. If we'd known then what we know now I'm sure<br />
things would've been done differently. That's not only for<br />
agriculture, it applies to a whole range of different<br />
industries. I think what we've got to do now is look to the<br />
future, not into the past.<br />
LYNEHAN: And now they see it very much in their own self<br />
interest to look after that land better, do they? </p>
<p>-2-<br />
FARLEY: Very, very clearly because the economic imperative<br />
is increasingly apparent. We're losing productivity as a<br />
result of land degredation and I think one of the great<br />
things about the Prime Minister's statement today is that<br />
there is a long term commitment so that farmers now can<br />
undertake long term planning.<br />
LYNEHAM: Phillip Toyne, tell us about this extraordinary<br />
alliance between the farmers and the greenies. I mean, many<br />
farmers think of the greenies as greenless, many greenies<br />
think of farmers as rednecks don't they? I mean, are they<br />
really comfortable in bed together?<br />
TOYNE: Well as a form of necessity. I think we both<br />
realise as groups that if we've got a problem that's so<br />
widespread, so chronic, that's going to be so costly to<br />
repair, then we've both got a very strong interest in seeing<br />
that it happens. It seemed to me and it seemed to Rick<br />
Farley that the best way to go was to combine forces and to<br />
make sure that it did happen.<br />
LYNEHAM: Which meant this sort of consensus that is<br />
politically irresistible to a man like Bob Hawke?<br />
TOYNE: Absolutely. I think that the Prime minister was<br />
extremely sensible, extremely visionary in accepting such an<br />
arrangement and his statement today will be well remembered<br />
for the land management package that he announced today. I<br />
mean, it was an exciting package to the extent that it was<br />
the first time, I think, that a Federal Government has<br />
really attempted to grapple effectively with the issues of<br />
economic development and environmental sustainability. I'm<br />
excited by that. We had our criticisms of the package but<br />
by and large I see it as a very positive step.<br />
LYNEHAM: Well, Mr Hawke, it's a good idea to see the<br />
bureaucracy using recycled paper. What about your own<br />
household though at the Lodge. Are you changing things<br />
there at all?<br />
PM: we are looking at what we can do as individuals, not<br />
only in regard to paper but, for instance, in the area of<br />
the pressure packs and so on. We're getting rid of those<br />
and they will be banned by legislation completely, I hope,<br />
within five years. But yes, we're going to look at what we<br />
can do. It's not going to be just words, it's action as far<br />
as we're concerned.<br />
LYNEHAM: perhaps recycled paper in the Prime<br />
Ministerial loo?<br />
PM: Well I'd like to see that, yes.<br />
LYNEHAM: The compost heap, is there one at the Lodge?<br />
PM: Yes there is. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
LYNEHAM: Is there a brick in the cistern?<br />
PM: brick in the cistern?<br />
LYNEHAM: Well it's supposed to save water isn't it?<br />
PM: Is that right? Well, I'll have to talk to the people<br />
in charge there and see about that.<br />
LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, given that the States have control<br />
of the coastal zone, is there very much the Commonwealth can<br />
do? PM: There are various things we can and will do. Firstly<br />
we've, as you know, referred to the Resource Assessment<br />
Commission the whole question of the coastal zone and we'll<br />
seek to involve all the States in the terms of reference so<br />
that all levels of government will be involved<br />
LYNEHAM: It's like a big stocktaking exercise is it?<br />
PM: Well, yes but it's an important thing to do. Secondly,<br />
we've established a national working group on coastal<br />
management which again will involve all groups the<br />
environmental groups, tourist industry and governments. We<br />
want to get this thing settled and work through an<br />
acceptable way, via the process of concensus. But let me<br />
say this, that the Commonwealth does have powers in regard<br />
to the corporations and it does have a corporation power and<br />
I'm not holding that up as a threat. But if the processes<br />
of consensus were not to work and you were to get something<br />
which was aggreviously unacceptable, then the corporation<br />
power and the foreign investment power would be available as<br />
a last resort. But obviously I think the Australian people,<br />
Paul, overwhelmingly would want the State Governments to<br />
accept their responsibilities in these matters, to follow<br />
the lead that we as a Commonwealth Government are giving.<br />
LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, on another Tasmanian issue the<br />
CSIRO report today on pulp mill standards. Bill Paisley of<br />
North Broken Hill says it vindicates the Wesley Vale<br />
proposal and he wants to see that back on track within 12<br />
months or so.<br />
PM: I don't think there'll be a mill at Wesley Vale. Let<br />
me remind you what CSIRO told us, and it was the basis upon<br />
which we made the decision we did. They said that the<br />
proposal there which would involve the pumping into the<br />
ocean each day of 13 tonnes of organochlorides was not<br />
acceptable. That's a view which I share. On the question<br />
of pulp mills our position is and I think with respect to<br />
our friends in the green movement, they have never, as I<br />
understand it, said, ' no pulp mills'. But what they have<br />
said, I think responsibly is, ' only pulp mills if you have<br />
acceptable environmental standards'. What we are going to<br />
do is to ensure that there are created national guidelines </p>
<p>-4-<br />
in regard to these matters which will ensure that the<br />
standards are acceptable. It may be that in Tasmania you<br />
could have a pulp mill but not on the Wesley Vale site<br />
pumping that 13 tonnes a day into the ocean. You may at<br />
another environmentally acceptable site, and with<br />
environmentally acceptable standards of operation, you may<br />
be able to do it.<br />
LYNEHA4: Let's go to Sydney now and the Opposition<br />
spokesman on the environment, Senator Chris Puplick.<br />
Senator, should there be a pulp mill at Wesley Vale?<br />
PUPLICK: I don't think that's the important environmental<br />
issue Paul. I think that that's just a side track on this<br />
particular issue.<br />
LYNEHAM: ( inaudible)<br />
PUPLICK: If you want to talk about the CSIRO you can<br />
talk about why it is with all of this research that CSIRO<br />
has now got to do as a result of this package, the Hawke<br />
Government has cut CSIRO funding by 32% over five years. If<br />
there's going to be all this money for foreign aid to deal<br />
with those questions, why in fact it's cut foreign aid from<br />
down to 0.3% of GDP. Why don't you get on to the<br />
substantive issues about soil and water quality matters<br />
which really are important in this debate.<br />
LYNEHA4: Alright, if you don't want to talk about Wesley<br />
Vale, let's talk about today's statement. What's the<br />
Opposition's reaction to it?<br />
PUPLICK: As far as the Government's decision to build on<br />
the soil conservation program introduced by the previous<br />
coalition government, and the national tree program<br />
introduced by the previous coalition government, we welcome<br />
those initiatives. But let me say in terms of one of the<br />
water quality management problems that the first act<br />
undertaken by the Hawke Government in May 1983 was to cut<br />
out the waters program introduced by the Fraser Government<br />
which within the five years from there on would've spent<br />
$ 640 million on improving water quality and water management<br />
in Australia. Now that was the first thing that the Hawke<br />
Government cut out when it came to office. cutting back<br />
all of the areas which are important and just relying on<br />
more studies, another one on coastal management when in fact<br />
we've already got a report down which'tells us what needs to<br />
be done there, no targets about Greenhouse gas emission, no<br />
ban on ozone depleting substances and this nonsense about<br />
World Heritage listing when you bear in mind that in fact it<br />
was our previous government that entered the first five<br />
places on the World Heritage list.<br />
LYNEHAM: Senator, very briefly, what did you think of Sir<br />
Ninian Stephen's appointment? </p>
<p>PUPLICK: I welcomed Sir Ninian's appointment. He is a most<br />
distinguished and emminent Australian. I'm sure he will do<br />
a brilliant job for Australia. we look forward to working<br />
with him in government.<br />
LYNEHAM: Thanks very much. Mr Hawke, if you have to rely<br />
on discussion with the States, without using the external<br />
affairs powers or without the extra powers you would have<br />
from the referendum, in the end what can you do except write<br />
them cheques?<br />
PM: Let me point out Paul that it's not a question of just<br />
talking with the States. We have overridden the States. We<br />
overrode the States in respect of the Franklin River. I<br />
remind you. Puplick's people condemned my Government for<br />
saving the Franklin. If they'd been in power the Franklin<br />
would be dammed. Now, we overrode them. We overrode the<br />
Queensland Government in regard to the Daintree Forest. I<br />
much prefer because it's my nature, you know that I much<br />
prefer concensus<br />
LYNEHAM: like that referendum. If you thought you<br />
could pull it off, wouldn't you?<br />
PM: Absolutely. There'd be no question about that. If in<br />
fact the Australian people could come to an understanding<br />
that the sorts of issues with which we are dealing are ones<br />
which in the end, many of them are global in nature and<br />
therefore require a national involvement and other issues<br />
just take no notice of State boundaries. There is a need<br />
for that sort of power. The responsibility is upon these<br />
people, our political opponents who have opposed us on every<br />
issue where we've saved the environment. If they would join<br />
us in helping to create a climate of opinion and support a<br />
referendum we would have one.<br />
LYNEHAM: Let's go back to Adelaide now. Lachlan MacIntosh,<br />
the mining Industy Council. If the farmers can get together<br />
with the greenies, why can't the miners?<br />
MacIntosh: There's no reason why they can't. There's been<br />
plenty of opportunities in the past and there has been<br />
discussions in the past. But I think the issue is really<br />
one of co-operation with all parties, not just, if you like,<br />
greenies and industrialists. I think the Prime Minister<br />
today has actually talked about some new mechanisms, new<br />
consultative mechanisms which he talked about before. we<br />
would like to see those happen. The sooner they happen then<br />
everybody will get round and talk about the real issues.<br />
That's the important one and I think the other important<br />
thing today is the global nature of the problem. There is a<br />
lot industry can do and will do in improving environmental<br />
management and a lot of technologies that can be exchanged<br />
between the different groups between the farming groups<br />
and the industry groups. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
LYNEHA4: Are you worried that the coastal zone study of<br />
resources might put some of the sand miners in jeopardy?<br />
MACINTOSH: I don't think so. I think they would welcome<br />
the opporutunity to put their case openly and honestly to<br />
the RAC because that's an appropriate body for that to be<br />
done. I was there yesterday at Stradbroke Island. There is<br />
an enormous amount of restoration technology available which<br />
could be useful in other parts of the coast.<br />
LYNEHA4: And your reaction to the fact that the Prime<br />
minister did not set firm limits on Greenhouse gas<br />
emissions? You'd be pleased about that wouldn't you?<br />
MACINTOSH: He might not have set clear targets but he's<br />
actually talked about the problem. I think that's important<br />
because it's no good saying in Australia that we take a<br />
level that's important perhaps in Europe. It's important to<br />
look in more detail at can we use our coal better here in<br />
Australia LYNEHAM: Not a global problem?<br />
MACINTOSH: It is a global problem but the CO2 issue is not<br />
necessarily the only issue. Setting a target to reduce here<br />
will mean no new power stations, no new jobs and perhaps no<br />
new processing plants. That's not what we want to do here.<br />
We are a developing country, not a developed country.<br />
LYNEHAM: So you want to see more downstream processing,<br />
don't you?<br />
MACINTOSH: I think that's what everyone in Australia does.<br />
Then we can afford to pay for the large amounts of money we<br />
need to redress the past problems in the environment.<br />
LYNEHA4: If we process here they won't be processed<br />
somewhere else.<br />
MACINTOSH: People need the minerals in the world. We all<br />
need them. You need them for your television screen<br />
tonight. People need those minerals, not only here but in<br />
the developing world generally. It's the important<br />
technology we can develop here in Australia if we do more<br />
processing. If we don't do it someone else will do it.<br />
LYNEHAM: Thanks very much for your time. Mr Hawke, any<br />
final comments?<br />
PM: Just on this last issue. Let me say it is right that<br />
there can be discussions between our friends in the mining<br />
industry and our friends in the environmental movement and<br />
ourselves. Don't let's just blacken the mining industry<br />
overall. I think there is now in the mining industry,<br />
compared with earlier days, a greater sense of understanding<br />
of their responsibility. On this final issue that you've </p>
<p>-7-<br />
talked about, about the levels. We accept our<br />
responsibility to play our part within the international<br />
context to work for a reduction of emission of gases. What<br />
Lachlan is talking about is that we are more efficient users<br />
of energy than most other countries. In terms of an overall<br />
global level, enterprise in Australia relatively is more<br />
likely to have a lower level of emission than in other<br />
places. So what we've got to do is to look at what we can<br />
do there and what we can do in other areas It's not<br />
only CO2there's methane, and there's a lot we can do in<br />
that area. our responsibility.<br />
LYNEHAM: Time's got away from us. Thanks to all our guests<br />
for joining us tonight. That's it. See you tomorrow night.<br />
PM: Thank you Paul.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
