<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2503</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE NATIONAL JEWISH MEMORIAL CENTRE - CANBERRA - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON - 13 DECEMBER 1971</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002503.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF THE NATIONAL JEWISH MEMORIAL CENTE<br />
CANBERRA<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
13 December, 1971.<br />
Mr. Jacobson, Your Excellencies, Distinguished Guests, Ladies<br />
and Gentlemen-, This afternoon we are about to add something to the<br />
history of Canberra and something of enduring importance to the<br />
vast panorama of the Jewish story in Australia.<br />
I wonder if I could, with some architectural licence<br />
considerable licence in fact describe this fine new building as<br />
a pillar. I do so because I see it as a pillar of faith in our<br />
national capital. A pillar of faith which will stand for a long,<br />
long time,. as the national centre of Australian Jewry the first<br />
of its kind and as a meeting place, a House of . worship, a school<br />
and a memorial to Jews who died for Australia.<br />
I sometimes think we miss the sight of history in the<br />
making whken we get mixed up in the process oursel-es on a summer<br />
afternoop in Canberra with familiar sights and familiar faces around<br />
US. But history this is, and my wife and I are h1onoured be with<br />
you on this very special occasion. I'm afraid we arc both ' oing to<br />
make speeches. We each know what the other is going to say and as<br />
I'm speaking first I have to be careful to keep in my own corner,<br />
Sir, I think it is almost ten years since the foundation<br />
stone was laid here by Rabbi Brodie, Chief Rabbi at that time, you<br />
have built well as the result of your own energetic fund-raising and,<br />
I understand, some help from friondly governments. The Commonwealth's<br />
corntribution to this centre.. as you know, is a perpctual lease of the<br />
land for a rental of ten cents a yaar on demand. To my knowledge the<br />
demand has never been made, nor likely to be, it's just one of those<br />
curious things put in to make overything look legal. All this<br />
having been said, I do congratulate those who havc worked so hard to<br />
make this Centre. You should bc well content and very proud. It is<br />
a handsome addition to the buildings in Canberra and, as I said, at<br />
the beginning, it is -a pillar of faith in our midst.<br />
Jewry has won an honoured and permanent place in<br />
Australia and I am proud to be Primo Minister in a country where<br />
bigotry is at a discount and where Australians accept each other<br />
for what they are. We are not troubled by what each man's faith<br />
might be or what form t4-he worship of his God might take. And I<br />
take this opportunity of acknowledging here what the Jewish community<br />
has done for Australia. It is to the la~ sting credit of the Jewish people and it<br />
is evidence of the durability of the spiritual values which bind them<br />
together that they have maintained their identity no matter where<br />
they have been born or where they have settled. ./ 2 </p>
<p>They have done this in Australia and their integration<br />
in the Australian community is complete. The Jewish community in<br />
Australia has given much to the development of an. Australian culture<br />
by the infusion of elements of their own rich, rare culture. And<br />
its members are sharing, very fully, in Australia's great effort at<br />
nation-building. I take just two names among many from the list of<br />
distinguished Jews who have brought honour to Australia. The late<br />
Sir Isaac Isaacs, our first Australian-born Governor-General and the<br />
late General Sir John Monash who led us in the first great war and<br />
gave so much of his talents to works of peace in this country when<br />
the battles were won. We remember them today because they were big<br />
men who thought and acted in a big way. They were national in their<br />
outlook and in their achievements.<br />
I think, too, gn this occasion, it is right that wt<br />
should pay our tribute to the fortitude of the Jewish people in<br />
Israel who press on with nation-building though the shadows of war<br />
lie always along their frontiers.<br />
There are three things, I think we should remember<br />
about Israeli-<br />
The first That Isreal came to be because of the courage of<br />
its people.<br />
And the determination of a majority of nations that<br />
the Jews shQuld be free, independent and able to live<br />
in the land of their fathers.<br />
Through its active membership of the United Nations<br />
Palestine Commission and the General Assembly, Australia<br />
helped to make this possible.<br />
The second That forbearance, courage, resolution and industry have<br />
made a nation in a timeless desert.<br />
And by that result the world is reminded once again<br />
that there are few limits to what men and women can do,<br />
given freedom and faith.<br />
and<br />
The third That the future holds a tremendous challenge for<br />
Israel, for other countries of the Middle East and<br />
indeed for us all. A challenge which has its dangers<br />
as well as its opportunities.<br />
Sir, there is much in common between cur two countries<br />
and in many ways we have faced the same hazards of nature in nationbuilding.<br />
It is distressing that tho issues which divide Israel<br />
from its Arab neighbours, with all of'whom Australia enjoys friendly<br />
relations, have not yet been resolved.<br />
The Australian Government is convinced of the need for<br />
a settlement which ensures the sovereignty, independence and<br />
territorial integrity of Israel and all other states in the Middle<br />
East. Without that there can be no lasting peace.<br />
Sir, this year international attention is being focussed<br />
through the United Nations on prejudice and discrimination on racial<br />
grounds. </p>
<p>My Government has strongly supported, in the United<br />
Nations and elsewhere, the riahts of peoole, including minorities,<br />
to freedom from fear and suspicion-without distinction as to race,<br />
language or religion.--In the United Nations last month, we again urged, as<br />
we have in earlier years, that Governments which find it difficult<br />
to eliminate prejudice against, for example, Jewish minorities,<br />
should at least allow those people to emigrate if they desire to do<br />
so. We hold strongly to the belief that people should be<br />
able, both in law and in practice, to pursue their cultural and<br />
religious heritage and traditions as they wish. This national<br />
centre, this -pillar of faith, reflects that belief. It expresses,<br />
too, in a noble form the confidence of the Jewish people that while<br />
their ancient homeland lies faraway along the Jord7. n, they have a<br />
home here where they are part of one people inhabiting one continent.<br />
And where Australians of every faith and persuasion are free to walk<br />
the ways of peace together.<br />
Now Mr. Jacobson, Ladies and Gentlemen, I understand<br />
I am to unveil the plaque and n-. mo this building. I am delighted<br />
to do so, and I name this building " The Mona and Louis Klein<br />
Building". </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
