<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3904</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT HIGH COURT PLAQUE UNVEILING, CANBERRA 29 SEPTEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003904.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT 2<br />
HIGH COURT PLAQUE UNVEILING,<br />
CANBERRA, 29 SEPTEMBER ] 975<br />
Mr Minister, Chief Justice, Your Honours, Your<br />
Excellencies, Ladies arnd Gentlemen.<br />
Today for the first time in Au * stralia's history<br />
the High Court of Australia is sitting in Canberra: the<br />
Chief Justice and all the Judges. And on a day like this<br />
it's well to recall how-nobly they have fulfilled one of<br />
their tenets:<br />
Let justice be done even though it Pours,<br />
But take good heart because on this site, one<br />
of Australia's national capital's great buildings will arise.<br />
There will be proper accommodation for the Supreme Court of<br />
this country, and for all those who have business before it.<br />
It may be difficult to envisage, in this tent today,<br />
that the ; public hall of the High Court of Australia, on this<br />
site, will be nearly 80 feet high I was told 24 metres higrh.<br />
Orlas you might expect me to say, 2.4 decamnetres. We've had to<br />
wait three quarters of a century to inaugurate the principal<br />
seat of the High Court of Australia at the seat of Government.<br />
Right from the beginning when the first, one of the greatest<br />
Attorneys-Genera, first introduced the legislation for the<br />
High Court, the Judiciary Act of 1903, it took a long time<br />
to get that piece of legislation through; several sessions<br />
in fact. But, in fact, it did finally get through both Houses.<br />
And right from the outset it was laid down that the principal<br />
geat of the High Court shall be at the seat of Government.<br />
Now, until 1927 they both were seated in Melbourne.<br />
And then the Goverrmient came to Canberra, and now we are<br />
making it possible for the High Court's principal seat to<br />
come to Canberra also.<br />
There are four great pillars of Australia's<br />
constitutional structure. The Constitution says, there<br />
shall be a Federal Executive; there shall be a Federal<br />
Parliament; there shall be a Federal Supreme Court of<br />
Australia, known as the High Court; there shall be an<br />
Interstate Commission. Now ' three, soon, will be<br />
seated in Canberra. Throughout the English speaking world the High<br />
Court of Australia is acknowledged as without superior in<br />
the common law. The Judges who serve there are quoted<br />
increasingly everywhere where the common law has been<br />
inherited as it has been in Australia. I make that commnent<br />
because it is well to recall how much of the business of tChe<br />
High Court; how much of the business that citizens bring<br />
before the High Court, is of the same nature as has been<br />
transacted before English Courts for centuries.. And the<br />
High Court of Australia has contributed to the elucidation<br />
and the development of the common law as much as any court<br />
in the world in this century. ./ 2 </p>
<p>We naturally, in public life, are preoccupied<br />
with the functions of the High Court as a Constitutional Court,<br />
following, of course, the Supreme Court of the United StatCes,<br />
the Supreme Court of Canada and followed, in turn, by the<br />
Supreme Court of India, and the Constitutional Court of West<br />
Germany. Because in Australia, as in the other Federal<br />
Democracies in the world, it has been thought proper that<br />
disputes, which inevitably arise, should be settled in the<br />
rational, properly argued atmosphere of court proceedings.<br />
Here I quote Professor-La Nauze's biography of<br />
Deakin: to explain it, the drive which Deakin brought to his<br />
grand design of having a High Court of Australia established<br />
right from the beginning of our Federation. So many people<br />
thought that it could be put off for years. But not Deakin,<br />
because to quote La Nauze, Deakin believed that:<br />
.1<br />
" without the authority of the High Court the<br />
Commonwealth would be in constant danger from the<br />
forces of provincialism. It was not that he<br />
expected from a High Court judgments which would<br />
0 necessarily favour the Commonwealth at the expense<br />
of the States. What was essential was that<br />
disputes between them should from the earliest<br />
years views of the Federation be examined and<br />
finally settled by a Court, and in a mental<br />
atmosphere, free from provincial association."<br />
I menti'on one other Chief Justice, the present<br />
Chief Justice. It came as no surprise to me, in the Parliament<br />
that Sir Garfield Barwick who had already proved himself a very<br />
great builder when he was the doyen of the profession in Australia<br />
beca'use those of us who then practised at the Sy dney Bar would<br />
remember, with gratitude, how much our-accommodation was improved<br />
because he devoted himself to seeing that the profession was<br />
adequately housed. Without him I doubt if there would have been<br />
adequate Inns foi barristers in Sydney or in due course in<br />
0 Melbourne or elsewhere in Australia. And the Chief Justice, of<br />
course, had the idea that in Sydney the Australian Government<br />
and the New South Wales Government should co-operate in<br />
establishing new courts, so that the public would not be confused<br />
by a dividing, and divided apparently unco-ordinated judicial<br />
system but he has for long been working for the High Court to<br />
be properly housed in its proper seat in Canberra, in a building<br />
worthy of the Supreme Courts, th Constitutional Courts of<br />
common law countries and of federal democracies.<br />
In October 1973,. he was one of the assessors to<br />
choose the successful architects. And on 8 October 1973 he and<br />
I announced the winners. And I think I must say, and in this I<br />
would be supported by the National Capital Development Commission,<br />
and a very great number of people in the profession, as well as<br />
in the administration, that since then Sir Garfield has been<br />
unremitting in seeing that this building proceeded. And I don't<br />
really believe that the plans could have been so far advanced but<br />
for the pressure, completely proper pressure, which he has brought<br />
to bear upon me in this way. </p>
<p>The building will be a noble one. It may not be as<br />
noble as the Chief Justice might have aspired to have it. But<br />
it's the best that the country can produce or afford and it will<br />
be in a splendid setting, it will be a worthy home for our<br />
Court which stands at the peak of our national judicial system.<br />
And all of us, I believe, on this occasion should pay tribute<br />
to those who over the decades have sought to have this court<br />
in Canberra. And not least to the Chief Justice and the present<br />
Justices who have spurred us to see that within not so many years<br />
three or four the principal seat of the High Court, a noble seat,<br />
will be at the seat of Government. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
