<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>696</transcript-id>
    <title>THE AUSTRALIAN ASSOCIATION OF BRITISH MANUFACTURES LUNCHEON HELD AT MELBOURNE ON 28TH FEBRUARY 1963 SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/02/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000696.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE AUS TRAL IAN ASSOCIATION OF BRITISH MAI\ 7[ TFCTERSI,<br />
LTffHTFON HE7. LDfA T MEL1O~ TH FFBR1ARY%-<br />
Speech by the PrIme Ministre th e Rt. Hon, R. G. Menzie s<br />
I usually begin a speech by saying " Sir", but<br />
today I am going right back to the grass-roots and therefore<br />
I say, Mr. Chairman, my Lords we have a couple of them here<br />
today Mr. High Commissioner, Mr. Ferguson and the rest of you<br />
I was delighted to hear from my old friend, Mr. Hawker, about the<br />
exhibit at the International Fair and to listen to his trailer<br />
is that the expression? of those things that are to come.<br />
And as a matter of fact, if I live so long and endure so long<br />
and there is enough time available, I am going with my Lord<br />
Simon afterwards to have a quick look at the British exhibit.<br />
I think you will all agree that as an honest broker<br />
I am placed in a somewhat difficult position today. I walked in<br />
and the first man I met was an arrant free-trader. i refrain<br />
from mentioning his name. And the next man I walked into was Tom<br />
Ramsay the President of the Australian Chamber of Manufacturers.<br />
And all my instincts, all my political instincts, said to me,<br />
" Laddie, this is the time to got out". But I was blocked in my<br />
retreat by two waiters, each of them oddly enough offering me a<br />
drink. And so I remained,<br />
But then I got a little comfort out of remembering<br />
that I had been provided by somebody with a little piece of<br />
paper about this Assotuiation and it recalled to my mind that one<br />
of your objectives is " to encourage reciprocal trade." Now, this<br />
is something frequently overlooked. i am sure that there were a<br />
lot of people who, looking on at Tariff Board proceedings and<br />
seeing over a long term of years the devoted and talented work of<br />
Mr. Ferguson, would regard him superficially as the enemy of<br />
Australian manufacturing. And of course that is quite wrong.<br />
There may be a lot of people who think that Australian manufacturers,<br />
who have so great and increasing a part to play in<br />
national development are to be regarded as the opponents of all<br />
imports of any kind Ircm other counmtries. Both of those conceptions<br />
are grievously wrong. And it is all summed up in the<br />
expression in your own objectives about encouragement of<br />
reciprocal trade. Now Sir,~ you concern us when I say " you" I am<br />
referring to the Issociation, bigoted fellows like yourself and<br />
others somewhat mere broadminded whom I see around me but you<br />
concern us I do not mean you alarm us, but you interest us<br />
you are our concern in at last two ways. And perhaps I might<br />
just state them almost categorically. First of all, without<br />
growing exports of British manufacturers from Great Britain and<br />
a correspondingly sound balance of trade and payments for Great<br />
Britain, Great Britain, either in or out of the Common Market,<br />
will have great difficulty in sustaining her economic and<br />
financial strength and with them her enormolus significance in<br />
the whole modern world. We all realise this, We rather thrive<br />
on differences in Australia. I remember one time when Winston<br />
Churchill said about us in a speech of his,," Ah, in Australia<br />
they conduct their politics with a fine 18h century vigour." 1<br />
And that is quite true; we thrive on differences. I do not<br />
thinik I would have lived as long as I have without them.<br />
But let us not so much enjoy our differences as to<br />
forget all the things that we have in common. And one of the<br />
things we all have in coramon hero today is that Great Britain<br />
must be and remain and increasingly be a powerful community in<br />
this world. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I know that some clever fellow in some English newspaper<br />
will once more accuse me of being sentimental. All right,<br />
I an, I an. But this is more than sentiment. Every consideration,<br />
not only of sentiment, but of self-interest, requires<br />
that we in Australia, the old Dominion, should believe, and<br />
believe in our hearts and in our minds that is even more<br />
important that Great Britain must continue to be strong for<br />
the good of the world. And therefore Great Britain must manufacture<br />
and she must export. We realise that. Indeed, we know<br />
that in this modern and highly complex world, with challenges<br />
around every corner, a new challenge almost every month, trade<br />
with Groat Britain for us in Australia remains essential.<br />
There aru a few people in Great Britain some of them highly<br />
placed who have yet to learn the massive extent of the trade<br />
between this country and Great Britain. Some of then, indeed,<br />
have yet to remember or to be told that over a considerable<br />
time of years now, when our own secondary industry had been<br />
developing apace, Great Britain has had. in terms of commodities,<br />
a highly favourable balance of trade with this country. And<br />
we have found in Great Britain our greatest single market.<br />
These things are not to be overlooked. New markets<br />
yes, we need. Groat Britain is searching for themn The whole<br />
strategic approach, as far as I understand it, of the Common<br />
Market negotiations was to develop new and enlarged markets for<br />
the products of British industry. And we ourselves cannot live<br />
on old markets. Wo may improve then, we may nurse them with<br />
jealous care, but we must develop new markets. Because this<br />
is a challenging world, The one thing that I want to say<br />
about that is that I hope that none of us will fail to remember<br />
that new markets are best when they are added to old markets and<br />
not when they are subtracted from them,<br />
Now, Sir, there is another thing that I would like to<br />
say to you. Is there as some people have thought, a necessary<br />
conflict between the British manufacturer and the Australian<br />
manufacturer? ( I apologies for my terminology because most<br />
of my life I have been explaining to people that we are British,<br />
but still these modern terms become very difficult. I remember<br />
a very distinguished British Minister once in Australia saying,<br />
" Would you think it wrong if we referred to ourselves as the<br />
British Government? It is so tiresome to say we are the U. K,<br />
Government, We will have to be calling ourselves the U. oK-ites<br />
like the Hittites and the Malachites, and this really will not<br />
do." I concede the point, this is purely for purposes of<br />
argument that I refer to the Fritish and to the Australian.)<br />
But is there a necessary conflict? And of course the answer<br />
is obviously " no" o<br />
Perhaps the answer needs a little elaboration. And<br />
the first piece of elaboration is one at which I have already<br />
hinted, All the history of modern times in Australia has shown<br />
that the more we have become industrialised, the greater has<br />
been our appetite for import; that the more we produce ourselves<br />
and the more we raise our own standards of living in Australia,<br />
the greater is our capacity for buying the products of other<br />
countries. And, indeed, as I have said to you we have bought<br />
more from Great Britain, talking in terms of commodities than<br />
Groat Britain has found it possible to buy from us. But this<br />
is not to be judged on a merely bilateral basis. This is to<br />
be judged on a multilateral basis, when you consider the state<br />
of affairs in the world. And whenever we feel a little<br />
disturbed, if we do, about this kind of thing, the more we<br />
have to remember that over the last decade, for example, when<br />
S0000... 0/ 3<br />
L </p>
<p>-3<br />
our manufactures have developed, when our imports have<br />
increased, when we have had some imbalance in commodity<br />
trade with Great Britain, wie have at the same time been<br />
enjoying an enormous national growth. which is vital to us;<br />
we have had massive immigration, much of it from the Old<br />
Country; we have had growing employment and we have had an<br />
investment of overseas capital in Australia which some people<br />
appear to believe comes almost entirely from the United<br />
States, but which in fact has come mostly from Great Britain.<br />
I was looking over the figures which some industrious<br />
member of my staff produced about our trade, because you know<br />
at a solemn gathering like this they do not think much of you<br />
unle-ss you quote a few figures and I am not, as a rule, very<br />
much in favour of doing that. But I did notice that although<br />
there has boen large importation into Australia, inevitably<br />
because, among others, our own manufacturers need them of<br />
commodities of metals, metal manufactures, machines and<br />
machinery, I regretted to observe that over the last ten<br />
years the percentage of these things coming to us from Great<br />
Britain has fallen. Not our total imports of such mattersthey<br />
have risen but the percentage from British sources<br />
has fallen. And I found myself asking, impertinently you<br />
may say, whether this argued some lack of enterprise in the<br />
Old Country, because believe me we noed an awful lot of<br />
enterprise here and Great Britain nee; ds an awful lot of<br />
enterprise if, in this complex world, with all sorts of<br />
doubtful things and uncertain factors, never more uncertain<br />
than they are at present on the fringes of Europe, you need<br />
and we need a tremendous development of enterprise and of<br />
ingenuity. I suppose that we are all, except on polling day,<br />
a little conservative. 1-can remember a time, not so very<br />
long ago when, if I encountered a British motorcar mianufacturer<br />
in England, ha took me on one side and lectured me' in<br />
an almost fatherly mannor on the wickedness of the very idea<br />
of Australia manufacturing a motor car. -tVhy don't you take<br />
what we give you, they are the best in the world." This is<br />
splendid, but it is no wray to conquer a world market. And,<br />
of course, as the cvents have shown, thuy were wrong.<br />
We are all a little disposed, are we not, to think<br />
that what we have made in the past an~ d sold in the past ought<br />
to be good enough for the future. We in Australia leok out<br />
on the enormous potential of the Asian market, the market of<br />
South West Pacific; but I suppose we are always tempted to<br />
sa-y, " Well, what vio make is so and so; why cannot we sell<br />
that?" Whereas the truth may be, and I am sure it is, that<br />
in all tthe business of manufacturing, whether it is here or<br />
in Great Britain, the constant search rm. ust be to see whether<br />
we can't produce something that these people who are so odd<br />
that they do not belong to our race or community would like to<br />
buy. And this is not just market research, this is actual<br />
research in productive techniques and in determining the<br />
matters to be produced.<br />
Look, we havo the job in front of us, a heavy job,<br />
a marvellous job if we can achieve it, a productive job, a<br />
job that will assure the powerful future of the Mother Country<br />
and support Ia rate of national growth in Australia that will<br />
be the wonder of our grandchildren. This is of tremendous<br />
importance. We miust do what we can to develop our trade by<br />
developing our idea-s and developing and diversifying our<br />
products. 006000060/ </p>
<p>1+<br />
The day has gone by for saying, " Well, we stand for<br />
this or this or this, come and get it and if you do not like<br />
it well, all the worse luck for you," I am sure that this is<br />
well in the minds of the members of this Association. I am<br />
sure that it is well in the minds of the manufacturers of<br />
Australia. Because if there are two things that are completely<br />
obvious to anybody, they are these, that it would be quite<br />
idle for British manufacturers to resist or resent the development<br />
of efficient Australian manufacturing, because that is<br />
essential to Australian growth. We can have no migration<br />
program without ito We can have no developmental program for<br />
the future without it. We cannot have full employment without<br />
it. It is essential to Australian growth that we should<br />
develop efficient Australian manufacturing. And I am sure<br />
that every man who represents Great Britain realises that to<br />
the full. Because of course unless Australia can grow and<br />
become stronger an more populous and more powerful then our<br />
contribution to the Commonwealth of which Great Britain is<br />
the centre, will be correspondingly diminished. It is therefore<br />
essential that we should grow and be strong.<br />
But equally, it would be a great mistake for<br />
Australian manufacturers to think in terms of a closed economy.<br />
I have struck a few troglcdytes here and there who really<br />
seem to me to believe in a closed economy, but not too many.<br />
They are not represented here today, Because in reality, so<br />
far from having ideas of a closed economy, or a mere prohibition<br />
against the introduction into this country of the products of<br />
others, the real vision of our industrial future must be one<br />
in which our own manufacturers find their market, not only hore,<br />
but abroad, and find their markets expanding, Because unless<br />
Australia, strategically as she is placed in the world's<br />
economy, can become a powerful supplier to other nations,<br />
then her future is cribbed, cabined and confined.<br />
And therefore we have a mutuality, do we not, of<br />
interest here the British manufacturers saying, " Te recognise<br />
the tremendous importance of the development of sound manufacturing<br />
enterprise in Australia," and Australian manufacturing<br />
on its side saying, " Yes, we recognise that but we also<br />
rocognise that our ultimate responsibility to Australia is to<br />
cater, not only for a protected market at home, but for a<br />
highly competitive market abroad." , When all these things work<br />
themselves out, we will find that, having begun by having<br />
differences, we have ended by finding a magnificent unity,<br />
I am, of course, as any of my critics could tell you,<br />
getting a bit long in the tooth; I have been in office too<br />
long; I quite agree with that, I do not want it to be used<br />
against me, but I agree with anything you care to say on those<br />
matters. But one thing I am quite sure about and that is that<br />
I shall ultimately come to the end of my course much happier<br />
if I feel that we have evolved relationships between us which<br />
have assured, not only the growth and power of the greatest<br />
country in the world, but the growth and power of what to most<br />
of us here today is the dearest country in the world,<br />
I I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
