<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3479</transcript-id>
    <title>INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION REPORT - INDUSTRIAL TRACTORS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003479.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* i) A USf K A . I A<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 379<br />
22 November 1974<br />
INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION REPORTINDUSTRIAL<br />
TRACTORS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, announced today that<br />
the Government has accepted the recommendations of the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission in its report on Industrial<br />
Tractors. The report was released on 13 August 1974.<br />
The Government's decision to implement thf! Commission's<br />
recommendations will mean that crawler tractors will continue<br />
to be dutiable at minimum rates while the General rate for<br />
other types of industri * al tractors will increase from the<br />
present rate of 15 per cent to 20 per cent.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that specified components of industrial<br />
tractors which previously were dutiable at rates different<br />
from those of the tractor unit itself will now attract the rate<br />
of duty of the tractor base.<br />
Mr Whitlam, said that for tractors forming the base for<br />
earthmoving equipment the tractor unit will be duitable at<br />
the appropriate tractor rate, but the earthmoving equipment<br />
portion would be regarded for duty purposes as earthmoving<br />
equipment. Licensing controls currently applying to imports of<br />
used, second hand and disposals equipment will continue.<br />
Mr Whitlam also mentioned that the Commission had<br />
suggested that by-law admission be granted to certain four wheei<br />
drive tractors and tractor chassis fitted with engines, and that<br />
the existing by-law treatment be continued in respect of<br />
transmissions, axles, etc. for industrial tractors. Mr Whitlam<br />
added that as the Government had been advised, since receipt<br />
of the Commission's report, of the recent commencement of<br />
production of certain four wheel drive tractors in Australia,<br />
the by-law power criterion suggested by the Commission for these<br />
tractors could be varied.<br />
A detailed statement bof the Customs tariff chanqes arising<br />
from the Government's decision will be issued by the Minister<br />
for Customs and Excise when arrangements have been finealis:-d<br />
to implement the new duty rates.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
