<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22251</transcript-id>
    <title>Honouring Australia&#039;s Anzac Heritage  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>As the nation prepares to honour our heroes in Anzac day services around the country, it gives me great pleasure to announce that the Australian War Memorial and Anzac Parade will be included in the National Heritage List.</p>
<p>Every year we remember and pay tribute to those who have contributed to the defence of our nation.   The Australian War Memorial holds a special place in commemorating the courage and sacrifice of generations of the men and women who helped defend our nation.</p>
<p> This majestic building is at the heart of our nation's ANZAC Day services, with thousands of people making an annual pilgrimage to attend the Dawn Service and marches along Anzac Parade.</p>
<p>The features of the Australian War Memorial, including the Roll of Honour, Hall of Memory, Tomb of the Unknown Solider, and the Memorials along Anzac Parade allow us to reflect on the nature and sacrifice of war and to commemorate and learn about our nation's military history.</p>
<p>C.E.W. Bean, Australia's Official First World War correspondent, began thinking about commemorating the sacrifice of Australians while he was serving at Gallipoli in 1915.  His vision was realised with the opening of the Memorial in 1941, during World War II when Australians again displayed that courage under fire.</p>
<p> This courage is eloquently illustrated in C.E.W Bean's war diaries reflecting his first hand observations and experiences in the trenches of Gallipoli.  I encourage all Australians to reflect on this important part of our national identity by accessing C.E.W Bean's diaries online at the National Library website.</p>
<p>By listing the Australian War Memorial and Anzac Parade on the National Heritage List, we recognise the courage of those who have served in our armed forces, here and overseas, in both the field of conflict and, more recently, as part of peace keeping missions in our region.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
