<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10343</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MIKE GIBSON, RADIO 2GB</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/05/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010343.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
14 May 1997 iq : H/ wv ia gov au/ prnc/ pressrcl/ gibsoii. hitnil<br />
14 May 1997<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MIKE GIBSON, RADIO 2GB<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
GIBSON: And we are talking to our Prime Minister in Canberra. John Howard, good morning.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Good morning Mike. Nice to be onl your program.<br />
GIBSON: Nice to have you. Hardly a glowing response to your Budget.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Depends who you read. That great financial writer Terry McCann thought it was terrific. People are<br />
attracted to the fact that for the first time ever a government is offering a real tax break for savings.<br />
For a long time governments have lectured Australians about the need to save. For the first time a<br />
government has put its tax incentives where its mouth's been. And that is a very good, across the<br />
board symbol to attract people to save and it's also a very good incentive. I think the other thing that<br />
people appreciate is that we inherited a deficit of $ 10.5 billion and we will have turned that into a<br />
surplus of $ 1.6 billion by the time we end our first term in government.<br />
GIBSON: We would have turned it into, not you. I mean, you're not giving us much.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, hang on, we've given you everything we said we would give you. We gave you the one, well I<br />
mean, look, the Australian taxpayers have enjoyed... it's not my money, it's our money.<br />
GIBSON:<br />
Did you give us the tax cuts you said you were going to give us?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, the $ 1 billion family tax break, delivered in full without deduction. On the I1st of July this year<br />
there will be a $ 600 million tax incentive for private health insurance. There will also be in more<br />
generous measure I might say from the 1 st of July of this year a $ 250 million capital gains tax break<br />
for small business. We have delivered our savings commitment more generously than we promised<br />
during the election campaign.<br />
I of' 6I f606/ 30/ 97 17: 35: 51 </p>
<p>14 My 197intp:// www. nia. gov. au/ pnic/ pressrel/ gibso. ltii<br />
GIBSON: Do you think this is a realistic, I mean Gareth Evans, as you of no doubt would expect, says the rebate<br />
for most people wouldn't buy a pair of socks. 1 mean, how many people have $ 60 000 saved, you<br />
know, put away in this country? How can you ever save $ 60 000?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it's not only, not only on bank savings Mike, it's on all other forms of investment. If you make a<br />
personal contribution to superannuation in respect of which you already haven't received a tax break<br />
then that is eligible. If you contribute personally to superannuation out of your after-tax income of a<br />
couple thousand dollars a year, you get the 15 per cent tax break on that contribution. If you get a<br />
rental return, you get it on that. So it's right across the board an it's uncomplicated and it's non means<br />
tested. GIBSON: Superannuation, that's a subject that's come up more than anything else in discussions this morning.<br />
Where do we stand in Australia? I mean there would be so many workers listening to you this<br />
morning, saying what's the point will I ever be able to retire to a similar lifestyle that I've enjoyed when<br />
I went to work?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the answer is under this Budget the superannuation circumstances are better. They're better<br />
because you get it, for the first time you'll have 15 per cent tax break on your own contribution. So<br />
that has got to be better. And that is enormously beneficial for a lot of women who have previously<br />
been poorly treated by superannuation. It's very valuable, the savings aspect of it is very valuable to<br />
self-funded retirees. But superannuation is certainly well supported in this Budget because on top of<br />
all the other incentives, your own personal contribution will attract the 15 per cent tax break.<br />
GIBSON: It's not a major issue to me but a lot of listeners have rung in and said why are you guy's exempt from<br />
superannuation rules, there's no suggestion that you won't be able to get out when your<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's not right. I'm sorry that rule will apply to us as well.<br />
GIBSON: Good. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It's applying across the board, that preservation rule.<br />
GIBSON: Unemployment. Besides Pauline Hanson, who we won't go into this morning because we've all had<br />
enough of her. Your biggest problem is unemployment. How will last night's Budget do anything to<br />
ease unemployment? 2 f 606/ 30/ 1977: 35: 54<br />
14 May 1997<br />
2 of 6 </p>
<p>14 ay197ttp: H/ wvw. tila. gov. au/ ptic/ pi-cssrel/ gibsoiitmi<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well it's the nations biggest challenge, I understand that. How will it help? Well to the extent that it<br />
has improved the strength of the economy it will encourage more growth. We're repaying $ 5 billion of<br />
debt this year. That means the Government is repaying debt rather than generating more debt and that<br />
will ease pressure on interest rates. The federation fund which involves the expenditure of $ 1 billion<br />
on major infrastructure projects, that will down the track have a beneficial impact on jobs. Lower<br />
interest rates, the confirmation of low rates of inflation and the promise of strong economic growth<br />
over the next two or three years. All of those things combined will create a better climate for jobs but<br />
I don't and can't promise and I never have that you can get rid of unemployment overnight. We made<br />
some changes to industrial laws which will in time help. We are endeavouring right at the moment to<br />
further liberalise the unfair dismissal laws so as to encourage small business to take on more staff but it<br />
looks as though we may be thwarted in the Senate on that because the Labor Party has said they will<br />
oppose it and if as I fear the Democrats and Senator H-arradine do the same, then my attempt to allow<br />
firms employing fewer than 15 people exemption from the unfair dismissal laws for employees<br />
employed for less than a year that, my attempt to do that will be thwarted by the Senate. Now if that<br />
happens, I'm going to put that into a Bill and send that Bill straight back to the Senate and see if they<br />
reject in the form of a Bill and then we'll see what happens.<br />
GIBSON: On the subject of unemployment though, there's been a lot of discussion again. You want people to<br />
work longer. You're telling them they can't retire till 60 at the earliest. You're offering them a sort of<br />
sugarcoated $ 20 000 to stay on until they're 70. They stay on, you get more income tax, you don't<br />
have to pay out the pension but they're in filling jobs so there must be fewer jobs for young people.<br />
PRIMVE MINISTER:<br />
No, no, well it never works like that Mike. The only way to create jobs for young people is to<br />
generate new jobs through more activity particularly in the small business sector. I think you'd know,<br />
we all know from our own work experience that somebody who's been with an organisation for a long<br />
period of time, that person is not mutually, is not interchangeable with somebody who's been there for<br />
a short period of time. They do different things. The idea that a pensioner's retirement is Howard's<br />
opportunity if we're at different ends of the age spectrum it never works like that.<br />
GIBSON: But it's the opportunity of the bloke who's underneath me to move up and the bloke who's underneath<br />
him to move up and when you down the ladder there's the bloke at the bottom who says ' hello, I've<br />
got a job'.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, but why shouldn't the bloke who's doing a perfectly good job and who's in perfectly good health<br />
and who wants to remain full-time or part-time in the workforce beyond a certain age, why shouldn't<br />
that person be encouraged to do so?<br />
GIBSON: I don't have a problem with that but there would be a lot of younger people saying ' Well, why<br />
shouldn't 1, in the bloom of my youth, be able to get a job?'. 3 f606/ 30/ 97 17: 35: 54<br />
14 May 1997<br />
3 of 6 </p>
<p>1a4y 19litip://%. iivlav gov au/ piic/ pressreVgibso. iutiii<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
But there are other ways in which you assist that to happen. You reduce the cost of employing those<br />
people, like getting rid of stupid unfair dismissal laws. That's a greater barrier to young people getting<br />
jobs than anything else. I see no mnerit in the false belief that by penalising older people, you're helping<br />
younger people, you're not. The only way to help younger people is to remove the impediments that<br />
employers now find against employing them. I get employer after employer saying to me ' Look, I'd be<br />
happy to take on young kids if I knew I wasn't going to land up in court on some unfair dismissal<br />
charge. I'd be happy if I could be free of some of red tape in employing them.' They are the things that<br />
we are endeavouring to address. And not having the pension bonus scheme, if we had not proceeded<br />
with that, that wouldn't have created one new job for a young person, but what it would have done<br />
was to have sent a signal to older Australians that we really don't have much concern for them, don't<br />
have enough concern for them. Now it's about expanding choice. I m-ean I believe in choice. I think if<br />
somebody can do the job, doesn't matter what age they are. And this idea that you are sort of on the<br />
scrap heap once you reach a certain age is ridiculous.<br />
GIBSON: It's nineteen minutes to ten. Our guest is the Prime Minister, John Howard. Medicine. I mean surely<br />
it's every Australian's right to be able to afford to go the chemist, get a prescription filled so you can<br />
enjoy decent health. Years ago we could all afford it. Today it would cost me $ 50 a month for blood<br />
pressure tablets, what with Pauline Hanson and following the North Sydney football team, Mr<br />
Howard, I'd probably need more of them.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I won't make any gratuitous comments about your sporting preference.<br />
GIBSON: Okay, but now it's going to cost me even more and people who can't afford it...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Not necessarily. All I've done. Can I tell you what we've done?<br />
GIBSON: Yeah. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We're saying that in a particular area if you've got two drugs that both do the same job, and one of<br />
themn is cheaper than the other, then we're only going to subsidise the cheaper one. The criterion is that<br />
they've got to be doing the same job. Now what's wrong with that? And it's not going to, according to<br />
my advice it's going to result on average if people do choose the dearer drug, going onl average,<br />
involve a premium payment by the patient or the customer of $ 2 per prescription. But you've got to<br />
understand this Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme is growing, the cost of it growing, the cost of it's<br />
growing hugely. Tt's growing at a faster rate than other areas of health. Unless you have some kind of<br />
additional discipline we are going to get into trouble about the cost of it. It really is a simple as that<br />
and the benchmark drugs are going to be established by the experts, not by the Health Minister<br />
although he's quite an expert in this area, he's a doctor. He's going to have an independent group to do<br />
it and that essentially is what it involves. You've got two drugs doing the same job. One is cheaper 4 f 606/ 30/ 1977: 35: 55<br />
14 May 1997<br />
4 of 6 </p>
<p>1M41tp 9y: 7/ / w%" v. nila. gov. atipiic/ pressrel/ gibsoii. itiiI<br />
than the other, the generic one's cheaper, then we'll subsidise that. What's wrong with that? Nothing<br />
wrong with that.<br />
GIBSON: Michael Lee, who's your opposition health spokesman says some doctors are already predicting<br />
patients lives will be at risk because...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Can I say, that is just, that is just so silly.<br />
GIBSON:<br />
What you're saying is, you know, that you cop the cheap jobs, if you want the better stuff, well....<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No it's not better. No, no, no a very important thing it's got to do the same job. It's just that in the<br />
nature of drug development you have breakthroughs in certain areas and then for years you have an<br />
expensive drug and then greater technology produces a generic drug that does the same job but you<br />
continue to subsidise the whole range. And all we're saying is that you subsidise the generic one. But<br />
the criterion has got to be that it does the same job.<br />
GIBSON: We have a question from one listener, and there are many thousands of them in Australia today as you<br />
know Prime Minister. She cares for her husband, he's very ill. She gets an allowance of $ 29.00 a week.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Is that the domiciliary care allowance?<br />
GIBSON: Yes, that's right. There are 34,000 people like her. They save you $ 850 million a year. She says you<br />
did nothing for them.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We are increasing the domiciliary care allowance in this Budget by about $ 16 a fortnight. Now if the<br />
lady is in receipt of that, I don't know whether she is or she isn't, then we would certainly be assisting<br />
her. This is the second budget in a row where we have lifted the assistance for carers and I don't think,<br />
having got the opportunity go by without making that point that this is a Budget that once again has<br />
improved the benefits for carers. Now if she's in receipt of that, then, that allowance, then there will be<br />
an increase, then if she's not then there won't be, but I don't know her precise circumstances.<br />
GIBSON: Income tax cuts. I know we got the rebate on savings, for those of us who do have savings, but are we<br />
ever going to get any tax cuts, I mean the top rate is as we all know 48.5 cents, company tax still only<br />
36 cents, no matter what tax rate you're on, when will you eventually give us a break? 06/ 30/ 97 17: 35: 56<br />
14 May 1997 </p>
<p>14M i1y9 7ittp:// wwv~ v. iia. gov. au/ piinc/ pressrel/ gibsoi. litinii<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well families got significant income tax cuts on the first of January this year, families earning less than<br />
$ 70,000 a year. Now they were targeted. And they were in relation to the number of children you had<br />
and if you were a single income family you got quite a bit more. Now as to the future it depends<br />
entirely on financial circumstances. I can't say anymore than that because I don't want speculation to<br />
run about something that we may not be able to deliver on. The only way though in the long term you<br />
can ever get tax down is to repay your debts and control your spending. And that is precisely what we<br />
did in our first budget and is what we've done in the second budget. One of the great values of<br />
repaying debt is that you no longer have to pay the interest on debt you've repaid. And our interest bill<br />
has been cut by almost a billion dollars in this budget and that's a tremendous turnaround. We're<br />
repaying $ 5 billion of debt this year. And all of that is laying the groundwork for the future because if<br />
you've repaid your debts and you've controlled your spending, it stands to reason that your capacity in<br />
the future to do something in other areas on the revenue side is much greater. But I can't and won't<br />
make any promises on that front because I don't want to be in a situation of being told that I haven't<br />
delivered on something.<br />
GIBSON: All right before you go, already your critics this morning are saying that you are preparing to give us<br />
something next time round. That this budget is really one in which you're cashing up for the next<br />
election. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I suppose they would say that wouldn't they? This budget should be judged on its own merits. It<br />
builds on the very big savings we made last year. It contains a very important savings tax initiative.<br />
Certainly in year three we will be in surplus but we need a surplus for the benefit of the country and I<br />
don't see surplus as things that should be squandered. As to what happens in next year's budget, well<br />
we've only just finished this year's and I think, we're a long way off speculating about a budget that's<br />
going to be brought down in a years time. I think this budget will be seen as getting the balance right.<br />
It will reinforce the growth in the economy. It will turn around a $ 10.5 billion deficit into a $ 1.6 billion<br />
surplus and that's a huge turnaround. And it will set this country up, it will sustain economic growth<br />
and low inflation and low interest rates for years into the future and that is a very valuable contribution<br />
to all of the Australian people.<br />
GIBSON: All right thanks for your time this morning. It's a gorgeous day in Sydney. 1 hope you have a nice day<br />
down in Canberra.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It's a great day here to Mike. Great to talk to you.<br />
GIBSON:<br />
You too. The Prime Minister of Australia, John Howard.<br />
Return to Media Interviews 06/ 30/ 97 17: 35: 57<br />
14 May 1997 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
