<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3117</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA SIGNS INTERNATIONAL COVENANTS ON HUMAN RIGHTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003117.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NO DATE<br />
20 December 1972<br />
AUSTRALIA SIGNS INPERNATIONAL COVENANTS ON HUMAN RIGHTS<br />
The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr E. G. Whitlam, announced today<br />
that Australia~ s Permanent Representative to the United Nations, Sir<br />
Laurence McIntyre signed on Monday 18 December in New York, two International<br />
Covenants on Human Rights. The Covenants are the International Covenant<br />
on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights and the International Covenant<br />
on Civil and Political Rights.<br />
Mr Whitlam said the signature was intended to affirm the Government's<br />
unequivocal agreement with the aims of the Covenants. In accordance with<br />
the Charter of the United Nations these are directed towards promoting<br />
and encouraging respect for human rights and fundamental freedom for all,<br />
0 without distinction as to race, sex, language or religion.<br />
Mr Whitlam said signature of the Covenants does not impose any<br />
immediately legally binding obligations on Australia. However, signature<br />
does imply that Australia will put itself in a position to ratify them as<br />
soon as practicable. The Government has directed that work should proceed<br />
at once with a view to seeing what steps may be necessary to enable<br />
Australia to ratify.<br />
Mr VWhitlam said he hoped Australia would be in a position to ratify<br />
the Covenants by the time we observe the 25th Anniversary of the Universal<br />
Declaration of Human Rights on 10 December 1973. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
