<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10846</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN-THAI RELATIONS: NEW BILATERAL MEASURES</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce a number of Agreements and initiatives which</p>
<p> further strengthen Australia's close relationship with Thailand,</p>
<p> and advance Australia's significant national interests in Thailand.</p>
<p>Australia will provide an additional $10.2 million in aid to Thailand</p>
<p> over the next two years, in response to Thailand's current economic</p>
<p> difficulties. This pledge raises the level of Australian bilateral</p>
<p> aid to Thailand over the next two years by 25 per cent above the increase</p>
<p> announced by Australia in December last year.</p>
<p>Australia will suspend an earlier agreement to graduate Thailand from</p>
<p> Australian development assistance by 2000-01. A new programme of Australian</p>
<p> support will be developed to focus on rehabilitating the banking and</p>
<p> finance system, on good governance and on reducing the impact of the</p>
<p> crisis on the poor and disadvantaged.</p>
<p>Under the new programme, Australia will fund 80 post-graduate scholarships</p>
<p> for Thai students whose Royal Thai Government scholarships cannot</p>
<p> be funded because of economic constraints in Thailand.</p>
<p>These scholarships are in addition to the 250 Thai students already</p>
<p> in Australia under the existing development assistance programme.</p>
<p>Australia and Thailand have concluded a new air services agreement</p>
<p> which will increase capacity and flexibility for airlines of both</p>
<p> countries to meet tourism and air freight demands beyond the year</p>
<p> 2000, strengthening the economic and people-to-people dimensions of</p>
<p> the bilateral relationship.</p>
<p>The new agreement will enable both Australian and Thai airlines to</p>
<p> nearly double capacity from a total of 37 B747 or equivalent services</p>
<p> to 70 flights per week by March 2000.</p>
<p>With immediate effect, Australian and Thai carriers could increase</p>
<p> capacity of freight services to a total of 14 per week.</p>
<p>Australia and Thailand are both agricultural trading nations and founder</p>
<p> members of the Cairns Group, and have a long history of cooperation</p>
<p> in the agriculture sector.</p>
<p>Today, I witnessed the signing of a memorandum of understanding on</p>
<p> agricultural cooperation which will provide for closer collaboration</p>
<p> on policy development, market access, trade promotion and industry</p>
<p> development.</p>
<p>I was also pleased to witness today the signing of a memorandum of</p>
<p> understanding on recognition of academic qualifications.</p>
<p>The MOU enables Australia and Thailand to work towards a broad framework</p>
<p> for cooperation on the mutual recognition of educational awards issued</p>
<p> by institutions from both countries. This will assist both Australian</p>
<p> professionals seeking to work in Thailand and the many Thai students</p>
<p> who are currently studying in Australia either privately or on scholarships.</p>
<p>It is increasingly important that we move to common regional understandings</p>
<p> on educational standards.</p>
<p>I am also pleased to announce the establishment of the Australia Thailand</p>
<p> Sports Foundation.</p>
<p>The Australian Government, through the Department of Foreign Affairs</p>
<p> and Trade's Asian Sports Linkages Programme and the Australian</p>
<p> Sports Commission, will contribute $40,000 (about one million baht)</p>
<p> towards the Foundation for each of the next two years. The Sports</p>
<p> Authority of Thailand will contribute a matching amount.</p>
<p>The foundation's first priority is to assist the Thai national</p>
<p> team prepare for the 1998 Asian Games and the Sydney 2000 Olympics.</p>
<p>These measures are a further reflection of the Government's active</p>
<p> regional diplomacy. They signal Australia's long-term commitment</p>
<p> to the region, and to building strong bilateral relationships which</p>
<p> advance Australia's economic and security interests.</p>
<p>  eral relationships which</p>
<p> advance Australia's economic and security interests.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
