<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>434</transcript-id>
    <title>PM  6/1962 - CONFERENCE WITH A.C.M.A.</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/01/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000434_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>62/ 009<br />P. M. No. 6/ 1962</p>
<p>The Prime Minister and several of his senior ministerial colleagues discussed today with representatives of the Associated Chambers of i. anufactures of Australia, the current level of<br />activity and trends in Australian manufacturing industries. The<br />views of the Associated Chambers were presented by Mr. John N.<br />Walker, Federal President; Mr. T. M. Ramsay, Vice President,<br />Victorian Chamber of Manufactures; Mr. Allison, President,<br />South Australian Chamber of Manufactures; Mr. Ashton,<br />President, , Western Australian Chamber of Manufactures; Mr. H. N.<br />Herford, President, Chamber of Manufactures of N. S. Mr. J. D.<br />Ferguson the immediate Past President of the Australian Chambers<br />and Mr. Ri'. C. Anderson, the Federal Director.<br />On behalf of Australian manufacturers, the industry<br />representatives submitted a three stage plan namely a short term<br />stimulus and medium and long term developments.<br />The short term prcposals are:<br />the immediate re-imposition under Article XIX of GATT of<br />Quantitative import Restrictions to cover the products of<br />particular industries. This should provide by far the most<br />important and immediate stimulus;<br />a firm statement by the Government of its w1ill to safeguard<br />Australian industrics;<br />acceptance by the Government of the principle of<br />anticipatory duties, and<br />a statement by the Govenment confirming that a clear<br />preference will be given to Australian made goods by the<br />Commonwealth Government in its purchasing policies.<br />For the Medium Term, the Associated Chambers suggested<br />the introduction of certain financial measures designed to<br />stimulate manufacturing activity.<br />In the Long Term, the Association asked for a restatement<br />of the obJ3 ctives of Tariff Policy and consideration of<br />improved protective techniques. The Associated Chambers also<br />affirmed that an assurance by the Government of a continuing high<br />level in the flow of migrants into Australia is essential to<br />maintain a climate favourable to industrial expansion.<br />Mr. d. D. Ferguson, who is also Deputy Chairman of<br />Chrysler Australia Ltd referred to the position of the motor<br />vehicle industry in Australia and the desirability for some<br />stimulation and assistance.<br />At the conclusion of the meeting, the Prime Minister<br />and Mr. ialker agreed that there had been a most valuable<br />discussion and exchange of views. Mr. Menzies said the<br />Government would give close consideration to every proposal<br />submitted by the Associated Chambers when the conferences<br />arranged with other representative bodies have been held.<br />CAN3. LRA,<br />18th January, 1962.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
