<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7550</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, WARREN SNOWDONS OFFICE DARWIN, 1 APRIL 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/04/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007550.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT 01 NEWS CCIFIRINCZ# WARREN SNCOM'sS OFPICI,<br />
DARVIN, 1 APRIL 1989<br />
9 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you have any comment to make<br />
on the latest Friedrich story, that he was involved with ASIS<br />
and that he is in fact a German citizen?<br />
PM: I don't know about the German citizen part, but I have<br />
nothing to add to the comments that I made before and that is<br />
that on the advice available to mep there is no substance in<br />
the allegations about intelligence connections. That's what<br />
I've been informed.<br />
JOURNALIST: What information do you know about him, Prime<br />
Minister from intelligence-<br />
PM: You know very well that I don't talk about<br />
communications I have with intelligence other than to make<br />
the statement that I have made.<br />
JOURNALIST: There's one report this morning that he was<br />
involved in a fraud case in West Germany Sir, do we know<br />
anything about that, any previous history<br />
PK: I don't know anything about that, but as I've said<br />
before what I did was to ask for a report in respect of any<br />
indications in areas of Commonwealth responsibility and<br />
information I have in this report, there is nothing in that<br />
area, but if there is any other matter which involves State<br />
jurisdiction, that's a matter for the States.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Mr Howard seems to have had something<br />
of a victory in Victoria by getting a joint Senate ticket<br />
PM: Well I wouldn't count those particular rule of chickens<br />
yet, there's a lot of hatching to be done yet. Senator<br />
Mo~ auran doesn't seem to regard it as a victory. I think<br />
there's a lot of dirty water that's gone under those bridges </p>
<p>2.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you read the latest article in<br />
the Bulletin about the increase in racism around Australia?<br />
in light of your commzents last night<br />
PM: I thought you were going to refer to another<br />
article in the Bulletin. T haven't read the article but I've<br />
skimmed it. I intend to read it on the plane going back.<br />
Well, I think we have to be honest and say that there is<br />
racism in Australia. I've never disguised that, but my own<br />
view is that one of the outcomes of 1998 is that we are<br />
becoming more understanding and more tolerant society, but. it<br />
would be dishonest with ourselves to disguise the fact that<br />
the re are elements of racism in this country, there are some<br />
dark and sinister forces and organisationas who are seeking to<br />
trade on prejudices. The basic point that Australia has<br />
to understand, as I've been saying before and as you heard me<br />
say last night, is that if people want to be nothing short of<br />
treacherous to the welfare of their children and future<br />
generations, then the best thing they can do to hurt their<br />
own children's future interests, is to preach this sort of<br />
gospel of hatred because it will condemn Auatralia in the<br />
eyes of the region and in the eyes of the world. You can't.<br />
as I said hers in Darwin last night, in a city which<br />
pre-eminently proves the virtues of. multiculturalism, the<br />
absence of discrimination, you can't have a double standard<br />
in respect of the people of this region. You can't say ' we<br />
love to trade with you, we love your commerce, we love your<br />
oconomics, but you're second class citizens'. That's not on.<br />
JOURNALIST: You were fairly strong on that last night Prime<br />
Minister? PM! Not just last night, I've been strong on it all my liie.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect it become an election issue, that<br />
the immiqration<br />
PM: I would hope not. I sincerely hope, as I've said in the<br />
0 Parliament and outside, by the time we come to the next<br />
election which is still a long way awnyp that there will be a<br />
resumption of what has been for the last virtually<br />
generation in this country, bipartisanship on this issue. I<br />
sincerely hope that that will be the case.<br />
JOURNALIST: How would you If it's not, Sir?<br />
PM: Oh well, that's hypothetical.<br />
JOURNALIST: Hazve tou been told by leaders of trading<br />
nations, that tha a their attitude to us, that<br />
PM: Well, of course it's been said, yes, but you don't need<br />
to be an intellectual genius or very deeply immersed in the<br />
political process to understand the reality of it.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
