<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2675</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIA, MCMAHON CH MP IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA - EXPORT INCENTIVES - 14 SEPTEMBER 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/09/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002675.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
WILLIA McMKAHON, CH, MP. IN THE HOUSE OF<br />
REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA<br />
FXPORT INCENTIVES<br />
14 SEPTEMBER, 1972<br />
The Governmient has decided in principle to extend export<br />
incentives beyond 30 juflC, 1973 the date on which legislation<br />
providing for these incentives expires.<br />
The existing incentive scheme has been under review and<br />
details of the new scheme wil1l be announced as soon as practicable.<br />
It is the intent of the Government that tho benefits under the<br />
new scheme will be comparable in nature and scope to those under<br />
the existing scheme.<br />
The Government is aware of the need for an early and<br />
positive statement of its intentions when the current scheme<br />
expires. Otherwise, doubts and uncertainties could arise in the<br />
business community, with dctrimental effect on forward planning<br />
and export sales together with doubts on investment decisions.<br />
The export incentive scheme was introduced in 1961.<br />
The operation of the scheme has coincidcd with a period of<br />
sustained export grow;~ th from $ 2,150 million in 1961/ 62 to<br />
$ 4,900 million in 1971/ 72. There are income tax rebates for<br />
oxpenditure made on export promotion and payroll tax rebates or<br />
incentive grants linked to e-xport growth. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
