<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9350</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP PRESS CONFERENCE, THE IMPERIAL HOTEL, TOKYO, JAPAN 6 SEPTEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009350.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, THE IMPERIAL HOTEL, TOKYO, JAPAN<br />
6 SEPTEMBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well, I'm speaking here about the Liberal's policy, about the Liberal's<br />
announcement today. Well, the first thing I would say about it is,<br />
we're probably seeing the last of the end of Mr Downer here. I don't<br />
think I've seen a more pathetic document in the last 20 years. After<br />
11 years of policy reform which is now remarked upon, around the<br />
world in a common-place way -after all those budgets and major<br />
economic statements, to see this blancmange of nonsense, is to say<br />
that the Liberal Party is either institutionally had it, or Mr Downer has<br />
come to the end of the line. I mean, to publish a document which<br />
says they are pro-fami lies", mpro-Australia', " pro-communities", " projobsu,<br />
I mean, begs the obvious question, would they ever say they<br />
were anti-family, anti-Australia, anti -communities and anti-jobs?<br />
Offered the chance to state the substance of his leadership, Mr<br />
Downer has offered us a catalogue of platitudes an insult to the<br />
intelligence of our fellow Australians. I've never see, I think, a more<br />
fatuous document than this one. And just by merely publishing it, it<br />
puts down the quality of public debate in Australia. In fact, John<br />
Hewson must be wondering what his dismissal is all about because<br />
" Fightback* looks like a " War and Peace" document compared to this,<br />
which is a " Mills and Boonp economic and social guide. Mr Downer<br />
says that this is " a cornerstone, a building-block of coalition policy", in<br />
fact it will support nothing of weight because there is nothing of<br />
weight in it. And I think it will haunt him as long as he lasts, or as<br />
long as it lasts, whichever the case may be.<br />
Now, he said of course that I would make a make a comment on this<br />
without reading it. Well, it's not exactly like getting across a major<br />
work on time or the theory of relativity I was able to knock over most<br />
of this and then still finish of my sushi within 25 minutes.<br />
The thing is, I just had a most interesting conversation with Mr Hata<br />
and Mr Watanabe about the politics of social change in Japan, and </p>
<p>2<br />
economic change imperative economic change and we were<br />
relating our respective experiences. I mean if this were to be<br />
Australia's trip back down the time tunnel to the sort Of policies of the<br />
sixties and seventies the Rip Van Winkle years of the Liberal Party<br />
then we would not only not keep up, but certainly not have a lead In<br />
change, as we have in Australia now over the last decade. I mean<br />
the document is sprinkled with nonsense, like this: " The coalition will<br />
implement a practical, common-sense" how many time have we<br />
heard that " a practical, common-sense approach to labour market<br />
reform". Well, what does that mean? Does It mean that the coalition<br />
can hold wages during a period of high growth? Does it mean that<br />
they would ever have reduced inflation to under And what does<br />
" 1practical, common-sense" m mean when you have got economic<br />
growth and demand running and pushed along by very high rates of<br />
economic growth? It goes on to things like this: " tax and family<br />
payments will ease family pressures". Well, what does that mean?<br />
Tax cuts? What does it mean? And if it is, what is the fiscal impact<br />
of these things? And that family payments?<br />
And then it says in the document that so many of the costs will by<br />
cutting out waste. All of this will be met by dealing with waste and<br />
other changes to efficiency. Well, you can make all the efficiency<br />
changes you like in the public sector of Australia in the delivery of<br />
services, but it won't cover the costs of these sort of things. And then<br />
I thought the Bobby Dazzler of all of them was that, he says in his<br />
press statement; " Let me be equally clear what this statement is noto,<br />
and he goes on to say what it isn't. Well never in all the statements<br />
that I have delivered from memory, nine or eight budgets, and about<br />
ten economic statements have I ever said what they were not.<br />
Because I thought proudly they said eloquently what they were.<br />
I didn't expect much from Mr Downer, but what he has given us is<br />
even less than I expected he would.<br />
J: One of the criticisms from Alexander Downer is that why should he<br />
play your game and be very specific about the policies?<br />
PM: Well, I said that yesterday. Policies are the substance of politics.<br />
This is the place where they are the things that one attaches oneself<br />
to, and articulates to the public in seeking to provide a proper basis to<br />
our public life, and to advance our society. If they are not about<br />
policies, what are they about? See, the thing about Mr Downer is he<br />
has his policies, but he doesn't think the public will like them. So,<br />
he's going to keep them hidden so they can't come under scrutiny<br />
until the closing weeks of an election campaign.<br />
Now, he talks about honesty, that he's an honest politician. He<br />
actually goes on to make that statement that I recorded yesterday<br />
saying that " I'm the most honest person you will ever meet'. You </p>
<p>have got to have a lot of front to say something like that. Now, having<br />
said it, he doesn't follow it through by honestly telling the public what<br />
he has in mind. So we have this sort of sham document which will<br />
then, in a sense, disguise the policies which he won't reveal until the<br />
closing days of an election campaign.<br />
J: ut why should he reveal them now? It will only give you 12 months<br />
to knock them down.<br />
PM: Why should he reveal them now? Because if he wants to be in the<br />
business of the public debate if he doesn't reveal them now, he's<br />
out of the public debate. I mean, if he doesn't have policies, he's not<br />
in the public debate. If he's not an agent of change, he's not in the<br />
public debate. He disqualifies himself by saying " I don't have<br />
policies' in which case he's disqualified or " I'm not prepared to<br />
reveal them" in which case, he's deceitful.<br />
J: But isn't it fair to say that an opposition Is there to scrutinise the<br />
Government to criticize and analyze what the Government is..<br />
PM: No. The Opposition is there as the alternative government. It's there<br />
to become the alternative government. You see, Australia can't<br />
afford, now, if ever but certainly not now, to go back to this sort of<br />
period of policy paralysis that the Liberals had through most of the<br />
sixties and seventies. I mean, the Australian community now wants<br />
the common wheel advanced. They want change, and they know<br />
they've got to get it. And to be saying, " oh, just by the way, I don't<br />
think I'll give you any for the moment because that nasty government<br />
might take the mickey out of me", is not going to be tolerated by the<br />
public and nor it should be.<br />
J: I don't recollect the Labor Party putting its policies out twelve months<br />
in advance of a federal election.<br />
PM: We had, in the 1982 election, in the 1980 election, changes to fiscal<br />
policy. Quite specific addition to the deficit in 1982 of SI .5billion a<br />
whole lot of other details. But whatever the then opposition did then,<br />
the whole national debate has moved on so much. I mean, you do<br />
get remarks from people in Japan, in Europe, how Australia is among<br />
the leading nations for change in the OECD in the world. And it is.<br />
J: Is John Hewson right then in saying that what he did in OFightback<br />
last summer really lifted the benchmark in terms of oppositions and<br />
what they need to deliver in terms of policy development?<br />
PM: Well, it was a set of policies. Whether you liked them or not, it was a<br />
set of policies. As I said, it was a veritable tome compared to this lot<br />
it was a " War and Peace" compared to this being on offer. </p>
<p>J: Mr Keating, references to the republic and the constitutional change<br />
do they set In place now the coalitions positions?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know. But you can always, I mean it's got things like this<br />
in it; " We'll restore a world-class education and training system*.<br />
Restore. Now, as you remember, three students in ten completed<br />
secondary school in 1982 it's now eight in ten, So he'll restore us<br />
back to three in ten. He'll restore us back to pathetic rates of tertiary<br />
places. He'll restore us back to the absolutely Cinderella status of<br />
technical and further education. He's going to help with savings and<br />
productivity, but he's going to afreeze the superannuation guarantee<br />
charge while working to provide effective superannuation care for<br />
retirement". In other words, he claims to be interested in families, the<br />
one bit of additional support for savings for a better standard of living<br />
in retirement for families has come from the Government's<br />
superannuation legislation. The only reason that Alexander Downer<br />
wants to freeze the superannuation guarantee charge* is that they<br />
don't want to see the empowerment of trade unions sitting as trustees<br />
of hundreds of billions of super-fund monies, and also they don't want<br />
to see any shift from business to individuals by way of enhanced<br />
income in retirement. So, they're going to help savings but they have<br />
got a very snakey policy on ordinary people, who are getting for the<br />
first time ever, a bit of a benefit a substantial benefit in fact from<br />
superannuation. I mean, it's full of those sort of inconsistencies.<br />
Look, let me just conclude my remarks on this point. It's the worst<br />
thing I've ever seen from them. Certainly, in the years I've been in<br />
office, and as I said the other day, they must be saying * we've done it<br />
again". They must be. They have to be saying, " we've done it again<br />
we've picked a dud".<br />
J: Tempted to go early, Mr Keating?<br />
PM: No. No. But you notice that Mr Downer has released this in my<br />
absence. I did make the remark that I would try and ping him, even if<br />
it was from the foyer of the Imperial Hotel. But, he has released it in<br />
my absence well, I'll just say this to Mr Downer, don't get too tricky<br />
with me. Mr Downer, we can all be tricky. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
