<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10961</transcript-id>
    <title>3 October 1998                                                TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ELECTION NIGHT SPEECH, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p> Thank you very much. And can I say to my fellow Australians</p>
<p>   that, although the final result in terms of seats will not be determined</p>
<p>   before some days yet, it is clear that the Coalition will have a</p>
<p>   working majority in the new Parliament.</p>
<p>I want, first and foremost, to thank the Australian people for</p>
<p>   returning the Government. I want to thank the Australian people</p>
<p>   for embracing a bold, economic reform that is in the long-term interests</p>
<p>   of the Australian community.</p>
<p>Some declarations about political precedence have been made tonight.</p>
<p>   Let me make a declaration about political precedence. This is probably</p>
<p>   the first time in the recent experience of western political parties</p>
<p>   that a party has successfully won an election championing such a</p>
<p>   major reform which so readily lent itself to a dishonest fear campaign.</p>
<p>And I am immensely proud of the fact that the Coalition stuck to</p>
<p>   its guns, we stared down that fear campaign and that the Australian</p>
<p>   people came with us.</p>
<p>I want to commit myself and the members of my Government, once</p>
<p>   again to the service of the Australian people. I have always seen</p>
<p>   myself in public life as a servant of the Australian people. And</p>
<p>   I regard it as a privilege beyond belief to have been twice elected</p>
<p>   as Prime Minister of Australia.</p>
<p>We now have a mandate to implement the policies that we took to</p>
<p>   the Australian people that we so honestly and openly and candidly</p>
<p>   laid before the Australian people. We have weathered the ferocious</p>
<p>   fear campaign and we have won the mandate of the Australian people.</p>
<p>I want, tonight, to acknowledge with sadness the loss of a number</p>
<p>   of my colleagues who</p>
<p>have been defeated. I want to thank them for their service to the</p>
<p>   Liberal Party and to their service to the National Party. And I</p>
<p>   know I express Tim Fischer's gratitude of extending those sentiments</p>
<p>   and those thoughts.</p>
<p>I want to salute the spectacular performance of several of my colleagues</p>
<p>   and I know it's always bad to single people out, but I'm</p>
<p>   going to do it. I want to particularly single out Trish Draper in</p>
<p>   the seat of Makin in South Australia. And in New South Wales and</p>
<p>   I want to salute the magnificent performance of Danna Vale and Jackie</p>
<p>   Kelly. But to all of my colleagues who have won in very difficult</p>
<p>   circumstances, I profess my profound gratitude.</p>
<p>I also want to thank the Liberal Party organisation. I want to</p>
<p>   thank Tony Staley the Federal President and Lynton Crosby, the Federal</p>
<p>   Director, and also may I extend my thanks to the various state organisations</p>
<p>   for the work they did in bringing about this magnificent result.</p>
<p>We are here tonight victorious because of superb organisation in</p>
<p>   the seats that really mattered and superb cooperation between the</p>
<p>   Parliamentary Party and the organisation.</p>
<p>I want to salute Tim Fischer, the Leader of the National Party.</p>
<p>   Tim is a great colleague and a wonderful friend. And he faced a</p>
<p>   very vicious challenge in his own seat and he beat that off in magnificent</p>
<p>   style.</p>
<p>I also extend my gratitude to Peter Costello, the Deputy Leader</p>
<p>   of the Liberal Party who has been a great Treasurer and a great</p>
<p>   colleague to work with. And can I also particularly thank the Premier</p>
<p>   of Victoria, Jeff Kennett. Jeff has been a forthright supporter</p>
<p>   of the cause of taxation reform and I acknowledge the contribution</p>
<p>   that he made during my election campaign.</p>
<p>And I say to all of my fellow Australians, that the government</p>
<p>   that you have elected tonight will lead this country into the 21st</p>
<p>   century. The government you have elected tonight will be a government</p>
<p>   for all Australians. The government you have elected tonight will</p>
<p>   dedicate itself to the welfare of all of the Australian people.</p>
<p>   I have said on other occasions that this country has unparalleled</p>
<p>   assets. No nation on earth so uniquely combines the heritage of</p>
<p>   our western civilisation, our great links with the nations of North</p>
<p>   America and our placement here in the Asia Pacific region. And we</p>
<p>   have a capacity and an opportunity to use that conjunction of circumstances</p>
<p>   to our benefit and to the benefit of the region and to the benefit</p>
<p>   of the entire world.</p>
<p>I want to dedicate my government to the maintenance of traditional</p>
<p>   Australian values. And they include those great values of mateship</p>
<p>   and egalitarianism. They also mean that great Australian value of</p>
<p>   tolerance and of treating people decently and of not discriminating</p>
<p>   against people according to their race or ethnic background.</p>
<p>We are a nation of many parts and many origins. And we should never</p>
<p>   forget that. And we should see that as a tremendous asset.</p>
<p>And I also want to commit myself very genuinely to the cause of</p>
<p>   true reconciliation with the Aboriginal people of Australia by the</p>
<p>   centenary of Federation. We may differ and debate about the best</p>
<p>   way of achieving reconciliation, but I think all Australians are</p>
<p>   united in a determination to achieve it.</p>
<p>Finally, ladies and gentlemen, I want to express my gratitude to</p>
<p>   two very special groups of people in my life. I want to thank my</p>
<p>   magnificent personal staff in particular, my Chief of Staff, Arthur</p>
<p>   Sinodinos. Through all the ups and downs in the last two-and-a-half</p>
<p>   years, Arthur and my personal staff have sustained me and kept me</p>
<p>   sane when the alternative seemed very likely. And I thank him and</p>
<p>   I thank all those around him very, very much for what they have</p>
<p>   done.</p>
<p>And finally, can I express my love and gratitude to my magnificent</p>
<p>   family. Thank you. No father could be prouder than I am of my three</p>
<p>   children. And I just want to say to Janette and to Melanie and to</p>
<p>   Tim and Richard, I love you very deeply and I thank you for everything</p>
<p>   that you've done for me.</p>
<p>And finally, to all of you wonderful people, you wonderful members</p>
<p>   and supporters of our wonderful Party, the Liberal Party of Australia,</p>
<p>   tonight belongs to you as much as it does to me. I thank you from</p>
<p>   the bottom of my heart for the loyalty that you've given me</p>
<p>   over the last two-and-a-half years and let's work together</p>
<p>   to build another great victory in three years time.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
