<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21217</transcript-id>
    <title>Opening of Belmont Aged Care Facility Belmont, Victoria </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/04/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Mr John Leper, Stewart McArthur the Member for Corangamite, Senator Tsebin Tchen, Senator for Victoria, staff of the Belmont, residents, ladies and gentlemen.  This is a wonderful facility.  I have visited many aged care facilities over the years in my various political capacities.  Some of them greet you by their very presence with a warmth and family congeniality, others not so much.  This is very much in the former category.  It is, to use that old clich‚, but it';s very relevant, it is a building that has the feeling of a home away from home, and that is very important.</p>
<p>I want to congratulate TLC and Mr Leper in particular for the example that has been set to others through the excellence of this facility and the other facilities that the organisation has established and run for quite a number of years.  Caring for an increasingly ageing community will be one of the great challenges for Australia over the next 50 years.  We are, in common with all other western societies, an ageing population and increasingly therefore the quality of care offered to older Australians, the options available through staying longer in their own homes if that is their choice and that is within their capacity, the sort of facilities that will be available to them when they leave their own homes, the connections they can maintain with their families and their communities, all of those things will be extremely important and society will require of all of us, particularly those of us in Government, and also those who are involved in the aged care sector, a comprehensive response.</p>
<p>  I am aware that there are additional needs for the aged care sector.  We have carried out a very searching examination of those needs through the courtesy of Professor Warren Hogan';s examination.  That report has been in the Government';s hands for some weeks and we will be announcing in the very, very near future a response.  It';s no secret to say that that response will involve, amongst other things, the provision of substantial additional resources out of the Federal Treasury for the aged care sector in Australia.  It is an important sector.  We want to get the balance right.  We want to keep faith with those who have contributed so much to the building of the modern Australia.</p>
<p>  You mentioned that one of your residents, Mr Grove, was going to march in the ANZAC Day march.  He is representative of a generation that has given so much to this country.  And by and large the segment of the Australian population now requiring moderate to intensive care in aged care facilities does represent the generation, some of whom went through both the Depression and World War II and most of whom in different ways lived or fought through World War II.  So we of other generations owe them a very special debt and part of that is to make sure that the aged care facilities provided for them are of the best possible quality and standard.</p>
<p>  We have asked, through the accreditation process, we have asked aged care facilities around Australia to meet certain standards.  I accept that for some, without in any way criticising their commitment to high quality care, that has required the commitment of additional resources and it has been difficult.  But in the long run, that can only be better for people who live and are cared for in these facilities.</p>
<p>  I was impressed, as Mr Leper explained the operation of Belmont to me, by the concept of mixed care, the idea of not having a clear demarcation between high and low care, and recognising that both from a caring point of a view, from the sense of community you get in the facility, and also the peace of mind of people who come into the facility, that concept of mixed care without that sharp division is something that is extremely positive and something very much to be welcomed.   This organisation has made a great contribution.  It has pioneered many approaches.  It has been a fine example of what can be done.  And in this area, as in so many other areas in providing human services, we need to have a partnership between the Government and the private sector, and certainly in the case of aged care, also many of the great welfare and religious organisations of Australia.  We are very good in Australia at getting cooperation and partnership between both these groups in our society.</p>
<p>  The Government can';t run aged care on its own.  I would hate to see every aged care facility run by the government.  That';s no disrespect to those who work very hard in the department, but it';s not really their (inaudible).  I wouldn';t like to see aged care left entirely to the private sector without some kind of government involvement and some kind of government supervision.  And where indeed would the aged care sector be without the sense of mission that is brought to it by so many of the great religious and other welfare organisations?</p>
<p>  But finally and most importantly, can I say a word for the staff and the administrative people who work in aged care homes.  Without them, and they do work well beyond the call of duty and far in excess of the remuneration that they receive, they work very very hard indeed, it';s hard work, but it is rewarding work when you have committed people.  And I just want to conclude my remarks before declaring this facility open, that I do appreciate and the community appreciates, what the nursing staff and the staff generally do in aged care facilities.  Overwhelmingly they are wonderful, warm hearted, dedicated, good Australians who do wonderful things for elderly Australians in our community and I very, very warmly thank them for it.</p>
<p>  And on that note, a very appropriate note of recognition, may I declare the Belmont open.  Can I congratulate Mr Leper on the work that he has done, the standard of care being offered, and may I wish all of the residents a long and happy life here.  Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
