<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2178</transcript-id>
    <title>AGREEMENT ON BARRIER REEF OIL DRILLING ENQUIRY</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002178.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS_ P. M. No. 24/ 1970<br />
AGREEMENT ON BARRIER REEF CIL DRILLING ENQUIRY<br />
The Prime Minister said he was delighted with the outcome of<br />
the conference with the Premier of Queensland.<br />
Agreement had been reached that there should be an enquiry into<br />
the possible damage which might be caused to the Barrier Reef through drilling<br />
for oil. The enquiry was to be an open enquiry with s ufficient authority to<br />
collect any evidence required. All interested parties could appear before the<br />
Committee and state their views, and adduce evidence to support those views.<br />
The Committee of enquiry was to be not less than three nor more<br />
than five. It was to consist of a judge as Chairman and representatives of<br />
marine biologists and petroleum engineers. The committee wras to be jointly<br />
agreed by the Commonwealth and the State Governments and was to report to<br />
both Governments. The terms of reference of the Committee were<br />
1. Taking into account existing world technology in relation to<br />
drilling, and safety precautions relating thereto, what<br />
dangers are there of an oil or gas leak in exploratory<br />
and production drilling in the area of the Great Barrier<br />
Reef.<br />
2. The probability of benefits accruing to the State of Queensland<br />
and other parts of the Commonwealth from exploration or<br />
drilling for petroleum in the vicinity of the Reef and the<br />
extent of the benefits thereby rendered probable.<br />
3. What are the existing safety precautions already prescribed<br />
or otherwise laid down, and, if exploration or drilling<br />
for petroleum on or near the Reef is permitted, what.<br />
conditions should be imposed before such drilling coul d<br />
take place.<br />
4. What would be the likely effect of an oil or gas leak and<br />
subsequent remedial measures on<br />
the coral reefs themselves<br />
the coastline<br />
the ecological and biological aspects of<br />
life of the area<br />
Whether there are areas, and if so where, where an oil leak,<br />
if it occurred, would cause no damage to the Reefs or<br />
ecological and biological aspects of the Reefs. / 2 </p>
<p>6. The area of the Great Barrier Reef referred to in the above terms<br />
of reference includes the entire area from low water mark on the<br />
mainland of Queensland to the outer line of the Reefs and includes<br />
also the area outside and adjacent to the outer line of Reefs.<br />
The question of the possibility of drilling during the holding<br />
of the enquiry was considered.<br />
As regards drilling in Repulse Bay, the Queensland Government<br />
stated that it did not feel it could repudiate its contractual obligations should<br />
Ampol/ Japex insist on drilling. But both Governments expressed the hope<br />
that Ampol/ Japex would inform the Queensland Government that they did not<br />
propose to drill pending the outcome of the enquiry.<br />
In regard to other areas of the Barrier ReefD both Governments<br />
expressed the hope and the desire that drilling should not take place<br />
pending the outcome of the enquiry and the Commovvealth stated that if the<br />
wish of the Governments concerned should be ignored, the<br />
conditions attached to drilling should be so stringent that no damage<br />
could occur. It was further agreed if, as a result of any action taken because<br />
of the report of the Committee, the question of compensation should arise,<br />
both Governments would at once confer on this matter.<br />
On the question of the depredations of the Crown of Thorns<br />
Starfish both Governments agreed that a joint Committee should be<br />
set up financed by a dollar for dollar grant from the State and Commcnw ealth<br />
Governments. It was noted that much investigation into this problem had<br />
already taken place but that no definitive proposals for action had so<br />
far been able to be recommended by the bodies concerned in<br />
investigation. CA NBERRA<br />
29 January 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
