<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3552</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT BY DR JF CAIRNS, ACTING PRIME MINISTER, MELBOURNE, 17 DECEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003552.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-PRESS STATEbIENT BY DR. J. F. CAIRNS, ACTING PRIME MINISTER<br />
HILIBOURNE DECEM. BER, 17, 1974<br />
There is no need for G. M. H. to threaten the Government, nor<br />
to sack thousands of workers to get action by the Government.<br />
A few weeks ago the Government had, with G. M. H. and all other<br />
sections of the industry, most extensive and constructive<br />
discussions. A National Plan for the automotive industry was the result.<br />
Among othe r things, it provided for the reduction to, and<br />
limitation of, imports to about 20 per cent of the total.<br />
G. M. H. and all others expressed complete approval.<br />
Necessary steps were immediately taken to implement the<br />
Plan. Imports began to fall and will continue to fall<br />
Officials of the Department of Manufacturing Industry have<br />
been in Japan for the past few weeks and from examination<br />
of invoices and orders established that imports of Japanese<br />
cars into Australia would be halved from the 36/ 37 per cent<br />
level in January. This information was conveyed to G. M. H.<br />
but they persisted in taking the action that they have taken.<br />
The consumer also has to be protected and imports must remainr<br />
sufficient to represent competition for the Australian monopoly<br />
producers of motor cars.<br />
The Australian Government also has a responsibility to<br />
Australian producers of wool, wheat and minerals.<br />
Japan is an important market and we muist buy front Japan.<br />
Japan has co-operated with us in reducing imports of motor </p>
<p>-2-<br />
cars into Australia. We are satisified we will continue to<br />
receive that co-operation.<br />
But G. M. H. threats and dismissals are not just the result<br />
of car imports into Australia.<br />
G. M. H. threats and dismissals are a result of decisions in<br />
Detroit and they are far greater in the United States, and<br />
the same is happening in Germany and in Japan where imports<br />
are not significant.<br />
The automotive industry all over the world is going through<br />
a basic re-construction. G. M. H. in Australia is part of this.<br />
If it wants to blame the Australian Government this may<br />
provide it with an excuse but that is no way to handle industry<br />
reconstruction problems.<br />
G. M. H. need not threaten the Government nor the workers just<br />
before Christmas.<br />
We will respond again and immediately. I am arranging<br />
conferences with the A. C. T. U. and the Unions, with all<br />
sections of the automative industry and finally, I hope,<br />
with We will tackle the problems of the automotive<br />
industry in Australia, not just from the point of view of<br />
reducing or eliminsating import competition but so we can<br />
plan our future together.<br />
I hope G. M. H. will respond too and not dismiss as they did<br />
yesterday every suggestion put forward by the Minister who<br />
is responsible for the industry.<br />
A solution can be found. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
