<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6882</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006882.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA15 April 1986<br />
The Australian Government was advised by the US<br />
Administration early this morning of immediately<br />
impending military action against Libya. President<br />
Reagan has since confirmed that the US has taken<br />
military action against targets which it regards as<br />
supporting terrorism.<br />
The Australian Government has counselled restraint by<br />
both the US and Libya in the course of the developing<br />
tensions between them. It deeply regrets that this<br />
conflict has taken place and urges both sides to suspend<br />
hostilities and engage in genuine efforts to bring about<br />
the peaceful resolution of their differences.<br />
This will mean that the US terminate its military<br />
engagement against Libya. It also means, as an absolute<br />
essential, that Colonel Qadaffi terminate his<br />
government's indiscriminate export of terrorist activity<br />
against civilians and civilian targets, especially US<br />
civilians. The United States has said that its action was motivated<br />
not only by evidence of Libyan involvement in and<br />
direction of past terrorist activities but also by<br />
indications of Libyan planning being well advanced for<br />
further operations against American citizens in a number<br />
of countries.<br />
The United States' military action was explained to us<br />
not in terms of revenge or reprisals but in terms of<br />
demonstrating that terrorism will incur a significant<br />
cost.<br />
The Government accepts that there is a substantial body<br />
of evidence of Libyan involvement in and direction of<br />
international terrorism. The Foreign Minister and I<br />
have been privy to apparently compelling evidence of a<br />
direct line of command between Libya and the Berlin<br />
nightclub bombing. </p>
<p>-2<br />
It is a matter of serious concern that following the<br />
Gulf of Sidra episode where Libya attacked American<br />
forces exercising in international waters and the United<br />
States retaliated -Libya's policy of extreme hostility<br />
against the United States has continued.<br />
The Government, in response to a request from President<br />
Reagan in January, took a number of economic measures<br />
against Libya and reduced Libya's official<br />
representation in Australia as part of collective<br />
international measures to demonstrate to Libya that its<br />
behaviour in support of international terrorism is<br />
totally unacceptable to the international community.<br />
The Government has expressed a desire to work with<br />
Western and other Governments for a concerted approach<br />
to dealing with international terrorism. The Minister<br />
for Foreign Affairs is pursuing this matter with Western<br />
and other Governments and will be reporting back to<br />
Cabinet on measures to promote a sustained long-term<br />
effort to defeat the threat of international terrorism.<br />
The Government is profoundly concerned that the<br />
situation has reached the point where Libyan actions<br />
have driven the US to regard it as essential that it<br />
take military action.<br />
Australia works persistently for a peaceful world. We<br />
are opposed to the use of violent means to resolve<br />
differences between nations and in particular to the<br />
resort to terrorism.<br />
Terrorism recognises no rules and respects no moral<br />
standards. The victims are almost always innocent<br />
victims. Australians have already been victims of this<br />
sort of activity. And that is another reason why we are<br />
implacably opposed to this sort of behaviour.<br />
Let me sum up the Government's position:<br />
We wish to see restraint and an early end to<br />
hostilities. We hope that the conflict will not widen and<br />
escalate.<br />
We are fully conscious of the intractable and<br />
bitter conflicts of the Middle East, and the need<br />
for them to be resolved if the Middle East is to<br />
cease to be a source of violence and terrorism not<br />
only in that region but throughout the world. We<br />
look for such a resolution.<br />
But an essential requirement for ending the<br />
fundamental confrontation between Libya and the US<br />
must be that Libya completely and convincingly<br />
disavows recourse to terrorism. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
