<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3932</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S INTERVIEW ON &#039;A CURRENT AFFAIR&#039;, 20 OCTOBER 1975 (RECORDED 19 OCTOBER 1975)</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003932.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S INTERVIEW ON ' A CURRENT AFFAIR', 20 OCTOBER 1975<br />
( Recorded 19 October 1975)<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Prime Minister do you think that people of Australia<br />
want a change of Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: At the moment they do. When our Budget is passed<br />
and commences to work, they will want to keep the present one.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Why don't you think they should have the right of<br />
having a change now?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Because a Government is entitled to last out its<br />
full term. For the second time the Opposition is trying to cut<br />
our term off half way.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You've made promises before, like the one that you've<br />
just made now, that when the Budget works things will get better.'<br />
You made those promises in May 1974; they didn't come true.<br />
Are you concerned?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I think things have improved in many respects.<br />
But we have had an immense amount of obstruction, as you know.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You think that now the promises that you make can<br />
be kept?<br />
PRIXE MINISTER: Yes. That's what the Opposition is frightened of.<br />
They realise that this is the best Budget for years.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Why can these promises be kept now and they<br />
weren't before?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well why do they want to prevent the Budget taking<br />
effect. Their judgement and mine is the same in each case, that<br />
this is a good Budget.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Don't they believe also that there have been other<br />
problems with the Government, changing of acting Prime Ministers and<br />
Deputy Prime Ministers, Loans Affairs?<br />
PRIRE MINISTER: So what? I demand the top standards in my Ministers;<br />
they didn't. Their Ministers misled Parliament; they covered up.<br />
Where mine have misled Parliament, they've gone.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Do you feel yourself in anyway negligent about<br />
what your Ministers have done behind your back?<br />
PRIM1E MINISTER: I'm disappointed. But nobody knew it; nobody could<br />
have known it.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Do you think that it is partially your fault that<br />
you didn't know?<br />
PRI'E MINISTER: No I don't. Everybody was misled.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: What do you mean by that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well nobody knew; nobody knew that Dr Cairns and<br />
Mr Connor weren't telling the truth. / 2 ' I<br />
r. I 1 </p>
<p>SCHILDBERGER: Shouldn't you have known, though, what was going on?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They -should have told me.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Does this mean. that there's not enough involvement<br />
between you and your Ministers?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, no. They concealed it from me, as from the<br />
Parliament. They've paid -the penalty. But as I say, I demand<br />
top standards from my Ministers. -But look at'Mr Fraser, look at<br />
Mr Lynch: they were Ministers for-the Army during the Vietnam<br />
involvement. Did they tell the truth? Their Prime Ministers<br />
covered up for them. Look at the VIP planes affair. A Prime<br />
Minister -then covered up for the Ministers concern--d; he might<br />
have been part of it. My standards are severe.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Why would your Ministers be disloyal to you?<br />
. PRIME MINISTER: It's not just disloyal to me; they're disloyal,<br />
they've let the Government down.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: There must be a reason?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I won't speculate what faults of nature there<br />
may" be. They were experienced parliamentarians; they'-ve paid<br />
. tte . penal'ty..<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Could it be that. you misled them?<br />
PRTIE ' MINISTER: Certainly not. Are you making any suggestion<br />
that I misled them?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: I'm suggesting that possibly they believed that<br />
they were doing the right thing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well they weren't. There is no excuse for telling<br />
other-than the truth, and the whole truth, to Parliament.<br />
. Liberal Prime Ministers have covered up for Ministers, but failed,<br />
' by ' that test. I will not cover up.<br />
S2HILDB3RGER: Prime. Minister, of the four politicians who-signed<br />
that Executive Minute 1-ast December about the Loans Affair, three<br />
are , gone, one is left, and that's you?<br />
P. RIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Does that feel a bit eerie?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, no. It's astonishing that no charges have been<br />
made in Parliament, where they could be made. See, you would<br />
hesitate to say anything now, because I could. sue you. But in<br />
PRrliament people can say things under -privilege. And nobody in<br />
Parliament over months has ever made a charge of impropriety or<br />
illegality by any of those Ministers or by me. Why those Ministers<br />
went, was not because of illegality or impropriety, it was because<br />
they misled -the -arliament.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Have you considered resigning?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Never.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: : Nc-t at all... </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, only last 1hursday, the House of Representatives<br />
by a very considerable majority, expressed its confidence in my<br />
Government. SCHILDBERGER: That's a matter of numbers; you had them?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course I did. And I shall until the middle<br />
of 1977, when the next House of Representatives election is due.<br />
And when it will be held.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You've threatened to Caucus on a couple of occasions<br />
that you might resign?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No I haven't.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: We've been led to believe that you...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well you were misled, because I have no intention<br />
of resigning.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Has it come into your mind at all in the last<br />
twelve months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Never.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: No dissatisfaction on your part with what the Labor<br />
Government of today is doing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I've been disappointed at the difficulties but<br />
on balance it's well worth while. I have a duty to give good<br />
government to this country and only a Labor Government can do it.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: When a managing director of a company, gets his<br />
company into disarray, a situation that Australia is at the moment...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The share holders are very well satisfied 1ifn the<br />
present managing director.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Are you sure?<br />
IRIM-E MINISTER: Certainly.. You saw the way they cheered him last<br />
, v eek.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: That's a limited number...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. It's the largest combination of members of<br />
Parliament in the Federal Parliament or anywhere in Australia. And<br />
they are very satisfied with the managing director.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: What about the people of Australia who are also the<br />
shareholders?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: When the Budget is passed and takes effect, they<br />
for a third time, will endorse the Whitlam Government. Because<br />
you'll notice that the Liberals don't put up any better proposals.<br />
They don't say what Budget they would pass. They know that this<br />
Budget is as good as the country can produce at this time and<br />
in the present circumstances. / 4 </p>
<p>SCHILDBERGER: Prime Minister, you are at present accusing the<br />
Opposition of taking unprecedented steps.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Certainly.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Could it be said that you are taking an unprecedented<br />
step in not facing the people?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. There never has been an occasion when an<br />
Opposition has threatened to reject a Budget or, in fact, a Money<br />
Bill. Mine is not the first Government which has not had a<br />
, majority in the Senate. But never, before my Government was in<br />
office, had an Opposition threatened to reject Supply or a Budget.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: But it did happen in May 1974?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No it didn't.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: ' There . was a threat of the rejection of a FIoney Bill?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: , Ncta Budget<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Not a Budget?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: . No, -ot a Budget.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: So basically the principle...<br />
PRIMS MINISTER: There was some argument about this, but you<br />
notice that in the Senate it was not rejected.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: But it didn'. t need to. be, because you went to the<br />
people. PRIME MINISTER: No, no we-didn't. The election was at the end<br />
of 1972.<br />
SCHILDBERTER: In 1974 there was an election?<br />
PRIME -MINISTER: I -thought you said<br />
SCHILDBERGER: 1974.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: On that occasion there was a threat. And on that<br />
occasion I asked the Governor-General to grant a double dissolution.<br />
Now if I do that again now, it will become a habit. I'm not going<br />
to fall for that again. That is, my first Government was cut<br />
:-off halfway through its term. My second Government will run its<br />
full term.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: So therefore you admit that . it -was unprecedented<br />
perhaps in ' 74?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It was a threat; it was a threat as there is only<br />
a threat at this . stage. You will notice that the Opposition hasn't<br />
yet. rejected-the Ludget, they're fooling around with it. They<br />
moved an anmndment and because a Labor Senator had died they were<br />
able to carry that amendment. The amendment was to defer the<br />
debate. Now if this Labor Senator hadn't died, there would have<br />
been : as-many . peopla . voting against the amendment . as voting for it.<br />
And therefore it would not . have been carried. As Senator Steele Hall<br />
said: The amentient to defer the debate on the Budget Bills, was<br />
carried . over a dead man's corpse. </p>
<p>SCHILDEERGER: But if that dead man had been there the Opposition<br />
could still have been able to reject the Budget and presumably<br />
would have?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They in fact haven't moved to reject the Budget.<br />
That is, they know how unprincipled not only unprecedented but<br />
unprincipled it would be to reject a Budget. There have been<br />
a hundred and thirty-nine Money Bills in the history of the<br />
Federal Parliament passed by the Senate, passed that is, getting<br />
a majority in the Senate although the Government of the day didn't<br />
have a majority in the Senate. No Money Bill has ever been reject: ed<br />
by the Senate before.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: It's fair to say that the Constitution provides for<br />
what the opposition is doing now. The Constitution doesn't.<br />
provide for what you' re doing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, that's not true. The Constitution may<br />
or may not say that the Senate can reject a Money Bill. The fact<br />
is the Senate never has rejected a Money Bill. The Constitution'<br />
also says that an election for the House of Representatives takes<br />
place when the Governor-in-Council decides. That is, when the<br />
Government decides. I have a majority in the House of Representatives.<br />
I will not be advising the Governor-General to issue writs for<br />
the House of Representatives until towards the end of my term.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: What about a half-Senate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I riay. But possibly not until it's due, which<br />
of course, must be before the end of next June.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You are giving thought to having it early?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm giving thought to it. But I don't want you<br />
to get any impression that I'm committed to it.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You're going to between you and the Opposition<br />
leader, between the two of you hurt a l. ot of people in the next<br />
coming weeks?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That is possible. If the Opposition persists in<br />
this unprecedented and reprehensible course of rejecting a* Budget,<br />
many people will be hurt.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Do you want to continue that hurt or do you believe<br />
that in your position as Leader you should prevent the hurt?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: NoI am determined to see that ' there will be<br />
stable Government in Australia. If I sell the pass on this<br />
occasion, there can never be stable government in Australia in<br />
the future. If I accept that the Senate can send the House of<br />
Representatives to the people, whenever it sees fit, then you can<br />
have governments in Australia going for six month periods only.<br />
I will not accept that. It's not just what my Government may think<br />
about it; it's what every future government also would think<br />
about it. When the people go to the polls, they expect to elect<br />
a House of Representatives, a government, for three years. They<br />
don't expect that the Senate-which will not be facing the people<br />
can send the House of Representatives to the people at six month<br />
intervals. </p>
<p>SCHILDBERGER: Could it be said that you're doing this at the moment<br />
because you, believe that you wouldn't win the election? In other<br />
words you're doing it for political reasons?<br />
' PRIME MINISTER: I would lose next Saturday. But when this Budget<br />
ispassed, I would win an election.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: So right now . though, you're doing it for political<br />
reasons?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. It's my duty to see that there is stable<br />
government in Australia. This sort of thing to which my government<br />
has been twice. subjected, has. never happened to any-previous<br />
Australian government. If I let it . happen a second time it<br />
" will -then become embedded in our political -practice. And whenever<br />
a. Government, . that is, a Party or Parties. with a majority<br />
in the House of Representatives doesn't have a majority in the<br />
Senate then-there will not be stable government. It is my duty<br />
to see that stable government is preserved in Australia. And shall.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Does the present situation worry you?<br />
PilME-MI-NI'STER: Of course it does. I have. learnt from the<br />
experience of last year. That is, I'm not... the Opposition<br />
-thought that, by threatening to reject the Budget, this tire, my<br />
reaction would be the -same as it was in April last year, when<br />
they threatened to refuse Supply. They thought that I would then<br />
ask the Governor-General to have a double dissolution. I shan't.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Are you being stubborn?<br />
P. RI,-E.. MINISTER: No. ' ve learnt from experience last year.<br />
* They. haven't. Mr Fraser has made the same mistake as Mr Snedden.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You say it's a mistake, but it's causing a lot of<br />
. hardship and can cause hardship?<br />
PRIME ' MI-NISTER: It can cause hardship and he is . responsible for it.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You won't take any of the responsibility?<br />
PRINE MINISTER: None whatever. I was elected for three years.<br />
' The -House of-Representatives has confidence in my Government.<br />
Governments are made or unmade in the House of Representatives.<br />
Last Thursday the House of Representatives expressed confidence<br />
-again in my Government. And also asserted the right of the House<br />
of Representatives to determine money matters.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Is -the'Constitution wrong in making it possible<br />
to let the Opposition do what it is now doing?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. But everybody had assumed that this would<br />
. never happen. There's no other country in the world where what<br />
' the Opposition is.-now; threatening could happen, . whether it is a<br />
' Federal system or unitary system. This wouldn't happen anywhere<br />
else in the world. And I'm determined on this occasion to end<br />
for all time the Senate's power over Money Bills. I am going to<br />
see . that what':; . threatened now fcr-the second time will never be<br />
threatened ag'in. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Only be establishing other precedents because you<br />
can't change the Constitution?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. But everybody had assumed that no Senate<br />
would reject a Money Bill. I mean the Canadian Senate theoretically<br />
can but it doesn't; it never has. This would be unthinkable<br />
everywhere else in the world.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Won't you accept that it's in the Constitution for<br />
a reason?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, it is not; it's not.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: It doesn't make a specific mention of the fact that<br />
Money Bills can be rejected?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It doesn't expressly say that, that's true. But<br />
everybody had assumed that that was the situation.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Why do you say that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well it's never happened. And it couldn't happen<br />
anywhere else in the world.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: If it shouldn't happen, then wouldn't it be<br />
specifically written into the Constitution?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It never has. People don't guard against unthinkable<br />
propositions. This had never been contemplted before. That is,<br />
nobody realised how obstructive the Senate could be. In the three<br />
years that my Government has been in office, the Senate has<br />
rejected more Bills than it had in the previous 71 years of its<br />
existence. SCHILDBERGER: Is the Labor Government today the sort of Government<br />
that you hoped to lead?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In many ways, yes; in many other ways it's been<br />
more difficult.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: In what ways?<br />
PRIME MINSITER: There are two principal ways. One is that we are<br />
faced with a world-wide period of economic difficulty; every<br />
western country, every trading country, every industrialised country<br />
is going through this bad bout of inflation and unemployment.<br />
The second thing is that I didn't think the Senate would be as<br />
obstructive as it has been. You'll remember when we were elected<br />
in December 1972, the Senate still had 18 months to run. And nobody<br />
suggested during that campaign that the Senate would reject Bills<br />
which we've brought in to carry out our election promises. And in<br />
May last year, when we were re-elected, nobody suggested that if the<br />
Senate was evenly divided which is what it was after the election<br />
that it would reject Bills which we've brought up in performance of<br />
our election promises. Nobody expected that. Nobody said it in<br />
May last year. Nobody said it in December ' 72. </p>
<p>SCHILDEERGER: You've often-been accused of fin.-ding scapegoats.<br />
Could it be said now that you are now lookin. r t these as<br />
scapegoats, as well as the Connors, Cairns arnd Creans?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well the figures show, don't they, that the<br />
' Senate has rejected more Bills in the last three years than in<br />
all the years between 1901 and 1972.<br />
SCHILDBERGER; But have they really done much -to harm your progress?<br />
PRIME. MINISTER: But of course they have. Of course.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Yes, but to cause problems we now have?<br />
' PRIME MINISTER: Of course they have; of course they have. We<br />
' have a very great number of economic and social pieces of<br />
legislation which we promised to bring in. And they have delayed<br />
-them or rejected them.<br />
SCHILD3ERGER: But they wouldn't have -helped you solve the<br />
unemployment problems or the . inflation... I<br />
PRIME-MINISTER: Of course they would; of course they would.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: ' Well -hy?<br />
: PRIM. E.. MITNISTER: Well look at the delay there was in passing<br />
-there ; still is in passing the Trade Practices and Corporatio. is<br />
Legislation. We promised that. It had been very thoroughly<br />
-examined over years before we came in by Senate comrmittees.<br />
When. we put it up, it's delayed, it's shelved, it's even<br />
rejected. SCHILDBERGER: One of the other reasons why your Government<br />
doesn't have -such a good name at the moment is the loans affair.<br />
Was that a mistake?<br />
, P. RIME MINISTER: . In retrospect, in retrospect, . yes.<br />
* SCHILDBERGER: It was?<br />
PRIME . MINISTER: It didn't succeed; to that extent. yes. But<br />
-I will point out " that the country isn't a cent'worse off. And<br />
Australia's overseas standing, its credit worthiness is the<br />
, highest in the world. -We.. have triple A rating.<br />
' SCHILDBERGER: Are. you-sorry that you don't have the $ 8,000 million?<br />
PRIME-MINISTER: We could have used it very advantageously. 8,000?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Well, whatever figure it really was.<br />
PRIME IINISTER: ' Yes, well we should be precise. No, itnever was<br />
-never 8,000 was it?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: 8,000 million?<br />
PRIME MIIISTER: No it. never -was, was it?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: I don't know. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well it's all in Hansard. This has been<br />
common knowledge for months. Are you trying to-mislead<br />
your viewers?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: No, I would like you to tell me how much it<br />
really was?<br />
-PRIME MINISTER: It was 4,000 in December and January last.<br />
And then after that, for three months, it was 2,000. It<br />
was never 8,000. Now don't you try to mislead your viewers.<br />
You know what the figures were.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: I find it hard to know.<br />
PRIME MINSITER: There is no difficulty at all. Every question<br />
which has been asked has been answered. Every one. And<br />
nobody has challenged them.<br />
SCHILDBERCER: Why did you keep it a secret in December of<br />
last year?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Because loan raisings are never bruited abroad.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: But this was slightly different from the normal<br />
loans?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, the same method. If there was anything<br />
improper, anything illegal, don't you think that somebody<br />
in Parliament would have made that allegation? Nobody has.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: But they didn't know about it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They've known every fact. For months they've<br />
brought Public Servants before the bar of the House, they've<br />
brought a migrant millionaire before a bar of the House.<br />
They could have brought Mr Khemlani, but didn't. That is,<br />
they know perfectly well all the facts that there are to be<br />
known. And there is no wrong-doing whatever. Nowisn't it<br />
amazing that if there were any wrong-doing, that Mr Fraser or<br />
Mr Lynch or these unknown Senators would not even.., don't<br />
you think they would have made the allegations? But they<br />
haven't. SCHILDBERGER: You told Parliament that you had never met<br />
Mr Khemlani. Did you ever speak to him on the telephone?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No. Now, go on, pursue this question? Are<br />
you suggesting that I've ever seen him, spoken to him,<br />
written tb him?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: I'm not suggesting that at all. I want to<br />
ask you.... </p>
<p>P-RIME MINISTER: Well you ask me? You ask me?.<br />
-SCHILDBEPRGER: I would like to know why you didn't have<br />
-involvement with Mr Khemlani?<br />
PRI-E MINISTER: Why should I?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Because he was our supersalesman out to<br />
' raise -a lot of -money on Australia's behalf?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: He wasn't our salesman at all. ' Michael,<br />
I don't-know whether'you-are trying-to mislead your viewersi<br />
he was never our intermediary; he was never our agent;* he<br />
-was never our -salesman. Now this is quite clear -from all<br />
. the doctjaments, from all the debates, from all the. answers.<br />
There-is no excuse for you not t-el ling -the facts. The<br />
-coquntry -isn'. t a cent ou of pocket.)<br />
SCRiILDBERGER: Well, what -involvement did he have then? Wasn't<br />
he given the authority to seek money on our behalf?<br />
PRIME MINISTE.: No,, he was not.<br />
1-SCHILDBERG&amp; P.: -By 1,1r Connor?<br />
* PRIE'~-INISER: Mr-Connor was given authority to enter into<br />
arrangements for loans if Mr Khemlani introduced. p?-ople. PBut<br />
,' MNr Khemlani -was not our agent. He would -have been the agent<br />
' for, any pros~ ectiv~ e lender. He-was -not our agent.<br />
SCHLDERER M~ Kemani now says hc was,-able<br />
*,, PRIME MINISTE.: No he doesn' 1t., he ' doesn'It.<br />
; SCHILDBERGER: I think..<br />
PRI-1E IMINISTER: Well if you're accurate, yes.<br />
, BSCH. ILDBEOGER: Well quoting-him accurately. * That -he<br />
provided the money, was able to provide the money on the terms<br />
. andconditi~ ons requested by the Australian Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: He never put . up a proposition. -He never oDut'-<br />
. up -a proposition.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Well he claims, of course, -that he has...<br />
PRIMEMINISTER: Well he never did, he never did.<br />
SCHILDEERGER: Why do you -think he bothered coming to<br />
Australia now.'?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Wel~ l I presurme , that scme of the moedia<br />
" facilitated is -visit.<br />
SCHILDSERGEBR: Why do you think he would -be saying this?<br />
What you are accus ing him, of course, -is -being -a liar? </p>
<p>-11-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I don't reme Mber him saying this.<br />
But all I can say is he never put up a proposition. Never.<br />
Never. SCHILDBERGER: Prime Minister what happens to Gough Whitlam<br />
if the Labor Party happens to be out of office in the next<br />
few months?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Labor Government will not be out of<br />
office until the end of its three year term.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: And at the end of that three year term if<br />
Labor is out of office, what happens to Gough Whitlam?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think we will win the next election. You<br />
would have thought in April last year we wouldn't have won<br />
that election. We did. And we will win the next. And it'; s my<br />
responsibility to advise the Governor-General when the writs<br />
for the next House of Representatives election will be issued.<br />
And they won't be issued for at least a year.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: What about the long term for Gough Whitlam?<br />
What does the future hold?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh I don't know. I haven't really thought<br />
ten years ahead.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Do you think you'll be in office that long?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I've said all along I'll get out when<br />
I'm 65. That gives me nearly six years.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: You still holding office then...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I expect so.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Who will be the next leader of the Labcr Party?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. The Party decides that.<br />
There are very many good prospects.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Who would you like to see as the next leader?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh no, I don't... it's not an immediate<br />
option is it?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: No. Perhaps in six years?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Of course it ever be in six years.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Will Bob Hawke even be leader of the Party?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: If he gets into Parliament he has a very<br />
good chance. </p>
<p>a -12-<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Would you like. to see him as Leader of the<br />
Party? PRIME MINISTER: I would like him to be in the Parliament.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: As Leader?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, that's for the members to decide<br />
who are in the Party, in the Parliament, isn't it?<br />
SCHILDBERGER: One last question. When does-the present<br />
crisis, when do you believe that it will be resolved?<br />
-PRIME MINISTER: Within a month.<br />
SCHILD3ERGER: . What will happen at the end of that month?<br />
PRI-ME MINISTER: The Senate willpass the Budget. -And it<br />
will begin to work. And we will soar in public estimation<br />
-again.<br />
ISCHILDBERGER: Have you been too confident over the years and<br />
. perhaps -are now : being too confident?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I've never been so certain of anything in<br />
' my life as I am, that the Senate's money power will be<br />
' broken as a result of this crisis. No future Australian<br />
Government will ever be threatened by the Senate again, with<br />
a. rejection of its Budget or a refusal of Supply. Never again.<br />
-SCHILDBERGER: And you won't feel guilty if in the meantite<br />
-there is fighting . in the streets...<br />
. PRIME MINISTER: No, no " fighting in the streets",<br />
. don't threw that in! Who said there'll be fighting in the<br />
. streets? There won't be fighting in the streets. People<br />
. are incensed about what the Liberals are . doing, a second<br />
grab, Fraser doing a Snedden.. They are incensed but there will<br />
ot be violence. But I am determined to see that stability<br />
of government in Australia is never again threatened in this<br />
-unprecedented and reprehensible fashion.<br />
SCHILDBERGER: Thank you Prime Minister. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
