<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6354</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER, PARLIAMENTARY DINNER FOR PRIME MINISTER OF BURMA, CANBERRA, 2 APRIL 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006354.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED UNTIL 8.3OPM/<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY DINNER<br />
FOR PRIME MINISTER OF BURMA -CANBERRA 2 APRIL 1984<br />
Prime Minister U Maung Maung Kha,<br />
Distinguished Visitors,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
Mr Prime Minister welcome.<br />
Australia and Burma are old friends. Since your<br />
independence the ties between our countries have grown and<br />
strengthened. The importance we attach to our bilateral relationship has<br />
been reflected in the visits which have taken place between<br />
leaders of both our countries.<br />
The visit of President U Ne Win in 1974 gave a significant<br />
impetus to our relationship, and your visit at this time,<br />
ten years later, Mr Prime Minister, is a further important<br />
development. On our side the visit to Burma by my distinguished<br />
predecessor Gough Whitlam, the visit by the then Deputy<br />
Prime Minister Doug Anthony in 1982, and the Foreign<br />
Minister, Bill Hayden's visit to Burma last year, have all<br />
contributed to stronger links and a closer understanding<br />
between us.<br />
On another level, Burmese students have been welcome guests<br />
in our country for many years.<br />
Those Australians who have visited Burma as tourists, aid<br />
advisors, and business people, have found in your country<br />
and its culture a serenity unknown in Western societies.<br />
Through such contacts our prople get to know each other<br />
better. I believe that we should work to strengthen such<br />
contacts. </p>
<p>Only through these people to people contacts, can we be<br />
confident of knowing and understanding each other properly.<br />
Australia's involvement in the Asian region has for some<br />
years been increasing. Indeed we see our future as being<br />
closely bound up with that of the rest of the region.<br />
Australia has great respect for Burma's strong, principled<br />
stance on international issues and for your independent view<br />
on the affairs of our region. Burma's moderate, measured<br />
international posture does not obscure your importance in<br />
the political and economic life of the South and South East<br />
Asian region.<br />
It is therefore fitting that we are able to welcome you Mr<br />
Prime Minister and your colleagues to Australia tonight.<br />
Mr Prime Minister,<br />
Australia, as you know, is an aligned nation. We attach<br />
great importance to our relations with the United States.<br />
The ANZUS alliance is a fundamental plank in Australia's<br />
general strategic posture.<br />
Burma I have noted has had a long and deep commitment to the<br />
foundational principles of the non-aligned movement. Your<br />
concern at the departure from those principles by some<br />
members of the movement led to your country's withdrawal<br />
from the movement.<br />
That decision by Burma reflected the very real importance<br />
your country attaches to the maintenance of independence in<br />
its foreign policy.<br />
Australia shares a similar commitment to the maintenance of<br />
an independent foreign policy.<br />
In this regard I was particularly impressed, Mr Prime<br />
Minister, during our meeting this afternoon, at the<br />
coincidence of our views on Cambodia. We both are aware of<br />
the dangers of isolating Vietnam. We also share a concern<br />
about great power involvement in the region.<br />
We both seek with our neighbours in the region ties of<br />
friendship and goodwill so that peace and prosperity can be<br />
strengthened. My Government will continue to pursue an independent and<br />
self-respecting foreign policy, based like that of Burma on<br />
a principled concern for peace and security.<br />
My recent visit to regional countries convinced me of the<br />
dynamic economic potential in our area. Intra-regional<br />
trade is growing more rapidly than world trade as a whole. </p>
<p>3.<br />
This regional inter-dependence, in both trade and commerce,<br />
indicates quite clearly that countries of the region will<br />
continue to benefit from each other's growth.<br />
During our discussions this afternoon you outlined your<br />
Government's plans to develop your natural resources.<br />
Australia has developed competitive, efficient, world<br />
standard expertise in ore extraction, concentration and<br />
benefication, the transportation of ores, and the<br />
establishment and management of mining projects.<br />
Our private sector, which has considerable expertise in<br />
mining, transportation infrastructure development, and in<br />
the supply of equipment, can play a real part in helping you<br />
to bring your plans in this area to fulfilment.<br />
I am pleased that you will be seeing something of our<br />
developments in mineral and offshore oil while you are here.<br />
I am also pleased that a delegation from your Ministry of<br />
for Mines will visit Australia later in the year to discuss<br />
in greater detail how we might be able to help Burma's<br />
development in these areas.<br />
As we discussed this afternoon Australia proposes to<br />
increase its aid to your country with an expanded program of<br />
$ 46 million over the next three years.<br />
This multi-year commitment will allow greater project<br />
flexibility and could also include involvement in the<br />
development of your minerals and mining sector.<br />
As I said before, we are old friends. That friendship was<br />
amply demonstrated in your gift of Burmese teak plywood to<br />
the appeal for the victims of the appalling bush fires in<br />
South East Australia in February of last year.<br />
We thank you for that gift.<br />
We were saddened to learn of the loss of life and property<br />
occasioned by the partial destruction by fire of the<br />
historic city of Mandalay. An Australian contribution to<br />
relieve the burden of that disaster has already been made.<br />
The prompt response that each country has made to disasters<br />
afflicting the other evinces not only humanitarian sentiment<br />
but the mutual regard that exists between our two peoples.<br />
Mr Prime Minister, Distinguished quests<br />
I look forward to the continued strengthening of relations<br />
between our two countries. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
