<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>172</transcript-id>
    <title>P.M. NO. 14/1960 - BLUE STREAK - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000172.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P. M. No. 14/ 60<br />
BLUE STREAK<br />
Statement by the Pyime Minister the Rt. IHonn JiL., jMenzies<br />
The United Kingdom Government have issued a<br />
statement concerning the long range missile Blue StreWd<br />
The statement was discussed with the Australian Government.<br />
The Australian Government concurred in it. Text of the<br />
statement is attached.<br />
CANBERRA 14th April, 1960. </p>
<p>0<br />
0<br />
0<br />
I 0 0 </p>
<p>3LUE S3TREAK<br />
The Government have been considering the future of the<br />
project for developing the long range ballistic missile Blue<br />
Streak and have been in touch with the Australian Government<br />
about it in view of their interest in the Joint Project and the<br />
operation of the Joomera range.<br />
The technique of controlling ballistic missiles has<br />
rapidly advanced. The vulnerability of missiles launched from<br />
static sites and the practicability of launching missiles of<br />
considerable range from'mobile platforms has now been established.<br />
In the light of our military advice to this effect and of the<br />
importance of reinforcing the effectiveness of the deterrent we<br />
have concluded and the Australian Government have fully accepted<br />
that we ought not to continue to develop as a military % Jeapon a<br />
missile that can be launched only from a fixed site.<br />
Today our strate-ic nuclear force is an effective and<br />
significant contribution to the deterrent power of the free<br />
world. The Government do not intend to give up this independent<br />
contribution and therefore some other vehicle will in due course<br />
be needed in place of Blue Streak to carry British manufactured<br />
nuclear warheads. The need for this is not immediately urgent<br />
since the effectiveness of the V--bomber force as the vehicle for<br />
these warheads will remain unimpaired for several years to come,<br />
nor is it possible at the moment to say with certainty which of<br />
several possibilities or combinations of them would be technically<br />
themost suitable. On present information there appears much<br />
to be said for prolonging the effectiveness of the V-bombers by<br />
buying supplies of the airborne ballistic missile Skybolt which<br />
is being developed in the United States. H. Mv. Government understands<br />
that the United States Govermient will be favourably disposed<br />
to the purchase by the United Kingdom at the appropriate<br />
time of supplies of this vehicle.<br />
The Government will now consider with the firms and<br />
other interests concerned as a. mat-ter of urgency whether the Blue<br />
Streak programme could be adapted for the development of a<br />
launcher for space satellites. A further statement will be made<br />
to tGhe House as soon as possible.<br />
This decision ofcourse does not mean that the ., rork at<br />
ioomera will be ended. On the contrary there are many other<br />
projects for which the range is needed. 11e thcer, fore expect<br />
that for some years to come at least there will be a substantial<br />
programme of work for that range. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
