<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8158</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF SPEECH TO INTERNATIONAL IRON AND STEEL ANNUAL CONFERENCE DINNER, REGENT HOTEL, SYDNEY 9 OCTOBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008158.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF SPEECH TO INTERNATIONAL IRON AND STEEL<br />
ANNUAL CONFERENCE DINNER, REGENT HOTEL, SYDNEY<br />
9 OCTOBER 19190<br />
E OE PRCOOF ONLY<br />
PM: Sir Robert and Brian Loton. Brian, thank you very<br />
much for that introduction. May I at the outset thank<br />
the conference for the invitation that they have extended<br />
to me. And secondly, most importantly, ladies and<br />
gentlemen, on behalf of the Government and the people of<br />
Australia, J: extend to you the most hearty welcome to our<br />
country. We thank you for the honour that you've done us by<br />
assembling and meeting here and having your important<br />
deliberations in our country. I wish you well for those<br />
deliberations and upon your return to your respective<br />
countries. I have, ladies and gentlemen, discarded my prepared<br />
speech. I think to some extent my friend and colleague<br />
Paul Keating; covered some of the ground that I had<br />
thought I would cover in talking about the economic<br />
development in this country.<br />
Rather I thought you might find it more helpful and I<br />
think in a -sense I would find it more interesting if I<br />
were really to share some thoughts with you on issues<br />
which in a sense are common to you in business and to we<br />
in Government.<br />
Because I believe that in a very real sense the<br />
challenges confronting business and Government are<br />
essentially the same. But when you strip it down the<br />
challenges that confront you in business and confronts us<br />
in Government is to try and read the environment in which<br />
we'fre operating. I don't use the environment in the more<br />
technical sense that it's talked about now but in the<br />
broader sense of the word. To read the environment in<br />
which we're operating and in a sense to try and shape<br />
that environment. That's the challenge that confronts<br />
you as businessmen. And it's certainly the challenge<br />
that confronts an intelligent Government.<br />
So, what I thought may be useful, is if I was to share<br />
some thoughts with you from a prospective of now having<br />
been Prime Minister of this country for over seven and a </p>
<p>half years, about how I've seen that in terms of<br />
Australia, how I've seen it in terms of the region and<br />
how I've seen it in terms of the world.<br />
May I talk about Australia first. This is indeed a<br />
remarkable country by any sort of standards that you<br />
would wish to apply. You would know that there has been<br />
applied to us the term, the lucky country. And in a<br />
very real sense that was an intelligent phrase to apply<br />
to Australia.<br />
I don't want to go right back into history but let me<br />
briefly talk in terms of the post-war period. The war<br />
for Australia was a dramatic, but compared with others,<br />
not a traumatic experience. True it is that Australia<br />
lost thousands of men, some women, in the war, and tens<br />
of thousands of Australian families were touched by the<br />
tragedy of war. But compared with the experience of<br />
others, Australia was not only not badly damaged but in a<br />
sense it was a growing up period for Australia.<br />
We had to learn to do things that we hadn't done before.<br />
Then, importantly, during the darkest period of the war,<br />
we had a Government, and I take pride in saying it was a<br />
Labor Government, which while accepting the challenge of<br />
defending this country in war, also had a view that in<br />
the post-war period we must try and shape a better<br />
Australia than the one within which we went into the war.<br />
And part of that thinking involved one of the most<br />
imaginative decisions that any country has ever<br />
undertaken, and that is the vast migration program that<br />
characterised the early post-war years in this country.<br />
At the end of the Second World War we were a country of<br />
seven million people. But with this vast migration<br />
program we expanded our population: we're now 17 million<br />
people. It was one of the great migration programs in<br />
the whole of recorded history.<br />
It posed the challenges for us as a society. And I can<br />
recall as a young man in my first year at university<br />
after the war in 1947. My first year as a law student<br />
seems like a thousand years ago. It's not; it's only<br />
some 43. And I can remember being touched and worried by<br />
the way in which my country was responding to some of<br />
these challenges of change at that time.<br />
We were not generous in our initial attitudes to those<br />
who had chosen to come from other countries and make<br />
Australia their home. In those days the target of shortsighted<br />
Australians was the Italians and the Greeks who<br />
were the major non-British groups who were making up the<br />
new wave of immigrants to our country. There were some<br />
unpleasant experiences for those people at that time.<br />
Of course we went through the period up until the 1960s<br />
where our immigration policy was characterised by racism. </p>
<p>We had the White Australia Policy which was morally<br />
shameful, anti as I've said, also economically insane.<br />
But to the gr7eat credit of both political parties in this<br />
country in the 1960s, we changed and have adopted a nondiscriminatory<br />
policy.<br />
In economic t: erms we were lucky in that period because a<br />
war-devastated world cried out for what we could produce<br />
in our great rural industries.<br />
The world pai~ d enormous prices for our wheat and our wool<br />
and our meat. We were exceedingly prosperous. We<br />
pursued a short-sighted policy industrially by erecting<br />
very considerable tariff barriers behind which we<br />
employed so many of these hundreds of thousands of people<br />
who came to make Australia their home.<br />
We were indeed the lucky country because we were paid so<br />
much for what we produced. And when the world started to<br />
be able more easily to feed itself and the prices for our<br />
agricultural commodities subsided, we went into our first<br />
great mineral. s boom.<br />
And so really in the whole of that period from the end of<br />
the Second World War up until the 70s, Australia was the<br />
lucky country. We were able to have considerably<br />
expanding popu * lations, fairly steady economic growth,<br />
fairly consistently full employment and rising standards<br />
of living.<br />
We were lucky, but in a paradoxical sense we were<br />
unlucky. Because the bounty which we so easily received<br />
tended to lead my fellow Australians into believing that<br />
in a sense the world owed us a living. There wasn't very<br />
much we really had to do to make our way in the world.<br />
It wasn't until really the 70s that there started to<br />
begin the dawn of understanding that the world wasn't<br />
quite as easy, as all that.<br />
But it hasn't been, I believe, until the 1980s and<br />
Brian, you've! been very generous in your comments about<br />
this I think it hasn't been until this last decade that<br />
Australia has really started to understand the truth of<br />
this tough, hard, competitive world in which we live.<br />
My friend and. colleague Paul Keating would last night<br />
have gone-through with you many of the economic<br />
decisions, the policy concepts that we've applied, to try<br />
and change Australia, as I have put it, in the last<br />
election, to try and change Australia from being thinking<br />
of itself as the lucky country into changing itself into<br />
being the clever country.<br />
I don't want to this evening, my friends, really go over<br />
all those things that my friend Paul has spoken with you<br />
about. But I did want to say something about, in a<br />
sense, what has been foundational to the economic policy </p>
<p>changes that we've made and in which in a sense I think<br />
are of significance for you as you think about this<br />
country and as you think about your own and as you think<br />
about the world.<br />
Because I think much of what has happened in this country<br />
in a way has been reflected in some of the vast changes<br />
around the world and to which I want to refer in a<br />
moment. I took the view when I became the Prime Minister of this<br />
country in 1983 that we were indeed an extremely<br />
fortunate country because there are very few countries in<br />
the world which are blessed with the features that we<br />
have.<br />
What I simply, and without being exhaustive, they are<br />
firstly a land of some 17 million people who<br />
paradoxically are very heterogeneous in terms of their<br />
countries of origin, but very homogeneous in the<br />
commitment, the universal commitment in this country to<br />
the processes of parliamentary democracy. The concepts<br />
and practice of terrorism are alien to Australians.<br />
So that is one great advantage that we have. The concept<br />
of the institutions of parliamentary democracy are deeply<br />
and unalterably entrenched in this country.<br />
As you know, from your industry, this is also a country<br />
of vast natural resources. Almost unmatched, in a sense,<br />
in the range and the depth of those resources.<br />
We are now strategically placed in the world, in a region<br />
which is the most dynamically-growing region of the<br />
world. So I thought it strange, as I assumed the<br />
responsibilities of Prime Ministership in this country,<br />
that we really hadn't done as well as I think we should<br />
have. It was because in a sense we were remarkably stupid<br />
amidst this luxury of benefits, if you like, and<br />
endowments that we had.<br />
It seemed to me that we were, as a society, an economy,<br />
stupidly short-sighted in the way in which we pursued our<br />
interests. As far as the trade union movement, the<br />
organised labour movement was concerned, we perceived our<br />
interests as just being involved in trying to get the<br />
biggest wage increases that we could and the best<br />
improvement in conditions on the assumption that there<br />
was a limitless cornucopia there which would provide the<br />
satisfaction for our desires.<br />
So that short-sightedness greed, if you like was I<br />
think at least equally matched on the side of business<br />
who didn't really have a sense of identity of interest<br />
with those whom they employed but sought to advance their<br />
interests by simply thinking of a maximisation of their </p>
<p>own position. And it was inevitable, if you had two<br />
sides of industry like that, and particularly if you had<br />
a Government which at times tended to fuel that<br />
atmosphere of confrontation, it was simply inevitable<br />
that this country was not going to do its best.<br />
And indeed, as Brian knows, as we've talked as recently<br />
as tonight, the steel industry in this country was in<br />
some sense a microcosm of the problems that we had. A<br />
great company, BHP, a very significant company in the<br />
history of this country and still a very significant part<br />
of our diversified economy.<br />
But within that industry, through a mixture of attitudes,<br />
the part of management and also of the trade union<br />
movement, the industry was running down and there was<br />
even contemplation perhaps of whether it would continue.<br />
But in a sense it was a microcosm of the problems of this<br />
country. The view that I brought with my colleagues to the<br />
Government was that we shouldn't be altruistic, in a<br />
sense, in believing that some sense of morality and some<br />
highly developed sense of the public good was going to<br />
motivate people into sensible action.<br />
It seemed to me that what may move people to more<br />
sensible action was a developed understanding of their<br />
own self-interest. Self-interest always is operative.<br />
I wanted, with my colleagues, to explain to the Labor<br />
movement and to explain to industry, that both their aims<br />
were legitimate. It is legitimate for working men and<br />
their organisations to want to improve their conditions,<br />
their standards, their own personal standards, and to<br />
improve their capacity to look after those who are<br />
dependent upon them.<br />
Those are legitimate, they are indeed worthy objectives.<br />
And equally, it is a totally worthy objective of industry<br />
that it should seek to grow, to prosper, to increase its<br />
profitable capacity to invest further and to grow.<br />
They are not, and should not, be seen to be contradictory<br />
aims. What we tried to convey to the trade union<br />
movement of this country, and to our friends in the<br />
business community was that if indeed that they concede<br />
their identity of interests, they were both more likely<br />
to prosper, that you would create a greater security of<br />
employment in this country, more jobs, and that you would<br />
create the environment for a growing industry if in fact<br />
there was more co-operation and consensus in approach<br />
than confrontation.<br />
So that was our philosophy, if you like, and it was<br />
reflected in this country in the Accord between the<br />
Government and the trade union movement and in which very<br />
substantially the business community co-operated. </p>
<p>In the result we have had remarkable successes. I don't<br />
know whether Paul went to all the statistics, but one<br />
which is fundamentally important as far as we are<br />
concerned has been the growth in employment.<br />
We've had a rate of employment growth which has given us<br />
1.6 million new jobs, with 90% of those new jobs in the<br />
private sector. A rate of employment growth which is<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the OECD.<br />
Those things could not have happened if in fact the trade<br />
union movement had not exercised, and as the business<br />
community has acknowledged, the very considerable<br />
restraint in the capacity they would have otherwise had<br />
to go for higher increases in money wages.<br />
We as a Government assume some of the responsibility of<br />
the expense of labour by significantly increasing what<br />
we're pleased to call the social wage. And in that way,<br />
Labor in this country was prepared to substitute to some<br />
extent increases in money wages for increases in the<br />
social wage which were reflected in the area of health<br />
care, education, child care and the like.<br />
Now in that way my friends, we have in this country, I<br />
think, attitudinally undergone a revolution. If there is<br />
one plea that I would make in talking about my country<br />
with so many representatives, distinguished<br />
representatives and strategically important<br />
representatives of industry from around the world, it is<br />
this. That you should please understand that any<br />
stereotype that you had in your mind about Australian<br />
industrial relations of the past is not true of the<br />
present. There has been more than almost a 60% reduction in<br />
industrial disputes in this country; a 10% reduction in<br />
non-farm real unit labour costs; a significant move from<br />
wages to profits which has been associated with an<br />
historically high level of investment. And those things<br />
basically have come about not simply through changes in<br />
economic policy of which you are aware, but all those<br />
have been founded upon this philosophical, if you like,<br />
attitude that this country which has been the lucky<br />
country can only be a successful and competitive country<br />
in this tough new world if it indeed was going to set<br />
about the business of trying to work more sensibly<br />
together. I do ask you to understand that you are looking at a<br />
country now which is undergoing that transformation,<br />
which is accepting the challenge that it can no longer be<br />
seen as the lucky country, that we have to make our way<br />
in the world, that we have to be competitive and in doing<br />
that, let me say to you that we understand that we can't<br />
do it by ourselves. </p>
<p>.4 . I 7<br />
We welcome investment from overseas in this country and<br />
wherever it comes. We understand that we need the best<br />
of new technology that is available from around the world<br />
which harnessed with our resources and with a skilled<br />
labour force is capable of developing this country in a<br />
way which we cannot do by ourselves.<br />
Now of course these changes that have been taking place<br />
in this lucky country which is now becoming a more<br />
sophisticated country have been occurring of course in a<br />
world and a region which is changing almost beyond<br />
measure. I would like to say just a few words about that<br />
if I may.<br />
We are of course, ladies and gentlemen, singularly<br />
fortunate to be living at this point in history. There<br />
has probably not been a more exciting time to be alive<br />
than this present age. The world that we're living in<br />
now is almost unrecognisably different from that world in<br />
which we all grew up. Not merely in material and<br />
technological terms, but now excitingly in political<br />
terms. We have witnessed just in this last few years the most<br />
dramatic transformation in international relationships in<br />
the whole of recorded history. Until just two or three<br />
years ago the two super powers were concentrating their<br />
efforts on a seemingly endless accumulation of the means<br />
of destruction which could destroy not only each other<br />
but the world thousands of times over.<br />
This was both frightening and it was economically insane.<br />
The of the magic chemistry of circumstances can't<br />
entirely wait and define but which, when history is<br />
written will pay very great tribute to two men, Reagan<br />
and Gorbachev. Due to a magic chemistry, but also due to<br />
what I see as an understanding at the international level<br />
of the truth of what we've seen in this country, that is<br />
that the true protection and advancement of the interests<br />
of the people of the Soviet Union and the people of the<br />
United States was much more likely to be achieved by<br />
consensus and co-operation than conflict and the absence<br />
of consensus. That understanding dawned and we have seen<br />
now those great powers seeking to work together to<br />
advance the interests of their own people in that way<br />
rather than by fighting one another.<br />
Of course that has immeasurable implications for us all.<br />
It is not the time or the occasion of course to attempt<br />
to analyse all the implications of what's happening. But<br />
I do say this, that it seems to me that it is profoundly<br />
in the interests of us all to ensure that those great<br />
changes that are taking place in Eastern Europe and the<br />
Soviet Union are given the maximum chance of succeeding.<br />
Because that will be good, not only for the people of<br />
Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, that they will come<br />
to understand the immeasurable benefits of a free society </p>
<p>S..<br />
8<br />
both in political and economic terms but it will also be<br />
of immeasurable benefit to the rest of the world in terms<br />
of our security and in economic terms in the opening up<br />
of greatly increased market opportunities and<br />
possibilities for international trade and commerce<br />
between us all.<br />
But even so far as this region is concerned, I would like<br />
to say just a few things here. Until we became the<br />
Government in 1983, Australians, thinking Australians had<br />
tended to express the view that Australia was part of the<br />
Asian region. But it had been very largely lip service.<br />
One of the commitments I made when I became Prime<br />
Minister was that we would try and translate that lip<br />
service into reality.<br />
And so in the seven and a half years since we have been<br />
in office, we have attempted in reality to move to enmesh<br />
the Australian economy into the economy of the region.<br />
That's been done essentially in these ways. Firstly by<br />
strengthening the bilateral relations that we have with<br />
the countries with the region. Very importantly, at the<br />
beginning of the last year, I took the initiative in<br />
Seoul to move to establish what has now become know as<br />
APEC, the Asian Pacific Economic Co-operation Council.<br />
We are proud here in Australia of the way in which the<br />
countries of the region have responded to that call.<br />
What we are seeking to do there is to give substance to<br />
the truth, that the countries of this region are the more<br />
likely to grow both in economic prosperity in terms of<br />
political security if we take steps to try and enmesh our<br />
economies together. And that movement now, I believe, is<br />
irreversible and the next stages of that process are to<br />
look to the enlargement of APEC by looking at the three<br />
Chinas; mainland China, Taiwan, Hong Kong. And then I<br />
believe later down the path we'll also be able to look<br />
at, if the Soviet Union develops a marked economy and it<br />
inevitably will, the possibility of the Soviet Union<br />
joining as well.<br />
As far as Australia is concerned my friends, we see our<br />
future very much as being identified with the region.<br />
May I say to my friends from Europe that it does not mean<br />
in any sense that we see an end to our important<br />
relationships with Europe. A country which has been<br />
established in the way we have which owes its<br />
institutions to the United Kingdom is not going to break<br />
those relationships into the future. But it is the case<br />
that if you look at it in economic terms our future is<br />
very much in this region.<br />
May I say particularly therefore to those representatives<br />
from Japan and other countries in this region that we<br />
want you to look at Australia no longer as some isolated<br />
outpost of Europe. We are a country which is indebted to </p>
<p>A I 9<br />
our origins for the institutions that have made us a<br />
great parliamentary democracy.<br />
But essentially our economic future is in this region and<br />
we seek to enmesh ourselves with it and we are in the<br />
position my friends where we have in a sense put our<br />
decisions where our mouth is.<br />
That leads me to the final thing that I want to say. It<br />
is this, that it will indeed be one of the great<br />
paradoxes of our time and one of the fatal paradoxes if<br />
we are part of this great transition in international<br />
political relationships which offer for the first time in<br />
the nuclear age the possibility of security, if we, as<br />
being part of that, make the fatal mistake of not showing<br />
the same degree of intelligence in the way we organise<br />
our international trading relationships.<br />
To be specific, we are now as an international community<br />
coming to a deadline in the Uruguay Round. It is<br />
scheduled to finish at the end of this year. I tend to<br />
think that because of the diversion of resources and<br />
intelligence that have been associated with the Gulf<br />
crisis that there may be some extension beyond the end of<br />
this year to try and get an outcome.<br />
But let me say this, that if we do not get a successful<br />
outcome to the Uruguay Round in which, speaking from a<br />
point of view of Australians there was appropriate<br />
recognition of the need to get a freeing up of trade in<br />
agricultural products, then it is very likely that the<br />
Uruguay Round will end in failure.<br />
If that were to happen, history certainly would teach us<br />
this, that if you descend into economic autarky because<br />
you cannot in fact have sensible international trading<br />
relations, then you move very quickly towards a deeply<br />
de-stabilised political situation. And that would indeed<br />
be the fatal paradox a world which has shown its<br />
capacity politically to come to mature decisions in terms<br />
of its relations but then blew that up against the wall<br />
by not being able to make sensible international trading<br />
decisions. That's why my friends we in Australia have taken a lead<br />
in the formation of the Cairns Group which has become now<br />
an established entity in these negotiations between the<br />
European. community and the United States of America. We<br />
will continue to show leadership in that area. Not<br />
simply in pursuit of our own interests, although they are<br />
present, but in the basis of a very firm conviction that<br />
our own interests and the interests of all other nations<br />
are only going to be properly served if we do have a<br />
fully freed-up international trading system. I believe<br />
you in your important industry will and should share<br />
those views. </p>
<p>So it means I hope that you will see in what I've been<br />
trying to say to you that we in this country have<br />
understood that we live in a world which is changing with<br />
almost alarming and immeasurable rapidity. In that<br />
rapidly changing world it has not been good enough, and<br />
it will not be good enough, to adhere to outmoded<br />
assumptions and practices of the past, whether that be on<br />
the part of unions, or government. We have attempted<br />
in this country to harness those forces of change<br />
constructively so that we can both advance our own<br />
interests and be a constructive partner in the region and<br />
the rest of the world.<br />
May I conclude by saying that I would think and believe<br />
many of those thoughts which I've expressed would be<br />
relevant to your own business operations within your own<br />
countries and in your relations, one with the other. And<br />
indeed the very fact that you're meeting together in this<br />
forum seems to me to be indicative of your understanding<br />
of that necessity to work with one another rather than<br />
against one another.<br />
So in conclusion I thank you again for the invitation<br />
that you've extended to me. I wish you well in your<br />
deliberations. Finally, I repeat, I hope that you will<br />
learn from your perhaps brief stay in this country that<br />
Australia is now a different country. We're not just the<br />
lucky country. We recognise that we are a country which<br />
has to be clever and has to live with the rest of the<br />
world, compete with the rest of the world, co-operate<br />
with the rest of the world.<br />
I can assure you that you will find in Australia a<br />
willing partner in your endeavours.<br />
Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
