<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11341</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT AUSTRALIAN BANKING &amp;amp; FINANCE AWARDS                 HILTON HOTEL, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, thank you very much, Maxine. To Graham Wallace, Chris Anderson,</p>
<p> Peter Charlton, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It's a particular honour for me to be here tonight, to say a</p>
<p> few words about the importance of your industry, perhaps one or two</p>
<p> other things as well and also to present awards to the winners. And</p>
<p> can I at the beginning congratulate Peter Charlton and his publication</p>
<p> for its sponsorship of these awards and Cable and Wireless of course</p>
<p> for its sponsorship of this gathering tonight. I can remember Peter</p>
<p> Charlton rather excitedly saying to me as we both boarded an aircraft</p>
<p> about ten years ago that he had taken over this magazine and he hoped</p>
<p> to make something really big of it. I think you have been very successful,</p>
<p> Peter, and I think the prestige of these annual banking and financial</p>
<p> awards is a testament to your energy and your drive.</p>
<p>The last year has been a very good year indeed, not only for the Australian</p>
<p> economy, but also for the banking and financial industry. You don't</p>
<p> need reminding that we have seen over the last year in relative terms</p>
<p> probably the greatest performance of the Australian economy for about</p>
<p> three decades. We have been truly successful in staring down the worst</p>
<p> economic collapse that the Asia Pacific region has seen in the lifetime</p>
<p> of most people in this room. And one of the reasons that we have been</p>
<p> able to do that is that we have had a very stable, a very secure,</p>
<p> a very well regulated and an increasingly outward looking banking</p>
<p> and financial industry in this country. And it's worth exploring</p>
<p> for a moment as to how that happened and also relating that series</p>
<p> of developments with other challenges and other issues that Australia</p>
<p> faces at the present time.</p>
<p>It will be twenty five years tomorrow since I entered Federal Parliament.</p>
<p> And the banking and financial system of our nation in the mid to late</p>
<p> 1970s was vastly different from what it is now. It was inward looking,</p>
<p> it was insular it operated in a different world environment, it operated</p>
<p> not entirely under a fixed exchange rate mechanism but under a system</p>
<p> known colloquially there as a crawling peg whereby the bands within</p>
<p> which the Australian dollars rate of exchange moved were strictly</p>
<p> circumscribed by government officials. And of course, no foreign banks</p>
<p> were allowed to operate in Australia. In 1979 when I was Treasurer</p>
<p> the Fraser Government commissioned the establishment of the Campbell</p>
<p> Inquiry. That Campbell Inquiry as everyone in this room knows was</p>
<p> quite historic in that it recommended major deregulation of the Australian</p>
<p> financial system. Some changes to implement those recommendations</p>
<p> had been made before the change of government occurred in 1983.</p>
<p>And although in opposition the Labor Party had been opposed to financial</p>
<p> deregulation when the Hawke government came to power there was a refreshing</p>
<p> change in policy. The new Prime Minister strongly supported by the</p>
<p> Reserve Bank of Australia argued for and secured the floating of the</p>
<p> Australian dollar and from then on his Treasurer, Mr Keating, my predecessor</p>
<p> as Prime Minister, set about enthusiastically implementing with some</p>
<p> change as a result of the recommendations of Vic Martin's committee</p>
<p> the recommendations of Campbell. And he did that with very strong</p>
<p> bipartisan support from myself as economic spokesman and generally</p>
<p> from the Coalition Opposition.</p>
<p>And so it came to be that as a result of that set of circumstances</p>
<p> and that chain of events Australia developed through the 1980s and</p>
<p> into the 1990s one of the most modern, progressive and outward looking</p>
<p> banking and financial systems in the world. The Australian approach</p>
<p> was seen as something of a model and in a number of areas we trail</p>
<p> blazed for other countries which in other areas it had been our custom</p>
<p> to follow. And in coming to office in 1996, my Treasurer, Peter Costello,</p>
<p> established the Wallis Inquiry which conducted something of a stocktake</p>
<p> of what had happened post-Campbell and recommended a number of other</p>
<p> very significant changes.</p>
<p>So, thus you can see that over a twenty year period we have had a</p>
<p> long continuity of reform and outward-looking policies in relation</p>
<p> to the banking and financial system. And it has borne fruit because</p>
<p> the strength and the stability and the progressivity of our banking</p>
<p> system is one of the reasons why we are seen as having such economic</p>
<p> strength in our region. And one of the ironies of watching how Australia</p>
<p> has performed with other nations in the region is to recall some of</p>
<p> the thing that were said about our banking practices and our economic</p>
<p> practices only a few years ago by some of the nations in our region</p>
<p> that seemed to be out performing us economically. There were even</p>
<p> suggestions that we were too stodgy, we were too conservative, we</p>
<p> were too heavily regulated and some of the prudential requirements</p>
<p> were too severe. Nobody says that anymore. One of the bull points</p>
<p> of the Australian economy is that we have a stable, strong, secure</p>
<p> and well and prudentially regulated banking system.</p>
<p>And it is a source of strength, it is a source of reassurance and</p>
<p> what a few years ago was perhaps seen as stodgy is now seen as one</p>
<p> of the reasons that makes Australia an extremely attractive place</p>
<p> in which to invest.</p>
<p>Now, the lesson in all of that, ladies and gentlemen, is that we can</p>
<p> have great reform, we can have beneficial change, we can have a world</p>
<p> class structure in this country if necessary reform enjoys strong</p>
<p> bipartisan support. It would not have been possible to have the strong</p>
<p> banking and financial structure we now have in this country had it</p>
<p> not been for the fact that both sides of politics saw the national</p>
<p> benefit and the national interest in that area. If one or other side</p>
<p> of politics at various stages over the last twenty years had run an</p>
<p> emotional, populist campaign against financial deregulation we would</p>
<p> not have the benefit of that deregulation which is there for all of</p>
<p> us to see. And it would not surprise you for me to say that there</p>
<p> is a lesson in that in relation to the great and burning economic</p>
<p> issue of today and that is taxation reform.</p>
<p>It is true that reforming Australia's taxation system remains</p>
<p> the largest piece of unfinished economic business in this country.</p>
<p> Of all the great challenges of economic reform that were obvious twenty</p>
<p> years ago to any serious player upon the Australian political scene,</p>
<p> one of them was taxation reform. We have reformed our industrial relations</p>
<p> system, although there is still more work to be done. We have reformed</p>
<p> our financial system quite dramatically, we have demolished the old</p>
<p> stultifying tariff structure that encourage inward looking introspection</p>
<p> so far as our industries are concerned. The one great area of further</p>
<p> reform remains our taxation system.</p>
<p>And that is why at the last election my government committed itself</p>
<p> with all the perils involved in total disclosure of every last detail</p>
<p> to the reform of that taxation system. [Tape break]...that</p>
<p> if we made full and accurate and painstaking disclosure our moral</p>
<p> case to ask that our proposals be passed through both Houses of Parliament</p>
<p> would be compelling, if not overwhelming. Reforming Australia's</p>
<p> taxation system is essential for many reasons. It's essential</p>
<p> to ensure that this country remains competitive in a global world.</p>
<p> It is no good saying to you that we are doing better now that we were</p>
<p> five years ago unless I am able to say to you that in five years time</p>
<p> we will be outperforming our competitors. In a global world it is</p>
<p> how you do against the other competitors in the race, not how you</p>
<p> do compared with how you were doing five years ago that really counts.</p>
<p>We need to reform the Australian taxation system if we are to realise</p>
<p> our dream of making Australia a world centre for financial services.</p>
<p> Because imbedded in the taxation reform package is the removal of</p>
<p> many taxes like the bank accounts debits tax, the financial institutions</p>
<p> duty, the stamp duty on share transactions, all of which contribute</p>
<p> towards providing reasons why financial institutions may not establish</p>
<p> their activities and do their business in this country.</p>
<p>We have so much going for us in the generic economic social and political</p>
<p> area that we would be very negligent indeed if we didn't remove</p>
<p> the other barriers that should be removed in order to realise that</p>
<p> dream. We have a stable political system. We have an absolutely superb</p>
<p> lifestyle. We have clear rules of corporate governance. We have an</p>
<p> incorruptible legal system. We speak the English language. We are</p>
<p> beautifully situated so far as the time zones are concerned and we're</p>
<p> seen to have an economy which has outperformed most not only in our</p>
<p> region but around the world. We therefore have a wonderful springboard</p>
<p> from which to launch our drive to become a major financial centre.</p>
<p>But one of the things that we need to remove, one of the barriers</p>
<p> we need to remove, is of course the barrier of a taxation system which</p>
<p> is not as conducive to making this country a financial centre as it</p>
<p> might be.</p>
<p>So, my friends, there is a lesson from the experience of financial</p>
<p> deregulation in the long run the national interest ought to prevail,</p>
<p> in the long run we should stop playing games about important reforms.</p>
<p> We didn't play games about financial reform and for that I have</p>
<p> always given credit to my political opponents. They should stop playing</p>
<p> games with taxation reform because the national interest demands that</p>
<p> we rid ourselves of a taxation system that has long outlived its usefulness.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, can I in advance congratulate all of those who</p>
<p> will be taking awards tonight. Can I thank the participants in the</p>
<p> banking and financial industry of Australia for the contribution they</p>
<p> have made to our national economic wealth, for the contribution they</p>
<p> have made to innovation in financial products, for the contribution</p>
<p> they have made to establishing the reputation of this country as a</p>
<p> wonderful country in which to do business.</p>
<p>I have valued for a long time my association with the financial community</p>
<p> not only of Sydney but of Australia generally. It is an industry and</p>
<p> a community that has changed enormously over the last twenty years.</p>
<p> And it has been associated during that period with the dynamism and</p>
<p> the change and the reform zeal of the Australian economy and the Australian</p>
<p> nation. It is truly part of the globalised modern Australia. It plays</p>
<p> an impressive role. It looks back on a year of enormous achievement</p>
<p> and quite rightly tonight those who have been the stars of that achievement</p>
<p> will be well and truly recognised by their peers. Thank you.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
