<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3849</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR EG WHITLAM QC MP, AT THE GURINDJI LAND CEREMONY ON 16 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003849.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR E. G. WHITLAM,<br />
AT THE GURINDJI LAND CEREMONY ON 16 AUGUST 1975<br />
Vincent Lingiari and men and women of the Gurindji people.<br />
On this great day, I, Prime Minister of Australia,<br />
speak to you on behalf of the Australian people all those<br />
who honour and love this land we live in.<br />
For them I want to say to you:<br />
First, that we congratulate you and those who shared<br />
your struggle, on the victory you have achieved 9 years after<br />
you walked off Wave Hill Station in protest.<br />
I want to acknowledge that we Australians have still<br />
much to do to redress the injustice and oppression that has<br />
for so long been the loss of Black Australians.<br />
I want to promise you that this act of restitution<br />
which we perform today will not stand alone your fight was<br />
not for yourselves alone and we are determined that Aboriginal<br />
Australians everywhere will be helped by it.<br />
I want to promise that, through their Government, the<br />
people of Australia will help you in your plans to use this<br />
land fruitfully for the Gurindji.<br />
And I want to give back to you formally in Aboriginal<br />
and Australian Law ownership of this land of your fathers.<br />
Vincent Lingiari I solemnly hand to you these deeds<br />
as proof, in Australian law, that these lands belong<br />
to the Gurindji people and I put into your hands part<br />
of the earth itself as a sign that this land will be<br />
the possession of you and your children forever.<br />
DAGURAGU, 16 August 1975 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
