<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4141</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO NATIONAL PRIVATE ENTERPRISE CONVENTION 4 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004141.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F76/ 111<br />
PRESS PLEASE ADDRESS TO NATIONAL PRIVATE ENTERPRISE CONVENTION 4 JUNE 1976<br />
This national private enterprise convention has set itself an important<br />
task to consider ways of improving understanding between business and<br />
government. But cooperation between business and government is only part of. the<br />
total approach. Equally important is understanding, cooperation and<br />
communication between business and unions, between business and<br />
employers. These other areas of communication and understanding are perhaps<br />
more difficult, but they are equally as important.<br />
Cooperation and understanding between all those engaged in decisions<br />
V affecting the economy is essential if Australia is to return'to<br />
sound economic growth.<br />
Cooperation and understanding has to exist between business and<br />
government, unions and government, and between unions and business.<br />
All of these relationships are important. None of them can be neglected<br />
without imperilling our chance of returning to a stable and<br />
pro'sperous economy.<br />
The principal economic task we face is bringing inflation down.<br />
That is not only a task for the Government. It is a task that all<br />
Australians have to face; That places a special responsibility on<br />
both the major organised seztions of the economy, business and<br />
trade unions. </p>
<p>The main priority must be to bring inflation under control. The<br />
reason for this should need no repetition. Unless inflation is<br />
controlled there can be no return to soundly based economic growth,<br />
no long-term solution to unemployment and no return to prosperity<br />
on which the realisation of private and public goals depends.<br />
The Government has had a consistent strategy to achieve. these<br />
objectives. It is strategy developed in opposition and constantly<br />
reiter~ ated. since.<br />
The main elements of this strategy have been to bring Government<br />
spending under control; to free resources to the private seCtor<br />
and to individuals; to pursue a responsible monetary policy with<br />
clearly announced goals, and to generate a climate of national<br />
responsibility in which wage and salary restraint will be Possibl~ e<br />
and in which both business and unions will act with a principal<br />
regard for the national interest.<br />
Immediately after coming to office we took steps to being<br />
implementing this strategy. We made a large number of immediate<br />
economies in administrative expenses and spending programmes,<br />
starting with the spending of Ministers and other Members of<br />
Parliament. We halted the growth of the Federal Public Service. 0<br />
There will be over 17,000 fewer people employed in the federal<br />
bureaucracy by the end of June than under ceilings set by the<br />
previous Government. We took a number of steps to help investmeni@<br />
and ease the cash crisis for many businesses. These included<br />
a 40% investment allowance; suspension of quarterly tax instalments;<br />
inquiry into operation of restrictive practices legislation and<br />
we stated our intentions for the long term growth of the money supply.<br />
The Treasurer's statement two weeks ago was a further key step<br />
in implementing this strategy.<br />
The measures announced by the Treasurer included savings to the<br />
Budget amounting to almost $ 2600 million; full personal income tax<br />
indexation; a new scheme of family allowances and a number of reforms<br />
in Medibank. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Let me now state briefly where these measures fit into our<br />
overall strategy. The expenditure restraints mean that, for<br />
the first time in several years, there can be a soundly based<br />
confidence in the community that Government spending has at last<br />
been brought under control.<br />
In recent years excessive Government spending has been the<br />
principal force fuelling excessive inflation and unemployment.<br />
The Government's need for resources has led to a heavy and<br />
growing tax burden on both individuals and companies. Along<br />
with other factors this has encouraged excessive wage and salary<br />
demands and has diverted to Government resources business needed<br />
to expand.<br />
When we came to Government we found public spending rising almost<br />
out of control.<br />
Reimposing responsibility on the public sector means that resources<br />
can be freed to the private sector and to individuals. </p>
<p>The various measures we have taken to assist business, and full<br />
personal income tax indexation, are only possible in the con~ text,-<br />
of restraint in public sector spending. Further, such restraint<br />
means that we can now plan for a responsible deficit in the<br />
August Budget a deficit consistent with a responsible monetary<br />
policy. The Government is not seeking to bring about a sudden upsurge<br />
in economic activity. Sudden shifts of course, would only create<br />
new risk~ s.<br />
The Government is, however, confident that the course of the economic<br />
recovery which is now occurring is entirely consistent with the<br />
Government's strategy. The strategy was not designed to achieve shorttime<br />
miracles. It was designed to-asset a new direction for<br />
Government policy which would secure a soundly based steady return<br />
to prosperity. There is now a growing amount of evidence that the@<br />
Australian economy is moving forward on the path to recovery.<br />
major indicators of production are moving in a favourable directio*<br />
Production of 80% of the items surveyed by the A. B. S. increased in<br />
the three months to April. The A. N. Z. index of factory production<br />
rose 4h% in the three months to April. The index is 10% higher than<br />
a year ago. Stocks in the March quarter increased for the first time<br />
since 1974.<br />
These trends resulted in a rise in gross non-farm product of 3.1%<br />
for the March quarter. A very encouraging turnabout.<br />
Demand is also strengthening. Retail sales firmed late in the<br />
March quarter and motor vehicle registration have increased strong. LO<br />
in the three consecutive months to April. Whilst capital expenditure<br />
in non-dwelling building and construction was depressed other<br />
expenditure, mainly plant equipment, rose 8% to offset this.<br />
overtime worked in recent . months' was the highest since late 1974.<br />
Surveys of capacity utilisation show early<br />
signs of recovery.<br />
Meanwhile, private dwelling activity remains a strong point in the<br />
economy, April approvals were the highest since January 1974.<br />
Loan approvals from banks and building societies continued at high<br />
levels 13% up the March quarter compared with a year earlier.<br />
Ot her strong points are registrations of new non-passenger motor<br />
vehicles up 18% in the Aril three months. Finance company business </p>
<p>for newly leased equipment March 76 was double the previous March.<br />
Despite all these positive signs, there remain some warnings against<br />
-complAacency. Unemployment is still far too high. Non-dwelling<br />
building and construction is still suffering from the low level of<br />
new work approvals last year. The rural economy labors under<br />
depressed world markets.<br />
Too much weight cannot be placed on individual indicators but an<br />
objective assessment of the picture across the board suggests that<br />
the measures the goveznrhent has taken are having their intended effect.<br />
This brings me bhck to the subject of national cooperation and to<br />
the requirement for mutual understanding between business, trade unions<br />
and government.<br />
It became very obvious over the last few years, that prosperity was<br />
being harmed by the lack of adequate consultation between government<br />
and business. In Opposition, we undertook to establish greatly<br />
improved procedures of consultation. Since the election, we moved<br />
rapidly to establish the economic consultative group. This group is<br />
chaired by the Treasurer. It includes the Minister for Industry and<br />
Commerce as Deputy Chairman, and leading business figures and trade<br />
unionists. The government's objective in forming the economic consultative<br />
group was to ensure that the government is kept informed about the<br />
state of affairs in the private sector.-At the same time, the group<br />
allows the government to present its assessment of economic<br />
conditions to the members of the group and receive their views upon it.<br />
A further move to improve consultation was made by Senator Cotton's<br />
announcement of industry advisory councils. The councils will provide<br />
a forum for government, parliamentarians, firms, unions, consumers<br />
and other interested groups, to discuss government policies of<br />
importance to the industry sectors concerned.<br />
In addition to the discussions that are arranged between government<br />
and industry on a formal and regular basis, there are of course,<br />
frequent informal meetings between myself, the Treasurer or relevant<br />
industry ministers and industry representatives. Similar informal<br />
meetings occur between government officials and industry representatives </p>
<p>-6-<br />
There has been a long tradition of consultations between s&amp; enior<br />
ministers and industry representatives prior to the Budget.<br />
I would expect the discussions this year to cover a wide range of<br />
matters. The government has initiated preparation of a white paper<br />
taking up the themes of the Jackson Report. One of * its main themes<br />
was-the need for improved government-industry cooperation.<br />
The government has called for submissions from industry and other<br />
interested parties. These will be of paramount importance to the<br />
formulation of government policy in this area.<br />
Theimportance of consultation between business and government is<br />
matched by the importance of consultations with the trade union<br />
movement. One consistent theme of the government's strategy has been the enorious<br />
importance of wage restraint. The government has sought to foster a<br />
climate in which people recognise the absolute need for wage and<br />
salary restraint if inflation is to be beaten. We have done thisS<br />
through our submissions to the Arbitration Commission, through our<br />
statements of strategy, and through.-the measures we-have introduced.<br />
Three months ago, we knew that we had to act. There had to be an<br />
unambiguous declaration of the importance the government placed on<br />
wage and salary restraint.<br />
I believe the climate we have sought to encourage is emerging.<br />
The recognition of a joint responsibility is growing. I also believe<br />
that there is also emerging a joint commitment to fulfil this<br />
responsibility. Great numbersof employees are recognising that<br />
if their wage and-salary increase is beyond a responsible point,<br />
the people who pay for it are their workmates.<br />
The costs of excessive wage increases are inflation, the loss of<br />
existing jobs, and the sacrifice of opportunities to create new jobs.<br />
The Treasurer's statement had a signfiicant role in the government's<br />
strategy in the area also. A guarantee that wages will be protected<br />
from unlegislated increases in taxation has been, of course, a major<br />
concern of the trade union movement.<br />
The trade union movement has taken a consistent view that the certainty<br />
provided by tax indexation would be a major factor in wage restraint.<br />
The pr otection afforded by the family allowances to wage earners near<br />
the minimum income with large families, has also been a long-standing<br />
concern of the trade union movement. </p>
<p>Full personal tax indexation at last provides an assurance to all<br />
wage, salary and income earners that there will be no increase in the<br />
tax burden without deliberate and public decision. The family<br />
allowances scheme shows the government's determinationto work in the<br />
interest of all Australians.<br />
These two measures establish the circumstances in which real wage<br />
restraint is possible. Full personal income tax ind~ xation and<br />
family allowances were major elements of the context for the<br />
Arbitration Commission's recent judgement. It was a judgement which<br />
certainly improves our capacity as a nation to bring inflation under<br />
control.-Throughout our term . of -office, the government has consulted<br />
extensively with the union movement. Legislation concerning<br />
organisations registered under the Conciliation and Arbitration Act,<br />
including proposals for secret ballots for trade unions was discussed<br />
with them on May 5. The trade union movement raised some very reasonablE<br />
points about the proposed legislation. Cabinet considered these points<br />
and amended the proposed legislation.<br />
In my address to the nation, I stated that the government would seek<br />
top level discussions with . the-union. ' movement about the economic<br />
situation. The ACTU agreed to these meetings and we will be having<br />
wide-ranging economic discussions with the trade union movement<br />
0 on 11/ 12th June. The government will have equivalent discussions<br />
with business. We have introduced the legislation concerning the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Act into the Parliament.<br />
In line with the government's determination to consult the trade union<br />
movement on legislation involving it, the legislation will not be<br />
proclaimed until the ACTU has an opportunity to make known its<br />
attitude on it.<br />
The trade union movement will thus have a further opportunity to put<br />
any further proposed amendments to the government before it becomes law. </p>
<p>I do not need to emphasise before this audience how critical<br />
industrial relations are to bringing inflation under control.<br />
There can be no stronger foundation for good industrial relations<br />
than widespread understanding of the true nature of the problems<br />
that face us.<br />
Talking about the need for anational cooperative effort has to<br />
be matched by cooperative action.<br />
Effective cooperation action has to be based on frank discussion,<br />
mutual consultations.<br />
Some Companies have very good procedures for discussing matters<br />
with employees.<br />
This is a time morethan ever, when the example of the best should'be<br />
followed by everyone.,<br />
If employees can get a clear picture of the impact of their wage<br />
and salary demands on their-own firm, I have no doubt that people<br />
will wish of-their own account, to act with great responsibility. 0<br />
Employees should not have to read in a newspaper the fate of the<br />
firm for which they work.<br />
You cannot treat the Australia~ n workman-like a piece of equipment.<br />
What chance can there be for good relations if management does not<br />
bother to inform employees about the condition of the business for<br />
which they work.<br />
This is where a major effort must be made.<br />
These are not new or radical ideas.<br />
They are practices which have been accepted by the best firms for<br />
a generation. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
For many years now, those who believe that the free enterprise<br />
system is best for all Australians have been-less active than we<br />
should in putting the case.<br />
That is one reason why we have suffered the experience of the<br />
last three years.<br />
It is good to see that an increasing number of people are<br />
taking action to see that there is a growing appreciation of the<br />
common interests of everyone in a profitable and efficient private<br />
sector. I believe it is important to remember that understanding is advanced<br />
not only by the availability of high quality objective material<br />
but even more importantly by relations within the particular firm<br />
and by the effort that management makes there.<br />
How can I explain to people that private enterprise is the best<br />
system for the average Australian if managements cannot be bothered<br />
explaining it to their own employees.<br />
Ask yourselves -where should the effort most be made.<br />
-To a government committed to the free enterprise system, or to employees<br />
who are often sceptical, and who often do not have a clear understanding<br />
of the benefits they derive from productive free enterprise.<br />
It needs to be explained even more clearly that new plant, new<br />
equipment, new jobs, are created out of profits.<br />
That in a country like Australia, profits are very widely distributeddirectly<br />
to shareholders and indirectly to the millions of holders<br />
of insurance and superannuation polic-ies.<br />
There needs to be a much clearer understanding of the central role<br />
of private enterprise in providing through taxation, the resources for<br />
Government to spend on suzh'-th'--ings as social welfare, education<br />
roads, defence, and so on. </p>
<p>Real expansion in social programmes which is not financed<br />
simply by transferring resources from some other group in the<br />
community must be financed out of growth.<br />
Real growth depends on healthy and vital private enterprise.<br />
Private enterprise does not merely provide the resources which<br />
Government can use to impro've its provision.<br />
A healthy private enterprise is an essential part of the life<br />
Australians value.<br />
Private enterprise provides the greatest opportunities: choice of<br />
rewarding jobs, choice of products and choice of services.<br />
It is the system which gives the man in the street the greatest<br />
control over what is produced. In this sense, it is the most<br />
democratic system the system which is most compatible with the<br />
freedom Australians value.<br />
No organisation whether it be a political party, a business<br />
organisation or a trade union, has an inherent right to survive. 0<br />
The justification of any of these organisations is whether they<br />
serve the people who belong to and support them.<br />
The private enterprise system achieves its ultimate justification<br />
in one fact alone it is the system which best serves the interests<br />
of the Australian people which is best able to provide the<br />
conditions and the resources for a better life for all Australians.<br />
Under the Labor Government, the survival of private enterprise<br />
was endangered. We were well on the way to a conformist,<br />
centralised society in which the real wealth of Australia, the productive<br />
energies and initiative of t-he Australian people were suppressed.<br />
The strategy the Government hraas adopted, the measures we have<br />
already announced, and will a= ounce in the coming months, will<br />
ensure that that does not happen. </p>
<p>-11-<br />
I am confident that our approach is already providing a solid<br />
basis for the revival of prosperity in Australia, and for the<br />
development in Australia of a society in which the interests<br />
of all Australians are truly served.<br />
oOo </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
