<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2854</transcript-id>
    <title>MINERALS AND THE FUTURE - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON EG WHITLAM QC MP, TO THE ANNUAL DINNER OF THE AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL, LAKESIDE HOTEL, CANBERRA, MONDAY 19 MARCH 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/03/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002854.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
MINERALS AND THE FUTURE<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM, M. P.,<br />
TO THE ANNUAL DINNER OF THE AUSTRALIAN MINING INDUSTRY COUNCIL<br />
LAKESIDE HOTEL, CANBERRA, MONDAY 19 MARCH 1973<br />
In the management of our mineral resources,<br />
the mining industry and the national Government have a common<br />
interest and a common responsibility. We are custodians of<br />
much of the nation's natural wealth. We are custodians<br />
of our country's soil and its physical riches. We have a<br />
joint interest in ensuring that these resources are managed<br />
in the interests of the whole nation, both for present and<br />
future generations. Last December the Australian people<br />
gave my Government a positive mandate to discharge this<br />
responsibility in partnership with the mining industry and<br />
its many associated enterprises. It is a duty we will not<br />
shirk. No one can dispute the fact that in a<br />
short time your industry has helped transform the face<br />
of our nation. It has transformed our landscape; it has<br />
transformed our balance of payments. It has brought<br />
Australia immense benefits, immense wealth, immense<br />
technological and industrial progress. While our gross<br />
national product and the total value of our exports doubled<br />
during the 19601s, the value of our mineral exports increased<br />
eight-fold. Minerals accounted for 7% of the value of<br />
our exports in the early sixties; they now account for<br />
more than 20%. We have thus restored the position of the<br />
gold rush days of 100 years ago, when gold and minerals,<br />
accounting for 47 per cent of Australia's exports,<br />
were our principal export commodity. For all practical<br />
purposes Australia is now self-sufficient in major<br />
minerals except crude oil and the prospects there<br />
look increasingly bright. This story is one of the great<br />
feats of modern exploration. It is due in large measure to<br />
the vision and enterprise of the men in this room tonight. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
But there are wider considerations that compel<br />
the involvement of modern government in the mining industry.<br />
Despite the size of our mineral reserves, it would be fallacious<br />
and dangerous to regard them as inexhaustible. There are<br />
limits, as other countries have already found. The notion<br />
of unrestricted mining and exploitation is one we cannot accept.<br />
We must be concerned at the effects of unbridled competition<br />
on the stability of international trade. We must recognise<br />
a growing concern in major industrialised countries at the<br />
rapid depletion of traditional energy sources and their<br />
increasing dependence on imports for their raw materials.<br />
We must be concerned to see that our minerals are sold at<br />
reasonable prices in world markets. We must be concerned<br />
to see that our future energy needs and industrial<br />
requirements are met. We must take account of the effect<br />
of mining on the rights of our Aboriginal people, on the<br />
environment and the control of pollution, problems<br />
of undoubted significance for all mankind. We must ensure<br />
the greatest possible measure of Australian ownership<br />
and participation in the mining industry. The industry<br />
is already 62% foreign owned. We do not want that figure<br />
to go higher. In short, for all these reasons, we cannot<br />
allow the future to take care of itself.<br />
EXPORTS Accordingly, my Government is implementing<br />
new policies. Our first step, as you know, has been to place<br />
controls on all mineral exports, whether in raw or semi-processed<br />
form. This, we believe, will ensure that exports are sold at<br />
reasonable prices on the world market. Our measures will<br />
encourage more processing of minerals in Australia, leading<br />
to greater employment opportunities, greater industrial<br />
self-sufficiency, and, not least, to a higher unit value<br />
for our exports themselves. In the longer term, through<br />
these controls, we can look to shipping economies for both<br />
buyer and seller, by reducing the volume of low-value<br />
materials being moved around the world. None of this<br />
means that the Australian Government wishes to cut off<br />
supplies of raw materials to valued business partners in<br />
other countries. We shall do business, and we shall do it<br />
with honour; but we do not regard the rape of our resources<br />
as inevitable, and we certainly do not intend to lie back and<br />
enjoy it. The basic objective of our new measures is to<br />
obtain the best return for Australia consistent with the realities<br />
of the market place and balanced mineral development. It would<br />
be foolish in administering the controls to ignore the market<br />
realities of an industry which has provided the main dynamic in<br />
our balance of payments. But judicious use of the export<br />
control powers will add to our foreign exchange earnings. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
My colleague, the Minister for minerals and<br />
Energy, has already said that the Government's export control<br />
powers will not be employed capriciously or vexatiously.<br />
This is a unanimous attitude among members of the Cabinet.<br />
We want to assure our trading partners that we are seeking<br />
no more than a fair price in our mineral contracts with<br />
them. It would be unreal to seek prices higher than the<br />
market will bear when alternative sources of supply are usually<br />
available. As the details of our policies are worked out in<br />
the months ahead, we shall take every opportunity to explain<br />
them in bilateral consultations and in international organisations<br />
concerned with minerals trade. Indeed, I see great scope for<br />
consultation between Governments on the problems of mineral<br />
development and trade. We are particularly conscious of the problems<br />
of Japan, our major market for minerals. Her vast industries<br />
are especially dependent on imports for their energy needs and<br />
raw materials. It is not, and I must insist on this, our<br />
purpose to try to exploit that dependence. But we believe it<br />
would be in the interests of both Japan and ourselves to work<br />
together more closely to secure for Japan a more reliable<br />
source of supply and to secure for Australian exporters more<br />
reasonable prices. Ne~ ither of these aims is likely to be fully<br />
achieved if trading arrangements are left almost entirely to private<br />
commercial negotiation. Both will be achieved if our mutual'<br />
interests our interdependence as trading partners are fully<br />
recognised at both government and commercial levels.<br />
The steps we have already taken will ensure that<br />
the Government is kept fully aware of marketing arrangements covering<br />
export prices and supply commitments. This is a prime purpose<br />
of our export controls. We need to be satisfied that our mineral<br />
export policies and practices are in the best interests of<br />
Australia and our trading partners. It is perfectly clear that<br />
large companies with interests crossing many national boundaries<br />
may conduct their business in a way which, while maximising<br />
returns for themselves, will be to the detriment of a particular<br />
country. We will satisfy ourselves that those companies operate<br />
in Australia in our interests as well as their own.<br />
REVALUAT ION I know of your special concern with the effect<br />
of recent currency fluctuations on your export contracts.<br />
On this point I hope to reassure you. The effect of the<br />
fluctuations, of course, is by no means uniform. Some currencies<br />
have been appreciated, others depreciated, others remain at<br />
their previous parities. As you know, companies with contracts<br />
written in U. S. dollars, which include most iron ore contracts,<br />
have suffered a reduction in their Australian dollar incomes. ./ 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
But several factors tend to offset this loss. In many cases,<br />
the immediate adverse effects on mining companies have been<br />
avoided by taking out forward exchange cover. In addition,<br />
the interest on and repayment of U. S. dollar borrowings<br />
will cost less in Australian dollars. There should also be<br />
increased shipments of minerals. For example, iron ore<br />
exports from the Pilbara to Japan for 1973-74 are expected<br />
to be substantially higher than in the current year. Other<br />
mineral exporters are enjoying increases in the world prices<br />
of their products, such as copper, zinc and lead. The<br />
mining industry can expect its sales to increase as the<br />
economies of customer countries expand.<br />
The Minister for Minerals and Energy has said<br />
that he expects appropriate relief to be given to exporters<br />
through the re-negotiation of contracts written in American<br />
dollars. In this he has the full support of the Government.<br />
Needless to say, he has your support. For our part we will<br />
be using our influence to see that suitable relief is<br />
forthcoming. On 15 February Mr. Connor discussed this problem<br />
with the Japanese Ambassador in Canberra. Mr. Connor pointed to<br />
the need for early discussions between Japanese and Australian<br />
businessmen. In a letter to Mr. Connor of 20 February, you,<br />
Mr. Phillips, indicated that your council welcomed the<br />
Government; s intervention to assist in renegotiation of contracts.<br />
We shall use all our influence to see that suitable relief is<br />
forthcoming. But I emphasise that any new negotiations would have*<br />
little prospect of success if the Government were to indicate in<br />
any way that it was considering compensation for mining companies<br />
for the effect of recent currency changes.<br />
For the future, it is certainly desirable that<br />
contracts should be written in Australian dollars or provide<br />
for stability ofreturns in terms of Australian dollars.<br />
With long term contracts, built-in safeguards will be needed<br />
to cope with currency changes and variations in demand. That<br />
should be the aim. Mining companies must keep it in mind.<br />
It is regrettable that this simple precaution was not observed<br />
with many contracts already written, tome which still have<br />
many years to run. It is also fair to remind you that some of<br />
your industry's financial problems stem from individual negotiations<br />
a few years ago with group buyers. I hope our new control<br />
mechanism will work to prevent individual suppliers being picked off,<br />
one by one, by overseas cartels.<br />
While we want fair prices for our minerals, we<br />
recognise that fixing appropriate export prices will need to be<br />
handled with care. In some cases there is no single, readily<br />
ascertainable price which can be regarded as a world price.<br />
Quality differences and locations need to be considered. There<br />
will also be times when it will be in the producer ' s and the<br />
nation's interest to permit sales at low prices, perhaps as low<br />
as the cost of production provided the nation and the producer<br />
can earn a satisfactory profit at the lower price. This may be<br />
necessary when we are trying to break into new markets. We know<br />
that in many instances mining companies operate in a buyer's<br />
market, and too rigid an application of controls could result in<br />
contracts being lost to other countries. </p>
<p>PROCESSING I have said that my Government wants more<br />
processing of our minerals. It is the policy of my party<br />
and my Government " to encourage the treatment and fabrication<br />
of mineral resources in Australia." At every stage of<br />
processing, the value of these resources is greatly increased.<br />
Your council has indicated that it supports more local<br />
processing, but that companies should not have to undertake<br />
further processing if it would be uneconomic to do so.<br />
This is a reasonable approach. Local processing places<br />
a heavy demand on capital and other resources. Before<br />
requiring a company to process in Australia, we will ensure<br />
that markets are available for the processed product. The<br />
State Governments, through the control they exercise over<br />
mining and exploration leases, generally require mining<br />
companies to undertake feasibility studies to determine<br />
whether processing is economic. My Government supports<br />
that requirement.<br />
ABORIGINES High among my Government's ambitions is to<br />
give natural rights to our Aboriginal people. We are determined<br />
that their interests will be preserved in any mining operations.<br />
Until the mid-1950s no mining in Aboriginal reserves in the<br />
Northern Territory was permitted. Then it was decided to allow<br />
prospecting and mining in the reserves, but to pay royalties<br />
on minerals to an Aboriginal Benefits Trust Fund. The decision<br />
to pay royalties into a fund for Aboriginal use was a somewhat<br />
oblique acknowledgement of Aboriginal rights in the land.<br />
The Crown, however, continued to collect royalties in the<br />
first instance and to control prospecting and mining.<br />
There are now two major mining operations in<br />
the Arnhem Land reserve and another, of course, in what was once<br />
part of the Aboriginal reserves on Cape York in Queensland.<br />
All three developments are close to Aboriginal communities.<br />
It would be difficult to draw up any social balance sheet of<br />
gains and losses of these Aboriginal communities. The indications<br />
are that none of the communities would wish to turn the clock back.<br />
It is certain, however, that they face critical problems in<br />
adjusting to the new situations, and that the benefits to the<br />
Aboriginals in terms of employment and training, which had been<br />
hoped for at the outset in the mid-50s, have not always been achieved.<br />
The Government has announced its intention to<br />
grant to the Aborigines title in the land in the Northern Territory<br />
reserves. Mr. Justice E. A. Woodward's commission is to advise on<br />
ways of implementing this policy. To avoid further complication of<br />
an already complex situation, the Government imposed a " freeze"<br />
on the issue of exploration licences and mining leases and of<br />
leases of land. This action, we know will create problems for the<br />
companies concerned. The Mining Industry Council has urged that<br />
the rights of those companies committed to exploration programs in<br />
the reserves should be renewed. These cases are being examined, as<br />
are the needs of operating companies, which need additional mining<br />
and land leases. Your council has also argued against any<br />
abdication of Government responsibility for, and control over,<br />
mineral resources. Decisions on this aspect of the land rights </p>
<p>issue will be taken only after the Government has had an<br />
opportunity to consider the report of Mr. Justice Woodward's<br />
Commission. The Commission hopes to report within a few<br />
months. The Mining Industry Council's submission will be<br />
carefully considered.<br />
ENVIRONMENT We must be equally concerned with the effect<br />
of mining on the total environment. Last month the Australian<br />
Government endorsed a policy of impact statement procedures<br />
to ensure that the environmental effects of any proposal are<br />
taken into account at all stages of decision making. Impact<br />
statements will be required where a proposal has significant<br />
environmental consequences, where Commonwealth funds are<br />
involved, or where Commonwealth constitutional power is<br />
involved. From January 1974 there will be public hearings<br />
before an impact statement is prepared.<br />
At this point, allow me to quote the words<br />
of H. R. H. The Duke of Edinburgh, who is now visiting Australia<br />
as chairman of the Australian Conservation Foundation.<br />
Writing on 18 September 1972 he said:<br />
" It might well be supposed that the<br />
conservation of nature and natural resources<br />
is something quite new in man's experience whereas,<br />
in fact, every civilisation in history which did not<br />
take active steps to control its growth had to suffer<br />
the exhaustion of raw materials or food, or both,<br />
and collapsed. The only difference today is that<br />
our civilisation has come to rely on a different<br />
set of the earth's resources which, until the<br />
development of industrial processes, had remained<br />
untapped. Technology has raised human standards<br />
of existence to heights beyond the imagination of<br />
previous civilisations, but it has also made it possible<br />
for astronomical numbers of people to inhabit the earth.<br />
" The problem is two-fold. Unchecked exponential<br />
growth in population numbers, coupled with exponential<br />
growth in the use of non-renewable mineral resources,<br />
is an extremely serious threat to the standards<br />
and very existence of our present civilisation.<br />
The threat is most serious to those enjoying<br />
the highest standards.<br />
" At the same time, the proliferation of the<br />
human population, the exploitation of natural resources<br />
and the constant increase in the demand for more<br />
food-growing land constitute an even more deadly threat<br />
to the continued existence of the natural and wild<br />
environment as we know it today." / 17 </p>
<p>These are among the reasons for my<br />
Government's involvement in the mining industry.<br />
The same concern is shared by Governments throughout<br />
the world. It is not our intention to bring to an end<br />
the truly magnificent achievements of the past decade<br />
or so. Rather it is our firm intention to help your<br />
industry, not hamper it; to encourage trade,<br />
not frustrate it. But we must look to the broadest<br />
long-term interests of our country. Your industry,<br />
I know, will benefit from my Government's<br />
participation. The one thing you can be sure of is that<br />
the free-wheeling approach of the previous Government<br />
is gone forever. We have much to share and much to gain<br />
in our trade with the rest of the world. But it must<br />
be clear that, in regard to minerals, Australia<br />
henceforth intends to be the mistress of her own<br />
household. CANBERRA 19 MARCH 1973 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
