<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1146</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISER, THE RIGHT HONOURABLE SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, THURSDAY 26TH AUGUST 1965 - THE DROUGHT</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001146.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE RIGHT HONOURABLE SIR ROBERT MENZIES, M. P.,<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, THURSDAY 26TH AUGUST, 1965.<br />
THE DROUGHT<br />
As Honourable Members will know the Government has for some<br />
time been giving attention to the drought situation in Central Australia<br />
and parts of Eastern Australia. We have had representations from the<br />
Premiers of New South Wales and Queensland, including proposals that<br />
the Commonwealth provide special financial assistance towards certain<br />
schemes of drought relief being undertaken by the States. There have<br />
also been representations from various interested organisations and<br />
individuals. The Government has given consideration to these matters<br />
and I should like to inform the House in general terms of the action<br />
that has already been taken in the Commonwealth sphere and to indicate<br />
some further steps the Government proposes to take.<br />
SIn this statement I am referring primarily to the drought<br />
in New South Wales and Queensland, and not to the drought that has<br />
persisted for a number of years in Central Australia. Although some<br />
of the measures to which I shall be referring are applicable equally<br />
to the two States and to the Northern Territory, the Commonwealth's<br />
position with regard to drought in the Territory is a special one<br />
arising from its direct responsibility for Northern Territory matters.<br />
My colleague the Minister for ferritories will be making a separate<br />
statement dealing with the question of the drought in the Northern<br />
Territory, Naturally, in our approach to the whole matter we have had<br />
well in mind the consequences of the drought for the nation and,<br />
more particularly, the plight of those who are suffering from the<br />
drought in a direct and personal way.<br />
The drought has had serious and widespread effects and some<br />
of these will continue. However, provided the drought does not<br />
extend into the coming season, the indications are that it should<br />
not have a seriously adverse effect on the overall economy in terms<br />
of loss of total rural production and export proceeds from primary<br />
products. Fortunately, the drought has already broken in certain areas, </p>
<p>2<br />
particularly the dairying areas along the coast but even in those<br />
areas the aftermath of the drought will have severe consequences<br />
for individual farmers. A serious position remains in inland<br />
sheep and wheat and cattle areas of northern New South Wales and<br />
southern Queensland despite some partial relief rains. The position<br />
could further deteriorate in those areas if the drought continues<br />
during the coming spring and summer with further heavy losses for<br />
the individual primary producers concerned.<br />
The provision of assistance for drought-affected primary<br />
producers is, under the constitutional division of responsibilities,<br />
essentially a matter for the State governments concerned. The<br />
State Governments of New South Wales and Queensland have introduced<br />
various special measures of assistance such as the provision of<br />
special loans at concessional rates of interest and freight<br />
concessions on the carriage of fodder and livestock, and have asked<br />
the Commonwealth to participate in the financing of these measures.<br />
Proposals for Commonwealth participation in drought assistance<br />
schemes for the benefit of individual primary producers have also<br />
been put before us by a number of organisations.<br />
The provision of assistance such as this is properly a<br />
State responsibility and the States have the administrative machinery<br />
to handle it. After careful consideration, we have decided that it<br />
would not be appropriate for the Commonwealth to participate directly<br />
in the financing of such measures nor do we think it would be a<br />
proper function for the Commonwealth to participate in making loans<br />
to individuals or providing other forms of direct financial<br />
assistance, to those who may be having difficulty, for reasons such<br />
as drought, in financing their business activities.<br />
At the same time, we are very conscious of the strains<br />
that special drought measures might put on the finances of the two<br />
States. When the new financial assistance arrangements for the next<br />
five years were evolved at our meeting last June with the Premiers, 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
it was accepted that the arrangements would stand unless there was<br />
a major change in the financial position of a State through<br />
circumstances beyond its control. If, as a result of action related<br />
to the drought, the States of New South Wales and Queensland find it<br />
necessary to meet abnormally large calls on their budgets that are<br />
established to be beyond their financial capacities, we will be<br />
prepared to consider assisting them by means of general purpose<br />
assistance grants. I am advising the two Premiers in these terms.<br />
There are two matters which do lie within the Commonwealth's<br />
particular sphere of responsibility and which have a bearing on the<br />
position of those suffering from the drought. I refer to taxation<br />
and the question of access to trading bank finances. In our<br />
consideration of both these matters we have been concerned to do<br />
whatever we reasonably can to help primary producers affected by<br />
the drought, in relation to both their needs for carrying on until<br />
the drought breaks and the problems they will encounter in<br />
rehabilitating their properties, especially by way of re-stocking,<br />
to get them back into shape for the resumption of normal production<br />
operations after the drought breaks.<br />
In the consideration of taxation measures, we have found<br />
that the present provisions of the income tax law, and the<br />
administration of that law by the Commissioner of Taxation, already<br />
go a long way towards meeting the taxation problems of those affected<br />
by the drought. It needs to be borne in mind that, by and large,<br />
taxation concessions are neither direct nor immediate in their<br />
effects on tax-payers' incomes and that being related to income,<br />
their benefit is greatest to those primary producers with large<br />
incomes, paying high rates of tax, and least to producers with small<br />
incomes, paying low rates of tax. There is thus limited scope for<br />
taxation concessions as an appropriate means of helping droughtaffected<br />
primary producers.<br />
With regard to profits arising from forced sales of livestock<br />
because of the drought, a matter which has been the subject of<br />
4 </p>
<p>4<br />
numerous representations, the law already gives the primary producer<br />
the right to elect to have those profits spread over five years,<br />
over the period during which in more normal circumstances they<br />
might be expected to arise. A producer who makes such an election<br />
would be liable to tax on only 1/ 5th of his additional profits in<br />
the year in which such profits arise. Subsequently the profits so<br />
spread must be applied wholly or principally to purchase replacement<br />
livestock. Expenditures on replacements being themselves deductible,<br />
the amount of abnormal profits carried over into the second and<br />
succeeding years need not, depending on re-stocking rates, involve<br />
any addition to a primary producer's tax liability in those years.<br />
In addition, of course, if a primary producer considers that the<br />
provisional tax notified in his assessment is too high, he may seek<br />
adjustment of that tax on the basis of his estimate of his current<br />
year's taxable income.<br />
The cost of purchasing fodder used to feed livestock, which<br />
has also been the subject of several requests, is already deductible<br />
in the year of acquisition, so that primary producers who are forced<br />
to buy-in additional fodder to maintain their stock may deduct as<br />
normal practice, the whole of the purchase price. Similarly, the<br />
cost of producing or purchasing a reasonable quantity of fodder for<br />
stockpiling against emergencies is deductible for income tax purposes.<br />
Concern had been expressed in several quarters at the<br />
possible inability of some drought-affected producers to meet their<br />
tax liabilities by the due date. The Commissioner of Taxation, who<br />
is responsible for the administration of the income tax law, has<br />
discretion under the law to grant extension of time for the payment<br />
of tax, and has assured the Government that he applies this discretion<br />
sympathetically when considering individual applications by primary<br />
producers in financial difficulties because of the drought.<br />
A particular problem that has arisen concerns the position<br />
of primary producers who, because of the drought, have shorn their<br />
flocks twice within the 1964-65 income year. As the law now stands,<br />
woolgrowers so placed are required to account for the proceeds and<br />
expenses of two wool clips in their 1964-65 income tax returns; there<br />
5 </p>
<p>is no provision in the law whereby proceeds of the second clip,<br />
net of direct expenses, can be transferred to the 1965-66 income year.<br />
To meet the situation, the Government has decided to<br />
introduce an amendment of the law so as to permit primary producers<br />
concerned to elect to reduce their 1964-65 income by the amount of<br />
the net proceeds of the second clip and to carry that amount forward<br />
into the 1965-66 income year.<br />
I turn now to the question of access to trading bank<br />
finance. The Reserve Bank has kept itself closely informed of<br />
developments in the drought situation, particularly with regard to<br />
the demands of primary producers affected by the drought for finance<br />
from the banking system.<br />
Preferential treatment is extended to the rural<br />
industries under the traditional policies of both the Reserve Bank<br />
and the trading banks, and the trading banks have assured the<br />
Reserve Bank that the demands for bank finance arising from the<br />
present drought are being dealt with sympathetically. As the<br />
implications of the drought became clearer, the Reserve Bank informed<br />
banks that in providing necessary finance for purposes arising<br />
from the drought, additional lending might be undertaken outside<br />
the general limitation on new lending commitments.<br />
The trading banks have been asked to continue to keep the<br />
Reserve Bank informed of the extent of demands for drought finance<br />
upon them. The Reserve Bank is closely watching the situation,<br />
including the trading banks' continuing ability to provide<br />
additional loan finance to drought-affected clients.<br />
We recognise of course that the measures of drought relief<br />
which the States and ourselves have introduced or contemplate do<br />
not deal with the long term problem of drought mitigation measures.<br />
The unfortunate consequences of the present drought have<br />
served to stimulate an awareness of the ravages that droughts in<br />
this country can cause, from the standpoint of both individual 6 </p>
<p>6<br />
primary producers and the nation as a whole, and there is general<br />
acceptance of the need for further action to mitigate the effects of<br />
droughts that will, inevitably and unhappily, continue to occur from<br />
time to time in the future. Already, following discussions in the<br />
Australian Agricultural Council, the the Bureau of<br />
Meteorology and the Bureau of Agricultural Economics are undertaking<br />
investigations into drought mitigation. We further intend to put<br />
to study the question of the role the Commonwealth and its agencies<br />
might play, within the sphere of Commonwealth responsibility, in<br />
the devising and execution of measures to mitigate the effects of<br />
future droughts. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
