<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2599</transcript-id>
    <title>CIVIC RECEPTION - SPRINGVALE TOWN HALL, MELBOURNE VIC - 19 MAY 1972 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/05/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002599.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBA. RGO: Not for release before<br />
6.30 p. m. 19 May 1972<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CIVIC RECEPTION<br />
SPRINGVALE TOWN HALL, MELBOURNE, VIC._ 19 May 1972<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt Hon.<br />
William McMahon, CF., MP.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
Thank you Councillor Marriott ( Mayor), Mrs Marriott<br />
and all Councillors. There are two fac-ts about your municipality that<br />
have attracted my attention. Yours is a growth area which can<br />
match any other part of Victoria and probably any other part<br />
of Australia. You are truly a part of the suburban explosion<br />
that is going on around the edges cf Australia's great cities.<br />
The second is that Springvale is a young area, Where there<br />
were farms a few years ago, you now have over 60,000 people in<br />
Springvale municipality alone. Many of them are young couples<br />
with their young families. M4any of them are new settlers<br />
taking advantage of the very large migrant hostel in this area.<br />
These two features growth and youth pose special<br />
poroblems to be solved and special needis to be met by<br />
government at all levels whether it be here with you at the<br />
local government level and I believe it is fundamental to<br />
preserve and co-operate with local government, or whether it<br />
be at the State Government lev,: AL, or w*,. ether it be a problem<br />
that may be placed in my " In T. ray" in the Federal Government<br />
in Canberra. When I mention the importance -e attach to local<br />
government in the Australian system, I am not just being<br />
complimentary. only last month, the Cabinet decided as a<br />
matter of principle that local government ought to be<br />
involved in " the convention" which has been proposed to<br />
review the Australian constitution. That demonstrates our<br />
serious intent when we speak about the role of local government.<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>These special needs and problems I have mentioned<br />
involve all three levels of government. And inevitably there<br />
will be areas where they overlap. But it should be remembered<br />
that these are problems of growth which occur against the<br />
background of a developing, diversifying and expanding national<br />
economy. These are problems which will not be swept away by<br />
words and promises. They will be overcome only by patient and<br />
intelligent co-operation between the three-tiers of our<br />
Australian system of government. There are some people in<br />
public life who find it fashionable these days to say that we<br />
have a " crisis" in our cities, and that our problems are<br />
similar to those of comparable cities overseas. Such claims<br />
are, of course, wildly inaccurate. Nevertheless, we in the<br />
Federal Government think there is a good reason for concern<br />
that action should be taken now to improve current living<br />
conditions, and to avoid greater problems in the future.<br />
No one would try to pretend that the cities do not<br />
have their problems: such matters as high land costs,<br />
atmospheric pollution, traffic congasion, long distance<br />
commuting, recreational congestion, lack of community centres<br />
in outer suburbs and the increased crime rate, violence and<br />
other similar problems. These matters are basically the<br />
direct responsibility of the two tiers of our government<br />
structure closest to the people, that is, the state and local<br />
governments. The Commonwealth Government sees as one of its<br />
first duties the management of the national economy. On that<br />
score I think I can claim here and now that our very flexible<br />
and responsive stance, and our willingness to act boldly and<br />
decide positively in stimulating the economy, is now paying<br />
off in the return of business confidence and the continuing<br />
improvement in employment.<br />
Secondly, we have, within this area of national<br />
economic policy, continually increased and improved our<br />
allocations to state and local governments. Before people<br />
become carried away with labels like " urbanisation" or<br />
" urban affairs" or the " challenge of the cities", they should<br />
stop for a moment to consider the billions for schools, for<br />
housing, for roads, for sewerage, for hospitals that has coyr. e<br />
out of the many years of practical co-operation between<br />
Commonwealth and State Governments under a Liberal Country<br />
Party Government. Thirdly, there are the ways in which we are giving<br />
direct assistance. Health and education are two areas where<br />
we have just made further improvements.<br />
But, Mr Mayor, I don't want to speak for too long<br />
as I want to meet personally as many of those who are here<br />
today. But I did want to tell you that we in Canberra and we<br />
in the Liberal Party see these matters in a sympathetic way,<br />
and how we are prepared to help co-operatively and constructively<br />
and without imposing long distance bureaucracy from local<br />
problems. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
