<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3843</transcript-id>
    <title>PAPUA NEW GUINEA - BOUGAINVILLE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003843.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
, A U Si IHAL IA Press Statement No. 43W-$ 4<br />
11 August 1975<br />
PAPUA NEW GLJINLA BOUGAINVTLLE<br />
Following his discussions with the Chief Minister of<br />
Papua New Guinea, Mr Michael Somare, today, the Prime Minister<br />
said that he wished to make crystal clec-r the Austral. ian Goverrnent's<br />
position in relation to Bougainville.<br />
The Prime Minister recalled that, in advising Mr Somare<br />
on 19 June that the date of 16 September for independen~ ce<br />
nominated by the House of Assembly was acceptable to the<br />
Australian Government, he had taken the opportunity to reaffirm<br />
that the Australian Government's policy was that Papua New Guinea<br />
should come to independence as one country in accordance with<br />
the wishes of the overwhelming majority of Papua New Guinea's<br />
elected representatives. This remained Australia's firm policy.<br />
The Prime Minister also recalled that he had informed<br />
Mr Somare on 19 June that the Australian Government would give<br />
no sympathy, aid or support in any form to any group in Papua<br />
New Guinea working to undermine their country's unity. This<br />
remained the firm Australian position.<br />
The Prime Minister said that he had today advised Mr Somare<br />
that a unilateral declaration of independence, if given effect,<br />
would be an illegal act. It could not by itself alter in terms of<br />
the law of Papua New Guinea the authority of the Government of<br />
Papua New Guinea over the whole of the territory of Papua New Guinea.<br />
Nor could it detract from Australia's international rights and<br />
duties under the Trusteeship Agreement.<br />
Austral. ian policy was to regard 13apua New Guinea as<br />
to tho-COv~ rnmenht 6E Papiua NOw C.., iinea. ii + his-i, siituatifoh Atistralla<br />
tr i d, 0 ,1 diir. dl rIns o'il Lu~ r-Ct on oby~ o~ i~<br />
c Ion t, howevor Lhal FillY Ili;'' Vco o~ I. lDicaktI l. J lIi i<br />
inidependott be. tcro 16 Sc pLi:' bc* woU! d Jt~ ki. drO 11ot ofliy tha finant<br />
of the Governnhunt of P. apua NOW ( Thiii': a bjut-clso that ot the Aitralian<br />
Government and the United Nationg. Tihe Aus -trtlian Government would<br />
not a., 3surit nor, in the PIm. ie M. i .' iiste:' s 2 uO~ gemvet, would. the<br />
United ' Nati. ns, / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Australian Government naturally remained interested<br />
and concerned about developments in Bougainville. The Prime<br />
Minister and Mr Somare had agreed to keep in the closest touch.<br />
The Prime Minister said that he had given Mr Somare<br />
renewed assurances of Australian support and had every<br />
confidence that the move to independence on 16 September of a<br />
united Papua New Guinea would proceed smoothly. He understood<br />
that the way was open for further discussions between the<br />
central government and the Bougainvilleans. He hoped that all<br />
concerned would use their best endeavours to find an amicable<br />
and enduring solution.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
