<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1119</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY  THE PRIME MINISTER, SIR ROBERT MENZIES AT THE AUSTRALIAN EMBASSY, WASHINGTON, U.S.A ON 9TH JUNE, 1965</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/06/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001119_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
65/ 086<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
SIR ROBERT NENZIES, AT THE AUSTRALIAN EM'BASH,<br />
WASHINGTON, U. S. A. ON 9TH JUNE, 1965.<br />
PRIME MINISTER I had a very interesting experience last'night.<br />
Just as I was about to go out to dinner with the Secretary<br />
of State the President rang me up and asked me to come to<br />
breakfast. It reminded me of the first time I ever was<br />
invited to have breakfast and have a talk was by Stanley<br />
Baldwin many years ago. What he wanted to see me about was<br />
what he had referred to initially earlier and that was the<br />
appointment of an Ambassador to Australia. He has got his<br />
mind settled on an Ambassador and it's not for me, of course,<br />
to announce the name of his Ambassador but he has got his mind<br />
fixed on it and they will be taking the steps necessary to<br />
secure the usual agreement in the next few days, and I think<br />
we may anticipate an announcement say in a week.<br />
Q* There is some technicality here, isn't there?<br />
( Then followed a brief discussion between the Prime Minister<br />
and the correspondents dealing with the United States procedure<br />
in that after the President announces his intention to<br />
nominate an Ambassador the Senate has the responsibility to<br />
approve the nomination. This was not clear on the recording.)<br />
Q. d~ ell, all this means is that it could be brought to<br />
announcement within a few days, couldn't it?<br />
P. M. Yes, he could announce his nomination. dIell, I think<br />
as soon as he gets the ' bll clear" from Canberra hie will make<br />
that announcement at once. He knoixis a good long time has<br />
elapsed since the previous Ambassador left. It was clearly<br />
on his mind because it was the first thing he mentioned when<br />
I went in to see him at the White House.<br />
Q. What time did you have breakfast, Sir?<br />
P. N. 8.30. I'm a night worker myself. I don't get on too<br />
well with conversation at breakfast.<br />
Q. How long did you stay, Sir?<br />
P. M. For about an hour and a quarter.<br />
Q6 How did you like the bacon and eggs, Sir?<br />
P. M. Jell, it's exactly what we had.<br />
Q. The rzesident's favourite?<br />
P. m. Is it? Well, my breakfast normally consists of a glass<br />
of orange juice and one piece of toastt However, it was<br />
very interesting.<br />
Qe Was anybody else present or just you and the President?<br />
P. m. Th ' re were four other people but two of them weren't<br />
concerned but the other two I think might have had some<br />
interest in this problem. a a a a a./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Q. Sir, I take it the President did, of course, give you<br />
the name of the neivr Ambassador.<br />
P. M. Oh, yes, I know who it is.<br />
Q4 Is it a career diplomat, can you tell us that?<br />
P. M. Oh, no, you mustn't ask me that now. I think it is<br />
his right to make his own announcement. And I think it will<br />
be well received,<br />
Q6 Would you give us a run-down on your visit, Sir?<br />
P. M. Yes, I think I could in some sort of fashion. Apart<br />
from this matter of the diplomat, my talks with the President<br />
have been almost entirely on Vietnam and the problems thot<br />
are associated with it. He gave me the opportunity yesterday<br />
morning of having three-quarters of an hour with Maxwell Taylor<br />
who, of course 7 is fresh from the scene and he gave me a<br />
singularly lucid account both of the military and political<br />
problems in South Vietnam and filled in a lot of detail and<br />
some background that I hadn't fully understood ;, efore. It<br />
u; ill be very useful from our point of view to have the benefit<br />
of his observations. On both fields both the political and<br />
the military, there is no doubt that ihe next couple of months<br />
will not be easy because of the wet the monsoons and in<br />
that period the Viet Cong will no doubt be making extra<br />
effortsi But I found no lack of either confidence or<br />
resoluteness, either with General Maxwell Taylor or with the<br />
President himself or with Mr. Dean Rusk or with Mr. McNamara<br />
I saw them allb I have had very useful discussions with<br />
Dean Rusk about a variety of matters that we're concerned<br />
about ' With the Stat3 Department. I don't say that we broke<br />
any particularly new ground but we brought each other up to<br />
date in the thinking of our own countries. I had a good<br />
talk yesterday afternoon with Mri McNamara. He was able to<br />
give me a satisfactory report on the... 4what I used to-call<br />
the what's it called now? Fill in which he sees<br />
no reason to believe that there will be any delay in delivery.<br />
As you know, we postponed the date for a year in which we were<br />
to get ours because, quite obviously with the new aircraft<br />
of a highly sophisticated kind like Lhis there will be teething<br />
troubles and we thought, and rightly, that it was better to<br />
have those attended to in the place where the plane is manufactured<br />
and where it is designed rather than in Australia because<br />
they would have far more facilities and the job could be done<br />
in a much smaller time. So we decided we would take the<br />
fully vetted machine even though that meant waiting twelve<br />
months for it, But I believe we'll get it on the date.<br />
Q* Sir, there has been considerable excitement by the<br />
statement yesterday of the role of the United States Forces<br />
in Vietnam.<br />
P. M. Yes, I heard about that. I don't understand it.<br />
Q. Is that the Australian role? Or some new idea that the<br />
Australians will be there to fight if necessary?<br />
P. M. It never occurred to me to the contrary. I don't think<br />
that the 1st Battalion of the Regular Army would thank you very<br />
much if they were cast for the role of onlookers. I always<br />
thought this matter was simple enough. I don't know why there<br />
should be thought to be much novelty about it. We send our<br />
troops in. They are under the command of an Australian soldier<br />
a 1P 0 ./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
P . M.<br />
( Contd.) Q0 P. M.<br />
Q P. M.<br />
QO P . M. 0 Bee 01/ 1<br />
who, as usual in these circumstances, will have of course a<br />
direct line of communication back to the Australian Government<br />
in case he wants to bring anything to our attention. But<br />
the Australian Battalion will be associated with American<br />
units under what might be described as a brigade formation<br />
which in its turn will be under the command of an American.<br />
I don't think either the United States or Australia anticipates<br />
that they are going to conduct completely independent<br />
campaigns; the notion rather is that they will be associated<br />
with Vietnamese forces and be in position to lend them<br />
assistance where that assistance is necessary. And, of<br />
course, there is good sense in that. We are there to help<br />
to defend South Vietnam and therefore of course, must work<br />
in the closest co-operation with the local forces and the<br />
local authorities. Related to that, Sir, now that Australia is playing a<br />
more active role in Vietnam, will we be consulted by the<br />
Americans on policy for the future of the area?<br />
Oh yes. Oht yes. We have a very close association with<br />
them. I discussed with Dean Rusk, for example, whether<br />
there was any way in which it was necessary to improve the<br />
exchange of information, or the exchange of ideas, Neither<br />
of us could think of one but if there is any blockage<br />
anywhere it will undoubtedly be removed, but I don't say<br />
there is any blockage. Our Commanding Officer on the spot<br />
is fully informed about military activities. On the<br />
political side, our own Ambassador is closely in touch with<br />
the American Ambassador and, of course, with the Prime<br />
Minister so that we get a good run of information there<br />
. and as between the Department here and in Australia there<br />
is a completely frank exchange of information. So there<br />
will be nio complaint on my side that there will be any<br />
failure of consultation or advance information. We'll get<br />
all that. Sir, does this extend to Indonesia/ Malaysia as well<br />
as to Vietnam? No. No. I'm talking about Vietnam because the<br />
Americans have no forces in Malaysia. We have, under a<br />
different obligation. You see, we regard our participation<br />
in South Vietnam as essentially a SEATO exercise from our<br />
point of view. The reason for that is quite clear, for the<br />
Treaty itself in the American view and in the Australian<br />
view these were both announced a long time ago imposes<br />
obligations that are several as well as joint. It is for<br />
that reason that South Vietnam being one of the protocol<br />
countries under the South-East Asian Treaty, we regard it<br />
as an essential ingredient an invitation from the Government<br />
of South Vietnam because that is provided for in the Treaty<br />
and, of course, we had that and we are there.<br />
Sir, the other members of SEATO obviously do not view<br />
the situation in the same light.<br />
Well, I think there is some reason to believe*..-,, For<br />
example France believes that the obligations are joint and<br />
not several therefore there has to be unanimity, therefore,<br />
in effect, somebody has a veto, That's a view that we<br />
reject. But we don't comment on what others the other<br />
parties in the SEATO Treaty, it's for them, and if we </p>
<p>4-<br />
P. M. regarded ourselves as having a several obligation, well, we<br />
( Contd.) grasp it by the wheel and act under it, and we [ lave. if<br />
some other country has a different view, well, it makes its<br />
own judgment.<br />
Q. Sir, what of General Taylor's hopes for the future?<br />
Pam@ Oh, well I think that I might safely say, without<br />
becoming General Taylor's spokesman that he's got a<br />
realistic view of' the immediate dif'liculties but an optimistic<br />
view about the ultimate result.<br />
Q. I An optimistic view?<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
Qo -Sir, can you tell us anything about your talks with<br />
Mr. Connor yesterday?<br />
P. m* Yes, we had a sort of run-down particularly on the<br />
question of the financial policy. I was able to give him the<br />
text of what Mr. Holt had said, publicly indicating the<br />
policy step by step of the Australian Government on these<br />
matters and Mr. Connor found this very satisfactory. His<br />
approach to our problems is quite a sympathetic one, quite a<br />
helpful one, and we ourselves, of course, found out from the<br />
American companies in Australia, the major people I think<br />
there were about 74 to whom I addressed a letter and we had<br />
full and frank information from I think 73 out of 74, so it's<br />
a pretty good reaction and the broad effect of it was that<br />
we were able to conclude that the impact of the new policy<br />
on investment passing into Australia will not be as severe as<br />
it was first thought either possible or likely. In short, I<br />
think we've got a good working mutual understanding with him<br />
and with his Department. We had some little anxiety well<br />
not littleT: about the development of these big iron ore<br />
deposits in the Jest and the bauxite deposits in the North,<br />
ach of which involved massive amounts of money and on which<br />
arrangements, largely through a banking consortium, had been<br />
arrived at. We had a little doubt at the moment as to whether<br />
they might continue but they've been completely approved,<br />
so there is no hitch on that side. That's very important<br />
for us.<br />
Q. Sir, can you tell us a little bit more of your talks<br />
with Secretary of State Rusk. I understand you discussed<br />
not only Vietnam but also Malaysia, Red China, Indonesia.<br />
P. M. Yes.<br />
Q. Would you care to give us something on these points?<br />
P. M. I don't think so.<br />
Q. Sir, the President is being troubled at the moment by<br />
a local group of intellectuals who are opposed to his Vietnamese<br />
policy. What would be the public reaction in Australia,<br />
Sir, in general, to our troops being in Vietnam?<br />
P. m. Very favourable, overwhelmingly favourable. As a matter/<br />
of fact, curiously enough, my political opponents as recently<br />
as last February produced a statement of policy which completely~<br />
upheld the American presence in South Vietnam. But since then<br />
they have been a little bro'ibeaten by what you call intellectuals<br />
and a certain amount of philosophical doubt has entered<br />
into their attitude. We really got to the point in course of<br />
o </p>
<p>P. M. discussion in the House of it being necessary to point out<br />
( Contd.) that it was a strange doctrine that it was quite right and<br />
proper for Americans to be engaged in South Vietnam but<br />
quite wrong and improper for Australians to be engaged. it<br />
looked to me rather like leaving everything to the United<br />
States. We all know that the United States is getting'a<br />
little browned off about being the world's gendarme and<br />
that's why they attacht great significance to what we can do<br />
to show the flag and show our-co-operation even though<br />
intrinsically it may be small. It has a symbolic value<br />
here which is far beyond the numbers, but I think, I am sure,<br />
it has given great encouragement to the President, for the<br />
very reason that you mention. I had to make a speech at<br />
the White House and it's a real business trying to remember<br />
w~ iat you said but I think one or two of the philosophic<br />
doubters were present. In fact I know they were. And I<br />
fell back in consequence oxi Shakespeare who said " And thus<br />
the native hue of resolution is sicklied o'er wi~ h the pale<br />
cast of thought" and that resolution is the operative word.<br />
Q. Do you expect to be troubled, Sir, if that's the right<br />
word, by the same kind of intellectuals, if that's the right<br />
word, in Australia?<br />
P. M. No, It accustomed to them. The more people I suc-. eed<br />
in putting into universities in Australia and I have had<br />
a fairly big hand in all that the more intellectuals there<br />
are, or aspiring intellectuals. But if the Government<br />
proceeded by purely intellectual processes, the country<br />
would fall into a grave state of disrepair.<br />
Q6 Sir, do you think the Australian and American people<br />
will have to be prepared for some reverses in Vietnam in<br />
the next couple of months?<br />
P. M. Yes. It stands to reason that in this monsoon season<br />
where there is a great deal of cloud and rain and therefore<br />
air activity is limited or inhibited and the guerrilla boys<br />
have all the benefits of mobility and working under cover,<br />
we must expect to have some reverses and what we have to do<br />
is not to get -them out of proportion because under these<br />
circumstances there will be reverses, but if they're matched<br />
in the broad by a progress over all, then they have to be<br />
taken and seen in their proper degree. But I am sure that<br />
in the next two months we'll from time to time read about<br />
some successful attack by Viet Cong on some battalion or<br />
some formation there, That is in the nature of a war<br />
against the concealed enemy. ; ide had it, you remember, at<br />
one stage in North Malaya. It took a long time to 3lean<br />
up*<br />
Q&amp; Sir, could you give us an appraisal of the Indonesian/<br />
Australian situation, the relation between the two countries<br />
and what your hopes may be?<br />
P. M. 4ell, wetve tIraughbitmade it clear to Indonesia tat<br />
we have every desire 6o be friend7y with a large neighbour<br />
of that kind, very close to us, with a great deal of interest<br />
in common, and that there is one matter alone on which we<br />
completely depart from them and that is on " confrontation"<br />
the policy towards Malaysia and on that we have of course,<br />
not only offered our views but we have comLiitted l'orces,<br />
That was under a declaration I made on behalf of the Government<br />
some time ago which was made not under formal<br />
obligation but unilaterally that we would be prepared to<br />
5 0 0 0 0 6 -/ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Pam. associate ourselves with British Forces in helping to defend<br />
( Contd.) the territorial integrity and political independence I<br />
think those were the words of Malaysia. And that's<br />
understood. Every now and again it produces some extravagant<br />
speeches but I think one must learn to live with extravagant<br />
speeches. They dontt disturb us unduly.<br />
Q. Sir, do you feel ttiat the ANZUS arrangement is<br />
satisfa ctory?<br />
P~ j~ jI do. I do, completely. By the way, somebody told<br />
me this morning that I'm supposed to have described the<br />
Australian battalion as the first batch or some such phrase.<br />
Certainly a phrase I never used or thought of. The broad<br />
. inference 1bias that we'll keep piling in more forces now.<br />
I think it is proper to say that in all these discussions<br />
nobody has asked for more. There has been no kind of<br />
pressure put on. On the contrary they understand very well<br />
the nature of our defence build-up and the fact that this<br />
takes time bringing in the new compulsory service people and<br />
getting them trained and getting them equipped and organised,<br />
This is not done overnight and they have a very accurate<br />
idea of the military strength we possess and the military<br />
strength that we aim at achieving over this period. But<br />
certainly we haven't reached a stage at which we have to<br />
give consideration or they have to suggest further forces.<br />
After all, the battalion has barely just arrived or is<br />
arriving. Early days to be talking about what happens<br />
thereafter. So I have given no hint publicly or privately<br />
about expanded forces. No inference is to be drawn from<br />
thiat one way or another because who am I to know how the<br />
circumstances will develop in the next year or two years.<br />
We are pretty fully stretched at present not only in terms<br />
of manpower but in the terms of the Budget, I think it is<br />
becoming pretty clear that this year's Budget w~ hich we will<br />
begin to discuss when I get back home will find a further<br />
increase in the Defence Vote by something in the order of<br />
or œ C90M. wrhich in our Budget, of course, is a very<br />
substantial item,.. coming as it does or as it will at a<br />
time when the Loan market is a little weak and when,<br />
therefore, the Commonwealth support for the Loan programmes<br />
whiich have just been arranged with the States rqay turn out<br />
to be quite substantial on the Budget itself. Last year<br />
we had a very lush Loan market. This year we can't expect<br />
it to be as good and this means that you may find yourself<br />
having to support or supplement the Loan market with X<br />
millions out of the Budget. I wouldntt like to say how<br />
much but it very probably would be substantial; and at a<br />
time when the Loan market is a bit weak, there is a<br />
disposition for the redemption obligations to grow because<br />
fewer people convert and that again is a Budget item. It<br />
comes into the cash position. So that we have a large<br />
Budget problem and apart from that, as I've said, of course<br />
there is the manpower problem. </p>
<p>PART TWO<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES) AT THE AUSTRALIAN EMBASSY,<br />
WASHINGTON, on 9TH JUNE, 1965<br />
Aft pr the Prime Minister had discussed the impact of the Defence<br />
bui4Ld-up on Australia's Budget and resources, he commented further<br />
on Jnited States' awareness of Australia's development problems)<br />
PRIKE MINISTER After all there is a great awareness here of<br />
the fact that the problem of growth of Australia and the<br />
development of resources is one of great importance to us<br />
and as we're an Ally, they want to see us growing stronger and<br />
Ithat's quite right. And when their enterprises have gone<br />
into Australia they have been active and they have been<br />
profitable. Some of them export quite largely and the<br />
Americans are realistic enough to know that you can't just<br />
chop off the supply of capital without in the long run<br />
hindering the development of these very enterprises. So<br />
that there is a common interest their enterprises want to<br />
succeed and we want them to succeed because we want the<br />
country to grow and our resources to develop.<br />
Q. Sir7did you extend an invitation to President<br />
Johnson to visit Australia sometime in the future?<br />
P. N. Look, there's no need to. He knows that, But if you<br />
want to know whether I said 114hen are you coming out or what<br />
have you, no, no, there's no point in that. He would like<br />
very much to come to Australia and of course we would like<br />
him to come, but not a very good time, I think, to be asking<br />
people to come away. I'd like Mr. McNamara to come to<br />
Australia but Mr. McNamara has got a plate full at present.<br />
It doesn't make it very easy for him to get out of the country.<br />
But they are all friendly. They would like to go but we<br />
haven't got to the stage of sending them an invitation.<br />
Q4 I wasn't thinking in terms of a formal invitation.<br />
P.* I V It might be quite embarrassing, you see, because<br />
they might have to say I do know the President's<br />
outlook on this matter and he would certainly like to come<br />
but I wouldn't have thought there was any chance this year.<br />
Q. Sir.. one other thing related to Vietnam. Since the<br />
announcement has been made, has it been possible to assess<br />
the reaction in Asia to Australia's decision in Vietnam?<br />
P4N. I donft think it has really. We get vague general<br />
remarks, approval here, and silence there. There are people<br />
concerned with what's going on inside South Vietnam as to<br />
whether there might be some resistance on the part of the<br />
local inhabitants to outsiders coming in with forces, and on<br />
this I discussed the matter not only with Max-rell Taylor but<br />
through our own Ambassador and with senior military officers<br />
we sent up recently to look over the ground and they are all<br />
of the opinion that this is welcomed and that is very<br />
important. It is to avoid any resistances or resentments of<br />
that kind that the military arrangements involve the close<br />
association of American troops with troops of South Vietnam.<br />
0 0 0 0 </p>
<p>8-<br />
Q. w Sir, reverting back to Mr. Connor again, I was<br />
wndering whether you discussed any trade barriers.<br />
PA4No, no, I didn't want to become involved myself in<br />
specific arguments about specific commodities because, vwell,<br />
this is not my field. I'm not the expert in this field.<br />
My colleague the Minister for .' rade is., He and his people<br />
are constantly in negotiation with them, I think Dr.<br />
Westerman was here in the last few days. No. I don't horn<br />
in on that. I occasionally may offer a broad remark which<br />
perhaps registers somewhere but not in detail.<br />
QO Just back to Vietnam if we might for a minute, Sir.<br />
Was General Taylor able to assure you or make clear the<br />
views of the South Vietnamese themselves on this war? Are<br />
they still wholeheartedly behind it?<br />
P. * He thinks the morale is good. Yes. Of course the<br />
war will begin to build up when the Viet Cong morale falls,<br />
but of course, the Viet Cong morale we may assume will be<br />
pretty good during this wet season because of the reason we<br />
mentioned earlier. Every now and then they have a little<br />
bit of a coup.<br />
QO You mentioned earlier, Sir, that you couldn't<br />
foretell what might happen in the next few years, or<br />
something to that effect. I was wondering is it the opinion<br />
of General Taylor and others that this war might go on for<br />
some years? No, I wouldn't put that view into his, They have<br />
to look at this thing as any other person would, step by<br />
step as it develops. I think any estimate as to the<br />
length of this trouble will be affected by whether during<br />
the wet season the Viet Cong really do make what I'll call<br />
some permanent headway and on that he's both confident and<br />
resolute. After that, who knows?<br />
Q. In other words, the next two months will be<br />
crucial? or three<br />
P. 0 1 think the next Iwo/ months in a sense will be<br />
crucial but in any event will be difficult, and morale<br />
will have to be maintained and these, as I said earlier,<br />
any little setbacks that occur here and there will have to<br />
be seen in their proper proportion and not regarded as the<br />
writing on the wall. But I think the public morale is<br />
pretty good on these things. One mustn't expect too much<br />
unhappiness. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
