<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4765</transcript-id>
    <title>DISCUSSIONS WITH MR N USHIBA - JAPANESE MINISTER OF STATE FOR EXTERNAL ECONOMIC AFFAIRS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004765.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 28 JULY 1978<br />
Discussions with Mr. N. Ushiba Japanese Minister of State<br />
for External Economic Affairs<br />
The Prime Minister will hold discussions at Nareeri next<br />
Monday ( 31 July) with Mr. Nobuhiko Ushiba, the Japanese<br />
Minister of State for External Economic Affairs. The<br />
following day, Mr. Ushiba will meet in Canberra with a<br />
number of senior Australian Government Ministers.<br />
Mr. Ushiba, who is visiting Australia from 31 July to 2 August<br />
as a guest of the Australian Government will be briefing<br />
Ministers on the outcome of the Bonn Summit held on<br />
16-17 July.<br />
The Prime Minister recalled that the Bonn Summit had been<br />
attended by the Heads of State of Canada, France, Federal<br />
Republic of Germany, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom,<br />
and the USA. The European Community was represented by<br />
the President of the European Council and by the President<br />
of the European Commission for discussion of matters within<br />
the Community's competence. The principal subjects discussed<br />
at the Summit were growth, employment and inflation; energy;<br />
external trade and protectionism; relations with developing<br />
countries; and international monetary policy.<br />
The Prime Minister said that Mr. Ushiba' s visit provided<br />
an excellent opportunity to exchange views with Japan on<br />
imporiint developments in the international economy elements<br />
of which, particularly in the trade area, are of considerable<br />
concern to the Australian Government. The Prime Minister<br />
said that the discussions with Mr. Ushiba would be a<br />
valuable supplement to the talks which he had<br />
held with Government leaders during his recent overseas visit.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
