<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6159</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006159.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4j STIA1JA L<br />
FOR MEDIA19 July 1983<br />
The attached letter has been sent to the Chief Minister<br />
of the Northern Territory, Mr Everingham, today. </p>
<p>714 PRIME MINISTER CANBEERRA<br />
My dear Chief Minister<br />
Thank you for your recent correspondence concerning<br />
the Alice Springs to Darwin railway and your request<br />
that I meet with you again to discuss this issue.<br />
In your corresponCence you have rejected the Commonwealth's<br />
offer in respect to the construction of the Alice Springs<br />
to Darwin railway and our proposal that an independent<br />
economic evaluation be held into the road and rail options<br />
for providing a high standard all-weather transport link<br />
to Darwin.<br />
I must say that I find this advice somewhat at odds with<br />
the recent announcement by yourself that you will join<br />
the Premier of Queensland in funding a feasibility study<br />
into rail links between Mt Isa, Alice Springs and Darwin.<br />
I have noted your statement that the Queensland<br />
Government would be prepared to meet the cost of building<br />
such a project.<br />
My communications with you on this matter have been made<br />
in good faith, in an attempt to find a solution in the<br />
interests of the Australian people, and particularly of<br />
economic development in the Northern Territory. Despite<br />
your initial rejection of it, I consider my offer for<br />
the Commonwealth to fund completely an independent economic<br />
inquiry into the interstate transport links of the<br />
Northern Territory to remain open. However, if you<br />
confirm your commitment to the proposal you announced today,<br />
to fund jointly with Queensland a feasibility study of<br />
the Mt Isa-Tennant Creek-Alice Springs-Darwin railway,<br />
this would seem to represent an irreversible rejection of<br />
interest in-the inquiry. Given the continued interest of<br />
my own Government, and of other parties including the<br />
South Australian Government, in carefully evaluating the<br />
proposal, the Commonwealth will need to keep its own<br />
options open even if you adopt this position.<br />
For the record, I repeat that your rejection of the<br />
Commonwealth's offer on the railway would not represent<br />
the end of our commitments to improvement of Northern<br />
Territory transport links. The Commonwealth would honour<br />
the undertaking it gave to you of ensuring that a high<br />
standard all-weathner land transport link was provided<br />
through the Northern Territory to Darwin. This would be<br />
achieved by completing the upgrading of the Stuart Highway..<br />
between Alice Springs and Darwin by 1987 and providing / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
additional rail infrastructure in respect to the<br />
Alice Springs rail service. As I have previously advised<br />
you, these works would involve additional Commonwealth<br />
grants of $ 50 million over this period.<br />
I am afraid that it will be impossible to meet you over<br />
the next two weeks, when the demands of budget preparation,<br />
including meetings of the Budget Cabinet, are added to<br />
the normal demands of my office. However, I have asked<br />
my Minister for Transport, Mr Peter Morris, to make himself<br />
available to meet with you on this matter as soon as a<br />
mutually satisfactory time can be arranged.<br />
Yours sincerely<br />
R. J. L. Hawke<br />
The Hon. Paul Everingham, MLA<br />
Chief Minister of the Northern Territory<br />
DARWIN NT 5790 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
