<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9893</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, PRESIDENTIAL PALACE, JAKARTA, 18 DECEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/12/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009893.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, PRESIDENTIAL PALACE, JAKARTA, 18 DECEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Can I just begin by saying that the signing of this agreement with<br />
Indonesia is a very satisfying moment for me. What it does is give full<br />
expression to the kind of relationship I believe we should have always<br />
had with Indonesia and it is a declaration of trust and cooperation on both<br />
of our parts where we are saying that the security of the region is a<br />
common interest between the two of us. They are saying the environment<br />
and security of our continent is of interest to them as we are saying the<br />
strategic environment of their archipelago are of interest to us.<br />
We were here, of course, at the founding of this state. We were the first<br />
country to support the Indonesian people against the Dutch in the post<br />
war decolonising period and we have much of substance and durability in<br />
this relationship. And, I think, the weight of it is given evidence by the fact<br />
that this is the most powerful, if you like in government terms, delegation<br />
to have visited a country the Prime Minister, the Deputy Prime Minister,<br />
the Foreign Minister and the Minister for Defence.<br />
So, you might remember that during the middle of 1991 1 gave an<br />
interview during the then leadership challenge saying that one of the<br />
things I wanted to do was to see a proper relationship with Indonesia and<br />
this sets up that structure within the broader architecture of the Asia-<br />
Pacific under the aegis of APEC.<br />
In these two ways we have given more substance to this relationship and<br />
declared more obviously our trust in it than we have ever done before.<br />
J: Prime Minister, there has been another demonstration in Australia today<br />
on the East Timor issue, what can you do or say to bring those people on<br />
board? </p>
<p>PM: It Is, I think, so obvious that the treaty for security is about maintaining a<br />
peaceful environment In the region. You have got this government<br />
seeking now to start the long process of the destocking of the nuclear<br />
arsenals. We have been responsible in a large part for a convention<br />
ridding the world of a whole treaty of weapons, of chemical weapons. The<br />
government's support for peace in Cambodia, what we have done in the<br />
region with APEC and what we are doing here is all about peace and<br />
security. So, why people would demonstrate about peace and security is<br />
beyond me and when they wish to focus on Timor, the only positive way, I<br />
think, Timor can be approached as an issue is in a relationship with this<br />
substance. So, I just think they have to understand where the<br />
government is coming from in terms of peace and security generally and<br />
Indonesia in particular.<br />
J: Do you think you could have won their support if you had made this a<br />
more public process<br />
PM: Well, if there had been a more public process there probably wouldn't<br />
have been a treaty.<br />
J: Doesn't that prove a point of perhaps needing greater public support for<br />
this treaty?<br />
PM: No, this treaty was negotiated privately within the due processes of<br />
government, of the Cabinet and in the authority given to the Parliament<br />
and to Its majority, the government and to its executive the Cabinet. All<br />
the appropriate protocols have been followed in the development of a<br />
treaty around sensitive issues. This wide notion that you can go out<br />
making a declaration that you want a treaty without even knowing whether<br />
the other partner has any intention of reciprocity.<br />
J: Could you see any further such bilateral treaties with Australia and other<br />
countries in the region?<br />
PM: Not really. This is the key one. The fact Is that we have put Into place in<br />
the last couple of years two key things, we have built a new political<br />
architecture in the Asia-Pacific with APEC which has North America,<br />
Japan, China, Korea and South East Asia and Australia and New Zealand<br />
and we have built a bilateral treaty of security with our nearest largest<br />
neighbour, That sort of structure Australia has never had before.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
