<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>207</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTITIVES ON THE 7TH SEPTEMBER, 1960</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1960</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000207_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. R. G.<br />
MENZIES, IN THE HOUSE OF REPAESENTATIVES ON THE<br />
SEPTEMBE. i, 960<br />
Before I refer to the principal topic of this debate,<br />
I should like to refer to two other natters that have been<br />
glanced at by other honorable mnmbers. The honorable member<br />
for lentworth ( Mr. Bury), in a thoughtful speech last night,<br />
made reference to the Public Service Board and offered some<br />
criticism of the inordinate delay that appears to exist in<br />
presenting the final report of the board to the Parliament. I<br />
am impressed by that criticism, and I certainly propose to try<br />
to get a better performance in that field. I know the reasons<br />
offered for the delay, but I think that the delay is far too<br />
great. The honorable member for Fremantle ( Mr. Beazley) made<br />
reference to the National Library. Perhaps I should point out<br />
for his information, because I know he is interested in this<br />
matter that we have taken the steps necessary to appoint the<br />
Council of the new National Library, and I hope to be in a<br />
position to announce its composition within a few days.<br />
Now I turn to the problem of the Commonwealth and<br />
education. I do not want to deliver a long speech on it,<br />
because the problem has been thrashed out more than once in this<br />
Parliament, either in the House or in commiitteeo However, I<br />
think that I ought to say something not for the first time<br />
about the much-debated constitutional problem, the problem of<br />
power. My friend, the honorable member for Bass ( Mr. Barnard),<br />
pointed out that we seen to have no difficulty in making laws<br />
with respect to health, medical services and pharmaceutical<br />
benefits and in having Comuonwealth Ministers in charge of these<br />
activities. I remind hin that that is provided for in the<br />
Constitution. Je have express powers in connexion with those<br />
matters as a result of the last successful constitutional<br />
referendum. So no problem of power arises in that field.<br />
There is no question as to the power of the Commonwealth<br />
to make grants to the States under section 96 of the<br />
Constitution. I do not know whether I am supposed to have been<br />
dragged reluctantly to a knowledge of that fact. All I can say<br />
is that, over 30 years ago on behalf, I think, of the State of<br />
South Australia I advanced an unsuccessful argunont in the<br />
High Cour' to the effect that the power under section 96was<br />
limited to setting our financial terms and conditions. The High<br />
Court, with unaccustomed unaninity, disagreed with me. It<br />
rejected the argument and said that the terns of section 96<br />
were as they stood that money could be granted to a State on<br />
such terms and conditions as the Comnonwealth Parliament laid<br />
down. That is now beyond all dispute, but honorable members<br />
opposite, as well as those on my own side, must have this in<br />
mind: If the Comonwealth proceeded to use its power to make<br />
grants under section 96 in such a fashion as to take out of the<br />
control of the States in adcministrative detail if you like<br />
some matter over which'they exercise authority, then federalism<br />
would disappear in a few years. The position of the States could<br />
be undermined if that took place. Consequently, any sensible<br />
government has been astute to avoid such unnecessary<br />
interference. On the very day when somebody in this chamber<br />
discovered section 96, and rather twitted me with notknowing<br />
about it, I presented a bill to make grants to the States, under<br />
section 96, with respect to universities. But although that<br />
legislation contains provisions for matching grants, for the<br />
distribution of the grants to the various universities and for<br />
financial assistance to residential colleges, nothing in it<br />
interferes with the internal management of universities by the </p>
<p>0 university authorities. The autonomy of those universities,<br />
including the great State universities, is preserved. ie have<br />
not interfered with natters of policy and administration which<br />
belong to the States.<br />
I think it is essential to have that aspect of the<br />
matter in mind. It is quite true that if the Cormonweolth<br />
Parliament wished to provide another œ 10,000,000, œ 20,000,000<br />
œ: 0,000,000 or œ 100,000,000 a year to the States over and<br />
above what it provides now, and if it could prudently do so, it<br />
could say, " This is a grant to the States for the purposes of<br />
education primary and secondary or scientific". But that is<br />
no discovery. The essence of this matter is that if the Coramonwealth<br />
starts to interfere with the educational policies of the<br />
States, with the way in which they go about their job in the<br />
educational field, that will be a very bad day for Australia.<br />
Although I have been very active in this field, as honorable<br />
mrembers know, I have always made that approach, in principle,<br />
to this problem. Although the argumont varies a little in detail, it<br />
is always put in some way such as this: First of all, it is<br />
said that education is vastly inportant; it is a great<br />
national problem. So it is. The Loader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr. Calwoll) was good enough to quote me as saying that it was<br />
a great national problem. I onoaged in the trifling task of<br />
looking at what was said on that occasion, and it is interesting<br />
to note that I went on to say that land settlement was a great<br />
national problem and so also were wateo supplies and power<br />
supplies. These are all vastly important national problems.<br />
The whole aspect of the matter is that some of them have been<br />
given into the hands of this Parliament for this Parliament to<br />
do what it wishes in relation to then, both in principle and in<br />
detail, while other problems of great national importance, as I<br />
agree, have been loft in the hands of the States.<br />
But, Sir, some say education is a great problem; it<br />
is vastly important. I agree that it is. Indeed, I venture to<br />
say with great humility, that no Prime Minister of this country<br />
has ever taken such an active and constructive interest in it as<br />
I have iyself. It is a very great problem. The next step in<br />
this strange syllogism is t. at the Conmronwealth, except in<br />
university matters, is accepting no financial responsibility in<br />
the solving of this problmr; it is leaving the problem to the<br />
under-nourished State Governumnts. The conclusion from this is<br />
that the Coi. i: onwealth Government ought to be condemned. Now<br />
Sir, the answer to all that kind of argument is a simple iater<br />
of facts. I just state it in this way: The Commonweaith by<br />
express legislation and by express grant under section 96 of<br />
the Constitution, has assumed large obligations in the field<br />
of university education. When I m: iade my announcement in 1958<br />
of our adoption of every recor. n-ondation of the Murray committee,<br />
the then Loader of the Opposition, Dr. Evatt, said that our<br />
attitude towards this matter was nunificent, That was his own<br />
-word. Did we stop there, or do we stop there? It is quite<br />
true that we do not make an ear-marked grant to the States for<br />
secondary education or primary education; but we provide the<br />
States with tax reimbursement and with support for a w orks loan<br />
programme, and a very large : nd material factor in both is the<br />
needs of the States educational systems. They nmow it; we know<br />
it. Everybody knows it except those who want to pretend the<br />
Commonwealth is doing nothing abut it.<br />
Sir, it seems to be forgotten that only last yoer<br />
in 1959 there was a groat conference with the State Premiers.<br />
The Premiers are not incapable, in ny very long experience of<br />
thon, of putting forward the claims and deserts of their own </p>
<p>3.<br />
States but in the 199 conference, a discussion took place<br />
about the reimbursement rules or formula. A new agreement was<br />
made for a period. of six years. This is an agreement an<br />
arrangement created to endure for six years and containing,<br />
in itself, all the oleoents of adjustment. It contains the<br />
basis on which the grant is to be increased, having regard to<br />
population and having reoard to increases in wages, with a<br />
little accommodating factor in addition. That arrangement was<br />
made after a discussion in which the State Premiers put forward<br />
the problems that they have, among other things, in the field<br />
of education because of imriigration and because of a rapidly<br />
increasing school population. All these things were put forward<br />
by the Premiers. They knew perfectly well that whatever figure<br />
was agreed upon, it would be a figure that paid regard to their<br />
educational needs.<br />
Perhaps I might interrupt myself there to mak-one<br />
point,-and indeed I ought to apologizc to the conmmittee for<br />
rehearsing matters that are already well known. Older members<br />
of this Parliament will remember that back in 1945 or 1946 I<br />
forget the precise year the then Prime Minister, Mr. Chifloy,<br />
arranged with the States for a form: ula on which tax reimbursement<br />
would be calculated. It was a formula that was to pay<br />
attention to increases in wages and increases in population.<br />
It was worked out and it was unanimously accepted by the States.<br />
In my own teor of office since the end of 19199, my own Governeont<br />
has never held the States to that formula as adjusted on<br />
the basis that was worked out. Jo have always added to it.<br />
Year after yea-, wo have mado additional payments to the States,<br />
sometimes running to as much as œ 20,000,000.<br />
Mr. Cairns How could you avoid it?<br />
MR. MENZIES: Jo do not have to worry about how to .' void it,<br />
but the honorable .: ember would be none the worse for knowing the<br />
facts. Indeed, he would be greatly improved. The fact is that<br />
we did make those additional payments year by year and we made<br />
then because we realized the pressures under which the States<br />
lived and recognized that they must be given proper troatment if<br />
they were to discharge their duties,,<br />
In 1959, the now arrangement was nr'. do, . ts offect in<br />
the first financial year was this: Whoroas in 1958-59 the States<br />
got œ 205, 00,000 in reimbursement grants, under the formula<br />
grants for 1959-60 they would got œ 2_ 14,000,00o Every State<br />
Premier accepted the new arrangement. The Premiers did not<br />
accept it, as might be suggestod, unwillingly needs must when<br />
the devil drives but each of then accepted it with great<br />
expressions of satisfaction, most of which are in the record of<br />
the Premiers' Conference. Anybody who knows any of the Premiers<br />
knows perfectly well that they felt this was a fine deal and<br />
that it gave them a feeling of security over a period of six<br />
years. During that period they would not need to co-ne back and<br />
argue about the basis on rwhich reimbursoront ought to occur.<br />
Indeed they could look forward to increasing roso. ircos to<br />
discharge their responsibilities, including their great education<br />
responsibilities. What is the effect of all that? I would like those<br />
who think of the problems of educ.-tion solely in terms of<br />
getting money over and above what is now provided from the<br />
Commonwealth to-recognize something else. I take my own State<br />
as an example, not because I iish to conpro the record df<br />
Victoria with any other State so far as I am able to judge<br />
every State has a very good record in this field but because<br />
the figures for Victoria have just emerged. As a result of this<br />
new agreement for six years , rwhich was entered into last yoer,<br />
Victoria, which had anticipated a deficit of over fœ 1,00,000<br />
actually had a surplus of over œ 300,000. That is an cxample of </p>
<p>4.<br />
how beneficial this arrangement -ras. But here is the point:<br />
In Victoria it was announced only the night before last that<br />
the 1960-61 Budget for Victoria would provide a record education<br />
vote of about œ+ 4,000,000. The 1945-46 vote, when ny friends<br />
opposite were in coi-mand of the exchequer, was œ 4,800,000. This<br />
year, over and above our universities grant which is, of<br />
course, a separate natter on our account, we have provided<br />
œ 54,000,000. By 1949-50 the vote had risen to œ 10,500,000; last<br />
year it was œ 45,600,000. This year the vote will rise from<br />
œ 45,600,000 to about œ 54,000,000. In other words there will<br />
be an increase of between œ 8,000,000 and œ 9,000,060 in one yearin<br />
a year in which it is said that we are starving the States<br />
of resources to spend on their educational needsl I venture<br />
to says with all moderation, that the statement that the<br />
Comonwealth carries no responsibility in the State educational<br />
field is utter humbug and the people who say it know that it is<br />
utter humbug. What they want to do is to deceive a lot of<br />
people into believing that primary and secondary education are<br />
being neglected6 As I have just demonstrated quite cloerly, we<br />
provide for those categories of education scores of millions of<br />
pounds every year through this fully accepted and woll-received<br />
six-year agreement on tax roinbu: rsements.,<br />
Apart altogether from tax reimbursements which deal<br />
with revenue matters, each year, the States come to the<br />
Australian Loan Council, very properly, and say, " We want to<br />
borrow money for a works prograime". The ro. uost may be for<br />
œ 300,000,000. The figure is usually a little high. t4e discuss<br />
between ourselves how ruch money can be borrowed on the market.<br />
It used to be the sole business of the Loan Council to decide<br />
how much could be borrowed on reasonable terms and conditions,<br />
and no other Commonwealth Government ever supplneented that<br />
amount out of Cormonwealth icvcnuo, In the last ten years<br />
however, we have supplemented borrowings out of the revenue of<br />
the Commonwealth every year. Instead of asking simply, " How<br />
much can be borrowed?" vo have tried to work out a reasonable<br />
figure which would give reasonable prospects to the States of<br />
carrying out their works prograLnnes, including the construction<br />
of school buildings a not inconsiderable itoe,<br />
This year, as usual, we agreed to a larger loan works<br />
programme than in the year before and in effect, though not<br />
technically so, we underwrote it. I say " not technically so"<br />
because technically we do not underwrite this programme. Ule<br />
make a monthly payment to the States of one-twelfth of the<br />
agreed upon programe, whether the money is to cone fron the<br />
loan market or not. Theorotically, Twe revi e this in ' anuary<br />
but in practice the payments remain the sani. So, in teorn. s of<br />
capital and revenue provision, this Co: IIonr'oal th is, by the<br />
financial machinery now oxisting., accepti. ng and discharging<br />
enormous responsibilities in respect of every form of education<br />
that we have in this country. I do not corplain about that.<br />
I am proud to be able to say that this is so because nobody<br />
has a more vivid understanding than I have nyself of the great<br />
importance of education to oor nation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
