<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9707</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP FREEDOM FLAME CEREMONY, BRISBANE, 15 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009707.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MIMiSTER THE HON P J KEATING, MP'<br />
FREEDOM FLAME CEREMONY, BRISBANE, 15 AUGUST 1995<br />
*" CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY*"<br />
This has been a very good year in the lifes of Australia. It was a great year when<br />
the war was won. and I think this fftieth anniversary year will go down as a very<br />
good one.<br />
We could not live upto the deeds, but Ithink wecan say that in the year of<br />
" Australia Remembers" the people of Australia lived up to the memory.<br />
And we have remembered. We do remember. We have felt the bonds between<br />
us and those Australians who, with our alies, fought and won the greatest of all<br />
victorles fifty year ego<br />
VP means Victory in the Pacific. It has also been called VJ Day Victory over<br />
Japan and some people thought that is what we should call it In Australia.<br />
I think most of us f OWtfirstt uterIst reafly important one -the " V for<br />
victory.. The victory over tyrny and aggression. The victory for freedom<br />
decency and justice. The victory for peace.<br />
That is what we are celebrating.<br />
And I think there Is reason to bellev that we have a little more cause to celebrate<br />
aftr today's statement by the Prime Minister of Japan.<br />
Today Mr Murayama acknowledged the " Irretf~ tl % Wta of Japanese<br />
aggression in World War 11 and the " tremendous damrage and suffeing" it<br />
caused. Mr Murayarna said: " I regard, in aspiit of humility, these irrefuitable facts of<br />
history, and express here once again my feelings of deep remorse, and state my<br />
heartfelt apoloy. </p>
<p>I am sure all Australians welcome Mr Murayarna's statement. We all feel that it is<br />
essential for the Japanese people to know and acknowledge the truth about the<br />
past.<br />
Australians have learned a lot about the past this year. We have learned a lot<br />
about the war and what victory meant.<br />
And we have learned how fortunate we are that we still have the things for which<br />
Australians fought<br />
We are free few people were ever so free, few countries were ever. so<br />
democratic. Few have ever enjoyed for so long the peace we have enjoyed in the past fifty<br />
years. We have our liberty, we have our rights, and we are at peace few nations were<br />
ever so fortunate.<br />
" Australia Remembers" has been a way of saying that we do not take this for<br />
granted a way of reminding ourselves that we never can.<br />
To remember has been to recognise that these great gifts were delivered to us at<br />
immeasurable human cost.<br />
It has been to remind us all that peace and freedom are hard won and we must<br />
be prepared to defend them.<br />
To remember has been to be reminded that when democracy needed defending<br />
in Europe, Australia sent help.<br />
And when we neee help, it was sent to us.<br />
When Australia remembered this year we remembered the help we received from<br />
the United States.<br />
We remembered all those from Britain and the countries of the Commonwealth<br />
who fought alongside Australians, suiffiered in prison camps with Australians, died<br />
and lie buried with Australians.<br />
To remember the Second World War Is to be reminded that free people have a<br />
duty to freedom everywhere.<br />
That might be the greatest lesson of all.<br />
This year has been a great one for another reason. </p>
<p>It has reminded us that while our world has changed dramatically, and while the<br />
young Australians of today are very different to those who fought the war fifty<br />
years ago, the bonds between our generations are unbreakable.<br />
It has reminded us that the passage of time and. changes in perspective and<br />
fashion cannot after the fact that we are the same people that we are part of the<br />
same Australian story.<br />
We have all drawn inspiration from remembering the deeds of the war generation.<br />
I sincerely hope that that great generation has drawn some comfort from seeing<br />
us inspired.<br />
We are all a little stronger for this year. And Australia is a little stronger.<br />
We not only know more about the war and what we won from it; I venture to say<br />
we know more about how to win.<br />
We know more about each other, more about the value of men and women from<br />
all parts of the continent, all backgrounds and all parts of the world, working<br />
together and sticking together.<br />
We certainly know more about what it is to be Australian and we know more<br />
about the duty that implies.<br />
Celebrating the generation of 1945 has taught us that it is our duty to live up to<br />
their love for this country and the sacrifice they made for it.<br />
It has taught us to believe in ourselves, defend freedom and cherish peace.<br />
Above all, it has taught us to be like those at Kokoda, or in the camps of Thailand<br />
and Burma to keep up the faith and keep going.<br />
I thank everyone who has made Australia Remembers such a wonderful event<br />
every organiser, every worker and every participant<br />
And most of all, I thank every member of that magnificent generation of<br />
Australians who won that victory for all of us fifty years ago.<br />
I v-<br />
A d. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
