<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4218</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORAL TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004218.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
, jASAI( A F76/ 174<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 22 AUGUST 1976<br />
ELECTORAL TALK<br />
The Government's first budget is a budget of reform.<br />
First and foremost it is a people's budget. It is not<br />
just a budget for business, for mining companies or for<br />
large producers. It is a document that recognises that<br />
people come first.<br />
The budget strategy follows a strong and consistent Liberal<br />
approach to national progress it places emphasis on individual<br />
opportunity and concern for those in need.<br />
Tonight I want to talk to you about the real reforms this<br />
budget presents to all Australians.<br />
In every sense, the Liberal/ NCP Government has pursued a<br />
consistent course for reform that was long overdue. Just on<br />
nine months ago, we told Australians there were many reforms<br />
we wanted to introduce. We said that some could and must<br />
be introduced immediately. That was last year, before the<br />
election. What has happened since?<br />
Quite simply, the Government has honoured its promises. We<br />
have brought in some of the most significant social reforms<br />
sinceFederation. And these reforms have been introduced in<br />
such a way that the community can afford.<br />
On May 20, the Treasurer announced a family allowance scheme<br />
that provided immediate and direct cash benefit to 300,000<br />
Australian low. income families and 800,000 children. This<br />
scheme is already in full operation. A great deal of personal<br />
hardship and suffering has been alleviated and a great deal<br />
more avoided. It has been applauded by trade unions, social<br />
welfare organisations, community groups and even supported<br />
by our political opponents.<br />
At the-same time) we announced the introduction of full indexation<br />
of personal income tax. We said we would do it within three<br />
years. It took just six months.<br />
Both of these reforms reforms that put people first were<br />
an integral part of our budget strategy. They are a keystone of<br />
Liberal philosophy. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
They were introduced before the formal August budget to<br />
provide the much-needed confidence and relief to those many<br />
thousands of Australians on low incomes who were not previously<br />
protected against the destructive -forces of inflation.<br />
We took the unprecedented step of introducing a major part of<br />
our budget strategy three months before the'budget was<br />
introduced, in the Parliament. We believe that those three<br />
months were too precious to waste. We could not let Australia wait.<br />
The formal budget introduced by the Treasurer last week<br />
followed our consistent course ' to reform.<br />
The Government allocated $ 5389 million for our continuing<br />
committment to maintain and improve Social Security benefits<br />
and welfare services.<br />
This figure about one quarter of the total budget outlayrepresents<br />
a 23 percent increase over the amount spent in<br />
this area last year.<br />
The Government has been concerned to make sure that people in<br />
greatest need receive the greatest assistance. We believe<br />
that this budget allows us to do just this.-<br />
Our concern for people is illustrated in many ways. Pensions<br />
will now be automtatically adjusted in line with Consumer Price Index<br />
increases. This move will protect pensioners against increased<br />
living costs. For the first time it will take pensioner<br />
payments out of the political arena.<br />
The separate property component in the means test for<br />
pensioners has been abolished. From early November pensioners<br />
will be means tested on income only. This will include income<br />
from property. It is not a test based on the combined value of<br />
income and property.<br />
Many pensioners will gain fromt this significant reform. It will,<br />
prevent injustices where-many people are now denied the pension<br />
simply because they own property.<br />
For the thousands of Australia's handicapped this has been a<br />
budget of real reform. No other Australian Government<br />
has done more for the handicapped than this Government.<br />
Allowances to handicapped children have been increased by 50 percent.<br />
From the beginning of November the allowance will jump from<br />
to $ 15 a week. Also, the handicapped children's benefit paid<br />
in respect to handicapped children in instutions has been increased<br />
from $ 3.50 a day to $ 5 a day. These two increases will benefit<br />
about 21,000 handicapped children.<br />
Funds for handicapped persons assistance will be $ 121 million<br />
over the next three years. This will assist voluntary organisations<br />
set up and operate sheltered workshops, therapy-and training<br />
centres and to provide accommodation for handicapped children<br />
and adults. </p>
<p>For all of Australia's handicapped children and adultsand<br />
the friends, relatives or guardians of the handicappedthis<br />
Government's first budget is a social document in<br />
the truest sense.<br />
The Government has shown to the handicapped that we are<br />
concerned first with people, and not just with figures.<br />
As previously announced, the Government has allocated<br />
$ 225 million over the next three years to subsidiso<br />
the building of aged persons accommodation. This again<br />
is a significant degree of assistance to an area of real need.<br />
It will provide urgently needed accommodation for about<br />
15,000 aged people.<br />
This programme will also assist voluntary organisations<br />
by ensuring a continuing of planning and building for<br />
the next three years. They will be able to borrow in this<br />
first year against the allocation for the remaining two years.<br />
In our budget we also introduced a special deduction to apply<br />
where an interest in an estate passes to a surviving spouse.<br />
The Government regards this as a necessary and important<br />
reform as it is an area of the law where personal tragedies are<br />
commonplace.<br />
Following a view put by the Henderson Inquiry into Poverty,<br />
the Government has decided to implement a trial programme<br />
designed to assist low income earners choose their own rental<br />
accommodation on the open market.<br />
If successful it will provide the Government with a new mechanism<br />
to make welfare housing sensitive to the needs of the users rather<br />
than-. those of the planners. The Government will look closely<br />
a t progress in this important social welfare area.<br />
From those in need of special as'sistance to ordinary working men<br />
and women this is a budget that puts people first.<br />
For the first time in four years, Australians were not hit<br />
with indirect taxes to help pay for expensive and wasteful<br />
Government programmes. There was no extra indirect tax on<br />
cigarettes, wine, beer or petrol. It was not needed, it was<br />
not wanted.<br />
In my Policy Speech late last year, I said that Australia<br />
needed reform. Our first budget that includes the May<br />
statement has advanced Australia one major step in fulfilling<br />
that need.<br />
I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
