<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9074</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP OPENING OF GEELONG WOOL COMBING LTD </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009074.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
OPENING OF GEELONG WOOL COMBING LTD PLANT, CORIO<br />
DECEMBER 1993<br />
I am very pleased to be here today at the opening of this<br />
wool combing facility in one of the great regional cities<br />
of Australia.<br />
This year marks the bicentenary of the invention of the<br />
first mechanical wool comb, an event which was followed<br />
by combers rioting in the streets of the English wool<br />
towns. You can't help having sympathy for the old Luddites, but<br />
historically speaking they won a few battles and<br />
comprehensively lost the war.<br />
It is very important that we Australians win the war: our<br />
industry has to be at the leading edge of progress.<br />
And this new plant is a perfect example: it will help the<br />
industry and the region.<br />
We are all well aware that the wool industry is going<br />
through a major transitional period that has not been<br />
easy for many growers. The collapse of the Reserve Price<br />
Scheme, the accumulation of a large wool stockpile and a<br />
massive debt, the effects of drought and a collapse of<br />
wool prices have all posed very significant challenges.<br />
Equally, we know that -Geelong has not had an easy time of<br />
it recently.<br />
But both the wool industry and the Geelong region are<br />
resilient: the basis for recovery is there in the quality<br />
of the product and the people.<br />
Both the wool industry and the people of Geelong know<br />
that our industries and our regions need to adapt to keep<br />
pace with international developments. Increasingly they<br />
know that unparalleled opportunity can come from a<br />
readiness to embrace the necessary change.<br />
And the Government is supporting them. </p>
<p>It is one of the truisms of the past that Australia<br />
rode on the sheep's back. And it is a truism of our<br />
present that for all the greatness of our primary and<br />
extractive industries we have to add value to the<br />
product. We have to get from our great resources the maximum in<br />
dollars and the maximum in jobs.<br />
Wool is a marvellous product a marvellous fibre. We<br />
count wool as a primary product but nature has already<br />
added value and marketability. Wool begins with a<br />
distinct comparative advantage. This plant builds on it.<br />
It adds more value.<br />
It can't be said often enough that the image of Australia<br />
stuck in a time warp where it is content to be a supplier<br />
of raw commodities for others to transform is false.<br />
The " dig it up and ship it out" mentality hasn't applied<br />
for a long time not to the Government, not to our<br />
businesses, not to our workers.<br />
That this has happened is a consequence of the energy of<br />
business and industry and the willingness of employees<br />
to confront necessity and embrace change.<br />
You will forgive me for saying that it is also the result<br />
of government policies which we began to apply a decade<br />
ago. Let me briefly run through a few facts.<br />
The Australian economy is now around 30 per cent more<br />
internationally competitive than 10 years ago.<br />
In the last decade, exports have doubled.<br />
They have grown from 13 per cent of GDP to 20 per cent.<br />
Exports of manufactures have trebled and now exceed those<br />
for rural products and minerals and fuels.<br />
In the past six years exports of Elaborately Transformed<br />
Manufactures have grown at an average rate of 19 per cent<br />
per annum and nearly trebled in value.<br />
Today, profits are at record levels.<br />
Inflation is low and under control.<br />
Interest rates are at historically low levels.<br />
Investment is beginning to grow, just as manufacturing<br />
output is growing strongly.<br />
A new culture of industrial relations has been<br />
established one which increases labour market </p>
<p>flexibility and productivity growth by widening the<br />
spread of enterprise bargaining.<br />
Our recent business tax initiatives have ensured that the<br />
competitiveness of our system is on a par with comparable<br />
OECD countries.<br />
We have reduced our corporate tax rate to 33 per cent.<br />
We have introduced a development allowance, a general<br />
investment allowance, a substantial acceleration of<br />
depreciation provisions and concessionally-taxed pooled<br />
development funds.<br />
And we have established an orderly and manifestly<br />
effective program for reducing tariff protection.<br />
There were those who doubted the wisdom of orderly tariff<br />
reduction. What they failed to appreciate was that the existing<br />
tariff regime was manifestly inefficient and unfair<br />
unfair to our trading partners, unfair to employees in<br />
other non-protected areas, unfair to consumers who had to<br />
pay more for their goods.<br />
We had no choice but to change the focus of those<br />
industries, which survived only through border<br />
protection. To bring them to an outlook which is more<br />
conducive to wealth creation for this country an export<br />
oriented outlook.<br />
And we are being proved right.<br />
Take one example. For years it has been axiomatic that<br />
Australians could never be internationally competitive in<br />
textile, clothing and footwear industries.<br />
Well, last year, exports in the TCF area rose by $ 534<br />
million, a 21 per cent increase on the previous year.<br />
They rose because the TCF industries embraced the<br />
necessity of a new industrial culture.<br />
The opening of this plant, as with other recent<br />
developments within the wool and wool processing<br />
industry, is a welcome sign that the wool industry is<br />
embracing this new culture too.<br />
Embracing the need for increased value adding.<br />
The importance of utilising new technology.<br />
The crucial requirement to be market-oriented to be<br />
closely attuned to the needs of its customers.<br />
And to export, export, export particularly to the<br />
rapidly growing markets in the Asia-Pacific region. </p>
<p>It is not enough, as everyone realises, that Australia<br />
continue to dominate the global supply of wool. We<br />
account f or some 30 per cent of world production and<br />
per cent of finer apparel wool but that wool, of<br />
itself, will not re-establish the pre-eminence of the<br />
wool industry in Australia.<br />
The bulk of our wool is still exported in greasy-form,<br />
with little or no value added. For example, Australia's<br />
production of wool tops accounts for only 4 per cent of<br />
global supply and even less in later stage processed<br />
products.<br />
Compare this with a country such as Uruguay which<br />
produces 3 per cent of the world's wool, but is the<br />
second largest exporter of wool tops.<br />
While it is pleasing to note that over the last decade<br />
Australia has doubled its exports of scoured and<br />
carbonised wool, and increased wool top exports by 75 per<br />
cent, there remains considerable scope for expansion in<br />
this area.<br />
It is clear that if we are to secure the Australian wool<br />
industry's long term future as a world supplier of a high<br />
quality wool and wool products, we need to strengthen<br />
linkages between the various segments of the wool<br />
production and marketing chain.<br />
This view was endorsed by the Garnaut Committee, which<br />
was established by the Government to review the wool<br />
industry's institutional and operational arrangements.<br />
The committee's recommendations for new institutional<br />
structures and a new market-driven approach were in large<br />
part taken up by both the Government and the industry,<br />
and new legislative arrangements to give effect to them<br />
have just been put into place.<br />
There is a solid base for Australia to expand its wool<br />
processing sector, particularly in early stage<br />
processing. We have access to a high quality and diverse wool clip.<br />
We have a close proximity to the growing markets of Asia.<br />
Our energy costs are competitive.<br />
For this industry, China will be a key. It alone has<br />
been responsible fo~ r a 20 per cent increase in sales in<br />
the region over the past decade.<br />
In June this year, I discussed with the Chinese Vice<br />
Premier the possibility of developing strategic long-term<br />
linkages between our respective wool and wool textile<br />
industries. </p>
<p>Following a series of negotiations at official and<br />
Ministerial level, agreement was reached whereby China<br />
would reduce, from 1 January 1994, its tariff on wool<br />
tops to 15% that is to the same level as applies to<br />
greasy and scoured wool.<br />
This agreement is an encouraging step forward. It is up<br />
to the industry now to follow it up. We simply cannot<br />
allow such opportunities to pass us by.<br />
The well justified satisfaction we take in the success of<br />
our new manufacturing industries should not lead us to<br />
conclude that our old established industries are of<br />
declining importance. The wool industry remains a great<br />
industry. The point which this new plant makes is that<br />
it can become a greater one.<br />
The decision by Bremer Woll-Kammerei ( BWK) to establish<br />
its first plant outside Germany, is tangible evidence<br />
that major foreign investors believe that Australia is a<br />
location where the wool industry can renew itself.<br />
The benefits that will flow from the establishment of<br />
this plant are significant, both locally and nationally.<br />
Total investment in the project is expected to be<br />
million, and it will create more than 150 new long<br />
term jobs, in addition to those that have been created<br />
during the construction phase.<br />
As a recognised world leader in the production of high<br />
quality wool tops, BWK will also bring state of the art<br />
processing technology to Australia.<br />
I understand that the additional capacity of this plant<br />
will increase to 8 per cent the proportion of the total<br />
Australian clip processed to tops stage by 1996 about<br />
$ 34 million a year of value will be added to the raw wool<br />
processed at the plant.<br />
The Government is substantially supporting this plant<br />
with a $ 5 million grant and a $ 15 million low interest<br />
loan<br />
This plant is the first to be supported under a<br />
million Further Wool Processing Program.<br />
In future, the projects funded will generate over<br />
$ 200 million of new investment, resulting in additional<br />
capacity of over 30 million kilograms of wool tops, a<br />
doubling of current top making capacity, and the creation<br />
of 445 new jobs. Most of this additional output is for<br />
export. This is yet another example of the importance to<br />
Australia of market access, and why the Government has<br />
placed so much importance on securing a successful GATT<br />
outcome. </p>
<p>That outcome now looks like delivering dollar benefits<br />
for Australia at a conservatively estimated<br />
billion. The immediate benefits to Australia will be in<br />
agriculture, but the result will also see the textiles<br />
and clothing sector again coming fully under the GATT<br />
through the phasing out of existing import restrictions<br />
under the Multi-Fibre Agreement ( MFA), particularly in<br />
the important US and European Union markets.<br />
This will free up the world trade in textiles and<br />
clothing, estimated to be worth more than $ 100 billion<br />
annually.<br />
Australia will directly benefit from the liberalisation<br />
in this sector as a substantial supplier of textile raw<br />
materials and a growing exporter of made-up articles.<br />
It is also reasonable to conclude that increased demand<br />
should also push up commodity prices.<br />
We are now in an excellent position to seize the<br />
initiative and capitalise on the opportunities opening in<br />
the international market for wool. I am confident that<br />
our wool and wool-processing industry can emerge as<br />
leading players.<br />
I am confident, too, that the Geelong region will play an<br />
important part in Australia's future success in this and<br />
other industries, just as it has in the past.<br />
Regional development is a matter of primary importance to<br />
the Government, and, as you may be aware, we will next<br />
week receive the report of a Task Force on regional<br />
development, chaired by Mr Bill Kelty.<br />
The Task Force has been inquiring into impediments to<br />
economic development in the regions of Australia, and<br />
into the ways in which regions can use their comparative<br />
advantages to build their future prosperity.<br />
There is no doubt that the internationalisation of the<br />
Australian economy has had differing impacts on different<br />
regions. We believe that if Governments, industry and regional<br />
communities get together, identify the opportunities and<br />
develop the strengths that already exist in abundance in<br />
our regions, it will have major consequences for the<br />
future well-being of this country.<br />
And for the regions themselves, it will ensure that new<br />
jobs and opportunities for enterprise and our youth can<br />
be offered, that the local knowledge and expertise<br />
essential to a prosperous future will not be lost, and<br />
that the regions, which give Australia not just strength </p>
<p>7<br />
but character, will be revitalised for the twenty first<br />
century. In conclusion, let me say again what a pleasure it is to<br />
be here today at the beginning of a new partnership<br />
between a great Australian industry and a great city of<br />
Australia. And now let me officially declare the Geelong Wool<br />
Combing facility open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
