<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18495</transcript-id>
    <title>Business leaders in Canberra for deregulation forum</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Leading business figures will head to Canberra tomorrow to attend the inaugural Business Advisory Forum.</p>
<p>Today the Government has released the list of 26 representatives who will join the Prime Minister and state and territory leaders at the Forum. The Minister for Finance and Deregulation and the Minister Assisting for Deregulation will also attend.</p>
<p>Business figures attending the Business Advisory Forum will:</p>
<p> * 	Nominate new areas of reform to help lift productivity and drive investment;<br />
 * 	Advise Governments on how best to progress the remaining areas of competition and regulatory reform; and<br />
 * 	Discuss ways in which to lift regulatory performance and ensure the economic benefits from key reforms are sustained over time.</p>
<p>Business leaders will be able to directly tell the PM, Premiers and Chief Ministers, from their own perspective, their priorities for cutting red tape.</p>
<p>As we build a new economy in response to the structural changes being driven by our high dollar, deregulation reforms are more important than ever as they have the potential to lower business costs and improve productivity.</p>
<p>We believe business leaders are best placed to advise on these matters because excessive red tape is often experienced at an individual, business or industry level.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister will chair the Forum, which is being supported by the Business Council of Australia, Australian Chamber of Commerce and Industry, Australian Industry Group and the Council of Small Business of Australia.</p>
<p>Through the Forum, the Gillard Government looks forward to working with business and the states to advance a new deregulation agenda over the coming year.</p>
<p>The outcomes of tomorrow's Forum will be incorporated into the discussion at the Council of Australian Governments meeting on Friday. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
