<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15880</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Karen Middleton, SBS TV News   </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/04/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PM: You know what actually hit me between the eyes, was this single undiluted call from the business community and those in our economic working group saying, ‘what we want most of all is a single, seamless national economy'. That is, a single national market. Whether it's in labour, product, carbon, electricity, water. Because the costs of doing business nationally in what is still a relatively small economy by global standards are too great.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: We saw some big picture ideas too and not surprising that we are hearing calls for the Republic. There was a vote yesterday suggesting that should happen within two years. And those calls actually came from within your own Government. What's your response to a two year time frame given that this has come from the floor of this Summit?</p>
<p>PM: Everyone at this Summit has been free to put their own views whether they are from the within the Government, or outside. I'm pretty relaxed about all that. I'm a Republican. Australia will become a Republic. The question is when. The mood of this Summit was obviously strong in support of a Republic. We just need to get the process right.</p>
<p>Remember, we lost the referendum on the Republic less than a decade ago. I don't believe it helps if we lose another one. We've got to get it right.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: Will you drive this forward now after having this brought to you from the Summit?</p>
<p>PM: Well, the relevant Ministers and I will spend some time looking at the details of the new proposal. They put forward a new, as I see it, two stage proposal. Let's work our way through that and see what it contains.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: A couple of other big picture ideas. A bill of rights, and a treaty  -  although that word wasn't specifically used, but that's what that indigenous group was talking about. Your response to those two suggestions?</p>
<p>PM: Well, on the question of a charter of rights, there is already, I believe, an investigation called for by the Labor Party through its last platform on that. And that's the best way forward because there are conflicting views as to what a charter of rights, a legislative charter of rights, does and what it doesn't do, and what its impacts might be. So, open mind on that. And there is already some investigatory work underway.</p>
<p>On the question of a proper legal recognition of indigenous Australia, we of course as a Labor Party are committed to constitutional recognition. And, that is something that we need to get the timing right on as well so that it passes with bipartisan support which will mean getting the language right.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: There was some frustration within the indigenous group that they were being pressured against proposing a treaty, and certainly using that word. And some other groups expressed frustration today that they felt like they have were being a little bit steamrolled by the Government. How do you respond to suggestions that you were steering the agenda across the board?</p>
<p>PM: There were a thousand delegates here you know. I got around to each group, but it's pretty hard to do that. Look, there's always going to be a bit of argy bargy in all of these things. That's just natural, normal, given our different views. But, I am perfectly relaxed about people putting forward their ideas. Whether we can deliver them or not.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: Will you only look at the final list of ideas? I mean, there were a lot of groups who came up with dozens of ideas that didn't make the final cut. How many of those will you look at as well?</p>
<p>PM: Well, the purpose of the Summit process was to distil the discussions in all these groups through the co-ordinators and co-chairs of each of these working groups. And ultimately, you have to respond to the final product of that. But if people have further ideas they want to communicate with the Government on, they're more than welcome. I did indicate today that we would be opening the website for 2020 so that the whole community, not just those who were Summit participants, get to put further submissions to Government as well. The curtains haven't come down.</p>
<p>MIDDLETON: Prime Minister, thank you very much.</p>
<p>PM: Thanks for having me on the program.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
