<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4639</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004639.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargo until delivery 7pm<br />
FOR PRESS 5 MARCH 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
This year promises sianrificant progress in the Australian<br />
economy. The results of the Covernment's firm and responsible economic<br />
management in the last two years will become even more evident.<br />
It will al -o be a year when the most dramatic tax cuts in<br />
Australia's history take direct effect throughout the economy.<br />
They will lift spending which will, in turn, assist industrial<br />
production and stimulate economic activity. They will help<br />
create jobs.<br />
The Government's economic strategy has been clear. For a long<br />
term and sustained reduction in the number of men and women<br />
seeking jobs, inflation had to be reduced.<br />
Inflation has been making Australian industry uncompetitive.<br />
This meant t-hat jobs were lost and opportunities for new jobs<br />
were squandered.<br />
our success in the fight against inflation is now without<br />
challenge it is under 10% for the first time since 1972.<br />
Inflation is still too high but the rate will fall even<br />
further this year.<br />
It is timely that with this succes * s the Government has already<br />
in operation policies that will help create more jobs without<br />
fuelling inflation.<br />
The point that needs to be made is the February tax cuts alone<br />
will put almost $ 1 billion into the hands of Australian families<br />
this year.<br />
This extra money can now be spent on things we need for ourselves<br />
and our families. That will mean more jobs for Australians.<br />
Of course, unless Government policies continue to bear down<br />
on inflation the additional benefits from the tax cuts will be<br />
eroded, and job opportunitles lost. That fight to beat inflation<br />
will go on as strongly as ever.<br />
In terms of their impact on the economy, the Government's tax<br />
cuts are comparable to the measures which other countries have<br />
taken to stimulate their economies. \ t / 2 </p>
<p>6 2.<br />
But the key point is that in Australia the stimulus is a<br />
responsible one. The growth in the money supply is being<br />
kept under proper control.<br />
In other words, the stimulus from these tax cuts will not<br />
push inflation up.<br />
It is worth recalling that these tax cuts have been made<br />
possible by control7ling Government spending. We have been<br />
prudent with taxpayers dollars, and are returning taxes to<br />
all Australians.<br />
While the Government in~ troduced its tax cuts arnd tax indexation<br />
in part as a stimulus the economy, we brought about these<br />
changes for another reason: we believed simply that Australians<br />
were paying too much tax. Until we acted, our tax system took<br />
away the incentive to work, the incentive to earn.<br />
Now, with inflation comi-ng down and with anti-inflationary<br />
pressures at-work in the economy, the Government's tax reforms<br />
are in place to provide a stimulus to the economy.<br />
They can create increased demand for porducts and services<br />
which will lead'. industry and business to create new jobs.<br />
The Australian economy is recovering. Government policies<br />
are working to create a climate of stability and certainty<br />
for private industry, which employs three out of every four<br />
Australians.<br />
As inflation continues to fall, as interest rates fall, and<br />
as the effects of almost $ 1 billion worth of the February tax<br />
cuts for this year alon3 take effect in the marketplace,<br />
unemployment will steadily fall.<br />
These are the powerful forces that will open up new job<br />
opportunities for Australia.<br />
Any attempt at the alternative the " quick fix" or return<br />
to the " one stroke of the pen" approach would be disastrous<br />
for Australia. The Government rejects that course. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
