<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8474</transcript-id>
    <title>MESSAGE TO PRESIDENT DE KLERK AND DR NELSON MANDELA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008474.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL 20. Mar. 92 17: 34 No. 032 P. 01/<br />
PRIME MINISTER ] 30/<br />
MESSAGES8 TO PRESIDENT DE KLERK AND DR NELSON MANDELA<br />
The following are text$ of messages sent today by the Prime<br />
Minister to President F W De Kierk and<br />
Dr Nelson Mandela following the recent South African<br />
referendum con political reform.<br />
Message to President De Kierc<br />
I would like to express to you personally my pleasure,<br />
and that of the people of Australia, at the outstanding<br />
result in the March 17 referendum. The overwhelming<br />
' yes' vote, as well as the unprecedented voter turnout,<br />
put beyond doubt the wish of white South Africans<br />
to see the reform process continued,<br />
The vote is, also a singular tribute to your own courage<br />
and perseverance and to that of the others on all sides<br />
of South African politics who have been involved in<br />
initiating and pursuing the historic reforms which are<br />
now underway in your country.<br />
Australians have been watching with great interest<br />
and not a little dismay given their winning form the<br />
exploits of your cricketers in the World Cup series.<br />
It has -been a welcome reminder for us all of the<br />
benefits of South Africa's return to full participation<br />
in the intercnational community.<br />
I am sure the referendum result will have greatly<br />
improved the prospects for progress at the next meeting<br />
of the Convention for a Democratic South Africa. I am<br />
confident that continued progress towards the adoption<br />
of a democratic non-racial constitution will permit<br />
further early moves towards the full restoration of<br />
commercial and economic relations between our two<br />
countries. </p>
<p>2<br />
Message to Dr Mandela<br />
I shared your relief and satisfaction at the result of<br />
the March 17 referendum. It is encouraging to know<br />
that the great majority of the white population in<br />
South Africa appreciates the urgent need for reform,<br />
and supports the historic process on which you,<br />
President de Kierk and other South African leaders are<br />
embarked. I am sure the referendum result will have greatly<br />
improved the prospects for progress at the next meeting<br />
of the Convention for a Democratic South Africa. I am<br />
confident that continued progress towards the adoption<br />
of a democratic non-racial constitution will permit<br />
further early moves towards the full restoration of<br />
commercial and economic relations between our two<br />
countries. I wish you' and your colleagues well as you enter what<br />
we all hope will be the final Stages in the dismantling<br />
of apartheid and the establishment of a truly<br />
democratic and non-racial South Africa.<br />
CANBERRA March 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
