<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8964</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING MP US CAPITOL GROUNDS WASHINGTON USA MONDAY 13 SEPTEMBER, 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/09/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008964.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 14. Sep. 93 9: 00 No. 002 P. 01/ 02<br />
K<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON. P.<br />
J. KXEATINGt M. P. U. S. CAPITOL GROUNDS, WASHINGTON, US. A.<br />
MONDAY 13 SEPTEMBERt 1993<br />
PM: There were a few questions on health but principally I think the, if you're after an<br />
impression of the last day or so, this is the right time to be in Washingtorr putting<br />
Australian views. With NAFTA about to be concluded in the Congress and with<br />
now the critical time with the Uruguay Round emerging with the end of the<br />
legislative fast track the Presdent has on Uruguay this is the time to be talking<br />
about trade structures. And the conversation I just had with Speaker Foley and<br />
senior representatives of the Congress was about international trading structures;<br />
what's best for America and the world and countries like Australia and the Pacific.<br />
So, I think coming here at the moment, talking about Uruguay, a successful<br />
conclusion of it and also the future of APEC and its design these are issues<br />
which are absolutely uppermost in the winds of American legislators and of<br />
course, the United States Adihinistrmtion.<br />
J: What points did you make about APEC?<br />
PM: Just that I think that it serves U. S. and Pacific interests generally. That is, either<br />
as an overlay to a successful Uruguay Round, that is something which can<br />
actually improve upon the outcome of Uruguay. Or in the event that the Uruguay<br />
Round fails and that the French seek to pull the rug on the Blair House<br />
Agreement, then in that case APEC defines a community with a high degree of<br />
integration. In fact APEC is more integrated in terms of intra-state trade than is<br />
the European Community or NAFTA. And it makes a lot of sense for the United<br />
States to be part of that, of that development even if it is in the configuration of<br />
NAFTA itself.<br />
J: Was the American response from Mr Kantor expressed in those terms to you?<br />
PM; They regard the legislative opportunity given to the fast track process to the<br />
President by the Congress as one which has to be taken up and therefore that the </p>
<p>I LL<br />
Round we Aceed to be mnovi toward a conclusion of the Round now so that the<br />
December 15 Idate is observed.<br />
But this arnbi~ ious notion of APEC as a community, was that somtething that was<br />
picked up by Mir Kantor?<br />
PM;. Yes, I hiks,<br />
high degree o<br />
repect upon<br />
to what rernit<br />
the vezydefir<br />
high degree a<br />
States as well<br />
J* ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I'd say that, h~<br />
within the ad~<br />
starting to tin<br />
fifty percent<br />
States and thu<br />
th= e times tI,<br />
there's a natu<br />
can see.<br />
J: How do they 3. As a defined body of naions who've got a common interest and a<br />
f integration-And how it develops, of course, will deped in some<br />
the Seattle ministerial meeting of APEC and the leadens' meeting as<br />
the leaders want to give APEC into the future. But there's no doubt<br />
ing of it, the drawing of a boundary around it, the recognition of the<br />
f integration is something which is obviously of use to the United<br />
as Australia.<br />
the Administration's mrind -there is a lot of enthusiasm for it<br />
ninistration. Less so in the Congress, but I think the Congress is<br />
lerstand the opportunity of APEC, the weight of the... the fact that<br />
of world GNP is in the APEC area and it is accessible to the United<br />
already United States exports to the Western Pacific are growing at<br />
e pace of imports to the United States from the Western Pacific. So,<br />
-al economic opportunity there which I think Congressional leaders<br />
see APEC and NAFTA fitting togeter, Prime Minister?<br />
Well, I wou4 l tink that they see APEC being an opportunity whether the United<br />
States appro ehes it in a singular way that is jointly or severally. Jointly with<br />
NAFTA or se rally with say Canada, the United States and Mexico. In either<br />
event, it mealis a higher level of trade, a higher velocity of trade, greater<br />
opportunity t6 be part of a larger block, a larger group of nations who are<br />
experiencing Irates of growth far higher than North America or Western Europe.<br />
What about LP, Prime Minister? How far did you push that and what was the<br />
reaction? r<br />
Well, I said: I them that we appreciated President Bush's commitment to<br />
Australians Jot to extend EEP into other markets And we would appreciate that<br />
assurance be ng kept. And that consideration being given to Australia in markets<br />
where EB? rmnerly hasn't been markets where Australia very defintely is.<br />
And the Trade Secretary said yes, he understood thai: and their decision to stay<br />
away from t1' e markets the market in Indonesia for instance was an example<br />
of the practi ~ al expression of that understanding.<br />
PM: J: PM: Ends. I 114. L.: Sep. 96 J; UU INU. ULJL r. UZ/ </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
