<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2984</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMONWEALTH HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/08/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002984.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 118 3 August 1973<br />
COMMONWEAITH HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING<br />
The following is the text of a statement issued in<br />
* Ottawa on 2 August ( Ottawa time) by the Prime Minister and<br />
Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr Whitlam, at the opening of the<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting:<br />
" The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
Mr Whitlamr, said in Ottawa this morning that he looked forward to<br />
wide-ranging and substantial discussions about present political<br />
trends in the world, economic issues including trade, monetary<br />
* and development questions and also on intra-Commonwealth relations,<br />
at the Commonwealth Meeting which starts in Ottawa today.<br />
Mr Whitlam reiterated that the Australian Government<br />
intended to adopt a more constructive and helpful approach towards<br />
the Commonwealth in the future.<br />
Although it was fashionable in some quarters to disparage<br />
the Commonwealth, Mr Whitlam said, he hoped the Ottawa meeting<br />
would give a new stimulus to constructive cooperation and<br />
consultation between the diverse members of the Commonwealth. * 12 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
More than half of these members were, he added, littoral<br />
states of the Indian and Pacific Oceans.<br />
Mr Whitlam said he saw in the Commonwealth a very valuable<br />
forum for cooperation, contacts and exchanges of views at all levels.<br />
He was, he added, looking forward to establishing personal<br />
contact with a number of Heads of Government, especially from<br />
African and Caribbean countries and to renewing personal contacts<br />
with others, including the host Prime Minister, Mr Trudeau.<br />
Senator Willesee's visit in June to a number of<br />
Commonwealth countries in Africa, the first such visit by an<br />
Australian Minister for many years, and his own visits to India,<br />
New Zealand, Britain and Mauritius earlier in the year, as well as<br />
his contacts with the Prime Minister of Fiji and his recent<br />
correspondence with the Prime Minister of Malaysia and Singapore,<br />
Tun Razak and Mr Lee Kuan Yew, had, Mr Whitlam said, been<br />
valuable in paving the way for effective Australian participation<br />
in the conference." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
