<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>824</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW COMMONWEALTH CASH AND CONVERSION LOAN BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES ON 9TH OCTOBER, 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000824_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NEW COMMIIONWEALTH CASH AND CONVERSION LOAN<br />
Broadcast by the Prime Minister, the Rt,<br />
Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
on 9th October, 1963.<br />
Good Evening Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I am speaking to you in my capacity as Chairman of<br />
the Australian Loan Council. I therefore speak on behalf of the<br />
Commonwealth Government and also on behalf of the six State<br />
Governments, all of whom, of course, have a direct interest in<br />
the success of the new Commonwealth œ-60M cash loan and the<br />
associated conversion loan which will open tomorrow.<br />
Subscriptions to the cash loan will form part of the<br />
1963-64 Loan Council borrowing programme of œ C27214. The largest<br />
single portion of the year's borrowing programme will be spenlt by<br />
the State housing authorities and building societies in providing<br />
new homes for our rapidly expanding pcpulation. Some œ C5014 will<br />
be spent in this way. An amount of the same order will be spent<br />
on schools universities, and the like requirements for education,<br />
The remainaer of the programme will be applied mainly to<br />
hospitals, railways, extensions of town and country electricity,<br />
gas and water supplies, irrigation schemes and sewerage and<br />
drainage works. So you will see that most people have, directly<br />
or indirectly, a stake in the success of the Loan Council programme,<br />
I have been asking you to subscribe to the Loan because<br />
you will thereby help to finance expansion of our economy, but<br />
perhaps I could also point out that the securities offered in the<br />
Loan represent a very sound investment for your savings. You can<br />
obtain yields ranging from per cent, on long-term<br />
securities to about œ E4.6.0 per cent, on medium-term securities<br />
and œ 3.16.6 per cent, on short-term securities. In addition, if<br />
you are a taxpayer9 you will have the advantage of a tax rebate<br />
of in the œ C which of course greatly improves the net yield<br />
from your securities, You may also happen to be one of nearly 100,000 holders<br />
of the œ 144-M 39" per cent. securities which mature next Tuesday.<br />
In that case, you inre invited to convert into the some securities<br />
as we are issuing in the cash loan. I hope you will do this<br />
because in an important sense, conversions are no different from<br />
loan subscriptions. If instead of converting, you redeem your<br />
securities the money paid to you will have to be found by your<br />
Commonwealth or State Governments from their own resources which<br />
are, of course, those of the people, including you.<br />
I would like also to mention the advantages offered<br />
by Special Bonds which are continuously on offer. We devised<br />
these a few years ago, They are specially designed for comparatively<br />
small investors. They give very good returns and they<br />
can be cashed in full at short notice from next April onwards,<br />
For these several reasons, I hope that we will have your support<br />
for the Loan, whether as a cash subscriber or as a converter<br />
of existing securities, This is, I repeat, very much a community<br />
enterprise and one in which your interests both as citizens and<br />
as individuals march together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
