<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5937</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING ADDRESS AT CHOGRM III, SUVA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005937.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY OCTOBER 14 1982<br />
OPENING ADDRESS AT CHOGRM III, SUVA<br />
I AM VERY PLEASED TO HAVE THE HONOUR TO RESPOND TO THE GRACIOUS<br />
WELCOME THAT HAS SEEN GIVEN US THIS MORNING. IT IS A TYPICALLY<br />
W) ARM FIJIAN PACIFIC WELCOE AN D ON. THAT CiARACTE. R ISES THE<br />
FRIENDS. HP AND THE WARMTH OF THE PACIFIC HOSPITALITY AND FRI -ENDSHPI<br />
BETWEEN PEOPLE WHO KNOW EACH OTHER.<br />
I WOULD LIKE TO SAY I AM ESPECIALLY GLAD TO SEE THE REPUBLIC OF<br />
MALDIVES, OUR NEWEST MEMBER, IN REPRESENTED HERE FOR THE FIRST<br />
TIME. THEIR REPRESENTATION STRENGHT'NS SMALL ISLAND REPRESENTATION<br />
WHICH IS A CHARACTERISTIC OF THIS AND EARLIER MEETINGS.<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH HEADS OF GOVERNMENT REGIONAL MEETING GIVES SMALL<br />
ISLAND STATES A MAJOR ROLE AND THAT IS ONE OF ITS SPECIAL CHARACTERISTICS<br />
PERHAPS UNLIKE ALMOST ANY OTHER INTERNATIONAL FORUM. IT IS AN<br />
OPPORTUNITY TO BE HEARD IN A WAY WHICH CAN SE SUBSTANTIAL AND I<br />
HOPE USEFUL AND PRACTICAL. AUSTRALIA BELIEVES IN THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
HEADS OF GOVERNMENT REGIONAL MEETINGS AND BELIEVES THAT THOSE MEETINGS<br />
ARE OF IMPORTANCE FOR OTHER REASONS. THERE IS A COMMON ASSOCIATION,<br />
THRE ARE COMMON BELIEFS ANONSGST ALL OF US WHICH GIVES US A<br />
COMMON PURPOSE AND PROVIDES A BASIS FOR FRANK AND PLAIN DIALOGUE<br />
ON PROBLEMS THAT WE OFTEN SHARE THAT ENABLES US TO SEARCH EACH OTHERS'<br />
MINDS IN REACHING FOR SOLUTIONS.<br />
THE COMMONWEALTH ITSELF HAS DEMONSTRATED THAT IT IS A FLEXIBLE<br />
ORGANISATION, ONE THAT DOES WORK BY CONSENSUS, THAT IS NOT IDEOLOGICAL.<br />
ONE OF ITS GREAT CHARACTERISTICS IS THAT REPRESENTATIVES<br />
WITH VERY DIFFERING POLITICAL IDEOLOGIES CAN SIT DOWN TOGETHER AND<br />
SEEK COMMON SOLUTIONS TO PRACTICAL PROBLEMS. IT IS DOUBTFUL IF THERE<br />
IS ANY OTHER WORLD FORUM WHICH ENABLES THAT TO TAKE PLACE IN THE<br />
SAME WAY. SO FAR AS THIS REGIONAL MEETING IS CONCERNED, ITS COMPARTIVE<br />
SMALLNESS AND THE COMMON ASIA-PACIFIC INTERESTS, PROVIDE US I<br />
BELIEVE, WITH AN ADDED ADVANTAGE.<br />
WE HAVE PRODUCED SOME PRACTICAL RESULTS. THE WORKING STUDY<br />
GROUPS IN TRADE, ENERGY AND IN INDUSTRY HAVE BEEN USEFUL DEMONSTRATIONS<br />
IN CO-OPERATION BETWEEN US. THIS THIRD COMMONWEALTH HEADS OF<br />
GOVERNMENT REGIONAL MEETING WILL PROVIDE A FURTHER OPPORTUNITY TO EXAMINE<br />
ISSUES OF SOME IMPORTANCE, THE LAW OF THE SEA CONVENTION,<br />
THE ATTITUDE TAKEN BY SOME MAJOR STATES, NOTABLY BY THE UNITED<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
STATES, OFFERS US AN OPPORTUNITY TO DISCUSS Ti-iE PRESENT IMPA~ SE<br />
IN THE NORTH-SOUTH DIALOGUE WHICH MUST REGAIN HOMENiUM. IT IS A<br />
MATTER OF GREAT REGRET THAT THE GLOBAL NEGOTIATIONS APPEAR TO BE<br />
STALLED DESPITE THE IMPETUS PROVIDED AT MELBOURNE LAST YEAR, AT<br />
CANCUN AND AT VERSAILLES. IT PROVIDED US WITH AN OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
STUDY THE REPORT ON OBSTACLES TO NORTH-SOUTH NEGOTIATIONS, TO<br />
SEE IF THERE IS ANY INDICATION THERE AS TO WHY IT IS SO DIFFICULT<br />
TO MAKE PROGRESS.<br />
THERE ARE OTHER COMMONWEALTH INITIATIVES THAT CAN BE TAKEN FURTHER<br />
IN THE NEXT TWO OR THREE DAYS. THE CAIRNCROSS REPORT ON THE<br />
IMPACT OF PROTECTION ON DEVELOPING COUNTRIES IS ONE OF GREAT<br />
SIGNIFICANCE TO A LARGE NUMBER OF OUR PRESENT MEMBERS, AND THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH FINANCE MINISTERS MEETING COMMUNIOUE WHICH INCLUDES THE<br />
PROPOSED STUDY AT INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC INSTITUTIONS, TO WHICH<br />
MR MULDOON HAS PAID A VERY SPECIAL INTEREST.<br />
THIS MEETING COMES AT A DIFFICULT TIME. THERE IS GLOBAL POLITICAL<br />
INSTABILITY OF A KIND THAT WE HAVE NOT SEEN FOR A VERY LONG WHILE.<br />
THE WORLD ECONOMY REAINS DEPRESSED AND DESPITE SOME WHO SEEH TO<br />
INDICATE HOPEFUL SIGNS IN THE UNITED STATES, THERE ARE PROSPECTS<br />
OF CONTINUING RECESSION, NOT NECESSARILY FOR MONTHS, BUT HMYBE FOR<br />
PERIODS MUCH LONGER THAN THAT. TRADE LIBERALISATION AGAINST THAT<br />
BACKGROUND BECOMES A MATER OF MAJOR CONCERN AND MAYBE THE ONLY WAY<br />
TO GENERATE GROWTH WITHIN THE DEVELOPED WORLD AND BETWEEN THE DEVELOPED<br />
AND THE DEVELOPING WORLD. THERE IS A NEED TO ACT TOGETHER<br />
TO FIGHT PROTECTIONISM.<br />
AUSTRALIA SOME TIME AGO ADVANCED CERTAIN INITIATIVES, A FREEZE<br />
ON PROTECTION, A FREEZE AND A REDUCTION ON EXPORT SUBSIDIES, AND<br />
ULTIMATELY MULTILATERAL CUTS IN PRESENT LEVELS OF PROTECTION.<br />
PROPOSALS SUCH AS THAT HAVE TO BE MULTILATERAL. THEY ARE NOT ONES<br />
EVEN THE LARGEST POWER COULD ACCOMMODATE ALONE. THE FORTHCOMING<br />
MINISTERIAL MEETING OF GATT WILL BE OF SIGNIFICANCE TO SEE IF ANY<br />
PROGRESS CAN BE MADE. THERE IS AN OPPORTUNITY HERE FOR US TO DISCUSS<br />
THESE MATTERS AND TO PROVIDE SOME FURTHER IMPETUS IN THE FIGHT<br />
AGAINST NOT JUST EXISTING LEVELS OF PROTECTION, BUT INCREASING<br />
LEVELS OF PROTECTION.<br />
WJE ARE LOOKING FORWARD TO THE DISCUSSIONS HERE TODAY. THERE ARE MANY<br />
MATTERS OF IMPORTANCE BEFORE US, BUT ABOVE ALL, IF THIS MEETING CAN<br />
DO SOMETHING TO HELP PROVIDE THE DETERMINATION, THE CONVICTION, AND<br />
THE WILL WHICH IS SO SORELY NEEDED NOT JUST AMONGST OUR PRESENT<br />
MEMBERS, BUT AMONGST THE WIDER WORLD, THEN THAT IN ITSELF WOULD -HAVE<br />
BEEN WORTHWHILE, BECAUSE SOMETIMES IT IS POSSIBLE TO SEE THE DIRECTIONS<br />
THAT OUGHT TO BE TAKEN, BUT AT THE SAME TIME, TO LACK THE COUlRAGE<br />
AND DETERMINATION TO TAKE THE INITIAL FIRST STEP. ONE OF THE<br />
MOST IMPORTANT THINGS THAT WE COULD ACHIEVE IS TO HELP PROVIDE THAT<br />
IMPETUS, HELP PROVIDE THAT SENSE OF DIRECTION AND HELP PROVIDE THE<br />
DETERMINATION WHICH WILL ENABLE PERHAPS OTHERS, WHO MAY BE LARGER<br />
AND MORE POWERFUL THAN ANY OF US HERE, TO TAKE STEPS AND DIRECTIONS<br />
THAT WOULD HELP THE WORLD GET OUT OF THE PRESENT RECESSION AND<br />
PRESENT DIFFICULTIES.<br />
YOUR EXCELLENCY, THE PRIME MINISTER RATU MARA, THANK YOU VERY MUCH<br />
INDEED FOR THE GENEROSITY OF YOUR WELCOME. THANK YOU VERY MUCH<br />
INDEED FOR THE HOSPITALITY THAT YOU HAVE ALREADY EXTENDED TO SU.<br />
IT WAS A TYPICALLY WARM AND GENEROUS WELCOME AND ONE WHICH I VALUE<br />
GREATELY AND I AM SURE WE ALL DO. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
