<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2797</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT ALBURY-WODONGA - THURSDAY 25 JANUARY 1973</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002797.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r" 3<br />
THE PiRIiME MIISTE'S P1S COIFERE~ iCE AT ALBURYS.<br />
T ODOITGA T-HIUSDAY, JAiJUAY 25, 1973<br />
PRIi IM. IiISTE2: Thanks ladies and gentlemen.<br />
Q. Your figure of 300,000; was this in agreement with the Premiers;<br />
would they have said that it may have been less?<br />
PRIiE MINISTER: I think there was the difference between 250,000 and<br />
300,000 which is minute in this context. The fact is that we all have<br />
confidence that a very large inland city can now be created through<br />
our co-operative efforts.<br />
Q. Could you put a price on this development?<br />
PRIME IIICTER IHo. I think one can take a general assessment that<br />
development of a new city like this will cost less per head than a<br />
development of Sydney or Melbourne to accommodate a similar number<br />
of people. It costs Governments C10,000 to nut a new resident in<br />
Cydney or Melbourne. It costs Governments ' 7,000 to put them in a<br />
nev polace like this.<br />
Prime Minister, in the Communique you say after the Governments<br />
have examined the report of preliminary study. Have you set a date<br />
for the start of that report and when you want its findings?<br />
PRIIM MINIISTE2: The study may easily be done within a couple of<br />
months we are informed.<br />
Prime Minister, do you or are you able to estimate the cost of<br />
the early studies of this particular project?<br />
P21IM1 MINIST2J-: It is quite a small amount really a couple of<br />
thousand dollars.<br />
Till it be done by Government departments or will you get<br />
outside opinions?<br />
SIR ROB3RT ASKIN: It is being done by H. U. JR. D. A. but with the<br />
co-operation of the Ctate Planning Authorities of Hev South Jales<br />
and Victoria.<br />
Q. Has the Commonwealth given any commitment that it will send<br />
public servants Commonwealth public servants to live in the<br />
Albury-Jodonga area?<br />
PRI12 MINIT ZT: ITo. ' very Federal Department has been asked to report<br />
on what number of public servants, in what sectors of the Federal public<br />
service can be efficiently established in Albury-Jodonga.<br />
Q. Is there any stage where that could possibly run to several<br />
thousand public servants coming to live here?<br />
PI MINTISTE: I think we can expect that there Aill be several<br />
thousand public servants living in the designated area. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
' Zir, has any cost been put on the acquiring of the land in the<br />
area?<br />
PPII1 MIHISTER: Io.<br />
Sir, how quickly would you like the feasibility study to be<br />
completed'-and the steps taken towards achieving this goal which<br />
you decided on today?<br />
PRIIi. M MIIST. R: Tell I think I have already said that it will probably<br />
be done . rithinr two months. You will notice that the Ministers concerned<br />
Ir. Uren, Mr. Fuller and ir. Murray-Dyrne can meet before there is any<br />
legislation. They can do that straight away and, furthermore, the three<br />
officials wiho will constitute the interim committee, they can meet<br />
straight away. It is not necessary to pass legislation through the<br />
three parliaments before the linisterial Council meets and operates<br />
and before the Interim Officials Committee meets and operates.<br />
0. Could you say, Sir, when you believe there will be 300,000 people<br />
living in this area. IHow many years?<br />
P-Ii. IIlTISTE: In my lifetime.<br />
In about 25 years?<br />
PRIi. E I: IIII: T2: You flatter me.<br />
Q. Were there any discussions on other development regions in either<br />
evw South . Tales or Victoria, like Eathurst or Orange?<br />
P2IIM MIIIST2 In passing, yes. Sir Robert Askin and I are issuing<br />
a statement about a feasibility study on the Bathurst and Orange region<br />
in which the Commonwealth and lHew South Wales are sharing the cost.<br />
2. Did Victoria go for any other development regions?<br />
PRII' 1Ei lISI S: Ho, There was no specific commitment to any other<br />
development regions. The great significance of this region in whose<br />
heart we are meeting today is that it seemed a clear centre where there<br />
was every prospect for success. Therefore, we could get the boosting<br />
of morale to show that Governments, in fact, can create a great new<br />
inland city at this time. It was also an area where you had two State<br />
governments able to co-operate and the Commonwealth for various<br />
historical and geographic reasons can also mak e a very significant<br />
contribution, so this was an excellent place to start it. If this is<br />
a success, as we all believe it will be, then there are good hopes of<br />
success for other regions including inland Australia.<br />
Your commitment to Orange-Dathurst, is this only in the<br />
feasibility studies or is it in the development.<br />
PrIIz MINISTER~: iTo, in feasibility studies. Te are anxious to know<br />
the facts, and if the facts show that it is a good prospect then ' we<br />
will be in it as a Commonwealth. </p>
<p>I<br />
Did Doew South Tales .:; ive you any feasibijlty jfactu's toC: ay onl<br />
Bathust-Orange?<br />
PRM2 ITOiI. S~<br />
W Uill you be stop-. i---g t6he building of Commonwealth build: ings in<br />
Sydney and Idclbourne before you ret ' he results of this feasibility<br />
study? IIE M'IISTE112: ' Jell ire have already announiced that tLhe Strin, 2St-reet<br />
project in 1.1lbourrne is being e-eaie and, as you knmow, the Public<br />
J! orks Committee of tlhe Fee-oral Parliament rejected a proposal fLor a<br />
7. Toolloornooloo projoct for Commonwealth public servants. This is<br />
really another aspect but wi-here Common,, wealth buildings are to be siteed<br />
is one o2 the terms of reference olfa Federal Cabinet committee at<br />
this-moment. And we will, of course, bear in mind not only regional<br />
centres such as Albjry_. Todongav but-also now cities new regional<br />
centres in the existing,, metropolitan areas of Sydney and 1Kelbourne.<br />
Ji nd Canberra?<br />
P~~ ILZ. HIIT't Jl1 tt has al1 ready been done in Canberra.<br />
U~ ill it ston, growth in Canberra?<br />
P2i1J2i2 ITO . Canberra wrould now rgrow i. 2 theo Commonwealth never<br />
undlertookr a further commitmont, 1 but there w-illl be furth-_-er commitments<br />
which' the Commowealth clearly wrill unidertak-: e in Ca-nberra. Ca nberra<br />
is nlow well ane. sureoly launched. It could carry on undler its ol-m<br />
steami if tha was necessary.<br />
C. Prime I1iinister* a personal cuestion. You have been virtually living<br />
with lry-WodonEga, in that even you have called Thitlamabad, for five<br />
' rears I think. How 0. o you feel now after this what you call historic<br />
takstoay* sthis 1how you really alway3.1s imiagined it. Have you got<br />
what you rea~ lly wrant-ed ?<br />
P2I112 I'I SST1E ' U1y word. This has been a very C-reat experience for all<br />
of us. Sure I have mentioned this complex -for quite some years and so<br />
ha-s Eir. Uren the two " tate governments haeas'a-ti nmn<br />
and there have been reprorts in wrhich-it hias been essly cited. How<br />
w ~ t haS e is tha we have all got together and wre hiave found<br />
h~ ow nvich easier it is to do it jointly. ! How 1 don'tat to eject the<br />
narme Aitlanabad but t is was tae one qiuestion in which wre didn't<br />
come to an agreement. I had sugrgested Isulinville and the-in it was<br />
sugge-sted 1Hamerton. Both t-he eponymous heros declined -the honour.<br />
Someone suggested Uronopolis or some less seemly variation still,<br />
but if you insist I will accept WJhitlama'oad.<br />
Q. ir ;' obort, you expressed what might'-be teormed as some reservations<br />
this morning in your opening; speech. kre you satisfLied w-ith the decisions<br />
that ha-ve been made today? </p>
<p>SIR OB2TX ASKIU: I don't remember expressing reservations. I<br />
ref'rred to the need for a careful examination of some of-the<br />
pro itions that were expected to be put up. As to whether I'm<br />
saised or not, I said before the conference that I felt it was an<br />
experient in co-operation between the three parties, and I said at the<br />
conclusion--of the conference in paying tribute to the Prime KMinister in<br />
convening" the -conference and the way he conducted it that I felt the<br />
experimcnt ' nd co-operation had boon eminently successful. I don't<br />
think we could have covered anymore , round and arrived at so many<br />
decisions of principle and auite a few on major detail in such a<br />
comparatively short time having in mind the enormity of the project<br />
. aVt e hnve set about launcinL todayi<br />
Pi2Ii iIiIZT: Sir Robert mentioned that he had made some gracious<br />
remarks about mo, and I appreciate what he said and I'm glad to<br />
acknowledge it here publicly, but I think that perhaps we should say<br />
that we all, at the end of the conference, paid tri'oute to the advisers<br />
that the three Governments have had here and those that they have had<br />
in their capitals, because it would have been impossible to have<br />
covered so many matters and to have decided so many matters but for the<br />
very fine public servants and advisers that the three Governments have<br />
available to them. The 70 per cent of the Australian people who live<br />
in areas over whichi the three Governments here represented preside are<br />
well served by their public servants.<br />
ill the Federal Government accept 7. th1eow outh ' Jales invitation<br />
to consider reducing steel prices in some form?<br />
PRI% IiIIHIST2I2: As you know, the Federal Government hasn't made any<br />
representations to 1r. Justico Mloore in his inquiry. Sir Robert Askin<br />
mentioned this matter to look at. It is certainly a relevant matter.<br />
Zome of you in the Federal Press Gallery may remember that I did raise<br />
this question in about August 1971 the fact that steel prices were<br />
fixed at capital city rates and any provincial centres including say,<br />
so large a one as Townsville iwhich is right on the coast, had to pa.-<br />
so much more, although the delivery cost from s. y Port Ke'nbla or<br />
Howcastle to Townsville is no treater than it is to some other places<br />
where the stooeel costs less. And the a. nswer I got from thie I'inistor for<br />
Trade and Indeustry at that time was that it was a matter for the<br />
commeorcial determination of the company concerned. I don't accept that<br />
proposition myself but it is too soon for me to say anything about it.<br />
Clearly one of the things we have to look at is the ava ilability of<br />
basic products in new centres, and governments can do a certain amount<br />
3ut it is certainly incumbent on large corporations to play their part<br />
as eoll. It is not fair that people should have to spend so miiuch<br />
more for the particular commodity you mention or for other basic<br />
comfmodities outside the State caitals.<br />
S Sir Robert Askin has indeed indicated that Bathurst and Orange<br />
would like to see some accelerated development. A question to Kr.<br />
: armor of r. Byrne:<br />
Jihat areas would they like to see noxt developed in Victoria? </p>
<p>" Tell we have already esignatbed, five areas for ccelerat'ed<br />
( level omc-Int--wzhich ' Jodonga wa-s one and, thei reason for designating<br />
' Jodngnae aso ti , vea s because of i's potential " or growth<br />
jointly with k~ bury ofLOthe" sort wkiich we haL-ve now determined on' today.<br />
0o the, remaininng four, therefore, whiich are Dallarat, Denciigo, the<br />
Lat robe Valley and Portlandl are tUhe -rea-s we have already deosignated<br />
lor accelerat-.-ed developmcn-t adin some respects they are already<br />
achieving it.<br />
1.. UPZ21r: I have hadO-discussionls with -Ir. Ilurray-Dyrne and there is<br />
another one undeiray so -s to balance tlie budget betwreen Victoria and<br />
Ilew South ' Tales. I don't watto ncxme it because there mieht be<br />
speculation in t'-he area.<br />
I0 Leaving-the Loan Council -, nd th2-e PA" remiers Conference aside, w-. ould<br />
you deoscribe today's r.' eeting-as a successful exorcise in federalism?<br />
P; I' 42: y word, I would.<br />
A~ w~ ir: I s up-ort that too.<br />
P1II1IiI1ISTE2: . Gentlemen, both thec Premiers have planes w-aitincg for<br />
them of course, my plane doesn't arrive bac'h-untU'il tomorrow morning<br />
so are thecre any more questions?<br />
have one further question about the Orallge-Bathurst area. ! Hanly<br />
people still feel that you did come here today hoping to got something<br />
for your project in rno-thstand thaat perhaps you may tend to<br />
take theo attitude tihat you wren't prepared to fully support Albury-<br />
' J-odonGa iunless you got more sunport for Or. ange-BL-thurst?<br />
Sj12 R0. BD'. Zc A k3XI: That wrouldl be one hundred per cent wrong, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
