<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5372</transcript-id>
    <title>QUEENSLAND DROUGHT ASSISTANCE TO PRIMARY PRODUCERS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005372.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 5 JUNE, 193<br />
QUEENSLAND DROUGHT ASSISTANCE TO PRIMARY PRODUCERS<br />
The Prime Minister today announced that, following consideration<br />
of an approach from the Premier, the Commonwealth Government<br />
has agreed to provide further drought assistance to Queensland.<br />
The Prime Minister was speaking in Surfers Paradise at the<br />
Annual Convention of the United Graziers' Association of<br />
Queensland. The announcement incorporates extensions to the<br />
Natural Disaster Financial Assistance Arrangements. The following<br />
will apply from today:-<br />
The maximum concession applicable to road transport<br />
concessions will be increased from 40 cents to 50 cents<br />
per kilometre for a loaded cattle truck, and from 4 cents<br />
to 5 cents per tonne per kilometre for fodder and water.<br />
The freight concession on water cartage will be extended<br />
to the carriage of water on properties to points beyond<br />
the farm gate. This concession, however, will not apply<br />
to transport of water between points within farms.<br />
per cent concession will apply to the cost of transporting<br />
essential machinery and equipment to affected properties<br />
or to and from where fodder is available. This concession<br />
will apply only to equipment which is an essential part<br />
of drought mitigation practices.<br />
In addition and because of the severity of this drought,<br />
the rate of concession payable on all rail and road transport<br />
movements of fodder, water and stock will be increased<br />
from 50 per cent to 75 per cent. This additional concession<br />
will apply for the duration of this drought only.<br />
Following on the Government's recently announced extension<br />
of the Natural Disaster Assistance arrangements to apply to<br />
primary producers in New South !' ales, these further measures<br />
will be of great value to the drought-affected ori. ary producers<br />
of Queensland.<br />
The State, of course, will be responsible for the administrative<br />
arrangements associated with distributing these further assistance<br />
measures. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
