<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8365</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER PARLIAMENTARY LUNCH IN HONOUR OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CYPRUS, HIS EXCELLENCY MR GEORGE VASSILIOU CANBERRA - 12 DECEMBER 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/12/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008365.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGATNSqT DELIVRay EMRARrOED UNTIL DFl. Tpg<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARLIAMENTARY LUNCH IN HONOUR OF THE<br />
PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CYPRUS,<br />
HIS EXCELLENCY MR GEORGE VASSILIOJ<br />
CAN4BERRA 12 DECEMBER 1991<br />
President Vassiliou<br />
Mrs Vassiliou<br />
Distinguished Guests<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Mr President<br />
I am very pleased you have been able to accept my invitatio<br />
to visit Australia. It is an honour and a pleasure to have<br />
you here.<br />
We last met at the Commonwealth Heads of Governent Meeting<br />
in Harare in October. The Harare CHOGM showed : he<br />
Commonwealth to be an organisation of continuing relevance<br />
and vitality, committed to the protection and promotion of<br />
just and honest government, fundamental human rights and<br />
democratic values. The commitment of your Government to th<br />
Commonwealth and its values has been reflected iLn your<br />
agreement to host the next CHOGM in 1993.<br />
Mr President, during our discussions this morning, we spoke<br />
at length about the still outstanding problem of the<br />
partition of Cyprus. I was most interested to hear your<br />
analysis of the present situation, and I was impressed by<br />
your determination to find a solution.<br />
As you know, Australia has always condemned the Turkish<br />
occupation of Cyprus. We uphold the sovereignty and<br />
territorial integrity of the Republic of Cyprus. And we<br />
have supported UN Security Council Resolutions 541, 550, 64<br />
and 716. We have consistently expressed oppositrion to the<br />
unilateral declaration of the Turkish republic of Northern<br />
Cyprus in 1983.<br />
3 8 JM'T<br />
1J </p>
<p>/ o 2.<br />
We have been extensively involved in efforts to restore<br />
peace in Cyprus through our participation in the United<br />
Nations peacekeeping force. At present, we have 20 men and<br />
women of the Australian Federal Police on duty there.<br />
Those men and women, and their colleagues from many other<br />
countries, provide an invaluable service. I have nothing<br />
but praise and respect for them, and I am proud of the<br />
contribution Australia has been able to make to that effort.<br />
The search for a just, peaceful and permanent solution to<br />
the problems of Cyprus is a major challenge to the<br />
international community. The ability of the international<br />
community to meet that challenge has been greatly<br />
strengthened over recent years by the emergence of the<br />
United Nations as a truly effective instrument of<br />
international action.<br />
We have fully supported the efforts of the current<br />
Secretary-General to resolve the Cyprus problem, and we urge<br />
his distinguished successor to continue and expand those<br />
efforts. We also urge the United States and the European<br />
Community to maintain the momentum for a UN-sponsored<br />
settlement. Last year I had the opportunity to discuss the issue with<br />
President Ozal. I pressed him then on the need for Turkey<br />
to take decisive steps if the issue is to be resolved. I<br />
believe he understands that it is in the interests of<br />
Turkey, and of the whole region, that the future of Cyprus<br />
should be resolved quickly, and in a just and durable<br />
manner. I urge Turkey's new Prime Minister, Oemirel, to<br />
commit himself to the search for such a resolution.<br />
We are disappointed that prospects are now fading for a<br />
high-level meeting between the parties before the end of the<br />
year, but we hope the momentum can be regained early in the<br />
new year.<br />
I believe the momentous changes that have swept the world in<br />
the past two years give cause for greater hope for a<br />
settlement for Cyprus.<br />
The old restraints of the Cold War have been broken. Old<br />
modes of thinking are no longer relevant. And there is a<br />
new spirit of international cooperation based on the<br />
realisation of common goals and interests.<br />
There are no easy answers. Imagination, flexibility and<br />
political determinatiLon are essential.<br />
All parties must participate constructively and openly in<br />
inter-communal negotiations. It is time to look forward to<br />
possibilities and op. portunities, rather than back to hatred<br />
and bitterness. </p>
<p>I believe it is becoming increasingly clear, in the post-<br />
Cold War world, that people's well-being can only be assured<br />
through the principles I outlined earlier, those identi'f ied<br />
and espoused by Commonwealth Heads of Government at the<br />
Harare meeting democracy, human rights, the rule of law,<br />
and just and honest government.<br />
Mr President,<br />
Australia is in a fortunate position. we are geographically<br />
remote from much of the world's turmoil, and suffer no<br />
immediate threats. We are rich in resources. we enjoy a<br />
democratic system of government. And, importantly, we have<br />
many Australians of diverse ethnic backgrounds who are<br />
willing to contribute to Australia's well-being.<br />
Australia is proud that, in particular since World War II,<br />
we have attracted to our shores millions of new settlers<br />
from more than 130 nations around the world. One of cur<br />
great assets is the vigour and vitality of our multicultural<br />
society.<br />
Cypriot migration and establishment in Australia has a long<br />
and proud history going back to the gold-rush era of the<br />
1850s. The period of upheaval in 1974 saw a substantial<br />
rise in immigration from Cyprus, with the result that around<br />
50,000 Cypriots now call Australia home.<br />
Cypriots participate in and contribute to all walks of' life<br />
education, sport, business and government. One well-known<br />
member of the Cypriot community who is also a member of<br />
this Parliament is Dr Andrew Theophanous, who I know is<br />
already known to you.<br />
These sons and daughters of Cyprus, now Australians, are<br />
very welcome among us. Like you, Mr President, they<br />
personify a rich and ancient culture, and a vibrant<br />
commitment to achievement. We have been enriched by their<br />
contribution to our multicultural society. And we respect<br />
the way in which they have contributed to our society and'<br />
economy through the traditions and achievements of their<br />
culture. Australia's multicultural society works because all<br />
Australians are able to express and share their individual<br />
cultural heritage, to practise their religion, to speak<br />
their language. It works because all Australians are<br />
treated equally. It works because there is an overriding<br />
commitment to Australia, to its institutions, its interests<br />
and its future.<br />
I believe the Australian achievement of a multicultural<br />
society has something to teach the world. Culture, history,<br />
language and race should not divide, or become the focus of<br />
hate diversity should enrich and invigorate society. </p>
<p>4.<br />
Mr President,<br />
Australia and Cyprus have! a close and friendly relationship,<br />
based on our historical Links, our Commonwealth membership,<br />
the ties of blood and cu: lture through the many Australians<br />
of Cypriot origin and our mutual interest in seeking a just<br />
and peaceful resolution to the partition of Cyprus.<br />
Your visit provides the opportunity to build on these solid<br />
foundations.<br />
Again, we are honoured by your presence here, and wish you a<br />
fruitful and enjoyable visit.<br />
" rV-9TTIIT-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
