<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1385</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: FUTURE OF SNOWY MOUNTAINS AUTHORITY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT.</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001385.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
UNTIL 5 PM. SUNDAY. 28TH AUGUST. 1966<br />
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 84/ 1966<br />
FUTURE OF ST0' VY MOUITAINS AUTHORITY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
The Commonwealth Jovernment has been giving a<br />
good deal of attention to the question of the future of the<br />
Snowy Mountains Authority. The major work in the Snowy Mountains<br />
area will be completed on present estimates by about 1972, and<br />
the Government hopes it will be found possible for a continuing<br />
use to be made of some of the specialised skills which the<br />
Authority can provide. Examination has been conducted by means of studies<br />
at the official level and inter-De artmental discussion. These<br />
have, of course, included consultaion with Sir William Hudson,<br />
Commissioner of the Snowy Mountains Authority and his senior<br />
colleagues. There has been consideration by Cabinet itself. WVhat<br />
clearly emerges is that it is mainly in the area of State works<br />
that the future collective use of the skills which the Authority<br />
has built up is likely to be found. The works programmes of the<br />
Commonwealth and notably the water resources programmes in the<br />
areas under its control offer limited scope compared with those<br />
of the States. Before a final decision can be made about the future<br />
of the Authority, it is necessary that the Commonwealth Government<br />
should be in possession of the views of State Governments as to<br />
whether thev would see a requirement within their works programmes<br />
and the funds likely to be available to them, to engage the skills<br />
of the Snowy team to the extent necessary to sustain a workable<br />
organisation. The Commonwealth's purpose would be to ascertain<br />
in general whether they would re-ard the continuation of the<br />
Auttorit as likely to serve Sta te and Commonwealth purposes in<br />
a valuab e way. Most of the State Governments have, of course,<br />
design and constructing authorities of their own, but some or<br />
indeed all, of them may feel that they could be considerably<br />
assisted by the services of the Authority. There have already been<br />
instances of this. Australia is the world's driest Continent7 and all<br />
Uovernments, State and Commonwealth, recognise that continuin&amp;<br />
progress in water conservation is essential to further expansion<br />
of production and to national development. Our recent drought<br />
experience has brought home to us all how gravely affected<br />
Australia continues to be by the lack of regular supplies of water<br />
in adequate quantities. There is much that Australia can do by<br />
its ovm efforts to meet its growing needs for power and water.<br />
The skills, experience and expertise of the Snowy Mountains<br />
Authority should if the States decide to avail themselves of<br />
them be capable of making a valuable contribution for these<br />
purposes. We propose, therefore, to consult promptly with the<br />
State Governments on the specific question of the Authority's<br />
future. Before we can finally decide on the size, role and<br />
structure of a continuing organisation, we must have been able to<br />
assess the extent to which tie States would avail themselves of<br />
the services of such an organisation.<br />
CANBERRA, 28th August, 1966.<br />
EI,, IBA~ RuOED </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
