<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17246</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Increased civilian effort in Afghanistan 24 April 2010  </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/04/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government will increase the Australian civilian effort in Afghanistan, focused on Oruzgan province.</p>
<p>Working alongside the Australian Defence Force, in an integrated civilian-military effort, Australia will increase its diplomatic, development assistance and police contribution to around 50 personnel.</p>
<p>This represents around a 50 percent increase of Australia's current contribution.</p>
<p>The additional diplomatic and development assistance staff will be based in Kabul, Kandahar and Tarin Kowt.</p>
<p>They will expand our delivery of practical development assistance projects that improve the capacity of national and local officials, and improve governance and service delivery at the local level.</p>
<p>The additional police personnel will be based in Tarin Kowt.</p>
<p>They will strengthen the work to mentor and train the Afghan National Police to allow a progressive transition to Afghan policing responsibility in the province.</p>
<p>Australia is committed to ensuring Afghanistan never again becomes a haven for the export of terrorism.</p>
<p>We are committed to supporting the United States in achieving this, and we are working closely with the Government of Afghanistan and our international partners.</p>
<p>The new strategy of the International Security Assistance Force in Afghanistan is focused on twin objectives of improving security and governance.</p>
<p>This increased civilian effort is a prudent and considered additional contribution to support those objectives.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
