<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2181</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTE OF MANAGEMENT - NSW DIVISION ANNUAL DINNER - SYDNEY NSW - PRESENTATION OF JOHN STOREY AWARD TO MR WW PETTINGELL - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, 5 FEBRUARY 1970</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/02/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002181.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTE OF MANAGEMENT<br />
N. S. W. DIVISION ANNUAL DINNER<br />
Sydney, N. S. W. t<br />
Presentation of John Storey award to Mr. W. W. Pettingell<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
FEBRUARY 1970<br />
Mr. President, Mr. Pettingell, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
One of the great pleasures for me tonight, and I am<br />
sure one of the great pleasures for you, is that before I came<br />
it was stipulated that I had not come in order to make a speech<br />
or to leave a message with you, but merely to appear on an<br />
occasion which seems to me to be one which deserves the<br />
greatest support which the government of this country can give.<br />
I come for two reasons. One is because this is a<br />
gathering of the Australian Institute of Management, and as the<br />
politician of caricature says " In this gathering I say without fear<br />
of contradiction that the Australian Institute of Management is an<br />
extraordinarily fine body of men. And if there may be some<br />
amongst us who cavil a little at men being selected, then to those<br />
I say that I fall back on the legal precept that the greater includes<br />
the less. And I mean this because what is required in this or<br />
other developing countries for we still are a developing country<br />
is capital, wherever we can get it, to the greatest degree that we<br />
can, subject to some small reservations as to the conditions on<br />
which it comes; and labour, which on the figures recently released,<br />
is getting more and more in demand and less and less available.<br />
But there is something over and above that, for what use<br />
is capital, what use is labour if it is not managed in such a way that<br />
from it the greatest possible benefit is received for the country? You<br />
can have a factory in which you have adequate machinery, in which you<br />
have a workforce of competent people, but what can you get from it if<br />
management is not capable of utilising what is provided?<br />
It is true, I think, as our trade union leaders would say<br />
and indeed I would say, that what is produced in a country is basically<br />
produced from the skills and the devotion and the work of the man on the<br />
factory floor, the man who runs the lathe, the foreman, and the people<br />
in the work force. It also remains true that in any given factory you<br />
could have exactly the same skills on the factory floor, exactly the </p>
<p>2.<br />
same number of people, but you could have a production which was<br />
small if the management was bad, or a production which was great<br />
if the management was good. And this is the great contribution<br />
that can be made to the growth of this country and to the well being<br />
of all who are in it. And because the Institute of Management does<br />
this, it is one of the pleasures to me of coming tonight.<br />
There is another, Sir, arising out of something<br />
which you said in the course of your speech. I thinkc, if I may<br />
paraphrase, you said that in the world today everybody knows what<br />
everybody else has and wants it. If I may speak personally for a<br />
moment, I am not unfamiliar with that approach! But this is not<br />
necessarily a bad thing, provided those who want it are prepared<br />
to earn it, are prepared to see how it has been achieved and to put<br />
In the effort and the brain power and the devotion which is required<br />
to get it. In this case what you have said is good, but of course if<br />
somebody, some other country sees what has been attained here and<br />
wants it, and doesn't want to put in that kind of effort, but merely<br />
expropriate it or take it away, then this does no good at all.<br />
And because this Institute of Management seeks to<br />
disseminate amongst the people of this country the techniques by<br />
which these things can be attained, that is another reason why I<br />
think it is of such significance to this country of Australia.<br />
But the second reason why I am so glad to be here is<br />
that it is a gathering to honour Mr. Pettingell, whom I see not for<br />
the first time today. You will have heard, if you didn't know<br />
before, he is indeed a man for all seasons. Indeed, hearing of<br />
how he sailed a partly finished boat to Hobart, one can only tremble<br />
for Ted Heath if that boat had been finished before he started.<br />
But seriously, Sir, no words of mine can add to the<br />
record which was read to the assembled gathering as to what you<br />
have done and what you are continuing to do. A man who has<br />
always sought the most direct route to whatever it is he sought to<br />
attain, and who I am glad to say is still doing it. He has been one<br />
of the pioneers of business management in this country, one of the<br />
people who has recognised that it is necessary if you have a factory<br />
force, if you have people working for you, to mobiise their talents,<br />
to utilise their skill to the greatest possible extent, and to realise<br />
the full potential of those for whom he is responsible in his sphere,<br />
to the benefit of his company, to the benefit of the people so utilised<br />
and to the benefit of the Australian nation.<br />
I am glad to say that there is a growing realisation of the<br />
importance of management and of the importance of research. You<br />
will know that there are experts coming to Australia on February 24-</p>
<p>3.<br />
( some of you will have dealt with them before) to advise on the<br />
setting up of a School of Business Management in this country, a<br />
post-graduate school, a real attempt to bring the techniques to the<br />
younger people who more and more will be taking over management<br />
in the expanding economy of our nation.<br />
And it affords me pleasure, not only that this is<br />
happening but that I will be able to get a bit of my own back by<br />
going to industry and saying, " Now you can provide the money<br />
that is required for the setting up of this school for the benefit<br />
of everybody. I still remember somebody promising me $ 10 million<br />
if we did it and I intend to collect that IOU. Of course that will<br />
only cover a part of the cost:<br />
But because of what you have done, Mr. Pettingell,<br />
a nd what those others in this room have done and are doing,<br />
because of the overriding significance of management for the<br />
full realisation of what we can do, because you are here tonight<br />
being honoured and because of those who are here to honour you,<br />
I have had the greatest delight in being able to be in some small<br />
way associated with this function.<br />
May I finish on this note? A short time ago, I went to<br />
Adelaide to deliver an address called " The William Queale<br />
Memorial Lecture" on management and training for management,<br />
and used these words, or something like these words: We have seen<br />
just recently the most extraordinary occurrence in man's history.<br />
We have seen people walking on the moon. The planning for this was<br />
started a decade or more ago. The people who took part in that<br />
journey deserve all the tribute we can pay them. But they could not<br />
have got there, they could not have walked on the moon, they could<br />
not have come back, had it not been for management techniques,<br />
for management planning, for the overseeing of every detail which<br />
led to that great and successful adventure. If that is so in a<br />
dramatic way, then if the same devotion and the same techniques,<br />
are applied to providing in this country the greater opportunities<br />
that are possible, this may be even greater than the success of the<br />
management techniques which led to the journey to the moon. This<br />
is very largely in your habds and in the hands of people like<br />
Mr. Pettingell, and it is for this reason I have been honoured to be<br />
with you tonight. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
