<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6166</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/08/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006166.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
J~ UT11ALiA a<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA August 2, 1983<br />
The Tasmanian Premier, Mr. Gray, must stop dissembling and<br />
playing politics over the Federal Government's decision to<br />
stop funding for the further construction of the Crotty Road.<br />
Mr. Gray is quoted on Monday as claiming that " the first inkling"<br />
o ptrhoajt echte hcaadm e ofo nltyh e onC oJmumloyn we28a. lth's intention to pull out of the<br />
He was quoted as saying that the decision to cut funding had<br />
been taken without consultation.<br />
The facts are these:<br />
1. The future of Crotty Road was raised by me in a letter<br />
to Mr. Gray on July 1 in which I suggested that<br />
construction work be continued " for the very<br />
immediate future" pending detailed consideration by<br />
the two governments.<br />
2. Mr. Gray wrote to me on July 21. The relevant extract<br />
is as follows:<br />
" I accept your assurance that for the very<br />
immediate future work continue on the Crotty Road.<br />
Work is in fact continuing on that road and the<br />
future direction of the road is of vital concern<br />
0 to my Government. I have already cautioned against<br />
the road being extended to Kelly Basin because of<br />
the dramatic consequential effects such an<br />
extension of the road would have on the economy and<br />
life of Strahan. I advise that State Cabinet<br />
considered this very matter on Monday, 11 July, and<br />
resolved to oppose any extension of the Crotty Road<br />
to Kelly Basin.<br />
" You should be made aware of the fact that if the<br />
King River Power Scheme is built, the part of the<br />
Crotty Road, which has virtually been completed<br />
will be flooded. The area of the road presently<br />
being constructed will not be flooded." / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
3. As well as talks on the future of Crotty Road between<br />
officials, the project was raised at the meeting with<br />
me, requested by Mr. Gray, on July 25. At that<br />
meeting there was a clear indication that the State<br />
had no need of its own for the road to proceed,<br />
regarded it as inappropriate for it in fact to proceed<br />
and left it as a matter for Commonwealth decision.<br />
Given the State Government attitude outlined on July 21, and<br />
reaffirmed at the July 25 meeting the Commonwealth believed<br />
that until the management plan for the wilderness areas was<br />
agreed to by both governments, there aas little point in<br />
continuing to spend money on a road that was going nowhere and<br />
which could eventually be flooded.<br />
I note that Mr. Gray has undertaken to bring forward the<br />
construction dates of the King River and Henty Anthony hydro<br />
schemes. The ' 7eoeral Government was already considering the<br />
0 funding of these schemes as part of its overall compensation<br />
package for Tasmania.<br />
Following the July 25 meeting, I wrote to Mr. Gray recalling<br />
that I had placed considerable emphasis for officials of the<br />
two governments to make early progress with studies of future<br />
power requirements.<br />
" We see this question as central to the nature of future<br />
arrangements between our governments and Senator Walsh has<br />
already put in hand an examination of broad policy options for<br />
the Commonwealth. I understand that your government expects<br />
shortly to consider a paper dealing with future needs that is<br />
being prepared by the HEC, and I would expect that work on the<br />
proposed joint studies could proceed in earnest once that<br />
action has been taken", my letter said.<br />
Mr. Gray has yet to formally advise that he is prepared to<br />
permit such a study.<br />
Mr. Gray should know that I am becoming weary of his provocative,<br />
ill-founded and deliberate deception for his own miserable<br />
political purposes.<br />
For its part the. Federal Government does not intend to be<br />
distracted from the fundamental task of formulating a<br />
compensation package which will provide the maximum benefit<br />
for all Tasmanians. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
