<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10270</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD, MP BROADCAST TELEPHONE LINK-UP WITH SENATOR RICHARD ALSTON NORTHGATE TELECOMMUNICATIONS LAUNCH - BALLARAT</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/03/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010270.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
' I -7<br />
13 March 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD, MP<br />
BROADCAST TELEPHONE LINK-UP<br />
WITH SENATOR RICHARD ALSTON<br />
NORTHGATE TELECOMMUNICATIONS LAUNCH BALLARAT<br />
E O E<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
How are you Richard?<br />
ALSTON: Well thank you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Where are you calling from?<br />
ALSTON: I'm calling from Ballarat. I've got a cast of thousands here it's almost like the<br />
Ballarat Football Grounds. They're all very excited at the prospect of talking to you<br />
because I'm calling from McArthur Street Primary School courtesy of Northgate<br />
Communications who are offering some very exciting telephone arrangements<br />
including free local phone calls, which is an Australia wide first, and very significant<br />
discounts on a range of other products and I'm sure you'll understand the significance<br />
of that for business competitiveness and to ensure that people outside the capital cities<br />
get a fair deal.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
This is the first, as I understand it, example of why some of the competitive rates now<br />
available in the major metropolitan areas are being made available in regional areas and<br />
from what you've just said it's even better in relation to the free local call. I don't<br />
know of that anywhere else in Australia. </p>
<p>ALSTON: No, it's going to be very hard to get on the line down here in Ballarat here I think.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
If you've got a teenage family you'll never get on the line.<br />
ALSTON: I never get them off that's the problem.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That is a very good example of what competition does because, let's face it, a few<br />
years ago you wouldn't have even dreamt of this occurring and it's just the advent of<br />
competition that has made it possible. They other great advantage of this is that it will<br />
give small business in regional areas a major boost because as you keep telling me<br />
wearing your communications hat that telecommunications costs are the second<br />
highest business cost behind wages and salaries. So anything that can be done to make<br />
that pricing structure more competitive is a damn good thing. Very good news for<br />
small business.<br />
ALSTON: Absolutely and I'm sure we'll see more of this in the months and years ahead.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Where are we at now, just remind me where we're at with the regional<br />
telecommunications infrastructure fujnd : that's the extra $ 250 million that we decided<br />
to set aside from the partial sale of Telstra to provide a capital injection to ensure that<br />
regional Australia gets a high level of telecommunications infrastructure.<br />
ALSTON: Well I'm pleased you asked that because we announced the composition of the board<br />
yesterday and it's to be chaired by Doug Anthony, who...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
He knows a bit about regional Australia.<br />
ALSTON: That he does indeed. And he's still, I think, living up in the north... </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I visited him there about eighteen months ago. His still living up at Mooloolaba.<br />
ALSTON: Well he'll have to travel all around Australia with this board because it will be<br />
responsible for making decision on a State by State basis about the monies that ought<br />
to be available to regional telecommunications. And the rest of the Fund members are<br />
very interesting, particularly for the people of Ballarat, because a local Professor Gerry<br />
Anderson who's the Vice Chancellor of the University of Ballarat will be on the Board<br />
together with Lindsay MacDonald, the Queensland wool farmer, Johanna Plante,<br />
Telecommunications Consultant and Eleanor Scholz, the Manager of regional South<br />
Australian Telecentre. As I've already told the multitudes here today, the money the<br />
first round of money will be made available in the May Budget and we expect that the<br />
Board will be inundated with applications.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
That's, rightly speaking, a rate of $ 50 million a year...<br />
ALSTON: That's right.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Over five years. And with that amount of money we really ought, when it's<br />
completed, to be able to see a royal class telecommunications infrastructure in all the<br />
regional areas. But that is really essential for a country as big as Australia. You must<br />
make certain that people living in regional and rural Australia are get the same<br />
telecommunications services and the same fruits of the communications exposure as<br />
the rest of the community. It's very important.<br />
ALSTON: Yes and it helps them to overcome the tyranny of distance.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Indeed it does. Well you've got a very experienced board there. Can you tell all the<br />
people at Ballarat that I really am quite excited about this development. This is the<br />
first really visible sign that the modern competitive communications market has well<br />
and truly arrived in regional Australia. And, of course, from the first of July this year<br />
we'll have central deregulation and full-blooded competition in so much of the<br />
telecommunications market and, well, I think the benefits will become very, very<br />
obvious as the months go by. </p>
<p>ALSTON: Yes and I think we're all very excited at the prospects after the first of July and we're<br />
very grateful to you, in particular, for your support...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well we've got to make certain there are no first and second class telecommunications<br />
or communications citizens in Australia and this notion that because you might live<br />
outside one of the big capital cities you somehow or other get short-changed is<br />
something we're absolutely determined to deny that because it's very important if<br />
you can have competitive costs in regional areas like Ballarat it means you stop the<br />
population drift, particularly the young, you'll generate more jobs and have a more<br />
competitive pricing structure for small business and that's hugely important.<br />
ALSTON: John, there's just one other thing that the people of Ballarat are very much looking<br />
forward to and that's the test match tomorrow night and they all know...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Not only the people of Ballarat, there's a bloke sometimes in Kirribilli, sometime in<br />
the Lodge who's also very interested in it too.<br />
ALSTON: We've got a bloke called Matthew Elliott who's obviously going to be making most of<br />
the runs but do you think there'll be anyone else in there helping him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well if form is any guide a bloke called Waugh and bloke called Blewett will probably<br />
do pretty well. Mark Taylor, I hope he's fully recovered from his back injury and I<br />
reckon millions of Australians will be wishing him well. They had a tremendous start<br />
that was a very classy performance in the first test, very classy performance. Now I'm<br />
very much of the view that they'll probably take this match out as well. I think it's a<br />
very good team and in a way it's all started to come together. The winning<br />
combination and the way which people have developed I think is just terrific.<br />
ALSTON: Yes it's a good all-round side isn't it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
A great side. </p>
<p>ALSTON: I can assure you that very many people here will be having late nights over the next...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, well thank you for your efforts in making certain that the spirit of the anti<br />
syphoning laws were honoured in relation to the direct telecast. There's one thing that<br />
Australians are entitled to have and that is free to air television access to major<br />
sporting events. Very, very important cricket, Aussie Rules, Rugby League, major<br />
Rugby Union tests, Tennis and Golf. Somebody will probably remind me that I've left<br />
something out.<br />
ALSTON: No, they want to know when you do any work if you're watching all of those.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Okay. Give my regards to Ballarat. I was there only a few weeks ago.<br />
ALSTON: I've got Michael Ronaldson here...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yeah, well say hello to Rono.<br />
ALSTON:<br />
Right. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
We wish you well and thanks again for a great job you're doing in relation to<br />
communications and thank you to Northgate communications.<br />
ALSTON: Can I just ask Brad Weinstock on behalf of Northgate to say a few words to you?<br />
WEINSTOCK: Prime Minister Howard, I'd like to thank you very much for participating in this<br />
exciting launch here today and we'd just like to ask you if the voice quality on your<br />
end is as crystal clear as it is here? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The voice quality is terrific here.<br />
WEINSTOCK: Terrific. PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It's, you know, very good. It's marvellous and I think it's a very, very important day<br />
for Ballarat. It's a great symbol of the coming of communications competition to<br />
regional Australia and I hope it's duplicated in many regional centres over the months<br />
and years ahead.<br />
WEINSTOCK: Well we look forward to making 40 more calls like throughout regional Australia.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
If the local calls are free is that right and the ones around Australia.<br />
WEINSTOCK: No, it's just local.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Oh gee. Okay. Thanks a lot.<br />
ends<br />
7-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
