<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4724</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004724.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 28 May 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
This year, important decisions will be made concerning the<br />
international economy and world trade. The decisions will<br />
be so important that they could well set the pattern to the<br />
end of this century.<br />
Australia is a great and significant trading nation. Therefore<br />
we have much at stake.<br />
We have a basic interest in an orderly and reasonable world<br />
trading system that recognises the rights and responsibilities<br />
of all nations.<br />
We recognise the limits of our influence in world economic<br />
affairs,* but at the same time it is our obligation to express<br />
views that we hold firmly and to advance Australia's cause<br />
in international forums at every opportunity.<br />
This year is important because the Tokyo round trade negotiations<br />
begun in 1973 are due to conclude in the middle of the year.<br />
America is aiming for an outline package of conclusions by<br />
mid-July.<br />
I am concerned that if there is no positive advance in these<br />
trade discussions that both Europe and the United States might<br />
revert to protectionism.<br />
President Carter has stood out against a protectionist Congress<br />
with great strength. But if what are called the Multi Lateral<br />
Trade Negotiations are not successful it would be harder to<br />
withstand those pressures. Increasing protectionism in Europe<br />
would also be likely.<br />
A reversion to protectionism would lead to beggar-thy-neighbour<br />
policies of the kind the world saw in the 1930' s with enormous<br />
damage to many countries. Because Australia is a significant<br />
trading country, we have a greater interest than most in<br />
preventing that from happening.<br />
My talks with the Prime Minister of Japan a few weeks ago<br />
concentrated on these issues. Japan also relies heavily on<br />
trade, upon access to markets in Europe and in America. We<br />
found a remarkable identity of view and agreed to cooperate<br />
and consult closely. </p>
<p>Australia believes there will be no success at these trade<br />
negotiations unless industrial goods, agriculture and commodities<br />
are all included in the final result.<br />
In the past, when there have been significant world trade<br />
meetings Europe and America made agreements about industrial<br />
goods but then they put agriculture aside.-in the " too hard"<br />
basket. While there are rules for fair trade in industrial<br />
goods, nations seem to reserve to themselves the right to have<br />
arbitrary restrictions on access to markets in agriculture and<br />
in comnmodities,.<br />
Over the next few months we will be trying to see that rules<br />
for fair trade in agriculture are promoted. Let me explain<br />
why this is so important.<br />
Trading nations need an expansion of markets. That will lead<br />
to an expansion of trade.<br />
It is only through an expansion of markets that we will be<br />
able to provide for increased output from our factories, from<br />
our farms and from our mines. Increased output, increased<br />
demand will lead to increased employment. It is the same in<br />
many countries.<br />
If world markets do not expand, nations are going to be left<br />
arguing about the cut-up of existing markets and that will<br />
do nothing for unemployment around the world.<br />
Under the guise of calling for a 40% tariff cut the major<br />
industrial nations have put forward a proposal which in fact<br />
is little more on average than a half a percent reduction in<br />
tariffs a year for eight years. In the first five years<br />
those reductions would be mandatory under the formula.<br />
Aeductions in the last three years would de-. cnd u-, on the<br />
economic circumstances of the time. The programme would start<br />
in 1980.<br />
This proposal of the formula applied to industrial items<br />
would cover less than 20% of world trade. It is not therefore<br />
a proposal of itself which can lead to an expansion of markets<br />
and an increase in world trade.<br />
That just underlines the importance of making sure that<br />
agriculture and commodities are part of the arrangements at<br />
the Multi Lateral Trade Negotiations to broaden the scope,<br />
the coverage of the agreements. That is important from a.<br />
number of points of view.<br />
The application of the formula to industrial goods would cover<br />
about 40% of the exports of Northern America and of Europe<br />
but only about 5% of Australia's exports.<br />
Developing countries need fairer terms of trade they need<br />
arrangements that will give them commodity and price stability. ./ 3 </p>
<p>Australia has some experience in that.<br />
For a long time we have been involved in the International<br />
Sugar Agreement, in the International Wheat Agreements, and<br />
we operate a wool marketing proposal which works greatly to<br />
the advantage of consumers and producers. It brings<br />
stability and predictability at a reasonable price into the<br />
trade. If it is possible for these commodities, it is possible for<br />
others. Australia has been trying to take a position that would bring<br />
the developed and developing world closer together.<br />
Through the last six months we have had some success, but it<br />
is enormously important to bring in the developing world with<br />
their tens of millions of people in need of more schools,<br />
better hospitals and all the infrastructure of government.<br />
That is not only a need in itself, but economic take-off in<br />
the developing world could well be a significant factor in<br />
providing a boost to markets and an expansion of demand that<br />
could sustain economic recovery through to the end of this<br />
century. So Australia does not base its plea and-argument for a<br />
better deal for the developing world on idealism alone.<br />
We base it on the mutual self interest and economic interdependence<br />
of all nations, developing and developed alike..<br />
On Wednesday I leave to further the discussions I had with<br />
the Prime Minister of Japan, with the Prime Ministers of<br />
Britain, of France and the Chancellor of Germany. They will<br />
be having an economic Summit meeting in Bonn in July, and<br />
their counsels will be of enormous importance in helping<br />
to come to a realistic and responsible conclusion.<br />
Following these discussions I will be holding further talks<br />
with Mr Lee Kuan Yew, Prime Minister of Singapore. The<br />
Prime Minister and I will then meet with the Prime Minister<br />
of Malaysia in Kuala Lumpur.<br />
Amongst other things, we will be discussing the-general<br />
world trade position as a result of my discussions in Europe,<br />
especially as they relate to the developing world.<br />
Australia has the desire to consult closely with countries<br />
in our region on these issues, as they are dependent on access<br />
to the great markets of the major industrialised countries.<br />
Australia today has special international obligations which<br />
are being met.<br />
We are taking a determined and vigorous part in negotiations<br />
on world economic issues. We owe this to our own community.<br />
Our meetings over the next three weeks further demonstrate<br />
our desire to continue to act as a responsible member of the<br />
international community. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
