<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7951</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT EDITED VERSION - 12 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007951.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, 7.30 REPORT<br />
EDITED VERSION 12 MARCH 1990<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, thanks for joining us.<br />
PM: Pleasure.<br />
LYNEHAM: The prevailing wisdom is that voters are very<br />
cynical at the moment. Do you agree with that?<br />
PM: No, I think the correct statement though Paul is<br />
that probably more people are going to cast a vote for<br />
the non-major parties than before. And as I've said, I<br />
think one of the major explanations of that is of the<br />
increased interest in environmental issues that has<br />
obviously arisen not only in Australia but around the<br />
world in the last three years.<br />
LYNEHAM: The National Media Liaison Unit at least two<br />
of its members, I've spoken with them over the phone at<br />
your campaign headquarters in Sydney. Are they on leave<br />
without pay or are they paid public servants at this<br />
stage? PM: They would still be on their normal pay arrangements<br />
as far as I understand. I don't know the circumstances.<br />
If you'd like I'll check and give you the answer but I<br />
would think they'd still be on their normal pay<br />
arrangements. LYNEHA4: Is it proper to have the taxpayer paying for<br />
people to help the ALP win power?<br />
PM: I would simply say this, that if you look at the<br />
situation that existed before we came into power, there<br />
was a much more blatant use of people on the payroll by<br />
our predecessors and you are aware of what happened then.<br />
But as I say, I don't know, I assume they are still on<br />
the same arrangements.<br />
LYNEHAM: If you quote your predecessors, does that mean<br />
your moral standards are set by the other side?<br />
PM: It certainly does not. It seems to me that there is<br />
an acceptance that in government you have people who are,<br />
if you like, involved in not only making sure that the<br />
people know what the government is doing, but also<br />
monitoring what's happening. I think that's been a </p>
<p>feature of Australian politics. I don't think that I got<br />
terribly upset about what happened before. I don't think<br />
people should be now.<br />
LYNEHAI: When will negotiations begin with the United<br />
States on the Australian takeover of North West Cape?<br />
PM: Quite quickly Paul. We have been in touch with the<br />
United States and we just got the reply back from them at<br />
the end of last week, from Dick Cheney, and they, as you<br />
understand, have welcomed the idea. I'm glad they have<br />
because I think it's very very significant. And they<br />
will expect, as we do, for the negotiations to start<br />
quite soon.<br />
LYNEHAM: Did Dick Cheney have any objections to you<br />
making this public during an election campaign?<br />
PM: No, why should he?<br />
LYNEHAM: Well, I mean, it does look to many as though<br />
Washington is letting you drape yourself in the Stars and<br />
Stripes, just as Menzies used to drape himself in the<br />
Union Jack.<br />
PM: Well, the cynicism is not only in the electorate,<br />
it's amongst the commentators. There is no foundation<br />
for that. Let me give you the reasons why it was<br />
important to do it now, and as soon as possible.<br />
Firstly, this is forward-looking. It is quite clear when<br />
you look at our defence strategic approach for the future<br />
that the use of our new submarines, which we are now<br />
constructing in Adelaide, it's going to be a very very<br />
important part of that future. The command and the<br />
control capacity for those submarines is fundamentally<br />
important. So we'd want to have a situation where we<br />
have control of that. Secondly, the 25 year agreement<br />
that has gone back from 1963, that ended in 1988 and new<br />
0 negotiations were about to start for the next stage. It<br />
obviously was much sensible that we put our proposal on<br />
the table before that started. Thirdly, there's been<br />
some degree of concern at Exmouth amongst the local<br />
population there as to what their future might be. It<br />
was appropriate that that concern should be allayed. For<br />
those three reasons it was appropriate that as soon as we<br />
got a response from the United States to our proposal<br />
that we should advance it. And particularly that I<br />
should announce it here in Western Australia.<br />
LYNEHAM: And entirely fortuitous that it's during an<br />
election campaign?<br />
PM: It would've been announced any rate. The important<br />
point that I'm making is that it should be done as soon<br />
as possible and if the election had been held in May, as<br />
was a possibility, it would've been announced now. It<br />
wouldn't have been held till then. </p>
<p>LYNEHAM: Do you still stand by Paul Keating's claim that<br />
current taxes on super fund earnings will not diminish<br />
any potential end benefit by one cent?<br />
PM: Yes I do. Most importantly what you've got now is a<br />
contrast in the public arena between the political<br />
statements of some people who are trying to support the<br />
Opposition and the only factual source, which is the<br />
Australian Tax Office, which points out that of the<br />
13,000 returns of funds that have been negotiated, when<br />
you look at it there's no net loss. And indeed I think<br />
only some about 400 out of 13,000 had any net capital<br />
gain in it, but which could be more than offset by the<br />
imputation credits.<br />
LYNEHAM: Let's look at that 13,000 Prime Minister. Are<br />
you aware that they're less than 10% of the total of<br />
160,000 returns on superannuation that will be processed<br />
by the end of this month?<br />
O PM: All I'm saying is that in respect of those that have<br />
been processed, there is the figure.<br />
LYNEHAM: These are less than 10% of the total returns<br />
that will come in by the end of this month. You would be<br />
a mug, if you owe money, to put your return in early.<br />
The normal pattern, if you've got to pay money to the<br />
taxman, you wait until the very last minute. Why is it<br />
the case that these 13,000 represent any real sample at<br />
all? PM: They represent the only sample that's available and<br />
on the basis of<br />
LYNEHAM: And in an abnormal year Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Not an abnormal year Mr Lyneham at all. I'm simply<br />
saying to you that what can be done other than to use the<br />
returns that have been processed. Secondly, to take<br />
account of what the major funds are saying. They've made<br />
it quite clear, two major ones, AMP and the National<br />
Mutual, have made it quite clear how they operate.<br />
Thirdly, you've got to ask yourself the question, what is<br />
the future, what is the future of a fund manager who does<br />
not in fact take advantage of the provisions that have<br />
been deliberately introduced to make sure that they<br />
shan't pay any net tax?<br />
LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, if it's only going to affect<br />
one percent into the future, and not those four million<br />
Australians in super funds, how is it the Treasurer can<br />
tell us there's already five billion out there waiting to<br />
be collected in the system, that it's the fastest growing<br />
tax in the Commonwealth. Where's all this coming from?<br />
PM: It's coming from the operation tax. It's got<br />
nothing to do with the superannuation system. </p>
<p>LYNEHAN: Let's say I'm a small business person or a<br />
farmer. I've worked hard, worked long in my business, I<br />
want to move up, I want to get a bigger business in the<br />
next town. I then sell my business where I live. I then<br />
get copped with a bill for capital gains tax, just at the<br />
time when I need that capital to go and develop my next<br />
business to create more wealth, employ more people. Why<br />
can't I roll that over if I'm going from one business to<br />
a similar one after all, the Beddall Committee<br />
recommended this why can't I roll it over and grow and<br />
help the country grow?<br />
PM: Well, ok. Well, let's just have a look at the facts<br />
of the situation. Firstly, which is not clear in the way<br />
you put your question, so let me make it clear, is that<br />
you don't get taxed on the nominal improvement in the<br />
value of your business. It's only on the real value. So<br />
that is an element which is not taxed. Secondly, let's<br />
look at the situation that's operated since the tax has<br />
come in. We've had very very significant economic growth<br />
in the country. I mean, it hasn't stopped growth. Let's<br />
look at what's happened<br />
LYNEHAM: Look at what's happened to small business Prime<br />
Minister. PM: Ok, let's<br />
LYNEHAM: High interest rates.<br />
PM: Ok Paul, don't get too excited. We can go on.<br />
Let's look at what's happened to business generally,<br />
including small business. The fact is that we have had,<br />
in the period since the capital gains tax has come in,<br />
the highest level of investment by business, which covers<br />
small business and large business, the highest level of<br />
imvestment as a proportion of gross domestic product. In<br />
the last year it was 13.5%.<br />
0 LYNEHAM: Ten thousand small businesses have gone bust<br />
since Christmas according to the Council of Small<br />
Business Organisations.<br />
PM: If the implication of your question is that it is<br />
the obligation of a government so to conduct macroeconomic<br />
and micro-economic policy that no business goes<br />
bust, then I'm quite happy to argue that proposition.<br />
Let's look at the facts over the whole of this period.<br />
The facts over the whole of this period are these, and<br />
never overlook them. 1.6 million new jobs with 93%, 93%<br />
Paul of those new jobs going into the private sector and<br />
overwhelmingly into the small business sector. You've<br />
never had growth of the small business sector like you've<br />
had in the seven years of the Hawke Labor Government.<br />
LYNEHAN: Why are so many of them in trouble? </p>
<p>PM: Well I'll tell you the answer. The answer is very<br />
simple. That in 1989 we'd had such a high level of<br />
growth the previous year, as you know, the statistic,<br />
very simple an eight percent increase in consumption, a<br />
four percent increase in production and that gap coming<br />
from imports. We had to slow it down. We had to slow it<br />
down with high interest rates. If we hadn't, if we<br />
hadn't slowed the rate of growth down, any loss of small<br />
businesses that you've had would be as nothing compared<br />
to what would've happened in the total collapse of the<br />
economy. LYNEHAM: At the last election you told us we shouldn't<br />
change horses in midstream because you needed another<br />
term to finish the job. The net national debt then was<br />
$ 83 billion. Now we're told you need another term to<br />
finish the job. The net national debt now is $ 118<br />
billion. How much more of this sort of job can Australia<br />
stand? PM: It's very clear it can stand a lot more of what we<br />
are doing and nothing of the alternative. Just let's<br />
look at what's in place to deal with this issue on our<br />
side and look at how that will be destroyed by the<br />
policies of the Opposition. Firstly, we have in place<br />
the facts more Australians than ever before at work,<br />
better educated and trained, and with a better level of<br />
technology and equipment than ever before. And that has<br />
flowed from our wages policy. Against that, against that<br />
a wages policy of our opponents which will mean a wages<br />
explosion and the destruction of the economy.<br />
LYNEHAM: Did you see the Industrial survey today<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: Yes I did indeed.<br />
LYNEHAM: Very gloomy.<br />
O PM: Not very gloomy at all. What's happened is that in<br />
fact I mean you want it both ways. Your question is<br />
just about debt, so what's been driving the debt upwards,<br />
the current account deficit? It has has been that we've<br />
been importing too much. Most of it's capital<br />
investment. So when I take action, as I have with tight<br />
monetary policy, to slow it down, I get attacked for<br />
that. LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, the bottom line is that demand<br />
has to stay below production if we're going to stabilise<br />
the debt. I mean you said this yourself fairly recently<br />
PM: ( inaudible)<br />
LYNEHAM: Exactly what does that mean? </p>
<p>PM: It means this. That what you've got to continue to<br />
do in Australia is what we're doing. And that is to have<br />
a massive restructuring of the Australian economy. To<br />
get what we've done, a 54% increase in manufactured<br />
exports in the last four years<br />
LYNEHAM: But it means you've got to keep the reins on<br />
for a fair while with tight monetary policy, doesn't it?<br />
PM: No, it means that in fact the combination of tight<br />
fiscal policy remember this. That in the last three<br />
years, in the last three years $ 17 billion of budget<br />
surplus, which has paid off the whole of our Commonwealth<br />
Government debt. Now you've got to keep on having a<br />
surplus. Not blow it out by the $ 6 billion hole on the<br />
outlays side that the conservatives were talking about,<br />
let alone the billions of dollars that they'd give back<br />
by way of the abolition of the capital gains tax.<br />
LYNEHAM: Both sides are now saying vote for us and<br />
you'll get lower interest rates. Andrew Peacock said<br />
significant and sustained. Isn't it a fact that neither<br />
of you can really do very much, that if they do fall it<br />
won't be very far?<br />
PM: On the contrary. Good question, sharp answer. The<br />
banking industry itself has said in regard to the<br />
existing policies of this Government that interest rates<br />
will come down. That's the statement of the banking<br />
sector which sets interest rates.. Against that the<br />
inevitable fact Paul that interest rates must rise under<br />
the impact of the coalition policies for two reasons.<br />
Wages explosion. Secondly, in regard to the surplus of<br />
government, we have now, as I say, a $ 17 billion surplus<br />
in the last three years. They'll blow it because they've<br />
got a $ 6 billion hole and they're also going to ruin<br />
their budget surplus situation by giving billions of<br />
dollars back to the, one percent. So as a result of both<br />
a wages explosion and the destruction of the Commonwealth<br />
Government budget surplus interest rates would have to<br />
rise. LYNEHAM: And they will come down under you?<br />
PM: Well, as I say, don't just rely on my statement<br />
which is based upon<br />
LYNEHAM: Well what is your statement?<br />
PM: My statement<br />
LYNEHAM: Massive, as Mr Peacock used to say?<br />
PM: No.<br />
LYNEHAM: Significant and sustained? </p>
<p>7<br />
PM: If you've got a problem with Mr Peacock about his<br />
incapacity to adhere to words, you have your argument<br />
with him. I rather enjoy your arguments with him. As<br />
far as I'm concerned, what I've said during this campaign<br />
is that the banking sector itself has said that interest<br />
rates will come down.<br />
LYNEHAM: And they'll be sustained falls?<br />
PM: I believe so.<br />
LYNEHAM: Of course you said yesterday that you couldn't<br />
be held to anything that you didn't control, that would<br />
be an honest mistake rather than a fib.<br />
PM: What I said was obviously what I must say. I can<br />
control these things. I have demonstrated that I can<br />
control wages outcome in this country. For seven years<br />
Paul, in regard to the wages outcome, we have either been<br />
on target or we'ye somewhat overestimated<br />
LYNEHAM: But not the inflation that erodes those wages?<br />
PM: We've gone through this and very simply let me<br />
repeat on this program what I've said before that like<br />
every other economist in this country, in the public and<br />
the private sector, we underestimated the level of<br />
demand, LYNEHAM: We don't vote for every other economist Mr<br />
Hawke, we vote for you and Paul Keating.<br />
PM: Adn I'll tell you what, and if you vote for me what<br />
you'll get, what you'll get is a continuation of record<br />
employment growth, of a rate of growth of the economy<br />
twice as fast under us as under our predecessors...<br />
average rate of 4.4% economic growth, a rate of 3.5% of<br />
S oefm pleomypmleonytm engtr ogwrtohw tahg, a inasntd ytohue'ilrl 0v. 7o, t e fifvoer at imgeosv ertnhem enrtate<br />
which has demonstrated that it can deliver a wages<br />
outcome, a sustainable wages outcome and not a wages<br />
explosion, and you'll vote for a government which has<br />
done what has never been done before. In all those<br />
years, 30 of the 33 years before I became Prime Minister,<br />
the Libs and the Nationals in control. They never got a<br />
budget surplus once. In three years, after rectifying<br />
their mistakes, a $ 17 billion surplus which I've used to<br />
pay off the Commonwealth Government debt overseas.<br />
LYNEHAM: Prime Minister, thanks for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you very much indeed Paul.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
