<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9826</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP AUSTRALIAN REPUBLICAN MOVEMENT 5TH ANNUAL DINNER, SYDNEY, 3 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009826.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
** Embargoed until 9: 00pm check against delivery<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
AUSTRALIAN REPUBUICAN MOVEMENT 5TH ANNUAL DINNER,<br />
SYDNEY, 3 NOVEMBER 1995<br />
It is a pleasure to be here, even if it is something of a daunting task to follow<br />
Robert Hughes, and I thank Malcolm Turnbull and the Australian Republican<br />
Movement for inviting me along.<br />
Robert Hughes is an expatriate Australian but a genuine patriot. He maintains<br />
a keen, intelligent and very sympathetic interest in his homeland; he has<br />
written a couple of the great books about Australian art and Australian<br />
history; and by his work and his character a sort of pragmatic Australian<br />
humanist he is a great ambassador for this country.<br />
He is to Australian arts and letters what Lew Hoad was to tennis.<br />
An unselfconscious ambassador for Australia to the world.<br />
And of course he is a republican.<br />
There used to be another kind of Australian expatriate of course the one<br />
who left and from a great distance heaped scorn upon the place. But these<br />
are much less common than they used to be and we are all grateful for that.<br />
We are not alarmed if Peter Carey decides to write his novels in New York<br />
instead of Sydney or Bacchus Marsh. We do not get a fit of the cringes if<br />
our film directors<br />
and actors base themselves in Hollywood, or our painters get themselves a<br />
villa in Tuscany, or our musicians set up camp with the Berlin Philharmonic or<br />
sing with the Scottish National Opera. </p>
<p>For those of us whose memories extend to the fifties and sixties, this<br />
represents a considerable change of heart. We are much more relaxed about<br />
it.<br />
And rightly. No one really leaves anywhere for good these days. Not in the<br />
way people used to.<br />
In part the change stems from the revolution in global economics and<br />
telecommunications. It is going to be increasingly difficult to be xenophobic<br />
and prosper in the modern world. If you are not open and interacting with<br />
the globe you will not be in the game.<br />
This demands a large measure of tolerance, openness and adaptability; and,<br />
remarkably for those of us who remember the days of insularity and the<br />
mighty cringe, suddenly these things can be said about Australia.<br />
This is a tolerant, open and adaptable society. It is hybrid, eclectic and<br />
infinitely diverse. I hesitate to use such terms in the presence of Robert<br />
Hughes, but Australia does seem to me to have a touch of the post moderns<br />
about it.<br />
That is not to say that it has happened overnight, only that it feels like it.<br />
Nor is it to say that this generation is singularly responsible for the change, in<br />
fact the foundations were laid a long while ago. The roots go down to the<br />
colonial democracies, to the democratic institutions we inherited from Britain,<br />
to the experience of war, to post-war immigration.<br />
It is impossible to overstate the significance of post-war immigration or the<br />
power of good it has done us. Nothing has wrought such a change on the<br />
national consciousness and the national fabric.<br />
And nothing was better calculated to drive away the fear and the prejudice.<br />
It is one of our great national successes, this transformation of Australia into<br />
a tolerant and diverse and outward looking modern society.<br />
Every day a thousand cliches are uttered about it but we really should take<br />
great pride in the achievement, because it proves something about both the<br />
old values of Australia and the new.<br />
And we should passionately defend the principles of tolerance and democracy<br />
on which it is built. </p>
<p>That is not to say that what has come to be called multiculturalism is beyond<br />
either criticism or the need for reform and adjustment.<br />
And in the past couple of years I have been making this point: what we have<br />
come to call multiculturalism must never become an ideology, or a<br />
bureaucratic citadel of political correctness.<br />
It must never become exclusive or exclusionist. It will self-destruct if it<br />
begins to mistake diversity for the mainstream. Nothing in the agenda of<br />
multiculturalism has ever said, and nor must it ever say, that the culture of<br />
pro-multicultural Australians is to be washed away.<br />
That includes those great institutions and traditions we inherited from Britain,<br />
and those Australians of earlier times adapted and invented.<br />
We are not discarding the old tiles in the social and cultural mosaic, we are<br />
adding to them.<br />
I suspect that the mark of a truly successful multicultural society is less the<br />
degree of diversity than the sense of unity, the sense of oneness.<br />
Diversity is easy to achieve, and we have proved that it can be managed in<br />
ways which are equitable and fair and which preserve social harmony.<br />
The real trick is creating the glue that holds it together. That is probably the<br />
hardest part. It is certainly the crucial part and the part we must be forever<br />
vigilant about.<br />
And it is the part where the republic comes in not as a sufficient condition<br />
for national cohesion and purpose, but a necessary one.<br />
And these are things we need.<br />
We have a huge continent and a small population. There is a a great deal of<br />
cultural diversity within the geographical and occupational spread before you<br />
even get to the ethnic differences. The federation is a loose one.<br />
I don't see these facts of Australian life as a threat to the nation though it is<br />
always worth bearing in mind that we cannot take our nationhood for<br />
granted. Rather I think that in them lies the clue to the sort of country, the sort of<br />
republic, we ought to and can become. </p>
<p>One that values the diversity of the place and the population; one that is<br />
deeply democratic, egalitarian and tolerant; one that expresses a love for the<br />
land and the best traditions of the people and yet can accommodate the new.<br />
In a sense, this is the other meaning of minimalist. As much as a republic<br />
will set a new direction for Australia and express our hopes for a new sense<br />
of common purpose, it will confirm what is already there.<br />
It will confirm our independence. It will confirm that tolerance and diversity<br />
and our democratic institutions and traditions, It will confirm our belief in<br />
Australia and our love of the land and the environment.<br />
I think that this is the essential beauty of it, the huge opportunity it presents<br />
to us. In a single essentially symbolic act we can confirm both the history<br />
and the contemporary reality of Australia, including our contemporary<br />
ambitions. I include among these our ambition to make women truly equal partners at<br />
every level of our national life; our ambition to give Aboriginal Australians<br />
both justice and opportunity and to make our Aboriginal cultural heritage<br />
secure. And I also include our ambitions in the region and the world. Our ambition to<br />
succeed in becoming a partner and player in the region. Our ambition to<br />
make this a clever and creative country.<br />
And we can do it at a hugely symbolic time at the close of our first century<br />
of nationhood, at the dawn of a new century.<br />
Few other countries have such a chance.<br />
I don't think I need to tell you that I believe it is altogether too good an<br />
opportunity for Australia to let pass.<br />
Now, this seems to me to have certain inescapable consequences for the<br />
Australian Republican Movement and for all those Australians who believe<br />
that our head of state should be an Australian.<br />
It means, perhaps above all, that we talk a good deal less to each other and<br />
a good deal less to Lloyd Waddy and his little band of soldiers and a good<br />
deal more to Australians who remain sceptical, uninterested or, for whatever<br />
reason, vaguely hostile.<br />
It means that the great debate the really great debate should now begin. </p>
<p>The republic is no longer an abstract idea, it is not something out there in the<br />
never never.<br />
I think Australians should now assume that there will be a referendum on this<br />
question before the year 2000. And I think the debate should be conducted<br />
with this in mind. Australians will soon be asked to decide whether they<br />
want as their head of state the monarch of Great Britain or an Australian.<br />
Now for most of us here all of us is a reasonable guess the issue is<br />
beyond doubt.<br />
I confess I sometimes cannot understand how anyone could fail to see why<br />
Australia should have an Australian head of state.<br />
And I also confess that sometimes, even though I know there are<br />
complexities to resolve and obstacles to overcome, I cannot understand why<br />
anyone should not have faith enough to think that we can overcome them.<br />
Nevertheless, I know and I'm sure all of you know, that there are good<br />
reasons why Australians are cautious and sceptical about this change.<br />
" If it ain't broke, don't fix it" sums it up pretty well. Of course, it's less a<br />
question of being broke than one of obsolescence. If being broke was the<br />
criterion for discarding something most of us would still be getting around by<br />
horse and cart.<br />
What we're talking about here is a trade-in. A trade-up. A new model<br />
called the Republic.<br />
Now, it is possible that events since France began exploding bombs in the<br />
Pacific again have possibly persuaded a lot more Australians that indeed it is<br />
broke. Many Australians, I know, fear the change to a republic. I think their greater<br />
fear should be that we will be left to share a head of state with a country<br />
which may very often in future feel itself obliged to oppose our interests in<br />
this region and the world.<br />
The British Government has made very clear what has been obvious for a<br />
long while that Australia's interests and Britain's interests are often very<br />
different and even fundamentally opposed. </p>
<p>This was made plain even before John Major declared his outright support for<br />
President Chirac's actions, when Britain stood alone among European nations<br />
in refusing to condemn the French nuclear testing program. Now it is plainer<br />
still. It should come as no surprise to anyone, of course.<br />
I seem to remember making a speech in the presence of Her Majesty The<br />
Queen shortly after I became Prime Minister; and in it saying that just as<br />
Britain had for many years been pursuing her interests in Europe, Australia<br />
was now pursuing Australia's interests in Asia and the Pacific. And drawing<br />
the conclusion that while we saw our heritage as shared, and there was<br />
much else to share in the future, we saw our destiny as distinctly different.<br />
It was entirely unexceptional. I was a little worried I might be accused of<br />
being platitudinous.<br />
But then that closet republican, John Hewson, rushed outside Parliament<br />
House and condemned me for showing too little respect.<br />
We can't be sure at all that Australians everywhere will see in the British<br />
Government's support for the French Government more evidence that it is<br />
silly for us to share a head of state with another country and I stress this,<br />
any other country.<br />
As confirmation that Britain would pursue its best interests regardless of<br />
ours, John Major's action this week approached the brutal. However, the<br />
lesson to be learned from it is not an anti-British one but one about the<br />
inappropriateness of Australia having a head of state who is not one of us.<br />
So how do we proceed?<br />
I think the answer is by persuading our countrymen and women that we can<br />
make the change to an Australian head of state without danger to our<br />
democracy and our federation and without offence to a Queen we hold in<br />
very high regard.<br />
And by resisting the course on which the conservative parties have<br />
embarked, which is to stall the debate and progress towards a republic by<br />
means of a charade called a peoples' convention.<br />
The peoples' convention they talk of has very little to do with genuine debate<br />
and democratic participation, and a great deal to do with political diversions<br />
and procrastination. </p>
<p>It is about to use an expression attributed to Mr Howard kicking the<br />
republican ball into touch. Mr Howard cannot be relied upon to change his<br />
views on the monarchy: I doubt if there is a more ardent monarchist in the<br />
country. Let me quote to you from an article Alex Mitchell wrote in the Sun Herald on<br />
June this year in which he referred to a discussion he'd had with a person<br />
he described as " a very senior Liberal". He meant John Howard. How would<br />
the Liberal Party respond to the republic he asked him<br />
No worries he replied. We can kick the whole thing into touch by<br />
calling for a peoples' convention, the peoples' convention is a perfect<br />
talking shop. It will keep the issue off the party political agenda and<br />
the election agenda. With the people's convention up and running, the<br />
Liberal Party wouldn't have to say or do anything about the republic.<br />
It would effectively bury the issue for as long as we want it.<br />
Later in the conversation he announced: I am a monarchist. I was<br />
born a monarchist and I will die a monarchist.<br />
Dare I say the rest of Australia need not die with him.<br />
Mr Howard can be relied upon to create smokescreens and confusion. He<br />
has lagged behind the progress of this nation throughout his political career,<br />
and that is what has made him a difficult opponent. The experience of being<br />
forever at odds with the direction of the country, forever trying to catch up,<br />
has made him Australia's foremost spoiler.<br />
We can be sure he will want to slow progress and he will do that by trying to<br />
create as much uncertainty in the public mind as he can. He will try to make<br />
the resolution of this issue appear more difficult than it really is.<br />
But we have got over him before and we can get over him again.<br />
If you ask Mr Howard what his policy is on the republic, what policy he will<br />
give you he will say: " you can be for it and against it". That is, he'd give<br />
you the direction either way.<br />
But what he is really saying is that he himself is against the republic and<br />
effectively, he would make certain there is no chance of a republic.<br />
John Howard says that if there was a referendum for a republic put by a<br />
Government led by him, he personally would be for the monarchy. </p>
<p>Does anybody in this country seriously believe that where such a referendum<br />
proposal must secure a majority of electors in a majority of States that such a<br />
proposition would have a snowball's chance in hell if the Government of the<br />
day wasn't going flat out for it.<br />
Particularly if the Prime Minister was running on the " no case"<br />
Any Government putting a referendum proposal for a republic would need an<br />
all out national effort an all out political effort.<br />
But to go into such a campaign with the Prime Minister saying that he is<br />
actually against the proposal would be to make a sham of the whole process.<br />
John Howard's shonky republic proposals mean one thing and one thing only<br />
no republicl<br />
A Coalition Government would mean no republic.<br />
There's only one way to an Australian republic and that's with the only Party<br />
which gives real meaning and expression to the great breadth of national<br />
sentiment and identity that is, of course, the Australian Labor Party.<br />
Like all great reforms, the Labor Party will have to carry the weight of this<br />
one too. But to carry it with an Opposition saying that they could be with<br />
you on the same proposal when their purpose is to destroy it is taking<br />
political chicanery too far.<br />
And we will do it by the same means. We will be appealing to the Australian<br />
people who are sceptical and pragmatic but not bad judges and who are not<br />
averse to necessary change.<br />
Mr Howard said the other day that the republic was now " election neutral".<br />
Let me tell you and him it is not. It is alive and well and all his efforts to<br />
neutralise and destroy it, will almost certainly fail.<br />
If we take our argument to the people of Australia and put our case well<br />
and the media of this country allow us to put it well ( and at least on their<br />
editorial pages they do support the republican cause) I am sure the people<br />
will vote for an Australian republic.<br />
We will have to take it well beyond the perception that the republic is for the<br />
well-heeled of Sydney and Melbourne. We will have to dispel any perception<br />
that it is a male and middle class movement without much consequence for<br />
the great majority of Australians. </p>
<p>And we will have to dispel some of the myths about the Government's<br />
proposals. For instance, it has been alleged that an Australian president<br />
elected by a two-thirds majority of parliament and only removable by the<br />
same means would be able to abuse the powers he or she would possess.<br />
In fact this method of election is much less likely to give us wilful or<br />
whimsical Presidents than a popular election, and Presidents much less likely<br />
to claim a popular mandate for their political or other beliefs.<br />
No President could be elected without bi-partisan support and no President<br />
could be removed without it. As we have said many times, popular election<br />
would mean that a Ninian Stephen or a Zelman Cowen would never become<br />
President of the Republic of Australia.<br />
And as we have also said, the requirement of bi-partisan support would<br />
insure against arbitrary or politically motivated removal of a President.<br />
The Government's proposals have been carefully constructed to avoid the<br />
appointment of Presidents who bring their own political agendas to the office<br />
of the head of state. Serving politicians would be disqualified for<br />
appointment for five years after leaving parliament and for those who<br />
remain in any doubt, I can ensure you that would disqualify me for life.<br />
An Australian head of state would be expressly required to exercise his or her<br />
powers, other than the reserve powers, in accordance with ministerial advice.<br />
And the reserve powers would have to be exercised in accordance with the<br />
Constitutional Conventions.<br />
The Government's proposal provides for a President who performs essentially<br />
the same functions as the Governor-General does now.<br />
Because we will have to answer these and many other questions about the<br />
implications of the move to an Australian head of state, the Government<br />
today released an information kit for distribution throughout the Australian<br />
community. Of course I will leave a few of the kits with you tonight and I hope that they<br />
will be of use in the great campaign that lies ahead of us. </p>
<p>We will need all the resources of reason and faith that we can muster. Even<br />
with the tide of history and logic running for us we can't expect to be easily<br />
carried ashore. We are going to have to swim. And we are going to have to<br />
expect the occasional attack from jellyfish and stingrays and the odd hold-up<br />
in the seaweed otherwise known as proposals for a peoples' convention.<br />
But the tide is with us and the incentive is certainly there. Drifting is no<br />
longer an option and drowning is simply not on.<br />
It really can and must be done and I urge you all to make the mighty effort it<br />
requires. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
