<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4163</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT THE JAPANESE PRESS CLUB - 18 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004163.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-1<br />
41 PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINIS-TER AT THE<br />
JAPANESE PRESS CLUB 18 JUNE 1976<br />
My visit to your country is the first I have made to a major power<br />
since becoming Prime Minister. It is no accident that this is so.<br />
* It is a matter of deliberate choice and considered priority.<br />
Our bilateral relationship with Japan is of the utmost importance.<br />
And there is no country which has a great role to play in the future<br />
of Asia and the Pacific.<br />
In achieving the conditions for stable and peaceful development<br />
in this region, Japan's contribution will be crucial. We also<br />
believe that Australia has an important part to play in achieving<br />
this goal.<br />
During the last few days I have spoken several times about the<br />
trade and economic relationship that exists between us. This<br />
relationship is enormously important in itself. It is also<br />
important in that it provides a secure foundation -based on<br />
mutual advantage, complementary resources and need -on which<br />
to build a wider, more comprehensive relationship.<br />
SThe Treaty of Friendship and Co-operation which your Prime Minister<br />
and I have signed recognises the fundamental importance of our<br />
economic relationship. The treaty seeks to strengthen our<br />
economic relations and place it on a more reliable and dependable<br />
footing.<br />
But it is more than that. The Treaty's overriding significance is<br />
that it provides tangible evidence of a will on the part of Australia<br />
and Japan to lend greater political substance to our dealings and<br />
work towards more certain relations based on close friendship,<br />
understanding and shared interests. It is one indicator of<br />
Japan's importance that Australia has not entered such an agreement<br />
with any other country.<br />
It is the non-economic aspects of our relationship that I would<br />
like to focus on today.<br />
Japan and Australia are two democratic and economically developed<br />
island countries. Both can either be described as being on the<br />
western rim of the Pacific basin or as adjacent to the Asian<br />
continent. The different descriptions are not without significance. They<br />
indicate the need, the necessity, for our countries to concern<br />
themselves with possibilities and problems in both directions. 2/ </p>
<p>more immediately, our two countries share a number of interests<br />
* and concerns. We are both democratic states with a respect for<br />
democratic institutions and for the human rights implied by these<br />
institutions. In a world where these institutions are under increasing challenge,<br />
our two countries bear a heavy responsibility to show that democracy<br />
has the capacity to respond to the ever-changing demands made upon<br />
it. We further share a deep concern for the maintenance of peace<br />
and security in the Asian-Pacific region.<br />
The maintenance of a stable balance between the great powers is of<br />
critical importance to both of us. This is, in fact, a concern that<br />
we share with all those concerned for the maintenance of peace and<br />
stability. Both of us have fundamental alliances across the Pacific, with the<br />
United States of America.<br />
Apart from our own efforts, it is to these alliances more thananything<br />
else, that we look as a protection for our security.<br />
We therefore have a common interest in ensuring America's continued<br />
interest in and commitment to the West Pacific.<br />
This is not just a selfish interest. It is based on a recognition<br />
that a convincing American presence is the key element in the<br />
maintenance of peace and stability in the region as a whole.<br />
When it seemed that the American presence in Asia could be taken<br />
for granted it was subject to much hostile criticism much of it<br />
from outside the region. Now that it is less certain, its value<br />
is much more widely realised.<br />
Now, those countries which place a high value on their American<br />
alliances should both make this clear and act in ways which will<br />
encourage a continuing American participation.<br />
While there are inevitable difficulties from time to time in<br />
relating to a country as powerful as the United States, these<br />
should always be seen in the context of the long term importance<br />
of this participation.<br />
Australia will be doing what it can to facilitate the performance<br />
by the United States of the role which only the world's greatest<br />
free power can play.<br />
China also has a key part to play in the stability of the region.<br />
During my visit to Peking, I shall be concerned to see how China<br />
perceives her role.<br />
Australia shares with Japan, a concern for stability in the Indian<br />
ocean. Trade links vital to both of us pass through this Ocean.<br />
The Australian Government has supported the development by the<br />
United States of logistic facilities at Diego Garcia because we<br />
believe that stability in the area requires a balance which these<br />
facilities will help to maintain. 3/ </p>
<p>It is, of course, our strong hope that the superpowers will not<br />
embark on unrestricted competition in the Indian Ocean, but rather<br />
that the balance can be maintained there at a relatively low level.<br />
The Australian Government is fully aware that in North East Asia<br />
Japan is necessarily involved in one of the most complex and<br />
difficult international situations which exists today. A<br />
situation involving four of the great powers and a bitterly<br />
divided country. A situation which requires the utmost delicacy<br />
and patience, and in which there are no easy options.<br />
In this context we welcome the Japanese Government's ratification<br />
of the Non-Proliferation Treaty. We recognise what was involved<br />
in deciding to remain the only one of the four major powers in the<br />
region to forego nuclear weapons.<br />
In a world threatened by nuclear proliferation it sets a courageous<br />
example. The region in which the interests of Japan and Australia come<br />
closest together is South East Asia. For you this region is<br />
obviously important in terms of trade and investment, and also<br />
because some of your most important trade routes pass through it.<br />
For us, it also has great strategic, political and economic<br />
importance. Australia will be seeking to establish as broad relations as possible<br />
with the countries of South East Asia. We want to identify and<br />
develop further areas of practical cooperation on shared political<br />
and strategic interests. Mutual non-interference between states and<br />
a commitment to the peaceful resolution of differences is of course,<br />
essential to the peaceful development of the region.<br />
It would not, we believe, be in the interests of the region's<br />
0 peaceful development for mutually exclusive groupings to develop<br />
which could foster antagonism at the expense of social and economic<br />
development. Australia stands ready to explore with the new Governments in<br />
Indo-China, the development of relations of mutual benefit.<br />
But I would suggest that for both our countries South East Asia has<br />
an importance which transcends all these considerations. The<br />
countries of this region have a claim on us in human and moral<br />
terms. We, in our relations with them have our most serious<br />
opportunity to show our capacity to be good and responsible citizens<br />
in our part of the world.<br />
Let me be quite clear about this. What is involved is not merely<br />
a matter of giving material aid. Nor is it a matter of Australia<br />
and Japan getting together to work out some schemes of assistance.<br />
The countries of South East Asia would rightly scorn such an<br />
approach. They are proud and resilient countries who value<br />
independence above everything.<br />
The thing which they value most is the respect which is rightfully<br />
theirs. In terms of assistance, there must be full and adequate<br />
consultation. 4/ </p>
<p>-4-<br />
Japan was the country which first successfully overcame the<br />
problem of moving very rapidly from a traditional to a modern<br />
society. It must have much to offer others who are following<br />
the same path.<br />
These obligations are not, of course, peculiar to Japan and<br />
Australia. They are obligations on all the developed countries<br />
which have been involved in South East Asia. And our two<br />
countries, as two of the world's great trading nations have interests<br />
and responsibilities which extend far beyond the region.<br />
This is particularly true of your country. A country with the<br />
economic dynamism and the social energy of Japan has the opportunity<br />
to play an equivalent political role in the international sphere.<br />
This is particularly true when international relations are dominated<br />
by economic issues. Economic issues which not only vitally affect<br />
you but on which you are singularly well equipped to contribute.<br />
In the last twenty-five years, Japan has astonished the world with<br />
the fastest economic expansion in human history, with its output<br />
growing at an annual average of 10%. The qualities that made<br />
this possible are ones which can make an immeasurable contribution<br />
to the peace and prosperity of the world during the remaining<br />
twenty-five years of this century, should you so determine.<br />
Giventhe similarity of our independent objectives it is clear that<br />
the further development of the relations between us, foreshadowed<br />
in the Basic Treaty, can be of great benefit to all countries of<br />
that region.<br />
The prosperity of both countries is secured the more our relationship<br />
develops, and out of that prosperity comes a greater capacity to<br />
help in our own ways the developing countries of the region.<br />
Ours must be an outward looking relationship, conscious of the<br />
responsibilities we have to the developing nations.<br />
How we co-operate together over the coming years will depend to a<br />
considerable extent on how well we understand each other and can<br />
empathise with each other. This will depend on how well we<br />
understand each other's cultures.<br />
It is unfortunately true that cultural relations are sometimes<br />
treated by politicans as not quite a serious matter, not quite as<br />
serious as, say trade and technology.<br />
This is a profound mistake. For two peoples as different in their<br />
heritage as our two peoples are, a deepening of relationships will<br />
ultimately be dependent on a further understanding of each other's<br />
cultures. It will require an extension of opportunities to meet<br />
in circumstances which promote such understanding.<br />
Unfortunately, even when Australians and Japanese see each other<br />
there is often no real meeting of minds. They Pee each other from<br />
behind the tinted windows of tourist buses, or within the security </p>
<p>of groups of their fellow countrymen, or in the formal conditions<br />
of conferences.<br />
This is a state of affairs which we are concerned to see change.<br />
Trhe signature in 1974 of the Australia-Japan Cultural Agreement<br />
was a valuable step towards the promotion of mutual understanding<br />
through cultural exchange. The establishment this year by my<br />
Government of the Australia-Japan Foundation will be a further<br />
significant step, as will also the opening of an office of the<br />
Japan Foundation in Sydney.<br />
The effects of these and similar measures will not be immediate<br />
or dramatic, but we beleive that in the long run they will be<br />
real and significant.<br />
I would like to turn now to say something about the discussions<br />
your Government and we have had in the last few days.<br />
These discussions have covered the whole range of our relationships.<br />
They have been the kind of discussions which two countries as<br />
closely linked as ours ought to have.<br />
One of the most striking aspects of these discussions has been the<br />
accord we have found between the two Governments on all fundamental<br />
matters. In Foreign Affairs I have found that the perceptions<br />
we have of the world are similar. obviously geography Japan<br />
in the north, Australia in the south gives us different emphases<br />
and at times differing immediate concerns. But in our broader<br />
understanding of reality there are marked similarities.<br />
In Trade as your Prime Minister has impressed on me there is a<br />
great responsibility on the developed nations. We agreed on the<br />
desirability of a reduction in trading barriers for the well-being<br />
of the international economy.<br />
We agreed that stability of trade is of great importance and that<br />
trading difficulties can be overcome by sensible discussion -and<br />
restraint between trading partners who have much to gain through<br />
co-operation.<br />
In the past there have been some disruptions in both directions;<br />
actions we have taken to protect our industries<br />
have restricted Japanese manufacturers' access to our<br />
markets. the policies we have now developed in relations to<br />
Nissan and Toyota have been welcomed by Japan and by<br />
the companies concerned.<br />
we in our turn have welcomed the re-opening of your<br />
markets for beef.<br />
I have emphasised that where difficulties arise there should be a<br />
shared responsibility to overcome them.<br />
* In relations such as ours, within the spirit of the<br />
Treaty, stability of Trade requires that markets should<br />
not be unduly disturbed or utterly denied. / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
There should be a sharing of the burdens, so that neither the<br />
producers of one country nor the consumers of the other are<br />
unduly disrupted.<br />
I have indicated also that we welcome Japanese investment. Historically<br />
investment in Australia has come from other sources. Change is<br />
inevitable. Japanese investment will help to secure stability of<br />
supply: participation in joint ventures will help provide certainty<br />
of market access.<br />
Throughout the discussions I have emphasised our determination<br />
to be a reliable supplier of those materials necessary for your<br />
factories for your prosperity.<br />
I have stressed the need for our industries to achieve proper<br />
commercial results through commercial negotiations. I have<br />
indicated that it is only in exceptional circumstances that<br />
SGovernment intervention would be necessary. I am impressed by the<br />
way Japan is conquering her economic problems. Australia too<br />
has been tackling similar problems with vigor in recent months,<br />
and we too, are making progress.<br />
There are still many matters which Ministers and Officials will<br />
be pursuing in greater detail. One of these will be a review<br />
of the Commerce Agreement.<br />
Our discussions have shown that the treaty we have just signed<br />
indeed reflects and reinforces a developing relationship of<br />
benefit to us both.<br />
I look forward to seeing Japan and Australia extend their links<br />
in future years. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
