<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7465</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007465.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F M. S; FKE55 OFFICE CRN TEL: 0I-OOZ-T-Z533<br />
1 PRIME MINISTER<br />
26B 0 E PROOF ONLY9<br />
HE&amp; O0E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think jakmfien it.-an<br />
for the F -aswllF as the M 1<br />
PM: No. It's no embarrassment for the Federal Government<br />
at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does the result of the<br />
PM: No. The date for the West Australian election has<br />
already been fixed.<br />
JOURNALIST! But does the result of the West Australian<br />
election rather<br />
PM: Effect what we' ll do federally? Is that the . question?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM; No,<br />
JOURNALIST: Not at all?<br />
PM: No is no.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you c * BBBO imply on behalf of<br />
Mr Dowding here or making some attempt to get things<br />
ready for the federal trail as well?<br />
PM: No. It's a State election campaign.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think WA Ino is the most important<br />
Issue here? You've spoken to a few voters today.<br />
PM: No of course not.<br />
JOURNALIST: What have people like the Shopping Centre<br />
people been speaking to you about? 2T, 01,83 10: 45 NO. 0035 F. 01 </p>
<p>r. M. s RKE35 OFFICE CRMB TEL; Oi-OOZ-TZ3Z23<br />
PM;: No-one's mentioned it to me.<br />
JOURNALIST: This is however one of the most marginal<br />
seats in the electorate. Was that deliberately chosen?<br />
PM: No. When I arrive in a State, whether it's Western<br />
Australia or any State, T put,_ myelf in the hands of<br />
the State Secretary and the campaign committee. They<br />
asked me to come here. So like the good loyal servant<br />
I come and do what I'm asked to do.<br />
JOURNALIST: And whpeplS hE nP<br />
, Sh^ a * tz ti isevening concerned with? What were<br />
they t-lking to you about?<br />
PM: They seemed very happy. I mean they were all saying<br />
that Mr Dowding's going to get back, and of course he<br />
deserves to. You mentioned WA Inc. Now it would<br />
obviouqly be silly to say that it's not an issue. It<br />
is to some extent. But the people of Western Australia<br />
are sensible. They know that under this Government,<br />
in co-operation with mine, you've had in the areas that<br />
matter magnificent achievements. The employment<br />
performance of this Government is virtually the best<br />
in Australia, it's next to Victoria and above the<br />
Australian average. They've created more Jobs and lesser<br />
unemployment levels in terms of State and Counlcil charges..<br />
very much less than the Australian average. He's kept<br />
those charges down. In the fied ucation and health<br />
the g t a. -3ve~ n -tfiisi m agnificent.<br />
Now these are the sorts of things that determine the<br />
welfare of the people in electorates like this. Those<br />
are the things that'll make their minds up. They've<br />
got the alternative of Mr Dowding who is an obvious leader<br />
with the full support of his team and his Party against<br />
a squabbling, policyless, negative Opposition. There's<br />
only one choice.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you give voters here any assurance that<br />
Tiii hard-pressed home owners, that interest<br />
SraTer ghis year?<br />
PM: They'll go down this year.<br />
ends ZT, 01,9 10: 45 N0.003 F. 02 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
