<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>974</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, K.T., C.H., Q.C., M.P., ON INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/08/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000974.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
Rt. Hon. SIR ROBERT MENZIES,<br />
M. P.,<br />
ON<br />
9INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS.<br />
( From the " Parliamentary Debates 13.8.64.]<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES ( Kooyong-<br />
Prime Minister) [ 11 propose to sacy<br />
something at, perhaps, some little length<br />
about the events in and around Vietnam,<br />
but before I do so, I think I should make<br />
a reference to one or two points that have<br />
been made by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
( Mr. Calwell). I think the honorable gentleman<br />
has almost a fixation about me. I<br />
appear to pop up like King Charles' head in<br />
all his speeches. I can understand that. But<br />
.' jNoyI just make a reference to what the<br />
~ nrable gentleman said about my alleged<br />
views on summit conferences? It is quite<br />
true that I made a speech in New York.<br />
It was a lunchtime speech and if anybody<br />
reDgdarod s soth. at as riotous living, he is welcome<br />
Mr. Peters-It depends on the lunch.<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-You do not<br />
get much if you are going to make a<br />
speech. What I was putting to that audience<br />
in New York was that there was no virtue,<br />
in itself, in having a summit meeting. A<br />
necessary condition of a summit meeting<br />
was that people on both sides--or on three<br />
sides in this case-should approach the<br />
matter in good faith and with a genuine<br />
desire to arrive at a settlement. I made the<br />
point that if one side-as in this casewent<br />
through the motions of saying: " Yes,<br />
10256/ 64. we will have a summit meeting and while<br />
the meeting was actually on, weakened the<br />
position of the other negotiators by military<br />
action-and that is the position along the<br />
frontiers of Borneo-then that is not a<br />
genuine summit meeting at all. it would be<br />
a dangerous kind of meeting to ' have<br />
because, by its implicit concession to force,<br />
it would * be a form of appeasement. That<br />
is what I said in New York, and if the<br />
Leader of the Opposition disagrees with<br />
that, he is welcome to do so. I certainly<br />
have ho apologies to make for those views.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition then said<br />
something of the usual kind to the effect<br />
that instead of talking in military terms, we<br />
ought to be increasing the aid we give to<br />
under-developed countries. It is very interesting<br />
' to, recall that we have two underdeveloped<br />
countries in our immediate<br />
neighbourhood and for which we have an<br />
immediate responsibility-Papua and New<br />
Guinea. If you take our net expenditure<br />
there-because we get no exploitation of<br />
these territories-and what we pay through<br />
the Colombo Plan and the aid of an economic<br />
kind ' that we give under the South<br />
East Asia Treaty Organisation agreement<br />
in all its various forms and through certain<br />
specialised agencies of the United Nations,<br />
you find that Australia today is providing<br />
the equivalent of 100 million American AUG m4G~ </p>
<p>dollars a year for these purposes. In anybody's<br />
language-and certainly in minethat<br />
is a very substantial sum of money.<br />
Therefore I put these facts on the -record<br />
because I would not have it believed that<br />
this country is falling down in its human<br />
responsibilities. I propose to say something now about<br />
Cyprus. I will not speak at any great length<br />
on this subject because it is more a matter<br />
of giving some information to the House.<br />
I propose, then, to address myself to the<br />
nub of this matter-the argument that goes<br />
on about Vietnam and our relations to it<br />
and the activities of certain small Australian<br />
forces in South Vietnam. The Republic of<br />
Cyprus-I want to get this matter out of the<br />
way first-was established as an independent<br />
state in 1960 following negotiations between<br />
the Greek and Turkish Prime Ministers. As<br />
honorable members know, the outcome of<br />
those negotiations was accepted by Great<br />
Britain. The settlement brought an endor<br />
so it was believed-to a long-drawn stalemate<br />
which had been caused by the preceding<br />
Greek Cypriot campaign for Enosis,<br />
or union with Greece, in the face of Turkish<br />
refusal to contemplate Cyprus falling into<br />
Greek hands and the consequent difficulties<br />
of Great Brtain as the governing or colonial<br />
power. The settlement made in 1960 provided<br />
for special constitutional safeguards. These<br />
were, in effect, a veto on certain legislation<br />
for the Turkish minority and for the right<br />
of the guarantor powers-Greece, Turkey<br />
and Great Britain-to intervene if the terms<br />
of the settlement were contravened.<br />
That settlement was received at the time<br />
with some hope. It has not worked out.<br />
In the opinion of the Prime Minister of<br />
Cyprus, Archbishop Makarios, the Constitution<br />
has failed. Disputes have arisen between<br />
the Turkish minority and the Greek<br />
Cypriot majority while Greece and Turkey,<br />
from the outside, have maintained,<br />
great interest, and from time to<br />
time, activity. These troubles began at the<br />
end of 1963 when Archbishop Makarios<br />
said the Constitution was unworkable.<br />
Attempts to settle the dispute were made,<br />
first, through the North Atlantic Treaty<br />
Organisation-because both Greece and<br />
Turkey belong to N. A. T. O.-and then when<br />
they failed, attempts at a settlement were<br />
made through the United Nations Organisation. Through the Security Council which<br />
acted on this matter, the United Nations<br />
arranged in March of this year for a United<br />
Nations force -to go to Cyprus to restore<br />
order. The United Nations also appointed<br />
a mediator and requests were made for<br />
certain financial assistance to which we<br />
made a small contribution. A request was<br />
also made for a police force for ordinary<br />
police purposes and Australia, through the<br />
courtesy of the various State Governments,<br />
has made a contribution to this force. The<br />
Security Council passed a series of resolutions<br />
concerning these arrangements on 4th<br />
March and 13th March and again on<br />
June of this year.<br />
In spite of these actions, the positio'&gt;<br />
has remained difficult and perhaps hat...'<br />
become more difficult. It is very hard<br />
to say that and I do not want to say<br />
anything which would appear to allocate<br />
any blame because I do not think it is for<br />
us to do that. I believe, as I am sure a'<br />
honorable members believe, that jiiL<br />
this complex affair-and it is immeasurably<br />
complex-it is important to stand<br />
behind the United Nations Security Council<br />
and to do all things possible or to encourage<br />
all things possible to be done to<br />
avoid civil war or a continuance of it and<br />
to bring about a peaceful settlement of the<br />
problem. This was the position when the Prime<br />
Ministers of the Commonwealth of Nations<br />
met in London. After considerable discussion,<br />
a statement on this matter w2-<br />
made in a communique and I quote froish..:<br />
it-The Prime Ministers expressed concern about<br />
the situation with regard to Cyprus. They reaffirmed<br />
their full support for the United Nations<br />
Security Council resolutions of 4th March,' 13t.-<br />
March and 20th June 1964. The Prime Ministel<br />
asserted that the Cyprus problem should be solvewithin<br />
the framework of the United Nations and<br />
in accordance with the principles of democracy<br />
and justice.<br />
They appealed to all countries concerned to<br />
refrain from any action which might undermine<br />
the task of the United Nations peacekeeping<br />
force to which a number of Commonwealth countries<br />
are contributing, or might prejudice the endeavours<br />
of the United Nations to find a lasting<br />
solution in conformity with the Charter of the<br />
United Nations.<br />
T his, I venture to say, was impeccably<br />
correct. The United Nations Security Council<br />
met again in emergency session, things<br />
not having improved very much, on Sunday<br />
last. The President appealed to the Turkish </p>
<p>and Cypriot Governments to cease hostilities.<br />
Now a resolution has again been passed.<br />
I was going to read it in its full terms, but<br />
it can be summarised by saying that it calls<br />
for an immediate cease fire by all parties,<br />
it calls for their co-operation with the United<br />
Nations peace keeping force and it calls<br />
upon all States to refrain from any action<br />
which could exacerbate the position. I think<br />
it will be agreed by all honorable members<br />
that we will not help a settlement of this<br />
extremely difficult matter by offering observations<br />
from the sidelines or by taking<br />
sides, because without a great deal more<br />
knowledge than any of us can have it might<br />
be very difficult to apportion all the blame<br />
one party and none of it to the other.<br />
all want a peaceful settlement, and the<br />
greatest prospect of that settlement will<br />
come from backing the actions of the<br />
Security Council.<br />
Now I would like to turn to the matter<br />
ich was the subject of the original state-<br />
-nent by my colleague, which has given rise<br />
to most of the debate, both outside the<br />
House and in it. My colleague's statement<br />
was a clear and objective one. It did not<br />
go in for fireworks. It put the House in<br />
possession of whatever official knowledge<br />
we had of these matters. I therefore do not<br />
need to repeat what he said. If it is any<br />
comfort to anybody to know it, I can say<br />
that before he made his statement he discussed<br />
the matter with me and we agreed<br />
that he was the appropriate Minister to<br />
ake the statement. So he made it.<br />
The Australian Government thoughf that<br />
the action of the United States of America,<br />
under attack in the Gulf of Tonkin, under<br />
attack in international waters, was well<br />
,-warranted and ought to be supported, and<br />
said so. Many people in different parts<br />
of the world said so. Oddly enough, I did<br />
not wait, as I am occasionally charged with<br />
waiting, to find out what the majority were<br />
doing. We were the first people to make a<br />
public announcement after the President's<br />
speech and after his indication of what he<br />
was going to do. Not for the first time, we<br />
were the first to speak. Does anybody seriously<br />
quarrel with what the President did?<br />
I almost pause for a reply, because the<br />
O) position, as I will show without any difficultv,<br />
has occupied the most ambiguous<br />
position on this point. It is a bitterly disappointing<br />
fact that the one sour note that<br />
reached the public print should have come from the Leader of the Australian Labour<br />
Party, the great alternative governing party<br />
in this country, accompanied by a sort of<br />
lecture to the President on his duty not to<br />
extend the struggle and to see that he had<br />
resort to the United Nations-he having<br />
publicly stated that he wanted no such<br />
extension and that he would seek such<br />
resort, and having acted accordingly.<br />
It is just as well, I think, to recall what<br />
the President said. My colleague quoted the<br />
language of the resolution of Congress, and<br />
I want to quote from the text of the President's<br />
nation-wide statement which preceded<br />
that resolution. After referring to the attack<br />
and the orders he had given, he said-<br />
This new act of agression aimed directly at our<br />
own forces again brings home to all of us in the<br />
United States the importance of the struggle for<br />
peace and security in South East Asia. Aggression<br />
by terror against the peaceful villagers of South<br />
Vietnam has now been joined by open aggression<br />
on the high seas against the United States of<br />
America. The determination of all Americans to<br />
carry out our full commitment to the people and<br />
Government of South Vietnam will be redoubled<br />
by this outrage.<br />
Without anticipating in detail what I will say<br />
a little later, it will be observed that the<br />
President referred to " our commitment to<br />
the people and Government of South<br />
Vietnam", which does not arise from a<br />
treaty. He has no treaty with South<br />
Vietnam. I will explain a little later, if it<br />
needs -to be explained, how these things arise<br />
and flow from the South East Asia Treaty,<br />
but it is worthwhile just reminding honorable<br />
members opposite the America does not<br />
feel it necessary to talk about a formal<br />
treaty before going to the aid of South<br />
Vietnam, and that America recognises a<br />
commitment that has not been drafted by<br />
a lawyer. This is a very important statement.<br />
Then the President went on-<br />
Yet our response for the present will be limited<br />
and fitting. We Americans know, though others<br />
appear to forget, the risks of spreading a conflict.<br />
We will seek no wider war.<br />
Then he went on to say-<br />
; I have instructed Ambassador Stevenson to<br />
raise this matter immediately and urgently before<br />
the Security Council of the United Nations.<br />
He ended by saying-<br />
It is a solemn responsibility to have to order<br />
even limited military action by forces whose overall<br />
strength is as vast and as awesome as those of<br />
the United States, but it is my considered conviction,<br />
shared throughout your Government, that<br />
firmness in the right is indispensible today for<br />
peace. That firmness will always be measured. Its<br />
mission is peace. </p>
<p>I venture to say that that was an historic<br />
and important statement, and it was followed<br />
by a resolution in Congress which<br />
was carried in one House with one dissentient<br />
vote and in the other House unanimously.<br />
I propose to refer to that resolution,<br />
which my colleague read to the House<br />
earlier. I believe that the resolution has no<br />
direct precedent in American history. We<br />
are living in a most historic period. I will<br />
quote just the operative passages of the<br />
resolution, if I may do so without wearying<br />
the House-<br />
The U. S. regards as vital to its national security<br />
and to world peace the maintenance of international<br />
peace and security in South East Asia.<br />
This is the American Congress speaking.<br />
Now, Sir, if I may interrupt the reading of<br />
the resolution, if we cast our minds back,<br />
particularly those of us who have been<br />
seised of the responsibilities for the Government<br />
here, we will remember very vividly<br />
how anxious we were only a few years ago<br />
about the possibility that in the conflict of<br />
ideas between the Western powers and the<br />
Soviet Union, and in the building up of the<br />
nuclear deterrent to armed hostilities in that<br />
connection, South East Asia might be overlooked.<br />
There was a very strong feeling at<br />
one time that perhaps it was a little in the<br />
background. The answer to that anxiety is<br />
in the passage I have just read.<br />
In all my discussions with the late President<br />
Kennedy and with President Johnson<br />
and with the Administration of the State<br />
Department 1 felt there was a growing<br />
realisation of the importance of South East<br />
Asia. This was a matter of some satisfaction<br />
to us because although we knew all too well<br />
the vital significance of the relationships<br />
across the Atlantic, we also felt that the<br />
problems of South East Asia came very near<br />
home and that our immediate security in<br />
Australia was much involved in them.<br />
Therefore, I repeat that this resolution by<br />
Congress is of historic importance. The<br />
resolution continued-<br />
Consonant with the Constitution and the Charter<br />
of the United Nations and in accordance with<br />
its obligations under the South East Asia Collective<br />
Defence Treaty, the United States is therefore<br />
prepared as the President determines to take all<br />
necessary steps, including the use of armed force,<br />
to assist any member or protocol State of the<br />
South East Asia Collective Defence Treaty requesting<br />
assistance in defence of its freedom.<br />
In this resolution we see the constitutional<br />
process referred to in the A. N. Z. U. S. Pact and in the South East Asia Collective Defence<br />
Treaty at work affirming the power<br />
of the President to take action as commander-<br />
in-chief. The importance of this cannot<br />
be overlooked by any Australian unless he is<br />
bemused by academic and unreal ideas.<br />
After all, the matter of substance -is the<br />
defence of freedom in South East Asia. I<br />
would sum this up by saying that the congressional<br />
resolution removes constitutional<br />
restraint on the President's freedom of<br />
action. Of course, -he still remains subject to<br />
the practical restraints which arise from his<br />
need to have in Congress broad support for<br />
whatever he does. But the important thing<br />
is that the resolution has affirmed that the<br />
. maintenance of peace and security in tl'-. V<br />
region-this region immediately adjoins _ j'<br />
-is in the vital interests of the United<br />
States. We would indeed be blind, Sir, if<br />
we did not realize and acknowledge that it<br />
is also in our vital interests.<br />
The South East Asia Collective Defenr<br />
Treaty ought to be referred to. I shoul,-'<br />
have expected its provisions, in the broad,<br />
to be very well known and not matters<br />
which needed to be recited every week,<br />
every year, or once in any other period of<br />
time. However, I think I should mention<br />
them, because they have been overlooked<br />
by some of the spokesmen opposite. The<br />
Treaty was made in September 1954 and<br />
was ratified early in 1955. It was negotiated<br />
on behalf of Australia by my Government.<br />
The parties to it were the United States, the<br />
United Kingdom, Thailand, the Philippines<br />
Pakistan, France, Australia and Ne/<br />
Zealand. The Treaty -itself paid proper<br />
attention to the promotion of the economic<br />
wellbeing and development of all peoples in<br />
the Treaty area. If honorable members care<br />
to look at Article IM, they will find that thiidea<br />
of economic advancement is not<br />
and has not been suddenly discovered by the<br />
Opposition. Mr. Uren.-Name it. It is only peanuts.<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-It has been<br />
of substantial assistance. It reads-<br />
The Parties undertake to strengthen their free<br />
institutions and to co-operate with one another in<br />
the further development of economic measures, including<br />
technical assistance, designed both to promote<br />
economic progress and social wellbeing<br />
and to further the individual and collective efforts<br />
of governments towards these ends.<br />
The parties to the Treaty were well aware<br />
of these points. The Treaty acknowledges<br />
that one of the facts of life was that unless </p>
<p>there was resistance to Communist aggression<br />
there would be no opportunity for<br />
economic advancement, peaceful life and<br />
peaceful development. Article II reads-<br />
In order more effectively to achieve the objectives<br />
of this Treaty, the Parties, separately and<br />
jointly-In other words, there is a joint and several<br />
obligation; it is not necessary to have a<br />
unanimous decision to discharge the obligationby<br />
means of continuous and effective self help and<br />
mutual aid will maintain and develop their individual<br />
and collective capacity to resist armed attack<br />
and to prevent the counter subversive activities<br />
directed from without against their territorial<br />
integrity and political stability.<br />
) ticle IV reads-<br />
1. Each Party recognises that aggression by<br />
means of armed attack in the treaty area against<br />
any of the Parties or against any State or<br />
territory which the Parties by unanimous agreement<br />
may hereafter designate-<br />
-lat is, the protocol States, including South<br />
,_ etnamwould endanger its own peace and safety, and<br />
agrees that it will in that event act to meet the<br />
common danger in accordance with its constitutional<br />
processes. Measures taken under this paragraph<br />
shall be immediately reported to the Security<br />
Council of the United Nations.<br />
As I have just indicated, the Treaty provided<br />
for the designation by unanimous vote<br />
of nations as protocol State South Vietnam,<br />
like Laos and Cambodia, is one of the<br />
protocol States.<br />
The Treaty contemplated, therefore, that<br />
protocol States might have to be<br />
J.; fended against aggression. It stated with<br />
particularity-It is understood that no action on the territory<br />
of any State designated by unanimous agreement<br />
shall be taken except at the invitation or with<br />
consent of the government concerned.<br />
., are in South Vietnam to the extent that<br />
we are ' there by the invitation of the Government<br />
of that country. The U. S. A. is there<br />
by the invitation of the Government of<br />
South Vietnam. We have no subsequent<br />
treaty with the protocol State; neither ' has<br />
the U. S. It is very disturbing, to say the<br />
least, that the Australian Labour Party<br />
should choose this period in international<br />
history to assert 1ihat Australia, which is<br />
acting at the request of South Vietnam,<br />
should not do so without some new and<br />
special treaty with the Government of South<br />
Vietnam. What a b-. arren performance that<br />
would ' be of the obligations of the South East Asian Collective Defence Treaty. The<br />
Leader of the Opposition said that people<br />
had not been sufficiently informed. I should<br />
have'thought that these matters were almost<br />
as familiar in the minds of people as anything<br />
could be. They have been referred to<br />
very frequently. I remind the House that<br />
extensive statements about our activities in<br />
South Vietnam have been made at the time<br />
of each performance on our part-first, by<br />
the late Mr. Townley when he was Minister<br />
for Defence, and later by Senator Paltridge<br />
as Minister for Defence.<br />
I am sorry if I seem to overdo it, but<br />
the point I want to make is that what is<br />
going on in South Vietnam through us in a<br />
small way, and through the U. S. in a large<br />
way, is the direct consequence of a treaty<br />
to which we are one of the parties. As a<br />
matter of fact, in 1961 South Vietnam<br />
appealed to the U. S. to increase military<br />
aid because of the violation of its territory<br />
in the north and the U. S. responded, but<br />
without a military alliance and without a<br />
treaty. It is interesting to recall that the<br />
Opposition-the Leader of the Opposition<br />
repeated the claim this morning-has long<br />
made it a matter of pride that when in<br />
government it invited U. S. forces to come<br />
here during the war. Did it make a treaty?<br />
Did the United States require a treaty? Did<br />
Australia require a treaty? No, because the<br />
realities of life were so overwhelmingly clear<br />
that this poor academic nonsense about<br />
having a treaty was never even thought of.<br />
But today we are told that -this is exactly<br />
what ought to be done.<br />
I have already taken quite a long time,<br />
but I just want to mention one or two<br />
other aspects of this matter quite briefly. I<br />
notice that the Opposition, including the<br />
Federal Executive of the Australian Labour<br />
Party, is saying that the right way to<br />
handle this matter is to reconstitute the<br />
Geneva Conference. Of course, the Geneva<br />
Conference established the cease fire and<br />
the ' boundary at the 17th parallel, and declared<br />
for a cessation of armed hostilities.<br />
What is it to be reconvened for? The<br />
Leader of the Opposition said the other<br />
day that the powers should meet to resu<br />
bscribe to and honour the agreements.<br />
But who has broken the agreements?<br />
Is it suggested that somebody not in the<br />
Communist zone is conducting a war of<br />
aggression? Does anybody think such nonsense<br />
for a moment? The -people who are </p>
<p>violating the cease fire and the essential<br />
substance of the Geneva accords are the<br />
people from the north, the north Vietnam<br />
forces, the Vietminh, backed as they<br />
unquestionably are at suitable times by the<br />
Communist Chinese, and having as their<br />
agents the Vietcong in their pockets of<br />
activity around South Vietnam. If there is<br />
any reaffirmation of belief in a cease fire to<br />
be made, it ought to be made by the people<br />
who are violating the agreements. The<br />
powers may, for all I know, have another<br />
conference in Geneva or elsewhere, and it<br />
will be a very good thing if a precondition<br />
is that there is a cessation of hostilities,<br />
a termination of these guerrilla activities,<br />
because, for the reasons I mentioned at<br />
the beginning of my speech, I believe<br />
firmly that good faith is an essential to<br />
any conference that may be called.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition has a<br />
general view which he puts. He appears to<br />
think that Australia is unnecessarily buying<br />
hostility with the Asian people. He is<br />
always fond of trying to create some<br />
division between the past and the present in<br />
this Government. He says we are buying<br />
hostility. Does he really believe that we<br />
would cultivate the respect of the Asian<br />
people if, as I rather think he would like<br />
us to do, we abandoned our support of<br />
Malaysia, which is vigorous in all respects,<br />
or if we said to South Vietnam and to the<br />
South East Asian Treaty countries that we<br />
were quite happy to have an agreement with<br />
them but that -we were very reluctant to<br />
perform an agreement? Is this the way to<br />
acquire the respect of our Asian neighbours?<br />
Sir, international goodwill is not to<br />
be firmly established on a basis of a denial<br />
of treaty obligations or a denial of the<br />
overall importance of resisting Communist<br />
aggression. But the Leader of the Opposition is not<br />
the only spokesman for the Labour Party.<br />
I think I have some right to expect that his<br />
most prominent colleague in the victory of<br />
the left wing in Victoria recently, a person<br />
whom I might describe as his running mate<br />
-the honorable member for Yarra ( Dr.<br />
J. F. Cairns)-a prospective deputy leader<br />
at least speaks with some authority on behalf<br />
of the Labour Party. If he does not,<br />
then the party has a curious way of disowning<br />
him. On 9th August, the honorable<br />
member for Yarra made a powerful speech, I gather, to 2,000 people at a<br />
Hiroshima commemoration rally in Sydney.<br />
He had, of course, an audience<br />
of people who advocated nuclear disarmament,<br />
ignoring the fact that if nuclear<br />
disarmament proceeded alone, the<br />
Communist powers would have overwhelming<br />
military strength. These people<br />
also apparently carried slogans about<br />
no war in Vietnam, a consummation<br />
devoutly to be wished for, I must say. But<br />
the pleas ought to be addressed not to our<br />
side, but to the other side if they are to<br />
have any true value.<br />
The honorable member for Yarra is<br />
reported, I hope accurately, as having said<br />
that Australia should not follow the Uni,,<br />
States line-of course, we have heard hn..<br />
say that many times-which he defined as<br />
pursuing a policy of war which had no basis<br />
in morals or justice. He was not talking<br />
about some war of the 19th century; he wasx<br />
talking about these incidents that have b7_)<br />
engaging our attention; he was talking about<br />
these activities of war in the Gulf of Tonkin<br />
and, by the way of counter attack, on the<br />
shores of North Vietnam.<br />
I ' have reminded the House, and, I hope,<br />
the people, of what the President of the<br />
United States said, and the manner in which<br />
he dealt with the matter and the manner in<br />
which Congress dealt with it-the high<br />
level on which the whole thing was put and<br />
the immense importance of it to the future<br />
of this country-yet a prospective leader of<br />
this country is heard to say that they Ei')<br />
pursuing a policy of war which has no bas-"<br />
in morals or justice.<br />
If that is not the view of the Oppositionand<br />
I do not believe for one moment that<br />
it can be-then I hope there will be tho---<br />
who will be willing to say so in their<br />
It was really an extraordinary summary<br />
of American policy. It is apparently both<br />
moral and just that aggressive Communist<br />
powers should seek to strike down free<br />
people but immoral and unjust to resist<br />
them. The honorable member for Yarra<br />
went on to say, according to the report, that<br />
the United States could not claim that it<br />
was being attacked in the present Vietnam<br />
crisis-I think the crews of the American<br />
destroyers would be fascinated to know that<br />
-or that it was acting in self-defence. He<br />
says that the United States cannot say that.<br />
The U. S. has said it. The honorable member<br />
for Yarra is challenging the veracity of </p>
<p>the head of the American Administration.<br />
He is challenging the intelligence and information<br />
of the entire Congress of the United<br />
States which has every avenue of inf ormation<br />
available to it.<br />
The honorable member for Yarra elaborated<br />
this astonishing proposition by saying<br />
that the North Vietnamese torpedo boats<br />
-I like that, because it admits that they<br />
were North Vi etnamese-had been within<br />
a few miles of their own shores when they<br />
came in to attack the United States ships.<br />
Does he really deny that they were 30<br />
miles off shore, as has been stated authoritatively<br />
in America?<br />
1d. Pollard.-Do the Americans deny<br />
Cuba? Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-The honorable<br />
member for Lalor ( Mr. Pollard) has<br />
a singular talent for changing the subject,<br />
I sympathise with him. If the honoremember<br />
wants now to set up another<br />
attack on the United States over Cuba,<br />
over what I thought was a remarkable<br />
effort on behalf of freedom by the late<br />
President Kennedy, let him say so. If we<br />
are to have a symposium of hatred and<br />
criticism of the United States, let us have<br />
it. At least we will know then where the<br />
Opposition stands. But to resume what I<br />
was saying: Is it really denied that the<br />
American destroyers were 30 miles offshore?<br />
Does the honorable member for Yarra or<br />
I~ body else assert that the warships of<br />
: 1,) nation when steaming in international<br />
waters may be attacked with impunity?<br />
The honorable member went on to<br />
charge the United States with helping to<br />
. prevent political, economic and social<br />
&gt; hnges in South Vietnam. This, of course,<br />
. a monstrous falsehood. But he ended<br />
up by saying that Australia should call<br />
immediately for a ceasefire in Vietnam,'<br />
to be followed by talks between all countries<br />
involved in the conflict. He is unaware,<br />
presumably, that the President of the<br />
United States has already put all these<br />
courses of action in train. We, Sir, do not<br />
direct ceasefires. This is not our function.<br />
The honorable member overlooks the<br />
obvious fact that no country has a greater<br />
interest than we have in the cessation of<br />
armed hostilities in South East Asia, provided<br />
that that cessation does not yield the<br />
field to the onward sweep of Communism. The honorable member also overlooks<br />
the fact that President Johnson himself took<br />
the earliest opportunity to encourage action<br />
by the Security Council. I have already<br />
referred to what the President said in his<br />
Address to the Nation. We in Australia are<br />
in a position in the world in which we have,<br />
no doubt, great opportunities, but equally,<br />
no, doubt, face great risks. The Opposition,<br />
in more recent days, has been rather fond<br />
of saying what we ought to be doing about<br />
defence. I do not resent any criticism in<br />
that field, because I do not regard our<br />
provision for defence as static. It must go<br />
on, develop and march with the times. The<br />
plea from the Opposition would be more<br />
eloquent if we had heard it over any considerable<br />
period of time. The fact is that<br />
we are, as the Treasurer ( Mr. Harold Holt)<br />
pointed out in the Budget Speech, spending<br />
50 per cent, more on defence than we were<br />
four years ago. And, as I say, that is not<br />
-the end of the story.<br />
I do not want to occu. py time on this, as<br />
it will no doubt be debated, as some one<br />
was suggesting earlier today; but let us suppose<br />
that the Opposition, being in office,<br />
spent much more on defence. Why would<br />
it do it? This is a question that the Opposition<br />
really should put to itself. Why would<br />
it do it? Would it do it because it thought<br />
that Australia's defence was -a matter for<br />
Austra-lia alone? Does it have that isolationist<br />
view? I could not believe that. Does<br />
it really believe that if we were attacked by<br />
a great power we could defend ourselves<br />
without allies and without mutual systems<br />
of defence? It could not believe such nonsense<br />
as that. Therefore, presumably, it<br />
would do it so that we might be in a position<br />
to make an effective contribution, worthy<br />
of us as a nation, to the common defence.<br />
But if we are to do that there must be some<br />
system of common defence. If we are to do<br />
that we really must have these alliances in<br />
substance with the people who have the<br />
greatest power to preserve freedom and<br />
who carry the major burden of its<br />
preservation. Surely the Labour Party must agree with<br />
that. If it does not, presumably it would<br />
never, if it had been in office, have tried to<br />
secure the A. N. Z. U. S. Pact or the South<br />
East Asia Treaty. But suppose it had<br />
entered into these pacts, and suppose it<br />
realised that the defence of Australia, and<br />
indeed of freedom generally, were a matter </p>
<p>of community of effort, of broad alliances<br />
with, to use the phrase that the honorable<br />
gentleman objects to so much, " great and<br />
powerful friends in the world Suppose it<br />
understood that. Are we really to understand<br />
that, having made those treaties, having<br />
done whatever it thought proper in the<br />
defence field, having perhaps more forces<br />
than we now have, it would have said in<br />
those circumstances, when Vietnam, a<br />
protocol country, asked for help: No. We<br />
are very sorry. We cannot give you help.<br />
We know that America is doing so. That is<br />
all right for America, but we cannot give<br />
you help unless you now sit down and<br />
thrash out a special mutual treaty with us."?<br />
I end there, because I referred to it earlier.<br />
This, to me, is the most fantastic evidence<br />
of the utterly unreal and utterly academic<br />
approach that these people have when they consider these great problems. When they<br />
did have the responsibility of government,<br />
when there were real things happening that<br />
they understood, they had no such<br />
approach. They did not talk about treaties<br />
then, but now they do. Now they want to<br />
put a clog in the operation of the machinery<br />
of the South East Asia Treaty. Why? Is it<br />
because they believe in the Treaty, or<br />
because at heart they do not believe in the<br />
Treaty? Or is it because, which seems most<br />
probable, they have such deep divisions of<br />
opinion between soberminded right wing<br />
members of the Labour Party Who, I will<br />
undertake to say, have agreed with almost<br />
everything I have said today, and a left wing<br />
which, in its heart, is not hostile to Cor~,<br />
munism but, in its heart, is deeply hosti._ j<br />
to the United States of America, the greatest<br />
free power in the world?<br />
BY AUTHORITY: A. J. ARTHUR, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
