<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18883</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech to the Ethnic Business Awards</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Sydney</p>
<p>CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY</p>
<p>We should never underestimate the boldness of the decision taken by Ben Chifley to open the doors to mass migration almost seven decades ago.</p>
<p>Yes, we had small ethnic communities like the Chinese who'd been attracted by the gold rush and the Italians who came to work in the canefields in the 1920s.</p>
<p>But overwhelmingly, we were a small, insular, homogenous community, and we were asked to embrace profound and lasting change.</p>
<p>Yet it worked.</p>
<p>Immigration worked.</p>
<p>And it worked because we made it work.</p>
<p>We accepted that our nation would never be defined by race or ethnicity like so many other countries.</p>
<p>Instead, we would define ourselves by our values and our way of life.</p>
<p>Our love of freedom and democracy.</p>
<p>Our egalitarian cast of mind and our relaxed outdoor lifestyle.</p>
<p>Our willingness to work hard and play fair.</p>
<p>And we said that anyone who embraced these things could be called an Australian.</p>
<p>Your admission ticket was your commitment.</p>
<p>The commitment to choose this place from all the world.</p>
<p>To serve it and fight for it, and to always call it home.</p>
<p>Friends,</p>
<p>That's the decision my parents made.</p>
<p>That's the decision you and your parents made around so many kitchen tables  -  in Sicily and Saigon, Beirut and Bangalore.</p>
<p>All those decisions converged, from the four points of the earth, upon this land  -  its future  -  and its possibilities.</p>
<p>In a sense, this is the story of two journeys. Our journey of post-war immigration and our journey of economic modernisation. And how they have intertwined across these extraordinary decades.</p>
<p>Australia was a great country before post-war migration.</p>
<p>But our migrants showed us a way to make it greater still.</p>
<p>Ethnic businesses are a big part of the story.</p>
<p>Your hard work and self-sacrifice are legendary, from the smallest corner store to the great enterprises founded by migrant pioneers like Westfield to business leaders like Ahmed Fahour at Australia Post.</p>
<p>And so many of you have invested time in building links between Australia and the countries from which you've come.</p>
<p>Today, the skills and connections of our ethnic businesses are more valuable than ever as the world's centre of economic gravity shifts our way: the transformation unprecedented in speed and scale, we call the ‘Asian Century'.</p>
<p>On Sunday I released a plan for our nation's future in the Asian Century. A plan for Australia to prosper and thrive in this age of unparalleled growth and change.</p>
<p>This is a century when innovators will flourish.</p>
<p>A century when Australia will be well served by its creative entrepreneurial culture and its vibrant multicultural society.</p>
<p>Our ethnic businesses are custodians of many of the capabilities we need to succeed: language skills; people to people links; knowledge of how business and government operates in Asian societies; and perhaps most importantly, helping to develop greater understanding of the diverse cultures of Asia among all Australians.</p>
<p>Since the first post-war migrants landed in Sydney in the summer of 1947, we learnt to value diversity as a source of strength for our society.</p>
<p>In more recent years, it has also become clear that diversity is a source of strength for our economy as well.</p>
<p>So in 2012, we can say with greater confidence than ever:</p>
<p>Post-war migration began as our nation's greatest experiment.</p>
<p>And it has become our nation's greatest success.</p>
<p>Because as migrants, we accepted that in a new land, we shouldn't only take but give as well.</p>
<p>And if the road was tougher because of our background, we would try all the harder to succeed.</p>
<p>Our parents didn't come here just because they sought jobs or prosperity. They come because they saw a country worth believing in.</p>
<p>A place so compelling they were willing to leave everything they knew and loved to be part of it.</p>
<p>And here on these bountiful shores, they would repay freedom and opportunity with effort and excellence.</p>
<p>The very effort and excellence represented in these awards, and in the remarkable men and women who receive them tonight.</p>
<p>On behalf of all Australians, I thank you for all that you have given to our country.</p>
<p>United in our diversity, and unafraid of the future, let us seize the opportunities of the Asian Century together.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
