<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22638</transcript-id>
    <title>Reforms to Boost ADF Recruitment and Retention  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce today $1 billion in new funding over the next 10 years for a series of initiatives to boost Australian Defence Force recruitment and retention.</p>
<p>Australia is exceptionally well served by our defence force, and I want to acknowledge the dedication and professionalism of our service men and women - many of whom are serving overseas - as we head into the Christmas season.</p>
<p>Developing and sustaining a highly capable defence force has been one of my Government's highest priorities. Accordingly, we have set the target of expanding the ADF from the current 51,000 full-time personnel to 57,000.</p>
<p>Australia's strong economy, record low unemployment and competitive labour market mean that to meet that target we have both to increase enlistment from around 4700 a year to around 6500 a year and reduce the current separation rate of around 11 per cent a year to below 10 per cent.</p>
<p>Major initiatives in this innovative and comprehensive package include:   Measures totalling $371 million over the next 10 years to streamline ADF recruiting by:  - reducing the time from enquiry to application and enlistment, and   - better aligning recruit entry standards with contemporary demographic and community realities - without compromising quality   A military gap year scheme worth $306 million over the next 10 years which will give up to 1000 17 to 24-year-olds who have finished year 12 (or equivalent) in the previous two years an opportunity to experience military training and lifestyle for 12 months.   Retention bonuses and allowances totalling $226 million over the next seven years for personnel in critical positions and with key skill sets.</p>
<p>This is the first phase of a major overhaul of ADF recruitment and retention strategies. It complements other initiatives Defence is taking, including enhancements to the Cadet program and a more supportive career planning system that will give ADF members greater control over their careers and more certainty and balance in their lives. Further measures will be announced during 2007.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
