<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23999</transcript-id>
    <title>A message from the Prime Minister - Future growth and prosperity</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Every week this Government is focusing on how to build a stronger and more prosperous economy.</p>
<p>Last weekend, we made great progress in strengthening the foundations of future growth and prosperity.</p>
<p>With the visit of President Xi, Australia concluded negotiations for a free trade agreement with China.</p>
<p>This agreement with China means more growth, more investment and more jobs.</p>
<p>It’s a better deal for our farmers – particularly for producers of dairy, beef, wine, seafood, grain and horticulture.</p>
<p>Industries such as education, telecommunications, tourism, construction and health will all benefit from being able to do business in China far more easily.</p>
<p>And households will benefit from lower prices on whitegoods, on clothes and on cars.</p>
<p>This agreement builds on the free trade agreements signed earlier this year with Korea and Japan.  These agreements will set Australia up for the long term.</p>
<p>We’ve also accelerated free trade discussions with India – one of the largest markets in the world.</p>
<p>This Government is making our economy stronger with freer trade and better infrastructure.</p>
<p>Last weekend, we also announced the establishment of a global infrastructure hub in Sydney that will help to generate jobs and investment.</p>
<p>And across Australia we are investing $50 billion in the largest infrastructure programme in our history.</p>
<p>In Sydney, WestConnex will create almost 10,000 jobs during construction and, when complete, by-pass 52 sets of traffic lights.</p>
<p>In Melbourne, Stage 1 of the East West Link is expected to allow 100,000 vehicles each day to bypass 23 sets of traffic lights.</p>
<p>Our progress in trade and infrastructure is all part of the Government’s Economic Action Strategy to build a strong and prosperous economy for a safe and secure Australia.</p>
<p>23 November 2014</p>
<p><a href="http://youtu.be/BJQVNQrhtxQ">http://youtu.be/BJQVNQrhtxQ</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
