<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4295</transcript-id>
    <title>NINTH NATIONAL CONVENTION OF YOUNG LIBERALS MOVEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/01/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004295.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4JAUSA ALIA<br />
FOR PRESS 7 JANUARY 1977<br />
EMBARGO: 2.00 p. m.<br />
NINTH NATIONAL CONVENTION OF YOUNG LIBERALS MOVEMENT<br />
It is a great pleasure for me to be here at the Ninth Annual<br />
Convention of the Young Liberal Movement.<br />
The Young Liberal Movement has always placed great emphasis<br />
on social issues. The Government values the part the Young<br />
Liberal Movement has in developing its forward policies its<br />
role as a sounding board for testing ideas, and in alerting<br />
the Government to the views of young people across the whole<br />
range of national issues.<br />
Today I would like to speak to you about the Government's approach<br />
to social reform, and place this within the larger context of the<br />
tasks that face it in the economic field.<br />
Outlinin" -his broader context is important because occasionally<br />
some people focus on only one aspect of Government policy and treat<br />
that aspect as if it is, or should be, the Government's exclusive<br />
preoccupation. Such a partial perspective neglects the fact that the Government<br />
has responsibilities in all areas of social policy. More importantly,<br />
it neglects the relationships between one area-of policy, one<br />
sphere of Government action, and another.<br />
The relations between actions taken in one area with our ability<br />
to act effectively in other areas is nowhere more apparent thau<br />
in the relationship between economic policy and the effectiveness<br />
of programmes to assist the poor and disadvantaged. 41<br />
When this Government was elected it faced an economy which~ had been<br />
thrown into fundamental disarray. What should have been one of<br />
the world's most prosperous economies had been afflicted ' by high<br />
unemployment, accelerating inflation and economic stagnation.<br />
Government spending had grown enormously doubling in three years,<br />
from $ 10 billion to $ 22 billion. In one year unemployment had<br />
increased by almost 200,000. Australia's deficit had reached<br />
record levels. Economic activity had declined.<br />
The poorest people in our society were harmed most by the erosion of<br />
living standards inflation brought, and by the unemployment<br />
which inevitably follows inflation. .2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
In this situation the Government had to give priority to righting<br />
the economy and defeating inflation. And we have pursued a , consistent<br />
economic strategy directed at achieving this goal.<br />
Although there is still a long way to go, at the end of our first<br />
year in office, we have made substantial progress towards dealing<br />
with Australia's economic problems.<br />
As the C. P. I. figures and a number of otherprice indices show,<br />
we have made significant progress., in winding back inflation.<br />
On the activity front, the estimates for the September quarter<br />
national accounts showed the third successive quarterly increase<br />
in gross non-farm product. Indicators for the December<br />
quarter show further gains in private spending and employment:<br />
and reports of retail trading in December have been particularly<br />
encouraging. It is worth noting that even if there were no<br />
further growth in the remainder of this financial year, the<br />
year as a whole would show a growth of 5.3% in real non-: Earm.<br />
G. D. P. over 197S/ 76.<br />
The decision to devalue was made inevitable by the almost universal<br />
belief that the dollar was overvalued, the consistent speculation<br />
against the Australian dollar and the uncompetitive position of<br />
Australia's export and import competing industries.<br />
Provided we pursue our anti-inflation strategy with even greater<br />
intensity devaluation presents us with the opportunity to build on<br />
the economic progress of the past twelve months. We intend to<br />
do so.<br />
Our economic strategy is an intrinsic part of our approach to social<br />
reform. The ability to effectively carry through social reform<br />
cannot be separated from a Government's capacity to provide<br />
the nation with responsible economic management.<br />
As the Henderson Report has pointed out, reducing inflation is<br />
central to our ability as a nation and as a Government to assist<br />
those who are disadvantaged or living in poverty.<br />
Our economic strategy is directed at supplying this essential<br />
condition of social welfare. It recognises that only an<br />
efficiently functioning economy, one which adequately rewards<br />
personal achievement and initiative can provide the material sinews<br />
necessary for social reform in many areas.<br />
But having said this, it should equally be recognised that<br />
economic management alone is not enough. All the social reforms<br />
Australia needs will not inevitably flow from economic recovery.<br />
Beating inflation is, and must be, the dominant objective of<br />
this Government it is not, and cannot be, the sole objective<br />
of a responsible Government.<br />
While we have been unrelenting in the fight against inflation, we hay<br />
also been carryring through the commitment which all of us here<br />
share as Liberals to achieving major social reforms. / 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
The objective of our reforms has beeun to bring meaningful<br />
change in those areas which require change. Change which is<br />
appropriate to the needs of the particular situation and -to the needs<br />
of people. Change which enhances the quality of Australian life'<br />
and which increases people's ability to achieve the things they<br />
valI. ue.<br />
If reforms are to achieve these goals they must co! mprehend<br />
and be responsibe to the complex character of Australia as a highly<br />
developed industrial society in which people pursue a diversity<br />
of objectives.<br />
Reform must be conducted with a sense of urgency because there<br />
are areas in our society which are in great need of change. They<br />
must also be conducted with an awareness of Australia's basic<br />
strengths and achievements.<br />
In all cases, policies and programmes must be constantly monitored<br />
to ensure that they are actually acheiving the purposes they were<br />
intended to. Inevitably, in a complex democratic society<br />
the knowledge that we must operate on will be incomplete..<br />
There will be instances where, despite careful planning, some programmE<br />
might have unforseen consequences that do not serve the ends the<br />
programme intended.<br />
In such cases, the Government must be prepared to act to remedy<br />
these consequences. Governments which refuse to do so on the<br />
grounds that remedial action casts into doubts their firmness or<br />
purpose are in fact admittingthe most fundamental weakness the<br />
refusal to see reality as it really is. Such Governmnents; evade<br />
their central responsibility coming to grips with that reality<br />
in the interests of the Australian people.<br />
A central element in coming to grips with problems is thE. ability<br />
to direct assistance to the people in need and ensure that they<br />
actually get the assistance which is directed at them.<br />
We have'acted to achieve this.<br />
In the area of children's services, Labor's programmes were<br />
primarily directed to funding pre-schools. Despite the o'bvious<br />
fact that the most urgent need of many working mothers particularly<br />
low income families is for full day care.<br />
The alternative to this is often leaving their children in<br />
unsuitable care or no care at all.<br />
Accordingly, we have changed the direction of the children's services<br />
programme to give greater emphasis to the provision of full day care<br />
facilities. Some people have argued that by reorientating the child care<br />
programme the Government is encouraging women to leave their<br />
children in care. They are refusing to face the -reality that<br />
thousands of mothers do work and are unable to make adequate<br />
provision for their children. The Government is responding to<br />
this reality. ./ 4 </p>
<p>Unemployment amongst Young people is a matter of particular concern<br />
to the whole community and the Government as I know it has been<br />
for the Young Liberal Movement which has made representations to<br />
us on this issue.<br />
The position of school leavers from 1975 who have been unable to<br />
establish themselves in stable employment has been especially<br />
pressing.. Accordingly, in extending the advantages of on the<br />
job training under the NEAT shceme to the young unemployed with<br />
the Special Youth Employment Training Programme, we have given<br />
priority to this group of young people.<br />
A special subsidy of $ S9 per week was arranged, and the programme<br />
took off from the moment it began. The acceptance the programme<br />
achieved in the community and particularly with employers, enabled<br />
the Government to extend the conditions for entry. By mid December<br />
3600 young-people had been placed in employment under the scheme.<br />
Where major changes have been necessary and where it is clear that a<br />
wide ranging change will actually bring improvement, we have<br />
not hesitated to make radical changes.<br />
The introduction of the new system of family allowances has been<br />
widely and I believe correctly identified as the most<br />
significant reform in the Australian social welfare system since<br />
Federation. It has improved the position of a vast number of<br />
fEamilies. It has given particularly important assistance to<br />
300,000 poorer families with 800,000 children who benefitted only<br />
partially or not at all from the previously operating system of<br />
tax rebates for children.<br />
Family allowances also exemplify our commitment to directing<br />
assistance to those in greatest need and making this assistance<br />
available in forms giving recipients the maximum feasible choice<br />
of how they will use that assistance.<br />
We have also made radical reforms in the Federal system and taxation<br />
policy. In the area of Federalism, the Government has brought about<br />
the most significant reform since Federation by giving State and<br />
local Government access to a fixed percentage of personal income<br />
tax receipts. This gives these governments an unprecedented<br />
degree of budgetary independence and capacity to meet their<br />
responsibilities and set their own priorities without interference<br />
from Canberra. For 1976-77 united grants to the States have been<br />
increased by almost 21% and to local government by almost<br />
These funds can be used as state and local government wish.<br />
The financial autonomy our reforms give, to these spheres of<br />
government will enable them to respond more effectively to their<br />
constituents while enabling the public to more sensitively evaluate<br />
the actions Governments take and the alternatives they might<br />
realistically have chosen. A major part of the significance<br />
of our Federalism reforms lies in the opportunities they offer<br />
the public for more effective and meaningful participation in state<br />
and local governments. / S </p>
<p>Tax indexation also enhances our democracy and increases governmental<br />
accountability to its citizens. No longer will governments be<br />
able to exact greater and greater po;-tions of people's incomes merely<br />
because of inflation. Where government needs more money, it will<br />
explicitly have to raise taxes, with all. the requirements for<br />
public discussion and justification that actions of this sort require.<br />
While making major changes in some areas, we have also heeded<br />
the warning the Henderson Report offered Australian Governments<br />
against " falling into the inflationary trap of attempting to<br />
carry out so miany social reforms or other public expenditures at<br />
once that they accelerate an . iFatonary spiral that does more<br />
to damage poor people than the assistance provided by the reform."<br />
All too often politicians haveassumed that the only requirement for<br />
successful social reform is a programme any programme so long<br />
as it involves the expenditure of large amounts of money.<br />
The expereince of the Labor years has shown us that money thrown<br />
at problems does not only often miss, but actually hurt those whom<br />
it was ostensibly aimed at assisting.<br />
The Government must be willing to try different methods of<br />
bringing about reforms, so that we can determine whether or not<br />
they will achieve the things we desire of them; so we can<br />
gauge the unintended consequences of the programme, and where<br />
possible, determine whether one approach is more effective than<br />
another.<br />
Accordingly, in some areas, the Government has adopted an experimental<br />
approach in order to determine the effectiveness of programmes.<br />
In the housing area, for example, we have begun work on the<br />
design to test the feasibility and effectiveness of providing<br />
subsidies earmarked for rent directly to families in need.<br />
We are also beginning an imaginative experiment with migrant<br />
resources centres in Melbourne and Sydney. Each of these centres<br />
is to be developed along distinct lines to assist the Government<br />
assess the relative effectiveness of the different approaches.<br />
The Melbourne centre involves the contracting out by the Government<br />
of the provision of some services to an ethnic welfare gr~ oup which<br />
is in close touch with the needs of migrants.<br />
The Sydney Resource Centre will be staffed by officers of the<br />
Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs, members of<br />
state government agencies and of voluntary organisations, and<br />
there will be close liaison with, and participation by, the ethnic<br />
communities who are served by the centre.<br />
Reform is not mere ly a matter of taking new initiatives which are<br />
striking in their innovativeness or imposing in their magnitude.<br />
Of fundamental importance is mal~ ing adjustments within the<br />
administrative machinery to render it more efficient and<br />
sensitive to the needs of thc people with which it deals.. If the<br />
people dealing with a government agency feel-that they are being<br />
treated insensitively, if a migrant feels lost because he cannot </p>
<p>communicate his problems to a Departmental officer; a person<br />
is bewildered by a complexity of forms and cannot cope;<br />
if a pensioner dependent on a pension cheque failes to recieve it<br />
puncutally and is caused distress, then the best, the most<br />
abstractly enlightened social security system will have failed that<br />
individual.<br />
Such failures cannot be taken lightly and dismissed as individual<br />
cases ultimately, there are only individual cases.<br />
,1e have sought to make changes in the administrative machinery<br />
which will make it more efficient and sensitive.<br />
In the Department of Social Security for instance we have made<br />
changes which will facilitate people's ability to get the benefits<br />
to which they are entitled in a more dignified and expeditious<br />
manner. Particular attention has been given to assisting<br />
migrants . One important improvement which has already been<br />
introduced is the installation of dual handset telephones linked<br />
to the telephone interpreter services-in many of the Department's<br />
counter areas. These handsets enable a counter officer and a<br />
migrant who are having difficulty in communicating to converse<br />
through an interpreter. The means test on pensions has been<br />
replaced by an income test which is simpler more readily<br />
understandable by recipients, and more equitable. Improvements<br />
in the computer system for social security benefits have reduced<br />
processing time thus making the system of payments faster and<br />
more punctual and also permitting an increase in the work<br />
effectiveness of social security personnel.<br />
I cannot pretend that the changes we have made will resolve all the<br />
problems in this area, but they are an important beginning, and<br />
we will do more.<br />
In the decades since Federation, the Commonwealth's bureaucracy<br />
has grown enormously in size, power, and in the range and diversity<br />
of its formal and informal discretions. Many citizens have felt<br />
powerless in the face of the governmental apparatus and believed<br />
they have little recourse against decisions emanating from it.<br />
'% Whea ve taken steps to ensure that people dealing with the government<br />
are treated faiirly promptly and according to the law, that discretion<br />
are properly used, that grievances against the government are properi.<br />
and impartially investigated and that -wheire grievances are justified<br />
they will be remedied. The Administrative Appeal Tribunal has<br />
been established. It has the power to review the merits of any decis<br />
of a Minister or official acting under statutory power where the<br />
relevant le ' gislation allows appeals to the Tribunal, and it<br />
may set aside or alter decisions of a othiistor-or official.<br />
The Ombudsman Act has been passed through Parliament and the<br />
government expects shortly to appoint the Federal Ombudsman.<br />
' The Ombudsman will be able to review all administrative acts of<br />
officials and recommend corrective action where he finds<br />
maladministration. These measures will enhance the freedom of all Australians and proti<br />
their rights in an area in which protection has long been needed an.<br />
too long delayed. If reform is to be, as it must be, an ongoing<br />
process, it is imperative that the machinery of government bc </p>
<p>7.<br />
structured to provide advice on needed reforms, and that<br />
the government have the advice and be able to consult groups<br />
which have special expertise in the area.<br />
We have taken steps to bring this about.<br />
To ensure that the needs of women are taken into account in the<br />
formulation of government policy, women's units have been<br />
established in a number of Departments and authorities.<br />
The Government also intends to establish a Women's Advisory Committee.<br />
An Inquiry has been established to report on youth matters and to<br />
examine the advantages of establishing a youth bureau or a youth<br />
advisory panel to advise the government. This Inquiry will<br />
provide an important means through which the government can consult<br />
with youth.<br />
In the area of Aboriginal affairs, an Inquiry into the NACC<br />
has made recommendations for increased involvement of Aboriginals<br />
in developing programmes and priorities in Aboriginal affairs.<br />
These are now being considered by the government.<br />
Some of the other reforms which we have initiated over the last<br />
year include: the legislation for the automatic adjustment<br />
of social security benefits every six months in accordance<br />
with movements in the CPI; the introduction of an improved home<br />
savings grant scheme that is in fact more extensive than the one<br />
we committed ourselves to during the 1975 election campai. g n;<br />
the decision to establish a Human Right's Commission ' which<br />
will promote human ri ghts and ensure that Australian laws<br />
are maintained in conformity with the United Nations International<br />
Covenant on Civil and Political Rights; the passage of the<br />
Aboriginal Land Rights Act through Parliament<br />
an Act which will be of major importance in restoring land to its<br />
traditional owners in the Northern Territory; the reintroduction of<br />
triennial funding for the eduation commission; the protection<br />
of the unique and fragile beauty of Fraser Island as an important<br />
part of our national heritage and the making of provision to<br />
assist those whose employment was affected by our decision on the<br />
island.<br />
This only sketches in the barest outlines some of the areas in which<br />
the government has acted to acheive reform in the past twelve months,<br />
and some of the steps taken to lay the groundwork for further<br />
action. There are other areas in which we are carefully considering the most<br />
effective ways of proceeding. Income Security and the care of the age<br />
are two areas in which we intend to act in the future.<br />
The government has elso tabled proposals for a Freedom of<br />
Information Act and intends to introduce Freedom of Information<br />
legislation in the next sitting of Parliament.<br />
Law reform particularly on matters touching the protection of the<br />
individual's rights, and freedoms against the state and Other<br />
indidividuals has a high priority with the Government.<br />
A number of references have been made to the Law Reform Commiss:; hml </p>
<p>in this respect. In this constant process of reform,<br />
I believe that the Young Liberal Movement has an important part to play,<br />
We need imaginative proposals for reform which avoid the cliches<br />
and posturing which have done Australia so much harm in the recent<br />
past. The Labor experience has shown us that one of the greatest<br />
traps a government call fall into is to attempt to win politicial<br />
kudos by dre-ssing up illconsidered change as reform. Such masquerades<br />
not only fail to come to grips with the real problems facing our<br />
society, but they often exacerbate the problems they were ostensibly<br />
intended to resolve. The reforms which we have made in the last year<br />
have been reforms of substance which will make a lasting and<br />
meaningful contribution to improving Australia, which will make a<br />
difference to people's ability to cope with the complexity of<br />
our society.<br />
In their depth, breadth and appropriateness, they represent a<br />
record of achievement of which any Liberal, any Australian, can<br />
be proud. Our reforms have recognised that radical action is<br />
necessary in some areas, that experimental approaches are necessary<br />
in others, and that there must be constant attention paid<br />
to the consequences of policies and to the administrative. mach-inery's<br />
capacity to implement programmes.<br />
They have been based on the recognition that qualitative<br />
criteria are more important than quantitative criteria in<br />
judging reforms. The important questions are not how many progiv:, mes<br />
has a government begun nor how much money has been expended on a<br />
programme. We have shown that there is room for reform in areas<br />
where no additional expenditure is needed.<br />
The Labor Government amply demonstrated that ill-considered<br />
expenditures do not make reforms and can in fact be counterproductive.<br />
The important questions that must be asked of a programme are:<br />
does the change actually assist the people who are most in need?<br />
Does it promote the elimination of those pockets of discrimination<br />
and areas of power imbalance that exist in our society?<br />
Does it materially assist the poor and disadvantaged while avoiding<br />
the debilitating loss of self-respect that over dependence brings?<br />
Does it make a contribution to enhancing the rights and<br />
freedoms of Australians? Does it make the government more<br />
responsible to the citizen and more responsible and accessible to him<br />
Judged against these standards, 1976 can be considered the year<br />
in which the Commonwealth Government carried through some of its<br />
most significant reforms since Federation.<br />
But these reforms can only be a beginning. There is a manifest<br />
need for further reform in many areas of our society. We will make<br />
these reforms. The basic strengths of our society, its<br />
egalitarianism, its lack of fundamental class or racial<br />
conflicts,, its great wealth gives us an unmatched potentiality for<br />
building a society which is unsurpassed in its equality;<br />
its opportunity, the independence Of its c , itizens, and their<br />
capacity to achieve the goals they value i~ n their own ways.<br />
We ave Oeguyl to real ise that potential. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
