<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5932</transcript-id>
    <title>SCHOLARSHIPS TO THE AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTE OF SPORT FOR DEVELOPING COMMONWEALTH COUNTRIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005932.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 1.00 PM<br />
llAUST 1A A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 8 OCTOBER 1982<br />
SCHOLARSHIPS TO THE AUSTRALIAN INSTITUTE OF SPORT FOR<br />
DEVELOPING COMMONWEALTH COUNTRIES<br />
The Australian Government will allocate ten sports scholarships<br />
a year at the Australian Institute of Sport to selected<br />
athletes from developing Commonwealth countries.<br />
This is not only in recognition of the highly successful<br />
Commonwealth Games in Brisbane, but also recognises that sport<br />
is an area of Commonwealth co-operation, and one in which<br />
there is already a firm foundation of friendship and co-operation.<br />
The scholarships will assist athletes from developing<br />
Commonwealth countries to expand and extend their sporting<br />
skills. The Brisbane Games has shown that there is great<br />
sporting talent in Commonwealth countries. Using the resources<br />
and skills available at the Australian Institute of Sport should<br />
make a real contribution to raising the levels of performance<br />
of athletes selected.<br />
The scholarships will be for one year, will cover return fares<br />
to Australia, living expenses in Australia, a living allowance<br />
and competition costs. The ten scholarships will be in addition<br />
to the 188 already available to Australian athletes. The national<br />
sporting bodies of developing countries will be asked to submit<br />
nominations. The Australian Institute of Sport will be<br />
working out selection procedures in consultation with the<br />
national sporting bodies and the Commonwealth Games Federation.<br />
The first scholarships will be available in 1983.<br />
Sport plays an important part in developing close links with<br />
other countries. The contribution overseas athletes can make<br />
in the Australian Institute of Sport and in Australia, and the<br />
contribution that Australia might make to the development of<br />
sporting skills in other Commonwealth countries, will add to<br />
these close links. ooo000ooo </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
