<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5827</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005827.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5.00pm<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 6 JUNE 1982<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Tax avoidance is an activity that costs every decent<br />
member of the Australian community dearly. Avoidance<br />
is, to be sure, a very slippery concept. But basically,<br />
it amounts to arranging one's affairs with the sole<br />
purpose minimising tax strictly, obeying the narrow<br />
terms of t~ ax legislation, but not its spirit and intent<br />
and ultimately it involves shifting the burden of<br />
taxation on to the honest taxpayer.<br />
Anyone who pays less than their fair share of tax does<br />
so at the expense of every other member of the<br />
community. For everyone benefits from<br />
Government-provided services, and from the protection of<br />
the law anid those who avoid paying their fair share of<br />
the cost of those services are bludging on those who do.<br />
But the financial cost of avoidance is not measured<br />
simply by the extra tax the rest of us have to pay. Tax<br />
revenue has to be devoted to devising, implementing and<br />
administering anti-avoidance laws and to prosecuting<br />
those caught cheating.<br />
The cost also includes the resources, the time and the<br />
effort not only of those who seek to avoid taxation but<br />
also of their advisers their high-priced accountants<br />
and lawyers who make a living off what they earn<br />
by promoting scheme after scheme to rip off the rest of<br />
the community.<br />
Tax avoidance not only involves financial costs : it is<br />
anti-social, and un-Australian. It is behaviour that<br />
undermines the social fabric; it does so as surely or<br />
more so as the irresponsible behaviour of that<br />
minority of militant unionists who think and act as if<br />
they can with impunity, trample on the rights of the<br />
community, of which they are part. And the person who<br />
indulges in avoidance by finding an artificial loophole<br />
to slip cut of tax is, in our view, as guilty of a crime<br />
against society as the person who evades tax by falsely<br />
declarinql his income. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
No government has done more to fight tax avoidance than<br />
the present Government and Treasurer John Howard has<br />
attacked tax avoidance more vigorously than any other<br />
Treasurer in Australia's history. It is indeed because<br />
of this Government's active campaign against tax<br />
avoidance and the publicity which we have given to this<br />
anti-social behaviour that the average Australian has<br />
become so iware of it. Under this Government we have<br />
acted on 26 occasions through 22 pieces of legislation<br />
against 54 separate schemes. In addition to directly<br />
attacking particular schemes of avoidance, we have<br />
incorporated through Part IV A of the Income Tax<br />
Assessment Act a general anti-avoidance provision. A<br />
key feature of this legislation is that blatant,<br />
artificial and contrived arrangements caught in its net<br />
are struck down as from 27 May 1981 when the legislation<br />
was passed. Whatever date in the future they are<br />
discovered an additional tax equal to double the tax<br />
sought to be avoided is automatically payable on any<br />
scheme struck down by Part IV A.<br />
We have also introduced the Crimes ( Taxation Offences)<br />
Act 1980 which provides gaol terms of up to five years,<br />
and fines of up to $ 50,000 for certain schemes which<br />
seek to reduce or remove the capacity of a company or<br />
trustee to pay tax.<br />
And through changes in the * Crimes Interpretations Act we<br />
have required the courts to have regard for the<br />
intention of the law rather than for finer points of its<br />
language. The Government is confident that together these measures<br />
are working and will continue to work to greatly<br />
diminish the incidence of tax avoidance.<br />
But let there be no misunderstanding. If the measures<br />
we have already taken don't go far enough to stop<br />
particular unacceptable practices, the Government will<br />
not hesitate to take further action. And this action<br />
might wel" L resort to an extension of the use of limited<br />
retrospectiv ity. o0000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
