<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5634</transcript-id>
    <title>GOVERNMENT/CAI TALKS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/08/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005634.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
,.&gt; AUSTRLA<br />
PRIME MINISTERFOR<br />
MEDIA VWEDNESD -12 AUGUST.-1981<br />
GOVERNMENT/ CAI TALKS<br />
The Prime Minister and Ministerial colleagues met with<br />
representatives of the Confederation of Australian Industryin<br />
Canberra today.<br />
Both parties agreed that there had been misunderstandings<br />
about the impact of the abandonment of the wage indexation<br />
system by the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission.<br />
Nothing could be more wrong than to say that the abandonment<br />
of that system had left a vacuum and that there were no<br />
rules. governing the determination of claims.<br />
Unions and employers continue to have the right to approach<br />
the Commission for the resolution of wage and other<br />
industrial claims.<br />
The Industrial Relations processes established under the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration Act still apply:<br />
the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission has<br />
responsibility by law to pay regard to the general<br />
community interest as well as economic issues in<br />
making awards<br />
the Commission has long-established principles to be<br />
applied in dealing with claims for new awards,<br />
variation of awards and certification of agreements.<br />
What should be clear to all is that no " free for all"<br />
situation exists. Any claims for wage increases will need<br />
to be supported with proper and substantive argument.<br />
Both the Government and Industry remain concerned at the<br />
potentially inflationary consequences for all Australians<br />
of excessive growth in incomes.<br />
There was an acceptance of the need for all parties to cooperate<br />
in making the Arbitration system work effectively<br />
and a conviction that this could be done.' This was coupled<br />
with a determination to ensure that the Arbitration system<br />
would be recognised as the best process for settling<br />
disputes. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Both parties agreed that they would do everything in their<br />
respective areas of responsibility to facilitate the<br />
determination of just claims before the Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Commission.<br />
This was coupled with a determination to ensure that the<br />
Arbitration system would be recognised as the best process<br />
for settling disputes.<br />
The Government informed the national employers, and they<br />
accepted it, that the Government's proper role in industrial<br />
relations is<br />
to provide the appropriate legislative framework<br />
for settling industrial claims and disputes<br />
to intervene as considered necessary in major<br />
national industrial relations cases before the<br />
appropriate Tribunal. </p>
<p>. d, 0,: 1 6 Present at Meeting<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Mr. Sinclair, Minister for Communications<br />
Senator Carrick, Minister for National Development and<br />
Energy<br />
Mr. Howard, Treasurer<br />
Mr. Viner, Minister for Industrial Relations<br />
Mr. Fife, Minister for Education<br />
Mr. Brown, Minister for Employment and Youth Affairs<br />
Representatives of the Confedederation of Australian<br />
Industry<br />
Mr. H. G. Aston, CBE, President, C. A. I.<br />
Sir Samuel Burston, OBE, Vic-President, C. A. I.<br />
Mr. J. E. Dixon, OBE, Chairman, National Employers Industrial<br />
Council, C. A. I.<br />
Mr. G. A. Mackay<br />
Mr. D. Dobbie<br />
mr. G. Polities, CMG, MBE<br />
Mr. R. G. Fry, MBE<br />
Mr. N. J. Mason,<br />
Mr. B. M. Noakes </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
