<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2700</transcript-id>
    <title>LOCAL GOVERNMENT ASSOCIATION CONFERENCE LUNCHEON CANBERRA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 23 OCTOBER 1972</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002700.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
LOCAL GOVER. NM'ENT ASSOCIATION CONFERENCE LUNCHEON<br />
CAN BE IRMA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt Hon. William McMahon, CH, MP.<br />
2.3 October 1972<br />
Thank you for giving me the opportunity to come to such<br />
a wonderful meeting as this in Canberra. I think it indicates not only<br />
the approach of the Local Government Authorities themselves, but it also<br />
indicates clearly that you recognise that the Commonwealth Government<br />
must take its part in assisting Local Government Authorities and permitting<br />
them to participate in government as the third tier. And I believe, Sir,<br />
it's proper that I should say to you as Chairman, that there can be no<br />
doubt at all that * part of the credit.-for attracting so many people to<br />
come to a meeting like this is due to you and the efforts that you've<br />
made in Local Government for so many years in the past.<br />
I do appreciate the efforts that you have made to give<br />
me the opportunity to speak on behalf of the Government, and to speak<br />
about Local Government itself and what it means to this country. I do<br />
so because as you know, we are approaching a Federal election and we.<br />
are doing so at a time when crucial decisions relating to the concepts<br />
and structures of Governments which have guided the progress and development<br />
of society for so many years are now un~ der review, and very substantial<br />
review too.<br />
It is true to say that there's no exaggeration in the<br />
phrase ' that what is at stake is the system of Federalism and the<br />
three-tiered system of Government'. No matter what phrases you might<br />
use, no matter how you might care to disguise intentions, it becomes<br />
clear that that is the choice that faces us.<br />
And that three-tiered system is one of Federal, State<br />
and Local Government. This is, I assure you again, and I want the<br />
words to sink in, no vague and undocumented threat. Nor is it an<br />
invention of Liberal Party politicians for electoral purposes*<br />
Let me quote the evidence of this by one of your own<br />
most respected Local Government experts, Mr Roy Stuckey. In commenting<br />
on the radical proposals of our politic-al opponents to attack and<br />
ultimately destroy the role of State and Local Governments as we know<br />
them today, he said, and I quote him " In effect, in one fell swoop,<br />
Mr Whitlam proposes doing away with the State Parliaments and 900 Local </p>
<p>Government-uni ' ts and-replacing them by what must * become a centralist<br />
and bureaucratic control from Canberra". And he goes on to say, and<br />
I completely agree with him in this, that " the people of Australia would<br />
never stand for such a proposal".<br />
But it is the last few words of Mr Stuckey's comment<br />
that I want to particularly draw to your attention today in looking at<br />
these dangerous designs for centralism. He said, and these are his<br />
words, " it would provide initially a dictatorship for the Party in<br />
power". No warning could be in clearer or in more distinct terms.<br />
Before I go on to delineate this serious threat to<br />
Local Government in more detail, I first want to describe to you my<br />
own attitudes to this problem as a Liberal and as a person who can<br />
claim a very long experience in Government. I am unashamedly a<br />
Federalist, and I believe that my record bears this out, particularly<br />
in the period since I took office as Prime Minister.<br />
Inherent in the Liberal philosophy of the individual<br />
is a distrust of, and A' emphasise these words, great concentrations<br />
of power and authority. And from this flows our commitment to the<br />
principle that Government should be as close to the people as possible<br />
through effective decentralisation and through maximum voluntary<br />
participation in Local Government.<br />
Now the.. proof : 6hat these principles are the ones which<br />
are more acceptable to Australians lies in the fact of the existence<br />
of the three-tiered system of government itself. It is the natural<br />
result of our history and our geography. And we intend to preserve<br />
and to strengthen it.<br />
A few months ago we had in Australia Professor David<br />
Donnison. Many of you will no doubt remember his presence here. And<br />
he is theC" Dir~ ctor of the Centre for Environmental Studies in London<br />
and an expert in these matters. He had an important message. He said<br />
" We should be suspicious of over-ambitious proposals which start from<br />
the top and work downwards. Since we barely know enouch to co-ordinate<br />
policies in one street, we should beqig not * by proposing brand-new<br />
systems for a whole society but by trying more effectively to link up<br />
the things we already know best".<br />
Only a few months ago, in July, I received here in<br />
Canberra, a deputation from the Australian Council of Local Government<br />
Associations. I understand too, that this was the first time in more<br />
than twenty years that a Prime Minister had received a deputation from<br />
the national representatives of the Local Government Associations.<br />
I told the deputation of my own and my Government's<br />
continuing concern for Local Government, and my own belief in the<br />
maintenance of truly local forms of Government. As life in our great<br />
cities in particular becomes more complex and more populous, I am<br />
convinced that our Local, Municipal and Shire administrations will need<br />
to play an even greater role in improving the quality of life of our<br />
citizens., not only over the range of traditional responsibilities, but<br />
in recreational, sporting and cultural activities to an increasing'-<br />
degree. Big cities should mean a greater, not a lesser role for<br />
Local Government, and I support this greater role. I have strongly 1/ 3 </p>
<p>supported the attendance of Local Government reoresentatives at the<br />
forthcoming Constitutional Convention, and although it is more a matter<br />
of decision for the States themselves, I have expresssed a definite view<br />
that Local Government representatives at the Convention will not only<br />
be able to speak, but they should be able to vote as well.<br />
I mentioned the States then because we should not forget<br />
that Local Government Authorities are created and function under State<br />
laws, as you well pointed out, Mr Chairman. And the Commonwealth does<br />
not wish to disturb at present the constitutional structure whereby the<br />
responsibility for determining the revenue-raising powers and supplementing<br />
the resources of Local Government lies with the State Parliaments.<br />
In accordance with that attitude, the Commonwealth does<br />
not normally provide direct grants to Lccal Governments. What it does<br />
do is to provide large amounts of untied assistance to the State Governments<br />
which they are free to disburrse as they themselves decide; so that<br />
it is true to say that indirectl bul-: in a very real way the Commonwealth<br />
provides considerable assistance to Local Government Authorities. May I<br />
now spell out some of our recent actions to illustrate this point<br />
The general revenue grants to the States have been<br />
increased considerably in recent years and this year we agreed to something<br />
of the ot ' 92 million, that is for the Burget year<br />
1972/ 73. Now t'is was an increase of something like $ 15r million, or<br />
over last year. The arrangements under which these grants will be paid<br />
over a five year period ending 1974/ 75 were initially determined at the<br />
Premiers' Conference of June 1970. However, they were very substantially<br />
revised as a result of the Premiers' Conference in June 1971 and 1972<br />
at which I had the good fortune to preside.<br />
There have, as a result, been very significant increases.<br />
For example it is estimated that the States wil. receive in 1972-73 over<br />
$ 420 million more in Commonwealth general revenue grants than they<br />
would have received had the 1970 arrrnvements continued unchanged. At<br />
the June 1971 Conference, besides agreeing tothese additional revenue<br />
grants, the States accepted our offer, the Commonwealth's offer, to<br />
transfer payroll tax to them and they have been levying that tax since<br />
September of last year.<br />
At the same Conference, and I think this is of enormous<br />
importance to you and your colleagues, ! r Chairman, we also agreed as<br />
a special measure cf assistance to Local Government Authorities that we,<br />
the Commonwealth, would meet the full cost of exempting the non-business<br />
activities of Local Government from pay-roll tax. The cost of that was<br />
$ 8 million in a full year and $ 6 million in 1971/ 72.<br />
In rural areas , e also provide the general range of<br />
Commonwealth assistance to rural industry. We have instituted an<br />
unemployment relief scheme, and we have included the provision of<br />
relief work grants as eligible under State drought relief measures. / 4 </p>
<p>In addition, at the Loan Council meeting in June this year,<br />
the limit on Local Government borrowings without the approval of the<br />
Council was aised from $ 300,000 to S40n, 00n.<br />
I believe, and I want to emphasise this point, that all<br />
these actions demonstrate our clear concern for the problems of Local<br />
Government and our support f'lr the Federalist system of Government too.<br />
Tgis is not to pretend that the present system is perfect by any means.<br />
But with all its shortcomings, it does through a division and a balance<br />
of power provide for decentralised administration, and an essential<br />
barrier ot the abuse of authority by an all powerful central Government<br />
which would replace elected bodies with commissions responsible only to<br />
one Parliament. Let there be no mistake about it. It is an all-powerful<br />
central Govenrment in Canberra that our opponents are dedicated to<br />
impose. Many of you will remember the speech in Canberra eleven months<br />
ago when the Leader of the Opposition spelt out his plan, and I now<br />
quote from it " We should have a House of Representatives for international<br />
matters and nationwide national matters, an assembly for the<br />
affairs of each of our dozen largest cities and regional assemblies<br />
for the few score areas of rural production and resource development<br />
outside these cities". There in clear and unmistakable and unambiguous terms<br />
the Leader of the Opposition advocates not only the abolition of the<br />
Senate and eisting State Governments, but also the destruction' of<br />
900 existing Municipal and Shire Councils and their replacement with a<br />
series of arogant and disinterested bureaucracies, bodies that would<br />
be answerable to Canberra, remote from the local problems of the<br />
citizne himself.<br />
citizen trying w d not be hard tn imacfine, the ligh<br />
tdoan a response from a remote eacrtabout<br />
an offensive drain or an unsatisfactory garbage service. And if<br />
anyone imagines that a Labor Government would be prevented from<br />
implementing its centralist dream by constitutional limitations,<br />
I'm sure that in these words you'll find that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition has the answer to that too.<br />
Speaking to the Fabian Society in Victoria last July,<br />
he said tat if Section 92 could be held up to be the bulwark of private<br />
enterprise, then Section 96 is the Charter qf rublic enterprise. And<br />
he went on to say that it would be intolerable if Labor was to use the<br />
alibi of the Constitution to excuse failure to achieve its social<br />
objectives; doubly intolerable because, he say3, that it is just not<br />
true that it need do so.<br />
Now this is clear notice from our opponents that a<br />
Labor Government would use Section 96 which allows the Commonwealth<br />
to grant assistance to the States on such terms and conditions as the<br />
Commonwealth things fit; as a vehicle for '-entralism by financial<br />
squeeze or as Professor Donnison put it more suczinctly, and now<br />
again I quote from him, to " tear the guts o. of r'tate Governments". </p>
<p>The message is therefore clear. A condition of<br />
obtaining financial assistance is toeing the centralist line, or if<br />
you like " Do what we say with Local Government or you don't get<br />
the money". So nobody can preterdthat the threat has not been spelled<br />
out. It is there. It is real, and to ignore it would I believe, be completely<br />
foolhardy. In our view, the present structure of Municipalities<br />
and Shires provides the indispensable network for grass roots contact<br />
between the citizens and. what can be an arbitrary leviathan of central<br />
government. Other countries are struggling to return Government to<br />
the people, to put decisions back down into the hands of those close to<br />
and responsible to the citizen at t~ v~ qrass roots.<br />
Do Australians want to go the way of the dictatorship of<br />
centralism, control by commission, the recioe of remote control I<br />
do not believe it for a second.<br />
Before I conclude, Mr Chairman, let me mention one other<br />
aspect of our pponentis delusions and at te same time let me issue a<br />
warning. They offer you the lure of Local Government representation<br />
on the Loan Council and that has a superficial attractiveness. But what<br />
again is the price tag Reduction of Local Government to a " few score<br />
bodies" for the whole of Australia.<br />
So I say we must beware of the lure of a " widened role"<br />
for Local Government in a unitary centralised system, which in reality<br />
is nothing n~ re than an invitation to destroy any vestige of so-called<br />
" Local" Government, and reolace Federalism with a centralised system<br />
dominated by the barons of boards and commissions reporting only tc<br />
Federal Parliament. Mr Chairman, thank you for giving me the opportunity<br />
of addressubg today so many distinguished Australian citizens, and<br />
thank you also for giving me the opportunity to speak here at a<br />
Conference where representatives of New Zealand are present, and<br />
representatives of most of the Local Government Authorities are ablP<br />
to come to Canberra, aid in time I hope, after the Constitutional ConventlLi<br />
is held theywillbe able to participate more fullyin the work of government,<br />
particularly helping those at the grass-roots of this great country of<br />
ours and with whom they are in the most immediate contact. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
