<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8903</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER&#039;S REMARKS FOLLOWING VISIT TO THE DEMILITARISED ZONE, KOREA, 23 JUNE 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/06/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008903.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER'S REMARKS FOLLOWING VISIT TO THE<br />
DEMILITARISED ZONE, KOREA, 23 JUNE 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: Well, I thilnk on this visit I have had the opportunity of developing a very good<br />
relationship, I think, with the President. Kim Young-Sam. and given the fact that<br />
It is the boginning of his five years in office this, for Australia, I think is a good<br />
thing. That is, that we have struck up what I think Is a warm personal<br />
relationship which I hope will endure now In our countries terms at least for the<br />
tenure of his Presidency. The other matter which I think we have succeeded In<br />
getting across Is the fact that Australia shouldn't be viewed simply as a<br />
producer of raw materials. That it is a producer of sophisticated products; that<br />
we have a deep research and development base and I think this is being<br />
understood in Korea. That people here know now that even though we supply<br />
them with Iron ore and coking coal, we are also a supplier of high technology<br />
goods manufactured goods and that we can do much In joint ventures with<br />
them, as well as supply them. And finaliy, I think that we have been able to<br />
develop a further consensus of view about the importance of APEC and<br />
pushing the APEC agenda along so that at the November meeting In the United<br />
States we can make positive headway in APEC's trade liberailsing role.<br />
Weli, my impression of the demilitarised zone Is, I think, the obvious one, and<br />
that is that thirty million people have lived behind it for forty years, for forty years<br />
a very large population has had, really, no joy and none of the fruits of growth<br />
and prosperity w~ ich the rest of the world has had, So thats a first dismal<br />
effect and observation I would make about it, The other Is that it just highlights<br />
just how successful the Korean Government, the Government of South Korea<br />
has been the Republic of Korea In developing a modern economy with this<br />
threat almost at its border, within an hour from Its capital city, within an hour<br />
from Seoul. And the tension which the country has lived under has been quite<br />
profound. So one hopes that with the effluxion of time Korea will be a reunited<br />
country and we will not see people living under this threat or thirty million<br />
people living in the relative poverty which they do in North Korea.<br />
ends T2EL3: . Jun. 93 9: 45 No. 004 P. 01/ 01 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
