<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5990</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR BOB HAWKE, TO THE COMMITTEE FOR DEVELOPMENT OF YOUTH EMPLOYMENT, MELBOURNE, 19 JANUARY 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/01/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005990.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-p*<br />
EAMT AR3. G0O 0E DP . AGMAINST DELIVERY tCHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PROME F10 N ESTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR BOB HAWKE, TO THE CMM4ITTEE FOR DEVELOPMENT<br />
OF YOtYIH EPLOYMENT, MELBOURNE, 19 JANUARY 1983<br />
I AM VERY PLEASED TO BE HERE TODAY TO JOIN IN THE<br />
OFFICIAL LAUNCHING OF THE COMMITTEE FOR DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
YOUTH EMPLOYMENT. I AM AWARE THAT THE COMMITTEE HAS FOR SOME TIME<br />
NOW BEEN WORKING QUIETLY BLHIND THE SCENES AND HAS ALREADY<br />
MADE SIGNIFICANT PROGRESS IN VICTORIA IN OPENING UP<br />
EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES FOR YOUNG PEOPLE. WHEN I LOOK AT<br />
THF EXPERTISE AND EXPERIENCE OF THE COMMITTEE'S MEMBERS, I<br />
AM CONFIDENT THAT YOU WILL BE ABLE TO GO ON AND ACHIEVE A GREAT<br />
DEAL MORE IN THIS MOSTIMPORTANT AREA.<br />
WHEN MY GOVERNMENT CAME TO OFFICE SOME 10 MONTHS AGO<br />
WE FACED A NUMBER OF SERIOUS ECONOMIC PROBLEMS NONE WORSE<br />
THAN THE DISASTROUS UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION, PARTICULARLY THAT<br />
FACING YOUNG AUSTRALIANS, WE PLACED THE HIGHEST PRIORITY ON<br />
TACKLING THIS PROBLEM, l'E BELIEVED THEN, AS WE DO NOW, THAT LEVELS<br />
OF UNEMPLOYMENT ' ANYTHING LIKE THOSE OF THE PAST COUPLE OF YEARS<br />
CANNOT AND SHOULD NOT BE TOLERATED.<br />
IN CONSEQUENCE, WE HAVE DEVELOPED<br />
POLICIES DIRECTED AT THE PROMOTION OF SUSTAINED ECONOMIC GROWTH,<br />
WHICH WILL LEAD TO INCREASED EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL<br />
AUSTRALIANS, INCLUDING YOUNG PEOPLE,<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN UNEMPLOYMENT PROBLEM HAS BEEN OF SUCH<br />
MAGNITUDE THAT ONLY SUSTAINED GROWTH IN EMPLOYMENT OVER LONG PERIODS<br />
CAN MAKE REAL HEADWAY AGAINST IT, </p>
<p>WE ARE MAKING SOME HEADWAY, BUT THERE IS A LONG<br />
ROAD AHEAD. THE POLICIES BASED ON CO-OPERATION BETWEEN<br />
GOVERNMENT, WORKERS AND BUSINESS THAT WE BEGAN TO PUT IN PLACE<br />
AT THE SUMMIT LAST APRIL HAVE ALLOWED US TO CAPITALISE ON THE GOO[<br />
FORTUNE OF THE BREAKING OF THE DROUGHT AND IMPROVED OVERSEAS<br />
ECONOMIC CONDITIONS. -IN THE EIGHT MONTHS FROM APRIL TO<br />
DECEMBER 1983, EMPLOYMENT ROSE BY OVER 158,000 JOBS -A SHARP<br />
REVERSAL FROM THE SITUATION IN THE IMMEDIATELY PRECEDING 3MONTHS, WHIEN<br />
OVER 14.. 6000 JOBS WERE LOST. THIS GROWTH IN EMPLOYMENT SUPPORTED<br />
SOME REDUCTION OF UNEMPLOYMENT ON A SEASONALLY ADJUSTED BASIS,<br />
FROM 10.3 PER CENT IN APRIL TO 9.2 PER CENT OF THE LABOUR FORCE.<br />
BUT WE HAVE ALWAYS RECOGNISED THAT EVEN WITH EXTRAORDINARILY<br />
RAPID AND SUSTAINED EMPLOYMENT GROWTH, ANY RETURN TO<br />
THE FULL EMPLOYMENT CONDITIONS OF THE POST-WAR GENERATION WILL<br />
BE A LONG, SLOW. AND. DIFFICULT PROCESS.<br />
AND THROUGH THIS PROCESS, UNEMPLOYMENT WILL AFFECT<br />
OUR YOUTH MOST SEVERELY-. UNEMPLOYMENT AMONGST TEENAGERS HAD<br />
BEEN INCREASING STEADILY UNTIL IT REACHED HISTORICALLY HIGH<br />
LEVELS IN 1982-83.. IN JANUARY 1983 THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE FOR<br />
TEENAGERS SEEKING FULL TIME WORK PEAKED AT 29 PER CENT. THERE<br />
HAS BEEN A SLIGHT DECLINE SINCE THEN, BUT THE RATE REMAINS<br />
UNACCEPTABLY HIGH.' THIS SITUATION IS BEING AGGRAVATED BY THE<br />
ARRIVAL OF THE CURRENT-ROUND OF SCHOOL LEAVERS LAST MONTH AND<br />
THIS MONTH. </p>
<p>3.<br />
NEARLY A QUARTER OF A MILLION PEOPLE ARE THOUGHT TO<br />
HAVE LEFT SCHOOL AT THE END OF LAST YEAR OF THESE AROJND<br />
1415,00 ARE NOW BEGINNING TO LOOK FOR WORK. THESE SCHOOL<br />
LEAVERS WILL FIND THEIR SEARCH FOR EMPLOYMENT MADE MORE<br />
DIFFICULT BY COMPETITION FROM THE ABNORMALLY HIGH PROPORTION<br />
OF THE PREVIOUS YEAR'S SCHOOL LEAVERS WHO ARE STILL UNEMPLOYED,<br />
AS AT OCTOBER 1983 SOME 60,000 TEENAGERS WERE STILL LOOKING<br />
FOR THEIR FIRST JOB.<br />
As I MENTIONED, SOUND ECONOMIC POLICIES ARE AN<br />
ESSENTIAL PART OF THE LONGER TERM RESPONSE TO YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT.<br />
BUT MANY HAVE USED THIS REALITY AS AN EXCUSE FOR TURNING THEIR<br />
BACKS ON THE IMMEDIATE NEEDS OF THE YOUNG PEOPLE AFFECTED.<br />
SPECIAL MEASURES ARE NECESSARY TO ALLEVIATE THE PERSONAL AND<br />
COMMUNITY IMPACT OF UNEMPLOYMENT, BOTH BY GOVERNMENT, AND THROUGH<br />
PRIVATE INITIATIVES, OF WHICH THE WORK OF YOUR COMMITTEE IS AN<br />
OUTSTANDING EXAMPLE,<br />
FOR THE GOVERNMENT'S PART, OUR MOST IMPORTANT INITIATIVE<br />
is THE COMMUNITY EMPLOYMENT PROGRAM, WE HAVE ALLOCATED $ 300<br />
MILLION TO THIS PROGRAM IN 1983-84 -THIS SHOULD RESULT IN THE<br />
CREATION OF UP To 40,000 JOBS THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA THIS FINANCIAL<br />
YEAR, WITH UP To 70,000 JOBS PER YEAR BEING CREATED WHEN THE<br />
PROGRAM IS FULLY OPERATIONAL. THESE JOBS WILL BE IN PROJECTS<br />
SPONSORED By FEDERAL, STATE AND LOCAL GOVERNMENTS AND COMMUNITY<br />
ORGANISATIONS. FUNDS FOR THESE PROJECTS HAVE STARTED TO FLOW,<br />
THE CEP GIVES SPECIAL PRIORITY FOR THE EMPLOYMENT OF THE MOST<br />
DISADVANTAGED JOB SEEKERS AND THOSE WHO ARE LEAST LIKELY TO<br />
BENEFIT FROM A GENERAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY, ESPECIALLY THE . LONG<br />
TERM UNEMPLOYMENT. IT IS A SAD FACT THAT MANY YOUNG PEOPLE<br />
NOW FIT INTO THIS CATEGORY. </p>
<p>COMMUNITY EMPLOYMENT PROGRAM JOBS HAVE A VITAL<br />
FUNCTION TO PERFORM, THAT OF PROVIDING PARTICIPANTS WITH<br />
SKILLS AND WORK EXPERIENCE. WE SEE THESE AS BEING NECESSARY<br />
FOR PEOPLE TO BREAK OUT OF THE UNEMPLOYMENT CYCLE INTO<br />
PERMANENT EMPLOYMENT IN THE OPEN LABOUR MARKET.<br />
WE INHERITED A MISCELLANY OF LABOUR MARKET AND TRAINING<br />
PROGRAMS. THE PROGRAMS WERE GENERALLY UNCO-ORDINATED AND<br />
MANY DEVELOPED UNDER SUBSTANTIALLY DIFFERENT LABOUR MARKET<br />
CONDITIONS. THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED THAT THERE IS A NEED<br />
FOR A MAJOR REVIEW OF THE PROGRAMS TO ENSURE THAT THEY FULLY<br />
MEET THE GOVERNMENT'S LABOUR MARKET POLICY OBJECTIVES. AN<br />
EXTERNAL COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY HEADED BY PETER KIRBY, CHAIRMAN<br />
OF THE TECHNICAL AND FURTHER EDUCATION BOARD OF VICTORIA<br />
HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED, WE ARE PARTICULARLY CONCERNED THAT THE PROGRAMS,<br />
THE MAJORITY OF WHICH ARE AIMED AT YOUNG PEOPLE, SHOULD BE<br />
BOTH COMPREHENSIVE AND INTEGRATED. ONLY IN THIS WAY CAN WE<br />
HOPE TO PROVIDE THE SKILLS NEEDED FOR FUTURE ECONOMIC<br />
DEVELOPMENT WHILE AT THE SAME TIME PROVIDING ADEQUATE SUPPORT<br />
TO THE MORE DISADVANTAGED MEMBERS OF SOCIETY WHO FIND IT<br />
DIFFICULT TO COMPETE IN THE OPEN MARKET WITHOUT ASSISTANCE. </p>
<p>THE COMMITTEE OF INQUIRY WILL BE MAKING AN INTERIM<br />
REPORT TO THE GOVERNMENT IN TIME FOR CONSIDERATION FOR THE NEXT<br />
BUDGET -AND A FINAL REPORT BEFORE THE END OF THIS YEAR.<br />
IN THE MEANTIME WE HAVE TAKEN STEPS TO STRENGTHEN<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY EXISTING PROGRAMS FOR YOUNG PEOPLE.<br />
WE HAVE EXPANDED THE COMMUNITY YOUTH SUPPORT SCHEME<br />
WITH A 27% INCREASE IN THE BUDGET ALLOCATION FOR THIS FINANCIAL<br />
YEAR. CYSS AIMS TO ENCOURAGE COMMUNITIES TO ASSIST LOCAL YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE THROUGH PERIODS O F UNEMPLOYMENT BY DEVELOPING THEIR<br />
SKILLS AND INCREASING THEIR~ SELF-RELIANCE. THE ADDITIONAL<br />
FUNDING HAS ALLOWED THE ESTABLISHMENT OF 31 NEW PROJECTS IN AREAS<br />
OF HIGH NEED. THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CYSS PROJECTS NOWI FUNDED<br />
THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA is 306. FUNDING FOR EXISTING PROGRAMS<br />
HAS ALSO BEEN SUBSTANTIALLY INCREASED:<br />
j GRANT LEVELS HAVE BEEN INCREASED BY UP To 21% TO<br />
TAKE ACCOUNT OF INCREASED PROJECT OPERATING COSTS;<br />
-38 EXISTING PROJECTS IN AREAS OF HIGH NEED HAVE HAD<br />
THEIR GRANT LEVELS UPGRADED.<br />
THESE MEASURES WILL ENSURE THAT CYSS PROJECTS CAN<br />
1CONTINUE TO PR OVIDE SUPPORT AND ASSIST IN MEETING THE NEEDS<br />
I OF UNEMPLOYED YOUNG PEOPLE IN-THEIR LOCAL AREA. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
WE HAVE MORE THAN DOUBLED THE FUNDING FOR THE<br />
VOLUNTEER YOUTH PROGRAM, THIS PROGRAM IS DESIGNED TO<br />
ASSIST UNEMPLOYED YOUNG PERSONS MAINTAIN AND DEVELOP THEIR<br />
CAPACITY FOR OBTAINING EMPLOYMENT THROUGH PARTICIPATION<br />
IN VOLUNTARY COMMUNITY SERVICE ACTIVITIES, WHILE THIS<br />
PROGRAM AT PRESENT INVOLVES ONLY 10 PROJECTS, SOME TWO<br />
AND A HALF THOUSAND YOUNG PEOPLE ARE EXPECTED TO TAKE<br />
ADVANTAGE OF THE OPPORTUNITIES OFFERED BY THE PROGRAM THIS<br />
YEAR. WE ARE PROVIDING MORE ASSISTANCE THAN EVER BEFORE<br />
UNDER THE SPECIAL YOUTH EMPLOYMENT TRAINING PROGRAM. THIS<br />
PROGRAM HELPS EMPLOYERS TAKE ON YOUNG PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN<br />
UNABLE TO ESTABLISH THEMSELVES IN THE LABOUR FORCE. IT PROVIDES<br />
NECESSARY WORK EXPERIENCE TO BRING THEM UP TO A LEVEL WHERE<br />
THEY ARE ABLE TO ADEQUATELY COMPETE FOR JOBS. THIS YEAR<br />
WE HOPE THAT SOME 90,000 YOUNG UNEMPLOYED WILL GAIN THE BENEFIT<br />
OF WORK EXPERIENCE UNDER THE PROGRAM,<br />
OVER THE PAST TWO YEARS THE YOUTH. EMPLOYMENT<br />
SITUATION HAS BEEN EXACERBATED BY A SERIOUS FALL IN THE NUMBER.<br />
OF APPRENTICESHIPS BECOMING AVAILABLE. THIS HAS AFFECTED BOTH<br />
SCHOOL LEAVERS SEEKING APPRENTICESHIPS AND THOSE WHO HAVE<br />
PARTIALLY COMPLETED THEIR APPRENTICESHIP BEFORE BEING LAID OFF.<br />
,17 </p>
<p>7.<br />
IN RESPONSE TO THIS SITUATION THE GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
ADOPTED A FLEXIBLE. APPROACH, ATTEMPTING AS FAR AS POSSIBLE<br />
TO TAILOR ASSISTANCE TO INDIVIDUAL NEEDS. ON THE ONE HAND<br />
WE PROVIDE SUBSTANTIAL ASSISTANCE TO PRIVATE EMPLOYERS TO<br />
ENCOURAGE THEM TO TAKE ON AND RETAIN APPRENTICES. ON THE<br />
OTHER, WE ARE PROV-IDING ASSISTANCE TO-THE STATES TO UNDERTAKE<br />
PRELIMINARY TRADE TRAINING COURSES FOR YOUNG PEOPLE UNABLE TO<br />
FIND AN APPRENTICESHIP. THE COURSES WILL GIVE PARTICIPANTS<br />
BASIC TRAINING IN THEIR CHOSEN TRADE AND MAKE THEM MORE<br />
ATTRACTIVE AS EMPLOYEES, AS THEY WILL NO LONGER HAVE TO BE<br />
TIRAINED FROM SCRATCH.<br />
THESE PRACTICAL MEASURES ARE BEING REINFORCED BY A<br />
MAJOR PROMOTIONAL CAMPAIGN FOCUSED ON INCREASING APPRENTICESHIP<br />
OPPORTUNITES FOR GRADUATES OF PRE-EMPLOYMENT COURSES AND<br />
THOSE WHO HAVE PARTLY COMPLETED THEIR APPRENTICESHIP. YOU<br />
MAY HAVE SEEN THE A: DVERTISEMENTS IN THE NATIONAL AND LOCAL<br />
PRESS ENCOURAGING EMPLOYERS TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF OPPORTUNITIES<br />
FOR EMPLOYING PARTLY TRAINED APPRENTICES.<br />
TOTAL EXPENDITURE ON MANPOWER AND TRAINING PROGRAMS<br />
IN 1983-84 IS EXPECTED TO BE $ 958 MILLION AN OVERALL<br />
INCREASE IN FUNDING OF 80% WHEN COMPARED WITH THE PREVIOUS<br />
YEAR. </p>
<p>THESE PROGPAMS ARE ALL CONCERNED WITH ASSISTING YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE AFTER THEY HAVE LEFT SCHOOL, I BELIEVE, HOWEVER, THAT<br />
WE ALSO NEED TO LOOK AT THE PROBLEMS BEING FACED BY AUSTRALIA'S<br />
YOUNG PEOPLE IN RELATION TO THE COMPARATIVELY LOW RETENTION<br />
RATES AT AUSTRALIAN SCHOOLS AND TERTIARY INSTITUTIONS.<br />
IN TODAY'S WORLD, YOUNG PEOPLE NEED A BROAD,<br />
DURABLE BASE OF SKILLS SO THAT THEY CAN PLAY A FULL PART IN<br />
SOCIETY AND BE SUCCESSFUL IN AN INCREASINGLY COMPETITIVE<br />
EMPLOYMENT MARKET IN AN INCREASINGLY COMPETITIVE WORLD ECONOMY,<br />
To TAKE MAXIMUM ADVANTAGE OF THE OPPORTUNITIES BEING MADE<br />
AVAILABLE THROUGH TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGE, YOUNG PEOPLE TODAY<br />
NEED MORE THAN THE ESSENTIAL SKILLS OF LITERACY AND NUMERACY.<br />
OUR YOUTH NEEDS FLEXIBILITY AND BROAD UNDERSTANDING SO THAT THEY<br />
ARE ABLE TO ADAPT READILY TO NEW TECHNOLOGIES AND THE RAPID<br />
PACE OF CHANGE. EDUCATION AND TRAINING MUST BE SEEN AS A LIFE-LONG<br />
PROCESS AS IT IS CERTAIN THAT MANY PEOPLE IN THE FUTURE WILL<br />
HAVE TO CHANGE THEIR OCCUPATION DURING THEIR WORKING LIFE.<br />
INCREASED SCHOOLING AND TRAINING ARE VITAL IF YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE ARE TO ACQUIRE THESE SKILLS AND REALISE THEIR FULL<br />
POTENTIAL AND IF AUSTRALIA IS TO HAVE THE SKILLED WORKFORCE<br />
WE NEED. GOVERNMENT POLICY AIMS TO ENCOURAGE INCREASED<br />
SCHOOLING AND TRAINING AFTER THE LEGAL SCHOOL LEAVING AGE. </p>
<p>IN PARTICULAR WE WANT TO ASSIST THE DISADVANTAGED<br />
AND OTHERS WHO LEAVE SCHOOL LACKING THE SKILL NECE3SARY TO<br />
OBTAIN JOBS, TO STAY ON.<br />
ACCORDINGLY, WE HAVE ALLOCATED $ 75.3 MILLION TO<br />
THE PARTICIPATION AND EQUITY PROGRAM IN 1984, THIS PROGRAM<br />
IS DIRECTLY AIMED AT REDUCING THE NUMBERS OF STUDENTS LEAVING<br />
FULL-TIME EDUCATION PREMATURELY WITH PARTICULAR EMPHASIS<br />
ON THOSE SCHOOLS WHERE MANY DO LEAVE EARLY. THE PROGRAM<br />
WILL BUILD UPON ACTIVITIES ALREADY UNDERWAY IN SCHOOLS<br />
AROUND AUSTRALIA, TO PROVIDE SUPPORT FOR INITIATIVES AND<br />
NEW IDEAS IN AREAS SUCH AS CURRICULUM CHANGE, ASSESSMENT, AND<br />
CO-OPERATION WITH THE TAFE SECTION. AN INTEGRAL PART OF THE<br />
PROGRAM WILL BE MEASURES TO MEET THE NEEDS OF GROUPS SUCH AS<br />
GIRLS, ABORIGINALS AND THOSE FROM NON-ENGLISH SPEAKING<br />
BACKGROUNDS, WHO HAVE TENDED TO BE DISADVANTAGED WITHIN THE<br />
EDUCATION SYSTEM,<br />
ALONG WITH THE NEED FOR -INCREASING PARTICIPATION<br />
AT THE SECONDARY LEVEL THERE IS A NEED FOR IMPROVED ACCESS TO<br />
TERTIARY EDUCATION. THE GOVERNMENT HAS PROVIDED A FURTHER<br />
MILLION IN 1984 FOR UNIVERSITIES AND COLLEGES OF ADVANCED<br />
EDUCATION FOR AN ADDITIONAL 3000 PLACES IN HIGHER EDUCATION. </p>
<p>WE SEE IT AS IMPORTANT ALSO THAT SCHOOLS PROVIDE<br />
VOCATIONALLY RELEVANT TRAINING. IN THE PRESENT DAY AND AGE<br />
COMPUTER LITERACY IS BECOMING AN INCREASINGLY ESSENTIAL<br />
PREREQUISITE TC A WIDE RANGE OF JOBS. ACCORDINGLY THE<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS INITIATED A NATIONAL COMPUTER EDUCATION PROGRAM<br />
OF $ 18M OVER THE NEXT THREE YEARS TO ENSURE THAT SCHOOLS<br />
PROVIDE AN ADEQUATE UNDERSTANDING OF THE USES OF NEW<br />
TECHNOLOGY, ITS IMPACT ON THE NATURE OF WORK, JOB OPPORTUNITIES<br />
AND TO REMEDY BASIC DEFICIENCIES IN COMPUTER LITERACY.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT CONVENTIONAL EDUCATION<br />
AND TRAINING PROGRAMS ARE NOT THE ONLY WAYS OF APPROACHING<br />
THE YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT PROBLEM OR INDEED UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
GENERALLY. WE SEE MERIT IN EXAMINING A RANGE OF POSSIBLE<br />
ALTERNATIVES INCLUDING CHANGES TO EXISTING WORK PATTERNS,<br />
AND SUPPORT FOR WORKER CO-OPERATIVES OR SMALL BUSINESSES<br />
ESTABLISHED BY THE UNEMPLOYED AS WELL AS DEVELOPMENT OF<br />
APPROACHES OUTSIDE THE CONVENTIONAL PRODUCTION SYSTEM.<br />
AS A RESULT WE HAVE EMBARKED UPON SOME EXPLORATORY INVESTIGATIONS<br />
INTO SUCH INNOVATIVE APPROACHES.<br />
THESE IDEAS ARE BREAKING NEW GROUND IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
AND AS SUCH, WILL NEED TIME AND CAUTION IN THEIR DEVELOPMENT.<br />
HOWEVER, THE COMMONWEALTH IS CONCERNED THAT THIS WORK SHOULD<br />
PROGRESS AND IS GIVING IT PRIORITY, IT IS ENCOURAGING TO SEE<br />
THE DEVELOPMENTS BY THE STATE GOVERNMENTS IN THIS AREA.<br />
,/ il </p>
<p>-11-<br />
THE PROBLEMS OF YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT ARE NOT ONLY<br />
THOSE THAT CAN BE MEASURED BY STATISTICS ALTHOUGH THEY<br />
ARE ALARMING ENOUGH, THE RAMIFICATIONS ARE WIDESPREAD AND<br />
ARE REACHING DEEP INTO THE NATURE OF OUR SOCIETY,<br />
THIS GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT<br />
MUST BE DEALT WITH IN A MANNER THAT BOTH RECOGNISES ITS<br />
IMPORTANCE, IN TERMS OF MAGNITUDE AND IMMEDIACY AND THE<br />
MANY SIDED NATURE OF THE PROBLEM. THERE IS MUCH MORE TO<br />
SOLVING THE PROBLEM THAN GIVING A HAND OUT TOGETHER WITH<br />
SOME GRATUITOUS NAME CALLING, THESE YOUNG PEOPLE ARE<br />
NOT UNEMPLOYED THROUGH ANY WISH OR FAULT OF THEIR OWN.<br />
THEY NEED TO BE GIVEN A CHANCE OR AS THE COMMITTEE HAS<br />
SO APTLY PUT IT: " GIVE YOUTH A FAIR Go",<br />
THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICIES AND PROGRAMS WHICH<br />
I MENTIONED EARLIER ARE NOT ONLY THERE TO PROVIDE THE NECESSARY<br />
FINANCIAL SUPPORT FOR THE UNEMPLOYED; THEY ARE ALSO POSITIVELY<br />
AIMED AT ASSISTING OUR YOUTH ACQUIRE THOSE SKILLS AND<br />
ABILITIES THAT WILL ENABLE THEM TO PARTICIPATE IN FULL AS<br />
MEMBERS OF THEIR COMMUNITY, BUT AS WITH OUR MACRO ECONOMIC<br />
POLICIES THE GOVERNMENT CAN ONLY PROVIDE AN APPROPRIATE FRAMEWORK<br />
AND SENSE OF DIRECTION THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE MUST BE<br />
INVOLVED IN MAKING THEM WORK. </p>
<p>13,<br />
IT IS FOR THIS REASON THAT I AM PARTICULARLY<br />
HEARTENED BY THE ACTIONS OF THIS COMMITTEE. WITHOUT WAITING<br />
FOR GOVERNMENT INITIATIVES OR ASSISTANCE YOU HAVE SET OUT TO<br />
MEET THE CHALLENGES OFFERED BY OUR ECONOMIC CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
IN THE BEST WAY POSSIBLE BY GENERATING JOBS FOR YOUNG<br />
PEOPLE. FURTHERMORE THIS IS BEING DONE THROUGH THE RESOURCES<br />
OF LOCAL COMMUNITY GROUPS, I AM SURE THAT AS THE RECOVERY<br />
GATHERS PACE YOU WILL HAVE INCREASING OPPORTUNITIES FOR<br />
EXPANDING YOUR WORK,<br />
THE WAY THE COMMITTEE HAS HARNESSED THE TALENTS AND ENERGIES<br />
OF A WIDE SECTION OF THE BUSINESS AND WIDER COMMUNITY IS<br />
ESPECIALLY IMPRESSIVE, YOURS IS EXACTLY THE TYPE OF<br />
CO-OPERATIVE ENDEAVOUR THAT IS NECESSARY TO COMPLEMENT THE<br />
EFFORTS OF GOVERNMENT, IT IS FURTHER EVIDENCE OF THE<br />
VALUE AND STRENGTH OF CO-OPERATION AMONGST AUSTRALIANS TO<br />
ADDRESS A GREAT NATIONAL ISSUE,<br />
I KNOW YOU WILL ALL HAVE BEEN HEARTENED BY THE<br />
ACCUMULATION OF INCREASINGLY UNEQUIVOCAL AND PERSUASIVE EVIDENCE<br />
THAT THE ECONOMY HAS TURNED AROUND AND BROUGHT WITH IT<br />
SIGNIFICANT GROWTH IN NATIONAL EMPLOYMENT LEVELS,<br />
I AM SURE YOU WOULD ALL AGREE, HOWEVER, THAT THIS<br />
IMPROVEMENT OFFERS NO CAUSE FOR COMPLACENCY.<br />
FOR ITS PART, THE GOVERNMENT IS AIMING TO CONSOLIDATE<br />
THIS RESURGENCE IN ACTIVITY BY PUTTING IN PLACE AND MAINTAINING<br />
AN APPROPRIATE MIX OF POLICIES. </p>
<p>14.<br />
THERE IS ALSO A CONTINUING NEED FOR MAXIMISING<br />
OPPORTUNTITIES AND FOR EXTENDING THE TYPE OF WORK AND<br />
COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT OF THE KIND INITIATED BY THIS<br />
COMMITTEE. I WELCOME THE COMMITMENT YOU HAVE MADE AND PRAISE<br />
THE APPROACH YOU ARE TAKING,<br />
I COMMEND THE COMMITTEE IN THE STRONGEST TERMS<br />
AS AN EXAMPLE TO THE REST OF THE COMMUNITY,<br />
I CONGRATULATE YOU AND I WISH YOU WELL IN THE<br />
PURSUIT OF YOUR GREAT OBJECTIVES, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
