<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6927</transcript-id>
    <title>SEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER NANJING UNIVERSITY - 23 MAY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006927.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ CAI N T~ r C<br />
j m! ' siVER 23 MAY 1986<br />
0~ W1. I( YOU ' lAVE P AZT'i<br />
Y 4' tTJA7TAEO PPOWRURNTAITY'Y T. T To TLk AT n-CS<br />
T; rT.: 7tff % EITY, AN I.-: TI iiTF LEARNIG WITH WHICH AUSFIALIA<br />
C 7I1 ' cCAxN EL SHALP. z CTOSE NANJING UNIVERSITY<br />
FCH ! 4 CHANCA . GAMK. EMET S WITH FOUR UNIVERSITIES IN MY<br />
A;. iL~ T~ v~ y' 2 CEx TO HOST VISITS TO AUSTRALIA IN<br />
C . T V TX 7-7 7 T rNDN A ! vUMV. ER OF PROFESSORIAL<br />
' AV X ANSION AND STRENGTHE*% NIG OF<br />
1LTTLIA At C-SA. WHIC H rAVE ACCE L EATED IN<br />
1 ANn -DU PuiZ Eu<br />
7. 7 r-V 7 G : 3 84TH YEAR. SINCE THIS<br />
N'c~ l 
C-ll . Z LY AY CONTRY IN:) THE IiS<br />
2. Y A %' y&gt; rC 0w U TRYN<br />
-1 cl-' 7TN<br />
A r[ f<br />
7 A -f :; yL f7 A T~ CI, T S<br />
TV? E LATE?" CAPTUR IN THS HZSORY CeN HAS<br />
C TCTCOQ; ICR CHINAP: TOTr aUTAI TOR THE ACI-'-' CIFIC<br />
CIA.\ E TC C'J-A: TAL9) TK hE 7L Ai<br />
A-4 WATC
CNWE R-COGNSE IS<br />
rI"; 3 T7T PW' 7DAAR S S &gt; AiN iN ATIYE ITS CO NCEPTIONf AND<br />
7) Z7 -0 7 1 T -r c .4 A A ! Wl17 R IS<br />
" I i-n U N E-E Z.<br />
TA ' ECG' U<br />
' mT-2 ~ c TEJ~ i THEA~ AS TR<br />
C~~ I~~ IA WE' 2( A c-p3E TCVPR 7HSI YTR PLANA WHTICEFHSE<br />
QUA~-fT E? L 7N: .7 a 1 CEN AD -12 PERCENT<br />
Cu W 7-9&gt; 2 CY INA A NOTi O0F CCOU ' SF.<br />
-c . LVv I\ TN ' U NiDV LCSOLRFD<br />
2T 7E' AREI. PicS7 Ii A U A LIA ElVYT H E VE$; GOOD START<br />
C lNA H4AS JIADE WE AR ALSO COVSCIOUS THAT CHINA ITSELF SEES THIS<br />
ON LY TYC-O__ 0PE NIN-G-SAG E I N A VF7 RY LON G T E. R7t pROC E SS. YOU HAVE THE<br />
TA L OF QUADRUL NG OUTPJ I Y T&gt; ET RN OF THE CENTURY. THAT WOULD<br />
' RA rTEcUSACHrCFC L STILL, AS HAS BEEN SAIV OLTH<br />
RsQCT kap. 1. t A<br />
A T R1? I S NOT FCOR-THE EASIEST ATHLETIC r7EAT TO<br />
*. 12/ </p>
<p>SJ 124C:<br />
A'COMPLISH. WE ARE ALL REALISTS-~ EKNOW THAT PLANNING SOMrETHING IS<br />
DLIcF7RENT FROM. ACC N6 IT T E c'' NTRY WITH THE OLDEST<br />
CTNUIOS HIST-ORY AND CITVILISATION IN TH-E WORLD, CHINA HAS FAR TO')<br />
jecH WISOM TO FAIL TO UNDSEzSTAND HOW EVENTS AND Ci-RCUMSTANCES WILL<br />
NECESSARILY COMPEL AfDJUSTMEN7S To EVEN THE BEST LAID PLANS. THE<br />
ACHIEVEMENT OF LCONOMIC GROWTH AND DEVELOIPMENT INEVITABELY INVOLVES<br />
THE UNCERTAINTY AND SOMIETIMES THE AGONY OF CONSTANTLY READJUSTING ANDDEVELOPING<br />
POLICY 10O MEET NEW CIRCUMSTANCES AND PROBLEMS.<br />
AS A POLITICAL PRACTITIONER T KNIw THIS WELL. AND I AM AWARE<br />
T?-AT CHINA HAS ENCoUNTERED PROBLEMS IN SUCH AREAS AS TH-' E BALANCE OF<br />
S~ THE AV. ATIAOIL. T F O-EG EX CHANGE AND CoNRLO<br />
3 S; INOW 1,41 T7HE LE ADcRG i CHINA. I i\ NOW THEIR<br />
T4ATI: To SURmi0UNT THESE SECONOM1IC DIFFICULTIES AND THE<br />
S, R G 0~ F R rE 1. C M, IT MlE NT oU TH DCE RN ISA T I) N R0 CE SS THIS<br />
cP7~ T O URG " V~ AI DISCUSSIONS IN 2BEIJIN\ Gj IN<br />
C E~ G~ U A E 11.1; NAN~ JING. ThEc VIEION 100ERNISA TIoN ISC-<br />
". EC EhAhE SEEEN AS SUSTAI ~ FO1T)<br />
7l V Ai~ E A<br />
U L_ Z4A~ A j/ k: Io p MEN C-iI\ T%! A S. Lm PE' Y A~ MATTER<br />
IEj, co N03A9Yo~ GRESS AS DETAC. HED<br />
V~ FO ; CS ECAUSE W A. 3<br />
C. OAkR T ( K AN ; 7E2AOV E THE CAPABILITY<br />
8J T-l Kk,! T~ A AC7.<br />
qA tW4 HI 9T 5 7 TE: O<br />
Tu x AREST T~ DN<br />
AN C_ EATIoNG<br />
IT; PN: D SNT A -l COUNTRIES.<br />
SPECIAL I N ITSEL<br />
T C RTAGT~<br />
O\ C WE ARE C! C, 7G0-02 ; 1i7 I<br />
7A-IL: 3T:~ xVAC STN~ Il U ,5
: 7 C, SlZ * J AtT~ 7 1T TA w H<br />
A L C~ AuT4~. ? UL UAO T-' L<br />
7~ V ON<br />
% I r C'LRL. 7 CIE G7 . -nCN<br />
AN\ AT b 07 7 c J; U<br />
eUTALA L7~ CHNA IS; VER A WE RA~ CT EYN OT TER<br />
S CCA7ET IODU R CAIA 7rCEI T IF ArE TOUDESAN<br />
CTN7 7U NA C7 2ROlERY X T~ OL F TIOH IAA" vE TRE<br />
CO A&amp; uR Nu u'I. NScj~ PCœ Z BTCe. CE TT<br />
* M~ SY 7ASL~ AS\ 1 E P, E~ O~ CLA OIN A. TIO<br />
OrN MOST')~ TEOAAT -UT l APRATS FOR~ VThISOR WH OCMACT E EOXTETU O<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>M VTS: T Sy-2. oLISESc MY GOVERNMENT'S AWARENESS OF THE<br />
1. P OR AC tC: TH . ORNSAT 1ON TAKI NG FLA CF HE RE A'-D THE<br />
THAT FOR OUR RELATIONSHIP.<br />
IT TAK ES ONLY A GLANCE AT THE MAP AND THE READING OF ANY<br />
STANDARD REFERENCE TO SEE THAT WE ARE AT DIFFERENJ ENDS OF THE<br />
kcESTERN PACIFIC OCEANv THAT WE HAVE DIFFERENT POLITICAL AND CULTURAL<br />
TRADITIONS, AND THAT OUR ECONOMIES CONTRAST IN CERTAIN FUNDAMENTAL<br />
RESFECTS. NEVERTHELESS WE DO OCCUPY THE SAME GENERAL REGION OF THE<br />
WORLD. O) UR D: 7FFERENT SYSTEMS Do) NOT MEAN! THiAT OUR PEOPLES HAVE<br />
7~ CE E APRATIONS FOR SECURITTY AND FOR A BETTER LIFE. AND OUR<br />
c Q rr " T ECON( STRU1CTURES ARE ACTUALLY A SOURCc OF STRENGTH<br />
0 i : z A7ERA! PAR,, LE SH 1,.<br />
~ A ~ vYFEW ER PEOPLE TH-AN,, C~ iNA BUT! v AT THE SAME<br />
A ~ UC~ i PR CAPTIA ENDOWMENT O ROUCS<br />
HAVYT TECiH'J&gt;_;_.) GiCA;_ SKILLS INDUSTRIAL CAPABLMIES. THESE<br />
F AC TO~ EHANCE OUR P07 NTIAL 1I!' PORTANCE TO EACH OTHER. AUSTRALIA<br />
7; ~ OSE1 7OED TO0i ~ A HE IMPOR T A NT CON7RTB2U-ON To THE<br />
T SAAT'. x T IE FIV~ YE .7 AN) A. ND BEYoNG. THIS<br />
cON-:: fC; c' S AE NO(. T QLy 7HRO1H T R L) T. BUAL S T GH<br />
.&amp; VEES. S TRMCEYN I EA CH OT HER'I S I N I) U STR 1E S TCN: CAL Co-<br />
7E. E9AN T T Ci! A K rE.( PtZ ; N A':: zS S-_ A NC E<br />
E; M14 XAAC. RN OI 13 A'LREAD VE DE,\' I7 2 1 ,; iE PA-' TERNI<br />
&gt; M S' 7 u Y. ARA S T' T OUR EXPO(' RTS WcERE WOOL,<br />
&gt; ONAOU~ AM~; ~ I~. HEMAOR 8INCHlINA' S; EXPO RTS TO US<br />
WERTE i :-js; r UCArC-UUUDEuSi -AZ EX-Tl<br />
777 P A'T OUR TWO CO'; q TE ARE C~ lHN7LED<br />
_ N" PEASF TN ' AY RD AS7 YEAP<br />
3 8P C S. 7 poCT-s y T:: E 007LJTo'\ CCo N 1C RrLA7: O0,<br />
-: 7C r~_ AYAC7AD L~ g<br />
RilE rS 1 A.-c OR t) PEbT NO' SO0<br />
r F'U: FT17 oRR,:. T : Y TiS-iS A UL 1<br />
l N: j C ) f7 C. I I~ T I Ok Y -7 T 7C I SE SE iZ 7; IT T<br />
A TiC_ ' R. i A. P5THC GO" PCH 7: F -7<br />
T% A TAV~ T VT. C~ TOA~. Ti<br />
A, 9 TXr ' N yC3A 7 Vc QW AS LAS E,(<br />
THYE MOfS DY P TVNE IN CHY AN YEARTT THR THE<br />
RROCr-Sci WE WANTr CONTRI-, UT THAT PROCESS..<br />
WE 0~ () OLICY mODERNISATION AS -LOSELY CONNECTE:: D TO YOUR<br />
pUolE y OF7 oOPpENt -% 9 THE OPENING OF S DOOR TO THCE<br />
14 </p>
<p>OUTSIDE WORLD IS A MARK OF YOUR CONFIDENCE AS A GREAT PEOPLE<br />
TmAT YOU CAN S0TH DRAW BENEFITS FROM OTHER COUNTRIES AND G:-IVE<br />
2&gt; EFITS ACK TO THEM. IT WAS MOST WLELCOME TO US THATPRMEZAO<br />
IN HIS SPEECH ON THE SEVENTH FIVE YEAR PLAN AT'jT HE NATIONAL<br />
PEOPLE'S CO) NGRESS IN MARCHi STRONGLY REAFFIRMED CHINA'S COMMITMENT<br />
TO THIS PO'LICY. WE WISH YOU SUCCESS IN CONSLIDATING MAJOR<br />
ECONOMIC REFORMS MADE TO DATE, AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO THE<br />
CO. NTINUATION OF THE PROCESS OF MAKING THE CHINESE ECONOMY MORE<br />
RE_ S PONSIVE AND MORE OUTWARD LOOKING.<br />
YOU CAN BE SURE THAT1 AUSTRALIAN POLICY WILL. REMAIN THE POLICY<br />
0: TE OiEPN_ DOO0R AS WE LL THE IMPORTANCE To MY COUNTRY OF FOREIGN<br />
Mt. ARL \ E: S OVERSFE75 CAPITALi AS ' WELL AS T7E VERY CLOSE* BOINDS<br />
F! U. r. ED OV T~ MGhA7TON,' fr-TODAY'S AUS73ALIA INTERNA TIONALIST RY<br />
N TU N A 0~ 7 7 c-C A ND INT EL LI. G ENT C o-0P E R ATIo N B AcE D<br />
j\ 32LE N 7 T 1 OU RTC KN IC AL S KI L!_ S AN NATURAL RESOURCES<br />
' AN 2 E 1 AuE A VA 1L A E TF C 0UNI R 1ESE T HA T l\' E E D TH E M<br />
ATTH_ " 4 W_ RcEA'! S= E THAT OUR SMALLER ECONOMY CANNOT DO<br />
CAN DR. W FROM OTHER COUNTRIES' SPECIALISED<br />
U r'UT S t4I C LA r CA! 2NC pr t iC FC Tf-1.\ 1V CO R OREVS<br />
CA N ALIS 1 1 RA ( uR C ER C0J-\ T~ iEcE' PRO'DUCTS WHICH ARE DEST MADE<br />
LAhEA;; C'VS A2. UR. SUJCH Cc--OERA~ l IN, SOCR IWHICH<br />
ERLA TiU. hAR : UA L.-,\ EAj n4AKzS BOTH. COU; NTR1ES<br />
V E P2OC! I C l-1 E VISIOP" OF M( fc', R,\ JSAT ION. BUT A L! L<br />
Y~: O r F UU SIMPLY EECALJSE<br />
' C:? zE _ HV ER _ 7 RA T CINS3YE TATT HPE is UIAN<br />
1. AS : 7 7ET71A A7L. O~ CIA<br />
S -3A L 1.4 b ~ YV L V S S G, OU R RE CE S. SVEN<br />
U2ATZ C;~. LO7 ' jv.: t) c* 3NA T 0N ' EC No C)<br />
0% : Y. TIG STu~ 1T IN\ PL AC: 7 z* 1 PATTE RN S 0g<br />
IO AT ARE T AN~ i 0U 7A-L RD OF 1IYING N<br />
P C NG WORLD~, Wi~-O) W THAT IWE TOO MUST JST AND RESTRUCTURE.<br />
3A,; 7 T C SO ORDNER TODIVERS. F . SR'ASœ OOYASDT<br />
A A' S Y TO( T r .4D E 44' Q L: IT ~ C WITh. TrHE WoRL D I N<br />
PP RCDU) C AN D 3, E RIk) CS<br />
~ c -c) R: A ARE I " 7 1 PURS IN E<br />
-LE r -i ENHANC 7N6I A CCO'! NR'<br />
CuE_ T HE ; 40RLD ECONOMIC AND tPOLiTTICA SS T A GE. oN THI1S<br />
AG-C1-I NA CA \% j -5RE:~ C Rr* IO'NL Y B EC O ME A ST GR:_ TT HR PL AYER.<br />
YT'N S AT SC O d'STOlR COCN7 i-R"' C
A~ C C IC; ASINCL _ X -_ ND ' EYi) NI'D MATTERZS<br />
7 r-11 ANALA: . lET 1) R 0.7-ADN TINA<br />
HV, v NCA ' I' 1 S SU v-17D. I NG5 7 NATE fRA<br />
' ENNAT L ( I C A lYL VEM'. ! NTERNAT IO( NAL F" RUS<br />
TI r~~. ENPYSE R\ AT : 1 I T3' YA 2 TYCi C. L; Q. R T y~_ T<br />
A. V 0' Y u ZuL 7 ANj c ER ZT I c TL S Z'S PE7R-IT A vE. RY<br />
C REI-ONSHIP TO E. C SUS TA EVEN WHE -IE AUST RAL IA AN D CH INA<br />
A IF E R EN T p -RE PECC T V FS ON A PARTICULAR NTERNATIONAL OR<br />
REGlONAL ISSUE.<br />
PREMIER ZHAO HAS SAID THAT THW WHOLE WORLD IS CONFRONGED WITH<br />
7" WO MAJO'. R CHALLENGcESs To tIA: NTAIN PEACE AND TO PROMOTE DEVELOPMENT.<br />
O.' 4 T IS IUADM? NSTO~ L UTEL'Y AGREE.<br />
HO'vW CAN EITHER AUSTRALIA'S ASPIRATIONS OR CHINA'S VISIONS BE<br />
U -f A. </p>
<p>REiALISED IN A WORLD WHICH IS NOT AT PEACE?<br />
FURTHERmt* i ' N A NUCLEAR WORLD IT IS AN OBVIOUS BUT VITALLY<br />
U'MPRTANT TRUTH THAT CONFLICT COULD MEAN NOT JUST A TEMPRARY SETBACK<br />
TO SOME OF O1UR HOPES, BUT THE ' LITERAL OBLITERATION OF ALL OUR HOPES.<br />
T:-iERE-MUST THEREFORE BE INTERNATIONAL STABILITY. THERE MUST 2EE<br />
AROMS CONTROL AND THERE M1UST ULTIMATELY BE DISARMAMENT. THOSE ARE<br />
CqUCIAL OBJECTIVES WHICH CHINA AND AUSTRALIA SHARE.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT HAS NEVER ACCEPTED THAT PE-ACE IS AN ISSUE OF<br />
LEGITIMATE INTEREST ONLY TO THE BIG POWERS OR THAT OTHERS CANNOT<br />
; J IDEAS AND EXERT INFLUENCE. INDEED MY GOVERNMENT HAS MADE A<br />
E7FFORT To DO JUST THIS. THROUGH A RANGE OF POLICIES9<br />
T C JMDNG ADVOCACY A COrPREHEN3-IVE NUCLEAR TEST BAN, AUSTRALIA<br />
h-ACT: V'EY SoUjGHT A iltRE 5TABLEC AND SECURE7 ENVIRONMENT AND TO)<br />
CO'~~'~ PROGRESS TOWA. RDS [ ITSARMAiMENT.<br />
E T, S 3~ i S'ic , COUNT-RIES WITH NUCLEAR WEAPONS, INCLUDING<br />
C-! IA, AS HAVI,\ G SPEC' AL RESPONSISILITIES TO CONTAIN AND WIND BACK<br />
, c TH VE371CAL AN" H03LO" T ?'. OLI* ERATION OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS.<br />
C' A RH" DES: HGOWNG RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN OUR<br />
T~ C Y~~ A ~ E 9~ S; HS VITAL ISUS MUCH MORE<br />
: GULARLY AN-U GR EP. TH AN PE-oRE.<br />
AP: EA a EP~ C C _ J] N A HAS GIVEN THE INITIA ; V TAKEN<br />
z i IuN 7 -SI'C, TCE AUSTRAIA-INCLUDED9 TO ES _ A P, I SH<br />
soT'. AC~ C~ 7V 5,~ AAESTAELISI-A SOU-rH PAC7' FIC<br />
L2:. . lœ rY HIHAS BEEN NEGOT7-IA! E) WAS<br />
. T Y lV THE7. SOU Tk PACIFIC FORUM,' AND HiAS<br />
F~ Y TFTEH REE. HRISN<br />
C' T:--~~ AA IN 4~ xxG E PSOTVEAPPROACH IT PAS hAS<br />
' 7 C~ WjU 7E7 E2 õ VE. TEN ME( S TE OTH<br />
TRi y:<br />
7 -N7. cEAA' : AS: I3C NIFICAN-T ACHIEVEM'ENT AS<br />
C" -Ri3IJ71IN TO SECURITYA<br />
I: U REGIO0 N.<br />
7 i~ r~ T H:-E iN I SC-W oRH LD CO0M M UNI TY HA S OC . S S E<br />
AT -77 V: 7ARS, ECO" U;' f .' O õ P'ENTi S. ITIA Ti7L Y CON D<br />
-AC. 1D'CK EN4 MAE I0 -T~ HREU LP OSITION OF m<br />: 1? T ION OF REATIV!-<br />
v.' E L1T07 3 0 N H-iE PAR3T OF MANY OF THoSE COUNTRAE<br />
E, e I~ yS ! N CO SULSTITUTE F~ OR TIA IAI<br />
IC C. TNA* S H A I<br />
SI( C SC7 E7 TT G R0 W T -AS STAYE,-AHEA' O<br />
i Ax.. ' TA: ETO~ ~ TH OL IHT-RAt-7C<br />
7 i A A R' IC A NEEXESS UCH REMAINS _ 3C<br />
i ;% 7GT A5 O~ ENV1YO0\ . NT HAS MA,-IE I T 0<br />
cl;* Y h A 7T" 4E-S C H EH GR OW H TARGETS THEY<br />
REL~ AT IoNS oOTR. E A,\ 4D S,' J THL M U S7 BE B A SE D-ON B, O) T HULCO N G<br />
R P IJ ~ C A~ L CnCICGœ( E) NT AN E 01' No IC GOOD SENSE. AUST.-ALIAN<br />
P: ThICY RECOGNISc THE IMPORTANCE OF A1i~) AND WE PROVIDE IT. BUT<br />
IxC7 ALSO1 RECOCNIISE T. HAT THIS IS NOT ENOUGH.<br />
T: RADE IS A CIONTRIBUTOR TO GROWTH AND DEVELOPMENT. THIS<br />
I 5N ' A;('~ CVOIANMCES RNED THAT WE MUST RESIST PR'SSURE. S<br />
OR ROEIO: MAN-tc W IY 1 INSIST TIHAT INTERNATIONAL NEGOTIATIONS<br />
PASEC)-O" N SECURING AN OPEN TRADING SYSTEM. / 6 </p>
<p>BJ1284U<br />
AGL-ADjUSTMENT IN THE DEVELOPED COU",, TRI7S IS I. PORTANTi<br />
PARTICULARLY IN THOSE SECTORS WHERE DEVELO PINGj CO-UNTRIES HAVE A<br />
REAL CHANCE OF GAINING MARKETS BECAUSE OF THEIR COMPARATIVE<br />
ADVANTAGE. INVESTMEN-IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES NEEDS TO: BE PURSUED<br />
WITH VIGOUR BY THOSE COUNTRIES WHICH ARE CAPITAL EXPORTERS.<br />
AS THE FIVE PRINCIPLES O F CHINA'S FOREIGN POLICY RECOGNISEi AND<br />
AS THE CHARTER OF THE UNITED NATIONS DOES ALSOi A WORLD ORDER<br />
eASED ON NORMS OF BEHAVIOUR FOR ALL COUNTRIESi GREAT AND SMALLi<br />
D"~_~~ ADDEVELOPING WILL BE BETTER THAN ONE BASED ON NAKED<br />
PotW. C* R A) FE,,, R OF THA T P! O'WE-R. CHINA AND AUSTRALIA ARE IN FUNDAMENTAL<br />
0O. 1 \ 1ETTH IS. WLL-SPR-L: FO 3 SUCH NCl,. AS OF l,'\ TcRNATILONAL<br />
CO'I~ s H COMMON DESIRE FOR PEACEi SEC"-URITY AND A BETTER LIFE<br />
il. A-TCH U'MAN BEINMIS SHARE AND WHICH TRANSCZeN%,,' IDEOLOGICAL<br />
CLE \ CEL WE CANN\ OT IN TH FCEO PTEYAL DANGERS BE NAIVE<br />
&gt; ORFREIG OR O UP. MEENCE POLICIES BUT tE MUST RETAIN OUR<br />
IDEA". IF PE-AC'E-AND DEVELOPMENT ARE To BE FURTHERE-D OVER THE LONG<br />
1 r~ v CO~ UNTh~ R ' C %-. HAVE I NTENSE POL IT ICAL DIALOGUE ON MAY ISSUES,<br />
EJT 7E 11E 19S A H A30 ER N 0OF FOREIGN PO) LITCY PRINCIPLES<br />
C-t OJLD SAY AQE 2 YOND PARTISAN DEBATE. i'NE OF THEM', IS THE<br />
: 0 0K~~ S 34A U 17177A C'E ZN UR VIEW Cl7T;-4E WO0" L D, ON A SI A<br />
YC U., 7R Y~ TH-R EG IN KC-' A U ST.' A A A ND CHITN A<br />
A IN t-1. T1ITCE~ Lht -I~ T R S IE JR AI-LY C. E N GN<br />
N DCDJ~ IAL DYAI. L iAVE PEEN<br />
C ONS N f ) R T YYE AR S RQ77EI T(" j LLC ER<br />
CUNFL. F T '~ WA DiTELAE A5A: 70' S. I<br />
TPE U~ T~( I ITjIGUO ( 7UIYC-UA<br />
FC i~ in C CR0,.-TH RA7r'C Ac E'~ E a ASIAN<br />
. T S. HAS BFN SUCCESSFUL NTTT( N-ULDGAMG<br />
A~ lN IENDS WITH7 TH oMATIO :' IF ) SA. PSTc:~<br />
r: AL 7VA -2 1 y -F MTCC2 ( r. 0 IpGT7 NSAT'I2T) U ' rl0N;\ J LD. NG<br />
3~ UT IN TH SOiUTH PACFW AS.&gt; R ISDC AS<br />
f A c': Sx T AT 10 C ' Orl 7RATO I N A OF F(, R U<br />
~ S7 RA L 1A A N-D C H N .4 4\ O A 7 -7T LL AR~ EAS<br />
' HE REGION.<br />
C Th E GOA L Cl U 7 ZV'F fC;~ I N DC ;<br />
C-~ 3~ AE ' O 7 r NJE: TTA;, C:-L LFc' AN, 0 L&gt;( A YOUt<br />
AITAL TA S A RO0ACH A SF BEEN T XLiEA'T':,)-PEACE-UL<br />
L I'T S-E TT L o T'-, SE P F! S i NOF:)~ AI<br />
A~? T Y PPARR CE. SUSCI E NC E T SS IE -AlT. UININ THE<br />
IN EA. PL'EASED TO SEE THEICRHAS r, NTACTrS THPAT A REC INOW<br />
TA&gt; LA EEL7 7 TU EOCRA T IC PCO L F' S P. E PU P; IC O F KC RE A A ND1<br />
R, ? LC O
ST: L-; N T P RE E 0 TE ST. ON. H7FOUR -, 1wo COUNTRIES START FROM<br />
DATEREx-T P7URSPECT IVES~ tUT-WE S'URELY '-; AVE A COMMON INTEREST IN<br />
A RcF -AXATIO'N OF TENSIONS ON T1HE PENINSULA.<br />
IN THE SOUTH PACIFIC9 THE CHALLENGE OF THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT<br />
O: 77 SMALL IScLAN,, D STATES REMAINS AND THERE ARE SOME UNCERTAINTIES<br />
A". OUT PfO!_ I1CAI STABILITYv FOR EXAMPLE IN NEW CALEDONIA.<br />
AGAINST THIS BACKGROUND1 AUSTRALIA TRIES IN ITS DIPLOMACY AND<br />
IN' OUR CO-OPFRATIVE PROGRAMSB IN THE REGION To BE A CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
' C<br />
~ l . q ' t~ lffl-S t'i / 7a.<br />
I </p>
<p>7-o 13J -12840<br />
INFLUENCE. WE ARE ACTIVELY DEVELOPING OUR LRLATIoNS WTHF FRIENDLY<br />
COUNTRI-Si INCLUDIING CHINAi AND WITH REGI( A;., AL ORGANISATIONS. WE<br />
CIVE A. ID AND WE ENCOURA. E TRADE THROUGH ACCESS To TlHE AUSTRALIAN<br />
MARKET. WE SEEKi AS I HAVE SAID, TO CONTRIBUTE TO POLITICAL<br />
STABILITY AND TO IMPROVE7D REGIONAL SECURIT-Y.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT FULLY SUPPORTS THE SINO-BRITISH AGREEMENT ON HONG<br />
KONG AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO THE SMOOTH IMPLEMENTATION OF THE<br />
AGREEMENT IN A WAY THAT TNCREASES PROSPERITY IN HONG KONG AND<br />
STRENGTHENS THE PEOPLE OF HONG KONG'S CONFIDENCE IN THEIR FUTURE<br />
AS A PART OF CHINA. WE LOOK FORWARD, ToOO To THE DAY WHEN THE<br />
CHINESE PEOPLE OIN BOTH SIDE-) S OF THE STRAITS OF TAIWAN CAN BE<br />
R'*: UNITE97 AS A RESULT OF PEACEFUL NEEl-OTIATIONS EETWEEN THEMI.<br />
WE REGARD THE TA7WAN QUES--TION AS AN, TENLAFIOFCN.<br />
PEACEFUL SETTLEMEN-V7' T OF THE7SE ISSUES WILL FURTHER ENHANCE STABILITY<br />
IN THE ASIA-PAClFL* C REGION4.<br />
BEYOND PARTICUI A. ("' cOJS T P ECTAL INTEREST TO CHINA,<br />
AUSTRALIIA' S HOPE I S O W CC:) NTINUE-TO) P AYASRN<br />
Co NS rRUCTIVE ROLE I REIONAL AFFAIRS GENERAL LY.<br />
I : AVE7 ' T 1) Vil 70( AY AS THE LEADER ( 7 Y GOVERNMENT BUTT<br />
T E T" HEc-V17 T A T A C. TRxG PO) S ITI VE A ND ENUR I NG REZL A TIONS-HIP<br />
ST GOC3 vYo~ 1 0TCAL 4 1D TrR AD E CONN E CTIONE HOWE VER GOO0 D<br />
T-S: 1AY SE T ES VcRY FoUNATFOR A RICH AND<br />
i. ASTIN CEA~ DEI : IL7LE 0 h ( REA'T; ST'D IVERScI TY OF F9RINDLY<br />
S S AT ALiL LE V E I-Ax! f ALL '-IEl-DSi EWE THE PEOPLES OF OUR<br />
WjAO jcTIA3 N EXC17: N G OR S REC7' T, 1. S I S. OUR FOREIGN<br />
MrkIENEITcS:': 2 ATUC 0, AU R 1 .4N, T. iC CH I N. A WE LL WA HEN<br />
0~ s TT-3A 7 N 141AF A-N EN COU4T E WITiH THI-S 7NIO~: s<br />
~ CIxUTL u~ CULTUR~ E LW-CH ~ TRUST ING IT<br />
G P S -PCE: 1) p Z-TTJ O 2. U C-EXCLEIVE ROL<br />
~~ A~ hATATING~~ L CO ATCHTE~ R : TUPC ! LOSE TrO " C-000<br />
A; lST 3 L 1AN S C AtNEz TC C -jI A J. AS T Y EA, TOI SEE FOR THEMSELVES TI's<br />
YfxAc ACN ~ T wE ENCo,. URAGE) AND CHINlA LELCCMESE<br />
' SC EVC 0FC1T0: i( AIF tUSTRA: AA HAS AGREEMENT=-C,-iINA<br />
FO X~ AGE~: SINC N TCV: OY ' i~., vDCATION, I THE<br />
~ EA A. A. AGC. F%~ THE; E EX C!-4N C ? IRC RAMS MAi E A Vlr'<br />
THROUI ~ TVV: II1 OF EXCHAPNj E D UT ALSO THROUGH THE<br />
r RECT 2P RSS CONA'S TH ~ S ES T AD L TCZ:<br />
I nESS R) CE Cr N AL-SOP A 0~ 7~ AC C NA<br />
Eh C. PcE, 7: 7 C -I N S. S AAUN A; A foA N'Y (' F<br />
Fi-GR'; AT-DE. EECURE . OFF* ICIAL . Jr\ D<br />
~ TAS 1 E.: TWEEN ATLEAST USTRALIAN UIEITIES<br />
A. L C0 LEE 3 F AD0V AN C ED E DUC AT7 I oN A N CUN E E T E RTI AR -Y<br />
TUTIOI~ NJCS LUDNG THIS GREAT UrINIVERSITY. TEEAE1<br />
AUSTRALIAN STUIDENTS STUDYING IN CHINESE UNIVERSITIES UNDER FULL<br />
GOVERNIMENT SCHOiLARSH: i: PlS. THERE 20 MORE GOVERNMENT SPONSORED<br />
SELF-FUNIDED AUSTRIA i7AN STUDENTS AND A SMALLER NUMBER OF TOTALLY<br />
FRIVATE STUDENTS. THESE NUMBERS IN BOTH DIRECTIONS ARE FAR TOO<br />
~ A~ L EWANIL SE~ ORINGTC) ETHER To ACHIEVE A SIGNIFICANT<br />
tN7 E CIuA LO4 TC) IT HE AUSTRALIA&amp; Nj MINISTER<br />
E D UC AT-7 LL B-TAIKING UP THIS ISSUE DURING HER VI-T TO CHINA<br />
I! N EETE ThIS YEAR. / 8 </p>
<p>W LLL At&gt;) 71! LIE TO INCREACT CONTACTS SET'W'EEN AUSTRALIAN AND<br />
C'INESE AC A&gt; lC S THE STUDY OF CHINESE LANGUAGE, HISTORY AND<br />
SOCIETY IS INCREASING IN AUSTRALIA, AND IT IS PLEASING TO NOTE THE<br />
OCYC(-) OMENr OF AUSTRAL: AN STUDIES PROGRAMS IN SEVERAL LEADING CHINESE<br />
UNIVERSITIES. THERE ARE MANY OBVIOUS AREAS OF MUTUAL INTEREST FOR<br />
RLCEARCH INCLUDING THOSE ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL ISSUES FACING ASIA<br />
At\ D THE PACIFIC TO WHCH I REFERRED EARLIER.<br />
I WANT ALSO TO MENTION EXCHANGES TAKING PLACE IN OTHER<br />
3CECIALISir AREAS.<br />
A uzCA; XC~ AkCC ThGRAM WAS ESTAT. EED Ix 1984 TO POIMOTE<br />
SCT: RNiiT i, 7, AL UNDERSTANDING OF EACH COUNTRY'S LEGAL SYSTElMs<br />
I STTiJTC: 6y AND uAl. S. T: S IS OF ENORMOUS RELEVANCE AT A TIME<br />
WE, C4T NA 7S O: 7CUSING ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF ITS OWN LEGAL FRAMEWORS<br />
AND " CAL EDUCATION. rIclA. CTCINCE AND TEC'iNOLOGY AGREEENT SIGNED<br />
I 119: iD CU2ELCW 7C%&gt; 7NTS PT ET N T-E AUSTRA'IAN AND<br />
C-A.-U ADEYIS OCF Cœ EVNC Ou; R SCiENrTISTS -I. AVE œ 0Ec WORKiNfjG<br />
TIGET--A DL AX3E7, OF WLS INClUDING GEOLOGY i METEOROLOGYI<br />
C ACh:_: G~ tC AI 4IS'il.~ hG 7UP2 SUCH : ICS-OEVREARYTION<br />
* EAQ-Ai% ST A
A T T AO R ARE cR THS.<br />
a 7. AE' X7T VISED C7-S7A LS Y&gt;; i TO STE CORrHEmBE: E<br />
IS 7 DI 1NG A C o-Ot) R ATV E ET T TC) UNCDERSTAND 2. ETTER<br />
7, zz ' J T T~' lr: FFORT SA : ED<br />
7 r, .1 E OF ( JAL E3NEFIT; -S AA % JTCC'-E WA'ES HOULD EOTH<br />
C 7 -u N.. 15, WAY ON A c-c: PERT: VETUE INU<br />
cfl NN 7EE ARI:: C1' TA C~ A; T v7: t C; IQ* TLTS<br />
UEEU; I N 7 3 A A lErT[ USEASE. œ V~-AA47 Ox TO HElTH, AUSTRAlIA<br />
CAL: 7OP. R AT r 1T CINA INt FILDrS RA , Ki F. O, RNUTITION TO<br />
Ah7 MLREOUM! I A RE; SE:. AC' R. C 0 SPOTS, M EDICIE. MANY<br />
C'-' A: CT WzR ;' NEASN D OFFIC IAS HAVE VIS: TE7F AUSTRALIA I N<br />
OCCx 1 TTIO) S STUDY RAL H EALT H CAP&gt; HOSPITAL nANAEMNT,<br />
3 C<br />
uu2P REAPI G( uAu-3 F( Rz A N : 9 1N LUE<br />
AC:-ERRA7T OF C GAGS ix THE ARTS " DqRAr A, DAXCE, MUSIC<br />
GsT MOII L T'AAN ALS'TE iuR S?' CVS,. O7X-NwQ ATOuETIS EALLTNG<br />
AnLTS C A L-I-Z 1: L N G<br />
C7 jA ID<br />
: E7 ND&gt; P T U ETAXCOU. DS AI . N A CC MtON<br />
; UtANITY TAH ON ATT TXXC-PC2RET F7Kt' AND F" YCI CAt<br />
7' 7 0-LRE AN A TN CflflIZ<br />
p 71I .1 / A&gt; USN' 7 UC,<br />
c ' TN'TC9Uz &gt;, m 
COOPRMO'AN UTUAL EXC;&gt;; A\% CE TH 7U-O5 EST SENSE. -I<br />
WOlR K WE ARE DI NG TOGETH ER : 7 FcstJO ' c 7R -v:) SHPI P A ND O PPOR TU NI TY.<br />
I T WI1LL I N TUJRN C REATE MO RE F R: TEN DSU27--AND4 OPE UPMR OPPORTUNITY<br />
FuR US BOTH IN THE FUTURE.<br />
To HAVE SUCH A RELATIONSH IP IS NO SM~ ALL THINGIN OL<br />
WI C H IS OFTE7 7N ANT AGONISTICt RELAT IONSHIPS OF W#% ARMTH AND UNDERSœ<br />
AN D ING AP. T 0 12CR I. Z ED. IN A WO. L) WH-ERE-_ THERE IS OFTEN<br />
SUJSPICION) i: 7N COUNTRY ' 3Y ANOT'HERi FRANKNESS AND TRUST ARE<br />
VAA C rOD-1I 1ES. IN A O. iu3 WHENDM ANY _ EOPLE SEE ONLY PROeLEMS<br />
1/ 9 9 r<br />
a -0 .5 i1., 1 84 </p>
<p>9<br />
AND DIFFICULTIES, SOURCES OF OPTIMISM ARE TO: LE VALUED. I HAVE<br />
F:, UD ALL THESE THINCS WARMTH, UNDERSTANDINC] FRANKNESSt TRUST<br />
A; iD OPTIMISM IN TIHC nEMRABLE VISIT TO CL-INA, AS I KNEW I WOULD.<br />
THEY ARE THE C: iARCTESTC-CS NOT ONLY OF THE FERSONAL CONTACTS<br />
I hAVE HAD WiTH CH: N: SE LEADERS 2UT OF THE RELATION\ S BETWEEN<br />
OUR TW4O NATIONS AND OUR TWO PEOPLES. WE CAN THEREORE LOOK FORWARD<br />
CI: CTLY TO A LAST 1NG R ATIN HrP OF rEAA-UTUAL BENEFI TMe<br />
C C:; E A i\ EXTEND ( AR) ARS D T TO OTHER AS WELL.<br />
hHT~ ADY YENAE-" TO CO -r ERATION I G-V<br />
YOU:: h; Y &gt; iji\ Uh. C ANE LL L U T-E YEARS AHEAD, I<br />
C r-7o 7hD Lc-t Y~ c: N7 I N UI C 7: T THI. S GREAT<br />
\ rr ( 3 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
