<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23627</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Remarks at bilateral meeting with His Excellency Mr Shinzo Abe, Prime Minister of Japan</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER ABBOTT:</strong></p>
<p>Shinzo it is a real honour to have you in this Parliament. I want to congratulate you for a really moving and heartfelt speech this morning.</p>
<p>I think that speech was truly the speech of a special friend of Australia.</p>
<p>I think today really has been the birth of a special relationship.</p>
<p>I very much appreciate everything that you’ve done in the time we’ve been working together and I am looking forward to ever closer cooperation on a whole range of matters; economic matters, regional matters, defence matters because I think that Australia and Japan have so much to offer to each other and to our region.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER ABE:</strong></p>
<p>First of all, thank you very much for hosting last night a wonderful dinner for me – myself – and for my wife as well.</p>
<p>Indeed when, Tony, you visited Japan in April you really started this new relationship between Japan and Australia.</p>
<p>This time, for me to be able to address the Australian Parliament has been a very much honourable moment for me.</p>
<p>After this we will be signing the Japan-Australia EPA as well as the agreement concerning the transfer of defence equipment and technology. I believe that through our economic cooperation as well as foreign policy, security, even cultural exchanges, people-to-people exchanges, these have really widened and strengthened our bilateral relationship.</p>
<p>Moving forward, I do hope that, Tony, we will be able to even further work together on regional issues as well as on global issues.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER ABBOTT:</strong></p>
<p>Well I’m looking forward to that very much.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
