<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9616</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RADIOS 2UE, 2GB, ABC, TUESDAY, 6 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009616.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RADIOS 2UE, 2GB, ABC, TUESDAY, 6 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: Well, in the end he had to come out and say something. He couldn't<br />
hide forever and we waited and what did we get? Nothing. Nothing.<br />
He is the same person he was in the late 1980s. There was nothing to<br />
him then and there is nothing to him now. So, the ' headland' speech:<br />
what was it about? The great changes in the international isation of<br />
Australia? The great change in our culture? The assertion of our<br />
identity? The shift into Asia? Nothing. It is about an independent<br />
auditor general or an independent speaker. So what. So what. What<br />
John Howard has proven and on television tonight he says with his<br />
most statesman-like voice that he could propose, he said ' I'm sure that<br />
the things that unite Australia is more important than things which<br />
divide us.' The very thing he said at his defeat at the election in 1987.<br />
So, he has done the full circle. What we got tonight was a hollow<br />
collection of cliches, exposing his complete paucity of policies. He has<br />
got no policy structure. He even goes on to say after a week of us<br />
fighting for the interests of the Australian battler' a week the<br />
Australian Labor Party has been fighting for them for 100 years and<br />
this Government has been fighting for their interests for 12 years. He<br />
said people may not want government out of their lives, but they do<br />
want it off their backs'. That is an American republican line. It is<br />
Liberal Party code for cutting government spending on welfare<br />
payments, but you don't find any mention of spending cuts in there.<br />
Then he talks about a pro-family industrial relations policy. In other<br />
words, you should appreciate the right to be sacked more easily. Very<br />
pro-family.<br />
Then he says he would destroy the Commonwealth external affairs<br />
power. That means no Gordon-below-Frankl ins. That means no<br />
Daintrees. No Kakadu National Parks. He says the use of this is illicit. </p>
<p>On foreign policy there is not a single, solitary policy about Australia's<br />
engagement with the region. He says, and listen to this one the<br />
next Coalition government will continue the pattern.' Could you<br />
imagine anything weaker or more vacuous when this Government is<br />
threading together the largest, free trade agreement in the history of<br />
the Asia-Pacific area with APEC and making bi-lateral relationships<br />
with countries like Indonesia and Japan of a quality that we have never<br />
had in the past. What does he say? the next Coalition government<br />
will continue the pattern'. You would be ashamed to put a statement<br />
like that out.<br />
Then he talks about the republic. But, he doesn't say whether he is for<br />
it or against it. He can't even say it. He is afraid to say what his<br />
position is because his position is against a republic. But now he<br />
thinks that a majority of opinion are in favour of it, he is not prepared to<br />
say, he is not prepared to say. Then he says a few interest groups<br />
are driving the government', but he declines to say who the interest<br />
groups are and to talk about them.<br />
He talks about starting with economic honesty. This is the same<br />
person who, for one week before the 1953 election, decided not to tell<br />
the Australian public what the Secretary to the Treasury told him. That<br />
is, that the Budget deficit wasn't $ 6 billion it was $ 9.6 billion. This is<br />
the same person who talks about no more fiscal slight of hand while<br />
when he was Treasurer he never, ever, published forward estimates of<br />
receipts, ever. And, only forward estimates of outlays for one year.<br />
This Government publishes forward estimates of outlays and forward<br />
estimates of receipts and the budget or surplus balance.<br />
He says he will provide a degree of predictability about the level<br />
and stability of tax rates'. Peter Costello says they won't rise.<br />
Apparently, he has now amended that upon more mature reflection<br />
because he has been caught out.<br />
It is the most empty vacuous set of statements that I have seen from a<br />
major party leader. This is Fightback, the rhetoric of Fightback,<br />
without the policies and the mathematics.<br />
J: Mr Howard said he made it quite clear that this speech was never<br />
going to include detailed policies.<br />
PM: Because he doesn't have any. This was his big opportunity to tell us<br />
where he wants to take Australia. What do you get from this? You<br />
don't even get a direction from him. It is so vacuous there is not even<br />
a direction. All these people in the media who wanted a contest at the<br />
next election, I'm sorry you're not going to get one. You are not going<br />
to get one because they are not up to it. To have a contest you have<br />
got to have the other side with some policies. They are not in the hunt. </p>
<p>This is the weakest effort I have seen by an Opposition Leader in the<br />
years I have been here.<br />
J: You are very quick to jump on it.<br />
PM: Because I am very quick to read it. You could get across it in<br />
pages. You could read the thing in a couple of minutes.<br />
J: Is it Mr Howard's " Things That Matter"?<br />
PM: The ' Things That Matter" that is, Mr Downer's " Things That Matter"<br />
looks positively solid compared to this dross. And, of course,<br />
Fightback! was an absolute mammoth of a document, compared to this<br />
rubbish.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Mr Howard said he was going to do a series of headland<br />
speeches this is only the first, doesn't he shouldn't he be able to<br />
take the chance to have a series of speeches outlining the broad detail<br />
of where he wants to go?<br />
PM: This is his first this was the one that was going to tell us the<br />
directions. This was the one that was going to give us an indication<br />
about the sort of government he would have, and you have got no idea<br />
from him, about the sort of government he would have. And when it<br />
comes to the hard things, about how would he cut $ 10,000 million out<br />
of outlays? I mean, who would be cut? Payments to pensioners?<br />
Payments to schools? Payments to the low-paid? And here he is<br />
talking about supporting battlers, and during his period of office, lowpaid<br />
people suffered enormously he has not supported any wage<br />
increase for Australian workers since 1981, bar the last 2. That was 2<br />
lots of So, he supported $ 16 wage increase in 14 years.<br />
J; Does this strategy make it harder for you for the Government to pin<br />
him down, to attack him, because he isn't presenting his policies until<br />
closer to the election, and you are relying on attacking him from when<br />
he was last in Government that was 12 years ago?<br />
PM: No. I'm relying on attacking him for the fact that he wants to replace<br />
to supplant this Government as the Government of Australia. He has<br />
no right with rubbish like this. And though the media might want a<br />
contest, they have no right in supporting rubbish like this.<br />
J: He has challenged you to set out what you think the reserve powers of<br />
a President should be under an Australian republic in your major<br />
speech will you?<br />
PM: My challenge to him is to say whether he is for a republic or not<br />
simple enough question. Forget the modalities for the moment is he<br />
in favour? I mean, it's not much of an ask, is it, to say " is it not </p>
<p>unreasonable to ask the alternative Prime Minister whether he believes<br />
an Australian should be our Head of State?"<br />
J: But what about...<br />
PM: And he won't answer it.<br />
J: But what about his challenge to you?<br />
PM: Just a second he will not answer that simple question it's not his<br />
challenge to mine that is the core matter. Unless he says he is in<br />
favour of an Australian republic, he disqualifies himself from having<br />
any part in the debate for a shift to a republic. And, of course,<br />
tomorrow night I will be saying precisely where the Government stands<br />
on this issue.<br />
J; So you believe Mr Howard has missed his opportunity to talk to<br />
Australians?<br />
PM: He missed his opportunity in the middle 1970s, when he left us with<br />
double-digit inflation, double-digit unemployment, and the highest<br />
Government spending in our history he should have been drummed<br />
out of the regiment of Australian politics. He has hung around, and<br />
waited to see all of his rivals retire, and in their paucity remember, he<br />
is their third choice in this term: he is their third choice after Hewson<br />
and Downer, and now you can see why he was their third choice. He<br />
is recycled, empty and vacuous.<br />
J; So, does seeing this make you want to call an election soon?<br />
PM; To see it makes me a little bit sad about the state of the Liberal Party<br />
and the alternative government. I mean, as an Australian, I have<br />
always believed that it is in the nation's best interests always to<br />
keep on the boil, two competent parties of government. What this<br />
speech proves is that there is only one the Australian Labor Party.<br />
J: Would you like to see a real contest?<br />
PM: The media will, but how are you going to get one when you have got a<br />
candidate such as Howard, who has got no policies? I mean, how can<br />
you get a contest when you have got someone without any substance?<br />
J: You say the journalists can't read opinion polls...<br />
PM: I think the last election proved that.<br />
J: Can you give us your reading of the 2 conflicting polls that came out<br />
today? </p>
<p>PM: I told you I think the Government is strengthening its underlying vote.<br />
We have now got the country growing at a consistent and sustainable<br />
rate, we have low inflation, we have the Budget back to surplus, we are<br />
seeing the Government now continuing on its big social policies such<br />
as Working Nation. We are having success with the long-term<br />
unemployed, the Government is about to announce its response on the<br />
republic, I have just come back from Japan building that bilateral<br />
relationship, we are working again on the strength and growth of<br />
APEC. I mean, these are the things from a Government of substance.<br />
After having just passed the Land Fund, and the year before last,<br />
Mabo. How could you compare a Government that is doing these<br />
things, with this worn out Liberal party?<br />
J: Well, how do you explain the poll that shows John Howard and the<br />
Coalition streaking ahead?<br />
PM: I think the public have always got a little needle into governments<br />
they want you to earn your freight. They say " how are you going to<br />
vote?", [ and they reply] " oh well, I don't know I might throw a vote to<br />
the Coalition", and that's to put a bit of ginger in the system. That's<br />
probably always been there, but we're in the position where we want to<br />
be right now, and that is one out and one back the best position to be<br />
in Australian politics.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
