<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6253</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OFFICIAL LAUCHING OF THE AUSTRALIAN ENCYCLOPAEDIA (4TH EDITION) - 2 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006253.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL 12.30 P. M.<br />
AUST<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OFFICIAL LAUNCHING OF THE AUSTRALIAN ENCYCLOPAEDIA<br />
( 4TH EDITION) 2 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
Let me say at the outseI: how pleased I am to be<br />
here to launch this new edition the fourth of the<br />
Australian Encyclopaedia.<br />
The existence of such a reference work is<br />
indispensable to the needs of contemporary Australia.<br />
There is now, both locally and world-wide, a<br />
growing interest in all things Australian<br />
In commercial, industrial, scientific, sporting<br />
and cultural fields across a wide range of Australian<br />
endeavour Australians are making distinctive and valuable<br />
contributions. We can point, for example, to an increasing number<br />
of Australian technological and manufacturing successes.<br />
The interscan airport approach sYStem is a particularly<br />
impressive recent case in point.<br />
On the cultural side, we take pleasure in the<br />
international reputation Australian3 have achieved in the<br />
highly competitive field of film and T. V. production.<br />
Australian authors have al. 5o won world acclaim;<br />
among them, Patrick White, our resident Nobel Prize winner<br />
for literature; Morris West, who invariably makes the world<br />
best-sellers list; and Thomas Kenea: ly, who last year won<br />
the prestigious British Booker-McC,-, nell prize with<br />
" Schindler's Ark".<br />
This encyclopaedia draws of these strands of<br />
Australian experience and achiever" r. t together in readily<br />
accessible form.<br />
That it has been done so t:! fectively is a tribute<br />
to the editorial advisory board members we are told<br />
established the preliminary list :-ncyclopaedia entries,<br />
recommended suitable consultants " ontributors and<br />
provided invaluable ongoing advice oi assistance to the<br />
editors. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Special recognition is due to<br />
Sir Harold White, former National and Parliamentary<br />
Librarian, who served as Chairman of the editorial<br />
board for both this 4th edition and its<br />
predecessor; Donald Horne, distinguished author and commentator;<br />
Bruce Pratt, Editor-in-Chief of the 3rd edition;<br />
and Dr Alan Day, senior lecturer in geology and<br />
geophysics at the University of Sydney.<br />
Through these board members I would also like to<br />
j pay tribute to the work of hundreds of specialist<br />
consultants and contributors who are too numerous to mention<br />
individually collectively they are responsible for what has<br />
Ibeen a massive enterprise<br />
The 12th volume deserves special mention. The<br />
appendix and index are no less an achievement than the other<br />
The indexing system is notably innovative and<br />
helpful. Significantly it is integrated with the<br />
encyclopaedia's own computerised typesetting and alphabetic<br />
sorting ptogram. This topical application of advances in information<br />
technology provides a more precise guide for the user than<br />
did the conventional folio and column indexing approach used<br />
previously.<br />
Ii I agree with the publishers of this encyclopaedia<br />
that its particular achievement is to present " a<br />
comprehensive-picture of Australia and its people both past<br />
and present" to present " a changing Australia in a changing<br />
wo rl1d"<br />
I think it is important that we appreciate the<br />
inevitability, scope and accelerating rate of change and<br />
the need to try to identify its causes, origins, trends and<br />
effects so that we can better confront and determine our<br />
future as a nation.<br />
There has hardly been a facet of contemporary<br />
Australia that has been untouched by change. </p>
<p>Even basic and cherished assumptions must<br />
regularly be reviewed.<br />
No longer, for example, can we view Australia as an<br />
island continent isolated on the rim of Asia.<br />
For, while our Western roots will continue to<br />
contribute significantly to Australia's distinctive<br />
character, it is indisputable that Culturally and<br />
economically our future will be very hound up with this<br />
region. Ongoing changes within Australia are also having<br />
profound implications for our future.<br />
I think it is especially significant, for example,<br />
that the information given about our Aboriginal people has<br />
been significantly expanded in this edition.<br />
This reflects not only greater awareness of the<br />
original inhabitants of our land, but more genuine interest<br />
in their way of life, their culture, beliefs and history<br />
and, I hope, a greater concern for their well-being<br />
and respect for their traditions and aspirations.<br />
Similarly the treatment of our ethnic communities<br />
has been expanded.<br />
Australia's emergence as a multi-cultural community<br />
has generated changes across the whole spectrum of national<br />
li fe from our recreational and cultural pursuits to<br />
welfare, employment and educational programs<br />
An equally profound but more subtle aspect of<br />
population change in Australia has to do with the ageing of<br />
our community. We tend to see ourselves as a ' young country',<br />
particularly by comparison with many other countries.<br />
But, paradoxically, we are a steadily ageing<br />
society. Recent Government projections suggest that in<br />
years time the number of Australians over 65 will have more<br />
than doubled, while the total population will only have<br />
grown by slightly more than one third.<br />
The implications this will. have for health, social<br />
security and education services, employment patterns and,<br />
not least, our own perceptions of ourselves are fundamental. </p>
<p>The perception and management of change is often a<br />
confusing and complex exercise.<br />
Adjustments in attitudes, social structures, And<br />
institutions are usually involved.<br />
A successful transition will depend, I believe, on<br />
the willingness of the social partners Government, unions,<br />
employers, and ultimately and most importantly, the people<br />
to consult at all levels in a climate of mutual trust and<br />
respect. A proper appreciation of the factors contributing<br />
to change, of the implications of change, is necessary to a<br />
healthy, well-ordered society.<br />
Anything which can help us understand our past and<br />
present, and gives us a perspective of the future, deserves<br />
our attention and respect..<br />
That is one of the many reasons why I commend this<br />
edition of the Australian Encyclopaedia.<br />
It is not, of course, an encyclopeadia's function<br />
to provide a particular perspective, nor to furnish<br />
ready-made conclusions, on any issue.<br />
The encyclopaedia properly leaves to its readers<br />
the responsibility of fashioning their own perspectives and<br />
the exercise of drawing their own conclusions.<br />
What I am suggesting is that the Australian<br />
Encyclopaedia can provide considerable help in such pursuits<br />
through its well presented entries<br />
through the excellent suggestions for further<br />
reading which accompany most entries<br />
through its useful cross-referencing between<br />
relevant entries<br />
and through its invaluable and comprehensive index<br />
system Again I must congratulate all who are responsible<br />
for the Australian Encyclopaedia it is a top quality<br />
production in every way<br />
Except on one point.<br />
It has been said that a book should not be judged<br />
by its cover but in this case I am compelled to make, if not<br />
a judgement, at least a comment. </p>
<p>For inside the cover of Volume One you will note<br />
that this edition of the Australian Encyclopaedia was<br />
printed in Singapore.<br />
The result may be absolutely first class.<br />
But, an equally fine job could have been done by<br />
our own printing industry<br />
and, I believe, at a comparable cost.<br />
When last July I launched the " Keep Printing in<br />
Australia" campaign, I did so with the conviction that<br />
Australia's printing industry could produce at a price and<br />
quality competitive with anywhere else in the world.<br />
I sincerely hope that the bicentennial edition of<br />
this Encyclopaedia will be all Australian.<br />
However, that criticism aside, this project shows<br />
again what Australians from all their diverse areas of<br />
skills, backgrounds and fields of interest can achieve when<br />
all work together towards a common aim.<br />
It gives me great pleasure to commend all those<br />
responsible for the preparation of this excellent 4th<br />
edition of the Australian Encyclopaedia and to welcome it to<br />
the bookshops and bookshelves of our nation. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
