<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1098</transcript-id>
    <title>VIETNAM - EXCHANGE OF LETTERS BETWEEN PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP AND THE RT. REV J S MOYES, CMG, AND CERTAIN ARCHBISHOPS AND BISHOPS</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/04/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Letter</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001098.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
V I E TN A M<br />
EXCHANGE OF LETTERS BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENIES, and<br />
THE RT. REV. J. S. MOYES, C. M. G.,<br />
AND CERTAIN ARCHBISHOPS AND BISHOPS </p>
<p>CONTENTS Page<br />
1. Bishops' letter<br />
12th March, 1965<br />
2. Prime Minister's Reply<br />
24th March, 1965<br />
3. Bishops' Letter<br />
9th April, 1965<br />
4. Prime Minister's Reply<br />
April, 1965<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S DEPARTMENT.<br />
CANBERRA. APRIL. 1965 1 2<br />
3 -6<br />
7<br />
11 17 </p>
<p>TEXT OF BISHOPS' LETTER<br />
OF 12th MARCH, 1965<br />
There are a number of us deeply concerned<br />
that our Government should be seen to be taking<br />
positive steps, with others, towards an honourable<br />
and peaceful. actt.. lmunt of the fighting in Vietnam.<br />
Already His Holiness the Pope, the<br />
Secretary-General of the United Nations,; U Thant,<br />
and the Lovrrnments of Canada, India and France have<br />
urged through both private and formal diplomatic<br />
channels their earnest desire for negotiations<br />
leading to peace.<br />
We are not concerned here to canvass the<br />
merits of the respeclive attitudes of the North and<br />
South Vietnamese Governments, or of the Governments<br />
of the United States and China.<br />
We have in mind, however, the attitude<br />
of Her Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom<br />
at the time of the Geneva Agreements in 1954, and<br />
since. We also realise that liberal opinion in<br />
thu as reflected by the " New York Times"<br />
and by sober commentatois like Mr. Walter Lippmann,<br />
by no means agrees with their Government's policy,<br />
Although the U. S. A. was not a signatory to the<br />
1954 Geneva Agreement, yet in a statement made on<br />
21st July that year they undertook to refrain from<br />
the threat of the use of force in the matter of<br />
Vietnam, </p>
<p>2.<br />
It seems to us that our Government,<br />
because we owe so much to our Ally, the United<br />
States of America, is morally bound to help<br />
our Ally, in the friendliest and most loyal<br />
spirit, to avoid a policy that can lead to an<br />
extension of hostilities, We would hope that<br />
our nation, living as we do in the Asian world,<br />
should join with the Pope. U Thant and the<br />
distinguished leaders of the other Western<br />
nations mentioned above, in bringing to a close<br />
a war that is costing so many lives and<br />
reducing the economy of Vietnam to chaos. </p>
<p>TEXT OF PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
REPLY OF 24th MARCH, 1965<br />
I have given careful thought to your letter<br />
of March 12th, relating to events in Vietnam. As<br />
your letter was published in the press, I shall<br />
give publicity to my reply, when you have received it.<br />
You urge that my Government should be seen<br />
to be taking " positive steps towards an honourable<br />
and peaceful settlement of the fighting in Vietnam".<br />
Now, that all of us in our country want peace<br />
is axiomatic. The whole strength of Australia's<br />
diplomatic forces in countries to which they are<br />
accredited is directed almost daily to the removal<br />
of difficulties and the promotion of peace. But<br />
before any nation such as the U. S. A. " negotiates"<br />
for peace, realism requires<br />
that the other party or parties to<br />
the conflict should be willing to<br />
negotiate; and<br />
that there should be a genuine ceasefire,<br />
strictly and honourably<br />
observed; and<br />
that there should be some reasonable<br />
assurance that aggression and subversion<br />
will come to an end.<br />
It is at this point that your letter<br />
surprises and distresses me. Although you are<br />
urging some form of political action upon me and my<br />
colleagues in relation to the fighting in Vietnam,<br />
you go on to say that you are " not concerned here to<br />
canvass the merits of the respective attitudes of the<br />
North and South Vietnamese Government, or the<br />
Governments of the United States and China". </p>
<p>Well, all I can say is that the<br />
Government is and must be concerned. Indeed,<br />
it seems elementary to me that unless we<br />
have some ideas on the merits of these matters,<br />
our actions will be those of expediency and<br />
not those of principle.<br />
I therefore address myself to the<br />
merits, to which, I fear, you attach little<br />
significance. You refer to the Geneva agreements of<br />
1954. These provided a military demarcation<br />
line at the 17th parallel, separating North and<br />
South Vietnam, with a demilitarised zone of<br />
five kilometres on each side. Each side was<br />
to " order and enforce the complete cessation<br />
of all hostilities in Vietnam by all armed<br />
forces under their control".<br />
North Vietnam is under Communist rule.<br />
The political views of Hanoi are not to be<br />
distinguished from those of Peking. There<br />
can, in our opinion, be no doubt that the<br />
Geneva Accords have been consistently violated<br />
by the Communists, partly by direct attacks<br />
across the line, partly by infiltration and<br />
supply, and partly by the establishment and<br />
maintenance of the Communist insurgents known<br />
as the Viet Cong, whose activities are directed<br />
to the overthrow of government in South Vietnam<br />
and to the ultimate establishment there of a<br />
Communist regime. These facts are not<br />
seriously denied. In 1960 they were expressly<br />
conceded by the Government and Communist Party<br />
in North Vietnam. At the request of the Government<br />
of South Vietnam the United States has<br />
deployed forces in that country, to aid in its<br />
defence, and we, under similar circumstances,<br />
have given military and material aid. These<br />
steps are denounced by the Communists as </p>
<p>" Imperialism", though it is quite clear that they<br />
have been taken in the defence of local freedom and<br />
self-government against an imperialist aggression which,<br />
if not restricted by deeds, will lead to the overrunning<br />
of South-East Asia by aggressive Communism<br />
and a complete loss of the existing freedom of non-<br />
Communist countries. Are there no merits here to be considered<br />
by Church leaders? There can be no true composition<br />
between atheistic and materialistic Communism and<br />
countries with deep religious beliefs. True, there<br />
can be, given good faith on both sides, peaceful coexistence<br />
and mutual tolerance. But these cannot<br />
continue if aggression continues and grows and is<br />
unchecked except by fine words.<br />
We have considered the merits, as any<br />
Government must. We believe as do all those who<br />
have been prepared to consider the merits, that the<br />
United States policies and actions in relation to<br />
South Vietnam are right, and should be supported;<br />
that they derive from a courageous and generous<br />
acceptance of responsibilities for the protection of<br />
human freedom. You urge that we join with some other<br />
authorities " in bringing to a close a war that is<br />
costing so many lives and reducing the economy of<br />
Vietnam to chaos".<br />
I agree that the war is costing many lives<br />
and is damaging Vietnam. But how is it to be brought<br />
to a close? The Viet Cong and the forces of Hanoi<br />
are backed by Communist China, a country which<br />
rejects peaceful co-existence and practises, as it<br />
has already shown in India and Tibet, an aggressive<br />
imperialism. Is the United States to withdraw, and<br />
abandon South Vietnam? This would no doubt lead to<br />
a conquest which would end the armed conflict by<br />
conceding victory to the Communists. </p>
<p>Or is the United States, without<br />
withdrawal or abandonment, to negotiate for<br />
peace? With whom? About what? These are two<br />
vital questions. How would they negotiate with the<br />
Viet Cong, well organised but hidden, practising<br />
the night attack upon villages, determined<br />
upon revolution by violence? How would they<br />
negotiate with North Vietnam, a country which<br />
has shown that it will be bound by no agreement?<br />
How could they negotiate with Communist<br />
China, the home of aggression, except upon a<br />
basis of assured independence and freedom for<br />
South Vietnam and those other countries of<br />
South-East Asia which are now threatened by<br />
Communist expansionism? Sir, the change of heart that is needed<br />
to lay a good foundation for a fruitful<br />
negotiation and a lasting peace must occur in the<br />
Communist bodies. It will occur all the sooner<br />
if aggression is met by resistance, if we remain<br />
clear about what it is that we are defending,<br />
and if we, and all our allies, can make it well<br />
understood that we are not concerned to conquer<br />
others, but that we will do our part to preserve<br />
freedom where it now exists. Freedom is, in<br />
this world, not expendable. And free people<br />
are not aggressors. </p>
<p>TEXT OF BISHOPS' LETTER<br />
OF 9th APRIL, 1965<br />
' le thank you for your thoughtful reply of<br />
March 24th to our joint letter of March 11th. We<br />
beg you to give further consideration to the urgent<br />
request of our letter, in the earnest hope that<br />
continuing discussion will clarify the real issues.<br />
It puzzles us that you should be<br />
" surprised and distressed" because we did not canvass<br />
set forth and discuss in detail all the<br />
facts. This, as you must realise, would have<br />
involved hundreds of pages. So far from " attaching<br />
little significance" to the " merits of these matters,"<br />
we naturally attach the greatest importance to them,<br />
as some of us have meanwhile made clear. We must<br />
insist, however, on examining the merits of both<br />
sides. The illegal activities of North Viet Nam are<br />
constantly being brought to our notice. We feel bound<br />
to point out that the South is not blameless. Your<br />
reference to the Geneva accords of 1954 as having<br />
been " consistently violated by the Communists" is<br />
surely less than the whole truth of the matter.<br />
Both North and South, and China and the United States,<br />
have violated the agreements. Two serious breaches<br />
of the spirit and letter of the Geneva agreements<br />
have been committed by the South, with full knowledge<br />
and approval, and active support, of the United States.<br />
They are:-i. the continued refusal to hold free<br />
elections; and<br />
ii. the grant of military bases to a foreign<br />
power.<br />
As to the fact is that it was agreed at<br />
Geneva on July 21st, 1954, that " General Elections<br />
shall be held in July, 1956, under the supervision </p>
<p>of an international commission composed of<br />
representatives of the member states of the<br />
international supervisory commission referred<br />
to in the agreements on the cessation of<br />
hostilities." These elections have never been<br />
held. Responsibility for this rests squarely<br />
on the Government of South Viet Nam, backed<br />
by the United States. No authority known<br />
to us disagrees that any fair and free election<br />
since 1954 would have resulted in a victory for<br />
the supporters of Ho Chi Minh. If people want<br />
to be communists, guns will not stop them.<br />
As to we remind you that<br />
Paragraph ( iv) of the Final Declaration on<br />
Indo-China of July 21st, 1954 reads; " The<br />
Conference takes note of the clauses<br />
prohibiting the introduction into Viet Nam of<br />
foreign troops and military personnel as well<br />
as of all kinds of arms and munitions." We<br />
remind you further of Paragraph of the same<br />
Declaration: " The Conference takes note<br />
that no military base at the disposition of a<br />
foreign State may be established in the<br />
regrouping zones of the two parties..."<br />
The main contention of your letter<br />
is that we are indifferent to the moral and<br />
religious elements in the situation, whereas<br />
you and your Government are deeply concerned<br />
with both. You think of the war as a crusade<br />
being carried out by the Christian forces<br />
of the " deeply religious" people of South<br />
Viet Nam, the United States and, presumably,<br />
Australia, against " the atheistic and<br />
materialistic" forces of North Viet Nam<br />
and China. We find ourselves unable to make<br />
this clear moral and religious distinction<br />
and, moreover, regard the making of such a<br />
distinction as in itself open to grave moral<br />
question. We can understand the desire to<br />
L </p>
<p>restrain the political imperialism of China, and<br />
even the necessity of using force to do it, but<br />
we cannot ourselves justify it on your grounds,<br />
namely, that the United States and ourselves are<br />
altruistically coming to the rescue of " local<br />
freedom and self government".<br />
The government of South Viet Nam rests<br />
upon no basis of popular or democratic support.<br />
It was from its beginning, until last year, a<br />
dictatorship of the late Mr. Ngo Dinh Diem. In these<br />
circumstances, it seems to us to be idealising the<br />
situation to write of U. S. support of " local<br />
freedom and self government."<br />
As for your observation that " there can be<br />
no true composition between atheistic and materialistic<br />
communism and countries with deep religious<br />
beliefs," we can only say that there are millions<br />
of Christians in Russia and China who are compelled to<br />
do just this. We have no right to criticise<br />
them, since we have not ourselves been put to this<br />
test. It seems to us preferable in this war, as<br />
with all wars, carefully to keep references to<br />
" deep religious belief" above the evil it may help<br />
to resolve, and not to misuse it to bolster one<br />
side of the case or the other.<br />
On one of your political judgements we feel<br />
bound to take issue. You say " the political<br />
views of Hanoi are not to be distinguished from<br />
those of Pekin." We doubt the validity of your<br />
identification. Is it not like identifying<br />
Moscow with Belgrade and Warsaw and Pekin?<br />
Finally, you ask how the war is to be<br />
brought to a close. We can only reiterate the<br />
hope which was the main point of our original<br />
letter, that you will use your great influence and </p>
<p>experience to support the possibility of<br />
negotiations. We cannot think that we, or<br />
others more distinguished, are hopelessly<br />
deluded in asking that negotiations become<br />
the declared objective of Australian<br />
diplomacy. In urging this plea, we are<br />
supported by His Holiness the Pope, by<br />
U Thant, and by the Governments of France and<br />
India, to which has been added the commanding<br />
voice of your fellow Prime Minister of a<br />
Dominion, Mr. Lester Pearson, and Her Majesty's<br />
Government in the United Kingdom. To all these<br />
have now been added the proposals of President<br />
Johnson himself. We feel no distress at<br />
finding ourselves in such company. </p>
<p>TEXT OF PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
REPLY OF 20th APRIL, 1965<br />
I have your letter of April 9th, answering<br />
mine to you of March 24th, and have given it my most<br />
earnest consideration. Fortified again, I may say, by close<br />
consultation with the Minister and Department of<br />
External Affairs, I will proceed to deal with the<br />
substance of your propositions.<br />
You dismiss the actions of North Vietnam,<br />
in a single phrase, as " illegal activities". The<br />
rest of your letter contains, in detail and at some<br />
length, a critical attack upon South Vietnam and<br />
her supporters. You accuse them of two violations of the<br />
Geneva Accords of 1954. You should recall that the<br />
United States and South Vietnamese governments did<br />
not subscribe to the Final Declaration, but made<br />
separate statements indicating that they would not<br />
use force to prevent the execution of the agreements.<br />
The United States declared that it would view any<br />
renewal of aggression, in violation of the<br />
agreement, with grave concern and as seriously<br />
threatening international peace and security.<br />
You allege two serious breaches by the<br />
South, approved and supported by the United States.<br />
They are, to use your own language,<br />
1. " The continued refusal to hold free<br />
elections".<br />
This refers, as you make clear, to elections over both<br />
North and South Vietnam. You then go on to assert<br />
a proposition which I find astonishing. </p>
<p>12.<br />
Your words are<br />
" These elections have never been<br />
held. Responsibility for this rests<br />
squarely on the Government of South<br />
Vietnam, backed by the United States.<br />
No authority known to us disagrees<br />
that any fair and free election<br />
since 1954 would have resulted in a<br />
victory for the supporters of<br />
Ho Chi Minh."<br />
Surely nobody will deny that North Vietnam is<br />
under complete Communist control, and that<br />
" free elections" simply cannot happen. That<br />
Ho Chi Minh would win in North Vietnam is clear<br />
enough, for there would and could be no other<br />
candidate. How you can blame South Vietnam for the<br />
absence of a " fair and free election" in North<br />
Vietnam therefore passes my comprehension.<br />
Let me remind you too that if the<br />
North had not actively sought to overthrow the<br />
government of the South by force, and by<br />
supporting the pockets of Communist Viet Cong<br />
in their violent campaigns in the South, the<br />
people of the South would be at peace, and the<br />
way for orderly self-government would be open.<br />
2. The second " serious breach" alleged<br />
by you is " the grant ( by South<br />
Vietnam), of military bases to a<br />
foreign power."<br />
The first answer to this is that it is simply<br />
inaccurate. No " military bases" have been<br />
granted to the United States. </p>
<p>True, that country has sent some forces into South<br />
Vietnam, at the request of that country, to<br />
assist in its defence against unprovoked aggression.<br />
So have we, in a small way. Such actions are in<br />
strict conformity with the Charter of the United<br />
Nations. I fear that you have overlooked the vital<br />
fact that South Vietnam did not begin these troubles.<br />
To play down the aggression and incitement from the<br />
North, and to devote your major criticism to the<br />
defenders, is a strange line of argument.<br />
You next accuse us of " idealising" the<br />
situation in Vietnam by speaking of support of<br />
local freedom and self-government". How do you<br />
suppose that freedom in South Vietnam can be fully<br />
achieved and maintained when that country is torn<br />
about by murderous subversion fomented and supported<br />
from the Communist North? A life and death struggle<br />
of this kind does not lend itself to theory.<br />
Finally, you appear to pray in aid the<br />
recent statement by President Johnson. I<br />
respectfully suggest that you study the full text<br />
of that statement. It powerfully supports what<br />
my colleague, Mir. Hasluck, and I have been saying<br />
about the course and causes of the events in<br />
Vietnam, and is fundamentally at odds with your own<br />
analysis. It explains the American presence and<br />
actions. It faces the facts.<br />
For example ( and I will not quote in<br />
extenso) the President said<br />
" Tonight Americans and Asians are dying for<br />
a world where each people may choose its<br />
ownpath to change. This is the<br />
principle for which our ancestors fought<br />
in the valleys of Pennsylvania. It is<br />
the principle for which our sons fight<br />
in the jungles of Vietnam." </p>
<p>14.<br />
" We fight because we must fight<br />
if we are to live in a world where<br />
every country can shape its own<br />
destiny. And only in such a<br />
world will our own freedom be<br />
finally secure. This kind of a<br />
world will never be built by<br />
bombs or bullets. Yet the<br />
infirmities of men are such that<br />
force must often precede reason<br />
and the waste of war, the works of<br />
peace. We wish this were not so.<br />
But we must deal with the world as<br />
it is, if it is ever to be as we wish."<br />
" But trained men and supplies,<br />
orders and arms, flow in a constant<br />
stream from North to South. This<br />
support is the heart-beat of the war.<br />
And it is a war of unparelled<br />
brutality. Simple farmers are the<br />
targets of assassination and kidnapping.<br />
Women and children are strangled in the<br />
night because their men are loyal<br />
to the government. Small and<br />
helpless villages are ravaged by sneak<br />
attacks. Large-scale raids are<br />
conducted on towns, and terror<br />
strikes in the heart of cities. The<br />
confused nature of this conflict cannot<br />
mask the fact that it is the new face<br />
of an old enemy. Over this war<br />
and all Asia is another reality,<br />
the deepening shadow of Communist<br />
China. The rulers of Hanoi are<br />
urged on by Peking. This is a regime<br />
which has destroyed freedom in Tibet,<br />
attacked India, and been condemned by<br />
the United Nations for aggression in<br />
Korea. It is a nation which is </p>
<p>helping the forces of violence in almost every<br />
continent. The contest in Vietnam<br />
is part of a wider pattern of aggressive<br />
purpose."<br />
And later he said<br />
" We will not be defeated. We will not<br />
grow tired. We will not withdraw,<br />
either openly or under the cloak of a<br />
meaningless agreement."<br />
And then " It should also be clear that the only path<br />
for reasonable men is the path of<br />
peaceful settlement. Such peace demands<br />
an independent South Vietnam securely<br />
guaranteed and able to shape its own<br />
relationships to all others free from<br />
outside interference tied to no alliance<br />
a military base for no other country."<br />
It is against the background of these clear<br />
statements and for their achievement that the<br />
President has said, once more, that he is willing to<br />
have discussions. It is because we agree with all this that,<br />
in answering a recent Parliamentary question, I said<br />
that I could not support a suggestion " that the United<br />
States, instead of fighting, should negotiate".<br />
My colleagues and I must decline to be cast<br />
for the roles of warmongers and supporters of<br />
illicit action on the part of the United States or<br />
South Vietnam. We are constantly aware of our duties<br />
to our country and our people. One of those duties<br />
is to do what we can to keep the peace, and to help<br />
others to keep it. Another is to be acutely </p>
<p>16.<br />
aware of the need to preserve the security of<br />
Australia. It would be a sorry day if, by<br />
undermining the will and capacity to resist<br />
in South-East Asia, we found aggressive<br />
Communism moving nearer to our own shores.<br />
We will observe our obligations under SEATO<br />
and ANZUS not only because Australia has<br />
pledged its word a reason compelling enough,<br />
in all conscience but because those obligations<br />
have been accepted on behalf of our own free<br />
future. To sum up, my Lord Bishop, we have<br />
never approached the problem in a negative way.<br />
We have no desire for hostilities to spread or<br />
to grow more intense, though, if this is forced<br />
upon us, we will face the resulting situation<br />
and not seek to avoid it.<br />
Like President Johnson, we wish South<br />
Vietnam and the whole of South and South-East<br />
Asia to live in peace and international amity<br />
and to have full and free opportunities for<br />
economic development and national independence.<br />
It is just because we believe in these positive<br />
objectives that we find ourselves unable to<br />
ignore the lessons of the 20th Century and to<br />
acquiesce placidly in the destruction of the<br />
independence of South Vietnam, either by direct<br />
outside armed Communist aggression or by internal<br />
armed Communist insurrection and subversion<br />
stimulated and sustained, as I am sure you must<br />
agree, through North Vietnam. </p>
<p>17.<br />
You have now twice publicly stated<br />
your views. This letter contains my second answer.<br />
You will, I am sure, understand that I must now<br />
leave the issues to the judgment of public opinion.<br />
I cannot, consistently with many pressing duties,<br />
continue this correspondence. But it has, I think,<br />
served a valuable public purpose. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
