<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5781</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/03/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005781.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Gover Inforri<br />
Unit Progr(<br />
. Date: n men?<br />
iati on 24l: M T R ANSC RIPi1<br />
~ rk Day<br />
Ith Mdarchi, 1982-. comonwoi4th GOweKaw~ i Ottim-&amp;<br />
4 Traevwy F1m,<br />
Broadcast VIG: 3AW<br />
INTERVIEW WITH P~ RII'tE MiNISTER<br />
LY<br />
Today I'm pleased to havie the Prime Nk. nister Rr. Fraser as a<br />
guest. on t: his piogram. I'm pleased because it's a most timely<br />
interview, For-quite a few~ days nbw;' we've been askilig J4r. r-raser<br />
to talk. -to us, because the Victorian State election is Just.<br />
over a week away, . a nd we thought he mig~ ht have some things to<br />
say on that. Houzing is a central--:, issue i11n this election,<br />
andl the -action -f Mr, Pxraser's Goveram'ent last week, in<br />
announcingj assistance for homebuyers would hAve in the niormal<br />
*-course-of things, helped the Thompson Governtment in its<br />
ff ighf. foK re-election', but perhaps it won't, because at the<br />
ame time as therederal Government announced it would help,<br />
it also announced that it ' had set in t'rain a 1 tper'cent rise<br />
in the coEst of home loans9.. And while ' the ' Victorian -Government<br />
moved swiftly'to coanter that w~ ith its home interest subsidy<br />
scheme mar-k2, the consensus of-political comment~ itoL's seemis-to<br />
be that the Federal* Go'ernj-ent's action could hurt rather than<br />
help Mr. Thompson. So we'll cove! r all that ground with<br />
Mx. Fraser. Blut it's particularly timely today that we're<br />
* talking because t he whole town's withf speoulation,. started<br />
with morning by The Age and splashed toniolit in the Herald that<br />
Mr. Anldriw Peacociz is preparing to . make a run against M1r. Fraser.<br />
On the line I have the man himself, the Prime Minister of<br />
Autralia, Rr. Malcolm Fraser, goodafternoon.<br />
PRIRPE IMINISTER:<br />
Good af ternfoon to you.. 2/ </p>
<p>-2<br />
DAY:<br />
mr. F-raser do you expect a challenge from Andrew Peacock?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER:<br />
V'o I don't.<br />
DAY:<br />
Would you ( laughs) well, that sort of takes-the wind out of my<br />
sails does~ n't it? it's been suggested that you might not<br />
object to a spill, that you have the nurnheris. and Mr. Peacocli<br />
hasn't, an~ d it's to your advantage to let him have a tilt at:<br />
your crown and lose, thereby-<br />
PRI61E MINISTER:<br />
Well : 1 think it's particularly' unfortunate,, and I think it's<br />
Herald.. I heard you referred to it, and you know, the run-up<br />
period to the Victorian election, because they are state<br />
__ issues anei this election in Victoria is going to be won on<br />
those issues, and quite obviously, stability and whatever is<br />
going to be helpfal to Lindsay Thompson in that period.<br />
DAY:<br />
Well why eto you think this speculation might have started at<br />
this Point?<br />
PRIME MINI: STER:<br />
Well you'dt have to ask somebody else that.<br />
DAY:<br />
ILa~ i. Last week you<br />
PRIME-MNISTER:<br />
Really, there are major jobs, major tasks in Government to be done.<br />
Quite obviously Australia faces problems. I suppose the<br />
Government or a country always does. 13ut there are very<br />
-Particular problems at the moment, some of them are home growni,<br />
and some are generated from events from overseas, arid you know-,<br />
our tash is to get on * ana do thle beqt job we possibly can. .3/ </p>
<p>DAY: But nevertheless there are polit<br />
I you of all, people are aware of*,<br />
and othe r observors to-b~ e distar<br />
result whatever it may be. ; ical realities which I'm sure<br />
and last week, you seemed to MO<br />
ioi-yourself from the Victorian<br />
PRI61S MINI: STER:<br />
I don't think so, no. I'd been aske-d a question about somethinlg,<br />
and it happens to be true that: for the f irst time that I can<br />
recall there are people trylnq', to say that tlie-State. eleetion<br />
is -for better or f or worse,. is the f ault of thh Federal Government.<br />
Now demon~ strably that' a not so. I believe that Lindsay<br />
Thompson is going to win, and wiin very well. But the factstill<br />
remains. People have voted ni election after an election,<br />
one way for Federal issues.. another way for State issues.<br />
You know, you could give examples, whether it's from New<br />
South Wales, fromn Victoria, or; from Tasmania, where the Labor<br />
Party are going to get booted right out whenever there's an<br />
election, and I think I was saying I find it very hard to<br />
understand why there seems to be a morbid determination amongst<br />
part of the media to say that whatever happens inl V. ictoria<br />
is of the consequence of Malcolm Fraser. They unfortunately<br />
know that-that's not so, and so does Victoria. Victoria wins,<br />
they win on State issues and not on Federal issues, and I'm sure<br />
you'd agree with that.<br />
DAY,. Yes, itake your point and I think you make the point well, but<br />
nevertheless there is still, page 1 lead of the Melbourne Her~ td<br />
tonight d&amp; rawing a line between a possible Liberal loss in<br />
Victoria andl a Peacock challenge to you. Now you say You don't<br />
think it will happen. You may'.% ell be right,. but the speculation<br />
is there, and it's my job to afik you for your reaction to it.<br />
PRIME MI1tN) STER:<br />
I tlhin^-I've given it to you haven't I? </p>
<p>I4. DAY;<br />
Yes, you donl. t expect ( laughs) ' to, have a challen ge.<br />
How damaging is it for you though to be looking over your<br />
shoulder. all the time?<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER:<br />
Well I'm ' not.. but it's fair-enough 1-thimk to make-the point<br />
that the job of Government is. vastly important. ] People of<br />
Liberal p'hilosophy and Liberalideas have cerain ideas of what<br />
we want for the future ofAustralia, for the kind of lives that:<br />
people can lead, the sort of opportunities we want to have<br />
available for Australian families, and for young. Australians<br />
in*-partic-ular, and we k~ now that there are problems in front<br />
of us, there are problems in front of all the major industrial.<br />
countries arourid the world, and fcrmotst of them,. their<br />
difficulties are muich, much greater than ours, and so whatever<br />
might be happening in the rear I find that I'm fully preoccupied<br />
with the bu. 9iness of Government, and I intend to keep<br />
-it that way#<br />
DAY: I tn, All right. Thank you for that. Let's move on to the<br />
homres issae, which together with financial management has<br />
dominated -the Victorian campaign. Your Governmerit was<br />
criticiced yesterday by what was see-n-bymotoerrsa<br />
a blatant assistance to theVictorian Liberals over your<br />
advertisements for your new home tax rebate scheme.<br />
PRIIAS MINrSTER:<br />
Well I thought that you just said that it should be felt that<br />
the whole thing might not be a help becauise of the interest<br />
rate increase, but what we're concerned about is that<br />
Australians with entitlements: under the proposcals will.-know<br />
what they are. and won't miss out because of inadequn-: te knowlee. ge W<br />
DAY: 3Is it juist a Coincidence then that the ads re weighted toware~ s<br />
Vi ctori a? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Wll I don't really believe they are weighted towards Victoria,<br />
but other people have made decisions about that, and they've<br />
answered t~ hem.. but the I<br />
DAY:<br />
w~ hat will the ads be saying?<br />
PRIHE bINISTER:<br />
But wait a minute, can Igo on please for a minute because-<br />
DAY; Sure. PRIM. E MINrSTER:<br />
I think you would agree that it would be quite impossible for<br />
a young couple to find out what their entitlement was if they.<br />
read all the newspapers.<br />
DAY: Yes. I admit to being confused myself. There a about<br />
six or seven schemes.__<br />
PRIM4E MINISTER:<br />
And therefore, to have an advertisement that in short compass<br />
gives an indication of what' s involved and how that young couple<br />
can go in detail and find out whether they are entitled to<br />
a new deposit aezistance, of two and a half to three and a half<br />
thousand dollars, on settlement or for the purchase of a house<br />
or a block of land, to find ouit if they are going to be. eligible<br />
for the rebate, because they purchased their first home over the<br />
last five years, or intend to purchase one shortly, to find out<br />
if they &amp; re going to be able to bo~ rrow., some of the additional<br />
400-million dollars which the banks have said they will lend over<br />
the next 12 nionths, to find out whet-her they will be eligible<br />
for alow interest rate start for a new loart th-rough the banking<br />
system, or whether they're el. igible for the shielding that the<br />
banks are prepared to offer to certain, well to all. people, iwho<br />
have ta1
is irnporltant-in-relation-to the entitlements of individual 1 .1 </p>
<p>PRU'WMITNISTER: cont...<br />
families, individual groups throughout the Austrzalianl communitY,<br />
and I believe that we have an obligation to make sure that<br />
people are: aware of their entitlements. if you want to,<br />
you know, quite obviously, the whole housing package was<br />
complex, it was an integrated package and -ijt involved very<br />
substantial negotiations between the Treasurer and the<br />
private banks, including the Coimonwealth Bank of course.<br />
And therefore it's taken a long while to put together. We.<br />
had said, the Treasurer said, and I said. thiat we'd be making<br />
a statement when we're ready. We recognised the importance<br />
of the problem, and the problem was in two parts. There was<br />
a _ p~ otage of! -capital,. so enough loans weren' t being mnade<br />
available, and important groups in the community, the price of<br />
the loan, in other words the interest was too high. Buth we<br />
said we'd make the statement when we were ready. If we'd<br />
been looking for pure political advantage of our oWn, I suppose<br />
y'ou might of expected that we would of announced something<br />
before Lowe. But I knew we couldn't be ready before Lowe and<br />
we weren' and we said so.<br />
DAY: Yes but. in that grezater scheue of things, surely -10 days<br />
wouldn't of made that much difference to people whio may or may<br />
not be entitled and certainly it would of insulated you fr-QM_<br />
any charges of blatantly assisting the Victorian Liberals, swit: h1<br />
Federal money, taxpayers, money.<br />
PR~ IME MTtj1STERYou'<br />
re tall1Jin9 about the advertisements?<br />
DAY: Yes. PRINFP 1MINrST1ER;<br />
Well I was~ mostly talkilig about the policy. I believe and the<br />
Treasurer took this Point this mornirt-g-hti-b nee<br />
of making sure that people know what their entitlements are and<br />
some of t. io~ e entitlements are imediate in terms of ma3
</p><p>-7-<br />
PRVIE MNIS'TER: Cont...<br />
choices between the old home savings grant scheme and going<br />
on to the new dieposit, assistance proposal, that we needed<br />
to let people JRnow what the score is. Now<br />
DAY:<br />
But in so doing you're still coppifig criticism for uising.<br />
taxpayers' money which may he seen to be helping theVictorian<br />
Liberals. PRIKrE MIN.( STER;<br />
I don't believe that the expenditure of a relatively small<br />
cmoutit of money is going to alter the balance in the State of.<br />
Victoria over issues that have, -in a sense, been fought ou t<br />
over many months. I don't believe that for one moment.<br />
DAY:<br />
Are you worried that this, the tax rebate pack~ age, and the<br />
homes package generally might be too limited. It affects only<br />
PRI14F MMISTERYes,<br />
hut s; omebody initerjected on me at Evans, Deakin a couple<br />
of weeks ago and I said when did you take out your loani. And this<br />
was before we announced anything. He sid 7 years ago. I said.<br />
w'hat was the value of your house at that time. He said $ 16,000.<br />
And obviously, lie's had very substantial. wage-increases zince,<br />
and obviously his house Is worth v'erat, very much more than the.<br />
$ 16 0O00 ho paid for it 7 years ago, And that particular person<br />
would be p) aying a much smaller part of hifj weekly wage on the<br />
home repayments-<br />
DAY: I agree v; hth you. That if, entirely Valid until he comes to .9ell<br />
and buy a new* house. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
MME MINISTBR:<br />
Well if he sells this house he will get the appreciated value f or<br />
it, and he ha s already made the investment over time, you see. So<br />
somebody whio has boughta-house earlier, sells that and buys another, V<br />
if they had paid off the first house, they should have a major<br />
p. Jof the equity for the one unless it is a substantially better house.<br />
This interview with the Prime Minister was recorded a little<br />
over an.-hour ago and sonte technical got into it then..<br />
We were about 30 second away from a break, which we've just<br />
taken, so we'll pick up the tape now.<br />
that<br />
There have~ been reports the economy is likely to get worse<br />
before it gets better and this-has led to speculation that<br />
you may call an early election. Will you?__<br />
I still believe the Parliament will go its full-term. What<br />
I have said, when Mr. 1eating indicated that he might want the<br />
Labor Party to refuse Supply, what I have said is that in those<br />
circumstances, quite plainly, the Liberal. Party bas got to be<br />
ready, bec; ause if the Labor Party co) mbine with the Demnocrats<br />
to refuse Supply, there will. obviously have to be an election.<br />
DAY: i~. you have tr. uched on this before. H-ow do you see the<br />
economic outlook% f orAutstralia.. in the next couple of years?<br />
The wage : ncrea-ses, coupled with shorter 1hours have been very,<br />
very unfortunatQ, because they've comte at a time when the rest<br />
of the wo:' ld has been, beconing more comipetitive. There's<br />
massve ueMployntu to neary 12 per. Dn-t in Britain aud<br />
8 and 9 Per cent in a number of other countries. Wle know it's<br />
too hig-here, but it's certainly riot as bad as in nios t o f the<br />
OECD countiries. 1because of the level of<br />
DAY:<br />
it's abouL-double American though isn't it?. 9/ </p>
<p>-9-<br />
DAY: it's about double the Americah rate?<br />
Here? DAY: Yes, P1RIMI MINI: STER:<br />
No, theArerican rate is very much above ours.<br />
DAY: What, infl~ ation? I'nm sorry, go on, uneimployment? F<br />
PRIR4E MIN'_ STER:__<br />
DAY: I'm sorry, I thoughit you were talking inflation.<br />
PR7" 4L MP-U~ STER:<br />
No, well) -their inflation rate is probably I suppose 8 or 9<br />
per cent on an annual basis at the moment. B~ it it's been<br />
coming down qiuite fast, But there' s no growth in the American.<br />
economy. Round about the begiuning of the year, they were<br />
prcoducing less than they had been. the year before, and that's<br />
the position again. ln~ a nuxnber.-of European countries, so<br />
under those circumrstances, it's not surprising they've been<br />
getting wage settlements arounrd 6, or 8 per cent. And<br />
againIst that background, they're becoming more competitive,<br />
better able to 2ell theiir goods, and we're finding that our<br />
prices are rising and it gets harder to sell Australian goods..<br />
Nqow this obviously mal-es it difficult for Australiandl-rms<br />
and difficult for Australian employment and we'% ve already begun<br />
to see this reflected in the figures arnd so the first, if -you<br />
like, challenge we have, probleim is the extent of the wages<br />
increaseE;, the ireduced hours, the additional cost that meant<br />
for indu : try n~ ing it Much harder to employ Australians. </p>
<p>PRIME 14INISTER: Cont...<br />
The other thing that's iade it. dif ficult is the continued<br />
downturn overseas and as a result of no growth, lower Inflation, I<br />
and greater cornpatitiveness in overseas countries.<br />
DAY; Just, butting in there if I may? How much do we depend on. theI<br />
Reagan economnic experiment working?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
The American~ economy is so large. and so in many ways, that it<br />
affects many, many coauntries, and-obviously it has an impact.<br />
on Australia, and especially through interest rates at the<br />
present time. So, we're significantly affected by what'<br />
happens irt the United States. We're also very much affected<br />
by what happens in Eur~ ope, That doesn't mean to say that<br />
you know, we thirow up our hands in horror and say it's all too.<br />
hard, They can mak~ e it difficult for us, ba. t.. we have..ñ obe<br />
ready, prepared to adjust our owa policies to do the best<br />
we possi. bly can to protect Australia in a difficult world<br />
envi2ronment. Now up to the pxesent time we have, because<br />
the econom~ y has grown, and expanded and household disposableincomes<br />
have qro , m while the world income has' beent as flat as<br />
it--ould' possibly be. The longer the world economy stays fl~ at?<br />
the harder it will be to protect Autralia. But that's<br />
our responsibility.<br />
DAY: Yeah, in : xecent days, Sir Phillip Lyrich has foresbadowed the<br />
possibilit~ y of a company tax reduction. Was-. he ju~ t--kite<br />
flying or did he have your bac'kiig in that?<br />
PRIME MINI) STER:<br />
He really has you krnow. if you read the speech-<br />
DA~ Y:<br />
I I m sorry, I've onl. y read the press report.. W'hat did he say<br />
then? </p>
<p>SPMRIMNI4SET rER:<br />
As he put it in the Parliament this morning, he pointed to the!<br />
fact that there are 1AC reports affectig the budgetary<br />
assistance for industry, depreciation allowances export<br />
incentiv~ es and investment allowances a a-nd whatever. And we've<br />
asked th e XAC to report to us on all of these matters. We'll<br />
have, there are two or three reports involved, we'l1' have themt<br />
all fairly shortly, and then we'll be examining the reports.<br />
Now the purpose of the examination in the first instance is not<br />
to reduce support for industry, but to see whether the support<br />
we are in fact providing has the most beneficial result for*<br />
industry. Now, this as I understand it, is what Sir Phillip<br />
was referring to,<br />
DAY: 14m. All right. ] By the fact you've accepted this invitation<br />
to talk to us today, you are, I-mean it's relatively rare, it's<br />
not every day you get the Prime Minifster to talk to you.<br />
Azrc-you stetting out to do a repair job on the Government's<br />
image. Do youa see the Government in trouble at the moment?<br />
H-ov~ long have you bec-n doing this programn?<br />
Ohl almost three months.<br />
PRIM~ E MNWSTIER:<br />
Well, you know, I've been 5peaking to -on talkback programs<br />
quite diriactly, qUite regUllarly I haven't been on your program<br />
before, b-at I'm happyf to do it on a reasonably regular basis<br />
if you'd like me to, because one of the advantager. of a talkhack<br />
progr'am, you ask the questions and my words jo, out as the'y<br />
coro. a. The y don't get edited, they kon't cjet chianged, they don't<br />
get interpretted. At least. not at the time.<br />
DAY: Some comm-antators have stiggested though that following Lotw-e, the<br />
Goverament's imange, and your imgwell if I may Sayl it, low, and<br />
I draw a ], iup, between those comments and your acceptance. We have<br />
asked bofore anid you've been too busy, ; w ich I can also unders3tanld.<br />
11 </p>
<p>12<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
The acceptance hasn't. . n fact been put to me beforeand. maTer<br />
it-should of<br />
DAY: Perhaps it. should of,<br />
PRINLE MINISTER:<br />
1efore and after Lowe, I've been on talk-back programs with<br />
Bert Newton and John LawS and other people in different States.<br />
DAY: This is the thinking man's program. ( laughs)<br />
PRIIKE MINISTER:<br />
ell I'm very happy to be on the thinking man's program.<br />
Aid so it may be just a function of the' fact that you have been operating<br />
three months and not longer.<br />
Are you going to miss David Barnett?<br />
PRVV-14INISTER:<br />
I will. He's been around a long time, but it's a veiry<br />
tough-and rugged-job and I go to bed at night and the press<br />
DAY: Have you got any one in mind to rep. ace him?<br />
PRI4E MINISTER:<br />
-gr. rgiiig him up all night.<br />
DAY: ( laughs) Have you got any one in Tnnd to replac him?<br />
Oell there are other people in the prez5 offic, and-at the<br />
moment they will. be carrying on. .13/ </p>
<p>13-<br />
DAY:<br />
All right, well one final question, and i do hesitate to raise<br />
it, because of the stink that issue caused at the time of<br />
CHOGM. But I've got my ear to the ground and I hear from<br />
tine to tjme that you're not in the best of health, and<br />
we don't report these tips from people allegedly in the no,<br />
because thiey can't be confirmed, so simply, can I ask you<br />
how is your health?<br />
PRIMP, MINJISTER:<br />
Fine. DAY: Fine. PRIRE MUISTER:<br />
lim. DAY: it is a demanding job?<br />
PRI( M E HINISTER.<br />
Yes, of course it is.<br />
DAY: But you looked to be enjoying yourEself at the Man from<br />
Snowy River prelview at the weekend.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
It w) as a great film, it really was, and I think it will be<br />
a wonderfuI f1 g carrier.<br />
DAY: I saw it: last night, anld I agree % ith you. I don't agree with<br />
you on everything Prime Minister, but I'll agree with you on that.<br />
PRTME, MTNIS'ER;<br />
You aqrrie with me oii t-he film, weli. that's a stai't, There inight<br />
be hope for: you yt. </p>
<p>14<br />
DAY: Oay, thank you very tnuch alid we' 1ll take you up on your<br />
offer of more iegular interviews,<br />
PRlIME ZINSTER:<br />
Thank you. ENDS. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
