<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23302</transcript-id>
    <title>Additional support for residents affected by Hazelwood fire</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/03/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Relocation payments will be made available to assist eligible local residents in Morwell South to temporarily relocate to avoid exposure to smoke and ash from the fires currently burning.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth and Victorian Governments have agreed to a joint funding package under the Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements following advice from Dr Rosemary Lester, Victoria’s Chief Health Officer.</p>
<p>Temporary relocation payments of up to $1,250 per week are available to eligible households under the joint-funding arrangement.</p>
<p>Dr Lester has advised that vulnerable people living in Morwell South, including people aged over 65, young children, pregnant women and people with a pre-existing heart or lung condition, should consider relocation because of the prospect of extended exposure to smoke and ash from the Hazelwood mine fire.</p>
<p>Residents seeking assistance are advised to contact the Department of Human Services (DHS) hotline on 1800 006 468 to make an appointment to speak to a DHS officer at one of the following three locations:</p>
<ul><li>Department of Human Services Office, 9-11 Hazelwood Road, Morwell</li>
</ul><ul><li>Commercial Road Primary School, Commercial Road, Morwell</li>
</ul><ul><li>Senior Citizens Hall, Maryvale Crescent, Morwell.</li>
</ul><p>The Victorian Government is working as a matter of urgency to finalise a range of support initiatives to assist small businesses who have been affected by this emergency.</p>
<p>These initiatives are being put in place through partnerships between the Victorian Government, Commonwealth Government and industry.</p>
<p>The Victorian Government will work in close partnership with businesses in Morwell to ensure that this assistance is targeted to the needs of the local community.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
