<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4649</transcript-id>
    <title>INQUIRY INTO WHALES AND WHALING, 19 MARCH 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/03/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004649.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR P~ RESS 19 IMARC!! 1978<br />
INQUIRY INTO WHALES AND WHALING<br />
The Government's concern to preserve and conserve the many<br />
species of whales is w-ell known. Australia has played a major<br />
part in instituting procedures in the International haling<br />
Commission designed to achieve this aim, and in fact a moratorium<br />
has been declared on the taking of certain species.<br />
In accordance with an earlier commitment, the Government is<br />
proceeding to establish an Inquiry to examine and report upon<br />
Australia's policies on whales and whali ' ng. The Inquiry will<br />
examine all available evidence and arguments, and miake<br />
reconmmendations on the best way in which Australia might pursue<br />
its policy of preservation and conservation of whales.<br />
The Inquiry will be asked to examine particularly whether<br />
Australian whaling, should continue or cease, the consequences for<br />
international whalingy of Australia's decision, and the operations<br />
of international reguLlatory mechanisms in so far as these bear<br />
on Australia's concern for preservation and conservation of whales.<br />
Terms of reference for the Inquiry are attached.. These have been<br />
discussed with interested parties, including both conservationists<br />
and whaling industry representatives.<br />
It is essential that all interested parties have an opportunity to<br />
contribute to the Inquiry. It will be open to the Inquiry to hold<br />
public sessions, and submissions will be sought from the general<br />
public, scientific experts, conservation groups and whaling<br />
interests as well as Commonwealth and State Government Departments<br />
and agencies.<br />
The Inquiry will also be able to draw on international expertise.<br />
This could include bringing experts to Australia or overseas travel<br />
by the Inquiry, but details are still to be determined in<br />
conjunction with the head of the Inquiry.<br />
The Inquiry will be conducted by the Honourable Sir Sydney Frost.<br />
Sir Sydney, formerly a Queen's Counsel at the Victorian Bar, took<br />
up an appointment in 1964 as a Judge of the Supreme Court of<br />
Papua New Guinea. On the independence of Papua New Guinea in 1975,<br />
he was appointed as its first Chief Justice,-a position from which<br />
he retired late last year.<br />
Sir Sydney will have the support of scientific advisers and a<br />
Secretariat. He has been asked to report in September or as soon<br />
as possible thereafter. 00--</p>
<p>InNp1x~ 0,' L~ 1 HA 1 1G<br />
1. The ury shall cexazrne and report upon<br />
A us{ r aIi a ' s pol iicS on Whale. s an. wa. rr. It shallmk<br />
recommrrenOdations~ oni th'e best way in which Alistralia Mir,' t<br />
pursue ilks plc c preservation and conser-vation of the<br />
many, species of whales ( also known as cetacea).<br />
2. The Inqiairy shall. in particular examaine:<br />
0 whether Australian whalingy should continue or<br />
cease;<br />
0 the consequences for international whalinC&gt;<br />
of Australia's decision;<br />
international regrulatory mechanisms in so far<br />
as These bear on Australia's concern for<br />
preservation and. conservation of whal1-e s.<br />
3. ithout limiting i ts scope in any y in cons-idering<br />
Australia's possible actions tha Inquiry shall examinne:<br />
the role of w~ hales in marine ecosystems anethe<br />
impact of past and current whale harvestinga<br />
strategies on the marine environment;<br />
any special features of whales which may make<br />
their conservation inprtnt<br />
significan~ t consequences2 if any, for other<br />
a-reas of conservation, policy;<br />
methods used in taking whales and whAether better<br />
ricthods are, possible.<br />
factors influencing the scale of Au stralian and<br />
vorid whaling activity includlin-the, demand for<br />
products derived whales arid the possibilities<br />
for Substitution; </p>
<p>I I 2.<br />
any Con; CIS1UolCoS feTor AustraLa-I it oT poyiuot atA<br />
industr-c al ( leveloppicmt, particuliarly ir Albariv<br />
the irnnlic; tions of Australia's policics on 200<br />
rautic&gt; KlL fish: i.-c, anim economic zones in<br />
Australiil w; aters, including those aljanccnt to<br />
the Aistrzlii-an Antarctic Territory;<br />
foreign relations aspects;<br />
any other considerations relevant to whales and<br />
whaling. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
