<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3426</transcript-id>
    <title>SPECIAL ASSISTANCE FOR COUNTRY CITIES AND TOWNS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003426.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 348<br />
22 October 1974<br />
SPECIAL ASSISTANCE FOR COUNTRY CITIES AND TOWS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, today announced details<br />
of a scheme to give special assistance to country cities and towns<br />
affected by certain Government decisions.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the Government had se-aside fundis<br />
for this purpose from the $ 10 million allocated for structural<br />
assistance. He said: " The Government has taken many decisions in<br />
the national interest acz part of its fight against inflation and<br />
its campaign for greater Productivity.<br />
" These policies must stand. The fight against inflation<br />
must go on. " Nevertheless, there are country cities and towns which<br />
find it difficult to cope immediately with the effects of some<br />
of these policies. " Our scheme is designed to help them over their<br />
difficulties and prevent unnecessary unemployment.<br />
" There will be continued close co-operation between<br />
the Australian and State Governments so that this policy is<br />
co-ordinated with decentralisation policy generally."<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that those initially eligible for<br />
assistance would be companies affected by:<br />
1. the 25% tariff cut;<br />
2. the consumer electronic components and equipment tariff decision;<br />
3. the domestic appliances tariff decision;<br />
4. the lifting of tariff quotas on woven shirts and knitted<br />
outergarments; the decision of 18 December 1973 to revise the subsidy and<br />
quota arrangements for the shipbuilding industry. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The C'overnment would consider extendinq its assistance,<br />
wherever necessary, to companies affected by other decisions<br />
involving structural change.<br />
The scheme will apply in all non-metropolitan centres<br />
except those immediately adjacent to capital cities.<br />
The Government will give priority to assistance to<br />
relevant companies in Launceston and Wangaratta.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said the scheme was being introduced to<br />
supplement existing adjustment assistance measures.<br />
The measures now approved include:<br />
Subsidies to companies. Where necessary pre-payment of<br />
subsidy may be arranged to grant immediate liquidity. A<br />
profit limitation will be applied to such payments.<br />
Capital grants to companies or local bodies for the establishment<br />
of viable alternative production and employment.<br />
Loan guarantees ( after necessary legislation has been passed)<br />
Finance to companies or local bodies for feasibility studies<br />
to improve methods of production or to examine alternative<br />
forms of production.<br />
Subsidies to help people travel from adversely affected towns<br />
to jobs in nearby towns.<br />
The scheme will be administered by the Department of<br />
Manufacturing Industry in consultation with other interested<br />
Departments pending the establishment of the Structural Adjustment<br />
Board. The Interim Committee on Structural Adjustment will review<br />
the program and provide advice on both policy and practical aspect3.<br />
All enquiries should be directed to the Department of Manufacturing<br />
Industry. A reference on the principles and operations of the<br />
scheme will be sent to the IAC after the scheme has been in operatlon<br />
for two years.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
