<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2784</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN HIGH COMMISSIONER&#039;S OFFICE, WELLINGTON - OUTWARD TELEGRAM</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002784_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUSTRALIAN HIGH COMMISSIONER'S OFFICE<br />
WELLINGTON<br />
Outward Telegram to<br />
RZUPX COUMW ( WsA/ AP0qM 2.2jV g .422aMe<br />
UNCLASSIFIED 110 FOLLOWING IS UNOFFICIAL TRANSCRIPT OF JOINT PRIME MINISTERIAL<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE HELD IN PARLIAMENT HOUSE, WELLINGTON, AFTERNOON<br />
OF 22 JANUARY 1972.<br />
BEGINS MR WHITLAM LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THE PRIME MINISTER HAS BEEN GOOD ENOUGH<br />
TO SUGGEST THAT I SHOULD ANNOUNCE THIS MATTER WHICH HIS CABINET<br />
WAS GOOD ENOUGH TO DECIDE WHEN I VISITED THEM THIS MORNING*<br />
I SUPPOSE THAT YOU HAD HEARD THAT MY GOVERNMENT HAD SOUGHT NEW<br />
ZEALAND'S ASSISTANCE IN ESTABLISHING A SCHOOL DENTAL SERVICE<br />
IN AUSTRALIA. THERE IS A START OF SUCH A SERVICE IN THE SMALLEST<br />
AUSTRALIAN STATE AND THE THIRD SMALLEST BUT NOT IN ANY OF THE<br />
OTHERS. YOU KNOW THE COMPLEXITIES OF THE AUSTRALIAN FEDERAL<br />
SYSTEM. THIS WOULD ORDINARILY BE A STATE RESPONSIBILITY, BUT<br />
SINCE THERE IS NO GOVERNMENT WHICH HAS ACCEPTED THE RESPONSIBILITY<br />
UP TILL NOW, IT'S FALLEN TO THE NEW COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT TO DO<br />
IT AND WE NATURALLY THOUGHT OF NEW ZEALAND'S EXPERIENCE EXTENDING I<br />
BELIEVE OVER 50 YEARS. SO WE SAID IN THE WORDS OF PAUL, WILL YOU<br />
COME OVER AND HELP US AND MR TIZARD PUT TO CABINET TODAY A PROPOSAL<br />
WHICH WILL, WE BELIEVE, ENABLE US TO TAKE UP 50 PLACES IN MARCH,<br />
ISN'T IT, AND ANOTHER 50 PLACES IN SEPTEMBER, AND THEN WE WOULD<br />
HOPE IN DUE COURSE THAT YOUR MATRON INSPECTORS WILL COME TO<br />
AUSTRALIA AND HELP TO ESTABLISH SIMILAR TRAINING FACILITIES THERE<br />
TO SUPERINTEND THE OPERArION OF THE SERVICE IN TilE SCHOOLS.<br />
WELL, I'D LIKE TO ACKNOWLE) GE PUBLICLY, AS I HAVE WARMLY IN<br />
PRIVATE, THAT THIS HAS BEEN A MOST GENEROUS ACTION BY THE NEW<br />
ZEALAND GOVERNMENT. IT'S A FIELf) WHERE NEW ZEALAND HAS HAD A<br />
SOCIAL WELFARE SCHEME OF GREAT BENEFIT FOR MANY YEARS. AUSTRALIA<br />
HAS NOT. SO YOU WERE WILLING To HELP US START. THE URGENCY OF<br />
IT FLOWS OF COURSE FROM THE FACT THAT THE YOUNG PEOPLE WHO WILL BE<br />
ENCOURAGED TO TAKE THIG CAREER ARE JUST GETTING THEIR EXAM<br />
RESULTS FROM THE END OF THEIR SECONDARY EDUCATION AND WILL BE<br />
DETERMINING WHAT THEY SHALL DO NEXT. SO MANY OF THEM WILL NOW BE<br />
ABLE TO SERVE IN THIS NEW FIIœ LI).<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER, IN RESPECT OF THE 50 PLACES THAT ARE GOING<br />
TO COME TO AUSTRALIA ( INAUDIBLE)<br />
MR WHITLAM NO, THEY WILL BE AUSTRALIANS COMING TO NEW ZEALAND<br />
TO OCCUPY THE SPARE PLACES WHICH NEW ZEALAND HAS CREATED FOR THEM.<br />
WILL THIS BE AT NEW ZEALAND'S EXPENSE?<br />
MR WHITLAM NO, NO, WE'LL BE QUITE WILLING TO PAY FOR THE WHOLE<br />
LOT </p>
<p>MR KIRK WE HAVE AGREED) IN PRINCIPLE TO THE TRAINING OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIANS HERE* THERE WILL BE SOME NEGOTIATIONS AT THE<br />
OFFICIAL LEVEL TO SET THE TERMS OF WHICH IT HAS ACHIEVED* WE<br />
ARE TOLD BY OUR ADVISERS THAT ONE OF THE REASONS WHY WE ARE ABLE<br />
TO MAKE PLACES AVAILABLE IS THAT THE WIDENED USE OF FLUORIDES<br />
HAS IMPROVED DENTAL HEALTH TO THE POINT THAT THERE IS SOME<br />
AVAILABLE ACCOMMODATION NOW INSID) E THE SERVICE SO THAT IT IS<br />
ABLE TO BE UTILISED IN THIS WAY.<br />
MR KIRK, COULD YOU TELL US THE NAME OF THE-SERVICE, WHAT<br />
SCHOOLS WILL THEY BE USING, WHAT COURSES WILL THEY BE UNDERTAKINC4?<br />
MR KIRK WELL,.-THEY'LL COME HERE TO, WELLINGTON. THE SCHOOL<br />
DENTAL SERVICE ( UNDERLINE THREE) IS IT'S POPULAR DESIGNATION<br />
THROUGHOUT NEW ZEALAND, AND IT HAS BEEN A SCHOOL THAT HAS BEEN<br />
INVOLVED IN THE TRAINING OF YOUNG WOMEN, THOUGH THERE IS NO<br />
SPECIFIC REASON WHY IT SHOULD BE EXCLUSIVELY HELD TO THEM* IT<br />
MAY WELL BE THAT AUSTRALIA OR OURSELVES MAY WANT TO TRAIN YOUNG<br />
MEN WHO CHOOSE TO TAKE UP THIS VOCATION. THERE IS NO STRICT<br />
LIMITATION ON WOMEN ONLY. AND IT PROVID) ES DENTAL CARE FOR<br />
PRE-SCHOOL AND PRIMARY SCHOOL CHILDREN THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.<br />
Qo THERE IS NO REASON FOR AUSTRALIA TO RECRUIT EXISTING TRAINED<br />
DENTAL SERVICES TO COME TO AUSTRALIA.<br />
MR KIRK NO, THEY WILL RECRUIT FROM THEIR OWN YOUNG PEOPLE AND<br />
IT IS PROPOSED THAT THE TRAINEES COME HERE, AND WE WELCOME IT<br />
FOR ANOTHER REASON BECAUSE IT GIVES US THE OPPORTUNITY TO EMPLOY<br />
SKILLED AND TRAINED NEW ZEALANDERS IN NEW ZEALAND RATHER THAN<br />
LOSE THEM ABROAD WHERE TRAINING HAS TAKEN THEM SOMEWHERE ELSE.<br />
Q, WHAT IS THE DURATION OF THE COURSE?<br />
MR KIRK I CAN'T TELL YOU THE FULL LENGTH OF THE COURSE, BUT THE<br />
SECON4D INTAKE WILL COME IN WHEN IT HAS BEEN RUNNING TWO YEARS.<br />
MR WHITLAM I THINK IT'S THAT. THE AUSTRALIANS HERE WILL KNOW,<br />
AND WHAT THE NEW ZFEALANDER MIGHTN'T APPRECIATE, THE NEW AUSTRALIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT IS WANTING TO CREATE A SUFFICIENT FRAMEWORK IN THE<br />
LIFETIME OF THIS PARLIAMENT IN THIS COMING THREE YEARS<br />
TO ENSURE THAT IN THE FOLLOWING PARLIAMENT OPPORTUNITIES FOR<br />
PRE-SCHOOL EDUCATION AND FOR-SOCIAL WORKERS AS WELL AS FOR<br />
DENTAL THERAPISTS OR DENTAL NURSES AND YOUTH LEADERS: AND IN<br />
AUSTRALIA THERE ARE JUST NOT AT PRESENT THE FACILITIES TO TRAIN<br />
THE YOUNG MEN AND WOMEN WHO WANT TO TAKE THESE CAREERS. THIS<br />
WAS ONE WHERE YOU COULD HELP US.<br />
Q-WHEN CAN WE EXPECT T1HAT THE YOUNG PEOPLE WHO ARE TRAINED<br />
HERE WILL BE ACTUALLY OPERATING IN AUSTRALIA?<br />
MR WHITLAM I DON'T KNOW. THI. WILL BETTER COME FROM MR TIZARO,<br />
THE NEW ZEALAND MINISTER FOR HEALTH, OR DR EVERINGIHAM, THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN ONE, WHO IS SENDING -US EXCELLENT INFORMATION OVER<br />
THIS WEEK. IT COULD BE POSSIBLE FOR THE FIRST OF THEM TO BE<br />
TRAINING IN MARCH.<br />
Q-I'D LIKE TO ASK MR KIRK WHETHER THIS INVOLES ANY<br />
ALTERATION OF THE NEW ZEALAND COURSE, TO ACCOMMODATE THESE.<br />
MR KIRK NO, THE MAINTENANCE OF THE BASIS OF TRAIN* ING, WILL BE<br />
CONTINUED AND IT WILL BE TO THE SAME STANDARD AND THE SAME WORK*<br />
Q. AND THE NUMBERS ACTUALLY UNDERGOING TRAINING WILL-NOT BE<br />
EXPANDED BY THIS PROCESS? </p>
<p>MR KIRK NO. WE HAVE SOME AVAILABLE CAPACITY AND' IT MEANS THAT WE<br />
CAN TAKE 50 IN THIS INTAKE AND 50 AGAIN IN SEPTEMBER. IF THERE<br />
IS AN EXPANSION OF THE FACILITIES NECESSARY TO PROVIDE FOR A<br />
GREATER NUMBER IF THIS WAS NEEDED, THAT ALSO CAN BE ARRANGED,<br />
AND AT THE POINT WHERE WE ARRIVE WHERE THE FACILITIES ARE GREATER<br />
THAN IS NEEDED THERE IS STILL BE POTENTIAL WITHIN THOSE FACILITIES<br />
FOR SOME SIMJLAR TRAINING AS PART OF DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE WITH<br />
OTHER COUNTRIES. IT'S NOT A MATTER OF ESTABLISHING FACILITIES<br />
WHICH COULD BECOME REDUNDANT. WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A LONGER<br />
TERM USAGE.<br />
Q* IS THIS SCHEME LIKELY TO BE THE FORERUNNER OF OTHER SCHEMES<br />
WHICH COULD POSSIBLY BE ON A RECIPROCAL BASIS?<br />
MR KIRK -IT COULD WELL BE WHERE THERE IS ADVANTAGE IN WORKING<br />
TOGETHER -WE'RE CERTAINLY GOING TO DO IT.<br />
PRIME MINISTER, CAN I ASK YOU ABOUT THE COM1MUNIQUE IN RESPECT<br />
OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS TESTING. YOU'VE AGREED TO WORK TOGETHER<br />
AND USE ALL APPROPRIATE MEANS. WOULD YOU BE PREPARED TO SAY<br />
WHAT MEANS YOU WOULD CONSIDER APPROPRIATE?<br />
MR WHITLAM NO, WE CERTAINLY DID DISCUSS MEANS, BUT QUITE<br />
FRANKLY WE DON'T WANT TO GO INTO DETAILS OF THESE THINGS AT<br />
THE MOMENT. I DON'T KNOW IF IN NEW ZEALAtnD THE ANSWER I's<br />
ACCEPTABLE THAT USED TO BE ACCEPTAB3LE IN AUSTRALIA RECENTLY,<br />
BUT THIS IS A HYPOTHETICAL QUESTION. WE ARE IN AUSTRALIA NOT<br />
GOING TO ASSUME THAT THE FRENCH WILL GO AHEf7AD WITH ANY FURTHER<br />
NUCLEAR TESTING REGARDLESS OF THE RESOLUTION OF THE GENERAL<br />
ASSEMBLY. IN NOVEMBER AND OF THE PROCEEDINGS WHICH AUSTRALIA IS<br />
GOING TO INTIATE IN THE WORLD COURT. YOU WILL REMEMBER THAT<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS TAKEN THIS STEP OF DELIVERING4 A NOTE TO FRANCE<br />
RAISING A LEGAL DISPUTE. WE ARE NOT AT THIS STAGE GOING TO<br />
ASSUME THAT THE FRENCH WILL PRESS ON.<br />
Q. DID YOU DISCUSS THE QUESTION OF AUSTRALIA'S CHALLENGE?<br />
HAS NEW ZEALAND AGREED TO SUPPORT IT?<br />
MR WHITLAM HERE AGAIN I THINK WE HAVE TO BE A LITTLE RETICENT<br />
WITH YOU IF YOU DON'T MIND, BECAUSE THERE ARE ELEMENTS OF THE<br />
COURT PROCEEDINGS WHICH WOULD BE PLACED) IN DOUBT IF WE WERE<br />
TO BROADCAST THE NATURE OF THE PROCEEDINGS OR THE BASIS OF THEM.<br />
Q. COULD I ASK MR KIRK WHETHER NEW ZEALAND IS GOING TO GO ALONG<br />
WITH AUSTRALIA FULLY ON THIS SUB11ISSION TO THE WORLD COURT?<br />
MR KIRK WE DON'T FIND OURSELVES IN ANY POSITION SO FAR AS THE<br />
APPROACH TO THE INTERN-ATION4AL COURT IS CONCERNED), AND INDEED<br />
WE HAVE CONDUCTED SOME PRELIMINARY EXAMINATION OF WHAT IS<br />
INVOLVED). FURTHERMORE WE HAVE GATHERED AN AMOUNT OF SCIENTIFIC<br />
INFORMATION4 THAT WOULD BE INVALUABLE ON ANY SUC1H COURT ACTION,<br />
AND I MIGHT ADD TO THAT SPECIFICALLY THAT, BYTr VIRTUE OF BEING<br />
CLOSER TO THE TEST AREA THAN AUSTRALIA, HAVE THAT MUCH ADDED<br />
STANDING TO THIS COMPLAINT, SO FAR AS FALLOUT FROM THE TESTS<br />
IS CONCERNED. FOR OUR PART OF IT, WE HAVE CONSIDERED THE<br />
APPROACH THAT AUSTRALIA HAS MADE TO THE INTERNATIONAL COURT.<br />
WE'RE INTERESTED IN IT. WE HAVE UNDERTAKEN SOME LEGAL STUDIES<br />
AND CERTAINLY WE'RE EXAMINING THE POSSIBILITY OF SUPPORTING<br />
AUSTRALIA IN THAT RESPECT. THOUGH THAT IS NOT ALL WE'RE<br />
EXAMINING. WE HAVE SIMILARLY CONSIDERED CONSULTATIONS WITH OTHER<br />
COUNTRIES AND WE WILL CONTINUE OF COURSE WITH THAT. BUT WE ARE<br />
NOT IN A POSITION OF ACCEPTING THAT FRANCE IS ENTRENCHED INTO<br />
THE POINT THAT IT WILL NOT CEASE THE TESTING, BUT WE'RE BEING<br />
PROVEN IN THAT SO FAR AS WE'RE ABLE, IF SUCH AN ENTRENCHMENT<br />
WOULD DEVELOP, THAT WE WOULD STILL BE IN A POSITION TO GO ON<br />
WITHOUT ANY GREAT LOSS OF* TIME. </p>
<p>SO THERE IS A POSSIBILITY THAT NEW ZEALAND WILL NOT GO ON<br />
WITH AUSTRALIA TO THE WORLD COURT?<br />
MR KIRK NO, WE'RE NOT EXAMINING IT FROM THAT POINT OF VIEW,<br />
I THINK THAT THERE ARE NO GROUNDS FOR JUSTIFYING THAT QUESTION.<br />
CAN I PUT IT ANOTHER WAY? YOU SAID A LITTLE WHILE AGO,<br />
EFFECTIVE MEANS OF CHALLENGING THE TESTS STEMS THROUGH AN<br />
INTERNATIONAL COURT FOR THE CHALLENGE TO BE EFFECTIVE.<br />
MR KIRK NO, I SAID EFFECTIVE MEANS, ' AND I DIDN'T MEAN THAT<br />
THIS WOULD BE SOME METHOD OF USING THE COURT, BUT AN EFFECT IVE<br />
AVENUE THAT IS OPEN TO BRING ABOUT NOT ONLY FRENCH TESTING.,<br />
BUT WE'RE CONCERNED TO BRING ABOUT THE* CESSATION OF ALL TESTING,<br />
AND-SO ANY EFFECTIVE AVENUE WOULD CERTAINLY BE EXAMINED) BY US<br />
AND WE'RE EXAMINING THE INTERNATIONAL COURT, THE PART THAT WE<br />
CAN PLAY IN IT AND THE POSSIBILITY OF HOW WE COULD BE LINKED<br />
WITH IT. AND WE SHOULD BE QUITE HAPPY TO CO-OPERATE IN EVERY WAY<br />
WE CAN WITH ANY ACTION THAT ADVANCES THE OBJECT OF BRIN( GING<br />
ABOUT THE CESSATION OF WEAPON4S TESTING.<br />
MR KIRK, IT HAS BEEN SUGGESTED, I THINK BY YOURSELF DURING<br />
THE ELECTION CAMPAIGN, I'M SUBJECT TO CORRECTION ON THAT POINT,<br />
THAT NEW ZEALAND COUL() SEND A SHIP WITH CABINET MINISTERS ABOARD<br />
TO THE AREA OF MURORUA ATOLL. WAS THIS ONE OF THE EFFECTIVE<br />
MEANS THAT YOU DISCUSSED WITH MR WHITLAM AND DID YOU ASK WHETHER<br />
THERE WAS ANY POSSIBILITY OF AUSTRALIA PROVIDING REFUELLING<br />
FACILITIES FOR SUCH A VENTURE?<br />
MR KIRK NO. WE DISCUSSED THIS QUESTION AND IT IS STILL VERY<br />
MUCH IN OUR MIND, BUT AS A LAST RESORT, AND I AM NOT PREPARED<br />
AT THIS STAGE THAT WE SHOULD BE SO UNSUCCESSFUL AS TO GET TO<br />
THE LAST RESORT BEFORE WE GET ANY MOVEMENT.<br />
IS THAT WHEN YOU THOUGH THE IDEA UP?<br />
MR KIRK OHl NO. WE ARE NOT ( INAUDIBLE) THE NEW ZEALAND<br />
VIEW RELENTING IN ANY WAY. WE WANT THOSE TESTS TO CEASE. I<br />
HOPE THAT FRANCE WILL REALISE WHAT DAMAGE IT IS DOING TO THE<br />
REPUTATION OF FRANCE TO CONTINUE THE TESTS AND WILL CEASE THAT<br />
PARTICULAR PROJECT, BUT I THINK IT'S PUTTING THE CAR BEFORE<br />
THE HORSE TO START FIGHTING FROM THE LAST DITCH. WE WANT TO<br />
START A BIT EARLIER THAN THAT.<br />
HAS THERE BEEN ANY ACTION OR COMMUNICATION WHICH SUGGESTS<br />
TO YOU POSITIVELY THAT FRANCE MAY IN FACT ACT UPON ITS PROPOSALS<br />
TO GO AHEAD AND HOLD THE TESTS?<br />
MR KIRK NO, AND I'M BOUND TO' SAY WE HAVE HAD NO RECENT OR<br />
EFFECTIVE COMMUNICATIONS THAT IT WILL CONTINUE. SO AT THIS<br />
STAGE IT IS AN OPEN QUESTION.<br />
Q-IN THE EVENT OF IT BEING NECESSARY TO GO TO THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
COURT OF JUSTIC AND THE APPEAL BE DONE TO GET AN INJUNCTION<br />
TO RESTRAIN IT WHAT IS THE LAST RESORT AS AUSTRALIA **( ZINAUDIBLE)<br />
MR WHITLAM WE SOUGHT OUT SEVERAL CONTINGENCIES, YES, BUT I<br />
DON'T WANT TO STATE WHAT THEY ARE. </p>
<p>MR KIRK I MIGHT ADD TO THAT IF I COUL). WE'RE ATTRACTED TO THE<br />
PROPOSITION OF GOING TO THE INTERNATIONAL C: OURT BECAUSE TO SMALL<br />
COUNTRIES THE RULE OF LAW IS TREMENDOUSLY IMPORTANT AND IT OFFERS<br />
ONE AVENUE OF ENDEAVOUR WHICH ALSO HIGHLIqHTS THE ATTACHMENT TO<br />
THE RULE OF LAW IN INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS. AND SMALL NATIONS<br />
THE WORLD OVER ARE TREMENDOUSLY DEPENDENT ON THE RULE OF LAW.<br />
THIS HAS CONSIDERABLE ATTRACTION AS FAR AS WE ARE CONCERNED*<br />
WAS THERE ANY DISCUSSION OF YOUR IDEA LAST YEAR,<br />
MR KIRK, OF YOUR HOLDIN~ G A CONFERENCE-OF ALL AFFECTED<br />
COUNTRIES NOTABLY AUSTRALIA, NEW ZEALAND, THE ISLAND<br />
TERRITORIES AND SOUTH AMERICAN COUNTRIES?<br />
MR KIRK YES, AS AN APPROACH, AND IT HAS NOT BEEN RULED OUT.<br />
WAS THAT CANVASSED THOUGH IN YOUR TALKS WITH MR WIIITLAM?<br />
MR KIRK OH YES.<br />
WHAT'S YOUR POSITION ON THAT MR WHITLAM? DO YOU SUPPORT<br />
THE CONCEPT OF HAVING A SOUTH PACIFIC CONFERENCE ON THE TESTS?<br />
MR WHITLAM I THINK THIS IS QUITE AN APPROPRIATE METHOD. AS<br />
I SAY, WE DON'T WANT TO CONCED THAT FRANCE WILL NOT FALL INTO<br />
LINE WITH THE OPINIONS EXPRESSED BY EVERY COUNTRY WITHIN<br />
THOUSANDS OF MILES OF THE TESTS, OR THAT THE STEPS WHICH WE<br />
HAVE IN MIND IN THE WORLD CO URT WOULDN'T SUCCEED IN PREVENTING;<br />
FRANCE FROM GOING AHEAD WITH THEM IF SHE WANTED TO. WE DON'T<br />
WANT TO ASSUME THAT FRANCE WILL CONTINUE TO DEFY WORLD OPINION<br />
OR, IF IT CAME TO THAT, TO DISREGARD THE WORLD COURT.<br />
Q9-WHAT MAKES YOU THIINK( THAT FRANCE MIGHT CHANGE ITS MIND NOW<br />
AFTER IT HASN'T AFTER ALL THE PRESSURES OF THE PAST?<br />
MR WHITLAMD WELL, FRANCE DID CHANGE HER MIND ONCE BEFORE ON<br />
NUCLEAR TESTS. SHE DID CONDUCT THEM MORE THAN TEN YEARS AGO<br />
IN THE SAHARA, AND THE AFRICAN NATIONS WHICH HAD BEEN HER<br />
COLONIES SECURED SO MUCH SUPPORT IN THE UNITED NATIONS THAT<br />
FRANCE DISCONTINUED IN THE SAHARA AND OF COURSE BROUGHT THEM TO<br />
OUR HEMISPHERE. BUT THEY WERE DISCONTINUED THROUGH POLITICAL<br />
ACTION IN THE SAHARA.<br />
IN PRACTICAL TERMS DO YOU THINK YOU HAVE ANY HOPE OF<br />
PERSUADING THEM NOT TO CONTINUE?<br />
MR WHITLAM YES. THAT THERE WERE NOT TESTS IN 1971 I THINK<br />
IT WAS... THERE IS QUITE A CHANCE AFTER ALL NOT EVERY<br />
FRENCHMAN SUPPORTS THIS COURSE.<br />
THE COMMUNIQUE REFERS TO '' FAILING, SUCH AN ASSURANCE'<br />
BUT IT DOESN'T SEEM TO BE QUITE SPECIFIC ABOUT SIMPLY AN ASSURANCE<br />
TO GIVE UP THE TESTS CINAUDIBLE).. PA; E 6, '' THE PRIME MINISTERS<br />
HAVE DECLARED THE GOVERNMENT'S INTENTION, FAILINQ SUCH AN<br />
ASSURANCE'". IT DOESN'T SEEM TO BE QUITE CLEAR FROM THE WORDING<br />
WHAT THE ASSURANCE SPECIFICALLY WAS THAT YOU SOUGHT. </p>
<p>MR WHITLAM THAT THEY WOULD NOT GO AHEAD.<br />
THAT IS IN FACT THE ASSURANCE THAT YOU SEEK?<br />
MR KIRK I THINK IF YOU GO TO THE FIRST PARAGRAPH OF THAT SECTION<br />
TO GET THE MEANING OF THAT " THEY EMPHASISED THAT THEIR<br />
OPPOSITION EXTENDED TO ALL FORMS OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS TESTING BY<br />
WHATEVER NATION AND REAFFIRMED THE OBJECTIVES OF A SUSPENSION<br />
OF ALL SUCH TESTING AND THE CONCLUSION OF A COMPREHENSIVE TEST<br />
BAN TREATY''. I THOUGHT ALSO IT MIGHT HAVE RELATED TO THE WORDS '' APPEALED<br />
IN PARTICULAR TO FRANCE TO APPRECIATE THE SPECIAL DECREE"'.<br />
WELL, IF THE ASSURANCE IS SIMPLY THE APPRECIATION OF FRANCE,<br />
CONCEIVABLY WE COULD SAY, '' YES WE APPRECIATE THAT...''<br />
MR WHITLAM WE WILL STILL GO AHEAD ( GARBILED CONVERSATION<br />
INAUD IBLE)<br />
Qe THE ASSURANCE IS SIMPLY TO STOP TESTS?<br />
MR WHITLAM YES.<br />
YOU REFER TO HAVING CONTINGENCY PLANS. BY<br />
DO YOU MEAN AUSTRALIA AND NEW ZEALAND OR AUSTRALIA?<br />
MR WHITLAM AUSTRALIA AND NEW ZEALAND.<br />
YOU'VE DISCUSSED CONTINGENCY PLANS AND AG4REED?<br />
MR WHITLAM YES.<br />
Q. YOU SAY YOU'VE GATHERED SOME SCIENTIFIC INFORMATION. CAN<br />
YOU SAY WHEN YOU GATHERED THAT?<br />
MR KIRK IT'S BEEN GATHERED OVER A PERIOD OF YEARS BECAUSE<br />
THOUGH THE SOUTH PACIFIC THE D6S. I. R. HAVE BEEN INVOLVED IN<br />
MONITORING; THE GATHERING OF INFORMATION.<br />
CAN YOU SAY WHAT THE CONCLUSIONS OF YOUR SCIENTIFIC<br />
INVESTIGATIONS ARE?<br />
MR KIRK I'M NOT IN A POSITION TO BE ABLE TO QUOTE YOU THE<br />
DETAILS OF THAT BUT I AM TOLD THAT THE INFORMATION IS HELD IN<br />
THE VOLUME OF ( INAUDIBLE) IN* RESPECT TO ( INAUDIBLE).<br />
MR WHITLAM, I WONDER IF YOU COULD GIVE US SOME COMMENT ON<br />
YOUR ATTITUDE TO THE FUTURE OF NEW REGIONAL ORGANISATIONS.<br />
YOU REFERRED TO ASEAN. YOU DON'T MENTION THE FUTURE OF ASPAC<br />
AND I WONDER IF YOU HAVE ANY COMMENT ON THE TWO GOVERNMENTS'<br />
ATTITUDE TO ASSOCIATION WITH EITHER OF THOSE BODIES.<br />
MR WHITLAM IT'S TRUE WE DO SAY QUITE AN AMOUNT HERE ABOUT OTHER<br />
REGIONAL BODIES. WE DISCUSSED ALL OF THESE BODIES, BUT LET ME<br />
GO OFF ON A COMMENT OF MY OWN. THE GREAT FAULT OF ASPAC NOW IS<br />
THAT IT INCLUDES REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CHIANG KAI-SHEK REGIME<br />
ON THE BASIS OF ITS CLAIM TO BE THE SOLE LEG.' AL GOVERNMENT OF<br />
CHINA. CLEARLY SOME MEMBERS OF ASPAC WOULD N iOT ACCEPT THAT<br />
CLAIM. JAPAN DOESN'T, NEITHER1 NEW ZEALAND NOR AUSTRALIA. IN<br />
NO CIRCUMSTANCES ONE WOULD EXPECT THAT SOME CHANGES OF<br />
MEMBERSHIP SHOULD TAKE PLACE OR SOME ADDITIONS TO MEMBERSHIP.<br />
THE ADVANTAGE OF ASPAC TO GIVE THE POSITIVE ASPECT IS THAT<br />
IT IS THE ONLY ORGANISATION WHICH HAS ( INAUDIBLE) BUT ASIAN<br />
OR WEST PACIFIC MATTERS, AND IT'S THE ONLY ONE WHICH INCLUDES,<br />
JAPAN AND NEW ZEALAND AND AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>Q. WOULD YOU LIKE TO SEE CHINA AS AN ADDITION?<br />
MR WHITLAM WELL TECHNICALLY, IN THE SENSE THAT CHIANG KAI-SHEK'S<br />
GOVERNMENT CLAIMS TO BE THE GOVERNMENT OF CHINA, SOME PEOPLE<br />
WOULD SAY THAT CHINA IS A MEMBER* I WOULD THINK THAT CHINA<br />
SHOULD BE IN THE TERMS IN WHICH JAPAN AND NEW4 ZEALAND AND<br />
AUSTRALIA RECOGNISE THE SITUATION NAMELY, THAT THE GOVERNMENT<br />
IN PEKING IS THE SOLE LEGAL GOVERNMENT OF CHINA. BUT AFTER ALL<br />
THERE ARE OTHER COUNTRIES TOO WHICH SHOULD BE INCLUDED. THE<br />
IDEAL WOULD BE TO NOT ONLY INCLUDE JAPAN, AUSTRALIA AND NEW<br />
ZEALAND IN ASEAN BUT THE WHOLE OF THAT EAST COAST OF ASIA..<br />
I DON'T THINK ONE OUGHT TO ASSUME THAT THIS COULD BE A MILITARY<br />
PACT. THE DAYS OF MILITARY PACTS ( INTERRUPTION) MUTUAL ASSISTANCETHE<br />
WORDING THERE COVERS THIS SITUATION YOU RAISE ABOUT ASPAC IN<br />
PART ICULAR.<br />
MR WHITLAM CAN I ASK YOU A QUESTION ABOUT THE CHAPTER IN<br />
THE COMMUNI1QUE ON TRAVEL. DOES THAT MEAN THAT THE RESTRICTIONS<br />
ON THE ENTRY OF NEW ZEALANDERS OF ASIAN AND PACIFIC ISLAND<br />
ORIGIN WILL NOW BE LIFTED?<br />
MR WHITLAM YES.<br />
Q. IS THERE ANYTHING TO STOP SAY AN INFLUX OF PACIFIC ISLANDERS<br />
INTO AUSTRALIA FROM NEW ZEALAND?<br />
MR KIRK IT WILL DEPEND OF COURSE FIRST ON THEIR BEING NEW<br />
ZEALANDERS* I THINK THAT THE DISTINCTION THAT OUGHT TO BE SEEN<br />
IN THIS, AND ONE THAT REALLY TROUBLES US A GREAT DEAL IN THIS<br />
COUNTRY, WAS ( INAUDIBLE), AND THE VOLUNTARY ACTION OF AUSTRALIA<br />
ELIMINATING THID DISTINCTION IS THAT OUR CONCERN REVOLVED ABOUT<br />
THE DISCRIMINATION OF ONE NEW ZEALANDER TO ANOTHER. IT'S<br />
NOT A QUESTION OF HIS ORIGIN, THE FACT WAS HE WAS A NEW ZEALANDER,<br />
AND A CHINESE WHO WAS NEW ZEALAND-BORN, A PACIFIC ISLANDER WHO WAS<br />
NEW ZEALAND-BORN AND A NEW ZEALANDER IN EVERY ASPECT WOULD BE<br />
TREATED DIFFERENTLY FROM EUROPEANS. NOW THAT DISTINCTION HAS<br />
REMAINED SO THAT IF THEY ARE NEW ZEALAND CITIZENS THE RULE<br />
APPLIES, BUT NOT IF THEY'RE NOT.<br />
DOES IT MEAN THAT THEY HAVE TO BE NECESSARILY NEW ZEALAND<br />
BORN NOR?<br />
MR MIRK NO, THEY HAVE TO BE NEW ZEALAND CITIZENS. BUT, FOR<br />
EXAMPLE ASIANS WHO ARE DUTCHMEN ABOUT TO BE NATURALISED IF ANY<br />
OF THE DUTCH MIGR~ ANTS SEEK TO BECOME NEW ZEALANDERS. BUT THEY<br />
HAVE To TAKE UP NEW ZEALAND CITIZENSHIP To QUALIFY, OR OBVIOUSLY<br />
THEY ARE NOT A NEW ZEALANDER.<br />
CAN I ASK MR WHITL-AM NOW IF THERE IS ANYTHINfj TO STOP THE<br />
NUMBER OF PACIFIC ISLANDERS BECOMING NEW ZEALAND CITIZENS<br />
AND GOING TO AUSTRALIA.<br />
MR WHITLAM IF THEY ARE NEW ZEALAND CITIZi:_ NS, OF IF THEY'RE<br />
CITIZENS OF COMMONWEALTH COUNTRIES WHO HAVE RESIDENT STATUS IN<br />
NEW ZEALAND, THEN THEY CAN COME TO AUSTRALIA WITHOUT PASSPORTS<br />
OR VISAS. </p>
<p>MR KIRK THEY DON'T THINK THERE IS ANY GREAT FEAR ON THAT SCORE.<br />
THE POINT I THINK YOU OUGHT TO UNDERSTAND IS THAT THE ISLAND<br />
POPULATION IN NEW ZEALAND, THAT IS PEOPLE WHO COME FROM THE<br />
ISLAND COUNTRIES TO OUR COUNTRY, ARE NOW NUMBERING SOMEWHERE<br />
ABOUT 36,000 AT PRESENT. MOST HAVE SET THEIR ROOTS DOWN AND<br />
MADE THEIR HOMES HERE AND ARE UNLIKELY TO SHIFT, BECAUSE IT IS<br />
NOT ONLY A QUESTION OF THEIR NEW ZEALAND CITIZENSHIP BUT THE<br />
MATTERS OF POLENYSIAN AFFINITY HAVING TO DEFINE CULTURALLY.<br />
I THINK FOR A START THERE ARE 37,000 PEOPLE IN THIS CATEGORY,<br />
AND THE IDEA THAT THIS BECOMES SOME SORT OF ROUND-ABOUT<br />
WAY OF MIGRATING TO AUSTRALIA ISN'T REALLY FAIR TREATMENT OF WHAT<br />
YOU PROPOSE. THE GOVERNMENT OF AUSTRALIA HAS SAID TO ALL NEW<br />
ZEALAND'S CITIZENS THAT THEY STAND EQUAL, AND WE ARE VERY HAPPY<br />
ABOUT THAT.<br />
I'D LIKE TO REFER BRIEFLY TO THIS QUESTION, IF I MAY SIR,<br />
OF REGIONAL ORGANISATIONS. MR WHITLAM, AT THE LUNCHEON TODAY<br />
YOU GAVE AN ASSURANCE THAT AUSTRALIA WOULD STRIVE TO THE UTMOST<br />
TO SEE THAT ALL CONSTRUCTIVE AND VALID ASSOCIATIONS THAT ARE<br />
INHERITED BE PRESERVED AND REINFORCE). WOULD YOU REGARD<br />
SEATO AS A CONSTRUCTIVE AND VALID ASSOCIATION?<br />
MR WHITLAM WELL LET'S SEE HOW IT DEVEILOPS. I HAVE USED THE<br />
WORD '' MORIBUND" ABOUT IT IN THE PAST, AND SINCE THEN PEKISTAN<br />
HAS DRAWN OUT OF IT, OR GIVEN NOTICE THAT IT'S GOING TO.<br />
MR KIRK, ON PAGE 3, SECOND LAST PARA( RAPH, IS A REFERENCE<br />
TO " GREATER INVOLVEMENT BY PARLIAHENTARIANS IN THE SOUTH<br />
PACIFIC AREA". THERE IS NO SPECIFIC MENTION OF THE PROPOSED<br />
PACIFIC COUNCIL WHICH IS PART AND PARCEL OF YOUR ELECTION<br />
MANIFESTO AND WHICH IS DESIGNED ALSO TO SET UP SOMETHING WHICH<br />
WOUNDS A BIT LIKE THE PARLIAMENT OF EUROPE., PARLIAMENTARIANS<br />
CONSULTING, MEETING REGULARLY.<br />
MR KIRK THE PARLIAMENT OF EUROPE HAS NO FORCE IN THE SENSE<br />
THAT THE NORDIC COUNCIL HAS, AND WHAT WE PROPOSE IS RELATED<br />
TO THE NORDIC COUNCIL.<br />
CAN YOU DISCUSS THE PROPOSED PACIFIC COUNCIL, OR DID YOU<br />
REACH ANY AGREEMENT ON IT WITH MR WHITLAM?<br />
MR KIRK WELL WHAT WE'VE DONE IS TO ACCEPT THAT IN THE<br />
PACIFIC MATTERS ARE NOT SETTLED' BY OUR DECISIONS ALONE, BUT<br />
SETTLED BY OTHERS, AND THE CONFERENCE HAD BEEN DEVELOPING AS<br />
A FORUM OF POLITICAL DISCUSSION, AND WHAT WE WILL DO IS OBVIOUSLY<br />
DISCUSS THE PROSPECTS OF THE PACIFIC COUNCIL INSIDE THE CONTEXT...<br />
IF THE PACIFIC CONFERENCE IS CAPABLE OF DEVELOPING ADEQUATELY<br />
THEN THAT'S THE COURSE WE'Ll. FOLLOW. BUT IT'S NOT JUST FOR US<br />
ALONE TO MAKE THAT DECISION. THE ISLANO COUNTRIES ALSO HAVE<br />
VIEWS ON THIS, AND ITrS A MATTER OF PUTTING IN IDEAS AND WORKING<br />
TOGETHER FOR DEVELOPMENT. IT'S ESSENTIAL IN MY VIEW: THAT<br />
THERE IS A POLITICAL FORUM WHERE POLITICAL TOPICS MAY BE FREELY<br />
DISCUSSED, IT IS VITAL THAT PARLIAMENT SHOULD BE REPRESENTED<br />
INTHAT FORUM, BECAUSE IN DEMOCRACY, AS WE'VE SEEN IN TWO<br />
IMPORTANT COUNTRIES RECENTLY, GOVERNMENTS HAVE CHANGED, AND I<br />
THINK IF PARLIAMENTS ARE REPRESENTED THEN THERE IS A CONTINUITY<br />
OF THE KNOWLEDGE AND A CONTINUITY OF EXPERIENCE INSIDE THE<br />
POLITICAL FORUM WHERE THESE DISCUSSIONS TAKE PLACE, SO THAT<br />
THE DOMESTIC POLITICAL CHANGES IN A COUNTRY DON'T NECESSARILY<br />
MEAN RADICAL CHANGES. IN THIS SORT OF FORUM, YOU CAN PRESERVE<br />
SOME SORT OF CONTINUITY OF APPROACH. WHEN I FIRST SUGGESTED<br />
THE CONCEPT OF A PACIFIC COUNCIL THERE WAS NO POLITICAL FORUM<br />
FOR DISCUSSION AND INDEED EVEN BEFORE IN WHICH THE HEADS<br />
OF STATE DISUCUSSED MATTERS OF CONCERN TO THE REGION AND THE<br />
INDIVIDUAL STATES DID NOT EXIST, AND THE PROPOSITION WAS<br />
PATTERNED ON THE NORDIC COUNCIL WHERE THEY WERE ABLE TO<br />
RATIONALISE DEVELOPMENT, THOUGH FOR EXAMPLE THE UNIVERSITY<br />
BENEFITTED CONSOLIDATED CENTRALISED LIBRARIES AND THINGS OF THIS<br />
KIND.<br />
I I </p>
<p>( CHANqE TO OTHER SIDE o: -rAPE)<br />
WHAT-WE ARE CONCERNED IS DRAWING TOGETHER A BIT<br />
CLOSER SO THAT WE CAN COORDINATE DEVELOPMENT AND SPEED) IT UP.,<br />
COLD I ASK YOU WHAT YOU SEE AS AN INTERNATIONAL<br />
REHABILITATION PROGRAMME IN INDO-CHINA?<br />
MR KIRK WELL, WE ARE LIKE AUSTRALIA, EXCEPT THAT WHILE WE<br />
TERMINATED MILITARY INVOLVEMENT IN THAT COUNTRY WE DIDN'T<br />
WITHDRAW FROM THE INDO-CHINJA REG~ ION, AND CONSEQUENTLY, ON THE<br />
DAY THAT WE ANNOUNCED THE WITHDRAWAL OF THE LAST OF OUR<br />
MILITARY FORCES THERE, WE ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT WE WOULD DOUBLE<br />
OVER THE NEXT FIVE YEARS OUR CONTRIBUTION FOR CIVILIAN<br />
REHABILITATION AND RECONSTRUCTION., AND FURTHERMORE, BECAUSE WE<br />
WANT TO SEE THE UNITED NATIONS HAVE AN EFFECTIVE AND CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
ROLE AND TO TRYAND DO WHAT WE CAIN TO HELP IN I1-S EFFECTIVE<br />
REHABILITATION AND STANDING OF WORLD-WIDE, HAVE UNDERTAKEN TO<br />
PUT A SUBSTANTIAL PART OF THE ASSISTANCE WE'VE GRANTED TO THE<br />
UNITED NATIONS SO THAT IT WILL GO BACK THR~ OUGH THAT BODY INTO<br />
INDO-CHINA. SO WE HAVE ACCEPTED IN FACT'THAT WE SHALL PAY EXTRA<br />
AND AMOUNT FOR CIVILIAN RECONSTRUCTION IN THE INDO-CHINA AREA.<br />
DOES THIS INCLUDE NORTH VIET-NAM?<br />
MR KIRK INDO-CHINA INCLUDES, LAOS, CAMBODIA, SOUTH VIET-NAM<br />
AND NORTH VIET-NAM.<br />
DO YOU EXPECT SIR, THAT, LIKE AUSTRALIA YOU MAY HAVE<br />
ULTIM1ATELY REPRESENTATION OF SOM~ E FORM IN HANOI?<br />
MR KIRK NO, WE HAVEN'T CONSID) ERED) FRANKLY, FOR A COUNTRY<br />
AS SMALL AS NEW ZEALAND WITH THE RESOURCES WE H4AVE WE'VE HAD TO<br />
FOLLOW FAIRLY STRICT PRIORITIES WHERE WE CAN OPEN NEW POSTS<br />
AND WE HAVEN'T ACCORDED A HIGH PRIORITY TO THIS, BECAUSE AT<br />
THE MOMENT WE ARE INVOLVED IN CONSIDERING THE OPENING OF A POST<br />
IN ( INAUDIBLE). THERE ARE LIMITATIONS ON RESOURCES WHICH HAVE<br />
POSED TIGHT RESTRICTIONS.<br />
ENDS. PLEASE NOTIFY MIR WOOLCOTTOR MR HOYLE OF RECEIPT OF THIS<br />
TRANSCR IPT*<br />
WE REGRET THE LACK OF CLARITY. OFFICIAL TEXT I. S EXPECTED<br />
TO BE AVAILABLE FROM MR KIRK'S OFFICE APPROXIMATELY 1000 HOURS<br />
LOCAL TIME 23 JANUARY. WE WILL CABLE THAT AS SOON AS<br />
AVAILABLE U1NLESS YOU ADVI. SE OTHERWI-SE.<br />
CCFM 110)<br />
ENDS 230035LT<br />
SHA </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
