<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4938</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT YOUNG LIBERAL&#039;S CONVENTION, BRISBANE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/01/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004938.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FIL<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 11 JANUARY 1979<br />
ADDRESS AT YOUNG LIBERALS' CONVENTION, BRISBANE<br />
It is good to be speaking today to young Australians because<br />
it is the young of this country who often provide our best<br />
and most creative ideas.<br />
Young people will be a vital part of the growth and development<br />
of Australia and young Australians have never been better<br />
educated, more able to contribute to our society. Australia<br />
needs your originality, your enthusiasm, your energy.<br />
This is a time of opportunity for young Australia because the<br />
economic strategy we have pursued over the past three years is<br />
putting Australia firmly on the road back to economic health.<br />
we have reduced inflation to under eight percent.<br />
and we are now seeing the benefits of our anti-inflation<br />
policies. Business investment has been rising strongly,<br />
consumer demand is more buoyant and the rural economy is having<br />
its best period for many years. As a result, we expect<br />
Australia's overall growth rate for 1979 to exceed the Q. E. C. D.<br />
average. The growing competitiveness of Australian industry has been<br />
noted in a number of recent economic surveys. One survey last<br />
month found that the quarterly rise in manufacturing unit costs<br />
was the lowest since December 1969. This is a vital breakthrough<br />
in our capacity to export and the same survey showed an upturn<br />
in manufacturing export deliveries for the second consecutive<br />
quarter for the first time since 1973.<br />
Another encouraging feature of the economy has been the fall in<br />
interest rates on bank and building society loans over 1978.<br />
Interest rates on the vast majority of home loans fell by one<br />
per cent over the last twelve months a saving to the home<br />
buyers of Australia of over $ 150 million a year. To businesses,<br />
the reduction in bank overdraft rates means significantly lower<br />
costs. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
one important indicator of Australia's development potential<br />
is the many large investment projects where construction is<br />
under way or could commence in the next one to two years.<br />
During the last election campaign I said that Australia was<br />
ready to go with $ 6,000 million worth of investment. Since'<br />
then, as the latest A. B. S. statistics and surveys indicate,<br />
an estimated $ 3.4 billion was spent on investment in mining<br />
and manufacturing in 1978 33 per cent up on the previous<br />
year. In addition to that, the latest survey by Phillip Lynch's<br />
Department shows that today $ 7.5 billion investment projects<br />
are ready to go.<br />
Government policies are encouraging and supporting developments<br />
in mining and in manufacturing by reducing costs and providing<br />
a more stable economic climate, by providing taxation incentives,<br />
by promoting exports and research and by helping State authorities<br />
to provide essential infrastructure for major resource and other<br />
projects. The Australian Government's energy policies have stimulated the<br />
oil and gas industry. In 10.78, 52 exploration oil wells were<br />
drilled, the highest number of wells drilled for five years and<br />
1979 is expected to be even better. The Government's policies<br />
have resulted in a substantial increase in petroleum exploration<br />
with minimum expenditure committed for the next five years of<br />
over $ 500 million.<br />
our energy policies have given Australia a much better chance<br />
to keep its substantial self-sufficiency in oil and develop<br />
export markets in gas. It is estimated that by 1985, 30 per cent<br />
of Australia's crude oil production will be derived from oil<br />
fields which have become viable as a consequence of these<br />
policies.. The Government is encouraged by these exciting prospects for<br />
Australia. As they are translated into lasting and noninflationary<br />
economic growth, employment will increase, new<br />
entrants to the workforce will be absorbed and the numbers of<br />
unemployed will be gradually reduced. This is the only way in<br />
which unemployment can and will be beaten.<br />
The magnitude of the economic problems we have inherited means<br />
that a return to high employment is a slow process and we have<br />
responded to this problem by devising a wide range of programmes<br />
to help the unemployed. Many of these programmes are especially<br />
directed at giving young people training and work experience,<br />
at extending their education and making it easier to enter the<br />
workforce on a satisfying and permanent basis. Since coming to<br />
office, more than 300,000 young people have been helped by such<br />
Government programmes. And in December we established the<br />
Department of Employment and Youth Affairs to allow a Cabinet<br />
Minister, Ian Viner, to concentrate his time and energies on<br />
this national problem. Ian has of course, spoken to you earlier<br />
in this conference. 3/ </p>
<p>-3-<br />
A major review of the effectiveness of Government manpower<br />
programmes is currently under way and we will continue to<br />
search for better ways of helping young Australians. If<br />
programmes can be expanded or improved they shall be.<br />
The Government has approved in principle the development of a<br />
voluntary youth community service scheme to provide unemployed<br />
young people the opportunity to involve themselves in worthwhile<br />
community activities and to assist them to acquire work<br />
experience and skills.<br />
Later this year, we will be holding a national conference on<br />
youth policy bringing together all sections of youth and the<br />
community to consider the economic and social issues facing the<br />
young, to provide information which will help improve the coordination<br />
of Government youth policy and suggest ways in which<br />
young people can get better access to Government.<br />
Solutions to the problpms of young unemployment of course require<br />
the cooperation of all members of the community and cooperation<br />
between Commonwealth and State Governments.<br />
In December I wrote to the State Premiers suggesting that we<br />
together look at possibilities for changes to our education<br />
system, covering such matters as alternative secondary school<br />
courses more attuned to the needs of early school leavers,<br />
courses outside the schooling system for those in the 16 to 18<br />
age group who have already left school and are unemployed,<br />
intensive summer holiday courses for school leavers, including<br />
labour market information, careers guidance and vocational<br />
counselling, and, in the longer term, a review of the whole<br />
process of schooling to take account of the rapid changes in<br />
our society. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
The State Education Ministers have responded to my invitation by<br />
forming a working party of senior officials to review what has<br />
been done to assist the transition from school to employment and<br />
to recommend additional action by both State and Commonwealth<br />
Education authorities. I have also invited the States to<br />
co-operate in a review to consider whether any of their legislative<br />
or institutional arrangements are having an adverse effect on<br />
unemployment. For example, inconsistent standards and regulations<br />
between the States may affect employment opportunities.<br />
Devising policies to alleviate youth unemployment requires<br />
information about the structure of our industry, about the<br />
education and training system and about the labour market.<br />
The Crawford Inquiry into structural change and the Williams<br />
Inquiry into education and training will help to provide this<br />
information.<br />
More recently, the Government has taken initiatives to examine<br />
other aspects of the labour market by establishing a Committee<br />
of Inquiry into the process of technological change in<br />
Australian industry. We have also supported a tripartite committee,<br />
under the auspices of the National Labour Consultative Council<br />
to examine the effects of certain factors for example penalty<br />
rates on the labour market. In the end, however the solution<br />
to the problem of unemployment is strengthening the economy.<br />
Additional jobs will be created only if our economy grows faster<br />
than it has been. For this to happen the constraints preventing<br />
faster growth, such as inflation, the imbalance between wages<br />
and productivity and the inadequacy of profits will have to be<br />
removed.<br />
The Government's specific measures to alleviate unemployment<br />
must be seen in the context of our drive to restore Australia's<br />
economic health, to remove the constraints holding back our<br />
economic progress and the capacity of private industry to<br />
provide employment.<br />
While we have been grappling with the fundamental economic<br />
issues facing Australia, we have not been distracted from other<br />
major areas of social concern.<br />
We are a Government of social and legislative reform as much as<br />
a Government of development and progress. We have the great<br />
advantage of a liberal philosophy a philosophy which allows<br />
us to recognise and respond effectively to the goals and<br />
aspirations of all Australians.<br />
The Liberal Government knows that young Australians give the<br />
highest priority to maintaining a free and open society. The<br />
young people of Australia know the importance of individual<br />
freedom and the opportunity to make their own way through life,<br />
to pursue the livelihood they choose, to express their views,<br />
to bring up their families and to live in the way they wish.<br />
Like all Australians the young seek a society where the laws of<br />
the land are observed, where each citizen has equal access to<br />
justice, where individuals are able to exercise their creativity<br />
and talents and where there is redress when Governments unfairly<br />
or unreasonably interfere with their lives. </p>
<p>in pursuing these goals the Liberal Government for the past three<br />
years, has been comprehensively reviewing Government programmes<br />
and existing legislation.<br />
Already a good deal has been done.<br />
Our policies have provided effective help for those in need while<br />
encouraging self-reliance. They have done a great deal for the<br />
less privileged in our society.<br />
We have introduced family allowances; one of the greatest social<br />
welfare innovations in Australia's history. We have increased<br />
the Government's help for the handicapped. We have helped the<br />
aged to live in their own homes and we have helped those requiring<br />
special accommodation.<br />
In three years, we have provided a total of $ 304 million for<br />
aged persons accommodation and home care services, an increase<br />
of some 38% over the previous three years.<br />
More than $ 80 million of this amount has been directed towards home<br />
care services which assist the aged and infirm to remain in the<br />
happiness and independence of their own homes by subsidising home<br />
help, home nursing, meals on wheels, senior citizen centres and<br />
welfare services. That is an increase in expenditure over the<br />
three Labor years of 112%.<br />
We have introduced the indexation of pensions, tax indexation,<br />
a fairer means test, revenue sharing with the States, the supporting<br />
parents benefit for sole fathers, Aboriginal land rights in the<br />
Northern Territory, a new deal for our migrants, self-government<br />
for the Northern Territory, three successful Constitutional<br />
amendments and abolition of Estate and Gift Duty.<br />
And for rural industry we have introduced the Primary Industry<br />
Bank, income equalisation deposits, fuel equalisation, improved<br />
tax averaging and many specific programmes supporting Australia's<br />
wool, meat, dairy and sugar industries.<br />
our programme of reform will continue in 1979 and I will give you<br />
just some examples. In seeking to play our part in enhancing<br />
human rights in Australia, the Government will proceed with a<br />
bill to ensure that Commonwealth laws, acts and practices conform<br />
with the international convenant on civil and political rights.<br />
The Government is also conducting discussions with the States to<br />
achieve a comprehensive and co-ordinated approach to protection<br />
of human rights throughout Australia.<br />
We propose to bring forward a bill to clarify and define the<br />
powers of A. S. I. O. and to establish a security appeals tribunal<br />
to provide an avenue of appeal for those affect~ d by an adverse<br />
security report. Legislation will be introduced to establish,<br />
in co-operation with the States, a new national companies and<br />
securities commission and to implement our agreement with the<br />
States on jurisdiction over off-shore matters.<br />
The Government has submitted references to the Australian Law<br />
Reform Commission on a number of other areas in which reform may<br />
be desirable, including insurance contracts, the laws relating<br />
to debtors, the incorporation in our legal system of traditional<br />
aboriginal law and defamation. The Government will consider<br />
these reports as soon as they are completed. .6/ </p>
<p>Since coming to office, the Government has also initiated a<br />
number of important Parliamentary reforms. The continued<br />
effectiveness of Parliament remains one of our strongest<br />
guarantees of individual liberty and democratic rule.<br />
We have taken steps to see that the procedures of Parliament keep<br />
pace with the increasing complexity of the executive Government.<br />
We have introduced legislation committees of the House of<br />
Representatives a House Expenditure Committee and we are<br />
legislating to authorise the Auditor-General to carry out, and<br />
report to Parliament on, efficiency audits on Government Departments.<br />
Perhaps, most importantly of all, the Government has undertaken to<br />
report to Parliament within six months on the recommendations of<br />
Parliamentary Committees.<br />
The Government will continue to review the Parliamentary processes.<br />
One matter under consideration is the possibility of the committee<br />
stage of the next Budget being carried forward in two or more<br />
committees which could sit concurrently, enabling more members to<br />
express their views on matters of importance to them.<br />
The Government has acted to protect the citizen against unwarranted<br />
interference by the bureaucracy. We have appointed the Ombudsman<br />
to investigate complaints, and the Administrative Appeals Tribunal<br />
now hears appeals from a wide range of bureaucratic decisions.<br />
We have also passed legislation requiring reasons to be given in<br />
writing for many administrative decisions made which affect<br />
individual citizens.<br />
Our reform programme has also tackled the difficult area of<br />
industrial relations. We know that Australians want a society<br />
in which industrial disputes are settled by consultation, reason<br />
and free choice by the individuals concerned.<br />
We have gone a long way towards this goal by providing protection<br />
for conscientious objectors, and 170 conscientious objectors<br />
were registered with the Industrial Relations Bureau in its first<br />
year of operation; by introducing secret postal ballots for<br />
union elections more than 360 union elections have been conducted<br />
by the Commonwealth Electoral Office during the past 12 months;<br />
by requiring unions to have their accounts audited and report<br />
regularly to their membership; by establishing the Industrial<br />
Relations Bureau and the National Labour Consultative Council.<br />
However, where consultation and conciliation breaks down it is<br />
essential that the rule of law should prevail, and we have<br />
strengthened our industrial laws accordingly.<br />
Education is a major priority of the Government, as it is of course<br />
with all parents and young Australians. The Government is committed<br />
to providing a high standard of education, one that will meet<br />
the career and social aspirations of young Australians. A great<br />
deal has been achieved already. 7/ </p>
<p>-7-<br />
The Government will examine all the information which becomes<br />
available, including the Williams Report, to assist us to upgrade<br />
the quality and accessibility of education for all Australians,<br />
and to make it more relevant to individual and community needs.<br />
Good health is also one of the first priorities of Australians,<br />
whether young or old. The Government is determined that no-one<br />
in the community need fear crippling financial costs from illness.<br />
At the same time, we believe that individuals should have the<br />
responsibility to provide for a part of th.-eir health costs.<br />
Our health initiatives reflect this philosophy; they give<br />
Australians one of the best and most efficIent health services<br />
in-the world.<br />
I believe we are well on the move towards the sort of Australia we<br />
all desire; a growing and prosperous country, with progress in both<br />
economic and human terms; a more responsible, imaginative, a<br />
fairer society.<br />
It is not our role as a Government to direct individuals and<br />
dogmatically lay down the goals they should follow. We wish to<br />
encourage the people of Australia to use their resources and their<br />
talents to the full. Australia needs contributions from all its<br />
people, and achieving our goals requires much more than mere lip<br />
service to theoretical ideas.<br />
Every Australian must seek to play a positive role in our work, in<br />
our relationship with our families, in our dealings with all members<br />
of the community so that we can achieve our goals.<br />
Employers can help by providing jobs and, in those cases where<br />
they employ young people under a Government youth employment<br />
programme, by keep them on when the initial subsidy ceases.<br />
Employers can boost the job satisfaction and productivity of all<br />
their staff by actively seeking to make employees aware of the<br />
decisions that affect their work-Dlace.<br />
Unions can help by realising that unreasonable wage increases harm<br />
the economy and contribute to unemployment.<br />
We can all play our part by working harder, by using our<br />
initiative, and by doing so, helping the economy to grow. Another<br />
way we all can contribute is by taking an active interest in<br />
Government. The Young Liberals have a special opportunity and responsibility to<br />
give us timely and relevant advice, particularly on those issues<br />
which most affect young Australians.<br />
Today, we are farewelling a Young Liberal, Dr. Bruce Noble, who has<br />
made a major contribution in advising government in his two years of<br />
invaluable service as National Young Liberal President. The time<br />
he has given to the movement has often meant great personal sacrifices<br />
for Bruce and his family, and I thank him warmly for all he has done<br />
for the Young Liberals and the help he has given to the Government. 8/ </p>
<p>-8-<br />
The Government welcomes comments and constructive criticism<br />
from all Australians which helps us in developing our programmes and<br />
in broadening our understanding of Australians' needs and<br />
aspirations.<br />
We seek a partnership between all members of the community,<br />
between governments, between employers and employees, between<br />
all Australians. With such a partnership and with a determination<br />
to make our aspirations a reality there is nothing this country<br />
and its people cannot achieve. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
