<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11303</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT ON ELECTRONIC COMMERCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that Prime Minister Obuchi and I have agreed</p>
<p> on a joint statement setting out common approaches and areas of cooperation</p>
<p> in the promotion of electronic commerce. This recognises that electronic</p>
<p> commerce presents opportunities and challenges of the highest economic</p>
<p> and social significance, warranting attention and collaboration at</p>
<p> the highest levels of government. It also reflects the importance</p>
<p> that Australia and Japan place on working together on policy issues</p>
<p> that are of domestic, regional, and indeed global significance.</p>
<p>The economic potential of the information economy is well recognised</p>
<p> by both our Governments. We embrace the efficiencies of electronic</p>
<p> commerce and its potential to facilitate new global markets for goods</p>
<p> and services, and to create new markets in services that were not</p>
<p> previously practicable. As the economies of Asia return to sustained</p>
<p> economic growth, the information economy will play an ever greater</p>
<p> part in linking us together and raising quality of life around the</p>
<p> globe.</p>
<p>This statement is also significant because it points the way to further</p>
<p> commercial cooperation and linkages between Australian and Japanese</p>
<p> corporations involved in electronic commerce and the Information Economy,</p>
<p> thus addressing an important new element to our excellent economic</p>
<p> relationship with Japan.</p>
<p>Today's joint statement builds on the cooperation Australia and Japan</p>
<p> have already enjoyed in a number of international fora dealing with</p>
<p> electronic commerce, and provides a platform for our two countries</p>
<p> to work more closely on priority issues to provide a secure environment</p>
<p> for the growth of electronic commerce.</p>
<p>The joint statement is intended to encourage:</p>
<p>   Building certainty and confidence with governments, business and</p>
<p>   consumers in key areas of electronic commerce;</p>
<p>   Facilitating the development of clear and consistent legal frameworks,</p>
<p>   nationally and internationally; and</p>
<p>   Promoting continuing dialogue between Australia and Japan on electronic</p>
<p>   commerce issues.</p>
<p>On the key policy principles, Australia and Japan have confirmed our</p>
<p> positions that the private sector should lead the development of electronic</p>
<p> commerce as far as possible, with minimum government intervention</p>
<p> and self-regulation wherever possible.</p>
<p>We have set out our common policy approaches to a number of the key</p>
<p> issues that arise in electronic commerce, including taxes and customs</p>
<p> duties; authentication of transactions; protection of privacy; consumer</p>
<p> protection issues; intellectual property protection; and the issues</p>
<p> that arise from electronic transmission of content.</p>
<p>We have also agreed that our Governments should act as role models</p>
<p> and catalysts in developing the information economy through such services</p>
<p> as electronic payments and electronic service delivery.</p>
<p>We have also endorsed the principles that the Internet should, as</p>
<p> far as possible, remain industry-led and self-governing.</p>
<p>Many of the points in this statement remain the subject of keen consideration</p>
<p> in global fora such as the World Trade Organisation, the OECD and</p>
<p> APEC. The common positions agreed with Japan today will help us both</p>
<p> to collaborate effectively in ensuring development of a flourishing,</p>
<p> global information economy.</p>
<p>A copy of the Joint Statement is attached.</p>
<p>The Government of Australia and the Government of Japan accept that</p>
<p> the growth of the information economy is a significant development</p>
<p> in global economic relations and benefits both countries, especially</p>
<p> in the conduct of international business. Electronic commerce, in</p>
<p> particular, allows access to new markets, improves the quality of</p>
<p> services, encourages innovation, and fosters more efficient supply</p>
<p> and distribution. These benefits should accelerate economic growth</p>
<p> around the world.</p>
<p>I. PURPOSE</p>
<p>This joint statement is intended to promote the development of electronic</p>
<p> commerce in both countries by:</p>
<p>  (a) building certainty and confidence with governments, businesses</p>
<p>   and consumers in key areas of electronic commerce;</p>
<p>  (b) facilitating the consideration and adoption of a clear and consistent</p>
<p>   legal framework;</p>
<p>  (c) promoting a dialogue between Australia and Japan on electronic</p>
<p>   commerce issues;</p>
<p>  (d) supporting and endorsing the following principles and policies,</p>
<p>   which should guide the development of electronic commerce.</p>
<p>II. POLICY PRINCIPLES</p>
<p>1. The private sector should lead in the development of electronic</p>
<p> commerce and in establishing business practices, both domestically</p>
<p> and internationally.</p>
<p>2. Governments should create a favourable environment which maximises</p>
<p> private sector initiatives and fosters open competition in electronic</p>
<p> commerce. They should avoid the imposition of unnecessary regulations</p>
<p> or restrictions on electronic commerce. They should also avoid imposing</p>
<p> unnecessary, restrictive or regulative measures on international trade</p>
<p> transacted electronically. Government actions, when needed, should</p>
<p> be clear, transparent, and predictable to the private sector.</p>
<p>3. Legislation may be needed to facilitate the efficient self-regulation</p>
<p> of electronic commerce.</p>
<p>However, governments should also encourage effective self-regulation</p>
<p> through codes of conduct, model contracts, guidelines, and enforcement</p>
<p> mechanisms developed by the private sector.</p>
<p>4. Cooperation and harmonisation among all countries, from all regions</p>
<p> of the world and all levels of development, will assist in the construction</p>
<p> of a seamless environment for electronic commerce.</p>
<p>5. Governments should contribute to reducing the cost of administrative</p>
<p> services and raising convenience for their citizens by facilitating</p>
<p> the use of information technology. They also have an important role</p>
<p> in facilitating progress towards the information society and information</p>
<p> economy. Governments should endeavour to deliver a high standard of</p>
<p> online services for the full benefit of every citizen.</p>
<p>III. POLICY APPROACHES</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan will adopt the following approaches</p>
<p> to key areas of electronic commerce and the information economy:</p>
<p>  1. Taxes and Tariffs</p>
<p>  A. Rules affecting the taxation of the Internet and electronic commerce</p>
<p>   should be neutral, efficient, simple to understand, and should promote</p>
<p>   certainty. The Governments of Australia and Japan will cooperate</p>
<p>   closely to ensure the effective and fair administration of their</p>
<p>   tax systems in relation to electronic commerce, including prevention</p>
<p>   of tax evasion and avoidance. In support of this the Australian</p>
<p>   and Japanese national tax authorities should continue to consult</p>
<p>   and cooperate on taxation issues associated with electronic commerce:</p>
<p>(a) within international fora, in particular within the Organisation</p>
<p> for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD);</p>
<p>(b)at a bilateral level in accordance with Article 18 of the Agreement</p>
<p> between the Commonwealth of Australia and Japan for the Avoidance</p>
<p> of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with Respect</p>
<p> to Taxes on Income.</p>
<p>  B. The Governments of Australia and Japan reaffirm the declaration</p>
<p>   by the World Trade Organization (WTO) in May 1998 to continue the</p>
<p>   current practice of not imposing customs duties on electronic transmissions.</p>
<p>2. Business and Consumer Confidence</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan recognise that it is essential</p>
<p> that business and consumers have confidence in electronic transactions.</p>
<p> Developments in this area should recognise the importance of private</p>
<p> sector leadership, and should promote both a competitive market for</p>
<p> and user confidence in electronic transactions. This will be facilitated</p>
<p> by action in the following areas:</p>
<p>A. Electronic Transactions and Authentication: The Governments</p>
<p> of Australia and Japan recognise the opportunity that electronic commerce</p>
<p> offers to facilitate and increase trade. Both Governments will work</p>
<p> to build a global framework that supports, domestically and internationally,</p>
<p> the recognition of electronic transactions and authentication methods.</p>
<p> Recognising that each country's history and culture has shaped its</p>
<p> transaction rules, at the international level the Governments of Australia</p>
<p> and Japan will support the development worldwide of a legal structure</p>
<p> that will facilitate a variety of authentication methods and technologies,</p>
<p> as well as a variety of implementation models, as long as the underlying</p>
<p> purpose of any authentication system is the encouragement of user</p>
<p> confidence in electronic commerce . This approach should:</p>
<p>  (a) Remove legal obstacles to electronic transactions by respecting</p>
<p>   relevant provisions from the UNCITRAL Model Law on Electronic Commerce.</p>
<p>  (b) Permit parties to an electronic transaction to determine by</p>
<p>   mutual agreement the appropriate authentication technologies and</p>
<p>   implementation models for their transaction, with assurance that,</p>
<p>   to the maximum extent possible, those technologies and implementation</p>
<p>   models will be recognised and enforced according to the agreement</p>
<p>   of the parties within the principles of law.</p>
<p>  (c) Permit parties to an electronic transaction to have the opportunity</p>
<p>   to prove in court that their authentication technique and their</p>
<p>   electronic transaction are valid.</p>
<p>  (d) Take a non-discriminatory approach to electronic authentication</p>
<p>   methods from other countries.</p>
<p>B. Privacy: Ensuring the effective protection of privacy with</p>
<p> regard to the processing of personal information on global information</p>
<p> networks is necessary, as is the need to continue the free flow of</p>
<p> information. The OECD Privacy Guidelines provide an appropriate basis</p>
<p> for policy development. With regard to frameworks for personal information</p>
<p> protection:</p>
<p>  (a) Governments and businesses should consider consumers' concerns</p>
<p>   about their personal information.</p>
<p>  (b) Governments should support industry in implementing effective</p>
<p>   privacy protection. Legislation can be provided in harmony with</p>
<p>   such support where considered appropriate by the Government.</p>
<p>  (c) Personal information should be collected and handled in a fair</p>
<p>   and reasonable manner consistent with generally accepted privacy</p>
<p>   principles.</p>
<p>  C. Critical Infrastructures: The Government of Australia</p>
<p>   and the Government of Japan believe information security should</p>
<p>   be achieved primarily through industry awareness and industry based</p>
<p>   solutions. Protection of information (as well as information systems</p>
<p>   and infrastructures themselves) is a key element in building user</p>
<p>   confidence. In some cases information infrastructures are critical</p>
<p>   to public safety and national economic welfare. The OECD Guidelines</p>
<p>   for the Security of Information Systems should be the basis for</p>
<p>   national approaches to information security. Governments should</p>
<p>   provide leadership and provide advice on threats, vulnerabilities</p>
<p>   and security responses to ensure that critical information infrastructures</p>
<p>   are protected.</p>
<p>  D. Consumer Protection: Consumers using electronic commerce</p>
<p>   should receive an equivalent level of protection to that provided</p>
<p>   for other forms of commerce. This can be promoted through enforcement</p>
<p>   of existing consumer protection laws and practices; modification</p>
<p>   of these laws and practices as necessary to accommodate the unique</p>
<p>   characteristics of the online market; consumer education; and industry-supported</p>
<p>   mechanisms to empower consumers and resolve consumer complaints</p>
<p>   and concerns.</p>
<p>3. Content</p>
<p>As the Internet is a medium for promoting, in a positive way, diffusion</p>
<p> of knowledge, cultural diversity and social interaction, as well as</p>
<p> a means of facilitating commerce,</p>
<p>  A. Governments should not prevent their citizens from accessing</p>
<p>   information simply because it is published online in another country.</p>
<p>  B. Where users do not wish to receive certain types of content (such</p>
<p>   as that which is unsuitable for children) filtering/blocking systems</p>
<p>   or other tools should be made available. Industry self-regulation</p>
<p>   will assist in the promotion of content labelling.</p>
<p>  C. Industry will need to deal appropriately with complaints about</p>
<p>   prohibited content. On-line service providers should be expected</p>
<p>   to work with domestic law enforcement authorities as well as with</p>
<p>   their international counterparts to stem the transmission of illegal</p>
<p>   content.</p>
<p>  D. The Governments of Australia and Japan will encourage</p>
<p>   international cooperation between law enforcement authorities to</p>
<p>   prevent, investigate and prosecute illegal activities on the Internet</p>
<p>   and the use of electronic commerce for criminal purposes.</p>
<p>4. Government Services and Information</p>
<p>  A. The Governments of Australia and Japan believe good administration</p>
<p>   will be promoted by governments pursuing excellence in the online</p>
<p>   delivery of government services and information. This should be</p>
<p>   done in a way that reflects the needs of citizens and minimises</p>
<p>   bureaucratic processes. Governments can act as role models and market</p>
<p>   catalysts in developing the information economy.</p>
<p>  B. Governments' effective use of electronic payments systems will</p>
<p>   enhance business and user confidence.</p>
<p>  C. Governments should encourage developments in authentication technologies,</p>
<p>   including public key and other technologies, to facilitate trade</p>
<p>   through the use of secure electronic exchanges of permits</p>
<p>   and licences. As part of that process, systematic authentication</p>
<p>   systems for governments should be developed, built, and implemented.</p>
<p>  D. The Governments of Australia and Japan recognise the value of,</p>
<p>   and will continue to support, international cooperation in electronic</p>
<p>   delivery of government services through bodies such as the International</p>
<p>   Council for Information Technology in Government Administration,</p>
<p>   and through collaborative work such as the G7 Government Online</p>
<p>   Project.</p>
<p>5. Internet Governance</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan acknowledge the following as</p>
<p> guiding principles for global governance of the Internet.</p>
<p>Policy development in all areas of Internet management should comprehensively</p>
<p> engage industry interests. As a general rule, responsible industry</p>
<p> self-regulation is preferable to government control because it is</p>
<p> likely to be more flexible and responsive to the changing needs of</p>
<p> the Internet and of Internet users. The self-regulatory process should,</p>
<p> as far as possible, reflect the bottom-up governance that has so far</p>
<p> characterised development of the Internet.</p>
<p>The Internet succeeds in great measure because it is a decentralised</p>
<p> system that encourages innovation and maximises individual freedom.</p>
<p> Where possible, market mechanisms that support competition and consumer</p>
<p> choice should drive the management of the Internet. This will lower</p>
<p> costs, promote innovation, encourage diversity, and enhance user choice</p>
<p> and satisfaction.</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan welcome the establishment of</p>
<p> the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers (ICANN), to</p>
<p> manage the global domain name system (DNS).</p>
<p>A. The Governments of Australia and Japan aim to ensure that the DNS</p>
<p> overseen by ICANN:</p>
<p>  (a) is global, fair and market-based;</p>
<p>  (b) reflects the geographically and functionally diverse nature</p>
<p>   of the Internet; and</p>
<p>  (c) provides for dispute settlement processes that are not burdensome</p>
<p>   and do not favour any specific jurisdiction.</p>
<p>  B. The Governments of Australia and Japan acknowledge the need for</p>
<p>   further work in international fora to address the issue of domain</p>
<p>   names and trade marks (including well-known marks).</p>
<p>  C. The Governments of Australia and Japan support the further development</p>
<p>   of a system of DNS management which is inclusive of all nations</p>
<p>   and is responsive to the requirements of Internet stakeholders worldwide.</p>
<p>6. Intellectual Property Rights</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan consider that growth of electronic</p>
<p> commerce depends on the adequate protection of intellectual property</p>
<p> rights (IPR), including industrial property rights and copyright.</p>
<p> The widespread and effective protection of patents and other IPR concerning</p>
<p> infrastructure of electronic commerce is essential for the progress</p>
<p> of electronic commerce. The WTO TRIPs Agreement provides international</p>
<p> minimum standards for intellectual property rights protection, that</p>
<p> are directly applicable to electronic commerce. The WTO electronic</p>
<p> commerce work program provides an opportunity to clarify the operation</p>
<p> of existing TRIPs rules in the digital environment. The Governments</p>
<p> of Australia and Japan will make an effort to take the necessary steps</p>
<p> to accede to and implement the World Intellectual Property Organisation</p>
<p> (WIPO) Copyright Treaty and will continue to study the issues involved</p>
<p> in accession to and implementation of the WIPO Performances and Phonograms</p>
<p> Treaty.</p>
<p>7. Infrastructure</p>
<p>The Governments of Australia and Japan consider that the supporting</p>
<p> infrastructure for online transactions must be technically and commercially</p>
<p> suitable, particularly in terms of adequate bandwidth and competitive</p>
<p> pricing. The optimal outcome will be achieved through the competitive</p>
<p> provision of infrastructure and telecommunication services within</p>
<p> a regulatory framework that encourages competition.</p>
<p>IV. ACTION AGENDA</p>
<p>Recognising that bilateral cooperation can complement the development</p>
<p> of essential multilateral frameworks, the Governments of Australia</p>
<p> and Japan will:</p>
<p>  (a) Work with the private sector and consumer groups in both countries</p>
<p>   to promote dialogue, cooperation and further action on the issues</p>
<p>   contained in this statement, including facilitating the translation</p>
<p>   of this cooperation into meaningful international frameworks.</p>
<p>  (b) continue to cooperate closely at relevant international fora</p>
<p>   (for example, the WTO, WIPO, WCO, OECD, UNCITRAL, UNCTAD</p>
<p>   and APEC).</p>
<p>  (c) Actively promote the exchange of information and views at government</p>
<p>   level on all relevant electronic commerce issues. This could include</p>
<p>   economic and trade issues such as how both governments can refrain</p>
<p>   from unnecessary impediments to trade, thereby ensuring a free transaction</p>
<p>   environment for electronic commerce, or how electronic commerce</p>
<p>   affects small and medium sized enterprises, including their ability</p>
<p>   to develop markets and generate employment; and the broader economic</p>
<p>   and social impacts of electronic commerce.</p>
<p>  (d) Work to ensure that the benefits of such exchanges are shared</p>
<p>   more broadly, particularly in the Asia Pacific region.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
