<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9751</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE CHAIRMAN OF THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009751.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EL: 6. Sep. 95 21: 49 No. 0260 100/<br />
STATEMENT BY THE CRHIMAN OF THE SOUTH PACIFIC FORUM<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING XP<br />
TESTING OF A NUCLEAR W~ EAPON BY FRANCE<br />
As current Chair of the South Pacific Forumn, on behalf of my Forum colleagues I<br />
condemn the test of a nuclear weapon by France in the South Pacific.<br />
France has defied the wishes of the people of the South Pacific, the appeal by the Asian<br />
nations as exprcssed in the recent ASEAN Reginal Forum statement that called on<br />
the nuclear weapon states to bring an immediate end to testing, and the voice of an<br />
increasing part of the European and international commnunity. The majority of the<br />
French people also oppose France's testing program in the South Pacific.<br />
Of particular concern to the countries of the South Pacific is the French Government's<br />
reluctance to fully address the environmental and health risks posed by the testing.<br />
Forum leaders reiterate thc calls made by South Pacific Environment Ministers in<br />
Brisbane on 17 August for:<br />
0 an immediate end to testing of nuclear weapons in the South Pacific and the closing<br />
of associated facilities, except those required for future environmental monitoring;<br />
France to accept full and exclusive responsibility for any adverse impacts from<br />
French testing on the South Pacific environment and people; and<br />
0 France to pruvide access to the international community to all French scientific<br />
data and to the testing sites themselves to enable an independent and<br />
comprehensive assessment of the effects of testing.<br />
Forumi countries call on the French Government to acknowledge the weight of opinion<br />
against nuclear testing and abandon immediately its testing program in the<br />
South Pacific.<br />
Forui Itders will consider nuclear testing issues as part of the South Pacific Forum<br />
Meeting in Madang, Papua New Guinea, from 13 -15 September.<br />
CANBERRA 7 September 1995 TEL </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
