<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7845</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007845.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2N<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 5 DECEMBER 1989<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER<br />
ASSISTING THE PRIME MINISTER ON PUBLIC SERVICE MATTERS,<br />
THE HON PETER MORRIS<br />
The Federal Government is committed to breaking down all<br />
remaining barriers to Equal Employment Opportunity.<br />
All Australians have the right to achieve their full<br />
employment potential and, while progress has already been<br />
made towards this goal in the Australian Public Service,<br />
we must move forward with vigour.<br />
To ensure continued progress, we are pleased to announce<br />
a four-part strategy to accelerate the implementation of<br />
Equal Employment Opportunity policies and practice in the<br />
Public Service into the 1990s.<br />
The strategy comprises<br />
S greater accountability to Ministers for EEO action<br />
and achievements through regular quarterly reporting<br />
by heads of agencies;<br />
S increased management awareness of EEO, through<br />
senior executive and middle management training and<br />
other initiatives;<br />
S a focus on EEO efforts in the regions, that is, in<br />
capital cities, regional centres and remote areas;<br />
and<br />
S the development of a strategic plan for EEO<br />
achievement in the Australian Public Service for the<br />
1990' s.<br />
People should have real employment choices limited only<br />
by their imaginations and capacities, rather than by<br />
artificial, attitudinal barriers.<br />
To achieve this, the Government wants to see improved<br />
implementation of EEO in the Australian Public Service,<br />
and we intend that the impetus for reform should extend<br />
well into the next decade. </p>
<p>Ignoring the talents and potential of staff because of<br />
biases against certain groups is simply bad management.<br />
Greater equity in staffing also means greater efficiency.<br />
The Public Service must always make the best use of the<br />
skills and potential of all available and potential<br />
employees. EEO ensures that the policy of merit<br />
selection for recruitment and promotion is given full<br />
effect and that the entire pool of talent in the<br />
community is tapped.<br />
Quarterly reporting will mean Ministers and managers have<br />
greater awareness of progress on EEO. Managers will also<br />
be encouraged to show leadership in developing EEO<br />
initiatives. The focus on regional efforts will ensure Service-wide<br />
benefits from this strategy. 72% of all federal public<br />
servants are employed in these areas. The profile of EEO<br />
in the regions will be raised through training of<br />
managers and better co-operative management efforts.<br />
These initiatives will be complemented by the development<br />
of a longer term strategy which will ensure that the way<br />
is clear for continued and improved EEO achievement over<br />
the next decade.<br />
The strategy will involve widespread consultation within<br />
the Service, with unions and managers, and with the wider<br />
community to establish the best ways to break down<br />
remaining barriers to the successful implementation of<br />
EEO throughout the Service. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
