<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1767</transcript-id>
    <title>CONFERENCE OF THE PRESIDING OFFICERS AND CLERKS OF THE AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENTS - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, SENATOR JOHN GORTON.</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/01/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001767.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CONF3RENCE OF THE PRSIDING OFFICERS AND CLERKS<br />
OF THE AUSTRALIAN PARLIAMENTS<br />
-8 FE196823RD JANUARY, 1968<br />
peech by the Prime Minister, Senator John Gorton<br />
A<br />
Mr Speaker, Mr President I'm not quite sure which is the correct form of<br />
address at this moment in this Chamber.<br />
This as has been pointed out, quite like old times to have<br />
a chance to stand in this place and to talk to a distinguished gathering, but<br />
it has one difference. Those on my left are not Opposition; those on my<br />
right are not Government,, rather all are independents gathered together to<br />
discuss how better to make a Parliament work, and If this Is the last speech<br />
that I male In this place, as it may well be, I can think of no better audience<br />
to which to make such a speech, itor any better subject on which to address<br />
you. This is, as the President has pointed out, as the Speaker<br />
has pointed out, the first occasion In Australia when you have all come<br />
together to discuss the duties you have to your various Parliaments, and<br />
through the Parliaments, to the Austraian people. That In Itself, I suggest,<br />
is pregnant with value for the future of Parliaments throughout Australia.<br />
Presidents and Speakers are most Important people. Indeed, to ordinary<br />
Members of Parliament, as you will have noticed, they have some of the<br />
attributes of Ben Bolt. Do you remember that old poem about Ben Bolt,, in<br />
which sweet Alice trembled with fear at his frown? That Is what we at<br />
any rate In this Chamber do with respect to our President, and I am sure<br />
that Presiding Officers in other Chambers find the same reaction from<br />
Members sitting in those Chambers. If they don't they ought to, and I am<br />
sure that after this Conference they will.<br />
Because one of the important jobs of Presiding Officers Is<br />
to keep In order Members of Parliament who occasionally get a little unruly,<br />
not infrequently get off the point and sometimes get a little difficult to<br />
understand, Presiding Officers have to keep them in order and keep them<br />
talling about the subject before the House. This Is a great necessity for<br />
the conduct of parliamentary business.<br />
But over and above that is a duty not laid down anywhere,<br />
not to be found in any manual, but nevertheless something which Is the<br />
oil which helps the wheels of Parliament to turn, and that Is to sit in the<br />
Chair, no matter from what party the man sitting In the chair may come,<br />
and inside the House act with complete Impartiality, and outside the House<br />
to take every opportunity to make the Members of both sides of the House<br />
mingle together in a social sort of a way, and so get to know each other<br />
as men and as human beings, so that when battle Is joined inside the Chamber,,<br />
it Is joined with the knowledge of the personality and the honesty of the<br />
person towards whom that argument is directed. This is a very significant<br />
part of the duties of a President and a Speaker.<br />
Of course they do have other matters which are sprung<br />
upon them suddenly and upon which, too, they must be judged. When<br />
something boils up in Parliament and points of order are taken, it Is<br />
suggested that somebody Is out of order and ought to be thrown out or at<br />
least subdued when this turbulence suddenly comes to the surface, this<br />
too has to be quelled by the President or the Speaker. How often have we </p>
<p>-2-<br />
seen them sitting in their Chairs, and seen the officials with whom I haven't<br />
yet spoken, wandering ur with perhaps an occasional word of advice because,<br />
of course, every President and every Speaker knows his Standing Orders<br />
completely and utterly and doesn't really need any advice. Nevertheless,<br />
one sees them going up and perhaps suggesting a nuance here or a nuance<br />
there before, ex cathedra, comes the final decision. I am sure, from my<br />
own observation, and I think you would all agree with me, that this little<br />
suggestion, this little reinforcement of what a President and Speaker was<br />
going t'o do anyway, by an official, is also of immense importance to the<br />
running of a Parliament. I think there is only one other thing I wish to say.<br />
Presiding Officers still, particularly in the House of Representatives, but<br />
I suppose in all Parliaments, when they are appointed to their position, by<br />
tradition are taken by the arms by two of their supporters and dragged,<br />
struggling and unwilling to the Chair. Since in most cases they have taken<br />
a certain amount of pains to make sure that they do get elected to the Chair,<br />
this occasionally surprises some people. But it has a very valid historical<br />
reason, as of course you all know, and it is a reason which needs to be<br />
remembered and needs to be applied, because you will recall initially that<br />
the Cpeaker was the man who spoke. Now, of course, he doesn't. He<br />
never says anything except " Don't say that" or " That's out of order:' but<br />
initially he was the man who cpoke for the House of Commons to the King,<br />
and said " You can't do this". " You can't impose that tax." " You are<br />
overstepping the law there". The position of Speaker in those days was a<br />
very dangerous occupation for a commoner to have. More than one Speaker<br />
suffered seriously as a consequence of speaking for the House over which<br />
he presided. That is why, originally, there was some real regret, there<br />
was some real opposition to being taken to a seat which in modern parlance,<br />
we would call a hot seat. ;' ell, that doesn't apply now, but what does apply now<br />
is still a necessity to speak for the House in the House, rather than speak<br />
for the Government in the House, or speak for the Opposition in the House,<br />
to speak for the institution of Parliament as opposed to the parties that make<br />
it up or the executive which depends upon its support. These are the reasons<br />
why you all are so honoured in the occupancy of these positions, and these are<br />
the reasons why we are so honoured that you have gathered here in Canberra<br />
to discuss how better, if it is possible to be better, to carry on the functions<br />
of Houses over which you preside and the business which comes before them.<br />
As I make what I hope will be my last address in<br />
this Chamber, particularly if the electors of Higgins support me, I am<br />
mindful that I will be changing from a President I know to a Speaker I do<br />
not know. Without stating the exact quotation because it mig t not sound<br />
proper or appropriate, let me say that I hope that the Speaker I do not know<br />
will be better than the President I know but he will have to be pretty good to<br />
fill that niche. It is with some regret that I leave this place. It is<br />
with pleasure that I see you ci tting here to make it, and all your Parliaments,<br />
a better place than it was before you came here.<br />
And that is why I have pleasure in declaring this<br />
Conference open. Thank you.<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
