<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6887</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH TRISH LAKE FOR THE 7.30 REPORT</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006887.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. PR. 18 ' 86 17: 33 PUSTRRLIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 02<br />
STRICTLY EMBARGOED UNTIL 730PM AET ( 7n<br />
q? 1el<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH TRISH LAKE FOR THE 730 REPORT<br />
17 April 1986<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
This is an unedited transcript and should be checked against<br />
what goes t6 air.<br />
LAKE Prime Minister, thanks for joining us. First to Libya.<br />
What did you talk about with President Reagan.<br />
PM1 Well, we didn't talk a great deal of time talking about<br />
it, although apart from talking with President Reagan I did<br />
receive considerable briefing on the subject. I merely, in<br />
the discussion with President REagan, reflected what we had<br />
said publicly both in Canberra before I left Australia and<br />
what was said by Ambassador Woolcott on our behalf in the<br />
Security Council. I<br />
LAKE: How strongly did you put that view again to him?<br />
PMi Well, we simply made the point that it is the future<br />
that is important and that we had taken the view that all<br />
available * venues that identified in Article 33 of the Charter 33<br />
of the United Nations, should be looked to try and find<br />
a basis fox a peaceful resolution to this matter. And as I<br />
said in Canberra before I left, and as Mr Hayden has said<br />
in Austral3a on behalf of the Government and as Ambassador<br />
Woolcott s~ id, the essential conditions for achieving the<br />
peaceful resolution is that Libya must repudiate the use of<br />
terrorism as a tactic of policy.<br />
LAKE: Was this as confined as the speeches that you had<br />
already ma~ e or were those conversations more lose, if you<br />
like, about Libya?<br />
PM: I am never lose in conversations.<br />
LAKE: But you know what I mean. Were you able to talk freely<br />
with him, as if you had really given him an idea of how Australia<br />
feels abou this? / 2<br />
N </p>
<p>APR. 18 ' 86 17: 34 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 03<br />
PM: Yes. Not only to President REagan but I have obviously<br />
also had discissions witbhSecretary of State George Shultz,<br />
a friend of mine of long-standing, and our position is clearly<br />
understood. LAKE: But did you give them the impression that Australia's<br />
solution or idea of a solution isn't necessarily bombing Libya?<br />
PM: As I said, my conversation with President Reagan and<br />
Secretary of State Shultz reflected, both conversations reflected<br />
our public statements. We have said that force cannot resolve a<br />
situation of a conflict of positions. And particularly, we said<br />
in that terrorism must be repudiated and I believe that the<br />
United States accepts that there must be some other way ultimately.<br />
And I repeat that the United States has invoked Article 51 which<br />
gives the right of self-defence and that that article itself<br />
goes on to say until the processes of the Charter are invoked and<br />
that is what ust be done. We have got to now try and say to<br />
Libya and the United States, let's get to the position where we<br />
can sit down and in some way talk through so that there will be<br />
recognition tIat terrorism is not acceptable and to the extent<br />
therefore that there are differences let's try and work a way<br />
through. Becuse there is no other way which is not going to<br />
involved not only danger to those immediately concerned by<br />
ultimately grave risk for the whole of the world.<br />
LAKE: But what did they say to you in terms of trying those<br />
parties, Israel, the Arab states, the PLO, together. I mean,<br />
did they to you that they would try to do that?<br />
PM: conversations with George Shultz, he gave me a very<br />
detailed rundqwn of some of the work in which the United States<br />
is currently engaged in in trying to find a way through the<br />
central issue in the Middle East, that is a resolution of the<br />
problems between Israel and the Palestinians. And the UNited<br />
States, I bel eve, has been ceaseless in trying to find a<br />
way through, the President has taken initiatives, he has<br />
encouraged initiatives by King Hussein of Jordan by Prime Minister<br />
Peres. I don t believe anyone with any basic can accuse the<br />
United States! of not consistently addressing itself to this<br />
central issuer<br />
LAKE: But haven't they jeopardised that by their action in Libya?<br />
PM: Well, thpy have taken the decision which they felt necessary<br />
in regard to protect their interests in circumstances of what<br />
they had of cpmpelling proof of an intention by Libya to direct<br />
acts of terrorism against their citizens abroad. Now that, I<br />
believe, has pot meant that the United States has ceased<br />
to address itself to the central issues that you have raised<br />
and properly raised. And I have no reason to believe that<br />
the United Sttaes will not continue to try and deal with what<br />
now for so many years has proved an intractable problem. And<br />
certainly I idicated on behalf of the Government and people of<br />
Australia that we will do whatever we can, we don't overstate our<br />
position, we will do whatever we can to play a part in trying / 3<br />
. o V t<br />
l l. ' k -eA . Ji' fv Uk l, </p>
<p>APR. 18 ' 86 17: 36 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 04<br />
5~ 5(/ 3.<br />
PM cont: to ideal with that central core problem.<br />
LAKE: Does i concern you that White House officials now are<br />
trying to put Ia complexion on your departure speech when you<br />
left the Whit House that Australia supports what American in<br />
Libya. PM: As I sai4 in the Press Conference in the last hour, what<br />
I and Mr Hayden on behalf of the Government of Australia and<br />
we have a responsibility of expressing the positions from the<br />
very moment w4 became aware of this, what we have been about<br />
is to state the position as we see it, both in terms of what<br />
has happened and more particularly as to the future. Now, I have<br />
had a situati'n already where there is a range of interpretations<br />
about our position. Mr Howard has said we don't the Americans.<br />
The Libyans said we support the Americans. And other people<br />
have different interpretations. I am not getting into the<br />
business, the auction, if you like, of interpretation. That<br />
can be for ot1ers. clear as to what we have said and<br />
particularly our concern for trying to find a way in the future<br />
to deal with tIhis problem.<br />
LAKE: You don't think you could have made it any clearer?<br />
PM: I could have made what any clearer?<br />
LAKE Your attitude to what has happened in Libya as far as<br />
the American ction is concerned. And where Australia stands<br />
on the issue.: different conclusions from it perhaps it could<br />
have been clegrer?<br />
PM: No, I don't believe we could have stated any more explicitly<br />
our interpretation of what has happened and what the task of the<br />
future is. As far as what happened and that links to the future<br />
we have made . t quite clear that the central issue must be the<br />
repudiation by Libya of thetacticof terrorism. And in those<br />
circumstances there is a possibility of using the processes<br />
envisaged by Article 33 of the United Nations Charter. And I<br />
must say I find somewhat annoying that I am a passive man, I find<br />
somewhat anno'ing, where do you put this statement on scale of<br />
support or non-support. What people should surely be concentrating<br />
upon is what s the process available, what are the processes<br />
available, into the future to try and resolve this.<br />
LAKE: Prime i4inister, slightly away from that subject but in<br />
defence matters, what other talks did you have today which touched<br />
on other area of defence?<br />
PM: Well, we talked about ANZUS. And I confirmed to the President<br />
that if, in txe event of New Zealand legislation of its<br />
current posit. on, that there is an end then to the commitments<br />
by the Unitedi States under ANZUS as far as New Zealand is concerned.<br />
And we have sid that the treaty should be left in existence, there<br />
should be an ñ nterchange of letters between the President and myself<br />
to ensure that the treaty remains operative as far as Australia and<br />
/ 4 w </p>
<p>APR. 18 ' 86 17: 38 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK 4.<br />
PM cont the United States is concerned. And we got a positive<br />
response from the President to that.<br />
LAKE: putting pressure on New Zealand<br />
PMt not rom day one sought that and I believe that they<br />
have not sought that for two reasons. One, they don't believe<br />
that it would be appropriate and secondly they wouldn't insult<br />
my integrity and intelligence by asking to be a messenger boy<br />
in that sense, they know that that would be repugnant to me.<br />
But we both take the view that New Zealand is a sovereign<br />
independent nation. We disagree with their position. But they<br />
are entitled to work that through themselves. The other area<br />
which I did talk about was the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone.<br />
And I stressed upon the President the fact that the signing and<br />
ratification of that treaty is totally consistent with the<br />
continuation of our obligations under the ANZUS treaty. And<br />
I pressed the view upon the President that it was in our interests<br />
and I believe the interests of the United States that they should<br />
adhere to the ' three protocols of that treaty.<br />
LAKEt Star Wars, American Bases, were they topics?<br />
PMt No, therl has been an indication, I didn't specifically<br />
go to that wi1h the President. There has been efforts<br />
George Shyltz as there was with Secretary of Defence W6inberger<br />
in Canberra lst week, they know precisely our position on the<br />
issues of Star Wars. As far as the bases are concerned, I<br />
indicated in the discussion with the President that we remain<br />
committed to our joint involvement in the bases which I emphasise<br />
again, are there for the purposes of verification and mutual<br />
deterrence. And not there for offensive purposes.<br />
LAKE: Now for your real reason for being here, agriculture.<br />
Tell me, what do you know about it, about the farm deal, what<br />
is happening, that you didn't know before you came here.<br />
PM: Well, I don't know any more about the farm deal now because<br />
I think I kney all there was to know about the farm deal before<br />
I got here. What I do know now that is that I have enlarged<br />
and streathenqd commitment from the President and riaht through<br />
the administration and importantly on the Hill, to a process of<br />
discussion and preparedness on the part of the United States to<br />
take into acccunt our concerns. Now, that doesn't mean that<br />
we 0on't perhaps at times be heard, but we have a complete<br />
preparedness on their part to let our concerns be put into<br />
their system and we will be doing that. And secondly, I now<br />
have an unqualified undertaking from the President that the<br />
United States: will take a leading role in trying to ensure<br />
that in the multi-lateral trade negotiations that commence later<br />
this year, that they with us, will be trying to ensure that<br />
international'trade in agricultural products is right up<br />
there on the agenda. And not pushed aside as a subsidiary<br />
issue. A. ti] t " f<br />
, ij! c,, </p>
<p>eP8.18 ' 86 17: 39 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 06<br />
LAKE: Your ipecific talks have been able to elevate that?<br />
PM: Let me pay to the preliminary work that was by Mr Dawkins<br />
here earlier in the year. I have been able substantially to<br />
build upon that.<br />
LAKEs and yet a spokesman, a senior White House official,<br />
said as far sB the White House was concerned there was not, or<br />
he couldn't tell us one single new outcome or agreement that<br />
came out of today's talks. Would that be fair?<br />
PMs No, I believe not. You have a position where the President<br />
of the United States has given a commitment to the Prime Minister<br />
of Australia! that the process of access to Australia for discussions<br />
with the United States on these issues as far as Australians is<br />
concerned is' there. That is new.<br />
LAKE: What would it mean though for farmers. The trade talks<br />
that go on, and they are often not necessarily inter-government<br />
anyway are they.<br />
PM: Elements of the decisions that concern trade are necessarily<br />
always involving governments. But the essential framework is<br />
created by governmental decisions. We will continue and our<br />
putting of the interests of Australian farmers in the United<br />
States as the decisions are taken about how they implement<br />
their program, we will be continuing to discuss these issues<br />
and involve the farmers organisations in Australia so that<br />
when we are putting the case of our farmers we will be doing<br />
it on the basis of full consultation with them.<br />
LAKE: But if a farmer or farmers who are involved in trying<br />
open up a trade avenue or protecting an existing trade avenue<br />
and an American organisation decides no they want that market,<br />
is it going to help just because you have spoken to Reagan<br />
about it?<br />
PM: Not only because I have spoken to Mr Reagan. But let<br />
me answer your hypothetical in a hypothetical way, If we were<br />
to find a s tuation where an Australian interest had been<br />
ignored in the implementation of part of the united States<br />
farm program, I believe we would be in a very much stronger<br />
position now to go to the President and to the Secretary of<br />
AGriculture and look you have taken that decision, you didn't<br />
take account of our interests, that is not consistent with the<br />
undertaking4 that we have received from you. Now, I think the<br />
fact that we have that capacity now makes it more likely that<br />
sort of thing is not going to happen.<br />
LAKE: Finally, what are the prospects of a Reagan visit to<br />
Australia in ' 88?<br />
PM: I have renewed the invitation, and he has expressed a very<br />
real intere t. I hope it comes out. Because if you look at the<br />
200 years of Australia's history, the relationship between our two<br />
countries has been extraordinarily close in peace, importantly,<br />
L 7 </p>
<p>PR. R. 18 ' 86 17: 41 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P0<br />
PM cont: extraordinarily close in the second World War.<br />
Australians and Americans owe a great deal to one another.<br />
We at time are dependent a great deal on one another.<br />
There is a c witment by both countries to certain basic<br />
democratic va ~. Use and it would be appropriate that in the<br />
year of our b centennial celebrations that the leader of<br />
the United States should at some part of that great year be<br />
with us.<br />
LAXEs Mr Hawker thank you very much.<br />
PM: Thank you.<br />
ando E SF, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
