<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8953</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP ADDRESS TO THE ACTU CONGRESS, SYDNEY, 31 AUGUST 1993</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/08/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008953.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ADDRESS TO THE ACTU CONGRESS, SYDNEY, 31 AUGUST 1993<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
Thank you very much, Martin ( Ferguson), members and executives, and<br />
delegates. Well, the newspapers were telling me that I couldn't come to the<br />
ACTU a week or so ago, in one of our celebrated spats over industrial<br />
relations and now more latterly over the Budget, they said a Labor Prime<br />
Minister couldn't speak at the ACTU. Well I would have broken the door in if I<br />
had to, to get in here. So, you have no doubt about me, if only for the video<br />
show, if nothing else, and that song at the start, I wouldn't have missed that<br />
for quids.<br />
But the fact is, why wouldn't we be together and why wouldn't be true<br />
believers after such an epic triumph as we had. We absolutely stole the<br />
election of the Liberal Party, when they so smugly believed it was theirs, it<br />
was in their lap, and they thought they only had to canter home to election<br />
day and that was it. You can see today's newspapers where we have the<br />
election contributions published, you know, generally it was Labor 20,000,<br />
Coalition 100,000, Labor 17,000, Coalition 75,000, and it goes on. That was<br />
the most well healed campaign they have ever had, their best organised, but<br />
they had at their core the hard right-wing agenda, as Malcolm Fraser has<br />
called it, and we came at them horizontally, vertically, laterally and swept<br />
them up on March 13. It was a great victory for Labor, and a great victory for<br />
the Labor movement.<br />
I can say that nothing moved me more than the meeting I had with your<br />
executive just after the election, about ten days after the election, when one<br />
really understood what it was all about, and when it had sunk in just how<br />
extraordinary a win we had had, and w hat it meant to everybody, those who<br />
did believe in a better Australia, who did believe in decent values, who<br />
believed in an inclusive society, who believed in a clearer sense of our<br />
national identity, and who believed in for justice for Australians, but in a<br />
society which was economically changing and economically efficient, and<br />
where we had all the social and economic balances largely brought together,<br />
and I think we had them right. And so it was a magnificent win and I am<br />
particularly indebted to the trade union movement for their faith in the<br />
Government, for their financial support which was very material, but beyond<br />
that the enthusiasm and commitment which each one of you gave in the </p>
<p>I 2<br />
course of the campaign from the various sectors, I mean, this made a real<br />
difference in the election, and it had the Labor movement together as last<br />
before perhaps in the early 1980s, but really probably never since 1972. And<br />
the amalgam of people we had, the various interests groups just made it so<br />
obvious to all of us.<br />
So, we have had a magnificent win, and we have now got to do something<br />
with it. Now, we have worn a bit of flak over the last week or two, and I wore<br />
a bit of flak yesterday as a matter of fact from some of the colleagues, but I<br />
am a flak taker and a flak giver, as Lee Matthew's said, a couple of months<br />
ago in Collingwood, there are only two kinds of players in this game, there is<br />
hitters and hitee's, and he said, I am buggered if I will be a hittee, well ditto<br />
for me, ditto for me. So, I think that we have got to come with the ebb and<br />
flow of these things. Now, look, I could have followed up the election with a<br />
round of warm inner glow speeches, quite easy for me, I can get emotional at<br />
the drop of a hat, and roll one of those off my tongue with comparative ease.<br />
And I am sure we would have all felt really good about the long tail on the<br />
comet, the long after glow, and then we could have had a Budget, nice and<br />
pat with a few things in it which paid passing lip service to the social wage,<br />
and everyone said well that's ok, we're back here and we are the crowd we<br />
thought we always were, and we are in office and we are carrying on, but<br />
instead of that what we have done is really hop into the big issues. I mean<br />
the biggest of the big issues. Like dealing with a two hundred year old<br />
problem of Mabo, which most every other Labor Government passed, found<br />
too hard, and where the great stain of dispossession and the shame of the<br />
injustice which came with it, has never been dealt with, that we have occupied<br />
the continent and not recognised the fact that the Australian indigenous<br />
people were here first and that they had truly to be given the same rights and<br />
entitlements in our society as the rest of us have, but perhaps even more<br />
than that, that we recognise a special cultural relationship that Aboriginal<br />
people have to the land.<br />
Now, it is only twenty years ago that the white Australia policy was put to bed.<br />
And we were dead lucky in the 1960s we were not marginalised like South<br />
Africa, dead lucky, running the kind of policy we were in this part of the world.<br />
And there are harder assessors of Australia watching now, all around us in<br />
the countries of the Asia-Pacific region saying, ok these people say they want<br />
to be part of us, that they are a multicultural society, that there is no basis in<br />
race or creed in their selection of their migrants, or the cast of their society,<br />
let's see what they do with their indigenous people, let's see how they deal<br />
with this challenge, the challenge of the High Court decision on Mabo. So, it<br />
is a real test for us, this one. Now, conservative people think we can fail ttie<br />
test and that rights conferred on Aboriginals are ok, but inherent rights are<br />
not. Seeing Aboriginal traditional law and custom in the common law of<br />
Australia is too much for them to stomach. They just don't want to give land<br />
to black people, and that's why we have to come to terms with this essential<br />
and basic requirement of our society, that is, that we are on terms and at<br />
peace with the original inhabitants of this country. Now it is hard, but we are<br />
moving towards it, we will have, I think, one of the most impressive pieces of<br />
common legislation ready in September, for introduction into Parliament and </p>
<p>the draft bill ready this week, the comment by the Aboriginal and Torres Strait<br />
Islander community, by the States and other interested parties.<br />
So, we have taken that Mabo challenge up, in the immediate period, from<br />
March to September, six months to put into place a body of administrative law<br />
in land management, in a decision which most countries would not have been<br />
able to handle in a decade. In six months we will have built, with a lot of<br />
consultation, a well thought through set of principles for the body of<br />
administrative law governing social justice and land management in this<br />
country. And it will be one of the greatest achievements of Labor ever, when<br />
that bill gets the Governor Generals assent. So, that's one of the things we<br />
have been doing since the election.<br />
The other thing is putting together AP EC, trying to find for Australia a place at<br />
a very big table for the first time in our history. Because we have seen the<br />
world moving into blocks in North America and in Europe, we don't<br />
particularly want to be in a restrictive trading block, in fact, we don't. We<br />
want to be in an open regional arrangement. So, Australia, this Government,<br />
has put together the concept of APEC, and in the last 18 months, and<br />
certainly since the election, I have done as much as I could possibly do to<br />
develop and promote the concept of an Asia-Pacific G7. That is, to take<br />
APEC from simply an information exchange, a body which is talking about<br />
economic change and getting a better idea of its constituency and its<br />
features, to one where there is real executive power, and to turn APEC into a<br />
heads of Government organisation. Now, we are still moving through this, but<br />
now President Clinton has invited all of the APEC leaders to attend a leaders<br />
meeting in the United States in November. And that means within a few<br />
years we have taken APEC from just an idea to a body, to an organisation,<br />
and when it comes together with countries like the United States, China,<br />
Japan, Indonesia, Malaysia, Singapore, Thailand, Canada, Australia, New<br />
Zealand. I mean, when this group comes together it will be representing over<br />
per cent of world gross domestic product and will be very much the focus<br />
of the fortunes and power of the Asia-Pacific.<br />
That is coming off, and it is coming off because in part of the work of this<br />
Government and the work since the election. The other thing we have been<br />
doing is working on our major fiscal challenge which is the Budget. To see<br />
that by the time we get through a strong recovery and private investment<br />
picks up in the middle ' 90s, where our demand on savings the Budget deficit,<br />
which we expanded through the One Nation period to kick the economy<br />
along, is winding itself back. It is 6 challenge we must meet. Because this<br />
time we have the option of a low inflationary long term recovery, the only<br />
thing that can spike it is a short fall of national savings, and the time to get<br />
that done is now, and we have been working on that, as we have been<br />
working with you on the industrial legislation and putting a package to<br />
improve our industrial relations system.<br />
Now, I should have thought a reasonable set of things to do in the five<br />
months since the election, that was Mabo, APEC, major fiscal challenge, our<br />
industrial relations, and of course we have also advanced now the processes<br />
on moving towards an Australian republic, with the establishment of the </p>
<p>committee to bring back options indicating in which ways we can make a<br />
competent change to a republican structure, and those processes being<br />
considered, those terms of reference had to be written, that committee set up,<br />
I have had some consultation with the committee now, and that committee is<br />
now in the process of writing its report.<br />
Now, I had some people in the media say, well the Government won an<br />
election it didn't expect to win, and after the election it is not sure what it is<br />
doing. I mean, really, really, with Mabo and APEC and the republic and the<br />
Budget, and industrial relations. Have a look at it, I mean the agenda is so<br />
huge, I mean it is unconventional maybe, but the Government takes on issues<br />
this large. But what's the bloody point in being conventional, what's the point<br />
in being conventional, you may as well, if you have got the mandate, hop into<br />
the big issues, and get the work done, get the thinking done, but the thinking<br />
on these things has got to be done properly, privately with time and<br />
consideration and when you have got it together well then is the time to go<br />
and sell all these things.<br />
These, I think, have been as time well spent, and time we well and truly well<br />
used, but the Budget of course has been a big part of it. And I want to say a<br />
couple of things to you about the Budget, because a lot of the essential<br />
strategy behind it has been lost in the public debate, but to put a major<br />
Budget together with these issues on the table at once takes a lot of doing.<br />
And we have got a Budget there now which does two things, it provides a<br />
stimulus of $ 2 billion this year, which is as large as One Nation and it also<br />
provides for a lower Budget deficit in the medium term, in 1996-97. That's the<br />
point of it. In other words we have given the economy a kick along with One<br />
Nation doing then again the unconventional thing, when we had everybody<br />
telling us to hang on to the low Budget deficits, don't expand fiscal policy,<br />
don't give the place a kick along, public demand has now played a very big<br />
part in kicking growth along. We have had 3.1 per cent growth for the year,<br />
for the last quarter, 1.2 per cent for the last quarter, and we have got a<br />
conservative 2.75 per cent growth for the year forecast in the Budget, we may<br />
do better than it, we may. But we have got a conservative number in there.<br />
At any rate we are growing faster than most OECD economies, in fact, I don't<br />
know any growing faster than us at the moment, and the One Nation package<br />
was the right thing to do, as well building good public infrastructure and<br />
getting it up.<br />
Now, we have given in this Budget another stimulus as big as One Nation, in<br />
other words we have got the ball rolling, but what we want to do now is keep it<br />
rolling so that we have a full blown recovery on our hands, and so that comes<br />
by way of the outlays changes and tax cuts, but we then get the Budget back<br />
to around 1 per cent of GDP in 1996-97 by the revenue measures which will<br />
then come in in the nexfone, two and three years. Now, you remember the<br />
United States debate and the television pictures of Vice President Gore<br />
casting the casting vote in the Senate on President Clinton's Budget, and<br />
there was great celebration in the United States that finally they got a Budget<br />
through, and that President Clinton had done more than his predecessors in<br />
dealing with the American fiscal policy. Well in 1996 the American Budget<br />
deficit will be at 3 per cent of GOP, ours will be at one, one. In other words </p>
<p>we will be fully set up for a recovery, while other people are still limping along<br />
with the Government's hands in the savings jar constraining private<br />
investment. We are sifting there with low inflation, a very competitive<br />
exchange rate, a profit share which is already high, stronger investment<br />
which we will see in this period and the savings balance adjusted via the<br />
public sector to let it all continue.<br />
Now, is that good Government, or is that not good Government. And what<br />
are our opponents doing? They are going to oppose the lot. They are going<br />
to oppose all the changes because they don't want to get to 1 per cent of<br />
GOP, after telling us that's what we should be doing. That change to 1 per<br />
cent of GOP was a key election commitment. It was as key as any other<br />
commitment, and part of it of course, part of the whole Budgetary scene is to<br />
make certain that the tax revenue to GOP comes back to about where it was<br />
in the last couple of years. That's all we are doing there, it's not as if there is<br />
a big tax hike. In fact, in every year between now and 1996 we are giving<br />
away more revenue than we are getting back. We. are giving away $ 3.8<br />
billion a year in the tax cuts each year, and we will be raising about $ 3 billion<br />
when the revenue measures are up and running. And that will mean that<br />
people on the tax cuts, particularly for people between $ 20,500 and $ 50,000<br />
will be paid from November and the result of that will be that we will see a<br />
substantial tax cut of around $ 8.00 to $ 10.00 a week being paid to workers in<br />
that average weekly earnings area of the economy.<br />
Now, even with the revenue changes, revenue to GOP, the key indice in the<br />
Budget, revenue to GOP this year is falling, it is a decimal point below last<br />
year, last year it was 23.6 per cent this year it will be 23.5 per cent. It is just<br />
that it won't be falling as fast because of the changes which we have made.<br />
But that will provide a stimulus as will our monetary policy. Let me just bear<br />
this in mind, we have just cut another half a percentage point off interest<br />
rates, how were we able to do that? Because the Reserve Bank and the<br />
market were convinced that the Government was going to take the Budget<br />
deficit down, so we have now got bill rates of 4.75 per cent. I mean, we had<br />
bill rates of 4.75 per cent when I was a teenager. And not only that, we have<br />
now got a housing rate of about 8.5 per cent. Now, you remember before the<br />
interest rates went up, the standard housing rate was 13.5 per cent, this was<br />
before the rise in rates in 1988-89, up to 18 per cent for cash rates, and I<br />
think housing peaked at 16 per cent or 17 per cent. But let's forget that part<br />
and just look at the standard rate which was 13.5 per cent. It is now 8.5 per<br />
cent, roughly, that's five per percentage points below that norm, and on a<br />
$ 70,000 mortgage, that's $ 70.00 a week. There is a $ 70.00 a week benefit<br />
going to ordinary wage and salary earners by way of their reduced interest<br />
rates because of lower inflation and because of a decent Budget going into<br />
place. So these are all part of the conferred benefits which are there, and I<br />
think the other important thing is the tax cuts.<br />
Now, I want to say something to you about the tax cuts, because we have had<br />
a bit of a view, a campaign, indeed, that we should abandon them, but at the<br />
time they were introduced in One Nation they met everybody's approval. But<br />
what happened after One Nation is the world dropped, the OECD area<br />
dropped by four percentage points of growth for two successive years, and </p>
<p>the OECD and IMF revised down their growth in two succeeding years, which<br />
meant the second round of tax cuts we put back, but we brought the first lot<br />
forward and maintained them. Now, some people have said, well look, these<br />
tax cuts go to higher income earners, well that's only in part true, they also go<br />
to people at or below average weekly earnings. So I asked the Department of<br />
Prime Minister and Cabinet last week to go back and look at all of the outlays<br />
and tax changes since 1983 and look at a number of category of people and<br />
see how they have been treated in terms of increases in disposable income.<br />
And it is quite interesting the result. Between March 1983 and July 1983 a<br />
process worker who was married with two children experienced an increase<br />
in real disposable income of 15 per cent, real. Not nominal real. That is a<br />
process worker with two children over the period, both on the tax side and<br />
through things like the family allowance supplement and other changes on<br />
the outlays side. If we take in the same time period a female machinist who is<br />
a sole parent with two children, she experienced an increase in real<br />
disposable income of 32 per cent. Between March 1983 and July 1994 a<br />
single income family with two children earning three quarters of average<br />
weekly earings, so this is someone payed above a process worker, obviously,<br />
at three quarters of AWE will have experienced an increase in real<br />
disposable income of 19 per cent.<br />
But a person on AWE with two children, on AWE with two children, the<br />
increase in real terms is really quite small. Because what happened in this<br />
period was all of the tax cuts were going in their greatest measure to those<br />
people below $ 20,000 and just above it. And, of course, a lot of the family<br />
payments were going in that area tailing off in the middle 20,000s. And the<br />
people at the top end, they had their tax cut cut from 60 to 47, but in part was<br />
paid for by the capital gains tax and the fringe benefits tax which basically<br />
covered the budgetary costs of that reduction. The people who deserve<br />
some support now are those in those areas of 2/ 3 of AWE, AWE and above<br />
AWE. And that is what these tax cuts do. So the notion that every tax cut we<br />
ever give has got to be skewed only down the bottom is a notion which I think<br />
is not fair to those who have waited last to get the kind of tax relief I think they<br />
ought to be getting. And who is to say anyone on $ 30,000 or $ 33,000 is<br />
wealthy? Or $ 36,000? Because if we even look at 1996 in three years' time,<br />
even with modest growth in average weekly earnings, we'll have AWE around<br />
$ 36,000. And if we don't change the tax scales those people will cascade<br />
into a marginal rate of 46 per cent. So every dollar they earn at weekends<br />
they will pay 46 per cent at the margin. Now I don't think the Labor movement<br />
can live with that kind of rate and I don't think this Government could and that<br />
is why we thought it was important to do that. And can I just say over the<br />
same period, for what it's worth, for a man on average weekly earnings who<br />
began receiving award superannuation in 1986, and of course, since<br />
enhanced by the SGC, the accrued benefit at Juine 1993 was $ 7,050, and in<br />
two years, that person's accrued benefit will be $ 11,150.<br />
So if you look at the tax~ and outlays side of the Budget, you've got the<br />
changes I've mentioned and superannuation, of course, underpinning it.<br />
Now in this Budget, we have kept our election commitments and funded them<br />
in ways which we think are advantageous to the economy and the community. </p>
<p>But let me go through some of the measures and I will also tell you what we<br />
decided yesterday in terms of revision to some of the Budget measures.<br />
Since the election, we have introduced the legislation for the home child care<br />
allowance which will go to 840,000 families paying $ 60 a fortnight, or $ 30 a<br />
week, and that will go to the dependent spouse who is looking after the<br />
children in the family. $ 30 a week, $ 60 a fortnight. Now $ 54 of that $ 60 was<br />
formerly paid as a dependent spouse rebate to the taxpayer. That is now<br />
being cashed out to the dependent spouse at home. But $ 6 of it is new, $ 3 a<br />
week of it is new.<br />
Then we have got the generalised child care rebate which* provides a rebate<br />
paid at Medicare counters for child care so that families who spend money on<br />
child care don't have to wait till the end of the year to get a rebate or<br />
something else, they can get it over the course of the year by going<br />
periodically to Medicare offices. And that is a generalised thing, it recognises<br />
child care as an expense in earning income and, of course, gives families a<br />
chance to earn that income and women, particularly, a chance to participate<br />
in the workforce.<br />
The labour market programs. We've increased those in the Budget. We<br />
doubled them last year to $ 1.6 billion, and in this year increased it so that<br />
now 500,000 unemployed people are being touched by those labour market<br />
programs. Where we are giving them either a wage subsidy, and/ or training<br />
and work experience for half a million. In the Budget the Newstart allowance<br />
for single adults increased by $ 6 a fortnight. Basic dental care was provided<br />
for health card holders, that is pensioners and beneficiaries who often find<br />
they just can't afford basic dental care. We created an extra 29,000 child<br />
care places in the community over the course of this year. We've diminished<br />
the waiting period for rental assistance for young homeless unemployed<br />
people, we've abolished that. There are improvements there for pensioners<br />
and for the arts and also, of course, there are other changes in respect of the<br />
labour market as they effect industrial relations.<br />
And, I suppose, the best guide to that is since 1983-84 spending on health,<br />
community services and social security. Well in 1983-84 it was 38.4 per cent<br />
of the Budget. This year it is 51 per cent of the Budget. So outlays on health,<br />
social security, community services and housing has risen from 38.4 per cent<br />
in 1983-84 to 51 per cent of Budget outlays this year. So they are the Budget<br />
measures and, of course, on top of those, the tax cuts.<br />
Now let me say a couple of things about the measures we have decided in<br />
the last day or so. They key changes are that we are going to increase the<br />
rebate from low income earners from $ 100 a week which we have in the<br />
Budget to $ 1 50. And that coupled with the home child care rate increase and<br />
other outlay benefits will improve the position of those people below, say,<br />
about $ 23,000. A reduction, we're reducing the differential between leaded<br />
and unleaded fuel from 5 cents to 2 cents a litre. In other words, the price of<br />
leaded petrol will go up now by 7 cents, not 10 cents and the differential with<br />
unleaded will be only 2 cents. </p>
<p>We are restoring eye tests under Medicare for full rebates for optometry.<br />
That is, optometry will be as now. And we've-amended the unused long<br />
service leave lump sum payment so that unused long service leave paid as a<br />
lump sum, accrued up until the 17 August 1993 will continue to attract a<br />
concessional rate of tax. Future long service leave lump sum entitlements as<br />
well as all unused annual leave will be taxed as normal income.<br />
Now those changes amount to about $ 110 million roughly this year, and just<br />
on $ 400 million in 1996-97. And that brings the Budget deficit to a projected<br />
1.2 instead of 1.1 per cent in 1996-97. Well the government has made a<br />
commitment to bring the Budget deficit in around 1 per cent, so that still fits<br />
that category. And this year we're putting the tax cuts back 2 weeks to make<br />
sure that the Budget is neutral in terms of those changes. So they will begin<br />
now on the second week of November in stead of 1 November.<br />
So those changes mean that there will be not only no detriments, but benefits<br />
for practically everybody. Now yesterday the Treasurer had these changes<br />
run through the Prismod model. The one which the Treasury constructed to<br />
look at the Liberal Party's Fightback and GST proposals. And when you put<br />
the tax and outlays changes in the Budget together in the Prismod model, it<br />
shows there are no detriments, and benefits right through the quintiles and<br />
the only place where there are any detriments whatsoever, are for those<br />
actually running down capital who have no relationship with the Government<br />
through the tax or social security, or spending systems. In other words for all<br />
the people in your constituency, there are no detriments and only benefits.<br />
But can I say, that even before these changes, on an earlier run of the<br />
Prismod model, there were only very few detriments anyway. Because what<br />
has been overlooked in the Budget debate, was all the outlays changes I've<br />
just mentioned and people focused on the revenue changes and thought that<br />
was the only way to make a judgement about it.<br />
But the key thing, of course, of all this in the Budget is employment. And in<br />
there, we have a forecast of 100,000 job growth over the course of this year<br />
and 500,000 more jobs over the next three years. At least 500,000 more<br />
jobs. Now we're confident that we can meet those forecasts. Because they<br />
are based on fairly conservative growth estimates. And that being the case,<br />
we will start to see improvements in the unemployment rate. And, of course,<br />
as you know we have got this major study into employment and to<br />
unemployment which will be concluded later this year and upon which the<br />
Government can take decisions.<br />
But if you look at the settings we have got now. We have got the Budget<br />
balance which has gone from an $ 8 billion surplus to a $ 16 billion deficit. A<br />
$ 24 billion change which has held a floor under the economy and provided a<br />
shock absorber to relieve a lot of the pain of the recession from the<br />
community of Australia. That was done by a Labor Government and it<br />
wouldn't have been done by a conservative government. We're adding a $ 2<br />
billion stimulus this year, to keep that going, to keep activity and growth and<br />
employment coming through. We have now got very low inflation and low<br />
interest rates and a high profit share. And that profit share now needs to be<br />
spent on higher investment to guarantee higher employment and better </p>
<p>employment levels over these next few years. And, of course, with the<br />
Budget balance tailing back to a 1 per cent of GOP deficit by 1996 as the<br />
private economy comes through, we should start to see a return to better<br />
rates of employment growth of the variety we are talking about. And on top of<br />
that, the labour market programs sifting there dealing with 1/ 2 million people,<br />
particularly those who are long-term unemployed, of which now over 300,000<br />
are in that category and 180,000 who have been unemployed for more than 2<br />
years. So those programs are particularly focussed on those people to give<br />
them job subsidies and training and work experience to get them back into<br />
the labour market while out in the economy, the big aggregates should be<br />
pulling employment along about 100,000 this year and 500,000 over three<br />
years. So that is our great challenge, to deal with unemployment and to get back the<br />
growth. And I am pleased that profits are picking up in-the economy and we<br />
are starting to see profits come through. But we want those profits spent on<br />
investment and the business community knows if they think they can just<br />
store up profits to levels above the 1980s experience, not just the golden<br />
years of the 60s, but as well as that the really high levels, the peaks of the<br />
1 980s. That if they think the profit share can get to above those levels and<br />
simply stick to it and not invest it, well I'm quite sure the ACTU will have a<br />
strategy to share some of that with themselves. And so we want to see it in<br />
investment, and if we see it in investment, we have got a chance of getting<br />
better employment.<br />
Could I just say a couple of things now about superannuation, very briefly.<br />
And that is, that the superannuation legal minimums will increase<br />
progressively to 9 per cent by the end of the decade. We are supporting that,<br />
and of course then we can look at taking it further, perhaps to 12 per cent,<br />
beyond then to that stage. And on the industrial agenda generally, let me say<br />
that we are supporting you before the Industrial Relations Commission for a<br />
safety net adjustment of $ 8 and we are supporting the development of<br />
enterprise agreements.<br />
Now I know there has been some discussion between us, some may say<br />
dispute between us, but I don't think that is true, about extending enterprise<br />
agreements. And we want to see enterprise agreements extended to the<br />
non-union sector. But we won't see it done in ways which allow for reduced<br />
wages and conditions or weaken trade union responsibilities. And I have got<br />
no doubt a way can be found to do that. We have already established a<br />
working party to consider with the ACTU, with your negotiating committee, a<br />
solution to the problem and I think one can be found. And the Cabinet will be<br />
giving that appropriate attention. But, I think, the thing is, this is a great<br />
opportunity for the labour movement because this election has given you the<br />
breathing space to get out there and organically expand the tentacles of<br />
unionism to make enterprise bargaining work, to involve your members and<br />
include, and bargain with your employers, and train people, and recruit<br />
people, and win the hearts and minds of young Australians who might not<br />
have been coming to unionism but through enterprise agreements. </p>
<p>So we see the enterprise agreement path as a sensible and organic operation<br />
of the organisation of the trade union movement which lets you build a more<br />
relevant place in the industrial culture of this country. And where you're not<br />
sitting at the whim and caprice of some centralised structure and where we<br />
have a golden opportunity in this next year to legislate in ways which really<br />
sets up a new industrial relations system for Australia, but one which you are<br />
a key part of and which give you all the opportunities to exploit.<br />
Let me just say a couple of things about the Accord and just say that the<br />
Accord has changed and you were discussing it here yesterday. In 1983 we<br />
had an Accord of detailed policy calling for detail commitments from unions,<br />
actual individual union commitments. We are not asking individual unions for<br />
those commitments in 1993 as we were in 1983. What we are asking for is a<br />
commitment to the basic ideals of the Labor movement, of Labor in<br />
government and a recognition of the need for the economy to be productive,<br />
to maintain low inflation and to keep our focus upon employment and<br />
unemployment. I do not think in asking that we are asking a great deal of you any more than<br />
you are asking of us. But together we have done so much and we changed<br />
Australia, we have made it a more competitive place. Just imagine where we<br />
would be if we didn't have a competitive manufacturing sector now. Imagine<br />
where we would be if all those new industries we have created were not<br />
created in this last decade, or if we were still only exporting 13 per cent of<br />
GDP instead of 20 per cent of GDP, or if the debt service ratio was where it<br />
was five or six years ago instead of where it is now, or if we were still drifting<br />
around that old industrial relations culture of a decade ago. Where would the<br />
country be? Where would our constituency be? And where would be the lot<br />
of ordinary Australians without the Accord and the processes?<br />
Can I say the opportunity is there for us, we are going to be in a growth cycle,<br />
the business cycle in on the upturn over the course of these next three years.<br />
We have already generated a recovery and a low inflationary one. We are<br />
setting up fiscal policy for the medium term so that we can capitalise upon it.<br />
We are dealing with employment in the best way we know how by bringing<br />
growth and investment back on again and dealing with those unemployed by<br />
a very expansive program of labour market reform and now looking at novel<br />
ways in ways we can deal with the unemployed on a long term basis to see if<br />
can do again something in Australia which is unique and interesting in the<br />
world. Our opponents of course, they have no such ideas. They met last weekend<br />
at their Federal Council which was the one meeting they had after five<br />
election losses on the trot to sit down and say well, what's wrong with us?<br />
Where have we gone wrong? In which way should we change and be more<br />
relevant? Basically they passed the opportunity up. They sat there and<br />
smothered with a lot of motions which were put around; which John Hewson<br />
weakly voted for and everybody sat there and sat mum on the whole thing.<br />
Maybe it was because of difficulties we were having with the Budget and they<br />
thought well, the Government is having a bad week, we won't distract </p>
<p>attention from them. But they passed up a great opportunity and if the<br />
problems of the Budget debate has meant that we have succeeded in<br />
keeping John Hewson as Leader of the Liberal Party for longer than his<br />
natural time cycle would have kept him, then it has been a damn good<br />
weekend all round.<br />
People say, he is walking around saying well, I told you so about the election<br />
he told us so we are raising $ 2.5 billion this Budget. The GST was going<br />
to raise $ 24 billion, over eight times as much and it was paid back not to the<br />
people who paid it. $ 7 billion going off payroll tax, $ 6 billion going off petrol,<br />
more than half of which is paid by business and $ 9 billion to abolish the<br />
wholesale sales tax. So the people paying the $ 24 billion would not have<br />
been the people who got the rebates in the other tax changes. And then to<br />
pay $ 12 billion of tax cuts, he was going to cut $ 10,000 million from<br />
government spending. We tried to take $ 90 million out by taking one of the<br />
ancillary medical services of optometry from the Budget. Now, if there is<br />
something easier than optometry, do you think we wouldn't have done it?<br />
You are looking around saying well here is one, oh no, that is too easy we will<br />
do the hard one.<br />
Here we are in a society like this flat out knocking in a major element of a<br />
program, $ 90 million out and they were going to cut $ 10,000 million out, but<br />
they are still committed to it. Griener, not Griener, what's his name<br />
Alexander Downer, Shirley Temple as I call him he was up there at the<br />
Press Club last week, committed to the $ 10,000 million still, but won't say<br />
where the $ 10,000 million is coming.<br />
Look, here is a Budget which is raising over the course of three years, $ 2.5-3<br />
billion and giving back Compare that to raising $ 24 billion and giving it<br />
all to different people who pay it and then cutting $ 10,000 million out of<br />
outlays and seeing the tax cuts from that go only to those on the top end of<br />
the tax system.<br />
Now, it is not to be compared with what we are doing. They are running<br />
around, these characters, trying to make a case for themselves about what<br />
we said in the election about taxation and I'll tell you what I said, so I will give<br />
you the full quote in full. I was asked a question and I said this to maintain<br />
the tax to GDP ratios we roughly have at the moment what's your policy?<br />
and I said to maintain the tax, that is the revenue to GDP ratios we roughly<br />
have at the moment. In other words what I'm promising is not to put up tax,<br />
that was not to put up revenue to GOP. In 1996 with these tax increases and<br />
the tax cuts, revenue to GOP will be about where it was last year and the year<br />
before. In other words, we are keeping our commitment absolutely, but because they<br />
run on a high tax policy with a GST and were canned for it, they have been<br />
seeking to imply somehow we are running on a low tax policy, well we are in<br />
the sense that revenue to GDP has been falling. But we can't let it fall to<br />
pieces, we have got to maintain it at some reasonable level to bring the<br />
Budget deficit down and as I said to you when I started, this year revenue to<br />
GOP is a decimal point below last year even with the revenue changes. In </p>
<p>1996-97 when we get there, it will be as it was a year or two years ago way<br />
below what it was in the middle 1980s.<br />
So we have kept our commitment absolutely on tax while at the same time we<br />
have kept the tax cut promise to see that people between $ 20-50,000 get a<br />
tax cut and because of the changes in the Budget, those under $ 23,000<br />
secure an increase in the rebate, a cash rebate, plus the home childcare<br />
allowance seeing not only do they not wear a detriment, but they wear<br />
benefits as well.<br />
In all of this we face a Liberal party which is now turning itself against any<br />
norms of decent governance. In the Senate they are opposing everything,<br />
they are opposing all of our fiscal measures how does John Hewson go to<br />
the business community speeches on a Friday telling them about how we<br />
should have a lower Budget deficit, then on Tuesday in the Senate, his<br />
Senators down all the measures. How can you live with that kind of duplicity<br />
and hope to get away with it? Well, of course, he can't. That is why he is not<br />
taken seriously in business he is a low impact player, as I said to him<br />
yesterday, a low impact player with a limited future and he has.<br />
I do not know whether some of you saw the ' Sunday' program on the Liberal<br />
party it was quite interesting. One fellow said well, the problem is we have<br />
got a hole in the centre, he said there is no core, nothing at the core of the<br />
policy. Malcolm Fraser said it was a right-wing group; they have turned the<br />
Liberal party into a right-wing party. I have got the quote here somewhere,<br />
but you all know what he said I think. That is, ' that it wasn't always this way'<br />
he said, ' but it has been taken over by a small group who have turned it into a<br />
right-wing conservative party'. That is really what has happened.<br />
On Mabo, John Hewson sat at his National Council, his Federal Council on<br />
the weekend while they carried a motion which said all options consistent with<br />
the responsibilities of the states for control of land use including a<br />
referendum. In other words he was running around weeks ago saying a<br />
referendum would be divisive, on Sunday he sits there doggo while they pass<br />
a resolution, he weakly puts his hand up for it, like a mouse, hoping he is not<br />
sighted, voting for a thing which abolishes native title and overturns the High<br />
Court decision. Is that leadership? Is that Leadership when he knows<br />
better? On the republic he said when all the younger, brighter people in the<br />
Liberal party were urging a conscience vote and support for the republic, he<br />
put his hand up for a motion which said the onus is on the Government to say<br />
why the Constitution should be changed.<br />
In other words, I have to say why we shouldn't have the Queen of Great<br />
Britain as Queen of Australia, as our Head of State forever. He-ioted for that<br />
Vproposition, the hand went up weakly for that one as well.<br />
In other words, the Liberal party which is always telling us about the rule of<br />
law, I mean how many times have they told us about the rule of law? Until<br />
our most supreme of Court the High Court says that Aboriginal custom and<br />
tradition is now part of the common law of Australia and they are not<br />
interested in the rule of law. It is the same as their behaviour in the Senate. </p>
<p>They have just a father of a hiding in the election what are they doing?<br />
Three months later, trying to deny the Government's legitimacy by voting its<br />
measures down in the Senate.<br />
Always they attack the legitimacy of the Labor party whether it is endorsed<br />
in popular mandates at the election always they attack you. In other words,<br />
this has never been the Liberal party, the party of convention, it has always<br />
only been the party of shabby convenience. And now where it is a rule of law<br />
and you have fops like Hugh Morgan, well dressed dandies, whose only<br />
clever thing was choosing his parents wisely and out there in the High<br />
Court. You would think butter wouldn't melt in their mouths three years ago<br />
about the High Court, now of course, it is a social 4peri mental group they<br />
say. All now attacking the legitimacy of our measures in the Senate because<br />
we didn't really win the election now they are saying won on a false premise.<br />
What false premise? John Hewson was roundly rejected and at their meeting<br />
instead of saying look, we have lost five elections on the trot, for God's sake<br />
let's sit down now and say what is wrong with us, lets have a good hard look<br />
at ourselves. No, no, they put these mealy mouthed propositions around and<br />
out goes his weak little hand up to vote for them.<br />
That is OK John, I have you covered four square covered. I have got you<br />
right in the sights. The trick for me will be preserving you.<br />
But I tell you this once we get things really rolling, that is we get this solid<br />
budgetary position into place, we get the great principles of Mabo established<br />
in our law and then we really get onto focussing about our place-in Asia and<br />
our right to an independent identity where we are represented by an<br />
Australian as our Head of State, that is when the heat will go on the Liberal<br />
party. That is when the heat will really come on and there will be no weak<br />
little motions then. We will be after them for 1996 like we are after them for<br />
1993. So I say this. Keep the faith as you have, you were true believers and I<br />
amongst others appreciated it ever so much that you were. We haven't let<br />
you down not in the Budget and we won't let you down. This is always<br />
going to be a traditional Labor Government, but it will never be a do nothing<br />
Labor Government. I won't see this be a government of shame, passing the<br />
parcel on Aboriginal rights like other governments before us have done. I<br />
won't see us lose the chance of making a statement about our identity, but<br />
more than anything else I won't see us lose the chance of seeing every<br />
Australian have as much chance as possible to a job and a chance to<br />
participate in what this society can hold.<br />
We will always have arguments rattling through trying to get things right, but<br />
that is part of our strength. At least we can have an argument. We do not<br />
have to have pap resolutions which we all vote for and then go out and rise<br />
and turn and twist afterwards. We can have our debates in public, at the<br />
ACTU Congress, at the Executive, at the wages committees, at your industrial<br />
organisation committees, in our Caucus we can have the debates because<br />
we truly stand for something, we represent Australian society and Australian<br />
culture as no political movement in this country does. </p>
<p>If our opponents who seek to deny our legitimacy or seek to face up to the<br />
issues, who weakly skirt the real issues in Australian society think they can<br />
sneak under our guard they can think again, because the public are more<br />
conscientious than that. They know we have got the big issues on and that<br />
we have been considering them for a few months we have been<br />
reconnoitring, working out how we deal with them and in which way we<br />
advance them, but get our act together on these things as we are on Mabo,<br />
on the Budget, on these other big issues and you will see, I hope, past<br />
breaking ground, big ground, 200 year old ground, the sort of ground that<br />
only a Labor government can break.<br />
That is what we are about and always remember this: together we are always<br />
strong, while ever the trade unions and the Labor party stick together we are<br />
too strong for the others. If they couldn't beat us in 1993, I think they have<br />
got buckleys in 1996.<br />
Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
