<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17185</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Minister for Health Minister for Rural and Regional Health $9.2 million for new and enhanced regional cancer services in Hervey Bay 12 April 2010</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/04/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Rudd Government will invest $9.2 million for an additional 16 chemotherapy chairs at Hervey Bay Hospital, as part of the Central Integrated Regional Cancer Service.</p>
<p>With some cancers, patients from rural areas are up to three times more likely to die within five years of diagnosis than their counterparts. The $9.2 million investment in Hervey Bay will work towards improving the services and care for the more than 18,400 Queensland residents diagnosed with cancer each year.</p>
<p>The services at Hervey Bay will work together with Bundaberg Hospital where the Rudd Government is investing $8.3 million for an additional 14 chemotherapy chairs, and with Rockhampton Hospital where the Prime Minister announced a $67 million investment in additional radiotherapy bunkers and 16 chemotherapy chairs.</p>
<p>When operating at full capacity, the Central Integrated Regional Cancer Service will provide radiotherapy for an estimated extra 828 patients per year, and chemotherapy treatment for an estimated extra 11,500 patients per year.</p>
<p>It forms part of the Rudd Government's $560 million investment in regional and rural cancer centres to ensure all Australians can get care closer to home and their community.</p>
<p>While Australia has better overall cancer survival rates than comparable countries, there is still unacceptable variation for some people, depending on the type of cancer, a person's socioeconomic status or where they live.</p>
<p>It is of great concern that for the 30 per cent of Australians living in rural and remote areas, outcomes are worse than for people living in the city.</p>
<p>Since coming into office, the Government has committed over $2.3 billion in cancer infrastructure, medicines, screening and research.</p>
<p>Today's announcement also shows the benefit of the Federal Government stepping up to the plate and providing funding for health services across Australia.</p>
<p>Under the National Health and Hospitals Network, the Rudd Government would provide 60 per cent of the funding for capital upgrades for public hospitals.</p>
<p>The Rudd Government's plan will see health services funded nationally and run locally through local hospital networks to deliver better outcomes for local communities. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
