<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4968</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004968.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PR, I 3 1~ I ON I<br />
FOR PRESS 25 FEBRUARY 1979<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
After three years of policies directed at overcoming inflation<br />
and rebuilding the economy, the signs of progress are clear.<br />
There is little doubt that 1979 is the year in which the<br />
fruits of our endeavours will become apparent.<br />
official figures provide increasing grounds for optimism.<br />
Consumer demand is encouraging, production has strengthened,<br />
private investment is growing strongly, investment in plant<br />
and machinery is much above last year, while the outlook for<br />
housing is showing signs of improvement.<br />
The rural economy too is showing a strength and a confidence<br />
that has not been seen in Australia for more than a decade.<br />
That is heartening news for every Australian.<br />
A most encouraging sign for Australia this year is the<br />
resurgence of investment in our country's great mineral<br />
resources. A clear pointer is new capital investment in<br />
mining. It was 75% higher in the year to September, while<br />
the latest survey by the industry itself shows an expected<br />
32% increase in 1979.<br />
This is a far cry from policies that stifled development<br />
between 1972 and 1975.<br />
In manufacturing, major new investments have been announced<br />
over the past few weeks. One of Australia's top companies,<br />
ICI, has committed a $ 900 million investment in Victoria and<br />
New South Wales. General Motors Holden, one of Australia's<br />
largest employers, is planning a new $ 210 million engine complex<br />
in Victoria.<br />
Only this week, the Metal Trades Industry Association released<br />
a survey which showed in the clearest terms increased confidence<br />
in the industry throughout Australia.<br />
Three-quarters of the companies surveyed expected improvement<br />
in general business conditions and employment this year.<br />
Nearly half the companies reported improved forward orders<br />
compared with just ten weeks ago. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
It is because of this decisive vote of confidence in Australia,<br />
and in the Government's policies, that we are seeing the first<br />
tentative stages of growth in manufacturing employment in<br />
five years.<br />
The competitiveness of Australia's firms has improved dramatically<br />
because we are steadily getting on top of inflation. In fact,<br />
Australia is more competitive than at any time in the last seven<br />
years. Despite this, much remains to be done, we must consolidate<br />
the gains already won.<br />
There is no room at all for the soft or easy option. Economic<br />
realities must be faced. There is no room for relaxation of<br />
the Government's firm economic management.<br />
However difficult these policies may seem in the short run,<br />
they are ultimately the only policies that can keep us on the<br />
road to prosperity and higher employment.<br />
Over the last two or three months we have seen some encouraging<br />
signs of increasing employment. These are tentative signs but<br />
they point in the same direction. Civilian employment has<br />
risen in Australia over the five months to November 1978, the<br />
first time this has occurred for five years.<br />
In October and November last year employment in manufacturing<br />
increased the largest increase over these two months for<br />
five years. Overtime, another key indicator of employment,<br />
has risen each month for the last seven months to the highest<br />
level since 1974. Similarly, the trend for new vacancies<br />
notified by companies to the Commonwealth Employment Service<br />
shows a better picture.<br />
In my first broadcast to you this year, I have pointed to a<br />
number of areas where the economy is moving ahead much better<br />
than it has.<br />
While we must treat the signs with caution the optimism in<br />
our industries, resurgence of investment in development in<br />
mining and manufacturing, a revitalised rural Australia they<br />
nevertheless give Australia firm ground for confidence.<br />
As each month passes, we will have further demonstration that<br />
Australia is recovering from the three years of Labor's<br />
mismanaqement that hit every Australian firmly and shattered<br />
our economy.<br />
Your Government' s policies are overcoming inflation, rebuilding<br />
the economy, providing new job opportunities and creating a<br />
better Australia.<br />
We will stay with the job you have given us. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
