<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11022</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER          THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP          PRESS CONFERENCE          THE ROYAL HOTEL - DURBAN, SOUTH AFRICA</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................</p>
<p>  Ladies and Gentlemen, let me say just a couple of things about the conference.</p>
<p>  This is the first Commonwealth Heads of Government Conference ever to be</p>
<p>   held in South Africa. I understand I am in fact the first Australian Prime</p>
<p>   Minister to have visited South Africa while in office, although several</p>
<p>   of my predecessors have visited this country after leaving office.</p>
<p>  The fact that it is being held in South Africa is very significant in itself</p>
<p>   and the holding of the conference here is another very, very important signal</p>
<p>   from the rest of the world of the importance it attaches to the transformation</p>
<p>   to democracy and racial equality which has occurred in South Africa and</p>
<p>   I know that all of South Africa's Commonwealth friends will wish that country</p>
<p>   well as it grapples with the enormous task of transforming its society into</p>
<p>   what it quite properly calls the new South Africa.</p>
<p>  This conference also marks the return to Commonwealth membership of the</p>
<p>   most populous nation in Africa, that is Nigeria, and President Obasanjo</p>
<p>   was present at the opening ceremony and today as the democratically elected</p>
<p>   leader of that country and that once again is a very important thing both</p>
<p>   in substance and also the symbolism of it is immensely important.</p>
<p>  I remain very much of the view that the Commonwealth is an extremely valuable</p>
<p>   association. There isn't any in the world quite like it because it brings</p>
<p>   together a group of nations which comprise something like a third of the</p>
<p>   world's population. The member States are bound together by some common</p>
<p>   historical linkages that in contemporary terms by a common commitment to</p>
<p>   a certain set of values and although each of us as Commonwealth members</p>
<p>   have our own particular regional, geographical and strategic associations</p>
<p>   which in narrow ways are more concentrated and more intense than our broader</p>
<p>   Commonwealth associations, it is a very valuable association for a country</p>
<p>   such as Australia. It is through the Commonwealth for example that we have</p>
<p>   linkages with the nations of Africa which we might not otherwise have. It</p>
<p>   is through the Commonwealth that we can build on those sorts of linkages</p>
<p>   and as was demonstrated in the roles played by some of my predecessors concerning</p>
<p>   South Africa and Zimbawbe or Rhodesia as it then was, Australia can play</p>
<p>   a very significant role so I regard the association as an extremely important</p>
<p>   one and one that adds value to this country's overseas associations.</p>
<p>  The audience I've just had with the Queen is normal in Commonwealth Heads</p>
<p>   of Government gathering. As you know it is not customary to go to into the</p>
<p>   details of the discussion which I don't intend to do, except to observe,</p>
<p>   not surprisngly, we talked about the referendum last weekend, we discussed</p>
<p>   in a general way arrangements for the visit to Australia next year by the</p>
<p>   Queen and the Duke of Edinburgh and I also briefed the Queen on the arrangements</p>
<p>   that have been put in place regarding the opening of the Olympic Games by</p>
<p>   the Governor-General.</p>
<p>  Are there any questions?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, given that 45 per cent 9of Australians voted for a republic</p>
<p>   last weekend what assurances were you able to give the Queen that she would</p>
<p>   receive a warm welcome in Australia in March?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, as I say Glenn, I'm not going to talk about what was discussed in</p>
<p>   any detail in accordance with the normal custom but I have separately dealt</p>
<p>   with that question. Australians are courteous people and I think I've already</p>
<p>   said back in Australia that those people who are interested in her visit</p>
<p>   will display interest, those who aren't will display disinterest. We are</p>
<p>   a sophisticated, yet extremely courteous people and it was always my view</p>
<p>   that the Queen would be received in a courteous fashion, even though by</p>
<p>   some people indifferently, irrespective of the outcome and I don't think</p>
<p>   the 45 percent who voted yes are any less courteous than the 55 percent</p>
<p>   who voted no. I don't think courtesy has a republican hue or anti-republican</p>
<p>   hue about it. I think it is a common Australian trait.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, the Olympic Games. Did you indicate that Sir William Deane</p>
<p>   would be opening it as the Head of State?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, let me simply say that I advised her of the arrangements that have</p>
<p>   been put in place.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  But Prime Minister if Sir William Dean is our effective head of state, what's</p>
<p>   the office held by the woman with whom you've just spent half an hour?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I've said to you before Malcolm that by law the Queen is the Queen</p>
<p>   of Australia. By undeniable constitutional convention the Governor-General</p>
<p>   has become the effective head of state. Now that's been the position for</p>
<p>   quite some time, it's been my position, it remains my position.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Did the Queen endorse your decision to step aside Mr Howard?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  As I say, I don't intend to go into that. I advised The Queen of the arrangements.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Could you give us some sense of the Queen's feelings about the Referendum</p>
<p>   without going into detail?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No look, please, I've indicated the areas that were discussed. As you know</p>
<p>   it is the normal practice not to go into the details. It was a practice</p>
<p>   that was respected by Mr Keating, and all of his predecessors so don't read</p>
<p>   anything in particular into my not wanting to go into the details, but I</p>
<p>   just choose to observe the normal practice.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Did she indicate that she was looking forward to the visit to Australia</p>
<p>   though?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Of course.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister why is that protocol necessary?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Why is it necessary?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Why is the protocol necessary? I mean if the Prime Minister is..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I think the protocol is necessary to maintain the above-politics character</p>
<p>   of the office. That is my understanding of the reason as otherwise from</p>
<p>   a canvassing of the views there could be construed a particular attitude</p>
<p>   on a political issue and that would then be intruding the monarch's or sovereign's</p>
<p>   views into a political issue. That is my understanding of why that protocol</p>
<p>   is observed and I think it's perfectly correct and it's entirely in accord</p>
<p>   with constitutional practice. I mean if I were, I mean I talk to the Governor-General</p>
<p>   on a regular basis. I don't go into the details of those conversations for</p>
<p>   exactly the same reasons.</p>
<p>  That is the reason, and I think it's an entirely sound reason and entirely</p>
<p>   in accord with the constitutional propriety of the position.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Are you able to say what sort of atmosphere the meeting was held in then</p>
<p>   Prime Minister? What was the tenor of the meeting? The tone of the meeting?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  A frank and cordial exchange of views. And it was good Durban water.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Were there any more details that you could possibly give us about the Queen's</p>
<p>   visit, like which States she'll be visiting and ..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No I can't, they're still being worked out. I mean I must say that I haven't,</p>
<p>   we've had some discussion about it, but I haven't really given it- as yet,</p>
<p>   all the details haven't been finalised.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Is it anticipated we'll get two more visits in a row given that she'll attend</p>
<p>   CHOGM in Canberra?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well she will be coming to CHOGM, well</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  That is two years in a row.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  One will be in March of 2000 and the other will be in November of 2001.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  November or early ..?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well CHOGM will be sometime in October or November. There's something else</p>
<p>   in November of 2001.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  An election?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Melbourne Cup.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister you're a prominent supporter of the role of the monarchy</p>
<p>   in Australia. What was it like for you then to bring a personal report of</p>
<p>   the referendum results to the Queen? How did you feel about that?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well look I think, I don't that that particularly entered my head.. Look</p>
<p>   I think the Queen was aware of the result before our meeting this afternoon.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  But I'm asking about your feelings personally?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Oh look, forget it.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  There's been some speculation about Prince William coming to Australia.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well I'm not aware of the basis of any of that. There are no, the government</p>
<p>   has no plans to issue any invitation, no.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, do you have any concerns at all that the Commonwealth doesn't</p>
<p>   tend to the Pacific/South East Asian region to which we are very importantly</p>
<p>   attached, and that it is Afro/Subcontinent-centric in any way. I mean just</p>
<p>   today..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well it's interesting you raise that because I was thinking as I was sitting</p>
<p>   around the table at the meeting that those who most quickly came with Australia</p>
<p>   when INTERFET was put together were Commonwealth countries. The responses</p>
<p>   we received from Britain, Canada and New Zealand were as speedy if not speedier</p>
<p>   than most. So I don't think the Commonwealth association was found wanting</p>
<p>   in relation to East Timor. It think it's something that people have tended</p>
<p>   to overlook and indeed the involvement of Singapore, the involvement of</p>
<p>   Malaysia,-now I don't want to decry in any way the contribution of non-Commonwealth</p>
<p>   countries in our region such as Thailand, which has been magnificent, and</p>
<p>   the Koreans, but if you look at it, the Commonwealth association, I'm not</p>
<p>   saying it was the only reason, but I don't think you could suggest for a</p>
<p>   moment when you look at the speed with which the British responded, and</p>
<p>   the New Zealanders and the Canadians.</p>
<p>  I mean the Canadians are very stretched. They have commitments in Kosovo,</p>
<p>   they have commitments all around the world, they are an ocean and half a</p>
<p>   world away geographically yet they have been very generous contributors.</p>
<p>   So I think the Commonwealth association means something and that was very</p>
<p>   much a contribution that was conditioned by an association with Australia</p>
<p>   as much as it was a contribution that was conditioned by, well it was certainly</p>
<p>   influenced by that. But it was also of course conditioned by Canada's very</p>
<p>   long record of commitment to peacekeeping operations. I mean I think given</p>
<p>   the other commitments of the Canadians it was very good.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, who will Australia support for the Secretary-General's position.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, we have already indicated that we are supporting Mr McKinnon.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, in the 1980s you came under some criticism for your views on</p>
<p>   South Africa..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Yes, I remember that.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Do you think your views have changed and matured on these sorts of issues</p>
<p>   over the years or what do you feel looking back on all that?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I guess we all change and mature over the years. I have no doubt that</p>
<p>   what happened here in South Africa in the early 1990s was right and just.</p>
<p>   I have no doubt that it was made possible by the combined efforts of two</p>
<p>   men, of Nelson Mandela and FW De Klerk. Mandela, I think I have said before,</p>
<p>   is one of the most impressive people I have met in life and I think it's</p>
<p>   a remarkable tribute to mankind's capacity to forgive that a person who</p>
<p>   could have lost 27 years of his life in detention without, in the eyes of</p>
<p>   some, a proper process and the sort of appalling conditions in which he</p>
<p>   was imprisoned can complete the transition that he completed is an extraordinary</p>
<p>   thing. I think it's also fair to say that De Klerk did make a contribution.</p>
<p>   To tell your own constituency that they have to surrender privileges that</p>
<p>   they have had all their life is always a challenge for a political leader</p>
<p>   and I think it's a remarkable experiment.not experiment, it is a remarkable</p>
<p>   investment in human goodwill what's happened here. So if you are saying,</p>
<p>   you know, was I right or wrong, look, I can only say what I have just said</p>
<p>   that I think there has been a.I mean, back in the 1980's, Michelle, I never</p>
<p>   said that I supported the regime, I argued for at that time, if I can remember</p>
<p>   right by a slightly different approach to things like sanctions. And indeed</p>
<p>   some of the most liberal thinkers of the old South Africa were opposed to</p>
<p>   economic sanctions if I remember rightly. Alan Paton and Helen Suzman were</p>
<p>   two people who fell into that category. But I mean, that's a bit academic</p>
<p>   isn't it?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Has your contact with Mr Mandela though changed your attitude to sanctions</p>
<p>   as a tool in that kind of.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I mean, I don't really spend a lot of time, I mean, life moves on</p>
<p>   and sanctions are.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  But do you think they are a valuable tool in circumstances other than the</p>
<p>   ones.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I mean, historically sanctions have been relative failures. I have to say</p>
<p>   that history demonstrated they probably have some value in relation to South</p>
<p>   Africa. I think they did. But they didn't work in Rhodesia, very effectively.</p>
<p>   Years and years ago they didn't work in the old Abyssinia, now Ethiopia.</p>
<p>   But the Americans have maintained them very strenuously in relation to Iraq</p>
<p>   and many people would argue that they've had some impact there. I think</p>
<p>   the jury has to be out, I think it depends entirely, Karen, on what the</p>
<p>   particular circumstance is.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  So what's your view then about sanctions on Pakistan that the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   was thinking about..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  On Pakistan as a result of.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Yes.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I think that would be entirely premature. I don't think that would</p>
<p>   be the right thing to do now, I think that would be overreacting at the</p>
<p>   present time. Tony Wright was trying to ask a question.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  No, I already asked exactly the same question word for word.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Prime Minister, what would your view then be on the movement within the</p>
<p>   Commonwealth to have a greater policing role on errant States who abuse</p>
<p>   human rights?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I think you have got to have a sense of proportion about these things.</p>
<p>   I mean, I don't suggest for a moment that you can conduct foreign policy</p>
<p>   entirely on pragmatic grounds, you have got to have a mixture of principle</p>
<p>   and pragmatism and getting the balance right is very important. I think</p>
<p>   the approach that the Commonwealth is taking at the moment is about right</p>
<p>   and it's having a lot of success. I mean, it did have an influence on Nigeria,</p>
<p>   there's no doubt about that. And I think the process of talk and discussions</p>
<p>   could have an impact on Pakistan. I think the, sort of, come the heavy straight</p>
<p>   away given the history of that country would be a mistake.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  But the Commonwealth is looking at expanding the role of the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   into other areas such as press freedom, for instance, and so on so that</p>
<p>   there are guidelines being developed. How far do you think those guidelines</p>
<p>   should go?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I think you have to take these things carefully. I don't think you</p>
<p>   should.and also I think we have to be very careful with multilateral associations.</p>
<p>   We have to be very careful about multi-national associations. You have got</p>
<p>   to be careful about overlap. I mean, there are other multi-national arrangements</p>
<p>   that have commitments and declarations of this kind and I think we have</p>
<p>   got to be very careful we don't have too much of an overlap.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Has East Timor been raised in any of your meetings today?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, yes. I had a bilateral meeting with the Prime Minister of Singapore</p>
<p>   and we talked about East Timor at that. And it was briefly mentioned in</p>
<p>   the plenary session today.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Has the issue of a republic coloured in any way your dealings with the other</p>
<p>   leaders?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  With whom?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  With the other leaders? Have they raised it?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  No, no, no. Well, there's a bit of interest by a couple of them but it hasn't</p>
<p>   coloured it. I mean, I don't - it hasn't made any difference where they</p>
<p>   don't ask.I don't say to any of them: how would you have voted sort of thing.</p>
<p>   I mean, everybody, I mean, you might have your jokes about these things</p>
<p>   but in all seriousness people quite properly regard it as our business.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  In what context was East Timor raised in the plenary session Prime Minister?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I made a reference to it. We were talking about standing up for the democratic</p>
<p>   process. And I said during the plenary session that I thought what had been</p>
<p>   done by a number of Commonwealth countries it's really my earlier point</p>
<p>   that when you look at it the Interfet has got a strong Commonwealth hue</p>
<p>   about it. Mozambique and Fiji are talking about a contribution to stage</p>
<p>   two. And the countries are already there. So there's a very strong Commonwealth</p>
<p>   presence and I just said it was an example of how Commonwealth nations have</p>
<p>   stood up for the right thing in relation to what had occurred in East Timor</p>
<p>   and I also made the observation that although it was not of direct concern</p>
<p>   to the Commonwealth because Indonesia was not a member that the fact that</p>
<p>   Indonesia had moved so positively towards democracy was a very encouraging</p>
<p>   sign.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Isn't it interesting that you raised it and no-one else in the Commonwealth</p>
<p>   did? The Secretary-General had a press conference yesterday where he talked</p>
<p>   about trouble spots of the world and he talked about Saddam and he didn't</p>
<p>   even talk about Kosovo.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, is it strange that I raised it? Well, I don't know.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  No, not strange that you raised it but isn't it significant that you raised</p>
<p>   it and no-one else.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I am not saying nobody else, I mean, it was raised fairly early by</p>
<p>   me after the discussion was started so I suppose I got in before anybody</p>
<p>   else. I mean, I don't know if anybody else would have raised it or not but</p>
<p>   I don't think there is anything strange about that.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Mr Howard, could you give us a run down on what else you..</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Could you give us a run down on what else you said in your contribution</p>
<p>   or contributions today?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I spoke of Nigeria's, you know, the welcome return of Nigeria. I naturally</p>
<p>   extended a bit of my thanks to Thabo Mbeki for South Africa's hospitality</p>
<p>   and I made a very brief reference to Timor and the Commonwealth contribution.</p>
<p>   But it was a very brief intervention. I believe in brief interventions at</p>
<p>   these things, it's very important. But I have got a few more things to say</p>
<p>   and I'll probably have something to announce tomorrow in relation to an</p>
<p>   Australian contribution.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  The trade aspect, Mr Howard, what would you hope to see out of the communique</p>
<p>   in relation to.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, we would like to see the strongest possible endorsement of a comprehensive</p>
<p>   world trade round. And that is in Australia's interests and I have a pretty</p>
<p>   single-minded view about pursuing those interests and that's what we'd like</p>
<p>   to see. Now, whether we get every last word we like I don't know because</p>
<p>   you have some different influences invading this but by and large I think</p>
<p>   that is what we will go after and I hope we can achieve it.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  There is a report to the Commonwealth which suggests a plan for restricting</p>
<p>   the trade in weapons, there's a small line..Given your interest in Australia's.</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, I'd look at that sympathetically. I would because I think there are</p>
<p>   too many hand guns in too many hands in too many countries in the world.</p>
<p>   And anything that can be done to remove them the better. I hold very strongly</p>
<p>   to the view that if you have a weapon in your house or on your person you</p>
<p>   are far more likely in rage and passion to use it than not.</p>
<p>  JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>  Would you recommend to APEC that they adopt the brooch approach rather than</p>
<p>   a silly jacket?</p>
<p>  PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>  Well, they have a brooch and a jacket. You get both at APEC because there</p>
<p>   are fewer nations I think. See you later.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
