<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3964</transcript-id>
    <title>PROFESSOR RI DOWNING</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/11/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003964.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1*-<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS'STATEMENT NO. 592<br />
November 1975<br />
PROFESSOR R. I. DOWNING<br />
I was deeply shocked to hear of Professor Downing's<br />
death. The loss of this outstanding Australian will be keenly<br />
felt in his own country and abroad. There was scarcely an'area<br />
of our intellectual and artistic life that he did not adorn<br />
with his wisdom, his experience and with the singular<br />
warmth and force of his personality.<br />
I took special satisfaction from his appointment as<br />
Chairman of the Australian Broadcasting Commission in 1973,<br />
He brought remarkable tolerance and sensitivity to<br />
his guidance of the ABC and high liberal principles to the<br />
difficult area of program standards.<br />
For more than 20 years he was associated with the<br />
University of Melbourne as an academic economist and administrator.<br />
He was on the Boards of the National Gallery of Victoria<br />
and the Melbourne Theatre Company. He made a lasting<br />
contribution to the Arts as a member of the Australia Council.<br />
As an economist and social critic identified with the<br />
most enlightened causes, Richard Downing was in the great<br />
humane tradition of Keynes and Galbraith. I extend, on behalf<br />
of the Government, my deepest sympathy to his widow and<br />
family and express my personal sorrow in the loss sustained<br />
by his many friends and by all his countrymen.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T.-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
