<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9326</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING, MP EPAC NATIONAL STRATEGIES CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009326.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I E L<br />
PMM MINISTER 76194<br />
STATEtJEN 3Y THE I1" LIME MLNISTER, THE NION P. J. K( EATING, MP<br />
EAC NATIONAL STRATEGEES CONFERE~ NCE<br />
As part of the changes that I announced last week for EPAC, I indicated that I would<br />
ask the Economic Planning Advisory Commission to convene a major Conference on<br />
Long-Termn National Strategies to be held in Sydney on November 24-25.<br />
In my view, it is appropriate that we take stock of our national ambitions fromn time to<br />
time in a clear-sighted way beyond the immediate concerns of the day.<br />
Various strategic analyses have been prepared over the past year by major industry and<br />
community groups. The National Strategies Conference will offer the opportunity to<br />
assess these ideas and to canvass our national goals,<br />
Using the theme " shaping our future", the conference will seek to assist the<br />
government and others in developing medium and long-term economic and social<br />
policies, to look at their integration with environmental concerns, and to assist in the<br />
development of better social decision-making. The aim of the Conference is to provide<br />
guidance on the high priority issues for Australia as we move towards the 21 st century<br />
and beyond.<br />
I will be attending the Conference and look forward to benefiting from its<br />
deliberations. The Conference will provide an important occasion for the<br />
consideration of our national priorities. I have asked EPAC to ensure that the<br />
conference proceedings are made available to members of the public,<br />
NOTE: The Conference program is the responsibility of EPAC and details will be announced<br />
later this month once speakers have been finalised. Conference registration is being<br />
handled by AIC Conferences, on an invitation basis given the limnited space available.<br />
The EPAC contact officer is: Lynda Tin, Executive Manager, National Strategies<br />
Task Force, ( Tel: ( 06) 270 2471 or 270 2448; Fax: ( 06) 270 2442),<br />
The AIC contact officer is: Bryan de Caires, General Manager ( Tel: ( 02) 210 5700,<br />
Fax: ( 02) 223 8216).<br />
C ANBERRA<br />
22 August 1994 I22 LL.: H L19.' 94 1(: 6b~ No. U2b F. Ul/ Ul </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
