<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10236</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP 7.30 REPORT WITH KERRY O&#039;BRIEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/02/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010236.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
February 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
7.30 REPORT WITH KERRY O'BRIEN<br />
O'BRIEN: John Howard, this Work for the Dole scheme will be compulsory apparently for those<br />
in remote regions but voluntary for people in other regions. Why the difference?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
No, it would be compulsory in those areas either in the regions or closer into the big<br />
cities where the local group whose scheme has been accepted believes it can only work<br />
on a compulsory basis. In other cases it may be voluntary, but what we are going to<br />
do if necessary and I think it is, is to amend the law to enable the Government to<br />
require people to give some time in return for their benefit. It will be on the strict<br />
principle that award rates will be payable so nobody can argue there is exploitation,<br />
and it is really built on the notion of mutual obligations in a society we provide the<br />
safety net and people who receive the benefit of that can, on reasonable conditions<br />
and in certain circumstances, be asked to do something in return.<br />
O'BRIEN: According to reports today it seems that the pilot is consigned to regional Australia.<br />
Why not the big cities as well where of course youth unemployment is also in many<br />
areas of the big cities an intractable problem? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Pilots are going to be in areas of greatest or highest youth unemployment and I've<br />
used the expression regional and rural fairly loosely. I mean, for example, I would<br />
envisage that one of the pilots could well be in an area like Campbelltown which is on<br />
the outskirts of Sydney and some people would say it is regional, some people would<br />
say it is suburban Sydney and an area like Logan City on the southern outskirts of<br />
Brisbane where you also have a very high level of youth unemployment.<br />
O'BRIEN: You say that I think the work will be generated by local businesses and community<br />
groups. What sort of work would business generate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, we would be expecting local submissions from combinations of local business<br />
groups and community organisations. We would only certify as suitable those<br />
proposals which didn't involve the displacement of current workers. I mean, three<br />
examples that come to mind, and one I quoted on the weekend of people meeting<br />
newly arrived tourists in Australia; another example I know of where a group of people<br />
contributed the materials and the advice and the help to enable a group of young<br />
people to convert an old disused hotel into a new tourist attraction. I've known of<br />
examples of where local community groups can get together and provide a pattern of<br />
work and the experience involved for young people in helping the care of older<br />
members of the community in all sorts of ways.<br />
O'BRIEN: Did you consult with any community groups before announcing the scheme?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Before the actual announcement a few days ago, no. But I have over a long period of<br />
time talked to lots of community groups about the capacity to tackle problems in this<br />
way. O'BRIEN: One reason I ask is that we had a call today from the Australian Council of<br />
Volunteering an umbrella group of volunteer organisations, covering something like<br />
000 volunteers. They say that they are totally opposed to this, that you can't and<br />
this applies particularly to compulsory that you can't force anyone, whether they are<br />
16 or 60, to do volunteer work necessarily well and responsibly.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, they are entitled to their view. I don't agree that you can't have an element of<br />
compulsion in something like this. I mean, it is based on this principle of mutual </p>
<p>obligations in a society. We provide the safety net and we ask that people accept the<br />
responsibility on reasonable and fair terms. It should be seen as something that is<br />
separate from all the volunteer activities that go on at the present time because that in<br />
the main does not involve people who are on unemployment benefits. I mean, the<br />
great bulk of volunteers in our society at the present time are not on unemployment<br />
benefits and haven't been on unemployment benefits, so the notion that you don't mix<br />
up a work for the dole scheme and the day to day efforts of volunteers is something<br />
that I think should be kept in mind in responding to their comments.<br />
O'BRIEN: Although what you are saying is you are expecting that some of that work and it might<br />
for some be compulsory, that some of the work might be working in charity kind of<br />
work, care work for older people. If you have somebody doing meals on wheels and<br />
they were rather resentful of the fact that they had been compelled to do it<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, it would depend very much on the individual proposals and obviously we will<br />
make a judgment in relation to those sorts of things but there has always been a great<br />
reservoir of voluntarism in Australian society and it is one of our great characteristics<br />
as a community. This is something in a sense which is separate from that and I don't<br />
think the two of them should be mixed up.<br />
O'BRIEN: The big issue that remains of course is whether there will be a real job for these people<br />
at the end of their time on this work for the dole scheme, and on that point, when do<br />
you believe that unemployment will start to trend down?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I can't make a prediction about that. I've only been Prime Minister for I11 months.<br />
The Labor Party was in power for 13 and a half years and I'm not going to make any<br />
prediction at the present time. The promise I make is that I will do everything I can to<br />
get it down, certainly at the end of the work for the dole scheme young people will be<br />
better motivated, they won't have that sense of despondency and isolation and<br />
alienation that many of them have now, and I think if we can achieve that we will have<br />
achieved great things.<br />
O'BRIEN: Do you agree with your Cabinet colleague, Senator Vanstone, who said on this<br />
programme in September last year, that if you can't get the rate down by the next<br />
election, you won't win it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I would never give away an election, Kerry, you know that. </p>
<p>O'BRIEN: I do.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that's my answer.<br />
O'BRIEN: But the point is you are saying now I11 months is not long enough to make a fair<br />
judgment on your record. I assume you'll agree that three years...<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well I don't make any concessions about the next election, so let's make that clear.<br />
O'BRIEN: So if unemployment is still 8.5% or even above it, you don't think that that necessarily<br />
should count against you?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, Kerry, I hope that we will have it down, but I can't promise that. But the<br />
Australian people will make a judgment on all of my efforts and the efforts of my<br />
government and as always I will accept the judgment of the Australian people, but I<br />
don't give any electoral contest away ever.<br />
O'BRIEN: On that other issue floating around still, that is Bob Woods and also Michael Cobb the<br />
Coalition backbencher who is under police investigation that's two names that we<br />
know about. Without asking for further names, do you know whether any other<br />
Coalition MPs are being investigated or have been complained against?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, if I did know I couldn't say and I don't think anybody should get excited about<br />
that answer.<br />
O'BRIEN: I know you gave that answer this morning on AM. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, it is the right answer, and that's why I'm giving it again. I mean, I'm not going<br />
if the right answer this morning is the right answer tonight, it doesn't change...<br />
O'BRIEN: I can understand, I can understand why quite reasonably.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, Kerry, I'm asking you to accept that there's a long standing practice that<br />
Attorneys-General and Prime Ministers don't comment on intelligence and security<br />
matters and police investigations when they are not in the public domain.<br />
O'BRIEN: Okay. You've made your own credibility, your own personal integrity, an important I<br />
think foundation stone of your Government, and on that point I think cartoonists are<br />
supposed to reflect reasonably a kind of popular mood out there of how people are<br />
reacting to issues. Did you, on that point, did you see Tanberg's cartoon in the Sydney<br />
Morning Herald last Friday on the Woods issue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes, I'm reminded now of it.<br />
O'BRIEN: How did you react to that at the time when you saw it on the front page of the Herald?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Look, I have been in politics so long that I sort of take most of these in their stride. I<br />
think the cartoons in recent times that I have taken exception to are those that have<br />
suggested that I am in favour of overturning the Mabo decision and going back to<br />
Terra Nullius that is about as dishonest as you can get in political reporting because<br />
the one thing I've said in relation to the Wik judgment that won't be entertained, that<br />
is an overturning of the Mabo decision itself, but by and large I take the Tanberg<br />
cartoons which I think are very good in my stride.<br />
O'BRIEN:<br />
That one does encapsulate a point as to how many people have reacted, doesn't it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well that's your judgement, and Tanberg's. It's ultimately for the working out of the<br />
political process whether it's anybody else's judgement. </p>
<p>4, O'BRIEN: What we now know, since the Ray Martin interview, is that you were told about Bob<br />
Woods by your Attorney-General in September. We now know you were told about<br />
Michael Cobb in July or August. We also know that in October two other assistant<br />
Ministers of yours were forced to resign because of the Ministerial code. So, you were<br />
told of one in July, another in September, there were two other I suppose not totally<br />
removed instances in October and yet you completely forgot about Bob Woods?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I'm not quite sure what all of that proves. I've already you asked me a question...<br />
O'BRIEN: I'm trying to elaborate.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, I'm not quite sure of the point you're trying to make. The simple fact is that I<br />
was asked on Ray Martin whether I knew about the investigation. I made a totally<br />
truthful statement when I said that Woods had given me the details of it ten days<br />
earlier and that was in fact the first time he and I had discussed it. I had at that time<br />
honestly forgotten the first mention that Daryl Williams made to me of it some months<br />
earlier. Now if you can criticise me for having forgotten it I had no motive for saying<br />
that I had forgotten it if I hadn't in reality have forgotten it. In fact, the common<br />
sense, the last thing you'd try and cover up. I forgot it. Now if people are going to<br />
mark me down for that then so be it. I'm human. As soon as I ascertained that my<br />
recollection had been faulty, I did something about it.<br />
O'BRIEN: But how often do you get told by your Attorney General that one of your colleagues is<br />
under police investigation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well you can make that point and you've made it, and the Australian people will make<br />
a judgment as to whether I've been dishonest with them. I haven't, but I just wear the<br />
fact that I forgot something in an interview where naturally the more recent discussion<br />
that I'd had with Bob Woods was very fresh in my mind and I think it was a very<br />
honest error and I think most reasonable people would understand that, but if you<br />
don't, well, I have to accept that.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
