<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8691</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, HON P J KEATING MP, FORMER GERMAN CHANCELLOR WILL BRANDT</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008691.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VflimiV miVIUUicf 112/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RON P J KEATING, MP<br />
FORMER GERMAN CHANCELLOR WILLY BRANDT<br />
I have sent today the following condolence message to the<br />
German Chancellor on the occasion of the-death of former<br />
Chancellor Willy Brandt.<br />
I was greatly saddened to learn of the death. earlier<br />
today of Willy Brandt, former Chancellor of the Federal<br />
Republic of Germany.<br />
Willy Brandt was one of the leading European statesmen<br />
of the post-war period, Both as Chancellor and private<br />
citizen, Wlilly Brandt played an important role in<br />
Germany's period of post-war adjustment and<br />
reconciliation. He was widely recognised as a<br />
courageous fighter for democracy.<br />
His term as Chancellor marked a turning point in West<br />
Germany's relations with the former eastern bloc. His<br />
efforts Were accorded recognition in 1971 when he was<br />
awarded the Nobel Peace Prize.<br />
His concern for the people of the developing world<br />
showed him to be a leader of great humanity and<br />
compassion. He will be remembered as a statesman of great courage<br />
and foresight and a leader of his generation. On<br />
behalf of the Government and the people of Australia I<br />
would like to pass to you and to his family my<br />
condolences.<br />
CANBERRA 9 October 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
