<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5569</transcript-id>
    <title>RESIGNATION OF THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/04/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005569.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS WEDNESDAY 15 APRIL 1981<br />
RESIGNATION OF THE MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS<br />
Mr Peacock has today resigned from the Ministry, and I<br />
have accepted his resignation. I regret both his departure<br />
and the manner of his departure.<br />
Mr Peacock won wide regard as Minister for Foreign Affairs<br />
and keenly approached his job as Minister for Industrial<br />
Relations. The charges which Mr Peacock has made about me are totally<br />
false. There is no substance in Mr Peacock's allegation<br />
that I have allowed false and damaging reports to be<br />
published about him.<br />
I reject utterly the charge that I have sought to undermine<br />
Mr Peacock's authority while he was a Minister. I have<br />
engaged in no acts of disloyalty to Mr Peacock or to his<br />
Office. I reject also the attempt through choice of words<br />
to draw a parallel with an earlier situation.<br />
The allegation of reluctance to consult Cabinet is completely<br />
false. The policies of my Government are established in<br />
Cabinet discussion. These policies are binding on all<br />
Ministers, and Cabinet discussion and consultation has been<br />
a central feature of my Government throughout its entire<br />
office. The practices of Cabinet consultation and<br />
discussion have been consistently maintained throughout<br />
the period of my Government office.<br />
I am aware that the responsibilities of office can impose a<br />
heavy burden on Ministers and I have always sought as part<br />
of my responsibilities as head of Government to assist<br />
Ministers through difficult periods.<br />
I have done so with Mr Peacock in the past.<br />
This time Mr Peacock's feelings and his frustration in his<br />
Ministry have obviously become too strong. Those feelings<br />
received expression in the statement which he issued today<br />
when he announced his resignation.<br />
I wish to make it clear that it was never my intention to<br />
contribute to the strain which Mr Peacock so clearly felt.<br />
0000000o0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
