<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4741</transcript-id>
    <title>REMUNERATION TRIBUNAL REVIEW, 21 JUNE 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/06/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004741.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 21 JUNE 1978<br />
REMUNERATION TRIBUNAL REVIEW<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Fraser, announced today that Ministers<br />
would not accept the increases in Ministerial salary and<br />
allowances proposed in the Remuneration Tribunal's 1978 Review.<br />
When the Parliament resumes in August, the Government will move<br />
for the disallowance of the Tribunal's Determinations Nos. 6 and 7<br />
which provided for increases in the special allowance and<br />
travelling allowance of Ministers, and in the salary, special<br />
allowances, and travelling allowance of office holders of the<br />
Parliament. The Government will also not proceed with implementation of the<br />
Tribunal's Report No. 1, which proposed increases in Ministerial<br />
salaries.<br />
Mr Fraser said that Ministers felt strongly that they should be<br />
setting an example of restraint to the community.<br />
In its submission to the Tribunal the Government had emphasised<br />
that it considered there should be no salary increases for<br />
persons within the Tribunal's jurisdiction, stating its<br />
belief that such offices are appropriate areas for establishing<br />
an example of restraint.<br />
It had pointed out to the Tribunal that the Government's overall<br />
commitment to wage restraint had formed the basis of its submission<br />
to National Wage/ Indexation hearings, when it had opposed any<br />
rise in award wages.. If, however, the Tribunal did not accept<br />
the Government's argument, the Government suggested there should<br />
not be any increase greater than that applying from a " flow on"<br />
of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission decisions to those<br />
office holders who had not received any increases since last year.<br />
Regrettably, the Tribunal had-not accepted the thrust of the<br />
Governnent' s argument.<br />
Mr Fraser said, however, that the Government was prepared to abide<br />
by the Tribunal's other findings. This would allow all Senators<br />
and Members to receive salary increases based on national wage<br />
case decisions which had already been received by other wage and<br />
salary earners. Senior public servants and statutory office<br />
holders were in a similar position. The Tribunal's recommendations<br />
in respect of Judges would be accepted. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
