<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>795</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES, KT, CH, QC, MP ON APPROPRIATION BILL 1963-64 - SECOND READING</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/08/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000795_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
D SPEECH BY<br />
Rt. Hon. Sir ROBERT MENZIES,<br />
D M. P<br />
ON<br />
I DAPPROPRIATION BILL 1963-64.<br />
Second Reading.<br />
( BUDGET DEBATE.)<br />
[ From the " Parliamentary Debates," 27th August, 1963.]<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES '( Kooyong-<br />
Prime Minister) [ 8.341.-Mr. Speaker, my<br />
purpose to-night is to deal with the amendment<br />
to the motion for the second reading<br />
of this bill submitted by the Leader of the<br />
Opposition ( Mr.' Caiwell), which constitutes<br />
a motion of no confidence in the Government.<br />
After all, as we have already indicated,<br />
that-exposes the Government at once<br />
to the risk of defeat. Therefore, it is proper<br />
that I deal with the matter. In order to<br />
remove any anxieties, perhaps I should make<br />
it quite clear that we-propose to vote against<br />
the amendment. I think that is fair enough.<br />
8444/ 63. I do not propose, Sir, to duplicate what<br />
has been said already-and said very wellby<br />
a number of honorable members on my<br />
side of the House. I would like to begin<br />
quietly, as I hope to continue, by mentioning<br />
that one of the remarkable things about<br />
my distinguished opponent's speech was that<br />
two of the Opposition's earlier cries were<br />
-abandoned. It is worth recording them so<br />
as to accord them, as it were, the proper<br />
o~ bsequies. First of all, we were accustomed<br />
over quite a period to being told by the<br />
Opposition that we had ruined the loan<br />
inarket. , That is very interesting. When the </p>
<p>loan market was a little sluggish, the Opposition<br />
explained that this was due to want<br />
of confidence in the Government. This<br />
capacity on the part of the Opposition,<br />
driven desperately by so many years in the<br />
wilderness, to have a bit each way fascinates<br />
me. The Opposition said that we had<br />
ruined the loan market. Now, it has to<br />
concede that the loan market was never<br />
heavier, never more successful. Opposition<br />
members said that they would restore the<br />
loan market by lower interest rates. We<br />
did that. We restored the loan market and<br />
then we reduced the long-term bond rate.<br />
And the loan market still was tremendously<br />
healthy. All I can hope is that the subscribers<br />
to Commonwealth loans issued on<br />
behalf of the States will continue to express<br />
their discontent with the Government in the<br />
same fashion.<br />
The second allegation that is worthy of<br />
passing thought, Sir, is that by dropping<br />
import licensing we imperilled our overseas<br />
balances. I remember listening in this<br />
House time after time to Labour leadershonorable<br />
members opposite have never had<br />
fewer than three or four at a time-saying,<br />
Look at the overseas balances you<br />
inherited from us and see how ' they have<br />
fallen When we got rid of import licensing<br />
for all practical purposes, we were told<br />
that we had taken the opportunity to destroy<br />
our overseas balances. At 30th June, the<br />
overseas balances of this country stood at<br />
œ E626,000,000 of gold and foreign exchange,<br />
plus an International Monetary Fund drawing<br />
right of 223,000,000. If this be the<br />
ruination of our overseas funds, we must<br />
have the dictionary re-written.<br />
11 just mention those things very quietly,<br />
Sir, because I think that, in order to observe<br />
continuity in politics, some of those who<br />
were not here at the time ought to know<br />
the kind of things that have been said by<br />
their leaders. I now pass on from that. I<br />
know that some of the things I shall say<br />
have already been said extremely well, but<br />
I just want to make my own speech on this<br />
subject as head of the Government that is<br />
under censure.<br />
Time after time in his speech, the Leader<br />
of the opposition made allegations of dishonesty.<br />
This is one of his favourite words.<br />
When I hear it from him, I take it seriously.<br />
if I heard it from somebody else, I would<br />
ignore it. We heard from the honorable gentleman repeated allegations of dishonesty.<br />
Yet the central allegation that appeared<br />
time after time in his speech was itse'<br />
completely dishonest. That allegation wa.<br />
that my colleague, the Treasurer ( Mr.<br />
Harold Holt), speaking on behalf of the<br />
Government, proposes a deficit of<br />
œ 300,000,000 and that this deficit-he kept<br />
on repeating it-contains the seeds of inifl<br />
tion. That statement was clearly, de,.<br />
liberately, repeatedly and grossly dishonest.<br />
We might as well have the facts out on<br />
this. He is not going to accuse us of dishonesty<br />
and escape from these perfectly<br />
clear statements about his own attack. I<br />
will come back to this in a moment and<br />
demonstrate -it, chapter and verse, but,<br />
before I do that, let me just continue with<br />
these rather agreeable, pleasant rzemarks.<br />
It is only a few months ago that the<br />
Leader of the Opposition was preaching depression<br />
and stagnation. All of us w<br />
were here remember that, do we noFt<br />
spoke about these things so yearningly that<br />
I almost believed he wanted them. Perhaps<br />
he did. He spoke about depression and<br />
stagnation. Now he invents a œ 300,000, OQ.<br />
deficit with, as he pointed out, increase<br />
expenditure but no increased taxation,<br />
he says now-or he did the other daythat<br />
this means a period of boom and bust.<br />
I use his own somewhat sculptural expression.<br />
To meet this, he wants largely increased<br />
expenditure to increase basic<br />
demand. That is what he called it. Apart<br />
from altering the graph of income tax to<br />
increase the burden upon those earning over<br />
œ 1,200 a year, which is the average wage<br />
earning of to-day--will say something<br />
about that in a moment because I want to<br />
keep the best till the last-he wants to reduce<br />
revenues from pay-roll tax, from petrol tax<br />
-1 need not go through the whole listbut<br />
he would increase expenditure on homes,<br />
on education, on defence and on northern<br />
development. This is a curious thing. He<br />
says this is a policy of boom and bust, that<br />
we are in for a deficit of œ 300,000,000,<br />
which he knows is completely untrue and<br />
which the Treasurer made it perfectly clear<br />
was untrue.<br />
Having said that, what does he do about<br />
it? If this contains the seeds of inflation,<br />
then obviously the revenues ought to be up,<br />
and, or, the expenditures ought to be down;<br />
because he finds in a deficit of œ 300,000,000<br />
all the seeds of inflation. What is his cure? </p>
<p>It is to increase the expenditures and reduce<br />
the revenues. Sir, this is almost incredible.<br />
.\ am perfectly certain . that if all the electors<br />
Australia could hear this statement, and<br />
think about it, they would refuse to entrust<br />
their fortunes to a prospective Prime Minister<br />
with these astonishing ideas.<br />
Before I pass on from that, I want to say<br />
7 word about what he proposes to do about<br />
-defence. He wants more money spent on<br />
defence. I took an extract from his speech,<br />
and I propose to read it out. This is a<br />
puzzle. Even a quiz competitor might be<br />
hard put to it to explain this-<br />
We will not pretend,-<br />
said the honorable gentlemanas<br />
this Government does, that the national interest<br />
is served by a system of down payments on the<br />
instalment plan for weapons and equipment which<br />
may be delivered anything from one to five years<br />
hence and which, when delivered, are obsolete or<br />
obsolescent.<br />
7rihis statement caught my ear at once. I<br />
asked myself: " What does the Leader of<br />
the Opposition mean by that? Has he discovered<br />
some profound means by which<br />
you can go and buy the latest weapons and<br />
"" he latest aircraft off the hook? If he has,<br />
-J would appeal to him as a somewhat<br />
occulting friend of mine to tell me the<br />
secret. Oh," he says, " you must not buy<br />
them on down payments; you must not buy<br />
them on the instalment plan Is he really<br />
innocent enough to think that you can get<br />
a' replacement fighter or a replacement<br />
bomber or a reconnaissance plane by going<br />
along to a shop and buying it? That, I<br />
thought, of all the things he said, was the<br />
most fantastic. Having looked at it, I concluded<br />
that, as he has a rather attractive<br />
sense of humour from time -to time, I must<br />
regard this as a sort of beau geste on his<br />
part. To sum all that up, let us put it in<br />
this way: His cure, and therefore presumably<br />
the cure of his party, for a boom is<br />
to have a bigger one, and the right way to<br />
avoid worrying about a bust is to make it a<br />
stone certainty.<br />
Now let me come back to this famous<br />
œ 300,000,000 deficit. I ask all honorable<br />
members to think about it quite seriously.<br />
If the honorable gentleman knows anything<br />
about these matters-and he should by now<br />
-he knows that the estimated cash deficit<br />
is œ 58,000,000, and he knows that, on all<br />
former occasions, acting on the old system of presenting the accounts in terms of cash<br />
results, this is a substantial deficit, th6ughi<br />
not the biggest one that we have ever<br />
budgeted for. The Treasurer explained this,<br />
I thought, in the simplest terms, and, of<br />
course, the figures establish it.<br />
In past years--and I say this for the oenefit<br />
of anybody who may not have followed<br />
these rather recondite Treasury problems,<br />
although the honorable gentleman opposite,<br />
of course, is familiar with them-revenue<br />
and loan items have been added together,<br />
revenue and loan or capital expenditures<br />
have been added together, we have subtracted<br />
one from the other and a cash result<br />
has been brought out. Under that system<br />
we determined that the cash deficit would<br />
be X or Y or Z. This year, we happen to<br />
have adopted the system which has applied<br />
-I think I am ' right, Mr. Treasurer-for a<br />
long time in Great Britain, where all of<br />
what we call the revenue and expenditure<br />
items are put above -the line and the capital<br />
items below the line. Adopting that<br />
system and assuming that we do not borrow<br />
a shilling on behalf of the States, there is a<br />
deficiency of œ 358,000,000. But because<br />
we know that, on behalf of the States, we<br />
will borrow large sums of money from the<br />
-public on the loan market, we make an<br />
estimate of the amount involved. The<br />
Treasurer estimated it-he cannot be precise<br />
at this stage-at œ 300,000,000. So you<br />
have a deficit of œ 358,000,000. You set off<br />
against that the œ 300,000,000 which you<br />
anticipate borrowing from the public-all<br />
on behalf of the States, mark you-and the<br />
deficit in cash of œ 58,000,000. The Leader of<br />
the Opposition knows that. It was explained<br />
with the utmost clarity in the Budget speech.<br />
Why does he now seek to deceive the public<br />
by talking about a record deficit of<br />
œ 300,000,000? That he has set out to<br />
deceive the public appears from his own<br />
speech. It is sometimes useful to quote<br />
your opponent, so I will weary the House<br />
by reading two or three passages from his<br />
speech. He said-<br />
Thus, we have the spectacle of a Treasurer who<br />
poured ridicule on the Opposition" s policy, in<br />
1961, of running a deficit of œ 100,000,000--<br />
Labour proposed a cash deficit of<br />
œ 100,000,000 in four or five months, which<br />
was equal to œ 300,000,000 in a yearhimself<br />
proposing a deficit of mote than<br />
œ 300,000,000 nearly three years later when, as far </p>
<p>as he is concerned, the unemployment problem<br />
has been solved.<br />
Here is a deliberate falsification. Here is a<br />
comparison of a cash deficit of œ 100,000,000<br />
and the œ 300,000,000 deficit in this Budget,<br />
which represents a cash deficit of only<br />
œ 58,000,000. The people of Australia<br />
deserve better treatment than that. They<br />
do not deserve to be deceived in this<br />
fashion. Plunging further, the honorable<br />
gentleman went on to say-<br />
In our view, this increase of over œ 200,000,000<br />
represents the cumulative results of the disastrous<br />
policy of too little too late--<br />
The honorable gentleman is a master of the<br />
clichewhic' he has followed ever since he and his<br />
Government destroyed full employment and business<br />
activity in November, 1960.<br />
I hope it is clear to all who are listening<br />
to me that here is a comparison between<br />
two utterly different things. But the honorable<br />
gentleman went on and stated-<br />
And yet, in what is claimed to be a propitious<br />
situation, the estimated budget deficit is the<br />
greatest on record.<br />
He knows that to be untrue, but although<br />
he knows that he says-<br />
Let me repeat. It is three times more than<br />
that contained in Labour's policy speech<br />
If the Treasurer's diagnosis is correct, then he is<br />
being highly irresponsible. He is imperilling price<br />
and cost stability because he lacks the courage--<br />
Let me repeat for the benefit of all concerned<br />
that I am quoting the words of the<br />
Leader of the Labour Partyto<br />
raise taxes to at least match the extra expenditure<br />
he is budgeting for.<br />
I say no more about that. I regard this as<br />
a rather unsavoury episode and I apologize<br />
for having had to take up so much time to<br />
expose it.<br />
I will go on with the author-if he is the<br />
author-of the motion of no confidence in<br />
the Government. He might say that this<br />
will be my last speech as Prime Minister.<br />
No doubt that is the expectation and therefore<br />
I must deal with these matters. He<br />
turned his attention to taxation. He said that<br />
he would reconstruct the income tax system<br />
to help the man receiving less than œ 24 a<br />
week: I imagine from what he said that<br />
he would like to save the man earning less<br />
than œ 24 a week 5s. a week in tax. I point<br />
out to honorable members that even that<br />
saving would increase the tax paid by those<br />
receiving more than œ 24 a week by an average of almost 10 per cent. I do not<br />
think the honorable gentleman, or those<br />
who advise him, has ever worked out th:-'<br />
problem to discover how the break-up L<br />
taxation in Australia occurs. There would<br />
be an average increase of about 10 per cent.<br />
The honorable gentleman might say,<br />
Those who are receiving œ 26, œ 28, œ 30 or<br />
œ 40 a week naturally would be required tI<br />
pay only a nominal increase I wonder<br />
what he would do when he reached those<br />
income brackets upon which we rely so<br />
much for investment and development in<br />
Australia! He has not told us.<br />
Then, hoping to strengthen his imperfect<br />
story-the one on which we are to be<br />
thrown out of office-the honorable gentleman<br />
mentioned direct and indirect taxation.<br />
He set out to convey the impression that<br />
under my Government there was ' a trend to<br />
increase indirect taxes and to reduce direc'<br />
taxes. The honorable gentleman said, ThL<br />
Labour Party when it comes to office" or<br />
" if it comes to office have forgotten<br />
which he said-" will reverse the trend towards<br />
indirect taxes This is a beautiful<br />
old argument. I have heard it all m,<br />
political life. It is said that the hard shell--<br />
tories or whatever we are called are the<br />
boys who want to pile on the indirect taxes<br />
because the ordinary fellow, the wageearner,<br />
has to pay them, and they cut down<br />
direct taxes, income tax ' and the like,<br />
because the silver-tails will -get some benefit.<br />
If the honorable gentleman wants a short<br />
course in political history he might direct<br />
himself to the facts. In 1948-49 he was a<br />
Minister in the last Labour government.<br />
Perhaps I could have said the latest Labour<br />
government, but I will call it the last. At<br />
that time Labour was the master of all it<br />
surveyed. It had a handsome majority in<br />
the House of Representatives and a handsome<br />
majority-at least a large one-in the<br />
Senate. In 1948-49 direct taxes in Australia<br />
were 56.6 per cent. of total taxes. Would<br />
honorable members be good enough to carry<br />
that figure in their minds? When we came<br />
into office-about half-way through the<br />
financial year 1949-50 and after the Budget<br />
had been established-the proportion was<br />
55.2 per cent. In 1961-62 the trend about<br />
which the honorable gentleman ! has complained<br />
had been so reversed under my<br />
Government that the proportion of direct </p>
<p>taxes had risen from 55.2 per cent, of total<br />
taxes to 59.9 per cent. In the financial year<br />
"' vered by this Budget it is 59.5 per cent.<br />
_ a it be well understood that under this<br />
Liberal-Country Party Administration the<br />
percentage of direct taxation has increased.<br />
It has not fallen. The honorable gentleman,<br />
having thought that he had something<br />
-) complain about, now finds that the boot<br />
ø on the other foot.<br />
I pass from that. The Leader of the<br />
Opposition has a thesis which, with great<br />
respect to him, is self-contradictory. In<br />
one breath he says that the Budget is potentially<br />
inflationary. His own expression was<br />
that it contained the seeds of inflation<br />
because there was a huge deficit. In the<br />
next breath he says that the Budget, although<br />
potentially inflationary, will fail to restore<br />
a strong basic demand. With great respect,<br />
I say that he cannot be right both ways. If<br />
~ is right in thinking that the Budget is<br />
ationary, then, of course, demand will<br />
expand excessively in relation to supply.<br />
But if what he calls basic consumer demand<br />
lags, then there can be no inflation unless,<br />
of course, there is some cost inflation by<br />
raising of costs in spite of the relative<br />
Ability, or the almost absolute stability, of<br />
the consumer price index.<br />
Then he went on to say that nothing has<br />
been done to restore the purchasing power<br />
of ordinary people. This is a time-honoured<br />
argument. I am happy to say that we have<br />
been put into office and kept in office for a<br />
long time by ordinary people-and ordinary<br />
people who are not fools. Let us have a<br />
look at the facts again. I apologize if I am<br />
repeating things infinitely well known to<br />
honorable members, but they deserve to be<br />
brought together. Just now I mentioned<br />
the consumer price index which is the most<br />
modern index of what I will call the cost<br />
of living. -It rose by 0.2 per cent.-that is<br />
a negligible fraction of a fraction-last year.<br />
But the wages and salaries paid in Australia<br />
in this time of terrible depression increased<br />
by œ 210,000,000, or 6 per cent., compared<br />
with 2 per cent. in the previous year. This<br />
is worth noting. In the March quarter<br />
of this year, with a stable consumer price<br />
index figure, average weekly earnings<br />
increased by 2.5 per cent.-in one quarter.<br />
These are not my figures; these are the<br />
figures of the Commonwealth Statistician<br />
who stands outside controversy and outside<br />
bias. The gross national product-rose. in<br />
1962-63-the last financial year which<br />
finished on 30th June-by 8 per cent. The<br />
consumer price index was static. The gross<br />
national expenditure-that is to say, the<br />
total market value of goods and services<br />
bought for use in the Australian economy<br />
-increased by œ 752,000,000,. or 10 per<br />
cent., in a dead year. Remember that I said<br />
the honorable gentleman talked about<br />
restoring consumer demand. Here you<br />
have the gross national expenditure rising by<br />
10 per cent., with the cost-price level<br />
reflected in the consumer price index<br />
remaining stable. Personal consumption<br />
rose by: œ 245,000,000, or 5 per cent. Private<br />
fixed capital expenditure rose by 13 per<br />
cent., including an 8 per cent. increase on<br />
dwellings, and was 4 per cent, higher than<br />
any previous rise in our history. We all<br />
ought to be crying ourselves to sleep when<br />
we contemplate these figures. The number<br />
of houses and flats approved in July this<br />
year was 9,465; in the same month last year<br />
the number was 8,200; and in July the previous<br />
year the number was 7,000. This is<br />
a tremendous symptom of development.<br />
Since honorable gentlemen ' opposite<br />
ohoose to concentrate their fire on the<br />
question of employment of people, I point<br />
out that in the last financial year the total<br />
numbers actively employed in Australia rose<br />
by 100,000. This is where we all are supposed<br />
to get down and weep and persuade<br />
people that misery is on hand, that disaster<br />
is about us and that there is a sluggish<br />
economy. But, of course, I am wrong. I<br />
apologize to the Leader of the Opposition<br />
because, although I have dealt with one of<br />
his remarks-that there is a sluggish<br />
economy-I am bound to say that on the<br />
other hand he had a saving bet on the seeds<br />
of inflation. I leave it to him.<br />
I want to turn away from that and say<br />
something very briefly about northern<br />
development. I would have said more<br />
about this, perhaps, if it were not for the<br />
fact that my colleague, the Minister for<br />
Territories ( Mr. Hasluck), in the course of<br />
this debate, made what I venture to describe<br />
as an extremely brilliant speech on this<br />
matter-a speech which I hope will be read<br />
and circulated very widely in this country.<br />
I gather that the Opposition wants a committee<br />
or a commission. Before we came<br />
into' office, the Labour Party established a </p>
<p>committee of Ministers from the Commonwealth,<br />
Queensland and Western Australia,<br />
with a committee of officials, to have a look<br />
at these matters. I have noticed that there<br />
has been some controversy on some television<br />
session; but I have made inquiries<br />
from impartial people as to the records in<br />
my own department. I find that the committee<br />
of Ministers last met in 1947 and<br />
that the committee of officials last met in<br />
February, 1948. After all, we did not come<br />
in till 19th December, 1949. What came<br />
of it? They thought it was a good idea. It<br />
might very well have been one. I do not<br />
discuss it. But what came of it, apart from<br />
tax zoning? If I give that in, what came<br />
of it? I do not know.<br />
We have gone about northern development<br />
in a practical way. We have collaborated<br />
with the Queensland and Western<br />
Australian governments and with private<br />
enterprise. By so doing we have helped in<br />
the most spectacular and valuable northern<br />
development in our history. In discussions<br />
of this kind projects have been selected.<br />
They have been selected by governments.<br />
After all, governments have the responsibility<br />
of performance; do not forget that.<br />
These projects have been discussed by<br />
governments as priority matters calculated<br />
to improve Australian commodity trade<br />
balances, to increase exports and to save<br />
imports. It is a pretty practical and effective<br />
system, Sir, which produces in our own<br />
time the great mineral developments, cattle<br />
roads development, water storage, irrigation,<br />
railway works in the north and so on.<br />
I will not bother about giving an<br />
exhaustive list of these things.<br />
Mr. O'Brien.-Oil.<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-Yes, oil.<br />
Mr. O'Brien.-You put it there, did you?<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-No, but we<br />
did what you did not do; we gave material<br />
help in the search for it. All I need to say<br />
because i am not going to repeat what<br />
has been said by my colleague-is: What<br />
do the people want-committees or results?<br />
I want to talk about my last topic with<br />
some particularity because it has been the<br />
subject of a very intensive campaign. The<br />
newspapers of 19th August contained an<br />
advertisement published by the Victorian Teachers Union of 22,000 teachers. It is<br />
very much in line with some of the things<br />
that I have heard from teachers in t)'<br />
House. I would like to read the advertis.<br />
ment. It is always a risk to do these things,<br />
but I will accept the risk. This is a large<br />
and costly advertisement and it contains<br />
explicitly and implicitly allegations which I<br />
propose to deal with and to denounce. I<br />
there be no mistake about this. Tvl<br />
advertisement reads-<br />
In 1945 Mr. R. G. Menzies, speaking in Parliament<br />
on the problems of State schools--<br />
This is 1945 when a Labour government<br />
was in office and I was Leader of the<br />
Oppositionsaid-And I am quoted in bits-<br />
" The Commonwealth must in my opinion give<br />
aid to the States. Whatever State Ministers<br />
of Education may say about what they would,<br />
like to do, there is a sharp limit to tb'<br />
resources." Now, after fourteen years of offi,<br />
Sir Robert Menzies-<br />
I was promoted in the meantimehas<br />
yet to fulfil this promise. The situation in<br />
the State schools has become far more serious,<br />
yet they still do not receive any Federal A'<br />
whatsoever. This aid is essential-to provide a,<br />
quate classrooms, equipment and playgrounds, to<br />
reduce the size of classes and to increase the<br />
number-To increase the number mind youof<br />
trained teachers. Yet Mr. Holt's<br />
Budget gave no direct aid to State primary,<br />
secondary and technical schools.<br />
Leave the Treasurer out of it for the<br />
moment; this is mostly about me-<br />
The schools need more money. Your children's<br />
future depends on it.<br />
That is signed " A public statement in education<br />
week from the Victorian Teachers<br />
Union of 22,000 teachers The reference<br />
to 22,000 teachers has a slight suggestion<br />
of pressure about it. Speaking for myself,<br />
I can resist nothing as well as that kind of<br />
pressure. I hesitate to believe that that advertisement<br />
represented the views of very many<br />
of the Victorian teachers.<br />
Mr. Barnard.-You should have been at<br />
the conference in Melbourne.<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-I know all<br />
about that. I know that the honorable<br />
member is a teacher. I understand his<br />
point of view. But I am speaking here </p>
<p>to-night as a man who has done more for<br />
education than any other Prime Minister<br />
the history of this country. The<br />
lctorian Teachers Union advertisement<br />
quoted what I said in 1945-a time when<br />
a . Labour government gave tax reimbursements<br />
to the States amounting in total to<br />
,34,800,000. That same government con-<br />
) ued in office for some years but made<br />
. provision in its budgets to subsidize or<br />
to underwrite State loan raisings, which<br />
were, incidentally, among other things for<br />
school buildings. Not a penny!<br />
Mr. Reynolds.-There was no need to<br />
underwrite them.<br />
Sir ROBERT MENZIES.-You are talking<br />
about fairly small matters. The tax<br />
reimbursement to the States was<br />
œ 34,800,000 but the fact is-and you cansqueak<br />
your way out of it-that at that<br />
_-Ane and until we came into office not one<br />
shilling was found out of . the Commonwealth<br />
Budget to supplement -loan raisings<br />
for the States'. programmes, including their<br />
programmes of works for education. Also,<br />
was a period in which the Common-<br />
_, ealth Government made no special grants<br />
to the States for universities or teaching<br />
hospitals. What is the position to-day. I want to<br />
say this as one who is supposed to have<br />
forsworn what he said in 1945: The tax<br />
reimbursement to the States, as even honorable<br />
members opposite must know,<br />
materially enables the States to pay their<br />
running education costs because it includes<br />
a calculation for growing population. The<br />
tax reimbursement has increased from<br />
œ 34,800,000 in 1945 to œ 318,400,000. That<br />
is something worth thinking about-an<br />
increase from œ 34,000,000 to œ 318,000,000<br />
under our Government. The tax reimbursement<br />
is now called financial assistance<br />
grant, but it is the same thing. The effect<br />
of this generous treatment of the States in<br />
revenue and loans-it was generous; it went<br />
beyond any formula that had ever been<br />
devised in the time of the Labour Government-<br />
has been that whereas the States<br />
spent on education in 1950-51, just after<br />
we came to power, an amount of<br />
œ 46,000,000, in 1960-61 they spent<br />
œ 184,000,000, and I would think that this<br />
year they will spend something more than œ 200,000,000. That . represents ; an enormous<br />
increase. Sir, it is a very strange performance for<br />
a teachers' -spokesman to assume that . Commonwealth<br />
. payments to the . States : contain<br />
no education aid. All along ,. we : have<br />
exceeded the Chifley formula -by supplementary<br />
grants. In 1959 when -my colleagues<br />
the Deputy Prime Minister ( Mr.<br />
McEwen) and the Treasurer were . at the<br />
Australian Loan Council and the Premiers'<br />
Conference we agreed to a greatly<br />
liberalized formula, and an important factor<br />
in all this was population and, therefore,<br />
school needs. Over the past thirteen years<br />
we have provided something that was aiever<br />
provided before in the time of the Labour<br />
government. ' We have provided . a grand<br />
total of œ 801,000,000 for State loan works<br />
over and above actual loan raisings. In<br />
1945 such assistance was unknown. I<br />
repeat: Over a period of thirteen years we<br />
have provided œ 801,000,000. I say without<br />
any fear whatever that but for those<br />
actions on our part State expenditure on<br />
schools and school equipment would have<br />
been immeasurably less than it was. Yet<br />
I am to be told that we have done nothing.<br />
I can understand some people who are not<br />
fully aware of these matters falling into the<br />
error of repeating that falsehood, but I can<br />
neither understand nor forgive people who<br />
know about them who will repeat it.<br />
Our performance in relation to universities<br />
is well known. I will not rehearse it.<br />
When I originally spoke about this matter<br />
. in the House and -announced that the<br />
Government would adopt the Murray ' com-<br />
ø mittee's report our action was hailed by the<br />
then Leader of the Opposition as munificent<br />
-those were his very words-and indeed,<br />
so it was, and it was proper.-The setting<br />
up of the Murray committee, the adoption<br />
of its report, the application of that report<br />
to the Australian Universities Commission,<br />
the introduction of a system of triennial<br />
grants, the inclusion of teaching hospitals<br />
-a very great development-the establishment<br />
of the tertiary education committee,<br />
which is now sitting and which I hope will<br />
report before long and which includes in<br />
. its scope all tertiary forms of training,<br />
including technological training-all these<br />
things we have done, but according to the<br />
advertisement we have done nothing. I<br />
must have misunderstood English when I<br />
was taught it at school. </p>
<p>The-Premiers had an extraordinary conference<br />
in February, 1963. On that occasion<br />
the Premier of New South Wales, Mr.<br />
Hefron, a man whose interest in education<br />
and service to its cause I tremendously<br />
admire-he has done a great deal for education-<br />
submitted a proposition once more<br />
that a special grant, not part of the general<br />
grant to -the States, should be earmarked<br />
for education and that a special inquiry<br />
should be held. The Acting Premier of<br />
Victoria, at that conference, said that what<br />
Victoria wanted was general assistance to<br />
the State budget so that-I quote his<br />
words-" we can retain the right to control<br />
education within our own budget".<br />
Mr.. Pizzey, of Queensland, a greatly<br />
respected member of the Queensland Government,<br />
agreed. He said, " We do not<br />
favour a special grant Sir Thomas<br />
Playford agreed. My old friend does not<br />
always agree. But he agreed on this<br />
occasion. The Premier of Western Australia<br />
repeated that whatever provision<br />
there was should be a part of the general<br />
grant. That was the state of mind of<br />
the clear majority of the Premiers.<br />
I have been speaking about the meeting in<br />
February, 1963. Then there was a normal<br />
meeting in June' of this year, when my two<br />
colleagues were present and I was out of<br />
the country-perhaps fortunately, but I<br />
do not know. My colleagues made an<br />
arrangement with the States for substantial<br />
increases in the provision to the States.<br />
Mark you, Mr. Speaker, this was done<br />
after the education discussion in February,<br />
1963, with the Premiers. They had said<br />
then, when this matter was very much in<br />
their minds, " We want a little more on<br />
our general grants so that we can cope<br />
with the problem, of State education"<br />
Later substantial increases were made.<br />
The financial assistance grants to the<br />
States were increased by œ 14,000,000. I<br />
will just give the actual increase. Considering<br />
that these grants had risen before,<br />
this was a big sum. The grants to the<br />
two claimant States went up by œ 200,000.<br />
That is nothing much. The additional<br />
assistance grants, which were special, went up by œ 2,500,000. There was other<br />
assistance of a revenue nature which went<br />
up by œ 1,700,000. The States works a'<br />
housing allocation went up by œ 17,000, L,,,<br />
and other assistance of a capital nature<br />
went up by œ 6,300,000. These two later<br />
items add up to œ 23,300,000 in one year,<br />
and if the first group I gave is added the<br />
total relevant improvement in the positi<br />
of the States in one year was œ 41,700,00i,:<br />
I have not included any federal aid roads<br />
grants or anything of that kind. Some<br />
of this œ 41,700,000 would include provision<br />
for schools and equipment, because<br />
the education votes of the States have<br />
become so large.<br />
The only other thing I want to say is<br />
by way of confirming what I have just<br />
said. Under present arrangements-all<br />
made since my 1945 speech and sinc,<br />
the 1949 election-the States have be,<br />
able to quadruple their expenditure on<br />
education. The proportion of their capital<br />
expenditure devoted to educational purposes,<br />
such as school buildings, rose from<br />
6 per cent. in 1949 to ' 20 per cent. j-<br />
1961-62. It is probably a little mo<br />
now. There was a reference in the'<br />
advertisements to teachers. In 1951, in<br />
government schools, there were 36,000<br />
full-time teachers and there were sixteen<br />
teachers' colleges. In 1961, after this socalled<br />
miserable default of mine in relation<br />
to education, there, were not 36,000<br />
full-time teachers by 63,700. There were<br />
19,000 teachers in training and instead<br />
of sixteen teachers' colleges there were 28.<br />
This, I venture to say, could be better.<br />
Everything could be better. But there is<br />
no case for a condemnation of our<br />
approach. On the contrary, there is conclusive<br />
proof that we have responded<br />
actively to the claims of education-claims<br />
which I profess to understand as well as<br />
any other man in this place.<br />
I conclude by saying that this advertised<br />
propaganda is badly informed, is<br />
inaccurate and, what is worse, is grossly<br />
unfair.<br />
By Authority: A. J. ARTHUR, Commonwealth Government Printer, Canberra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
