<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11123</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   PRESS CONFERENCE                 PRIME MINISTER&amp;#146;S COURTYARD, PARLIAMENT HOUSE                                                   </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: GST Bill, Democrats' leadership spill, Constitutional</p>
<p> preamble, Oakdale miners, business tax, John Ralph Report,</p>
<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, I've called this news conference</p>
<p> to say how very pleased I am that the committee stage of the debate</p>
<p> in the Senate relating to the main GST bill has now been completed.</p>
<p> And I'm delighted to note that all of the Government amendments</p>
<p> supported by the Australian Democrats have been accepted by the Senate,</p>
<p> amendments moved by the Labor Party and the Greens have been rejected.</p>
<p> This is a major step towards a new taxation system for Australia.</p>
<p>I thank the Australian Democrats and most particularly their Leader,</p>
<p> Senator Lees, for their support, for her leadership in relation to</p>
<p> that support. I also very warmly thank my Senate colleagues, and I'll</p>
<p> have an opportunity of doing so again next week, for their stewardship</p>
<p> of what has turned out to be a marathon debate. It's worth noting</p>
<p> that when you add in the Senate Committee hearings, this issue has</p>
<p> been under almost continuous debate and discussion now for a period</p>
<p> of six or seven months.</p>
<p>But the important thing is that today we are a giant step closer to</p>
<p> realising the goal the Government has set itself now for almost two</p>
<p> years, and that is to achieve a modern, reformed, revitalised taxation</p>
<p> system, fairer, more efficient and providing much more incentive for</p>
<p> the Australian community. And I look forward to the further votes</p>
<p> in the Senate on Monday. And if they go, as we hope they will, the</p>
<p> return of that legislation to the House of Representatives on Monday</p>
<p> evening for final acceptance by the Parliament of the plan I announced</p>
<p> to the people in September of 1998, which will give this nation in</p>
<p> the next century a new taxation system.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Will the next hurdle be the implementation of the GST?</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Well, we of course will implement it efficiently and fairly. I don't</p>
<p> see that as a hurdle. We will provide resources so that the Australian</p>
<p> public can be fully informed about the implementation, about how it</p>
<p> will operate. I remain very much of the view that once the legislation</p>
<p> is through and the community knows the matter has been resolved that</p>
<p> the community will go on to the next issue. I don't think we're</p>
<p> going to have a third campaign fought on a GST. I know some people</p>
<p> around this building have a fond hope that there will be a third GST</p>
<p> election campaign. They don't understand politics or political</p>
<p> history. What will happen is when the GST comes into operation the</p>
<p> public will see the benefits of the taxation cuts. Traders and small</p>
<p> business people will have been fully informed and advised and helped</p>
<p> and assisted in relation to implementation and handling any detail</p>
<p> of the new taxation system. And as has occurred in other countries</p>
<p> where there has been a sensible introduction, in other words you have</p>
<p> got rid of an existing old-fashioned indirect tax and introduced personal</p>
<p> income tax cuts at the same as you bring in the goods and services</p>
<p> tax, where that has happened, as in New Zealand, things have gone</p>
<p> very smoothly.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Given that this is a plan that you didn't put up in the first</p>
<p> place...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's 85 per cent of it, Dennis.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Is there any chance of trying to move and get the next 15%?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>This is it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, how important is Meg Lees continued leadership of the Democrats</p>
<p> to a continuation of your new productive relationship with that party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Michelle, I don't presume and I've been around here</p>
<p> long enough not to even dream of presuming to give another political</p>
<p> party advice about its leadership. That's not the sort of advice</p>
<p> that's ever welcome. And I can only report that I have found</p>
<p> her an honourable, straightforward, decent person with whom to deal.</p>
<p> She has expressed great confidence about her position. I certainly</p>
<p> believe that she's given credibility and status and clout to</p>
<p> the Australian Democrats in a way that no other leader that party's</p>
<p> had for quite a while has been able to do. And she's certainly</p>
<p> been infinitely more successful in achieving wins for the Australian</p>
<p> Democrats and for their values and beliefs than her predecessor. As</p>
<p> to what happens, that is entirely a matter for the Australian Democrats</p>
<p> and it's not for me to give any advice. I note, however, her</p>
<p> expressions of confidence and she certainly has a proven track record</p>
<p> of delivering what she says she can deliver.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Is it not destabilising for your Government when the people that you</p>
<p> have to rely on to get your legislation through the Senate have got</p>
<p> a leadership that is in crisis?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You didn't seriously ask that question, Paul, did you? Of course</p>
<p> it's not. Destabilising for our government? Oh yes! I mean, we</p>
<p> are on the verge of an historic reform of the Australian taxation</p>
<p> system and you're talking about a destabilised government.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Does it cause you difficulties having...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I thought we'd spent the last five minutes talking about</p>
<p> getting every amendment through. No.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, how quickly do you move on to business taxation reform</p>
<p> after next week and do you expect the Democrats will be as accommodating</p>
<p> on that issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>On the assumption that the Parliament votes, in the final votes, supports</p>
<p> all of our package that we will then turn our attention to business</p>
<p> tax. John Ralph has requested an extension of time until the end of</p>
<p> July, which is not all that long off, certainly not for me. I'll</p>
<p> be away for a couple of weeks in the early part of July and we've</p>
<p> got a Federal Council meeting of the Liberal Party so there's</p>
<p> plenty to do while we're waiting for the final report. But we'll</p>
<p> turn our minds to that very quickly. As far as the Democrats are concerned,</p>
<p> I'm not making any assumptions, I'm not taking anything</p>
<p> for granted. I hope that on this issue the Labor Party might decide</p>
<p> to actually become part of the Australian political contest again</p>
<p> instead of throwing mud and throwing saying no, which has been their</p>
<p> stock in trade particularly over the last month. I mean we have seen</p>
<p> in the last week a dramatic demonstration of the different styles</p>
<p> of politics in this country. I can't think of a week where the</p>
<p> Government has done and achieved more solid policy and more gains</p>
<p> for the long-term benefit of the country. Taxation, the environment,</p>
<p> reaffirmation of the green corps today, youth wages yesterday. It's</p>
<p> been an extraordinary week. The further privatisation of Telstra,</p>
<p> all the benefits that flow out of that. And what have we had from</p>
<p> the Labor Party? A shaking of heads and a throwing of mud.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Why won't the GST be an issue at the next election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, some people may try to make it. I make the prediction that the</p>
<p> Australian people will move onto something else.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>What extent would you really deal with the Labor Party over business</p>
<p> tax reform?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well our position Dennis is that we are always ready to deal constructively</p>
<p> with other political parties and the Labor Party could have dealt</p>
<p> itself into the taxation debate a long time ago. And they would have</p>
<p> in my view been more highly regarded by the Australian people as a</p>
<p> result of it. If the Labor Party shows a willingness to be constructive</p>
<p> for a change then we'll respond. But of course it's got</p>
<p> to be a response against the background of the principles for which</p>
<p> we stand.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Will you be sending a pamphlet to every household explaining the new</p>
<p> changes?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We will certainly be doing as any government has a right to do, and</p>
<p> indeed has a duty to do with a new law, we'll be making resources</p>
<p> available to explain how that new law effects people. Now whether</p>
<p> that involves sending a communication to every household, or what</p>
<p> combination of household communication plus radio or television advertisements,</p>
<p> or information documents to businessmen and women. Whatever combination</p>
<p> is needed will be embraced because people have got to know how the</p>
<p> new system operates.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Will the Government pay for that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well of course the government will pay for that. It will be the law</p>
<p> of the country and nobody will have a right to complain about the</p>
<p> responsibility of the government to explain to the Australian people</p>
<p> how a new law operates. I mean we've been down that road before</p>
<p> and the attempt by the Labor Party to denigrate our information campaign</p>
<p> last year failed. Here we're talking about a situation of an</p>
<p> information campaign after the law has been passed. I mean they'd</p>
<p> be doubly out of court complaining about that.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Will the Coalition again promise the full sale of Telstra for the</p>
<p> next campaign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well our policy remains Michelle to achieve, subject to the benchmarking</p>
<p> and the inquiry of which we've already spoken about the adequacy</p>
<p> of the social obligations being met by Telstra, we remain committed.</p>
<p> So the answer to that is if it hasn't happened before then the</p>
<p> answer is yes.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister have you given up any chance of getting your voluntary</p>
<p> student unionism through in this session?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let's see what time we've got left next week. I mean</p>
<p> I remain very committed, and the Government remains very committed</p>
<p> to voluntary student unionism. It's been something dear to the</p>
<p> hearts of many of us because it's one of those Liberal principles.</p>
<p> Very pure, straightforward, unambiguous Liberal principle that nobody</p>
<p> should be compelled to join something, and I hope we can still get</p>
<p> it through but we'll wait and see.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Won't the lamb decision be a difficulty for you on your trip</p>
<p> to the United States?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The lamb decision? Well the lamb issue could be yes, in one way it</p>
<p> won't be. If the decision goes the right way it will make a joyous</p>
<p> visit....it's make the visit even more joyous.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Can you make a comment on the passing of Peter Abeles?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Peter Abeles' death removes a very significant business figure</p>
<p> from the Australian scene. Peter Abeles was one of a number of a generation</p>
<p> of business men and women in this country who were born in Europe</p>
<p> and who left Europe as young people leaving behind a continent devastated</p>
<p> by war, and many of them like Peter Abeles fled persecution and came</p>
<p> to this country and made an immense contribution to this country.</p>
<p> And he of course dominated the transport industry through his positions</p>
<p> in both Ansett Transport Industries and TNT for several decades and</p>
<p> he's certainly a very significant figure and I express my condolences</p>
<p> to his family and remark upon his great contribution to the Australian</p>
<p> business scene.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Do you think that too close to the Labor government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't want to talk about that. People are entitled to have</p>
<p> business associations and associates who are in business. I'm</p>
<p> not going to comment on that.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>... rejection reintroduced legislation on youth wages and what</p>
<p> would you now do to get that through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look I'm feeling very warm about the Democrats at the moment.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Did you advise Mr Entsch to resign his secretaryship of his companies?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look decisions are ultimately taken by people taking into account</p>
<p> a whole lot of considerations and a whole lot of factors and if you</p>
<p> want to talk to Mr Entsch about that you do so.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]... your own stand in support of Mr Entsch?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>My own stand in support in of Mr Entsch, yes.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] now resigned those directorships, does that alter your</p>
<p> defence of Mr Entsch?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no. Not the slightest. Why would it?</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] by pulling out of those directorships, he acknowledges</p>
<p> that there is some question about .....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it doesn't acknowledge of any admission of anything. I mean</p>
<p> you can talk to him but I imagine that one of the reasons why it's</p>
<p> occurred is that, you know, he has been subjected to an enormous amount</p>
<p> of unfair criticism and abuse from the Labor Party. Why would anybody</p>
<p> want to go through that again. That doesn't mean to say that</p>
<p> it's any admission of guilt and I don't retract or recant</p>
<p> or go back on anything I've said. I've regarded the whole</p>
<p> thing as a ridiculous beat-up over something that did not involve</p>
<p> any dishonesty on his part. I mean the Labor Party has extended an</p>
<p> enormous amount of energy this week throwing dirt, and I don't</p>
<p> think it's helped them and I think they've made a very big</p>
<p> mistake doing so. If there was any real evidence of dishonesty or</p>
<p> corruption or fraud it would be a different matter. He would've</p>
<p> been out on his ear. But there's been no evidence of that and</p>
<p> it I think he's taken the view that, you know, what's the</p>
<p> point of going through all that again, particularly as that company</p>
<p> would continue to carry on business and there's just no point,</p>
<p> presumably, in going through that again.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Mr Howard [inaudible] back to preambles and other issues for the rest</p>
<p> of the year, what is your plan now to try and get that firstly through</p>
<p> the Senate, how much...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I haven't really given the preamble a great deal of thought,</p>
<p> Michelle. I'll have a think about it over the next week or two</p>
<p> but it's not  whilst I would like to have a preamble to</p>
<p> put, whilst I think we have got a good opportunity if people are sensible</p>
<p> and see the wisdom of agreeing on what is common ground, if people</p>
<p> hold out for something they know that one of the other political parties</p>
<p> won't agree to and we end up not having a preamble, well, it</p>
<p> won't be because I haven't tried. I mean, that's my</p>
<p> position.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, does the Government [inaudible] termination payments</p>
<p> with Patricks, is it valid to say that that's a precedent which</p>
<p> might assist the Oakdale miners?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there is a difference of course  the redundancies in the</p>
<p> waterfront industry were funded by the companies as part of an overall</p>
<p> plan put forward in large measure by the companies themselves to rationalise</p>
<p> the size of the workforce.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>But the Government assisted [inaudible].</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, but we didn't fund it. We didn't fund the redundancies</p>
<p> on the waterfront. Those redundancies were paid for by a levy on the</p>
<p> companies. We provided a guarantee but we didn't fund them. The</p>
<p> costs of those redundancies are borne by P&amp;O and by Patricks and</p>
<p> by the smaller stevedores. So, there are some similarities, Malcolm,</p>
<p> but they're not on all fores. One the issue of the miners, Mr</p>
<p> Reith and Senator Minchin had a talk to them and we are very sympathetic</p>
<p> to their plight. I feel very sorry for those men and we are looking</p>
<p> at the whole situation. It's not an easy issue as the former</p>
<p> government found because they didn't do anything about it. And</p>
<p> it's an issue that we are studying very closely. I remind you</p>
<p> we are encouraging the Securities Commission to look to see whether</p>
<p> any avenue for recovery against the companies or their affiliates</p>
<p> is available. I'm not saying there is but we've certainly</p>
<p> encouraged them to do so and they'll do that very comprehensively</p>
<p> I'm sure. And Mr Reith and Senator Minchin will be talking to</p>
<p> the Cabinet about the issue more broadly over the next week or two.</p>
<p> But we are particularly sympathetic and it does a raise a very difficult</p>
<p> issue and we'll try and get a balanced response to it.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, can I ask you about the Democrats' proposal for</p>
<p> a minimum company tax, I was wondering what you think of that idea,</p>
<p> do you think that's a good way to get business to pay an adequate</p>
<p> amount of company tax or do you think it's too complicated a</p>
<p> structure?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's been referred to the Ralph Committee. That's</p>
<p> really all I have to say about it at this stage. It's been referred</p>
<p> to the Ralph Committee to be examined. I don't really care to</p>
<p> say anything more about it at the moment. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
