<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9856</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP JOHN HOWARD AND THE MARKS ROYAL COMMISSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009856.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 137/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
JOHN HOWARD AND THE MARKS ROYAL COMMISSION<br />
John Howard's claims today concerning Justice Marks are transparently<br />
dishonest. His only truthful statement was his grudging admission that the Telstra matter<br />
and the Marks Royal Commission were totally " unrelated".<br />
Mr Howard claimed on " AM" that the Government had appointed Justice Marks<br />
to carry out a Telstra review this is untrue. Justice Marks was appointed by<br />
Telstra, not the Government.<br />
For Mr Howard to imply that the appointment of Justice Marks by Telstra long<br />
before the establishment of the Marks Royal Commission somehow invalidates<br />
the Government's criticism of the Commission is either ignorant or deliberately<br />
deceptive. Criticism of Justice Marks followed his acceptance of a politically motivated<br />
Royal Commission. His previous professional life has never been at issue.<br />
The Marks Royal Commission was the product of deliberately narrow terms of<br />
reference designed to deny Dr Lawrence natural justice while the terms of<br />
reference in the Teistra inquiry were wide ranging and properly constructed.<br />
There was also no question of improper contact between the Government and<br />
Justice Marks in the Telstra case. In the Western Australian case the contact<br />
between Richard Court's staff and the Royal Commissioner is open to question.<br />
It is drawing a long bow indeed to compare Mr Marks' involvement a year ago<br />
with an external Telstra review with his later involvement in Richard Court's and<br />
John Howard's politically malevolent Royal Commission. It is also completely<br />
dishonest for Mr Howard to say the two cases were run " simultaneously".<br />
With the connivance of John Howard, Richard Court established a Royal<br />
Commission with the express purpose of having terms of reference guide the<br />
Royal Commissioner towards a ' guilty' finding. </p>
<p>2<br />
It was a vicious $ 5 million political onslaught against one woman. It was the<br />
most savage and systemic personal attack against someone in political life in<br />
the post war period.<br />
Its findings were left open to doubt by even the Royal Commissioner himself.<br />
Mr Howard's dishonesty in exploiting this matter deserves to be condemned.<br />
CANBERRA 24 November 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
