<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8080</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HMAS SUCCESS, 13 AUGUST 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/08/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008080.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HMAS SUCCESS, 13 AUGUST<br />
1990 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, it's the most serious decision I've had to<br />
take as Prime Minister, in consultation with my<br />
colleagues. But in the end, it's not a hard decision in<br />
that one knows that you can't sensibly follow a policy of<br />
appeasement in situations like this. It's of course, my<br />
hope that by the time our men get there in these three<br />
ships the need for their presence will have<br />
evaporated. But I was terribly impressed by the spirit<br />
of the officers and men with whom I had the opportunity<br />
of speaking. There was no sense of wild jingoism, there<br />
was a sense of understanding of the potential danger into<br />
which they were going and a very sober assessment of<br />
that, but a serious commitment to undertaking that<br />
mission and undertaking it successfully. I want to say<br />
to the people of Australia that they are entitled to feel<br />
very proud of these 600 men who are going on these three<br />
ships. JOURNALIST: Given it is such a serious mission, do you<br />
think it was wise not to have actually got the formal<br />
approval of Cabinet before committing our forces?<br />
PM: Well, I wouldn't have done it if I hadn't thought it<br />
was wise.<br />
JOURNALIST: And what about the criticism that's emerged,<br />
some of it even from within your own Party, about the<br />
wisdom of this decision, particularly the suggestion that<br />
we're once again playing hand maidens to the United<br />
States? PM: Well that, of course, is a nonsense. If that sort<br />
of reasoning had been allowed to stand, then you would be<br />
giving signs of encouragement to dictators who feel that<br />
they can simply invade and annex a small neighbour. This<br />
is not simply a United States issue, this is a world<br />
issue. Just as in the 1930s, appeasement was wrong then<br />
and the world paid a terrible price for it, so would<br />
appeasement be wrong in the 1990s. The important thing<br />
we've got to understand is this that the Cold War has<br />
come to an end, we are entering a new era and in that new </p>
<p>2<br />
era where the threat of superpower conflict has gone,<br />
then it's terribly important that the world shows that<br />
it's prepared to act and to act together to enforce the<br />
principles of the United Nations Charter. And Australia<br />
cannot, certainly should not, shirk its responsibilities<br />
in that situation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, talking to the family of one<br />
sailor there today, they expressed the view to me that<br />
what difference do 600 sailors make. What would you say<br />
to that?<br />
PM: Well, you spoke to one, I spoke to many more than<br />
one and overwhelmingly, I mean, as far as I was<br />
concerned, without exception, families to whom I spoke<br />
expressed the view that this is the right decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: What about the, if we could turn to one<br />
S other topic for a moment<br />
PM: No, wait a minute. Is there any more on<br />
JOURNALIST: What were some of the comments you were<br />
getting from family members<br />
PM: Well, there was obviously sadness that their loved<br />
ones were leaving and going into a situation of potential<br />
danger and that's precisely what you would have expected.<br />
But, as I say, all of them understood, that's all I spoke<br />
to, understood the decision and supported it.<br />
JOURNALIST: And walking around the ships, how did you<br />
feel, like, how did you<br />
PM: As I've said this is, in a sense, the most serious<br />
decision that I've had to take in my period as Prime<br />
Minister, but while I thought long and hard about it and<br />
discussed it with my colleagues, in the end it was not a<br />
hard decision because the issue was clear.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you, by having taken this decision, what<br />
do you feel for the Australians trapped in Iraq and<br />
Kuwait? Haven't you raised the prospect that they are<br />
going to have a fairly uncomfortable if not<br />
PM: They were having an uncomfortable time any rate, as<br />
were the thousands of Americans, British, Australians,<br />
Europeans who are now confined within Iraq and Kuwait and<br />
we have been ceaseless in our diplomatic attempts, both<br />
directly through our own representatives and through<br />
other friendly powers and the representations that have<br />
been made for the safety of those people.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have any reason, any more reason for<br />
optimism at this moment given those contacts that you've<br />
had though? </p>
<p>PM: One must honestly say that in regard to the people<br />
that are confined within Iraq and Kuwait that we haven't<br />
any evidence at this moment of any saner, more humane<br />
attitude on the part of the Iraqi authorities, but we<br />
will continue to press them to ensure the safety of those<br />
people. JOURNALIST: Would you consider calling back the ships if<br />
they started to<br />
PM: That's a question I'm not prepared to address.<br />
JOURNALIST: If we could deal with just one other issue.<br />
The Left meeting yesterday on the not privatisation,<br />
on Telecom and on the airlines, how much harder does that<br />
make it for the Government to reach a rational decision<br />
on those two questions?<br />
PM: I've got no public comment upon the processes that<br />
are going on within the Party. I welcome the fact that<br />
discussions are taking place. I'm confident that in the<br />
end we'll get sensible decisions.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
