<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3149</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S ADDRESS AT STATE DINNER, KUALA LUMPUR</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003149_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4/ DATE<br />
M/' 2 0 11 February 1974.<br />
PRIME MINISTERS ADDRESS AT STATE DINNER,<br />
KUAL~ A LJUMPUR<br />
The following is an amended text of an address given by the<br />
Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, at a State dinner in his honour in<br />
Kuala Lumpur on 29 January 1974. This text should replace that<br />
issued in our news release number M/ 9 of 29 January 1974:<br />
" It is -thoroughly appropriate that I should have begun my<br />
visit to six countries in the South-East Asian region here, in<br />
Malaysia. I am no stranger to your country.<br />
I come as an old friend as the guest of old friends.<br />
I come as Prime Minister of a nation with a long and<br />
proven friendship towards the people of Malaysia.<br />
I come to re-affirm that friendship and to seek new ways<br />
to strengthen the Cooperation which has existed between our twro<br />
countries for more than two decades.<br />
There is no country in the region which better exemplifiLes<br />
the spirit of national independence and regional cooperation than<br />
your own, I believe further there is no country in the region where<br />
the policies of my own government are better understood and where<br />
the responses and attitudes of our two governments to the changes,<br />
challenges and opportunities in the region are more in harmony.<br />
In this climate olf change, in seeking new solutions to new;<br />
pblems, Malaysia has responded with vigour and imagination.<br />
We Australians have in our own way tried to do the same.,<br />
Our views at so many points coincide, and so do the<br />
interest of our two nations.<br />
In particular, we march in step on three fundamental<br />
matters. ~ J~ WIT </p>
<p>WVe both believe that the detente between the great poiier,-N<br />
can work, that it must be made to work and that the smaller pol-aers<br />
like Malaysia. and Australia can help to make it . work.<br />
We both believe deeply that this region should not become<br />
the area for confrontation and comnpetition betweec-' n the great<br />
powers. We both believe that regional cooperation and regional<br />
associations have a vital contribution to make to the stability<br />
and prosperity of this region.<br />
It is against this background of shared interests, shared<br />
attitudes and shared aspirations that I wish the policies and<br />
actions of* -the Australian Governient to be seen.<br />
In Australia, we have broadened the range of our international<br />
contacts.<br />
Ve have sought to break doiwn ideological constraints which<br />
had for so long obstructed meaningful relationships with<br />
countries such as China, East Germany and North Viet-Nam.<br />
We have placed our relationships with the United States<br />
and the United Kingdom on the basis of a more mature partnership.<br />
We have widened our horizons and sought great cooperation<br />
with the medium and smaller powers of Africa, Latin America and<br />
the Pacific. We have given our ful. support to all questions of human<br />
rights and declared our opposition to any forms of lingering<br />
colonialism. We have sought to remove any taint of racism from our<br />
national and international policies.<br />
I wish to make it quite clear that our interest in<br />
South East Asia continues undiminished.<br />
Our genuine concern about the well-being of M~ alaysia and<br />
our other neighbours in the region is a central and enduring<br />
feature of Australian foreign policy.<br />
What has changed in our attitude to South East Asia is<br />
not the degree of our interest or of our involvement, but the<br />
nature of that interest and that involvement.<br />
We seek to turn away from the destructive confrontations<br />
of the past to constructive cooperation in the future. </p>
<p>3.<br />
In the context of our common view, it ' s worthwhile<br />
recalling that some of my Government's earliest decisions brought<br />
us even more in line with the policy of the Malaysian goverrent<br />
After coming to office, we ended our military role in.<br />
Viet-Nam a role which Malaysia did not undertake.<br />
We ended our military assistance previously given to<br />
Cambodia Malaysia had never given such military assistance.<br />
We reduced our involvement with ASPAC an organisation<br />
in which Malaysia no longer participates, and we sought<br />
successfully to change the military emphasis of SEATO an<br />
organisation of which Malaysia was never a member.<br />
My Government has set a new course for Australia in th'is<br />
region. We have shifted the emphasis of our continuing involvement<br />
in South East Asia from one primarily based on ideological<br />
considerations and military alliances to one based increasingly.<br />
on developing trade with the countries of the region, on promoting<br />
progress through constructive aid programs, on encouraging<br />
security through regional cooperation, on a positive response<br />
to the recent proposals that we should consider financial<br />
assistance to agreed ASEAN projects, and on the development of<br />
cultural contacts through the negotiati~ on of cultural agreements<br />
with the countries of South East Asia.<br />
We see in this re-orientation of our diplomatic efforts<br />
the opportunity, which has been too often missed or ignored in<br />
the past, to establish endu. ring relationships with the countries<br />
of this region0<br />
It is not our wish to forge ties based on transitory<br />
concerns but to seek out ways of developing bonds based on an<br />
identification of those interests -which will continue<br />
irrespective of the governments in power in Australia. or the<br />
region. Our main endeavours will henceforth be directed towards<br />
expanding relations in those fields most likely to produce lasting<br />
social and economic advantages for both us and our neighbours. </p>
<p>Some manifestations of this change are already evident.<br />
In recent months we have joined IVDSEA, The Ministerial<br />
Conference for the Economic Development of South East Asia.<br />
Only yesterday in B3angkok we were proclaimed an associate<br />
member of SEAYEG, The South East Asian Ministers of Education<br />
Organisation. Earlier this month we met for the first time with the<br />
Secretaries-General of ASEAI to discuss ways in which Australia<br />
might assist ASEAN projects.<br />
I stress that isolationism is not a policy option . fbr<br />
Australia. Ve are going through a period of change and adjus-tent<br />
which I believe will resulIt in more fruitful Australian<br />
involvement than ever before with the countries of South East Asia.<br />
In this re-orientation I would stress that we have not<br />
sought to widen our interests and contacts at the expense of<br />
older friendships. And this applies with special force to Malaysia and<br />
the ASEAN nations.<br />
For too long our interests in this region were seen<br />
excessively in terms of defence.<br />
We do not now look on the countries of South East Asia<br />
as buffer states or as constituting some northern Military line<br />
where some potential future enemy of Australia should be held.<br />
Rather, we see these countries, especially Malaysia,<br />
Singapore, Thailand, Indonesia and the Philippines, as countries<br />
which have a common interest with Australia and New Zealand in<br />
consolidating the security and stability of this region as a<br />
whole. In particular we seek close relations with the Commonwealth<br />
nations in South East Asia and the Pacific and Indian Ocean areas.<br />
Australia's own defence capability is enhanced by mutual<br />
defence arrangements.<br />
My Government gave a pledge to the Australian people to<br />
honour the full terms of the Five Power Arrangements until a more<br />
positive and enduring settlement is reached in establishing peace,<br />
freedom and neutrality in this region. </p>
<p>I SAustralian Air Force Squadrons will. I remoin at Butterworth<br />
as long as they r elevant to the needs of both our nations<br />
and relevant to the realities of the region.<br />
This is a matter which, in consultation with your<br />
government, we shall review as appr opriate.<br />
Our defence association is only on aspect o f the relations<br />
between our two nations and our two peoples.<br />
We have our longstanding common bond through our membership<br />
of the Commonwealth.<br />
We have increasingly fruitful cooperation at the United<br />
Nations and the Australian Government now, as a matter of policy,<br />
consults closely with the countries of South East Asia before<br />
determining our position at the United Nations.<br />
A glance at our voting patterns in the United Nations will<br />
show that since December 1972 we have voted together to a much<br />
greater extent than ever before.<br />
We have at present over. 6000 Malaysian students in<br />
Australia, many of whom have enriched our culture and widened our<br />
perspectives. Others who have returned occupy prominent positions in<br />
your Goverrment and Public Service.<br />
This exchange can only strengthen the understanding of a<br />
friendship for each country in the other.<br />
Trade and Australian investment in Malaysia have developed<br />
rapidly. Only a week ago I arnounced a new Australian policy on<br />
Australian investment overseas, especially in developing<br />
countries. We want to encourage private Australian investment on a<br />
joint venture basis in Mlalaysia in a way which will benefit the<br />
people of Malaysia and will be favourable to the ownership and<br />
control of enterprises by Malaysians.<br />
We understand and accept the wish of developing countries<br />
to regulate foreign investment in accordance with their own<br />
national aspiratLons and development plans.<br />
We seek no less for ourselves and we see Australian<br />
investment overseas in the context of mutual benefit and of<br />
economic cooperatio~ n without exploitationø </p>
<p>Recently the number of Australian tourists visiting Malaysia<br />
has increased greatly.<br />
There has also been a rapid growth in the cultural exchanges<br />
between our two countries.<br />
This is a matter which I believe worthy of further active<br />
encouragement. I believe that these programs of exchange between peoples<br />
and cultures have an increasingly greater part to play in<br />
developing a wider, enduring understanding between peoples and<br />
cultures have an increasingly greater part to play in developing<br />
a wider, enduring understanding between neighbours with different<br />
cultural backgrounds.<br />
Let us freely acknowledge the differences in culture, but<br />
let us learn more about each other and from each other.<br />
All these links have contributed to a high level of<br />
awareness and understanding of each other.<br />
W~ e, in Australia, have been impressed by the economic<br />
success of Malaysia.<br />
I note that in your recent mid-term r eview of the second<br />
Malaysia plan you have not only achieved, but have exceeded, your<br />
growth target. The importance of economic success is absolute because<br />
only with economic progress will there be social advancement and<br />
regional stability.<br />
I do not, however, wish to comment only on Malaysia's<br />
contribution to the economic development of the region.<br />
If anything in the past few years we have watched with<br />
even greater admiration the way Malaysia has evolved her foreign.<br />
policies to match the changed realities of the area.<br />
Malaysia has, along with Indonesia, the Philippines,<br />
Singapore and Thailand, established a workable, relevant and<br />
important regional grouping ASEAN.<br />
ASEA14 is an example to all of us of the co-operation and<br />
understanding which can be achieved if countries with a common<br />
interest in progress come together to promote that common interest.<br />
Malaysia has also used that forum to advance its concept<br />
of a zone of peace, freedom and neutrality. </p>
<p>Australia applauds this initiative and welcomes the<br />
objectives which the ASEAN countries have set for themselves for<br />
a zone of peace, freedom and neutrality in South East Asia.<br />
It is a creative concept which, if fulfilled, will not<br />
only benefit the nations in the zone, it will itself be a further<br />
step towards detente, if the great powers are able to agree not to<br />
use this region as the field for destructive rivalry.<br />
You have acknowledgethat the zone of peace, freedom<br />
and neutrality will not be achieved overnight.<br />
It is evident that the great powers will need to show<br />
more trust towards each other before they will come to a point<br />
when they can agree mutually to accept the zone.<br />
The search for detente has begun and I believe the<br />
realisation will grow that it is only the imaginative farsightedness<br />
of such new initiatives which will enable our world to<br />
attain the peace and justice we all desire.<br />
In the same spirit of hope but with the swuae awareness of<br />
the difficulties in the way, my Government has suggested that<br />
some wider' regional arrangement for information consultation<br />
between the nations of the whole region should be established<br />
in the future.<br />
We consider that it is important that the countries of<br />
the Asian and Pacific region should be able to come together to<br />
discuss common interests in an atmosphere free of crisis, free<br />
of pomp, free of drama, and free of excessive expectations of<br />
any spectacular results.<br />
I recognise that such a forum cannot be achieved quickly,<br />
it has to evolve from withIn the region, out of the wishes of<br />
the countries of the region.<br />
Like the zone of peace, freedom and neutrality, it will<br />
only come about when the countries concerned agree that it is in<br />
their mutual interests to have such a forum.<br />
Lest there be any misunderstandings, I want to emphasise<br />
that we do not see such an association competing with ASEAN in<br />
any way* On the contrary, we would see it as being complementsry to<br />
ASEAN which has proved itself to be a close viable and natural<br />
grouping of South East Asian states. </p>
<p>Malaysia and Australia are both moving in the same general<br />
direction and, with the benefit of our long-standing friendship<br />
and understanding, we should, by working together, make our goals<br />
that much more capable of achievement.<br />
1We share the same great goals.<br />
Wie are marching together towards them.<br />
In some matters, such as normalisation of relations with<br />
China, Australia has been able to move more quickly than Malaysia0<br />
In others, such as the establishment of relations with<br />
North Korea, Mvalaysia has moved more quickly than Australia.<br />
This has been ' because of differences in our circumstances<br />
rather than differences in our ultimate goals.<br />
We are each involved in our own way in an important<br />
humanitarian experiment.<br />
You, within Malaysia, are trying to forge a free,<br />
prosperous and harmonious multi-racial society.<br />
We, in AustGralia, notwithstanding our European origins,<br />
are trying to build strong bridges and develop lasting links with<br />
Malaysia and the countries of South East Asia.<br />
But we both seek, I believe, the same end, namely to<br />
cooperate closely, as good neighbours should, in a wider<br />
effort to promote a stable, more prosperous and peaceful<br />
multi-racial South East Asian region.<br />
When one sees the severity of the test which the detente<br />
much undergo, as shown so suddenly and dangerously in the<br />
Middle East when one sees the continuing frustration. of our high<br />
hopes just one year ago for real peace in Indo-China, it would<br />
be an exceptionally bold or excessively naive man who declares<br />
his unqualified optimism about the course of events and their<br />
outcome. Yet, fundamentally, I am an optimist, certainly about the<br />
future of our region.<br />
Diplomacy must be based on realistic hopes rather than on<br />
resignation and despair.<br />
And from no country in the region, from the effectiveness<br />
of its Government, the growing prosperity of its people, and the<br />
imaginative policies of its leaders, do I draw more encouragement<br />
sustain that opt~ imism and that hope than I do from Malaysia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
