<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11282</transcript-id>
    <title>THE REFERENDUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/10/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>  I have previously indicated my intention to make a considered statement<br />
   on the referenda to be held on November 6.</p>
<p>  Accordingly, I attach a statement of my reasons for voting 'no' to the proposed<br />
   republic as well as a statement in support of the preamble.</p>
<p>  I have drawn upon this material to detail my position in a newsletter to<br />
   my constituents.</p>
<p>  Introduction</p>
<p>  On 6 November Australia will vote on two constitutional proposals - one<br />
   on a republic and another on a preamble to the constitution.</p>
<p>  The people of Australia are entitled to know how I intend to vote and why.</p>
<p>  The referendum on the issue of a republic fulfils a promise I made to the<br />
   Australian people, on behalf of the Coalition, before the 1996 election<br />
   and before I became Prime Minister.</p>
<p>  As Leader of the Opposition, I promised that if elected the Coalition would<br />
   hold a Constitutional Convention and, furthermore, give the people of Australia<br />
   a vote on the issue before the turn of the century.</p>
<p>  At the Convention, held in February 1998, I said that if clear support for<br />
   a particular republican model emerged then the Government would put that<br />
   model to the people at a referendum.</p>
<p>  Clear support for the model now proposed did emerge from the Convention.<br />
   In fulfilment of our pledge, the referendum is now being held.</p>
<p>  I have never disguised my personal views on this issue. I have been completely<br />
   consistent. I told the Australian people prior to both the elections of<br />
   1996 and 1998 that I supported current constitutional arrangements. At the<br />
   Constitutional Convention, I voted in favour of our present system.</p>
<p>  Why I will vote "No" to a Republic</p>
<p>  I will vote 'no' to Australia becoming a republic because I do not believe<br />
   in changing a constitutional system which works so well and has helped bring<br />
   such stability to our nation.</p>
<p>  The changes being proposed would not make Australia's constitution or system<br />
   of Government any better or more effective. They are not as simple or as<br />
   minuscule as their proponents would like people to believe.</p>
<p>  There are no demonstrated benefits from the proposed changes. They would<br />
   add nothing to the already democratic character of Australia.</p>
<p>  They will not enhance our independence.</p>
<p>  There is nothing to be gained from tampering with a system of government<br />
   which has contributed to our country being one of only a handful of nations<br />
   which has remained fully democratic throughout the 20th century.</p>
<p>  Some of the checks and balances in our present system would be weakened<br />
   under the republic being proposed.</p>
<p>  The president could be less secure in his or her position, than is the Governor-General.<br />
   This in turn could, among other things, affect the appropriate exercise<br />
   of the reserve powers by a president in a future republic.</p>
<p>  An Australian Head of State</p>
<p>  The main argument advanced by republicans is that our head of state should<br />
   be an Australian.</p>
<p>  The Queen is Queen of Australia. However, under our present constitution,<br />
   the Governor-General is effectively Australia's head of state. The only<br />
   constitutional duty performed by the Queen relates to the appointment of<br />
   the Governor-General which must be done on the recommendation of the Prime<br />
   Minister of the day.</p>
<p>  Since 1965 every Governor-General of Australia has been an Australian. It<br />
   is inconceivable that any future occupant of that office would be other<br />
   than an Australian.</p>
<p>  The circumstances of history have given Australia a very stable and workable<br />
   system of government.</p>
<p>  Executive political authority is vested in the Prime Minister and other<br />
   members of the Cabinet who must always come from the majority party in the<br />
   House of Representatives. The essentially ceremonial functions of government<br />
   are separated from the day to day executive responsibilities.</p>
<p>  A fundamental characteristic of our system is not only the separation of<br />
   the ceremonial and executive functions of government, but also that the<br />
   person discharging the formal or ceremonial functions is so politically<br />
   neutral - both in reality and perception - that he or she can act as the<br />
   ultimate defender of the constitutional integrity of the nation.</p>
<p>  I do not believe that the republican proposal would be as effective as present<br />
   arrangements in delivering that outcome.</p>
<p>  The Governor-General is the ultimate constitutional umpire. He exercises<br />
   the reserve powers of the crown, completely free of any interference from<br />
   anyone.</p>
<p>  His powers flow from the Australian Constitution. They do not flow from<br />
   the Queen. He acts in accordance with the Constitution of Australia. Although<br />
   he is the Queen's representative, he does not take instructions from her.</p>
<p>  He acts in accordance with the powers given to him by the Constitution as<br />
   well as the conventions of the Crown which have been developed and distilled<br />
   through hundreds of years of constitutional practice.</p>
<p>  That is one of the reasons why our system of government is so stable.</p>
<p>  It has evolved over a long period of time.</p>
<p>  Its history is a strength not a weakness.</p>
<p>  We should not lightly put aside something which has worked so well and helped<br />
   give us such stability.</p>
<p>  That the Governor-General is the effective head of state of Australia and<br />
   must act in accordance with the Australian Constitution was clearly illustrated<br />
   in November 1975.</p>
<p>  After the Governor-General had withdrawn Mr Whitlam's commission as Prime<br />
   Minister, the House of Representatives passed a vote of no confidence in<br />
   the caretaker Fraser Government.</p>
<p>  The text of that resolution was sent to the Queen with a request that she<br />
   intervene. The reply on her behalf was as follows : ".. the Australian<br />
   Constitution firmly places the prerogative powers of the Crown in the hands<br />
   of the Governor-General. and the Queen has no part in the decisions which<br />
   the Governor-General must take in accordance with the Constitution. it would<br />
   not be proper for Her to intervene in person in matters which are so clearly<br />
   placed within the jurisdiction of the Governor-General by the Constitution<br />
   Act."</p>
<p>  In other words, the matter was to be resolved by Australians under the terms<br />
   of the Australian Constitution which, incidentally, had been assented to<br />
   by Australians before its adoption in 1901.</p>
<p>  An independent nation</p>
<p>  Australia is a fully independent and sovereign nation. Even staunch republicans<br />
   like the former Prime Minister Mr Gough Whitlam acknowledge this. The 1988<br />
   report of the Hawke Government's Constitutional Commission, of which Mr<br />
   Whitlam was a member, found that "Australia had achieved full independence<br />
   as a sovereign state of the world" sometime between 1926 and the end<br />
   of World War II and was so recognised by the world community.</p>
<p>  Despite this some argue, including the former Prime Minister Mr Keating,<br />
   that Australia must become a republic to demonstrate to the world, and especially<br />
   to the Asian-Pacific region, that it is a truly independent nation.</p>
<p>  This is a shallow argument with no merit or substance.</p>
<p>  Mutual respect is the basis of good relations between nations.</p>
<p>  Just as Australia does not seek to tell other nations how to arrange their<br />
   constitutions, so it is that our friends in the region and elsewhere do<br />
   not seek to tell us what form our constitution should take.</p>
<p>  This reality was best captured by the senior Minister of Singapore, Mr Lee<br />
   Kuan Yew, probably the elder statesman of Asia and certainly a good judge<br />
   of the mood of the region.</p>
<p>  Addressing the National Press Club in 1994 he said: "I don't think<br />
   Asia understands what the argument is about. Australia would not generate<br />
   greater esteem in Asia as a republic than it does with its present constitutional<br />
   arrangements."</p>
<p>  Moreover, my experience from all the negotiations in which I have been involved<br />
   concerning East Timor in recent months is the strongest evidence to me of<br />
   how empty and transparent is the proposition that Australia must become<br />
   a republic to demonstrate its independence to the world.</p>
<p>  Those negotiations were as intense and as high level as any negotiations<br />
   in which any Australian Prime Minister has been involved since World War<br />
   II.</p>
<p>  They involved frequent discussions with the leaders of many of our regional<br />
   neighbours, the President of the United States, the Prime Ministers of New<br />
   Zealand, Canada, Portugal and Japan and the Secretary-General of the United<br />
   Nations.</p>
<p>  They led to Australia, for the first time in her history, being asked to<br />
   lead a multinational force.</p>
<p>  To suggest that I came to those negotiations otherwise than as the Prime<br />
   Minister of a completely independent nation is ludicrous.</p>
<p>  It would be equally ludicrous to suggest that the outcome of those negotiations<br />
   would have been either different or better if Australia had come to them<br />
   as a republic.</p>
<p>  This "independence" argument is one of the poorest of all advanced<br />
   in favour of a republic.</p>
<p>  A directly elected President?</p>
<p>  I will vote 'no' because I support the present system, not because I prefer<br />
   some other kind of republic than the one on offer.</p>
<p>  I do not support a directly elected presidency.</p>
<p>  This would produce rival power centres in our political system.</p>
<p>  Under such an arrangement both the Prime Minister and the president would<br />
   claim popular mandates.</p>
<p>  Even if the president's powers were carefully laid out in the Constitution,<br />
   the adversarial nature of Australian politics would ensure that tension<br />
   between the two would arise.</p>
<p>  Flaws in the republican model</p>
<p>  Although my principal reason for voting no is that I support the present<br />
   system, I am obliged to point out that there are flaws in the republican<br />
   model that people are being asked to support.</p>
<p>  This is due in no small measure to the fact that it is a compromise model<br />
   designed to attract the support of direct election republicans for an appointment<br />
   process which gives the power to appoint the president to the members of<br />
   the Commonwealth Parliament.</p>
<p>  In the process the worst of both worlds has resulted.</p>
<p>  Final power to choose the president rests with parliament and not the people.<br />
   This is undoubtedly unsatisfactory to those who want a direct election for<br />
   the president.</p>
<p>  Under the republican model being proposed, public nomination for the presidency<br />
   would be called for by a committee comprising 32 people, half of them chosen<br />
   by the Prime Minister and the other half serving members of the Commonwealth<br />
   and State Parliaments and the Territory Legislative Assemblies.</p>
<p>  This Committee would recommend a short list to the Prime Minister who would<br />
   then propose a candidate of his choice to the Parliament. He would not,<br />
   incidentally, be obliged to nominate a person from the short list.</p>
<p>  This is a "Claytons" public consultation process. It is designed<br />
   to placate the direct election republicans with the illusion of public involvement<br />
   in the selection process.</p>
<p>  But it is without one of the advantages of a pure parliamentary appointment<br />
   model (where there is no such public consultation process) which is that,<br />
   in practice, the full range of talented Australians would be available for<br />
   the post of president - as is the case now with the appointment of the Governor-General.</p>
<p>  Under the republican proposal being put at the referendum many Australians<br />
   holding prominent positions might not submit themselves to the nomination<br />
   process either because of the embarrassment at not being short listed or<br />
   chosen, or through a fear that their rejection, or the possibility of public<br />
   knowledge that they were under consideration, might reduce their capacity<br />
   to discharge their current duties.</p>
<p>  Would, for example, a High Court judge, or even an eminent businessman or<br />
   community leader allow their names to go forward if they feared that their<br />
   involvement in the nomination process might compromise the performance of<br />
   their current duties?</p>
<p>  Australia has been extremely well served by its Governors-General. If the<br />
   republic is supported at the referendum then I do not believe that the pool<br />
   from which a future president would be drawn will be as deep as the one<br />
   now available for the Governor-General.</p>
<p>  Dismissal of a President</p>
<p>  There has been much debate about whether, or not, the president in the proposed<br />
   republic would be more or less secure in his or her office than is the Governor-General<br />
   under the present Constitution.</p>
<p>  I believe that, on balance, the Governor-General has greater security of<br />
   tenure. Let me state why.</p>
<p>  Under the proposed republic, the president can be summarily dismissed by<br />
   the Prime Minister by notice in writing at any time without reason or appeal.</p>
<p>  The requirement that the dismissal be approved by the House of Representatives<br />
   within thirty days adds little to the president's security of tenure.</p>
<p>  The government party, with a majority in the House of Representatives, would<br />
   scarcely repudiate their own Prime Minister's action in dismissing the president.<br />
   Even if it did, that would not reinstate the president. His or her removal<br />
   would be final and absolute.</p>
<p>  No Australian Governor-General has been dismissed from office.</p>
<p>  If in the future, a Prime Minister did wish to have a Governor-General dismissed,<br />
   it would almost certainly be for a political reason and any action taken<br />
   to secure the dismissal would be highly controversial.</p>
<p>  In those circumstances, a recommendation from the Prime Minister to the<br />
   Queen to remove the Governor-General would be seen to involve her directly<br />
   in a political dispute.</p>
<p>  Although a future Prime Minister might be willing to do this, a natural<br />
   reluctance to involve the monarch very directly in a political dispute could<br />
   act as a constraint on a Prime Minister recommending removal of a Governor-General.</p>
<p>  However, under the conventions of our system the Queen would be bound to<br />
   accept the advice of the Prime Minister to remove the Governor-General.<br />
   The very requirement of formal advice to the Queen, together with the formal<br />
   consideration by her and the time taken, however short this may be, could<br />
   act as a valuable additional check against totally arbitrary removal.</p>
<p>  I therefore find it difficult to accept the argument advanced by some that<br />
   the president in the proposed republican model would have greater security<br />
   of tenure than the Governor-General.</p>
<p>  As I say, I believe that, on balance, the reverse is the case.</p>
<p>  Reserve powers</p>
<p>  Under the model it is not proposed to specify the reserve powers of the<br />
   Governor-General. It is commonly believed that the reserve powers relate<br />
   to appointing and dismissing the Prime Minister, refusing to dissolve the<br />
   Parliament and forcing a dissolution of the Parliament.</p>
<p>  Any lessened security of tenure which has come about by the more arbitrary<br />
   process laid down for the dismissal of a president could also influence<br />
   him or her in the appropriate exercise of these reserve powers.</p>
<p>  Another referendum?</p>
<p>  Recently the Leader of the Opposition, Mr Beazley, and others, have raised<br />
   the possibility of another referendum being held, if the republic wins on<br />
   6 November, to give Australians the chance of deciding whether or not they<br />
   wish to directly elect the president.</p>
<p>  This is a stunt to entice direct election republicans into supporting the<br />
   'yes' case .</p>
<p>  If the republic wins on 6 November there won't be a referendum for a directly<br />
   elected president. The republicans will have got what they wanted.</p>
<p>  Almost all of the prominent politicians who support the 'yes' case for the<br />
   referendum are in favour of the members of Federal Parliament choosing the<br />
   president. Few of them are direct electionists.</p>
<p>  In addition, the majority of those Members of Parliament who advocate a<br />
   'no' vote are just as opposed to a directly elected president as they are<br />
   to the model being proposed.</p>
<p>  If the referendum wins therefore, these two groups will make common cause<br />
   to oppose a direct election option being put to the people.</p>
<p>  I do not agree with those who want a republic in which the people directly<br />
   vote for a president. Their cause is not my cause. I oppose any change to<br />
   the present system.</p>
<p>  I do, however, understand why so many of them are advocating a 'no' vote<br />
   on 6 November.</p>
<p>  If the republican model on offer, whereby the president is chosen by two-thirds<br />
   of the members of the Commonwealth Parliament, wins on 6 November it will<br />
   be there forever.</p>
<p>  Conclusion</p>
<p>  The current Federal Government is the first since Federation to give Australians<br />
   a choice between retaining their form of Government under our Constitution<br />
   or changing to a republican alternative.</p>
<p>  Consistent with our great democratic traditions the result, whatever it<br />
   may be, should be embraced by all Australians.</p>
<p>  My support for a constitutional monarchy is not based on nostalgia.</p>
<p>  Rather it is based on a belief that we will not give ourselves a better<br />
   system of Government if Australia becomes a republic and, in all probability,<br />
   will give ourselves a less effective one.</p>
<p>  I am more ready than most to argue the cause of change when I believe that<br />
   it is in the national interest to do so.</p>
<p>  On issues such as industrial relations and taxation reforms as well as privatisation,<br />
   I have been willing to advocate the need for fundamental reforms, even in<br />
   the face of fierce opposition, because I have seen such reforms as being<br />
   in Australia's interests.</p>
<p>  On other issues however - and the constitutional change to a republic is<br />
   one of them - I will staunchly oppose change because I do not think it will<br />
   benefit Australia. Not all change is for the better, I cannot support change<br />
   for change's sake.</p>
<p>  Prudent nations elect to keep those institutions which continue to work,<br />
   and discard those which don't.</p>
<p>  Not even the most zealous republicans in our midst would claim that our<br />
   system has broken down, that the constitutional monarchy in Australia is<br />
   in a state of crisis.</p>
<p>  In fact, republicans have paid a massive compliment to the present system<br />
   by continually arguing that the change they want is minuscule, that it is<br />
   virtually no change at all.</p>
<p>  Some republicans imply that it is almost unAustralian not to want a republic.<br />
   Such an attitude is offensive.</p>
<p>  There are passionate and deeply patriotic Australians on both sides of this<br />
   debate.</p>
<p>  As I move around Australia I find no great groundswell for change. Intense<br />
   debate is confined to the deeply committed on each side.</p>
<p>  Even amongst many who intend to vote 'yes' there is a ready acknowledgment<br />
   that there are far more important issues on the national agenda.</p>
<p>  In these circumstances Australians are right to be sceptical about the need<br />
   for change. I hope they reject the republic. It will not produce a better<br />
   Australia.</p>
<p>  Why I say "Yes" to the preamble</p>
<p>  As well as voting on the republican issue people are being asked to approve<br />
   a preamble. A preamble is a broad statement of values and principles which<br />
   aim to reflect the spirit, traditions and sentiment which underpin our commitment<br />
   to the Constitution.</p>
<p>  It would also provide Australians with an opportunity to highlight the aspirations<br />
   we share as we enter the second century of our nationhood.</p>
<p>  The great value of the preamble is that it can unite republicans and anti-republicans<br />
   behind commonly held Australian values. It is not conditional on whether<br />
   the republic is supported or rejected.</p>
<p>  It can also make a contribution to the reconciliation process which is one<br />
   of the most important issues we face as a nation as we enter the new century.<br />
   The preamble honours "Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders, the nation's<br />
   first people, for their deep kinship with their lands and for their ancient<br />
   and continuing cultures which enrich the life of our country".</p>
<p>  The preamble also talks about those people who defended our country and<br />
   our liberty in time of war. It honours all those Australians who contributed<br />
   in so many different ways and expresses the deep respect and appreciation<br />
   of a grateful nation.</p>
<p>  The important role of the States and Territories in our federal system of<br />
   Government is highlighted as is the nation building contribution of generations<br />
   of immigrants, our responsibility to preserve our unique natural environment<br />
   and the special value we place on both fairness and achievement.</p>
<p>  This is a worthy affirmation of national values and ideals that is suitably<br />
   made as we prepare to celebrate the centenary of our Federation.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
