<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9284</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP LAUNCH OF THE GREAT BARRIER REEF STRATEGIC PLAN, TOWNSVILLE, WEDNESDAY, 20 JULY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/07/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009284.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
i7<br />
A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
LAUNCH OF THE GREAT BARRIER REEF STRATEGIC PLAN,<br />
TOWNSVILLE, WEDNESDAY, 20 JULY 1994<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, may I begin by saying what a<br />
pleasure it is to be here with you today for the launch of<br />
the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority's strategic<br />
plan. It is always a pleasure to visit an area as beautiful as<br />
Townsville and the welcome you have given me today<br />
makes my visit even more enjoyable.<br />
I don't think that anyone who has experienced the<br />
magnificence of the Great Barrier Reef would deny its<br />
significance, nationally and internationally. It ranks as<br />
one of Australia's greatest and best known natural<br />
features. It constitutes the world's largest marine<br />
protected area, extending for some 2,000 kilometres along<br />
Australia's northeast coast and covering an area of<br />
344,000 square kilometres about the same area as<br />
Victoria and Tasmania combined.<br />
While the reef is an area of stunning natural beauty, it is<br />
also an extremely fragile habitat for thousands of different<br />
species of marine life, and has been declared the world's<br />
first particularly sensitive area by the International<br />
Maritime Organisation.<br />
The reef is not only significant for its natural beauty and<br />
as a habitat, but also for its recreational, cultural and<br />
economic relevance. This encompasses commercial and<br />
recreational fishing, Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander<br />
heritage and activities, and tourism.<br />
Economically, the reef is estimated to be worth an<br />
estimated $ 1.4 billion per annum in tourism and fishing<br />
income, with tourism income growing at an estimated 10<br />
per cent a year. The significance of an environmental<br />
feature unique in the world can never be measured in<br />
monetary terms, but I do think it is possible to note that<br />
the regional and national investment in the Great Barrier </p>
<p>Reef has an economically measurable facet, in addition to<br />
its other dimensions.<br />
This collective investment is underpinned by a<br />
responsibility to protect and preserve the reef for the<br />
benefit of future generations of Australians and, indeed,<br />
for all those from around the world who are yet to marvel<br />
at the beauty of the reef.<br />
Managing the reef in an ecologically sustainable way has<br />
been a priority for the Commonwealth and the Queensland<br />
Governments. I am pleased to be able to say that the<br />
peace and harmony which the reef can inspire have<br />
extended into Commonwealth-State relations when issues<br />
of protecting the reef have come up. Several<br />
complementary management agreements for the reef have<br />
been concluded between Queensland and the<br />
Commonwealth, and I thank the Queensland Government<br />
for its very welcome continued co-operation.<br />
Recognition of the need to protect the reef dates back to<br />
1975 when the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Act was<br />
passed with bipartisan support. Formal international<br />
recognition of the reef's universal value came in 1981,<br />
when it was inscribed on the World Heritage List.<br />
To further protect it, the Commonwealth enacted legislation<br />
in 1991 making it compulsory for all large vessels,<br />
particularly those carrying oil and environmentally<br />
hazardous chemicals, to carry a pilot while navigating the<br />
northern section of the reef. No other country in the world<br />
has been able to obtain international acceptance of the<br />
need for foreign ships to carry pilots in international<br />
waters, and I think this acceptance indicates the<br />
international recognition of the need to protect this unique<br />
natural wonder.<br />
It is this need for protection and ecologically sustainable<br />
management of the reef that prompted the Great Barrier<br />
Reef Strategic Plan. The plan itself is an achievement<br />
unique in the world, and perhaps rightly so given the<br />
unique nature of the reef.<br />
It represents an ambitious and farsighted effort to develop<br />
a long term vision for the Great Barrier Reef World<br />
Heritage Area, by formulating appropriate objectives and<br />
management strategies for ecologically sustainable<br />
development. Creating the plan involved a comprehensive..<br />
consultative process in which more than 60 peak<br />
organisations and representative bodies from a wide cross<br />
section of the community participated. An independent<br />
chairperson was employed to ensure that competing<br />
interests were considered and to facilitate the joint<br />
decision making process. </p>
<p>A draft plan was widely circulated for public comment and<br />
the final plan has been endorsed by the Queensland<br />
Government and the 60 or more government and nongovernment<br />
bodies. This, of course, reflects what<br />
ecologically sustainable development is all about,<br />
achieving an agreed and workable balance underpinned by<br />
maintenance of the ecological systems on which life<br />
depends. It is a great example of an Australian solution to an<br />
Australian challenge. The challenge was one which no<br />
other country had faced, the solution is one which other<br />
countries and other regions of Australia can take as a<br />
model. I must congratulate Kayt Raymond on her<br />
considerable work as facilitator and leader of the<br />
negotiation and discussion process.<br />
Even at this early stage the strategic plan has already<br />
proven to be a useful and valuable working instrument.<br />
The plan formed a key component of the proposal for a Cooperative<br />
Research Centre to which my government<br />
pledged $ 12.8 million over seven years in 1992. The<br />
centre carries out research into the sustainable<br />
development of the Great Barrier Reef and focuses upon<br />
enabling tourism and environmental managers to<br />
successfully address the stresses which impact upon the<br />
reef. The plan was employed in formulating the Marine<br />
Conservation Strategy devised by the Australian committee<br />
to the International Union for the Conservation of Nature.<br />
It also played a role in the Queensland Government's<br />
decision to ban petroleum exploration and production in its<br />
area of responsibility within the wider World Heritage area.<br />
I want to take this opportunity to extend my congratulations<br />
and thanks to all those involved in formulation of the Great<br />
Barrier Reef Strategic Plan, particularly the Great Barrier<br />
Reef Marine Park Authority and the Queensland<br />
Government. I wish all of those involved with the plan<br />
every success in achieving their objective of long term<br />
ecologically sustainable development for the Great Barrier<br />
Reef. It is an objective all Australians share and one of<br />
significance to the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
