<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6353</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING ACA PREMISES, 30 MARCH 1984, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006353.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGOED UNTIL 4.3OPM CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF ACA PREMISES 30 MARCH 1984 -SYDNEY 0<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It was with real pleasure that I accepted your invitation to<br />
participate in this official opening of the Australian<br />
Consumer Association's ( ACA's) new building.<br />
I have for a long time been impressed with ACA's<br />
contribution to the Australian consumer movement.<br />
1984 has been something of a landmark year for the ACA. The<br />
ACA is celebrating its 25th anniversary and this year its<br />
magazine " Choice" passed the 200,000 subscription mark for<br />
the first time. This suggests the Association is regularly<br />
reaching at least a million readers and that its role in<br />
assisting people make informed purchasing decisions is<br />
widely appreciated.<br />
No doubt these impressive new premises and laboratory<br />
facilities for testing products will enable ACA to further<br />
enhance the quality of its service to consumers.<br />
But as you all know the ACA's role is wider than this.<br />
The establishment in 1979 by ACA of a public affairs unit<br />
was an important extension of its activities beyond the<br />
traditional product testing role. The ACA has for some time<br />
also been very active in seeking to secure attention to<br />
consumer interests by Government decision-makers on a broad<br />
range of matters from health care to communications. This<br />
pressure from ACA was needed and has been effectively<br />
applied. Partly as a result of such pressures Governments today are<br />
more sensitive to legitimate consumer concerns. The<br />
Australian Labor movement has for a long time shared those<br />
concerns and my Government rates them highly. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Indeed, in accord with the extensive! commitments in the 1982<br />
ALP policy platform, the Australian Labor Government is<br />
playing an active and innovative role in consumer affairs.<br />
At a most fundamental level, and of particular interest to<br />
consumers, has been the fact that the Government has turned<br />
the economy on to a path of strong recovery. In doing so we<br />
have laid the basis for continued non-inflationary growth<br />
and increased employment opportunities in the medium and<br />
longer term.. Particular priority has been given to<br />
restoring equality in Australia's social and economic<br />
fabric. Central to our strategy has been the Prices and Incomes<br />
Accord which, as well as ushering in a new era of industrial<br />
harmony in Australia, has provided a firm underpinning to<br />
consumer confidence.<br />
Our policies have helped to produce strong growth in private<br />
consumption expenditure. Coupled with strong public<br />
spending, rebuilding of stocks and our ability to export,<br />
private consumption has been a major element in turning the<br />
economy around and setting it on the path to sustained<br />
recovery. The Government has also embarked on a course aimed at<br />
facilitating structural change as a means of enhancing the<br />
prospects of medium and longer term growth. Such change<br />
will bring with it increased employment and improved living<br />
standards. It should also benefit consumers directly. They<br />
will enjoy lower prices made possible by increased<br />
efficiency in Australian industry and by the reduced burden<br />
of supporting high cost industries.<br />
The Government recognises that a closely focussed set of<br />
policy measures is also needed if more particular concerns<br />
associated with consumer welfare are adequately to be<br />
addressed. Accordingly the Australian Labor Government has<br />
moved rapidly to put the necessary policies into place.<br />
The new Prices Surveillance Authority, which began<br />
operations on 19 March, will directly benefit consumers.<br />
The Authority has been developed as an important instrument<br />
of price restraint. The operations of the authority will<br />
involve monitoring and examining applications for price<br />
increases, and conducting inquiries into prices in<br />
particular areas.<br />
It is not anticipated that the authority will need to<br />
monitor prices over a wide section of industry. The<br />
Government acknowledges and accepts that competitive markets<br />
provide the most effective defence against unwarranted price<br />
increases. The selection of goods and services subjected to<br />
surveillance will focus on areas where effective competitive<br />
disciplines are not present and where price or wage<br />
decisions have pervasive effects throughout the economy. </p>
<p>Another significant milestone for all Australian consumers<br />
is the Medicare Scheme introduced on 1 February.<br />
Those who will gain most from the launch of Medicare are the<br />
two million Australians who up until now have not been<br />
eligible for Government health benefits, who have not been<br />
able to afford private health insurance, and who have had no<br />
protection against crippling medical and hospital bills.<br />
With the introduction of Medicare, for the first time in<br />
many years, Australians are now able to face illness in the<br />
family in the sure knowledge that medical services an~ d<br />
public hospital accommodation and treatment are theirs by<br />
right. All Australians regardless of income are now entitled to<br />
Medicare benefits.<br />
Nor shall we be deflected from this commitment by the<br />
current obstructionism of the doctors.<br />
The Government is dedicated to the operation of an<br />
efficient, high standard health care system. We intend to<br />
provide this through Medicare at a cost that is affordable<br />
to the Australian people.<br />
In this regard the Government simply cannot ignore questions<br />
such as the rapidly increasing cost of diagnostic services.<br />
Diagnostic service costs have increased 40% faster over the<br />
past four years than have costs of all other medical<br />
benefits. It is vital to the future of Medicare, and<br />
clearly in the patients' interests, that such cost increases<br />
by curbed. The Government is determined that they will be.<br />
The Government also has a general responsibility to regulate<br />
the use of public health facilities for private profit, to<br />
ensure that exploitation of the providers of those<br />
facilities the taxpayers does not occur. It takes this<br />
responsibility most seriously.<br />
Another major initiative of benefit to all Australians is<br />
the protection afforded by the recently passed Sex<br />
Discrimination Act. Protection is now guaranteed throughout<br />
Australia against discrimination on the grounds of sex,<br />
marital status or pregnancy in the provision of goods or<br />
services, in working facilities available, in accommodation<br />
and in the disposal of land. It is now, for example,<br />
unlawful to deny a loan to a woman because she is a woman or<br />
to refuse applications for emergency housing on the basis of<br />
the applicant's marital status. The Government has now<br />
ensured that those disadvantaged or alone at law have the<br />
full protection of the law.* </p>
<p>4.<br />
The enactment of the Trade Practices Act in 1974 by the then<br />
Labor Government marked the major entry of the Commonwealth<br />
into consumer affairs.<br />
This Government is committed to ensuring the Act continues<br />
to provide effective protection for consumers. To this end<br />
a draft amending bill was released for public comment on 21<br />
February 1984.<br />
The Government wants to obtain the views of consumer groups<br />
and other interested parties on the proposed amendments.<br />
Their views will be taken into account before amending<br />
legislation is introduced in the Parliament later this year.<br />
The Government will continue to encourage and support the<br />
active enforcement of the Trade Practices Act by the Trade<br />
Practices Commission.<br />
Under the previous Government the Commission was severely<br />
hampered in its forcement activities by a ministerial<br />
direction which required the Commsssion to limit its<br />
consumer protection work to matters that raised issues of<br />
importance at the national level and which were brought to<br />
attention from outside the Commission. The Attorney-General<br />
has recently revoked this restrictive direction.<br />
There has, as well, been a substantial increase in the<br />
number of prosecution proceedings instituted by the<br />
Commission under the consumer protection provisions of the<br />
Trade Practices Act during the past year. It has also been<br />
proposed that penalties for breaches of the Act be increased<br />
five-fold an increase that would bring penalties to a<br />
level more likely to serve as a deterrant than was the case<br />
previously. The Government is as well making useful progress in<br />
consultation with the States and Territories on the<br />
development of uniform consumer protection laws throughout<br />
Australia. The Standing Committee of Commonwealth and State Consumer<br />
Affairs Ministers is actively pursuing this issue, and has<br />
established a special working party of officers to examine<br />
it. State ministers have asked the Commonwealth to consider<br />
a number of additional changes to the present Trade<br />
Practices Act which they consider would facilitate the<br />
achievement of uniformity by making the act a suitable basis<br />
for mirror legislation elsewhere in the Commonwealth. A<br />
list of these changes has been released for public comment.<br />
Consumers also have a major interest in information relating<br />
to Government activities, programs and service. The Freedom<br />
of Information Act makes a substantial contribution to the<br />
evolution of open Government in Australia. </p>
<p>The legislation has been strengthened by amendments which<br />
came into force on 1 January 1984. Those amendments widen<br />
the scope of the Act as well as clarifying and improving its<br />
practical operation. They have also provided for<br />
researchers being given access to material ante-dating the<br />
original legislation. In this way we have given the Act a<br />
greater practical significance.<br />
I understand that ACA has been active in stimulating public<br />
awareness of the rights of citizens under the new Act. In<br />
particular, ACA is to be congratulated on its work with the<br />
Public Interest Advocacy Centre in the development of a<br />
handbook to assist community groups in using the FOL<br />
legislation. The Government has also moved quickly to legislate to<br />
protect consumers in other areas such as insurance.<br />
Last year we introduced two Bills into Parliament one to<br />
regulate the activities of Life and General Insurance Agents<br />
to strengthen the finacial stability of the industry; the<br />
other to improve the information flow and general<br />
relationship between the insurer and the insured.<br />
Public comment on the Bills is being analysed with a view to<br />
proceeding with the Bills in the Autumn Session of<br />
Parliament. The Government is also committed to ensuring that the<br />
consumer voice will be heard and taken into account in<br />
Government decision-making.<br />
The Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations ( AFCO),<br />
of which ACA is a member, was established in 1974 with the<br />
sponsorship of the then Labor Government. AFCO receives<br />
considerable financial support from the Government to assist<br />
it in representing the consumer viewpoint to Government and<br />
in industry policy formulation and decision-making bodies.<br />
The Government is appointing consumer representatives to<br />
appropriate advisory bodies. We have, for example, already<br />
appointed Dr John Braithwaite of AFCO to EPAC, our chief<br />
economic advisory council.<br />
The new and expanded membership of the National Consumer<br />
Affairs Advisory Council was announced on 15 March. The<br />
Government expects the Council to play an increasing role in<br />
developing policy advice on consumer affairs matters.<br />
By revitalising the National Consumer Affairs Advisory<br />
Council, which includes members from consumer organisations,<br />
business, trade unions and Government, we have provided a<br />
national focus for consumer interests. Through it we also<br />
hope to foster more effective and productive co-operation<br />
and liaison between business organisations and consumer<br />
groups on matters of consumer interest. </p>
<p>Ladies and gentelmen,<br />
Work is underway in many other areas, including consumer<br />
education and information programs, product safety and<br />
recall procedures for hazardous products, uniformity of<br />
packaging and labelling and a national compensation scheme<br />
for loss or damage resulting from the collapse of a travel<br />
agency plus licensing legislation for travel agents.<br />
Notwithstanding this, there is still much to be done to<br />
ensure that consumer concerns are addressed in a<br />
comprehensive an adequate manner.<br />
The Government looks forward to meeting this challenge in<br />
co-operation with a strong consumer movement.<br />
In this regard ACA has a particularly important role to<br />
play. It is therefore with pleasure that I formally open this new<br />
building. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
