<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1656</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, CH, MP, ON APPROPRIATION BILL (NO.1) 1967-68 - SECOND READING</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/09/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001656.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
9PEECH 14 SEP 19J67ZBY<br />
Le?~<br />
The Rt Hon. HAROLD HOLT, M. P.,<br />
09<br />
APPROPRIATION BIll ( No. 1) 1967-68<br />
SECOND READING<br />
( BUDGET ' DEBATE)<br />
rFrom t&amp; e ' Parliamentary Debates', 5 September 1967]<br />
Mr HAROLD' HOLT ( Higgins-Prime<br />
Minister) [ 8.* 27)-The honourable member<br />
for Bendigo ( Mr Beaton) is an amiable,<br />
pleasant-mannered fellow, and he has<br />
done his best tonight to lash himself into<br />
a fury through the written script that he<br />
has just given us. But I do give him full<br />
marks for brazen effrontery because in the<br />
earlier part of his address he told us that<br />
the members of his Party were in a<br />
position to amend a budget if they chose<br />
to' do so. The honourable member knows<br />
that not one in ten of the parliamentary<br />
meiiib~ rs of the Australian Labor Party<br />
has any say in the formation of policies<br />
which are adopted and which the members<br />
of the, Opposition are required to pursue,<br />
like dumb, driven cattle, in this Parliament.<br />
I would like to spend some time on<br />
some of the extravagant things that the<br />
hohourabli member said, but my own time<br />
is* limited tonight. I hope that in the course<br />
of what I have to' say I will cover several<br />
of the matters to which the honourable<br />
mirml~ er has directed* attention. I would like<br />
1253/ 67 to deal particularly with some of his<br />
references to social services and matters of<br />
that kind.<br />
Let me start by saying something about<br />
those who are the spokesmen for this<br />
regimented band who sit opposite us. First,<br />
to do him the honour that is due to his<br />
position of Federal President of the Australian<br />
Labor Party, I quote Senator Keeffe.<br />
It is only because he holds that office that<br />
I think it desirable or appropriate to refer<br />
to his statements, but when he happens to<br />
head the body which decides the policies<br />
which the elected representatives of the<br />
people on the Opposition side of the House<br />
have to follow he is entitled at least to<br />
this nominal recognition. Long before my<br />
colleague presented his Budget Senator<br />
Keeffe said, as reported in the Melbourne<br />
' Age' on 1st August: ' The Australian<br />
economy is like a worn out motor vehicle.<br />
The Government has patched it up here<br />
and there but basically the economic<br />
machine is no longer roadworthy'. I merely </p>
<p>ask honourable members to note those<br />
remarks and bear in mind that they come<br />
from the head of the supreme policy<br />
making body of the Labor Party. I then<br />
ask honourable members to dismiss the<br />
remarks from their minds as being completely<br />
without entitlement to the regard<br />
of this place, certainly as they apply to<br />
the state of Australia as we know it at the<br />
present time. But, of course, the Leader<br />
of the Opposition ( Mr Whitlam) had his<br />
own comment to make. He professed to<br />
find in the Budget no sense of purpose<br />
or direction, no guide lines for national.<br />
growth and no evidence that the Government<br />
is prepared to take initiatives and<br />
accept responsibilities in order to achieve<br />
that growth. He asserted that the Government<br />
is neglecting national development,<br />
social services and the needs of the States.<br />
Let us look at a few facts. It is not easy,<br />
of course, to go back and compare what<br />
a Labor government in office has done. It<br />
is not easy to find from the professions of<br />
policy what a Labor government would do.<br />
If we look at Labor's printed platform we<br />
see in its modern form a picture on the<br />
front cover of the man of destiny. The old<br />
car has been given a new coat of duco, but<br />
the works are the same if we bother to<br />
examine it. But even if we examine this<br />
document we will find there is a gloss or<br />
an interpretation of policy provided to suit<br />
the audiences of the day-something which<br />
differs very much from the precise statement<br />
appearing in the printed document. So I<br />
have to go back a long-way, but there have<br />
been in this country, so far as national<br />
politics are concerned, periods when a<br />
Labor government has been in office, but on<br />
those occasions the people of Australia have<br />
quickly had cause to regret that Labor was<br />
in power. And when the people have put<br />
the Labor government out they have kept it<br />
out long enough for another generation to<br />
come along which has forgotten the kind of<br />
government that existed earlier. So if I<br />
want to show what a Labor government<br />
would have done in circumstances corresponding<br />
to those which exist now I must<br />
go back far into the past.<br />
Frankly, we on this side are getting a<br />
little fed up with the humbug from honourable<br />
gentlemen opposite who claim that they<br />
have some monopoly of concern for the<br />
less privileged sections of the community, who claim that only they have concern for<br />
the pensioner, the widow, the children or<br />
the repatriated soldier. They can make these<br />
sweeping generalisations and these offensive<br />
sneers, but what counts with the people are<br />
the facts, and I have the facts. The last<br />
Budget brought down by a Labor government<br />
was in 1949-50. That Budget provided<br />
a total of $ 185.6m for national welfare in<br />
Australia. In this Budget we have provided<br />
a total for national welfare of $ 1,071m. We<br />
may talk about changes in the value of<br />
money and population growth, but we still<br />
, cannot avoid the proper conclusion that<br />
there has been a very substantial improvement<br />
in the real benefits conferred on those<br />
people who are beneficiaries under the<br />
National Welfare Fund.<br />
We have just been chided about our<br />
health scheme. What sort of health scheme<br />
existed when Labor was in office? There<br />
was a hospital benefits scheme of a sort. In<br />
1949-50 Labor spent $ 610,000 on pharmaceutical<br />
benefits. This year we are providing<br />
in the Budget $ 75.2m for pharmaceutical<br />
benefits. Under the last Labor Government<br />
there was no medical benefits scheme. This<br />
year we are spending in this field $ 45.8m.<br />
Honourable members opposite weep their<br />
crocodile tears about the pensioners. What<br />
about the provision of pharmaceutical<br />
benefits for pensioners? Not a cracker was<br />
spent in this direction when Labor was last<br />
in office, but this year we will spend<br />
$ 38.1m on pharmaceutical benefits for pensioners.<br />
Under Labor there was no medical<br />
services scheme for pensioners. This year<br />
in this area we have provided $ 16.5m.<br />
I could talk about the aged persons<br />
homes scheme, which is an innovation of<br />
this Government. I could talk about the<br />
liberalisation of the means test under this<br />
Government. I could talk about the<br />
improved position of the single pensioner,<br />
whether man or woman, widowed or unmarried,<br />
under this Government. All these<br />
facets go to make up the whole: Labor in<br />
1949-50 provided $ 185.6m for national<br />
welfare, whereas we in this Budget have<br />
provided $ 1,071m. We have been able to<br />
do this because under our leadership the<br />
economy has expanded and thrived. From<br />
it, without wrecking initiative or preventing<br />
people' from getting on with the job, we<br />
have been able to provide an increasing<br />
amount for the pensioners of this country. </p>
<p>There is another practical test of the<br />
Government's concern for national welfare<br />
and that is the proportion of the Budget<br />
devoted to social welfare. It must be borne<br />
in mind that compared with 1949-50, we<br />
have had to more than double the proportion<br />
of the Budget devoted to defence. In 1949-<br />
only 8.3% of the Budget was earmarked<br />
for defence. That was the last Budget<br />
presented by a Labor government. This<br />
year's Budget provides 17.25% of total expenditure<br />
for defence. But despite the<br />
claims on us of defence, development, international<br />
aid and education, in this Budget<br />
we have provided 20.55% of total expenditure<br />
for social welfare. This compares<br />
with a figure of 18.7% provided for social<br />
welfare when Labor was last in office. I<br />
referred to our commitment in the field<br />
of education. Relatively speaking, the<br />
allocation for education in the last Labor<br />
Budget was negligible. I concede immediately<br />
that the Labor Government's last<br />
Budget was very much smaller than today's<br />
Budget for a variety of reasons.<br />
But today we are making a larger percentage<br />
of the total Budget available for<br />
social welfare, and it is an infinitely larger<br />
budget because we have been able to promote<br />
the growth of the country enormously.<br />
As the Treasurer ( Mr McMahon) has<br />
pointed out, over the last 5 years we have<br />
averaged, in terms of constant prices, an<br />
increase of 5f% in our gross national product.<br />
This figure has not been exceeded in<br />
that period by any industrialised country<br />
with the exception of Japan. I remind<br />
honourable members that in the period to<br />
which I have referred we experienced a<br />
dreadful drought year during which the<br />
increase in our gross national product was<br />
of the order of only And still honourable<br />
gentlemen opposite sneer at us and<br />
talk about a worn out motor. Whom do<br />
they think they are talking to? Do they<br />
think they are addressing the fully employed<br />
people of this country who know that no<br />
other country has succeeded in maintaining<br />
a level of employment so consistently<br />
high as has this Government since it came<br />
to office in 1949? Who has devoted such a<br />
large proportion of the Budget to social welfare?<br />
Who has been able to provide the<br />
best defence set-up in the history of Australia<br />
apart from a period of all out war?<br />
The people are not fools. They cannot be misled by such specious nonsense as comes<br />
from honourable gentlemen opposite.<br />
I do not want to devote all of my time<br />
tonight to these matters. The Leader of the<br />
Opposition has found the Budget unsatisfactory.<br />
He cannot find it extravagant and<br />
unrealistic as regards promises because of<br />
what was put to us from his side at the<br />
last elections. He will not find in the Budget<br />
the kind of bureaucratic plan that<br />
gladdens his heart. He will not find a<br />
detailed blueprint to predetermine the future<br />
pattern of growth and structure of an<br />
economy which can point to the kind of<br />
record I have indicated. This Government<br />
does not go in for that kind of thing. What<br />
is to be found is a record of achievement<br />
which most countries and most objective<br />
observers applaud. He will find a continuation<br />
of the ' sound and responsible policies<br />
which have made our achievements possible<br />
and which offer the best prospects of<br />
further rapid progress in the future. He<br />
acknowledges-we accept his acknowledgment-<br />
that there is a fundamental difference<br />
between the approach of this<br />
Government and the parties that support<br />
it towards the development of the nation<br />
and the approach of the Labor Party. He<br />
says that the Budget is highly doctrinaire,<br />
expressing the old blind faith in the natural<br />
superiority of private enterprise over public<br />
endeavour. It is not the Government that<br />
is doctrinaire in its approach. This is<br />
plainly shown by our record. In the<br />
Government's view the public sector and<br />
the private sector each have essential and<br />
complementary roles to play in national<br />
growth. At times circumstances will call for<br />
a faster expansion of public sector activities<br />
than private sector activities and at other<br />
times the converse will be appropriate.<br />
Over the past few years circumstances have<br />
made it necessary to give greater emphasis<br />
to the public sector. The Government has<br />
done this. Between 1962-63 and 1966-67<br />
public sector spending as a proportion of<br />
total spending increased from 19% to 21%.<br />
In the past 2 years 44% of the increase in<br />
employment has gone to the public sector.<br />
But now, as my colleague the Treasurer<br />
pointed out so convincingly, there is a need<br />
to ensure that the private sector and particularly<br />
private developmental activity is<br />
given scope for greater growth. </p>
<p>The Leader of the Opposition's speech<br />
was directed almost wholly to decrying what<br />
the Government has done and is doing,<br />
and on this I have mentioned some of the<br />
important facts. Defence is another element.<br />
As our present defence build up began 5<br />
years ago, we might well review briefly<br />
what we have achieved in the economy during<br />
this period, despite the diversion of<br />
a very large amount of resources to<br />
defence. The facts about the increases in<br />
defence expenditure are well known and I<br />
need not repeat them beyond observing<br />
that the provision we are making for<br />
defence this year is nearly $ 700m or 160%<br />
greater than in 1962-63-5 years ago. What<br />
has happened in other directions? Notwithstanding<br />
this rapid build up in the defence<br />
effort, the economy has kept growing at<br />
a good rate and on sound lines and the<br />
high rate of investment, both by the public<br />
sector and the private sector, has been sustained.<br />
Only one country, Japan, retains<br />
more of its gross national income for capital<br />
investment purposes than does Australia.<br />
Exports have been rising strongly and our<br />
external financial position has been kept<br />
sound. Considerable improvements have<br />
been made, as I pointed out, in social and<br />
welfare services, and assistance to the States<br />
has also been rising rapidly. I do not need<br />
to go into all the figures because I have<br />
a more important task tonight, and that is<br />
to examine the alternatives which would<br />
be presented by a government from the<br />
other side of the House. Our aim is balanced<br />
economic growth. We have achieved that<br />
to an unparalleled degree in the last 5 years.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition said that<br />
the economy was barely rolling and had<br />
been in a downswing in the past 2 years;<br />
but he did not quote any figures on the<br />
growth of the economy to support his<br />
assertion. He did not because he could not.<br />
I have already indicated to the House the<br />
extent to which we have sustained the<br />
growth in our national product over these<br />
years in a more even way, despite a<br />
drought, than almost any other country.<br />
Mr Webb-Come on. Liven it up.<br />
Mr DEPUTY SPEAKER ( Mr Lucock)<br />
-Order! The honourable member for<br />
Stirling will cease interjecting.<br />
Mr Webb-I am trying to get the right<br />
honourable gentleman moving. Mr HAROLD HOLT-I will get moving<br />
all right. I am coming to the honourable<br />
member for Stirling right now. I hope to<br />
remind him where he stands. Honourable<br />
members opposite sometimes chide the<br />
Government on high prices. When we came<br />
into office, despite all the controls that the<br />
doctrinaire Labor leaders had been applying,<br />
inflation was running at the rate of<br />
just under 10% per annum.<br />
Mr Duthie-That is an invention.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I shall give the<br />
honourable gentleman the precise statistics.<br />
I shall read a comment that a well respected<br />
Labor authority, Professor Arndt, made in<br />
the Chifley Memorial Lecture in 1956. He<br />
said: S. it is high time Labor took the problem of<br />
inflation as seriously as it has always taken the<br />
problem of deflation and unemployment<br />
Labor's record on this problem in its years of<br />
Opposition has been lamentable<br />
And it has remained lamentable over the<br />
years that have elapsed since then. What is<br />
the policy of the Opposition? It is not easily<br />
ascertained because Labor has not been in<br />
office for many years. The Labor Parry has<br />
a document which purports to contain the<br />
official platform and programme of the<br />
Party but whenever members of the Party<br />
are asked to explain it they give a different<br />
interpretation. They were pinned down on<br />
the subject of Vietnam in quite precise terms<br />
the other day and decided on a policy of<br />
troops out unless the United States accepts<br />
cohditions which the Opposition knows to<br />
be entirely unacceptable to that country.<br />
The honourable member for Melbourne ( Mr<br />
Calwell) claimed this decision to be a vindication<br />
of his policy and the honourable<br />
member for Yarra ( Dr J. F. Cairns) said it<br />
was something that justified his position.<br />
The decision was described by Mr Brown,<br />
the State President of the Labor Party in<br />
Victoria, as a ' troops out unless' policy. So<br />
that is where the Opposition stands on that<br />
issue. But where does it stand on its Socialist<br />
pledge because I am dealing now with economic<br />
issues and if Labor is the alternative<br />
government the country is entitled to know<br />
its economic policy. I understand the Leader<br />
of the Opposition is unavoidably absent<br />
tonight. I regret that because I would have<br />
liked to say this to his face and I expect<br />
to do so as time goes on. I will quote from<br />
an article that he wrote. I do not think he </p>
<p>will challenge its accuracy. This article was<br />
published in the ' Australian' of 18th February<br />
1967, after the honourable gentleman<br />
had been appointed Leader of the Opposition.<br />
The article is headed ' Labor and the<br />
Future'. I would happily incorporate the<br />
entire article in Hansard should anyone so<br />
desire. In the course of the article the<br />
Leader of the Opposition said:<br />
There never was an age when socialism was so<br />
nearly inevitable; there never was a country where<br />
it was so necessary.<br />
I ask the House to dwell on those two<br />
sentences because there will be a lot of<br />
receding from them at a later point. I will<br />
repeat the passage:<br />
There never was an age when socialism was so<br />
nearly inevitable; there never was a country where<br />
it was so necessary.<br />
I remember the former Leader of the<br />
Opposition, the honourable member for<br />
Melbourne, saying publicly that he wanted<br />
to change the face of Australia and the<br />
present leader is reported to have said-<br />
I think in a Chifley Memorial Addressthat<br />
the intention of the Labor Party was<br />
not simply to redistribute income but to remould<br />
Australia. I do not know how many<br />
Australians want the face of the country<br />
changed or how many want the country remoulded.<br />
The country is doing pretty well.<br />
It has the high standard of progress that I<br />
have mentioned, it has a happy people, and<br />
it is increasing its standing in the eyes of the<br />
rest of the world. Nobody who votes for<br />
honourable gentlemen opposite in a desire<br />
to remove this Government will be able to<br />
say to us afterwards, ' We didn't know it<br />
was loaded', because the Opposition has<br />
shown that it is loaded. Anyone who cares<br />
to study what the Leader of the Opposition<br />
has been consistentlysaying over the years<br />
will realise that it is in the tone of the<br />
sentences I have quoted. In the same speech,<br />
the honourable gentleman. continued:<br />
Australia's danger is that it may acquire a sort<br />
of ' socialism' in a fit of absence of mind, under<br />
the uncomprehending glare of a Government whose<br />
doctrinaire objections to what is happening become<br />
more obsessive as they grow more irrelevant.<br />
As units in the economy grow larger and become<br />
more international and as society becomes more<br />
technological and urban, so socialism becomes<br />
more relevant and urgent. The forces which man<br />
is unleashing in the world must be the subject of<br />
public and not exclusively private decision and<br />
control. Our social and political advance-the degree to<br />
which the people, through their elected representatives,<br />
control and fashion their own future-is<br />
badly lagging behind scientific and technological<br />
change. Democratic socialism is a philosophy about the<br />
value of man.<br />
I say Liberalism is a philosophy about the<br />
value of man-the freedom, the opportunity,<br />
the incentive, that can be given to<br />
man. There is a fundamental cleavage<br />
between the viewpoint of those who sit in<br />
support of the Government-we cannot get<br />
them all on this side of the House, but I<br />
embrace those who support the Government<br />
on these matters-and those who<br />
support the Socialist doctrines opposite.<br />
Public ownership and public control of the<br />
economy are more than ever central to a<br />
Labor programme for government. The<br />
members of the Labor Party sometimes<br />
plead the limitations of the Constitution.<br />
But the Leader of the Opposition does not.<br />
In the same article, he says:<br />
The limitations of the Constitution are real.<br />
They are not absolute. I have no sympathy with<br />
an attitude which finds in the presumed limitations<br />
of the Constitution an excuse for avoiding<br />
the search for constructive, relevant and realistic<br />
methods of applying our policy and attaining our<br />
objectives. The honourable gentleman has indicated<br />
where he stands. He will gloss it over, he<br />
will blur it, he will fog it up, he will make<br />
it impossible of discernment to a critical<br />
audience. But there it is in plain black and<br />
white. If that is not what the Opposition<br />
stands for, what does it stand for? I would<br />
like to have quoted from what the shadow<br />
Treasurer said. He said that the Budget is<br />
an engine for the redistribution of the<br />
wealth of the community, which is only a<br />
polite way of saying: We are going to take<br />
from him and give to him or to her. Up<br />
to a point, that is so. Up to a point, that<br />
is what we do. I do not know any free<br />
country in the world where what is produced<br />
by the community is more fairly<br />
and evenly distributed amongst the community<br />
than it is in Australia. If anyone<br />
opposite can point to a country where it<br />
is, then let him point to it. What honourable<br />
members opposite would do would be<br />
to kill the productive forces of the community.<br />
We realise the good sense of keeping<br />
incentive alive, of encouraging people<br />
with a willingness to take risks to put their<br />
effort into the job, to hazard their savings </p>
<p>in order to do something better for themselves.<br />
We realise the importance of encouraging<br />
capital, not just of domestic<br />
capital, although 90% of our own investment<br />
in Australia comes from our own resources,<br />
but the capital of others who come here<br />
and take the risks with us. Honourable<br />
members opposite chide us about northern<br />
development. I wonder whether they know<br />
that at this moment projects are going on<br />
in the north of Australia to the value of<br />
S2,000m. Do they know that the rate of<br />
population growth in the north of Australia<br />
has been greater than in the south of Australia<br />
over the last significant period of<br />
years-I think it is the last 5 years-for<br />
which I have statistics? They chide us that<br />
there is not this development going on and<br />
they say that private investment will not<br />
undertake it. But this is what is being done,<br />
and it is being done because we have<br />
created the kind of climate in which people<br />
who are prepared to take risks feel tnat<br />
there will be a reward-a return for their<br />
risks. We are told there is no Australian<br />
equity in this sort of investment. Why,<br />
from every $ 100 of profit we take $ 42.50<br />
in tax. If any of the remainder apart from<br />
what is ploughed back into further development<br />
in the business is remitted overseas,<br />
then we take 15%, or 30% o, according to<br />
the relevant rate of tax, of what is remitted.<br />
So we have. a very real practical potential<br />
interest in the profitability of investment in<br />
Australia. I repeat that the investment made<br />
by our own people represents from 85%<br />
to 90% of the total of the investment which<br />
others from overseas are prepared to make.<br />
It is because of that that we have had the<br />
enormous growth in our national income<br />
which has not merely enabled us to more<br />
than double the defence provision of this<br />
country over the last 5 years but which<br />
has enabled us to go on steadily improving<br />
the provision for development, the provision<br />
-for social welfare and the provision for<br />
international aid.<br />
I feel that my colleague the Treasurer<br />
is to be congratulated on bringing down a<br />
Budget which has enjoyed a more favour-,<br />
able national reception than any Budget<br />
that I can recall in my public lifetime. He<br />
has done that with a full consciousness that he is keeping alive the spirit of enterprise,<br />
that he is giving encouragement to<br />
incentive, and that he is building up a<br />
national income from which our standards<br />
are improved and from which our defence<br />
effort can be strengthened and because of<br />
which confidence in the future of Aus<br />
tralia will be strongly sustained.<br />
When the people of Australia know<br />
these things, when they consider in far<br />
more detail than I can give tonight, but<br />
in the kind of detail which I hope honourable<br />
members on this side of the House<br />
will be giving in the period ahead, what<br />
alternative is offered in terms of policy<br />
by honourable gentlemen opposite, then I<br />
do not think they will have any doubt as<br />
to where they should turn. I can recall a<br />
very respected Labor leader in this House<br />
telling us years ago of Labor's attitude to<br />
employment. We have sustained full<br />
employment. I refer to the late Mr Chifley.<br />
Mlr Curtin-The Prime Minister called<br />
him a Communist.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I have never<br />
called him a Communist in my life, but I<br />
know people in the honourable member's<br />
Party who helped to bring him to an untimely<br />
end. The honourable member should<br />
not stir up these old embers. I have<br />
been in this place a long time and I know<br />
the factors which operated on some former<br />
Labour leaders. The late Mr Chifley,<br />
dedicated as he was to full employment,<br />
made it clear that Labor's view on full<br />
employment was not the voluntary movement<br />
of people from job to job. He pointed<br />
out that there might have to be transfers<br />
of whole communities. I can remember his<br />
saying something to this effect-and<br />
honourable members opposite will not<br />
challenge it: ' You need not think you are<br />
going to sleep in the same bed every night<br />
or look at the same Town Hall clock. You<br />
will go where a job is provided for you.'<br />
We have sustained full employment in this<br />
country on a voluntary basis. We have<br />
enabled people to take the jobs of their<br />
own choosing and -the economic climate<br />
has been so right that not only have they<br />
had the jobs but the great mass of new<br />
settlers who have come to us have been<br />
quickly placed in employment and added<br />
to our strength.<br />
BY AUTHORITY: A. J. ARTHUR~, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA, A. C. T, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
