<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19430</transcript-id>
    <title>Speech To The Ethnic Business Awards</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/06/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>I want to offer a special acknowledgment to the Founder and Chairman of these Awards, Mr Joseph Assaf</p>
<p>Joseph has made a towering contribution to multiculturalism and to the business community.</p>
<p>His deep commitment to the values of innovation, tolerance and social equity has become legendary.</p>
<p>That's why I've appointed Joseph to the Civil Society 20 group  -  the C20  -  as part of our wider engagement process for the G20 meeting in Australia next year.</p>
<p>A big part of our effort will be showcasing Australia's multicultural success-story and how it helps us reach out to the world.</p>
<p>Multiculturalism is a success story.</p>
<p>Perhaps our greatest success as a modern nation.</p>
<p>And 25 years of the Ethnic Business Awards show just what that achievement means.</p>
<p>For a quarter of a century, we've been celebrating men and women who have come to this country with their worldly goods in a suitcase, with hands ready for hard work and heads busy with ambitious dreams.</p>
<p>Migrants who have founded the businesses that have shaped this nation.</p>
<p>The tradesmen and labourers who delivered nation-building infrastructure like the Snowy Hydro scheme.</p>
<p>The family construction companies that built our city suburbs, street by street, in the post-war boom years.</p>
<p>The mum-and-dad entrepreneurs who gave us great and enduring family-owned businesses, from the corner shop to our iconic department stores and shopping malls.</p>
<p>The men and women who have become property moguls and giants of manufacturing.</p>
<p>And the ones who have created the local jobs that have kept our towns and our regional economies humming.</p>
<p>And now, new generations of arrivals who are engaging the world, at the outer frontiers of new technologies.</p>
<p>Ethnic businesses have much to do with the prosperity, stability and strength of our economy.</p>
<p>While there are some who leave the land of their birth in desperation, fleeing war or persecution, escaping a nightmare, many others  -  including my family  -  make the life-changing decision as a clear choice.</p>
<p>As the fulfilment of a dream.</p>
<p>Through human history, migration has, to some extent, selected the risk-takers.</p>
<p>The men and women who see opportunity and seize it.</p>
<p>Those who see a glass half full and have a plan for the other half.</p>
<p>The very qualities so essential to business and entrepreneurialism.</p>
<p>Thirty per cent of small business owners operating in Australia today were born overseas.</p>
<p>Six of the top 10 Australian billionaires listed in BRW's Richest 200 list had a first- or second-generation migrant or refugee background.</p>
<p>The spirit, energy and ingenuity of our ethnic businessmen and women are things that cannot be taught, or bought.</p>
<p>They come from within.</p>
<p>But there are things governments can do to make the first steps of a new migrant steadier.</p>
<p>Things we can do as a generous and welcoming community, and which we have been doing for decades through programs like the successful Adult Migrant English Program.</p>
<p>But it is important that we also hold out a hand not just of welcome, but of help, to the children of those who have newly arrived.</p>
<p>The boys and girls who will design the cities of our tomorrow, manufacture the products of our future, dream up the innovations of the next century.</p>
<p>But before they embark on those lives, they need a good education.</p>
<p>And that means proficiency in English.</p>
<p>Our schools already offer effective and intensive English-language tuition.</p>
<p>But I believe we can do more.</p>
<p>That's why, as part of the Government's National Plan for School Improvement I'm determined to see greater resources go to students who speak languages other than English at home.</p>
<p>About 100,000 girls and boys stand to benefit from this additional funding.</p>
<p>It's an important investment.</p>
<p>An investment in the lives and prospects of individual boys and girls, at a time of profound transition in their lives.</p>
<p>I want to make sure that the new life we hold out to migrant children and their families is a life of genuine opportunity from the very start.</p>
<p>Of course, if proficiency in English is crucial for those making new homes here, proficiency in languages other than English  -  particularly the languages of Asia  -  is becoming essential to our national economic interest.</p>
<p>The Asian Century has dawned.</p>
<p>The centre of world economic activity is moving closer.</p>
<p>The share of world output generated within 10,000km of Australia's borders has doubled over the past half century.</p>
<p>It now accounts for more than a third of all global output.</p>
<p>This will rise to around half of all global output by 2030 - the year a child born today will finish high school.</p>
<p>I want that child  -  and every child of that generation  -  to have the chance to continuously study a priority Asian language throughout their years of schooling:</p>
<p>Mandarin, Hindi, Indonesian or Japanese.</p>
<p>Of course, the reality is that the example of multilingualism is already being set for us, daily by members of the ethnic business community.</p>
<p>Men and women fluent in the languages of our current and future trading partners, and fluent too in the cultural nuances so crucial in a global marketplace.</p>
<p>Our ethnic businessmen and women carried these skills with them when they came to Australia.</p>
<p>Now they pass them to their children and grandchildren.</p>
<p>It's an inheritance from which we all gain.</p>
<p>We've come a long way from the days when we tended to think of ourselves as a melting pot headed towards the goal of assimilation.</p>
<p>We no longer use that language.</p>
<p>And we no longer seek the uniformity that it dictated.</p>
<p>Migrants aren't forced to anglicise their names and disguise their backgrounds.</p>
<p>We can be proudly Lebanese-Australian.</p>
<p>Staunchly Greek-Australian.</p>
<p>We can observe Ramadan, or Hanukkah, or Vesak.</p>
<p>We can trace our family trees, preserve our faiths  -  or profess no faith at all  -  and feel safe in doing so.</p>
<p>We can carry forward our ancestors' names, pass on our mother tongues.</p>
<p>We can gather to mark Glendi or Diwali.</p>
<p>As the founder of these awards, Joseph Assaf, has pointed out, we need look no further than the Chinese and Indian diasporas to know that a growing number of individuals see themselves  -  and behave  -  as transnationals.</p>
<p>Proud Australians, but fully engaged in a wider world of commerce, culture and intellectual inquiry.</p>
<p>Australians, but with a special, and precious, entrée to the world economy.</p>
<p>With the cultural insights, the language skills and the contacts.</p>
<p>Joseph gave a speech some years ago in which he remarked that on Christmas Day, seven million phone calls were made from Australia.</p>
<p>Seven million living connections to the world beyond our shores.</p>
<p>That speech was delivered almost a decade ago.</p>
<p>These days, I imagine, the ‘living connection' is increasingly made through Skype.</p>
<p>The Christmas card has become a text message.</p>
<p>Indeed, the very first text message ever sent, back in 1992, contained just two words:  “Merry Christmas”.</p>
<p>And if our social connections across the world are now maintained via swipe-screens and Facebook, business is increasingly conducted the same way: instantly; urgently, immediately.</p>
<p>The tyranny of distance has become the tyranny of 24/7.</p>
<p>It's a tyranny I suspect Joseph Assaf meets head-on, with gusto.</p>
<p>Most of you know his story  -  the archetypal migrant story.</p>
<p>The 22-year-old Lebanese migrant working in a factory and teaching himself English.</p>
<p>In time, founder of the communications agency Etcom.</p>
<p>Founder of these awards, 25 years ago.</p>
<p>A mover and shaker in ethnic radio, on countless boards and committees.</p>
<p>A sought-after conference speaker.</p>
<p>A passionate advocate for education.</p>
<p>But passionate, above all, about the precious gift of multiculturalism that defines us as a people.</p>
<p>Congratulations Joseph on 25 years of the Ethnic Business Awards.</p>
<p>And congratulations to all those ethnic businessmen and women whose stories and successes are so central to Australia's national story.</p>
<p>Our story.</p>
<p>Our unique contribution to the shape of the world.</p>
<p>Written  -  in pride and unity  -  together.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
