<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7842</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, KIRRIBILLI HOUSE, SYDNEY 3 DECEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/12/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007842.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, KIRRIBILLI HOUSE, SYDNEY<br />
3 DECEMBER 1989<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: How are you Sir?<br />
PM: I'm very very well indeed thank you. I'd obviously<br />
like to take this first opportunity of extending my sincere<br />
congratulations to Wayne Goss and his team there for their<br />
historic victory in restoring Labor to government in<br />
Queensland for the first time in 32 years. They ran a<br />
magnificent campaign which Wayne Goss led with singular<br />
success. He was able, properly, to persuade the people of<br />
Queensland that that election was about restoring integrity<br />
to government in Queensland, to provide what Queenslanders<br />
increasingly wanted to achieve the elimination of<br />
corruption and its replacement by clean and efficient<br />
government. And what Queenslanders saw was that the only<br />
way that could be done was by Goss and Labor. The<br />
alternative was a continuation of the coalition of<br />
inefficient and corrupt forces which have darkened<br />
Queensland politics for more than a generation. I look<br />
forward to working in close cooperation with an outstanding<br />
leader and a new, good, clean, efficient government in<br />
Queensland. JOURNALIST: Some Queenslanders are saying they now know how<br />
the East Berliners must feel.<br />
PM: I saw the analogies that were drawn. That may be<br />
overdrawing the situation. But there is no doubt that there<br />
has been a darkness in politics in Queensland. We've seen<br />
the dark side of politics and it's come from the<br />
conservative forces. I think it's not just for Queensland<br />
but I think for all of us in Australia it's going to be a<br />
lifting of a dark veil in that very very important part of<br />
Australia, because Queensland is a very very important part<br />
of Australia despite the attempts by some of the<br />
conservative leaders to try and give an impression that<br />
they're not part of Australia.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it will do much for Labor Party<br />
morale around Australia. </p>
<p>PM: I think a simple question would you rather from the<br />
Labor Party point of view see us win up there or lose?<br />
Answer simple you'd rather win. I don't want to overdraw<br />
the situation because we've said that the issues were state<br />
issues and they predominantly were. The only respect in<br />
which people may project the election of the campaign and<br />
the result in Queensland in some sense federally is on the<br />
question of the unity of purpose of the competing parties<br />
and of leadership. Up there you had a united Labor Party<br />
and you had bickering, incompatible conservatives. That<br />
situation that characterised the Queensland election is true<br />
of the federal picture.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you believe you can take any<br />
credit for Labor's win<br />
41 PM: No, not essentially. The overall picture in Queensland<br />
in the election was State issues. I said that from the<br />
beginning. I'm not going to be a hypocrite afterwards and<br />
having said that they were State issues turn around and say<br />
' no, heap the praise on me'.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it will lead to recriminations<br />
within the federal coalition?<br />
PM: I think at the end of this last week in federal<br />
politics they had so much that they had to worry about, a<br />
leader who simply doesn't understand his own policies,<br />
understands no economics, is incapable of handling a press<br />
conference and responding to any questions which have any<br />
economic implications at all. That's set in train its own<br />
set of problems. But added to that you will have some<br />
difficulties created by the Queensland result because the<br />
intensity of the hatreds in Queensland between the Liberals<br />
and Nationals were perhaps best indicated by that ferocious<br />
attack that Innes made on Sir Robert Sparkes of the National<br />
Party in his last speech there at the end of last week.<br />
They hate John Moore. That's heartily reciprocated. So<br />
that must have some federal implications.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it going to mean anything in terms of<br />
federal elections?<br />
PM: No. I repeat the point I made that this was<br />
essentially about Queensland issues. As I say, I'm not<br />
going to be hypocritical and switch around and say now this<br />
is for us. But clearly in the post-election situation it<br />
has advantages for us in that to have a decent, clean,<br />
efficient administration up there which is concerned about<br />
issues rather than political point scoring means that we're<br />
going to be able to have a much more effective cooperation<br />
between the Federal and State Government. Now that must be<br />
an advantage for the people of Queensland and then in a<br />
sense that must be an advantage for us politically. But<br />
most importantly that advantage comes to us because the<br />
people are going to be better off. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Do you expect a positive spin-off in a federal<br />
election? PM: I would think it's much better to be campaigning in the<br />
State up there with a friendly, cooperative State Labor<br />
government than the alternative, yes. It means that the<br />
base will be stronger and there will be a greater sense of<br />
purpose I think and of positive thinking on the part of the<br />
whole Labor organisation up there. It must in that sense be<br />
a plus.<br />
JOURNALIST: It's been stated that the National Party lost<br />
in Queensland because it wasn't listening to its electorate<br />
on issues that concerned the electorate. The same thing has<br />
been said about the Federal Labor Government, that it is not<br />
listening to the electorate with respect to interest rates<br />
and other economic-related<br />
PM: Well it's totally wrong. I can assure you I'm<br />
listening very much to the electorate and I'm talking very<br />
much to the electorate. I'll just make the simple point<br />
again, which I think is increasingly being understood, that<br />
Hawke is an intelligent Prime Minister, hasn't got interest<br />
rates up there because he's a masochist wanting to hurt<br />
himself or a sadist wanting to hurt the people. I will have<br />
interest rates down as soon as I responsibly can do it. But<br />
we have had to have them up there, high, to try and level<br />
off the tempo of economic activity so that we can get a<br />
sustainable level of imports. I think increasingly people<br />
are coming to understand that. Also it's important to say<br />
that we are now starting to see some signs which give us the<br />
confidence that we will be able to do that. But I repeat,<br />
we won't be doing it a day earlier than is economically<br />
responsible. Nor will they be kept on a day longer than is<br />
necessary. JOURNALIST: Any idea when we'll be going to a federal<br />
election as yet?<br />
PM: I have some idea but I didn't think that this beautiful<br />
Sunday morning on the steps of Kirribilli was the time to<br />
announce it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think last night's result will have any<br />
bearing on when that election is called?<br />
PM: No.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
