<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2056</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY RALLY - KING&#039;S SCHOOL, PARRAMATTA, N.S.W. 24 MAY 1969 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/05/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002056.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
LIBERAL__ PARTY RALLY Y<br />
KING'SSCHOOL, PARRAMATTA, N. S. W. 24 MAY 1969<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. Bowen, Parliamentary Colleagues, Your Grace the<br />
Archbishop, and Distinguished Guests:-<br />
The main object which I have in mind today is to have the<br />
opportunity later for my wife and I to meet as many of you as it is possible<br />
for us to do. But before we can arrive at what I hope will be the mrost<br />
enjoyable part of the afternoon, and what I know will be for us the most<br />
enjoyable part of the afternoon, I should take some time, I think, to<br />
discuss with you my beliefs as to what politics is all about. Because<br />
after all, you are all here as members and supporters of the Liberal<br />
Party, and as members and supporters of one of our best members of<br />
the Liberal Party in Nigel Bowen.<br />
But why is it that you are prepared, as I know so many of<br />
you are, to go out at election times and to man polling booths when it is<br />
120 degrees in the shade or raining cats and dogs and on every election<br />
I can remember it has either been one or the other. Why is it that you<br />
are prepared to do that, to give of your time and of your effort to address<br />
envelopes, to attend branch meetings, to go out from your own fireside<br />
and divorce yourselves from your own desires to play golf or to do<br />
whatever it is that is of greatest interest to you? What is the motivation<br />
behind it? It is not, I am sure, just to get Mr. Smith or Mr. Brown<br />
or Mr. Jones in some particular position. It must be more than that and<br />
I know it is more than that.<br />
It is, I think, because you have a vision of what this country<br />
can do under proper leadership, of what this country can become for<br />
yourselves and for your children if the proper measures are taken. And<br />
because you have this vision, I believe that what it is that motivates you<br />
is the desire to participate in achieving the end that your vision says is<br />
possible of achievement. And that is what politics, basically, is all about.<br />
I suppose that the most important thing in politics, though<br />
it is not a pressing burden on us now, but still the most important thing,<br />
is to see that within a country there is retained that freedom of expression,<br />
that capacity to express dissent, provided it is not expressed by violence;<br />
that ability to disagree with governments without fear of retaliation; / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
that chance to cast a secret ballot, knowing it will be secret and that no<br />
retaliation can result from it; that ability to choose and change<br />
governments, that freedom and democracy which we take for granted<br />
but which is, when we look at the world, the prerogative of only a small<br />
part of it. And basically that is the first requirement to be kept.<br />
I am bound to say that I think that the side of politics which<br />
you support is more likely to retain those basic freedoms than are any<br />
other kinds of politics in this country. For after all, it is not the Liberals,<br />
if they disagree with something, who seek to resort to violence because<br />
they cannot win majority opinion. It is not the Liberals who attack<br />
physically those who disagree with them. It is not the Liberals who pelt<br />
missiles at distinguished citizens of Australia because they don't like<br />
what those distinguished citizens are doing. It is rather people supporting<br />
the other side. But after that, what is politics about? I think it is to keep<br />
the security of this country against attack from abroad so that these basic<br />
freedoms can be retained, not only within against attack but against<br />
attack from without. And I believe that that side of politics which you<br />
support is more concerned in times of peace with preparing against attack<br />
from without, with preparing for the security of this country, than is the<br />
other side of politics. We have, as you know, and not without some agony of spirit<br />
and some time spent examining all the possibilities, decided to accept the<br />
challenge to our north posed by the withdrawal of British forces. We have<br />
decided to involve ourselves in the region to which we are contiguous and<br />
to help it economically, to help it financially, to help it technically and<br />
to provide a visible token of our willingness to assist it to defend itself.<br />
And this in a new era was a great and momentous decision.<br />
We did not adopt that course proposed by our opponents of<br />
sending some Australian forces in and out in a kind of a jack-in-the-box<br />
approach of " Now you see them now you don't", which is as psychologically<br />
inept as it is logically and logistically absurd. Rather we have decided<br />
that our security is helped by helping the security of the nations to our<br />
north, have adopted that principle and I believe in that way have greatly<br />
helped our future security and that is another and most important thing<br />
that politics is all about.<br />
just as it is of the utmost importance for us, a small<br />
country in a dangerous world, to be sure as sure as one can be in the<br />
world that in times of stress and danger should they come, we will be<br />
able to call upon the assistance of a great power, knowing that we deserve<br />
it because we will know that we have lived up to the spirit of the treaty<br />
we formed with it, and are not seeking only to take but are willing to take<br />
and to give for our own security and, as I believe, that of the free world<br />
generally. / 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
Having achieved the proper processes of democracy inside<br />
a country and guarded them, having guarded the country itself these,<br />
important as they are, are only the foundation for what we do with what<br />
we have gained by those measures. It is essential that we should provide<br />
for the people of this country an opportunity for work if they are prepared<br />
to work and this has been and will be done; that we should bring into<br />
this country new manpower without which the development of this country<br />
would languish; that we should marshal for the development and growth<br />
materially of this country capital resources and technological know-how,<br />
not only from within ourselves but from abroad. Because if there was<br />
ever a country that needed quickly to grow materially, that needed quickly<br />
to grow in manpower, then that country is Australia at this moment in the<br />
world's history. And these are things, I believe, that we can do with our<br />
team better than any of our opponents can do. And you must believe that<br />
too and that must be another reason why you are prepared to give of your<br />
time and effort and thought to help us continue a path, and continue an<br />
upward path which for the last two decades has been unparalleled in<br />
Australia's past history.<br />
Now these are material things of which I spoke, but you<br />
must wish too, I am sure, that in a country defended, insofar as its<br />
strength will enable it to be defended, growing insofar as its resources<br />
will al'low it to grow, there should also be more than a mere material<br />
approach. You must, and I know you do, want to see that within such a<br />
community there is a real attempt, a real effort made to look after the<br />
ill, the unfortunate, the aged and the handicapped amongst us. And you<br />
must and I am sure you do want to see provided for the people and the<br />
young people of Australia not merely an opportunity for a job, not merely<br />
an opportunity for material advancement, but an opportunity to choose the<br />
kind of job, the kind of work which an individual feels he is most fitted to<br />
perform, to try and train an individual, whether they wish to be an artist<br />
or an artisan, a captain of industry or a captain in the merchant navy,<br />
whatever field of endeavour an individual feels he should be drawn towards.<br />
A country which is great will help such an individual to develop in the way<br />
in which his own internal urges seek to make him develop, and in that way,<br />
as I believe, will give him a feeling of participation, a feeling of wishing<br />
to give rather than demanding to be given to. Because no great country<br />
can continue to be great if the citizens who make it up clamour only to be<br />
given to and do not have a wish, an urge and an opportunity to give in<br />
return. And this, though perhaps it is one of the hardest tasks, is still<br />
a matter of what politics is all about.<br />
So I believe at this juncture in our history is the fostering<br />
of a spirit of pride in being Australian, a fostering of an Australian<br />
nationalism, no matter whether one lives in New South Wales, Victoria,<br />
Parramatta, Malvern or wherever it may be; an elation at some advance<br />
in this nation of ours, whether that advance be Cove, Bass Strait, Sydney,<br />
Mt. Newman, wherever. A feeling that this, wherever it is situated, is<br />
something which helps our nation as a whole, and that should attract our<br />
first and greatest loyalty. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
I do not mean that we should foster or seek to foster a<br />
feeling of chauvinistic pride. I feel that we should seek to foster a feeling<br />
of pride, an acknowledgment of the great challenges that face us and a<br />
willingness to overcome them, and should join with that a feeling of<br />
humility at the tasks in front of us, at the luck this country has had and<br />
has exploited, at the requirement to help our neighbours because of the<br />
luck which we have had and which, with hard work, we have exploited.<br />
These approaches to the life of a nation are the very basic<br />
fabric of which politics is made. If it were just a matter of who is in and<br />
who is out, if it were not a matter bound up with philosophies, if it were<br />
not a matter bound up with approaches, if it were not a matter which over<br />
the centuries has led communities to, in many cases, physical fighting,<br />
then it would not matter much. But in fact if what I have said is true<br />
and I believe it is then it matters greatly, and so it matters greatly,<br />
I believe, that you are prepared to work as you are, that you are prepared<br />
to come here today as you have, because in so doing you are contributing<br />
greatly to the achievement of that vision, to the advancement of that nation<br />
to which you belong, and I belong, and which I think can only I will not<br />
say " only" and which I think can best be advanced by the application of<br />
the beliefs which you and we have in common. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
