<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5831</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/06/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005831.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A AS DELIVERED<br />
FOR MEDIA THURSDAY, 10 JUNE 1982<br />
ADDRESS TO THE AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE<br />
Thank you very much Mr Chairman for that welcome. I would like<br />
to welcome on behalf of the Government all of-those of-you<br />
who have come from other countries amongst whom I have recognised<br />
a number of old friends. I understand that Michael Somare<br />
and myself were both affectod by MrWran'Is industrial troubles<br />
this morning. I don't know what can be read from the fact that<br />
Michael Somare took to the air to get here and I took to the<br />
water, but not in the way that my one of my predecessors might have.<br />
It was just in a police launch crossing the harbour.<br />
I am personall1y very pleased to be opening this convention<br />
whose objective is to achieve a stronger Pacific economy, a<br />
stronger Pacific community. I think that is vastly important<br />
for all of us. It is an important objective and it is very<br />
much worth Working for. I would like to congratulate the<br />
Australian and Sydney Chambers of Commerce on this convention.<br />
Private enterprise, through organisations such as yours can<br />
achieve a g: ceat deal in building friendly relations<br />
around the P~ acific, and encouraging the fullest co-operation<br />
between Pacific countries and partners.<br />
The Pacific-is plainly one of the world's most dynamic and<br />
exciting regions. It is the region for the future.<br />
It is also one of the most diverse, with tremendous<br />
S dwiiftfheirne nicte, s bbeettweweene n thtehier neseidzse s, a ndt heciarp absitlrietnigtehs, oft hetihre cpootuenntrtiiaels<br />
and the degree of development which they have attained.<br />
In thinking about Pacific development, this diversity has to be<br />
recognised as fundamental, as it is recognised in the existing<br />
network of Pacific institutions and arrangements. This network<br />
is extensive and effective, and I would like to say something about<br />
Australia's part in it because these matters are very closely bound<br />
up with the questions of trade and economic development which I shall<br />
turn to later.<br />
Our involvement is substantial, at bilateral and multilateral<br />
levels, including governments and business, together and separately,<br />
covering questions of trade and economic co-operation, and development<br />
assistance. With the ASEAN countries, we have the annual ASEAN-Australia Forum,<br />
a high level intergovernmental consultative mechanism, our Foreign<br />
Minister meets regularly with all ASEAN Foreign. Miuisters, we hold<br />
regular ASEAN Trade Fairs in Australia to assit those countries to<br />
develop markets here and the Australia/ ASEAN business co-operation<br />
committees meet regularly. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
There is a highly sophisticated pattern of contacts with<br />
Japan, especially through the two parallel business co-operation<br />
committees, and the Australia/ Japan ministerial committee which is<br />
to meet next month.<br />
The Australia/ Korea business co-operation committee is a thriving<br />
body, and is next to meet in Australia in August. There are<br />
annual official disuccsions with China, and the Australia/ China<br />
joint trade committee will meet in Peking later this month.<br />
At a broader regional level, Australia is actively involved<br />
in the Asian Development Bank and the Economic Commission -for<br />
Asia and the Pacific ( ESCAP). Australia was the fourth largest<br />
contributor in absolute terms to the recent replenshmrent of the<br />
Asian Development Fund, which lends to poorer countries, and by far<br />
the largest contributor in terms of relative gross national<br />
product. We will continue to play an active and constructive role<br />
in the financing of the forthcoming general capital increase for<br />
the Bank, and we are encouraging the Bank to diversify its lending<br />
to smaller scale projects which have part relevance to a numrber of countries.<br />
The Commonwealth Heads of Government Regional Meeting, itself<br />
an Australian initiative, brings together the Heads of<br />
Government of Commonwealth countries in Asia and the Pacific; the<br />
next meeting in October in Suva will have a particular focus on<br />
Pacif ic issues as indeed earlier meetings of this particular body has also.<br />
In t he South Pacific region, we were a founder member of both<br />
the South Pacific Commission and the South Pacific Forum, which<br />
comprises the independent nations of the South Pacific and will.<br />
next be meeting in Rotorua in August. There-are a wide range of<br />
practical co-operative bodies and arrangements under the auspices<br />
of the Forum, most importantly S. P. E. C. ( South Pacific Bureau<br />
for Economic: Co-operation), also the Regional Trade Agreement,<br />
SPARTECA, signed in 1980, a unique, one way trade agreement under<br />
which Australia and New Zealand are granting preferential and<br />
duty free access on a non-reciprocal basis to the widest possible<br />
range of island products.<br />
We also have important bilateral relationships with New Zealand.<br />
The draft joint report on Closer Economic Relations has just<br />
been published, and with Papua New Guinea, with which we<br />
maintain a s; pecial relationship in both aid and trade areas,<br />
especially -through our assistance to the sPNG Budget, and<br />
through the Pactra Trading Agreement which has given<br />
PNG goods non-reciprocal preferential access to Austr~ lia' s<br />
markets since 1977.<br />
Australian economic assistance to the Asia Pacific region is<br />
of major importance. We are currently committed to providing<br />
$ 345 million to South East Asian countries in bilateral project<br />
aid; under the current three year program we are<br />
$ 120 million to the South Pacific region which represents the<br />
region of greatest growth in Australian development assistance over the<br />
last 6 or 7 years; and we are </p>
<p>-3<br />
encouraging through our aid program joint ventures between<br />
Australian 6ompanies and Pacific governments. But we<br />
acknowledge that our financial assistance in no way matches<br />
the impetus for development provided by increased trade and<br />
business co-oeration between our nations.<br />
The P acific region has long been a major trading area for<br />
Australia, but in recent years trade in both directions has<br />
increased strongly. Between 1974 and 1980, the value of<br />
trade between Australia and other regional economies<br />
virtually doubled in both directions and, at the end of that<br />
period, 70% of our exports and almost 50% of our imports<br />
were within the Pacific region broadly defined.<br />
It is sometimes pointed out that there is a substantial imbalance<br />
in two-way trade, in Australia's favour.* But it needs to<br />
be recognised that in most of those cases, Australia is<br />
exporting raw materials to countries which process them into<br />
manufactured goods to be sold to the major world markets.<br />
With a population of only 15 million people, Australia<br />
inevitably provides only a limited market for the exports of<br />
the western Pacific countries. But it is worth noting that<br />
by the standards of most other developed countries, imports<br />
already supply a large and growing proportion of our market.<br />
For example, inper capita terms our imports of clothing,<br />
footwear and textiles far exceed those of the United States,<br />
the European Communities or Japan. When people are talking about<br />
whether the Australian' markets or are closed m'arkets, it is worth<br />
noting what wre do by comparison with other advanced industrial<br />
countries. Moreover, in recognition of the importance of trade to the<br />
process of economic development, as well as the special<br />
arrangements for forum island countries,-we provide preferential<br />
access to Autralia's market for a wide range of goods produced<br />
by developing countries. And in the contex * t of a new seven<br />
year program of assistance for our domestic textiles, clothing<br />
and footwear industries, not only will assistance be significantly<br />
reduced over time, and access to the Australian market further<br />
increased, but a new developing-country preference scheme has<br />
been incorporated which extends preference to many goods<br />
for the first time, and which will allow developing countries<br />
to further raise their share of the--Australian market. It is<br />
worth noting that when industries really seek to become<br />
competitive, sometimes remarkable things happen. ' There is one<br />
major textile firm operating in Australia which is now establishing<br />
offices in " long Kong and Singapore because it believes it can<br />
compete and -export effectively into those markets. That is not<br />
something that-anyone would have expected a few years ago.<br />
The economic links between Australia and the region also<br />
extend to in-vestment flows. The development of Australia's<br />
resources, from which the countries of the Pacific as well<br />
as Australia obtain great benefit, requires large amounts<br />
of capital. Foreign investment, in partnership with<br />
domestic capital, has been welcomed by tfte Australian Government<br />
under clear -guidelines that have been understood and accepted<br />
by the international community, and a series of decisions<br />
in recent years relaxing controls on outward portfolio<br />
investment have resulted in strong growth in investment overseas<br />
by Australians, much of it to Pacific countries. </p>
<p>-4<br />
It is particularly pleasing that investment in Australia from<br />
the Pacific region has been increasing strongly. Indeed<br />
in recent years, Japan and the ASEAN countries combined are<br />
rivalling, the United States as the ' second largest source of<br />
foreign investment inflows, and the development of joint<br />
ventures between Australian and other Pacific countryI<br />
businesses has been welcomed by the Australian Government.<br />
The economic links, through trade and investment, between<br />
Australia and other countries of the-Pacific indeed, the<br />
economic links between all countries of the region, are both<br />
a source and a consequence of economic growth, and it is<br />
tihrocogh sustained growth that those links will be strengthened.<br />
Growth rates and economic achievement already seen in this<br />
region must seem miraculous ~ in many other parts of the world.<br />
For when one remembers the condition of the region as little<br />
as 25 or 30 years ago, its economic performance over more<br />
recent yearsc has bqen truly remarkable, particularly against<br />
a background of world economic slowdown wht. ch has prevailed<br />
since the early 1970s. Japan, of course, has been one of the<br />
world's fastest growing nations for over 30 years, and has<br />
contributed in a very real way to regional stability and<br />
development.<br />
Australia too has grown and developed immensely in the<br />
last three decades, and in recent years, we have had<br />
substantial success in swimming against the international<br />
tide of recession. Indeed, in 1981 when the average real<br />
growth rate in the OECD was only about and when some<br />
economies were actually shrinking, Australia's real growth<br />
rate was 5% the highest growth rate of all the OECD<br />
countries. -But even our growth rate-was surpassed by those<br />
inthe! newly industrialising countries of the. western Pacific,<br />
for in in 1981, real GNP expanded in Hong Kong by over<br />
in Singapore by nearly 10%, in Korea by in Indonesia by<br />
nearly 8% 0, and in Malaysia by nearly 7%.<br />
The countries which have done best in recent times have been<br />
adopting outward.-looking policies, they have been willing<br />
to adapt their industrial structure to capture growth areas<br />
of the world market, they have worked hard for their success,<br />
by making the most of their advantages despite the lack of<br />
resources which many of them suffer. Almost all western<br />
Pacific rim countries achieved strong export volume growth<br />
rates through the 1970s. Korea averaged over 25%, Taiwan<br />
province over 18%, Singapore and Thailand both over 12%,<br />
and Indonesia over 10% and this very plainly tells the<br />
story of the basis of their remarkable success.<br />
Economic interelationships between the countries of the<br />
Pacific region have also grown apace. For all regional<br />
counrie, except the United States and Japan, more than </p>
<p>half of their trade is with other aountries within the region, and ZEor<br />
most the proportion is much higher. In the case of Japan,<br />
almost half of its trade is intra-regional; and the United States<br />
States trade with the Pacific is assuming increasing<br />
importance, as-evidenced by the fact that in 1978 its trade<br />
with the west Pacific-exceeded total trade with west and<br />
east Europe for the first time in its history.<br />
It is also worth egphasising that while resource endowments<br />
within. 1the region are unevenly shared, and while the lack<br />
of a resourse base has not inhibited remarkable growth<br />
in several countries, the economic strength of the Pacific<br />
region is underpinned by a rich resource endowment. The<br />
region. contains five of the world's major food exporters,<br />
Australia, Canada, New Zealand, Thailand, and the United<br />
States, and these same countries, together with Indonesia,<br />
Malaysia and the Philippines, produce-between them most<br />
industrial raw materials. Indeed, the region provides<br />
or: nore of : the world market economies production of copper,<br />
lead, nickel, tin and iron ore, and a lesser but nonetheless<br />
significant percentage of many other minerals.<br />
However, despite the regions considerable underlying sources<br />
of strength, despite its growing economic interdependence,<br />
and despite its remarkable ecomomic perform~ ance against world<br />
trends in recent years, it is clear that no region,.' no country can<br />
remain immune forever against sustained recession in Europe<br />
and North kmerica. We are all affected by stagnant world<br />
trade and -depressed commodity prices, and the problems are<br />
especially acute for the Pacific islands, which are<br />
typically dependent on export earnings from one or a small<br />
number of commodities.<br />
I. vwould add that world recession is likely to make it more<br />
difficult for prosperous countries to provide the kind of<br />
assistance, and even pursue the kind of policies, which<br />
will help -developing T1hird World countries to achieve growth.<br />
The outlook for the-world economy continues to be bleak.<br />
Predictions of an imminent up-turn in growth and activity<br />
are repeatedly made, but that predicted recovery repeatedly<br />
fails to materialise. At some point those that<br />
say there will be American recovery in Six months, will have<br />
to be proved right, but they have been saying that for the<br />
last 30 years, and I don't know yet which six months are going<br />
to be the crucial six months. Economic growth in the major<br />
OECD countries continues to decline. Last year, for the first<br />
time in over 20 years, world trade actually fell. Is it any<br />
wonder then that unemployment in the OECD countries will<br />
reach 30 mrillion people during this year? If you asked<br />
any leaders of western countries 10 or 15 years ago could the~ y<br />
envisage the circumstances ' in which unemployment in the<br />
advanced industrial countries would reach 30 million by 1982,<br />
they all would have said no, what nonsense, what stupidity,<br />
we know much better than that how to manage-our economies.<br />
It is going to reach that number of 30 million this year<br />
and I wonder how much higher it will have to go before<br />
western leaders show the kind of imagination that will be<br />
needed to get the major world economies back on a growth path..<br />
/ 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
While tariffs have not increased markedly since the Tokyo<br />
MTN round of a short while ago, they remain high for many<br />
products of importance to exporting developing countries<br />
and non-tariff barriers have risen. That Tokyo round did<br />
not deal fairly with developing countries. That Tokyo round<br />
did not deal fairly with trade in agricultural countries.<br />
The has never given protection to trade in agricultural<br />
goods which it-has sought to give in trade and industrial<br />
goods. These matters were not dealt with adequately at the<br />
Tokyo rounds. There is-' no suggestion that theyare being<br />
dealt with adequately yet.<br />
On some estimates, about 40% of world trade faces non-tariff<br />
barriers and these.. bakriers are far more prevalent for<br />
agricultural than industrial products. Many of the more<br />
recent non-tariff barriers such as voluntary restraint<br />
agreements-which characterise the new wave of protectionism,<br />
fall outside the rules of the game and reflect a greater<br />
recourse to bilateralism. It is not surprising that<br />
significant concern is emerging about the effectiveness of<br />
the open mrultilateral market-orientated international<br />
trading system, as incorporated in the GATT and the MTN<br />
codes. I cannot say too strongly that a breakdown of<br />
multilateralism offers the greatest possible threat to<br />
small or middle ranking couxftries because it is the large<br />
and powerful that can enter into that bargaining game and<br />
make arrangements to suit themselves. If Papua New Guinea,<br />
Thailand or Australia need to get into a competitive subsidy<br />
business to keep an export market, how can they do that<br />
against the combined weight of the European Economic Community<br />
of 260 m:. ilion people? We can be outbid every time and<br />
this is the question of wanting to establish a voluntary<br />
restraint-agreement. Obviously the combined weight of<br />
North Amercica or the EEC makes it much easier for them to<br />
establish a voluntary restraint agreement against Thailand,<br />
or the Philippines, or New Zealand or Australia than the<br />
o . ther way around. If we sought to apply a voluntary<br />
restraint agreement against the great and the powerful, I<br />
suggest tEaat we would find it a good deal harder.<br />
Voluntary restraint agreements are just as much a restraint<br />
of trade as formal quantitive restrictions. They operate<br />
in exactly the same way and it is not good enough for<br />
people who have voluntary restraint agreements and who<br />
apply them, to be pious about it and say they don't have<br />
quantitive restrictions, that they don't have barriers to<br />
trade because the exporter whoever it is, has voluntarily<br />
agreed to limit exports. It is a very effective mechanism.<br />
It happened to one of our major industries in relation to<br />
Europe and it was not an agricultural industry. The<br />
underlYir.. g threat of course is that if you don't accept the<br />
voluntary restraint agreement, you won't have any access at<br />
all. That'is the underlying threat, and that is how<br />
voluntary restraint agreements come into being, it is how<br />
they are applied. Middle ranking countries find it very<br />
difficult: to compete actively inthat kind of game. / 7 </p>
<p>I can memernber that John McEwan always used to say that the<br />
only protection in trade for countries such as Australia, the<br />
only protection of trade for the developing world, is an<br />
open, fair, multilateral system whereby bilateral agreements<br />
are outlawed. That has been very significantly and substantially<br />
broken down in recent times. I must say that I am not<br />
entirely persuaded that the recent economic Summit at Versailles<br />
tackled these problems with the kind of vision which I believe<br />
the world currently calls for.<br />
The impact of the current world economic downturn not<br />
only threatens the rising living standards which people in<br />
the westhave come to expect, it is particularly<br />
damaging to the prospects of the countries which are economically<br />
weak.. It was against this whole background that Australia proposed<br />
a number of initiatives for consideration in the context<br />
of last weekend's Versailles Summit. Our proposal focussed<br />
on the importance of trade in generating sustainable<br />
economic recovery, and sought to get growth restarted in the<br />
major economies by proposing a standstill, and a subsequent<br />
winding back of protection devices as well as of export<br />
incentives a~ nd subsidies.<br />
It is the easiest thing in the world for countries to-say<br />
we are not -going to increase protection, but if countries<br />
are not prepared to make that proclamation then obviously<br />
they are reserving themselves the right to increase protection<br />
further. There have been one or two suggestions in Australia<br />
that we speak with two voices in this issue, one at home and<br />
one overseas. That I suggest is not correct and shows a<br />
naive. analysis of whata country acting alone can do. We speak<br />
with one voice, but if the principles of comoaritive advantage<br />
are in fact to work, and if a country is to get any benefits<br />
from lowering its own trade barriers, we have got to know that<br />
we can get better access into other markets overseas. There<br />
is no point. in taking away all protection from a particular<br />
country, whether it is Australia, or New Zealand or whatever<br />
unless at the same time you can get better access to those<br />
things which you know you can do best whether it is in the<br />
agricultural, or the mining or the'industrial areas. That is<br />
why it has to be multilateral, that is why it has to be<br />
many sided and not just one country acting alone.<br />
It applies in particular to countries<br />
that have quantitive restrictions against a very large percentage<br />
of our exports. If you got quantitive restrictions against<br />
a larger percentage of your exports, how can could you possibly<br />
by lowering; barriers into your own markets get better<br />
access in t: he markets overseas unless there is a reciprocal<br />
multilAteral move. It is not just possible.<br />
That is why I believe it is im~ mensely important for nations<br />
acting together to be prepared to move in these directions,<br />
but it is not possible, I don't believe it is possible forp<br />
a great powerful country like the United States, or Britain or </p>
<p>8-<br />
Germany to act in thdae areas alone, unilaterally. It is<br />
possible to act in concert and to act together, and it is<br />
then that the theory of comparative advanqage would truly<br />
operate and it is then that living standards in the countries<br />
concerned in trade around the world would grow and we would<br />
all prosper.<br />
Although the Versailles Summit did not itself take any<br />
specific -action, it has recognised the need for action to be<br />
taken along these lines. While the Communique is of course<br />
only a declaration of broad intent it is to be welcomed and<br />
contains muc(, h with which Australia can agree. It not only<br />
re-affirms the commitment to resist protectionist pressures<br />
and trade diLstorting practices, and to complete the work<br />
of the Tokyo round, including improvements to GATT's capacity<br />
to solve current and future trade problems, it also<br />
undertakes to work towards further opening of markets<br />
to co-operate with developing countries, in particular<br />
NIC's to ex]? and trade opportunities, and it endorses full<br />
participation in the forthcoming GATT Ministerial Conference<br />
in other to take concrete steps to achieve those ends.<br />
Now while that much has been said and that much we can agree<br />
with, the test is going to depend on what happens at that<br />
GATT ministerial conference as to whether concrete action is<br />
in fact taken or whether it is just again a statement that<br />
is a desirable objective, without a political will and a<br />
commitment behind it to achieve that and that is what the world<br />
very sorely needs right at the present time.<br />
While the Summit identified a number of desirable objectives,<br />
and indicated support for a number of desirable actions, the<br />
deferral of specific action until the GATT Ministerial<br />
Meeting in November means that the whole trading world will<br />
now be looking even more keenly to the United States to achieve<br />
an early resolution of its dispute over its 1983 and subsequent<br />
budgets. If I learnt anything in ' theUnited States in my recent<br />
visit, and if there . is any unanimity about the future course<br />
of the United States economy, it was that one, there must<br />
be an agreement about the Budget deficit, there must be<br />
agreement that shows that that deficit will decline not<br />
only this year but in also in subsequeht years. It is only then that<br />
the United States interest rates would start to fall. There<br />
might have been many differences about the level of the deficit<br />
and all thE! rest, but amongst everyone I met there was.<br />
agreement about those two critical elements, the need for<br />
agreement about the deficit and a clear perception that<br />
arrangements that are made which will reducing the.' deficit<br />
in later years and it is only then that there would be a<br />
fall of sicjnificance in the US interest rates.<br />
While this is going to be vastly important for the United<br />
States, it will be vastly important to the whole trading<br />
world, for countries like Australia, because the maintenance<br />
of high interest rates is going beyond a certain point,<br />
established situations which are not sustainable within<br />
any country, within any industry or activity. / 19 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
Ainudstursatrliiaal~ wisieldl ccoonutnitnruiees toin prceos-so pfeorra tipoons itbievcea usaec tithoen beyco no-miic<br />
prospects and prosperity of peoples throughout the world<br />
depend upon it, none more than the outward looking, exportoriented<br />
economies of the developing codntries of the<br />
western Pacific.<br />
When I addressed the Pacific Basin Economic Council two<br />
years ago, E* outlined a series-of obstacles in the path<br />
of the Pacific community idea, but I then expressed my<br />
conviction -that at some point, whether sooner or later,<br />
the Pacific concept will be given greater'substance, greater<br />
meaning-. by institutional mear., of one form-or another Since then<br />
the search for the most appropriate means and. practic~ il study<br />
of the issues involved has proglrcssed. Australia<br />
subsequently sponsored a seminar at the iAiitU latk-e in 1980<br />
under Sir John Crawford'Is direction.-A second seminar was held<br />
in Bangkok last week with further encouraging results.. There<br />
was recognition at Bangkok of increasing interdependence,<br />
the importance of Pacific contacts for all Pacific countries.<br />
Task forces have been established to study investment and<br />
technology, transfer between Pacific countries and also trade<br />
and manufacturers in primary products and Indonesia has<br />
invited participants to a further conference in 1983.<br />
I would particularly like to thank the Deputy Prime Minister<br />
of Thailand who is here today for his key role not only in<br />
making the Bangkok seminar the success that it was, but also<br />
in making it possible. The objective of a stronger Pacific<br />
community and economy is one that we obviously all share and<br />
by pursuing it through a variety of avenues, it is possible<br />
to take account of all the factors inolved, including the<br />
regional groupings which have become important in achieving_<br />
economic development.<br />
It is obvio usly a more difficult concept than that of the<br />
establishment of the European Community because in the original<br />
establishment of that community, you had countries that were<br />
more similar either in size or history or from the nature of<br />
. activities, the degree of industrialisation, the stage of their<br />
development., than you would find through the great diversity<br />
of countriE! s in the Pacific. It is that very diversity I<br />
believe which poses the challenge and establishes some<br />
difficulty in determining what the true shape and form of<br />
the Pacific community as it one day will emerge and might<br />
ultimately be.<br />
During my vrisit to Korea, President Chun raised with me the<br />
idea of a s; ummit meeting of heads of government of Pacific<br />
countries. other regions, for example the Europeans,<br />
the Africans, the Americas have arrangements of this kind,<br />
but no single meeting pulls together Pacific countries.<br />
it is an idea worth pursuing, for meetings of heads of<br />
government help to focus minds on issues in * a way that cannot<br />
otherwise I believe be achieved. Heads of government when<br />
they meet, hopefully want the meeting to be successful so they </p>
<p>10<br />
put their officials to work before the meeting saying: " what can<br />
we do that will be positive and well-received?" and it really<br />
does focus the mind on the problems to be solved and solutions<br />
to be reached. So it is an idea worth pursuing and we are<br />
examining it closely.<br />
It goes without saying that for such a summit to take place,<br />
the groundwork would need to be carefully laid and it would<br />
need a consensus to emerge in support of the proposals among<br />
an appropriate group of Pacific countries. The summit could<br />
have a useful place as part of the overall strategy of<br />
evolutionary progress through wide-ranging discussions in<br />
which your convention will, I am quite certain, play a very<br />
significant part.<br />
I wish you every success in your deliberations. You have a<br />
noted group of speakers coming later during the day and<br />
again, I welcome all those that have travelled overseas<br />
to be with you on this occasion. I have great pleasure<br />
in declaring the convention officially open.<br />
oOoo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
