<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10719</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL RADIO 3AW, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/03/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, thank you for agreeing to this.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's a pleasure.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the health system's a mess, what are you going</p>
<p>   to do about it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't agree it's a mess. I agree it could be</p>
<p>   better. But health care in Australia is at a higher level than in</p>
<p>   most other countries in the world.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Kennett has just said that elderly people were scared witless</p>
<p>   by your changes on nursing homes. He said this on AM - scared</p>
<p>   witless. And now they're bearing the brunt of what amounts</p>
<p>   to Federal incompetence on health.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>[10 SECOND TAPE BREAK]...recognised and been fixed and they won't</p>
<p>   be repeated. But I don't think it helps very much for anybody</p>
<p>   in authority to just slag the health system. The average Australian</p>
<p>   has access to better quality, cheaper health care than does the</p>
<p>   average British citizen or the average American citizen. If you</p>
<p>   get sick in the United States and you're not well off, you</p>
<p>   can be in real bother.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But I put it to you - people in Victoria tell me they are concerned</p>
<p>   that if they get sick they won't get the sort of treatment</p>
<p>   they need. The hospitals are dirty, they're under-staffed...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that is a combined responsibility of both the State and the</p>
<p>   Federal governments...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But we [inaudible] do about it. Jeff Kennett says it's your</p>
<p>   fault.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it doesn't help in a situation like this for a Premier</p>
<p>   to try and heap all of the blame onto the Prime Minister or the</p>
<p>   Federal Government or, indeed, for the Federal Government to heap</p>
<p>   all of the blame onto the State government.</p>
<p>What are we doing? Well, to start with we put about $500 million</p>
<p>   a year into trying to stop the catastrophic fall in the number of</p>
<p>   people in private health insurance...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well it's failed.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it hasn't totally failed.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well it's still going.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Neil, the rate of exiting from private health insurance has</p>
<p>   slowed very markedly and it doesn't help for people in authority,</p>
<p>   including State Premiers, to constantly publicly criticise the quality</p>
<p>   of private health insurance. The other observation I would make</p>
<p>   is that - you say, what are we doing - in the new Medicare agreement</p>
<p>   we are offering the States an agreement that involves a three and</p>
<p>   a half per cent increase, and that is in a climate of zero inflation.</p>
<p>   On top of that, we are offering them a guarantee that for every</p>
<p>   one per cent, if it were to happen, more people leaving private</p>
<p>   health insurance, there will be another $83 million added to the</p>
<p>   money that the Commonwealth pays to the States. On top of that,</p>
<p>   we are giving them a further guarantee in relation to the operating</p>
<p>   costs of hospitals. </p>
<p>We are offering them more money. We are prepared to play our part.</p>
<p>   It doesn't help the patients of Victorian hospitals for the</p>
<p>   Victorian Government to say: well, it's all the fault of the</p>
<p>   Federal Government. That is the kind of mindless buck passing which</p>
<p>   the Australian public is fed-up with. I would not insult a State</p>
<p>   government by saying it is all their fault. I do not think it helps</p>
<p>   the citizens of Victoria for the State Government to, in effect,</p>
<p>   suggest it's all my fault. It's not and the Australian</p>
<p>   public knows that. What they want the Premier and the Prime Minister</p>
<p>   to do is to work together sensibly.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, hopefully that happens today at the Premiers' Conference.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we've made a very fair offer and we hope the Premiers</p>
<p>   will accept it.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, they're already saying no, aren't they?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we'll wait and see.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. Another issue - guns. And again, Jeff Kennett says Australia</p>
<p>   went over the top at the time of Port Arthur. We went over the top.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't agree with that. I don't think Australia</p>
<p>   went over the top at all. It was an appalling tragedy - an appalling</p>
<p>   tragedy - and out of that disaster came the hope of a safer Australian</p>
<p>   community. We had some uniform gun laws. I received the cooperation</p>
<p>   of all Premiers, of the Leader of the Opposition federally, and</p>
<p>   I always thank them for that. I did not go over the top in my own</p>
<p>   language or my own handling of that. But I believe that the Australian</p>
<p>   public wants a maintenance in full of that uniform...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well is that threatened by what Victoria's doing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we're going to talk about it today.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>You know what they're doing.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't want any changes.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>None at all.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't. I don't want any changes to the agreement.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well what Victoria's doing changes the agreement, does it</p>
<p>   not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I want to hear exactly what they're intending to do</p>
<p>   because you sometimes get very mixed signals through the airwaves.</p>
<p>   But my simple proposition is that I would like all of those at the</p>
<p>   meeting today to reaffirm the commitment of their governments to</p>
<p>   the uniform agreement.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is it possible that there will be a financial penalty if Victoria</p>
<p>   does change it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I haven't raised the question of sanctions.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Would you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I want to have a sensible talk.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yeah, but you're taking a firm line and Victoria's taking</p>
<p>   a firm line.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am certainly taking a firm line but it doesn't help on something</p>
<p>   like this where I'm optimistic that people will cooperate and</p>
<p>   see commonsense. It doesn't help to talk provocatively in advance.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Fair enough. Would you like the Federal Government, though, to</p>
<p>   take over if the States are given a power over all gun laws, make</p>
<p>   it a Federal responsibility?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I hope that doesn't become necessary.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. Now...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But can I just it make it very clear - my bottom line is, I am</p>
<p>   against any watering down of the uniform agreement.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>All right, now, hopefully that will be resolved today.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I hope so.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Senator Parer, the Minister for Resources, should he sell his shares?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Senator Parer, so far, has not been involved in any conflict of</p>
<p>   interest. The question of whether his family trust disposes of shares</p>
<p>   in a coal mining company is a matter that will have to be decided</p>
<p>   by the people who run that trust.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Would you advise him to sell his shares?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I am in constant communication with Senator Parer regarding</p>
<p>   the untrue allegations that have been made against him...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, is it true that the company's involved in a dispute</p>
<p>   over native title?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well if it is, I don't know. That's not Senator Parer's</p>
<p>   fault, is it?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, no. But his company and he's the Minister for Resources</p>
<p>   and he's speaking on native title.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But what is wrong, what is wrong with...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Because he benefits directly.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm sorry, but that's the equivalent of saying that Peter</p>
<p>   Costello should resign as Federal Treasurer when interest rates</p>
<p>   came down because he has a housing mortgage and he benefited from</p>
<p>   his action in bringing about cuts in interest rates.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But not it's not, with respect, Prime Minister...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Why isn't it?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>We're talking about $2 million worth of shares. We're</p>
<p>   talking about discussions with Japanese companies as a share holder</p>
<p>   when he's Minister. And we're talking about a native title</p>
<p>   claim from which his company could benefit.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I don't think his company would benefit from the native</p>
<p>   title claim. I think quite the reverse, in fact.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>All right, I take your point. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah, I mean, for heaven's sake.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Which company would benefit [inaudible]...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He didn't initiate the native title - but you see, Neil, with</p>
<p>   respect, when something like this happens you get an hysteria and</p>
<p>   you get allegations made that have absolutely no evidence of bad</p>
<p>   faith or bad conduct. I mean, look at all the allegations that have</p>
<p>   been made this week, that he played golf and spoke to his former</p>
<p>   business partner who's his family lawyer. I mean, I defend</p>
<p>   Senator Parer's right, I defend the right of any of my Ministers</p>
<p>   to maintain social contact, to have meals with, of course. I mean,</p>
<p>   how anybody could argue against that is beyond me.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But Mr Howard, he has spoken on the Native Title Act and</p>
<p>   opposed it.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>What's wrong with that?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well because his company will benefit if his stand goes through.</p>
<p>   Surely that's a conflict of interest.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, it's not. That's the equivalent of saying that a</p>
<p>   farmer can never be Minister for Primary Industry. What is the difference?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>The difference is that the Minister should be declaring it and</p>
<p>   hasn't.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, hang on, no, he has declared it to me.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>When?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>He declared it to me ages ago.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>And you've been comfortable with it all along.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, no, I tell you what I did. I sent it all off to the Secretary</p>
<p>   of my Department, as I've sent all the pecuniary interest forms</p>
<p>   that have been given to me by my Ministers. And the Secretary of</p>
<p>   my Department went through it and he certified in writing to me</p>
<p>   that it was in order.</p>
<p>Senator Parer has behaved in good faith from the very beginning</p>
<p>   on this. He made full disclosure to me of his family trust's</p>
<p>   interest in this company. He made full disclosure to me of other</p>
<p>   interests that he had. He had been checked. He believed in good</p>
<p>   faith that he complied with the guidelines and until any evidence</p>
<p>   is produced to me that he has been involved in an actual conflict</p>
<p>   of interest - I mean, an actual conflict of interest would be if</p>
<p>   Senator Parer as Minister for Resources took an act that specifically</p>
<p>   benefited his company or a small group of companies in the resource</p>
<p>   sector, in the same way that if a farmer is the Minister for Primary</p>
<p>   Industry and takes action that specifically benefits his farm. But</p>
<p>   if he's involved in a decision which benefits the generality</p>
<p>   of farmers or the generality of coal producers or the generality</p>
<p>   of mortgagees, as in the case of Peter Costello with falling interest</p>
<p>   rates, to suggest that they should resign or there's a conflict</p>
<p>   of interest would render it impossible to have anybody with any</p>
<p>   business acumen to be a minister in your government. Australia would</p>
<p>   be the loser as a result.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>He says that he is considering selling the shares. Would you advise</p>
<p>   him to do so?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I am in discussion with him about a number of matters and</p>
<p>   I don't care to say anything more than that except to repeat</p>
<p>   that he has not done anything dishonest. He made full disclosure...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I don't think anybody's saying he's done anything</p>
<p>   dishonest, there's a conflict of interest.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there isn't. </p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yeah, but the Ministers you've sacked in the past didn't</p>
<p>   do anything dishonest, they had a conflict.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, can I go through the three that were affected by these guidelines.</p>
<p>   In the case of both Brian Gibson and Jim Short, they took specific</p>
<p>   action relating to a company in which they held shares. Now that</p>
<p>   is different from Senator Parer's case. In the case of Mr Prosser,</p>
<p>   claims were made that Mr Prosser was involved, however innocently</p>
<p>   in his mind, he was involved in lobbying for and advocating the</p>
<p>   cause of his business interests whilst being Minister. There is</p>
<p>   no evidence, at all, that Senator Parer has done that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What about his meeting with this Japanese...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But that Japanese company has literally hundreds of millions of</p>
<p>   dollars invested in the entire coal mining industry in Australia.</p>
<p>   It would be extraordinary in the extreme if, on a ministerial visit</p>
<p>   to Japan, he did not talk to the executives of that company. What</p>
<p>   would have been wrong would have been for Senator Parer to have</p>
<p>   said to the executives of that company: I would like you to do something</p>
<p>   specific for the company in which my family trust has an interest.</p>
<p>   Now isn't that a difference?</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yes it is.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And that is the key difference. While he is acting generically</p>
<p>   in the interest of the coal industry and that involves talking to</p>
<p>   major investors in the industry in Australia, he is not doing anything</p>
<p>   wrong.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, may we take a call?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Sure.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mark, go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Neil, Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>I am an average Australian and I am a citizen and I suppose I'm</p>
<p>   still undecided about the Telstra sale and I was wondering why should</p>
<p>   I support it and why would I be better off if it is sold?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, you could buy some shares in it and I don't know whether</p>
<p>   you are in a position to do that. I don't know your financial</p>
<p>   position on that, and that of course is your business. Another way</p>
<p>   you would be better off, of course is, that we will be able to reduce,</p>
<p>   by 40 per cent, the total Federal Government debt of Australia and</p>
<p>   I will tell you how that will directly benefit you. That will help</p>
<p>   to keep interest rates down and they, in fact, over time, with other</p>
<p>   circumstances lead to a further reduction in interest rates.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Are you surprised that the poll done here in Victoria yesterday,</p>
<p>   are you surprised that commentators said the Telstra thing was a</p>
<p>   masterstroke, the public doesn't seem to be going along with</p>
<p>   it overwhelmingly. I mean, in the polls you have seen so far.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it depends a bit Neil on the question that you ask. If you</p>
<p>   say to people, are you in favour of selling Telstra, the natural</p>
<p>   reaction of a lot of people is to say: no. If you say to them are</p>
<p>   you in favour of allowing the men and women of Australia to buy</p>
<p>   the remaining two-thirds of Telstra, the answer can be very different.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>OK. But you appeal the public is with you on it, despite the polls..</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I do. I do.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Isn't it a bit risky. I think I have mentioned here before,</p>
<p>   the calls that we get are very negative.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. You have got to take some risks in politics. I mean what is</p>
<p>   the point of being a Prime Minister of this country if you never</p>
<p>   take any risk, you just sit there and do nothing.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But I would have thought when you introduced, when you went this</p>
<p>   way on Sunday that you would have thought, now this is what could</p>
<p>   win the election for me. You might say it is the right thing to</p>
<p>   do but this will popular. (Inaudible).</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We will wait and see.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>That's fair enough. Speaking of an election. What criteria</p>
<p>   will influence you in deciding on an election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it is, you make a political judgement as to the correct</p>
<p>   time. You also take very much into account having it at a time which</p>
<p>   will, sort of, not cause any disruption of the community. I mean,</p>
<p>   normally elections don't cause disruption but you have got</p>
<p>   to keep those things in mind but all Prime Ministers try and choose,</p>
<p>   I guess a right time, not only in a political sense, but also in</p>
<p>   the sense of the national interest.</p>
<p> [COMMERCIAL BREAK]</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>And we are with the Prime Minister of Australia, John Howard, we'll</p>
<p>   take some more calls in a moment. Mr Howard the poll I mentioned</p>
<p>   a moment ago, that same poll showed Kim Beazley ahead of you in</p>
<p>   Victoria. Could you go into this election an underdog?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know. You see one of things that I try not to</p>
<p>   do, as Prime Minister, is to double as a political commentator.</p>
<p>   I mean naturally everybody likes to always read polls that are favourable.</p>
<p>   Sometimes they are not so favourable and we live in a more volatile</p>
<p>   political climate, and I have said repeatedly to my political colleagues</p>
<p>   that they can't assume that we will automatically win the next</p>
<p>   election with ease. I believed that from day one because we are</p>
<p>   living in a different world. People bounce around in their political</p>
<p>   affections a lot more freely and easily these days than they used</p>
<p>   to.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay Doug, go ahead please for the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, I am in favour of a GST like the John Hewson plan,</p>
<p>   just before the last election, but I wonder why don't you market</p>
<p>   it so laymen people, like myself can see the benefits. I am a sales</p>
<p>   rep and when GST was last opposed I was talking to a lot of businesses</p>
<p>   and they all said that they would hire between two to five people,</p>
<p>   these are medium sized businesses.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>That's an interesting point on marketing Prime Minister. I</p>
<p>   have in fact been following a newsletter Peter Costello is sending</p>
<p>   out to his electorate which is an introduction to it, which is all</p>
<p>   about tax. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We are sending that to as many electorates as possible around Australia</p>
<p>   and it is building a case for tax reform. On Doug's point I</p>
<p>   guess my answer, Doug, is just give us a go. When we release the</p>
<p>   policy I believe the marketing of it will be superior to the marketing</p>
<p>   of taxation changes in the past. I know it is always difficult to</p>
<p>   embark upon major reform but I deep down believe we need a better</p>
<p>   tax system because the present tax system is unfair and increasingly</p>
<p>   unworkable and I am prepared to have a go. If the Australian people</p>
<p>   reject me as a result, well I will accept that with the best of</p>
<p>   grace. I will be disappointed but I believe I owe it to the Australian</p>
<p>   people to try an implement a new, modern tax system for the 21st</p>
<p>   Century.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>While we are on tax, will be reviewing negative gearing?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. Negative gearing is not something that is on our agenda.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>It is on the Labor Party agenda. It was reported today. There have</p>
<p>   been rumours in the accounting community that you, the Liberal Government</p>
<p>   would review negative gearing.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think. Look, the problem with getting rid of negative gearing</p>
<p>   is that you would push rents up very sharply, very sharply indeed.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>So it is not on the agenda for you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there are pretty good reasons for that. You push rents up</p>
<p>   very sharply and you would also depress house prices and that would</p>
<p>   have a very adverse affect on people, particularly in Sydney and</p>
<p>   Melbourne. Could I just remind people, the Hawke Government tried</p>
<p>   this in the mid 1980s and after 18 months they abandoned it because</p>
<p>   rents went through the roof and it affected poor people more sharply</p>
<p>   than anyone else.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Michelle, you are speaking to the Prime Minister. Go ahead please.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Good morning Neil, good morning Mr Prime Minister. I have a major</p>
<p>   concern with the health insurance policies that are around. We're</p>
<p>   a family on $35,000 a year. We have had top cover my whole life.</p>
<p>   Last week I had to go in and lower it. In the last six months I</p>
<p>   have had over $6,000 worth of medical bills, out of my own pocket,</p>
<p>   and I can't afford my health insurance but at the same time</p>
<p>   I can't afford to drop it, so I have had to lower it where</p>
<p>   it is not enough to cover me.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Michelle, you say you have had $6,000 of medical bills out of your</p>
<p>   own pocket.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You or your family has obviously had some very serious operations?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>No, I have IVF treatment which is not covered because your Government,</p>
<p>   that I voted in, has dropped...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am sorry what treatment was that?</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>IVF.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yes, yes. Well I sympathise with your position but whilst it</p>
<p>   is a very, very important treatment and absolutely precious for</p>
<p>   your own personal situation - I am glad you mentioned what it was</p>
<p>   because it is not something that is occurring to everybody everyday</p>
<p>   - but I understand the particular circumstances of what...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But the story of people being able to afford health cover is fairly</p>
<p>   common.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yeah I know, but I don't think you can say that that particular</p>
<p>   case is typical of the whole situation.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, there is a report in the Financial Review today</p>
<p>   of a foreign affairs report to the Government on Indonesia, are</p>
<p>   you aware of that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I have seen hundreds of reports on Indonesia across my desk</p>
<p>   but that particular one, I am not sure. </p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>It says Indonesia is breaching the IMF guidelines with expensive</p>
<p>   family and cronie projects, now if that is the case why on earth</p>
<p>   are we getting involved in helping them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, we of course are not giving them any money, we are lending</p>
<p>   them money and it is repayable and we are doing that because we</p>
<p>   have a vested national interest in doing it.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But do you believe they are doing this...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Neil, I have to acknowledge that standards on these sorts of things</p>
<p>   in other countries are different from what they are in Australia</p>
<p>   and that applies no matter who is in office and I acknowledge that</p>
<p>   but you have to look at the broader picture. Is it in Australia's</p>
<p>   interests to see Indonesia sink further down into social dislocation</p>
<p>   and poverty and economic collapse? The answer to that is no. We</p>
<p>   have markets in Indonesia. We sell products in Indonesia. We sell</p>
<p>   services to Indonesia and it is in our selfish national interest,</p>
<p>   if I can put it that way, to make sure Indonesia doesn't fall</p>
<p>   over, and that is why we take the broader view that we do.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Do I support cronyism? Of course I don't but unfortunately,</p>
<p>   there are different approaches to these things in different countries.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is it cronyism in Indonesia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>For a person in my position in a delicate situation like this,</p>
<p>   as you know words are bullets.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Do you, on a broader point, do you expect that what is happening</p>
<p>   in Indonesia will lead to a flood of refugees in this country?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I hope not. I believe that if wiser counsel prevails and an agreement</p>
<p>   can be made with the IMF and if the rest of the world is appropriately</p>
<p>   demanding of Indonesia but not unreasonable, then the situation</p>
<p>   can be stabilised and major social dislocation avoided. But it's</p>
<p>   going to be very difficult.</p>
<p> MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, Christine go ahead please for the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>CALLER:</p>
<p>Hello Neil, hello Mr Howard. I just wanted to say that I totally</p>
<p>   support your stand on guns and I think it's terrific what you've</p>
<p>   done so far. I totally disagree with the states who are trying to</p>
<p>   weaken the gun laws. I don't want Australia to become like</p>
<p>   the USA where every man, woman and child owns a gun. In fact...to</p>
<p>   say on this one, Mr Howard, stick to your guns.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well thank you, I think you speak for the vast bulk of Australians</p>
<p>   in saying we don't want to go down the American path. I am</p>
<p>   sorry this issue has come up again. I don't want to have arguments</p>
<p>   with the states about it but the Australian people demand the maintenance</p>
<p>   of the tough gun laws we've got and I am personally very strongly</p>
<p>   committed to them. I believe in what was done two years ago and</p>
<p>   I feel quite emotionally committed to the maintenance of those laws.</p>
<p> MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Did you... I was going to ask you about that because I know you</p>
<p>   followed the case of Walter Mikac very carefully and in fact I sent</p>
<p>   you a tape of the speech he gave at the funeral. How did you feel</p>
<p>   meeting him yesterday? Did you feel that he'd been let down?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't think he's been. I am still optimistic that</p>
<p>   we will maintain the integrity of those laws because everybody feels</p>
<p>   pretty keenly about this and I am pretty optimistic about what can</p>
<p>   be agreed today. He seemed in quite good spirits. I have met him</p>
<p>   on a number of occasions over the years. You just can't even</p>
<p>   begin, of course, to comprehend what a man like that has been through</p>
<p>   and naturally, how strongly he would feel about this issue.</p>
<p> MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, we will take one more call. I think we've got time. Brian,</p>
<p>   go ahead please.
</p>]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
