<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11137</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER AND                 MINISTER FOR IMMIGRATION AND ETHNIC AFFAIRS                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP, AND                 THE HON PHILIP RUDDOCK MP                JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE &amp;#150; SYDNEY                                                             Subject: $124 million boost for the fight against illegal immigration</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/06/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINSITER:</p>
<p>Good afternoon ladies and gentlemen. Mr Ruddock and I have called</p>
<p> this news conference to announce the Government's decision to</p>
<p> provide a major boost to the capacity of Australia to fight the growing</p>
<p> challenge of illegal immigration. I should point out at the beginning</p>
<p> that so far the response to the increased threat of illegal immigration</p>
<p> to this country has been highly successful. Today's measures</p>
<p> which are very significant are designed to preempt what we see to</p>
<p> be an increased attempt by people from various parts of the world</p>
<p> to engage in people smuggling into Australia.</p>
<p>Australia has become increasingly attractive, not only because of</p>
<p> the quality of life in this country but because there is a perception</p>
<p> in some quarters that it is possible once one has arrived in Australia</p>
<p> to use the legal system to stay here for a lengthy period of time</p>
<p> even though one may have been initially arrived as an illegal immigrant.</p>
<p>Today's measures which provide $124 million over a period of</p>
<p> four years do provide a major increase in the capacity of this country</p>
<p> to improve the surveillance of its coast line, and importantly, very</p>
<p> importantly, today's measures increase Australia's capacity</p>
<p> to detect and deter illegal immigrants and immigration before they</p>
<p> get to this country and before in some cases they commence their departure</p>
<p> from the source country.</p>
<p>There are nine principle measures contained in today's announcement.</p>
<p> Today's announcement arises out of the establishment of a taskforce</p>
<p> under the chairmanship of Mr Max Moore-Wilton, the secretary of my</p>
<p> department, which I established in April of this year. I can report</p>
<p> that every single recommendation made by the taskforce has been adopted</p>
<p> by the Government.</p>
<p>The principle measures involve two additional Dash 8 aircraft to extend</p>
<p> the footprint and the intensity of Coastwatch aerial surveillance,</p>
<p> particularly along the east coast. And if you have a look at the map</p>
<p> you can see, indicated in red, the existing regular surveillance area</p>
<p> ,and the area in green, in outer areas that as a result of the new</p>
<p> measures that I'm announcing today will come within the footprint</p>
<p> of the surveillance activities. So we're going to provide two</p>
<p> additional Dash 8 aircraft and they will extend the footprint and</p>
<p> the intensity of Coastwatch's aerial surveillance, particularly</p>
<p> along the eastern coastline.</p>
<p>We're going to provide an additional night capable helicopter</p>
<p> to be deployed in the Torres Strait. We're going to establish</p>
<p> a national surveillance centre at Coastwatch's Canberra headquarters</p>
<p> with electronic links to State government agencies and defence establishments.</p>
<p>We're going to establish a new position of Director-General of</p>
<p> Coastwatch who will report directly to the head of the Australian</p>
<p> Customs Service, and this position will be filled on secondment by</p>
<p> a senior officer of the Australian Defence Force. And liaison arrangements</p>
<p> between Coastwatch, Defence and other agencies will be significantly</p>
<p> strengthened.</p>
<p>Importantly we're going to expand Australia's capacity to</p>
<p> detect and deter illegal immigration from source and transit countries</p>
<p> through posting twelve immigration officers to major source and transit</p>
<p> countries, including as airport liaison officers at key airports.</p>
<p>We're also going to conclude bilateral agreements with source</p>
<p> and transit countries for cooperation on people smuggling issues and</p>
<p> to provide for the return of illegal arrivals. And we're going</p>
<p> to provide strong support for the conclusion as soon as possible of</p>
<p> a protocol on people smuggling to the proposed UN Convention on Transnational</p>
<p> Organised Crime.</p>
<p>We're going to establish a high level information oversight committee</p>
<p> chaired by the Office of National Assessments to coordinate information</p>
<p> and intelligence on people smuggling, and we're going to introduce</p>
<p> comprehensive legislative amendments which the Government will put</p>
<p> before Parliament shortly to strengthen maritime investigatory and</p>
<p> enforcement powers to complement legislation on stronger penalties</p>
<p> against people smuggling.</p>
<p>The Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs, Mr Ruddock,</p>
<p> has indicated on a number of occasions over the past few months that</p>
<p> there is a very significant increase in people smuggling activities</p>
<p> around the world. It's estimated that illegal immigration reaches</p>
<p> something like 4 million people annually. Australia is clearly seen</p>
<p> as a very attractive target. There's no doubt about that. Australia</p>
<p> is seen as a more attractive target than many other countries and</p>
<p> that is because it's a very attractive country in which to live,</p>
<p> it has a very stable political system, it's a very fair and open</p>
<p> society, we have a very big coastline and importantly also we are</p>
<p> seen, or we are perceived to have laws that do make it easy for people</p>
<p> once they get here to tie up the legal system and stay for a long</p>
<p> period of time. And can I say on that again that the Labor Party would</p>
<p> help enormously the national interest if it facilitated the passage</p>
<p> through the Senate of some legislation that will deal with that problem.</p>
<p> And Mr Ruddock has asked them in the national interest on a number</p>
<p> of occasions and I repeat that request today. Protecting this country</p>
<p> against illegal immigration ought to be above partisan politics. And</p>
<p> we've been trying for, what Philip, a couple of years?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Yes, it's been underway for some time now.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's been underway for some time now to get this legislation</p>
<p> through the Senate and if we could get it through the Senate it would</p>
<p> send a very strong message to the crime syndicates in potential source</p>
<p> countries who are trying to exploit the human misery involving people</p>
<p> smuggling. It would send a very strong signal to them that we are</p>
<p> no longer such an easy mark. But that of course doesn't mean</p>
<p> that we shouldn't be taking other measures and the measures that</p>
<p> I've announced today will provide a major boost to our capacity</p>
<p> to fight illegal immigration, and it will as the map indicates, significantly</p>
<p> increase our capacity for coastal surveillance. We've chosen</p>
<p> areas which we believe will provide the greatest possible return from</p>
<p> the investment undertaken. But these measures are undertaken in a</p>
<p> preemptive fashion against future risk, not acknowledging that there's</p>
<p> been any past failure because the immigration authorities and the</p>
<p> customs authorities and the Australian Federal Police have been very</p>
<p> successful so far. And I want to compliment the Minister in particular</p>
<p> for the skillful way he's handled the very difficult issues including</p>
<p> a number of very well reported examples in recent months of detecting</p>
<p> a scheme for illegal immigrants to come to this country, sending a</p>
<p> warning through our embassies in those countries that they shouldn't</p>
<p> even try, and those warnings being highly successful. But we're</p>
<p> not complacent and because of that we've decided to make this</p>
<p> additional substantial commitment which we believe will dramatically</p>
<p> strengthen our capacity to deal with illegal immigration. Any questions.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Yes. Can you briefly outline what that legislation is that you think</p>
<p> that you want passed through?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well there are two pieces of legislation. The first relates to penalties</p>
<p> and it's going to the Labor caucus this week. I would like to</p>
<p> see it through the Senate. It can be attached to a bill that's</p>
<p> awaiting passage and in that sense we can deal with the increase in</p>
<p> penalties very quickly if we get that level of cooperation. The second</p>
<p> issue is in relation to judicial review. The bill's been before</p>
<p> the Senate for quite a while now. It was reintroduced at the beginning</p>
<p> of this Parliamentary term. And the Labor Party and others have indicated</p>
<p> their opposition to it. I've put a number of propositions to</p>
<p> the Labor Party in the way of dealing with those people who are principally</p>
<p> in detention. We might be able to put a privative clause in relation</p>
<p> to those matters to expedite our dealing with people who are held</p>
<p> in detention because judicial review can mean that you have to detain</p>
<p> people for many years. And you know the sorts of difficulties that</p>
<p> occur. We saw that in relation to the lady from China, that if you</p>
<p> have people in detention over long periods of time exploiting all</p>
<p> those possibilities, even though they have no lawful right to be here,</p>
<p> it can produce that sort of opportunity for delay. The bill is one</p>
<p> which is designed to enhance the decisions of the Refugee Review Tribunal</p>
<p> so that they would be final and determinative and that the option</p>
<p> of going to the court for further judicial review would no longer</p>
<p> be available.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Isn't it true that sometimes when appeals are made against the</p>
<p> Refugee Review Tribunal decision that they are thrown out, and that</p>
<p> person who's allowed to stay? That's the case at the moment</p>
<p> isn't it?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well it's true that there have on rare occasions been decisions</p>
<p> that have suggested that a legal, and sometimes I must say highly</p>
<p> technical point can lead to a decision being revisited. But what we</p>
<p> know is that over 9000 decisions over four or five years, less than</p>
<p> 50 actually different outcomes were obtained through court intervention.</p>
<p> And if you compare that with the final appeal which exists for everybody,</p>
<p> which is the application to the Minister for exercise of discretion,</p>
<p> I would have acceded in appropriate humanitarian cases to something</p>
<p> like 150 cases over the same period of time. Now my view is any lawyer</p>
<p> worth his salt ought to be able to put before me a substantial case,</p>
<p> and they certainly don't need to go to the courts at tens of</p>
<p> millions of dollars to get a different outcome.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is it something you've discussed with the Democrats?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>It's something that I discussed with the Democrats, Senator Harradine,</p>
<p> the Greens, and Labor. But look, there is a lobby and the lobby has</p>
<p> a degree of self interest. It's a very profitable area. We've</p>
<p> seen the marketing of class actions now by some members of the legal</p>
<p> profession which have led to 5,000 people, most of them of course</p>
<p> in the community as over stayers, but 5,000 people able to remain</p>
<p> in Australia. In many cases accessing Medicare and until we limited</p>
<p> access to work rights fairly recently, able to access work rights</p>
<p> lawfully. And of course one suspects that many of them having maintained</p>
<p> themselves here lawfully on a bridging visa because a class action</p>
<p> has started are probably unlawfully working in any event.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well the penalties in the legislation involve ten years penal servitude</p>
<p> as a maximum for being involved in people smuggling, and 20 years</p>
<p> as a maximum penalty for those who are involved in people smuggling</p>
<p> of 5 or more persons. Look there's one other matter I would mention.</p>
<p> I've seen in the press lately some comments that have suggested</p>
<p> that we should have a fairly benign view in relation to people smuggling,</p>
<p> that in some way these are people of great ingenuity and people who</p>
<p> would eventually make outstanding Australian citizens and therefore</p>
<p> we ought to put this issue as if it's of little consequence to</p>
<p> one side. There are very very important reasons why we have visa arrangements</p>
<p> to test people's eligibility to come, and we seek to enter people</p>
<p> within a framework of law.</p>
<p>It turns on the need to protect the Australian community not only</p>
<p> from quarantine risks that can occur if people land clandestinely,</p>
<p> which can jeopardise our economy in very significant ways but more</p>
<p> importantly, people who come in this way, if they were able to land</p>
<p> clandestinely may well have diseases, because they wouldn't have</p>
<p> been medically checked. Very often they come from places where tuberculosis</p>
<p> is a major disease that impacts on these communities. And any view</p>
<p> that you should turn a blind eye to these matters, as I have seen</p>
<p> written in some pieces lately, I think shows a very scant regard for</p>
<p> the broad national interest.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well there certainly are. We have been very successful to date in</p>
<p> thwarting a number of very large scale people smuggling ventures.</p>
<p> There was the 2000 people who were buying a passage on a vessel from</p>
<p> Somalia which when it was disclosed that they had no lawful right</p>
<p> to enter Australia they were very angry with the organisers, because</p>
<p> they had been lead to believe that such a venture would be lawful.</p>
<p>Now we saw the same in Indonesia this last week, where 100 young Javanese</p>
<p> males were the subjects of a people smuggling venture that was being</p>
<p> put together. Working together with the Indonesian authorities we</p>
<p> were able to properly brief people as to what their lawful entitlements</p>
<p> were and to discover the extent to which they were being mislead by</p>
<p> the organisers, they were being mislead to believe that what they</p>
<p> were doing might well be lawful, they were being mislead into believing</p>
<p> that that in due course there could be amnesties in relation to people</p>
<p> who might get here, they were being mislead in relation to their ability</p>
<p> to access employment in Australia. And one of the aspects of the measures</p>
<p> that the Prime Minister has announced today will be an enhanced capacity</p>
<p> to work abroad in alerting people to the way in which you do apply</p>
<p> to Australia if you wish to come lawfully and the potential risks</p>
<p> that befall you if you try to come unlawfully.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What is the situation on the ground in Fujian Province, which is one</p>
<p> of the big problem areas, which has been one of the centres of illegal</p>
<p> immigration for more than ten years?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well it's been a centre of illegal immigration to other countries.</p>
<p> The arrivals in Australia in the past were primarily from Beihei and</p>
<p> a significant programme was put in place complemented, I might say,</p>
<p> by successful returns. And what we have been seeking to do in relation</p>
<p> to the returns that we have been able to facilitate this year, on</p>
<p> each occasion is to ensure that in the media in China attention is</p>
<p> drawn to the fact that people attempted to enter Australia in this</p>
<p> way, that they have been returned, that they were duped, that they</p>
<p> suffered significant economic loss and that people ought not to be</p>
<p> inveigled by false promises. While we have had some comments to say</p>
<p> about the Opposition about where they could work cooperatively with</p>
<p> us in some additional measures, I might say, that one of the very</p>
<p> useful statements that was made recently, was that there would be</p>
<p> no amnesty, for people who arrive in Australian unlawfully. The Government</p>
<p> has affirmed that that is its position and the Opposition did, in</p>
<p> relation to that matter, indicate that if at some stage in the future</p>
<p> there was some change of Government there would be no amnesty that</p>
<p> would be implemented by them.</p>
<p>So we are endeavouring to ensure that the message in the broadest</p>
<p> possible way is brought to people in Fujian. The Secretary of my department</p>
<p> went there along with Andrew Metcalf, who is the head of the board</p>
<p> of control area and spent some time in the Fujian province. The head</p>
<p> of our mission in Beijing was there with the last group of people</p>
<p> who were returned from Australia. The media were informed of those</p>
<p> matters at that time. I have spoken to journalists from a number of</p>
<p> Chinese papers including the People's Daily, to brief them, from</p>
<p> here, on the way in which if people have an aspiration to come to</p>
<p> Australia they should test those matters at our Mission, rather than</p>
<p> being inveigled into these sorts of exercises.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>I mean that is a, I said to the Prime Minister that he better be prepared</p>
<p> for this question</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER</p>
<p>And we are.</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>And the situation is this. We locate something like 12,000 people</p>
<p> a year who are unlawfully in Australia. Now that is a large number</p>
<p> of people. We estimate that there are 50  51,000 people who</p>
<p> have overstayed visitors and so we would guess that more than 20%</p>
<p> of people are located during the course of a year. Now when you do</p>
<p> locate people you debrief them. You find out what travel documents</p>
<p> they've got, when they came to Australia and how. And while we</p>
<p> find an occasional stowaway, and stowaways have been a feature of</p>
<p> illegal immigration over a long period of time, we have never yet</p>
<p> found a person who has landed in Australia clandestinely and is here</p>
<p> unlawfully.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the measures that you announced today, are they in</p>
<p> response to the increase in targeting of Australia that has been noticed</p>
<p> in recent years? Would they have been made without...inaudible</p>
<p>PRIME MINSITER:</p>
<p>Well, they are being undertaken because there is a heightened challenge</p>
<p> to this country from illegal immigration, that's obvious. The</p>
<p> Minister has outlined the steps we have taken to prevent hundreds</p>
<p> of people starting the journey to Australia. There have been some</p>
<p> well publicised illegal arrivals and those people have all been successfully</p>
<p> intercepted and they are being returned in an orderly, efficient and</p>
<p> speedy fashion.</p>
<p>But we can't be complacent. We have a big coastline, we are attractive</p>
<p> and we're seen at the moment, unfortunately in some source countries</p>
<p> as having laws that do allow people, once they get a foothold here,</p>
<p> to tie up the system for a long time. And we want to send a very strong</p>
<p> message to the rest of the world that we are not only strengthening</p>
<p> ourselves against illegal immigration but if we can get that legislation</p>
<p> through the parliament that would send a very loud message to the</p>
<p> rest of the world that the idea that we are a very soft touch is no</p>
<p> longer valid and it is very important that we get that legislation</p>
<p> through, very important indeed.</p>
<p>These measures will greatly strengthen, as you can see, the footprint</p>
<p> is very significantly expanded, the green area illustrates the additional</p>
<p> area that will be under regular surveillance and I think it is a very</p>
<p> good investment and I think it will give a lot of reassurance to the</p>
<p> Australian public that we are alive to the threat posed by illegal</p>
<p> immigration. You can't eliminate it, you can't stop people</p>
<p> wanting to come to Australia. But you can send a very strong message</p>
<p> to them that they can't expect to be allowed to stay here and</p>
<p> tie up the legal system. And you can also strengthen your country's</p>
<p> capacity to detect illegal arrivals and that is what we are doing</p>
<p> and very importantly by sending additional immigration officers to</p>
<p> source countries we're increasing our capacity to seek out those</p>
<p> who would seek to come here, tell them that there's nothing in</p>
<p> it and warn them of the consequences of coming. And that kind of preventative</p>
<p> approach is a very good investment. It's worked very well so</p>
<p> far and we're going to increase it by posting additional officers</p>
<p> from the department, Mr Ruddock's department to the potential</p>
<p> source countries.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What countries are they going to?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>The particularly places that they'll be placed will be Shanghai,</p>
<p> Guangzhou, New Delhi, Colombo, Nairobi, Pretoria and Ankara, and the</p>
<p> airport liaison staff will be in Kuala Lumpur, Bangkok, Denpasar,</p>
<p> Singapore and Dubai. If you look at the areas from which at the moment</p>
<p> we are targeted and it's both in relation to aircraft arrivals</p>
<p> as well as boat arrivals. China has been significant. Areas like Sri</p>
<p> Lanka, much of Africa, particularly through...from places like</p>
<p> Somalia we've seen efforts and a good deal out of the Middle</p>
<p> East, Iraq, Iran, more recently Bangladesh. Countries like Afghanistan,</p>
<p> Algeria, have been the areas in which we are increasingly seeing unlawful</p>
<p> movements.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What boats do you know of that are heading this way and [inaudible]?</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>Well they're operational matters and we.....</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>There's talk of a boat sinking somewhere near the Philippines.</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>I'm not aware of such a matter but certainly we hear of matters</p>
<p> from time to time. That's intelligence information. That's</p>
<p> one of the reasons we want to have these additional staff.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You can be rest assured we'll provide what information we can</p>
<p> but no information that might limit our capacity to deal effectively</p>
<p> with the problem.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible]</p>
<p>RUDDOCK:</p>
<p>No I wouldn't say that either.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>People smuggling aside, the most unlawful, you know, the country from</p>
<p> which most unlawful people are here, is that from the UK isn&amp;</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
