<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8054</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008054.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
000<br />
NATIONAL 9 NU'IVOR I CANBEIR RA HULREIx.,<br />
VR" SGALLRYARLIAMENT 11OUSE CANIIERRA<br />
PlIN( 0127) 3 300 FAX: ( 062) 73 3097<br />
Date: 8 July 1990 Time: 0900<br />
Source: National Nine Network Programme: Sunday<br />
Jim Waley: For once, Labor's numbers men got it wrong.<br />
Wednesday, July 11 was generally felt to be the day Bob<br />
Hawke would go into the record book as Australia's second<br />
longest serving Prime Minister. Perhaps they forgot a leap<br />
year. But when-former Science Minister, Barry Jones,<br />
checked the sums he declared Tuesday the day Mr Hawke<br />
displaces Malcolm Fraser as runner-up to the all-time champ,<br />
Sir Robert Menzies. Sunday's political editor, Laurie<br />
Oakes, wasn't caught out though. He prepared our cover<br />
story on the Hawke factor, 2,679 days on.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: When Bob Hawke extended his winning to streak<br />
to four elections in a row last March he shared his triumph<br />
with his staff at the Lodge. The staff have served him for<br />
seven years and four months, almost double the average<br />
tenure of Australia's 23 Prime Ministers and come Tuesday,<br />
when he exceeds Malcolm Fraser's term, longer than any save<br />
Sir Robert Menzies.<br />
MALCOLM FRASER: I would like to congratulate him.<br />
Australian Prime Ministers have often been very short-lived<br />
except Sir Robert Menzies and Bob has come up into second<br />
place. Good luck.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: For a man who likes breaking records it is a<br />
particularly satisfying milestone.<br />
BOB HAWKE: It is a matter of pride. The satisfaction is<br />
basically that we have been in office long enough now to do<br />
things. The great problem of Labor in the past was that<br />
they were there for short period of time and couldn't really<br />
have a lasting impact. I think we have been able to do </p>
<p>2<br />
that. LAURIE OAKES: The Hawke Government has purged the memory of<br />
the turbulent Whitlam years. His Prime Ministership has<br />
coincided with an unprecedented period of Labor dominance at<br />
both the State and Federal level and while there are signs<br />
that dominance may now be waning, the achievement wins<br />
praise even from the man he defeated in 1983 and whose<br />
record he is about to overtake.<br />
MALCOLM FRASER: There aren't too many Australians who like<br />
their politics. When one half of us were frightened by the<br />
policies of one party and the other half were frightened by<br />
the policies of the other party. It was a deep ideological<br />
divide and the Labor Party under Bob Hawke and Paul Keating<br />
seems to have put all that into the past. It is not a<br />
socialist ideological debate any more. It ought to be a<br />
debate purely about competence. Who can do the job best.<br />
Whose balance of policies is best. This really is the major<br />
benefit that has come from the Hawke/ Keating axis.<br />
BOB HAWKE: I think Malcolm Fraser is right if he has said<br />
that I have had that preparedness to adapt. Now some of<br />
your opponents outside your party and perhaps at times more<br />
vehemently within your party will describe that as a<br />
weakness or as betrayal. I think it is a betrayal of your<br />
trust if you are not prepared to adhere to the goal of<br />
creating the greatest amount of happiness and prosperity and<br />
security that you can for your country. That what's your<br />
responsibility is.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: With the Government battling deep-seated<br />
economic problems, happiness and prosperity haven't exactly<br />
been Australia's lot for a siieable chunk of the Hawke<br />
years. Yet no modern Prime Minister has been so<br />
consistently popular. Another of his records is a 78 per<br />
cent public approval rating early in his term and it has<br />
only been in the last two months that an Opposition leader<br />
has managed to get his nose in front and keep it there for<br />
more than one poll.<br />
TONY EGGLETON: I think that Menzies's dominance of the </p>
<p>political scene was quite different from Hawke's. Hawke has<br />
been liked, even though that liking may be receding now, but<br />
Menzies was not ever a popular figure in the same sense. He<br />
was a much respected figure.<br />
BARRY COHEN: The public like him and they trust him. He<br />
has certainly got something that no Labor politician in<br />
history has had. A continuing to use his words love<br />
affair with the Australian people.<br />
BOB HAWKE: And for a fair bit of the time a lot of them<br />
reciprocated not with a constancy that measures changes but<br />
I think we are basically good mates.<br />
TONY EGGLETON: One of his strengths has actually been<br />
another personality. I think that his credibility has been<br />
greatly supported by Paul Keating as his Treasurer. I think<br />
it has been a combination of the likeable Bob with the tough<br />
Treasurer that has actually provided the combination that<br />
has been successful.<br />
PAUL KEATING: I think Bob himself would say that a<br />
substantial part of that is the team. I think the team<br />
would say the substantial part of it is him. He has had, I<br />
think, exceptionally good Cabinets. The part of the<br />
strength he has drawn from that has been his style of<br />
leadership which has been to let those Cabinets and those<br />
Ministers go about their portfolio responsibilities and to<br />
make and recommend changes in their own right.<br />
SIR JOHN GORTON: I think it is almost all Hawke personally.<br />
The team helps of course. It also hinders quite a bit. But<br />
I think it is Hawke personally and the feeling he has got<br />
among the people.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: There was a time ' when you wouldn't have had<br />
a schooner on Hawke becoming Prime Minister at all let along<br />
a sober and enduring one. He drank, swore and womanised<br />
with a recklessness that was unprecedented in public life<br />
but a lot of Australians loved the larrikin image. And at<br />
ALP gatherings it wasn't Whitlam's autograph they gave their<br />
shirts for, it was Hawke's. Sir John Gorton recalls how the<br />
then head of Australian Council of Trade Unions used to </p>
<p>behave in the Prime Minister's Office in those days.<br />
SIR JOHN GORTON: He used to come up to the office to see me<br />
when he was up here and he would sit down and he would talk<br />
to you very sensibly. He would have a can a beer and he<br />
would sit and talk to you. He would have another can of<br />
beer and then he would talk not so sensibly and in the<br />
finish he was just arrogant and just laying everything down<br />
and bashing the table and I am very glad he is not like that<br />
now. LAURIE OAKES: When you look back on the old Hawke, I think<br />
it is fairly true to say that you were a drunk, loudmouthed,<br />
aggressive person. None of that is unfair, is it?<br />
BOB HAWKE: No, there were all those things there but there<br />
was a constancy. I was always a very, very hard worker. I<br />
was a hard drinker. I can't disguise that fact and I don't<br />
intend to but I was never an alcoholic in the sense that<br />
most alcoholics can't work. When I made the very conscious<br />
decision which.. is now just over 10 years ago it was May<br />
1980, a decade without a drop it was a tough decision but<br />
one that I have never regretted because I could never have<br />
been Prime Minister if I hadn't made the decision.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: In the mid-1970s when he announced that he<br />
would give up the grog if he decided to enter Parliament,<br />
Hawke also promised to swear off swearing if he made a run<br />
for the Prime Ministership. A newspaper editorial said with<br />
considerable prescience at the time, a non-drinking Hawke is<br />
conceivable but a non-swearing Hawke is not bloody likely.<br />
But from the moment he got the Labor leadership Hawke<br />
underwent what amounted almost to a personality change.<br />
It wasn't only the drinking though. You changed the way you<br />
dressed, you changed your grooming.<br />
BOB HAWKE: I was never very flash on fashion everyone tells<br />
me and the fact that I was colour blind didn't help. Now I<br />
get a bit more guidance about it and I probably take a bit<br />
more notice because I am not just Bob Hawke. I am<br />
representing the country. I think Australians would want me<br />
to look pretty respectable.<br />
I </p>
<p>TONY EGGLETON: The tribute I would pay to Bob Hawke has<br />
been in fact his capacity to discipline himself since he<br />
became Prime Minister. I think the way he changed his<br />
style, his approach to life and disciplined himself was<br />
really quite amazing.<br />
BOB HAWKE: I am saying that I made that statement that I<br />
will not be making a challenge and I adhere to that<br />
statement. If you want to make your speculation, do it<br />
without me. I have made my position clear.<br />
REPORTER: But you could cut it stone dead right now.<br />
BOB HAWKE: I have made it quite clear. I have said it three<br />
times. You are just being a bloody pest. I have made it<br />
quite clear and you know it. Play that program to yourself.<br />
I have said it three times.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: That side of the old Hawke has come through<br />
much less often since he decided to act with Prime<br />
Ministerial dignity and got a group of minders around him to<br />
keep him on the straight and narrow. But Liberal Party<br />
research shows that when he lapses the effect on his<br />
standing in the electorate is noticeable.<br />
TONY EGGLETON: The angry, aggressive abrasive side of Mr<br />
Hawke is not an attractive aspect in the community and<br />
whenever he has lost that discipline the blip that shows up<br />
in the research is quite immediate. You will see an angry<br />
outburst and a moment of lost control and because the<br />
electorate really just like him as a person basically they<br />
feel he would make quite a nice chap to live next door and<br />
he seems quite a nice fellow but as soon as that image<br />
changes by an angry outburst it does have an immediate<br />
effect in the polls.<br />
BARRY COHEN: He can show tears, he can cry and he can also<br />
do his lolly. He also, incidentally, is oversensitive on<br />
some issues and sometimes you know he is wrong because it is<br />
bluster. You know he is in trouble.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON: Mr Hawke, can I ask you if you feel a<br />
little bit embarrassed tonight at the blood bits on your<br />
hands? </p>
<p>BOB HAWKE: You're not improving are you? I thought you<br />
would make a better start to the year than that. It is a<br />
ridiculous question and you know it is ridiculous. I have<br />
no blood on my hands.<br />
RICHARD CARLETON: Do you expect people to believe that you<br />
didn't know that meeting was taking place?<br />
BOB HAWKE: I would expect them to believe that you are a<br />
damned impertinent.<br />
BARRY COHEN: You will find that is one of his not-so-nice<br />
qualities. That he can be a bully. The only answer with<br />
Bob when he is doing his bullying is to call his bluff. I<br />
have seen those that do and he backs off.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: Hawke didn't follow the traditional<br />
parliamentary path to leadership. He was an MP for less<br />
than three years before getting the top job. He believes<br />
that has affected the media coverage of his Prime<br />
Ministership. BOB HAWKE: When I came to Canberra I was unique as far as<br />
the Press was concerned because I was already a national<br />
figure having been President of the ACTU for a decade. I<br />
owed nothing to the Canberra gallery. Not a thing. I<br />
didn't need them. I didn't go to them. I didn't use them.<br />
I became Prime Minister without them. I think and I am<br />
not saying this in a bitchy way or a complaining way that<br />
subconsciously that has been something that the Canberra<br />
gallery has been aware of.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: He did owe a great deal to Bill Hayden, worn<br />
down by constant sniping and pressure until he agreed to<br />
step aside as the Labor leader and hand over to Hawke on the<br />
very day in February 1983 that Malcolm Fraser made his<br />
fateful decision to call an election.<br />
BILL HAYDEN: I am not convinced that the Labor Party would<br />
not win under my leadership. I think that a drover's dog<br />
could lead the Labor Party to victory.<br />
TONY EGGLETON: I think Mr Hawke actually has been a very<br />
lucky Prime Minister in many ways from the very moment he<br />
came in and how he came in as leader because I think Mr </p>
<p>Hawke would have made a very poor Opposition Leader.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: Leaders of the bloodless coup that put Hawke<br />
into the leadership and the Lodge thought he would act as a<br />
popular figurehead while more serious politicians got on<br />
with the business of Government. But Hawke's new deputy,<br />
the heir apparent, and briefly a rival for the leadership<br />
two years ago says he has turned out to be a very serious<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
PAUL KEATING: The Prime Ministership is a serious job. I<br />
am not for a moment implying that anyone who has had it<br />
hasn't for a moment been serious about it but none in the<br />
post-War years have really been as serious about reestablishing<br />
the basis of Australian wealth. If you<br />
actually look for the Prime Minister who actually faced real<br />
problems squarely, and adjusted the nation accordingly, I<br />
think you have probably got to go back to Curtin.<br />
TOM UREN: I think there are too many of his Ministers that<br />
are, in fact,, economic rationalists first and Labor<br />
politicians secondly and I think that Hawke fills the gap<br />
that they don't really understand and that is the great<br />
thing about Hawke.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: Twenty years at the ACTU did breed in him the<br />
feel for a constituency far broader than any Parliamentary<br />
seat. An identification with ordinary Australians few<br />
contemporary politicians can match.<br />
BOB HAWKE: I feel still very close to them but you are<br />
right in the sense that I don't have the same amount of time<br />
to be as close as I was.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: Do you feel cut off. For instance, in the<br />
election when you didn't know the price of beer which I<br />
suppose is understandable for a teetotaller but that kind of<br />
thing. Knowing the price of bread and butter.<br />
BOB HAWKE: You certainly don't have the same knowledge of<br />
detail because you are isolated from a lot of it. That is<br />
true but the real question is are you isolated from what<br />
people are thinking and the concerns and do they write to<br />
you and do you write back to them. You have a look at my </p>
<p>correspondence and people are writing to me all the time and<br />
I am responding to them particularly young people. I know<br />
what their concerns are.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: What some Labor colleagues find hard to<br />
accept is that Hawke is also able to get close to people at<br />
the top of the wealth and social scale.<br />
TOM UREN: I would say that the thing that irks me more<br />
about Hawke at present, apart from our ideological<br />
differences, is his interests with some of the captains of<br />
industry. I think that some of his relationships with some<br />
of those people would curdle a Labor man a little bit<br />
because you can't have all things. You can't represent the<br />
whole of the people. That's all Irish. Labor Parties were<br />
elected to represent the class and I think that imprint<br />
should be made a bit more clearly.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: There must be some regrets and<br />
disappointments. BOB HAWKE: I must say that I am terribly disappointed about<br />
the child poverty issue. I made a mistake in not using the<br />
exact language in the delivered policy speech that was in<br />
the document.<br />
' By 1990 no Australian child will be living in poverty'.<br />
What we were going to do was to remove the financial need<br />
for any child to live in poverty. But that enormous<br />
achievement of which I am inordinately proud has been<br />
unquestionably clouded by the shorthand language that was<br />
used and that's a disappointment.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: After more than 7 years the constant<br />
pressure, media attention, lose of privacy might be expected<br />
to be taking its toll but this Prime Minister the positives<br />
easily outweigh the negatives.<br />
BOB HAWKE: Laurie, it is impossible for me to convey to you<br />
or to your viewers out there the sense of pride and the<br />
pleasure that goes with this job. Those costs are there but<br />
when you do the balance sheet it is overwhelmingly that<br />
side. LAURIE OAKES: Does the milestone matter? </p>
<p>PAUL KEATING: No, it doesn't matter a bit. It is only<br />
about the quality, never the time.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: Do you now start thinking about winding down<br />
or hanging up the gloves or do you look at the next one and<br />
look at Menzies record?<br />
BOB HAWKE: I am not looking at Menzies record but I am in<br />
no sense winding down. To do so would be an insult to the<br />
Australian people. If I were to say now that I have passed<br />
some record milestone I will start to take it easy, I<br />
wouldn't deserve to be Prime Minister for another day.<br />
LAURIE OAKES: How will you celebrate on the day?<br />
BOB HAWKE: I might have an extra cup of tea, Laurie.<br />
Jim Waley: Laurie Oakes reporting on Bob Hawke's record.<br />
In case you wondered we did invite Gough Whitlam to<br />
contribute his view on the subject. An offer he politely<br />
declined. For 0rivate rese~ amb ority. Wkiitst.: every effort is fnade~ to ensure accu~ racy for the beAef. Tv<br />
bf 9ur ctimets, no teqat or other res pnstbil1ty is taken ror errors and otoissions.<br />
( Transcript by Monitair Pty Limited)<br />
Inquiries to Peter Harvey, Press Gallery, Parliament<br />
House, Canberra. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
