<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7799</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007799.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 NOVEMBER<br />
1989 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you expect any other members<br />
of the ALP to be offering public advice about where the<br />
Government's going wrong or have they all just about had a<br />
go by now?<br />
PM: I would hope they wouldn't be. I was pretty straight<br />
forward on Friday in saying that we hadn't had a<br />
particularly good week and the fact that we hadn't had a<br />
particularly good week has apparently led some of my<br />
colleagues to make a few observations. But let me say also<br />
on Friday in the evening I was in Melbourne and we had a<br />
very fine function in Melbourne of the Victorian Branch and<br />
the attitude and the feeling there was enormous. Now I have<br />
made it plain I hope in a way which will be adhered to that<br />
if there are views to be put they should be put within the<br />
framework of the Government and any views should be conveyed<br />
to us. The position is basically quite clear as far as the<br />
Government is concerned. We believe that our fundamental<br />
economic policies are working and working well. They'll<br />
produce the right outcomes and the responsibility is now<br />
upon myself and my colleagues to make this clear and to<br />
continue to show that within the Australian political scene<br />
it is only the Government which has policies which are both<br />
relevant and can work against the snake oil mixture which is<br />
now being peddled by the opposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: What does it say about the Government though,<br />
that there's been this sudden outburst and people the likes<br />
of John Kerin, John Button and the NSW Branch as well?<br />
PM: Well John Button? What are you referring to about John<br />
Button? JOURNALIST: John Button today suggesting that<br />
PM: I was glad you mentioned today because I, not<br />
surprisingly, took the opportunity of looking at the<br />
transcript of the interview he had with Pru and I didn't<br />
find any problem with that. quite a beat up if you<br />
tried to make anything out of what John said. Pru put to<br />
him after eliciting from him that by comparison with what<br />
else was available in the opposition John Howard had a<br />
certain-measure of talent, she then asked him about a March </p>
<p>-2-<br />
economic statement. We another signal about wages<br />
directions and tax directions and John said this; " yes, I<br />
think we need another signal, I agree with that but that's a<br />
matter in terms of what the signals will be and it's a<br />
matter for my Cabinet colleagues, then the Prime Minister to<br />
determine. It's not for me to announce a new program'. Now<br />
that's an eminently reasonable statement by my friend and<br />
colleague, John Button. Let me say on that issue about<br />
signals. We will, as usual, be meeting with the ACTU in<br />
February or March of next year to discuss wages outcome for<br />
the following financial year. We have the situation now<br />
where the existing processes are bedding down, we'll talk to<br />
them again in February or March. There'll be a statement<br />
about wages direction coming out of that and as we've done<br />
in the past we will be consistently and continuously<br />
monitoring the economy. if we had the belief then that we<br />
had to add to the statement about wages outcomes by anything<br />
else then we would make that decision. But let me make it<br />
clear, we have no plans at this stage for a March Statement.<br />
We don't see any need for it but we have consistently shown<br />
since 1983 that in the process of continuously monitoring<br />
what's happening in the economy then we will make the<br />
decisions and the announcements that are necessary. So to<br />
bring that together again, we'll be talking with them in the<br />
beginning of the year about wages, we'll be making a<br />
statement. If there's anything more that needs to be said<br />
or done, then we'll do it. But there is no need to have a<br />
reaffirmation at this stage or indicate a reaffirmation of<br />
Government policy because the policy is working. If you<br />
look at the three elements of it, of fiscal policy, of<br />
monetary policy and wages policy, they're all tight, they<br />
are working. You've got the evidence today again of the ANZ<br />
employment index showing a further slowing down there. The<br />
Westpac Melbourne Institute indicators are showing a slowing<br />
down. So it's clear I believe that the economic policy of<br />
the Government is working and the important thing about that<br />
policy is that it's relevant. The issues facing the country<br />
are the high level of economic activity which brings with it<br />
problems on the external front and on the inflation front<br />
and the evidence is that all three arms of policy are tight<br />
and are working.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, would you prefer your s enior<br />
Ministers if they had criticisms, for example about the<br />
pilots' dispute or about the way which the balance is needed<br />
between environment and development and indeed whether a<br />
signal should be sent out, that they should make these<br />
concerns known within the confines of Cabinet and did you<br />
transmit this view to them today in Cabinet?<br />
PM: In the Cabinet today I had a brief opening statement to<br />
them where I indicated more or less what I'd said publicly<br />
last week, not the most glorious week last week, that there<br />
was no need for any concern about where the Government was<br />
heading and that we would continue with the existing<br />
directions of policy. For any observations they wanted to<br />
make there was the opportunity to make them. There was no </p>
<p>-3-<br />
question asked, no criticism made, as you would expect there<br />
not to be for the reasons that I'd put, that the<br />
fundamentals of policy are working, we're going in the right<br />
directions. Let me say this, as I've said in Sydney on<br />
Friday, I don't think I could've been more open and direct<br />
in acknowledging that we as I have put it in my language<br />
on Friday a less than glorious week, last week. All of<br />
us, including myself have some responsibility for that and<br />
in that context I think you've got to ask yourself well why<br />
is it that it was perhaps the most noticeable? That was<br />
because in the six and a half years we've been in Government<br />
this Government has dominated both the Parliament and the<br />
political agenda. Now when you have a situation that the<br />
Opposition's at last come out of its cocoon and produced<br />
what it calls an Economic Action Plan then there is going to<br />
be some difference of emphasis, if they have a relatively<br />
good week, that's going to be noticed. But let me say this;<br />
that increasingly what I said would happen is happening and<br />
that is that you're going to have more and more<br />
concentration upon the woeful inadequacies of this miscalled<br />
Economic Action Plan. I mean it is being ridiculed now,<br />
you've seen it in today's Press. The different world of Dr<br />
Hewson, the world which throws out all the economic<br />
certitudes and relationships, the snake oil salesman on<br />
behalf of Mr Peacock and the Opposition, are going to<br />
miraculously now remedy simultaneously the problems of<br />
inflation, unemployment, interest rates and foreign debt.<br />
It has been suggested by one commentator it's real Nobel<br />
Prize material, to do something that's never been done<br />
before. Now what's going to happen now properly is that<br />
there is going to be a zeroing in on this snake oil policy<br />
which is being peddled. It is both economically absurd and<br />
it is socially obnoxious and the pattern of politics in the<br />
period between now and the next election will involve two<br />
things. It will involve an analysis of the record of the<br />
Government and obviously by comparison with what they've<br />
done when they were in office and it's also going to involve<br />
particularly an analysis of what both parties can promise<br />
for the future. On the basis of what's been advanced by the<br />
Opposition, they are in terms of the Australian society<br />
going to promise without any possible question of argument a<br />
return to a massively divided and confrontationist Australia<br />
on the one hand and an economic policy which is as I say,<br />
absurd. JOURANLIST: Have you or do you intend to make contact with<br />
Mr Loosley or Mr Carr about their comments over the weekend?<br />
PM: I have spoken with Mr Loosley.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, can rural Australia expect any<br />
new spending initiatives before the next election?<br />
PM: There's a submission before the Cabinet today which<br />
deals with both a review of what we've done in regard to<br />
non-metropolitan Australia, which is of course a remarkable<br />
series of achievements already and a consideration of some<br />
further possible initiatives. That's a matter to be<br />
considered. </p>
<p>JOURANLIST: What did you say to Mr Loosley, Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: What did I say to Mr Loosley? I think that probably<br />
it's a sensible thing that the conversation I had with Mr<br />
Loosley should remain between Stephen and myself. As far as<br />
I'm concerned, it will.<br />
JOURNALIST: What was the tone of your conversation?<br />
PM: Very genial. My relations with as with my discussion<br />
with John Kerin the other night you see there is a<br />
difference, a fundamental difference between the two sides<br />
of politics in Australia today and just let's spend a very<br />
short time on them. I haven't attempted to deny that there<br />
have been some statements on my side of politics that<br />
probably would've been better not made publicly, but these<br />
are the differences of emphasis that have been made by<br />
people within a party which is fundamentally united about<br />
our philosophy and our direction for this country and they<br />
are statements made between people who have essentially a<br />
sensible working relationship and a shared commitment to the<br />
policies and philosophy of this Government. Against that on<br />
the other side of politics you have people who simply<br />
despise one another and deeply despise one another. I mean<br />
you won't have a situation on the Government side of having<br />
two senior figures, one, the Leader and the other, the<br />
previous Leader, that is Peacock and Howard making it<br />
publicly clear that they simply do not trust one another.<br />
The divisions and the hatreds on the other side of politics<br />
are profound. Here and on the Government side in the recent<br />
week or so you've had some concerns about emphasis<br />
expressed. I think they would've been better expressed<br />
directly within the private processes of the Party and of<br />
the Government. That hasn't happened. But the contrast<br />
between the two sides remains profound.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why do you believe that this is happening now,<br />
Mr Hawke? Why are the outbreaks of publicity happening<br />
right at this time? Is it because of the economic of<br />
your position?<br />
PM: Because of?<br />
JOURNALIST: The opposition's economic statement?<br />
PM: I think the fact that they've now produced a statement<br />
obviously changes the political scenario somewhat because up<br />
until that point they had nothing to run on other than the<br />
critical observations they wanted to make about Government.<br />
Now they've put out a policy and as we acknowledged at the<br />
time, if part of that policy involved the presentation of<br />
certain handouts, that's going to be attractive to some<br />
people until those things are analysed. They've created a<br />
somewhat different framework. But in no long term sense,<br />
one which is of any concern or adverse, of creating adverse<br />
problems for the Government. On the contrary when the time<br />
passes and there's more and more analysis of the social </p>
<p>inequity and the economic irrelevance of their statement,<br />
the more that goes on the worse for them and the better for<br />
the Government. Also I suppose you're reaching the end of<br />
what has been a pretty hectic year, a hard working year.<br />
All my Ministers and I don't think there's any argument<br />
between us on this all of us are very hard working people<br />
and I guess we'll all be looking forward to the break at the<br />
end of the year. But I look forward to it not merely<br />
because it's the end of a hard working year, but I truly<br />
look forward to it in terms that within this period we're<br />
going to be able to position ourselves, in my judgement,<br />
remarkably well to demolish the policies which are now<br />
emerging from the Opposition. Because without any question<br />
those policies are now, as I said on Friday night, creating<br />
a position of a fundamental ideological divide. There will<br />
be no election, in my judgement, in the post-war period more<br />
important than the upcoming election. Any nonsense that's<br />
been talked by inadequate analysis about this being a<br />
political scene that two parties of the centre with only<br />
peripheral issues of difference between them must surely now<br />
have been absolutely eliminated in the minds of any thinking<br />
person. You've got a stark alternative and I'm looking<br />
forward, eagerly, to exposing the starkness of that<br />
alternative and what constitutes the differences between our<br />
two parties.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you've said that you had yourself<br />
contributed somewhat to last week's problems. How would you<br />
identify your own did you go wrong?<br />
PM: I think I was a bit tired at the end of the week and<br />
some of my answers were a bit long and probably a bit dreary<br />
and that probably didn't give the sort of stimulus in which<br />
a leader ought to<br />
JOURNALIST: What about the matter of the disputes?<br />
PM: Well I'm glad you asked that and I do wish that in the<br />
reporting on it there would consistently at least be an<br />
0 accurate reporting of what I said. I said I mean<br />
adjectives do mean something I said quite clearly that the<br />
industrial dispute was over and let me make it clear before<br />
going back to that, I at that point made it quite cl-ear, as<br />
I do now, that the problems that are associated with that<br />
original dispute, that the problems associated with that.<br />
dispute are still with the industry, that there is a<br />
rebuilding problem going on and I at no point then or since<br />
seek to diminish the problems and not only the individuals<br />
but also particularly the tourism industry have suffered and<br />
to some extent are still suffering. I think it was less<br />
than fair to the reporting of what I've said that that<br />
wasn't made clear. I understood then and I understand now<br />
that individuals and the tourism industry have suffered and<br />
are continuing to suffer from the aftermath of what was<br />
originally that industri-al dispute. But it was more the<br />
point I was making was more than merely a technical one and<br />
no-one I notice has questioned the accuracy, the technical<br />
accuracy of what I've said. But there's more to it </p>
<p>-6-<br />
Michelle, than merely a technical and legal point. The<br />
reality which must be understood is that as a result of the<br />
ending of the industrial dispute in the technical sense, the<br />
reality that flows from that is that the AFAP has no part in<br />
the rebuilding operation that's going on. This is a point<br />
that I wanted to make clear and which is indisputedly true.<br />
The AFAP has no part in the resolution of the rebuilding<br />
program which is going on and that's not because it's<br />
something that I wanted to produce but it's a result of<br />
their decision. It's not merely the resignation of their<br />
members from the two airlines but when that resignation was<br />
followed up by the taking of their long service leave<br />
entitlements and the complete severance of the relationship<br />
of their members with the two airlines, then that fact<br />
which is a fact and not a Prime Ministerial opinion is<br />
relevant to the processes now of rebuilding. What is<br />
happening now as you've seen is what I said would happen.<br />
That is once they made that decision to sever themselves,<br />
then the airlines, with the assistance of the Government,<br />
have gone about the process of rebuilding airline services<br />
in this country. As you've seen, according to the<br />
statements of the airlines they have now provided a<br />
scheduled service, announced service according to which<br />
people are able to book into December and then they will be<br />
doing the further scheduling for the period from January<br />
through to March. So I want to make it clear that I was<br />
making not merely a legal point which is unarguably,<br />
indisputably correct but it's also more than that, it's to<br />
establish the point that now in the resolution of the<br />
problems which are continuing following that industrial<br />
dispute, in the resolution of the problems that are real<br />
then the AFAP their decision has no part in resolving<br />
those issues in rebuilding the airlines.<br />
JOURNALIST: You indicated earlier on that after the talks<br />
between the Government and the ACTU next year, there'll be<br />
some sort of statement on wages direction and possible wages<br />
outcomes. Is that likely to be a broad statement which<br />
could also include matters such as tax which<br />
PM: No, I specifically went to that, Paul. I specifically<br />
went to that. I said there will definitely be a statement<br />
coming out of that meeting in terms of wages. In terms of<br />
our analysis and continual monitoring of the economy, what's<br />
happening if and we get to that stage it's our judgement<br />
that there needs to be more done or said, then that will be<br />
done. But we haven't at this stage got any plans for what<br />
you might call a March Statement. But if we regard it as<br />
necessary to add to what we'll be saying and doing in regard<br />
to wages, that will be done.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, is there room in that sort of wages<br />
statement for a component relating to child care?<br />
PM: well conceivably there could be. We'll be reviewing<br />
all of our areas of relevant policy and by that I mean<br />
within the context of the social wage approach our wages<br />
policy as you know has this essential foundation and that is </p>
<p>that we seek and have achieved successfully, restraint in<br />
the making of money wage claims which restraint is<br />
compensated by outlays in the area of the social wage. Now<br />
what you do in regard to child care has been seen properly<br />
as a component of that and it can continue to be seen as<br />
such.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime minister, were you caught on the back<br />
foot though by the Opposition's proposal to more than<br />
quadriple the spending on child care?<br />
PM: Not caught on the back foot. I mean, we'll be quite<br />
happy as we go up to the election to compare both our<br />
performance and our policy on child care with the<br />
Opposition. I mean, look at what we've done in the area of<br />
child care. It's been, I think, a remarkable achievement.<br />
It was not the best kept secret that that's an area at which<br />
. they were looking. I simply say this to you, that I will be<br />
quite confident by the time we go to the election of<br />
comparing our position, our achievements and our policy in<br />
that area with the Opposition, both in terms of that area of<br />
policy itself, but also, very importantly, that policy<br />
within the general framework of what we're doing for<br />
Australian families.<br />
JOURNALIST: special work to be done on this area, Mr<br />
Hawke? PM: No, I haven't asked for any special work to be done.<br />
There may be work being done, but I haven't specifically<br />
asked for any.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why are your expectations tax cuts trade<br />
off the<br />
PM: No, we haven't I mean, it's just far too early, it<br />
would be quite irresponsible to say that's what you'd do.<br />
It may well be, it could well be. I'm speaking<br />
theoretically now, but it could well be, in terms of the<br />
analysis, of what was happening in the economy, it could be<br />
that it was quite clear that the best thing to do would be<br />
to increase your surplus, that that would be in the best<br />
interests of everyone. So, to commit yourself now to a wage<br />
tax trade off would be premature.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I'm simply saying that what, I repeat what I said<br />
earlier, and that is that we will continuously monitor<br />
what's happening in the economy including what's happening<br />
to wages outcome, inflation, demand pressures and so on.<br />
We'll obviously, as I've said, be talking to the ACTU about<br />
wages outcomes. Now, as I've said in answer to another<br />
question, remember Paul here, I said that, according to the<br />
monitoring that we are doing and the analysis around the<br />
if we regard it as appropriate to have anything<br />
-attached to the statement about what we see as the wages<br />
outcome" then that will be done. But it would be </p>
<p>-8-<br />
irresponsible to say ' yes, it will be a further tax cut now'<br />
when your assessment at the time might<br />
JOURNALIST: trade off<br />
PM: I'm simply, I mean, I think I'm expressing myself<br />
lucidly and that is to say to you that that is a<br />
possibility. That's one thing that could be on the table as<br />
being said, that that's one thing that could be there. But<br />
there are a number of issues that will be examined and in<br />
terms of our analysis of the economic situation, we'll make<br />
the decision and the range of decisions that we think are<br />
most appropriate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, if the economy does not show any<br />
clear signs of slowing by early next year, will that create<br />
pre conditions for the Government to stand<br />
PM: Well, I think,...... let's say this. I think we can<br />
probably say today, with a little bit more assurance than I<br />
could have, say a month ago, that there are more signs now<br />
of the economy slowing down than we would have a month<br />
ago. I mean, I've just referred in one of my previous<br />
answers to the latest ANZ employment index which gives a<br />
further indication of a slowing down in the demand for<br />
labour. You've got the Westpac Melbourne Institute survey<br />
of leading economic indicators which are showing a further<br />
slowdown. So, I think that we can say that there is some<br />
more evidence of a slowing down now than there was then. I<br />
would expect by that time for there to be further evidence.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just on that point Mr Hawke, given your<br />
confidence that the economy is slowing and also that the<br />
base economic are in fact Are you more confident<br />
now than before that we'll see interest rates falling<br />
towards the end of this financial year?<br />
PM: Well, while I've said, Paul, that there's somewhat more<br />
evidence available now about a slowing down, I repeat what I<br />
said before, that we will need to be quite confident in our<br />
own mind that the slowing down has reached a point where we<br />
could with confidence contemplate an easing of monetary<br />
policy. I'm not going to pre-empt that other than to repeat<br />
what I've said. I do think there's somewhat more evidence<br />
of a slowing down now than there was, say, a month ago.<br />
JOURNALIST: pharmacy dispute?<br />
PM: I'm glad you went to that question, Paul. Let me make<br />
this point quickly by way of giving it an historical<br />
background because it is relevant to answering your<br />
question. What we were confronted with was a situation<br />
where there was an attempt to negotiate with the industry.<br />
We were very close to getting an agreement in the earlier<br />
part of this year. Now,. I wish we could have got there.<br />
But we couldn't, so we had to go to the Tribunal which<br />
* exists under the legislation established by our<br />
predecessors. Under that decision, there was a point put to </p>
<p>us as a Government as to how much taxpayers' money should go<br />
to pharmacy remuneration. We've got a responsibility to<br />
respect that. But the PBRT did indicate that there were<br />
other areas which were relevant to the emoluments and the<br />
profession of the pharmacy which were outside their purview<br />
and which was appropriate for Government to look at. Now,<br />
we've done that. As you know we sought, in that context,<br />
after the PBRT decision, we sought to have negotiations with<br />
the Guild. That didn't work. So, by last week's decision<br />
what we've done is to settle the parameters of the<br />
resolution of this matter. You may have noticed that the<br />
analysis that's taken place of that decision, some have said<br />
it was too generous and, of course, some areas of the<br />
industry have said it didn't go far enough. We believe<br />
we've got the balance about right. What's happening now is<br />
that the industry in its various components is<br />
considering the decision of the Government. I simply want<br />
to express the hope that now that that decision has been<br />
made and the decision has been made and the framework of<br />
that decision will be implemented. We would like to have<br />
the position where the Guild could be associated with its<br />
implementation and within that framework, there may be some<br />
issues at the margin which were capable of further<br />
discussion, but I want, I want the industry to understand<br />
that the framework has been settled, we had to settle it. I<br />
hope that they will now respond positively to the very many<br />
elements in it which are manifestly of value to the<br />
profession. I mean, it does contain $ 60 million outlay in<br />
its three component parts, the professional allowance,....<br />
pharmacy allowance, the restructuring allowance. Together<br />
some $ 60 million. Secondly, it does contain the mark up<br />
concept which has been important to them and a preparedness<br />
on our part to go with them to the PBRT and argue for the<br />
mark up. Thirdly, a preparedness to put a representative of<br />
the retail pharmacy, well not correct to say representative,<br />
but a person with experience in the retail pharmacy industry<br />
on the Tribunal, something that they've asked for. Now<br />
quite clearly that is a decision which addresses matters of<br />
concern to them and it sets down the parameters. We hope<br />
that they would now come in and be associated with the<br />
implementation of that concept.<br />
JOURNALIST: compensation for the airlines still<br />
justified and when will it end?<br />
PM: Well, let's-get the language right. The compensation<br />
has been not to the airlines for losses, it has been to meet<br />
the situation of enabling them to keep on their employees<br />
for whom otherwise there would not been gainful employment.<br />
By definition, as they are increasing their activities,<br />
which they are very substantially, then the rationale for<br />
that payment diminishes and is diminishing. There will be<br />
discussions going on now in the immediate future with the<br />
airlines, both about that area, how much longer that is<br />
necessary and also how much longer it will be necessary to<br />
have the supplementation of services by the RAAF and<br />
international airlines. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: How much is it costing the Government at the<br />
moment? PM: I haven't got the figures<br />
JOURNALIST: Roughly.<br />
PM: No, let me simply say this. By the time that process<br />
of payment for their otherwise redundant employees, by the<br />
time that's finished it will be a significantly lesser<br />
amount than the figure of $ 100 million that's been talked<br />
about earlier in the dispute.<br />
JOURNALIST: For the record, Prime Minister, could you<br />
categorically again rule out a half Senate election?<br />
PM: Yes, there's no half Senate election.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, the latest polling shows that your<br />
vote in Melbourne is God awful. why is this, and what can<br />
you do about it?<br />
PM: Well, I don't just fragment what we've got to do,<br />
Michelle. I think that the essential things that we have to<br />
do to some extent been covered in earlier comments that I<br />
made and it's true, not only for Melbourne, true for<br />
Australia generally. I think we have to do these things.<br />
We have to communicate the achievements of the Government in<br />
the fundamental areas of importance for the Australian<br />
people. That includes not just economic policy generally,<br />
micro economic policy reform, that's been done in the area<br />
of employment and for families. What we've done also<br />
internationally in terms of the future of this country.<br />
We've got to communicate those achievements which are very,<br />
very substantial. But, I think, increasingly, as I've said,<br />
what we have to do not only for Melbourne but for the rest<br />
of Australia, is to starkly and sharply draw out the<br />
contrasts between what the conservatives are offering as an<br />
alternative Government and what we offer. quite clear<br />
that they are offering nothing more than a return to the<br />
divisiveness, the confrontationism and the inequity of the<br />
past. I don't think the people of Melbourne, or for that<br />
matter the people of any other part of Australia, are going<br />
to take too kindly to the proposition that billions of<br />
dollars of capital tax gain liability are going to be<br />
made capable of avoidance so to benefit one percent of the<br />
population at the expense of the great masses of people of<br />
Melbourne and elsewhere in Australia. That is typical in a<br />
glaringly obvious example of the sort of society that the<br />
Liberals and National Party want to create. When the people<br />
of Melbourne and the people of Australia understand that I<br />
have no doubt what their judgement will be.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think that John Elliott is an election<br />
issue? </p>
<p>-11-<br />
PM: Good question. I think, rather than John Elliott<br />
himself, I think John Elliott himself to some extent is an<br />
issue. But I think that what John Elliott represents is an<br />
election issue. John Elliott, because he is President of<br />
the Liberal Party is the starkest example, if you like, of<br />
what is represented by the Liberal Party policy, the<br />
Liberal/ National Party policy. In a very dramatic and<br />
unavoidable way, Elliott is there, on the scene and can be<br />
shown as epitomising what their policy is about. Their<br />
policy is about giving John Elliott and his ilk billions of<br />
dollars of benefit of a total perversion of the tax revenue<br />
system of this country. That it means going back to what<br />
this country suffered from in the seven years before we came<br />
to Government. That is, that those with the greatest<br />
capacity to make a contribution to the revenue of the<br />
country are going to be free from that responsibility. That<br />
means not simply that this is a grossly inequitable society<br />
that they want to create, but in terms of the real interests<br />
of ordinary Australians, that means Government being denied,<br />
literally, for a time billions of dollars of revenue which<br />
could otherwise be used in advancing the real interests of<br />
ordinary Australians. So, John Elliott, in a sense,<br />
epitomises, represents that stark contrast between the two<br />
sorts of Australia that are on offer and in respect of which<br />
a choice has to be made at the next election.<br />
JOURNALIST: In spite of the events of the past week are you<br />
confident that you have or can stop the rot in the Party?<br />
PM: Stop the rot what?<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I thought you said something after that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Stop the rot in the Party.<br />
PM: I don't accept that there's rot in the Party. I mean<br />
that's an overstatement. I think I've been totally frank in<br />
acknowledging that there've been problems. No-one can say<br />
well look the Prime Minister has tried to dodge the fact.<br />
I've acknowledged it but I've tried to put it in the*<br />
perspective. I think that we would be better off if what<br />
had happened hadn't. But there's no sense in which this is<br />
a rot. I don't have to stop the rot. What I've got to stop<br />
and what I will stop is a certain lack of discipline I think<br />
that's been exhibited and getting everyone together and<br />
united and a tight disciplined Government which has been<br />
the hallmark of our six and a half years. There'll be no<br />
problem in achieving that.<br />
JOURNALIST: been criticisms, a couple of criticisms,<br />
firstly your handling of the pilots' dispute and in the<br />
pre-empting of various Cabinet decisions that you have lost<br />
your capacity for concensus. </p>
<p>-12-<br />
PM: No, none of the analysis, that's wrong. My<br />
approach to the running of this Government is still very<br />
much a consensual approach. The Ministers still have, both<br />
within the Cabinet and in terms of approaching me, a very<br />
great deal of freedom as they should have.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudiable)<br />
PM: How about letting me finish the answer old boy. Thank<br />
you very much indeed. I'm indebted to you. That they have<br />
that freedom in the I think the one issue that's probably<br />
been talked about where I pretty firmly put a position<br />
before Cabinet in regard to Kakadu. Now there, that wasn't<br />
at the beginning of the Cabinet consideration of this<br />
matter. The matter had been before Cabinet on a number of<br />
hours before that on different occasions. I reached the<br />
point where I'd listen to all that had been said and thought<br />
about it and I wanted to concentrate the discussion. I did<br />
that by making it clear what I thought was the appropriate<br />
outcome. And that was agreed to. But in terms of the<br />
handling of this Government's business I think probably more<br />
than it's been the case with any other Prime Minister that I<br />
understand, and as far as we can look back, mine has been an<br />
approach of making sure that every minister has a full<br />
opportunity to make his or her input. I have no intention<br />
of changing from that course and I haven't. You mentioned<br />
the pilots' dispute there. We had a lengthy discussion in<br />
the Cabinet about that and as far as I can recall there was<br />
unanimous support for the approach that we've adopted.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think that Mr Elliott played some role<br />
in the formulation of the Liberal tax policy, specifically<br />
on capital gains tax?<br />
PM: I don't know what the nature of his input was.<br />
JOURNALIST: Coming back to Senator Button Mr Hawke, you did<br />
say there was a need for I think you said..<br />
PM: ( inaudible)<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I think another signal.<br />
JOURNALIST: It does suggest that there's a need for at<br />
least an adjustment in policy at the present time.<br />
PM: No it doesn't. C'mon. Let me read it out to you again<br />
Milton. I think we need another signal, I agree with that.<br />
But that's a matter in terms of what the signals will be and<br />
when. It's a matter for my Cabinet colleagues and the Prime<br />
Minister to determine. That's a I find that a perfectly<br />
unobjectionable statement and I've addressed myself to it by<br />
saying that we will be indicating to the Australian<br />
electorate at the appropriate time in this area of economic<br />
policy which has been talked about, what new developments </p>
<p>-13-<br />
there'll be. we don't there's no need for a signal from<br />
the Government as to whether its policy is working. The<br />
policy is working. As I said, each arm of policy is there.<br />
It's tight fiscal, monetary, wages. They're tight and<br />
they're working. I've given the evidence. More<br />
indications, just most recently of how it's working, if<br />
there's one side of politics that really needs to be put<br />
right on the line about what its policy means, more than a<br />
signal but an explanation of what this different world in<br />
inverted commas is that's involved in their policy, it's the<br />
Opposition. It is a joke. It's no coincidence that you<br />
have a significant economic commentator coming out today and<br />
ridiculing it. it's rewriting the text books. Most<br />
interestingly of course, and if you're going to really get<br />
down to the guts of their non-policy, the fact that it's<br />
snake oil irrelevant nonsense, it's this. That at the heart<br />
of it it's wages policy. They say there that what's<br />
their phrase I'll just get their phrase about wages<br />
policy. " If you move decisively and quickly" this is on<br />
wages " if you move decisively and quickly you can avoid<br />
any significant effect on unemployment." Now there is no<br />
commentator in Australia I suggest who will begin to give<br />
creedence to what they're saying in that area. There is no<br />
way known to man or woman that they can bring in a wages<br />
policy which is the central linchpin of producing all their<br />
other snake oil promises on inflation and interest rates and<br />
foreign debt and unemployment. Wages policy is critical and<br />
there is no way that they can make that work.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, number of indications of the<br />
slowing up of the economy require before they can<br />
determine there's enough confidence monetary policy?<br />
PM: That would be an act of judgement taking account the<br />
range of indications. And the areas that are important as<br />
you know are in employment, housing and so on. When you're<br />
looking at all those indicators we feel that together we've<br />
got a firm enough basis for saying that the economy is<br />
slowing down in a way which would be relevant to having<br />
0 confidence about the level of imports and activity and also<br />
the inflation. Bring those things together enable<br />
us to form that judgement, then at that point the decision<br />
will be made in regard to measuring of monetary polity.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have you conceded that in the<br />
Parliament last week you didn't perhaps put How do<br />
you think you can improve you own personal game?<br />
PM: I think that basically the game has been played one<br />
thing I could probably do is try and get a little bit more<br />
sleep.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Mr Peacock has just told the Jewish<br />
community leaders that he's ordered his shadow foreign<br />
minister, Senator Hill, not to talk to PLO leaders such as<br />
Terzi, the UN Ambassador. So how do you see that sort of<br />
decision? </p>
<p>-14-<br />
PM: It's a little bit a case of trying to close the stable<br />
door after the horse or the Hill has bolted, isn't it. If<br />
you wanted a massive piece of hypocrisy it's the<br />
advertisement in the I forget which one it was but one<br />
of the newspapers in the Jewish community which sought to<br />
differentiate the Government and the Opposition<br />
saying that they would not have any such conversation. But<br />
of course they had already had those conversations. A<br />
massive piece of hypocrisy. But not unusual in line with so<br />
much of the hypocrisy that characterises everything they<br />
address themselves to. Last question.<br />
JOURNALIST: ask you to comment on your wife's entry<br />
into journalism.<br />
PM: I was very proud of it. a) I was proud of the fact<br />
that she was asked to contribute and b) I thought the first<br />
article was impressive, well-written, sensitive and relevant<br />
to the interests I think of a large number of Australian<br />
people. JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Certainly a very considerable newspaper and importantly<br />
a very large readership.<br />
JOURNALIST: Melbourne Cup?<br />
PM: Well this rain has disrupted a lot of things. If it<br />
hadn't rained I would've thought that Empire Rose was again<br />
a good thing and would have double-up wins. I think all I<br />
can say is at this stage I'll be wanting to see what the<br />
track is like tomorrow. If the track is good then I think<br />
Empire Rose will win again. If the track is rain affected<br />
then it becomes much more open and I think you'd have to<br />
take account of Coshking. An outsider with a bit of a<br />
chance in those circumstances is Fleetwood Lad. I think<br />
that's got a chance in those circumstances. So if I took a<br />
prime track, Empire Rose. If it's wet, then perhaps<br />
Coshking. Fleetwood Lad as an outsider.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
