<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5180</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF &#039;AM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005180.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 19 OCTOBER 1979<br />
from the Press Office Summary of<br />
Rumours are rife in London and Washington claiming that the<br />
Soviet leader is dead. There is no confirmation from Moscow<br />
that Mr Brezhnev is either ill or dead, although many diplomats.<br />
believe he has been either very over-tired or that his chronic<br />
ill-health has suddenly worsened.<br />
The Carter administration moved swiftly today following a Judge's<br />
ruling that would block the United States from ending the mutual<br />
defence treaty with Taiwan.<br />
Report on the stories coming from Kampuchea of disease,<br />
malnutrition and the deaths occurring from them.<br />
What has been seen as a desperate effort to fix the Victorian<br />
coalition rift occurred last night at the. Lodge. State and<br />
Federal leaders of the Liberal and Country parties met last<br />
night to prevent further animosity developing between the<br />
two parties. Local branches of the Liberal Party in Gippsland<br />
are still determined to press ahead with their plans to run<br />
a candidate against Mr Peter Nixon. Interview with the<br />
Leader of the National Party in Victoria, Mr Ross Edwards,<br />
has suggested that yesterday's meeting has committed the<br />
Liberal Party leadership at least into attempting to restrain<br />
their branch members. Interview with Mr Ross Edwards who said<br />
the meeting yesterday was very successful and a good deal of<br />
progress was made.<br />
There will be further discussion on Coalition unity when the<br />
Prime Minister and Federal Liberal Party officials gather<br />
with State Party leaders for their annual meeting. of particular<br />
concern will be the separate Senate ticket issue in Victoria<br />
and also Queensland, where one celebrated nomination has come<br />
from the Premier' s wife.<br />
There has been a breakthrough at the Zimbabwe-Rhodesia peace<br />
talks. After a short meeting between Lord Carrington and the<br />
leaders of the Patriotic Front it was announced that all parties<br />
have now agreed to a draft constitution for the country.<br />
South Africa is again stalling on the United Nations plan for<br />
a peaceful transfer to independence in Namibia. There is now<br />
great scepticism amongst the five Western nations supporting<br />
the scheme as to whether the South African government has any<br />
real interest in going ahead with it.<br />
The Philippines defence minister has revealed for the first time<br />
the existence of a new rebel group led by several priests.<br />
The group is reported to be comprised mainly of Catholic laymen<br />
and sympathisers.<br />
The Nobel Prize for Literature has been awarded to a Greek poet.<br />
The Federal Government has been attacked once again over its<br />
amendments to the Conciliation and Arbitration Act, this time<br />
by one of its own members. Senator Missen has described the / 2<br />
L. </p>
<p>changes as provocative and counter-productive. Interviewed:<br />
" Because of the very great powers in the de-registration area<br />
obviously unions will be fearful of this, obviously they will<br />
resist it very strongly, and one might have more trouble than<br />
we would have without that part of the legislation".<br />
Question: Do you think the Government has just simply overreacted.<br />
Senator Missen: I think so. I think that I would have liked to have<br />
seen more consultation about the legislation before hand, including<br />
the lawyer members of the Law and Government Committee who of course<br />
didn't see this before the Bill arrived in the Party, and who I think<br />
could have contributed to it.<br />
Question: Why do you think the Government has overreacted?<br />
Senator Missen: Well, I don't know why because I'm a backbencher<br />
and I am therefore not privy to the discussions that have gone on<br />
in cabinet. There is a serious situation in regard to sfrikes at<br />
the present time, and a lot of key areas where a lot of damage is<br />
done to the community. I think they feel something has got to be<br />
done about this, and there is a lot of pressure to do it, and I<br />
suppose that makes for urgent action.<br />
Question: But in that context, and given your reservations,<br />
do you think the Government has been provocative?<br />
Se nator Missen: I think the result of the Bill is provocative<br />
and I think something about it the way in which the Bill has<br />
actually been handled. It has been fairly secret and not taken<br />
into consideration people both the Commissioners and lawyers<br />
and so forth who might have, I think, been able to help overcome<br />
some of the problems in the Bill,<br />
Question: Why do you think there has been that element of secrecy<br />
about it?<br />
Senator Missen: To stop an enormous campaign developing before the<br />
thing is even in the Parliament, and probably making it more difficult<br />
to discuss it in any impartial sort of way. That might be the reason.<br />
Question: Even apart from your very strong Views you decided not<br />
to cross the floor. Why is that?<br />
Senator Missen: Well, I have not announced this to the Party. I made<br />
no intention known that I would, and I think I have pointed out the<br />
dubious -' constit: utional position. It may be that the Bill will<br />
be read down by the High Court, and it won't be so objectionable,<br />
but I saw no reason myself to make some sort: of grand gesture by<br />
what you call ' crossing the floor' that would have had no affect<br />
on the Bill. / 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
A few weeks ago, the EEC's executive commission was the subject<br />
of a critical auditor's report over the amount of money its<br />
13 members spent on expenses, air travel, drinks, flowers and<br />
so on, so the last thing the commission president, Roy Jenkins<br />
needed was the most. recent scandal involving the Dutch commissioner<br />
whose peccadilloes led to the replacement of a $ 10,000 plate glass<br />
in an exclusive hotel, broken by during a heated political debate. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
