<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7540</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN JOST, RADIO 3UZ MELBURNE - 22 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007540.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF RADIO INTERVIEW WITH JOHN JOST, RADIO 3uz<br />
MELBOURNE -22 MARCH 1989<br />
Z6 0 9 PROOF ON4LY<br />
JOST: And it is welcome to the Prime Minister of Australia,<br />
Bob Hawke. Thanks for joining us.<br />
PM: Pleasure John as always.<br />
JOST: Well Prime Minister you have been making a big media<br />
splash lately.<br />
PM: Well, there seems to have been a bit of coverage, yes<br />
John. JOST: Big coverage. I want to ask you, why did you talk so<br />
frankly about your marriage to Clive Robertson?<br />
PM: Well there was nothing planned about it. As you know,<br />
I always say to any interviewer beforehand I don't want to<br />
know what the questions are. That's what I said to him. I<br />
had no idea what the questions were, and I believe in<br />
tellini the truth. Questions were asked, there was no point<br />
in avoiding them.<br />
JOST.-I suppose you have to say this about Australia. it<br />
is probably the only country, the only Western democracy in<br />
the world where you could speak so frankly, and make such<br />
admissions. FM: Well I don't know whether that is so John. But I think<br />
I know Australia and Australians better than any one just<br />
about. I don't want to, even now on this program# I don't<br />
want to go on talking about-<br />
JOST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I'm just making the point if you'll excuse me. I don't<br />
want to go on and on about essentially private matters, I<br />
did want to take the opportunity really at that time of<br />
paying a tribute to my wife. And I did that. But I had no<br />
feeling that it would be offensive, or that Australians<br />
wouldn't expect me, if asked, as I was, to talk about these<br />
matters. I did. it was nothing more complex than that. </p>
<p>2.<br />
JOST: well it was a personal interview and i ather it was<br />
put to you on that basis. But it does obviously it does<br />
impact into the political arena because I know that the<br />
Government's got some concerns, for instance, about the vote<br />
of women, the level of support from women voters. And I<br />
was wondering what you think, because you probably know the<br />
electorate better than I do, how that interview last night<br />
would impact say on women.<br />
PM: I've got no idea. I don't think we should think of<br />
women as essentially different as human beings, as voters,<br />
than men. There are some issues which areo particular<br />
interest to women, and I acknowledge that and I think in<br />
that area of issues of particular concern to women like<br />
education and -child care and so on, we've got a particularly<br />
good record. But on this issue of the reaction of women to<br />
what I may say in these areas, I think generally they will<br />
have the same reaction as men. I haven't thought about it.<br />
JOST: Why do you think the standing of the Government is a<br />
little bit lower with women than it is with men?<br />
PM: I don't know. It may be that women traditionally are a<br />
little bit more conservative than men. There-is the<br />
suggestion that is the case john. Obviously to some extent<br />
we have to accept some blame in communication in those areas<br />
that I've mentioned. By example, points that are of a<br />
particular interest to women, we haven't communicated our<br />
successes there, I think, as we should have. I don't haveI<br />
any feeling of agro about this. I just think that we have a<br />
good story to tell to the electorate generally, and in a<br />
sense, to women in particular and we've just got to<br />
communicate that story better.<br />
JOST: well maybe you make the point though, that men and<br />
women do have similar, these days, certainly have similar<br />
aspirations, perhaps react similarily. But, as I was<br />
thinking that perhaps the problem with the female vote it<br />
that women do have control, I think, of most expenditure in<br />
households and they, when they go down to the supermarket,<br />
are perhaps aware that there is not as much money now as<br />
there was a few years ago to spend and they feel that<br />
PHt well that's not right. Lets got the facts right.<br />
That simply ion't right. There has been in real terms a<br />
five per cent increase in average real per capita income.<br />
And that's because while there hasn't been a real reduction<br />
in real wages, there has been an enormous increase in<br />
employment. So more people in households are employed.<br />
we've increased jobs, as you know, four times faster than<br />
the previous government. We are increasing them more than<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the world. So there are more<br />
people in jobs and we have increased the level of benefits<br />
in real terms. So it is simply not right of you to say that<br />
there is less money. in average real per capita terms a<br />
five per cent increase since we've been in office. I 1VW I WW X C7 % 7 1CP r-qV= </p>
<p>W -o W I-.<br />
3.<br />
JOST: What about the suggestion that over the last five or<br />
six years there has actually been a sort of reduction in our<br />
overall living standards though?<br />
PM: if you take an employedtperson at the beginning and an<br />
employed person at the end, thre has been a reduction<br />
because there has been a reduction in real wages. I'm<br />
simply saying if you take average per capita in a household<br />
income, then there has been a five-per cent increase, anid<br />
that is simply because there are more people in households<br />
in employment. The benefits for people at the lower level<br />
of income, and particularly what we gave done in regard to<br />
sole parents and where you've got kids living in low income<br />
areas, all we've put in there, for instance, has meant that<br />
taking the combination of the increase in jobs and the<br />
increase in benefits that there has been this increase in<br />
income. Now that doesn't mean, and I don't avoid the fact<br />
that for some people who have been continously in<br />
employment, there has been a reduction in standards. The<br />
interesting thing about our opponents on this has been that<br />
they have been trumpeting around the country that there has<br />
been a reduction in standards, and they put fancy figures on<br />
it $ 50 a week. And yet you pick up this document that he<br />
wants to live by, but which he'll die by, this Future<br />
Directions, and you go to the very heart of that document<br />
and they attack us for protecting the standards of people.<br />
They say that there has been a loss of national income<br />
because of the decline in the terms of trade, national<br />
income's gone down but this awful Labor Government has<br />
protected the standards of the people in the community.<br />
They can't have it both ways.<br />
JOST: well of course that is somthing you've got to Bell<br />
very hard to people isn't it. The fact that, and I would<br />
imagine the economists would agree with this statement, that<br />
if the Liberals came in they may well be much harsher with<br />
the electorate on the economic front than your Government.<br />
PM: Well that's one of the horns of many of the dilemmas on<br />
which they are stuck. Because they are saying, with<br />
different voices, but they are saying that they will cut<br />
expenditures more than we-have. But, you notice John that<br />
they are reluctant in the extreme to the point of total<br />
refusal at this stage to say where they will cut. They will*<br />
not be able to go up to an election and that's quite a<br />
long way off the election but they will not be able to go<br />
into the election simply saying we'll cut more, without<br />
saying where.<br />
JOST: Well Prime Minister, still using Clive Robertson~' s<br />
interview with you last night as a counter point. You<br />
mentioned....... a life after politics, doing interviews,<br />
a particular of interviews with international figures.<br />
PM: Not just international, with some Australian people<br />
too.<br />
_ r </p>
<p>4.<br />
JOST: Of course. That wasn't the question I was 9oing to<br />
ask. I was going to say what impact personally electoral<br />
loss, electoral defeat would have on you.<br />
PM1 On?<br />
JOST: On you?<br />
PM: Well I don't accept that there is going to be electoral<br />
defeat. I mean, that's such a hypothetical question I don't<br />
face that.<br />
JOST: I think that there's a chance that you could. I<br />
think that this election is going to be the hardest election<br />
you've fought.. I think that you're the life of the<br />
Government, you've been there for six years, with interest<br />
rates, inflation, maybe there's a little bit of hope is<br />
abating down there among the people and<br />
-7 WW-= 9 IWW 0 W-V Cr -Iwz W </p>
<p>PM.-I don't believe that's true, I think hope is rising, it's entitled to.<br />
In Api, the Treasurer, Paul-will be announicing the significant tax cuts which we<br />
targeted, as they should be ,_ or electoral reasons, because of the restraint.<br />
that's been exearcised, they'll be targetted towards those people in the cannunity<br />
' who noed and deserve assistance. So, I think that we're going through a tough<br />
period at the mm~ ent for sane of the reasons you're talking about, but I have no<br />
sense of pessiniu. i<br />
JOST: Well when you were advised last year about tbe paramsters for this year' s<br />
budget, Treasury obviously got it wrong and caused -the Government to get it wrong<br />
Oni thG qwsntion of how strongly the Government was going to grow.<br />
PM: Not jusL Treasury, I mean, economi~ cs as we know, it's true to say that it.' s<br />
not an exact science, you've got to makB the best assessments that you.-can, it's<br />
a very caiplex profesiion because you've not only got to make judgements. about your~<br />
own internal operations of the Australian economy~, but very much also you've got to<br />
try and got it right about the level of international activity, and that iapinges<br />
upon the prices that you receive for your eqports., There' s a cau~ lex. interaction<br />
of decisions by individuals and groups here and all over the world which are going<br />
to, in the end, say what happens. Now, it in true that there was an underestimate<br />
of the level of activity and what we've done sinply, John,. is what ' we've done<br />
through six years. When ' we are confronted with a given . set of economic circmtnatnces<br />
f tich require action, albeit tough action, we take it. As I keep saying, and I want<br />
~ o inpress upon your listeners and I know they're intelligent ad will uzzderutand<br />
it, they will know thaL Bob Hawke wouldn't want to have interest rates for one day<br />
higher than is necessary. I mean, I'Im no I dot I know people don ' t liJ~ e high<br />
interest rates. And they are there, high, now, trying to bring back activity because<br />
that is in the betst inter~ sts of this country, which I ' m about trying to do the best<br />
for. It would be against the interests of Australia and Australians to allow this<br />
level of activity to continue, because we can't sustain a level_ of iffpoits which<br />
goes with that level of activity. OK? You've got to do the tough thing and the tough<br />
thing is high interest rates. I don't like doing it but it's the right thing,<br />
and I will not refrain fromn taking what is the right action in the interests of this<br />
country. Just as last night, I mean I was up tiLl.-I got to bed about half past two<br />
this mo~ rning because we had this long, long, long Cabinet session where we finally<br />
had to make a decision about the extra airpor~ t capacity in Sydney. Now the easy,<br />
political decision John, would've been to say, no extension at Kingsford-StiaLh,<br />
77. </p>
<p>-W L-W<br />
6<br />
because we've gut seats around. there which I frankly acknowledge will be put at. sos<br />
risk because of the position we've taken. But I changed my view. I originally<br />
thought when I started to became INMDIBLE this, that the econncmics of it,<br />
as well as aviation principles, would suggest you go straight out to Badgory's.<br />
The mrIm I looked at it, the more I got... with . infonmation in response. to questions<br />
I asked... the more it was clear that the right decision for this country, for Sydney,<br />
for the aviation industry, for tourinm, the more it becme clear that the right<br />
decision was a tough political one, We took it.<br />
JOST Where does it leave Gary Punch, your Aviation Minister Ais basically standing<br />
four-square against the decision Cabinet took. last night..<br />
PM: I've got to honestly say that iL's created difficulties for Gaxy. But<br />
rre. say this, in respect of him. No person could've more strongly, outside<br />
Cabinet argued his case. And I say, in tribute to him, that he argued his<br />
strongly, and franom his perspective, very effectively in the Cabinet. let and inside tt<br />
case<br />
JOST: Are you going to leave him in the position?<br />
PM: Well I've had a discussion with him and I said well look you just think about<br />
it Gary, it's up to you to cane back to me and give nm your thoughts.... as the first<br />
step in my thinking... I want you to think about it. In a very mature way ho had.<br />
that discussion with me this morning, early, and he'll come back to me and give<br />
me his thoughts and in the light of his thoughts I'll make a decision.<br />
7 </p>
<p>JOST: Well obviously he has a position for himself, but<br />
clearly you'd have a position for the Government. And if<br />
you've got a bloke who has opposed it, it would be a lot<br />
easier-and make a lot of sense, would it not, to put him<br />
into another portfolio. And it might give you the<br />
opportunity to shuffle a few people around as well?<br />
PM: well, prima facie there is a case of obviously if he<br />
were to say that well he doesn't think that comfortably he<br />
could do it, if that was his view, well I would have to take<br />
that into account, and I would. But you talk about creating<br />
the opportunity for some extensive reshuffle. There is no<br />
extensive reshuffle required. If you look now at the end of<br />
six years in office with this Government and compare it with<br />
the six years ' of my predecessors, this has been a remarkably<br />
stable Government, it is regarded as one of outstanding<br />
calibre. You have the situation where the senior figure on<br />
the Opposition* Howson, the Shadow minister for Finance,<br />
spoke of it properly as, you know the outstanding Ministry<br />
since the war. It is. But if a slight change is judged<br />
desirable in the circumstances to which you refer, it will<br />
be made.<br />
JOST: It just seems that there are a couple of queries<br />
about the Ministry. And I certainlywudarewtio<br />
that it has been a very stable ongoing administration. But<br />
people get tired. We've got Senator Peter Walsh sort of<br />
saying, feeling enervated I guess and feeling that he might<br />
like to get out.<br />
Pm: well let me pick that up quickly. Again I didn't try<br />
and dodge this issue. I acknowledged quite freely that<br />
Peter had come to see me and he said he was tired. And he<br />
was. He's got, in many senses, one of the worst jobs in the<br />
ministry. JOST: Oh, he's got to be a bastard all the time.<br />
PM: That's right. It's not a word I'd normally use on air,<br />
but that's--a-fair description. He's Mr No so often to<br />
proposals which intrinsicall are worthwhile, but taking the<br />
overall view just can't be dlforded, or have to be cut back.<br />
And Peter is not an ogre. I mean Peter is a very, very<br />
decent committed bloke whose concern with the wel1fare of<br />
ordinary Australians<br />
JOST: maybe you'd like another track to run around?<br />
PM: well, I don't think so. it's just that it's very, very<br />
intellectually and psychologically enervating to be having<br />
to be Mr No, Mr tough guy. And he's honest enough to say<br />
that he's psychically a bit run down with it and of course<br />
it's added to by the fact that he's West Australian and that<br />
adds a bit more pressure. But the important thing is this.<br />
We talked about it maturely and Peter is so committed to<br />
this Government, and what it's about, he said yes, I will<br />
stay. </p>
<p>pP WN p Tq I-MP<br />
a.<br />
JOST: Wesley Vale. I mean that seemed to me to be, and<br />
I've got to be honest with you, just starting from the<br />
ground floor up, they put it in the wrong place, both sides<br />
indulged in misinformation it's very hard for observers<br />
like me to know who was telling the truth and I'm talking<br />
about how dirty it was going to be. it's a fantastic<br />
proposal and proposition for Australia economically<br />
speaking. But we had the Tasmanian government going in one<br />
direction, half your Government going I mean obviously you<br />
people wanted to do it. You had the conservation movement<br />
against it and you had Graham Richardson in the end arguing<br />
against it with a lot of scientific support from CSIRO. A<br />
terrible shambles really.<br />
PM: well in one sense a shambles, but not as far as my<br />
Government was concerned and you can't put a position of a<br />
split in my Cabinet. I mean all of us<br />
JOST: I'm not say it was a split. You've got to have<br />
arguments obviously.<br />
FM: Yes. Discussions. But there wasn't one person in the<br />
Cabinet, Graham Richarson Included who, in principle, was<br />
against the idea of a mill, because what we need as far as<br />
we can is to have value added processes to our raw material.<br />
And that is good in terms of our balance of payments<br />
considerations, employment considerations. But, let me make<br />
it quite clear to your listeners, I've said it before and<br />
its important that it be said again. while I'm Prime<br />
minister, while this Labor Government is in power we will<br />
pursue development, but not development at any price, and<br />
the price was too high. We made it clear that they just<br />
couldn't assume that they could get away with no<br />
environmental impact statements, which is essentially what<br />
they tried to do and we expected that they would have higher<br />
standards. Then they put to us, well a proposal which<br />
wasn't acceptable and we weren't going to have thirteen<br />
tonnes of these chlorides going into the ocean every day.<br />
-V W-= </p>
<p>9,<br />
tape break<br />
Pm: Yes we will be doing that but there can be no<br />
suggestion that the joint venturers were booby trapped.<br />
JOST: They tried to booby trap you..<br />
PM: I don't want to be nasty about them and I don't intend<br />
to be but it's quite clear they thought they'd be able to<br />
steamroll the Tasmanian Government and it's not too<br />
difficult to do that and they did it. They seemed to think<br />
that we were so desperate for the mill and foreign exchange<br />
and so on that we would just cop anything. Now, they had no<br />
reason to believe that. The a~ reement between us and<br />
Tasmania was that Tasmania would handle, they had to make<br />
their decisions and then once they had done that it would<br />
come to us. That was understood all the way along. But<br />
through that it's quite clear that we had strong views about<br />
standards and in the end they conceded that it wasn't what<br />
they were proposing, weren't the highest standards at all.<br />
They certainly weren't. I'm not going to cop a situation<br />
where there is danger to the environment which means that<br />
we'll hand onto future generations an Australia which has<br />
been unnecessarily damaged. When we had, as we did then,<br />
the report from the Cs IRO, then no responsible government in<br />
receipt of that advice could have gone ahead. The mark of<br />
the difference between me and my Government and Howard and<br />
the opposition and I hope all Australians understand this.<br />
What did Howard say? It doesn't matter a damn about the<br />
CSIRO. He said, we would've gone ahead. well that's the<br />
difference and that's the difference going up to the next<br />
election. Development at any rice, whatever the best<br />
independent scientific advice isof hurt to this<br />
environment, damage to future generations, the oppositiongo<br />
ahead. well if that's what Australians want then they've<br />
got that choice.<br />
JOST: There's one question that alluded me, we changed the<br />
subject. I was going to ask you, we're looking at an<br />
inflation rate I think at the moment of . about-7-8%, the<br />
Budget parameters were for about we're looking at<br />
interest rates at about 16, I'm not sure what the Budget<br />
parameter was for that. There is some talk about interest<br />
rates slipping up a bit higher, there seems to me a bit of<br />
inflationary pressure building up in the United States.<br />
Could you put a figure on wha? you think the inflatior rate<br />
will be by the end of this year and what you think the<br />
interest rate will be?<br />
PM: No, when the Treasurer brings down the Budget in August<br />
then, as is usual, as part of that process there will be<br />
figures contained in the associated papers which will set<br />
out the assumptions as to the inflation expectations. MM WW WW cr R7 CV-P </p>
<p>C 19 CL. CO'S fin<br />
JOST: Can you see moderation?<br />
PM: Yes I can, there will be moderation in inflation in my judgment.<br />
JOST, And interest rates?<br />
PM: Well I've said at the beginning of this year, when I was asked a very sinple and<br />
perhaps not very sophisticated question, I was asked in January would interest<br />
rates fall by the end of . the year and I said yes, I believe they would. Now that's<br />
not a prediction in regard to the inmediate fuLure. This is March we're talking,<br />
we're still in March and my judgrent is, as it was in January, that before the end<br />
f the year they'll fall, but I am not going to do a disservice to the markets and<br />
4ore importantly to the people of this country by sitting here in your . studio<br />
or anywhere else and saying tamorrow or the next week this is what interest rates<br />
will be. That would be counter-productive and I don't intend to do it. I'm sinply<br />
saying that in terms of how I see the fundamentals moving through this year, that<br />
before the end of this year interest rates will be moving down.<br />
JOST: A lot of people hope you're right.<br />
PM: And I hope I'm right. I mean I repeat the point I made before John, just let<br />
me talk directly to your listeners. There's no-one that'd be happier than Bob<br />
Hawke if 1 believe that the best thing for Australia now would be to bring interest<br />
rates dowm. Bang, it'd be done, because I know it'd be nice and politically it'd be<br />
-a ut, but it would be economically wrong and I'm not going to do the econanically<br />
wrong thing.<br />
JUS T Well, as you pointed out it's March and next month it's April and we've got<br />
an econan c statement comning next April and there are going to be tax cuts in that.<br />
I was wondering if there are going to be any micro-econnmic measures in it as well.<br />
PM. Not necessarily right in the April Statement. as we have been continuously on<br />
micro-econanic reforms, very inportant areas like the waterfront and the Maritire<br />
industry. We will, not necessarily in the April Statement, but in the period<br />
in the near future after that be making a series of statements and announcing<br />
decisions in inportant areas affecting the micro-econcmy.<br />
JOST: Well, one I suppose is the transport industry) another one and closely related<br />
is the waterfront, as you mentioned. Well, tle problem there, what is it? Is it<br />
the unions? mw. W% W 9W 3. C7 10 C P a 0u </p>
<p>s~ S WW S C ~ C I-S 3.<br />
11<br />
PM. It's a mixture of attitudes of unions and employers and let me say just how longentrenched<br />
this has been. I just ask you to remember this. If you look, we'r now<br />
in 1989. We go back to 1949, forty years. Of that forty years, John, thirty-one of..<br />
them, conservative governrents. So if you've got entrenched attitudes and positions<br />
in Australia, you talk about now, it's as I say, thirty-one of those forty years<br />
conservative governments. We have done more in this six years than in the whole of V<br />
previous period carombined, to tackle problems of the micro-econamy. Just lot ine<br />
quickly remind you and your listeners of the sort of things we've done... of<br />
deregulating the financial market, bringing in the banks, the massive tariff reforms,<br />
ending of the two airline policy, making competitive your Goverrment business<br />
enterprises so that they are subject to competition and that they've got to operate<br />
on camrercial lines, now tackling this area of the waterfront and Maritime industry.<br />
SNow over all that period that I've been talking about, unions and employers in those<br />
two industries have adopted attitudes and practices which have been . o their<br />
mutual advantage, but which not in all circumstances have necessarily been to the<br />
advantage to this country. Some of their arrangemnts... I'mn not trying to set them<br />
up as an evil conglomerate of always acting against the interests of the country,<br />
somae of the things that they have done together have been to the advantage of the<br />
country, not all of them. And it's only this Governmant which is now really<br />
effectively; tackling those issues. And I can say this. That during this year, during<br />
this year there will be significant changes on the waterfront and in the Maritire<br />
industry brought about as a result of our activities.<br />
JOST: I think a lot of people reckon it's overdue, a lot of people felt that maybe<br />
the Government's been a bit slow to move on the waterfront.<br />
PM: Well, at least we are moving and we' ll get results. For thirty-one years under<br />
that nmob it got worse and worse.<br />
JOST Election timing. We've heard Mr Howard suggest July.<br />
PM: Who takes any noLice of Mr-IvwqcrA.<br />
JOST, Oh well, lots of people take a lot of notice of himn. I mean you know that.<br />
You said he was assiduous and hard-vworking end loyal last night.<br />
PM: Yes, yes I did. </p>
<p>12<br />
JOST: Anyway, leaving aside that because I ' m being frivolous but the point is that<br />
he's certainly talking election in July. I suppose the favourable option<br />
fraom my point of view, judging your position would be Noveber, Deoeirer or<br />
February.<br />
PM: I don't really want to go on and on about this. No, I'm not objecting to thequestion<br />
John. I'm sinply saying that what I've said is that the real eriool<br />
that one would talk about, whether it was this Government or any uLber, the sort of<br />
period you'd be talking about would be the end of this year up until the middle<br />
of next year. Now that's the... I've got no reason to change that. That's the<br />
sort of picture. I'm not planning for an election this year, I'm not planning for<br />
an election this year. It may be though, in terms of what I've said that towards<br />
0the end of this year, that's a reasonable tine to be thinking about your timn-spaon<br />
for an election. But I haven't got in my mind that ' 89 is an election year.<br />
I'm not thinking of ' 89 as an election year.<br />
JOST: It makes sense of course to go next year, after your budget's care in. There<br />
are going to be social welfare rreasures there... you've hiad your tax cuts earlier<br />
in the year, they' ll bite. Presumably interest rates will be dropping.. I mean if the<br />
theory's in place you'll be well-placed to go in February. Or, as you say, between<br />
now and February and whenever you liks.<br />
PM: I think the contrast is going to be there between the Governmsnt that has the<br />
guts to make the tough decisions and do things which has got policies and a pretty<br />
stark alternative and that will be there in the whole of the period that I'm talking<br />
about. </p>
<p>JOST: if you're re-elected you are looking at ta ton<br />
year term as Prime Minister and as we said, we've had<br />
this situation of a stable administration with consistent<br />
performances by your Ministers, but obviously you're going<br />
to have do a lot of rebuilding in your last term in Government<br />
aren't you? You will probably be looking at departing at<br />
same stage. *. pin you down on that but it's a fact of<br />
life and other people, very important people like Johnny<br />
Button, and we could go on-<br />
PM: Let me just make the point. That's a fair obsorvation<br />
that you're going to. In terms of stability of people in<br />
important positions, we've now been in six years so that<br />
gives you an opportunity of a pretty fair comparison with<br />
the seven years of the other mob. There's been an infinitely<br />
greater stability in the tenure and the performance of senior<br />
Ministers in my Government than not only in that previous<br />
government but just about in any other. It is a fact of<br />
life that people after six years or more are going to say<br />
some of them are going to say well, ok I've made my<br />
contribution, it's time to move either to another portfolio<br />
or to move on. I'm in the very fortunate position, the<br />
Party is, the Government, is, and the people of this country<br />
are, that on my backbench I've got a range of people of<br />
very considerable talent. The contrast between the Government<br />
and the Opposition is Just remarkable. I have senior Liberal<br />
People saying to me that they wouldn't give people on the<br />
other side a job in their enterprises. And they contrast<br />
that with the Government side. There's an enormous amount<br />
of talent there. So when as we get into that next stage<br />
some people want to have a rest, I'm in the fortunate position<br />
of having a great pool of talent from which I can..<br />
JOST: You've got Simon Crean coming through too. What<br />
sort of PM do you think he'll make?<br />
PM: I've said, as has Paul, that it's going to be good<br />
having Simon there as a person upon whom at some stage they<br />
will be able to look and perhaps call for leadership. The<br />
front runner without any question is Paul Keating.<br />
JOST: Do you think after Simon Creani leaves the union movement<br />
that he'll be easily replaced?<br />
PM: The ACTU has been able to replace poople with talent<br />
over time.<br />
JOST: It seems to me though that every time they stick<br />
a NSW bloke in there he's there for a little while and then<br />
he's replaced by a Victorian. Cliff Dolan lasted about<br />
4 minutes and we've got this new bloke Ferguson, is it. </p>
<p>14<br />
PM: Yes, but a very significant difference in age. Cliff<br />
came to the Presidency of the ACTU obviously at the latter<br />
stages of his career in the trade union movement. He took<br />
it, and it was understood that he took it in terms that<br />
he wasn't going to be there for very long. With Martin,<br />
he's a much youngor guy.<br />
JOST: Could I ask you a personal question?<br />
PM: Just for a change.<br />
JOST; How's Hazel?<br />
PM: She is beaUt. stie's just something special.<br />
JOST: I'd have to say I reckon you needed a facelift more<br />
than she did.<br />
PM: I can't tell whether you do, you've got it covered<br />
with all that fuzz. But from what I can see you wouldn't<br />
go so badly with one yourself mate.<br />
JOST: I think if I could have the fuzz sort of pushed up<br />
a bit it could fill that big gap between the ears. It'd<br />
be very nice. I've got no obJection to people having<br />
I actually thought all the discussion was in rather bad<br />
taste actually.<br />
PM: Well the simple fact is I thought she looked beaut<br />
as she was but she is her person.<br />
JOST: As a matter of fact a good friend of mine was in<br />
hospital with her, I knew all about it.<br />
PM: I thought you might have. If Hazel wanted to do it<br />
then that's the beginning and the end of it as far as I'm<br />
concerned. I simply would like also to take this opportunity<br />
of saying what I said on the Bert Newton show the other<br />
day, to slam that bloody Sunday Press rag here for the totally<br />
untrue and I won't use the word I was going to use bastardry<br />
that they went in with on Sunday that she had done it under<br />
pressure from the Party. Totally, absolutely maliciously<br />
untrue. JOST: Prime Minister, I think on that note I'll let you<br />
have the last word.<br />
PM!ñ Thanks mate.<br />
JOST: Thanks very much for Joining us.<br />
PM: it's a pleasure as always John.<br />
JOST: We'll see you again no doubt.<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
