<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15444</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Media Statement with the Premier of New South Wales, the Hon Morris Iemma MP APEC Preparations</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/07/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>In eight weeks time, Sydney will host the most significant gathering of world leaders ever hosted in Australia: the APEC Economic Leaders Meeting. APEC 2007 will bring together the leaders of economies that account for over half the world's GDP, almost 70 per cent of Australia's total international trade and nine of the top 10 NSW merchandise export markets.  </p>
<p>The focus of the APEC Economic Leaders Meeting will be on economic development, trade, regional security, job creation and climate change.</p>
<p>Today the Prime Minister, the Hon John Howard MP, and the Premier of NSW,   the Hon Morris Iemma MP met to review APEC planning. The two leaders reaffirmed their commitment to the close consultation and detailed preparation that has been occurring between Commonwealth and NSW agencies since 2004 to ensure APEC is a success.</p>
<p>Sydney will not be locked down during APEC, although there will be disruption to the city, particularly in the northern part of the CBD. </p>
<p>Detailed plans are in place to ensure the security of Sydney residents and the visiting delegations.</p>
<p>During APEC, the Sydney Harbour Bridge, Cahill Expressway, Harbour Tunnel, Western Distributor and Eastern Distributor will remain open. It will be possible to catch ferries to and from Circular Quay and walk through the city centre. During APEC it will also be possible to visit, shop or dine at East Circular Quay, Darling Harbour or in The Rocks.</p>
<p>The security overlay for APEC will increase gradually from 2 September when preparatory meetings of senior officials commence at the Sydney Convention and Exhibition Centre at Darling Harbour. </p>
<p>As previously announced, Friday 7 September will be a public holiday in the Sydney metropolitan area. Security operations will be at their most significant over the long weekend from Friday 7  to Sunday 9 September when international leaders are arriving and gathered for their meetings. </p>
<p>Motorists should expect delays, especially around the airport and between the airport and the city on 7 and 9 September, and are encouraged to avoid driving into the city if possible.</p>
<p>The NSW Government, endorsed by the APEC Taskforce, has legislated that areas of the Sydney CBD, Hickson Road, Darling Harbour and parts of the Harbour off Circular Quay are </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
