<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8031</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 12 JUNE 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/06/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008031.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 12 JUNE<br />
1990 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what do you think of Mr<br />
Maxwell's attempt to buy into The West Australian?<br />
PM: Don't think it will be successful.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why not?<br />
PM: Because it we've given an indication quite<br />
clearly in the past of our attitude on these matters.<br />
I'll obviously want to have a yarn with Paul about it,<br />
but we've been at one on our thinking on this issue.<br />
We've reflected it in regard to The Age previously and I<br />
wouldn't see that there'd be any reason to change that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the question of the<br />
Cambodians in the Northern Territory, the Roman Catholic<br />
church there is making representations to the Government<br />
suggesting on the grounds of legality, practicality and<br />
humanity they ought to be able to stay. What sort of<br />
response can you<br />
PM: Well, as I've made clear from the very beginning,<br />
those processes that deal with these matters are under<br />
way. That is the DORS, the Determination of Refugee<br />
Status, they are being followed through in respect of<br />
these people and it's right, as it should be, and I made<br />
it quite clear at all times that that is the case. What<br />
I am concerned to establish for everyone to understand,<br />
and let there be no doubt about this, that Australia is<br />
not going to have some completely open door where people<br />
can expect they make up their mind that they will<br />
determine Australia's immigration policy simply by coming<br />
here. That's not the way it's going to happen under this<br />
Government. No government, I believe, in the world has<br />
got a better record of compassion and constructive<br />
concern for refugees than has my Government. We've taken<br />
on a per capita basis, and I extend credit to our<br />
predecessor Government on this as well, on a per capita<br />
basis, we've taken more refugees than any other country<br />
in the world. Particularly that's true in regard to<br />
refugees from Indo China and under my leadership we'll<br />
continue to show compassion, but compassion<br />
constructive and orderly compassion is not the same </p>
<p>2<br />
thing as saying here is an open door for anyone who wants<br />
to come. This is, the compassion is concerned with<br />
genuine refugees, there are others who've made their mind<br />
up that they don't particularly like the environment in<br />
which they live for economic reasons and are prepared to<br />
pay, as seems to be the case, a reasonable amount of<br />
money to people who are organising these departures. Now<br />
I'm simply making it clear, I believe, on behalf not only<br />
of the Government but of the people of Australia, that we<br />
are a sovereign independent nation which will determine<br />
its immigration policy and the categories of its<br />
immigration policy autonomously. We will not have these<br />
things taken out of our hands. Now for those that have<br />
arrived then, of course, the processes of the<br />
Determination of Refugee Status will go ahead, but I'm<br />
making it quite clear what the attitude of the Government<br />
is to this, to this situation people thinking they can<br />
just pay whatever they like, take whatever risk they like<br />
and come here and think that they are just going to<br />
automatically be accepted in this country. That's not<br />
the way it's going to work.<br />
JOURNALIST: process working for these people<br />
returning to Cambodia?<br />
PM: Well, of course, this is precisely what we've got<br />
people in Cambodia now. We've got, as you know, a group<br />
of people there who are talking with the Government of<br />
Cambodia precisely about that, Geoff. I mean, we, as I<br />
say, are in a very strong position in conducting these<br />
discussions because of the reputation, the factual<br />
reputation, that we have for compassion in regard to<br />
genuine refugees. So we speak from a position of<br />
strength. But we will want to be having discussions with<br />
the Cambodian authorities to ensure that as much is done<br />
as is possible to prevent the departure of these people<br />
on the expectation that they are going to be able just be<br />
given unqualified entry into this country.<br />
JOURNALIST: How many boat people have been returned in<br />
the past from Australia to various countries?<br />
PM: I don't know the answer to that question, but what<br />
I'Im concerned about is that we have now, over a period of<br />
time, something like 200 odd of these people from<br />
Cambodia have arrived in what essentially appear to be,<br />
as I understand it, about three different boat loads.<br />
Now it's quite necessary from a point of view of this<br />
country that the Prime Minister and the Government make<br />
it quite clear that there's not going to be some passive<br />
position as far as this country is concerned on this<br />
issue. JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what is Australia's<br />
assessment of the return of Po1 Pot? I mean, this is a<br />
fear that some of these, people have expressed. How does<br />
our Government view that as a </p>
<p>PM: No, our policy has been very, very clear on this and<br />
we are at one with virtually all the countries of the<br />
region and around the world, who have been involved in<br />
the processes of trying to find a resolution to this<br />
continuing tragedy of Cambodia. There has been the view<br />
taken that the Khmer Rouge is a part of the realities on<br />
the ground, if you could put it that way, in Cambodia and<br />
all countries, including for instance the United States,<br />
have recognised that there has been a, a part for those<br />
people to play in the processes of discussion. And<br />
indeed, in the Australian plan that we have over recent<br />
months advanced, we have had discussions as you know,<br />
as a matter of public record had discussions with<br />
representatives of the Khmer Rouge as well, but we are at<br />
one with other nations in ensuring that out of these<br />
processes that are being followed and the various<br />
strands that are being followed, that there be no<br />
situation in which the Khmer Rouge is allowed to take<br />
over Cambodia again. There's been very considerable<br />
advance in the last 12 months or more in the activities<br />
of various groups and individual nations to try and get a<br />
resolution of the situation in Cambodia and it would be<br />
true to say that we are further advanced now than we were<br />
a couple of years ago. There are still sticking points,<br />
but there is a commonality of position that whatever, in<br />
the end, is adopted has got to be one which ensures that<br />
there will be the opportunity for the free expression of<br />
the will of the Cambodian people. And we are all<br />
confident, those who know anything about the situation,<br />
have had anything to do with it, that in those<br />
circumstances where the people of Cambodia are provided<br />
with the opportunity of expressing their wishes, then the<br />
Khmer Rouge will not be in a position where they'll be<br />
able to exercise power in that unfortunate country.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you happy with the way<br />
the short term English language courses in Australia were<br />
monitored as they developed? And what do you make of the<br />
fact that a high percentage of the Chinese students, by<br />
the time of the massacre of Beijing, had overstayed their<br />
visas? You talk of queue jumping in the context of the<br />
Cambodians, isn't that another form of it?<br />
PM: Well, this is not something new. We've recognised<br />
that, that there were unfortunate features about that and<br />
that, of course, has been reflected in decisions that the<br />
Government has taken to tighten up these matters and<br />
particularly it involved the Chinese and you know the<br />
reactions that there were in China about the tightening<br />
up that we've undertaken. We recognise, as I say, that<br />
there were problems in that and the decisions that we've<br />
taken are directed towards trying to ensure that we don't<br />
get a repetition of that in the future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why is it that the DORS Committee process,<br />
or a process like that, couldn't have been applied to<br />
those students. Was it simply that it was too big a<br />
task? </p>
<p>PM: Well, you've got, you've got some 20,000 Chinese<br />
here who come into that pre-Tienanmen Square category.<br />
Now the decision that will be taken, I believe, by the<br />
Government which I've indicated will make the distinction<br />
between the period of approximately the 20th of June,<br />
before and after. Now in regard to the period before,<br />
with some 20,000 people there, it, quite apart from the,<br />
the humanitarian consideration which has led us to the<br />
position that I have annunciated, you would also have in<br />
that. situation, mechanical problems of dealing with such<br />
a very large number. I understand that the rate of<br />
processing through the DORS Committee is of the order of<br />
about 40 a month, so you have a, a mechanical problem<br />
there. Of course, in regard to the post-Tienanmen Square<br />
group, I have made it quite clear that the assumption<br />
there, the assumption there will be that those people<br />
will return to China.<br />
JOURNALIST: But is it not the case that some of those<br />
people would be<br />
PM: And I, and I, look, I don't quite understand why<br />
it's difficult for people to hear, listen and understand<br />
what I've said on this. I've said now on three separate<br />
occasions, that in respect of the post-Tienanmen Square<br />
people, as indeed for anyone in this country, whether<br />
they are post-Tienanmen Square Chinese or others, the<br />
DORS processes are available and they will be available<br />
to those people. I've said that three times.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the Department of<br />
Immigration says that there are at least 60,000 illegal<br />
overstayers in Australia. We're also told concerned<br />
that they didn't have sufficient resources to tackle this<br />
problem. Do you think that they need more resources?<br />
PM: Well, that's, that's undoubtedly a question which<br />
the, which the Minister will be putting before us in the<br />
Cabinet. That's a matter which will have to be decided,<br />
considered and decided.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have we had any indication from<br />
the Cambodian Government whether they're prepared to take<br />
these boat people back?<br />
PM: Well, what I've seen so far and I haven't had the<br />
opportunity of talking, obviously, with the Foreign<br />
Minister yet, that's something I'll do as soon as it is<br />
possible. But I've seen the public observations that<br />
they are willing to accept these people if they return<br />
voluntarily, but not if, not to accept them if they don't<br />
want to come back. But these are exactly the sorts of<br />
issues which must be talked about between us and the<br />
authorities of Cambodia and that's precisely what's<br />
happening. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said you don't know the<br />
numbers who've been returned before, but what has been<br />
the process in dealing with boat people before who<br />
haven't been given refugee status?<br />
PM: Well if the, if the DORS Committee determines that<br />
they don't satisfy the requirements and are therefore<br />
eligible for staying in this country as refugees, then<br />
they will be returned.<br />
JOURNALIST: But they have been returned in the past?<br />
PM: Well, I'm not sure about the, you're talking about<br />
the people from Cambodia, I don't know whether in respect<br />
of the DORS Committee that where they have made a<br />
decision if they've made a decision, that they don't<br />
satisfy the category, whether as yet any have been<br />
returned. But<br />
JOURNALIST: I'm talking about the Vietnamese people and<br />
other boat people in the past, not this particular group.<br />
PM: Yes, well, as I would understand, where they don't<br />
meet the requirements, then we, we move to return them.<br />
But of course in regard to Vietnam, you know that we've<br />
had to be part, and properly part, of an international<br />
consideration of this matter. A meeting was held in<br />
Geneva last year in June and the comprehensive action<br />
plan was adopted there and we are part of the, the<br />
international attempt to deal now with this situation<br />
which is requiring an agreement on the part of, of<br />
Vietnam that they should accept the orderly return of<br />
people who've not been accepted, most particularly in<br />
Hong Kong, but not exclusively there and we've been an<br />
important part of the process of drawing up that common<br />
action plan. Now as to whether, out of Australia, we've<br />
had the return from people to Vietnam who have been<br />
through the DORS process, I can't say.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, is there any prospect that we<br />
would review our attitude to the Hun Sen regime as part<br />
of this process of..<br />
PM:. No, I don't think there's any question of reviewing<br />
our attitude towards the Hun Sen regime. We have, as<br />
I've said, Geoff, over the last couple of years, as we've<br />
played, as I think you'll appreciate, a fairly<br />
significant role in consideration of how best to resolve<br />
the, the tragedy of Cambodia. We've had communications,<br />
consultations, discussions with the regime, with Hun Sen<br />
directly, our representatives have met with him, our<br />
Ministers have met with him, Mr Costello has met with him<br />
and we'll continue to do that on the basis that the Hun<br />
Sen regime does not represent, as it stands, what will be<br />
the final outcome of these processes. What we want to<br />
see is the establishment of a process in which there can<br />
be free and fair and internationally supervised elections<br />
which will determine what will be the ultimate government </p>
<p>of that country. But until that occurs we'll have<br />
whatever intercourse with that government is necessary,<br />
both in the context of discussing these people, the boat<br />
people and also in terms of discussing the, the question<br />
of trying to get a resolution of the Cambodian problem.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just back on the Chinese<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: Just back on the Chinese students<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you got any thoughts as to how long<br />
they should be allowed to stay in Australia, whether<br />
PM: Well, I have, I have indeed got ideas about that and<br />
I've discussed it with Mr Hand, but those details will be<br />
contained in the submission which Mr Hand is bringing to<br />
the Cabinet. But I've got a very clear idea and so has<br />
he as to the sort of period that we would, we would<br />
determine, that they should-stay. I mean, without, I<br />
won't go to that period. I know exactly what it is and<br />
what Mr Hand will be recommending following the<br />
discussions that I've had with him, but conceptually I<br />
can go to it in this sense. You are going to have to<br />
have some period of time which you believe will make you<br />
feel that at the end of that time, one should be able to<br />
make a judgement about the situation in China. What's<br />
the sort of situation to which these people would be<br />
likely to be returning and that, by definition, is not<br />
something which is just six months away but you are not<br />
going to make it ten years.<br />
JOURNALIST: Li Peng<br />
PM: Li Peng, yes?<br />
JOURNALIST: Li Peng late last week<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: was saying some very conciliatory things<br />
about the students and saying they would be welcomed<br />
back. How seriously do you take that?<br />
PM: Well, I have observed the comments that have been<br />
made by Li Peng. We are, of course, as you would be<br />
aware, in possession of a whole range of information<br />
about practices and attitudes in China and all those<br />
things have to be taken into account. I mean, just one<br />
statement by the Premier doesn't constitute the totality'<br />
of the considerations which would determine our position.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, as you move towards deciding<br />
how long the students can stay, where there's a question<br />
of family reunion.. </p>
<p>7<br />
PM: Well, that's one of the considerations which the<br />
Minister will be addressing in his submission and I, I<br />
don't want to go any further into that detail. It's<br />
obviously a relevant question which will be part of the<br />
submission.<br />
JOURNALIST: When do you expect Cabinet to discuss these<br />
things? PM: Relatively near future. I had my discussion with<br />
the Minister now over a week ago and he's gone off to<br />
prepare his submission and so it will be relatively<br />
near future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, can we take it from your remarks<br />
that you are ruling out permanent residency being given?<br />
PM: Am I ruling out?<br />
JOURNALIST: We can take it from your earlier comments<br />
that you are ruling out permanent residency being granted<br />
to the students?<br />
PM: The concept will be, Michelle, as I say, I've used<br />
the phrase quite deliberately, separate category for<br />
these people which will take account of the facts of<br />
what's happened in China and one will have to determine<br />
what one thinks is an appropriate period which they can<br />
stay and with the assumption, in regard to those people,<br />
that, that they will want to stay and would be entitled<br />
to, but you are going to have to have a period of time in<br />
which it's appropriate for them and for us to make a<br />
judgement. I mean, what you've got to understand in this<br />
is that we shouldn't be assuming that of all these<br />
20,000, they'll all want to st3y. I mean, one would<br />
assume that for very, very many of them, if China were to<br />
return to some sort of normalcy, whatever word you want<br />
to use, that they would want to return to China. So the,<br />
the intelligent thing to do is to say in regard to these<br />
people, well alright we understand your position, we've<br />
got to set a period of time which you can stay and by the<br />
end of which time it is reasonable to expect that you and<br />
we will be able to make a judgement.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, can I get absolutely crystal<br />
clear this question of the boat people. Has Australia<br />
sent any boat people back to where they came from?<br />
PM: Not of the, as I understand it, there have been<br />
three boat loads and there have been, there has been no<br />
return of those people, as I understand it. Now what we<br />
are saying is that, making it quite clear, that if the<br />
DORS Committee in respect of these people makes a<br />
decision that they don't satisfy the criteria, then it<br />
will be our wish that they go back to the point from<br />
which they came. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I mean, I simply haven't kept up there may have<br />
been some. I don't think any have gone back at this<br />
stage. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, to what extent is a resolution in<br />
Cambodia necessary in resolving the problem as far as<br />
Vietnamese and Cambodian boat people and has that been a<br />
factor in Senator Evans' taking the issue up as strongly<br />
as he has?<br />
PM: No, no, no. Our concern with the situation in<br />
Cambodia goes back to our first day of Government. It<br />
was unrelated to any question of boat people from<br />
Cambodia to here we'd had this continuing tragedy in<br />
Cambodia and one of the first things I did as Prime<br />
Minister was to call my then Foreign Minister in, Bill<br />
Hayden, and to say we should take some role in Indc China<br />
W in trying to do what we can, given the nature of the<br />
relationships that we enjoy with China, with the United<br />
States and with the ASEAN countries, that I took the view<br />
from day one that we had, because of those range of<br />
relationships, the capacity to play some role without<br />
overstating it and we did from day one. It was quite<br />
independent of any question of boat people because there<br />
has been continuing tragedy in Indo China generally-<br />
Vietnam and Cambodia in particular. And so Australia has<br />
been very much at the forefront both in bilateral<br />
discussions, regional discussions, global discussions and<br />
within the United Nations in trying to play a<br />
constructive role to get a resolution of this matter.<br />
It's been quite independent of any consideration of boat<br />
people. JOURNALIST: Mr Keating said last night in London<br />
that beyond 25 percent represented a controlling<br />
interest, will Cabinet be considering lifting the foreign<br />
ownership limits on newspapers from 15 percent up to<br />
around about the 25 percent limit or perhaps in line,<br />
percent limit on TV?<br />
PM: Well, I haven't, I haven't directed any attention to<br />
such a proposition, but if the, the Minister directly<br />
concerned in the Communications area or Mr Keating want<br />
to raise that matter, well, it's appropriate to be raised<br />
but there's nothing on the table at the moment.<br />
JOURNALIST: What of Rupert Murdoch, isn't there a<br />
contradiction PM: Well, he, he was in a situation where he started of f<br />
as an Aussie and then changed his position..<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what's going to happen to<br />
the students you've got two categories of Chinese<br />
students, one automatically will get some sort of period<br />
which you'l11 determine, but those who came afterwards, on </p>
<p>what basis will the DORS Committee consider them? On the<br />
basis of some sort of temporary refuge in Australia..<br />
PM: No, the, the assumption in regard to those people<br />
is, as I've said on, I don't know how many occasions now,<br />
this will be at least the fourth, fifth. The assumption<br />
in regard to those who've come post June the 20th is that<br />
they will return to China. That's the assumption. Now<br />
I've said and it is getting rather boring to<br />
understand simple things is a bit surprising. Those<br />
people, nevertheless, have the right to apply to the DORS<br />
Committee process. If they choose to do tha t, then<br />
they'll be considered.<br />
JOURNALIST: will they be allowed to stay for that<br />
period PM: No, no, no. Look it I hope I'm not sounding, you<br />
know, beyond patience, but it is basically an<br />
extraordinarily simple proposition which I'll repeat for<br />
you. For those who came before the 20th, the Cabinet<br />
will be making a decision that there will be a period of<br />
time that they will stay. Right? That's not<br />
complicated. There will be no such provision for those<br />
after that period and if they apply under the DORS<br />
process, then while they are being considered under the<br />
DORS process, they stay. I mean, you don't have them<br />
being considered by the DORS Committee and kick them out<br />
while they are being considered. They will have, if they<br />
choose to make the application, they will have the rights<br />
of remaining here while they are so considered. But with<br />
no, no period of time for them, saying for that period<br />
you are here without question.<br />
JOURNALIST: But on a completely different basis had<br />
they been there two days or three days before?<br />
PM: But you've got to make the assumption, and this<br />
is the whole essence of distinction, you've got to make<br />
the assumption that those who came here after the events<br />
of Tienanmen Square came here with certain knowledge.<br />
You've got to make a different assumption about them,<br />
than you do about those who were here before. I mean,<br />
no-one's questioned that, either here or anywhere else.<br />
JOURNALIST: So they must prove they're refugees, these<br />
later ones-<br />
PM: The ones who are here after the 20th have no<br />
assumption in their favour. The assumption in regard to<br />
them is that they will return.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister they also have a right though<br />
I understand to apply, if they don't apply as refugees,<br />
to apply for grant of residence on humanitarian grounds.<br />
Now currently under your new migration regulations, there<br />
loophole in thim, no applications are being processed<br />
on humanitarian grounds, because of the regulations. Can </p>
<p>you say what the Government is going to do about that,<br />
and whether you believe that is partly responsible for<br />
the huge backlog in immigration at the moment?<br />
PM: I don't believe it's responsible for the huge<br />
backlog, but all I can say is that any rights that people<br />
have under the existing law will remain. We've not<br />
JOURNALIST: But under the new regulations nobody<br />
qualifies for grant of residence on humanitarian grounds.<br />
PM: Well if the new regulations have that impact then<br />
that's what the case is. I am not engaged, and the<br />
Cabinet will not be engaged, in changing anything other<br />
than in terms that I have indicated. That is to indicate<br />
in regard to Chinese who have come before Tienanmen<br />
Square. I'm not going to go over it again. We'll be<br />
doing that. We won't be making any other changes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well Mr Hawke. Two questions. Why are the<br />
Cambodians in the Northern Territory being held virtually<br />
incommunicado and will they be given the sort of help<br />
that they will need to make an application to the DORS<br />
Committee? Social work help, translators you can<br />
imagine someone coming out of Cambodia might not have in<br />
his head a full knowledge of the Australian refugee<br />
procedures. PM: They will get the normal assistance that is<br />
available to anyone who takes who seeks to take<br />
advantage of the DORS procedures.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, will they get social service, in<br />
terms of interpreters and why are they being held<br />
incommunicado at the moment?<br />
PM: Well you use the phrase incommunicado. I mean these<br />
people have arrived here other than in accordance with<br />
the legal immigration procedures and they are therefore<br />
not here legally. They are accommodated, dealt with<br />
according to the normal procedures, which make available<br />
to them the opportunity of putting their case to DORS.<br />
Now obviously there are certain facilities made available<br />
to them in terms of interpreters, language and so on and<br />
an indication of what their rights are. That has been<br />
going on for many years and the same facilities are being<br />
applied to these people. And will be applied. We are<br />
not seeking to change the law in regard to those people.<br />
What I'm seeking to do is to make clear to people who are<br />
in that country, now in Cambodia and who may be<br />
contemplating coming here, that they need not think that<br />
here is a country which is going to abandon its sovereign<br />
right to determine the level of its immigration intake.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible) Mr Willis any, or given him<br />
any indication that he could have an overseas posting<br />
with the Government and has he given any indication that </p>
<p>he might accept it? or do you expect him to stay the<br />
full term?<br />
PM: I don't go to any question of don't read too much<br />
into this but I don't go to publicly to discussions<br />
I have with any of my Ministers about their futures.<br />
Whether in regard to the tenure of the portfolio they<br />
have got, possible changes to another, or possible<br />
departure from Government. If I have such discussions<br />
with my Ministers they are, as far as I'm concerned,<br />
entirely personal and confidential.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect to reshuffle, to have to<br />
reshuffle your Cabinet in the next eighteen months?<br />
PM: No. We've just won an election. We've just had a<br />
very significant reshuffle. I haven't directed my mind<br />
to the question of reshuffle. I think we have a superbly<br />
equipped Ministry as a matter of fact, whoare doing their<br />
job really well. My mind is not on reshuffling at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, was Senator Richardson wrong when<br />
he apparently tells anybody who will listen that Ralph<br />
Willis will be gone by the end of the year and he will be<br />
offered the Finance portfolio?<br />
PM: No, I don't know. I mean if you assert Geoff and<br />
I know that you are assiduous in trying to follow up<br />
these things. Sometimes factually and sometimes with a<br />
fervent imagination. But if he's saying that, I accept<br />
you word for it. I'm not saying it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Senator Richardson said yesterday<br />
that the Party should look at falling membership and also<br />
said that some Ministers weren't spending enough time<br />
talking to the grass roots. Are you aware of this<br />
problem and what steps do you think should be taken to<br />
overcome this.<br />
PM: I don't think it's a great problem. I think Graham<br />
is absolutely right in sounding out the warning that all<br />
of us, myself included, should as far as it's consistent<br />
with the discharge of our Ministerial duties, spend as<br />
much time as we can, with the grass roots. I think<br />
that's a very sensible suggestion to be making. But how<br />
far it's a problem I haven't come to any conclusion about<br />
that. But I think it's a very sensible thing to be<br />
telling all Ministers, spend as much time as you can with<br />
the rank and file.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible) with the grass roots. Will<br />
you be at the Victorian Conference next weekend?<br />
PM: No, I wouldn't think so.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why is that?<br />
PM: Because I don't usually go. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: It's a pretty important Conference and<br />
you've just been to the New South Wales one.<br />
PM: I have just been to the* New South Wales one. Yes.<br />
But I've been Prime Minister now for seven odd years. I<br />
think I'm not sure Michelle how many times I've been<br />
to the Victorian Conference in that period, but I don't<br />
think it's more than a couple at the most. I can<br />
remember going once.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why don't you then?<br />
PM: Well, why don't I go to a whole lot of other ones?<br />
I mean I've got plenty of things to do and<br />
JOURNALIST: It is your home State.<br />
S ePMxa: lteIdt ips osmityi ohnom, e I Swtaatsen. ' t aB urte gevuelanr baefttoerne deI r waast tihn ethis<br />
Conference in Victoria. If they feel they would like me<br />
to be there and I f elt that I want to go, well then that<br />
would be arranged. I haven't felt any compulsion to be<br />
there next weekend. None at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke the Privacy Commissioner has<br />
revealed that an enormous amount of information, held by<br />
your Departments, on people who make FOI requests, people<br />
who, public servants and people write to you. That<br />
includes tax f ile numbers, debts, political<br />
police.... Why is that a new concerned? Should the<br />
Government look at that?<br />
PM: I read the report, particularly a headline report in<br />
the Sydney Morning Herald. I'll get a report on that<br />
just to find out whether in fact there is anything to be<br />
concerned about. I didn't listen to it, but I'm informed<br />
that the P * rivacy Commissioner, this morning seemed to<br />
play down very considerably, the import of what was in<br />
the paper. But I don't tkae these things lightly. I<br />
mean I understand, as I think anyone should, that it is<br />
inevitable that in our society that the range of<br />
departments that we have, Social Security, Taxation and<br />
so on, there are going to be millions of reports and<br />
files and the right approach for Government is to ensure<br />
that there is the balance, the proper balance between<br />
having the information that is necessary to provide the<br />
services of Government on the one hand, but on the other<br />
to ensure the appropriate levels of privacy, so that<br />
people's personal affairs are not made available to<br />
people or to an extent, that is not necessary to ensure<br />
the discharge of that obligation of Government of<br />
providing a service. Now we shouldn't be surprise that<br />
there are millions of files. That's' inevitable. But<br />
I'Ill ask for a report to reassure myself that there is no<br />
breach of the requirements of privacy. If I get any<br />
indication from that report that there is cause for<br />
concern, then I'll initiate action. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on the economy, will it be your<br />
objective in the coming Budget discussions, to ensure<br />
that the Government spending is restrained to the extent<br />
that there is no increase real increase in outlays in<br />
1990-91?<br />
PM: We've had four years, as you know, in a row Geoff of<br />
real reductions in outlays. We'll make the decisions<br />
which we think are appropriate for the Budget of 1990-91.<br />
We will be engaged, without any question in this period<br />
as I've said just in the last few days, in looking for<br />
areas of reductions in expenditure. Just what the<br />
balance will be I'm not quite sure. But there certainly<br />
will be reductions. That will be done because it's<br />
necessary from our own point of view. And it's also<br />
necessary if we are going to be asking the States to play<br />
their part. Now just what those figures will be is a<br />
matter that will come out of the processes of ERC which<br />
unfortunately start next week.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was Mr Clark out of line when he says<br />
billion the cuts?<br />
PM: Is Mr Clark out of line? When has he ever been line<br />
with the Government?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke has ERC determined any broad target<br />
for these spending cuts as yet?<br />
PM: There have been some considerations, some of I<br />
think target might be overstating it but there are some<br />
ball park figures that have been thrown around.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is $ 1.6 billion in the ball park?<br />
PM: Good try. Good try.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you expect to cut, squeeze the States in<br />
real terms at the Premiers' Conference?<br />
PM: Another good try boy. Good try. We'll be expecting<br />
the States to play a part in restraint. Now just what<br />
that figure will be is precisely what we've got to direct<br />
our attention to in the weeks ahead. But it's quite<br />
clear that the States haven't exercised in the last few<br />
years the same level of restraint as there has been at<br />
the level of the Commonwealth and they are going to be<br />
required to exercise restraint in this period ahead of<br />
US. JOURNALIST: Are you at all sympathetic to the arguments<br />
of the States that if you want them to speed up the<br />
process of micro reform, or in some cases, launch that<br />
process, then you oughtn't to be as tough with them<br />
financially? </p>
<p>PM: Yes, but that is a rather simplistic way of putting<br />
it. If I were a Premier of a State with a Premiers'<br />
Conference coming up on the 28th of this month, where I'd<br />
heard the Federal Government talking about the need for<br />
restraint, and I'd also heard that same Government<br />
talking about the need for co-operation from the States<br />
to pursue micro economic reform, I guess that I would try<br />
and meld those two things and come along and say now<br />
don't be too tough on me if you want me to play my part<br />
in micro economic reform. I suppose that's human nature.<br />
But the facts are that the Premiers have got to<br />
understand that at this Conference on the 28th of this<br />
month, that we are going to have a macro economic task in<br />
front of us which is consistent with the sort of things<br />
that we've had to do over the last seven years. We've<br />
got to get the macro economic settings right. And we<br />
will do that and we won't really be terribly responsive<br />
to a proposition which if it was put as crudely as this,<br />
well don't hit us too hard, because if you do we won't<br />
co-operate in the micro economic area. Now, and I would<br />
trust that the Premiers wouldn't be so crass as to put<br />
the proposition in those terms. Now, that is a different<br />
proposition however from specific areas of micro economic<br />
reform, where it may be abeled to be argued that if<br />
you're going to give effect to a particular reform, that<br />
some sort of assistance may be required. Now that's a<br />
quite different proposition and what is quite clear is<br />
that I will be raising at this Premiers' Conference the<br />
need for co-operation in the area of micro economic<br />
reform. I'll expect to get that co-operation and I think<br />
the Premiers will be entitled to expect that we will take<br />
a sensible and rational approach to that issue. We will.<br />
But if there's some attempt just to have this simple<br />
proposition, don't be too hard on us. If you are we<br />
won't be too co-operative. There won't be any mileage in<br />
that one for them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would it be reflected also in your own<br />
Budget in say a change of emphasis towards infrastructure<br />
funding away from other areas of the Budget, given the<br />
importance of infrastructure funding to some of the more<br />
critical areas of microeconomic reform rail, road, the<br />
waterfront etc?<br />
PM: Well we'll, as we have in the past, we'll make those<br />
decisions in regard to funding which we believe Take<br />
the area of roads. Let's just look at that. In a period<br />
of very very considerable financiel restraint on the part<br />
of the Commonwealth where there've been these, as I say,<br />
four successive years of real reductions in outlays,<br />
we've nevertheless in the area of roads in our general<br />
decisions and then in the last 12 months in two separate<br />
specific decisions made more funding available for roads.<br />
So we will make the decisions in regard to infrastructure<br />
funding which are necessary to give effect to the sorts<br />
of decisions that we think are necessary to get the<br />
competitive structure of this economy into place. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Will that be at the cost of the transfer<br />
system etc?<br />
PM: When you say at the cost of, I mean, in the end when<br />
a government has drawn up its Budget and there is this<br />
amount of money available for the transfer system, there<br />
is this amount of money available for roads, there is<br />
this amount of money available for defence, then by<br />
definition there has been a series of judgements which<br />
have said well we think the priority we have there<br />
requires that amount of money. Now you have not got<br />
unlimited resources so it means that you have been able<br />
to do less elsewhere in terms of matching that priority.<br />
I mean that's the nature of government, that's the<br />
toughness of government in one way. I mean you've got a<br />
position where so many of the areas of government, of<br />
outlays and expenditures, can put a good case for more,<br />
just looked at alone. Very easy. I mean this is really<br />
what we go through in the Expenditure Review Committee<br />
year after year. Every Minister's able to basically put<br />
a very very good case for more. He can say look if you<br />
give me more, he will be this positive response and that<br />
outcome and benefit. But in the end it's the aggregates<br />
and the inter-relationship of the aggregates which<br />
determine the health of the economy. So your Minister<br />
can say look I'll have a very healthy little situation<br />
here if you give me another hundred million, but if you<br />
give that one a hundred million, and this one a hundred<br />
million and this one half a billion and so on, while he<br />
might think he's getting a healthy outcome in respect of<br />
the proposal that he puts to you and he probably would<br />
be, looked at alone if you don't look at the aggregate<br />
outcome you won't have a healthy economy as a whole..<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, at the Premiers' Conference on the<br />
28th, how much work will you actually be able to do on<br />
microeconomic reform? You've just mentioned specifics of<br />
particular areas<br />
PM: I think what I want to be doing at the Premiers'<br />
Conference on this issue is to really say these things.<br />
We must realise that the sort of microeconomic reform<br />
that we need in this country is not going to come simply<br />
from decisions by the Commonwealth Government alone. By<br />
definition there is so much of it which is in your<br />
domain, obviously while electricity, power and<br />
generation and so on, without being exhaustive about it.<br />
Now therefore I'll be saying what I want is a situation<br />
of your commitment to joining with us in trying to bring<br />
about the most effective sort of reform in these areas<br />
thtwe possibly can. And to establish really, not then<br />
at that meeting on the 28th a series of decisions about<br />
each of these areas, but rather to set up firstly their<br />
agreement of the importance of cooperation and secondly a<br />
process to follow from the Premiers' Committee for giving<br />
effect to that commitment. I believe that we will get a<br />
commitment from the Premiers of the need for such<br />
cooperation. So then, if they give that commitment and </p>
<p>that agreement, then to establish a process of<br />
cooperation. Now just what will be involved in that it's<br />
too early to say. Conceivably, and I say conceivably, it<br />
could mean another special Premiers' Conference,<br />
conceivably, as part of that process. Or it could mean a<br />
series of meetings with particular Ministers in<br />
particular areas. But that's what I see the 28th as<br />
being about. Acceptance of the commitment, the<br />
cooperation in the area of microeconomic reform and<br />
agreement to a process. Because as I said the other<br />
night, what we've got to realise in this country, and<br />
it's terribly important that I think this, it's in our<br />
minds as a community. You're going to have by 1992,<br />
which is only a couple of years away, in Europe 12 states<br />
who will have made a series of decisions about their<br />
relationships which will mean that there will be less<br />
obstacles, impediments to the free movement of goods and<br />
services in Europe than there will be in Australia<br />
between the States of Australia. Now that's not a burden<br />
that we can intelligently continue to carry on into the<br />
future. Now we don't have in this country a disposition<br />
to change these things by transference in a<br />
constitutional sense of powers between the States and the<br />
Commonwealth. So what we've intelligently got to do is<br />
to sit down and say well how are we going to cooperate to<br />
make sure that we really do have one economic, national<br />
economic unit when it comes to these issues? I believe<br />
that the Premiers will be responsive to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Rather than say lumping the States together<br />
and saying they haven't played their part, isn't it<br />
really fairer to acknowledge that in fact some States<br />
such as NSW have made significant steps along the path<br />
microeconomic reform<br />
PM: Wall it is the case, certainly Milton, that the<br />
records of the States both in terms of general economic<br />
policy and microeconomic reform in particular are not<br />
uniform. I accept that and that will be acknowledged in<br />
the discussions we have. I mean obviously it's not<br />
appropriate for me to try and award marks out of ten to<br />
all the States here now. It's neither appropriate nor in<br />
the self-interest of the Government an appropriate thing<br />
to do. But it will be reflected in the discussions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Two Labor States in fact, WA and Victoria,<br />
have lost a lot of money, of their taxpayers money over<br />
recent years. Will that be a consideration that you will<br />
take into account at the Premiers' Conference?<br />
PM: I think it's maybe a consideration that they would<br />
like us to take into account but I don't think they'll<br />
get terribly far with that proposition.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just clarifying something establishing<br />
some sort of consensus if you like on the national goals<br />
of this Premiers' Conference. Do you see any possibility </p>
<p>that specific purpose grants could be used or directed at<br />
this round of State funding to microeconomic issues?<br />
PM: No such decisions see being made at this<br />
conference. We will be responsive to anything that the<br />
States want to say to us in this area of microeconomic<br />
reform. But I wouldn't see any decisions being made at<br />
this conference within that framework or on those<br />
criteria. But we really, as I say, have. just got to get<br />
very firmly onto the agenda at this Premiers' Conference<br />
these issues and be prepared on the part of the<br />
Commonwealth and of the States to have everything into<br />
the ring on this. What are the things that have got to<br />
be done by the Commonwealth and the States to ensure that<br />
we create the best microeconomic framework in this<br />
country to ensure an efficient and internationally<br />
competitive economy? That's the responsibility that<br />
we've got irrespective of our politics, whether it's<br />
Liberal Premiers like Nick Greiner or overwhelmingly<br />
Labor Premiers as they are and ourselves. We've got to<br />
put political differences aside, regional differences<br />
a * side and say how together do we act to make this<br />
national Australian economy as internationally<br />
competitive and efficient as we possibly can?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you just commenced three inquiries<br />
by the Industry Commission in the areas applying to the<br />
States' rail, electricity and marketing authorities.<br />
Aren't you shortcircuiting that<br />
PM: Of course we're not. The first thing to note is<br />
that those three inquiries that you refer to have been<br />
set up after consultation with and agreement from the<br />
States. This is not something that we've imposed upon<br />
the States. It represents the outcome of discussions and<br />
agreements with them. Governments, Federal and State,<br />
don't just then say we'll put everything on hold and<br />
we'll wait until we get those reports, either the interim<br />
or a final report. I mean you've obviously got to<br />
address these and other issues yourself. I mean you take<br />
the area of trying to get an integrated rail freight<br />
system in this country. There obviously is much that can<br />
be done in discussion between us and the States on that<br />
issue without simply waiting for the report from the<br />
Industry Commission.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke you mentioned some of the carrots<br />
you've offered the States in terms of speeding up the<br />
process of micro reform. What about the stick? How<br />
prepared is the Commonwealth to use its powers of funding<br />
and borrowing to push the States into micro reform?<br />
PM: Well I hope we'll get this matter resolved in a way<br />
which involves a maximum degree of cooperation. I mean<br />
you know that's the way I prefer to do things. Not<br />
simply because of my nature but also because in the end<br />
processes which reflect agreement and cooperation will<br />
stick better than anything else. Now how in that process </p>
<p>you get, as you put it, the appropriate combination of<br />
carrots and sticks is too early to say. But really what<br />
I want to do is to get a position from the end of this<br />
month of commitment to process. How in working out that<br />
process, what we'll need to do and what they'll need to<br />
do, that's exactly the guts of what the discussions into<br />
the processes are going to have to be about.<br />
JOURNALIST: Administrative Services Minister,<br />
Stewart West, has suggested that NSW and Victoria<br />
should be compensated for the infrastructure costs of<br />
immigration. He was critical of the Government for not<br />
having considered it before. a) Was he right that you<br />
should have considered it before, and b) are you going to<br />
. start doing it now?<br />
PM: I've got really no comment to make on what Stewart<br />
said. Stewart was a member of the Government when all<br />
those things were being done.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: That doesn't follow. Nor the fact that I say it<br />
doesn't follow means that something will be done. But<br />
your proposition because of what I've just said means<br />
that nothing will be done or something like that, that<br />
doesn't follow.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, a week or so ago Senator Ray said<br />
on behalf of the Foreign Minister that the Government<br />
would be considering the implications of the attempted<br />
PLO raid on the Israeli and also Arafat's attitude on<br />
this. Have you had an opportunity to do anything about<br />
this or does the Government continue, attempt to continue<br />
directly.. PM: I understand that the Foreign Minister is having a<br />
review of the situation. I'm given to understand that<br />
he's doing that. No doubt at some stage he will report<br />
to me on that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you believe that had you<br />
waited until the Cabinet decision had been made that<br />
there would have been less confusion and concern in the<br />
community over the Chinese and Cambodian issue?<br />
PM: N ot at all. I mean the confusion in the community<br />
that you talk about, which, may I say as gently as I can<br />
f lows very considerably from the incapacity of some of<br />
your colleagues to understand simple propositions, is not<br />
something which necessarily would've been any different<br />
after the Cabinet decision. I mean the things that I've<br />
said are very simple, straightforward and may I say<br />
unchanged from the day I first spoke on it. I read with<br />
a certain amount of amusement I must say about Hawke<br />
changing his position, Hawke backing down. Absolute<br />
bloody balderdash. Hawke hasn't changed his position one<br />
fraction. For the simple reason that what. the Prime </p>
<p>19<br />
Minister said in the first place was sensible, reflected<br />
the requirements of this country and will be given effect<br />
to by the Government.<br />
JOURNALIST: Australian and Qantas need about $ 800<br />
million. Some of your Caucus backbenchers are saying<br />
that one possibility would be for superannuation funds to<br />
be encouraged or perhaps an investment vehicle to provide<br />
that sort of money. Are you attracted to that idea at<br />
all? PM: I'm attracted to this matter being discussed within<br />
the Party. I'm very interested to see that they are<br />
addressing their minds to a range of possibilities. The<br />
Government will have to make decisions about the funding<br />
of our airlines and any thoughts that anyone has on this<br />
matter within the Government process is welcome.<br />
* JOURNALIST: Will that be in the Budget?<br />
PM: I'm not quite sure whether it will be in the Budget.<br />
We'll obviously have to address this issue in the not too<br />
distant future.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just given the effort that we are putting<br />
into making sure that a peaceful settlement eventuates in<br />
Cambodia and given-how crucial China's position is on<br />
this, have you had any information conveyed to you that<br />
the recent decision on Chinese students might have upset<br />
or set back that process.<br />
PM: No. I don't believe that the position that China<br />
will adopt, both for itself and in terms of any influence<br />
it may have on the Khmer Rouge, is going to be impacted<br />
upon in any way by this decision. I mean, after all,<br />
other countries have made similar sorts of decisions<br />
the United States, Canada and so on. I think they'll<br />
understand. They may like it indicated they don't<br />
particularly like the decision we've made but<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well you've seen in the press the indication from<br />
spokespersons for the Chinese government that they<br />
haven't approved of the decision. That's all I'm going<br />
on. I haven't had any letter from Li Peng. But in the<br />
broad sweep of these sorts of issues the Chinese<br />
government will make a decision which it thinks is in its<br />
best interests in regard to how the situation in Cambodia<br />
should be resolved. I can only express the hope that it<br />
will be a decision both, as I say, in regard to their own<br />
direct involvement but more importantly in regard to the<br />
influence they have on the Khmer Rouge. That it will be<br />
a decision which is supportive of what now I see as a<br />
gathering momentum for a process of resolution. We've<br />
moved a long way since the f irst discussions took place.<br />
I think it was in December of ' 87 in Paris. That was<br />
when we had sort of the first coming together of the </p>
<p>groups. And we're now really getting down in the<br />
discussions which are taking place within the P5, that's<br />
the Permanent Five, of the Security Council, and<br />
discussions which have been taking place under the Paris<br />
Conference procedures and in the initiatives from<br />
Thailand and most recently reflected in the Tokyo<br />
meeting. Now really getting down to quite concrete and<br />
detailed issues, what for instance is the role of the<br />
State National Council, the issue of how you can vest<br />
some appropriate sovereignty in the State National<br />
Council which would enable then the concept of agreement<br />
to a United Nations, some sort of United Nations process<br />
in the interim leading up to the election and the<br />
oversight of the election. You're getting down to<br />
detailed questions of how do you relate proposals about a<br />
cease fire which now have been considered, but relating<br />
that as they must be to an overall permanent settlement.<br />
Now these are quite specific questions in which there<br />
have been considerable advances made so we are, I think,<br />
now in a position where we've got more reason to be<br />
confident than three years ago, although still<br />
recognising that there are very very hard decisions that<br />
have to be made. I'm hopeful that on all the evidence<br />
available to me that the various parties will be able to<br />
reach a point of agreement so that all their legitimate<br />
interests can be taken into account. There is no doubt<br />
that in that the position of China is very important. No<br />
doubt about that at all. But I would not expect that the<br />
decisions that they will make on this will be affected by<br />
the sorts of things we've been talking about here.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
