<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7996</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HYATT ON COLLINS, 25 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007996.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r i ; 3 rmcvO rr I cc crlrl'" V PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, HYATT ON COLLINS, 25 MARCH<br />
1990 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIaST: Prime Minister, is there any doubt in your mind<br />
about the outcome?<br />
PM: I believe we're going tO win, but I must observe the<br />
proprieties. The Qoujjt is not finished. What I am saying<br />
ia that on our beat judgement in regard to the seats still<br />
not deoided that the best bet is that we will emerge with a<br />
majority. JOURNALIST: Where did it go wrong for Labor, given that<br />
it's going<br />
PM: Well, the answer, the enswer to that Is quite obvious<br />
isn't it? I mean, you don't need to be a genius to know<br />
that if you put Victoria to one side, it woo virtually a<br />
status quo election.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did Mr Caln ring with his apologies this<br />
morning? PM: I don't respond to that question.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: What was the big issue here in Victorla?<br />
PM; Well, there seem to have been a number of issues. We<br />
b d that long stoppage involving the transport system and<br />
tot me say that one of my casualties, one of my Victorian<br />
casualties with whom I've spoen this morning, said he was<br />
soratched, scratch ticket out of the, out of the election in<br />
his judgement that that coat him the election now. So<br />
there were a number of factora.<br />
JOURNALIST; Prime Minister, State issues were<br />
responsible prlmarily for the appalling result in Victoria?<br />
PM: Well, what I'm saying is that as far as Federal issues<br />
were concerned, I think that probably Viotoria was no more<br />
affected by them than the rest of Australia. There's no </p>
<p>reason why they should have been and if you put Victoria to<br />
One side and look at the outcome,, it's virtually a status<br />
quo with some losses and offset by gains. Here in Victoria<br />
it seoms to be the assessment, if you watched John Howard<br />
lout night, John HIoward was making quite clear what his<br />
assessment was, my own people are making that assessment.<br />
Now, In putting that, lym not trying to just say well, we<br />
only lost seats S-n Victoria because of State issues. We<br />
could have lost seats in Victoria if the Victorian<br />
Government had been running, running as a very popular<br />
Government which it woon't, but the extent of the lose in<br />
Victoria seem$ to me very mvch a result of State factors,<br />
JOURNALISTi ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
0 JOURNALIST: What does the result mean for the National<br />
Party? PM: Well, I would think one thing you can say with<br />
certainty it means a change of loader.<br />
3OURNALIMT When will you be able to assure Autai'<br />
neighbours and allies that Australia does have a stable<br />
Government? PMt I think they know that now.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what in fact do you think the<br />
elevation of Carmen Lawrence to the Premiership in WA has?<br />
PM I can't quontify it. it was obviously a plus.<br />
JOURALIST: The transport reforms In Victoria example<br />
of micro economio reform. How does this auger well for your<br />
determination to push ahead with such reform?<br />
PM: Wall, in judging my Government on micro economic<br />
reforms you don't have to look at systems In Victoria.<br />
I repeat the statement that I've mae which hoe remained<br />
unchallenged throughout this campaign. I've done more with<br />
my colleagues in micro economic reform than has ever been<br />
done before in this country and we will continue apace with<br />
micro economic reform.<br />
JOURN~ ALIST: Was you policy suggesting that in fact the<br />
Victorian Government shouldn't have gone ahead with those<br />
sort of reforms<br />
PM: I think that there were arguments about not just what<br />
was done, but the way things were 0one and so on, but what<br />
we're about is in the Federal scene and I have a method with<br />
my colleagues of consultation and that has worked. I mean,<br />
the best illustration of that, I think, was that If you look<br />
at the, at the waterfront. During the campaign itself you<br />
had employers and users of our waterfront industry meeting,<br />
actually during the campaign and making the judgement. </p>
<p>Saying, firstly, applause to the Hawke Labor Government for<br />
What they'd done, b) what they were, as a way they were<br />
doing it and, c) saying that our approach was the way to go<br />
as compared with the way the Oppoaition woe talking. So<br />
we've, we've got the, not only runs on the board but the<br />
procedure recommends iteelf to the people who are involved.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, given that you are acting in<br />
only a caretaker capacity, where does that leave any<br />
approach to the Reaerve Bank on interest rates?<br />
PM: It means that no no approach will be made to the<br />
Reserve Bank until I move from being caretaker to going Into<br />
the fourth term.<br />
JOURNALI4ST: So in other words any hope that people might<br />
have had for a reduction within a couple of weeks may now be<br />
extended by a couple of weeks possibly?<br />
PM: I don't see, I don't follow your arithmetic. I don't<br />
believe that it's going to be two weeks before I'm confirmed<br />
in my fourth term.<br />
JOURNALIST; When do you think that will be Mr Hlawke?<br />
FMt Well I can't be absolutely precise about that. This is<br />
a matter, in the end, for the electoral authorities, but I<br />
would hope that by the, by the end of this week ahead of us<br />
that we'd be in that position.<br />
JOURNALIST: interest rates will Come dlown by a<br />
perentage point in a few weeks time?<br />
PM: I've answered those questions, I've got nothing more to<br />
add to that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what would you have done<br />
differently? PM: In the campaign?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM4: Nothing that I can think of. I hope that that don't<br />
sound arrogant, but I look back over it and obviously there<br />
are one or two things that you would, would marginally<br />
W1henge, but I made a clear decision before the election<br />
started which waa this that there were things I wanted to<br />
do and to promise to the people in this election, but that I<br />
wanted to make sure that in funding terms I had made the<br />
savings that would enable us to do that. So we sot down and<br />
did a lot of hard work in the Expenditure Review Committee,<br />
confirmed by the Cabinet, as to savings. Once I knew I had<br />
those savings then 1, with my colleagues, worked 6ut the<br />
funded promises we could make. Now that set the framework<br />
for Labor. I was able to go into thle campaign with a<br />
promise, a plan, a vision, funded for the future and I<br />
believe that was the right way to go and it certainly set </p>
<p>the contrast with our opponents who still think that you can<br />
bribe the Australian electorate with billions of dollars of<br />
unfunded promises. so the basic framework I wouldn't, I<br />
wouldn't change. An I Baid with a little bit of flippancy<br />
on Friday when I was asked a similar question, I said well<br />
if I'd known how It would have been interpreted I wouldn't<br />
have had my tantrum of temper, as it was put, anld sea of<br />
microphones at the opera House which was, by the deep<br />
analysis of so many of you as seen as Hlawke out of control.<br />
I mean, I wouldn't have given you that opportunity for<br />
mimanalysis. I mean, I mean, I hate to have misled you.<br />
It's not fair of me.<br />
JOURNALIST: You believe the debato over the HFP had any<br />
effect on the outcome?<br />
PM: Well all I can say on that question about the debate on<br />
the tWP is that I'm very, very pleased to say that I was<br />
told In the end that, as far as could be ascertained, the,<br />
the MFP debate had not hurt us and that would confirm my<br />
judgemtent about the Australian people, But I went to<br />
JOURNALIST; ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, can I finish? I want to say that the card that<br />
was played in the campaign and my opponents know the card<br />
and what the card was and why they played it was an<br />
exitremely unfortunate event, I think one of the moot<br />
unfortunate events, in, in the post war history of Australia<br />
and x.' m glad that my judgement of the Australian people on<br />
theee issues has been confirmed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will. it be a Hawke/ Keating leadership team<br />
going into the n~ ext election, Mr Hawke?<br />
PM! Well Hawke will be the Prime Minister. The Deputy<br />
0 Prime Minister is a matter for decision by the, by the<br />
Ca~ uu. I'mf pleased to see that Paul seems to be<br />
reconsidering his view, he seemed to have Indicated earlier<br />
that he may not be interested in the Deputy Prime<br />
MinistershipI he seems to be reconsidering that. So it will<br />
be a matter whether he decides to stand. If he stands, he<br />
obviously stands with a very good chance.<br />
JOURNALISTI: tip for the team on the other aide, Prime<br />
Minister going into the next election?<br />
PM: Well, X always in this political analyais look to<br />
history as a basis for informing my mind, and I look at<br />
their history. I think we may have come to the and of the<br />
hirdy gir-dy syndrome, so this time arounld it's John Howard,<br />
this time around it's Andrew, this time around It's John<br />
Howard. I think we've probably come to the end of the hirdy<br />
girdy. They'll change their game probably a bit<br />
mischievous of me to really speculate, but I'm feeling<br />
slightly mischievous after a long night's sleep I would<br />
have thought that the, the moat likely sort of candidates<br />
that are emerging. and who would have been now on the </p>
<p>I r . rq-Wor c VCfl T~<br />
telephone for hours and hours and hours, would be John<br />
Howson, rred Chaney they'V6 probably spent more time on<br />
the telephone both ringing and being rung and if they were<br />
betting, I would bet Hewson emerging as the leader. NOW for<br />
the quinella I'm not quite sure, but it may bet it may be a<br />
Hewton/ McLachlen quinella.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think you now vindicated with John Stone<br />
having beaten you for the Rhodes scholarship back<br />
PM: Well, you know, one day you'll get it right, one day<br />
you'll get it right. I was never a candidate against John<br />
Stone for the Rhodes scholarship. I mean, that's now<br />
nearly 40 years ago. You know, I've been telling people,<br />
You know, the facts about this thing. But suppose,<br />
reasonable hope that in 50 years, in half a century you<br />
might get it right.<br />
JOURNALIST: How do you foal about Janine Haines bowing out<br />
Of politics and also her claim that it was dirty tricks<br />
campaign? PM: Well, I think, let me say this, I think that Janine<br />
Hainee, you know, she's not my pin-up politician, but 1, I<br />
look, no, no, let me say this, I think that Janine Haines<br />
did show a lot of courage. I think she showed a lot of<br />
courage in having a go and I think she is to be applauded<br />
for that. I alwayS felt confident that Gordon Bhlney would<br />
come through and, as you know, I'm not speaking after the<br />
event now, I said all along that I thought Gordon would get<br />
through and may I take this opportunity of publicly<br />
congratVlating him and his team of supporters for their<br />
steadfastness. But I applaud Janine Hfaines for her courage<br />
and the fact that she's now having a little bit of, you<br />
know, post defeat complaints about others, well, that's<br />
understandable. JOURNALIST; Are you worried about how the markets might<br />
react during this week oE uncertainty?<br />
PM: No, no.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think Mr Peacock's delaying the<br />
inevitable by not conceding?<br />
PM: Well, that's for, that's for Mr Peacock and those<br />
&amp;" round him. Suffice it for me to conduct myself in the way<br />
that I think is eppropriate.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's required now for the rebuilding process<br />
here in Victoria?<br />
PM: Well, the understanding that next time round we'll win<br />
a lot Of these seats back, as I'm sure we will and I have<br />
already tried to speak to as many of the casualties as I<br />
could, there's two or three I've got to yet speak to, but<br />
I'm impressed by their commitment, which is an important<br />
port of the answer to your question. They haven't dropped </p>
<p>3, r-r-~ V V o10r-r-1CC C r1r4 0 T = L ' 1 -Q V~ Z:-T<br />
IIU I ILLLUUVI IL<br />
their bundle and I'm also impteased by the pride they have<br />
in Labor's national achievement. It really warmed me this<br />
morning to speak to these people who've been beaten and they<br />
recognise the particularity of Victoria, but they had a<br />
great sense of pride in Labor's national achievement and<br />
that was greet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is there any of those casualties that you're<br />
sorriest to see go?<br />
PM: No, that would be invidious to people. I have come in<br />
Sevenl years to appreciate all my colleagues. I mean it Is<br />
true that in the earlier stagea of our Government I guess<br />
the factionalism and the edges of factionalitm were a bit<br />
sharper then. But I've come to appreciate the merit * of all<br />
my colleagues and they have, in their various ways, I think,<br />
represented their constituencies very well, with commitment,<br />
with integrity and I'll miss them all.<br />
OOURNALIST: Mr Hawks, how do you think you'll be able to<br />
work with Ted Mack and Helen Caldiott if they're there?<br />
PM: The first thing that one must say to that, the degree<br />
of work that will need to be done with them will obviously<br />
depond upon the outcome in the number of seats. it our<br />
majority in part depended upon them we'll obviously have to<br />
get a very specific modis I am hopeful that we'll have<br />
a majority in out own right. But I will obviously take the<br />
opportunity at an appropriately early time to speak with<br />
them if they would want to speak with me and I think I'll be<br />
able to have a oivilised relationship with them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could Mrs Hawks tell us how she feels about the<br />
election result?<br />
MRS HAWKE: I feel Very happy about it. There's a tinge of<br />
sadness of course about Victoria but I think that nationally<br />
the Labor Party has done very well. And I think, in the<br />
end, I agree with Bob that they, they are pretty good<br />
Judges. ends -a% </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
