<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7416</transcript-id>
    <title>EMERGENCY RELIEF PROGRAM TO THE STATES</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007416.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER<br />FOR MEDIA 21 OCTOBER 1988<br />The Commonwealth has decided to take up the constructive<br />suggestion of the Premier of South Australia, John Bannon,<br />as a way of resolving a disagreement over the transfer of<br />the Emergency Relief Program to the States.<br />Emergency Relief is provided to people in immediate need for<br />ad hoc assistance. it is provided through voluntary<br />organisations with money supplied by both the Commonwealth<br />and the States.<br />Both the States and the Commonwealth had administrative<br />apparatus to support the program. In the interest of<br />removing administrative overlap the Commonwealth proposed to<br />transfer the program ' to the States at the last Premiers'<br />Conference with the continuing Commonwealth financial<br />support coming through general revenue assistance.<br />Several States objected on the grounds that Emergency Relief<br />is an income support program, and that they preferred<br />Commonwealth funds to be clearly identified.<br />Emergency relief programs have been run historically by the<br />States, whereas the Commonwealth has contributed to them<br />directly only recently. The involvement of two levels of<br />government in such programs leads to confusion in the minds<br />of potential recipients, and adds needlessly to the costs of<br />running welfare activities.<br />For these reasons, and in particular given the States,<br />continued representations to me to rationalise Commonwealth<br />administrative overlap with the States, it was sensible to<br />include Emergency Relief in the offer document for transfer<br />to the States at the Premiers' Conference.<br />Taking up Mr Bannon's suggestion that the program be<br />transferred by way of a specific purpose payment meets one-.<br />of the States' main concerns. The arrangement can commence<br />immediately, with funds allocated this financial year being<br />subject to future indexation, using the Consumer Price Index<br />as from 1989-90, so that real value is maintained.<br />Other than requiring that the money be used for payment to<br />non-government agencies for emergency relief, I would not<br />see the Commonwealth involved in program determination or<br />administration. It should be understood that the States<br />will maintain their effort in this area and that the above<br />represents the Commonwealth's financial limit. 2855</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
