<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8803</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DR HEWSON AND &quot;THE TAX CHEAT MENTALITY&quot;</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008803.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: 29. Jan. 93 12: 52 No. 011 P. 01/ 02<br />
-im<br />
PRIME MINISTER 11/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DR HEWSON AND " THE TAX CHEAT MENTALITY"<br />
It has been revealed today that Dr Hewson believes the<br />
tax minimisation scheme he was involved in amounts to, in<br />
his own" woTr-ds, ". 6tax cheatery."<br />
As part of an address to the National Press Club a little<br />
over a year ago Dr Hewson attacked the very practices of<br />
which he knew himself to be guilty.<br />
He described at length tax minimisation of the exact<br />
variety he was involved in 88 part of what he called " the<br />
tax cheat mentality" in Australia.<br />
For the past few days Dr Hewson has defended his tax<br />
minimisation practices.<br />
He and other Liberals have viciously attacked me and the<br />
Government for raising legitimate questions about a<br />
person who says it is okay for a wealthy person to<br />
minimise tax, while wage and salary earners must pay<br />
per cent on everything they buy.<br />
In his address he even attacked people who minimised tax<br />
to 15 per cent instead of paying the top rate of 47<br />
cents! He actually nominated the 15 per cent average tax<br />
rate.<br />
With all the compassion he could muster he bemoaned the<br />
fact that these opportunities were not available to the<br />
average PAYE taxpayer.<br />
He attacked those who used superannuation to minimise<br />
tax: " They want to talk about tax rorting, people are<br />
using superannuation as a basis of minimising tax<br />
pay 15 per cent on an employer contribution on<br />
superannuation and downther<br />
peK enLaidJon hatinnMe st11l rubtantial1y<br />
lass than the topax rate of 47 cents." </p>
<p>TEL: 29. Jan. 9 12: 52 No. 011 P. 02/ 02<br />
There was also scope for other minimisation practices, he<br />
said, but " those opportunities and a host of others are<br />
not available to the average PAYE taxpayer, they are part<br />
of the tax cheat mentality or tax minimisation mentality<br />
that exists in Australia."<br />
He knew when he was saying those words he was describing<br />
an arrangement which he had himself previously entered<br />
into. Dr Hewson's Press Club remarks reveal him as being<br />
totally insincere with the public end two-faced.<br />
CANBERRA January 29, 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
