<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6884</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006884.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 16 APRIL 1986<br />
The Australian Permanent Representative to the United Nations,<br />
His Excellency Mr Richard Woolcott, will make the following<br />
statement to the Security Council later today!<br />
" Australia speaks today mindful of the primary responsibility<br />
of the Security Council for the maintenance of international<br />
peace and security. World attention is focussed on this body<br />
and people around the world look to us to take positive action<br />
to achieve a peaceful resolution of the issue before us. We<br />
must respond effectively to the challenge.<br />
As tension has developed in the Central Mediterranean,<br />
Australia has continued to counsel restraint. As a matter<br />
of principle Australia rejects any attempts to resolve<br />
differences between nations by violent measures and in<br />
particular through terrorism. This is a principle which<br />
has guided the Australian Delegation in its approach to many<br />
of the issues which have come before this body.<br />
As the Prime Minister said on 15 April, the Australian<br />
Government deeply regrets that this conflict has taken place.<br />
We urge both sides to engage in genuine efforts to bring<br />
about the peaceful resolution of their differences.<br />
It will mean, as an absolute and essential condition, that<br />
Colonel Gaddafi terminate his Government's direction and<br />
export of, and support for, terrorist activity against<br />
civilians and civilian targets, such as have beeni perpetrated<br />
recently against United States civilians. This would also<br />
mean that the United States should desist from further<br />
military action against Libya.<br />
It was an occasion for some satisfaction when the Fortieth<br />
General Assembly adopted by consensus a resolution on measures<br />
to prevent international terrorism. That resolution unequivocally<br />
condemned as criminal all acts, methods and practices of<br />
terrorism wherever and by whomever committed. The resolution,<br />
I repeat, was adopted by consensus.<br />
And yet, terrorism has continued.<br />
The Australian Government accepts that there is a substantial<br />
body of evidence of Libyan involvement in and direction of<br />
international terrorism. This situation cannot continue.<br />
ti. 1 </p>
<p>We have all condemned such outrages. We have deplored the<br />
loss of innocent human lives and the poisoning of relations<br />
among States which result from these pernicious acts. We<br />
therefore stand ready to work with the whole membership of<br />
this organisation to bring international terrorism to an end.<br />
If terrorism cannot be rooted out, the international community<br />
faces a dark future of increasing violence. Already, the<br />
situation has reached the point where the United States has<br />
felt compelled by Libyan actions to regard it as essential to<br />
take military action. Threats of further violence have followed<br />
from several quarters. There have been some calls to arms, when<br />
the world should be calling for mediation, negotiation,<br />
conciliation in short a peaceful settlement.<br />
If we do not make a stand in favour of such peaceful means, we<br />
will be surrendering to an intensifying cycle of violence.<br />
Mr President, having stated the position of the Australian<br />
Government on the question before the Security Council, I now<br />
wish to move onto new ground.<br />
In this debate so far, we have heard a substantial number of<br />
interventions. These have attempted to establish the parameters<br />
of discussion. They have been deficient, however, in that they<br />
have not addressed clearly and sufficiently the question of wihat<br />
can be done to contain and stop this conflict and in<br />
particular what the Security Council can do to this end.<br />
If our work this week is not to be a complete failure, yet<br />
another sterile exchange without constructive end, it is<br />
necessary that all of us, members of the Council and members<br />
of the United Nations, should turn our minds actively and<br />
without further delay to the discharge of our responsibilities<br />
to avoid further tensions and to bring our deliberations to a<br />
constructive conclusion.<br />
The Security Council has wide powers in this regard under<br />
Chapter VI of the Charter. I mention Article 33 whereby<br />
the Council may call upon parties to settle their dispute<br />
by a variety of means, Article 34 whereby the Council<br />
may investigate any dispute, and Article 36 whereby the<br />
Council may at any stage recommend appropriate procedures. </p>
<p>Members of the Council may have difficulty agreeing upon the<br />
precise and total nature of the dispute. But there should be<br />
no question of disagreement that, within the purpose of the<br />
articles I have cited, the maintenance of international peace<br />
and security has been endangered. Article 36( 1) captures this<br />
point precisely in its reference to a dispute of the nature<br />
referred to in Article 33 " or of a situation of like nature"<br />
There is also a range of procedures available for the Council<br />
to pursue these objectives, which would merit urgent<br />
examination in the case before us. In saying this we have<br />
in mind the role the Secretary-General might play in this<br />
matter and Australia would naturally support any such<br />
endeavours by him.<br />
It is my objective now to press the Council to assume<br />
its responsibilities in this regard.<br />
I do not necessarily wish to make firm proposals as to the<br />
exact method that the Council itself might employ. That is<br />
for consideration and decision by members. But the Council<br />
needs to act constructively with the cooperation of the parties<br />
and it may assist the Council's deliberations if I identify a<br />
number of courses:<br />
the Security Council must play its part and I believe<br />
the President of the Council has the responsibility<br />
under the Charter to channel the Council's energy in<br />
constructive ways.<br />
The peaceful means of dispute settlement elaborated in<br />
Article 33 of the Charter are also worthy of careful<br />
consideration. Finally, Mr President, I note that the parties themselves<br />
could bring the dispute to a speedy end by making and<br />
strictly observing genuine and binding commitments to the<br />
Security Council about their future conduct. These<br />
commitments would include on the one hand a pledge<br />
concerning the strictest respect for and adherence<br />
to the terms of UNGA Res40/ 6&amp; whichunequivocally condemns<br />
terrorism and calls on all states to refrain from<br />
organising, instigating, assisting or participating in<br />
terrorist acts. They would also include on the other<br />
hand a reciprocal commitment to refrain from recourse<br />
to armed force. The Council could examine urgently how<br />
such commitments might be undertaken by the present<br />
parties and by all states concerned.<br />
Mr President, I have indicated that the Australian Government<br />
wishes the Council to move from the stage of debate to the<br />
stage of accepting its responsibilities to promote a peaceful<br />
settlement, on terms acceptable to the parties and to the<br />
world community.<br />
I suggest that you, Mr President, should institute and pursue<br />
consultations among member states to this end. You will have the<br />
full coooerat. ion of the Australian deleqat n in that endeavou." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
