<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18977</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of Interview with Sarah Hawke - ABC News 24</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/01/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Video Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PM: First and foremost people need to keep themselves safe. This is an ongoing situation so listen to local authorities, make sure that you're absorbing all of the local warnings.</p>
<p>We want to keep people safe.</p>
<p>For those that have lost their homes, a devastating experience, and we'll be working with them as will the state government to support people through.</p>
<p>There are media reports that a life has been lost. I'm not in a position to confirm that but bushfires are very dangerous things.</p>
<p>So right around the country we're seeing hot weather. Please keep yourselves safe. The one thing that's irreplaceable here is you. Make sure you're looking after your own safety.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: There are reports of about 85 homes that have been destroyed in Tasmania alone.</p>
<p>Is there any concept of what support may be offered at this stage, or is it just too early? What is the situation there?</p>
<p>PM: We're still at the stage where fighting the fire is the main focus.</p>
<p>We will move to the recovery stage, and when we do that of course there are payments and support that do flow and we'll be making announcements about that when we can at the appropriate point.</p>
<p>We want to make sure now as the fire's still there that people are safe, and then we'll support communities.</p>
<p>I've been in contact with our local member Dick Adams who is there working with the community.</p>
<p>Tassie's a strong place; really strong community bonds and I'm confident that people will work to support each other at this difficult time.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: And how often are you being kept updated? Is that through the authorities in Tasmania or more through  -  how's that being done?</p>
<p>PM: We have arrangements where our federal government officials work closely with state government officials.</p>
<p>We've had to do this on a lot of occasions unfortunately; Queensland floods, cyclone; we've had a lot of practice about how best to work together.</p>
<p>So the systems are very good and that means I get continuous feeds of information which is fantastic.</p>
<p>And I would like to say a word of thanks to everybody who's out there, whether it's the fire fighters on the front line or the officials who are somewhat further back but who are also working hard to make sure the emergency gets dealt with.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What are your thoughts when you see the pictures of the television coming through, particularly this morning?</p>
<p>PM: They always break your heart when you see those sorts of pictures.</p>
<p>I'm obviously from Victoria, we saw that huge loss of life in the Victorian bushfires, and the destructive power of fire is just so awesome, the actual destructive power of it.</p>
<p>So whenever you see those pictures, whenever you see that kind of loss it really does touch a chord in you.</p>
<p>It's a very Australian thing to fear and also to understand the devastation of bushfire.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST: And obviously monitoring across the other states as well at this stage?</p>
<p>PM: Well this extreme heat is very widespread and that means there are risks in more areas than Tasmania. The best thing people can do is stay in touch with their local authorities and local community warnings.</p>
<p>We do have more ways of getting information to people now, and that's a good thing, but it still means people need to take the information on board and respond to it.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
