<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7539</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, RADIO 3UZ, MELBURNE 22 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007539.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF DOORSTOP, RADIO 3UZ, MELBOURNE<br />
22 MARCH 1909<br />
R. 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: How much electoral damage do You think the<br />
airport decision will do to your Government? Will it<br />
threaLten your Government's survival?<br />
PM: No, I don't think it will threaten the survival<br />
but it is the case that in regard to a few seats around<br />
the airport there'll be some strong feelings. I believe<br />
that once the message gets out, which is the truth, that<br />
there will be a reduction in the number of Lhose affected<br />
by noise which will result from a combination of the;<br />
gradual introduction of quieter aircraft plus the virtual<br />
closing of the east-west runway when the parallel northsouth<br />
runway comes in. When those facts are understood<br />
and it's understood that we had the courage Lo take the<br />
decision which was in the interest of the country as<br />
a whole then I think it will be accepted. But thei ea-: y<br />
political decision would've been to go the other way.<br />
JOURNALIST: How many seats do you think you might lose?<br />
PM: I'm not saying that we'll lose any. I'm simply<br />
saying that it was a hard political decision to take.<br />
JOURNALIST: You must have advice that particular seats<br />
are in very gravo danger.<br />
PM: You don't need advice, you know that seats like<br />
Barton and St George, Phillip, Kingsford-Smith, Sydney<br />
to some extent, you know these are the seat~ s that are<br />
an issue where the question of the additional use of<br />
Kingsford-Smith airporL has been an issue. Now as I<br />
say, the easy thing for me to have done would've been<br />
to say I'm not going to run any risk. But we've been<br />
in Government for six years now and I think we've established<br />
a reputation of being prepared to take tough decisions<br />
in regard to issues which may initially be electoralY<br />
unpopular. I mean you don't get to the position of Prime<br />
Minister in this country at least I don't to take </p>
<p>2<br />
decisions which I think are against the interests of<br />
this country. At the present moment people are saying<br />
look at the high interest rates. The easy thitng we could<br />
say is yes,. let's have some low interest rates. But<br />
I know LliaL LhaL would be Liiu wrong devisioi for Lhis<br />
country. You've got to take the decisions which you<br />
believe are right for the country. In the end I have<br />
faith, as I've always had, in the good judgement of the<br />
Australian people, that they will understand that we're<br />
taking the right decisions.<br />
JOURNALIST:. You desperately need those seats and you<br />
also don't want high interest rates coming up to an election.<br />
So are those two factors going to affect your election<br />
timing?<br />
PM: They don't affect the election timing at all. I've<br />
said quite consistently that the sort of period that<br />
would be Involved is the sort of end of this year up<br />
until about the middle of next year. I've Just said<br />
on the program here Lhat I'm not looking at 1989 as an<br />
election year. Within that timeframe I said that you could<br />
thdve it. at. the end of the year. But I'm not thinking<br />
of 1989 as an election year.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
