<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6553</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH TO GOVERNMENT AIRCRAFT FACTORIES, AVALON, 16 NOVEMBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006553.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH TO GOVERNMENT AIRCRAFT FACTORIES -AVALON<br />
16 NOVEMBER 1984<br />
IT GIVES ME GREAT PLEASURE TO BE HERE TODAY TO CELEBRATE<br />
THE ROLL-OUT OF THE FIRST F/ A-18 HORNET ASSEMBLED IN<br />
AUSTRALIA, THIS AIRCRAFT HAS PROBABLY ATTRACTED MORE PRAISE THAN<br />
ANY PREVIOUS FIGHTER PLANE$<br />
IDON'T WISH TO COMPETE WITH THE SUPERLATIVES WHICH WERE<br />
LAVISHLY DISTRIBUTED AT THE HAND-OVER LAST MONTH IN<br />
ST Louis OF THE: FIRST RAAF HORNET. INSTEAD I WANT TO<br />
EMPHASISE THE G6* VERNMENT'S COMMITMENT TO THE UPGRADING<br />
OF AUSTRALIA'S DEFENCE CAPABILITY AND THE'ROLE IN THIS<br />
PROGRAM OF THE F/ A-18.<br />
PROVIDING FOR NATIONAL DEFENCE IS THE MOST FUNDAMENTAL OF<br />
ALL GOVERNMENT RESPONSIBILITIES.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS ADDRESSING THIS RESPONSIBILITY IN A<br />
SENSITIVE AND EFFECTIVE MANNER$ / 2.01. </p>
<p>A<br />
FIRST, WE HAVE GIVEN VERY HIGH PRIORITY TO PROMOTING<br />
FRIENDLY AND CO-OPERATIVE RELATIONS WITH AND AMONG THE<br />
COUNTRIES IN OUR IMMEDIATE REGION, THOSE RELATIONS TODAY<br />
ARE MARKED BY AN UNPRECEDENTED DEGREE OF CLOSENESS AND<br />
MUTUAL CONFIDENCE. THIS IS AN IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
REDUCING THE RISK OF ARMED CONFLICT.<br />
SECOND, WE HAVE SUPPORTED MEASURES THAT PROMOTE A STABLE<br />
INTERNATIONAL ORDER, ESPECIALLY THE STABILITY OF THE<br />
STRATEGIC NUCLEAR BALANCE, WE HAVE DONE THIS THROUGH:<br />
PROMOTING EFFECTIVE ARMS CONTROdL AND DISARMAMENT<br />
MEASURES. LABOR WILL NEVER CONTEMPLATE'* A NUCLEAR<br />
WEAPONS OPTION FOR THIS COUNTRYj<br />
THROUGH EtiSURING THAT ANZUS IS A CLOSE AND<br />
' EFFECTIVE PARTNERSHIP;<br />
AND THROUGH OUR INVOLVEMENT IN INTERNATIONAL<br />
PEACEKEEPING OPERATIONS IN SITUATIONS OF ACUTE<br />
INTERNATIONAL TENSION.<br />
THIRD, THERE is AUSTRALIA'S DEFENCE EFFORT ITSELF. HERE<br />
WE ASPIRE TO A CAPABILITY THAT IS VISIBLY DEFENSIVE AND<br />
SUFFICIENTLY POTENT TO BE A CREDIBLE DETERRENT. / 34 0 a </p>
<p>IN GOVERNMENT WE HAVE INCREASELD DEFENCE SPENDINC SUBSTANTiALLY, iT IS<br />
OUR FIRM INTENTION TO MAINTAIN SIGNIFICANT GROWTH IN DEFENCE SPENDING AND<br />
A GREATER DEGREE OF DEFENCE SELF-RELIANCE.<br />
IN OUR FIRST TWO BUDGETS WE HAVE INCREASED DEFENCE EXPENDITURE AT AN<br />
AVERAGE RATE OF ABOUT 3.7 PER CENT IN REAL TERMS. THIS COMPARES WITH<br />
AN AVERAGE INCREASE UNDER THE FRASER GOVERNMENT OF ABOUT 2.5 PER CENT.<br />
THIS SHOWS THE NONSENSE OF OUR OPPONENTS' TALK ABOUT OUR SO-CALLED ' CUTS'<br />
IN DEFENCE SPENDING. THE FACT IS THAT UNDER LABOR DEFENCE SPENDING HAS<br />
INCREASED MORE RAPIDLY THAN UNDER OUR PREDECESSORS.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT IS TAKING ADVANTAGE OF OUR CURRENT FAVOURABLE SECURITY<br />
OUTLOOK TO CONCENTRATE ON INVESTMENTS THAT WILL CONSOLIDATE AND ENHANCE<br />
OUR DEFENCE CAPABILITY OVER THE LONGER TERM PARTICULARLY INVESTMENTS<br />
IN MAJOR EQUIPMENT AND FACILITIES.<br />
THE F/ A-18s ARE PERHAPS THE MOST IMPRESSIVE AND TANGIBLE EXPRESSION<br />
OF THIS POLICY TO DATE. THEY WILL MAKE A MAJOR CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
OUR ABILITY TO PRESENT OURSELVES AS A FORMIDABLE AND INDEPENDENT<br />
DEFENCE PRESENCE IN OUR REGION.<br />
THE VERSATILITY OF THE F/ A-18s, AS A TACTICAL FIGHTER, IN ALL<br />
WEATHER CONDITIONS, ITS MANOEUVRABILITY AND ITS EASE OF<br />
MAINTENANCE ALL MAKE IT PARTICULARLY SUITED TO OUR. NEEDS,<br />
THIS AIRCRAFT IS ALSO IN THE FOREFRONT OF TECHNOLOGY AND, BECAUSE<br />
OF ITS ADVANCED DESIGN, WILL BE ASSURED OF LONG SERVICE WITH THE<br />
RAAF. s </p>
<p>THE INTRODUCTION OF THE F/ A-18 INTO THE RAAF WILL ALSO<br />
GREATLY BENEFIT THE AUSTRALIAN DEFENCE INDUSTRY. THIS<br />
IS BY FAR THE LARGEST SINGLE DEFENCE PROJECT EVER<br />
MANAGED IN AUSTRALIA AND IT WILL PROVIDE THE DOMINANT<br />
WORKLOAD FOR THE AUSTRALIAN AIRCRAFT INDUSTRY FOR QUITE A<br />
FEW YEARS TO COME.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN AEROSPACE INDUSTRY IS ALSO BENEFITTING<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY FROM THE F/ A-18 PROGRAM. THE GOVERNMENT IS<br />
PROVIDING CAPITAL INFRASTRUCTURE AND TRAINING TO THE<br />
VALUE OF $ 94.5 MILLION FOR THE MANUFACTURE OF COMPONENT<br />
PARTS, AND FOR THE ASSEMBLY OF ENGINES AND AIRCRAFT.<br />
THIS WORK, AND ASSOCIATED OFFSET WORK, WILL INVOLVE SOME<br />
2,000 JOBS IN THE INDUSTRY OVER THE NEXT 10 YEARS1<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN BUILDING INDUSTRY WILL ALSO BENEFIT FROM<br />
THE PROJECT AS THERE WILL BE EXTENSIVE WORK THIS YEAR TO<br />
PREPARE THE RAAF BASE AT WILLIAMTOWN, NSW, FOR THE<br />
INTRODUCTION OF THE F/ A-18 AND TO RF-DEVELOP THE RAAF BASE<br />
AT TINDAL IN THE NORTHERN TERRITORY.<br />
IN THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A NEW LEVEL OF SECURITY FOR THE<br />
NORTH AND FOR AUSTRALIA AS A WHOLE, THE F/ A-18 WILL PLAY<br />
A VITAL ROLE FOR MANY YEARS TO COME.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT AIRCRAFT FACTORIES AND ALL THOSE ASSOCIATED<br />
WITH THIS PROJECT CAN BE PROUD OF THEIR CONTRIBUTION TO<br />
THAT ACHIEVEMENTI </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
