<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40022</transcript-id>
    <title>Visit to New Zealand</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Next week I go to New Zealand to meet Prime Minister Key on my first international trip as Prime Minister. It is appropriate that my first destination is New Zealand.</p>
<p>Australia and New Zealand have a close relationship thanks to our shared history, deep economic integration and our close work together on regional and international issues. This year we commemorated a defining moment in our relationship with the centenary of ANZAC.</p>
<p>On 17 October, Prime Minister Key and I will discuss a range of bilateral and international issues, including further deepening our bilateral relationship, engagement with our Pacific neighbours, combating terrorism and the situation in Iraq and Syria. We will discuss priorities for upcoming summits including the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) meeting, the East Asia Summit and the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting (CHOGM).</p>
<p>We will discuss climate change, a critical issue of importance globally, and particularly for our Pacific neighbours, ahead of the UN climate change Conference of Parties in Paris later this year.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Key and I will place high priority on advancing issues of importance to the deep economic, trade and investment relationship shared between our two countries. We will also discuss the movement of our citizens between Australia and New Zealand.</p>
<p>In 2014-15, trans-Tasman goods and services trade was valued at around $23.4 billion. Australia is New Zealand’s largest investor, with Australia’s total investments in New Zealand in 2014 totalling $99.9 billion.</p>
<p>I look forward to meeting Prime Minister Key. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
