<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2157</transcript-id>
    <title>MR WHITLAM&#039;S APOLOGIA - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/01/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002157.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 3/ 1970<br />
MR. WHITLAM'S APOLOGIA<br />
Statement by the Prime Mvinister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. Whitlam is clearly trying to extricate himself from<br />
the result of those indiscretions which have led native leaders in New<br />
Guinea to tell him to pack up and go home and cease fermenting trouble.<br />
The facts are that Mr. Whitlam made a flying visit to a<br />
troubled area the Gazelle Peninsula. Once there he engaged in illconsidered<br />
demagogy and increased the chances of trouble and violence<br />
in that area. He deepened and worsened the divisions among the Tolai<br />
people divisions which the Government has been seeking to heal. He<br />
spoke to one section of the Tolai people and left the impression, in an<br />
unsophisticated area, that he and the people of Australia supported not<br />
only the aims but the methods including violence to which that section<br />
has resorted. He refrained from calming the fears felt by some of the<br />
Tolai that their land may be endangered by the multi-racial Council. Yet<br />
he must know this fear to be baseless.<br />
He must have known that the Administrator and Government<br />
officials were subjected to violence when they went to the area to " listen"<br />
and to discuss this problem. Yet he publicly admires the " fervour" of<br />
those who used that violence.<br />
Either through foolishness or by design he has made a<br />
, difficult situation worse. He has refused to support what he calls<br />
" technical legality" and has instead tacitly encouraged clearly illegal<br />
action. If this results in greater violence and Australia's name is<br />
thereby damaged he will to a very large degree be responsible if<br />
responsible is a word which can properly be used in relation to his actions<br />
in this matter. The Government will seek to remove the fears felt by a<br />
section of the Tolais, to relieve the difficulties in the region, and to<br />
repair the damage done by this visit. But this will now be more difficult.<br />
CANBERRA 12 January 1970 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
