<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7624</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR, 5 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007624.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
57-<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JANA WENDT, A CURRENT AFFAIR,<br />
JUNE 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
WENDT: Australia has already lodged a formal protest with<br />
the Chinese over the brutal suppresion of the Beijing<br />
students and Prime Minister Bob Hawke has called off a<br />
planned visit to China later this year. But the Federal<br />
Government has stopped short of severing diplomatic links or<br />
imposing trade sanctions. The Prime Minister joins us now<br />
live from Parliament House in Canberra. Mr Hawke thank you<br />
for your time this evening.<br />
PM: My pleasure.<br />
WENDT: You have expressed our disapproval as a nation for<br />
what's happened in China. Can I ask you how you feel<br />
personally about all this?<br />
PM: I feel a sense of tragedy Jana, tragedy for the people<br />
that have been killed and injured, a sense of tragedy for<br />
the nation of China because this has in one blow smashed in<br />
a sense all the goodwill that over the last few years China<br />
has accumulated by the opening up of its doors, the change<br />
of direction, its economic policies, the gradual appearance<br />
of a more open society.<br />
WENDT: Do you think we've been misguided in thinking that<br />
China is changing?<br />
PM: No I don't think we have. The world has taken the view<br />
on the evidence that the changes have been for the better.<br />
In economic terms it's had a more open economy. There has<br />
been more of a market economy. There has been more openings<br />
to the West. There have been more joint ventures. There's<br />
been the introduction of more technology from the West.<br />
There's been more cooperation. And while the economic<br />
opening up and freeing up of the system has not been<br />
accompanied by the same degree of opening on the political<br />
front, nevertheless it has become a relatively to what it<br />
was before a freer society.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke what more can we do as a nation tonight?<br />
PM: I think what we have to do is to keep our people there<br />
so that we can both continue directly from our people there<br />
to make our position clear and also to monitor the situation<br />
so that we can be as well informed as we possibly can. We </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM ( cont): have approximately 500 people in China this is<br />
not just Embassy people but people who are there at the<br />
Embassy, students, business people, approximately 500<br />
Australians permanently there, and we have to see that their<br />
interests are guarded and watched and I don't think it makes<br />
sense for Australia Jana, or for any other western country<br />
to pull out their diplomatic representation. But what is<br />
necessary is that we make clear in the strongest and most<br />
unequivocal terms our repudiation of the violence and the<br />
tragedy and to put to the authorities of China, the ageing<br />
authorities of China, that force can never provide a lasting<br />
resolution of the sorts of problems that they see themselves<br />
confronted with.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke this is a shocking death toll. Isn't it<br />
time for us to do something more like trade sanctions for<br />
instance?<br />
PM: No I don't think anyone in a country in the world is<br />
yet contemplating that sort of approach. You've got to<br />
understand the economic framework of China that exports<br />
constitute only about 14% of their level of production.<br />
They are relatively well placed in terms of their reserves.<br />
They have reserves that would cover the best part of 6<br />
months of imports. So I don't think that makes sense at<br />
tahuitsh orsittaigee. s arJea nan ott hagto idnoge stno ' tc ommee ant o thtahte iri f sethnes esC hiannde sechange<br />
direction and that we get an acceleration of violence that<br />
we together with the rest of the world may not have to<br />
contemplate different sorts of action.<br />
WENDT: So some action is possible in that regard. Let me<br />
just ask you quickly, what about those 13,000 or so Chinese<br />
students in Australia who have so far stuck their necks out<br />
in support of the demonstrations, what can we do for them if<br />
they seek political asylum?<br />
PM: Firstly let me say I think they are courageous in<br />
making it clear their identification with their colleagues<br />
in China. I commend them for their courage because in a<br />
sense there is a risk. At this stage the question of asylum<br />
has not arisen and we will have to look at that further down<br />
the track if you have a situation where you had a worsening<br />
of the position in China and these people here were able to<br />
establish that they would be at risk. But that's down the<br />
track Jana.<br />
WENDT: Prime Minister if you'd like to stay with us, after<br />
the break we'd like to look at an issue much closer to home<br />
and that is rising interest rates. We'll be back with more<br />
in a moment. ( break)<br />
WENDT: Prime Minister Hawke is still with us in Canberra<br />
and he has agreed to watch this report on one street in the<br />
mortgage belt where interest rates have hit hardest. Prime<br />
Minister, do those people have a legitimate gripe? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: Of course they do. I understand their position and I<br />
hope that they will understand when I say that I understand<br />
that there is no way Jana, and I say this directly to those<br />
people, there is no way that I would have interest rates at<br />
this level for a day longer than was necessary. We don't<br />
have them there for fun Jana, we don't have them there on<br />
the basis of saying well we know that people there, out in<br />
Kingsgrove Street, are going to be hurt. You don't do it<br />
for that reason. The problem that we have is that we have<br />
an economy which has been growing so fast with so many new<br />
jobs being created and so much investment taking place which<br />
is creating new jobs that we've reached a point where we<br />
have to bring back that level of activity. Because we can't<br />
afford, Jana, as a nation we can't afford to keep up that<br />
level of activity any longer. The only way that we've got<br />
to bring down that level of activity is for some time to<br />
have interest rates fairly high.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, it's pretty clear from what those people<br />
are saying that your explanation just now means nothing to<br />
them. PM: I can understand that. If I were in their position I<br />
would be hurt, I would be angry and I would be looking to<br />
take it out on the Government. I can understand that, I'm<br />
not bitter about them. I'm simply asking them to believe me<br />
when I say this, that if we were to lower interest rates<br />
now, artificially, then the result for them and for all<br />
Australians would be very much worse, because I tell you<br />
what would happen. What would happen is that the dollar<br />
would plunge and in that situation you would then have<br />
interest rates which would go right through the roof, far<br />
worse than they are now.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke, those people are saying that you and your<br />
Treasurer are responsible for creating the economic<br />
circumstances whereby those interest rates are so<br />
astronomically high now.<br />
PM: If I can answer that, and if you'll let me answer it,<br />
let me say this. Of-course the Government is responsible<br />
for economic policy. We are also responsible in the conduct<br />
of that economic policy over the six years we've been in<br />
office for creating 1,400,000 jobs.<br />
WENDT: Mr. Hawke, if I can interrupt you, it really doesn't<br />
mean anything to those people that we're talking about now.<br />
PM: Jana, you say, I mean I get half an answer out, let me<br />
please make the point, I mean you are saying they say I'm<br />
responsible and my Government's responsible for what's<br />
happened in this country. We are, they are right. What I'm </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( cont): trying to say, put it in the perspective that we<br />
have been responsible for massive economic growth and<br />
unfortunately the growth which has been reflected in the<br />
massive increase in jobs is now simply too high and we do<br />
have to rein back that level of growth.<br />
WENDT: Well, can I say to you that the plumber and the<br />
public servant and the truck driver and the policeman in<br />
that story don't buy that argument. They are hurting. They<br />
are people who are not asking for more money, they are<br />
saying we simply can't make it any more because of what the<br />
Government has done to us.<br />
PM: Well, you say they are not asking for more money. In a<br />
sense, the community has been and we are delivering on that.<br />
Next month, if you take, let me take an average family,<br />
average weekly earnings and with one income and with two<br />
kids, they will be getting another $ 24 a week as a result of<br />
the tax cuts.<br />
WENDT: But Mr Hawke, even your Treasurer is saying that<br />
those tax cuts will be eaten up to a certain degree by these<br />
increasing interest rates.<br />
PM: There is no doubt about that. Of course to some extent<br />
the increases in money that they receive, about $ 24 a week<br />
on average, of course that will be partially eaten up by<br />
increases in interest rates, I understand that. I'm simply<br />
making the point that as a result of the combination of<br />
policies, there are jobs, these people are in work, they are<br />
going to get very substantial tax cuts which tax cuts will<br />
add up, on average, to over $ 100 a month.<br />
WENDT: But to some of those people, those tax cuts you<br />
understand are meaningless.<br />
PM: Well, look, $ 100 a month coming in can't be<br />
meaningless.<br />
WENDT: Well, some of these people have had their mortgages<br />
rise by $ 120 in a couple of those cases.<br />
PM: OK, I accept<br />
WENDT: There goes the tax cut.<br />
PM: I accept what they say, but on average, around<br />
Australia the tax cuts that people will be getting will more<br />
than offset, on average, the increases in interest rates.<br />
Now, look, I want those people to understand we haven't been<br />
conducting economic policy to create more jobs, to have<br />
Australia growing, on the basis then that we want to hurt<br />
people, we want to help people, but the only way now that we<br />
can help people is by calling some sort of a halt to the<br />
rate of growth that we've got, Jana. So this is not going<br />
to last forever, we've got to have it for a while to rein<br />
back the level of activity and when that happens, then<br />
interest rates will be coming down. </p>
<p>WENDT: Well, Mr Hawke, they've heard you say that before.<br />
You told them back in January that interest rates would fall<br />
and they're still waiting.<br />
PM: Well, I understand that. The rate of growth in the<br />
economy has surprised not only the Government, but every<br />
economic commentator in this country. The rate of growth,<br />
the continued expansion, has been beyond what everyone<br />
expected and so we have to now haul that back. I simply say<br />
to those people, I'm thinking all the time, all the time,<br />
there's not a day goes past when I don't direct my thinking<br />
to what's the range of things that we can do so that we can<br />
get the right policies in place, the tight policy, so that<br />
as soon as possible those interest rates will be coming<br />
down. I just express the hope that in that period we've<br />
got, the next few months, when the tax cuts will be coming<br />
in, that that will enable them to hold the line and then<br />
holding the line with those tax cuts within a situation then<br />
when interest rates will come down.<br />
WENDT: Mr Hawke we will have to leave it there I'm afraid.<br />
I do appreciate your time this evening.<br />
PM: Thank you very much indeed Jana.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
