<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12737</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP  DOORSTOP AT CLARIDGES HOTEL, LONDON   </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/04/2002</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: paying respects to the Queen Mother.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE...........  </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It was a very impressive occasion - the extraordinary public turnout just self-evidently from all sections of the community.  The Usher of the Black Rod remarked to me that of all the tens of thousands of people who had filed through not one mobile telephone had gone off and that probably is as good a metaphor - as good a modern metaphor - as any for the regard that people have for the occasion.  I think it';s a very interesting and obviously an unambiguous response from the British public and also of course from many Commonwealth visitors. I';m glad I';ve been able to come to represent Australia.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What did you observe of the other British citizens who were filing through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, as I say it was everybody.  All ages and people - a different racial mix.  Seemed to be representative of the entire country which was very interesting.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Someone gave you some flowers did they Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.  A dear lady came up to me and said ‘I love your country'; and she kissed me on the cheek and gave me the flowers.  So it was pretty touching. She';s got every reason to love Australia - it';s a great country.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you notice whether there were any Australians in the crowd?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don';t know.  I mean it';s sometimes hard to tell, particularly on an occasion like that where people don';t feel they can be as demonstrative as they normally are.  It';s hardly the occasion for people to call out ‘Hi John!'; - not really - perhaps outside.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Thank you Prime Minister</p>
<p>[ends] </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
