<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4900</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE VICTORIAN YOUNG LIBERALS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004900.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
LtBARGO 1.30 p. m.<br />
PRIMIE MINISTER 7<br />
FOR PRESS 26 NOVEMBER 1978<br />
ADDRESS TO THE VICTORIAN YOUN,\ G LIBERALS<br />
It's very good to be here today, and sDeaking at this venue.<br />
know that the economy is improving, that confidence is increasing<br />
and that we have made major social reforms, but I never thought<br />
that I'd be able to say that the Liberals have arrived at Camelot.<br />
Outside this building, however, there are still a great many<br />
things to achieve, and this Party, with its commritment with its<br />
philosophy, and its policies will achieve them.<br />
We will achieve them because our primary concern as a Party<br />
is with people with people's gifts and talents, and<br />
their right to develop them to the full; with people's freedom<br />
to determine their own lives arnd the life of this country;<br />
with people's right to take risks and be rewarded for success;<br />
with people's need for help and ' compassion when in difficulty help<br />
which does not diminish their dignity but enhances it.<br />
We believe that it is people that are valuable, that it is people's<br />
opportunities that should be expanded, not the power and intrusiveness<br />
of the state. As John Stuart Mill said, " A state that dwarfs its<br />
men in order that they may be more docile instruments in its<br />
hands even for beneficial purposes will find that with<br />
small men no great thing can be accomplished."<br />
The Liberal idea is a stable, humane and civilised society, a<br />
society enriched by a diversity of cultures and lifestyles, a<br />
society unified by a national purpose and identity, a society in<br />
which people can accomplish great things.<br />
The Liberal tradition has been an inspiration to social reform in<br />
Australia for a century. It was the Liberals who introduced:<br />
votes for women and eighteen year olds; the secret ballot;<br />
the arbitration system; old age pensions; tariff protection for<br />
local industry; and Commonwealth funding for education.<br />
Under this Government we have introduiced such fundamental reforms<br />
as family allowances, the indexation of pensions, tax indexation and<br />
revenue sharing with the States. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
The fundamental commitment of the Liberal tradition, a belief<br />
in people and their potential, their creativity, is as<br />
important to the future of our country and to this Stateas<br />
it has ever been. That's why it's so important that we<br />
win the election coming up in Victoria. That's why Victorian<br />
Young Liberals) with their commitment to Liberalism shoulddo<br />
their utmost to return the government. It's not a matter<br />
of power for power's sake it's a matter of-whether Victoria is<br />
governed by a Party committed to people, or by a Party committed<br />
to imposing a stifling and corrosive ideology.<br />
Frankly, it would be astounding if a Party that had been in governmen<br />
for over two decades did not have its rough patches. But make no<br />
mistake about it the yawning gap between the principles of the<br />
Liberal Party and those of the A. L. P. is just as wide as it has ever<br />
been. Liberals are committed to curbing the power of big government, to<br />
checking the encroachments of the bureaucracy. The A. L. P. wants<br />
more government more intrusive bureaucracy.<br />
In Victoria, the A. L. P. has again reaffirmed without any qualificatic<br />
its desire to socialise the means of production, distribution and<br />
exchange. Just two weeks ago, the State A. L. P. refused to amend<br />
the original 1921 wording of their policy on nationalisation.<br />
What a decisive step forward into the future that was.<br />
The Liberals are committed to individual freedom, and have supported<br />
the cause of Soviet defenders of human rights. At its conference<br />
a fortnight ago, the Labor Party in Victoria refused to condemn the<br />
Soviet Government's infringements of human rights.<br />
Despite the mountains of evidence from objective, impartial sources,<br />
the. A. L. P. preferred to believe the official Soviet line.<br />
The Liberals have been forging new policies, which are meeting<br />
today's challenges. The A. L. P. is still caught up in the toils<br />
of old dogma, failed policies discredited plans.' It's no wonder<br />
that Labor has consistently adopted a negative approach to<br />
Australia's future. Mr Hayden has called the 1980' s " the decade<br />
of despair"~," the decade of gloom", " the dismal decade." The only<br />
phrase Mr Hayden has not yet used is " a decade of doom.'' and<br />
with the Labor -Party looking down the barrel of ten years and more<br />
of Opposition, I've no doubt we'll see that phrase creep into<br />
Mr Hayden's vocabulary before long.<br />
We utterly reject the Labor Party's policy of defeatism and<br />
despondency. We reject their policies, which generated an<br />
explosion of prices, wages and government spending, which<br />
gravely weakened the economy. .13 </p>
<p>J 3.<br />
One of the first tasks we faced was to get inflation down, and<br />
governments around the world are coming to accept the<br />
correctness of this priority. For instance, the British Labor<br />
Prime Minister, Mr Callaghan, said in October:<br />
" The beginning for the Government is now do we keep inflation<br />
down? " It is the Government's inescapable responsibility to keep<br />
down inflation, not against anybody, but in the interests<br />
of the whole of the people of this country."<br />
We have already had great success in reducing inflation,<br />
and by maintaining our policies we will force inflation further<br />
down. The more we can get inflation down, the more quickly we<br />
implement the programmes that will realise our goals for Australia.<br />
The goals for which we are striving are not pie-in-the-sky,<br />
or unrealistic. As Liberals, we have a vision of Australia's<br />
future. Our vision is of an Australia which is a country of growth<br />
and developrrent; of prosperity and enlightenment, of stability<br />
and security, of compassion and effective help for those in need.<br />
A country in which the quality of freedom and opportunity for<br />
individuals has no equal anywhere.<br />
To make this vision a reality, the actions of government, of<br />
voluntary organisations, of individual Australians, must be spurred<br />
forward by a common commitment, J; eading us to be a more caring,<br />
more responsible, more creative, more tolerant, more<br />
self-reliant nation.<br />
After three years of Liberal government, we have already<br />
started on the road to realising this great ideal. It is our goal<br />
to build a vigorous economy, strengthened through the initiative<br />
and capacity of its people, and through emphasis on competition<br />
and private initiative rather than government restrictions.<br />
We are making progress towards this goal. Lower inflation is making<br />
our industry competitive again. Manufacturers are looking again<br />
to export markets.<br />
I know that at least one major motor vehicle manufacturer is<br />
rebuilding its export organisation, and an industry survey found that<br />
during the September quarter Australian exporters of manufactured<br />
goods reported an increase of 5 percent in export deliveries<br />
the first reported upturn since September 1972.<br />
Mining and oil exploration and development are rising sharply.<br />
Two companies alone have committed themselves to spending<br />
$ 1,000 million in Bass Strait and off Western Australia, directly<br />
because of the Goverrnent's realistic energy and oil pricing policy.<br />
Our goal is a society in which satisfying work is available to those<br />
who seek it, a society in which Australian Youth * can realise their<br />
aspirations to live a fulfilling life doing productive creative<br />
work. A4 </p>
<p>Our economic policies are establishing the foundations of a stror1<br />
and diversified economy which will meet these needs. We reject<br />
the self-serving and defeatist pessimism of the Labor Party<br />
the creators of unemployment in this country, the men who now<br />
hypocritically and falsely talk about a lost generation.<br />
The facts are there if they would only face up to them. Last year,<br />
about 250,000 young people left school, according to surveys<br />
by the Australian Bureau of Statistics. By February 1978,<br />
135,000 had already found work; by September this had risen<br />
to 180,000; 40,000 young people either continued their education<br />
or did not seek employment. This means that of 1978' s original<br />
250,000 school leavers, 30,000 had not'found jobs by<br />
September this year. What is more, by October, no more than 17,500 of<br />
last year's school leavers were registered with the C. E. S.<br />
This number is far too large but to talk as Labor persists<br />
in doing of a lost generation is in utter.-defiance of the facts.<br />
For those of our young people that do need help in getting<br />
a job, for those of our young people that need training or job<br />
experience, we have a coherent and extensive network of training<br />
programmes. Overall, the Government is spending $ 240 million on<br />
employment and training.<br />
Our NEAT Scheme, the Special Youth Employment Training Programme,<br />
and a number of other programmes are providing meaningful help<br />
to those who do not have jobs particularly to the young unemployed.<br />
At the end of October 1978, six times as many people were being<br />
trained under NEAT as at the end of December 1975, and we have<br />
changed NEAT to give a much greater emphasis to on-the-job training<br />
training more directly related'to industries' needs.<br />
Our programmes to assist young people include the introduction of<br />
a Special Youth Employment Thaining Programme. More than 80,000<br />
young people have already been assisted by this programme, since<br />
it was introduced in October 1976, and there are'another 35,000<br />
people in training under the scheme at the moment.<br />
A further 45,000 young people have been assisted under the<br />
Community Youth Support Scheme and the Educational Programme<br />
for Unemployed Youth has provided remedial education assistance<br />
for over 3,600 young people who have never had a fair go in their<br />
whole lives. In all, more than 300,000 people have been helped<br />
through these schemes.<br />
We have never been for one moment complacent about these schemes,<br />
and in the next few weeks, Tony Street will have a complete review<br />
of the various training programmes before Cabinet. If the,<br />
programmes can be effectively improved, if they can be expanded,<br />
if they can be developed, they certainly will be.<br />
We are also awaiting the report of the inquiry under Professor<br />
Williams.. which was set up in October 1976. That inquiry was<br />
established because we were concerned to make sure that our<br />
educational system was adequately designed to meet the educational<br />
needs and preferences of the individual and the requirements of the<br />
labour market. The results of that long and difficult inquiry should<br />
be available shortly, and we are looking for a constructive report<br />
which will clearly involVe the states and many sections of the<br />
community in its implementation. </p>
<p>7<br />
It is our goal, in cooperation with the States, to take new<br />
initiatives to secure Australia's future growth and development.<br />
Just three weeks ago, the Commonwealth and the States, showing a<br />
common commitment and a common purpose, agreed that for the first<br />
time state authorities can borrow over $ 1,700 million overseas<br />
to develop such essential facilities as railways, ports, power<br />
projects, water supplies and pipelines.<br />
For Victoria, this will meanfurther progress for the crucial Loy<br />
Yang power project, and a new world trade centre in Melbourne<br />
which will bring business and capital to the State and to Australia.<br />
Our goal is to help people buy their own homes, and because of our<br />
success in combating inflation, interest on housing loans have<br />
been falling. In the course of this year, home interest rates<br />
have fallen by 1 percent. On a home loan of say $ 25,000, being<br />
repaid over 25 years this means a saving in the order of $ 17 a<br />
month $ 5,000 over the period of the loan. In a full year,<br />
this is a total saving of around $ 150 million to families with<br />
home loans.<br />
Our goal is to provide effective and compassionate assistance to<br />
those in need and government welfare programmes are constantly<br />
being re-designed to achieve this end. By introducing the<br />
family allowance by indexing pensions , by reforming the outdated<br />
means test, by providing a completely new deal for the<br />
handicapped, by extending the supporting parent's benefit to sole<br />
fathers, this Government has al~ eady established a record of<br />
innovation and compassion in its welfare services.<br />
As a result of the Galbally Report, new programmes are being<br />
introduced for our migrant and ethnic communities which will provide<br />
a real breakthrough in overcoming the language barrier, and helping<br />
newly arrived migrants to adjust quickly and smoothly to Australian<br />
society. Our goal is a free and civilised society in which the basic rights<br />
of our citizens are protected. We are working towards a society<br />
in which justice is available to all, in which the rule of law prevailE<br />
for all; in which minorities have no cause for fear; in which<br />
bureaucracies are responsive to people's needs, and there is<br />
redress for ill-considered decisions by public servants.<br />
Our goal is a society in which employers and employees thrash<br />
out their differences through consultation and conciliation,<br />
working together for the benefit for employees, management,<br />
shareholders and consumers alike.<br />
At the same time, we recognise that where conciliation fails,<br />
the rule of law must prevail. The reforms already introduced in<br />
industrial law have made significant advances by providing<br />
protection for conscientious objectors, by introducing secret postal<br />
ballots for union elections, by requiring unions to have their<br />
accounts audited and report regularly to their membership, by<br />
establishin g the Industrial Relations Bureau and the National Labour<br />
Consultative Council. / 16 </p>
<p>Our goal is to find solutions to the problems created by our<br />
complex industrial society. Together with the States and<br />
voluntary welfare organisations, we are acting to meet the problems<br />
of drug abuse, of family breakdown of frustration and alienation.<br />
Our goal is a healthy Australia with health services equal to any<br />
in the world, provided at a reasonable cost -with the consumer<br />
retaining a right of choice. The substantial reforms we<br />
have made in health insurance and preventive medicine have advanced<br />
Australia a significant distance towards this goal.<br />
Our aim is for Australia to enjoy a high sta. ndard of education,<br />
which encourages Australians to be inventive, constructive and<br />
Self-reliant; which meets with the needs of out multi-cultural<br />
society; and which provides all Australians with indispensable.<br />
basic skills.<br />
The steady improvements which have been achieved will continue.<br />
We have made significant progress in the last three years.<br />
The goals to which we aspire will be achieved. But this is not just<br />
a job for Government. What we must all do is to relate these goals<br />
to our daily lives. In some cases, some fundamental rethinking is<br />
required. Let us look at a few examples. It is the goal of all Australians<br />
to see that jobs are available for those looking for work.<br />
It is time union leaders showed . real concern for the unemployed by<br />
restraining their wage claims, so that working men and women stop<br />
being priced out of the labour market.<br />
All Australians believe that tHe handicapped should receive a fair<br />
deal. It is time more employers showed real concern for the<br />
handicapped by finding them work as vacancies occur.<br />
We all believe that Australia should grow and develop in strength and<br />
prosperity. It is time all Australians encouraged and welcomed<br />
the generation of healthy profits by business and industry<br />
the profits that are essential to investment, the profits that<br />
are essential to jobs. We all believe we live in a great country<br />
it is time we stopped knocking Australia.<br />
Our nation has the undoubted capacity to achieve the goals and<br />
aspirations we share. We ask only one thing of this nation for<br />
the men and women of Australia to recognise their common interests,<br />
to recognise that by working together with determination and<br />
unity of purpose, these goals can be attained.<br />
In realising this promise, in achieving these goals, the Government<br />
seeks a partnership with the community, between Commonwealth, State<br />
and local government; between employers and employees;<br />
between Government agencies, voluntary assocations and individual<br />
Australians. With such a partnership, with a real sense of common purpose, and pric<br />
in our country, with a deep commitment to the future of our country,<br />
there is nothing Australia cannot achieve. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
