<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5459</transcript-id>
    <title>EXTRACT FROM ADDRESS AT THE OPENING OF THE HAMILTON CAMPAIGN HEADQUARTERS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/09/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005459.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
111'. n kZ A'<br />
FOR MEDIA MQNDAY, 29 SEPTEMBER, 1980<br />
EXTRACT FROM ADDRESS AT THE OPENING OF THE<br />
HAMILTON CAMPAIGN HEADQUARTERS<br />
Inflation would approach 20 per cent under an A. L. P. Government<br />
and Labor Party policies would put an end to the wave of<br />
development now taking place.<br />
Announced Labor policies would guarantee that. Labor has<br />
promised to spend $ 2.5 billion in six areas of expenditure<br />
as costed by Government Departments.<br />
That massive increase in expenditure would plainly be<br />
inflationary. On top of that the Labor Party has already proclaimed a hands-off<br />
policy towards wage cases before the Arbitration Commission.<br />
That was A. L. P. policy between 1972 and 1975 and as a result<br />
award wages went up by nearly 40 per cent in one year alone.<br />
Massive Government expenditure, unreasonable wage increases<br />
leading to wage inflation would destroy the strength of<br />
Australian industry.<br />
Primary industry has significantly recovered from the damage<br />
of the Labor years. Massive wage increases and massive<br />
increases in Government expenditure would be the death knell<br />
of rural prosperity.<br />
Last year manufacLuring exports increased by 30 per cent. All<br />
that would be ended. Under Labor's inflation, manufacturing<br />
industry would no longer be able to export.<br />
That was the position before. Since their policies are the<br />
same, it would be the position again.<br />
During the three years of Labor Government, personal income<br />
tax collections rose by 125 per cent.<br />
Labor is obsessed with spending more money. They are not<br />
concerned about producing more, or creating a wealthier, stronger,<br />
and more vital Australia.<br />
Their policies are a disaster. They are &amp;-party of disaster.<br />
They are a party of doom. They are a party that would destroy<br />
the strength of Australia. 12 </p>
<p>-2<br />
While Mr. llawke last week twice said that Labor would no~ t<br />
increase taxation, he is plainly not stating Labor policy.<br />
lie is not telling the truth. Both Mr. Hayden and M4r. Willis<br />
have promised to increase taxes.<br />
They have promised a capital gains tax, a resources rent tax,<br />
a levy on domestic oil producers and a number of other tax<br />
initiatives, including the termination of family trust<br />
arrangements and the restructuring of tax scales to collect<br />
more tax.<br />
flow Mr. H-awke can twice last week, in a barefa~ ed way, say<br />
that Mr. Hayden has promised lower taxes, is beyond credibility<br />
and comprehension.<br />
When will Mr. Hlawke stand up and tell. the truth that<br />
Mr. Hayden is pledged to increase a number of substantial taxes.<br />
Their expenditure proposals show they will have to.<br />
They are a policy of disaster. Much has been achieved over<br />
the pa-r; t five years. it would al. l be destroye--d with anot-her<br />
bout o~ f Labor. 000---<br />
, scr </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
