<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17372</transcript-id>
    <title>Commonwealth assistance for New South Wales flood-affected communities</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Attorney-General Robert McClelland today announced the Federal Government would provide financial assistance to NSW communities affected by flooding in the state's west.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister said the Commonwealth assistance was designed to help out our farmers and their families in times of need.</p>
<p>While high rain fall on Australia's East Coast in recent weeks is good news for our dams, for many crop farmers excessive rain is leading to delays in harvesting and affecting the quality of production.</p>
<p>The Gillard Labor Government is focused on supporting these flood affected families, particularly as we go into the Christmas period.</p>
<p>Commonwealth assistance is being provided to NSW through the Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA) and will apply to the natural disaster declared areas covered by Mid-Western Regional Council and Weddin, Wellington, Warrumbungle, Cootamundra, Coonamble, Harden and Young Shires.</p>
<p>Under the NDRRA, financial support will also be provided by the Commonwealth to NSW for the restoration of essential public infrastructure, such as roads, bridges and schools, where expenditure exceeds certain thresholds and requirements.</p>
<p>In addition to funding the cost of counter disaster operations (on a 50/50 basis with NSW), funding will also include disaster relief and recovery assistance including:</p>
<p> * 	personal hardship and distress grants to low-income earners whose principal residence has been damaged;<br />
 * 	concessional loans of up to $130,000 for small businesses and primary producers;<br />
 * 	concessional loans of up to $25,000 for voluntary, non-profit organisations; and<br />
 * 	road and rail freight subsidies of up to $15,000 to assist primary producers for the carriage of livestock and fodder.</p>
<p>Attorney General Robert McClelland said the Commonwealth Government would continue to monitor the situation in the disaster declared areas and work with the State Governments to provide assistance to communities affected by the floods.</p>
<p>We strongly urge anyone in these declared areas to contact the flood hotline to see if they are eligible for assistance.</p>
<p>We will also continue to monitor the situation in other flood affected areas along the east coast of Australia.</p>
<p>For information about assistance, phone the NSW Emergency Management Hotline on 1800 227 228.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
