<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2477</transcript-id>
    <title>ATLAS COPCO - OPENING OF NEW PLANT - BLACKTOWN NSW - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON - 11 OCTOBER 1971</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002477.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ATLAS COPCO OPENING OF NEW PLANT<br />
BLACKTOWN N. S. W.<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen: 11Otbr97<br />
Thank you Sir-Ian for referring to my friendship with<br />
Dr. Wallenberg. I know him primarily as a very distinguished member<br />
of the banking community, and a financier of international repute.<br />
And I also know him but in a lesser way as an industrialist. So<br />
I looked forward, when I was invited here, to being able to renew<br />
my acquaintance with him. And I hope at the same time, to be able<br />
to try and get his impressions of what is happening in the international<br />
O maobnoevet arayll , m arwkheetns , w e whcaenn wheo pec anf orh opteh e foArm erai craena lisgunrcmheanrtg eo f onp ariimtpioerst, s and<br />
to be removed. I<br />
But that meeting will be delayed. I hope it's in the not<br />
too distant future that I'll be able to meet him again.<br />
And Sir Ian, if I can . thank you particularly when you<br />
referred to compression, compressed air and similar matters, that<br />
you did it in an industrial context, and not in the context in front<br />
of my colleagues of compressed air in the Federal Parliament. I<br />
can assure you, we're grateful that this subject wasn't raised<br />
with all the implications it has for my colleagues on the other side<br />
of the House and for myself.<br />
But having said all that, may I join with you Sir Ian, in<br />
hoping that in the not too distant future we will be able to get a<br />
resolution of world parities in the international money markets.<br />
Because I believe that while it doesn't interfere with us to any<br />
great extent at the moment, nonetheless, it does interfere with the<br />
free flow of world trade, and consequently if it proceeds over a<br />
very long period of time, it must effect us. It effects us indirectly<br />
because it will effect the trade of the developing countries and<br />
for that matter, all the developed countries as well.<br />
And I can add to that that I do hope this surcharge that has<br />
been imposed is also removed in double-quick time, because of the<br />
impact that it can have, and the reaction that is likely to be-caused<br />
in other countries if it is not taken off very quickly. The Americans,<br />
we know, have a major problem a very big one because their<br />
balance of payments deficit is a huge one. But other countries are,<br />
I am sure, looking at it in a realistic way. We want all countries to be<br />
able to play their part in trying to come to a speedy resolution for<br />
all of us. But now, Sir, may I turn to the substance of what I wanted<br />
to say to you here today. And the first point that I want to mention<br />
is that we do welcome our friends from Sweden and , their new enterprise.<br />
This enterprise Atlas Copco brings with it a very famous Sviedish<br />
name. It is associated with the name of Wallenberg and that name is<br />
very well known in this country of ours. / 2 </p>
<p>Now I'm sure of this. That because of the management<br />
techniques that are so well-known to your Corporation, because<br />
of the new type of product it is now introducing, that it will<br />
be a great asset to this country. And one I can assure you<br />
that as an Acting Treasurer and as a Prime Minister, we welcome.<br />
Now the second reason why I want to welcome you here<br />
is a pleasant one. You mentioned the word growth. We like to<br />
use three different phrases together, or three different words<br />
together growth, progress and prosperity. 7,<br />
And I believe that not only do we ensure growth in<br />
the material sense as a result of the establishment of these new<br />
sections of your factory, but it will also add to our progress<br />
in this community, and I think to the prosperity of many, many<br />
sections of our people as well. Because a new plant does mean<br />
progress, and a new plant does give a demonstration from overseas,<br />
and capital is a very sensitive thing and usually works in<br />
those places where it can get the best and the most stable return.<br />
But it also demonstrates the confidence of your own people, and<br />
the management of your own people in Sweden in the future<br />
prosperity of this country.<br />
There is another reason too and I'll have to come<br />
back to what both you and Sir Ian said a few moments ago -and<br />
this does give me the opportunity for a little propaganda -that<br />
whilst at the moment we have a very satisfactory trade balance<br />
and we've got a very happy balance of payments surplus at the<br />
moment too, nonetheless, we do want to be able to ensure, that<br />
over a long period, we can not only have trade surplusses, but<br />
the problem of balance of payments difficulties will be banished<br />
for all time. Now I think you know Sir, that so far as our direct trade<br />
with Sweden is concerned, we export to you only a little less than<br />
one sixth of what you export to us. And so consequently we've<br />
always looked forward with a great deal of pleasure to the day<br />
when industries could be established here that could in some way,<br />
rectify to a moderate extent the difference in the balance of<br />
payments between the two countries.<br />
Naturally I a4leased to be able to say in your<br />
presence, and in the presence of Sir Ian as well, that last year<br />
our trade increased by something of the order of thirty per cent.<br />
So we can look forward in the days to come in an improvement in<br />
the balance. But what is much more important to us is that you are<br />
engaging in new activities and that those activities will in<br />
the future permit us together to improve the export trade.<br />
And again if I can refer to Sir Ian in a very favourable<br />
way. On the last two-occasions when I've had the pleasure of<br />
meeting him in Canberra, he's advised me of' the kind ofa. ctivities<br />
that he is engaged in. And he gave me an insight at least into<br />
one industry, that was exclusively oriented towards the export<br />
markets. I believe Sir, that your Corporation is oriented to<br />
export markets as well. </p>
<p>Now when I heard of these ideas and these new enterprises, I<br />
couldn't help but think of the words " taking coals to Newcastle". It's<br />
not so many generations ago when nobody thought it was within the bounds<br />
of contemplation that anyone could shift coals to Newcastle. But we in<br />
this country seem to be developing the facilties to move all sorts of<br />
commodities to all sorts of hitherto unexpected places. We export quite<br />
a lot of spaghetti to Italy. We send a lot of our flowers to Holland.<br />
And I am pleased to be able to state, that as a result of some discussions<br />
I have had in Melbournewithin the course of the last few weeks that<br />
we are now sending knives and forks to Sheffield.<br />
So you can see, Sir, that we are getting heavily engaged in<br />
international trade and we are doing so in a very sensible way..<br />
But today I don't want to refer principally to these matters of<br />
trade. To an audience as distinguished as this, and one heavily involved<br />
S in the problem of industrial management and productivity, I want to<br />
Vmention three matters that I regard to be of crucial importance to us<br />
ones that have to be solved.<br />
The first one involves this Corporation in the same way as<br />
it involves every other corporation manufacturing goods in AustralhV<br />
And the problem that we face today is this. That now for a little<br />
more than a year, probably approaching a period of about two years,<br />
we have had wild-cat strikes, unpredictable wild-cat strikes of a size,<br />
of a dimension that I believe are cutting back our prospects for<br />
production in the future. And they are most certainly reducing our<br />
productivity and therefore the very basis on which we are able to get<br />
a reduction of costs and one of the instruments through which we can<br />
effect inflation. Now many of them, and I want to emphasise these<br />
words, are strikes that are purely based upon domestic political<br />
Srequirements that have no association whatsoever with the idea that they<br />
can win greater pay packets and more purchasing power for the people<br />
who might be employed in the industry involved.<br />
They're certainly helping prices to go up. Looked at in the<br />
other way, they're not helping us to keep prices down. And I repeat it<br />
again, because it is of basic importance to us : It is one of the<br />
greatest impediments that we have to keeping inflationary forces under<br />
restraint. And equally too, because of the difficulties it creates, the<br />
uncertainties it creates in the minds of so many people, I think it<br />
is preventing domestic demand from increasing at a moderate pace and<br />
in a way in which I can assure you we would like it to increase at the<br />
moment. But coming back to this problem of political and other industrial<br />
wild-cat strikes the point that I want to make here today is that last<br />
year the working man lost $ 31 million because of industrial disputes.<br />
That is three times more than they lost in 1967. It's an appalling record<br />
and it's an appalling record against the backgroun ' d that average earnings,<br />
and if you like average wages, are increasing at an unprecedented pace.<br />
Now my worry, and it's one of the biggest worries, is that it's<br />
left-wing and communist controlled unions, that are, I believe, probably<br />
responsible for more of the strikes than from any other section of<br />
the community-. / 4 </p>
<p>But I also want to emphasise that I do not believe that the<br />
great majority of working men want these strikes to continue. They<br />
want to get on with the job. They want prices to be fairly stable.<br />
They want to be able to look after their families. And consequently<br />
it must be our responsibility as the Government to try and ensure that<br />
it is the wish of the working man that prevails and not the wish of<br />
their left-wing supporters.<br />
And the second point I want to mention concerns what is funadmental<br />
to industrial success. And that is our system of arbitration. Now this<br />
is a system that most of you know has stood us in very good stead ever<br />
since the arbitration system was established. As a member of a Cabinet,<br />
who for eight years was responsible for the Department of Labour and<br />
National Service, I can assure you that I developed a respect for the<br />
system of arbitration. I know the advantages that it can bring. And<br />
it must be our responsibility as a Government to try and strengthen that<br />
system, and not permit others to destroy it, or weaken it. We must<br />
ensure that objective if it is practical.<br />
The arbitration system has served Australians remarkably well.<br />
._ Ihats banished sweated labour into the recesses of history. It brought<br />
W a degree of equality in payment-for work performed that could not be<br />
brought by any other system. There is one regret that I have at the<br />
moment, and it is a very deep regret. It is the way in which under the<br />
present system of settlement of industrial disputes the rewards<br />
are not going within a fair degree of equality to all workers, but are<br />
going into the hands of those where the industrial might and strength<br />
is the greatest and where they can use the greatest muscle in order<br />
to wring rewards out of employers.<br />
But I don't for one moment think that this is the end of the<br />
problem. I can assure you that we are doing all in our power now, to be<br />
able to contemplate first of all, and finally to be able to bring<br />
reforms to Parliament in order to strengthen arbitration and to look at<br />
the whole system of industrial strength to see what advantage we can<br />
obtain from it.<br />
* And whenlI look at this I want to assure you that the system of<br />
sanctions must remain as an essential element in the arbitral machinery.<br />
And they must apply, not only to the employee or to the trade unionist,<br />
but as you know as well as I do, they have to apply to the employer as<br />
well. Now I can't stress too strongly how fundamental the preservation<br />
of the arbitration system is to industrial peace and stability. I want<br />
to assiire you that we will do all in our power to sustain arbitration.<br />
We will not permit it to be destroyed.<br />
So I must urge you not to sell it short. Don't drop it because<br />
you've nothing better to put in its place. Don't nege it, or don't<br />
please I ask you, let it fail by lack of use.<br />
The final point I want to put to you, and this is one, 1-believe,<br />
Sir, will appeal to you. That is the problem of productivity. All of<br />
us, I think, understand this problem of productivity and inflation. But<br />
the moment there is any increase in average incomes or earnings that is<br />
greater than the increase in producitivity, then naturally enough you<br />
do get an inflationary pressure. Something of the order of 6 or 7 per cen.<br />
today that is the difference between the growth in productivity<br />
and'-'-he growth in average earnings. </p>
<p>Now what we want to attempt to do, although it is a very difficult<br />
objective, is to try and reduce the gap to the maximum extent that we<br />
can do. Not that we believe it is a tolerable alternative, because we<br />
don't think we can. But what we want to do is to reduce the gap so<br />
that we get a degree of inflation that is acceptable and one that<br />
can be readily absorbed in the international community.<br />
The next point that I want to make to you about productivity is<br />
this It doesn't necessarily mean more work. It doesn't-necessarily<br />
mean more work. It doesn't necessarily mean that you work harder. It<br />
has, Mr. Johnsson, as you so clearly implied, meant that you have to<br />
work with a greater degree of efficiency. And it is for this, and for<br />
other reasons why we welcome your Corporation coming here. Because we<br />
do feel from what we have heard and what I have seen, that you would<br />
introduce efficiency into the management of this plant.<br />
Now Mr. Chairman, I haven't had a good look around this<br />
factory. I regret to say I have to go to Canberra quite soon. But from<br />
what I have read, particularly from the little pamphlet that was sent<br />
to me a few days ago, I can assure you that I recognise the degree of<br />
efficiency that you show.<br />
I know of the management and labour skills that you have in<br />
this factory in Blacktown.<br />
I believe the manufacturing industries of Australia are making<br />
a magnificent contribution to our growing industrial greatness. They<br />
are providing resourceful and skilful service, and they are doing much<br />
to strengthen our self-reliance as a nation. This new plant today adds<br />
to their number and their diversity. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
