<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9489</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP HONEST QUESTIONS FOR HONEST JOHN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009489.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 9/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
HONEST QUESTIONS FOR HONEST JOHN ' I<br />
The Leader of the Opposition, Mr Howard, should tell the Australian public<br />
exactly where he stands on cross media ownership.<br />
The Government has a view on the issue, and has the courage to stand by it<br />
regardless of who chooses to grumble about it.<br />
John Howard once said that he opposed cross media ownership rules, and<br />
that he thought the competition provisions of the Trade Practices Act were a<br />
sufficient safeguard against media monopolies.<br />
Then, in 1991, he was party to a unanimous shadow cabinet decision that<br />
diversity of ownership should be the paramount consideration when drafting<br />
media legislation.<br />
Now he says the cross media ownership laws are out of date, but he stops<br />
short of saying what he would do, claiming that doing so is " a mug's game."<br />
If Mr Howard is serious about being Opposition Leader, he must stop being<br />
vague and offer a view. What does he believe? What has he said to others?<br />
What has he promised interested parties, including Mr Kerry Packer?<br />
In Sydney last Wednesday, Mr Howard said: " I haven't spoken to Mr Packer<br />
for some weeks."<br />
Mr Howard should say precisely when he last spoke to Mr Packer, and on<br />
what subject.<br />
Mr Howard has contended and I agree with him that it is not intrinsically<br />
improper for political leaders to meet senior business people, including media<br />
proprietors. Mr Howard said:" It is normal for people to talk to senior people." </p>
<p>However, the extraordinary nature of Mr Howard's recent contact with Mr<br />
Packer, the timing of Mr Packer's assault on Fairfax, and the level of disquiet<br />
about the matter among some Liberals requires an explanation from Mr<br />
Howard. I have made it clear to Mr Packer, and to the community that I am in favour<br />
of plurality in the Australian media, and that I will not allow the national<br />
interest to be bulldozed.<br />
Mr Howard should make his position clear. Is it a policy of surrender? Is he<br />
opposed to cross media ownership rules? Is he opposed to media diversity,<br />
and in favour of further concentration of ownership of the Australian media?<br />
The public has a right to know his view. Vague is not best; vague will not do.<br />
CANBERRA FEBRUARY, 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
