<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5118</transcript-id>
    <title>TEXT OF THE PRIME MINISTER&#039;S STATEMENT AT THE OPENING SESSION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/08/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005118.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
0. XX113 MKCR<br />
TOR 0310 02.08.79<br />
O. XX0113 2120 1.8.79 UNC<br />
TO. PP CANBERRA/ 096 T -pr C<br />
FM. XXX CONFERENCE POST C" 2 3:<br />
FILE I<br />
UN C L A S S I F IED<br />
CHOGM FROM LUSAKA<br />
FOLLOWIN G IS TEXT OF THE PRIME MINIiSTER'S STATEMENT AT<br />
THE OPENING SESSION TODAY:<br />
BEGINS: I AM HONOURED TO HAVE BEEN INVITED TO REPLY TO YOUR SPEECH OF<br />
WELCOME, MR. PRESIDENT. ON BEHALF OF US ALL, I WOULD LIKE TO<br />
THANK YOU FOR YOUR WARM WELCOME AND YOUR GRACIOUS HOSPITALITY,<br />
I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK SONNY RAMPHAL AND HIS SECRETARIAT<br />
FOR THEIR DEDICATED WORK IN PREPARING FOR THIS CONFERENCE.<br />
r THIS IS AN HISTORIC OCCASION. IT IS THE FIRST Tt-iE THAT A<br />
RECULAR COMMONWEALTH HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING HAS BEE; HELD IN<br />
AFRICA. YOU, MR. PRESIDENT, HAVE BEEN FIR. i IN YOUR RESOLVE THAT,<br />
WHATEVER THE DIFFICULTIES, THIS CONFERENCE SHOULD BE HELD IN<br />
ZAMBIA A MEMBER COUNTRY WHICH OCCUPIES A FRONT LINE POSITION IN<br />
SOUTHER AFRICAN AFFAIRS, WHICH HAS SUFFERED GREATLY BECAUSE OF<br />
THE PROBLEMS OF THE REGION, AND WHICH HAS MUCH TO CONTRIBUTE TO<br />
THE RESOLUTION OF THOSE PROBLEMS.<br />
MR. PRESIDENT, I BELIEVE YOU TO BE RIGHT IN YOUR CONVICTION<br />
THAT THE LOGIC OF THE COMMONWEALTH'S HISTORY AND CHARACTER REQUIRED<br />
THAT THIS CONFERENCE BE HELD IN SOUTHERN AFRICA. THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
AS IT IS REPRESENTED HERE IS THE PRODUCT OF A MOVEMENT WHICH HAS<br />
SWEPT THE WORLD OVER THE LAST THIRTY YEARS, CONVERTING COLONIES<br />
INTO INDEPENDENT COUNTRIES AND ESTABLISHING POLITICAL EQUALITY<br />
BETWEEN PEOPLES IRRESPECTIVE OF RACE AND COLOUR, MR. PRESIDENT,<br />
IN TERMS OF THAT MAJOR TRANSFORMATION IN GLOBAL AFFAIRS, THERE<br />
IS STILL UNFINISHED BUSINESS TO BE ATTENDED TO IN SOUTHERN AFRICA<br />
AND TIME IS RUNNING OUT. AS THE PROCESS BEGAN IN THE COMMONWEALTH,<br />
AS THE COMMONWEALTH HAS BOTH CONTRIBUTED TO AND REFLECTED ITS<br />
COURSE, IT IS APPROPRIATE AND INDEED ESSENTIAL: THAT WE SHOULD<br />
ESTABLISH THE RELEFANCE OF THIS INSTITUTION BY CONCERNING OURSELVES<br />
WITH ITS COMPLETION. / 2 IV<br />
~ as~ </p>
<p>XX113<br />
THE ISSUES INVOLVED IN SOUTHERN AFRICA, AND IN PARTICULAR<br />
IN ZIMBABWE, ARE ENORMOUSLY COMPLEX ONES. THEY PRESENT DIFFERENT<br />
MEMBER STATES WITH DIFFERENT PROBLEMS, BOTH DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL.<br />
BUT I BELIEVE THAT AS WE DELIBERATE IN THIS CONFERENCE<br />
WE SHOULD KEEP THREE THINGS FIRMLY IN MIND.<br />
FIRST, IT IS VITAL THAT ' WE RECOGNISE AND BUILD ON THE<br />
SUBSTANTIAL AREAS OF AGREEMENT WHICH EXIST AMONG US ON THIS ISSUE,<br />
THAT WE NOT BE DOMINATED BY NEGATIVE ASPECTS. NO ONE AT THIS MEETING<br />
BELIEVES THAT A SETTLEMENT IS COMPATIBLE WITH A CONSTITUTIONAL<br />
SITUATION IN SALISBURY, WHICH IS TAINTED IN ANY WAY WITH<br />
RACIALISM. WE ARE ALL IN FAVOUR OF MAJORITY RULE TRUE MAJORITY<br />
RULE WHICH TAKES ACCOUNT OF ALL ( UNDERLINE ONE) THE PARTIES<br />
CONCERNED AND WHICH IS REFLECTED NOT ONLY IN ELECTIONS BUT IN THE<br />
UNDERLYING STRUCTURE OF POWER AND AUTHORITY.<br />
NO ONE WANTS A SOLUTION THROUGH SLAUGHTER AND BLOODSHED, BOTH<br />
BECAUSE IT WILL PRODUCE UNTOLD SUFFERING TO INNOCENT PEOPLE AND<br />
BECAUSE IT WILL BREED NEW HATREDS, EVERYONE WANTS TO SEE OUTSIDE<br />
INTERFERENCE IN THE REGION DIMINISH NOT GROW. NO ONE WANTS<br />
TO SEE THE COMMONWEALTH DAMAGED. If IS IMPERATIVE THAT AS WE<br />
ENTER THE THICKETS OF TECHNICALITIES AND CONTROVERSIES, WE DO NOT<br />
ALLOW THEM TO OBSCURE THESE BASIC POINTS. FORMIDABLE AS THE<br />
DIFFERENCES ON SOME ISSUES ARE, I BELIEVE THAT, AS FAR AS THOSE<br />
OF US PRESENT AT THIS MEETING ARE CONCERNED, THEY ARE DIFFERENCES<br />
ABOUT MEANS AND TIMING, NOT ABOUT ENDS. WE MUST NOT ALLOW MEANS-TO<br />
DOMINATE ENDS.<br />
MR. PRESIDENT, I WOULD LIKE TO ELABORATE BRIEFLY ON ONE OF<br />
THESE ELEMENTS OF AGREEMENT. THE ESSENTIAL CAUSE OF THE GRAVE<br />
SITUATION IN SOUTHERN AFRICA IS RACIALISM, THE. BELIEF THAT ONE RACE<br />
IS SUPERIOR TO ANOTHER AND THEREFORE ENJOYS A NATURAL RIGHT TO<br />
DOMINATE, EXPLOIT AND DISCRIMINATE AGAINST OTHERS. THIS IS A<br />
BELIEF THAT ALL HERE CATEGORICALLY REJECT. ALL OPPRESSION IS<br />
REPUGNANT, BUT THERE IS AN OBSCENITY ABOUT OPPRESSION BASED ON NO<br />
MORE THAN THE COLOUR OF A PERSON'S SKIN. YOU, MR. PRESIDENT, WERE<br />
THE GUIDING HAND BEHIND THE DECLARATION OF COMMONWEALTH PRINCIPLES<br />
MADE BY THE HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING IN SINGAPORE IN 1971, WHEN<br />
MEMBERS RECOGNISED RACIAL PREJUDICE AS A DANGEROUS SICKNESS AND<br />
RACIAL DISCRIMINATION AS AN UNMITIGATED EVIL. IT IS NOT ONLY<br />
APPROPRIATE BUT IMPERATIVE THAT AT THIS TIME, IN THIS PLACE, WE<br />
SHOULD SOLEMNLY REAFFIRM OUR ADHERENCE TO THAT DECLARATION,<br />
THE SECOND THING WE SHOULD KEEP IN MIND IS THAT, WHATEVER ELSE<br />
IT HAS DONE AND WHATEVER ONE NIGHT THINK ABOUT PARTICULAR ASPECTS<br />
OF IT, THE RECENT ELECTION HAS CREATED CONDITIONS FOR'MOVEMENT.<br />
BUT IN ITSELF, THE ELECTION SETTLES ( UNDERLINE ONE) NOTHING LET<br />
THERE BE NO DOUBT ABOUT THAT. IT HAS ( UNDERLINE ONE) HOWEVER,<br />
BROUGHT ABOUT A DIFFERENT SITUATION. IT HAS CREATED NEW FACTS<br />
/ 3 -ii 1 </p>
<p>XX113<br />
y AND DISTURBED A STALEMATE. THERE HAVE BEEN SIGNIFICANT<br />
CONSTITUTIONAL CHANGES, AND IT IS CLEAR THAT BEFORE AGREEMENT IS<br />
REACHED, AND THE ESSENTIAL ACCEPTANCE OF THAT AGREEMENT BY A<br />
NUMBER OF AFRICAN STATES IS ACHIEVED, THERE WILL HAVE TO BE FURTHER<br />
CHANGES. AS TO WHAT HAPPENS NEXT, THAT IS NOT IN THE LAP OF THE<br />
GODS. IT IS, TO A VERY LARGE EXTENT, IN OUR LAPS. MUCH DEPENDS<br />
ON WHETHER WE CAN SEIZE, AND SEIZE WITH DETERMINATION AND VISION<br />
THE OPPORTUNITY PROVIDED BY THE COMPARATIVE FLUIDITY WHICH NOW<br />
EXISTS, IN ORDER TO ADVANCE TOWARDS A SETTLEMENT. TIME IS RUNNING<br />
OUT AND WE MAY NOT HAVE SUCH AN OPPORTUNITY AGAIN.<br />
THIRDLY, MR. PRESIDENT, I THINK IT IS CLEAR THAT IF A NONVIOLENT<br />
SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM OF ZIMBABWE IS TO BE FOUND IT WILL<br />
INVOLVE FLEXIBILITY ON ALL SIDES FLEXIBILITY NOT ABOUT THE<br />
OBJECTIVE OF A NON-RACIALIST SOCIETY, BUT CONCERNING THE PROCESS<br />
OF ARRIVING AT THAT OBJECTIVE AND THE INDIVIDUAL INTERESTS OF<br />
THE PRINCIPALS. COMPROMISE AND MODERATION SHOULD BE SEEN NOT<br />
MERELY IN TERMS OF ESTABLISHING A BRIDGE BETWEEN DIFFERENT POSITIONS.<br />
THEY SHOULD BE SEEN AS POSITIVE VALUES IN THEIR OWN<br />
RIGHT THE ESSENTIAL VALUES BOTH OF DEMOCRATIC POLITICS AND OF<br />
PEACEFUL RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN STATES WHICH ARE SIMULTANEOUSLY<br />
SOVEREIGN AND INTERDEPENDENT. THERE IS AN URGENT NEED TO RALLY<br />
AND INVIGORATE THE FORCES OF MODERATION AND REASONABLENESS IN<br />
INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS. WE SHOULD ADVOCATE AND PROCLAIM<br />
MODERATION NOT APOLOGETICALLY AND OUT OF EXPEDIENCY, BUT<br />
CONFIDENTLY EVEN PASSIONATELY AS A. MATTER OF FUNDAMENTAL<br />
PRINCIPLE. IF WE DO SO, THE BRIDGES ARE LIKELY TO EMERGE OF THEIR<br />
OWN ACCORD.<br />
MR. PRESIDENT AND FELLOW DELEGATES, IT IS OUR SOLEMN DUTY AT<br />
THIS MEETING TO CONTRIBUTE POSITIVELY TO THE SEARCH FOR<br />
COMPREHENSIVE, EQUITABLE AND PEACEFUL SOLUTIONS TO THE PROBLEMS<br />
OF THIS REGION. AT THE END OF THE DAY IT IS VITAL THAT WE UILL<br />
HAVE REACHED AGREEMENT AMONG OURSELVES WHICH WILL ENABLE CONSTRUCTIVE<br />
NEGOTIATION AND CONSULTATION TO PROCEED,<br />
MR. PRESIDENT, INEVITABLY THE PROBLEMS OF SOUTHERN AFRICA WILL<br />
OCCUPY THE CENTRAL PLACE IN THIS CONFERENCE. BUT THERE IS MUCH<br />
ELSE THAT IS URGENT ON OUR AGENDA.<br />
IF A MAJOR THEME OF THE LAST QUARTER CENTURY HAS BEEN THE ENDING<br />
OF COLONIALISM, THE REMAINDER OF THIS CENTURY IS LIKELY TO BE<br />
INCREASINGLY PREOCCUPIED WITH ECONOMIC PROBLEMS. WE HAVE ALREADY<br />
DEMONSTRATED THE SCOPE FOR COMMONWEALTH ACTION ON ECONOMIC<br />
MATTERS BY THE INITIATIVE WE TOOK ON THE COMMON FUND AT THE LAST<br />
HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING. I BELIEVE THAT THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
CAN LEGITIMATELY CLAIM CONSIDERABLE CREDIT FOR THE FACT THAT<br />
THE COMMON FUND PROPOSAL REPRESENTS ONE OF THE FEW AREAS. IN<br />
WHICH REAL PROGRESS HAS BEEN MADE SINCE THEN.<br />
S-,, y </p>
<p>I. o l^ S,<br />
XX113<br />
WE MUST ALL VIEW WITH GRAVE CONCERN ASSESSMENTS THAT THERE IS'<br />
LITTLE LIKELIHOOD OF AN IMPROVEMENT IN THE SLOW GROWTH IN<br />
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ACTIVITY AND INTERNATIONAL TRADE THAT HAS<br />
BEEN EXPERIENCED SINCE 1973.<br />
WHAT THESE ASSESSMENTS IMPLY IS THAT THERE HAS BEEN A SERIOUS<br />
DETERIORATION IN THE PROSPECTS FOR REDUCING POVERTY AND<br />
RAISING LIVING STANDARDS IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES.<br />
I BELIEVE THAT A PREREQUISITE TO REMEDYING THIS OUTLOOK MUST BE<br />
TO DEAL WITH THE DUAL SCOURGES OF INFLATION AND PROTECTION.<br />
THESE ARE INTERCONNECTED PROBLEMS WHOSE SOLUTION LIES PRIMARILY<br />
IN THE HANDS OF POWERFUL DEVELOPED STATES, THERE IS ALSO AN URGENT<br />
NEED TO ENSURE THAT INADEQUATE SUPPLIES OF OIL DO NOT ACT AS A<br />
CONSTRAINT ON ECONOMIC GROWTH OR ENDANGER THE INTER-DEPENDENT.<br />
ECONOMIC SYSTEM WHICH HAS THE POTENTIAL TO PROVIDE GREAT MUTUAL<br />
BENEFITS. THE ISSUES ARE COMPLEX AND I SHALL NOT DWELL ON THEM FURTHER<br />
NOW EXCEPT TO SAY THAT I BELIEVE THE TIME HAS COME FOR A NEW<br />
AND BOLD APPROACH TO GET THE WORLD ECONOMY MOVING AT A FASTER<br />
RATE AND TO ENSURE THAT ALL PARTICIPANTS HAVE EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES<br />
TO SHARE IN THE BENEFITS.<br />
A STRONG AND DETERMINED EFFORT WILL BE NEEDED, INVOLVING<br />
ATTENTION AND CONSIDERATION BY WORLD LEADERS. IF WE APPEAL TO THE<br />
CONCEPT OF INTERDEPENDENCE, WE M. UST MEAN WHAT WE SAY AND ALL PLAY<br />
A PART ACCORDING TO OUR ABILITY.<br />
ANOTHER ISSUE WHICH IN ONE WAY CR ANOTHER TOUCHES MOST OF US<br />
IS THAT OF REFUGEES. MR. PRESIDENT, I KNOW THAT YOUR COUNTRY<br />
AND MANY OF OUR OTHER AFRICAN MEMBVERS HAVE HAD TO COPE WITH THIS<br />
AND WITH THE ATTENDANT TRAGIC PROBLEMS OF DIVIDED FAMILIES,<br />
TEMPORARY ARRANGEMENTS WHICH TEND TO BECOME PERMANENT, INTERNATIONAL<br />
INDIFFERENCE AND CONSEQUENT PRESSURE ON ALL TOO SCARCE RESOURCESo<br />
THE PROBLEM IS NOW ASSUMING CRISIS PROPORTIONS IN OUR OWN PART<br />
OF THE WORLD AS A RESULT NOT ONLY OF THE INEVITABLE DISRUPTION<br />
RESULTING FROM CONFLICT BUT OF A DELIBERATELY PURSUED POLICY<br />
WHICH, AGAIN, HAS A RACIALIST COMPONENT. WE MUST ADDRESS. OURSELVES<br />
TO IT. HUMANITY REQUIRES US TO COME TO THE AID OF THE VICTIMS<br />
OF SUCH ACTION. BUT HUMANITY AND REALISM ALSO DEMAND THAT THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
COMMUNITY ATTACK THE PROBLEM AT ITS SOURCE, THAT WE MOBILISE<br />
PRESSURE TO END THE POLICIES OF PERSECUTION AND EXPULSION<br />
WHICH RESULT IN MASS EXODUS.<br />
I HAVE TOUCHED ON A NUMBER OF THE CENTRAL ISSUES CONFRONTING<br />
IHIS CONFERENCE. BUT IN CONCLUDING I URGE THAT IN DEALING WITH<br />
S<br />
r. . r 5 </p>
<p>xx<br />
ACTION: DEP FOREIGN AFFAIRS<br />
DEP P M AND CABINET T/ T<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOREIGN MINISTER<br />
DEP ADMIN SVCS<br />
DEP EDUCATION<br />
DEP FINANCE<br />
DEP NAT DEV<br />
DEP PRIMARY IND DEP DEP DEP DEP<br />
ONA JiO SCI AND ENV<br />
SPL TDE REP<br />
TDE AND RSCS<br />
TREASURY<br />
7 am ai-. likz i po 1<br />
113<br />
MAJOR GLOBAL AND REGIONAL PROBLEMS, WE TAKE CARE NOT TO NEGLECTSOME<br />
OF THE LESS DRAMATIC ONES. IN PARTICULAR, LET US BEAR IN<br />
MIND THE SPECIAL AND OFTEN PRESSING PROBLEMS FACED BY SMALL.<br />
STATES, REMEMBERING THAT THERE IS A SIGNIFICANT AND GROWING NUMBER<br />
OF SUCH STATES AMONG OUR MEMBERS.<br />
MR. PRESIDENT, I BELIEVE, AS IT THINK YOU DO, THAT THIS MEETING<br />
WILL BE A CRUCIAL ONE FOR THE COMMCNWEALTH. RARELY, IF EVER,<br />
HAVE WE GATHERED TO ADDRESS PROBLEMS OF SUCH MAGNITUDE AND<br />
URGENCY. RARELY HAVE WE HAD THE EYES OF THE INTERNATIONAL<br />
COMMUNITY SO FIRMLY ON US. AND RARELY, HAVE WE HAD AS GREAT<br />
AN OPPORTUNITY TO DEMONSTRATE THE VALUE OF THIS INSTITUTION BY<br />
MAKING A POSITIVE CONTRIBUTION TO WORLD ORDER.<br />
IF WE RISE TO THE OCCASION, IF, UNDER YOUR LEADERSHIP, WE<br />
SET ASIDE SECTIONAL AND SHORT-TERM CONSIDERATIONS AND SHOW THE<br />
STATESMANSHIP, WISDOM AND RESOLUTION WHICH THE CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
DEMAND, WE HAVE IT WITHIN OUR MEANS TO CONTRIBUTE TO PEACE IN<br />
AFRICA AND TO ESTABLISH BEYOND DOUBT THAT THE COMMONWEALTH IS<br />
GOING TO BE A KEY INSTITUTION IN THE LAST DECADES OF THIS<br />
CENTURY. IF WE SPEAK TO EACH OTHER AND WITH EACH OTHER, INSTEAD<br />
OF AT EACH OTHER OR PAST EACH OTHER, IN A WEEK'S TIME WE WILL<br />
EMERGE A STRONGER AND MORE RELEVANT BODY.<br />
MR. PRESIDENT, LET THAT L-E OUR DETERMINATION,<br />
ENDS. XC. O. XXO113 2120 1.8o79 096 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
