<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41614</transcript-id>
    <title>Rail Upgrades to Improve Traffic Around Sydney Airport</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/05/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>A major injection of funds by the Turnbull Government will improve Sydney’s rail network and get more trucks off the road.</p>
<p>The Government will fully fund a $400 million project to duplicate the remaining single‑track section of Sydney’s Port Botany Rail Line.</p>
<p>The funding will also deliver a passing loop at Cabramatta, allowing trains to pass.</p>
<p>Duplicating the Botany line will improve freight movement on Sydney’s rail network and encourage a shift in freight from road to rail – reducing traffic congestion in and around Sydney Airport and Port Botany.</p>
<p>Listed by Infrastructure Australia as a High Priority Initiative, this critical project will strengthen rail connection efficiency, improve freight transit times and increase service reliability for the Sydney region.</p>
<p>This is a vital upgrade to ease pressure on Sydney’s transport system. It will enable freight to be moved faster and easier - allowing businesses to get goods to market faster - and it will ease traffic around the airport by taking more heavy vehicles off the road.</p>
<p>The Australian Rail Track Corporation will deliver the project on behalf of the Australian Government. It will support about 150 jobs during construction.</p>
<p>The project will include new rail bridges, civil works and duplicated rail tracks across the 2.9 kilometre length of the freight line between Mascot and Botany, along with the construction of a 1.4 kilometre passing loop between Cabramatta and Warwick Farm.</p>
<p>This commitment will support the freight logistics and supply chain activities of existing intermodal terminals such as at Enfield and Chullora, as well as the new terminal under construction at Moorebank. This will ensure the region is prepared for the expected growth in containerised freight and future freight rail service needs.</p>
<p>Through this investment, the Australian Government is delivering on its commitment to increase freight productivity, ease road congestion and streamline supply chains for businesses and consumers.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
