<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2447</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF TASMANIAN STATE COUNCIL - LIBERAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA - DEVONPORT - 16 JULY 1971 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/07/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002447_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF TASMANIANT-STATE COUNCIL LIBERAL<br />
PARTY OF AUSTRALIA DEVONPORT 16jLYj 1971<br />
õ p! eScby the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
Mr. Chairman, Mr. Premier, Senator Wright, my Parliamentary Colleagues, Ladies<br />
and Gentlemen: While I am here I want to pass on, if I can, something of the spirit<br />
that is abroad in Australia today on behalf of the Liberal cause.<br />
As our President has said in the last four months I have visited fair of<br />
the six Australian States. Of course I don't count in New South Wales because it's<br />
the State in which I live. But what I can say to you, and I can say it to you with<br />
emphasis, is that I have been heartened by the obvious vitality of our movement, the<br />
enthusiasm of the Party members and the readiness of the organisation and the<br />
political wings to get together and to get things done.<br />
Only a few days ago my Press Off icer and my Department gave me a<br />
record of our achievements of the last four months 430 independent and separate<br />
initiatives taken successfully by the Government. Frankly it gave me a great cause for<br />
pleasure. We've got a good team in Canberra, and I've been conscious of a new<br />
unity among the Branches and the councils of the Party. There is a coming together<br />
and a gathering of the clans, as I see it, in readiness for the next election. I honestly<br />
believe we have the team and the policies to win, and not only to win, but I believe<br />
we will pick up seats. It's the size of the victory I want to be sure about. Now is the<br />
time for all of us to get cracking and to make that victory, and the numbers that we<br />
have in the House, a big one.<br />
I'd like to get Franklin back for a start. As I said a few moments ago,<br />
I believe that our record in the last few months has been pretty good -over 40 initiatives<br />
successfully taken. I've met the Premiers of the States on two occasions in that time,<br />
and I believe each time successfully.<br />
I think I've made it clear that the Commonwealth doesn't want to play the<br />
role of Headmaster. For political and economic and for social reasons I believe in<br />
a Federal system of Government. But what I do want is to work together and to<br />
co-operate closely, as we are meant to do under the Constitution. And that<br />
Constitution belongs to you and shouldn't be altered unless it is with your consent. I<br />
want it to survive until you change it, and I want to be able to play my part in making<br />
it work better. The things we've done so far have included growth taxes for the States.<br />
We gave a special increase to the pensioners, and in many other aspects of our social<br />
welfare we have shown new inititatives. In particular I want to emphasise what has<br />
been done for our aborigines. Because here I believe the story has been imperfectly<br />
told. All the reforms that William Wentworth asked me to carry out as a result of<br />
consultations with the aboriginal councils themselves, were in fact either carried out<br />
or bettered. And our massive programme for aboriginal development in the Northern<br />
Territory is, I think, a very good one. / 2 </p>
<p>We've-also been tackling a variety of problems arising from the pressures<br />
of the-economy including a review of the arbitration system to see what can be done<br />
about cost inflation arising largely from excessive wage increases. I'll say more to<br />
you about this subject in a few moments'time.<br />
We are giving very special attention to the crisis in our rural industries,<br />
especially how we'll be able to help them when Britain enters the European Community.<br />
But before I touch on these subjects, let me come back to Labor Party activities.<br />
Because I believe that by their tolerance and tacit encouragement of industrial disputes<br />
they are indifferent to the problems of the economy.<br />
In the time that I have been Prime Minister I have nct heard one Member<br />
of the Opposition other than Alan Fraser of Eden-Monaro, who is a Liberal in mind<br />
and in thought raise his voice in opposition to the activities of the left-wing trade<br />
unions and the activities of the left-wing in his own Party.<br />
There has been an indifferent and a gross affront to law and order in<br />
the community by elements in the trade union movement during the Springboks tour. I<br />
believe most Australians want that tour to be successful. They don't want politics to<br />
get mixed up with a sporting event.<br />
You know too, the waterside workers cut off Tasmania from the Port<br />
of Melbourne as part of an industrial campaign against the Springboks. That was a<br />
blatant political act without any industrial motive whatsoever. And in recent weeks, in<br />
defiance of a promise given to the ACTU and the Australian people, they're again engaged<br />
in these tactics of depriving you people of the ability to carry on your businesses<br />
effectively. Now the Labor Party also wants to write down our rural industries.<br />
They said as much at their Launceston conference. Mr. Hayden, a not very eminent<br />
member of the Labor Party, and not a man who can be regarded as gifted or knowledgeable<br />
in rural affairs, but he said, speaking as it were for an-industrial metropolitan community,<br />
that our primary industry should be controlled on a self-supporting basis and that<br />
whatever reforms were to be carried out should be carried out in a defined period.<br />
What he meant was that many of our great industries the wheat industry<br />
and the sugar industry, both of which have stabilization schemes, should be deprived<br />
of them, and the wool industry shouldn't be givenpprotection because it has to be<br />
self-supporting. Those industries should be permitted to fight their own battles within<br />
a definable period, and be permitted to fight an international company without the<br />
support of the Government and the Australian people.<br />
Now he, and those who voted it through just didn't know what they were<br />
talking about. Their one so-called expert in primary industries, Dr. Patterson,<br />
virtually disowned it publicly on television on the night the decision was made or if it<br />
wasn't that night it was immediately after the conference. But it is the self-same<br />
Dr. Patterson who is now playing the games of the Communists in China, by being<br />
critical of our attitude to the sale of wiheat to China. We don't want to interfere, because<br />
we know what a magnificent job the Wheat Board is doing, and we're faily certain that<br />
if these attacks had not occurred, then our Wheat Board had reasonable prospects of<br />
commencing negotiations with the China purchasing agency within the course of the<br />
Inn foxiv u-4: 4-o it thair activities have harmed the cause of the Wheat Board, and<br />
having harmed the cause of the Wheat Boardhave. I he-lieve. hni-mod ite anLis MIe'<br />
Australian wheat producers. / 3 </p>
<p>Now if I may go further, the Party Leaders have been on parade in Peking,<br />
in a massive propaganda exercise, skilfully contrived by Chou En-Lai, offending as<br />
many of Australia's friends as they could. In fact, Mr. Whitlam and his entourage,<br />
and I ask you to remember who they are, and the type of people they are, are the<br />
advocates for China against the interests of this country. And it must be our task as<br />
Liberals to expose the shallowness of all these activities.<br />
Let me take two of them, and two only because as our President has<br />
said, my time and your time is limited. I'll talk first of all about the industrial<br />
intrusion into non-industrial matters as one subject, and our attitude to Mainland<br />
China as the other. Let's have a look into the industrial fields first. You've heard of<br />
Mr. Hawke I take it he's our new foreign demagogue. But he's doing a cook's tour<br />
of Europe at the moment, after stirring up a hornet's nest here, and finding it pretty<br />
angry one. For some months now, we have seen some elements in the Trade Union<br />
movement, Mr. Hawke as their principal spokesman, butting into all sorts of fields<br />
where they have no right to be, and where no industrial issue was involved, poking<br />
their nose in because they wanted to tell you exactly what they wanted you to do. They<br />
tried to stop the export of merino sheep and they failed. Mr. Hawke busied himself<br />
with some gratuitous advice to a television station on the kind of programme it should<br />
have. If he could do that, couldn't he do it to the media, all the media press,<br />
television, radio and other kind of activities that he thought came within his sights.<br />
He led the way in an attempt to stop the Springboks tour. And what they did was really<br />
an attempt to deny people their freedom of choice within the law, and an attempt, as<br />
a final result, to have a showdown with the Government.<br />
They inspired and provoked demonstrators into actions which became a<br />
challenge to public law and order within the Commonwealth. I believe the Australian<br />
public is fed up with all of this, and I believe a lot of responsible trade unionists the<br />
bulk of whom are good, hard-working Australians are also fed up with it too.<br />
I have said many times that my Government and I find apartheid repugnant<br />
as a political and a social philosophy. But apartheid wasn't really the issue in the challenge<br />
to law and order when the Springboks arrived. It was a pretext and it was an excuse<br />
by Mr. Hawke and some of his colleagues to show their form and to show their capacity<br />
for intimidation. And the professional demonstrators and dissenters and a lot of them<br />
were jumped on the band wagon without wasting a second of time.<br />
Now the Government, our Government in Canberra, had to make its<br />
position clear. And at the time I stated three important principles that were dear to<br />
us, and that we would ensure were followed and observed. I think that they're worthwhile<br />
repeating at the moment. And they are and I repeat what I have said but a<br />
few moments ago that the Australian people, the you and me's of this world, the<br />
people that constitute not only the Liberal and the Labor Parties, the uncommitted,<br />
the young and everyone in the community, have a right of freedom of choice within<br />
the law at all times. Nobody has the right to deprive them of this freedom of choice. e / 4 </p>
<p>And the second great principle is that no group or organisation should be<br />
permitted to intimidate the lawful Government of the country whether it happens to<br />
be State, Local Government, or Federal Government as it exists in Canberra. Now<br />
we reject absolutely any attempt by elements in the Trade Union movement to achieve<br />
their objectives, industrial or otherwise, by force and intimidation.<br />
And the last one a fairly simple one is that frankly we believe there<br />
is an area of politics, we believe there is an area of sport. We believe there are areas<br />
of cultural relations such as musical activities, or the movement of ballet companies,<br />
and we do not think for one moment, that the sporting and other organisations should be<br />
under duress from any source purely for political motives. I also remind you too, if<br />
I can~ of the basis on which we operate.<br />
I believe that the principles that we have held ever since we were first<br />
formed as a Party remain just as valid and absolute today as they did when they were<br />
first announced. So what I want to read to you now is a part of what was said by us<br />
in a little document published by Sir Robert Menzies called " We Believe". It's this:<br />
" The Liberal Party offers the spirit of adventure, the<br />
fire freedoms of thought and speech and choice, the<br />
great human right to choose an avocation and fail,<br />
or to choose an avocation and succeed.<br />
In other words, to put it in my own way, to act as men and women, and to<br />
be able to do what you want to do, providing you do it, as 1 said before, within the law.<br />
I think we should keep on remembering this against the possible background of<br />
increasing industrial outrages in the months to come.<br />
May I now come to the other subject I want to mention and that is China.<br />
And before I come into the body of my speech, may I just mention two facts to you.<br />
The first one relates to the fact that memories are short, and that -there<br />
are some discussions taking place today about the possibilities of another Geneva-type<br />
convention. I well remember, shortly after I became the External Affairs Minister<br />
( now the Foreign Minister) going up to South Vietnam to see our own troops and to see<br />
how Vietnamisation was progressing. And on the way there I met representatives<br />
of various Asian countries. Together we decided that we would have a conference<br />
in Djakarta, dedicated to trying to get peace in Cambodia and to permit this country<br />
to be able to live free, and particularly free from intimidation from the North.<br />
We invited China, we invited the Communist countries, but they<br />
blatantly refused to come. But we did send emissaries around the world trying to<br />
find out whether there was anything that could be done and we even tested the United<br />
Nations without result.<br />
So I want you to understand that we as a Liberal Government have been<br />
seeking for peace. Thinking that the cause of peace was one of the highest ideals<br />
that we asLiberals possess, and a) nsequently I now want to debunk any idea that<br />
somebody has take n the initiative away from us. It is totally false. We want peace,<br />
we know that Vietnamisation is succeeding and we do know it now, we at least want to<br />
preserve the basic cause for which we fought, and that was the right of the South<br />
Vietnamese to be able to determine their own future. 0 0 </p>
<p>Now may I come to the second point that I wanted to mention to you, and<br />
that is about recognition of Continental China, the People's Republic of China in the<br />
United Nations, and recognition itself.<br />
Shortly after I became Minister for External Affairs, I called for papers<br />
to be prepared and presented to the Cabinet, as to what our attitude should be at the<br />
United Nations, because as I mentioned a few moments ago, we had then taken up a<br />
precise and definite attitude,<br />
Similarly, too, did I decide, or did I recommend and the Cabinet decided<br />
that we would make the preliminary move, called a dialogue, with the People's Republic<br />
of China to see what their attitude might be, to recognition. Now when I talk about the<br />
People's Republic for brevity's sake I'll say " China", but I want you to understand<br />
that it means Peking China, or Communist China. We have had meetings with their<br />
plenipotentiaries so far unsuccessful. Not because of our attitude -we did make<br />
an attempt to show them what we were prepared to do-but because of the fact that<br />
they were not prepared to listen unless we agreed to all of the terms that they had<br />
proposed. So now may I come back then to the speech that I want to make and speak<br />
to you about China itself.<br />
There has been, as we all know, certainly most Liberals will know, some<br />
evidence that China was getting ready to lift the boom which has kept her isolated from<br />
the Western world for so long. And, as is prudent, we have had our China policy<br />
under review for a considerable time. I repeat this again, because I don't want to let<br />
somebody jump onto the band wagon and say the opposite that recent developments<br />
in our policy have been precipitated by public interest in China's person-to-person<br />
or as somebody calls it the ping-pong diplomacy.<br />
Neither do I think China's new interest in the outside world reflects a<br />
change of heart. I don't. It would be more accurate to describe her recent initiatives<br />
as a new tactical approach to old goals. Not new, but with skill, and with diplomatic<br />
common sense, they have used the Labor mission for the benefit of the Chinese themselves.<br />
Now the goals, and I want to emphasise this of the Chinese people, are<br />
these. You know that up on the Ussuri and other parts of the North, they have the problems<br />
with the Soviet, and consequently one of their biggest and most immediate problems is<br />
that of border security. They want a reduction in the influence of the United States and<br />
of the Soviet. They want a check on Japan and they want the spread of Maoist revolutionary<br />
theories by securing better relationships with smaller powers. And, of course,<br />
they do want the recovery of Taiwan, that is the Republic of China.<br />
Nevertheless whatever our dislike of her political philosophy, we<br />
regard China as a fact of life in the region. And, indeed, as a fact of life in the wider<br />
world, and we must look forward in the long run to normal relations with them.<br />
But I want to emphasise, we will have a dialogue not on their terms,<br />
but on terms that we regard as satisfactory to us as Australians and to the people<br />
of this country. / 6 </p>
<p>The position now is that fifty-four countries have diplomatic relations<br />
with China and sixty-three with Taiwan. Since last October nine countries have<br />
announced they will establish diplomatic relations, but none of them was in our region<br />
None were immediately to the North of us, none were countries with which we have<br />
regional associations and relationships, and whose security we regard as important<br />
to our own. Not only as a result of my mission to the United Nations, but in what<br />
I have been able to learn since, I have formed the opinion that it is probably that<br />
either this year or next, Peking will become a member of the General Assembly of the<br />
United INations and will I think have a seat on the Security Council. We will not oppose<br />
membership I have said this over and over again. It niusn't be forgotten. Some<br />
people will attempt to jump on the band wagon and try and prove to the c ontrary.<br />
But what we will do is this, we will do all in our power to ensure that<br />
Taiwan, that has 14 million people, that is a member of the United Nations now,<br />
and is recognised by us and is a very good trading partner of ours -Taiwan is a<br />
better trading partner than China itself, that is Continental China -that Taiwan's<br />
posritio2 is recogniscd and its position in the United Nations sustained.<br />
When we are taking this action, of course, we consult with our friends,<br />
part icularly the United States, Japan arid New Zealand. They, toohave already had<br />
some contact with China through diplomatic sources. Or perhaps I should take that<br />
back and I should localise it to ourselves. I don't want to speak for them. I repeat<br />
again that we have had contact with the Chinese Government through other national<br />
sources, We have set out directly to Peking what is our long-term goal and our<br />
desire to take progressive steps towards this. It would be very optimistic to expect<br />
any quick returns. We must move cautiously, with our own national self-interest<br />
uppermost in our minds at all times. And I want to repeat that because I want you to<br />
understand the contrast. VWe will move slowly and cautiously, beca4,% eit is our vital<br />
interest that must be uppermost in our minds. And the contrast is the mission<br />
of the Labor Party recently in Mainland China was moving ilot in our interests, but<br />
dangerously close to the interests of Mainland China-, and dangerously opposed to<br />
the interests of many of our great friends.<br />
N-ow the question of recognition will arise in due course, but as I saidit<br />
may be a long way off. And we don't intend to rush it. Let me give you a few more<br />
facts about the relationships we already have with the People's Republic. This is<br />
important, because some would create the impression that they are completely isolated.<br />
There has been a two-way trade between us both for a good many years,<br />
and recently, and the businessmen here should be told this, we recently liberalised<br />
the list of strategic exports so that the range of trade could be widely extended. And<br />
I ask all businessmen to have a look at this restricted list because they will see, that<br />
that range of opportunities is great, and has been expanded by the Liberal-Country<br />
Party Government in recent months.<br />
There is no discrimination against China in our tariff and import policies.<br />
Although China is not a member of GATT', we have applied GATT rules against<br />
nondiscrimination to China and we will continue to do so. We give her, like other<br />
countries, most favoured nation treatment. / 7 </p>
<p>Furthermore, we have no barriers to visitors from the People's<br />
Republic. They want to come here, and unless there are defence or PtL: dLC%' 1A4 rpnwe<br />
permit them to come, and to come freely. They can come as it were, like any<br />
other visitors, subject only to procedures of a normal kind which I've just mentioned.<br />
But on its part, China exercises the strictest control over visitors. Here there is no<br />
reciprocity and this must be understood by all of us.<br />
Now gentlemen, you will have been reading about this and I've spoken<br />
about it a few moments ago and that is the Labor Party' s mission to China in the last<br />
week. I have already exposed the shams and the absurdities of it all. But I want to go<br />
over some of the points again because they are of considerable importance to you and<br />
they are of overwhelming importance to the security of this country.<br />
They went to China to play politics with w~ heat. I emphasise they went<br />
to play politics. Mr. Anthony said yesterday, that we warnt to leave it to the<br />
established organisations to carry out our trading relations, particularly if they have<br />
been as extraordinarily successful as the Wheat Board. Mr. Anthony said only<br />
py eusrctehradsa4y n gt haagt etnhcei eWs. h eaTt hBe oBaroda rdit sfeellft , htIt'J e had sntrcoonsagt chnotcp es that the iWhthhea t BhouarVd would<br />
sooni have received an invitation to go to Hong Kong to negotiate further contracts.<br />
But because of the attitude, and the activities of the Labor Partythose<br />
hopes were dashed. Instead of going, they have had to be suspended for some time.<br />
I want you to understand that politics and trade relations don't mix. If<br />
you do play politics you can do great harm and damage to Australia's rural industries.<br />
In this case I believe they have done damage to the cause of wheat.<br />
In a series of public statements, Mr. V. 7hitlam committed himself and<br />
his Party to a policy, which I think is an affront to most of Australia's friends and<br />
allies in South-East Asia and the Pacific. And here again I want to interpolate that<br />
Dr. Patterson apparently says that I have been attacking China. Far from the truth.<br />
I've been attacking not China but Mr. Whitlam's intrusion into Foreign Affairs, and his<br />
insulting references to our friends. I can understand Dr. Patterson's confusion of<br />
mind. Whitlam has become the advocate for China. He is not the advocate<br />
for this country. This I have said can be dangerous for us.<br />
The Chinese Premier, Mr. Chou En-Lai cannot be blamed for taking<br />
up the opportunity for some telling propaganda when Mr. Whitlam went to see him.<br />
What is dangerous, and what is damaging, is the extent to which Mr. Whitlam picked<br />
up and made his own the points China has been trying to impose on the world for<br />
years. He said he would recognise China immediately if he were to win the<br />
next elections. He went further. He would sever diplomatic relationships with Taiwan<br />
and further still, he would declare Peking the " sole Government to China". </p>
<p>In other wordshe would abandon Taiwan, that has been very close to us,<br />
and friendly with us, and as I said a few moments ago, has been a good trading partner,<br />
and one that has assumed its proper role in the diplomatic and international world<br />
and does play its part as a responsible member of that world. These are perhaps<br />
the most startling by a political leader without power or authority in many, many<br />
years. I wonder if this could have happened if it had been the late Mr. Chiefly<br />
or the late Mr. Curtin. Could they ever have conceived of operating in a way that could<br />
be inimical to the interests of this country and dangerous to them.<br />
He made matters worse by gratuitously insulting countries like<br />
Thailand and the Philippines, who are friendly, and a country like the Soviet Union<br />
with whom we are trying and have, in fact, developed a better understanding.<br />
There was no dialogue about his meeting with the Chinese. He took the<br />
bait and he swallowed it whole. He came away without any assurances from Premier<br />
Chou at all. He made all the concessions in a field which was not in his area to operate<br />
anyway. This is an area for Government, and not an area for an itinerant politician<br />
moving into China, and now trying to move into other parts of South-East Asia.<br />
In addition he allowed himself to be used as a spokesman for the North<br />
Vietnamese and Chinese propositions at the Paris peace talks.<br />
Altogether it was an extraordinary performance. For us it is a warning<br />
and a sample of what Mr. Whitlam and the Labor Party would do if they ever come to<br />
power. We as Liberals, every single one of you, from the Premier. to myself,<br />
you joining with us, must make certain this does not happen.<br />
I come back to where I started, that the Liberal Party commands the<br />
loyalty of the great mass of Australians. Everywhere I've been in the last four<br />
months, I've become more and more convinced of the certainty of that statement.<br />
I believe we Liberals have a record behind us to justify that confidence, and that<br />
we have progressive policies to keep that confidence alive. I am sure we will win<br />
the next elections, but with your help, with the help of Angus Bethune, with<br />
the help of the other Liberal Premiers, let's make it a good one. Let's make it a<br />
handsome victory and give us the opportunity to carry on our policies, for at least<br />
another three years. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
