<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4877</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED IN MELBOURNE OVER HCF CONTROVERSY - 3 NOVEMBER 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004877.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRINE HI-J-S'ER INTERVIEWED IN INETBOURNE OVER HCF ( fl4MRVERSY 3 NOVmBER 1978<br />
Question: Can you guarantee that chronically ill patients will<br />
receive some adequate form of health protection?<br />
Mr. Fraser: The Government is very concerned about this.<br />
Ralph Hunt is concerned and we had talked about it this<br />
morning and we are quite determined that the chronically ill<br />
people should be protected and I have asked the Minister to<br />
prepare an urgent report for Cabinet on the issue. we will be<br />
looking at it next week. I can't go beyond that because I don't<br />
know the details but we will have the report and it will be<br />
taken further through the Cabinet meeting.<br />
Question: What about private funds such as HCF, which has<br />
told chronically ill patients that their costs will not be met?<br />
Mr. Fraser: I think that people insure not to cover when they<br />
are well, as you an ' d I are, but to cover the circumstances when<br />
they are ill and if somebody has a long terminal chronic illness<br />
they need the cover of insurance all the more. Now, I think we<br />
need to show a little concern for those who need help most and<br />
that's why Ralph Hunt's concerned; that's why I'm concerned.<br />
I am surprised at the attitude that some funds have taken. Now<br />
the Government's got an intention in this matter. It's * a firm<br />
one but how that shall be encompassed -well, we need a report<br />
from the Minister on that. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
