<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8746</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING DR HEWSONS DOCTORS</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008746.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 132/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON~. P. J. KEATING<br />
DR HEWSON'S DOCTORS<br />
It is no wonder the AMA. is campaigning for Dr Hewson.<br />
Doctors can expect $ 760 million from the fee increases<br />
which Dr Hewson will allow, and another $ 300 million<br />
from the increased numbers of private patients which Dr<br />
Hewson's policies are designed to create.<br />
Dr Howson has offered doctors what is surely the biggest<br />
-bribe per person in Australian history more than $ 1<br />
billion for about 40,000 people.<br />
This from the man who so often accuses others of doing<br />
deals with vested interests.<br />
If the Doctors for Dr Hewson are really concerned about<br />
people and not their own pockets, they might ask<br />
themselves whether his economic and social policies are<br />
good for Australians' health?<br />
is the withdrawal of $ 7 billion from the economy good for<br />
people's health?<br />
Is a 15 per cent tax on food and services good for their<br />
health? Is knocking them of f unemployment benefits after nine<br />
months good for their health?<br />
Are lower wages and less job security good for their<br />
health? And Australians might ask themselves why the elite of the<br />
medical profession would campaign for the type of health<br />
system which Americang have just overwhelmingly rejected?<br />
Why would they campaign against a system which is fair,<br />
comprehensive and makes-quality health care * accessible to<br />
all. And one which is consistently supported by a<br />
majority of Australians? </p>
<p>J.-4* ui F<br />
2<br />
Dr Hewson tells us that he's out to break the mould of<br />
Australian politiCS. This is palpable nonsense.<br />
In fact he's out to break the mould of<br />
society. His industrial relations policy is one example.<br />
His health policy is another.<br />
As Peter shack the former health spokesman stated in the<br />
notorious January 1990 press conference with " all the<br />
frankness" he could muster, " the Liberal and National<br />
Parties do not have a particularly good track record in<br />
health." There appears to be no danger of Dr Hewson displaying<br />
the courage and honesty of Mr Shack.<br />
He hasn't held a press conference for a year.<br />
CANBERRA December 1 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
