<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9233</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, HYATT HOTEL, MELBOURNE FRIDAY 13 MAY, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009233.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J<br />
KEATING, MP<br />
HYATT HOTEL, MELBOURNE<br />
FRIDAY 13 MAY, 1994<br />
J: ( inaudible)... Mr Kennett's bid for the Soccer World Cup?<br />
PM: No, I think States take these things on themselves and generally<br />
manage them well.<br />
J: How will the Aboriginal land fund be administered?<br />
PM: Oh, I don't think this doorstop is the place to assess the Aboriginal<br />
land fund. But, I tell you what I would like to say I would like to pass<br />
a comment about JohnSmith, the late John Smith, the Leader of the<br />
British Labour Party. And just record the fact that this was somebody<br />
of great substance, a great loss to Britain, to the Labour Party, to<br />
British society. He was a man who believed in a modern economy and<br />
the modernisation of the British economy, but being able to do so in<br />
the context of a social policy which provided a lot of cohesion and<br />
compassion. And he's going to be very greatly missed. I extend my<br />
sympathies to his wife and family and to the British Labour Party and<br />
say that, in the Australian Labour Party he was thought of very highly.<br />
For the future, we wish the Labour Party well in the choice of its new<br />
leader but many people in Australia remember John Smith and his<br />
contribution fondly, and well.<br />
J: Prime Minister, are you still confident the Budget will pass without<br />
trouble given that Kernot has spoken...( inaudible)... Dr Hewson?<br />
PM: Well, the Budget has four and a half percent growth forecast in it, it<br />
consolidates the tax cuts of last year, it has no new taxes or increases<br />
in tax rates and it has a whole lot of social spending the Aboriginal<br />
land fund, $ 500 million on Aboriginal programs, $ 209 million for breast<br />
cancer, money for a child immunisation program, money for foreign<br />
aid... These are all the things that I would have thought that the </p>
<p>Democrats and the Greens, particularly, would be supporting. And, I'd<br />
find it very difficult for them to take exception to it.<br />
J: On world cup soccer, it can't be just one city that vies for it, it has to be<br />
a national effort. Will you support Mr Kennett in that?<br />
PM: Well, he's not approached me about it.<br />
J: Don't you think it is wrong that he hasn't?<br />
PM: Well, the answer is no. I don't go around, at every street corner,<br />
building stadiums. I mean, governments have a process by which they<br />
deal with one another about matters like this.<br />
J: Cambodia Prime Minister...( inaudible)...?<br />
PM: Well, we want to see the peace in Cambodia consolidated. We've<br />
always hoped that the Khmer Rouge would join in a political compact<br />
with other parties in Cambodia. And we will be underwriting<br />
assistance to Cambodia I think, probably, well into the future. We<br />
haven't decided how best that should be done. Whether that's with<br />
any military material which may be used by the government there, in<br />
whatever way, or whether it ought to be just by civil programs. But,<br />
this is a matter the government can think about.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, I don't think I'm here to go through a history of Cambodia, either.<br />
J: On the structural... ( inaudible)... of the Budget, is there any pressure<br />
on monetary policy...( inaudible)?<br />
PM: Well, as I said here today, I hope eloquently, that is, Australia's return<br />
to a balanced Budget and surplus will be faster than all Western<br />
economies bar one, Germany. And the reason Germany's coming<br />
down is because it's had a bigger problem than we have had. So, to<br />
take the Australian Budget down faster would be appropriate only if the<br />
growth is faster than we predict. And, if it is, it will be good for the<br />
country and good for the Budget. But, we've got endemically low<br />
inflation and, therefore, the portents for interest rates into the future<br />
are pretty good.<br />
Ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
