<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5672</transcript-id>
    <title>STATE TO THE HOUSE: RIVER MURRAY WATERS AGREEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/10/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005672.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 20 OCTOBER, 1981<br />
STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE: RIVER MURRAY WATERS AGREEMENT'<br />
I am pleased to inform the House that the Commonwealth,<br />
New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia have endorsed<br />
a draft of a new River Murray Waters Agreement. This was the<br />
outcome of a meeting'which the Minister for National Development<br />
and Energy and I attended last Friday in Melbourne, together<br />
. with the three respective Premiers and their Water Resources<br />
Ministers. The Premiers and I have agreed that the draft new agreement<br />
now be referred to the Crown law advisers of the four<br />
Governments with a view to the early introduction of the<br />
necessary legislation.<br />
In the meantime, the River Murray Commission has been<br />
authorised to operate fully within the terms of the new agreement,<br />
pending completion of the necessary legislative action. The<br />
draft new agreement is the result of the first major review<br />
of the agreement signed in 1914.<br />
It is now proposed to expand the responsibilities of the River<br />
Murray Commission to include water quality in addition to the<br />
responsibilities it now has for water quantity in the main stem<br />
of the ri'Ver and associated storages. At the same time, the<br />
agreement is being updated to make it more relevant to present<br />
day requirements by giving the River Murray Commission<br />
responsibilities in regard to other water management objectives.<br />
Under the proposed new agreement, the River Murray Commission will<br />
be authorised to formulate river water quality objectives or<br />
standards, as appropriate, for various locations on the river.<br />
State authorities will be required to inform the Commission<br />
of all proposals under their consideration which could<br />
significantly affect water quality and quantity in the river and<br />
provide the necessary information to permit an assessment of<br />
their likely impact.<br />
Obviously, the agreed water quality objectives will be of central<br />
relevance to such an assessment. The Commission will be empowered<br />
to make representations as necessary to the appropriate State<br />
authority on such proposals.<br />
Further, the water distribution provisions of the new agreement<br />
will enable account to be taken of the quality of the inflows<br />
of tributaries and man-made outfalls in assessing the credits of<br />
the States in the Commission's water accounting procedures. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Rules are to be drawn up for this purpose. As in every<br />
river system, water quality in the River Murray is the end<br />
product of numerous activities which take place in the catchment<br />
in irrigation, dryland agriculture, processing industries,<br />
urban centres, forestry, etc. These are all State responsibilities.-<br />
There is no intention of the River Murray Commission having a<br />
regulatory function, the power of sanctions in regard to these<br />
matters or the right to interfere in the States' affairs.<br />
The new arrangements aim at a joint assessment of all'r'elevant.<br />
water and land use and other factors significantly affecting<br />
water quality. This is consistent with the development of<br />
river management strategies where a river and its catchment fall<br />
within the responsibility of a single Government.-<br />
While in this regard-the River Murray Commission will have onl. y<br />
the power of persuasion, its representations will be based on<br />
mutually agreed water quality objectives or standards, and onl<br />
an ever increasing body of knowledge of the river system and its<br />
problems. Subject to the new water quality provisions, the current water<br />
sharing principles and arrangements between the three States will<br />
continue. South Australia will be entitled to 1.85 million<br />
megalitres annually as measured at the South Australian border<br />
in accordance with specified monthly volumes. This includes t: he<br />
recent 23% increase made possible by the completion of'<br />
Dartmouth pam. The two upper States will share the balance of<br />
* the water ieources available to the River Murray Commission, but<br />
with some flexibility to cope with year-to-year pressures in<br />
* water demands.<br />
While the River Murray Water Agreement is, and will continue to remain,<br />
the main policy instrument for the Commonwealth's involvement<br />
with the three States in the management of the nation's most<br />
important water resource, considerable financial assistance has<br />
been provided to the three States for those salinity control and<br />
drainage works in the Murray valley which fall outside the ar-ea<br />
of the Commission' s own responsibilities.<br />
These are all priority works recommended by consulting engineers,<br />
Maunsell and Partners, in the plan of action they proposed in<br />
their 1979 report on salinity and drainage problems in the<br />
Murray valley. By the end of this financial year, we will have<br />
provided about $ 18 million in grants to the cost of underground<br />
and surface saline water drainage works on a dollar for dollar<br />
basis with the three States a total of around $ 36 million.<br />
Together, we are well advanced in the implementation of urgent<br />
works identified in the Maunsell plan of action.<br />
It is the view of this Government that before any decisions are<br />
contemplated regarding a follow-up to the implementation of the<br />
plan of action, time must be allowed for thp.-accumulation and.<br />
assessment of vital information arising from three important<br />
recent joint Commonwealth/ States initiatives. / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
We need to know the effectiveness of the new water quality<br />
responsibilities now proposed for the River Murray Commission, the<br />
full operational impact of Dartmouth Dam and the efficiency of<br />
salinity control projects already completed, or under construction..<br />
Subject to this review, we will give careful consideration to new<br />
salinity control projects in accordance with priorities identified<br />
by the States in conjunction with the River Murray Commission-<br />
This was done, recognising that to an extent, because of the measurls<br />
already undertaken, the Maunsell report is already to a degree outof<br />
date.<br />
Basic data for this purpose is already being gathered. The-<br />
Commission has now established a water quality monitoring network<br />
along the river to record salinity and other key parameters and.<br />
consultants are being engaged shortly to develop a mathematical<br />
computer model to simulate the operations of the river system, no't<br />
only in terms of river flows and storage changes, but also in<br />
terms of river water quality. This model should be an invaluable<br />
instrument in the development and operation of long term strategies<br />
to reduce salinity in the river system to manageable<br />
proportions, and all efforts are being made to ensure its early<br />
completion. There are already signs that recent initiatives by the four<br />
Governments are gradually becoming effective. Water quality<br />
recordings by the River Murray Commission during last season' s<br />
severe drought indicated that salinity levels were lower than<br />
in previous comparable dry periods. This comparative improvement has<br />
been attributed to the initial operations of Dartmouth Dam, now<br />
about two-thirds full, and the effectiveness of already completed<br />
salinity control works.<br />
High river flows resulting from heavy winter rains and melting<br />
snow are having a beneficial flushing effect on the river system<br />
and adequate water supplies of good quality should be available'<br />
next season.<br />
It is recognised throughout the world where irrigation has<br />
induced salinity problems, that techniques which reduce the<br />
application of water surplus to plant requirements are essential<br />
to the success of any long-term strategy to bring the problem<br />
under control. Amendments in May and December 1980 to the Income<br />
Tax Assessment Act now provide strong inventives to irrigators to<br />
improve their watering practices. The new provisions of the Act<br />
allow full deductibility of expenditures for income tax assessment<br />
purposes on water conservation and conveyance, salinity control<br />
and associate drainage works in the same year as they are incurred.<br />
We understand that these incentives are now starting to become<br />
effective. However, a better definition of the magnitude of<br />
the problem is required and the four Governments agreed last<br />
Friday that a Commonwealth/ States working group should review the<br />
extent to which irrigators are now adopting improved irrigation<br />
practices and assess the possible need for additional incentives. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
It is clear that without complementary preventative measures<br />
at the farm level, initiatives by the four Governments in the<br />
fight against salinity will be impaired. The Government is<br />
mindful of South Australia's specific problems with River Murray<br />
water quality particularly during prolonged periods of<br />
minimum river flow conditions. To some extent, these problems;<br />
originate outside the State.<br />
In relation to drinking water, there is the additional problem of<br />
turbidity caused by the presence of suspended soil particles<br />
and organic material, which reflect run-off conditions in the'<br />
vast catchment including parts of Queensland.<br />
Commonwealth financial assistance, already reaching $ 40 million,<br />
is enabling South Australia to build a water filtration schemef<br />
or metropolitan Adelaide. Two filtration installations are<br />
already operational.<br />
' The scheme, when completed, will contribute significantly to<br />
an improvement in the colour and taste of drinking W4ater from the<br />
Murray integrated into Adelaide's water supplies. The River Murray<br />
Waters Agreement has worked to the advantage of all three States<br />
for over 60 years. Admittedly, managing the river for water<br />
quantity is far less demanding than taking account also of water<br />
quality, having regard particularly to the Constitutional<br />
role of the States in practically all aspects of water and land<br />
use which affect river water quality.<br />
We do not tnderestimate the difficulties and complex issues<br />
which lie ' ahead. But with goodwill on the part of everyone concerned<br />
and a determination to make the proposed new River Murray Waters<br />
Agreement work, the long-term environmental health of the river<br />
and the economic well-being of the numerous urban centres and the<br />
great irrigation settlements in the Murray Valley can be assured.<br />
The River Murray Commission and the agreement between the States<br />
is an example of the way in which many officials, or is the result<br />
of the way in which many officials and Ministers have over the years<br />
worked together to make sure that this great natural resource: is<br />
preserved and improved for future years. There are not only many<br />
thousands of farmers, many thousands of irrigators, but tens of<br />
thousands of people in rural communities as well the much larger<br />
number throughout South Australia of course who are dependent: on<br />
the River Murray and its systems. It really is one of Australia's<br />
greatest natural resources. It is only going to be used in the<br />
future to the best advantage of everyone concerned while the<br />
Governments concerned are prepared to work in co-operation,<br />
* recognising their responsibilities, each to each other. I would<br />
like to pay recognition to the officials of the Commonwealth and of<br />
the States, the State Ministers and to other Premiers who he: lped to<br />
bring this agreement about in a way which I believe is going to be<br />
beneficial to a very large part of Australia.<br />
00 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
