<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1703</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, CH, MP, ON WANT OF CONFIDENCE MOTION ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE VIP FLIGHT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001703.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY '&amp; iR<br />
The Rt Hon. HAROLD HOLT, M. P.,<br />
ON<br />
WANT OF CONFIDENCE MOTION<br />
ROYAL AUSTRALIAN AIR FORCE VIP FLIGHT<br />
.[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 31 October 1967]<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT ( Higgins-Prime<br />
Minister) * 2.55]-Mr Speaker, the Leader<br />
of the Opposition ( Mr Whitlam) has moved<br />
what by parliamentary practice is the most<br />
serious motion within the capacity of any<br />
member or section of the Parliament to<br />
move. He has moved that the House has<br />
no confidence in the Government. If that<br />
motion were carried, of course, the Government<br />
would go out of office. This is not an<br />
unfamiliar parliamentary technique; we<br />
have witnessed it many times over the<br />
years. It has become almost traditional in<br />
relation to the Budget brought down by the<br />
Treasurer. But with the whole gamut of<br />
Government policy to range over, with all<br />
the varied activities of a Commonwealth<br />
Government involved in military operations,<br />
involved in far-reaching foreign policy<br />
relationships, with the conduct of a great<br />
buoyant developing economy, with the<br />
problems of employment and social welfare<br />
-the whole gamut of national policy to<br />
seize on as a ground for attacking a government<br />
in office-the Opposition has not<br />
found an opportunity to do this until now<br />
when it comes to us on this particular issue.<br />
I am glad to think that the Commonwealth<br />
of Australia is regarded by honourable<br />
gentlemen opposite as being in such good<br />
15240/ 67 state in its domestic, foreign and defence<br />
situation that they have to turn to this<br />
issue in order to attack us.<br />
I welcome the motion. In point of fact<br />
I had intended not to anticipate it but to<br />
deal with what I believe were thoroughly<br />
unjustified and cowardly allegations made<br />
in the Senate last Friday against me and<br />
others. It is a welcome change to find the<br />
Leader of the Opposition, who throws out<br />
his chest and says ' I will debate with you<br />
in any forum of the Commonwealth',<br />
coming into this Parliament and debating<br />
with us here in the place where these<br />
debates should be conducted. If he really<br />
believed, and the Leader of the Opposition<br />
in the Senate ( Senator Murphy) believed,<br />
that I had lied to the Parliament and that<br />
my colleague the Minister for Air ( MT<br />
Howson) had. lied to the Parliament or that<br />
the Treasurer ( Mr McMahon) had lied to<br />
the Parliament, the proper place for him to<br />
state that was here before me where I<br />
could hear the charge and answer it. But<br />
the Leader of -the Opposition let his hatchet<br />
man in the Senate get the run on us. He<br />
let the matter run all round Australia on<br />
a Friday when we were not sitting, knowing<br />
that there would be no effective opportunity<br />
for me to deal with this matter at </p>
<p>length and to have it on the record until<br />
the Parliament met on the Tuesday.<br />
As soon as I saw these reports I let it be<br />
known through my own Press secretary to<br />
the Press Gallery in a formal set of words<br />
that I not only repudiated these charges but<br />
also that I would be seeking an opportunity<br />
to comment on them. The Leader of the<br />
Opposition said that he did not know that I<br />
was going to make a statement here today.<br />
Mr Irwin-He is a liar.<br />
Mr SPEAKER-Order! The honourable<br />
member for Mitchell will withdraw that<br />
remark. Mr Irwin-I withdraw it.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I do not know<br />
how far the honourable gentleman consults<br />
his colleagues. He says that he sought<br />
information from the Leader of the House<br />
( Mr Snedden). We were not able to ascertain<br />
until I had returned from lunch what<br />
the Opposition was doing. The Leader of<br />
the Opposition could have ascertained as<br />
soon as Cabinet rose what we were doing.<br />
I have here not notes prepared to answer<br />
the honourable gentleman in relation to a<br />
motion of no confidence but notes for a<br />
statement which I was to make to the<br />
House in which I would have dealt with the<br />
position which had arisen in the Senate.<br />
Mr Daly-Make it now.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I will, and I shall<br />
take longer to do it than the Leader of the<br />
Opposition who went through one of the<br />
most laboured performances on a motion<br />
of no confidence that I have heard in this<br />
place. The irony of it is that a motion of<br />
no confidence on the ground of the Government's<br />
untruthfulness is presented by a man<br />
who, as Leader of the Opposition, has<br />
established a record for lack of credibility<br />
unequalled, in my experience, in the history<br />
of Federation. He is the man who says:<br />
' The Government cannot tell us the facts<br />
or the truth.' There is not a man on this<br />
side of the House who has not challenged<br />
the credibility of statements made by the<br />
honourable gentleman opposite. I mention<br />
only one in passing. He told us the other<br />
day that only one government in South<br />
East Asia supported the bombing policy<br />
of the United States of America. I will<br />
not elaborate. There will be another<br />
occasion when we can examine his statement<br />
in more detail. But should we move a motion of no confidence in the Leader<br />
of the Opposition because he so wilfully<br />
misstated the facts of that situation? There<br />
are scores of illustrations.<br />
In the statement I proposed to make to<br />
the House I wanted to deal with three<br />
aspects. One was the important constitutional<br />
issue raised in the Senate. I hope that<br />
honourable members of this House of<br />
Representatives who have some regard for<br />
the authority of this chamber will allow me<br />
to develop that, because it concerns where<br />
we stand and where governments drawn<br />
principally from this chamber stand in<br />
relation to the Houses of the Parliament.<br />
The second aspect of my intended statement-<br />
I felt almost apologetic at having to<br />
do this-dealt with what I can describe only<br />
as the trivia raised in the Senate discussion.<br />
I had made two statements to the<br />
House on this subject. After the second I<br />
replied to the Leader of the Opposition who<br />
had spoken following my statement. So, had<br />
I made another statement today, it would<br />
have been my fourth statement-and I hope<br />
a reasonably comprehensive statement, in<br />
four weeks on the VIP fleet.<br />
I think it was in my second statement<br />
that I said: ' I hope we can avoid the pettifogging<br />
and concentrate on the pertinent'.<br />
The need for this comment is apparent to<br />
anybody who takes the trouble to read the<br />
debate in the Senate. It is true that two<br />
issues of substance were raised. I have mentioned<br />
the constitutional issue. I will deal<br />
with the other later. It relates to the information<br />
given by the Government. Much<br />
of the rest of the debate was devoted to the<br />
pettifogging trivial matters that had led<br />
me to warn the Parliament, and long before<br />
that to warn the Press, that the<br />
answers to the questions asked of us, if<br />
given by us in the form sought, could only<br />
create a quite misleading impression and<br />
give a distorted view of-what is happening.<br />
That is why we delayed the answers to the<br />
five questions asked by Senator Turnbull.<br />
Unless the Parliament had a background<br />
knowledge of how the flight is actually conducted<br />
and an authoritative statement on<br />
the subject, the answers would be hopelessly<br />
misleading and in some respects, for practical<br />
reasons that can be instanced, would be<br />
to a degree inaccurate. What I feared would<br />
happen did happen and I will come to some<br />
of the detail of it in a moment. As I said,<br />
while I apologise to the House for taking </p>
<p>time to deal with matters which to fair<br />
minded and sensible people must seem<br />
pretty trivial, they are on the record and<br />
while they stand uncorrected I know the use<br />
that will be made of them by honourable<br />
gentlemen opposite.<br />
Mr Courtnay-You bet your boots.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I know that boots<br />
are a weapon of offence with which you<br />
would be familiar. We do not act in that<br />
way. Your philosophy is boots and all. But<br />
we do not think that is the way the Australian<br />
people would like to have their<br />
fighting done. Let me just deal-and I will<br />
try to do it quite speedily-with these<br />
aspects. Firstly, the attack on my wife and<br />
my family. I concede that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition and, indeed, the only other<br />
honourable member who spoke at any length<br />
on this matter, the honourable member for<br />
Hindmarsh ( Mr Clyde Cameron), said that<br />
there was a need for the VIP flight and that<br />
it was proper that the Prime Minister, going<br />
about his official duties, should use it. The<br />
honourable member for Hindmarsh conceded<br />
the same right to the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, as indeed I have always done<br />
myself. The honourable member said-and I<br />
give the honourable member for Hindmarsh,<br />
who is not usually liberal minded in these<br />
matters, credit for saying-that he did not<br />
see anything improper in my wife or my<br />
family accompanying me; that he was not<br />
churlish in these matters, if I can quote his<br />
own phrase. In point of fact I have exercised<br />
a good deal of care in relation to this,<br />
bccause I have had no wish either to<br />
embarrass my colleagues or to give the<br />
public any impression of abuse.<br />
When I drew on my own recollections the<br />
other day-and I say at this point of time<br />
quite clearly that I was drawing on my<br />
recollections-I had no knowledge of the<br />
papers which were subsequently produced in<br />
the Senate chamber. I have never misled this<br />
Parliament wilfully or wittingly in the 31<br />
years during which I have ' been a member<br />
of it. I have never had an attack that was<br />
established or, for that matter, as far as I<br />
can recall, seriously pressed against my good<br />
faith in providing information to this Parliament.<br />
If honourable gentlemen opposite try<br />
to dredge through the Hansard records over<br />
these decades, let them find the examples<br />
where my own good faith and the information I have given to this Parliament have<br />
come under attack. When I was speaking of<br />
my family I said that there had been only<br />
one occasion on which a flight had brought<br />
them on a journey without my personally<br />
being present. I have since had an opportunity<br />
of checking through the records and<br />
I find there were two other occasions, and I<br />
will mention them.<br />
One was an occasion on which an aircraft<br />
had been ordered for me because I was<br />
accompanying President Johnson to Melbourne<br />
on his official visit to Melbourne and<br />
as I was about to go on the aircraft-and my<br />
family were to accompany me back to Canberra<br />
in order to take part in official celebrations<br />
here connected with the President's<br />
visit-the President asked me whether I<br />
would join him on his aircraft so that we<br />
could have talks together. This flight appears<br />
on the manifest as a flight for my family,<br />
but it was a plane ordered to take me back<br />
to Canberra. This is one of the illustrations<br />
I have given of how, even when we present<br />
all the documents to the Parliament, misleading<br />
interpretations can still be brought<br />
into a matter. It may interest the House to<br />
know that the whole of my family returned<br />
the following day by commercial aircraft at<br />
their and my expense.<br />
The only other occasion-and my wife<br />
reminded me of this one-was on<br />
the day which preceded a 7.30 a. m.<br />
takeoff for Western Australia where<br />
we were going for several days of<br />
official visit to Perth and to developmental<br />
projects in the west. My wife had a<br />
speaking engagement in Sydney and she had<br />
to be there and back in time to get ready<br />
for this early morning takeoff the next day<br />
and to undertake all the necessary preparation<br />
for what looked like being a week's<br />
absence from either Melbourne or Canberra.<br />
As she was going to Sydney on this<br />
occasion she invited two of her daughters-inlaw<br />
to go with her for company. I do not<br />
know whether she was expected to make the<br />
flight alone and just sit and meditate, but<br />
anyhow, if it was a crime, she committed<br />
the crime of asking two of her daughters-inlaw<br />
to go with her on the flight there and<br />
back. I invite the honourable gentleman<br />
opposite to name any other occasions. They<br />
are the only two that I have been able to<br />
ascertain in addition to the one which I<br />
mentioned. I said then that no flight had<br />
been ordered especially for members of<br />
I </p>
<p>my family. When Princess Alexandra was<br />
here she was entertained by me at the<br />
Lodge. I wished to have my family with<br />
me while I provided this entertainment. The<br />
next morning an aircraft was going to Melbourne<br />
to pick up at least three Ministers.<br />
Two of the boys went off by commercial<br />
aircraft in the morning-because they wanted<br />
to be back at their offices in time. The rest<br />
of the family went down in the aircraft<br />
which was going to Melbourne anyhow to<br />
pick up the Ministers. I know of no<br />
occasion when an aircraft was positioned<br />
to take members of my family, other than<br />
my wife, to any occasion whatever.<br />
When not accompanying me, my wife<br />
has flown far more by commercial aircraft<br />
than she has by VIP aircraft. She does this<br />
when she goes about her official occasions.<br />
I think it proper that if she needs to have<br />
a VIP aircraft to make one of these trips<br />
it should be available to her. My wife has<br />
made two journeys to Whyalla. The first<br />
of these trips was made entirely by commercial<br />
aircraft. In order to get from Canberra<br />
to an aircraft which would pick her<br />
up at the appropriate time to take her to<br />
Whyalla and the function, and then wait<br />
till the chain of connections could be established,<br />
it took her the best part of 3 days<br />
to do the job. She said to me what a boon<br />
the new Mystere was because it left Canberra<br />
at 9.30 on the one morning, arrived<br />
at Whyalla by lunch time and returned<br />
to Canberra by lunch time the next day. I<br />
might add that this was an occasion when<br />
something was made of the fact that the<br />
passenger on the flight was the Ambassador<br />
of the United States of America, affectionately-<br />
or was it derisively-referred to<br />
by one of the honourable member's party<br />
colleagues in the other place as the ' Talking<br />
Horse'. That was his reference to this particular<br />
flight. Honourable members opposite<br />
may laugh about it if they wish, but those<br />
were the circumstances.<br />
I will not go through all the details as<br />
far as my colleague the Treasurer is concerned-<br />
he will speak for himself-except<br />
to say that he is one of the most hardworking<br />
men who has ever held a ministerial<br />
portfolio. He is handling a Budget of<br />
$ 6,000m apart from all the other financial<br />
transactions of the Treasury. He does not<br />
travel by himself, apart from the officials.<br />
The honourable gentleman made no mention of the fact that Ministers were frequently<br />
with the Treasurer because it sometimes<br />
happens that after a delayed Cabinet<br />
meeting they go in a group together. The<br />
Treasurer is named as the applicant for<br />
the flight and that is why he has clocked<br />
up such a record. He is the applicant.<br />
Ministers go along with him. If we were<br />
able to save an hour a day in working time<br />
for the Treasurer, I would think that any<br />
business organisation handling that kind<br />
of money would regard the saving as very<br />
well incurred.<br />
Reference has also been made to a gentleman<br />
who caught an aircraft that was going<br />
to pick up my colleague the Minister for<br />
Trade and Industry ( Mr McEwen) to bring<br />
him back to Canberra, so that they could<br />
talk on the trip back to Canberra. This was<br />
presented as a flight which this man had<br />
just managed to secure for himself. If honourable<br />
members look through these records<br />
which deal with people such as Hazel Craig,<br />
members of my own personal staff and<br />
others, they will find that in every instance<br />
the positioning of the aircraft that was being<br />
used for a particular flight was sought and<br />
obtained by somebody who was entitled to<br />
secure it. I could go through a mass of<br />
detail in this regard. However, I am not<br />
going to burden the House with it. I do not<br />
know of any occasion where it can fairly<br />
be said: ' There was an abuse in that particular<br />
instance'. I said earlier that the<br />
responsibility for this rests with my colleague,<br />
the Minister for Air, and with<br />
mygelf. Finally, I wish to refer to the point made<br />
by the Leader of the Opposition about the<br />
ordering of aircraft. Well, he has a point of<br />
semantics here, and I acknowledge it. What<br />
happened was that the aircraft for the flight<br />
were decided upon by Cabinet in the period<br />
of office of my predecessor. I have never run<br />
away from that decision. I was a party to<br />
it and I approved of it. But once the Cabinet<br />
decision had been taken, so far as I was<br />
concerned the matter was in the machine.<br />
I did not care when the aircraft were<br />
ordered. That was a job for the Minister<br />
for Air. The decision had been taken, and<br />
if the honourable gentleman wants this<br />
strictly on the record, as it should be, I<br />
make an amendment and say that no aircraft<br />
for the VIP flight was decided upon<br />
and added to that flight during my period </p>
<p>as Prime Minister of Australia. I hope that<br />
satisfies him.<br />
Let me just turn to the other matter<br />
which is, I believe, of some importance to<br />
this country constitutionally. I refer to the<br />
quite arrogant statement-<br />
Mr Clyde Cameron--Can you deal with<br />
the statement that the material was not<br />
available? Mr HAROLD HOLT-Yes, I am coming<br />
to that. I still have nearly 25 minutes<br />
left, even without an extension of time.<br />
Mr Cross-And you are uphill.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-Well, I have<br />
been uphill most of my life and I have got<br />
to the summit. I doubt that any honourable<br />
member opposite will ever get to it. The<br />
Leader of the Opposition in the Senate<br />
in opening his speech said this:<br />
Responsible government means that the Government<br />
is responsible for its administration to each<br />
House of the Parliament. For that purpose each<br />
House has an undoubted authority to require the<br />
Government to answer questions and to supply<br />
records bearing upon that administration. Each<br />
House is entitled to full and truthful disclosure by<br />
the Government. To deny this is to repudiate<br />
responsible government; to depart from it is to<br />
break down responsible government.<br />
The point I want to make is that it is<br />
the duty of a government to give as much<br />
information as it can which will be of<br />
assistance to either of the two chambers.<br />
Neither chamber has authority to require<br />
of an executive the tabling or presentation<br />
of documents or information which the<br />
government feels it would be against the<br />
public interest to table or present, or the<br />
tabling or presentation of which would<br />
constitute a breach of confidence which the<br />
government should preserve. But take this<br />
statement of the Leader of the Opposition<br />
in the Senate-an arrogant statement, I<br />
repeat-at its face value. He could demand<br />
the tabling of Cabinet minutes or of Cabinet<br />
documents. Of course he has no authority<br />
to do this. Or he could demand the tabling<br />
of confidential exchanges between the<br />
Premier of any State and the Prime Minister.<br />
Mr Odgers, the Clerk of the Senate,<br />
who has never been laggard in presenting<br />
the claims of that chamber, has had something<br />
to say on this matter which I regard<br />
of some constitutional importance. That is why I mention it. I quote from his book<br />
' Australian Senate Practice' at page 428:<br />
Upon a motion being agreed to for the tabling<br />
of Papers, the Clerk transmits a copy of the<br />
resolution to the responsible Department. The<br />
Paper is then delivered to the Clerk of the Senate,<br />
and by him laid on the table. The practice of<br />
moving for the tabling of papers was more<br />
common in the early years of the Senate.<br />
Then some precedents are given, and Mr<br />
Odgers continues:<br />
The question may one day arise: What happens<br />
if the Senate orders the production of certain<br />
papers and the responsible Minister refuses to<br />
table such papers? Technically, disobedience to<br />
the orders of the Senate is a contempt of the<br />
House. However, it is an issue yet to be resolved<br />
as to whether the Senate would take the matter<br />
further if, notwithstanding an order of the Senate,<br />
a Minister claimed he was entitled to refuse to<br />
table papers on the ground that certain documents<br />
were of a confidential nature or that disclosures<br />
would not be in the public interest.<br />
I am going to quote to the Housebecause,<br />
as a person who has been a<br />
member of this chamber for very many<br />
years and who is jealous of its rights and<br />
of the rights of a democratically elected<br />
Government I want it on the record-a<br />
sta'ement made by the Minister for Education<br />
in the Tasmanian House of Assembly<br />
on 17th May 1960. This is a statement<br />
that I think might well be adopted as sound<br />
policy in this chamber. It is in these terms:<br />
The particular practice which has caused the<br />
Government to consider this matter is the practice<br />
of requiring the return of a departmental file or<br />
of all papers and correspondence relating to a<br />
particular matter. If acceded to, such an order<br />
would. bring before the House a number of papers<br />
some , of which may be of a kind which should<br />
not be disclosed. The Minister is entitled to oppose<br />
an order for the tabling of papers of that kind,<br />
and if an order is made in the same circumstances<br />
he is entitled to refuse to comply with it.<br />
Considerations of public policy and a due<br />
regard for the interests of the State may require<br />
the Minister to withhold information either sought<br />
for or ordered to be returned. Were it otherwise,<br />
it would be impossible to carry on the Government<br />
with safety and honour. To disclose certain<br />
information may endanger the interests of the<br />
State or of individuals whose conduct or affairs<br />
are not in question, and to disclose information<br />
given in confidence would be dishonourable and,<br />
moreover, would stop any more information being<br />
given in confidence. The Minister concerned must<br />
of necessity take responsibility for decisions on<br />
these matters and so long as the House gives him<br />
its confidence its confidence must extend to such<br />
decisions. The same principles which apply to<br />
giving information to the House apply to select<br />
committees, which are not entitled to information<br />
which the House cannot demand or receive.<br />
It is possible that on some occasions a Minister<br />
would be willing to make available in his office, </p>
<p>or some other appropriate place, a file or particular<br />
document for perusal by members of the<br />
House, thus avoiding publishing the file or documents<br />
by laying them on the table of the House.<br />
I desire to make it clear to the House, however,<br />
that the Government has no wish to withhold<br />
from the House any information it is entitled to<br />
and that Ministers will not, without very good<br />
reason, refuse it any information.<br />
Having read that, Sir, I say that I agree with<br />
the sentiments expressed. So far as it has<br />
been within my capacity, I have sought to<br />
give to this House the information that it<br />
required. That brings me to the matter on<br />
which the Leader of the Opposition has<br />
dwelt in relation to the answers supplied<br />
to the question which was asked in this<br />
place by the honourable member for<br />
Grayndler ( Mr Daly) but which actually<br />
followed in point of time, as I recall it, a<br />
question asked in the other place by Senator<br />
Gair, the Leader of the Australian Democratic<br />
Labor Party. The interesting thing<br />
that the House will find about this business<br />
is that the answer given by us was not one<br />
that somebody could interpret as an answer<br />
protecting the position of the Government.<br />
In point of fact, it was an answer to a question<br />
asked by Senator Gair about use made<br />
by the then Leader of the Opposition of<br />
an aircraft on a flight to Western Australia<br />
and the people whom he took with him.<br />
The Leader of the Australian Democratic<br />
Labor Party asked about this. I suppose<br />
that if the Government had had the<br />
information readily available and had<br />
wanted to score some point off the Opposition,<br />
it could have said: ' Here is the<br />
information. This is what it is'. But the<br />
answer given at the time was that<br />
the particulars were not available.<br />
I hope that I do not do the honourable<br />
member for Grayndler an injustice, but he<br />
put his question during a period when he<br />
had ideas-not for his own advancement<br />
for he is, perhaps, too modest for thatthat<br />
some change in the leadership of the<br />
Australian Labor Party might be desirable.<br />
When he put his question on notice, rightly<br />
or wrongly, it was freely interpreted at the<br />
time as another attempt to give a bit of a<br />
nudge to the then Leader of the Opposition.<br />
Opposition members-Oh!<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT--The honourable<br />
gentleman received that same comment by<br />
way of reply. I move on from there to the answers<br />
given to Senator Turnbull, who had put<br />
several questions on the notice paper in<br />
another place. I tried to make available the<br />
detail that could be secured. I may say that<br />
the practice, as is well known in this<br />
House, is normally for a department to prepare<br />
a draft of an answer, submit it the<br />
the Minister and for the Minister then to<br />
settle his draft which is initialled by him<br />
and comes into the House. My own Department,<br />
which is asked questions which feed<br />
out into virtually every Department of<br />
state in one form or another, has to lean<br />
very heavily on the information supplied<br />
by the other department concerned. When<br />
the questions had been asked by Senator<br />
Turnbull-and I repeat that I mentioned a<br />
little earlier-I felt that before they were<br />
answered in detail, because to take them as<br />
they stood could result in the giving of misleading<br />
information, I should make a statement<br />
to the House. I set out, then, the way<br />
in which the fleet operated, the background<br />
to it and the history of it. The House will<br />
be familiar with those circumstances.<br />
Indeed, previously, as I told the<br />
House only the other day, the then<br />
Leader of the Opposition has notified<br />
my predecessor that the then Prime<br />
Minister would not find the then Leader<br />
of the Opposition questioning his use of<br />
the VIP fleet. After I had made my first<br />
statement neither the Leader of the Opposition,<br />
nor any of his colleagues, saw fit to<br />
take the opportunity then presented to discuss<br />
the matter. I believe I interpret their<br />
attitude correctly. As of that time honourable<br />
members opposite recognised the<br />
operation of the fleet as a necessary adjunct<br />
of modern government, as it is in so many<br />
other countries of the world.<br />
In between the time that I made that<br />
statement and the next one the honourable<br />
senators had been busy. They could see<br />
some political mileage in this, particularly<br />
with a Senate election forthcoming. Somewhat<br />
half-heartedly, when I had made my<br />
second statement, the Leader of the Opposition<br />
rose and made some comment. As I<br />
recall it, the principal ground of criticism<br />
was the Government's purchase of the<br />
BACllls, a matter that I dealt with by<br />
way of reply. The honourable member for<br />
Hindmarsh followed the Leader of the<br />
Opposition. His principal complaint was<br />
about the frequency of the use made of </p>
<p>the aircraft by the Treasurer. The honourable<br />
member confirmed -that this facility<br />
should be available for the Prime Minister<br />
and Leader of the Opposition. He believed<br />
that it should not be used too frequently<br />
by other Ministers, anrd in particular it<br />
should not be used by junior Ministers<br />
except in some abnormal circumstance.<br />
In my first statement I had said that I<br />
would examine the feasibility of getting<br />
costing done on ahis. I was not looking to<br />
conceal information; I was looking for ways<br />
and means by which this Parliament could<br />
be supplied with additional information on<br />
which there could be some periodical<br />
scrutiny of the costs of the service and some<br />
discussion as to how it operated. That<br />
statement was, I think I can reasonably<br />
state, well received in the House and produced<br />
only these two speeches of a not<br />
very penetrating kind from the Leader of<br />
the Opposition and his colleague. At that<br />
time, in addition to giving the story about<br />
dissection of costs, we dredged through the<br />
information available, or so I was given ; to<br />
understand, and I tabled a document which,<br />
of its very nature, was too unwieldy to<br />
incorporate in Hansard and said that the<br />
House could see the details which this<br />
statement produced.<br />
The matter then-went to the other place.<br />
Honourable senators were not satisfied with<br />
the information that had been supplied.<br />
They said: ' No. We want details about<br />
passengers.' It was in relation to the point<br />
about passengers that in each of the answers<br />
we said that the details were not available.<br />
To the best of my knowledge and understanding<br />
they were not available. I had<br />
always ' been given to understand that details<br />
of passengers were not kept for any length<br />
of time but were destroyed shortly afterwards<br />
because they were kept mainly for<br />
safety and recording purposes.<br />
The official book which is preserved, and<br />
preserved for a continuing period of years,<br />
is what is known as the Flight Authorisation<br />
Book. I have a copy of it here in my<br />
hand. I saw it for the first time last night. I<br />
did not know of the existence of this book<br />
or of the manifests which I also have here<br />
-manifests of a similar form if not related<br />
to identically the same matters, were tabled<br />
in the Senate-until my colleague, the<br />
Leader of the Government in the Senate<br />
( Senator Gorton), told me -that he would<br />
be tabling this information in addition to what I had already supplied following the<br />
request from honourable senators for<br />
papers. I inform the House, and I think<br />
the House will accept my statement, that<br />
the first time I knew of the existence either<br />
of this Flight Authorisation Book or of these<br />
manifests was when this was mentioned to<br />
me by the Leader of the Government in<br />
the Senate. The first time that I actually<br />
set eyes on them in this form was last<br />
night when I asked the Secretary of the<br />
Department of Air if he could make them<br />
available to me for inspection.<br />
Honourable members will find that this<br />
Flight Authorisation Book sets out in considerable<br />
detail matters such as action before<br />
flight, action after flight, serial number of<br />
order, date, type and number of aircraft,<br />
pilot or pilots, navigator, crew, the duty or<br />
practice ordered, time ordered -to start,<br />
duration of flight, initials of flight commander<br />
ordering flight, initials of pilot that<br />
he understands the order, time of take off,<br />
time landed, day or night, task training<br />
sequence, DCO-whatever that means-and<br />
initials of pilot as having reported -to flight<br />
commander on landing. That book contains<br />
no details of passengers except that where<br />
a VIP flight is involved it mentions the<br />
name of the Minister applying for the flight.<br />
If the Leader of the Opposition cares to<br />
look at this book he will see that many of<br />
the tasks listed are not VIP tasks but tasks<br />
associated with the operation of No. 34<br />
Squadron-training flights, the instrument<br />
landing system and so on.<br />
I niow refer to the manifests. These do<br />
set out the lists of passengers. Copies are<br />
made so that when a flight goes from one<br />
point to another a copy is left at the departure<br />
point and one is retained by the<br />
Squadron. If any amendment is necessary<br />
because of changes in the passenger composition<br />
then adjustments are made.<br />
Originally I was told that these were not<br />
kept for any great length of time and that<br />
the time they were kept might vary. I understand<br />
that there is an order that they<br />
should be kept for 12 months. How far<br />
that order is strictly observed I am in no<br />
position to say. But I have been told by<br />
the Secretary of the Department of Air<br />
that because once these manifests are used<br />
by the Squadron they are then used by<br />
other sections of the Air Force from time<br />
to time, it is doubtful if more than<br />
of them can be put together in one heap </p>
<p>at any one point of time. Others are<br />
scattered right throughout the Air Force<br />
for various purposes. They may ' be in the<br />
possession of a person checking on the<br />
instrument landing system, a person checking<br />
on the hours the aircraft has flown or<br />
a person checking for any other purpose.<br />
I do not claim to be a technician in Air<br />
Force matters; I am merely passing on what<br />
the Secretary of Air informed me. He only<br />
put the figure of 70% as a guess because<br />
nobody could be authoritative about it. The<br />
Secretary would not claim more than about<br />
accuracy for the detail shown on the<br />
manifests themselves because of sudden<br />
changes in movement. The Leader of<br />
the Opposition gave an example of this<br />
himself when he said that a Mr Wyndham<br />
was shown on a manifest. I understand<br />
from the Leader of the Opposition that<br />
Mr Wyndham did not travel at the time;<br />
nevertheless he is shown on the manifest.<br />
Mr Whitlam-He has never travelled in<br />
VIP aircraft with me.<br />
Mr HAROLD HOLT-I am merely<br />
making the point that these things are not<br />
necessarily precise and it has never been<br />
claimed that they are precise. I am not<br />
going to prejudge what the Minister for Air<br />
will have to say about these allegations. We<br />
have a good tradition in Australia that<br />
before we find a man culpable we give him<br />
a chance to speak in his own defence and<br />
to make his own explanation. The Leader<br />
of the Opposition has launched a no confidence<br />
motion against me, against the<br />
Minister for Air and against the Treasurer,<br />
but the Minister for Air has not yet had<br />
an opportunity to give his explanation. I<br />
admit readily to the House that I am<br />
troubled by the fact that answers were given<br />
in a form which did not accord with<br />
information which the Government itself<br />
has supplied. I emphasise that point; this<br />
was not something that was found somewhere<br />
around the country; we supplied this<br />
information as soon as we knew it was<br />
available and we did it after consultation<br />
between the Leader of the Government in<br />
the Senate and myself. We were not trying to conceal this information from the<br />
Parliament. Information on this matter can be misleading.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition was<br />
shown, as he will recall, as having had<br />
relatively few flights compared with the<br />
Treasurer. In point of fact if we apply the<br />
tests of hours in the air or mileage flown<br />
the result is not quite the same. We find<br />
that the Leader of the Opposition flew about<br />
60% of the mileage flown by the Treasurer<br />
-if positioning is taken into account-and<br />
had about 80% of the Treasurer's time in<br />
the air. Yet on the facts which were given<br />
the House in quite good faith-but with the<br />
warning that they could ' be misleading<br />
-one gets the picture of eight flights made<br />
by the Leader of the Opposition as against<br />
fifty-four flights made by the Treasurer. I<br />
just make known to the House the problem<br />
which the Minister for Air has had in<br />
facing up to these matters. He wanted to<br />
give accurate information. He was asked<br />
about passengers. It may be that he felt that<br />
because of the incompleteness and, to a<br />
degree, the inaccuracy of these records he<br />
could not validly say that a list of passengers<br />
was available. I am not trying to interpret<br />
what his -thinking was in the matter. I<br />
merely say, for myself and for the Government,<br />
that we have tried to keep the House<br />
fully informed. Of course, I will seek an<br />
opportunity to discuss with the Minister for<br />
Air how this matter developed. As a result<br />
of that discussion I hope to make such<br />
further information as arises available to the<br />
public and to members of both Houses of<br />
this Parliament.<br />
The Leader of the Opposition has moved<br />
a motion of no confidence. The effect of<br />
that motion would be, if carried, to throw<br />
this Government out of office and to put<br />
into Parliament and into government<br />
honourable gentlemen opposite, whose<br />
policies represent such a gulf of thinking<br />
between ourselves and themselves, and<br />
which were rejected wholeheartedly by the<br />
Australian people, that on a sober consideration<br />
of the facts I have no doubt about<br />
the position this House will take.<br />
BY AUTHORITY: A. J. ARTHUR, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
