<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11144</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   DOORSTOP INTERVIEW                 OPERA HOUSE, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>[Tape begins] Well the election result is due overwhelmingly to a</p>
<p> decision made about State political issues. I congratulate Mr Carr.</p>
<p> I will work constructively with him as Prime Minister and Premier</p>
<p> over the next few years. I commiserate with Mrs Chikarovski. I think</p>
<p> over the four-year period the Australian public, the New South Wales'</p>
<p> public made a judgement that the Labor Party ought to be returned.</p>
<p> And I do agree with Mr Carr that this campaign was fought overwhelmingly</p>
<p> on State political issues.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you agree with Mr Kennett that (inaudible) Mrs Chikarovski should</p>
<p> resign?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I haven't heard that he said that. And can I say that in</p>
<p> the wake of an election result it's always necessary that people</p>
<p> take a deep breath and they seriously examine why certain results</p>
<p> occur. I think the reality is that oppositions have got to develop</p>
<p> policies over a period of years. You can't just conjure them</p>
<p> up in the last few weeks.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think the Coalition would have done better under Peter Collins'</p>
<p> leadership?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think you can assert that at all. But they decided to</p>
<p> change leaders so it's a hypothetical question.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Nogarotto should be sacked in the opinion of Mr Kennett, do you</p>
<p> share that view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, six months ago people hailed the Coalition result in New South</p>
<p> Wales as being the main reason why my Government was returned. I think</p>
<p> it's very important that we don't blame the organisation.</p>
<p> I don't think it's the fault of the Liberal Party organisation</p>
<p> that we lost; I think collective responsibility lies with the parliamentary</p>
<p> party here in New South Wales  a collective responsibility,</p>
<p> and I'm sure that they understand that and I'm sure they're</p>
<p> going to set about to do something to change things but, they have</p>
<p> to do that over a period of four years. You can't do a little</p>
<p> over a few years and then imagine in the last few weeks you can turn</p>
<p> things around. Politics is not like that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Were there too many gaffes, were there too many....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to give a running commentary on the style of the</p>
<p> campaign.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Were you happy with the way the campaign went?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think that is a matter for others to comment on. All I can say to</p>
<p> the NSW organisation is that it performed magnificently and I agree</p>
<p> with what Mr Carr said  there were areas of Sydney like Menai</p>
<p> and Penrith that voted overwhelmingly for the Liberal Party six months</p>
<p> ago in the federal election and they voted with equal strength for</p>
<p> the Labor Party yesterday, and what that indicates very clearly is</p>
<p> that this was an election fought on State issues, and on entirely</p>
<p> different issues and you cannot blame the organisation....[inaudible]....</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
