<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2705</transcript-id>
    <title>FURLOUGH (LONG SERVICE LEAVE) FOR COMMONWEALTH OFFICERS AND EMPLOYEES AND FOR MEMBERS OF THE DEFENCE FORCES - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT  HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002705.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PM. No. .92/ 1972<br />
FURLOUGH ( LONG SERVICE3 LEFAVE) FOR COMMONWUEALTH OFFICERS<br />
AI4D EYNLOYEES AND FOR MEMBERS OF THE DEFENCE FORCES<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. William<br />
. Mciah'EoH CH, M?<br />
The Public Service Board has reviewed furlough-<br />
( long service leave) prov4 sions fcr Commonwealth officers and<br />
employees, having regard to various representations, including<br />
those-from staff associations. The ' 31overnment ha-, a'noroved the Board' s<br />
recommendations for a numiber of legislative amendments. These<br />
include: * reduction of the .) asic qualifying period ' from<br />
to 10 years<br />
* provision for furlough to be -made a right<br />
* paymentL-to t-he estate of a dece--ased officer or<br />
amp. loyee 1* 7hero th-Ierc are no dependants<br />
* extension of furlough to part-tm emloee<br />
* recognition for-furlough purposes of prior<br />
service with local cgoverning bodies.<br />
The Governmenit has authorised the Public Servico<br />
Board to advise relevant staff associations of the Proposed<br />
amendments and have anv necessarv discussions on detailis, -prior<br />
to the proarat,-ion of legi&amp; slation.<br />
The Government has also ani proved that any new<br />
provisions should have simultaneous app-ation to all members of<br />
the Def -ence Forces. The new provisions il come into effect when the<br />
relevant legislation the Public Service Act, the Commonwealth<br />
Employees' Furlough Act and the Service Firnancial Regulations<br />
can be amend~ ed.<br />
CA-NBERRA,<br />
26 Octobor 1972 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
