<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8433</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/03/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008433.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 21/ 92<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
YUGOSLAVIAN REPUBLIC OF MACEDONIA<br />
The Australian Government is acutely conscious of the<br />
sensitivities that are involved in relation to the question<br />
of the recognition of what is presently known as the<br />
Yugoslavian Republic of Macedonia.<br />
From the point of view of the people living in this and<br />
other parts of the region, and their friends and relatives<br />
abroad, we understand and symnpathise with their struggle to<br />
fulfil their legitimate aspirations for democracy and<br />
independence. We are concerned at the continuing human<br />
suffering which exists in the former Yugoslavia, and are<br />
totally supportive of the efforts within the EC and the UN<br />
to bring about a lasting peace.<br />
From the point of view of Greece, and the Greek community in<br />
Australia, the question of the recognition of the<br />
Yugoslavian republic known as Macedonia creates a number of<br />
problems which do not exist in relation to other present or<br />
former Yugoslavian republics.<br />
Greek concerns include:<br />
the use of the name " Macedonia", with all its<br />
historical and cultural associations with ancient<br />
Macedonia; doubts about Skopje's commitment to accepting the<br />
scovereignty and inviolability of the whole of<br />
present day Greece; and<br />
the question of the protection of minorities, in<br />
particular the Albanians who boycotted the 1991<br />
independence referendum. </p>
<p>Australia will not proceed to recognition until these basic:<br />
outstanding questions are resolved:<br />
the use of the word " Macedonia" being settled in a<br />
way that does not cause further tension with<br />
Greece; Greece's concern about possible territorial claims<br />
or aspirations being fully met; and<br />
the international community's concern about the<br />
protection of minorities being fully satisfied.<br />
We are aware of divided opinion on these issues in Europe<br />
and of efforts to find a mutually acceptable outcome between<br />
Athens and Skopje.<br />
Australia is firmly of the view that the recognition issue<br />
should be determined in a way which avoids creating new<br />
tensions in a region already undergoing such rapid change.<br />
CANBERRA 3 March 1992 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
