<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>143</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, C.H., Q.C., M.P. RECORDED FOR THE CELEBRATION PARTY TO MARK FIRST TEN YEARS OF FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HELD IN SYDNEY, THURSSDAY, 10TH DECEMBER, 1959</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000143_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTEI_, THE RT.<br />
HON. R. G. MENZIES, X. P. RECORDED<br />
FOR THE CELEBR TION PARTY TO MARK<br />
FIRST TEN YEARS OF FEDLEPAL GOVERNMENT<br />
HELD IN SYDNEY, THURSDAY, 10TH DECEMBER,<br />
1959<br />
I am very proud that you should have drunk my health<br />
( in my absence from Australia) and given me so much credit, undeserved<br />
though it may be, for the events of the last 10 years.<br />
On the other hand, I am very sorry that I should not be with<br />
you on so happy an occasion. My wife, who has done so much, has<br />
the same emotions. As you know, our relationships with South-East Asia are<br />
of tremendous importance to us. It would be a misfortune if we<br />
uere always to consider them in military terms. I therefore<br />
accepted invitations to go to Indonesia and to Malaya for a brief<br />
visit of goodwill and of understanding. It is of the greatest<br />
importance that in our dealings vrith our Asian neighbours we<br />
should emphasise our points of unity and not dwell too heavily<br />
upon our possible points of difference. Thus, it is that one<br />
of the main things to say to the Indonesians is that, apart from<br />
our difference of opinion about dest New Guinea, we both have all<br />
the reasons in the world for getting to understand each other and<br />
establishing positive friendship.<br />
In the case of Malaya, re already have considerable<br />
historical and current reasons for being friends. Australian<br />
capital and skill were many years ago invested in Malaya, particularly<br />
in tin and in rubber. Through the former Governor-<br />
General of Australia, Sir ; Jilliam McKell, we played an active and<br />
constructive part in the devising of the Malayan constition after<br />
the achievement of Malayan self-government.<br />
The Prime Ministei, Tunka Abdul Rahman, recently visited<br />
Australia and was, I am sure, delighted at his reception and<br />
at the instinctive friendliness of our people.<br />
As part of the British Commonwealth reserve of forces,<br />
we have been and are represented, in all arms, with the willing<br />
co-operation of the Malayan people.<br />
To return to Indonesia, it is, of course, w½ ell-known<br />
that we recognise Dutch sovereignty in West New Guinea and that<br />
on this matter we have, so to speak, agreed to disagree with the<br />
Indonesian administration.<br />
As we are in no sense anxious to piomote hostility we<br />
have, in the first places strongly supported the reference ol the<br />
Indonesian territorial claim to the Permanent Court of International<br />
Justice. The Government of Indonesia has, for its own<br />
reasons, not thought this to be a suitable tribunal. We have<br />
made it clear that, as we recognise Dutch sovereignty, so equally,<br />
do we recognise the right of the Dutch to co4duct negotiations<br />
with Indonesia so long as those negotiations are not conducted<br />
under either threat or duress. On this matter you will recall,<br />
as I do, that the Indonesian Foreign Minister, Dr. Subandrio, on<br />
his recent visit to Australia entered upon a joint declaration to<br />
the effect that Indonesia did not intend to solve those differences<br />
of opinion by force of arms. This, you will agree, is a<br />
civilised attitude and, as your government, 9 we , rill do our best<br />
to preserve it.<br />
It seems to me that the truth is that the great problEms<br />
before the new nation of Indonesia are those of civil administration<br />
and economic develop ent. Ue will do all in our power to<br />
help to solve these poblems. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Indeed, it may be said about both-of these neighbouring<br />
countries Indonesia and Malaya that Australia has a<br />
genuine interest in seeing them develop as free, well-administered<br />
and self-governing communities, with rising standards of<br />
living and that pride in democracy which is the best assurance<br />
of resistance to Communism.<br />
Looking back over these 10 years, we feel proud of the<br />
economic and social development of our own country. ' e have<br />
experienced unpopularity and popularity, but at all times we<br />
have tried to maintain a steady course; a c0ourse which in the<br />
result has, I believe, as you do contributed powerfully to the<br />
g-reatest period of national deveiopment within living memory.<br />
But we have not confined ourselves to domesiic and economic affairs.<br />
* We have set about the task of build1ing up these friendships<br />
and associations abroad which mean so much to our national<br />
security and our national future.<br />
It may occasionally be forgotten that the Colombo Plan<br />
originated with Australian initiative; that we played an active<br />
and I think, a determining part in the creation of the ANZUS<br />
Pact with the United States and New Zealand;, and that we were one<br />
of the founders of the South-East Asian Treaty which has done so<br />
much to stabilise those freedom-loving countries in South and<br />
South-East Asia who are determined not to paiss within Communist<br />
control. In short, we have had a positive, constructive and<br />
fruitful foreign policy. Our association with Great Britain and<br />
the other nations of the British Commonwealth has never been<br />
stronger or more genuine. Our association with the United States<br />
of America has never been so happy or so helpful. Thus it is<br />
that I think we may say at the end of a decadie of government that<br />
both at home and abroad we have served our country with integrity<br />
and with success. It is a good thing that ~ Ve should be able to<br />
say this to ourselves at this time.<br />
That I should say it to you is not an expression of<br />
personal self-satisfaction, because nobody kriows half so well as<br />
I do how much the progress of events has depbnded upon the intense<br />
loyalty and co-operation which has beep received from<br />
Ministei-s, Parliamentary Members and the manyr thousands of Party<br />
Members in the field of organisation whose names are perhaps not<br />
well known but without whose sacrificial work we could never hope<br />
to achieve success.<br />
Ten years seems a long time lookiing forward. it<br />
seems an astonishingly short time looking back. But I see no<br />
reason to doubt that so long as we provide s~ rvice to the Australian<br />
people, a sound character rhich inspires that service,<br />
and a patriotism which prefers the interests of the nation to the<br />
interests of the individual, we should be able to look forw. ard to<br />
another decade of which wve may be as proud a$ we are of the<br />
years just ended. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
