<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5481</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005481.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY 9 NOVEMBER 1980<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Last Tuesday Americans electe d a new President. Governor Reagan<br />
will be sworn in early in the New Year and with him a new<br />
Republican administration will come into office. I have<br />
congratulated President-Elect Governor Reagan, on behalf of the<br />
Government and people of Australia. He has the good wishes of<br />
all of us.<br />
The job of the President of the United States is a truly onerous<br />
one. The problems he faces concern his own country. They are<br />
also of great significance to the democratic world. We have<br />
common objective's and common ideals in wishing to preserve the<br />
kind of freedom and liberty so important in a democratic societ~ y.<br />
At this time in the transition of power in the United States I<br />
would like to say something about the relationship between Australia<br />
and our traditional friend and ally. There is a long tradition<br />
of close ties between our two countries I ndeed, it will be my<br />
objective to work for a continuing strengthening of that relationship.<br />
Because of the unsettled world we live in, a strong relationship<br />
between the United States and Australia and our regional neighbours.<br />
is of continuing significance.<br />
The United States is the unchallenged leader of the free world<br />
and the cornerstone of the Western alliance. Its role is of the<br />
utmost importance to the peace and well-being of the world and<br />
to the security of Australia. In shouldering its world burden,<br />
the United States made an enormous contribution to the recovery of<br />
post-war Europe through what was called the Marshall Plan. It<br />
also showed great generosity and wisdom in the post-war recons-truction<br />
of Japan. For many years, it has provided large amounts of aid for<br />
developing countries.<br />
In our part of the world, for thirty years the United States has<br />
been the largest partner in the Anzus Treaty, which is vital to<br />
Australia's security. In the years following World War II the<br />
United States was enormously strong by comparison with other<br />
countries. Economically, militarily and in terms of political<br />
influence, the United States was the predominant power in the world.<br />
For many years, United States power and strength tended to be -taken<br />
for granted. Because the United States was so strong, it was often<br />
left to carry the burden of safeguarding the Tnterests of the free<br />
world. </p>
<p>However, over the last decade there have been important changes<br />
in the position of the United States relative to other countries.<br />
Within the NATO Alliance, the economic and political balance<br />
between the United States and Western Europe has changed<br />
substantially. Western Europe has resumed its position as one<br />
of the major economic centres of the world. Japan's importance<br />
has grown greatly. A number of developing countries, especially<br />
in Asia are establishing a new strength. OPEC has emerged as an<br />
important factor on the world scene, with great power to influence<br />
the economies of industrialised countries through its oil pricing<br />
policies. Thus the world has changed greatl~ y from that of the earlier postwar<br />
years when the United States had unparalleled overall military<br />
and economic power. Now Soviet conventional superiority is matched<br />
by nuclear parity or as some judge even by nuclear superiority.<br />
As a result of many events over twenty years, the United States'<br />
confidence in its own special leadership role has been to some<br />
extent eroded. It is important that it be re-established. As I<br />
have indicated on other occasions it is important that the Western<br />
alliance be strengthened. It must also adjust to the current<br />
realities of world power and influence.<br />
Europe is wealthier, Europe has more power and an undoubted voice,<br />
quite different from the years when the alliance was first formed.<br />
It is no. good enough for other countries to sit back and allow<br />
the United States to carry -the burden of defence of the free world<br />
alone. That applies -to the powerful countries of Europe. It<br />
applies also to middle ranking countries such as Australia.<br />
Without having any unreal view of what a country Australia's size<br />
can achieve, there is much that we can do. We need to pursue<br />
adequate defence policies as we are. But in addition where we<br />
have shared objectives and concerns, a common understanding of the<br />
problems and dangers in the worl. d, then we have an obligation and<br />
responsibility to state our own views. If the course is difficult,<br />
it is not good enough to leave it to the United States alone.<br />
An American President needs the support of Congress and of people.<br />
That can be more easily sustained if it is also known that there<br />
are other countries with similar views, with shared objectives.<br />
We do not support the United States simply because it is the<br />
United States or because there is an Anzus Alliance. We support<br />
the United States when we believe it to be right, when out of our<br />
own analysis, our own judgement, we share United States' concerns<br />
and objectives. In particular, with Soviet conventional and<br />
strategic military power at an all time high, it is essential<br />
that we have a strong and vital United States working in close<br />
co-operation with her allies.<br />
Over recent years there has been a very close relationship between<br />
the United States and Australia. I established a close working<br />
relationship with. Pre! sident Carter and I hope to do the same with<br />
President-Elect Reagan. 3 </p>
<p>It will be an advantage that his views on containing Government<br />
expenditure, on giving people greater freedom to choose, and on<br />
the paramount importance of reducing inflation views which<br />
have been given such overwhelming endorsement by the American<br />
people are also views which I and my Government have held and<br />
pursued vigorously for the past five years with the support of<br />
the Australian people. None of this means that we have similar<br />
views to the United States on all things. Of course we do not<br />
and we cannot. We have our own perspectives. And if there are<br />
differences of view then they will be stated. But in recent<br />
years we have developed a close identity of view on the main<br />
challenges confronting free societies in the 1980s.<br />
I look forward to working very closely with the new United States'<br />
administration, building on the traditional strength and solidarity<br />
of Australian/ American alliance. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
