<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11251</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL APPROACH TO PROBLEM GAMBLING</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/12/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
  Excessive gambling blights the lives of thousands of Australians and their<br />
   families every year.</p>
<p>  Problem gambling has become a major social concern.</p>
<p>  The challenge for all governments in Australia is to find a response which<br />
   balances the undoubted right of individual Australians to gamble if they<br />
   wish with the ongoing responsibility of governments for overall community<br />
   welfare.</p>
<p>  The regulation of gambling has traditionally been a State responsibility.<br />
   It is not our desire to change this. The Commonwealth, however, does have<br />
   a leadership role in coordinating a national response to problem gambling.</p>
<p>  Importantly also, the Commonwealth has a direct responsibility in relation<br />
   to the use of the internet for gambling. I am particularly concerned about<br />
   the effect of a rapid expansion of internet gambling and the Government<br />
   will be investigating the feasibility and consequences of banning internet<br />
   gambling.</p>
<p>  Today I have released the final report of the Productivity Commission on<br />
   Australia's gambling industries. A key recommendation of that report is<br />
   the establishment of a ministerial council on gambling aimed at achieving<br />
   a national approach to the challenge of problem gambling.</p>
<p>  The Government will adopt that recommendation. I have written today to the<br />
   Premiers and Chief Ministers proposing the establishment of a Ministerial<br />
   Council on Gambling.</p>
<p>  That council will report to the Council of Australian Governments. It will<br />
   focus on stopping the further expansion of gambling in Australia, on the<br />
   impacts of problem gambling on families and communities, on internet gambling<br />
   and on consumer protection.</p>
<p>  The Minister for Family and Community Services will represent the Commonwealth<br />
   on the Council, with other Ministers participating on relevant issues.</p>
<p>  The Productivity Commission report is the first comprehensive investigation<br />
   of gambling in Australia and it is the first time we have had a complete<br />
   picture not only of the economics and regulatory structure of the gambling<br />
   industries, but also of the social consequences of the recent rapid expansion<br />
   of gambling in this country.</p>
<p>  I am particularly disturbed by the findings of the report about the extent<br />
   and severity of problem gambling. The report found that around 290,000 Australians<br />
   are problem gamblers and account for over $3 billion in losses annually.</p>
<p>  This is disastrous not only for these problem gamblers, but also for the<br />
   estimated 1.5 million people they directly affect as a result of bankruptcy,<br />
   divorce, suicide and lost time at work.</p>
<p>  I have been pleased to see that the publication of the draft of this report<br />
   in July this year has already generated a great deal of concern about problem<br />
   gambling and its effects on families and the community. State and Territory<br />
   governments have announced a range of measures to address the uncontrolled<br />
   expansion of gambling and improvements to services for problem gamblers.</p>
<p>  We need, however, a national response to what is clearly a national problem.<br />
   By working together with the industry and the community, the Commonwealth<br />
   and the States and Territories can achieve the best economic and social<br />
   outcomes for the Australian community.</p>
<p>  It will be important for the gambling industry and communities themselves<br />
   to work with governments in addressing the issues in the Commission's report.<br />
   I have therefore proposed that an expert advisory body to the Council be<br />
   established with membership from community organisations and also from the<br />
   gambling industry itself.</p>
<p>  Internet gambling has the potential to dramatically increase the number<br />
   of problem gamblers because it will be accessible to every household 24<br />
   hours a day.</p>
<p>  I would envisage that this issue will be a major focus of the proposed Ministerial<br />
   Council on Gambling and its advisory body. In addition the Government will<br />
   be undertaking consultations with relevant industry and consumer groups<br />
   and will also take account of the forthcoming report of the Senate Information<br />
   Technology Committee's inquiry into on-line gambling.</p>
<p>  The Commonwealth Government will also undertake a range of measures to increase<br />
   the priority given to the prevention and treatment of problem gambling within<br />
   the Government's own social policy programmes. These measures include new<br />
   approaches to informing and helping Australians from particular groups with<br />
   special needs, such as youth, veterans, Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders<br />
   and people from culturally diverse backgrounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
