<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3544</transcript-id>
    <title>STATE AGENTS-GENERAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003544.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
JAUSA.% AI I<br />
PRIME MONBSTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 413<br />
13 December 1974<br />
STATE AGENTS-GENERAL<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, today denied reports<br />
that he had any intention of raising with the British Government<br />
the position of State Agents-General in London.<br />
Mr Whitlam said he appreciated that the Agents-<br />
General had a role to perform in relation to commercial and<br />
related matters to which the States attributed considerable<br />
importance. There was, however, no suggestion that Agents-<br />
General exercised diplomatic functions, as these were the<br />
sole concern of the Australian Government.<br />
There was no foundation whatsoever for the Queensland<br />
Premier' s assertion that the question of a border with<br />
Papua New Guinea and the Torres Strait area would be raised<br />
with the British Government.<br />
" The Premier will be aware that a first round of<br />
discussions, of an essentially preliminary nature, was held<br />
in Canberra on 13 November between officials of the Australian<br />
and Queensland Governments.<br />
" At this meeting it was agreed that a second, and<br />
more technical, meeting be held after the Queensland elections.<br />
The expectation was that this meeting would be held in the<br />
week beginning 16 December.<br />
" The Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet was<br />
advised this week by Queensland officials that processes<br />
associated with the formation of a new Queensland Government<br />
would not be complete until 23 December and that, therefore,<br />
the proposed meeting would have to be deferred until some time<br />
in January, probably the last week in January," , Mr Whitlam said.<br />
The-Prime Minister added that he had no intention of<br />
canvassing in public the matters which would be raised during<br />
his impending private talks with Her Majesty The Queen or<br />
with the British Government.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
