<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6347</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, QUARANTINE STATION, NORTH HEAD, 16 MARCH 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006347.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHEC AGANSTDAEGLAIIENRSYTE MBDEALRIGVOEERDY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
QUARANTINE STATION NORTH HEAD -16 MARCH 1984<br />
Mr Premier, Distinguished Guests,. Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />
This is a small but significant ceremony-to commemorate the<br />
transfer of the former North Head Quarantine Station to New<br />
South Wales. That it occurs at all reflects the close<br />
co-operative arrangements existing between the Australian<br />
and New South Wales Governments. Such co-operation now<br />
extends into many fields of community interest. That it<br />
should continue is in the interests of all of us -of all<br />
Australians. This former quarantine station site of about 27 hectares is<br />
being transferred to the State under the provisions of the<br />
Land Exchange Agrqement between the Commonwealth and the<br />
State for inclusion in the proposed Sydney Harbour National<br />
Park. The Agreement is unique in Commonwealth/-State negotiations<br />
on the purchase/ disposal of Government owned property.<br />
Among other things, it requires the purchasing government to<br />
use the land for a prior nominated purpose at an agreed<br />
value based on that use.<br />
I have been advised that the current size of the Sydney<br />
Harbour National Park is about 465 hectares. Of this area<br />
the Commonwealth is contributing 80 per cent 372 hectares,<br />
with only 82 hectares remaining to be transferred. The<br />
State has so far contributed 93 hectares..<br />
The North Head component is the largest and one of the most<br />
prominent areas of the proposed National Park. This area,<br />
contributed by the Commonwealth, comprises over 55 per cent<br />
of the total park area.<br />
In the 1800' s, North Head on the northern side of the<br />
entrance to Sydney Harbour, was isolated and unpopulated.<br />
Store beach was protected from the southerlies and provided<br />
safe anchorage, drinking water and sandy beaches.<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY </p>
<p>Before the area was proclaimed for quarantine purposes ships<br />
arriving from overseas used to put ashore on the beach at<br />
North Head, with some provisions or rations, passengers and<br />
crew who appeared to be suffering from a communicable<br />
disease. A scare resulting from an outbreak of cholera in England and<br />
Ireland prompted Governor Bourke on 14 August 1832, to<br />
proclaim the site for quarantine purposes.<br />
In 1837 temporary buildings were erected between Collin's<br />
Flat and Store Beach. By the end of that year the occupants<br />
moved up the hill to the present station site where nine<br />
permanent buildings were being erected. These buildings<br />
were finished in May 1838.<br />
When the Commonwealth was established in 1901, the Federal<br />
Constitution included quarantine as a specific Commonwealth<br />
responsibility. The Commonwealth Quarantine Act was passed<br />
in March 1908 and came into force on 1 July 1909. As a<br />
result the station, which originally operated under State<br />
legislation, was transferred to the Commonweath.<br />
The station has many links with early white settlement in<br />
Australia and is part of our historic heritage. It is<br />
especially interesting that rock carvings, made by crew and<br />
passengers, may be found in a number of locations such as<br />
Store Beach, Spring Cove and Old Man's Hat.<br />
Over the last 10 years the need for human quarantine<br />
stations has diminished with the advent of better public<br />
health services, the eradication of smallpox and changing<br />
world disease patterns. Quarantinable diseases such as<br />
typhoid and cholera contracted by travellers from overseas<br />
are very few and each State has agreed that any cases or<br />
suspect cases can be adequately handled within the existing<br />
State health authority system.<br />
The transfer of this property is tangible evidence of the<br />
Commonwealth's desire to see that any lands it holds are put<br />
to the most appropriate uses and, wherever practicable, are<br />
made available to all Australians.<br />
Mr Premier, I am delighted that, through a spirit of mutual<br />
co-operation, such a worthwhile asset will be opened to the<br />
public. I know that its inclusion in the Sydney Harbour<br />
National Park will enhance what is generally and rightly<br />
regarded as the most picturesque harbour in the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
