<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2103</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: AWARD OF VICTORIA CROSS FOR GALLANTRY IN VIETNAM - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002103.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 70/ 1969<br />
AWARD OF VICTORIA CROSS FOR GALLANTRY<br />
IN VIETNAM<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Her Majesty The Queen has awarded the Victoria Cross to<br />
a member of the Australian Army Training Team in Vietnam, Warrant<br />
Officer Class 2 Rayene Stewart Simpson, D. C. M.<br />
Warrant Officer Simpson displayed outstanding heroism on<br />
two separate occasions during an operation with a mobile strike force in<br />
Kontum Province in May this year.<br />
A veteran of the Second World War, Korea, and the<br />
Malayan Emergency, Warrant Officer Simpson came originally from<br />
Chippendale in New South Wales. He is still serving with the Training<br />
Team in Vietnam. Warrant Officer Simpson's repeated acts of personal bravery<br />
in last May's operation were an inspiration to all Vietnamese, United<br />
States and Australian soldiers who served with him. His conspicuous<br />
gallantry was in the highest tradition of the Australian Army.<br />
I have sent Warrant Officer Simpson the following message:-<br />
" On behalf of the Commonwealth Government, my<br />
colleagues and I offer you our most sincere<br />
congratulations on the award of the Victoria Cross<br />
bestowed on you by Her Majesty The Queen.<br />
Australia is proud of you. Your exceptional<br />
valour and leadership while serving as an adviser<br />
of the Australian Army Training Team in Vietnam<br />
must be an inspiration to all Australians."<br />
CANBERRA 2 1August 1969<br />
Note: Attached:-Details of Warrant Officer Simpsont s actions.<br />
Personal background on Warrant Officer Simpson. </p>
<p>BACKGROUND TO V. C. AWARD<br />
Details of Action: On 6 May 1969 Warrant Off icer Simpson was serving as a<br />
company commander in a Mobile Strike Force Battalion on a search and<br />
clear operation in Kontum Province. When one of his platoons became<br />
heavily engaged with the enemy, he led the remainder of his company to<br />
its assistance. The enemy who were equipped with automatic weapons and<br />
grenades were in strong defensive positions and well protected by the<br />
covering fire of other troops dispersed about their positions. Disregarding<br />
the dangers involved, he placed himself at the front of his troops, thus<br />
becoming a focal point of enemy fire, and personally led the assault on the<br />
left flank of the enemy position.<br />
As the company moved forward, an Australian warrant<br />
officer commanding one of the platoons was seriously wounded and the<br />
attack began to falter. Warrant Off icer Simpson, at great personal risk<br />
and under heavy fire, rushed across open ground to the wounded warrant<br />
officer and carried him to a position of safety. He then returned to his<br />
company where, with complete disregard for his safety, he crawled forward<br />
to within ten metres of the enemy and threw grenades into their positions.<br />
As darkness fell, Warrant Officer Simpson realised he<br />
could not break into the enemy position. He ordered his company to<br />
withdraw and threw smoke grenades as a protective cover. Then, carrying<br />
a wounded platoon leader and with the assistance of five Vietnamese soldiers,<br />
he covered the withdrawal of his company.<br />
Mr. Gorton said his leadership and personal bravery<br />
throughout this action were outstanding.<br />
On 11 May in the same operation, Warrant Officer Simpson'sa<br />
Battalion Commander was killed and an Australian warrant officer and<br />
several Vietnamese soldiers were wounded. In addition, one other Australian<br />
warrant off icer who had been separated from most of his troops had been<br />
pinned down by enemy fire. Warrant Off icer Simpson quickly organised two<br />
platoons of Vietnamese soldiers and several advisers and led them to the<br />
position of the contact. On reaching the position, the element with Warrant Off icer<br />
Simpson came under heavy fire and all but a few of the soldiers with him<br />
fell back. Disregarding his own safety, he moved forward in the face of<br />
accurate enemy machine gun fire in order to cover the initial evacuation<br />
of the casualties. The wounded were eventually moved out of the line of<br />
fire, most of which was being directed at Warrant Officer Simpson from<br />
close range. In the words of one American eye-witness, " The whole area<br />
was sprayed. Warrant Off icet Simpson's area caught the full blast and the<br />
tree he was beside was ripPed apart. His leadership and encouragement<br />
motivated myself and others so the wounded were pulled out safely." / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
At what appeared to be the risk of almost certain death he<br />
made several attempts to move forward to recover his Battalion'<br />
Commander's body, but on each occasion was stopped by heavy accurate<br />
fire. Realising the position was becoming untenable and that priority<br />
should be given to extricating all casualties as quickly as possible,<br />
Warrant Officer Simpson alone and still under enemy fire, covered the<br />
withdrawal of the wounded by keeping himself between them and the enemy.<br />
He fought on and by his outstanding courage prevented the enemy advancing<br />
until the wounded were removed from the immediate vicinity.<br />
The Prime Minister said Warrant Officer Simpson's gallant<br />
and individual action and his coolness under prolonged fire were exceptional<br />
and were instrumental in achieving the successful evacuation of the wounded<br />
to a helicopter evacuation pad.<br />
Personal Background: Rayene Stewart Simpson was born at Chippendale, New<br />
South Wales on 16 February 1926. He enlisted in the AIF on 15 March 1944<br />
and served overseas in Morotai, Tarakan, and Rabaul. He was discharged<br />
on 9 January 1947 and subsequently re-enlisted on 17 January 1951.<br />
During his second enlistment, Warrant Officer Simpson<br />
served in Korea, Malaysia and Vietnam. During his second tour with the<br />
Australian Army Training Team in Vietnam he was wounded in action in<br />
October 1964 and was subsequently awarded the Distinguished Conduct<br />
Medal for bravery. Warrant Officer Simpson was discharged on 16 May 1966<br />
but again re-enlisted on 2 May 1967 and has served continuously with the<br />
Training Team in Vietnam since that date.<br />
His Decorations and Medals are: Victoria Cross,<br />
Distinguished Conduct Medal, Pacific Star, War Medal 1939-45, Australia<br />
Service Medal 1939-45, K~ orea Medal, United Nations Service Medal ( Korea),<br />
General Service Medal with Malaya Clasp, Vietnam Medal, and Vietnamese<br />
Campaign Medal. Warrant Officer Simpson is married and his wife resides at<br />
5-30-1 Chome Yayoicho-Nakano-ku, Tokyo, Japan.<br />
V. C. Warrant Officer Simpson's award is the 95th Victoria Cross<br />
awarded to an Australian and is the third since World War IL / 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The last two awards were made to the late Warrant Officer<br />
Kevin Arthur Wheatley for action in Quang Ngai Province, South Vietnam<br />
on 13 November 1965 and to the late Major Peter John Badcoe for his<br />
actions between February and April 1967 in South Vietnam. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
