<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3907</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER ATTHE BOOK LAUNCHING OF TJ RYAN - A POLITICAL BIOGRAPHY BY DENIS MURPHY AT BRISBANE, 3 OCTOBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003907.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1 7 4 OVER THE YEARS, THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR PARTY HAS NOT ENJOYED<br />
A VERY GOOD PRESS. By CONTRAST, WE HAVE BEEN GENERALLY<br />
WELL-TREATED BY HISTORY AND THE HISTORIANS, IT IS<br />
SOME CONSOLATION TO KNOW THAT HISTORY WILL RENDER A<br />
FAVOURABLE VERDICT. THE DIFFICULTY IS TO WAIT AROUND<br />
LONG ENOUGH FOR THE JUDGEMENT TO BE HANDED DOWN.<br />
IF POSTERITY HAD THE V/ OTE, LABOR WOULD NEVER BE OUT<br />
OF OFFICE. As IT IS WE HAVE THE PARADOX THAT WHILE<br />
AUSTRALIAN POLITICAL HISTORY TENDS VERY LARGELY TO BE<br />
WRITTEN IN TERMS OF THE HISTORY OF THE AUSTRALIAN LABOR<br />
PARTY, THE PARTY AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL HAS HELD OFFICE<br />
ONLY 18 YEARS OF THE 714 YEARS OF FEDERATION.<br />
THE ARRIVAL OF DENIS IURPHY'S BOOK ' LIFE OF T. J. RYAN'<br />
FIFTY-FIVE YEARS AFTER HIS DEATH, DOES POINT TO THE<br />
RATHER LEISURELY PACE AT WHICH OUR ACADEMIC HISTORIANS<br />
PRODUCE THEIR ASSESSM~ ENTS. THE GAPS ARE ENORMOUS.<br />
THERE IS STILL NO DEFINITIVE WORK ON PARKES, GRIFFITH,<br />
BARTON, FISHER, LYONS, AND ABOVE ALL, CURTIN.<br />
THE LAST WORD HAS NOT BEEN SAID ABOUT HUGHES, BRUCE,<br />
OR CHIFLEY, As FAR AS I AM AWARE, NO-ONE HAS YET<br />
UNDERTAKEN THE FORMIDABLE TASK OF ASSESSING THE MENZIES ERA.<br />
THE JOURNALISTS HAVE BEEN MUCH MORE PROMPTO<br />
IN MORE THAN ONE SENSE, ALAN REID DID GORTONAND<br />
I SHOULD GIVE A PLUG FOR LAURIE OAKES' BOOK ON WHITLAM<br />
WHICH INEXPLICABLY HAS BEEN REMAINDERED AT 35 CENTS,<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER AT BOOK LAUNCHING OF<br />
T. J. RYAN A POLITICAL BIOGRAPHY<br />
BY<br />
DENIS MURPHY.<br />
AT BRISBANE, 3 OCTOBER 1975 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THERE IS OF COURSE A POIGNANCY ABOUT THE STORY OF<br />
T. J. RYAN. HE DIED AT FORTY-FIVE IN THE PRIME OF LIFE,<br />
AT THE HEIGHT OF HIS POWERS, WITH EVERY PROSPECT OF EVEN<br />
GREATER ACHIEVEMENTS AHEAD OF HIM. THERE WAS EVERY REASON<br />
TO BELIEVE THAT HE WOULD SHORTLY BECOME THE LEADER OF THE<br />
FEDERAL PARLIAMENTARY LABOR PARTY AND PRIME MINISTER.<br />
DEATH WROTE A GREAT QUESTION MARK ON HIS CAREER.<br />
T. J. RYAN WAS SUPERBLY EQUIPPED BY TEMPERAMENT AND<br />
TRAINING FOR THE ROLE HE PLAYED AND FOR THE LARGER ROLE<br />
TO WHICH HE ASPIRED. THE STATUE IN THE EXECUTIVE GARDENS<br />
REPRESENTS HIM AS A KING'S COUNSEL.' HE WAS . IN FACT<br />
THE ONLY LAWYER TO HEAD THE QUEENSLAND GOVERNMENT THIS<br />
CENTURY. THERE IS A DOUBLE FIRST THERE THE ONLY<br />
LAWYER PREMIER AND THE ONLY QUEENSLAND PREMIER OF THIS<br />
CENTURY TO HAVE A STATUE SO FAR. IN FACT JACK PIZZEY<br />
ALSO VERY TRAGICALLY CUT OFF AT THE HEIGHT OF HIS CAREER<br />
IS THE ONLY OTHER QUEENSLAND PREMIER THIS CENTURY TO<br />
HAVE OBTAINED A DEGREE. RYAN'S LEGAL TRAINING WAS<br />
OBVIOUSLY OF VERY GREAT IMPORTANCE TO HIM IN THE TWO<br />
GREAT CONSTITUTIONAL AND LEGAL BATTLES OF HIS CAREERAGAINST<br />
THE PRETENSIONS OF THE UPPER HOUSE, THE HAPPILY<br />
DEFUNCT LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL, AND AGAINST HUGHES. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
THE HEART OF DENIS MURPHY'S BOOK IS THE STRUGGLE BETWEEN<br />
RYAN AND HUGHES OVER CONSCRIPTION. THERE IS TRAGEDY,<br />
COMEDY, REAL DRAMA AND MERE MELODRAMA. FORTUNATELY<br />
IN THESE DAYS OF REASON AND LIGHT, AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTERS<br />
AND -QUEENSLAND PREMIERS ARE ABLE TO BASE THEIR RELATIONS<br />
ON A SPIRIT OF CO-OPERATION AND MUTUAL RESPECT.<br />
RYAN TRANSFERRED TO FEDERAL POLITICS FOR THE SPECIFIC<br />
PURPOSE OF DEFEATING HUGHES IN THE NATIONAL ARENA.<br />
IN THE EVENT, IT WAS NOT RYAN WHO DID FOR HUGHES*<br />
HE WAS DESTROYED BY HIS OWN COLLEAGUES, THUS ESTABLISHING<br />
THE GREAT CONSERVATIVE TRADITION, OF WHICH IN THEIR TURN<br />
LATHAM, MENZIES, GORTON AND SNEDDEN WERE ALL VICTIMS,<br />
WITH LYONS AND HOLT SAVED FROM A SIMILAR FATE BY DEATH.<br />
THERE IS ONE ASPECT OF RYAN'S CONDUCT IN THE FIGHT AGAINST<br />
CONSCRIPTION WHICH MERITS MENTION. THE DEFECTION OF<br />
HUGHES AND EVERY STATE LABOR LEADER EXCEPT RYAN DEALT A<br />
VERY HEAVY BLOW TO THE CONFIDENCE OF THE PARTY NOT ONLY<br />
IN THEIR LEADERS BUT IN THE VERY PRINCIPLE OF LEADERSHIP<br />
ITSELF. THE PARLIAMENTARY WING AND PARLIAMENTARY LEADERSHIP<br />
BECAME HEAVILY SUSPECT. THERE WAS A STRONG ATTEMPT TO<br />
TAKE THE ELECTION OF THE PARLIAMENTARY LEADERSHIP AWAY FROM<br />
THE PARLIAMENTARIANS AND PLACE IT IN THE HANDS OF THE MACHINE.<br />
THIS DID IN FACT SUCCEED IN NEW SOUTH WALES, AND LANG OWED<br />
HIS POSITION TO THE CENTRAL EXECUTIVE, NOT THE NEW SOUTH<br />
WALES CAUCUS. </p>
<p>THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT RYAN BY HIS STATURE AND HIS<br />
FIRM LOYALTY TO THE PRINCIPLE OF PARLIAMENTARY INDEPENDENCE<br />
MADE THE MAJOR CONTRIBUTION IN PREVENTING THIS OCCURRING<br />
AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL. THE PARTY'S CONFIDENCE IN<br />
ITS LEADERSHIP WAS NOT REALLY RESTORED UNTIL CURTIN<br />
BUT RYAN MORE THAN ANYONE ELSE PRESERVED THE PRINCIPLE<br />
INTACT. SO CURTIN AND ALL HIS SUCCESSORS OWE THIS<br />
DEBT To RYAN.<br />
DENIS MURPHY'S BOOK DOCUMENTS A NOTABLE FEATURE OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN POLITICAL LIFE THE AMAZING CONSISTENCY.'<br />
THE STERILITY, THE SHEER LACK OF IMAGINATION IN THE<br />
INVECTIVE USED AGAINST THE LABOR PARTY. HERE ARE<br />
SOME DESCRIPTIONS OF RYAN AND HIS GOVERNMENT:<br />
i 8TYRANNY. TREACHERY TREASON<br />
MOB RULE COMMUNIST BOLSHEVIK<br />
DISLOYAL TO THE CROWN A CONTEMPTIBLE CONSPIRACY<br />
REPREHENSIBLE... . A THREAT TO THE AUSTRALIAN WAY<br />
OF LIFE...," 1<br />
AND OF COURSE THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE GOVERNMENT INSURANCE<br />
OFFICE WAS VIOLENT REVOLUTIONARY SOCIALIST ATTEMPT<br />
TO DESTROY FREEDOM OF ENTERPRISE AND THE RIGHTS OF FREE<br />
CHOICE.." IT IS ALL SO DEPRESSINGLY FAMILIAR. </p>
<p>BEFORE RYAN'S LEADERSHIP THE PARTY'S STRENGTH IN<br />
QUEENSLAND WAS BASED IN THE OUTBACK AND THE CENTRAL<br />
AND NORTHERN PROVINCIAL TOWNS, HIS POLITICAL<br />
ACHIEVEMENT WAS TO FORGE A NEW BASE IN BRISBANE.<br />
THE ALLIANCE BETWEEN THE CAPITAL AND THE GREAT<br />
PROVINCIAL CITIES LAID THE FOUNDATIONS FOR LABOR'S<br />
ASCENDANCY IN QUEENSLAND WHICH LASTED ALMOST UNBROKEN<br />
FOR NEARLY HALF A CENTURY, TO RESTORE THAT<br />
ALLIANCE IS STILL THE KEY TO POLITICAL SUCCESS FOR<br />
THE PARTY IN QUEENSLAND,<br />
I CONGRATULATE DENIS ON HIS PAINSTAKING WORK, HIS<br />
PATIENT RESEARCH, HIS VERY READABLE RE-CREATION OF<br />
A TURBULENT BUT VERY FRUITFUL PERIOD IN THE POLITICAL<br />
LIFE OF QUEENSLAND AND OF AUSTRALIA, IN THIS RECORD<br />
OF A GREAT CAREER UNTIMELY CUT OFF, HE HAS MADE A<br />
MAJOR CONTRIBUTION TO OUR HISTORY, OUR POLITICS<br />
OUR UNDERSTANDING OF THAT HISTORY AND THOSE POLITICS,<br />
,11a I I, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
