<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18927</transcript-id>
    <title>2012 Prime Minister&#039;s Australian Exporter of the Year Awards</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/2012</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Canberra</p>
<p>Prime Minister Julia Gillard has named Queensland premium auto manufacturer PWR Performance Products as the 2012 Australian Exporter of the Year.</p>
<p>PWR Performance Products caters to the high-performance racing industry and automotive aftermarket. Its range includes light-weight radiators, oil coolers and intercoolers.</p>
<p>Over 50 per cent of Formula 1 teams and 90 per cent of NASCAR teams now use PWR cooling solutions and the company recently secured contracts with Porsche, Pagani, and Jaguar-Williams among others.</p>
<p>Last financial year it increased export sales by 33 per cent.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister congratulated PWR Performance Products on setting a new benchmark for high-value Australian manufacturing.</p>
<p>The Australian Export Awards this year marked its 50th anniversary, making it one of the country's longest-running business award programs, as well as one of the most prestigious.</p>
<p>The Awards honour successful Australian exporters and celebrate their contribution to the national economy.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Australian Exporter of the Year is selected from the winners of 12 national categories.</p>
<p>PWR Performance Products was also the winner of the Small to Medium Manufacturer Award.</p>
<p>The 50th Australian Export Awards ceremony was hosted in Canberra tonight by Trade and Competitiveness Minister Craig Emerson, and co-presented by the Australian Trade Commission and Australian Chamber of Commerce and Industry.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
