<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6267</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT - PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE - 17 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006267.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT -PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE-<br />
17 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Ladies and gentlemen, I thought I'd just make a brief<br />
statement about the visit which will commence later on today<br />
and then be available for any questions you'd like to ask.<br />
I'm going to refer firstly to the visit to Thailand. As I<br />
said in the Parliament yesterday, of course I'm looking forward<br />
to that visit with Bill Hayden to meet Prime Minister Prem<br />
and Foreign Minister Siddhi. We will naturally be talking about<br />
two ranges of issues the bilateral issues between our two<br />
countries and the question of concern recently in matters<br />
raised particularly by the Singaporean Foreign Minister:<br />
our relations with ASEAN.<br />
While I'm there I shall making two important statements, one<br />
on regional political issues and the other on regional economic<br />
issues. I can't stress too much the importance that we attach<br />
to this visit. It will be the first visit to Thailand by an<br />
Australian Prime Minister since my Labor predecessor, Gough<br />
Whitlam, was there in 1974. On the actual ASEAN issue, as<br />
I said in the Parliament yesterday, we believe that it's<br />
appropriate now that these issues should be discussed in the<br />
talks in Thailand. Bill will be following them up when he<br />
goes to Indonesia in talks with Dr Mochtar. And I believe,<br />
and I'm quite confident, that out of these direct discussions<br />
there and Bill's follow up in Jakarta, and the opportunities<br />
that I'll have in Dehli to talk with the representatives of<br />
Singapore and Malaysia, I'm quite confident that we will be<br />
able to have a clear understanding of what is basically an<br />
identical position on the major thrust of our concern about<br />
Indo-China.<br />
The purpose of the discussion, of course, will not simply be<br />
to clear up those points but in the process I will be emphasising,<br />
as Bill and I have, this matter of importance that this Goi'ernment<br />
is going to make its decisions in regard to all national<br />
questions as a sovereign, independent nation. ' And on the<br />
basis of the assessment of this Government of what the interests<br />
of Australia demand. Out of all those discussions, both there<br />
and in Bangkoki Bill's in Jakarta, my further discussions in<br />
India, we will continue to see what we cain do to try and help<br />
the resolution of the situation in Indo-China. Repeating as<br />
both Bill and I have said from the beginining that we don't<br />
in any way over-estimate our capacities ini that regard or<br />
under-estimate the difficlties of the i-sueCS with which We're<br />
d e al. i ng. </p>
<p>PM: cant<br />
The second stage, of course, is the visit to Dehli for the<br />
purpose of the CHOGM meeting. I'll make a couple of preliminary<br />
comments about that and then go to some of the issues.<br />
Obviously it's my first CHOGM meeting and I and my Government<br />
attach importance to the meeting. It gives the opportunity<br />
of bringing together heads of government from a wide and<br />
diverse range of countries to come together by certain interests.<br />
Naturally enough I'm looking forward to the opportunity that<br />
this will provide of meeting a range of leaders from the<br />
Commonwealth countries many of whom I have not yet had the<br />
opportunity of meeting.<br />
Coming to the conference itself. There are, as we see it, two<br />
major agenda items at the meeting. one, if you like, dealing<br />
with the international political situation and the other<br />
with the international economic scene, particularly as that<br />
international economic situation effects the welfare of<br />
developing countries. I'd just make these points generally<br />
about these major agenda items as far as we are concerned.<br />
I will be making what I hope will be useful and constructive<br />
contributions to these two major agenda items. I will not<br />
be attempting to make any dramatic new initiative nor, may I<br />
say, will I be adopting positions at the conference on themes<br />
which are different from those which my Government pursues at<br />
home. As far as the first general item is concerned the international<br />
political situation I will be stressing the great importance<br />
that our Government attaches to the need for constructive and<br />
realistic approaches in the area of disarmament and international<br />
arms control. There are two particular points that I'd make<br />
in that regard as to why we have a deep interest in that.<br />
Firstly, given that we have in this country joint facilities<br />
which are significant in the whole question of the verification<br />
of arms control, we have a right therefore to have a position<br />
on this issue. We are particularly concerned for that reason.<br />
And, of course, secondly, and it's heightened somewhat by the<br />
recent decision that the Government has taken in regard to the<br />
supply of uranium we have a particularly vested interest in<br />
making sure that the non-proliferation treaty is made as<br />
effective as possible and that there be the strictest adherence<br />
to the principles in that treaty.,<br />
On the international economic issues agenda, on behalf of<br />
our Government I will be urging that there should be flexi-ble<br />
and realistic responses to the serious contemporary international<br />
situation. Now, of course, finally for any of the countries<br />
represented at CHOGM, as for indeed many other countries in the<br />
world, ultimately their economic well-being will be primarily<br />
determined by the sets of economic decisions that they make<br />
themselves. But as we know we all live i~ n an inter-dependent<br />
world and we will be arguing that it's crucial that the domestic<br />
policies of the major countries, and particularly of the United<br />
States, should be of a kind which are not going to of themselves<br />
to involve avoidable economic hardships for the rest of the<br />
world. </p>
<p>PM: cont<br />
And that of course particularly refers to the adverse impact<br />
that there will be on the rest of the world in an economic and<br />
trading sense if there's a continuation of large domestic<br />
deficits in the United States. And of course what is required<br />
in current economic difficulties internationally is a<br />
strengthening of the international institutions whose primary<br />
concern is to facilitate the economic development of the<br />
less developed countries. And we will be in tac contribution<br />
that I make at-CHOGM stressing that point so that there can<br />
be a restoration of the opportunities for growth and the<br />
creation of a free and open international trading system.<br />
And while I will be addressing those issues in those generalterms<br />
in the contribution that I make I will hope to be making<br />
some specific contribution to the program on those issues.<br />
In respect of current political items may I just say that<br />
obviously I will be looking forward on behalf of Australia<br />
to hearing from other Commonwealth countries and the<br />
Secretary-General of the Commonwealth, Sonny Ramphal, as to<br />
their assessment of the current position in Grenada. You<br />
know on behalf of the Australian Government that I've made<br />
quite clear that we are not going to be providing armed<br />
forces for the peace-keeping force. We will consider whether<br />
there is any other contribution that we, together with other<br />
Commonwealth countries, may be able to make other than the<br />
contribution of armed forces to any peace-keeping there.<br />
I shall also, of course, be registering the concern of our<br />
Government at the irresponsible unilateral declaration of<br />
independence by the Turkish section in Cyprus and as I said<br />
yesterday I will be indicating that we will be prepared with<br />
our Commonwealth colleagues to take whatever steps may be<br />
possible to restore the unity and sovereignty and territorial<br />
integrity of the island and to safeguard the legitimate interests<br />
of the two major communities on the island.<br />
Just finally may I refer to the fact that, of course, the<br />
general question of Southern Africa will be a matter of<br />
discussion at the conference either specifically in formal<br />
sessions or in the corridors and I will be indicating the<br />
strengthening of the position of Australia as a result of<br />
recent decisions by our Government.<br />
One that might be regarded as a minor item, but as you will<br />
appreciate is a matter of some p~ irticular interest to me<br />
in regard to the operation of the Commonwealth itself, I believe<br />
that the initiative taken two or three years ago to establish<br />
a Commonwealth Trade Union Secretariat is a sensible one.<br />
I will be indicating that I think that the effectiveness<br />
of the Commonwealth itself will be strengt-hened in addition-to<br />
the regularity and formalisation of the meetings of heads of<br />
governments that other institutions within the Commonwealth<br />
also seek to have a degree of co-operation which is reflected<br />
I think Usefully in the establishment of the Commonwealth Trade<br />
Union Secretariat.<br />
Ladies and gentelcinen, that's all I wIould like to say at this<br />
stage. I ' in open to any que'stions if you'd like to address themn. </p>
<p>DENNIS GRANT: Mr. Hawke, in respect of this Bretton Woods<br />
proposal which you will be specifically addressing, could I<br />
ask you a question, but could I ask you to answer it in<br />
two ways, firstly as an economist and secondly as a Prime<br />
Minister. PM: They are mutually exclusive are they? OK, I'll try.<br />
GRANT: Will you be supportive of the proposal for<br />
PM: Speaking as an economist it really is an unreal<br />
di" chotomy you are putting to me as an economist let me say<br />
this. We share the concern of Mr. Muldoon who is identified<br />
as the author of these proposals. We share the concern of<br />
Mr. Muldoon and others about the basic issue which is letting<br />
them make this proposal and that is a feel. ing that the world<br />
of the 1980s is a very different one from that of the<br />
immediate post-war period in which the institutions were<br />
established and that there needs to be an examination of the<br />
best way in which the international community can provide<br />
the support system and the stimulatory mechanisms which are<br />
going to address the problems, particularly of the developing<br />
world. And so we recognise that there have been difficulties<br />
in the operations of those instruments, particularly the<br />
IMF and the World Bank. We will be seeking to say<br />
that the first emphasis should be upon trying to make those<br />
institutions more effective and you will appreciate that<br />
steps are under way to try and bring~ that result about,<br />
including, I'm pleased to say, the initiatives of the United<br />
States administration in regard to their commitments to the<br />
IMF. Now I believe that if you look at the way in which<br />
Mr. Muldoon has been talking about these proposals there has<br />
been some change in his approach in that he is not now stressing<br />
so much the gathering together of another great international<br />
conference, but he seems to be talking now more about at least<br />
in the first step of some core group of leaders of some<br />
nations. So, both as an economist and as a Prime Minister,<br />
let me say, we will be indicating our sharing of the concern<br />
about what is a real problem, but our tendency will be<br />
towards seeking to make the existing institutions more<br />
effective. That-does not preclude the possiblity perhaps at<br />
some further stage of looking at the possibility of some<br />
conference, large or small, but I think that is the important<br />
first step.<br />
KEN BEGG: Prime Minister, do you'have any reason to believe<br />
that the Americans may have been responsible in some way for<br />
our difference of opinion with ASEAN, particularly the<br />
Singaporean Foreign Minister?<br />
PM: No, I don't think the Americans have been responsible.<br />
Ithink that the past record under previous Labor and non-Labor<br />
Governments in this country would indicate a tendency at times<br />
for those sorts of problems to arise autonomously from<br />
within some of the ASEAN countries. You would be aware of thle<br />
difficulties that the previous Fraser Government had with ASEAN, </p>
<p>and particularly with Singapore inregard to a number of these<br />
issues. You remember the civil aviation matter and so on and<br />
the question when they were no longer prepared to recognise<br />
the Pol Pot regime. So there is a record which shows that<br />
the current difficulties are not something which has just<br />
arisen now. Now, I am aware of what has come out in one<br />
newspaper in this country relating to alleged off the record<br />
background briefings which now seem in some respects to need a<br />
new definition, but I don't want to enter into that. It seems<br />
to me that that is a matter between that newspaper and with<br />
that correspondent and the Americans. I notice the press<br />
release that has been put out by the United States Embassy in<br />
which they deny the thrust of that story and they make the<br />
point, which I think is a perfectly valid one, it is not in<br />
the United States interests, it is not in ASEAN interests and<br />
not in Australian interests to have any significant divergences<br />
or public disputes. That seems to me to be an obviously<br />
correct statement and I accept it. It is conceivable that<br />
in some background conversations there have been some<br />
emphases made. I don't accept that if that has happened that<br />
that in any way reflects the position of the United States<br />
administration. I am particularly pleased to note in the<br />
press release from the Embassy, Ken, they go out of their way<br />
to stress their pleasure if I can put it that way with the<br />
statement on behalf of the Australian Government by Bill<br />
Hayden in regard to the ANZUS situation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you think that as a result of<br />
the current problems with the ASEAN countries that the<br />
Australian initiative concerning Vietnam is now a lost cause?<br />
PMI wouldn't say it is a lost cause, but I think it is right<br />
tEo get that initiative, as you call it, into its perspective.<br />
I repeat what both Bill Hayden and I have said from the<br />
beginning. We haven't tried to overstate what it is that we<br />
are about nor the difficulties of the objective of getting a<br />
more constructive dialogue between all the parties to the issue.<br />
No, I think that the conditions which made it realistic to<br />
think about that still pertain. That is that despite the<br />
current diversion, if you like, our relations with the ASEAN<br />
countries are sound and good. our relations with China are<br />
excellent. Our relations with the United States are<br />
excellent and we do have a capacity for dialogue with Vietnam.<br />
Now, all those basic conditions still pertain. I don't think<br />
anything that has happened changes those basic conditions.<br />
Therefore, within the limitations that we acknowledged at the<br />
beginning, I think there is still a capacity to try and<br />
facilitate<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Hawke, without pre-empting the talks in Bangkok,<br />
do you * ee the emphasis in the discussions over the rift in<br />
ASEAN being on reclarifying Australia's position on Kampuchea,<br />
or telling the ASEAN nations that Australia will determine its<br />
own policy? </p>
<p>PM: Well, I think it is a melding of both. You will be<br />
aware that I won't be having to say anything new in<br />
Bangkok for both Bill Hayden and I within the Parliament<br />
and elsewhere have emphasised as strongly as we can our<br />
view about the situation in Kampuchea which is in regard to<br />
the fundamentals at one with the ASEAN countries. We have<br />
criticised as strongly as it is possible to do the invasion<br />
of Kampuchea by the forces of Vietnam and have indicated<br />
that the withdrawal of those forces is a necessary precondition<br />
of the emergence of an acceptable condition in<br />
Kampuchea. So-I don't have to go to Thailand and say that<br />
for the first time. I think the task is to make it clear<br />
to the Thai leaders that that is our position, that we have<br />
stated it publicly and we reiterate it to them. Within the<br />
context of doing that I will, of course, be explaining the<br />
reasons why we did not co-sponsor the ASEAN resolution on<br />
Kampuchea and I will be emphasising in that context that of<br />
course it is not only the right, but indeed the responsibility<br />
of any Australian Government in assessing its position on<br />
these matters to do so independently and in a way which<br />
reflects our judgement of the best interests of this country.<br />
Let me conclude by saying that I find in these circumstances<br />
I find no difficulty or contradiction in that situation in<br />
that what we adjudge to be in Australia's best interest<br />
and what we believe is the right assessment of the position<br />
in Kampuchea. I see no basic divergence between that<br />
judgement and that analysis on our part and that of ASEAN.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr. Fraser put a great deal of credence and<br />
significance on the Commonwealth and indeed CHOGM. Can I ask<br />
if you put that same form of significance and credence on<br />
the meeting that essentially can't force an issue and doesn't<br />
have the power to force through decisions that they make?<br />
PM: Well let me make 2-3 comments about that quickly. I am<br />
not in the business of trying to denigrate my predecessor.<br />
He is past and nothing is served by engaging in that exercise.<br />
I tried gently in my opening remarks to make the point that<br />
I am not going to use CHOGM as an opportunity for appearing to<br />
put positions or initiatives which are not consistent with<br />
policies that we put at home. Secondly, I would say that I<br />
don't think it is a fair assessment to down-grade CHOGM in the<br />
way I think was implicit in your question because their<br />
track record has some significant plusses in it. Indeed, I<br />
think no other institution internationally could have<br />
produced the outcome in Zimbabwe, that did in fact come out of<br />
the Commonwealth. So I think the value of the Commonwealth<br />
is to recognise its strengths and its limitations. You<br />
tended to emphasise its limitations. I think once you approach<br />
it in that way there is the capacity of getting the best out<br />
of it. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr. Hlawke, how important do you think it is for<br />
Australia to develop and broaden its links with Vietnam,<br />
particularly as part of the initiatives which you have<br />
referred to. And secondly, are we prepared to do this if<br />
countries such as China and the United States make it clear<br />
that they oppose this approach?<br />
PM: I think the correct answer to that, Paul, is along these<br />
li1nes. I think it would be against the interests of<br />
Australia ( inaudible)<br />
if we were to say look, it is important above all else that<br />
we strengthen the relations with Vietnam and say that could<br />
conceivably have certain plusses about it. You have got to<br />
put these things in . the balance. It is tremendously important<br />
for the future of this country. There is nothing more<br />
important for the future of this country than that Australia<br />
has very sound and constructive relations with the range<br />
of countries in our area because the future welfare of our<br />
children and their children is going to depend ' upon<br />
Australia being able positively to be linked into the very<br />
significant economic development which has been, is and will<br />
continue to take place in this area. We as a Government are<br />
not going to do anything in respect of one country which if<br />
pursued mindlessly would prejudice our capacity so to link in<br />
to the optimal extent with the other countries. I think the<br />
secret, if I can put it that way, is that we have to understand<br />
and the other countries of the area have to understand, that<br />
it is in none of our interests that Vietnam continues to be in<br />
a situation of virtual isolation in the international<br />
community resting solely almost solely if I can put it that<br />
way on a relationship with the Soviet Union and so I hope<br />
that gradually through these processes of dialogue to which<br />
I have referred and that there will be able to be developed<br />
a situation not simply where we are able to develop an<br />
effective relationship with Vietnam, but that would be part of<br />
a process in which Vietnam itself is brought broadly back into<br />
the community of nations. Now that is, I think, a correct<br />
statement of objectives and principles. I can see that giving<br />
effect to those objectives and those principles may create<br />
difficulties, but I believe that it is capable of being<br />
achieved. JOURNALIST: Can I bring you back, just for a second to a<br />
question raised by Ken Begg earlier? Apart from the official<br />
document put out by the US Embassy yesterday, have you had<br />
any personal assurances from the Americans that there are<br />
no basis in these claims that have been made consistently over<br />
the last couple of. days and not just by the Sydney Morning<br />
Herald. PM: I had, as you know, a discussion with the United States<br />
Ambassador recently and you would imagine that we discussed<br />
this issue and without going into the details of that<br />
discussion, it is fair to say that he did give me that assurance. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, could I ask you on a different<br />
subject a French business daily has reported that<br />
quoting you as saying that Australia is prepared to review<br />
uranium exports on certain conditions and you are quoted<br />
as saying " we shall deliver 250 tonnes of uranium late in 1984".<br />
PM: Yes, that has been brought to my attention. Let me say<br />
unequivocally that that report is wrong. There is no<br />
foundation for it and to save your time I merely indicate<br />
that there is a transcript a full transcript of that<br />
conversation that I had with the French journalist on 8th<br />
of this month and that is available in my office.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, Mr. Cheysson said yesterday he would be<br />
surprised if the Australian Government did not meet the<br />
commitment on the contracts. Do you think he has got reason<br />
to be surprised?<br />
PM: Well, I simply put the position as it is. I don't think<br />
that the putting of that position is aided by my commenting<br />
upon the state of mind of Mr. Cheysson. The position is that<br />
we indicated that we are not going to deliver uranium to<br />
France at any point before the due date which is the end<br />
of the latter part of 84, as you know. We have indicated<br />
quite clearly that we will continue to have discussions with<br />
the French. We will be having the Slattyer enquiry and<br />
together in both ways we will be trying to achieve a situation<br />
where the French would not be persisting with their tests.<br />
Let me make the point that it is quite clearly not in<br />
Australia's interests to create a situation of disarray, not<br />
merely with France, but with the European community and that<br />
is something, of course, that we are not seeking to achieve.<br />
It would be futile to try and achieve that position but at<br />
the same time we have to take account and I take account<br />
and the Government takes account of the well-based concern<br />
about the actions of the French in regard to nuclear testing<br />
and so our current position is clear. We will continue to<br />
address ourselves to it. Both Bill Hayden and myself aid<br />
other relevant Ministers and nothing is served by speculating<br />
about a future position. We are not, as I say, going to be<br />
making any early deliveries. We will be addressing ourselves<br />
to the situation in the hope that we will be able to have an<br />
acceptable situation between us and the French on this issue.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, could you describe the<br />
circumstances in your meeting, some years ago with a man<br />
described by the Opposition last week as having mafia<br />
connections or a mafia background?<br />
PM: Yes, I can. Before I do that can I take it that there<br />
are no further questions on the international<br />
Yes, let me make it quite clear that as I think you all<br />
understand, the meeting that you refer to was one of total<br />
innocence and one-offedness. In 1978 I went to a I don't<br />
know what you'd cal. it a cafe/ bar that had been suggested<br />
to me as an interesting place near where I was staying. I<br />
went there with David Combe, who for his own reasons has seen<br />
fit with recent-circumstances to raise this issue. And spent </p>
<p>a couple of hours there and this gentlemen whose name<br />
what was it Sal Ameno or whatever it is apparently was<br />
there -a somewhat Daman Runyonesque character, as I<br />
recall but may I say if I saw him as he walked into this<br />
room again, I wouldn't recognise him. I never saw him again<br />
and left and that was it. I wouldn't have known what he<br />
was then. It has been indicated to me subsequently what<br />
he was and is and that was the beginning and the end and<br />
I don't imagine that the gentleman, Mr. Combe, who has seen<br />
fit to raise this issue, suggests that that meeting was<br />
established that he has mafia connections or links and, of<br />
course, that is true equally as it is with me.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, did you have any indications since then<br />
that you may have been filmed or photographed by the FBI<br />
as you were coming or going?<br />
PM: No, I had no indications then or since. I'm not in<br />
constant communication or even unconstant communications<br />
with the FBI.<br />
OAKES: They didn't send you the negatives?<br />
PM: NO, I'm not aware of anything like that, Laurie.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you recall anything that was discussed<br />
with the genteleman<br />
PM: No, I can't. I can't. I can just remember that David<br />
and I were rather amused by the way the fellow talked and<br />
he was a character. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
