<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1343</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO US AND UK - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT, AT BLAIR HOUSE, WASHINGTON - 1ST JULY 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/07/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001343_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRi ii IT ISTER'S VIS. IT TO U. S. . IND U. K.<br />
Press Conference gaivte, n by thToe Primee . inister,<br />
Mr. Harold Holt, B. alta ir THouse,., ashinton. 1st July, 1966.<br />
Q. ' ould you sum up how your feel about this visit?<br />
HR. HOLT: Mr. Cox, as you know, mjy rain pu. rpose in co:: ing to<br />
iashington was to establish a closer working relationship .;: ith<br />
the President and senior mei. bers of his Administration, I think<br />
it can be fairly clai., ed that this objective has been completely<br />
satisfactory and successful viewed from . y standpoint. Certainly<br />
I have been shown a '. ar kindness and generosity of reception,<br />
and in my discussions I have found all those with w-hom I have<br />
talked forthcoming in giving me whatever infori.: ation was sought<br />
from them. i have had some very useful discussions with some of<br />
the leading members of the Administration, and these will be<br />
helpful not only to a better ! nderstanding c United States policy<br />
as it applies henceforth, but I will have a background to<br />
developments as they occur from now on.<br />
I am the more strongly persuaded than ever that the<br />
President is making every conceivable effort to secure a peaceful<br />
outcome to the struggle in South Viet larn, but I an also firi; ly<br />
clearly of the mind that his own resolution remains unwavering,<br />
and in that he has the full support of his colleagues. That is<br />
the strong impression I have gained from my talks with him.<br />
Q. iir, Prime Minister, there is some oriticism in Australia<br />
in one or two newspapers and in one or two political quarters that<br />
you are being too fulsome about American policy. Any cormment?<br />
MR. HOLT: w. ell, if I am fulsome, I believe we have every reason to<br />
be. If Australia cannot be appreciative of what Am. erica has<br />
meant to our country in terms of security and coradeship, then<br />
there is little room for gratitude left in the world. That does<br />
not mean that we have to agree at all tii: es vitheverything that is<br />
done or said, but what it does mean, that there is a basic friendship<br />
and comradeship between us which surmounts any minor<br />
differences which may arise from time to time in sole aspect of<br />
government..<br />
Q. Mr. Prime . inister, may I ask so: ething going to the<br />
point of how, much consultation there is between the two<br />
governments? For instance, on the decision to bomb Hanoi and<br />
Haiphong, were you informed just as the planes :, ere about to<br />
take off or did you have enough advance notice that you could<br />
express your views?<br />
im. HOLT: / e had enough advance notice,<br />
Does that mean, sir, before you left Australia? </p>
<p>JEHO: ell, I ao not '. znt to go ilto detail about -hat is<br />
obviously highly confidential discussions botween goverm.-ents.<br />
Iaade the poijnt before to you that from-thile tiLe I took oflice,<br />
President Johnson made it knov. n to i; C that he wished the sale<br />
intimate basis of consultation ;' hich has developed between Sir<br />
Robert lenzies and himself to continue, and that has been the<br />
situation bet&gt;-. en us, .; hat this visit has done has been to put<br />
all those intimate consultations into a frame'w. ork of personal<br />
association. oes thAt mean, Lr. Prim. e minister, it is between the<br />
President and the Prime linister, or on the State -epartrient<br />
Lxternal Aifairs level? Just the machinery, I mean?<br />
il. IHOLT: .1ell, there are at timnes coL: L:, unications which remain<br />
on a President to Prime linister basis. . ie both have the<br />
responsibilities of final judgment and leadership in our<br />
respective Adm. inistrations. There are other occasions and other<br />
topics on which clearly discussion inside the Australian<br />
Government is sought and it occurs from, timie to tine.<br />
Q. Are your talks this week, sir, in anything of the nature<br />
of decisions on any points or understandings?<br />
IR. HOLT: Iell, they haven't been talks on mere generalities or<br />
exoressions of good ill, however sincere and desirable, There<br />
have been some good working sessions on matters in which we are<br />
both interested, but I an afraid i cannot develop the themes.<br />
Q. 1r. Prime lii: ister, could you give us your appraisal<br />
of' the situation in ca. munist China, and to -hat degrce it is<br />
now affecting the situation in Viet 11am? Do you think there are<br />
any efforts to, ards peace?<br />
1i2. HOLT: ell, I an not sure that I apprehend the -iuestion<br />
completely. I do not think anyone can have a very authoritative<br />
view at the present time as to just ,. hat is happening inside<br />
cona; unist China, In fact, I doubt whether the couunist leaders<br />
themselves can have a very clear view of all the currents that<br />
apear to be swirling around in that country There appear to be<br />
significant changes occLr. rn g, and this is s-,: mething quite<br />
distinct fro-the ideological conflict or tacticl conflict that<br />
has been going on between China and Soviet icussia. ., ith an<br />
ageingleader in China, it appears th!. t there are forces working<br />
towrds the' day *; hen soxc change in leadership will occur. But<br />
ho.: far there are fundamental policy changes, it -wo! ald take<br />
somileone mnore highly specialized in analy. sis of the China<br />
situation than myself to answer that question.<br />
r. Prime i iter, has yo-r visit to , ashington sho* wn<br />
you any wvay in w; hich lustralia can take initiative to! wards peace<br />
in Viet Nan?<br />
LR. HOUP: I do not think so. It is well kno-', n that we supoort<br />
the efforts for peace. There has been : o indication that any<br />
level the Hanoi Govern.:. ent old be receptive to a peace move.<br />
Australians aLe a friendly people and a conciliatory people. </p>
<p>( Mr. Holt contd)<br />
I think th: Kt they 1ould be Jlad to join in mny capacity in the<br />
task of securing pieace, if this co-ld be negotiated, but there<br />
is no fresh initiative that seti. is possible aa-si leD, ean Ruskl<br />
puts it, the other fellow keeps hanging up the phone.<br />
Q. He said this in Canberra yesterday?<br />
HOLT: Yes.<br />
Q. sir, does the oosition of 1Australia in firx support of<br />
the United States policy in Viet 1Nani have any overtones for you<br />
when you have you, discussions with Prime inister ilson in<br />
London next week? . ill there be an effort at persuasion wIade<br />
there?<br />
vMR. HOLT: NO. I look fo2rw; ard to hav. i. ng a very frank and full<br />
discussion with Prime ister dilbson. It goes without saying<br />
that it w1ill be a friendly discussion, and it would be a sad day<br />
in the affairs of our two countries :. hen ie could not speak<br />
frankly to each other, exhibiting those in which ve can find full<br />
agreeiment and those in which so. e dizferences nmay exist. I do<br />
notrayself forsee difficulties in discussion, but they , would be not<br />
worth the journey from the distance th t I have ,: iade if they were<br />
not to be in fact frank and searching discussions. I am sure : e<br />
shall have those.<br />
Q. Do your talks give you any<br />
MR. HOLT: I was going to make a com. ent about the introductory<br />
part of your question. I don't know ;. hether I have yet miade it<br />
sufficiently clear in this country that Austrlia's attitude in<br />
relation to same is not merely a process of following in the wake<br />
of American policies. That ' ustralia has seen the struggle in<br />
South Viet NThim as Jrore directly involving it ththe United States<br />
itself. I think it is an act of far-sighted statesmanship for the<br />
United States to join in the resistance to aggression there, but<br />
if there were not champions on the nainland of . isia, then<br />
Australia and i. any other countries would feel far less secure<br />
than they uo at this tim-e. And so vie have quite an independent<br />
judgment which fortunately leads us to the sam. e conclusions as<br />
those which have been reached by the United States.<br />
Have your talks given any indication at all whether a<br />
terination of the war can be measured in terms of years or<br />
nonths?<br />
MR. HOLT: iell, I will put it in a slightly difrerent v. a y. I find<br />
rather more optimismi here, as I did in Canberra, than I have<br />
known at any earlier point of time as to the outcom. e. But I<br />
think it is best that i don't put a tine factor too precisely in<br />
this sort of thing, but undoubtedly there is a feeling hicm -; as<br />
reflected by the Foreign iIinisters and others at the SEATO<br />
Conference coming frc.; the area them , selves, and I find that<br />
reflected also hc; re in .: ashinrgton at all levels where I have held<br />
discussions.<br />
Q. Even amfong the critics of the Johnson Adinistration,<br />
sir? </p>
<p>Ii7~.~-TO'iP: NO, o, w s) e-k--ng of' tihose inside thed~~ trt n<br />
P:., rhaps there hasn' t bEen tiim-e or perhaps peo_,. le are rather too<br />
polite ,, hcn they encounter<br />
I know1M, sir.<br />
x. R HOLY: But Ihaven't touched off a debate on this iiatcr<br />
Q. I notice SOf&gt; O-. of the Luests at dinner parties have<br />
included strong critics of the Johnson Adxiinistration. I , onder<br />
whether you had any chance " or argurment?<br />
M. HOLT: No, I haven't had and they haven't soughtu to Y.; ake an<br />
argument of it. At the -, h. ite House luncheon I thinik sittin-g<br />
immiediately opposite was . senator Fuibric-ht, but he made his<br />
vie-. w1s kno clearly a;-n d vigorously enough.<br />
Q. Did you get across to him, sir, how m71any troops there<br />
are? Did you -et across to himi imany Au stralian troops are<br />
in action?<br />
M. HOLT: I aim: still fi-nding it a little diflicult to ha--ve people<br />
realize that -' astralia is not represented m-, erely iLn Viet NHa;;, and<br />
1 have been rather surprised to learn the extent of ignor. ance in<br />
relation to the .,, ustralian population. -iiven our good friend the<br />
President yesterday ga,: ve an enlarger., ent to the point that as a<br />
form---er ImiliAgratioi i-nister th-t delighted ebut I found in a<br />
numerofplaces som, e surprise th't A1-, stralia has as yet only<br />
reached eleve n and a half iimillion peo. ple. It is rather<br />
flatte really, because -, wec appepar to make a big--er noise<br />
than that. Did I understand you to say, sir, that you find i~ t a<br />
little difi'icult to ire upon peo. ple that lustralians are<br />
actually fijghting in Viet NaLLI?<br />
1IR. HOLT: Oh, No,, N\ o, that ' usti:-lans are at other points around<br />
S3octh Last Alsia.<br />
Q. Yes.<br />
1M. HOLT: For examj-, ple, w., e have trcoops in .' est . Ilays ia, wehave<br />
theia in Borneo, . e halve them at Ubon, in ThaiL3:. nd. have<br />
responsibilities in respect of Papus and iJew Guine3a, land. u ha-. ve<br />
a requja-ehment to use superior trained regular service i~ icn for the<br />
expansion of our oiwn forces both in the regular ariy units and<br />
the civilian m-i litary force, the CuPT as w., e call it.<br />
No%' w, all of the gocner-, lr of newispapr knws bu<br />
it, that kustralia ha,; s a task l'orce of four and a hal:,; f thousand<br />
in South Vict Niami and th: ot-doesn't seim very but as a<br />
force of regular ; e-ta uLtroops, thcludiiug the Il1ational<br />
~~ ervice re -otpon ngtie t the num,--bers up, nd hay rig<br />
regard to the rotatl-nml aspect of that service, this is not<br />
wit'hout so:: e stress on our failrly 1lmited resources. But w e<br />
have shown ourselves in a sitaation of' need. 71Jis has been<br />
dePmonstrutuAd ccrtailyl in thc. tx, o world wars, ofi supjyi-ng that<br />
neud i-Jhen it is rcequired of us. </p>
<p>( MR. Holt contd j.<br />
I think that it is wel recognized now by the Ad. miniistration<br />
here that Australia does h . ve a problem of development as . veli<br />
as a need to supply forces in the defence fiuid. There is I<br />
think as a result of the discussions we have held from the<br />
begiining of t'iis year on.,. rc:-s a recognition that these<br />
development tasks do create demands on our rescurces -which place<br />
some li. it on our capacity in other directions.<br />
I don't knovi whether I have : uoted to you before the<br />
figure of savings in consumption in Australia, which amount to<br />
about 28 per cent of our gross national incom: e, and in the<br />
United States and Great Britain there is a with-holding frcm<br />
consumption of about 17 to 18 per cent as against 28 in Australia,<br />
and ours is the highest figure of any country in the world with<br />
the exception of Japan, so that we are using our own resources<br />
and abstaining fr'm consumption of -what ie produce ourselves,<br />
in order to develop and defend.<br />
Q. Could you expand a little on what makes the situation<br />
look a little brighter in South Viet -Nam?<br />
IR. HOLT: ,' ell, a combination of factors. I think the military<br />
operations themselves are proving much more effective. The<br />
defection rate is quiite significant. There is more information<br />
being gathered which is enabling more effective military actions<br />
to follow up. I think that the political situation has<br />
brightened internally, at least to the extent that Prime Minister<br />
Ky is coming through his trouble with the buddhists rather better,<br />
I think, than i: ost observers had expected. shall still watch<br />
with interest the ej. ergence of the Assembly, the constituent<br />
Assembly, following its elections, and no doubt there '.-ill be<br />
political problems associated :. ith the drafting of a constitution.<br />
But there Is am; ongst the diplomatic and ilitary representatives<br />
not only of the United States, but of Viet Nam, of our owm<br />
country and other countries represented there, a feeling that<br />
significant progress is being maie both in the military field,<br />
in the organization of the country, and with sa: Te improvement in<br />
the political atmosphere.<br />
I think, too, there are portents around the area in<br />
other countries '. which have their own significance. I firmily<br />
believe that you would not h:. ve had develop on the scale and the<br />
man!-er that it did the action against co. mmLunis in Indonesia,<br />
if there had been a general feeling in Indonesia that co. ~. munism<br />
was going to win in -sia, and the announcement of military<br />
participation by Thailand, the final discussion/ fe Philippines<br />
to make engineers and security forces available, I think these<br />
things all reflect the assess: ments v. hich governments of both<br />
countries : make of the situation.<br />
Q. Did you get any kind of clues about the kind of<br />
government in South Viet Nanm vhich would be tolerated by<br />
Australia ancd iAerica, in the event of elections or in the<br />
event of a pacification, especially the election' </p>
<p>6.<br />
fi. HOLT: I do not think it is for ~ s to try to dict.' to a for21<br />
01 i&amp; overi-ment. . hat is dlesired, I think, is a govcrniwint<br />
capablo of' rumni!_ ig the country cffectivuly, protecting<br />
individual liberties, providing for an ii1roved cconlO-. ic<br />
manageTment and 30is.,., 74 standal-ds that ' s the sort of<br />
government thlat 6o, -th Viet 1Llai; a is looking f or. Until the<br />
railitar, operati,_ ns can be broi.--h: t succeLssful_ lfy~ tU 1f<br />
ccai-ly you ar-e going tr) have a strong 1m. ilitary influence in any<br />
governr~ ent hihMay be œ! med.<br />
P-i-e Ivinst r, it is 1O. OC o'clock, so I think it Ls<br />
bes t ~ eshoudid close.<br />
HC. Thank you for the very generous cover that you have<br />
Liven to our' visit here, That ccrtainly helped toy ards ma. I~ kin-g<br />
it i: orc sacccssful. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
