<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1921</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. J.G. GORTON IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, CANBERRA, 19TH SEPTEMBER 1968 - AUSTRALIAN LOAN IN GERMANY</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/09/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001921.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
2 5SEP 1960<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRiME MINISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
J. G. GORTON IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES,<br />
CANBERRA<br />
19TH SEPTEMBER 1968<br />
AUSTRALIAN LOAN IN GERMANY<br />
The Commonwealth Treasurer, Mr McMahon, today comple~ ed<br />
a successful round of negotiations and signed a loan agreement in<br />
Frankfurt, Germany, with the Deutsche Bank for the issue of DM 200 million<br />
6 million) Commonwealth securities maturing in 1974. The Deutsche<br />
Bank will arrange for the private placement of the securities with fina ncial<br />
institutions. The terms and conditions of the loan were settled with the<br />
approval of the Australian Loan Council. The securities will have an<br />
interest coupon of 6. 25 per cent, and Will be issued at 99. 5 per cent to<br />
give a yield to maturity of 6, 35 per cent. The net proceeds of the loan<br />
will be paid to the Commonwealth on 30 September. The foreign currency<br />
proceeds will be added to Australia's international reserves and the<br />
Australian currency equivalent will be applied to the Commonwealth<br />
Government's share of the 1968-69 works and housing programme approved<br />
by the Australian Loan Council.<br />
The Commonwealth has not previously borrowed for works and<br />
housing programmes for periods of less than ten years. However, with<br />
the pubki loan markets in New York and London effectively closed to<br />
Australia because of high borrowing costs, the amount tha t could be<br />
obtained through long-term loans is limited and advantage has been taken<br />
of the availability of medium-term finance in Europe. This will add<br />
usefully to our oversea loan raisings this year. The Government regards<br />
this as a highly successful outcome which reflects great credit on<br />
Australia's status as a borrower in the European market.<br />
The Commonwealth has previously raised two public loans in<br />
Germany, each for DM 100 million 3 million), in October 1967 and<br />
July 1968, through underwriting syndicates led by the Deutsche Bank. In<br />
addition a loan of DM 16. 8 million 8 million) was arranged with the<br />
Deutsche Bank in February last for Trans-Australia Airlines. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
