<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5944</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON HIS VISIT TO SOUTH AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/10/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005944.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1-7 EMBARGO: 6.3Opn<br />
J &gt;) AU 6 ALIA JT<br />
FOR MEDIA FRIDAY, 22 OCTOBER 1982<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER ON HIS VISIT TO<br />
SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
It has given me very great pleasure today to name the<br />
new international terminal at Adelaide airport after Tom<br />
Playford.<br />
Tom Playford was not only a father figure to South<br />
Australians, his name is almost synonymous with the<br />
economic development of this State. During his years as<br />
Premier he transformed South Australia from an<br />
agricultural economy to one of Australia's major<br />
industrial and manufacturing centres. That was a<br />
notable achievement by a man who had the determination<br />
and the drive to help build South Australia and<br />
Australia. The new terminal, which has been built at a cost to the<br />
Commonwealth Government of $ 11 million, and the<br />
beginning of international services into Adelaide will<br />
give South Australia's growing tourist industry a great<br />
boost and will help develop this State's business<br />
contacts with the rest of the world.<br />
This achievement is very much the work of David Tonkin<br />
who in his determination to build up South Australia has<br />
shown much of the same drive and determination which Tom<br />
Playford had. He inherited a dispirited, depressed<br />
State, and in a difficult world economic environment he<br />
has laid the foundations for an important new phase in<br />
the development of the South Australian economy : he has<br />
worked to rebuild its manufacturing base and he has<br />
begun to develop this State's enormous potential as a<br />
resource producer.<br />
Extensive exploration over the last three years has<br />
revealed the vast reserves of good quality coal which<br />
South Australia has, in particular the Wintinna coal<br />
field in the Arckaringa Basin in the far north of the<br />
State. This is estimated to contain 1,500 million<br />
tonnes of coal. The Government has encouraged<br />
exploration for oil and gas in the Cooper basin in the<br />
.12 </p>
<p>-north east of South Australia and the results of that<br />
exploration have been most impressive. This year about<br />
million are being spent on exploration there. It<br />
has also enabled the significant development based on a<br />
fractionation plant at Stony Point to proceed which I<br />
have seen today. In total that project will involve<br />
expenditure of about $ 1 billion.<br />
But above all, the South Australian Government has gone<br />
ahead with the development of the giant Roxby Downs<br />
copper, gold and uranium project. As the Minister for<br />
Trade and Resources pointed out in Parliament this week<br />
the draft Environmental Impact Statement estimates that<br />
Roxby Downs has at least 2,000 million tonnes of<br />
mineralised material. For planning purposes, production<br />
capacity has been set at 150,000 tonnes of copper a<br />
year, 3,000 tonnes of uranium oxide a year, 3,400<br />
kilograms of gold a year, and up to 23,000 kilograms of<br />
silver a year. The annual value of production could<br />
range from $ 442 million to $ 658 million per annum. The<br />
capital cost of the project in 1981 terms will be $ 1,400<br />
million. During the construction stage between 9,300<br />
and 18,600 jobs will be created directly and indirectly<br />
in South Australia. The production workforce will be<br />
2,400, but the total employment generated in the long<br />
term will be between 5,700 and 8,300. A township of<br />
8,000 rising to 9,000 will be established with planning<br />
envisaging a town population of approximately 30,000<br />
people. That is a project of immense importance to the<br />
Iron Triange, to South Australia and to all Australians.<br />
And it brings with it the possibility that South<br />
Australia may be chosen as the site for a uranium<br />
enrichment plant.<br />
That development would be destroyed by the election of a<br />
State Labor Government on 6 November. The Roxby Downs<br />
project would be abandoned, the uranium enrichment plant<br />
could not come to South Australia, the great<br />
opportunities which have been created for this State by<br />
the Tonkin Government would be lost.<br />
And let there be no doubt that Labor would destroy the<br />
uranium industry. They w ant to shut the industry down.<br />
In July Labor amended its uranium policy. But that<br />
amendment makes no difference to the policy's objective.<br />
As Mr Hayden on 8 July said after the policy had been<br />
amended :" Our policy unequivocally supports the<br />
objective of an end to the uranium industry".<br />
On 11 July he said: " There has been misrepresentation<br />
and uninformed comment suggesting we have abandoned our<br />
opposition to uranium mining in Australia. Thi s is a<br />
travesty of the facts". 3 </p>
<p>And the mover of the amendment said " They ( the ALP)<br />
have built conditions into it ( the uranium policy) which<br />
bluntly I do not think can be met".<br />
By closing down our uranium industry Labor would be<br />
denying energy to a world which, over the next few<br />
years, is bound to be short of energy. Labor would deny<br />
Australians jobs and they would deny our country<br />
about $ 4 billion in export earnings.<br />
For that reason alone South Australians, all<br />
Australians, cannot afford narrow, ideological Labor<br />
governments which would destroy great opportunities to<br />
build our country up. South Australians should take as<br />
a warning what Mr Wran has done in New South Wales where<br />
bad economic management has led to massive increases<br />
in State charges and taxes. They should take as a<br />
warning what Mr Cain has done in his first budget in<br />
Victoria: he has increased expenditure and revenue by<br />
over 24% and State taxes have been put up by nearly<br />
These big spending plans are reminiscent of the gross<br />
extravagence of the Whitlam years. That is the pattern<br />
of Labor Governments everywhere.<br />
David Tonkin has laid the foundations for a complete<br />
reversal in S. A.' s fortunes. He deserves every support<br />
to build on those firm foundations. ooo000ooo---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
