<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10758</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP RADIO INTERVIEW WITH DAVID HOOKES RADIO 3AW, MELBOURNE BROADCAST 6.00 PM - 8.00 PM AEST</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>Welcome back to Sports Today. Well today in Adelaide, on the eve</p>
<p>   of Ian Healy's 100th Test match, the Prime Minister of Australia,</p>
<p>   the Right Honourable Mr John Howard opened the Bradman Collection</p>
<p>   at the South Australian State Library and </p>
<p>Sir Donald Bradman has given something like 150 of personal items</p>
<p>   to the Library and the Prime Minister was there to open it, as we</p>
<p>   said, and he joins us on the line on Sports Today. Mr Prime Minister,</p>
<p>   thank you very much for your time. What a moment it must have been</p>
<p>   for you today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is a great exhibition, David. The fact that so many personal</p>
<p>   items have been donated by Sir Donald, not just the bats that he</p>
<p>   used to score his great accumulation of runs but also memorabilia</p>
<p>   that he has collected over the years from all around the world.</p>
<p>   And it really has been put together in a wonderful exhibition and</p>
<p>   I am sure it will be something of a Mecca not only in South Australia</p>
<p>   but around Australia, for cricket lovers. And the support that the</p>
<p>   exhibition has received from the business community in South Australia,</p>
<p>   and of course from the cricketing fraternity, has been immense.</p>
<p>   It was really - for a cricket lover like myself - it was quite a</p>
<p>   privilege and experience to open the exhibition.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>John, do you think that if you had used one of those bats that</p>
<p>   Sir Donald made 1,000 runs, your batting career might have been</p>
<p>   a bit better?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am sure it would have been different. I was actually handed one</p>
<p>   of them and the one where he got his, where he reached his thousand</p>
<p>   runs in the 1930 tour of England and it felt real good.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>John, for those people listening over here in Melbourne, who may</p>
<p>   venture over during the footy season to Adelaide and wanted to go</p>
<p>   to the State Library, what sort of area does the collection take</p>
<p>   up?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh it doesn't take up a huge area but it is the sort of thing</p>
<p>   that you can either take half an hour or six hours. And the Library,</p>
<p>   of course, is in the centre of Adelaide. It is not very far from</p>
<p>   the Adelaide Oval and it really is in an ideal spot and it has been</p>
<p>   very, very beautifully done and there is - as well as all the old</p>
<p>   memorabilia - there is plenty of, there is an electronic presentation</p>
<p>   of all his records and his scrap books and his performances and</p>
<p>   it is the best exhibition of that kind that I think I have ever</p>
<p>   seen because its got a very imaginative arrangement. It has got</p>
<p>   all of his old blazers, his old creams, his old boats, his old pads</p>
<p>   and then of course, naturally, the bats and the stumps and it has</p>
<p>   even got a little cocktail table which is held up by three stumps</p>
<p>   which was one that apparently he had made for his home. So it is</p>
<p>   a wonderful exhibition and of course having it on the eve of the</p>
<p>   Test match it gave it an extra special zing. And of course, Donald</p>
<p>   and his late wife Jessie, who lived in Adelaide since 1934, are</p>
<p>   really, of course, became the most revered citizens of that city.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>And I notice also John that you unveiled a bronze bust of Sir Donald?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I did.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>Some 99 of him made and I do believe John that his family spoke</p>
<p>   to him about the fact that he had given so much to this library</p>
<p>   and so much to the Bowral Museum in NSW that there was nothing left</p>
<p>   for the family to have and that Sir Donald was really pleased when</p>
<p>   he was presented with that with Michael Brock, the Chairman of that</p>
<p>   Committee. And he said to Michael, well I have got something now</p>
<p>   to hand down to my family.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Typical of the man. He has been very generous in memorabilia and</p>
<p>   he has been painstaking in helping the library and the exhibition</p>
<p>   and the people sponsoring it in assembling so much. And the only</p>
<p>   thing, incidentally, they haven't been able to track down is</p>
<p>   a baggy green because he has given them all away. Now I just hope</p>
<p>   that as a result of the publicity being given to the exhibition,</p>
<p>   somebody who has got one of his baggy greens will donate it to the</p>
<p>   exhibition. So it will be very interesting to see if that occurs.</p>
<p>   But over the years you can imagine just how many there were and</p>
<p>   incredibly enough they haven't been able to get an original,</p>
<p>   they have got a replica but not actually one that he wore.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>It is not in the bar at The Lodge is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I have to say not that. It is not in the bar at The Lodge.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>I spoke to you a couple of days ago in Perth and you made the point</p>
<p>   that you saw Sir Donald play?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I saw Sir Donald play once. I saw his last innings on the Sydney</p>
<p>   Cricket Ground. I went onto The Hill at the Sydney Cricket Ground</p>
<p>   in 1949 with my father, to see him play in the Kippax Oldfield Testimonial.</p>
<p>   And he got, from recollection, about 50. And that was the very last</p>
<p>   time that he appeared on the Sydney Cricket Ground and I have never</p>
<p>   forgotten the amazing reception that he received from the Sydney</p>
<p>   crowd. And, of course, in those days we had The Hill and it was</p>
<p>   something that I always remember. But I only ever saw him play once</p>
<p>   and of course that is now almost 50 years ago.</p>
<p>But I said in my speech earlier today that the extraordinary thing</p>
<p>   about him is that the years haven't dimmed the affection in</p>
<p>   which he is held. And he really is the greatest living Australian</p>
<p>   and in many ways he was Australia's first celebrity and he</p>
<p>   has remained Australia's greatest celebrity.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>Yes and he turns 90 on August the 27th this year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>August the 27th this year he will turn 90 and he is just an amazing</p>
<p>   figure, who is not only a great sporting giant but he has played</p>
<p>   a very significant role in the culture of this country. He was a</p>
<p>   great source of hope and inspiration and leadership to a very depressed</p>
<p>   group of Australians during The Great Depression.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>He certainly was. Well John we do thank you for your time, we know</p>
<p>   that you have got a very busy day today and I also have heard from</p>
<p>   your staff that you were hoping to get the first day of the final</p>
<p>   Test match in Adelaide tomorrow but you have had to put that on</p>
<p>   hold sadly, for yourself?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have had to put that on hold, I really must go to Katherine to</p>
<p>   see the people who have been left devastated by these floods and</p>
<p>   I therefore won't be able to go to the cricket. But I will</p>
<p>   be listening to it, but I really must go to Katherine.</p>
<p>HOOKES:</p>
<p>Well John, thank you very much for your time. Pass on our best</p>
<p>   wishes to those people in Katherine for those floods, let us hope</p>
<p>   that they can get themselves back in order. We do appreciate your</p>
<p>   time and let us hope that tomorrows Test match is a good one and</p>
<p>   let us hope those people in Victoria who venture to Adelaide can</p>
<p>   get to the library and see the collection.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thanks, th</p>
<p>Thanks, thanks a lot.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
