<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9400</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP DEATH OF DR PETER WILENSKI, AC</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009400.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
K<br />
( f<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
DEATH OF DR PETER WILENSKI, AC<br />
Peter Wilenski died this morning after a long struggle with a very difficult<br />
illness. He leaves behind his wife, Jill, and two young children, Michael and<br />
Katy. I offer to them heartfelt condolences on my own behalf, and on behalf<br />
of the Government, its ministers and the public service as a whole.<br />
In a long career in many different positions as public servant, academic,<br />
ministerial adviser, arnd diplomat he made an enormous contribution to<br />
Australian public life. He played a key role in the revolutionary changes<br />
which transformed the face of Australian public administration, beginning with<br />
his involvement in the Coombs Royal Commission on Australian Government<br />
Administration in 1974 during the Whitlam Government. During his<br />
subsequent career, he headed four different government departments under<br />
three Labor governments as well as being chairman of the Public Service<br />
Board. The necessity of change was something he saw very clearly and articulated<br />
persuasively. Successive Labor governments availed themselves of his<br />
capacity to design and implement change.<br />
It was also a very important part of how Peter saw himself, and in that regard<br />
as in the happiness he found with his family his life was one of immense<br />
personal fulfilment.<br />
Throughout his life he was passionately committed to advancing social<br />
justice. His intellectual talent and his skill at public administration were<br />
illuminated by a strong sense of fairness. He was instrumental in creating a<br />
pmuebnl. ic sector inw hich women could begin to have the same opportunities as<br />
The pioneer Australian feminist, Edna Ryan, said today about Peter that ' he<br />
was a most unusual bureaucrat and a well-informed feminist. Probably no<br />
man gave more than Peter to the cause of the status of women in Australia'. 29 Cl 3 </p>
<p>2<br />
As Australia's ambassador to the United Nations in New York from 1989 to<br />
1992 he applied these same management skills and social commitment to<br />
advance the cause of reform of the United Nations and to focus the attention<br />
of the international community on to the needs of women and human rights<br />
icI sac<br />
He was a person of many dimensions. He had a great love of art, and a<br />
staggering array of interests in issues as diverse as his first profession,<br />
medicine, development assistance, and higher education.<br />
Australia has lost a national figure. We mourn that. But at the same time he<br />
has left us much for which the Government and country can be deeply<br />
thankful. CANBERRA 3 November 1994<br />
4 2964 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
