<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2691</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE RT HON W MCMAHON CH MP PRIME MINISTER ON NATIONAL URBAN AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY BILL 1972 SECOND READING</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002691.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH B3Y<br />
The Rt Hon. W. MeMAHON, M. P.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
ON<br />
National Urban and Regional Development<br />
Authority Bill 1972<br />
Second Reading<br />
[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 11 October 1972]<br />
Mr McMAHON ( Lowe-Prime Minister)<br />
( 11.40)-1 move:<br />
That the Bill be now read a second time.<br />
On 19th September, I made a statement<br />
to the House announcing that the Government<br />
proposed to take new initiatives to<br />
work with the States towards urban and<br />
regional development objectives. I said that<br />
the Government had decided that it will take<br />
immediate steps financially and in other<br />
ways in a co-ordinated programme with the<br />
State Governments. The introduction of this<br />
-Bill fulfils the commitment I then gave to<br />
introduce interim legislation into Parliament<br />
this session. Although the legislation<br />
is interim, the new authority set up by the<br />
bill will nevertheless be required to operate<br />
with vigour and in accord with its charter<br />
from the outset. In a vast country which is<br />
developing as rapidly as Australia, it is<br />
most important that the Government take<br />
responsible action which will influence the<br />
distribution of population and economic<br />
activity to the economic and social advantage<br />
of the nation.<br />
The stresses and strains of growth are having<br />
an impact on the living conditions and<br />
the environment of the entire Australian community. These pressures which are<br />
being felt in many countries, present issues<br />
of national moment warranting co-operative<br />
action between the Commonwealth and<br />
the States. We have the experience of the<br />
United Kingdom, France and Canada<br />
amongst others to draw on. The Government<br />
believes that unless we embark on a<br />
vigorous, imaginative and responsible programme<br />
of urban and regional development,<br />
in partnership with the States, our<br />
efforts to secure a better quality of life for<br />
the Australian community through a wide<br />
variety of existing programmes will be<br />
compromised. The consequences of the<br />
imbalance caused by the concentration of<br />
population and employment around the<br />
principal Australian cities with the resulting<br />
problems of congestion and pollution<br />
are such that action must now be taken.<br />
The trend to increasing concentration is<br />
already evident to a degree which is causing<br />
concern. If no action is taken, the<br />
problem will become more acute as our<br />
population grows from 13 million to possibly<br />
22 million over the balance of the<br />
century. The increasing concentration of<br />
population in our great cities will magnify<br />
the consequences of increasing population </p>
<p>growth. It is the geographical distribution<br />
of population and industry rather than total<br />
scale which calls for our attention.<br />
We believe it is widely accepted that<br />
these are national problems requiring urgent<br />
attention, and that the Commonwealth<br />
should participate with the States in solving<br />
them. We believe too that a properly conceived<br />
and well managed programme of<br />
urban and regional development will be<br />
approved and welcomed by the community<br />
generally. It is clear that the Commonwealth<br />
and States must work together. It<br />
is also clear that there will be a need for<br />
additional expenditure and the Commonwealth<br />
stands ready to contribute its share.<br />
As, importantly, we will shape our own<br />
policies and programmes where appropriate<br />
so as to ensure that urban and regional<br />
implications are fully taken into account.<br />
The implementation of a successful national<br />
programme of urban and regional development<br />
could mark a turning point in the<br />
social and economic life of this country.<br />
Our efforts must be successful. Therefore,<br />
they must be properly conceived. The<br />
Commonwealth/ State Officials' Committee<br />
on Decentralisation which conducted its<br />
researches in the Australian context concluded<br />
that the only type of decentralisation<br />
which offers significant prospects of success<br />
is selective decentralisation. As I stated on<br />
19th September, the Commonwealth endorses<br />
this conclusion and favours the<br />
development of a small number of carefully<br />
selected centres, having regard to factors<br />
likely to be favourable to their<br />
growth. Later on, with the benefit of more<br />
experience and the availability of more<br />
resources, it can be expected that additional<br />
centres will be selected for accelerated<br />
growth. We will want to identify and encourage<br />
the balanced growth of submetropolitan<br />
centres as an alternative to<br />
growth in the existing city areas.<br />
In co-operation with the States, we will<br />
look for those sub-metropolitan centres that<br />
offer the greatest potential for rapid development.<br />
These will be centres near to but<br />
distinct from the existing major cities. It is<br />
our view that the development of regional<br />
growth centres and sub-metropolitan centres<br />
-projects capable of being defined, programmed<br />
and financed-offers the most<br />
direct and beneficial means of immediate<br />
Commonwealth involvement. As I have<br />
emphasised, however, the action to be taken must be taken in consultation and<br />
partnership with the States. Our early discussions<br />
with the States will have as their<br />
first objective the fullest understanding of<br />
the nature of the problems to be overcome.<br />
We will be seeking to establish how best<br />
the combined resources of the Commonwealth<br />
and State Governments can be marshalled<br />
to tackle these in an economic way<br />
and in the interests of the nation as a<br />
whole. As I have said previously, it will be<br />
necessary to guard against the cost of<br />
development of selected centres being inflated<br />
by increases in land values directly<br />
attributable to the policy initiatives of the<br />
States and the Commonwealth. This bill is<br />
the first step towards implementation of a<br />
new Commonwealth initiative. It is, however,<br />
designed to establish the National<br />
Urban and Regional Development Authority<br />
on a proper and sound basis and to enable<br />
it to commence its work immediately. The<br />
nature of any later legislation will, of course,<br />
be determined in the light of experience.<br />
Nevertheless, the name given to the<br />
Authority clearly indicates the Government's<br />
longer term interest. We are concerned<br />
with national objectives in urban<br />
and regional development and we are concerned<br />
with development itself. Ours is a<br />
practical approach and the concept of a<br />
statutory authority and of the title chosen<br />
for it reflects our practical aims.<br />
It is proposed that the Authority be constituted<br />
by a Commissioner. I have already<br />
announced that with the passage of the<br />
legislation, the Government proposes to<br />
invite Sir John Overall to serve as the first<br />
Commissioner and to guide the new organisation<br />
in its initial establishment period. The<br />
Government is fortunate in having a person<br />
as experienced and so able as Sir John to<br />
call on until his retirement in July next<br />
year. The bill also provides for the Commissioner<br />
to be assisted by a Deputy Commissioner.<br />
The appointment of statutory office<br />
holders will be effected as soon as possible<br />
after the bill is passed. The duties of the<br />
Authority are stated in Clause 12. It will<br />
be required to investigate and report to the<br />
Prime Minister on matters relating to urban<br />
or regional development. This investigation<br />
and advice would be designed to assist the<br />
Government in making decisions having<br />
urban and regional implications. It will also </p>
<p>be designed to assist the Government in<br />
its consideration of the grant of financial<br />
assistance to a State in connection with<br />
urban or regional development.<br />
Such matters as the selection of centres<br />
for the promotion of rapid growth, the<br />
particular steps by which this might be<br />
encouraged, practical arrangements for<br />
rapid development, and financial questions<br />
including the scale of Commonwealth support,<br />
are relevant to the establishment of a<br />
co-ordinated programme. Advice would be<br />
available to the Government from the<br />
Authority on the terms and conditions on<br />
which financial assistance for urban and<br />
regional development might be granted by<br />
Parliament. The bill provides for the Authority<br />
to have power to do all things that are<br />
necessary or convenient for the performance<br />
of its functions. It may undertake pilot<br />
or experimental projects, studies, including<br />
feasibility studies. It may enter into consultative<br />
engagements with professional groups<br />
and Government agencies, and provide information<br />
and advice to other authorities.<br />
Provision is made in the Bill for the<br />
Authority to comply with any directions<br />
given by the Prime Minister with respect to<br />
matters to be investigated by the Authority.<br />
This clause will ensure, for example, that<br />
decisions reached by the Ministerial Council,<br />
consisting of the Prime Minister and the<br />
Premiers, to which I referred in my statement<br />
in this House on 19th September, are<br />
followed through in the operations of the<br />
Authority. In addition to the normal provision for<br />
an annual report, the Authority is required<br />
to report to the Prime Minister not later<br />
than 30th June 1973 on matters relating<br />
to urban and regional development during<br />
the 5-year period thereafter. It is not the<br />
Government's intention that the Authority<br />
should produce by that time a definitive<br />
statement on a national urban and regional<br />
development strategy. The Government<br />
does, however, propose to move in an<br />
expenditure sense commencing from the<br />
financial year 1973-74. It will be the<br />
responsibility of the Authority, therefore,<br />
to advise the Government in time for its<br />
Budget considerations in 1973 of the broad<br />
direction in which Commonwealth activities<br />
in urban and regional development<br />
might be shaped over the 5-year period.<br />
This will not be a final blueprint but rather the first statement of an active programme.<br />
The steps involved in its preparation will<br />
be discussed by the Ministerial Council.<br />
Funds will be made available during this<br />
present financial year 1972-73 for the initial<br />
operations of the Authority.<br />
The Bill, of course, contains appropriate<br />
provisions relating to officers' rights, staff,<br />
audit and finance. The Bill establishes an<br />
advisory committee of up to 12 members<br />
including the Commissioner. The committee<br />
will be comprised of persons who, by<br />
virtue of their knowledge and experience,<br />
can assist the Authority in the performance<br />
of its duties. This is a formal committee<br />
created by the statute with membership<br />
appointed by the Prime Minister and<br />
designed to ensure the availability of a<br />
wide range of advice and response to the<br />
Authority. At the level of governments, I have<br />
already mentioned that we propose the<br />
establishment of a ministerial council consisting<br />
of the Prime Minister and Premiers<br />
as -the principal body for consultation and<br />
co-ordination in the field of urban and<br />
regional development. I have already<br />
written to the Premiers about the Commonwealths<br />
intentions. Honourable members<br />
have already noted from my remarks<br />
that the Authority will be responsible to<br />
me as Prime Minister. This central place in<br />
the machinery of Government will add<br />
strength to the discussions between me and<br />
my State colleagues.<br />
This Bill is amongst the most important<br />
legislation introduced into the Federal<br />
Parliament during the post-war years. It<br />
marks our recognition that there is a direct<br />
contribution that the Commonwealth Government<br />
can make in national urban and<br />
regional development for the benefit of all<br />
Australians. Commonwealth assistance for<br />
urban and regional development is not new.<br />
What is -new is Commonwealth participation<br />
with the States in a co-ordinated programme<br />
of urban and regional development.<br />
Our objectives-the objectives of the<br />
Liberal and Country Parties-will not be<br />
achieved easily or overnight. But it is<br />
important to make a start in -the prevailing<br />
climate of accord about the need for new<br />
initiatives and the broad nature of them.<br />
We will pursue these objectives vigorously.<br />
I commend the Bill to the House.<br />
2054817220581G7.2 . MuRRAY, Government Printer, Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
