<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8834</transcript-id>
    <title>LABOR SUPPORTS SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/03/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008834.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
0<br />
I<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
LABOR SUPPORTS SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY<br />
The Labor Goverrncent recognises science, technology and engineering as fundamental to<br />
a growing economy, a clean environment and a world class health system.<br />
The Government has an important role to play in supporting Australian science, not only<br />
through funding for basic research in universities, but by encouraging a long-term<br />
commitment from our business sector.<br />
Labor has a proud record of support for Australian science. Since 1982-83 funding has<br />
increased to $ 2.9 billion per year, a 39% increase in real terms. The 1992-93 Budget<br />
included the fourth successive real increase. i,<br />
We are committed to building on this record in order to make the most of our clever ideas<br />
and thereby underpin our growing international comptiies.<br />
We will continue to support the national science effort through commitment to institutions<br />
such as the CSIRO. The CTSIRO is more than a scientific research agency. Like the ABC,<br />
it is a nationa icon. It plays an important role in preserving the nation's heritage,<br />
encouraging ideas and strengthening national cohesion.<br />
We will also continue to support our high quality health and medical research system.<br />
Since 1982-83, Commonwealth funding of this important area has more than doubled in<br />
real terms. The results, in terms of research which improves the health of all Australians,<br />
have been outstanding. Labor will work with medical researchers and the business sector<br />
to lift research funding to 2.0% of total health expenditure by the year 2000. The National<br />
Health and Medical Research Council's Research Strategy will be important in helping<br />
the Government achieve this goal.<br />
Labor recognises that science involves a long-term investment. Funding cannot be turned<br />
on and off like a tap. It is for these reasons that the Government made the_ 150% R&amp; D tax<br />
concession a permanent part of the tax system. introduced and extended the Cooperative<br />
Research Centres program and will continue indefinitely univcrsikv. Tescarch infrastructure.<br />
funding beyond 1994.<br />
6926 </p>
<p>While Labor will invest substantially in the nation's technological future. te Coalition<br />
will cut research funding. According to Fightback. $ 20 million will be slashed from the<br />
science budget.<br />
The importance of science and technology was completely ignored by Dr Hewson in his<br />
campaign launch.<br />
Dr Hewson should recognise the importance of science and engineering, and the need for<br />
continuing government support. He must:<br />
pledge to maintain current levels of science funding and resile from the<br />
cuts proposed in Fightback;<br />
match Labor's commitments of $ 52 million per year for higher education<br />
research infrastructure and $ 25 million per year for ten new Cooperative<br />
Research Centres.<br />
The Coalition has failed to demonstrate either an understanding of or sympathy with the<br />
needs and aspirations of Australia's scientists and engineers. By contrast. Labor has<br />
worked hard to give science, technology and engineering a stronger role in Australia's<br />
future. It understands their importance and willcontinue to support them accordingly.<br />
CANBERRA 4 MARCH 1993 6927 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
