<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>29</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR. MENZIE MONDAY JUNE 13, 1995 </title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/06/1955</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000029.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
P R I V I L E G E C A S. E<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. MENZIES.<br />
MONDAY,' JUNE 13, 1955.<br />
TO MEMBERS: This is forwarded with the<br />
compliments of the Prime Minister. He trusts<br />
it will be helpful and that you will make use<br />
if it. P R I VI L E G EC A S. E </p>
<p>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER. MR. MENZIES<br />
PRIVILEGE CASE June 13. 1955.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Menzies. today<br />
made the following observations on the privilege case<br />
dealt with by the Commonwealth Parliament last week:--<br />
QUESTION: Who gave Parliament the right to deal with<br />
breaches of parliamentary privileges?<br />
ANSWER:. The Commonwealth Constitution did, by<br />
Section 49. which reads:.-<br />
' The powers, privileges and immunities of the Senate<br />
and of the House of Representatives, and of the<br />
members and the committees of each House, shall be<br />
such as are declared by the Parliament, and until<br />
declared shall be those of the Commons House of<br />
Parliament of the United Kingdom, and of its members<br />
and committees, at the establishment of the Common..-<br />
wealth..<br />
. Parliament has not thought it necessary<br />
to declare any new powers, privileges and immunities.<br />
but has been content to rest upon those already wellestablished<br />
by the House of Commons over the course<br />
of centuries.<br />
k. OUESTION What is the most important of these<br />
privileg. s. from a public point of view? </p>
<p>ANSWER: The privilege to speak freely in<br />
Parliament on behalf of the electors without fear<br />
or favour. This is the greatest of the Parliamentary<br />
privileges, for without it Parliament would become<br />
ineffective. The privilege does not exist as a sort<br />
of personal property of the individual member nor is<br />
he guilty of a selfish action when he seeks to defend,<br />
it. The privilege is that of the people speaking<br />
through their institution of Parliament. It must not<br />
be forgotten that the vital conflict in the 17th<br />
century was between the power and privilege of the<br />
King and the power and privilege of the Pa-rliament.<br />
It is only because that struggle was won by Parliament<br />
that modern democracy has become possible. -If a<br />
member-of Parliament can be threatened into silence<br />
on matters which, otherwise. * Ihe would think it his<br />
duty to lay before Parliament. then the most important<br />
of the people's democratic rights has been ta-ken away<br />
and the true function of Parliament threatened.<br />
QUESTION: But why should Parliament act as the<br />
judge in-the matter'when a breach of privilege is<br />
alleged?<br />
ANSWER: In the United Kingdom and in<br />
Australia anc*. as I believe, in all other 3ritish<br />
countries, the Parliament always has-been the judge.<br />
for the very good reason that it is constitutionally<br />
the expressed-custodian of its own rights and<br />
privileges.,. which. as I have said.. are the rights and<br />
privileges of the electors.<br />
QUESTION-Could Parliament. on this occasion.<br />
by some existing procedure. have delega-ted its<br />
-aut-hority to a Court? </p>
<p>ANSWER: No. Assuming that it could properly make<br />
such a law ( as to which I offer no opinion) Parliament<br />
would have had to legislate to define an offence and to<br />
invest some Court with the jurisdiction to investigate<br />
that offence. Clearly, any such law could not be made<br />
to apply to the case of Browne and Fitzpatrick except<br />
by retrospective operation; which would have been<br />
contrary to one of our most deeply-held principles of<br />
criminal jurisprudence.<br />
QUESTION: Were these men denied a fair hearing?<br />
ANSWER: All the facts are to the contrary. They<br />
appeared before the Committee of Privileges which,<br />
I stress, is an all-party Committee and, thereafter,<br />
fully and frankly admitted what they had done and. the<br />
reasons why they had done it. In a substantiallsense<br />
they pleaded guilty. This is made manifest by the<br />
unanimous report of the Committee which was unanimously<br />
agreedwith by the House. I do not want to re-state<br />
all the facts in the report but those who read it will<br />
see that Fitzpatrick agreed that the idea in printing<br />
the.. newspaper articles about Mr. Morgan wasto<br />
intimidate him and to prevent him saying things in<br />
Parliament. This statement was made by Fitzpatrick<br />
on several occasions. When asked by one member of the<br />
Conmmittee whet~ her, he realised that the documents would<br />
affect Mr. Morgan's reputation very seriously.<br />
Fitzpatrick replied that that was why it was put out.<br />
So far as Browne was concerned<br />
Fitzpatrick stated quite openly the reason-why he had<br />
employed ; rowne ' I told him to get stuck into him<br />
( Morgan). That is what I employed him for'.<br />
The witness. Browne. admitted to being<br />
the author of the articles and to having been paid<br />
for writing them. No attempt was made to prove the </p>
<p>charges against Mr. Morgan. In answer to the<br />
Committee. Mr. Browne said that he did not have<br />
the proof with him, nor did he possess the proof<br />
at the time the article was written. Mr.<br />
Fitzpatrick. when asked ' Have you any personal<br />
evidence of. any charges against. Mr. Morgan'.,<br />
replied: ' No_. The Committee found,, as it was bound to<br />
find on the undisputed evidence, that a deliberate<br />
attempt had been made to misrepresent Mr. Morgan<br />
and that both Fitzpatrick and Browne had been<br />
guilty of a serious breach of privilege by<br />
publishing articles intended to influence and<br />
intimidate a member ( the Honourable Member for<br />
Reid) in his conduct in the House and in<br />
deliberately attempting.. to impute corrupt conduct.<br />
as a Member ( Mr. Morg. an) for the express purpose<br />
of discrediting. and silencing him.<br />
There is, so far as .1 know, nothing in<br />
the general principles of the law which prevents<br />
somebody accused of an offence from pleading<br />
guilty and being dealt with accordingly.<br />
OUESTION: Did the House . of RepOresentatives act<br />
hastily ifn this matter?<br />
ANSWER: It did not. The unanimous report of the<br />
Committee was tabled during, the evening session on<br />
Wednesday, June 8th. Consideration of it was,<br />
deferred until next day. so that members might have<br />
an opportunity of reading it. I, myself. though<br />
much pressed with work. devoted several hours to<br />
studying the report and past Parliamentary practice.<br />
The matter. in fact, did not come on for discussion<br />
until the afternoon of Thursday, June 9th.. when.<br />
as Prime Minister. I moved that the house agree with<br />
the report of the Committee. This was discussed for<br />
some time and'the motion was then unanimously carried. </p>
<p>I thenx prooosed a motion that Fitzpatrick and Browne<br />
be notified to attend the House at 10 a. m. on Friday<br />
June 10th. They attended and they were heard one<br />
of them Browne at considerable length. It was<br />
necessary that they should be both seen and heard in<br />
a matter of such gravity.<br />
When Browne's speech was concluded. I<br />
suggested a suspension of sittings so that members<br />
could consider the material put before them.<br />
I immediately had a discussion with my<br />
Cabinet. because it will be agreed that a Government<br />
should be prepared to give some lead in such a matter.<br />
I then had a meeting of a few minutes with the Govern<br />
ment parties in which I told them what I was proposing<br />
to do. There was no question of action on party lines-<br />
Members were. obviously going to exercise a judicial<br />
function and could make their own decisions. 3ut. at<br />
the same time. my general impression was that. at any<br />
. rate., most Government supporters agreed with the<br />
Government's view. I understand ( I may have been<br />
misinformed) that the Executive of the Opposition<br />
also had discussions. The debate was resumed on a motion by<br />
myself. for the imposition of a term of imprisonment<br />
and an amendment by Dr. Evatt favouring the imposition<br />
of very substantial fines. It will be observed that<br />
we both thought a serious offence had been properly<br />
proved, and deserved se. rious punishment. The only<br />
difference was as to the nature of the penalty. The<br />
' debate continued on a high and responsible level:<br />
with the possible exception of one rather unfortunate<br />
and intemperate speech. with the final decision not<br />
being reched until almost the end of the afternoon<br />
session, The vote of the House was overwhelmingly<br />
in favour of imprisonment, members of all four parties<br />
forming part df the majority. </p>
<p>OUESTION Would a reprimand have been an adequate<br />
punishment in this case?<br />
ANSWE.: Hiaving regard to-what I have explained<br />
as the nature of the offence and of the finding<br />
-iade by the Committee, a-nd unanimously approved by<br />
the House, a mere reprimand would have been<br />
farcical. It would have amounted to a statement<br />
by the House of Representatives that a conspiracy<br />
to silence a member of Parliament was a trifling<br />
matter. It should not be forgotten that the<br />
freedom of Parliament and of every member in it<br />
is vital to the continuation of free self--government.<br />
OUESTION: Would not a fine have been preferable to<br />
committal to orison for contemot?<br />
ANSwEr Under the disclosed circumstances which<br />
indicated that Browne had been employed to do vha<br />
he did. it is in the highest-degree unlikely that<br />
any fine imposed upon him would have been paid by<br />
him. Indeed. Fitzpatrick had. before the Committee,<br />
declared that he assumed full responsibility for the<br />
whole matter. To impose a fine would, therefore.<br />
have meant that no punishment would have been<br />
inflicted upon Browne at all, while: so far as<br />
Fitzpatrick was concerned, even a substantial fine<br />
would, not have caused him any notable inconvenience.<br />
I should add that the power of the House<br />
to impose a fine is extremely doubtful, having been<br />
denied by several leading constitutional authorities.<br />
As the Constitution points out. the powers are those<br />
of the House of Commons, The House of Commons has<br />
not imposed a fine for breach of privilege since<br />
1666 but has invariably proceeded, either by<br />
committal to custody or by reprimand: in appropriate<br />
cases. In one of the most recent cases only a few<br />
years ago where a Member of Parliament was found<br />
guilty of a serious breach of privilege, the House of<br />
Commons actually expelled him from his seat in the<br />
House. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
QUESTION-: Are the privileges and immunities of<br />
Parliament inconsistent with, or a threat to. the<br />
freedom of the Press?<br />
ANSWER: No. the simple historic fact is that<br />
the modern protection of the freedom of Parliament<br />
and the equally modern freedom of the press have<br />
gone hand in hand. One cannot exist adequately<br />
without the other. Parliament makes no challenge<br />
to the right of newspapers or citizens to<br />
criticise Members of Parliament, closely or even<br />
bitterly. We are in a position to be attacked,<br />
and to accept as well as to use free speech. No<br />
Parliament see'kst. o restrain such freedom.<br />
But the case is different when an<br />
attempt is made to prevent free speech on the part<br />
of a people's representative in Parliament. No<br />
reputable newspaper either demands or expects<br />
the right to silence a Member of Parliament.<br />
speal-ing in his place in the House.<br />
QUESTION: Hbving regard to the great public<br />
interest in this matter, should Parliament address<br />
itself to a review of the machinery for declaring<br />
and enforcing its-jfivileges?<br />
ANSWER: There could be no possible objection<br />
to this course. Indeed, I would welcome it. and<br />
will promote, in co-operation with the Opposition,<br />
the fullest consideration of it during the next<br />
sittings. But it should be-understood that no<br />
future law, ought to be made to operate<br />
retrospectively. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
