<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2030</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO THE U.S. AND CANADA 1969:CANADA - PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR.JOHN GORTON, AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB, OTTAWA</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002030.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO THE U. S.<br />
AND CANADA 1969<br />
CANADAV 4Y96<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. JOHN -GORTON, AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB,<br />
OTTAWA 3 APRIL 1969<br />
PM. It is pleasant to be visiting Canada, and I hope an augury<br />
of the visits backwards and forwards by ministers between our two<br />
countries, both of which are so interested in the Pacific. This is an<br />
area where, I think, we have an opportunity for greater joint action in<br />
the future than we may have had in the past.<br />
I would like publicly to announce that there will be an<br />
Australian parliamentary delegation visiting Canada this year. It will<br />
be lead by one of our ministers and will have six other members, three<br />
of whom will be from the government parties. The details of the<br />
programme haven't been worked out, but the visit will occur during<br />
the Australian winter recess which is round about June, and I think will<br />
be of immense advantage to our own members of parliament. We are<br />
grateful that the opportunity for this visit has been afforded to us, as<br />
I am grateful for. the opportunity for my owna short visit. And that is<br />
all I think I wish to say by way of an opening comment. It's over to you.<br />
Q. Did you discuss the price of wheat with Mr. Pepin and<br />
the Prime Minister, and what were the upshots of these discussions?<br />
PM. Well, we mentioned the subject of wheat, and as you<br />
know, it is suggested that Australia is doing something about freights<br />
which is enabling it to sell wheat at lower than the I. G. A. arrangements.<br />
This, on the other hand, in my view, has not by any means been<br />
demonstrated, although as a result of the claim which, as I say has<br />
not been demonstrated to our satisfaction, both the United States and<br />
Canada have felt it necessary to drop the price at which they are sellibg<br />
wheat. But the upshot of the discussion, I think, can be put this way:<br />
that these things ought to be clearly demonstrated and shown to be<br />
matters of fact, and there's a technical meeting going on in Washington<br />
today and tomorrow or tomorrow and the next day, I'm not sure<br />
which but more important than that is the clear agreement between<br />
all our three countries that it is essential that the International Grains<br />
Agreement should be made to work. We all have an equal interest in<br />
seeing that it works and there will be further discussions on this<br />
matter with our Minister for Trade when Mr. Pepin comes to Australia.<br />
Q. I believe you've had your problems too with foreign<br />
ownership. Do you have any very definite ideas as to what should be<br />
done with it, do you have any policies in the direction of buying back<br />
Australian industry? / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
PM. -NWljiawemusAruhsatvraeli-ai ni f we're to develop<br />
as quickly as we., have-to-develop, if we're to. bring . in the number of'<br />
migrants that we need to bringin1Jif~ we~ re. to -bring in the technological<br />
know-how, if we're to have the capital which we can't generate from<br />
within a population of our own size, then we must have large quantities<br />
of overseas capital, We start from that point. It just must come<br />
either from the United States, the United Kingdom, or other countries.<br />
What we have been saying is that we welcome this, we need it, we must<br />
have it. But we would like countries who come in for developmental<br />
purposes to give an opportunity for Australian equity in their enterprise<br />
at the beginning, if possible, of that enterprise. This has been an<br />
expression of governmental opinion, and I am told that it has had some<br />
effect even though it is not a matter of legislative compulsion. We<br />
believe that responsible companies, and most of the big companies are<br />
responsible, will take notice of expressions of governmental desires<br />
and governmental opinion, and we want to see a participation by<br />
Australians in equity holdings in the development of Australia. It is<br />
very difficult to translate this, in fact I think it would be wrong to try<br />
to translate this, in any codified legal form because there are so many<br />
variations and combinations that it would be self-destructive to try and<br />
do it. But we do express the view that good corporate behaviour, which<br />
is a phrase I think one of your own former ministers developed, does<br />
require that the capital which comes in and is owned from abroad<br />
must or should give Australians a chance at some stage to<br />
participate in the growth of these companies. We don't expect that an<br />
Australian should be given an advantage to come in and buy shares in<br />
the company after it has been proved to be successful, and not take a<br />
risk before. it's been proved to be successful. But we'd just like them<br />
to have a chance to have some participation in growth.<br />
Q. Are you moving at all in the direction of a development<br />
fund similar to ours which would enable the government to plow<br />
Canadian savings into it?<br />
PM. Well, we've got a resources development bank,<br />
Australian Resources Development Bank, which I think has some<br />
relation to the fund you are going to set up you haven't set it up yet,<br />
I think which you are going to set up. But I haven't studied it<br />
sufficiently to know how close those relationships are, but there is an<br />
Australian Resources Development Bank.<br />
Q. I'm sorry, Sir, but I would like to get back to wheat. I'd<br />
like to pin it down. Do you deny outright that Australia had anything to<br />
do with breaking the International Grains Agreement?<br />
Pm. Well, I haven't seen any conclusive figures or facts<br />
produced that indicate that there was anything for me to deny.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, you have a reputation for always<br />
wanting to see what the weather is well ahead. Could you tell us<br />
something of your defence policies after 1971, and whether you will<br />
have to rely much more on your own defence resources and not perhaps<br />
on the Americans, if they so choose to move some of their forces?<br />
Are you on your own? </p>
<p>3-<br />
PM. It depends on what part of the world you are talking<br />
about. I would regard Australia and New Zealand as in fact being<br />
covered by the Anzus agreement we have with the United States. But<br />
if you are talking of the region to our north, where not the United States<br />
but Britain, in fact, took the main heat and burden of the day until<br />
recently, then we have made it clear that we regard ourselves as having<br />
an obligation in that region. A responsibility not only militarily, but<br />
to try to help economic growth, to try to help build the standard of<br />
living, to try to bring the countries in the region into a better<br />
understanding of each other, and to provide some defence forces there<br />
on the spot and visible after 1971. I don't know that I've got enough of<br />
a crystal ball to know whether if something developed after that period<br />
of time we would then be on our own or not. The United Kingdom has<br />
indicated that under certain circumstances it would be coming back to<br />
the region, but these circumstances are not clear. All I can say is that<br />
we feel that at the request of Malaysia and Sirgapore, in particular, and<br />
with the unstinted acquiescence of Indonesia, we do feel we can contribute<br />
towards stability by having some forces stationed in that area, and<br />
therefore a declared military interest. By contributing to stability we<br />
are going to contribute to that kind of economic growth which, in the<br />
long run, is the real basis of security.<br />
Q. Are you going to increase your defence budget?<br />
Pm. I think you'd have to wait until the budget came down,<br />
but if you are talking in terms of money as distinct from talking in<br />
terms of gross national product, I would think it quite likely that this<br />
would have to occur.<br />
Q. You know that Canada trades a lot around the world, but<br />
has almost no merchant navy. You, being an island, must have similar<br />
problems. How do you tackle that field?<br />
PM. Well, we've just recently made when I say recently,<br />
I mean some months ago the announcement that we propose to obtain<br />
ships ourselves, one to take part in the Japanese-Australian conference,<br />
one to take part in the Australian-European conference, and one to take<br />
part in the Australian-West Coast of America conference. These ships<br />
will be Australian manned, and they will, in fact, herald the entry of<br />
Australia into having some ships of its own.<br />
Q. What is the actual situation?<br />
Pm. Well, at the moment we've just decided to buy them.<br />
At the moment we only do coastal shipping.<br />
Q. Mr. Prime Minister, did you have an exchange of views<br />
with Mr. Trudeau on the recognition of Red China?<br />
PM. No, that was not a subject that was discussed at any<br />
length at all.<br />
Q. Do you have plans for opening up Australia for these<br />
people to the north, or do you still have a strong white Australia policy?<br />
e / 4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
PM. Well, we don't use the term you've just used. We call<br />
it ' restrictive immigration policy' and we always have. And, there are<br />
some reasons, I think, for calling it a restrictive immigration policy<br />
because if it were able to be accurately described in the words you've<br />
used, then there would be nothing but white people allowed to immigrate<br />
to Australia and this is not the case. Apart from some ten or twelve<br />
thousand students from Asian countries which we have constantly in<br />
Australia, there are many who become naturalized Australians. Of<br />
course, if someone marries an Australian, they automatically become<br />
naturalized, but l am speaking of people who have been living there for<br />
some time and who apply for naturalization and becone naturalized<br />
Australians. The policy has been liberalized considerably over recent<br />
years. Again speak from memory but I think I'm pretty accurate in<br />
this. I think at one stage people from our north had to live in Australia<br />
for 15 years before they could apply for naturalization. Now it's five,<br />
the same as people from any other country. So, there has been quite a<br />
liberalization and quite an increase in the numbers coming to us. But<br />
we do look for two things. We do look to see that such people integrate<br />
with the Australian community; in other words that they will belong to<br />
the local football club or the local tennis club and have a circle of friends<br />
amongst the community in which they live rather than communities of<br />
their own. This is of pretty great significance, we think. I believe<br />
that at the moment it is true to say there is less racial feeling in<br />
Australia than almost any other country that I know. It just doesn't<br />
occur to people. It just simply doesn't occur to people that there is<br />
a racial question, and I think one of the reasons for this is because<br />
there is a reasonably small minority and an integrated minority.<br />
Q. The Trudeau government is facing a real problem in<br />
Western Canada for various reasons. Western Canadians feel this<br />
government is not adopting an economic policy vis-a-vis the American<br />
market they would like, but more specifically in relation to your case,<br />
western Canadians, particularly British Columbians, feel Canada should<br />
pay far more attention to the Pacific nations, the Pacific Rim as they<br />
call it, from an economic point of view. Could you tell us if you feel<br />
that Canada is doing enough in the Pacific area, in a general sense?<br />
PM. I don't think it's up to me to indicate what I think the<br />
policies of Canada, or the policies of Mr. Trudeau should be, but I<br />
have understood and I think it has been made clear, has it not, that<br />
there has been more emphasis placed by this government on interests<br />
in the Pacific than has been the case in the past. At least so it has<br />
seemed to me. And we welcome that.<br />
Q. For obvious reasons, your country took a f irm stand<br />
in South East Asia. Did you discuss the Vietnam situation and the<br />
Paris talks with our Prime Minister?<br />
PM. What I did was explain the reasons why Australia has<br />
taken the stand it has taken in Vietnam arid why the government<br />
believes it is right for us to be there. </p>
<p>Q. Could you tell us what other matters came into your<br />
discussions with our Prime Minister, and in particular, as a result<br />
of these talks, is there a possibility of Mr. Trudeau making a<br />
reciprocating visit to Australia in the near future?<br />
PM. Well, I hope there is, but the question of a return visit<br />
wasn't raised. I had previously understood that it would be some time<br />
before Mr. Trudeau could make a visit, but he knows and has known<br />
since the London Conference that we would be delighted to welcome<br />
him, more than delighted to welcome him, at any time he could get<br />
away from Canada to come and talk to us.<br />
Q. What about the other matters you discussed?<br />
PM. Well, we had a quick survey of situations in South East<br />
Asia, generally, not confined to Vietnam, but generally. I put forward<br />
some views of my own on behalf of the Australian government on the<br />
importance we attached to the region of Indonesia, Malaysia, and<br />
Singapore, and its economic development and the improvement of the<br />
standard of life of its people. And we had, as you say, some<br />
discussions on wheat, and several other matters relating to how we<br />
could seek to have greater numbers of visits between our two countries.<br />
And we both, I think, agree on this: that talking closer affinity is good<br />
and Mr. Trudeau is doing it and I'm doing it and we want it. But it<br />
is not going to happen on Tuesday week. One of the difficulties of<br />
wanting something and saying this is what should happen is that if<br />
you're not careful, everybody says in a fortnight's time, " VWell,<br />
you've said you'd like this, and it hasn't happened, so what's the<br />
good of it?" It's not like that; it's something that must grow and<br />
grow gradually. I believe the seeds are growing and will grow.<br />
Q. I wanted to go back to the Canadian recognition of Red<br />
China. What are your views of Canada' s attitude on this matter? What<br />
is the position of the Australian government? I gather that you have no<br />
intention of following that course with Peking. Could you tell us what<br />
your personal view of this matter is?<br />
PM. Well, our view is that the Canadian government is a<br />
completely independent government and a government quite capable<br />
of making its own judgments. Such jUdgrn-nts as3 it wishes to make<br />
we will naturally respect.<br />
Q. What about your own position vis-a-vis China?<br />
PM. I think our own position is clear. That we do not intend<br />
to recognize Red China. That has been our announced policy and at<br />
this stage I see no change in it.<br />
Q. In what areas do you anticipate this joint action, as<br />
mentioned in your opening statement? / 6 </p>
<p>-6-<br />
PM. Well it could well be in the economic field, in various<br />
countries in Asia. It could be an interest perhaps of Canada in helping<br />
the economic growth of countries around our part of the world. It could<br />
h~ e visits not only of politicians and of academics but of experts of<br />
various kinds who could try and study various problems not only in<br />
Australia, but again in that area of the world. Not anything startling<br />
or significant for a start.<br />
Q. Foreign aid, health, and so on.<br />
PM. That kind of thing, yes.<br />
Q. Canada's attempt to establish diplomatic relations with<br />
communist China seems to be based on the assumption that recognition<br />
of the Peking regime might lessen tensions in the Far East, in the<br />
Pacific area, and in the world generally. What is your view of this<br />
assumption?<br />
PM. Well, I am not sure that that is the assumption that the<br />
Canadian government has made and I'm certainly not going to be put into<br />
any position of commenting on any Canadian government decisions. I<br />
think we would all of us, eventually, wish to see China brought into the<br />
community of nations, and behaving as a responsible member of the<br />
community of nations. This must be the long-term hope of the world,<br />
but for our own part, looking at it as at present, we don't propose to<br />
change our present policy.<br />
Q. Do you see China as the main threat in your area?<br />
PM. I'm not quite sure what you mean as the main threat in<br />
our particular area. I don't expect to be invaded by China next week<br />
or anything of that kind, but I don't think there is much to be served<br />
by picking out particular places and calling them main threats anyway.<br />
Q. Did you and Mr. Trudeau discuss Mr. Nixon's recent<br />
anti-ballistic missile decision?<br />
PM. No, not at all. This, I think, is a matter which affects<br />
Canada but not us.<br />
Q. In light of your recent discussions with President Nixon<br />
do you feel his policy in Vietnam has changed any from President<br />
Johnson?<br />
PM. I would think it essential that any discussions that were<br />
held between President Nixon and myself, if they were to be meaningful<br />
discussions, were discussions which were held between President Nixon<br />
and myself and remain between President Nixon and myself.<br />
Q. I wanted to ask you if President Nixon or Prime Minister<br />
Trudeau asked you to abide by I. G. A. prices. / 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
PM. The-answer-to that is no. President Nixon did not mention<br />
the-matter of. wheat -at all, and Mr. Trudeau did not ask us to abide by<br />
the 1. G. A. price. The matter rather lies along these lines. That the<br />
United States and Canada have dropped their prices below 1. G. A. prices<br />
and they say that they did this because they felt that although Australia<br />
had not dropped its prices below 1. G. A. prices, there~ was something<br />
funny going on with freight rates. But I gather that they haven't quite<br />
been able to point out exactly what it is that is alleged to be funny that<br />
is going on with freight rates. This, I think, will be the subject of these<br />
technical discussions that are taking place. If, in fact, it can be shown<br />
that in a disguised sort of a way and it hasn't yet been shown that<br />
Australia is dropping below the I. G. A. ( prices), then that would be<br />
serious and we would meet with Canada and the United States in order<br />
to make sure that the 1. G. A. which is so important to all our three<br />
countries, would meet the ends for which it was designed. But none<br />
of that is to indicate that I am in any way accepting that there is anything<br />
funny going on.<br />
Q. Don't you feel it rather odd that the trade minister of<br />
our country says to you openly and publicly that he feels that there is<br />
something going on in the freight rates?<br />
PM. I'm paraphrasing. You're not to say that I put those words<br />
into his mouth I'm paraphrasing the general thing that there is a<br />
question of whether freight rates are accurately worked out according<br />
to the formula which was devised. Now, that's a better way of putting<br />
it, but my own way of putting it means exactly the same thing.<br />
Q. I was going to ask you about China again. Perhaps it<br />
might give you an opportunity to say something you might want to say.<br />
In the light of Canada's position with China, in the light of the statements<br />
by Senator Kennedy about the U. S. moving closer to China, is there any<br />
possibility of Australia doing the sensible thing and reviewing its position?<br />
PM. I believe as I said before that ultimately we all want to<br />
bring China into the community of nations as a responsible member of<br />
the community of nations, and I am sure that any steps that Australia<br />
takes, if and when it takes them, will be sensible steps.<br />
Q. I think it would be very helpful, with regard to communist<br />
China, if you would explain why you do not now recognise the communist<br />
China government.<br />
PM. I think there are a number of reasons. One is that the<br />
communist Chinese government does not, in fact, look with favour upon<br />
being recognised unless its claim to Formosa is also recognised. And<br />
we would have some strong reservations about a community of 12 or<br />
13 million people, a community which is probably giving to its citizens<br />
one of the highest living standards of any country in Asia, being handed<br />
over willy-nilly, to the control of a power to which it didn't wish to<br />
go. That would seem to us to be wrong. That's one reason. / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
Q. I was-wondering while-you were in Washington, did you<br />
see any signs-of---change-in-the America nattitude, a softening?<br />
PM. Well, we didn't discuss that matter at all so I had no<br />
chance to see any signs.<br />
Q. You are going to see our defence minister. Do you know<br />
of any problem on this level?<br />
PM. None whatsoever, but I would be interested in his views<br />
of how the use of joint services by the Canadian Armed Forces i s<br />
progressing, and in telling him of our defence explaining to him our<br />
own defence policy as to our involvement in our region. But there is no<br />
sort of concrete defence proposals between the defence services of our<br />
two countries that I know of.<br />
Q. In your talks in Washington, did President Nixon give<br />
any indication that the United States is contemplating reducing the<br />
level of its forces in Vietnam this year? And, additionally, is Australia<br />
contemplating any reduction in the level of its forces in Vietnam?<br />
PM. I would answer only for Australia, and I am saying under<br />
present circumstances there would be no reduction of Australian forces<br />
in Vietnam this yeari But you're asking me to predicate something on a<br />
whole lot of things that might or mightn't happen.<br />
Q. This involves the domino theory going back to communist<br />
China. Do you fear is there a fear in Australia that if there is<br />
a communist victory in Vietnam that Australia will eventually be on the<br />
Chinese or communist Asian domino board?<br />
PM. I'd like to rephrase that question for you, if I may. I<br />
still think that if aggression and force succeeds in South Vietnam, that<br />
Laos and Cambodia would be in a position where they would be either<br />
completely dominated or perhaps occupied. And I think it quite likely<br />
that countries at present having some difficulty would also be more open<br />
to infiltration and subversion. In other words, 1, like most of the pEople<br />
who live in that area, as distinct from people who live in other areas,<br />
most of the people who live in that area don't dismiss the domino theory<br />
as being sheer nonsense. Neither do I.<br />
Q. Do you think that Australia would eventually be on the<br />
domino board?<br />
PM. I have no fear about Australia as such at all. But I feel<br />
that it could well be as we have seen in our lifetime once before, if one<br />
place after another becomes the focal point of subversion and disruption<br />
and overthrowing. Rightly or wrongly, and this is a matter for each<br />
man's individual judgment and conscience, we felt in Korea and in the<br />
emergency in Malaya and in the confrontation between Indonesia and<br />
Malaya, and in Vietnam that aggression, even small aggression, should<br />
/ 9 </p>
<p>-9-<br />
be prevented from succeeding; or else one would run into the same<br />
danger the world ran into before when aggression in Poland and<br />
aggression in the Sudatenland, when aggression in Austria was allowed<br />
step by step to succeed. We believe that for all nations, and particularly<br />
for small ones, there ought to be a world in which aggression doesn't<br />
take place. That if it does take place, it should be seen to be not<br />
successful. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
