<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1979</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO THE U.K. 1969 - EXTRACTS FROM SPEECH MADE BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, TO THE COMMONWEALTH PRIME MINISTERS&#039; CONFERENCE - 13 JANUARY 1969</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/01/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001979.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO THE U. K. 1969<br />
EXTRACTS FROM SPEECH MADE BY THE PRIME<br />
MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, TO THE<br />
COMMONWEALTH PRIME MINISTERS' CONFERENCE<br />
13 JANUARY 1969<br />
Australia attaches great importance to the work of<br />
UNCTAD and we think it is bringing about a greater awareness of the<br />
problems of developing countries. Although there was, I know, a<br />
widespread feeling of disappointment among the developing countries<br />
that the concrete results from the second UNCTAD conference last year<br />
were not greater, resolutions on tariff preferences, commodity problems,<br />
increased aid and improved aid terms, all pointed in the right direction.<br />
In 1966, Australia introduced a system of tariff preferences<br />
for exports of developing countries, which we have since enlarged. We<br />
believe that this system is the most effective way for us to help developing<br />
countries increase their exports of manufactured and semi-manufactured<br />
goods. Trade is, in the last analysis, more important than aid.<br />
Whilst our hopes for really acceptable conditions of access to markets<br />
for agricultural products in the major industrial countries were not<br />
realised in the Kennedy Round, there were some credits, we now have a<br />
new international grains arrangement and a new international sugar<br />
agreement. Australia has always stressed the need for international<br />
commodity agreements in certain products and the arrangements for<br />
wheat and sugar, together with those that already exist for tin and coffee,<br />
are signposts for the future and show that if producers and consumers<br />
are both willing, we can get results.<br />
We were greatly pleased at the inclusion in the sugar<br />
agreement of the special provisions for developing countries the<br />
" hardship fund" for sugar and the preferential allocation of short falls.<br />
We also supported the Food Aid Convention for wheat. Let me emphasise<br />
here we support in the strongest way the remarks of the distinguished<br />
representative from Jamaica. We would urge those countries which have<br />
not yet done so to take the necessary steps to accept the international<br />
sugar agreement. On the broader front in the international monetary<br />
field I believe we can expect further action to see how the system<br />
might be improved and I hope that the International Monetary Fund<br />
will play a central role in any review. There is, I believe, a continuing<br />
need for a multi-lateral approach to international financial and economic<br />
problems. In the past year or so we have had no less than three crises<br />
in the international monetary field...., the sterling devaluation, the gold<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>crisis and the recent run out of French francs into deutschmarks. But<br />
despite these crises some progress has been made by the two reserve<br />
currency countries towards a balance of payments equilibrium, which,<br />
if it is attained, must help all around this table.<br />
We all know how severe were the measures imposed on<br />
the British people in the last two years and I understand Britain now expects<br />
to move faster towards first, a balance of payments equilibrium and<br />
then, a surplus which is necessary to meet debt obligations. I am sure<br />
we all wish our British colleagues every success in their efforts for they<br />
are as important to Britain as they are important to all d us.<br />
The new Special Drawing Rights scheme will support the<br />
present structure of reserve assets. The scheme, as you know, is<br />
non-discriminatory and open to all members of the fund. We, in<br />
Australia, earnestly hope that other members of the Commonwealth who<br />
have not already joined will do so soon.<br />
I have previously stated that Australia which in one sense<br />
is a developed country, and in another equally valid sense a developing<br />
and underdeveloped country is playing a part in international aid which<br />
is by no means inconsiderable. It will continue to play that part. We<br />
cannot, however, agree to support the proposition to contribute to a<br />
multi-lateral fund within the Commonwealth and under the control of the<br />
Secretariat. We shall continue to provide our aid under existing multilateral<br />
arrangements and bi-laterally for proposals discussed and agreed<br />
between ourselves and the country concerned either within or without<br />
the Commonwealth. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
