<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4559</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT RALLY AT DEAKIN, MELBOURNE, 25 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004559.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRE" SS 25 NOVEMBER 1977<br />
ADDRESS AT RAL~ LY AT DFAXIN, MELBOURNE<br />
On necember 10 the peopl. e of Australia 1will be deciding<br />
on the kind of country Australia is to become in the next<br />
decade. Do you want Australians having the freedomn to<br />
build the kind of life they want? Do you want incentives<br />
to achiev'e and rewards for initiative? Do you want<br />
opportunities -and productive jobs for our young people?<br />
Do you want the poor and disadvantaged to have genuine<br />
assistance which words and increases self respect?<br />
if you want this, then the party for yon is the Liberal Party.<br />
The Government has had to face many tough and sometimes<br />
unpopular aecisions. Our responsibility is above all<br />
to take the decisions we believe are right for Australia,<br />
whether those decisions are popujlar or not.<br />
We have not told people there are easy answers. We have<br />
not'courted-popularity with rhetoric and easy formulas.<br />
we are doing thie job of getting Australia back on her feet.<br />
After the damage of IMr Whitlain's biq spendingi hicgh tax<br />
inco-mvetent government, a government that ehanged. its policy<br />
from week to week as the factions in the Labor Party wrangled<br />
with each other. We have told the Aus)-tralian people the<br />
truth about the way to cet Australia back to prosperity.<br />
We have rej4ected the road of lavish promises, of " crash"<br />
progjrammes, of cheap point scoring. We are doing the job<br />
we were elected to do. We are 5oing to keep doing that job<br />
after December<br />
in the forefront of our minds has been the certain knowledge<br />
that if we are going to restore employment those who genuinel y<br />
want work we have got to gjet the economy on a sound foot ingj.<br />
Thatis our responsiblity to all Australians.<br />
it is our responsibility to everyone seeking a job. it is<br />
our Yesponsiblity to the young people leaving school next<br />
month. it is our responsiblity to all those who have come to<br />
Australia from other count-riez in the faith that Australia<br />
can offer them freedomn and opportunities beyond any other<br />
place in the world.<br />
We are fulfilling that responsibility. We'are keeping that<br />
promise. F~ or two years vie have pursued a steady course.<br />
our policies are succeeding. They are the only policies<br />
that will succeed. </p>
<p>We have halved Labor' inflation to create jobs.<br />
Tnterest rates are cominq dlown -thatwl help uniemployIMernt.<br />
' We h-ave supportedl re p" onsible wage rostraint that i~ s<br />
helping employmnent. We have givcen Autsitralian industry<br />
the protction we promised -that is helpimnq e-mploprient1.<br />
lie have endea Labor's tax rp-bff A-ncomie taxes at last<br />
are coming~ dowin that. will be C1 Rmajof oost to -jobs.<br />
The crushJinq1 tax burden which in%-reascd 125 rntunder<br />
r ' Ti. an is being : eiedat last.<br />
1, et iie talk for a mo,, ment about taxation bccause it has becomre<br />
%-he nmA: Jox jciss_ of -this electAion campaigi. Tedfrne<br />
between the two parities or, taxatl-ion reveal the fundamental,<br />
contrast betveen the philosophies of the cgovemcnt and<br />
Mix Whiltla-m's Lalbor riarty. Wie have talken the view) that<br />
a reduction in the personal ta, birder, is essential to<br />
eorioomic recovery and to boosting j'ob onprtunities.<br />
Taxes which are too high encovirage people to scek hiqher wages,<br />
tL-o cpestredticing ti-he tax bUrden helps tco tcVke the steam<br />
ou~ t of the wage push; it redu! ces the upward pr-essu-re on<br />
prices it helps . to control1 inflataon. At the _ farne timc by<br />
Ptitting moniey directly into the hands of constuners<br />
createS jobs b-ecause as demanid cmeseployers are encourcaqed<br />
to hire moye people. chcigmorginal tax -&amp;-atcs increases<br />
incentive ane, procluct1. ion. We also believe that excessive<br />
I-axes erode people' z. free&amp; oni to neet 1their own needs in the<br />
that suJits them best. In the last two year;,&gt; our<br />
tax changes have savedc Nostralian -taxpayers $ 3,300 ilIlion.<br />
In February Auisralians will become thc beneficiLaries of a major<br />
tax cduction, N ew tax scales and ino many case-9 creatly<br />
:( ecduced niarginal ratcs almost a quarter mi1. on low income<br />
now paying it-x will pay not tax at all -in line with<br />
the government' general policy of heaping4 thone most in need.<br />
The Governmentl. s deterniination to red~ uce the burenr:, of personal,<br />
taxation does not end there. Evxeryone knows of families who<br />
hatve been hax-xassed and put through great distrosE; by death<br />
duties. JTsinesses have ' been broken u) p, w. idows have had to<br />
strtiqqle along wiJthJ~ less, fani~ ilies have had no choice<br />
but to sink themselves der-p into debt. Under this government<br />
this distress and worry for the bereaved will cease.<br />
As -frolf Nyoniday all estates passinmy betvieeni man and Wife,<br />
parent. and child, will totally free of Feederal estate<br />
and gift duty. Ovcer the life of the next P: arliament all<br />
erstate anl ( lift duty will be entirely abolished. Mr Whi tlam<br />
attacked thi s de-cision by claimiiing that it would not<br />
benefit nny people. H~ e said " estate duty is p_-aid) on a<br />
person's estate if it is w; orth more th-an $ 90,000". Hie was<br />
clearly implying that no duty is payable for an estate<br />
of any lesser valuie. This claim is utlterly false. The triiniimm<br />
for many estates is only $ 20,000, For othex-si the mlaii~ m<br />
is $ 40,000. * 4r VNIhitlam's claimn tha~ t only the wealthy bencfit<br />
from suc-h a change is compleLely wr'ong. </p>
<p>Eyvaeyr bou 1300 0Cstates have to pny estatQ duty<br />
mrany havirvg soveral benoficia~ c Tht; msthat wtany<br />
thousands of people are affected each yi. ar by estate duty<br />
itany of them entirely dependent on the deiceasvd's estate<br />
for Suppoxt. It's clear that Rr 1hitlam wants to tax<br />
AusticaliLans to death and keep on tax~ ing them after they are<br />
dead In his incredible poli
tha.: t he would0 retCurn to the policios which had so damraged<br />
A-ustralia when Jhe was in office highor not lower personal<br />
trixes; full wage indexation ; hugh " cash" spending<br />
p xo gra i fe s; and poorly thought-out schemes.<br />
Six of his programmes alone cost $ 3000 million he hasn't told<br />
how. orc N-The; xe he would. get the money for this.<br />
Put it's clear he'd either tax it or print it. Ta it or<br />
pxint it whic. h is it to be? On Sundcay 12rilhitlam<br />
riaid that tax&gt; indexation wyould hbe positponed for a while.<br />
on Tuesday Yir W'illis said that Lab: or would bring in -full<br />
tax indexation from next Ouly anz3 Mx Whitlam let it beknown<br />
that he agreed. On Wednesday, Mz Hayden sai3 the economy<br />
Could not cope with fultl tax~ indexatlion, and Mr Hurfoxd<br />
saiLd in Cairns that he had not read the papers yet so he<br />
cou~ d ot sy what Labor's policy w~ as.<br />
in the midst of all this confusion and contradiction<br />
MNx-Whitlata announced that Mr Hurford would today mnake the<br />
elerintive Fstatem~ ent on what Labor's' policy was, a press<br />
conjference _-was scheduled for noon. Wll, it is long past<br />
noon and there has still been no pres s conference.<br />
Poor Fir Hurford left in the lujrch aclain. Acdmist the<br />
confusion of Labor's p-overty ofeconomic -spokesmen, one fact<br />
stands out starkl1y to abolish payroll tax.<br />
Laborc would have to pay the States $ 8,10 mnillioni in the r s<br />
half of 1978. In thbe financial year 1978-79 they would hiave<br />
to Jfind $ 1900 -million. Labor has said that they would<br />
-Finance this by raising the Australian people's taxes.<br />
That's a total of $ 2,750 million which they 1-ou-ld rip off<br />
the people of Auistralia. To finance this they have said<br />
that thley would repeal the law reformingj the tax scales<br />
which this cjovernmvnt brought in. This would raise about<br />
() milion this year and. $ 1470 million next year.<br />
Buit this would-still fall far short of the total ainount<br />
they need to finance the abolition of payroll tax. a short<br />
fall of some $ 880 million, no less. This is why they<br />
will not cominit themselves to tax indexation. It is crystal<br />
clear that they do niot intend to maintain it.<br />
Mtr lWhitla-m will have to take at least $ 6 a week from the mnan on<br />
average earnings, Mir Whitlam would remove the incentive<br />
vie have qilven people to work overtime. He wouldI increase tax<br />
rates f-rom-, i 32 percent to 45 percent. He would rip this nioney<br />
out of the hands of the Australian people and give<br />
it to big and profitable cormpanies. 3ust to take a few<br />
examples. Utah would get a windfall of $ 2 million. </p>
<p>$__ MILLION<br />
C RAl11<br />
1-0i i3MK S<br />
C 2-the f act of -the 7-attrer is thait tishin,--ay_-oil tax<br />
~~ co'tu i n eas clcyjnent. IrDmtr ; cs t1hat, and<br />
co3n10et dd tet<br />
The Goencthasared xi$ apw; ltx<br />
relrli~ sion scheme: fcund thu~ t 4 t does not ce-ate ep. oyrneni..<br />
recn ou v e y o f ig e ernf L C; y Tc, ealed a&gt; t n t one<br />
Ccriwk surveyed -waiz preparel " Co foxecast an", oras in<br />
t. jheir own plyre~ levels, ifE Ynayroll tcax ~-eabolished.<br />
Tile 8Qrvey Showed tha, n the contrtary, eal~ cr<br />
consid-ee! Mr 1-hitan andt Mr Nawe's policy ' Lufcll wage<br />
1~ 1~ ut~ o tec c i ty o: bu si n es toc create new<br />
iosworse_ not Ina. t' 3r. habo r ' s so he me w4c'u I: rt the<br />
. J~ emlovdanrt : manfy slmall siewenhcar-e already<br />
~ mtfrom pa-ycl i tax, btwould be lumberedc with higher<br />
wqe costs and i~ personal tax comolitments.<br />
Ro? Kr Cripp has gcot into the act. Lfie a parrot he has come<br />
olut wiAth exactly t'j. i cam e d iSa s-L,. r ou s e c orno i c PoCT)-'; . A<br />
1, abor Party. LiAc Labor, hie wanu,-to spend i-nf liaionary<br />
8,0 m-iillion. tlj Ei Luab: or, he wantgs to end p4--011 tax for<br />
Comnpanies. L k e L. alao r h e oan t s ay, o r h e w't s-: y<br />
wh ax-e w e Iposz-inarice al' -nse schemc-s.<br />
On one economic is-sule M~ Chbipp has maae aizn Ea<br />
of out-bidding Mr k htar ny et 1oi lmin rcrease<br />
txon overtime. Z Chipp vants to end any c-7rtimae being<br />
padat all, by er~ diric lealty rates. That on the<br />
r-o on s tti ff. The nis. oudnever accopt that. The Axrbitration i<br />
wom~ 2. nvou! 6 newver -, gree to it. T hje Li b -raI Paty<br />
will have nothIng t do wi-thn thr-destructive _ con: omic poli. cl-Zos<br />
Of either party.<br />
Ltsloolk at the ne-,, t planlk Laber ' s cncicpolicy.<br />
tnhis policy sp~ ae Mr Whitiam comnittedl LaQrto resor<br />
integrity to the ge indlematCion udie.-<br />
it has t-aken a bare eight days for this item of Mr Whit-Lam<br />
Policy speech to crash in ruins. M~ r Whitlan's careful<br />
formulas have come unstuzck they canf now be seen for what<br />
they w--ere -devices to conce al decisions M! X1 laf was not<br />
pepared to place -erethe PAustTaliar peopzeR.<br />
I-ecislorns ho knew would be iris-tantly rejectad if -they ever </p>
<p>became knowrn. HeI said Labo-' Iwold restor: e inltegrity<br />
to-he wage ineat-in qieLre.<br />
lie meaint -Labor has reachedl an aqrec-mertt with the trade<br />
union movemen't which, after all, pays the Labor -Party' a<br />
bill,. s that they woulet bac'K the trade iinions clais for naxinur<br />
wasincreases regardless of t41 onejuroe o<br />
cenploywcent and f1o.-r INustralia's chances of economiic recovery.<br />
ror tile last eight days, Au stralia has witnessed incredible<br />
pre\' aracation F49 La + bor has trieed to keep this ayreemrent<br />
concen" Ied. Mr WhitU!' s0 policy speech was only hsolrs old when<br />
Mr flayden said that 11, r Whitlam's formu" La i-neant suipport for full<br />
wage indexation but only for people on less -than average<br />
iqeeklIy cearnings. y Sundiay Mx Witlwm waos saying that Labor<br />
wantcod full wage iriiexation forc everyone. Mr H-ay'den confessed<br />
he miaght wrong. " I fee: l I'mxr on sh~ aky ground", he saidl.<br />
iie said questions o-n -wager indexationi sh~ ould be directedl to<br />
Ir vWillis: " T work the economic area" " it's a demarcation.<br />
pxoblem." So rmuch for iMr )-ayden afs an economric: ianager.<br />
if he baliceg wages policy is outsido the econic area,<br />
he certainly on shak; y grouind. Mr Whitlam with his usual<br />
deylrc e of frnk 3a irccted his pxess secretary to say;<br />
" Tm here wa s n o ota i ct on " between himnsel I ard Kr Hayden<br />
on wac . flexatlon. The pxess secretary said: " We are<br />
coiruitted to full wage inde&gt; xatin, but no one has over arked<br />
abouit the level at which full dndexatiori would6 apply."<br />
1, ow today, M~ r 13awke has come straight oiit an-d said, with brutal<br />
frainkness, that he is not pre-pared to wear M-r Hayden's<br />
position on wageincde&gt; atioj. Mr Hawkze has made Crystal<br />
clear that under himn the trade union im'ovement stands for the<br />
biggest wage grab it can get regardless of how many people arc<br />
thrown ouit o~ f jobs as a resuolt.<br />
The Labor Party is once again demonstrating wlhat Australians<br />
learnt to grea-t cost in 19-73-75: the Labor Party<br />
does not unlers tand the economy, has no: economic policy,<br />
and under its present ontiuton is incapa-ble of foi-malating<br />
an economic policy. The Governm-ent has a clear consistent<br />
policy decided by Cabinet. There is one policy, the policy is<br />
clear. Unlike the Labor Party the government has pi-rsued positive<br />
and constructive policies which actually work. 120,000 people<br />
mostly ycunq people, have been helped by our training schemes<br />
the CP47rAFC' Stchenie for apprentices, the NEAT scheme, the<br />
education rprocgrame for unemploye6 youth to namne some<br />
of these schemes, eaCh of which is designed to do a particular<br />
job, and is goinig it. We are spending more-than $ 10+ 0 million<br />
on train ing and j ob assistance schemes which especially<br />
help young people -learn new skills. </p>
<p>One of the m. Tost. im:? Dctzntaihceare -the qovernment has<br />
an outstanainq rcco-rd of a,-Jc-vemer~ t -is in relation to<br />
t~ e ;:" qil1atloni. It his 45 inute pol10c peeoh<br />
Mxr Ti tI I d id 1" ot hIV e o1nICcCo nt: rt Ic-1. ive vord to propo Ge<br />
about-, thu trade Imiolls Mr Hweand thie . Ift-WATin<br />
u) nion laeswouldntt allow iL-. The lf'iguin<br />
pay mconey to the Labk-or Party, They hav" e a large voice<br />
tIe-j nn ofticial ALP icy That'I w! hy -it i F<br />
Labor's official -Poli4cy to put unions iabove thC: law.<br />
Th at' s -wy I; bor end orsed t he V ic torian power st rhC<br />
TAhe y enrd6or-s e d a~ st rik e wh ic h TidJ ofA'f 6450D, 000 p e ) plIe fo r<br />
wes; they end orcsed a str~ tke wh ich threw 3 -0 0Q peopl e<br />
cnpceyouit otf a job. faboc.-e' policy ol lettintq the<br />
-onacio ns have their Iheail xe-su. ItcI-. in a reooxd period<br />
oi strPnes and dnduiatriat. lwasncss w; b-rn Jhey' we.-e in<br />
Cf) fiC e. WT have s-how'n that a gove rrCmerlt prepared t1-o<br />
take a flirtni and faiir stand cani protect. the. to putblic.<br />
v; e have ihown this in the aic control. Ser stie nth~ e<br />
posalworkers dispute, in the case of th CTsu~ anixrn<br />
moratorunv they backeld do-wn. AIin -thb Victorcianl pxwer<br />
diSPut'-e, it was our n-ove t~ o tt he iutenri , oen iirm olved<br />
+ hat led to the s;-kr tur;-nInC to % work.<br />
Of courze, bir 1~ weclaimcs the-% credift or bceirg the Cireat<br />
ne:. ace miakex-An that elspute. yohn~ have seen Lcabor' z<br />
~ wner i n which he is in a motel room u rel pac)'; anc<br />
his Y; aqs to-, go out-and resolve another of his dispute-,<br />
well An the, case oY the V~ ictoxicin di; r pvOte, it took<br />
Mr J-. Awke 9 ek to Pack hi s bags ( let ( O* tL of his lotel<br />
room and take a hanid.<br />
unliTkC the Labox-Party we hcave ta-ken the viewi-, that no one<br />
can be abc: te law, that individual unionistps havc: ia<br />
rigjht to haheaxrd, and to ) o pCL tct from Intimidation,<br />
thsat, it is the responsibility of: the qove* crim: nt--to prot-ect<br />
the intILerests ol-th-e whole com-lanity.-<br />
We have ree laws pro-tecting~ individual utiionistG and gie<br />
resonsblerank anid file unionists the chance -to makv, t'heir<br />
voiccs hCe4) d secxret posta:: l ball ots for union elec-tions are<br />
now compu'&amp; 1sory, therc is a four yea.-, celling on the ter of<br />
office of union. officials,. We hav,, e set up~ the Thdjwstriaj<br />
Pelatiorns Bureau, to 1* protectq-the p-ublic Jlntecrcot and<br />
alJ'o to zAct ; is an inutilombud!, zmrn, Unions are o<br />
revtire3 to tell their members ho) w union dues are spenvt,. IL, ie<br />
aye pxotsectirig indivi6duals. against: being forcedl to jioin<br />
unions against tI-he-ir -will. Diarnaq Tnq Secondary boycott,-, have<br />
b--en bried. Al~ l this add,-uip tou -fIrrA and regponsible<br />
policy which has the support oif all aepni~ unoitrnd<br />
which protectsa the rciqhts of the individual uniionst andI the<br />
pub'Lic. </p>
<p>L3, de5 an1d q e It 1c,' we0 Want Australia to beable to<br />
Waac-r(,-a1 co" iLbut-ion in th---1etsr! of the worlc6; if wc<br />
va nt Austr: Dlia ' kto be -ce-2pectt-d in t~ he cc ils of the AwOrld;<br />
if we want A ustraa -to wzoving in top qe3r we have<br />
to i-ake a stand-u-aj-5 a people ( inS, take . it noc1w.<br />
c yeac of tile gay KO OMnMaoTSy<br />
11ave been laid, ." OT et o vel. xcveyopyventst are<br />
i-ovinc in every par-. o{ ul: aia oniec<br />
Ai3 bIA4Cdno lip. If we can keelC, to the present Course<br />
O'ur futur-' e is lzn-1imt 0 r. The inrqedIient Aiistra2.! ia now ne, j<br />
certainty-v-cer-tainty that the rrespLcmsible policies<br />
ofr ithc ' Last two y~~ swill be contiie iorc the next<br />
th~-e years. Certainty tha't ab z~ rs~ a clovermm-~ ent which<br />
cudws hat it 4; 3 dciinq and has a policy that "'; Orhs.<br />
Mr 14hita'~ s axroach of government by wr; anTgle has becn. tricd<br />
an6 it doe~ n't woxh. Australia neeeds rcsponsiblc waqje restraint.<br />
n-Pees cons1-ructive policies for tradc urions.<br />
Austral Jka needs responsible spending I70rarcunes, not lav ish<br />
ill conceived " crasht' pyoyr-ates. liustrcalia needs lower<br />
not higher tax,-es.<br />
Thi s i the ay to get unemploynmEnnt ( lown-an u keep i4t down. j<br />
S qfet o ihte-job. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
