<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9020</transcript-id>
    <title>TASK FORCE ON URBAN DESIGN</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009020.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
9, PRIME MINISTER<br />
TASK FORCE ON URBAN DESIGN<br />
During a speech in Sydney this morning I announced that I have appointed a Task<br />
Force on Urban Design to report to the Deputy Prime Minister and myself on ways in<br />
which the day-to-day working, residential and recreational environment of Australians<br />
might be enhanced by more thoughtful attention to urban design.<br />
The Task Force has been asked to report by early next year under the terms of the<br />
following charter:<br />
" The Task Force should review the quality of urban design in Australia and make<br />
recommendations to the Prime Minister and Deputy Prime Minister for improvement.<br />
It should particularly focus on ways in which the day-to-day working, residential and<br />
recreational environment of most Australians might be enhanced by more thoughtful<br />
attention to urban design.<br />
Urban ( or ' community') design should be understood to apply to all scales and types of<br />
urban activities and to be concerned about the physical arrangement and functioning of<br />
urban activities, the physical appearance of the built environment and its relationship to<br />
the natural environment, the way in which people experience it and the social and<br />
economic factors which influence its quality.<br />
The Task Force should examine all influences on the way in which urban growth and<br />
change takes place, including informal but conventional practices and formal planning<br />
controls. It should consider the impact of current trends in urban development and<br />
whether current practices are adequate to create pleasing results.<br />
The Task Force should determine how improved design may enhance the quality of the<br />
built environment and provide examples of the way in which this might occur. In<br />
'-making eommendations forimprvements, thereport may wish to increase examples<br />
in Australia or in other countries of more successful urban design than is commonly<br />
encountered in Australia.<br />
In making its recommendations the Task Force should bear in mind their feasibility,<br />
equity, practicality and cost. It should also take into account current complementary<br />
work on urban planning issues, including the Better Cities Program and the National<br />
Urban Development Program." </p>
<p>The members of the Task Force are:<br />
Mr John Mant ( Convenor)<br />
Solicitor Planner<br />
Phillips Fox<br />
SYDNEY Professor David Yencken<br />
Professor Landscape Architecture<br />
Melbourne University<br />
MELBOURNE Professor Evan Walker<br />
Dean of School of Architecture<br />
Melbourne University<br />
MELBOURNE Mr Alex Tzannes<br />
Architect SYDNEY<br />
Mr Michael Llewellyn-Smith<br />
General Manager<br />
Adelaide City Council<br />
ADELAIDE Ms Wendy Morris<br />
Architect Urban Designer<br />
Department of Planning Urban Growth<br />
MELBOURNE Professor Peter Droege<br />
Professor of Urban Design<br />
Sydney University<br />
SYDNEY Mr Espie Dods<br />
Architect SYDNEY Mr Neville Gruzman<br />
Architect Councillor<br />
SYDNEY Mr Geoff Campbell<br />
Planner Deputy Prime Minister's Ofce<br />
CANBERRA </p>
<p>1.3<br />
Dr Catherine Bull<br />
Landcape Designer<br />
Queensland University of Technology<br />
QUEENSLAND Mr Michael Dickinson<br />
Journalist Belle Magazine<br />
SYDNEY Mr John Mant can be contacted on 02 296 8127.<br />
3 November, 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
