<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3108</transcript-id>
    <title>HUMAN RIGHTS DAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003108.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
A ArAF<br />
b-O E G<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 1 8 December 1972<br />
HUMAN RIGHTS DAY<br />
The Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mr E. G.<br />
WVhitlam, today issued the following statement on the occasion of Human<br />
Rights Day. " Human Rights Day on 10th December 1972 marks the twenty-fourth<br />
S anniversary of the adoption of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights<br />
on 10th December, 194* 8. 1 recall with a sense of pride that it was an<br />
eminent Australian, the late Dr Herbert Evatt, who was President of the<br />
General Assembly at the time that the Declaration was adopted.<br />
Since the adoption of the Universal Declaration, the United<br />
Nations has been active in drawing up new international conventions<br />
and declarations aimed at the protection of human rights. Altogether<br />
they spell out in considerable detail the various rights and freedoms<br />
0 set out in the Declaration. Of the Conventions, perhaps the most<br />
important are the International Convention on the Elimination of All<br />
Forms of Racial Discrimination, vwhich was adopted by the United Nations<br />
General Assembly in 1965, and the International Covenants on Human Rights<br />
which were adopted by the United Nations General Assembly a year later.<br />
My Government attaches great importance to Australia becoming<br />
a party to these international instruments. Racism and racial discrimination<br />
are reprehensible and we shall take all necessary steps to prohibit<br />
discrimination on grounds of race. Indeed, I have already set in train </p>
<p>action to expedite Australia's ratification of the Racial' Discrimination<br />
Convention and relevant I. L. O. Conventions.<br />
The two International Covenants oh Human Rights cover important<br />
economic, social and cultural rights as well as civil and political<br />
rights. It is our intention that Australia should shortly sign the two<br />
Covenants, as a first step towards ratification."<br />
Mr Whitlam drew particular attention to the preamble of the<br />
Universal Declaration which called on peoples all over the world to<br />
renew their determination " to reaffirm faith in fundamental human rights,<br />
in the dignity and worth of the human person, in the equal rights of g<br />
men and women and to promote racial progress and better standards of<br />
life in larger freedom". 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
