<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6510</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH BOB MAUMILL, RADIO 6PR, </title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006510.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>'. 4 PRIME MINISTERR<br />TRANSCRIPT INTERVIEW WITH BOB MAUMILL, RADIO 6PR<br />19 OCTOBER 1984<br />O. E. PROOF ONLY</p>
<p><br />MAUM ILL: How has it been since last I spoke to you, oh,' it must be nineteen months ago?</p>
<p><br />PM: It's been the most interesting and rewarding period of my life, I guess, Bob. We've had the opportunity of loading the Government to<br />deliver the promise we'made to Australia that we'd turn it round<br />from the recession and thedivisiveness and the confrontation, of<br />early 1983 to the country which now has the highest rate of<br />economic growth in the world a happier, more united country,<br />more hope for our young people. And it's been a matter of pleasure<br />and pride to be associated with that.</p>
<p><br />HAUMILL: Any personal disappointments in the job?</p>
<p><br />PM: W ell nothing that you wouldn't have expected, just in the sense that it's a terribly lonely and isolated job in many respects. Very long hours I don't complain about that but it means that your capacity to maintain the personal friendships and links; that you had before has diminished. You simply haven't got the time or  the opportunity. And that's a drawback.</p>
<p><br />MAUMILL: It's been said by friends of mine from the BBC who have been in Australia looking at our country and our style of politics that<br />one of your most brilliant performers and they use the word<br />sincerity is your wife, Hazel. Now I've met Hazel on a number<br />of occasions. I've interviewed Ffer on this programne. We had a<br />rap one time behind the scenes when you and I both performed before<br />a live audience in Hyde Park over here. And my friends from the BBC<br />said they were struck by the simplicity of Hazel Hawke's approach<br />to political life and her sincerity.</p>
<p><br />PM: Mm. She's a remarkable-woman. I knew, Bob, what her qualities<br />were, but I don't think even I realised how magnificent she would<br />be in the job because up until I became Prime Minister she had<br />consciously and for good reasons remained in the background with<br />the family hadn't been into public projection. When I became<br />Prime Minister she accepted that as my wife she inevitably had<br />duties and obligations to play a different role from the one she<br />had in the past. And none of us had seen her in this more<br />continuously projected position, but she has been nothing short of<br />superb.</p>
<p>MAUM ILL: Sincerity and strength?</p>
<p><br />PM: Yes. All of that. And an articulatness she's got everything.</p>
<p><br />MAUMILL: Do you feel that you can always rely-on her, that she's not going to go out in public and make a gaffe? What I'm really asking is has Hazel got political nous? </p>
<p><br />PM: Yes. She's got nous in the sense that she doesn't play politics. mean ifa person espouses cause it may just as well apply<br />these days to a man whose wife is in public life but if the<br />spouse hasn't himself or herself been naturally and continuously<br />in politics and they then come to that role and are trying to<br />play it, they'll make mistakes. There'll be gaffes. But she's<br />not in that... . oh she Just calls it as sees it. And therefore,<br />there are not going to be those gaffes I think.</p>
<p><br />MAUMILL: Prime Minister will you carry any scars out of recent political battles, and</p>
<p><br />PM: I will out of recent cricket battles! ( Laughter) Bob..</p>
<p>PM: ( Laughter) The best shiner I've ever seen!</p>
<p>PM: You ain't seen the best of it! You know it's really diminishing a bit now!</p>
<p><br />MAUMILL: What about the scars because of accusations that have been made on the floor of Parliament?</p>
<p><br />PM: Oh I think the scars are being worn by those who made the<br />accusations. It was very as well as being low, gutter politics<br />on the part of those who did it the Leader of the Oppositio'n and<br />others it was also stupid. Because I've been aL publicly ex; posed<br />figure for so long peopl~ e know my nature and to be making those<br />allegations that I'm a crook and I associate with crooks and I'm<br />directed by those who direct crooks were so manifestly absurd.<br />64r-11' 1Lj84" L_ MEIJI" LA" I Ur4 P. ZS</p>
<p>a'a. lS-JVe1 L-IM ISON tRtI r-T( 9) S5e6P. 4<br />PM.. 4 IPERTH<br />Then they were given the opportunity. That fornight ago, the<br />Tuesday, in the Parliament, three weeks now. They were given the<br />opportunity. And I think there is nothing that the Australian<br />people really despise more than those who make recklessly, willful,<br />false allegations given the chance to stand up and, they don't.<br />People despise that. So the scars are not with me, but with<br />others. MAUMILL: The last time we spoke on this programme was the day that<br />Australia won the America's Cup -a joyous time for all of us.<br />PM: Yeah. MAUM ILL:<br />At that time I said that I felt that your parliamentary performances<br />indicated that you were trying to find your feet, that you had<br />a tendency at times to labour the point in an effort to make it.<br />Not so now. Economy of wordage seems to have come into your<br />parliamentary performances and you go straight for the jugular.<br />PM: Well. ) AAUMILL:.<br />You learned a bit about the game.<br />PM: Well I hope I'm an intelligent person, Bob, and I think I am and<br />if you don't learn at anything you do then it's very silly. And<br />I am a better parliamentary performer now than the brief time ago<br />when I went into the place. I hope that everything that I do now<br />I do better through time, except playing the hook shot. I used<br />to be able to play that very much better...<br />MAUMILL: ( Laughter) As the black eye will testifyi</p>
<p>PM. 5 PERTH<br />MAUMILL: Prime Minister we also discussed last time you were here the<br />Hawke luck. There's a lot of it and a lot of it is good luck.<br />You said we won the America's Cup, the drought's broken, Auatralia<br />is on the threshold ofan era of prosperity because of the breaking<br />of the drought % we'd suddenly been projected into the international<br />eye particularly in the business community the OECD figures<br />were all great and their view of-us was excellent. Can we keep<br />i t up?<br />PM: Yes I believe we-can. You're quite right in pointing out, as I<br />have myself, that we've had our share of good fortune. The<br />breaking of the drought certainly was good, not only for the.<br />rural community, but for the country as a whole. But let me put<br />it this way, Paul Keating, my brilliant Treasuer hasn't recently<br />been awarded the prize as the world's number one finance minister<br />because the drought broke. Ile has been awarded that in recognition<br />of his and the Government's spectacular efforts in turning this<br />economy around from the point where we'd had the worst recession<br />since the Great Depression, the place was economically stagnant.<br />We've turned that round, where in the last twelve months we've<br />had the highest rate of economic growth in the world. And that's<br />happened because we've made the right decisions, but in turn.<br />that goes back to the people themselves. What I promised<br />Australia in February and March of ' 83 when we were campaigning<br />was that I wanted to bring Australia together. And I said if<br />we come together, work together, then there is nothing we cannot<br />do. Now the people have responded to that and the results have<br />been spectacular.<br />MAUM ILL:<br />The accord. It was aL central plank . in everything that Hawke.<br />wanted to do that was to get business and unions together. It's<br />derided by some people, namely John Stone, yet, overseas it's been<br />accepted by people over there who have trouble getting the unions<br />and the business community together as a sort of a utopian ideal 6<br />r-4 ril I U 04 1 H I SON SEEkv. LL; k=. p i</p>
<p>PM. .6 PERTH<br />that they should all strive for. That an accord where unions<br />and business get together and sort out their problems rather, than<br />having lengthy strikes and, if you like, confrontation. Would you<br />say it can continue?<br />PM: Yes it will. It will continue for a number of reasons, not least<br />of which is the self-interest ofrtbe peoples involved. I mean<br />I never underrate in life the motive of self-interest. Everyone<br />has it. Now as far as the trade unions are concerned, they want<br />to have a position where ordinary working men and women that they<br />represent are going to he able to maintain their standards of<br />living and through time gradually improve them. And the business<br />community, equally legitimately, wants an environment in which they<br />arc going to be able to increase their profitability, their capacity<br />for more investment, their capacity to create more jobs. Now the<br />accord which exists in the formal sense between the trade unions<br />and Government, but which in reality has been exctended to the<br />business community, the business community and the trade unions<br />understand the truth of what I've been putting for so long. And<br />that is that in working together and co-operating they're each<br />much more likely to achieve those objectives if they work together<br />rather than fight one another. So there's a self-interest for the<br />trade unions. There's a self-interest for the business community<br />and there's an intereist for the Government on behalf of the people<br />in working together rather than against one another. And we've<br />produced those spectacular results. We've created more than a<br />quarter of a million new jobs since the summit. Prior to that a<br />quarter of a million rise in unemployment in the last twelve<br />months. We've halved inflation from 11.2 per cent down to<br />significantly less than half of that. We've reduced interent<br />rates and as far as the ' business community is concerned prol'itability<br />has returned to the levels of more than a decade ago. Real unit<br />labour costs have been reduced to the levels of the 1960s and the<br />trade union movement has been able to maintain the real standards<br />or its members. So,. everyone is'better off. And while everyone / 7<br />A r1rAJ. L 04 L_ I I : A_-1; cV I p P-rH ia%_ 0 p. IS</p>
<p>b'frlI. LUsNf-IL MEIJIM LI~ iISON SERUXC~~ PTHCI~ 9) 3~~ 79e6 ~ 7 PER~ TH<br />sees that the results are better with industrial disputation the<br />lowest for 16 years then, for all these reasons, people are<br />going to say it's more sensible to live and work this way.<br />MAUMILL: People are also saying; will the Hawke Government impose a<br />capital gains tax if they're re-elected?<br />PM: Well let me say that Mr Peacock is doing his very best as he sort<br />of nips around the edges without talking about matters of substance<br />to try and instill some fear on this subject. Now the facts are<br />quite clear and I'm glad, Bob, that you've giv me the<br />opportunity of going to it we have said that the whole area of<br />tax is one in which we ought to have the processes of public<br />consultation in the same way as we've conducted economic policy<br />since we came into office. The reason why the economy is going so<br />well is because we talk with the various groups in the community<br />and try and get a degree of concensus. That's what we'll do in<br />tax. And what I've said is that if you're going to have a total<br />review of the tax system then capital gains would be one issue,<br />obviously, that would be involved in that debate. But what<br />Mr Peacock won't face up to is the fact that the. Liberal Party<br />says that in any total review of the tax system from their point<br />of view a capital gains tax would be inevitable. Could I Just read<br />to your listeners, Bob, what was in The Australian newspaper of<br />the 20th of August. And it refers to the " federal Liberal Party<br />was told yesterday by its economy committee that it Must immediately<br />release a new and imaginative taxation package" and goes on, " the<br />committee said the long-term Liberal taxation strategy should be<br />based on a total overhaul of the taxation system". And it then<br />said, " it would be inevitable, the committee said, that a Liberal<br />Government would have to look at a capital gains tax in some form<br />as part of that long-term strategy". Now that's what they sEay.<br />It's no good Mr Peacock getting up on Monday and announcing his<br />tax policy and saying, " no, no, no, never a capital gains tax" ./ 8</p>
<p>t1&amp; EIt-, r -4 -rr 4I vatJN ? 2Z 5 579 4 Cdb<br />PM.. 8 PERTH<br />because if there's one thing the people of Australia know about<br />the Liberals and tax is you can't believe what they say. People<br />haven't got short memories. They remember 1977 in the election<br />campaign you remember it Bob the " fist full of dollars".<br />This was Liberal Party policy, here's our policy, there's your<br />fist full of dollars. People fell for that and elected the Libs.<br />As soon as they were back in Canberra they took the dollars and<br />within a short time imposed a super tax on them. So he can<br />say what he likes on Monday at his tax launch, but they have in<br />fact disclosed their hand. With the Liberals a capital gains tax<br />is inevitable. It's not with us. But what is the case is that<br />we will honestly talk with the community about it and the whole<br />system of tax. We want a fair tax system.<br />MAUMILL: I<br />So you're not ruling out the possibility that there'll be a<br />capital gains tax, but you're saying there'll be no capital<br />gains tax without community input to see how the if you like<br />the blow can be softend the most?<br />PM: Well see.,. and it's to be understood in that context of a<br />V community discussion. It's not simply to be loo'ked at as a blow<br />because the argument that's basically put by those who advocate a<br />capital gains tax isnot that it's a general, revenue-raising tax<br />which affects the great mass of people. It wouldn't. If it<br />were imposed it wouldn't affect the great mass of people becakuse,<br />clearly, it would not at least as far a Labor were concerned, if<br />it did it it wouldn't affect the family home. With the Liberals<br />it might. They may well say well we'll cover the family home.<br />MAUMILL: Are you saying quite categorically that people who have bought and<br />paid for over a period of time the family homejpossibly sell it,<br />go into something smaller a unit, when they're at retirement age...<br />./ 9</p>
<p>L-i L. A ISON SERVICE. PTH ( 09&gt;) Z5 790G6 P. 9<br />PM. .9 PERTH<br />PM: No capital gains tax.<br />MAUMILL: would not that wouldn't be touched by capital gains tax?<br />PM: Let me make it clear. I am not-. aying there will be a capital<br />gains tax because there's got to be the community consultation<br />that is about the whole tax system. But what I do say is quite<br />clearly to the extent that there has been thinking about this<br />there would be no capital gains tax on the family bome, if it's<br />sold and people move out of that. We can says that because there<br />has been some consideration of this issue. With the Liberals<br />you don't know in their capital gains tax what they would do.<br />But I wanted to make this point, Bob. A capital gains tax would<br />not be seen if it were to come in as a significant revenue-raiser.<br />And you talked about it being a blow the greatest blow that's<br />been imposed upon the Australian taxpayer in our history as a<br />nation is what was done by the Liberals and National Party<br />between 1976 and 1981 when they fostered the tax avoidance<br />industry in this country. And... I mean I... perhaps I could<br />Just read to you briefly, Bob?<br />IAUMILL: By all means. Plenty of time. Our sponsors have been kind<br />enough to waive all the commercials this morning. So we have<br />an uninterrupted run Prime Minister.<br />PM): Thank-you sponsors. But I'm relating this question of the<br />capital gains tax to whether you see it as a blow. The namf,<br />Commissioner Costigan is a pretty well known one isn't it?<br />HAUMILL: Yeah. He's done a fair bit to sort of expose those who have not<br />paid the tax that was their due. -3</p>
<p>t' 4t IZ A4 . L. rI'I4-1'~ i. L, 4 rIIE jt:, I-1&gt;<br />PM. 10 PERTH<br />PM: Well in December 1981, Bob. ho brought down one of his interim<br />reports. And this is what he had to say, he's talking of the<br />tax avoidance industry. This is December 1981 and, the date is<br />very important December ' 81 -he said: " This industry, the<br />tax avoidance industry, has developed in -_ Australia, particularly<br />over the last five years", now see, December ' 81. That's from<br />1976 to 1981 the years of the Liberal Party in government.<br />He said in that period " the industry has developed at a rate<br />far in excess of any other industry and has brought with it<br />profits comparable only to the heady days of the Victorian goldrush."<br />And he said, Bob, " the amounts involved are very large indeed<br />amounting to many hundreds of millions of dollars per year or<br />more." And he went on to say that that had involved a protection<br />of a very wealthy minority and it meant that the ordinary, honest,<br />average law-abiding taxpayer had had to cope the burden.<br />MAUMILL: You're saying that the Fraser/ Howard years were the halcyon ( lays?<br />PM:<br />The halcyon days of the tax avoidance industry. The fastest<br />growing industry in Australia. Now coming back to your capital<br />gains tax and whether it's a blow or not. What many people argue,<br />Bob, is that the most important role of a capital gains tax is as<br />part of the armoury against tax avoidance, not that it would be a<br />tax that would be imposed on the ordinary, average citizen. Because<br />they wouldn't be in a situation where it; would attract it. ] 3ut<br />the absence of a capital gains tax, it's argued, has been<br />sigfiificant in the growth of the tax avoidance industry. So when<br />we have the community discussion after the election about getting<br />a fair tax system that means that the ordinary people get a fair<br />go and we have an efficient tax system it's in that context that<br />a capital gains tax would be argued. Arid, of course, I suppose<br />it's not surprising that your Peacocks and your ilowards, who<br />were ministers in that period right through that period 176 to<br />' 81 which allowed the growth o1' the tax industry which cost I/ j1</p>
<p>PM.. 11 PERTH<br />you and your listeners the ordinary law abiding people<br />hundreds of millions of-dollars a year with the absence of a<br />capital gains tax. it's not surprising I suppose as they protected<br />the tax avoiders in that period and have continued to do it in<br />Opposition, that they might still be talking and saying a capital<br />gains tax is a bad thing. Now I'm simply saying I haven't got<br />a commitment to this position, but what I believe 99 per cent of<br />the Australian community has got a commitment to, is getting a<br />fair and equitable and efficient tax system and within that they<br />will want to have a look at all the element which are necessary<br />to get fairness and equity.</p>
<p>PERTH<br />PM4 12<br />MAUM IJ L " I don't think anyone in the Australian community<br />would be opposed to a tax, that tax windfall profits<br />that taxed speculators who through inside knowledge<br />or more than a litle sharp business practi~ ce or<br />if you like, business nous, suddenly without the u-se<br />of labour or input, suddenly have several million<br />dollars or hundreds of thousands of tax free dollare<br />dropped in their lap.<br />I-think most people in the broader Australian community<br />would support the idea-* of taxing that kind of windfall<br />profit. What I believe most people are opposed to<br />is a tax that taxes those people who have over many<br />many years strived to build up a cap~ tal base, and<br />when they go into the years of their life when they<br />want to sit baick and enjoy it, suddenly, they'vo said,<br />along com~ es the taxman and says we're going to take<br />a bit of it..<br />Now, you're saying that that as far as you can see<br />those people will, and their assets will be protccted.<br />I've got to a~ k you, in this discussion that will<br />take place on revam-ping our tax eystem, who'll be<br />involved? Will it sort of be a taxation summnit<br />rneeting?"<br />HAWKE " well, we,* could I just pick up the first part of<br />what yolu said and then come to the latter part of<br />the questilh, Bob, the question of whether there<br />should bo a tax upon windfall or speculative gains,<br />of course, it's a very good point you make because<br />what people don't, alot of people don't recognise<br />is that there is in existence now, and has been for<br />sometime, a Capital Gains Tax on those sorts of<br />things. if a person: -ir deliberatu-ly in the business of buying<br />and 60) ling for the purpose mnaking an income in that<br />way, then that attracts tax on&amp; that capital gain.<br />If a person does that sort.. of thing also deliberately<br />within a period of less than a otated time in the<br />legislation, it's there, so ther. e is a aapita] gafns<br />tax in the system at the moment to ca-tch that cort<br />of thing, and thlat's; why I say, I'm not going to<br />say that there will be some additional capital gains<br />tax, because it may well be you see, that what is<br />there in the system now together with other changas<br />to create a fail-er tax system may be eniough,<br />But there i~ q a capital gains tax thero no, in one<br />seCnse. It's argued perhaps that to ai~ st in the<br />fight against tax avoidance, there~ may be a nead for<br />something further.<br />But going to the next point that was involved in what<br />you're saying, of course, the ordinary peroon who<br />buys a homne and that, through tim~ e improvee in valucp<br />that person would never attroot a capital oainf vs~ y<br />ot" l luo-4# 4L-MEDIOi L-Ir-ilSON P.</p>
<p>v1. f AJ6 r1 L. r.~ N X : I-Ir<br />IPM 13PERTH<br />in two situations WhiCh would cover for them<br />the 100% OituatiOr i f they stay inl their home<br />and they never realise, niever sell, Then by<br />definition therc is 110 caPital gains tax,<br />Capital gains tax wouild only, in any eystem anywhere,<br />operate it the person % 4-olcs got the aisset<br />actually realises it and rsells it."<br />t4AUMILL :" But they might<br />HiAWK~ E; i " Yeah, but the more imPOr7tant SitUations you're<br />concrie about.,.. what if they move from their<br />home, they sell it to -go and settle somewhere<br />else, capital gains tax does not apply to the disposal<br />of your family home."<br />MAUMILL i " And it won'* t apply under a H~ awke government?"<br />HAW~ KE " if there is any addition, if we db have a capital<br />gains tax beyond what's there in the system now,<br />and I'Ive 5ot to Pay if'I because you can't say we I're<br />going to have et., commvunity public ditcussiom aboit.<br />this thing, ?. ind' allow the whole thing to be tosoed<br />around and ina advance, say I'm corry there can't<br />be a discusaion about this; bcaufe I've made up my<br />mind on it.<br />But I'm 133, y in~ i in answer to your question, if there<br />Were to be sorne extended form of capital gains tax,<br />It would never cover the domestic--Zamily home, vwhich<br />m~ eans that the great mass of Australians would not<br />be adversely affected. blut vihere they could be<br />very beneficially affected, it is argu~ ed, where<br />4, the great Mass of Australians could be helped, is<br />where they've been hit in the past; by theu Liberals.<br />The ordinary taxpayer, the ordinary person listening<br />to this-program has paid over the years of the<br />Liberal and National Paorty Government, they have<br />paid hundreds of dollars more in tax, Bob, because<br />of tile tax avoidance industry which has beon protected<br />by Mr. Peacock ahd Mr. HIoward.<br />N~ ow, it is arguod that vie could eliminate totally tile<br />tax avoidance industry if there was a capital gains<br />tax. 5ystem there which prevented those who have<br />avoided rn-' eting their income tax. obligations by going<br />( 1on the capital approciation route..<br />Now, ao far au your ordinary li1stener is concerned,<br />they shouldn't be worried therefore about this<br />situation, it may offer them some! additional form of<br />protection."</p>
<p>" Prime minister, the other curly one of course<br />iS aboriginal land rights. Here In Western<br />Auotralia the Burke Covernrnent has been applauded<br />In the editorials of our more conservative<br />newspapers for the stance that they've taken on<br />the ' quez.-: ior of aboriginal land rights..<br />Brian B~ urke hau been forced to walkf to tread a<br />ve~ ry dif ficul t path, he and. hi. s. CabA met seem to<br />have come up with a proposal th~ at Is acceptable<br />to most people that held fears about the coming<br />of aboriginal land rights, but at the same time<br />they haven't walked away from the issue.<br />They've taken. alot of the wind out of the sails<br />of the Opposition over here who seem to be the only<br />ones at present who nre dissenting from wThat Brian<br />Burke's clone. But they're now saying that anything<br />that the Burke Government does in the area of<br />aboriginal land rights can of course be ruled out<br />by federal legislation that will apply.<br />So, what they're really eaying is although Burkie<br />has done a pretty good job of ( grasping the nettle<br />and not getting his hands stun( 4 andl of course satisf:<br />to scrne dogree most parties, Bob Hawko's going to<br />wreck. all his good work. Is tLhat the case?"<br />, I s girt is not the case and it's just another measure<br />of the hopelessness of the Liberal Opposition here<br />and federally. They ruined this country irl the<br />period until the beginning of 1983 by creating<br />ctivJsivcness, of seoking del. 1berately to creato<br />confrontatiovism, division within Australia.<br />Thtat's brought Auj3tralia to kts. knees and why<br />Amotraliant are now I'n the positiob at the end of<br />1984 Of h-EVing a much hotter economy, a Much belater<br />DCUOioY IS because we nre healers of division,<br />not the creators. Of confrontation and to their<br />great disappoinitment, I have to Day to then, that<br />0gain they are fanning the firei; of confrontotion<br />-ruiesly, I have been in full consultation With<br />Mr. Burke before I came over her-e and since I've been<br />hore and within a Matter of an hour or so there will<br />bo a press conference at which there will be released<br />a statement agreed between 14r. ElurI0 and myself<br />which indicatos thnt this nonsense w~ hich has been<br />pedalled by the. Opposition that vie would come in<br />over the top of Mr. burke is like all thoir lien<br />toflC emear3 and innvendo groundlesso fal: seunbnced..<br />-Perhaps that's cloar enough." 0./ is<br />PM 14'<br />MAUIILL:<br />HAWKE ~' ing</p>
<p>HAUMILL :" The Federal position on aboriginal land rights<br />then will not cut across what the Burke Government's<br />doing. Y'ou're saying that categorically?"<br />HAWKE i " I think I saiid it pretty categorically then, yes.",<br />MAUM IL I " Prime Minister, organised crime was the big iusue<br />that the opposition was running with and they ran<br />with it for several montho, I just can't get anyone<br />in the opposition now to talk about it.<br />I've noted that A. ndrew Peacock has studiously<br />almost fanatically, kept away from the subject.<br />I listened to him on other radio stations, and our<br />own racdio atation when he was in town during the week,<br />I listened to him on A~ M this mlorning, and I got tapes<br />of all his interviews on ' Various radio and tclevisioi,<br />stations sent to us over here, and I've looked at<br />the lot before I did this interview, for two weeka<br />now and particularly in the last seven days he has<br />kopt right away from thee question of organised crime,<br />he just doesn't went to answer quentions on it.<br />Would you say that ar. far as the biberals are<br />concerned, organised crime is an iosue that they<br />can't win?"<br />HAWKI " Well, of cours3e t's an irvue they can't win,<br />because they chose and again Bob) it fits in with<br />what I've* Just been saying, I ask you and your listeners<br />to cast their'rninO back, you've bc: en looking at the<br />way they've been conducting themselves. Over the<br />lost few rnontbs, have they been addressing themselves<br />to economic policy issues at all? No. Havo they<br />been questioning the economic recovery? No,<br />Have thoy been addreotinn themnselves, to the long term<br />sorts of policies that are needed for Australia,<br />that we've been working on to create a betLar more<br />secure economic future? No. What were they talking<br />about? Exclusively, organised crime. ' They wcrae<br />accuuing me, Mr. Peacock got up and went on for weeko<br />and 6aid I was a crook, that I associated w~ ith<br />criminals and. that I was directed by those who directed<br />criminals. Now that % Yns hia charge, his concept oZ his<br />reoponsibility to the people of Aortralia that aa<br />Leader of the Oppooition to concentrate on issues<br />Was to say that'a the is&amp; Ue. That's what he talked<br />about. I said alright when we got back to<br />Parlianicnt now come on, hore you are you've got the<br />K Parliament, the gull protection of Parlianientary<br />p3rivilege, come on. put it outL. And he was ex~ posed<br />in f'ront of the whole og Australia for wrhat he Is,<br />a m1an who will engage in a lying technique og-amears<br />and innuendo, creating falseh1oods and then when<br />given the opportunity not 9acing up to it.</p>
<p>tNow he has damaged himtselfi you rightlY identifynow,<br />that having been exposed as fraildulent<br />in his charges# not being able to bach them because<br />of course he can't, then he's walked 4ay from it<br />but he cannot walk away from It in the judgement of<br />the Australian people.<br />What faith ic&amp; the ordinary Australian man and1 woman~<br />going to have in *' Leader of the Opposit ion who<br />aspires. to the office of Prime Minister, who abuse&amp;.<br />the intelligence of the average voter by saying to<br />you Mr. Mrs. Australia, I'm going to get up in<br />the Parliament and go round Australia saying these<br />thinge about the Priime Minister, saying these things<br />about organised crime, that the Prime Minister woul. d<br />protect criminals, that's the judgement I the<br />Leader of the Opposition, make. about your intelligence.<br />I'll do all thee things, I'll say all these thin'ga<br />then I crawl away. Now what is the voter going to<br />0ay about that person?~ They won't makie him Prime<br />Minlister and hii, Party won't leave him Leader of the<br />Opposition."<br />MAU14ILL HAWKE: " The National Crimes Authority has taken over much<br />of the work that the COStigarL Royal Cornnission was<br />doing. Are you satisfied'that the lWational Crimes<br />Authority's got enough teeth and can you give us<br />some ideai how it Will operate?"<br />" Yes I can. ' But perhaps from t'he Point of view of<br />your listeners Bob w'hat is even more important<br />than ' the Cact that I'm satisfid is perhops the fact<br />that the members of the 1National Crime Authority<br />are ontisfied. I just remind you ogf the composition<br />of the National Crimes Authority.<br />The chairman of it Mr. Justice Stewart, w; ho is<br />univernally recognised aa the moot experiencod<br />gighter of organised crime in this country and<br />Indeed, the opposition in the debate in the<br />Porlirncnt ackncwledged his integrity, his<br />cormpetencet his capacity, so he's the Chairman.<br />Tha other two men ) era and we appointed him, and<br />the other two mcmbers have, we gave two, names<br />oursolves but they then have to be endorse( 3 by<br />all the State GoVernmonts an( I the N~ orthern Territory<br />Governmonts. T'he other tuo -unanimously endorsed.<br />N~ ow the U. rst fir. Man, finqham, previously Dleputy<br />Tibara'l Premier of Tevmania, QC and Mr. DwyerOC,<br />front N. elbourna. Those two unanimously ondorocd<br />by all Lhe Covornments, Labor and non-Labor ao I<br />haive tha three of than Mr,. Stewart., N&amp;-. Bi nghawp~<br />( lr. Dwyer in my office, the Prime hiniioter's 0ffico<br />Ld1</p>
<p>in Carberra and I directly asked do you need any<br />more powars, do you want me to give you any more<br />powers? No. We're satisfied with what we've got.<br />Second question. Do you believe they'll be adequate<br />for you to do your job? Answer Yes.<br />Now there you have it, They are constituted under<br />the law of the Commionwealth zind importantly<br />CongtituLed in a way which carries with it the full<br />c-peration of the States ofutria<br />You can't havea an effective Crime Authority operating<br />in AUstrolia if i-t simply imposed from Can~ berra and<br />you've got conflict with the sfates. What we've done<br />is to create a sitiuation Where those in it, these<br />experienne3 people sy'wecve got adequate powers and<br />we'va got the co-opcration of the States, now their<br />job will be in the immeiato sense, they will have<br />handed over to them all the work of the Costigan<br />Corsxnission, so that they can study that and they<br />con make recommendat ions to the inter-governmental<br />conmrittee as to what the references should be for<br />them on which to procced,<br />Not only do they have the actual work of the Costiqan<br />Corisujon handed over to them, bVit all of the<br />facilitics, the computer facilities, all the data<br />base of the Costigan Ccmmission, the specialists<br />Involved in the work~ of the Costigan Commnission, all.<br />go over to the National Crim~ e Authority."<br />( 4AUM LL t " Now you're saying that the people go over too?"<br />1LAWK13 i " Tho people go over, the data baoe, the systemts,<br />all go over from Costigan to the National crime~<br />Authority, similarly, aal that material, data base<br />from M'r. Stewart's own Royal Ct), miosion goes vver<br />to the National Crime Authority.<br />Do they've got nll that experience, all the people<br />till. the material, they will no1a perceive the difference<br />betwcen the National Crime Authority and the R~ oyal<br />CommicsfonG3 and this involves no reflection upon the<br />Roycil Commiscions but the Royal Commissioic do not<br />have the job of svterblying hard admxissable evidence<br />for prooOQutions, Novi this is what the National<br />Crime Authority will do, and will move now; to the<br />important tank of starting to get those major criminalD<br />w-. here they belong and that's behind bars."<br />L4AUMI! LL :" Prime LMinlater, enough of the tough questiono~ lotla<br />get on to come of the lighater oner). I XiIh L-le tiay<br />Bill1 Hayden's handling himself and I'm sura that most<br />Australians do withi exception of David McNichol of<br />The Bulletin who uays he's. a iatr<br />Bill Hayden scems to have grown in stature, to a<br />m~ ore confident, tougher B~ ill Hayden, he waihn the<br />V / 21n</p>
<p>PM 18<br />. HAWKE~ Fts~ rI~ 41j a<br />international arena, the arena~ of international<br />affairs with more than a little! authority and Ws'<br />AOL frightcned to make Australia's feelings about<br />contonLious isuls well % nown,<br />After a scratchy start with your political relations#<br />you must be very very happy with his performance."<br />" Well, T want to say thi.&lt;. thjit="" bill="" as="" you="" say=""&gt; has been an outstanding Foreign Minister and I<br />believe that Bill1 in happier now than he's ever been<br />in his political career. He and I went throuagh a<br />period of trauma and I'd be quite silly to deny that<br />of couroa and he was hurt and disappointed, but I<br />must say from the time I've asoumed the Leadership<br />of the Party, Bill and 1-Iarticu , arly once wo came<br />into govornmant, as Minititer for Foreign Affairs,-<br />Bill has been in constant co~ unication with me<br />his first visiE overscaos in Apr: il of 1983 when he<br />went to Indones~ ia and wit to talk not only with the<br />Xndoncsians but to tnke up the whole problem of this<br />area of Xnclo-China and our relatlonshipa with the<br />Ase~ n. oLates, I put to him my vi~ ews, how I thought<br />Vi~ e could in faict play torm Gort of role because of<br />our gjood relationis with all the countries concerned<br />and he agreed with tha~ t, lie went on and he's viorked<br />on tHat basir in thot area in complate co-Qrdination<br />wIL1h me aS he has as lie goes into the other areac.<br />lie talks. Withl fme and he has as you say articulated<br />Australia's position. forcefully. I believe that<br />19 you look now, at the end of M94 at Australia's<br />international relationkihip5, we have without ziny<br />queotion a better relationship now with tho countrie~ s<br />of our region than has ever been the case before.<br />Por instance, when I caj to offico, the relationship<br />botucen ourselves and M'alaysia were Very very distanL,<br />there was a rigidity there, now I've mot flr. Nartere*<br />tho Prime Minister of fzAaysia wTho I think is an<br />outstanding man and we havv extremely cordial and<br />prOductive relations there.<br />Importantly, ;-we have wit~ h China as tm-ll, Now i n<br />all these things, it's b'een a constructive co-opxirativc<br />relonship between mys. elf an~ l B3ill Hayden.<br />lie's doing his.. and Lionel Bov. en oz; finistor for<br />Tr~ e! let me say, w-hich is at) im~ portant pcirt of yourintornationnI<br />relat--ion-. 1-ip. With the United Statea.,<br />thiv country has never had a batter rolationship with<br />tha United States than we have now*' That's~ not a<br />eelationship of sycophanicy, it'n a rclationolhip of<br />aonztructive, fixrm, warm alliance rolationrihip but<br />Oo in which if wei have aot-ao differenes~ of viety about<br />ptirtictilar ADL3UG01 WdJ put them."<br />r 4</p>
<p>I'm 19<br />HAUMILL g " For a long titne though they took Us~ for gjranted,<br />Would you GaY that's changed?"<br />HAMIE " Yes, they don't taie us for granted, now." 1<br />MAUIMLL t OAIJ the way with LBJ and all that." 1<br />HAWNE t " No it's not that.. but wiit they do recognise is<br />that we have a coriitment to a free democratic<br />Way Of lifO as the best sort of environ society<br />for people anYwhere in the world, to be able to<br />growi up in.<br />110 are commlitted to the free democratic Pystcm ar,<br />6% gainst tyrannous dictators3hips, alld it,$ that<br />Commitment which shared comnmitrn~ nt, which binds<br />the United States and Auatrakia together, flow<br />that doean't m~ ean that in some interpretations<br />of iuome issues we won't have ditforences,. but why<br />the relationship is so good is because the United<br />Statca knows that we chare. that basic coiimrent.,<br />It 1( 3 unquestionable and unsha~ zeable that they liscon<br />to uco If on somne particular issues we have a slightly<br />diffarent emp~ hasis and Intoerpretation ond the factu<br />are that thore i5 a continuous warmiclosoepersona.<br />co!? X'unication betwcen the Secretairy of S3tate,. Ge. orge<br />Schultz and riyself~ and the Preoident. of the Vnited<br />States 4nd ivyselg.<br />And that adde, to the relationahips that are created<br />by Bill Hlayden in his-viork as Foreign M~ inister<br />and Australians have very very good reason to ba<br />extrtly satisi -ed with what has bean done in thlo<br />Poriod og office by its Tmininter for Forcign Affillr<br />and rmysell and Lionel Dowen, the three who have the<br />major responsibility of cementing good relationo<br />with othor countries in the world."</p>
<p>PM.. 20 PERTH<br />MAUMILL: The Soviet Union is one of our big customers. The Soviet Union<br />buys much of what we produce. For many years they have been a<br />customer a customer that we have often called nasty names. How<br />are relationships at the moment with the Soviet Union? Are we<br />talking to them?<br />PM: Yes we talk with them. Here again what has been done is that the<br />Soviet Union has been left in no doubt whatsoever about our<br />attitudes to what they do in the area of human rights. Their<br />totally unjustifiable excursion into and remaining in Afghanistan,<br />the building up of their military presence in Vietnam very<br />significant building up of military presence there. Now we make<br />it quite clear to the Soviet Union our abhorrence of these things<br />but there is a responsibility in government to make the distinction<br />between putting on the' record and telling people what you disapprove<br />of, as we do unequivocably with the Soviet Union, and then<br />recognising that they exist, that they are a major element in the<br />world commerical and trading relationship. So we don't call people<br />names just for the sake of calling names and we have restored a<br />more constructive trading relationship with them, as indeed the<br />United States is in the process of doing. And that of course is<br />to the benefit of our farmers and others in Australia whose<br />welfare depends on being able to have access to as many markets<br />as you possibly can.<br />M AUMILL:<br />Prime Minister, Paul Keating when the Hawke Government first took<br />office looked really crook. I mean he was no good thing to last<br />the term. He was black under the eyes, green around the gills, had<br />a lot of trouble fronting up, lost weight, his suits were hanging<br />on him as though he was a scarecrow. I thought, well Paul Keating<br />is not going to see the distance. He can't cop the pressure. Now<br />at that time John Howard was sort of the school master of Australian<br />economics because he was constantly in the public eye giving forth<br />with opinion. Lately, during parliamentary broadcasts and<br />televised debates, Paul Keating has put on weight, the black .*/ 21</p>
<p>PM. .21 PERTH<br />circles have gone, the confidence has returned, he's loving the<br />Job and he very firmly often very caustically, some would almost<br />say bordering on the cruelly -put John Howard and any other<br />spokesman on economic matters from the other side firmly in their<br />place. Now, honestly has Keating's performance superb performancebeen<br />a surprise to you? He's always been a tough political co'okie.<br />PM: Well look I think you have summed it up very well. It may be a<br />little bit unfair of me to ask whether it has been a surprise.<br />But I think the honest answer is the extent of his and the speed<br />of his acquisition of supremacy has I think been somewhat<br />surprising. You are quite right, that when Bill Keating er<br />sorry when Bill Hayden put Paul Neating into the position of<br />shadow Treasurer at the beginning of -' 83 it came as a surprise<br />and everyone said well he's thrown Paul in the deep end. And<br />within a matter of just days really he was,: there in an election<br />campaign being the Treasurer spokesman for the Labor Party. And<br />then again within just a matter of weeks fie's the Treasurer. -So<br />he's thrown into this most complex of portfolios with just a<br />matter of weeks in the shadow position with no formal training in the<br />past in economics and financial matters, ftlthoug-h as shadow Minister<br />for Minerals and Energy impinging in many areas; and it was clear<br />in those early days that he was battling. And he recognised that.<br />But I had confidence in his ability because he is a very intel ligent<br />mhan and a hard working man. I knew lie would get there. But yes,<br />frankly I was surprised with the speed-with which, and the<br />comprehensiveness with which) he mastered that intricate portfolio.<br />I just saw him day by day grow in confidence and capacity. It was<br />said in those early days that he was a creature of John Stone and<br />the Treasury and there were some very cruel cartoons you remember.<br />But no one draws those anymore. Let me say this. Keating lasted<br />the course, one other gentleman didn't.<br />MAUMILL: Yes, riell John Stone's having an awful lot to say now. Do you see<br />him as a future Liberal politician?</p>
<p>PM. .22 PERTH<br />PM: The Liberals would run a mile from him. Well some of the Liberals<br />would. MAUMILL: He almost sounds as though he's running for office.<br />PM: Ye8s. Of course, in the latter days of.. his* Treasurership, Mr Howard<br />wasn't really talking with Mr Stone. They used to conduct their<br />' communications by correspondence. I don't think John Howard would<br />be welcoming John Stone. But look I think this is a democracy.<br />I observe that there is this hypocracy involved. Mr. Stone was<br />the one when he was a public servant who talked about the standards,<br />and the integrity, the apolitical nature of the public servant and<br />so on. Well, you know, he's seemed to forget that in his latter<br />days. But that doesn't worry me, I mean I'm not concerned about<br />it. This is a democracy. If Mr Stone wants to engage in his<br />observations let him do so. I would just en passant make t; he<br />observation that I don't know what Mr Stone thinks gives hi~ m any<br />right to be talking with any_ degree of authority about the Age<br />tapes for instance. I mean Senator Evans and his rejoinder<br />exposed the complete inadequacy of M. r Stone's knowledge or<br />competence in that area. But if John Stone wants to talk in this<br />environment, let him talk. I mean I think the reaction of' the<br />editorials have been pretty telling. They've made it clear what<br />they think about his contribution.<br />MAUMILL: Almost cruel.<br />PMU:<br />Well, almost cruel but if John would like after the election to<br />formally get into the political process, I don't think ho'd be<br />applying to the Labor Party for membership. But he can if he<br />wants to, you know, I think he'd hdv'e a pretty slow pr ogress<br />through the ranks. He could try the Liberal Party.-./ 23</p>
<p>PM. .2 3 PERTH<br />MAUMILL: Held have a lot of trouble getting it seconded.<br />PM: Well no, no, look we're on a very serious subject. He could try<br />the Liberal Party, but Johnny Howard would be very, very, very<br />opposed to that. I mean he'd be getting around thea branch and<br />saying, " wht' this? We can't have this happening." Now he<br />could try the National Party. Now that would be an interesting<br />alliance, but he. of course some of the most vitriolic attacks<br />that Mr Stone has made in the past upon political people is on<br />the National Party so I don't think he'd get in there. So<br />what does that leave? Well, perhaps there could be something<br />in this story about after the eclipse of the Liberals in this<br />next election that there's going to be a move for a new conservative<br />force in-Australian politics. Now we might see a new party. Now<br />who could it have? It could have John Stone, have Sir Joh. Who<br />else could it have?<br />MAUHILL: Porter, from Queensland?<br />PM: Oh yeah and I don't know whether Mr Hassell, he might, he might<br />cause he's pretty conservative they tell ine you might have this<br />group. Now it would be a question of who would be leader. Would<br />it be John Stone, or J ! oh Petersen, or, or M~ r Hassell. It could<br />be interesting couldn't it? But if John would like to do that<br />to get into politics I would welcome it.<br />P": ( Laughter) Prime Minister I listen to parliamentary debates and<br />obviously one of you most rewarding moments of late has been the<br />return of Mick Young to your side on the front bench.</p>
<p>PM. .24 PERTH<br />MAUMILL: And who'll ever forget. Mick Young's telling retort to Ian Sinclair<br />when Mick Young held up in Parliament the results of the investigation<br />into his alleged customs misdemeanour and said to Ian Sinclair:<br />" Ian, you'd give your right arm to have a report like that."<br />PM:<br />Report like that!<br />HAUMILL: And what's more, " Ian, I didn't sign this myself!" which was a<br />reference to certain police investigations in the past. Is Mick<br />accident prone, or is hie just a good bloke who tries to do the<br />right thing and just doesn't pay attention to detail?<br />PM4: Well Hick is overwhelmingly a good bloke. In the first episod~ e<br />it was a situation where in good faith and without any intention<br />of harming the national security he was trying to help a friend.<br />He admitted he was wrong. And he paid a penalty for that. And<br />he didn't attempt to excuse what he'd done.<br />MAUMILL: Doesn't run away from it does he?<br />PM:<br />No he didn't run away from it. Now he paid a penalty and he.' s<br />back i~ n now with the Paddington Bear Affair. Now this was another<br />classic case of the tactics of the Opposition. And before I go<br />to those tactics just let me remind you of the difference between<br />how we approach this matter and how earlier, wvhen the Opposition<br />wiere in Government with the affair involving two ministers I<br />don't name them because I don't want to rub anything into their<br />names,. or<br />MUWAILL: And the colour television.</p>
<p>PM. .25 PERTH<br />PM: Yeah well that's what I'm talking about. But I don't want to<br />mention the names. I simply make the point that that happened,<br />the incident happened in October, and it was covered up and it<br />came out, not by their volition, but it came out six months l. ater<br />in April. Now as distinct from that here! in this case, when ' the<br />Minister for Customs, John Button, brought to my attention and<br />I think it was the fifth of July as I recall -that there was<br />this problem, I said well make sure that tie normal investigations<br />proceed. No special treatment. And that was the attitude of<br />John Button himself. And so that went on. And on the twentieth<br />of July the final report from the Controller-General of Customs<br />was given to Mr Button, And the Controller-General said, well<br />as far as he was concerned everything was okay. I said to Senator<br />Button: " Are you satisfied?" He said yes and I said: " Well I<br />am." 1 And I said: " Now that that's solved "( inaudiblc) I aid to Mick~" you makde<br />public. " Hle said sure okay and he went in and it was put out -to<br />the public. No attempt to hide it. There it was. Volunteered<br />out on the table. So this was the great issue for the great issue<br />for the Liberals and the National Party. These people who had set<br />their standards of covering things up that this was the big<br />issue. Now what happened? We had the inquiry when it looked as<br />though there was some other element that we perhaps hadn't considered.<br />Had the inquiry. The Black inquiry. There it was. And as Uick<br />Young said, a total exoneration.-complete. As he said to<br />Mr Sinclair, " wouldn't you give your right arm for a report like<br />that?" So that's the tactics of the Opposition wiltl seek to<br />latch on to these miserable things, But again, do you hear them<br />talking about it now?<br />UiUMILL:<br />Prime Minister have you got any good news for Australians? What's<br />coming up that's good?<br />I think there's a lot that's coming up that's good. And it's</p>
<p>PM.. 26 PERTH<br />built upon what's happened in the last period since the beginning<br />of ' 83. As I say Australia can be proud of the fact that in this<br />last period we've had the highest rate of economic growth in the<br />world. Under a Treasurer who's got the accolade now of the world's<br />number one finance minister. Now the projections for the rest of<br />this financial year are strong. There's going to be continued<br />strong growth. I promised Australia, you remember in February of<br />' 83, that we would create 500 000 new jobs. in three years. We're<br />ahead of target and employment growth will go on in this period<br />ahead. We'll get that 500 000 jobs in the first three years.<br />There will be gradually rising standards of living. There will<br />be a continuation of industrial peace. We've had the lowest level<br />of industrial disputes for the last 15 years. That will continue.<br />In the business community there will be significant deregulation<br />in the whole area of business, as we have deregulated the financial<br />community. The Australian people in business and in their personal<br />affairs will have now available to them in 1985 a much larger more<br />competitive banking framework. We'll have banks in from overseas<br />who will services to offer and approaches which will be far more<br />imaginative than the old existing few Australian banks that we've<br />had here. So that's going to make it better for individuals and<br />for business. . We will, and I say this particularly for Western<br />Australians, that the relationship with China is developing rapidly<br />for the benefit of Australia and for the benefit of China. We<br />now, as you know, will have a new iron ore mine developed in<br />Western Australia the Channar deposit with the Chinese.<br />That's the first new iron ore mine for years and years and<br />years. That's going to create more jobs and there's the<br />distinct likelihood that there'll be further developments<br />affecting Western Australia involving the Chinese. So these<br />things are good. Most importantly it will continue to be good<br />because the basis that we established last year for these things<br />is there. That is, we've effected a national reconciliation.<br />We've asked Australians to put Australia first and. that's the secret.<br />And I say I want the trade unions, I want businesses, State government,:<br />local government, and ourselves before we make decisions or adopt<br />attitudes ask ourselves what's best for Australia. If we do . tt<br />o</p>
<p>PM.. 27 PER~ TH<br />we'll continue to grow and we'll do what Australia's been doing<br />in the last couple-of years it's winning again and will<br />continue to do that.<br />MAUM ILL:<br />Prime Minister I've got an interest in Fremantle. That's my<br />town. That's where I'm from.<br />PM: Yep.<br />MAUM ILL:<br />I'm giving some consideration to running for Mayor of Fremantle<br />now that the best mayor the place has ever had, Bill McKenzie,<br />has taken an important job. And I've put my name forward as<br />mayor. PM: Have you!<br />U4AU MI LL<br />So naturally I'm interested on behalf of all Fremnantle residentAs<br />to know if you'll give us a hand financially during the America ' s<br />Cup period? .428</p>
<p>pn28<br />HAWKE MJWMILL HAMt 14AUMILL: ' We've ma~ de $ 30m. available, Bob and we've put it up<br />front becauce we recogn~ se that we, as the Federal<br />Government, have got responsibility irn this m~ atter,<br />So firstly, put the money up, secondly, I've created<br />I've 4ppo. inted John Dawkins as the Minister to<br />represent us in a committee between the Federal<br />Government and the State Government and the City of<br />Promantle to co-ordinate activities so yes, rrernantle<br />can be assured of total support from the Federal<br />Government because I believe the defence of the<br />Amierica's Cup iD going to be great for Pr'm'antle,<br />great for Western Australia, great for Australia.<br />Ahnd I don't use words loosely, I mean the money that's<br />going to pour into this country, the employment that'sG<br />going to ba created by these tens of thousands of<br />visitors is marvellous.<br />Our responsibility is to make sure, Bobo that this<br />happens in a way which-, is going to provide lasting<br />benefits to the people of the area. We don It want<br />the citizens of F'remantle just. to be the vict~ ims of<br />some transient passing thing, we~ went the davelopments<br />that are created to deal with this challenge ' to be<br />of lasting bonefit, to the citizens of Fremantle.<br />I beliove it will be."<br />" Prime Mi4nirter, you've givc-n us plenty of yomr ' time<br />but there xt&gt;; one more question,"<br />" Why the hell aire vie he3vinc thsbod l ion? n<br />" Well, good question. And tho ankswer is very simple.<br />Tihe Libe~ rals and The National Party at the beginning<br />of 190J3 called on an early election witD a double<br />Gissolution of both nouses of Parliam~ ent, now that<br />threw the whole question of elections omt of kilter.<br />Because under the constitution, I'vo had to call,<br />I would have had to cDIl an election for half the<br />Senate by April, noxt April, you just have * to do<br />that, holf the Senate. Now if I'd just done that<br />and thon caid vo'll let the H-ouce of Representatives<br />run on, it woujld hoave meant that in a relatively<br />* hort time after that I then wolild have had to havo<br />a H~ ouse of Reprosorntativos election. Dut what I've<br />done, these things, nnd I think that evory one of<br />yjour listoners uill underan it, I'vo sa3. W crights<br />we'll do for the tv.-nty-third. Uie what'c boon the<br />normal thiog in thc pact irc to havo the !' ouse og<br />noprosntativea an"" thc half! Scoate clection together,<br />' 11lhla vc ' it nou Gind thzit ri art that if the peoplo<br />Poau tho rfocErcnum which I Ilut for !; FU~ tCncouD<br />elections, tic will fievor again hnvo the aitu~ ttio&gt; n</p>
<p>PM 29 of Pririe ministera calling extra electione.<br />we will sava the people of Australia $ 19m. by<br />having the two together rather than two separate<br />ones and that's the reason."<br />N'AUHILL Primne Plinister, just before you go and your otaff<br />now are saying that you've odot to get on to your<br />next appointment.<br />You said before that there would be discussions<br />within the community about a re-vamped-taxation<br />system, and I'd applaud that, I said who'd bc<br />involved in such discussions. Do you envisage<br />a taxation suflmit, simlalr to-the economic sumits:<br />that you held before where people such as the<br />Australian Taxpayer's Associatlon, the various<br />Treasurers from State Governments, yourself, Pail<br />Keating9, l'eaders of businov3s, community groups<br />would bc represented, the T~ rade UnIon Movement,<br />would be represented at a taxation tsuiv,, it,-I mean<br />itle something that we have discussed off air and<br />you scined at that time to have something up your<br />zleovo about an announcemient.<br />W~ ould a taxation summit be possible? I think it.<br />would be welcomed."<br />HlAWKE :" It's a good idea Bob and I'll certainly give<br />consideration to that %-, hat we'd had in mind<br />tins that ue'd atart the discussions in what is,<br />the mini ,., ummit we'\' e set up,. under legisl. ation,<br />that's the economic planning advisory council<br />where the business co'iiunity and trade unions and<br />locral governmenta, State Governrientcs and welfare<br />ory afisations aro rcpresonted on thnt, on EPAC,<br />which meets regularly in the Caibinct room under<br />my Chairmanship.<br />NWv to project that back Into a'ournmit concept,<br />Is attractive and I'll give thovght to that,<br />It may viall be that as we Vot the fvrrmol dscusions<br />going ; within E-PAC, that it might m~ akeolcot of sense<br />to oxp4and that into a sumft Idea tiherc there could<br />be a projection of viows by repronentatives of tt. e<br />peoplo in a more dircct way, It's a good thoucht<br />and I W1l give nttantion to it."<br />VIAUVIILL i " Pr'. 1mc Hinister, thanks for joining us on GPR again<br />you havo an important press conference coming up<br />with otit Pronler very soon, we've run overtinte but<br />as usual it'e been a rivetting discusoion.<br />Thanks to overyone who participated today An puttin~ g<br />the piroggri together and look fork-. cir to ocvircg<br />1 ob Ha,. A1, o round as our Prime Hiinioter fox somie tim3<br />to cor,-Tihat is a personal view, not necessarily<br />the view of the stati'on and tht Board of Directors."<br />IfAI( ll: N aughs).... well thanks 8ob, I hnve this press<br />0</p>
<p>~. 1<br />PM but cortainly at the pross conference there will<br />t* a statement reflecting the discussions that<br />Brian and I have had, but to you, thank you very<br />rhuch, it's QXways enjoyable to talk with yo., to<br />respond to your questions and I thank you for your<br />personal indication of support and you never know<br />we might have a chance with the Board on the station<br />as well,"<br />MAUM ILL ( laughs) Thanhs Prime minister.<br />You've been listening to Bob Hawnill talking to<br />the Pritne tnister of Aurtralia, fir. Bob Hawke,<br />41</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
