<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10767</transcript-id>
    <title>29 November 1998                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  DOORSTOP INTERVIEW FOLLOWING FULL BOARD MEETING                  OF THE COUNCIL FOR ABORIGINAL RECONCILIATION      </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>I've just had a very good meeting with the Council. It was</p>
<p>   the first chance I've had to meet them. And I repeated what</p>
<p>   I'd said on election night and I repeated the Government's</p>
<p>   commitment to achieving, if it could, the positive outcome for the</p>
<p>   reconciliation process by the time of the Centenary of Federation.</p>
<p>   I stressed that it was important that expectations be realistic.</p>
<p>   I outlined, in very general terms, some of the things that we had</p>
<p>   in mind and I thought it was a useful meeting. And we've agreed</p>
<p>   to work together on a reconciliation document. You may remember</p>
<p>   that during the election campaign I said that I supported the putting</p>
<p>   together of a document. I certainly don't see it as a treaty.</p>
<p>   I think I've made that clear before and that is understood.</p>
<p>   But there is no reason in my mind that we cannot put together a</p>
<p>   document which records a number of things and expresses the desire</p>
<p>   of Australians, right across the community, to not only enjoy but</p>
<p>   to build upon the process of reconciliation. It won't be easy</p>
<p>   but there is goodwill on the part of the Government, there is goodwill</p>
<p>   in the community and I know that the leadership of the indigenous</p>
<p>   people of Australia would want to achieve that outcome. The Council</p>
<p>   is a bipartisan body and it brings together a lot of very thoughtful</p>
<p>   people who have a genuine commitment to the process. And I'm</p>
<p>   cautiously optimistic  I don't want to put it any more</p>
<p>   strongly than that  that we can achieve a positive outcome.</p>
<p>   And I certainly intend, with Mr Ruddock having the special responsibility,</p>
<p>   I certainly intend to work very hard to achieve that outcome.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, you said that there was some general things that</p>
<p>   you outlined. Are you able to tell us more about that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think any document of this kind must have, as a starting</p>
<p>   point, that we are all Australians together, the indivisibility</p>
<p>   of the Australian nation. It must be a document that acknowledges</p>
<p>   the historical truths of this country, the prior occupation of it</p>
<p>   by the indigenous people. It must acknowledge injustices. It must</p>
<p>   deal with current disadvantage. But it must focus also on the need</p>
<p>   to have practical outcomes to improve the position of indigenous</p>
<p>   Australians. It ought to be a document that inspirational as well</p>
<p>   as aspirational. Now, that's perhaps a fairly demanding menu</p>
<p>   but I'm optimistic that it can be achieved. But it's very</p>
<p>   important that people have realistic expectations.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did the Council express a view to you as to whether the document</p>
<p>   should contain an apology?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, we haven't got into that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You said that it's not going to be a simple process or it's</p>
<p>   going to be difficult, what aspects make it difficult?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think the whole history of this issue.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Is the timing, the timeframe?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't think it's the timeframe. But if people approach</p>
<p>   it with, what I might say, goodwill and realism then we may be able</p>
<p>   to achieve a positive outcome.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, are you confident that relations will be more harmonious</p>
<p>   during your second term than they were in your first term?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think they were harmonious with a lot of people in the</p>
<p>   communities. There were some disagreements on particular issues</p>
<p>   but this is a two-way process. There's goodwill on the part</p>
<p>   of the Government and I expect goodwill in return from the rest</p>
<p>   of the community on this issue and I'm hopeful that that can</p>
<p>   be the case.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you want this document ready for the Centenary of Federation...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that would be the appropriate time. You've got to remember</p>
<p>   that the Council itself has been charged by the Parliament with</p>
<p>   reporting on whether a document is feasible or not.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Could the document feed in as some sort of preamble to the Constitution?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh look, that's a separate issue and I think we've got</p>
<p>   to keep those two things separate because unless the people vote</p>
<p>   at the end of next year to change the Constitution there won't</p>
<p>   be any new preamble.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, your Treasurer said this morning that the Government</p>
<p>   would be accepting the major recommendations of the Vos Report.</p>
<p>   When we see the legislation on Wednesday, how many changes will</p>
<p>   there be contained in that bill from what you've already flagged?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm sorry, I don't quite understand the import of that</p>
<p>   question.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well, Cabinet has had to fine-tune the tax package as adopted by...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yes, I always said it would.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>How wide-ranging will those changes be?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there'll be some fine-tuning. I always said that. But</p>
<p>   there won't be any alteration in the basic thrust.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, you said that banks will have to increase competition</p>
<p>   before there'll be any big mergers between the big four. What</p>
<p>   do you think about the idea that local councils now want to start</p>
<p>   their own banks...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm in favour of thousands of flowers blooming everywhere,</p>
<p>   whether it be in banks or anything else. But there isn't enough</p>
<p>   competition as yet, certainly in some of the important small business</p>
<p>   areas, and that is why the current stance is going to continue.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So there's no immediate mergers.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no, that's been made very clear. I made that clear when</p>
<p>   I spoke to the National Farmers' Federation but to my amazement</p>
<p>   some news outlets chose to interpret those remarks in completely</p>
<p>   the opposite way. What Mr Costello said this morning was on all</p>
<p>   fours with what I had said to the National Farmers' Federation</p>
<p>   a few days ago. </p>
<p>Thank you</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
