<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8923</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008923.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL:<br />
PRIME MINISTER86/ 93<br />
STATEM1ENT BY THE PRIME MINISTERt TJlE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
THE EXTENT OF NATIVE TITLE<br />
Sections of the media today have treated as a revelation the Governmcnt's view that<br />
the Mabo High Court decision will not increase sharply the amount of land able to be<br />
granted to Aborigines and Torres Strait Islanders.<br />
Some commentators have wondered aloud why the Government did not say so sooner.<br />
In fact, the Government and I personally have been making this point repeatedly<br />
since the handing down of the High Court decision in June last year.<br />
I find it extraordinary that some in the media having peddled exaggerated and illinformned<br />
interpretations of the impact of Mabo for months now seek to blame the<br />
Government for allowing such views to be put about. The truth is, the Government has<br />
consistently urged all interested parties to be calm about the issue, and from the outset<br />
has reassured private land holders that their property is not under threat.<br />
The consistency of my approach is demonstrated in the following remarks:<br />
Mabo, even in its fit/ les: expression, will only give to a minority of the<br />
Aboriginal community land because many of them were dispos. sessed of the land and<br />
tecrefore can't make a cla/ im. John Laws Program, 2UE, 21 June, 1993<br />
i. t doesn't mean that large parts of Australia, particularly of the built uip<br />
areas of Australia, the urban areas ofAustralia will be subject to a native title claim.<br />
Wher-efreehold titlk has been issued the native title has been held to have been<br />
extinguished; where leasehold has been Issued, the native title in most Cases or In<br />
many caves has beeni extinguished" NSW ALP Conference, 13 June, 1993<br />
" It is important to recognise that existing legal rights in relation to property<br />
continue, and it is wrong to see the H-igha Courts decision terms ( if existing land<br />
holif'rs losing their land. However, the decisionm introduices a new element into<br />
A ustrallami landf tenure, in the form of native title, and thereby creates a needfor<br />
clarity in t1e definition amid alplication of native title fig/ ts, especially in relation to<br />
other interests it land." Redfern Speech, 10 December 1992<br />
EL: 30.-jul. 93 16: 12 No. 007 P. 01/ 02 </p>
<p>I .1 think it is Word? saying that the court's decision does not challenge the<br />
granting offreehold or leasehold title over musch of/ A , istralia, a~ some people have<br />
feared it might, and it does not interfere with private property rights of this kind<br />
Parliament, 4 June, 1992<br />
To their credit, this view has been reinforced by some in the Aboriginal community,<br />
including Mick Dodson of the Northern Land Council, who said in January this year:<br />
" Our advice on Mabo is that clearly there are the majority, thc overwheliming majority<br />
of forms of land tenure in this country are unaffected by Mabo. People have nothing to<br />
fear, The existing property rights in those lands is secure."<br />
It has also been suggested in the press today that this realistic assessment of the<br />
consequences for land ownership in Australia calls into question the linking of Mabo to<br />
the issue of Aboriginal reconciliation. This is simply not the case, and reveals a<br />
fundamental lack of understanding of the High Court decision.<br />
The Government still holds thc view that the Mabo decision provides an opportunity to<br />
achieve reconciliation with Aboriginal people. However, this link between Mabo and<br />
reconciliation was never based on an assumption that the Mabo judgment would lead<br />
to vast new tracts of land being granted to Aboriginal people.<br />
Rather, it is based on the decision itself. By jettisoning the fallacy of terra nullius and<br />
recognising Aboriginal dispossession, the Mabo decision has left us far better prepared<br />
psychologically to proceed with the process of reconciliation. The foundations of<br />
discrimination and prejudice have becn kicked away.<br />
Many Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islandcr people will receive no benefit from the<br />
Mabo decision. They have been dispossessed.<br />
There needs to be and the Government intends to deliver a package of social justice<br />
measures for them, in keeping with thle spirit of the Mabo decision.<br />
CANBERRA JULY, 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
