<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17557</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister’s New Year message</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/01/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Government</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Happy New Year.</p>
<p>As the fireworks fade and the cricket moves from Melbourne to Sydney, I'm proud to be Australian and excited about the year ahead.</p>
<p>Australia can look forward to 2011 confident in our future as a fair and prosperous nation.</p>
<p>As the New Year begins, we have much to look forward to.</p>
<p>I still think we are lucky. But I also think the harder we work, the luckier we get.</p>
<p>So I think 2011 will be a good year for Australia because of the capacity and decency of the millions of Australians who now contribute, in their own way, without thanks or praise, to making it a better place.</p>
<p>In our mines, in our factories, in our hospitals, in our schools and even on patrol outside Tarin Kowt, Australians will do amazing things this year.</p>
<p>As I look forward to 2011, I do see some challenges for our country.</p>
<p>Like creating jobs in a strong economy, giving every child a great start in life at school, tackling climate change and persevering in our mission in Afghanistan. Real challenges for our country. Big things to be achieved. We wouldn't want it any other way.</p>
<p>And my overwhelming sense at the start of this New Year is optimism.</p>
<p>Optimism because of what has already been achieved by the people who have made Australia what is today.</p>
<p>Australia is a wonderful country, the greatest country on earth.</p>
<p>I know this year we can do great things together.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoy the rest of your break, and come back full of energy and excitement - but not too soon. Happy New Year.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
