<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21825</transcript-id>
    <title>Taskforce on Workplace Relations Reform  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/07/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>  I am pleased to announce the appointment of a Taskforce on Workplace Relations Reform.</p>
<p>The Taskforce will assist the Minister for Employment and Workplace Relations, the Hon Kevin Andrews MP, in communicating details of the Government's workplace reforms to the Australian community.</p>
<p>I have appointed Mr Andrew Robb AO MP as Chairman of the Taskforce   and Senator Santo Santoro as Deputy Chairman.</p>
<p>Mr Robb and Senator Santoro have extensive knowledge of workplace relations issues and a long term commitment to reform. They have both demonstrated a particular interest in small business matters.</p>
<p>Prior to entering Parliament, Mr Robb was a successful business adviser and previously held roles as Executive Director of the National Farmers' Federation and Federal Director of the Liberal Party of Australia. Senator Santoro was Minister for Industrial Relations in the previous Coalition Government in Queensland.</p>
<p>  The Taskforce will also include the Hon Alan Cadman MP, Mr Stuart Henry MP, Senator Guy Barnett, Dr Andrew Southcott MP, Ms Sophie Panopoulos MP and Mr Luke Hartsuyker MP.</p>
<p>All members of the Taskforce have experience in this area and will provide a valuable contribution in helping inform Australian workers, employers and their families about the Government's workplace relations reforms.</p>
<p>It is crucial that the Australian community understands what reforms are being proposed - and just as importantly, what isn't being contemplated. The Taskforce will help inform Australians about why the workplace relations changes are needed to ensure the economy remains strong, unemployment stays low and wages and productivity continue to grow.</p>
<p>  The Taskforce will work closely with Mr Andrews and other members of the Government on matters relating to the Coalition's workplace relations reforms.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
