<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9149</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, 225 ST GEORGES TERRACE, PERTH, 9 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009149.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING, MP<br />
DOORSTOP, 225 ST GEORGES TERRACE, PERTH, 9 MARCH 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I just had a discussion with a very representative group about the<br />
labour market and the Green Paper proposals that the Government<br />
has published to deal with the problems of the long-term unemployed.<br />
I had a chance there to listen to what particular sectors involved in this<br />
this is the technical and further and education, TAFE; the Salvation<br />
Army; SkillShare; the Labour Council; the employers; Chambers of<br />
Manufactures so one does get a fairly, I think, representative view. I<br />
regard this as valuable because picking up some of the texture and<br />
text of this discussion is very important in thinking about how such<br />
changes ought to be made. That is, how do we make the long-term<br />
unemployed jobs ready again? How do we train them and give them<br />
confidence and give them the prospects of getting employment? And<br />
do we make a national commitment to them? I think, the answer is<br />
those questions have all got to be answered in the affirmative and, I<br />
think, the group I have just seen are suggesting ways where we can<br />
make the labour market programs work better; how they are better<br />
understood by business; how they are more readily taken up; and I<br />
regarded that as a very valuable and helpful discussion.<br />
J: Prime Minister, on Medicare, is there room for a change in the way that<br />
the levy is applied at all?<br />
PM: This debate seems to be running around the columns. Look, the<br />
Government has had a look at the health system every year it has<br />
been in office from the day Medicare was first set up. But there is<br />
nothing around at the moment to promote major changes, that warrant<br />
an increase in the levy.<br />
J: Mr Keating, can you categorically rule out any increase in the<br />
Medicare levy? </p>
<p>PM: I was saying, there is just nothing around that warrants a change to the<br />
levy of the kind described.<br />
J: What about a-phased increase similar to the tax rates?<br />
PM: Yes,' but you can ask me about every other tax in the system too. I<br />
mean, there is just no point in me trying to give you answers to them.<br />
J: You said earlier today that it was undecided..<br />
PM: No, no, no, not undecided about the Medicare levy. What the<br />
Expenditure Review Committee does every year is look at the health<br />
system because things change all the time and every year we look at<br />
the changes. I have seen in the last ten years the mechanical costs of<br />
pathology and diagnostic imaging drop enormously as we've seen<br />
miniaturisation and computerisation and medical science change the<br />
productivity of those tests so therefore we pay less. All those sorts of<br />
things are always under review.<br />
JL: So, can you rule out any rise?<br />
PM: You would like me to rule out every tax change and everything else.<br />
No, I don't make statements like that. There is nothing to rule it in, that<br />
is the point.<br />
J: Can you rule out an incremental change just 1.4 per cent for higher<br />
income; 1.8 per cent..<br />
PM: This has been tried on me before by people who have suggested that<br />
higher income earners should pay a higher levy I don't believe that<br />
and I have said that plenty of times.<br />
J: In Fremantle the Liberals are saying that Carmen Lawrence is going to<br />
be your puppet in Canberra rather than representing the people of<br />
Fremantle. What do you say to that?<br />
PM: That is the sort of partisan, biased nonsense you would expect from<br />
the Liberal party. That is what I say to that. Carmen Lawrence was<br />
Premier of this State, she has made a contribution to public life, as a<br />
woman in public life, which stands the test of any in the country and.<br />
she will be a great Western Australian representative in the national<br />
Parliament. Bear in mind that you already have the Minister for<br />
Finance from Western Australia in the Cabinet; you have got the<br />
Minister for Industry in the Cabinet; you have got the Assistant<br />
Treasurer and until recently you had the Treasurer Western Australia<br />
is well represented in the Cabinet of the Commonwealth. Dr Lawrence<br />
will join the caucus of the Government and may, of course, at some<br />
point join the Ministry. In which case she will end up an absolutely tiptop<br />
representative of this State. The Liberals can eat their tiny hearts<br />
out. The fact is, she will better represent West Australian interest than </p>
<p>3<br />
the sort of carping that goes on now by the Liberals under the claim of<br />
parochial interests.<br />
J: Mr Court seems to want to talk to you about _ Mabo. Perhaps he has<br />
painted himself into a corner and is looking for a way out, shouldn't<br />
you offer him that?<br />
PM: You can ask him is he going to drop his challenge to the High Court<br />
case. The answer is no, he is not. The fact is, if I see Mr Court any<br />
more than I've seen him then I will offer him bed and breakfast at the<br />
Lodge. Honestly, I keep bumping into him at lunch, at breakfast and<br />
everything else. I am a pretty reasonable person. I'm sitting for lunch,<br />
I can always take time off to discsuss Mabo or anything else.<br />
J: If he drops the challenge will you talk to him?<br />
PM: But he has never raised these questions with me. But if he drops the<br />
challenge he can then be part of the co-operative scheme. Remember<br />
this, this is a Commonwealth law carried by the House of<br />
Representatives and the Senate. It has been complied with by all<br />
other States bar Western Australia. If Western Australia complies the<br />
structure is set up for certainty, sense and a decency and the<br />
management of the native title issue.<br />
J: So the conditions are that you will talk to him if he drops theHigh<br />
Court challenge?<br />
PM: Just remember this, that I offered his government and his bureaucracy<br />
access to all of the Mabo discussions all last year and he would not<br />
participate. They would not send their bureaucrats to the multistate/<br />
commonwealth meetings.<br />
J: Prime Minister, by coincidence there has been, as of yesterday, as<br />
native title claim, a very nice stretch of the river front in the Fremantle<br />
46 dcfnate. -Have you been briefed -on that all<br />
PM: Howard Sattler asked me about it this morning. Who owns the land at<br />
this stage?<br />
J: I think it is public open space, but your view on that is quite<br />
coincidental, there seems to be..<br />
PM: Look, if there is any grant of interest by the State or dedication of the<br />
land that means that any native title claim is subordinate to that. That<br />
is what it means. But the thing is, this can be all decided in the<br />
Western Australian Supreme Court, if the Court government complies<br />
with the Commonwealth legislation. Otherwise it will be decided in the<br />
Federal Court of Australia. Again, the Federal Court of Australia will<br />
hear it here in Perth. </p>
<p>J: spending a lot of time with Carmen Lawrence on this particular<br />
campaign. Is that because you are worried about your low popularity<br />
or the Labor party is worried about your low popularity in WA?<br />
PM: We have got to get past the point where the Liberals feed you dunce<br />
lines and you all repeat them. You are paid to think, to be jolly, to be<br />
looking at the big scene and to pick the right things out, not to be<br />
parrots for the Liberal party. The fact is, I am seeing Carmen at a car<br />
plant later. I saw her yesterday. She and I have had a good<br />
discussion about the issues here. In campaigning for her today I have<br />
dealt with Commonwealth issues on a large rating and popular radio<br />
program. Last night she and I shared our campaigning responsibilities<br />
and she went to one function and I went to another at the Notre Dame<br />
University Graduation and we are doing the things which have to be<br />
done in a campaign. We don't have to be walking side by side<br />
everywhere to put the Commonwealth interests. This is nonsense stuff<br />
from the Liberals. Where are the Liberals today? Here is Peter Reith<br />
saying, look, we have had a gut full of all of this he said about the<br />
Liberal party leadership and we have got this what you might call play<br />
ground rules. Andrew has had two goes, so I want two goes says<br />
John Howard. Andrew has had two goes, so little Johnny Howard gets<br />
two goes. Hewson is saying no, no, no it is still my go. Reith is<br />
saying, look, we have had a gut full of the whole lot.<br />
The truth is the Liberal party doesn't know where it stands in policy;<br />
where it stands philosophically; Malcolm Fraser said a week ago in a<br />
national newspaper none of us know a year after Fightback was<br />
dropped any policies that the Liberal party stands for. The Liberal<br />
party today has leadership troubles because it has no policies. Now,<br />
here we are in a by-election four by-elections in fact with the other<br />
major party, Coalition parties, having no policy and a dispute about the<br />
leadership and they are worried about whether I am here walking<br />
shoulder to shoulder with Carmen. They have major troubles.<br />
J: Would you be expecting then a swing on Saturday?<br />
PM: I think Dr Lawrence has a huge standing in Western Australia. I think<br />
the Labor party is very privileged to have her as a federal candidate. I<br />
think the people of Fremantle will be well served by her as the Member<br />
for Fremantle and I expect her to be returned well. Now, Dr Hewson<br />
has just taken a punch on the nose in the Werriwa by-election and now<br />
we will see what will happen in Fremantle, but I bet you pounds to<br />
peanuts, it will only lift the debate within the Liberal party about how<br />
much longer Dr Hewson stays.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
