<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11018</transcript-id>
    <title>12 May 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                   RADIO INTERVIEW WITH MATT PEACOCK &amp;#150;                 AM PROGRAMME                                                  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: budget, surplus, unemployment, private health insurance,</p>
<p> research and development, tax package</p>
<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, welcome to AM. Are you having sleepless nights wondering</p>
<p> how to spend the pots of money?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. I thought Peter's introduction was a touch over the top.</p>
<p> I don't think it's fair to categorise the situation as rolling</p>
<p> in money. Surpluses don't sit in the bank. They are used to pay</p>
<p> off debt and it's very important that we pay off our debt and</p>
<p> that we set ourselves up as a debt free nation at a federal government</p>
<p> level in the 21st Century.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Once you sell Telstra you'd be able to do that and still have</p>
<p> several billion left over for compensation for the GST would you not?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you've always got to be on guard against hubris and complacency</p>
<p> and smugness. The world is a very unpredictable place economically.</p>
<p> The outlook at the moment is very good, but things can change. Things</p>
<p> could change in the United States, things could change in Europe.</p>
<p> I don't think they will, but they could. And a sensible government</p>
<p> doesn't spend beyond its capacity. A sensible government, to</p>
<p> use an old expression, always keeps something in store for a rainy</p>
<p> day. A sensible government always recognises that you should have</p>
<p> a bit in reserve in case things turn against you. And that has been</p>
<p> one of the pieces of reasoning behind the construction of this budget.</p>
<p> Look, let me make it very clear, economic times in Australia generally</p>
<p> are very good. They're the best they've been for 30 years.</p>
<p> Nobody denies that. But there are still pockets of underprivileged</p>
<p> in our society, and there is still areas of rural Australia which</p>
<p> are doing it very hard. And I want the people in those areas that</p>
<p> I understand that and that the relatively boom conditions of some</p>
<p> parts of Australia are not being universally and uniformly shared</p>
<p> throughout our nation. And it's one of the constant challenges</p>
<p> of my Government to communicate an understanding of that to people</p>
<p> in the bush, and to bring about measures that help them and promote</p>
<p> their enjoyment in future in time of the economic prosperity of the</p>
<p> rest of country.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>And what's the message to the unemployed in this country? Work</p>
<p> for the dole and wait for Telstra and the GST?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. I think the message for the unemployed is that it is lower now</p>
<p> than it's been for ten years. If you have continued strong growth</p>
<p> we can maintain the gains of the past two years. But if you want further</p>
<p> major reductions in unemployment which we want, then we need to further</p>
<p> reform the labor market. Get rid of our stupid unfair dismissal laws,</p>
<p> entrench youth wages so that the cost of employing young people doesn't</p>
<p> go up and therefore you can employ more of them. And that immediately</p>
<p> throws an onus on the Labor Party and the Democrats in the Senate</p>
<p> to stop obstructing legislation which will further reduce Australia's</p>
<p> unemployment level.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Your Government says it's for choice. What choice does a young</p>
<p> employed person have today in terms of their health insurance? You're</p>
<p> saying insure now or pay the whole bill when you get sick when you</p>
<p> are older.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You're probably saying to a young bloke in his late 20s, take</p>
<p> out private health insurance now so that when you're 45 and have</p>
<p> a family, and you might feel a greater need, it won't be as expensive</p>
<p> as if you leave it until then to join a private health fund. And I</p>
<p> think what we are essentially doing is providing a further incentive</p>
<p> for young healthy people to enter private health insurance at an earlier,</p>
<p> at age 30 or less. We're going to provide a period of grace at</p>
<p> 12 months so that anybody between ,say 30 and 65, who's not in</p>
<p> a private health insurance fund can join during that 12 month grace</p>
<p> period without additional penalty through higher premium. And then</p>
<p> it will only be after that that the rise in premiums will begin to</p>
<p> take affect in relation to people who haven't joined by the time</p>
<p> they've reached the age of 30.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Is this the last major change that you think will be necessary to</p>
<p> save the private health funds?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it is a further major structural reform. You can never say in</p>
<p> an area like health that you have stopped reform. It's always</p>
<p> silly to say this is the last thing we're ever going to do.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But you've done a lot for the private health funds.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We have. But we're not doing it for the funds, we're doing</p>
<p> it for the system. And the public system needs a private system. Everybody</p>
<p> says to me, State governments, Labor, everybody says to me that you</p>
<p> need to get more people into private health insurance so as to help</p>
<p> the public sector  to help Medicare. And everything we are doing,</p>
<p> it's not designed to help the private health funds. We have no</p>
<p> special brief for them. But we are trying to get more people into</p>
<p> private health insurance because we think it's good for the system.</p>
<p> That's why we provided a 30% universal tax rebate, that's</p>
<p> why we have provided this lifetime health cover. And I'm very</p>
<p> pleased at the reaction to it. It's a good solid ongoing futuristic</p>
<p> policy. It's not a gimmick, it's not a quick fix, it's</p>
<p> not a band-aid solution. It's something that over time will build</p>
<p> in the value that it adds to the strength of the health insurance</p>
<p> system.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Now you also appear to have picked health as the big winner for research</p>
<p> and development. What about other areas of research and development,</p>
<p> in industry? I mean that's at a serious stage of decline isn't</p>
<p> it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well let's just come to that in a moment. But you can't</p>
<p> just slide over what we're doing in health and medical research.</p>
<p> We are doubling, doubling it. Not increasing by 50% but doubling the</p>
<p> amount of money that this country will spend on health and medical</p>
<p> research.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Picking it as a winner?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we are very good at it. I mean very good, for a nation of 18</p>
<p> million people, we are world class when it comes to the quality of</p>
<p> our doctors and our medical researchers. And as we go into the 21st</p>
<p> Century, we really do have to take ourselves to the forefront of some</p>
<p> of these leading edge areas. If we are ready to continue to grow and</p>
<p> expand and prosper, we have got to build on our strengths. And one</p>
<p> of our strengths is that we are very good at medical research. We</p>
<p> have superb doctors, wonderful surgeons, dedicated researchers. So</p>
<p> we're going to double the funding, that's another $600 million</p>
<p> over a period of 6 years. I think the first 25 years of the next century</p>
<p> is going to see an influence of gene technology for example, comparable</p>
<p> to the influence of information technology perhaps during the last</p>
<p> 25 years of this century. And we have to be right up there at the</p>
<p> front. And what this budget has done in relation to the money for</p>
<p> health and medical research, and the commitment to gene technology,</p>
<p> what we have done is to make it possible for this country to be a</p>
<p> world class player and performer, and for the great intellectual asset</p>
<p> that we have. This budget is very much about husbanding and building</p>
<p> on the intellectual capital and the intellectual resources of our</p>
<p> nation. Very much about that and that is very much about the future.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Some of the reaction this morning though from the players in R&amp;D</p>
<p> is quite critical. It's saying well you've got health, yes,</p>
<p> and you've doubled that, but there's a whole area of industrial</p>
<p> research and development. I mean BHP just cut it in half. Are you</p>
<p> concerned about the decline in R&amp;D in other areas?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well you can always provide more in the industrial area, and we provided</p>
<p> additional support in our investing for growth statement in 1997.</p>
<p> But our aim last night was very much to focus on those areas of health</p>
<p> and medical research where traditionally the government has carried</p>
<p> the lion's share of the responsibility.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Now if I could hark back to the points made by Peter Martin at the</p>
<p> start of this programme, we have the GST package of course, but here</p>
<p> we have this huge surplus. I mean if the taxation system is not broke,</p>
<p> why fix it. You know, it's hardly an eroding tax base with that</p>
<p> surplus is it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt, we have a strong economy now, we have a big surplus now, and</p>
<p> therefore out of that surplus we're able to pay debt. Because</p>
<p> we reformed the system a few years ago, today's strength is a</p>
<p> product of yesterday's reform. Tomorrow's strength will</p>
<p> be a product of today's reform. And if we want to protect our</p>
<p> position we need to do better in exporting, and you can do better</p>
<p> in exporting through a GST, you take $4.5 billion of our exports.</p>
<p> We want to make our domestic industries more competitive against imports</p>
<p> and you can do that through a GST, you take $10.5 billion off the</p>
<p> costs of doing business in this country. A huge nation like Australia</p>
<p> should help its farmers by reducing the fuel bill by $3.5 billion</p>
<p> which we'll do through a GST. And the nugget of gold in that</p>
<p> tax reform package is that 80% of all Australian taxpayers will be</p>
<p> on a top rate of 30% or less. The only way you can deliver that is</p>
<p> through the GST reform. I mean I can't think of anything better</p>
<p> for a booming optimistic forward looking Australia in the 21st</p>
<p> Century than to have a tax system where you say to 80% of people,</p>
<p> you can work and know that you've got a top marginal rate of</p>
<p> 30 cents in the dollar. Now that is a huge injection of incentive</p>
<p> to middle Australia.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>And you're going to need a huge injection of enthusiasm from</p>
<p> the sounds of things from Senator Brian Harradine to get his vote.</p>
<p> Let's hear what he had to say.</p>
<p>SENATOR HARRADINE:</p>
<p>I must say how I feel, I feel that I, because of what I did last</p>
<p> year, have let families down. But I did so only after being given</p>
<p> quite clear assurance that there would be adequate compensation. There</p>
<p> was no mention, and in my mind no thought, that it would be tied in</p>
<p> with the GST package.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>That was Senator Harradine talking about what he says was a promise</p>
<p> by you to compensate low-income families over the youth allowance.</p>
<p> Whose idea was it to tie it to the GST vote?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm not going to get into a public dialogue with any of</p>
<p> my colleagues surrounding the GST.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But he doesn't sound like a happy man.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Matt, I'm not....if I have something to say to Brian</p>
<p> Harradine, or indeed any Senator, I'll do so to them. The Government</p>
<p> keeps its promises, I keep my promises. Last night we delivered every</p>
<p> single promise we made to the Australian people in the last election.</p>
<p> But beyond that I'm not going to respond on your or any other</p>
<p> programme to anything that Brian or anybody else has said in relation</p>
<p> to that particular issue.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>But presumably you'll be meeting with him very soon. You've</p>
<p> only had, what, two or three weeks, sitting weeks left before the</p>
<p> deadline of June the 30th.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Matt I meet lots of people.</p>
<p>PEACOCK:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thanks very much for joining us.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
