<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24008</transcript-id>
    <title>Commonwealth Science Council brings scientists and business leaders together to collaborate</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/11/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth Science Council will hold its first meeting today, bringing together the nation’s most eminent scientists and business people to provide advice on boosting Australia’s prosperity and competitiveness.</p>
<p>The Council is one of the foundation initiatives of the Commonwealth Government’s <em>Industry Innovation and Competitiveness Agenda</em>.</p>
<p>The Council will provide advice on strategies to ensure our research effort addresses national priorities and sharpens incentives for collaboration between research and industry.</p>
<p>It will focus on science as the catalyst for industry growth and efforts to further capitalise on our areas of competitive strength, foster stronger links between business and science and boost the commercial returns from Australia’s extensive research portfolio.</p>
<p>The Government is consulting with industry and researchers to ensure the annual $9.2 billion investment in science and research is targeted to deliver the best commercial outcomes and practical benefits, as well as to maximise private sector investment.</p>
<p>Australia ranks among the best in the world for scientific research and innovation, but falls away when compared with international competitors on measures of translating that research into commercial outcomes. The rate of collaboration between businesses and researchers is comparatively low.</p>
<p>Council members from the science and research sector are Professor Timothy Davis, Professor Ian Frazer AC, Professor Nalini Joshi, Professor Tanya Monro, Professor Brian Schmidt AC.</p>
<p>Council members from business and industry are Mr Ken Boal, Dr Michael Chaney AO, Dr Jackie Fairley, Mr David Knox, and Ms Catherine Livingstone AO.</p>
<p>The Council also includes the Ministers for Industry, Education and Health, as well as Australia’s Chief Scientist, Professor Ian Chubb AC.</p>
<p>27 November 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
