<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8838</transcript-id>
    <title>DR HEWSON ATTEMPTS TO CON MIDDLE AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008838.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4,<br />
iti J, STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RON P J KEATING NP<br />
DR HEWSON ATTEMPTS TO CON MIDDLE AUSTR&amp; LIA<br />
Last night Dr Howson attempted perhaps the most profound<br />
deceit so far in his campaign to win office. In debating<br />
-health care. he said the following:<br />
OK, so you have to make a decision as to where you<br />
cut off and at what point it is appropriate for<br />
people to start to take out private Insurance. We<br />
made the decision at $ 40,000 for a single and<br />
$ 50,000 f or a couple on the grounds that at those<br />
income levels they are getting very large taxc cuts<br />
and if they have got kids they are getting a<br />
doubling or a whatever their income level is, they<br />
are either getting a doubling or a 50 per cent<br />
increase in family allowances, We've got a lot of<br />
money targeted into the system, but to make the<br />
system work you've got to get people to take out<br />
private insurance. He should be required to take it<br />
out a" so should all the wealthy.<br />
In truth, Fightback says that under Dr Hewson's so-called<br />
" plan" faii16mFsQtith an income of $ 40-55,000 will receive<br />
an increase in their Family Allowance of 6 per cent.<br />
Families with a total ind6ie Wf_$ 55,000 or above will<br />
have their Family Allowance abolished. Not doubled or<br />
increased by 50 per cent as Dr Hewson said, but increased<br />
by just 6 per cent or abolished altogether.<br />
Only 15 per cent of families will have their Family<br />
Allowance doubled under Dr Hewson's plan. 100,000<br />
families will 1-a the allowance.<br />
Or Hewson appears to believe that families with a<br />
household income of S55,000 are wealthy. They will be<br />
forced into private health insurance or pay a penalty of<br />
$ 800 per annum. They will lose the Family Allowance.<br />
And they will pay a 15 per cent CST.<br />
Families in this-. middle income bracket would be<br />
significantly worse off under the Coalition's so-called<br />
. plan".<br />
7018 </p>
<p>It is a perfect example of the way in which their GST<br />
package will attack Australian living standards and our<br />
way of life and Dr Hewson'sa remarks last night are a<br />
perfect example of the lengths they will go to in their<br />
efforts to disguise this fact.<br />
Dr Howson says he has a plan. It is the wrong plan. It<br />
is not the plan he says it is. Everything Dr Hewson says<br />
should be checked against the reality of his intentions<br />
most of which can be found in Fightback Mark 1.<br />
SYDNEY 8 March 1993 7019 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
