<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4928</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/12/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004928.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 17 DECEMBER 1978<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
I would like to talk to you tonight about the National Wage Case<br />
decision bought down by the Arbitration Commission last Tuesday.<br />
The Commission has decided to grant in full the wage increase<br />
of 4 percent sought by the trade unions at the hearings.<br />
This decision to award the 4 percent flow-on is the worst<br />
possible Christmas present that could be made this year to the<br />
unemployed. How long is it going to take before trade union<br />
leaders and the Arbitration Commission come to understand that<br />
price operates in the market for labour as it operates for<br />
everyth,, ing else.<br />
When there is too much of any commodity in the market and the price<br />
is raised then the quantity sold must fall. The tragedy in<br />
this case is that the commodity we are talking about is labour<br />
the lives and wellbeing of people. If there are more<br />
people than jobs and the cost of employing people goes up then it<br />
becomes harder to find work.<br />
What prudent business manager would raise the price of his<br />
product when it is already hard to sell? Yet, that is what has<br />
happened just now.<br />
The Government argued against any increase at all based on an<br />
irrefutable proposition first put forward by a Labor Government<br />
Treasurer some years ago, that one man's way increase is another<br />
man's job. There is no worse time for this decision to be made<br />
than when tens of thousands of school leavers are coming onto<br />
the labour market.<br />
Already as a result of trade union activity over the past few years,<br />
wage prices for these youngsters are so high that they constitute<br />
a positive deterrent to employers. Young men and women entering<br />
the workforce for the first time could once acquire the experience<br />
they needed at comparatively low wages. But for some time, it<br />
has been starkly apparent that many employers consider they are<br />
unable to get a reasonable return from unskilled staff at<br />
present salaries. / 2 </p>
<p>Now these salary levels have been raised by another 4 percent<br />
as 200,000 school leavers are about to start their search<br />
for jobs.<br />
The President of the Arbitration Commission, Mr Justice Sir<br />
John Moore, has awarded the full flow-on of 4 percent in a<br />
climate of concern about the growing level of strike activity.<br />
With clear signs that some trade union leaders are unwilling<br />
to accept wage restraint he has said that if the number of<br />
disputes continued to grow it would throw into question the<br />
future of the present system of national wage case hearings<br />
before the Arbitration Commission.<br />
It is a topsy-turvy world when the trade unions embark on a<br />
campaign of action which hits at the ability of industry to<br />
provide jobs for the trade unions' own members.<br />
The Gover ' nment is calling for a report as a matter or urgency<br />
on how wage fixing at these hearings can be made consistent<br />
with the Government's economic aims, and particularly with the<br />
aim of increasing employment opportunities.<br />
Because the States are also involved in this wage fixing process<br />
they have been asked to cooperate. Their wage fixing tribunals<br />
often leap-frog Commonwealth tribunals and the results can be<br />
serious. In the meantime, let me emphasise that the Government remains<br />
determined to continue the fight against inflation, a fight<br />
which is having results in reduced inflation, lower interest<br />
rates and developing business confidence.<br />
Indeed, a short while ago the Confeasration of Australian Industry<br />
and the Bank of New South Wales reported that manufacturing activity<br />
strengthened markedly in the last three months of the year,<br />
with most of those taking part in the survey saying it was their<br />
best three months for four years.<br />
The struggle of the past three years against the excesses which<br />
the Government inherited at the end of 1975 is one which must<br />
continue if economic recovery is to be consolidated. Wage restraint<br />
is essential to raise the level of job activity and to fight<br />
unemployment without a resurgence of inflation.<br />
I can only call on the trade union leaders to show restraint in the<br />
interests not only of their own trade union members, but of the<br />
nation as a whole, in particular in the interests of those who<br />
are at present unem-loyed. Their success at the last National<br />
Wage Case Hearings can help no-one. It harms the young and<br />
adds to the ranks of the unemployed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
