<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10423</transcript-id>
    <title>Ministerial Changes </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/07/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010423.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Honourable Geoff Prosser MP has resigned from the Ministry today. His resignation letter and my response are attached.</p>
<p>I thank Geoff Prosser for the work he has done for the Coalition, both as a Minister and before that as Shadow Minister for Finance.</p>
<p>Responsibility for small business matters will now be assumed by Mr Peter Reith who will retain his responsibility for Industrial Relations and will become the Minister for Workplace Relations and Small Business.</p>
<p>The transfer of the small business responsibility to a senior Cabinet Minister emphasises the Government's strong belief that small business has a critical role to play in the employment and economic future of Australia.</p>
<p>Mr Reith's role as Minister assisting the Prime Minister in Public Service Matters will be assumed by Dr David Kemp MP, Minister for Schools, Vocational Education and Training.</p>
<p>Senator Chris Ellison of Western Australia will be the new Minister. He will become the Minister for Customs and Consumer Affairs. He will also have the additional responsibility of Minister assisting the Attorney General. His particular focus in that role will be the Justice aspects of the Attorney General's portfolio.</p>
<p>In recognition of Mr Reith's increased responsibilities, Mr Alan Cadman MP will become his Parliamentary Secretary. Mr Reith will retain his duties as Leader of the House.</p>
<p>Mr Neil Andrew MP, the Member for Wakefield will be the new Chief Government Whip.</p>
<p>Mrs Trish Worth MP will become the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Health in place of Senator Ellison.</p>
<p>Mr Peter Slipper MP, Member for Fisher in Queensland, will replace Mrs Worth in her former role as Government Whip.</p>
<p>11 July 1997</p>
<p>(see attached PDF for letters - <a href="http://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/transcripts/00010423.pdf">http://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/transcripts/00010423.pdf</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
