<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8380</transcript-id>
    <title>DOORSTOP BY THE HON P.J. KEATING MP, PRIME MINISTER WEDNESDAY 15 JANUEARY 1992, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/01/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008380.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER]<br />
DOORSTOP B~ Y THE HON P. J. KEATING MP, PRIME MINISTER<br />
WEDNESDAY 15 JANUARY 1992, !-ELBOU:. NE<br />
PM: The discussions have been very productive and<br />
enthusiastic. I think that people want the economy to<br />
get back to growth, they want growth planned, they want<br />
things which imporve and build on the general<br />
improvements in the economy over the last decade. many<br />
believe that there are a lot of fundamental strengths in<br />
the economy that will come out quite strong when we can<br />
come out, but they want leadership on the real issues<br />
and the real issues are growth, restoration of growth<br />
and employment, a recovery, and adding to our<br />
fundamental structural strengths and there have been<br />
some good ideas proposed. I think I~ f anyone listens<br />
well, and in public life you have to be a reasonable<br />
listener, that there is a lot of obvious stuff said but<br />
there is always the odd little jewel that falls out end<br />
if you're alert you can find it.<br />
The Government is working in this statement in a<br />
framework, obviously the framework we have worked in<br />
from the 80s was to internationalise Australia, to<br />
globalise our markets but what we want to do now is<br />
engender a ' recovery but do it in a way that adds to our<br />
structural strengths and so even though we are working<br />
in a framework and we have our own ideas, those ideas<br />
can be complemented and added to by the practical.<br />
experience of people in Australian business and that's<br />
why this process has occurred and I think it is going to<br />
be a very valuable one.<br />
J: Mr Keating, any jewels today?<br />
PM: A couple of things. A couple of good things.<br />
J: Mr Keating the business people all seem to be prepared<br />
for extra spending, does that fit in to your framework?<br />
PM: Let's be clear about this, there was not spending<br />
greater than the tax cuts we provided in the 1980s,<br />
middle 80s and late 80s, to hold the inflation rate<br />
which we succeeded in doing. We went through a boom<br />
without wages taking of f via the 1989 $ 6 billion tax<br />
cuts. In other words, the surplus was not ñ mnmutible.<br />
Likewise, nor is the deficit depending though upon what<br />
is responsible and sensible, what is cyclical and what </p>
<p>-2<br />
is structural, these are the qualitative things both<br />
quantative and qualitative, that the government will<br />
keep its eye on. I mean this is the most experienced<br />
fiscal group in Australia's long constitutional history.<br />
Nearly a decade of the one group of people stewarding<br />
Commonwealth fiscal policy and we are going to do it<br />
very carefully.<br />
J: Will you be seeking any of f-setting savings Mr Keating<br />
towards spending<br />
PM: Well, they are all policy choices for the Cabinet, and<br />
for the specialised gruop of Ministers these matters<br />
have not been determined at this stage.<br />
J: But spending cuts are a possibility?<br />
PM: Well, everything is a possibility.<br />
J: Mr Keating will tomorrow's meetings be a mirror image of<br />
today, or does it move on a notch flow?<br />
PM: Well they will be different people from various<br />
different other walks of life including the trade<br />
unions.. But there is a tremendous amount of pride in<br />
what woh have achieved as a structural change, I mean<br />
most of' these pople today have remarked about that,<br />
about how their business is now more productive, even<br />
though the squeeze has made them more productive, that;' s<br />
unfortunately led to lay-off s by many of them, but the<br />
outcoinw has been more productive companies ready to<br />
pick up on any roll that comes through the economy, they<br />
want the economy to spring back into activity, so do we,<br />
it's about trying to find the beat way of doing it.<br />
J: Do you think they are relying too much on wanting the<br />
Government to kick-start the economy, they are not doing<br />
enough themselves?<br />
PM: No I don't think so. A decade ago such a conversation<br />
would have been complaints about protection not enough<br />
of it, complaints about wages. What we saw Is what I<br />
think is what we predicted. valuable contributions by<br />
people who are wide-eyed and constructive and trying to<br />
put sensible and constructive proposals which the<br />
Government ' can do. I mean it is a very nice<br />
constructive quality to the discussion.<br />
J: Mr Keating, what is the prospect of a wage tax trade of f<br />
being included in the statement?<br />
PM: Well it is too early to say, and the hard news game<br />
which I know you are all in, it's too early to say. The<br />
Government will just have to consider its position on<br />
all these matters on inflation, the inflation proopects,<br />
activity, therefore wages, wages prospects, etc. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
J: Mr Keating, are you disappointed that two major opinion<br />
polls show your approval rating to be a record low?<br />
PM: Well, I had not expected to be bouncing out in this<br />
climate with a gaggle of polls sort of announcing my<br />
entrance to the Prime Ministerial stage, but I've<br />
always been best fighting from behind, I've always felt<br />
uncomfortable out in front. It generally slows me down<br />
and while I don't want to be obviously too far behind,<br />
being behind for me is a positive stimulus.<br />
J: Does it surprise you that your<br />
PM: Not really, I don't think. Not really.<br />
J: Mr Keating, is the Government prepared to reconsider<br />
the Coronation Hill decision?<br />
PM: No we have not. The general view of the Cabinet was<br />
that it should not be reconsidered.<br />
J: Mr Keating, the upturn has now been delayed. When is<br />
it your hope and expectation that we'll see reasonable<br />
signs of the economy coming good?<br />
PM: Obviously, the earlier the better in 1992.<br />
J: What are your expectations?<br />
PM: Well, it would be foolhardy for me to be nominating<br />
turning points and then you would be scoring off the<br />
days and weeks. You know I've been around for too long<br />
for that sort of stuff. We'll be trying to engender a<br />
recovery as quick as possible. One thing is for sure,<br />
nobody believes, as far as I know, certainly no one<br />
said to us, that what Australia needs to help itself iLs<br />
a new tax. I mean it would be a novel twist of<br />
priorities if we thought what Australia needed now in a<br />
recession Was just to give it something to go on with,<br />
it was a tax on its food, a tax on its clothing and to<br />
belt up its inflation rate. No one, of course, was<br />
advocating that.<br />
J: Is there a sense of desperation from the talks today at<br />
all?<br />
PM: I think a sense of well placed and good natured<br />
optimism but with cautious optimism.<br />
J: In reality Mr Keating, did you actually hear anything<br />
that you hadn't considered before in all your years<br />
Treasurer?<br />
PM: Yes, a couple of things.<br />
J: special treatment for the States? </p>
<p>PM: Well no, all States will be treated we will be<br />
treating the Commonwealth as a Commonwealth and all<br />
States: equitably. But I do think that Victoria has<br />
taken a large brunt of the recession and confidence<br />
levels, and activity levels are lower in Victoria. I<br />
have said this often. This is still true.<br />
J: Does this justify some special help?<br />
PM: Not particularly, but it justifies consideration about<br />
the State of the economy and Victoria in particular.<br />
J: How about tarriff levels, is there a need to wind back<br />
PM: No, I don't think so and they are phased. They are<br />
predictable and the change in the exchange rate of late<br />
will only, if you like, soften the impact of the<br />
reduction.<br />
J: There is no question of hurting<br />
PM: Well, that might be true but the fact is it is not<br />
hurting the export industries who have got the monkey<br />
of protection off their back. It's not hurting, it's<br />
helping them.<br />
J: Prime Minister, can you give us some scope of<br />
responsible fiscal stimulus might be?<br />
PM: No I can't, and that's something it is very early<br />
days but it was very important for us, I think, to take<br />
the opportunity to say to people who are at the<br />
coalface, what do you think about this?, what's your<br />
view?, give us some of your thoughts. We are working<br />
in this framework, if you have got general ideas about<br />
where we want to go but if you can add to that we would<br />
appreciate it particularly if it fits into our<br />
framework and I think it has been well worth doing.<br />
J: Was the anecdotal evidence you got today generally<br />
gloomier than official forecasts?<br />
PM: No. People think the economy is flat, not falling<br />
further, but flat off a generally low base and they<br />
want to see a pick up in a domestic economy as quickly<br />
as possible as we do. They are not into ideology, they<br />
are in-to a practical purposeful shift of activity in<br />
employnent.<br />
J: Do you have any problem with the risk of over<br />
stimulating?<br />
PM: Not off these low levels of activity I don't think but<br />
that's within reason, of course. But again, I remind<br />
you of eight years of fiscal stewardship by this<br />
Governent, I mean it is without </p>
<p>J: How soon will we see<br />
PM: Well that's one of the things we will be considering<br />
obviously in the course of these approval processes.<br />
J: Jewels more regularly during that period?<br />
PM: Well I did, I was always a good listener. You have to<br />
be in public life to be a reasonable listener. I have<br />
met a lot of people in business, in fact at my luncheon<br />
meeting two of them were reminding me of a discussion I<br />
had a year earlier with a very similar group, two of<br />
the members of which were common around the same themes<br />
at a dinner I had at Pacific Dunlop.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I did a lot of it. I saw a lot of business groups,<br />
interest groups while I was Treasurer. But that's to<br />
say I thought it was my responsibility to develop these<br />
ideas myself within frameworks from things I heard and<br />
within the general framework the Government was working<br />
in.<br />
J: What's the theme of today then, you have your own main<br />
framework and they'll just add to it?<br />
PM: No, the Government is obviously working in a framework,<br />
but the framework is now the one most Australian<br />
businesses are working in and therefore they are not<br />
coming at you or looking for increased protection, they<br />
are not: coming at you with complaints about wages.<br />
There's a commonality in the framework now so therefore<br />
we are very receptive to things which are put.<br />
J: Prime Minister, where most business you spoke to today<br />
mentioned depreciation and some mentioned special<br />
investment allowances. Are you disposed towards<br />
measures like that?<br />
PM: Well I can't say I am. It's entirely reasonable they<br />
should mention them and therefore their things will be<br />
considered. Thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
