<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9437</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH DEBBIE SPILLANCE AND IAN ROGERSON, TRIPLE J, 6 DECEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/12/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009437.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
)( 03<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J<br />
KEATING MP, INTERVIEW WITH DEBBIE SPILLANE AND IAN<br />
ROGERSON, TRIPLE J, 6 DECEMBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
IR: It is about 10 minutes past 5 and we are coming to you live from the<br />
beautiful mezzanine area here at the Parliament House complex, and<br />
we are joined by a special guest now, Deb?<br />
OS: Yes, we have the Prime Minister Paul Keating we were calling him Mr<br />
Keating off-air, but on-air we are going to be incredibly familar and just<br />
call him Paul. After all, we are on first name terms with Slim Dusty,<br />
you know.<br />
PM: Well, why not?<br />
DS: We know all the legends on this program. Now Paul firstly, we have<br />
been listening to all your talk about Triple J, and the expansion we<br />
know what is in it for us what is in it for you guys?<br />
PM: Well I think what is in it for us is that the nation's young people get a<br />
network a broadcast network they wouldn't have otherwise had, they<br />
get the chance of innovation, to hear people put their views, to hear<br />
new music that's enough I think.<br />
IR: It's not part of the deal that we have to have Parliamentary Question<br />
Time at any stage, is it?<br />
PM: No. Well that's a sort of area of light entertainment that you are not<br />
required to have. There's enough coverage of that we have got a<br />
whole bunch of junkies in this building that cover that.<br />
IR: Now, of course that has been going on all day today, and it will go this<br />
evening, won't it? </p>
<p>PM: The real show is only on Mondays and Thursdays that's my show.<br />
But you are welcome to tune in and pick the highlights. You can ask<br />
Mr Laurie Oakes he will tell you what the highlights are. Or Mr<br />
Lyneham, he will know.<br />
DS: I must admit that we are pretty relieved at Triple J today that the<br />
Coalition didn't do anything about the leadership today, because we<br />
didn't want our announcement swamped, and so they have been very<br />
polite.<br />
PM: Yes, I thought this this morning there is a great danger that if they<br />
actually dump Alexander today he'll blot you right out.<br />
DS: Were you worried about Triple J not getting enough publicity?<br />
PM: I was. And I wanted to make sure that at least he made it through until<br />
tomorrow. And it looks like he is going to make it.<br />
DS: How much longer, do you think?<br />
PM: Well, he will get to tomorrow.<br />
IR: You were mentioning the fact that you were white hot just a day or so<br />
ago....<br />
PM: That is for Mr Howard. I have a special attachment, not to Mr Howard,<br />
for Mr Howard, and...<br />
DS: Where will you be putting the attachment in?<br />
PM: Well, there are a few obvious places. But the thing is he does bring<br />
out the best in me, I have got to say, and when he bobbed up in 1986<br />
and 1987, I made sure that I didn't miss him. And I will just give him a<br />
cheerio call to let him know that I am still there.<br />
DS: Give him something to look forward to, that is what I reckon...<br />
PM: I am. Give him some encouragement... let's bring him out...<br />
IR: It's a bit like Avon calling..<br />
PM: Absolutely. Ding dong it's Avon calling.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
