<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5630</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/08/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005630.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5: 00PM<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY AUGUST 9 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Di scussions which the Government is to hold this week with<br />
representatives of employer groups and the ACTU on Wednesday,<br />
followed by a special Premiers' Conference and Loan Council<br />
meeting on Thursday, will help to decide the direction of the<br />
Australian economy. For we stand at a critical point: In one<br />
direction there is a path to sustained prosperity, continued<br />
growth in employment opportunities and rising real living<br />
standards. In the other direction is a path back to the<br />
economic conditions we faced five or six years ago, with<br />
rapidly growing prices, rising unemployment and economic<br />
stagnation.<br />
As a result of the Government's policies, pursued steadfastly<br />
for nearly six years, the Australian economy now has an<br />
underlying strength which is the envy of other major industrial<br />
nations. In the yearto March, excluding the drought affected<br />
farm sector, the economy grew at a real rate of 5.6 per cent,<br />
a rate considerably higher than any of our major trading<br />
partners were able to achieve, and a rate which the OECD has<br />
predicted we can sustain or improve if our policies are<br />
maintained. Employment has also been growing rapidly, particularly in the<br />
last two years during which over 300,000 new jobs have been<br />
created, and the unemployment rate on a month by month basis<br />
has been lower throughout 1981 than in any of the previous<br />
four years.<br />
Our success in restoring the health of the economy has derived<br />
primarily from the pursuit of policies which have restored<br />
business confidence and our international competitiveness<br />
by reducing the rate of inflation. Our inflation rate of 8.8%<br />
in the year to June remains significantly below that of our<br />
major trading partners, but it will have to be lowered still<br />
further to keep us ahead, and the Government remains determined<br />
that reducing inflation should have the highest priority. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
One of the* many signs of the faith that now exists world-wide<br />
in Australia's economic strength and prospects is the increasing<br />
strength of the Australian dollar relative to the currencies<br />
of the countries with which we trade. It is particularly interesting<br />
to observe, for example, that the Canadian dollar is now worth<br />
only 72 Australian cents. But the confidence that the world<br />
has expressed in Australia's prospects, the real gains that we<br />
have made in recent years, can so easily be frittered away.<br />
It is the danger of that happening, particularly through a<br />
renewed burst of inflation caused by a wages explosion, that<br />
has led me to call for the top-level meetings during the coming<br />
week. To some extent, the very success of our economic policies have<br />
contributed to the wage pressures that exist, and the Governmenthas<br />
acknowledged the need for flexibility in the wage<br />
determination system. The Government is not against wage<br />
* increases as such, but in the interests of all Australians<br />
they. . have to be wage increases that industry can afford to<br />
pay . fithout reducing employment. In all of this, we have to<br />
think of those without jobs as well as those with them.<br />
What we are concerned about is excessive wage increases that<br />
can only harm other people.* The growth we now have in the<br />
economy has established the circumstances in which some<br />
employers feel they can give in to wage increases when<br />
otherwise they would not and when some unions feel in a<br />
strong position to bargain and demand more. But these pressures<br />
should be resisted.<br />
At the talks this week, the Government will be discussing<br />
the options that are open to us to resist those pressures,<br />
options which ultimately have to be argued out before the<br />
Arbitration Commission. I have noted that the ACTU President,<br />
Mr Dolan, has said he'" does not want wage earners to bear the<br />
full brunt of economic stability. I agree with him on that,<br />
but there are people at present without jobs who want to be<br />
wage earners, and I am sure he would want more people to be<br />
employed, as we would.<br />
I also ' want to make the point that throughout last year, wages<br />
increased by 13% to 14% while inflation was so quite<br />
plainly there was a very real increase in wages and living<br />
standards over the past 12 months. There are questions as<br />
to whether that was fairly shared amongst the community, or<br />
whether an undue proportion of it went to strong unions and their<br />
members. What about the unions that have not been able to argue<br />
their case so well because their bargaining power or ' clout' has<br />
not been great? It is not a question of wanting Australian working<br />
men and women to bear the brunt or pay the cost of economic stability,<br />
it is a question of establishing circumstances which are fair<br />
and reasonable, that will enable this country to capitalise<br />
on the enormous advantages that Australia has, and on the<br />
great gains that have been made since 1975. That is why an<br />
orderly system of wage determination and less industrial disputation<br />
is essential. / 3 </p>
<p>IL -3-<br />
Too much should not be expected of the discussions this<br />
week, for the history of industrial relations is a continuing<br />
history of human relations, and dramatic answers are unlikely<br />
to be found. What we can achieve is a clearer understanding<br />
of the options facing the country, the mutual responsibilities<br />
on all governments, on the ACTU, and on employers to make sure<br />
that we all put Australia first, to make sure that we all<br />
act as people belonging to one country which we are determined<br />
to build and make a better place for our children.<br />
4 -r li-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
