<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10553</transcript-id>
    <title>RECEPTION FOR THE CHINESE NATIONAL PEOPLE&#039;S CONGRESS CANBERRA - 6 MAY 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/05/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010553.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
RECEPTION FOR THE CHINESE NATIONAL PEOPLES' CONGRESS<br />
CANBERRA 6 MAY 1986<br />
Mr Peng Chong, and distinguished members of the delegation<br />
of the National Peoples' Congress of the Peoples' Republic<br />
of China.<br />
It gives me great pleasure to welcome you to Australia on<br />
behalf of the Government and people of Australia.<br />
Senator McClelland led an Australian Parliamentary<br />
delegation to China last year and was received by your<br />
National Peoples' Congress with the traditional hospitality<br />
for which the Chinese people are famous. I hope our<br />
hospitality will reciprocate in some part the kindness and<br />
generosity you showed the Australian delegation in China.<br />
Distinguished guests, Australia places considerable<br />
importance on the development of mutual beneficial relations<br />
with China. This view is not only shared by my government<br />
but by all major political parties of Australia, as I am<br />
sure my colleague the Leader of the Opposition will agree.<br />
Australia and China have made remarkable progress in the<br />
development of constructive friendly relations since 1972.<br />
I am pleased this progress has been accelerated under my<br />
Government in the past three years.<br />
When Premier Zhao visited Australia in April 1983 we began a<br />
new phase of co-operation. Premier Zhao and I agreed during<br />
my visit to China in February 1984 that we should work<br />
together to make the Australia/ China relationship a model<br />
for co-operative relations between countries of different<br />
political and economic systems.<br />
We have developed the concept of sectoral initiatives and<br />
the China Action Plan, both of which are designed to promote<br />
greater economic co-operation which takes advantage of the<br />
economic strength and requirements for growth in each<br />
country. Premier Zhao and I were able to agree in 1984 on the first<br />
of the sectoral initiatives, in Iron and Steel. We are<br />
continuing to develop this initiative as well as extending<br />
the concept to other important fields. These include<br />
non-ferrous metals, transport and woollen products. </p>
<p>At the same time we have not concentrated only on our<br />
economic relations. Both countries believe this<br />
relationship of genuine friendship and co-operation should<br />
be as broadly-based as possible. Apart from trade and<br />
commercial relations, we regard cultural, scientific,<br />
technological and sporting exchanges as essential elements<br />
of the relationship.<br />
Moreover, over the past few years we have developed a most<br />
productive dialogue on a wide range of regional and<br />
international issues of importance to both countries.<br />
The visit to Australia of General-Secretary Hu Yaobang in<br />
April 1985 was a high point in recent exchanges between our<br />
countries. I myself am looking forward to my visit to China in just<br />
under two weeks time, when I will be able to renew my valued<br />
friendships with senior Chinese leaders. I also look<br />
forward to seeing more of the diversity and achievements of<br />
China when I visit a number of important centres outside<br />
Beijing, including Chengdu [ Cheng-doo], Nanjing [ Nan-jing]<br />
and Xiamen [ See-ar-men].<br />
Parliamentary exchanges are a most important element in<br />
developing people-to-people contacts between our two<br />
countries. For this reason your visit is particularly<br />
welcome and I wish you a most successful, interesting and<br />
pleasant visit to Australia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
