<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3571</transcript-id>
    <title>PERTH AIRPORT STATEMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003571.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
56<br />
AUSTRALiA.<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 425<br />
27 December 1974<br />
PERTH AIRPORT STATEMENT<br />
The Prime Minister released the following statement<br />
on his arrival at Perth Airport this afternoon.<br />
" I have been appalled by the reports I have had of<br />
the loss of life and damage in Darwin.<br />
I am going to see the extent of the destruction and<br />
shall then consult with the Ministers who will be directly<br />
concerned with helping the citizens of Darwin and re-constructing<br />
their city. I have called a specLl Cabinet meeting in Sydney on<br />
Monday. I will make a statement after the Cabinet.<br />
I want to extend my sympathy to those who have suffered<br />
in Darwin and promise again that we will do all in our power<br />
to restore and re-build the city as soon as possible and help<br />
those who need our assistance."<br />
Mr. Whitlam flew immediately to Alice Springs where<br />
he will stay overnight. He will confer there with Mr. John<br />
Menadue, of the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet<br />
who will accompany him to Darwin tomorrow morning.<br />
Mr. Whitlam is due to leave Alice Springs at 6.00 a. m.<br />
tomorrow and is scheduled to arrive in Darwin at 8.05 a. m.<br />
He will spend the whole of the day in the Darwin area, returning<br />
to Mt. Isa at night. On Sunday, Mr. Whitlam will fly from<br />
Mt. Isa to Sydney where the special Cabinet meeting will be<br />
held on Monday.<br />
CANBERRA, AC. T.<br />
0 ' 4-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
