<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>18018</transcript-id>
    <title>Retirement of Barry Hall</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/2011</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I was sorry to hear the news today that Barry Hall will be retiring from AFL footy at the end of this season.</p>
<p>I want to take the opportunity to congratulate Barry on his achievements and wish him good luck for the rest of the season and in the next phase of his life.</p>
<p>Barry Hall has worked hard and earned great respect in the West.</p>
<p>Barry's been a proud competitor at three AFL clubs and Bulldogs fans have been proud to call him ours since 2010.</p>
<p>It was an honour to have Barry present me with a supporters' jumper at the start of this year.</p>
<p>Barry's kicked a century of goals in red white and blue  -  five on the weekend  -  and the pace he showed for his goal in the second quarter on Sunday makes me think he could play on forever. </p>
<p>I'm sure I'll see him on the field in one last finals campaign later this year.</p>
<p>Barry's life in footy has been through many phases  -  from a tearaway rookie, to ultimate success in 2005, and then playing on as a respected veteran in the West. </p>
<p>He has friends and fans at each of the clubs he's played for and has been a worthy servant of each.  </p>
<p>Very few footballers will equal Barry's achievements: more than 250 games at the elite level, four-time All-Australian, 2005 premiership captain for the Sydney Swans.</p>
<p>It's lovely to hear Barry talk about how he remembers growing up in Broadford, racing home from school, kicking the ball around the back paddock, pretending he was Simon Beasley, getting handballs from Doug Hawkins. </p>
<p>I'm sure tonight there will be children in back yards and back paddocks imagining themselves as Barry Hall, getting a handball from Matty Boyd.</p>
<p>Well done Barry. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
