<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40668</transcript-id>
    <title>Remarks at a morning tea with Australian Defence Force Personnel  Keswick Barracks</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>We have your local Minister for Defence Industry, Christopher Pyne, and the French Defence Minister - you know we’ve just signed here the inter-governmental agreement between the Commonwealth of Australia and the French Republic for the design and the build of the 12 submarines.</p>
<p>This is the largest single investment in our whole defence industry plan. It is critically important for the security of Australia and for our future growth as a first world, advanced, innovative economy at the cutting edge of technology.</p>
<p>This secures our nation’s future in every respect – vitally important. And it is wonderful to have this partnership with France. One hundred years ago, your forebears in the Australian Defence Forces were fighting in France with the soldiers of France and our allies to defend France’s freedom.</p>
<p>Today, you and your comrades-in-arms are serving with the servicemen and women of France to crush, destroy Daesh in the Middle East.</p>
<p>It’s a long history and this opens up a new era of collaboration, to go for half a century or more. It is a very historic day.</p>
<p>I know, speaking on behalf of Christopher and myself, and I’m sure the French Minister will echo this, we salute you, we thank you for your service. We understand the sacrifices that you and your families make.</p>
<p>I want to say to you again, as you’ve heard me say many times, in these Centenary years, we best honour the diggers of 1916 by supporting the servicemen and women, the veterans and their families of 2016.</p>
<p>Thank you for your service and I hope you all have a very happy Christmas. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
