<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3066</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO JAPAN AND CHINA</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/11/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003066.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES BY THE PRIME MINISTER,<br />
MR. E. G. WHITLAM, WEDNESDAY 7.11.73<br />
VISIT TO JAPAN AND CHINA<br />
I seek leave to make a brief statement on the visit by<br />
certain of my Ministerial colleaguesand me to Japan and China.<br />
The Ministerial delegation to Japan, for the second<br />
Australia-Japan Ministerial Committee, was the largest and<br />
most senior ever to represent Australia abroad. My visit to<br />
Peking was the first by any Australian Prime Minister. Both<br />
visits were marked by great warmth on both sides; both visits<br />
were characterised by frankness and firmness from both sides;<br />
both visits notably advanced the interests of Australia and<br />
our friendship and understanding with these two great neighbours,<br />
Japan and China.<br />
On the visit to Japan from 26 October to 31 October<br />
I was accompanied by the Minister for Overseas Trade, the Treasurer,<br />
the Minister for Primary Industry and the Minister for Minerals and<br />
Energy. On the visit to China from 31 October to 4 November<br />
I was accompanied by the Treasurer and the Minister for Northern<br />
Development. In both countries my colleagues and I were supported<br />
by senior officials.<br />
I firmly believe that the visit will prove to be of<br />
considerable importance and value to the whole of Australia.<br />
With Japan, we have both broadened and more clearly defined<br />
the Australian-Japanese relationship and formed a firm basis for<br />
its continuing and future development in the years ahead.<br />
In China I consider that my visit symbolised the successful<br />
ending of a generation of lost contact between Australia and the<br />
most populous nation on earth. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Japan is our major trading partner in the world and China<br />
is the only one of the world's five major powers with whiCh,<br />
until last December, we have not had any meaningful or regular<br />
official contact.<br />
In Japan, the talks with Prime Minister Tanaka and Foreign<br />
Minister Ohira, and the wide-ranging and very frank and<br />
substantial discussions at the Ministerial Committee Meeting,<br />
have broadened the Australian-Japaneseunderstanding which is vital<br />
to both countries.<br />
I believe that any misunderstanding that existed in Japan<br />
about the nature of the Government's policies on minerals and<br />
energy and on overseas investment have now been cleared away.<br />
Likewise, any uncertainties the Japanese may have felt about the<br />
reliability of Australia as a long-term supplier of the raw materials<br />
which are essential to Japan has also been dispelled.<br />
In Japan, too, I believe that valuable understandings have<br />
been reached about the long-term access for Australian primary<br />
products to the important and growing Japanese market.<br />
The exceptionally close and important relations between<br />
Japan and Australia are to be expressed in a broad bilateral<br />
treaty. Mr. Tanaka readily accepted my suggestion, and himself<br />
announced that the Treaty be called the Treaty of Nara bearing<br />
the title of Japan's ancient capital, which I also visited.<br />
It will be identified as the Nippon-Australia Relations Agreement<br />
NARA. Australian and Japanese officials will very soon begin<br />
detailed discussion on the Agreement.<br />
I believe the Treaty of Nara will be seen as one of the<br />
historic treaties which Australia will have entered intO. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
Honourable members will note that we have also agreed to<br />
enter into two further agreements with Japan a Cultural<br />
Agreement and an agreement on the protection of migratory and<br />
other birds as well as to conduct wide-ranging official discussions<br />
on a number of issues including access for agricultural products,<br />
tariffs, and minerals and energy matters, including uranium.<br />
We have also agreed to renew the Agreement on Commerce with Japan,<br />
which was last revised in 1963. There was a useful exchange of<br />
views on developments in Papua New Guinea in which that country's<br />
Minister for Defence and Foreign Relations, Mr. Maori Kiki,<br />
participated. I believe my visit to China was most valuable in restoring<br />
balance to our foreign policy and in diversifying our foreign<br />
relations. I had no less than 11 hours of formal talks with Premier<br />
Chou En-lai and over an hour with Chairman Mao Tsetung. As<br />
Honourable members will appreciate, in the extensive time accorded<br />
to me by Premier Chou the discussions extended over a very wide<br />
range of international issues of interest to both countries.<br />
I believe that we now have a much greater understanding<br />
of Chinese attitudes on these issues. I believe, too, that on the<br />
Chinese side, there is now a much clearer and first-hand understanding<br />
our policies. While there were areas of agreement, there were<br />
also issues on which our policies differed and, in such cases, I<br />
did not hesitate to put our position fully and frankly to my Chinese<br />
hosts. For example, I reaffirmed at the highest level the Australian<br />
Government's determined opposition to nuclear testing in the<br />
atmosphere. our differences on these and other matters were<br />
discussed on a basis of mutual respect.<br />
I believe that the warmth ot the reception I and my party<br />
received in Peking demonstrates that China like Japatn recognises,<br />
to a greater extent than some Australians may believe, the growing<br />
importance of Australia as a middle power, especially in the Asian<br />
and Pacific region. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
As Honourable Members will know, important and valuable<br />
arrangements were made for the sale to China of up to 300,000<br />
tons of sugar per year for a three to five year period commencing<br />
in 1975. Arrangements were also made for the active promotion of<br />
closer consultations between Australian and Chinese officials<br />
and for a program of visits in both directions. The Australian<br />
and Chinese Foreign Ministers are to exchange visits at times<br />
to be determined in 1974. It was also agreed that we should develop<br />
a planned program of cultural, scientific, and technological<br />
exchanges between Australia and China, and that representative<br />
missions in these fields would be exchanged in 1974.<br />
Honourable Members will be pleased to know that an<br />
understanding in principle was reached between the two sides<br />
on travel from China to Australia by relatives of Australian<br />
citizens of Chinese descent and Chinese citizens residing in<br />
Australia. This should facilitate family reunions.<br />
I believe that my visit will give new direction and<br />
increased momentum to our existing relationship with Japan and<br />
will lead to the development of a more meaningful relationship<br />
and a continuing dialoguewith China which, for so long, for<br />
much too long has been a closed book to this country.<br />
I would like to pay tribute in the Parliament to the tireless<br />
efforts of the Australian Embassies in Tokyo and Peking during our<br />
visit. The ambassadors and their staffs performed, under<br />
considerable pressure, in a manner of which Australia should be<br />
proud. I would also like to record here my appreciation of the<br />
objective and constructive advice tendered to my ministers and me<br />
by the senior officials who accompanied us from Australia.<br />
I table the Communique issued in Tokyo after my visit to<br />
Japan as Prime Minister, the Joint Communique adopted by thO<br />
Australia-Japan Ministerial Committee, my statement to that<br />
Committee setting out the Government's policy on foreign investment<br />
in Australia, and the Joint Press Communique issued in Peking on<br />
4 November. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
