<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11562</transcript-id>
    <title>Illicit Drugs Policy</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Royal Australasian College of Physicians suggested in its report released yesterday that government policy on illicit drugs primarily centres on law enforcement. In respect of current Federal Government policy, this suggestion is inaccurate.</p>
<p>While law enforcement is an essential component of the Government's Tough on Drugs strategy, this plan also emphasises prevention through education and treatment and rehabilitation.</p>
<p>With regard to current Government policy, the report cites figures from a 1992 United Nations document which stated that 84 per cent of government spending in response to illicit drugs was then dedicated to law enforcement, with the remaining 16 per cent going to treatment, rehabilitation and education.</p>
<p>The figures used are far too old to be meaningful in the current context. The Tough on Drugs plan which commenced in 1997, is worth $515 million. Under Tough on Drugs $303 million has been allocated for treatment, rehabilitation, research and education. This represents 59 per cent of total funds available - not 16% as claimed by the College.</p>
<p>Tough on Drugs has provided more than $60 million in grants go to non-government organisations to introduce and expand treatment and rehabilitation services across the country. We have also allocated $110 million to the diversion programme which gives drugs users the option of undertaking treatment and/or education rather than getting caught up in the criminal justice system.</p>
<p>The second, and equally important element of the Tough on Drugs plan involves educating young people and the wider community about the dangers of drugs and the benefits of a healthy lifestyle. Education is the key to preventing drug use by future generations.</p>
<p>The Federal Government's plan has also provided significant additional resources for law enforcement worth more than $210 million, or 41 per cent of the total funds allocated. Law enforcement initiatives continue to be an essential component of the strategy. The additional resources for law enforcement have resulted in an increase in the number and size of seizures across the country, particularly of heroin, cocaine and ecstasy.</p>
<p>Tough on Drugs is a comprehensive policy with a balance of approaches focussed on law enforcement, education and treatment and rehabilitation. It emphasises prevention and early intervention. It is an effective policy response to the scourge of illicit drugs within the Australian community.</p>
<p>The report by the College also supports the introduction of injecting rooms, and in certain circumstances, heroin trials. Heroin trials and/or injecting rooms remain unacceptable proposals to the Federal Government.</p>
<p>The 1999 World Health Organisation (WHO) commissioned evaluation of the Swiss heroin trial cast significant doubt over previous claims about the benefits of the Swiss trial.</p>
<p>The evaluation pointed to the fact that the Swiss trial included comprehensive social and psychological services.</p>
<p>Given the provision of the non-drug treatment and support, it cannot be concluded that it was the prescription of heroin that contributed to the improved the health and welfare of participants, as some have claimed.</p>
<p>The Federal Government also believes that the introduction of injecting rooms or a heroin trial or both would be damaging to the Australian community insofar as such a step would signal that illicit drug use is acceptable. It is far better to concentrate on supporting the provision of a range of prevention, treatment and rehabilitation services as the Government is doing.</p>
<p>The Tough on Drugs strategy is already helping many more people than injecting rooms or heroin trials ever could.</p>
<p>13 December 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
