<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4363</transcript-id>
    <title>MESSAGE TO EMPLOYER AND EMPLOYEE ORGANISATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004363.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PR 95ME M STEER<br />
FOR PRESS 14 APRIL 1977<br />
M4ESSAGE TO EMIPLOYER AND EM'PLOYEE ORGANISATIONS<br />
The following message is being sent to employer and employee<br />
organisations throughout Australia.<br />
" Australia has been grappling with high inflation rates for a<br />
number of years now. Although some progress has been made, we<br />
are still experiencing double digit wage and price increases.<br />
The persistence of inflation and the recognition of how it<br />
continues to sap the strength of our economy, has led to a<br />
dramatic and unprecedented initiative by the Commonwealth and<br />
State Governments.<br />
Meeting in Premiers' Conference in Canberra on 13 April, the<br />
Heads of the Commonwealth and all State Governments unanimously<br />
called for a three month halt in price and wage increases.<br />
The agreement signed by all Heads of Government is as follows:<br />
Prices and Incomes Restraint<br />
The Heads of the Commonwealth and all State Governments,<br />
meeting in Premiers' Conference in Canberra today,<br />
unanimously called for a three month halt in price and<br />
wage increases. They agreed that such restraint was<br />
urgently needed if Australia is to overcome its current<br />
economic problems.<br />
It was agreed that all Heads of Government will approach<br />
employer and professional organisations and put to them<br />
the proposal that their membership should voluntarily<br />
comm~ it themselves to a pause for a period of three months<br />
from increases in the prices of their goods and services.<br />
At the same time, all Heads of Governments will be making<br />
an approach to the ACTU and other employee organisations<br />
to seek a voluntary commitment to a three months pause<br />
from wage increases.<br />
Governments would not expect either the business organisations<br />
or the union organisations to agree to such voluntary restraint<br />
arrangements without agreement by the others. I Imnediately </p>
<p>-2<br />
Immediately following agreement to the proposal for a<br />
voluntary general pause from increases in prices and<br />
incomes, approaches would be made to the Arbitration<br />
Commission and the Prices Justification Tribunal for the<br />
implementation of the general pause.<br />
Governments would also use their influence and the powers<br />
available to them towards achieving a successful outcome.<br />
Governments will commit themselves to not increasing their<br />
own charges during the period of the pause. Local<br />
Government will be expected to do likewise.<br />
All Heads of Governments commit themselves to work for<br />
this voluntary pause. Upon its achievement, a further<br />
conference of Heads of Government will be held to consider<br />
what further steps should be taken.<br />
The Heads of Governments called on all members of the<br />
Australian community to give full support to this vital<br />
endeavour to help overcome inflation.<br />
M. Fraser Prime Minister<br />
Neville Wran Premier of New South Wales<br />
R. J. flamer Premier of Victoria<br />
J. Bjelke-Petersen Premier of Queensland<br />
D. A. Dunstan Premier of South Australia<br />
Sir Charles Court Premier of Western Australia<br />
1A. Neilson Premier of Tasmania<br />
I also add that my Government and the States are now taking all steps<br />
to achieve a successful outcome to our joint initiative. I regard it<br />
as essential that in the period while the necessary agreement of the<br />
relevant -parties is being sought, restraint is shown by all and that<br />
there be -no action to get in ahead of the three month pause which is<br />
~ proposed. The PJT has been requested to monitor prices in the community and to<br />
investigate any claims that increases in prices have occurred. The<br />
Tribunal waill be reporting on its monitoring.<br />
Pending agreement to these proposals, the Tribunal has also been asked<br />
to defer decisions on price increases as from today.<br />
In cases where the Prices Justification Act requires the Tribunal to<br />
make a decision during this period, companies are being asked to<br />
agree voluntarily to a deferment of decisions on these price applications<br />
Your co-op eration is vital to the success of these measures, and I<br />
look forward to hearing of your support for this crucial national<br />
initiative as soon as possible." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
