<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40229</transcript-id>
    <title>The Centre for Defence Industry Capability</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister, the Hon Malcolm Turnbull MP, Minister for Defence, Senator the Hon Marise Payne, and Minister for Industry, Innovation and Science, the Hon Christopher Pyne MP, today announced the new Centre for Defence Industry Capability (CDIC) will be headquartered in Adelaide.</p>
<p>The headquarters will both foster and drive innovation in the defence industry right across Australia and open up export opportunities.</p>
<p>A key initiative of the 2016 Defence White Paper, the CDIC will bring together the private sector, Defence and AusIndustry to transform the relationship between Defence and industry to help deliver the cutting-edge capability our armed forces require.</p>
<p>This is a 10-year, $230 million investment that will create more jobs and drive growth in Adelaide and across the country.</p>
<p>The CDIC will work with small-to-medium enterprises across Australia to promote defence industry competitiveness and guide the priorities across defence industry.</p>
<p>The Centre will also offer a range of advisory services including mentoring, defence market access, export facilitation and global supply chain development.</p>
<p>The Turnbull Government recognises that Australia’s defence industry’s capacity for innovation will be vital to maintain a world-class Defence Force.<br />
In addition to its Adelaide headquarters, the Centre will have a network of advisors in key locations across Australia to engage directly with industry.</p>
<p>South Australia is at the forefront of the Turnbull Government’s plan to renew Australia’s naval fleet, and create a world-class, sustainable naval shipbuilding industry. An innovative and competitive Australian defence industry is critical to support the delivery of major capability projects, including the Future Frigates and Future Submarines.</p>
<p>Innovation will drive greater growth and more jobs. This is essential to creating a 21st Century economy for Australia.</p>
<p>The CDIC, along with the Defence Innovation Hub and the Next Generation Technologies Fund announced in the Defence Industry Policy Statement will generate economic benefits, deliver jobs and encourage innovation across Australia.</p>
<p>The CDIC and the Innovation Hub will provide new ways for defence and industry to work together, and will ensure a closer alignment between industry’s investment in future skills and Defence’s capability needs.</p>
<p>Led by an advisory board comprising senior members of industry and Defence, the CDIC will commence operations in the second half of 2016 and receive $230 million in funding over the next decade.</p>
<p>To find out more about the CDIC visit <a href="http://www.business.gov.au/CDIC">www.business.gov.au/CDIC</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
