<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5306</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE AUSTRALIAN PETROLEUM EXPLORATION ASSOCIATION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/03/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005306.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4A16e1f FLLa<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FORMEDIA MONDAY, MARC /, Z4_<br />
ADDRESS TO THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PETROLEUM EXPLORATION ASSOCIATION<br />
In accepting the invitation to address you today, I am aware<br />
of the essential contribution which your association and its<br />
members can make to Australia's success in the decade ahead.<br />
Your enterprise and your initiative: will be central to ensuring<br />
that Australia's development in the 80s makes full use of our<br />
resource capacity.<br />
This is a potentially rewarding task.<br />
It involves daunting challenges of course, but then higher<br />
rewards always do.<br />
Each decade brings with it challenge and change.<br />
On top of high inflation and slower growth, the world is now<br />
caught up in the problems created by unstable oil supplies and<br />
the rapid rise in the real cost of liquid fuels.<br />
In this environment, there is a tendency to forget that at the<br />
beginning of the last decade, we were about to confront economic<br />
difficulties which subsequently challenged the capacity and the<br />
will of international leadership.<br />
The post war period brought with it unprecendented economic growth.<br />
It made possible a much wider availability of goods and services.<br />
It was attended by appropriate community attitudes of responsibility<br />
and restraint.<br />
All these brought new meaning to the word civilisation.<br />
But by the beginning of the last decade, ever-rising community<br />
expectations, unaccompanied by any corresponding commitment to<br />
productivity, were met by governmenis yielding to public spending<br />
demands with little regard for economic responsibility.<br />
At the same time, community attitudes were changing dramatically.<br />
The contribution to be made to community life by excellence and<br />
achievement gained only limited recognition. </p>
<p>-2<br />
The dedication to economic growth, which is essential if community<br />
demands are to be met, was itself under attack.<br />
In these circumstances it is hardly surprising that inflation was with<br />
US. Yet many nations and many leaders were slow to recognise the corroding<br />
effects of inflation, though Maynard Keynes had said in 1920:<br />
" There is no surer means of overturning the existing<br />
basis of society than to debauch the currency, the<br />
process engages all the hidden forces of economic<br />
law on the side of destruction and does it in a<br />
manner which no one man in a million is able to<br />
diagnose."<br />
Fortunately, time has enlarged our understanding of the diagnosis.<br />
Uncontrolled spending by government, fed by high taxation, irresponsibl<br />
wage increases and big deficits, was at the heart of the inflation<br />
problem. In other words, in the mid 70s, many developed economies suffered<br />
from weaknesses in management and from defects in policy.<br />
As if that were not enough to test the international economic<br />
will, the energy crisis of 1973 and 1974 brought another challenge<br />
for management and for policies.<br />
Oil consuming countries suffered from a trebling of price. s by oil<br />
exporting states at a time when we might have reasonably hoped for<br />
a progressive, less disruptive change in pricing policy.<br />
For the world~ as a whole, the switch from low to high cost energy<br />
overnight, helped transform a limited downturn in the world economy<br />
into a fullscale recession, and greatly worsened the already serious<br />
inflation position.<br />
The boom years were well and truly at an end. The spectre of higher<br />
unemployment faced many countries.<br />
Few nations could escape the onset of lower growth rates with the<br />
result that the confidence in and the capacity of our free society<br />
was challenged again.<br />
Of course, Australia was affected by these international events but<br />
the response of the government of the day was, in itself, a<br />
transparent crisis of management and policy.<br />
Because in many ways Australia was in a more fortunate position<br />
than most other countries.<br />
Our natural resources, significantly developed at the end of the<br />
our great endowments of energy; our long record of lower<br />
inflation; these should have provided the foundation for a relative<br />
improvement in Australia's position during these difficult years,<br />
Yet, we lost ground.<br />
Instead of the government working to counteract the effects of the<br />
first energy crisis, government policies compounded it so severely<br />
that all these years have been needed to recover the position we now<br />
enjoy of strong and still rising international competitiveness.<br />
Indeed, the importance of the first energy crisis was not<br />
grasped by many countries. </p>
<p>-3<br />
Some were slow to allow domestic fuel prices to reflect<br />
international prices. Others did not set in train the necessary<br />
action to reduce dependence on petroleum products. Too many<br />
governments accepted an air of dangerous complacency.<br />
The result was that many countries were not in a good position<br />
to respond to the most recent energy crisis. Severe adjustments<br />
have been required by countries in order to cope with the<br />
continuing energy problem.<br />
Had the lessons of 1973 and 1974 been properly absorbed,<br />
these adjustments could have been more gradual and less<br />
disruptive. The lesson of today is that we must avoid the<br />
mistakes of the<br />
There appears no reasonable prospect of maintaining long-term<br />
balance between oil demand and supply at recent prices. Indeed,<br />
as we move towards the end of the century, the prospect is one<br />
of even higher real prices for oil.<br />
During 1979, the average official price of O. P. E. C. crude oil<br />
rose by more than 100 per cent. Projections for 1980 of lower<br />
growth in industrialised countries may give some respite in<br />
the early part of the decade from the acute demand pressures on<br />
available supplies. However, undoubtedly, a challenge is at<br />
hand. But all this only serves to remind us of the real<br />
opportunities that exist in Australia, as a result of changes<br />
in the world energy and economic order.<br />
What we are facing is not catastrophe but opportunity. And it is<br />
an opportunity which Australia is uniquely placed to meet.<br />
Already we are one of the few net energy exporters among<br />
O. E. C. D. countries. We possess substantial reserves of uranium<br />
and black and brown coal. We have significant reserves of liquid<br />
petroleum gas and natural gas. And the possibilities for<br />
alternative sources of oil from shale and coal liquefaction<br />
demonstrate that, in a world increasingly short of energy supplies,<br />
Australia occupies a privileged position.<br />
The Government's role in response to this privilege is designed<br />
to achieve three objectives: greater explorat~ ion and-development<br />
of all our energy resources;. conservation of our scarce energy<br />
resources; and greater use of alternatives to our present<br />
oil supplies.<br />
It is this total strategy which can only be properly served<br />
by aggressive management and forward looking policies which were<br />
markedly absent from the approach of the<br />
The key element in the Government's strategy is our oil pari ty<br />
pricing policy, which is the only responsible course to pursue<br />
in the light of the current energy dilemma. There is no escaping<br />
the reality that price must be used as a barometer of scarcity.<br />
To adhere, for short term political purposes, to the principle<br />
of cheaper petrol would be to adhere to a policy endorsing the<br />
rapid reduction in scarce fuel reserves. / 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
Such a policy makes neither economic nor energy sense.<br />
It needs to be remembered that our super grade petrol price<br />
of around 34 cents a litre still compares more than favourably<br />
with New Zealand 43 cents; Germany 59 cents; Japan 62 cents;<br />
Italy 73 cents and France 75 cents a litre.<br />
Even the whose petrol prices in the past have been<br />
below Australian prices, will now, as a result of the gasoline<br />
conservation fee recently announced by President Carter, have<br />
prices broadly comparable with ours.<br />
One of the central challenges of the 80s is to recognise as<br />
a nation, that we have no right to sell out our energy future.<br />
As a nation, we do have a responsibility for the energy needs<br />
of the next generation.<br />
To irresponsibly dismantle parity pricing would be to entice<br />
industry to postpone new technologies; defer conservation;<br />
and delay replacement. It would mean that Australian liquid fuel<br />
reserves would be squandered and Australia would become a<br />
defenceless victim of the international oil market beggars<br />
for fuel, not just at parity prices, but even spot prices; prices<br />
which cash in on factors of limited supply and unlimited demand.<br />
But above al-l, our import parity policy recognises that expertise<br />
in energy development is international.. We have to compete for<br />
capital, technology and management with rewards that are<br />
internationally competitive. Without parity pricing this cannot<br />
be achieved.<br />
Pleasingly, realistic market prices for oil have now increased<br />
our reserves, encouraged conservation and the search for<br />
alternatives to expensive petroleum products. But when we might<br />
have expected the Australian petroleum exploration industry<br />
to be responding to the first energy crisis, it was, in fact,<br />
in a state of regression. The level of investment in petroleum<br />
exploration had fallen from $ 109 million in 1972 to $ 65 million<br />
in 1975.<br />
This was a direct consequence of the energy and economic policies<br />
of the government of the day. They dismantled many of the special<br />
incentives for the mining and petroleum industries provided<br />
through the taxation system. The whole confidence of the<br />
industry was shaken. The economic deterioration through which<br />
Australia was passing made large scale investment an<br />
unattractive commercial proposition.<br />
The last four years have seen a welcome resurgence in investment<br />
activity. Expenditure on exploration has gradually risen in<br />
response to government incentives and improved economic health.<br />
In 1979 it totalled $ 228 million and in the first half * of 1980<br />
is estimated at $ 170 million.<br />
Further, it is estimated that total expenditure on exploration<br />
and development will exceed $ 500 million in 1980.<br />
The recent announcement by Esso/ BHP that development expenditure<br />
in the Bass Strait will exceed one billion dollars is a striking<br />
illustration of the revived confidence in the industry. </p>
<p>It is the determination of this government that expenditure<br />
in the search for oil, in and around Australia, should continue<br />
its upward momentum.<br />
We have modified our taxation system to assist this objective,<br />
and we welcome the key role being played by major international<br />
groups in providing much of the enormous capital resources<br />
and fast developing technology-that is needed.<br />
The Government encourages the partnership between overseas and<br />
Australian companies and entrepreneurs in the exploration for,<br />
and development of, oil and other energy reserves.<br />
I congratulate the increasing number of Australian companies<br />
who are diversifying their interests into these areas while at<br />
the same time building up Australian expertise in energy based<br />
projects. I am particularly pleased that there is still a role for smaller<br />
businesses and companies in energy development, both at the<br />
exploration stage and in providing service facilities for the<br />
mining and exploration industry.<br />
The impact of parity pricing on the Government's second objective,<br />
oil conservation, is already evident.<br />
Australians are looking to smaller, and more fuel efficient motor<br />
vehicles and the increase in petrol consumption last year was<br />
per cent below the average annual increase of the previous five<br />
years. Even though it inevitably t akes time for policies to produce the<br />
desired effect, these are heartening developments..<br />
The third objective in the Government's energy strategy is the<br />
promotion of greater use of alternatives to our present oil supplies.<br />
In the pursuit of this objective, the Commonwealth has acted with<br />
the States in a number of areas to ensure the development of<br />
projects which help provide for the future energy needs of Australians<br />
and reduce our dependence on oil.<br />
The last two Loan Council Meetings approved special State borrowings<br />
of: $ 1,358 million for electricity power generation;<br />
$ 461 million for the Dampier-Perth pipeline and service facilities<br />
associated with the North West Shelf natural gas programme;<br />
$ 182 million for rail electrification; $ 53 million for conversion<br />
away from oil fired power generation..<br />
Of these monies totalling $ 2,165 million, $ 535 million will have<br />
been drawn by the end of 1979-80.<br />
It is clear that substantial progress is being made under this<br />
historic borrowing programme.<br />
At the same conference, the Commonwealth proposed the electrification<br />
of the Melbourne-Sydney rail link. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
In co-operation with Victoria and New South Wales preliminary<br />
investigations and planning work are under way.<br />
In addition, agreement was reached that a separate joint study be<br />
undertaken on the practicability of electrifying significant parts<br />
of the Government railway systems of Australia.<br />
At the same conference, agreement was also reached between the<br />
Commonwealth, Queensland and New South Wales Governments-that a<br />
s tudy be undertaken to determine the requirements which will assist<br />
in expanding our exports of steaming coal.<br />
These exports are expected to rise from 6 million tonnes a year<br />
to approximately 100 million tonnes by the turn of the century<br />
and infrastructure will obviously be needed so that orders can<br />
be met.<br />
There is no doubt that such initiatives advance significantly<br />
the move towards increased oil substitution.<br />
Many of them ensure the role that electricity will continue to<br />
play as a prime source of energy for Australia's development in<br />
the decade ahead.<br />
In fact the -energy crisis has brought our abundant raw materials<br />
and energy reserves closer together primarily through the ready<br />
availability of electrity generation based on our abundant coal<br />
reserves.<br />
Particularly is this so in relation to bauxite, alumina and<br />
aluminium where $ 4.5 billion of investment in refineries And<br />
smelters is either committed or at the final decision stage.<br />
What is more, of the $ 17 billion of mining and manufacturing<br />
investment projects about to go in Australia, $ 12 billion relate<br />
either to investment for energy exports; or investment in energy<br />
projects which will provide alternatives to oil use; or investment<br />
in industries in which non-oil energy input is a large proportion<br />
of total cost.<br />
Yet such figures, if anything, understate the likely exploration<br />
and development expenditure in Bass Strait and the North West<br />
Shelf and do not include the giant Rundle shale oil project.<br />
This project could involve a total cost of many billions of<br />
dollars and has the potential to greatly reduce Australia's<br />
dependence on scarce and costly supplies of imported crude oil.<br />
It would have no chance of proceeding without the Government's<br />
import parity pricing policy.<br />
It has been deliberate policy of this Government to provide<br />
incentives for exploration and development.<br />
Furthermore, the Government has adopted a wide range of initiatives<br />
designed to encourage the conversion from oil fired industrial<br />
equipment to other energy sources; or, where possible, the<br />
replacement of industrial equipment by units using other energy<br />
sources. .7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
The Government has also acted to encourage the use of alternative<br />
fuels for motor vehicles by removing the road tax on LPG and by<br />
removing the sales tax from kits which convert vehicles to LPG<br />
or compressed natural gas.<br />
These incentives, designed to reduce our dependence on oil, have<br />
been complemented by the significant improvement in Australia's<br />
economy which is our greatest incentive to investment.<br />
This improvement has been broad based and has had far reaching<br />
effects. It is the result of deliberate Government policies and concentrated<br />
efforts by the Government to provide an economic environment to<br />
which private sector forces would respond.<br />
Now, the demand for Australian products overseas, and the<br />
increasing interest being shown in Australian investment,<br />
indicate a new respect for, and confidence in, the Australian<br />
economy. The most significant factor contributing towards this respect<br />
has been the success achieved in absolute and relative terms in<br />
the fight against inflation.<br />
It must remalin a continuing and unyielding commitment.<br />
At the core of the fight against inflation is the need to continue<br />
resisting intervention by Government in the operation of the<br />
economy. In Australia in recent years while the size of the economy has<br />
grown in real terms, the share of the total economy taken by<br />
Commonwealth budget outlays has fallen.<br />
Such a trend improves economic performance in Australia while<br />
enhancing the individual freedom of all Australians.<br />
Tn the years ahead, the securing of economic growth will very much<br />
depend on our success in recognising the proper limits of<br />
Government economic power.<br />
Governments should not seek to do what private enterprise can do<br />
much better.<br />
Such a view recognises that there are limits to Govern ment influence;<br />
that Government intrusion, direct or indirect, into private<br />
decision making, will generally not advance the well being of the<br />
community.<br />
This belief needs to be increasingly reinforced.<br />
Whatever reasons are used to justify increasifig the size of<br />
government especially in areas outside its proper function, for<br />
practical reasons, and on well-documented evidence, such economic<br />
behaviour is doomed to fail.<br />
Governments must acknowledge that if they wish to expand their<br />
involvement in the economic affairs of the nation, they will<br />
damage the private sector which is the engine of growth and<br />
progress. </p>
<p>-8<br />
This view is not shared by our political opponents.<br />
Their promise to establish an Australian hydrocarbon corporation<br />
for development by the Government of oil and gas resources has<br />
an air of threatening deja vu about it.<br />
It represents a recycling of past failures.<br />
The last Australian Labor Party Government had similar grandiose<br />
plans unsupported by rational economic analysis.<br />
They brought Australia to an unprecedented level of investment<br />
fatigue.<br />
Those companies which had made discoveries and did have viable<br />
development plans were stopped in their tracks.<br />
overseas investors withdrew.<br />
Government intervention of this kind would produce the same<br />
effects. It is doomed to fail because the Government sees its reputation<br />
depending on the reputation of its own allegedly commercial<br />
corporation. Its failure would be seen as the Government's failure, to avoid<br />
this, the Government would be prompted to give its enterprise<br />
preferential treatment; to take decisions that are not based on<br />
proper commercial considerations.<br />
In such a sensitive and economically powerful area as energy<br />
development, this could lead to preferences for licences or<br />
leases secured by an almost unlimited access to taxpayers money.<br />
There is a dangerous tendency for Socialists lo be so bemused by<br />
ideology that they are unable to understand that there are<br />
individuals and businesses capable of operating more profitably<br />
and with better regard for the community interest than can be<br />
achieved by creatures of Government.<br />
The establishment of such a corporation would give to the Government<br />
economic power equal to that provided by the resources it seeks<br />
to control. / 9 </p>
<p>9-<br />
The grave limitations of this would be reflected in two<br />
ways. In the first place the government would regulate<br />
and control the industry in marked contrast to our determination<br />
to allow price and the commercial market to determine the<br />
industry's future. ' But ' worse, the hydro-carbon corporation would<br />
lock capital and labour into a perpetuation of the inefficiencies<br />
that such schemes inevitably bting.<br />
The private sector, on the other hand, must always maintain<br />
a close relationship between its borrowing, its costs and<br />
the viability of its venture. In other words, it must be<br />
commercial to survive.<br />
Such disciplines and restraints do not attend large socialist<br />
enterprises. On the contrary the kind of enterprises proposed<br />
by the Labor Party abuse government power, in particular its<br />
capital raising power, and in so doing reduce the funds, the<br />
resources and the scope for development of private business<br />
initiatives. And when this happens, more often than not,<br />
efficiency, accountability, innovation, flexibility, and market<br />
adjustment are also sacrificed.<br />
We cannot afford this or any other impediment to the gathering<br />
momentum in energy exploration and development.<br />
Yet other attitudes of the Labor Party, to which all Party<br />
members are committed, are as bizarre as they are dangerous.<br />
In a somewhat uncharacteristic gesture the Party pledges<br />
itself " to regenerate Australian industry". It is the formula<br />
for this which is interesting. For amongst its commitments<br />
is one to: monitor trans national corporations in<br />
Australia obtaining information such as their investment,<br />
marketing and trading policies Why, you may ask.<br />
To: " Supply ( this information) to the relevant trade unions<br />
as well as all relevant international organisations such as<br />
the U. N. Centre of Trans National Corporations, the I. L. O. and<br />
U. N. C. T. A. D. and appropriate international trade union<br />
organisations..." I said that Labor policies in the 70s producea investment fatigue.<br />
This would produce investment rigor mortis.<br />
One serious problem which is casting long shadows over Autai's<br />
continuing economic growth is industrial disputes. Unchecked<br />
union power poses a grave threat to our standard of living and<br />
places in jeopardy our hard won reputation as a reliable trading<br />
partner. All members of the Australian community, including Government,<br />
increasingly feel that union power is excessive and too often<br />
exercised selfishly and irresponsibly. Union leadership is<br />
increasingly seen as out of step with the aspirations of union<br />
membership. Responsible union leadership must strive to insist on<br />
increased productivity if it desires increased benifits, because<br />
unearned gains by any members of the community can only be achieved<br />
to the eventual detriment of the welfare of all Australians.<br />
This has happened too often in recent times and leads me to a point<br />
of fundamental concern the role of trade unions and the<br />
role of the law. </p>
<p>10<br />
There are those who say that industrial matters must be solved<br />
by reconciliation, negotiation, or conciliation; that the law<br />
has no part in it. In the ideal world this would be true. But<br />
we do not live in an ideal world. People are not always<br />
reasonable. When organisations have power, as trade unions<br />
do, all experience shows that this power must be exercised<br />
within the framework of the law. The community must know<br />
that justice and the law can, and will be, upheld.<br />
Some unions have incomes of millions of dollars a year; they<br />
have enormous power; in some circumstances more power than any<br />
corporation in this nation. Yet nobody suggests that corporations<br />
should be allowed to operate outside the law, however much some<br />
companies might like it. Penalties for failing to operate<br />
in a fair and reasonable manner do exist and they are high.<br />
Why then, when we come to industrial relations which damages<br />
the interests of infinitely more people than any company ever<br />
could, do some people suggest that there should be no law.<br />
That laws only provoke; that we should always negotiate. That<br />
is not a credible position for any government, for any people.<br />
We have to have law to establish the framework within which<br />
trade unions operate; also we have to have law that can and<br />
will be upheld. It is not helpful for some people to say<br />
( especially politicans) that there should be no law; that<br />
its just a question of reasonableness. What is reasonable to<br />
one person is often unreasonable to another.<br />
The community should not be left to expect that what unions<br />
regard as reasonable should be the final arbiter of the way<br />
the country is to be run. At the moment, there is an unhealthy<br />
balance between some people and groups possessing indisputable<br />
political, economic and union power and the bulk of Australians<br />
to whom these are denied.<br />
If we are to live up to our proud record as a genuinely free<br />
society, balance must be restored. In that process of restoration,<br />
all Australians, I am sure, would want the spirit of co-operation<br />
to prevail rather than the application-of law, But if<br />
co-operation and reason fail, it is only the rule of law that<br />
can protect Australians.<br />
It is essential that this should be so if the great promise of<br />
the 80s is to be matched by performance. We have got a lot<br />
going for us as a nation. In a difficult world, we are better<br />
placed than most. The advantages we enjoy over many of our<br />
trading partners point to a decade of opportunity for Australia.<br />
Because of our international competitiveness, investment possibilities<br />
have dramatically increased. In this investment climate, we are<br />
uniquely placed with raw materials and energy reserves the world needs.<br />
It is appropriate that the theme of your conference highlights<br />
the challenges ahead. But let us not forget the opportunities<br />
and rewards. As individuals, as business, as government, working<br />
alone or in opposition to one another we cannot properly utilise<br />
the nations human and physical resources. Working together, in<br />
partnership, our prospects as a nation are unlimited.<br />
I welcome your continuing role in this partnership and wish your<br />
association and its members success in the years ahead.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
