<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>366</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIEME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES IN THE HOUSE OF PREPRESENTATIVES THURSDAY, 7TH SEPTEMBER, 1961 BERLIN</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000366.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER. THE RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES<br />
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
THURSDAY, 7TH SEPTEMBER, 1961<br />
BERLIN<br />
I have already laid on the table of the House a<br />
chronology of events since the end of the ' Jar and a collection<br />
of documents relating to the period from May, 1959, to the<br />
present time. Copies of a comprehensive collation of papers<br />
prepared for the United States Senate and covering the period<br />
before May 1959 have been available to Honorable Members in the<br />
Library. How the Berlin Situation came about<br />
History of estern ights<br />
The two collections are not confined simply t-Berlin<br />
but relate to the larger question of a post-war settlement in<br />
Germany, of which the problem of Berlin forms part.<br />
How did the Berlin situation come about? It is a<br />
product of the unconditional surrender of Germany and of the<br />
arrangements made in the closing stages of the Second Jorld War<br />
for the future occupation of Germany by the four principal<br />
victorious belligerent powers. These arrangements were intenae<br />
to be temporar, and to govern the administration of Germany<br />
pending the negotiation of a German peace treaty.<br />
Perhaps we might begin by looking at the situation in<br />
early 1945, when the Allied Armies were advancing into Germany.<br />
At that time, for military reasons which need not detain us now,<br />
the Western strategy was not to race for Berlin, but rather to<br />
concentrate on objectives which were judged to be of more<br />
importance for the early destruction of the German armies. Sir<br />
Winston Churchill, in his war memoirs, tells how he questioned<br />
this strategy, because of the political importance of Berlin.<br />
But it was adopted; and in consequence, the Western armies were<br />
halted along the general line of the Elbe, West of Berlin, and<br />
it was there that the mooeeting with Soviet forces advncing from<br />
the East took place. In some cases, Western troops were in fact<br />
withdrawn to this general line.<br />
In the agreements worked out in the European Control<br />
Commission which gave each of the chiaf belligerents a zone of<br />
occupation in Germany, the zonal boundaries were so drawn as to<br />
leave Berlin as a special area within the Soviet zone of<br />
occupation, by which it was surrounded. For Berlin itself,<br />
arrangements were made for a special regime of joint four-power<br />
control. For administrative purposes, the area of Greater<br />
Berlin was divided into four sectors, each allotted to one of<br />
the four occupying Powers; but Berlin itself was to be<br />
administered as a unit by a Four-Power Kommandatura of the<br />
United Kingdom, United States, French and Soviet Military<br />
Commands. These early agreements were made in the period from<br />
before the surrender of Germany until a time immediately after<br />
it. As I have said, they were intended to lay down the general<br />
lines of the arrangements that would obtain pending the<br />
conclusion of a peace settlement. </p>
<p>In addition to the rights of the Four Major Powers,<br />
those agreements also defined certain rights of the other<br />
belligerents against Germany. As one of these belligerents<br />
Australia was enabled to establish a Military Mission in Berlin,<br />
which it still maintains.<br />
The rights of the victors include the right to<br />
maintain garrisons in Berlin and the right to free access to the<br />
city for this purpose. Such a right is essential to the Western<br />
position in Berlin. Without it Western forces cannot be<br />
maintained there, and without these forces there would be little<br />
physical obstacle to the extension of Communist control over<br />
Jest Berlin. The manner in which the Western powers and the Soviet<br />
Union exercise their rights ( notably for the Western Powers this<br />
right of access) forms the subject of the various agreements<br />
among the four powers. But it is important to stress that the<br />
rights themselves, being originally derived from the unconditionlsurrender<br />
of Germany, do not depend for their validity upon the<br />
continued acquiescence of any one of the four. Accordingly, the<br />
rights of the Western powers in Berlin cannot be lawfully<br />
cancelled or reduced by the Soviet Union.<br />
Events leading up to the current crisis<br />
The divisions which after the War opened up between the<br />
wartime allies have prevented the effective negotiation of a<br />
German peace treaty. However, having consolidated its physical<br />
hold on the zone of occupation in Eastern Germany which fell to<br />
it on the surrender of Germany, and having installed Communist<br />
officials in key positions, the Soviet Government sot up in 19:-9<br />
a Communist regime there, the so-called German Democratic<br />
Republic. Since then it has worked to place its special sector<br />
of occupation in Berlin formally under the control of that<br />
regime. These developments were accompanied by measures to<br />
restrict freedom of movenent from East to West Gornany. These<br />
measures were and are in breach of various four-power agreements,<br />
and most strikingly of the Paris Agreement of 1949, which ended<br />
the Blockade of 1948-49. It is understandable that in these<br />
circumstances the existence of a free West Berlin, enjoying the<br />
protection of the Western powers, and with living st: andards so<br />
superior to those of East Berlin, has been an increasing<br />
embarrassment to the Russians. They showed early signs of<br />
wishing to put an end to this state of affairs, in the imposition<br />
of the Berlin blockade in 1948. This attempt was defeated by<br />
Allied resolution and the Air Lift and for some years there was<br />
little trouble. But towards the end of 1958 Mr. Khrushchev faced the<br />
Western powers with an ultimatum calling for the conclusion of a<br />
separate peace treaty with East Germany ( which would formally<br />
legitimate the Communist regime there and perpetuate the division<br />
of Germany) and for the establishment of lest Berlin as a socalled<br />
" free city".<br />
There followed a Foreign Ministers' Conference held in<br />
Geneva in the European summer of 1959. At this Conference, the<br />
Western Powers made constructive proposals designed to ensure<br />
free elections for the whole of Germany and at the sane time to<br />
safeguard both iestern and Soviet security. Mr. Khrushchev<br />
refused to agree, and though he temporarily withdrew his<br />
ultimatum there wore indications that he would again raise the<br />
subject when he judged the time was ripe. </p>
<p>The present crisis was set in train by a Soviet<br />
momorandun delivered to United States officials in Vienna at the<br />
time of President Kennedy's meeting there with Mr. Khrushchev on<br />
3rd and 4th June, 1961. The text of this memorandum is set out<br />
in the paper I have tabled; I shall describe its contents in a<br />
moment. The Attitude of the Two Sides<br />
The Soviet View<br />
Essentially, the Soviet Union wishes to perpetuate the<br />
division of Germany because it knows that a freely elected all<br />
German Governnent would certainly not choose the Communist<br />
social, economic and political institutions which the Soviet<br />
Union has imposed on the people of East Germany.<br />
The aim of its policy is to strengthen and stabilise<br />
the Communist regime in East Germany, to obtain international<br />
recognition of it, to dim the beacon light which West Berlin<br />
shines into the darkness of East Germany, and to close off the<br />
escape route which it offers to the oppressed population of the<br />
Eastern zones. Each year since the war some 200,000 refugees from<br />
Communist rule have fled by way of West Berlin. The flight of<br />
these refugees has naturally disturbed the rules of Eastern<br />
Germany, because of the consequences both for the ocoionmy of the<br />
Eastern Zone and also for the prestige of the Communist regime<br />
which the Soviet Union supports there. According to official<br />
figures, some 2.7 million people have fled from the Eastoen z'ne<br />
of Germany since 1949. Some estimates place the total number who<br />
have fled since 1946 at nearer four million. Out of a total<br />
population of 17 million, either of these is a formidable figure.<br />
It shows, more dramatically than anything else could, the misery<br />
and oppression which rule in the Eastern zone, in striking<br />
contrast to the freedom and prosperity of West Berlin and of<br />
JWestern Germany. It is small wonder that the Corm-unists regard<br />
West Berlin as a " cancer" in Mr. Khrushchev's teom, and that they<br />
wish to seal off the means of escape which it offers.<br />
The " Free City" Proposal<br />
The thome of the Soviet omeorandum of Juno this year<br />
and of subsequent speeches by Mr. Khrushchev is that there is an<br />
urgent need for a Peace Treaty to be signed with " both German<br />
states" ( that is the Federal Republic of Germany and the<br />
Cormunist regir. e in East Germany) by all the powers at war with<br />
Germany; that, if the Western powers refuse to sign, the<br />
Communist powers will conclude by the end of this year a<br />
separate peace treaty with East Germany; and that this treaty<br />
will terminate the present basis of Western rights in East<br />
Germany and in Berlin and will define the status of West Berlin<br />
as a " free city". The Western powers would then be obliged to<br />
work out with the East German regime new arrangements for their<br />
right of access to Berlin. Mr. Khrushchev has stated that any<br />
attempt to raintain Western rights by force would be mot by<br />
force. But he has also suggested that, after the signature of<br />
the peace treaty Western rights of access to Berlin would not<br />
necessarily suffer interference. The Warsaw Pact powers have<br />
issued a declaration stating that a denilitarised " free city" of<br />
West Berlin would itself enjoy free comr. unications. But nothing<br />
was promised in this declaration about access for Western troops<br />
and clearly, if the Soviet view were accepted this would be a<br />
matter for the East German Government to determine. </p>
<p>No gotiations The Russians have not suggested negotiations except on<br />
their own terms. Any conciliatory signs fron then have been<br />
balanced by stateents of their willingness to resort to force<br />
if necessary to defend the so-called sovereignty of the German<br />
Democratic Republic.<br />
The Western View<br />
The Western attitude towards the Berlin problem has<br />
always been that it is, essentially, part of the wider problem of<br />
a German settlement and indeed of a European postwar<br />
settlement. They have long considered, as the Soviet Union<br />
claims to believe, that a peace settlement in Germany which would<br />
make it possible to end the occupation regirme in Berlin is<br />
overdue. In a series of unsuccessful negotiations with the<br />
Soviet Union extending over many years, they have endeavoured to<br />
reach agreement on arrangements which while meeting legitimate<br />
Soviet fears about its own security ( fears which, in the light<br />
of modern history can be understood3 would ensure a stable and<br />
peaceful Germany in future.<br />
Together with the Soviet Union the Western powers are<br />
committed, by signature of the United Nations Charter, as well<br />
as by agreements specifically relating to Germany, to respect<br />
the principle of self-determination.<br />
The Western attitude has also been based on the<br />
conviction that a divided Germany would prove a source of<br />
constant tension in Europe and that the only really pe:. manent<br />
solution lies in the reunification of the country by moans or<br />
free all-German elections followed by the conclusion of a peace<br />
treaty with a single German governrlent. Such a Treaty could be<br />
combined with various measures constituting a European security<br />
system to guard against any revival of German militarism. For<br />
the same reason, the Western powers have been opposed to the<br />
recognition of a separate puppet state in the Eastern zone of<br />
Germany, which would inply acceptance of the permanent<br />
division of Germany. They have withheld formal recognition of<br />
the Oder-Neisse line as the Eastern frontier of a future Germany<br />
on the ground that the determination of Gernany's frontiers is<br />
properly a matter for an all-Gernan peace treaty.<br />
The Western powers have, however, made it clear in the<br />
past that they are prepared to enter into negotiations and they<br />
have on various occasions in the past made constructive proposals.<br />
At the Foreign Ministers' Conference at Geneva in 1959 they<br />
proposed an advance in three phases towards the conclusion of a<br />
peace settlement with an All-German Governmont: first, free<br />
elections throughout Berlin to establish a united city there;<br />
second, a mixed German comnittee ( from Westrbnd-, rany) to draft<br />
an electoral law and submit it to plebiscite; third,<br />
elections for an all-German assembly and the formation of an all-<br />
German Government to conclude a peace treaty. They proposed<br />
that, concurrently with stages two and throe, there should be<br />
certain reductions in military strength in central Europe.<br />
These proposals wore not accepted by the Soviet Union.<br />
The Western Powers will no doubt be prepared to enter<br />
into further negotiations. In such negotiations, they would<br />
undoubtedly continue to defend and secure the freedio of the<br />
inhabitants of West Berlin, the rights of the Western forces to<br />
be there, and the rights of access of these forces. </p>
<p>The Inmportance of Berlin<br />
In the years since the unconditional surrender of<br />
Germany a democratic state has been established in iWestern<br />
Germany with a Government deriving from the freely exercised<br />
vote of the population. Under the able leadership of Chancellor<br />
Adenauer the Federal Republic of Germany, though not a nember of<br />
the United Nations, has developed into a loyal member of the<br />
free world, to the strength of which its economic vitality<br />
contributes. Similarly, the zone of Western occupation in Berlin,<br />
West Berlin, has prospered as the result of its inhabitants'<br />
efforts and under the protection of the rights that the Western<br />
powers enjoy there.<br />
Two and a quarter million people now live in West<br />
Berlin. They have steadfastly resisted Communist pressure and<br />
the Western Powers have a responsibility for their future, to<br />
see that they are not abandoned to Comr: unist oppression. They<br />
cannot be allowed to share the fate of the other German millions<br />
in the Eastern zone, the nature of which is so eloquently<br />
attested by the refu~ goe figures I quoted just now.<br />
The existence of free Berlin is of importance not only<br />
to Germans, but to all the peoples of Eastern Europe and<br />
indeed, to people everywhere in the world. To hand the<br />
Bcrliners over to Communism would not only be wrong in itself<br />
and a denial of every principle of justice; it would also be a<br />
fatal blow to the hopes and confidence of people everywhere in<br />
the determination of the Western powers to defend their frooecnm<br />
What happens in Berlin will affect the balance of power and<br />
reputation between the Communists and the Wust in areas<br />
geographically much closer to us than Berlin itself.<br />
Future Prospects What may we expect to see in the next few weeks and<br />
months? It is likely that there will be a series of measures<br />
and counter-measures over Berlin by the Co. mmunists and the allied<br />
powers. The sealing off of West Berlin by the East German<br />
authorities on 13th August, and their subsequent action to draw<br />
the ring round Berlin tighter is an example of the action open to<br />
the Communists; as is their apparent threat to air col. u-i. cations<br />
with Berlin in their latest note to the -estorn Powers. ' J. is<br />
note, it may be observed, has boon speedily and firmly rebuffed..<br />
Against this background of tension there may well be a<br />
neow series of negotiations. I will not venture any prediction<br />
about their exact timing, location or outcome.<br />
It is possible that at some stage there will be a<br />
recourse to the United Nations. Article 107 of the Charter<br />
envisages that action in relation to former enemies may be taken<br />
" by the Governments having responsibility for such action." It<br />
will be recalled however that the problem of Berlin was placed<br />
before the United Nations at the time of the Soviet Blockede of<br />
Berlin in 1948. A Security Council resolution was vetoed by the<br />
Soviet Union, and an appeol by the President of the General<br />
Assembly and Secretary-General produced no perceptible result.<br />
The lifting of the blockade was the result primarily of the<br />
steadfastness of the Western Powers and of their patient.<br />
negotiations with the Soviet Union. But the United Nations<br />
interest may have helped to bring to bear on the U. S. S. R. the<br />
force of world opinion, and it was the Soviet United Nations </p>
<p>representative through whom the U. S. S. R. announced its<br />
willingness to lift restrictions as soon as a date had been set<br />
for a meeting of Foreign Ministers. The possibility of the<br />
United Nations playing a useful role in the present crisis can<br />
therefore not be excluded.<br />
Conclusion The Berlin situation is both difficult and dangerous<br />
and much patience, firmness and good sense will be needed to avoid<br />
its manifest dangers.<br />
These dangers will be rocogn. sed by both sides. In<br />
particular, I believe that the Cormunists would do well to<br />
realise that, though the Western nations will never be the<br />
aggressors, they will if necessary defend their rights.<br />
As to Australia, we shall of course continue to support<br />
the Western position in Berlin and the right of Berliners to<br />
freedom which we have maintained in the past. I night recall our<br />
contribution in 1948 to the Western airlift, in which R. A. A. F.<br />
aircrew helped to nan the aircraft which beat the blockade.<br />
We are in close touch with other Governnents '. ad with<br />
our own missions including those in Bonn and in Berlin itself<br />
about the developing situation; and I shall inform the House<br />
fron tine to tine of events as they occur.<br />
indeed, since this statement was first drafted, a new<br />
move has been nade by the Soviet Union. It has in substance<br />
abandoned the negotiations for a cessation of nuclear weapons<br />
tests, first by the dramatic statement that the Soviet would te. t<br />
another bomb; and then, within a matter of hours, the actual<br />
carrying out of that and further tests.<br />
In order that this entirely cynical and dangerous<br />
action may be fully understood, I should remind the House that on<br />
August 28th 1959, the Soviet Government made the following<br />
announcement " The Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union have<br />
decided not to resur. e nuclear explosions in the Soviet Uhion<br />
if the Western Powers do not resume the testing of atomic<br />
and hydrogen weapons. Only in the event of the resumpti. on<br />
by them of the testing of nuclear weapons will the SF~ v. l1t<br />
Union be freed from this self-imposed undertaking."<br />
The Soviet Union has professed to believe, as th-<br />
Western world certainly does, and as the Commonwealth Prime<br />
Ministers publicly declared earlier this year, that the cussation<br />
of further nuclear testing would be a step in the direction of<br />
disarmament, would serve to reduce tension, and would offer to<br />
the people of the world some hope of a reduction in international<br />
tension. Honorable Members will be wll aware that the Soviet<br />
Union has by every instrument of propaganda, including statomcn:-ts<br />
made by Mr. Khrushchev to me in New York at the end of last yc. ar,<br />
professed a desire for complete disarmament to be arrived at b<br />
organised stagos.<br />
Thefirst stage clearly would be to hold up the<br />
development of now and even nore terrible weapons of destruction.<br />
The Soviet Union has now, by its action, exhibited its contempt<br />
for such an idea. We will no doubt be t-cld that the decision to<br />
explode these further bombs is due to the tension resulting from<br />
the Berlin crisis. But, as I have pointed out earlier in this<br />
statonent, this is a crisis manufactured by the Soviet itself, </p>
<p>The immediate effect of this last action by the Soviet<br />
Union might well have been to produce an imediate resumption of<br />
testing by the Western Powers and an abandonment of hope that so<br />
sensible a measure could ever be achieved.<br />
It is therefore of significance that on Sunday last,<br />
President Kennedy and Mr. Macnillan made the following staterent-<br />
" The President of the United States and the Prime<br />
Minister of the United Kingdom propose to Chairman Khrushchev<br />
that their three Governnents agree, effective iim-ediately,<br />
nnt to conduct nuclear tests which take place in the<br />
atmosphere and produce radio-active fallout. Their ain in<br />
this proposal is to protect mankind from the increasing<br />
hazards fron atmospheric pollution and to contribute to the<br />
reduction of international tensions.<br />
They urge Chairman Khrushchev to cable his irmediate<br />
acceptance of this offer and his cessation of further<br />
atmospheric tests.<br />
They further urge that their representatives at<br />
Geneva meet not later than September 9th to record this<br />
agreement and report it to the United Nations. Thry<br />
sincerely hope that the Soviet Union will accept this offer,<br />
which remains open for the period indicated.<br />
They point out that, with regard to atmospheric<br />
testing, the United States and the United Kingdom are<br />
prepared to rely upon existing means of Jotection, which<br />
they believe to be adequate, and are not suggesting<br />
additional controls. But they reaffirm their serious desi-e<br />
to conclude a Nuclear Test Ban Treaty, applicable to other<br />
forms of testing as , ell, and regret that the Soviet<br />
Government has blocked such an agreement."<br />
The reply which will presumably be made to this<br />
statement will be a complete test of the good faith and pacific<br />
intentions of the Communists.<br />
On Tuesday, 5th September, on the day that the third<br />
Soviet nuclear explosion was announced, President Kennedy, after<br />
careful thought and a thorough review of all the factors invol) ved,<br />
issued a statement ordering " the resumption of nuclear teo-, in<br />
the laboratory and underground, with no fall-out". It<br />
emphasised that this announcement did not qualify in any :/ the<br />
Western offer to make an agreement. Nevertheless, in the.<br />
circumstances, which clearly show that the Soviet has cm-: ' ed on<br />
a series of tests which, it must be presumed, will materially<br />
increase Soviet nuclear weapons capability, the steps taken by<br />
President Kennedy are, in his own words, those " which prudent<br />
men find essential". I will reserve further comments on this subject till<br />
next week when a further statement to the House may be<br />
appropriate. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
