<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24386</transcript-id>
    <title> Address at farewell for the Taskforce Taji Deployment, Gallipoli Barracks, Enoggera</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/04/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Task Group members, you leave for your mission in Iraq with the support and the blessing of the Australian Government, the Australian Parliament and the Australian people.</p>
<p>Your work in the Middle East is vital not just for the freedom and the security of the countries of that region, but for the freedom and the security of our country, too.</p>
<p>We know that the Daesh death cult, which now holds sway over so much of Eastern Syria and Northern Iraq, has been reaching out here to Australia as well.</p>
<p>So, your work is protecting our country as well as helping the people and the country of Iraq.</p>
<p>You are going to train and not to fight but you are a strong, a well-equipped, a highly professional and a committed force and I know that you will give a very good account of yourself.</p>
<p>I know that you are more than capable of looking after yourselves in every way that might be necessary.</p>
<p>It's also fitting on the eve of the centenary of ANZAC that this yet again is a partnership between Australia and New Zealand.</p>
<p>We respect and honour our Kiwi cousins.</p>
<p>I know they will do an outstanding job along with us.</p>
<p>Finally, let me say that you are going abroad to a far country, to uphold our interests and our values, to keep us safe.</p>
<p>You go abroad to support us and while you are away we will do all we can to support your loved ones.</p>
<p>They will miss you.</p>
<p>We will miss you.</p>
<p>We will support them on your behalf as you support us – for they also serve who only stand and wait.</p>
<p>Good luck.</p>
<p>May God bless you, and we look forward to welcoming you back after your mission is accomplished.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
