<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24830</transcript-id>
    <title>Grand Gateway interchange opens ahead of schedule</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/09/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth and Western Australian Governments are delivering world class roads and a stronger economy by today opening the Grand Gateway near Perth airport – four months ahead of schedule.</p>
<p>Thousands of motorists will have their travel times slashed following the completion of this final section of the Tonkin Highway/Leach Highway interchange, a major part of the Gateway WA project.</p>
<p>This upgrade at Grand Gateway, which has supported more than 1,000 construction jobs, will significantly improve access around the airport and surrounding industrial areas meaning businesses can get their products to market more quickly and efficiently.</p>
<p>Gateway WA is the largest road project ever to be undertaken in Perth and is jointly funded by the Commonwealth ($676 million) and the Western Australian Government ($310 million). The entire project has created 7,000 jobs.</p>
<p>When fully complete, the Gateway WA will deliver a fully upgraded road network around the consolidated Perth Airport terminal and nearby Kewdale and Forrestfield industrial estates.</p>
<p>This project is vital to Western Australia’s future economic prosperity with passenger air travel and the road freight task around Perth expected to double over the next decade.</p>
<p>Combined with the consolidation of the Perth airport domestic and international terminals, there was a clear need to deliver this upgrade quickly to reduce congestion and improve safety for motorists and freight operators.</p>
<p>The Tonkin Highway/Leach Highway intersection has been plagued by heavy congestion and lengthy traffic delays at peak periods, which is stifling Perth’s productive capacity.</p>
<p>This new free-flow interchange will unlock the surrounding road network and ensure motorists enjoy uninterrupted movement in all directions.</p>
<p>To date, Gateway WA has invested more than $500 million in third party suppliers and subcontractors. The vast majority of this work has been delivered by more than 600 Western Australian businesses.</p>
<p>The Gateway WA project includes the construction and upgrade of five main interchanges, widening Tonkin Highway to six lanes between Great Eastern Highway and Roe Highway and upgrading Leach Highway between Tonkin Highway and Orrong Road to expressway standard.</p>
<p>Other major upgrades will continue on the Tonkin/Roe Highway interchange and other associated road sections which are expected to be completed by March 2016.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Government is investing a record $50 billion to build world class infrastructure for a stronger and more prosperous Australia.</p>
<p>Visit <a href="http://gatewaywa.com.au/">http://gatewaywa.com.au/</a> for more information.</p>
<p>13 September 2015 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
