<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1437</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL BROADCAST NO. 5</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001437_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>EMBARJOED UNTIL 7.15 P. M. 21ST NOVEMBER, 1966.<br />NATIONAL BROADCAST NO.<br />BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT<br />In the course of this campaign 11r. Calwell has<br />said our system of selective compulsory National Service<br />is immoral, unjust and undemocratic. He was saying the<br />same thing nearly half a century ago.<br />TPhen the whole world was in arms in . Jorld ' ar I<br />Mr. Calwell opposed conscription.<br />V7: hen his own leader, Mr. Curtin, decided in " lorld<br />War II to bring in conscription for service outside Australia<br />Mr. Calwell then a Member of the Labor Party in the House<br />of Representatives opposed Labor's Prime Mihister<br />stubbornly and bitterly. Presumably in Mr. Calwell's view<br />Mr. Curtin's policy was immoral, unjust and undemocratic.<br />But Australia and the Labor Party rejected Mr.<br />Calwell's view in 1942.<br />Australia will reject his view today.<br />hat are the facts?<br />First there is nothing unusual about National<br />Service. All but a handful oœ the more significant<br />countries of the world have some system of National Service.<br />Our form of National Service is selective. Only a<br />small proportion of our young men reaching the age of twenty<br />is required to serve.<br />We introduced National Service when it became clear<br />that under our voluntary system we could maintain an army<br />of only about 24,000 men.<br />Our military advisers and the Cabinet's own assessment<br />told us that we needed an army of at least 40,000 to<br />meet treaty commitments and our security needs.<br />Y2e want an army of 40,000 because planning with our<br />allies is so ordered That a quick response can be provided<br />for various security situations that could arise.<br />We require forces that can be instantly available,<br />among other things, to prevent a conflict growing to<br />dangerous proportions.<br />3efore we introduced the present system of National<br />Service we examined alternatives. ' We found them all<br />impractical or unrealistic from a military viewpoint.<br />For example, under a system recommended by some<br />of calling for volunteers from national servicemen for<br />overseas duty, our service planners would never know how<br />many volunteers might come ? orward. Units trained<br />together would have to be broken up and re-formed. Our<br />response to an emergency would be weakened and delayed.</p>
<p>-2-<br />The suggestion that we should call for volunteers<br />from the Citizen Military Forces is based on a misunderstanding<br />of the purpose and the role of the C. M. F. This<br />is two-f old: to provide back-up forces in a situation of<br />defence emergency and to provide for expansion in the army<br />in the event of general , var.<br />Young men reaching the age of twenty have the<br />alternative of serving with the C. M. F. if hey wish to<br />avoid havi ng their names go forward for the National<br />Service ballot.<br />Integration of the National Servicemen into the<br />regular army units has gone very well indeed. There is a<br />healthy respect and comradeship between the National<br />Servicemen and the regular soldiers. They have pride in<br />their units. They know the importance of their tasks.<br />They know that they are well-trained for their tasks.<br />In Vietnam National Servicemen have been as one with<br />their regular army colleagues in efficiency, in resolution<br />and in courage.<br />Where the security of Australia is involved, the<br />government must make the decisions to provide the forces<br />the nation requires. That has been our responsibility.<br />We have accepted it. We are confident that knowing the<br />nation's needs you will support us.<br />( This talk will be broadcast by the A. B. C. National<br />Network at 7.15 Monday, 21st November, 1966.)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
