<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41566</transcript-id>
    <title>Latrobe Valley gets jobs boost</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Turnbull Government will create 1200 new jobs in the Latrobe Valley with the announcement of 19 successful projects under the Regional Jobs and Investment Package.</p>
<p>The $20 million package will foster stronger regional communities and ensure their prosperity continues into the future.</p>
<p>This commitment will drive jobs and economic growth in the Latrobe Valley and is part of a $220 million investment by the Turnbull Government to help diversify regional economies, stimulate economic growth and deliver sustainable employment.</p>
<p>The 19 organisations set to benefit from today's announcement highlight both the innovation and future business prowess of the region.</p>
<p>The Large Scale Hydroponic Strawberry Glasshouse Facility in Hazelwood, a $34.43 million project, will deliver a 12 hectare state-of-art facility, allowing Mecrus Pty Ltd to be the first business in the world to grow hydroponic strawberries every day of the year.</p>
<p>In addition, this facility will create almost 140 ongoing jobs, with the community also seeing an immediate benefit with 80 construction jobs expected to be created.</p>
<p>Gippsland Rotary Centenary House will receive an upgrade from the construction of 13 additional accommodation units, supporting patients and families visiting the Gippsland Cancer Care Centre.</p>
<p>These large motel-style units, complete with kitchenette and ensuite, will almost double the capacity of the Care Centre to meet future demand, while providing more affordable accommodation.</p>
<p>This project is expected to create 25 jobs during construction, along with two ongoing jobs, providing additional support to economy.</p>
<p>These two projects are examples of how the Australian Government is continuing its work to diversify the economies of our regions and create employment and investment opportunities for residents.</p>
<p>For more information on grant programs available to regional Australians, visit <a href="https://www.grants.gov.au/">https://www.grants.gov.au/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
