<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2409</transcript-id>
    <title>PARLIAMENTARY LUNCHEON IN HONOUR OF THE KING AND QUEEN OF NEPAL - CANBERRA ACT - 23 APRIL 1971 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002409_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARLLAMEhTT'ARY LUNCHEON R4 HONGUR OF THE<br />
KING AND QUEEN OF N, EPAL<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. 23 APRIL 1971<br />
õ peechby the Prime Minister, Mr. William McMahon<br />
Your Maje.; ties, Members of the Diplomatic Corps, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
Sir, this is the first time a reigning monarch from Nepal has come to Australia,<br />
arid the first time that a reigning monarch from Nepal has been in the Parliament House<br />
of the Commonwealth. We welcome you and we welcome your wife.<br />
Sir, you should know that there has been a long association in one way or<br />
another between the Nepalese people and ourselves. Many of us here today, if not all of<br />
us, remember the fact that at Gallipoli, Gurkha troops shared the responsibility with our<br />
own Fourth Brigade under General Monash. We can never forget their braveness. We<br />
can never forget the assistance they gave us under the most troubled and difficult<br />
conditions. And I well remember on many occasions, listening to a former Governor-<br />
General of ours, Viscount Slim, when he continually referred to the tract that he liked<br />
talking to the Gurkhas. He liked talking to your own people, and above all, he liked their<br />
steadfastness under action, under active service conditions, and how much he liked them<br />
fighting because he knew they would never fail.<br />
But there are other reasons, too, Sir, why we have got reasons for happin ess.<br />
Our own Colombo Plan was, in the days when I was Foreign Minister and that was<br />
only a few weeks ago was, I believe, a little out of proportion to the vote that we gave<br />
to other countries. I hope it hasn't changed, but if I find it has, or there is a likelihood<br />
of change, I can assure you I will be the first one reminding my c&amp; gethe Treasurer.<br />
Now, Sir, we have a Colombo Plan, as you know, and we have already had<br />
something of the order of 90 of your young students come here. We welcome them, and<br />
we hope that more will come in the days to come. I can't say that we will bu-ild up the<br />
programme because it is a difficulty for you just as much as it is for us. But we do like<br />
them. We regard them as people who are adaptable, people who are fitting into the<br />
educational system of this country and I hope they go back much better trained and able<br />
to play their part in the future of your country.<br />
And, too, Sir, we have these problems of tourism. Yours is a magnificent<br />
country, of grandeur and of plains of the ranges and the mountains and the plains.<br />
Providentially, nature built the ranges on the North and the plains on the South. And I<br />
think, Sir, it has been a protection to you and it will, I believe, in time be a protection<br />
to others. But I am sure what we can do is to build up our tourism. At least I know that<br />
in the case of my own two children, not only do they know of Everest and of the exploits<br />
of Hillary and of Sherpa Tensing, but they also, Sir, would like to come and find the<br />
Abominable Snowman, if they could, even if they have to beseech your help, as probably<br />
the best guide there is in Nepal, in order to try and find him. a. / 2 </p>
<p>Then Sir, may I turn to you as a person and as a reigning constitutional monarch.<br />
I have looked with awe, Sir, at all the portfolios that you have held. Roughly, I have<br />
held about fourteen, one way or the other, but I believe, Sir, as I looked at the record,<br />
you have held ever so many more than I have. And you have been there less time than<br />
I have. I wonder how you fit into them the Treasurer, as well as the Chief<br />
Administrator, as well as the Head of your National Development Corporation, and I<br />
believe one or two other portfolios which for the moment the names evade me.<br />
But, Sir, if I can look at what you have done the World Health Organisation,<br />
in education for the young people and the people of the universities and the colleges, in<br />
looking after the women and children. I think, Sir, that you have given the kind of<br />
leadership that any country in the world, including our own, would be proud of.<br />
And besides that, I was asked today by one of my officials, if I would care to<br />
recite " The Man From Snowy River". Naturally it caught me a little by surprise because<br />
it is so long since I have heard it. And when they asked me to do it, I couldn't<br />
remember the opening bars. But I was told, Sir, that if I did ring you, Sir, as a. poet<br />
in your own right, you who know the ranges and the mountains so well, would have<br />
responded. And I perhaps, Sir, might have been a little flabbergasted and certainly<br />
would have been put in the shade with the eloquence of your speech.<br />
But, Sir, may I now turn to your Constitutional activities as the reigning<br />
monarch, Head of State and Head of Government together. Sir, if I can refer to three<br />
areas in which you have taken a part.<br />
First of all, I want to refer to your activities in what we call the Panchayat<br />
System of government, which commences right at the grass roots, and goes through<br />
local government and other organisation working up to the central government under<br />
yourself, both as Prime Minister and Head of State. Sir, we hope that this scheme<br />
is successful, drawing the people into the government at the lower levels, giving them<br />
the opportunity to participate, and in time strengthening the very fabric of government<br />
in your own country.<br />
But there are two other reforms that I believe will meet with the warmest<br />
of warm approval by Members of Parliament and of the Australian people. The first<br />
one is your adoption of the rule of law the application of law to everyone, no matter<br />
who they might be and without any kind of discrimination, fairly and judiciously and<br />
making sure that every single person in the community has the protection of an<br />
independent judiciary. Secondly, the programme of " Back to the Village", designed<br />
to ensure that the leadership shall come from you down to the paeons and the people and<br />
back from the paeons and the people to the government itself, in combination working<br />
in the interests of your own country.<br />
Sir, naturally enough, we want each of these programmes to be successful<br />
and we feel reasonably confident that under your direction and leadership that they will<br />
be. In the international field that I have recently vacated, as I said a few moments<br />
ago, I knew that on the last occasion I was at the United Nations the 25th anniversary<br />
celebrations you were there too. Equally, too, can I say that the year before, whilst<br />
I wasn't there, I knew that you were there, and that you played your part as the<br />
leader of your own delegation and you certainly took a prominent part in the Economic<br />
and Social Council. / 3 </p>
<p>Internationally, too, with the non-aligned countries, you have taken a very<br />
prominent part. First of all in Belgrade and later on in Lusaka. And we, Sir, again<br />
if I can repeat these words, welcome the part that you played to try and mould this'<br />
th~ ird force together. To be a force that can make a contribution, and in time a bigger<br />
contribution, to try and ensure that there is a better balance of forces in the world"'<br />
4nd consequently a greater prospect for peace, a greater prospect of success for the<br />
things that we hold dear in your and in our time.<br />
And, finally, Sir, may I say something to you about the grace and charm of<br />
your wife. She, too, complements in very nearly every way your own activities. 7 with<br />
the young women, with the children, with health and educational organisations, in<br />
the. arts and in culture, and too, in conservation measures. We welcome you, Your<br />
Maiesty, along with your husband, and we do hope that in the days to come, in reven<br />
days that you are with us, they will be days of unequalled joy for both His Majesty<br />
and for yourself. Now His Majesty himself. I first of all should say this to you as a maiter of<br />
fact. Normally a reigning monarch under circumstances like this doesn't make a<br />
speech. But the mood has caught him not while he was sitting here in Parliament<br />
House, for which he would have been forgiven, but on the way here. Without urging<br />
but voluntarily of his own free will, he has decided he would like to say a few words<br />
to you in Nepalese, but translated by his Foreign Minister. I wanted you to know this<br />
before I called upon the Leader of the Opposition to support the Toast.<br />
But, Sir, I want to assure you before I sit down that we, the representatives<br />
of the Australian people welcome you. We know that the Australian people Mvuld<br />
welcome you too if they were given the chance. Thank you for coming. We will<br />
always welcome you back again. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
