<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11458</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            PRESS CONFERENCE &amp;#150; PARLIAMENT HOUSE                     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: allegations in The Australian newspaper; Stan Howard; National</p>
<p> Textiles; Braybrook workers; unemployment figures; Minister Moore</p>
<p>E&amp;OE..........................................................................................</p>
<p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, I've called this news conference this</p>
<p> morning to reply to the extraordinary editorial attack on the probity</p>
<p> of, not only myself, but also my Government in The Australian newspaper</p>
<p> this morning and also the front page article written by Mark Westfield.</p>
<p>The editorial represents a slur not only on me, but also on the entire</p>
<p> Government. I explicitly repudiate the allegations of impropriety. I deny</p>
<p> absolutely that the Government's decision was conditioned by, and</p>
<p> influenced by the fact that my brother was the Chairman of National Textiles,</p>
<p> or that it was motivated by a desire to protect or to assist my brother</p>
<p> in some way. I also repudiate Mr Westfield's argument that my public</p>
<p> urging of people to support the deed of arrangement was designed to protect</p>
<p> my brother from a more searching examination by either the administrator</p>
<p> or a potential liquidator. That is wrong, and it will be apparent from</p>
<p> something I will say in a moment about an ASIC investigation that a mere</p>
<p> telephone call to my office would have prevented that absurd claim being</p>
<p> made.</p>
<p>But for the record, I deny absolutely that the decision undermined my</p>
<p> probity or that of the Government. To allege that a decision undermines</p>
<p> the probity of the Government or the Prime Minister is quite a serious</p>
<p> allegation. It suggests that there is a lack of incorruptibility. I deny</p>
<p> that the decision was improper, and I desire, I deny that the decision</p>
<p> amounted to favouritism if not corruption in the words of The Australian</p>
<p> editorial.</p>
<p>I should inform you that at the commencement of the Cabinet meeting,</p>
<p> I outlined in some detail my brother's involvement in National Textiles.</p>
<p> I described as best I could recall, any discussion I'd had with him</p>
<p> over a period of eighteen months or two years concerning the company.</p>
<p> They weren't many. In fact, he's always made it a point never</p>
<p> to discuss matters involving his commercial interests with me unless a</p>
<p> failure on his part to do so would represent a failing of his obligations</p>
<p> as a director of those companies.</p>
<p>I have never sought in any way to favour any member of my family as far</p>
<p> as the decisions of the Government are concerned. And this rotten attempt</p>
<p> to suggest that this decision was designed to do that is one that I emphatically</p>
<p> repudiate.</p>
<p>I described the association to the Cabinet. I made a full disclosure</p>
<p> of it. Of course, the association is a relationship, it's not an</p>
<p> economic dependency. He's not dependent on me and I am not dependent</p>
<p> on him. But of course, there is a close association. After the matter</p>
<p> had been discussed, I in fact indicated and commenced to give affect to</p>
<p> it, an intention to leave the room, - the Cabinet room - while the final</p>
<p> decision was being taken. But I was encouraged by my colleagues to remain</p>
<p> because they could not see any point by having made a full disclosure</p>
<p> of the association that I in fact should remain.</p>
<p>The reason why I publicly exhorted on the 7.30 Report, for people</p>
<p> to get behind the deed of arrangement, was that all the advice I had was</p>
<p> that that was the best way of the workers getting their full money as</p>
<p> quickly as possible. That's why I did it. It had nothing to do with</p>
<p> protecting my brother's position. In any event, ASIC has been looking</p>
<p> at the affairs of National Textiles for some days. And, I understand on</p>
<p> advice from the Treasurer, about half an hour ago, that ASIC has decided</p>
<p> to conduct a formal investigation into the company. That doesn't</p>
<p> mean that there's any evidence of wrong doing, it simply means that</p>
<p> they've decided to conduct a formal investigation.</p>
<p>So, if The Australian had bothered to enquire, it might have been</p>
<p> told that. It might also have been told that Cabinet discussed the involvement</p>
<p> of ASIC and the whole thrust of Cabinet was that if it was appropriate</p>
<p> for ASIC to look at this, or investigate it, then that ought to occur.</p>
<p>So, overall the Government of course repudiates these allegations. It</p>
<p> was always going to be difficult for me and the Government to deal with</p>
<p> something where a member of my family was involved. But, unless the absurd</p>
<p> proposition is made that my brother, or indeed any other relative of a</p>
<p> Prime Minister, or senior politician should have no business interests</p>
<p> at all, it is inevitable that this kind of situation can and will arise.</p>
<p> I have sought at all times to dealing completely at an arm's length</p>
<p> way.</p>
<p>And one of the things I find quite extraordinary is that the very same</p>
<p> newspaper carries an article by Mr McGregor claiming that my decision</p>
<p> and that of the Government to support assistance to these workers was</p>
<p> very heavily influenced by the meeting I had with them in Williamtown</p>
<p> last Friday. And that's true. I was heavily influenced by that.</p>
<p>This is not the first time the Government has acted to see that workers</p>
<p> get their full entitlements. We did in Oakdale. And it was also of course</p>
<p> the activity of ASIC with strong support from the Government, that resulted</p>
<p> in the workers at the Cobar mine recovering some 85% of their entitlements.</p>
<p>So the claim that in some way this has been motivated by a desire on</p>
<p> my part to protect my brother is wrong, I totally repudiate it and it</p>
<p> is a despicable slur on me and one the other members of the Government.</p>
<p> Because this is an attack, not just on me, its an attack on the entire</p>
<p> Government. Because the Cabinet was aware in complete detail of my brother's</p>
<p> involvement and were in position of all the facts. And it collectively</p>
<p> took a decision, a decision that we stand by. It included a decision for</p>
<p> the first time in the history of this country to establish a safety net</p>
<p> scheme for workers' entitlements. Any questions?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will you be taking legal action Mr Howard?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have sought some advice.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard could you tell us about the conversation that you did have</p>
<p> with your brother about this matter? And when you first became aware of</p>
<p> the trouble into which the company's heading.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well yes, I think probably a year ago or more my brother would have mentioned</p>
<p> to me that the company had sought some assistance and I think this has</p>
<p> come out in the Senate Estimates in Senator Minchin's Department.</p>
<p> And he said, look, I am not asking for any favours but he said we would,</p>
<p> you know, like a response and apparently there had not been so he had</p>
<p> been informed. And I said, look, I don't want to get involved but</p>
<p> I will see that the thing is dealt with appropriately. I saw Mr Brenda</p>
<p> and Mr Bart, Mr Bart is from National Textiles and Mr Brenda is from Bruck</p>
<p> and I said to them that there was an amount of money available and I said</p>
<p> if their proposal fitted the criteria as determined by Senator Minchin,</p>
<p> they'd get help and if it didn't fit the criteria they wouldn't</p>
<p> get help. I said they weren't going to get any special favours nor</p>
<p> indeed should they, sort of, be specially penalised because of the sensitivity</p>
<p> about my brother's involvement. And I think I also had a discussion</p>
<p> with Senator Minchin and I said to him, look, Stan's involved in</p>
<p> this, I just want you to know. I said, that shouldn't mean that it</p>
<p> gets any favourable treatment but it shouldn't equally mean that</p>
<p> the company gets penalised because of it. It should be dealt with on the</p>
<p> merits.</p>
<p>I think Stan may have rung me the morning of or the day before the company</p>
<p> went into administration. He was...he rang me to inform me that that</p>
<p> was going to happen. He said he wanted me to know in advance and we didn't</p>
<p> discuss any of the details of it but he felt that because he thought it</p>
<p> might get a bit of publicity because of his involvement that I ought to</p>
<p> know about it. And that would have been, I think, the morning of or the</p>
<p> day before, I don't remember. I then didn't speak to him, and</p>
<p> of course we didn't discuss the question of workers' entitlements</p>
<p> at that stage I had no knowledge of that. I simply knew that as a result</p>
<p> of what he told me that the company might go into administration because</p>
<p> sometimes companies go into administration and they are able to meet their</p>
<p> employees entitlements so it didn't automatically follow that there</p>
<p> was a problem for the workers. It subsequently emerged. I then had a few</p>
<p> discussions with Mr Reith over the holiday period about the handling of</p>
<p> the issue, I mean, we were both conscious of the inevitable sensitivities.</p>
<p> Then I think from recollection Stan and I had no discussion about it until</p>
<p> he rang me during my trip to, sort of, just give me an up to date briefing</p>
<p> on where he saw things in relation to what was unfolding. I don't</p>
<p> recall, as I indicated to Richard McGregor yesterday, that there was any</p>
<p> discussion between us about, you know, certainly not about what the Government</p>
<p> was going to do. I mean, he read the papers and he knew that I was being</p>
<p> urged to help and perhaps it may have been understood by him that we were</p>
<p> having a look at things. I don't know but I certainly don't</p>
<p> recall any detailed discussion. Now, that's essentially it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You never discussed workers' entitlements with your brother?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. Not in...I mean, I have no recollection of discussing the workers</p>
<p> entitlement issue with Stan. I mean, the recollection I have of that conversation</p>
<p> was that he said, oh well, you know, there's a bit of to-ing and</p>
<p> fro-ing on the deed of arrangement and you may have canvassed the same</p>
<p> ground that was appearing in the newspapers about the jockeying between</p>
<p> the bank and one of the individual creditors. I think the individual creditor</p>
<p> Bart. I mean, there was no particular reason why we shouldn't have</p>
<p> discussed things but on the other hand we'd adopted the general rule</p>
<p> of minimum discussion of detail involving his business affairs through</p>
<p> a sensitivity towards suggestions that in some way he was getting favourable</p>
<p> treatment.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did he get better access to you as a result of it being your brother?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Of being my brother? I don't think so. I think he's, in fact,</p>
<p> had less access to me on a whole range of business issues. I mean, he</p>
<p> just doesn't do that. He is not the sort of person who rings me up</p>
<p> in relation to his own business affairs. He goes out of his way to respect</p>
<p> the sensitivities. I mean, we are very close on a personal basis, I am</p>
<p> with all of my brothers, but he understands the potential for mischief</p>
<p> making and that's why he has gone out of his way. But, I mean, you</p>
<p> can get to a ridiculous situation where, I suppose...you know, you</p>
<p> don't want a situation where a company gets penalised because the</p>
<p> Chairman happens to be the Prime Minister's brother. I mean, he is</p>
<p> entitled to have a business and professional career to the full separate</p>
<p> and apart from the fact that he's my brother.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>When did your brother first hear that the Federal Cabinet had decided</p>
<p> on a special one-off arrangement...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know Paul. I haven't spoken to Stan about this issue</p>
<p> for some days.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Have you met representatives of any other textile company in similar</p>
<p> circumstances seeking assistance?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'd have to check Jim. I'd have to check, I just don't</p>
<p> know. I mean, I meet a lot of people. But I kept a diary note of my meeting</p>
<p> with Mr Bart and Mr Brenda and it was a fairly anodyne meeting.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, why did you have that meeting and not Senator Minchin though?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I beg your pardon?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Why was it you that had that meeting, that initial meeting, and not Senator</p>
<p> Minchin?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, because Mr Brenda, I have known Mr Brenda for a long time and I</p>
<p> didn't think it unreasonable to see him. I see a lot of people. I</p>
<p> mean, that's happens to me all the time. I mean, there's nothing</p>
<p> sinister about seeing people. I mean, let's look at what happened,</p>
<p> the company didn't end up getting any assistance so I don't</p>
<p> think anybody can suggest that, you know, the thing was handled wrongly</p>
<p> or improperly. But if we get to a situation where the motives for any</p>
<p> individual meeting are being questioned well, I mean, you are just in</p>
<p> a, you know, you are permanently bound and gagged from doing anything.</p>
<p> But I would have thought that a willingness on the part of a Prime Minister</p>
<p> to see one of the most prominent people in not only the Sydney business</p>
<p> community, the Sydney Jewish community but also the textile industry in</p>
<p> Australia and to say, well, if you are entitled to Government help you'll</p>
<p> get it but it will be determined by the Minister and not by me. If you</p>
<p> are not, well, you are not.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You didn't think though that perhaps because your brother was involved</p>
<p> it might have been better to separate yourself and allow Senator Minchin</p>
<p> to see him rather than yourself?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I would have thought the fact that my brother and I had just, sort</p>
<p> of, kept at arms length and that I'd said to him and my brother that</p>
<p> decisions on the merits are going to be made by Senator Minchin and not</p>
<p> by me. I mean, I, in fact, did the very thing that your question implies</p>
<p> I should have done and that is left decisions to Senator Minchin. I spoke</p>
<p> to Senator Minchin about this and I said I should warn you that you have</p>
<p> got something in your system that involves a company of which my brother</p>
<p> is Chairman. Now, I want you to know that, I want your Department to know</p>
<p> that so that it's all in the open. And I don't want any favours</p>
<p> for National textiles or my brother but equally I don't want you</p>
<p> to clobber them just because Stan's the Chairman. Now, in the end,</p>
<p> he decided on the merits not to give any assistance. My brother did not</p>
<p> then come to me and say Minchin's knocked us back, will you have</p>
<p> another look at it? No he didn't. I in fact didn't know until</p>
<p> after the company had gone into liquidation....into administration</p>
<p> that Minchin in fact had knocked it back.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, are you aware of the case involving the Braybrook workers</p>
<p> in Melbourne whose textile company that went under, under similar circumstances</p>
<p> to National Textiles, and are in an area which has even higher unemployment</p>
<p> than at Rutherford? And would you consider doing the same kind of arrangement</p>
<p> for them that you've done for National Textiles?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Jim I'm aware of some of the details and look, there are quite</p>
<p> a number of people, and in fact if you go back over the last 15 or 20</p>
<p> years you'll probably find hundreds of thousands of people, or tens</p>
<p> of thousands of people who in different ways have been you know, short</p>
<p> changed on their entitlements as a result of company failure. Now if you</p>
<p> go back to one there's no reason why you don't go back to others</p>
<p> and still more. It's not as if National Textiles is the first one</p>
<p> that we've done. I mean we did do Oakdale.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Well Braybrook existed in the same time frame as......</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well no, you say the same time frame but I mean once you go back a couple</p>
<p> of years there's no reason why you shouldn't go back four years.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>But Prime Minister, Braybrook was late last year, late last year, and</p>
<p> the textiles industry suffered under restructuring in an area of 16.3%</p>
<p> unemployment, 50% higher than the Hunter. The rules you spelt out to us</p>
<p> under which you made the textiles decision, why wouldn't you also</p>
<p> consider....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well what was spelt out as a result of the Cabinet decision was that</p>
<p> we would have a safety net scheme and that that scheme would have affect</p>
<p> from the 1st of January. And that was the decision that was</p>
<p> announced by the Government. Now you always have, look I'm intensely</p>
<p> sympathetic with and sorry about people who are affected by these things,</p>
<p> very much so. I mean this is a very difficult issue. I mean as evidenced</p>
<p> by the fact that no federal government has really tried to tackle it before.</p>
<p> And we are trying to get for the future with effect from the 1st</p>
<p> of January a safety net scheme. Now we acted in relation to National Textiles</p>
<p> additionally for the reasons I've outlined. Mr Reith and I have both</p>
<p> said that in the future we might consider once off supplementation in</p>
<p> particular circumstances, but we're not giving any sort of generic</p>
<p> commitment to that. We do have a generic commitment to a safety net scheme.</p>
<p> The funding arrangements are yet to be finally resolved. I would like</p>
<p> and the Government would like the possibility of insurance to be investigated</p>
<p> because we don't think it's unreasonable that business should</p>
<p> look at an insurance scheme. I know they don't like it but this is</p>
<p> something where there are legitimately different views in the community</p>
<p> as to how these things should be funded.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, the people from Braybrook have been on television, quite</p>
<p> moving statements, and they said the only difference they can see between</p>
<p> their firm and National Textiles is that their firm's not run by</p>
<p> your brother. Now can you see why they think that, [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'd say to them that that's not the reason. The reason</p>
<p> why National Textiles is being assisted is that you have to start these</p>
<p> things at some stage. And National Textiles is being assisted basically</p>
<p> through a combination of the safety net scheme plus the additional assistance</p>
<p> for the reasons that I've outlined.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>And you won't rethink.....?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well my reason for the Government not rethinking that is that if you</p>
<p> rethink that you then have to go back and back, and there will be no end</p>
<p> to it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister did you know about Braybrook, or did your Cabinet know</p>
<p> about Braybrook when you considered the issue about your brother's</p>
<p> company?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well the Braybrook matter was certainly not discussed, certainly not</p>
<p> in front of it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you know about it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I certainly did not have it in my mind when the matter was discussed</p>
<p> in Cabinet.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So can you say that at least one part of this is valid, that they didn't</p>
<p> get the publicity that National Textiles got because your brother wasn't</p>
<p> involved? Haven't they got a point?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I wouldn't have thought it was a point to the detriment of</p>
<p> the Government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>It's a point to their detriment though isn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Laurie, if a scheme had been started several years ago by the former</p>
<p> government, or it had been started by the current government when it came</p>
<p> into office then the Braybrook people, the Oakdale people, the National</p>
<p> Textiles people all would have been covered by a safety net scheme. My</p>
<p> reason for saying that we can't go back beyond the 1st</p>
<p> of January is that if you go back beyond the 1st of January</p>
<p> for one or two cases that have received publicity they then provoke further</p>
<p> cases further back, and there is really no end to it. And I don't</p>
<p> think I can, taking everything into account and no matter how sympathetic</p>
<p> I am to individual cases that have been brought to my attention. I mean</p>
<p> just as there's been a focus on Braybrook as a result on this, if</p>
<p> something were done about that there might then be other cases that come</p>
<p> up and going back a number of years. They might go back to five or ten</p>
<p> years and in principle there's probably no reason if you go back</p>
<p> for one why you shouldn't go back for others. I mean it has long</p>
<p> been the case that when governments bring in new benefits and new safety</p>
<p> nets, they make them prospective.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister what would you say to some of your critics who are now</p>
<p> suggesting that politics in this case took precedence over policy?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that can always be said and I would never for a moment deny that</p>
<p> the Cabinet doesn't take political considerations into account in</p>
<p> reaching decisions. I'm not so crass as to assert that. I think there</p>
<p> are policy considerations in relation to high unemployment in regional</p>
<p> areas and I think there are political considerations. I mean we all know</p>
<p> that. I'm on pretending that. My resentment about this editorial</p>
<p> does not relate to the criticism it contains concerning the policy quality</p>
<p> process. I mean I might disagree with it but newspapers have an inherent</p>
<p> right, all political commentators have inherent right to have views about</p>
<p> the policy content and validity of government decisions. But what I am</p>
<p> particularly incensed about is the suggestion that in some way this is</p>
<p> improper or lacking in probity, or suggesting some kind of corruption.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] criticised Murdoch newspapers for running a campaign against</p>
<p> the GST and [inaudible] policy. Are you suggesting that this could be</p>
<p> a widening of the campaign [inaudible]?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No. Look I deal with things issue by issue, media outlet by media outlet.</p>
<p> And it's a question of dealing with the facts, the circumstances</p>
<p> of each case.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>So you don't see what was in The Australian this morning</p>
<p> as a digitorial'?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have said what I feel about The Australian's editorial</p>
<p> this morning. I haven't often called a news conference to deal with</p>
<p> an individual editorial and that's a measure of I think the seriousness</p>
<p> of the attack that this editorial makes on the foundations of trust involved</p>
<p> in a government. And that's what I....I mean by all means criticise</p>
<p> the Government's policies. By all means say they're policies</p>
<p> on the run, say they are politically motivated. I mean I'm not saying</p>
<p> those allegations are correct. That is one category of allegation. It's</p>
<p> entirely another thing to say that this decision was motivated by a desire</p>
<p> on the part of the whole Government full knowing my brother's involvement</p>
<p> to in some way protect or bail out my brother. I mean that is absurd and</p>
<p> wrong and repugnant.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, on this morning's labour force figures Prime Minister,</p>
<p> are you disappointed to see that both employment which is down 26,000,</p>
<p> and the participation rate has fallen by as much as 0.4%?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Jim, you know with these things you can only get a proper read out</p>
<p> if you look at a long-term trend. Now the participation rate is down,</p>
<p> the employment figure is down. The participation rate and the employment</p>
<p> figures last month were both very strong and that is why there was aberrantly</p>
<p> an increase in the unemployment rate. You can only really look at the</p>
<p> trend. The trend is still very strong. But you know, they do go up and</p>
<p> down each month. I mean we have a much stronger employment scene in this</p>
<p> country now than we had four years ago. All our advice is that the strength</p>
<p> of that was going to continue but to what extent I don't know. It's</p>
<p> very hard to predict. I mean we still have a long way to go with unemployment</p>
<p> but it is true that we have many areas of the country that have virtually</p>
<p> seen off unemployment as we used to understand it but there are still</p>
<p> a number of areas that don't have that privilege.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] approve of Mr Moore's getting of market analysis advice</p>
<p> at taxpayers expense?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Mr Moore explained that on AM this morning I thought very</p>
<p> well.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do other Ministers....[Inaudible]</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, I don't know what arrangements other Ministers make</p>
<p> about advice seeking. As I understand it, Mr Moore said he wanted some</p>
<p> economic briefing and I thought he gave a very good reason why he should</p>
<p> have it and his Department went out and got it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Can't he rely on Treasury for instance?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, he might</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
