<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>328</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 26/1961 - NEW AUDITOR-GENERAL FOR THE COMMONWEALTH - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000328.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
61/ 032<br />
P. M. No. 26/ 1961<br />
NEW AUDITOR-GENERAL FOR THE COMMONWEALTH<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Menzies, ainounced today the<br />
appointment of Mr. V. J. U. Skermer, as Auditor-General<br />
for the Commonwealth. He succeeds Mr. H. C. Newman, who<br />
retires this week-end.<br />
Mr. Menzies. said that Mr. Skermer, was a highly<br />
experienced audit official, who had occupied a number of senior<br />
I positions in the Commonwealth Audit Office. Since 1951, Mr.<br />
Skermer has been Secretary and Chief Inspector of the AuditCffice<br />
aand, in that position, has been deputy to the Auditor-General.<br />
He has acted as Auditor-General for the Commonwealth on a number<br />
of occasions during the absence of the Auditor-General.<br />
Mr. Skermer, who is 53, was awarded the O. B. E. in the<br />
New Year Honours List for 1961 for his distinguished public<br />
Sservice. Mr. Newman, whom Mr. Skermer replaces, has been Auditor<br />
S-General since 1955. Ho retires after a career in the Commonwealth<br />
Public Service extending over more than fifty years.<br />
Reforring to Mr. Newman's retirement, the Prime Minister<br />
expressed high praise for his work as Auditor-General. Mr.<br />
Menzies said that Mr. Newman had served the Commonwealth with<br />
great distinction throughout his long Public Service career.<br />
Mr. Newman was awarded the O. B. E. in 195+ and, in the<br />
1960 New Year Honours List, was promoted to Commander of the<br />
British Empire.<br />
CANBERRA, 4+ th June, 1961. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
