<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1570</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES ON THURSDAY, 4TH MAY 1967 - BRITISH APPLICATION TO JOIN THE EUROPEAN COMMON MARKET</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/05/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001570.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
a~ b~ r<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE MAY 1967<br />
RT. HON. HAROLD HOLT, IN THE HOUSE * 8A~,<br />
OF REPRESENTATIVES ON THURSDAY, LBA~<br />
4TH MAY, 1967<br />
BRITISH APPLICATION TO JOIN THE EUROPEAN<br />
COMMON MARKET<br />
I promised the House yesterday that I would comment on the<br />
announcement made by the Prime Minister of Britain ( Mr. Wilson in the<br />
House of Commons on Tuesday to the effect that Britain proposed to make<br />
an application to join the European Economic Community.<br />
We know the British Government has given much thought to<br />
the course it should follow. Honourable Members will recall the earlier<br />
attempt to join the European Economic Community which failed in 1963.<br />
That was during the Prime Ministership of Mr. Macmillan. Mr. Wilson has<br />
now said " All of us realise that this is an historic decision which could well<br />
determine the future of Britain, Europe and indeed of the world for decades<br />
to come". Each nation is entitled to make decisions in what it conceives to<br />
be in its own national interest. But equally, it is to be expected that when<br />
major decisions are taken which will affect countries of such historic<br />
relationship as Britain and Australia, then the interests of the countries<br />
affected will be considered, and the decisions influenced. Now that the<br />
British Government has decided that an application to join the Common Market<br />
should go forward, we will be looking to the Government and people of<br />
Britain to ensure that the terms of entry take full consideration of the interests<br />
of Commonwealth countries, which include Australia. In the longer term,<br />
it is in all our interests that Britain should remain strong, and indeed grow<br />
stronger. Only a strong Britain can remain a power of significance in the<br />
world, and we all wish this to be so.<br />
During recent months, we have been aware that Britain has been<br />
contemplating further approaches to the European Economic Community.<br />
Throughout this period the British Government has kept us advised about the<br />
essential nature of the discussions at Ministerial level with the individual<br />
member governments of the European Economic Community.<br />
More recently, the British Government has kept us informed of<br />
the development of its own thinking and as recently as last week, my<br />
colleague, the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Trade and Industry,<br />
discussed the matter with British Ministers in London.<br />
We have no doubt that as matters proceed, the British Government<br />
will continue to keep us informed of essential developments. We would hope,<br />
however, that we would also have the opportunity for meaningful consultations.<br />
Both publicly and privately the British Government has continually<br />
emphasised that entry into the European Economic Community would be<br />
subject to adequate safeguards to protect " the essential interests of the<br />
Commonwealth". I note that in making his announcement, Mr. Wilson<br />
referred specifically to the special problems of New Zealand. We certainly<br />
have a full appreciation of those problems. Mr. Wilson referred also to<br />
Commonwealth sugar producers, and we welcome this reference. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
But our important interests, of course, go very much wider, and<br />
we would expect that Jin seeking measures to safeguard the essential interests<br />
of the Commonwealth, Britain would take full account of her contractual<br />
obligations to Australia and of -the heavy dependence of a number of our<br />
export industries on the British Market.<br />
Because there appears to be some conflict between the<br />
essential interests of the Commonwealth and the present European Economic<br />
Community regime, and because at this stage we do not know what safeguards<br />
Britain will be able to negotiate, it is not pract;. cable for us to make any<br />
firm judgment on the extent to which Australia's exports are likely to be<br />
affected by Britain ' s eventual entry into the European Economic Community.<br />
The impact of British membership of the European Economic<br />
Community upon Australian trading interests would depend upon the extent<br />
to which our preferential entry to the British market i~ s affected. We sell to<br />
Britain under preferential conditions products to the value of approximately<br />
four hundred million dollars. This four hundred million dollars of trade is<br />
concentrated in a relatively few products, and in some cases represents a<br />
substantial share of the total export market for the industries concerned.<br />
There are also whole communities whose basic idustries have<br />
geared themselves to the British market. We must recognise that their<br />
future could be affected, perhaps seriously, . fthe British market is lost or<br />
substantially reduced. The Government will, of course, be watching this<br />
aspect of the problem with particular care.<br />
In recent years there appears to have developed, both in Britain<br />
and in Europe, a belief that there may be no great need to take special<br />
measures to protect Australia's export position because we have been<br />
diversifying our export trade and have been building up markets in other<br />
areas. Over the past five years, the share of our total exports going to<br />
Britain has declined from about twenty-four per cent. to about seventeen and<br />
a half per cent. But the total value of exports preferential and other to<br />
Britain has increased slightly,-Handlast year amounted to about four hundred<br />
and seventy-five million dollars in total.<br />
In certain agricultural products recent -increases in production<br />
and availability have enabled us to expand our ex,, ports to the world and to<br />
develop some new markets. As a consequence, the proportion of total<br />
exports going to Britain has declined somewhat. Nevertheless, the absolute<br />
volume of shipments to Britain has increased.<br />
I refer particularly to beef, butter, fresh fruit, canned fruit and<br />
sugar. In the case of these key products, our dependence on the British<br />
market has, in fact, increased. There are some other products such as<br />
wheat, flour, dried fruits and canned meat, where the British market 4s of<br />
prime importance. During earlier British negotiations to join the European Economic<br />
Community, it was suggested, both in Britain and in Europe, that the<br />
problems of countries such as Australia could be met through the establishment<br />
of effective world commodity agreements which would lead to improved access<br />
and remunerative prices for agricultural products. From the early stages<br />
of the Kennedy Round -1 was agreed by the more important participants that<br />
effective commodity agreements were essert ial to the success of these<br />
negotiations. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
The concluding stages of the Kennedy Round are now being reached<br />
in Geneva. The final result will not be known until the negotiations have<br />
formally been completed, but the prospects of a successful outcome are<br />
far from bright. It appears possible that there may be a Ministerial meeting<br />
in Geneva next week. The success of this meeting, if held, in opening up<br />
new prospects for world trade in agricultural products, will affect to a<br />
significant degree the extent to which our export trade could still find<br />
opportunities, following a successful British application to join the European<br />
Economic Community. Turning now to the financial and economic implications of British<br />
membership of the European Economic Commwity. Australia has had a long<br />
history of close financial co-operation with Britain, and no doubt there will<br />
be changes in some of these relationships if Britain joins the Common Market.<br />
There is little point in speculation at this time as to all the possible financial<br />
ramifications but we cannot ignore the possibility that there may be difficulties<br />
for us. Much will depend on terms and conditions of British . membership.<br />
However, I feel I should mention one issue which will be of considerable<br />
interest to us namely, the future level of capital flows from Britain to<br />
Australia. At the present time, Britain is imposing some restraints on the<br />
outf low of investment to developed countries of the sterling area such as<br />
Australia. Nevertheless our position is still better than that of developed<br />
countries outside the sterling area.<br />
If Britain were to join the European Economic Community in the<br />
near future, it seems likely that it would have to alter its current policies on<br />
the control of outward private capital flows. In that event, whatever<br />
preferences we may have now in respect of British investments abroad could<br />
be quickly abridged.<br />
I do not need to emphasise here the extent to which the growth of<br />
the Australian economy has been assisted recent years by the strong<br />
inflow of capital from abroad. Most of this ' s private capital and almost<br />
half has come from Britain. In 1965-66, private overseas investment in<br />
Australian companies from Britain amounted to some two hundred and fifty<br />
million dollars. V. e are thus talking about one of the more important elements<br />
in our balance of payments and one of the more important factors contributing<br />
to a higher rate of growth in the Australian economy.<br />
Rather similar considerations apply in the case of official capital<br />
transact i ons abroad. Australia, as a member of the sterling area, has had<br />
greater access to the London capital market than non-sterling area countries.<br />
If Britain joins the E-_ uropean Economic Community, we may be faced with a<br />
reduction of borrowing opportunities in London. As we have about $ 25C million<br />
of official debt maturing in London over the next five years and some $ SC. C<br />
million maturing over the next ten years, the question of access to the London<br />
capital market is of considerable importance to us.<br />
It is, of course, difficult to make an informed judgment on these<br />
matters now. Indeed, pending clarification of the terms and conditions of<br />
membership, it is virtually impossible to make a precise assessment of the<br />
financial and economic implications for Australia. Vie shall certainly be doing<br />
our best to ensure that Australia's interests are taken into account.<br />
In conclusion, it seems fitting to observe that the British approach<br />
to the European Economic Community is still at a very early stage indeed the<br />
application, although foreshadowed, has not yet been made. Substantial<br />
discussions are ahead, and it will only be out of these that we can gauge the<br />
likely consequences, and thus what action can be taken to safeguard the interests<br />
which are important to us. As I have said, we look to a process of continuing<br />
consultation and discussion. We shall, as we can, keep Honourable Members<br />
informed of developments. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
