<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4066</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT PRESS STATEMENT - 20 FEBRUARY 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004066.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
IM~.<br />
AUSiRALIA<br />
PRIME Mf3IM3STER February 1976<br />
JOINT PRESS STATFMENT<br />
In a joint statement issued today, the Prime Minister,<br />
Mr. Nalcolm Fraser and the Premier of Queensland, Mr. J. Bjelke-<br />
Petersen, announced the implementation of a wide range of relief<br />
Iand restoration measures to assist those affected by the serious<br />
and protracted flooding experienced in many areas of Queensland<br />
recently.<br />
I The Prime Minister and the Premier said that their two Governments<br />
were working together in a co-operative and expeditious way to<br />
assist individuals, businesses and public authorities in need as<br />
p a result of these floods. The agreed measures of assistance<br />
include:-<br />
p relief of personal hardship and distress;<br />
special subsidies to primary producers towards the cost of<br />
fodder dropped by aircraft to stranded and starving<br />
stock in flooded areas on an emergency basis;<br />
loan assistance on concessional terms to primary producers,<br />
small businesses, sporting bodies and charitable and<br />
church organisations for restoration and repairs;<br />
transport concessions, in addition to the above, for<br />
primary producers;<br />
assistance to oublic authorities for the emergency<br />
repair and protection of essential services; and </p>
<p>2.<br />
assi: tane for the restoration of Stata and<br />
local government assets dam-naged or destroyed by the floods.<br />
Having regard to the particular circumstances arising from these<br />
floods it has been agreed that the scheme of assistance for the<br />
relief of personal hardship and distress should in ths case<br />
comprehend, where appropriate, assistance in respect of<br />
essential repairs to owner occupied dwellings. However,<br />
this assistance will b subject to means test and to other<br />
appropriate conditions.<br />
These measures are to be administered by State authorities<br />
and all enquiries on eligibility etc. should be directed to<br />
those authorities. The Commonwealth Government will, however,<br />
contribute towards the financing of the costs of the measures<br />
under established natural disaster assistance arrangements. * er<br />
these arrangements the Commonwealth Government meets the full<br />
costs of agreed measures necessitated by major disasters once e<br />
State has met an annual " base" amount from its own resources.<br />
For 1975-76 this base amount is $ 2 million.<br />
Expenditure in excess of that amount has already been incurred by<br />
the State this year in respect of earlier disasters K so that<br />
in practice the full costs of the agreed measures in this fin-ar-ncial<br />
year will fall on the Commonwealth. </p>
<p>3.<br />
Details of levels of assistance are under consideration<br />
by our respective Treasurers, Mr Lynch and Sir Gordon<br />
Chalk and will be announced as soon as possible.<br />
The Prime Minister and the Premier paid tribute to the<br />
work of Service personnel, the Natural Disasters<br />
Organisation officers of the State emergency services<br />
and the many volunteers involved. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
