<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10388</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP INTERVIEW, BBC RADIO 4 LONDON</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010388.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Fax from 3 16<br />
JUN 20 ' 97 18: 36 20/ 06/ 97 18: 42 Pg:<br />
P. 7<br />
June 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
INTERVIEW, BBC RADIO 4<br />
LONDON<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
JOURNALIST-. should be a bit of a restful change from his troubles back home. A~ fer a huge<br />
victory over his Labor opponent, Paul Keating, 15 months ago, his government is now<br />
under heavy criticism over a sluggish economy, its handling of aboriginal affairs, and<br />
even sex and corruption scandals. Then there's the question of republicanism.<br />
Mr H-oward is a monarchist but the latest polls in Australia show that 55 per cent of<br />
Australians want a republic. The Australian Prime Minister's with us. Good morning.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Good morning, very nice to be here.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well we're happy to have you. Now, I suppose you will be raising the matter of a<br />
republic with the Queen at lunch.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well the Convention is not to discuss what you discuss in those circumstances, but<br />
there's no secret of the fact that there's a debate about Australia's constitutional future<br />
and it will be something that the Australian people will ultimately vote on and make a<br />
decision about. The place of the monarchy in Australia is obviously very different<br />
from what it was 30 or 40 years ago and it's one of those issues that is bubbling along<br />
in the background, it's not in the forefront of public debate, and there's still a<br />
significant division of opinion, but ultimately there'll be a vote on it and people will<br />
make a decision. </p>
<p>Fax from 3 16 2/ 69 84 g<br />
JUN 20 ' 97 18: 37 2A6/ 71: 2P8 2<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
Now before the vote you want to decide when the vote is going to be.<br />
PRIM MINISTER.<br />
There'll be a referendum at the end of the year.<br />
JOURNALIST-. You'll ca this convention?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
' Well we promised the convention in the lead-up to the last election, and it will be held<br />
in December of this year and if a consensus emerges from that, well that will be put to<br />
the people. If there's not a consensus then we will have, probably have an indicative<br />
plebiscite to determine public opinion. So I think the issue will obviously continue to<br />
be debated. Whatever happens on that front, the bilateral relationship between<br />
Australia and Britain will remain very strong, but whilst it's an issue that will continue<br />
to be debated and it is important in a long term since obviously it's not a front of the<br />
mind, front-burner issue. The performance of the economy and our links with the<br />
Asia-Pacific region are far more front-mind issues.<br />
JOURNALIST:<br />
It's going to be a front-burner issue increasingly though as the year 2000 approaches<br />
and the Sydney Olympics approach and people will say, do we want a royal presence<br />
there? PRIME MINISTER:<br />
I don't think people are going to get terribly fussed either way about that. I said some<br />
time ago when, before I was Leader of the Opposition and therefore a potential Prime<br />
Minister, that I saw some merit in the Prime Minister of the day, whoever he or she<br />
may be, opening the Olympic Games.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well now, let us talk about somiethng else that's been dogging you and apart from<br />
your own problems with the economy... </p>
<p>Fax from 3 16 20/ 06/ 97 18: 42 Pg: 3<br />
JUN 20 ' 97 18: 37 P. 9<br />
3<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Can I just take you up on that. I have to say that any description of the Australian<br />
economy, it's growth rate according to the latest OECD report is right at the top of<br />
the OECD league, and we will have a budget surplus in the third year of our electoral<br />
cycle, having turned around a $ 10.5 billion deficit, and we have a growth rate<br />
predicted this year of around 3.5 per cent, so any description of sluggish is just so<br />
inaccurate, I do have to emphasise that because I'm not going to cop unfair<br />
descriptions of the Australian economy, inaccurate ones either.<br />
JOURNALIST: Alright, fair enough. Blut in the limited time we've got here, I'd like to move onto the<br />
question of race in Australia and the aboriginal population, and obviously your views<br />
on that have been very closely watched, and people felt that it was a mistake of you<br />
not to apologise in the speech .( inaudible).<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well, some people differ on a lot of various issues....<br />
JOURNALIST: In that sort of atmosphere there has been the rise in popularity of a politician called<br />
Pauline Hanson, who is now top of the headlines in Australia, who has been saying<br />
things like, it is not true to say that aboriginals are disadvantaged. This must be of<br />
concern to you, that that kind of right-wingery is now getting quite a lot of popular<br />
support.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Well you have a certain amount of right-wingery in all western countries.<br />
JOURNALIST: Including our own.<br />
PRIME MINISTER:<br />
Yes indeed, indeed. And I think on a scale of ten, extreme views in Australia are lower<br />
than they are in many other countries. There's nothing unusual in western society in<br />
people expressing extreme views being thrown up from time to time. The views that<br />
she expresses are minority views and any suggestion that Australia is a racist country is<br />
one that I repudiate completely. It is not true of anybody to say that the Australian<br />
aborigines are not disadvantaged as an identifiable group. They are clearly a very<br />
disadvantaged people and the philosophy of my government is rather than dwelling on<br />
the past is to focus on remedying current disadvantages as we go into the fiuture.<br />
JOURNALIST: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
