<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10759</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                INTERVIEW WITH RAY HADLEY                JOHN LAWS MORNING SHOW, RADIO 2UE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Yesterday in Adelaide the Prime Minister John Howard announced his</p>
<p> new approach to one of our biggest problems, youth unemployment. Basically</p>
<p> the rules are going to be tougher. Long-term unemployed youngsters</p>
<p> on the dole with have to do certain things to keep getting the dole,</p>
<p> either go into some training course or do community work or even relocate</p>
<p> to areas where there are more jobs. I like it tough, fair but pretty</p>
<p> sensible. The Prime Minister John Howard on line from South Australia</p>
<p> to explain more about it. Prime Minister, good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Ray.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Did you enjoy your break?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I did, I did enjoy my break. I read a few books and I had a good break.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>That is good. It is a good part of the world to enjoy a break up there.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is, I was pursued by the odd journalist, but it was nonetheless</p>
<p> pleasant. And I played a lot of golf, I can't say that the handicap</p>
<p> is any lower, but I enjoyed that as well.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I can speak from experience, playing more doesn't make it get</p>
<p> better.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is one of the frustrating things about golf, I find if I haven't</p>
<p> played for about three months the first game after the three months</p>
<p> is not too bad and the second game is awful.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>You are like those horses, good first up from a spell sometimes.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is right.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Unemployment down, but youth unemployment rate is on the rise is this</p>
<p> repackaging an attempt to stem the flow of children and young people</p>
<p> on the dole?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It is a two-pronged attack. One part of it is to ensure that we put</p>
<p> more resources into removing the causes of youth unemployment. And</p>
<p> one of those is that a lot of young people leave school now can't</p>
<p> read and write properly and that is the main reason why they can't</p>
<p> get a job or can't hold down a job.</p>
<p>Now one of the new rules we are going to introduce is, that if you</p>
<p> have been out of work for six months and your literacy and numeracy</p>
<p> skills are below par then we are going to provide you with a remedial</p>
<p> course so that you do become literate and numerate. But it will be</p>
<p> a condition of your getting the unemployment benefit that you go along</p>
<p> to those classes. Now I think that is fair and reasonable and it will</p>
<p> also help the young person involved. It will improve that person's</p>
<p> skills, but at the same time it is saying to the community that under</p>
<p> our mutual obligation approach, we will look after people who can't</p>
<p> get work provided they give something back in return.</p>
<p>Now for other people, giving something back in return could involve</p>
<p> being involved in a work the dole scheme. Still others will have the</p>
<p> option, if they live in an area of high unemployment of relocating</p>
<p> to an area of higher employment. It will not, as one of the papers</p>
<p> wrongly suggested this morning, I think the Sydney Morning Herald,</p>
<p> result in people being compelled to move it is just that that will</p>
<p> be one of the options that is available to meet their obligation to</p>
<p> the community.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I think that will allay a few fears for people in rural Australia.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look if they don't want to move they have got the option of going</p>
<p> into a work for the dole scheme or going into something else. There</p>
<p> are five or six alternatives that are available. But the principle</p>
<p> Ray is a very simple one, and that is, if you are between 18 and 24,</p>
<p> you have been out of work for six months, then if you are to continue</p>
<p> to get the full unemployment benefit you have got to do something</p>
<p> in return. Now that can be in one of these literacy and numeracy courses,</p>
<p> it can be in a work for the dole scheme, it could be in some kind</p>
<p> of voluntary work, it could be in a training place, it will depend</p>
<p> upon the circumstances of the individual. But you have got to do something</p>
<p> to continue to get the full rate of the unemployment benefit.</p>
<p>It is a general principle and it is based on, as I say, the notion</p>
<p> of mutual obligation. We look after them, we are not prepared to have</p>
<p> people starving and begging in the streets in this country, that is</p>
<p> not the Australian way, but we say to people who aren't in work,</p>
<p> ok we will look after you but we ask you to do something in return.</p>
<p> And we are not asking them to be involved in slave labour, we are</p>
<p> simply asking them to put some time back into the community in one</p>
<p> of a variety of ways. I think it is fair, I think it is a principle</p>
<p> that most Australians support. And it is also a principle I think</p>
<p> young people will support.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I think you will get support for that. Now I don't know whether</p>
<p> I have discussed this with you before but it is one of my old soap-box</p>
<p> issues. In 1972 when I left school all of a sudden it was made more</p>
<p> attractive for young people to be on the dole, as a result people</p>
<p> my age, entering their 44th year, have children who have never worked,</p>
<p> they have never worked, is this about breaking a cycle as well?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh it is, very much so. Ray, there is no doubt that in the early 70s</p>
<p> there was a profound cultural change in this area and habits of work</p>
<p> began to disappear from sections of the community. And what we are</p>
<p> about, as much as anything else in the work for the dole approach,</p>
<p> is to give to young people the habit and the discipline, if you like,</p>
<p> of work.</p>
<p>I mean, the very notion of having to be somewhere at a particular</p>
<p> time and the habit of work is a very, very important element. And</p>
<p> when you have grown up in an environment where you friends and your</p>
<p> family members aren't in work then the habit of work is something</p>
<p> that is very difficult to attain. And what we are trying to do here</p>
<p> is to, through this mutual obligation approach, get people into the</p>
<p> habit and the pattern of work and that will make them more attractive</p>
<p> for a full-time job.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>You have allotted $383 million over 4 years, how will that money be</p>
<p> spent?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it will be spent, some of it on creating the 12,000, we estimate,</p>
<p> literacy and numeracy training places which will be needed for the</p>
<p> people whose literacy and numeracy skills are down. We are generating</p>
<p> another 25,000 work for the dole places. We are introducing a very</p>
<p> innovative scheme, on a pilot basis to see how it goes, and that is</p>
<p> a system of what is called mentoring'. In other words,</p>
<p> we are inviting people from the community, and there are already a</p>
<p> lot of service organisations who are anxious to help, people to really</p>
<p> take a young person or one or two young people under their wing and</p>
<p> on a one-on-one basis give them advice.</p>
<p>Really like, you might call unemployment counsellors on a voluntary</p>
<p> basis. I mean, there are a lot of people who volunteer their time</p>
<p> to work in magnificent organisations like Lifeline and they will spend</p>
<p> several hours a night on a telephone counselling young people who</p>
<p> are in all situations of despair. Now there are a lot of people in</p>
<p> the community who are prepared to spend a bit of time each week talking</p>
<p> to young people, giving them advice, giving them encouragement, giving</p>
<p> them hope because some young people don't have any of that because</p>
<p> they come from collapsed family structures, they don't have many</p>
<p> friends, they have low self-esteem. And if we could sort of get two</p>
<p> or three young people a mentor, so to speak, I think over a period</p>
<p> of time that would help.</p>
<p>Now we are doing it on a pilot basis and we are only, at this stage,</p>
<p> going to try and look after about a thousand young people but it is</p>
<p> yet another way of doing two things. We are going to try and tap community</p>
<p> idealism, because there are a lot of people out there who want to</p>
<p> help young people, they don't want to knock them they want to</p>
<p> help them. And they realise, particularly people who have had a happy,</p>
<p> successful family background they would like to give something in</p>
<p> return, give something back to the community for young people who</p>
<p> haven't. And I think this could be the beginning of yet another</p>
<p> way of tackling an extremely difficult problem.</p>
<p>I am not saying it is the answer, and I am not pretending that a thousand</p>
<p> places is going to solve the problem, but if it works on a pilot basis</p>
<p> then it is something that can be spread through the community.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Just on another issue. The news room just passed me a wire service</p>
<p> story which you would probably interested in. International mining</p>
<p> giant Rio Tinto won an appeal in the Australian Industrial Relations</p>
<p> Commission quashing an earlier decision for the Commission to intervene</p>
<p> in industrial disputes. Of course, in relation to their dispute with</p>
<p> the Hunter Valley No.1 coal miners strike. Do you think this will</p>
<p> lead to a renewal of strike action there?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well it shouldn't. I will need, and Peter Reith will undoubtedly</p>
<p> analyse that decision. It is a very interesting development. What</p>
<p> we've sought to do in the industrial relations area and this</p>
<p> applies to the waterfront, as much as to the coal fields, is that</p>
<p> we've sought to change the law to open the whole system up to</p>
<p> more competition and to the use of non-union staff, non-union employees.</p>
<p>We are not trying to destroy the unions, we are not trying to stop</p>
<p> people belonging to unions, we never will. But what we are endeavouring</p>
<p> to do is to say to people and to companies, if you want to start a</p>
<p> new business, in the case of the waterfront and providing you act</p>
<p> within the law, good luck, go ahead and do it. It is more competition,</p>
<p> lower prices, better product for the consumer. In the case of the</p>
<p> coal fields then you have got to get rid of many of those disruptive</p>
<p> work practices which, I mean all of these things have been made more</p>
<p> urgent and more necessary, Ray, because of what has happened in Asia.</p>
<p>I mean, anybody who thinks what has happened in Asia is a reason for</p>
<p> us to rest on our oars and think that we have done all we need to</p>
<p> do is completely wrong and complacent. What has happened in Asia is</p>
<p> a reminder both of the strengths we have, because we have been able</p>
<p> to withstand the storm, but on the other hand, it is a warning to</p>
<p> us that we have to run even faster and become even more competitive</p>
<p> to make certain that we keep the contagion, if you like, away from</p>
<p> Australia.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>On a similar theme, you are clearly behind the Farmers' Federation</p>
<p> in their battle with the Maritime Unions, how do you see that issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what the Farmers' Federation is doing is the right of any</p>
<p> group of Australians, and that is to start a business. And they are</p>
<p> using the newly liberalised law to allow them to start a business.</p>
<p> They're not trying to destroy the union, they're trying</p>
<p> to start a business, run it profitably, take business away from existing</p>
<p> stevedores and get business for themselves. Now that is what everybody</p>
<p> does. I mean we are all subjected to competition, your radio station</p>
<p> is subjected to competition, people try and take my job away from</p>
<p> me every three years, people are always competing for the support</p>
<p> of the Australian community.</p>
<p>It seems there is only one section of the Australian community that</p>
<p> thinks it should never face any competition and that is the Maritime</p>
<p> Union of Australia. Because, I mean the only people, Ray, who are</p>
<p> talking warfare, talking thuggery, talking belligerence are the members</p>
<p> of the Maritime Union of Australia. I think the farmers are exercising</p>
<p> their right. They're Australian citizens who are doing their</p>
<p> level best to start a new business and heaven knows we need more productive,</p>
<p> we really do need more productive and more competitive wharves because</p>
<p> the cost of putting stuff through Australian wharves is too high and</p>
<p> if the cost were lower we would sell more abroad and we would all</p>
<p> be better off. And that is what the NFF is endeavouring to do and</p>
<p> good luck to them and I think most Australians will support them.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I defy anyone that watched that 60 Minutes Report late last year to</p>
<p> have any support for the work practices that were explained to us.</p>
<p> I mean it was just quite incredible.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look you can not defend the indefensible and that is what the MUA</p>
<p> is trying to do.</p>
<p>I just say to the members of the MUA, look, nobody is trying to take</p>
<p> away your job, nobody is trying to destroy your union. All we are</p>
<p> endeavouring to do is to get more competition and more productivity</p>
<p> into the Australian waterfront. And the consumer, the Australian citizen,</p>
<p> the exporter, the importer will be better off as a result.</p>
<p>Even the Labor Party said at its national conference that it was in</p>
<p> favour of boosting productivity at container ports. Now, let's</p>
<p> see how they react. Let's see whether Mr Beazley is led by the</p>
<p> nose by Mr Coombs, or whether he like, joins me, in calling for more</p>
<p> productive Australian wharves. I mean the test on these things is</p>
<p> the national interest. I mean the government's responsibility</p>
<p> is to do things that help the whole of Australia, not sections of</p>
<p> Australia. I mean we're for all of us, not just for a section</p>
<p> of us and that is what we are trying to do.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I said on air, on this programme, this week, I agree completely with</p>
<p> your firm rebuke of the Member of Oxley, who bagged Cathy Freeman.</p>
<p> I think that was your strongest, the strongest I have heard you on</p>
<p> the issue. Have you simply had enough of her whingeing, like the rest</p>
<p> of us?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When I hear anybody say a stupid bigoted thing, I will attack them</p>
<p> and what she said was stupid, it was bigoted and it was ungracious</p>
<p> and wrong. I mean, I had actually been present. I gave Cathy Freeman</p>
<p> the Australian of the Year Award. I heard her speech in which she</p>
<p> rejoiced in the fact that she was an Australian. She also said, quite</p>
<p> understandably, quite properly, that she was very proud of her Aboriginal</p>
<p> background. Now how could anybody complain about that.</p>
<p>And there was this rather odd suggestion from the Member for Oxley</p>
<p> that the decision had been made by the Government and in order to</p>
<p> embarrass her. I mean, I didn't make the decision but I tell</p>
<p> you what I applauded it.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Maybe you could later rest the conspiracy theorists' and tell</p>
<p> us exactly how the decision...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The decision is made by the Australia Day Council and the Australia</p>
<p> Day Council is chaired by Kevin Gosper, of Olympic fame, and it is</p>
<p> made up of people who are chairmen of the various state committees</p>
<p> of the Australia Day Council around Australia and some other people</p>
<p> who are appointed as ordinary council members. And many of the people</p>
<p> on the current council would have been appointed during the time the</p>
<p> former government was in office, many by us, many by state governments</p>
<p> of different persuasions. It is a mixture of citizens and they meet</p>
<p> and they take nominations from the various state bodies and from elsewhere</p>
<p> and then they come up with a decision.</p>
<p>And I was notified that Cathy Freeman had been chosen as the Australian</p>
<p> of the Year about, probably, I guess, 10 days, before the announcement</p>
<p> was made. I naturally kept it to myself because we wanted it to be</p>
<p> held for the Day. She was amongst a, sort of, group of finalists -</p>
<p> so to speak - who came to Perth and I made the announcement. Now I</p>
<p> didn't play any role in it. The only role I played was to happily</p>
<p> have the privilege of making the announcement. And the same applied</p>
<p> to the girl who was chosen as the Young Australian of the Year about</p>
<p> probably, I guess, 10 days before the announcement was made. I naturally</p>
<p> kept it to myself because we wanted it to be held for the day. She</p>
<p> was amongst a group of finalists, so to speak, who came to Perth and</p>
<p> I made the announcement. Now, I didn't play any role in it. The</p>
<p> only role I played was to happily have the privilege of making the</p>
<p> announcement. And the same applied to the girl who was chosen as the</p>
<p> Young Australian of the Year.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>Tan Le.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Tan Le. And she...in fact, I didn't know her identity until the</p>
<p> morning of the announcement. And once again, I played no personal</p>
<p> role. But let me say in relation to both choices, I thought they were</p>
<p> excellent. And each of the young women gave incredibly gracious acceptance</p>
<p> speeches and each of them are very good Australians. And I just thought</p>
<p> it was a singularly ungracious intervention by Mrs Hanson. I mean,</p>
<p> I just found it quite extraordinary.</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>The republic convention starts in a week or so. A pretty diverse set</p>
<p> of candidates. You have admitted an understanding of having an Australian</p>
<p> as our Head of State in more recent times. Is that a softening of</p>
<p> your position?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's not a change Ray. My position is that I think the</p>
<p> present system works very well and I don't believe that any replacement</p>
<p> system is going to work better. I understand that there are a lot</p>
<p> of people who want to change it because they feel uncomfortable with</p>
<p> the symbolism of the present system. And what I'm saying is that</p>
<p> although I myself do not think we would be better off with a different</p>
<p> system and I don't think for a moment that this country lacks</p>
<p> independence or that in some way the present system diminishes us</p>
<p> as a nation, I don't believe that at all. I mean, I've never</p>
<p> felt anything other than Australian. And I can say Ray, when I go</p>
<p> overseas and when I offer support to countries in our region, none</p>
<p> of them turn around to me and say, I don't think we can take</p>
<p> that support because you're not an independent country. I mean,</p>
<p> the idea that we're not independent is just ridiculous. But there</p>
<p> are a lot of people who say, despite that or whatever may be the arguments</p>
<p> in favour of the present system, we would like to change. Now, I understand</p>
<p> that. I'm not saying I agree with it. But I understand it. And</p>
<p> what I'm urging people to do at the convention is to agree on</p>
<p> what is the best alternative if there is to be a change, not that</p>
<p> I support it.</p>
<p>I mean, if we are to become a republic I'd rather it be a good</p>
<p> republic than a bad republic. And I think people ought to play a constructive</p>
<p> role. They should go there recognising that we are first and foremost</p>
<p> all Australians and we each have a positive view about the future</p>
<p> of our country. Let's agree on an alternative to the present</p>
<p> system so that that alternative can be put alongside the present system</p>
<p> and the Australian community can have a vote on it. So that if there</p>
<p> is to be a change, we can have that change on the 1st of January,</p>
<p> 2001.</p>
<p>Now, equally, if the people reject that change, well, let's forget</p>
<p> it for the time being and let's celebrate our centenary without</p>
<p> the distraction of a debate on the republic. Now, I think that is</p>
<p> the positive, constructive way. It doesn't mean that I personally</p>
<p> have changed my own view. But it does mean that as Prime Minister</p>
<p> my first responsibility is to get a result. I want a smooth convention.</p>
<p> I want one where people fearlessly express their views but at the</p>
<p> same time they work towards an outcome that gives people the opportunity</p>
<p> of expressing a choice.</p>
<p>We all know that when the referendum comes one of the options is to</p>
<p> vote to retain the present system. We all know that. But what we don't</p>
<p> know is what the alternative is. Now, I don't like the idea of</p>
<p> a popular presidential election because I think you'll end up</p>
<p> having two Prime Ministers. I mean, if you have a popular presidential</p>
<p> election you could end up with a Labor President and a Liberal Prime</p>
<p> Minister or vice versa. I mean, you can imagine what a shemozzle that</p>
<p> would be. I mean, you've got to get</p>
<p>something done. It's hard enough now with the Senate. But if</p>
<p> you had that, just imagine if you had a Liberal Prime Minister or</p>
<p> a Labor Prime Minister and a Liberal President and you had the Democrats</p>
<p> controlling the Senate. I mean, heavens above, you'd get nothing</p>
<p> done. And on top of that you've got the States. And then people</p>
<p> will say:- Why doesn't the Government?' Well, I mean,</p>
<p> in that sort of situation, what can the Government do?</p>
<p>HADLEY:</p>
<p>I see Mr Beazley has changed his position on the popularly elected</p>
<p> president in more recent times.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I think he's probably looked at</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
