<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4869</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE AT PORT MORESBY, 30 OCTOBER 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/10/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004869.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT<br />
Prime Minister's Press Conference at Port Moresby<br />
October 1978<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
This is principally an opportunity to give you a chance ask any<br />
questions related to what I said last night and this morning at<br />
the handing over of the Library. I think the Library is a<br />
particularly fitting gift as an Independence gift, and I hope<br />
very much that there will be an on-going link, and I'm sure there<br />
will be, between the Australian National Library and this<br />
Library, and between other Australian insititutions and this<br />
Library. As I also indicated in the speech this morning, I believe<br />
that.. in the National Library and in.-our own Archives we ought to<br />
look through documents and see which documents of a historical<br />
nature would more appropriately find their final home in Papua-<br />
New Guinea, and I will be very surprised if there aren't such<br />
documents in our care at the moment. We would want to hand them<br />
over to Papua-New Guinea on a future occasion. I had very useful<br />
discussions with the Prime Minister Michael Somare earlier-this<br />
morning, and as you know there are on-going consultations on a<br />
numiber of issues. Over the last several months there have been<br />
very successful negotiations between Papua-New Guinea and Australia<br />
on what at different times seemed to be a very vexed border issue<br />
in the Torres Strait. I think you know Ian Viner and the Foreign<br />
Minister, Andrew Peacock and Mr Petersen are visiting Torres Strait<br />
shortly to go through that with Torres Strait Islanders. In 1976<br />
we entered a five-year aid agreement with Papua-New Guinea, and<br />
the basis of that aid agreement was to provide $ 900 m. in annual<br />
instalments of $ 180 m. The agreement also provided for topping-up<br />
in each year, and the first years have been $ 10 in., $ 20 in., and<br />
m. over and above the $ 180 mn., and we need to have a topping<br />
up arrangement for the last two years of the current five-year<br />
arrangement, and Sir John Crawford will be over here shortly to<br />
advise us on the best means of pursuing that. Papua-New Guinea<br />
has put the point of view that rather than having annual discussions<br />
about it, it would be better if it could be related to an<br />
appropriate formula. We have no objection to that in principal<br />
if such . a formula can be found, and Sir John Crawford will be here<br />
and part of his task is to recommend in relation to that. This<br />
morning, of course, the Prime Minister rose with me what might<br />
happen beyond 1981, and quite clearly an Australian commitment<br />
does continue and obviously it has been a substantial commitment<br />
and will continue to be a substantial commitment, althou~ h in<br />
accordance with Papua-New Guinea's own efforts and wishes they<br />
want the Australian grant component to become smaller part of their<br />
total national effort, and a smaller part of their total Budgetary<br />
circumstances, and it's obviously part of their drive towards<br />
independence and being independent or less dependent on<br />
the very substantial aid that ha's come from Australia. All I<br />
can say is do you have any questions:<br />
Question: Prime Minister, the point you made about Papua-New Guinea asking<br />
if they would like the content of their Budget to be of increasingly<br />
less importance in depending on Australian aid, I wonder could we<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
ask you does this envisage an actual drop in the amount of money<br />
involved in Australian aid?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think it's too early to indicate that at the moment. It is<br />
worth noting that the topping-up provisions in the first three<br />
years of the current five-year aid program have increased each<br />
year, so that would be going contrary to the thrust of the question.<br />
Question:<br />
Would that mean that they are aiming at a bigger budget of their<br />
own? Prime Minister:<br />
Their own Budget has been growing, yes.<br />
Question: So do we diminish in terms of relationships?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well it's open at the moment. I think it would be wrong to draw<br />
conclusions as to what would happen beyond the five-year program.<br />
But obviously there will need to be discussions, and Papua-New<br />
Guinea will need to know the basis of provision from Australia,<br />
and the whole purpose of the five-year program which I think<br />
is a unique one is a supplement to the Budget and not tied to<br />
project aid, leaving it entirely to Papua-New Guinea to determine<br />
how the funds should be spent. I think that principal has been<br />
much appreciated in Papua-New Guinea, and the Prime Minister has<br />
mentioned it to me and the former Treasurer on. a number of<br />
occasions. That will give us plenty of time over the next two<br />
years to work out appropriate arrangements to go beyond 1981.<br />
Question: New Guinea is being very successful in containing inflation.<br />
Is there anything Australia might learn out of this.<br />
Prime minister:<br />
Oh yes indeed. I think indeed you relate your aspirations to<br />
your resources. I think we are learning that slowly in Australia.<br />
But Papua-New Guinea never had the circumstance I think in which<br />
the Government expenditures went up by 4.6% in one year and wage<br />
rates went up by over 50% over a three year period. We are well<br />
aware of developping nation aspirations and resources must march<br />
hand in hand.<br />
Question: Mr Fraser, Papua-New Guinea's Foreign Minister last week indicated<br />
he was seeking support from other members of the South Pacific<br />
Forum, including Australia, to pressure metropolitan powers: / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
the United Kingdom and the U. S. and France and the Pacific to<br />
accelerate the decolonisation process. In particular you seem<br />
to be referring to France and New Caledonia. What attitude would<br />
Australia take in such a campaign?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well this matter hasn't been raised with me during this visit,<br />
but any point of view thrusting in that direction is one that<br />
we clearly want to discuss and assess upon its merits. I think<br />
it's worth noting the remarks I made last night, which weren't<br />
in the printed text of the speech. The process of independence<br />
is much better a bit sooner rather than later rather than too<br />
late, and so-it's better to err on the side of the process being<br />
completed earlier rather than later.<br />
Question:. Prime Minister, I wonder if you discussed the Fisheries Agency<br />
with Mr Somare this morning, and whether as he was suggesting<br />
last night Australia might take the view more in mind what<br />
Papua-New Guinea is doing.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well I don't think we've got a view out of line with Papua-<br />
New Guinea' s in relation to this. We did discuss this matter<br />
this morning, and there will be discussions between our officials<br />
about the form of the Agency and what it will do, and we always<br />
envisaged that that would happen. I think it is worth noting that<br />
the resolution adopted by the Forum countries was one which I<br />
proposed and was adopted unanimously. There had been quite sharp<br />
differences of view expressed in the Forum by some of the island<br />
nations, and the resolution that I proposed was one which people<br />
on all sides were able to accept, and accept very willingly.<br />
As you know, Australia doesn't have a commercial or a material<br />
interest in what happens in relation to these matters, but we<br />
had thought that because of the present American law in relation<br />
to tuna fishing that an involvement with the United States could<br />
be beneficial to Pacific nations. That would enable them to<br />
override their present law, and in a sense bring tuna fishing under<br />
regulation. The Pacific States are taking the view that at this<br />
stage they don't want a relationship with the United States they<br />
want to sort out their own arrangements first. Since this is a<br />
matter that affects them, I think that is what is important, and<br />
Australia will provide every assistance it can to see that the<br />
Forum Fisheries Agency is launched as speedily as possible, and<br />
launched with a useful and constructive charter and in a sensible<br />
way. Then again in the terms of the agreement and resolution<br />
that were passed at the last Forum meeting, at a later point the<br />
wider issues will again be discussed. I think that was a sensible<br />
resolution of contrary points of view. Australia put a point of<br />
view at the Forum meeting, but having put it as far as we are<br />
concerned it is the majority view of the Pacific nations that<br />
ought to prevail, because they are the nations that are affected<br />
by whatever arrangements might be made. It would be quite wrong<br />
for Australia to seek to argue further her own view or seek to<br />
/ 4 </p>
<p>-4<br />
have that view imposed. I wouldn't be a party to that for one<br />
minute. I don't think there is any difference between ourselves<br />
and Papua-New Guinea on this issue, because the Prime Minister<br />
indicated to me this morning that he is not adverse to re-examining<br />
the wider question at a later point. Australia is completely<br />
relaxed about the issue. We want arrangements that suit the<br />
national aspirations of Pacific nations, and I think that's what<br />
we ' ye got.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, is your government considering giving political<br />
asylum to the Papuan Freedom Fighters?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I haven't heard of that question raised. We've certainly got no<br />
plans in that direction at all.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, the Leader of the Opposition ( remainder of<br />
question inaudible).<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
If any part of the aid that we did provide each year was directly<br />
to the Parliament building, that would be for Papua-New Guinea<br />
to decide. The whole purpose of the grant that we do provide to<br />
Papua-New Guinea is that it is in grant form, and it is spent as<br />
Papua-New Guinea's chooses. So, within that sum, it is for<br />
Papua-New Guinea to determine their priorities. I thought the<br />
Leader of the Opposition was making the point that he rather<br />
thought Papua-New Guinea would have a permanent Parliament House<br />
before Australia, so maybe Papua-New Guinea should help us with<br />
ours. Question: On the subject of ( inaudible), the Papua-New Guinean government<br />
has requested the United Nations ( remainder inaudible).<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'm not advised on this point. Obviously if a request was put<br />
to us by Papua-New Guinea we would consider it seriously, as we<br />
would any communication from Papua-New Guinea, official<br />
communication. I'm not advised of the totality of the consequences<br />
of such a matter at the moment, and before giving a definitive<br />
response I'd certainly want to liook at it closely.<br />
Question: You can't see any particular problem with it though? </p>
<p>Prime Minister:<br />
I don't think I want to add to what I've already said.<br />
Question: ( Totally inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'd hope that we could have a ceremony in Australia before<br />
Christmas, and I would hope it might be a ceremony in which<br />
both Torres Strait Islanders and people from Daru and others<br />
as necessary will amongst themselves be involved. Rather than<br />
just the Prime Ministers getting together in a room and signing<br />
it, I think it is an historic agreement. I don't know any other<br />
agreement of the same time of that nature. There has been a<br />
great deal of good will on both sides, and so much of it has<br />
been motivated by which to protect the traditional way of life<br />
of Torres Strait Islanders and people of Daru and the coastal<br />
regions, and therefore the final ceremony is thought appropriate.<br />
I think it would be good if figures from these people could also<br />
be present during the occasion.<br />
Question: Are you suggesting that it might be signed in the islands<br />
themselves? Prime Minister:<br />
No I don't think so. It will probably be signed in Canberra.<br />
That's the present intention.<br />
Question: Mr Edwards did mention certain events in Victoria at the weekend.<br />
I was wondering if you would care to add to the comments you<br />
made last night.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
We all know that there have been a number of State issues<br />
involved that have run furiously in Victorian newspapers and<br />
other newspapers in Australia over many many months. Indeed<br />
one particular issue was running for years, and quite clearly<br />
that issue had an impact on events within Victoria. I think it's<br />
rather naive to suggest that the result of that election was not<br />
influenced by State events.<br />
Question: Trees in St. Kilda road is another long-standing issue in Melbourne. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
That has always been an issue I think.<br />
Question: Does that by-election nevertheless on that issue you were alluding<br />
to prompt you into any sort of Federal action? It runs over a<br />
little bit into Canberra.<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Not really I don't think, no. What people I think fail to<br />
understand, and maybe not enought are yet seeing, is that our<br />
policies in many ways are now starting to work in a very real<br />
way. Having said interest rates were coming down they are,<br />
the Reserve Bank has been operating in the markets on the bond<br />
rates over the last month since the indigestion caused by the<br />
special method of financing Commonwealth formal loans has been<br />
completed, and the rates have moved down again. Now that's going<br />
to flow into other areas. But one of the very pleasing things<br />
that I've seen over the last two to three months, and it's only<br />
in that time that it has emerged, is the number of industries<br />
that are saying to me that their costs are competitive, they<br />
are getting a better share of the local market, and they can<br />
get into exports. All sorts of things, it might very often be<br />
in small industries employing a hundred people, 150 people.<br />
Womens underwear, foundation garments, are being made in Victoria<br />
and exported to Japan. I have used colour television sets to<br />
Hong Kong on many occasions. Furniture made in Brisbane going<br />
to Sweden. A number of these are in labour intensive areas,<br />
where Australians if they produce something well can compete.<br />
I don't want it to be a commercial, but the latest automobile<br />
to hit the Australian market I think is a very, very good vehicle<br />
indeed, and I hope its competitor that comes on the market early<br />
next year will be equally good. But the more pleasing thing<br />
about that is that General Motors have told me that they believe<br />
their costs are competitive with Germany and with the United States;<br />
they are rebuilding an export organisation; budgeting for a larger<br />
number of exports; and control is slowly getting back in the area<br />
of activity that had been lost for a long while. That is good news,<br />
they have put on a lot of people over the last six or eight months,<br />
and they intend to put on more over the next few months. This is<br />
happening on a number of areas throughout activity in Australia.<br />
We alway knew that our policies were going to take some time to<br />
w ork, but they are starting to work, and I think that should be a<br />
cause for great satisfaction for all people in Australia, and<br />
especially for the working men and women of Australia.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, did you raise with Mr Somare the question of<br />
( inaudible) sugar from the EEC countries?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
No I didn't. No. But you know that there has been GATT action<br />
in relation to that, and I think that's on track. / 7 </p>
<p>-7<br />
Question: Mr Garland indicated that there was a large amount of support<br />
for Australia in GATT. Do you think that will be effective in<br />
stopping the EEC from doing this in other areas, particularly in<br />
the Pacific region where they seem to be increasingly interested?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well, I would certainly hope so. Everyone one speaks to the<br />
Germans have recognised that this kind of activity is damaging<br />
to relationships with other countries, such as Australia they<br />
believe it is not a good activity, that it ought to stop. But<br />
I haven't got the slightest doubt, I can't put any kind of ( inaudible)<br />
on it, but I haven't got the slightest doubt that at some stage<br />
there will be a change in the common agricultural policies, and<br />
I'm not talking of revolution in relation to it, because we know<br />
that European farmers are going to continue to be protected, but<br />
we are talking about changes at the margin and changes in the<br />
policies of export subsidies, because the weight the total<br />
weight and the burden of the subsidies on the taxpayers of<br />
Europe, there will be a shift and change for that factor alone.<br />
Now if our advocacy can help to bring a change sooner rather than<br />
later that's obviously to our advantage. Something like $ 12,000 m.<br />
a year is spent on subsidies. That, in Australian terms and in<br />
Papua-New Guinean terms is a reasonable amount of money. It's<br />
worth noting that their subsidies in this area are twice what the<br />
developping world asked for by way of a foundation fund, the<br />
Common Fund. That tends to put that into perspective too.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, there was a report earlier from Canberra this<br />
morning that said you had been invited to economic summfti in<br />
Tokyo next June. Can you confirm that, and if so what is its<br />
significance?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I'd like to have a look at that report. I wouldn't normally<br />
expect Australia to be involved in an economic summit, and I<br />
have said that in the Parliament on other occasions and given<br />
specific reasons for it. But there have been some discussions<br />
in relation to this -not of Australia's initiative I might add.<br />
But I'd like to have a look at that report before commenting.<br />
Question: on Japan's initiative?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well let me just say not on Australia's initiative. / 8 </p>
<p>8<br />
Prime Minister ( continued):<br />
I wouldn't want that reported back as an off-hand answer to an<br />
invitation. I think the point's to be made that on the basis<br />
of the size of the Parliament, Australia would not expect to be<br />
present at that kind of meeting. But views have been expressed<br />
about the forthcoming summit because of its geographic location.<br />
Question: ( inaudible)<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
I think there needs to be co-operation in this area, because<br />
the 200 mile economic zones of both countries obviously impinge,<br />
and as you know, we both don't have a clear 200 miles between<br />
Australia and Papua-New Guinea, so policies affecting these areas<br />
of reconcentration and co-operation are well worth pursuing, and<br />
I'm sure that this will take place.<br />
Question: Prime Minister, one last point, is Mr Whitlam going to be a<br />
constant travelling companion?<br />
Prime Minister:<br />
Well I think that's up to him. Of course he is welcome. I was<br />
very surprised to see some comments in the Media before I came<br />
that he might not be, or surprise that he was coming up on the<br />
same aircraft. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
