<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>916</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESENTATION OF AWARDS TO SCHOOLS OF ART AND ARCHITECTURE, ROYAL MELBOURNE INSITITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, MELBOURNE - 10TH APRIL, 1964 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/04/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000916_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESENTATION OF A~ dARDS TO SCHOOLS OF ART<br />
AND ARCHITE'CTURE ROYAL MELBOURNE INSTITUTE<br />
OF TECHN6LOGY, MELBOURNE APRIL. 1961<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies.<br />
Sir and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I am pretty good at giving things away, but I regret<br />
to say to those who are waiting to get the awards in their<br />
clutches that they have to l~ isten to me for a few minutes first.<br />
This seems to be the drill.<br />
When you said, Sir, just towards the end of your<br />
remarks that you hoped the day would never come when a lot of<br />
data was fed into one end of a computer and a painting in oils<br />
came out at the other, I wasn't half so surprised as you were.<br />
I've seen quite a few of late that looked as if they had been<br />
produced in exactly that fashion. ( Laughter) However, I am<br />
never controversial about these matters. I won't go further<br />
than that. Butl~ it's quite true Sir that here we celebrate<br />
the marriage of science and ari. 1his is a very great<br />
technological institute, very well known all over Australia,<br />
and in a technological age ithas a very great deal to<br />
contribute to the life of thetcountry. But art has its own<br />
place and, I hope, an enduring one, and however scientific we<br />
become, I hope we will never quite lose our sense of beauty,<br />
our sense of capturing in some form or another something that<br />
we can Jive with and enjoy and something that we can pass on<br />
to succeeding generations as part of the proof that we are<br />
civilised, A lot of people think that civilisation is best<br />
expressed by supersonic aircraft, by the telephone which never<br />
stops ringing and on which you sometimes get the caller<br />
television in which my taste I am happy to say, is of tUe<br />
Tese are all very useful things to have around but<br />
they are not any necessary proof of civilisation. But here,<br />
particularly in this section, you are dealing with matters of<br />
a different kind, matters I think which will recommend us to<br />
our successors even more than some of the applied scientific<br />
affairs with which we become increasingly familiar,<br />
Architecture, as I was reminded just before I sat<br />
down iste father or mother or is it both? ( Laughter) of<br />
all thesarts. I suppose that's because the primitive Eskimo<br />
built an igloo and left a pormanent mark on architecture, or<br />
somebody else leaned something up against a cliff and left<br />
another permanent mark on architecture. I am prepared to<br />
admit that architecture is one of the great and enduring arts,<br />
today a science an engineering feat. All I venture to say<br />
is that I hope It will never lose its conception that in<br />
addition to being a scientific affair and an engineering<br />
enterprise it is a contribution to art, whatever the form<br />
of the building may be.<br />
One of my troubles about that, if I may say this<br />
to my architectural tutor, is that I do think nowadays that<br />
we are tending to lose a little individuality that we are<br />
tending to internationalise architectural design. I sometimes<br />
fear that in fifty yearst time, it will be very hard except by </p>
<p>-2-<br />
looking for some water, some stream, some lake, to distinguish<br />
one city from another. This, I think, would be a tragedy.<br />
You take London, which is already beginning up in<br />
the city to incorporate some of what I will call the international<br />
ideas on architecture, Well, when I first knew it indeed as<br />
a great deal of it still stands, London has character, a<br />
character of its own, Quite true that the buildings tended<br />
to be lower; quite true that a place like Bush House could at<br />
one time be referred to enthusiastically as a skyscraper when<br />
it wasn't. But London and Portland Stone and the whole quality<br />
and character of the architectural landscape had a unique<br />
quality, I think, of its own.<br />
I remember many, many years ago we -ere having lunch<br />
with James Bone ( Muirhead Bonets brother)ø James Bone was the<br />
London Editor of what was then called the " Manchester Guardian"<br />
and a brilliant writer and essayist, and he said to me, " What<br />
is your most vivid impression about London." I said, " Oh,<br />
Portland Stone. Look at it. ' Jashed white and brilliant where<br />
the weather takes it and full of dark velvety shadows where the<br />
weather doesn't take it, maturing so quickly, getting a quality,<br />
a patina of its own so soon." He said, " Man your observation<br />
is right." He said, " This is it." " ell," I said, it is<br />
almost to me a thuab-print of the London scene,'" He promptly<br />
then, to my immense satisfaction, pulled dovrn a book that he<br />
had written in which he had used that very expression, a book<br />
called the " London Perambulator". It is so good that it has<br />
never been a best-sellera ( Laughter)<br />
Do you see what I mean? It will b a poor day when<br />
any nation loses its own character and becomes merely part of<br />
the general mass of mankind, It will be a poor day when our<br />
own architecture in Australia doesn't possess some quality of<br />
its own which indicates to us and to the onlookers something<br />
of the feeling and spirit of Australia. Itts all right to say,<br />
as no doubt people do occasionally that the Georgian architects<br />
of Nash Adam, so on, the Adam Brothers, are now outdated and<br />
they diL't know much about the problems of lighting and all<br />
this kind of thing, but they did, and those like them, make a<br />
,.; ontribution to the century of good taste which nobody has quite<br />
succeeded in destroying. T has disappeared in many places<br />
but there it is. It is something that you don't see anywhere<br />
else, And the same, Sir, if I may say so, goes about art,<br />
about depictive art, Let's take painting. Now, I have no<br />
feeling of resistance to any form of experimentation in painting.<br />
Some I understand and some I don't. I suppose that occasionally<br />
applies to the painter himself for all I know but there it is,<br />
and so be it that he has learnt the elements ol his craft, so<br />
be it he does know about drawing and about putting on paint and<br />
about getting a sense of modelling and composition-give him<br />
all that and he is a free man to investigate any field that he<br />
likes and I do hope again that we won't develop into a state<br />
of aflairs in which a particular composition, a particular<br />
abstract, a particular whatever-it-may-be looks as if it might<br />
have been painted anywhere in the world. In other words,<br />
that this is just part of a uniform international movement,<br />
Letts have our own character in our work and see that<br />
it interprets something of our own feelings, our own environment,<br />
our own upbringingg our own sense of our own nationality. I am<br />
not a great believer in uniformity. I would hate to think that<br />
s. o. o./ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
the time would come when neither our buildings nor our pictures<br />
nor our sculpturescouild be distinguished from the buildings and<br />
pictures and sculptures of any other country in the world.<br />
Let's have a bit of good, healthy individualism on this matter.<br />
And I think the right way to bring that about if<br />
I may say so, is to do what you do here, to have people taught-,<br />
those who were enthusiasts those who want to do these magnificent<br />
things, to have them taughi the elements, and it is essential<br />
that they should be, Nobody could make a speech that anybody<br />
would listen to unless he understood the language that he was<br />
using and had understood its composition, how it is made up, how<br />
it balances itself. These are all part of the rudiments of the<br />
kind of education that ultimately enables a man or woman to get<br />
up and make a speech or to write something that may be understood<br />
and enjoyed, and similarly, you cannot, at your peril, neglect<br />
the basic training in any of these arts.<br />
Nowl Sir, yon said quite rightly that I have suffered<br />
considerably from artists in my time. There are two classes of<br />
portrait-painter fcr example, One is the chap who really<br />
legitimately gets you to sit for him. If he is an imaginative,<br />
gay character, he chatters to you and you chatter to him a~ nd in<br />
the meantime he gets down some resemblance to you on canvas.<br />
There is the other and more earnest fellow who poses you in the<br />
chair and then says " You see that knot on the window over<br />
there? Now, if you iwouldn't mind that's right, put your<br />
head back a bit, yes just watch that." And as you<br />
watch that ( Laughter) you go to sleep. I may say I am not a<br />
bad sitter because I lo stay awake. On each occasion when Ilve<br />
been sitting for a portrait, I have devoted the whole of the<br />
time to preparing a speech on the Budget, ( Laughter) On one<br />
occasion I composed an entire policy speech under the influence<br />
of Ivor ? Iele. This is, I think, a good thirg.<br />
But I was told by one portrait-painter that he had to<br />
paint a famous general, and the famous general wanted to be painted<br />
in a rather heavy uniform and it was very hot weather in a veiry<br />
hot country an'. the famous soldier nominated after lunch for the<br />
sittings. He had a good lunch and he would come in and sit and<br />
in three minutes he would be asleep. It is very difficult to<br />
paint a sleeping mane The artist said, " Well, I wonder whether<br />
you can bring your personal assistant with you, Sir?" having had<br />
three awful failures, you see, " and talk with hm and this will<br />
help to keep you awake and give me a chance." So the personal<br />
assistant came the next time and sat there, and in three minutes<br />
they were both asleep. ( Laughter) The artist then said. " Sir,<br />
I am terribly sorry, could I have just one sitting after<br />
breakfast?" and he had one and, without mentioning any names,<br />
you may see it in the War Memorial at Canberra. One sitting.<br />
The other experience, of course, that I have had is<br />
being sent portraits by people who have never seen me ( Laughter)<br />
but who have looked at alleged photographs of me in the Press.<br />
These arrive at quite a steady rate at my house a couple of times<br />
a year, and these are very embarrassing because they are not<br />
always good. ( Laughter) I must confess that I have only been<br />
modelled if thatts the right word once and that was when I<br />
had to come up here and sit for Victor, you see, on several<br />
occasions, and he put me in a chair, perched me up a bit, had a<br />
look, got this great mass of stuff and slapped it around and<br />
then began to do this and that. He seemed to me I being of an<br />
ample build, to devote too much time to putting bits on ( Laughter)<br />
0/ 4 </p>
<p>and too little time to taking bits off, But still, after a<br />
couple of these sittings, I thought that he had a most<br />
encouraging head, but the next time I came up, he had done<br />
two more. He was practically running a raffle with himself<br />
as to which one of them he regarded as being the best,<br />
( Laughter) But I must say that he was quite civil about it,<br />
I enjoyed it, Each time I arrived downstairs, I received a<br />
warm welcome from such students as were around and when I<br />
left, I received an equally warm farewell. AnA therefore~ I have,<br />
in a sense, suffered from people of thf. s kind but . L rematn<br />
their friend and I remain their admirer.<br />
I for one, am tremendously proud of the stream<br />
of Australian art in all its stages going back to the original<br />
work done in the beginning of the nineteenth century yes,<br />
it's old-fashioned to us, you see every leaf on eve.-y twig but<br />
it had a qualicy of its own. It nowr has tremendous historic<br />
interest, Then we have moved onthere through the influence<br />
of the impressionists and have come on now to a later stage<br />
with other influenc3es and I really believe that if you were to<br />
mount a perfect and wall b&amp; lanced historical exhibition of<br />
Australian painting and trallan drawing, you would have<br />
just about as interestin g/ liece of history as you could find.<br />
I know that we did it up to 3 point in the exhibition that<br />
went to the late G~ lery in London, But a comprehensive one.<br />
It would be splendid. All the people who like the very oldfashioned<br />
would be down that end of the gallery and people~<br />
like myself who have a secret and not-so-secret passion for<br />
the impressionists would be about here and all my more modern<br />
and up-to-date friends one or two of whom I see hero today,<br />
would be up at this ena of the gallery. But we could move around<br />
and get to know each other and feel that we were looking at<br />
something of historic interest0<br />
There are many things for which we think we may be<br />
remembered but for which we may ' turn out to be forgotten and<br />
I believe that art is long and art is enduring, wvhether It is<br />
the art of the architoct or the art of the painter or the art<br />
of the draughtsman of the decorator all these varied forms<br />
that I have been glancing at this afternoon this is something<br />
Ei., during. It doesnt disappear with yesterh. yts newspaper,<br />
it doesntt find the fate of something that is written on water,<br />
I believe it endures and your business here is to see that those<br />
who come through here, through this division of this Institute,<br />
will be all the time aiming to make their contribution to<br />
something that has an enduring quality and an enduring<br />
chara cter. And I know that the work here is done well, the<br />
instructional work here is on a very high level and I am<br />
therefore delighted to have been with you this afternoon, to<br />
have stood for a few minutes between those who have been<br />
awarded the prizes and the prizes that they will receive.<br />
I am told I hope rightly all I do is to hand over an<br />
envelope. This seems to me to be an admirable idea because<br />
you can't put anything heavy in an envelope but you can put<br />
paper that folds, so I hope it works out that way. Thank<br />
you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
