<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6511</transcript-id>
    <title>STATE AFFAIR (CHANNEL 7 WITH HOWARD SATTLER),  ELECTION CAMPAIGN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006511.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><br />DATE TOPIC STATE AFFAIR ( Channel 7 with Howard Sattler)<br />FRIDAY 19 OCTOBER 1984<br />ELECTION CAMPAIGN interview with. the Prime Ninister</p>
<p><strong>SATTLER:</strong> Why are you bothering to debate Andrew Pcacock when you're so far ahead? You've got nothing to win.</p>
<p><br /><strong>PM </strong>Well it's true that the challenger in those circumstances has always had some advantage. But it seemed to me that I had said before that there should be a debate. And the only question that had arisen as to whether there would not be was because of the untenable behaviour of the Leader of the ODposition over recent months. But I believed then in the circumstances that it ws appropriate to have the debate. I debate him all the time in parliament. I have no fear or worry about debating him.</p>
<p><br /><strong>SATTLER: </strong>Ronald Reagan said that of a fellow called Walter Mondale.<br />.9<br />o: e<br />Vell he did. l'rra<br />alonad lt-gar n a bit oldar. V K 7. ' e<br />P., q N.. 1TER<br />z'<br />: r: t</p>
<p>PM. .2 PERTH<br />President because, I think, of his age. But there's another debate to go. I wouldn't write off President fleagan.</p>
<p><br /><strong>SATTLER:</strong> A lot of people wionder why you're campaigning at all. I mean you're so far ahead and why not just say nothing?</p>
<p><br /><strong>PM:</strong> Because I believe the pcople are entitled,-H~ ward, to a full<br />exposition and a continuous exposition from me. I don't think it<br />would do justice to the Australi. n peopla for me to say to them<br />well I know you support me and the Government and I take that for<br />granted. I want to gro to the people and do really two, things: to<br />explain what we've done to justify the trust they'imposed in us,<br />how together this Government and t: he people have changed Australia<br />into a much better place nowv than it was before; and, to contrast<br />our programme and wvhat we of-fer for the Suture against the abysmal<br />performance of the valternative governmenz._ I think they're<br />entitled to a full programme from me and they'll get it.</p>
<p><br />SATTLER: Well wve thou~ ght we'd go out and ask some of the people what t~ iey'd like to asl1, you, rather thant people like me hogging all1 the quostions. So, here's the first one.  lighto Howard.</p>
<p><br />QUESTION: Mr Hawke I would like to ask, you one q~ uestion. MTat would be your top priority as far as you're concerned? To ma I think th~. t a man or a girl having a job is the highest priority in ' Cheir<br />life? PH: I agfree with you. And that's vhat we've made our~ top) prYiolityr</p>
<p>PM. <br />Howard, in the period we've been in Government. I said. as you<br />will recall during the last election campaign, that we would do<br />these things: we would halt the enormous rise in unemployment.<br />In the twelve months before came to office there was an increase<br />of a quarter of a million in unemployment, We've done that.<br />We've reduced unemployment from 10.3 per cent down to 8.6 per cent.<br />SATTLER: From a senior citizen to a young man. Let's* hear what he has<br />to say.<br />PM: Young man.<br />QUESTION: I was just wondering, mate, how come you don't think of some ideas<br />like putting unemployed people in houses and giving them fool<br />parcels instead. of giving them dole cheques and them m-iaybe they'd<br />want to work a bit. You know, go out anid get a job, instead of<br />burmning around, you know, ' cause they need smokes and they need<br />to go out every now and agein.<br />Well we've, we have in fact increa,. ed the funding that's<br />Qavailable for honusing for the unemployed.. But we think that the<br />riost important thing that vie can do for the unemployed is to<br />mahe worlt.<br />QUESTI ON:<br />M. y name's Joanna and I'd like to 1, now if you think you're good<br />look; ing?<br />( Lauahter) I'm not as good looking'at the moment ac I vns. I'lv( e<br />got a bit of a shiner. Oh passing, I think.</p>
<p>PEI... 4 PERTH<br />SATT. ER:<br />Let's talk about your job now and I think the next questionEtr<br />wants to know a little bit about the money you get for it,<br />QUESTION: Hi Mr Hawke, I'm Naomi. How do you justify your high salary?<br />PH: Well I don't set it. All I can say is t. hat as a result of the<br />decisions that I've taken we've knocked back salary increases.<br />If I'd left it to those whose indlependent job it is to determine<br />what it is that I should be paid and others should be paid, it<br />would be much more than it is. We'Ive kniocked back the. increases<br />they suggested.<br />SATTLER: And I think you'll recognise the next questioner.</p>
<p><br />PIA: 17bo'Is this?</p>
<p><br />QUESTION: ( Bill Nassell, 17A Opposition Leader)<br />Prime Minister given that W~ estern Australia's Aboriginal popi1l tion,<br />which is two per cent of the total population of the State, already<br />owns eight per cent of the land area of Western Australia; and<br />given that Labor policy is firmly cozmmitted to the granting of<br />Aboriginal land rights in W~ estern Australia: I ask you how riuch<br />of W~ estern Australia.-you believe should be open to claim by<br />Aborgines on the basis of their race?</p>
<p><br />Pn: 17ell the position</p>
<p><br />BATTLER: You do recognise the questionor?</p>
<p>S' t*<br />S 1<br />PM. .5 PERTH<br />PL4: Well I don't want to be rude. It is Mr Bassell is it?</p>
<p><br />SATTLER: It is Mr Hassell.</p>
<p><br />PM: Oh I see. I'm not being rude because I don't believe I've met<br />him before as far as I understand. And he's not a well known<br />figure in the Eastern States of Australia. The answer to that<br />is quite clear. And indeed, today, Mr Burke and I have released<br />a statement which makes the position of the Government of Western<br />Australia and my Government at one. And may I say to Mr Hassell<br />that that position has been endorsed by the miners and I believe<br />that he is very much in a minority on this issue.</p>
<p><br />SATTLER Small business is said to be the backbone of Australia and we<br />thought we'd ask one of Perth's growing businessmen, he certainly<br />is, Alistair Norwood, to ask you a question as well.</p>
<p><br />PM: Sure.</p>
<p>QUESTION: Ur Prime Minister in these times of high unemployment, opportunities<br />in the retail and service industries particularly for school<br />leavers would be much greater if these industries could operate<br />extended hours without the burden of penalty rates thereby allowing<br />the use of additional staff. Has your Government considered the<br />effects on unemployment by the introduction of n fired hourly rate<br />of pay, and is there any plan to introduce such a measure?<br />p11:<br />No I understand that there's been argutment about the effezt of<br />penalty rates, but all I can Sray is that the research that's bsen<br />v? i</p>
<p>PMI.. 6 TPERTH</p>
<p><br />conducted in Australia and overseas is not conclusive about the<br />impact of relative rates of pay between Juniors and seniors and<br />penalty rates on the levels of employment. But clearly we would<br />not do anything which is going to make more difficult the<br />employment of more people, and particularly young people.</p>
<p><br />SATTLER: So 1984 has been a year of giving, but what about 1985? Are<br />you going to take so much of it back from. us: in taxes maybe<br />capital gains taxes?</p>
<p><br />P11: No certainly not. The Liberal opponents: that we've got are the<br />masters of deceptive promises. 1977 in the election campaign you'!<br />remember the fist full of dollars, vote for us as soon as they<br />were re-elected they grabbed it all back and more.---Nov this is<br />the first goverrnent for a very, very long period which have<br />given the people of Australia real tax cuts. In a matter of days<br />now, in the beginning of November all Australians will receive a<br />real tax cut. And I say real because it's more than was necessary<br />just to cover indexation. If we're just given indexation to cover<br />wages moving into higher brackets that would have been a full year<br />cost of $ 1.3 billion. The real tax cuts that we're giving the<br />people of Australia will cost in a full year $ 2.1 billion. So they<br />are the first real tax cuts. And they will stay and they'll<br />not be taken back.</p>
<p><br /><strong>SATTLER:</strong> ( Introduces segement from Mile Carlton's puppets) He must have known something.</p>
<p><br />p11PMHost of it I enjoy. / 7</p>
<p>P2.. 7 PERTH<br /><strong>SATTLER</strong>: You don't mind him at all?</p>
<p><br /><strong>PM: </strong>No, no. I mean if you let that sort of thing get under your skin you shouldn't be in the business.</p>
<p>SATTLER: Mr Hawke thanks for </p>
<p>PM: Thank-you very much joining us. Howard.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
