<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4103</transcript-id>
    <title>PERTH PRESS CONFERENCE - FRIDAY, 21ST APRIL, 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/04/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004103_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
M~ ~ L1 F76/ 74 74.<br />
FOR PRESS A; RIL 23, 1976<br />
PR AUSS CCUIZF2 PYQD 21ST -A21Re-J 9-7-16<br />
Ct I -a u . a-2&amp; XIy Ute fears of Uio-&amp; -Wio believe<br />
dPalai-: I anti. lhere ~ tIs d" ubt abnout this. t-Ar. Rhititam<br />
was oe heze a wiea ago ama -trying to stax-t ~ ox about~<br />
this particu). ar-3uwject--Re. knows that it it; mischievous<br />
and he knows that it does the econamy ) iax. Tihat' s pzobably<br />
why be Clid it.<br />
11: Fraser, rePoxts have it that the new federalism~ scheme<br />
will mean double i ncom~ e taxation, for all. the Siates<br />
from July neaxt yeax. Is this right?<br />
JijEWiN ; 5Jhere -will bc-, aritax forzTu, on(-assessmfent, One coletir<br />
Trhat 0, oesrP't mean~ cdovble tax-ation..<br />
Blut the tax couldI vary from State to stzate-.<br />
M IST!?: Taxes. very between States nows and vcy-sta-, t-ially. There ' s<br />
W nothing new in that.<br />
The income tax could vary?<br />
the United States?<br />
M'E MItNISTER: More like in C: anaeia.<br />
Is the federalism scheme going to cozft -Ehe t4axpayer more..* y<br />
ME M1N1$ TBR: No,-I trieve At will cost him less beca-Use he lwi-l be RACiG<br />
to see WhO is sPendi-ng his money and that % Ail, mean. that.. ps ple<br />
will be accovntable for what they dio. State Preixers wh<br />
sop port that proposal truly want to be responsible for their<br />
own affairs, as the Premier of tbi! 3 1tate does. N1ow State<br />
Premiers or Leaders of the-Opposition. who say t. iay do, 11t lik!, e<br />
these proposals want. to be able to hide 1b-ehind the aqe oldcry<br />
Canberra hasn' t given me enough mtoney and th eyefore<br />
can't do t<br />
You3 wouldn't have any control over the ov'erall. leve" L of intoxne<br />
tax that was being levied. That wouil( be tip to the Premiers~,<br />
how much they added on to the tax lev-td by the Connsonwe3ti.<br />
ST1I) N:<br />
STION:<br />
ST~ IC'N~<br />
ST ION:<br />
ST I( JN<br />
S T. IN:<br />
' STJ ON<br />
03 MIN I&amp; STBR: MAI79inally </p>
<p>NR 1sar o part Ott r-v nu~~-ta ac-tte<br />
Poliies ' aor n r allrl 1with the q~ nral and overall<br />
econcfiic poiicies that are Ze., azdlu as beiin eS:_ arY for<br />
the-gcO~ d eco-noritic nD~ f Ar stralia. 17' D th' 1at ' iS-Dot<br />
a olues tio-n of vontrol but it ansq ui ion ol consultation.<br />
r&amp; lpi CCDF.-ato--rher. in he pa,: ist Pre oier-; Cofexenric<br />
have just: been baruains, eaich com out with the motthat<br />
can possible be-Clot, in ft-ure-uuncir tha Tiew fegeaia<br />
pr ) osa* i there woui he arn rvonetiwic e; ex<br />
an~ 1 1th-e Prime utoa. lXdr rb e a-Ile to sit dec~ on tocrether<br />
ann d ea.. Uy dis~ uss wbat would be 2-5-st in the ovexall1 intexestu.<br />
of all 4utralliis-it lzwOuld b2 a. Completely different<br />
ciiate id that is wihy I believe IM spite of czotradictions<br />
to thle contranry, wie have beenabl get tbrouqh41. t-wo<br />
Prelnier~ i' ConfereTzea, the last one ' LT zecord txin., wi-th. the<br />
wit. 1 a great deal of goodwill . and believe a great deal of<br />
undrstandingby all parties to thotie Iyarticular Conferenices<br />
and that ncluas. twia Premniers who flontt lhapPEM to~ share , y<br />
-2TR) 1N:, What about the next P11remiers' Confertnce? Are-yo* 4 qoing0<br />
to be as genrerous next tirre?<br />
iIS~ h; L cvnlt think it's a question of qeynerosity thank it': s<br />
a qjuestion' of recoqriisina Somethina that is snsible and a<br />
son,-; ible system. I thJLk that is whtat h as attracted people<br />
to therie particular pro'posals-There w. ere deprediictions<br />
in face of tefirst Conference, there Ifere VwOrse pxedictiops<br />
in face of the seuvnd Conference emd nobody know what to say<br />
whan the Confexence was aver with all mat-ters agreed on this<br />
particular su. bject before twelv'e o'clock.<br />
i-STSON: Can you tell us how far tax. indexation will go in the next<br />
badget.<br />
IMF? MINITR: Not tody, no. 1 would. like to be able to, Wle are daerried<br />
to go as far as we poss ible cin witli index~ ation asid we axe<br />
f ~ 1. y. 1 ana comnpleze~ y rzvnn ittud. to izhat.<br />
, STION: The A. N. Ban% 2ays that economic recovery won't spx-ing from<br />
new investment. Izt says that . it will. fkapend f-n cor~<br />
spending. Do you agree with this assess~ nent?<br />
IME M~ jNISVT~ L: n thi; Oz wiy hbAld or-abaoiute statemept tends to ovarstate<br />
a particiilax po-, ition. Reoovery depends on a nu-nmher of<br />
f ac Lor S.<br />
flST~ ON: no you reu. tly expect the Anstraiiin worer to accept<br />
less wag7as? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
;-N5 STR-Nc im '_ Fñ t&amp; 7. Ttr -ticF ' r ofI r-ai ic~ s<br />
than IPdersr.<br />
2 asat -, uarxIjY Waq -c: A sz -4-o *:&gt; ar_-vienc<br />
. oby~ a faz -tile-n e~ Ef thos its~ vec<br />
~~ Th 11rG-t. If o th I f 13 2 i -nC a-2. 7h eY<br />
imi2, the " rati c 2~ vexy ixl<br />
tbi~~ t--ñ trojnfpCa ~ zir -' rases os~<br />
du h'in -or avclle alc-' anI' Omc* iI Iu. tbjI'TkR 2i' c: o6 a1Eo<br />
und -rstand that ñ~~ eis Tjot : 11y3 ~ In, qetig ighr wagez<br />
if his neiq'hbour thexreby l'bes'is ) or,.<br />
STION: PCC1: rding to the latest Trading 13ank ppiore&amp; s le are savJ.,-j<br />
at a very high level. that maet with yolar approval or<br />
woi-ld you pr-Lfer that they wuEt ojutL_ and spent.<br />
14E tNS~ Teear-indicatinon-s that. . Over th~ e pa5t tvo<br />
or three years people havie become. concerned albout the fut-uxe<br />
of their jo'bs. Thley have also become COPCex-nexl ' ecauase 01E<br />
coyit-. tantly raisang prices. Tahs uelpeopt to save<br />
! nore than thbey wouxld. nor-mally save. Saving in Itself is<br />
good and sensible but if -failiies are saving i , ioxe than theyinight<br />
regard as noxinal or xeason bIl~ e bLecause of particular<br />
c ir cu-ms tan-c s o f i Ila U41. o3 or f e ar of ui . Qixnt ths can n<br />
f act add to some of the dif ficulties that we:_ axe ha-virno<br />
at the present time. L~ et i. nc take just ona sa! Tmple if yo Inave<br />
got families all around Australia Baying that t-hey ax e<br />
not going to buy a motor car this year Lcatse* of their conCmcrnj<br />
for the future, obviougly -that has a SIgi -f'. car't impact; fx t-a<br />
fI utuayre toem ppelcoypmlee nits anddo wpxhoatd uycotui orn. o ormf atlhlye dmoo. tor iii'nyeohaust xyh'a. d planneawdh z<br />
to buy a new re-rigerar-or then buy it, if youo bad planned to<br />
-buy a new automobile, then buy' it, and don't pos tpone these<br />
purchases.<br />
3STION: There is nothing that you Would thinyk of doi-ng to enOuage<br />
people to go out and buy a new refrigerator or car?<br />
4.1<br />
( FME lJIN. SiTER: I have said over tbe past month or so, puople should spend<br />
as they normally would because if you get families all ar-c-nd<br />
the country postponing their nornmal epcnituires, obviously4<br />
tha~ t h~ as a cuumulative effect on productia'ori cind Aobs in P. large I<br />
ncber of~ ldustriess andl we don't , iant thZ-at to : c~<br />
3, ON Ax o eeigi mind that pxices axe going up all the ' time<br />
and that it is safer to buy now thanc-to Wait Until the erO<br />
of the. year when it would cost wiore?<br />
[ ME MTNT$ TR: That is a factor that people could very sensib. 1 take irto<br />
account in deciding to buy maybe a little earlie~ r thavi they<br />
o, , h w i se wol.. 3ut : 1 would alec h 1-that result o<br />
the Arbitration Commission. proceed inqt Over the nex~ t few days<br />
that we are going to get%-a syatem of.' wage fixation withini<br />
indexation qruideliries thbat will enable ug to break the back<br />
of inflation and that will do an enormous amount for co~ nfidence </p>
<p>-4-<br />
throcGae. hout t-he hustraIi an CO) TO~ M~ i Tty,<br />
* STIONI: That co. es before price xc: trictions?<br />
MP) E 14-~ ISTER1: There if, already price restriction. UPThere is a Prices<br />
, luhstficatinnf Trribunal.. No cornpanx has brokj) en quideli'nes<br />
laid down by that Tribanal. ITicre have bezen quite a nmh~ er<br />
-lt~ ce v--ions that I-ave sotighl to 7,-thiher wage incxcases<br />
tha th e cq39ielinc-s would have periltted aiiid so. the two bocii-es<br />
cdcn't operate-in the ., aary . The Arbit~ cation Cvwrkissioru<br />
tereis to set riin1fla not maim ap th. e; Prices iu-stific-ation<br />
Tilb~ onal the way it :_-perates va~ ry 3ejtiysets aimn<br />
I 4nmit E; There has been a great shift Fvway fromn prsfitg to<br />
Wallies Over the ThsLtt-o Or thxce x'ea~ cz. That is why a nmIe<br />
olf LfiXjii5 FM1VOAL1-t0hhV iVofey for inveS" CTient. Ta t JL S<br />
whv a nujr~ er of firmns h~ ave contsacted Lind why t-here axe<br />
job"-S aviailabile n) ow thban most of us wouLi Iide to see. !, he oftb<br />
point I wou-ilk to make An this area~ Act * s assume the<br />
' overnmert does ?. IX thu tMn~ is thbat are rigqh-t in terms'.<br />
oa zxensibLe econoimic strategy for rcecovery and cj row. tjh, anod<br />
1 beieve -the start wie have -made in this dir-ction Lee<br />
right, ar, 0 that the poiswe 31ave 1rrtrcdcixd are right but.<br />
thco t-est strategy tJebt ocsir e aqly destxoyece<br />
in the wanes area, ar,( I 1 bCj4-jev the Australi'an comm-junity' is<br />
com~ ing to ,; nd:;-rstarjd. t-hat.<br />
' A ON We have s; ome local reaction -to -jhe cc,.-ing) rce-sus.. Some people<br />
say that the n ed qiestionnaire r'oloses some Tpossible<br />
_ irlrinrgc_ -ent o0 avacy. D~ o you ha-ve'a ' Cear; tion to tUhis?<br />
:. mTe MJvtsteL-: I say~ this reor; in U&amp; e newspapers today and . T have as') edl<br />
qjuestions ab) out it. I ),_ now thcer: e is always con-stant<br />
from those who collect the statisetics -to for more questi-o<br />
atndl cet mora Ii~ Txhnitko~.~ e ie tihat csvn<br />
ai~ asked that auqfht nt o be b: ut* have a; 3ked for a report<br />
in this particnular ingtance. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
