<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>758</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 51/1963 - OVERSEAS VISIT - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000758.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P, M. No, 51/ 1963<br />
OVERSEAS VISIT<br />
Statement by the Prime MinisterL,. the Rt, Ho Sir Robet Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies, will leave<br />
Sydney on Thursday, June 13 by Qantas, flying direct to London<br />
through the Middle Easto He will fly from Canberra to Sydney<br />
on Wednesday, June 12,<br />
During his overseas jour) ney, lasting for one<br />
month, the Priime Minister wi. ll have discussions with the Prime<br />
Minister of Great Eritain, Mr. Harold Macmillan and other<br />
members of the British Cabinet on matters of mutual interest<br />
including trade and international affairs, He will also meet<br />
the President of the United States, Mr, Kennedy, in Washington,<br />
and the Prime Minister of Canada7 Mr. Lester Pearson, and<br />
members of the Canadian Cabinet in Ci: tawa,<br />
The Prime Minister's itinerary provides for him<br />
to be in Edinburgh on July 1I where he will be installed in<br />
the Order of the Thistle in the Order's Chapel in St. Giles'<br />
Cathedral at a ceremony to be attended by Her Majesty The<br />
Queen. Sir Robert will fly from London to New York on<br />
July 2. On July 3, he will go to Charlottesville, Virginia,<br />
where on Independence Day, July 4, at the invitation of the<br />
Jefferson Memorial Fcu. ndation, he will deliver the Thomas<br />
Jefferson Memorial Oration at Jefferson's home, Monticello.<br />
On July 5, the Prime Ministur will be in Ottawa<br />
and on July 8 and 9 in Washington,<br />
He will leave San Francisco on July 11, arriving<br />
in Sydney on Saturday, July 13.<br />
Dame Pattie Menzies will accompany Sir Robert and<br />
their elder son, Mr Kenneth Menzies, who is travelling<br />
privately, will also be with them on the journey,<br />
Two members of the Prime Ministerts personal<br />
staff, Miss L. H. Craig, private secretary, and Mr. R. C. Maley,<br />
press secretary, will also be in the party,<br />
Mr. J. F, Nimmo, Deputy Secretary of the Prime<br />
Minister's Department2 is travelling to London ahead of the<br />
Prime Minister to assist in the London and other discussions,<br />
CANBERRA, 11th June, 1963. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
