<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9532</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP ERRORS IN THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009532.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 2q3 25/ 9<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP<br />
ERRORS IN THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD<br />
The Federal Government has no plans to introduce a permanent honour<br />
guard to officiate at ceremonial welcomes and no such plan has been<br />
considered by me.<br />
The story in today's Sydney Morning Herald suggesting that I asked the<br />
Defence Department to consider forming such a permanent honour<br />
guard is riddled with errors and omits a specific denial issued by my<br />
office last night.<br />
My office told the newspaper such a guard would be " out of the<br />
question" due to the high cost of establishing such a unit.<br />
I understand that the newspaper made no effort to contact Senator Ray<br />
or his office about the story.<br />
I have not suggested to the Department of Defence that it consider<br />
forming a " permanent honour guard" for visiting dignitaries.<br />
Last year I asked PM&amp; C officials to look at the question of welcoming<br />
ceremonies to see if their form was still relevant to contemporary<br />
Australia.<br />
As a result, the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet had some<br />
official level discussions, including with the Department of Defence,<br />
about these matters.<br />
The Defence Department advised PM&amp; C officials that the ADF is finding<br />
it increasingly difficult to meet the traditional requirements for honour<br />
guards to greet high-level civilian and military visitors as growing<br />
numbers of uniformed defence personnel are now located out of<br />
Canberra. </p>
<p>Defence advised that one option to meet this need would be the<br />
formation of a permanent ceremonial guard unit, but that this would be<br />
costly. This Defence proposal was not taken up by my Department and I was<br />
not made aware of it.<br />
I have not been " highly impressed" with " French ceremonial welcomes"<br />
because I have never had a French ceremonial welcome. I have not<br />
made a state visit to France.<br />
No RAAF VIP fleet Boeing 707 has " had a $ 14 million refit", nor is any<br />
$ 14 million refit underway. The newspaper did not ask my office about<br />
this matter. I have in fact specifically ruled out the construction of a<br />
permanent VIP suite in the aircraft.<br />
The only work currently being looked at is on noise mitigation for the VIP<br />
fleet. CANBERRA 29 March 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
