<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>581</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR RELEASE THURSDAY 16/8/1962  FOR FRIDAY MORNING PAPERS P.M.NO 19/1962  VISIT OF KING AND QUEEN OF THAILAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000581.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR RELEASE THURSDAY_ 16/ 8/ 1962 FOR FRIDAY MORNING<br />
PAPERS P, No. 1962<br />
VISIT OF KING AND QUEEN OF THAILAND<br />
Their Majesties King Bhumibcl and Queen Sirikit<br />
of Thailand will pa: s through. Sydney earl on Saturday<br />
morning on their way to New Zealand to begin a State<br />
visit, They will return on August 26th for their State<br />
visit to Australia. Their Majssties will leave Bangkok at 11,30 amY<br />
tomorrow ( Friday) in a Qantas aircraft, chartered by the<br />
Government of Thai. land, and after refuelling at Singapore,<br />
are expected in Darwin at midnight. The Royal couple<br />
will alight at Darwi. n where they will be met by the Minister<br />
for Territories, Mro Hasluck, and the Administrator of<br />
the Northern Territory and Mrso Roger Notto<br />
The aircraft's arrival time of 7 am, in Sydney<br />
is the equivalent of 4 a. mr Bangkok time, and with a<br />
ceremonial arrival in New Zealand and an exacting programme<br />
in prospect, Their Majesties have expressed a wish to remain<br />
aboard the aircraft during its brief stopover in Sydney in<br />
order to obtain as much rest as possible.<br />
While the aircraft is on the ground in Sydney,<br />
arrangements have been made to set accommr. odation aside for<br />
any other members of the party who may wish to alight<br />
The Minister for External Affairs, Sir Garfield<br />
Barwick, will be at the airport to greet the Foreign<br />
Minister of Thailand, Mr. Thanat Khoman who will be accompanying<br />
Their Majesties in both New Zealand and Australia.<br />
CANBERRA, 16th August, 1962, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
