<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24450</transcript-id>
    <title>Growing jobs and small business package to help small businesses invest more, grow more and employ more</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/05/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The 2015 Budget is the next step in the Government’s plan to build a strong, safe and prosperous future for all Australians.</p>
<p>This Budget is about building jobs, growth and opportunity and providing a credible path to surplus.</p>
<p>The new $5.5 billion Growing Jobs and Small Business package will help small businesses invest more, grow more, and employ more.</p>
<p>This package will help employers create jobs and assist Australia’s unemployed, particularly unemployed youth, to build the skills to get into work. </p>
<p>This is the biggest small business initiative in our nation’s history. </p>
<p>The Government is committed to ensuring Australia is the very best place to start and grow a small business. </p>
<p>Small businesses are the engine room of our economy. </p>
<p>96 per cent of all Australia’s businesses are small businesses, employing over 4.5 million people and producing over $330 billion of our nation’s total economic output.</p>
<p>As our economy changes, the role of our small businesses will be even more important. With the economy in transition we are freeing up small business to create new jobs.</p>
<p>At the heart of the Growing Jobs and Small Business package are tax cuts for over 2 million Australian small businesses to help drive investment and employment across our economy. </p>
<p>The 2015 Budget delivers $3.25 billion in tax cuts for small business and $1.75 billion in accelerated depreciation measures in addition to the benefits Australian small businesses are gaining from the abolition of the carbon tax:</p>
<p>•	from 1 July 2015, the Government will cut the company tax rate for up to 780,000 incorporated businesses with annual turnover up to $2 million by 1.5 percentage points to 28.5 per cent;<br />
•	from 1 July 2015, the Government will also provide a 5 per cent tax discount for over one and a half million sole traders, trusts and partnership structures which are unincorporated businesses with annual turnover up to $2 million, capped at $1,000, through their end of year tax return; and<br />
•	from Budget night until 30 June 2017, small businesses with turnover below $2 million will be able to fully and immediately deduct every asset they acquire that is valued up to $20,000 for tax purposes - a substantial increase from the previous $1,000 threshold.</p>
<p>Australian small businesses will have the lowest company tax rate for public and private companies since 1967.</p>
<p>The Growing Jobs and Small Business package also includes measures to reduce the red tape and regulatory impediments that hinder small businesses growth:</p>
<p>•	changes to the Fringe Benefits Tax (FBT) system will expand the FBT exemption for work related portable electronic devices;<br />
•	reforms to Capital Gains Tax (CGT) rollover will enable small businesses to change the legal structure of their business without incurring a CGT liability; and<br />
•	the Government will consult on potential changes to the Corporations Act to reduce compliance costs and make it easier for small proprietary companies to raise new capital.</p>
<p>The Growing Jobs and Small Business package will encourage business start-ups and entrepreneurship:</p>
<p>•	start-ups will be able to immediately deduct professional expenses incurred when they begin a business, such as legal expenses on establishing a company, trust or partnership, rather than writing them off over five years. This will provide immediate cash flow benefits for small businesses;<br />
•	streamlined business registration processes will make it quicker and simpler to set up a new business. A single online registration site will be developed for business registration including company registration;<br />
•	the Government will remove obstacles to crowd-sourced equity funding to help promote small business access to finance by increasing the availability of innovative sources of funding; and<br />
•	from 1 July 2015, expanded tax concessions for Employee Share Schemes will make it easier for small start-up companies to attract and retain the skills and talent they need to grow. </p>
<p>These measures will help encourage investment, innovation and the start-up of new businesses, which will help Australia’s economic future.</p>
<p>The Growing Jobs and Small Business package will also help employers to take on inexperienced and mature workers.</p>
<p>Since the Government was elected, around a quarter of a million new jobs have been created – but there is more work to do.</p>
<p>New measures will focus on making job seekers more employable, reducing the costs of taking on new staff, and bringing job seekers and job providers together. </p>
<p>The Government is investing $6.8 billion to establish jobactive to improve the quality of services delivered to job seekers and employers. The new jobactive system will be focused on results and reward performance not process. </p>
<p>There will be a $1.2 billion pool for wage subsidies to support employers to provide job opportunities and assist job seekers into work.</p>
<p>The Government will also deliver a $331 million Youth Employment Strategy, an $18 million National Work Experience programme, and changes to Restart to make it easier for small businesses to receive Government support when they employ older workers. </p>
<p>The Government’s Growing Jobs and Small Business package will create the right conditions for Australian small businesses to thrive and grow. </p>
<p>Further details on the Government’s Growing Jobs and Small Business package can be found at <a href="http://www.budget.gov.au">www.budget.gov.au</a></p>
<p>12 May 2015</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
