<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6438</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT, PRESS CONFERENCE, TRAVELODGE HOTEL, 8 AUGUST 1984, 5.30PM</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/08/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006438.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4jAUSTAI k<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
Transcript Press Conference Travelodge Hotel<br />
8 August 1984 5.30 pm.<br />
E 0 E Proof Only<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke how did you interpret what Mr Somare<br />
had to say this morning about Mr Lange's position on nuclear<br />
issues. Well the only way it can be interpreted and that was<br />
what he was saying that what individual countries do about<br />
the question of visits of nuclear armed and nuclear powered<br />
ships is a matter for each individual country. I mean he had<br />
no intention of intervening in that position. And I understand<br />
that subsequently he's made that quite clear.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does the election of Mr Lange however boost the<br />
chances of getting a nuclear free Pacific?<br />
No because the question of a nuclear free zone in the<br />
South Pacific had its own momentum from within the countries<br />
of the area. I should qualify my answer by saying to the<br />
extent that Mr Lange's predecessor had been perhaps less than<br />
enthusiastic about the concept it means that we will have<br />
New Zealand supporting the position that I'd been advancing in<br />
the Forum last-year.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are there some problems with the proposal at this<br />
stage. Well only the proposal of taking a concept which is what:<br />
you always have, taking a concept from a position of a concept<br />
into a treaty. That will take some time. But I believe it's<br />
achievable. It's not something that's going to happen overnight.<br />
But there is obviously widespread support amongst the countries<br />
of the region for it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is there division among the South Pacific nations<br />
about the question of nuclear ships passing through the South<br />
Pacific. In other words is that consistent with a nuclear freE!<br />
zone in the South Pacific.<br />
Oh yes, it's consistent with it and we have made it clear<br />
at all times that our proposal for such a nuclear free zone would<br />
embrace the right of ships of our ally, the United States, to<br />
pass through. r* d ~ UinIr fWr nr 1 </p>
<p>JDURNALIST: Well having said that what are the principles<br />
that Australia would be putting to the South Pacific Forum<br />
later this month?<br />
The same principles as we advanced very explicitly<br />
last year and that is that we believe that in this area<br />
it should be a nuclear free zone in terms of the non-storage<br />
or acquisition of nuclear weapons. It should be free from<br />
testing of nuclear explosive devices and there should be<br />
no dumping of nuclear waste products in the area.<br />
JOURNALIST': In between now and the" South Pacific Forum<br />
in two or three weeks time would thiere 11p further communication<br />
with the French Government. No, not with the French Government?<br />
No, not with the French Government directly. What's<br />
been happening at the official level is there's been an<br />
interchange of views and by the time we get to the Forum<br />
we'll be in a position to further discuss this matter<br />
more specifically. It will be after that that I imagine<br />
collectively and perhaps individually there'll be a.<br />
communication to the French Government of the position<br />
of the countries of the region.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you saying Mr Hawke that you'd be happy<br />
with an agreement for a nuclear free zone which allows<br />
individual governments to make a decision as to whether<br />
or not they allow nuclear ship visits?<br />
No, the question of being happy with it, that's what<br />
we ' ye had as our position consistently from the beginning.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke in Geneva Mr Hayden suggested that<br />
Australia might have to have another look at its position<br />
on the bases if progress wasn't made by the Americans towards;<br />
disarmament. What is your comment on that.<br />
I've seen the reference to that. In fact I've spoken<br />
with Bill Hayden today by phone and there is no story here.<br />
What Bill said in his speech in Geneva was precisely what<br />
he has been saying from the time we've been in Government<br />
and that is that we have, as an independent Australian<br />
Government, a view a strong view about the necessity<br />
for moves by the great powers towards nuclear disarmament.<br />
And we have used our position, I think our particular<br />
position, with the United States to put that view. And of<br />
course we've already had, as it were, a positive result<br />
from the exercise of that influence. You will recall that<br />
in November of last year we were able to persuade the<br />
United States to change what had been its previous view<br />
of opposition as to the work of the Committee of Disarmament<br />
to enable the Australian sponsored resolution for work on<br />
a comprehensive test ban treaty to proceed. And the United<br />
States, as a result very substantially of our advocacy to them<br />
changed that vote from opposition to abcstengion. And then<br />
just in June of this year we got their agreement to the form<br />
for a draft memorandum of approach on this issue. So what </p>
<p>P. M. cant Bill was saying in Geneva was really that we<br />
will be continuing to put that view. And in the conversation<br />
I had with him today he indicated to me that the American<br />
representative in Geneva had expressed their approbation<br />
of the view that was put.* And I am confident, as is Bill<br />
Hayden, that with that reaction from the United States<br />
we'll be able to continue into the future what we have<br />
effectively done in the past. And that is being a constructive<br />
and positive ally with the United States in the ANZUS relationship<br />
still to establish that we are not a nation which simply accepts<br />
automatically what any other nation or any superpower does.<br />
We maintain the right which we've exercised to-put our<br />
view strongly and it's a matter of pleasure to both the<br />
Foreign.-Minister and myself that we have been able to<br />
use this special relationship with thepjnited States to<br />
achieve those positive results since November of last year,<br />
and we'll continue to do that.-<br />
JOURNALIST: But the Australian position is, is that it will<br />
review its attitude towards the bases if there's not<br />
satisfactory progress by the U. S. on disarmament.<br />
No, that's putting the emphasis the wrong way.. There<br />
will be a continuation of the position that we've adopted<br />
now, to this point. And that is that we will push in all<br />
the relevant international forums and in our discussions<br />
with the United States the necessity for positive action<br />
to move towards reducing the level of nuclear armaments.<br />
And we have received to this point positive responses<br />
from the United States. So the question of review of the<br />
bases situation doesn't arise. Mr Hayden had been responding<br />
in hypothetical situation and as he pointed out to me the<br />
facts are that the United States has indicated since his<br />
speech in Geneva a very positive response to what he had<br />
to say.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you contact Mr Hayden or how come you were speaking<br />
to him today.<br />
Yes I contacted him by phone.<br />
JOURNALIST: Over this matter?<br />
Yes I wanted to talk to him about that and some we of ten<br />
speak to one another while he's away.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you think the Americans in any<br />
way have been dragging their feet on this disarmament issue.<br />
I don't think we can just stand up and say they've been<br />
dragging their feet. I mean there are -two superpowezs involved<br />
in this situation and both Mr Hayden and I are satisfied from~<br />
the discussion that we've had at our various levels of the<br />
administration that they do want to see positive moves in<br />
this area. They haven't always received the degree of positive<br />
response from the Soviet Union that you would like to see. </p>
<p>P. M. cant Now we are going to continue to press our<br />
position both with the United States, with whom we have a<br />
special relationship. We'll also be putting the view<br />
to the Soviet Union and particularly in regard to the<br />
development we've been able to achieve on disarmament<br />
in regard to the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty. What's<br />
required there to enable that work to proceed is a positive<br />
response from the Soviet Union. And as we've said recently<br />
we will be putting to the Soviet Union that there should<br />
be a positive response from them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke if you are satisfied with the approach<br />
that the-Americans have been adopting why were Mr Hayden's<br />
remarks seen as necessary?<br />
What you've got to understand is that there are two<br />
stages. Mr Hayden made his speech and then he was asked<br />
hypothetical questions following that speech. And he<br />
responded to those hypothetical questions what he's made<br />
clear to me, what the actual position is, what the response<br />
of the Americans has been. And he believes that that response<br />
which they have made to him will be one which will become<br />
clear publicly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it wise for him to be responding to hypothetical<br />
situations given your own attitude to hypothetical questions.<br />
Well that's almost a quasi-hypothetical one itself.<br />
It will have been quite clear to you, as I'm sure it has<br />
been to everyone else at any rate, from the time that Mr Hayden<br />
has been Foreign Minister that we have a very close co-operation.<br />
And I have on many occasions as well as privately, publicly,<br />
gone out of my way to express not only my confidence, but<br />
my wholehearted satisfaction at the way he's discharging his<br />
job of Foreign Minister.<br />
JOURNALIST: On New Caledonia in the discussions during today's<br />
talks with other leaders what position did you put for<br />
Australia. I'm glad you asked that question. because there's some<br />
suggestion that it may not be clearly understood. The<br />
quick run down of what I said was in these terms that I<br />
suppose of all the countries represented around the table<br />
there today, no country more than Australia had been<br />
engaged in the rather difficult situations with the French<br />
both in regard to testing and also, of course, in regard<br />
to the question of exp6rts of uranium to France. positions<br />
of arguments. Having said that I said that one needed to<br />
understand the position of the French and-I was in a position<br />
well to do that because of the meetings I had with President.<br />
Mitterand in Paris last year. And I conveyed to the meeting<br />
what had been said to me by President Mitterand and I'm in<br />
a position to say that to you essentially what the President<br />
said to me was that France had no economic or strategic<br />
imperatives to remain in New Caledonia. If they could they<br />
would rather be out of it now. He used the example he said<br />
that if it was a Zimbabwe he said, we wouldn't be there, because<br />
of th * e ethnic composition of the country in Zimbabwe was quite<br />
clear.. There were no problems and colonial power should have<br />
.2 ' I 1<br />
.1 A<br />
I 13 S </p>
<p>P. M. cant been out. He said the unfortunate situation<br />
in regard to New Caledonia was that the Kanak population,<br />
with which he said his own historical association of being tl-. e<br />
closest rather than with the Colons, is nevertheless in a minority.<br />
They are about 43 per cent of the population. And if in fact.<br />
France was simply unilaterally immediately to hand over<br />
independence it would be the Kanaks at this point who would<br />
suffer because they didn't have the arms, the arms were with<br />
the Colons. They didn't have at this stage the degree of<br />
professional and technical training that the Colons did.<br />
And a position of immediate independence would be one in<br />
which they'would suffer. And what the French were about is<br />
to try in the intervening period to create a situation wherein<br />
the Kanaks would come to a position whei~ e at the time<br />
of independence they would be better equipped to benefit<br />
from it. And in fact the Statute of Internal Autonomy which<br />
would be passed by the French legislature in the near future<br />
is bxplicitly based upon the right of the Kanaks to<br />
independenceAnd the provision within that Statute the approach<br />
for the referendum to be held in 1989 is premised upon the<br />
intention of the French to create that situation. And so,<br />
as I said, I was in a position to judge the integrity of<br />
President Mitterand on this and 1I adjudged his integrity to<br />
be complete upon it a view which was Endorsed by colleagues<br />
around the table today. And I said all of that in the<br />
context of course that we were totally committed. I have<br />
consistently been and so has the Government to the<br />
concept of independence as soon as possible and one within<br />
which the Kanaks would have the opportunity to exercise<br />
their independent rights. And that in fact, that exposition<br />
which I gave, was one which was accepted without demur around<br />
the table.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would your approach be seen as cautious.<br />
Well I don't know whether partiecular adjectives are,<br />
one particular adjective, is adequate to describe a complex<br />
situation. And what I would say, and the view that I believe<br />
was accepted and shared around the table, was that we all know<br />
that we want an end to colonialism in this area. That's<br />
clear and unequivocal. What we must be concerned about is<br />
that in the process of the end of the co~ lonial regime which<br />
we want to see as coming as soon as possible, that you<br />
must try and ensure that the act of ending the colonial<br />
regime in fact happens in a way which is not going to be<br />
against the interests of the people with whom you're most<br />
concerned. Now if you describe that as cautious, well that<br />
may be the appropriate adjective. I believe it's realistic<br />
being based as it is upon a commitment to.. the earliest<br />
possible end of colonialism. And as I say that exposition<br />
which I put was, I believe, shared around the table. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Where's the next CHOGRM going to be held.<br />
In Malaysia, but no date has been fixed for it. I think<br />
what should be understood is that there was an acceptance of:<br />
the value of the CHOGRM. concept. It has a value particularly<br />
for the smaller states the less developed states who<br />
are embraced within CHOGRM. But there was a feeling that WE!<br />
shouldn't necessarily commit ourselves to an automatic meeting<br />
every two years. Dr Mahat ir, the Prime Minister of<br />
Malaysia, offered to host the next meeting and when that<br />
will be held will emerge from a co-ordination of our views<br />
as to when it will be worthwhile. ' The practical work should<br />
proceed-amongst the various functional committees that deal<br />
with issues of trade, agriculture' and m~ aritime issues. And<br />
when the functional work of ' those committe has reached<br />
a point where a meeting of the., political heads of Government.<br />
would be useful, that's when it will take place.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister are you satisfied that it is<br />
worthwhile that the South Pacific Forum, ASEAN and CHOGRM.<br />
( should continue).<br />
Oh well, You're talking about quite different<br />
organisations there. But let me go to each one of them.<br />
There's no doubt about the South Pacific Forum. There.. s no-one<br />
who has any doubt about the usefulness of that organisation<br />
and the functional work that it does and its service in the<br />
South Pacific area. That is clearly useful and Australia<br />
willingly makes a substantial financial contribution to the<br />
work of the Forum because successive Governments have<br />
recognised the practical value of the work that's done there.<br />
With CHOGR4 there may be a view in some quarters that that<br />
merely duplicates the work of the South Pacific Forum, but<br />
of course that's not the case. Because in CHOGRM in addition<br />
to the Pacific states you also have the involvement of some<br />
of the Asian Governments and that gives an opportunity of<br />
interchange of views and experience which doesn't become<br />
available through the Forum. And I think that what was<br />
accepted today is that there must be a concentration upon<br />
the func onal committee work of CHOGRM. So it has that<br />
advantage and you've got to remember that there are the<br />
smaller nations who are, as it were, associate members of<br />
CHOGM who don't get the right therefore of full involvement<br />
in the overall CHOGM meetings. Those three are the Maldives,<br />
Tuvalu and Nauru. Now obviously for those three who are<br />
not full members of CHOGM, CHOGRM has its significance.<br />
Now you mentioned ASEAN well of course that is a quite<br />
different body and there is no question I think in anyone's<br />
mind either within ASEAN or outside it of the usefulness<br />
of that body. It has achieved a status ahd an efficacy<br />
which I think would have surprised even the original<br />
founders of it. And so its viability and usefulness is<br />
simply not in question. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
