<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16722</transcript-id>
    <title>GP Superclinics for South Australia Joint Media Release  with the Minister for Health and  the South Australian Minister for Health Adelaide</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/07/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p> The Prime Minister today signed three funding agreements for the Noarlunga, Playford North and Modbury GP Super Clinics. </p>
<p>The three GP Super Clinics represent a $57.5 million investment in better health care for South Australians. </p>
<p>The Prime Minister signed the three contracts today while visiting Flinders Medical Centre with the Minister for Health and Ageing for a consultation on the National Health and Hospital Reform Commission Report. </p>
<p>Both Noarlunga and Modbury GP Super Clinics will receive $25 million each, jointly funded by the Commonwealth and South Australian Governments.  These clinics will also be GP Plus Health Care Centres under South Australia's GP Plus Health Care Strategy. </p>
<p>The Noarlunga GP Super Clinic will be built within the Noarlunga Hospital and Health Village precinct and allow for virtual integration with existing local health service providers. </p>
<p>The Modbury GP Super Clinic will be built across two sites with a hub at Tea Tree Gully and a spoke at Gilles Plains Primary Health Care Service. </p>
<p>Both the Modbury and Noarlunga GP Super Clinics will provide a range of services with a particular focus on patients with chronic and complex conditions.  Services will be available from privately practising GPs, practice nurses, specialists, dentists and allied health providers. </p>
<p>The $7.5 million Playford North GP Super Clinic will be operated by Adelaide Unicare in partnership with the University of Adelaide and the University of South Australia.  </p>
<p>The clinic will operate from a new purpose-built facility within the ‘Playford Alive' precinct, which will incorporate learning design features.  </p>
<p>The clinic will provide education-led, one-stop primary health care to this growing suburb in Adelaide's north.  Allied health services will be provided in areas such as physiotherapy, psychology, exercise therapy, occupation therapy, drug and alcohol counselling, mental health and nutrition advice services. </p>
<p>All three clinics will have a strong focus on education and training and will support inter-professional learning by undergraduate and postgraduate medical, nursing and allied health students. </p>
<p>These GP Super Clinics deliver on an election commitment of the Rudd Government to provide primary health care services where they are most needed. $275 million has been allocated to establish 32 GP Super Clinics in communities right around the country.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
