<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24798</transcript-id>
    <title>Statement on the passing of Gordon Darling </title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Mr Speaker, I now rise to acknowledge the passing of one of our country's most generous philanthropists, Leonard Gordon Darling AC CMG, who passed away at the end of August.</p>
<p>Gordon Darling was the scion of a famous family – a very famous family – many of whose members have excelled in a whole range of fields.</p>
<p>His grandfather, John, was one of the founders and later chairmen of the Broken Hill Proprietary Company Limited and after distinguished service in the Australian Imperial Force in World War II in the Middle East and in New Guinea, Gordon was the longest serving director of BHP and was in fact the last family member to serve on its board.</p>
<p>Gordon Darling appreciated that a wealthier and more productive economy meant more opportunities for philanthropy.</p>
<p>He wasn't just a businessman.</p>
<p>He was someone who wanted to use the fruits of business to serve the community more widely.</p>
<p>He was the inaugural chairman of the board of the National Gallery of Australia from 1982 to 1986.</p>
<p>In 1991, he established the Gordon Darling Foundation which continues to provide funding and staff development opportunities for public art institutions right across our country.</p>
<p>Gordon and his wife, Marilyn, were the founding patrons of the National Portrait Gallery and they have done magnificent work with this splendid institution.</p>
<p>They funded its beginnings and they drove its establishment as one of our best, best institutions.</p>
<p>In his own words – and I’m quoting him – he said, <em>“All those things, much to my surprise, have been much higher profile and a much more rewarding experience than 40 years in business.” </em></p>
<p>So, Mr Speaker, on behalf of all Australians, I acknowledge the legacy that Gordon Darling has left to our nation.</p>
<p>I extend my deepest condolences to his wife, Marilyn Darling AC, herself a remarkable philanthropist in her own right, and to his family, his children and his grandchildren.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
