<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9121</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, TO THE LAUNCH OF THE VICTOR CHANG CARDIAC RESEARCH INSTITUTE SYDNEY, FEBRUARY 15, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009121.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I L L<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME ZIINISTERO THE HOW* P 3 KEATING MP, TO<br />
TzZ LAUNCH OF THlE VICTOR CHANG CARDIAC RESEARCH INST ITUTZ<br />
SYDNE~ Y, FEBRUARY 15, 1994<br />
When senator Richardson suggested that I come along to the<br />
launch of the victor Chang Cardiac Research institute, I<br />
accepted without much resistance.<br />
The Institute promises to do two things which are of<br />
irresistible appeal.<br />
First, it honours Victor Chang a great Australian, a great<br />
surgeon and a great humanitarian.<br />
Second, it provides for research into a form of disease<br />
suffere4 by 130,000 Australians and which kills as many as<br />
200 people every week.<br />
In fact, I suspect most people My age live in a certain<br />
degree of fear of heart disease, most of us have had friends<br />
who have suffered froam-if or di-ed from it.<br />
Perhaps I should add a third reason why I was keen to say a<br />
few words here today and that is th~ at the Institute will<br />
be attached to St Vincents which has an unsurpassed<br />
reputation based in equal proportions on its excellence in<br />
health care and medical research, and its core values of<br />
compassion, human dignity and social justice.<br />
St Vincents is a hospital with a philosophy and that is<br />
something all great institutions need.<br />
And no hospital could have a better philosophy tnan that<br />
provided by the Sisters of Charity.<br />
The Sisters of Charity bring to St Vincents a compassionate<br />
web, a family culture which, far from being at odds with<br />
modern management principles and strategies, strengthens<br />
them puts humanity into the technocratic void, if you<br />
like. The great thing about St Vincents and the great thing<br />
about this new Victor Chang Cardiac Research institute is<br />
that the nighest standards of medical excellence, and the<br />
most advanced techniques and technology, are delivered to<br />
all Australians regardless of their social and financial<br />
clrcun~ tances. i D r c U L, 4 i i 10 u </p>
<p>TEL 2<br />
And f or this we have the mission of the Sisters of Charity<br />
to thank.<br />
It goes to show that a$ health care goes through rapid<br />
changes because of advances in medical science arnd<br />
technology, the importance of traditional values is<br />
undiminished though it may be these days even more<br />
essential to assert them.<br />
This new Institute will have, as I understand it, three main<br />
goals. First, to improve the lives and life expectancy of all<br />
Australians. Second, to save millions of dollars each year in health<br />
costs. And third, to make internationally recognised contributions<br />
to our understanding of heart muscle disease.<br />
It has been fashionable in recent years for all modern<br />
corporations and institutions to have what Is called a<br />
Mission Statement a document worked up in the company<br />
defining common goals and corporate philosophies.<br />
You couldn't have a better Mission Statement for a hospital<br />
than the Mission of the Sisters of Charity.<br />
And I daresay you couldn't have a better name to call<br />
yourself by then Victor Chang.<br />
I met Dr Chang but did rnot know him well, but I know people<br />
who did and I read the testimonials after his tragic and<br />
outrageous death, and I have heard people talking today.<br />
There is no doubting his extraordinary quialities.<br />
It has, perhaps, not been adequately acknowledged that among<br />
his great contributions to Australia was the work he did in<br />
fostering cooperation between Australian medicine and<br />
medical research and medicine in the countries of South-East<br />
Asia. I hope his work as an ambassador for Australia Is not<br />
forgotten, and that advances made at this Institute which<br />
bears his name will flow on to those countries In Asia in<br />
which he took such an interest.<br />
He was, as I said, a great man, an marvellous surgeon and,<br />
perhaps most of all, a man with a genuine personal concern<br />
and understanding for his patients.<br />
it was Victor Chang's great dreasm to see here at St V1. nrents<br />
H~ ealth Care Campus a team of world class researchers<br />
pursuing the unique challenges of heart disease. iS FeD ' J4 iZ 6 iAO UU,: Uzi </p>
<p>I C L 3<br />
With tbe creation of this Research Institute, Viotor Chang's<br />
dream can be realised.<br />
So, it remains for me to say just two things:<br />
First, i urge all AUstralians to give all they can to<br />
this appeal, for in so doing It they will be not only<br />
helping to carry on the work and the memory of victor<br />
Chang, helping themselves and their fellow Australians.<br />
And second, I congratulate and sincerely thank all those<br />
who have given to the cause already both those who<br />
have given money and those who have given their time<br />
and their skill and effort.<br />
I declare this Victor Chang Cardiac Research Institute<br />
officially launched.<br />
SYDNEY February 1994 I r C ,1 1 * 4U ,. lQ r, V </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
