<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7305</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER OPENING OF BRISBANE AIRPORT BRISBANE - 19 MARCH 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/03/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007305.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
OPENING OF BRISBANE AIRPORT<br />
BRISBANE 19 MARCH 1988<br />
David Sullivan, Chairman, Federal Airports Corporation, Peter<br />
Morris, Minister for Transport and Communication Support,<br />
Premier Michael Ahern<br />
Queensland has a proud history of involvement in Australian<br />
aviation. Bert Hinkler put Bundaberg before the eyes of the<br />
world; Qantas commenced regular operations from Charleville in<br />
1922 and has grown to become a major force in world aviation; and<br />
the famous association of Kingsford Smith and Ulm with Eagle Farm<br />
and Brisbane is exemplified by the blue aircraft, emblazoned with<br />
the Southern Cross, which is proudly on display not far from<br />
here. Queensland's long association with aviation is not merely of<br />
historic interest.<br />
For if ever a country benefited from man's desire to fly, it was<br />
Australia. A well serviced, stable civil aviation industry is<br />
essential to our national life. It shrinks the distances between<br />
our population centres and our industries, and brings us together<br />
as a nation.<br />
It is for this reason that many hundreds of millions of dollars<br />
are spent annually by the Commonwealth government on maintaining<br />
and developing airports and other aviation infrastructure, such<br />
as the state-of-the-art facilities we see here today.<br />
It is for this reason too that the Federal Government has<br />
established the Federal Airports Corporation to manage the<br />
nation's major airports in a professional and efficient fashion.<br />
The full extent of Commonwealth expenditur e on civil aviation is<br />
often not well recognised. Even after industry charges are<br />
excluded, the Commonwealth is this year contributing some $ 330<br />
million. The total cost of our involvement in building this new<br />
airport has been about $ 425 million. 00516<br />
iffi... 9T 6?<br />
1 </p>
<p>The new Brisbane airport is proof that the people of Queensland<br />
and Australia are getting value for those substantial<br />
expenditures: First, we have built an air terminal capable of handling<br />
passenger traffic into the 21st century: up to 10,000<br />
people an hour during peak times, or 7 million<br />
passengers a year, can be accommodated comfortably here;<br />
Second, we have built longer runways, to cater properly<br />
for long distance international flights;<br />
Third, we have brought an end to operational<br />
restrictions, such as curfews, that retarded development<br />
of Eagle Farm over the years, and<br />
Fourth, we have installed state-of-the-art air traffic<br />
control and safety facilities, to ensure Australia's<br />
excellent record in aviation safety is maintained.<br />
And in the long run, we have ensured that Brisbane.* nd Queensland<br />
can fulfil their enormous potential for national and<br />
international tourism.<br />
That is especially important in our Bicentennial year.<br />
In Queensland the Bicentennial means Expo the largest single<br />
event in our Bicentennial calendar, and truly-a national event,<br />
whose success I believe is assured.<br />
With some 50 Governments and 20 corporations committed to attend,<br />
Expo has generated enormous enthusiasm, both among Australians<br />
and abroad.<br />
This enthusiasm will be proven when the millions of visitors<br />
start coming from interstate and overseas.<br />
The State Government of course has a particularly significant<br />
role in fostering the development of the range of facilities to<br />
meet the demands of international and national tourists.<br />
But it would have been difficult, to say the least, to cater for<br />
their needs without an efficient and comfortable airport system.<br />
Through the efforts of my Government and a committed workforce<br />
and project group, Brisbane, and the nation, has that airport and<br />
Expo's success is that much more assured.<br />
This airport is a long term investment by my Government in the<br />
future of Queensland. I have every confidence that it will<br />
provide invaluable service well into the next century.<br />
The people of Queensland and their visitors will from now on be<br />
able to take advantage of an airport as good as any in the world.<br />
With that confidence, it gives me great pleasure to declare the<br />
new Brisbane International Airport open. 005 . I. 62 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
