<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5274</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH CARL ROBERTSON - NEWSWEEK 27 FEBRUARY 1980</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005274.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH CARL ROBERTSON NEWSWEEK<br />
27 FEBRUARY 1980<br />
Question<br />
Newsweek is doing a major coverpiece on Australia and focussing<br />
in part on your own statements and actions in the last couple of<br />
months. There is no question in my mind that you are quite and<br />
have long believed in the Soviet threat. But I wanted to get<br />
stuck into more general questions about where you think Australia<br />
is headed in 1980. Do you think Australia is going in a new<br />
direction in the 1980s?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not think in the sense of any radical change I would say no.<br />
But I think the Australian economy has developed in strength and<br />
depth and while the shortage has been difficult for all countries<br />
including Australia, there is in a perverse kind of way a very<br />
real advantage for us in what has happened in the energy area.<br />
We do have good supplies of other forms of energy. We are not<br />
self sufficient in oil as you know. But coal, uranium, natural gaswe<br />
have more than we need for ourselves at the moment. Electricity<br />
based on coal is very cheap in this country. Because we are a<br />
resource rich and an energy rich country our export base is very<br />
strong, keeping our economy run a bit tighter than some others with<br />
inflation a bit lower than some others attracts more investment<br />
to Australia. Coupled with our own due resources I think we are<br />
going to see much better processing here. It is already happening<br />
in the aluminium. industry, very substantially. It is going to be<br />
cheaper for other countries to process minerals Australian based<br />
energy. Question But do you think-' that the focus on energy will see you through<br />
or sort of override commonly mentioned problems of the world<br />
economy dangers?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it will.<br />
Question I think that to transcend that the fact that a lot of it is going<br />
to be energy.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well obviously what happens will affect us. But four years ago we<br />
made up our minds that we were not going to get much help through<br />
an increase in trade, through an expanding world economy. If that<br />
happens all right it will help us it will help everyone else.<br />
But we saw inflation as being too high. We saw high inflation continuing in<br />
too many countries. Therefore we said we have got to get our<br />
inflation below other people's. We have got to get our manufactures<br />
exported. We have got to get a larger share of existing markets.<br />
We have got to develop Australia's minerals and energy resources<br />
in a way that has not happened before. So if you like that is a<br />
new direction or a new emphasis. Coupled with the strength of rural 2 </p>
<p>Prime Minister.( continued)<br />
exports, it really has placed Australia in a very strong position<br />
as we enter the 1980s.<br />
Question Do you think there's a chance of the manufacturing industries<br />
being left behind a bit by the Government in minerals and primary<br />
industries? Prime Minister<br />
Manufacturing industries are very important as employers of<br />
labour. And in the last year the physical volume of their exports<br />
has gone up nearly 30 per cent. We are now exporting to a<br />
remarkable number of countries including some labour intensive<br />
things where we have a particular expertise. So we are not<br />
defeatists or despondent about the future of manufacturing industries<br />
as much as we might have been.<br />
Question There's quite a debate on the new technology and how that's going<br />
to ( inaud). Do you think enough is being done by if something<br />
is sort of brought up and you see a full page letter in the paperbut<br />
is doesn't seem to have created the sort of serious debate<br />
that you would expect, because it seems to me that Australia is<br />
well placed to take the new technology and make it an export item<br />
as well.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well we are and~ ii think we have to. I do not believe any<br />
advanced industrial country has got any choice other than to<br />
embrace virtually all the new technology which comes their way,<br />
which they can create or devise for themselves. This is not<br />
really a new argument. New technology and the technology debate of<br />
today is another form.-of the argument that occurred when the<br />
Industrial Revolution started and people were frightened for the<br />
future of cottage industries and frightened for the future of<br />
employment." Industrialisation then led to a greater level of<br />
employment than had ever occurred in an industrial state. What<br />
we have to do is to look to the advantages of modern. technology;<br />
producing things cheaper so you sell more of them, producing more<br />
things and increasing people's standards, increasing the range<br />
of products that-they will want to buy and thereby increasing the<br />
numbers of jobs. If people just sit back in a defeatist way and<br />
say if we had modern technology we can build that telephone with<br />
less labour therefore-we won't have modern technology we will<br />
end up by selling no telephones because somebody will be doing it<br />
cheaper. So there is no option. New technology-opens new<br />
opportunities for businessmen, for entrepreneurs. It opens new<br />
markets and it is going to be up to those with inventiveness and<br />
ingenuity, the capacity to go out and achieve things, to take<br />
advantage of it. We have appointed a major committee under Professor<br />
Rupert Myers, who is Head of a very technologically based<br />
university, to advise us on the introduction of new technology and<br />
those matters of particular application and of concern to Australia. 3 </p>
<p>Prime minister ( continued)<br />
I think it will be a very useful report and I-am not suggesting<br />
that new technology should be introduced thoughtlessly from the<br />
point of view of employees. There needs to be consultation.<br />
There needs to be phasing in. There needs to training and retraining.<br />
. Some industries have worked<br />
out a good way of accommodating themselves to it and others not<br />
so good. More progress to be made. None of that is an argument<br />
against it. It is just the way you go about it.<br />
Question There seems to be a glut of liberal arts type students on the job<br />
market and a real shortage from what I have gathered during the.<br />
initial story I did, a real shortage of skilled manpower. Is<br />
there going to be more attention focussed on training and retraining.<br />
I know some companies are quite innovative. Do you think anyone<br />
in the Government is going to be doing something?<br />
Prime minister<br />
No we are doing quite a lot. Companies are encouraged to take on<br />
more apprentices. Quite directly under Government training<br />
programmes, by the end of this year and the last three or four<br />
years over half a million young Australians mostly but not exclusively<br />
young people, will have been given training under various training<br />
programmes run by the Government in co-operation with industry.<br />
And that is quite a large number. We are spending much more on<br />
technically based college courses or Technical and Further Education,<br />
as we call it. This again is designed to encourage those with<br />
professional, technical skills. There are new programmes of<br />
transition from school-to work. One of the things a number of us<br />
believe is that the Secondary School system has become too academic<br />
not enough attention is being given to thevocationally minded.<br />
So in all of these areas there is certainly a role for Governments<br />
working either for its own training programmes or in co-operation<br />
with industry.<br />
Question Why haven't the unions been more co-operative? I think they<br />
realise as much as anybody else that it could be a very good time<br />
in the 80s for Australia. Why aren't they except perhaps for<br />
personal greed and wanting all the money for themselves.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Sometimes unions are-remarkably short-sighted. Sometimes they are<br />
remarkably conservative in the sense that they won't change their<br />
habits. Some of the older people who can remember the difficult<br />
times of the 1930s and they just say you know we've got a closed<br />
shop, we've got a union membership it takes a long while to<br />
expand that membership and therefore we're in a stronger bargaining<br />
position. Others are just resistant to change. But some unions<br />
are now coming to accept in some degree adult apprenticeship,<br />
which is the really important thing.<br />
Question Adult apprenticeship? </p>
<p>4<br />
Prime Minister<br />
To give a bloke of 30 or 40 or whatever an opportunity to gain<br />
skills and have those skills recognised that they might have<br />
missed out on because they did not get opportunities as kids.<br />
Now up to the present most unions shut these people out. But<br />
with patient negotiation hopefully we will overcome that. It is<br />
a short-sighted view and in many ways it is a very conservative<br />
view and a misplaced one, conserving the wrong things.<br />
Question Self survival seems to be a big factor.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think it is but that is still short-sighted and selfish.<br />
Quest ion<br />
The defence, increase in defence expenditure you announced last<br />
Tuesday it seems to have created quite a stir within the defence<br />
and academic establishment the types that I have talked to.<br />
And I think-that you are with Afghanistan onto an issue, for the<br />
first time I think the Australian public is listening and talking<br />
about defence as an issue. I think it's been pretty hard to raise<br />
much interest before.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Probably. In the recent past that would be true.<br />
Question<br />
But do you think you are going to be able to sustain an interest<br />
in defence that you would need to sustain the massive capital<br />
expenditure you'-re involved in.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well I think we are going to have to in peace time. We have never<br />
been a country that spends very large sums on defence. But with<br />
the expense of modern equipments we are going to have to spend<br />
substantial sums. It still lifts defence spending to 3 per cent<br />
of GDP, not above that. So by other larger nations' standards it<br />
is not high. But the new programme will be 1.6-billion in<br />
constant dollars over five years more than the previous guidance.<br />
The defence vote will be rising in real terms between 5 and 7 per<br />
cent a year instead'df-about' 2 per cent a year. In our terms<br />
the increase is substantial. It will give us small but hard hitting<br />
and effective forces. I think that is the position isn't it?<br />
There has always been an underlying strength and interest in defence in<br />
Australia and it does not take very much to bring it to the surface.<br />
Question Moving to what some people would call a forward defence. What<br />
expression do you use?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No we used to have a so-called forward defence policy but that was </p>
<p>Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
years ago when the British were very actively in Malaysia and we<br />
were helping them there. These sort of slogans tend to depict a<br />
policy wrongly simple because they try to do it much too briefly.<br />
We are obviously interested in the security and peace of Asean and of our<br />
own region.. Our forces are increasingly becoming equipped to<br />
operate by themselves or equipped to operate with allies, using<br />
very often allies logistics supply lines and now we believe we<br />
have got to have a capacity to do things more on our own.<br />
Question<br />
Would you say that that's a lesson that Australia learned from the<br />
Vietnam and the post Vietnam... . that you should be more independent.<br />
I think that was something that you did stress in your speech last<br />
week. as part of but independent.<br />
Prime Minister.<br />
Well it's partly that. But at the same time the British don't have<br />
much of a presence left in Southeast Asia and they did have a<br />
substantial one and therefore the option of operating with them or<br />
alongside them is not as real as it once was. There have been<br />
some perceptions of change in the United States policy. There was<br />
the Guam Doctrine. We have never doubted the efficacy of the<br />
Anzus Treaty. But at the same time we have* envisaged the possibility<br />
of being involved in conflicts that are related to Australia's<br />
security well we might have. to operate by ourselves. That might<br />
be in a time scale in the distance. But it takes a long while to<br />
build up the infrastructure and the basic support and the logistics<br />
and the industry capacity for an independently operated force.<br />
And we have been moving in this direction in spite of the difficulties<br />
that very sophisticated equipments pose in terms of maintenance and<br />
in terms of buying them and understanding them and all the rest.<br />
We want to continue on that path. Because it does represent a more<br />
independent national effort and gives us a greater degree of<br />
independence in what we do, not necessarily tied to one ally or<br />
another.. I think that ages and beyond that is the only approach<br />
that makes sense for Australia. That doesn't mean to say that<br />
allies are not important. Of course they are. But our own sense<br />
of independence and ability to do things is also important.<br />
Question That is in some ways a new development isn't it?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Of it has come about over the'last ten years.<br />
Question<br />
You seem to be leading Australia. Has this always been your view<br />
of what we've just been talking about you know developing your<br />
independence, infrastructure,* logistics, manufacturing is that<br />
something you have always felt.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
In defence certainly. And it certainly would have been from the<br />
time I was Minister for Defence and maybe minister for the Army. 6 </p>
<p>Prime minister ( continued)<br />
But times change and the policies that were appropriate to this<br />
place when I first came into the Parliament 25 years ago are not<br />
necessarily appropriate today. You have got to be prepared to<br />
adapt and adjust your policies and make them relevant and appropriate<br />
to now and the future.<br />
Question Do you see Australia as taking a more active role within the region?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think we are. We are certainly taking a much more active role in<br />
the Pacific and that's important because they are small fragileeconomies.<br />
They need some support and assistance. I think they<br />
would much sooner have it from New Zealand or Australia than<br />
countries further afield. But other people will do it and get a<br />
leg in if we don't play our role. That obviously has strategic<br />
consequences as well. In Southeast Asia we have always had an<br />
active policy our overseas aid and defence aid has been concentrated<br />
in that area and as I indicated the other day we are looking to see<br />
if they are _ willing or would like to expand some of those relationships.<br />
Question You ' ye expanded quite often in the past on the concept of the<br />
Pacific Community something which was brought up during the<br />
Ohira visit and I think it was something fairly concrete to come<br />
out of the Ohira visit. Have you any more thoughts since that<br />
Ohira visit you were especially that was in the early post<br />
Afghanistan invasion days is there something you can talk any<br />
more about in the United States or in the region?<br />
Ptime Minister<br />
No not really. I think the United States' position is that they<br />
applaud the concept but would like others to be the front runners.<br />
People have not really got in mind some sort of defence associationsocial,<br />
economic, trade, cultural but a great deal more work<br />
needs doing before you can put even bones on the. idea and then<br />
flesh on the-bones. The concept is good and many people applaud it<br />
but then you ask them what do you mean. How do you develop a<br />
Pacific community that comprises nations of very diverse backgrounds,<br />
culture, size, strength, geography. Japan on the one hand, the<br />
small island states of the Pacific with a few thousand people total<br />
population the Asean groups of nations you have got to make<br />
sure that they don't. regard this concept as something that threatens<br />
the integrity of that group and you would not want it to, because<br />
the strength of Asean is very important. What is happening at the<br />
moment is very careful soundings going on of the attitudes of other<br />
countries and it will be dependent upon that whether or-not we go.<br />
ahead with the seminar which Japan and Australia agreed would be a<br />
good idea. We hope other countries will join us. But there are<br />
some sensitivities. There are enormous differences between the<br />
countries of the Pacific. In other words there isn't the kind of<br />
natural affiliation that you would have got from the European<br />
Community for example. That is not. depreciating the idea, that is<br />
just saying that it needs working on. 7 </p>
<p>Question I understand the American Ambassador to Micronesia was just down<br />
here. Prime Minister<br />
Well Mansfield was here from Japan.<br />
Question., I heard that someone was here just last ( inaud)<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well he could have been. I did not meet him.<br />
Question The Americans are fairly set to give Micronesia some sort of'<br />
self governing status. Is that something which interests Australia?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Well all th-6 Pacific States are becoming independent and self<br />
governing. That is a move that is sweeping through the Pacific.<br />
But it is also going to be very important that those countries<br />
keep together in their own bodies in their own groupings.<br />
Question Do you see the. Soviets as willing to play up any weaknesses in...<br />
Prime Minister<br />
There have been some suggestions that they are prepared to provide<br />
air force or ( inaud) bases in some of these islands and if they<br />
are given half a chance I suspect they might like to and then<br />
what does it later develop into.<br />
Question There was that. thing in Tonga a couple of years ago.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
That's right, yes. Well that was the main feeler that went out<br />
I think.<br />
Question The New Hebrides is having a lot of problems which could be a<br />
( inaud).<br />
Prime. Minister<br />
Some. Question I know you are pretty pressed for time but jumping to another<br />
subject do you think, I mean it's part of my hassles with my<br />
editors in New York and I sometimes feel sympathy when you are 8 </p>
<p>saying in effect that no-one is paying us enough attention down<br />
here. Prime Minister<br />
I haven't said that. Our journalists said it.<br />
Question In effect. But do you think Australia is taken seriously-enough?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I think Australia is taken seriously in Washington and State [ epartrent<br />
political circles and in the-White House. I think Australia is.<br />
taken seriously for quite different reasons in the financial<br />
circles in New York. I attended an economic club dinner and 1,000<br />
people turned up. I don't think 1,000 people turned up just<br />
because they liked Malcolm Fraser. I think they had<br />
some interest in Australia and what Australia is doing and some<br />
interest in the kinds of policies that we pursue. Because we have<br />
got a reputation in New York for economic policies that work and<br />
keeping a tight reign on government expenditure and all sorts of<br />
things. And that is appreciated. So in those areas I think<br />
Australia well ( inaud) if somebody has got a project to develop<br />
here you will find plenty of people in New York that will be<br />
prepared to provide the funds. That is the sort of reputation we<br />
want. Now it doesn't worry us if we don't get many column inches<br />
in New York newspapers or in the Washington Post. And I can well<br />
understand what the 140 or 150 nations represented in Washingtonhow<br />
people get involved in their own domestic affairs. You go across<br />
to the United States and a. number of the newspapers there hardly<br />
even write any national news. It's only in the East coast newspapers<br />
and I suppose to an extent in the West coast papers, when<br />
I've been in the country where you really find international events<br />
reported at all. So I am used to it. But it doesn't worry me.<br />
Question But are you disappointed that. Australia hasn't in world economic<br />
forums it seems that I know that you liaise very closely with the<br />
Americans and the Japanese for example and that they carry<br />
Australia's arguments-to these forms -but why hasn't Australia<br />
become an invited. partner of these..<br />
Prime Minister<br />
Japan wanted us to be and I think the Americans would have accepted<br />
it and the British would have, may be Germany. But there are one<br />
or two in the economic group that didn't want us. There are<br />
economies than Canada's but bigger than ours. The present membership<br />
is based on the size of their economies. Now if they make a<br />
juncture with a country with Australia's size economy they are<br />
going to be a number of others in between within the European area<br />
that will give problems to the Europeans and say how do you put<br />
Australia-on and leave us off our economy is bigger. And I can<br />
understand that sort of argument. I can also understand arguments<br />
that said the world's geography has got to be balanced and that was<br />
the argument that the Japanese used. I don't know that that matters<br />
very much. We can make our own way and seem to be doing it all<br />
right. I don't know that our presence at those forums is going to<br />
really strengthen the anti inflationary policies of the countries </p>
<p>9<br />
Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
that are not receiving an adequate anti inflationary policy.<br />
But in other areas of course, in the political domain, I would<br />
like to see more discussions amongst an even. nore restricted group and<br />
that is Britain,. France, Germany and the United States. I think<br />
much of the future of the independent nations of the world depends<br />
upon a very even closer link and liaison between those major four<br />
countries.-I suppose I am saying in practical terms that there<br />
are things that I believe they can and ought to be saying to each<br />
other which they probably wouldn't say in any larger grouping. But that is<br />
on political and strategic matters rather than on economic matters.<br />
Question But do you think that such talks' however informal would tend<br />
to put off your own regional the other nations within the region?<br />
Prime minister<br />
What sort of things?<br />
Question You know if you are talking about forming a group of independent<br />
nations like mostly European and. American nations wouldn't<br />
that put off the regional allies a bit why aren't you talking to<br />
us as much as you're talking to them?<br />
Prime minister<br />
I think they talk to us and to others in different sorts of fortums.<br />
Look so much depends upon a concerted European/ North American<br />
policy in dealing with the S oviet Union. And it can be achieved<br />
through those four nations.<br />
Question I.<br />
But how would you assess the relationship between Australia and<br />
the region?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
This region?<br />
Question Yes. Prime Minister<br />
I would have thought-it's good. Sometimes our own economic writers<br />
down here write things that I think are nonsense about our trade<br />
relationships with Asean. But the Asean countries are well aware<br />
that their exports to us have been increasing by 30 to 40 per cent<br />
a year for ten years, even though they started from a low base<br />
that rate of growth-that starts to build up we have introduced<br />
many special policies to help them get into our markets because<br />
they started later than many others. I am opening a second Asean<br />
Australia trade fair later this year. And I think they understand<br />
that we buy on a per capita basis much more their manufactured<br />
goods than does any other advanced industrial country more than<br />
Japan, America or Europe. And we will go on doing so. We have got<br />
a </p>
<p>Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
a close identity of interest in the security and stability of the<br />
region. With Malaysia, Singapore, Indonesia we have got defence<br />
aid programmes we have got a five power defence arrangement that<br />
still exists with Singapore, Malaysia and New Zealand, Australia<br />
and Britain.<br />
Question That's right. Everyone is still there except the Brits I guess?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
The Philippines have put aside a trade treaty for a long while<br />
because they were not satisfied with trade arrangements.-But when<br />
I was there last time it was brought up, dusted over and signed.<br />
So I think the relationship with the region is a good one.<br />
Question Would you agree that there have been strains and misunderstandings.<br />
Prime minister<br />
Oh going back over 25 30 year period at different times of<br />
course there have been some. There have occasionallybeen strains<br />
and misunderstandings in relation to our immigration policy<br />
sometimes in relation to trade-policy. But we have tried to work<br />
on it and I think those difficulties I hope have permanently passed<br />
us. And relationships with Japan could not be better. So we have<br />
concentrated our diplomatic efforts and initiatives in this area<br />
the last 3 or 4 years may be started to branch out a little bit and<br />
develop closer links with the Indian subcontinent. And in the<br />
last 3 or 4 years we are giving much more attention to the Pacific.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
