<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3029</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER - ROYAL VISIT 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003029.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: NOT FGO RELEASE BEFORE 6.00 P. h. EST MONDAY 1 OCTOBER<br />
STATEI-ENT BY THE PIiE MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 132<br />
1 OCTOBEa 1973<br />
ROYAL VISIT 1974<br />
The Queen and Prince Philip have been pleased to agree<br />
to the following dates for their visits to Norfolk Island, Papua<br />
New Guinea and Australia in February/ March next year.<br />
Monday<br />
to Tuesday Friday<br />
to Wednesday Wednesday<br />
to Friday Friday<br />
to Tuesday Tuesday<br />
to Friday Saturday<br />
to Sunday 11 February<br />
12 February<br />
22 February<br />
27 February<br />
27 February<br />
1 March<br />
1 March<br />
5 March<br />
5 Miarch<br />
8 1iarch<br />
9 March<br />
10 March Norfolk Island<br />
Papua New Guinea<br />
Canberra Scuth Australia<br />
Western Australia<br />
Northern Territory<br />
On the first stages of the visit The Princess Anne and<br />
Captain Mark Phillips will accompany The Queen and Prince Philip.<br />
The Royal Party will visit Norfolk Island and Papua New Guinea<br />
aboard the itoyal Yacht BRITANNIA.<br />
They will also accompany The Queen and Prince Philip on<br />
the flight from Port Mioresby to Canberra on Wednesday 27 February<br />
but other commitments will make it necessary for them to return to<br />
London by air from Sydney on Thursday 28 February.<br />
They will therefore leave Canberra by air for Sydney on<br />
Wednesday 27 February and stay overnight at Government house.<br />
The Queen and Prince Philip will rejoin the iroyal Yacht<br />
BRITANNIA at Darwin and leave Australia from there on Sunday<br />
March 1974. Consultations will now take place to prepare a program<br />
of engagements for the visit, These details will be publicly<br />
announced when approved.<br />
CANBERJRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
