<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6195</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT TO THE PARLIAMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAWKE, 6 SEPTEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006195.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4-A-1S'IT A<br />
IA I<br />
PRIME PAINIgSTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
STATEMENT TO THE PARLIAMENT BY ' THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HANKE<br />
6 S ET. LE 198-3<br />
MR SPEAKER, I SEEK LEAVE TO MAKE A STATEMENT TO THE<br />
HOUSE ON THE TRAGIC EPISODE WHICH SHOCKED THE WORLD<br />
LAST WEEK,<br />
ON THE BASIS OF INFORMATION AVAILABLE TO IT., THE<br />
GOVERNMENT HAS NO DOUBT THAT KOREAN AIRLINES FLIGHT 7,<br />
EN ROUTE FROM ANCHORAGE TO SEOUL, WAS SHOT DOWN BY<br />
A SOVIET FIGHTER AIRCRAFT EARLY IN THE MORNING OF<br />
1 SEPTEMBER AUSTRALIAN EASTERN STANDARD TIME,<br />
I<br />
MiR SPEAKER, THERE ARE MANY UNANSWERED QUESTIONS<br />
SURROUNDING THIS DISASTER, THE BASIC ONES ARE:<br />
HOW WAS IT POSSIBLE FOR MILITARY AIRCRAFT<br />
9<br />
TO FIRE ON AND DESTROY . A CIVILI. AI AIRLINER<br />
IN PEACE TIME; AND<br />
WHY HAS THE SOVIET UNION BEEN UNABLE OR UNWILLING<br />
TO PRODUCE A COHERENT., CONVINCING AND SUITABLY<br />
REGRETFUL ACCOUNT OF THESE APPALLING CIRCUMSTANCES.<br />
i 2/, </p>
<p>2.<br />
WHATEVER THE ANSWER TO THESE AND TO THE OTHER IMPORTANT<br />
QUESTION OF HOW THE AIRLINER STRAYED SO FAR OFF COURSE<br />
INTO SOVIET AIRSPACE, THE SIMPLE FACT IS THAT AN<br />
UNARMED CIVILIAN AIRLINER SERVING NO MILITARY PURPOSE<br />
WAS SHOT DOWN BY A SOVIET FIGHTER AIRCRAFT. THERE CAN<br />
BE NO JUSTIFICATION FOR SUCH A BARBARIC ACT, 269<br />
PASSENGERS AND CREW, INCLUDING 4 AUSTRALIANS, HAVE DIED.<br />
FOLLOWING THIS TRAGEDY, THE GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN ACfION<br />
TO BRING TO THE ATTENTION OF THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT ITS<br />
DEEP CONCERN AND SHOCK AND HAS SOUGHT A PROMPT AND FULL<br />
EXPLANATION OF SOVIET ACTIONS. THE SOVIET AMBASSADOR<br />
IN AUSTRALIA WAS CALLED TO THE DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN<br />
AFFAIRS ON 2 SEPTEMBER AND REQUESTED TO PROVIDE A<br />
FULL AND PROPER ACCOUNT OF THE CIRCUMSTANCES SURROUNDING<br />
THIS UNJUSTIFIABLE ACT. ON THE SAME DAY, OUR AMBASSADOR<br />
IN MOSCOW, MR EVANS, CALLED ON THE SOVIET FOREIGN MINISTRY<br />
AND MADE THE SAME REQUEST.<br />
SO FAR, THE SOVIET AUTHORITIES HAVE PROVIDED NO INFORMATION<br />
IN RESPONSE TO OUR REQUEST. THEY HAVE SIMPLY DRAWN OUR<br />
ATTENTION TO STATEMENTS MADE BY'THE OFFICIAL SOVIET<br />
NEWSAGENCY, TASS, APART FROM THE FACT THAT THE<br />
STATEMENTS SO FAR ISSUED BY TASS HAVE BEEN TOTALLY<br />
INADEQUATE AND DELIBERATELY MISLEADING THEY, HAVE,<br />
FOR EXAMPLE, MADE THE PREPOSTEROUS CLAIM THAT THE<br />
KOREAN AIRLINER WAS ON AN INTELLIGENCE MISSION THEY<br />
ARE QUITE INAPPROPRIATE AS COMMUNICATIONS BETWEEN GOVERNMENTS. </p>
<p>THE FOREIGN MINISTER AND I HAVE MADE CRYSTAL CLEAR THE<br />
GOVERNMENT'S OUTRAGE AND CONDEMNATION AT WHAT HAS OCCURRED.<br />
WE WILL MAINTAIN PERSISTENT AND STRONG PRESSURE FOR AN<br />
ADEQUATE EXPLANAT ION.<br />
IHAVE PERSONALLY EXPRESSED OUR CONDOLENCES TO THE B3EREAVED<br />
AUSTRALIA'N FAMILIES. * 1HAVE ALSO SENT A MESSAGE OF<br />
SYMPATHY TO PRESIDEINT CHUN DOO Hj, qAN OF THE REPUBLIC<br />
OF KOREAj WHO WILL BE PAYING AN OFFICIAL VISIT TO<br />
AUSTRALIA NEXT MONTH. PRESIDENT CHUN HAS EXPRESSED TO MiE<br />
HIS COUNTRY'IS APPRECIATION OF OUR SUPPORT AND SYMPATHY.<br />
AUSTRALIA WAS AT THE FOREFRONT OF THOSE COUNTRIES WIHICH<br />
CALLED FOR AN EMERGENCY MEETING OF THE SECURITY COUNCIL<br />
TO DISCUSS THIS TRAGEDY. THIS TOOK PLACE ON FRIDAY<br />
2 SEPTEMBER AND WILL RESUME ON 6 SEPTEMBER ( US TIME),<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN ACTING PERMANENT REPRESENTATIVE., M4R JOSEPH,<br />
EXPRESSED AUSTRALIA'IS SHOCK AND INDIGNATION AT THE<br />
DOWNING OF THE KAL FLIGHT. DESRIBING THE INCIDENT AS<br />
A MASAR IN THE SKY MR JOSEPH SAID:<br />
" AUSTRALIA JOINS WITH OTHER MEMBERS OF THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY ' I DEMANDING A* IMMEDIATE<br />
AND FULL ACCOUNTrING FROM THE SOVIET AUTHORITIES.<br />
WE HAVE PUT THIS REQUEST BILATERALLY AND I<br />
REPEAT IT HERE TODAY IN'A MULTILATERAL CONTEXT,<br />
THE EXPLANATIONS SO FAR EMANATING FROM MOSCOW<br />
ABOUT THE EPISODE ARE IN. OUR VIEW ENTIRELY<br />
INADEQUATE. THERE HAS BEEN A REFUSAL THUS FAR </p>
<p>LI<br />
EITHER TO ACKNOWLEDGE RESPONSIBILITY OR EVEN TO<br />
EXTEND A CONVINCING EXPRESSION OF REGRET FOR<br />
THE ACTIONS THIS IS DEPLORABLE, WE APPEAL TO<br />
THE SOVIET UNION., IF THE SOVIET AUTHORITIES<br />
GIVE IN TO THE INSTINCT TO COVER UP, iT WILL<br />
ONLY CONFIRM THE WORST FEA-RS OF THOSE WHO<br />
SUSPECT THEM MOST, WITH REPERCUSSIONS ACROSS<br />
THE SPECTRUM OF I NTERNAT IONAL RELATIONS,"<br />
MR JOSEPH WENT ON TO SAY:<br />
" IN THIS REGARD, MR PRESIDENT, I MUST SAY THAT<br />
ONE CANNOT BUT FEEL PROFOUNDLY DISTURBED BY<br />
THE LATEST TASS STATEMENT WHICH WAS READ OUT<br />
TO THE COUNCIL EARLIER THIS AFTERNOON BY<br />
THE DELEGATION OF THE USSR, WE SEE NO ELEMENT<br />
OF CONTRITION IN THE STATEMENTS IT AMOUNTS, AT<br />
LEAST ON FIRST READING, TO BLAMING THE VICTIMS<br />
THEMSELVES, I WOULD REMIND THE SOVIET DELEGATION<br />
THAT SOME OF THOSE VICTIMS WERE AUSTRALIAN CITIZENS<br />
AND I WOULD SAY FIRMLY 011 THE BEHALF OF THESE<br />
VICTIMS, NOW DECEASED, THAT THEY WERE ENTIRELY<br />
BLAMELESS IN THIS APPALL4NG EPISODE. 1qF* R EJECT<br />
THIS LATEST ATTEMPTED EVPASION OF RESPONSIBILITY."<br />
I BELIEVE THAT THIS HOUSE WOULD FULLY SUPPORT THE STANCE<br />
TAKEN BY THIS GOVERNMENT BEFOR'E THE UNITED NATIONS. </p>
<p>* l s 4. j<br />
IR SPEAKER, THIS INCIDENT IS ONE OF THE GRAVEST CONCERN<br />
TO EVERY NATION. IT IS INCOMPATIBLE WITH ACCEPTED<br />
NORMS OF CIVILISED BEHAVIOUR BEfWEEN NATIONS AND<br />
CONTRARY TO PRINCiPLES OF INTERNATIONAL LAW. MOREOVER,<br />
iT HAS VERY SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES FOR THE SAFETY OF<br />
AIR NAVIGATION.<br />
SADLY, THIS INCIDENT IS NOT THE FIRST OF ITS KIND.<br />
HONOURABLE MEMBERS WILL RECALL THAT IN 1978 SOVIET<br />
FIGHTERS OPENED FIRE ON AND FORCED TO LAND ANOTHER<br />
KAL FLIGHT, ALSO WITH SOME LOSS OF LIFE, EARLIER,<br />
IN 1973, A LIBYAN AIRCRAFT STRAYED UNWITTINGLY<br />
OVER THE SINAI DESERT AND WAS SHOT DOWN BY ISRAELI<br />
FIGHTERS WITH A LOSS OF OVER 100 PASSENGERS AND CREW.<br />
THAT ACTION WAS TAKEN ONLY AFTER THE PILOT ACKNOWLEDGED,<br />
BUT DID NOT HEED, THE WARNINGS AND SIGNALS GIVEN BY<br />
THE FIGHTERS. FURTHERMORE, THE ISRAELI GOVERNMENT<br />
PROMPTLY PROVIDED DETAILS OF THE INCIDENT, ISSUED<br />
A STATEMENT EXPRESSING " DEEP SORROW" AT THE LOSS OF LIFE<br />
AND ANNOUNCED EX GRATIA PAYMENTS OF COMPENSATION TO<br />
THE FAMILIES OF THOSE KILLED IN EXPLICIT DEFERENCE<br />
TO HUMANITARIAN CONSIDERATIONS'.<br />
MR SPEAKER, THERE IS A GRIM IRONY IN THE FACT THAT THE<br />
SOVIET REPRESENTATIVE TO AN EMERGENCY SESSION OF THE<br />
INTERNATIONAL CIVIL AVIATION ORGANISATION ( ICAO) IN<br />
FEBRUARY 1973 DESCRIBED THAT INCIDENT AS A " CRIMINAL<br />
ACT OF INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM" AND SAID THAT " ICAO<br />
COULD NOT REMAIN ALO) F? FROM THE BARBARIC ACT<br />
COMMITTED BY ISRAEL 6/. </p>
<p>IN 1955, COMPENSATION WAS ALSO OFFERED BY THE BULGARIAN<br />
GOVERNMENT AFTER ITS AIRFORCE HAD SHOT DOWN AN ISRAELI<br />
AIRLINER IN BULGARIAN AIRSPACE KILL. ING 64 PASSENGERS<br />
AND CREW'. THE BULGARIANS OFFERED TO PAY COMPENSATION<br />
TO THE FA* IILIES OF THOSE KILLED, TO PUNISH " THOSE<br />
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CATASTROPHE" AND TO TAKE MEASURES<br />
TO PREVENT A REPITITION OF SUCH INCIDENTS. THERE ARE,<br />
THEREFORE, MR SPEAKER, PRECEDENTS FOR THE KIND OF<br />
RESPONSE WHICH THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY HAS EVERY<br />
RIGHT NOW TO EXPECT OF THE SOVIET UNTION.<br />
MR SPEAKER, THERE IS ANOTHER DIMENSION TO THIS TRAGEDY,<br />
TO WHICH I WOULD LIKE TO DRAW THE ATTENTION OF THE HOUSE.<br />
THE INCIDENT IS A REMINDER OF THE CONSEQUENCES OF<br />
CONTINUED HOSTILITY AND LACK OF COMMUNICATION AND DIALOGUE<br />
IN THE KOREAN PENINSULA. AUSTRALIA HAS RECOGNISED TWO<br />
STATES AND TWO GOVERNMENTS ON THE KOREAN PENINSULA<br />
SINCE 1974. OTHER WESTERN NATIONS WHICH HAVE RELATIONS<br />
WITH THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA ( SOUTH KOREA) HAVE MADE CLEAR<br />
THAT THEY WOULD BE PREPARED TO RECOGNISE THE DPRK<br />
( NORTH KOREA) IF THE DPRK AND ITS FRIENDS, INCLUDING<br />
THE SOVIET UNION, WOULD COME TO TERMS WITH THE REALITY<br />
THAT THERE HAS EXISTEI? IN SOUTH KOREA FOR OVER 30 YEARS<br />
A SOVEREIGN GOVERNMENT, THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA,<br />
V<br />
IT IS OUR FIRM CONVICTION THAT THE CONTINUING FAILURE<br />
OF THE SOVIET UNION AND OTHERS TO RECOGNISE THAT REALITY,<br />
WHILE ATTEMPTING TO DENY THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA ITS<br />
LEGITIMATE PLACE IN THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND ITS<br />
RIGHTS IN INTERNATIO'AL LAW HAS CONTRIBUTED T-0 THE CIRCUMSTANCES 7/ </p>
<p>IN WHICH THIS APPALLING ACTION HAS TAKEN PLACE,<br />
MR SPEAKER, CABINET DISCUSSED THIS MATTER YESTERDAV<br />
AND EXAMINED POSSIBLE FUTURE ACTION WHICH AUSTRALIA,<br />
TOGETHER WITH OTHER NATIONS PRINCIPALLY AFFECTED,<br />
MIGHT TAKE, IN ITS DELIBERATIONS THE GOVERNMENT<br />
WAS MINDFUL OF THE CALM AND DEEPLY MOVING WORDS<br />
I<br />
OF MR RAY GRENFELL, THE BROTHER OF ONE OF THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN VICTIMS, WHO AFTER EXPRESSING HIS SHOCK<br />
AND DISBELIEF AT THE DESTRUCTION OF AN UNARMED<br />
PASSENGER AIRCRAFT SAID " BUT WE DON'T BELIEVE<br />
THERE SHOULD BE ANY FURTHER VIOLENCE OR RETRIBUTION<br />
ONE ACT LIKE THAT DOES NOT DESERVE ANOTHER ACT".<br />
WE HAVE DECIDED TO CONTINUE TO PRESS THE SOVIET AUTHORITIES<br />
FOR A FULL ACCOUNTING OF THEIR ACTIONS. WE ARE<br />
EXAMINING WHAT STEPS MIGHT BE TAKEN TO STRENGTHEN THE<br />
SAFETY OF INTERNATIONAL CIVIL AVIATION. WE ARE<br />
SUPPORTING THE CONVENING OF ANI EXTRAORDINARY MEETING<br />
OF THE COUNCIL OF THE INTERNATIONAL CIVIL AVIATION<br />
ORGANISATION IN MONTREAL NEXT WEEK. THERE WE WILL SEEK<br />
k<br />
A FULL ACCOUNTING BY TH! E SOVIET. UNION AND A THOROUGH<br />
IMPARTIAL INVESTIGATION IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE<br />
9<br />
CHICAGO CONVENTION, r<br />
THE SHOOTING DOWN OF, THE KOREAN AIRCRAFT WAS A CLEAR<br />
INFRINGEMENT OF CUSTOMARY INTERNATIONAL LAW AND OF THE<br />
PRINCIPLES UNDERLYING THE 194 , CHICAGO CONVENTION ON<br />
INTERNATIONAL CIVIL AVIATION, TO W. HICH THE USSR IS A PARTY.<br />
S. 8/ </p>
<p>8,<br />
IT IS OPEN TO THE GOVERNMENT, UNDER INTERNATIONAL LAW.,<br />
TO CLAIM COMPENSATION FROM THE USSR FOR THE LOSS OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN LIVES. WE ARE GIVING CLOSE CONSIDERATION<br />
TO THIS POSSIBILITY. OBVIOUSLY ANY AMOUNT OF<br />
COMPENSATION WILL NOT RECOMPENSE THE GRIEF OF THOSE<br />
FAMILIES WHO HAVE LOST LOVED ONES IN THIS DISASTER.<br />
THE GOVERNMENT REGARDS THIS TRAGEDY AS AN AFFRONT<br />
TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, AS A RESULT, AUSTRALIA<br />
WILL SEEK TO CO-ORDINATE ITS RESPONSE AS WIDELY AS<br />
POSSIBLE WITH OTHER COUNTRIES AND PARTICULARLY WITH<br />
THE COUNTRIES OF THE ASIA/ PACIFIC REGION.<br />
IN THIS CONNECTION, I SPOKE WITH US SECRETARY OF STATE,<br />
GEORGE SHULTZ ON 5 SEPTEMBER AND HAVE CONFIRMED THAT<br />
OUR ATTITUDE TO THIS DISASTER IS CLOSELY CONSISTENT<br />
WITH THAT OF THE UNITED STATES. PRESIDENT REAGAN'S<br />
STRONG, CLEAR AND MEASURED STATEMENT THIS MORNING<br />
EXPRESSES THE PROFOUND CONCERN AND ABHORRENCE FELT BY<br />
ALL CIVILISED COUNTRIES AT WHAT IA'S OCCURRED, WHILE<br />
KEEPING OPEN THE CHANNELS OF COMMUNICATION ESSENTIAL<br />
TO PRESERVE INTERNATIONAL SEC. URITY,<br />
MR SPEAKER, THE SOVIET UNION IS NOW SEEKING TO EVADE<br />
i<br />
ITS RESPONSIBILITIES, TO SHIFT THE BLAME AND TO<br />
CATEGORISE THE JUSTIFIED INTERNATIONAL OUTRAGE AT<br />
ITS ACTION, AS CONFECTED INDIGNATION<br />
FOR PROPAGANDA PURPOSES. THE GOV'ERNMENT REITERATES THAT<br />
i<br />
THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT M. UPT PROVIIE A FULL AND ADEQUATE </p>
<p>9,<br />
ACCOUNT OF THIS TRAGEDY, I AM SURE THAT THE HOUSE<br />
WILL JOIN &gt; 1E IN CALLING ON THE USSR TO CEASE HIDING<br />
BEHIND EVASIVE STATEMENTS AND TO ACCEPT ITS<br />
RESPONSIBILITIES BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY<br />
FOR THE TRAGIC CONSEQUENCES OF ITS ACTION,<br />
U 9<br />
I -f r </p>
<p>MR SPEAKER, I SEEK LEAVE TO MOVE A RESOLUTION,<br />
( WHEN LEAVE GRANTED)<br />
I MOVE THAT THIS HOUSE:<br />
EXPRESSES AUSTRALIA'S SHOCK AND INDIGNATION<br />
AT THE TOTALLY UNJUSTIFIED DESTRUCTION OF<br />
A KOREAN AIRLINES , BOEING 747 BY SOVIET<br />
FIGHTER AIRCRAFT;<br />
EXTENDS ITS DEEPEST SYMPATHY TO THE FAMILIES OF<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN AND OTHER VICTIMS.;<br />
CALLS UPON THE USSR TO GIVE A FULL, TRUTHFUL,<br />
PROMPT AND APPROPRIATELY REGRETFUL ACCOUNT<br />
OF THIS TRAGIC EPISODE;<br />
URGES THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO TAKE<br />
MEASURES TO PREVENT THE RECURRENCE OF SUCH<br />
A TRAGEDY; AND<br />
SUPPORTS THE RESPONSE OF THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
i,<br />
GOVERNMENT AS OUTLINED IN THE PRIME MINISTER'S<br />
STATEMENT. i<br />
I<br />
i, i<br />
1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
