<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6179</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR RJL HAWKE, AT LAUNCHING OF NEW VICTA MOWER, SYDNEY, 12 AUGUST 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/08/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006179.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR R. J. L. HAWKE AT LAUNCHING<br />
OF NEW VICTA MOWER, SYDNEY, 12 AUGUST 1983.<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
IT IS MY PLEASURE TODAY TO LAUN(; i OFFICIALLY THE NEW VICTA<br />
VORTEX LAWI ( lOWER.<br />
AID WHILE I'M OBVIOUSLY NOT IN THE BUSI'IESS OF PRODUCT<br />
ENDORSEMENT, ITS ENTIRELY APPROPRIATE THAT AN AUSTRALIAN<br />
PRIME MINISTER SHOULD BE ASSOCIATED WiTH SUCH A VERY<br />
AUSTRALIAN NAME AND VERY AUSTRALIAN PRODUCTAND<br />
ESPECIALLY A PRIME MINI:; TER WHO REPRESENTS A MELBOURNE<br />
ELECTORATEAND LEST ANYONE FORGET I AM STILL THE MEMBER FOR WILLS!<br />
IT'S A FACT OFTEN REMARKED UPON BUT STILL A REMARKABLE<br />
FACT THAT, DESPITE OUR NATIONAL SELF-IMAGE, WE ARE THE<br />
MOST URBANISED NATION ON EARTH. A HIGHER PROPORTION OF US<br />
LIVE IN CITIES AND BIG CENTRES THAN ANY OTHER PEOPLE<br />
ANYWHERE IN THE WORLDBUT<br />
IT IS NOT SO OFTEN REALISED THAT WE ARE ALSO THE MOST<br />
SUBURBANISED PEOPLE ON EARTH. </p>
<p>IlILE MO i: UF US LIVE I CITICS, FCW: R OF US LIVE IN L.' iL<br />
rLTYø , AID Nor ONLY THAT WE HAVE THE LARGEST SUBURBS WI1H THE<br />
LOWEST C: ISIIY OF POPULAI ION ON EA,
AND THAT MEANS, ON AVERAGE, WE HAVE THE BIGGESr BACK YARDUS<br />
OR FRONT GARDENS ON EARTH.<br />
AND THAT'S WHERE THE VICTA LAWNMOWER COMES IN.<br />
VICTA IS AN AUSTRALIAN TRADITION. BUT IN FACT THIS<br />
PARTICULAR VERSION THE VORTEX IS REALLY SOMETHING OF A<br />
DEPARTURE FROM THE AUSSIE TRADITION.<br />
BECAUSE THIS IS TO BE A QUIET LAWNMOWER WHICH FOR SUBURBAN<br />
AUSTRALIA SEEMS ALMOST A CONTRADICTION IN TERMS!<br />
So AS AN AUSTRALIAN, A SUBURBANITE, A NEIGHBOUR, HOW COULD I<br />
DO OTHER THAN WISH IT WELL.<br />
BUT SERIOUSLY, I DO WISH THIS PROJECT WELL AS AN EXAMPLE OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN ENTERPRISE AND INNOVATION AND, IN PARTICULAR,<br />
AN EXAMPLE . OF CO-OPERATION BETWEEN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE AND A<br />
GOVERNMENT AGENCY.<br />
I UNDERSTAND CSIRO PROVIDED ASSr. STANCE IN TpE MASSIVE TASK<br />
OF DEVELOPING AND TESTING THIS PRODUCT. </p>
<p>ANI I ALSO IJNlDEWSTAND THAr THE NEW PowER " TORQU ENGINE WAS<br />
SUBJECTED TO OVER 50,000 HOURS OF TESTING IN ITS COMBINED<br />
DEVELOPMENT AND TESTING PROGRAM.<br />
1: 1I TIII. SE IFFi: CULT rIM. S WIIHEN MANY SECTOR. OF MANUJFAC rtJR IG<br />
INDUSTRY A: E EXPLRIENCING ACUTE PROBLEMS IT IS HEARTENING TO<br />
SEE COMPANIES LIKE VICTA LIMITED WHICH OPT FOR INNOVATION<br />
AND ARE PR-PARED TO SET A STAKE IN THE FUTURE.<br />
MY GOVERNMENT IS WORKING TOWARDS THE CREATION OF ANl<br />
EVNIRONMENT WITHIN WHICH EFFICIENT, INNOVATIVE FIRMS CAN<br />
PROSPER AND EXPAND. THIS IS ESSENTIAL IF WE ARE TO MEET AND<br />
REVERSE THE DISASTROUS DECLINE IN EMPLOYMENT IN THE PERIOD<br />
BEFORE THIS YEAR'S ELECTION.<br />
A FAVOURABLE ENVIRONMENT IN WHICH EFFICIENT AND INNOVATIVE<br />
COMPANIES CAN PLAN FOR THE FUTURE WITH CONFIDENCE AND<br />
CERTAINTY, HAS TWO PARTS: STABLE AND EFFECTIVE INDUSTRY<br />
POLICY; AND BUOYANT DEMAND FOR PRODUCTS WITHIN AUSTRALIA.<br />
WE HAVE BEEN WORKING ON BOTH FRONTS.<br />
OUR INDUSTRY POLICY HAS EMPHASISED CONTINUITY AND CERTAINTY<br />
IN POLICY, OVER THE LONG PERIODS NECESSARY FOR INVESTMENT TO<br />
YIELD THE PROFITS THAT ARE ITS JUSTIFICATION. BUSINESS<br />
FACES ENOUGH UNCERTAINTY WITHOUT GOVERNMENT ADDING TO IT. </p>
<p>ON EAJSIJS I ' JG 1HAT rHERE IS BUOYANT DOMESTIC DEMAND FOR<br />
AUSTRALIAN PRODUCTS, OUR MAJOR TASK SINCE TAKING OFFICE IIA'i<br />
BEEN TO IULPLACE THE STAGNATION AND DECLINE IN THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMY WITH SUSTAINED GROWTH.<br />
THE BUDGET tHAT 4ILL BE INTRODUCED TO THE PARLIAMENT NEXT<br />
TUESDAY WEEK BY THE TREASURER, PAUL KEATING, WILL SEt THE<br />
SCENE FOR A YEAR OF SIGNIFICANT GROWTH.<br />
THE DEEP-SEATED PROBLEMS OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY CANNOT BE<br />
SOLVED IN ONE YEAR, OR EVEN TWO OR THREE. BUT THIS YEAR WE<br />
WILL MAKE A WORTHWHILE START.<br />
WE ARE COMMITTED TO USING EXPANSIONARY FISCAL AND MONETARY<br />
POLICIES TO GETTING AUSTRALIA MOVING AGAIN. THE PRICES AND<br />
INCOMES ACCORD ALLOW US TO GO FURTHER ON EXPANSION WITHOUT<br />
INFLATIONARY CONSEQUENCES THAN WOULD OTHERWISE BE POSSIBLE.<br />
THE STIMULUS TO BE PROVIDED BY OUR EXPANSIONARY FISCAL AND<br />
MONETARY POLICIES WILL BE CAREFULLY CONTROLLED, TO PREVENT<br />
FIERCE COMPETITION FOR FUNDS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND<br />
PRIVATE INVESTORS. SUCH A COURSE WOULD THREATEN PRIVATE<br />
SECTOR RECOVERY BY PUSHING INTEREST RATES HIGHER THAN THEY<br />
WOULD OTHERWISE-BE.<br />
THIS. YEAR WE HAVE JUDGED THAT A BUDGET DEFICIT UP TO ABOUT<br />
BILLION WILL PROVIDE SULBSrAWTIAL STIMULUS TO GROWTH,<br />
WHILE AVOIDING EXCESSIVE PRESSURES ON FINANCIAL MARKETS. </p>
<p>As THE ECONOMY EXPANDS IN THE YEAR AIIEA'D, WE EXPCOT PRIVATE<br />
INVESTMENT TO RECOVER FROM THE LOW LEVELS OF THE CURRENT<br />
FI. A'ICIAL YFAR. THIS MEANS THAT WE WILL NEED TO REDUCE THE<br />
GOvE; NIMENT BORROWING IN 1984-85 AND SUBSEQUEN1 YEARS.<br />
HOLDING THE BUDGET DEFICIT TO $ 8.5 BILLION THIS YEAR, A! ID<br />
BRINGING IT DOWN IN FUTURE, REQUIRES FIP-i COMMITMENT TO<br />
LIMITING THE GROWTH IN OUTLAYS, AND TO MAINTAINING THE<br />
TAXATION BASE.<br />
FORTUNATELY FOR THE FUTURE OF AUSTRALIA, THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
PEOPLE RECOGNISE THAT FIRM MEASURES ARE REQUIkED IN THE<br />
INTERESTS OF NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY. THERE WAS CLEAR<br />
EVIDENCE OF THIS IN THE REACTION OF MOST AUSTRALIANS TO THE<br />
MAY ECONOMIC STATEMENT.<br />
IF WE ARE PREPARED TO WORK TOGETHER IN THE NATIONAL<br />
INTEREST, AND IF THOSE WHO ARE COMFORTABLY OFF IN AUSTRALIA<br />
ARE PREPARED TO BE REASONABLE IN THE DEMANDS FHEY MAKE FOR<br />
HIGHER INCOMES AND BETTER SERVICES, WE WILL BE ABLE TO MAKE<br />
1983-84 THE FIRST YEAR OF A LONG PERIOD OF GROWTH.<br />
THAT WILL HELP ALL AUSTRALIANS, INCLUDING OWNERS AND WORKERS<br />
IN FIRMS SELLING MOTOR MOWERS.<br />
iN THE DYNAMIC WORLD OF BUSINESS, INNOVATIONS OF THE SORT<br />
EPITOMISED BY THIS NEW MOWER REPE'SESENT THE ACHIEVEMENTS<br />
WHICH FIRMS MUST STRIVE FOR IN ORDER TO ENSURE THEIR<br />
COMPETITIVENESS. </p>
<p>BLLI! VL THA f VILIA i AN FXAMiPL E OF A CO M PANY THAr H'Sv 1Lr<br />
r I L; C H A L . Etl'L WI 1r lIAE RF-LEA'' I ( F .' HIS NEW LAWflMOWC<br />
r O Dv W! AIE qI INES SIPI G THE SAME IT OF INNVArION ANJD<br />
t-T C PR1 1; C! XI*' C IF) BY HE FO) UNIWIHl OF ICTA LTD. ? l'Y N<br />
Vi.: T'Jl IRIi ll\ if. 0 UN-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
