<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9681</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP 47TH ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE QUEENSLAND GRAINGROWERS ASSOCIATION, ROMA, 2 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009681.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
47TH ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE QUEENSLAND GRAINGROWERS<br />
ASSOCIATION, ROMA, 2 AUGUST 1995<br />
I am very pleased to be here, and thank you for inviting me.<br />
Some people thought it was a rather eccentric thing for a Labor Prime Minister<br />
to do to come up to Roma and open the 47th annual conference of the<br />
Queensland Graingrowers Association.<br />
" Not a vote among them", they said. People who mostly feel removed from the<br />
centre of things.<br />
By which I think they meant people who feel their voices are not being heard,<br />
who feel alienated from the political system, who feel the Government is out of<br />
touch. But then, that is an argument for coming not staying away.<br />
It's nothing new for people to feel that governments are remote I daresay it<br />
forms part of the popular definition, and it has done, I suspect, since<br />
governments were invented.<br />
Democratic governments included I reckon within a week of the first popularly<br />
elected person being sent off to represent his electorate, there were people<br />
saying " he's out of touch". Before he got there.<br />
So I don't think that this is a new phenomenon. But nor do I think it is one to<br />
be ignored. It is essential that governments understand what is happening in<br />
communities. Essential that they listen to the people. Essential, above all,<br />
that having listened and having understood, they make policies in the national<br />
interest.<br />
As I've said before: good governments listen, but so do many bad<br />
governments. The difference is in what they do. </p>
<p>In fact there is only one judgement to be made about all governments and<br />
that is whether the government of the nation has acted in the interests of the<br />
nation. And, by definition, in the interests of the people.<br />
The judgement is when these people were in strife and when their industry<br />
was in strife, did the Government do what a national government should do?<br />
Did it do what was necessary?<br />
Now, I think that in the case of Queensland's farmers, generally speaking, we<br />
have.<br />
And I'm pleased to see that lan MacFarlane said as much yesterday.<br />
Speaking of listening, I was pleased to listen to lan when I first came up here<br />
to look at the drought areas and in fact if you're within 50 metres of lan you're<br />
listening to him. And I'm delighted to be up here listening to him again. He's a<br />
passionate Australian and a formidable advocate for the farming community.<br />
I know there is much more to do. There is always more to do. Whether it is a<br />
farm, an industry, or an entire economy there is always more to do.<br />
I think farmers like yourselves have that at least in common with Prime<br />
Ministers and Treasurers we are both familiar with the sensation that the job<br />
never ends, that we never get to the last chapter, the one where we are<br />
entirely out of the woods.<br />
But if we are diligent and adaptable and hardworking we do get to better times<br />
we do get to comfort zones, we do work our way into a position where we can<br />
begin to make the hopes realities, and a position where we can survive the<br />
hard times.<br />
Let me tell you that is what we have been working towards these last twelve<br />
years. It is what the whole effort has been for: to get Australia onto a pattern of<br />
sustainable growth, to make us more productive and competitive, to make our<br />
economy more diverse and durable, to get more of us working in modern jobs,<br />
more of us trained in modern skills all of us, farmers included, able to share<br />
in the wealth of this country, and the future of this country. And all of us,<br />
farmers included farmers especially able to survive the hard times.<br />
Now I think we've made a lot of progress in this regard. I think we've made<br />
remarkable progress.<br />
But I am not in any doubt and never have been that a lot of Australians do not<br />
share this view.<br />
I am very much aware that the broad data on which governments are obliged<br />
to make their assessments of the nation's economic health do not always tally<br />
with the problems households and communities are having. </p>
<p>I also know that a healthy stock market does not mean that the same<br />
confidence abounds in Australian communities.<br />
And I know that this applies to rural and urban communities around the<br />
country. I have to say that the broad data have a lot to recommend them and I never<br />
heard a good reason why a government or a Prime Minister should not<br />
advertise national progress and say that in real and comparative terms<br />
Australia is making remarkable progress.<br />
Sure as hell, the Opposition won't say it.<br />
I think Australians should know that Australia has grown in every one of the<br />
last 16 quarters; and that with this economic growth we have had<br />
unprecedented employmet grpwth; and that we have had this with low<br />
* jnfi-atiorn-and we can confidently expect this low inflation growth to-Tcdhtinue.<br />
As the editorial in The Australian said at the weekend " This may be the<br />
healthiest recovery the nation has had certainly in modern times."<br />
It is unprecedented in our modern history we have growth which shows every<br />
sign of being sustainable.<br />
At this point my more experienced listeners will no doubt be preparing<br />
themselves for a recitation of government achievements.<br />
I will spare you the unabridged edition it takes a long time: but allow me to<br />
mention a couple of important recent developments.<br />
Among the good news the Government feels bound to advertise is the level of<br />
Australian productivity it has grown in the last three years at least twice the<br />
rate of New Zealand's. Let me say beware the new cultural cringe to New<br />
Zealand, and beware those who tell you that their labour market is more<br />
efficient than ours.<br />
The second bit of news we find irresistible is savings. For a generation we<br />
have tended to substitute inflation for savings.<br />
The double digit inflation we experienced in the 1970s and early 1980s did<br />
lasting damage to the culture of saving for the future, and it has proved very<br />
hard to re-establish.<br />
But we are now doing that. We've got low inflation that's fundamental. And<br />
with the reforms to superannuation we introduced in the Budget, personal<br />
savings will rise, national savings will increase substantially and I think we<br />
will see a savings ethic emerge in the Australian community. </p>
<p>These savings directly address our current account problem.<br />
The current account deficit won't go away immediately.<br />
Whose mortgage ever did? Some people win the lottery, but nations don't.<br />
The current account will turn not by a miracle or any stroke of luck or by<br />
wishful thinking. It will turn by saving and investing wisely, by continuing to<br />
work hard, by making the most of our resources by insisting, even if we make<br />
a fetish of it, that we stick to the path of sustainable, low inflation long-term<br />
growth. I will stop this good news bulletin there. I want to get back to farmers and, in<br />
particular, grain growers.<br />
And I'd like to get there by this means: I said that national governments ought<br />
to be judged by what they do for the national interest and the nation's people.<br />
I said, beware of those who only talk about listening. Beware of those who<br />
pretend they can satisfy everyone's need, who pretend they can be all things<br />
to all people.<br />
Now I know that many Australians are not feeling the full effects of the good<br />
news I have just broadcast.<br />
And I know that there are people preying on their disillusionment, feeding their<br />
frustration with messages of gloom and despair and by implication suggesting<br />
that, if only the government would do a couple of simple things, there would be<br />
bounties for everyone.<br />
The fact is that just now we are all coming to terms with a new kind of<br />
Australia. An Australia in which we have prolonged economic growth without<br />
inflation not a boom, not another sequence of wage-price spirals, but<br />
sustainable growth.<br />
It is the sort of growth which will enable us to plan and invest as a nation;<br />
realise more and more of our national ambitions and survive the downturns<br />
much better.<br />
And in the end that means personal returns more and better jobs, more<br />
security, more prosperity, better services, better communities.<br />
It is the sort of growth I might also say which has been made possible by<br />
Australians' own hard work, sacrifice and adaptability over the last decade.<br />
Low inflation, higher productivity, saving through superannuation these<br />
require government decisions, and often difficult decisions; but above all they<br />
have required a real effort from Australians.<br />
The sort of effort for which Australian farmers have long been admired. </p>
<p>Farmers surely know better than anyone the value of things I have been<br />
talking about.<br />
And I sincerely hope that they also know the Government knows the value of<br />
farmers. There are two ways to measure their value.<br />
You can do it with figures.<br />
Rural exports contribute about $ 20 billion annually to Australia's export<br />
earnings. That's about 35 per cent of the total.<br />
Of that we estimate that the 1995 harvest of wheat and coarse grains will be<br />
worth about $ 4 billion.<br />
It means that for all the changes to the structure of the economy, and all the<br />
essential diversification, rural Australia remains a very big player. And it<br />
always will.<br />
The other way of measuring the value of farmers is by their contribution to the<br />
spirit of the country. By the example they set.<br />
Some of these people who are growing the $ 4 billion harvest have been in the<br />
drought for as long as five years.<br />
They have endured extreme hardship and real despair.<br />
But they have stuck in there and, with the rain, they have planted nearly<br />
million hectares and, all being well, they will harvest about 25 million tonnes.<br />
The toughness and spirit of Australia's farming families should be an<br />
inspiration to the rest of Australia.<br />
And I think it is.<br />
And that is one very good reason as good as their productivity and efficiency,<br />
as good as the value of their harvests why Australia's farming families must<br />
survive. They are essential to the national psyche.<br />
Some, I know, will not be able to stay on the land. But this Government is<br />
determined to see that the vast majority do.<br />
It is one of the great challenges of the next decade or so: to see that the<br />
100,000 or so farming families of Australia are not replaced by a thousand or<br />
so companies. </p>
<p>I read somewhere that agriculture and grazing in Australia has caused the<br />
extinction of 78 species of plants.<br />
When you think about for it for a while, that becomes a very sad fact. Because<br />
extinction is irreversible. These are bits of our universe, pieces of the great<br />
design, gone forever.<br />
And if you think about it a bit longer you think we have to make sure that what<br />
has happened to these plants does not happen to our farmers.<br />
It's a challenge for all of us and I'm sure we won't fail it.<br />
I think the last year or so has demonstrated that the farmers of Australia and<br />
the Government have the capacity to work effectively together.<br />
In fact, looked at objectively, I think the last twelve years have demonstrated<br />
that. But what is so encouraging is the expansion of our collaborative effort.<br />
And I hope that the thinking on both sides has caught up with the<br />
contemporary reality.<br />
Canberra is indeed a long way from here. And here is not Labor's heartland.<br />
But, whatever, rural Australia thinks of the Government, the Government thinks<br />
well of rural Australia and when rural Australia needed help we did our very<br />
best to provide it. We still are.<br />
That is not a plea for thanks. What we are doing is no more than a<br />
government should do. We should not just listen we should work in<br />
partnership.<br />
Among other reasons, I say it to make the point that the next time we hear the<br />
fashionable anti-government refrain which has swept America and is getting<br />
louder here, I hope we can agree to at least say hang on, where else but from<br />
government will we get the help we need? I hope we can agree to eliminate<br />
the irrational and misinformed and prejudiced from our political debate.<br />
The fact is that while governments can't do everything, there is no substitute<br />
for them when it comes to a lot of the essentials.<br />
Here in Queensland, 5,500 farm families are receiving Government assistance<br />
at the rate of nearly $ 2 million a week. Across eastern Australia we have<br />
committed nearly $ 600 million.<br />
Large areas of eastern Australia, including many parts of Queensland, have<br />
received good autumn rains. </p>
<p>But we recognise that some parts of central Queensland are again in<br />
desperate need. We recognise that even those farmers who have got the rain<br />
they needed, now need help to rebuild.<br />
We are under no illusion that there is no more to be done.<br />
There is always more to be done!<br />
Nor do we think that helping farmers through the drought is the only job we<br />
have to do in rural Australia.<br />
I said earlier that Australia's rural industries continue to be of primary<br />
importance to the national economy, and Australian farming families of equal<br />
significance to the national fabric.<br />
We want to see Australian farms and Australian farming communities flourish<br />
and grow in the 21 st century.<br />
Farming families are a great national resource. It follows that the land they<br />
farm must be able to sustain their use of it.<br />
There can scarcely be a more important issue for Australian farmers than this<br />
and it is no less important for the Government.<br />
I don't believe there is anyone in this room who does not believe that our<br />
agriculture should be sustainable agriculture. And if by a simple snap of their<br />
fingers they could make if sustainable,_ Fiar sure that is what everyone would<br />
do.<br />
We need a collective national snap of the fingers. Not to do it, but to resolve<br />
to do it.<br />
We should recognise at once that this will be a difficult process. It will be a bit<br />
like farming; there will be ups and downs, set-backs, disappointments.<br />
But if any Australians know how to live with difficulty and endure a protracted<br />
struggle it is Australian farmers.<br />
I think we should take to the effort for sustainable development this sort of<br />
spirit. Whenever we talk about the degradation of our land we tend to sit in<br />
judgement on earlier generations of farmers and often the judgements are<br />
harsh. I am inclined to think that we should take a more positive view. They had the<br />
courage, ambition and energy to take on the land, and their efforts were<br />
substantially responsible for the nation's prosperity. </p>
<p>Their efforts made them legendary Australians. We now need the efforts of<br />
this generation of Australian farmers to make the country not only prosperous,<br />
but sustainable which means that there will still be farmers on the land<br />
and 100 years from now.<br />
Do this, and to those farmers of the future you will be legendary.<br />
The partnership between Australian farmers and the Australian Government in<br />
the National Landcare Program has been one of the great phenomena of the<br />
recent times.<br />
And it has been phenomenal. Not only because it has drawn so many farmers<br />
into the movement; and not only because this has had the effect of improving<br />
our land management practices.<br />
The remarkable thing about Landcare is that it has tapped the passion of<br />
farming Australians for the land itself. We have seen an incredibly swift<br />
change in the culture of Australian farming and that has created an infinitely<br />
more fertile environment for further change.<br />
A more scientific approach to the land has implications for productivity, for the<br />
quality of our products and therefore their success in export markets, for the<br />
viability of farms and therefore of farming communities.<br />
Of course it has also had the effect of bringing farmers into the centre of the<br />
debate about the environment and that is wher* e they should be, where they<br />
must be if we are to reach the right decisions about the land we live in.<br />
In recent times, Australian farmers and the Australian Government have also<br />
worked together very effectively to put Australia's case against the market<br />
distorting subsidies of the United States.<br />
No doubt many of you here are aware of the work being done by the Farm Bill<br />
Working Group to encourage change in US agricultural policies that<br />
significantly affect our interests. We have had considerable successes. While<br />
we should not over-estimate our influence, nor should we under-estimate our<br />
successes. And we certainly must continue. In particular we have to press for the EEP<br />
and the Dairy Export Incentive Program to be dismantled.<br />
Again, what matters is the collaborative environment we have established<br />
between the Government and the industry. It provides us with the necessary<br />
condition for doing so much more.<br />
In that context, I have to say that nothing has improved the environment in<br />
which we work so much as those major early reforms of a Labor Government. I<br />
mean those perennial structural problems which faced Australian agriculture. </p>
<p>Progressively dismantling the tariff wall has reduced the burden that is borne<br />
by our internationally competitive industries including agriculture.<br />
Floating the dollar delivered the biggest increase in competitiveness ever<br />
achieved in this country with labour changes, a 40 per cent increase since<br />
1983.<br />
And our greater competitiveness is not simply due to the nominal depreciation<br />
of the exchange rate.<br />
The Accord has meant that the depreciation did not simply translate into higher<br />
wages. The Accord has meant permanent increases in our international<br />
competitiveness. It has meant much more as well in productivity, flexibility<br />
and creativity, and industrial harmony. The last year has not only been a year<br />
of growth it has also been a year which recorded the lowest rate of industrial<br />
disputes since World War II.<br />
The benefits to Australia, including rural Australia, are immeasurable.<br />
I wouldn't be doing the Government justice if I did not remind you as well of the<br />
benefits that will flow from the Uruguay Round and APEC.<br />
For example, the Uruguay Round provides for a total reduction of 36 per cent<br />
in the quantity of subsidised grain exports and for a reduction of 21 per cent in<br />
expenditure on export subsidies.<br />
At the same time Australia has been leading the way in the formation and<br />
development of APEC. With the Bogor Declaration we have a framework<br />
within which free trade can be developed in the most dynamic economic area<br />
in the world. The benefits to Australia, not least to Australia's grain growers,<br />
will be enormous.<br />
Let me conclude by addressing a couple of the issues which specifically<br />
concern the grains industry. Our objectives might be summarised as growth,<br />
competitiveness and self-reliance.<br />
We want to see increased production and access to markets; institutional and<br />
market arrangements which maximise the competitiveness of the Australian<br />
industry; and an industry willing and able to take responsibility for its own<br />
affairs. To these ends we have deregulated the domestic wheat market and reoriented<br />
the Australian Wheat Board away from being solely a bulk supplier and<br />
towards differentiated product. The Board now has the ability to engage in<br />
value-adding of wheat and wheat products.<br />
Without going into details, grain growers can also expect major benefits to flow<br />
from the recent competition policy agreement between the Commonwealth and<br />
the States. </p>
<p>I know Bob Collins wants to hear the industry's views about new marketing<br />
arrangements before he puts considered options before the Government; and<br />
we are expecting to hear these views soon after a series of grower meetings in<br />
September.<br />
The ultimate objective is to allow growers every chance to seek out production<br />
and market opportunities, and the point of competitiveness is to help farmers<br />
reach this objective without hindrance or unwarranted costs.<br />
A self-reliant industry means one in which government participation is limited<br />
to ensuring that any clear public interest requirements are met.<br />
It also means an industry which is sustainable in an agronomic, economic and<br />
environmental sense.<br />
The drought has dramatically reduced grain production and this has led us to<br />
undertake the biggest peacetime importation of grain in Australia's history.<br />
Some 390,000 tonnes of whole grain has arrived in Australian ports since last<br />
December and there is potential for another 100,000 tonnes under existing<br />
import permits.<br />
I know that is not a fact calculated to please people in this room.<br />
I know that some of you have argued that the Government should divert some<br />
of our export grains to domestic use.<br />
But we took the view that the costs of this would be too high. It would damage<br />
our relations with established customers. It would also be a bad business<br />
decision because we can import the necessary grain for a lower price than we<br />
are receiving on the export market.<br />
We do not believe imports constitute a long-term threat to traditional suppliers<br />
to the domestic market, if for no other reason than the much higher cost of<br />
shipping and handling imported grain.<br />
We understand that the issue of imported grain creates imperatives for our<br />
quarantine and inspection services, we have therefore developed protocols to<br />
prevent the introduction of exotic pests, diseases and weeds.<br />
We have also developed appropriate cartage arrangements such as secure<br />
transport systems and dust suppression measures and these will be trialed in<br />
November. </p>
<p>While we are vigorously protecting our national interest in quarantine matters,<br />
we must also be mindful of our broader interests where Australia is currently<br />
challenging the legitimacy of import standards in a number of countries and<br />
our success will rely heavily on demonstrating that similar decisions affecting<br />
our own industry have an objective scientific basis.<br />
I will finish with these few remarks. Like other sectors of Australian industry,<br />
Australian agriculture has made extraordinary adjustments in recent years.<br />
Australian farmers have responded to the challenges of a rapidly changing<br />
Australian and international economy.<br />
They have proved their adaptability and at the same time confirmed what we<br />
have always known about them that they are not only highly efficient, but<br />
highly resilient and durable.<br />
It has been one of the very beneficial by-products of the great economic<br />
changes of recent years, that the relationships between the national<br />
Government and Australian industry and the Australian workforce have been<br />
substantially redefined.<br />
This is true of our relationship with rural industry and nothing is more<br />
important than that we continue to develop this relationship.<br />
The fact is that we can't succeed without each other. We do have a common<br />
interest and it is in the national interest that we recognise this.<br />
In recent times the drought has dominated at least the public side of our<br />
partnership; but it won't end with drought; and I look forward to developing with<br />
you new strategies for the prosperity of rural Australia in the better times that<br />
surely lie ahead.<br />
Even allowing for future droughts and all the other problems which regularly<br />
beset Australia's farmers, the potential is virtually unlimited.<br />
The farmers in this room and their families are overdue for some rewards and I<br />
can assure you we will do every practicable thing to see that they come your<br />
way. Thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
