<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4844</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH PETER HARVEY ON SIDE STEPS OF PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/10/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004844.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 9 OCTOBER. 1978/<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PETER HARVEY<br />
ON SIDE STEPS OF<br />
PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
Peter Harvey: What is your reaction to Mr. Wran' s victory<br />
in N. S. W. A great deal of play is being made on the fact<br />
that this now opens the way to Mr. Wran to come into Canberra;<br />
that this is in fact an election that was fought on Federal<br />
issues.<br />
Prime Minister: Well, I don't think it was fought on Federal<br />
issues. If Mr. Wran was going to try and come to Canberra<br />
as a result of this, and I know he has kept his options-open,<br />
that in itself says something about Mr. Hayden I think<br />
no doubt Mr. Hayden wouldn't like all that much. I think that<br />
we've got to be plain about it. It's a great personal tribute<br />
to Mr. Wran, there is no doubt about that. He did distance<br />
himself a bit from traditional Labor policies and attitudes.<br />
The advertisements and the publicity during the campaign<br />
were saying vote for the Wran Government, they weren't saying<br />
vote for the Labor Government and this in the circumstances in<br />
N. S. W. was obviously highly successful. I also think its<br />
worthwhile looking at the policies that the Wran Government<br />
has in fact been following. Over the last two or three<br />
budgets there has been reasonable expenditure restraint. In<br />
each budget there has been some form of tax concession, tax<br />
reductions, and I think its worth noting that the tax reductions<br />
would not have been possible if it were not for the pretty<br />
generous financial arrangements and tax reimbursement grants that<br />
the Commonwealth has made to the states. You can take that<br />
beyond N. S. W. It's not just NSW that's brought down budgets<br />
that have offered tax cuts. I think every state has, over the<br />
last two or three years and you haven't had the position of<br />
state governments putting up taxes to a very significant extent.<br />
I suppose with a bit of odd irony, one might almost say that<br />
we've been too generous with the states and if we hadn't been<br />
so generous we wouldn't have to had raise as much revenue as<br />
ourselves in this last budget to bring it out as an overall<br />
responsible budget.<br />
The other thing that I think is worth saying about NSW is again,<br />
that Mr. Wran played an extremely skillful campaign. I can<br />
remember seeing one particular telecast which was a prepared one,<br />
and he said at one point of course I am at one with the<br />
Commonwealth Government in its fight against inflation. Now,<br />
that doesn't sound like condemnation of Federal Government<br />
policies. So far as Mr. Wran is concerned, he has also of course </p>
<p>2<br />
been claiming an improvement in NSW industry. He's even<br />
been claiming in one of the advertisements an improvement<br />
in the employment situation from that which existed two or<br />
three years ago. Now if that's so, if Mr. Wran is right<br />
in relation to those matters, that again has to come back<br />
to the Federal Government's economic policies. So, I think<br />
there are many unique factors about the NSW election.<br />
It's unfortunate that Peter Coleman wasn't there longer.<br />
He took over in very difficult circumstances. There had<br />
been divisions and problems and I think he will be a sad<br />
loss to the NSW Party. He was a good man.<br />
Peter Harvey: But one aspect of any measure of the election<br />
has to be, surely, a vote against Federal Government policies.<br />
Do you really believe it didn't play any part?<br />
Prime Minister: I think it was an election, in spite of<br />
what I've said, that was significantly on state issues.<br />
Mr. Wran won, once before, shortly after we've had a landslide<br />
victory and then not so long after that again we had a further<br />
landslide victory. People have shown quite plainly that they<br />
are capable of voting one way in the State and another way in<br />
the Federal elections. That's not new in Australian politics.<br />
They've done it since time immemorial. They make their judgements.<br />
Again, I think Mr. Wran pointed to that over the last day<br />
or two. I've really been making the point there have been a<br />
number of unique factors about the NSW election. I say that<br />
without in any sense trying to diminish the credit that is<br />
clearly due to Neville Wran for a very significant victory.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
