<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10307</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP ADDRESS TO LILLEY COMMUNITY LUNCHEON</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/04/1997</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010307.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
16 April 1997 TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
ADDRESS TO LILLEY COMMUNITY LUNCHEON<br />
E O E<br />
Well thank you very much Elizabeth the feeling is mutual. Can I say that on the second<br />
of March of last year there were a lot of wonderful victories and there were a lot of<br />
individual results that gave a special pleasure. A few of us in Sydney got a special<br />
pleasure when Robert Tickner suffered a 12% swing in Hughes, but gee a lot of us got<br />
enormous pleasure when Wayne Swan got dumped too.<br />
He was meant to be that sort of top gun you beaut whiz bang campaign strategist and the<br />
local Liberal Party organisation in Lilley have demonstrated the quality and strength of a<br />
good grass roots campaign, and the 7% swing that Elizabeth and you together achieved on<br />
the second of March last year was one of those terrific result, and Elizabeth has done a<br />
fantastically energetic job. She is a true citizen of the electorate that she represents in the<br />
national parliament. She is a very energetic pursuer of things that matter so far as the<br />
electorate of Lilley is concerned and she is also a very very effective member of the much<br />
enlarged Federal Parliamentary Liberal and National Party contingent that has come out of<br />
Queensland as a result of the last election.<br />
But that of course is very pleasant history, but nonetheless political history. We won in<br />
March of last year, we had a great victory. Our political responsibility as Liberals is to<br />
retain the support and the esteem that we enjoyed in March of last year and the broad<br />
responsibility of the Government is to govern in the interests of all of the Australian<br />
community. And governing in the interests of all of the Australian community means<br />
attending to such things as trying to find a workable solution to the Native Title mess that<br />
we have inherited from the Labor Government and which has been made worse by an<br />
impractical decision of the High Court of Australia. It also involves continuing to<br />
implement measures that provide greater incentives for small business and it also includes<br />
as I recognise this morning a continued concern for the environment of Australia and a<br />
continued implementation of policies that will benefit the environment throughout the </p>
<p>entire nation. But at a local micro level, it also involves recognising the particular<br />
problems of this electorate and I know that today Elizabeth has announced federal funding<br />
of $ 435 000 that is going to pay for the improvement of three road accident black spots in<br />
Lutwyche, Bracken and Geebung and I think I pronounced all of those absolutely<br />
correctly. It is always one of the hazards of a travelling Prime Minister. There are two<br />
hazards you pronounce the local names wrong, or you forget the name of the local<br />
candidate. Now that will never happen with Elizabeth she is absolutely unforgettable,<br />
but there are many leaders and some Prime Ministers, other Prime Ministers I should say,<br />
in the past who have sort of fallen into that.<br />
But we've got $ 66 000 for the street closure at Lutwyche Road, at Stoneleigh and Trunro<br />
Streets at a cost of $ 66 000; 1 new traffic signals with turn arrows at the intersection of<br />
Bracken Ridge Road and Bracken Street, Bracken that's $ 157 000, and new traffic<br />
signals with turn arrows at Newman Street and Railway Parade, Geebung $ 212 000. So<br />
don't say we ignore the local grass roots issues. And Elizabeth has made an<br />
announcement about that today.<br />
But ladies and gentlemen I'm here to speak to you very very briefly today as part of two<br />
day visit to Queensland, centred originally around a Cabinet meeting that we had in<br />
Brisbane yesterday. We are going to follow this habit of taking the Cabinet around<br />
Australia. We are not going to Just sit ourselves down in Canberra and expect everybody<br />
to come to us, we are going to progressively come to you and the whole purpose of a<br />
government that tries to represent all of the Australian community ought to be seen<br />
travelling around Australia. And we've had a number of Cabinet meetings in Sydney,<br />
we've had a couple in Melbourne, we've had one in Perth, we've now had one in<br />
Brisbane, we've had one or two in regional areas of Australia and over the next few years<br />
we'll be going up to far North Queensland and we'll be going into the provincial areas of<br />
New South Wales, into South Australia, Tasmania and so on. Because it is part of the<br />
philosophy of my government to see Australia as being composed of more than the<br />
triangle of Canberra, Melbourne and Sydney, important though that is to the entire nation.<br />
The other thing that I should briefly say to you ladies and gentlemen is that this morning I<br />
made a very important announcement about the status of Senator Colston. I made it clear<br />
that when the Parliament resumes we would no longer accept his vote in the Senate. And<br />
we've done that because we believe, despite any consequences that may flow in terms of<br />
support for Government legislation, we think in all of the circumstances the appropriate<br />
thing is until these matters are resolved and he like any other Australian citizen is entitled<br />
to a presumption of innocence, he's entitled to his day in court, he's entitled to a fair trial,<br />
equally we are entitled to make a value judgment about the damage the issue may be doing<br />
to people's perception of the institution, and what I've said on behalf of the Government is<br />
that when Parliament resumes if he votes for us on a particular measure then a Liberal or<br />
National Party Senator will be absented from that division so that we don't benefit from<br />
his vote. And we believe that is the right thing to do. It may not in the short term be the<br />
most comfortable thing to do but in the long term I think it is the right thing to do for the<br />
institution of Parliament, and I made it clear this morning that that is a unilateral decision </p>
<p>on our part. I would expect the Labor Party to match it, but if it doesn't well that's for<br />
the Labor Party to explain away, Just indeed as it is for the Labor Party to explain away<br />
what apparently is the true reason that Senator Colston was not sent to Norfolk Island by<br />
the former Government. Apparently there was a deal made to bring Mr Courtice do you<br />
remember him, he was the member for Hinkler the deal was made to bring Mr Courtice<br />
into the Senate and to send Senator Colston to Norfolk Island, but Mr Ludwig, I think his<br />
name is, who runs the Australian Workers' Union here in Queensland didn't like Mr<br />
Courtice and he said " no, that can't happen", and the cleverly arranged deal then fell apart.<br />
So it has got nothing to do with high minded decisions about not sending somebody<br />
who'd rorted his travel allowance to Norfolk Island it's got everything to do with the<br />
fact that a union thug gave the thumbs down to a deal that both Mr Keating and Mr<br />
Beazley had put their names to a few months earlier. Very very interesting revelation<br />
today and it rather exposes the fact that all of this sanctimonious talk from the Labor Party<br />
about how they vigorously pursued things in this affair is precisely that, sanctimonious<br />
talk. But ladies and gentlemen I don't want to say any more about that issue. It has thrown up<br />
its difficulties. I repeat that like any other Australian he is entitled to his day in court, to a<br />
fair trial, to a presumption of innocence but until the matter is dealt with, we have taken<br />
decisive action to as it were take him out of the Parliamentary equation. I think that is the<br />
right thing to do and I think the Australian people will see it in those terms.<br />
There are just two other things that I want to say and that is to say as there are a lot of<br />
members and supporters of the Liberal Party here today, I want to thank the rank and file<br />
of the Liberal Party for the contribution that you have made to the fact that we have now<br />
after a very long political drought, we now hold office federally, and we also hold office in<br />
Coalition with the National Party here in Queensland. You need the rank and file of a<br />
political party when you go through periods of unpopularity. People in my situation are<br />
the fortunate beneficiaries in a way as far as the political profile is concerned of electoral<br />
success. But you are the people who keep the Party going, who make it all possible, and<br />
I've always had a profound respect for the rank and file of the Liberal Party, I've always<br />
displayed immense gratitude towards the Liberal Party organisation for the opportunity<br />
that it has given me. I would never have been a Member of Parliament, I certainly<br />
wouldn't have been leader of the Liberal Party and most certainly not Prime Minister of<br />
Australia had it not been for the understanding and support over the years that I received<br />
from the Liberal Party organisation. And I want to take this opportunity in the presence<br />
of your member, who let me remind you holds one of the most marginal seats in the<br />
country. It was a great win but it is an equally great challenge to hold onto the seat at the<br />
next election and she's doing her bit and I know that you are doing your bit and we'll<br />
endeavour at a Government level to do our bit to ensure that Elizabeth is returned with an<br />
increased majority whenever the next election is held.<br />
The other thing that I wanted to speak about very briefly is the importance in the policy<br />
approaches of the government, the importance that we attach to small business. I came </p>
<p>from a small business family and I was brought up to believe that about the most<br />
worthwhile thing anybody could do was to start a business with nothing and to work your<br />
insides out trying to make something and then give your own children a more financially<br />
secure start in life than you yourself may have had. And that was the ethic under which I<br />
was brought up and its the ethic that is very significantly influenced the lives of millions of<br />
Australians over the years. And it's a very important ethic, and it's a very important value<br />
system to the Liberal Party. It doesn't mean that we are hostile to people who aren't in<br />
small business. It doesn't mean that we don't appreciate the contribution of people in the<br />
public sector police and nurses and people in the armed forces and all the other hundreds<br />
of thousands of people who do an excellent job in the public sector, but what it does mean<br />
is that there is a special place in the value of the Liberal Party for small business. Because<br />
it expresses that notion of self-help and it also of course in a practical way, a reinvigorated<br />
small business sector still offers the best hope we have over time of reducing the still<br />
unacceptably high level of unemployment that we have in Australia. And I have been quite<br />
meticulous in seeing to it that all of the commitments we made to the small business<br />
community before the last election have been honoured. I don't pretend that it's still not<br />
difficult for small business, it is. And I know that many men and women in Australia in<br />
small business, and let me make the point in passing that more than 30 per cent of<br />
proprietors of small business in Australia are women, and the proportion of small<br />
businesses run and managed by women in Australia is growing at a very very rapid rate.<br />
So I use the description men and women in small business very advisedly and very<br />
deliberately. And I'm conscious that it has been difficult. I'm conscious that you don't<br />
always gets the same deal from the banks that large companies get. I'm conscious that<br />
you had to struggle with some pretty unreasonable industrial relations laws. And I'm very<br />
pleased that we were able to get our industrial relations laws through the Parliament. I'm<br />
very pleased that we were able to go a bit further in our Small Business Statement a few<br />
weeks ago and to say that any small business employing fewer than 15 people, and that's a<br />
very large number of small businesses in Australia, are completely exempt from any unfair<br />
dismissal laws at a Federal level in relation to people who have been employed for a period<br />
of less than 12 months, and I hope that that particular decision will be duplicated at a<br />
Queensland level by the Queensland government. I had a talk to my friend Santoro at the<br />
weekend, he's the local Minister for Industrial Relations, and pointed out to him the<br />
wisdom of Queensland having the same law as applied nationally and I hope that the<br />
Queensland government will not waste any time Mrs Cunningham willing in bringing<br />
Queensland industrial awards into line with those operating nationally.<br />
In the same area I am very happy to say that we promised in the last election campaign<br />
that we would give a capital gains tax roll-over relief for people who sold one business<br />
and invested the proceeds in another. Now what we have done in that area and it will<br />
come into operation on the first of July this year, what we have done in that area actually<br />
goes beyond what I promised in the election campaign. And after the first of July it will be<br />
possible for any person running a small business in Australia to sell that business and invest<br />
up to $ 5 million, $ 5 million of the proceeds into another business, not necessarily of the<br />
same kind, but indeed of any kind. In other words you can go from a book making<br />
business into a bakery, or you can go from a garage into a computer software company, </p>
<p>and you can invest up to $ 5 million without incurring any liability for capital gains tax.<br />
Now it does represent a very very significant change to the taxation circumstances under<br />
which small business will operate in Australia. We've also made a number of significant<br />
changes to the fringe benefits tax laws. We've said that any company that pays less than<br />
000 worth of fringe benefits in any one year will no longer be obliged to keep records<br />
in relation to fringe benefits tax provided that business maintains the same or a lower level<br />
of fringe benefits and of course continues to pay on a historic basis the amount of tax that<br />
it paid in fringe benefits in the previous year. That will relieve probably 20 000 to 30 000<br />
more small businesses in Australia from any obligation at all to keep fringe benefits tax<br />
records. We said that we would provide provisional tax relief through lifting the<br />
provisional tax uplift factor for small business to the tune of about $ 180 million a year, and<br />
that was implemented last year. We are also well down the road to implementing our<br />
commitment in relation to relieving small business of the regulatory burden of red tape and<br />
of course the reductions in interest rates that have occurred have in the main flowed<br />
through to the small business sector. But I would have to acknowledge that small<br />
business does not have from the banking system the same competitive conditions that<br />
apply in relation to home buyers and we have said that one of the reasons why we are not<br />
agreeable to the further merger of the major trading banks in Australia is that we don't<br />
believe the conditions of competition which are needed for that to occur are sufficiently in<br />
evidence and in particular we would like to see more being done by those banks for small<br />
business. And it's a theme that I will repeat endlessly as I go around Australia because I<br />
am not satisfied that the competitive conditions for small business are good enough,<br />
anywhere near good enough, and there does need to be more competitive banking<br />
conditions and lower interest rates for small business.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen for those of you who have been standing and have been kept by me<br />
for far too long, can I say again how absolutely delighted I am to be with Elizabeth in the<br />
Electorate of Lilley. I applaud her efforts as your representative. I thank you for the<br />
tremendous effort you put in getting her elected. I congratulate all of you on that<br />
magnificent seven per cent swing that you achieved and long may she continue to<br />
represent the people not only of Chermside, but the people of Lilley in the national<br />
Parliament. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
