<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6824</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF HOWARD SATTLER, 6PR</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006824.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF HOWARD SATTLER, 6PR<br />
27 January 1986<br />
E 0 E Proof Only<br />
SATTLER: How are you going?<br />
PM: Good.<br />
SATTLER: You are looking well.<br />
PM: You have got to look well in Western Australia.<br />
This beautiful weather you have got, Howard.<br />
SATTLER: You have just got the job with our tourist<br />
bureau. Today we are going to look particularly at<br />
the issues where the State and Federal Governments cross<br />
paths because that is why you are here. We have got<br />
a state election on on February 8th. And there are<br />
a number of areas which I am sure have been talked about<br />
previously. Interest rates is not a bad one to kick<br />
off with. And they were thought to be a big<br />
factor in the last state election.<br />
But it seems that Brian Burke has successfully hived<br />
off, if you like, the blame if there is any) nyu<br />
Government. How do you feel about that?<br />
PM: I don't know that that is what Brian has done.<br />
He has recognised the factual situation and has taken<br />
very effective steps to contain the impact of the upward<br />
move in interest rates. And those moves that he hras<br />
undertaken I support entirely. The Australian people,<br />
including the people of Western Australia, understand<br />
when you are talking about interest rates you just don't<br />
pick that out. You look at what is happening to the<br />
control of the economy as a whole, in which interest<br />
rate policy is but one element. And they see the fact,<br />
recognised again today, that Australia's economic performance<br />
is at the top of the world scale. That has again today<br />
been acknowledged in the United States. We have got<br />
higher growth, higher employment rates than anywhere<br />
else. We have got the highest employment growth rates<br />
in our country's history. When in that total mix of<br />
policies you have to do something in one area to protect<br />
what is happening elsewhere the people of Australia<br />
understand that. I<br />
SATTLER: Brian Burke is so confident he has said that<br />
khjlidsistnow on. imterest rates frm ee on nh<br />
e veI s going to go aongii. o ~ u ou have stepped </p>
<p>SATTLER cont: back a little bit from that. YOu are<br />
not as confident as him?<br />
PM: It is not a question of being confident. I am<br />
not getting into the area of making definitive statements<br />
about what is happening in the interest rate area.<br />
We can see the moves that have taken place recently.<br />
Brian has referred to the assessments that have been<br />
made by independent economists in that way. They say<br />
that interest rates have peaked and it is perfectly<br />
legitimate for him to point to that.<br />
SATTLER: Are they people to be believed? Well, if<br />
you had one person saying it, then I guess you wouldn't<br />
place much emphasis on it. But what Brian Burke has<br />
said is that if you loolI. ' YOinments that is what they<br />
are all saying. And if you get the range of comments<br />
I * think that is something to be taken into account.<br />
SATTLER: Let's talk about a couple of other areas.<br />
Interest rates was one. But the fertiliser bounty<br />
and you made him very happy about that but I am<br />
not so sure that you don't regret having given it to<br />
the Western Australian people.<br />
PM: I am fascinated as Prime MInister the way that<br />
you and other analysts after the event say didn't<br />
he do it wrong or I wonder now doesn't he think hie, WiJsh<br />
ke'd dopie, it differently. I just don't know the basis<br />
for this analysis that you undertake. Let's just look<br />
at what the facts were. This issue arose in a period<br />
when the Cabinet was in recess. We weren't due to meet<br />
until the 20th of January. I had resumed the Prime Ministership.<br />
I had had a fortnight off in which I had handed over to Lionel<br />
Bowen. I had resumed the Prime Ministership. I was operating<br />
from Sydney. Brian Burke came to see me in that interregnum<br />
before the Cabinet met and said look I have got a particular<br />
problem in this election situation. This is a big issue, is<br />
there something you can do about it because the anti-dumping<br />
duties as having this very serious impact. I said I will<br />
meet you. And I met him with Senator Button and Mr Kerin<br />
the two relevant ministers. And I undertook to talk about<br />
it with him because he, from Western Australia, was putting<br />
it up there. And it was done on the basis all right I will<br />
give you a decision which is relevant to you he whole matter<br />
affecting Australian farmers generally will fte considered<br />
in Gbitzf% That was a perfectly logical way to<br />
do it. It was the proper way to do it.<br />
A particular issue Mr Burke was confronted with it, we gave<br />
him an answer. We then considered it in Cabinet. We will<br />
be making a decision which will be giving the benefit of this<br />
protection to all Australians. ' So I just don't quite understand<br />
what you are on about.<br />
SATTLER: Well, it is just the fact that he had it happen<br />
for Western Australia<br />
PM: H-e was there and he quite properly in that situation,<br />
I have got an immediate issue can you do something. Yes<br />
I will but I tell you I am doing this in the context that<br />
YR t~ 1A1 ARFefldthe whole thing when Cabinet meets. That </p>
<p>SATTLER: Oo land rights. You seem to have kept your options<br />
open there on legislation. Although he<br />
says look if someone tries to impose land rights<br />
on me I will ? quit. Could you afford to lose him under those<br />
circumstances. PM: We won't be losing Mr Burke. I dealt with this issue<br />
yesterday) Howard. I simply said that I have a full understanding<br />
of Mr Burke's position. We have made it quite clear that<br />
we would hope that these matters can be handled at the<br />
state level. It is what we want to see happen if we can.<br />
Nothing will be done in regard to Western Australia that<br />
doesn't take full accountas Mr Burke has said needs to be<br />
taken account, of Western Australia' s rights and interests<br />
in this matter.<br />
SATTLER: So there could be land rights legislation at a<br />
federal level which will have different application in different<br />
states.<br />
PM: You don't put it exactly correctly. What we have said<br />
in the Parliament and outside, the MInister Mr Holding has<br />
said, that we would prefer a situation where the actual states,<br />
by their legislationcovered. this area of interest with generally<br />
broad principles being observed. Now what Mr Holding is doin3<br />
is having discussions with all the states and with interested<br />
parties.* That sort of thing is going" And in regard to western<br />
Australia where this issue has been in the public arena, and<br />
a question of possible legislation was in question last year,<br />
we have said all right we understand Mr Burke's position,<br />
And nothing that we will be doing will be done without full<br />
consultation and cooperation with him. Now there it is.<br />
It is quite clear in South Australia you have a situation<br />
where the state will make its decisions. Discussions are<br />
going on with Queensland, New South Wales, Victoria. Despite<br />
the frantic-efforts of a bereft Mr H-assell and a Liberal Party<br />
which is internally divided here and divided federally where<br />
Mr Hassell and Mr Howard are in totally different positions<br />
on fundamental things like interest rates. They are desperately<br />
trying to whip this issue up. bo1r<br />
SATTLER: Will we definitely have federal/ lanI rights legislation<br />
this year?<br />
PM: There is no definiteness about that. And I repeat that<br />
the Minister has said on behalf of the Government we prefer<br />
a situation where this issue could be covered by states.<br />
Now he has said that, and I have said it and I say it again.<br />
CALLER: Welcome to WA. The subject I would like to speak<br />
to you about today is interest rates. I note recently that<br />
the Finance Ministers of the large Western economies have<br />
held discussions to devise means of reducing interest rates<br />
in the international market place. How successful do you<br />
think these discussions will be in finding a solution to the<br />
interest rates problem given the complex state of the world<br />
and its money market. And if these talks do produce positive<br />
results, when can we in Australia expect interest rates to<br />
drop? </p>
<p>PM: Thanks very much for that question. It is probably one<br />
of the most profound questions I have received on talkback<br />
radio. It is very important because what happens in the areas<br />
that you are talking about will have its effect, to some extent,<br />
on the economic fortunes in this country. You-have got to<br />
go back a few months and recall that these ministers met in<br />
the latter part of last year in Tokyo and decided then that<br />
they were going to take action because of the way in which<br />
the United States dollar impact was adversely affecting theme<br />
And money was going into the United States, H-Iigh interest<br />
rates and of course as far as they were concerned they believed<br />
that not enough was being done internally in the United States<br />
to create an exchange rate and interest rate environment which<br />
was going to help them. As a result of their very significant<br />
operations, they did have the impact that they set out to<br />
do. They have recently met again and have, as I read it,<br />
refrained from taking the level of intervention in the exchange<br />
markets that they did then in regard to the dollar. But I<br />
think the important thing from our point of view is that they<br />
are prepared, they have indicated a preparedness nowto act<br />
in a way which will bring about a more appropriate relationship<br />
in interest and exchange rates to facilitate better trade<br />
and capital flows between the major countries of the world.<br />
Now from our point of view, the fact that they are prepared<br />
to take this action, they have demonstrated last year that<br />
they would, it seems to me is useful. But then coming to<br />
the final point of your question, what sort of timetable of<br />
impact does that have on Australia, neither I nor anyone.<br />
else can answer it because the fact that Ministers see the<br />
problem, they then have to be prepared to obtain within their<br />
own constituencies. in eL41<br />
country the determination of the governmental and financial<br />
authorities to take the series of steps that are necessary.<br />
As I say, at the end of last year, the latter part of last<br />
year, action was taken. And I just draw the conclusion from<br />
that that if during 1986 developments in the United States<br />
are adverse in a way which they will make the judgement that<br />
requires further action, they will take it. And that<br />
is, from Australia's point of view, a plus. Having said that,<br />
that still leaves the situation where we in Australia have<br />
to make our sets of decisions, which, within the whole framework<br />
of economic policy, to get the sort of right outcomes here<br />
as far as we can determine it ourself. And I simply want<br />
to conclude by making the point that since we have been in<br />
Government, it is nearly three years, we have consistently<br />
made the related sets of decisions which have brought about<br />
the position, recognised again this morning it! 3 happening<br />
consistently where the international judgement has been<br />
that the Australian economic performance is at the top of<br />
the international table. So we will continue to make the<br />
decisions here which will give us high rates of economic growth,<br />
high rates of employment growth' and with sustainable levels<br />
of inflation. To the extent that there is a greater preparedness<br />
internationally to make the right sort of decisions between<br />
the major economies and the United States that will be a plus<br />
for us as well.<br />
CALLER: Mr H-awke, welcome to the West. OVer here we have<br />
had a lot of talk about privatisation from Mr H-assell and<br />
the Liberals. I wonder if we could have your views on what<br />
you think about privatisation. </p>
<p>PM: The first thing 1 have got to say is that you need a<br />
radar set to track Mr Hassell on this. Back in October, just<br />
relatively a few weeks ago, Mr Hassell was embracing this<br />
word with the greatest enthusiasm seen for very, very many<br />
years. He was so in love with the word that he said he was<br />
going to keep using it all the time because it sent shivers<br />
down Mr Burke's spine. That is how important, how central<br />
to his strategy privatisation was going to be. Of course,<br />
Mr H-assell and the conservatives here have found out that<br />
it certainly sends shivers down people's spine. But not Mr<br />
Burke. It sends shivers down the spines of the electorate.<br />
And so having found out that the electorate doesn't like<br />
privatisation, Mr Hassell is now saying he doesn't, and it<br />
is not an important part of the campaign. It was going to<br />
be the centrepiece, now it has been cast aside. Now, that<br />
may be all right in one sense for him to say that but I don't<br />
think people are going to really believe him very much.<br />
Particularly, as Mr Howard, his Federal Leader, is still in<br />
love with the concept. Let me say this it is a load of<br />
hogwash. And everyone who knows anything about running the<br />
affairs of the community understands this. You have got the<br />
position where, if the Conservatives were ever given the chance<br />
and remember they haven't won a mainland election the Liberals<br />
since 1980, so they are not going to get the chance, but<br />
if they were it would mean they would be thinking about getting<br />
rid of operations like Telecom, Australia Post and the<br />
Commonwealth Bank. And in many of these areas, in the nature<br />
of things, there is already monopoly position so they would<br />
be handing over a monopoly of<br />
to their friends in the private sector who would then make<br />
a decision whether they would provide services or not. And<br />
their criteria as to whether they would provide services<br />
to the public would be in terms of whether they could make<br />
a profit. So you look in the area of Telecom for instance.<br />
The people who would suffer would be the people in rural<br />
Australia. At the moment, and it is fair, it is absolutely<br />
fair, we people in the major metropolitan areas, because of<br />
the density of operations really provide a subsidy through<br />
the public utility of Telecom, to people in country Australia.<br />
Now if Mr Hassell and Mr Howard have their way, and they<br />
sold off Telecom to their private friends then the people<br />
in country Western Australia would either not be getting a<br />
service or would be paying infinitely more for it because<br />
no longer would there be the cross subsidisation. And David,<br />
it is because the electors have seen that in South Australia<br />
they spoke very clearly on it that Mr Hassell is running<br />
away from what just a short time ago he said was the central<br />
piece of his philosophy. Now, I simply don't believe that<br />
in his mind he has run away from it. Just through the term<br />
of the campaign he is going to say it is not important.<br />
But if the electors of Western'Australia were to do what of<br />
course they won't, and that was to give him the opportunity<br />
he would be in collusion then with Mr Howard to try and impose<br />
upon the people of Western Australia, this stupid policy.<br />
And let me say to rural Western Australia it would be the<br />
people in the country areas of Western Australia who would<br />
pay most dearly if the Hassells of this world were ever given<br />
the chance to play around with this dreadful concept in Practice.<br />
SATTLER: Prime Minister, I wonder what you might think about </p>
<p>SATTLER cont: the concept or the prospect of privatisation<br />
in reverse story in the weekend papers here that TAA looks<br />
like it might buy East West Airlines.<br />
PM: I saw that. I don't know whether there is any substance<br />
in that. Let me simply say in regard to airline policy<br />
which I understand is very important for Western Australia,<br />
that as you know we have got Mr May conducting the enquiry<br />
at the moment. We will be looking forward with very much<br />
interest to Mr May's report and we will examine that. And<br />
in that context the review which has to be undertaken later<br />
down the line, in terms of decision on the two airline policy<br />
will be taken.<br />
SATTLER: The next caller wants to talk about airlines.<br />
Good morning Sam.<br />
CALLER: Good morning Howard, good morning Mr Hawke.<br />
PM: Godd morning Sam.<br />
CALLER: My problem, Mr Hawke, nothing to do with politics<br />
or elections. Regulation of international airfares. It seems<br />
that we have cartel with a benchmark set by Qantas, they set<br />
the fare, then all the other major international airlines<br />
ha-V6 Ot 1d follow. Now when Mr Beazley was the Minister<br />
for Aviation I asked him the same question. He said the<br />
Government or the Transport Department do not set the airfares.<br />
But on getting in touch with the international airlines they<br />
inform me that the benchmark is set by Qantas and all the<br />
other airlines must follow. Now, is any idea of deregulation<br />
of international air fares? That is the first question.<br />
I will give you the next one quick so you can get cracking.<br />
Our international debt Mr Hawke 75 billion. It costs a<br />
lot of lolly for interest on that isn't it.<br />
PM: Let me deal with them in that order. As far as the<br />
international air fares are concerned it is not right to<br />
say that Qantas sets the benchmark and then everyone else<br />
follows. It is a pretty competitive area. What you may have<br />
been seeing is just recently Qantas did, as I read, make some<br />
changes, some competitive changes. And they were then followed<br />
in that area by others. But at other times the initiative<br />
has been taken by other airlines, other than Qantas. And<br />
Qantas with the others have tended to then react because none<br />
of the airlines in this very, very competitive business can<br />
allow one to establish an air passenger or freight schedule<br />
which is way out of line with our own. Otherwise they go<br />
fairly quickly out of business. Now in regard to international<br />
debt the second part of your question. The two or three<br />
points that need to made about that. Firstly, most of that<br />
debt to which you refer is the private sector debt. In other<br />
words, the private sector has undertaken borrowing against<br />
investment projects here in Australia which in their commercial<br />
judgement are going to produce a cash flow which is both able<br />
to service the debt and provide them with a profit. That<br />
is the simple criteria under which the private sector operates,<br />
and properly operates. So they are covered by their investment </p>
<p>PM cont: and the cash flow expect,-' ions out of investments<br />
they have made wittn that borrowing. Als far as<br />
Australia's government borrowing is concerned, we are more<br />
than covered by our own reserve position. Having said that<br />
thirdly, however, we don't believe that one can go on accumulating<br />
a foreign debt forever at an increasing rate. And our policies<br />
have been directed towards ensuring a turnaround in our current<br />
account deficits. And we believe that that is in the process<br />
of succeeding. By the end of this financial year that the<br />
current account deficit will have been reduced down to about<br />
4 per cent from the level of about 5 that it has been earlier.<br />
And we are not talking boastfully about this, but we are<br />
quietly confident that set if related decisions that we've<br />
taken in this area will as far as Government can make the<br />
appropriate decisions be having it moving in the right direction.<br />
But I go back on the first point. I must emphasise to you<br />
tEhat predominantly the level of that debt is as a result of<br />
commercial decisions by the private sector.<br />
SATTLER: Okay let's take a call which is probably most<br />
appropriate today bringing Australia together. Hello Alf.<br />
CALLER: Good morning Mr Hawke and welcome to West Australia.<br />
I would like to thank you very very much for the job you're<br />
doing for this country and to bring all us together. And<br />
we are talking to each other as Liberals, Democrats, Country<br />
Parties and so on. So now we are really a united nation and<br />
I hope you keep doing the job for a long time to come.<br />
Thank you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Thank you very much Alf. Well what might<br />
one say after that except to say very seriously I hope that<br />
this time Australians will this Australia Day weekend just<br />
take a little time to think back what's happened in Australia<br />
in the last three years. I think we are a very, very much<br />
better, more optimistic country now in 1986 than we were in<br />
1983 and that's because the policies we've been able to pursue<br />
as you say, up to a very large extent been based upon trying<br />
to bring Australians together, to get them to work together<br />
and I think thef7ve responded magnificently and I want-to<br />
thank them and karticularly, while I'm here the people of<br />
Western Australia because in the very significant growth that's<br />
taken place in Australia in this latter three year period<br />
Western Australia's contribution has been outstanding. So,<br />
thank you for thanking me and I reciprocate and thank you<br />
and the people of Australia for their cooperation.<br />
SATTLER: Last call for the Prime Minister today. Good<br />
morning Thomas.<br />
CALLER: Good morning Mr Hawke.<br />
PM: Good morning. That doesn't sound like Thomas.<br />
CALLER: It is.<br />
PM: How old are you Tom?<br />
CALLER: I'm thirteen.<br />
PM: I see, what's Your comment or question Tom? </p>
<p>CALLER: Jell, I'd like to ask you why fuel prices differ<br />
and how long is petrol going to stay down?<br />
PM: I see. Well, why they differ through time and in various<br />
places I guess you mean Thomas. Well, if yol. z look at it<br />
through time, there are a number of factors that will determine<br />
it. At the Government level we periodically, every couple<br />
of months now, review the price and that takes account of<br />
really two things. What's happened to movements in the<br />
international level of fuel prices, the crude that is involved<br />
because our policy is called the import parity pricing policy<br />
because we want to conserve our own resources by pricing them<br />
in relation to what's happening in the world market. So that's<br />
one factor, that what's happening to those international crude<br />
prices and what's happening to the price of our dollar, our<br />
exchange rate. And our decision therefore, each couple of<br />
months, will tend to reflect those elements. So that through<br />
time will have an impact. Then, secondly, both through time<br />
and between places the actual discounting policies of the<br />
major oil companies will affect it and they might be making<br />
different decisions in different places and in different times.<br />
So those are the two different sets of elements Thomas that<br />
have an impact upon the price of the petrol pump.<br />
SATTLER: Prime Minister, thank you for coming in today.<br />
You talk about Australians and wanting to meet more Western<br />
Australians. Well, I understand that you're going to be at<br />
the Subiaco Australia Day Picnic at Lake Monger today<br />
and at Fry Park, Kelmscott at 6 o'clock tonight. Plenty of<br />
fresh air, hey?<br />
PM: I am. Monger Lake is going to bring back some memories,<br />
' cause that was just at the back of the hill where I lived.<br />
I used to go down there as a kid and swim and play around.<br />
SATTLER: Alright, thanks for joining us. I know there's<br />
some bad news coming up in the cricket shortly which will<br />
upset you.. I think we had 2 for about 130 or 40 or something<br />
like that.<br />
PM: Oh, dear, oh dear. Well, we' re sitting pretty comfortably<br />
to get in the final though I think Howard.<br />
SATTLER: Thanks for joining us.<br />
PM: My pleasure. Thank you very much indeed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
