<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5176</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF &#039;NEWSVOICE&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/10/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005176.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINI* STER_ COE 17<br />
from the Press Office Summary of, " Newsv6* ice"<br />
A meeting of combined railway unions this morning agreed on<br />
a* 48-hour strike by Victorian trains, trains and buses. The<br />
State transport minister told Parliament this afternoon the<br />
Government would not allow the men to strike for two days and<br />
then return to work to collect weekend penalty rates. He said<br />
the strike could well last for a longer period than even the<br />
unions realised, but he estimates a return to work on Monday.<br />
' ANSW union'official Mr. Jim Walsh warned today that if the<br />
Victorian transport minister carriesout any threats of longer<br />
periods of no work for the strikers, the Australian Railways<br />
Union might have to consider a blockade of Victoria in<br />
retaliation next week. Trains from NSW would be halted at<br />
the border, but preferably such action should be taken at<br />
a national level, he said.<br />
There has been strong trading in Ansett shares on the Sydney<br />
and Melbourne stock exchanges today. A total of about 325,000<br />
shares changed hands in this morning's trading. At the moment<br />
about 6% of the shares are owned by Mr Rupert Murdoch, and a<br />
further 14% by Mr Holmes a Court.<br />
The Head of the new Australian Federal Police revealed today<br />
he would like to have greater powers in fighting organised<br />
crime in Australia,-including the right to tap the telephones<br />
of suspects. Commissioner Sir Colin Woods, addressing the<br />
National Press Club in Canberra, said he intended to make<br />
the Federal police as accountable as possible in its operations.<br />
The Federal Government this afternoon signed its controversial<br />
fishing agr-eeient with Japan.. The signing took place in<br />
Canberra between the Japanese Ambassador to Australia and<br />
Mr Nixon. This afternoon questions were still being asked<br />
in Parliament as to whether the agreement for Japanese long-line<br />
tuna trawlers to operate inside Australia's 200-mile fishing<br />
limit Contained adequate safeguards for black marlin and other<br />
game fish.<br />
A warning has been issued to people travelling to tropical<br />
areas such as Papua-New Guinea and South East Asia to take<br />
precautions against malaria. This follows news today of a<br />
dramatic increase in the incidence of malaria in Queensland.<br />
In the first nine months of this year 102 cases were reported.<br />
People intending -to buy a new car in the United States have<br />
been given something to think about. Authorities in Washington<br />
have just finished carrying out safety tests on 20 new American<br />
cars, and only seven of the models met the standard required.<br />
The President of the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission,<br />
Sir John Moore, is to discuss the Federal Government's proposed<br />
amendment to the country's industrial laws with the Federal<br />
Government. This follows a meeting Sir John held in Sydney<br />
today with-representatives of Australia's 25 Arbitration<br />
Commissioners to discuss their objections to the proposed ./ 2 </p>
<p>amendments which went before the Senate in Canberra this afternoon<br />
for a second reading. Sir John this afternoon announced that he<br />
would discuss the government's amendments with Mr Street, and<br />
he issued a brief statement about the meeting they held:<br />
" An informal discussion took place this afternoon<br />
about the consultative provisions of the proposed<br />
new legislation. Those present were a number of<br />
senior presidential members of the Commission and<br />
the executive of the Commissioner's Association.<br />
As a result of this discussion, it was agreed that<br />
the president would seek an opportunity to discuss<br />
those provisions with the Minister."<br />
The consultative provisions about which Sir John speaks are<br />
the Government's plans that Commissioners must consult with<br />
their deputy president before making or varying an award<br />
dealing with wages or conditions. The 25 Commissioners have<br />
complained about these and other provisions in two telex<br />
messages they sent to Mr Street, the texts of which were<br />
leaked to the media in Canberra this week. The Commissioners<br />
also told the Minister that they were not happy with union<br />
deregistration proposals in the amendments.<br />
0o---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
