<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17249</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Minister for Innovation Building expertise in national security: launch of the National Security College 24 April 2010 </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government today has formally opened the National Security College at the Australian National University, which will become a central institution in shaping the future of the nation's security policy and personnel.</p>
<p>In the 21st century Australia faces a more complex national security environment than at any time in its history.</p>
<p>To respond to the challenges the Australian Government is working to build a new level of expertise among our national security professionals.</p>
<p>The National Security College will draw together policy makers and others into high-level courses to deepen national security capability.</p>
<p>The College will receive up to $17.3 million over four years to assist with its establishment.</p>
<p>Its courses will be designed to strengthen the ability of national security leaders to analyse Australia's strategic environment and the dynamics of change within it, and to recognise and respond to threats. It will foster a new national security culture.</p>
<p>The College will be the training ground for future generations of national security experts.</p>
<p>Australia depends upon having trusted networks of interaction between the government's national security professionals and those in state and local governments, business, academia and the community engaged in national security matters.</p>
<p>The National Security College will help improve coordination, cooperation and collaboration across government, and will be a key element of our new national security community.</p>
<p>A new building will be constructed for the College the ANU, likely to open around the end of 2012.</p>
<p>Professor Michael L'Estrange AO, former Secretary of the Department of Foreign and Trade, is the founding Executive Director of the National Security College.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
