<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7455</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S SPEECH AT LAUNCH OF THE CONVICT WORKERS OLD MINT, SYDNEY FRIDAY, 13 JANUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/01/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007455.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~~ ALI L3)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH AT LAUNCH OF<br />
THE CONVICT WORKERS<br />
OLD MINT, SYDNEY<br />
FRIDAY, 13 JANUARY 1989<br />
Ladies and G-entlemen<br />
1am delighted to be here today to launch Convict Workers.<br />
The occasion, and the historic setting of the old Mint in<br />
which we stand, provide me with an opportunity to reflect -on<br />
the Bicentennial Year, and on the sense of our history which<br />
it engendered.<br />
The Bicentenary was not, nor was it ever intended to be,<br />
merely a birthday party. Re-enactments of historical events<br />
served to direct attention to our past. So too did the<br />
publication of hundreds of new history books stimulated by<br />
the Bicentenary.<br />
As a young nation, concerned with our place in the world, we<br />
need to examine our national identity, and to search out our<br />
roots not out of an antiquarian interest in the past but<br />
as a means of discovering our present and assessing our<br />
future. The Bicentenary helped us to understand our<br />
origins, to think honestly about our strengths and our<br />
weaknesses as a nation, and to plan for the challenges<br />
ahead. it is a matter of record, and regret, that not all<br />
Australians took that opportunity. For reasons of political<br />
convenience rather than conviction, some sought to replace a<br />
sense of history with a misplaced sense of nostalgia,<br />
through the deceptive slogan, " One Australia"; pride in our<br />
developing national identity was supplanted by a crude and<br />
divisive nationalism, which hurt thousands of Australians<br />
and left many of the wondering whether they were truly at<br />
home in this country; and a simplistic view of an avowedly<br />
conformist past provided a bleak vision of our " future<br />
directions". Fortunately, most Australians used the time productively.<br />
1988 saw a nation-wide ' historic records search' designed to<br />
locate those records of our past which remain in private<br />
hands, treasured as heirlooms by the families that created<br />
them. A wealth of written material was uncovered: diaries<br />
and letters and account books which will help us to re-write </p>
<p>our history. The project symbolized the fact that our<br />
development as a nation is based on the lives of ordinary<br />
Australians going about their everyday business. Our past<br />
has been made, as ; iii -u future, by those who until now<br />
have rarely featured our history textbooks by those who<br />
reap our harvests, dia cur ores, build our manufactured<br />
goods, provide cur serv,_ ces, bring up our families.<br />
The lives of so-cailed crolnary Australians are enormously<br />
complex and % var-eo, as are their backgrounds. Some trace<br />
their roots, wilth increasing pride, to the rich diversity of<br />
Aboriginal cuit--res wnich existed on this continent for at<br />
least 40,000 v'ears '_ efcre the convict workers arrived. In a<br />
splendid twist : r ._-rcny, the Bicentenary has succeeded in<br />
making Austrañ i, ns m. ore aware that our history did not begin<br />
in 1788.<br />
Other Australians, -with equal enthusiuasm, trace their<br />
heritage to those ,, ho were transported to these shores or<br />
-who come as free settlers seven or eight generations ago.<br />
But now, as throughout our history, a large proportion of<br />
Australians are immigrants. The institutional structure<br />
which today characterises Australia parliamentary<br />
democracy, the rule of law, freedom of speech were ideas<br />
transplanted in a new world by wave after wave of British<br />
and Irish settlers. Increasingly that structure and the<br />
ideas of fairness, equity and tolerance which it nourished<br />
has provided a home for settlers from continental Europe,<br />
the middle East and Asia. Out of that creative interplay of<br />
diverse cultures in a new nation has evolved an exciting,<br />
vibrant and innovative society a multicultural society<br />
presented so convincingly in Jim Jupp's Encyclopaedia of the<br />
Australian People, another important Bicentennial project to<br />
which a number of the authors here today contributed.<br />
But rich and significant as are the day-to-day lives of<br />
Australians, too often they are made inarticulate by<br />
history. I am often frustrated by the fact that my every<br />
word and deed is liable to interpretation and dare I say<br />
misinterpretation by media commentators, and my actions<br />
significant or trivial preserved for posterity. Yet it is<br />
equally frustrating that the Australians whom I meet, whose<br />
concerns are of such consequence to the making of political<br />
decisions, and whose interests gave rise to the great party<br />
which I am now so proud to lead that those same<br />
Australians are too often absent from our history.<br />
The difficulty is that interpretation is to a large extent<br />
shaped by the written records at hand, in which the voices<br />
of Australian workers are often heard only at second hand.<br />
Thankfully convicts did leave records criminal records.<br />
And the book which ITlaunch today, through application of a<br />
computer technology unimaginable a generation ago, uses<br />
those records to paint a portrait of our first European<br />
workers which bears little resemblance to the stereotype of<br />
Fagin that is usually encountered in our history. </p>
<p>Convict workers forces us to re-assess the foundations of<br />
those values wich we recognise as distinctively Australian.<br />
In a mere two hundred years we have developed from a British<br />
open prison to an independent niation enmeshed in the<br />
economies of Asia and the Pacific Rim. And that remarkable<br />
development has coloured the way in which we have viewed our<br />
cast. in 1388 c~ nviczism w~ as still viewed as a stain on our<br />
history, a deep embarrassment to an affluent society in<br />
-which -workers -were building one of the world's first Labor<br />
part~ es. After all, only twenty years before had the last<br />
fleet of ccnvic: s teen landed in West Australia.<br />
By 1938, :-ransported criminals had been retrospectively<br />
pardoned. Australian schoolchildren were taught that those<br />
who were reail cuilty remained back in Britain: the<br />
convicts were victims, pushed into poaching or theft by<br />
poverty, and often sent to Australia for their political<br />
persuasions. In my generation a new historical vision emerged, expounded<br />
most brilliantly by Manning Clark. I was taught that we had<br />
to be more honest about our past and that honesty meant<br />
coming to terms with our unsavoury beginnings, and<br />
recognising that those transported were unskilled hardened<br />
criminals. But, as Manning Clark himself emphasized recently, each<br />
generation has the task of re-interpreting its history, of<br />
viewing the past from a new present. Convict Workers is<br />
just such a radical challenge to prevailing orthodToxy.<br />
It is perhaps not surprising that during a period in which<br />
our immigration policy has become such a matter of debate<br />
that Convict Workers examines transported criminals as<br />
migrants. Nor is it surprising that our contemporary<br />
concern with improving education and training opportunities<br />
for Australian workers finds expression in a book which<br />
assesses our convict forbears, both women and men, in terms<br />
of their human capital not just as thieves but as youthful<br />
workers possessing remarkably high levels of literacy, work<br />
skill and physical fitness; not just prisoners undergoing<br />
punishment but as a well-organised, efficient labour force.<br />
I doubt that the controversial findings of this book will be<br />
accepted readily. Nor should they be. What the book does<br />
achieve is a sophisticated re-examination of our beginning<br />
as a convict society, and the impact of that experience on<br />
our values today. It makes us look more critically at<br />
conventional wisdom. Here we discover not just 20,000<br />
thieves and villains, but 20,000 workers cooks and<br />
carpenters, plasterers and ploughmen, soldiers and sailors,<br />
gardeners and governesses, and even, I note with some<br />
enthusiasm, a cricket-ball stitcher. Many, perhaps most, of<br />
those transported for criminal offences not only had manual<br />
skills of value to building a new colony but also had ideas<br />
as to the sort of society that they wanted to create when<br />
they regained their status as free workers. </p>
<p>There can be no doubt that many of the conclusions of this<br />
book that convict diet was nutritionally high, that<br />
working conditions -were good, that the lash was used in<br />
moderation will arouse considerable controversy. But more<br />
fundamentally this oook, by presenting transported convicts<br />
as migrants and workers, allows Australia's history as a<br />
oenal settlement to become an integral part of the economic<br />
nistory of an imrmiarant society, rather than being treated<br />
as an unsavoury aberration that : preceded free settlement.<br />
On that score alone the nook . s to be welcomed.<br />
To Steve Nicholas, he Editor of Convict Workers; and to his<br />
fellow authors Kr~ s Corcoran, BarreysrDvdMeit,<br />
Debbie Oxley, John Perkins and of course to Peter Shergold<br />
who is doing an outstanding job as Head of the Office of<br />
multicultural Affairs in my Department; I offer my<br />
congratulations for a stimulating reinterpretation of our<br />
past. I am delighted that Cambridge University press are<br />
now publishina in Australia, and have chosen this book as<br />
the first in a series of studies in Australian history. if<br />
later volumes are as provocative as this the press will have<br />
contributed to a significant re-evaluation of our past by<br />
the time that we celebrate our next important anniversary<br />
our centenary as a nation in 2001.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, it gives me great pleasure to launch<br />
Convict Workers. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
