<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>20568</transcript-id>
    <title>ACT Bushfire Appeal  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/01/2003</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Commonwealth Government will contribute $500,000 to the Canberra Bushfire Recovery Appeal established by the ACT Government to assist those who have been affected by bushfires.</p>
<p>Australians are deeply concerned at the loss of life and the many injuries inflicted on the Canberra community.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the destruction of property and the damage caused by these bushfires has taken an enormous toll on the ACT.</p>
<p>My sympathy and that of all Australians are with all those affected at this time.</p>
<p>As the people of Canberra know only too well the threat to homes and property is still present, and our thoughts are with all those in the ACT and in those states where communities continue to face possible danger from bushfires.</p>
<p>The tremendous efforts of the firefighters, police, emergency services and other personnel including the many volunteers, who have fought the fires and provided assistance to those who have suffered injury and loss has been inspiring. I thank them for all that they are doing to assist the community through this difficult time.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth Government stands ready to assist in whatever way is appropriate the territory and state authorities in their efforts to combat the fires.</p>
<p>In addition to contributing to the appeal, the Commonwealth will be providing short and long term relief under Natural Disaster Relief Arrangements (NDRA) established to deal with these types of disasters whenever they occur throughout Australia.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth will meet 50% of the cost of personal hardship and distress payments made to people by the ACT Government to provide emergency food, clothing and accommodation or to make essential housing repairs or replace essential household goods.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth will also, above agreed thresholds, meet 50% and then 75% of the costs to the ACT Government of providing concessional interest rate loans and grants, replacing essential public assets and counselling services.</p>
<p>I would encourage all Australians to support the Canberra Bushfire Recovery Appeal.</p>
<p>Contributions to the fund will be tax deductible, and can be made at Commonwealth Bank branches, National Australia Bank branches, ACTAB outlets and at ACT Government shopfronts.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
