<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9702</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING,  MP AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS PACIFIC TRIBUTE LUNCHEON-TOWNSVILLE 14 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009702.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AIi;<br />
PRIME MINISTER 1<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MPR<br />
AUSTRALIA REMEMBERS PACIFIC TRIBUTE LUNCHEON TOWNS VILLE<br />
14 AUGUST 1995 ** CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY m<br />
Ambassador, distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen.<br />
It is a pleasure and a privilege to be in Townsville to pay tribute to this brave city<br />
on the 50th anniversary of the end of the war in the Pacific.<br />
I have always had a feeling Townsvilles story is probably not as well known as it<br />
should be.<br />
Not all Australians are aware that the city was bombed on four occasions in July<br />
1942; and not everyone appreciates the stress and hardship it endured during the<br />
War.<br />
The Japanese airmen were not as accurate as they might have been with their<br />
bombs, but the incidents do give us some idea of the pressure the people of<br />
Townsville were under and the strategic importance of Townsville to the conduct<br />
of the war.<br />
In the darkest days when a Japanese invasion of the Australian mainland seemed<br />
imminent a report by Sir John Lavarak recommended that 10,000 civilians be<br />
evacuated south. The evacuation never happened, but between 1939 and 1942<br />
about twenty five percent of Townsville's population left<br />
This place was an entry point for refugees from South -east Asia after the fall of<br />
Singapore, and a refuge for soldiers, sailors and airmen returning from battle in<br />
New Guinea and the Pacific.<br />
Townsville was also, of course, a major embarkation point for troops and<br />
supplies, and it was the most important Allied airbase in Australia </p>
<p>This was the home of the " Kennedy' Regiment, 31 st Battalion which served in the<br />
Middle East and at Kokoda, Buna and Gona; and, when linked with the 51 st<br />
Battalion. at Lae and Ramu Valley, and at Balikpapan in Borneo.<br />
Then, as now, Townsville was recognised as a vital link in the chain of Australia's<br />
northern defence.<br />
As Allied forces led by the United States first resisted and then began to drive<br />
back the Japanese, Townsville's role became pivotal.<br />
It was the home to the 5th American Air Force and I believe it still is, in the<br />
sense that they have Freedom of Entry to the city.<br />
Its presence involved thousands of civilians and military men and women, both<br />
American and Australian, in the service of the US Army Air Force.<br />
During the War Townsville was host, all told, to 90,000 troops the highest<br />
soldierlcivilian ratio of any Australian city.<br />
There were two RAAF squadrons No 7 Beaufort Bomber and No 80 Kittyhawk.<br />
The No 1 Wireless Unit of the RAAF was located here at a top secret Central<br />
Bureau of Intelligence base intercepting and decoding Japanese signals.<br />
Among those engaged in Intelligence were members of the Women's Auxiliary<br />
Australian Airforce and the Australian Women's Army Service.<br />
The RAN worked out of Townsville of course, shipping Australian and American<br />
troops to New Guinea and the Pacific Islands and providing escorts and patrols.<br />
As the most important Allied Military and Air base in the north of Australia and the<br />
Headquarters, for Naval Intelligence, no city in Australia no community in<br />
Australia made a greater contribution to victory in the Pacific.<br />
You can't turn a civilian town into a military base without putting strain on the<br />
community. But Townsville clearly wthstood the strain. The civilian population<br />
returned, the city grew and developed.<br />
Today the city combines thetwin sads of tshstory as afrofer ownanda<br />
grrison town. It has an important place In Australia's economic future and a<br />
continuing strategic role In our defence.<br />
Two thousand nine hundred soldiers of the Australian Army's Third Brigade are<br />
here as part of the Ready Deployment Force. Among their many essential tasks<br />
are conventional mil" tr operaitions; protected evacuations of Australian nationals,<br />
and the provision of personnel and equipment for UN or multinational operations. </p>
<p>3<br />
The Brigade has recently distinguished itself in operations in Somalia, Cambodia<br />
and Bougainville and provided support to Australia's medical contingent In<br />
Rwanda which arrives back in Townsville in about ten days.<br />
The R. AAF took over Townsville Aerodromne in 1939 and it maintains a significant<br />
presence, with 1,250 personnel providing support for air operations.<br />
The Army's 5th Aviation Regiment, which is also based at RMAF Townsville, was<br />
deployed to Cambodia to support UN sponsored elections, and more rcntly to<br />
Buka in Bougainville as part of Operation Lagoon.<br />
So the Townsville tradition continues. As I've said on other occasions, this is one.<br />
of the outstanding cities of Australia.<br />
It has the strength which comes from its place on the northern frontier. It has<br />
withstood the ups and downs of droughts and depressions which afflict rural life.<br />
And carried more than its share of the weight of the war and emerged stronger<br />
than it began.<br />
In 1995 there are signs in Townsville to remind us of the past in particular those<br />
memorials to the great alliance with the United States the Coral Sea Memorial<br />
and the memorial to the 5th American Air Force.<br />
With Ed Perkins here today I want to py tribute to the American men and women<br />
who fought and died so bravely in the war against Japan they fought for our<br />
freedom as weli as America's, and you may be sure that this country will never<br />
forget that<br />
But, above all, today I want to pay tribute on behalf of the nation to the people of<br />
Townsville, for all they did for Australia during the war and all they continue to do.<br />
I mentioned the visible signs of Townsville's contribution to the war but I think<br />
the real indication lies in all that has been done since, all that is being done now.<br />
It lies in the spirit of the place and the people. I think that is what counted and<br />
today It has been my privilege to join you here in tribute. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
