<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3915</transcript-id>
    <title>HIGH COURT JUDGEMENTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003915.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Lp<br />
Jj, USTRALr. -6<br />
PIRI ME MWISTEER Press Statement No. 571<br />
October 1975<br />
HIGH COURT JUDGEMENTS<br />
This morning the High Court delivered judgements<br />
on a Queensland Act of Parliament and three Australian Acts<br />
of Parliament. It declared that the Act of the Queensland<br />
Parliament was not valid and the Acts of the Australian<br />
Parliament were valid.<br />
The significance of the judgement on the first of<br />
the Australian Acts of Parliament is that it confirms that the<br />
people of the Northern Territory and the Australian Capital<br />
Territory can elect two Senators to represent them and vote<br />
for them. Those Senators will be elected on the first occasion<br />
that there is a general election for the Federal Parliament,<br />
whether it is an election for half the Senate or whether it is<br />
an eleb&amp; tilohn"' fo r the'-Iiouse -of.. R6presentat~ ives. fitis an<br />
e -, for~ lhlf ~ t~ Snt~ hyiiak of., ice , f roin the<br />
day that the poll is declared. And, incidentially, the<br />
successors to Senator Bunton and Senator Field would take<br />
office, not from the 1st of July next from but the day the<br />
poll was declared. T'he sianificance of the judgement on the other federal<br />
Acts, concerns the principle of one vote, one value. Therehave<br />
been suggestions that the Australian Government should not<br />
have sought to distribute the States on this basis of one vote,<br />
one value, because these Acts were under challenge in the<br />
High Court. The High Court has now said that these Acts were<br />
valid. Accordingly the distribution of the States on the<br />
principle of one vote, one value, should go ahead.<br />
There have been some ironies in the question of<br />
representation of the Territories in the Senate, in that when<br />
these Bills were first debated two and a half years ago, the<br />
Liberals opposed them but the Country Party in the House of<br />
Representatives supported them. In the Senate the Liberal Senators<br />
and the Country Party Senators all opposed them. On the two<br />
subsequent occasions when the Bill for Territory Representation<br />
in the Senate was passed by the House of Representatives the<br />
Opposition didn't record votes against -it, but in the Senate on<br />
those two further occasions every Liberal and Country Party<br />
Senator opposed the Bill. At the joint sitting the Liberal and<br />
Country Parties opposed the Bill. There is obviously a<br />
difference of opinion in * the Country Party on this question.<br />
The Bill was challenged by the Queensland Premier, a member of<br />
the Country Party, in the High Court although supported by<br />
members of the Country Party in the Hour, of Representatives </p>
<p>-2-<br />
on the only occasion when a vote was taken in the House of<br />
Representatives. The Country Party Premier of Queensland<br />
sought to denyr the right of the Country Party to have a vote<br />
for the Country Party MHember for the House of Representatives<br />
for the N-, orthern Territory or to have a senator for the Northern<br />
Territory at all.<br />
The Liberal governments of New South Wales and Victoria<br />
supported the Queensland government in its challenges to the<br />
one vote, one value bills which were first introduced in<br />
March 1973.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. &gt; A jI 1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
