<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9724</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP, AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE PHILIPPINES, HIS EXCELLENCY MR FIDEL RAMOS, JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 22 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009724.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I<br />
( J)<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP,<br />
AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE PHILIPPINES, HIS EXCELLENCY MR<br />
FIDEL RAMOS, JOINT PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE,<br />
CANBERRA, 22 AUGUST 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: Well can I just say a few words by way of introduction. Firstly, how<br />
delighted I am to see the President in Australia. I thank him, sincerely,<br />
for coming, for showing this interest in the bilateral relationship, for<br />
spending so much time in Australia and seeking to learn more about<br />
this country and define the relevance in the relationship between the<br />
two of us. We very greatly appreciate the visit and his conscientious<br />
effort in it. During the course of our discussions this morning, we have<br />
had a talk around the issues which are of interest to us and which we<br />
have in common. Of course, the, if you like, stewardship of the region<br />
in which we live. We are all bound by the Pacific Ocean, we're Pacific<br />
countries and we have that community of interest. Of course the<br />
President and I have been part of the founding group of APEC and we<br />
both were at the Bogor summit meeting in Indonesia last year. We will<br />
be attending the Osaka meeting of APEC this year where the action<br />
plan we hope will be advanced coming from the Bogor Declaration<br />
and, of course, many of you will know that the meeting the following<br />
year will be in the Philippines, under the stewardship of the President.<br />
So we have both a direct and active interest in this issue and I think we<br />
are, let's say, quietly excited about the prospect of putting a Pacific<br />
Rim organisation together with free trade objectives that advance<br />
intercommunal trade and the movement of people that will go with it.<br />
In other words, building a comprehensive and effective regional<br />
economy which also has its own natural strategic value and<br />
people-to-people values as well. So we have that between us. On the<br />
bilateral relationship, I think we see us having a growing bilateral<br />
relationship. The Philippines is a country of just on 70 million people,<br />
it is a member of ASEAN, it provides a lot of the weight in ASEAN, and<br />
I think it is true to say Australia has not done enough with the<br />
Philippines. We are finding together that we have things in common<br />
and the President and I, 1 think, are committed to advancing those<br />
things both by way of investment, by trade, tourism, etc. We are, of<br />
course, democracies. We have very similar cultural and democratic </p>
<p>values and the President and I think that this is something we bring to<br />
the Asia Pacific area and something we can be proud to proselytise<br />
about. So we have had. I will round up my remarks on this, a<br />
discussion about the bilateral relationship, about the multilateral<br />
relationship in the region. our relations with other countries in the<br />
region and a commitment by both of us to see us do more together,<br />
country to country. Could I conclude, again, by saying how pleased I<br />
am to see the President in Australia on such an extended visit and<br />
invite him to make some remarks to you.<br />
FR: Thank you, Mr Prime Minister. Ladies and gentlemen, firstly let me<br />
express the deep appreciation of the Philippines Government and our<br />
people for this opportunity to visit Australia on the invitation of<br />
His Excellency Governor General Bill Hayden and Prime Minister<br />
Paul Keating. The relationship between the Philippines and Australia<br />
goes a long, long way back, even before World War 11. But that<br />
relationship, of course, has been strengthened and reinforced by our<br />
common defence of freedom and democracy in our part of the world.<br />
Maybe not too many Australians now remember the very valuable<br />
contribution of Australia to the liberation of the Philippines under<br />
General Macarthur in late 1944 up to Victory in the Pacific in<br />
August 1945, but the record is there. And I am here to express the<br />
appreciation of our people for that very valuable contribution on the<br />
part of the Australian people. Of course our relationship is reinforced<br />
by our bilateral relations in this contemporary age, cooperation in trade<br />
investment, but beyond the economic and material aspects, we also<br />
have continuing and deep cooperation in education, in health, in<br />
environmental protection and in human resource development. All this<br />
within our bilateral framework as well as within the larger framework of<br />
APEC and between us and itself, which the Philippines is a founding<br />
member and Australia and New Zealand. We have discovered during<br />
this visit that aside from the longitudinal, or north-south, kind of flow<br />
that we can create an even more beneficial relationship between<br />
Australia, the Philippines and the rest of ASEAN through a lateral or a<br />
latitudinal flow which we hope to develop some more. For instance,<br />
the Philippines pioneered together with Brunei, Indonesia and<br />
Malaysia the establishment of the East ASEAN growth area and we<br />
see now that the Northern Territory of Australia has become a very<br />
active player in that almost borderless kind of an economy and this<br />
has to do not only with trade investment, environmental protection,<br />
forestry, but also tourism, education and sports. Mrs Ramos, in fact, is<br />
President of the Philippines Badminton Association and part of<br />
the Philippines Olympic Committee is now meeting with your sports<br />
leaders to create a new momentum between the Philippines and<br />
Australian sports. Australia being recognised as part of the world<br />
leaders in physical fitness and sports development. We are also<br />
looking at the APEC meetings together as neighbours. The one in<br />
Osaka in 1995 and, of course, the one that we will host in the<br />
Philippines some time in November or December 1996. And already<br />
there are projects and programs being put on the ground in the<br />
Philippines which are the result of Phi lippine/ Australian initiatives<br />
during our first leaders summit at Blake Island in Seattle in November </p>
<p>1993. Australia supported the proposal of the Philippines for<br />
something tangible on the ground to be put in by APEC and this will be<br />
a Centre for the transfer of technology for small and medium<br />
enterprises. We have broken ground in the community of Los Banos,<br />
which is a college town in the Philippines south of Manila, for this<br />
Centre and by mid-1996 this should be an ongoing concern for the<br />
benefit of the 18 member economies of APEC with the more advanced<br />
countries like Australia contributing to the fund of knowledge for the<br />
developing countries like the Philippines in small and medium<br />
enterprises, upon which the economy of Australia has been founded<br />
from the very beginning. All in all I would like to assess that so far, up<br />
to this point, this visit has been most productive. We are just about<br />
two-thirds finished with it, but we are seeing even more opportunities<br />
as we move on to Brisbane, Queensland, tomorrow and eventually to<br />
Darwin, which is so close to the Philippines that you might say Darwin<br />
is mid-way between Manila and Sydney and so we thank you<br />
Mr Prime Minister for all the hospitality, all the support, all the<br />
cooperation and I am sure that all of this will lead down to great mutual<br />
benefit between our two peoples.<br />
PM: Thank you, President. Thank you very much for those sentiments.<br />
I am happy to take questions.<br />
J: inaudible<br />
PM: Well the President and I had a quite extensive discussion on this topic<br />
this morning. I think that this is a theme we have been over at other<br />
times when we have met, perhaps not as well defined as the President<br />
has defined it in the last day or two. I think Australia sees itself having<br />
a strong partnership with the countries of ASEAN. Particularly the<br />
countries which like Australia are not a part of continental Asia<br />
Indonesia, the Philippines, etc and we think that there is some value<br />
in some more formal commercial links between Australia, and New<br />
Zealand can I say, and the ASEAN group of countries and this can<br />
perhaps most obviously come through AFTA, some linkage between<br />
Australia and New Zealand and AFTA, and I think if we get that<br />
commercial linkage going then the natural strategic linkages come, in<br />
a sense, with it. In North Asia though there are very big economies<br />
and societies Japan, the second largest economy in the world, China,<br />
the largest emerging economy, the largest nation in the world in a<br />
sense, they stand in their own right. The rest of us, being smaller, can<br />
have quite a large economy of influence by doing things together and I<br />
think these sentiments, which the President has expressed, fall on very<br />
fertile ground here in Australia. That is, there is, I think, the possibility<br />
of creating a South East Asian regional economy and group of<br />
countries and community with a very clear community of interest which<br />
is not part of the orbit of Japan, or China, or the United States, or any<br />
of the great powers. But a regional economy in which we all share and<br />
benefit.<br />
J: Mr President, you have spoken of Australia and the Philippines as both<br />
being democracies in Asia. Do you think [ inaudible]?<br />
I </p>
<p>FIR: I do not think it would be necessary for any nation to curtail its<br />
democracy or democratic system or culture in order to accommodate<br />
with the rest of the countries in the Asia Pacific. I think the trend now,<br />
under this freer world trading regime. is for countries to become more<br />
transparent, for the economic environment to be more level and fair<br />
and predictable, and this is where we are in the Philippines and.<br />
I would say, also Australia. I think that in the end, and we are seeing<br />
this already in Taiwan and also the Republic of Korea, that it will be<br />
the freer, the more transparent and the more predictable kind of<br />
regimes that will predominate. If I may amplify on my proposals about<br />
Australia, the Philippines, ASEAN itself, being effective,<br />
counter-veiling, or counter-balancing, forces in our part of the world.<br />
This is not to say that I favour a military or a defence alliance.<br />
No, there is no way that it could be that way. But the combined<br />
economic clout and influence of countries like Australia, New Zealand,<br />
all of ASEAN, must eventually C-10 as we call it in the Philippines<br />
and in the rest of Asia, meaning the ten countries of South East Asia,<br />
to include Cambodia, Laos and Myamar could exert great effective<br />
moral-suasion over the big powers in the Asia Pacific to the extent that<br />
there would be no unpredictable happenings, no sudden shocks, that<br />
would threaten the stability of the Asia Pacific. Afterall, it is the<br />
stability and the peace that continue to reign in this region that ensures<br />
our dynamic economic growth and our social cohesion. So this is the<br />
road that I see for countries like Australia and the Philippines and Asia<br />
being the middle forces the moderating forces in our part of the<br />
world.<br />
J: Mr President, you clearly see Australia as playing a role in the region.<br />
But other countries in Asia, most notably Malaysia, has some problem<br />
with Australia playing a greater role. Why do you think they have that<br />
problem with Australia and what is your view of Australia's overall<br />
position in Asia? Are we Asian, are we on the fringes, where do you<br />
see us?<br />
FIR: Well the Philippines itself has no problems with any of its neighbours<br />
in the Asia Pacific and around the world in fact. I do believe that in the<br />
end, really not too far from now in terms of years, that everyone will<br />
come around to seeing that the most important condition that we must<br />
all try to attain is inter-dependence, mutual support and<br />
accommodation. There is no question that our cultures, our histories,<br />
our societies are uniquely different from each other. But there is<br />
enough room, there is enough benefit in the world, for each one to<br />
enjoy. I have said it in the past, I have said it here in Australia, I said it<br />
over in New Zealand, that what is more important about becoming, or<br />
being a part of Asia, or Asia Pacific to be more specific about it, is just<br />
to be there, just to do what you have to do. And this must be a<br />
two-way kind of thing Australia to Asia-Pacific and the rest of us in<br />
Asia-Pacific to Australia. Let's just do it. Let's not be tied in with<br />
labels, intentions and proposals. Let's just be there, let's just do it. </p>
<p>J: Do you see that role being emphasised through APEC and, if that's so,<br />
how happy are you with the preparations for Osaka?<br />
FR: Yes, well, APEC is a very important forum and it has proven to be<br />
effective since it was organised on the proposal of Australia back in<br />
1989. The ASEAN regional forum is another important venue for really<br />
ensuring the stability of our region and the AFTA is another framework<br />
that provides beneficial opportunities for everyone. Certainly, if<br />
Australia and New Zealand. through the CER, come into that<br />
framework for freer trade, we, in the Philippines, would welcome that.<br />
PM: I think we might have one more question, because I know that the<br />
President will be addressing the Press Club, which will give you an<br />
opportunity to invite other questions, so perhaps one from the other<br />
Philippines side if there is one.<br />
J: Can you just summarise your points of discussion?<br />
FR: Yes, first we talked about our bilateral relations which have always<br />
been very good and new opportunities for reinforcing the bilateral<br />
relationship, especially in regard to the people-to-people kind of thing<br />
education, tourism, small and medium enterprises, social development<br />
and values, forms for personal interaction among ordinary people.<br />
We also, of course, reviewed our regional situation under the<br />
framework of APEC, the ASEAN regional forum, as well as new<br />
opportunities for increasing trade investment, tourism, other forms of<br />
economic and educational cooperation.<br />
J: Prime Minister, did you talk about nuclear testing by France and<br />
China?<br />
PM: We did. We discussed that and I think the President and I agreed on<br />
this point. That is, one, that the countries of the South Pacific should<br />
be respected, the small island states particularly and, secondly, runs<br />
counter to the non-proliferation objectives of the rest of the world for a<br />
major power and a major democracy to be, in a sense, flouting those<br />
objectives with a testing program and the same is true, of course, of<br />
China. I think we were, I can say, happily at one on this point.<br />
J: Prime Minister, on another matter closer to home if I may, [ inaudible]?<br />
PM: Well I think he is doing a press conference today and I think courtesy<br />
would demand that I let him speak for himself. Thank you very much<br />
indeed.<br />
FR: Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen. See you in the next one,<br />
at the Press Club.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
