<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1340</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO U.S AND U.K NATIONAL PRESS CLUB. ASHINGTON ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER MR HAROLD HOLT  30TH JUNE. 1966</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/06/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001340_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIEIE MINISTER'S VISIT TO U. S. AND U. K.<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB. *. ASHINGTON. June, 1966.<br />
Presideat ( Mr. Booth):<br />
Gentlemen, it may interest you to know that at this<br />
very hour in Canberra the Secretary of State, Mr. Dean Rusk,<br />
is addressing the Press Club of Canberra.<br />
I would like to introduce the distinguished guests at<br />
this table. On my left, His Excellency, iMr. John Keith iraller,<br />
the Australian Ambassador.<br />
On my right, our very own, the Honourable Edward Clark,<br />
United States Ambassador to Australia.<br />
On my left, Sir John Bunting, Permanent Head of the<br />
Prime Minister's Department.<br />
On my right, Sir Lawrence icIntyre, the Deputy Secretary<br />
of the Department of External Affairs of Australia.<br />
On my left, the Honourable Robert Furlonger, the Minister<br />
of Australia. On my'right, the Honourable John I. c Naughton, Assistant<br />
Secretary of Defence for International Security Affairs.<br />
On my left, a most iL: portant man, f. r. Tony Eggleton, the<br />
Prime Minister's Press Secretary.<br />
On my right, the Honourable Ray Farrell, Co; uIissioner of<br />
Immaigration and Naturalization.<br />
His job is the one that our distinguished guest used to<br />
hold in Australia. On my left, an old friend, the Honourable Claude Pepper<br />
of Florida. On my right, the Honourable William Battle, former<br />
American Ambassador to Australia now with the State Department.<br />
On my left, a distinguished member of this club, Press<br />
Attache to the Australian Embassy, Mr. John Malone.<br />
Gentlemen, the nation, the city, and especially the<br />
National Press Club we are proud to have as our guest of honour<br />
a distinguished statesman from down under. His country is a most<br />
remarkable one. It is almost the exact size as ours. It has<br />
everything going for it that ours has great cities, vast<br />
stretches of farm land, mountains, prairies, and it is all tended<br />
and brought to bloom and fruition by fewer than twenty million<br />
people. HOLT Twelve.<br />
Twelve, I'm told. I was giving them a few. ( laughter).<br />
Australia is a land where an A1. erican at least this one<br />
feels more at home than in any other country but his own. Our<br />
guest became Prime " inister of Australia last January. He<br />
succeeded a veritable legend, Sir Robert 1ienzies, who was Prime<br />
Minister for a generation. And, incidentally, who also spoke<br />
from this platform. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Our guest is the leader of the majority Liberal Party<br />
in Australia. That is the party to belong to just now. But<br />
he knows this country and city well, having participated in<br />
many , orld Bank and other financial meetings here.<br />
But he is not all business by any means. He is a<br />
skilful skinciver and spearfisherman, who enjoys water ski-ing<br />
and power boating. He is a familiar figure at the Melbourne<br />
race track and he goes the right way with top hat and tails.<br />
How good he is at picking the horses his biographers don't say.<br />
He is here today representing his coilntry, the faithful<br />
ally of the United States, through thick and thin, good times<br />
and bad. Gentlemen, the distinguished Prime Mlinister of Australia,<br />
the Right Honourable Harold Holt.<br />
MR. HOLT: ir. President Booth, Your Excellencies, Distinguished<br />
Guests, Gentlemen of the National Press Club, and other types<br />
not otherwise included;<br />
This all makes me feel very good. In the first place it<br />
is, as most of you have discovered, regarded by most of the<br />
politicians of the world as something of a status symbol to have<br />
the National Press Club. These things are taking a well defined<br />
pattern at these times. If you can get your photo in'Timd' or<br />
" Newsweek" or matters of that sort, well, you arc well on your<br />
way to recognition. I have only had my photo, I think, twice in<br />
" Time On one occasion I was sitting along side David<br />
Rockefeller, who is rather better knovm here than I am. And on<br />
the other occasion I appeared with three of ry delightful<br />
daughters-in-law in their bikinis. A nd I got more international<br />
recognition from that than in my thirty years in public life.<br />
( laughter). Indeed, as I came across the United States, I was a<br />
little chastened because, although I was shown every courtesy<br />
and attention at the splendid hotel in San<br />
Francisco, they kept addressing me as M1r. Ambassador. When I<br />
went up to my room some generous friend had sent along a couple<br />
of bottles of hooch but it was addressed correctly to me by<br />
name so there was no argument as to the possessor, but it<br />
described me as the Prime Miniister of Canada. ( laughter). Then<br />
we got on the aircraft to co! te across to w'ashington auiwe<br />
hadn't been off the ground very long when a somewhat worried<br />
looking captain of the aircraft came along and he saw me<br />
lounging in the front seat with a sweater on, by this stage, and<br />
my collar loosened and my tie a bit askew and he said, " I am<br />
looking for the Prime Minister of Australia. But unfortunately,"<br />
he said, " I don't know his name." ( laughter). So, gentlemen,<br />
my eg3 needed a bit of building by the time I got to ashington.<br />
And thank you very much for asking me here. I see around me a<br />
lot of friends. Some I have made at earlier times, some whc<br />
apparently have just come along for the very nice lunch. </p>
<p>On my right you will see a man who can usually be<br />
distinguished by the " Yellow Roses of Texas" in his buttonhole,<br />
your distinguished Amibassador to mW country, iir. Edward Clark.<br />
Now, I am not without hope that by the time he ends his term of<br />
duty with us we will have persuaded him to remain permanently.<br />
I think he finds rather larger areas of land to be cultivated<br />
there than in Texas. It's a little cheaper and the oil has yet<br />
to be found. And, of course, we have around the room others whose<br />
friendship I have valued over the years in which I was engaged<br />
in the rather esoteric mysteries of' the Secretaryship of Finance.<br />
But today I want to speak principally to you about the<br />
sort of view that we have developed from the part of the world<br />
in which I live about what has beco,.-e the major external issue<br />
in this country and indeed in other parts of the world the<br />
issue of Viet Nam. And I think it would assist a clearer<br />
understanding for us all if v could turn our eyes away for a<br />
week or two from, the daily episodic reportings to consider the<br />
environment, the general situation, the total picture which<br />
relates to Viet Nan and its place in Asia generally. Benause<br />
from much of the criticism that I have been reading, the woods<br />
seem to have been lost sight of as people inspect the trees. And<br />
if we want to assess the value of our participation in South<br />
Viet Nam, then I believe those who criticize must broaden their<br />
horizons and sue wvhat has been achieved by resistance to<br />
communism in South Last Asia and study in turn what this will mean<br />
to the Asia of tomorrow. The military operations would then<br />
fall into place as marking the continuing challenge of communisia<br />
in Asia. The stakes, gentlemen, are very large, and that is why<br />
three successive presidents of this great country, m-den who<br />
should have at their fingertips information, informed advice to<br />
an extent and of a , juality which very few other people could<br />
hope to match, even the best informed of us. And in the exercise<br />
of their country's heavy resoonsibility of free . orld leadership,<br />
they have firmly decided, one succeeding the other, that the<br />
i-ilitary po,. er and economic strength of the mightiest nation in<br />
human history must be brought into the scale to preserveafœ eedom<br />
and hope and progress in the countries of Asia. There/ a illion<br />
people a billion and half people, rather east of Suez, and<br />
their number grows appreciably each year. In India alone the<br />
population increases to an extent equivalent to the total<br />
population of my country -rhich, IVr. President, despite our best<br />
efforts and a very active Immigration programme, has only<br />
advanced to about eleven and a half million. 1, whleya rt lifted<br />
for a momcnt when you said twenty million. ( laughter). That is<br />
-where we hope to get. and get with other goals in sight.<br />
But, gentle-men, they are people of quality. Je are very proud<br />
of our Australian people.<br />
But the one and a half billion people east of Suez may<br />
have doubled their number by the end of this century. And Asia<br />
has become a dynamic theatre of social ferment and revolutionary<br />
economic change. In this region and I contrast it, as I say<br />
this, with the continent of Africa there are countries rich<br />
in resources with ancient civilizations, but some have been slow<br />
to adapt themselves to the possibilities of -doiern techniques. </p>
<p>Most of these countries are going through dramatic processes<br />
of change, varying greatly in kind. You get, for example, the<br />
modern industrialization which has occurred in Japan and, on<br />
the other hand, the regimentation of the coru,, unist administration<br />
in China of the 700 million people of that country. The only<br />
major military power on the mainland of Asia is communist China.<br />
No country Li Asia bould feel itself secure from the threat of<br />
communist aggression but for the power and resolution of the<br />
United States of America. And so we might fairly ask the critics<br />
who don't like what is going on in South Viet Nam, do they want<br />
a world in which a communist dominated Asia forms a major part?<br />
That is a fair question. They may feel that the issue can end<br />
in South Viet Nam. None of us who live in that area of the world,<br />
and I speak as one who has in the course of this year not only<br />
been to South Viet Nam but through several of the countries of<br />
Asia. I come to you as one who opened on 1Monday morning in<br />
Canberra the conference of SEATO powers. And on the preceding<br />
weekend I was able to have talks there with Michael Stewart, Dean<br />
Rusk, and the Foreign Mi: isters of all these SEATO countries<br />
attending that conference.<br />
And they are under no doubt as to the fact that a<br />
continuing threat exists. They welco e what have been quite<br />
favourable developments in the course of the past twelve years.<br />
And there are very hopeful developments em-erging in A'sia. But<br />
without American strength in ! sia then we might as well hand it<br />
over to cormmunism of the Chinese brand.<br />
ve in , ustralia share the views of your lead,. rs, and I<br />
would hope and believe of millions of your fellow Americans, that<br />
a critical battle is being fought in South Viet Nam for the<br />
future of mankind. This conflict symbolizes the challenge of<br />
communism in Asia and is the current , major expression of it. ,. e<br />
have tried to see alL this in the perspective of history. -7e are<br />
inclined in Australia to see things perhaps in direct simple<br />
terms. But you are not necessarily i-Aore likely to be wrong on<br />
that account. I think you can over-complicate the situation<br />
to a point where, as I say, you lose sight of the woods because<br />
your are concentrating too much on the detail. And there is<br />
plenty of detail, of course, to be seen in South Viet Nam, in<br />
the complex, dificult situation. And that is why the communists<br />
are there, because it is difficult, it is complex. It is not<br />
easy to produce national unity which would make the task of<br />
defending the country and building it up again so much easier.<br />
But we work with the conditions as we find them. And the issue<br />
is still clear enough in our eyes. In these simple direct terms<br />
we saw our role in world war I and world II. de were a cocintry<br />
of only seven million people in those times, and i'ustralia<br />
sustained nearly half a million casualties in those two world<br />
wars. I think I speak correctly when I say that in the first<br />
world war we lost more men killed than the United States itself.<br />
And tha is how we saw the communist challenge in Berlin and in<br />
Cuba. We fought it with you in Korea and we joiridwith British<br />
and other Corinonwealth forces in fighting it in Malaya. He see<br />
South Viet Nam in the same context, a crucial struggle for human<br />
liberty. </p>
<p>Never forget that the United States has not only put troops<br />
into Asia, it has also put heart. And I speak for one of the<br />
countries in the region which has felt heart, encouragement,<br />
and strength froin the knowledge that the resistance that could<br />
be made would oe backed in strength by the United States.<br />
Reienber, that as far back as 1954, President hisenhower<br />
decided to exteid both economic and military aid tc South Viet<br />
Nam, to enable the development of a strong, viable state. And<br />
during the next five years So-th Viet Nam made economic and<br />
social progress which some observers described as miraculous.<br />
And that progress was not halted by the South Vietnamese themselves.<br />
It was halted by a campaign of subversion, of terror,<br />
of infiltration, and finally of organized military aggression.<br />
Remeiiber also what your country has done to help the<br />
economic and social growth of countries such as Korea, Taiwan,<br />
and Thail* nd. It stands ready to assist and suppo't co-operative<br />
programxes for economic development in Asia. Your goal and ours<br />
is for peace and a better life for all who are willing to live<br />
at peace with th-ir neighbours.<br />
The United States is working and building for these<br />
objectives. ' e have heard a lot of discussion and debate about<br />
the so-called Domino Theory. ; ell, those of us who take the<br />
view from down under believe that, thanks to the assistance of<br />
this country, the Domino Theory is working in reverse.<br />
' ve believe that because the United States is in Asia,<br />
other people arc encouraged to stay there and help the emerging<br />
young Asian countries to work out their own future without fear<br />
and without the persisting monaoe of a philosophy which Mlao<br />
Tse-Tung says grows out of the barrel of a gun.<br />
It is in our judgment shortsighted for' the industrialized<br />
nations of the Lest to believe that they can contract out of the<br />
problems, the troubles and agonies of Asia. The challenge thrown<br />
down by communism in Viet Nam is a challenge not only to So. tth<br />
Viet Nan, it is a challenge to the whole free world.<br />
Lcl-t me say something about peace in Viet Nam. Peace in<br />
A sia. Peace 11 ove the world. I'e have been nauseated by the<br />
propaganda which describes the free world as imperialistic and<br />
the coimunist world is benevolent and humanitarian. The converse<br />
is demonstrably true. No man has worked harder for peace in<br />
Viet Nam than your President, and he is not alone in this. Most<br />
of the world supports him. Only Hanoi and Peking will not have<br />
peace. , Jhat they want is surrender and a victory far<br />
totalitarian communism.<br />
, e believe in the kind of peace that carries with it<br />
the right of small nations to grow and develop in their owm way.<br />
ie believe in a living kind of peace. The comunists offer the<br />
peace of the grave.<br />
The Aerican decisions I see as turning points in history<br />
were the Marshall Aid Programme, which opened a new vista for<br />
human welfare, and the other was the decision to give military<br />
support and aid to South Korea. iIhere would we have been had<br />
America turned its back at that critical time upon support far<br />
South Korea? </p>
<p>There would have been undoubtedly today a Korea entirely<br />
dominated by the comm-unists. And forces would have been<br />
released at that early stage which would have pressed on the<br />
other weak countries south of China itself.<br />
But thanks to the United States' strength, Asia is<br />
stirring. , e are at the dawning, I believe, of an exciting new<br />
phase in human affairs. And I speak as one who has talked in<br />
these recent years, and more particularly in recent months, with<br />
leaders of countries such as those to be found in Malaysia, in<br />
Thailand, in Taiwan, in Korea, in other parts of South East Asia.<br />
There is a mood for co-operation. With Japan, for example, a<br />
country which has produced the most remarkable industrial<br />
expansion of iroiern times.<br />
Our own trade with Japan today is running at about four<br />
and a half times the dimension of the early 1950' s. And Australia<br />
and Japan are both withholding from consumption more of their<br />
gross national product than any other countries to be found in the<br />
world about 28 per cent in the case of Australia, which compares<br />
with 17 or 18 per cent in this country and the United Kingdom.<br />
And so we are, we believe, at an exciting phase of<br />
development in human history. Here are countries which have never<br />
found either the i ill nor the means to co-operate, except under<br />
the force of oppression, down through the earlier centuries.<br />
India, another country which has gone through a<br />
signifioant re-orientatior.. of thinking and movement. In<br />
Indonesia, one of the richest countries of the world potentially,<br />
a hundred million people which today find themselves in<br />
administrative and economic chaos, but with resources so<br />
potentially strong that a decade of capable administration and<br />
management could make them one of the strong economic powers in<br />
Asia of the future. And here is how this great country, and we<br />
say it with gratitude and appreciation, because where else do<br />
the countries of South East Asia and ultimately of Asia turn,<br />
except to the strength and generosity of this country,<br />
until enlightenment, perhaps, brings greater support from other<br />
countries who would, one would have thought, from the generosity<br />
extended to them, when their reconstruction was a matter of<br />
necessity in the post-war years, one would have thought that they<br />
would have joined gladly in this task of defending liberty and<br />
progress in this troubled area of the world.<br />
Jell, thanks, I repeat, to the United States, Asia is<br />
stirring. And we are ourselves with optimism facing the future<br />
ahead of us. ;, hat the United States has done is, we believe, of<br />
epochal significance. It represents the engagement of the<br />
riches and opportunities of the world with the revolution and<br />
potential of Asia. It is quite impossible, of course, to assess<br />
let alone overestimate the value and the sheer magnitude<br />
that the service rendered by the American Government and people<br />
on behalf of individual liberty, human dignity, and national<br />
self-respect throughout the world since the second world war.<br />
There has been nothing in history to approach the totality of<br />
American generosity and enlightenment as expressed in a unique<br />
combination of economic and financial assistance to the needy,<br />
military protection to the weak, and dedication to the cause<br />
of freedom everywhere. </p>
<p>oe need to remind ourselves of all this from time to<br />
time. It is all too often forgotten by individuals and<br />
beneficiary nations under the passing stresses and irritations<br />
of international life. I wonder where estern Europe would<br />
stand today had it not been for the Marshall Plan and the American<br />
contribution to NATO. And nowhere, perhaps, has there been a<br />
better example of Aerican reso-lution and patience than in Viet<br />
Nam. We are convinced that it has put fresh hope into those<br />
Asian countries that are at the same time jealous of their<br />
independence and depressed by the harsh realities of living<br />
close to communist China.<br />
So far from inviting a mounting chorus of protest, the<br />
American 6xample has encouraged some of these countries to come<br />
in with military help for the people of South Viet Nam. First<br />
the Republic of Korea and now Thailand and the Philippines. I<br />
am convinced that others of them, while constrained to preserve<br />
a posture of aloofness and even disapproval for public purposes,<br />
are privately thankful for what the United States is doing<br />
The results of all this are to be seen everywhere. The<br />
successful holding operation in Viet Nam has brought time for<br />
a re-appraisal in Indonesia, as I have mentioned, of the prospeet<br />
of the harsh and sterile realities of comnunism, and with it the<br />
promise of an end to Indonesia's confrontation of Malaysia.<br />
There has been the recent meeting of free nations in<br />
Seoul, the first such meeting held by them, out of which has<br />
come a new regional grouping to be knovm as ASPAC. The Foreign<br />
Mfinister of South Viet Nan was present at our SEATO ieeting in<br />
Canberra and this meeting was concerned not primarily with<br />
matters of defence and security, but with opportunities for<br />
political, economic, social, and cultural co-operation, looking<br />
towards the future, free from the shadow of aggression and war.<br />
The military forces of all the countries engaged hpve as<br />
a major part of their task the Civic Action and Rural<br />
Development Prvgrammes, a totally new concept that military<br />
forces have brought to their responsibility in military<br />
operations. !., hat better testimony could there be to the<br />
fruitfulness of American aid and allied policies and actions<br />
in South Viet Nam.<br />
Let me end with a tribute to the steadfastness of the<br />
United States' aims and objectives in that country, and to the<br />
courage and fortitude of all of those military and civilian<br />
alike, who are carrying them through difficult and frustrating<br />
conditions. V'qe are grateful for the resolution, clarity cf<br />
purpose of your President and his Administration.<br />
As I said last night, it is a ggod thing that this<br />
administration has the defence in depth from so many ablenmn,<br />
all firmly and resolutely determined to see this thing through.<br />
Their efforts have the full support of the Australian Government,<br />
of the substantial majority of our people. And I express our<br />
appreciation and our gratitude for them. </p>
<p>NR. BOOTIH: Mvr. Prime Mi_, ister, you have several hundred sharp<br />
newsmnen here. They have asked some hard questions arnd some<br />
easy ones. Let me say again that I do not write the questions<br />
sir. I merely ask them. And the first question. Sir, we are<br />
not used to having our policies so enthusiastically supported.<br />
( laughter). ( applause).<br />
12ll. HOLT: a7ell, frankly, currently, not is our eyes. And that is<br />
rnot simply a blind acceptance of everything that the United<br />
States cares to produce. It is because the Australian people<br />
and the American people are inheritors together of~ a great<br />
democratic tradition. We think very much alike on the problems<br />
which affect the world. I'We have great principles held in coiaion.<br />
And I believe that we can be appreciative that there is a champion<br />
to defend those principles of the strength which you hold.<br />
As we grow in our own strength and determined we are<br />
to go on with our growth then I hope we shall be making an<br />
increatingly strong contribution to our common causes, whether<br />
it be in the field of military effort, of international aid, or<br />
of co-operation for other useful international purposes. But<br />
currently the only problehis between us are SOI:!-e rather some<br />
trade problems the 25 cents a pound. on -wool and a few other<br />
odds and ends like that. ( laughter). In the international<br />
foreign affairs field we see the situation very closely with<br />
your ox'in outlook. ( applause).<br />
! IR. B'O'OTIH: Sir, what is the nature of the problems iiwhich devolve<br />
upon Australia because of the changing British stance East of<br />
Suez?<br />
11R. HOLT: Well, 11. r. Chairman, as explained to me by the Primie<br />
Minister of the United Kingdom, the situation remains unchanged<br />
froin the understanding ,-; hich was discussed with us by the Min,-ister<br />
for . efence, Mr. Healy, earlier this year in Canberra, and then<br />
subsequently foniiing part of the defence review which he made to<br />
the House of Com-,.. ons.<br />
Mr. Harold " l-ilson has reaffirmed that position quite<br />
recently in public statement and in the text of the speech which<br />
he made to his own party m-, em-bers.<br />
Now. wie are currently concerned, of course, with the end<br />
of confrontation situation. But confrontation has not yet ended<br />
formally. We hope things will work out satisfactorily. But, of<br />
course, there have been in the past times when all that looked<br />
promising in Indonesia didn't work out quite the way that we had<br />
hoped. We are m,, ore optimistic at this time. But we have ahead<br />
of us a consideration of where we all stand once that situation<br />
has satisfactorily ended.<br />
Now the United Kingdom has made it clear that it will<br />
stay on in the military force and presence in Singapore and I<br />
would think with other Commi~ onwealth forces in Malaysia for an<br />
indefinite time ahead. In what strength remains to be made hown,<br />
but we are more concerned to have the British presence there as<br />
a moderating and stabilizing influence than with the question of<br />
just how -, anv people there are. </p>
<p>W1e pursued, in Australia,. in company with the British,<br />
both in Australia and the United Kingdomn, a study of possible<br />
alternative base situations in-Australia if a situation<br />
developed in which the United Kingdom could not effectively<br />
maintain its force. in the bases where they at present are<br />
stationed. But we would hope and we would believe that this decision<br />
having been made is welcaned by the countries of the area<br />
conc~ erned, that Great Britain will, as far ahead as we can see,<br />
maintain a presence East of Suez in almost certainly the same<br />
areas where they are at present held.<br />
MR. BOOTH: Thank you, sir. In the light of Australia's maembership<br />
of the recently created ASPAC, w., ould you say that Australia is<br />
now going to get closer and more co-operation with its Asian<br />
neighbours than was the case in the past?<br />
vM. HOLT: Mr. President, that I believe is undoubtedly so. This<br />
was a welcome development for as and no less welcome was the<br />
warmth with which Australia Luid New Zealand were accepted into<br />
the cor-pany of A sian countries. have cone to know sevexral<br />
of them of course, closely, either through our SEATO cooperation<br />
or in the case of those outside SEATO, in trade<br />
developments of recent time.<br />
And this is a symptomr, I believe, of the emerging<br />
spirit of co-operation, of hope in Asia. There are potentialities<br />
for trade which become quite exciting as new resources are<br />
opened up and as better technical trade co-operation, machinery<br />
is developed between us. This aspect, emergence, and the earlier<br />
meeting of the Education Ministers at Bankok, the useful meeting<br />
of SEATO which has just been held, the As ian Development Bank as<br />
a new institution servicing the area, the undertaking which<br />
President Johnson has given that there will be a billion-dollar<br />
programme of development in the area if co-operation can be<br />
successfully developed all these things are hopeful symptoms.<br />
Hanging over all is the menacing cloud of colm-unism<br />
which we must dispel. But subject to that I believe that, the<br />
Asia of the next fifty years cannot only make great forward<br />
strides, contributing notably to human welfare and progress, but<br />
that it can appreciably improve the standards of the people of<br />
the world as a consequence of this economic growth.<br />
MKR. BOOITH: Thank you. 11r. Prime Minister,/ 0? e our colleagues asked<br />
for your comment on the prospects for increased Australian<br />
economic co-operation with Japan in, first, the development of<br />
Australian mineral resources and, secondly, the general<br />
development of South East Asia.<br />
KR. HOLT: M1r. President, you are being very kind. There must be<br />
a tough one or two stuck in that pack that you have there.<br />
( laughter). . fof course, as I indicated earlier, have had a<br />
remarkable growth of trade with Japan. It has multiplied by<br />
four and a half timies, as I have said, since the early fifties.<br />
But, even at that, wie believe wie are really just at the early<br />
launching point of the trade between the two countries. </p>
<p>Let me illustrate this for you b. .': hat is hap. ening with<br />
respect to iron ore. are at the present time developing<br />
great deposits in one part of .: estern Australia. It has been<br />
estimated that there are 15,000 million to 18,000 million or<br />
should I say billion, to make the figures miore intelligible<br />
or 18 billion tons of good quality iron ore. And contracts<br />
are currently held for somewhere in the neighbourhood of dollars<br />
billion for the supply of this ore to Japan. That is just<br />
one item which is only in the early stages. These are the initial<br />
contracts which have been secured.<br />
In some instances we shall require Japanese in association<br />
with our ov. n and of that of other investing countries, most<br />
notably the United States itself, particularly since soime strength<br />
has been ijposed in the United Kingdon on further investment from<br />
there. But we see, as I described it the other day, Mr. President,<br />
the Australia of today is the sort of Pandora's box of mineral<br />
wealth. There is hardly a week or a month which passes without<br />
so,. e new mineral discovery of consequence coming to our notice.<br />
And there are quite responsible people who predict that within a<br />
measurable period of years our export inco... e from minerals will<br />
exceed our export income from our traditional staple export, wool.<br />
Now this should be not only a source of tremendous strength to us<br />
but would assist in avoiding the sort of fluctuations in the<br />
Australian economy which conditions of drought or lower world<br />
prices for our primary product have brought to us.<br />
We face a future in which Japan will figure prominently<br />
and there is a very good basis for co-operation developing in the<br />
trade field between the two countries.<br />
KR. BOOTH: Kr. Prime Miinister, in my introductory remarks I am<br />
afraid I gave my American colleagues more credit than they<br />
deserved for the increase in population in your country. But<br />
there are two questions in that area. To what extent did American<br />
servicemen contribute to your population increase? ( laughter).<br />
And do you favor any changes in your Immigration policy so as to<br />
attract additional population from neighbouring Asian countries?<br />
MR. HOLT: Mr. President, so far as I can gather, the American<br />
forces were notably active but not notably productive. ( laughter).<br />
( applause).<br />
MR. BOOTH: The second, I am not sure you need to answer it after that<br />
answer, sir. ( laughter. But do you favour any changes in your<br />
Immigration policies/ s to attract additional population from<br />
neighbouri . g Asian countries?<br />
MR. HOLT: . iell, . uhrr esident, the sting was in the tail, of<br />
course. have/ stablished Immigration policy but it has been<br />
reviewed frcm time to time. And it is operating, I think, not<br />
unsatisfactorily at the present time. I made a few liberalizations<br />
myself, of not very extensive kinds, but at least they<br />
were :. oves which I ino; gave considrable pleasure in the<br />
countries of Asia. One -was to establish the same period of<br />
naturalization for non-Europeans as well as for buropeans. -, e<br />
do admit for a number of purposes people fro::, Asia and those who<br />
have had a period of residence of five years or more can aply<br />
for naturalization. </p>
<p>11.<br />
Any non--European who iarries an Australian spouse, a male or a<br />
f~ male, as the case may be, beco;-mes eligible for citiz3nship<br />
of the country and the children of that mArriage, of course,<br />
enjoy full Australian citizenship.<br />
We have at the present time well over 11,000 Asian<br />
students in our vaLous schools and universities. And i know<br />
that the governments of the countries from which these students<br />
come do not favour any change in our iruaigration policy which<br />
would have the effect of enabling a considerable proportion of<br />
these or sone significant number of these to remain in Australia<br />
rather than to go back to the country which needs their skilled<br />
servizes so very much.<br />
But these are matters which can be talked over quite<br />
calmly and sensibly between us. It is well recognized that the<br />
Australian policy is based on the desirability of maintaining<br />
a homogeneu population that can integrate one element with<br />
another. are currently, of course, attracting migrants from<br />
many countries of Europe and we have quite a task at this period<br />
of our history in successfully integrating. And I think we have<br />
been doing it successfully and the people from so many other<br />
countries who have to develop familiarity with the Australian<br />
scene. But as our position in Asia increases from time to timae,<br />
no doubt, there will be a desirability to have skilled people.<br />
Special projects will call for soze presence of executives or<br />
even a labour shortage could produce some need for a modifieation,<br />
temporary or otherwise.<br />
These things, I repeat, are all capable of being<br />
handled within the ambit of the programme. There is some<br />
flexibility given to the department for the permanent admission<br />
of people who have special distinctions and skills. And it may<br />
interest you to know that the permanent condactor of the Sydney<br />
Symphony Orchestra is a very delightful person who an<br />
American negro. And so there it in. ic are able/ t ese ways,<br />
I think, to administer our programiae with humanity and with<br />
good serse.<br />
1R. BOCCM. Pr. Prime Ei ister, there is as much interest in<br />
Indonesia a number of questions. I think I shall ask them all<br />
at once so that you can expostulate generally on your feeling<br />
about Indonesia because tine presses us.<br />
Q. The first is. Please, a word about Indonesian<br />
development from the Prime liinister, of a country once fearful<br />
of Sukarno's expansionism. And the next one. hat is your<br />
view of Indonesia's greatest present need? And third. In what<br />
way can or sho. d oestern countries assist economic rehabilitation<br />
in Indonesia, especially how should Australia? And<br />
fourth, Considering the recent changes in the<br />
Indonesian GovernLat, how would you characterize present<br />
Indonesian-Australian relations? </p>
<p>-v<br />
12.<br />
MR. HOLT: izj. President, if I tried to answer in general terms<br />
I think it will cover the questions which are raised.<br />
14e in Australia have always attached great importance<br />
to friendly relations, co-operative relations with our<br />
nearest neighbour, Indonesia, which is literally only a matter<br />
of minutes flying time, at least, these days from the<br />
No: othern mainland of our country. And even througi the period<br />
in which Australian troops have been engaging Indonesian troops<br />
on the border of Borneo, we have kept a line of friendly contact<br />
going with them. Now the extent of the communist purge which<br />
has occurred in Indonesia has yet to be either evaluated in<br />
numbers or in consequence. I have here estimates which have<br />
ranged from low field, 300,000, to high field, about a million,<br />
of the figures of those who were liquidated in the communist<br />
purge. And I think one can reasonably assume from that there<br />
has been a re-orientation of policy in Indonesia.<br />
Now while we may not ourselves approve of the methods,<br />
at least if Indonesia is turning towards more co-operative<br />
relationships with those of us who are in the free world camp,<br />
then I think that can greatly improve the general prospect of<br />
stability and progress in South East Asia generally. And the<br />
country, as I said earlier, is tremendously rich in resources.<br />
T know from discussions I have had with some of the entrepreneurs<br />
from your country that provided they could see a period of<br />
stability ahead and faithful dealing froma the government, then<br />
they would be encouraged to make substantial investment of the<br />
developmental kind in that country.<br />
The future of Indonesian international policy is not<br />
so clearly to be seen. Quite certainly, it wouldn't be linking<br />
up with that of cori. unist China. I should think it would<br />
probably seek or pursue a nonaligned role. But there has oeen<br />
over recent times such a display of friendship from Indonesia to<br />
Thailand, for example, and the talks regarding the ending of<br />
confrontation with Malaysia were conducted in such a friendly<br />
atmosphere that ' ie are hopeful that at no distant point of time,<br />
providing we go ahead with developments like ASPAC for cooperative<br />
economiic purposes in the region, that Indonesia would<br />
find itself attracted to membership of such company.<br />
But it is a hopeful sign and I should have put it on the<br />
score earlier of the things which the United States is playing,<br />
that its policy in South East Asia has secured. If there had not<br />
been a resolute, continuing presence of United States strength<br />
in South Viet Nan, we would never, in my judgment, have secured<br />
the outcome which has occurred in recent time in Indonesia.<br />
MR. BOO Mr. Prime Minister, we have had these wide-ranging<br />
questions of viorld import. But there are plenty of us in this<br />
audience who write for newspapers in tovns such as Fargo, North<br />
Dakota, in the great plains of Canada, Topeka, Kansas, . here<br />
wheat is big, sir do you feel that the world price of wheat is<br />
being held down by the operation of the United States export<br />
subsidy?<br />
MI. HOLT: vell, I would like to turn that one over to my<br />
colleague, Deputy Prime 1, lLister John chwen, the Leader of the<br />
Country P; arty in the coalition government which I have the<br />
honour to lead. </p>
<p>13.<br />
I an sure that John ;. ould say that the price of wheat<br />
is too low. I don't know how many causes he would ascribe to<br />
this, but anything any of you gentlemen can do to assure not<br />
only a better price for wheat but for sugar and a few other of<br />
these basic primary commodities, will be greatly welcomed by<br />
the Holt Government in Australia. ( laughter). ( applause).<br />
MR. BOOTH: There are many other great questions that I wish we<br />
could ask, but we can't because, as you see, time presses us,<br />
Ihen I introduced this table I purposely failed to introduce a<br />
distinguished member of this club : who sits here. , ie have a<br />
little ceremony coming up. Roy Macartney, who is a member of<br />
this club, known to most of you out there, greatly admired and<br />
loved, is the correspondent of the Melbourne Age of Melbourne,<br />
Australia. Not only is he a great reporter, he is a great tennis<br />
player, And he has just won the National Press Club tennis<br />
championship. And I shall ask Mr. Macartney to come to this<br />
place and the Prime Minister of Australia . ill award him the<br />
trophy. Mr. Macartney.<br />
MvR. HOLT: Mr. Roy Macartney, I offer congratulations not only from<br />
myself, which is purely a personal matter, but froim the rmembers<br />
of this club for this notable achievement marking yet another<br />
Australian triumph in the field of tennis. It couldn't have been<br />
more timely, gentlemen, because for the first time in living<br />
memory there is no Australian in the quarter finals at . iimbledon.<br />
And so Roy, you have kept the tennis reputation of Australia<br />
high. I don't know how you've managed it with all these<br />
penetrating dispatches that I have been reading back home from<br />
your pen. But it just shows that the versatility of the<br />
Australian abroadis something which has to be seen to be believed.<br />
I now present to you this trophy. I don't know whether it is<br />
do you have to win it three years too?-<br />
iMR. BOOTH: No, it is his.<br />
HOLT: ® Ie. l l, here you are. And unless he finds out by some<br />
other process the editor of your paper will not discover this<br />
rather this rather uncomfortable secret, as I imagine it to be.<br />
Gentlemen, I am sure we all join . n applauding a great Australian<br />
athlete, I give you Mr. Roy Macartney.<br />
MR. MACARTUEY: Thank you very much, Mr. Prime Minister. It is quite<br />
a handsome trophy. It would have been more decorative, perhaps,<br />
if it was one of your swimming companions. Thank you very much.<br />
R. BOOTH: It just shows how snart these Australians are. The<br />
Prime Minister anticipated my last question but he may have some<br />
notion after having just presented this trophy. Mr. Prime<br />
Minister, what is your government doing about getting one of<br />
your players into the finals at iiibledon?<br />
KR. HOLT: dell, I think . e will demand a replay or else submit it<br />
to the United Nations, something of that sort, vr. President.<br />
MR. BOOTH: Thank you, sir.<br />
MR. HOLT: Thank you very much. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
