<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5462</transcript-id>
    <title>&#039;UNIONS AND WAGES&#039; EXTRACT FROM ADDRESS AT ROCKDALE TOWN HALL</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/10/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005462.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Jjj~. USt At I A
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR ME~ DIA WEDbNESDAY, I. OCTOBER, 1980<br />
" UNIONS AND WAGES-I"<br />
Ek'rZACT. FROMMDURSS AT~ ROCKDALE TOPTN HALL<br />
The Labor Party's " hands-off" policy towards unionls would be<br />
the recipe for economic disaster in Australia.<br />
Unions would be allowed to run riot; to do what they wanted<br />
and get what they wanted.<br />
16t6 w'ould be 1972-75 all over again.<br />
141. Hawke has made it quite plaITI that Labor's irresponsible<br />
approach to unions and wages has not changed one iotaL from the<br />
Whitlan years.<br />
If the Labor Party were in Covernment there would be no<br />
responsible argumient put by the Gov. ernment in the Arbitcatio<br />
Co-inission for the public interest against the unreasonable<br />
demands of extireme unions.<br />
We would have the same massi. ve escalation in wages that occurred<br />
in 1972-75, and with At the samae massive inflation push.<br />
That was et a time when Mr. Hawke as President of the AL. P and<br />
the ACTU was presumably a person of sotme intluence in the union<br />
movement and the Labor Party.<br />
That was at a time when time lost through industrial disputes<br />
rose! to 6 million mn days.<br />
That was at a time when award wagez rose 38 per cent in a sillgle<br />
year, That was. a time. of total irresponsibility by the trade union<br />
movement because they expected, and knew, that the Labor<br />
Government would acquiesce inj their demands.<br />
Labor in 1980 has the same scenario for its industrial reiatlon! s.<br />
Mr. Hawke wantts it al] l over again but from, a differenrt position.<br />
Coupled with Laborls plans for riassive increases in Government<br />
spending, we woulad again se,_ infl~ ation ruied towqavds<br />
per cent,<br />
it has happened before. It mzusL not happen again. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
