<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9368</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP ALP NATIONAL CONFERENCE, HOBART, TASMANIA 29 SEPTEMBER, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009368.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4 4.,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ALP NATIONAL CON FERENCE9 HOBART, TASMANIA<br />
29 SEPTEMBER, 1994<br />
PMV: Well, I thought I would give you some impressions of mine, of the<br />
conference and give you a chance to ask some questions, if you wish.<br />
We're getting towards the end of it and this wAil be probably the last<br />
opportunity to get something to air for news. The first thing I would say<br />
is I think the conference has reflected the general policy unity in the<br />
Labor Party and the general willingness to apply the task of getting<br />
things done to move the Party into the next three years. These<br />
conferences are on every three years and there is. I think, something<br />
which was commented on through the week, a generally business-like<br />
attitude by the Party to its work. Some have said it is too dull. Well,<br />
the fact is, it is aboLlt making the policies. A lot of these debates are<br />
had earlier, as you know, and you can say lots of things about the<br />
Labor Party, but never that it Is dull.<br />
There are a couple of what I call headline issues, which will come out<br />
of this conference. One, in particular, which I think will be around<br />
when all of us are gone and that was the decision, a very historic one,<br />
to increase the representation for women in the parliaments. That is<br />
the keynote change of this conference. That is the one that will<br />
change the character of Australian politics, it's the one which will lift<br />
the opportunities for women to participate in the parliaments of the<br />
country. So, this, I think and I will come back to it: in a moment<br />
was a very historic change, and one that I think we had to have a rule<br />
for. Not a principle, but a rule. And, as a consequence, we have a<br />
rule.<br />
The next major issue was the privatisations. This has always been<br />
somewhat of a difficult issue for the Labor Party. Of course, we've had<br />
a number of these debates, we had it with a competitive Telecom, we<br />
had it with the privatisation of QANTAS, we've had It now, again, with<br />
the privatisation of the major airport assets of the country. In agreeing<br />
to It, It will mean that we will be able to expand airport facilities to meet<br />
tourism in particular, which is growing rapidly. W. are in the fastest<br />
growing part of the tourism Industry world wide, in the Asia-Pacific. </p>
<p>The growth In tourist destinations to Australia is profound, and we<br />
really need the asset growth in these particular investments and they<br />
would not have come from the Commonwealth Budget. They need to<br />
come privately and they now will. But, as well as that there will be a<br />
yield to the Commonwealth Budget which is coming from the proceeds,<br />
which is important in the Government's medium term fiscal strategy.<br />
Now, this was a must issue for the government and one which I am<br />
pleased to say, the Party faced up to, and sensibly. But, I will come<br />
back to it if you like.<br />
Industri al Relations, again I think an acceptance of the directions the<br />
government has been taking. I was very pleased at the embrace of<br />
enterprise bargaining which was part and parcel of the amendments<br />
and the debate, which we haven't had in full measure until now. And,<br />
an understanding that the award system is there as an underpinning<br />
and, I think, a general, broad appreciation of that.<br />
Now, the other issue which, of course, you are getting yourselves<br />
worked up about today, uranium. Uranium is one of those issues<br />
which I think attitudes change in, over time. But, it is one which is<br />
deeply held in the Labor Party and one which I think, as a party, and<br />
for my part as the leader, one has got to make a decision about<br />
whether you really put a tear through the party in changing it at this<br />
point. And, even if one wanted to do it, taking a running jump at it.<br />
well, in this respect I have not taken a running jump at this issue<br />
because to have taken the running jump I would have had to have<br />
started running about four to six weeks ago. And, I would have been<br />
well and truly in the air before the conference stared. As it turned out,<br />
the thing I was running on was the vote for women, the vote in favor of<br />
the representation of women, and the thing that the Government just<br />
had to get through, the privatisations. So, what will happen is uranium<br />
will be referred off to the National Executive for a report to the next<br />
conference. By and large, beyond that Labor Party conferences can be a great<br />
strength for the Labor Party. They can be a problem for it, mostly in<br />
years gone by they have been a strength for it. I think this one has on<br />
this occasion. Now I think the Party does realise what a tremendous<br />
opportunity in government it has and I made these points, I hope<br />
clearly, in the industrial debate, at least as far as the industrial<br />
legislation was concerned today. So, it is a case then of the timing of<br />
these conferences fitting in contemporaneously with each parliament.<br />
It means that, In terms of policy, the board is set up to the next election<br />
and beyond. And, we get a chance then to review where we go from<br />
there. So, I'd be glad to take questions from you.<br />
J: ( inaudible question about PM's role in uranium policy discussions) </p>
<p>PM: No, I had a few discussions with people but again people have had<br />
some discussions with me as well I didn't, before I came I basically<br />
decided not to touch uranium because I wanted to be sure that the<br />
airport FAC package would get through and that the vote for<br />
representation for women would get through and I just might remind<br />
you that that was only a very close thing. The Left Caucus only<br />
decided to agree to it about 20 minutes before the vote.<br />
J: The FAC?<br />
PM: No, the vote for women. And, basically to try and run the uranium<br />
discussion as well, in that environment, wasn't really worth doing. And<br />
when I was here a few people were saying, " Look there is still a<br />
chance to change this", and I had, then, a couple of discussions with<br />
people but, you've really got to have your heart and your back in one<br />
of these changes to get them through.<br />
J: But, Prime Minister, you say that the present policy on uranium is<br />
outdated. I mean, you would like a change, wouldn't you and you did<br />
have discussions with people. Brian Ede said you were quite helpful...<br />
PM: Yes, Brian Ede approached me, I didn't approach him, saying he<br />
wanted my support for it. And, I said, " Look, I don't think there is a<br />
majority here for it, I don't think people are prepared to make the<br />
change yet. u But, I said we'll see as the week goes on wthat people<br />
have got to say. Now, you know the AWU's position in Queensland,<br />
they were flatly opposed to it and by the time that they could see that<br />
their tactic with CRA was not going to change CRA's industrial<br />
position, then they yeilded their position. But, to get a change like this<br />
up you've really got to go full bore at it.<br />
J: But regardless of that dispute within CRA and the AWUI what does the<br />
fact that there has been no change say to large companies like CRA,<br />
and foreign investors?<br />
PM: Very little, very little Indeed. Look, let me just give you some data here<br />
which Is worth recording. Ranger has got a capacity of 3,000 tonnes<br />
this year, it is producing 1,335. Olympic Dam has a capacity of 1 ,900<br />
tonnes and it is producting 1,325. If you had all the prospectives up,<br />
the lot of them, they come to about 7,300 tonnes in a year, if you add<br />
the lot together. That's everything, Kintyre, CRA, Koongarra, Veelirie,<br />
North Ranger, Ben Lomond, Beverley, all these together. Wherein, at<br />
the moment we are producing 5,000 tonnes the truth is, we can't meet<br />
the capacity of our mines to produce now. Now, were this to have<br />
changed, the mine that people would have had the greatest<br />
expectation for was Pan Continental. The old Pan Continental mine, it<br />
has got tremendous environmental problems. And, there would be no<br />
guarantee, far from a guarantee that that would ever begin in the East<br />
Alligator Rivers region. So, you're talking about really, Koongarra, </p>
<p>which has got 15,000 tonnes of reserves compared to Ranger and<br />
Olympic Dam which have got 427,000. So, in economic terms it<br />
doesn't matter very much at all. And, that's the point. Essentially, in<br />
economic terms, it Is not a pressing matter, it is not a pressing matter<br />
in political terms.<br />
J: Prime Minister, this motion didn't seem to be dead until some time this<br />
morning. Were you prepared for a motion to be put but, basically, it<br />
looked like a fairly transparent attempt to lock out a company like CRA<br />
because it didn't please the union movement?<br />
PM: Well, let me make my position clear about CRA I don't support their<br />
tactics of trying to squeeze unions out of their mines. But, be that as it<br />
may, these companies have done very well out of the Government and<br />
its industrial relations policy, in the profit share in the economy, in the<br />
competitiveness via the exchange rate, in everything that has come<br />
with it. And, part of it is, I think, not picking the eyes out of the policy<br />
mix, which, I think, Is their intention. But, no proposal was ever<br />
agreed. And, therefore, in general terms, the only place you can go<br />
with uranium after the current policy is to go to a policy where they just<br />
get up, individually, on their merits. Now, that basically means, maybe<br />
Koongarra, maybe this Kintyre thing in the future. But, the truth is that<br />
the existing operators can't sell their product.<br />
J: Isn't this a case of by pushing this off to the National Executive once<br />
again, which you 41d after the 1991 conference you face the<br />
prospect of simply having the same mess that you've had this lost<br />
week, revisited In three years time.<br />
PM: Yes, but there are always some issues that will drag along. This was<br />
not an issue two weeks ago, this was not an issue one week ago, it<br />
was not an issue last weekend. There were only two issues that were<br />
issues over those timeframes: that was the vote for female<br />
representation in the parliaments and the FAC and the assets. Now,<br />
each conference has its purpose, this issue has been hanging around<br />
since I'm not quite sure when we changed the policy to<br />
accommodate Olympic Dam I think, 1980. This is 13 years later yet<br />
we've had privatisation of QANTAS, telecommunications, each<br />
conference has served its purpose. This conferences purpose has<br />
been, in the broad, in the big issues, to be the representation issue<br />
and the privatisations.<br />
J: Would you like to see the policy opened up in the future?<br />
PM: Well, look, a policy which has no arbitrary quality to it is better than<br />
one without it. But, again, in economic terms, it matters very little.<br />
Certainly at this point The world market is over supplied and we've<br />
got more capacity than we can handle. </p>
<p>J: There was a late amendment carried which appeared to be related to<br />
the uranium debate, allowing exploration in National Parks, it was<br />
carried by 51 votes to 50, and during the debate the Environment<br />
Minister, Senator Faulkner, said that there was a direct nexus between<br />
exploration and future mining... ( inaudible) which would constitute<br />
an administrative, legal and political nightmare for the Labor Party.<br />
What do you say about that and the fact that the amendment was<br />
carried?<br />
PM: Well, I was told it was carried just as I was coming up here and I didn't<br />
hear all of the debate, obviously. Well, what is in the Party policy in<br />
respect of say. National Parks, without seeing the words of the<br />
amendment, the sense of it as I understand it, is that the Party may<br />
provide for exploration in National Parks. But, that doesn't mean to<br />
say that the Government would or should.<br />
J: What is your attitude?<br />
PM: Well, I'll have to have a look at it and see what it says and take some<br />
advice. My attitude, generally, has been that National Parks are<br />
declared to be National Parks for that very reason. That is, to<br />
preserve them.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)... a uranium policy that half the Cabinet has described as<br />
absurd. Is the the symbolism in that, is there not a problem in that..?<br />
PM: I don't think so. I don't think so. There are lots of if you want to<br />
track through the great document of the Labor Party's policies and the<br />
one the Coalition had and tick off the ones you think are absurd, there<br />
would be a lot df ticks on the pages, I can tell you.<br />
J: Do you think that basically the change in the platform to allow<br />
exploration in National Parks should be ignored?<br />
PM: I will have a look at the. change and I will make a judgement about it. I<br />
am not going to respond to it without knowing what was said and what<br />
was meant.<br />
J: Mr Keating what did you think of Bill Ludwig's attempts to link it with<br />
industrial relations?<br />
PM: Well, I think he worked out that that was not a goer. And, the reason it<br />
is not a goer is that you can basically fit this Kintyre reserve in your<br />
eye. It is basically a fleck of dust in the eye compared to a decent<br />
deposit and there was no way that CRA were going to change their<br />
Industrial relations policy to mine a thimble full of uranium. They were<br />
never going to do it and I am surprised that Bill ever thought that they<br />
would. </p>
<p>J: What sympathy do you have for local Aborigines in Kakadu who have<br />
been pushing for the opening up of Koongarra and ( inaudible) and<br />
how do you think it sits with the whole native title efforts of the last<br />
couple of years?<br />
PM: Well, native title never gave Aboriginal people the right to minerals.<br />
These are always issues of larger national moment and larger national<br />
moment they will always be. Including in that, of course, the rights of<br />
Aboriginal people and their views. But, I mean, that's about the only<br />
weight I would put on it.<br />
J: Mr Keating, given you said that if this was an issue to get through<br />
you'd have to approach it four or five weeks before the conference...<br />
PM: Well, not four or five, a couple of months at least.<br />
J: a couple of months, do you think it was handled badly by the people<br />
who were pushing for a change?<br />
PM: No, you mean the uranium issue here?<br />
J: Yes.<br />
PM: Well, look, the thing was, if you look back a month or three weeks ago,<br />
what were the issues? The major issue, I thought, two issues, the<br />
ones that I mentioned. I didn't believe we could go through this<br />
conference withoUt setting a rule rather than a principle for the<br />
representation of women. Now, I told my faction that at the National<br />
Executive meeting in Canberra. Some people were still hankering<br />
after a principle, I said, " Well, if you do, I will stand you up at the<br />
conference, as long as you understand that." And, I will say this, for<br />
people on the right of the Party, they came to the party with a rule.<br />
That rule was not accepted by the Left, in general. And, the Left<br />
Caucus, of course, were having, there was a lot of gnashing of teeth<br />
minutes or so before the decision. I think their concern is that seats<br />
which may go to the Left will go to women on the Right. And,<br />
therefore, there was not equanimity of view. There was, in the end, I<br />
am happy to say. So, the notion that you know, they were saying that<br />
this was a pro-cooked result, this was a foregone conclusion... It was<br />
not a foregone conclusion at all. And, they knew that unless it was<br />
going to be agreed there would be a very tough battle on the floor of<br />
the conference in which I would put my views, very firmly. Now, I am<br />
delighted with the fact that the whole party has agreed to this and It will<br />
change the face of Australian politics and the Labor Party. And this is<br />
a very great change and when, looking back over these conferences<br />
with some hindsight, this will stand out as a very large and significant<br />
change. </p>
<p>On the other issue, of course, the privatisation, it was imperitive for the<br />
government that we get this change through. That's in fiscal terms,<br />
imperitive that we get it through. And, we basically were making clear<br />
that just for efficiency reasons and servicing these airports as well as<br />
the fiscal reasons, we really needed this change.<br />
J: What is your reaction to the Current Account deficit announced today?<br />
PM: Well, it is one month's deficit. It is higher than we'd like it to be but it is<br />
crammed full of capital goods and probably at this phase of the<br />
recovery that is what one would expect to start to see. Certainly, we<br />
need a lot of capital equipment to try and keep the supply response in<br />
the economy cracking. What is one of the big issues in the<br />
sustuinability of this recovery and that is the supply capacity of the<br />
economy. The supply capacity of the economy will only be there with<br />
investment goods and particularly plant and equipment and there was<br />
a lot of that in these. There were a few lumpy things as well. Now,<br />
there is a bit of extra debt in there and there is a bit of lost earnings<br />
coming through from the drought but, by and large, you can't ever take<br />
a month's number as being indicative of the trend<br />
J: Does it put more pressure on the Budget policy?<br />
PM: No, no.<br />
J: Mr Keating, on what do you base your confidence that the affirmative<br />
action rule ( inaudible)?<br />
PM: Oh, because I think that by and large that the Party has decided that<br />
the time has come, that we will be a stronger and better party if more<br />
women are represented. And, it is going to take a lot of changes,<br />
particularly in states where you've still got rank and file preselection<br />
systems. People are going to have to, factions are going to have to<br />
decide who gets particular seats and how they get them, some time<br />
ahead of them getting them. So, it will take a bit of doing but I think<br />
there is a lot of goodwill towards the doing of it and nobody is going to<br />
leave themselves vulnerable to a National Executive decision.<br />
PM: Do you have any sympathy for men who might miss out on<br />
preselection because of this rule change?<br />
PM: Well, I think, by and large, the men, as you put it, have had more than<br />
their share of the market for most of the century so I don't think feeling<br />
sorry for them is quite the term.<br />
J: Mr Keating, would the symbolism of Carmen Lawrence as your deputy<br />
serve the Labor Party well? </p>
<p>PM: Well, what's the point of me debating the deputy leader of the Labor<br />
Party, here? None.<br />
J: Prime Minister, despite uranium, which You say was not really an<br />
issue, this was a really stage-managed conference, everything was<br />
sewn up. Do you think that sort of sterility of debate is a good thing for<br />
the Labor Party, why aren't things more vigorous now?<br />
PM: You mean you'd like more pictures for the television in the evenings?<br />
J: No, no, just more vigorous debate.<br />
PM: Well, what you have is not sterility, I don't think, at all. That Is, that<br />
was there a real debate at this conference about the representation of<br />
woman? Well, you're damn right there was. And, it was happening<br />
right under your nose, out there, but it was inside a locked room where<br />
people were debating their future and whether they could live with this<br />
rule change. I mean, that is a really live Issue and It was a really live<br />
debate. The same with, you know the to-ings and fro-ings over the last<br />
six weeks or so in respect of the FAC and privatisation. It has been on<br />
and off and on and off, people saying yes and another proposal being<br />
put; then the idea of leasing etcetera. And, finally, a resolution. It is<br />
the antitheses of sterility. Now, the fact that they are agreed by the<br />
time that they are here only means that the whole pressure cooker<br />
atmosphere of the conference coming produces the result. In other<br />
words, the vitality which should be there in policy determination, is, in<br />
fact, there. And, I think the notion that the conference is, I saw a bit of<br />
comment this morning that if there are not fights on the floor then we<br />
don't have a vigorous debate. Well, there is obviously a vigorous<br />
debate here and there has been.<br />
J: Where was passion on the floor, though?<br />
PM: Well, I thought there was a fair bit of passion when the representation<br />
for women went through and there was a passion not only from the<br />
women in the Labor Party but also female journalists as well. I thought<br />
even you were passionate about it. Maybe I was mistaken but I<br />
thought you were getting a bit teary eyed about<br />
J: No, no, no, you've got the wrong girl.<br />
PM: You don't get teary eyed?<br />
J: I wasn't teary eyed in this instance. Please.<br />
PM: Oh. Thank you.<br />
J: Is Bernie Fraser setting a move for you on fiscal policy. do you think? </p>
<p>PM: Well, I don't think so but central banks will always put as much weight<br />
on the government as possible. And this is central banks the world<br />
over. But, the government has a medium term fiscal strategy which we<br />
adopted when we expanded fiscal policy with One Nation in 1992. We<br />
want to be able to show that we had a ballooning of outlays for the<br />
purpos es of a fiscal stimulus, to lift the economy up, and we wanted to<br />
be able to show, demonstrably, graphically, that it would come down.<br />
So, you can't do that with just the forward estimate for just one year.<br />
Until 1992 we only had a forward estimate for one year. And, we went<br />
to the medium term projectory to show that what we Intended with One<br />
Nation was a stimulus and we would then withdraw it. Well, basically,<br />
that's what we've showed and that's what we've done and that strategy<br />
was based on solid economic growth and low inflation and that's<br />
exactly what we have. So, we don't have demand growing now like we<br />
had it growing In the eighties. That's just not the case. And, of course,<br />
we don't have inflation now, as in the eighties. So, the elements of<br />
that medium term strategy which we laid down are being met almost in<br />
a copy book way. So, the question is, why change it?<br />
J: Normally through a recovery governments will progressively tighten<br />
fiscal policy?<br />
PM: But, let me just say a couple of things to you. We've got<br />
unemployment at nine and a half per cent. We'll have the deficit back<br />
to two and a half percent of GDP in this financial year, in 1994-95.<br />
That's a very big juxtaposition of numbers. Nine and a half per cent<br />
unemployment and two and a half per cent on the deficit. The deficit<br />
peaked at over four per cent in the early eighties when unemployment<br />
reached ten per cent and it was almost five per cent in the mid..<br />
seventies when unemployment was under six per cent. Here we are<br />
with unemployment at nine and a halt per cent, that is arguing the case<br />
for a continuing stimulus and we've got the deficit already, this year, at<br />
two and a half per cent of GDP.<br />
J: Why then, does Bernie Fraser keep ( inaudible) to keep the pressure<br />
up?<br />
PM: I think that central bankers always want as much, if they can have<br />
more of a hand from fiscal policy, as they see it, the better. But, I just<br />
think that one has got to look back and that is why I think the OECD<br />
made it clear when it made those remarks a couple of weeks ago in its<br />
report, it said the Australian proposal to get back to one per cent of<br />
GDP as a deficit, by 1996-97, was realistic and better than most other<br />
OECD countries.<br />
J: So, Bernie Frasers wrong..? </p>
<p>PM; Well, if the notion is that we have to and he hasn't said this but if<br />
you're reading into it the notion being that no deficit Is too low and<br />
no surplus too great, yes that Is wrong.<br />
J: Prime Minister, do you think the next conference will be as easy to<br />
manage as this one, with twice as many delegates at Vt<br />
PM: Well, I don't know, the NSW conference has always had 1,000 and<br />
we've always managed that. Maybe the bigger they are the easier<br />
they are. I don't know.<br />
J: Prime Minister, on industrial relations you seem to be suggesting that<br />
some of the bigger unions were dragging the chain again.. ( inaudible)?<br />
PM: Oh look, I think the happy hunting ground of the central wage fixing<br />
system has been exactly just that, happy hunting grounds and people<br />
have wanted to keep it as long as they could. But, the better unions, I<br />
think, see the opportunity of enterprise bargaining to really be relevant<br />
to their members, to get themselves higher real incomes and also to<br />
make the companies more profitable. And, that is why this change<br />
they don't like the flexibility agreements because they are non union.<br />
In other words, let's take a business, maybe a cake shop with eight<br />
people, which is paying under a federal award but is not unionised.<br />
That proprietor and those employees can agree to vary the award.<br />
Now, the unions don't like that. This has induced them into a real love<br />
affair with enterprise bargaining. Well, I reckon that is just a terrific<br />
outcome if they push that harder, certified agreements as they're<br />
called. And, this will mean that unions will earn themselves and I<br />
say earn earn themselves an organic place in the labour market.<br />
So, instead of simply just rolling on to pick up subscriptions they* are<br />
actually helping people get wage increases, enterprise per enterprise.<br />
And, that is the kind of change that the labour movement has to<br />
embrace so that it is, in a sense, free of the industrial relations<br />
commission. Less vulnerable to a change in the IR Act.<br />
J: Mr Keating. .( inaudible) the Access Economics report/<br />
PM: I don't even know what they are, Michael, what are they?<br />
J: Well it suggested there was very substantial scope for expanding<br />
exports, or are you saying that can be done within the ? 7<br />
PM: Well, there is either a rebuke to be handed out to the sales people at<br />
Ranger and Olympic Dam because there is 600 tonnes spare<br />
capacity at Olympic Dam and there is 1,700 tonnes in Ranger.<br />
J: Just on that point, Mr. Keating, it will be another two years before it<br />
comes back from the. </p>
<p>PM: I don't think the uranium market is going to change iii two years, three<br />
years<br />
JX Add to that another six years of lead up time for starting the new mine<br />
and then you have eight or nine years, isn't that time for markets to<br />
change..?<br />
PM: Well, we haven't seen It. This policy went into place in 1976 in the<br />
Labor Party, it was changed in 1980 as I remember it, inl respect of<br />
Olympic Dam, that's 13 years ago and we've never seen a buoyant<br />
market from that day to this.<br />
J: Are you also saying on uranium and women and the FAC, that once<br />
every three years the Labor Party can't keep more than two balls In the<br />
air at once?<br />
PM: Oh, sometimes we keep a lot in the air at once...<br />
J: Yes, but this time.<br />
PM: But it is a matter of how you rank them. I mean, the women's<br />
representation ona was a big issue, the FAC was a completely<br />
necessary Issue. But, whether in fact for a mining policy which already<br />
allows mining which is already oversupplied and mines are working at<br />
under capacity, where do you rank it in the ranking of Issues? The<br />
thing is, you can't rank it highly. So, you may say it is numerically<br />
three balls but it is really two soccer balls and one ball bearing.<br />
J: The companics seem to think they can make some money out of it or<br />
they wouldn't be in there pushing it, so whiy not let the market decide?<br />
PM: Well, who is here pushing it? I think, in the main it has always been<br />
FRA who have now bought the Pan Continental interest at Jobiluka.<br />
And, mining companies will always try and have as much flexibility as<br />
they can get. But, there wMl always be, for that mine and the flood<br />
plain of the East Alligator River, there will always be a big<br />
environmental Issue. Okay, thanks.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
