<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5367</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005367.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR '-EDIA SUNDAY 1 JUNE 1980<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
Over the past few years Australian farmers have experienced<br />
the highs and lows of life on the land.<br />
There have been both bountiful seasons and the curse of drought.<br />
Cattle were shot as virtually worthless only a few years ago.<br />
Now, livestock are much sought after once again.<br />
The wool corporation emptied its warehouses as wool again<br />
became the gblden fleece.<br />
In fact, the recovery of our great rural industries from the<br />
deep depression of the mid-1970s has been quite remarkable.<br />
In the past two years, the value of rural production and exports<br />
has increased by 60 per cent while real income per farm has more<br />
than doubled to be 75 per cent higher than in the first few years<br />
of the 1970s.<br />
The whole nation has benefited.<br />
And yet again Australian farmers have demonstrated their<br />
traditional resilience and the rural sector has been central to<br />
strong and balanced economic growth.<br />
The fruits of our recovery can be seen in such diverse ways as<br />
the revival of business in country towns, improved company returns<br />
and tlhe renewed interest in agricultural training courses.<br />
Nowlhere is the benefit to the nation more evident than in the<br />
massive contribution to Australia's balance of payments of the<br />
$ 3 billion increase in rural exports over the past two years.<br />
As we enter a new decade, it is timely to remind ourselves of<br />
the continuing importance of rural industries; to reflect on<br />
the lessons of the 1970s; and to look at what the 1980s has in<br />
store for Australian farmers.<br />
At a time when mineral energy development attracts so much<br />
attention and this is completely understandable it is not<br />
often appreciated that this year wheat, and not coal, is<br />
Australia's largest single export earner and that the rural<br />
sector contributes 43. per cent of Australia's export earnings.<br />
/-/ gQt9RY I-ILE </p>
<p>I am sure that the inid-1970s will never be forgotten by country<br />
people. In the devastating year of 1974-75 aElone, a year of reasonable<br />
seasonal conditions, unit farm costs rose by 30 per cent and<br />
real-income earnings feiY . by over 40 per cent.<br />
The strong recovery from those depths is due not only to reasonable<br />
seasons but also to the influence of: a favourable economic<br />
environment achieved through sound and consistent economic<br />
management. Australia's inflation rate is now significantly below the OECD<br />
average. As a result, our competitive position in world markets<br />
is better than it has been for many years.<br />
One lesson we all learned from the ihid-1970s was that no sector<br />
of th~ e economy is more devastated by runaway inflation t-han the<br />
export-orientated rural sector. For as costs rise, our capacity<br />
to compete overseas is severely reduced.<br />
During the past five years, Australia's primary producers have<br />
responded to the Government's initiatives designed to create a<br />
more stable economic environment. The creation of the Primary<br />
Industry Bank, the Income Equalisation Scheme, and the Rural<br />
Adjustment Scheme have all had beneficial effects cn the viability<br />
of rural industries.<br />
To se--ure continuing improvement in the viability of the rural.<br />
sector, the Government has also:<br />
significantly modified the tax averaging provisions.<br />
introduced in full the Fuel Price Equalisation Scheme<br />
increased the floor price for wool from 250 cents in 1975-76<br />
to 318 cents per kilo.<br />
abolished federal death duties<br />
reduced fluctuations in returns to wheat growers and<br />
facilitated.. earlier payments for wheat deliveries<br />
selectively underwritten prescribed dairy products<br />
provided special depreciation provisions for buildings<br />
for the storage of hay, grain and fodder<br />
and recently introduced new ' taxation concessions to assist<br />
in increased water storage.<br />
Under these initiatives, wheat plantings have increased by<br />
per cent over the past two years. The value of wool production<br />
has increased by 38 per cent in the same period. The dairy<br />
industry has undergone one of the most successful adjustments<br />
in Australian agricultural history. The sugar industry is at<br />
last enjoying better prices, and it has the security of long-term<br />
contracts for a large part of its exports. Smaller industries<br />
such as oil seeds, cotton and rice are growing strongly.<br />
Livestock herds are being re-built. </p>
<p>Of course the best news for producers and for all ralians<br />
in the past week has been the cjoo3 rain over much cf the rural<br />
area. The outlook for the 1980-81 season is now b-ie_ than it<br />
was a few weeks ago when drought was tightening its v: ic.<br />
I am advised that the 1980 wheat crop is now off to an encouraging<br />
start and if adequate follow-up rains occur another goo harvest<br />
is likely. Pasture growth in many areas will be dependent on<br />
temperatures from now on, but hopefully hand-feeding should become<br />
less prevalent. Surface water supplies have iirproved and herd<br />
re-building is likely to gather momentum. As markets for rural<br />
produce remain strong, the rural. economy looks set for anot. her<br />
reasonable year. No-one know better than the farmer that in the<br />
good times we must consolidate our advantages and build on our<br />
opportunities. So it must be with Australia.<br />
We cannot allow the significant successes of the last five years<br />
to be eroded by the faulty economic management and defective<br />
policies which dealt such a body blow to the rural sector in the<br />
mid 1970s.<br />
We enter the 1980s with the kind of stability and international<br />
competitiveness that should act as an incentive to all of us.<br />
In the years-ahead our geographic location will be one of our<br />
great advantages. We are a net food and energy exporter in a<br />
region with expanding demand for Australian goods and services of<br />
all kinds.<br />
This provides for Australian primary producers as it does for<br />
all others a challenging role. It is a role which the Government<br />
is determined will be fully and productively played out.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
