<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7450</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER CLOSING CEREMONY OF THE BIECENTENARY ADELAIDE - 31DECEMBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/12/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007450.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
CLOSING CEREMONY OF THE BICENTENARY<br />
ALDELAIDE 31 DECEMBER 1988<br />
John Bannon<br />
John Howard<br />
Jim Kirk<br />
Ladies and Gent*--: e-<br />
Young Austrai.. ins<br />
I am delighted 7: e n. ere in the Adelaide foothills at the<br />
National Ausz:. 3lian Scout Jamboree to share with so<br />
many young Austraihans the closing ceremony of our<br />
Bicentenary. Speaxing today to you I speak through you, to<br />
young people throughout the nation.<br />
This year we have celebrated our achievements as a nation<br />
with some tremendous events the Tall Ships on Sydney<br />
Harbour on Australia Day, Expo in Brisbane, and hundreds of<br />
community events in cities and towns around the nation.<br />
Indeed the Bicentenary has provided some magnificent<br />
memories the cattle treks, the camel races, the bonfires,<br />
the historic climb to the peak of Mount Everest,<br />
re-enactments of historical events. It has given us world<br />
class sporting events and a brilliant program of art and<br />
entertainment. But the Bicentenary has not been only, or even mainly, about<br />
celebrations such as these. Just as importantly, it gave us<br />
an opportunity to think about our past and our future. It<br />
helped us to understand our origins, to think honestly about<br />
our strengths and our weaknesses as a nation, to plan for<br />
the challenges ahead and to build a Bicentennial legacy for<br />
the future.<br />
This is a legacy of a lasting nature a legacy which you<br />
and the Australians of the future will use, enjoy and<br />
benefit from. </p>
<p>Together we have built new parks and cycling paths, heritage<br />
trails and walking tracks along the routes of the early<br />
explorers. There are new sporting facilities and galleries<br />
and museums such as the Stockman's Hall of Fame in<br />
Queensland and the Adelaide Railway museum and the Science<br />
and Technology Centre in Canberra with its hands-on<br />
scientific displays which will be enjoyed by children and<br />
adults for years to come.<br />
And of course there is our new Parliament House a place<br />
which is not just a building but a clear sign of Australia's<br />
commitment to our future as a democratic nation.<br />
I think as a result of the Bicentenary we have come to a<br />
better understanding of who we are as Australians and what<br />
our place in the world is we have a clearer appreciation<br />
of the achievements of our forebears in creating a nation<br />
that is free, democratic, independent and prosperous and<br />
we have a sharper determination to take that legacy of<br />
freedom, democracy, independence and prosperity and to<br />
ensure it is passed on, in total, to future generations of<br />
Australians. That's why we have this year gained a clearer recognition of<br />
the achievements of Aboriginal Australians the original<br />
inhabitants of this continent whose culture reaches back<br />
40,000 years and more into the Dreamtime. More than ever<br />
before I believe Australians stand ready to put right the<br />
wrongs done to Aboriginal people and to work for a fairer<br />
society for all Australians.<br />
We are more aware too of the part migrants have played in<br />
the development of our nation, and we have worked for<br />
greater understanding among the peoples from many lands who<br />
together make up the free and tolerant Australia in which we<br />
can all take pride.<br />
And when we think of the thousands of people from overseas<br />
who visited Australia this year for the Bicentenary Prime<br />
Ministers and Presidents, scientists and scholars, students<br />
on exchange programs, tourists who visited Expo or who just<br />
came to see what a great country we've got when we think<br />
of all these people we realise that the Bicentenary has been<br />
a very important year in terms of building friendships<br />
abroad and showing the world how proud we are to be<br />
Australians. Because we do have much to be proud of, and we have among us<br />
and especially among our young people people of courage,<br />
resourcefulness, good humour and tolerance. We can go<br />
forward with confidence, knowing we have much to offer the<br />
world. It's to help those young Australians that I'm pleased to<br />
announce at this the last event of the Bicentenary year<br />
that the Government will be establishing a special legacy to<br />
be called the Bicentennial Youth Foundation. </p>
<p>A lot of planning has still to be done, but I can tell you<br />
that the Foundation will be provided with an endowment of<br />
million from the Australian Bicentennial Authority.<br />
It will help young Australians aged 16 to 25, who might not<br />
otherwise have the opportunity to develop their capabilities<br />
to contribute to Australia's future in fields such as the<br />
arts, commerce, industry, science, sport and community work.<br />
The Bicentennial Authority will select a group of qiialjiied<br />
Australians to serv'e as a Board of Directors whose job will<br />
be to see that 7rants are made in areas which will truly<br />
benefit the ccm. mun.:,:.<br />
The Foundaticnw-: ea. Ls accord with my Government's<br />
determination -a Ke Australia a fairer place, and to help<br />
families giv-tei: ni. dren the best possible start in<br />
life, the best ss:. *-ducation, and the best chance for<br />
useful emplo:-. er.'<br />
I congratul.-i nd the Australian Bicentennial<br />
Authority ative. And I take this opportunity<br />
to thank Jim u~ tnarity for their hard work and<br />
diligence in : ii :: uly memorable Bicentennial year.<br />
What will Aus,:: a. . i in one hundred years, when your<br />
children and : nildren are celebrating the tercentenary<br />
the three -uncreatl. anniversary of European settlement of<br />
this continent'<br />
It's impossible to make anything but the most general of<br />
educated guesses because we can be sure only that the next<br />
ten decades will be decades of massive change in the world<br />
economy, in technological developments, in our society.<br />
But we, today, have a special responsibility to those<br />
Australians of the future. It's up to us and especially<br />
it will be up to you as the future leaders of Australia to<br />
ensure that those third century celebrations take place in a<br />
world that is at peace and in an Australia in which all<br />
Australians have an equal opportunity to enjoy the benefits<br />
of living in this great country.<br />
So as our Bicentenary now comes to a close, I give you, our<br />
young people, this challenge : look into our past and see<br />
what we have done well and what we have done less well; look<br />
at our present and see what is good and what needs to be<br />
changed; then look to the future and ask yourself what<br />
contribution you can make to building an even better<br />
Au st r ali a. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
