<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>138</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES AT THE OPENING OF FEDERAL COUNCIL OF LIBERAL PARTY CONFERENCE AT THE ALBERT HALL, CANBERRA, 16TH NOVEMBER, 1959</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1959</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000138_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER-~ THE RT. HON. RG.<br />
MENZIES AT THE OPENING OF FELRAL COUNCIL OF<br />
LIBERAL PARTY CONF". ENCE AT THE ALBERT HALL,<br />
CANBI2LRA 3 16TH NOVEMBER, 3 1959<br />
Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
This is, cC course, not the first time that I have had<br />
the pleasure of opening the Annual Meeting of the Council. In<br />
fact as I walked in this morning I was reminded of a few facts<br />
that I had almost forgotten. But it is always a great pleasure<br />
to come here because this is always a most important meeting.<br />
Naturally as we approach the end of ten years we look<br />
back and we look around us. I was called on the other day by a<br />
very well-known American Journalist who had been on his travels<br />
around the world and hie said something to me which other people<br />
have said also, and therefore it's worth recording. He said:<br />
" You know there are very many interesting countries in the<br />
world, but Australia, today, is a most exciting country". Now<br />
lots of people have said that to me; not because they wanted to<br />
please me because most of them had nothing to gain from my<br />
opinion. But they are right: this is a most exciting country,<br />
It isn't exciting because we are exciting nobody a&amp; er accused<br />
us of that it isn't exciting because we have revolutions or<br />
counter-revolutions, or change our Government every few months.<br />
All that kind of excitement is absent from Australia. It is<br />
exciting because no country of even comparable size in the<br />
world or population inthe world is doing so much, is so busy<br />
building its future, so busy creating the great nation that it<br />
will some day be. This is what strikes the intelligent onlooker:<br />
" Ten million people", he says to himself " that's not many;<br />
what goes on here?" and when he looks around and finds out what<br />
goes on here his first impression is that it's an amazing thing<br />
that ten million people should be achieving it. And of course,<br />
particularly, because he is so frequently told before he comes<br />
to Australia that we are easy-going, ' that we are not very fond<br />
of work, that we are devoted to sport and that, really, we are<br />
not very seriously-minded people. That's what he is told before<br />
he comes here and wvhen he comes here he finds an almost turbulent<br />
process of developiient going on and he finds Australia attracting<br />
the attention of the rest ofthe world and attracting the<br />
resources of the rest of the world as nobody ten years ago<br />
would have imagined to be possible.<br />
Now, that I think is all completely true and the paradox<br />
of it is that this dynamic process that is going on in Australia<br />
should be to some material extent the consequence of<br />
steady, stable and sober Government policies. That may sound<br />
paradoxical, but of course, itis a profoundly true thing. A lot<br />
of racketting, and excitement and speculation and speculative<br />
ideas in the top bracket of Government and you'll find a good<br />
deal of dullness further down, and a good deal of anxiety, a<br />
loss of confidence; but if you can create all those things a<br />
feeling of confidence, a feeling that there is stability, that<br />
there is soundness, 7 that steady and intelligent courses are being<br />
pursued if you can find that in Government, whether it's<br />
Federal or State, then you have the pro-condition for this<br />
enormous development. There are many things that are set out in thiat very<br />
good little pamphlet " The First Ten Years" which I hope that<br />
quite a number of people will have read before long, but which<br />
many people have not yet read. perhaps thore is one aspect<br />
of this matter that ought to be mentioned: I just want tCo say<br />
a few words about, in fact about four aspects of the last ton<br />
years. And the first is on the financial side. Ton years ago </p>
<p>when we came back into office we had been told quite blankly by<br />
our predecessors, that it was quite impossible to get hold crf<br />
dollars; that dollars could neither be begged, borrowed or<br />
stolen; that in points of fact we must accommodate ourselves to<br />
the idea that the world of trade was being divided into two<br />
parts and that we must live on hard commons in relation to dollars.<br />
Tlithin six months of our roturnir spite of that gloomy<br />
advice, we had secured in ' Jashington from the tlorld Bank<br />
100 million dollars for vitally needed developmental machinery<br />
in Australia six months after we came into office. And since<br />
then the process has gone on. Ten years ago the amount of investment<br />
inthis country on private account from overseas was<br />
very small, relatively small at any rate. But the last three<br />
years, or four years, whenever we have a look at the Budget, we<br />
have found ourselves saying this: " iVell, there was an inflow<br />
of capital last year of œ_ 90m, per, private investment, or œ lO00m.<br />
It would be unreasonable to suppose that so high a figure could<br />
be maintained; we'd better be a little cautious on this, and<br />
perhaps discount it a bit for next year". But it goes on growing;<br />
it goes on growing in an almost fantastic way. Some of<br />
its effects, of course, need watching; others are splendid.<br />
But those of you who cast your despairing eye on the<br />
Stock Exchan.; e reports occasionally will not have failed to<br />
notice the terrific flurry on the market, the immense buying demand,<br />
very largely brought about by an inflow of money seeking<br />
investment in Australia. And they are not seeking investment,<br />
whether it is in factories or in scrip, they are not seeking investment<br />
in Australia just for the purpose of making a qtdck<br />
profit and going away with it: the great beauty of the overwhelming<br />
bulk o f this investment in Australia is that it has<br />
gone into g&amp; reat enterprises, I giving a massive employment to Australia,<br />
using the subsidiary industries to the fullest possible<br />
extent, and, to a very large extent, ploughing their profits<br />
back into furthe-r Australian development. I tell you that all<br />
this change in the financial complexion of Australia means quite<br />
clearly that in the lifetime of most of us inthis room, we will<br />
see substantial experts of manufactured goods to an extent that<br />
vie hadn't dre3amed of a few years ago. The whole face of this<br />
country is being changed. Now, we would, of course be fools if<br />
we claimed that we did it, because we didn't. Perhaps the wisest<br />
way to put it is this: that we had enough brains not to prevent<br />
it from being done; we had eneugh intelligence to create the<br />
political climate in which it could be done, and I may say that<br />
all of these people, from wherever they come, with their money,<br />
with their skill, with their mate rial, to invest in the development<br />
of Australia, will say that the first thing they like about<br />
Australia is that it has stability of Govurnment and appears to<br />
have got rid of Socialist ideas, Ten years ago, as you know,<br />
the State Governments were, overwhelmingly, in the terms of<br />
numbers, Labour. Today we look around and vie find that that<br />
position is completely reversed. People overseas don't fail to<br />
notice this thing; people overseas have not failed to notice<br />
that after 9 years of continuous office we were given a record<br />
majority. They read into this, and very proporly, a determination<br />
on the part of the people of Australia to maintain sensible<br />
policies, encouraging private e) nterprise, and not discoura<br />
gin g it, with all the stability that they require and all<br />
the confidence in the future for which they had hoped. Now,<br />
Sir, these recommendations and facts are, I think, tremendously<br />
important; they are much more important than any catch-penny<br />
policy that our opponents may be able to put forward.<br />
In the second place in the overall economy of Australia<br />
we see the position: we've had our shifts and changes of fortune,<br />
but we have not had shifts and changes of policy; we've<br />
had some ups and downs but, by and large, over the last ten<br />
years the economic growth of Australia has been immense. Nobody </p>
<p>looking around it could deny it. It is always interesting to me<br />
to encounter, for example the Commonwealth Parliamentary Associa<br />
-tion representatives uho were here the other day; people from<br />
countries and being politicians, most experiencod in the art<br />
of criticism; not disposed to say that something is very good<br />
without some thought. And I think that every one of the representatives<br />
who came hero from 50 or 60 different Parliaments and<br />
who looked around Australia on a splendid journey which was<br />
made and on which they saw many things, not one of them failed<br />
to be impressed by the remarkable growth of the country, and<br />
the opening up of an even more remarkable future. When I say<br />
something about " a remarkable future" I think that it is worth<br />
recalling that very largely because of the vast increase in expenditure<br />
on research my oi. m Government has increased the<br />
amount going to C. S. I. RoO. quite spectacularly over this period<br />
of time. The increasing interest in research on the part of<br />
private enterprise, the encouragement to research by some of the<br />
great primary industries who have levied themselves for this<br />
ppurpose and the work of people like the Bureau of Mineral Resources,<br />
the Commonwe_-alth body which has done almost fabulous<br />
work, as a result of allthese things, and a dozen others, our<br />
old conception of Australia is disappearing. You know, when I<br />
was a young man some wise man sitting in a University study somewhere,<br />
came to the conclusion and proved it by irrefutable<br />
logic that the population of Australia could never be more than<br />
millions because there was no hope for the dead heart of<br />
Australia, no hope of bringing into cultivation land which did<br />
not have adequate rainfall and so on, and even more recently,<br />
as I've told you before, just before the lar this last War<br />
we were told by most reputable experts that the optimum population<br />
that would be reached in Australia was 7 million and we<br />
wouldn't reach that until 1975. That was the climate of mind.<br />
Does anybody believe such nonsense today? When we see soil<br />
being brought under fruitful cultivation which was regarded as<br />
hopeless once; when we find mineral resources being opened<br />
that nobody ever dreamed of, with a broad hint in all the circumstances<br />
that we are almost just at the beginning of mineral<br />
development, does anybody believe these gloomy prophecies when<br />
he sees the work done by the use of trace elements and the like<br />
to bring into proper and rich pastoral production land on<br />
which stock would once fade away. This all appears to the<br />
imagination; this is something of which we must be proud, as<br />
Australians, and which should give us the greatest feeling of<br />
assurance that we will maintain the interests of other people.<br />
I hope we will; that we won't push them back, because I believe<br />
that Australia is roughly at the same period in her history with<br />
a population of 10 million as the United States of America was<br />
in its time, and every prominent American, every highly responsible<br />
American entrepreneur in whatever field, and I know that<br />
some of my State colleagues can confirm this, everyone of them<br />
who has a look at Australia is bound to say before he finishes:<br />
" You know this isjust like the period in American history when<br />
our expansion was beginning and the whole world seemed open to<br />
us" Now the third thing, looking back, is our industrial<br />
position. We have, by and large, over this period of 10 years<br />
had substantially full employment. Je have som times had overfull<br />
employment; we've sometimes had a little spatter of unemployment<br />
but we've never had anything that in any way resembles<br />
the pro-war circumstances in the industrial field. And one<br />
would have expected that with plenty of jobs to be got we might<br />
have expected a good deal of industrial trouble because it is<br />
easier to go on strike to put it bluntly if there are other<br />
jobs around the corner, than it is to go on strike when jobs are<br />
short. And so the cynics, particularly the cynics on the other<br />
side said: " Ah! you see; This Government is -oing to encoun-</p>
<p>4.<br />
ter trouble. The only people who can handle, who can understand,<br />
who can be understood by the Trades Unionists, is the Labour<br />
Party". What nonsense it's turned out to be. I venture to<br />
say that the relations between Government and Trade Union movements<br />
have never been better than in the last ten years. That,<br />
indeed, is why so many Trade Unionists vote for us: our relations<br />
have never been better. And as for the relations between<br />
the great body of Trade Unionists and the community, so far as<br />
that is concerned mark the fact that the loss of work by industrial<br />
trouble is fantastically small. Year by year, year by<br />
year, we've gone on recording fresh records in the small number<br />
of days lost. In point of fact, our present and recent experience<br />
has been such that less time and work have been lost by<br />
industrial trouble than would be occasioned by the granting of<br />
a half-day's holiday in Australia. Of course lots of people<br />
from overseas, years ago, used to say: " Well, Australia, it's<br />
got very tough trade unions; it's always having strikes. We<br />
read about them in the cables strikes and industrial disputes<br />
of all kinds. They even have a special provision in their<br />
Constitution about Industrial disputes. What a land of disputation<br />
it must be." They have only to come here; they have only<br />
to become interested in this country, to get hold of the facts<br />
and they discover that the very reverse is true and in that<br />
field I venture to say that we may claim some credit for the<br />
state of affairs which I have referred to.<br />
And then, finally, looking outside our own country, at<br />
International affairs. You know, this notion one hears, sometimes<br />
in one's own party, or in one's own party organization,<br />
that we have been pretty lucky, that we are rather, on the whole.<br />
inert, and that we suffer from that blessed word " complacency"<br />
in large doses, I get so tired of hearing that kind of thing because<br />
people who say it must have had their eyes closed to<br />
what has been going on, not years but continuously going on<br />
at the present time.<br />
I've said something about some aspects of it but look<br />
at the International picture. Where were we ten years ago before<br />
this inert Government came into power in the Commonwealth?<br />
Where were we internationally? oe had succeeded in quarrelling<br />
with the United States of America; we had been making such<br />
loud noises of self-assertion that people occasionally wondered<br />
what side we were on, on the great issues of the world, and<br />
today, after a continuous processI venture to say that our<br />
status, not only in the British Commonwealth, but in the whlole<br />
world was never as high; that we have achieved a reputation<br />
for responsibility and good sense and co-operation. Certainly<br />
our standing with the United States on the one side and Great<br />
Britain on the other was never more intimate. I have the great<br />
privilege as the Prime Minister to be in frequent communication<br />
of a personal kind with the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom<br />
and in less frequent communication of a personal kind with the<br />
President of the United States of America. Je can communicato<br />
with each other as friends. Je are of unquestioned standing<br />
in the free world and in respect of our own problems in the<br />
South east of Asia, in the south-west Pacific, which are problems<br />
which, under Communist pressure, might become more and<br />
more acute, without us being able to restrain them, in relation<br />
to. this area, we have taken an active and successful part in<br />
promoting two great International Agreements one the ANZUS<br />
Agreement with the United States of America and New Zealand<br />
and ourselves, a negotiation in which we played a most loading<br />
part and the South-East Asian Treaty Organization in which,<br />
again, the United States is involved, and, of course, Great<br />
Britin and ourselves and Now Zealand and two or three of the<br />
Souti East Asian countries.<br />
That Agreement itself was a notable achievement in<br />
diplomacy and just to show that all this isn't past history and<br />
that we have given up the ghost and have no more ideas to pro-</p>
<p>4 b -duce I hope you have all noticed that in these discussions in<br />
Washington in relation to Antarctica, the chief promotion of<br />
ideas and of an Agreement betwken the Nations has come from<br />
Australia through my colleague Mr. Casey. And in the result<br />
we are going to see an International sot of affairs in Antarctica<br />
which will achieve much good results two things in particular;<br />
one, I wont say the demilitarization of Antarctica because<br />
it hasn't been militarised, but an Agreement that it<br />
shall not be used for military purposes. That would have seemed<br />
silly, wouldn't it, once, until they began to develop rockets<br />
and guided missiles and sputniks and the like; very important<br />
today. And in the second place, the combination of the resources<br />
of nations for the exploitation of scientific knowledge<br />
or, indeed, of scientific matter of any kind in the Antarctic<br />
area and that again is of tremendous importance to us.<br />
Even meteorologically, it would be a wonderful thing if we<br />
could have access to all the scientific meteorological knowledge<br />
gathered by other nations to have a foot-hold in the Antarctic<br />
so that we might pool the results, it would improve our own<br />
poor knowledge of our weather in Australia out of all recognition.<br />
So, Sir, things go on, but as we are getting towards<br />
the end of our tenth year I thought that it might be an opportunity<br />
for saying something to all our friends here today<br />
those iho are the labourers in the field in the Liberal cause<br />
something of the pride that I know you feel and that I know I<br />
feel in what has been going on and something of the complete<br />
confidence that eo have that so long as we maintain the steady<br />
course, the strong-minded ideas that we have had in the past,<br />
then nothing can prevent Austrqlia from flourishing and becoming<br />
great. Sir, I declare the Conference open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
