<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10883</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO QUEENSLAND DIVISION STATE CONVENTION                MANSFIELD, QUEENSLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/11/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much, Bob, and to all of my fellow Liberals here in</p>
<p> Queensland I would like to thank you very warmly for that immensely</p>
<p> encouraging and supportive welcome. It's very difficult, on an</p>
<p> occasion like this, to really summon the right words to express the</p>
<p> sense of gratitude, the sense of excitement and the sense of anticipation</p>
<p> of our Liberal achievements yet to be realised. Because what has happened</p>
<p> over the last month and what happened in the election on the 3rd</p>
<p> of October in so many ways was more important, more crucial, more</p>
<p> emphatic and more successful than our victory in March of 1996. What</p>
<p> we have done by winning again and winning again in a convincing fashion</p>
<p> is to give to the Coalition a heaven-sent opportunity to remake the</p>
<p> political map of Australia.</p>
<p>I want to start my remarks this morning by congratulating Bob Carroll</p>
<p> and all the other office bearers of the Queensland Division on their</p>
<p> election to their respective positions. I do express my gratitude</p>
<p> to the Queensland organisation, to your President, to your State Director,</p>
<p> Greg Goebel, and to all the other staff and all the other branch and</p>
<p> conference members who worked so very hard to deliver what is, by</p>
<p> historical standards, a quite extraordinary result. For the Coalition</p>
<p> to hold 19 out of the 26 federal divisions in Queensland and 14 of</p>
<p> those divisions to be held by the Liberal Party is a very remarkable</p>
<p> achievement.</p>
<p>Our sweeping win in 1996 delivered a first-class group of people into</p>
<p> the Parliament. The Labor Party was left here in Queensland with a</p>
<p> bare two seats and one seat, Oxley, in the hands of an Independent.</p>
<p> And I do want to record my regret and my gratitude and my sense of</p>
<p> political commiseration with a number of my colleagues and friends</p>
<p> who were not successful on the 3rd of October.</p>
<p>I do want to thank Andrea West and Elizabeth Grace and Graeme McDougall,</p>
<p> three members who lost their seats through no fault of their own but</p>
<p> through the inevitable swing back, to some degree, of the political</p>
<p> pendulum which was to be expected after the subsidence of the intense</p>
<p> anti-Keating feeling of March of 1996. But all of them worked extremely</p>
<p> hard as members of Parliament and I express my gratitude to them and</p>
<p> my sense of thanks for the work that they did as very dedicated, committed</p>
<p> and hard-working local members. To those people who fought as candidates,</p>
<p> not being members of Parliament and who were unsuccessful  and</p>
<p> I don't think anybody will mind me particularly singling out</p>
<p> Rod Henshaw for the campaign that he waged in the seat of Dickson.</p>
<p> To Cameron Thompson, the victor in Blair, and to all others who campaigned</p>
<p> so very hard and who won so convincingly.</p>
<p>It is, as I said, by any stretch of political comparison a great result</p>
<p> here in Queensland and it reflects very favourably on the work of</p>
<p> the Liberal Party here in Queensland, a party that has gone through</p>
<p> difficulties over the years and has faced challenges, particularly</p>
<p> in the nature of Coalition politics here in Queensland which, as I</p>
<p> don't need any reminding, have their own distinctive flavour</p>
<p> and characteristic. But you've done it well and you've done</p>
<p> it convincingly and once again the Liberal Party and the National</p>
<p> Party working together, separate political organisations, separate</p>
<p> and distinctive philosophies on some issues but nonetheless always</p>
<p> united in a determination to politically destroy the Australian Labor</p>
<p> Party.</p>
<p>It is very important in the wake of a victory such as we achieved</p>
<p> on the 3rd of October to understand the nature of what</p>
<p> was achieved and to understand the true meaning and the character</p>
<p> of that victory. It is always a mistake for a political party to misread</p>
<p> an election result. Paul Keating did it in 1993 and he paid very dearly</p>
<p> in 1996. It was always a mistake for us to imagine that the extraordinarily</p>
<p> high swings that were achieved in 1996 could be maintained forever</p>
<p> because there was within that vote, as I said earlier, an intense,</p>
<p> almost unprecedented degree of feeling within the Australian community</p>
<p> that a change of government was needed.</p>
<p>In the years that I've been actively involved in politics I've</p>
<p> experienced, on a number of occasions, in 1972, in 1975, in 1983 and</p>
<p> again in 1996, an intense and obvious and unstoppable desire on the</p>
<p> part of the Australian people for a change of government. But on other</p>
<p> occasions that hasn't been present. And inevitably, therefore,</p>
<p> we faced a fight to retain all of the ground that we had won in 1996.</p>
<p> That we were able to win by a comfortable majority of 12 seats which</p>
<p> by any historical analysis is a reasonable, ordinary, working majority</p>
<p> for any incumbent government.</p>
<p>We face the challenge of ensuring that our victory in 1998 is followed</p>
<p> by subsequent victories in the years ahead but that won't be</p>
<p> achieved by assuming that what operated in 1998 is going to operate</p>
<p> in the year 2001. I've said on a number of occasions since the</p>
<p> election that every election is an island. There is no such thing</p>
<p> as a continuum in the politics of this country. Each election throws</p>
<p> up different issues, different challenges and different circumstances.</p>
<p> And I can see in their reaction to the result of 1998 the seeds of</p>
<p> the Labor Party's grand illusion. I don't think the Labor</p>
<p> Party really does understand that the circumstances of 1998 won't</p>
<p> be present in the year 2001. And just as 1998 was very different from</p>
<p> 1996, so the year 2001 will be very different from 1998.</p>
<p>We've learnt a lot of things from the last election but one of</p>
<p> the things that we have learnt from the last election is that when</p>
<p> it comes to marginal seat campaigning the true professionals in Australia</p>
<p> are the members of the Liberal Party. We watched election after election</p>
<p> being taken from us in the 1980s because the Labor Party out campaigned</p>
<p> us in marginal seats. We've now been able to turn that experience</p>
<p> on its head because one of the many lessons to come out of 1998 was</p>
<p> the superb marginal seat campaigning of many of our members. And I</p>
<p> thank them and I congratulate all of them for that.</p>
<p>Something that won't be present, of course, in the year 2001</p>
<p> is the political challenge of introducing a bold tax reform plan.</p>
<p> We all knew that that added a special dimension of difficulty to the</p>
<p> campaign. We all knew that any plan of that magnitude and boldness</p>
<p> was naturally exposed to an intensely dishonest fear campaign and,</p>
<p> of course, the Labor Party didn't disappointed us on that score.</p>
<p> They ran one of the most dishonest, ferociously simplistic, destructive,</p>
<p> against the national interest, political campaigns that I have seen</p>
<p> in 25 years in politics. Everybody who's had anything to do with</p>
<p> the governance of this country over the last quarter of a century,</p>
<p> whether they're Labor, Liberal or National, knows in their heart</p>
<p> that this country needs fundamental taxation reform  everyone</p>
<p> knows that.</p>
<p>And in their own way, in various times holding other positions, three</p>
<p> successive leaders of the Australian Labor Party, Bob Hawke, Paul</p>
<p> Keating and Kim Beazley, have espoused the same cause that I took</p>
<p> to the Australian people on the 3rd of October. They espoused</p>
<p> the cause of taxation reform. And if ever there was a time that something</p>
<p> had to be called for the long-term interest of our country it was</p>
<p> on the 3rd of October and that issue was taxation reform.</p>
<p> And I am immensely proud of the fact that the Liberal Party of Australia</p>
<p> had the courage, the determination, the resilience and the commitment</p>
<p> to the national interest to stick to our guns and to go that election</p>
<p> with a bold plan of taxation reform.</p>
<p>I and many people in this room have wanted taxation reform in this</p>
<p> country for more than 20 years and at long last we have the authority</p>
<p> of the Australian people to do it. And I want to say to our opponents</p>
<p> in the Senate, be they members of the Labor Party or members of the</p>
<p> Australian Democrats, having put our political bodies on the line</p>
<p> on the 3rd of October and having won the support of the Australian</p>
<p> people, we intend to use every legitimate means at our disposal to</p>
<p> see that the will of the Australian people is implemented.</p>
<p>This extraordinary proposition that you should go through what was</p>
<p> effectively a seven-week election campaign, that you should put your</p>
<p> whole political future on the line both individually as a party in</p>
<p> championing the cause of something that everybody in their heart knows</p>
<p> is right and is in the best interests of the country, and then having</p>
<p> won that battle and having survived that challenge and having got</p>
<p> across the line with a comfortable working majority, that you should</p>
<p> somehow or other then sit around and wait until your opponents are</p>
<p> in the best tactical advantage in the Senate before you put your legislation</p>
<p> forward is a piece of political intelligence that completely escapes</p>
<p> me.</p>
<p>I thought politics was about forming a view about what was good for</p>
<p> Australia, arguing your case to the Australian people and if they</p>
<p> voted for you you did it. And that essentially is what I've always</p>
<p> understood politics to be about but obviously, even though I've</p>
<p> been in Parliament for 25 years, I have a lot to learn but we'll</p>
<p> wait and see about that. The other thing that we must remember about</p>
<p> the election, and now that the election is over I rather enjoy the</p>
<p> role of being a commentator for a moment. I spent a lot of time in</p>
<p> the campaign saying I wasn't going to be a commentator because</p>
<p> commentary by Prime Ministers in election campaigns is very dangerous.</p>
<p> After it's over it's a different matter.</p>
<p>The other thing we ought to understand about this election is that</p>
<p> any dillusion by the Labor Party that in some way the result represented</p>
<p> a Labor resurgence is utterly disproved by any analysis of the figures.</p>
<p> What essentially happened nation wide, it varied a bit from State</p>
<p> to State, what essentially happened nation wide in this election was</p>
<p> that the Labor Party's primary vote barely rose. It rose perhaps</p>
<p> 1 to 1.5 points nation- wide. The Coalition's primary vote fell</p>
<p> by 8 to 9 % nation wide and almost all of that went to One Nation.</p>
<p>And then via the distribution of preferences by One Nation about half</p>
<p> of that 8% to 9% was passed through to the Labor Party. The Labor</p>
<p> Party profited from One Nation. We lost seats because of One Nation.</p>
<p> The party that did the most self sacrificing thing in placing One</p>
<p> Nation last was the Liberal Party of Australia, not the Australian</p>
<p> Labor Party. But it was the right decision and I want to say that</p>
<p> I never had any doubt that it was the right decision to take because</p>
<p> it would have distracted and beset and befuddled and provided hurdles</p>
<p> throughout the entire campaign if the issue had not been taken off</p>
<p> the political agenda. And I think in the long term Australian politics</p>
<p> is better for the fact that there are no representatives of One Nation</p>
<p> in the House of Representatives. Far, far better.</p>
<p>So we ought to understand why it happened. We ought to understand</p>
<p> the lessons that we should learn from it. We shouldn't be reluctant</p>
<p> to enjoy for a moment, to saviour for a moment, a second federal electoral</p>
<p> victory. We should contemplate the responsibility that we now have</p>
<p> to manage the affairs of our nation at a time of great historical</p>
<p> moment, at a time of intense national excitement. Over the next three</p>
<p> years Australia will experience a number of quite remarkable events.</p>
<p> We will host the Olympic Games of the year 2000 and that is not just</p>
<p> an event for the city of Sydney, it is an event for the entire nation.</p>
<p> We will also of course, and most importantly, we will celebrate the</p>
<p> centenary of the formation of the Australian nation, the centenary</p>
<p> of federation in the year 2001 will represent the greatest opportunity</p>
<p> that anybody in the lifetime of anybody in this room has had to reflect</p>
<p> upon the Australian achievement.</p>
<p>And to me I see the centenary of federation, not as an occasion for</p>
<p> negative, reflective, introspective, defensive, national naval gazing</p>
<p> but rather as an opportunity to celebrate the intense and great achievements</p>
<p> of the Australian people and of the Australian nation.</p>
<p>It is an occasion for celebration. It is an occasion to reflect upon</p>
<p> what this nation has achieved. It is an occasion to remind the world</p>
<p> again that the tolerant liberal credentials of this country are without</p>
<p> parallel anywhere in the world. It is also of course an occasion,</p>
<p> as any nation should do, to reflect upon the mistakes and the blemishes</p>
<p> of the past and no nation is free of them. But few have achieved what</p>
<p> this country has achieved and I would like to see that celebration</p>
<p> as being very much a celebration of the Australian achievement, because</p>
<p> it has been an incredible achievement and it has been an achievement</p>
<p> that has been purchased at a very heavy cost by some of our number</p>
<p> who have given their lives to defend the kind of life that we now</p>
<p> enjoy and the kind of society that we now celebrate.</p>
<p>The next three years are of course an opportunity to provide to this</p>
<p> country the economic leadership that has so far protected Australia</p>
<p> against the worst impact of the Asian economic downturn. Last week's</p>
<p> inflation figure was an extraordinarily good result. And it was a</p>
<p> dramatic reminder to the Australian community and to the rest of the</p>
<p> world of just how well this country has been managed economically</p>
<p> over the last two-and-a-half years. Every day goes by we are given</p>
<p> more and more proof of the wisdom of the Government's action</p>
<p> when it came to office in March of 1996 to get the budget back into</p>
<p> balance. There may have been decisions taken that caused pain and</p>
<p> unhappiness and hostility. There may have been people in this room</p>
<p> who disagreed with some of the decisions that we took. There were</p>
<p> people in the community who were affected by those decisions. But</p>
<p> at the end of the day if we had not got our economy in order we would</p>
<p> now be suffering some of the depredation and some of the pain, to</p>
<p> some of the order that is now being suffered by our friends and our</p>
<p> neighbours in the Asian-Pacific region.</p>
<p>If we had not taken action to protect the Australian economy we would</p>
<p> now have higher interest rates, higher inflation, higher unemployment,</p>
<p> lower economic growth, lower economic growth, lower business investment,</p>
<p> a weaker currency and a vulnerability to the world in stark contrast</p>
<p> to the example of strength and resilience that we now represent to</p>
<p> the world. And that is why those decisions, my friends, were so important.</p>
<p>But over the next three years we must not only care for the economic</p>
<p> health of this country but we must do it in a way that respects the</p>
<p> social fabric. We must do it in a way that continues to protect and</p>
<p> nurture the values that provide a decent social security safety net,</p>
<p> that recognise the importance within our community of strong functional</p>
<p> Australian families, and that recognise that good government is not</p>
<p> just about good economics and good bookkeeping. It is also about the</p>
<p> values of our society, it is also about the things that we hold dear.</p>
<p> It is also about confronting some of the non-economic challenges to</p>
<p> the Australian way of life. It's about recognising as a federal</p>
<p> government that we have a role in fighting the drug menace within</p>
<p> our society. It is about recognising the importance of high educational</p>
<p> standards within the Australian community. It is also about recognising</p>
<p> the limited but strategic role that the federal government must play</p>
<p> in the war against crime within the Australian community. It is about</p>
<p> recognising that we are to achieve, what I think all of us want, and</p>
<p> that is a strong and fair and caring Australian society as we move</p>
<p> into the third Christian millennium.</p>
<p>We can't as a government do it alone, nor can the individual</p>
<p> do it on his or her own or nor can it be left to the great community</p>
<p> organisations of our nation. What we need is a partnership between</p>
<p> the government, great community organisations and individuals. A partnership</p>
<p> that recognises that the role of government is not to be intrusive</p>
<p> but rather to be supportive. The government does have a limited role</p>
<p> in our society but nonetheless an important and a strategic role.</p>
<p> There are some things that governments can do that no other part of</p>
<p> society can do. But there are many things that governments over the</p>
<p> past have tried to do and they have been miserable failures. And the</p>
<p> art of good government in the 1990s, as we come towards the close</p>
<p> of this century, the art of good government will be to recognise where</p>
<p> it should intervene in that limited but strategic way. To recognise</p>
<p> that if you want a strong economy you'll only get that through</p>
<p> an essentially unregulated thriving progressive and forward looking</p>
<p> business sector and business community.</p>
<p>But if you really want to provide a proper social security safety</p>
<p> net you not only need the provision of support from the government</p>
<p> through pensions and Medicare and all the other things that make up</p>
<p> the social security safety net, but you also need to supplement that</p>
<p> with the work of the great community organisations such as the Salvation</p>
<p> Army and the St Vincent De Paul, and all the other great organisations</p>
<p> that have a coal face understanding of human misery and human hardship</p>
<p> that most of us don't have. And working in cooperation with those</p>
<p> great welfare organisations we can renew and renew in a very effective</p>
<p> way the compassionate side of our society. But importantly we also</p>
<p> need the partnership of individuals because if the Liberal Party stands</p>
<p> for anything, and it does stand for many things, it stands above all</p>
<p> else for the importance and the sanctity of each individual man and</p>
<p> woman within the Australian community. It has always been the most</p>
<p> important element of the Liberal belief that we should build a society</p>
<p> where every man and woman has the absolute right to pursue to the</p>
<p> maximum that his or her talents will allow their dream and their destiny</p>
<p> and their hopes for their lives and for the lives of their families.</p>
<p>There is no better welfare system of course in any community than</p>
<p> a collection of stable functioning families. United stable supporting</p>
<p> families remains still the best nurturing environment for children,</p>
<p> the best emotional bedrock for young adults and the greatest source</p>
<p> of companionship and emotional support and love throughout life at</p>
<p> whatever age.</p>
<p>So as we contemplate the next three years we are right to feel proud</p>
<p> of what the Liberal Party has achieved. We are right to feel proud</p>
<p> of the political courage the party displayed in going to the electorate</p>
<p> with a bold reform plan. And we are right to anticipate the responsibilities</p>
<p> of the next three years. They will be very different from the last</p>
<p> two-and-a-half. We will need to blend our economic realism with our</p>
<p> social responsibility and our social concern, and getting the balance</p>
<p> right will be very important for the future of our party. There is</p>
<p> no hostility, there is no permanent conflict, there is no enduring</p>
<p> antagonism between an economically efficient society and a socially</p>
<p> compassionate society. The idea that in some way you can't run</p>
<p> the economy well without neglecting the social side of your responsibilities</p>
<p> as a government is a very short sighted view. The two are mutually</p>
<p> reinforcing. The one is not possible without the other. If you don't</p>
<p> have an efficient wealthy society you cannot help the less privileged</p>
<p> within our community. If you don't help the less privileged within</p>
<p> our community what is the point of having a wealthy powerful society</p>
<p> economically. The two are mutually reinforcing. The two matter as</p>
<p> much to me as I know they matter to you. And the successful blending</p>
<p> of those two and the quality that that will bring to the lives of</p>
<p> the Australian community will be our goal and our responsibility over</p>
<p> the next three years. Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
