<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10694</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER             THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                PRESS CONFERENCE                REGENT HOTEL, KUALA LUMPUR</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/11/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.......................................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, this morning I had three very important</p>
<p> bilateral meetings - with President Habibie of Indonesia, President</p>
<p> Kim Dae-Jung of Korea, and the new Japanese Prime Minister, Mr Obuchi.</p>
<p>It was in fact my first meeting with each of those three gentlemen</p>
<p> in their current positions. I had previously met Dr Habibie when he</p>
<p> was a Minister in the Indonesian Government. I think it's fair</p>
<p> to say that Dr Habibie and I spent most of our time talking about</p>
<p> the domestic reforms and the domestic situation in Indonesia. He assured</p>
<p> me of the commitment of his Government towards greater liberalisation</p>
<p> in that country. He expressed a great deal of optimism about the measures</p>
<p> that had been adopted at the recent meeting of the Assembly, and he</p>
<p> was hopeful that those measures would be seen as a very significant</p>
<p> gesture towards a more open liberal and democratic political system</p>
<p> in Indonesia.</p>
<p>He was very grateful for the support that Australia had given Indonesia</p>
<p> in her time of very great difficulty a few months ago. He was particularly</p>
<p> grateful for the fact that Australia had argued with other nations</p>
<p> for a better understanding of the social problems faced by Indonesia</p>
<p> because of the economic downturn. He drew attention to the way in</p>
<p> which his country's currency had stabilised, compared with what</p>
<p> it had obtained a few months ago, and as befits his personality, was</p>
<p> very upbeat about the future of both his Government and Indonesia.</p>
<p> I extended an invitation to him to visit Australia and I'm very</p>
<p> hopeful that he will take up that invitation next year.</p>
<p>I was particularly pleased to meet President Kim Dae-Jung of Korea.</p>
<p> I think all of you know what an incredible experience he's been</p>
<p> through politically in his own country, and what a remarkable achievement</p>
<p> it is for him after all that's happened, to become President</p>
<p> of Korea, and of course assume the presidency of that country at a</p>
<p> time of extraordinary economic challenge and difficulty.</p>
<p>He once again was very appreciative of the support that Australia</p>
<p> extended through the IMF bail-out to Korea. He gave me a detailed</p>
<p> rundown of the measures that had been taken to strengthen the Korean</p>
<p> economy, and it's fair to say that Korea, along with Thailand,</p>
<p> certainly accepted some very severe economic medicine in order to</p>
<p> get their domestic economies back into shape. He made the very important</p>
<p> observation to me that it was essential that each country in the region</p>
<p> make sure that its domestic economic foundations and fundamentals</p>
<p> were in order, and that action on the international multilateral front</p>
<p> should be seen as a supplement for, and not a replacement of, domestic</p>
<p> economic change and domestic economic correction. And I was very encouraged</p>
<p> at the continued commitment that he showed towards economic reform</p>
<p> and economic change.</p>
<p>Both he and President Habibie welcomed the Australian initiative relating</p>
<p> to economic and financial governance, and of course that particular</p>
<p> initiative will allocate from the 50 million dollars in question something</p>
<p> in the order of 18 or 19 million dollars for projects to improve the</p>
<p> economic and financial governance of different institutions within</p>
<p> Indonesia. So, it's a particularly important initiative for that</p>
<p> country, but there will also be benefits for other countries as well.</p>
<p>I also appreciated the opportunity to meet Mr Obuchi. We exchanged</p>
<p> some reminiscences about broad-based indirect taxes. He drew my attention</p>
<p> to the fact that his political mentor, Mr Takeshita, had been the</p>
<p> Prime Minister of Japan when the broad-based indirect tax was introduced.</p>
<p> He said it was introduced at three percent and now it's five,</p>
<p> and now there's agitation for it to come back to three. And I</p>
<p> made the observation later in the discussion that it was always important</p>
<p> to introduce it at a realistic level at the beginning, and therefore</p>
<p> there'd be absolutely no pressure for any increase, and absolutely</p>
<p> no argument about that.</p>
<p>He gave me also a rundown on what had occurred in Japan. He detailed</p>
<p> the stimulus package he announced yesterday and also alluded to the</p>
<p> joint announcement that had been made by Japan and the United States</p>
<p> last night. He of course recognises that his Government must get the</p>
<p> Japanese economy back into positive growth and he recognises that</p>
<p> that is their overriding responsibility.</p>
<p>He felt the banking reforms that had been passed by the Japanese Diet</p>
<p> would make a very big contribution towards repairing some of the fundamentals</p>
<p> that need to be repaired in Japan. I emphasised to him the value of</p>
<p> course of Japan to us, and how important the strength of the Japanese</p>
<p> economy was to Australia's economic future, and he renewed an</p>
<p> invitation, which I intend to take up, to pay a state visit to Japan</p>
<p> next year. It's part of a longstanding arrangement, an official</p>
<p> visit I think is the correct expression (thank you, Mr Thawley), and</p>
<p> I hope to take up that invitation next year, and of course the relationship</p>
<p> between our two countries is well known, quite fundamental to us,</p>
<p> and the strength of the Japanese economy is very important to the</p>
<p> strength of the economic direction of the whole world.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, Vice President Al Gore praised the "brave people of</p>
<p> Malaysia" for fighting for reforms and freedoms through the reformasi</p>
<p> movement in Malaysia. Does Australia also support the reformasi movement</p>
<p> here?</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Everybody has their own way of dealing with issues which they want</p>
<p> to comment on. I chose to meet the Prime Minister of Malaysia and</p>
<p> to express my views to him, that's the Australian way. Vice President</p>
<p> Gore has chosen to express some views, that's his decision and</p>
<p> he's got a perfect right to do that. I think our view on the</p>
<p> issue, which you no doubt have in mind in asking that question, is</p>
<p> well-known and we believe in an open democratic system as the preferable</p>
<p> way of running a country. We also recognise that different countries</p>
<p> have different views and have different cultures and the intelligent</p>
<p> thing to do and I think productive thing for a country Australia's</p>
<p> size and where Australia is located, to do is to always be identified</p>
<p> with liberal democratic values and always to be seen as a country</p>
<p> that values those approaches and puts great store on them, but not</p>
<p> to be seen as a country which sees its prime role in the world as</p>
<p> lecturing others as to how they should run their systems of government.</p>
<p>Now our position in relation to the former Deputy Prime Minister of</p>
<p> this country of Malaysia is well-known. In fact I think I was probably</p>
<p> the first regional leader to say something about it, so I'm not</p>
<p> going to accept from anybody any suggestion that Australia has been</p>
<p> reluctant to express a point of view. But you must understand that</p>
<p> we are part of this region, we often do things a little differently</p>
<p> from others because we have different interests, and we have a different</p>
<p> approach, and what is the Australian way is the way best-calculated</p>
<p> to register our point of view, but by the same token to have a continuing</p>
<p> influence in the region. And I've often spoken of the fact that</p>
<p> Australia brings unique insights to this region because of our geographic</p>
<p> proximity. That was clearly demonstrated in the insights we brought</p>
<p> when Indonesia was in deep financial, political and social difficulty</p>
<p> some time ago. And I think our insights there were right and they</p>
<p> helped the situation and that is now widely recognised and I think</p>
<p> that same observation must of necessity be made in other matters.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does Australia support the reformasi movement in Malaysia of which</p>
<p> Anwar is a part?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, what Australia support is a transparent trial of him, and what</p>
<p> Australia supports is continuing moves in all countries towards a</p>
<p> more open liberal democratic society. I'm not going to attach</p>
<p> myself to this or that description, or this or that tag of something</p>
<p> else. Of course we support a more liberal open approach in all countries,</p>
<p> but we also respect the right of countries to have the system of governance</p>
<p> that they think is best for their society.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Now is it the case that this has been....reform in Indonesia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think it's possible, Craig, to give a simplistic</p>
<p> yes or no answer to that sort of question. I think the issues involved</p>
<p> are far more complicated than the simplicity of that question suggests.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Gore's remarks also extended to Indonesia. Was there any discussion</p>
<p> between you and Dr Habibie today on those remarks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I haven't read the full text of Mr Gore's remarks,</p>
<p> you may have, I haven't. I read a report of them. Indonesia has</p>
<p> come some distance from where it was, and I'd repeat what I said</p>
<p> yesterday. People should have an understanding of the huge social</p>
<p> and economic and political transformation that faces Indonesia. It's</p>
<p> a very large country. There are significant internal conflicts and</p>
<p> pressures, and I think people should have an understanding of what</p>
<p> is involved.</p>
<p>We all want a more liberal and open and democratic society in that</p>
<p> country, of course we do. But we've got to recognise, and I speak</p>
<p> as an Australian, and speaking as Australian Prime Minister, we've</p>
<p> got to recognise that every society is different, and you don't</p>
<p> necessarily achieve desirable outcomes by constantly hectoring other</p>
<p> nations in order to change the way they run their life. You must retain</p>
<p> influence, and the best way for a country of 18 million people to</p>
<p> retain influence is to hold fast to its own values, but by the same</p>
<p> token have a capacity to understand that other countries may want</p>
<p> to do things differently. And nations of 18 million people obviously</p>
<p> will deport themselves differently on occasions than nations of over</p>
<p> 200 million.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does Australia believe that the Indonesian Military went too far last</p>
<p> week?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I'm not going to give a judgement yes or no on that. I think</p>
<p> that is the sort of peremptory black and white judgement that it is</p>
<p> not helpful for Australian Prime Ministers to make. You give considered</p>
<p> observations over a period of time, and we have made it very, very</p>
<p> plain that we want more reform. We've made that very plain, but</p>
<p> we're also making it very plain that we appreciate the steps</p>
<p> that Indonesia has already taken. And the bilateral relationship between</p>
<p> Australia and Indonesia, let me say to you, has survived the most</p>
<p> enormous changes that have taken place in Indonesia over the last</p>
<p> 12 months in very good shape, and one of the reasons why it has survived</p>
<p> in very good shape is that I haven't run around giving advice</p>
<p> every hour of the day of every day, as to what the Indonesian people</p>
<p> and the Indonesian authorities should do. And if you want to care</p>
<p> for the Australian national interest, and the Australian national</p>
<p> interest lies in keeping a strong bilateral relationship with Indonesia,</p>
<p> you don't spend all your time giving lectures to other countries</p>
<p> and other societies.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Will Australia contribute to the US$5 billion dollars aid.. (inaudible)?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we will obviously have a look at any approaches, but you've</p>
<p> got to bear in mind that Australia has already made, given her size,</p>
<p> very significant contributions to the financial bail-outs in the region</p>
<p> and we've contributed, along with Japan we're the only country</p>
<p> to have contributed to each of the three IMF bail-outs, and in each</p>
<p> case it's been the equivalent of US $1 billion dollars, and we've</p>
<p> also increased our bilateral aid to Indonesia, and we've also</p>
<p> announced a 50 million dollar package in relation to financial and</p>
<p> economic governance, so I don't think anybody can suggest that</p>
<p> Australia hasn't already made a very significant contribution.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>On the issue of the announcement last night, the five/10 billion dollar</p>
<p> package or whatever it is, I understand that Australia has been approached</p>
<p> on a bilateral basis by some East-Asian countries, asking whether</p>
<p> the country would be prepared to give some form of guarantee to loan-raising</p>
<p> programs by those countries.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not aware of the details of those approaches. I would</p>
<p> be happy obviously to consider any approaches, I say consider, but</p>
<p> I simply make the point that we've already contributed very generously</p>
<p> and I'm just not going to make an on-the-run further commitment.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, has Australia been approached to, and asked to send officials</p>
<p> to meet in Tokyo, on the bailout? There's going to be a meeting</p>
<p> shortly in Tokyo to...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there's been an invitation. You're talking about the</p>
<p> (inaudible), the announcement that was made last night? Well obviously</p>
<p> Australia will, at an official level, involve itself in discussions,</p>
<p> yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>The Malaysian Trade Minister has taken great umbrage at Vice President</p>
<p> Gore's speech, and said it could spoil APEC before it begins.</p>
<p> Do you share that concern?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, I don't think APEC will be spoilt, no I don't. No, I</p>
<p> don't think APEC will be spoilt at all.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think that Mr Gore went too far...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mr Who?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Did you think that US Vice President Gore went too far....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, look I'm not going to give him advice either.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>I understand the question of bail for Mr Anwar was raised..</p>
<p>PRIME MINITSER:</p>
<p>Who by?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Between Wan Azizah and Mr Downer. Does Australia support....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh, look I've already made a very detailed statement about Anwar</p>
<p> and we've made our position very clear. I'm not going to</p>
<p> sort of micro-analyse every aspect of it. Our position is we want</p>
<p> a transparent trial, I said that to Dr Mahathir. I didn't say</p>
<p> it through a speech, I said it to him. That remains our position.</p>
<p> And as to the minutiae of that, I just don't think there's</p>
<p> anything I can add. I'm not going to do it. Thank you.</p>
<p>  [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
