<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3919</transcript-id>
    <title>CONSUMER PROTECTION</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003919.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
if;<br />
PRIUVE -PAISTER Press Statement No. 575<br />
14 October 1975<br />
CONSUMER PROTECTION<br />
The Prime Minister today announced that following<br />
an amendment to the Administrative Arrangements Order approved<br />
by the Governor-General, the Minister for Science and Consumer<br />
Affairs, the Hon. Clyde Cameron, has assumed<br />
responsibility, for administration of consumer protection<br />
provisions ( Part V) of the Trade Practices Act.<br />
The Minister for Science and Consumer Affairs<br />
will administer these matters and the staff of the Trade<br />
Practices Commission which has been handling consumer protection<br />
matters in Canberra and all State capitals are being transferred<br />
from the Trade Practices Commission to the Department of<br />
Science and Consumer Affairs for this purpose.<br />
These arrangements consolidate under the<br />
Minister for Science and Consumer Affairs the Government's<br />
policies in the field of consumer protection. The Government<br />
contemplates that ultimately consumer protection functions<br />
will be undertaken by the Australian Consumer Protection<br />
Authority. A Bill to establish that Authority is to be<br />
introduced into the Parliament today.<br />
The Trade Practices Commission will now ce~ ase<br />
to handle any consumer protection matters. Current investigations<br />
and proceedings will be continued by the transferred staff.<br />
All enquiries on consumer protection matters should now be<br />
directed to the Department of Science and Consumer Affairs.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
