<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7905</transcript-id>
    <title>PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE 16 FEBRUARY 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/02/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007905.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARTIAL TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE,<br />
16 FEBRUARY 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, can you tell us, in your<br />
considerations yesterday what were the main factors that<br />
led you to opt for March 24 later, was there a main<br />
factor and can you quickly sketch in the decision-making<br />
timetable you went through yesterday and last night?<br />
PM: That's a comphrehensive question. I can't, Peter,<br />
give you a weighting of the factors. It is being<br />
suggested, I see, that the troubles within the Liberal<br />
Party and the conservative parties has been a dominant<br />
factor. But just let me say this is fascinating as the<br />
continuing trauma and bitterness of the Liberal Party at<br />
the leadership and the rank and file level is. As<br />
fascinating as that is, Peter, we really couldn't be<br />
expected to sit down and wait and see that played out to<br />
its conclusion. I mean, there is a limit to one's<br />
patience in these matters. The basic fact is the one<br />
I've referred to that, of course, the Parliament has<br />
essentially run its full term. By any judgement the<br />
country has got itself, with all our assistance<br />
politicians and the media its got itself into an<br />
election mode. I don't know about you but speaking for<br />
myself I couldn't have really stood three months<br />
campaigning, mate.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Good. So I'm glad you endorse that. We would've<br />
gone collectively bonkers, so I think that was more<br />
important than anything.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Sorry Peter, there was another part of your question<br />
the process of decision-making.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could you just quickly sketch in yesterday's<br />
decision-making timetable?<br />
PM: Well, we had the our group of Ministers were<br />
meeting to go on with consideration of a number of issues<br />
that we will want to be addressing during the campaign.<br />
I did receive some reports from people who've been doing </p>
<p>some research on our behalf and got that later on in the<br />
day. But let me say this, that as distinct from some<br />
interpretations of the media, that I had a horde of<br />
minders there saying ' c'mon Hawkey, you've got to go,<br />
you've got to go'. Very unreal. I mean I really run the<br />
ship in this area. I'm indebted to all those people<br />
around me who I love and respect and admire but I'd been<br />
firming up towards this view for some time. But I do<br />
want to say, Peter, that overwhelmingly I couldn't stand<br />
the thought, and most importantly I don't think my<br />
friends out there in the Australian electorate could've<br />
stood the thought of what would've been about a three<br />
month campaign.<br />
JOURNALIST: mood of the community, do you concede<br />
that this election result is likely to be a very, very<br />
tight one or alternatively do you believe, and are you<br />
prepared to predict that you can come back with an<br />
increased majority?<br />
PM: Paul, I think it is possible, I think it is possible<br />
to come back with an increased majority. But let me say<br />
this. I'm not in any sense complacent or cocky about<br />
this campaign. I believe, for the reasons that I have<br />
outlined, that the electorate is going to, as it comes up<br />
to election day, realise that this is an extremely<br />
important election. I've expressed the view Paul before<br />
that in my judgement it's the most important election<br />
since 1949. Because I deeply believe that the decision<br />
in this election will essentially determine the sort of<br />
character of the nation that we're going to go into the<br />
21st Century with. Therefore I think that as we come up<br />
to the point where people have to cast their vote, they<br />
will for the reasons that I've gone to and that I don't<br />
repeat, see that the only option is a Hawke Labor<br />
Government. But I realise, as I say, that it's going to<br />
be a tight campaign. We're going to have to fight hard,<br />
work hard. And I give the commitment we'll do that. So<br />
I think we'll win. I think the conditions are possibly<br />
there for an improvement in our majority. But my<br />
overwhelming point is that I have no complacency.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, there was another reduction in<br />
interest rates yesterday.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: When do you expect this will filter through<br />
to home loans and do you think the banks will be damned<br />
if they do and damned if they don't, during the election<br />
campaign, move on rates?<br />
PM: Yes, well, the second point is a very good question.<br />
As to the first Niki, you know I make a point that I'm<br />
not going to attempt to say at what point the easing in<br />
monetary policy are reflected in the further move<br />
downwards in the cash rates and which has now been<br />
reflected in the banks' decision about reduction in the </p>
<p>prime rates. I'm not going to say when that will be<br />
reflected into mortgage rates. But quite clearly, and<br />
it's much more important in this sense Niki, and what I<br />
say and what's now being said again by the banks. The<br />
banks are saying that the conditions are there for a<br />
reduction in mortgage rates in the near and forseeable<br />
future. That's the statement, the attitude, the position<br />
of the banks themselves. And that's relevant. Now your<br />
second point is a very good one. In a sense they are<br />
damned if they do, damned if they don't. I mean if they<br />
were to move now I guess there would be some who were<br />
saying well there they are saying that they are<br />
indicating that they want the Hawke Government returned.<br />
If they don't do it I guess a lot of people will be<br />
saying well come on, you are paid less for your money<br />
now, you're getting better margin, why isn't that passed<br />
on now. That's a decision that the banks will have to<br />
make.<br />
SJOURNALIST: Two questions if I might Mr Hawke. The<br />
first one is, is this final term do we see at the end<br />
of this, does Bob Hawke disappear off the political<br />
landscape? Second one is you said earlier on that next<br />
week Mr Keating would announce any tax cuts that might<br />
have been negotiated. Well, I wonder if we could come<br />
clean on that. Are we going to get a tax cut?<br />
PM: Let me two good questions. The first, of course,<br />
we've been through before, Dennis. There I repeat what<br />
I've said. I will lead the Party in this election I<br />
believe, and I certainly hope to victory, and I will lead<br />
the Government through the whole of the next term and<br />
into the next election. I would expect that at some time<br />
during that next period I would retire. That's my<br />
anticipation at this stage. Now as to the second<br />
question. The language was deliberate in the sense that<br />
nothing has been finalised. The negotiations are still<br />
taking place. Quite clearly, as Paul and I have openly<br />
Ssaid, the question of tax cuts is there on the table. It<br />
is being negotiated. Let me make the point very briefly,<br />
as you know and appreciate. Here is the distinction<br />
between ourselves and our political opponents in terms of<br />
economic management. Because we have been able to<br />
demonstrate in seven years that it doesn't make any damn<br />
sense at all if you're trying to run an economy to look<br />
at the remuneration, the real income standards of wage<br />
and salary earners simply in terms of their wage and<br />
salary packet. In other words you, sensibly, if you're<br />
going to get a degree of equilibrium in the economy and<br />
allow growth both in terms of output and employment, that<br />
you don't load all the cost on the employer, that the<br />
community through the social wage, through tax adjustment<br />
and other things, picks up some of that remuneration to<br />
wage and salary earners. Now the question of relevant<br />
tax adjustments is part of that concept. That's why I<br />
mean it's not an accident I mean, you're going to hear<br />
a lot of these statistics through the campaign. You've<br />
heard them before but you'll hear more of them through </p>
<p>the campaign. It is simply no accident, Dennis, that we<br />
in seven years have had a rate of economic growth twice<br />
that of the previous seven years. It is no accident that<br />
we've had a rate of employment growth five times what was<br />
there under the conservatives. The question that you've<br />
asked me is absolutely central to that achievement. You<br />
have to make sure that in looking at the real disposable<br />
income of wage and salary earners, which is critically<br />
important, which determines their standards, how far<br />
you're able to of fload what would otherwise be<br />
inflationary, super-inflationary costs arising from<br />
excessive money wage increases, how far you can reduce<br />
that by the things that you do in regard to tax cuts and<br />
other things. I'll come to the other things just<br />
briefly. But on the tax cuts therefore it's obviously on<br />
the table. The language was not devious, it was simply<br />
yes it's on the table, it's being negotiated and whatever<br />
will be negotiated through there will be revealed by Mr<br />
Keating this week. Of course within this framework the<br />
other elements of the social wage are foundational and<br />
this is why the fiasco, the absolute fiasco of the<br />
conservatives on health is so important. I mean, the<br />
community is upset and disappointed by the<br />
irresponsibility of an Opposition which, after seven<br />
years, can't produce a health policy but their concern<br />
goes beyond just the fact of their incapacity to produce<br />
a health policy because it goes right to the very heart<br />
of economic management. Right to the heart of economic<br />
management. It's what signals the certainty of a return<br />
to the economic chaos of pre-' 83 because if wage and<br />
salary earners have the certainty of Medicare taken away<br />
from them and a position where they're going to have a<br />
very considerable outlay, net outlay, through the<br />
abolition of Medicare, then in those circumstances you go<br />
for greater money wage increases. So, here is the very<br />
heart of the difference between the conservatives and<br />
ourselves. It is no wonder that in the last year before<br />
we came to office, unemployment increased by a quarter of<br />
a million, that unemployment went through the roof and<br />
inflation went through the roof. It happened because<br />
they had no wages and no sensible relationship between<br />
what you do in the tax area, what you do in the social<br />
wage area and it is all revealed now that what they are<br />
promising to the Australia of 1990 is a replay of the<br />
economic and social disaster of the early<br />
JOURNALIST: On the social wage, Mr Hawke<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Leaked Finance documents suggest the<br />
Government is going to spend up to a $ 1 billion on<br />
outlays over the next three years if it's re-elected.<br />
How will the Government fund those commitments, and<br />
secondly, you've said that the Government has completed a<br />
wide ranging micro economic reform agenda. </p>
<p>PM: When I said complete is not the right word. I<br />
mean-JOURNALIST: Do you foresee further micro economic-<br />
PM: Yes, indeed. I'm glad for that question, the two<br />
parts of it. Firstly, you refer to this document. I<br />
mean, just let me say about that it's a working document.<br />
It's one of those things that obviously prefer hadn't<br />
leaked, but its, on its face it's a working document, an<br />
incomplete document and it doesn't meet obviously what I<br />
have said and I'll repeat it here. And it's the heart of<br />
your question. Whatever proposals I and Paul Keating and<br />
my Ministers unveil as we go through the election, the<br />
complete range of proposals that we unveil, we will at<br />
the same time as we do that through the campaign, by the<br />
time the people go into the polling booths they will see<br />
the complete funding, the complete funding of our<br />
proposals which that document didn't have on it. It's<br />
clear, it didn't, it was obviously an incomplete working<br />
document. I repeat that whatever we propose, whatever<br />
initiatives will be fully funded.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is the principle to do it from reduced<br />
surplus or<br />
PM: You will see, you will see that the way in which it<br />
will be done will be acceptable to you, it will be<br />
acceptable to all commentators. It will be a full<br />
funding and not only that, but very, very important<br />
indeed let me make the point right at the start of the<br />
campaign it will be in stark contrast, may I say, to<br />
that yawning, enormous credibility gap that the<br />
Opposition's already got. A $ 6 billion credibility gap<br />
as to where the money's coming from and you know what<br />
we're talking about there, the elements of it. Their tax<br />
proposal, the two tier proposal which is about $ 3<br />
billion, take your choice $ 2.6 billion plus in regard to<br />
health, billion in regard to roads $ 400 million in<br />
regard to education. It's of the order of $ 6 billion.<br />
Now any proposals that I and my Ministers make during<br />
this campaign, you'll see where the money's coming from.<br />
They've got to explain where $ 6 billion is<br />
JOURNALIST: The party research is showing overwhelming<br />
cynicism amongst voters. Don't both sides of politics<br />
have to take some responsibility for that and how will<br />
you be seeking to address it during the campaign?<br />
PM: Well, it's a good question. There is evidence that<br />
there is a greater degree of support, or certainly prima<br />
facie support, for the non mainstream, neither Labor nor<br />
the conservative parties and that's explained, I suppose,<br />
in a number of ways and it's certainly part of the<br />
explanation, not totally, is that not only in this<br />
country but, you know, right around the world,<br />
environmental questions have assumed, you know, some<br />
overwhelming for more people. That's part of the </p>
<p>explanation. Now as far as I'm concerned, speaking for<br />
my side of politics, you will find me during this<br />
campaign continuously, and I suppose if you've got to<br />
hear it as you travel around with me it might get tedious<br />
for you it might even get tedious for me having to say<br />
it again and again but what I will responsibly try and<br />
do is to explain the facts of achievement during this<br />
period, contrast them with the others, but also indicate<br />
our capacity to continue to meet what after all are the<br />
fundamental requirements of the people in this community.<br />
What are they? I mean, it's not rhetoric, I mean, and<br />
they'll get plenty of that including from me there'll be<br />
rhetoric, but in the end Australian families, I think,<br />
don't want to hear a politician getting up and saying<br />
' I've got concern for families, I love families' I mean<br />
who doesn't? I suppose there are some who don't, but I<br />
don't have to, sort of, put my credibility about love of<br />
family on the line. But they want to hear more than the<br />
fact that you love families. I mean, the welfare of<br />
families is not, families don't live on Mars. Families<br />
in fact have their welfare determined by whether they can<br />
get a job, whether in fact their kids are going to be<br />
educated, whether they are going to have a secure and<br />
equitable health policy so that if they get sick they can<br />
be sure they are going to be looked after. Now these are<br />
fundamentals and I am going to, for my side of politics,<br />
if there is a degree of cynicism out there, I'm going to<br />
be showing that in seven years, on these tests that<br />
matter jobs, economic growth, health, education and,<br />
importantly, on the environment. On all these things,<br />
Glenn, that matter, I'm going to show that we have<br />
delivered and have got the capacity to continue to<br />
deliver and improve our delivery. I believe that by<br />
addressing those things because in a campaign, I mean,<br />
the minds get much more wonderfully concentrated and they<br />
do start to say ' well, look it's not rhetoric, but which<br />
of these two on the record, and on their policies that<br />
they are putting before us are more likely to deliver on<br />
jobs and on health and on education, on the environment?'<br />
And I just have the feeling that by the time we get to 24<br />
March as those issues are there, and it's not just a<br />
question of achievements, but it's also a question of<br />
comparison, that whatever degree of cynicism there may be<br />
there will, to a considerable extent, be dissipated and<br />
they'll say ' well, we mightn't like everything that Hawke<br />
and his Government have done, but on these issues that<br />
matter there is just no choice but to vote Labor'<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, to go back to the earlier question<br />
on micro reform<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will that be included in the statements<br />
which you flagged, how vital do you see it on your next<br />
term's agenda and if it's not top, what do you see as the<br />
theme of your next term's agenda? </p>
<p>PM: Well, just let me pick up the micro reform part of<br />
the question first. We will be, I'll be making a<br />
statement during the campaign in regard to it and I don't<br />
want to pre-empt what I'll be saying there. As to<br />
rankings of issues, Michelle, I think it's a bit unreal<br />
to rank issues. I mean, if I were to say look that issue<br />
is most important, I think, you know, that's politically<br />
unwise. I think there are a range of issues which are<br />
important, of great importance, for some a particular<br />
issue is more important than others. I think what the<br />
electorate is going to want is to see from me and from Mr<br />
Peacock our elaboration of our policy positions and our<br />
ability to talk about achievements in regard to a range<br />
of issues which I will do, but if, and I come to the guts<br />
of your question, what's the sort of theme, I would put<br />
it in this way, that and it really, this is something I<br />
have said to you at the I think it was in the Press<br />
Club at the end of the year so I'm not manufacturing<br />
something new. I don't think that any intelligent<br />
politician and any intelligent Prime Minister will go in<br />
a election, say ' ladies and gentlemen, I've just<br />
discovered some new goals and just woke up with a new<br />
vision'. I mean, I had a vision about this country when<br />
I became Prime Minister and, as I said in an interview<br />
I've just done recently, I was in the singularly<br />
fortunate position when I became Prime Minister that,<br />
having had the trust of the two succeeding Governments,<br />
that is of the Whitlam Government and the Fraser<br />
Government, I'd been on two committees of inquiry, the<br />
Jackson Committee under the Whitlam Government and the<br />
Crawford Committee under the Fraser Government. They,<br />
both Prime Ministers appointed me to that. Now I had the<br />
opportunity when I became Prime Minister, as a result of<br />
that experience, of understanding the Australian economy<br />
and the challenges in the international environment with<br />
which we were operating. So I had a vision then that<br />
what this country had to do were these things, and what<br />
I'll be saying in the election is how we've tried to<br />
achieve them and the ways in which we'll do it more.<br />
Basic thing, Michelle, that I'll be promising to the<br />
Australian people is a commitment through macro economic<br />
and micro economic policies to the creation of a more<br />
efficient and competitive Australian economy. The future<br />
of our kids more than anything else depends upon this<br />
economy being efficient, being able to compete. And I<br />
will point to the fact that, as a result of the basically<br />
important decisions we've made, we have effected the most<br />
dramatic change ever. You don't, in seven years, double<br />
the rate of economic growth over the previous seven years<br />
without having relevant policies to produce it. So we<br />
must have an efficient, competitive economy, and,<br />
Michelle, as you know, to get to that position some hard<br />
decisions have had to be taken. I mean, you can't<br />
transform or begin the transformation of an economy to<br />
one which doubles its rate of growth and has a rate of<br />
employment growth five times faster than it had before.<br />
You can't do those things without tough decisions. I<br />
mean, let me put it this way, the $ 1.6 million new jobs </p>
<p>that we've created reflect the fact that some people in<br />
employment who could have exercised their power and got<br />
higher real wage increases, haven't got it. I mean,<br />
there are sacrifices that the community as a whole<br />
together has been prepared to make under Labor to become<br />
a more competitive economy to grow stronger. So that's<br />
the first thing, the economy must be made more<br />
competitive, more able to grow, more able to produce<br />
jobs. But, as I said, secondly, and associated with<br />
that, we have to be an Australia now I believe it<br />
should be more evidently true than when I said it in<br />
March of 1983 I said then if the economy, the<br />
Australian economy, is going to grow and seize its<br />
opportunities, it has to become more and more enmeshed<br />
with the region. You will recall my phrase of 1983,<br />
Australia has to become more enmeshed with the region,<br />
the most dynamically growing region of the world. So<br />
that is the second thing. We have to, by the range of<br />
decisions that we make, effectively become more enmeshed<br />
in the region. Thirdly, I'll be saying that my theme<br />
through this period has been and will continue to be that<br />
we cannot just judge the achievement of this society in<br />
straight economic output terms. They remain<br />
foundational, but that is not the only criterion. We<br />
have to create a society which is fairer, in which those<br />
who depend for their well-being, not simply upon their<br />
own involvement in the productive processes because there<br />
are many who can't be the aged, the young we have to<br />
be a society which is more compassionate towards them and<br />
the proof of that over the period of my Government has<br />
been, that compared with when we came to office, the<br />
outlays as a proportion of total outlays excluding public<br />
debt interest which goes on social justice programs has<br />
increased from 50 percent to 59 percent which is an<br />
increase of $ 9 billion in real terms. So you have to be<br />
a fairer society and you have to be a society which is<br />
concerned with the quality of the environment in which<br />
you live and which you are going to hand on. So that is<br />
the next element and, finally, you have to be, I believe,<br />
a society which is respected internationally. Not one<br />
which simply tags along in some irrelevant way in a world<br />
which you may wish was something like it was 30, 40,<br />
100 years ago, but to understand that you live in a<br />
world which is changing more dynamically and rapidly than<br />
in any other point in history. If Australia is going to<br />
be respected and if you are going to do the right things<br />
by the children of today, then you have to be a country<br />
which is part of shaping those processes of change and,<br />
as I have done in the area of micro economic reform,<br />
Michelle, I issue the challenge to my conservative<br />
opponents. You show any period, any period when you had<br />
the governance of this country which can begin to come<br />
within a bull's roar of the international achievements of<br />
the Hawke Labor Government. Australia now stands higher<br />
in the international councils of the world than it ever<br />
has before. So these are the themes I repeat them. A<br />
competitive, more efficient Australian economy, one which<br />
is more enmeshed in the region, but still recognising the </p>
<p>9<br />
opportunities that exist in other parts of the world, a<br />
fairer society in terms of discharging our obligations to<br />
those really in need and within that framework of the<br />
quality of society, one which is environmentally<br />
responsible and, fourthly, a country which acknowledges<br />
is part of shaping the processes of international change.<br />
Those are the themes, those issues create, provide the<br />
framework if you like within which our decisions have<br />
been made and in which we will continue to make the<br />
decisions which are necessary to meet the welfare of the<br />
Australian people.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I've got to go to Queensland<br />
JOURNALIST: One more question?<br />
PM: Two.<br />
JOURNALIST: On the environment<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
JOURNALIST: are you planning any big, major<br />
environmental package during the campaign? And secondly,<br />
did the Governor General wish you luck?<br />
PM: We will be certainly concerned with the environment.<br />
I'm not nominating any great new packages in the<br />
environment, but we will be certainly talking about it<br />
and indicating the things that we have done and the<br />
directions that we're taking. As to the second part of<br />
your question, let me say that, as you would expect, the<br />
Governor General behaved himself, conducted himself with<br />
total propriety.<br />
And may I say I hope to be seeing you all regularly<br />
during the campaign at conferences like this. I'm<br />
looking forward to them, I hope you will be. Whether it<br />
will be a feature of the campaign as a whole, I don't<br />
know. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
