<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1929</transcript-id>
    <title>68TH ANNUAL GENERAL MEETING OF WEST AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES, PERTH, W.A - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/09/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001929.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
68TH ANNUAL GENERAL MEETING OF<br />
WEST AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF MANUFACTURES<br />
PERTH, A" er~ ISEPTEMBER 1968<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, _ NfC16n Gorton<br />
Mr. President, Mr. Premier, Colleagues and Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
This, I think, is the fourth, or possibly the fifth address<br />
that I have made today in my visit to Western Australia. It will consequently<br />
not be very long and, for those of you who may have been attending any of<br />
the other occasions, I daresay it might tend to be a little repetitive.<br />
First, Sir, may I say this. In the course of an address to<br />
myself and to the Premier you said rather more nice things than nasty<br />
things, which is quite pleasant but not altogether usual, but you did, and<br />
for that I want to express my appreciation. But you also raised some<br />
interesting points and I know that since you always, quite properly and<br />
rightly believe that it is a good thing for the Chambers of Mauufactures<br />
and others to tell governments what they ought to do, so you would not<br />
object too strenuously if occasionally a representative of a government<br />
suggested to Chambers of Manufactures what perhaps they ought to do.<br />
This may have a little more relevance to this particular<br />
State of Australia at the present time than it would have for many others.<br />
You raised the question quite early in your speech of Commonwealth/ State<br />
financial relations and how important they were, with perhaps some tinge<br />
of a suggestion that Commonwealth/ State financial relations ought perhas~-<br />
to be revised. But you went on to say, and to say quite properly, that the<br />
developments that are taking place in this part of the nation today call for<br />
vast amounts of capital from overseas and also call for large amounts of<br />
capital from the State Government. And, you will agree with me, I am<br />
sure, that the level of those requirements is far more than this State<br />
Government could raise from the resources of this State and from the<br />
taxpayers of this State, if those were the only resources on which they<br />
could draw. If you would agree with me in that and I think it is<br />
incontrovertible then there is one thing at least about Commonwealth/ State<br />
financial relations with which you must agree. That is a system of uniform<br />
taxation throughout Australia under which an Australian Government collects<br />
all the income tax available and under which an Australian Government<br />
provides for the states that are developing and that cannot from their own<br />
resources get all that is needed.... this system cannot but be for the good<br />
of the smaller developing states.<br />
This is an argument, as I have said earlier today, which is<br />
not always received with universal approbation in states like New South<br />
Wales and in Victoria. But if this Chamber of Manufactures wants this<br />
State to get as much capital as possible to progress, then the system at<br />
present in existence is the best and indeed the only one. I hope, Sir, you<br />
won't go too far in endeavouring to upset the basis of Commonwealth/ State<br />
financial relations at present existing. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
You also mentioned the recent completion of the railway<br />
line, which I think was opened the other day, and just as you gave credit<br />
to that former product of Western Australia, Mr. Snedden, for pushing<br />
ahead with the immigration policy, so may I be allowed to give credit to<br />
that present product of Western Australia, Mr. Freeth. He didn't beg&amp; n<br />
this project because it was begun by Mr. Opperman, but ever since, almost<br />
ever since its inception, Mr. Freeth has been engaged in seeing that it'<br />
was done at not more than 300 or 400 per cent above the initial estimate<br />
for the cost of the railway:<br />
You have spoken, too, of your problems, not least the<br />
problem of labour, and you will I know you and the other manufacturers<br />
here realise that in examining this two thoughts are thrown up. One of<br />
them is and this is true for the whole of this nation and not just for this<br />
State that if all the labour -one has available is in employment, and by<br />
and large throughout Australia, all the employable labour is in employment,<br />
and if all the material resources that can be produced are demanded and<br />
are used, then, Sir, it is no use merely saying let us have more money<br />
and then we can do more things. Because if that were acceded to, the<br />
sole result of providing more money, all labour being employed, all<br />
material being used, would be to push up the price of labour and push up<br />
the price of materials and not in fact to get anything more done.<br />
It may well be that resources should be diverted from<br />
something to something else, but when all resources are used, that is the<br />
only way in which some new things can be done, and you as manufacturers<br />
would know that. The second problem, as you mentioned, is one for which I<br />
think all in this room, in a way, would be grateful, and that is that you are<br />
facing the problems of growth. Now, the problems of growth can be quite<br />
uncomfortable, but surely they are more exciting than the problems of<br />
stagnation or the problems of decay. Surely there is a knowledge that in<br />
applying new managerial techniques, and if it is possible and I am not<br />
suggesting it for a moment better managerial techniques to manufacturing<br />
processes, then this help s to overcome the problems of growth, and once<br />
that is overcome then new ones will arise because new growth will<br />
immediately evolve. Indeed, new growth will evolve here and nothing can<br />
stop it. But since it will evolve here, since nothing can stop it, then here<br />
is a very great responsibility, not only on governments but on those charged<br />
with the management of factories, on those charged with the supervision of<br />
the production of the goods. It is a responsibility to see that in the<br />
circumstances in which we find ourselves, every possible effort is made<br />
to ensure that these goods are produced in the most efficient way and with<br />
the most efficient management. I am sure you won't mind me saying that<br />
to you. As I said earlier, this appears self-evident.<br />
You mentioned another matter, that of tertiary education,<br />
particularly tertiary technological education, and with w~ hat you have said<br />
with one exception I completely and utterly agree. And I know, because<br />
I have worked with them on this, that your State Government completely<br />
and utterly agrees. You have created here in Wlestern Australia in your<br />
Institute of Technology, which we now call the College of Advanced Education,<br />
a technological institution separate from the universities, which is a blue<br />
print for this kind of institution throughout Australia. You have given it,<br />
your Government has given it autonomy. The courses in it will provide<br />
the sort of people whom you said manufacturers wanted. There is no reason<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
in the world why sandwich courses of the kind that you suggested should<br />
not be provided there and every reason why they should. And if there is<br />
to be some argument about whether the end product of this, the man who<br />
is the end product, should be given a degree or a diploma, well, that is<br />
an argument for another time and another place. What really counts,*<br />
surely, is not his description at the en( I but what kind of an education hp<br />
has had, what kind of a product that institution produces and what kincl<br />
of a judgment you people in this room make of that end product. Because<br />
that judgment will be translated into employing that end product at a<br />
remuneration you think he is worth, and if he is worth what I believe he<br />
will be and what I think you believe he will be, then these institutes will<br />
be, as far as parents are concerned, something which will take the place<br />
of universities, not altogether, but for those better fitted for this kind of<br />
education. Sir, it is an exciting thing to come to Western Australia.<br />
You can be sure that there will be visits from me as long as I maybe<br />
destined to remain Prime Minister, not only annually, but more often than<br />
that, just as in the past I have spent so much time here, either as Minister<br />
for the Navy or as Minister for Education. But because I have been here<br />
so much in the past, because I helped to start because I did start the<br />
Leeuwin Naval Station, because I worked so closely in the Institute of<br />
Technology and the Secondary Teachers' College and the science blocks<br />
and the technical schools which jointly the State and ourselves built here,<br />
I have been able to notice the increasing tempo of development. And on<br />
this last quick tour of your North, it was for an Australian I would not<br />
claim to be a West Australian for an Australian a most exciting thing to<br />
see what is happening in Hamersley, in Mt. Tom Price, Port Hedland, in<br />
Dampier, Kambalda, in all the places that you know so well. It was<br />
exciting not only to see what is happening but to feel in the air the vibrancy<br />
and the forward -look ing drive which is so evident and which has as one of<br />
its results the growth of Perth and the growth of industrial opportunities<br />
for those of you engaged in manufacture in Perth.<br />
Not only does this feeling of excitement exhilirate the spirit,<br />
but it makes somebody charged with the conduct of the nation's affairs realise<br />
more fully how much overseas exchange is being earned by what is going<br />
on here, and in Queensland, and in the Northern Territory and in other<br />
similar places. But here tonight I speak of Western Australia of how much<br />
this contributes to our defence capacity because so much of what we buy for<br />
defence purposes now I am sure less in the future but so much of what<br />
we buy for defence capacities now is bought from overseas, has been bought<br />
from overseas, calls for overseas exchange, which on current account we<br />
cannot earn, but which the overseas earnings you are making will help us<br />
earn. This overseas exchange contributes to our capacity to help the nations<br />
closest to us because there again it is an expenditure of overseas funds wvhich<br />
we use in order to try and raise their living standards for purposes of<br />
humanity and I suppose, if the truth were to be told, ultimately for purposes<br />
of our own. Because as their living standards rise, so will their markets<br />
become more available to us, so will their demands for our products rise,<br />
so can we join together with them in trying to improve the general prosperity<br />
of the whole region. So do we realise what is being done to help to build the<br />
population which we must have, and must have as quickly as possible,<br />
possibly for survival, certainly for arrival at that future which still lies<br />
before us. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
So these things, these things which contribute not only to<br />
what I have spoken of but, as I am sure you West Australians would be<br />
the first to agree, to contribute to the capacity of factories in Eastern<br />
States to grow and to use the foreign exchange so earned though they<br />
earn a little themselves, you know, from exports, from mining oil and<br />
from things of this kind but it does . contribute as a whole. You would<br />
agree with that and so would 1. But its importance I hope this has come<br />
a little out of what I have said is not an importance confined to this part<br />
of Australia, but because of the things I have just enumerated, an importance<br />
to the nation of Australia which, on the whole, I think most of you here,<br />
if not all of you here, wou] ld regard as being greater than any single part<br />
of the nation. Having said that, I ask you also to remember this. What<br />
you have done and what is happening here contributes, what happens in<br />
Queensland contributes, what happens in Bass Strait contributes, all of<br />
it together is going to build all of us together into a nation in which your<br />
manufactures are wanted, but that is just a small part of it. I know each<br />
one of you here wants to increase his factory, wants to increase his<br />
production, wants to improve methods, but I don't believe that that is the<br />
basic drive of any human being or of any Australian. Necessary? Yes.<br />
Basic? No. I think you want to do these things for a purpose, and that<br />
purpose is to feel that as you increase your production, as you improve<br />
your manufactures, as you improve your factories, so you are not only<br />
getting benefits from this yourselves, but so you are contributing to the<br />
sort of life your children can lead, the sort of nation you want to see.<br />
You want not only the satisfaction of achievement but the satisfaction of<br />
contribution. This, I think, is happening here. This, I think, is happening<br />
throughout Australia. How it may best be continued must, of course, be<br />
a subject of debate and it would be a pity were it not. All kinds of<br />
suggestions, Sir, I have no doubt will come from you as the President of<br />
the Chamber of Manufactures or your successor, and will come from<br />
other presidents in other states. Some of them will be sensible. Some<br />
of them may be open to question Governments themselves will make<br />
suggestions. It is possible that some of them may be sensible. It is<br />
certain that they will all be open to question.<br />
But one thing I am sure of, and forgive me if perhaps I am<br />
just a little personal as I conclude on this note. For somebody who does<br />
have a resp~ onsibility to try to see that we follow the proper path in Australia<br />
economically and in other ways, there are from time to time burdens, there<br />
are from time to time decisions to be taken which one cannot be sure are<br />
correct decisions because there is so , nLuch on one side and so much on<br />
another and one has to balance and take a choice. But the sustenance of<br />
somebody who has to do that is very great because it comes from the<br />
Australian people who I have found have been willing to accept honest<br />
mistakes, have been willing to support what they believe to be honest<br />
policies, have been in fact thoroughly decent as one would expect the<br />
Australian population in general to be.<br />
With this knowledge, and with this experience, I can but<br />
tell you this, that the Commonwealth Government, with the State<br />
Government, listening to but not necessarily taking all advice offered will<br />
do what we can to make proper judgments, to choose the priorities we think<br />
are right, to put on one side, if necessary, things that ought to be done but<br />
which cannot yet be done because things clamour with more need on the other </p>
<p>side. And I am certain that we will altogether go ahead, not in all parts<br />
of Australia perhaps as quickly as we are going in the West now, but in<br />
all parts go ahead, and that on the path on which we are moving, we will,<br />
step by step, arrive as a nation which for strength and industry, for<br />
compassion to its ill, for moral approach to world problems..... well,<br />
perhaps, be a nation better than has been known before.<br />
These words were written some time ago:-<br />
" All of the past is prelude."<br />
Sir, I translate that in my own words for Australia and Western<br />
Australia, I translate:-<br />
" All the past is prelude."<br />
into:-" You ain't seen nothing yet."<br />
And you haven't. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
