<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6891</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW FOR NBC TODAY SHOW WITH JANE PAULEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006891.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
APR. 19 ' 86 02: 33 PUSTRRLIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK<br />
TRANSCRIOT OF INTERVIEW FOR NBC TODAY SHOW WITH JANE PAULEY<br />
18 APRIL 1986<br />
SO E PROOF ONLY<br />
PAULEY: As if it were possible, world events have become<br />
even more turbulent in the last several weeks making friends<br />
all the more critical. Australia is an important friend<br />
and ally. Australia's Prime Minister, Bob Hawke, is in<br />
Washington for a visit. He joins us from there. Good<br />
morning, Mr Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Gooc morning, Jane.<br />
PAULEY: You have certainly chosen an interesting week to<br />
visit Washington. Have you been pressed to endorse the<br />
action ir Libya Monday night?<br />
PM: No,<br />
statement statement<br />
with the<br />
reflecte*<br />
PAULEY: think thi<br />
could I A<br />
air stri)<br />
PM: You<br />
statemen<br />
upon whi4<br />
opportun: I regard<br />
that we i<br />
seeing f4<br />
Jane, is<br />
terrorim by Libya<br />
conflict we haven't been pressed on that at all. We made our<br />
in Canberra before we left. We made a very clear<br />
in the United Nations on Thursday and our conversation<br />
President and other members of the Administration have<br />
I their understanding of those statements.<br />
Your statements are, well let's say ambiguous. I<br />
i Administration interprets them as support, but<br />
Lsk you directly, do you support the Administration's<br />
: e against Libya?<br />
could ask me directly, and my answer is that the<br />
shows quite clearly our understanding of the basis<br />
Ph the United States took their action. I had the<br />
6ty, as has my Foreign Minister, of seeing the evidence.<br />
the evidence as authentic and compelling. Having said<br />
rurncdee rstand that basis, we have said that we don't like<br />
as a basis of the resolution of conflict. Our concerz<br />
to look to the future and to say that the ending of<br />
the direction and the export and control of terrorism<br />
is an essential condition to bring an* end to this<br />
PAULEYt Your neighbour and mutual alliance partner New Zealand<br />
has thre atened the continuity of the ANZUS with its<br />
anti-nuc . ear government. I understand there is a significant<br />
anti-nuc; ear movement growing, even your own political party.<br />
-W calchf Sr<br />
PRIME MINISTER P. 02<br />
5934 1 </p>
<p>APR. 19 ' 86 02: 35 AUSTRALIAN DIPLOMATIC NETWORK P. 03<br />
I 2.<br />
5934<br />
PMs What Jne?<br />
PAULEYt Catching, what some have called the New Zealand fever,<br />
the anti-nuclear fever?<br />
PM: -No, that exists in our country. It exists in every free<br />
country in the world. It is not particularly allowed to<br />
-flourish behind the Iron Curtain, but in all democracies<br />
you have got it. In our country, we are quite unequivocal,<br />
as a Government and a clear majority of the Australian people,<br />
we are in favour of ANZUS. It is going to stay in place.<br />
We don't agree with the New Zealand position. If they<br />
continue their position and put it into legislation, the<br />
President of the United States and I will exchange letters<br />
of intent which will maintain the operation of the ANZUS<br />
between Ausiralia and the United States.<br />
PAULEY. Your business here, I think, is agriculture first<br />
and foremosi. Is Australia getting caught in a squeeze play<br />
between western Europe and the United States in agriculture?<br />
PM1 Yes, we are. And not only are we being hurt in the process.<br />
We have losi about a billion dollars a year in the last five<br />
years as a result of what the Europeans have done. The United<br />
States, in a sense understandably, is now going into the<br />
business of trying to out-subsidise Europe. That can't go<br />
on because in the end, the tax payers pockots and the United<br />
States are Jlust going to be dipped into more and more, which<br />
is going totally corrupt the international trading regime.<br />
And decent and efficient producers like Australia are going<br />
to suffer. And that is why I have said to the President, and<br />
he has agreed, that the United States has to take the lead<br />
with our support in the new multi-lateral trade negotiations<br />
which commente later this year, Jane, to have agriculture right<br />
up there on the agenda to see that you can have a new<br />
international trading regime where efficient producers are<br />
going to be able a reasonable price for their product.<br />
PAULEYs Prime Minister Hawke, thank you for joining us.<br />
We look forward to seeing you in Australia come next year.<br />
PM: Thank ypu and we are looking forward to seeing you all<br />
there. And Z hope you are up there against us in the Cup.<br />
ends o' ON t6 41 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
