<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6740</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER ON 2UE, ALAN JONES, 24 SEPTEMBER 1985, 9.10AM</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006740.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
PRIME MINISTER 0ON ZUE ALAN IJONES -24 September 1985<br />
E 50 E PROOF ONLY,<br />
' JONES: Well the tax package has been launched and the tax<br />
debate about its merits has begun. To see how the Prime Minister<br />
is bearing up under the challenge of selling it, he's with me<br />
this morning. Godd morning, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Good morning, Alan.<br />
JONESs Prime Minister can we just go right to the hub of the<br />
thing, do you think this is a proposal, the tax change, where<br />
there are considerable risks for you but not a lot of rewards.<br />
I'm just wondering how, for example, you respond to yesterday's<br />
Sydney morning Herald editorial which said that in three years<br />
more than a million people who are now in the 30% tax bracket<br />
will be paying tax at the marginal rate of 40%. Is that still<br />
a worry.<br />
PM: Well I think the greater worry would have been if we had<br />
done nothing because the tax system had disintegrated, Alan,<br />
and we had to take measures which were going to ensure that<br />
' avoidance and evasion loopholes-were closed off . and that we made<br />
' these steps to reduce the tax rates, marginal tax rates. Xff we<br />
hadn't done that you were just going to have an intolerable<br />
situation. So, no, I don't think that we've taken risks. I<br />
think we've taken the right measures and all the first evidence<br />
seems to be that the Australian people have--reacted accordingly.<br />
JONES: out if this brings as it suggests here, about one million<br />
people into a higher marginal rate and then they're only on about<br />
three quarters of average weekly earnings, may we not still have<br />
to contemplate a move to indirect tax to relieve that personal<br />
tax load.<br />
PM. well we've made our calculations, Alan, on the basis of<br />
what we believe is going to be necessary to relieve burdens.<br />
Those calculations have been made on the best data av~ ilable<br />
to Us. We're Confident that we've produced a situation which<br />
the great majority of Australians are going to be better off.<br />
Now we will keep the whole of economic policy under constant<br />
review.-as we have done. And it's a result of keeping that econonic<br />
policy making under cons tant; revi ew that we've produced an<br />
economic performance in this country which is the envy of the<br />
rest of the world. </p>
<p>* JONks! well can ye just take the difficult question of fringe<br />
benefits I have said i'm not opposed to a tax on fringe benefits<br />
but I wonder if we are taxing all benefits. And if I could take<br />
perhaps the most current example, and that is namely Vr Armstrong,<br />
who's received a payment of $ 500,000 and yet he's going to be<br />
taxed at 31% rather than at the marginal rates. 1s it true then<br />
that we are taxing all fringe benefits.<br />
PM. well let me say in regard to Vr Armstrong I'm simply not<br />
in a position to comment on that. As you know I've asked<br />
Mr xeid to write to me on the subject of-that separation payment<br />
and until 1 receive a reply from 14r Reid I simply can't talk<br />
about that. but going to your question more generally, what<br />
we've done in a long period of examination of this issue now<br />
is to try and ensure that all those areas where these benefits<br />
were being used as a method of emolument substitution that<br />
meant the avoidance of legitimate tax payments, that they have<br />
been covered. I guess in any tax systemn, Alan, you're not<br />
going to be able to cover every single little item that may<br />
come into that category. But i think we have done the best<br />
job that can be done in the circumstances. And I repeat, Alan,<br />
it's one which seems to have received the support of the<br />
majority of the Australian people. Because, after all, the<br />
majokity of the Australian people do the right thing and<br />
they want to see those who are not doing it brought into the<br />
same situation.<br />
JONES: Sure, I'll come to that in a moment. I agree with that.<br />
point.-But I'm just wondering in relation to taxing the fringe<br />
benefit whether some taxpayers aren't paying twice. For example,<br />
if the taxpayer's a private employer, then he's going to pay the<br />
tax on his empl. oyeee benefits. b~ ut the taxpayer is also the<br />
employer of the public sector, so isn't he also paying that<br />
tax as well.<br />
PMt the latter part?<br />
JONES: well the employer is in fact the taxpayer-when It comes to<br />
~ he public sector.<br />
PM: Well you take the individual employer in regard to the<br />
benefits of his employee it is true that we ' are taxing those<br />
In the hand of the employer and Mr Keating has been quite straightforward<br />
in his discussions with the business community and everyone<br />
about that. And we think that on the basis of the enormous increase<br />
in profits that have been affected under the policies of our<br />
Government and taking into account the very substantial benefits<br />
that we're giving to the business community through the full<br />
imputation system and no tax on dividends, that this is an impost<br />
which is reasonable for them to bear. NoV i'm not sure what you' 9re<br />
saying as to the next point though..<br />
JONES: well if I could use and example, could 1, because I am<br />
opposed personally to tax and I'm forgetting that Bob Havke:' s<br />
thel.' Prime Minister a tax on the Prime Minister's benefits.<br />
but let me just take the comparison between a Prime Minister and<br />
a managing director of a company. If the managing director had<br />
the Prime Minister's benefits that's houses, ~ cars, planes, meals,<br />
allowances and if they were taxed, don't you concede that that<br />
would be hell of a burden on his company, in ot'her words, the </p>
<p>-YONES cont private sector is going to be more burdened by<br />
this than would gay a Bob Hawke or his employer.<br />
PM: Well let me say in regard to Bob Hawke, I've made it quite<br />
clear from the beginning of this tax debate, as you know, that<br />
I seek no benefit of it at-all and I simply wan * t to say in regard<br />
to my own situation that I will expect the Tax Commissioner to<br />
treat me as is appropriate in his exercise of Jud . gement under<br />
the law. And I won't be seeking any benefits, and if I get hit<br />
in some respevt you won't hear me complaining.<br />
JONES: But you're like me, you're only an employee in that<br />
sense because we're taxing the employer. What I was saying is<br />
your employer is the taxpayer which makes the position somewhat<br />
different from the corporate world.<br />
PM; In that sense let me just say this in regard to the<br />
corporate world where the managing director or the person you<br />
I ant to think of as an equivalent, travels, and his travel is<br />
in pursuit of his business then that will be claimable. If he<br />
goes overseas on a business trip, Alan, and he is doing that<br />
in the pursuit of his business, that will be deductible.<br />
( COMMERCIAL BREAK)<br />
JONES: PM, what would you say to the case that's bee n argued in<br />
SOAte quarters that the reason the tax on fringe benefits was<br />
made payable in the hands of the employer, or by the employer,<br />
is because unions or MP's wouldn't wear it if their. taxes were<br />
paid in their own hands.<br />
PM: Well it is the case in regard to some areas of employment<br />
that Ao; literally there would be an industrial difficulty. And<br />
we had discu ssions with the employers before we did this. Now<br />
don't let me appear to misrepresent the situation and imply tha~ t<br />
the employers supported the way we've done this they don't.<br />
' ut i'm simply saying that in the discussions with the employers<br />
. h at Paul Keating and I had this point was covered and there was<br />
a recognition as to the reason why we were doing it, that there<br />
would be enormous difficulties particularly in s ' ome areas of doing<br />
the taxing the other way. Now this didn't mean the employers<br />
were supportive of the concept, but they did understand that<br />
it could create enormous problems for them if it were done<br />
the other way. Now we've:-quite readily acknowledgeo, Alan, that<br />
you can see some conceptual difficulties, if you like, in this ' way.<br />
But I want to go back to the point I made to you before, and that is<br />
that the employers of this country have prospered enormously under<br />
the policies that we've brought in. I just remind you that when<br />
we came to office the profit share in the Australian national<br />
Income was down to historically low levels of about 12 per cent.<br />
Now we've pushed it up to where it's gone back to historically<br />
high levbls of 15, 16%. And In that process the, amoun~ t of profit<br />
has increased by something like $ 6 billion-Now we have made the<br />
Judgement In the total balance of things that this is something that<br />
is reasonable to do, particularly Alan, when we've given employers<br />
Something that conservative Governments for 30 years wouldn't give </p>
<p>PM cont...: them and that's full imputation. Now they've said<br />
to us. business has said to us, that this is centrally important<br />
for their well-being, to have full imputation. We've done it.<br />
We've brought the marginal rates down from 60 to 49. so if<br />
you're going to talk about impact upon business, I thihk'if you<br />
look at it in total, a reasonable view is that the business<br />
community is going to do quite well out of this.<br />
JONES: Yes, I was just thinking actually not so touch of that<br />
but of course of the implications if people, to maintain existing<br />
benefits, anj want to maintain people in employment at those<br />
benefits, may put up prices,-then that impinges of course upon<br />
people who are buying and the sorts of people we're protecting.<br />
Because yesterday, if I can just put it to you, X read where the<br />
union movement sections 6f the union movement were saying that<br />
they are not going to surrender the benefits at all. Now I<br />
understood a tax on fringe benefit to suggest that perhaps the<br />
benefit as it was being received was more than they were<br />
entitled to. Now isn't the employer going to be in some<br />
difficulty, if he seeks to wind back the benefit he really is<br />
ioing to be in difficulty with the union. And if he doesn't he's<br />
g~ ot to pay the tax.<br />
PM: Oh well I think you'll find over time, Alan, that there will<br />
be some gradual winding back of these benefits. 1 mean I don't<br />
expect it to happen Immediately. But what you've got to understand<br />
is if you look at current salary packages that exist for people,<br />
they've been built up over a period of time and when employers 4<br />
have seen what's happening elsewhere in the market they do<br />
some matching of these things. But I think ' the corresponding<br />
thing will happen there~~ ill be n~ o doubt that in some areas<br />
there will start to be a gradual winding back of some of these<br />
benefits or that there will be substitution of cash payments,<br />
straight additions to salaries, in place of benefits. Vow it's<br />
going to take some time, Alan, for that change in composition to<br />
take place. It will work itself out in the market. But I don't<br />
think it really makes very much sense to represent this which<br />
is going to bring in,-well I think the fringe benefits paymentbrings<br />
in less than half a billion dollars, to see this in a<br />
otal emolument package of this nation, the total wage and<br />
salary package is something which is going to be dramatically<br />
overturthing. JONES: Well on that basis, and that was one of the reasons<br />
I asked you the question about the gamble at the beginning, PM,<br />
because you are committed to a $ 2000 billion tax package next<br />
year with the union movement, and this is likely to only net<br />
you about $ 800 million, and that was the nature of the gamble<br />
in part that I was talking about. Where are you going to get<br />
the other $ 1200 million from?<br />
PM:. Well yod-get. it through economic gvowth. I mkean one of the<br />
great advantages that we've got, Alan, is is a result of our<br />
economic policies and the stringent trilogy restraints that<br />
we've imposed upon ourselves, that means that with growth our<br />
revenues grow. Wd've got one of the fastest growing economies<br />
in the world. That means growth In revenue.* but we are<br />
committed by the trilogy not to allow that to become an </p>
<p>FM cont...: excessive take by way of taxation. So ye will be<br />
able out of the processes of growth to finance this. But we've<br />
given the Australian community the additional promises, Alan, that<br />
we yre not going to be increasing Government outlays at a rapid<br />
rate. we'll constrain those outlays to be within the rate of<br />
growth of the economy.<br />
JONES: Could I just tackde the capital gain thing, because it<br />
neems to me that there Is an assumption when people talk about<br />
capital gain that everyone is making a capital gain in a fairly<br />
underhand way designed to sort of make a quick quid. And I'm<br />
really thinking of the people and I'm sure that you've lived<br />
this aspect of your life as we'all have, where you hope in<br />
retirement you'll be able to realise something with a few<br />
bob, to be less dependent on Government and therefore whenJ<br />
you get 10 or 15 thousand dollars, you put it as a deposit on<br />
a second house. Now it seems to me that we are by imposing<br />
a capital gain on that, taxing investment and risk-taking and0.<br />
thrift and personal saving, when we ought to be encouraging<br />
people to do all of those things.<br />
PM:-Let me put it to you this way. I think the best answer to<br />
y'our concerns you've expressed is if you'd been in the House<br />
of Representatives when Paul Keating was delivering his speech,<br />
and when he got to his capital gains section, you've never seen<br />
such a lot of mournful faces on the other side. They were really<br />
Bating, Alan, you rotten thing Keating, why weren't you more<br />
severe, you terrible thing, you promised to be much tougher than<br />
this. And that's what they were saying virtually.<br />
JONES: Yes, I appreciate that you've watered it back.-<br />
miserable looking pack of fellows. You know I've never<br />
seen anything like it. Now that's the answer to your question.<br />
This, Alan, is not a tough capital gains tax. But it is a<br />
necessary one. Just let me make that clear. we have not been<br />
seeking to impose a capital gains tax to hurt the sort of people<br />
that you're talking about because those sort of aspirations that<br />
people have are legitimate. what ye needed to do was to bring<br />
in a capital gains tax as an instrument there to stop deliberate<br />
schemes where people were traversing the barrier and moving<br />
income into capital as part of a process of avoiding tax.<br />
JONES: Right, but still the little bloke with the second house<br />
is going to be ' taxed at 49 per cent.<br />
PM: No, but only on his real capital gain. AInd remember this,<br />
there are these elements of it if he's done * that already, his<br />
existing property as you know is not touched. Secondly, and<br />
implicit in your question, it doesn't affect the domestic home,<br />
the major home. Thirdly, it's not on nominal gains, it is only<br />
for real capital gains. in other words if the bloke has bought<br />
his house for $ 100,000 and over a period of, time it's gone up<br />
to say $ 130,000-and'. there's been 20% inflation, he's only taxed<br />
on that $ 10,000. So it's a very very mild capital gain and I'm<br />
sure that the overwhelming majority of Australians are going<br />
to say if it's necessary to have that mild capital gains tax<br />
to ensure that we have another instrument there to 13top the<br />
tax avoiders and the evaders, which we do need, then I'm sure<br />
they're going to say well we approve of that. </p>
<p>JuNrS; Sure, I don't want to labour the point, but all I'm saying<br />
is that the bloke really only does invest in that second house<br />
to get that capital gain. I mean there's not much return<br />
as you would know the rent that you get on an investment<br />
in housing, where wedesparately need housing acoOmmo~ ation<br />
being built the return on that's not great. And even when<br />
you take the real gain in that he's going to give 49 percent<br />
of that up to the Government. but it Just seems a dininoentive.<br />
PM: Let me say this, Alan, the more usual pattern with the<br />
person who invests in that second house, is that it's usually<br />
their holiday or esaLibl&amp; shedl. retirementt home that they're looking<br />
to. Now when that person sells their principal residence they're<br />
not going to pay a cent of capital gain on that. So the normal<br />
pattern of investment for Australians is not going to be<br />
adversely affected. I mean the normal of your listeners<br />
who has bought a second home, normally that's the one they<br />
go to havu their halildTnyr. and that they're going to retire to.<br />
And they sell, when they come to do that, and they sell their<br />
principal residence, they will not pay a cent of capital gain<br />
.) on that. So really for the normal pattern of Australians they're<br />
not going to be hurt in that respect. Now-as to residential<br />
buildings, there's no Government,-and I think you've bleen generous<br />
enough in the past torecognise this we've done so much in the<br />
area of residential housing, we lifted the housing/ construction<br />
industry off its knees. They were building 100,000 units a', year<br />
when we came to ortice. We'vc t Ihat up to over ISO, nOfD now.<br />
We've put enormous increases into public welfare housing and<br />
we've given the tax incentive for residential building now.<br />
We've brought that in.-So we're addressing the issue of the<br />
increase of our housing stock in other direct ways, Alan.<br />
And you've got. to have and I'd think you'd appreciate that<br />
the tax avoidance and evasion has been grossly unfair in this<br />
country to the sort of people that you're talking about the<br />
decent, honest, ordinary people and we must have the instruments<br />
there to cut that out. And that's why we've got to have that<br />
pattern. ( COMMERCIAL BREAK)<br />
JONES: Prime Minister, just finally if I might just cover that<br />
question of poverty traps because you have done quite a bit<br />
about that. Where do you see tho biggest initiative of the<br />
Government in solving the poverty trap problem.<br />
PM: Well when you say the biggest initiative, Alan, what we've<br />
done there is to pat ii.-boat $ 215 million, as you know, and that<br />
is going to help in three ways. firstly, in increasing the<br />
amount of private income that a pensioner may earn, we've<br />
increased that by $ 10 a week for single pensioners, and<br />
a week for pensioner couples. And what that means that a single<br />
pensioner now, Alan, can earn each week without affecting the<br />
pension, up to $ 40 now and for couples up to $ 70. Now our<br />
calculations are that that will mean the pension payment received<br />
by all of the 450,000 recipients who currently get a part-time<br />
pension, that will increase by up to $ 5 a week. So it's the<br />
first area. Secondly, and this is very important, we'll abolish<br />
the separate income test on rent assistance ond the calculations </p>
<p>7.<br />
PM cont...: are that that will reduce the marginal rate of<br />
Income withdrawal faced by about 7U0, U0O pensioners, and<br />
A benefit of up to about $ 15 per week will flow to about 300,000<br />
pensioners. And thirdly, and very importantly, in regard to I<br />
pensioners with children, that amount thAt a pensioner can earn<br />
without a reduction of pensions is going to be increased by<br />
$ 6 for each child. And the statement that was brought in by<br />
Paul Keating gave an example. Alan. if you take the case of<br />
supporting parent or pensioner with two children living in<br />
rental accommodation, what those measures would mean, it would<br />
mean th.~ t if riirh a poncivinr earno'd cay $ 100 a wook of private<br />
income, the social security pension plus rent assistance S s<br />
reduced by $ 44 a week. Now from November that pensioner now<br />
would lose only 18 a week, so there'd be a total gain<br />
JONES., Right $ 2b in front..<br />
PM:-So that I think is a necessary part of the package. Because<br />
we regard it as essential to reduce those higher marginal tax<br />
; ates to bring more equity, efficiency and incentive into the<br />
system. But while were doing that in the upper ranges it<br />
was very important that we looked after the least privileged<br />
section in the community who had been faced, because of these<br />
poverty traps, at times with marginal rates of tax of over<br />
100 per cent.<br />
JONES: Yes, quite, plus of course the raising of the ceiling<br />
of the non-taxable component of incomes. PM, could I just<br />
end perhaps with the ubiquitous Dr Armstrong. I'm just wondering<br />
whether you regret the fact that you didn't tell, froma the outset<br />
the House everything about his resignation.<br />
PM: I think that my reputation for straightforwardness is<br />
pretty well known. what my concern, Alan, from the beginning was<br />
not to do anything which was going to create more likelihood of<br />
political disputation in regard to an inc! ident we wanted<br />
handled in a way which wouldn't bring problems to the Bicentennial<br />
Authority or for that matter any undue hurt, personal hurt, to<br />
) Armstrong.<br />
JONES: But did you recommend that he should go.<br />
PM: I told the House quite clearly that 6n the basis of all the I<br />
information put to me, Alan, it was a clear view that the best<br />
interests of the Authority would be served if that happened.<br />
I made that quite clear.<br />
JONES-. Sure, but now you worked as a President of the AC2Tu<br />
and on a salary of about $ 27,000 a year because people in union<br />
organisations and employer organisations aren't paid a loot.<br />
PH: SAId with feeling.<br />
3ONUS6: Said with feeling. surely you wouldn't approve of a<br />
termination payment of halt a million dollars. </p>
<p>PM: But you've put your finger right on the point, unfortunately,<br />
because of the 1~ gislation brought in by our predecessors I had<br />
no authority to determine the conditions. Mr Reid made it<br />
quite clear when I indicated to him I thought that the change<br />
should take place, he said and Mr Reid was quite right in saying<br />
this, Alan, that the matter of the negotiation of the dismissal<br />
well that's not the right-word.-of the termination, the severance,<br />
of Dr Armstrong was a matter for him. It was a matter for the<br />
Authority. I had no* right to determine the conditions.<br />
JONES: z Well then has he erred in striking such a ridiculously<br />
high figure.<br />
PM. well what he put to me was the question on the contraeL<br />
that they'd negotiated. See they had negotiated the contract<br />
for Dr Armstrong in the first place, and he put to me that there'd<br />
be a question of buying out the contract-and that there were<br />
six years to go, and given the level of salaryit was gbing to<br />
be a pretty high figure. Now all I'm saying, Alan I'm not<br />
trying to av6id responsibility I didn't have the authority.<br />
JONES: Well should you have that authority.<br />
PM-Well you now againl,. if I might congratulate you, you logically<br />
go to the next point. And I've said to the media yesterday<br />
when I had a press conference with them, that I have my<br />
Department now looking at this issue, a range of options, as<br />
to whether in fact there should be a different sort of<br />
relationship between Government and the Authority whether,<br />
and I think this will appeal to your sense of humour, whether<br />
we should be deprivatising the Authority-I mean we have the<br />
Opposition pressing for privatisation and the removal of<br />
Government control, it may be the case that what we've got to<br />
look at is reversing what they did. They established this as<br />
a separate company, private company, away from Government.<br />
JONES: Could I say, though, that in this current climate<br />
if Mr Reid in the structuring of the contractual a;, rranagements<br />
for termination has been so insensitive to public opinion as<br />
to pay a bloke after a limited number of years service who<br />
) obviously wasn't doing an adequate job, half a million dollars,<br />
shouldn't then Mr Reid g0.<br />
PM: Well let me say this, that I'm waiting for a response from<br />
Mr Reid on this matter of the composition of the payment.<br />
Now I think it would be grossly unfair of me to Mr Reid to<br />
make any judgements on this issue until I have received the<br />
correspondence from Mr Reid and spoken to him. And I think<br />
you'd agree that that's the fair thing to do.<br />
JONES: Yes, I do Prime Minister. Finally could I just ask<br />
you to clarify Mr Keating said the other day that because<br />
Alan Bond's Amekica's Cup Challenge boat may have Foster's Lager<br />
printed on its outside, that the America' s Cup syndicated costs<br />
to defend the cup may be a tax deduction. is that a view you<br />
take. PM: I haven't addressed my mind to it, Alan. I will discuss<br />
the matter with my good friend and colleague, Mr Keating, and<br />
give you a considered answer.<br />
ENDS a,, l .47-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
