<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>915</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS:  P.M. 23/1964  AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATION AT MACARTHUR FUNERAL STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT, HON, SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/04/1964</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000915.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. 23/ 1964<br />
AUSTRALIAN REPRESENTATION AT MacARTHUR<br />
FUNEA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
The Prime Minister ( Sir Robert Menzies) announced<br />
today that Australia would be represented at the funeral of<br />
General of the Army Douglas MacArthur by the Australian<br />
Ambassador to the United States, Sir Howard Beale, K. B. E.,<br />
the Rt. Hon. FM. Forde and General Sir John Northcott,<br />
K. C. MG., C. B.<br />
The Head of the Australian Joint Services Staff<br />
in Washington, Major General C. Long will represent<br />
the Australian Military Services at the funeral which takes<br />
place on Saturday, April 11.<br />
Mr. Forde and Sir John Northcott will leave Sydney<br />
by air for the United States tomorrow ( Thursday) evening and<br />
will arrive in Washington on Friday morning ( Washington time).<br />
CANBERRA 8th April, 1964.<br />
BACKGROUND NOTE Mr. Forde was Minister for the Army and<br />
Deputy Prime Minister in 194+ 2, when General MacArthur arrived<br />
in Australia to establish his headquarters here and he continued<br />
to be Minister for the Army throughout the period in which General<br />
MacArthur was stationed in Australia.<br />
Sir John Northcott, a former Governor of<br />
New South Wales, was Chief of the General Staff from 1942 to<br />
1945 and was Commander of the British Commonwealth Occupation<br />
Force in Japan in 1945/ 4+ 6. Both of these appointments brought<br />
him into close contact with the late General MacArthur.<br />
J I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
