<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2569</transcript-id>
    <title>MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON CH MP - 26 APRIL 1972 - INDUSTRIAL LAWLESSNESS</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/04/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002569.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4. 0 PRIME MINISTER<br />
MACQUARIE NETWORK WEEKLY BROADCAST<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON.<br />
WILLIAM McMAHON, CH, MP. 26 APRIL 1972<br />
INDUSTRIAL LAWLESSNESS<br />
This evening I want to talk to you . about industrial lawlessness<br />
and stikes. Before I do-this I want to sketch in the background against which<br />
the problem has to be considered. I assure you that our economy i-s<br />
basically sound and that no other country has prospects quite as good.<br />
For over twenty years our production and living standards have grown.<br />
And today is only the. foundation of what we can do in the next twenrty<br />
years. Let me return to the problem of industrial unrest and lawlessness<br />
and its cost to the community in lost production and the uncertainties<br />
it creates. I will also explain what my Government is doing about it.<br />
For m-st of those twenty years Australia has had relative industrial<br />
peace. The significant exception to this rule has been the last three<br />
years. Until then, the conciliation and arbitration system worked well,<br />
and it brought a wide range of benefits to wage and salary earners,<br />
particularly those less able to look after themselves. But in the last<br />
O tahrrbeiet rayetairosn hiansd usbtereina lw eapkeeanceed . h as Itbse eenf vfieoctliavtee d suanrdv ivtahle wihs olteh rseyastteenme d. o. f<br />
During 1971 the number of working days lost in strikes. increased<br />
by 28% compared with 1970. In money terms, the loss -of wages last<br />
year was $ 45 million. Excessive wage increases and industrial trouble<br />
undoubtedly push up prices and are the root cause of inflation. Theserising<br />
prices affect everyone. They seriously worry you. This worry<br />
is understandable because most people naturally expect continual<br />
improvement in their standard of living. But they will not get it<br />
through the destruction of the arbitration system or the failure of<br />
some big unions to accept awards. This new industrial lawlessness<br />
S coincidedvith the capture of the A. C. T. U. by a leftist coalition. As<br />
Ssoon as they-secured the election. of Mr Hawke, the principles of<br />
industrial unionism followed by Mr Albert Monk-were undermined. In<br />
its-_ pJLace. we see more -political strikes and an attack on the<br />
. disciplinary provisions of the Arbitration Act. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
At the same time there are moves towards collective bargaining<br />
and more power to the big radical unions. No-one has yet invented<br />
an effective means of enforcing collective bargaining. Overseas, it<br />
has produced big and prolonged strikes. But let me explain what we<br />
are doing to help solvo these problems. Some months ago my Government<br />
ordared a thoroughgoing review of the arbitration system. We recognised<br />
the need to modernise and strengthen a system which has served this<br />
country so well for so long. We do not deny the right to strike.<br />
We do think that under our arbitration system there should be very<br />
few occasions when a strike can be justified. When disputes are<br />
legitimately settled by arbitration, the award must be obeyed.<br />
Discipline is essential to an effective arbitration system.<br />
That is why we will strengthen the disciplinary powers of the<br />
Arbitration Commission in the new legislation we introduced in the<br />
Parliament only this afternoon. That is why we will have secret<br />
S ballots. We have already strengthened the power of arbitrators in<br />
Wthe Public Service.<br />
You will remember the problems we had with postal workers and<br />
their failure to satisfactorily maintain telephone services over<br />
S the Christmas/ New Year period. Initially the union involved refused<br />
Sto take its claim to arbitration and took Dart in a course of action<br />
which disrupted telephonc services to an intolerable extent. So we<br />
introduced a hill to give the Public Service arb trator power to<br />
introduce into awards the principle cf " no work no pay". Until then<br />
we had no real power to ensure that Governnent employees satisfactorily<br />
carried out their jobs of providing you with services. We now<br />
have the power and can use it.<br />
To sum up. We reject industrial violence. We reject political<br />
unionism. We stand for conciliation and arbitration as the foundation<br />
of sound industrial relations. That's why we want conciliation and<br />
arbitration to be successful. That's why we have acted. That's why<br />
we have taken the major decisions I've mentioned; decisions made to<br />
ensure that you are provided with the services you need and richly<br />
deserve. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
