<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7497</transcript-id>
    <title>LAUNCH OF KEITH MURDOCH SOUND ARCHIVE OF AUSTRLIA IN THE WAR OF 1939-45 CANBERRA -17 FEBRUARY 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/02/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007497.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
LAUNCH OF KEITH MURDOCH SOUND ARCHIVE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA IN THE WAR OF 1939-45<br />
CANBERRA 17 FEBRUARY 1989<br />
Dame Beryl Beaurepaire,<br />
Les Hollings,<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen.<br />
Here in this commemorative courtyard we are reminded<br />
forcefully of the enormous sacrifice Australia has paid in<br />
time of war.<br />
The Roll of Honour lists the names of Australian men and<br />
women who died in the service of our country an awesomfe<br />
list outlining in stark human terms the magnitude of<br />
Australia's contribution to the defence of liberty and<br />
democracy.<br />
Australia, and possibly New Zealand and Canada, are<br />
remarkable among nations in that we know, by name, every<br />
individual who has died on a battlefield for the nation.,<br />
And of course the records held here at the Australian War<br />
Memorial tell us a great deal more about Australia's war~<br />
time experiences.<br />
But there has always been an imbalance in the Memorial'S<br />
archival holdings.<br />
There is a rich vein of letters, diaries and other documents<br />
about Australians in the First World war.<br />
But for the Second World War, a combination of a decline in<br />
letter writing and more strictly enforced secrecy rules<br />
means that fewer first hand records exist.<br />
It's simply much harder to document what it was like to be<br />
an Australian serviceman or woman in the Second World War.<br />
It is that problem which the Keith Murdoch Sound Archive is<br />
designed to rectify.<br />
This Archive will capture for posterity the tales of<br />
hundreds of ordinary men and women caught up in the<br />
extraordinary events of war. </p>
<p>The Archive will be made up of some 500 interviews drawn<br />
from all the services, all ranks and the many theatres in<br />
which Australians served.<br />
It will record in individual ways the personalities, the<br />
experiences, and the feelings of those who served their<br />
country so well.<br />
I believe that many of the people already approached for<br />
these interviews had to be coaxed into relating their<br />
experiences. Some of them have said that in recording these interviews<br />
for the archive they told their stories for the first time.<br />
Their reticence is understandable but I think they too<br />
modestly underestimate how important it is that their<br />
stories are told.<br />
If their memories are not recorded now we risk losing them<br />
forever and that would indeed be an irreplaceable and<br />
tragic loss.<br />
This Sound Archive will be housed in the Memorial's Research<br />
Centre which is already well-known for its magnificent<br />
archives of documents and photographs.<br />
It will be invaluable to historians, film-makers,<br />
researchers and members of the public who want to learn more<br />
about those who served their country.<br />
It will also provide material for incorporation in the<br />
Memorial's galleries to give a special personal insight into<br />
those displays.<br />
I congratulate you, Dame Beryl, and your Council for your<br />
foresight in pursuing this worthy objective. The War<br />
Memorial has long sought to fill the gaps in the records of<br />
the Second World War and you can rightly be satisfied that<br />
that task is now being achieved.<br />
I also congratulate and express my gratitude to News Limited<br />
for its generosity in making possible the creation of the<br />
Archive. It is most appropriate that News Limited, through Rupert<br />
Murdoch, should provide sponsorship for the Keith Murdoch<br />
Sound Archive.<br />
Sir Keith Murdoch, as a journalist and as a newspaper<br />
proprietor, was a man of great influence in Australian<br />
history, including in two world wars.<br />
As a war correspondent during the First World War, he was<br />
severely critical of the Dardanelles campaign which<br />
eventually led to the recall of the British commander from<br />
the war zone. </p>
<p>3.<br />
As Director-General of Information during the Second World<br />
War he also made an important contribution to Australia.<br />
I hope News Limited's generous support will be matched by<br />
others in the private sector to help ensure that the<br />
Australian War Memorial maintains its reputation for<br />
excellence and innovation.<br />
In opening the Sound Archive now, and accepting it on behalf<br />
of the Australian people, I want finally to thank those<br />
people whose voices have been and will be recorded for<br />
posterity. Some of them are here today. Let me express my<br />
thanks to you, and through you to your fellow archivists,<br />
for your participation in this vital national project. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
