<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3198</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY TEH PRIME MINISTER THE HON E.G. WHITLAM, QC, MP, TO THE LABOR WOMEN&#039;S CONFERENCE OF THE A.L.P., TRADES HALL, SYDNEY, SUNDAY 31 MARCH 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003198.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1II<br />
THE SENATE v THE PEOPLE<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME IINISTER,<br />
THE HON. E. G. WHITLAM.,<br />
TO THE LABOR WOMEN'S CONIFERENCE OF THE A. L. P.,<br />
TRADES HALL, SYDNEY,<br />
SUNDAY 31 MARCH 1974<br />
THE SENATE ELECTION ON 18 MAY WILL BE THE FIFTH<br />
SENATE ELECTION SINCE I HAVE BEEN LEADER OR DEPUTY LEADER<br />
OF THE PARTY; IT WILL BE THE EIGHTH SENATE ELECTION,<br />
AND THE ELEVENTH ELECTION FOR EITHER HOUSE, SINCE I<br />
BECAME A MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT. I HOPE YOU WILL NOT<br />
THINK IT MERE GALLANTRY ON MY PART IF I CLAIM TO HAVE<br />
A LONGER MEMORY OF POLITICAL EVENTS THAN MOST OF THE<br />
LADIES IN THIS ROOM. THE FACT IS THAT I CANNOT RECALL<br />
A MORE IMPORTANT SENATE ELECTION THAN THE ONE WE FACE NOW.<br />
THE ISSUES AT STAKE, THE IMPLICATIONS FOR THE PARLIAMENT,<br />
FOR THE PEOPLE, FOR DEMOCRACY ITSELF, WILL BE CRUCIAL<br />
AND FAR-REACHING, FOR THE FIRST TIME, AND PERHAPS FOR<br />
THE ONLY TIME, WE WILL BE FIGHTING A SENATE CAMPAIGN<br />
OF GENUINE AND HISTORIC SIGNIFICANCE. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I SAY THIS NOT MERELY BECAUSE OF THE REFERENDUMS<br />
TO BE HELD WITH THE SENATE ELECTION, IMPORTANT AS THESE<br />
REFERENDUMS ARE. CERTAINLY THEY WILL GIVE AN ADDED<br />
MEANING, AN ADDED DIMENSION, AN ADDED ZEST TO OUR<br />
CAMPAIGN. RATHERj I BASE MY CLAIM ABOUT THE IMPORTANCE<br />
OF THIS ELECTION ON THE UNIQUE AND SPECIAL CHARACTER<br />
OF THE ISSUES OR RATHER, THE CENTRAL ISSUE.<br />
THIS WILL BE A CAMPAIGN, NOT JUST FOR THE SENATE,<br />
BUT ABOUT THE SENATE. THE PEOPLE WILL BE PASSING<br />
JUDGMENT ON THE ROLE, THE RECORD AND THE RELEVANCE<br />
OF THE SENATE ITSELF. THEY WILL BE PASSING JUDGMENT<br />
ON THE OPPOSITION IN THE SENATE AND THE RECORD AND<br />
MOTIVES AND CREDIBILITY OF THE OPPOSITION AS A WHOLE-FOR<br />
MAKE NO MISTAKE, THIS WILL BE VERY MUCH AN ELECTION ABOUT<br />
THE OPPOSITION, IT IS THE OPPOSITION WHOSE PERFORMANCE<br />
IS IN QUESTION. IT IS THE OPPOSITION WHOSE GOOD FAITH<br />
AND EFFECTIVENESS WE MUST EXAMINE. IS IT UNITED?<br />
IS IT BELIEVABLE? DOES IT SPEAK WITH ONE VOICE?<br />
IS IT MOTIVATED BY CONCERN FOR THE NATIONAL INTEREST<br />
OR MERELY BY SPITE, BY RESENTMENT AND A LUST TO RETURN<br />
TO POWER? THE RECORD OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THIS ELECTION<br />
WILL BE OF GREAT IMPORTANCE; THE RECORD OF THE OPPOSITION<br />
AND THE RECORD OF THE SENATE WILL BE OF SUPREME<br />
IMPORTANCE, IT IS THAT RECORD THAT I WANT TO EXAMINE<br />
TODAY. IT IS A PATHETIC AND CONTEMPTIBLE RECORD;<br />
IT IS A PATHETIC AND CONTEMPTIBLE OPPOSITION,<br />
e p ,/ 3 </p>
<p>-3-<br />
IN DECEMBER 1972 SIXTEEN MONTHS AGO THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE ELECTED A LABOR GOVERNMENT WITH A<br />
DECISIVE MAJORITY IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES,<br />
THE POLICIES ON WHICH THE GOVERNMENT WAS ELECTED HAD BEEN<br />
CLEARLY STATED, THEY HAD BEEN FORMULATED OVER MANY<br />
YEARS IN THE PUBLIC DECISION-MAKING FORUMS OF THE PARTY,<br />
MOST OF THOSE POLICIES WERE PUT TO THE PEOPLE NOT ONCE,<br />
BUT TWICE, IN THE ELECTIONS OF 1969 THERE WAS A SWING<br />
OF MORE THAN 6% TO THE LABOR PARTY, IN 1972, WHEN A<br />
SIMILAR PROGRAM WAS SUBMITTED TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE,<br />
THERE WAS A FURTHER SWING TO LABOR OF THE ORDER OF 2,7,%<br />
THOSE TWO ELECTIONS SAW AN EMPHATIC AND RE-ITERATED EXPRESSION<br />
OF PUBLIC CONFIDENCE IN THE POLICIES OF A LABOR GOVERNMENT,<br />
IN THE MONTHS SINCE THE LAST ELECTION THE GOVERNMENT<br />
HAS ACTED WITH ALL POSSIBLE SPEED TO IMPLEMENT THE<br />
POLICIES FOR WHICH THE PEOPLE VOTED,<br />
WE HAVE MADE GREAT PROGRESS TOWARDS A MORE JUST,<br />
MORE PROSPEROUS AND MORE HUMANE SOCIETY, MUCH OF OUR<br />
PROGRAM HAS BEEN IMPLEMENTED,. IWE HAVE DONE MANY<br />
THINGS THAT WE PROMISED TO DO; WE HAVE DONE NOTHING THAT<br />
WE DID NOT PROMISE TO-DO, IT IS TRUE THAT THERE HAVE BEEN<br />
UNFORESEEN FRUSTRATIONS AND UNPREDICTABLE DISTRACTIONS;<br />
BUT FOR THE MOST PART ACTING WITH GOOD FAITH, ACTING<br />
WITH DETERMINATION AND VIGOR, BY SHEER HARD WORK AND<br />
A VOLUME OF PARLIAMENTARY BUSINESS THAT SURPASSES ALL<br />
RECORDS WE HAVE SOUGHT TO DISCHARGE IN FULL MEASURE<br />
THE TRUST PLACED UPON US BY THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, a / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
FOR ALL OUR ACTIVITY, FOR ALL OUR DETERMINATION<br />
TO GIVE EFFECT TO THE PEOPLE'S WILL, THERE ARE GREAT<br />
AND IMPORTANT THINGS WE HAVE BEEN PREVENTED FROM DOING,<br />
THE SENATE HAS BLOCKED AND DELAYED, AMENDED AND<br />
FRUSTRATED SIGNIFICANT PARTS OF OUR PROGRAM,<br />
NOW THERE ARE TWO THINGS ABOUT THE SENATE<br />
THAT I ASK YOU TO REMEMBER. THE FIRST IS THAT NO PARTY<br />
HAS A MAJORITY IN THE SENATE, iJO PARTY, AS THE SENATE<br />
NOW STANDS, CAN CLAIM A MANDATE IN THAT CHAMBER,<br />
IT IS TRUE THAT THE COMBINED NON-LABOR PARTIES<br />
THAT CURIOUS COLLECTION OF FRUSTRATED LIBERALS,<br />
COUNTRY PARTY BACKWOODSMEN, SPLINTER GROUPS AND<br />
DISAFFECTED INDEPENDENTS WHO SUPPORT THEM<br />
CAN MUSTER A MAJORITY; OF COURSE THEY CAN,<br />
BUT IT IS MEANINGLESS TO SUGGEST THAT THIS CONSTITUTES<br />
AN OPPOSITION MAJORITY IN THE TRUE SENSE, OR THAT ANY<br />
MANDATE EXISTS FOR A POLICY OF OBSTRUCTION. </p>
<p>AND THAT BRINGS ME TO THE SECOND ESSENTIAL<br />
FACT ABOUT THE SENATE AS IT STANDS, THE SENATORS WHO<br />
HAVE BLOCKED AND FRUSTRATED THE GOVERNMENT'S PROGRAM<br />
WERE ELECTED YEARS BEFORE THE GOVERNMENT IN THE HOUSE<br />
OF REPRESENTATIVES, HALF OF THEM WERE ELECTED IN<br />
DECEMBER 1967; THE REST OF THEM WERE ELECTED IN<br />
DECEMBER 1970, TRULY THEY ARE VOICES FROM THE PAST;<br />
TRULY THEY ARE YESTERDAY'S MEN, YET THESE SENATORS,<br />
SOME OF THEM ELECTED U YEARS AGO, PRESUME TO SIT IN<br />
JUDGMENT ON A GOVERNMENT WHOSE POLICIES HAVE BEEN<br />
TWICE ENDORSED BY THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WITHIN THE<br />
PAST 42 YEARS, I CAN THINK OFNO MORE FLAGRANT<br />
ANACHRONISM THAT THIS, I CAN THINK OF NOTHING THAT<br />
MAKES A GREATER MOCKERY OF A SUPPOSEDLY DEMOCRATIC<br />
LEGISLATURE, </p>
<p>-6-<br />
I HAVE SAID THAT THE PERFORMANCE AND<br />
CAPACITY OF THE OPPOSITION IS CENTRAL TO THIS<br />
SENATE CAMPAIGN, SIXTEEN MONTHS AGO THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
PEOPLE PASSED JUDGMENT ON OUR OPPONENTS AS A GOVERNMENT;<br />
ON 18 MAY THEY WILL HAVE THEIR FIRST OPPORTUNITY TO<br />
JUDGE THEM AS AN OPPOSITION, I MUST SAY THE PROSPECT<br />
IS A DAUNTING ONE, FOR THE LIFE OF ME I CAN'T DECIDE<br />
WHETHER THEY ARE WORSE IN OPPOSITION OR WORSE IN<br />
GOVERNMENT. AT LEAST THEY CAN'T DO AS MUCH HARM<br />
IN OPPOSITION, IN GOVERNMENT THEY ARE EXPERT IN<br />
DAMAGING THE COUNTRY, BUT IN OPPOSITION THEY HAVE<br />
A POSITIVE GENIUS FOR DAMAGING THEMSELVES,<br />
ON BALANCE I THINK I PREFER THE LATTER, ,/ 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
I KNOW SOME OF YOU MUST BE AS CONFUSED AS I<br />
AM ABOUT RECENT EVENTS IN THE OPPOSITION PARTIES,<br />
THE FACT IS THAT WE HAVE NEVER HAD A MORE CONFUSED,<br />
MORE DIVIDED, MORE DISCREDITED OR MORE DEBILITATED<br />
OPPOSITION THAN WE HAVE NOW, I THINK WE CAN BEST<br />
APPROACH THEIR PROBLEMS ON A STATE BY STATE BASIS<br />
THAT IS A GOOD SENATE PRINCIPLE, AFTER ALL BUT<br />
THERE ARE ONE OR TWO GENERAL QUESTIONS TO CLEAR UP<br />
FIRST, FOR EXAMPLE, WHICH PARTIES BELONG TO THE<br />
OPPOSITION AND WHICH DO NOT? I AM NOT CLEAR WHETHER<br />
THE DLP BELONGS TO THE OPPOSITION, MR ANTHONY<br />
APPARENTLY THINKS IT DOES, BUT SIR CHARLES CUTLER<br />
IN NEW SOUTH WALES THINKS THE DLP IS FINISHED,<br />
NEVERTHELESS, THE DLP HAS MERGED WITH THE COUNTRY<br />
PARTY IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA AND QUEENSLAND, AND WHAT<br />
IS THE POSITION OF THE AUSTRALIA PARTY, WHICH MR SNEDDEN<br />
HAS INVITED TO JOIN FORCES WITH THE LIBERALS?<br />
OF COURSE IT WAS AN EXCELLENT IDEA AND IT WAS WELL<br />
RECEIVED BY EVERYONE IN THE LIBERAL PARTY EXCEPT<br />
MR MALCOLM FRASER, MR FRASER DECLARED THAT THE<br />
DIFFERENCES BETWEEN THE AUSTRALIA PARTY AND LIBERAL<br />
PARTY WERE " TOTALLY UNBRIDGEABLE". SENATOR<br />
HANNAN SEEMS TO THINK THAT THE DIFFERENCES IN THE<br />
LIBERAL PARTY ARE ALSO TOTALLY UNBRIDGEABLE, I,/ 8 </p>
<p>0<br />
SENATOR HANNAN HAS FORMED HIS OWN PARTY TO GET RID OF<br />
THE TRENDIES IN VICTORIA, AND FIR STEELE HALL HAS FORMED<br />
HIS OWN PARTY TO ATTRACT MORE TRENDIES IN SOUTH AUSTRALIA,<br />
I AM STILL NOT SURE WHETHER LIBERAL VOTERS IN QUEENSLAND<br />
WILL BE VOTING FOR THEIR OWN SENATE TEAM OR FOR A JOINT<br />
TICKET WITH THE COUNTRY PARTY OR IS IT THE INATIONAL<br />
COUNTRY PARTY? OR THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE, AS THEY CALL<br />
IT IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA?<br />
I MUST SAY THERE ARE SERIOUS DILEMMAS FOR<br />
OPPOSITION SUPPORTERS IN THIS SITUATION; IF THE DLP<br />
MATES WITH THE COUNTRY PARTY AND THE AUSTRALIA PARTY<br />
MATES WITH THE LIBERALS AND THE LIBERALS MATE WITH THE<br />
COUNTRY PARTY, DOES THIS MEAN THAT THE DLP HAS MERGED<br />
WITH THE AUSTRALIA PARTY? DOES SENATOR HANNAN SUPPORT<br />
THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE? DOES GORDON BARTON GIVE HIS<br />
PREFERENCES TO THE IIATIONAL LIBERAL PARTY? DOES<br />
MALCOLM FRASER SUPPORT STEELE HALL? DOES THE DLP GIVE<br />
ITS PREFERENCE TO CUTLER OR COURT CHARLES THE FIRST<br />
OR CHARLES THE SECOND? IT MAY SIMPLIFY MATTERS IF I<br />
LIST ALL THE OPPOSITION PARTIES, NOT NECESSARILY IN ORDER<br />
OF IMPORTANCE. AT LAST COUNT WE HAD THE LIBERAL PARTY,<br />
THE COUNTRY PARTY, THE LIBERAL COUNTRY LEAGUE, THE<br />
NATIONAL COUNTRY PARTY, THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE, THE<br />
NATIONAL LIBERAL PARTY, THE DLP, THE AUSTRALIA PARTY<br />
AND THE STEELE HALL PARTY, I HEARD MR ANTHONY SAY THE<br />
OTHER DAY THAT HE WANTED A SINGLE ANTI-SOCIALIST ALLIANCE<br />
THROUGHOUT AUSTRALIA. I CAN ONLY SAY THAT AT THE RATE<br />
THINGS ARE GOING, WE'LL SOON HAVE MORE ANTI-SOCIALIST<br />
PARTIES THAN ANTI-SOCIALIST SENATORS. / 9 </p>
<p>DOES ANYONE SERIOUSLY SUGGEST THAT THIS<br />
SQUABBLING COLLECTION OF BITTER AND DISAPPOINTED MEN,<br />
THESE BRAWLERS AND BACKBITERSi TRENDIES AND NON-TRENDIES,<br />
PHONY PROGRESSIVES AND UNREPENTANT REACTIONARIES, HAVE<br />
ANY CLAIM TO THE CONFIDENCE OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE?<br />
WHO SPEAKS FOR THE OPPOSITION? WHO LEADS THE OPPOSITION?<br />
YOUR GUESS IS AS GOOD AS MINE. JUDGING FROM THE PRESS<br />
IN RECENT WEEKS, THEIR MOST PROLIFIC AND CONSISTENT<br />
PROPAGANDIST IS SIR ROBERT M'ENZIES. ONLY LAST WEEK<br />
PlR fICMAHON WAS-LAMENTING IN THE PRESS THAT HE WISHED<br />
HIS PARTY HAD DONE AS MUCH FOR EDUCATION AS WE HAVE.<br />
NIOT LONG AGO HE SAID IT WAS A GREAT PITY THAT HIS<br />
GOVERNMENT HAD NOT ABOLISHED CONSCRIPTION AND SET UP<br />
THE INDUSTRIES ASSISTANCE COMMISSION. I REMIND YOU THAT<br />
WHEN THE LEGISLATION FOR THAT COMMISSION WAS BEFORE THE<br />
PARLIAMENT THE LIBERALS SUPPORTED IT WHILE THEIR SO-CALLED<br />
ALLIES IN THE COUNTRY PARTY OPPOSED IT. AND IF YOU TAKE<br />
THAT OTHER GREAT LANDMARK IN THE GOVERNMENT' S FIRST YEAR<br />
OF OFFICE OUR ADDITIONAL GRANTS TO SCHOOLS IT<br />
WAS THE COUNTRY PARTY THAT SUPPORTED IT WHILE THE LIBERALS<br />
VOTED AGAINST IT. WHAT UNITY! WHAT A COALITION!<br />
WHAT A COMMENTARY ON AN OPPOSITION THAT IN 16 MONTHS<br />
HAS PRODUCED NOT A SINGLE NEW POLICY, NOT A SINGLE FRESH<br />
AND CONSTRUCTIVE IDEA. VIE ALL KNOW WHAT 111R SNEDDEN<br />
IS AGAINST[ HE IS AGAINST EVERYTHING.. BUT WHAT IS<br />
MR SNEDDEN M~? / lo </p>
<p>10<br />
HE'S FOR REDUCED GOVERNMENT'SPENDING, BUT WHAT<br />
GOVERNMENT SPENDING DOES HE WANT TO REDUCE?<br />
HE DOESN'T SAY. HE SIMPLY WANTS US TO SPEND MORE<br />
ON DEFENCE, MORE ON UNNECESSARY SUPERPHOSPHATE BOUNTIES,<br />
MORE ON PRIVATE SCHOOLS THAT ARE ALREADY WELL OFF,<br />
THE CONSISTENT THEME OF THE OPPOSITION IS A NEGATIVE<br />
THEME. THE CONSISTENT VOICE OF THE OPPOSITION IS A<br />
WHINGER'S VOICE. THEY ARE A PARTY OF NARKS AND KNOCKERS<br />
AGAINST EVERYTHING AND IN FAVOUR OF NOTHING.<br />
I BELIEVE THERE IS A CLEAR REASON FOR THE CHRONIC<br />
DISUNITY AND DISARRAY IN THE OPPOSITION PARTIES. AND IT<br />
IS THIS: THEY HAVE NOT ACCEPTED THE FACT OF THEIR DEFEAT.<br />
THEY GO ON BELIEVING THAT THE VERDICT OF THE PEOPLE IN<br />
DECEMBER 1972 WAS A TEMPORARY ABERRATION; THAT SOONER<br />
OR LATER NO MATTER HOW DIVIDED THEIR RANKS, HOW BARREN<br />
THEIR IDEAS, HOW MUDDLED THEIR POLICIES ON BASIC ISSUES<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WILL RETURN THEM TO OFFICE. THEY<br />
HAVE A DEEP CONTEMPT, NOT ONLY FOR THE WILL OF THE PEOPLE,<br />
BUT FOR THE GOOD SENSE OF THE PEOPLE. THEY BELIEVE THEY<br />
CAN FLOUT THE CLEARLY EXPRESSED WISH OF THE ELECTORATE FOR<br />
A PROGRAM OF ORDERED CHANGE AND SOCIAL REFORM, FOR<br />
ENLIGHTENED POLICIES TOWARDS OUR NEIGHBOURS, FOR SOCIAL<br />
JUSTICE AT HOME AND MORE MATURE AND INDEPENDENT POLICIES<br />
ABROAD, ,/ 11 </p>
<p>11-<br />
THE SENATE HAS BEEN'THE GREAT INSTRUMENT<br />
FOR THIS CAMPAIGN OF OBSTRUCTION. SINCE WE TOOK OFFICE<br />
THE SENATE HAS REJECTED 15 BILLS, DEFERRED ANOTHER<br />
AND AMENDED 21, I LIST THE 15 BILLS THEY HAVE<br />
REJECTED:<br />
COMMONWEALTH ELECTORAL TWO BILLS;<br />
CONCILIATION AND ARBITRATION;<br />
REPRESENTATION TWO BILLS;<br />
LAND ACQUISITION ( AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY);<br />
SEAS AND SUBMERGED LANDS ( ROYALTY ON MINERALS);<br />
HEALTH INSURANCE;<br />
HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION;<br />
AND, FOUR CONSTITUTION ALTERATION BILLS.<br />
IT IS NOT DIFFICULT TO FIND A COMMON THEME IN THEIR<br />
OBSTRUCTIVE TACTICS. THE OPPOSITION MAY LACK A COMMON<br />
VOICE BUT IT HAS NEVER LACKED A COMMON CAUSE; AND THAT<br />
CAUSE IS THE DEFENCE OF VESTED INTERESTS. ,/ 12 </p>
<p>12-<br />
IN DEFENCE OF THESE VESTED INTERESTS THEY<br />
REJECTED THE DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLE OF EQUAL ELECTORATES,<br />
THEY COMPLAIN ABOUT INDUSTRIAL UNREST IN THE COMMUNITY,<br />
YET THEY BLOCKED OUR ATTEMPTS TO MODERNISE AND<br />
DEMOCRATISE THE TRADE UNION MOVEMENT AND PROMOTE THE<br />
CONDITIONS FOR GENUINE INDUSTRIAL STABILITY, THEY<br />
SOUGHT TO DENY REPRESENTATION IN THE SENATE TO THE<br />
PEOPLE OF THE NORTHERN TERRITORY AND THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
CAPITAL TERRITORY; THEY SOUGHT TO DENY TO LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENT DIRECT ACCESS TO NATIONAL REVENUES AND BORROWINGS,:<br />
THEY PRESERVED FOR FOREIGN MINING INTERESTS THE RIGHT<br />
TO EXPLOIT OUR OFF-SHORE RESOURCES; THEY FOUGIIT TO<br />
PRESERVE THE INEQUITY AND INEFFICIENCY OF AN ANTIQUATED<br />
HEALTH SERVICE, BY SHELVING THE TRADE PRACTICES BILL<br />
THEY LEFT THE DOOR OPEN TO MONOPOLIES AND CARTELS TO FIX<br />
PRICES, ORGANISE CARTELS AND EXPLOIT THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
CONSUMER, BY SHELVING THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION BILL THEY BLOCKED THE MOST<br />
EFFECTIVE INSTRUMENT FOR ENSURING AUSTRALIAN CONTROL OF<br />
OUR INDUSTRIES AND DEVELOPING NEW INDUSTRIES, THEY HAVE<br />
LEFT THE DOOR OPEN TO FOREIGN TAKEOVERS AND FOREIGN<br />
CONTROL OF THE AUSTRALIAN ECONOMY, YET FOR ALL THE<br />
LEGISLATION I HAVE MENTIONED THE GOVERNMENT HAD A<br />
CLEAR MANDATE FROM THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, </p>
<p>13<br />
DESPITE THE EFFORTS OF THE SENATE TO OBSTRUCT<br />
OUR REFORMS, THERE IS ONE AREA IN WHICH THEY ARE POWERLESS,<br />
THEY HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO PREVENT US PUTTING OUR REFERENDUM<br />
PROPOSALS TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE AT THE SAME TIME AS<br />
THE SENATE ELECTIONS, THIS WAS NOT FOR WANT OF TRYING,<br />
THE SENATE WAS DETERMINED THAT WHATEVER THE SENATE MIGHT<br />
THINK OF OUR REFERENDUMS, THE PEOPLE WOULD BE DENIED<br />
AN OPPORTUNITY TO DECIDE THE ISSUES FOR THEMSELVES,<br />
THE CONSTITUTION, HOWEVER, ENABLES REFERENDUMS TO BE<br />
PUT TO THE PEOPLE EVEN IF THE SENATE OBSTRUCTS THEM.<br />
THAT IS WHAT WE ARE DOING, OUR REFERENDUMS ARE<br />
DESIGNED TO GIVE A NEW DEAL TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND<br />
TO ENTRENCH IN THE CONSTITUTION THE BASIC DEMOCRATIC<br />
RIGHTS OF THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE, I SUMMARIZE WHAT<br />
OUR PROPOSALS SEEK TO ACHIEVE:<br />
1. i, To ENTRENCH THE RIGHT TO VOTE FOR ALL<br />
ADULT CITIZENS IN BOTH STATE AND AUSTRALIAN<br />
ELECTIONS,<br />
2, To ESTABLISH THE DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLE FOR<br />
BOTH THE AUSTRALIAN AND STATE PARLIAMENTS<br />
THAT MEMBERS SHOULD REPRESENT EQUAL NUMBERS<br />
OF PEOPLE,<br />
3, To ENSURE THAT STATE UPPER HOUSES ARE ELECTED<br />
DIRECTLY BY THE PEOPLE, / 14 </p>
<p>1' 4<br />
4. TO GRANT CITIZENS IN THE l'IlORTHERN TERRITORY<br />
AND THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY THE<br />
RIGHT TO VOTE IN REFERENDUMS.<br />
TO ENSURE THAT THE PARLIAMENT OF AUSTRALIA<br />
REFLECTS THE POPULAR WILL AT THE TIME-THAT THE<br />
PEOPLE OF AUSTRALIA DETERMINE THEIR GOVERNMENT,<br />
THE SECOND BROAD OBJECTIVE OF OUR REFERENDUM<br />
PROPOSALS IS TO BALANCE THE FUNCTIONS AND FINANCES. OF<br />
THE THREE LEVELS OF GOVERNMENT. THREE FURTHER PROPOSALS<br />
WILL REMOVE CONSTITUTIONAL OBSTACLES TO THE RATIONAL<br />
CO-ORDINATION OF INTERGOVERNMENT RELATIONS.<br />
THEY WILL ENABLE US:-<br />
1. TO FACILITATE THE REFERENCE OF LEGISLATIVE<br />
POWERS FROM THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT TO THE<br />
STATES AND VICE VERSA IF BOTH-AGREE THAT THE<br />
OTHER LEVEL OF GOVERNMENT WOULD EXERCISE<br />
THOSE POWERS MORE EFFECTIVELY.<br />
2. TO ENHANCE THE ROLE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT BY<br />
EXTENDING THE PROVISIONS IN THE CONSTITUTION<br />
WHICH GOVERN THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT' S<br />
RELATIONSHIP WITH STATE GOVERNMENTS TO LOCAL<br />
GOVERNMENTS AS WELL.<br />
3. To INVOLVE THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE MORE CLOSELY<br />
IN DETERMINING THE BALANCE OF FUNCTIONS BY<br />
FACILITATING ALTERATIONS TO THE CONSTITUTION. </p>
<p>15<br />
NOW TWO OF THESE PROPOSALS THE ONE FOR SIMULTANEOUS<br />
ELECTIONS OF THE SENATE AND THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<br />
AND THE ONE FACILITATING AMENDMENTS TO THE CONSTITUTION<br />
WERE RECOMMENDED 1C YEARS AGO IN THE REPORT OF THE<br />
CONSTITUTIONAL REVIEW COMMITTEE SET UP UNDER SIR ROBERT<br />
MENZIES. THEY COULD HAVE BEEN PUT TO THE PEOPLE<br />
AND THEY SHOULD HAVE BEEN PUT TO THE PEOPLE AT ANY<br />
TIME SINCE THEN. THE PROPOSAL TO FACILITATE AMENDMENTS<br />
TO THE CONSTITUTION WAS CLEARLY EXPLAINED IN THE REVIEW<br />
COMMITTEE'S REPORT IN THESE TERMS:<br />
A CLEAR MAJORITY OF THE ELECTORS WHO<br />
VOTE AT A REFERENDUM ARE IN FAVOUR OF A PROPOSED<br />
LAW, THEIR WILL SHOULD NOT BE FRUSTRATED BECAUSE<br />
SEPARATE MAJORITIES OF ELECTORS HAVE NOT BEEN<br />
OBTAINED IN A MAJORITY OF THE STATES, IT IS,<br />
IN THE COMMITTEE'S OPINION, MORE IN ACCORD<br />
WITH DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLE AND THE DEVELOPMENTS<br />
SINCE FEDERATION THAT IT SHOULD BE SUFFICIENT<br />
TO OBTAIN SEPARATE MAJORITIES IN AT LEAST ONE<br />
HALF OF THE NUMBER OF STATES': / 1G </p>
<p>1G<br />
THAT IS THE PURPOSE OF OUR REFERENDUM.<br />
INSTEAD OF REQUIRING A MAJORITY IN FOUR STATES OUT<br />
OF SIX, A MAJORITY OF ALL THE PEOPLE. THE TWO THIRDS<br />
MAJORITY IS UNREASONABLY HIGH. IN THE WORDS OF THE<br />
CONSTITUTION REVIEW COMMITTEE, IT MEANS THAT<br />
" FOR EVERY STATE IN WHICH THERE IS AN ADVERSE VOTE<br />
THERE MUST BE A FAVOURABLE VOTE IN TWO STATES<br />
A CONSTITUTIONAL CHANGE HAS TO BE SUPPORTED NOT<br />
ONLY BY A MAJORITY OF STATES BUT BY TWO THIRDS<br />
OF THE STATES."' / 17 </p>
<p>17-<br />
OUR REFERENDUM ON EQUAL ELECTORATES THAT IS,<br />
ELECTORATES HAVING THE SAME NUMBER OF PEOPLE RESULTS<br />
FROM THE SENATE'S FAILURE LAST YEAR TO PASS OUR<br />
LEGISLATION FOR ELECTORAL REFORM, THE SENATE TWICE<br />
REJECTED OUR BILL TO REDUCE THE PRESENT DISPARITY<br />
IN THE SIZE OF ELECTORATES, HIAD THIS LEGISLATION BEEN<br />
PASSED OUR REFERENDUM WOULD NOT BE NECESSARY,<br />
IN THE SAME WAY, IF THE PREMIERS LAST YEAR HAD ACCEPTED<br />
OUR PROPOSAL TO GIVE LOCAL GOVERNMENT DIRECT ACCESS<br />
TO THE FINANCIAL RESOURCES OF THE NATION, OUR<br />
REFERENDUM ON LOCAL GOVERNMENT WOULD NOT BE NECESSARY,<br />
EVERY ONE OF OUR REFERENDUM PROPOSALS IS A CONSEQUENCE<br />
OF THE FAILURE OF THE STATES OR THE SENATE TO AGREE<br />
TO MEASURES FOR WHICH THE GOVERNMENT HAD A MANDATE,<br />
OR THE FAILURE OF OUR PREDECESSORS TO PUT REFORMS<br />
TO THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE WHICH WERE APPROVED IG YEARS<br />
AGO BY AN ALL-PARTY COMMITTEE ON THE CONSTITUTION, / 1I; </p>
<p>1<br />
So LET ME SUMMARISE THE ISSUES AT STAKE ON<br />
18 MAY, THEY ARE CLEAR AND SIMPLE ISSUES AND THEY<br />
INVOLVE QUITE BASIC QUESTIONS OF DEMOCRACY, HAS THE<br />
SENATE THE RIGHT TO OBSTRUCT A PROGRAM CLEARLY ENDORSED<br />
BY THE AUSTRALIAN PEOPLE? CLEARLY IT HAS NOT,<br />
SHOULD A SENATE ELECTED IN 1967 AND 1970 BE ALLOWED TO<br />
OBSTRUCT A GOVERNMENT ELECTED IN 1972? CLEARLY IT SHOULD NOT,<br />
SHOULD AN OPPOSITION GUILTY OF THIS OBSTRUCTION<br />
AN OPPOSITION BEREFT OF LEADERSHIP AND DEVOID OF PURPOSE<br />
BE ENCOURAGED TO PURSUE ITS OBSTRUCTIONIST TACTICS<br />
FURTHER? IT SHOULD NOT, SHOULD A SENATE THAT<br />
HAS DONE ITS BEST TO PREVENT THE PEOPLE DECIDING<br />
BASIC QUESTIONS OF DEMOCRACY BE ENTITLED TO THE<br />
PEOPLE'S CONFIDENCE? IT SHOULD NOT, / 19 </p>
<p>19<br />
THESE ARE NOT ACADEMIC OR TECHNICAL QUESTIONS,<br />
THEY AFFECT THE ESSENTIAL RIGHTS OF THE PEOPLE<br />
AND THE PEOPLE ON 18 MAY WILL BE ABLE TO DECIDE THEM,<br />
I LOOK FORWARD TO THIS CAMPAIGN, PERHAPS, LIKE ME,<br />
YOU HAVE FOUND SENATE ELECTIONS IN THE PAST SOMEWHAT<br />
ARID AND POINTLESS AFFAIRS, THE REASON HAS BEEN<br />
THAT NO CRUCIAL ISSUES WERE INVOLVED; NO GOVERNMENT'S<br />
FUTURE WAS AT STAKE; NO BROAD POLITICAL PRINCIPLE<br />
WAS TO BE RESOLVED, ON 13 MAY THE REAL ISSUE,<br />
THE REAL PRINCIPLE, WILL BE UNMISTAKABLE, IT IS<br />
WHETHER THE GOVERNMENT OF THIS COUNTRY IS TO BE<br />
RESPONSIBLE TO THE PEOPLE WHO ELECTED IT, OR<br />
WHETHER IT IS* TO REMAIN AT THE MERCY OF A SENATE<br />
ELECTED YEARS BEFORE, AND DOMINATED BY THOSE<br />
WHO HAVE FORFEITED ALL CLAIM TO BE A UNITED AND<br />
CREDIBLE OPPOSITION. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
