<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8999</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON PJ KEATING, MP APEC BUSINESS CONSULTATIVE PANEL</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/10/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008999.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
15/ 10 ' 93 09: 02 ' 006 273 2923 PM PRESS OFFICE ] 001<br />
PRIME MINISTER 114/ 93<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
APEC BUSINESS CONSULTATIVE PANEL<br />
I am very much looking forward to participating in the informal APEC Leaders<br />
Economic Conference to be hosted by President Clinton in Seattle on<br />
November.<br />
The meeting represents a historic opportunity for the Asia-Pacific region. It<br />
will build on the increasing economic integration o6 the APEC economies and<br />
give expression to the growing sense of community in our region as well as<br />
focusing the world's attention on the dynamism of Asia.<br />
The active participation of the private sectors of the APEC economies<br />
including Australian business is integral to the success of APEC's further<br />
development. Governments can show the way and create the right conditions<br />
for the development of trade and investment. Ultimately, it is for business to<br />
export and invest.<br />
SI regard it. as essential, in the lead-up to such a significant event, to hear the<br />
views of Australian business about the way ahead for APEC.<br />
I have therefore decided to establish an APEC Business Consultative Panel<br />
which I will chair to assist me in preparing for the November Leaders<br />
meeting. I have invited the following senior Australian business people to<br />
participate in the Panel:<br />
Mr Rodney Adler ( Chief Executive Officer, FAI Insurance)<br />
Mr Frank Blount ( Chief Executive Officer, AOTC)<br />
. Mr Philip Bass-( Managing-DireGor, Pacific Dunlop)<br />
Mr Robert Ferguson ( Joint Managing Director, Bankers Trust)<br />
Mr Bill Ferris ( Executive Chairman, Australian Mezzanine Investments)<br />
Mr Brian Finn ( Chairman and Chief Executive, IFIM Australia)<br />
Mrs Janet Holmes a Court ( Chairman, Heytesbury Holdings)<br />
Mr David Murray ( Managing Director, Commonwealth Bank of Australia)<br />
Mr Michael Nugent ( Chief Executive Officer, Goodman Fielder)<br />
Mr Gary Pemberton ( Chairman, QANTAS Airways)<br />
Mr John Prescott ( Managing Director and Chief Executive Officer, BHP) </p>
<p>2<br />
Mr Doug Shears ( Executive Chairman, lCM Australia)<br />
Dr John Stocker ( Chief Executive, OSIRO)<br />
Mr Andrew Tumbull ( Managing Director and Chief Executive Officer, Bums<br />
Philp) Mr Stan Wallis ( Managing Director, AMCOR)<br />
Mr Dick Warburton ( Chairman, Du Pont ( Australia))<br />
I expect that the first meeting of the Business Consultative panel will take<br />
place in early November in Canberra.<br />
CANBERRA 14 OCTOBER 1993 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
