<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7828</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO 6PR, PERTH -24 NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007828.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, RADIO 6PR, PERTH 24<br />
NOVEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Does this hit at the right to strike, this<br />
decision? PM: No, and I haven't had the chance of reading the<br />
total transcript of the Judge's decision but I've seen some<br />
reference where he refers to the right to strike as<br />
fundamental. Well, get this in perspective that the trade<br />
union movement has operated in this country for the last six<br />
years now under the Accord. They've been able to negotiate<br />
wage increases within that system and this sort of situation<br />
has arisen because the pilots deliberately decided against<br />
the pleas which I made to them and others made to them<br />
including Kelty and Crean don't go outside the system,<br />
here is a system within which there is a means for handling<br />
disputes, including where there is a withdrawal of labour.<br />
Here is a system the Conciliation and Arbitration system,<br />
within that you can hand in your claims, advance your<br />
claims, there can be withdrawal of labour. But they said<br />
no, we're going to withdraw from the protective apparatus<br />
which exists within that system and go out into the American<br />
style straight bargaining system, use our muscle, go for<br />
percent. Now I pleaded with them and I said look that's<br />
silly. Don't do that. Stay within the system because if<br />
you go outside the system then you get exposed to all the<br />
dangers of that. I get no satisifaction at all and I deeply<br />
regret that the Federation of Air Pilots didn't accept the<br />
advice that was given, not just by me, but by the trade<br />
union movement and by the airlines to process their claims<br />
within the system. If they'd done that, they could have got<br />
significant salary increases, they would have had the<br />
opportunity of arguing, within the system, for how their<br />
conditions should be adjusted to the demands of a changing<br />
industry. They could have done all that, but they said at<br />
the beginning of the year and it's in writing they were<br />
going to enter into a battle with their employers. They<br />
said this we're going into a battle with. the employers,<br />
with the Government and with the arbitration system. We're<br />
AAI &amp; Am6A </p>
<p>going to take them all on outside the system. Now, it was a<br />
silly decision and I regret that they have done it. I<br />
repeat, as I've been saying now for weeks and weeks, there<br />
is the possibility of a place for them if they do what the<br />
Commission has said. The Commission has said you accept<br />
these conditions, not special for the pilots but it applies<br />
to everyone else. That is you withdraw your embargo on your<br />
members being employed by the airlines, I mean, they're not<br />
employed well then where are you? Secondly that you accept<br />
the decisions of the Commission. Thirdly you accept the<br />
National Wage Case guidelines. They said if you do those<br />
things which is not special to you, but it applies to every<br />
other organisation of workers, then you can apply to be<br />
bound by the award which is now the contract and if you then<br />
become bound by the award, you can then lodge an application<br />
to argue about that contract, as to whether it should be<br />
changed. So the pilots have, in the first place, chosen to<br />
say no, damn the system. We're going out into that<br />
big rough world on our own. OK. We wanted them not to.<br />
Now the position is that they have a method of seeking to<br />
get back into it which the Commission has given to them.<br />
It's up to them, but they seem not to have accepted the well<br />
intended advice of myself, of the trade union movement, of<br />
everyone else. They haven't accepted that advice for so<br />
long now I don't know whether they will at this point.<br />
JOURNALIST: What would you say to Brian McCarthy<br />
PM: I've said it all.<br />
JOURNALIST: What did you think of yesterday's decision,<br />
damages decision?<br />
PM: Well, it unfortunately is the inevitable result. once<br />
you've made, as the leadership of the Federation did see,<br />
they are supposedly and I don't mean that derogatively,<br />
they're not just supposedly they are people of<br />
intelligence. They deliberately made a choice. There is a<br />
system there, industrial relations system in which provided<br />
for a method for everyone to process claims for increased<br />
wages. There is that system or they could go out into the<br />
/ LJJJ ommonwarcsystem. So when you ask me what do I think about<br />
it, all can say is, as a result of their decision to go<br />
out of the system where they had the protection, where they<br />
could argue and they could even withdraw their labour and so<br />
on and they said no we're out of that. I can't have an<br />
opinion about that other than the one I've expressed.<br />
JOURNALIST: So it serves them right.<br />
PM: That's your words and you could read the whole of my<br />
transcript and you wouldn't read anything out of that. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: I'm asking do you think it serves them right?<br />
PM: No, I don't want to express that view. I mean, my view<br />
is in what I've already said and that is that I deeply<br />
wished that they'd stay within the system. I mean,<br />
everything on the record shows that Hawke, the conciliator,<br />
the person who's built his whole life, whole public life on<br />
trying to get conciliation, consensus, negotiation, that was<br />
why I pleaded stay in the system. So, I don't talk about<br />
serving them right or anything like that. I am deeply hurt<br />
that this situation has arisen. It's not the Hawke style.<br />
The Hawke style is negotiation, discussion, argument if you<br />
like, but argument within a framework which provides for a<br />
peaceful resolution of disputes. That's the whole of my<br />
life and that's why I pleaded with them not to go this path.<br />
So that's why I get no glee, no satisfaction, no pleasure<br />
out of that decision. The only satisfaction, the only<br />
satisfaction Hawke gets out of it is that having had the<br />
issues exposed before an independent judicial authority,<br />
that judicial authority has repudiated the AFAP's monstrous<br />
misrepresentation that there was a conspiracy between Hawke<br />
and the airlines that's what they've been saying. The<br />
Judge has said that's a nonsense and those that were<br />
spoiling for a fight were the Federation. That's the only<br />
satisfaction I get, that after having all that aired, the<br />
evidence given, the Judge has said no conspiracy, as there<br />
never has been on my part because I wanted them to stay in<br />
the system and that they were the ones spoiling for a fight.<br />
I get satisfaction out of having that established, out of<br />
nothing else.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
