<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6248</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, LAUNCHING OF THE MORETON BY-ELECTION CAMPAIGN, BRISBANE, 26 OCTOBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006248.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EBRODUTL1PM<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCHING THE MORETON BY-ELECTION CAMPAIGN<br />
BRISBANE 26 OCTOBER 1983<br />
I am delighted to be back in Brisbane to launch<br />
Labor's campaign for the Moreton By-election.<br />
It is less than 8 months since the people of<br />
Australia'elected a Federal Labor Government.<br />
We were elected:<br />
to arrest the economic decline and then restore<br />
growth to reverse the trend towards greater inequality<br />
to bring Australians together<br />
We are meeting those commitments.<br />
We promised to convene a National Economic Summit<br />
Conference of unions, employers and governments to lay the<br />
basis for cc-operative solutions to Australia's economic<br />
problems. We have done that.<br />
We promised to establish an Economic Planning<br />
Advisory Council to provide, for the first time, an<br />
integrated basis for consistent, long-term economic<br />
planning. We have done that.<br />
We promised to establish a Community Employment<br />
Program to directly create jobs, particularly for the<br />
long-term unemployed.<br />
We have done that. EMBARGOED UNTIL 1 P. M. </p>
<p>We promised to introduce a First Flame Ownership<br />
Assistance Scheme to enable lower income families to buy<br />
their own home.<br />
We have done that.,<br />
In fact the housing grant we are providing $ 7,000<br />
-is a full $ 2,000 above what we promised.<br />
We promised to put in hand arrangements for the<br />
introduction of Medicare a simple, universal, equitable<br />
health care system.<br />
We have done that.<br />
We promised to increase education allowances and to<br />
distribute education resources more equitably.<br />
We have done that.<br />
We promised to introduce legislation to outlaw<br />
discrimination against women.<br />
We have done that.<br />
We promised to arrest the decline in employment<br />
that was occurring under the previous Government.<br />
We have done that.<br />
We promised to create 500,000 jobs in our first 3<br />
years of government.<br />
We are on target.<br />
No Government has moved so quickly to meet so many<br />
of its election commitments as this Government.<br />
We are keepingj our promises.<br />
There is one promise that is perhaps more important<br />
for the livelihood of Australians than any other.<br />
That is our promise to restore economic growth.<br />
Within 12 months we will have implemented that<br />
commi tment. During the last financial year for which the<br />
previous Government was responsible there was negative<br />
economic growth. Real non-farmn product fell by 2 per cent through<br />
the course of the financial year. </p>
<p>3.<br />
Durinq this financial year there will be a dramatic<br />
improvement. No longer will there be negative growth.<br />
Instead, growth in real non-farmn product is<br />
expected to be at least 5 to 6 per cent over the course of<br />
this financial year.<br />
This is the largest turnaround in Australia's<br />
economic growth performance since the Second World War.<br />
This growth forecast is not the Government's<br />
forecast. It is the forecast of the Government's official'<br />
advisers in the Treasury and the Reserve Bank<br />
disinterested parties with no axe to grind for this<br />
Government. They say: within 12 months Australia will be back<br />
on the economic growth path.<br />
This would not have occurred without the Federal<br />
Labor Government's economic policies.<br />
We are turning the economy round.<br />
We are putting Australia back on the path of<br />
long-term economic growth.<br />
This return to sustained economic growth will be<br />
central to achieving so many of the aspirations of<br />
Australians in the 1980' s and 1990' Is.<br />
Growth will create jobs for Australians young and<br />
old and take people off the unemployment queues.<br />
Growth will finance increases in pensions and<br />
social security benefits.<br />
Growth will make it possible for governments to<br />
ease the burden * of taxation.<br />
Growth will mean an expanding cake so that workers<br />
and employers don't have to turn on each other to meet their<br />
a sp i ra tions. Growth will mean rising productivity so that the<br />
living standards of wage and salary earners can rise without<br />
fuelling inflation.<br />
We promised to restore economic growth. </p>
<p>We have made that promise a cornerstone of our<br />
economic policy.<br />
We are keeping that promise.<br />
The Labor Party is the Party of economic cjrowth.<br />
A Labor vote in Moreton is a vote for growth, for<br />
expansion, for development, for the future.<br />
The Liberal Party is the Party of stagnation, of<br />
depression. Fo r seven yea rs the Li beral s i n fli cted the ir<br />
Depression economics on Australia.<br />
For seven years the enormous potential of Australia<br />
was squandered. For seven years Australia lived in the past.<br />
Of course we have not been able to move on all our<br />
promises as quickly as we would like.<br />
-A ' Case in point is our commitment to lower personal<br />
taxation. The reason for the delay is simple the deception<br />
of the previous Government.<br />
Within 24 hours of coming to office we were told by<br />
our officials that the prospective Budget deficit was $ 9.6<br />
billion not the $ 6 bil lion the previous Government told<br />
the Australian people it would be.<br />
That was their leg~ acy a $ 9.6 billion deficit<br />
John Howard's poisoned chalice passed on to us.<br />
Mr Fraser, Mr Peacock arid Mr Howard grossly<br />
deceived the Australian people about the size of the<br />
deficit. When we discovered that deception we had no choice<br />
asea responsible Government we had to delay the taxation<br />
changes we had proposed.<br />
It has taken the Federal Labor Government to<br />
implement policies to get Auistralia moving, to meet the<br />
challenge of economic growth head-on.<br />
A Government of unity, of strength, of purpose<br />
A Government that will allow Australians to plan<br />
and build for the future with confidence. </p>
<p>Under Labor's policies the first signs of the<br />
econom ic recovery havce emerged.<br />
We have already turned round the housing industry.<br />
We have create~ d 80,000 new jobs since April.<br />
Confidence is returning to the business community.<br />
Confidence is returning to Australia.<br />
M~ eaniwhile the Liberals have learnt nothing from the<br />
events of March<br />
They are confEused.<br />
They are divided.<br />
They are leaderless.<br />
They are a shambles.<br />
They need to be told in the clearest terms that<br />
they will not even be considered for government while they<br />
lack unity, while they lack policies, while they lack any.<br />
semblance of a vision for Australia.<br />
The Liberals' much-vaunted Valder Report exalts<br />
them to aggressively present Liberal philosophies and " win<br />
the intellectual debate".<br />
Their problem, however, is that they are<br />
deeply divided on basic policy questions and are in no<br />
position to even carry on a debate let alone win one.<br />
These divisions have prevented the Liberals from<br />
adopting any coherent policy on Such fundamentally important<br />
issues as the wages policy appropriate for Australia today.<br />
If there is one lesson that is devastatingly clear<br />
from the Queensland election it is this.<br />
The people of Australia do not want in government<br />
pQlitical parties that are divided among themselves.<br />
The Liberal Party in Queensland is split down the<br />
middle. The Liberal Party federally is also deeply divided.<br />
That is just not good enough.<br />
The Liberals' stand on tax avoidance is a scandal. </p>
<p>Their recent: re-jection in the Senate of the<br />
Government's tax recouIpment legislation shows breathtakingly<br />
their duplicity and double standards.<br />
The effect of their action is to protect the tax<br />
avoiders and rip-off merchants of this country<br />
to the tune of $ 60 million this financial year and<br />
$ 270 million in aggregate<br />
That is Andrew Peacock's bill to the ordinary,<br />
law-abiding taxpayers of Australia.<br />
These funds lost by the Liberals are equivalent to<br />
7,000 new jobs under the Community Employment Program.<br />
These funds would have enabled a one per cent<br />
reduction in personal income tax for every taxpayer.<br />
Instead the Liberals have handed the money straight<br />
back to the tax avoiders of Australia.<br />
I know there has been a degree of concern among<br />
pensioners about the Government's proposal to reintroduce an<br />
assets tesit on pensions.<br />
There is no need for this concern.<br />
The great bulk of pensioners more than 80 per<br />
cent will not be adversely affected at all.<br />
In addition, the Government is at present carefully<br />
reviewing the proposed arrangements.<br />
We are looking at possible ano-Malies and other<br />
concerns that have been brought to our notice.<br />
The Social Security Minister, Senator Grimes, is<br />
having extensive consultations with pensioner organizations.<br />
If we find changes are needed, changes will be<br />
made. We want to make the assets test as fair and<br />
equitable as we possibly can.<br />
And we want to protect the position of the vast<br />
majority of pensioners who are not wealthy and are not<br />
exploiting the system.<br />
There has also been a degree of unw.. arranted concern<br />
ab-out the taxa tion o f supe rannuat i-r lump s ums<br />
The new measures will be phased in very gradually. </p>
<p>Particula-rly low rates will apply for at least tho<br />
first 10 years anid quite modest rates over the long-term11.<br />
The return of an employee's own superannuation<br />
contributions is to be wholly tax exempt.<br />
And even that part which attracts tax is to incur a<br />
concessional rate of 15 per cent on the first $ 50,000 with a<br />
tax rate of 30 per c-ent: thereafter.<br />
The Government introduced these measures because<br />
only a minority ( 5f the workforce have been able to take the<br />
special and excessive tax benefits applying to lump sums.<br />
By commencing these measures now the Government is<br />
ensuring a fair and secure retirement can be afforded for<br />
all members of our rapidly growing eli'erly population.<br />
Here in Moreton Labor has an outstanding candidate.<br />
Barbara Robson has stood for Moreton three timesin<br />
1977, 1980 and 1983.<br />
Each time she has improved Labor's vote.<br />
Last time she almost won.<br />
This time she will win.<br />
There are already six Labor women in the Hlouse of<br />
Representatives. She will make it seven.<br />
Barbara is known as the shadow Member for Moreton.<br />
She has earnied that title through strenuous efforts<br />
to sort out people's problems housing, social security,<br />
immigration, education.<br />
Barbara's ties with Moreton date back to her school<br />
days at Cavendish Road High School.<br />
She taught for many years at schools in jMoreton.<br />
She likes challenges anid helping people.<br />
Her opponent has already collected a very generous<br />
parliamentary lumnp SUM S~ iperannUation payout $ 276,000.<br />
Now he wants another go.<br />
Mr Cameron has no commitment whatsoever to the<br />
electorate of Moreton. </p>
<p>He has already converted t1wo Federal electorates<br />
into Labor seats.<br />
Ile won't get another chance.<br />
Barbara Robson has worked tirelessly in Moreton.<br />
She has earned the seat of Moreton.<br />
She deserves the seat of Moreton.<br />
On November 5 she will be the Member for Moreton. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
