<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3196</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION TO 30TH ECAFE CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003196.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
t-A A NNO DATE<br />
M/ 44 23 March 1974<br />
AUSTRALIAN DELEGATION TO 50TH ECAFE CONFERENCE<br />
The Prime Minister and Acting Minister for Foreign<br />
Affairs, Mro Whitlam, announced today that the Minister for<br />
Science and Minister Assisting the Minister for Foreign<br />
Affairs, Mr. Morrison, would lead the Australian Delegation<br />
to the 30th session of the UN Economic Commission for Asia<br />
and the Far East ( ECAFE), to be held in Colombo, Sri Lanka,<br />
from 27 March to 8 April.<br />
Mr. Whitlam said that the annual sessions of ECAFE<br />
reviewed the economic and social situation in the region and<br />
the commission's activities throughout the previous year. The<br />
commission's future priorities and work programs were also<br />
decided at these sessions.<br />
The session would provide a valuable opportunity for<br />
cons. ideration by member countries of the fundamental economic<br />
and social problems of the area. It was envisaged that a new<br />
development strategy for ECAFE would be discussed at the session.<br />
In keeping with its policy of encouraging economic, social and<br />
political co-operation in the Asian and Pacific region,' the<br />
Australian delegation would play a constructive role in this<br />
work. Mr. Morrison would make the Australian statement in the<br />
session's general debate.<br />
As in previous years, the delegation would include<br />
officers of the Departments of Foreign Affairs, Overseas Trade<br />
and the Treasury. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
