<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22089</transcript-id>
    <title>Press Conference Commonwealth Parliamentary Offices, Sydney </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/12/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am pleased to announce that the Government's biofuels target announced in the election campaign of 2001, that we would have 350 megalitres of biofuel production by 2010, that that target will easily be met. It is, on current indications, and detail will be found in the industry action plans that I will release immediately after this news conference; it's likely that the original target of 350 will be passed sometime between 2008 and 2009.</p>
<p> It is a conservative projection that we will pass it. You will see from the industry action plans that the likelihood is that it will be significantly exceeded. This is very good news. I promised in September when I met the chief executives of the oil majors and the independents that we would have industry action plans, we would work together. I want to thank the oil companies and the independents for their cooperation. I'm pleased to acknowledge that significant work is already underway.</p>
<p> There are now 400 service stations across Australia selling ethanol and bio-diesel blends. BP recently opened three sites in Canberra to provide an E10 product to service the government fleet. Shell recently launched Shell Optimax Extreme a super-high octane fuel formulated with 5 per cent ethanol through Coles Express. Optimax Extreme will be the official fuel of the V8 Supercars Championship for 2006 and Caltex has signed a contract for the supply of ethanol from Dalby bio-refinery to a new biofuels supplier. And finally the independent fuel companies have continued to make a big contribution. United sells ethanol blends at over 90 locations Australia-wide. Australian Farmers Fuel sells bio-diesel at more than 50 outlets across Australia and Neumann Petroleum and Freedom Fuels each sell retail biofuels at 25 service stations. I'm very pleased with the progress that's being made, it's more than I expected. It's very welcomed.</p>
<p> We have I believe restored a lot of confidence in the use of biofuels, particularly ethanol. You will recall that several years ago as a result of a blatantly political campaign targeting Mr Dick Honan and my alleged improper association with him in some way, that there was a lot of erosion of public confidence in the use of ethanol and biofuels generally. Now, we have redressed that imbalance and there's a better understanding and I welcome the contribution that has been made, and I am particularly pleased that the targets set out in 2001 of 350 megalitres by the year 2010; that target is easily going to be met on current indications and that is a very welcome thing. I want to thank the oil companies; I want to thank a number of my colleagues for the contribution that they have made for arguing the case for a better understanding.</p>
<p> I single out Senator Ron Boswell, the leader of the National Party in the Senate who has campaigned very strongly for a more sensible approach to ethanol and to biofuels. I thank my Ministerial colleague Ian Macfarlane for the sensible and co-operative approach that he has taken towards this issue. I think we now have got it back on to an even keel and we can get a very sensible response and so that I wont be accused of failing to practice what I preach, as a result of a special trial that has been carried out on the heavily protected Commonwealth vehicles, I am advised that appropriate performance will be achieved through the use of one of the super-high octane fuels and as soon as the cards are available, my driver in Sydney will be availing himself of that fuel very early in the new year and there will be a similar situation in Canberra. Are there any questions about this or indeed anything else seeing this will certainly be, I expect, my last news conference before Christmas.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What difference will it make to the environment by having these targets exceeded; do you have any bench marks?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well there is a lot of debate about that. Many people believe that the environmental advantages are high, others are more sceptical. I think the important thing is to give people choice. The most recent report that we received was a lot more optimistic about the environmental advantages and therefore it makes a great deal of sense that the availability of biofuels and the use of biofuels be greater.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You singled out Senator Boswell there who has consistently pushed biofuels. Is this announcement now something of a Christmas present for Mr Boswell to raise his stock at home and thanks for his support?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The question of the National Party Senate ticket in Queensland is a matter for the Queensland National Party; I don't have any comment on that.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p> Mr Howard on Telstra, do you think that Telstra can get a fair hearing from the ACCC over its pricing policies? And do you think there is a case for the Government to intervene in the process?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am confident that the process is working, correctly.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard do you welcome the freeing of Brian Ambrosio from the Gaza Strip</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh very much so. It must have been a traumatic experience for him. These short-term kidnappings in the Gaza are not uncommon. I learnt the details of this yesterday afternoon and I want to say, on behalf of the Australian Government and behalf of the people of Australia; to him and his family how very grateful we are that he has been released unharmed. Although, psychologically it would have been a horrifying experience, but we are delighted that he has been released and we have great regard for the good work he's carrying out as the deputy principal of the International School and it will naturally be a matter for him as to whether he returns to that position.  But we are very pleased that he is out safe and sound.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Richard Pratt, big donor to the Liberal Party.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you have any comments on the case?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't have any comments on the case, no I don't. That is entirely a matter that must be dealt with in accordance with the processes. Quite separately from that I am very pleased to say that I have known Mr Pratt for a very long period of time. He is a person who's made an enormous contribution to the Australian nation and to the Australian community. I make no secret of that fact and that's freely acknowledged and freely understood. As to the particulars of this case I have no comment at all for reasons I am sure you'll understand.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Does Mr Pratt have your support?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I can't comment on the case. If you are asking do I know Mr Pratt? Yes. Do I like Mr Pratt? Yes. Do I think Mr Pratt has made a big contribution to the Australian community? Yes. Do I have any comment on this case? No I do not.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think collusion between companies in Australia, particularly in (inaudible) is a problem?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Look I am not going to get into that today because it inevitably will be regarded as a comment on this particular case and that's why you've asked me the question. So I am not going to give you the answer you want.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>In relation to the recent ceremony between Elton John and his partner, could you foresee a civil partnership law being passed Australia?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I would be opposed to it. I think marriage is for men and women. That's why we amended the Marriage Act. I don't say that in any sense of hostility or discrimination towards gay people but I believe very strongly that marriage is exclusively a union for life of a man and a woman to the exclusion of others. That is the common understanding of marriage in the Judaeo-Christian tradition and I would be opposed to a recognition of civil unions, although I am strongly in favour - as my Government has demonstrated - strongly in favour of removing any property and other discrimination that exists against people who have same-sex relationships.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What do you think about the Greenpeace action against Japanese whaling ships in the Antarctic and is Australia doing enough to register its opposition to whaling?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p> Well I, in my last meeting with the Japanese Prime Minister, only a couple of weeks ago- or ten days ago, I raised whaling with him. Although we spent a large part of our meeting discussing Iraq and areas where the Japanese and Australian Governments are in full agreement, I did not lose the opportunity of telling him of my continued opposition to Japan's position on whaling. However, I do not support action which endangers lives or breaks the law.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>What's on your Christmas wish list?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I wish my fellow Australians a very happy and peaceful and enjoyable time with their families. I ask them to remember those in the community who don't have the blessing of a family and close friends and for them Christmas can be a lonely time. I have recorded a Christmas message that gathers up some of these thoughts and that will be available for all of you in the next little while, I imagine.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think it is possible that we might have more violence on the beaches such as in Cronulla?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I'm quite optimistic that we won't. I really am quite optimistic that people will see that nothing is ever achieved by violence. Violence is repugnant, no matter who engages in it, it is never to be excused and never to be justified and I am optimistic that we won't and I would encourage Australians to enjoy their Christmas as they traditionally do.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do you think police may have overreacted? I mean shutting down beaches...</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Look I am not going to criticise the police. My golden rule in these circumstances is to support the police, it is a difficult job. We like to have the police there. We demand that the police be there to protect us when something goes wrong and part of that understanding, part of that covenant is that they have to be supported in difficult situations and I do. I have a lot of respect for the police and you won't be hearing me criticising them.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>More broadly, what do you think about the New South Wales Government's handling of what appears to be some criminal elements in the community.</p>
<p> PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that is a matter that perhaps is better commented upon away from the context of recent weeks. I might in another context have views about that, but my approach in relation to these matters has been to give support to the immediate actions that have been taken by the New South Wales Government and the New South Wales Police to do with a difficult situation. But obviously in another context, and perhaps even more particularly the New South Wales Opposition may have views on that matter, but it is not something I want to offer a view on in the current context because my approach is one of giving support to the New South Wales Government and the New South Wales Police to deal with what is essentially a law and order problem. My view has consistently been, and I still haven't altered it, that these matters should be dealt with primarily in a law and order context. Those who have broken the law be it last Sunday week, on last Sunday week or on other occasions should be prosecuted and they should be prosecuted without regard to their background, their motives or their ethnicity.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the new Fair Pay Commissioner Ian Harper was also the non-executive director of a company that went broke and didn't pay it's workers for a time. Was the Government aware that he'd been involved in that company, ADX Limited?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>All of that was dealt with yesterday. It was made specifically; the Government was made specifically aware of all of that. The liquidator has given what I thought was a very strong clean bill of health to Ian Harper and he has indicated that to his knowledge all of the entitlements have been paid. I don't think there is any concern about his position, he retains my full confidence. I think he will be an excellent chairman of this body.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Wasn't there still question over due notice in that case?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You are heading towards ten years as Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh we don't want to start talking about all of that on the eve of Christmas; I don't want to do that.</p>
<p> JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>You're not feeling tired?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No I don't feel tired, no I don't. I am looking forward to Christmas though; I am looking forward to spending some time with my family. They're in Sydney, where I will be for the next few weeks. I will be going to some cricket and, but the important thing is that all of you and the rest of my fellow Australians enjoy Christmas as I hope they do and you all look forward with energy to a very active and full 2006. Thank you very much and Merry Christmas.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
