<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6300</transcript-id>
    <title>TANSCRIPT, PRESS CONFERENCE, 27 JANUARY 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/01/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006300.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E, AUSTlAI. IA<br />
TRANSCRIPT PRESS CONFERENCE 27 JANUARY 1984<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
Well, ladies and gentlemen, I thought what would be most<br />
useful is if I were to give an outline of the objectives and<br />
themes of the visit that I'm about to undertake in general<br />
terms and then some comments about the particular countries,<br />
and then be open to any questions you'd like to ask.<br />
Obviouslv one of the main purposes of the visit is to establish<br />
a personal contact and exchange views with the regional<br />
leaders that I've not previously met Mr Nakasone, the Prime<br />
Minister of Japan; President of Chun, Republic of Korea,<br />
Dr Mahathir in Malaysia, and also to build upon the relations<br />
that I've already established with Premier Zhao of China<br />
and Lee Kuan Yew of Singapore. In this way I want to give<br />
further substance to the very high priority which the Covernment<br />
attaches to its relations with the Asia Pacific region and to<br />
look for ways in which we can strengthen the role of Australia<br />
as an integral member of that region which is the most dynamic<br />
and fastest growing economic region in the world. Within that<br />
objective, and particularly we ould seek to promote the<br />
potential role that we see Australia may have as an exporter<br />
of advanced services to the region. We will be particularly<br />
concerned with further exploring the possibilities of regional<br />
consultation and co-operation in a new multi-lateral trade<br />
negotiations round as I foreshadowed in my speech in Bangkok<br />
on the 22nd of November and we'll be doing this with the<br />
aim of attempting to promote more open international trading<br />
systems. I'll certainly be wanting to familiarise myself<br />
directly through these contacts with the political and<br />
strategic equation in north east Asia where the vital interests<br />
of four major powers, the United States, the Soviet Union,<br />
China and Japan, are directly involved.. And it's quite<br />
clear that the maintenance of stability in this region<br />
is vital to Australia's interests.<br />
I will be seeking also, as far as the ASEAN members are<br />
concerned, to further strengthen the relations that we<br />
have with ASEAN relations which clearly have already been<br />
strengthened following the discussions that we've had<br />
successfully with them in regard to the differences that<br />
did arise on our non-sponsorship of the Kampuchean resolution.<br />
And one matter of particular interest in Japan will be to<br />
consider the relevance to our country of the industry policy<br />
making practices in Japan which as you know are based firmly<br />
upon the co-operation between government, business and the<br />
trade unions. You will recall that over the years I have S. ./ 2 </p>
<p>cont... . often referred to the relevance that I've seen<br />
in the successfuil Japanese practices in that respect and I<br />
will ta,,-e the opportunity of directly having discussions with<br />
leaders in Japan as to the way in which those processes have<br />
been and are operating.<br />
Now if I may briefly refer to the individual countr es to<br />
which I'll be going in the order in whitch I'll be visiting<br />
them. We will be in Hong Kong briefly and clearly I would take<br />
the opportunity there of reviewing the current state of<br />
negotiations on the future of Hong Kong. Now while Australia<br />
is clearly not directly involved in what happens there, we<br />
nevertheless have a strong interest in the satisfactory outcome<br />
of those negotiations as far as China and Britain and the<br />
people of Hong Kong themselves are concerned.<br />
In Japan we will be having talks which we regard as fundamentally<br />
important. Japan is our mos: t important trading partner and<br />
it's a country whose political role over time is coming to<br />
reflect it's important global and economic position. I've<br />
not yet had the opportunity of persona. contact with<br />
Mr Nakasone and I'm looking forward to doing that and to<br />
discussing with him and others important strategic developments<br />
in north east and south east Asia, including Indo-China and<br />
on the question of arms control and disarmament. And jery<br />
importantly, as far as Japan is concerned, we'll be wanting<br />
to discuss and acquaint ourselves as intimately as -we can with<br />
the changes that are taking place in Japanese economic structure<br />
in relation' to the chaniges that are taking place here because<br />
those changes that are taking piace in Japan have a basic<br />
significance for the economic and trading relationship between<br />
our two countries. And a matter of particular importance<br />
that we'll be directing our attention to, and seeking to engage<br />
equally the Japanese in attaching importance to it, is that in<br />
negotiations by Japan with third countries that the Japanese<br />
wil. not succumb to pressure which will disregard the<br />
legitimate interests of Australia as a reliable and relevant<br />
supplier. For Korea, it will be recognised I think, that this is a<br />
country whose increasing economic strength is important to us<br />
and the security of which country is equally important in terms<br />
of the strategic security of north east Asia. I will, of course,<br />
be meeting President Chun who was tragically prevented, as a<br />
result of the Rangoon atrocity, from coming to Australia in<br />
October. And we will obviously be particularly interested<br />
in discussing with President Chun the assessment that he<br />
makes of the stability and security of the region following those<br />
tragic events and the KAL airliner tragedy. Trade between<br />
Australia and the Republic of Korea has reached a figure<br />
of over $ 1 billion $ 1.1 billion in 1982/ 83 which made the<br />
ROK our fifth largest customer. So we'll be obviously<br />
exploring the prospects for further developments of economic<br />
co-operation and trade between our countries. / 3 </p>
<p>As far as China is concerned you will apprecia-. e that I had<br />
the opportunity very early in the ]. ife of our Government<br />
of welcoming Premier Zhao here in Canberra. And 1 can say<br />
that I found him one of the outstanding world leaders that<br />
Ive met ' in my period in office and VIll be looking forward<br />
to having discussions with him about a number of matters,<br />
not necessarily in this order of importance. But the<br />
sorts of things that we'll be concerned about will be to have<br />
the benefit of insight from him flowing from the recent<br />
international discussions they've been having in Japan and<br />
in the United States and to get their assessment of<br />
developments in Sino-Soviet relations and, of course, in<br />
South East Asia in general and Indo-China in particular<br />
and on the question of international disarmament. I will<br />
be wanting to take further with Premier Zhao the extraordinarly<br />
interesting discussions that I had with him about the<br />
fundamental changes that are taking place in China in their<br />
economic philosophy and practices -changes which I think, still,<br />
the rest of the world haven't fully appreciated as to the<br />
si,,&gt;-ificance that they hold for the rest of the world. And<br />
I will be very interested to see how in that period, now of<br />
almost twelve months since he outlined to me those fundamental<br />
changes which had begun in the agricultural sector and which<br />
they were in the process of transferring into the area of<br />
secondary industry, just how those changes have developed.<br />
Within that overall framework. we will be exploring 1-he<br />
possibility of further trade and economic relationships<br />
between our two countries and moost particularly we will be<br />
exploring the prospects for even closer agricultural co-operation<br />
between China and Australia.<br />
As for Singapore, and there of course I will be renewing<br />
the close relations I forged with Prime Minister Lee Kuari Yew.<br />
at CHOGM, we'll be discussing international security and<br />
economic matters with the Prime MiniSter. And we'll, of course,<br />
particularly with him be discussing the concept that we are<br />
seeking to develop of regional co-operation in an approach<br />
to new MTN ground which we would seek to bring to fruition.<br />
Particularly also I would be irnterested in talking with<br />
the Prime Minister of Singapore about their experience as<br />
an international financial centre because you will appreciate<br />
that we are looking at the possibilities in that respect<br />
for this country.<br />
Finally I refer to Malaysia, an important country, it's a key<br />
member of ASEAN, of the group of 77 of the non-aligned movement<br />
and of the Islamic group of countries. So in those respects<br />
it has an importance for us. I'll be exchanging views with<br />
Dr Mahathir who I've not previously miet about the samne sorts<br />
of issues that I'll be talking about in Singapore and I would<br />
expect him, as probably also in Singapore, I would expect him<br />
to raise the question of our forces in Butterworth.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen, those are the general objectives and<br />
aims that I have on this visit on behalf of this country and<br />
particularly some of the matters that I'll be seeking to<br />
raise and discuss in the particular countries that I'll be<br />
visiting. / 4 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, it's obviously a very wide-ranging<br />
trip, but if you could put one themc, to us, what would that<br />
be? The theme would be that Australia's destiny is inevitably<br />
and irrevocably with the Asian and Pacific region and the<br />
quality and standard of life of Australians in our time and<br />
their children is going to be significantly determined by<br />
the quality and the substance of the relationships with<br />
this area. And the visit is directed towards doing all that<br />
we can to ensure that this relationship with the countries<br />
of the region is based upon a mutl-ual recognition of our<br />
inter-locked interests and to establish those attitudes<br />
and policies in relationships in a way which are most likely<br />
to maximise Australia's chance of a constructive involvement<br />
with those countries, which as I've said, have been for some<br />
time and look like being well into the future the most dynamic<br />
and fastest growing economic region in ithe world.<br />
JOURNALIST: What sort of f'oedback have we had over the last<br />
couple of months, since your 13angkok speech in particular,<br />
following the visit of the officials to the region about the<br />
possibility or regional co-operation on the trade ground.<br />
You would appreciate that I can't. go into the details<br />
at this stage of the responses because I want to pick those<br />
up in the countries. But I can say the primary reactions<br />
foliowing the visit earlier this month of Dr Garnaut, my<br />
personal adviser, and a representative from the Departmcnt of<br />
Trade have been very positive. There is a recognition of two<br />
things if I can put it this way that the previous MTN<br />
negotiations have not been satisfactory from the point of<br />
view of the co-mmodit-' es of greatest concern to ourselves<br />
and to the other countries in this region. Secondly, that<br />
we as much as any area of the world have a vested interest<br />
in the opening up of a freer international trading system.<br />
And thirdly that if that is to be done through the medium<br />
of a MTN round that it can only be useful if there is an<br />
advance on what happened before when our interests as far<br />
Australia is concerned agricultural products and processed<br />
mineral products and many of the sorts of products of Importance.<br />
to the countries in this region didn't get dealt. with. So<br />
they see merit in the concept of a new round and of a regional<br />
approach in that. Now I don't want to overstae*. it t-here is<br />
the interest, there is we believe the sense of a regional interest<br />
and I would hope that out of the discussions that we have we<br />
will be able to adopt practical steps then to give effect<br />
to what seems to be out of these intitial discussions, the<br />
recognition of common interest.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Prime ministers for some years have<br />
been saying in Australia that it's important to develop<br />
our relationships with Asia because that's where our future<br />
lies. Do you see this trip as taking our relations with<br />
South East Asia and Asia as a whole into a new direction or<br />
are you merely shoring up the relationshijps that are already<br />
there? </p>
<p>No I a: n not concerned with in any way reflecting<br />
upon what's happened in the past. I think rather I would<br />
say that it has been useful over the past decade that there<br />
has been in broad terms a bi-partisan recognition of the<br />
realities of our inevitable relationships with the region.<br />
What we're trying to do is to translate what has been a<br />
broad recognition into practical steps to give effect to<br />
that recognition. I refer to the initiatives that we are<br />
taking now in regard to the MTN. We have perceived, and<br />
as I answered in response to Paul Kelly's question, we are<br />
getting a response in the same direction from the countries<br />
of the area that we have the same interests in opening up<br />
and freeing the international trading system, that we have<br />
a lot of mutual interests in the new directions that such<br />
a round should take. So I give that as an example of the<br />
practical way in which we are now saying, well look, we are<br />
part of the region. Don't let's just talk about it and say<br />
we are part of the region. Let's identify the ways in which<br />
we can through a mutuality of interests act to the benefit<br />
of the region as a whole. And that is obviously in the<br />
immediate sense perhaps the most important initiative we are<br />
taking. But I make the second, and for these purposes the<br />
final point, that from the beginning of our time in Government<br />
we've tried to look at all the aspects of our relations with<br />
the countries of the region whether they be political or<br />
trading or broadly economic in a way where we just don't<br />
make a decision in one area, political, economic or trading<br />
alone. But we have tried to integrate the approaches that<br />
we take so that all that we do will collectively strengthen<br />
the understanding of the courtries of the region that we, in<br />
Australia, do regard ourselves as a member of the region.<br />
So I -think that's how I would distinguish our Government from<br />
the past. Not that we have a sudden, new, blinding understanding<br />
of what, after all, is a pretty obvious fact, I think, that<br />
the future of Australia is bound up with the area, but rather<br />
we are moving in specific ways to give concrete practical<br />
effect to that reality.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you said at the outset that<br />
you'd like to see Australia exporting advanced services<br />
to the region and I ask this question in the context of<br />
projections done by Chase Econoretric the other day which<br />
was reported in the paper saying that unless Australia changes<br />
it's ways, by the end of the decade we are going to have the<br />
lowest productivity of any country in the region and third<br />
highest inflation. In that regard what do you think you can<br />
benefit, or do you believe that's correct, and secondly<br />
do you believe you're gaining benefit by changing Australia's<br />
direction. / 6 </p>
<p>Well, I think if you were to project into the future<br />
let's say ' he next decade the comparative rates of economic<br />
growth of Australia and the countries to which you refer, the<br />
sorts of conclusions that are listed would be likely to follow.<br />
What can we do about that? We can't, nor of course do we want<br />
to, on the contrary, reduce the rates of growth of the countries<br />
of those regions because an expanding, prosperous region if<br />
sensibly handled by us in our relations with the region is<br />
a plus for Australia it can be a plus for Australia. What<br />
we are aiming to do is to reduce the discrepancy between the<br />
rates of growth by increasing our own rate of growth. And I<br />
know that we've only been in office for just under a year and<br />
it may adjudged too early by some to draw conclusions as to our<br />
success. But nevertheless it is the fact that in terms of<br />
the growth of non-farm product there is a very dramatic<br />
turnaround taking place in this countryoAnd we, while recognising<br />
some of the particular factors involved in that, are nevertheless<br />
seeking to adopt a range of economic policies which will increase<br />
the rate of growth and the trend rate of growth in AustraliD.<br />
So that will effect the final line of the judgements that Chase<br />
has made. Now coming particularly to the question of the sorts<br />
of advanced services that we may be able to contemplate exporting.<br />
Without being exhaustive the sorts of things that do occur to us,<br />
and that we will be discussing, are the financial services, educationia<br />
services, agricultural services I believe that we have a vast<br />
accumulated experience in that area which already there is evidence<br />
that it is welcomed in some of these countries. And one of the<br />
particular matters that we'll be discussing in China will be how<br />
we'll be able to develop that further. So those are examples<br />
of the sorts of things that I believe we can contemplate exporting<br />
in greater quantity and concept to the countries of the region.<br />
JOURNALIST: So you're. not worried by the projection?<br />
Well I think any government here of Australia ought to be<br />
worried that there would be a relative falling away by what's<br />
happening in the countries of the region. It ought to be seen,<br />
however, as not a threat which is what I'm trying to say, but a<br />
spur, if you like, a reason for being very astringent as<br />
Australians in examining the way we do things. If I could<br />
divert just briefly you will recall, I know you're all assiduous<br />
readers of all my speeches but one of the themes that I have<br />
been trying to put to Australia over many years is that we have<br />
been a lucky country in the post-war period, that it all in<br />
a sense fell into our lap. We weren't hurt by the war, the<br />
war in many ways was the best stimulus that occurred to Australia<br />
in terms of the reviewing its capacities to do things. At the end<br />
of the war a non-devastated Australia was able to supply it's rural<br />
products to the rest of the world. It gave us enormous income, it </p>
<p>cont... assist-ed us to have the framework within which<br />
we could set up new manufactuing industries. Then when the<br />
rest of the world was falling back into place and the demands<br />
for our products had fallen away from the great peaks of that<br />
immediate post-war period, then we had our first mineral boom<br />
and that lifted us again. And so in different ways from the<br />
war and post-war period it all was pretty easy for us. But<br />
it's become apparent from, I would say the last decade, I mean<br />
I: d guess it would have to be about -although the signs were<br />
there before that but it became most dramatically apparent<br />
I suppose from about 1973 that the world was a very different<br />
place in that we coaldn't any longer rely on the ' lucky country'<br />
syndrome. That if we were going to be able to at least maintain<br />
the steadily growing standards of living that we had enjoyed<br />
in that post war period, then we wsre going to have to act<br />
to do it. It wasn't going to happen. We weren't going to<br />
be the residual beneficiaries of what was happening elsewhere.<br />
And we certainly won't be just the residual beneficiaries of<br />
the growth of this region. We're going to have to act to enmesh<br />
ourselves in that growth pattern and that is going to .: equire<br />
changes in the way we do things in Australia. It's going to<br />
require changed attitudes by governments, by business and by<br />
the trade unions and that is in part of what we're about on this<br />
trip that we're going to visit these countries, understand more<br />
clearly by being there and talking with their leadership about<br />
precisely what is happening, what are the specific changes in<br />
economic direction, how it is that they are getting these rates<br />
of growth and what does that mean for us. Now to give an example<br />
to relate it to the general exposition I just gave we benefitted<br />
in Australia in the late 50' s and 60' s from the nature of the<br />
expansion of the Japanese economy in steel and in automobiles;<br />
Obviously that created a demand for our iron ore and our coal and<br />
we did benefit. But now the changing structure of the Japanese<br />
economy is going to mean that the sorts of projections that were<br />
made for our raw materials there need to be revised. We will still<br />
have significant absolute exports but the rates of growth that<br />
were projected before need to be changed. The Japanese are changing<br />
their emphasis and directions in their economy. So what we've got<br />
to try and do is to see in relation to those changes how can we mesh<br />
in, what are the sorts of changed structure of exports that we can.<br />
contemplate to get the benefit of the new directions of economic<br />
growth there as with Korea. If you're going to get the benefit<br />
in Australia of these changed directions in the momentum of growth<br />
in those countries it follows by definition that you've got to<br />
have changes in your country. You can't just say well if they<br />
are changing direction we just keep churning out increasing<br />
projections of iron ore and coal, if that's not what they need.<br />
So it's imperative that we in Australia start to understand the<br />
changes that we've got to make if we're going to get the benefit<br />
of their changed patterns of growth.<br />
JOURNALIST: since Australia is coming out of the recession<br />
what sort of message will you have for leaders ( tape break)<br />
protection policy?<br />
I will reiterate what I've said in a number of speeches<br />
in Australia over recent months and that is that while we were<br />
coming out of the recession it would have been inappropriate to<br />
talk about changes in the industry structure. But that as we now<br />
/ A </p>
<p>cont...<br />
have the growing confidence of growth we will be engaging in<br />
discussions with industry, and always when I talk about industry<br />
I include the trade unions wor];. ers are a part of industry after<br />
all. And we will be increasing the range and depth of our<br />
discussions with industry along the lines that I have been putting<br />
in my exposition here. You can't if you're going to do the job<br />
for Australia it has to be done just talk words and recognise<br />
what's happening there and not make the reciprocal changes that<br />
are necessary here and I will be indicating to the leaders of these<br />
countries that we as a government will be working with industry<br />
in Australia to gradually make the sorts of adjustments that<br />
are necessary for our benefit and for theirs.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, may I ask a question about your<br />
trip and also a domestic one.<br />
Well could we just get the trip out of the way first?<br />
JOURNALIST: I wanted to ask you something about Queencland<br />
and Medicare are you putting that on the basis that that's a<br />
sort of foreign relationship<br />
JOURNALIST: Have the Singapore and Malaysian Governments<br />
strongly put to you that they want a RAAF fighter squadron<br />
maintained at Butterworth as part of the integrated air defence<br />
of the region and how does this fit in with the wish of the<br />
Defence Department and the RAAF to have all the five F18 Hornet<br />
squadrons stationed back in Australia.<br />
There has been a clear indication to the Government by<br />
the soui. ces that you mention of a desire for a retention of a<br />
signicant presence at Butterworth and that's understandable.<br />
You're also right in saying that there's a view within Defence<br />
here that in particalarlyin the light of the acquisition of our<br />
new front line aircraft a more efficient way of developing our<br />
capacities to use those aircraft to their full potential would<br />
involve their location in Australia. Now clearly we have two<br />
criteria therefore which have to be taken into account in the<br />
decisions that we make in this regard. We had attached, and will<br />
continue to attach very considerable importance to our defence<br />
relationships with the countries of the region. I will be<br />
going to these countries, and particularly you're talking<br />
about Malaysia and Singapore in your question, to have them<br />
tell me directly what their assessment is of the role that<br />
we have played up until this point and what in their assessment<br />
of the future strategic situation in the area they see as being<br />
involved in a continued form of presence. We have made no decision<br />
here and deliberately the Cabinet has declined to make a decision<br />
because they want me to have the opportunity of having those<br />
discussions. After I've had them we will make a decision here<br />
which I am hopeful will be able to meet the two criteria. It<br />
may require some different form of presence there but it is<br />
important that we take both considerations into acccount. That is<br />
the ideal position, if you like, of our defence force people here<br />
as to what they say would be the ideal way of using our relatively<br />
limited facilities and, on the other hand, the very real need<br />
that we ought to take into account as seen by Malaysia and<br />
Singapore of some presence there. I think the two things can<br />
be made compatible. / 9 </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, is rotation one of the options<br />
you are looking for?<br />
It is one of the options, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: are you going to support in Tokyo to establish<br />
a Pacific Economic Community<br />
No I would not be proposing the P. C. C. concept. That as<br />
you know is something that has been advanced in various quarters<br />
and I would simply record most particularly the suggestion<br />
as emanated from the Republic of Korea, the concept has emanated<br />
from there. No, we take the view that from the assessments we<br />
have made it would not be right to say that the countries of<br />
the region feel that at least at this stage that sort of concept<br />
is appropriate. It implies a range of formal mechanisms and<br />
relationships which the countries of the region are not desirous<br />
of at this stage. But rather it makes sense to us to take things<br />
a step at a time and we believe that the sort of step that we<br />
had '-lked about of identifying mutual and mutually reinforcing<br />
interests between the countries of the region, how to use those<br />
within the global multilateral trading context, to see that our<br />
interests are advanced. We have, as you will have seen from<br />
the speech I made on 22 November in Bangkok what might be called<br />
a fall-back position that if our support for a new MTN round<br />
which was first talked about at the ministerial meeting of GATT<br />
ministers in November of ' 82 and has been reinforced subsequently<br />
by Prime Minister Nakasone and U. S. Special Trade representative<br />
Brock, if those moves don't come to fruition well we have a sort<br />
of fall-back position then of saying, well let's then as countries<br />
of the region examine the possibility within the region but still<br />
consistent with our multi-lateral obligations to see if there<br />
are ways in which we can expand trade within the region. That's<br />
very much a second best. So the concept of a PCC at this stage<br />
is not consistent with that process of realistic gradualism as<br />
I would describe our approach.<br />
JOURNALIST: You said that you would urge the countries you are<br />
visiting to resist pressure from third countries to take more of<br />
their exports which might damage Australian interests. Which<br />
countries did you have most in mind.<br />
Well quite clearly an area of concern is the negotiations<br />
between Japan and the United States. And I'm not being exhaustive<br />
about it one area is the negotiations with regard to beef.<br />
There are two strands of concern if you like in this area.<br />
There is the direct trading negotiations Japan and the<br />
United States at the moment. But. there is this enormous deficit<br />
of $ 20 billion odd relationship between the United States and<br />
Japan. Now obvious. y in negotiations between those two countries<br />
there's going to be an effort to start to make inroads into that<br />
enormous trade deficit by increasing the exports from the United<br />
States to Japan, say in beef. Now that's beautiful if you're<br />
sitting in the United States. But it's not too good if you<br />
look at it from the point of view of Australia which has built<br />
up over the years a reputation properly as a reliable supplier<br />
of quality products. So I give you that as an example. Now that's<br />
one strand. Now the other strand, of course, is that one of the </p>
<p>P. M. cont... great problems in the global international<br />
relationship is the enormous increase in indebtedness of<br />
many countries of the third world. And there will be some<br />
attempts to redirect some trading patterns in an attempt to meet<br />
or to increase the capacities of these countries to meet the<br />
commitments they have under that huge and growing indebtedness.<br />
Now that is a legitimate concern But we as Australians<br />
have to be concerned that that is not conducted in a way which<br />
unreasonably disrupts established trading patterns between<br />
Australia and Japan. Now those are the sorts of things I<br />
have in mind.<br />
JOURNALIST: You could forecast that perhaps if we'd extend<br />
the credit, such as which the Americans do to ensure<br />
our market. Don't let's be hypothetical about it. We've had, going<br />
beyond the countries of the region that I'm visiting now, in<br />
respect of our wheat sales we've had to meet the new approaches<br />
of the United States for instance in trading with Egypt and<br />
Irai-because unless we're prepared to go some way down the<br />
paths that they've established we are not going to get sales.<br />
It goes back to the sort of issues that I've talked about<br />
before we've had three bites of the cherry if you like<br />
or the three whacks behind the ear as far as developments<br />
in Europe are concerned. We lost our t: aditional markets there,<br />
then we were hurt again when under the impact of the CAP policy<br />
there they built up these enormous surplusses and were dumping<br />
them on our markets. And then the third whack behind the ear<br />
was when the United States was responding to those developments<br />
and we've had to try and meet that. And so you can see why<br />
we attach such importance to try. ng to get a new MTN round.<br />
We've got a vested interest inside the countries of the region<br />
to which I'm going to try and ensure that we get a more freed-up<br />
international trading system than the one with which we're faced<br />
at the moment.<br />
JOURNALIST: In October last year at the Australia/ Japan<br />
Economic Committee in Melbourne you gave a very critical speech<br />
import of coal and iron ore and you hoped to existing<br />
contracts. Will you speak to Mr Nakasone about this?<br />
Well referring back to the speech that I gave in<br />
Melbourne. I wouldn't say it was extremely critical. I would<br />
prefer to describe it as a typically frank and direct speech.<br />
But I make this point that it wasn't a negative speech, it wasn't<br />
one in which I was just saying look this is a terrible thing<br />
that's happening. It was put as you recall, if you read the<br />
speech in the context of a recognition on my part and the part<br />
of the Government of the basic changes that are taking place in<br />
the Japanese economy and that it would be the height of unrealism<br />
on our part to expect that we could in the next few years have<br />
levels of exports which were related to a pattern of economic<br />
development and expansion which was not happening. But I was<br />
trying to make the point that in difficult times within Australia,<br />
particularly in respect of our rural products we had remained tctall\<br />
reliable suppliers and that I was trying to convey to our friends<br />
in Japan at government and business levels that we attached great<br />
importance to remaining reliable suppliers. And I have also said </p>
<p>11.<br />
P. M. cont not only in that speech, but elsewhere, that I think<br />
there's been a tendency -Lo exaggorate some of the difficulties<br />
that have arisen as a result of industrial action in this country.<br />
What I was therefore trying to say in that speech, and what I'll<br />
be saying to Prime Minister Nakasone is please operate on the basis,<br />
and we expect you to operate on the basis, that our record show-. s<br />
that we are fundamentally reliable suppliers, that we've made<br />
the decisions structurally and in other ways within Australia to<br />
maintain the reputation of being reliable suppliers. We deserve<br />
recognition and credit for that fact. Now, on that basis let us<br />
together try and understand what the new directions of economic<br />
development are going to be and what sort of arrangements mutually<br />
we ought to be able to make and fix and adhere to, so that in the<br />
years ahead both for Japan and Australia for our mutual benefit<br />
we will be able to go ahead together Now that's was if you like<br />
the structure of the speech, the intent of the speech. It was<br />
not negatively looking-at the past. I thought I had to refer -to<br />
certain features. Butirmuch :.. ore it was a speech about the<br />
future. JOURNALIST: Mr Prime Minister, you talk a lot about your<br />
attitudes towards Asia, to the Indian Ocean and Africa. What<br />
about your attiLtudes towards Europe?<br />
1 would put it in these ways. Europe obviously carries<br />
a diminished economic significance for us in trading teirms.<br />
It's fallen away as a trading partner. I don't say that<br />
critically. I mean the world is a changing and developing<br />
place and we would seek to increase within the economic<br />
realities of' tod2ay and tomorro-we would seek to increase<br />
as far as we could, trade with them. We have no inhibitions<br />
against Europe. There are no animus on our part. But we've<br />
got to recognise the realities of the world in which we live.<br />
But if there are opportunities to increase trade, for instance<br />
our exports of coal, I just use that as an example, we're<br />
working on that to see if we can. We would wish to increase<br />
trade. Now trade is only one part of the complex of relationships.<br />
Politically we recognise the enormous importance of the<br />
developments that are taking place in Europe in their relations<br />
with the eastern bloc.. We are urging our allies, the United<br />
States, to engage in constructive negotiations with the<br />
Soviet Union and we trust that the Soviet Union will respond<br />
so that the current impasse that exists there hopefully can<br />
be resolved. We understand the apprehensions of Europe and<br />
the nations of western Europe in those regards. We will do<br />
what we can in our small way to try and get the negotiation<br />
processes going again. We have a European tradition and<br />
background and while, as I say, into the future more arid more<br />
we are going to be part of in our economic trading terms in<br />
region of Asia and the Pacific, that doesn't mean that we cut off<br />
the past. That the sensible thing for the Government to do is<br />
recognise that tradition and to recognise the changing economic<br />
realities of the world and to do what we can to yet the best<br />
for one another out of those. We shouldn't, either Europe or<br />
Australia, we sh-ouldn't think that Australia's development in this<br />
region means that we turn our back completely on Europe. We can't<br />
do that, we don't want to do that. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
