<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4806</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS AT DINNER FOR NORTHERN TERRITORY MINISTRY AND LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/09/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004806.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 7.00 p. m. ,, AUSTKALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 7 SEPTEMBER 1978<br />
Address at<br />
Dinner for Northern Territory Ministry<br />
and<br />
Legislative Assembly<br />
This is an historic occasion for the Northern Territory and<br />
for Australia's development as a nation, for tomorrow marks<br />
the opening of the first sittings of the Legislative<br />
Assembly since the attainment of self-government.<br />
This is therefore a most opportune and appropriate time for<br />
me, on behalf of the Commonwealth Government and in the<br />
presence of a broad section of the people of the Northern<br />
Territory to honour the members of the Legislative<br />
Assembly, and particularly the Ministers who form your first<br />
government: Paul Everinghan, Marshall Perron, Ian Tuxworth,<br />
Jim Robertson and Roger Steele.<br />
They are to be congratulated on the zeal, foresight and<br />
determination with which they have pursued their personal<br />
and collective vision, shared by many others, to see established<br />
the first self-governing body politic created in this country<br />
since Federation.<br />
I can tell you from first hand experience that your Chief<br />
Minister and his colleagues are most adept at pushing the<br />
Territory's case. Paul Everingham took up the cause of selfgovernment<br />
for the Territory, first conceived by people such<br />
as Jock Nelson and " Tiger" Brennan, and nurtured by his<br />
immediate predecessor, Goff Letts. He took it up most<br />
effectively, in that forthright no-nonsense manner of his,<br />
arguing very firmly on your behalf during the negotiations<br />
which led to self-government becoming a reality.<br />
Your Chief Minister and his colleagues have been willing to<br />
take on the very great responsibility of leading the Territory<br />
into self-government. It is a small Ministerial team, and it<br />
is always hard to be first. But I have a feeling that they<br />
are going to prove to be a very hard act to follow. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
In the past, the Northern Territory has not been without<br />
its critics. A 1937 Royal Commission reported to the<br />
Commonwealth Government of the day that the Territory<br />
was " a detriment" and a " heavy liability to Australia".<br />
In a jocular vein the great Banjo Paterson described<br />
Darwin as a " city of booze, blow and blasphemy where the<br />
citizens... . started drinking gin immediately after breakfast<br />
and kept it up till after midnight". Paterson also described<br />
the Territory as the land of " later on"<br />
Well, Ladies and Gentlemen, the " later on" has well and<br />
truly arrived. The so-called " detriment" and " liability"<br />
is now a cosmopolitan, lively, and unique part of Australia,<br />
with a great future ahead of it. The population-is now over<br />
100,000 and growing. Mining, cattle raising, fishing and<br />
tourism in particular will all help to guarantee a solid<br />
basis for the Territory's future.<br />
The 1st of July must have represented, for many people, a<br />
moment of considerable personal satisfaction. The demand<br />
for a greater say in the development of the Northern<br />
Territory has had a long and at times turbulent history.<br />
I suppose it really began not long after 1911, when the<br />
Northern Territory became a Commonwealth responsibility.<br />
Since then many Territorians have bridled at their affairs<br />
being dominated by a Government and a bureaucracy many miles<br />
to the south, which they felt did not always fully understand<br />
conditions in the Territory.<br />
The growth in status of your Legislative Assembly was<br />
painfully slow 37 years to establish the Legislative<br />
Council and another 27 years before it became fully elected.<br />
Your representative in the Federal Parliament did' not arrive<br />
until. 1922, and then without a voting power the full vote<br />
was not awarded until 1968.<br />
I recall that when Mr Menzies, as he then was, was Attorney-<br />
General in the Lyons Government, he was joined in the<br />
Parliament by a man who some here tonight may remember<br />
MacAlister Blain. Blain had won the seat for the Northern<br />
Territory in the 1934 election by promising that he would<br />
get a. vote for the Member for the Territory within 12 months<br />
or else resign.<br />
Sir Robert Menzies later recalled that Blain visited him<br />
one day and said " I am in trouble; if I don't get a vote<br />
within a year I will have to resign", at which Sir Robert<br />
wished him a pleasant year in the Parliament.<br />
In the end, Sir Robert persuaded Cabinet to pass legislation<br />
giving the Member for the Northern Territory a vote on the<br />
disallowance of any ordinances of the Northern Territory, and<br />
that was enough to let Blain remain the Member for the<br />
Northern Territory for 15 years. / 13<br />
7-</p>
<p>My Government has always seen self-government and eventual<br />
Statehood for the Northern Territory as an important aim.<br />
Our determination to see self-government implemented here<br />
was based on a simple and fundamental proposition we do<br />
not believe that in all matters politicians and bureaucrats<br />
in Canberra necessarily know what is best for the people<br />
of the Territ-ory.<br />
For over two years we have worked with the executive members<br />
of the Legislative Assembly in planning and negotiating the<br />
administrative and financial structure for the Territory's<br />
new status.<br />
On 1st July, as the culmination of all our efforts, a wide<br />
range of functions was transferred to the new government of<br />
the Northern Territory. On 1st January next, responsibility<br />
for health will be transferred; and on 1st July 1979,<br />
education will also be transferred.<br />
The Territory government will then have taken on most of the<br />
functions and responsibilities of a State, and the Territory's<br />
finances will also have been established along the lines of<br />
those of the States.<br />
A totally new relationship has arisen from the aspirations<br />
of the people of this territory to have less domination<br />
from Canberra. The Commonwealth remains extremely conscious<br />
of its responsibilities to the people of the Northern Territory.<br />
The difference is that your political representatives are<br />
now in a far stronger position to affect the future direction<br />
of the Territory. I believe that the arrangements that have<br />
been developed are both fair and sensible. We have achieved<br />
that result, I believe, only because of the genuine co-operation<br />
which has been a hallmark of all the negotiations.-that have<br />
taken place between my Government and your Territory's ministers.<br />
Crucial to the move to self-government was a mutually<br />
satisfactory and effective financial agreement. While, of<br />
course, there is far more to self-government than financial<br />
matters, both the Commonwealth and your Ministers recognised<br />
that it was absolutely imperative that the new government<br />
commence its operations on a sound financial basis.<br />
I believe that the memorandum of understanding, which many<br />
of you will have read, provides just such a basis. The first<br />
Northern Territory Budget will include a considerable payment<br />
from the Commonwealth a net amount of some $ 237 million,<br />
with borrowings of a further $ 14 million.<br />
The size of this allocation was very carelully considered,<br />
and I believe it to be reasonable and responsible in the<br />
circumstances. Contributions by the Commonwealth to future<br />
budgets of Northern Territory governments will be the subject<br />
of negotiation at the time. But in the event of disagreement,<br />
the Territory government will have the right to apply for an<br />
inquiry to be made by the Commonwealth Grants Commission. / 4 </p>
<p>4<br />
That Commission is an independent body whose recommendations<br />
are given enormous weight by the Commonwealth and all the<br />
States. Neither the Commonwealth nor the Northern Territory<br />
Government will be able to direct its findingsand both<br />
governments will look to the Grants Commis ; ion as an impartial<br />
body ensuring a fair deal for the Territory.<br />
An important question for the future will be the degree of<br />
consultation and practical co-operation which is allowed<br />
to evolve between the Commonwealth Government and the<br />
government of the Northern Territory.<br />
We have already achieved a high degree of co-operation and<br />
accord with the States, and I am su're my friend the Premier<br />
of Queensland would agree with that. Far more can be achieved<br />
within a Federal system like ours by consultation than can<br />
ever be obtained by confrontation and mutual suspicion.<br />
My Government's wholehearted support for our Federal system<br />
is rooted in the belief that power needs to be shared.<br />
Authority has to be decentralised and brought closer to the<br />
people. We should not insist that all decisions should be<br />
made from Canberra.<br />
It was this approach that led us to agree to share power<br />
with. the States on off-shore matters, where previously<br />
there was disagreement and considerable friction. It was<br />
for the same reason that we have decided to consult with<br />
the States on the negotiation of international treaties<br />
which affect them, and on future appointments to the High<br />
Court. These are all innovations which previous Commonwealth<br />
Governments would not have dreamt of undertaking. I am<br />
convinced that, in most instances, much more can. be achieved<br />
to make our Federal system work responsibly and effectively<br />
by co-operation and consultation than by constant legal<br />
challenges and disputes.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen, the future of the Northern Territory<br />
is bright because its natural resources are vast, and because<br />
there are people here with a capacity for initiative, practical<br />
common sense, and plain hard work.<br />
Your recovery from the absolute devastation of Cyclone Tracey<br />
provides tangible proof that all these qualities are alive<br />
and well in the Territory. It is not so much the material<br />
recovery that I find so stimulating, but the deeper and far<br />
more important recovery that is reflected in the vitality,<br />
the cheerfulness and the camaraderie that is so obvious in<br />
this city.<br />
It i~ s these characteristics which your leaders and the members<br />
of the Legislative Assembly, vhomiwe honour tonight, will need<br />
to draw on most heavily in coping with the many problems<br />
and challenges that the future holds for you.<br />
I 00 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
