<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2626</transcript-id>
    <title>ATMOSPHERIC TESTS OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002626.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM'S NO 63/ 72<br />
ATMOSPHERIC TESTS OF NUCLEAR WEFAPONS<br />
Statement by the Prime Ministers of Australia and New Zealand, The<br />
Rt Hon. William McMahon, and The Rt Hon. J. R. Marshall, M. P.<br />
The Prime Ministers of Australia and New Zealand, meeting<br />
in Canberra today, agreed to a joint message for transmission to the<br />
Chairman of the Conference of the Committee on Disarmament in Geneva.<br />
The text of the joint message reads<br />
Upon the resumption of the meetings of the Conference<br />
of the Committee on Disarmament, it is a matter of the deepest<br />
regret that it should prove necessary for the Australian and<br />
New Zealand Prime Ministers, meeting in Canberra, to address<br />
themselves to you to express their joint protest that a<br />
further series of atmospheric tests of nuclear weapons should<br />
be imminent in the South Pacific.<br />
' Thc GOYr3= Qe-nt of France must bear the full responsibility<br />
for the decision which it has apparently taken to proceed<br />
with such tests. It does so contrary to the aopeals made<br />
to it by many Pacific countries, contrary tolthe urging of<br />
the General Assembly and contrary to the recent call by the<br />
Stockholm Conference which has especially cohdemned those<br />
tests carried out in the atmosohere.<br />
" The Australian and New Zealand Governments<br />
reflecting the grave concern felt throughout their<br />
communities and conscious that the problem of<br />
atmospheric testing in their region is part only of a<br />
broader problem;<br />
recalling . their support at the U. N. General Assembly<br />
November 1971 for resolution 2828( c), which stressed<br />
the urgency of bringing to a halt all nuclear weapon<br />
testing in all environments by all States;<br />
call jointly on the Conference of the Committee on<br />
Disarmament to continue to accord high priority to the<br />
question of the urgent need for the suspension of . such<br />
tests and the formulation of a comprehensive test ban<br />
treaty. / 2 </p>
<p>" We should be grateful if you would take steps to arrange<br />
for this message to be circulated as an official document<br />
of the Conference of the Committee on Disarmament.<br />
Signed William McMahon,<br />
Prime Minister of Australia.<br />
Canberra June 1972 J. R. Marshall<br />
Prime Minister of New Zealand.<br />
Canberra June 1972<br />
NOTE FOR PRESS:<br />
The text of the joint message has also been released to the<br />
New Zealand press. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
