<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5261</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF 12.30 NEWS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/02/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005261.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME From the Press Office SUMMARY OF 12.30 NEWS<br />
A series of bombs in Rhodesia's-capital, Salisbury, has killed at least<br />
2 people and damaged a church and a luxury hotel.<br />
In the elections so far the Rhodesian Front.-Party, led by Mr Smith,<br />
appears headed for a clean sweep for the 20 seats reserved for white<br />
voters. The rest of the 100 seats in the new Parliament will be contested<br />
by black candidates at the end of this month.<br />
The Australian Broadcasting Tribunal is to be given power to conduct a<br />
much wider range of inquiries than the present radio and television<br />
license renewal hearings. The Minister for Post and Telecommunications,<br />
Mr Staley, said today the Broadcasting and Television. Act would be<br />
amended-to enable the Tribunal to conduct general public enquiries.<br />
Mr Staley said this was a direct result from the previous round of license<br />
renewal hearings which did not satisfy anyone.<br />
Mr Staley<br />
Most people felt that they weren ' t getting a fair crack of the whip,<br />
and we believe that this new sort of inquiry will enable all the issues<br />
which are general issues as far as the public and the industry are<br />
concerned to be properly and fully canvassed and taken into account before<br />
the Tribunal makes final decisions on policies.<br />
Mr Staley said that in future people attending the inquiries would be able<br />
to comment on whether services were adequate, in a particular region. He<br />
said the new inquiry is to be more informal than license renewal hearings,<br />
could explore the broadcasting needs of particular communities. Where<br />
possible the general inquiries would preceed license hearings.<br />
The Federal Government has approved substantial increases in overseas<br />
airfares and freight charges for airlines flying out of Australia to the<br />
United States and Canada. The increases announced by Federal transport<br />
Minister, Mr Hunt, will come into effect on March 1. Mr Hunt said the<br />
Government approved the increases to counter rises in-. aviation fuel costs.<br />
More from Pat Macquire in Canberra. Under the new charges, the first<br />
class and economy fare from Australia to the United States will increase<br />
by 12.5%, while promotional fares such as Apex and Budget will rise by<br />
Between Australia and Canada, the first class and economy fare will<br />
go up by 11% and promotional fares On both routes freight rates will<br />
increase by Mr Hunt . said the increases would not affect passengers<br />
who purchase their tickets before midnight tonight, meaning people who<br />
bought tickets under the advanced purchase apex system would not be<br />
required to pay the extra charges. The increase is the fourth price over<br />
the Pacific route since the introduction of the Apex and Budget fares<br />
12 months ago. Bob Macquire, Canberra.<br />
The President of the United. States Olympic Committee says it will probably<br />
support President Carter's call for a boycott of the Moscow Olympics.<br />
Mr Robert Caines said the.-Committee's decision will be made at a meeting<br />
in April, 3 months before the Games are scheduled to begin.<br />
President Carter has repeated that unless the Soviet Union withdraws its<br />
troops from Afghanistan by February 20, neither he nor the American<br />
Congress nor the American people would support sending an Olympic team to<br />
Moscow. In other moves the Malaysian Government has reaffirmed that<br />
/-/&amp; Ropy </p>
<p>it will not send a team to Moscow and the city of London has officially<br />
abandoned its plan to stage the 1988 Games. Meanwhile, a spokesma4 for<br />
British athletes has criticised Mrs Thatcher's advice that the athletes<br />
should boycott the Olympics. The Secretary of the International Athletes<br />
Club, Derek Johnson, who won a silver medal in the 1956 Melbourne<br />
Olympics, said he would advise his Committee to support participation in<br />
the Olympics.<br />
Passengers booked on Russian cruise ships after 31 May, will have to<br />
cancel their bookings as a result of the Federal Governments ban on<br />
Russian crew ships entering Australian Ports. The Federal Minister for<br />
Transport, Mr Hunt, announced the ban on the Soviet cruise ships last<br />
night. A director of Russian CTC line said today in Sydney that about<br />
100 people were booked on cruises after 31 May.<br />
The Federal Treasurer, Mr Howard, has declined to comment on higher<br />
interest rates announced today by the ANZ Banking Group.. The Treasurer<br />
told a Liberal Party function in Brisbane it was not realistic or helpful<br />
for him to generalise or speculate on the future of interest rates in<br />
Australia. The ANZ Bank says interest from overdrafts of less than<br />
100,000 dollars will rise by from the beginning of next month.<br />
Storemen and Packers employed by Melbourne Wool brokers today voted to<br />
continue their strike in protest against thereduction of their pay rise<br />
from $ 15.90 to $ 8.<br />
A cyclone watch is now in effect ' in-the North-west of Western Australia<br />
for tropical cyclone Enid which developed early today.<br />
The 11 people accused of complicity in a murder thats become known as the<br />
case of the Handlers Corpse will appear in an English court on May 19.<br />
Three dutchmen who operated a secret laboratory in a Scottish village<br />
to produce millions of amphetemin tablets have been jailed for 12 years.<br />
The report of the inquiry into the viability of the Christmas Island<br />
Phosphate Industry is expected to be tabled in Federal Parliament next<br />
week. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
