<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9789</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, 6PR, PERTH, 10 OCTOBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009789.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
p<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH RON EDWARDS, 6PR, PERTH, 10 OCTOBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
RE: Welcome, Prime Minister<br />
PM: Ron, thanks. Very good I'm very glad to be back here.<br />
RE: We've got some good weather. You have been out to Claisebrook for<br />
the opening of part of that Better Cities program down there.<br />
PM: It's a very nice development, I think. And the thing I think is<br />
particularly good about it is that it brings the, if you like, the Eastern<br />
end of the the city, into contact again with the river.<br />
RE: That was something that was lacking.<br />
PM: Yes. Because the river sort of went around and sort of vanished<br />
anonymously.<br />
RE: Yep.<br />
PM: There's a Casino on the other side, so it sort of makes that link,<br />
doesn't it? You know, the new development makes the link down to<br />
the edge of the river, across the river onto the Casino it gives the<br />
city a continuity.<br />
RE: And importantly, I think, it expresses the role of Government in with<br />
the private sector in redeveloping our cities Government's can<br />
actually provide the vision, and the structural things. It's very difficult<br />
to ask the private sector to carry that cost always, but Government's<br />
can do that.<br />
PM: Well, I don't think an individual developer can do a thing like this.<br />
You know, cleaning up the old drains, and cleaning up a century of </p>
<p>rubbish and refuse, and pollution. But now it's done, obviously there<br />
will be more development, more housing built there, and the old<br />
factories around it will get offers they probably can't refuse and we'll<br />
see more housing. It will be a bit like, I suppose the best example is<br />
Darling Harbour in Sydney, where once the Government of NSW did<br />
a key part, they were able to do more. And that's what we thought<br />
we'd do with the Commonwealth Better Cities Program, which we<br />
have used here with Western Australia. And, of course, in Perth the<br />
other one that springs to mind is Fremantle. When I was Treasurer,<br />
we the Commonwealth Government invested about $ 30 million in<br />
Fremantle in the middle 80s, and it was then the old port city, but a lot<br />
of industrial archaeology there. And now, Fremantle is a great place.<br />
RE: All my friends who come to Perth, they always say you must go to<br />
Fremantle, because it's just got something to offer.<br />
PM: It has. And it's a lovely outlook to the city here, and a sort of social<br />
place and it really didn't exist like that before this Government put<br />
the money into it.<br />
RE: I have to raise a question Clarry Isaacs phoned me after<br />
Claisebrook and said that he'd hoped that Aboriginal people would<br />
have been invited to be part of that process. It's important, isn't it,<br />
that we involve Aboriginals in...<br />
; r P M: But they were involved. I mean, Clarry's only a grandstander, I'm<br />
afraid, and you know, they were involved in it, but they're, sort of, he<br />
was going I've got to get his permission to cross the Bridge, and all<br />
this sort of stuff, I mean, it's just basically a bit of grandstanding.<br />
RE: Yeah. So you don't take it any further than that you think that they<br />
were effectively involved in the whole process?<br />
PM; They were. Absolutely. And I mean, he had an identity problem it<br />
wasn't me he should have been railing against, it was the Premier.<br />
I'm the one supporting the Native Title Legislation.<br />
RE: Right. How are you getting on this time with your visit, in talking with<br />
the Premier?<br />
PM: Okay. I mean, I don't like his policies, and I don't like his politics. I<br />
made that clear today about Carmen Lawrence he defeated Carmen<br />
in an election, he didn't need to go after her and try to destroy her<br />
personally.<br />
RE; Might he not say that he was entitled to find out whether or not she<br />
told the truth to the Parliament and the public? </p>
<p>PM: Not at all entitled. I mean, what how would he go if I said well,<br />
listen, I'm entitled to know what went on in the Howard Cabinets the<br />
Fraser/ Howard Cabinets you know, why John Howard let all those<br />
bottom of the harbour schemes go on for a few years, and we'll see<br />
what each Cabinet Minister said to one another. They would be<br />
screaming blue murder. And if he wanted to do that, why didn't he<br />
put . the Liberals who represented Penny Easton's interests in the<br />
Parliament for 2 years, Masters and the other chap?<br />
RE: Lightfoot.<br />
PM: That's right Lightfoot. I think it was Masters or Lightfoot who said on<br />
radio here a couple of weeks ago a month ago quite brazenly, oh<br />
no, we were representing Penny's interests, and we spoke to her and<br />
she said no, I want you to go on. But the Premier puts the Terms of<br />
Reference together, but only about when Brian Easton wanted to put<br />
his views. But I thought the Clerk of the Upper House said it all, Mr<br />
Marquet, he said it is his view I don't think I'm mis-quoting there<br />
was a question of propriety about whether the then Premier Carmen<br />
Lawrence should have intervened to stop Mr Haviland presenting<br />
the petition. In other words, Mr Easton had a right to put his views to<br />
the Parliament in a petition, and it would have been improper to have<br />
interrupted or intervened in that process. And that is essentially what<br />
I think the Clerk said, and that was a key point. I think it was the key<br />
point I mean, these were the things also that were said by Mr Gyles<br />
yesterday in the summing up. So, it was a spiteful little exercise, I<br />
mean....<br />
RE: But it damaged Carmen Lawrence, though?<br />
PM: Richard Court said today oh, we don't attack people personally over<br />
here, he said, responding to my comments today. No he's only<br />
attacked her with a $ 5 million Royal Commission.<br />
RE: But he has damaged her politically?<br />
PM: Well, he's attacked her personally by arraigning the State against her<br />
with a $ 5 million Royal Commission it's the worst personal attack in<br />
history, in this country, I think.<br />
RE: So you will repudiate any of the findings from Commissioner Marks?<br />
PM: Look, I think that if the Commissioner picks up the points Mr Gyles<br />
made yesterday, that it's immaterial whether Carmen Lawrence knew<br />
these things or not, the key question is did Mr Easton have a right to<br />
present a petition to Parliament? The answer is he did. Was the<br />
petition presented correctly was it a breach of the privileges of<br />
Parliament? A Committee of the Parliament said no, it wasn't. And<br />
the Clerk has called in to question the rights of anybody to actually </p>
<p>interfere with the presentation of a petition. Now, I think that if the<br />
Royal Commissioner keeps on those points, he can't go wrong.<br />
RE: Right. If you had to sum up your tactics in the Parliament in relation<br />
to the Royal Commission, do you think they were successful, because<br />
certainly you took a strong line, didn't you?<br />
PM: I did. There was no I mean, chit-chats in Cabinets or Cabinet anterooms<br />
about what Ministers say, and then opening up like with some<br />
sort of can-opener the whole question of Ministerial responsibility and<br />
Cabinet secrecy once you throw those things out, you throw out the<br />
whole workings of a Westminster style Government. See, if now no<br />
Cabinet Minister in Western Australia can say well if I say this in the<br />
Cabinet Room, how do I know that I won't be called to account for<br />
these words in some Royal Commission in 3 years time? I mean, I<br />
had better shut up I had better be quiet. And once that enters into<br />
our into the free-flow of debate in the Cabinet, who is running the<br />
place, and how can it be run? And that's what Richard Court see,<br />
the Liberals always do this they break all the standards of Australian<br />
politics. They did it in 1975 by refusing supply in the Senate, he has<br />
done it now by breaching the confidentiality of the Cabinet with a<br />
Royal Commission, and he has done it by chasing out an opponent<br />
who has done nothing illegal, created no misdemeanour, but by<br />
arraigning a Royal Commission against them. In other words, they<br />
always if they have a choice of doing what is right and wrong, they<br />
will take the wrong course.<br />
RE: You have mentioned the question of conventions do you think that<br />
when you began to debate the Royal Commission in the Parliament,<br />
you may have broken a convention, because at that stage that really<br />
was the case?<br />
PM: No. No Mr Howard before I debated it, John Howard was asking<br />
me questions about things that Mr Kovaks had said. They were using<br />
all of the testimony in their questions. And how dare I refer to this.<br />
So what I did was read the transcript. I said well, listen, I want to get<br />
your point of objection clear about this you don't want me to read the<br />
transcript of the Royal Commission, but the Royal Commissioner<br />
publishes the transcript on a disc every afternoon. And the media<br />
can read it, and the journalists can read but what? The Parliament<br />
can't? Is that what you're saying? You know, their objections fell to<br />
nothing.<br />
RE: Right. You mentioned John Howard if I can paint this picture to you:<br />
you were at the Rugby League Grand Final there following the<br />
Canterbury Bankstown Bulldogs, I still call them that, like to call them<br />
that.<br />
PM: The Bulldogs. </p>
<p>RE: Yeah. And they weren't really the favourites at the time, they had a<br />
difficult year, and in fact, if anything you would say they were a bit<br />
behind Manly when it came to the game, but in the end they won.<br />
PM: They did.<br />
RE: Do you see yourself in that role, a bit like up against John Howard<br />
that you have had a difficult year, you're not in front....<br />
PM: Except but I haven't got a champion to beat, have I? I mean, he's<br />
not a world-beater.<br />
RE: Dogged?<br />
PM: I mean, no he's just stuck around. He's been around for<br />
years, and that's about it. I mean, today on radio in Adelaide he<br />
said he got asked by an interviewer, what do you think will<br />
Industrial Relations be the big election issue, the big issue in this<br />
election? And Mr Howard said no, I think the big issue will be that the<br />
nation should be led by a new group of people. Not a group of<br />
people that have got ideas, or a group of people that have got<br />
policies that they will publish, not a group of people who understand<br />
that we live in Asia, but by a group of people presumably who don't<br />
want to know about Asia. And a new group new people like John<br />
Howard, who was a Minister 20 years ago, and John Moore, who was<br />
a Minister 20 years ago. I mean, it is going to take more for John<br />
Howard to say I want my turn. You remember Ron, in the Parliament,<br />
I used to mock him and say in this perennial debate and contest he<br />
had with Andrew Peacock, I used to say John's view is Andrew got 2<br />
turns, so he wanted 2 turns. Andrew got 2 turns at the leadership, he<br />
wanted 2 turns. Now he's saying, look, basically our policy is that it's<br />
our turn. Our policy is at the coming election, you should vote for us<br />
because it's our turn. This other lot have had 5 elections on the trot,<br />
and it's our turn. And we say hang on Mr Howard, what about your<br />
policies? ( and he would say] oh well, I'm keeping those quiet until the<br />
last gasp of the election campaign". And can I say, what was said<br />
today by Cheryl Kernot, I endorse and that is, she said the<br />
Democrats won't respect any mandate a Coalition Government will<br />
have unless the people could actually see the policies they are<br />
elected upon.<br />
RE: Do you think that John Howard is being very smart, and not making<br />
the mistake of John Hewson laying it all out, and in fact, keeping it<br />
very quiet? And to that extent, it's making it more difficult for you? I<br />
mean, they think it's probably working.<br />
PM: But I don't think it does, Ron. I don't think the public want sneaky<br />
behaviour. I mean, there's Andrew Robb two Sunday's ago on the </p>
<p>Sunday program saying we have our policies 98% prepared. Well, if<br />
that's the case, why not show the public? I mean, aren't the public<br />
entitled to see what the leader of a major party, the direction in which<br />
he will take the country? Now, he's saying no. On the other hand,<br />
the Government publishes budgets full of details. When I published<br />
the blueprint for the republic full of structure and details, you know.<br />
Accord Mark VIII with the Unions, low inflation, full of structure and<br />
detail. And he thinks he can slide through slip under the wire on<br />
polling day saying " look, I'll give you 5 minutes glance at these<br />
policies, and away I'll go". But, as I squeeze him to actually put some<br />
out, you can see he doesn't represent much. He had one last week<br />
on defence policy. And what was he basically saying? That we<br />
should be very wary of South East Asia because they could still be<br />
enemies. We have got to cuddle up to the United States. Now, you<br />
have a look at Western Australia Ron, what we have done we have<br />
made HMAS Stirling the major west coast base of Australia. Before<br />
that, it was all in Sydney. The Liberals used to have the tanks at<br />
Puckapunyal as if we were going to be attacked from Antarctica, or<br />
somewhere like that. We have now got them arraigned in Northern<br />
Australia we have got these bases across the North places like<br />
Tindal. And we have got Singapore doing its flying training here in<br />
Western Australia, its tank training in Queensland, we have had<br />
Kangaroo 95 exercises with the Indonesian Army, and the United<br />
States but John Howard doesn't like any of that. So when he<br />
actually puts a policy out, the speech he made on foreign affairs and<br />
defence, could have been written by Harold Holt. It could have been<br />
spoken by Harold Holt in 1967 or 1966.<br />
So, I think that I can see why he doesn't want the policies out there,<br />
because when he puts them out a week ago, before that, he took a<br />
view about Mascot airport. And you might say well, in Perth what<br />
matters to us here about Mascot airport? Well, simply this he says,<br />
Mr Howard says, I'm the leader to crack the last of the tough nuts:<br />
our waterfront, courts, industrial relations, but what happens? On<br />
Mascot he gets a bit of pressure in his own seat of Bennelong which<br />
he holds by 3.5% and he wants to cut Mascot's capacity back by<br />
This is the gateway to Australia this is the port on which all<br />
the others work. You know, and what it reveals is the first bit of<br />
pressure, and down he goes. So, he doesn't want to publish policies,<br />
but it's very interesting I thought today that it was very revealing<br />
when asked well, what do you think will be the big issue in the<br />
election campaign Mr Howard, he's saying I think it's time we were led<br />
by a new group of people. Essentially, he's saying he's trying to run<br />
the " It's Time" theme of 1972. The difference was that Gough<br />
Whitlam was a real leader, and Bill McMahon wasn't. Here, I hope,<br />
the reverse is the case. </p>
<p>RE: We, incidentally, did ask John Howard to come on today he's in<br />
Adelaide, and he said he's too busy. We've got the Prime Minister<br />
Paul Keating with us.<br />
( ad break)<br />
RE: Paul, industrial relations, do you support the trade union blockade of<br />
Western Australia that is foreshadowed?<br />
PM: I got asked this question earlier Ron, and I made this point that this<br />
year we have got the lowest number of industrial disputes in Australia<br />
since 1940. That is seven working days lost per thousand workers.<br />
When John Howard was last the Treasurer it was 690 days lost per<br />
thousand worker. That is 70 compared to 690. It is an era of almost<br />
unprecedented industrial peace and the reason that is there is<br />
because we have a co-operative policy in place under the Accord with<br />
the trade unions, that we run Australia at about 4 per cent growth,<br />
strong employment growth and they do sensible things on wages. But,<br />
there is no reason for industrial disputation in Australia. The fact that it<br />
is on here is because of very unfair industrial relations policies by Mr<br />
Court and Mr Kierath and the Western Australian Government. They<br />
are going for peoples' throats and they are protesting.<br />
RE: It does lead you to the ultimate difficulty though doesn't it, that they<br />
have got a tactic on which is to put on an economic blockade in<br />
Western Australia. The Opposition Leader Jim McGinty says he is<br />
pretty uncomfortable with that. Would you similarly be uncomfortable?<br />
PM: I have spent 12 years being uncomfortable with those tactics, but you<br />
have got to be fair dinkum, you have got to be decent about these<br />
things. If there was decent policies here this tactic wouldn't be there.<br />
If there was decency being shown here by Mr Kierath and others these<br />
people would not be proposing these policies.<br />
RE: Did it worry you what Mick Young had to say to the backbench, that is<br />
that the blue collar vote, the workers of Australia were deserting the<br />
Government. That in fact after some time of enterprise bargaining<br />
there was a feeling that no matter what happened their conditions were<br />
going to be worse and that they responded to that.<br />
PM: I think they did in Queensland, but I certainly don't think that is a view<br />
shared nationally. Yesterday I spoke to the CFMEU the<br />
Construction, Forestry, Mining, Energy workers union in NSW the<br />
bluest of blue collar type unions, I don't find anything but generally<br />
warm support. Basically because the Government has delivered on<br />
the key commitments it made. At the last election, the most solemn<br />
commitment I made was to restore the economy back to growth and to<br />
employment. We have had since then 16 consecutive quarters of<br />
growth when in the quarter we are now living in, Ron, when those </p>
<p>numbers are published in November we will have the longest growth<br />
phase since the Second World War. The longest continuous growth<br />
phase since the Second World War. That was the key commitment I<br />
gave. The other commitment was employment, to not leave the<br />
unemployed behind. We have 680,000 job growth and the other thing<br />
we committed ourselves to was a fair industrial relations act which we<br />
introduced and we have now got enterprise bargaining and under that<br />
the safety net. If you can't get an enterprise bargain you get an $ 8<br />
increase or a $ 10 increase under the safety net.<br />
Now, in the enterprise bargains we had a thing called the no<br />
disadvantage test. A group of employees in a union can sit down with<br />
the business and say ' look, we will dispense with certain conditions<br />
providing it is compensated in the pay.' So, the test is applied so that<br />
there is no disadvantage. In other words, the working person doesn't<br />
come away from an enterprise bargain less well off. They can come<br />
away better off, but not less well off. Now, of course, Mr Howard wants<br />
none of this. Mr Court wants none of it. Mr Kierath none of it. As a<br />
consequence I think that we have got a lively debate, but I certainly<br />
don't accept the view that blue collar workers are leaving the Labor<br />
Party. Can I just make this point, I don't think blue collar workers are any<br />
different from white collar workers or any other worker. They want the<br />
policies be implemented that they believe are actually best for<br />
Australia. The idea that you can segment them out is so manipulative,<br />
that we can segment you out and say ' well, you are a blue collarie, so<br />
you have only got these interests' and if they get fixed up you will be<br />
right. Blue collar people have the interest of the country at heart in the<br />
broadest sense its identity, its ethos, its values, its place in the world<br />
and they look at all of those things,, not just industrial relations.<br />
RE: Is industrial relations going to be for you this time what the GST was<br />
last time. That is the clear dividing line between yourself and the<br />
Opposition?<br />
PM: Again, there is a lot of rewriting of policy here, Ron. Not by you but by<br />
commentators. The last election was won by the Government because<br />
we believed in a broad, inclusive Australian society. The GST was just<br />
an example of the unfairness. It wasn't won on the GST. It was won<br />
across the board and across the board it will be won again. You see, I<br />
think that when people say that industrial relations will be the major<br />
issue in an election campaign, in fact they understate the case<br />
because what we think about industrial relations defines our ideas of<br />
Australia. That is, what sort of people we are, what sort of society we<br />
should become. It is not just about pay rates. It is the values we have.<br />
I think they measure how much we actually believe in the ties that bind<br />
us as Australians. In other words, the right to a job, the right to decent<br />
rates of pay, the relationship between employers and employees is </p>
<p>part of the bindings of Australia. It is not just a narrow thing about<br />
money and wages. This the Coalition do not understand.<br />
Can I say, at the moment the profit share in the economy that is, the<br />
proportion of national income going to profits is right up against the<br />
historic precedent having no historic precedent. So, what is Mr<br />
Kierath and Mr Court saying? That they want to cut the wages of<br />
working people? I just visited the nurses today. They can't get a<br />
safety net increase of There is nothing rational about that, it is just<br />
spiteful.<br />
RE: Graeme Kierath says he wants to debate you about industrial relations.<br />
PM: Yes, but when I get down to debating State Ministers, Ron, I'd have<br />
them hanging around my legs wouldn't 1, from one end of the country<br />
to the other.<br />
RE: He says his dispute is not with workers, it is with only union officials.<br />
PM: He says that, but he is quite happy to take a group of nurses, nurses of<br />
all people, and firstly oppose them getting a safety net increase of $ 8<br />
which is now a year late and secondly remove from them penalty rates,<br />
overtime rates. I gave the figures today, most nurses work weekends,<br />
part of a weekend or work at times out of normal working times. If you<br />
take them back to ordinary rates, they lose about 20-25 per cent of<br />
their income. It is just vindictive and mean spirited.<br />
RE: If I can take us for a moment on the question of refugees. It has been<br />
said that the Government has been mean spirited towards East<br />
Timorese refugees, that we should be taking them because we have a<br />
responsibility the Indonesian Goverrnent has not behaved well in<br />
that occupied territory and that we should have a special role in<br />
dealing with them. What is your response to that?<br />
PM: We have very clear laws in this country about refugees. Refugees are<br />
treated well here. There is a whole legal. process that has been<br />
negotiated, in a sense, between the government and the courts. As<br />
various pieces of legislation have been tested in the federal court we<br />
now have a regime were people are assessed for refugee status.<br />
Timorese people have Portuguese citizenship. So, they have no<br />
refugee status though the Government has taken the view that Timor is<br />
part of Indonesia, is a province of Indonesia, those people still have<br />
Portuguese citizenship status.<br />
RE: Isn't that effectively saying what the Indonesians could therefore do is<br />
deport them all to Portugal then if we were to follow that line?<br />
PM: Some people in Australia will still have, for instance, citizenship in<br />
other countries in Great Britain many people in Perth would have an </p>
<p>Australian passport and a British passport. They would have<br />
Australian citizenship and they would have British citizenship they<br />
would have dual citizenship. These people have dual citizenship<br />
therefore they cannot argue that they are refugees.<br />
RE: I have never felt comfortable about East Timor though since the<br />
invasion period, I think Australia probably owed Timor a bit more and<br />
we should have given them a bit more and this maybe is one of those<br />
tests.<br />
PM: But what happened, 20 years ago there was a civil war going on in<br />
Timor. The Portuguese did nothing with the place, they left it<br />
undeveloped and had it gone to a free vote, it is often argued, that the<br />
people there would have voted for incorporation of Timor into<br />
Indonesia. As it was Indonesia annexed Timor. Here is an island in<br />
the archipelago in a state of civil war with the Portuguese, just about<br />
the worst colonial power, and people were surprised in the final<br />
analysis that it was annexed and incorporated into Indonesia. It may<br />
have gone that way in a free vote, but Australia has a relationship with<br />
Indonesia which is built on many foundations. It is a nation of 190<br />
million people. It is a nation of great diversity, of great diversity in the<br />
cultures and there is, I think, a substantial tolerance that exists<br />
between the interaction of those cultures in that very complex country.<br />
RE: Would you hope to get relations with Malaysia onto as good a level as<br />
we have with Indonesia?<br />
PM: Can I just say this about Indonesia, we can't throw it up the flue and<br />
say well look, because we don't like all the things that are going on in<br />
Timor we will rupture the relationship with you across the board. I<br />
have never believed that was in. Australia's interests. But what we<br />
have because we have a stronger relationship with Indonesia we do<br />
push the case very solidly about Timor. When ever I get the<br />
opportunity to speak to President Soeharto I raise these issues and I<br />
am quite happy too. But we can't have a phoney campaign about<br />
refugee status for people who enjoy the citizenship of Portugal.<br />
RE: So, would you like to have the relationship with Dr Mahithir in Malaysia<br />
that you have got with President Soeharto?<br />
PM: I haven't got a bad relationship with Dr Mahithir. It is a-co-operative<br />
one, Australia is doing a lot with Malaysia and I think doing it cooperatively<br />
and reasonably well. They are all important to us. A few<br />
moments ago: I made-reference. to what Mr Howard-said, but I would<br />
just like to get this point across to people. He said that there were<br />
unresolved, tensions between the Government's focus on defence<br />
partnerships for instance, flying training by the Singaporeans,<br />
Indonesians coming to Kangaroo 95 tensions between the<br />
Government's focus on defence partnerships with the region versus<br />
~~ rj~ </p>
<p>the region as a potential source of threats. This is simply code<br />
language for fear of south-east Asia.<br />
Why should Australians not have a good relationship with our largest<br />
nearest neighbour Indonesia? It is imperative we have it, with<br />
Malaysia, with Singapore, with Vietnam. John Howard wouldn't see<br />
the leader of Vietnam when he came here two months ago, but that<br />
person Do Muoi went home to meet the US Secretary of State.<br />
This idea that we reject the community around us, we live in an<br />
isolation and then we run off to Washington and say ' please look after<br />
our interests', I mean, is a dreadful way to protect the security of<br />
Australians and to lose that engagement.<br />
RE: Final quickly, employment for over 50s, there is a problem of<br />
unemployment for over 50s. Can we make a special effort to do<br />
something about that, we were talking about that earlier today?<br />
PM: This is what we introduced Working Nation for and that we are now<br />
starting to get very large effects from it. This year we have had about<br />
400,000 job growth, of that 400,000, 100,000 has gone to the longer<br />
term unemployed because we are now case managing these people.<br />
We can now get to find out about their aptitudes, their work<br />
experience, what they are doing, give them a job subsidy and get them<br />
moving. In that huge employment growth we have had in the last two<br />
or three years, we are starting to make inroads into both the younger<br />
and the older unemployed groups as we have never done before.<br />
RE: Paul, it is good to see you, earlier I mentioned the grand final involving<br />
Canterbury-Bankstown and Manly, are we getting to the finals time in<br />
terms of elections. Are we building towards that and how far off in the<br />
future is it?<br />
PM: Ron, I have had three Opposition Leaders now in this Parliament Dr<br />
Hewson, Mr Downer and Mr Howard all saying we are going to an<br />
early election. Well, here we are in October 1995 and the Parliament<br />
expires about March or April of 1996 and we still haven't had an<br />
election because I don't think the public appreciate governments being<br />
tricky with them. They don't want Prime Minister's who are tricky with<br />
them trying to call polls, to slip past the Opposition in a bad phase or<br />
something like that. I have always thought the Parliament should run<br />
its full term.<br />
RE: OK, Paul Keating, thanks for joining us. Good to see you in Perth.<br />
PM: Good, Ron.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
