<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15473</transcript-id>
    <title>Allan Taylor AM</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/06/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I was greatly saddened to hear of the death yesterday of Allan Taylor, AM, one of Australia's most distinguished former diplomats and public servants.</p>
<p>Allan joined the then Department of External Affairs in 1966. His early diplomatic service was in Islamabad, Bangkok and Jakarta. He served as High Commissioner to Nigeria and High Commissioner to Papua New Guinea. His diplomatic career culminated when he returned to Indonesia to serve as Ambassador between 1993 and 1996, at a challenging time in the bilateral relationship. He also filled various senior positions in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet.</p>
<p>Allan's final government appointment before his retirement was as Director-General of the Australian Secret Intelligence Service from 1998 to 2003.</p>
<p>He was appointed as a Member in the General Division of the Order of Australia in 1995 and was a recipient of the Centenary Medal in 2003. He was chairman of the Australia-Indonesia Institute and a member of the National Archives of Australia Advisory Council. </p>
<p>I came to know Allan well during his period as the head of the International Division in my Department. I respected him enormously for his experience, his quiet assurance and above all his exceptionally sound judgment. I have no doubt that Allan's success as a diplomat owed much to the tact, understated style and unaffected charm that all who knew him will remember with great fondness. He brought these attributes to each of the many important roles he filled with such dedication and distinction.</p>
<p>On behalf of the government I wish to put on record my warm appreciation for a life of service to Australia's national interests and to her people.</p>
<p>Our thoughts and prayers are with Carol and Allan's family.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
