<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22181</transcript-id>
    <title>2006 Prime Minister&#039;s Awards for Excellence in Community Business Partnerships  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that nominations are now open for the 2006 Prime Minister's Awards for Excellence in Community Business Partnerships.  These awards recognise the significant social benefits achieved when business and community groups work together.</p>
<p>Businesses working in partnership with community groups are helping to tackle many of the social and environmental issues that affect our society.</p>
<p> Community organisations have become more adept at harnessing business resources to support social objectives while also lifting their profile in the wider community.  Together they are helping to improve our communities and enhance the nation.</p>
<p>The awards celebrate the efforts and achievements of the most successful business and community partnerships and the valuable role they play in dealing with social and environmental issues.</p>
<p>Through the awards, which began in 1999, more than 1000 partnerships have been identified and encouraged.  Past national winners have come from across Australia and the recipients have become role models for their communities and other business groups.</p>
<p>Each year these partnerships are becoming more varied, ambitious and far-reaching in their positive impact on the community.</p>
<p> In addition to the state and national awards, three special awards will be presented to:   the business that, through its partnership, has had the greatest positive impact on its community;    the media organisation that has most prominently and positively reported on community business partnerships and corporate social responsibility; and    an outstanding partnership that has been operating for more than five years.</p>
<p>Winners will receive their awards at a special ceremony and dinner.  Each winning partnership will receive $10,000 for the their community program or project.</p>
<p> Nomination forms and further information are available at: <a href="http://www.partnerships.gov.au">www.partnerships.gov.au</a> or Freecall 1800 102 014.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
