<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10889</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER             THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO 500 CLUB LUNCHEON, PERTH</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................................................................................................</p>
<p>To my friend and colleague Richard Court, to Mr Peter Middleton,</p>
<p>   my other state and federal parliamentary colleagues, ladies and</p>
<p>   gentlemen.</p>
<p>As always it's a huge delight to be in Western Australia.</p>
<p>   And as always as Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia,</p>
<p>   I acknowledge very genuinely the immense contribution, particularly</p>
<p>   at this time, because of the importance of export income to Australia,</p>
<p>   I acknowledge the tremendous contribution of the State of Western</p>
<p>   Australia to Australia's aggregate national wealth. And I particularly</p>
<p>   acknowledge the leadership over decades that has been displayed</p>
<p>   by coalition governments in relation to the development of the resource</p>
<p>   sector of Western Australia. And the announcement to which Richard</p>
<p>   referred a few moments ago is yet the latest in a long list of resource</p>
<p>   projects which if they had not been developed and there had not</p>
<p>   been the visionary leadership in this state on our side of politics</p>
<p>   to develop, the Australian nation today would be the poorer and</p>
<p>   all of its citizens would be more vulnerable to the uncertainties</p>
<p>   of a hostile global economy. </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen there are a number of reasons why it's</p>
<p>   always a delight to be in Western Australia and why it's important</p>
<p>   as Prime Minister of the entire country that one regularly visits</p>
<p>   every part of the Commonwealth. One of the reasons of course as</p>
<p>   many of you will remember is that my predecessor systematically</p>
<p>   insulted the State of Western Australia by going for a period of</p>
<p>   I think of almost twelve months between visits. And one of the things</p>
<p>   that I resolved to do when I became Prime Minister was to visit</p>
<p>   this State on a very regular basis to meet the business community,</p>
<p>   to hear their concerns, to take their advice - or at least listen</p>
<p>   to it - and sometimes to take it. And to meet the people of Western</p>
<p>   Australia. And also if I had any spare time to do the odd bit of</p>
<p>   campaigning for my federal colleagues who hold such a high proportion</p>
<p>   of the seats in this State. </p>
<p>I want today to say something about the economic fundamentals of</p>
<p>   Australia. For reasons you will understand I am not going to explore</p>
<p>   future levels of anything. But I am going to say something about</p>
<p>   the fundamentals of the Australian economy because it's very</p>
<p>   important we understand how strong our economy really is. And when</p>
<p>   I make the claim and when Peter Costello makes the claim that our</p>
<p>   economic foundations are stronger now than they have been for twenty</p>
<p>   five years that is no idle piece of political rhetoric. </p>
<p>We do have the lowest inflation rate in the western world. We do</p>
<p>   have a strong level of business investment. We do have a situation</p>
<p>   where, having inherited a budget deficit courtesy of Mr Beazley</p>
<p>   of $10.5billion, in just two years in three Budgets we have turned</p>
<p>   that into a surplus of $2.7billion. And I take the opportunity of</p>
<p>   congratulating Peter Costello as my Treasurer for the excellent</p>
<p>   job that he's done in the economic management of Australia.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen some people at the moment are making comparisons</p>
<p>   between Australia now and Australia in 1986 when my predecessor</p>
<p>   as Prime Minister, then as Treasurer, made that chance remark from</p>
<p>   the kitchen somewhere in Victoria when he was talking on the telephone</p>
<p>   to John Laws, it was later elevated into a very carefully designed,</p>
<p>   politically shrewd remark - in fact it was an off the cuff observation</p>
<p>   - about Australia becoming a banana republic. Now I think it's</p>
<p>   worth me running through a few comparisons between Australia then</p>
<p>   and Australia now. And I think it's very relevant to the economic</p>
<p>   debate which is taking place at present. In mid 1986 our inflation</p>
<p>   rate was 8.8%, our underlying inflation rate is now 1.5% and the</p>
<p>   headline inflation rate is the remarkable minus at .2%. The current</p>
<p>   account deficit is forecast now to be 5.25% of GDP - it was well</p>
<p>   above 6.5% in the mid 1980s. In the mid 1980s we had a budget deficit</p>
<p>   of 2% of GDP, we now have a surplus of 0.5% of GDP. Our debt servicing</p>
<p>   ratio - a very very important measure of long term economic strength</p>
<p>   internationally - our debt servicing ratio was 15.3% in the mid</p>
<p>   1980s - it is now 10.8%. And our terms of trade in 1998 are significantly</p>
<p>   better than what they were in the mid 1980s. </p>
<p>Now I mention those figures ladies and gentlemen not to burden</p>
<p>   you with a lot of statistics but merely to make the observation</p>
<p>   that the underlying strengths of the Australian economy now are</p>
<p>   the soundest that they have been for a very long period of time</p>
<p>   and they are infinitely more sound and more durable and more beckoning</p>
<p>   to the rest of the world than what they were in the mid 1980s. It</p>
<p>   is obvious that if we had not taken the measures we took when we</p>
<p>   came to office in March of 1996, the Australian economy now would</p>
<p>   have been infinitely more at risk than it is. And I do invite you</p>
<p>   for a moment to contemplate what would have happened to economic</p>
<p>   management in this country if we had not taken the measures that</p>
<p>   we took in 1996. </p>
<p>Can you imagine where we would be now if we had persisted with</p>
<p>   running a budget deficit of $10.5billion a year, if we had not tackled</p>
<p>   the accumulated debt of $95-100billion a year. Can you imagine where</p>
<p>   we would be if we had to set out to reform our industrial relations</p>
<p>   system, that if we had pretended that the Beazley/Keating approach</p>
<p>   of constantly running up debt was the only way forward for Australia.</p>
<p>   And in view of everything that has happened, particularly in the</p>
<p>   Asia Pacific Region, I can't stress too strongly how weakened</p>
<p>   and vulnerable and enfeebled the Australian economy would have been</p>
<p>   under that kind of leadership and indeed how much stronger and better</p>
<p>   placed it is under the sort of leadership that it's been given</p>
<p>   over the past two and a quarter years. </p>
<p>And of course in that context one has to contemplate the prospect</p>
<p>   of handing over the management of the Australian economy to the</p>
<p>   treasuryship of Gareth Evans. Of handing over the management of</p>
<p>   the Australian economy to people who fought tooth and nail every</p>
<p>   measure that my Government took to restore the strength of the Australian</p>
<p>   economy after it was elected to office. Not only did our Labor predecessors</p>
<p>   create the problem and leave it behind for us to fix, but they set</p>
<p>   about systematically trying to stop us fixing the problem. Because</p>
<p>   if you go through the records of the current Parliament, you will</p>
<p>   find that virtually every single measure that we took to get the</p>
<p>   budget into surplus was in fact fought by the Australian Labor Party</p>
<p>   and if they had had their way they would have perpetuated the economic</p>
<p>   legacy that they bequeathed to us in March of 1996.</p>
<p>Now I mention these things ladies and gentlemen because in the</p>
<p>   nature of political combat people are going to be making judgements</p>
<p>   about economic performance over the next few months. Of course we</p>
<p>   have an election in this country sometime between now and when the</p>
<p>   election is constitutionally due. Now I hope all the ladies and</p>
<p>   gentlemen of the press got that because that's the story out</p>
<p>   of today. We will eventually have an election. When that is of course</p>
<p>   is something that is yet to be resolved. But it is important, as</p>
<p>   we draw close to that election whenever it is, that we do remember</p>
<p>   what the situation was in March of 1996, we contemplate what my</p>
<p>   Government has done to turn that situation around and we also properly</p>
<p>   ask the question, what would have happened if the former Government</p>
<p>   had stayed in office and what might happen if it were returned to</p>
<p>   office at the next election. Labor would be a huge economic risk.</p>
<p>   It's track record demonstrates that and nothing which is being</p>
<p>   said in the two and a quarter years that we have been in Government</p>
<p>   alters my view on that and I notice that Mr Beazley today said that</p>
<p>   he had been Prime Minister over the last couple of years unemployment</p>
<p>   would have been down to 6%. It's funny that in the time that</p>
<p>   he had a go he got a post-Depression level of 11.2% and at average</p>
<p>   8.7% over the whole time that his party was in Government.</p>
<p>But ladies and gentlemen, having said something about the fundamentals</p>
<p>   of the Australian economy I want to narrow my focus of my speech</p>
<p>   to two very important issues. And one of those is the issue of taxation</p>
<p>   reform. We need self evidently as a nation to build our competitiveness</p>
<p>   to the maximum extent possible. The past few weeks, the past few</p>
<p>   days, the past few months, have driven home like perhaps no other</p>
<p>   set of circumstances have driven home the reality that we live in</p>
<p>   a globalised economy. Some of us might wish it otherwise. Some of</p>
<p>   us might like to believe you could turn the clock back and you could</p>
<p>   return to a nostalgic era when we weren't in a global economy.</p>
<p>   Whether we like it or not that is just not possible and in order</p>
<p>   for this country to survive and to prosper and to build the living</p>
<p>   standards of Australians all over our continent what we have to</p>
<p>   do above everything else is to be competitive. And every single</p>
<p>   measure that my Government has taken over the past two and a quarter</p>
<p>   years has been designed to build the strengths of the Australian</p>
<p>   economy and to improve its competitiveness. That is why we set about</p>
<p>   curing a budget deficit. That is why we have set about reforming</p>
<p>   the industrial relations system. But there is one great untouched</p>
<p>   area of economic reform which is crying aloud for attention. It</p>
<p>   is crying aloud for attention like no other area of economic reform</p>
<p>   and that is the overwhelming need to reform Australia's increasingly</p>
<p>   outdated and old fashioned taxation system. This is a cause that</p>
<p>   I have spoken about on many occasions in the past in the various</p>
<p>   positions I have held other than that of Prime Minister. It's</p>
<p>   got a lot of form, it's got a lot of track record and it's</p>
<p>   got a lot of history - the taxation debate in this country. It was</p>
<p>   attempted in the early 1980s by the then Treasurer in the Fraser</p>
<p>   Government and he was unsuccessful. It was attempted by the then</p>
<p>   Treasurer in the Hawke Labor Government and he was also unsuccessful.</p>
<p>   It was attempted by John Hewson as Leader of the Coalition in 1993</p>
<p>   and it was also unsuccessful so far as the electorate was concerned.</p>
<p>   Now I guess with that sort of track record the hypothetical man</p>
<p>   from Mars would say: why on earth would anybody be stupid</p>
<p>   enough to attempt it again?'. Now that's not a bad question</p>
<p>   - on the surface. Well let me examine it for a moment. Let me put</p>
<p>   to you very seriously that if you care about the future of this</p>
<p>   country and if you care about its future economic security and competitiveness,</p>
<p>   this is really the last great opportunity, perhaps in the political</p>
<p>   and business experience of most in this room to achieve taxation</p>
<p>   reform.</p>
<p>We have a rather rigid political system at the moment where it's</p>
<p>   every difficult for one side of politics to get control of both</p>
<p>   Houses of Parliament. In fact that hasn't been the case since</p>
<p>   the middle of 1981 and the prospect of that changing under the current</p>
<p>   electoral system is just about zero. Now some people say to me "oh,</p>
<p>   John, forget about this taxation reform, what you ought to do is</p>
<p>   to go the election on your policies on your record, talk a bit about</p>
<p>   Labor say how bad they are and invite the public to put you back</p>
<p>   and if anybody says anything to you about taxation promise them</p>
<p>   a meeting." Now that of course is what Bob Hawke did in 1984.</p>
<p>   But ladies and gentlemen I can't do that and what's more</p>
<p>   I won't do that and the reason that I can't and won't</p>
<p>   do that is that the Australian public would treat it with justifiable</p>
<p>   contempt.</p>
<p>They would say that this man and his Treasurer have gone around</p>
<p>   the country over the past few months and told us that taxation reform</p>
<p>   was necessary and desirable and now when they get a bit close to</p>
<p>   the event and the heat is on they go to water. But there's</p>
<p>   another reason why you can't solve it by having a meeting and</p>
<p>   that is that there's absolutely no prospect that you'd</p>
<p>   get agreement at the meeting. At the end of the day governments</p>
<p>   are elected to make decisions, they are elected to govern, they</p>
<p>   are elected to give a lead on fundamental political and economic</p>
<p>   reform. And what is more if we did have a meeting and we came up</p>
<p>   with some mish-mash out of that meeting we'd then have to have</p>
<p>   an election because there is no way that the Opposition parties</p>
<p>   in the Senate would vote in favour of the proposal that might come</p>
<p>   out of that meeting.</p>
<p>So however you look at it, politically, economically and strategically?</p>
<p>   The imperative is that we present to the Australian people - as</p>
<p>   we will - a comprehensive taxation reform plan before the election.</p>
<p>   Now I know it is difficult and I know there will be a scare campaign</p>
<p>   and I know that Kim Beazley, despite the fact that he wholeheartedly</p>
<p>   supported Paul Keating's 12.5 consumption tax in 1986 and Gareth</p>
<p>   Evans threw down his glasses and his papers after two days of discussion</p>
<p>   and said that nobody had been able to punch a hole in the Keating</p>
<p>   idea in 1986. Despite all of that, they will campaign with all the</p>
<p>   vigour at their disposal in a negative, despoiling fashion to stop</p>
<p>   the cause of tax reform. And Peter Costello and I and our colleagues</p>
<p>   will need all of your help and all of your goodwill and all of your</p>
<p>   support and all of your commitment to win that great debate. And</p>
<p>   I don't underestimate the battle that lies ahead but there</p>
<p>   is really no alternative. If you are to have a decent taxation system</p>
<p>   in this country, if we are to break out of the unfairness and the</p>
<p>   uncompetitiveness of the present system there is really no other</p>
<p>   moment and there is no other way. However you look at it, putting</p>
<p>   it off is not going to solve the problem and therefore it is absolutely</p>
<p>   essential that we embark upon the course to which we are committed.</p>
<p>   And I believe that if you appeal to the Australian people in the</p>
<p>   right way and if you fulfil two very important criteria in that</p>
<p>   appeal then you will be able to win support for something as fundamental</p>
<p>   as taxation reform. </p>
<p>There are two things that we have to do above all else. We have</p>
<p>   to persuade the Australian people that delivering a different taxation</p>
<p>   system is in the national interest. It is not enough to say it's</p>
<p>   in the interest of the business community or it is in the interest</p>
<p>   of families, important though those groups are. It's not enough</p>
<p>   to say it is in the interest of the farmers or the city people or</p>
<p>   whatever. What we have to do is to demonstrate that Australia will</p>
<p>   be a better country economically, a fairer country economically</p>
<p>   and a more competitive country economically with a new and fairer</p>
<p>   and better taxation system. Because at the end of the day Australians</p>
<p>   are great patriots, they may understate their patriotism. They may</p>
<p>   not be as demonstrable as Americans or others but deep down all</p>
<p>   Australians wherever they live worry about the reputation of this</p>
<p>   country, worry about the sort of future which is going to be left</p>
<p>   to their children and grandchildren. And they worry about the strength</p>
<p>   of the Australian economy around the world.</p>
<p>So if we can pitch our campaign, which we definitely will, towards</p>
<p>   the cause of delivering a taxation system which is fairer and better</p>
<p>   in the national interest then that will win wide appeal. The other</p>
<p>   thing we need to do is that we have to demonstrate that the changes</p>
<p>   we have in mind are fair and they are fair to all sections of the</p>
<p>   community. That they are not a giveaway to the rich but equally</p>
<p>   they are changes that recognise the importance of the wealth generating</p>
<p>   and the wealth creating sector of the Australian community. And</p>
<p>   they must be reforms and changes that protect the vulnerable and</p>
<p>   the weak and the poor within our community because none of us, particularly</p>
<p>   those charged with political responsibility, should ever forget</p>
<p>   the fact that there are genuinely vulnerable and weak and poor people</p>
<p>   economically within our community. And that has always been a very</p>
<p>   important part of the Liberal legacy to care for those people as</p>
<p>   part of our broader policies of national and economic development.</p>
<p>   Taxation reform is very dear to my heart. I know it is very dear</p>
<p>   to the heart of the Treasurer and it is very dear to the heart of</p>
<p>   many people on our side of politics. We've had the courage</p>
<p>   to tackle the deficit problem. We've had the courage to tackle</p>
<p>   industrial relations. We've had the courage to tackle many</p>
<p>   other issues that have come our way over the last two and a quarter</p>
<p>   years. And I regard tackling taxation reform as the next logical</p>
<p>   step of strengthening and buttressing the Australian economy in</p>
<p>   an increasingly uncertain world. And what is happening in the Asia</p>
<p>   Pacific region and what is happening globally at the present time</p>
<p>   makes it more, not less necessary, to pursue the cause of taxation</p>
<p>   reform. Don't be misguided by anybody running around an saying:</p>
<p>   oh there is a bit of difficulty on the world currency markets,</p>
<p>   there's a bit of turmoil, there is a bit of a meltdown in the</p>
<p>   Asia Pacific region, therefore in these uncertain times you ought</p>
<p>   to put taxation reform on the shelf.' That would be completely</p>
<p>   the wrong thing to do. It is precisely at a time like this that</p>
<p>   a Government should retain its nerve and its determination to pursue</p>
<p>   the next logical element of economic reform and that is taxation</p>
<p>   reform.</p>
<p>My friends, the last specific issue that I want to address is one</p>
<p>   that was referred to by Richard Court and that is the issue of native</p>
<p>   title reform. I am very aware that the Native Title Act in its present</p>
<p>   form has a more adverse effect on the people of Western Australia</p>
<p>   than any other State in the Commonwealth. I am very aware of the</p>
<p>   clog that it represents on the development of the resource industry</p>
<p>   in this State. And I am very aware of the loss of wealth that has</p>
<p>   already occurred as a result of the negative operation of that legislation.</p>
<p>   That is why we set about after the Wik decision to create a balanced</p>
<p>   plan, a fair plan that provided the basis of lasting and effective</p>
<p>   reform to the Native Title Act. And one of the most aggravating</p>
<p>   and unreasonable and inaccurate claims that is made about the Government's</p>
<p>   Native Title Bill is that it represents in some way a sell-out of</p>
<p>   the interests of all people in the Australian community other than</p>
<p>   the farmers and the miners - it doesn't. </p>
<p>It does, of course, represent a proper accommodation of the interests</p>
<p>   of the farming and mining communities, not only in Western Australia</p>
<p>   but throughout the whole of the country. But it does take into account</p>
<p>   the proper and legitimate interests of the indigenous community.</p>
<p>   And it is the product of a genuine attempt on my part, helped by</p>
<p>   a number of my colleagues, to build a compromise which respected</p>
<p>   the basic principle of the Mabo decision but also gives security,</p>
<p>   both in terms of title and process to the farming and mining communities.</p>
<p>   And the proposition that the only way you can settle the issue is</p>
<p>   for us to further compromise completely ignores the fact that in</p>
<p>   arriving at the position where we are now, we have already compromised</p>
<p>   a great deal in the eyes of many people within the Australian community.</p>
<p>   And I say that very deliberately at present because there is some</p>
<p>   debate about whether or not now might not be the time to see whether</p>
<p>   the minor parties and others in the Senate would again address the</p>
<p>   native title issue. </p>
<p>Well, can I say that if I got an assurance that the Native Title</p>
<p>   Bill was going to be passed through the Senate if it were presented</p>
<p>   again in its present form, of course I would present it again. But</p>
<p>   until I receive any such assurance, the idea that the Government</p>
<p>   should further compromise is absolutely ridiculous. I went through</p>
<p>   months of difficult negotiation with States, with the mining and</p>
<p>   the farming communities and with representatives of Australia's</p>
<p>   indigenous people. And I arrived at a situation which was not entirely</p>
<p>   satisfactory to any one group but did represent a decent and honourable</p>
<p>   compromise and it's that legislation that is now lying twice</p>
<p>   rejected by the Federal Senate. And it's that legislation which</p>
<p>   constitutes the only proper basis on which we can satisfactorily</p>
<p>   resolve this issue. And this proposition that by some way brokering</p>
<p>   a compromise of the Native Title legislation will shut people out</p>
<p>   of potential election to the Federal Senate is completely misguided.</p>
<p>   Indeed, if the Liberal and National parties were to negotiate away</p>
<p>   their position on this issue, that would provide a very fertile</p>
<p>   breeding ground for more rabid propositions that would say to Australia's</p>
<p>   rural communities, those parties that have traditionally represented</p>
<p>   your interests are no longer willing to do so. </p>
<p>So I want to make it very clear to you, I make it very clear in</p>
<p>   the presence of your Premier, that I was very serious when I said</p>
<p>   in May of last year, when with Tim Fischer I met a group of pastoralists</p>
<p>   and debated this issue at Longreach in Queensland that having arrived</p>
<p>   at a commitment to my 10 point plan, we were not only determined</p>
<p>   to put that into legislation but we were determined to pursue that</p>
<p>   legislation until it was approved in accordance with the Constitutional</p>
<p>   processes of the Australian Parliament. </p>
<p>Can I finally say to all of you, ladies and gentlemen, that when</p>
<p>   I was elected as Prime Minister I made what I regarded then and</p>
<p>   I still regard as the most important commitment that any Prime Minister</p>
<p>   on any side of politics can make to the people who choose to elect</p>
<p>   you and that is, I said, that I would endeavour to the best of my</p>
<p>   ability to govern for all Australians. That although we campaign</p>
<p>   on our own political platforms when we are given office we have</p>
<p>   a responsibility to govern for the entire community. And that commitment</p>
<p>   I have taken seriously and I will continue to take seriously whilever</p>
<p>   the Australian people choose to have me as their Prime Minister.</p>
<p>   But I also take very seriously the links that my Party and the National</p>
<p>   Party have with the business community of Australia. We, of course,</p>
<p>   are not owned by the business community in the way that the Labor</p>
<p>   Party is owned by the trade union movement. There are occasions</p>
<p>   when the business community disagrees and disagrees very strongly</p>
<p>   with measures that we have taken. And in my dealings in the last</p>
<p>   24 years I can recall occasions when the business community has</p>
<p>   been critical of decisions taken by the Liberal Party and I am sure</p>
<p>   that will be the case in the future. But we do share a broad spectrum</p>
<p>   of agreement on a large number of issues. We do believe that the</p>
<p>   wealth generating sector of the Australian economy is crucial. We</p>
<p>   do believe that the bulk of the jobs in this country come from the</p>
<p>   wealth generating sector. We believe in decent levels of profit.</p>
<p>   We believe in decent compassionate capitalism. We believe in attracting</p>
<p>   business investment. We believe in the minimum levels of Government</p>
<p>   intervention consistent with maintaining a proper social security</p>
<p>   safety net. And we believe very much that this country has to play</p>
<p>   a very pro-active role both in terms of exports and imports in the</p>
<p>   world economic environment. And over the last two and a quarter</p>
<p>   years I have been very grateful to the advice and the communication</p>
<p>   that I have received and had with the business community all over</p>
<p>   Australia and not least here in Perth.</p>
<p>And I want to say how important it is that the linkages established</p>
<p>   by such groups as the 500 Club not only be maintained but also developed.</p>
<p>   Being in Government in modern times is an extremely challenging</p>
<p>   task. No one country in the world is the complete master of its</p>
<p>   own economic destiny. Even a nation as powerful as that of the United</p>
<p>   States must live by the constraints of a global economy. And we</p>
<p>   see in relation to Japan, the second most powerful economy in the</p>
<p>   world, a very powerful living out of that proposition that we are</p>
<p>   all part of the global economy now and whether we like it or not</p>
<p>   we can't escape it. And it is, therefore, very important in</p>
<p>   the process of governing, the Prime Ministers and governments that</p>
<p>   hold the essential values of private enterprise of investment and</p>
<p>   all the things that flow from it maintain their close links with</p>
<p>   the business communit</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
