<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5029</transcript-id>
    <title>EXCHANGE OF COMMONWEALTH AND STATE LANDS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005029.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
N PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 27 APRIL-1979<br />
C^ OOMFM ONWEUASNTRDAL ITS TATE ANDS<br />
TPhrei me Minister of Australia, Mr Fraser, and the Premier<br />
of New South Wales, 1Mr Wran, have exchanged l6tters'authorising<br />
tetransfer of certain Commonwealth and Stat' lands details<br />
of which are set out in the attached schedule., The letters also<br />
provide for future exchanges-by mutual agreein~ nt of the two<br />
Governments. The announcement that the way is now clear toiadd areas of<br />
significance to the Sydney Harbour National Pqrk was made,<br />
appropriately, during this week of commemoratilve celebrations<br />
being held to mark the centenary of the estab1~ ishment of the<br />
Royal National Park as the first National Park in At~ strAlia<br />
and the second National Park established in the World.<br />
This import~ nt and historic agreement was readhed at discussions<br />
rep~ resentin&amp; the Commonwealth and the M. inister for Lands and<br />
Services, the Hon. W. F. Crabtree, representin. the State.<br />
P RIIVIN IV18 õ SISTER I¾<br />
The exchangEs follow discussions between the State and Commonwealth<br />
FORdating back to 1969 and reflect the State's desire to preserve<br />
: EXCHANGE OF COMMONWEALTH AND STATE iLANDS<br />
Thefor all tPrMimien ister owAneusft ralia, Mr Frasneir, f icant vantage pointsr<br />
of New Soutokoinn e of the Wran, have excharbnged leoursandtters authgaete worisingay<br />
to the Citransfer of Sydcertain Commonwealth and Sta lands details<br />
of which are setdlands out iPno rthe attackson, North Head, South Head, Maildsdoletters<br />
Head anprfoovrid ef uture exchangesb y mutualland at Greemn Point, Steel Point<br />
Governments.<br />
The announcement that the way is now cavailatob lbeea ard d aed to the Sydney<br />
significance to the Sydney HarbPoaurrk . Nrka tional was made,<br />
appropriately, during this week of commemorative celebrations<br />
beingo theld to mark the entean ry of the establbiysh mentS tthaoetf ea cqfuoirred<br />
Royal Necreational Park as the firsNt ational Pareas along the coastlinelia<br />
two on Botany Bay and one on Rushcutters Bay..<br />
and the second National Parkt oe isnvt aarbtielioisuthslee dp arklands arounrld. Sydney<br />
and land fimportant and historic agreelopment was reaolsworhyd at discussionst. Marys.<br />
between the Minister for Administrative Services, the Hon. J. E. McLeay,<br />
reTresentingCo mtmhoe nweailtasl tthu rn iwni ll acquireist itle to lands andit<br />
Services, th. e Hon. W. F. Crabtree, representing the State.<br />
The exchanges follow discussions between the State and Commonwealth<br />
dtoccupies at Hols1w9o69r thya ndr eflecrtth e State's desire to presneortv ei nclude<br />
pubfor all time public ownership of the magnificant vantage pointsroads.<br />
o'verlooking one of the World's finest harbours and the gateway<br />
to the City of Sydney.<br />
The main hec. dlands on Port Jackson, North Head, South Head, Middle<br />
Head and Dob'royd Head as well as land at Green Point, Steel Point<br />
and Georges Heights will all be available to be added to the Sydney<br />
Harbour National Park.<br />
Ten other areas in Sydney are being acquired by the State for<br />
recreational purposes. They include five areas along the coastline,<br />
two on Botany Bay and one on Rushcutters Bay.<br />
The State will obtain title to various parklands around. Sydney<br />
and land for residential development at Holsworthy and st. Marys.<br />
The Commonwealth in its turn will acquire title to land it<br />
occupies at Holsworthy and Beecroft Peninsula which does not include<br />
public roads. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Sydney Harbour National Park I<br />
Purchase of the harbour foreshore lands is s bject to an undertaki<br />
by the State that they will be permanently d dicated for national<br />
park purposes except for Tania Park which witl continue to be<br />
used for public recreation and the sewerage treatment works<br />
located at North Head.<br />
" A total of 376 ha is to be added to the Sydpey Harbour National<br />
Park, 254 ha immediately and the remainder when the Commonwealth<br />
removes or vacates its facilities for defence quarantine and<br />
training from the areas concerned", Mr Frase* said.<br />
o0o--</p>
<p>THE SC]] UEL<br />
Sydniey Ev<. rholi="" nationajd="" park=""></.>
The land to be transferredl imrned. atcly comprises<br />
157.6 ha at North Head, 4.9 ha at Sov. th d, 38,. 3 ha at<br />
M'iddle Head, 38.1 ha at Dobroyd Head, whi-ch does ' not incl~ ude<br />
the ' rea of Tania Park which will continuie Ito be -utilized<br />
for recreation purposes, -0.4 ha at Stool P'intT 1.1 h a at<br />
Green Point and 13.4 ha-at Georges '-1e ig h ts<br />
HolsworthIy and Beecroft Peninsula<br />
The Prend. haasr announced that ti<br />
sell top1; bhe Cominonweajth 13,600 hectares oi<br />
and 2,8? 0) qctares of land which. does not J<br />
at Beecroft Peninsula*<br />
., Both tho*; e) areas have be~ n. used I<br />
for ]) efea. ce jurposesff.<br />
They will ontinue -to-be so used<br />
which will provide, . aaety buffer zone arc<br />
Atomic EKaeroy Comis; Esion's establishment a-t<br />
Ten. SmalL_ Axeas for Public~ Recreation<br />
TeCommonwealth is to sell to tl<br />
areas. ii -Sydney Tfor,' reorational purposes. Ice State is to<br />
Sland at Holsworthy<br />
nlde public roads<br />
y the Commonwealth<br />
e xc ept f or an ar ea<br />
~ und tij0 Australian<br />
Lucaq Heighits.<br />
ke Sta-e ten smv. 11<br />
Detilsaf he nioe pomientar . as ar<br />
I s1 , t t c*-F 13U~ r 1XrsSi et rve<br />
Thi s 5 ha are"-accomrnodat'es a jlipwaSr, Naval<br />
Resoarch Lab o rator, t-he Command Sailing Pl, ol and the R. A. N.<br />
Sailing Association. The latnd is to be transferred imr ediat* l n<br />
l eas ed back, at a nom-. inal. rental,. * to the C 6nronw~ althi pending<br />
relocvatiin of the nwal facilities.<br />
A lease of the area it presentlyloccu-,.) es will be<br />
gCranted to the R. A. N. -Sailing Association when the Cornronv; ealth<br />
lease is terminated,<br />
En-incers Dep.-ot Mo'or e Park I<br />
This 3,6.3 ha area, occiried by tJI'e Arm', separates<br />
PvIrts Of' Sydney Shovwgiound and. the S:' dney $ ports* Ground.<br />
The laind is to be transferred imipkdiat41Y and leased<br />
habvCk2 v nomll. rental to the Commonwe4Jlth poending re). ocatibin.<br />
of th1c e~ 1 ~. isiin </p>
<p>TVie Coi,,! ceaelth liar.; undcriiJ;' n to iise ' its licst<br />
ond. eavours to vacate the land no later thanj 1983 : and carl ier,<br />
if possible.<br />
Bumborah Point -BotPPY BOX<br />
Th is 3.5 2 h a ar ea of CorflaIon. ealthlan h0aji<br />
B6tany Bv: j Port Develop:-ment Project a-rea an4. i s Wesently<br />
being used by the ' Maritime Services Board a's its Nqorks4<br />
construction deo.<br />
the land is to be transferred inunediatleay.<br />
Following completion of the Port Develo~ ment Project<br />
the land I. s to be restored as a recreation reserve,<br />
Henry. Hcec La Porouse<br />
Thi~ s 25.66 ha area of coastal heath land slopes<br />
dovn to irnclude Co-7., wong Ba. y situated between Henry Head and<br />
Bare IsJ. d. The land is to be transferred innmdiately.<br />
Ba. rronioc-v Iod-Palmi fle,-chI<br />
This 21.62 ha area. of rugged natur~ al bu~ hland<br />
comrises the outer slopes anid -vaterfrontage ar oi4d the'<br />
lighthouse reserve on the southern headland ito Br'ken Bay. It<br />
adjoins Governor Pbilliij Park.<br />
The land is t'o be transferred. irm6! diately.<br />
Sifrnal JIlM Vaucluse<br />
This 1.9 ha area is in two ports.<br />
The northernmiost section is to be ' transferred<br />
immedia-tely and'the remainder when vacated b; the tommonwealth.<br />
Ut adjoins the Signal -Station and enjoys magnificent<br />
views alon! 7 the coastline.<br />
The remaining four areas, to be triinsfer~ ed<br />
immcdi. a'-l. are loocted at-<br />
Clark Reserve, Vaucluse ( 0.04 ha)<br />
Nlark I s park, Bondi ( 2.64 hia) I<br />
siPliar it, Bo; ndi ( 9.35 ha)<br />
Burrows Park, ( addition), Clov,; ellyi (. 27 ha) </p>
<p>4 3.<br />
IsriV, ' c'r to ait* ~-lt2<br />
The Commonwealth is to sell 328 h ecI,*' 8. tLs or land<br />
near. Hohworliy for urban development.<br />
The land is to be transferred iniricdiately.<br />
St, Nr: 1. This 109.3 ha area has already be'en trdnsforred to<br />
the State for residential developmient by tVae New ' South Wales<br />
Land Comnr. iission. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
