<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4747</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW WITH ANDREW CLARK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004747.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT 4 JULY 1978<br />
INTERVIEW WITH ANDREWV CLARK<br />
QUESTION: The first question I want to ask you is that a<br />
Feature of the Governments foreign policy especially<br />
( inaulible) for this Common Fund concept and the access<br />
of Thi--rd World countries to developed markets and I just want<br />
to -kn'ow how you see that policy meshing in with what you<br />
might call domestic economic policy. If it does mesh in<br />
with that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It does mesh in with it. Our policies<br />
in relation to the Common Fund are based in a belief that<br />
the developing world needs to given a fair and reasonable<br />
opportunity to trade. Official aid will have had to increase<br />
many times to make up for the fall in world trade fall in<br />
the terms of trade of the commodities that are important<br />
to the developing world over the last few years and many of<br />
these countries are dependent upon one or two commodities<br />
for their overseas income, for their development projects<br />
and its ' gets very difficult for them. The Australian economy<br />
used to be dependent upon wool, meat and wheat, it's now<br />
much more diversified but if something serious happened to<br />
one of those major industries, the whole Australian economy<br />
felt it. We, for a l. ong while, have been a supporter of<br />
commodity stabilisation arrangements within Australia. We<br />
participated in international stabilisation arrangements;<br />
international wheat agreements, international sugar agreements,<br />
the Commonwealth Sugar Agreement. We in fact, through the<br />
Wool Corporation, run a stabilisation programme for the wool<br />
industry which is in a sense an example of what an international<br />
commodity arrangementi-can be and I think should be. It's<br />
been an economic operation, a properly viable commercial<br />
operation and it's been responsibly financed and we also<br />
undertake and support, as you know, promotion and research<br />
activities which in a sense is an example of what other<br />
measures could be in terms of the Common Fund; research and<br />
promotion related to the product. While the multilateral<br />
trade negotiations are pre-eminently designed to help the<br />
major industrial countries and while there is a major<br />
argument going on about the role of agriculture in those<br />
negotiations, commodities related to the Third World,<br />
developing world, are not really part of the MTN, they are<br />
part of the UNCTAD, UNCTAD negotiating conference and Common<br />
Fund. So, if there is to be an advance across the broadest<br />
possible spectrum of world trade you've got to*-obviously<br />
include industrial tariff matters, agriculture and Common<br />
Fund for commodities through the UNCTAD forum. Now, this is<br />
very much of concern to Australia because we are a very<br />
significant trading nation with a large proportion of our<br />
gross domestic product dependent upon trade and we are also<br />
very much aware that our trade has been growing most rapidly<br />
with many developing countries that are emerging in the process<br />
of industrialisation, the Koreas of this world, the ASEAN<br />
countries where two-way trade has grown very greatly. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
So, we've got a broad based interest in all of these<br />
matters but of very particular national interest because<br />
an expansion of markets and growth of world trade is going<br />
to mean a great deal for Australia.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think its fair, just looking at the<br />
two ar-an half years since you've been in government, to<br />
say that in the first year and in the budget you announced<br />
these changes which were aimed at an investment led<br />
recovery and then the tax changes and the alteration in<br />
the tax scale announced in the ' 77 budget and introduced<br />
in February led to a view of a consumer led recovery and<br />
now that the latest changes on foreign investment guidelines<br />
mean there should be a foreign investment -led recovery.<br />
Is that fair?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm very glad you asked that question because<br />
it just shows how false labels can be. Obviously a number of<br />
different factors can assist in economic recovery, but no<br />
one factor can establish, provide, achieve, recovery of itself<br />
and I think it was,, broadly speaking, a press nickname<br />
consumer-led recovery, investment-led recovery or overseas<br />
investment -led recovery. For economic recovery you've got to<br />
get all the basic underlying factors in your economy right:<br />
getting tax levels right, getting the appropriate climate<br />
for investment right, having inflation down, having<br />
industrial relatio * ns climate and a great many other factors<br />
are ' all relevan-t to recovery, they all make their corntribution<br />
and the Government has never believed that one factor and<br />
one factor alone is . going to achieve recovery, youlve got<br />
to work at a whole range of factors-look through all your<br />
arms of economic policy get them all as righnt as you can,<br />
and that's what will achieve recovery but I did see one<br />
editorial the other day which was saying we are -now moving<br />
towards a different kind of recovery which you have just<br />
mentioned in your question. It's just onefactor of many<br />
and the economy would be better described if labels were<br />
aVoided. QUESTION: Is it fair to say that the Government is placing<br />
more emp asis on investment from abroad in helping to stimulate<br />
more local demand and towards a stronger economy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think I'd put it this way: for a long while<br />
-1 have beli11evethe world trading WL3ic~ J. ae going to<br />
r * emain difficult and that view was certainly reinforced on my<br />
recent visit. You had a situation in which the British are<br />
leaning back on the reigns of their economy, interest rates<br />
have risen several points in a matter of two or three months.<br />
There will be a rising unemployment in Britain. I was told<br />
that there w., ill be over 100,000 more unemployed in France by<br />
Christmas. We are approaching the 200 Yen dollar and there is<br />
more and :: ore concern being expressed from the President downward<br />
about inflation in the United States. They are going to almost 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
certainly have to lean back in places in relation to<br />
their economy. So the immediate~ prospects for a greater<br />
rate of growth in world trade, for a greater expansion<br />
of world markets,. are not great. There are still too many<br />
basic faults in many economies which have to be put right.<br />
Now acgainst that background, and against the background on<br />
which Australia depends very much on world trade,.-what can<br />
we best do to assist the Australian cause in a trading climate<br />
which is. going to remain difficult. We have got some obvious<br />
advant-ages; we are a great resource producer, we have resources<br />
which overseas countries, many developed countries and<br />
developing countries, need. How can we therefore make Australia<br />
more' attractive than other potential suppliers? If we can<br />
make Australia more attractive then other potential suppliers<br />
we'll attract a larger share of whatever investment there is<br />
in these particular areas, and if we do that, it's one of the<br />
factors, not the factor, but one of the factors which will<br />
help Australia and Australian recovery and in that sense,<br />
it is the share of world trade and the structure of world<br />
trade that becomes very important to Australia, all against<br />
the background in which not particularly optimistic about<br />
any significant increase in world trade which would help<br />
everyone. QUESTION:-Do you agree that since the election, and this is<br />
obviusly referring to the trade question ( inaudible)<br />
do you agree that since the election, the Government has<br />
definitely become, in its public statements, much more flexible<br />
on the protection issue. As I say, I'm referring that to<br />
the trade question and that not high protection in Australia I<br />
know it doesn't-apply to all commodities or all manufactured<br />
goods but to certain goods that high protection is now looked<br />
on as a short-term, anti-unemployment policy and that lowering<br />
protection is now an official long-term aim of this-Government.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: You could have read that into the White Paper<br />
on manufacturing without any inconsistency at all.% 9 that<br />
doesn't have to be a new view. In theory, barriers to trade<br />
are not good but we Live in a very imperfect world and Australia<br />
lives in a world where there are very considerable difficulties,<br />
with non-tariff barriers against up to 40% of our exports and<br />
non-tariff barriers related to 7% or 8% of our imports. It's<br />
not generally realized that in the sensitive areas of<br />
employment, Australia has made a greater contribution to trade<br />
than any other developed countrymmV'% you look at the<br />
textiles,, apparel and footware area, for example, we import<br />
much more per head, sometimes six or eight times more per<br />
head than other developed countries North America, Europe,<br />
or Japan. I've used this figure before but if the ASEAN<br />
countries had the same per capita access to the North American<br />
and the European markets as they have to Australia, they would<br />
be sellirlg an extra $ 1,000 million worth of goods a year.<br />
Their extoorts to ' Australia have been increasing at about 40% a<br />
4 </p>
<p>4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
year for several years. Now, even though it starts<br />
from a low base, that rate of progression starts to build<br />
up to a very substantial amount and so I reject the view<br />
that Australia's markets have been unduly closed in the<br />
total trading enviornment in which we are living, our<br />
markets are much, much more open than many countries, more<br />
open than any of the European markets, taking trade as a<br />
whole-A-' gain, we've got to take note of the fact that<br />
we're a market of. 14 million people, we're not like the<br />
Swede-n, for example, that lives next door to a very large<br />
tradin.; -bloc. We've got considerable transport difficulties<br />
in get7ing products overseas. So there are cost disadvantages<br />
for a lar-; e part of Australian manufacturing industry that's<br />
going to be with us and that needs to be taken into account and<br />
they need to be given a fair and proper opportunity to compete<br />
and our determination to provide the necessary protection<br />
for Australian manufacturing industry is in no-way diurinished, but<br />
wedoreogiz tata general lowering of barriers for trade<br />
will strengthen the Australian economy and at the same time strengthen<br />
Australian manufacturing industry. I don't think there is any<br />
inconsistency in having a present position that says in the<br />
trading clinnate in which we are living we've got to provide<br />
this protection but if we have a trading climate which opens<br />
up many markets to Australia which are now closed to Australia,<br />
t. hat will so strengthen the Australian economy overall, that<br />
we ourselves can assist in the process of lowering trade<br />
barriers. What you have to do to protect your own industries<br />
depends very much on the trading world in which you have to<br />
live and a-country Australia's size can't be a pacesetter.<br />
But we can. throw open our markets and destroy all our<br />
industries but that doesn't mean to say we are going to get<br />
any better access overseas.<br />
QUESTION: Would it be fair then to say that perhaps the<br />
Governmenit's more flexible on protection policy because it<br />
is now in a situation to negotiate what economists call a<br />
trade-off device?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think maybe the totality of the Government's<br />
approach is better understood and better perceived.<br />
QUESTION: Overseas or locally?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think there's been any basic change<br />
in attitude at all.<br />
QUESTION: As everyone has been saying, if all ove'r the world<br />
it's a pretty tough international climate at the moment, looking<br />
at the worst possible scenario for Australia, in other words,<br />
that you dont negotiate any greater access for us at the EEC<br />
or any other maj . or concessions which would help us, what is<br />
basically the Government's fullback position over the next<br />
three yea-rs? How will Australia survive?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We'll go for our life in markets in whatever<br />
countries we can find them. Take the developing countries of<br />
Asia and the Western Pacific, the Koreas, Taiwan, Phillippines,<br />
in all of_ these areas two-way trade has been growing very </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
markedly and I've got no doubt it will go on doing so.<br />
There's been a very great emphasis on the development of<br />
trade in developing countries, in new markets in the<br />
Middle East.<br />
( b rea]%-)<br />
There are some trade figures here to go from 1972-3 to<br />
1976-: to give examples of an increase in trade. The total<br />
trade increased from 164 million to 688 million or 320%.<br />
But the t-rade with Iran has increased 480%, Egypt 250%,<br />
Iraq 3,10.1, Kuwait 200, Saudi Arabia 290, United Arab<br />
Q9UESTION\:_ United Arab Emirates, is it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes,, 2' 00%, S. Korea 260%. Well, Southeast<br />
Aa, Korea, the Middle East, these are new areas of trade<br />
for Australia and we haven't been they are not as much in<br />
the news as our,, if you like, trade offensive against the<br />
European Community, but its again in the European Community<br />
we run up against two problems; non-tariff barriers that<br />
prevent us trading which doesn't happen in these areas, doesn't<br />
happen in Southeast Asia, and secondly, $ 4,000 million worth<br />
of export subsidies competing directly with Australia's<br />
exports in third markets and both of those areas are of<br />
enormous importance to us. We can't get into the counter<br />
subsidy gamne with 260 million people, technologically the<br />
wealthiest and most advanced industrial group the world has<br />
ever seen. We have to try and get, through argument, through<br />
persuasion, sensible trading rules that stop Europe wrecking<br />
other people's third markets and it's just as important as<br />
getting entree into Europe for some of our commodities.<br />
QUESTION: Just moving on to! this tax area. In the long-term,<br />
doyou agree with the A9b Report that the weight of tax,<br />
and this in the context of this Government inquiry into BAT,<br />
that the weight of tax should be shifted towards taxation of<br />
goods and services and away from the taxation of income?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We've made some move * s in that direction by<br />
trying to lighten the burden of income tax and the reforms<br />
in that area are very substantial. I would like to put your<br />
question in a sense in historical perspective. Indirect<br />
taxes originally have the name for being regressive and<br />
unfortunate taxes because they would be on the basic<br />
necessities of life for people on a sustenance wage and it<br />
was out of that historical background that the philosophical<br />
objection to indirect taxes arose but Australia is not a<br />
sustenance economy and by world standards average incomes in<br />
this country are high and therefore a different set of<br />
arguments come to the fore. Indirect taxes have been low,<br />
still are low, and income taxes have been very high, and by<br />
some country's standards are still high. I think there is<br />
a very strong argument in that many people want a greater<br />
command ov-er how they spend their incomes and if income taxes<br />
are lower and indirect taxes are higher, they have that choice.<br />
If income taxes overall are higher they don't have that choice. / 6 </p>
<p>-6<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
It's easy, to give you an example, if somebody wants<br />
to buy a V-8 motor car that with present emission rules<br />
might ' give 10 miles to the gallon around cities, that's<br />
his choice, and if he's paying more tax for the privilege<br />
throug-, h higher prices petrol and whatever, that's still<br />
his chnoice. He can get just as-comfortable transport,<br />
much nore efficient transport, in buying an economy vehicle<br />
and ozne that will get him there just as quickly and maybe<br />
a goo* d: L deal safer. That's his choice whether he wants to<br />
spend :~ sincome on using a lot of petrol and a great big<br />
heavy V-S motor car or whether he wants to buy a different<br />
sort of1 -; rehicle. That's his choice. I think it's right<br />
to give individuals as great a command as possible over<br />
their own income as we can. I believe we are living in<br />
quite a different environment from one which prevailed in<br />
earlier days when the name of regressive taxes as related<br />
to indirect tax. That's not the sort of world we live in.<br />
QUESTION: Referring to this recent decision on the<br />
resources tax. Why didn't the Government decide to impose<br />
the tax on. Bass Strait Oil when a large part of the profits,<br />
as you know, I'm not talking about the question of whether<br />
the profits should be taxed, but when a large section of<br />
those profits are the direct result of a change in<br />
Government policy.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The companies know quite well that the<br />
extra return to the people of Australia can come -through a<br />
levy just as easily as through a resources tax and in fact<br />
that's what's happening just at this moment. So the choice<br />
there is not whether the community is going to get a proper<br />
return for Government induced decisions in relation to that,<br />
it's a question of how they weregoing to get that return.<br />
So far as other resources are concerned, so far as uranium<br />
is concerned, you know quite well that we've made a decision<br />
that there will be 75% Australian ownership so you've got<br />
the question of royalties, you've got the question of royalties<br />
to Aboriginals in the Northern Territory, you've got company<br />
tax, you've got income tax on individuals and we believe out<br />
of all that the community can get an adequate return, especially<br />
in relation to uranium because it is 75% Australian ownership.<br />
One of the major arguments against the resource tax is that<br />
if you did have it and you related it to Bass Strait Oil<br />
only, and to uranium which is what we have said, nobody outside<br />
in the investment world would have known or understood that<br />
the tax was related to those two things only, they all'wbuld have<br />
believed its going to be extended to all resource development<br />
and that would have been an inhibition on development but when<br />
you take the basis of royalties that states can put on for<br />
things that happen in state areas the foreign investment<br />
guidelines, the question of company tax and individual tax,<br />
the community can get and does get and adequate and proper<br />
return. QUESTION: Looking at the mix of-your federalism and your<br />
tax indexation policies, this is goin bakto hywr<br />
proposed in ' 75 or initially proposed in ' 75, they can be 7 </p>
<p>7-<br />
QUESTION: ( continued)<br />
both together regarded as instruments for a radical<br />
alteration in the scope and Structure of government and<br />
also as the key elements in your economic policy can be<br />
regarde-d as both those things. Which is the most important<br />
to YOU;<br />
PRIME1 MINISTER: I think you've got to take the policy as<br />
a whol-e and I wouldn't want to break up different-elements<br />
of it say one is more is important than others because<br />
they are operating in different fields. Let me take a<br />
non-finani-ial matter for a moment. You know the arguments<br />
that had gone on over-seas and submerged lands for a decade,<br />
even more, and its bedevilled relationships between the<br />
Commonwealth and the States, it's even inhibited development<br />
because who's responsible offshore? And do the laws stand up?<br />
Do decisions stand up? More than a year ago we set about,<br />
in a major enterprise to resolve all these matters offshore<br />
mining for minerals and petroleum, fisheries, criminal<br />
jurisdiction, navigation, all the areas affecting offshore<br />
relationships. Now we've broadly determined the pattern<br />
of what's going to happen, through joint authorities and<br />
through a Series of agreements with the states. Very<br />
considerable progress has been made, the pattern of what<br />
we are doing in cooperation with the states has been set.<br />
I think they are very happy with it and over the course of<br />
the next 12 months, I hope there will be final agreement<br />
on the remaining matters but more work yet remains to be<br />
done by officials. The remaining areas are in a specific<br />
subject matter areas. So this has been a major cooperative<br />
enterprisenow which has gone very well. We haven't stuck<br />
on the full letter of the power available to the Commonwealth<br />
under the High Court decision. We've said we've got a<br />
practical problem between governments which we want to<br />
resolve as practical people, and jointly we will want to<br />
pass laws with you which bring that about. Now we are<br />
achieving that and I think that's a very major advance.<br />
You never could have got to that position with a<br />
Commonwealth Government that was insisting on saying this<br />
is is the letter of the law, this is what we are going<br />
to do. It's even in relation to treaties which is fully<br />
a Commonwealth power, the consultative processes, the<br />
willingness to put in federal clauses in the treaty, the<br />
willingness to have the states have their own observers<br />
present during the treaty-making process. All of these<br />
things are an example of cooperative federalism which is<br />
I think a very important development and I believe the<br />
Premiers would regard it as a very important development.<br />
So there are non-financial aspects of our approach which are<br />
often overlooked. They don't get headlines because we are<br />
not in conl: lict. In the financial area, we want the states<br />
to have -c're responsibility for the things which they<br />
themselves have to do. They've got to take that responsibility<br />
for themSelves and if states are constantly to say that we<br />
can't do his because the Commonwealth won't give us enough<br />
money, t-r-en the authority and the erosion of state's powers<br />
will be a continuous and inevitable process and that's not / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
something that I want to see, I don't believe it's<br />
something that the majority of Australians want to see.<br />
So policies which provide the possibility of the states<br />
having a greater financial responsibility for their own<br />
affairs is more consistent with the maintenance of state's<br />
rights than any other possible policy. I think some<br />
Premiers understand this very well and some others understand<br />
it bu:_ don't want it because they don't want to lose their<br />
excuse the Commonwealth as a scapegoat. I can't see why a<br />
Commonwealth should be a scapegoat for all the economic<br />
policies o-f states. One of the first things you need to<br />
look to in terms of the financial management of any<br />
governn7en: is what's that government doing with its own<br />
bureaucracy, what's it doing with its-own employment levels<br />
and on the -figures of our statistician andI don't believe<br />
those figures lie, in the twelve months to-March, state and<br />
local government employment went up four percent. That<br />
doesn't to me indicate great financial stringency. If you<br />
look at the growth in the day labour forces of the states,<br />
construction projects and all sorts of things, the growth<br />
has been very great indeed. They can get the work done<br />
more economically, more effectively, by putting many projects<br />
out to tender and getting some competition into the business.<br />
Our day labour forces have shrunk very considerably over the<br />
last two and a half years and I'm not saying we've got to the<br />
end of that process. So, the financial aspects of the<br />
policy are obviously very important and the states spend,<br />
state and ' Local government together, spend such a high<br />
proportion of total government, comprise such a high<br />
proportion of total government expenditure that what they<br />
do is obviously important for the totality of economic<br />
policy and it can become very difficult if you've got<br />
states running in one direction with the Commonwealth<br />
responsible for financial management, believing the direction<br />
should be different. I hope that one of the results from<br />
the financial pressures that have been put upon the states<br />
at the moment, through the last Premier's Conference, will be<br />
for the first time to get to act with much greater strength<br />
its responsibility in wage policies.<br />
QUESTION: Just on the question of how the Federal Government<br />
spends money and how the states spend money, the Report of<br />
the Centre for Financial Relations, the Matthews Centre at<br />
the says that the states have shown themselves to be<br />
much more sensitive than the Commonwealth to the needs to<br />
maintain capital spending and other expenditures with<br />
employment-creating effects, -although the Commonwealth has<br />
the primary responsibility for economic management the<br />
states have felt obliged to move into the vacuum created by<br />
the Commonwealth despite the dearth of capital funds.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think they've felt obliged, we've<br />
urged them to do so because of the generosity of the payments<br />
under income tax-~ sharing which have gone up very greatly and<br />
this year Have gone up by 10% which is three or four percent<br />
in real terms. Increases in other years were just as<br />
generous. But quite deliberately, of you look at semi-government<br />
programmnzes, last year, the year before, and even this year, / 19 </p>
<p>9-<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
the increases in funds for semi-government authorities<br />
have been considerable. So, while the capital projects for<br />
the states themselves, which do become a charge on the<br />
Federal Budget, have been held very tight, and especially<br />
this year, we have said, look, you've got plenty of leeway<br />
from' " he general revenue grants, to divert some of that<br />
money to capital expenditure and you've been more than<br />
gener--usly treated in relation to semi-government<br />
expndture and we've done that quite deliberately because we<br />
know : i iortance-of capital works in relation to activity<br />
in the economy. One of the difficulties in our scene, is<br />
the way cur own budget structure, so much of it is already<br />
pre-e2D-te in payments to the states, a lot of which goes<br />
to capital works so you know that's not just a state it<br />
doesn't aDear in our book really as capital works but its<br />
capital works by the time they spend it a lot. Then so much<br />
of it goes to health and welfare, which is not capital works<br />
or overwhelmingly isn't and we have enormous payments in that<br />
arena which the states obviously don't have and against the<br />
need for f0inancial restraint, to have a deficit that's<br />
responsible, to be able to finance that deficit in a<br />
non-inflationary way. The room for manouvre in a Commonwealth<br />
budget is obviously limited. That's another way of saying we<br />
would like to be in at position to spend more funds on<br />
capital works, but you can't go down that path if it means<br />
that overall your economic policies are going to be<br />
under mined. The overall structure of the budget and the<br />
budgetary aggregates is more important even than our desire to<br />
spend more funds in capital works.<br />
QUESTION: You raised that question about wages, I want to<br />
go back to that in a minute, but just going back to taxes.<br />
What is your opinion of the vote on Proposition 13 in<br />
California, where they pegged back property taxes very<br />
substantially? Following on from that, do you think we should<br />
have more and more cuts in taxes?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: We've got to try and make sure that our taxes<br />
are based in a way that they don't destroy incentive, they<br />
don't cause undue hardship and the examination that John<br />
Howard announced some time ago is designed to put us in a<br />
position of being able to make judgements about the overall<br />
equity in tax and made it plain its not designed to be taxing<br />
more in total. We have, as you know, made very significant<br />
reductions in taxation in some areas relating to companies,<br />
relating to individuals. It is sometimes forgotten that<br />
tax indexation provides a continuous cut year after year<br />
after year. It's designed to make government's honest,<br />
it puts a rod on a government's back. That was done very<br />
deliberately as an act of policy because we have seen the<br />
damage done when easy funds come to governments and so<br />
easily spent and too easily spent. The commitment for<br />
indexation is undiminished, let there be no mistake about<br />
that, it's half tax indexation for this year because of<br />
the size of the total income tax reform and to ease in<br />
the financial obligations as far as the Commonwealth is<br />
concerne-A. There was half indexation for this year but<br />
this year alone. So there is continuing tax reform built </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
into what we've already done. There are clearly areas<br />
where the Government would like to be able to give further<br />
tax relief that would be well, I don't believe anyone<br />
expects them, we are in that kind of situation this year.<br />
I wo-uld like to make a word about California because I<br />
had a= niqht there on the way through just before the vote<br />
and cne -night in California and speaking to a few natives<br />
of the State, it's perfectly obvious that that proposition<br />
was gD-. n to go through because many people there's been<br />
a land boom in California and property values for many<br />
people haegone up enormously and the property taxes have<br />
theref': ore-gone up to such an extent that people are being<br />
forced o-u: of homes that they might have been in for a lifetime.<br />
But incomes haven't gone up enough to cover the increase<br />
in property taxes and against that background there no doubt<br />
that that particular referendum was going to be carried.<br />
I think there are about 13, no 17 states, where there is the<br />
possibility for this citizen initiative in referendums, and<br />
I have no doubt that a number of other states would be<br />
moving along the same path.<br />
QUESTION: Do you agree that that was a right, correct<br />
course to : take?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think governments have got to maintain<br />
control, we have a capacity for referendum. I'm not sure that<br />
citizen initiated referendums is really a good way of<br />
running a government, of running a country or a state. Ter<br />
There is a message in what happened in California for<br />
governments that seek to impose too high a tax in one area<br />
or another, and a very clear message but I don't believe<br />
in this country we've got to the position where property<br />
taxes have risen to an extent they have in California and<br />
the very extreme circumstances which have developed as a<br />
result, putting enormous hardship on thousands of people,<br />
also against the background in which they had a surplus in<br />
their budget of $ 3 million for $ 4 million, or it might have<br />
been $ 3 billion or $ 4 billion it would have been $ 3 billion<br />
or $ 4 billion.<br />
QUESTION: Just on.. this tax area. Just taking the changes<br />
in the tax scale and the cuts that were announced in the<br />
' 77 budget, the recent changes to Medibank and the abolition<br />
of the resources tax. It's fair to say that the Government's<br />
redistributing money to the higher, to the people higher<br />
up in the scale and I mean, is this being done to stimulate<br />
because the Government believes this will stimulate<br />
investment and economic recovery for simple philosophical<br />
reasons or because this is the base area of the Government's<br />
promoting support?<br />
( break in tape) ./ 1 </p>
<p>11<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
I reject the view that we've been redistributing income<br />
away from lower income people to higher income people.<br />
You've got to look at other things.<br />
9gUESTION: The basic points are the family allowance<br />
PRIME': MINISTER: I'd reject the view that we've been<br />
rediS-_ ributing income away from -lower income people<br />
to h-rincome people. You've got to look at other<br />
things; ' in~ addition. Family allowances was a deliberate<br />
measure designed to distribute away from middle and<br />
higher-income people to lower income people because the<br />
earli--: 7 7: a x rebate or before that the tax concession was<br />
greatesz advantage to people on high incomes, . high marginal<br />
rates or tax and now of course, there is a very great<br />
benefit a-a number of low income families*, about 300,000<br />
of them, who probably would have got no benefit at all<br />
because their incomes were not high enough to get advantage<br />
of the other arrangements. I don't believe the resources<br />
taxes are properly part of this equation because for Bass<br />
Strait Oil it's not a question of resources tax or no tax,<br />
its a question of the levy which is in existence now or<br />
a resources tax, and we made the decision quite plainly that<br />
it's the le vy. So far as uranium is concerned, you've got<br />
to have in : iind that there is 75% Australian ownership, you've<br />
got a royalty situation, then you've got company tax and<br />
you've got income tax and I believe it is the community,<br />
through those mechanisms will get a fair and proper return<br />
from whatever the income is.<br />
( break in tape)<br />
If you look at the tax reforms that we did introduce,<br />
the percentage of tax payable by those with an income up<br />
to $ 16,000 was a fraction under 62%. After the tax changes<br />
it was a fraction over 62% and the range $ 16,000 to $ 32,000,<br />
before the changes it was 25%, after the changes, a mere<br />
fraction below 25%. For those over 32,000, they were paying<br />
before the budget changes, a little under 13%. They are now<br />
paying 12 it went from 12.7 to 12 1/ 2 percent. So there<br />
has been no basic * change in the proportions of income tax<br />
collected from the different income groups in those scales<br />
and you've also got to have a mind of course that the tax<br />
threshold has significantly changed, that there are well over<br />
200 ,000 families who as a result of the change, again in the<br />
low income area, were paying no . tax at all, so to that<br />
extent, again, the * reforms were helping low income people.<br />
* QUESTION: -Dealing with each of these separately, I don't<br />
want to make this too long a question, but dealing with each of thes<br />
separately, how much has your attitude towards economic policy<br />
been influenced by first the visit here of Mr. Wolff the<br />
American t-rade negotiator, secondly, your recent trip to Japan,<br />
and thirdly, your recent trip to West Germany. Also I'm<br />
talking about your talks with Wolff Mr. Fukuda, and<br />
Mr. Schmidt. / 12 </p>
<p>12<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't think that the discussions with<br />
Mr. Wolff would have influenced economic policy to much<br />
' extent. The main purpose of those discussions was to make<br />
our attitude to trade understood and to get the point<br />
across that Australia is not the closed market which he had<br />
implied it was in the press conference he had given in<br />
Singapore before he even got here. And that was why I had<br />
cdscussions with Mr. Wolff and also to emphasise the importance<br />
of agriculture in the multilateral trade negotiations. Since<br />
then, well Mr. Anthony had assurances and the Government<br />
had,-I've ha-d personal assurances from Mr. Strauss and a.<br />
matter thatz has not yet become public, a personal assurance<br />
in a lett-r : ron-the President, that agriculture must be a<br />
part of tha nualtilateral trade negotiations. Now that is the<br />
first tilme -, nIich the President has given Australia that<br />
specific assurance. Would you like to get that letter. Well,<br />
that's the first time, I haven't used that before and it's.<br />
a very recent letter. My visit to Japan, the motivation for<br />
that was exactly the same as the visit to Europe; concern with<br />
what's happening in international trade field, concern with<br />
what's happening in international economies. I've found an<br />
identity of view with Japan over a wide range of issues as a<br />
result. They are in the process of shifting their position on<br />
the Common Fund. I think, not insignificantly as a result of<br />
discussions that I had at that time but then experts on the<br />
Common Fund were in Japan were with me and I had very extensive<br />
discussions wi:: h Japanese officials after my discussions with<br />
the Prime Minister and they've had Government discussions about<br />
the Common Furnd since I don't think the main basis or thrust<br />
of Australia's policies were altered as a result of that but<br />
I do believe-, I know, that the communication that we have with<br />
Japan is much closer as a result. Our officials, their officials,<br />
when they are together in international forums get together<br />
and exchange views. The discussions I had in Paris with<br />
(~ c~ c\ e.) were relaxed and frank and open, as were the<br />
discussions down here. We got away from the large forum of about<br />
people from either side sitting on it. But. all sorts of<br />
issues have been remarkably useful. We are informed of what<br />
happens in the major discussions in which Japan is playing a role.<br />
I think the visit to Japan has put the relationship between two<br />
countries on a new basis because for the first time Australia was<br />
going to Japan to talk about major international issues of concern<br />
to both countries and not going to have a discussion or an<br />
argument, if you like, about bilateral matters and I might indeed<br />
have been the first head of government to go to Japan to do just<br />
thatbecause generally whether it's Europe, or America, or Australia<br />
in earlier times, it was to talk about bilateral problems. and<br />
I believe that Japan has appreciated that and they've responded<br />
to it very warmly and I believe very constructively. I've made<br />
no secret from the fact that I believe that Japan's policies<br />
are more right than wrong and Germany's policies are more right<br />
than wrong in the international context. There is no future in it<br />
if the stronger economies damage their economies in an effort to<br />
help weaker economies that ought to be doing things for themselves.<br />
The American balance of payments problem can't be solved by<br />
Japan. It can7-be sol ed with an energy policy and anti-inflationary<br />
policies and United States knows that. Now this is not to say<br />
that there are not obligations on creditor countries such as<br />
Japan and Germany, of course there are and again I believe that<br />
Japan is wanting to show itself as . a good international citizen. / 13 </p>
<p>13<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
They are making not gestures, positive moves in terms<br />
of more official aid and they're making moves to try and<br />
reduce their overseas balances and those moves are sometimes<br />
frustrated because other countries don't do what they ought<br />
to do. If inflation in other countries goes on increasing<br />
at a rate which is much higher than Japan's or much higher<br />
than Ger~ any's, the efforts of Japan, for example, to reduce<br />
its balarce of payments surplus is made much more difficult.<br />
Again, the sorts of policies that Germany has pursued are ones<br />
that Aust.-ral-ia would basically support. I won't name the<br />
country, but in one country, indirectly an allegedly responsible<br />
minister Dut it to me that there would be no problems if<br />
Germany reflated to an annual rate of 11 percent. All that would<br />
do is to make Germany's economy as weak as the others.<br />
( Side Two of tape)<br />
to be good trading partners and to contribute to stability<br />
in the international trading scene. They cannot solve the<br />
problems of weaker economies. They can't do for those countries<br />
the things that they've got to do for themselves.<br />
QUESTION: I've-been told that in the case of Germany, apart<br />
from agreeing . with their economic policies, you're very<br />
impressed in a more direct, personal sense, with them and<br />
perhaps this may go back in history to the economic policies<br />
that were pursued by Dr. Erhardt, when he was their Economics<br />
Minister, which seem to be fairly similar to our own and I want<br />
to ask, that this be true,, but the situation then of course was<br />
a very different international situation and do you think that<br />
it's realistic or even desirable to expect that the Australian<br />
work force could behave in the same way as the German work force.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Industry is structured differently, unions<br />
are structured differently.<br />
QUESTION: Well, just the people are different.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: And people are different, of course they are.<br />
But one of the Things which was disturbing in the current push<br />
for wage increases outside the Arbitration Commission at the<br />
moment, is that some Union leaders would seem to have learnt<br />
absolutely nothing from the history of recent times. There is<br />
not the slightest doubt, in the view of this government, that<br />
the very rapid rate of wage increase has been a material factor<br />
contributing to unemployment and the higherwages are the<br />
more unemployment there will be. The success we will have in<br />
moving people back into employment will depend very materially<br />
on the degree of wage restraint there is in the trade union<br />
movement. Nobody can say that the totality of the budgetary<br />
policies, the tax policies and the wage policies of this<br />
Government are acting unreasonably or unfairly to wage earners<br />
in Australia. You've, again got to look at it in the context of<br />
tax cuts, in the context of family allowances, and all the other<br />
things we are doing. The Arbitration Commission decisions have<br />
very significantly compensated trade unionists for increases<br />
in the Consumer Price Index, but in so doing there is not the<br />
./ 14 </p>
<p>14<br />
PRI ME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
slightest doubt in the view of the Government that<br />
the Arbitration Commission is contributing to a continuing<br />
high level of unemployment in Australia. Now I said at the<br />
time of the last election that from February unemployment<br />
would fall and it would go on falling. Ithas fallen, it<br />
has gone on falling but whether that process can continue<br />
depends On a number of-factors. It depends upon world trade,<br />
the grow:-. of world trade, Australia's share of that. It will<br />
depend upoJn our capacity to get inflation down further. It<br />
will depenc very materially on getting' greater stability<br />
into wage taxation and on the general level of industrial<br />
disputes.<br />
~ QUESTION: I wannt you to be more specific about that. Can<br />
you tell me ifE you want the system of wage I know the<br />
Commonwealth responsibility as far as wage indexation is<br />
very indirect at most,-but do you want the system...<br />
of wage fixation changed, do you want the across the board<br />
nature of wage rises which exist in Australia changed, do<br />
you want the market to play much more of a role in the fixation<br />
of wages?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I believe there have been advantages to<br />
Australia througih the centralised Arbitration Commission system.<br />
Because of the-position we are in there have been difficulties<br />
with the comp) ression of margins for skilled labour and that's<br />
something which will have to be tackled at some stage but when<br />
you have...<br />
QUESTION: Sorr-. Y for interrupting, but how would that be tackled,<br />
for example?<br />
PRIME MINISTER:-When it is tackled, I think it ought to be<br />
tackled through the Arbitration Commission. They've had<br />
margins decisions before, but I'm not saying that we've got<br />
to that stage yet because the wage/ profit relativities are<br />
still out of kilter and the sort of across the board judgements<br />
that have been made in recent times are probably the only ones<br />
that we could have had, although we would have liked judgements<br />
at a lower level, and that would have helped very greatly. But<br />
the nature of the Arbitration Commission' s decisions have led<br />
to a compression of margins and that obviously has long-term<br />
consequences which at an appropriate time would have to be<br />
tackled, and I would say that further progress has to be made<br />
in getting inflation down and further progress has to be made<br />
in the general objective of wage restraint. I had said something<br />
earlier about the states. The states have gone on employing<br />
more people, they haven't helped us, many of them, in the<br />
Arbitration Commission. Ibelieve all governments know that<br />
too great a rate of increase in wages will lead to more<br />
unemployment, but some for political grounds don't want to say so.<br />
I believe thae: people who, whether it's a trade union leader<br />
or anyone else who wittingly or unwittingly deceives his own<br />
constituents, trade unionists, workers in factories throughout<br />
Australia, is doing a great disservice to that constituency<br />
in putting th-e sort of views that are so often put about wages </p>
<p>15<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
and full indexation, or even more than full indexation.<br />
I don't believe the average worker believes it. The average<br />
worker I am certain knows that if wages go up too much there<br />
will be more unemployment. He is often not given an opportunity<br />
to express his view in a responsible way and I think the<br />
average trade unionist is way ahead of some of his leaders, way<br />
ahead of some political leaders, in these particular matters.<br />
I. will cgve you, in relation to Carter's letter which was dated<br />
the 13th of June this year, in which he says: I will not consider<br />
these negotiations a success unless they lead us towards<br />
significantz liberalisation of world trade in agricultural<br />
products. QUESTION: 3ut does he specifically refer to the question of<br />
agriculture being put in, I mean that hasn't even been established<br />
yet, has it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In that relationship, yes. That sentence is in<br />
the context of a general paragraph about the MTN. " I will not<br />
consider these negotiations" that's the MTN. Now Strauss had<br />
said that before.<br />
QUESTION: Bu: this is the first time it's come from the<br />
President? PRIME MINISTER: It's the first time, that I'm aware, that it's<br />
come from the President and it's come quite directly in a<br />
personal letter to myself. / 16 </p>
<p>16<br />
QUESTION: I know that one of the concerns of people who<br />
oe o the concerns of the Government is that if and<br />
when there is an economic recovery, wages do not go up<br />
with that recovery like they always have and its not always<br />
like they would tend to do. In other words, if that there is<br />
more demand that workers can flex their muscles.<br />
PRIME MIN', ISTER: Well, what I would hope, as recovery gathers<br />
pace, -:-nszead of wages going up unreasonably you have more<br />
people :-Ding into the work force. Again, Australians are<br />
going to have to understand that as there is a level of<br />
greater a.-tivity in this country the wage share of that can<br />
go in two directions: it can go into higher wages in those<br />
who are er: i-loyed, or to perhaps a lesser level of wages for<br />
a much larger number of people.<br />
QUESTION: Just to change subject entirely you've been in<br />
office narly as long as Mr. Whitlam. What do you think<br />
was his major contribution to Australia?<br />
PRIME MINITSTER: I think I'm too close to Mr. Whitlam to<br />
Zak a juc.; ement about that and I haven't really well,<br />
putting it in that way, you're asking for a positive<br />
contributton.<br />
QUESTION: I'm not necessarily I'm asking for a<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The major damage was a destruction of a<br />
healthy economy.<br />
QUESTION: Could I ask now if there was a positive<br />
contribution? PRIME MINISTER: If you can say that a situation of complete<br />
adutter turmoil in which Australians reassessed their values<br />
and reassessed their sense of direction is a positive<br />
contribution. QUESTION: That's all you are prepared<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well then he achieved that. I think I'm<br />
too close to Mr. Whitlam There are obviously other<br />
things, and looking back over the record which would<br />
have to have merit and I don't want to be ungenerous about<br />
somebody who is departing the political scene. You might<br />
find this an odd remark what I am just going to say<br />
my mind has always focussed on the future. What's past is<br />
past, what's past is done with and it can't be altered and<br />
it's what we can do to effectively influence the future which<br />
is important to all Australians wherever they may be. The<br />
times when you give a proper judgement on the Whitlam years,<br />
I'd have 7-o consciously think back with overall the<br />
initiatives that are taken and give you a considered reply<br />
but when : hnings are past they move out of my mind very quickly.<br />
/ 17 </p>
<p>17<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued).<br />
There is so much in the present and so much<br />
affecting the future that I devote all my energies to that.<br />
QUESTION: As you know, you are constantly criticised<br />
as ce~ ng too centralised, too dominating, in the process<br />
of gz'-ernnmeft, that is you personally, and you've publicly<br />
rejec-e_. that charge quite often, once again. So I don't<br />
want to go over old ground, as you say, but I want you to<br />
be more specific in rejecting that charge.<br />
PRIMIE-M! TNSTER: Well I don't make statements about policy<br />
before zhe Government's made a view. So therefore you don't<br />
find me expressing views that are contrary to the views of<br />
the Government and the occasions when I might get'defeated<br />
in Cabinet therefore aren't on the public record but the<br />
Cabinet is a cabinet of people who've got forthright minds<br />
and they express them forthrightly and I don't respect a<br />
minister who isn't prepared to argue for what he believes<br />
and the ministers know that very. well indeed." Somebody<br />
would have to be inside the Cabinet room and know the nature<br />
of the discussions and the nature of the arguments that go<br />
on to really understand the way the system works. But that's<br />
what its got to be, but there is a collective responsibility.<br />
It's my responsibility to make sure that I don't, and a very<br />
significanz one, to make sure that in a sense that-I don't<br />
havb an identity outside the identity of the Government because<br />
then you start to have two views Fraser's view and the<br />
" Government's view ahd that would be damaging to any Government<br />
and I don't intend to let it happen. But I think you've only<br />
got to look at the nature of the people in the Cabinet and<br />
in the Ministry as a whole. It's aMinistry of very great<br />
talent, it's a very young Ministry, maybe the youngest in<br />
Australia's history and there are very few over ' 50' s in<br />
the total team. I don't think I can be more specific than<br />
that. It's a collective operation. Maybe ther6 are one or<br />
two things that can be said. There was one occasion, I've<br />
forgotten the subject matter, but a Minister announced something<br />
and the headline was " Fraser does this.." or " Fraser does<br />
that..". There is a habit in the media of personalizing<br />
decisions, it's a Government decision, it's gone through<br />
Cabinet and oh no, it's Fraser's decision. I'm not going<br />
to'name the subject matter because the Cabinet made it,<br />
the decision, while I was away. I still regard myself just<br />
as much responsible and bound by that decision as any other<br />
member of Cabinet. Life goes on and when I'm out of the<br />
country and unlike Mr. Whitlam I told the Cabinet to go on<br />
getting work done. I don't want things to be set aside when<br />
I'm out of the way there will be too big a list for me. to deal<br />
with when I come back. And that applied in particular over<br />
this last : rip and Doug Anthony had specific instructions to<br />
/ 18 </p>
<p>18<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ( continued)<br />
go on with the job of getting business through<br />
Cabinet and he did. But there was one decision announced<br />
and later on the commentators said " pers6nal decision of<br />
Fraser.' s". Well on that particular matter it was a decision<br />
taken by Government when I wasn't even in the country.<br />
Now this kind of reporting gives an impression that Fraser<br />
makes a decision, Fraser makes a decision, but the decisions<br />
are Government.<br />
QUESTION: The other claim that's been made in public in<br />
criticism of you is that certain sections of business can<br />
get dezisions made by Government from the top without<br />
going through the conventional public service channels and<br />
there's twi examples of that last year; one was the reference<br />
to the TAA, on Sir John Lysaght s on steel and iron, and the<br />
other one was the reference to the TAA Sir J. C. Williamson's<br />
or it must have been IAC, not J. C. Williamson's while the<br />
inquiry into the arts was going on.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I happened to be-responsible for the arts<br />
at that time and quite plainly if I was responsible for the<br />
arts and there was a problem in relation to J. C. Williamson's,<br />
as there had been, should we do something about it or should<br />
we not, as the Minister responsible for the arts I would have<br />
thought I should have taken some action to get advice in<br />
relation to it so the Government could make a decision and<br />
that's what happened. In relation to other matters; if people<br />
see me, I will say to the Minister, what's happening, what's<br />
the Department doing about this? And you generally find that<br />
they are well advanced in the process anyway. Now, I hope<br />
it's not leading to a position that the Prime Minister's got<br />
to stay in his office and not see anyone, not speak to anyone<br />
and not to be able to feel or hear outside what people outside<br />
this city, outside the Public Service are saying because I<br />
think that would be extraordinarly damaging. It would be<br />
very insular and obviously people put views to me and I am<br />
going to make'sure that I remain in a position in which they<br />
will go on putting views to me whether it's going into a<br />
pub and seeing what the blokes in the bar are saying there or<br />
whether it's an industrial or financial concern that's got<br />
some problems. I think I need to be capable of hearing what's<br />
said. QUESTION: Since the election campaign when you made that<br />
comment about the Royal Commission on Human Relations, I think<br />
I'm right, I may not be right but I think I'm right in saying<br />
that you've made. virtually no comments about what is loosely<br />
termed the social area of politics, no public comments that<br />
' is, or no important public comments. Is there any reason<br />
for that personally? And secondly, I want to ask you a<br />
specific social question, that is, what is your attitude towards<br />
the legislation legalising homosexual acts between consenting<br />
adults in Drivate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is legislation that's gone through the<br />
Parliament... / 19 </p>
<p>19<br />
QUESTION: The Federal Parliament? As you know it's<br />
a national happens nationally and I think there's only<br />
legislation to the South Australian Parliament.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, it's a matter for the States and<br />
State Parliaments.<br />
QUESTION: What is your attitude though, you must have<br />
an ai:: iu e?<br />
PRIME ITNISTER: I've on a number ofoccasions made statements<br />
to the e:: ect that people ought to be allowed to lead their<br />
own li estyles so long as they don't impinge upon the rights<br />
and position of other people or affect the lives of other<br />
people in a way that is unfortunate or undesirable. I don't<br />
alter that general'comment at all.<br />
QUESTION: Can you answer that specific question about<br />
homosexuality? PRIME MINISTER: Well, I think it's covered by what I've<br />
said. I don't see this is an area in which the Commonwealth<br />
needs to buy into what happens in the States. See, I have<br />
written to the Premiers on the Royal Commission on Human<br />
Relationships and asking them their views in relation to it<br />
and I don't think there have been responses yet, because so<br />
much of that, or the results of that; will depend upon State<br />
( inaudible) action and state legislation and before the<br />
Commonwealth wants to state a view we want the reactions of<br />
the states, we want the reactions of the community. Now this<br />
is a classic example of what I believe it's damaging, if I,<br />
Fraser, state views about things and the Government at a<br />
subsequent stage comes to a view. I don't believe I should,<br />
and in relation to that Royal Commission we need to assess<br />
the total position, the total reaction, then the Government<br />
will make a deal about whatever it ought to do in the areas<br />
( inaudible).<br />
QUESTION: This is a social area it's one where traditionally<br />
Parliaments have had, as you know, vote on conscience so therefore<br />
it's not a Party matter, or isn't necessarily a matter of<br />
Government policy.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Commonwealth Parliament has dealt with<br />
/ the that matter so far as/ Commonwealth arena is concerned. The<br />
rest is up to the States.<br />
QUESTION: Can I interpret your previous statement as<br />
saying that you don't necessarily approve of the act, but you<br />
would approve of the legislation that would not make it<br />
a criminal offence. That's what I'm really asking you.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: No, I don't believe it should be a criminal<br />
offence... with certain obvious safeguards.<br />
QUESTION: Assuming there is some strong economic recovery<br />
in Australia, which means without in any way becoming<br />
profligate, the Government doesn't have to be as-careful or<br />
as worried about day to day expenses as it does at the moment. </p>
<p>20<br />
' QUESTION: ( continued) What are the areas which haven't<br />
been nominated at all yet, where you would like to see a<br />
major initiative in Australia, which would obviously<br />
cost money, I'm not saying how much it would cost but<br />
a major initiative?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think one of the things that would<br />
assist Australia in many ways is to be able to do more<br />
to i-prove the basic infrastructure of this country. That<br />
not only helps citizens in their daily lives but would<br />
help business to be more efficient.<br />
QUESTION: Can you be more specific?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Ports, harbours, communications, the<br />
infrastructure financing guidelines in the proposals that<br />
are now being examined, Commonwealth/ State officials coming<br />
out of the Loan Council decision are ( inaudible) in this<br />
kind of direction and these are things which help industry,<br />
make Australia more efficient country, run on a better basis,<br />
make us better able to compete. This is the kind of area<br />
where greater expenditure, when that's possible, will I believe<br />
do the greatestgood for Australia. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
