<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5684</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005684.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 8 NOVEMBER 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
On a visit to South Australia at the weekend I was privileged<br />
to open a new swimmning pool for the handicapped at Minda Homes<br />
in Adelaide. This pool will both serve therapeutic purposes<br />
) and provide an avenue for recreation. The opportunities<br />
for rehabilitation offered by the Minda swimming pool are<br />
an example of the contribution being made throughout Australia<br />
by indivi'duals, voluntary agencies, organisations and<br />
governments in an effort to assist handicapped and disabled<br />
Australians to realise their fullest potential in this, the<br />
International Year of Disabled Persons.<br />
The Government has played a substantial part in encouraging<br />
and supporting these intiatives, for the Government's Liberal<br />
philosophy is one of concern for the well-being and fullest<br />
development of all people in our society. Commonwealth<br />
Government financial support for disabled and handicapped<br />
persons amounts to $ 1.1 billion this financial year. Even<br />
though governments and the community are doing much more than<br />
was the case, there are'still unfulfilled needs, and<br />
much yet remains to be done.<br />
However, the 39% real increase in expenditure that has taken<br />
place since the 1975 Labor Budget illustrates the real and<br />
sympathetic commitment of this Government -to the well-being<br />
of handicapped and disabled persons. A wide range of programmnes<br />
are being funded by the Government, including invalid pensions,<br />
sheltered employment allowances, handicapped children's<br />
benefits, subsidies to non-profit organisations and local<br />
government bodies which provide facilities for physically<br />
and intellectually handicapped people, ' and assistance for the<br />
production and publication of Braille and audio books for the<br />
print handicapped.%<br />
The International Year for Disabled Persons is not just a<br />
" one-off" exercise. Its impact will be of more lasting value<br />
in helping to achieve greater understanding and more -practical<br />
responses to the needs of handicapped people, and so far as<br />
the Government is concerned, our commitment to the cause of<br />
disabled persons will be a continuing one. ./ 2 % Z<br />
Y14<br />
_ A r_<br />
4, AUST LIA L </p>
<p>2<br />
There is growing support for less paternalistic or protective<br />
services, so that disabled people will have a greater<br />
measure of control over their own lives, and more freedom<br />
to pursue their own lives and interests in surroundings<br />
as normal as possible. I am confident that this progressive<br />
and responsible view will increasingly prevail from now on<br />
and while further consolidation will be needed, I see this<br />
as a major achievement of the International Year for<br />
Disabled Persons.<br />
The Government shares the view which is growing in the<br />
community that disabled people should be encouraged to develop<br />
their capacities to the fullest extent, that they should be<br />
enabled wherever possible and desirable, to live by themselves,<br />
or with their families, and to use community facilities as<br />
do the rest of us. Today, there is a widespread desire to<br />
) see disabled people being encouraged to accept the challenges<br />
of everyday living to the fullest extent of their abilities.<br />
To enjoy a meaningful home life and participate in all<br />
social, Greative or recreational activities is a right to<br />
which all people are entitled.<br />
I believe that when a disabled person is prepared to live<br />
independently and wants to do so, that ought to be encouraged.<br />
The community must be prepared to meet each case on an<br />
individual basis for without this response, the theme of<br />
the International Year for Disabled Persons " full participation<br />
and equality" will remain unfulfilled. 00o---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
