<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>19272</transcript-id>
    <title>Anzac Day Address</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/04/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Morning Service, Townsville</p>
<p>"Australians said goodbye ... and promised never to forget."</p>
<p>ANZAC DAY ADDRESS</p>
<p>MORNING SERVICE, TOWNSVILLE</p>
<p>25 APRIL 2013</p>
<p>CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY</p>
<p>So often, war means saying goodbye.</p>
<p>This city of Townsville understands that truth so well.</p>
<p>No one better exemplifies the ANZAC story of duty and sacrifice than the uniformed men and women of this garrison city who leave here so often to serve Australia overseas.</p>
<p>We honour you today.</p>
<p>No one better exemplifies the respect, the admiration, the affection, the love, we feel for our people in uniform than the families and citizens of this great Australian community.</p>
<p>Today, we honour your sacrifice too.</p>
<p>Saying goodbye in the hope your loved one will come back.</p>
<p>That is the story of this community today  -  it has been the story of so many Australian communities throughout our history  -  just as it was the story of the families and communities who farewelled the ANZACs in 1914 and 1915.</p>
<p>On docks and at railway stations around our land, mothers, wives, little brothers and sisters bravely suppressed tears.</p>
<p>Fathers extended grim handshakes.</p>
<p>Australians said good bye and promised never to forget.</p>
<p>Those who have been to war  -  you who have been to war  -  never forget its horror.</p>
<p>So many spend a lifetime comprehending the strange miracle of their own survival.The families of 102 000 Australians who died for us never forget war's horror too.</p>
<p>The dreadful sight of a clergyman or telegram boy coming up the driveway.</p>
<p>Or the phone ringing unexpectedly in the cool of night.</p>
<p>The wounded never forget the horror of war, imprinted as it is on their bodies and their minds.</p>
<p>They returned to lives that could never be what they once were.</p>
<p>Their loved ones often facing a different and longer battle behind the walls of the family home.</p>
<p>This is war as our country has known it  -  war as we remember it on this day.</p>
<p>War as the worst of human experience, war with its full dreadful price.</p>
<p>But with its pride and victories as well.</p>
<p>We remember that today, we remember our whole experience.</p>
<p>So if you want to know about Townsville, come here on ANZAC Day.</p>
<p>If you want to understand Australians, watch us on ANZAC Day.</p>
<p>You will see ceremonies as grave and solemn as any in Europe.</p>
<p>A nation which expresses its most eloquent patriotic spirit in the silences we share on this day.</p>
<p>Moments later, joyful laughter, rum and milk, two-up and the telling of stories that get taller by the hour  -  softening perhaps, but never denying, the truths of this day.</p>
<p>So much has been given to our nation by all who served.</p>
<p>And so little is asked in return.</p>
<p>That for a few hours each year, we hush the busy course of our lives and dedicate this day, to remember.</p>
<p>Lest we forget.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
