<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8116</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERNCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 SEPTEMBER 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008116.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
I. J PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, 6 SEPTEMBER 1990<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Cabinet tonight has made a number of major threshold decisions<br />
on micro economic reform. Going to telecommunications f irst, the<br />
Cabinet agreed to the introduction of effective competition as<br />
fundamental to any policy change that'll be finally decided. The<br />
Government will regulate effectively to ensure that such competition<br />
delivers the lowest possible prices to consumers and the highest<br />
possible quality of services and the early introduction of new<br />
technologies and community service obligations, particularly to rural<br />
and regional areas and to pensioners, will be guaranteed. Telecom<br />
itself will be retained in full public ownership and in the<br />
implementation of these changes, every attempt will be made to ensure<br />
the maximum participation of Australian industry.<br />
In regard to the airlines, it was agreed the Commonwealth would sell<br />
equity in both Australian Airlines and Qantas and that the extent of<br />
that divestment would be decided by Cabinet before the 24th of<br />
September. We will ensure in this way that the airline's capital<br />
needs are adequately met and obviously in that way, consequently take<br />
pressure off the Budget. As I say, the Cabinet will finalise its<br />
position on these issues before the 24th September, although you will<br />
see that we have, as I say, made major threshold decisions now in<br />
this regard. It was recognised that out of the processes of asset<br />
sale or licence sales, there will be potential for the Government to<br />
tackle high priority national infrastructure projects.<br />
Now, may I just make a couple of general comments about those<br />
decisions and the background to them. I know that it's been a matter<br />
of considerable comment by you all as to the extent of the processes<br />
in which we've been engaged, including the less than perfectly kept<br />
state secret that there are some divisions of opinion and emphasis<br />
amongst Ministers on this subject. I want to make the point that<br />
it's not in any sense surprising that there should be this extensive<br />
debate and these differences because what we're dealing with are<br />
issues which have been of fundamental philosophical importance to the<br />
Labor movement for a very long period of time. The suggestion that<br />
there could be serious change in the Party's position on these issues<br />
has aroused, naturally enough, very considerable discussion, debate,<br />
concern and fairly deeply held differences of opinion in the Party.<br />
The important thing is that the debate has been conducted in a<br />
serious way and there is no doubt that very many people in the Party<br />
have moved from what had previously been quite deeply entrenched<br />
positions and as far as the Government is concerned we've welcomed<br />
those discussions. </p>
<p>We have believed it's appropriate for us at this point to give these<br />
indications of principle as to where we stand. We will take account<br />
of the discussions that will go on in the next week or so, but before<br />
the conference is held, there will be a final indication of the<br />
details of the Government's view in these matters.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what do you mean by effective<br />
competition?<br />
PM: Well, it's a statement that, of principle, there must be<br />
ef fective competition. It is the case that still there would be<br />
differences of opinion as to what constitutes effective competition.<br />
For instance, and I'm not going to debate the issues and I don't<br />
think you're inviting me to, but for instance, some would say that<br />
without network competition you won't have effective competition.<br />
Others say that there are ways of getting effective competition<br />
without going to that point. Now that's still an issue which i's<br />
going to involve some discussion within the Party, so we're not<br />
trying to dodge the issue, we're saying as a principle there must be<br />
effective competition and by the time the Cabinet comes to make its<br />
final decision we'll spell out what we believe is involved in<br />
effective competition.<br />
JOURNALIST: You've talked about equity in Australian Airlines and<br />
Qantas PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have a figure on that at this point?<br />
PM: Well, the Cabinet hasn't. I think it would be fair to say that<br />
overwhelmingly Cabinet has a view as to what is appropriate in regard<br />
to Australian and in regard to Qantas, but we're not going to<br />
finalise that position until we've had the opportunity of some<br />
further discussion within the Party, but I can say that there's a<br />
fairly clear view and it wouldn't necessarily be the same for each<br />
airline. JOURNALIST: 49 percent for example?<br />
PM: Well, I think it's at least 49 percent.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, if Cabinet takes detailed decisions on<br />
these matters before September 24 and the special Party conference<br />
on that date<br />
PM: It sounds like a hypothetical coming up.<br />
JOURNALIST: Bit of a hypothetical, but should the special Party<br />
conference decide differently, can those Cabinet decisions be<br />
reversed? PM: I would believe that the view that Cabinet comes to would,<br />
because of its merit, be accepted by the Party conference. I<br />
understand and say to my Government colleagues that we have an<br />
obligation to listen to what the Party is saying. It's a bit of a<br />
reciprocal. I mean, they have an obligatio/ n also, I think, to listen </p>
<p>to what the Government is saying and thinking and I am optimistic<br />
that we'll get a mutuality in the process that will mean that the<br />
merit of the decision that's come to by the Government will be<br />
accepted by the Party.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said that these were threshold decisions,<br />
but in relation to telecommunications didn't you announce at the<br />
Press Club virtually those same principles yourself as very firm<br />
principles that you were already committed to?<br />
PM: Yes, although that's true to some extent, but I think it's, it<br />
should be noted that we are indicating in the decision that there<br />
will be a sale of some assets involved in the Government position in<br />
Telecom and that, to this point, has not been a position which is<br />
consistent with the Party policy as it stands.<br />
JOURNALIST: But the competition decision really was taken quite a<br />
while ago wasn't it, by you at least?<br />
PM: Well, that's true, but it's also equally true that since I made<br />
my statement to the Press Club that there are significant sections<br />
of the Party who've said they don't agree with that. They've said<br />
there shouldn't be any competition, it should be left as it is and<br />
what the Cabinet has confirmed in its decision tonight is that there<br />
shall be effective competition.<br />
JOURNALIST: decision is in relation to the future of Telecom and<br />
OTC. Are they coming together in a merger?<br />
PM: Well, that hasn't been so decided.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why has there been a delay in decision making?<br />
I understood<br />
PM: Well, that could I just finish in answer to Paul that the<br />
Cabinet will, I think, come to a specific decision on that next week.<br />
In other words, we won't be waiting right up until the eve of the<br />
conference to make that decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: Why couldn't you make it tonight, Mr Hawke?<br />
PM: Because there were good reasons in our consideration not to,<br />
which were not unrelated to the view that there was still room for<br />
some further discussion in that area.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Beg your pardon?<br />
JOURNALIST: Is one of those reasons the discussions that Minister<br />
Beazley had with the ACTU the other day?<br />
PM: That was one of the elements, one of the elements.<br />
JOURNALIST: So there'll be further talks with the ACTU?<br />
PM: The further talks that will take place, I think, could well<br />
include further discussions with some elements of the ACTU. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Foreign ownership, Mr Hawke<br />
PM: Sorry.<br />
JOURNALIST: Foreign ownership.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was it discussed in any of the telecommunications or<br />
airlines PM: It didn't, it had some passing discussion in regard to<br />
telecommunications. It was part of the discussion there, but in<br />
regard to the airlines, we didn't go to that in detail. It was<br />
really the very broad discussion that we had there. Although, let<br />
me say this, that in regard to the airlines we talked about that and<br />
it was quite clear that there will be limitations upon the level of<br />
capacity of foreign ownership of Australian airlines.<br />
JOURNALIST: On telecommunications, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: On telecommunications we haven't got any more detail<br />
tonight than we've had in a long time. Doesn't this make the<br />
Government look paralysed?<br />
PM: Well, I have no doubt that if that's what you think that's what<br />
you'll write. It will be incorrect. We're not paralysed. It was<br />
the point of making the comments I did in my opening remarks. We are<br />
not dealing with some peripheral issue in the affairs of the Labor<br />
Party here. We are dealing with something which, by anyone's<br />
standard who knows anything about the Labor movement, goes to deeply<br />
held issues on which there are very, very profound feelings. We<br />
could have been cavalier about it if you like, and said, alright<br />
we'll just say this is the decision of the Government and say there's<br />
been enough discussion in the Party, that's it. It's been sensible,<br />
in our judgement, to recognise that there's room for further<br />
discussion although what we felt we needed to do was to, as a<br />
Cabinet, indicate certain basic positions of principle. I think will<br />
be of some assistance in helping the process of discussion that will<br />
continue to go on up to and including the conference. Now, if you<br />
don't think that's intelligent, that it's a more intelligent way, a<br />
Ramboish way of saying to the Party, well you've had your turn,<br />
you'ye had enough time to discuss it, here's what we're going to ram<br />
down your throat and that that would not look a position of<br />
paralysis, well you write that if that's your interpretation. But<br />
permit me to say it would be a very inadequate analysis. </p>
<p>S<br />
JOURNALIST: You started walking down this path three<br />
years ago. It's a long time.<br />
PM: Yes, it is a long time. It will mean that when we do<br />
make the decision culminating in the conference that<br />
there will be a fundamental change in the position of the<br />
Australian Labor Party. If I've been responsible for<br />
initiating that, as I believe I have been, if it's taken<br />
three years, so be it. I would simply point out that in<br />
a period of seven and a half years in Government we have,<br />
as I've said before and you've heard me say, undertaken<br />
more micro-economic reform in that period than has ever<br />
been undertaken in any comparable period. Now we're<br />
setting ourselves to go further down that path which<br />
stands in the starkest of contrast to the absolute<br />
paralysis, if I can use that word, of the conservatives<br />
in power who never changed anything.<br />
JOURNALIST: With all proceeds Mr Hawke, will all the<br />
proceeds of the assets be used on infrastructure or<br />
will some be used to pay off our debt? And what<br />
mechanism do you have in mind for bringing that about?<br />
PM: I've made my position quite clear that I don't<br />
believe that it is responsible to say that you can just<br />
get a lump of money from the sale of assets and apply<br />
them to some particular area of expenditure. I believe<br />
that what you are certainly able to do with<br />
responsibility is to use the savings in respect of public<br />
debt interest in this area. It is very likely that out<br />
of the decisions that will be made by the Party there<br />
would be considerable amounts of money which would fit<br />
into that category.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Mr Beazley has been going around<br />
the Party, presumably with your acting consent, in the<br />
last few weeks promoting that option. Does he still have<br />
your support in that option?<br />
PM: I think you will have seen reference to the fact<br />
that I've expressed views as to possible alternatives to<br />
the model that the Minister has put. I happen to believe<br />
that his proposal would bring in significant competition<br />
and profound changes into the system. I think there are<br />
arguments as to whether an alternative may also have<br />
advantages, some different advantages. But if the<br />
decision in the end is the Beazley model it's my view<br />
that it will involve very very significant and I think<br />
irreversible changes for the Australian economy.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you indicate whether your own position<br />
is still support for Mr Beazley?<br />
PM: I have no reason to change what I've said and that<br />
is that I think there is room for argument that an<br />
alternative proposal could bring other advantages. But I<br />
recognise that this is an area in which that is clearly<br />
capable of argument. Certainly I know that Mr Beazley </p>
<p>profoundly believes and will so argue that his model is<br />
the best. Now there is still some further discussion to<br />
be had on that but I want to make it quite clear that if<br />
out of those discussions it is in fact the model that's<br />
been proposed by Mr Beazley that is the one that is<br />
adopted, I firmly believe that that would involve very<br />
significant improvements for Australia in that it would<br />
mean real competition introduced into the<br />
telecommunications industry.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think it would have been in<br />
retrospect better to have had this Cabinet discussion<br />
started the process rather than when Mr Beazley had gone<br />
this far with the Party?<br />
PM: Well you could perhaps argue that. But I don't have<br />
a strong feeling about that. It was inevitable, if you<br />
go back to what I said at the beginning of this<br />
conference, you had to know that you were dealing with<br />
S issues of very very deep concern in which there were<br />
going to be profound differences of opinion. It would<br />
have been an exercise in self-delusion if you would have<br />
thought that simply by adopting some particular technique<br />
of discussion at the beginning you were going to sweep<br />
that under the table. There is no way, whatever your<br />
technique that you adopted, that you were going to be<br />
able to avoid first of all a conference. Because you<br />
couldn't have changes without a conference. If you think<br />
that you're going to have a special conference of the<br />
Labor Party and wave some magic wand and in the period<br />
between making the decision have the special conference<br />
and the time of that special conference you weren't going<br />
to have profound discussions within the Party, I mean<br />
you're deluding yourself. You know nothing about the<br />
Party. JOURNALIST: You said that you wanted to keep Telecom,<br />
Cabinet wanted to keep Telecom in full public ownership.<br />
S Are there any aspects of Telecom, assets of Telecom which<br />
could be sold off, and if so, how? And what has Cabinet<br />
decided on who should own Aussat and OTC?<br />
PM: I would think that you could say that there is I<br />
think within the Party generally the question of Aussat<br />
is not really an issue about it being disposed of. There<br />
is still some debate in certain sections of the Party in<br />
regard to OTC.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, could I clarify the position<br />
of the airlines? I'm not sure what you meant. Has<br />
Cabinet made a decision about the proportion of<br />
privatisation and<br />
PM: No. The exact words Laurie. Cabinet agrees that<br />
the Commonwealth should sell ordinary voting shares in<br />
Australian Airlines Limited and Qantas Airways Limited.<br />
The extent of this devestment to be determined before the<br />
24th of September. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you expect Mr Keating to push<br />
on with his option, and should he?<br />
PM: Well I think that within the decision that's been<br />
made it will be open for anyone, Paul or any others who<br />
may have a different version or a different emphasis, to<br />
do that. When the Cabinet makes its decision next week<br />
on form then all Cabinet Ministers will be bound by it.<br />
JOURNALIST: You talked about competition. Does that in<br />
your view mean competition on the basic network?<br />
PM: That's the view I have.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you clarify the process for the Party<br />
resolution as far as the National Executive is<br />
concerned and will the final resolution still give<br />
Cabinet some flexibility?<br />
PM: I believe from the discussions I've had today that<br />
you won't have a firm detailed decision from the National<br />
Executive tomorrow. Rather you'd have a form of decision<br />
I would think and expect that it was broad enough to say<br />
that there would need to be changes in the Party platform<br />
to achieve certain broad positions and then leaving the<br />
detail of that still to be the subject of the sort of<br />
discussion for instance that we'll be having in the<br />
Cabinet and other sections of the Party will be having<br />
before the conference.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, Martin Ferguson today made some<br />
statements basically embracing the Beazley option. How<br />
important will that be in your view in terms of the<br />
internal factional debate in the ALP?<br />
PM: It will have different importance for different<br />
factions and for different parts of different factions.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I think the answer to your question is that<br />
different parts of the Left would attach different<br />
emphasis to the views of Martin Ferguson. I don't think<br />
that's a particularly clever answer. I think it's just<br />
the correct answer.<br />
JOURNALIST: How soon will people get cheaper airfares or<br />
cheaper phone calls out of this<br />
PM: I think the question of the level of airfares will<br />
be in part a function of the decision that's already<br />
taken which is going to with effect with the end of<br />
the two airline system. In fact you're already starting<br />
the see the effect of that. So the disentanglement of<br />
causes in reductions in airfares will be a bit difficult<br />
to take. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: I would think quite quickly. I mean you would have<br />
to obviously work out a tender process and we would<br />
clearly be wanting to do that as quickly as possible. I<br />
would think it would be, I would hope certainly it would<br />
be within this financial year.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does that apply telecommunications?<br />
PM: No, that was in respect of I thought your question<br />
was in regard to airlines there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well what about telecommunications?<br />
PM: It's conceivable that it might take somewhat longer<br />
in regard to Telecom. But I would need to be advised on<br />
that. JOURNALIST: When you said competition means competition<br />
in the basic network, is that your view?<br />
PM: I answered that question there. I was asked<br />
specifically the question then, just a moment ago, did I<br />
think that it meant that. My answer to that was yes. If<br />
you'd noted my earliest answer, I said that for some<br />
people in the Party it means network competition. Others<br />
believe that you can have effective competition with<br />
something less than that. I've answered what I think.<br />
JOURNALIST: So what I wanted clarified was the Cabinet<br />
decision in favour of competition refers to also those<br />
people who believe you don't need network competition.<br />
PM: Yes I've already said that in my earlier answer.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, on the proceeds you've said<br />
that Cabinet will make detailed decisions before the<br />
24th. Will it go to Caucus before the 24th as well?<br />
PM: I would think not. I would think not. But I<br />
haven't specifically addressed myself to that. I don't<br />
know that there's any expectation that that would be the<br />
case. But I wouldn't think so.<br />
JOURNALIST: concern Mr Hawke is the privatisation of<br />
OTC one of the issues still before the Cabinet?<br />
PM: Yes, that is something which is in a sense still on<br />
the table. That will be determined next week.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you think the Party might be prepared to<br />
go that far?<br />
PM: Some parts of the Party would. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: How concerned are you at the divisions and<br />
how confident are you that consensus can be reached by<br />
the 24th?<br />
PM: I meant what I said earlier Michael that I'm not in<br />
any sense surprised at the divisions that have<br />
transpired. It would have been an exercise in ignorance<br />
for anyone to expect that you could go to the issue of<br />
the possible privatisation of Government-owned airlines<br />
or the introduction of competition into Telecom without<br />
having significant debate and division within the Party.<br />
Just impossible. That was what was going to happen. The<br />
fact is we've been prepared to face up to that, have<br />
fairly prolonged processes which are inevitable. Once<br />
the conference was set that was going to happen in the<br />
period up until the conference. But as I've said before,<br />
the important point is this, that at the end of that<br />
process the political debate, the real political debate<br />
will be set. And it will be the debate between the<br />
Australian Labor Party which believes, in the area of<br />
Telecom, in retaining a fully-fledged Telecom facility<br />
within full public ownership. That will be the position<br />
of the Australian Labor Party. Against that you will<br />
have the conservatives of this country who would dispose<br />
of the totality of the telecommunication industry to the<br />
private sector. That will be the debate. It will be a<br />
clear debate and it will be a debate that we will win.<br />
JOURNALIST: PM, you said that the process looked<br />
inelegant, I think were your words, once before<br />
PM: Sure, sure.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you agree that it's looking even<br />
distinctly messy at the moment?<br />
PM: No. I mean I'm sure that that's the way you want to<br />
9 write it. But I just go back, I mean you seem to want me<br />
to say it five times. I must sound good in saying it so<br />
I'll say it the fifth time. It was inevitable. You<br />
cannot go to an issue, a sacred issue in the Labor Party<br />
like the ownership, the public ownership of its assets<br />
and the airline industry and the question of uncompeted<br />
against Telecom, you can't go to those issues if you know<br />
anything about the facts of political life and expect<br />
that there will be other than pretty vigorous debate and<br />
argumentation. Anyone who thought that you weren't going<br />
to have that simply doesn't know their politics and<br />
doesn't know their Labor Party. I just come back to the<br />
point I made in which and which I hope I walk out<br />
now, that having gone through what you might want to<br />
describe as our mess or our trauma or our exhilarating<br />
experience, whichever way you want to look at it and<br />
however you want to describe it, what the realities will<br />
be at the end, we will have made up our mind and it will<br />
be in this telecommunications area unequivocally in<br />
favour or a fully publicly-owned telecommunication<br />
facility operating across the spectrum internationally </p>
<p>and domestically. And against that the conservatives who<br />
want to throw it all over to the private sector. I<br />
repeat, that will be the debate and it's the one we will<br />
win. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
