<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7715</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JOHN JOST, RADIO 3LO 21 AUGUST 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007715.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
( Q-<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JOHN JOST, RADIO<br />
21 AUGUST 1989<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
JOST: on the programme today Australia's Prime Minister Mr<br />
Bob Hawke and Mr Hawke is sitting down in front of me right<br />
now. Good morning Prime Minister.<br />
0 Good Morning John<br />
JOST: Well thanks for joining us.<br />
My pleasure. Sorry I'm late but there was a bit of a<br />
traffic jam.<br />
JOST: I know it is not easy. I understand that. If I<br />
didn't leave home to get in here at 6am I'd probably miss it<br />
myself. I was just wondering as I was listening to your<br />
programme whether you dedicated that first song to the<br />
pilots. JOST: Well I will ask you about the pilots?<br />
I thought you might.<br />
0 JOST: First up not so much about the pilots, about the<br />
tactics of it. I suppose it would be traditional would it<br />
not to apply for a bans cause and then I suppose if the<br />
Pilots Federation breaches that clause to fine or have them<br />
fined for contempt. Why is the Government suggesting that<br />
the pilots be put out of the system? What makes them so<br />
different? Because we have a situation now where the whole wage<br />
fixing process in the country is operating under the<br />
centralised direction of the Industrial Relations Commission<br />
and the wage and salary earners of Australia in general have<br />
submitted to that system in a way which has effected the<br />
capacity to create one and a half million new jobs. These<br />
people are saying well we are not going to be part of that<br />
system. And therefore it is appropriate, as the<br />
Commissioners put to them, well you make your mind up. Be in<br />
it or not. If you're out of it then quite clearly with the </p>
<p>-2-<br />
approbation of the whole of the organized workforce then all<br />
the processes of the law are properly available to be used<br />
against them. Now let me make it clear as I did In my press<br />
conference yesterday John. I don't want to see that. I'm<br />
not trying to push them out of the system. I desperately<br />
would hope that they would make the decision to stay in and<br />
to stop regarding themselves as something different. This<br />
mythology that pilots are trying to create about themselves<br />
that somehow they are unique because they get up there and<br />
fly an areoplane that somehow not only are they sort of<br />
physically above us all but in other ways. It is about time<br />
they in a sense came back to earth.<br />
JOST: They compare themselves to judges.<br />
Well why? Why do they compare themselves to judges?<br />
What in the name of anything that starts to make sense have<br />
they got in common with judges. Look lets get down to the<br />
facts. Lets stop this mythology that pilots are something<br />
different. I mean in terms what are they? They are people<br />
that fly an aeroplane. Great responsibility. But so have<br />
bus drivers got great responsibility.<br />
JOST: Pilots do do exams every year.* They have quite a<br />
high standard of qualification and they have to maintain<br />
those qualifications. Look, of course they have to have qualifications, but<br />
in terms of actually learning to fly, to become a pilot, it<br />
is not something flash. It's a relatively easy thing to do.<br />
There is no mystery about flying an aeroplane. I learnt to<br />
fly an aeroplane when I was at Oxford and flew an aeroplane.<br />
JOST: What sort of aeroplane did you fly?<br />
They were chipmunks, and I tell you what. You compare<br />
these JOST: Hawke and the Chipmunk.<br />
PM: Hawke and the Chipmunk. Yes, had a lot of fun<br />
too. And of course that's a great thing about this<br />
profession. People love it, they want to fly, they get great<br />
pleasure out of flying. It is exhilarating. They want to<br />
get their exhilarition away from their exhilariation as to<br />
what they are worth. I mean-<br />
JOST: Do you think they have been overpaid for 20 years? </p>
<p>Well I am not saying that they have been overpaid for<br />
for 30 years. But what I'm certainly saying is that they are<br />
not worth the 30% increase now.<br />
JOST: Right. That is a nonsense.<br />
JOST: Well just on the tactics you are using, because it is<br />
a little bit reminiscent I suppose in the class of action<br />
as say the dollar sweeps case.<br />
Well what about it?<br />
JOST: Well it is just interesting to me that you take that<br />
route. It may well encourage employees, or employers I<br />
should say in other industries or other areas to do the same<br />
thing that you may not necessarilly like<br />
Well I don't encourage that at all. What I'm saying<br />
is that we have got a Conciliation and Arbitration system<br />
which is working well in the interests of all Australians.<br />
There's been wage restraint exercised by people considerably<br />
less well placed than these greedy pilots. Ordinary working<br />
men and women and many of them I might say who've had to work<br />
a lot harder to get their qualifications than pilots. I mean<br />
you look at a trades person. They do their 4 or 5 years<br />
apprenticeship. They have not got the glory and glamour of<br />
pilots, but if you look at it objectively in terms of the<br />
training that these people do to acquire their capacity they<br />
do relatively much more than pilots do. And yet because<br />
these people are up in the air with this glory of flying<br />
people around they suddenly say they are entitled to another<br />
I mean it is a nonsense. I mean we've got, look at the<br />
fellows who are flying in the Air Force<br />
JOST: Judges. But why? Why do you compare a pilot with a judge?<br />
JOST: I'm not. I'm pointing out that judges are<br />
Judges have exercised enormous salary restraint,<br />
enormous salary restraint. They are not part of the general<br />
wage and salary system. They haven't had an award with all<br />
the rights and obligations of a Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
system. Judges haven't had. These people had the rights and<br />
the obligations of the Conciliation and Arbitration system.<br />
Now they want to say alright we're out. O. K. if they're out<br />
they'll cop all that goes with being out. </p>
<p>JOST: Could I please put something to you on this question<br />
of people who are on higher salaries and I suppose pilots are<br />
a sort of a classic because they fit the band of individual<br />
or the band of salary that I'm thinking of. Those people in<br />
those salaries who sort of have a statutory limitation on<br />
increases are the ones that would have depended I suppose or<br />
would have hoped that the marginal rate of tax would come<br />
down from 49 to 39 because that wouuld sort of somehow or<br />
other make up that would be their sort of wages tax<br />
write-off for exercising restraint. And I'm thinking of<br />
people like of judges<br />
Well there's been a movement for judges and so there<br />
should have been because in respect of judges you had the<br />
situation that the ranks from which they come, that's the<br />
barristers who by and large are very well paid.<br />
JOST: And you've got to get good Judges.<br />
And you've got to get good judges.<br />
JOST: And who want's to be a good who, one of those great<br />
barristers want to go to the bench if they're going to loose<br />
so much money.<br />
Yes well that's obviously partly true and we've had to<br />
take account of that. I think the community would say they<br />
want a good judicial system and there is no discernable<br />
objection to a situation that people who are going to be<br />
there in that important position judges shouldn't have<br />
got a significant salary increase. As I say, they are not<br />
part of the award system. They're not people who are there<br />
getting their rights and their obligations under the system.<br />
The pilots are.<br />
JOST: Can I just-<br />
Just the basic point that annoys all hell out of me is<br />
the way in which these people are trying to glorify<br />
themselves because they fly an aeroplane. And may I say for<br />
less than 10 hours a week do they fly the damn thing. I mean<br />
your listeners understand, the average hours that these<br />
people are actually at the stick Is about eight hours a week.<br />
JOST: But you could blame management for being inefficient<br />
on that front couldn't you. It's not the pilots' fault. </p>
<p>Well, what you can blame is the fact that over a<br />
period of years the pilots have exercised their muscles and<br />
at one stage or another, managements have caved in. Not<br />
because they have wanted to but they thought they haven't had<br />
any alternative. Well they've got an alternative now. I<br />
mean the pilots have got to understand, and I hope they do<br />
stay within the system at 4 o'clock this afternoon, but<br />
there's not going to be a cave in by the airlines or by the<br />
Government. They're going to start to realise<br />
JOST: Would you use the Government's VIP fleet if the<br />
Well just wait and see what we'll use.<br />
JOST: It's going to be boots and all will it?<br />
All of us John are the product of our history. All of<br />
us. Now these people are the product of a history where in<br />
the past where they've gone in and had a fight, pretty soon<br />
either Ansett or TAA as it was have caved in. Now that's<br />
their history and that's the sort of fight they think they<br />
will go into if they go on with this. Well let me tell them<br />
its a different fight they're going Into.<br />
JOST: What about the Beville workers? What if they push the<br />
wage decision forward? They could sort of tip the whole box<br />
and dice over too.<br />
Look, we've been going for over six years now under<br />
the Accord and as I've said I'm getting a bit sick and tired<br />
of people saying the Accord is finished, it's all over, what<br />
if these do, what if this do that. I think you've got the<br />
situation where you've got some very, very good people on the<br />
union side, you've some very good people on the employers<br />
side. I think of Bert-Evans and the people around him in the<br />
metal trades employers, and you've got the ACTU. They with<br />
the Commission, with the very wise guidance of the Industrial<br />
Relations Commission, they'll work It out.<br />
JOST: Just like to ask you a couple of quick ones? Well<br />
actually about that accord though. It is a source of<br />
constant amazement to look at it, how it does endure<br />
But why should it be?<br />
JOST: Well, it is interesting. I will tell you why.<br />
Because for instance say at one stage I think when it first<br />
came down I mean we have had various remodelings of it.<br />
We've had full indexation promised. We've had quarterly wage<br />
adjustments promised under it. A whole lot of things which<br />
haven't been delivered. But I just the point about the </p>
<p>-6-<br />
question is this. Is one when you are in Government you are<br />
literally learning on the job and you find you make a deal<br />
like that, you make a deal like an Accord one or Accord two<br />
and you've literally got to scrap...<br />
Look, look go back to the beginning. I'm now talking<br />
as one of the proud fathers of the Accord, the whole concept.<br />
And what did I say at the beginning? I said this will be a<br />
flexible instrument. I mean you can't in life, unless you<br />
want to be a real whacker, say look here, I've got something<br />
which is absolutely unchangeable. I mean in the areas of<br />
human and organizational I've suddenly found some<br />
instrument which is absolutely inflexible when you are<br />
dealing with the a relations between groups. But it's the<br />
concept, the concept was a very simple one. That is that you<br />
are much more likely trade unions, organized workers and<br />
employers -to get the achievement of your mutual interests<br />
if you co-operate, talk together, than if you have a head on<br />
confrontation. Now its worked out. I mean on the side of<br />
employers their profitability has increased. On the side of<br />
workers they've got, as I say, a million and a half new<br />
jobs. It's a rate of job creation four times faster than it<br />
was before and<br />
JOST: They've lost on their wages though.<br />
Yes but we have delivered on the Accord in terms of<br />
the massive improvements in the social wage. Look at what's<br />
been delivered in terms of health care, pensions,<br />
superannuation, education, all the things we promised we<br />
would deliver on. So there has been that flexibility. And I<br />
said in 1983 when we delivered the Accord, I said this will<br />
work because it is in the interests of all the people<br />
concerned that it shall work. There will be flexibility.<br />
That's what there's bee-n.<br />
JOST: Can I ask you a couple of quick ones?<br />
Quick comments really. Live sheep exports to Saudi Arabia.<br />
What's going on there?<br />
Its a very disturbing situation. You've had last year<br />
a level of exports, about a quarter of a billion dollars. As<br />
far as I can ascertain as I have been briefed by listening to<br />
Mr Kerin, the shipments have not been of a kind that can in<br />
any objective way be not approved. We have therefore<br />
arranged for a high level delegation to go there and try to<br />
get this thing sorted out. I believe that it can be because<br />
the reputation of the Australian farmers and suppliers is<br />
high. </p>
<p>-7-<br />
JOST: Well our sheep have pox, they have got<br />
bi uetongue. Well wait a minute.<br />
JOST: I mean this is what the Saudi's are saying.<br />
Yes, that's what they are saying. I'm glad you added<br />
that. They are saying that. What is being said by our<br />
people here is that that's not the case.<br />
JOST: And they pull the plug on a while he was there?<br />
We'll we've been unable to unload the sheep elsewhere<br />
there in the Middle East but, I mean let me say this. If in<br />
fact what they are alleging was true then it would have to be<br />
dealt with. But the thing is to get the facts sorted out.<br />
JOST: It is obviously not true. I mean have they got some<br />
sort of internal problem the Saudis?<br />
Well I don't know. This is what we are going to find<br />
out John.<br />
JOST: Yes it is a fasciniating one. At the weekend there<br />
was a push from within the ALP to revive the idea of a<br />
referendum over the environment?<br />
P. M: Yes<br />
JOST: Does that idea appeal to you?<br />
I saw that reference. Let's see as we go. What we<br />
have discovered, painfully, in this country is that if you<br />
haven't got bipartigsan support you haven't got much chance of<br />
getting a referendum carried. What we've said to the<br />
opposition, if you're dinkum you would indicate your support<br />
for this and we could go ahead with great confidence then.<br />
So just let's see how this thing develops.<br />
JOST: If you could get a situation-<br />
May I just add to this. The fundamental difference<br />
between ourselves and the Opposition. We are dinkum about<br />
the environment. We don't believe that the Federal<br />
Government should not be prepared to override the States in<br />
certain circumstances. The Opposition say no, no<br />
interference with State rights, which means in the end if you<br />
adhered to that position that the level of Australian<br />
standards would be equal to the worst of the States. I don't<br />
like that. </p>
<p>-8-<br />
JOST: Well look another one. It's a long way down the track<br />
but at the moment we have had, in the aftermath of the<br />
Fitzgerald Inquiry, the suggestion that there should be one<br />
vote one value in Queensland. Obviously that may not come to<br />
fruition, the desire or wish as expressed by Mr Fitzgerald.<br />
Does that tempt you to have another go at one vote one value<br />
if Queensland won't clean itself up?<br />
Well, not a temptation. But I go back to the point I<br />
just made. I think the Australian people need to ask why the<br />
conservative parties in this country, the Liberals and the<br />
National Party, that unholy marriage, why are they opposed to<br />
the concept of one vote one value? If the Liberals would say<br />
yes we would support that we would do it like a shot.<br />
JOST: Is it possible that you might find yourself asking<br />
them if there was intrangience on behalf of the National<br />
Party Well, I don't know. There is no evidence that there<br />
is any principle on the part of the Liberals at all. As far<br />
as the National Party well what a joke they have become.<br />
The National Party is just rural warfare incorporated.<br />
JOST: Yes well look I tell you there was a bit of warfare it<br />
seems to me between Treasury and the Reserve Bank?<br />
Is there? Well inform me John.<br />
JOST: You have to interpet the Reserve Bank it's a<br />
pretty delphic body as you know.<br />
Well I have been on it. I was a member of the Board<br />
of the Reserve Bank for about seven years.<br />
PM: don't have any misconceptions about that.<br />
JOST: And no doubt you will correct my interpretation.<br />
But there does appear to be a question in whether high<br />
interest rates will be enough to slow the economy coming from<br />
the Reserve Bank. They feel there should be more done.<br />
Look, when you are talking about an economy which is<br />
growing very strongly and you're using monetry policy<br />
together with tight fiscal and wages policy to slow things<br />
down, it is not a question of competition or anything like<br />
that. Economists and commentators, whether they are in the<br />
Reserve Bank, the Treasury, the private banking system, the<br />
acedamic World </p>
<p>-9-<br />
JOST; Of course they argue. I accept that.<br />
They are differences of opinion.<br />
JOST: I accept that.<br />
It's quite legitimate to have a perception expressed,<br />
whether it's from the Reserve Bank or elsewhere, it might<br />
take a little bit longer than some people think. What's<br />
strange about that? I mean I doubt if you would find, if I<br />
got you a dozen economists, whether you would get anything<br />
other than about six or seven different opinions. If they<br />
said what week is it going to slow down, or is it-going to be<br />
definite that interest rates start coming down. Out of a<br />
dozen economists you would probably get ten different<br />
opinions. JOST: What you would say, I mean I could only agree with,<br />
because I'm aware that you yourself for instance rather like<br />
this idea of some sort of concessions on the interest and tax<br />
front. Now, wait a minute, you are in a very jumpy position<br />
this morning John, I mean jumping to positions. What I liked<br />
was the idea of examining it. Now don't give me this<br />
business. I mean you've got no basis saying I like the idea.<br />
The one thing I liked was when something was there on the<br />
table, which prima facie could have some merit, what I<br />
demanded was that it be examined. We examined it and on<br />
balance it was certainly not the right thing to do.<br />
JOST: Did the suggestion come to you from the Reserve Bank?<br />
No. About some decision to, some proposal to<br />
JOST: Interest deductability on, you know, the<br />
non-inflation But, you're talking about the mortgage adjustment<br />
first of all, now you're talking about the inflation<br />
adjustment. JOST: No, no, I'm really talking about the, I'm talking<br />
about the tax break on interest rates.<br />
The inflation adjustment for interest on both sides of<br />
the ledger?<br />
JOST: Yes. The receipts and outlays. </p>
<p>JOST: Yes. No, on that one, that didn't come from the Reserve<br />
Bank to me.<br />
JOST: Cos it would appear that the Reserve Bank likes..<br />
Let me be quite clear. Was one of the fellows on my<br />
staff, an economist on my staff a very good mind he said<br />
you know this is worth having a look at. Boy did we have a<br />
look at it. We had a look at it and so did Treasury and dear<br />
oh dear. I mean you heard what I said on the Sunday<br />
Programme three weeks ago. I made the assertion they will<br />
not go to the election with this one. And how would you like<br />
ten dollars worth of that?<br />
JOST: O. K. Well listen, a quick question about this<br />
Melbourne-Sydney very fast train.<br />
Yes.<br />
JOST: Do you support that?<br />
Yes.<br />
JOST: It's interesting to-me. It was suggested and Jim<br />
Kennan confirmed it down here that the promoters of that<br />
scheme would be interested in setting up a couple of cities<br />
along the track, somewhere down the line between Melbourne<br />
and Sydney. Now that, I mean it would be a huge<br />
decentralization exercise and no doubt a huge capital expense<br />
and it would probably involve a lot of help from governments.<br />
P. M. Clearly the concept that's involved by the developers<br />
is that they would have--access under legislation by<br />
governments of INSW and Victoria to land which would be able<br />
to be developed. And this would form part of the basis under<br />
which they would finance the development.<br />
JOST: Sure. That's been made quite clear from the beginning. Now<br />
as far as the governments are concerned though the developers<br />
have made it quite clear that they are not looking for, do<br />
not expect financial support from governments. My support<br />
from the Commonwealth Government which is very firm<br />
support-</p>
<p>11<br />
JOST: I was really thinking in terms of co-operation,<br />
because if you<br />
It would require co-operation yes for sure.<br />
JOST: Because if you were to create a city and if so what<br />
sort of cities are they talking about?<br />
You are talking about developments which will make it<br />
very, very much more attractive for people to buy land on<br />
these routes at very very much lesser prices and in more<br />
congenial environments than are continually crowding out in<br />
Sydney and in Melbourne.<br />
JOST: So you see the cities feeding Sydney and Melbourne<br />
with workers or with their own work base.<br />
It will work in two ways. They will, you will be able<br />
to provide commuters who will want to go into Sydney or<br />
Melbourne. But also I see these things developing as<br />
economic centres in their own right. It will be a<br />
combination of both.<br />
JOST: It's a pretty big, it would be an enormous project<br />
wouldn't it. I mean I can't...<br />
Of course it is but you know what the world is<br />
about. JOST: I'm not criticising.<br />
I know you are not<br />
JOST: I'm just interested in a few facts on it, because all<br />
we've heard is, we've heard a few environmental arguments<br />
I'm not implying John that you are criticising it but<br />
I just find I'm a little bit surprised when people say isn't<br />
this a big thing. What the world is about, what progress is<br />
about is big developments.<br />
JOST: Sure, and I would imagine that's the sort of<br />
development that if you are going to develop that's the sort<br />
of thing Federal Government ought be getting into.<br />
Absolutely.<br />
JOST: But, its interesting to know sort of city, what sort<br />
of vision you would have for It? </p>
<p>-12-<br />
Well, I have told you the vision. Its a vision that<br />
we have a city now of Sydney of about three and a half to<br />
three and a quarter million people bursting at the seams, by<br />
nature limited on the one side by the ocean, on the other<br />
side by the mountains. Limited in terms of its capacity for<br />
proper expansion. Melbourne, relatively much better placed<br />
but still a very very large city. People who want to be able<br />
to get land at a reasonable price in congenial conditions. I<br />
see the exciting vision of an opening up of a whole corridor<br />
along the eastern states which is going to provide the<br />
opportunity for an expansion of our economy and the<br />
development of better living conditions for hundreds of<br />
thousands of our people.<br />
JOST: Mr Hawke thank you very much, but just temporarily,<br />
because I have been given approval in another way that you<br />
don't know about to keep you here for another 10 minutes<br />
after the news break.<br />
That's beaut, because I always enjoy it.<br />
JOST: Mr Hawke, looking down the track a bit what do you<br />
think your major difficulties will be in the next federal<br />
election? Urn<br />
JOST: Apart from fixing a date?<br />
No I don't have any difficulty about that. That will<br />
come easily. In a sense I think one of the major problems is<br />
going to be complancency. I think the Australian people are<br />
increasingly coming to understand the correctness of the<br />
Governments economic policies, the commitment we have to<br />
making the tough decistens and not just take the easy way<br />
out. They're certainly getting increasing evidence of the<br />
internal bitterness and division, hatreds,. lack of policy and<br />
direction of the Opposition. I think one of the things I'll<br />
have to guard against with myself to some extent, although<br />
not much there but with others, will be a sense of<br />
complacency. We have got to keep on making the, at times,<br />
tough decisions because we can't afford to have a level of<br />
economic activity bringing in imports at a level which we<br />
can't afford to pay for and earn by our exporting activity.<br />
Now, provided we keep our nerve and keep making those<br />
decisions we will be respected by the Australian people and<br />
we will win the election.<br />
JOST: In your election campaign though you would have<br />
underline that fact.' I mean you would be selling them a hard<br />
diet, wouldn't you? </p>
<p>-13-<br />
Well not just a hard diet. Go back to 1987. People,<br />
as I have said before, told me I couldn't win then because we<br />
had tough policies there and I said well I have a greater<br />
respect for the Australian people than most of the<br />
commentators seem to have. If you tell them as it is then<br />
they understand that. You say its just hard diet. Yes it is<br />
hard in some respects but it's not a bad story we've got to<br />
tell in so many ways. I mean you show me a period in<br />
Australian history when we have been creating jobs at the<br />
rate we've created them in our six and a half years in<br />
Government twice as fast as the rest of the world. Where<br />
in terms of our education system when we came to office, the<br />
legacy of the Libs, only 36% of our kids staying in the<br />
education system. Now its 58% and rising. Where we have had<br />
these historic achievements in terms of<br />
JOST: What proportion of that group will get to tertiary<br />
education? Well that's rising, which is reflected by the fact<br />
that we have created over 200% more tertiary places than was<br />
created under our predecessors. In this next four year<br />
period we will be creating new places which will be<br />
equivalant to the size of Adelaide, Melbourne and Sydney<br />
Universities. So that's to take account of more people that<br />
are staying on in the tertiary system as well.<br />
JOST: I take it that it's fairly easier for those people<br />
who graduate from tertiary institutions to get jobs than it<br />
would be say if those kids had not gone there.<br />
PX: That's right, yes. I mean all the evidence shows it.<br />
The more our young people are trained and educated, whether<br />
it be in the secondary, the technical or the university<br />
atmosphere the greater is their chance of employment.<br />
JOST: Itd just like to whip through a few things with you.<br />
Last week you suggested you might leave the Labor Party at<br />
the election after the next election. You also said Paul<br />
Keating would eventually be Prime Minister. Was that just<br />
one option?<br />
PM: Whyt do you think I might lead It into three elections<br />
after this one?<br />
JOST: You might decide to go </p>
<p>-14-<br />
PM: I'm not. Don't lot that get any..<br />
JOST: Right, we've settled that. well it jutse. that<br />
Mr Keating obviously gets frustrated with hisslotand he's<br />
likely to get frustrated again. No matter what his good<br />
intentions are now he's going to get frustrated within six<br />
months probably after the election.<br />
PM: ( inaudible)<br />
JOST: John Dawkins..<br />
PM: You fellas amuse me. Paul and I make it quite clear<br />
what the situation is. I heard you and Michelle going on<br />
about it this morning.<br />
JOST: It's fair enough though because a lot of people<br />
PM: sure it's fair enough. It's a lovely free<br />
democracy. If you and Miche 1le and all the others want to<br />
play games about<br />
JOST: Paul Keating was playing games this time last year<br />
wasn't he?<br />
PM: He got a little bit frustrated. The tact of life is<br />
that we fixed that up very quickly and as you will find both<br />
Paul and myself say our working relationship has never been<br />
better. Now that's a fact so if you want to play around and<br />
conjure up ideas and thoughts say that's beaut, that's<br />
what our information tree democracy is about.<br />
JOST: Do you think it'd be right then for him to be<br />
Treasurer for ten years?<br />
PM: You wouldn't have a better Treasurer. But I'm not<br />
suggesting that he needs to be for ten years. You see Paul<br />
enjoys being Treasurer. He would certainly enjoy being<br />
Prime Minister. I'm making the point he does enjoy being<br />
Treasurer. I've made it clear to Paul that if he' wanted<br />
to or to try some other portfolio of course he could.<br />
That was in no way wanting to push him. On the contrary<br />
because I reckon he's such a great Treasurer. But in<br />
fairness to him I have in the past raised and did he<br />
want to think about it. He makes the point that apart from<br />
the Prime Ministership there's no other portfolio that<br />
really grabs him like Treasurer that's understandable.<br />
JOST: You are satisfied that it you do go yu ultr<br />
next time that you won't be costing Australia the next best<br />
Prime minister? </p>
<p>PM: Sure, sure.<br />
JOST: Right. Next time around if you win what reforms are<br />
left to you? What do you do? What have you got left in you<br />
as a leader of this country?<br />
PM: Well, you don't change goal posts and say after this<br />
election I'm going to get a new vision, a new set of<br />
visions. I've been amused by some of the commentators who<br />
say well what's the vision? We had our vision when we came<br />
to office in ' 83 and that vision put as simply as I can was<br />
an Australia which would be remember what the three ' r's<br />
were when I was in opposition for that brief period? The<br />
three ' r's were reconciliation, recovery and reconstruction.<br />
That was the Hawke concept on which the election of ' 83 was<br />
fought. That was a vision. we had to be reconciled as a<br />
nation. We were in conflict one with the other. The Accord<br />
and the negotiations that we carry on constantly the<br />
apparatus that we have for consultation with all the<br />
community is involved in the process of reconciliation. We<br />
had to have the immediate recovery from the worst recession<br />
in 50 years and then reconstruction and that reconstruction<br />
was a reconstruction not only of our economy but of our<br />
social welfare system and of our place in the world. And<br />
that's what we are about and it's going to be really a<br />
continuation of that reconstruction of Australia to make our<br />
economy more dynamic more internationally competitive it's<br />
going to be a continuing reconstruction of our social<br />
welfare system so that it's more targeted upon those in need<br />
that's what we will be doing and will increase it.<br />
JOST: Are you sorry that you didn't get into saymicro-<br />
economic reforms quicker?<br />
We didi I mean, what sort of micro-economic reform do<br />
we have in the financial system. I mean the most<br />
revolutionary reform..<br />
JOST: I'm thinking about the transport system..<br />
Oh yes, but you said, your question was are you sorry<br />
you didn't get into micro-economic reform quicker and I'm<br />
saying in answer to that question my darling John, that we<br />
dived right into micro-economic reform with the most<br />
fundamental way that had ever been done.<br />
JOST: O. K. alright, you de-regulated the financial system<br />
idea Prime Minister and I acknowledge that but there are<br />
other harder ones aren't there and the labor area particular<br />
the water fronts one of them? </p>
<p>-16-<br />
Yes, well I'm not dodging, I'll come to that. But<br />
let me.. don't give the impression that this one that we did<br />
in the beginning of bringing in 16 foreign banks,<br />
de-regulating the financial market and floating the dollar,<br />
that was just an easy piece of cake. I mean if it was that<br />
easy that the champions of do-regulation and free enterprise<br />
under Fraser and Howard and Peacock for 7 years hadn't had<br />
the guts or the wit or the imagination to doit that's how<br />
easy it was, So, sure in regard to the Transport Industry,<br />
we've already do-regulated the Airline Industry into the two<br />
Airline Policy and on the area of the w'ater front and the<br />
Maritime Industry what we have done, is to recognise the<br />
reality that the other people dodged for 7 years, they did<br />
nothing. What we've done now for a period is to say, bring<br />
the parties together, get independent advice as well and we<br />
are now right in the process of getting the form on both the<br />
' 4ater ? ront and in the Maritime Industry and that will be<br />
something significant that's never been done before.<br />
JOST: We've got two minutes left. I'd like to get on with<br />
personal matter or. semi personal. Your son Steven Hawke he<br />
has written a book about the Nukenbar Confrontation between<br />
the Abori gin?,-and the Cil compante-5 and I think you are<br />
going to launch it.<br />
P. M: Nol you are wrong there mate.<br />
JOST: You're not?<br />
No<br />
JOST: Are you proud of him?<br />
Yes of course I am. By the way Manning Clarke is<br />
going to launch it.<br />
JOST: Oh Manning Well it's just and I will be<br />
talking to him in a couple of weeks and I just thought and<br />
wondered if you have read the manuscript or anything like<br />
that? I've got the it was Hazel gave it to me on Friday<br />
night and I've started to read it.<br />
JOST: It seems to be a pretty good book?<br />
He's a pretty good blokel </p>
<p>-17-<br />
JOST: What sort I mean I know that you don't often<br />
get asked questions about this or if you do you don't often<br />
talk about it, but he has had an interesting life and he has<br />
clearly reacted in a way, he has been conscious of you being<br />
Prime minister and he has headed off..<br />
he has made his own life somewhere else.<br />
And yes I am very proud of him.<br />
JOST: I gather though that you are a lot closer to your<br />
family these days?<br />
I have always been close in terms of love and<br />
affection. one of the problems in my life is that I wasn't<br />
as physically close to them as I should have been and at<br />
times could have been. I was pursuing a) and not just<br />
pursuing~ and just involved in a career as for the<br />
ACTU which just involved the iconstantly long hours and<br />
then as President as the ACTU and then going into Parliament<br />
and through all that process I was away from them alot. I<br />
think it is true to Bay) John., which I think in a sense you<br />
are hinting about is now a closeness between us all.<br />
JOST: ( inaudible)<br />
JOST: I'm just wondering if thev',-e influencing you as sort<br />
of a politician. I<br />
PM: Too right they influence me.<br />
JOST: Don Chipp went from a right winger to a sort of a<br />
radical Liberal.<br />
PM: If any father in these days in these days I think<br />
whether he is Prime Minister or whatever he<br />
radio interviewer~ he is not influenced by his or her kids is<br />
a very strange person. I mean because... one of the things<br />
about life people will not understand it as we come to the<br />
end of the 20th cen turyx what a different world it was when<br />
we were growing up. I mean,, in those days kids were to be<br />
seen and not heard type of thing. But now it is different,<br />
kids are both seen and are to be heard. They are not<br />
repared and rightly not. prepared just to take the world as<br />
t is and say will you wait until you grow up and you may be<br />
a radio interviewer or a politician then you do something<br />
about it. They rightly say it is our world and we want to<br />
be heard.<br />
JOST: Is Steven pestering you about Aboriginal affairs?<br />
Steven doesn't pester Mel He will occasionally let<br />
me know of a view but he is not a pesterer. </p>
<p>-18-<br />
JOST: Has he put it to you that that Aboriginal Treaty<br />
should be We've had a yarn about these things but its not in<br />
any constant sense.<br />
JOST: How is it going anyway?<br />
Well Gerry Hand will be coming up with proposals<br />
about a structure of consultation both on the Aboriginal<br />
side and non Aboriginal side in this Budget. There have<br />
been funds allocated for that purpose and both the<br />
Aboriginal side and the non Aboriginal side expressing the<br />
view that they want to be able to work through this thing<br />
slowly. It is not something that is going to be able to be<br />
just kicked in being overnight. It has my full<br />
enthusiastic support at a pace which those involved think is<br />
most appropriate.<br />
JOST: Thanks very much for coming in todayl<br />
John it is always a great pleasure to with you.<br />
JOST: Well it was good of you to stay on that extra<br />
minutes. Pleasure Johni<br />
JOST: Thank you that was Prime Minister of Australia Mr Bob<br />
Hawke. ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
