<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2216</transcript-id>
    <title>TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, ON CHANNEL 7, MELBOURNE, 12 APRIL 1970</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/04/1970</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002216.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
" IMEET THE PRESS##<br />
TELEVISION ITWERVIEW GIVEN BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER, MR JOHN GORTON, OH<br />
CHANNEL 7, MELBOURNE 12 APRIL 1970<br />
Panel Reg Leonard<br />
Vince Matthews<br />
Trevor Sykes<br />
Chairman Frederick Howard<br />
Chairman: The choice of an opening topic for our discussion with the<br />
Prime Minister was dictated by the echoes that are going round the<br />
country from the disorder in Parliament earlier in the week.<br />
Prime Minister, we would value your comments on that, and I vould<br />
like also to have your opinion on whether there is behind this type of<br />
disorder some frustration and strain indicating that the Parliamentary<br />
system is not functioning these days as it should.<br />
PM: You would like a comment first on the actual disorders?<br />
Well, the comment I would give is that disorders of this kind in<br />
Parliament which have not been seen in any Australian Parliament<br />
before and I think probably in no English speaking Parliament in the<br />
world, are not an attack on a government; they are an attack on<br />
the institution of Parliament itself. If this sort of thing were to<br />
continue, then the institution of Parliament would become unworkable,<br />
and if it did, then the best method of government with the opportunity<br />
for freedom and the opportunity for the provision of order mould<br />
become unworkable and the whole process of democratic government<br />
would be attacked at its roots.<br />
Q. Isn't one of the major problems, Prime Minister, the urgency<br />
with which the Government is trying to push through a pile of<br />
legislation and not giving the opportunity to the Opposition to debate<br />
this legislation?<br />
PM: No, I don't think it is. I don't think in the Session of<br />
Parliament so far there has been any indication of an attempt to push<br />
through a great pile of legislation. There is a great deal there.<br />
It has been brought in. It has been left at the Second Reading<br />
stage and it must eventually be brought forward and debated, but I<br />
think that the functioning of Parliament must depend not only on the<br />
Standing Orders which Parliamentarians make, but on the way in / 2 </p>
<p>which they are applied, Now, there is a requirement for a government<br />
to give to an opposition an opportunity to debate, an-opportunity to move<br />
amendments, an opportunity to bring forward matters of public<br />
importance. This is a requirement. But there is also a requirement<br />
on the Opposition not to abuse the Standing Orders in order to prevent<br />
legislation coming forward, in order to waste time. And I believe<br />
that the Opposition in this case has in fact been seeking to abuse the<br />
rights they have in order to waste time. Can I give an example of that?<br />
One of the things that an Opposition should be able to do is to bring<br />
forward matters of public urgency which they think ought to be<br />
ventilated something is wrong somewhere and they want to make that<br />
public. And when that happens, always in the past there have been<br />
three or four speakers aside, by agreement, and then you have gone<br />
on to the ordinary Parliamentary business. And this is important, but<br />
it shourld only happen at spaced intervals. You can't have it every day.<br />
If it was done every day, then the time of Parliament would be taken<br />
up every day for the purposes of the Opposition, and this is what the<br />
Opposition have been trying to do. They have almost every day been<br />
bringing forward urgency motions expecting or hoping to have three<br />
or four speakers aside. And if that were permitted, then the business<br />
of Parliament would be taken out of the Government's hands. This is,<br />
I think, an attempt to abuse the right, and it forces the Government<br />
to gag.<br />
Q. Apart from what they claim to be the over-enthusiastic use<br />
of the gag, the Opposition also claims that the Leader of the House<br />
broke undertakings. What is your comment on that? Is it so?<br />
PM: Well, I am never a party to undertakings. They are made<br />
between the Leader of the Hcuse and the spokesman, whoever it may<br />
be generally it is Barnard on the Opposition side. So I can't speak<br />
from direct participation. I can only say that I just don't believe that<br />
this has happened, and I haven't seen evidence produced that it has<br />
happened. It is claimed that there was an agreement broken in the<br />
necessary Constitutional one-day sitting, but I don't believe that<br />
was so, and there was a claim that on another occasion an agreement<br />
was broken. I have seen nothing to support that whatever. On the<br />
other hand, the Leader of the House tells me that there have been<br />
many occasions on which agreements have been made with the<br />
spokesman for the Opposition, and the spokesman for the Opposition<br />
has later come along and said " Sorry, I can't keep this agreement.<br />
I can't control my own boys. Now this is a sort of an agrument<br />
between the people making the arrangements. / 3 </p>
<p>Q. But woulcxi't the Opposition have more time for its urgency<br />
motonsand the Government more time to conduct its business if<br />
the Pairltiment sat more often? There was quite a long break over<br />
Christmas.<br />
P M: We had a long break over Christmas indeed, and I think<br />
that the results of that long break are probably showing up in the<br />
greatest legislative programme perhaps that has ever been bmvught<br />
before the Commonwealth Parliament. There is a need, you know,<br />
for Cabinet to sit with its advisers and to work out the details of the<br />
legislation which it wants the Parliament to pass. And the programme<br />
that was brought forward in the Governor-General's Speech reflects,<br />
I think, the work that was done in this direction over that break.<br />
Q. Moving on to another field, Sir, it seems from Canberra<br />
these days that you are a much more confident Prime Minister than<br />
you were when you fought the election last October. Some of your<br />
closest advisers even insist that you are a changed man. Why have<br />
y you developed this new confidence and what has been responsible for<br />
the change?<br />
PM: Well, I don't know that I would agree that I was a changed<br />
man. I hope whoever it was that said it would agree that it was a<br />
change for the better. I am not sure, but I don't really think I am.<br />
I suppose one becomes more confident when one has won an election<br />
in one's own right, even if o-ne has only just won it. We have a team<br />
of Cabinet Ministers which I have picked myself completely and I<br />
think it is a good team and I think it is working very wiell indeed. I<br />
think we have got a programme which has been brought forward<br />
showing just where we are going in defence, just what our goals are,<br />
what our foreign affairs approach is; and on the legislative side,<br />
the tidying up of a great deal of legislation, and the bringing in of such<br />
important things as the Health Bill, the Industries Development<br />
Corporation, off shore legislation for minerals, a whole number of things<br />
which I believe are quite important to Australia. Perhaps that is the<br />
explanation, I don't know.<br />
Q. In contrast, last month only, I think it was, you gave an<br />
interesting interview in which you said one reason for your added<br />
confidence might " maybe I have a new philosophy" were your<br />
exact words. Now what does that mysterious sentence mean? / 4 </p>
<p>PM: Well, I think it means that one understands precisely<br />
what it is one is seeking to do in many fields not in every field<br />
one is convinced after long thought that the reasons for those goals are<br />
proper reasons, one seeks to get a team behind one and explain them<br />
to the Aust ralian people and why they are good, and one says that as<br />
long as all this is done and genuinely done to one's own satisfaction,<br />
there is always going to be an awful lot of people vAio disagree with you<br />
and who criticise you on everything. Well, that's too bad. I am not<br />
going to let that grind me down any more.<br />
Q. Looking at the Liberal Party, it was assumned when you<br />
came to power that you were determined to make changes within the<br />
Par-ty and its philosophy and thinking. Is this assumption still correct?<br />
Are you determined to push the Party in the direction you think the<br />
events are moving it anyway?<br />
PM: I don't know that any one man, even a Prine Minister, can<br />
push a Party in any direction that it doesn't want to go, but I think<br />
it is possible to get a Party rethinking, re-examining the basic dogma<br />
if I can use that word which it has had for such a long period of<br />
time, and I do want, and I think I have succeeded, in getting the<br />
Liberal Party to stand off and have another look at a number of things<br />
which had previously been taken for granted. And I think that this is<br />
good.<br />
Q. Prime Minister, you mentioned just now, a couple of items<br />
that were on your agenda. The were things we intended to question<br />
you about, anyway. One was the Industries Development Corporation,<br />
as I see it in relation to olir overseas credit, and the other was the<br />
Health programme. I wonder if we could look first at this Industries<br />
Development Corporation which I believe you have recently two<br />
days ago been talking about in Perth. Does it lend itself to a layman's<br />
explanation in simple words?<br />
PM: Oh, I think it does, but I should give this preliminary<br />
statement. We believe that we must have overseas capital flowing<br />
into Australia for development and for processing minerals and for<br />
all the expansion which is required. We can't generate enough inside<br />
Australia and rather than not progress, it is much better to have<br />
overseas capital flowing in. Anything I say is not directed against<br />
an inflow of overseas capital, because this is essential, but there<br />
is a price to pay for the inflow of overseas capita there are<br />
great benefits but there is also a price to pay. There are the<br />
e 9. </p>
<p>requirements to pay interest payments overseas when the enterprise<br />
becomes viable. -There is repatriation of capital. There are all sorts<br />
of prices which need to be paid. And we would like to keep that price<br />
as low as possible by seeing as much Australian participation in<br />
enterprises as is possible. Statistically, this isn't now happening.<br />
Statistically, the amount of Australian ownership and control in nmany<br />
industries is dropping, and this is due to either one of two things. Either<br />
there is no will in Australian industry for Australian participation<br />
and ownership. I discount that. I am sure there is and I am sure<br />
there is a will. Or there are not sufficient avenues by which the<br />
Australian ownership and control can be retained, and this is an attempt<br />
to provide another avenue by which this ownership and control can be<br />
maintained. You see, many of our smaller industries must expand.<br />
They have got to become more massive than they have ever been<br />
before if they are going to compete on the world with the big companies<br />
of the world. If they are going to be able to sell inside Australia with<br />
a minimum of tariff protection, they hi ye got to expand, so they have<br />
got to get capital. Now, at the moment, very often they have to take<br />
in an overseas partner, maybe a majority partner in order to get that<br />
capital from overseas. We are seeking to set up a corporation to which<br />
a small company can go a relatively small company in world terms<br />
to which it can go and say " You, the Industrial Gorpoiation have a status<br />
and a standing internationally at least as good as Comalco or Hamersley<br />
or any other of these companies. Will you, if you judge that our<br />
proposition is a good business proposition, will you try and borrow<br />
overseas capital for us so that we don't have to give away our equity",<br />
and this is the basic objective of this new exercise.<br />
Chairman: Mr. Sykes, would you like to come in on this?<br />
Q. How high is the danger that this corporation could be used<br />
as a political tool?<br />
PM: The legislation will divorce the corporation entirely it<br />
must, from any governmental or any ministerial con~ trol. The board<br />
of directors will be drawn predominantly from private industry,. It will<br />
be required to make its judgments on the same sort off business judgements<br />
that any other private board of directors would mak', e, and it is completely<br />
and utterly essential to the scheme you put your finger on it that<br />
it must be divorced from government control.<br />
Q. Was there any thought when Cabinet agreed on this one<br />
that it was necessary because the Australian Resources Development<br />
B. nk was not doing the job that it was set up to do? / 6 </p>
<p>Q. If the economy is overheated, the farmers suggest they<br />
are in a deep freeze.<br />
PM: They are.<br />
Q. What is the Government proposing to do about the<br />
plight of rural industry? Mr. Nixon addressed some farmers here<br />
and suggested he was taking a message loud and clear to the Cabinet.<br />
Was that message received loud and clear?<br />
PM: You asked what the Government is going to do. One of<br />
the things we have done and one of the things for which we have been<br />
attacked by, I think, some rather troglodyte economists, is we have<br />
not raised the interest rate for the farmers because they are that<br />
is for people who draw the major amount of their income from rural<br />
production because they are in this difficult situation. You see<br />
the objective of raising the interest rate was to make money dearer,<br />
to damp down demand, to damp down requirement. Well, the farmers<br />
haven't got the demand, they aren't making the requirements, because<br />
wool is at the lowest price it has been since i942, so we felt it was<br />
using a kind of a bludgeon to hammer people who weren't in fact<br />
putting out inflationary pressures. That is one thing that we have<br />
done. You asked me what we were going to do. Yes, Mr. Nixon<br />
and Mr. Fraser both brought back to Cabinet their reports of the<br />
meeting that was held in Melbourne. That meeting didn't put forward<br />
any proposals, you may remember. It just said " We would like<br />
things to be better, and it is now up to the Government to seek to put<br />
forward proposals". Well, what are you going to do? Take wheat,<br />
for example, you can't just go on growing increasing quantities of a<br />
commodity that the world market doesn't want. It is just impossible<br />
to do that, or that if it does want, it will pay a price that isn't viable.<br />
And so there, quotas on growth are coming in, and I believe that<br />
will reach a stage where the demand will meet the supply. Dairyfarming<br />
we are still seeking to iron out with the States and have<br />
almost reached the stage of reconstruction of dairy farms. Wool<br />
is a commodity which is different, because there the world does<br />
want it. There is no question that everything that is produced is sold,<br />
but they are not prepared at the moment to pay the price that is<br />
required for it. Now we have got to look into whether the marketing<br />
methods are sufficiently good, whether more could be obtained there,<br />
whether fringe benefits in the way of core testing andi sample selling<br />
and these sort of things could be done, and we are waiting now on a<br />
report from the committee set up by the Wool Board on vii ich we will<br />
finally do what we can to help this industry. / 8 </p>
<p>Q. Prime Minister, another section of the community which<br />
is rather hot and bothered is general practitioners and the health<br />
insurance. Can you tell us anything about the prospects of a<br />
compromise or a settlement with them?<br />
PM: Well, all I can say on that is that we said that there should<br />
be no economic bar to a patient going to a specialist and getting<br />
specialist treatment if he needs it. That he should not, as he had<br />
in the past, have to pay the difference between a general practitioner's<br />
fee and a specialist's fee. He must be protected. Anid this we will<br />
not depart from. This must happen as far as the Government is<br />
concerned. Anybody who needs to have specialist treatment and Vhio<br />
has paid his insurance should be relieved of the fear of great expense<br />
as a result. And differential rebates are absolutely essential. Now<br />
if there are areas in which we can have discussions the general<br />
practitioners, I think, call it updating of rebates N~ hich in fact<br />
means periodic increasing of their fees, if these sort of things can<br />
be worked out, fine. But the basic thing is that we must continue<br />
to prctect the patient. Now the general practitioners fear that if<br />
we do this, everybody will go to a specialist even to have a boil<br />
lanced or a toeache looked at or something of that kind. This is<br />
just a fear they have expressed. Only experience can show whether<br />
it will be true or not. I don't think it will, because even now you have<br />
got to wait awhile before you can go and see a specialist. If everybody<br />
went it would be weeks before you could get in. Also, I think people<br />
would trust and rely on their general practitioner family doctor.<br />
If tnat did happen, and I don't believe it will, we would be just as<br />
disturbed as the medical profession because of the cost to the taxpayer.<br />
We would then have to see whether there was some referral system<br />
that could prevent that. But basically, we have got to protect the<br />
patient as we said we would against the great cost of specialist fees.<br />
Chairman: Could we now have just some quick, short questions.<br />
Q. Could I just ask one, coming from the tropical North? We<br />
are interested greatly, of course, as other places are in offshore<br />
development of various kinds. Has your Government any specific<br />
programme for control particularly and for the preservation<br />
of Australian rights in these enterprises? a / 9 </p>
<p>PM: In the enterprises which may enter mineral exploration<br />
off shore? Well, we are bringing legislation forward to resolve the<br />
question of who it is that has the sovereignty and owns the right<br />
over the sea bottom from low water mark to the continental shelf.<br />
Both the State Governments and ourselves now claim it. We are<br />
bringing legislation forward to put it beyond doubt. if it is challenged<br />
in the High Court, then that will be it. It will be settled. That<br />
would have to be decided before we could say yes, vie had intentions<br />
of doing this, that or the other. But were it decided in our favour,<br />
then we would want to see two things. We would want to see that<br />
th ere was no danger from a conservation point of view, or a pollution<br />
point of view or changing the ecological balance point of view, and<br />
we would want, insofar as it was possible to see, that Australians had<br />
some share in anything that went on in that way.<br />
Q. One quick one, Sir. Do you propose to go to New Guinea<br />
this year?<br />
PM: Yes, I do. I can't tellI you when, but I definitely wish to<br />
go at some stage before the end of the year.<br />
Q. Another quick one. In the potentially menacing economic<br />
situation, when are we likely,, if ever, to see an easing of the load<br />
on the middle income-earners taxation load?<br />
PM: Well, what we have to do is to make sure that the general<br />
economy grows but that inflation is restrained. This is essential, as<br />
I think you would agree. We have set forward our aims in regard<br />
to reducing taxation on middle and lower income groups and this is<br />
an aim which I thinkqas I said before, is an aim which we will achieve<br />
with responsibility, as soon as we can.<br />
Chairman: A last quick one.<br />
Q. D oesn't the imposition of higher interest rates just to put<br />
the brakes on inflation hurt a lot of little people?<br />
PM: Well, it probably could be argued that it did. You might<br />
have housing in mind.<br />
Q. I have.<br />
PM: Yes, I thought you might have housing in mind. It could well<br />
be argued that it did, although I am told that in most cases the yearly<br />
cost to those people will not be greater but the period of time over<br />
which they have to pay off what they owe will have to be extended. But<br />
that has to be balanced against what would the cost to the house builder<br />
be if inflation were not to be checked in this way. The capital cost of<br />
each house to somebody who now moves in would rise considerably, and<br />
I think in the long run they would be worse off.<br />
Chairman: Prime Minister, I am afraid our time for questions has run<br />
our. One of the easiest question times I am sure you have had: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
