<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40040</transcript-id>
    <title>Our brightest science minds receive prestigious PM’s prizes</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/10/2015</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>An Australian National University professor whose work has transformed our understanding of the world’s most important biological reaction – photosynthesis – is one of the recipients of the prestigious Prime Minister’s Prizes for Science, announced today.</p>
<p>Distinguished Professor Graham Farquhar will receive the major Prime Minister’s Prize for Science, worth $250,000, at a ceremony at Parliament House at 7pm this evening.</p>
<p>Another major prize, the inaugural Prime Minister’s $250,000 Prize for Innovation, will be awarded to Laureate Professor Graeme Jameson, from the University of Newcastle.</p>
<p>Professor Jameson’s technologies use trillions of bubbles to capture coal dust that would otherwise have been wasted, and have transformed the recovery of coal and minerals over the past 30 years.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull, who will present the prizes, said the awards recognised how Australia’s brightest science minds were playing a key role in the nation’s quest to become more agile, innovative and creative.</p>
<p>“It’s vitally important that science in Australia goes from strength to strength as we create the jobs of the future,” Mr Turnbull said.</p>
<p>“The recipients of these prizes are demonstrating the power of scientific discovery and the important role it plays in a modern, prosperous economy,” he said.</p>
<p>Other Prime Minister’s Prizes for Science winners announced today are:</p>
<ul><li>Dr Jane Elith—$50 000 Frank Fenner Prize for Life Scientist of the Year.</li>
<li>Associate Professor Cyrille Boyer —$50 000 Malcolm McIntosh Prize for Physical Scientist of the Year.</li>
<li>Dr Ken Silburn—$50 000 Prime Minister’s Prize for Excellence in Science Teaching in Secondary Schools.</li>
<li>Mrs Rebecca Johnson—$50 000 Prime Minister’s Prize for Excellence in Science Teaching in Primary Schools.</li>
</ul><p>Minister for Industry, Innovation and Science the Hon Christopher Pyne MP congratulated the winners on their prizes and noted the contribution they had made to science in this country.</p>
<p>“Science is central to our competitiveness, our creativity and our ability as a nation,” Mr Pyne said.</p>
<p>“As the calibre of these prize winners demonstrates, this is an exciting time for science in Australia. The work that is happening in labs, universities and institutions now will position us to succeed in the years, decades and generations to come,” he said.</p>
<p>Full citations, photos, videos and overlay are available online on the science website.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
