<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9810</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P.J. KEATING MP VICTORIAN AGRICULTURE-RECOVERY AND LONGER TERM GROWTH </title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009810.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
VICTORIAN AGRICULTURE RECOVERY AND LONGER TERM GROWTH<br />
I am pleased to announce today a Drought Recovery and Management<br />
Facility which will better position Victorian agriculture to take full advantage of<br />
the recovery from drought.<br />
It is also intended to secure the longer term competitive position of Victorian<br />
agriculture in the international market place.<br />
I understand recent rains hold out the prospect for good crops and pasture<br />
recovery. But our capacity to maximise the opportunities arising from these<br />
favourable conditions will depend on how rapidly farm businesses are able to<br />
recover from the impact of drought, and how well we deal with the rural<br />
adjustment pressures that have built up over recent years.<br />
Adjustment pressures are particularly pronounced at this time in Victoria,<br />
which has experienced successive years of relatively poor incomes resulting<br />
from a period of generally poor commodity-prices and other adverse<br />
conditions followed by the drought. This has seriously weakened the<br />
financial position of many farm businesses and their capacity to respond to<br />
the current recovery.<br />
The recovery period now in prospect provides an opportunity to facilitate<br />
necessary adjustment in Victoria, especially in the wheat and sheep sectors.<br />
The enhanced productivity and re-establishment support to be offered under<br />
the $ 15 million Drought Recovery and Management Facility through the Rural<br />
Adjustment Scheme will assist farmers and graziers to improve the<br />
productivity of their farm businesses and to secure their longer term<br />
competitiveness. Longer term adjustment will be supported by helping those<br />
in the deepest trouble to leave sooner rather than later, and with dignity.<br />
Up to $ 7.5 million will be made available by the Commonwealth to Victorian<br />
farmers under the Facility, and the Victorian Government will be approached<br />
to match this on a dollar for dollar basis. I<br />
117/ 95 </p>
<p>This support is being complemented by $ 3.17 million Commonwealth funding<br />
to match the Victorian Government's contribution to the extension of the<br />
Wimmera-Mallee pipeline to facilitate improved drought preparedness and<br />
management. The Commonwealth has agreed, subject to environmental clearances, to<br />
provide $ 2.55 million for construction of stage 3 of the pipeline.<br />
An additional $ 620,000 for associated property management improvements<br />
and community participation to secure the benefits of the project will also be<br />
provided. Together, these initiatives will greatly strengthen the capacity of the<br />
Wimmera and Mallee regions to deal effectively with ongoing adjustment<br />
challenges. BALLARAT October 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
