<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>12393</transcript-id>
    <title>Joint Statement with the Chairman of ATSIC Mr Geoff Clark -Waugh and Gillespie to Captain Sides in Historic Indigenous Cricket Match</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/2001</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australian cricket team captain Steve Waugh and Test fast bowler Jason Gillespie will take opposing sides in an historic cricket match in Canberra next month.</p>
<p>Steve Waugh will captain the Prime Minister's XI and Jason Gillespie an ATSIC Chairman's XI in the match to be played at Manuka Oval on April 19.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister and the Chairman of ATSIC are delighted that these two players, who have both played such an important part in the success of the world record breaking Australian team, have agreed to lead the respective sides.</p>
<p>The involvement of the Australian captain and one of his exciting frontline bowlers in this special event is testament to the enormous goodwill the match has generated.</p>
<p>It will also help achieve a key aim of the match - the development of more young Indigenous cricketers into first class players.</p>
<p>Indigenous players were the cricket pioneers forming the first Australian team to tour England back in 1868.</p>
<p>This match will enable young stars to have the experience of playing against and alongside some of the world's best.</p>
<p>It will also kick-off a development process with the Australian Cricket Board which hopefully will lead to more Indigenous cricketers playing first class cricket, and in the Australian national team.</p>
<p>The Chairman of ATSIC said he wants to see Indigenous cricketers "back where we belong."</p>
<p>The response from talented Indigenous cricketers to the cricket match has been overwhelming. More than 100 top-class cricketers have sought selection.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister and the Chairman of ATSIC are finalising the selection of their respective squads and an announcement will be made in the near future.</p>
<p>11 March 2001</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
