<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3565</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT TO IRELAND: PRESS CONFERENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003565.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
DI1 P'AR I MNIN I 01 I l iS<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM-. O. DU303 MKII<br />
TOR 1228 24.12.74<br />
O. DU3C8 2130 23.12.74 UNC N"<br />
TO. PP LONDON/ 103s<br />
RP PP CANBERRA/ 430<br />
RP. RR BRUSSELS/ 19 PARIS/ 14 BONN/ I1<br />
RR ROME/ 09 THE HAGUE/ 11<br />
FM. DUBLIN/ FILE 221/ 4/ 7/ 1/ 3 AND 300/ 7<br />
U N C L A S S I F I E D<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT TO IRELAND: PRESS CONFERENCE.<br />
FOR MRS DWYER ( ASSISTANT PRESS SECRETARY)<br />
FOLLOWING IS TEXT OF THE PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE<br />
IN DUBLIN AFTERNOON OF 23 DECEMBER:<br />
BEGINS:<br />
Q. I UNDERSTAND MR PRIME MINISTER THAT YOU DISCUSSED WITH THE<br />
TAOISEACH THE TRADE BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND IRELAND, BOTH OF THEM,<br />
WITH THE EEC. ' NOW YOU APPARENTLY EXPRESSED SOME PARTICULAR<br />
INTEREST IN MEAT AND SUGAR. IN WHAT WAY WOULD IRELAND BE ABLE<br />
TO ASSIST THIS IN THE EEC CONTEXT?<br />
THE TAOISEACH DID POINT OUT TO ME THE GRATIFYING INCREASE<br />
IN SALES BY IRELAND TO AUSTRALIA. WE ARE NATURALLY ALSO CONCERNED<br />
WITH THE CONTRIBUTION THAT CAN BE MADE BY IRELAND AS ONE OF THE<br />
NINE IN THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY. AUSTRALIA WAS FOUNDED BY<br />
THE... BY TWO OF THE THREE NEW MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY, BRITAIN<br />
AND IRELAND, AND WE BELIEVE THAT THOSE TWO NEW MEMBERS WILL<br />
UNDERSTAND THE LINKS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND WESTERN EUROPE AND HOPEFULi<br />
BE SYMPATHETIC TOWARDS THEM. THE COMMUNITY IS ONE OF THE<br />
THREE BIG ECONOMIC GROUPINGS WITH WHICH AUSTRALIA HAS TRADE,<br />
THE OTHER TWO BEING, OF. COURSE, JAPAN AND THE UNITED STATES.<br />
Q. LAURIE OAKES, MELBOURNE SUN: PRIME MINISTER, WE'RE TOLD<br />
TIAT WHEN YOU SPOKE TO THE IRISH PRIME MINISTER TODAY YOU.<br />
DISCUSSED THE SITUATION IN NORTHERN IRELAND AND PRESUMABLY IT<br />
IS NOT WITHOUT RELEVANCE THAT THE BOMBS WERE GETTING GRADUALLY<br />
CLOSER TO YOUR HOTEL BEFORE THE TRUCE CAME INTO EFFECT AT<br />
MIDNIGHT. CAN YOU GIVE US YOUR VIEWS ON THE SITUATION IN<br />
NORTHrERN IRELAND?<br />
THE BOMBS WERE FOR THE LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION,<br />
NOT FOR PRIME MINISTER. NATURALLY, SERIOUSLY, THOSE WITH ME, AND<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>0. I Ni INI OR I N ' IT \ I R" S<br />
I NWARD CAB LEG R AM 2-O. DU308<br />
I TO0, WERE VERY ANXIOUS TO HEAR WHAT THE TAOISEACH HAD TO SAY<br />
ABOUT THE POSITION IN IRELAND. I AM TALKING ABOUT THE WHOLE<br />
ISLAND. AND IT WAS VALUABLE FOR US TO HAVE HIS ASSESSMENT AND<br />
HIS ANALYSIS OF THE POSSIBILITIES. HE HAS, OF COURSE, WRITTEN<br />
AND SPOKEN ON THIS MATTER, AND I HAVE A PUBLICATION, A BOOK,<br />
OF HIS ON THIS SUBJECT.<br />
Q. MR WHITLAM, TOM MCLOUGHLIN, IRISH TELEVISION: IF I COULD<br />
GET BACK JUST TO THE PURPOSE OF YOUR VISIT. I UNDERSTAND YOU<br />
WILL BE VISITING OTHER EEC COUNTRIES. WHAT EXACTLY ARE YOU<br />
LOOKING FOR? WE ARE VISITING SEVEN OF THE NINE, ALL EXCEPT DENMARK<br />
AND LUXEMBOURG. WE WANT TO REAFFIRM THE TIES BETWEEN AUSTRALIA<br />
AND WESTERN EUROPE. THESE ARE HISTORIC, CULTURAL, AS WELL AS<br />
BEING COMMERCIAL. I HAVE BEEN ASKED A QUESTION ALREADY ABOUT<br />
THE COMMERCIAL TIES AND THESE ARE OF VERY GREAT SIGNIFICANCE.<br />
MANY OF THE PRODUCTS WHICH AUSTRALIA HAS TRADITIONALLY<br />
EXPORTED ARE NOW IN SOME JEOPARDY BECAUSE THEY WERE EXPORTED<br />
TO ENGLAND, AND ENGLAND CAN NOW IMPORT THEM ONLY WITHIN THE<br />
EEC CONTEXT. THERE ARE OTHER PRODUCTS IN THE AGRICULTURAL,<br />
PASTORAL FIELD, WHERE THE COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE MAY WELL BE<br />
INTERESTED IN HAVING SUCH A SECURE HIGH QUALITY AND RELATIVELY<br />
CHEAP SOURCE OF SUPPLY AS AUSTRALIA AUSTRALIA IS INTERESTED<br />
IN SEEING THAT THERE ARE LONG-TERM ARRANGEMENTS FOR ANY SUCH<br />
PRODUCTS. IN ADDITION TO THAT, AUSTRALIA IS A VERY WELL-ENDOWED<br />
COUNTRY IN RESPECT TO ENERGY RESOURCES AND IN BRUSSELS A WEEK<br />
AGO I WAS DISCUSSING WITH THE COMMISSION THE POSSIBILITY OF<br />
DEVELOPING THESE RESOURCES IN AUSTRALIA AND ESTABLISHING A LONGTERM<br />
MARKET FOR THEM WITH THE COMMUNITY. IN PARTICULAR, OF COURSE,<br />
URANIUM AND COAL.<br />
Q. HAS BRITAIN'S ENTRY INTO THE EEC CAUSED YOU VERY SERIOUS<br />
ECONOMIC PROBLEMS IN AUSTRALIA?<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS ADJUSTED TO THEM. IN 1962 WHEN PRIME<br />
MINISTER MC MILLAN FIRST APPLIED TO JOIN... FIRST SOUGHT BRITAIN'S<br />
ADMISSION TO THE COMMUNITY ABOUT 20 PERCENT OF AUSTRALIAOS EXPORTS<br />
WENT TO BRITAIN. NOW IT. IS BARELY 6 PER CENT. AUSTRALIA HAS<br />
ADJUSTED HER EXPORT PATTERN VERY GREATLY IN THE INTERIM. JAPAN<br />
IS NOW TiE LARGEST COMMERCIAL PARTNER OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
Q. ARE YOU HOPEFUL THAT YOU MAY BE ABLE TO COME TO SOME LONGTERM<br />
TRADE AGREEMENT WITH THE EEC?<br />
NOT OVERALL. WE ARE THINKING. OF VARIOUS COMMODITIES<br />
AND LONG TERM ARRANGEMENTSFOR-THOSE COMMODITIES. WE ARE GOING<br />
TO HAVE REGULAR CONSULTATIONS BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND. THE COMMISSION<br />
. o,/ 3 </p>
<p>D I'ARTMN NT 01-OI ' OR IGN A \-AIRS<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM 3-O. DU308<br />
fHE FIRST ONES WILL BE IN THE MIDDLE OF 1975 -WE EXPECT.<br />
0. YOUR COMMUNIQUE MENTIONS ESPECIALLY BEEF AND SUGAR. I AM<br />
SURE YOU ARE AWARE THAT WE EXPORT BOTH AND THAT WE HAVE BEEN<br />
HAVING DIFFICULTIES, LIKE YOURSELF, IN RELATION TO BEEF. CAN YOU<br />
THEREFORE TELL ME WHAT RESPONSE YOU HAD IN YOUR TALKS TODAY ON<br />
THOSE TWO ITEMS?<br />
IRELAND HAS ALWAYS BEEN A VERY LARGE EXPORTER OF BEEF<br />
TO BRITAIN, AND WOULD I EXPECT BE A LARGE EXPORTER OF BEEF TO THE<br />
COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE. THERE ARE OTHER MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY<br />
WHICH WOULD ALSO DEPEND ON THE BEEF MARKET IN THE COMMUNITY AS<br />
A WHOLE SUCH AS DENMARK, AND THE LOW COUNTRIES. THE FDIFFICULTY<br />
HAS ARISEN IN THE LAST YEAR, WHERE SO MANY PEOPLE THOUGHT THAT<br />
: THE MARKET FOR IMPORTS IN THE COMMUNITY WOULD BE MUCH LARGER AND<br />
WOULD CONTINUE MUCH LARGER THAN IS NOW LIKELY TO BE THE-CASE.<br />
UT NEVERTHELESS THERE IS LIKELY TO-BE A MARKET FOR IMPORTS FROM<br />
COUNTRIES NOT IN THE MARKET, AND AUSTRALIA IS I. NTERESTED IN<br />
INVESTIGATING THOSE POSSIBILITIES ON A LONG-TERM BASIS. WE WANT<br />
TO SEE THAT IF WE GUARANTEE OR MAKE ANY INVESTMENTS IN PROVIDING<br />
FACILITIES FOR THOSE EXPORTS THAT WE CAN GET A RETURN ON THOSE<br />
FACILITIES. I DON'T WANT YOU TO THINK THAT IRELAND'S AND AUSTRALIA'S<br />
INTERESTS ARE TOTALLY OPPOSED TO EACH OTHER. CLEARLY<br />
WE OBVIOUSLY ARE RIVALS IN AN EXTENT AND IRELAND WOULD HAVE<br />
FIRST CLAIM. BUT IT IS VERY LIKELY THAT THE COMMUNITY WILL NEED<br />
FROM SEASON TO SEASON MORE BEEF THAN IT CAN ITSELF PRODUCE, AND<br />
AUSTRALIA WOULD CLEARLY BE A SUITABLE SUPPLIER BECAUSE OF PRICE<br />
AND QUALITY.<br />
Q'. Q D'ARCY OF 0-10 NETWORK: PRIME MINISTER, MY QUESTIONN<br />
FOLLOWS ONE ASKED BY LAURIE OAKES EARLIER ON. WITHOUT ASKING<br />
YOU TO COMMENT ON THE INTERNAL PROBLEMS OF ANY PARTICULAR<br />
COUNTRY SIR, COULD I ASK YOU WHAT YOUR ATTITUDE IS GENERALLY<br />
STOWARDS TERRORISM, ESPECIALLY OF THE TYPE THAT IS SEEN IN<br />
RECENT DAYS? WELL OBVIOUSLY MY GOVERNMENT, LIKE EVERY GOVERNMENT<br />
MUST DO ALL IT CAN TO STAMP OUT TERRORISM, TO IDENTIFY-THE PEOPLE<br />
THAT ARE LIKELY TO PERPETRATE IT.<br />
Q. MR PRIME MINISTER JUST TO CLARIFY YOUR ANSWER ON BEEF, DO<br />
YOU WISH TO SEE AN END TO THE EEC BEEF EMBARGO OR NOT?<br />
A TOTAL EMBARGO, CERTAINLY, OF COURSE. -I WOULD THINK<br />
THAT OVER THE YEARS IT IS UNLIKELY THAT THE MOST AFFLUENT<br />
PARTS OF THE WORLD, SUCH AS NORTH AMERICA AND WESTERN EUROPE AND<br />
THE SOVIET UNION WILL BE SELF-CONTAINED IN BEEF. AUSTRALIA,<br />
CLIMATICALLY AND BECAUSE OF HER AREA, CAN PRODUCE BEEF VERY<br />
ADVANTAGEOUSLY. / 4 N </p>
<p>11 P \ RTMI\' N I r 1 a ; N I\ 1 III<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM" V<br />
\\ xSX<br />
4-O. DU308<br />
Q. DID YOU FIND MR PRIME MINISTER THAT MR COSGRAVE AGREED WITH<br />
THAT POINT OF-VIEW.?<br />
OH, WELL. WE DIDN'T GO INTO ANY DETAILS ON THESE MATTERS,<br />
OBVIOUSLY WE-HAD A GENERAL DISCUSSION ON THESE MATTERS,.. AND. IT--<br />
WAS VERY USEFUL FOR US TO . HAVETHE VIEW OF . IREL. AND -SI-NCE' IT' HAS<br />
BEEN A VERY GREAT EXPORTER OF BEEF TO COUNTRIES WHICH. ARE NOW INTHE<br />
MARKET.<br />
Q. DID HE GIVE YOU ANY ASSURANCES?<br />
NO, NO OF COURSE NOT, AND T. HEY WEREN'T SOUGHT.<br />
NO, I'LL FINISH THE QUESTION..... REGARDING IRELAND'S<br />
ATTITUDE TO PERHAPS AUSTRALIAN SALES OF SUGAR TO THE COMMON<br />
MARKET. NO, THERE WAS SCARCELY ANY THERE WAS SOME DISCUSSION<br />
ON THIS WITH THE TAOISEACH AND HIS MINISTERS, BUT NO, NO DETAIL<br />
DISCUSSION LIKE THAT.<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER, GLENNON, IRISH INDEPDENDENT: IT IS REPORTED<br />
HERE TH-AT OUR MINISTER OF LABOUR FAILED TO KEEP SOME APPOINTMENTS<br />
. MADE BY YOUR GOVERNMENT WHEN HE WAS ON A VISIT TC AUSTRALIA SOME<br />
WEEKS AGO. DID THIS QUESTION COME UP IN ANY WAY BETWEEN YOURSELF<br />
AND THE TAOISEACH?<br />
NO, IN NO WAY WHATEVER. NO WAY WHATEVER. MR O'LEARY WAS<br />
A GUEST OF THF AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT WHILE HE WAS IN AUSTRALIA.<br />
IN PARTICULAR, HE SAW MY MINISTER FOR LABOUR. THAT IS THE<br />
-IRISH MINISTER FOR LABOUR SAW THE AUSTRALIAN MINISTER FOR LABOUR.<br />
AND I KNOW THAT MY MINISTER APPRECIATED THE EXCHANGE OF VIEWS.<br />
FURTHERMORE, THE IRISH MINISTER FOR LABOUR, MR 0' LEARY ALSO<br />
VISITED PAPUA NEW GUINEA. AND HIS VIEWS, HIS ASSESSMENT THERE<br />
WERE HELPFUL TO MY GOVERNMENT.<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER. A QUESTION MOSTLY OF INTEREST TO AUSTRALIAN<br />
READERS. FOLLOWING YOUR LONDON PRESS CONFERENCE AND YOUR COMMENTS<br />
ON G. M. H. COULD I ASK YOU IF YOU BELIEVE THAT THE G. M. H.<br />
DECISION TO SACK WORKERS IN AUSTRALIA WAS ONE IMPOSED ON THE<br />
AUSTRALIAN COMPANY FROM DETROIT?<br />
I DON'T KNOW.<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER, HAVING SAMPLED THE IRISH HOSPITALITY.....<br />
P. M. WHAT, IS THAT SO OBVIOUS? / 5 </p>
<p>I) ' ARTMI N T 01 F ORlI N Al I AIRRS<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM 5. O. BDEUTW3IER0IES8HN SITROUIASTN IHDRI SH BEERST. ILL LESBS ETWEEN<br />
Q. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF GUINNESS STOUT? DO YOU THINK THAT<br />
IT RATES WITH FOSTER'S LAWGER? I P<br />
I WOULD HAVE THOUGHT THEY WERE... THEY WERE DIFFERENT LAC<br />
SUBSTANCES. I WOULDN'T HAVE THOUGHT THERE WAS ANY SIMILARITY<br />
BETWEEN IRISH STOUT AND IRISH BEER. STILL LESS BETWEEN IRISH<br />
STOUT AND AUSTRALIAN BEER. I MEAN, I.. TE THE TAOISEACH'SEK AGO SOME<br />
LUNCHEON TOOK PLACE IN A MONUMENT TO IRISHB E STODL ETNHO<br />
VEAGH HOUSE. A MONUMENT TO GUINNESS PATRIOTISM AND<br />
HOSPITALITY AND THE RESPONSE WHICH THE IRISH PEOPLE OVER THEIC<br />
CENTURIES HAVE MADE TO THAT PRODUCT. A MAGNIFICENT PLACE,<br />
EXCELLENT HOSPITAL IT Y. YEAR<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER HIGHFIELD, ABC. WAS THERE ANY DISCUSSION<br />
BETWEEN YOURSELF AND THE IRISH AUTHORITIES ON THE QUESTION OF<br />
AUSTRALIAN SUPPORT FOR TERRORISM HERE? SEVERAL WEEK AGO SOWMEIT<br />
WEAPONS WERE FOUND WHICH WERE ALLEGED TO BE STOLEN FROME<br />
AUSTRALIAN ARMY STORESE R I I<br />
P. I M: NEVER MENTIONED.<br />
Q. YOUR EXCELLENCY. HAVING IN MIND THE ECONOMIC COLLAPSE WHICH<br />
IS FORECAST FOR THESE ISLANDS IN THE NEXT YEAR WOULD YOU<br />
ENCOURAGE MORE EMMIGRATION FROM THESE ISLANDS TO AUSTRALIA IN<br />
THE NEXT SAY TWO. OR THREE YEARS? WL H B<br />
IRISH MIGRANTS HAVE BEEN VERY NUMEROUS TO AUSTRALIA,<br />
AND I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THERE WILL CONTINUE TO BE A SIGNIFICANT<br />
AND A VALUABLE MIGRATION FROM IRELAND TO AUSTRALIA. AUSTRALIAN....<br />
MIGRATION TO AUSTRALIA WILL NOW DEPEND PRINCIPALLY ON PEOPLE IN<br />
AUSTRALIA WHO NOMINATE CLOSE RELATIVES AS INDIVIDUALS. IT WILL<br />
NOT BE OFFICIAL SPONSORSHIP SO MUCH AS INDIVIDUAL SPONSORSHIP.,<br />
YOU MUST HAVE A JOB TO GO TO AND PARTICULARLY, OF COURSE, YOU<br />
OUGHT TO BE A CLOSE RELATIVE. AND THERE ARE MANY PEOPLE IN<br />
AUSTRALIA WHO HAVE CLOSE RELATIVES IN IRELAND. NEVERTHELESS,<br />
I WOULD EXPECT THAT MIGRATION WILL NOT BE AS COPIOUS AS IT WAS,<br />
SAY, TWENTY YEARS AGO. THERE IS NOT THE SAME SCOPE TO EMPLOY<br />
MIGRANTS IN AUSTRALIA AS THERE USED TO BE AND AT THE SAME TIME<br />
THE INTEGRATION OF EUROPE AS A WHOLE WILL MEAN, I EXPECT, THAT<br />
FEWER PEOPLE WILL BE LEAVING EUROPE FOR OTHER CONTINENTS.<br />
Q. PRIME MINISTER. AFTER EIGHT MONTHS IT IS FAIRLY CLEAR<br />
THAT MR GAIR THRIVES ON THE DIPLOMATIC LIFE. CAN YOU TELL US<br />
WHEN HIS TERM ENDS AT THE END OF THREE YEARS WILL HE BE OFFERED<br />
ANOTHER DIPLOMATIC POST?<br />
I'LL CONSIDER THAT IN MY NEXT GOVERNMENT.<br />
Q. DID THE TAOISEACH ACCEPT YOUR INVITATION.... / 6 </p>
<p>S-DlIDEARTIn-NT OF FOR(, EJN AFIA\ IRS<br />
INWARD CABLEGRAM 6-O. DU308<br />
PARDON?<br />
Q. DID THE TAOISEACH ACCEPT YOUR INVITATION TO GO TO AUSTRALIA.<br />
-"-AND. IF HE DID WHEN IS HE GOING?<br />
AH WELL., I BELIEVE THAT THE TAOISEACH IS SERIOUSLY<br />
CONSIDERING THE POSSIBILITY OF VISITING AUSTRALIA. MIND YOU<br />
AUSTRALIANS ARE NOT IN A VERY STRONG POSITION TO PRESS THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER OF IRELAND TO VISIT AUSTRALIA, BECAUSE IT'S<br />
33 YEARS AND MORE SINCE AN AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER LAST<br />
VISIT-ED IRELAND. HOWEVER, I DON'T SUPPOSE THERE'S EVER<br />
BEEN A VISIT BY AN IRISH PRIME MINISTER TO. AUSTRALIA. I WOULD<br />
-TIN( K IT WOUL-D BE VERY APPROPRIATE IT WOULD UNDOUBTEDLY BE<br />
VE-RY WARMLY RECEIVED, IF A TAOISEACH WERE TO VISIT AUSTRALIA,<br />
LECUSE AUSTRALIA HAS PEEN ONE OF THE PRINCIPAL IRISH COLONIES.<br />
THE ONLY LARGER ONES WOULD BE THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA.<br />
Q. MR WHITLAM. POWER, IRISH INDPENDENT: DO YOU SEE YOURSELF<br />
COMING BACK FOR A LONGER VISIT TO IRELAND? THIS IS YOUR SECOND<br />
TIME HERE ISN'T IT AND EACH TIME IT WAS ONLY FOR A ONE-DAY VISIT?<br />
P. M. NO IT'S MY FOURTH TIME I'VE BEEN HERE. THIS IS THE<br />
FOURTH TIME I'VE VISITED IRELAND. I CAME HERE IN 1962, 1967<br />
AND IN JANUARY 1972. FOR A MAN WHO HASN'T GOT A DROP OF<br />
IRISH BLOOD IN HIS VEINS, I'M A FAIRLY REGULAR VISITOR.<br />
IN-TERJECTION: AMBASSADOR GAIR.. YOU'RE AN R. C. A REGULAR CUSTOMER.<br />
P. M. AM AN ADHERENT I AM AN ADHERENT OF THE<br />
CHURCH OF IRELAND. I AM A SEPARATED BROTHER.<br />
AMBASSADOR GAIR: WE'RE PRAYING FOR YOU EVERY DAY.<br />
THE..-. I'VE COME TO KNOW THE LEADING MEMBERS OF THE IRISH<br />
GOVERNMENT AND THE IRISH OPPOSITION ON THESE VISITS AND SEVERAL<br />
OF THEM HAVE VISITED AUSTRALIA. MR COSTELLO AND MR O'LEARY OF<br />
COURSE HAVE BEEN THERE THIS YEAR. SO IT IS VERY EASY FOR ME<br />
TO PICK UP A CONVERSATION WITH MR LYNCH OR MR COSGRAVE BECAUSE<br />
I'VE HAD SEVERAL -CONVERSATIONS WITH THEM OVER THE YEARS.<br />
Q. DO YOU SEE YOURSELF HAVING AN EXTENDED HOLIDAY HERE AT<br />
SOME STAGE? I THINK IT WOULD BE VERY PLEASANT.<br />
INTERJEC'i ON: AMBASSADOR GAIR. I'VE INVITED HIM TO COME OVER.<br />
Q. MR WHITLAM CAN YO TELL ME YOUR COMMINIQUE REFERS TO THE<br />
FACT THAT YOU DISCUSSED WITH THE TAOISEACH THE SUMMIT MEETINGS<br />
OF HEADS OF GOVERNMENT IN PARIS. CAN YOU ELABORATE ON THAT A<br />
/ 7 </p>
<p>INWARD ( CABlEGRAM 7-0. DU308<br />
LITTLE BIT? YOU SHOULD GET THAT FROM THE TAOISEACH HIMSELF. BUT HE..<br />
YOU KNOW, THERE'S NO POINT IN ME, AT SECOND HAND, GIVING THE<br />
ACCOUNT WHICH HE'S ABLE SO WELL TO GIVE SINCE HE AND DR FITZGERALD<br />
PARTICIPATED IN THEM. I'M... I'LL BE VERY GLAD TO HEAR THROUGH<br />
THE AMBASELADOR AND OVER THE NEXT FEW MONTH WHEN MR... DR<br />
FITZGiEH. ALD WILL BE PRESIDING.<br />
Q. 1 JL. T WASN'T TOO CLEAR WHAT THIS REFERENCE WAS. I UNDERSTAND<br />
NOW.<br />
Polo: ARE VERY INIERESTED, NATURALLY, IN HAVING THE IRISH<br />
ASSESLMUhT OF TRENDS IN THE COMMUNITY.<br />
Q. MR UHITLAM, ARE YOU MISSING THE AUSTRALIAN CHRISTMAS?<br />
P. M. Oh, I DON'T MIND CHRISTMAS IN THE BRITISH ISLES...<br />
CHRISTMAS IS I'M AMONG FRIENDS HERE... BOSOM OF MY FAMILY.<br />
ENDS. RINI" :' INISTER<br />
REI I ISTER<br />
FOREIC: N AFFAIRS<br />
MIN AND DEPT DEFENCE<br />
JIO<br />
MIN AND DEPT LABOR AND IMMIGRATION ( C)<br />
MIN AND DEPT OVERSEAS TRADE<br />
MIN AND DEPT MINERALS AND ENERGY<br />
TREAShRER AND TREASURY<br />
PMS PRESS OFFICE<br />
PMS PRIVATE OFFICE<br />
AIS ( C)<br />
PM AND C<br />
MR B JOHNS ( PM AND C)<br />
MR MENADUE<br />
ADAA ( C)<br />
MIN1 AND DEPT AGRICULTURE R. GRIFFITr<br />
S3 EC AeM<br />
3 1 EC -c15I\ ii<br />
nr v~<br />
NoO C ~ Ef<br />
i. j<br />
1 1 \ 11 1-N1l. 1N 1 M I ( W I \ 1 I l)* b'S1 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
