<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4270</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF WOOL HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004270.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-AQA 4112TI<br />
PRIME MIN, STER<br />
MOR PRESS NOVEMBER 81 ) 976<br />
OPENIN' OF~ WOOL HOUST&amp;<br />
I was very pleased to receive your invitation to open W~ ool<br />
House the' new home of the Australian Wool Corporation.<br />
The Australian Wool industry has been fortunate in having<br />
such a body as the Australian Wool Corporation to work onF<br />
The Wool Corporation and its predecessor organisations<br />
have worked with great dedication and resourcefulness to meet C<br />
the challenges confronting the industry and to promote the<br />
welfare and best interests of the wool industry as a whole.<br />
The major challenge facing wool growers over the years has<br />
been to strengthen their selling position in a market<br />
situation where some 100,000 sellers face only few buyers.,<br />
This has meant an extensive and continuing effort on the<br />
part of growers to promote their product and to iimprove<br />
Product marketing arrangements. K<br />
It has also produced a remarkable and sustained research<br />
effort. to improve the quality of the product itaelf.<br />
T he wool industry has always sought to stand on itp, own feet.<br />
All its efforts have emphasised self-help-of strengthening the<br />
industry bv its own efforts.<br />
This pattern was clearly set in 1936 when the original<br />
Australian Wool Board was established at the request of<br />
wool~ grower organizations. The Board was established to<br />
promote the greater use of wool and to sponsor research of<br />
benefit to the industry.<br />
Woolgrowers, at the time, asked the Government to levy them<br />
f or the purpose and this self-imposed levy has been maintained<br />
ever since with the rate being changed only at the request of,<br />
or after consultation with the industry.<br />
At about the same time in 1937 a major step was taken to<br />
promote the use of wool through the formation of the International<br />
Wool Secretariate. Represenitatives of Auistralia's partners in<br />
the International Wool Secretariat axe here today, </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Promotion and research to support the efforts of growers have<br />
developed greatly since that time. Since 1945 the Government<br />
has contributed to wool research designed to enhance<br />
productivity and assist wool in competition with synthetic<br />
fibres. Research has already yielded benefits worth many millions of<br />
dollars to the wool industry and no doubt much more can be<br />
achieved in the future. Sound and adequate arrangements must<br />
therefore be ensured for the continuation of wool research.<br />
Since 1964 Government and woolgrowers have been partners in<br />
financing the promotion of wool.<br />
The present arrangements for joint financing of wool research<br />
by woolgrowers and the Government will expire in June next,<br />
as will arrangements for the funding of wool promotion.<br />
The Industries Assistance Commission has made recommendations<br />
as to how wool promotion and research should be financed in<br />
future years. These recommendations formed part of comprehensive<br />
reports on the funding of rural research and promotion in<br />
general. The Government is studying the Commission's reports and<br />
re-appraising the principles which should be followed in the<br />
future. In these deliberations the particular circumstances<br />
and needs of the wool industry are receiving close attention.<br />
The issue of wool marketing came to the fore in 1970 with<br />
a disastrous slump in wool prices.<br />
As a major step to improve marketing conditions a reserve<br />
price scheme was established and administered by the former<br />
wool commission. Twice in the past five years this scheme<br />
has averted a situation of catastrophic price decline.<br />
The scheme, of course, is now under the Australian Wool<br />
Corporation, and it continues in an even more positive way<br />
to protect the industry from price collapse, and to put a<br />
friend in the market which will enable the growers to sell<br />
from a position of strength and confidence.<br />
Through the scheme, the Corporation has exerted a powerful<br />
stabilising influence on wool prices, and it has the complete<br />
support of the Commonwealth Government.<br />
In July this year, the floor price for wool was increased to<br />
234 cents per kilogram clean whole clip average a rise of<br />
14%. It has further been announced that the floor level for<br />
next season will not be less than the level decided upon for<br />
1976/ 77.<br />
Further changes in marketing arrangements must be judged against<br />
the Government's intention to give stability to the floor price<br />
for two years ahead.<br />
It ought to be remembered that the floor we have announced is<br />
a minimum. c<br />
7-</p>
<p>-3-<br />
We very much hope that market conditions will enable the'<br />
floor price to be raised further in the review which will<br />
take place towards the start of the next selling season.<br />
The measure that we have taken so far in this regard reflects<br />
the confidence of the Government in the future of the<br />
, wool industry.<br />
These arrangements are, of course, being funded by the<br />
woolgrowers themselves. Not only are the Government loans<br />
now being steadily repaid but the Corporation is returning<br />
in addition, very substantial amounts by way of interest.<br />
To date the Government loans have returned some $ 60 million<br />
in interest payments.<br />
That surely gives the lie completely to anyone who suggests that<br />
what the Government has done is an unreasonable subisdy to the<br />
wool industry.<br />
It is a loan at a profitable rate of interest.<br />
There is, of course, a contingent liaibility resting on the<br />
Government. As a result of these market arrangements therefore,<br />
the Government has a responsibility which cannot be put aside.<br />
Because of our undertaking to back the Ccrporation, the<br />
contingent liaibility broadens our responsibility to the<br />
whole community. That cannot be ignored in evaluating<br />
any proposals for reform.<br />
Another circumstance against which future changes in marketing<br />
arrangements must be assessed is the capacity of any such<br />
changes to reduce handling costs.<br />
Handling costs for wool remain a major problem.<br />
No grower can be pleased at a situation where levy, handling<br />
and selling charges which are met by growers absorb some<br />
of the value of the clip. In addition, growers also meet<br />
shearing, classing and transport costs which absorb almost<br />
a further estimated 15% of the value of the clip.<br />
The Australian Wool Corporation has advanced comprehensive<br />
proposals which, if adopted, would significantly reshape<br />
the present system of wool marketing. The previous Government<br />
had the proposals studied at great-length by an indepartmental<br />
committee but was unable to reach a decision on them. / 4 </p>
<p>My Government has exanined the carlier studies and arranged<br />
for further scrutiny of aspects not covered previously or<br />
requiring a fresh appraisal.<br />
However, areas still remain in which judgements arc difficult.<br />
Let me say that the objectives of the proposals are worthwhile.<br />
Ho\ wever, the proposals themselves are far-reaching of their<br />
nature and would reTqire fundamental changes in marketing<br />
arrangements.<br />
We need to have in mind that changes in arrangements which<br />
would be irreversible must lcave no doubt about their success.<br />
The Government is therefore determined to explore thoroughly<br />
all policy options including ideas advanced since the Corporation's<br />
proposals were formulated, to ensure that any changes ultimately<br />
adopted are in harmony with the best long-term interests of the<br />
wool industry.<br />
The wool industry has contributed greatly to Australia's growth.<br />
If it were not for the overseas funds this industry earns, and<br />
has earned, the standard of living of everyone in Australia<br />
would be considerably less.<br />
Let me reaffirm my Government's confidence in the contribution<br />
the wool industry will continue to make to the future of Australia<br />
and to the standard of living of all Australians.<br />
The Commonwealth Government has stood firmly by the industry<br />
in the past and it intends to fully maintain that backing<br />
for the future.<br />
In doing so it will continue its support for the vital role<br />
of the Australian Wool Corporation.<br />
The Corporation is a substantial organisation. It has offices<br />
in all Australian states, and has market liaison representatives<br />
in various overseas locations.<br />
The new Wool Douse provides appropriate accommodation for the<br />
Corporation. The wool industry has been well served by the Australian Wool<br />
Corporation and its predecessors.<br />
It is with much pleasure that I now declare Wool Bouse open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
