<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40264</transcript-id>
    <title>Statement on Federation</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/03/2016</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australia’s governments must work together to solve the big issues.</p>
<p>Our economic plan is designed to ensure that as our economy transitions from the mining boom to a wider and more diverse economy, we continue to deliver the vital services and infrastructure Australians expect.</p>
<p>In Canberra on Friday, I will meet with Premiers and Territory Chief Ministers to discuss our plan to fund services in the years ahead, in the most effective way for all Australians.</p>
<p>For you.</p>
<p>Currently, Canberra collects taxes and provides the states and territories almost $50 billion a year in tied grants each year to fund services and build infrastructure. This results in ongoing arguments, negotiations and duplication in administration.</p>
<p>In many areas responsibility is far from clear and the only thing in ample supply is finger pointing and blame.</p>
<p>We’re all sick of it.</p>
<p>A way to solve this problem would be to give the states and territories a proportion of personal income tax - rather than demanding money from Canberra they would be raising money themselves and be accountable to their own voters.</p>
<p>The focus of governments should be about delivering better services – not arguing over funding.</p>
<p>The key principles will be that this is not about increasing the total tax take - any income tax surrendered by the Commonwealth to the States would be offset by a reduction in Commonwealth grants to the states.</p>
<p>Taxpayers would not notice any administrative change - the Australian Tax Office would continue to manage the collection of income tax.</p>
<p>So, clearer lines of responsibility, less duplication, more open accountability.</p>
<p>The States' lack of financial freedom, their constant begging to the Commonwealth, the constant blame game - this is what is wrong with our federation.</p>
<p>Now we can't reform it ourselves - this has to be agreed with the States and we know it will take some time.</p>
<p>But the question for us all is this: do we want to keep complaining about the issue as we have done for decades? Or do we want to do something about it.</p>
<p>Let’s stop the predictable arguments, and focus instead on the best way to deliver effective services for all Australians.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
