<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3560</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, DR JF CAIRNS, MELBOURNE, 20 DECEMBER 1974</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003560.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L~ Ih A CJLR : Piws" 1 11 S' D. c iWr<br />
' FTho Actinra Primei Mi riW-Ler, Dr. f. F. Cairns, ta cp'.:. dt'<br />
aro-i7 t-knb h ic Loi:. iar tuoe. ~ cmhn a'-Jir CL<br />
11 i. q'il Couri: the Vc of Au: ra Iic)-1 Go~ e'ran unir,)* clvm j<br />
T tu 1 thc worst ev: mple ofI pl. 3. y-rpoJ-L-Ies the Cd<br />
evI. redp -oplc: tlhat ~* chave ee Dr. Cai-cms SLid.<br />
. I;: 1hc Stiate; haCd cons.:-Ldeyre-d Lh c' wJ S a-A3 LI : irig wronc! : 1.<br />
' iY'f'CSC t ~ iC2-~ 5 t was open frLh( om at TZJ<br />
co ns-; : i1uc. tC LV sugoucst ions a nd. these would ai ' U0 e ill<br />
t; 3'. c-I into CC. ount.<br />
TiIhey d9&amp; ota,. dI theimseives of thatI sji'iple oruiy<br />
Thie cdetructivc acti-on of the Victorian Goverwmcrit th'ae the<br />
Australian Covc. cnrn'-wt ' rs ent. re welfare psrogrrnaic and hItCE, r~~<br />
tChe my-d, tite hai dica. pped, the hoieluoss and the~ UlCL) O'<br />
1I) w my. oemntcould conitemplaLe suha bodly-blow to t.-7A<br />
Fsec io; n cif thie com-mui. irhIy is &gt; c.-yoiid compr eherisioy'.<br />
P~ rocj-~ ststhat are in jeom -cdy ifth Icnjc ov ccvcv<br />
sue ce00s iGeJu7 o\ ernmunt stcn~ shus ~ teVuICsi? c.:<br />
~' udL~ iehL~ idi~:?: p&amp;', a. sis-tCanco sheitce2 o sh js<br />
handicappd hi1. ucJ trainaing and accurpodu iio* n1 Ihhetrs<br />
vi Lal-meAls-on-wheels service, and tbleovtne~ tr<br />
to) as,'-Ast cruani-al-ioyus which poid acToaion f-orchrJc~<br />
S~ eof-those prograimmes were in : i s tonc c, when -w2 LCoc) o c, 1t<br />
peJ iti-ca]. rature of the challenje is thus coaafiroucT.<br />
ThVec-oanMove aliso destrct-ive because it car. otKLy d( I<br />
the application of re-o. mployment measures which the Australiari<br />
conside-s to be of prime importance.<br />
bespliethe actCion of the ' vicl;: orizn Govcerrjm'iienL, the i~ c1a<br />
Govx'e:.: nraent will continue to adm. inister th: e schecaes -icl1y and.<br />
ade-~ ua. el. Ly<br />
DE the St-ate:.; iaro adamarwtnL aholit p-Lrs isting with thceir osL. cLv<br />
appl'icution it--is to be IhoPE'., 3-ihIatl the Hiigh Court once, azc1 f: 0-1 OJI<br />
wiiJ upk: iold 1-ho rigMc of thc C! crlu oirr&amp; n:.. Oa-SS<br />
cLii~ i ~ e~ e3 ~~ OflC-ii: n-. y beu.. rp yd </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
