<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23006</transcript-id>
    <title>Establishment of the Prime Minister&#039;s Business Advisory Council </title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Today, I announce the appointment of Mr Maurice Newman AC as the Chairman of the Prime Minister’s Business Advisory Council.</p>
<p>Mr Newman is a former Chairman of the Australian Stock Exchange, Deutsche Bank (Asia Pacific), the Australian Broadcasting Corporation as well as a former Chancellor of Macquarie University.</p>
<p>Government and business have a shared interest in the economic success of Australia.</p>
<p>We appreciate that a strong economy needs profitable and dynamic businesses to sustain it.</p>
<p>Strong and successful Australian businesses mean more jobs and more revenue to fund the provision of services and investment in infrastructure.</p>
<p>The previous government’s class war on business and sectors of our economy did little to engender confidence and economic opportunity.</p>
<p>A strong relationship with business characterised the Hawke, Keating and Howard governments. I want to restore a working relationship between government and Australian business.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister’s Business Advisory Council will meet three times a year with senior members of the Government.</p>
<p>It will include representatives from the manufacturing, agricultural, services and information sectors as well as from the resources sector because Australia’s future depends on having a diverse five pillar economy.</p>
<p>Interested persons who wish to apply to be part of the Advisory Council can register their interest by email at <a href="mailto:businessadvisorycouncil@pmc.gov.au">businessadvisorycouncil@pmc.gov.au</a> or by post at:</p>
<p>Prime Minister’s Business Advisory Council</p>
<p>Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet</p>
<p>PO Box 6500</p>
<p>CANBERRA  ACT  2600</p>
<p>Applications must be received by Friday 11 October 2013.</p>
<p>I look forward to working with Mr Newman and members of the Advisory Council.</p>
<p>26 September 2013</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
