<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10818</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW FUNDING FOR YOUTH HOMELESS PILOT PROGRAMME</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/06/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce an additional $2.3 million for a six-month</p>
<p> extension of the Youth Homeless Pilot Programme and to launch the</p>
<p> interim report of the Youth Homeless Taskforce.</p>
<p>The funding boost will allow the Youth Homeless Pilot Programme to</p>
<p> continue its valuable and innovative work while the Government considers</p>
<p> a response to the taskforce's recommendations for future policy</p>
<p> directions.</p>
<p>One of my first actions as Prime Minister was to personally convene</p>
<p> a meeting of community leaders to discuss youth homelessness -- a</p>
<p> meeting that lead to the formation of the 14-member Youth Homeless</p>
<p> Taskforce.</p>
<p>Youth homelessness is a terrible problem which often begins a cycle</p>
<p> of dependency for young people and has ramifications across the entire</p>
<p> community.</p>
<p>The taskforce has established 26 Pilot Projects around Australia with</p>
<p> the aim of trialing a range of innovative early intervention and family</p>
<p> reconciliation strategies in conjunction with community organisations</p>
<p> to combat homelessness. These pilots have been in operation for almost</p>
<p> a year and I commend the taskforce and the project participants for</p>
<p> their work.</p>
<p>The work has already highlighted how parents need support and information</p>
<p> after young people leave home. To assist parents in this situation,</p>
<p> my Government has recently announced the trial of a parent liaison</p>
<p> service. This service will allow parents to obtain information on</p>
<p> a "hot line" on the homeless rate assessment and provide</p>
<p> them with an opportunity to raise concerns.</p>
<p>I am looking forward to receiving the final report of the taskforce</p>
<p> later this year. I am sure it will build on the strengths of the interim</p>
<p> report and the success of the work of the pilots.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
