<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9570</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MERCER, TODAY TONIGHT, CHANNEL 7 10 MAY 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009570.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ t~ x I<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MERCER, TODAY TONIGHT, CHANNEL 7<br />
MAY 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
NM: Prime Minister, welcome to the program.<br />
PM: Thank you Neil.<br />
NM: Do you accept that in many ways, this Budget is a critical test of your<br />
own personal credibility?<br />
PM: I don't think that is right at all. I was re-hired by the nation in 1993,<br />
to re-start growth and employment and that is exactly what we have<br />
done. I 1<br />
NM: And the promised tax cuts of course, which you haven't delivered,<br />
Prime Minister?<br />
PM: No that's not right Neil. They were paid... . the first round was paid<br />
a week probably doesn't mean much to you, Neil but it was<br />
paid at the end of 1993<br />
NM: The second round has been paid?<br />
PM: . the second round $ 4000 million of it is going to be paid into<br />
superannuation accounts. Now, let's take the two issues: on growth,<br />
we have had the fastest growing Western world economy since the<br />
election. On employment, we have had the largest fall in<br />
unemployment in our history. On inflation, we are down to between<br />
2% and We have paid the first round of tax cuts, and now on<br />
the second round we are paying into people's supera ' nnuation<br />
accounts so that every Australian working person will have what they<br />
have never had before, and that is a massive pool of savings for<br />
them in retirement. And the country will end up with a massive pool<br />
of savings to relieve our call on overseas debt. </p>
<p>NM: But Prime Minister, they won't have that $ 10 or $ 15 in the hand as<br />
you promised. They will have something in 20 or 30 years time.<br />
PM: Understand this in 1993 the Government suspended the second<br />
round of the tax cuts, and we said " we would bring them back,<br />
probably in 1998....<br />
NM: What I'm putting to you is that....<br />
PM: do you recall that?<br />
NM: What I am putting to you, Prime Minister, is that a lot of people are<br />
now very cynical, given that promise.... . you see, that promise has<br />
been broken.<br />
PM: Mr Howard has been running around saying that all day...<br />
NM: . he's been saying that you are dishonest and a liar.<br />
PM: Let me tell you this he was Treasurer in the 1977 election and<br />
promised tax cuts, and he then took them away 5 months later and<br />
he got in these headlines " Lies, lies, lies" do you remember that?<br />
NM: I do indeed, Prime Minister. A lot of people would say that headline<br />
applies to you today.<br />
PM: How could they? Neil, don't be ridiculous if we are paying $ 4000<br />
million off the Budget $ 4000 million off the Budget who do you<br />
think we are paying it to? To Martians?<br />
NM: John Howard says...<br />
PM: No. Come on you answer me.<br />
NM: John Howard....<br />
PM: Leave John Howard you have made your little claim.<br />
NM: No the point I'm making is, Prime Minister, is that you promised<br />
voters 10 or 15 bucks in the hand they will not have that when you<br />
said they would have it, and what I'm putting is that you are trying to<br />
convince people that black is white.<br />
PM: Let me just remind you, again. In the election campaign of 1993, I<br />
couldn't get a line for the tax cuts. You know what they said to me?<br />
" Oh, come on Prime Minister you promised those in 1992 in One<br />
Natio! You know Neil, through the election campaign I was saying<br />
to people like you " but what about the tax cuts" " oh, come on Prime<br />
Minister, don't mention those". The tax cuts never rated a line in the </p>
<p>1993 election this is all a bit of re-writing of history. But, they<br />
certainly rated a line in peoples bank-books when they were paid at<br />
the end of 1993. And let me just tell you this you ask your viewers<br />
this question would they rather $ 10 a week in their hands, or $ 15 a<br />
week, rather than this: a person on 100% of average weekly<br />
earnings that is, someone on $ 33,000 a year will, as a<br />
consequence of last night's policy change, mean that at the end of<br />
their working life if they start their working life and finish it 40 years<br />
later they will end up with a parcel of $ 461,000. This is a person<br />
on $ 33,000 a year...<br />
NM: We're going to ask that question, Prime Minister.<br />
PM: . and then they pick up an annual retirement annuity of $ 30,000 a<br />
year.<br />
NM: We are going to ask that question.<br />
PM; $ 33,000 a year.<br />
NM: What I am putting to you you're confident that Australians will buy<br />
that sales pitch?<br />
PM: Neil, it's hardly a sales pitch.<br />
NM: But it's a gamble on your part.<br />
PM: It's not a gamble at all. What other Government would have the wit,<br />
the conscientiousness, the imagination to actually build for the<br />
average working person a big nest egg in retirement so that they<br />
never have to worry again about their retirement. That is, a person<br />
on $ 33,000 a year goes into retirement on $ 30,000 a year not just<br />
the pension, but $ 30,000 a year. That can only come from a Labor<br />
Government.<br />
NM: Prime Minister, let's talk about families. John Howard says that the<br />
big losers in this Budget are families Medicare levy is up, the cost<br />
of a family car is up at least $ 1000, they have lost their tax cuts, and<br />
there is a 12% GST on the home on buildings.<br />
PM: There is not a GST on the home. This is from John Howard, who<br />
wanted to put a 15% GST on the whole of the home that is bricks,<br />
mortar, tiles, concrete this is an extension of the sales tax for taps,<br />
copper pipes, drill bits, pieces of plumbing. In other words, some of<br />
the products used in building not bricks, not mortar, not concrete,<br />
not timber. But John Howard wanted to put 15% on them last year at<br />
the election.<br />
NM: We have to wind up, Prime Minister how do you rank this Budget in<br />
terms of Budgets that have been delivered since 1983, very quickly? </p>
<p>4<br />
PM: It's a surplus, it takes the pressure off interest rates, it keeps growth<br />
going through the 1990s, and it delivers the biggest savings nest<br />
egg to fill the greatest savings pot-hole we have ever had.<br />
NM: Prime Minister, thanks very much for your time.<br />
PM: Thank you Neil.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
