<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7805</transcript-id>
    <title>THE PRIME MINISTER, MR BOB HAWKE, INTERVIEWED BY MR RICHARD CARLETON ON 60 MINUTES, SUNDAY 12TH NOVEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/11/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007805.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MINTErS: MR BOB HAWKE12.11.89 Paqe 1<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER, MR BOB HAWKE,<br />
INTERVIEWED BY MR RICHARD CARLETON<br />
ON 60 MINUTES, SUNDAY 12th November 1989<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HNWEs<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RAIIKE;<br />
MR CARLETON: Do you fear a united Germany?<br />
Fear, no, I think we shouldn't fear it, I<br />
think it is inevitable.<br />
But two mighty wars this century, why not a<br />
third?<br />
Because we do live in times of the most<br />
-dramatic change. War in 1914-12, even war<br />
in 1939-45, while disastrous, never<br />
threatened the annihilation of mankind from<br />
this planet. Now war means that.<br />
According to the Prime Minister, it is not<br />
just East Germany, it is the whole<br />
communist system that is in trouble. c22 </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB HAWXZ 12.11.89 waqe 2<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON;<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWIN:<br />
MR CARLETON: I mean, you have had now more than seventy<br />
years of this rule, in the Soviet Union,<br />
and they still can't feed themselves.<br />
Their people still queue up for basic<br />
necessities. It is a. failed economic<br />
sytemn.<br />
Failure, and economics. You have been in<br />
power, not seventy years but seven years.<br />
Nearly., We've got an inflation rate of eight per.<br />
cent and each month we are spending two<br />
billion dollars more overseas than we<br />
earn. Skf.. by those two measures you are a<br />
failure too may I suggest.<br />
You may suggest it, but may I suggest that<br />
that is a very selective picking of the<br />
critera. May I suggest-<br />
We'll go to interest rates as well.<br />
Sure, and we'll go to employment. We'll go<br />
to the fact that we have created 1.6<br />
million new jobs, which is a rate of<br />
employment creation more than four times<br />
faster than our predecessors, more than<br />
twice as fast as the rest of the world.<br />
Look, I'll concede that you've been a good<br />
Prime Minister. That Australia is a more<br />
gentle, a caring and a more equal place<br />
MINUTES: MR BOB RAWXZ12.11.89 Paqe 2 </p>
<p>XZNUT! S: MR BOB RAWKE 12.11.89 Psa. 3<br />
MR HAWKE: Yen.<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE: than it was some years ago. But the fact<br />
of the matter is air, that you have failed.<br />
No veil<br />
zVve got to pay 17 per cent for a housing<br />
interest loan here. In Japan they pay six.<br />
okay. inl France and Germany they pay less than<br />
ten. In Switzerland they pay six too.<br />
okay, okay.<br />
Why under your management have we got to<br />
pay 17?<br />
well the rates of interest under us haven't<br />
reached the peak that they did under the<br />
other mob first of all.<br />
Well no<br />
Well wait a minute. But wait a minute, you<br />
don't live in Switzerland, you live in<br />
Australia. You'* ve got to make a choice,<br />
within an historical context, where in fact<br />
no government in th. past has been able to<br />
control wages. And so historically in<br />
Australia that's where you're going to<br />
live I hope, I hope you're not going to<br />
live in Japan or somewhere else<br />
MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKE12,11.89 Pace 3 </p>
<p>MINUTES: HR BOB HAWKE 12.11.89 Paqe 4<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RANKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RANKS: Nov come on, onto the point.<br />
in Australia, the... context is this. That<br />
historically no government has been able to<br />
control wages, to keep a situation where<br />
the Richard Carletons and everyone in this<br />
community have got security of employment.<br />
Because there's been boom and bust.<br />
Interest rates are at that level, not<br />
because I want to impose any hardship on<br />
you, and I guess you can probably cope.<br />
But certainly I don't want to impose<br />
hardship on your ordinary viewers. But I<br />
know, from our historical experience, that<br />
if I don't have monetary policy tight for<br />
the time being, then the economy will<br />
collapse, because you will suck in that<br />
many imports that the exchange rate will<br />
collapse, interest rates through the roof<br />
and the economy's gone.<br />
So we've got to all exercise the restraint<br />
and bear the pain of high interest rates to<br />
just bring the level of activity down<br />
-somewhat.<br />
Mr Hawke, I've been listening to<br />
politicians for years and years and years<br />
telling me about..<br />
I've been listenting to interviewers too<br />
MINUTES: MR BOB RAPME12.11.89 Paqe 4 </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB ELANKE121.9ae5<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLSTON;<br />
MR RAWEE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON: Yes, I know. Telling me that they've just<br />
about got the solution, just give me a few<br />
more months, a few more weeks, even a year,<br />
one more term in office.<br />
But I'm not saying, I'm not saying, just<br />
wait for a few more I'm saying with<br />
pride, that in this six and a half years,<br />
getting on for seven years I'm saying,<br />
look at that, I'm not saying just wait for<br />
that, I'm saying that now that kids are<br />
getting employment. Their parents who are<br />
in work have got secure employment.<br />
That's a product of the past, of what we've<br />
done. Prime minister, Bangladesh can run an<br />
airline. Zaire can run an airline.<br />
Australia can't. May I suggest<br />
Australia can run an airline, what are you<br />
talking about.<br />
we're not doing a real good job at the<br />
moment. on the contrary, I mean, you compare the<br />
airlines of Australia with those<br />
countries. We leave them for dead.<br />
Well there's no airline, I couldn't get a<br />
plane today, couldn't get a plane on<br />
Wednesday. The programme's been chartering<br />
planes for 13 weeks.<br />
I 12.11.89 Pace </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR DOE HAWKE 12.11.89 Pan. 6<br />
MR HAWE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RAWKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RAWKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE: Now, now are you really saying<br />
The airlines are in chaos hers.<br />
Are you really saying . to me, you are<br />
comparing Zaire and Bangladesh and you want<br />
to compare our airlines with theirs, and<br />
you take this moment. If you took the<br />
point up<br />
13 weeks without planes. St5 the buck's got<br />
to stop somewhere and I suggest it stops<br />
vith you.<br />
The buck has stopped. The fact is that the<br />
airlines are being recreated. They will be<br />
back in full operation in the early part of<br />
next year.<br />
March, says Abeles.<br />
Well-We've had it for three months and we're<br />
looking at another five.<br />
Okay, okay. What's the alternative? The<br />
alternative-we could have fixed this<br />
dispute, that started back, in the middle<br />
of last year. Could have fixed it,<br />
eliminated it, just like that, by doing<br />
what? Saying to the pilots<br />
MCR aCvRLiZnONg: in to the pilots.<br />
MINUT29i MR BOB HAWKE12.11.89 Paan 6<br />
MR CARLZTOX: </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKE 12.11.89 Paae 7<br />
MR HAWIKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKEs<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWE:<br />
MR CARLETON: Yes, and I tell you what, if we've done<br />
that, you would have not only destroyed<br />
your airline industry, you would have<br />
destroyed the Australian economy.<br />
But look, it's a disgrace that Australia<br />
can't have planes in the air for what is<br />
going to be eight months apparently.<br />
We've had planes in the air, we haven't had<br />
as many but<br />
Oh but it's laughable, what's going on now.<br />
Well, it's hardly laughable. They are<br />
being built up gradually and the full<br />
system will be restored. And it will be<br />
restored but we-<br />
By March?!<br />
But, but, Just, okay, just, stop the anger<br />
a bit and come down to no you-<br />
Put it now The tourism industry that's<br />
being ruined,-and Skase is going bust<br />
because he can't fill the mirage resorts,<br />
no planes will go there.<br />
Yes, you are saying* you are saying Skase<br />
is going bust because of the airlines<br />
dispute I would love to have an<br />
anaog is that your analysis?<br />
.: r-Mirage resorts going bust because the<br />
planes won't go there. </p>
<p>MIUTES: MR 30B HAWKE 21.9Pq<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HANKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR ZAWKS:<br />
MR CARLETON: Are you saying that Skase is going bust<br />
because the airlines<br />
Skase's Mirage Resorts, all right?<br />
Get the grin off your face, you know you're<br />
you know<br />
You too.<br />
You know, yeah. Now, let's go back to<br />
this. if you want to compare the airline<br />
industry, in Australia, into the future,<br />
with what it's been, let me tell you this.<br />
That when the airlines resume operations in<br />
a full sense next year, we will have an<br />
airline industry which will be fifty per<br />
cent more productive than the one we had<br />
from the middle of 1989.<br />
True it is, problems now, and I have never<br />
denied that, but-<br />
But you can't!<br />
No0, but what about, what about acknowledging,<br />
what about acknowledging the fact, no<br />
one's disputing it, that as from the<br />
beginning of next year, a fifty per cent,<br />
and a continuously fifty per cent more<br />
productive and efficient airline industry.<br />
That will be the outcome.<br />
Prime llinist~ r, I just can't, for the life<br />
of me 12.11.89 Paqe 8 </p>
<p>MINUTS: MR BOB HAWKE 12.11.89 Pace 9<br />
MR NKI:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RANKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RANKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR3 HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETOM:<br />
MR HAWKE i well you just ignore that do you?<br />
No, no. Well if it comes about, if and<br />
when it comes about, fine.<br />
Why, why won't it come about.<br />
Well YOU say it will, it probably will.<br />
Yes. But how can you sit there and believe that<br />
you have given leadership to this country,<br />
when we've had our airlines down<br />
The leadership that this country required<br />
is the leadership that I have given, and<br />
that is, not what the alternative you<br />
know what the opposition were saying? Give<br />
in. Give in. That's not leadership, that<br />
There's got to be a better way.<br />
There-is no way, there is no way Richard,<br />
when you have a situation of having<br />
pleaded, as I did, with the AFAP. I<br />
pleaded with them. I said, negotiate<br />
within the system, like every other<br />
organisation. They refused. If they had<br />
been given in to then you know that every<br />
other union would have said, okay, that's<br />
the norm, thirty per cent. </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB VIWKE l2. ll. 89Paqe<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR RNKSI:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HIAWKE: And there were many with the industrial<br />
muscle and capacity to talce it and grab<br />
it. That would haye ruined the economy.<br />
And leadership was about not giving in to<br />
blackmail to destroy the industrial<br />
relation~ saystem, and to destroy the<br />
Australian economy. That is what<br />
leadership was about.<br />
Prime Minister, I want to suggest to you<br />
that maybe, just maybe, you've lost just a<br />
bit of your touch on this.<br />
well-I mean-<br />
You can suggest it, but you're wrong.<br />
The community I suggest is laughing at you,<br />
not with you, when you say silly thingslike,<br />
there's no dispute in the airline<br />
industy.<br />
Well if I'd said that, they would be<br />
entitled to laugh at me and so would you<br />
and so would everyone. The trouble is, I<br />
never said it. Now why, what purpose do<br />
you have? I assume not deliberately, but<br />
what purpose do you have in misquoting me?<br />
I never said that. if I had they would<br />
have been entitled to laugh at me.<br />
MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKE12.11.89 Paqe </p>
<p>Now if you quote, and it's a pity you<br />
can't, if you quoted accurately what I<br />
said, that the industrial dispute was<br />
finished. A point which has been conceded<br />
may I say by every editorial writer. Every<br />
person who's commented on the dispute.<br />
Hawke is correct in saying that the<br />
industrial dispute is over. And that is<br />
simply, not a semantic point. It's a very<br />
important point to understand about that.<br />
It is true, as a fact, that once the<br />
Federation of Pilots said to their members#<br />
you resign, resign, and take all your<br />
entitlements, which they have done, then<br />
the Federation didn't have employees.<br />
And what's been happening, and this is the<br />
point of saying that that industrial<br />
dispute is over, not that the problems in<br />
the industry and the aftermath of that<br />
industrial dispute aren't there, but the<br />
important point is what the industrial<br />
Relations Commission has said, that the<br />
rebuilding of the airlines industry is not<br />
in the resolution of a finished, over<br />
industrial dispute. The resolution of the<br />
problems is in encouraging people now to<br />
sign those contracts.<br />
MR CARLETON: Srto assert that the industrial dispute is<br />
over, as you have done here today, I think,<br />
lifts peals of laughter across the suburbs<br />
of Melbourne. </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKE 21.9 ae1<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
RR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:-<br />
MR HANKS:<br />
MR CARLETON: Well it doesn't, it doesn't lift, it<br />
doesn't bring peals of laughter, from those<br />
who know the realities. I mean, you ask<br />
But if the realities out there are out<br />
there at the airport, you just can't ge t on<br />
a plane.<br />
But I am not saying -Imean, why do you<br />
insist Richard in misrepresenting what I am<br />
saying. I am not saying, that there aren't<br />
still problems. of course there are<br />
problems. Aren't there going to be<br />
problems if all the pilots in an industry<br />
resign. They . resign~ i They finishdheir<br />
employment nexus. You only have an<br />
industrial dispute, an industrial dispute<br />
as we know it within our system# if you've<br />
got employees, and an employer there.<br />
There is no industrial dispute between the<br />
airlines and those people who are now<br />
employed by them. No industrial dispute at<br />
all. So you are saying-<br />
And there will be no industrial dispute<br />
between the airlines and the increasing<br />
numbers of people who are going back into<br />
them, as pilots.<br />
You said the other day that you were a<br />
little tired, I think I quote you correctly<br />
12.11.89 Pace 12 </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR SOB HAWK! 12.11.89_ Paqe 13<br />
MR SAWKZ:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWEE:<br />
MR CARLXTON:<br />
MR HAWIN: No no, no. I no let me get it straight<br />
again. I<br />
maybe I've got two mistakes, ' a little<br />
tired and a bit dreary' was wore both of<br />
those wrong?<br />
No no. I said about the answers I gave you,<br />
I mean you are running things there get<br />
your research people to do it better. I<br />
was asked about what had been, not a<br />
glorious week in Parliament. And in I<br />
said, in respect to myself, a few of my<br />
answers might have been a bit long and a<br />
bit boring.<br />
And they said, what are you going to do<br />
about it. And I said, I'm going to get a<br />
bit more sleep. But I can assure you#<br />
Richard, I will be going into this period<br />
between now and the next election as<br />
vibrant and as fit and active as I've ever<br />
been. Do you think it's possible that the<br />
community is getting a bit tired of you?.<br />
Oh, they could be. I don't know, I don't<br />
know that any person can ever retain, I<br />
mean I reached very very high lerels of<br />
approval, I would have regarded Aas<br />
impossible, I did at the time, and I said<br />
so. You'll never, I said to my people,<br />
you'll never have those levels of approval<br />
retained.<br />
MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKE12.11.89 Paqe 13 </p>
<p>M! NU~ rIS:_ MR BOB IIAWKE 12.11.89 Page_ 14<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWRLS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
14R HAWKS:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE: And I wouldn't have the approval rating in<br />
19 at the end of 1989 that I had in 1983<br />
and I never expected to retain those.<br />
What is your approval rating now?<br />
it varies which, which poll you can see.<br />
But just lot me Bay this. Which is an<br />
important thing. I wouldn't swap my<br />
approval rating<br />
For Andrew'sl<br />
Ah well, you said it, you said it.<br />
Had any second thoughts about Keating?<br />
I've never had any second thoughts, I mean<br />
I've always thought since he's been my<br />
Treasurer, that he is an outstanding<br />
Treasurer and never had any doubts about<br />
that and he still is an outstanding<br />
Treasurer. But it was unforgiveable the attack he made<br />
on Elliott the other day, I mean totally<br />
unsubstantiated, totally personal and he<br />
should apologise for it surely?<br />
Look, Paul will make his decision about~ he<br />
handles those things. I think he feels<br />
that he might have handled it different,<br />
differently, if he had had his time again.<br />
MINMS: MR BOB RAWKE12.11.39 Page 14 </p>
<p>MINUTES: MR BOB HAWKS 12.11.89 Paqe<br />
MR CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
14R CARLETON:<br />
MR HAWKE:<br />
MR CARLETONs well why can't he stand up and be a man and<br />
and apologise?<br />
Well look, I am not going to be interviewed<br />
for, for Paul. I will defend Paul as a<br />
Treasurer, I will defend him as a great<br />
parliamentarian. I will defend him as a<br />
man who's got an enormous comaittment to<br />
this country.<br />
Now in terms of particular actions over a<br />
particular issue, and why shouldn't he do<br />
something now, you should ask Paul. All<br />
I'm saying is, I have total confidence in<br />
Paul Keating as-an outstanding Treasurer.<br />
I say of him, and I think he would say this<br />
of himself if you asked him, that he would<br />
have preferred, if he could have had his<br />
time again on that issue, to have handled<br />
it somewhat differently.<br />
I might have got a few lines wrong there in<br />
those quotes Prime Minister but X wasn't<br />
wrong, you don't want to correct me*-about<br />
saying that you've been a good Prime<br />
Minister? Thanks mate.<br />
Thanks a lot.<br />
MINUTZS: MR BOB RAWXE12.11.89 Pacre </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
