<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7543</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, DEMNAN PUBLIC SCHOOL, DENMAN 32 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007543.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, DENMIAN PUBLIC SCHOOL, DENMAN<br />
23 MARCH 1989<br />
E &amp; EO0-PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what do you think of the allegations<br />
by people like Sandra Nor that you're just a little bit<br />
too closely involved with Sir Peter Abeles and that's influenced<br />
Your decision on the airport?<br />
PM: Just let me suggest you be very careful about that<br />
because I've spoken to my solicitors this morning and a<br />
writ will be issued against the Sydney Morning Herald.<br />
It's completely false, totally defamatory and will be proceeded<br />
against. JOURNALIST: Will you be taking any action against Sandra<br />
Norio. PM: I've told you, I've instructed my solicitors to issue<br />
proceedings against the Sydney Morning Herald.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's Gary Punch's future?<br />
PM: I've spoken to Gary and he has as a matter of fact<br />
conveyed to me that he thinks that it is appropriate that<br />
he should have a change of ministry. I can understand that<br />
so I'll just consider that. I think what he says is understandable<br />
and I'll consider what change is appropriate.<br />
JOURNALIST: What other portfolio<br />
PM: I'm not discussing that now. I said I've received from<br />
him an indication that held like a change. I'm not going<br />
to discuss here on the media Just what's in my mind about<br />
that. I'll deal with it quite quickly and when I've made<br />
my decision I'll announce it.<br />
JOURNALIST: What sort of solidarity do you expect from<br />
the Cabinet in terms of numbers and gathering numbers for<br />
Caucus meetings-<br />
PM: The Cabinet principle is quite simple. Everyone in<br />
Cabinet is bound by the decisions. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Would Senator Richardson be able to gather.<br />
numbers on that issue in Caucus?<br />
PM: I don't think he'll be doing that. He'll be supporting<br />
the Cabinet decision.<br />
JOURNALIST: Will the backbench revolt have any chance of<br />
getting ahead?<br />
PM: It's your phrase ' revolt', I don't accept the accuracy<br />
of the phrase. Obviously some people are not happy with<br />
the decision, they'll raise it in Caucus. But the Cabinet<br />
decision will be upheld.<br />
JOUR~ NALIST: Mr Howard is talking about a July election.<br />
PM: Thank you for raising that. Let's just deal with this<br />
fellow Howard. He's been caught, as I say, with his political<br />
and fiscal pants around his ankles. He promised at the<br />
beginning of 1988 that he would have his tax policies ready<br />
by when August of 1988. They're not out yet, six months<br />
later. I've promised right through last year, beginning<br />
of this year, I said we will be making an announoeme t about<br />
tax cuts to operate from July 1989. I've been s inF , rom<br />
last year. We've gone ahead on the basis that we ye got<br />
policies in place, we'll deliver what we promised. He hasn't<br />
got a policy. He promised the people of Australia he'd<br />
have it by August of ' 88. hmrn't got it. In the absence<br />
of a policy what's he got to do? As we're delivering on<br />
time as promised, he's got to say, ' oh, it's an election'.<br />
He's wrong, he's got no policies, he's got no basis of Policy<br />
to have any answer to the Government's position so he calls<br />
early election. I'm very good at numbers, I'm very good<br />
at counting, but I'm not that good that I can keep count<br />
of the number of lies and mis-statements that Mr Howard<br />
keeps pushing out to the Australian people. There will<br />
be no July election. All this reveals is the stark contrast<br />
of the Australian political scene. A Government which steadfastly<br />
through 1988 has promised tax cuts from July 1989, a Government<br />
which will be delivering honest promises. Against that<br />
an Opposition leader who promised from early ' 88 the delivery<br />
to the Australian public of his tax policies by August of<br />
' 88 non delivery. That is delivery by the Government,<br />
non delivery by Howard, result Howard calling..,<br />
He's wrong.<br />
JOURNALIST: When you stop all the guesswork then and come<br />
out with a date? 0%<br />
PM: Let me be charitable you're playing games aren't<br />
you saying we'll come out with a date, that I'll annotince<br />
a date in March of 1989 as to the next election. Don't<br />
let's play games. I've been saying all the way along consistently<br />
that the period for an election will be roughly from W* e..<br />
end of this year to the middle of 1990. I've been saying </p>
<p>that consistently, I'm saying I'm not in an election mode,<br />
I don't see that we're preparing for an election in 1989.<br />
It's possible at the end of the year, more lik~ ely into next<br />
year. Now no Prime Minister in those circumstances has<br />
ever announced an election date, you know that, it's a good<br />
funny question.<br />
JOURNALIST: So definitely no July election?<br />
PM: I have said that, I repeat it. No July election. Mr<br />
Howard as usual is wrong and he's wrong not Just because<br />
he's silly which he is but he's wrong for much more<br />
fundamental reasons, which I've said. He's been revealed<br />
as unable to develop a policy, unable to . deliver on his<br />
unequivocal promise made at the beginninq-o f 1988 that he'd<br />
hve his tax policies ready and . revealed'by August of 1988.<br />
oa~ n the other'khand'consistently have said through last<br />
year. tax cuts on the basis of our policies from July ' 89.<br />
That will be delivered.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Carr's comments that migrants might have<br />
to out of Sydney in the future because of the population<br />
pressures there and things lik~ e the problems of-<br />
PM: The only thing I have to say about that is that in<br />
the latest review that we made at the end of last year of<br />
our migration policy, we have given additional points under<br />
the point system to those who are nominated for areas ou+<br />
of the major cites, and particularly out of Sydney. So<br />
those who are being nominated to go to other areas will<br />
have a greater chance of getting in under the point system.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
