<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15162</transcript-id>
    <title>Australian Broadband Guarantee</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/03/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased today to announce the Australian Broadband Guarantee, a new measure to ensure that all Australians have affordable access to a high-quality Internet connection.</p>
<p>Broadband Internet is a key economic driver and is increasingly important for the delivery of business and education services, as well as for individuals in the home.</p>
<p>Under the Australian Broadband Guarantee, the Government will commit almost $163 million to provide subsidised Internet access for Australians currently unable to gain a reasonable access to broadband service at their principal place of residence or small business.</p>
<p>Today's announcement will make Australia one of the few countries in the world to ensure an affordable broadband service to all households and small businesses. Australian Government programs have already helped more than one million households and small businesses access broadband Internet.</p>
<p>The Australian Broadband Guarantee will provide a smooth transition to the $600 million Broadband Connect infrastructure program and broadband access for people in metropolitan, outer metropolitan and regional Australia who, for technical or geographical reasons, do not have broadband services at present.  The $600 million Broadband Connect Infrastructure Program will establish an efficient, sustainable broadband network across regional Australia to enable the roll-out of higher speed Internet.</p>
<p>The Government has committed $1.1 billion to the total Connect Australia package and from June 2008 a further $2 billion from the Communications Fund will be available to enhance telecommunication services and to continue the Australian Broadband Guarantee.  More details on the Australian Broadband Guarantee are available at <a href="http://www.dcita.gov.au">www.dcita.gov.au</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
