<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2004</transcript-id>
    <title>LAUNCHING OF NEW FIVE-YEAR APPEAL BY GEELONG GRAMMAR SCHOOL - GEELONG, VICTORIA - 24 FEBRUARY 1969 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/02/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002004.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PARLIAMENTARY (/ 0P 4<br />
LAUNCHING OF NEW FIVE-YEAR APPEAL<br />
BY GEELONG GRAMMAR SCHOOL<br />
GEELONG, VICTORIA 24 FEBRUARY 1969<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Carton<br />
Mr. Southey, Mr. Headmaster, Ladies and Gentlemen:-<br />
It is not a sacrifice, Sir, but a pleasure for my wife and<br />
I to have been asked tonigTht to attend such a cheerful and, in a way, such<br />
a nostalgic gathering. Indeed, it is' such a cheerful gathering that I am<br />
touched with a little wand of doubt as to whether everybody here knows<br />
precisely why it is they have been asked: But fortunately speaking of<br />
course politically it is not for me to tell you, but for those who are to<br />
speak later. I think the function that has been assigned to me, which I<br />
notice has been said to be going to take twenty minutes, but which in fact<br />
is going to take very much less, is to take your minds for a moment off<br />
what those who follow me will say and to use an American football term<br />
run interference. I said " a cheerful and a nostalgic gathering", and it is<br />
nostalgic for me to stand here again in this vaulted hall which seems<br />
to have changed very little, except for being elongated a little bit, since<br />
the time when I sat here as a very small boy and was very lucky if I got<br />
a slice of toast at breakfast as a mark of favour from one of those<br />
handmaidens who used to wait upon us. If you got one, you knew you were<br />
right, that she rather liked you that day. Otherwise you didn't get toast<br />
at all. But not only does the nostalgia come from the hall itself or<br />
from the portraits that one sees hanging opposite one here. I have seen<br />
three headmasters of this school. Admittedly I had a brief acquaintance<br />
with the first. But I remember him wiell, for it was he who did his best<br />
to have me expelled at an early stage from this school. It was for what<br />
I still believe was the relatively mild misdemeanour of having brought<br />
down from my home a 25/ 50 Browning automatic with a full clip of<br />
cartridges, which I was accustomed to use in the bucolic glades of Mystic<br />
Park, and which I had no intention of using upon him or upon any master<br />
or any boy: But it appeared to him, coming as he did from England, that<br />
the discovery of such a lethal weapon in a locked cupboard to which,<br />
incidentally, he should not have had a key was something which deserved<br />
/ 2 </p>
<p>the gravest condemnation. However, he was argued out of his intentions<br />
and subsequently left, with no bullet holes anywhere around him, and was<br />
superseded by the headmaster whom I suppose most of us here know, Mr.<br />
R. Darling. Trhat was the second headmaster that I knew. Mr. Garnett<br />
, is the third. It is my hope, and my belief, that in the years which lie<br />
ahead of this school there will be portrait after portrait around the walls<br />
of this great hall. And perhaps in another hundred years there will be<br />
an indication, through those portraits, of the progress which this school<br />
has made, just as there is an indication for those who knew the school in<br />
the time of Dr. Brown, in the time of Dr. Darling, and now in the time of<br />
Dr. Garnett, of the progress which has been made in the last twenty-five<br />
or thirty years. I believe it is essential that such progress should be made<br />
by independent schools in Australia. There are three main reasons why<br />
I say this. We have always, I think, believed that there was a democratic<br />
right for parents, if they were prepared to make some sacrifice themselves,<br />
to choose the type of school to which they would send their children. They<br />
should not be denied by any act or any law or any economic action of those<br />
in power the opportunity always provided they would help to pay for it<br />
themselves to choose that form of education for their children which<br />
they believed would suit their children best.<br />
This exercise of a democratic right is so wound up with<br />
oreducational system and should continue to be so wound up with it<br />
tat I myself regard it as one of the most important facets of education<br />
W in this nation of Australia.<br />
Secondly, Sir, there is an educational advantage in this.<br />
By that I do not mean that this or any other school of this type is at any<br />
9 tshpee csitfaicte . t imIe d ob entotet rm feitatend t htoat eadtu aclalt. e tIht em yaoyu nbge thaint misa ya sncoht oboel. ruInt dbeyp endsi<br />
on the headmaster. It depends on the staff. It depends, in the case of a I<br />
state school,* equally on the headmaster and the staff.<br />
Nor do I mean that all new educational advances come from<br />
schools such as this, because they don't. But. what I do mean is that when<br />
there are two educational systems side by side, when there are schools tLtt<br />
are run by the state and when there are schools that are run as this school'<br />
is run, then there is more room for experiments in educational attitudes,<br />
in educational methods, and there is less likelihood of bureaucratic control<br />
of all curricula and education. Indeed it is this competition, if that is the<br />
word, and I think perhaps it is, not in the sense of competition in the markel<br />
place, but in the sense of competition for excellence which spurs both thel<br />
state and the private school to the benefit of both. I: / 3 </p>
<p>Were there but one system of education, were we to have<br />
a system such as I am told exists in France where a Minister for Education<br />
can, at a given moment, say, ttffi every school in France at this hour of<br />
eleven o'clock in the morning, the third form is being read to from page<br />
649 of the second volume of Proust" then we would indeed be in danger<br />
of having a monolithic system. A monolithic system can be moribund.<br />
One in competition cannot. And these are the educational advantages that<br />
schools such as this bring to the community.<br />
Thirdly, of course, though having been a parent I know it<br />
is difficult for parents to understand, there is an economic advantage<br />
not of course to those who have children going through the school at a<br />
particular time, but to the community at large. Because if all those -who<br />
attend this and other schools such as this throughout Australia were<br />
tomorrow to have the doors shut to them, and be required to go to state<br />
schools, then this would be impossible. The bill to be paid would be so<br />
great that school fees would seem as nothing in comparison to the taxes<br />
which would be placed upon you. Thirdly, therefore, there is this economic<br />
advantage. Sir, this school is one with a long and distinguished record.<br />
It has been a beneficiary in certain ways from Commonwealth Government<br />
schemes and State Government schemes, but what it has also done is<br />
something which the Chairman mentioned. It has sent out from its portals<br />
graduates, not only to one state of this country but to Queensland, Western<br />
Australia, Tasmania, South Australia to the whole of the nation of<br />
Australia and they have come back here tonight from all corners of the<br />
land to the one part of the nation which gave them education.<br />
Perhaps this happens in other schools too. I believe it does.<br />
I believe it will happen more and more, but it is another great advantage.<br />
I believe that, through this medium, there should be a national outlook able<br />
the more easily to be disseminated than would be the case perhaps in some<br />
other schools. Now, it is not for me to talk any longer. It is for those who<br />
are to follow me now to speak to you, but I do conclude by saying this.<br />
Those of you who know the young of today, the young at any school, the<br />
young perhaps at this school and those of you who know them well would<br />
probably not, most of you, describe them by the word " meek". Certainly,<br />
the ones I have run across could not be so described. But, Sir, meek or<br />
not, they will inherit Australia, and they will do the better for this nation, 1K<br />
and for the children they will bear tQ you as grandchildren, if they are<br />
given every possible facility for education which this nation or this school<br />
or you yourselves can provide.<br />
It is as true today as it was true when Disraeli said in the<br />
19th century of England that " upon the education of this country the fate of<br />
this country depends", and it is upon the contributions that schools such as<br />
this make to education, that the education of this country depends. That is<br />
why tonight, with some nostalgia and great affection, I am so honoured to<br />
have been asked to speak to you for a short time. I thank you. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
