<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8841</transcript-id>
    <title>NATIONAL PRESS CLUB</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/03/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008841.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
C 1. 4.<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
NATIONAL PRESS CLUB<br />
CANBERRA 11 MARCH 1993<br />
I thought he might have surprised us.<br />
I thought, seeing that there is an election on Saturday,<br />
he might have come along for a debate.<br />
I thought he might have stopped impersonating American<br />
Presidents, stopped running, and come along to answer some<br />
questions from the people whose democratic purpose is to<br />
ask them.<br />
No such luck.<br />
Dr Hewson has broken one of the traditions of Australian<br />
-poltics:.. we don't have such a lot of home grown<br />
traditions but one of them is that leaders make<br />
themselves accountable to the press in the week before an<br />
election. Dr Hewson has not answered a question of substance since<br />
Christmas. Every time he has been asked a question of substance and<br />
that is about three times he has fallen over.<br />
Dr Hewson has not been able to accommodate anyone who is<br />
asking for facts about his so-called " plan".<br />
. His campaign itself has been a falsehOOd.<br />
S1D 17nitation of Freaent Clinwios campaign disguises<br />
c fact that QEhat rlinton standt for, Hewson despises.<br />
U .* C14miCF ha% Vrn a mask in this campaign.<br />
If W* AX ans have not seen behind it yet, they still<br />
have two days.<br />
Dr Hewson has been unable to provide 4= wAth facts on the<br />
GST. 71 4F </p>
<p>He has said it will create 2 million jobs. He has said it<br />
consistently. There is not one person in this room who believes that.<br />
I daresay, there is not one economist in Australia who<br />
believes it.<br />
I would venture to say there are a good many people in<br />
this room and a good many economists who believe that it<br />
will create no jobs or, wnrR, it will cost jobs.<br />
I am one of the latter. I am sure I am not the only one<br />
to have heard reports in recent weeks of companies in my<br />
case some of the finance houses of Sydney and Melbournewhich<br />
are planning lay-offs of workers when the GST is<br />
introduced. That is the first great deceit of the Hewson campaign.<br />
They say the GS'r will create jobs.<br />
The GST will not create jobs.<br />
I would also venture to say that there is not one person<br />
in this room, nor I imagine is there one doctor in<br />
Australia, who doesn't know that Dr Hewson is going to rip<br />
the heart out of Medicare and leave it a universal health<br />
care system in name only.<br />
Dr Hewson would move the Australian health system towards<br />
the American system.<br />
The American strategy of publicly subsidising private<br />
health care and insurance has left 35 million Americans<br />
without insurance, and given doctors and private health<br />
insurance companies the ability to unremittingly Jack up<br />
health costs.<br />
Just as they promise to do in Australia: in their own<br />
journal. In the Sydney seat of Lowe 9 out of 10 doctors<br />
promise to increase their fees.<br />
It's your money or your health.<br />
American health care costs are more than 50 per cent<br />
gredftii'tiin-Kust-ral-j 850 per cent greater and a<br />
fraction of the service.<br />
Last year in the United States employer spending on health<br />
care exceeded total after tax profits.<br />
Last year in Australia employers paid nothing and were<br />
that much more Competitive as a result.<br />
In America a huge part of the population lives in fear of<br />
being sick or injured because of the health bills they<br />
would have to pay. In Australia the only thing to fear is the sickness<br />
itself.<br />
There are waiinlis-ts-it is true. In the campaign<br />
speech I announced action to remedy it by contracting out<br />
the treatment of public patients in private _ hospitals.<br />
This is additional to the S70 million we have given the<br />
States to shorten waiting lists.<br />
But if those waiting lists were twice as long they would<br />
not constitute a reason to adopt the American health care<br />
system. That is the second great deceit of this campaign.<br />
The Liberals say they won't destroy Medicare.<br />
The fact is they will.<br />
I am also sure that there isn't a single person in this<br />
room who doesn't know that Dr Hewson's industrial<br />
relations 2pgram will destroy the cooperative ethic on<br />
whc ifER1naustrial relations are based; or that he will<br />
throw people onto individual contracts and destroy thereby<br />
their security, their wages and conditions, and their<br />
dignity. That is the third great deceit.<br />
Dr Hewson's industrial relations policy is not designed to<br />
reduce unemployment but to drive wages down.<br />
I don't believe there is anyone here who doesn't know that<br />
Dr Hewson's plan for Australia is a plan of radical<br />
regression. A plan conceived in the bowels of a computer in the late<br />
1970s, using the Thatcherite software that was all the<br />
rage at Johns Hopkins in those days.<br />
Dr Hewson's so-called " plan" for Australia is an old plan<br />
that has failed wherever it has been tried with<br />
disastrous economic and social consequences.<br />
My great fear is that the damage he could do in three<br />
years, would take us decades to. jepair.<br />
Then there is the one about selling Telecom to an overseas<br />
buyer for S20 billion.<br />
This is the one from the man who talks about national<br />
sovereignty and creating jobs and funding promises.<br />
On each of these counts, the Telecom sale is a fraud.<br />
Does anyone think that Dr Hewson will get $ 20 billion for<br />
Telecom?<br />
7146 </p>
<p>Does anyone seriously think that there will be more jobs<br />
in Telecom if it is sold?<br />
The only way they could get anywhere near S20 billion<br />
would be to sell it overseas and remove all protection for<br />
Australian consumers and workers. It would have to mean<br />
timed local calls. It would certainly mean huge job<br />
losses. Creating jobs in Telecom by selling it overseas is about<br />
as likely as creating jobs in tourism by making it cheaper<br />
to holiday in Bali than it is in Cairns which is what<br />
the GST will do.<br />
So there is another great deceit.<br />
And here is another little one.<br />
On every Fightback pamphlet that has gone out in the last<br />
12 months the Opposition claims that it will abolish seven<br />
taxes. One of them, the coal -export levy, is a standing<br />
joke because it is already abolished.<br />
There is another one there under the heading " customs<br />
duties". The Coalition says it will abnlish cus tom duty.<br />
That means, unequivocally, zero tariffs.<br />
But when it suits them, they say they are not for zero<br />
tariffs not immediately, in some industries, in some<br />
electorates. Both thin~ s cannot be true.<br />
This whole ' plan" of Dr Hewson is a deceit.<br />
He does not have a plan, he has an obsession.<br />
He does not have facts, he has gimmicks.<br />
He has only one fact at his disposal unemployment.<br />
The one big negative of our national life at present.<br />
Unemployment is the great curse of the nineties.<br />
And it is apparent again in today's figures. Essentially,<br />
they are " as you were" figures, which makes the point that<br />
unemployment is going to be immensely difficult to deal<br />
with and it won't be fixed quickly. That's why we need<br />
the full focus of the nation's energies; and why we don't<br />
need those energies dissipated in a divisive scramble for<br />
a piece of the cake.<br />
7148 The figures mean simply that unemployment is too high.<br />
They also show that the unemployment rate may be<br />
flattening out, which is consistent with recent statistics<br />
showing that the economy is picking up.<br />
But this is really beside the point. If unemployment has<br />
in fact peaked, that is no reason for complacency. It is<br />
certainly no comfort for the unemployed.<br />
The central issue is which party is best equipped to deal<br />
with unemployment, and that means which party will succeed<br />
best at getting the economy moving.<br />
It also poses the question which party is best equipped<br />
to help the unemployed directly?<br />
There is no simple answer to unemployment, but there is no<br />
doubt that the best answer in the long-term and the shortterm<br />
is economic growth. and the way to get growth is by<br />
investing and our efforts are aimed precisely at this<br />
point investment in Australian companies.<br />
By contrast, it seems to me beyond doubt that Dr Hewson's<br />
so-called " plan" will not be a remedy but a new disease.<br />
If unemployment is our greatest problem now, how much<br />
worse will it be if we stifle the recovery with a 15 per<br />
cent tax on virtually everything we buy and everything we<br />
use. How much worse will it be if we deal with the problem of<br />
unemployment in an atmosphere of industrial and social<br />
turmoil. How much harder will it be to find solutions, or to find<br />
the concerted national will to solve the problem, if the<br />
rest of the population is divided, insecure and rancorous.<br />
If unemployment is a great problem now, how muc~ h worse<br />
willitZ. P without a universal health care system, or with<br />
an unfair education system.<br />
If unemployment is a tragedy now, how mucrh worse will it<br />
be with S10 billion taken out of the Budget.<br />
How much worse will it be wit~ i social security spending<br />
cut? How much worse with funding for regional areas cut?<br />
How much worse with cuts to State services like State<br />
schools?<br />
How much worse with S800 million cut out of funds for the<br />
unemployed and people left to wait much longer for their<br />
benefits? </p>
<p>6<br />
If unemployment is the worst fact of our national life at<br />
present, how much worse will it be if Government " gets out<br />
of the way" as Dr Hewson says it should, and people are<br />
left to fend entirely for themselves?<br />
How much worgep will it he if we put inflation back in the<br />
system? How much worge will it he if we add a tax burden and an<br />
accountancy burden and a time burden to the small<br />
businesses which we know are going to drive growth and<br />
create jobs?<br />
Since the campaign started, a raft of positive indicators<br />
have appeared illustrating our economic progress.<br />
Tuesday's figures on job vacancies and retail sales were<br />
the most encouraging since 1990. Export figures have been<br />
positive.% Today this very day if you distil the politics out of<br />
this morning's press you will find unequivocally positive<br />
economic news. There's a story about our continuing<br />
export surge, another about our growing manufacturing<br />
sector, another about an Australian company landing a Sl<br />
billion contract in Laos. There is much more but John<br />
Hewson of course won't tell you. For twelve months<br />
wherever there has been hope, Dr Hewson has counselled<br />
despair. That's why today I have released a document accompanying<br />
this speech which describes some of the good things which<br />
are happening in Australia, and which Dr Hewson refuses to<br />
talk about.<br />
There is no . quesrion that the direction we are going is<br />
the right one. We are going too slowly to lower the<br />
unemployment figure, but that is not a reason for changing<br />
course. It's a reason for accelerating progress where we can and<br />
we have done this by lowering company tax rates, by<br />
introducing an investment allowance of 20 per cent and by<br />
cultivating a.. nebankint _ culjture.<br />
Every sensible thing that can be done to speed the pace of<br />
recovery and long-term reform is being done, or is<br />
proposed for a second Keating Government.<br />
And the things we do are all directed at the goal of<br />
creating employment and helping the unemployed through<br />
with training and other forms of assistance.<br />
Some of you will have seen the statistics released this<br />
week on the success of labour market programs. They are<br />
working. They are helping thousands and thousands of<br />
Australians. 7<br />
So why wreck the recovery? Why wreck the safety net, the<br />
humane and constructive government interventions? Why<br />
wreck the social fabric of Australia?<br />
my message for those people who are presently wondering<br />
whether to desert the Labor Government is think very<br />
carefully. Think about what you would lose.<br />
In an election the choice is not between one party and a<br />
vacuum, it's a choice between two parties.<br />
Ask yourself whether by voting for policies which are<br />
proven failures elsewhere in the world, you won't be<br />
punishing Australia and the next generation of<br />
Australians. Ask yourself whether the absolute hollowness, the absolute<br />
fraudulence of Dr Hewson's campaign is not an indication<br />
that a vote for Dr Hewson is a leap in the dark.<br />
To the people of Australia, between now and Saturday, I<br />
would say, every time you hear Dr Hewson say he has a<br />
plan, ask yourself do I understand. Has he explained it<br />
to me. And if the answer is no or maybe don't vote for<br />
him. In this forum this week, Dr Hewson had a chance to explain<br />
his so-called " plan" a chance to explain how it would<br />
create a single job, how it would not destroy the social<br />
fabric of Australia, how it differs from the plans of<br />
Thatcher, Reagan, Douglas and Mulroney he had a chance<br />
to explain it in this forum and he refused. He chose to<br />
play soccer and shout slogans instead.<br />
Let me give the oldest advice in the world to the people<br />
who are contemplating the big jump. Don't do it. For<br />
your own sake don't do it. For Australia's sake don't do<br />
it. For your kid's sake don't do it.<br />
I have been to this Press Club 18 times in the last<br />
decade. I've been four times in the past year. I don't<br />
know how many press conferences I have given in the last<br />
twelve months, or how many doorstops that my staff said I<br />
let go on too long.<br />
I don't believe it can be said that I've ever run away<br />
from scrutiny, or from the opportunity to explain our<br />
policies, or failed to face up to the ramifications of<br />
those policies.<br />
As Treasurer and then Prime Minister, I have taken full<br />
responsibility for the economic and social affairs of<br />
Australia. And all the responsibility that is mine, I<br />
will shoulder. All the damage that the recession has<br />
done, I will attempt to repair. Every sensible thing that<br />
can be done, will be done. Much of it is already being<br />
done and I want the chance to build on this.<br />
7150 </p>
<p>AS I said in the campaign launch, fifteen years ago I<br />
began to imagine an Australia which not only exported<br />
minerals and farm products, but Sophisticated<br />
manufactures. The thought occurred to me and a few other colleagues that<br />
Australia could be what no one had really ever imagined it<br />
could be that is. a country integrated with the world<br />
( you've heard it before I know), focussed on the region,<br />
competitive, creative, sophisticated secure.<br />
And as every one of you know this is happening. Any one<br />
who was old enough and compos mantis in the 1970s will<br />
know what a huge change there has been.<br />
You've heard the figures exporting nearly one-quarter of<br />
our total product, exporting 70 per cent of it to Asia,<br />
exporting quantities of elaborately transformed<br />
manufactures we never dreamed we could make.<br />
Some of you will have seen the McKinsey report on the new<br />
breed of Australian company which is emerging. Some of<br />
you will have noticed that in the last two months, a<br />
S2 billion contract has been signed by BHP with the<br />
Vietnamese Government, and yesterday a $ 1 billion<br />
hydro-electric project in Laos one of the largest<br />
construction projects yet in Indo-China.<br />
These-things are happening as a result of a conscious<br />
decision by the Australian people to change. These things<br />
are happening because we intended them to hKappen.<br />
The new Australia the Australia of the nineties will<br />
be different from the Australia of any other era. And the<br />
essential difference will be this: the Australia of the<br />
nineties will be one entirely conceived by Australians and<br />
brought into being by Australians and wearing the stamp<br />
Aius~ tralija on everything it does.<br />
Now I say that is at stake on Saturday. Our economic<br />
future is at stake, and so is the quality of our society<br />
the Australian stamp of our society.<br />
So much is at risk. A society where chil~ d-Car -e is,<br />
finally, a right. A society which believes women should<br />
get equal pay and be able to participate fully in all<br />
areas of work and life. A society which cherishes those<br />
who spend part of their lives caring for children or sick<br />
people. Those of you who know me will know what I believe.<br />
Whatever my faults, I don't think hiding my beliefs is one<br />
of them.<br />
Very simply I believe in creating a high wage, high skill<br />
and high productivity ' Australia. John Hewson believes in<br />
a low wage, low productivity Australia. John Howson believes in dismantling the public sector he<br />
hates the., public sector. I, believe in making the public<br />
sector, as it is in every successful country, more<br />
efficient, more people-oriented.<br />
John Howson believes in fear in the workplace. I believe<br />
in cooperation and creativity in the workplace.<br />
John Howson believes in private health insurance. I<br />
believe in sharing our personal health care risks through<br />
a national public and private system working in<br />
cooperation. John Hewson believes in zero tariffs as an end in itself.<br />
I believe in using tariff reform as a fair benchmark to<br />
improve our industry with long term plans and safeguards.<br />
John Howson believes in American razzamatazz and hoopla<br />
and carefully staged passion plays and bunfights, and<br />
American advisers, and the constant reiteration of poll<br />
driven phrases.<br />
I don't believe in it, myself. I think it's an assault on<br />
good democratic Australian traditions. I think it's<br />
rubbish. I think one should face the music scratchy,<br />
discordant, unpleasant music though it might be. I think<br />
you have to say what you believe and be prepared to defend<br />
it in detail.<br />
This way at least, when people vote on Saturday they will<br />
know what they will get with Paul Keating. To judge him<br />
by his campaign, the same cannot be said of John Hewson.<br />
Finally, let me say this if people are not convinced by<br />
Dr Howson's intention to impose a GST, to make Medicare a<br />
universal health system in name only, to destroy the basic<br />
rights of workers and the cooperative ethic of the<br />
Australian workplace, to turn our colleges and<br />
universities into businesses, to set back our environment<br />
programs a generation or more if they're not convinced<br />
that Dr Hewson's policies represent a threat to our way of<br />
life and our values, perhaps it will help to think of it<br />
in philosophical terms.<br />
Dr Howson's philosophy is based on the idea of selfinterest<br />
and survival of the fittest. Remember what<br />
Margaret Thatcher said: there is no such thing as<br />
society, only individuals making their way. This is Dr<br />
Hewson' s philosophy.<br />
He wants to impose this idea on Australia. That's what he<br />
means by breaking the mould.<br />
What he doesn't like about Australia is the humanitarian,<br />
community ethos the one that is there in Australia from<br />
the beginning of our European history until now. Think<br />
about it. The heroes of Australia have always been and<br />
remain the champions of the underdog. </p>
<p>Now this may not fit well with the economics that Dr<br />
Hewson believes in, but it fits well with Australia. It<br />
is what we are. It has sprung from our history. It is<br />
what unites us it is the principal bond between us.<br />
I hope I never see the day when our traditions are<br />
subverted by the doctrine of unmitigated self-interest.<br />
That is Dr Hewson's doctrine if I fought him on nothing<br />
else, as an Australian, I would fight him on this.<br />
So if you're not persuaded that ripping up the . social wage<br />
and introducing a giant flat tax will irrevocably-dam8<br />
the fabric and the way of life of Australia, be persuaded<br />
by this.<br />
Be persuaded by the philosophical change, the change in<br />
the ethic be persuaded by all those statements Dr Hewson<br />
has made in the last couple of years, the most telling of<br />
which was that one in the Budget reply when he said, we<br />
must not reach back for people because they will drag us<br />
down. This goes to the heart of it. Ultimately this is the<br />
nature of the risk. John Hewson has been projecting a<br />
more temperate image in recent weeks of course but<br />
perhaps the best reminder of John Hewson's old Fightback 1<br />
persona came in January, in a speech byAshley_<br />
Goldsworthy, the Liberal Party Federal President.<br />
Goldsworthy said Australia needed a jolt. " Life has to<br />
become tougher", he said " with less security and greater<br />
uncertainty". Be warned:-this is the brave new world of Dr Hewson. Let<br />
dog eat dog. Let the lucky and the rich prosper and the<br />
rest gather the crumbs that fall. Dr Hewson is an<br />
unashamed theorist of trickle down economics. If he is<br />
allowed to become a practitioner of this theory, he will<br />
turn Australia on its head.<br />
Call it scaremongering if you like. I do fear for<br />
Australia. I fear for the people. I fear for all those<br />
things which bind us together, and in which I believe<br />
above all other things.<br />
But it's not scaremongering. It's factmongering.<br />
Exposing the facts which Dr Hewson won't reveal.<br />
I am absolutely sure that Dr Hewson will be bad for<br />
Australia. His agenda is radical, disruptive,<br />
destructive. I sincerely hope and believe that<br />
Australians will recognise that they cannot take the risk. NE S L a AS<br />
11 March 1993<br />
COALITION WILL RUIN GAS INDUSTRY<br />
Claims today by Tim Fischer about the future of gas in the Nowra region are a<br />
cheap diversion from the Coalition's real agenda of ruiningthe gas industry<br />
The Federal Minister for Resources, Alan Griffiths, stonglv refuted claims by<br />
Mr Fischer that Labor would not build the gas p, eine extension to Nowra.<br />
" Labor has committed $ 15 million to extende Moomba-Sydney pipeline to<br />
Nowra, to ensure gas is supplied as cheaq as possible to the region, especially<br />
the crucial APPM paper recycling plan ocated in Nowra," Mr Griffiths said.<br />
" We stand by this commitment. T people of Nowra can be assured that the<br />
pipeline extension will be deli ed."<br />
The Coalition plans to sell o the pipeline, regardless of the consequences.<br />
Mr Fischer is today ipdulging in pathetic politics to disguise the fact that the<br />
pipeline extension to Nowra will not be built under the Coalition the pipeline<br />
will simply be soldoff to meet the Coalition's unrealisable promises.<br />
" Only last week, Mr Fischer spoke at the Australian LP gas conference, where<br />
the Coalitio's GST policies were condemned as representing an end to the auto<br />
LP gas industry.<br />
" Furtermore, Mr Fischer knows full well that the Coalition's GST policies will<br />
cripple attempts by the gas industry to extend gas pipelines which supply gas<br />
to'more Australians," the Minister said.<br />
/ Labor was the force behind the Moomba-Sydney pipeline, which now supplies<br />
gas to Sydney and the many country centres Mr Fischer claims to represent,<br />
including Wagga, Orange, Cowra and Young. Under Labor the Pipeline is<br />
being extended to Griffith, Leeton and Narrandera.<br />
Only Labor has a true commitment to develop Australian gas resources to meet<br />
Australian energy needs.<br />
Further information: Kristen Barry ( 06) 2777480<br />
" 7 1. s A </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
