<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5716</transcript-id>
    <title>POLAND</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/12/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005716.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 15 DECEMBER, 1981<br />
POLAND<br />
Cabinet today discussed recent developments-in Poland and<br />
received a briefing from the Minister for Foreign Affairs,<br />
the Hon. Tony Street, on his recent visit to Warsaw.<br />
The Prime Minister said that Cabinet was seriously concerned<br />
at developments in Poland and the possible implications of<br />
them, both within Poland and internationally. It was difficult<br />
to obtain a clear picture of the situation because of the clamp<br />
down on communications within Poland and from Poland to the<br />
outside world. As a result, the Government believes that it is<br />
too early to reach any hard assessment of the situation but<br />
will continue to keep the issues under very close consideration.<br />
" Certainly the Government remains convinced of the need for the<br />
Polish people themselves to resolve their own problems without.<br />
outside interference or coercion", the Prime Minister said. No<br />
country should presume to interfere in Poland's affairs at<br />
this or ahy other time.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the Polish crisis, which had<br />
developed since . August 1980, continued to have the most serious<br />
implications for international stability. The imposition of<br />
martial law at the weekend by the Polish leadership would seem<br />
to represent a serious new phase in the crisis.<br />
Australia, with many other countries, sincerely hoped that these<br />
extreme and repressive measures would so-on end and that they<br />
would not lead to the reversal of the main elements of reform<br />
which had been achieved in Poland in the past 17 months. In<br />
these respects the Government noted the undertakings of the<br />
Polish Leader, General Jaruzelski, undertakings which have<br />
also been conveyed formally by the Polish Government to the<br />
Australian Embassy in Warsaw. The Government also warned that<br />
if martial law led to violence, it would arouse the indignation of<br />
the international community and do much to negate the widesprEtad<br />
sympathy and appreciation of Poland's political and economic<br />
difficulties. The Prime Minister urged that there be an early<br />
return to civil and trade union liberties and expressed the wish<br />
that current developments should not impede the spirit of<br />
conciliation and compromise which had hitherto characterised<br />
the efforts of the Polish people to find their own solution to<br />
their difficulties. / 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
In regard to the Polish Government's request for further<br />
Australian economic support which was made to the Minister<br />
for Foreign Affairs in Warsaw, Cabinet decided that until<br />
the situation in Poland was clearer, it could not take any<br />
decisions on this request.<br />
Nonetheless, Cabinet was mindful of the close interrelationship<br />
between economic recovery and the achievement of political<br />
stability through conciliation and consensus.<br />
A further matter considered by the Government was the question<br />
of Polish refugees and in this regard the Minister for Immigration<br />
and Ethnic Affairs and the Minister for Foreign Affairs will.<br />
keep under review the implications of current developments in<br />
Poland for Australia's policy towards Polish immigration and<br />
refugee movement. The Government is aware of and sympathises<br />
with the concerns of the Polish community in Australia over<br />
the well-being of friends and relations in Poland at this<br />
difficult time. The Government will also engage in<br />
consultations with other Governments and particularly those of<br />
Canada and the United States on Polish refugee questions.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
