<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10681</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                ADDRESS TO THE APEC BUSINESS SUMMIT                 FOLLOWED BY A QUESTION AND ANSWER SESSION                PUTRA WORLD TRADE CENTRE, KUALA LUMPUR</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE.......................................................................................................</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mr Chairman, to the President of Korea, to the President of Peru,</p>
<p> Ladies and Gentlemen. I would like to commence my brief remarks by</p>
<p> welcoming the President of Peru attending for the first time, as the</p>
<p> Leader of a new member of APEC. As the Leader of a country which has</p>
<p> been relatively untouched by the economic downturn that has afflicted</p>
<p> the Asian Pacific region over the last eighteen months, let me register</p>
<p> one or two observations.</p>
<p>The first of those is that Australia is very conscious of the devastating</p>
<p> social impact of the economic downturn in so many of the nations of</p>
<p> the Asian Pacific region. And Australia is also acutely aware of the</p>
<p> painful adjustment process that has been undertaken in so many of</p>
<p> those countries, and I am full of personal, and on behalf of my government,</p>
<p> national admiration for the steps that have already been undertaken</p>
<p> by so many of the Leaders in this region. We understand that it has</p>
<p> not been easy and we understand the political courage involved and</p>
<p> the economic pain also involved in that process.</p>
<p>In preparing for this Leaders' meeting, my thoughts have really</p>
<p> been centred in four areas. The first of those is that we should collectively</p>
<p> reaffirm our commitment to open markets, the second is that we should</p>
<p> adopt, where possible, policies that will promote growth. Thirdly,</p>
<p> we should strengthen economic and financial sector management in our</p>
<p> economies, and finally we should take action to improve the international</p>
<p> financial system.</p>
<p>It has to be acknowledged that the Trade Ministers' outcome on</p>
<p> EVSL was second best from an APEC point of view, but at least the</p>
<p> process is moving forward, and that decision has to be understood</p>
<p> against the background of the difficulties that I referred to a moment</p>
<p> ago. I think we all understand the need to promote national policies</p>
<p> which encourage greater economic growth, and we all have different</p>
<p> stories to tell in relation to that. But the burden of my remarks</p>
<p> really falls in relation to the third and fourth points that I made.</p>
<p>The need to strengthen economic and financial sector management is,</p>
<p> in my view, paramount if investor confidence is to be restored. And</p>
<p> this must mean building up the institutions of economic governance</p>
<p> by adopting international best practice and by adhering to codes in</p>
<p> areas such as banking supervision, securities regulation and fiscal</p>
<p> transparency. To further this goal I announce today an Australian</p>
<p> Government initiative on financial and economic management.</p>
<p>The initiative involves a commitment of $50 million dollars over three</p>
<p> years. It builds on the APEC survey we did on economic governance.</p>
<p> It will help APEC members take practical steps to strengthen economic</p>
<p> and financial management. Examples of what we have in mind include</p>
<p> training for central bank officials and technical assistance with</p>
<p> issuing government bonds. This initiative complements other initiatives</p>
<p> which have been independently implemented by private sector participants.</p>
<p> For example, the Australian Securities Institute has formed a joint</p>
<p> venture with a Malaysian fund manager to provide courses to improve</p>
<p> the country's financial industry skills.</p>
<p>My final area of concern is to ensure that urgent action is taken</p>
<p> to improve the international financial system. I see three priority</p>
<p> areas requiring immediate attention. Firstly, disclosure and monitoring</p>
<p> of hedge funds. Secondly, crisis management and private sector involvement,</p>
<p> an IMF anti-contagion contingency funding. We certainly need prompt</p>
<p> action on the first two, and possible actions could involve a taskforce</p>
<p> of experts led desirably by the United States to develop practical</p>
<p> proposals to better control short term capital flows, particularly</p>
<p> hedge-funds, and also a working group focused on either the G22 or</p>
<p> APEC to develop proposals for crisis management, principally the orderly</p>
<p> workout arrangements for sovereign and corporate debt.</p>
<p>In this connection I would like to emphasise the importance that G22</p>
<p> can play. Unlike G7, it has broad representation and has a strong</p>
<p> Asian voice. I think there may be value in G22 leaders meeting when</p>
<p> there are outcomes in this context to ratify.</p>
<p>Before sitting down, could I just make a point about globalisation.</p>
<p> There is, of course, a lot of debate about the impact of globalisation,</p>
<p> particularly against the background of what has happened over the</p>
<p> last eighteen months. Without detracting from what I said at the beginning,</p>
<p> let me emphasise that globalisation is inescapable and there is a</p>
<p> responsibility on governments to provide a well-balanced explanation</p>
<p> to their domestic and to their world constituency of the advantages</p>
<p> of globalisation. There will inevitably be adjustment costs in both</p>
<p> developed and developing economies and all governments have to deal</p>
<p> with this. But we should never lose sight of the enormous benefits</p>
<p> of globalisation. Indeed much of East Asia's remarkable growth</p>
<p> over recent years has been built on the benefits of a global economy</p>
<p> and what it has brought in terms of investment, technology transfer</p>
<p> and rising living standards. And that experience should be set against</p>
<p> the understandable concerns about the developments over the last eighteen</p>
<p> months.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>Thank you Mr Chairman, distinguished leaders, I am a delegate from</p>
<p> the Bank of China. As you may have noticed, Bank of China is one of</p>
<p> the platinum sponsors of this summit. The notion behind our sponsorship</p>
<p> is quite clear, that we shall do our best to encourage and promote</p>
<p> the business into actions and exchanges all over the world, so we</p>
<p> can benefit from such kind of interactions and exchanges. But, we</p>
<p> have also noticed that what a single business entity could achieve</p>
<p> is rather limited as compared to what could be done on the inter-governmental</p>
<p> level. So in this regard I would like to have your opinions and point</p>
<p> of views regarding the past performance, its effect in this of the</p>
<p> APEC, and based on its performance, and what is your view about the</p>
<p> future of APEC. Will it be corrupt into another talk-shop? It could</p>
<p> be a question to any of you or all of you.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Sir, I certainly don't see APEC just becoming another talk-shop.</p>
<p> There's always a danger with any organisation, any grouping such</p>
<p> as this, that that will happen. I think APEC has achieved an enormous</p>
<p> amount in focusing the attention of a remarkably diverse group of</p>
<p> countries on the benefits of trade liberalisation. It's very</p>
<p> important that APEC never sees its role as being to duplicate the</p>
<p> institutional behaviour of other international groupings.</p>
<p>There's always a tendency to see APEC perhaps in the context</p>
<p> of duplicating the role of the IMF or the World Bank. It certainly</p>
<p> shouldn't attempt to do that. It was established as a body to</p>
<p> promote trade liberalisation. I expressed some disappointment in my</p>
<p> speech about the Trade Ministers' conclusion in relation to the</p>
<p> EVSL and I don't retreat from that, but I think it's important</p>
<p> that we still see the decision that was taken as a move forward and</p>
<p> that we take the opportunity at this meeting of focusing on some of</p>
<p> the more positive outcomes in the area of economic governance, of</p>
<p> financial management, and the like.</p>
<p>It is the case that many of the members of APEC have passed through</p>
<p> the most difficult economic experience that they've had for thirty</p>
<p> or forty years. It's therefore not surprising that there would</p>
<p> be some domestic political strains in the member countries, in relation</p>
<p> to the impact of the economic downturn, and what comes out of APEC</p>
<p> has to be seen against that background. I'm an optimist about</p>
<p> APEC. It has focused the attention of governments of various political</p>
<p> persuasions in my country, as well as in many other countries, on</p>
<p> the benefits of trade liberalisation.</p>
<p>The biggest single challenge for political leaders in relation to</p>
<p> trade liberalisation is to explain its benefits. It's incredibly</p>
<p> easy to explain the disadvantages, or let me not so much say explain,</p>
<p> but to promote resentment about the disadvantages of trade liberalisation.</p>
<p> It's far easier to point to an industry that has closed down</p>
<p> because of import penetration. It is far harder to point to an example</p>
<p> of an industry that is gaining new markets as a result of them being</p>
<p> opened as a consequence of trade liberalisation. And if I had a message</p>
<p> to the business men and women here today, I would say that if you</p>
<p> believe in APEC, and you believe in the cause of trade liberalisation,</p>
<p> you have a responsibility along with your political leaders to explain</p>
<p> the benefits of trade liberalisation, because if you don't, you</p>
<p> will lose the argument.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I want to pose a question to President Kim of Korea. Is he satisfied</p>
<p> with the IMF measures which have been introduced into his country?</p>
<p> And if he's not satisfied, what would he have done? And secondly,</p>
<p> is there any danger of his country, since its opening the banks and</p>
<p> other institutions and businesses to foreign participation, is there</p>
<p> any danger of his country losing its economic independence?</p>
<p>CHAIRMAN:</p>
<p>May I please ask President Kim to respond to that question, and of</p>
<p> course Prime Minister Howard too, if he wishes to respond?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think the only thing I'd add, Mr Chairman, to that is that</p>
<p> I don't think for some years now has it been possible to speak</p>
<p> of any country in the world having complete economic independence.</p>
<p> I don't think in the present circumstances, or in the recent</p>
<p> past, countries that have suffered a severe economic downturn have</p>
<p> had any realistic alternative other than to accept assistance from</p>
<p> the International Monetry Fund. I think Korea responded in a very</p>
<p> intelligent fashion. The IMF bailout, to which Australia was a very</p>
<p> willing contributor, has certainly stabilised the economy of Korea.</p>
<p> We see that as beneficial, not only for the people of Korea, but also</p>
<p> so far as our own participation is concerned, very beneficial for</p>
<p> the people of Australia. Korea, I am very happy to say, is one of</p>
<p> Australia's major purchasers, in fact our second best buyer in</p>
<p> the whole of the Asian Pacific region, and it's just an example</p>
<p> to me of the inter-dependence of the region and the fact that that</p>
<p> kind of economic cooperation within the region is an example of a</p>
<p> sophisticated response to a neighbour's economic difficulty,</p>
<p> and issues of economic independence and economic sovereignty don't</p>
<p> really come into it. It's a question of international common</p>
<p> sense.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>My name is Richard Drabnik from the University of Southern California</p>
<p> in Los Angeles. President Kim and President Fujimori and Prime Minister</p>
<p> Howard all talked about the inter-relationship between finance and</p>
<p> trade and finance and liberalisation, my question is a structural</p>
<p> one. The finance ministers from the APEC economies are not here in</p>
<p> Kuala Lumpur, and they will not meet until six months from now perhaps,</p>
<p> and my question is, how do the Presidents and Prime Ministers interact</p>
<p> with their Finance Ministers in a systematic way to bring to the table,</p>
<p> the ideas and concerns that you have collectively, and that the Finance</p>
<p> Ministers will have collectively, what are the mechanisms for the</p>
<p> APEC process to work more smoothly between the political leadership</p>
<p> at the highest level and the Finance Ministers.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Sir, just speaking for my own part and for the Australian experience,</p>
<p> we of course operate in very close collaboration, and the views that</p>
<p> I express here are the views of my entire government on these matters</p>
<p> and they're very much in synchronisation with the view of our</p>
<p> Finance Minister, which we call our Treasurer, although we do have</p>
<p> a Finance Minister but he doesn't discharge the responsibilities</p>
<p> of a Finance Minister in the APEC context, and very much the views</p>
<p> of our Federal Treasury, there's really no lack of information</p>
<p> flows within the Australian Government and I don't think there's</p>
<p> going to be any real difficulty in the views that I will be expressing</p>
<p> at this meeting, likewise being expressed and communicated by our</p>
<p> Treasurer when he comes to the meeting of APEC Finance Ministers.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I come from China. I have to say that I'm very thrilled to have</p>
<p> a face-to-face discussion with country leaders, and that is my pleasure.</p>
<p> I would like to address three questions, very simple ones. I have</p>
<p> learned that President Clinton is not going to show up and attend</p>
<p> this APEC meeting, and I would like to ask the first question to the</p>
<p> two country leaders on the panel. What's your feelings about</p>
<p> that because the Iraq crisis he can't come? What's your</p>
<p> feeling? And the second question is, without President Clinton attending</p>
<p> this APEC what kind of influence will there be on the Leaders'</p>
<p> Meeting? Will the impact be more negative or will it be more positive?</p>
<p> And the third question is, between the Iraq crisis and this Asian</p>
<p> or global financial crisis, who is more in crisis?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mr Chairman, it's always good to have the President of the United</p>
<p> States at an international gathering but speaking for the Australian</p>
<p> Government I completely understand why he has regrettably felt unable</p>
<p> to come to this meeting. I'm quite certain that the meeting will</p>
<p> be a very productive and positive one, and that Vice President Gore</p>
<p> will fill his shoes very effectively.</p>
<p>As to comparing the two crises, I agree with my colleague from Korea,</p>
<p> you can't really compare them. There are vital interests at stake</p>
<p> for the entire world in relation to the two of them, they are entirely</p>
<p> dissimilar and I wouldn't seek to establish a hierarchy of threat</p>
<p> between the two of them. They're both quite serious and they're</p>
<p> both very important, and there are vital world interests at stake</p>
<p> in both of them.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I am a Korean student currently studying at the International School</p>
<p> of Kuala Lumpur. My question is how can APEC nations protect their</p>
<p> currencies from rapid increases and decreases, even as they promote</p>
<p> freer financial markets and attract increased foreign investment to</p>
<p> the region?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Sir, a certain amount of volatility is an unavoidable consequence</p>
<p> of an open exchange rate system and nothing that I said about the</p>
<p> desirability of examining some measures in relation to capital flows</p>
<p> and hedge funds should be taken as altering that fact. I don't</p>
<p> think any country, be it a developed country or a developing country,</p>
<p> or one that's been touched or relatively untouched by the recent</p>
<p> international economic crisis, is immune from currency fluctuations</p>
<p> and currency instability.</p>
<p>There does seem to be a mistaken belief in some quarters, that in</p>
<p> some way you can regulate your way out of adverse international judgements</p>
<p> being made against your economy. That can't happen, the days</p>
<p> of that occurring perhaps never existed, and they certainly aren't</p>
<p> going to return, so I think my answer to you is that it's just</p>
<p> not possible to insulate the currency of any nation against a certain</p>
<p> degree of volatility. I think there is a case for seeing if you can,</p>
<p> as it were at the margin, monitor and control the severity of that</p>
<p> volatility, but not imagining that you can get rid of it altogether,</p>
<p> because that is utterly unrealistic and it is quite incompatible with</p>
<p> an open exchange rate system, and quite incompatible with the essentially</p>
<p> globalised world economy in which we now live.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I'm from the International School of Kuala Lumpur, and I was</p>
<p> just wondering how can APEC improve the educational systems and employment</p>
<p> opportunities for young people in the member nations, and how are</p>
<p> your countries approaching this issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think it's very important when we're looking at APEC not</p>
<p> to assign to it too many specific tasks above and beyond the task</p>
<p> of promoting trade liberalisation, and above and beyond the task of</p>
<p> improving the general economic health and stability of the financial</p>
<p> systems and the economic systems of the member countries. I don't</p>
<p> say that because I regard fostering educational opportunities as being</p>
<p> unimportant, indeed I'm very conscious speaking as I do in the</p>
<p> Malaysian capital, over the last decade something like 150,000 Malaysians</p>
<p> have had their education within my country, and we continue to regard</p>
<p> the access of people from this region to Australian schools and to</p>
<p> Australian universities, as a very important part of our participation</p>
<p> as a good neighbour in the Asia Pacific region. The scope for promoting</p>
<p> that kind of thing is best, in my opinion, done through different</p>
<p> forums on a bilateral basis between individual countries. I think</p>
<p> it's important to keep the focus of APEC as much as possible</p>
<p> on the trade liberalisation goals and the general economic health</p>
<p> and strength of the member countries. That, as I say, is not to in</p>
<p> any way down play the education role, it's simply to see it as</p>
<p> being responded to in another context.</p>
<p>QUESTION:</p>
<p>I would like to put this question to both the APEC leaders. During</p>
<p> the experience of the past eighteen months, what is the opinion of</p>
<p> the two APEC leaders present here, President Kim Dae Jung of Korea</p>
<p> and Prime Minister Howard of Australia, as to the proposal that there</p>
<p> should be some type of supervisory structure to regulate the activities</p>
<p> of international currency traders?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, my view is that the idea of any elaborate supervisory structure</p>
<p> is probably not desirable. There is an argument to develop some responses</p>
<p> to the repetitive capital flows and the activities of some hedge funds.</p>
<p> I think it is fair to say that because of the activities of some of</p>
<p> these, a number of countries paid a much higher price and suffered</p>
<p> a great deal more than they deserved to. And I can understand the</p>
<p> concern of those countries, but you either believe in an essentially</p>
<p> open economy around the world, an open currency system, or you don't.</p>
<p> And I think once you start talking about elaborate supervisory structures</p>
<p> you do start to run into some difficulties. I think the sort of proposal</p>
<p> that I outlined in my brief remarks represents the distance that we</p>
<p> ought to be willing to go, but once we start going significantly further</p>
<p> than that, I think we will run into some fundamental incompatibility</p>
<p> with the sort of open trading system and open currency system in which</p>
<p> I think most of us in this room still believe.</p>
<p> [ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
