<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5214</transcript-id>
    <title>PROFESSOR ARNDT TO CHAIR COMMONWEALTH GROUP OF EXPERTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/12/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005214.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, 9 DECEMBER 1979<br />
PROFESSOR ARNDT TO CHAIR<br />
COMMONWEALTH GROUP OF EXPERTS<br />
The Prime Minister announced today that a distinguished academic<br />
economist from the Australian National University,<br />
Professor H. W. Arndt, is to chair a Commonwealth group of<br />
experts to make a comprehensive study of factors restraining<br />
growth within world economies.<br />
The Prime Minister recalled that Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
at their recent meeting in Lusaka had recognised that a<br />
continuation of slow growth in the global economy would further<br />
damage the prospects of increasing living standards in both<br />
developed and developing countries, and could have adverse<br />
effects . on their political and social structures. They had<br />
agreed to an Australian proposal that there would be considerable<br />
advantage in a study by independent Commonwealth experts that<br />
focusses on the constraints on economic growth and structural<br />
change in developed and developing nations, and identifies<br />
specific measures necessary to reduce these constraints. The<br />
Group which will comprise about 10 independent Commonwealth<br />
experts is to report in time to assist Commonwealth gove rnments<br />
in their preparation for the Special Session of the United<br />
Nations General Assembly in 1980.<br />
In welcoming Professor Arndt's appointment as Chairman of this<br />
Group the Prime Minister said that Professor Arndt, who is<br />
currently Professor of Economics in the Research School of<br />
Pacific Studies at the A. N. U. and formerly Dean of the<br />
Faculty of Economics, has been an adviser to many international<br />
bodies and has-written widely on economic matters.<br />
Th. e earlier part of Professor Arndt's career had been devoted<br />
to a study of macro-economics. In the last fif teen years he<br />
has been concerned with the problems of economic development,<br />
particularly in Indonesia, and with the linkage of the problems<br />
of developed and developing countries.<br />
Professor Arndt's most recent publication is The Rise and Fall of<br />
Economic Growth: A Study in Contemporary Thought. In the<br />
early 1960' s Professor Arndt conducted a study on the economic<br />
growth in Europe for the United Nations and in the early<br />
1970' s he contributed to the first OECD economic survey<br />
of Australia. -00 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
