<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1534</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 43/1967 - QUEENSLAND FLOODS - STATEMENT BY THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. JOHN MCEWEN</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001534.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 43/ 1967<br />
QUEENSLAND FLOODS<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon.<br />
John McEwen<br />
Commenting today on the floods in North Queensland, the<br />
Acting Prime Minister said that as soon as news of the disaster was received,<br />
the Government arranged for Commonwealth officials to keep in close touch<br />
with the Premier's Department in Queensland so that it could be kept fully<br />
informed of developments. At the same time, requests for assistance were<br />
received by the Services which did all they aould to assist those affected<br />
by the flooding. The Acting Prime Minister said that in accordance with the<br />
constitutional division of responsibilities, the provision of relief following<br />
natural disasters is a matter which falls within the province of the States.<br />
However, in recognition of the need on humanitarian grounds to take special<br />
action for the quick alleviation of individual cases of hardship, sudCessive<br />
Commonwealth Governments have adopted the policy of assisting State<br />
Governments in the financing of relief schemes where the damage has beefl<br />
severe or widespread, but the initiative in setting up these schemes rests<br />
with the State concerned. The Commonwealth participates at the request of<br />
the State and on the basis of matching the amount of money which the StateI<br />
customarily makes available.<br />
Mr. McEwen said that a telegram had been received from the<br />
Premier of Queensland on 17th March, requesting Commonwealth financial<br />
assistance and the Prime Minister telegraphed in reply to the effect that the<br />
Commonwealth is prepared to participate with the State on the customary<br />
dollar for dollar basis for the relief of personal hardship. When the Queens<br />
lard Government has forwarded an assessment of damage done to other assets,<br />
the Commonwealth will give prompt consideration to the question of assistance<br />
to the State to help in financing the restoration of those assets.<br />
Referring to suggestions that had been made in some quarters<br />
that the Commonwealth Government had acted promptly to assist in<br />
rehabilitation of the bushfire devastated area in Tasmania but had remained<br />
silent about the Queensland floods, Mr. McEwen emphasised that the Commonwealth<br />
does not enter into this field of State administration unless it is asked<br />
to do so by the Premier of the State. The help which the Commonwealth gave<br />
to Tasmania followed the request from the Premier of that State. When the<br />
assessment by the Queensland Government of the damage done by the<br />
Queensland floods has been received, the Commonwealth Government will<br />
give it the same quick consideration that it did in respect of the request<br />
which it received from Tasmania.<br />
CANBERRA, 29th March, 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
