<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8779</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J. KEATING, MP DOORSTOP, BOTANIC GARDENS, ADELAIDE, 21 DECEMBER 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/12/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008779.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PR"% ME MINISTER. 711EE HON P. J. KEATING, MOP<br />
DOORSTOP, BOTANIC GARDENS, ADELAIDE, 21 DECEMBER 1992<br />
E OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime AMister, the newspapers this morning have got a poll which shows that thc<br />
Coalition's Fightback Mark II seems to havc been well received. Do you believe<br />
that that poil will be sustained?<br />
PM: No, those polls are, I mean wel see what the polls say. That will take a while, a<br />
poll over the -weekend on a mautter like this is just next to worthless. We knew<br />
News limited were doing this polL we told thL-rn dial last week, that they apparently<br />
wanted a story for today. I don't think this is the one to take much notice of.<br />
J: Are you concerned that it has turned the corner a bit for the Opposition?<br />
PM: Dr Hewson, is running on a policy he doesn't believe, ti~ s is the biggest con job in<br />
Australian history. This guy was telling me, Iwo weeks ago, the stimulatoty policies<br />
were wrong. He said One Nation was a mistake and now he is trying to emulate<br />
the Government's policies. What rve said in the House is that if Australia wants<br />
stimulatory policies delivered, let the people who actually believe in them do them<br />
and thafs the Government. He is running on policies he doesn't believe, on money<br />
he doesn't have. I notice this morning he's trying to back away now from Telecom,<br />
Owa is the centre piec-e of his funding on Friday, is this morning, he's ninning back<br />
away from it. people have got to understand this about Telecom either Dr<br />
Hewson drives a competitor out, that is Optus, to lif the profitability of Telecom to<br />
sell it or he lets Telecom do the Qomrnercial thing and put in timed local phone<br />
calls. You notice in his statermt there was no talk what so ever of declines in<br />
prices or phone prices which the Governmnent has, that is, inflation minus five per<br />
cent which we have as the guidelines for Telecom charting none of dial. To makec<br />
Telecom a profitable show to sell it, you've got to let it do the totally commercial<br />
thing and the totally commercial thing is timed local phone calls. There is no way<br />
Tclcom could be floated to private institutions without it being able to charge<br />
market prices for its product and that is, timned local calls. So, Dr Iifewson today in </p>
<p>a quite startling display of back pedalling, is running off the Telecon thing which<br />
last Friday was the centre piece of his funding.<br />
J: You said One Nation is ten months old, is it time for a face lift beforc the next<br />
federal election.-<br />
PM: You say that, but look, the Liberal party has come to our policy, we haven't come<br />
to theirs. They are the ones who now say stimulator. policies, they are the ones<br />
saying One Nation was right. Remember John Hcwson said, look I took a year to<br />
put this policy together, he said this last year, he took a year to put this together, he<br />
said we thought about this, we've dotted every we've crossed every' t, what he<br />
told us last Friday was that Fightback was wrong and what was right was the One<br />
Nation policy of a stimulus and basically a policy of inclusion tbr the community.<br />
He is the one who has had to shift ground, not the Govcmcnt. So, it's not a<br />
matter of giving One Nation a facelili, One Nation is tiding on supremely as I said<br />
as an idea. The thing that has had it is old Fightback Mark I, she's in the garbage<br />
bin.<br />
J: So we can't expect any more givc-a-ways before the next before the next<br />
PM: I think it is very intcresting in Australian politics, after a decade of abstemious<br />
economics, the media of Australia arc now inviting the parties to spend their heads<br />
off.<br />
J: Would you say if* th e trends in these early polls are sustained, that makes a<br />
February election very unlikely'?<br />
PM: Why should I debate election dates with you jokers.<br />
J: Is today's cnironmental story the start of an election campaign?<br />
PM: That was there anyway, that's been there for months, after months of work and<br />
planning, this was on. We set this date three or four months ago. The thing is polls<br />
taken over Saturday after look, you don't have to be a political sciCntist to know<br />
this fact a poll taken on Saturday after a statement released on Friday is rubbish.<br />
J: Prime Minister, last wcck Senator Richardson said that although the environmental<br />
movement wasn't exactly in love with the Labor party that Labor could still depend<br />
on the votes because the alternative was even more unattractive. Is this what today<br />
is all about?.<br />
PM: No, what today is about just continuing to build on the job. The soil and water<br />
issues, the larger role on Murray Darling river system, which the Commonwealth<br />
can play because it is a trans-state national issue, is, I think, another important<br />
thing to be doing in the environment agenda. As is a lot of the measures today, to<br />
deal with feral animals, to deal with nimosa pigra, to deal with locking up some of </p>
<p>these pastoral lease areas which have been part of contiguous envirownent<br />
protection tones. Thiese are all item~ s on the agenda, the study into Shoalwater Bay,<br />
one of the last great virgin areas of the Australian east coast. Thcsw arc things<br />
which come from a party that is interested in the environment again it is the same<br />
point in terms of stimnulatory policy, the Government believes in it and delivers<br />
those policies. In terms of having a decent saiety net and including the Australian<br />
community in the policy,, the Governmient. believes it and deliver-, the policies. The<br />
same as the-envirornent, the Government delivers it and belheves the policies. The<br />
Opposition don't believe it and they% a re out there now tryin to say that the hard<br />
hearted view of last week is now all off. There was a Richard Nixon phrase. I can't<br />
remember it, it was inoperative, I think. It has all the sincerity of that sort of<br />
treatmnent and I just think the public are much too sharp for Dr Hewson, they'll sce<br />
right through him and his cynical Federal Director, NMr Robb and his poll driven<br />
research and his poll driven policies.<br />
J: Would you see any special flood relief for South Australia?<br />
PM: Thurc is a permanent Commonwealth-State regime for flood and drought relief and<br />
any problems in South Australia will come up under that regime.<br />
J: How important is South Australia in the reckoning for the next election, Will it be<br />
an important decider -for yo-u'?<br />
PM: The thing is this. Dr Howson has a South Australian policy, it's a zero tariffs, zero<br />
Adelaide policy. That's his policy. Zero L-anfi; zero Adelaide. On Friday he never<br />
shifted that policy, he stuc; k to Lzfl) tariffs for the motor vehicle industry and that<br />
will see and in mainy other areas of the manufacturing industry the largest base of<br />
South Australian employment decimated by imports. H~ e had a chance to consider<br />
his position, he took it, but didn't change.<br />
J: Melbourne's Northland College is due to be closed do you have any comment on<br />
Mr Kennett's actions there?<br />
PM: Dr Hewsons says IMr Kennelt'. s problemn policies are the cause of my problems. Mr<br />
Kennett doesn't have a OST. Mr Kennett is running on Dr Hcwson's industrial<br />
relations policy. Thle only thing is he put it into place first because he got elected.<br />
Now Dr Hewson is disparaging in rhctoric Mr Kcrneit, but still adoping,<br />
absolutely, all of his policies. The main thrust, that is to put eight million<br />
Australians onto commron law contracts. What we are seeing from D r Hcwson is<br />
no change. I Iis policy is basically this, prices up and wages down. Prices up under<br />
a consumption tax. wages down under an indi~ itrial relations policy where eight<br />
million Australians award conditions and pay are destroyed and where he pushes<br />
people onto comnion law contracts. All that Jeff Kennett had done for the rest of<br />
us is show us in action what John Ilfewson's policy had in the print and it is pretty<br />
c; ynical of himnfow to disparage Mr Kennett when he, Dr I lewson, is the author of<br />
Mr Kenniett's policy. </p>
<p>J; The Northland Clege is an AIboriginal College, the Melbourne people are pretty<br />
upset.<br />
PM: Mr Kennett is closing schools all ovur Victoria and again he's got to deal with his<br />
own community on these things. but what he has done is introduce the first leg of'<br />
John Illewson's and John Howard's Industrial relations policy and in doing that he's<br />
done in a sense some serneie to the nation in alerting Australians to what they can<br />
expect from a Hewson Governmcni because Dr Hewson again had the opportunity<br />
lWt Friday to ditch this crazy industrial relations policy. All he did was reassert it.<br />
J: Prime Minister, how confident are you that Labor will pick up green preferences at<br />
the next fecderal Clection?<br />
PM: Anyone who is genuinely interested in the environmecnt has got to look at the<br />
environmental record of the Government and its obvious, the whole Party's obvious<br />
concern and commitment to the environmncnt. Not just the Government, but the<br />
Party. And if it is a two party choice, if you left it to the likes of M~ r Reith and Dr<br />
Hewson they'd mine Hyde Park.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Standard and Poors don't seem tot) % concernedth at Coalition policies<br />
would be that negative tbr Australia's credit rating, how do you react to thar.<br />
PM: And we are not too concerned about what they think.<br />
J: But they have just reaffirmed the..<br />
PM: In political terms, what's that matter.<br />
Premier Arnold ha.-asked you to break the nexus between Commonwcalth public<br />
servants and politicians pay, have you considered that yet?<br />
PM: Understand ths, there's nothing about the I iherals, you see them when they are<br />
unfetteredA, at their natural worst. Thu night that Nkfr Kennett was putting through<br />
the cuts to peoples pay, he was putting through a wage increase for State ministers.<br />
And of course would be, they think, horn to rule squad think the world could never<br />
pay them enough. " o in a totalty phoney display of contrition for this, Dr I lewson<br />
said on Friday, yes he'd cut Ml's' pay back. Ml's' pays have been caught up under<br />
a now long standing series of arrangements where they are treated the sa1me<br />
basically as members of the public service, he knows that.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
