<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4333</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/02/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004333.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 27 FEBRUARY 1977<br />
EMBARGO: APPROX: 7.00 p. m.<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
The rate of inflation in Australia came under scrutiny in the<br />
Federal Parliament during last week, following release of the<br />
December quarter Consumer Price Index.<br />
One clear and irrefutable fact emerged the underlying rate of<br />
inflation in Australia has shown a sustained and measurable<br />
decline. The facts show that we have been getting on top of<br />
inflation. They show that our policies of government spending<br />
restraint and the transfer of resources to private industry are<br />
the right policies.<br />
For the 12 months of 1976 the Consumer Price Index excluding<br />
Medibank was 10.8 percent. This was the lowest increase for<br />
four years and 50 percent lower than the 1975 figure.<br />
The statisticians figure for the December quarter increase in the<br />
C. P. I. was 6 percent. However, as Australians know this figure<br />
included 3.2 percent for the cost of the Medibank levy and<br />
othEr health costs.<br />
For the quarter there was an underlying increase in the price<br />
of a nominated range of goods and services by 2.8 percent.<br />
Although inflation in Australia is significantly less than it was<br />
12 maonths ago, it is still far too high. It is for this reason<br />
that: the decisions coming from this week's national wage case<br />
wil L be critical in our fight against inflation. The Government<br />
will be presenting a strong and detailed argument for t: he<br />
max: LMUlf possible restraint in wage increases.<br />
The main cause of inflation in Australia over recent years, for<br />
which we are still paying, was excessive wage and salary demands.<br />
Aus-: ralians know that wages have gone up dramatically in the past<br />
few years. We also now know that the extra money that fills pay<br />
packets has not enabled people to buy more goods and services.<br />
Normally, wage increases can be responsibly financed by increases in<br />
productivity. A company increases its output, improves profit, and<br />
is -able to pay increased wages. Until recently, however, there has<br />
been~ very little growth. In its last year of office, Labor / 2 </p>
<p>presided over the physical decline of most of the productive<br />
output of the economy. In these circumstances wage increases<br />
had the effect of increasing inflation. This in turn lead<br />
to cutbacks in business activities at the expense of jobs.<br />
I have said before as have people like Mr Crean and Mr Whitlam,<br />
that one man's pay increase in another man's job. That is still<br />
the rule.<br />
Today many Australian companies are returning to profit. They are<br />
starting to compete more aggressively in the marketplace. They<br />
are planning ahead with renewed confidence. They have faith in<br />
this nation' s capacity to recovery from economic depression.<br />
But this new spirit, and new optimism which is being translated into<br />
positive investment decisions, will be destroyed if these companies<br />
are forced to feed large parts of their profit back into paying<br />
excessive wage increases.<br />
These companies now have the opportunity to put profits back where<br />
they belong and that is, back in the business. They can put<br />
profit into new plant, new processes, and expansion programmes<br />
which in turn will lead to greater production and more jobs.<br />
It is only in these circumstances that the great producers and<br />
employers of labour will be able to grant wage increases without<br />
destroying their business.<br />
Until then, the employer the man who takes risk with his<br />
capital must be given a fair go at recovering his profit<br />
and using it to put back into his business. It is for this<br />
reason that the need for wage restraint at this time is utterly<br />
critical. It will remain crucial for quite some period.<br />
The Treasurer and Minister for Employment and Industrial Relations<br />
have already told Parliament that the Federal Government will be<br />
pressing the need for the maximum possible restraint in awarding<br />
any wage increases before the Commission.<br />
In this regard, it was interesting to note Mr Hawke's comment that<br />
the ACTU would be pressing for a full 6 percent flow on of the<br />
C. P. I. into wages. His call for the full flow on is utterly.<br />
irresponsible. It is not a call that would be supported by the<br />
unionists he purports to represent.<br />
Mr Hawke's pleas for the full flow on amount to nothing less than<br />
a call for higher inflation, higher and continually increasing<br />
unemployment and a shattering of business confidence.<br />
His public statements will not distract the Government from acting<br />
in the national interest.<br />
Australia today is growing stronger. We have made a good start<br />
in our economic recovery. It is imperative that the gains we<br />
have made are not frittered away or destroyed.<br />
000000000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
