<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9745</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP AT THE MCARTHUR RIVER MINE, NORTHERN TERRITORY, 6 SEPTEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009745.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
r ( 9<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP AT THE McARTHUR RIVER MINE, NORTHERN TERRITORY, 6<br />
SEPTEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Mr Keating, what will the Australian Government be saying to the<br />
French Ambassador regarding the test?<br />
PM: We will be saying that we are outraged by the fact the French have<br />
decided to detonate this bomb, that this is a mindless decision, that it is<br />
unnecessary, that the risks for everybody is the proliferation risk, the<br />
risk for France is not that it doesn't have a comptent weapon, but rather<br />
that other non-nuclear states develop weapons. We have already<br />
undertaken a series of sanctions, the strongest by Australia against any<br />
other democracy. We have cancelled defence contracts, we have<br />
withdrawn our Ambassador, we have protested directly to the French<br />
Government, we are taking the matter to the United Nations. Australia<br />
has led the opposition to France in the world. This has made a<br />
difference I think to the French opinion at home. It has certainly made a<br />
difference to European opinion and it is this pressure which, I think,<br />
President Chirac is now feeling.<br />
J: Do you think the French Government really cares that Australia is<br />
outraged?<br />
PM: It cares and it is understood that, I think, we have hurt them in doing<br />
this. But understand, this is against the Government of France, not the<br />
people of France. It is not their decision, it is President Chiracs<br />
decision and we have made it clear to President Chirac and his<br />
Government as I think we are changing opinion in Europe too that<br />
other European states, whose opinions they care about mightily, are<br />
now making their views felt, such as in the European Parliament and<br />
other places.<br />
J: Will you expel the French Ambassador, Mr Keating? </p>
<p>PM: No, we want the contact to be able to register, to keep the linkages.<br />
That is what you do in these things. You express your anger, your<br />
outrage, but you try and get a better outcome.<br />
J: Mr Keating, what is the possibility of extra uranium sales confirmed?<br />
PM: Well uranium sales to France are not an issue in this, they are not an<br />
issue in this anymore than sales of other things to France are by<br />
Australia.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you think the French now may reduce the number of<br />
tests, or do you think this is going to..<br />
PM: They may do under the weight of international pressure, but I am very<br />
pleased about the fact that Australia has led that. That we have made<br />
the difference in what, I think, the French Government thought was an<br />
easy decision to take.<br />
J: You have taken a lot of action until now, is there anymore you can<br />
take?<br />
PM: Well they are fairly strong actions we have cancelled defence<br />
contracts, at the time we withdraw our Ambassador, we have led<br />
delegations there and Minister Bilney will be leading another one<br />
shortly to continue the campaign that we have waged to date.<br />
J: Tim Fischer says that the Federal Government reaction hasn't been<br />
strong enough, that you should expel the French Ambassador.<br />
PM: Well it has been so strong as to affect French public opinion and I think<br />
affect the view of the French Presidency. That is pretty strong.<br />
J: But it hasn't been strong enough to stop them testing. They didn't even<br />
delay their start?<br />
PM: Well they are a democracy and they can make their own decisions.<br />
Mururoa is not part of Australia, it is a French territory. But I think<br />
because it is a democracy, we are more outraged. If this was a<br />
totalitarian regime, you could perhaps understand how public opinion<br />
and international opinion has been bypassed, but what really gets up<br />
our nose is that this is a democracy and it is a democracy we have<br />
fought for.<br />
J: Mr Keating, can you tell me your thoughts this morning when you heard<br />
the bomb had been detonated?<br />
PM: Well one of anger and one of extreme disappointment about the fact<br />
that France does not understand that the real risk for the world is for<br />
smaller states to acquire nuclear weapons and that they have a vested<br />
interest, as we all have, in stopping that happen.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
