<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1698</transcript-id>
    <title>DROUGHT RELIEF VICTORIA AND SOUTH AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/10/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001698.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 27 OCT1961<br />
L P. M. No. 110/ 1967.<br />
DROUGHT RELIEF VICTORIA AND SOUTH AUSTRALIA<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
On Monday last discussions were held between officials from<br />
the Commonwealth and States of Victoria and South Australia about<br />
ways in which the Commonwealth might help the two States provide<br />
relief in those areas at present suffering from drought. I had<br />
already indicated the Commonwealth Government's willingness to<br />
provide such assistance and the purpose of these talks was to<br />
examine the specific measures proposed by the two States for<br />
drought relief.<br />
The Commonwealth's general policy towards natural disaster<br />
relief is that where State Governments, which have the primary<br />
responsibility in this area, do not have sufficient financial<br />
resources to provide the assistance required, the Commonwealth<br />
is prepared to help meet the cost of such relief measures as<br />
appear to be appropriate in the circumstances. Thus where the<br />
disaster is on a large scale, as was the case in the droughts<br />
in New South Wales and Queensland and the bush fires in Tasmania,<br />
we are prepared to assist State Governments in financing such<br />
expenditures. Over the past two years the Commonwealth has<br />
provided .43 million in assistance to reimburse State for<br />
expenditure incurred in providing relief from the effects of<br />
natural disasters.<br />
As regards the request made by the Governments of Victoria<br />
and South Australia, the Commonwealth Government has agreed to<br />
meet the total cost of the specific measures which the two States<br />
consider to be necessary at this stage, and to make an immediate initial<br />
advance of P'l million to each State. These measures are as<br />
follows:-loans to enable primary producers to continue in<br />
production where cred. it is not available through<br />
normal commercial channels;<br />
rebates on freight in respect of the transport of<br />
fodder and water to drought-affected areas, the<br />
transport of starving stock out of drought areas<br />
and their subsequent return;<br />
some miscellaneous items of expenditure in relation<br />
to the drought, which may include cloud seeding and<br />
certain emergency water supply measures.<br />
The Commonwealth will give sy7mpathetic consideration to<br />
extending the present ariangements as necessary.<br />
The present arrangements will apply to expenditure on drought<br />
relief incurred by the two States from 1st October 1967. It has<br />
also been agred that the arrangements will be examined before the<br />
end of the 1967/ 68 financial year so as to determine what<br />
arrangements should apply for 1968/ 69. Assistance to the States<br />
will take the form of loans wheie the States themselves make<br />
loans; assistance in respect of other expenditure will take the<br />
form of grants.<br />
It is not possible to say at this stage what the expenditure<br />
of the two States on relief measures will be in 1967/ 68, but<br />
estimates have been mentioned of the order of a total of<br />
million. CADTBERRA October, 1967. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
