<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9772</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, &quot;7.30 REPORT&quot;, ABC TV, 28 SEPTEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009772.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, " 7.30 REPORT', ABC TV,<br />
28 SEPTEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
UNDER EMBARGO UNTIL 7.30 PM<br />
J: Prime Minister, welcome to the program.<br />
PM: Good, Paul.<br />
J: Surely many Sydneysiders would agree with John Howard's<br />
suggestion that the aircraft noise should be shared more fairly by<br />
greater use of the east-west runway.<br />
PM: Opening the east-west runway will just make Mascot inherently unsafe<br />
and it will basically add another 100,000 people to the noise level.<br />
J: Unsafe because of the intersecting runways?<br />
PM: Because of the intersection of the flight paths.<br />
J: But there were intersecting runways there for a long time.<br />
PM: But not two runways. They are now intersecting two runways. At one<br />
stage, until this runway was built, they intersected only one runway.<br />
In fact John Howard has this to say about building the runway. This is<br />
a press release of his from 1989. ' The Government is playing<br />
carelessly with a situation that could too easily result in a major<br />
tragedy. The risk must be averted. In the interests of safety, airport<br />
facilities should be upgraded immediately including construction of the<br />
third runway." I mean he hasn't got a leg to stand on. What has<br />
happened, Paul, here is he has had a little bit of pressure from his own<br />
electorate. He holds this seat of Bennelong, he has held it for<br />
years. He is out there telling us he is the champion of </p>
<p>micro-economic reform. The largest micro change of the air traffic<br />
system of Australia, was the third runway in Sydney. He is now saying<br />
" cut its capacity dramatically by putting a cross-wind runway across it."<br />
J: But all politicians respond to electorate pressure. I mean Bob Hawke<br />
did it to you in the Tax Summit, didn't he? A bit of pressure from<br />
Bill Kelty and your cart ran off the road.<br />
PM: But the Government didn't respond to the pressure when it made the<br />
decision to build the runway and it did build the runway. You see<br />
John Howard is saying, " Elect me, Prime Minister of Australia. I will do<br />
the hard things in the micro-economy." He said recently, " The greatest<br />
priority that faces the Government at the present time is the national<br />
economic interest to reignite the process of micro-economic reform."<br />
The biggest micro-economic reform in aviation, is the third runway at<br />
Mascot. It is the thing that let's the whole national system flow. It is<br />
the gateway to Australia. He is saying, " You elect me Prime Minister<br />
because Labor can't take the fight any further on waterfront, on the<br />
shipping, in the airports, in the labour market. I will clean up and do<br />
the hard bits." The first whiff of grapeshot, the first bit of pressure from<br />
a seat he has held for 20 years, and he goes to water. He runs away<br />
from statements he has made, absolutely categorical statements in<br />
favour of building this thing.<br />
J: But you say he is sort of shutting it down, or you imply he is almost<br />
destroying the third runway. He is just saying, " Hang on for a few<br />
months. Deal with the noise problem."<br />
PM: No, he is not saying that at all. If we run an east-west runway now<br />
across the two intersecting flight paths, it would be inherently unsafe.<br />
Therefore, to try to make it safe you would have to drop the capacity<br />
back enormously and you would never make it safe. That is what he is<br />
saying. Secondly, he is saying, " If you don't do it, I will knock $ 2 billion<br />
out of the Budget from the asset sales. I will refuse the passage of the<br />
asset sales legislation in the Senate." This is the same person who is<br />
telling us we should have bigger surpluses. You see the thing about<br />
him is he can't take any pressure. He was like it when he was<br />
Treasurer, he was like it when he was Opposition Leader in the<br />
The first bit of weight goes on and he snaps.<br />
J: But he is over 9 points ahead in the polls, he can't be doing everything<br />
wrong?<br />
PM: And he is weak and sneaky to go with it, Paul.<br />
J: But the people<br />
PM: He is weak because he always caves in on the big ones. You know<br />
what we call him in the Parliament gunna Howard. He was gunna </p>
<p>float the exchange rate, but he didn't do it. He was gunna deregulate<br />
the financial markets, but he didn't do it. He was gunna knock the tariff<br />
wall over, but he didn't do it. He was going to fix the ports and<br />
wharves, but he didn't do it.<br />
J: He'd say he is going to beat you at the next election, and he will do it.<br />
PM: Well he won't. Look, do you think the public are going to say, here is a<br />
man who knows this airport should be built, who supported its building,<br />
who cajoled the Government of the day to build it and now for the<br />
weakest of political reasons he is now saying he wants to cut its<br />
capacity dramatically and not only that he will actually knock $ 2 billion<br />
out of the Budget while he is doing it.<br />
J: You said yesterday it was still your intention to stretch the Parliament<br />
out. Does that amount to " I have definitely ruled out an election before<br />
Christmas"?<br />
PM: No, because Prime Ministers with any sense don't rule anything out.<br />
J: Do you concede you would get clobbered if you went now?<br />
PM: No, I don't concede that at all. I mean the Government is about 7 to<br />
8 percentage points, two party preferred, at difference with the<br />
Coalition in the published polls.<br />
PL: And your private polling says you lose by 20 seats.<br />
PM: No it doesn't. And the moment a poll happens, people start shifting<br />
their position immediately. But I do believe the public expect that<br />
when they give a government a mandate, they expect it to go and do<br />
it. The mandate we were given, was to restore growth to the<br />
economy, and employment. We have now had 16 consecutive<br />
quarters of growth 4 straight years of growth.. We have had nearly<br />
680,000 job growth....<br />
PL: And you have got what people are calling a voteless recovery?<br />
PM: Well, I don't... let's wait and see. I mean, what will they do? Take an<br />
outfit that has got no policies, that has no strategy for dealing with<br />
wages?<br />
PL: Well, the election is a way off yet he can out his policies, can't he?<br />
PM: that's got other than cutting wages, which is his only policy that<br />
on the micro-changes which will keep the efficiency of Australia<br />
going, at the first test he fails it. </p>
<p>PL: Can you show me a piece of paper where John Howard says his plan<br />
is to cut wages?<br />
PM: Yes. I can show you a piece of paper which says that they will go to<br />
individual employment contracts, and they will not have the Labor<br />
Party's this Government's no-disadvantage test. That means that<br />
penalty rates, holiday leave loading, overtime....<br />
PL: But Peter Reith recently said that they would keep the nodisadvantage<br />
tests.<br />
PM: No. He said a no-disadvantage test not the no-disadvantage test.<br />
PL: Well, until you discover what their components are, you can't...<br />
PM: No, no, no. What he says is this if you want to take away... we say<br />
this, if you want to have an enterprise bargain, and remove overtime,<br />
holiday leave loadings and penalty rates, you can do it provided that<br />
the overall package leaves the working person no worse off. In other<br />
words, you can get the flexibility, but they have to be either no worse<br />
off, or advantaged. What they would do is just simply let them lose it,<br />
as the Western Australian legislation makes clear which Mr Howard<br />
has endorsed.<br />
PL: But until you see their policies, many voters are going to say here's<br />
Paul Keating with the old scare campaign again.<br />
PM: No, no, forget about the policies have a look at this week. Here he<br />
is this week, he is going to try and knock.... has he been saying we<br />
should have a bigger budget surplus? Why then, is he going to try<br />
and punch a $ 2 billion hole in it by refusing the sale of the airports in<br />
the Senate? Hasn't he said for years that we should have built a third<br />
runway in Sydney to improve the micro-economic efficiency of the<br />
East Coast air traffic system? He has why now is he trying to stifle<br />
it? I mean, the fact is he represents nothing.<br />
PL: Talking of representation, was Jennie George right when she said<br />
yesterday that in the lead-up to the election, the ALP could not forget<br />
that it was in power purely to represent the interests of workers?<br />
PM: It's in power to advance the national interest, which is best advanced<br />
through growth and employment. And whenever that happens,<br />
working Australians always get a piece of the action the biggest<br />
piece of the action and the place is more cohesive, and better. I<br />
think that's what she means, and that's what we mean.<br />
PL: And given that you have so many marginals that you are holding by<br />
such a slim margin, and the Opposition only needs to win 9 to take </p>
<p>Government, how can you possibly be seen now as having any real<br />
prospects of victory?<br />
PM: Oh, well, I mean, that's a pretty dull question, Paul, from a smart<br />
character like you.<br />
PL: Well, how can you?<br />
PM: You know that all these elections are won by the last half a<br />
percentage point they have been won by the last half a percentage<br />
point since Federation. I mean, they are all to get 50% plus 1 the<br />
hard bit is getting the 49.5% first to put the last half a percent on.<br />
PL: Yeah, but you are so far behind from that?<br />
PM; No, we are not. Look, the thing is that the Government has done the<br />
things that it was asked to do at the last poll. I stood up there at that<br />
policy speech in Bankstown, and I said we will restore growth and<br />
employment to the economy, we won't leave the unemployed behind.<br />
And we have done exactly that. And look what has happened since<br />
Mabo, APEC, the structure for the republic, Working Nation for the<br />
long-term unemployed...<br />
PL: But you have been very frustrated that there has not been any real<br />
appreciation of these efforts?<br />
PM: Well, I don't think that pollsters I have always said to you it takes a<br />
politician to read the hieroglyphics of the polls. I mean, you have got<br />
to understand what people are saying behind them, what they think.<br />
And also, I think, the public are smart enough now, they know they<br />
can always give the Government-a needle through the polls, just the<br />
same as a by-election. But it is a wholly different matter in the old<br />
ballot box on election day.<br />
PL: Thanks for your time.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
