<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6035</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA NEEDS SOME ANSWERS FROM MR HAWKE</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/02/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006035.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
POR HBDI ** 25 FEERUAY 1983-<br />
AUSTRAIA NBEEDS SOME ANSWERS FROM MR HAWKE<br />
Auatralians have a right to some answers from Mr Hawke.<br />
If Australians are to make a proper judgment about issues inthis<br />
election, they will need better than the waffle, evasion<br />
and side-stepping that we get everyday from the man who seeks<br />
to olaim the mantle of Government.<br />
He has refused to answer questions about the detail on the<br />
cost of his promises.<br />
He ducks and evades a whole range of matters relating to his<br />
Prices and Incomes Policy. He won't say who will determine<br />
profit levels and acceptable levels of income for the<br />
self-employed.<br />
He is imprecise about how he will u8e capital gains tax. Re<br />
hasn't said what additional transactions will be taxed to<br />
ensure what he calls " effective application of the existing<br />
capital gains tax". Or is he saying that the Tax Commissioner<br />
is not applying the existing law honestly and diligently?<br />
On uranium, Mr Bawke is as imprecise and evasive as ever. He<br />
contradicts his Deputy and his uranium spokesman and pretends<br />
that the question of uranium development in South Australia<br />
still has to be looked at yet in the end it is dragged from<br />
him that well, yes, he would have to implement ALP policy.<br />
It is time that Mr Hawke gave some clear and precise answers<br />
to important policy q-uestions. He is no longer on the stage.<br />
He is seeking the Prime Ministership. -oOo-</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
