<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9538</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, BOURKE, WEDNESDAY, 5 APRIL 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/04/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009538.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
C:<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, BOURKE, WEDNESDAY, 5 APRIL 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PMV: Well, I have just had a meeting with the farm community here and we<br />
have just been talking about the problems of drought and drought<br />
protection for the future, problems about water storage and how areas<br />
like the western region here and NSW can survive drought into the<br />
future. We discussed some of the measures the Commonwealth has<br />
already introduced, some things that we might change and they are<br />
going to give me a submission about that. But, I am happy to take<br />
questions by and large.<br />
J: You said this morning that you wanted to take the ' spirit of Fred<br />
Hollows', of getting things done, to Aboriginal health. Can Carmen<br />
Lawrence do that in control of the Department of Health?<br />
PMV: I think that we spend $ 34 billion a year on health and the important<br />
thing is to let the Aboriginal community into those big programs. I think<br />
also the Commonwealth Department of Health has the possibility of<br />
being able to deal with the State health departments to try to get some<br />
of these services delivered. Anyway these are matters the<br />
Government is currently reviewing.<br />
J: You said you didn't want to interfere in the super league, but doesn't<br />
the Government have a role in ensuring that the best football is free to<br />
air?<br />
PMV: The Government has got a thing called anti-syphoning rules, so that<br />
the public are able to watch all the things that they currently see the<br />
Winfield Cup is part of that and it is subject to it but this is not really a<br />
matter for the Government. It is a matter for the courts, it is I think, a<br />
matter for the rugby league and News Limited and the courts and we<br />
will see what happens. We are seeing, obviously, a change in the<br />
organisation of football, but the Government has always said and has<br />
done what it said in protecting what one would term, supporters and<br />
viewers interests in terms of sport and, of course, not just football. </p>
<p>2<br />
J: So, if it got to the stage where it wasn't going to be on free to air, you<br />
could intervene?<br />
PM: It is not a matter for us. This is really a matter for, as I say, News<br />
Limited, the rugby league and the courts, I think.<br />
J: Is Senator Noel Crichton-Browne someone that you feel should be in<br />
the Senate?<br />
PM: I think the important thing about this is that other people have been<br />
saying correctly, I think, about Mr Howard that this is a test of his<br />
leadership and he put around a day or so ago that he obliged Senator<br />
Crichton-Browne to resign. In other words, ' look at me, what a strong<br />
person I am'. It turned out that it's not true. I think Senator Crichton-<br />
Browne resigned himself and notified Mr Howard. What this reveals is<br />
what we have always known about Mr Howard he is utterly indecisive<br />
and lacks strength. This was most obviously revealed when he had<br />
two representatives representing himself on the Western Australian<br />
executive and now, when faced with this sort of problem it gets<br />
resolved by the Senator resigning himself, not being obliged to by Mr<br />
Howard. This will be the same in every matter Mr Howard touches<br />
lacks decisiveness and lacks strength.<br />
J: Do you think Labor will do better in the Senate now in WA?<br />
PM: The next Federal election is quite a way off, so I'm confident that when<br />
we get past the fairy floss of polls and the rest down to the real issues<br />
the Labor party didn't win five elections on the trot for nothing. It won<br />
them because it was better. Thank you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
