<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8366</transcript-id>
    <title>CONVENTION FOR A DEMOCRATIC SOUTH AFRICA</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/12/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008366.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>0<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 13 December 1991<br />
I warmly welcome the announcement that the Convention for<br />
a Democratic South Africa ( CODESA) will be held on 20-21<br />
December in Johannesburg. CODESA will be the forum for<br />
negotiation of a new constitution for South Africa and<br />
over twenty South African political groups have agreed to<br />
attend. This is a crucial stage in the process towards a nonracial,<br />
democratic South Africa. While this process will<br />
undoubtedly be a difficult one, I am deeply heartened by<br />
the spirit of goodwill and cooperation with which parties<br />
are approaching the negotiations.<br />
The Commonwealth has been at the forefront of<br />
international efforts to end apartheid in South Africa<br />
and it is clear that its efforts have been rewarded by<br />
the progress that has been made. At Harare in October,<br />
Commonwealth Heads of Government pledged to assist the<br />
transition to a non-racial South Africa.<br />
In this spirit the Commonwealth has accepted an<br />
invitation from CODESA's Co-Chairpersons to send<br />
observers to this historic meeting. I welcome the<br />
invitation and I am pleased to announce that Sir Ninian<br />
Stephen will participate in the Commonwealth observer<br />
team. Sir Ninian will join five other eminent representatives<br />
from Commonwealth member states in observing the<br />
proceedings of the two-day inaugural session of CODESA.<br />
It is my sincere hope that CODESA will lead to the<br />
peaceful achievement of a democratic, non-racial South<br />
Africa. On behalf of the Australian Government and<br />
people, I wish the participants well in the difficult<br />
task ahead of them.<br />
386~ 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
