<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1530</transcript-id>
    <title>ASIAN TOUR 1967 - SINGAPORE DEPARTURE PRESS CONFERENCE - 29TH MARCH 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001530.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASIAN TOUR 1967 SINGAPORE<br />
DEPARTURE PRESS CONFERENCE 29TH MARCH, 1967<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know that there is anything particularly that I wanted to<br />
add to what I said yesterday. I did mention yesterday, I think,<br />
that these were four countries I had not previously visited. All<br />
of them have a significance of a special sort for Australia.<br />
Cambodia is a country with which we have a special relationship<br />
in that, although we respect the neutrality and non-alignment of<br />
Cambodia we have been able to maintain good relations to a point<br />
where we represent American interests in Cambodia and we<br />
represent Cambodian interests in South Vietnam.<br />
In Laos, there is a strategic significance for all of us who<br />
have an interest in the security and stability of this area, and<br />
I am looking forward to seeing at first hand something of the<br />
situation there and having useful talks.<br />
Then on to Taiwan. Australia has recently decided to<br />
establish an Embassy in Taiwan. We recognise the wonderful<br />
economic progress we applaud the economic progress which<br />
is being made there. There is a growing trade between our two<br />
countries and we have always made it clear that whatever future<br />
arrangement develops in relation to Mainland China this should not<br />
be reached at the expense of the 13 million people living in Taiwan.<br />
They are entitled to a separate national existence if that is<br />
the course they choose to pursue.<br />
Then South Korea, Australia has a special interest in South<br />
Korea. We were the first country, as I recall it, to declare<br />
ourselves alongside the f orces of the United States in helping to<br />
resist conMInU41t aggression in South Korea, and of course we<br />
have been associated with our allied forces in Vietnam. I last<br />
met with President Park at the Manila Conference.<br />
Q. Is there any question of an Australian pull-out from this part<br />
of the world Singapore and Malaysia?<br />
P. M. No, Australia has no plan to withdraw forces from this area<br />
and indeed, as I pointed out yesterday in relation to the British<br />
presence here, we regard the presence of these friendly forces,<br />
which we urd erstand are welcomed by Malaysia and Singapore,<br />
as contributing to stabil ty in the e. and able to add to the<br />
security and stability of the region as a whole. We have no<br />
plans to reduce our own forces.<br />
Q. Do you feel the coming British pull-out will weaken the defence<br />
situation here from the military point of view? </p>
<p>4 -2<br />
P. M. Well, I don't think that this is the British intention. They<br />
would wish to contribute to security here and, as I said yesterday,<br />
we have known all along that the forces which have been built<br />
up beyond the normal strength to meet the confrontation issue<br />
were likely to be reduced to at least the pre -confrontation level<br />
but I have no recent knowledge on this matter.<br />
Q. There has been much talk of the establishment of a British base<br />
in Darwin and elsewhere in Australia. Do you think that such a<br />
base, a British base, could successfully help to replace Singapore<br />
in the military sense?<br />
P. M. Well, we have made it clear that we would prefer to see the<br />
establishment continued in this area. We have well-appointed<br />
barracks here and the naval base itself of course is a great asset,<br />
a contribution to the joint security of this total area. But I think<br />
if I interpret the British thinking, they were disposed to move to<br />
bases in Australia only if it was found that they were not desired<br />
to remain cii in their existing baces.<br />
Q. One more question, Sir. Do you think that in the 1970' s<br />
Australia could assume the role the British have played?<br />
P. M. Well, we don't aspire to be more than a good neighbour making<br />
a contribution to peaceful progress here, helping in the resistance<br />
to aggression.<br />
We found our own forces involved in a military sense five times<br />
in the last twenty-five years in this area of the world, but they<br />
have always been involved in resistance to aggression and in a<br />
defensive capacity. And that is what we see as our continuing<br />
role in this area of the world. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
