<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9155</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP AUSTRALIA TODAY INDONESIA 94 OVERSEAS PASSANGER TERMINAL SYDNEY WEDNESDAY  16 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009155.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
AUSTRALIA TODAY INDONES IA ' 94<br />
OVERSEAS PASSENGER TERMINAL, SYDNEY<br />
WEDNESDAY 16 MARCH 1994<br />
I am very pleased to be able to launch the Australia<br />
Today Indonesia ' 94 promotion. Prime Ministers are<br />
always pleased to open things.<br />
But, for both political and national reasons, I think I<br />
am entitled to take an extra measure of pleasure today.<br />
No country is more important to Australia than Indonesia<br />
If we fail to get this relationship right, and nurture<br />
and develop it, the whole web of our foreign relations is<br />
incomplete.<br />
When I became Prime Minister, I was determined that one<br />
of my highest priorities would be to ensure that<br />
Australia's relationship with Indonesia received the<br />
attention I believed it deserved.<br />
We live adjacent to the fourth most populous country in<br />
the world.<br />
Too few Australians understand the importance of this<br />
neighbour of ours these 180 million neighbours of ours.<br />
Too few understand the riches and variety of Indonesian<br />
culture. And too few appreciate the pace of economic and social<br />
change taking place in Indonesia, where the economy has<br />
been growing in real terms at a rate of 6.7 percent a<br />
year since 1965.<br />
For too long we were inclined to see both Indonesia<br />
itself, and our relationship with Indonesia, in almost<br />
exclusively political terms.<br />
The Australian fear of Indonesia as an expansionist<br />
power, forged during the Sukarno era, persisted long<br />
after President Sukarno and his-policies had gone. </p>
<p>And Australian ignorance of Indonesia continued long<br />
after we should have known better.<br />
So I made a deliberate decision to make my first overseas<br />
visit as Prime Minister to Jakarta.<br />
And I decided to state publicly there what all<br />
Australians need to understand: that the emergence of the<br />
New Order government of President Soeharto, and the<br />
stability and prosperity which his government has brought<br />
to the sprawling archipelago to our north, was the single<br />
most beneficial strategic development to have affected<br />
Australia and its region in the past thirty years.<br />
An Indonesia mired in poverty, split by ethnic or<br />
regional tensions, and hostile to Australia, would have<br />
had incalculable consequences for this country.<br />
And not just for our security but for our economic<br />
prosperity as well.<br />
One of my aims during my visit in April 1992 was to<br />
examine ways in which our relationship could be broadened<br />
away from its concentration on political issues on<br />
which we were sometimes at odds to a much broader<br />
agenda of economic, social and cultural cooperation.<br />
I was convinced then, as I still am, that as Indonesia<br />
developed, so the complementarities between us would<br />
grow. Indonesia's economy has grown five and a half times since<br />
1966.<br />
And every year since then the income of each Indonesian<br />
has grown on average by four and a half percent.<br />
The percentage of people living below the poverty line<br />
fell from forty percent in 1976 to around seventeen<br />
percent in 1987.<br />
An economy heavily dependent on commodities, and<br />
particularly on oil, has been transformed, reformed and<br />
deregulated. The industrial sector now accounts for 23 percent of GDP,<br />
more than agriculture.<br />
There are parallels, of course, with Australia's<br />
experience over the past eleven years.<br />
Our economy, too, has been modernised and opened up to<br />
the world through financial deregulation and tariff cuts.<br />
Our exports have trebled and have grown as a percentage<br />
of our GDP from 13 percent to 20 percent. </p>
<p>Our manufacturing exports are growing rapidly and are now<br />
consistently stronger than the rural exports for which we<br />
are better known.<br />
Services exports are also becoming an increasingly<br />
important element in our trade, growing from $ 4.2 billion<br />
in 1981-82 to $ 15 billion in 1992-93.<br />
So, with these changes, we have become more efficient,<br />
productive and competitive than ever before.<br />
With these changes in Indonesia and Australia have come<br />
new opportunities for cooperation.<br />
And our two governments must foster this co-operation.<br />
I have been very pleased to discover on my two visits to<br />
Jakarta, and in meetings with Indonesian Ministers here,<br />
that President Soeharto and his senior colleagues very<br />
much share this approach.<br />
In April 1992, President Soeharto and I agreed that the<br />
establishment of an Australia-Indonesia Ministerial Forum<br />
would be one useful way of broadening our relationship.<br />
We wanted the Forum to include a range of economic<br />
Ministers who until then had not had a great deal to do<br />
with the bilateral relationship.<br />
That Forum has begun its work well, establishing working<br />
groups in a number of areas of practical importance to us<br />
such as agriculture and food co-operation.<br />
Its activities are designed to reflect and to accelerate<br />
broader movements already underway in our relationship.<br />
Here are some figures which bear this out.<br />
At more than $ 3 billion, two-way trade is nearly three<br />
times its level five years ago.<br />
Australian approved investment in Indonesia over the past<br />
five years amounts to nearly $ 700 million.<br />
Sixty percent more Indonesians were enrolled in higher<br />
education in Australia in 1993 than one year earlier.<br />
The number of Indonesian visitors to Australia almost<br />
doubled in two years to 1993.<br />
So my simple proposition is this: no relationship<br />
Australia has offers greater potential, on the social,<br />
the cultural or the economic fronts, than this one with<br />
Indonesia. I happen to think that this holds true for Indonesia as<br />
well, although that is something Indonesia will have to<br />
decide. </p>
<p>But having said that, potential is just that<br />
potential. Despite encouraging figures such as those I have given,<br />
we should not fool ourselves that there is anything<br />
inevitable about the trend at work here.<br />
For example, our bilateral trade grew by only 1.5 percent<br />
during 1993. This was the lowest increase in several<br />
years. And although there are several particular reasons<br />
for this, it is not a good enough result.<br />
If the relationship is to live up to its potential,<br />
effort will be required from the whole range of people in<br />
our communities.<br />
But, we can certainly do much more in the economic area.<br />
To take just one example, we hope to sign shortly an<br />
agreement with Indonesia which will facilitate increased<br />
co-operation in science and technology.<br />
And in the area of language, all Australian Governments<br />
are putting their money where their mouths are with the<br />
recent decision by the Council of Australian Governments<br />
to endorse a new national strategy for Asian languages<br />
and culture which will greatly increase the number of<br />
Australian students learning four key Asian languages,<br />
including Indonesian.<br />
There are other areas worth our attention, too.<br />
Changes in Australia and Indonesia and in the world<br />
around us since the end of the Cold War should compel us<br />
to take a fresh look at our strategic relationship.<br />
I believe great potential exists for further defence cooperation<br />
between Australia and Indonesia.<br />
The Government's recent strategic review proposed the<br />
concept of a strategic partnership with the countries of<br />
our region.<br />
If we are to turn into reality our policy of seeking<br />
defence in and with Asia, instead of against Asia,<br />
Indonesia is the most important place it will have to be<br />
done. Already we share many strategic interests. We have no<br />
conflicting interests in this part of the world, and<br />
there is a great complementarity in our respective<br />
defence postures.<br />
And despite the differences in the structure and<br />
functions of our defence forces, new areas of practical<br />
co-operation are opening up to us. </p>
<p>On the political front, we are working together very well<br />
in regional organisations such as the ASEAN post-<br />
Ministerial consultations and we will co-operate closely<br />
in the new ASEAN Regional Forum.<br />
We have also worked together effectively on particular<br />
issues such as Cambodia and regional chemical weapons<br />
arms control and, of course, in APEC.<br />
President Soeharto and I have spoken on several<br />
occasions about APEC. We both see the great potential<br />
the organisation offers for keeping up the momentum of<br />
growth across the whole Asia Pacific region.<br />
And each of us is conscious of the opportunities APEC<br />
offers to ASEAN and the developing countries of the<br />
region, as well as the developed ones.<br />
Indonesia is the Chair of APEC this year, in addition to<br />
its chairmanship of the non-aligned movement. This is a<br />
real tribute to Indonesia's standing in the world.<br />
In my view the APEC Leaders' meeting in Jakarta in<br />
November will be a decisive moment for APEC and the<br />
region. I have offered President Soeharto any help that<br />
Australia can usefully provide.<br />
But despite the bright prospects in areas like these, it<br />
would be foolish to claim that the road ahead will always<br />
be smooth.<br />
I do not doubt that Australia's relationship with<br />
Indonesia will encounter problems from time to time.<br />
We are different people with different cultures and<br />
different views on issues which matter to us.<br />
The management of those differences is part of the<br />
challenge. We will always want to be able to talk<br />
frankly and directly about them. But it is the way in<br />
which we come to grips with them which can give the<br />
relationship its particular value.<br />
Some years ago people in both Australia and Indonesia<br />
liked to refer to the idea that good fences make good<br />
neighbours; that good relations were a matter of keeping<br />
the palings in repair. In my view, the need for such<br />
defensive thinking is well past. As both countries<br />
change, we should and can approach our relationship with<br />
much greater confidence.<br />
I believe that Australia can establish with Indonesia a<br />
partnership which can stand as a model for co-operation<br />
between developed and developing countries, between<br />
countries based on western structures and values and<br />
those based on Asian models. </p>
<p>The task will not be easy. It will require more energy<br />
and commitment; warm hearts and, when required, cool<br />
heads. If a relationship of the sort we want is to endure, we<br />
have to look beyond mutual economic interests and to<br />
establish a deeper understanding.<br />
There is no doubt that work is required on both sides.<br />
We need be in no doubt that Australians' lack of<br />
knowledge about Indonesia is matched by misconceptions in<br />
Indonesia about Australia.<br />
A recent survey commissioned by the Australian Government<br />
found that almost two-thirds of Indonesians believe that<br />
the White Australia policy is still practised. Fewer than<br />
one in five Indonesians see Australia as a modern society<br />
or an advanced country. Australia is perceived to have<br />
relatively low expertise in defence, shipping, aerospace,<br />
mining and manufacturing.<br />
There are other more positive aspects to the survey<br />
findings. But it shows how far we have to go.<br />
This is one reason why the Australian Government is<br />
putting this effort into the Australia Today Indonesia<br />
' 94 promotion.<br />
Australia Today will be a showcase in Indonesia for<br />
Australia's achievements in a whole range of areas from<br />
trade and technology to the arts and tourism.<br />
It will be the most comprehensive promotion that<br />
Australia has ever undertaken abroad, and with the<br />
highest level of participation. More than 500 Australian<br />
organisation represented by at least 1500 individuals,<br />
will take part.<br />
When I visited President Soeharto last October, I was<br />
pleased to receive his support for the promotion.<br />
I am also delighted that the patron of the event will be<br />
the Indonesian Co-ordinating Minister for Trade and<br />
Industry, Mr Hartarto, who knows Australia and<br />
Australians well.<br />
I should particularly note the contribution of some of<br />
the corporate sponsors of the promotion.<br />
New Hope Corporation<br />
Austindo Group<br />
Krakatau Steel<br />
BHP<br />
. CRA </p>
<p>* Coca Cola Amatil<br />
* Price Waterhouse<br />
* ANZ Banking Group<br />
* Commonwealth Bank of Australia<br />
* Blake Dawson Waldron<br />
* Southcorp Wines<br />
* Australian Meat and Livestock Corporation<br />
* TNT Express Worldwide ( Australia)<br />
These are all far-sighted companies. They all have a bit<br />
of vision about them. They understand the potential I<br />
have talked about today.<br />
Several of my Cabinet colleagues will attend Australia<br />
Today events, and the Minister for Trade, Senator<br />
McMullan, will lead a trade mission of business leaders.<br />
The ' Visions for the Future' exhibition will provide a<br />
showcase for Australian science and technology that will<br />
last beyond this promotion and will help sell the message<br />
of Australian achievements in other parts of the world as<br />
well. All Australian states will be represented in this<br />
promotion. In particular, the Queensland and the Western<br />
Australian state governments will have programs in<br />
Semarang and Surabaya respectively, to celebrate their<br />
flourishing sister-state relationships with the<br />
Indonesian provinces of East Java and Central Java.<br />
The cultural program we are putting on will give<br />
Indonesians a taste of the best we have to offer in the<br />
arts, entertainment and sport everything from<br />
exhibitions of art including Aboriginal art the West<br />
Australian Ballet, the Tasmanian Symphony Orchestra,<br />
theatre and music.<br />
Elite national teams in soccer, volley ball and badminton<br />
will meet their Indonesian counterparts.<br />
Several top Australian sports coaches will work with<br />
Indonesian sports people a good beginning to the kind<br />
of cooperation which might be possible in the lead-up to<br />
the 2000 Olympic Games in Sydney.<br />
' Australia Today Indonesia' will go some way towards<br />
letting Indonesians know about the achievements of the<br />
continent to their south. At the same time it will<br />
expose large numbers of Australians for the first time to<br />
modern Indonesia. </p>
<p>It should go a long way towards creating a better<br />
cultural understanding and, thereby, a better culture<br />
for business and trade.<br />
When this promotion is over, the challenge will remain.<br />
But it will be one we should welcome.<br />
It is in every sense an historic challenge. The chance<br />
to set up for the twenty first century a strong, dynamic<br />
enduring relationship between Australia and<br />
Indonesia. An immensely profitable and creative<br />
relationship between ourselves and the 180 million people<br />
to our north.<br />
Without doubt, there is no more exciting and potentially<br />
rewarding challenge facing us between now and the end of<br />
this century.<br />
That a prominent business group like the Institute of<br />
Company Directors has associated itself with this event<br />
is yet another welcome sign of the growing willingness of<br />
the Australian business community to get engaged with<br />
Asia. I congratulate them, and everyone else associated with<br />
the project and now take great pleasure in launching<br />
it. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
