<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1886</transcript-id>
    <title>DJAKARTA SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON, AT A DINNER IN HONOUR PRESIDENT SUHARTO  14 JUNE 1968</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/06/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001886.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
V IS 1T TO SOUTH EA ST ASI1A 1968<br />
DJAKARTA<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON,<br />
AT A DINNER IN HONOUR OF PRESIDENT SUHARTO 14 JUNE 1968<br />
Mr. President, Your Excellencies, Ladies and Gentlemen:-<br />
It would, for any Australian Prime Minister, at any time, be a<br />
special privilege to be a host to the President of the Republic of Indonesia. But<br />
on this occasion there is perhaps a doubly special pleasure because quite soon,<br />
I think perhaps tomorrow, you begin a series of fairs and carnivals in Djakarta<br />
to celebrate the 44 1st anniversary of the foundation of this city. It is therefore<br />
doubly pleasant that I should have quite inadvertently so timed this visit that it<br />
coincides with this celebration.<br />
It is perhaps salutary to someone from Australia to consider this<br />
Wand to consider that this city, in which we are tonight, was founded 250 years<br />
0before the nation which I represent was founded in my country. This long stretch<br />
of history behind you was reinforced to me last night by the cultural exhibition<br />
Swhich you so kindly presented and which was from the various parts of this<br />
Vgreat archipelago. You showed dances stretching back three, four, five hundred<br />
years and which we for our part cannot match. Our own national existence has<br />
been shorter than has been the existence of this city though we do draw from<br />
centuries past, a culture from Great Britdin that we must turn and will turn to<br />
our own ends as people from other nations come and make a new nation in<br />
Australia'. But it is a double privilege to have you as the guest of honour,<br />
for we in Australia have a keen awareness of the leadership which you are giving<br />
Sto this nation in difficult times; a keen awareness of the problems which you<br />
Wwith courage and imagination are seeking in these times to overcome. We wish<br />
you all success in these endeavours, not only for your own sake but for our own<br />
sake too and for those of other neighbouring countries. For if you achieve success<br />
in the task which you have set yourself, then our future will be the easier, so<br />
will the future of other neighbouring countries: so will the future of the region<br />
as a whole. In this great and difficult task which you have before you we will,<br />
as far as our nation is concerned, be helpful as far as we are able, considering<br />
the commitments at home and abroad which we have.<br />
Sir, what we can do will depend on many factors, but I do assure<br />
you that we will try as a nation to play that part in helping to fulfil the dreams<br />
you have for -the future of your nation and the dreams we have for the future of<br />
the whole of the region to which we are contiguous, of which perhaps ultimately<br />
we will be an important part. Sir, you will know that just recently we have<br />
taken a decision in Australia to double next year the amount of aid which last<br />
year we provided to Indonesia and it is a matter of special pride that this was<br />
one of the first decisions made by the Australian Government since I became<br />
Prime Minister of my country. But that is, in the context of the problems<br />
facing you, a small contribution. We will, besides that, stand behind you in<br />
the councils of the world to seek to see that other greater countries, not<br />
contributing more per head perhaps, but contributing more in total, enjoin<br />
with you and ourselves in the goal you have set.<br />
We are glad to have large numbers of your students studying in<br />
our country, and we hope that when they return, as they do return, to their<br />
homeland, the result of their studies will be shown in technological progress,<br />
in administrative progress, in the general assistance to you in your governmental<br />
activities which through such training we hope to give. / 2 </p>
<p>.39<br />
00 0 </p>
<p>And you will know that, regarding investment in this country, the<br />
first main conference in Indonesia of private firms and private individuals took<br />
place in August of last year and had, as its origin in Australia, a large number<br />
of Australia's leading businessmen and industrialists who came to Djakarta at<br />
that time to participate and who, as regards many of them, have pursued their<br />
interests since then. In some cases, in turn, investment will follow. In other<br />
cases, investment might not follow but technical assistance, technological<br />
assistance, will be there for the asking and we feel that it is possible that in the<br />
context of the Indonesian economy, the technical assistance which we can provide<br />
may be, and I say only may be, more significant and more appropriate than the<br />
technical assistance of some greater complexes of some greater countries,<br />
because it may be that at our stage of development, and at your stage of.<br />
development, this technical assistance will be better than it might be from some<br />
mighty complex of a power country.<br />
But this iimportant as it is, must go side by side with agricultural<br />
Simprovements which I know is close to your hearts. Is it impossible to increase<br />
Vfood production in Indonesia? If it is possible to double the production per hectare<br />
of land, for example, of rice, then that must be a basic requirement for future<br />
progress in any direction because the production of food in sufficient quantities,<br />
to ensure that food is sold without an increase in price must be the basis on which<br />
all other building takes place and we would be interested, Sir, in seeking to try<br />
and play a part in that should you regard that as a large priority in the many other<br />
activities in which you are engaged.<br />
I do not wish to traverse the whole field of co-operation between<br />
our two nations. I think we have made some advance in the cultural agreement<br />
signed between our two countries: one which provides for exchange of scientific<br />
knowledge for bringing closer together the academics in our country and in yours:<br />
for bringing to our own nation those cultural heritages which you have: for<br />
Sbringing for the Indonesian people that which we can do to entertain them. These<br />
Vmust, in the long run, build up to a better understanding between our two peoples<br />
and indeed, Sir, it is my belief that the signing of such an agreement will give<br />
added impetus to an interest already evident but not as evident as it should be<br />
in Australia to the studying of Indonesian language, of Indonesian history, of<br />
Indonesian culture, and this I believe will take place in our country in the future.<br />
That step has been a part of the past between Indonesia and<br />
Australia that I think is a part of the vision of the future between Indonesia and<br />
Australia but there are tensions in the whole of the area in which you find<br />
yourselves geographically and we find ourselves geographically, and I would hope<br />
that it would be possible in the course of the future, the near future, to see that<br />
these intentions were as far as possible damped down and that you and we and all<br />
the other nations in this area could at least say to each other that we respect and<br />
honour the territorial boundaries of each nation and will not, under any<br />
circumstances, seek to upset them. This is, Sir, just a matter of damping<br />
down the tensions: if it happened it would be good, and if after it happened or<br />
while it was happening we could, together, seek to improve, however slowly,<br />
but constantly the living standards of the individuals in each country, then we<br />
would be laying a real foundation for what is possible if the men and the women<br />
of each nation in this area, under the leadership provided to them, are prepared<br />
to make it possible, and because I think that you, Sir, are prepared to make it<br />
possible and because I think you are aiming at making it possible. T1hat is the<br />
third reason why tonight I have such a sense of privilege in having you beside<br />
me in the Indonesian capital, and in asking all those gathered here to rise and<br />
drink with me to the President of the Republic of Indonesia. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
