<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41477</transcript-id>
    <title>100,000 more Australians move off welfare and into work</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/02/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>More than 100,000 of the most disadvantaged Australians - many of them long-term unemployed welfare recipients - have gained a job through the Turnbull Government’s wage subsidy program since 2015.</p>
<p>Wage subsidies are supporting businesses to give vital work opportunities to Australians facing disadvantage.</p>
<p>The best form of welfare is a job. The Turnbull Government is committed to getting as many Australians into work as possible by creating more and better jobs. Every Australian deserves a job to support themselves and their families.</p>
<p>This Government has created record jobs growth, with more than 1,100 jobs being created every day and more than 900,000 created since the Coalition came to government. Most new jobs are full-time and female workforce participation is at an all-time high.</p>
<p>The number of jobs in Australia has increased for the 16th straight month in January — the longest consecutive run of jobs growth ever.</p>
<p>These jobs are helping those on welfare improve their standard of living by moving off welfare and into meaningful work. Around 140,000 people have moved off welfare over the past four years.</p>
<p>The Wage Subsidy Program offers subsidies of up to $10,000 to employers who hire and retain eligible people in ongoing positions. Wage subsidies are available for positions taken by parents, mature-age workers, youth, long-term unemployed and indigenous Australians who are registered with an employment services provider.</p>
<p>This targeted incentive is available for any Australian business. The Coalition is proud of its record in helping 100,000 disadvantaged unemployed people into jobs and encourages more businesses to take this opportunity to receive support in giving unemployed Australians the chance to get back into work.</p>
<p>For more information about the available wage subsidies visit the Department of Jobs and Small Business website.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
