<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>573</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS RELEASE :  TATE GALLERY SHOW IN  PERTH STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER , THE RT. HON. R.G MENSIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000573.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-I2/ o9<br />
PRESS RELEASE TATE GALUARY SHOW IN PERTH<br />
Statement by tha Minister. the Rt. Hon. R. G. Monsies<br />
The Prime Minister said today that arrangements<br />
were being completed to present in the Art Gallery at<br />
Perth the exhibition of Australian paintings which<br />
has been assembled for showing ( from January to March<br />
next year) in the Tat* Gallery in London.<br />
The exhibition " Australian paintings<br />
Colonial Impressionist Contemporary" would<br />
be seen in Perth later this year en route to London.<br />
It has been assembled by the Comonwealth Art Advisory<br />
Board in response to an ihvitation from the Trustees<br />
of the Tate Gallery.<br />
Comprising over 200 pictures, it is the<br />
largest and most important exhibition ever to leave<br />
Australia, and contains many irreplaceable works.<br />
Mr. Menzies said he welcomed the invitation<br />
from the Perth Gallery authorities, not only because<br />
of the importance of this exhibition, but also because<br />
it would give the people of Perth separated by great<br />
distanoes from the other State GaLeries, an opportunity<br />
to see a comprehensive exhibition of Australian art.<br />
The Perth Gallery was also to be thanked<br />
for its generosity in lending pictures for the<br />
exhibition in London. Works by Western Australian<br />
artists Robert Juniper and Guy Grep Smith are included<br />
in the exhibition.<br />
PERTH, July, 1962. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
