<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22557</transcript-id>
    <title>The Prime Minister&#039;s Prize for Australian History  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/11/2006</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>At the Australian History summit on 17 August 2006, I announced the establishment of the Prime Minister's Prize for Australian History.  This $100,000 prize will be awarded annually in recognition of an outstanding piece of work that contributed significantly to our understanding of Australian history.</p>
<p>  I am very pleased to announce that the following eminent historians have accepted my invitation to be members of the Australian History Prize advisory committee:</p>
<p>     Emeritus Professor Geoffrey Blainey AC - former Ernest Scott Professor of History, University of Melbourne and former Chancellor of the University of Ballarat.</p>
<p>  Associate Professor Gregory Melleuish - Associate Professor of History and Politics at the University of Wollongong.</p>
<p>  Ms Jackie Huggins - Deputy Director of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies Unit at the University of Queensland.</p>
<p>  Dr Tom Frame - Anglican Bishop to the Australian Defence Force and acclaimed military historian and biographer.</p>
<p>Ms Lisa Paul, Secretary of the Department of Education, Science and Training, will chair the committee. The committee will provide me with a shortlist of potential winners from the nominations received. With such impressive combined expertise, I am confident that the committee's views on nominated works will be invaluable.  Nominations for the 2006 prize can be made now and are open until 17 November 2006.  Further details about the Prime Minister's Prize for Australian History (including information about how to nominate) is available at <a href="http://www.dest.gov.au/pmhistoryprize">www.dest.gov.au/pmhistoryprize</a></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
