<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>579</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY RT. HON. R G MENZIES, CH, QC, MP, ON BUDGET 1962-63</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/08/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000579_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH BY<br />
~ Rt. Hon. R. G. MENZIES, CH, M. P.<br />
ON<br />
BUDGET 1962-63.<br />
[ Fromn the " Parliamentary Debates," 16th A ugust, 1962.]<br />
Mr. MENZIES ( Kooyong--Prime Minishonorable<br />
member for<br />
I. rra ( Mr. Cairns) has a rich vein of<br />
humour that I have always admired; but he<br />
really ought to make up his mind one of<br />
these days what it is he means because in<br />
the last five minutes of his speech, he<br />
Jbpted in his attack on the Government<br />
two utterly inconsistent positions. In the<br />
first place, he drew a picture of the Government<br />
as full1 of low cunning. He says<br />
we arc going to make ourselves more<br />
unpopular in the next six months; we are<br />
getting ready to do something in a year's<br />
time when the election is getting nearer.<br />
You can imagine the low cunning with<br />
which this cold-blooded Government is<br />
planning a political future. That rather<br />
surprises me because after the last election<br />
I was given to understand by the Opposition<br />
that we would not be here very long.<br />
Now the Opposition has us engaging in a<br />
three years' plan, all cold and calculated.<br />
7500/ 62. In the next breath, the honorable member<br />
for Yarra has said that the Government<br />
is frightened-frightened of the<br />
future and of all sorts of things.<br />
You know, I find it difficult to<br />
believe that anybody except the honorable<br />
member for Yarra could be at<br />
one and the same time consumed by terror<br />
and full of cold-blooded, low, calculating<br />
cunning. However, I do not want to worry<br />
about him now. I will do that if and<br />
when he becomes the Treasurer of the<br />
Commonwealth of Australia.<br />
I want to say something now about the<br />
motion of censure moved by the Deputy<br />
Leader of the Opposition ( Mr. Whitlam),<br />
and then I want to say something about our<br />
own policy, in a positive sense. The speech<br />
by the Deputy Leader of the Opposition<br />
was very interesting. It was a not very<br />
original exercise in phrase-making. I<br />
seemed to hear, as I listened to it, all the<br />
cliches which enjoy currency in half-baked </p>
<p>socialistic academic circles. I gather from<br />
this morning's press that we may expect to<br />
hear more of these in the future, fresh from<br />
the National University. I know the honorable<br />
member opposite who is interjecting<br />
does not like anything except the sound of<br />
his own voice and the distant waves from a<br />
certain foreign country. But may 1, even<br />
with difficulty, return to what I was saying<br />
about the speech made by the Deputy<br />
Leader of the Opposition?<br />
He accused us-I made a note of a few<br />
of his phrases-of ineptitude, unprincipled<br />
conduct, neglect, callousness, incompetence,<br />
and intellectual and political dishonesty. I<br />
hope I will be allowed to say to the Deputy<br />
Leader of the Opposition that for him to<br />
accuse anybody of those offences really<br />
hurts. It hurts profoundly. Presumably-the<br />
honorable member for Yarra gave a hint of<br />
it in the closing passages of his speech-the<br />
country has suffered from our ineptitude,<br />
unprincipled conduct, neglect, callousness,<br />
incompetence, and intellectual and political<br />
dishonesty for twelve years or more without<br />
knowing it. That is the most astonishing<br />
performance in democratic history. Here<br />
is a community which, time after time after<br />
time, has had elections, but we are still in<br />
government. The poor simpletons, as we<br />
are told-the Australian electorate-did not<br />
know the kind of people who were conducting<br />
the affairs of this country.<br />
The CHAIRMAN.-Order! The honorable<br />
member for Wills is interjecting. He<br />
must keep order.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Sir, I do not expect<br />
honorable members opposite to be very<br />
happy. Now that they have decided they<br />
cannot win, they have determined that they<br />
will squeal. Let them squeal.<br />
The CHAJRMA4N.-Order! Honorable<br />
members are still interjecting. The Deputy<br />
Leader of the Opposition was extended the<br />
courtesy of being heard in silence, and I<br />
expect the same courtesy to be extended to<br />
the Prime Minister. If that courtesy is<br />
not extended, the Chair will be forced to<br />
take action.<br />
Mr. MENZIIES-The favourite phrase<br />
which ran through the speech of the Deputy<br />
Leader of the Opposition was that the Australian<br />
economy was a stagnant economy.<br />
We have heard this time and time and<br />
time before. I have heard it ever since we came into office in 1949. Until we had<br />
been here for a year or two we did not hear<br />
much of it, but thereafter there were constant<br />
references to a stagnant economy<br />
The stagnancy of the economy, presumably,<br />
is due to the defects that the Deputy Leader<br />
of the Opposition has enumerated. Sir, I<br />
do not want to labour the obvious, but<br />
what has happened in this stagnant<br />
economy during our dull, incompetent and<br />
unimaginative regime? I will tell you, Sir,<br />
for the benefit of all those who are not<br />
sitting in opposition and therefore are not<br />
professionally bound to disregard it. The<br />
population of this country in that period<br />
time has risen from 8,000,000 to ON<br />
10,500,000. Mr. Ward.-You had nothing to do with<br />
that. Mr. MENZIES.-I had as much to<br />
with it as the honorable member. My contributions<br />
to the population during that<br />
period were all by deputy. The net value<br />
of production in Australia has trebled in<br />
that time. There are very nearly 18,000<br />
more factories in Australia. There have<br />
been enormous increases in mineral<br />
development and production. The value of<br />
our exports has doubled. Just under<br />
1,000,000 houses and flats have been built,<br />
so that already, in the proportion of homes<br />
to population, Australia leads the won",<br />
General revenue grants to the States, whk<br />
have their own great responsibilities in the<br />
federal system, are almost five times what<br />
they were when honorable gentlemen opposite<br />
went out of office. The loan works<br />
programme-sustained by the Comma<br />
wealth Government for the first time in th,<br />
Commonwealth's history-is nearly four<br />
times what it was in 1949.<br />
But, Sir, there are, of course, other continuing<br />
proofs of progress in this stagnant<br />
economy. Too few people realize<br />
that a cash deficit of œ E120,000,000-I will<br />
put it in round figures-will of itself have<br />
a most expansionary effect. We shall pay<br />
out to the citizens œ 120,000,000 more than<br />
will be collected from them. So far from<br />
being timorous-I think that was another<br />
of the words used by the Deputy Leader<br />
of the Opposition-this is adventurous<br />
finance. Add to the deficit the tax refunds </p>
<p>now being made, and it is clear that purchasing<br />
power in Australia this financial<br />
year will be uncommonly high. The real<br />
task of any government to-day, as well as<br />
of the business community and all sensible<br />
citizens, is to get that purchasing power<br />
exercised. Sir, there are other factors. The gross<br />
national product in the June quarter of this<br />
year-this year of so-called super-stagnation,<br />
but a year in which no change<br />
occurred in the consumer price indexshowed<br />
an increase of 7.6 per cent. over<br />
tJhoe oJfu noef tqhue a" rtsetar gonfa ti1o9n6" 1 . ofH ethree iesc ofnuortmheyr.<br />
eposits in the savings bank, which are not<br />
the haunt of the rich, amounted in 1961-<br />
62-the financial year we have just ended<br />
-to œ 157,000,000. Hire-purchase debts<br />
_ ll by œ 40,000,000. The banks were<br />
) ost liquid. Our external balances, a great<br />
source of anxiety to us only two years ago,<br />
rose and are healthy. And all of this has<br />
occurred, Sir, and is occurring in a period<br />
of stable price levels and stable monetary<br />
values. I say no more about the allegation<br />
that the Australian economy is stagnant.<br />
Most people in other parts of the world<br />
would love to live in a country with so<br />
stagnant an economy as is Australia's.<br />
I know that the professional task of<br />
honorable members opposite is, to use the<br />
Jd phrase, to cry stinking fish-to make<br />
erybody believe that the Australian people<br />
are in the depths of misery. The Opposition<br />
thinks that once it convinces the people that<br />
they are in the depths of misery, they will<br />
vote for Labour-you have to be pretty<br />
_) iserable to vote for the Labour Party, but<br />
. nat is what honorable members opposite<br />
are hoping for.<br />
Now let me say something about the<br />
bases of our policy. The first item in our<br />
policy-this does not distinguish us from<br />
-other people-is to build up Australia's<br />
population. An increased population is<br />
vital to Australia. Whatever fluctuations<br />
may have occurred in our population, let<br />
me remind honorable members that in 1949<br />
the population was a little more than<br />
8,000,000, but to-day it is well over<br />
10,500,000. Our second great objective is<br />
to maintain full employment of man-power<br />
and resources. The two things must go together<br />
if we are to develop Australia. It is true that in January of this year<br />
131,000 people were registered for employment,<br />
but last month that figure was down<br />
to 90,000. That is a magnificent reduction<br />
in that period of time. That process of<br />
reduction will continue. I do not need to<br />
be reminded that honorable members opposite<br />
will cry themselves to sleep if the number<br />
of persons unemployed declines to the<br />
point where it disappears, because then they<br />
will have lost their one great claim to statesmanship.<br />
The reduction in the number of<br />
persons unemployed has occurred with the<br />
full effect of the February measures<br />
obviously yet to be seen, and most<br />
obviously with the full effect of a<br />
œ 120,000,000 cash deficit yet to make its<br />
mark on the spending power and willingness<br />
to buy of the Australian community. Of<br />
course I am optimistic. The honorable member<br />
for Yarra, who obviously has never had<br />
to associate himself with the compilation of<br />
estimates, says: " But your estimated figure<br />
for unemployment benefit is such and such.<br />
That means you have reconciled yourselves<br />
to a certain volume of unemployment." I<br />
would be very sorry for the man who, having<br />
approached the Treasurer with an estimate<br />
of how much had to go out in unemployment<br />
benefit, had to go back and ask<br />
for more. Of course, when the honorable<br />
member for Yarra is older and wiser<br />
Mr. Jones.-When he is grey headed, like<br />
you! Mr. MENZIES.-Yes, when he is greyheaded<br />
like me, or is the honorable member<br />
referring to the honorable member for<br />
Barton ( Mr. Reynolds)? The fact is that<br />
confidence-the important element in<br />
putting all this purchasing power to workis<br />
attacked and undermined by an Opposition<br />
which relies on unemployment to put<br />
it into office, but, as I gladly acknowledge<br />
from the honorable member for Yarra, not<br />
for three years-that is what I gathered<br />
from his remarks.<br />
Our third objective is to restrain inflation.<br />
I did not hear anything about restraining<br />
inflation in speeches made by honorable<br />
members opposite. As far as one can judge,<br />
the Deputy Leader of the Opposition neither<br />
says nor cares whether anything is done<br />
about inflation. In fact, at one stage during<br />
his remarks, as clich6 followed clich6 I<br />
expected him to say that inflation was a </p>
<p>bogy-but I have heard that one before.<br />
He seems to believe-presumably his party<br />
believes it too-that stability in the value of<br />
income of any kind and in costs is stagnation.<br />
This is something about which everybody<br />
should begin to think. It is something<br />
about which I invite the people of Australia<br />
to think. Do they believe that stability<br />
in the price level-in the value of the money<br />
they receive and in the cost of things they<br />
buy-is stagnation? No sensible person<br />
could possibly believe it.<br />
We have had eighteen months of stability<br />
in the consumer price index, and in that<br />
period we have conducted, or materially<br />
contributed to, some of the greatest works<br />
of development in the history of Australia.<br />
Far from believing that stability means<br />
stagnation, we have proclaimed that stability<br />
is a condition of growth and development.<br />
We have spent vast sums of money on the<br />
Snowy Mountains scheme, on the standardization<br />
of rail gauges, on a great project in<br />
Western Australia, on a now-completed<br />
programme in Victoria and on the Mount<br />
Isa railway. The latter is a very great enterprise<br />
involving the development of our<br />
copper resources and the export of copper<br />
from this country. We have given encouragement<br />
to the coal ports, and we have assisted<br />
the building of beef cattle roads in the<br />
north. It would be tiresome to list all the<br />
undertakings that this Government has<br />
helped. They are all in the minds of honorable<br />
members. The point I make is that<br />
those projects have been completed or<br />
undertaken by us in a period of stability,<br />
which the honorable member for Yarra continually<br />
confuses with stagnation.<br />
Our next great objective is to see that<br />
there is a steady and strong growth of<br />
manufacturing in Australia, because manufacturing<br />
is one of the essential conditions<br />
of full employment in a growing population.<br />
Every honorable member knows that. There<br />
is a limit to the extent to which an increased<br />
population may find gainful employment in<br />
rural affairs. Everybody knows that. We<br />
must find employment in secondary industry<br />
and in tertiary industry for the fast-increasing<br />
population that is coming to this<br />
stagnant" country.<br />
Our next objective is to reduce costs of<br />
production or, alternatively, to prevent them<br />
from rising. I am speaking now abopt manufacturing industry. I remind honorable<br />
members that it is this Government<br />
that has introduced investment allowances<br />
to help manufacturing industry to improve<br />
its plant and to reduce its costs. It is this<br />
Government that has introduced export tax<br />
concessions in order to give material inducements<br />
to manufacturers to get into the<br />
export business and not leave it all to the<br />
primary industries. It is this Government<br />
that has expedited tariff procedures. It is<br />
this Government that has introduced provision<br />
for quota restrictions in selected cases<br />
of some urgency and particularity. It is<br />
this Government that has introduced exp"<br />
payments insurance in order -to encoura,<br />
export industries. I think it will be understood<br />
that all of those things have a great<br />
bearing on costs of production because if<br />
manufacturers in Australia developed N.<br />
large export market their turnover wot)<br />
be greater, their unit costs would come<br />
down and they themselves would be able<br />
to resist other pressures upwards on the<br />
cost level. Therefore, the whole objective<br />
that we have, in the case of manufacturing,<br />
is to increase turnover, to facilitate the<br />
maintenance of plant efficiency and to<br />
reduce unit costs. With the primary industries,<br />
we have pursued, and are pursuing,<br />
corresponding policies.<br />
Let me remind the committee-and I<br />
find that I need to remind the Depu<br />
Leader of the Opposition, because, fromn<br />
first to last, he had not a word or a thought<br />
to spare for the rural industries in Australia-<br />
that the exports of primary products<br />
by Australia produced most of tincome<br />
which enables manufacturing iL<br />
dustry to have the imports of plant and<br />
materials that it must have if it is to grow<br />
and to employ people. Here is the perfect<br />
example of interdependence. Manufacturing<br />
industry needs materials. To a great extent<br />
still, it needs plant from overseas. It cannot<br />
buy plant and materials overseas unless<br />
we establish overseas credits by the export<br />
of primary commodities. As a result, the<br />
preservation of the primary industries and<br />
the strictest attention to their cost level<br />
have a direct bearing on the extent to which<br />
manufacturing industry can grow and<br />
employ the increasing population that I<br />
stipulated for at the very beginning. </p>
<p>So I can add, in the case of primary<br />
industry, also, that the avoidance of inflated<br />
costs is essentially related to increased productivity<br />
of the land. So far, the results,<br />
in terms of increased productivity, of the<br />
use of applied science or -technology, have<br />
been quite remarkable, as has been the<br />
development of new and wider markets. All<br />
of these things are being attended to by this<br />
Government. The Treasurer ( Mr. Harold<br />
Holt) is a much-abused man. He has been<br />
responsible for some of these things. The<br />
Minister for Trade ( Mr. McEwen) has been<br />
responsible for others. I suppose that I<br />
-may regard myself as the innocent by-<br />
) ander. These things have been done and<br />
are being done by this Government. Yet,<br />
Sir, the problems of production, of costs<br />
and of export for both primary and secondary<br />
industries were not regarded as being<br />
orth five minutes' time by the Opposition<br />
) hen it presented what 1, in my innocence,<br />
regarded as the policy speech on behalf of<br />
an alternative government.<br />
It is quite clear, as all honorable members<br />
who followed the speech made by the<br />
Deputy Leader of the Opposition will remember,<br />
that the first fatal omission from<br />
that speech was his failure to say anything<br />
about rural costs. On the contrary, he<br />
advocated, in a rather broad and undetailed<br />
fashion, a policy of acute inflation,<br />
laughing at the idea that we need to worry<br />
I'Pout the stability of costs because, in his<br />
. Jpinion, stability, if we achieve it, will be<br />
equivalent to stagnation. This is the<br />
thought right down in his mind, or in the<br />
minds of these academic observers and<br />
-advisers of his.<br />
I have stated the first thing omitted from<br />
the Deputy Leader of the Opposition's<br />
speech. I am talking about major matters.<br />
The second thing is that there was in it<br />
not a word about the need to encourage<br />
the productivity of the export industries and<br />
to increase export income, because the<br />
Deputy Leader of the Opposition failed to<br />
realize that those two things are essential<br />
to full employment. Is this a draft of the<br />
policy of those who hope to form the next<br />
Labour government? If it is, let the man<br />
on the land in Australia take warning. He<br />
will be forgotten and irretrievably damaged,<br />
and full employment will be imperilled by<br />
lack of real nourishment for the great<br />
primary and secondary industries. Sir, we hear a lot about full employment.<br />
We are asked questions about it now and<br />
then, and there are arguments about words.<br />
But full employment is not an artificial idea<br />
or something to be achieved by some sleight<br />
of hand, by some artifice on the part of<br />
a government. It is the desired end of<br />
national and industrial actions operating<br />
together to create a ' state of affairs in which<br />
people are employed -because they are<br />
needed for work. In other words, you can<br />
look at full employment as if it were a<br />
theory, or you can look at it as the desired<br />
end of a great co-operative effort throughout<br />
the. country-an effort in wvhich action<br />
is productively directed and people are<br />
productively employed.<br />
The next objective that we have in our<br />
policy, Sir, is to develop the basic resources<br />
of the country. Honorable -members opposite<br />
would * be hard put to it to deny that<br />
during our term of office the most astonishing<br />
development of these resources has<br />
occurred. This development is quite right,<br />
because basic resources and public works<br />
are the foundations of real growth in both<br />
the public and the private sectors of the<br />
economy. I have said this before, and I<br />
repeat it: I do not accept this artificial<br />
division of the economy betwveen the public<br />
sector and the -private sector. We look at<br />
the works programmes of the States and wc<br />
think that tbey are very good programmes.<br />
They are very good indeed. Without them<br />
and without our works programme, private<br />
industry could not grow. It could not<br />
employ people. It could not see them<br />
housed and provided with transport, schools<br />
and all the amenities of civilized society.<br />
So we must not draw these acute distinctions.<br />
But wve must understand that if we<br />
are to have all these things, the roots of<br />
development must be deep in the soil of<br />
Australia. We must look at our basic<br />
resources, wherever they are, and expose<br />
them and use them in the service of thc<br />
people of Australia.<br />
Our next objective of policy, Mr. Chairman,<br />
is to raise the standard of living by<br />
massive assistance in housing, by the maintenance<br />
of industrial peace, by large and<br />
growing payments to the States for transport,<br />
schools and water supply, and by<br />
development generally. I lump those things<br />
together. I wish I had enough time and the </p>
<p>committee had enough patience to enable<br />
me to take them one by one and analyse<br />
them, but I must lump them together for<br />
my present purpose. Assistance in each of<br />
these fields represents a powerful contribution<br />
to the improvement of the standard of<br />
living. In consequence of this assistance,<br />
the standard of living has actually been<br />
rising in this stagnant economy!<br />
Next, Sir-I hope the Opposition will<br />
pay some attention to this-one of our<br />
great purposes has been to maintain the<br />
public credit so as to ensure the maximum<br />
capital raisings in Australia, a substantial<br />
inflow of capital, on both public and private<br />
account, from abroad, and, generally..<br />
Australia's international financial repute.<br />
Nothing is more valuable to a country than<br />
a good reputation. The Deputy Leader of<br />
the Opposition, speaking, I admit, with not<br />
too much knowledge about this matter, said<br />
that if we would give the Australian Labour<br />
Party the chance it would redu~ ce the<br />
interest cost of raising money on the public<br />
account. That seems quite simple to do if<br />
you say it quickly. It is not so simple<br />
to do. As a matter of fact, it was quite<br />
wrong for him to say this, because he<br />
wanted to create the impression that there<br />
was an unduly high interest rate on public<br />
securities in Australia as compared with<br />
other countries. I will take the long-termi<br />
yield, which always affords a basis of comparison.<br />
On the long term, twenty-year<br />
yield, what were the current figures in July<br />
of this year-that is, last month? They<br />
were: Australia, 5 per cent.; Great Britain,<br />
6 per cent.; West Germany-no one has<br />
ever said that West Germany's was -a stagnant<br />
economy, for it has been throbbing<br />
with activity ever since the war-6 per<br />
cent., not 5 per cent. as in Australia; and<br />
Canada, which has great access to powerful<br />
financial resources from the United<br />
States of America, 51 per cent. Australia<br />
was the lowest of the lot.<br />
Having made those remarks, I just want<br />
to make two particular comments. Time<br />
would not reasonably permit me to make<br />
more. First, we were charged the other<br />
night with callous treatment of the unemployed.<br />
I take it that that is the general<br />
belief of the Opposition. I -hope that all<br />
honorable members on the Opposition front<br />
bench agree with that charge-callous<br />
treatment of the unemployed. Mr. Ward.-That is an understatement.<br />
Mr. MIENZIES.-He will always rise if<br />
you cast the fly enough. That is an<br />
understatement says the honorable member<br />
for East Sydney. Well, well! Sir, I<br />
seem to remember that the Australian<br />
Labour Party was in office for a number of<br />
years-eight years. I remember that well,<br />
because I was sitting on the Opposition<br />
side of the chamber. The Labour Party<br />
was in office for eight years. It was not<br />
notably deficient in talent, compared with<br />
those now on the Opposition side. Labou!<br />
was in office for eight years, had majorities<br />
and ran the country. In 1949-my year'<br />
grace, if I may put it that way-whe..<br />
Labour was still in office, there was substantial<br />
unemployment for a time. I am<br />
not worrying about-<br />
Mr. Allan Fraser.-Of course you ar--<br />
not! Mr. MENZIES.-I know that the unemployment<br />
arose primarily from a Communist-<br />
inspired coal strike. But do not<br />
forget that right through the period there<br />
was some unemployment.<br />
Mr. Allan Fraser.-Three hundred.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-You ought to study the<br />
figures. I defy you to find any time in<br />
the whole of that period when no people<br />
were registered as unemployed. There<br />
were masses of people unemployed. Any<br />
how,' whether they were unemployed for<br />
short time or a long time, or whether they<br />
were few or many-<br />
Mr. Reynolds.-Many jobs were available.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I am talking aboL)<br />
people receiving unemployment benefit.<br />
Even you must understand that when they<br />
were drawing benefit they did not have a<br />
job; so let us discuss it in that way. Few or<br />
many, it does not matter; they were still<br />
unemployed. What did the Labour Party<br />
provide for them? The benefit for an adult<br />
or a married minor was 25s. a week and<br />
for a wife, œ 1.<br />
Mr. Pollard.-And it bought three times<br />
as many pounds of butter as your benefit<br />
will buy.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-The honorable member<br />
for Lalor will be advocating a reduction<br />
in the price of butter shortly. Really, </p>
<p>Reggie, you must behavel Mr. Chairman,<br />
I know Opposition members want to<br />
interrupt the reception of this speech.<br />
The benefit was 25s. for an adult or a<br />
married minor, œ 1 for a wife, 5s. for one<br />
child, nothing for any more children, and<br />
a permissible income of This year,<br />
under this " callous" Government which<br />
does not care what happens to the unemployed-<br />
that was the phrase used by the<br />
Opposition, so we had better accept it-<br />
Mr. Uren.-Who created the unemployment?<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-Under this Governent<br />
in 1962, no thanks to you, the adult<br />
married minor receives, not 25s., but<br />
œ 4 2s. 6d.; the wife receives, not but<br />
each child receives 15s., not just one<br />
child receiving 5s.; and the permissible income<br />
is Let me just summarize that.<br />
"' bour provided for an unemployed man<br />
/ th a wife and two children, œ 2 10s. a<br />
week. Mr. Pollard.-You provided nothing in<br />
1939. Mr. MENZIES.-I know you do not like<br />
it, but for once in your life take it. I will<br />
repeat it.<br />
Mr. Pollard.-Why don't-<br />
Mr. MENZLES.-I will repeat it as long<br />
as the honorable member for Lalor does<br />
not want it to be heard.<br />
-' The CHAIRMAN.-Order! I warn the<br />
, onorable member for Lalor that he must<br />
cease interjecting.<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I know what happens<br />
the moment you get them like this. The<br />
-moment you have them on the hip, they<br />
Sgin to say, " What did Lord Wellington<br />
-say in 1832?" This is the oldest debating<br />
exercise in the world.<br />
Mr. Peters.-What did he say?<br />
Mr. MENZIES.-I haven't a clue. Probably<br />
all he did in 1832 was to vote against<br />
the Reform Bill.<br />
I will repeat this; it will ultimately reach<br />
the public ear. Labour provided for an<br />
unemployed man with a wife and two<br />
children, œ 2 10s. a week, and permitted an<br />
additional earning of œ 1 a week. For the<br />
same family we provide, not œ 2 10s., but<br />
œ 8 12s. 6d., with permitted additional income<br />
of not It is of no use for<br />
honorable members opposite to say, " Ah, but the cost of living has increased No<br />
increase in the cost of living that has<br />
occurred can explain the difference in the<br />
benefits paid. Opposition members have<br />
my deepest sympathy when confronted by<br />
these figures, when they have it demonstrated<br />
that this argument about callousness<br />
to the unemployed is hypocritical drivel.<br />
When this is demonstrated to them, of<br />
course, they run back and ask what happened<br />
in-oh, dear, dear!<br />
The second particular comment that I<br />
want to make-I might well make 50, but<br />
I will limit myself-is that the honorable<br />
gentleman said in his projected budget<br />
there would be an emergency grant to the<br />
States for education. He did not give any<br />
details of this. I confess it puzzles me a<br />
little. An emergency grant! Does he<br />
mean for one year? Does he think -that a<br />
grant for one year will solve the problem?<br />
Or does he mean that it is to be permanent<br />
and therefore not an emergency grant? He<br />
really ought to tell us, I think, at some convenient<br />
time, which idea he has in his<br />
mind. But under this stagnant Government,<br />
in this " stagnant" period in Australian<br />
economic and social history, what has happened?<br />
In 1950, -the States, which have<br />
the prime responsibility for educationgreatly<br />
assisted by us, as I will show-were<br />
spending œ 46,000,000 on education. In<br />
spite of us and our villainy, in 1960-61, ten<br />
years later, they spent, not œ 46,000,000,<br />
but œ 184,000,000. This does not sound<br />
much like stagnation. From 1951, when<br />
we began it, ' to the current financial year,<br />
Commonwealth direct payments to State<br />
universities rose from œ 1,000,000 to just<br />
under œ 16,000,000, and our scholarship<br />
provision was multiplied four times. I will<br />
not take too much time on this, because I<br />
am preparing a statement which will show<br />
how much the Commonwealth contributes<br />
directly and indirectly -to State education<br />
expenditure. The figures will show that in<br />
1950-51 the Commonwealth component of<br />
the œ 46,000,000 that the States spent was<br />
œ 22,000,000, and -that out of the current<br />
œ 184,000,000 the Commonwealth component<br />
was no less than œ 85,000,000. But,<br />
Sir, I will not anticipate because I think<br />
it is due to the honorable members that I<br />
should have a paper prepared-and it is<br />
now well in hand-to deal with these<br />
matters. </p>
<p>I have briefly explained the objectives of<br />
our policy and I have explained them, I<br />
hope, in positive terms. We know quite<br />
well, if nobody else does, that in any country<br />
economic conditions will fluctuate.<br />
But that does not mean that a long-term<br />
policy cannot be pursued with vigour and<br />
determination provided that it is widely<br />
understood and that targets are clearly<br />
seen. If we compare our progress in Australia-<br />
this great country of ours-for the<br />
last decade with that of any other comparable<br />
country we shall see that our advance<br />
has been steady and sure. True, we have<br />
recently had some recession of business<br />
activity-now recovering-and some unemployment.<br />
But this Budget, coming as it<br />
does on top of the liberal measures of a<br />
few months ago, is expansionary and will,<br />
subject to one element to which I shall<br />
refer again in a few minutes, facilitate a<br />
full return to a rapid but sound national<br />
growth. The large deficit of nearly<br />
œ 120,000,000 is, for reasons I have mentioned,<br />
calculated to stimulate this process.<br />
Sir, our foundations are solid and sure.<br />
Our overseas reserves and our balance of<br />
payments, which gave us great concern in<br />
the boom months of 1960, have been restored<br />
to health. The banking position and<br />
the availability of credit are both satisfactory.<br />
We have cost and price stability.<br />
The inflow of capital for Australian investment<br />
is being maintained. The public credit<br />
is high. We are confident of a good future,<br />
and we are determined to achieve it. Our<br />
task -is not to produce a return to an inflation<br />
which, in its turn, could produce<br />
rapidly rising costs and prices with excessive<br />
labour turnover, inefficiency and damaging<br />
speculation. That that is not our task, I<br />
am happy to say, was recognized by every<br />
businessman and primary producer with<br />
whom we had discussions about six weeks<br />
ago. Our duty is not negative but positive. It<br />
is to promote a climate favorable to rapid<br />
but sound growth of national resources and primary and secondary exports and the new<br />
and enlarged markets that we need in a<br />
changing and challenging world. To do all<br />
these things we must and will accept some<br />
risks, but not foolish risks. However the<br />
chances in this national adventure may fall,<br />
we do not propose ever to lose sight of the<br />
need for growth, which is supremely important,<br />
nor of the basic condition of<br />
growth, the preservation by the joint efforts<br />
of science, management and labour of a<br />
general cost level which will enable us to<br />
meet and overcome competition both at<br />
home and abroad in the products of our<br />
fields and factories.<br />
Sir, before I conclude, may I say thi<br />
Much play has been made by our opponents,<br />
evidently unacquainted with the fact that<br />
the economy, as well as road transport, has<br />
its traffic problems, on the brilliant term<br />
stop-go Adopting this metaphorical ex<br />
pression I can say for the Government tha<br />
economically speaking, we shall drive ahead<br />
on the right road as fast as we sensibly can.<br />
We hope to have the green light with us. We<br />
may well occasionally see the amber light,<br />
which means caution, but we will not drive<br />
through the red light just because some<br />
passing pedestrian would regard that as a<br />
proof of liberal thought.<br />
I said that there was one element operating<br />
against a full return to speedy growth.<br />
That element is insufficient confidence up<br />
the line from consumer-buyer to manufac<br />
turer. For all the reasons I have mentione.<br />
there should be to-day a powerful surge of<br />
confidence. Those who devote their major<br />
attention to the defects of our present position,<br />
and withdraw their attention from the<br />
real foundations of prosperity, do a grer<br />
disservice to the nation. They promote it,<br />
the public mind that very ill-founded uncertainty<br />
which is the sole remaining cause of<br />
the degree of unemployment that still exists.<br />
There is no room for pessimism in a<br />
country whose entire history is a triumph<br />
for hope and faith and confidence.<br />
BY AUTHORITY: A. J. ARTHUR, COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT PRINTER, CANBERRA. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
