<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6272</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER AUSTRALIA-THAI CHAMBER OF COMMERCE BANGKOK, 22 NOVEMBER 1983</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/11/1983</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006272.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY_. tj__ EMBARGOED UNTIL 2 P. M. LOCAL<br />
PRIME MiNISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE AUSTRALIAN PRIM. E MINISTER<br />
AUSTRALIA-THAI CHAMBER OF COMMERCE<br />
BANGKOK 22 NOVEMBER 1983<br />
MR CHAIRMAN<br />
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR WARM WELCOME.<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN-THAI CHAMBER OF COMMERCE HAS MADE A . VALUABLE<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THAILAND AND<br />
AUSTRALIA. PERHAPS MOST SIGNIFICANTLY THE EXISTENCE OF THE CHAMBER<br />
REFLECTS AN AUSTRALIAN COMMERCIAL PRESENCE ON THE GROUND<br />
HERE IN THAILAND; ITS MEMBERSHIP COMPRISES AUSTRALIANS AND<br />
THAIS ACTIVELY INTERESTED IN EXPLORING AND DEVELOPING<br />
OPPORTUNITIES FOR MUTUALLY BENEFICIAL ECONOMIC AND TRADE<br />
DEVELOPMENT IN THE SOUTH EAST ASIAN REGION.<br />
THIS, I BELIEVE, IS THE ONLY WAY ULTIMATELY TO GIVE SUBSTANCE<br />
TO REGIONAL ECONOMIC RELATIONS.<br />
THERE ARE QUITE DRAMATIC CHANGES TAKING PLACE IN OUR REGION.<br />
AT A TIME OF SUCH ADJUSTMENT AND CHANGE, IT IS SOMETIMES<br />
DIFFICULT TO APPRECIATE THEIR DIMENSIONS AND CONSEQUENCES,<br />
BUT IT IS ONLY IF WE ARE PREPARED FOR ADJUSTMENT AND CHANGE<br />
THAT VIE WILL BE ABLE TO REAP THE BENEFITS, </p>
<p>THE MOST CRUCIAL CHANGES APPARENT IN THIS REGION STEM<br />
DIRECTLY FROM THE DRAMATIC REORDERING OF GROWTH PATTERNS<br />
WITHIN AND BETWEEN COUNTRIES OF THE REGION,<br />
THIS REORDERING HAS BEEN OF SUCH A FUNDAMENTAL CHARACTER<br />
THAT IT REQUIRES A BASIC REAPPRAISAL OF THE CIRCUMSTANCES<br />
WITHIN WHICH COUNTRIES OF THE REGION NOW DEAL WITH EACH<br />
OTHER, IT ALSO COMPELS ATTENTION TO THE QUITE CRITICAL DOMESTIC<br />
ADJUSTMENTS WITHIN THE COUNTRIES OF THE REGION THAT ARE<br />
MADE NECESSARY BY AND INEVITABLY ACCOMPANY SUCH CHANGE,<br />
FOR ITS PART AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT POLICY WILL BE DIRECTED<br />
TO ENSURING THAT AUSTRALIA IS AN EFFECTIVE PARTICIPANT IN<br />
THE PROCESS OF CHANGE GOING ON ABOUT US,<br />
RATHER THAN BEING WARY OF CHANGE, AUSTRALIA WANTS IT TO<br />
WORK TO THE ADVANTAGE BOTH OF ITSELF AND ITS REGIONAL PARTNERS,<br />
OUR COMMITMENT IS TO AN INVOLVED ROLE ONE THAT WOULD SEE<br />
AUSTRALIA BOTH CONTRIBUTING TO AND BENEFITTING FROM THE<br />
DYNAMISM OF THE REGIONAL SITUATION,<br />
THE THRUST OF AUSTRALIAN DOMESTIC ECONOMIC POLICY REFLECTS<br />
THIS COMMITMENT, ,/ 3 </p>
<p>THAT POLICY IS NOT ONLY GEARED TO TURNING THE AUSTRALIAN<br />
ECONOMY AROUND ( AN OBJECTIVE WHICH RECENT INDICATORS SUGGEST<br />
IS ATTAINABLE AND BEING GRADUALLY REALISED), BUT IS ALSO<br />
AIMED AT ENSURING THAT AUSTRALIA IS WELL-PLACED TO PARTICIPATE<br />
IN AND BENEFIT FROM THIS WIDER PROCESS OF CHANGE,<br />
My GOVERNMENT'IS COMMITMENT TO THE REDUCTION OVER THE LONG<br />
TERM OF EXISTING LEVELS OF PROTECTION IN AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
IS PART OF THIS POLICY APPROACH.<br />
RECENT MEASURES INTRODUCED TO SUPPORT THE ESTABLISHMENT IN<br />
AUSTRALIA OF A VENTURE CAPITAL MARKET AND TO ASSIST, THROUGH<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY DEVELOPMEN4T CORPORATION, THE FINANCING<br />
OF THE NECESSARY RESTRUCTURING AND REVITALIZATION OF AUSTRALIAN<br />
INDUSTRY ARE ALSO PART OF THIS POLICY THRUST.<br />
As WELL, POLICIES WE HAVE INTRODUCED AND ARE DEVELOPING TO<br />
SECURE A BETTER TRAINED, MORE FLEXIBLE AUSTRALIAN WORKFORCE<br />
ARE DESIGNED TO BE AN INTEGRAL PART OF THE SAME INDUSTRY<br />
STRATEGY, IT WOULD NOT COME, THEREFORE, ASA GREAT SURPRISE TO MANY OF<br />
YOU THAT my GOVERNMENT ATTACHES A GREAT DEAL OF IMPORTANCE<br />
TO ALL ASPECTS OF OUR RELATIONSHIPS WITH OUR NEIGHBOURS,<br />
INCLUDING THAILAND,<br />
IN MY ADDRESS LAST NIGHT I POINTED TO THE CONSIDERABLE DEPTH<br />
AND EXTENT OF AUSTRALIA ' S RELATIONS WITH THE ASEAN COUNTRIES. 4 </p>
<p>J<br />
IWAS PARTICULARLY PLEASED THAT ON THIS VISIT, SOME TEN YEARS<br />
SINCE THE LAST BY AN AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER, BOTH GENERAL<br />
PREM AND I WERE ABLE TO FULLY AND COMPLETELY TO HAVE ACHIEVED<br />
UNDERSTANDING OF EACH OTHER'S INTERESTS AND PERCEPTIONS.<br />
IN ALL THAT AUSTRALIA DOES WITH THAILAND WE ARE PARTICULARLY<br />
MINDFUL OF THAILAND'S POSITION AS A " FRONT-LINE" STATE.<br />
IT WAS ESPECIALLY FOR THIS REASON THAT I THOUGHT IT NECESSARY<br />
TO GET THE BENEFIT OF PRIME MINISTER PREM'S AND FOREIGN MINISTER<br />
SIDDHI'S PERCEPTIONS OF THE CONTEMPORARY REGIONAL SITUATION.<br />
THE TALKS WE HAVE HAD WERE MOST VALUABLE AND PRODUCTIVE IN THIS<br />
REGARD. BOTH PRIME MINISTER PREM AND FOREIGN MINISTER SIDDHI DEEPLY<br />
IMPRESSED ME NOT ONLY WITH THE COMPELLING CHARACTER OF THEIR<br />
ASSESSMENT OF CONTEMPORARY PROBLEMS, BUT ALSO FOR THE GENUINE<br />
WARMTH AND FRIENDSHIP THEY DEMONSTRATED TOWARDS ME AND AUSTRALIA.<br />
IDEEPLY APPRECIATE THIS AND SEE IT AS PROVIDING AN ABSOLUTELY<br />
SOLID BASIS ON. WHICH FUTURE AUSTRALIA/ THAILAND RELATIONS CAN<br />
D EVE LOP.<br />
. BOTH AUSTRALIAN AND THAILAND WANT PEACE, STABILITY AND ECONOMIC<br />
GROWTH IN THE REGION. a c / 14A </p>
<p>4A<br />
THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT IS GIVING A HIGH PRIORITY TO ITS<br />
EFFORTS IN THIS DIRECTION<br />
CRUCIAL TO THIS IS UNDERSTANDING,<br />
IN PART THIS MEANS BEING ABLE TO CROSS SOCIAL AND CULTURAL<br />
DIVIDES, BRIDGING SUCH DIVIDES NOT ONLY REQUIRES AN ABILITY TO<br />
ACCEPT DIFFERENCE, BUT ALSO REQUIRES THE TYPE OF FAMILIARITY<br />
BORN ONLY OF YEARS OF INTERACTION AND JOINT ENDEAVOUR,<br />
IT IS PLEASING THAT AUSTRALIANS IN INCREASING NUMBERS ARE<br />
GETTING OUT INTO THE REGION AND BUILDING EXTENSIVE NETWORKS<br />
OF PRODUCTIVE CONTACT, </p>
<p>EQUALLY IMPORTANTLY A GROWING NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM THE REGION<br />
CAN CLAIM FIRST HAND EXPERIENCE OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE VALUE OF SUCH PERSON-TO-PERSON CONTACT, OF INTERACTION<br />
BETWEEN OUR SOC. IETIES, IS INESTIMABLE.<br />
WE SEE AT WORK IN THIS REGION THE UNDERLYING TRENDS THAT AREFUNDAMENTALLY<br />
RESHAPING THE CHARACTER OF CONTEMPORARY TRADE<br />
AND PRODUCTION PATTERNS.<br />
WORLD TRADE IS IMPOSING INCREASINGLY COMPETITIVE OBLIGATIONS,<br />
AND MAJOR STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENTS AND TECHNOLOGICAL INNOVATIONS<br />
THROUGHOUT THE WORLD S INDUSTRIAL NATIONS ARE RESULTING IN<br />
MAJOR SHIFTS IN WORLD PRODUCTION AND CONSUMPTION PATTERNS.<br />
RISING LIVING STANDARDS AND INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT IN DEVELOPING<br />
COUNTRIES MANY OF THEM IN OUR OWN REGION ARE CONTRIBUTING<br />
TO THESE SHIFTS.<br />
WHILE THE WORLD ECONOMY HAS BEEN STRUGGLING TO ABSORB THE<br />
IMPACT OF THE OIL CRISES AND PROLONGED RECESSION IN INDUSTRIAL<br />
COUNTRIES, THIS REGION HAS NOT ONLY MANAGED TO ADJUST EFFECTIVELY;<br />
IT HAS CONTINUED TO RECORD ECONOMIC GROWTH RATES WHICH ARE<br />
IMPRESSIVE BY ANY STANDARDS.<br />
THE ASEAN REGION'S GROWTH HAS ALSO BEEN STRENGTHENED BY ITS STRONG<br />
AND INCREASING INVOLVEMENT IN INTERNATIONAL TRADE, AND ESPECIALLY<br />
BY THE INCREASING FOREIGN TRADE ORIENTATION OF ITS MANUFACTURING<br />
INDUSTRY IN RECENT YEARS. </p>
<p>FOR ASEAN, LIKE AUSTRALIA, THE STRONG GROWTH OF IMPORT<br />
DEMAND IN OUR NEIGHBOUR, JAPAN, HAS CONTRIBUTED TO A MORE<br />
FAVOURABLE INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC ENVIRONMENT IN RECENT<br />
DECADES, AND HAS STIMULATED OUR INTERACTION WITH EACH OTHER.<br />
THE RAPID GROWTH OF JAPAN HAS CONTRIBUTED TO AN APPRECIATIONI<br />
OF WHAT IS NECESSARY FOR ECONOMIC EXPANSION, AND OF WHAT IS<br />
POSSIBLE, THROUGHOUT OUR REGION,<br />
WHILE DIFFERENT INSTITUTIONS AND CULTURAL PATTERNS DO NOT<br />
ALLOW THE USE OF JAPANESE PATTERNS OF DEVELOPMENT AS A MODEL<br />
SIMPLY TO BE COPIED, WE HAVE ALL BEEN IMPRESSED BY THE RAPID<br />
STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT IN JAPAN'S EXPORT-ORIENTED INDUSTRIAL<br />
SECTOR, IN RESPONSE TO INTERNATIONAL MARKET CONDITIONS.<br />
PUT SIMPLY, A LOT OF JAPAN'S SUCCESS HAS RUBBED OFF ON THE<br />
REGION WITHIN WHICH IT IS LOCATED,<br />
AT THE SAME TIME MANY COUNTRIES OF THE REGION HAVE DEMONSTRATED<br />
A DYNAMISM OF THEIR OWN.<br />
WITH FEW EXCEPTIONS THE ECONOMIES OF THE WESTERN PACIFIC<br />
HAVE ACCEPTED THE ADVANTAGES FOR GROWTH OF EXPORT-ORIENTED<br />
INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT, AND THE RAPID STRUCTURAL ADJUSTMENT<br />
WITH WHICH THEY ARE ASSOCIATED, .1/ 7 </p>
<p>COUNTRIES OF THIS REGION HAVE ADJUSTED QUICKLY INTO GROWTH<br />
AREAS OF THE WORLD MARKET,<br />
THEY HAVE ALSO BECOME VERY COMPETITIVE IN SLOWER GROWING<br />
MARKETS, THEIR EXPOSURE TO INTERNATIONAL COMPETITION HAS HASTENED<br />
THE PROCESS OF SOPHISTICATION OF THEIR MANUFACTURING AND<br />
SERVICES SECTORS,<br />
AN IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTING FACTOR IN THIS HAS BEEN THE<br />
STRIKING GROWTH OF ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIPS WITHIN THE<br />
REGION, THE INTERDEPENDENCE OF THE REGION IS A FACT WHICH IS NOW<br />
WELL UNDERSTOOD,<br />
THE SUPPLY CAPACITY WITHIN THE PACIFIC REGION OFFERS ADEQUATE<br />
POTENTIAL FOR MEETING THE BULK OF PRESENT OR PROSPECTIVE<br />
IMPORT DEMAND REQUIREMENTS AND FOR PROVIDING A LARGE MEASURE<br />
OF REGIONAL FOOD AND RESOURCE TRADE SECURITY,<br />
THIS PROVIDES A SECURE BASIS FOR COUNTRIES WHICH ARE<br />
LESS WELL ENDOWED WITH NATURAL RESOURCES TO PURSUE STRATEGIES<br />
OF RAPID INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT. </p>
<p>ALMOST 40 PER CENT OF THE WESTERN PACIFIC REGION'S TRADE IS<br />
INTRA-REGIONAL,<br />
THE INTRA-REGIONAL COMPONENT GREW BY AROUND 24 PER CENT PER<br />
ANNUM BETWEEN 1970 AND 1980 SOMEWHAT FASTER THAN THE GROWTH<br />
OF WORLD TRADE AS A WHOLE.<br />
THERE ARE ALSO STRONG INVESTMENT AND COMMERCIAL LINKS IN THE<br />
REGION AND POLITICAL TIES ARE INCREASINGLY STRONG.<br />
THIS INTERDEPENDENCE SUGGESTS THAT COUNTRIES IN THE REGION<br />
WILL CONTINUE TO BENEFIT FROM EACH OTHER'S GROWTH,<br />
THESE TRENDS REINFORCE MY VIEW THAT A SOUND BA. SIS EXISTS<br />
WITHIN THIS REGION TO ENHANCE ITS OWN PROSPERITY THROUGH<br />
CO-OPERATIVE ACTION AND TO CONTRIBUTE IMPORTANTLY TO GLOBAL<br />
ECONOMIC WELFARE.<br />
FAR FROM BEING INCOMPATIBLE THESE TWIN OBJECTIVES ARE MUTUALLY<br />
REINFORCING: THE MOST USEFUL FORMS OF REGIONAL CO-OPERATION<br />
ARE CONSISTENT WITH AND MAY WELL ENHANCE THE PROSPECTS OF<br />
ACTION ON A BROADER MULTILATERAL BASIS, ESPECIALLY GIVEN THE<br />
RAPIDLY GROWING IMPORTANCE OF WESTERN PACIFIC COUNTRIES IN<br />
THE WORLD ECONOMY.<br />
CO-ORDINATED ACTION BY THE ASEAN COUNTRIES IS A CONTEMPORARY<br />
AND SUCCESSFUL EXAMPLE OF REGIONAL ACTION CONTRIBUTING TO<br />
IMPROVEMENTS IN THE MULTILATERAL TRADING SYSTEM, ./ 9 </p>
<p>ON A SOMEWHAT BROADER BASIS, I SEE NO REASON WHY COUNTRIES<br />
OF THE REGION SHOULD NOT JOIN TOGETHER, IN A MANNER<br />
CONSISTENT WITH THEIR SHARED INTERESTS AND CAPACITIES, TO<br />
SECURE GENERALLY AGREED OBJECTIVES.<br />
MOST COUNTRIES OF THE REGION, FOR EXAMPLE, ACCEPT THE<br />
ADVANTAGES OF A HIGH LEVEL OF INVOLVEMENT IN INTERNATIONAL<br />
TRADE, AND OF THE MARKET DISCIPLINE ASSOCIATED WITH THAT,<br />
AS WELL AS WELCOMING FOREIGN INVESTMENT.<br />
CONTINUED GROWTH OF COUNTRIES OF THE REGION HAS THEREFORE<br />
BEEN THREATENED BY THE RECENT SLOW-DOWN AND DECLINE IN<br />
WORLD TRADE.<br />
THE RECENT RECESSION-INDUCED PROLIFERATION OF PROTECTIONIST<br />
BARRIERS, AND THE ENCROACHMENT OF BILATERALISM IN TRADE<br />
ARRANGEMENTS, CONSTITUTE MAJOR CHALLENGES TO THE VERY<br />
BASIS OF THE ORDERLY INTERNATIONAL TRADING SYSTEM UPON WHICH<br />
WE ALL DEPEND,<br />
WE NEED CONCERTED EFFORTS TO RE-ESTABLISH CONDITIONS CONSISTENT<br />
WITH AN OPEN, MULTILATERAL TRADE REGIME. WE MUST GET BEYOND<br />
WORDS AND EXHORTATIONS PURPOSEFUL ACTION AND A SENSE OF<br />
COMMITMENT IS WHAT IS REQUIRED. </p>
<p>IN LINE WI'TH THI* S', WE OF THE REGION SHOULD BE SOMEWHAT MORE<br />
ACTIVE, AND THEREFORE MORE EFFECTIVE IN SECURING ADHERENCE<br />
TO THIS PRI'NCIPLE, ESPECIALLY IN RESPECT OF THE TRADE IN<br />
GOODS THAT ARE OF SPECIAL INTEREST TO BOTH INDUSTRIALISED AND<br />
DEVELOPING COUN4TRIES IN THE REGION.<br />
MANY OF YOU WOULD BE AWARE THAT UNITED STATES TRADE<br />
REPRESENTATIVE BROCK RECENTLY PROPOSED THAT A NEW ROUND<br />
OF INTERNATIONAL TRADE NEGOTIATIONS COMMENCE IN 1987, WITH<br />
PREPARATION TO BEGIN IN LATE 1984 OR EARLY 1985.<br />
REPRESENTATIVE BROCK HAS SUGGESTED THAT THE NEW ROUND, AMONG<br />
OTHER THINGS,, FOCUS ON REDUCING THE NON-TARIFF BARRIERS TO<br />
TRADE IN INDUSTRY AND AGRICULTURE, PRIMARILY GOVERNMENT<br />
SUBS IDIES.<br />
MANY COUNTRIES IN THIS REGION HAVE PARTICULAR PROBLEMS WITH<br />
SUCH MATTERS AND WOULD STAND TO GAIN CONSIDERABLY FROM ANY<br />
PROCESS WHICH MIGHT SECURE PROGRESS ON THEM,<br />
THE DOMINANCE OF GATT BY THE ESTABLISHED INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES<br />
AND THE TREATMENT OF TRADE IN AGRICULTURAL COMMODITIES AS<br />
" SPECIAL HAS LED TO THE DENIAL OF THE INTERESTS OF FOODEXPORTING<br />
COUNTRIES LIKE AUSTRALIA AND THAILAND. THIS<br />
DOMINANCE HAS ALSO LED TO THE DENIAL OF THE INTERESTS OF<br />
NEWLY INDUSTRIALISING COUNTRIES LIKE ALL OF THE ASEAN MEMBERS<br />
IN RESPECT OF LABOUR INTENSIVE EXPORTS SUCH AS TEXTILES,<br />
CLOTHING AND FOOTWEAR. </p>
<p>11.<br />
AUSTRALIA FOR ITS PART WOULD STRONGLY SUPPORT A NEW ROUND<br />
OF MULTILATERAL TRADE NEGOTIATIONS, BUT ONLY IF IT WAS<br />
CONFIDENT THAT IT WOULD ADDRESS SERIOUSLY AND EFFECTIVELY<br />
THESE MATTERS-OF SPECIAL IMPORTANCE TO AUSTRALIA, NEW<br />
ZEALAND AND OUR DEVELOPING COUNTRY NEIGHBOURS IN THE<br />
ASIA PACIFIC REGION'<br />
THE CHANCES OF ACHIEVING AN APPROPRIATELY STRUCTURED<br />
ROUND OF NEGOTIATIONS WOULD BE GREATLY ENHANCED IF THE<br />
COUNTRIES OF THIS REGION WERE TO APPLY THEIR FULL AND UNITED<br />
WEIGHT TO ITS ACHIEVEMENT.<br />
CERTAINLY THE DAY SHOULD BE LONG PAST WHEN NEGOTIATIONS<br />
OF THE KIND NOW PROPOSED CAN, AS IN PREVIOUS ROUNDS,<br />
RESTRICT SERIOUS DELIBERATIONS TO PARTICULAR TARIFF<br />
REDUCTIONS AND SELECTIVE FORMS OF MARKET LIBERALISATION<br />
OF-INTEREST ONLY TO A LIMITED NUMBER OF INDUSTRIAL MAJORS,<br />
THIS REGION AS. A REGION BY WHICH I MEAN THE WESTERN<br />
PACIFIC, INCLUDING JAPAN SHOULD BE CONSIDERING HOW IT<br />
MIGHT MOST EFFECTIVELY APPROACH THESE NEGOTIATIONS.<br />
THE REGION NEEDS TO BECOME INCREASINGLY AWARE OF THE KIND<br />
OF IDENTIFIABLE AND SPECIAL ROLE IT CAN PLAY IN TRADE<br />
NEGOTIATIONS OF THIS KIND.<br />
NOT TO DO SO MIGHT WELL MEAN THAT THE COMPETITIVE EDGE MANY<br />
IN THE REGION NOW ENJOY IN SO MANY AREAS COULD BE ERODED. </p>
<p>12.<br />
AUSTRALIA, THE ASEAN COUNTRIES, NEW ZEALAND AND THE MARKET<br />
ECONOMIES OF NORTHEAST ASIA SHOULD WORK WITHIN THE<br />
MULTILATERAL SYSTEM TO ENSURE THAT ANY NEGOTIATIONS ARE<br />
ABOUT GENUINE TRADE LIBERALISATION.<br />
WE SHOULD ALSO ENCOURAGE THE EFFORTS OF THE UNITED STATES AND<br />
CANADA IN THIS DIRECTION.<br />
THIS KIND OF RESULT WOULD ENSURE THAT THE REGION CAN<br />
MAXIMISE ITS OWN GROWTH POTENTIAL AND AT THE SAME TIME<br />
IMPROVE THE WORLD TRADING ENVIRONMENT,<br />
THE MAJOR ESTABLISHED TRADING POWERS HAVE NEVER SEEMED<br />
LESS ABLE TO FORMULATE POLICIES WHICH WILL IMPROVE THE<br />
TRADING ENVIRONMENT.<br />
WE IN THE REGION THEREFORE OWE IT TO OURSELVES TO FILL THE<br />
VACUUM. I RECOGNISE THAT CO-ORDINATION OF A REGIONAL PERSPECTIVE ON<br />
THESE MATTERS WILL BE NO EASY MATTER.<br />
AT THE VERY LEAST WE SHOULD HAVE TO PROMOTE AN ATMOSPHERE<br />
CONDUCIVE TO THE ADOPTION OF SPECIFIC CO-ORDINATED POLICY<br />
ACTIONS TO ACHIEVE SHARED TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT OBJECTIVES, / 13 </p>
<p>13.<br />
THIS OBVIOUSLY WILL TAKE TIME AND A DELIBERATE EFFORT WILL BE<br />
NEEDED TO RECONCILE DIFFERING NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES ON THE<br />
BASI-S OF ENHANCED UNDERSTANDING OF THE CRITICAL ISSUES.<br />
IT IS IN THE INTERESTS OF ALL OF US THAT THE EFFORT BE MADE.,<br />
AUSTRALIA IS PREPARED TO PLAY ITS PART. IN MY DISCUSSIONS WITH<br />
PRIME MINISTER PREM YESTERDAY, I ASSURED HIM THAT AUSTRALIA WAS<br />
PREPARED TO TAKE ACTION IN ALL RELEVANT INTERNATIONAL FORA TO<br />
TRY TO ACHIEVE THE CREATION OF A MORE OPEN TRADING ENVIRONMENT.<br />
IT IS GENERALLY RECOGNISED THAT THE AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY<br />
ASSISTANCE PROGRAM IS HIGHLY TRANSPARENT. IT IS LESS OFTEN<br />
APPRECIATED THAT BOTH NOMINAL AND EFFECTIVE AUSTRALIAN RATES<br />
OF ASSISTANCE TO THE MANUFACTURING SECTOR HAVE DECLINED<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY IN THE PAST FIFTEEN YEARS By 33 PER CENT IN<br />
THE CASE OF THE NOMINAL RATE OF ASSISTANCE AND By 28 PER CENT<br />
IN THE EFFECTIVE RATE IN THE PERIOD 1968-69 TO 1981-82.<br />
BUT IF OUR BEST EFFORTS SHOULD FAIL TO OVERCOME THE CONSISTENT<br />
COMMITMENT OF MANY OF THE OLD INDUSTRIAL COUNTRIES TO PATTERNS<br />
OF TRADE THAT DISCRIMINATE AGAINST AUSTRALIA, THE ASEAN<br />
COUNTRIES, AND OTHER COUNTRIES IN OUR REGION, WE SHOULD NOT LET<br />
THAT BE THE END OF THE MATTER.<br />
THERE WOULD STILL BE SCOPE FOR NEGOTIATIONS ON TRADE EXPANSION<br />
AMONG COUNTRIES WITHIN OUR OWN REGION, ON A NON-DISCRIMINATORY<br />
BASIS, BUT FOCUSSED ON COMMODITIES IN WHICH COUNTRIES IN OUR<br />
OWN REGION ARE THE MOST COMPETITIVE SUPPLIERS. </p>
<p>AUSTRALIA WOULD BE WILLING TO JOIN OTHER COUNTRIES IN OUR<br />
REGION IN A REGIONALLY BASED SEARCH FOR A NON-DISCRIMINATORY<br />
AGREEMENT ON TRADE EXPANSION THAT SERVED THE NATIONAL INTERESTS<br />
OF EACH OF OUR COUNTRIES.<br />
THE RECENT HOBART TRADE CONFERENCE ON PROTECTIONISM AND THE<br />
ASIAN PACIFIC REGION'WAS A USEFUL FIRST STEP IN EXPLORING<br />
THE POSSIBILITIES SUCH AN APPROACH MIGHT OFFER.<br />
THE RATE AT WHICH THE BILATERAL TRADE AND ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP<br />
BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND THAILAND HAS DEVELOPED IN RECENT YEARS<br />
SUGGESTS THAT THERE IS REAL SCOPE FOR JOINT ACTION OF THE KIND<br />
I AM ADVOCATING.<br />
THAILAND, A COUNTRY RICH IN HUMAN AND MATERIAL RESOURCES,<br />
CLEARLY HAS THE CAPACITY AND FLEXIBILITY TO MAKE ITS OWN<br />
DISTINCTIVE CONTRIBUTION TO REGIONAL GROWTH PATTERNS.<br />
THE THAI ECONOMY IS PROVING TO BE AMONG THE MOST ROBUST<br />
WITHIN THE REGION.<br />
ITS TRADITIONAL STRENGTH AS A COMMODITY PRODUCER HAS LONG<br />
BEEN RECOGNISED.<br />
MORE RECENTLY INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT HAS BEEN PROCEEDING RAPIDLY.<br />
OPPORTUNITIES ABOUND IN THESE CIRCUMSTANCES FOR INVESTORS,<br />
EXPORTERS AND CONSULTANTS.<br />
0<br />
BILATERAL AUSTRALIA/ TAHI IAND TRADE REFLECTS THIS, </p>
<p>IT HAS BEEN GROWING RAPIDLY,<br />
AS IT HAS DONE SO THE EXTENT TO WHICH WE SHARE COMMON INTERESTS<br />
HAS BECOME INCREASINGLY. APPARENT.<br />
As COMMODITY PRODUCERS BOTH OF FOODSTUFFS AND MINERALS<br />
WE HAVE AN INTEREST IN SEEING THAT THE ADVANTAGES OF AN OPEN,<br />
MULTILATERAL TRADING SYSTEM ACCRUE TO THESE PRODUCTS.<br />
IN THIS CONTEXT IT IS IN OUR MUTUAL INTERESTS TO WORK TOGETHER<br />
TO DISMANTLE THOSE BARRIERS BOTH TARIFF AND NON-TARIFF<br />
IMPEDING TRADE BASED ON RATIONAL ECONOMIC PRINCIPLES.<br />
SECOND, AUSTRALIA HAS TECHNOLOGY, EXPERTISE AND EQUIPMENT WHICH<br />
CAN ASSIST THAILAND IN ITS ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.<br />
WE HAVE A LOT TO OFFER IN THE FIELDS OF RURAL AND MINERAL<br />
RESOURCE DEVELOPMENT, AND ALSO IN THE AREAS OF PUBLIC HEALTH<br />
AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT.<br />
PRIME MINISTER PREM EXPRESSED INTEREST YESTERDAY IN AUSTRALIA<br />
INCREASING ITS INVOLVEMENT IN THESE AREAS IN THAILAND, AND I<br />
HAVE AGREED THAT AUSTRALIAN AND THAI OFFICIALS SHOULD WORK<br />
TOGETHER TO IDENTIFY SPECIFIC PROPOSALS FOR THE CONSIDERATION<br />
OF THE TWO GOVERNMENTS,<br />
NEEDLESS TO SAY IF EFFECT IS TO BE GIVEN TO THESE PROPOSALS<br />
BOTH GOVERNMENTS WILL REQUIRE THE ACTIVE SUPPORT OF THE PRIVATE<br />
SECTOR IN BOTH COUNTRIES, </p>
<p>16.<br />
I AM SURE THAT IT IS HELPFUL TO ALL OF YOU HERE TO HAVE<br />
THIS SENSE OF THE PRIORITIES OF OUR RESPECTIVE GOVERNMENTS<br />
FOR FUTURE CO-OPERATIVE SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT IN<br />
THAILAND,.<br />
As FOR THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT, IT IS DETERMINED TO IMPROVE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S EXPORT PERFORMANCE,<br />
THE GOVERNMENT HAS ALREADY TAKEN STEPS TO GIVE EFFECT TO<br />
THIS INTENTION,<br />
IT HAS ANNOUNCED A NUMBER OF MEASURES DESIGNED TO ENABLE THE<br />
EXPORT FINANCE AND INSURANCE CORPORATION TO OFFER MORE<br />
ATTRACTIVE AND FLEXIBLE FACILITIES IN THE FIELD OF EXPORT<br />
FINANCE. THIS WILL BE OF BENEFIT NOT ONLY TO AUSTRALIAN EXPORTERS,<br />
BUT TO THOSE WHO WISH TO AVAIL THEMSELVES OF AUSTRALIAN<br />
MACHINERY AND EQUIPMENT FOR THEIR ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.<br />
PENDING THE OUTCOME OF THE CURRENT EXAMINATION OF AUSTRALIA'S<br />
AID PROGRAM BY THE JACKSON COMMITTEE, THE GOVERNMENT HAS<br />
SUBSTANTIALLY INCREASED TO $ 60 MILLION THE TOTAL FUNDING"<br />
COMMITMENT PERMISSIBLE TO THE AUSTRALIAN DEVELOPMENT<br />
ASSISTANCE BUREAU TO PROVIDE AID GRANTS IN CONJUNCTION WITH<br />
EFIC LOANS TO ASSIST COUNTRIES ENTERING UPON DEVELOPMENT<br />
PROJECTS BASED ON AUSTRALIAN SOURCES, S. 117 </p>
<p>17,<br />
As WELL AS TAKING SUCH STEPS TO ASSIST AUSTRALIAN EXPORTERS,<br />
AND ENCOURAGE THEM TO BE MORE OUTWARD LOOKING, THE<br />
GOVERNMENT IS DEVELOPING A MORE TARGETTED APPROACH TO EXPORT<br />
DEVELOPMENT. A MEDIUM-SIZED COUNTRY LIKE AUSTRALIA CANNOT<br />
AFFORD TO SPREAD ITS EFFORTS TOO THINLY, AND ACCORDINGLY<br />
WE ARE GIVING PRIORITY TO DEVELOPING THE ECONOMIC LINKS<br />
WITH THE ASIAN PACIFIC REGION,<br />
A FURTHER FACTOR ENHANCING ECONOMIC RELATIONS BETWEEN<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THAILAND HAS BEEN THE USEFUL, IF NOT DRAMATIC,<br />
CONTRIBUTION TO THAILAND'S ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN INVESTMENT.<br />
FOR THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF 1983 THE NUMBER OF APPROVALS<br />
OF AUSTRALIAN INVESTMENT PROPOSALS BY THE THAILAND BOARD<br />
OF INVESTMENT EXCEEDED THOSE OF ANY OTHER COUNTRY.<br />
A NUMBER OF JOINT AUSTRALIAN-THAI VENTURES ARE THE LEADING<br />
COMPANIES IN THEIR RESPECTIVE SECTORS IN THAI INDUSTRY.<br />
WHILE THE LEVEL OF AUSTRALIAN INVESTMENT IN THAILAND IS<br />
NOT LARGE, THE MANAGEMENT SKILLS AND EXPERTISE ACCOMPANYING<br />
IT ARE OF PARTICULAR RELEVANCE.<br />
AUSTRALIA'S EXPERTISE IN AGRICULTURE, FOOD PROCESSING,<br />
MINERALS DEVELOPMENT AND AGRICULTURAL AND MINING MACHINERY<br />
DEVELOPMENT ARE WELL RECOGNISED, / 18 </p>
<p>18.<br />
THEY FIND A PARTICULAR APPLICATION IN OUR AID PROGRAM TO<br />
THAILAND. THAT PROGRAM, . WHICH THIS YEAR IS EXPECTED TO TOTAL AROUND<br />
MILLION, IS DEVOTED PRINCIPALLY TO AGRICULTURAL PROJECTS<br />
BUT IS ALSO SUPPORTING THAILAND'S EFFORTS TO REPLACE OIL<br />
IMPORTS WITH INDIGENOUS ENERGY RESOURCES AND IS CONTRIBUTING<br />
THROUGH ROAD AND DAM CONSTRUCTION TO'THAILAND'S INFRASTRUCTURE<br />
DEVELOPMENT. OBVIOUSLY THE RANGE AND DEPTH OF AUSTRALIA'S RELATIONS WITH<br />
THAILAND IS CONSIDERABLE,<br />
THIS CONTRIBUTES IMPORTANTLY TO PROSPERITY IN BOTH OUR<br />
COUNTRIES. IT ALSO CONSTITUTES A VERY SOUND BASIS UPON WHICH TO DEVELOP<br />
CO-OPERATIVE POLICY ACTION INTO THE LONGER TERM.<br />
THIS FINDS PARTICULAR AND IMMEDIATE APPLICATION IN OUR SHARED<br />
INTERESTS AS COMMODITY PRODUCERS,<br />
WE HAVE BOTH SUFFERED THE CONSEQUENCES OF RECESSION IND. UCED<br />
FALLS IN COMMODITY PRICESj AND BOTH STAND TO GAIN FROM A<br />
RESTORATION OF COMMODITY PRICES THAT JUSTIFY INVESTMENT. / 19 </p>
<p>19,<br />
THE SITUATION IN THE SUGAR MARKET IS A MATTER OF ESPECIAL<br />
ANXIETY. AUSTRALIA AND THAILAND HAVE BOTH BEEN WORKING TOGETHER I<br />
BELIEVE VERY EFFECTIVELY IN THE HOPE OF SECURING A NEW<br />
INTERNATIONAL SUGAR AGREEMENT, WITH EEC MEMBERSHIP, WHICH<br />
WOULD STABILISE PRICES AT LEVELS REMUNERATIVE FOR EFFICIENT<br />
SUGAR PRODUCERS,<br />
THE SUBSIDISED SUGAR EXPORTS OF THE EEC HAVE IN PAST YEARS<br />
GROSSLY DISTORTED WORLD SUGAR MARKETS TO THE DETRIMENT OF<br />
BOTH THE THAI AND AUSTRALIAN SUGAR INDUSTRIES.<br />
PROBLEMS IN THE TIN MARKET HAVE ALSO BEEN OF CONCERN NOT<br />
ONLY TO AUSTRALIA AND THAILAND, BUT ALSO TO MALAYSIA AND<br />
INDONESIA.<br />
AUSTRALIA SHARES THOSE CONCERNS,<br />
IT IS, I BELIEVE, A STRONG REGIONAL INTEREST THAT STABLE<br />
CONDITIONS BE RESTORED TO THE TIN MARKET.<br />
ACCORDINGLY AS I YESTERDAY ADVISED PRIME MINISTER PREM WE<br />
HAVE DECIDED IMMEDIATELY TO JOIN OUR ASEAN NEIGHBOURS,<br />
THAILAND, MALAYSIA AND INDONESIA, AS MEMBERS OF THE RECENTLY<br />
FORMED ASSOCIATION OF TIN PRODUCING COUNTRIES ( ATPC). </p>
<p>WE SEE THIS AS USEFULLY COMPLEMENTING ACTIVITIES OTHERWISE<br />
BEING MOUNTED UNDER THE INTERNATIONAL TIN AGREEMENT ( ITA).<br />
MORE GENERALLY AUSTRALIA IS COMMITTED TO BUILDING A STRONG,<br />
MUTUALLY BENEFICIAL ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP WITH ITS NEIGHBOURS<br />
IN ASEAN AND THE WI* DER REGIO0* N OF ASIA AND THE PACIFIC.<br />
THE ASEAN COUNTRIES HAVE BECOME A MAJOR MARKET FOR<br />
AUSTRALIAN GOODS AND EVERYTHING POINTS TO0 CONTINUATION AND<br />
INTENSIFICATION OF THIS PATTERN.<br />
FIELDS SUCH AS BANKING, COMMUNICATIONS, SOFTWARE, INTERMEDIATE<br />
TECHNOLOGY, CONSULTING SKILLS AND EDUCATION ARE ONLY NOW<br />
OPENING UP.<br />
AUSTRALIA HAS A CONSIDERABLE AMOUNT TO OFFER IN THESE AREAS<br />
AS WELL AS IN NEW AND GROWING MARKETS FOR RAW MATERIALS,<br />
PRIMARY PRODUCTS, AND PROCESSED GOODS.<br />
REALISATION OF THE FULL POTENTIAL PRESENTED BY THESE<br />
OPPORTUNITIES WILL HINGE IN PART ON A VERY CONSIDERABLE<br />
STEPPING UP OF AUSTRALIAN INVOLVEMENT WITH THE REGION.<br />
AUSTRALIAN INVESTMENT IN GROWTH MARKETS, A CAREFUL BUT<br />
DELIBERATE SEARCHING OUT OF JOINT-VENTURE OPPORTUNITIES,<br />
AND DELIBERATE ATTENTION TO CONSOLIDATING AND DEVELOPING<br />
SUPPORT SERVICES, PARTICULARLY IN BANKING AND TRANSPORTATION,<br />
ARE AMONG THE ELEMENTS MOST CRUCIAL TO SUCCESSFUL, LONG-TERM<br />
CONSOLIDATION AIND EXPANSION OF THIS INVOLVEMENT, ./ 21 </p>
<p>21.<br />
THIS IN TURN PRESUMES AN ABILITY TO DEVELOP THE SKILLS,<br />
POLICIES AND ATTITUDES NECESSARY TO MATCH THE DEMANDS OF<br />
THE REGION.<br />
WE ARE HELPED CONSIDERABLY IN THIS, AS I SUGGESTED AT THE<br />
OUTSET, BY THE UNDERSTANDING GENERATED BY THE INCREASINGLY<br />
LARGE TWO-WAY FLOW OF PEOPLE BETWEEN AUSTRALIA AND THE<br />
ASEAN COUNTRIES,<br />
WHAT HAS BEEN LACKING UNTIL NOW, HOWEVER, HAS BEEN A<br />
COHERENT STRATEGY,<br />
THE TIME HAS COME TO MOVE BEYOND PIECEMEAL, OFTEN INCONSISTENT,<br />
RESPONSES TO VAGUE GLIMMERINGS OF OPPORTUNITY, TO A CAREFULLY<br />
TARGETTED, DELIBERATELY INTEGRATED APPROACH THAT COMBINES<br />
THE BEST THAT ON-THE-SPOT EXPERIENCE CAN OFFER WITH NECESSARY<br />
CAPITAL EXPERTISE AND POLICY BACK-UP.<br />
WHILE REALISATION OF THIS OBJECTIVE WILL REQUIRE A GREAT<br />
DEAL OF EFFORT, * A COMMITMENT TO DELIBERATE, ., BALANCED, AND<br />
CONSISTENT APPROACHES IS IN AUSTRALIA'S VIEW VITAL.<br />
WHAT IS NEEDED NOW IS MOST CAREFUL ATTENTION TO MATTERS<br />
SUCH AS CONDITIONS CONDUCIVE TO A CONFIDENT INVESTMENT<br />
CLIMATE, THE EFFECTIVENESS OF MECHANISMS FOR TECHNOLOGY<br />
TRANSFER, AND THE ADOPTION OF TRADE AND ECONOMIC POLICIES<br />
SUPPORTIVE OF DEVELOPMENT STRATEGIES APPROPRIATE TO<br />
CONTINUED GROWTH IN INCOMES WITHIN THE REGION, </p>
<p>22.<br />
ALL GOVERNMENTS WITHIN THE REGION DO, I BELIEVE, SHARE AN<br />
INTERST IN SUCH MATTERS,<br />
I HAVE ALREADY SUGGESTED THAT A PARTICULAR APPLICATION OF<br />
THAT INTEREST WOULD LIE IN THE GENERATION OF A JOINT<br />
REGIONAL APPROACH TO ISSUES OF COMMON CONCERN SHOULD A FUTURE<br />
ROUND OF MULTILATERAL TRADE NEGOTIATIONS MATERIALISE,<br />
BUT LOOKING FURTHER INTO THE FUTURE AND CONSIDERING THE<br />
DEPTH OF SHARED INTERESTS BETWEEN COUNTRIES OF THE REGION,<br />
CO-OPERATIVE ENDEAVOUR BETWEEN US SHOULD NOT BE CONFINED<br />
TO TRADE MATTERS.<br />
THE MORE WE CAN CONSOLIDATE ECONOMIC AND TRADING INTERESTS<br />
BETWEEN ALL COUNTRIES OF THE REGION, THE GREATER NOT ONLY<br />
WILL BE THE CONTRIBUTION TO INDIVIDUAL COUNTRY PROSPERITY<br />
BUT ALSO THE STIMULUS TO INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC GROWTH AND<br />
RECOVERY,<br />
ACCORDINGLY RATHER THAN BEING CONTINUALLY DAUNTED BY THE<br />
COMPLEXITIES AND SENSITIVITIES OF ACHIEVING EFFECTIVE<br />
CONSOLIDATION OF SUCH INTERESTS, WE SHOULD, AT BOTH THE<br />
NATIONAL AND REGIONAL LEVELSj BE PREPARED TO PUT ASIDE THE<br />
BLINKERS AND BEGIN SERIOUSLY EXPLORING THE SCOPE FOR WELLCO-<br />
ORDINATED, TRULY CO-OPERATIVE APPROACHES,<br />
UTLIMATELY WE ALL STAND TO GAIN FROM SUCH APPROACHES, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
