<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2014</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/03/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002014.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS P. M. No. 26, 1969<br />
ECONOM. C CONSULTATiONS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr dahn Gorton<br />
The Government met with represeatatives of industry<br />
and commerce in Canberra today.<br />
Today's discussions were with national organisations<br />
representing primiary industries, manufacturing industries and<br />
commerce. The Government saw these organisations in three separate<br />
groups, thereby continuing the practice begun in j-, My last year.<br />
The talks were again worthwhile in providing Ministers<br />
with an up-to-date appreciation of the views of those directly involved<br />
in commerce and industry.<br />
The series of economic consultations will continue<br />
tomorrow when Ministers will hold separate discussions with representatives<br />
of the Export Development Council, the Manufacturing Industries<br />
Advisory Council and the Australian Council of Trade Unions.<br />
Attached is a list of those taking part in today's talks.<br />
CANBERRA, March 1969 </p>
<p>NATIONAL ORGANISATIONS REPRESENTED AT<br />
ECONOMIC CONSULTATIONS<br />
MARCH 1969<br />
Primary Industry Group<br />
National Farmers' Union<br />
of Australia President Mr F. J. McAvoy, CBE<br />
Australian Primary Producers'<br />
Union President Mr R. B. Gerrand<br />
Australian Wool Growers' and<br />
Graziers' Council President Mr B. A. Wright<br />
Australian Wool and Meat<br />
Producers' Federation President Mr R. V. Sewell, OBE<br />
Australian Wheat Growers'<br />
Federation President Mr T. M. Saint<br />
Australian Mining Industry<br />
Council President Mr N. S. Kirby<br />
Manufacturing Industry Group<br />
Associated Chambers of<br />
Manufactures of Australia President Mr J. C. Campbell<br />
Master Builders' Federation<br />
of Australia President Mr R. A. O'Neill<br />
Federal Chamber of Automotive Executive<br />
Industries Member Mr N. W. Lawrance<br />
Commercial Group<br />
Associated Chambers of<br />
Commerce of Australia President Mr B. R. Macklin<br />
Australian Bankers' Association Chairman Mr C. H. Rennie<br />
Australian Council of Retailers President Mr T. Luxton, DSO, MBE </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
