<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2921</transcript-id>
    <title>PREMIERS&#039; CONFERENCE ON PRICES AND INCOMES MATTERS AND ALL OTHER ASPECTS OF INFLATION - OPENING STATEMENT BY PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/05/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002921.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PREMIERS' CONFERENCE ON PRICES AND<br />
INCOMES MATTERS AM) ALL OTHER ASPECTS<br />
01? INFLATION<br />
OPENING STATEMENT BY PRIME MINISTER<br />
There can be today no more important reason for the<br />
Australian Government and the State Governments to come together<br />
than for the purpose of addressing ourselves jointly to action<br />
against inflation. The ready response of all Premiers to the proposal<br />
for this meeting is a measure of your concern about the prob~ lem<br />
of inflation. That concern is fully shared by the Australian<br />
Government and I am convinced by the Australian people.<br />
It is, I may say, a concern which is not peculiar to<br />
Australia. In all the advanced economics of the world, people<br />
are expressing similar concern. Our own position is no worse<br />
than many and a good deal better than some. But that.. as I<br />
shall have reason to point out, is in itself cold comfort.<br />
As you all know, the initiative for this meeting came<br />
from the Premier of Victoria. Mr. Hlamer wrote to me on 9 April<br />
suggesting that what was necessary to achieve effective action<br />
against inflation was the development and implementation of a<br />
comprehensive national prices and incomes policy. He pointed<br />
to the division of relevant constitutional powers between the<br />
Australian Government and the State Governments and. suggested<br />
that a Premiers' conference should be convened in an effort to<br />
achieve close understanding and co-operation between all of us<br />
in this matter. We moved quickly to welcome thait initiative;<br />
and you have responded promptly to my invitation to meet here<br />
today " tto discuss prices and income matters and all other aspects<br />
of inflation" </p>
<p>I 2.<br />
Let there be no doubt as to the seriousness with which<br />
the Australian government views inflation. We have been elected<br />
on a platform of social change. We have promised the Australian<br />
people a program of wide-ranging and overdue reforms in the<br />
social structure of this country. To carry out that program<br />
is the primary objective of this government.<br />
But we now find the possibilities for desirable social<br />
change threatened by a potential resurgence of inflationary<br />
pressures. We are fully alert to the distortions inflation<br />
wreaks on the distribution of incomes; its insidious effect in<br />
reducing the real value of savings; its unfair impact upon those<br />
in greatest need; its adverse longer-term consequences for<br />
growth; and, above all, the danger that if no action is taken<br />
inflation will develop into accelerating inflation.<br />
To the extent that inflationary pressures re-emerged it<br />
would reduce our capacity, both in the Budget and more generally,<br />
to bring about the social changes which are our foremost aim.<br />
Because we have a responsibility to pursue our program to carry<br />
out our mandate we must find effective means of tackling<br />
inflation. We are determined that the realisation of our program<br />
will not be thwarted by any lack of resolution in coping with<br />
inflation, I fully recognize that political views around this table<br />
differ. But in this matter all of us have a common interest.<br />
Inflation adds to the problems of us all. Most certainly,<br />
inflation runs counter to all that my Government stands for and<br />
seeks to achieve. Now that the worst manifestations of last year's </p>
<p>3.<br />
unemployment situation are behind us, we rank inflation as the<br />
number one economic problem. We will do all we can to bring<br />
rising prices under control.<br />
But inflation is an evil which permeates the economy and,<br />
more, the society. It is widely recognised that there is no<br />
simple solution to it-it has to be tackled across a broad front,<br />
and by every means at the command of governments. I hardly need<br />
to add that, in the Australian context, that means that the State<br />
governments have a vital role to play. Mr Iamer's message and the<br />
presence of every Premier acknowledges this fact.<br />
I turn now to the measures which the Australian Government<br />
has already taken, and the further measures which we propose, to<br />
bear down against rising prices:-<br />
SRevaluation: On 23 December within three weeks of taking<br />
office the Australian Government revalued the Australian<br />
dollar. The primary purpose of that measure was not to<br />
curb rising prices but to correct a fundamental disequilibrium<br />
in Australia's balance of payments. But a secondary purpose<br />
was to exert a downward influence on our domestic price level.<br />
In this respect our decision to revalue is having, and for<br />
some time ahead, will continue to have beneficial effects on<br />
prices in wide areas of the economy.<br />
SReaction to Devaluation of the U. S. Dollar: It was with<br />
these same joint considerations in mind that we determined<br />
what reaction should be given to the announcement on<br />
12 February that the United States dollar was to be<br />
devalued. Our decision to sit pat and thereby<br />
appreciate further against the U. S. dollar and any </p>
<p>other currencies which followed it, wholly or in part<br />
was in line with our decision of 23 December. As a result<br />
of these twin decisions, import prices are now stable they<br />
may even be falling moderately. That in itself is testimony<br />
to the beneficial effects of the decisions in providing a<br />
countervailing influence against rising prices. Similarly,<br />
those firms which had previously undertaken borrowings in<br />
foreign currency should now be enjoying actual or prospective<br />
windfall gains as a result of the recent changes in relative<br />
exchange rates. It is our feeling that the sense of<br />
corporate well-being that must bring should also find some<br />
reflection in the market-place for prices.<br />
Inquiry into Proposed B. H. P. Price Rises: At the request<br />
of the nation's largest industrial enterprise we set up an<br />
inquiry into steel price rises proposed by the company. In<br />
the result rises averaging 3 per cent occurred instead of the<br />
rises of 7 per cent proposed. Steel prices have wide<br />
repercussions throughout the economy. There can be no doubt<br />
that, had steel prices risen by 7 per cent, prices generally<br />
would be rising even faster than they now are.<br />
Joint Parliamentary Committee on Prices: Other things being<br />
equal, importers should now be seeing reductions in the landed<br />
prices of their goods. We are concerned to ensure that such<br />
reductions are passed on. They were intended to accrue, and<br />
should accrue, not to a particular group but to the Australian<br />
people as a whole. We look for appropriate action in that<br />
field from the price-setters involved. And to encourage them<br />
in that action we have referred the question to the Joint<br />
Parliamentary Committee on Prices, as one of its first major<br />
areas of investigation.<br />
We have, similarly, referred to that Committee fr investigation<br />
the question of meat prices the recent </p>
<p>sharp rise in which has so greatly contributed to<br />
the large rise in the Consumer Price Index recorded<br />
in the March quarter.<br />
Our attention has been drawn more recently to the<br />
marked disparity which now exists between retail<br />
prices of petrol in Sydney and Melbourne. My colleague,<br />
the Minister for Minerals and Energy, has now received<br />
a report on this matter which has been prepared for the<br />
Australian Automobile Association. As he has said<br />
yesterday in the House, this matter will be pursued<br />
with vigour and to the full limit of the Government's<br />
powers.<br />
Liquidity Measures: As I said in my statement announcing<br />
the revaluation of the Australian dollar, the flood<br />
of foreign capital into Australia had resulted, by the<br />
time we took office, in " a build-up of domestic liquidity<br />
to a dangerously excessive level". With the economy<br />
picking up pace there was here a tinder-box ready for<br />
the match. It was, clearly, imperative that action be<br />
taken to dampen any such prospective conflagration.<br />
Simultaneously therefore with revaluation we moved to<br />
check any further build-up of liquidity from this source<br />
by imposing the 25 per cent deposit requirement scheme<br />
on new borrowings abroad. Such borrowings have, to all<br />
intents and purposes, largely ceased, </p>
<p>Again, by way of follow-up to this the Treasurer<br />
on 1 February last announced measures to broaden<br />
the coverage of restrictions on overseas borrowing<br />
and associated measures. The coverage of the controls<br />
was extended to include not only formal contracts to<br />
borrow but also indirect forms of borrowing and<br />
transactions having a similar effect on capital inflow.<br />
Monetary Policy: The measures I have just referred to<br />
were of course taken within the context of our policies<br />
towards the balance of payments and the inflow of<br />
capital from abroad. But, as I have made clear, they<br />
were also taken having in mind the contribution they<br />
could make towards diminishing a major problem<br />
the state of domestic liquidity. This brings me to<br />
the subject of monetary policy generally.<br />
It is I think agreed on all sides that, whatever other<br />
steps may be necessary to check inflation, all are likely<br />
to prove futile unless fiscal and monetary policies in<br />
the broad are sensibly and responsibly geared to the<br />
productive capacity of the economy. Such policies are<br />
not, in themselves, enough: but we believe and we<br />
are supported by all competent opinion both within<br />
Australia and overseas that they are the essential<br />
basis, the sine qua non, for an effective antiinflationary<br />
strategy. </p>
<p>On the monetary front, with economic activity<br />
continuing to expand strongly, continuation of<br />
the unduly easy stance of monetary policy would<br />
have been fraught with dangers for the period ahead.<br />
We have, accordingly, seen as appropriate the decision<br />
by the Reserve Bank to make a call of one per cent to<br />
the Statutory Reserve Deposits of the major trading<br />
banks in April.<br />
Similarly, in approaching the difficult decisions<br />
involved in setting terms for the May loan recently<br />
announced decisions in which of course you in your<br />
capacities as members of the Loan Council have so<br />
responsibly participated we have had to set aside<br />
what we would have liked to do in favour of what it<br />
was clearly necessary to do. We have, in short, met<br />
the yields which, since the February loan, had emerged<br />
in the market. To have attempted to maintain a lower<br />
yield structure would have meant continuing large-scale<br />
purchases of bonds by the Reserve Bank with consequent<br />
expansionary effects upon the liquidity of the private<br />
sector. In present and prospective circumstances we<br />
were not prepared to countenance such an outcome.<br />
In these connections I should also say that the Treasury<br />
and the Reserve Bank have been asked to make a detailed<br />
study of the various aspects of the regulation of the<br />
financing activities of non-bank financial<br />
intermediaries. </p>
<p>STask Force to Review the Programs of the<br />
Previous Government: The Government is, of<br />
course, aware that in approaching questions of<br />
overall economic management it will be necessary<br />
for it to give considerable attention to fiscal<br />
as well as to monetary policy. As a first step<br />
in that regard I announced on 3 April last the<br />
constitution of a special " task force", under the<br />
Chairmanship of Dr. Coombs, to examine the programs<br />
carried over from the previous government.<br />
Its efforts should assist us in seeing what scope<br />
there may be for pruning expenditures. Clearly,<br />
it will be necessary in that or other ways to<br />
" make room", within the totality of the public<br />
and private demands upon the economy, for the<br />
carrying through of our own priority programs.<br />
SPrices Justification Machinery: My colleague the<br />
Treasurer has, only yesterday, introduced into the<br />
Parliament a Prices Justification Bill, I shall not<br />
seek to detail its provisions here. However, companies<br />
will be required to give prior indication of price<br />
rises so that they can be examined, their effects<br />
assessed and their justification determined by the<br />
Tribunal set up for the purpose. The Tribunal may also<br />
investigate cases where circumstances suggest price<br />
reductions should have occurred, but have not, It<br />
will also be able to inquire into and report on price<br />
increases which companies made prior to the measures<br />
coming into force in the hope of beating the gun, </p>
<p>We shall be appointing to the Tribunal persons of the<br />
standing and quality of those who have constituted the Trade<br />
Practices Tribunal. In that case, of course, the members were<br />
appointed by our predecessors. They have our respect and<br />
confidence. Restrictive Trade Practices Legislation: As an important<br />
aspect of its attitude towards competition policy with<br />
the bearing that has upon the ability of price-setters to<br />
push up prices the Government proposes to introduce<br />
more effective legislation to deal with restrictive trade<br />
practices. The proposed legislation will deal with contracts<br />
in restraint of trade, monopolization, resale price<br />
maintenance, price discrimination, anti-competitive mergers,<br />
exclusive dealing that substantially lessens competition<br />
or leads to a monopoly position and unfair and deceptive<br />
practices affecting consumers. It will deal with these<br />
provisions by directly prohibiting them instead of, as at<br />
present, leaving them to be restrained separately after timeconsuming<br />
enquiries. By this means the legislation will<br />
have an early impact on the economy.<br />
Protection Policy: Another aspect of what I have called<br />
competition policy is to be found, of course, in the<br />
area of protection against competition from overseas. The<br />
Government has confirmed its support for the progressive<br />
review of the tariff by the Tariff Board which is now<br />
in progress. We will ensure that the further references<br />
required to enable the Board to complete its review will go<br />
forward. The Government proposes to establish a Protection Commission<br />
to advise on assistance for both primary and secondary industry.<br />
Some two months ago I asked Sir John Crawford to advise on the<br />
functions, structure, </p>
<p>membership and procedures of the proposed Commission.<br />
Sir John's report will be available about the middle of the<br />
year and the Government will act promptly when the report<br />
has been received.<br />
Action in the The Minister for the Capital Territory,<br />
who is present with us here today, has approved the<br />
preparation of legislation to set up a Business Leases<br />
Review Board to examine harsh, unconscionable or unfair<br />
rentals of commercial premises which are producing<br />
unnecessary inflationary repercussions in the Territory.<br />
The Minister has also approved the establishment of a<br />
comprehensive AOC. T. Homes Insurance Scheme similar to the<br />
successful low premium War Service Homes Insurance Scheme,<br />
The Minister is examining proposals for a public conveyancing<br />
service, controls over excessive advertising and similar ways<br />
of reducing ultimate costs to the consumer. By way of<br />
buttressing, within the Capital Territory, the actions<br />
possible uinder the amb~ it of the Prices Justification Tribunal,<br />
the Minister has also ap~ proved the re-activation of the Prices<br />
Regulation Ordinance which was introduced by the Chifley<br />
Government but which has lain dormant for some years.<br />
* Consumer Protection: The Australian Government has been<br />
concerned about the need for improved means of protecting<br />
consumers against unfair trading practices. To that end<br />
we are moving to exploit the capacities of our own<br />
scientific and technical experts in thle formulation and<br />
implementation of a framework of standards for consumer<br />
products. </p>
<p>11.<br />
The Cities: We believe that inefficient cities are one<br />
source of inflationary pressures. Present-day<br />
inefficiencies in our major cities increase the costs<br />
borne by city dwellers in their capacities as home-buyers,<br />
as commuters, as rate-payers and as taxpayers more generally.<br />
In the longer-term, the policies of the Australian<br />
Government, designed as they will be progressively to<br />
improve the efficiency of city living in Australia and the<br />
welfare of our city dwellers, will contribute to<br />
removing the inflationary pressures which these present<br />
inefficiencies help to generate.<br />
Proposed Establishment of Housing Standards Committee:<br />
As a contribution to improving efficiency and reducing<br />
costs in the housing construction industry, the<br />
Australian Government is contemplating a forum<br />
in which housing standards and guidelines based upon<br />
proper technical analysis rather than upon traditional<br />
notions will be worked out. It would involve an expert<br />
technical unit in the Australian Department of Housing<br />
to undertake the necessary research, development and<br />
co-ordination, this work to be undertaken in close<br />
association with all interested parties. We would<br />
establish an " Australian Housing Standards Committee" for<br />
this purpose. </p>
<p>SConsultations with Management and Trade Unions:<br />
Economic management is largely the responsibility of<br />
the Australian Government. We accept that responsibility,<br />
and our actions have already gone far to reflect that.<br />
However, one group or one Government alone cannot grapple<br />
fully with the problem. To do so requires a wider effort.<br />
In a real sense, that is why we are here today.<br />
I shall come shortly to the ways in which the States<br />
can support our own efforts, But there is also the<br />
private sector. We are planning this year to have<br />
economic consultations, as our predecessors did, with<br />
representatives of important areas of the economy<br />
manufacturing, commerce, the trade unions and so on.<br />
We will be putting it to them-to employers and<br />
unionists alike that we look to them to support by<br />
the exercise of restraint in their price and wage<br />
proposals the policies which this government already has<br />
initiated or has in hand.<br />
Just as we will be seeking the support of the nongovernment<br />
sector to these ends, we would hope that<br />
you, the political leaders in your States, will take<br />
opportunities to do the same.<br />
What the Commonwealth Seeks of the States<br />
I spoke earlier of Mr. Hamer's reference to the division<br />
of relevant constitutional powers between the Australian<br />
government and the State governments0 There is certainly scope<br />
for complementary action by our several governments which will </p>
<p>13.<br />
bear on particular aspects of the inflationary problem. Five<br />
months ago when we came into office we sought and obtained the<br />
co-operation of the States in immediate measures to relieve the<br />
unemployment situation that was concerning us all. I hope that<br />
we can look to the State Governments for the same willing<br />
co-operation as we address ourselves to the rather different<br />
problems of today.<br />
Specifically, I would now like to suggest the<br />
following areas which appear to be promising in this respect.<br />
Action to Complement the Australian Government's<br />
Prices Justification Legislation. The legislation<br />
introduced yesterday by my colleague the Treasurer<br />
will apply only to companies whose receipts exceeded<br />
million in the preceding financial year. That<br />
limit has been struck to ensure that the scheme is<br />
administratively manageable. The Australian Government's<br />
legislation will bring under scrutiny prices charged by<br />
the larger companies which are the " price leaders" in<br />
respect of many products. But there are large areas<br />
of economic activity which will not be brought under<br />
scrutiny. That is to say, there is ample scope for<br />
complementary action by the State Governments to<br />
support and reinforce the impact of the Australian<br />
Government's initiative,<br />
Land Prices. The Australian and State Governments<br />
need to consider, together, whether something can<br />
be done about soaring land prices. In the longer-</p>
<p>14.<br />
term, new cities will help to take pressure off<br />
living space in and around our existing cities.<br />
But action with a more immediate impact is also<br />
needed. I wrote to all Premiers on 27 December 1972, seeking<br />
co-operation on this important matter. My colleague,<br />
the Minister for Urban and Regional Development, is<br />
actively pursuing it. Your Governments have been<br />
invited to introduce legislation to stabilise land<br />
prices so that land needed later for growth and<br />
development can be acquired at prices free from<br />
speculation. The Australian Government is discussing<br />
with your Governments the establishment of State Land<br />
Commissions, to participate actively in the land<br />
market and to increase the flow of residential land<br />
at reasonable prices.<br />
I know that some States are more advanced, and more<br />
willing to advance, in these directions than are<br />
other States. I know too that the problems vary in<br />
intensity and nature as between States. We hope that<br />
all States will be prepared to make their contribution<br />
to the prime objective of giving Australian families<br />
access to land at fair prices.<br />
Building Costs. There are various possible ways in<br />
which State Governments might act to check the serious<br />
upward spiral in building costs and particularly,<br />
of course, the costs of housing construction. </p>
<p>As the Treasury said yesterday in its published<br />
Round-up of Economic Statistics, the demands being<br />
made upon the housing sector are now clearly<br />
excessive. As a result, house-building is under<br />
severe strain from lack of men and materials.<br />
Office-building is also going on apace especially<br />
in the central business districts of the big cities<br />
and there is some evidence of a prospective glut in<br />
this sector. Some reduction in activity in officebuilding<br />
would of course release resources and this<br />
could marginally ease the problems in the housing<br />
sector. We recognise, of course, that the scope for<br />
transferring the particular resources concerned is<br />
limited and it would in any case no doubt take some<br />
time before any significant relief could be hoped for.<br />
But the Government believes that the State Governments<br />
particularly those in whose States most of the large<br />
office projects are going forward should at least<br />
examine the possibilities. Is there a glut? Will<br />
there be a glut? What could be gained for housing if<br />
office building were restrained? And what means of<br />
restraint are available? Surely these are matters which<br />
are worthy of some examination by State Governments in<br />
co-operation with us.<br />
As a separate matter, I have been personally disappointed<br />
in the slow and reluctant acceptance by some of the<br />
States of the Australian Model Uniform Building Code<br />
which you yourselves have worked out and I sincerely<br />
hope that those States which have not so far adopted it<br />
will do so. I would propose to invite each Premier to nominate </p>
<p>a representative or representatives to engage in the<br />
work of the contemplated Australian Housing Standards<br />
Committee. We shall provide more details in direct<br />
ministerial contacts.<br />
Restrictive Trade Practices. I referred earlier to the<br />
Australian Government's proposal to introduce more<br />
effective legislation to deal with restrictive trade<br />
practices. These practices are rife in Australia and<br />
their very purpose is usually to keep prices up. They<br />
serve to aggravate inflationary trends and the need for<br />
effective legislation to control them is pressing.<br />
The Australian Government recognizes that the existing<br />
Restrictive Trade Practices Act is not effective for<br />
this purpose. More effective legislation is being<br />
prepared and it will be introduced into the Australian<br />
Parliament as soon as possible, But there will not be<br />
sufficient constitutional power to permit the legislation<br />
to cover the whole field of restrictive trade practices.<br />
The legislation will depend, in the main, on the<br />
corporations power as that power was construed by the<br />
High Court in the Concrete Pipes case. There are still<br />
many uncertainties as to the scope of this power and<br />
it is plainly limited in a number of respects. For<br />
example, many trade practices, particularly those<br />
relating to services, do not involve corporations.<br />
This is, I believe, an area where a co-operative<br />
effect by the Australian and the State Governments can<br />
and should be made. Some states have already indicated </p>
<p>17.<br />
a willingness to co-operate by enacting legislation<br />
referring to the Australian Parliament the necessary<br />
power to deal with those trade practices that are at<br />
present beyond its reach. We are grateful for their<br />
indications of willingness to co-operate and propose<br />
to take the matter up with them very soon now that<br />
the nature of our own proposed legislation is almost<br />
settled. I hope th. at other States will f6llow suit<br />
and make it possible for the Australian Parliament<br />
to deal effectively with the whole range of these<br />
undesirable practices. The best method of co-operation<br />
in regard to this matter would be a reference of power<br />
similar to the one that was effected by Tasmania in<br />
1966. A State that was not prepared to refer power<br />
could assist by enacting legislation complementing<br />
that of the Australian Parliament. I would hope that<br />
this course would also be seriously considered.<br />
Consumer Protection. I have already referred to our<br />
own intentions in this field. But if effective action<br />
is to be taken Australia-wide it will need the active<br />
support and co-operation of the States. In that<br />
context, I suggest that the Premiers might ask their<br />
appropriate Ministers to meet with the Australian<br />
Minister of Science to discuss ways of arriving at<br />
uniform standards for consumer products and ensuring<br />
that those standards are observed.<br />
Measures of this kind make a direct contribution to<br />
community welfare; but in the present context we<br />
also see them as assisting competitive market forces<br />
B P </p>
<p>18.<br />
to reduce the scope for irresponsible pricing.<br />
0 a 0 0 a 0<br />
Finally, a word on incomes. Some take the position<br />
that the be-all and end-all of anti-inflationary policies is<br />
to fulminate against wage rises. That is not our position.<br />
On the contrary, we have moved to correct, in the areas under<br />
our own control, some evident anomalies and injustices. We<br />
have acted to increase social service payments to those who<br />
have been most cruelly harmed by inflation. We make no apology<br />
for acting quickly to honour our election pledges in these<br />
fields. We are happy that in Tuesday's decision the<br />
Arbitration Commission has recognized the particular needs of<br />
low wage earners in giving them a substantial rise from the<br />
unrealistically low levels of the recent past. The Government<br />
does not take any rigid and doctrinaire position on these matters<br />
and our attitude to future wage claims, in National Wage Cases<br />
and elsewhere, will pay full regard to all of the circumstances,<br />
social and economic, which prevail at the time.<br />
Tuesday's award was, of course, a large one, and it<br />
will add substantially to costs. With productivity rising as<br />
the output of the economy picks up, the greater part of industry<br />
should be well-placed at present largely to absorb these<br />
increased costs. I now invite the Premiers, in turn, to put forward<br />
their own proposals and their views on the suggestions I have<br />
made. We will not solve everything in one day. But we can<br />
make progress in identifying areas where the national and State<br />
Governments can act together against a problem which, as I began<br />
by saying, confronts us all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
