<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6895</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN BRUSSELS, 22 APRIL 1986</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/04/1986</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006895.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E 0 E PROOF ONLY A___ 0<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE IN BRUSSELS 22 APRIL 1986<br />
PflIM[ MINISTCR Ladics and gentlemen, I have just had together with<br />
colleagues an extremely useful meeting with tho Prcoidrnnt of thc Commission<br />
arid Cummiisioriier De Clercq. We agreed Lhat at tho outset that both the<br />
Community and Australia faced a numiber tiF cuiriiii problems anid that it<br />
was important that two important bodies such as the Community and<br />
AuLtiUl iU " h~ uuld iFcsume turltL'ucLive, c'ordial, cooperation dincuissions on<br />
these and other related) matters. I appreciated very much the fact that<br />
the Commission had acceded so readily to our request for this meeting, but<br />
most particularly for thd&amp; armthand constructive nutuic or the discussions.<br />
Let me say thnt we have reached agreement on a number of issues and that<br />
I would be prepared now to go through those Items with you.<br />
FIrstLly, we have ttyreed that thero will be by the<br />
Commission a reaffirmation of the agreement that I achievod when I was<br />
here on the last occasion which in shorthand terms can be referred to<br />
ats the" Aiidrlessen agreement", whereby they have Underta9ken not to interfere<br />
withi the Auul. rtiliar markel~ t iii Atla In Lire six countries of:. Jap. an, Korea,<br />
Taiwan, Malaysia, Singapore and Papua New Guinea by the operation of<br />
export restitutions. That agreement which we reached before has been<br />
subsLtinLlally adhered to and hias. now been reconfirmed.<br />
Secondly, the Pi-e-iderl. byreed with our position that<br />
agriculture trade in -agricultural pruuur'ts shouuld * have a pro~ milierntL place<br />
In the new multilateral trado negotiation round which will commence later<br />
Thirdly, there wa3 agreement that there should be<br />
a resumption of Ministerial consultations. As you know, they were postponed<br />
eurlie' thits yPEa by Llhe deuisioi, of tine Commission and it has now been<br />
agreed that those talks should be resumed. They will be resumed this<br />
year erid there will now be discussions at an official level as to the time<br />
rut tLue resumption of those discussions.<br />
Fourthly, there was agreement too that we cannot wait<br />
until the outcome of the MTN rounds, which can be quite prolonged,<br />
Lu address ourselves to the questions of subsidies and farm stock<br />
iii Curope arid Lthe President has agreed that in regard to<br />
subsidies there wtiuld be a stansd-still and roll-back position in regard<br />
to subsidios anid that there would be a careful rentraint in the question<br />
ur ditipusuisor the accumulated farmi stocks so that that fact of disposal of' those<br />
surpluz3 stocks utuld it or Itself be totiadditional disruptive factor<br />
in international trade in agricultural products.<br />
Fiflily, we agreed that in the light of the decision<br />
by -the Commuity that. Lhey wtLed to give added emphasis to new research<br />
and development in the field of technology within the Community that<br />
It would be appropriate that there should be cooperation between Australia<br />
and the Cumrmiunity in the-e aretiu. Tu yive effect to that agreement<br />
there will in the very near future, by May or June, be a high-level mission<br />
from the Comimunity visiting Australia to have consultations with us in<br />
Australia In tihe area or research and development and we believe that<br />
this will be of benefit both to the Commuity and Australia in terms<br />
of' activities within Australia and within the Community and may also<br />
provide a beneficial basis for activities by us in a combined sense<br />
lit our reyioti. May I say on that point that the framework of<br />
consultationo that are evIdeuiced by titn resumption of the Ministerial </p>
<p>FROM AMBASSADE RUSTR4.22.1986 19: 01P. 3<br />
-2-<br />
talks and the fact that the Commission will be coming to Australia in<br />
regard to research and tochnology, i1 als1o reflected further in the<br />
euggeation-by President Dclorn which I immediatecly took up,<br />
that he thought it would he useful that in tho icad-up to the * new MTN<br />
round and during it there should be~ liai, 4iuu it, a FrLm1liZed seIle<br />
between ourselves and the ConmitiuiLy, and we have uYreed Lu thUi.<br />
The whole mppru-xti i . iiet-ure ii reflected in the resumption<br />
of the Ministerial talks, the hi1gh-level mission on research and<br />
technology, the suggestion about a formal framework of consultations,<br />
In regard to the MTN is evidence, 1 would suggcst, tuF the determination<br />
on the part of the Community and ourselves to establish a Ibrud<br />
framework of continuing consultation so that the respective interests<br />
of the two groups can be best adveiied. Theni we oyzeed in œ' eij. rd<br />
to the question ort beer imorts into the Cummiiunity what iu t<br />
technically referred talance sheet beer coideriiiiui,, scime. Lhiii<br />
that emerges from the 1979 Tokyo Round, the arrangements that emerged<br />
from there have not worked out as intended at that time and wo have<br />
agreed that later this year thero will be specific discussions at the<br />
official level to try and improve the possibility of access by<br />
beef into the Community. With regard Lo the Inr~ erratlurnal<br />
Dairy Agrecment where there have been some suggestions that there<br />
may have been somye lack of strict adherence to the minimum price<br />
requirements of the International Dairy Ayruemeril, we 8yreed in) our<br />
discusion1s today LhuL there ihould be a commitment and adherence<br />
by both parties to the provisiomsof the International Dairy Agreement<br />
and, finally, we noted that there was Gome concerti on our part ut;<br />
to the possible impact upoi~ 916de, rluwinyt Fiumi the cutivesri iii the<br />
beef industry about the action of the Community in regard to hormone<br />
growth promotants. Now I know you have all crossed that subject,<br />
hormone growth promotants, so I won't Insult your inLelliqenue by<br />
going into the details or it uther than to say that the Commu'unl ty<br />
had decided to ban the hormone growth promotants3' use and to<br />
require exporters of beef to the Community to certify that meat<br />
ent~ eritiy the Cum'munity does~ mo from animals that have boon troatoci<br />
with HGP . Now I know you are going to write columns and columns<br />
about that and so you can finish all your writing on that subject<br />
1) y uayiny that there has beei ayreemiiLn that we will discust that isLie.<br />
between us which at any rate wouldn't be coming into opcration<br />
before I January 1988 to ensure as far as possible out of those<br />
discussions our concerns con be token into account.<br />
So ladies and gentlemen I don't apologise for<br />
the length of that summary because I think you will appreciate<br />
that in a very short. time we havu been able tu CuVer the IbruuI<br />
issues of concerni to AuniLrallts and also to have taken up a number of<br />
particular matters which will be to our mutual benefit. Over to<br />
you. May I say in fairness to President Delors<br />
that as well as discussing these issues they did take thes opportunity<br />
of saying to us that they welcomed thes Cominuity welu: ed Dite<br />
action that this Governiment thad taken in regard to the gradual move<br />
to the reduction of protection levels in Australia as evidenced inwhat<br />
we have done in the steel induBtry plait uind ifi thu muLur veh1icle<br />
production plan and expressed the hope that we would continue the<br />
thrust that we'd established In that areb. </p>
<p>FROM AMBflSSADE AUSTR 4.22.1986 19,02 P. 4<br />
-3-<br />
Greg sorry<br />
GREG HYWOOD Mr H-owkc you mentioned atand-still ond wind-back<br />
provisions on subsidies, could you go into some more detail about exactly<br />
what Mr Delora agreed to in regard to that.<br />
PRIME MINISTER--Well what he pointed out was that already under the<br />
thuzA of the Commnission itzself there had 1bwtv ive beylnning or wind-bac1
subsidies, a reduction in the leveI-joV payments under subsidy programs<br />
aiid LhaL Uhi: haW3 bet( Vere-iLud in torne loss or standard of living of<br />
farmers. But. despite this in t he-Community that there was a commitment<br />
by the Commission to a continuation of that process. In other Words,<br />
Greg, the point that was being made agreod between LIS that we<br />
couldn't affordt, giveii the very substantiael probloms that were co~ nfronting<br />
thle Community anid which were merylny Into the international trading<br />
reyinit-tis ta rt'ult or the very substauiLial increase in subsidisation<br />
that had taken placel over tho years which had led to increased production,<br />
we cuuld tiut afford to wail fur thle outcomne of the MIN round, which,<br />
you know, Could guo0i1 FUV quite u conrlideL'able ptrlod or timfe, and<br />
that the thrust of the Community in this area, we were given to understandI<br />
would continue pending the more general determination of thes-e<br />
1t3. uem witi tiñ h Ciiiinewui'k ur Lh MTN.<br />
Do you think agricultural Ministers' meeting in<br />
Luxembourg will ( inaudible)<br />
PRIMEF MIN15TER /~ Olya~ lt the bauiu tit the upermticni of tile Community<br />
is that you have tho Commission itself making it~ s functional rolc is<br />
to make recommendations, the decisions are made by the Ministers3,<br />
anid thie story has beeii one of the Commission, I believe, having an<br />
overall perspective of the need to have this standstill and wind-back<br />
in the processes which have led to the difficulties within Europe<br />
Und inlure yellera1Jy~ he irteriiAiur'l tradinig arena and they have<br />
had degrees of success and I would believe that given the dimension<br />
6f the problems In budgetary terms and in income transfer terms<br />
riom Loiisunier to rarmerG the dimensions. cif thooe problems<br />
that vie have grounds for optimism Lliat the recommondations an d attitudes<br />
of. the Commission will come to recommend themselves t~ o the Ministers.<br />
OL-0'. J </p>
<p>hi<br />
Ouestion ( Milton Cockburn, Sydney Morning Herald)<br />
( inaudibli but relates to immzigration requiremnents for<br />
Australian tourists entering Bali)<br />
Prim,! Minister: M~ iltoni I, just as I wAlked into the Pr'e" Conference ' I wa3<br />
appraiaed of this development, so by definition, I don't<br />
know all the details I will attempt to, as soon as we get<br />
to R~ omeo 1, o St. fuller details on it, so 1' cn not inclined to<br />
make any observation until I have those, that further<br />
information. I would simply say obviously, on the face of<br />
what you say and what I've Jjt been given before I ca~ me ina<br />
it's not a development which I welcome but can't say any<br />
more than that until I oet fiurther inf'ormation.<br />
cuketio Prime Minister, coming back to the European food exports to your are3, how<br />
do you recoriAlc the assurance3 given to you by Pr'esident Delors and verbal<br />
Plans b~ y F'i'en and German~ agricultural Ministers to aimr for a gi 4nt . expozft<br />
Qfferwsive to get rid of Euaropean surpluses. Has anybody told you ina so mrany<br />
WOtr( 1, i 1. 1 ] r~ praa wnUld actually sort of exclude youir area as a target of<br />
this export offensive?<br />
Prime Minister: Let me maike two points about it. Firstly, we recogise that<br />
ir you're going to be looking at the longer termi and part of<br />
the resolution of the problem with which we'ro confronted<br />
bY definition involve the disposal of these' lirp' . accu: niluted<br />
surpluses. While the overhang the international mnarket<br />
yu're going to continue to have a problem. So what has<br />
3pecifically been said to us on that point is that care will<br />
be taken to try and effect an orderly disposal of those<br />
surpluses bo that, as I said before, an unorderly disposal<br />
of them won't pose an additional problem to the ones we already<br />
have; that's the first point. The second point is that I<br />
think that as a result of the discussions we've had here todaythe<br />
reaffirmation of the Andriessen agreenent and the<br />
estab. ishmaent as you will see of an agreement for a broad<br />
range of oonsultative mechanisms, that I wo-ald hope that our<br />
capacity now to put the case of Australia in regard to<br />
apecific markets and specific commodities has been enhanced.<br />
Now I don't want to overstate and say that as a result of<br />
the meeting we've had today that we've eliminated probboens,<br />
it would be stupid to any that and !-don't makce that claim,<br />
Whnat I do say is that as a result of today I think the basis<br />
and them~ raiwwork for relations between the Coimunity and<br />
Australia has been significantly Improved.<br />
Question ( Michelle Grattani, Melbourne Age)<br />
( Inaudible but relating to Mrs Dawkins)<br />
would you car'e to reaffirm your cosplete confidence In Mr. Dawkins? </p>
<p>Prime Minister Well, let's rrmako two points. The first is that, as you<br />
know, I make a practice of not cormmenting on internal<br />
developments while I'm overseas, but having said that, you<br />
know the statement I made in the Parliament before about my<br />
confidence in the Minister and that stands,<br />
Question: Will you be'lookir. e at the matter when you get to Rome?<br />
Prime Minister I had that question put to me at a Press Conference in<br />
London yest-eray. I answered in the negative and nothing<br />
has changed between then and now to make me alter that answer.<br />
Question ( Greg Hywood, Financial Review)<br />
( inaudible, but relates to Mr. Dawkins' alleged suing of one<br />
o hi'offici&amp; ls)<br />
Prime inister Creg, I'm not changing, even in the space of one rrminute,<br />
the answer that I've just given, that is that I'm not<br />
cormenting on developments at home while I'm away. It's<br />
clear that when I return to Australia I will seek to be<br />
fully acquainted with all these developments, It rmay be that<br />
then I'll have some corment back in Australia.<br />
Questiori Prime Vinister, if you( inaudible but refers to Andriessen aereement)<br />
Prime Minister Well, let me say this, that the Andriessen agreement hich<br />
covered the six countries that are concerned emerged fromn<br />
discussions that we had because we had a particular immediate<br />
Concern about those countries. You used the word ' poaching';<br />
I don't want to use that word, I simply want to make the point<br />
that over the years as the Community has sought to dispose of<br />
the enormous surpluses in production which have flowed from<br />
their policies hbre, that has created problems in various<br />
areas for us. Now, I don't want, in the light of what has<br />
been a vary, very positive and constructive session I've had<br />
with the President and Commissioner De Clercq, to go into<br />
negatives. We've had our problems, it's obvious; I think<br />
we're now in u position to have a better opportunity of<br />
dealirg with those problems than we've had in the past. and<br />
I'm encourgod vory much by tho attitude of the Conmission.<br />
Question i<br />
You seem to have a. touching faith<br />
Comnission to deliver. A lot of<br />
dressed up by the Cmmiision and<br />
is only one player. 0 Prime Minister, in the ability of the<br />
the farm disposal programes have been<br />
officials of the Twelvc but the Colmission<br />
U -r </p>
<p>I<br />
Prime Minister Well, I may be a person of touching faith, not only in<br />
the Cornission but in a range of people; now that's a question<br />
for others to decide but if I could be somewhat detached<br />
about it I think you've got to say, well, when I've talked<br />
with them before and got agreements, have they been adhered<br />
to. The answer on that is, yes.. When I met them beforo I<br />
specirically got the Wgreement, the Andriessen agreement;<br />
that has been adhered to in the period since they agreedo*<br />
Now I hope I've made it clear, I'm sure I did in<br />
the observation I made a while aso<br />
that I don't believe that as a result of the meeting I've<br />
had just now, that all the problems are behind us, far Am<br />
it; but I do believe that both in regard to the i~ m. ediate,<br />
short term future situation and the longer term, there are<br />
considerable areas or agreement.<br />
In regard to the immediate period, there is an understanding,<br />
an agreement to continue consultations at the Ministerial<br />
level and they've been interrupted and at the official level<br />
on a range of matters. Now I believe that nothing but good<br />
can come out of that and in the longer term we have the<br />
agreement of the Commission to the need to ensure that<br />
agriculture has a prominent place in the New KTN Pound.<br />
Now, I don't think it's a question of touching faith, to<br />
have a positive reaction to that outcome. We don't want<br />
to delude ourselves that all the problems have been solved.<br />
I certainly don't.<br />
Question i<br />
Will the Comon Agricultural Policy be. included in the KTN Round?<br />
Prime Ministers You can't talk about international trade in agriculture without.<br />
CAP being involved in the discussions, but there will be<br />
different emphases upon that. The Community will have a<br />
different emphas. s and attitude towards that than we will but<br />
you won't b6 able to have agriculture as a prominent item<br />
on the agenda without CAP being in there.<br />
Question And do you think they'. re agreed on that.<br />
Prime Minister Well, once they say, I mean they are realists, once they<br />
say that agriculture must have a prominent place they understand<br />
that it will be there, that people will discuss it.<br />
Question Prime Minister, about a month ago there were a series of angry statements<br />
coming out in Canberra to the effect that Australians were getting caught<br />
up in a sort of an agricultural trade war between the Uhited States and the<br />
EinEC W. asZhni ntghtoen , l igdho t yoouf fceoenlv etrhsaatti ofnesa r yiosu ' vnoew haAd6 vbioattehd ? h ereT ahnadt tIh eth ifneka, r iesa rnlioewr<br />
gne, that you're much more relaxed about it.<br />
I </p>
<p>7-<br />
Prime Mlinister No, I'm not rzr. h more relaxad but let me i kv LhU points<br />
which are relevant to your question. In both Washington<br />
and here in Brussels I have voiced, I think effectively and<br />
certainly strongly, the concerns that Australia has about<br />
this new development of, as you put it and I think not tQg<br />
graphically, the oalbllity of a trace war in agricultural<br />
products between the United States and Europe. Now I've<br />
said to both of them that we welcome the fact that they<br />
recognise the dangers and that they are having discussions<br />
about it. The third point I've made and I repeat it here<br />
strungly we don't want to see a situation in which, where<br />
they do have discussions, that they settle the possible<br />
problems between them through some deals which leave Australia<br />
end others out in the cold. So I think the dangers, the<br />
possible dangers of this conflict between the United States<br />
and Europe is still a real one. What I have done is to<br />
convey, a4 strongly Am T can in both Woohington mud hiv, our<br />
concern about that and the two things; one, that there must<br />
not be some bilateral deals done at the expense of others<br />
and secondly, in the longer term more important, that these<br />
matters have to be resolved finally by ensuring, as we've<br />
said, that agriculture does have a prominent place in the<br />
14TN Round and that it has applied to it, the same relevantly<br />
operative sorts of provisions that have been effective in<br />
other areas of international trade.<br />
Queotion Prime Minister<br />
Question Prime Minister i ( Inaudible, but relates to time frame for application of<br />
Andriessen agreement. Questioner suggested another 12 months)<br />
No,, not for another twelve months, the time period wasn't<br />
mentioned but I have no reason to believe that it won't, that<br />
the presumption, let me put it this way, the presumption<br />
should be that it will continue to operate, When we agreed<br />
on it in the first place, when I was here last time, I'm<br />
trying to recall theworde, but I think the phraseology was<br />
that Lhere would be no change that would be contemplated by<br />
the Commission without consulting with us. I think that was<br />
the Substance of the way they approached it and I have no<br />
reason to believe that that wouldn't continue to be the case<br />
and certainly nothing was said in the discussions today which<br />
would lead us to believe that we can't continue to count on<br />
that undertaking.<br />
( Unaudible e relates to US beef coming onto world market<br />
as result of' whole herd-dairy buy-up'scheme)<br />
The whole herd dairy buy-up scheme; I didn't raise that<br />
but let me go back, I mean I said in Washington that, in<br />
my discussions with the Americans, I pointed out what was<br />
the underatanding that we got from the Europeans under the<br />
Andriessen areement and that we would, you know the very </p>
<p>minimun we could<br />
undertaking from<br />
expect the sam; expect from the Americans it we had that<br />
the Europeam that we should be able to<br />
understanding from the Americans.<br />
Question Prime Minister, the Community supports farmers prices by annually, I would<br />
say, 90 billion US dollars; the United States supports their price3 by<br />
about 21 billion dollars. How much does the Australian Covernment spend to<br />
support their farmers?<br />
Prime Minister Its by, comment, I mean this is not a matter I had to argue<br />
with in the United States or here, its accepted there air)' in<br />
the whole international trading cotmunity, that Australians,<br />
Australia's auricultural sector is extraordinarily lightly<br />
assisted. As far as exports are concerned, which is the<br />
major area that we're talking about, we don't subsidise<br />
exports; as far as the internal operational sector is<br />
concerned, a very, very light degree of subsidy and that's<br />
not something I have to argue, it hasn't been argued by<br />
the Europeanu or the Americans.<br />
Question The MTN is still a matter of months off, not tomorrow and<br />
Primo Minister To be precis the Ministerial meeting is in September...<br />
Question ( contd.)<br />
Right, and anything that comes out of it will presumably take time to<br />
have its effect on the international market. Would you care to speculate<br />
how much time?<br />
Prime . inister No, but it's because I'm conscious of the fact, looking at<br />
previous experience, that the Round can take a long time,<br />
that we directly went into the discussions with our friends<br />
here, that there would be a continued addressing to th&amp;<br />
issues of subsidies and disposals. It's because it's going<br />
to take, and when you're talking about the time of the Round<br />
you're not talking about months, you can be talking about<br />
years, and that's why the immediate undertakings have an<br />
added importance.<br />
Question I was talking to Alan Oxley a couple of weeks ago<br />
Prime Minister Oh, that's interesting<br />
Ouestion( contd.)( inaudible relates to prolonged time-span of MTN<br />
negotiations) that inevitably Australia is<br />
going to go through a very costly and painful process. What I'm trying to<br />
ask io how well you can survive it. </p>
<p>Prime Minister Well, let me put it this way. Our capacity to survive<br />
in a bearable fomn would be less, and sipaificuntly losse,<br />
it we had not addressed ourselves both in the United StaLes<br />
and here, to these issues and have got the understanding<br />
of the Americans and of the Europeans that we can't wait<br />
to deal with the problems of international trade in agricultural<br />
commoditiea on the outcome of the Round. There<br />
has got to be preparedness to talk and act in these areas<br />
while those talks are firstly coming Into place and while<br />
they're continuing.<br />
Question ( creg Hywood, Financial Review)<br />
( inaudible relates to when the international deoline in<br />
interest rates will flow on to Australla)<br />
Prime , iniater Well, as you know, there's been a reasonably significant<br />
decline in rates within Australik over the last couple of<br />
months. Broadly speaking, there is an attitude on nmy part,<br />
a4 you kliow, that I don't think in this context it's very<br />
profitable to be making predictions about interest. rate<br />
movements but I would simply say that what's been happening<br />
internationally would add to what I'v -aid in t4e reent.....<br />
past in Australia and that is that we, I think, have the<br />
broad framework within which it's legitimate to expect<br />
a continuation of that trend that we've seen earlier in<br />
Australia. Really Greg, I don't want to be more specific<br />
than that. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
