<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1439</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 113/1966 - BARBADOS INDEPENDENCE CELEBRATIONS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/11/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001439.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
66/ 152<br />
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 113/ 1966<br />
BARBADOS INDEPENDENCE CELEBRATIONS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Holt<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Holt, announced today that Sir<br />
Keith Wilson would represent the Australian Government on the occasion<br />
of the independence of Barbados.<br />
Barbados, which has been a British Colony since the<br />
seventeenth century, Will achieve irid~ pendence on 30th November.<br />
Celebrations to mark the event will be held in the capital, BridgetoWft,<br />
between 28th November and 3rd December.<br />
Barbados has expressed a wish to become a membe r of the<br />
Commonwealth, and Australia, along with other Commonwealth nations,<br />
has agreed to welcome it into the Commonwealth association and to<br />
sponsor its application for membership of the United Nations. Barbados<br />
S will become the 26th member of the Commonwealth.<br />
Mr. Holt said that Sir Keith Wilson would carry with him<br />
a congratulatory message conveying the very warm wishes of the<br />
Government and people of Australia. Sir Keith would present the<br />
Government of Barbados with an Australian landscape and library of<br />
Australian books, and the Barbados Legislature with a desk set from the<br />
Australian Parliament. Sir Keith V~ llson is a distinguished former member of the<br />
Australian Parliament. He was elected to the Senate in 1937 and, after<br />
serving in the Middle East theatre in the AIF, was elected in 1949 to the<br />
House of Representatives as the Member for Sturt, which he has<br />
represented continuously since 1955. Sir Keith was a member of the<br />
Australian delegation to the United Nations in 1964.<br />
CANBERRA. 21st November, 1966. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
