<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5190</transcript-id>
    <title>SUMMARY OF ABC&#039;S &#039;AM&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/11/1979</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005190.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER-THURSDAY, 8 NOVEMBER 1979<br />
From the Press Office<br />
SUMMARY OF ABC'S<br />
Iran's humiliation of the United States continues. Former<br />
U. S. Attorney-General, Ramsey Clark, heading for Tehran to<br />
negotiate the release of the 60 American hostages has been<br />
ordered to stay in Athens until the Iranian authorities clarify<br />
whether they will talk to them or not. The Ayatollah Khomeini<br />
has stated there will be no talks without the Shah being<br />
returned to Iran.<br />
Staff at the Australian Embassy in Tehran have been told to<br />
keep a low profile.<br />
One of the countries most concerned about the possibility<br />
of the Ayatoll * ah using oil diplomacy is Japan, which relies<br />
heavily on Iranian oil. To make the situation worse, Japan<br />
has large investments in Iran.<br />
In Queensland, the unions and the State Government look set for<br />
a head-on confrontation. On the one hand, there is the Government<br />
with its tough new Essential Services Legislation and on the<br />
other the unions, who held a mass meeting in Brisbane yesterday<br />
pledg ing to close the State down if the laws are used.<br />
President of the Trades and Labour. Council in Queensland<br />
interviewed.<br />
According to the British Government, the Zimbawe-Rhodesia<br />
peace talks in London are very close to settlement. As a result<br />
it has been trying to rush through Parliament the necessary<br />
legislation for a transitional government in Salisbury. After<br />
nine weeks of talks, the British Government now thinks it is<br />
close to settling its last major colonial problem, the Government<br />
has now rushed legislation into the Parliament to give<br />
Zimbabwe-Rhodesia if the peace talks succeed. They have decided<br />
from next week to lift a small section of the sanctions against<br />
the breakaway colony.<br />
Senator Edward Kennedy has formally declared his candidacy<br />
for the Democratic Party Presidential nomination.<br />
In a report to the Minister for Health, Mr. Hunt, the National.<br />
Health and Medical Research Council has made it-clear that<br />
total lead intake by Australians are producing significant<br />
adverse health effects. It is understood that the Council believes<br />
that lead levels in petrol should continue to be phased down.<br />
The Chairman of the Council, Dr. William Langsford, interviewed.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
