<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9705</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP DOORSTOP, SHERATON BREAKWATER CASINO-HOTEL, TOWNSVILLE, MONDAY, 14 AUGUST 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/08/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009705.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
q N<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, SHERATON BREAKWATER CASINO-HOTEL,<br />
TOWNSVILLE, MONDAY, 14 AUGUST 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, where is Carmen Lawrence now that she seems to<br />
have lost her avenue for..<br />
PM: Well, she hasn't lost the avenue, she hasn't lost the matter, it is a<br />
jurisdictional matter where the High Court has said that the Western<br />
Australian action she has, that process has to be complete before it<br />
would be competent for the High Court to hear it. So, the matter of<br />
substance is not yet determined. But, the legal options which she<br />
might have will now have to be considered and no doubt she will do<br />
that.<br />
J: Are you happy to continue supporting her while she exhausts every<br />
legal option that she has available to her?<br />
PM: Of course I am because this process of the Royal Commission in<br />
Western Australia is directed to extending the arm of the Western<br />
Australian Executive and in this matter, she has taken the view and so<br />
has the Federal Cabinet that the rights of MPs versus the Executive<br />
are important ones. But again, I think, she has taken the view right<br />
through that she is prepared to tell her story at the appropriate<br />
moment.<br />
J: Her affairs must be doing some damage to the Party?<br />
PM: I don't think it is doing as much as the Liberal Party is doing to itself in<br />
Western Australia. In Western Australia we have now a third person<br />
hopping out of the Liberal Party on the weekend after Mr Rocher and<br />
Mr Filing. Now, Mr Howard told everybody last week that he was<br />
resolving the matter and he had this, as he said, this sort of mock<br />
expulsion of Senator Crichton-Browne. Well, if that has assuaged the<br />
fears of Western Australian MPs, Mr Rocher wouldn't have run as an<br />
Independent, Mr Filing may have come back into the Party and </p>
<p>certainly the candidate for Swan wouldn't have shifted from the Liberal<br />
Party to Independent status. I notice in the Sydney Sunday Telegraph<br />
a story which says " Howard's strategy may backfire on him". Mr<br />
Howard told all those gullible enough to believe him last week that he<br />
had exercised authority and secured the agreement to push Senator<br />
Crichton-Browne away from the processes of the Liberal Party. What<br />
we now know is that this is untrue. It turns out that Mr Court and David<br />
Honey prevailed upon Senator Crichton-Browne to remove himself<br />
from the activities of the Liberal Party. After having found that out, Mr<br />
Howard then put out a statement. In other words, it wasn't Mr Howard<br />
who did that at all. Let me just say, and I am winking here, there is at<br />
least one Canberra journalist who said to me if it is to be revealed that<br />
Mr Howard was not central to Mr Crichton-Browne' s " removal" from the<br />
Liberal Party, he would say so volubly in his medium Now is his<br />
opportunity because Mr Howard has told an enormous porky here.<br />
What he has done, basically, it is a very revealing article. It says that,<br />
for instance, last week Mr Howard said ' I got rid of Noel Crichton-<br />
Browne from the Liberal Senate ticket'. Senior Liberals dispute this.<br />
They say Senator Crichton-Browne made his decision to stand down<br />
from the Senate solely after discussions with the Western Australian<br />
Premier and are adamant that Mr Howard had no influence on his<br />
decision. Howard will say anything and he does. It goes on to say ' Mr<br />
Howard's announcement banning Senator Crichton-Browne from party<br />
meetings also came after he ( Crichton-Browne) had announced his<br />
withdrawal from party affairs.<br />
So, certainly this is hurting the Liberal Party in Western Australia and<br />
what it shows is John Howard's weakness, indecisiveness, lack of<br />
support for those who have supported him. By contrast, last week, I<br />
said I was supporting Martin Ferguson. I made it clear that I would be<br />
supporting him at the National Executive were it to have met today and<br />
as you know that matter was resolved within the Labor Party with other<br />
candidates withdrawing. So, again, let me just underline here John<br />
Howard's duplicity and weakness in dealing with these people in his<br />
Party in Western Australian over Senator Crichton-Browne. They are<br />
leaving the Liberal Party in droves in Western Australia. There is a<br />
real crisis there, a complete party split is on over there and let me<br />
complete on those words by the former Senator Reg Withers when he<br />
said there is a civil war on over there and that is exactly what is on in<br />
the Western Australian Liberal Party.<br />
J: Prime Minister, have you given any consideration or had any<br />
discussions, even in private, about who might take over the health<br />
portfolio..<br />
PM: None, what so ever and I'm not considering it.<br />
J: Would you be comfortable with Carmen Lawrence giving evidence at<br />
the Royal Commission? </p>
<p>PM: Of course I would be comfortable with her giving her evidence in any<br />
body. But, again, there is a matter of principle here about the rights of<br />
the Executive and the rights of Members of Parliament and that will<br />
probably run its full course.<br />
J: Does Martin Ferguson go to the preselection for the seat of Batman as<br />
damaged goods now?<br />
PM: No, I think, the public are very shrewd assessors of these processes<br />
and they see that Martin Ferguson represented working Australians<br />
over a long period of time in the Miscellaneous Workers Union and<br />
then as President of the ACTU and they would see it as a natural shift<br />
for him to make a change to the Federal Parliament in the Labor Party.<br />
This will be good for the Labor Party. It will make us stronger, it will<br />
make the Government stronger and, again, it just renews that contact<br />
we have had with working Australians, to have the leader of the<br />
industrial movement in the federal caucus. So, I would think most<br />
Australians will regard this as a sensible outcome and like me would<br />
probably appreciate the commitment which was made by the other<br />
candidates and the decision which they took to withdraw from the<br />
contest.<br />
J: of Independents, Phil Cleary, says he may run somebody..<br />
PM: Well, good on you Phil, do your hardest. In a democracy you can put<br />
your money, put your deposit down and it is everyone for themselves.<br />
J: Have you written off the next election as a loss?<br />
PM: Where do you get those questions for God's sake. I mean, has the<br />
sun got to you?<br />
J: Are you prepared to consider the plea by veterans from the pacific that<br />
they get some personal reward?<br />
PM: We have a mature system of supporting veterans and we have had it<br />
in place now for a very long period of time and you might also know<br />
that those who were particularly disadvantaged, prisoners of war, you<br />
might have seen Tom Uren's remarks of a day or so ago, supporting<br />
the Government in support of those people who did suffer at the hands<br />
of the Japanese and Germans. But in the broad, of course, we have a<br />
very mature system of assessment and support for veterans.<br />
J: What about ones in the Pacific, in Papua New Guinea and Solomon<br />
Islands?<br />
PM: That is for the whole of the service in the Second World War. Thank<br />
you.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
