<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>792</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE R G MENZIES SCHOOL OF HUMANITIES - MONASH UNIVERSITY, MELBOURNE ON 24TH AUGUST, 1963 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/08/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000792_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
63/ 700<br />
OPENING OF THE R. G. MEilNZIES SCHOOL OF<br />
HUMANITIES MONASH UNIVERSITY MELBOURNE<br />
ON 24TH AUGUST, 1961<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mr, Chancellor, Most Potent, Grave and Reverend Seniors<br />
sitting here behind me, and Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I propose, with your concurrence to institute a<br />
new rule and that is that I don't speak wit; h my hat on,<br />
I can't ( Laughter) I'm very grateful to the Dean of the<br />
Faculty of Arts for having varied the usual form. I always<br />
have to remember when I open anything that apart from uttering<br />
a number of words and if possible saying something I have to<br />
open~ whatever it is and he has given me an alternativo today.<br />
I may either open this School or I may pronounce the benediction<br />
over it. ( Laughter) I now do both,<br />
Mr. Chancellor, your account of how this new movement<br />
in the university world occurred was still interesting to mo<br />
though I had played a part in it. I don't mind telling you<br />
that your broad hints about the future and the slight side<br />
touc~ ios on the same theme by the Dean of the Faculty of Arts<br />
( Laughter) may appear to you to have passed unnoticed by me<br />
because I observed a straight face, but the reason for that<br />
was that looking back in the audience I saw that my colleague,<br />
the Treasurer, was present and so he knows now as much as I do<br />
and if he doesntt know it, I think the Chairman of the<br />
Universities Commission who is also lurking in this audience<br />
will no doubt have made a note of it. And so in due course,<br />
something dreadful will happen, financially, which will be<br />
something very good for the universities of Australia,<br />
You have to do a groat deal of good by stealth.<br />
I offer that piece of gratuitous advice to those who are now<br />
training for some occupation in life. Do it by stealth.<br />
I remember when I had this idea of establish~ ing a committee<br />
with the possibility of getting Keith Murray to come and<br />
preside over it. I didn't care to mention this to the<br />
Treasurer at the time who wasntt Mr. Holt at that timeuntil<br />
it was practically completed. I was in England and I<br />
spoke to Sir Keith Murray and he said, " We lli I would be very<br />
happy. This is the kind of thing that I have had some<br />
experience of, that I would like to do something about, but<br />
I work with the Chancellor of the Exchequer a very happy<br />
arrangement and I will need to have his approval." The<br />
Chancellor of the day was Mr. Harold Macmillan, so I want and<br />
got his approval, Thus the Committee began.<br />
When I had assembled the Committee I then broke the<br />
news to the Treasurer and he said, " Well, ola. man, I know you<br />
are very interested in this kind of thing." I said, I<br />
certainly am", I said, of course, " I warn you, this will c ost<br />
money,"' and he said, " Yes, I had an idea that it would," and I<br />
said, " Any committee of competence that goes into the position<br />
of the universities tremendously pressed as they were at that<br />
time by a vast flood of increase in those requiring university<br />
training well, the cost will be high."<br />
Up to that time, the Commonwealth Government had got<br />
along very quietly with a few special grants of a limited kind-<br />
I think we ran to zabout œ l4in the course of a year but this<br />
060 0 / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
one was bound to be in far greater figures than that. And I<br />
must say for my then colleague that he took this very well and<br />
the Committee then got to work and produced its first report,<br />
its first triennial recommendation and it was very large, as it<br />
seemed at that time and once more I adopted what you might be<br />
pleased to describe as rather devious methods.<br />
I knew that if this report were distributed to the<br />
Ministers too far ahead of a Cabinet Meeting too many of them<br />
might get to know too much about it and so I had to circulate<br />
it one day and deal with it the next, And we came out at the<br />
end of the day in Cabinet completely approving of all the recommendations<br />
that had been made and since then, of course, you know<br />
the story. I know some of it,<br />
I know that for the first triennium under the<br />
auspices of the Universities Commission what had seemed large<br />
figuires in the Murray Report turned out to be quite insignificant<br />
and Sir Leslie Martin has developed nowadays almost a habit of<br />
avoiding my eye because he knows and I know that the next<br />
triennium will be such as to lcavc. the second. one looking a<br />
poor relation. Well, this is all good. It may be difficult<br />
it is difficult, but it is incredibly good and I am happy to think<br />
that what has happened in the universities of Australia has been,<br />
in a sense, revolutionary, never suff. Licient the day will never<br />
come when university authorities will say they are content with<br />
what they have. It ca4n't come, This is not a static community,<br />
it is not a static world that we live in. Problems are increasing<br />
and the demand for people with cultivated intelligence is a<br />
growing demand not only here but all over the world and<br />
consequently, I am not here to say, " Well, gentlemen, call it<br />
a day, will you? It is becoming a little uncomfortable,~ I am<br />
quite prepared to say to you that I will wonder what has htappened<br />
to the universities if they ever reach that comfortable position.<br />
This is eatts and a task which any man claiming any<br />
elements of statesmanship at all ought to be delighted to<br />
participate in,<br />
Of course Sir, it is always worth remembering, and<br />
I am sure that you all remember it, that while there are great<br />
f'inancial problems, great problems of building, great problems<br />
of securing equipment and of keeping abreast of the developing<br />
equipment, particularly in the scientific faculties, although<br />
all those present problems, one of the great problems will be to<br />
maintain in a growing university field the high quality of<br />
university staffs. This is a problem which occasions me<br />
although I am not responsible for dealing with it very much<br />
but this occasions me more thought than all these other physical<br />
problems to which I have referred, because we must maintain'the<br />
high standards. If there is one thing we can't afford in this<br />
country7 it is to lower the standards of university training and<br />
to have first-class people, first-class men, first-class women<br />
in the various faculties is net going to be easy. Nor indeed,<br />
Sir can we contemplate that we are going to secure much help<br />
on Zhat front from outside Australia because all countrie-, s feel<br />
the saime pressure, the same urge, the same urgent demand to<br />
maintain standards and to keep up and expand their first-class<br />
teaching population. This is something that I think must inspire<br />
everybody to greater and greater efforts,<br />
And, Sir particularly here, what a marvellous thing<br />
it is, as I said to the Chancellor after lunch, what a marvellous<br />
thing i t is to have the honour of presiding over and contributing<br />
to the growth of a new university, something straight from the<br />
grass roots, not just inheriting somebody else's work but<br />
0 / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
creating something on the spot. This is tremendous. You know,<br />
quite recently in America I delivered the Jefferson Oration, as<br />
they are pleased to call it, at Monticello.<br />
I suppose most of you remember that when Jefferson<br />
drafted his own epitaph for his own memorial stone, he wrote<br />
out " Thomas Jefferson" and his dates, " Draftsman of the<br />
Declaration of Independence, Creator of the Virginia Statute for<br />
Religious Toleration, Founder of the Universitly of Virginia."<br />
Not a word about having been an ambassador, not a word about<br />
having been Secretary of State in George Wvashaington's admninistration,<br />
not a word about having been Vice President, not a word<br />
about having been President, for two terms, of the United States<br />
of America just these three simple things. And when he was<br />
asked by one of his relatives, " Why didn't you include these<br />
great matters?", he said, " Wfell, I wanted to have put on my<br />
memorial what I had don3 for the people, not what the people<br />
had done for me." Now this is superb. It's so simple and yet<br />
it's full of that imaginative quality which is required in the<br />
creation of anything, and here with this new University what<br />
a task, what an opportunity for many among you to be able to<br />
look back and say, " WJell, I was one of the creators in the true<br />
sense of the Monash University."<br />
Now, Sir, I just want to say a word, if I may,<br />
about that very great man after whom this Univ( ersity is named.<br />
lie was never involved in politics and therefore, perhaps, he<br />
escaped the barbed tongaes of undergraduates, I am perfectly<br />
certain that nobody would ever havoe dreamed of referring to a<br />
building with which Sir John Monash was associated as " Jack's<br />
Shack" ( Laughter) but I am told that already the ungodly in this<br />
University are referring to this as " Ming's ' ting" ( Laughter)<br />
But, Sir the naming of this university, this was a positive<br />
inspiration. One of the greatest of Australians of all time<br />
wonderful engineer, a famous and tremendous soldier a scholar<br />
in his own right a great expert in many fields of life and'an<br />
advocate, not only an advocate of good causes, but stopping at<br />
the word " ladvocate" 7one of the greatest advocates I ever<br />
listened to in my life; a man who understood the art of<br />
persuasive spoech, the art of clear speech, who used no jargon<br />
but who went clear to the point persuasively to the point, with<br />
effects thpt I had the opportunity of witnessing in my own<br />
political life more than once. And, Sir, because the University<br />
is named after this great and famous man, I feel that a very<br />
great honour, even indifferently earned, has beon conferred upon<br />
me to have my name associated with one school of study in the<br />
University named aftor him. It will always be a source of<br />
immense pleasure and pride to me and to my family and to my<br />
descendonts. Now Sir, before I conclude, I would like to make<br />
one small contribution on the subject of the humanities. In<br />
this century, and particularly perhaps in the lost twenty years<br />
of it, there has been a very great, inevitable and proper<br />
concentration of mind on what I will call, in the natural sense,<br />
scientific studies, not only for prestige purposes and doing<br />
some violence to the moon or something of that kind. No, but<br />
because this world with its explosion of population, with the<br />
urgent demand that exists all over the world to increase the use<br />
of resources, the discovery of resources, the scientific application<br />
of resources in order to meet a growing population, has<br />
become a task of tremendous urgency and of very great international<br />
significance. And therefore it's right that there should be<br />
this attention, but it is wrong to think ns some people do, that<br />
studies which are not related to practical results of that kind<br />
are idlo and useless, 0 </p>
<p>This century hasn't failed either in science<br />
or in technology. It has produced almost the golden age of<br />
science and technology, but in terms of civilisation it has<br />
had failure after failure written up against it and that's<br />
because we have become too fond of the idea that we are clever<br />
people, that we are very, very smart to be able to understand<br />
all the forces of Nature and to harness them, to deal with them,<br />
whereas the truth, of course, is that civilisation I repeat<br />
something that I have said before many times civilisation is<br />
in the heart and mind of people and the task of the humanist the<br />
task of the people who teach and learn in a school of humanities<br />
it not to forget that history for example, is no useless study,<br />
since a man who is ignorant of it will have no sense of proportion,<br />
no benefit of experience in dealing with new problems as they<br />
arise. Languages...... and I throw in with a dying<br />
inflexion a word of classics because a precise understanding<br />
of words and a dislike of jargon will save this world from<br />
many confusions, and as many hostilities have arisen in the<br />
world and in society through misunderstanding as through gross<br />
differences of points of view. Philosophy,... how important<br />
that we should have physics and go beyond it to metaphysics*<br />
that we should understand something about the source and nature<br />
of ideas so that the man who passes through and who is even<br />
lightly touched by these things is forever thereafter a wiser<br />
man, a better-informed man, a better-balanced man. And, of<br />
course, so far as literature is concerned, I don't understand<br />
people who regard the reading of great masters of prose or of<br />
poetry as an irrelevant occupation, exhibiting a slight but<br />
perceptible eccentricity. If I could compel every man sitting<br />
in all the parliaments of Australia to read something of this<br />
kind every night on going back from Parliament House the<br />
standard of debate would rise in the most magnificent fashion.<br />
( Lughter) ( Applause) Sir, I say no more about that. I merely<br />
reiterate that what we want in the world is undoubtedly great<br />
physicists and great chemists and great engineers and what-haveyou<br />
because the world is crying aloud for their work for the<br />
sake of its own problems and its own human beings all over the<br />
world, but it needs even more that wisdom, human understanding,<br />
which produces what I would call an educated tolerance of ideas,<br />
It needs these things far more because wars, disasters of that<br />
kind, bestial repressions here and there the kind of thing we<br />
become accustomed to reading about almost every day in the<br />
newspapers don't arise from mechanical causes they don't arise<br />
because of some jealousy between one scientist and another.<br />
On the contrary, science tends more and more to be international<br />
in its quality, in its thought. These things arise from the<br />
fact that men have inadequately learned to understand men or to<br />
have men understand them, because there is not this quiet,<br />
passionless humanity sufficiently distributed around the world<br />
to make the very thought of some of these events that I have<br />
mentioned impossible. Sir, I repeat, you've done me a very great<br />
honour. I shall remember this occasion but I shall remember even<br />
more the fact that in this new university being pursued as it is<br />
with such vigour, such imagination, having as it most certainly<br />
has, a great future you should have thought fit to associate<br />
my name with a great section of that University; this is, I think,<br />
the greatest honour that any university could pay to any man.<br />
So I give it my blessing and I once more declare it open, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
