<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4392</transcript-id>
    <title>REFERENDUM CAMPAIGN ADDRESS - GREEK COMMUNITY CENTRE, BRISBANE - 9 MAY 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004392.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E f. IB AR GO0 8.00 P. M. Ij~ h'RAflA E<br />
PRIMEMINISTER<br />
FOJI PRESS<br />
REEEDU4 CAM4PAI GN ADDP3SS GREEK COMONITY . CNTK'R11,. 1RI. S. BNE<br />
it is very good to be here in Brisbane again. A-s you know,<br />
things havebeen a little hectic on the travel front since the<br />
controllers strike which has brought Australian air travel to<br />
almost a complete stop.<br />
The air controllers already earn almos t twvice as much as most-I<br />
Australians, and now they are demanding a further $ 7,000 a year.<br />
Their strike is disrupting the commtunity, and -causing peoplej<br />
considerable hardship, particularly since the strike coincides<br />
with school holidays. It has directly put at risk the Jobs of<br />
over -30,000, Australians. The Governmnent is determined to ensuxre<br />
that the proper process of the Arbitration and Coflciliation<br />
leciislation should b-8 observed. We believe this.-rresponsiile<br />
strike zhould be settled as qu-ickly as possible on its own merits,<br />
uninfluenced by industrial action.<br />
But what we are here to discuss today is the four referenidum<br />
proposals Australia will be volting on in twelve days time. It is<br />
importantL that we talk about this because the success of the<br />
referendums will ma~ ke a major contribution to the constitutional<br />
development of our counitry. It will establish whether as a nation<br />
we are willing to make constitutional changes which will introduce<br />
( N major and considered Teforims to improve our constitution. I<br />
The men who framed the constitutdon over 70 years ago served<br />
Australia well. They drew up a document which has not been outdated<br />
by the pas-age of 70 years, a-nd they realised that at<br />
particular moments in time, constitutional changes would have<br />
t-o be made to ia-intain the vitality of thie constitution, changes<br />
which would bring parts of the constitution into line wt.<br />
contenporary p~ toblems and issues. That is why they built a<br />
referendum mechanais into the constitution. It is our responsibility<br />
to vse the mochanism to bring about necessary change,<br />
and this is our opportunity to show we can use referendums as the<br />
Fouinding Fathers intended, to bring about sensible and practical<br />
reform~ s whicha will make the constitution serve the needs of our<br />
society better.<br />
Th1e fo0ur constitutional referendumu propose fair, sensible and<br />
just changes tL-o reform the constitution and I amt sure that the.-y<br />
will be successful. In the past, people have tended to vote ? 4o<br />
on constitutional questions, and in many cases there was a good<br />
reason for this. M'any past referendims tried to get; more power<br />
for-federal politicians, and more power for-Canberra. They sought<br />
to weaken the states. These referendums are different. / They do not </p>
<p>-2<br />
They do riot . seek more power for politicians. They do not seekt<br />
power for Canberra. They do niot wieaken the states. These refer,<br />
meet all the requirenyents Australi. jans have set for constitutiona<br />
changes<br />
The proposals have been care fully considered, and there has been<br />
extensive consultatioq about them.. There was detailed discussi<br />
of'the principles of 411 four referendums at the Hobart ConStitU<br />
Convention last year. I" The Comimonwealth, all the states, local<br />
governhment, and all the * major parties were represented at that<br />
convention. The principle-s". of -the four proposals were adopted<br />
overwhelmingly by the'convention.<br />
-The changes are supported on a bipartisan basis by all the major<br />
fedearal parties. Each of the four proposals vie are now supv" s-twas<br />
passed in the Hfouse of Representatives without a single A is.,<br />
voice, and each was passed by an overwhelming majority in the Se<br />
Putting thie four proposals forward is evidence of our concer-n to<br />
necessary constitutional reforats, and of our support for the' 7'<br />
constitutional convention which the Mcmahon Liberal Government<br />
' I established. The people have to be allowed to vote on thcse proposals which a<br />
generally supported and which are sotuid. Otherwise -the Constitu:<br />
Convention would be a meaningless exercise. Clearly, the issue<br />
constitutional reform is more important than that.<br />
Ii. The four changes are these. First, -that -there should be simulta:<br />
elections for the Senate and House of Representatives. It is si-T<br />
coiwion sense that the elections always be held at the same Vtwie,<br />
that the only time you have to vote in a Federal election is' , The;<br />
have to choose Australia's Government. This proposal will maint'.<br />
Br and strengthen the Senate. It also imans we will not have to vot<br />
Ienl ecatsi omnasn y inf edtheer aln eexlte cftoiuorn sy. e arsO. therwIt iseis wes omcoeutilmdl esh avsea ida s thco; lany a<br />
simultaneous elections can be achieved by bringing the House of<br />
Representatives election forwa-rd to coincide with that of the Set-<br />
Unfortunately, that is just not practical. At the last acotiori,<br />
two Houses were elected at the same time, because there was -a doi.<br />
dissolution. Despite this, they are now out of phase once again.<br />
Thi~ s is because under the constitution Senators terms are back-dr,<br />
to the previous July 1. The term for the House of Representativ.<br />
the other hand, only begins when members are sworn in, uisvally s(;<br />
weeks after the election. This means that unless the constitutio<br />
changed, the only -way -short of continual double dissolutions<br />
bring the elections together would be repeatedly to cut short thc<br />
term of the House of Representatives.<br />
V'ar from weakening the Senate, the simulitaneous elections<br />
will strengthen it. In 1975 it was quite by chanc that Bills ex~<br />
* which enabled the Governor General to order a double dissolution<br />
make both Houses face the people. Had the Senate not been abjLe to<br />
wthaes qpeuoitpel e byth ecmhasneclev est, h ats o thteh act irtchuemirs taanccteios nse _-m4sigtehdt pbeer rttjnu dgedi that,.<br />
double dissol. ution to occur a numaber of Senators would not havt,<br />
agreed to block supply. They would not have felt they had the r~. </p>
<p>to make the House of Representatives g0 to an electionl alonewithout<br />
the voters being ablie to pass a judgement on the Senate's<br />
hctions at the same time.<br />
The Senate's powers are great. But unless the present. situation is<br />
changed, unless the Senate ca.' n face the people if it sends the House<br />
of Representatives to an election, I can foresee two alter-native<br />
consequences, either of which will diminish the Senate's power and<br />
authority.<br />
on the one hand, the Senate might refuse to check a bad Government<br />
unless there happened to exist the circumstances which would permit<br />
a double ftsolution. Senators would not act because their actions<br />
could not be judged by the people at the election. This would erode<br />
the Senate's powers.<br />
Alternatively, if Senators were to make the House of Representatives<br />
go to an election without facing tlie people themselves, then there<br />
would be a public outcry against the Senate which could lead to the<br />
Senate's powers being restricted or abolished. tither of these<br />
S aslttaetrensa, tiavneds bawdo ufldo r bAe ubsatCd rafloiar. deTmhoact raisti c wghyo vietr nmise nti, n pboardta nfot. r ththaet<br />
this referendum be passed. It will preserve and protect the Senate's<br />
powers, and protection of the powers of the Senate, where all states<br />
are equally represented, means protection of the States.<br />
The second referendum proposal is that, whenever ' a Senator dies or<br />
resigns, he will. be replaced, for the remaindr of his term of office.<br />
by a member of the samne party. This will guarantee that your choice<br />
of parties for -the-Senate cannot be altered, by accident or design.<br />
our system of proportional represetntation for the Senate is designed<br />
to ensu. re that -&amp; he Senate represents all sectors of the electorate in<br />
precisely the correct proportions. Yet under the constitution as it<br />
presently stands, a vacancy in the Senate can result in a complete<br />
change in the party ba-la-nce. it is fundamental to our democracy that<br />
only the people should determine the balance of the parties in tbe<br />
W Senate. Once this proposal is accepted, the peoples choice will be<br />
preserved until they have an opportunity to make another choice at<br />
the next, election.<br />
The th-ird referendium propbsal is that voters in the ACT and Northern V<br />
Territory should have a vote in all future referendums. This is a[<br />
fuidemental right all other Australians have, but which voters in<br />
the territories are denied. I know of no rational or reasonable<br />
argument for denying territorial voters this basic right. Territorial~<br />
voters have the same obligations as other Australians. They pay ta. xes,<br />
they are obliged to observe the laws of the Commonwealth, they vote<br />
for members of Parliament. The outcome of referendums affeot<br />
them as much as they do other Australians. Oar demouracy is the<br />
weakder until the voters of the territories have the basic right to<br />
vote in referendums restored to them. / The fourth </p>
<p>A<br />
The fourth. and final refarendwn proposal is to set a r-etiring<br />
age for Federal. justices-. fl igh court justices would : retire at<br />
and the retirement age for other Federal Court Judges would<br />
be determined by Parliament. -The ' proposal does not affect the<br />
terms of judges already appointed to ' 1the Rench_. There is thus<br />
no question of acting in breach of -the' existing Judges terms of<br />
appointment. This proposal. i-s 6nL1%_ reasonable. Most jobs have<br />
retirement ages, and for gobd rea-son. Judges are as af fected by<br />
old age as the rest of us. It is only fair that after the age of<br />
responsibility should b handed over to younger people. This<br />
is even more important now that the new system of Federal Family<br />
Courts have been set up, K~<br />
All four referendum proposals ar'fir, just and reasonable.<br />
They meet all the requirement's for iuccess. They have been<br />
extensively considered. They&gt; have the support of all major<br />
Federal parties. They do not involve more power for Canberra,<br />
they will make the constitution work better-<br />
The polls show that all the referendums are supported by substantial<br />
m~ ajorities in all states. There is particularly strong support in<br />
Queensand, for every proposal, and Queensland have always been in<br />
the forefront of constitutional changes with a particularly stro4<br />
record for supporting referendum proposals. Queensland has voted<br />
Yes on 18 of the 32 referendums since Federation a far higher<br />
proportion than some of the southern states.<br />
But we all know that there is no surer guarantee of defeat, than<br />
complace-ntly believing success is assured.<br />
To g arantee success, we should all go out and work for the<br />
referendums, by talking to people about-them, by manning polling<br />
booths, by doing all we can to increase. support for them.<br />
If we all do this, then I have no doubt the referendums will<br />
be agreed to by a strong majority in Queensland. And this Is<br />
of tundamnental importance to the referendums being passed overall. ' C C </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
