<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4718</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S VISIT, 23 MAY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/05/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004718.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
If-VX OV A M vk Iv<br />
M II A<br />
FOR PRESS 23 MAY 1978<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT<br />
The Prime Minister will leave Australia in early June for a<br />
visit to New York, London, Paris and Bonn.<br />
While in New York he will'address the United Nations Special<br />
Session on Disarmament.<br />
This will be the first major conference held on disarmament in<br />
years and will provide an opportunity to express the views<br />
of Australia about the urgent need to concentrate the world's<br />
resources on economic and social progress rather than on<br />
building of armaments.<br />
In New York the Prime Minister will also meet with leading<br />
businessmen. Following his visit to New York, he will meet Prime Minister<br />
Callaghan in London on 9 June, Prime Minister Barre in Paris<br />
on 13 June, and Chancellor Schmidt in Bonn on 16 June.<br />
During these meetings he will raise international economic<br />
issues such as the present state of the global economy and<br />
relations between developed and developing countries.<br />
The Prime Minister attaches particular importance to achieving<br />
a substantial liberalisation in global trade.<br />
In the present round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations the<br />
major industrialised countries are not taking sufficient account<br />
of the interests of agricultural producing nations and<br />
developing countries.<br />
Unless there is a satisfactory offer on agriculture, then the MTN<br />
will be a failure. It will not improve the trading prospects<br />
of many of the developing countries and would be of little value<br />
to Australia.<br />
There is a need for the major developed countries to be more<br />
forthcoming in their position on the proposed Common Fund for the<br />
stabilisation of commodity prices.<br />
This is a matter of vital concern to many developing countries.<br />
He will be making this and other related points to European<br />
leaders during his visit. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
