<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7536</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH CLIVE ROBERTSON NEWSWORLD, 21 MARCH 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/03/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007536.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF UNEDITED INTERVIEW WITH CLIVE ROBERTSON,<br />
NEWSWORLD, 21 MARCH 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
ROBERTSON: Mr Hawke the first time I was aware of you, you<br />
were long side-boarded, dark haired, boss of the ACTU with a<br />
lot of fire and I remember you being interviewed by two<br />
people in Perth and they must have offended you and you<br />
walked out. So they called you back and of course you had<br />
all the trump cards. You don't seem to do that so often<br />
now. PM: Well, perhaps the interviewers are better and perhaps<br />
I've matured. I don't think it is often much value whether<br />
it's on a TV interview or anywhere walking out on anything.<br />
ROBERTSON: It made good television though.<br />
PM: Probably did. It wasn't done for effect, I must have<br />
been very annoyed Clive.<br />
ROBERTSON: You seem to be somewhat toned down. I remember<br />
they used to say to you ' Oh Hawke's going to change', this<br />
is no disrespect, they used to say ' Hawke's going to change<br />
when he gets into Government, he can't be the ocker sort of<br />
bloke of the people, he's got to moderate a little'. Yet<br />
you seem to have swung back a bit, because you are very good<br />
0 with people, out on the hustings, out with people. You have<br />
something that perhaps a lot of your colleagues don't quite<br />
have. Are you conscious of that?<br />
PM: very simple, I know it doesn't sound funny, I hope it<br />
doesn't. I just do love people, I get on very well with<br />
people, always have. It's nothing that's come to me as<br />
Prime minister, but all my life I've mixed with people right<br />
across the spectrum. I really enjoy people. For a lot of<br />
politicians it's a chore, going out and mixing and meeting.<br />
Not for me, it's a stimulus, I enjoy it.<br />
ROBERTSON: It comes across well. I wonder if, on either<br />
side of politics, whether many understand how important that<br />
is. PM: I think a lot of them don't Clive. I'm not one of the<br />
Canberra knockers about the geography of Canberra, I think<br />
the idea of having a national capital is good but there is<br />
something about it in this sense that some people tend to<br />
think that that's where it all happens, that it really is </p>
<p>-2-<br />
the centre of the Australian universe. Well that of course<br />
is nonsense. It's convenient and proper I think to have a<br />
national capital but you've got to be out there meeting and<br />
mixing with people. You get your strength from it, it's a<br />
two-way thing.<br />
ROBERTSON: Give you a buzz does it?<br />
PM: Yes it does actually, it does give me a buzz really.<br />
ROBERTSON: Do you get down occasionally and need that sort<br />
of response?<br />
PM: No, not very often. No, I'm not a person who gets<br />
downs really. I mean, occasionally you get a bit tired, but<br />
I just have such I suppose I've expressed this by a love<br />
affair with the country, I just love Australia. I think<br />
it's just so far and away the best country in the world. I<br />
love the people and so it's very hard to get down being<br />
Prime Minister of Australia, I mean it's just an enormous<br />
privilege to be leader of it.<br />
ROBERTSON: Not a bad job is it?<br />
PM: I just do think it's the best country, I think we're<br />
the best people and I'm proud to say it.<br />
ROBERTSON: Do you ever, in your quieter moments at home<br />
when the phone is not ringing and you're not under pressure<br />
to make decisions or anything, are you ever sort of, a<br />
little in awe of the amount of power you have in a country<br />
like this?<br />
PM: It's a funny sort of thing Clive. Although I've had<br />
positions of power, it's been a while now as President of<br />
the ACTU for ten years and Prime Minister now for six. I<br />
can honestly say that I don't think about power. I'm not<br />
flash in my lifestyle and I mean the exercise of power has<br />
never seemed to me to justify the paradings and pomposity of<br />
so many leaders I see around the world. I bought when I was<br />
in Brussels once, there is a magnificent poster shop there<br />
and there was one that struck me, it was done in beautiful<br />
gold it was this sort of throne and a pair of general's<br />
boots, just the throne and the boots and the dust and the<br />
ashes. I've always had it displayed. I think it's a very<br />
salutory reminder of the transience of people with power.<br />
what I'm interested in is the sorts of things that you can<br />
do, being in a position of power, but the actual power<br />
itself has never been a fascination for me.<br />
ROBERTSON: It's interesting you should say that because our<br />
conception is, of course, that the politicians' raison<br />
d'etre, is their raison d'etre, they just want to be in<br />
power. You don't find that? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: No, it would obviously be dishonest Clive, if I didn't<br />
say that I hadn't pursued the position of power. I have. I<br />
wanted to be Prime Minister, I wanted to be Prime Minister<br />
for a long time. But I can honestly say, you know I think<br />
people who are with me would testify to this, that it's not<br />
a thing that I flaunt, it's not a thing that exercises the<br />
mind. Here I am, Bob Hawke, powerful Prime minister. What<br />
I am interested in is the things that you can do being in<br />
that powerful position, but I know that when the great<br />
prospectives of history are written, the pomposities or<br />
pretentions * of any individual myself included, will be just<br />
as dust. The important thing will be, well did that fellow<br />
do something at that time that made some marginal<br />
differences? And I hope that will be the judgement.<br />
ROBERTSON: Harking back to those days with your long<br />
side-boards and your dark hair, of which you have a lot<br />
which I would like when you die if you could will that to<br />
me. PM: Do a deal mate.<br />
ROBERTSON: You were described as loving a drink in those<br />
stories.<br />
PM: That would have been an understatement.<br />
ROBERTSON: Yes. How bad was the drink?<br />
PM: I was never an alcoholic in the sense that I could<br />
never work. I mean I worked, always worked very hard,<br />
always worked very hard. The reason I gave it up in the<br />
end, I just realised one night it was not the most elegant<br />
position, I was having a wee as a matter of fact and I<br />
wasn't full. But it's not a time when I normally get into<br />
profound thinking when I'm having a wee, but I just and<br />
0 I thought well I got to the stage where at the end of the<br />
day I'm looking forward too much to a drink, it was becoming<br />
something of a crutch to me. And I thought that was pretty<br />
unintelligent. So I just gave it up then and that's nine<br />
years ago now, I haven't had a drop since.<br />
ROBERTSON: How do you do that? I mean anyone who's got a<br />
problem with drink admitted or otherwise, wonders how a man<br />
can do that.<br />
PM: As I say, I wasn't an alcoholic in a sense that I just<br />
was being destroyed by it.<br />
ROBERTSON: Alcoholics never admit they are anyway.<br />
PM: Well, no I think I can be objective about it just in<br />
terms of the amount of work I did Clive. I mean anyone who<br />
knew me knew that I worked very hard. I did both here and<br />
when I was overseas, I worked very hard. But I know,<br />
looking at myself honestly, that I wasn't working as </p>
<p>-4-<br />
PM ( cont): efficiently, anywhere near as efficiently as I<br />
could have because of drink. I just didn't think it was an<br />
intelligent position to get into, to have it there as a<br />
crutch, that I needed it. And so I said no.<br />
ROBERTSON: Who was most surprised, yourself?<br />
PM: In one sense I was. I know that Hazel was very, very<br />
pleasantly surprised.<br />
ROBERTSON: How did you break the news to her?<br />
PM: I just told her.<br />
ROBERTSON: And she said ' yes dear'?<br />
PM: She said ' I hope that's going to work'.<br />
ROBERTSON: You're also accused, I use the word accused<br />
because no-one likes of being a womaniser. What do<br />
they mean by a womaniser?<br />
PM: They mean that I wasn't faithful to my wife.<br />
ROBERTSON: was that true?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
ROBERTSON: Did you stop that?<br />
PM: Yes. I don't think it's a thing Clive that I want to<br />
talk a great deal about, but the one thing I do want to say<br />
about it is the enormous, I don't know whether debt is the<br />
right word, but well I just do feel indebted to Hazel that<br />
she understood that it was a part of a pretty volatile,<br />
exuberant character and she knew that my love for her had<br />
never changed. I've always loved Hazel, always will. She<br />
understood very helpful.<br />
ROBERTSON: What do you think of the woman?<br />
PM: She's just an incredible woman, an incredible woman.<br />
She's a woman who, and I don't say this against her father<br />
who was a remarkable bloke in his way. But he had an idea<br />
as a lot of parents did in those days in the immediate<br />
post-war period that a place for a woman was not in a<br />
university, whatever her IQ. Hazel had consistently duxed<br />
her class in primary school and secondary school was just<br />
told ' well that's it, you don't go on to university, you go<br />
into a commercial career'. She's a very talented pianist<br />
too and so I've always felt very, very strong feelings about<br />
how this woman who had the capacity to have done a<br />
university degree and done anything in that area was stopped<br />
from doing it and yet was able to retain her charity towards<br />
her father and towards those who stopped her doing this with<br />
no sense of jealousy about other people who'd had the<br />
opportunity and the privilege of doing it. </p>
<p>ROBERTSON: How did you meet her?<br />
PM: Through the Church. Dad was a Congretational Minister<br />
as you know and she was in the same Congretational Church,<br />
it was a couple of suburbs away and we met through that. We<br />
started going out together when we were about 17 so we've<br />
been together for over 40 years now.<br />
ROBERTSON: It's a long relationship isn't it?<br />
PM: It is and I guess there are not very many women who<br />
would have put up with me in all that time.<br />
ROBERTSON: Does she always agree with your decisions, I<br />
mean does she<br />
PM: No, not with every decision.<br />
ROBERTSON: Does she have much influence if she doesn't<br />
agree? PM: Not with every decision. Well, another great strength<br />
of Hazel, she doesn't try and in a sense take advantage of<br />
the fact that she's the Prime Minister's wife, that she<br />
shares the same pillow with me and has the opportunity of<br />
perhaps getting to me in a way that no-one else can. She<br />
doesn't do that. We generally have a feeling Clive which is<br />
on the same wavelength, so the reasons for disagreement are<br />
very rare.<br />
ROBERTSON: What nickname does she have for you?<br />
PM: I don't think she has any nickname really. No, it's<br />
just Bob. Bob and Haze, Bob and Haze.<br />
ROBERTSON: We've had this little funny one, of course,<br />
you probably won't mention it. She recently had some<br />
cosmetic surgery, I'm surprised she told anyone. Is that<br />
part of the necessity, is it?<br />
PM: Well I mean, she didn't set out to make an<br />
announcement, it became known. She felt it appropriate to<br />
be straightforward about it and that's one of the things<br />
about her which is so attractive I think that she is a<br />
straightforward person.<br />
ROBERTSON: Do you think she needed the facelift?<br />
PM: Well I didn't think personally. I think she's very<br />
attractive. I mean I don't think she looks nearly sixty,<br />
she's in her sixtieth year and I think she's remarkably well<br />
preserved. But this is a personal thing and I think what<br />
she said was right, if people, not just Hazel, but if people<br />
feel that they are going to feel more comfortable doing it,<br />
then by all means if they're in a position to do it. She<br />
had my full support in doing it and still has. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
ROBERTSON: I didn't think she needed it. Pass that on to<br />
her will you?<br />
PM: That's very kind of you.<br />
ROBERTSON: Well that might make her feel bad now that she<br />
did it. She should've rung me first.<br />
PM: No, no,<br />
ROBERTSON: Now the media. You've been very clever with the<br />
media over the years. I was given a list of instructions of<br />
how to deal with you.<br />
PM: Were you?<br />
O ROBERTSON: Of course.<br />
PM: I bet you screwed it up and took no notice of it at<br />
all. ROBERTSON: Well I bore it in mind, but I thought, well if<br />
you wanted to play a game or whatever that's entirely up to<br />
you. You're boss man. They said that you'd try<br />
intimidating me earlier on to try and get the trump cards,<br />
that you can change very quickly from suddenly snapping or<br />
what have you. Is this a conscious thing that you've got to<br />
be in charge all the time regardless of the questions or is<br />
it just what the media seem to bring out in you?<br />
PM: No. Well, I mean if we rolled the tape on what we've<br />
been doing here I think you'd see I don't feel any<br />
compulsion to be in charge. But what I do feel a compulsion<br />
about is to have integrity from the interviewer. If someone<br />
plays games with me, then they'll find the sharp Hawke.<br />
S ROBERTSON: Have any defeated you? I mean are there a few<br />
that you'd rather not talk to again?<br />
PM: I cannot recall anyone who's defeated me. I think<br />
however that the sharpness of my reaction at times where<br />
I've been confronted with something that I've thought is not<br />
proper that that may not have won me the points. But I've<br />
been satisfied that if I'm faced with some crap or some<br />
lies, then I just don't take crap and lies lying down. I<br />
deal with it. It doesn't necessarily mean you always win<br />
the points I suppose.<br />
ROBERTSON: It must be very difficult for you, you've been<br />
in the limelight for a long time, to know that anything you<br />
say is taken down and used in evidence, out of context,<br />
years later. Does that make you very cautious in the way<br />
you say some things? Does it make you slow down what you<br />
say, or use words that are general and non specific? I<br />
mean, how do you defend yourself? </p>
<p>-7-<br />
PM:. I suppose at the margin you do that Clive. But I've<br />
taken the view in public life and I've been in it now for<br />
nearly 30 years. I went to the ACTU in 1958 as advocate and<br />
I started my first case in ' 59 so that's 30 years now.<br />
Really, I've operated on the principle in public life, say<br />
it as you see it, say it as you feel, you'll get some losses<br />
at times if you do that but overall in the end I think<br />
people I hope though what they say is ' well, when you've<br />
got Hawkie you're getting it as it is from him'. I think if<br />
you try to be too let me just qualify it. Every<br />
politician at times has got to be a little bit careful.<br />
There is not. a politician alive that doesn't have to be.<br />
But basically I call it as I see it.<br />
ROBERTSON: The most unflappable man I have seen on<br />
television has got to be Paul Keating. He could tell us the<br />
end of the world is coming next week and phrase it in such a<br />
way that we wouldn't worry. Do you admire that in him, that<br />
unflappability? PM: Yes, it's not just that, there are many things I admire<br />
in Paul Keating.<br />
ROBERTSON: Is that a coldness though, his unflappability?<br />
I mean, he doesn't have your, there's been no opportunity<br />
for us to see your ability with the common man in Keating.<br />
Is that something he should work on?<br />
PM: I'm on record as saying that I think Paul probably<br />
needs to try to get a bit more time to get around, but<br />
that's been said in a very positive sense. I just take the<br />
view that in terms of his professional capacity as a<br />
Treasurer, he is easily the best Treasurer Australia has had<br />
and one of the best that's around. He's so absorbed with<br />
that that he doesn't have very much time for these other<br />
things. I think that he understands that as time goes on he<br />
wants to find a bit more time to do that.<br />
ROBERTSON: Does he want to find time to be Prime Minister<br />
do you think?<br />
PM: Yes, of course he does. That's a perfectly legitimate<br />
ambition on his part.<br />
ROBERTSON: But not now?<br />
PM: No, no we have a very clear and amicable understanding.<br />
I don't think our relations have been better than they are<br />
now, at any stage.<br />
ROBERTSON: what's his clock collection like?<br />
PM: I haven't seen it all, but what I've seen is very<br />
impressive. It's a great tribute to Paul, he is self<br />
educated in this area as in most areas. He left school very<br />
early and his knowledge of economics is collossal.<br />
Self-taught, he had an intuitive understanding of finance </p>
<p>-8-<br />
PM ( cont): and economics which he's honed up and in this<br />
area of his passion for that period, it's not only<br />
clocks but he's extremely well read and articulate on the<br />
history, the art, the culture, the politics of that 19th<br />
century period and it is something which he's also turned to<br />
his advantage in that he got in early and these things are<br />
valuable. ROBERTSON: Like everything If you had to write a<br />
reference for Mr Howard, now I want you to be charitable<br />
here, forget about politics. If you had to write a<br />
reference, literally a reference for Mr Howard, what would<br />
you write?<br />
PM: That's a good question. If I had to be absolutely fair<br />
I would say that John Howard is a hard-working assiduous<br />
man. I think that's true. That he, if it had to be honest,<br />
it would have to have the warts as well as the pluses,..<br />
the hard-working and the assiduous is there, that I think<br />
that any person he worked for, outside of politics, he'd be<br />
loyal to. I mean he tried to get Andrew's job and so that's<br />
fair enough, I tried to get Bill's job. If I was writing a<br />
reference for him outside of politics I believe he would be<br />
loyal to those for whom he worked. So that's it<br />
assiduous, hard-working, loyalty, commitment. Those things<br />
I'd refer to.<br />
ROBERTSON: It's not bad.<br />
PM: Well, I don't think he'd come to me for a reference.<br />
ROBERTSON: No that was my next question but I think you've<br />
probably pre-empted that. A lot of true blue Labor voters<br />
say Hawke is not a Whitlam. Whitlam was the last of the<br />
real Labor type Prime Ministers, that you've gone a bit to<br />
the right. Do you find that there are shoes there that<br />
you're still trying to fit into or<br />
PM: Certainly not. May I say that they don't say that to<br />
me. There was a period I think when there was some thought<br />
that when we had to do a lot of the tough things that we<br />
weren't historically Labor because the truth is that the<br />
Hawke Labor Government is squarely in the historical Labor<br />
tradition. I'm not talking about the Whitlam position, I'm<br />
talking about the historical Labor tradition. I mean, what<br />
is the Labor tradition so that we don't waffle. Let's get<br />
down to the realities. The tradition of Labor is that the<br />
resources of the country should be used to give the ordinary<br />
person, those not born with privilege, the best possible<br />
chance. Now, how have we done that? Well in obvious ways<br />
we've done it, without going into a long political speel,<br />
but just going to the guts of* it. Jobs no kid or person<br />
is going to have a chance of developing if they haven't got<br />
a job. So we've created 1.3 million jobs which is four<br />
times faster than Fraser and Howard. It's more than twice<br />
as fast as the rest of the world. No Labor Government has<br />
ever done that, but then secondly and what was fundamental<br />
for me, I said it at the beginning, one thing we are going </p>
<p>PM ( cont): to change is that no kid, if we can help it, is<br />
going to be able to be denied the opportunity of education<br />
because they come from lower income parents. When we came<br />
to office, 36 percent of kids stayed on in school, one of<br />
the worst in the western world. It's now 58 percent and<br />
we'll have it up to 65 percent at the beginning of the<br />
And we've done that by pouring money in, it used to be $ 23<br />
the secondary education allowance for lower income and<br />
middle incomes, it's gone up now to $ 50. So the kids from<br />
working class families and middle income families who are<br />
not going on to school and who are therefore being denied<br />
for the rest of their life Clive, the rest of their life,<br />
the opportunity of developing their talents Now that's<br />
what a decent Government, a decent Labor Government is<br />
about. Those sorts of things.<br />
ROBERTSON: I might mention, since you brought up political<br />
issues, there's not much money in the till though. To keep<br />
going like this, you'd have to be an idealist won't you?<br />
PM: You can't do everything for people.<br />
ROBERTSON: You really have got troubles financially?<br />
PM: We've got troubles externally. We have a significant<br />
debt which is largely in the private sector's hands, but a<br />
significant debt. We can't keep going at a level of<br />
activity which is going to suck in imports and add to our<br />
external ROBERTSON: But are we in trouble as such?<br />
PM: No, we've got to be very careful but to say we're in<br />
trouble is putting a one sided picture. I mean, you know<br />
the rest of the world, I mean I would put this. There is<br />
just about every other country in the world would want to<br />
swap with Australia. You look at all the pluses we've got.<br />
ROBERTSON: But even so Mr Hawke, if you say it was a<br />
domestic situation, you are at home and your kids are at<br />
home, right?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
ROBERTSON: You're the boss of the ACTU and you've got this<br />
level of indebtedness for the family. What would you say to<br />
the family? You'd say ' we've got to cut down, Bankcard is<br />
out, we can't do this, this is the way it is, no more<br />
steaks'. That's what you'd do isn't it?<br />
PM: We have been. I mean<br />
ROBERTSON: You're not actually saying that are you? I<br />
asked someone why does Mr Hawke and Mr Keating say this, and<br />
they say it's not political expediency to say we're in<br />
trouble. </p>
<p>PM:. But it's not right to say that we haven't told the<br />
message as it should be. I was criticised by a lot of<br />
people in my Party before the ' 87 election for doing just<br />
this. They said ' you can't go and tell them things are<br />
crook and they've got to pull their belts in'. I said well<br />
that's the way it is and I went out and told them. I mean,<br />
John Howard was saying here is a $ 26 a week tax cut and I<br />
said that's irresponsible, we've got to tighten our belts<br />
and we won.<br />
ROBERTSON: I don't see your statement as being emphatic as<br />
you say it is. I don't see that you keep reminding us that<br />
we're really in trouble.<br />
PM: Because I don't that's the accurate way of putting it,<br />
to say that we're in trouble. I've said, just last week<br />
when the balance of payments figures came out, I said I'm<br />
glad that they're at the lower end, but then I said there's<br />
no room for complacency, we've still got to slow things<br />
down. we can't keep pulling in imports. That's what I<br />
really Why would I be running a tight monetary policy<br />
like I am now? I mean it's deadly, a tight monetary policy<br />
for a politician. Most people don't like high interest<br />
rates, but I've said to them we've got to have a high, tight<br />
monetary policy, we've got to have high interest rates to<br />
calm things down.<br />
ROBERTSON: Is your mortgage paid off, is it?<br />
PM: Yes, it is.<br />
ROBERTSON: That's nice isn't it?<br />
PM: Well, I'm lucky, but I had to go through the tough<br />
times, I really did. I was just thinking the other day, the<br />
times that Hazel and I went through, they were tough.<br />
ROBERTSON: Getting onto other things now, as we tend to<br />
say, in your travels you have been involved with protocol.<br />
Sometimes you don't look terribly comfortable. That's only<br />
my perception. Are you?<br />
PM: No, as I was saying in earlier part of the interview,<br />
all this pomp and ceremony has never meant anything to me.<br />
I always have to have someone there putting me in the right<br />
direction. I mean I never get excited about this, it's<br />
something that's got to be done. I accept that it's part of<br />
the job, but it's not something that I like very much.<br />
ROBERTSON: I'm told that you have, quote, appalling table<br />
manners. PM: That is appallingly untrue.<br />
ROBERTSON: Well why do they say that?<br />
PM: Who's they? </p>
<p>-11-<br />
ROBERTSON: I knew you'd say that. I'm not going to reveal<br />
it. I'll tell you later.<br />
PM: Will you? OK. It may be that people are referring to<br />
the fact that I'm not a diner outer and this business of<br />
spending hours at a dining table gives me the irates. I<br />
mean people on the dinner circuit, the restaurant circuit<br />
count me out. It just is something that I've never ever<br />
been interested in.<br />
ROBERTSON: Well what does that do to you when you're there<br />
and you have, to be there?<br />
PM: Well, I hope I can make interesting conversation but I<br />
really find sitting around at a table for hours and hours,<br />
it just is not something that grabs me and perhaps that<br />
feeling has come through to people.<br />
ROBERTSON: Now you are looking very fit.<br />
PM: Never felt better.<br />
ROBERTSON: You are looking fit and reflect on this, I<br />
was saying to someone, I said ' gee he's fit'. I said ' yes<br />
well who wants a sick tired old Prime minister, bad for<br />
moral'. How do you keep fit?<br />
PM: Thanks to Hazel basically. She's got me on to the<br />
body is just a machine. I mean, with a motor engine you<br />
wouldn't put crap into it because you know that run<br />
down. This is a much more sophisticated machine our body,<br />
so what you put into it really determines to a very large<br />
extent how you'll operate and function and Hazel's really<br />
got me on to t he sensible dietary regime and I get a fair<br />
bit of exercise so if you get good intake and exercise and<br />
once you put your head down you can go to sleep, which I<br />
can. ROBERTSON: How much sleep would you have on average?<br />
PM: It varies. I suppose when things are pretty tight and<br />
tough, six hours perhaps. But I can go on less than that<br />
for nights as long as I can grab eight or nine.<br />
ROBERTSON: What's the nicest thing anyone has ever said<br />
about you? Forget about modesty now, but the way you have<br />
evolved. The nicest thing.<br />
PM: The nicest thing I've had said to me was by a lady, I<br />
was out in the hustings some time ago and she said to me,<br />
it's the thing I want to feeland I think she said<br />
' Australia is a better place now',. She said we like one<br />
another now more than we used to before you came'.<br />
ROBERTSON: It's nice isn't it? </p>
<p>-12-<br />
PM: It's what I hope, that's what I hope the judgement will<br />
be and to have it said by this lady was beaut.<br />
ROBERTSON: You've heard of Dame Nellie Melba haven't you?<br />
PM: Yes, I have.<br />
ROBERTSON: She kept leaving. I wonder when you're going to<br />
not throw in the towel, what's the expression? Retire<br />
perhaps Would you retire too?<br />
PM: Well, r've gone on record as saying I'd like to get on<br />
that side of the table on television. I really do, I don't<br />
have a great compulsion to write a book but I have had the<br />
opportunity Clive in this position of meeting a whole range<br />
of people around the world and in this country who, in my<br />
judgement, have been significant in changing things or<br />
creating the conditions for change, have influenced people<br />
and events. I would love to do a series of interviews with<br />
some of these people on television so that I could share<br />
with millions of other people my understanding of the<br />
influence of those people.<br />
ROBERTSON: I wonder if you'd be a pussy cat as an<br />
interviewer? PM: I hope what I'd be is that people wouldn't know Bob<br />
Hawke was there. I think that's<br />
ROBERTSON: The means, not the end?<br />
PM: Yes, my model of an interviewer was Freeman in Face to<br />
Face. Remember the BBC series about 20 odd years ago.<br />
Brilliantly well informed and researched, didn't have a<br />
script there, question A, B, C He just flowed because he<br />
knew enough about it, flowed with the interviewee and so<br />
what was coming across was the interviewee. I think the big<br />
mistake with interviewers Clive is that they try and project<br />
themselves. The secret of interviewing is to know the<br />
subject so that you can get that person there giving out<br />
what they've got to say.<br />
ROBERTSON: A couple of ancillary questions here about the<br />
new Parliament House. I won't ask you how we can afford it<br />
in the light of things but it's there. It appears now you<br />
can drive straight in and not have the confrontation on the<br />
steps which is a thing we miss. You might not always miss<br />
it, but it's not a bad vehicle for covering the events of<br />
the day. Do you miss that at all?<br />
PM: No, basically because I've substituted for it. I mean<br />
it wasn't good for the media, it wasn't good for me. It was<br />
physically and, in every sense, it was crazy. So what we've<br />
substituted there, they are happy about it and I am, is that<br />
we pretty regularly have the meeting inside, in a press<br />
conference situation, I think it's better. </p>
<p>-13-<br />
ROBERTSON: Inside I gather there's a $ 90 million circa,<br />
million setup of television cameras everywhere. Is that<br />
going to herald one day having parliament broadcast?<br />
PM4: Well my view about it is that I think it would be a<br />
good idea, but I don't know whether people will want it or.<br />
not. But my own view is that I think it ought to be and<br />
this is a purely personal view. I'm not talking about the<br />
Party or the Government or the Parliament. I think it ought<br />
to be televised and so that the stations could make their<br />
judgement about how much they wanted to show. I don't know<br />
that people would want to have it on permanently but it<br />
ought to be ' capable of being televised permanently so that<br />
it could be televised. I think the only thing you'd have to<br />
watch then in fairness, is that it wasn't just dramatically<br />
spectacular grabs of grubby stuff. I mean that would be a<br />
bit unfair to the institution and it would be to any human<br />
being. I mean just to get the bad stuff is to project the<br />
wrong image. So I think you need to get some balance.<br />
ROBERTSON: Well it would be a nice justification for the<br />
money spent on what's already there wouldn't it?<br />
PM4: Yes, I think<br />
ROBERTSON: Why was it put in, for that<br />
PM4: On the assumption that it would be used, that people<br />
would want it televised at some stage I think.<br />
ROBERTSON: Final question. What is it that really moves<br />
you in the world? That always gets to you? Mine is reading<br />
poetry. I can't read poetry without crying. What's your<br />
emotional Archilles heel?<br />
PM: Hurt. I can't stand seeing, particularly people who<br />
can't I can't stand people being hurt, and hurt<br />
particularly unfairly. If I see a child being hurt, my<br />
emotions come up. That's the thing that hurts me. Hurt.<br />
ROBERTSON: Mr Hawke, thank you.<br />
PM: Thanks Clive.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
