<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9270</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON PJ KEATING MP ADDRESS TO THE FINANCIAL REVIEWS CONFERENCE &quot;AUSTRALIAN INDUSTRY AND THE KEATING GOVERMENT&quot; SYDNEY TUESDAY 5 JULY 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/07/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009270.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
ADDRESS TO THE FINANCIAL REVIEWS CONFERENCE " AUSTRALIAN<br />
INDUSTRY AND THE KEATING GOVERNMENT', SYDNEY,<br />
TUESDAY 5 JULY 1994<br />
Let me begin by congratulating the Financial Review for taking the initiative in<br />
organising this conference on the future of Australian industry.<br />
Just a few years ago there were some who would have placed a question<br />
mark at the end of the title of any conference on Australian industry.<br />
And the agenda would have largely revolved around tariff levels and sectoral<br />
support measures.<br />
At such a conference there would also have been those who argued we would<br />
be better off to turn our backs on the reforms of the<br />
We should, the argumentwyould run, have re-regulated the economy and<br />
returned to a regime which sheltered Australian industry from a more<br />
competitive world.<br />
At the heart of that debate was a test of our national will and a test of our<br />
national nerve.<br />
Last week in Jakarta I saw the results of having passed those tests.<br />
In Indonesia I had the privilege of opening Australia's biggest ever trade<br />
promotion in that country.<br />
More than 200 exhibitors participated in an impressive display of just how<br />
much Australia has to offer the world and, in particular, the Asia Pacific.<br />
After visiting the exhibition you could not fail to be struck by what a distance<br />
we have travelled in the past decade. </p>
<p>The overwhelming impression the exhibition projected was of a diverse,<br />
vibrant economy with world class capacities in services and manufactures.<br />
Industry sectors ranging from building and construction to education and<br />
training and from marine, engineering and manufacturing services to power<br />
and energy were all strongly represented.<br />
So I come to this conference this morning with fresh evidence of what<br />
Australian industry is achieving and a well-founded confidence that we will<br />
build on these successes.<br />
The Financial Review has therefore picked a very appropriate time to stage an<br />
examination and discussion of industry policy.<br />
As a starting point the Government does not see industry policy being<br />
developed and implemented in isolation from the other major policy streams.<br />
Industry depends for its success as much on macro-economic, industrial<br />
relations and trade policy and micro-economic reforms as it does on specific<br />
industry develo~~ ri6nt aind supp'ori m-easures.-<br />
In fact, much of what we are striving to achieve in industry policy is intertwined<br />
with our objectives in these other areas.<br />
Industries committed to world best practice need a Government committed to<br />
ensuring the domestic impediments are cleared away.<br />
Our industry policy is, therefore, in many respects an international competition<br />
policy which seeks to identify and encourage those characteristics we need to<br />
be able to compete in world markets.<br />
Australian industry should. approach the future with optimism.<br />
Few other developed countiribs can match the circumstances in which<br />
Australia presently finds itself. Few countries have such good prospects for<br />
growth. No predictions for the future of Australian industry can be made, however,<br />
without comparing its condition now with the situation of a decade ago.<br />
While we had some strong export industries at that time particularly in mining<br />
and agriculture the manufacturing sector was still sheltered from<br />
international competition by absurdly high tariff barriers.<br />
For all this protection, the reality was that industry was not strong.<br />
The steel industry, with our resource endowments, should have been one of<br />
the nation's strongest industries. Instead it was going out the door backwards. 4/ 7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>Australian made cars were becoming less and less competitive both in terms<br />
of price and quality. The response of the outgoing government was to<br />
propose yet more protection, with tariffs~ of up to 125 per cent.<br />
While other countries were increasingly participating in world trade, we were<br />
putting the shutters up.<br />
When we introduced the first tranche of tariff reductions we were warned we<br />
would have a disaster on our hands. While the last generation of Australian<br />
managers may have been found wanting in certain respects, they certainly<br />
had an entrepreneurial approach to finding reasons for government<br />
assistance. We were told that our market was too small to allow international<br />
competition, our labour force was unskilled, lazy and strike-prone and that<br />
nobody else had a level playing field and so why should we.<br />
Instead we have a story of outstanding success.<br />
Exports of elaborately transformed manufacturing have grown by 17 per cent a<br />
year ince 1988, one of the very highest rates of growth in the OECD.<br />
Services exports, which have grown by about 9 per cent a year, now account<br />
for 20 per cent of exports.<br />
Small firms have emerged from the former torpid business environment and<br />
become innovative and export-oriented McKinsey has identified more than<br />
700 small and medium manufacturing exporters.<br />
Foreign-owned companies that told us they could well leave Australia without<br />
protection, have invested in state of the art plant, competed successfully with<br />
imports and also entered export markets.<br />
Whole industries that were set to be counted among the dead or dying have<br />
undergone Lazarus-like revivals.<br />
Firms have embraced innoVtion, giving us one of the highest growth rates of<br />
business R&amp; D among developed economies if even from a relatively low base.<br />
The reasons for such success are complex. Partly it is due to the basic skills<br />
that were lying dormant in Australian industry. We were also helped by some<br />
natural good fortune, such as our location in this dynamic region of the world<br />
and the fact that we are reaping great benefits, in terms of productive<br />
diversity, from our multicultural population.<br />
Some credit must also go to the Government, for having the courage to take<br />
the hard choices and stick with them.<br />
Policies in a range of areas will support the future growth of Australian<br />
industry, and a continuation of its success in world markets. They will help us<br />
maintain high rates of employment growth so we can reduce unemployment.<br />
We want to bring an unemployment rate of 5 per cent within our grasp by the<br />
4/ 7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>turn of the century. To achieve this, we must have a high rate of economic<br />
growth. We must also ensure that this growth is sustainable.<br />
We have made an impressive start.<br />
We are growing at an annual rate of 5 per cent, which makes Australia a star<br />
performer among OECD countries. We have added 260,000 new jobs over<br />
the past year and re duced the unemployment rate to under 10 per cent.<br />
Inflation is running at less than 1 1/ 2 per cent and expectations are for a<br />
continued low inflation environment.<br />
As a nation we can take satisfaction from this progress.<br />
But even more importantly, we can expect to see strong growth with low<br />
inflation continue.<br />
Of course, there will be the permanently miserable who will want to talk up the<br />
risk of the economy overheating, of economic boom followed by economic<br />
bust. In their minds, the risk flickers from too little growth to too much growth.<br />
But the reality is quite the contrary. The nature of this recovery gives us<br />
confidence that strong growth can be sustained. We have what we term a<br />
" 1rolling" recovery.<br />
Initially, the recovery was driven by public demand, the pick up in dwelling<br />
investment and strong exports. The strong export performance is set to<br />
continue, but as the recovery proceeds the stimulus from the public sector is<br />
quite deliberately being wound back while the dwelling cycle will naturally<br />
begin to wane. In its place, business fixed investment will both support overall<br />
demand and provide the wherewithal for greater production.<br />
The rolling nature of the recovery is not limited to what is happening in<br />
Australia, it is also a characteristic of what is happening internationally. Some<br />
of you may have seen a sh~ t article in the latest OECD Economic Outlook<br />
reporting that major OECD economies are not synchronised in their current<br />
cycles. The US recovered earlier than Japan and much of Europe which are<br />
both now beginning to turn.<br />
The consequences for Australia are very healthy. Commodity prices have not<br />
gone on a roller coaster, with the result that our exchange rate has been more<br />
stable. Our traders continue to benefit from favourable international<br />
competitiveness which is still around 30 per cent better than in the early 1980s<br />
notwithstanding the recent rise in the Australian dollar.<br />
Moreover, as this international cycle has helped keep inflation low worldwide<br />
so our rolling recovery has helped in Australia. The OECD now sees inflation<br />
remaining between 2 and 2 1/ 2 per cent over 1994 and 1995.<br />
We have established a low inflation culture and we intend to keep it. 4/ 7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>We have not done this by telling the Reserve Bank to blindly pursue zero<br />
inflation and then washing our hands oftthe matter. Instead, we have given<br />
inflation a central role in all economic policy.<br />
Of course, monetary policy has a major role to play in containing inflation. But<br />
monetary policy, by itself, doesn't deliver a change to the culture of inflation. It<br />
is too indiscriminate and cannot be left to apply indefinitely.<br />
Today's low inflation has been achieved through monetary and fiscal policies<br />
as well as through the Accord with the unions and the flexibility we have<br />
introduced into the supply side of the economy. The attitudes of those directly<br />
involved in setting prices or wages have been changed.<br />
And it is these changed attitudes that are at the heart of keeping inflation low.<br />
We won't achieve that by relying on any simple-minded formula to control<br />
interest rates. Instead, we need to maintain comprehensive policy action<br />
through: the continuing commitment to low inflation via the Accord VII;<br />
the improved responsiveness of our workplaces to enterprise bargaining<br />
and higher skill levels;<br />
the lessening of the risk of bottlenecks by re-engaging those unemployed<br />
for lengthy periods with the labour market;<br />
the greater competition to our product markets from domestic and<br />
international sources, via the exchange rate and lower tariffs;<br />
the progressive winding back of fiscal stimulus as the recovery proceeds;<br />
and when action is warranted, appropriate adjustments to monetary policy.<br />
All of this represents a mature approach to policy. And the increasingly<br />
mature approach to business that we are seeing in our workplaces is also<br />
delivering results.<br />
The A=" r will continue to play a central role in wages policy. It has been<br />
crucial in achieving appropriate aggregate wage outcomes since 1983 and<br />
pulling inflation down. It has facilitated the move towards a more<br />
decentralised productivity related wage fixing system.<br />
Enterprise bargaining has become the primary focus for wage fixing and a<br />
vital catalyst for workplace reform. The new industrial relations legislation<br />
provides the framework to achieve the labour market flexibility, productivity<br />
growth and wage restraint necessary for strong and sustainable economic<br />
growth. 4V7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>As I announced in Working Nation, the Government aims to see 80 per cent of<br />
employees in the Federal award sector-covered by direct bargains by the end<br />
of 1996.<br />
In addition, awards will be reviewed and simplified.<br />
Working Nation spells out the close interrelationship between industry policy,<br />
the creation of secure and rewarding jobs in flexible high productivity<br />
workplaces, and the policies we need to educate and train the work force that<br />
industry needs.<br />
Working Nation contains a number of important initiatives to get<br />
unemployment down and the skills of our work force up including a Job<br />
Compact for those unemployed for over 18 months, and a Youth Training<br />
Initiative. Under these initiatives training and jobs will be provided for people who have<br />
become marginalised from the mainstream of economic life during the<br />
recession. We want to ensure that this is a recovery for all Australians not just for the<br />
top end of town.<br />
But the case for doing so is not just based on equity arguments, important as<br />
they are. Failing to address long-term unemployment would be very costly to<br />
the whole economy.<br />
But we are succeeding in meeting this challenge. In the past three years,<br />
close to a quarter of a million long-term unemployed workers have been hired<br />
by employers through JOBSTART subsidies alone.<br />
As from yesterday, the attractiveness of Jobstart has been improved.<br />
Subsidies have been incregsed, the period of subsidy has been extended to<br />
9 months and a bonus payment is available to employers who keep these<br />
workers on for a year.<br />
Employers will also have the incentive of the new training wage which will be<br />
payable to all unemployed people and new entrants to the labour force.<br />
Together with Jobstart, this will mean an employer will be able to receive<br />
subsidies ranging from $ 5000 to $ 8260 for taking on a long-term unemployed<br />
person. The training initiatives in the White Paper were also directed to the longer<br />
term needs of industry. They encompass a comprehensive strategy to enable<br />
industry to sharpen its competitive advantage through getting the training it<br />
needs. 4/ 7194 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>We all must recognise that training is not a welfare issue. It is not something<br />
the Government is promoting because we feel sorry for the unemployed.<br />
Training is a mainstream economic issue, and promoting training is the<br />
responsibility of all of us business, unions and government.<br />
Both management and work force skills are vital to the competitiveness of<br />
firms. Access to capital and investment in technology are important of course,<br />
but these can often be replicated by competitors. Replication based on the<br />
skills of individuals in a firm's work force is much more difficult.<br />
Whatever the reasons for the failure to invest in training in the past, Working<br />
Nation wipes out any excuse for this state of affairs to continue.<br />
The Government has set up NETTFORCE, chaired by Lindsay Fox and<br />
including Ivan Deveson, Bert Evans, Ted Wright and Bill Kelty as members, to<br />
ensure companies are aware of the benefits available, and assist them to take<br />
full advantage of them.<br />
NETTFORCE is developing 21 national, industry-based traineeships. It aims<br />
to cut through the delays of the past and provide employers with a one-stop<br />
shop to put together training and industrial packages to get trainees employed<br />
quickly. Industry is being given the opportunity to have more say in early vocational<br />
education. The Australian Student Traineeship Foundation announced in the<br />
White Paper will provide funds directly to local groups, which may be<br />
committees of employers, to run traineeships for year 11 and 12 students.<br />
Students will combine school studies with work experience in local industry<br />
and off-the-job training. The traineeships will allow young people to complete<br />
their training in a shorter time.<br />
Industry must set the direction of training and drive the administrative<br />
processes so that they are simple and relevant to the needs of firms.<br />
I I<br />
To show our faith in this approach, the Government has suspended the<br />
Training Guarantee Levy. Now it is up to industry to take advantage of the<br />
funding we have provided. It is up to industry to take control of the training<br />
agenda. Industry must play a strong, positive role and capitalise on the opportunities<br />
the world is offering. The game plan has been spelt out in Working Nation.<br />
There, we have set out a comprehensive industry policy that will help<br />
Australian firms achieve world class excellence. It is about providing a<br />
competitive environment for doing business and enhancing the capacity of<br />
businesses to succeed by being competitive both in Australia and on world<br />
markets.<br />
Tax policies have worked to reduce industry costs and enhance our<br />
competitiveness. Australia is the lowest taxed country in the OECD. Working<br />
417/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>Nation includes tax initiatives to encourage private investment in public<br />
infrastructure, investment in smaller and medium sized enterprises and the<br />
location of regional headquarters in Australia.<br />
The Government's telecommunications, Government Business Enterprises,<br />
shipping, aviation and waterfront reforms are reducing input costs, increasing<br />
the quality of goods and services and ensuring the reliability of supply.<br />
We've introduced competition to telecommunications and seen domestic call<br />
rates fall by about 13 per cent and international rates by more than<br />
per cent in the past three years. Further falls in prices and improvements<br />
in service quality and diversity can be expected as carriers position<br />
themselves for increased competition after 1997.<br />
While domestic costs have been cut, the export sector of the<br />
telecommunications industry is thriving. Exports reached $ 545 million during<br />
1991-92 and are likely to grow to as much as $ 2 billion in 1996-97.<br />
In shipping, the average crew level on Australian ships has come down from<br />
28 in 1959 to 18 and is expected to be reduced to as low as 16 in 1995.<br />
These reductions will save over $ 80 million a year across the Australian flag<br />
fleet, or about $ 1.2 million a year on an average ship.<br />
On the waterfront, the workforce has been reduced from 9000 to fewer than<br />
4000 in the face of strongly increasing trade volumes, more than doubling<br />
labour productivity. Container handling rates in the more efficient terminals<br />
are now at levels comparable with our trading partners. Ship turnaround times<br />
have been cut by nearly 45 per cent. Truck queues and waiting times are<br />
much shorter.<br />
We are increasingly look~ ing to the States to achieve, in partnership with the<br />
Commonwealth, rapid progress with the reform priorities that remain. Here<br />
governments are working to reform electricity, gas and water supplies, further<br />
maritime reform, and to ref&amp; m the legal profession. Industry will benefit from<br />
lower input costs and better services.<br />
Most importantly, we are working with the States to implement a national<br />
competition policy, which will increase the transparency of pricing practices of<br />
public monopolies and provide a more systematic basis for reforming public<br />
utilities, the professions and agricultural production and marketing.<br />
The transformation that our manufacturing and services sectors have<br />
undergone during the past decade has produced a new generation of firms<br />
and business leaders.<br />
No longer are they producing just for a protected domestic market, accepting<br />
second best methods. 4/ 7194 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>Rather they are operating at the leading edge of their industries using world<br />
best practices and technology.<br />
Our industry policy reflects these changes. From a phase when the focus was<br />
on opening up the Australian economy, we have moved to policies which<br />
support our firms to grow, be innovators and ultimately prosper in world<br />
markets.<br />
Access to finance will be improved through a range of measures including the<br />
provision of expert advice, promotion of the role of the Commonwealth<br />
Development Bank, greater tax concessions for equity finance provided by<br />
Pooled Development Funds, and the extension of the Export Finance<br />
Insurance Corporation's facilities to cover the services sector and<br />
manufactured goods.<br />
Innovation will be encouraged by a more generous R&amp; D tax concession, a<br />
program assisting small and medium sized enterprises ( SMEs) to<br />
commercialise new technology and a national network for technology access<br />
and diffusion.<br />
Management and marketing skills will be encouraged by expanding enterprise<br />
development services to SMEs including a major effort to target potential<br />
exporters focusing on innovation, quality, research and development,<br />
marketing and management skills. SMEs will also be helped to form networks<br />
and alliances.<br />
SMEs will benefit from the National Regional Development Strategy that will<br />
provide more than $ 150 million to regions over the next four years to enhance<br />
the development of their competitive industries.<br />
The establishment of Au~ lndustry within the Industry, Science and Technology<br />
portfolio will improve coordination and delivery of programs and bring together<br />
all the Commonwealth's business assistance programs under a unified<br />
marketing structure. The Chair of Auslndustry's Advisory Board and a<br />
significant proportion of its membership will be drawn from the private sector.<br />
Auslndustry will provide the entry point for all Commonwealth business<br />
improvement programs and, through the existing network of the National<br />
Industry Extension Service, provide a major link to State and Territory<br />
programs.<br />
The successful pursuit of global m~ rkets is vital to the future success of<br />
Australian industry. The growth of world trade has been faster than the<br />
growth of world output in nearly every year since World War 11 and much of<br />
this growth has been happening right on our doorstep with exports from the<br />
developing Asian countries growing at twice the rate of world exports over the<br />
past decade. 4/ 7194 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>The successful conclusion of the Uruguay Round and the creation of the new<br />
World Trading Organisation will add around $ 400 billion annually to the world<br />
economy. For Australia alone the Uruguay Round will be eventually worth an<br />
annual $ 5 billion.<br />
As well as big gains for Australian farmers and miners, the Round outcome<br />
will bring great opportunities for our manufacturers and services exporters.<br />
The Round achieved the largest global tariff cutting package ever negotiated<br />
with tariff cuts on products of interest to Australia of more than 50 per cent.<br />
The new GATT agreement on services will allow Australian services exports,<br />
already worth some $ 15 billion, to compete on an equal footing in this fast<br />
growing $ 1 trillion ($ 1,000 billion) area of world trade. Sectors such as<br />
telecommunications, banking, insurance, professional and business service<br />
sectors stand to benefit substantially from this agreement. On current trends<br />
by the end of next year Australia could well be a net exporter of services.<br />
With APEC, we are working to build an enduring framework for trade and<br />
economic relations in the Asia-Pacific. Already, APEC is doing work that will<br />
greatly facilitate Asia-Pacific trade and investment.<br />
In November this year, I expect APEC leaders will endorse a set of investment<br />
principles that will define some common approaches to the treatment of<br />
foreign direct investment flows. Work on harmonising product standards and<br />
mutual recognition of standards and conformance arrangements is also<br />
proceeding well. This will have tangible benefits for Australian businesses<br />
trading and investing in the region.<br />
Having recently met President Soeharto, who will chair this year's APEC<br />
leaders' meeting, I am convinced that in November APEC leaders will again<br />
push APEC on to a higher. plane of activity. President Soeharto and I both<br />
want our region to be actively involved in liberalising trade, facilitating<br />
commerce and strengthening economic linkages between APEC members,<br />
whose economies are now the powerhouse of the world economy.<br />
And we want business to drive the APEC process. After all, business, not<br />
government is responsible for the high level of economic integration amongst<br />
APEC economies intra-APEC trade is even higher than intra-EU trade.<br />
Business now needs to give APEC governments a clear message on what it<br />
wants. One way this will happen is through the APEC Business Forum, which<br />
was established by APEC leaders last year in Seattle and will report to the<br />
November 1994 leaders meeting in Bogor, Indonesia.<br />
We are exploring with ASEAN countries the possible link between CER and<br />
the ASEAN Free Trade Area ( AFTA). This is an attractive proposal. Our<br />
economies are very complementary and linking them could create a market of<br />
335 million people with a GDP of about $ 1 trillion. ASEAN members have<br />
4V7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
<p>agreed that the idea merits further consideration and we will continue to<br />
discuss it with them.<br />
At home, the Government is working directly with exporters through Austrade's<br />
and other exporter assistance programs and in industry-based strategies<br />
such as for those for agri-food, construction, and health services to jointly<br />
harness Government and industry export efforts.<br />
Australia is on the threshold of a new and exciting era.<br />
Australia has opened up, culturally and economically, to the rest of the world.<br />
We are ready to reap the harvest of opportunities presented by the new<br />
technologies, the new era of trade driven world growth and our proximity to the<br />
most dynamic and fastest growing region of the world.<br />
Our immigration and multicultural policies have nurtured a unique human<br />
resource on which astute businesses are beginning to capitalise a culturally<br />
and linguistically diverse nation, whose migrant and ethnic communities are<br />
drawn from all parts of the world, including our fastest growing export markets<br />
in the Asia-Pacific.<br />
All this means that Australia can become one of the great social democracies<br />
and one of the great trading nations a nation with a vibrant, multidimensional<br />
culture underwriting a strong, vigorous and internationally<br />
competitive industrial base trading extensively in all the continents. Our<br />
cornerstone will be especially close links to the Asia-Pacific nations.<br />
In all this, industry must play a prime role. Industry must be able to capitalise<br />
on the full range of skills, talents and potential in Australia's human resources,<br />
including its youth, its women, and its many migrant and ethnic communities.<br />
There is still a long way to go. We will succeed because we are a naturally<br />
innovative nation with the will to change. Our unique combination of policies<br />
to free up markets, while en'suring social justice for all, provides the<br />
opportunities, fairness and cohesion needed to succeed.<br />
Thank you 4/ 7/ 94 9: 54 PM </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
