<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>15232</transcript-id>
    <title>theradio.com Weekly Message  - Deforestation</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/04/2007</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...</p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.90Mb - 124secs)</p>
<p>More than 4.4 million trees are cut down around the world every day and over a year, an area twice the size of Tasmania is cleared of forests. </p>
<p>This is having a marked impact on global warming. Almost 20 per cent of global greenhouse gas emissions come from clearing forests - that's more than all the world's emissions from transport combined. </p>
<p>My Government has decided to tackle this problem head on. We will provide $200 million to kickstart a global fund to support forest planting and sustainable forest management and limit the destruction of remaining forests. </p>
<p>If the world can halve the rate of global deforestation we could reduce greenhouse gas emissions by three billion tonnes a year - more than five times Australia's total annual emissions. </p>
<p>Under this program we will invite like-minded countries such as the United States, the United Kingdom, Germany, Brazil, New Zealand, Japan and Indonesia to join the initiative. </p>
<p>It will be particularly helpful in changing forest management in many of our neighbouring countries including the Solomon Islands, Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu.</p>
<p>It comes on top of practical action within Australia to reduce emissions - including seed funding for more than $3 billion worth of climate change projects - and our adds to our reputation as a world leader in sustainable forest management. </p>
<p>The Global Initiative on Forests and Climate is another example of my Government's practical action to reduce global greenhouse gas emissions. </p>
<p>This action helps to cut greenhouse gas emissions but does not hurt the Australian economy. </p>
<p>  Listen to this Speech (MP3 -   1.90Mb - 124secs)</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
