<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6621</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 17 APRIL 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/04/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006621.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
-4~ j A UST&gt; AIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 17 April 1985<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, the New Zealand Rugby Union team is<br />
going to South Africa.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have any comment on that.<br />
PM: I think it's very sad. I applauded in the Parliament<br />
yesterday the attempts by Mr Lange to dissuade the New Zealand<br />
Rugby Union from that course of action. I regret that they have<br />
not seen fit to accede to his strong advice in this respect. In<br />
my conversations with Mr Lange today I expressed the hope thatthe<br />
decision would be the other way. I can't understand how those<br />
responsible for the administration of the code there can do<br />
something which is going to cause very very considerable<br />
dissension within New Zealand itself and possibly cause<br />
repurcusslons, adverse repurcussions, for them in other fields<br />
where they seek to compete internationally with other nations,<br />
quite apart, of course, from the basic question of principle that<br />
they can be giving aid and comfort to a rascist regime like that.<br />
JOURNALIST: In view of the decision by the New Zealand Rugby do<br />
you think that Australia should play rugby with New Zealand as<br />
planned, I think, in June or July.<br />
PM: Well, we'd have to give consideration to that and to see<br />
w ; hether in these circumstances that would involve an infringement<br />
of either the letter of the spirit of the Gleneagles Agreement.<br />
We'll have a look at that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister will you allow the All-Blacks people<br />
to transit in Australia.<br />
PM: We'll have to give consideration to that Laurie. Obviously,<br />
by definition, the matter hasn't arisen until just an hour or so<br />
ago. We'll give consideration..<br />
JOURNALIST: Presumably Prime Minister this strengthens those in<br />
the Australian cricket community who believe that touring South<br />
Africa is acceptable. </p>
<p>PM: Well I don't know whether it would strengthen them or not.<br />
I'd just like to say a couple of things that. You know I gave an<br />
answer in the Parliament yesterday. If it is the case that these<br />
1offers have been made I would certainly express the renewed hope<br />
that those involved should not take any comfort or support from<br />
the decision of the New Zealand Rugby Union. Another point I want<br />
Al to make on it I notice in reading about the rumours, there's<br />
some suggestion that the players who would accept would be<br />
beneficiaries of a very considerable amount of money because it is<br />
said the contracts have been signed in a third country and<br />
negotiated in a way which would avoid the payment of the income<br />
tax in Australia. Can I just say this to those who may be<br />
7 contemplating this offer, because it's been made, that the<br />
Australian Tax Office will be looking extraordinarily closely at<br />
any arrangements with a view to ensuring that tax to be paid in<br />
Australia in that can at all possibly can be done they should not<br />
be contemplating the acceptance of any such offer if they are on<br />
the basis that there will be any slackness as far as the<br />
Australian Taxation authorities are concerned.<br />
JOURNALIST: ( Inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, I would hope that under the existing legislation there<br />
I iwould be sufficient powers, but we'll be looking at it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir, if the tour does take place would you be<br />
prepared to take action to prevent it, such as by canc-elling<br />
passports or refusing to issue passports<br />
PM: Well, I think you know the way I always operate. I don't<br />
like to go down the path unnecessarily. And I indeed expect that<br />
as a result of the actions within the cricket community itself<br />
that if there is something in fact nipped here, it can be nipped<br />
in the bud. If against all the policy of the Cricket Board and of<br />
4 the Government, which I repeat has been so overwhelmingly<br />
supported by sportsmen and women and organised sporting bodies in<br />
Australia, if a few cricketers decided to put themselves beyond<br />
the pale, then we would have to look at that. But I'm not going<br />
to hypothesise on that at this stage.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke on a different subject, are you attracted to<br />
the idea of changing the world parity pricing policy to offset the<br />
inflation devaluation.<br />
PM: Michelle, I never cease to admire your tenacity in seeking to<br />
get me to debate my clear rules in these conferences. That's a<br />
matter that will be discussed in the Cabinet shortly and that's<br />
where I'll put my point of view.<br />
JOURNALIST: the Queensland power dispute you claim that the<br />
Premier has deliberately brought about this national blockade is<br />
an extremely serious charge.<br />
.4 </p>
<p>PM: Well the Queensland economy is in a very serious state.<br />
Those figures which I read out to the Parliament today are a<br />
devastating indictment of the Queensland Government and the<br />
Queensland Premier gross economic mismanagement, which is<br />
dragging that State down and down. I would think that the<br />
Queensland Government and its Premier wouldn't like the spotlight<br />
to be on their own abysmal incompetence as demonstrated. And this<br />
could be a very handy diversion. But I would just go back to the<br />
basic point that I made again in the Parliament the sensible<br />
thing to do is to sit down and talk. It won't be resolved in any<br />
other way.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well what can you do now that Sir Joh has rejected<br />
your invitation.<br />
PM: Well I suppose wait for good sense to emerge. It's a fairly<br />
slow process up there.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you attracted to the idea of Federal legislation<br />
of some kind to override aspects of Queensland's..<br />
PM: I'm not attracted to it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Would you consider it.<br />
PM: Well again we're in the hypothetical area. I don't want to<br />
complicate the situation. I've gone as far as saying I'm not<br />
attracted to the id -ea and I maintain the hope that better sense<br />
will prevail up there.<br />
JOURNALIST: The reality is, sir, that you can't really do very<br />
much can you?<br />
PM: Well I've been involved i n industrial relations for a fairly<br />
long time and probably know as much about it as most people in the<br />
country and I can recall on many occasions it being said there's<br />
nothing you can do. There's no industrial dispute in the history<br />
of this country that hasn't been settled. The sensible thing to<br />
realise, if you are concerned with the interests of the people, is<br />
that it's better to settle them early by negotiation than making<br />
an enormous number of people suffer needlessly.<br />
JOURNALIST: This is hardly just an industrial dispute though,<br />
it's more political than industrial.<br />
PM: Well I think obviously, Gary, there are political elements to<br />
i-t. I mean I've made the point that I think there's a large<br />
diversionary element in it. But there would have been political<br />
elements in other disputes too, so it doesn't really take away<br />
from the basic truth of the proposition I make.<br />
JOURNALIST: Senator Macklin's Bill, one-vote-one-value when<br />
will you be deciding your approach to that. </p>
<p>PM: Cabinet will consider that shortly.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister was there any sort of breakthrough on<br />
Kampuchea as a result of your talks with the Chinese and, if so,<br />
can you tell us what..<br />
PM: It wouldn't be right to say a breakthrough, no. But what we<br />
really did together I had some initial talks with the General<br />
Secretary and then I had Bill Hayden in with us. And what we<br />
really did together was to expose our thinking. Bill explained to<br />
the General Secretary the discussions that he'd had with the<br />
Vietnamese and the Kampuchean Prime Minister. And I think it is<br />
fair to say this that we established that we had identical<br />
objectives. And those objectives quite clearly are that we wished<br />
to see the emergence of an independent Kampuchea which would be<br />
able to resume contact in all fields economically, socially and<br />
politically with its neighbours in the region. And that to<br />
achieve that situation there needed to be a total withdrawal of<br />
the Vietnamese forces. The Chinese leadership made it clear that,<br />
and let me say this is not entirely new ground but a<br />
clarification, that they would be prepared to enter into dialogue<br />
when there was a statement of the intention to totally withdraw<br />
and the commencement of the actual withdrawal a real withdrawal<br />
and not the withdrawal of some replaced by others which has<br />
happened in the past that if there was the statement and the<br />
real beginning of a withdrawal they would be prepared to enter<br />
into dialogue on this matter. Mr Hu Yaobang repeated again, and<br />
he had said this to me when I met him last year, that the Chinese<br />
were not looking to the emergence of a Kampuchea ruled by the<br />
Khmer Rouge that what China wanted to see was a Government of<br />
coalition under the leadership of Sihanouk. The Chinese<br />
leadership expressed their satisfaction with gratitude for the<br />
work that Australia had been doing in seeking to open up the<br />
possibilities of dialogue in this area. And, as distinct from<br />
some suggestions that appeared to be in some press reports from<br />
overseas earlier, there is no suggestion of a perception on the<br />
part of Hu Yaobang that he saw some differences between Bill<br />
Hayden and myself. He indeed congratulated Mr Hayden on the<br />
outstanding work that he'd been doing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, on tax reform, do you think it's practical<br />
to talk about substantial reforms of the tax system without some<br />
form of broadly based indirect tax.<br />
PM: Oh, it's possible to talk about it Mike. I mean I think what<br />
you've got to do in this period is-to try and examine all options<br />
that are available and there must be some option which doesn't<br />
include that. As I've said consistently, you've got to look at<br />
the balance of considerations that apply that's economic<br />
efficiency, equity, simplicity and acceptability. Now those are<br />
all relevant criteria. And if you accept that those are relevant<br />
criteria then I think it's appropriate in the course leading up<br />
to the White Paper and then to the Summit beyond, to have a look<br />
at a variety of packages to see in that process and out of that </p>
<p>process whether one package rather than another is more likely to<br />
satisfy those criteria. And this process is continuing.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Keating's view that if Cabinet Members were<br />
presented with information on economic forecasting that they'd<br />
probably leak.<br />
PM: Well I just want to say two things about this. I answered a<br />
question in the Parliament on it and indicated there that I was<br />
considering the correspondence that I'd received from Bill and<br />
Paul and we'll have a look at this in Cabinet. So I don't really<br />
want to say anything more about it other than to make briefly the<br />
second point. And that is to say that I am a student of history<br />
and there is some, let me say, precedent for disclosing it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, could I just return to Queensland for<br />
moment having seen the way in which conceptions and<br />
misconceptions about the Australian politics can feed into the<br />
exchange rate, aren't you at all concerned that the seemingly<br />
fatalistic conceptions of the governments and the ACTU..<br />
industrial tactics might create the impression abroad that we have<br />
a government that is soft on industrial anarchy?<br />
PM: No, because I still take the view Max that there is an<br />
Tement of rationality in the markets here and overseas and all<br />
they have to do is to look at the record of this Government in<br />
regard to industrial relations. I don't want to bore you again<br />
going into the detail, but it is the fact that under. this<br />
Government's control of and approach to industrial relations this<br />
country has had the best record for 17 years. And it stands in<br />
stark contrast the policies of confrontation that operation in Qld<br />
and therefore the rational judgement to make is that it is better,<br />
you are going to have a better situation in the longer term if you<br />
don't keep on the path of confrontation. Now of course in the<br />
mean time there will be difficulties. And I deplore that fact.<br />
But you have got to have your perspectives right on this and I<br />
believe that the more rational elements of the markets will have<br />
their perspectives right. And the alternative is simple. I mean,<br />
you go back to the earlier period when you had the conservatives<br />
in government, now they attempted the rhetoric of confrontation,<br />
at times they talked about resorting beyond rhetoric to<br />
legislation. But what was their record. It was an abyssmal<br />
record. So if you are looking at what happens to the level of<br />
economic performance, what happens to the impact upon economic<br />
performance of an industrial relations situation. The clear and<br />
indisputable fact is that the approach of the confrontationists<br />
hasn't worked. It has produced worse economic results. The<br />
alternative of our approach, which is not rhetoric about<br />
concensus, but it is practical discussion, negotiations produces<br />
the better economic result. And it would be entirely irrational<br />
for the market to make a judgement which was not reconcilable with<br />
the facts and with the records. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Would you have preferred a different approach by the<br />
ACTU, in specifying 51 companies?<br />
PM: Well I am not in the business any more telling the ACTU how<br />
to run its business. We have made it clear to the ACTU that we<br />
would prefer a situation in which there wasn't industrial<br />
confrontation, industrial action and reaction, and that is why I<br />
have behind the scenes and publicly now been trying to get the<br />
Queensland Government to sit down with us and with the ACTU. it<br />
is inevitable I guess that if you have a situation where the<br />
Queensland Government, which is in this dispute on one side, says<br />
it is not going to talk, it is not going to negotiate, it is not<br />
going to discuss, human nature being what it is here, not only in<br />
this country, but around the free world, you are going to have<br />
reaction. And you don't have to be theoretical about this, you<br />
simply have to know your Australian history, know your history of<br />
other countries, and in the end, I repeat, in the end, this<br />
dispute will be resolved as a result of discussion and<br />
negotiation. That is as certain as, I won't use the phrase that<br />
has drifted into the political lexicon recently. He has actually<br />
named a horse that, that is about as successful as he is in some<br />
other respects. It is as certain as anything you like to nominate<br />
that this dispute will finally be resolved by discussion, by<br />
negotiation. The tragedy is-that the Queensland Premier is<br />
determined to spread out the time before that happens and the<br />
spreading out of that time benefits no-one. It is against th~ e<br />
interests of the people of Queensland and it is against the<br />
interests of the people of Australia. And it is ultimately<br />
against the interests of the Queensland Government and all people<br />
and all parties concerned. And that is the tragedy that he is<br />
hell bent on spreading out this spreading before ultimately there<br />
is a negotiation to settle it.<br />
JOURNALIST: When you say the dispute will in fact be resolved, Mr<br />
Hawke, that is on the assumption that there has to . be some change<br />
to Queensland laws<br />
PM: No that assumption is not necessarily correct because the<br />
matter I believe could be resolved without the repeal of the<br />
laws. I mean you can have legislation on the statute book which<br />
is not implemented. And you know that is true in the federal and<br />
in a number of state spheres. So the matter is capable of<br />
resolution without the actual repeal of the legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke can you give us your reaction the defeat in<br />
the WA Legislative Council earlier today of the Burke Government's<br />
land rights legislation and say what your Government now intends<br />
to do about applying national uniform principles to WA?<br />
PM: Well I regret that the attempt by the Western Australian<br />
G overnment to affect some improvement in this area, was defeated<br />
by interests in the Legislative Council which are not reflective<br />
of the, I think, of the view of reasonable people. That they were<br />
not concerned with dealing with this on a consideration of its </p>
<p>merits. It is quite clear that the Western Australian Government,<br />
although'it hadn't come to, in all respects, exactly the same<br />
positions as the Commonwealth has indicated in its model approach,<br />
nevertheless addressed itself to the problems in way which had<br />
involved consultation not only with the aboriginal people but with<br />
the mining industry, the rural industry and it is interesting that<br />
the mining industry in Western Australia supported the legislation<br />
and as I understand it sought to get the Liberal Party and the<br />
others in the Legislative Council to agree. So that indicates I<br />
think the reasonable of approach of the West Australian<br />
Government. But the Liberal Party was not interested in<br />
realities, it was not interested how you could get a<br />
reconciliation of the legitimate interests of the aboriginal<br />
people and of the mining industry. That is of no concern to them.<br />
Like their colleagues here in this place, they are concerned<br />
always with political point scoring, gimmickery. The last thing<br />
on their agenda of politics is the real public interest. They are<br />
the same all over Australia, federally and there. Now, what we<br />
will do is to continue what we are doing. That is, Clyde Holding<br />
has drawn up, not a final bill, it's modelled as a basis for<br />
discussion around Australia with the states, with the aboriginal<br />
people, with mining communities, with the farming communities, and<br />
he will proceed with those discussions and when they have been<br />
taken through to an appropriate point then the Commonwealth will<br />
legislate.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can I take you back to Mr Lange once more, and<br />
presumably you didn't only discuss rugby, can you give us a<br />
summary of what you did discuss and was there a specifically a reiteration<br />
of each side's position on the nuclear ships question?<br />
PM: Well we discussed a range of issues. I can't go to them all,<br />
ti1me doesn't permit. But we did talk about that issue. I reiterated<br />
the view of the Australian Government, I didn't do it<br />
with heat or fury or venom but just calmly said well we have got<br />
our position and you have got yours, we think we are right.<br />
JOURNALIST: And he said the same?<br />
PM: Well he left me with the impression that he wasn't going to<br />
change his position.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did you repeat the position I think you made in your<br />
January letter to Mr Lange that different interpretations and<br />
obligations under the treaty were I think if I remember rightly<br />
unacceptable?<br />
PM: Well I don't recall the exact language but let me say what<br />
the thrust of that letter was and what our position is. We don't<br />
need to depend upon any letter of January or February or any other<br />
date. The position of the Australian Government is quite clear<br />
and indeed it is unequivocal. And that is that we have an<br />
alliance relationship and we believe that under that alliance<br />
relationship the capacity of the ships of the naval vessels of the </p>
<p>United. States to visit our ports is an intrinsic element of that<br />
treaty relationship. We don't take the view that the United<br />
States can have two navies, one for the rest of the world and one<br />
for treaty partner, New Zealand. That is not consistent with any<br />
realities that are seen, in our view. Now, and we have so acted.<br />
Now, the New Zealand Government has a different view. Now they<br />
are entitled to have that. Now we have from the outset not tried<br />
internally or externally to engage in political point scoring.<br />
Again as distinct from our political opponents. Just let me<br />
remind you of the Peacock track record on this one. Last year<br />
what did he say. He said the Australian Government must bring<br />
pressure to bear upon New Zealand. It is totally unacceptable<br />
that they can have this position. Australia and the Australian<br />
Government should negotiate a new treaty with the United States<br />
and if I were there, he said, I would give the New Zealand<br />
Government 3 months, this was in October so they were given till<br />
January, and then after 3 months if they hadn't come to heel, if<br />
they hadn't responded to this hectoring and bullying then the time<br />
had come, there must be bilateral new treaty negotiated with the<br />
United States. Well as in so many things, it is just a pity that<br />
they hadn't stopped their attempt at political point scoring and<br />
thought about the issues and realised what should have been<br />
obvious to any reasonably intelligent person from day one. The<br />
United States wasn't interested in the negotiation of a new<br />
treaty. The position of the United States was identical with the<br />
position of Australia and that is that the treaty should stay in<br />
place, should be there, that if the New Zealand Government acted<br />
in a way which didn't enable the continuation of the normal<br />
operation of the treaty, then there should be discussions between<br />
the United States and Australia to ensure that leaving the treaty<br />
in place you would work out what need to be done to look after the<br />
interests of the two countries. Now that has been the consistent<br />
position of the United States and of Australia. When belatedly Mr<br />
Peacock very, very belatedly started to understand the realities<br />
of the situation, that it was nonsense to talk about the<br />
negotiation of a new treaty. He then said now the role of<br />
Australia should be to try and bring the United States and New<br />
Zealand together and of course we keep the treaty. Now you have<br />
got, you should have this role. Now it is quite clear that in<br />
this area, as in so many others, the Australian people can't pay<br />
any attention to the posturing of the Peac ocks and the<br />
conservatives. What is in the interests of this country is what<br />
we have been doing from the beginning, that is a situation has<br />
been created outside our control, we had nothing to do with it, so<br />
our primary responsibility is to look after the interests, the<br />
security interests of Australia. We have done that. The<br />
relationship between Australia and the United States remains as<br />
strong as ever. It is very interesting to note, very interesting<br />
to note in the light again of the political posturing of the<br />
Peacocks and the conservatives in the House about the damage to<br />
the United States/ Australian alliance. What did the Ambassador of<br />
the United States say last night in Sydney. I guess he knows a<br />
bit more about it than Mr Peacock and the conservatives. After<br />
all he is very close, personally to the President of the United </p>
<p>Statesaa n d he is reported as saying in Sydney last night that the<br />
relationship between Australia and the United States out of these<br />
recent events is as strong, he said, perhaps stronger than it has<br />
ever been. Now there are the realities. Because the United<br />
States administration realises that what this Government is been<br />
doing from the word go is to deal with the realities. Not to<br />
politically posture, but to say now what needs to be done in a<br />
situation created by others to protect the relationship. And we<br />
have done that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister could you at any stage or have you<br />
expressed to Mr Lange concern that he has misrepresented<br />
Australian Government policy first in a speech and later in a<br />
magazine article in New Zealand..<br />
PM: You refer to the Listener article?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM: There has been correspondence between Mr Hayden and Mr Lange<br />
on this where Mr Hayden pointed out the error of interpretation by<br />
Mr Lange. Mr Lange graciously has accepted that he was wrong on<br />
that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Did he a polog ise?<br />
PM: We are not about the business of securing apologies. Two<br />
civilised people, Mr Lange and Mr Hayden. Mr Hayden wrote to Mr<br />
Lange and said you are wrong, proved that he was wrong. And Mr<br />
Lange in a civilised fashion said I accept.<br />
JOURNALIST: clarification he called it.<br />
PM: Well I mean I don't know. I don't mind how you describe it.<br />
The proposition that he put in the article was not accurate. Mr<br />
Hayden in a very calm letter pointed that out. It was accepted by<br />
Mr Lange. So there was no need for me today to say anything more<br />
about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Lange has recently paraded around Africa<br />
displaying a collection of nuke-busters T-shirts. Have you any<br />
comments on that display given..<br />
PM: Well it may be good for the New Zealand clothing industry and<br />
the New Zealand economy. And I think, as he would, it needs all<br />
the help it can. If that opens up new markets well that's good.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke did you and Mr Lange discuss at any stage<br />
whatever the Chinese position might be on nuclear armed ships.<br />
PM: Yes, we did have a discussion about that.<br />
JOURNALIST: Were you able to enlighten Mr Lange or vice versa. </p>
<p>PM: I wa's able to enlighten Mr Lange, I think.<br />
JOURNALIST: Could you enlighten us.<br />
PM: I think you already have been. You had the opportunity of<br />
speaking to my dear friend Hu Yaobang and I think my dear friend<br />
Hu Yaobang made it very clear he knows what the position is, I<br />
know what the position is and I think Mr Lange now knows what the<br />
position is.<br />
JOURNALIST: Back on Queensland..<br />
PM: I like this Africa, New Zealand..<br />
JOURNALIST: You said that the point-scoring that's going on at<br />
the moment between the Government and the Opposition over<br />
Queensland. Do you think that might be the opportunity for some<br />
statesmanship whereby your Government uses its special<br />
relationship with the ACTU and the Opposition uses its special<br />
relationship with the Queensland Premier to [ negotiations].<br />
PM: Well, I've done that. I mean I haven't got a special<br />
relationship with Sir Joh and I doubt, may I say, whether Mr<br />
Peacock has. I mean you know I never disclose confidential<br />
discussions, but I'm left with the impression out of discussions<br />
with Sir Joh that he doesn't have Mr Peacock on a political<br />
pedestal. Nevertheless there may be some residual relationship<br />
there which Mr Peacock is able to either directly or vicariously<br />
take advantage of. I've done what I can do as Prime Minister of<br />
Australia. I've said the Federal Government wants to negotiate<br />
with you. I've got agreement with the ACTU that they will sit<br />
down and there is no doubt that if the three of us sat down we<br />
could settle it. Now, if you're right then there may be a role<br />
for Mr Peacock to pick up the. phone to Joh and-say well, look,<br />
Hawke's done the right thi'ng, he's talked to the ACTU, they are<br />
prepared to sit down and negotiate, now I ask you to do the same<br />
thing. But you'd have to wonder on the performance of the last<br />
couple of days whether he's prepared to do that. It's a great<br />
misfortune.<br />
JOURNALIST: that the Opposition has more influence with the<br />
Bjelke-Petersen Government than yourself.<br />
PM: I mean I can't really say about that. I mean I suppose you<br />
would think they ought to but Sir Joh has been very very<br />
derogatory in many of his comments about the Opposition and I just<br />
don't know what the state of their relationship is. But prima<br />
facie you'd think that they ought to have the opportunity of doing<br />
something. ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
