<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>435</transcript-id>
    <title>PM 5/1962 - BUSH FIRES IN VICTORIA AND ADDITIONAL FLOOD RELIEF IN NEW SOUTH WALES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/01/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000435_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>BUSH 1PIRES IN TICTORIA</p>
<p>The tragic bush fires in Victoria have shocked us all, and I extend my sympathy to those who have suffered bereavement, loss of their homes or personal distress in other ways. </p>
<p>I have received a request today from the Acting Premier<br />of Victoria, Mr. Rylah, through Senator Gorton for Commonwealth<br />financial assistance and I have replied as foliows<br />" You have requested Cowmonwealth grant towards<br />cost of providing relief to persons in distress as result<br />of disastrous bushfires. On behalf of Commonwealth<br />Government I wish again to extend deepest sympathy to all<br />people affected by this disaster. -Je are readily prepared<br />to join with ycar Government in contributing towards the<br />cost of a scheme designed to provide for the immediate<br />relief of persons in distressed and necessitous<br />circumstances. I assume that at the ea liest opportunity<br />you will furnish details of the damage and provide an<br />estimate of the cost of relief measures. Meantime<br />Commonwealth funds will be made available if required on<br />the usual conditions, namely ( one) for with State<br />Government ( two) the joint funds are used only for relief<br />of personal hardship and ( three) expenditure is in due<br />course certified by State Auditor-General."<br />In November last, the Commonwealth made a grant of up<br />to œ 30,000 on a for basis with the State of New South ; ales<br />for the relief of personal hardship resulting from the recent<br />serious floods in New South Wales.</p>
<p>The Premier of New South Wales, ir. Heffron has now informed me that additional funds will be needed for this purpose and he has asked the Commonwealth to provide a further œ 20,000 to match a similar amount to be made available by the State. 7e have agreed to provide a further grant of up to œ 20,000. as sought by the Premier.</p>
<p>CANBERR. A,<br />18th January, 1962.</p>
<p><strong>P. M. No. 5/1962</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
