<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4383</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE ACT DIVISION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY ANNUAL DINNER - 2 MAY 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>02/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004383.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E? 413APGO: 7.3 p . f AUSTRAL! A<br />
FOR PRESS 2 M1AY 197 7<br />
ADDRESS TO THE A. C. T. DIVISIO. N OF THE LIBERAL PARTY.: ANNUAL D'<br />
Madam Chairman.<br />
The political rights of residents of the Australian Capital<br />
Territory have reached a cross road. A referendum will soon<br />
decide whether ACT residents will have the right to vote in<br />
future referendums. High Court challenges lave been zma:-de<br />
against the ACT's representation in the Commo'nwealth aianz<br />
and we are moving towards a substantially greater dc,-* ree of ogovernment<br />
for the ACT.<br />
It therefore seems appropriate to speak to you tonight abou te<br />
politimi rights not only of ACT residents but of all Austraia! z.<br />
Flowing from our over-riding concern for the individu.-al, Liberals<br />
* believe that all Australians should be adequately in-formed of<br />
Government decisions, have as great a say as possible suchL<br />
decisions, be given the greatest maximum degree of choice in how<br />
they live their lives, and be protected from unnecessai-Y ivas--. oz<br />
of personal privacy.<br />
We have initiated a wide ranging progra~ te designed to i:-, rove<br />
the quality ofIustralian democracy. Our determination nco give<br />
the people of the ACT their democratic rights is an imncr7arn<br />
part of this prcg-ra-mze. First, on 21 M, 1ay, we will tc. a ot<br />
of the people the prcDosal that ACT and 11crthern Territc.--<br />
residents have a vote at all future referenciums. I t s ee<br />
extraordinary that Territorial voters have so long been l~ nc-.<br />
such a fundamental right. The outcome of referendums isjust<br />
as important to Territory voters as it is to all dther Asrlz<br />
Iknow of no rational and reasonable argurment for d-rnyin-soma--<br />
Australians this basic right. But more of referend,= s later.<br />
We have also decided to introduce a substantial measare of sel.-<br />
Dngaeomvtaeiirnl-einSdm ternpatrt oivfpeoo rs aanltsdh e ffAoinCrT a nt. bc1y2ii a9 dl etlrpcao, nw, saeftresi rn gt oO fa awnpi odweele er crtaaenrdeg e nAooCf-T, . Alsg~ sevzb~ v?<br />
aicsdo nmztih-dtenc ieonrteardta. ito icnnaI tl 7cl-4aupsibtt aeb le, c lsotsraicr-slnys1eI fdric ca ha-o; newtr gveeavdre er, a tos thtohafe t Cbocel= iccua) yursn e. -2Canirh..<br />
SoM-e 7people mnay think th.. tb~ e pre~ sent system works Ie<br />
endsho~ dnot be alLered. But as Canberra b-) co-nos a-,<br />
ignrceraetaerz indgelgyr eel arogfe aaunthdo iycOndnr~ oPWlexb itm etropolis, accepitbionirga<br />
* desirable and ', IneScapable. </p>
<p>Since ACT and Northern Territory representation in the Federal<br />
Parliament is under challenge in the courts, I cannot comment<br />
extensively on this issue, except to say that the Government<br />
wholeheartedly supports representation of the ACT and Northern<br />
Territory in the Parliament.<br />
Australians have a lively tradition of effective scrutiny of the<br />
activities-of Governments and officials. We have a vigorous.<br />
press which is seldom reluctant to criticise the Government of<br />
the day, and Parliament provides many avenues for inquiry into<br />
Government activity, notably Question Time, and the activities<br />
of the Public Accounts Committee, the Senate Estimates Committees<br />
and the Auditor General.<br />
The Liberal Pat-ty has been committed both in opposition and<br />
GovernmenttD increasing Parliament's effectiveness. It is our<br />
intention to strengthen the traditional Parliamentary safeguards<br />
and the investigatory role of Parliament. We have established a<br />
Public Expenditure Committee which has already. commenced its task<br />
of carefully vetting particular areas of public expenditure, and<br />
this process of reform will be a continuing one. We are commiiitted<br />
to safeguarding the public interest against any tendencies to<br />
excessive secrecy or interference in Australians' lives, and to<br />
take steps to meet the increasing demands placed upon Government<br />
for information on its activities.<br />
We as Liberals have a commitment to increase citizen's participation<br />
in decision making. First, we are most conc erned to protect<br />
individual privacy. In April last year we referred the matter<br />
of protection of privacy to the Australian Law Reform Commission.<br />
With the increased computerisation of data on the personal details<br />
of each of us, it has become necessary to legislate to give positive<br />
protection to the privacy of each of us. The Law Reform Commissi4on<br />
recently issued a discussion paper called Privacy and Publication-<br />
Proposals for Protection The Commission is now inviting public<br />
comment on these proposals. When the Government has received the<br />
Commission's final report, we shall give serious consideration to<br />
introducing legislation to increase your rights against unwarranzed<br />
invations of personal privacy. The Government has also initiated<br />
a programme to increase the publication by Government Departments<br />
of relevant and useful information. We propose to publish manuals<br />
and rules of procedure adopted by Commonwealth Departments.<br />
All Departments with significant operational functions will produce<br />
informative and relevant annual reports, even where there is no<br />
statutory requirement to do so. The Government is also considering<br />
reform of the Government Information Services pursuant to<br />
recommendations submitted by the Coombs Royal Commission.<br />
Our third policy objective in this area is to confer certain rights<br />
on individual Australians to obtain upon demand information about<br />
Government activities. While a Government must not reveal advice<br />
*. given to it in confidence there is often no good reason ub'y<br />
factual information held by the Government should not be disclosed.<br />
/ We believe </p>
<p>-3-<br />
We believe that there should be a positive requirement, backed<br />
by the force of law, that such information be made available<br />
when it is sought, subject only to limitations which are clearly,<br />
necessary in the national interest. We intend to bring forward<br />
legislation on freedom of information which will incorporate<br />
this principle. Moreover, we will introduce comprehensive<br />
archives legislation which will set out in clear terms the<br />
rights of bona fide researchers to obtain access to records<br />
held by the Government.<br />
Finally, we have introduced a number of measures to enable<br />
individual citizens to obtain prompt and fair readiness of<br />
genuine grievances. We have brought into operation an administrative<br />
appeals Tribunal. It is empowered to review a wide variety<br />
of Government administrative decisions which affect individuals.<br />
The Tribunal reviews the whole case on its merits and may<br />
substitute its decisions for that of the official who made<br />
the original decision. To complement this initiative, we<br />
propose to introduce a new simplified system to make it easier<br />
for citizens to test the legality of administrative action by<br />
Government officials.<br />
A citizen may have a decision reviewed by the new Federal Court<br />
if he feels the decision is not simply misguided by illegal and<br />
beyond the powers of the official concerned. In addition, the<br />
newly appointed Ombudsman, Professor Richardson of the ANU, will<br />
be able to assist directly citizens with a justified grievance<br />
against some Government action. The Ombudsman will commence<br />
operations about the end of June this year.<br />
To review the adequacy of all these procedures, the Government has<br />
established an Administrative Review Council. One of its first<br />
tasks will be to recommend standard procedures to be adopted by<br />
all Commonwealth Administrative Tribunals. We are also taking,<br />
steps to implement the international covenant on Civil and Politica.<br />
Rights. To this end, we intend to establish a Human Rights<br />
Commission.<br />
This concerted programme of reform and enhancement of our democrati.:<br />
system provides the context for the referendumsa on 21 May. You,<br />
in the ACT, will be able to vote on only one question your<br />
choice of a National Song for Australia. But voters in the six<br />
states will be asked to vote on four proposed changes to the<br />
Constitution. These four proposal-are considered and necessary<br />
reforms which will improve our Constitution. I am well aware that<br />
the success rate of referendums in the past has been low, an-. often<br />
for good reason. For so many of the referendums in the past have<br />
been nothing more than a grab for power by the Commonwealth.<br />
These re ' ferendums are different. They protect the rights of the<br />
states. They maintain the power of the Senate. They do not<br />
extend~ the power of the C'ommonwealth, and they do not seek more<br />
power for politicians. All the changes are fair and sensible<br />
reforms which will improve our Constitution. / The fot= </p>
<p>':-Tfhoeur changes are these. First, that Senate and House of<br />
SRepresentatives elections always be held at. the same time. It is<br />
' simply common sense that the elections be held together, and that<br />
S i: the only time you have to vote in a Federal Election is when you<br />
have to choose Australia's Government. This proposal will maintain<br />
and strengthen the power of the Senate. . It also means we will not<br />
have to vote in-as many Federal Elections.<br />
" It is sometimes said that elections can be brought together by the<br />
Representatives election being brought forward to match the Senate.<br />
That is not practical. Even after the last Double Dissolution, when<br />
the elections were held together, the two Houses are now out of<br />
phase. That is because the Senate's term is fixed by the<br />
Constitution and is back-dated to'the previous July 1. The term of<br />
Members of the House of Representatives dates from the time of swearir<br />
in, usually a few weeks after the election. Thus, if the elections a:<br />
to be together, under present provisions there would be the continual<br />
risk of having to cut short the term of the House of Representatives<br />
already a relatively short term of only three years.. This will not<br />
help good government.<br />
The second referendum proposal is that, whenever a Senator dies or<br />
resigns, he will be replaced for the remainder of his term of<br />
office by a member of the same party.. This will guarantee that<br />
your choice of parties for the Senate cannot be altered, by<br />
accident, or by design. It is fundamental to our democracy that<br />
only the people should determine the balance of the parties in the<br />
SSenate. The third proposal to which I have already referred is to give<br />
voters in the ACT and the Northern Territory the basic right to<br />
vote at referendums. This is precisely the right all other<br />
Australians have now. It is a right which residents of Canberra<br />
used to hold and which was taken away when the ACT was created.<br />
Our democracy is the weaker until this basic right to vote is<br />
restored to citizens in the ACT and Northern Territory.<br />
The last proposal is to set a retiring age for Federal Judges.<br />
High Court Judges would retire at 70, and the retirement age for<br />
other Federal Court Judges would be determined by Parliament. Most<br />
jobs have retirement ages, and for good reason. Judges are as<br />
affected by old age as the rest of us. Federal Judges will still<br />
be completely independent. All State Judges are subject to retiring<br />
ages. No one has ever suggested they are not independent.,<br />
So those are the four changes on which Australians will vote on<br />
21 May. Although Liberals in the ACT are precluded from voting<br />
on them I am delighted that a number of Liberals from Canberra<br />
have been actively campaigning in the States for a Yes vote.<br />
The proposed changes are simple and straightforward. They are fair<br />
and sensible. It is for this reason that I am confident that these<br />
referendums will succeed.<br />
Madam Chairman, thank you for your invitation to me to address the<br />
ACT Division of the Liberal Party tonight. I wish your Division ever<br />
success in the Legislative Assembly elections to be held later this<br />
year. The increasing role which citizens here are being asked to<br />
Splay in the Government of the ACT provides a great challenge to the<br />
S Liberal Party, and I am confident that you will accept that challenge<br />
and take a leading role in this transition to greater authority andc<br />
r. e sponsibility.. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
