<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10650</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                  THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                  RADIO INTERVIEW                MIKE GIBSON - 2GB</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/05/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............................................</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>John Howard, good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Mike, how are you?</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Pretty good thank you. You must have a smile on your face this</p>
<p>   morning?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think all Australians ought to have a smile on their face</p>
<p>   this morning because we are back in the black. We've turned</p>
<p>   around a $10.5 billion annual deficit we inherited two years ago</p>
<p>   into a surplus of $2.7 billion. That surplus won't sit there</p>
<p>   moulding away. We are going to use it to repay the debts that were</p>
<p>   accumulated in earlier years. But it really does lock in the economic</p>
<p>   advances of the last couple of years, the low interest rates. I</p>
<p>   mean, home buyers are getting a better deal now then they've</p>
<p>   had for 30 years, the equivalent for an average home buyer of about</p>
<p>   $3800 a year saving of his or her loan. We've got very low</p>
<p>   inflation. We've weathered the worst of the Asian economic</p>
<p>   downturn. It's affected us a bit, but just imagine where we</p>
<p>   would be if we hadn't have taken the measures we have over</p>
<p>   the last couple of years. And it does step the country up for a</p>
<p>   relatively debt free third millennium and that is wonderfully confident,</p>
<p>   reassuring message to be able to give to the people of Australia</p>
<p>   that we're laying the foundations of sustained prosperity in</p>
<p>   the next millennium because we're clearing the debts of the</p>
<p>   past. We're paying off the bankcard, we're getting the</p>
<p>   show back on the road in a way that householders understand and</p>
<p>   people running family businesses understand. If you're a Government</p>
<p>   you can't live beyond your means forever without paying the</p>
<p>   piper and in the end the same thing applies with an individual and</p>
<p>   I think people understand that.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Inevitably, your critics this morning say this is a boring budget.</p>
<p>   You haven't taken much from us but haven't given us a</p>
<p>   great deal either. None of those public servants you sacked are</p>
<p>   going to get their jobs back, 9000 more, in fact, are going to go.</p>
<p>   Unemployment is unlikely to decrease. We still have a current account</p>
<p>   deficit of $31 billion. Hospitals, childcare, education, continue</p>
<p>   to suffer and your still hellbent on selling something that belongs</p>
<p>   to us, Prime Minister - Telstra.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we're going to sell it into the direct personal ownership</p>
<p>   of the men and women of Australia. I mean do you think if you owned</p>
<p>   shares in something, don't you agree that your sense of personal</p>
<p>   ownership is greater than if the Government owns it? I mean I certainly</p>
<p>   feel that if I've got shares in something, and incidentally</p>
<p>   I don't have any shares, but if I did have shares, I would</p>
<p>   think I would have a greater sense of personal involvement in and</p>
<p>   ownership of something if I had shares in it....</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>But not all of us are going to own shares in Telstra.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I mean we have now got, as a result of the sale of one third of</p>
<p>   Telstra, we saw 600,000 men and women, 600,000 Australians buying</p>
<p>   shares for the first time in their lives. First time in their lives.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Well those of us who won't be buying shares are concerned</p>
<p>   as you know, particularly on the issue of timed calls.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we don't have to worry about those, that will be guaranteed</p>
<p>   by legislation.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>For how long?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well for as long as we're in office. I mean I can't answer</p>
<p>   for any future government but I can answer for the Government I</p>
<p>   lead and the Government I lead will guarantee that by legislation.</p>
<p>   Now what happens after that is beyond my control so that's</p>
<p>   another reason not to get rid of us of course. But what we do is</p>
<p>   what I've said and so you don't have to worry about timed</p>
<p>   calls. But just getting back to the Budget, the sense of relief</p>
<p>   I believe people will feel that finally this mountain of debt has</p>
<p>   been scaled and we're able to sort of look beyond it into the</p>
<p>   future with, with a feeling that the past is not going to keep catching</p>
<p>   up with us and slowing us down. I think that is a very important</p>
<p>   psychological factor. It allows people to focus more on the national</p>
<p>   future rather than be shackled by the past.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Talking about the past catching up with you Prime Minister. The</p>
<p>   greatest beneficiaries last night were the aged. Clearly, the policies</p>
<p>   of your recent past, you threatened them earlier this year.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We didn't threaten them.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Well, I think the reaction of older listeners to this programme,</p>
<p>   and older Australians right across the nation, they felt under threat.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I think some of them got scared unnecessarily but that's behind</p>
<p>   us. That's been fixed. The accommodation bond was scrapped,</p>
<p>   nobody's home is at risk and we've moved onto something</p>
<p>   new. And that new thing will have....we have the package to help</p>
<p>   people stay in their own homes, which I released a few weeks ago,</p>
<p>   and that was very, very well received. And last night I announced</p>
<p>   the extension of the seniors card. That is a card that gives people</p>
<p>   access to the pharmaceuticals at the concessional rate that pensioners</p>
<p>   can have it at, that's $3.20. But the contributions of a maximum</p>
<p>   $3.20. That will now be available to self-funded retirees up to</p>
<p>   an aggregate income of a couple of $67,000 a year. It's a very</p>
<p>   generous extension and about a quarter of a million self-funded</p>
<p>   retirees will benefit. Now these are people who have been careful</p>
<p>   and thrifty and have saved all their lives and are not a burden</p>
<p>   on the taxpayer because they look after themselves. In the main,</p>
<p>   they haven't got any real benefits in the fall in interest</p>
<p>   rates because they tend to be lenders rather than borrowers and</p>
<p>   I think it's a fair thing to say to them, you've made</p>
<p>   a huge contribution because of your thrift and the community is</p>
<p>   going to give you a little bit in return by extending this concession</p>
<p>   to you.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Are you confident that last night you bought back the trust of</p>
<p>   Australia's older voter?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We did this because it was the right thing to do. It wasn't</p>
<p>   a question of buying back anything or buying anything at all. It</p>
<p>   was a question of doing the right thing by and important section</p>
<p>   of the Australian community. I think it's only fair that you</p>
<p>   reward thrift. You reward a group of people who have taken a burden</p>
<p>   off society by being careful and prudent during their lives and</p>
<p>   have belonged to a generation who have believed in saving and thrift</p>
<p>   and care and prudence. And I think they ought to be saluted and</p>
<p>   rewarded and not ignored. </p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>At 9:13am my guest is the Prime Minister, John Howard. That yawning</p>
<p>   current account deficit, which means that imports can only cost</p>
<p>   us more, when do you expect that to start to decrease?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, Mike it's a function largely of what is happening in</p>
<p>   Asia, not totally but largely a function of our exports being affected.</p>
<p>   And one of the differences between it and other occasions when the</p>
<p>   current account deficit has got much higher, is that we now have</p>
<p>   a budget surplus and not a budget deficit. We have very low inflation</p>
<p>   and all the other economic fundamentals are very strong and that</p>
<p>   means that we can handle it with relative ease compared with the</p>
<p>   difficulties that we faced on earlier occasions. </p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Now, after last night's easy Budget that took us down the</p>
<p>   yellow brick road, according to the Daily Telegraph, after last</p>
<p>   night's easy Budget, when are you going to announce your plans</p>
<p>   for tax reform?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that'll be some time over the next little while. I can't</p>
<p>   tell you exactly when. We are obviously going to release it before</p>
<p>   the election and in time for people to have a good look at it before</p>
<p>   the election. Peter Costello and I have done a lot of work, the</p>
<p>   broad architecture has been settled but there is still a lot of</p>
<p>   work to be done on it. Now that the Budget is out of the way, and</p>
<p>   after allowing a week or so for the follow-up meetings and speeches</p>
<p>   and interviews that are involved in selling a Budget, we'll</p>
<p>   then get back to the tax package and I hope we'll be in a position</p>
<p>   to release it not too far down the track but I don't want to</p>
<p>   start raising speculation about a particular period of time. It's</p>
<p>   a very big reform. It will involve reductions in personal income</p>
<p>   tax and it's very important that we get it right. And get the</p>
<p>   mix right, and the mix of economic and other considerations right.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>As Prime Minister, our former Treasurer, you are a bloke who's</p>
<p>   been seeking taxation reform for many years. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>It's one of my great goals. </p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>That's right.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There is no doubt about that Mike. There are two things over the</p>
<p>   last 10 or 15 years that I have really wanted to achieve so far</p>
<p>   as reform is concerned. I have wanted to reform the tax system and</p>
<p>   I've wanted to reform the industrial relations system. Now</p>
<p>   we've achieved an enormous amount in reforming the industrial</p>
<p>   relations system, and can I make the point, we are not going to</p>
<p>   be blown off course on waterfront reform. It is difficult, we always</p>
<p>   knew it would be difficult. We always knew people would try and</p>
<p>   obstruct us. But our aim is to get a more efficient waterfront and</p>
<p>   to get rid of compulsory unionism. Our aim is not to destroy the</p>
<p>   Maritime Union or to hurt anybody in that union. Our aim has always</p>
<p>   been to get a more efficient waterfront, and we are going to stick</p>
<p>   at that.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>We've seen you in relation to your waterfront reforms and</p>
<p>   the way you've gone about it. Taxation reform, as you say,</p>
<p>   it's been on your mind for years and years. What sort of taxation</p>
<p>   reform would you like to see.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I want one that, first of all, is fairer. And I want one that</p>
<p>   will not involve any increase in the overall tax burden. I want</p>
<p>   one that involves reductions in personal income tax. I want one</p>
<p>   that is an improvement on the existing wholesale tax system where</p>
<p>   some things are completely untaxed and other things are taxed at</p>
<p>   32 per cent and you get a very uneven and a very indiscriminate</p>
<p>   effect. And obviously you have to look at a broad based, indirect</p>
<p>   tax as one of the elements. I have to say to you that the present</p>
<p>   system is seen increasingly by the community as being unfair and</p>
<p>   it is seen as not very friendly towards families. I'd like</p>
<p>   to see the tax system be more sympathetic to the cost of bringing</p>
<p>   up children, because there is no doubt in the world that when people</p>
<p>   have children, their expenses go up and their income earning capacity</p>
<p>   goes down.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>All right, you'll be cheered because you want us to pay less</p>
<p>   income tax. As you've been thinking about this for so many,</p>
<p>   many years, what sort of figure, what sort of rate of GST would</p>
<p>   you like to see instituted?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Mike, I can't.....</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>I was going to say if you were the Prime Minister, but you are</p>
<p>   the Prime Minister.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Mike, can you hear me, I seem to have lost you. But I am not in</p>
<p>   a position, of course, to get into the specifics of particular tax</p>
<p>   rates, but all I can assure you is that when the package comes out</p>
<p>   the Australian community will see in this Government, a Government</p>
<p>   that's been prepared to tackle reform in one of those areas</p>
<p>   that people have wanted reform in for years, and I am a great believer</p>
<p>   that you are elected to high office in this country to do things,</p>
<p>   not to sit there and enjoy the prestige of the office. You are elected</p>
<p>   to tackle the hard problems, and we've tried to do that. We've</p>
<p>   tackled the Budget, we've tackled industrial relations reform,</p>
<p>   we've tackled welfare cheating, we've introduced the principle</p>
<p>   of mutual obligation with work for the dole. We are now going to</p>
<p>   tackle taxation reform. Now this is a reformist Government that</p>
<p>   believes in using the privilege of office to try and tackle the</p>
<p>   difficult problems.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Kim Beazley this morning says that you are lucky. You are lucky</p>
<p>   to get the surplus that you got.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I could be so lucky. Mr Beazley says I'm lucky? I mean thanks</p>
<p>   Kim, you left me a deficit of $10.5 billion. I'd hate to think</p>
<p>   how that deficit would be if I was unlucky. You make your own luck</p>
<p>   in politics. We've had an Asian economic downturn. If we hadn't</p>
<p>   of had an Asian economic downturn, the rate of growth would have</p>
<p>   been higher. If we hadn't of been left with a Budget deficit</p>
<p>   of $10.5 billion a year, budget making over the last couple of years</p>
<p>   would have been easier and we wouldn't have had to take difficult</p>
<p>   decisions. The Labor Party had 13 years to fix the waterfront and</p>
<p>   didn't. It had 13 years to fix the tax system and didn't.</p>
<p>   It had 13 years to fix all the other things that it now claims to</p>
<p>   have the magical solutions to. You make your own luck in politics.</p>
<p>   I think this has been a good Government. I don't accept that</p>
<p>   it's been a lucky Government.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>All right, a man who perhaps didn't make his own luck, John</p>
<p>   Hewson, 1993, a GST. When it comes time for you to announce your</p>
<p>   package, will there be any question that any Australian might ask</p>
<p>   you that you won't be able to answer?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I hope not. But I always have great admiration for the perspicacity</p>
<p>   of my fellow Australians. And I don't have any inflated idea</p>
<p>   of my own ability. I do my honest best to answer questions that</p>
<p>   are put to me, my honest best, but nobody can run around the country</p>
<p>   saying he's got the answer to everything.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Your honest best. When are you likely to call an election?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't know yet Mike. I just don't know. The options</p>
<p>   are pretty well on the table. If it's to be a double it's</p>
<p>   got to be called, the Parliament has got to be dissolved before</p>
<p>   the 29th of October. If it's not to be a double, well we can</p>
<p>   have the election after Christmas. I just don't know yet. There</p>
<p>   is nothing I can do about the election speculation because I keep</p>
<p>   getting asked the question because I have honestly not decided when.</p>
<p>   And I won't be making up my mind for some time yet. </p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>When you do call an election, where do you see yourself directing</p>
<p>   your preferences in regard to Pauline Hanson?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that's something where there are a whole range of views</p>
<p>   across the country. Some divisions of the Liberal Party want her</p>
<p>   put last, others have different views, and we will be discussing</p>
<p>   that at an organisational level when we get a bit closer to the</p>
<p>   election. In Victoria there is a view that uniformly it ought to</p>
<p>   be last. In Queensland, there is a different view. In New South</p>
<p>   Wales, there is a different view again and it is something that</p>
<p>   I have to manage as Party Leader and I have to pay regard to views</p>
<p>   in the party all around the nation. And, of course, I will be contributing</p>
<p>   my own view when those discussions take place. I'm going to</p>
<p>   make the point Mike, that Liberal Party preferences, of course,</p>
<p>   don't get distributed. The only preferences that really count</p>
<p>   in elections are the preferences of minor parties. It's really</p>
<p>   where the preferences of minor parties voters go that are important.</p>
<p>   And I will certainly be saying to people who are former Coalition</p>
<p>   voters who might be tempted to vote for Pauline Hanson, don't</p>
<p>   waste your time because we can address the legitimate concerns you</p>
<p>   have without some of the baggage that goes with voting for her.</p>
<p>   The stupid anti-Asian remarks that she's made and the very</p>
<p>   insensitive remarks she's made about Aborigines. I mean, all</p>
<p>   the people who are a bit attracted to her because they think she's</p>
<p>   got simple answers to life's difficult problems. Nobody has</p>
<p>   got simple answers to difficult problems and nobody has a magic</p>
<p>   wand. And I don't think we really want anybody in this country</p>
<p>   making remarks that are in any way related to the racial background</p>
<p>   of people. So I say to people who are attracted to her, you can</p>
<p>   have your concerns about economic security and employment prospects</p>
<p>   and ensuring that Governments govern for the mainstream you can</p>
<p>   have those concerns met by the Coalition but without having the</p>
<p>   baggage of supporting her.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>You said you'll make your thoughts quite clear as far as preferences</p>
<p>   are concerned, obviously before the next Federal election. What</p>
<p>   were your thoughts when you heard that the Libs in Queensland had</p>
<p>   directed her preferences to go before the Labor Party?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I'm not sure that they have. My latest mail on that and,</p>
<p>   incidentally, I was not consulted about that because it is purely</p>
<p>   a State election.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>What would you have said if you were consulted?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well that would be a matter between myself and the Queensland division,</p>
<p>   and my position, my understanding at the moment is that they are</p>
<p>   going to look at it on a seat by seat basis and in some seats they'll</p>
<p>   put Labor last. In other seats they'll put her candidate last.</p>
<p>   But I repeat, Liberal preferences don't matter. They don't</p>
<p>   get distributed. The only preferences that matter are the preferences</p>
<p>   of minor parties and I mean it's a completely costless political</p>
<p>   exercise as far as the Labor Party is concerned in saying we'll</p>
<p>   put her last because they don't hold many marginal seats any</p>
<p>   more and they're in an entirely different situation.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Closing on the subject of Mrs Hanson, and I'm sure you'll</p>
<p>   be delighted that we do. Is there one quality about Mrs Hanson that</p>
<p>   you admire?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>That was quick. Your last word on the Budget because I know it's</p>
<p>   something that you want to sell this morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I think it is a Budget that has set up Australia's future.</p>
<p>   It's given the Australian community a huge sense of relief</p>
<p>   that the monkey of debt has been got off their backs and it makes</p>
<p>   people feel a lot freer and a lot more open and a lot more hopeful</p>
<p>   about the future and that's very important.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>So what do you do for the rest of the week besides selling your</p>
<p>   Budget......</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Not much at all.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>Is there a celebratory lunch today Prime Minister?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, no celebrations. You never stop in this business particularly</p>
<p>   in the wake of budgets.</p>
<p>GIBSON:</p>
<p>I thank you for your time this morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thanks Mike.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
