<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3541</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S OVERSEAS VISIT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003541.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
4j)' A ) IHALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 410<br />
December 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S OVERSEAS VISIT<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam, said today that<br />
he had no intention of postponing again his visit to<br />
Europe, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Pakistan.<br />
The Prime Minister said that while Australia faces<br />
a number of difficulties related to the economy, it would<br />
be irresponsible to give the impression overseas and<br />
indeed in Australia that the country was in such a<br />
parlous state that the Prime Minister was unable to leave<br />
it during the summer recess. Moreover, to cancel or<br />
postpono again the visit at this stage would be a discourtesy<br />
to Heads of Government of the host countries who appreciated<br />
the necessity for deferring the visit in July, immediately<br />
after the elections.<br />
The Prime Minister said that there were many important<br />
reasons why the visit should proceed at this time. In<br />
addition to other matters which would be discussed he saw<br />
considerable value in discussions on common economic problems<br />
faced, not only by Australia, but by the developed countries<br />
of Western Europe.<br />
The Prime Minister said that at a time of crisis<br />
in the world economy there was an urgent and continuing need<br />
for leaders of Western countries to concert their economic<br />
policies in the interests of stability and welfare.<br />
One of the great dangers of the present situation<br />
was that countries might feel themselves compelled to<br />
embark on beggar-my-neighbour policies which could only lead<br />
to economic disaster.<br />
Policies of restricti * on policies that curtail<br />
employment, production and welfare could be fatal to the<br />
framework of the world economy as we knew it and could<br />
threaten everywhere those liberal and democratic forms<br />
that were so vital a part of our political heritage. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
The Prime Minister said that discussion of these<br />
grave economic problems with European leaders at this<br />
time was not a luxury but a responsibility which any<br />
Australian Prime Minister should assume.<br />
For this reason, too, he would be accompanied on<br />
the visit not only by senior Foreign Affairs officials<br />
and the Secretary of the Department of Overseas Trade,<br />
but also by the Secretary of the Department of Minerals and<br />
Energy and by a senior Treasury official so that<br />
important matters affecting energy and the economy might<br />
be fully discussed.<br />
CANBERRA, A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
