<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8367</transcript-id>
    <title>THE HON P.J. KEATING, PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE 19 DECEMBER 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/12/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008367.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
THE HON PJ. KEATING, PRESS CONFERENCE, PARLIAMENT HOUSE<br />
19 DECEMBER 1991<br />
E OE PROOF ONLY<br />
PK: Could I begin by saying that I'm very greatly honoured and more than a little nervous<br />
at the great responsibility the Labor Party has entrusted to me tonight. -Thie first thing<br />
I'd like to do is pay tribute to my predecessor, Bob Hawke, who has been a great<br />
leader of the Labor Party, who has won an unequalled, unparalleled, four consecutive<br />
election victories an electoral record I will never match, and few of us could ever<br />
hope to match; and who, in partnership with me and our party, has changed the way<br />
in which Australia is and the way in which it works. I speak on behalf of the whole<br />
of the Parliamentary Labor Party today, in thanking Bob for his leadership for the way<br />
in which he conducted himself today, with the dignity and the pluck in the House and<br />
at his press conference; and having lead Labor to victory, he's lost a ballot in the<br />
manner of his choosing in the Caucus of the Parliamentary Labor Party and he's<br />
shown great credit, I believe, to himself in the way in which he's conducted himself<br />
as Prime Minister and to the Labor Party as a Government. Could I, in my first<br />
words as Prime Minister elect, Leader of the Labor Party elect, to you, the Australian<br />
people, say that I want to make three commitments to them. The first is I pledge to<br />
give everything I've got to the job and the country. The second is to deal honestly<br />
with the people, to tell them the truth. In tough times, of course, the temptation is<br />
always to gild the lily. I'll be resisting that temptation as much as is humanly<br />
possible. I'll speak honestly with them, to them, and realistically, and I'll listen<br />
accordingly. The third commitment is I pledge to fight the battle against<br />
unemployment and for economic recovery with all of the energy I can muster. I<br />
promise never to turn a blind eye to the suffering that some are enduring and never<br />
to agree that it is acceptable for some Australians to be written off or sacrificed in the<br />
so-called national interest. I want each Australian to have the opportunity to pursue<br />
with dignity and hope a fair share of our national prosperity. So there are the three<br />
commitments I give. In the next few weeks, I've got these important tasks. To<br />
restore unity and harmony to the Government, because it would be futile to deny that<br />
the recent past has been a somewhat traumatic experience for all of us. It's imperative<br />
that we're now all pulling in the same direction, and for my part of course, need I say<br />
there'll be no recriminations whatsoever, no raking over old ground, but only a<br />
commitment to get on with the task of governing this country. Over the holiday<br />
period, I will spend time talking to my colleagues and working on proposals I want<br />
to put before the Cabinet in the early new year. I would like to start 1992 with a<br />
cohesive and comprehensive plan to push Australia ahead. I've got a good idea<br />
already of what should be in that plan, what should be done, but I want to tie it all<br />
together and make sure we have it right. With that and above all that, the thing that<br />
the Government, I and the Government, must do in the immediate period ahead is get<br />
confidence in Australia going again, to get the country moving, to try and engender<br />
confidence in the community, confidence in the business community, and get the<br />
country cracking. While the economy is now much too weak and unemployment </p>
<p>2<br />
much too high, I believe we can emerge from this recession a much stronger economy<br />
than ever before. This period gives us great opportunities and the 90s hold for<br />
Australia very great promise, very great promise indeed. So, could I conclude on this<br />
point, by saying that I will need the help of the Australian people, their understanding<br />
and their patience as indeed I will need it from you. In time, I hope, that I can earn<br />
their trust and their patience and their support both as leader of the Party and for and<br />
on behalf of the Party and the Government. Thank you.<br />
J: Mr Keating, do you expect a Cabinet re-shuffle?<br />
PK: I do not believe that there should be any spill of positions in the L-abor Party. I think<br />
it's very important for harmony that that not be so, and I'd like some time to think<br />
about portfolio responsibilities, the Ministerial arrangements, that should obtain and<br />
naturally, the people who should fill them.<br />
J: What about Ralph Willis, the Treasurer?<br />
PK: Well, that goes for everybody.<br />
J: How can you respond to speculation that people now seek a mandate from the<br />
Australian people and take Australia to an early election?<br />
PK: I've never heard that speculation. I've got to give you marks for trying there, though.<br />
J: Mr Keating, unemployment figures, what are you going to do to get their<br />
confidence?<br />
PK: Well, along with Bob and the Government, I spent seven and a half of my eight and<br />
a half years trying to engender employment growth into this economy. We inherited<br />
10.5 percent unemployment in 1983 and we brought it down sharply through the<br />
eighties, and it's a matter of profound regret to me that that employment was<br />
overtaken by a rise in unemployment, and the result is that there's been a substantial<br />
level of misery in the community as a result. I want to go back to doing what we do<br />
best, that is creating jobs and making the Australian economy grow but doing it in<br />
a way which preserves the great gains on inflation, doing it in a way which<br />
advantages all Australians.<br />
J: Mr Hawke spoke a few minutes ago on the need for new directions in economi<br />
policy. Do you think that's right?<br />
PK: I think governments have a substantial pride in the authorship of their policies, and<br />
we're entitled to be proud of the great change of Australia to an international country,<br />
and all of the things which are part and parcel of it. I suppose it is probably a human<br />
failing if nothing else that governments then spend time defending their structure,<br />
defending their policy, and not be as alert to the shifts which they ought to be making.<br />
I think policy dexterity and keeping alert to those shifts is going to be important. I<br />
agree with Bob about that. But again, we're not talking about putting policy on its<br />
head. We're not talking about taking Australia back to the closed days of the </p>
<p>and 70' s. We're talking about policy which is going to make Australia fairer,<br />
better, with more growth and more employment, but at the same time keeping that<br />
great historic change into an international society.<br />
J: Are you worried about blowing out the deficit and boosting interest rates? Are you<br />
talking about massive jobs requiring a lot of money?<br />
PK: Part of the framework of my views were sketched out in a speech I made at the<br />
Collingwood Football Club a month or two ago, and I have got a framework in my<br />
mind, but I'd like to put that to the Cabinet and the Caucus. I think that's the right<br />
place to put it. So, rather than get into any detail, that's what I'd prefer to do.<br />
J: Mr Keating, what about the recession Australia had to have?<br />
PK: It's one of the statements I made as Treasurer I regret, because it did not reflect the<br />
Government's policy, and it was a statement which seemed too uncaring at the time.<br />
The Government was never after a recession. Policy was only about a slowdown.<br />
You remember at the time, we were spending twice what we were producing. The<br />
economy had to be slowed and I had the job as Treasurer, of inducing that slowdown.<br />
We never wanted a recession. It's a pity that the recession we now have is deeper<br />
than any of us would have wanted it to be, or needed it to be. So, it was a shorthand<br />
way, on my part, of trying to describe the slowdown, but I think an inadequate one.<br />
You can never consign Australians to the misery of unemployment, believing there's<br />
a higher purpose to it. There can be no higher purpose, and therefore it's important<br />
to get the economy growing again so that what we thought policy was about back then<br />
in 1988, which was a slowdown and became a recession, quickly becomes, as quickly<br />
as we can make it happen, a recovery.<br />
J: Mr Keating, you spoke of feeling humble today. Have you learnt a new humility on<br />
the backbench?<br />
PK: I must say I think that public life is a humbling experience for anybody who has had<br />
major responsibilities, it's a humbling experience. Can I say that I said in the Caucus<br />
tonight, I enjoyed immensely the six months on the backbench. I found the<br />
camaraderie, the wit, the open-mindedness, the fun of many of the people there to give<br />
me a great charge. It's one of the nicest things that's happened to me in public life,<br />
is having that time there. I think that as a result, I will be determined, as a leader of<br />
the Party, to be more in touch with the Caucus than I ever was. We all commit the<br />
sin of moving into the Cabinet processes, not consulting the Caucus enough, and<br />
invariably we miss a step somewhere. So, it only reinforces me in my view that that<br />
experience, which I had a very pleasant one, means that the Government must be<br />
closer to the Caucus. Cabinet must be closer to the Caucus.<br />
J: Did you have time to look at the GST package while you were on the backbench?<br />
PK: I've had a look at it.<br />
J: What do you think of it? </p>
<p>4<br />
PK: Dr Hewson has proposed what he believes is a plan for Australia. But it's the wrong<br />
plan. It's the wrong plan. It's a plan which is about making a tenth-order issue,<br />
about whether you tax income or expenditure, as a first-order issue, when we know,<br />
all of us, that the first-order issues are employment, growth, investment, maintenance<br />
of low-levels of inflation, further production, change in the workplace, enterprise<br />
bargaining, national economic efficiency. T'hey are the furst-order issues. Whether<br />
you tax income or expenditure is a tenth-order issue. What Dr Hewson has done is<br />
said ' look, I'll take a tenth-order issue and I'll bring it up here and try and solve it as<br />
a first-order issue'. Well, franikly, basically, his proposition amounts to no more than<br />
a shift of income to the wealthy at the expense of the low-paid.<br />
J: A vote of 56/ 51. Is that a strong enough base on which to rebuild harmony in the<br />
Labor Party?<br />
PK: I think so. I took considerable heart from both what Bob said and the tone of what<br />
he said, and also what colleagues in the Caucus said to me, who voted for Bob. I<br />
think so. From my part, the Caucus will not find me lacking in any goodwill towards<br />
them. My Cabinet colleagues won't. I think we have the prospect of being a unified<br />
force. I said in the Caucus that we can only succeed on a basis of friendship. And<br />
basically without that friendship, we just won't get the cohesion, I think, we need to<br />
come from a very long way back in the electoral stakes.<br />
J: Mr Keating, why do you feel better equipped to lead Labor to the election in 1993<br />
than Mr Hawke?<br />
PK: Well I think, look it is the issue of generational change. I think I could say Bob and<br />
I conducted a government which contained two leaders. And we worked as a good<br />
team for a very long period of time. Probably a record period in Australian politics<br />
for two people to work as closely and as effectively as we did. But, time tells. I<br />
think it told on both of us in our work, in our relationship and I think that the need<br />
for policy shifts, that dexterity I mentioned earlier, and generational change is<br />
important. I think it is important for a political party to change itself. Afterall, this<br />
is a very long period. Bob is the second longest serving prime minister by a very<br />
large margin. It is a long time and, therefore, I think that every person who leads a<br />
party comes to it with different views and perspectives and I believe the Australian<br />
people are looking for both hope and direction for the 1990s and this country can be<br />
in a very good position in the 1990s, notwithstanding the fact we've got a recession.<br />
Notwithstanding the fact we've got a recession we can be well set up in the 1990s and<br />
I believe I can play a role in that and that's why I believe that I will serve the Labor<br />
Party well.<br />
J: You've just admitted that the recession was a mistake. How can you inject confidence<br />
in the community that you won't make another mistake as momentous as that?<br />
PK: Well, when I say it was a mistake, it was not.., the policies we adopted were intended<br />
only to slow the economy. It unfortunately became a recession, but there were<br />
substantial contributing factors. Those factors now don't exist and I think that if one<br />
looks at the record of the Government from 1983, we engendered twice as much </p>
<p>growth in the Australian economy in our first seven or eight years as in the previous<br />
seven or eight years. So, while we've certainly had a recession, there is an enormous<br />
shift of employment and wealth there as well. So, certainly, the recession we didn't<br />
need, but what has come in these years of change is enormous strength and change<br />
to this economy. And I think the Labor Party and the Government can be relied upon<br />
to continue that ambition for change.<br />
J: Mr Keating, when can we expect you to throw the switch to vaudeville as you<br />
promised some months ago?<br />
PK: Well, if you'd have been here for many years, as some others were, you'd have<br />
known I've thrown it often, often, and, I hope, well.<br />
J: What will you be telling George Bush about U. S. trade policy? And how's your golf<br />
swing?<br />
PK: Well, my golf swing? That's not good. The last time it swung well was when I was<br />
a teenager. But. I've known George Bush since 1970, and there is a lot in him that,<br />
a lot about him where you see the good, the very good side of Americans. I'm sure<br />
he will forgive me my golf swing. And we can discuss, when he arrives, issues of<br />
moment, and of substance to both countries, and to the world.<br />
ITeh money markets, Mr Keating, are expecting interest rates to come down to about<br />
that's the 90 day rates. Is that part of your economic program ( inaudible) a sharp<br />
cut in interest rates?<br />
PK: No, I don't want to start speaking now about what the Government may consider. But<br />
all options, including monetary options, would be on the table. I'd like to consider<br />
those in the freedom and privacy of the Cabinet room, in the first instance.<br />
J: ( inaudible) any shifts in the emphasis of the Australia/ U. S. relationship?<br />
PK: Well, the Australian/ U. S. relationship, I think, is a longstanding one. It's been<br />
improved, I think, by the Government, by Bob Hawke's Government, by Bob's<br />
relationship with President Reagan and President Bush. And I can only hope that I<br />
can maintain a relationship of the quality. I would certainly make that an ambition<br />
of mine.<br />
J: which suggested that you thought that Mr Hawke had been a little too subservient<br />
to the Americans. Will you be reflecting that in anything you say ( inaudible)?<br />
PK: No, I didn't say that. I said that, I made some reference to telephone calls. I think<br />
that, I don't think American Presidents, not someone of George Bush's experience.<br />
I've met him on about four or five occasions since 1970 in various jobs. I don't think<br />
they expect any nation to do other than consider its own interests. And that's what<br />
we must always, sensibly do. I mean, you've got James Baker, at the moment, talking<br />
to the leaders of the former Soviet states. I mean, I'm sure, the Americans are very<br />
wide-eyed about national interest. </p>
<p>6<br />
J: ( inaudible) next year. And more generally, ( inaudible) relationship with the<br />
Asia/ Pacific region?<br />
PK: Well, I think, Australia is an Asia/ Pacific nation. And, as time goes by, as we are<br />
seeing the central focus of our trade and our foreign policy is going to be more to the<br />
Asia/ Pacific area. This is obvious with the APEC arrangements which Australia has<br />
championed, which have been adopted now by all the Pacific Basin countries, or most<br />
of the Pacific Basin countries. So, therefore, I regard the Asia/ Pacific area as our area<br />
of interest, as our backyard, as the principal focus of economic trade and foreign<br />
policy.<br />
J: will you be going to Jakarta?<br />
PK: Well, I haven't thought about that.<br />
J: Are you concerned about your unpopularity with the Australian public?<br />
PK: Well, its a matter of what popularity is about. I think when we had some, if you like,<br />
dissection of polls, I think there was a great discernment being shown by the public<br />
about what they expect in leaders. They expect leaders to do things, they expect<br />
leaders to lead, to strike out. The essence of leadership is being out there, in front,<br />
and I think that this community has a very realistic view of their situation in the<br />
1990' s, that they hope and expect for a decent life, and physical and economic<br />
security. And they want governments to provide that for them, they don't want* more<br />
than that I don't think. I mean, I think they've got reasonable expectations. And I<br />
think if any leader can provide policies to meet those expectations, he or she will be<br />
approved of. And I hope in providing those I could be approved of too.<br />
J: A year ago you said Australia had never had a great leader, I presume you think that's<br />
about to change. I just wonder what qualities of greatness you might bring to the job?<br />
PK: Well, that's for you to make judgements about over time, isn't it. One would always<br />
hope one could bring any quality of greatness to such a position.<br />
J: ( inaudible) that this leadership challenge has taken place at a time the people think the<br />
Government should have been concentrating on the recession?<br />
PK: Well, I think we were concentrating on the essentials, its a matter of how we<br />
concentrated on them. I wouldn't try and say that there wasn't, that the first challenge<br />
wasn't a distraction for the Party, but a relatively short one, and the Government's<br />
largely gone about its business. And this resolution today is a couple of weeks in the<br />
making, but until then I don't think there has been that great a distraction. I know<br />
that the Party will be glad that the distraction is behind it, whatever distraction there<br />
was is behind it, and I'm glad of that too, as Bob said he was.<br />
J: How great do you think the resentment is in the community?<br />
PK: I can't judge that. You're a better judge of that than I am, I think. </p>
<p>7<br />
J: Would you have mounted a challenge this week if Bob Hawke hadn't made the move<br />
he did today, for the sake of the Party?<br />
PK: Well, Bob made the move, that's the point. Bob declared his position vacant which<br />
was, I think, the right gesture for somebody of his statre, as a Prime Minister of<br />
longstanding, a leader of longstanding, and in the position of that vacancy I<br />
nominated.<br />
J: Mr Keating you didn't attend Question Time today, why was that?<br />
PK: Well, I don't... As Treasurer of course, I always had to attend it as a rule. I've not<br />
been entirely punctual as a backbencher and I was less punctual today.<br />
J: ( inaudible) embarrassing for ( inaudible)<br />
PK: No, but I thought in the circumstances it was best I wasn't there. I think it's probably<br />
right.<br />
J: ( inaudible) given your position in the Parliament, I know what you've just said, and<br />
given Mr Hawke's legendary ability as a campaigner, that Caucus has in fact taken<br />
something of a gamble today in an electoral sense?<br />
PK: I think they've picked up on the view in the community that the community is looking<br />
for change. If a party says we don't think we'll give you any more change, they say,<br />
well thank-you we don't need you anymore. And I think they, but as I said, not the<br />
right kind of change, not the right kind of change. I think he's picked up on sentiment<br />
but not responded to it properly, Dr Hewson, I mean.<br />
J: So what's the right kind of change ( inaudible) You've said that there are some<br />
decisions that you might, sort of treat a bit differently these days, having been out in<br />
the community, you sense a different set of priorities, perhaps. I mean, do you<br />
believe that the basic structural changes that the Government started should continue,<br />
for example. There is a lot of resistance in the Labor movement to those changes<br />
now.<br />
PK: Well, the basic change is one from a closed to an open society. And I don't think<br />
there is any dispute about that within the portals of the Labor Party. And in any<br />
recession there will always be questioning about policy stances, but I don't think<br />
anyone would now believe that our security could be enhanced in the way in which<br />
it has been in a closed place. So, we can always discuss and debate how the opening<br />
of this economy and its continuation goes into the future, its meeting the challenge of<br />
international efficiency, you can always debate those things. But I don't think the<br />
basic thing is being debated.<br />
ITeh pace of change is going to be a very important issue at the next election isn't it?<br />
PK: I've always believed that. I think if you offer the public sensible change, we have in<br />
this country, very fortunately, a very conscientious community. </p>
<p>J: When will the abolition of the Medicare co-payment occur? And have you discussed<br />
it with Mr Howe?<br />
PK: Well, I think most of you know my views about this. We considered it many times<br />
when I was Treasurer, in the Expenditure Review Committee. But I will be speaking<br />
first to the Ministers involved, and putting my views to the Cabinet, as the appropriate<br />
place to consider the matter.<br />
J: Are you happy for Mr Howe to remain as your Deputy?<br />
PK: Delighted. I think we can both help each other make the Party stronger and better.<br />
J: Mr Keating, the changes you are proposed require a mini Budget?<br />
PK: Well, I said, I hope in 1992 to present a plan for the ongoing, a plan for change for<br />
Australia as we go through the 1990' s. That will be obviously something of<br />
substance, and whether you want to give it a mini Budget tag is up to you.<br />
J: Mr Keating, Mr Hawke was planning a Cabinet meeting tomorrow to start producing<br />
a new plan to boost employment. Will you proceed with that?<br />
PK: No, I don't think any of the Cabinet think tomorrow would be an appropriate day to<br />
start.<br />
J: ( inaudible) was a couple of weeks in the making. How much responsibility do you<br />
bear, personally, for the turbulence that has virtually crippled the Government over the<br />
last couple of weeks<br />
PK: Well, until a few minutes ago I haven't made a public comment since the 8th of<br />
November. And I think I can say that if the Government had been able to respond<br />
more fulsomely to the Opposition's consumption tax package then the likelihood of<br />
this matter being debated before Christmas would have been remote. I can say to you<br />
that in the last session of Parliament when it finished, my expectation was we would<br />
go away for Christmas and we would come back here on the 25th of February. And<br />
those events changed though, I think.<br />
J: When do you expect the recession to end?<br />
PK: Well, I'll be taking some advice on that, but I think it will end during 1992. But it's<br />
not very wise of me to try and be precise about the point, or to be clever about it,<br />
because I don't think it's easy to be clever about picking the turning points in any<br />
economy.<br />
J: If the Government's attack on the GST unfulsome, why didn't you help them over the<br />
last few weeks?<br />
PK: Well, it was up, I think, for. It's not really, I think, an acceptable argument for a<br />
backbencher to say that in the initial phases of the presentation of such a package, and </p>
<p>9<br />
the requirement on the Government to respond to it, that I should have been out there,<br />
if you like, putting a view. And also one without the support that comes with<br />
Ministerial office. So, it was properly the job of the Government, of the Prime<br />
Minister and the Treasurer, and I recognised that.<br />
J: Do you believe that ' Fightback' has carried you to into the Prime Ministership?<br />
PK: Its caused a debate in our Party about our direction and our leadership, which may<br />
have led to the events of today. So what, in terms of the package.<br />
J: The Party, under Mr Hawke, came under fairly heavy criticism for pandering to<br />
sectional interests and lobby groups. Do you see any shift in emphasis there?<br />
PK: Well, I think the Hawke Government, one of its hallmarks was a consensus approach<br />
to Australian society. And it's because of that approach we were able to do many<br />
more policy things and changes more rapidly than could ever have been undertaken<br />
by a Government taking a confrontationist approach. In the course of those<br />
discussions people may say we're subject to lobbying. Well, if a Government is<br />
listening, and a Government is responsive, I don't think the public can complain about<br />
it. I think it is a very good sign, and I think it changed the way in which Australian<br />
politics worked.<br />
J: Is there any other decisions such as the Medicare co-payment policy that you would<br />
be looking to review quite soon?<br />
PK: None that comes to mind.<br />
J: Mr Keating, will you be asking Mr Hawke for any advice?<br />
PK: From time to time I may well do. He made me the offer, very kindly, and I'll very<br />
happily take it up.<br />
J: Would you like to see him remain on the backbench?<br />
PK: Well, it's a matter for Bob. He can remain there at his own pleasure.<br />
J: Is he a future Governor-General?<br />
PK: You should have asked him that. That's a question for him. Before I go, again<br />
thank-you. I want to just conclude on this point by thanking the Parliamentary Labor<br />
Party for supporting me today, those who did, and those who didn't. And I also thank<br />
my wife who has supported me through these years, and through these times of<br />
difficulty, and my family. Without that kind of support it is not possible to do a<br />
public job like these, under this sort of pressure. Most particularly, I thank the<br />
Australian people for having the forbearance to see the Labor Party change its<br />
leadership, and I hope the patience to see us change owr policies, as needs be, to take<br />
Australia to a better future in the 1990' s.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
