<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5740</transcript-id>
    <title>HONORARY ORDERS OF AUSTRALIA</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/01/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005740.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STRICTLY UNDER EMBARGO UNTIL<br />
0001 HRS AEDT, TUESDAY,<br />
26 JANUARY, 1982<br />
.~ UST L1.<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 26 JANUARY, 1982<br />
HONORARY ORDERS OF AUSTRALIA<br />
Her Majesty The Queen has approved the Government's<br />
recommendations f * or three honorary appointments to the<br />
Order of Australia.<br />
The awards are of Companion in the General Division of the<br />
order of Australia and mark distinguished service given to<br />
Australia by non-Australians.<br />
This is the second list of honorary awards to be given under<br />
the provisions of the Constitution of the Order of Australia.<br />
The first four honorary appointments were announced on<br />
Australia Day 1980.<br />
The awards of Honorary Companion are to:<br />
Mother Teresa*( Bojaxhiu*), O. B. E.<br />
Missionaries of Charity, Lower Circular Road,<br />
Calcutta 16, India.<br />
His* Excellency Mr. Shridath Surendranath* Ramphal,* Kt', Q. C.<br />
Secretary-General, Commonwealth Secretariat,<br />
Marlborough House, London.<br />
The Rt. Hon+. Brian Edward Talboys, C'. H.<br />
of 1 Hamilton Avenue, Winton, New Zealand. Former<br />
New Zealand % Minister for Foreign Affairs and<br />
Overseas Trade.<br />
Mr. Fraser said the Government when making its recommendations<br />
had had in mind the high standards set by the Council for the<br />
Order of Australia in recommending awards to Australian citizens.<br />
Honorary awards would continue to be limited and recommended on<br />
rare occasions at the Government's discretion.<br />
Details of each of the citations are in the announcement by the<br />
Governor-General of The Queen's approval of the three honorary<br />
appointments. 00 </p>
<p>IL LcUU1L! LLiI1 U<br />
Order of Australia: General Division<br />
Appointments of Honorary Companion<br />
Mother Teresa ( Bojaxhiu), O. B. E.<br />
Missionaries of Charity, 54a Lower Circular Road,<br />
Calcutta 16, India. Nobel Peace Prize Winner, 1979.<br />
Mother Teresa has devoted a significant part of her life<br />
to working for the poor and needy of many countries.<br />
She founded the Missionaries of Charity which operates<br />
more than 200 Missions in various countries. In<br />
Australia, there are Missions of the Order at Bourke,<br />
New South Wales; Katherine, Northern Territory; and<br />
Fitzroy, Victoria. She has visited Australia on many<br />
occasions. During a visit last October, Mother Teresa<br />
had talks on the establishment of a house of the<br />
Missionaries of Charity which opened early this month<br />
in West Avenue, Queanbeyan, New South Wales.<br />
His Excellency Mr. Shridath Surendranath Ramphal, Kt, C. M. G. Q. C.<br />
Secretary-General, Commonwealth Secretariat, Marlborough<br />
House, London. Mr. Ramphal has served the Commonwealth<br />
Secretariat with distinction since 1975. He has shown an<br />
eminent understanding of affairs concerning the nations of<br />
the Commonwealth and the international community in general.<br />
This has contributed to a wide appreciation of Australia's<br />
role in the Commonwealth. He played a leading role in the<br />
first Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting held in<br />
Melbourne recently.<br />
The Rt. Honourable Brian Edward Talboys, C. H.<br />
Former New Zealand Minister for Foreign Affairs and Overseas<br />
Trade, of 1 Hamilton Avenue, Winton, New Zealand. Mr. Talboys<br />
has made an outstanding contribution over many years to<br />
relations between Australia and New Zealand and to the ANZUS<br />
Alliance. In official negotiations on various matters he has<br />
shown a particular understanding of the importance of each<br />
country to the other. This understanding has contributed<br />
in a most sighiificant way to the cementing of our bilateral<br />
relationship and is symbolised by his co-signature of<br />
the Nareen Declaration in 1978. 000--_ I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
