<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>551</transcript-id>
    <title>YOUNG LIBERALS RALLY, HAWTHORN TOWN HALL, MELBOURNE ON YTH JULY 1962 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R G MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/07/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000551_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
YOUJNG LIBERALS3 L'LY , IA-THOT11 TONHALL,<br />
Sp~~ P~ in~ iLee, e.~ c h~ by~ e Hon. R. G-Menzies<br />
Mr, Chairman., Mr,, Seanl.-;% n and I. adies and Clentlemen<br />
This is a v, rv interestin--evening for me, beas<br />
1 began my political, my parliamentary ife, 7 if you may so<br />
describe it, in this hal. it wasn~ t as gr.-and in those days,<br />
but Hawthorn was the centre of the old seat of East Yarra,<br />
which I b elieve still continues, and which I had the honour<br />
of representing in Parli~ ament ini the Upper House many, many<br />
years ago, Mr. S2canil'!-n has also recalled to mly mind that sQm3<br />
trifle of 33 or 34j years ago we established a rathier radical<br />
moverment called -the Young Fationalists, * r^ d lik-. e -to tell you<br />
that all this ha ' ppened in tbi. study of my lhouse in Kew, where<br />
1Billy Kent Hughes and Mr,, Grceenwood who was tiaen Member for<br />
Nunawading, and I sat down and we agreed about one thing,<br />
unanimously, the sort of thing that you have in mind very<br />
frequently of late-, " Time tha old boys were shaken up a bit"<br />
( Lauglhter, 9 Applause). Ind so we dec: ided to shake them up a<br />
bit. Perhaps we did,<br />
All I can say for myself is that in those Jaays and<br />
for at least ten years thereafter, I found myself referred to<br />
quite habitually, as a promising young mani and nowr, of<br />
cours'e, people dontt say it to my face I know from around<br />
the corner, that they are beginning to say sijhe old boy has<br />
had a good run". ( Laughter, Applause),<br />
However, Sir, I am not unduly disturbed about that,-<br />
because I just want to remaind you that I really couldn't leave<br />
at the present time, btx-cause I am--the Government'ls majority<br />
( Laughter Applause). I see my distinguished collea gue<br />
Harold Hoit * here, whom I still. rofer to as " young HaroldI~<br />
( Laughter) and hie's registering a protest,, He thinks hers<br />
the Clvrnin' majority.,,-( Laughter) And so lie is. All1<br />
I know is that we have a majority of one, and it is a case of<br />
all hands to th. e pump, until the&amp; next elcction, a-' ter which<br />
we'll have a majority of much beer thnoo Har, hoar)<br />
( Applause) I want particularly I_, orighti to address mayself to<br />
the, what I'll call compendiousl~ y, Youn~ g Liberals, because<br />
they have somthng to contribute to th-e affairs of tha naotion.<br />
The drive, the dyrnamism of the noxt ten-twenty, thirty years<br />
is in your hands., And T th~ ei-fore iv., a1. t to taTlk to you in<br />
that sense. What is the business of govc-rnnient? The business<br />
of government in the Coimionwealth of Aist'. al-ia is to produ~ ce,<br />
to expound, to advocalte ,,, eat objectivoe:: of uational poli-* C-y,<br />
We exre not here just to win an elcotion. Ncx are you here<br />
just to hclp to Win arn e. LCoticn., I-1 are here ; O-o win something,<br />
to do something for oair coutntry. Arid there fare we must at<br />
all times, try to behave according to t! 1e standa~ e. Ths of stlatesmanship<br />
and not just acccrdinL to-the,, standards of vote-getting,<br />
I am the last person to dony thLat unless you haNve votes, you<br />
have singularly little o'pportu-i-ity of tV-he statosmanship,<br />
( Laughter) But getting votcos ii2 PWe be-anll and -the enJ-all.<br />
We must have sorn pictur-o J. n cour mindsc of wshot wo want -to do,<br />
This perhaps is maoreo tai o.-n ic -the yocung than it is<br />
-for me. Though it i isuprl imaprtant for me because I have<br />
the major respon-sibi11ty in rgovcrnment, But it is vastly<br />
important for you), </p>
<p>Whiat are -tho, object ive:, s of na-tona1 polifcy?<br />
Iwould v\ ienture to sa-" y to you. i'n a -few conciso fentencas<br />
i. hat lj a/ c in mind, is of 01.19 owc-objective irust~ ba,<br />
-Go buil. d a balanced, stroig, proEgrCes,_ vo( and civilised notion<br />
in which. advances a:, e shared all secticns of tiao people0<br />
Noxu that mnay sound. to you a'lmost a platitude,, it isn't such<br />
a platitude. Wha~ t did 1 say " a bzalanced nation". A ny<br />
cheapjack can como al~ ong wiLtha somec rati,. or rmsretricious poliCy,<br />
some catchpenny policy, and get votes and disturb thae balance<br />
ofC the naition but it is balonnoc that counts,~ if a Ination is<br />
to build on its f~ oundations0 Wo want a-strong natilon., thnat's<br />
el~ ementary. We want a progrossive one" IP11 say something<br />
botthis later on, b-cus thre e those whlo were to be<br />
heard last year who appeared to be -under the impression that<br />
the Federal Government alidntt believe in progrc-s9 but believed<br />
ñ Ln some vjrotched form of stagnation,, And we -at'Iler lost that<br />
propaganda battl. e. So I repeat:, , e want a pr-ogressive nation.,<br />
There is nothiLng for thto youang in this country<br />
that can attract thenj or us, unlo._: s it is tlie vision of<br />
progress for the:, future, bua above all1 things, twe t-iant a<br />
civilised nation,, Not a nation in wichn every, p lI I<br />
issue is determined in terms of pounds shil' ings and ponce..<br />
Nota~ teiaistc aton but a nation that tunes itself to<br />
high endeavouro and to great ide-alsi a civilised na-tio~ n, 0<br />
In the course of Dy thl-irty-odd years in Parliaraentq<br />
one way or anothoiuI'eher a good. deal about the alleged<br />
class struggle in 1Australia0There are alwais pecople to be<br />
fol. m~ d who ir. ant to set class against,, class, !-nat class I<br />
be* Lcng -to, Ivve neverr quito di" scovered9 but I do believe that<br />
there is only one groat and, hionouraibie class distinction in<br />
Australia and that's th.-[ e distiln-ction between the industrIous<br />
and the idle. W4hcinevor hecar , m7y Co-, m, nmi st . Iwas going<br />
to say 11frio. ndrs" theyore nt,( Laughter) Whenever I<br />
hear the Communssrte arCriunists talki ng about the<br />
class struggle so muohc~ be-Love( d of Marx, I remind myself that<br />
in this cotuntry of naina. anci. yours, all thaot Class s-tuff is<br />
out of date, Yo'alre a wokror you're notv, and whenever<br />
they say inr. the Jor6s of tte old u] ltimaitum the MLanifestCo<br />
QWr" krs of the iiorl-d unite" l I foo lih ang " Hoar-, 9<br />
, e a r' t ao fvro c'D h zro s of'L stralia iuniting<br />
becauso, , be Leve me t I e future ofL the~ o country depends upon<br />
the-porcentr-o of pople afhoc iwTUroors and theo pw,, C entage<br />
of thIe people Wbno are not" Thiis is tlie 7, ne class distinction<br />
thLat I recoganise0 So T. paS on from that, Wihnat is the second<br />
great objective of natIi-onal pol1icy? It is the objective o f<br />
building, our young rnation iLn'ko a strong and splendid he-ritage<br />
and this can' t be achieved by a. people who acquire hoabits of<br />
do D-ondency0 It centb acOL~ cl. by peopl e who ha -e been<br />
reared up -to Say the3 curymnt s. Logan 1+ Why doosn2t th. o Governmeont<br />
do something abo--u t it? Tt alw1, ays soe1-, 1. to meto be<br />
theo mest ele-montary thin. g ~ n tho th-at if you iwant an<br />
inepndn ntini rmjtbe built' up if indopendent people.<br />
Tf yo--wnt -a nation th-. at is -tn a prsltion to<br />
be pushed over by,, othur nat-o. ns o f error if you like. ' Ou-t of<br />
gi. cateGr devot+ ion and ntuoLaa,-Lhn You ; qji]. J f-ind i in EL<br />
nation which_ has leanrn O. Lto-soyj Lalv it to thnu Government,<br />
doñ!-t leave it to mc.; Th1-is is a ticme,, ndous t. ing, I beg<br />
ovfe y oug an and evelrry ,/, ung w; oma-n heetonighLt to<br />
recall i~ t an irtdopoen nP; r ' ti-on. necdn epe<br />
people of ccu: a~ e~ a~ iha spir.-t' of . adventure<br />
with a desire to , and n a~ Kya dosiare to receive<br />
3 0 0 S 0 </p>
<p>from that mystic body known as th-government a rising . evel<br />
of civic unselfishness. I hope that nobody will suppose that I'm being,<br />
as you might say, parscnical about this. I'm afraid as a<br />
working politician I've been in the midst of the fray for<br />
many, many years, and my greatest disappointments in politics<br />
have been at the persistence of selfish judgments, of selfish<br />
standards, a loss of the old spirit of independence which.<br />
after all, has made Australia what it is today. This is a<br />
great banner for you to carry, You will be told by older<br />
people who will pretend that they are wiser people, " But all<br />
that's airy, fairy stuff that doesn't matter." I tell you,<br />
as one of the oldest, if not the wisest among them, that this<br />
is the only thing that does count. That we, in our time,<br />
should make an unselfish contribution to a great country which<br />
will be greater and greater as time goes on, but which must<br />
not be allowed to become merely greater in economic terms at<br />
the sacrifice of civilised standards of life, and of thought,<br />
and of character, Now, Sir, having said that, may I just say something<br />
about what we're pleased to call nowadays, the economic<br />
policy for Australia; the national objectives, because I find,<br />
rather to my surprise, that some of these objectives, particularly<br />
in our own Party are not all that well understood.<br />
So I will try to illustrate a few of them.<br />
We must build up, in Australia, if we are to be<br />
a great country and an independent country, a groat and growing<br />
population. That doesn't necessarily mean only at home, but<br />
by immigration from abroad. It's been, I think, one of the<br />
glories of the post-war period in Australia. This has been<br />
no party matter. One of the glories, that our population<br />
has been increasing in Australia at least as rapidly per cent<br />
as the population of Japan This is a very interesting<br />
rellection. A few millions a year ago, a little more a little<br />
time later. When in 1949 you sent me and my colleagues back<br />
into power in Australia, the population seemod to some people to<br />
have reached almost an optimum level, But today, there are<br />
between two and three million people more than there wore then,<br />
many of them coming from distant countries, many of them coming<br />
here with now traditions and new histories and new cultures<br />
and finding their place in the Australian community to our<br />
immense enrichment. And as we look forward to the future, we know now<br />
that the pessimists of the twenties who thought that we would<br />
never have a population of more than six or seven millions are<br />
completely out of date, But today we have ten and a half<br />
and the day will come before long when we will have twenty or<br />
thirty and become, in terms of population, a very, very<br />
considerable nation, And that's tremendously important.<br />
This is a big country. ItJs no mere figure of speech to say<br />
that I nyer go into the United States of America without<br />
reminding myself that that country is roughly the same size<br />
geographically, as Australia and that it has 180 or 190 million<br />
people. And, if there's one thing that helps the people in<br />
the United States to understand something of the problems of<br />
Australia, it is their superb, optimistic belief, looking back<br />
on their own history, that the day will cone when Australia<br />
will have as many people as they have today. They look back<br />
on their own history they look back on their own great<br />
migration waves and they look at us as if we were a sort of<br />
younger brother, going through the experiences of growth which<br />
they had themsclves. Ani this is a great tasko We must not<br />
falter in it. We must build up our population, e / o4 </p>
<p>Dut J. i we are to b' Ld op ce11" co -t i orni e mt<br />
not build uo an armay O'f: pole who1 1" vC r-0o TO toC' do xid<br />
tbe~ s . qere mry second objecti-ve ione. s Je v eq<br />
in l-, ustraiia, thue f,: ullest enmloyment' of manpower and of<br />
available resources,, You w Lbtod vrnwadth<br />
uitia relference to current fi.--urias tnia tftere is sofae<br />
registered un-employmont today,,<br />
Ladies and gen.-tlcmen., Ihnlo1o kl hack: ove(-r the<br />
last twleyearsD, T musL say tfaat th-e record of ful-l employinent<br />
i. n A1ustralia has bee) n so r; emarkcable. -that nobody before<br />
thie wrar -, ould h~ ave believed it Possible,. I weant to say<br />
to You, the younger people " Don't take those things for<br />
granted." Whan i first w-n-t into the Fedoral Parliament<br />
aIs Member for Kocyong, wheon I i-ias an itornpy-Gc,.-eral under<br />
the -late IMr, Lyons we; had, in -ustrzalIJa, a Lvlof<br />
unemployment w. hstrigfrom the-pa of tryDoi-cern.,<br />
in th( 3 great dy f JT laibad fallen ' L. o fifteeon, totwelve;,<br />
tcn, and theose a cthievom., i. ntIs wore ro-i. rdod as so<br />
remarkabloe in 1Ius-, tLaJ~ ia tt L the Lyons Gover. nme--nt w as r--<br />
elected time afte r tin0 tl today, a" ltar theio war, 7w ith<br />
all. the circums'an,-icz th'at ! have cxi etd, we take certain<br />
ttiings for gvantcd, The faict arnd I dont 6 doy It, I<br />
assort i-t-ta one o-f our g-reatest objecti-ves of nzational<br />
poliy mr~ atn verto etun to state 0 o ffairs, but<br />
to liave a full employmnt!* in u o,. m country ofmen, of<br />
manpower, and of physical rG-sourcos,,<br />
Blut, Sir, v mentionevd two th1-ings whl'ich oroduce<br />
thneir -prob-lorms Moro anid more~ peoplo, ancthaer qu-iraror of a0<br />
million peoplc a y~ aer th.-probleom of ' ull onlotc and,<br />
t te same time, weo -I-ust-rest-r-in inflat-Ion, No,, v, don't<br />
homisled by some of tiU allgedwsare h. il akt<br />
you and say that all t 1Lalk of Infl-ation is nsne<br />
Infliation of t currcoy-a ! rclcting -ice level the,<br />
sucking---ip of r. eal va 7CIIII t MmiI o ny the L ' oi r, 7ceiVe-3<br />
is a -trcman'lous socia p* Yoblem -nd i~ f itis allo-J'ed to<br />
Continuea, is a trxwnerdous social cri. Influction imust<br />
be rostrain~ j'r. And , ven1h ea ve spoke,-n in the pas a bout<br />
Stab. li1ty, ani tv-c. Lira thtv ' av rdcd tbljy<br />
a lt~ ofpepl hvetakc, n thei op-.-ortunity of saying. " Oh,<br />
ye! s. but stbJi. mero t~ eio% Ad sn you got thte<br />
bflrloigwtw ii -a11 f, 7--3w~ thn9 but the? governr"<br />
c--. nt is al1l-for ot--i t; Dn"~ je rionsomn-' e this is, J 4t<br />
a, pity th-at anybody,-, proJe. -sing b a smp-portor of the<br />
government sh-oul. d be bogieu. 3d tby Sua nonse--Snse00. f cour se,<br />
stability is lprai<br />
For thIast o. Lhtcon m.-onths. as a re-sult of<br />
p-olicie(-s of theo FPrlOvaimn, olicie) s for whicha ray<br />
colleag ue the Titeasurcr h.-s been L;-ost (': ickedily blamed as if<br />
hwe er soo. y and singl~ y rcsm~ oefo31 then--L) nrder tho se<br />
policie-s we havo fo) r the-J. ast cig~ en, month'-s had coirpleiAe<br />
b l-, jlity in C3. rLSLIMir LrI. OeS 4n Australia, Eighteen i. onths<br />
howould have th.-ought it -ossJ ble" oe t; ie? Arid that<br />
ha s -tuant Lht. h vailue o f 1.-one; ha s bcoo-n pre Se+ rvodc, The<br />
3plw t4.-C thoir n the sav-nogs bark haenotIj zceen<br />
taom,;:-fiter awa y+ Thuc pe-)-lo wln hkave inve stjA JIn gover-nment<br />
stocks im vc-seolee of1hhir ivm mrsmn-b filtor<br />
awa pep-jOJv n&gt; xdicmshv bThne able to<br />
s-y wvJLi er~~ tv-~ I " esnIb. II~ Ic n-r whLat tha-t -Inc-jae is<br />
WDrth" 21-. 1 h o t beae~ e~~ in tecou-ntry the<br />
beenr achieved0 e a 0 a a/ </p>
<p>Now, I said to you just now that there are people who<br />
believe t-hat. when we talk of stability, we Liberals, wevre<br />
talking in negative terms, we're professing something that's<br />
the opposite number of growtho In fact, you'll hear the<br />
question put, won't you " Are you for growth, or are you for<br />
stability?" Je happen to be for both, and in order to remind<br />
you how important stability is for growth I just want to tell<br />
you that over this period of eighteen months when this hardearned<br />
stability has been achieved, we have, at the same time,<br />
carried out or heavily contributed to, one of the greatest<br />
development programmes in the history of Australia the Snowy<br />
Mountains Scheme, Some of you have been there, Some of<br />
you have seen it.<br />
If, at one stage in our life, preferably just before<br />
an election, I had been able to say, " All right, We are<br />
going to spend œ 400M on hydro-electric schemes and irrigation<br />
headworks on the Snowy," people would have said, " Ah, there's<br />
a progressive man, That's a fine chap. Yes, he's for growth,<br />
Hets the man for our money," But this is exactly what we've<br />
been doing. Year after year I hesitate to mention the figures<br />
in the presence of Harold Holt, who has to flinch under them<br />
year by year, poor chap, But year by year, we're finding out<br />
of the Budget round about œ 20M for the Snowy and by the time it<br />
is finished, it will have cost œ 400M-odd and it will be then<br />
acknowledged to be what many people now acknowledge it to be<br />
one of the wonders of the world, one of the great developmental<br />
projects in this country or in this hemisphere.<br />
At the same time, over this pericd think of the other<br />
matters uniform gauge, I came down in the now train from<br />
Sydney to Melbourne the " Aurora" 0 We had a great deal to do<br />
with this, It is perhaps forgotten. A great deal to do with<br />
it, Seventy percnt, of it in the long run. And this great<br />
piece of development Sydney to Melbourne on a uniform gauge<br />
has already, I am happy to say, although it was finished only<br />
a month or two ago has already made a powerful contribution<br />
to freight returns and to passenger returns on that line, In<br />
other words, this has been a rumarkable contribution to the<br />
stability of the railways system in Australia,<br />
Up in Queensland, where they were beguiled into thinking<br />
the opposite, ( Laughter) c. What have we done over this<br />
period? I am talking now about a period of eighteen months<br />
of stability on the price level the Mt, Isa venture this<br />
tremendous railway conversion, which will enable Mt, Isa mine to<br />
become the greatest copper mine in the world, and a tremendous<br />
source of export wealth for this country beef roads, coal<br />
ports in Queensland and in New South Wales to enable an export<br />
trade in coal to go on and to grow, Al aiese things have<br />
been happening at a time when we were told that stability in our<br />
mouths meant stagnation, Did you ever hear such nnsense?<br />
I think, you know, that our political opponents frequently<br />
rely on their implicit belief that no Liberal has a good memory.<br />
I wanyou younger ones about this, You must cultivate a good<br />
memory. You must keep on, You don't want to be like the Lourbons<br />
and learn nothing and forget nothingr., but at any rate start by<br />
forgetting nothing, because they want you to forget th.: t when at<br />
the end of ' 1949 you sent us back into powc. r, one of the great<br />
problems in Australia was coal. Do you remember it? Some of<br />
you older ones will, Coal. , Jo were importing coal in Australia<br />
from South Africa and from other places0 There was a tremcndous<br />
shortage of coal, Po. wer was rationed because the power stations<br />
were short of coal. People forgt thse ths tings For the first<br />
two or three years of this po) r, stagnant, decadent governncnt of<br />
0 * f000 .16 </p>
<p>yours, wev er devoting our attention to getting coal from<br />
anywhere that it cculd. be got from. And today, nrt only does<br />
Australia have all the coal that it needs, but it is developing<br />
very large export markets for coal to the other countries of<br />
the world. We never have a deputation today to say we're<br />
short of coal, but we do have deputations to say, " Ie're short<br />
of the ways and means of exporting our coalo Give us a better<br />
port, give us better handling facilities. Do something for<br />
us that will enable us to use our surplus of coal for the<br />
advantage of Australia,"<br />
You heard something about beef roads. We don't have<br />
too many beef roads in Hawthorn, ( Laughter) The only one I<br />
can remember offhand is the run down towards the Richmond<br />
Abattoirs. The beef roads in Queensland, in ! est Australia,<br />
in the Northern Territory, in parts of New South Wales and<br />
South Australia these are tremendously important, because<br />
we have entered into the export phase of our lives as a nation,<br />
and we want to provide the ways and means for getting cattle<br />
to market, and getting stock to market in good condition with<br />
proper speed, so that our exports of these matters to the world<br />
may grow and flourish, No Government in the history of the<br />
Commonwealth has done so much in this field or is doing so<br />
much as your own Government and all this has been going on<br />
at a time when anti-inflationary measures were regarded as the<br />
very definition of stagnation by our own opponents,<br />
Now, Sir, I don't want to go on and make a catalogue<br />
of these matters; I've quoted a few examples to demonstrate<br />
to you that that great objective of policy to restr?' n<br />
inflation is the very condition of encouraging growth and<br />
development. If my colleague, the Treasurer were speaking<br />
to you tonight, he would Le able to tell you that as a result<br />
of this stability, as a result of the philosophies and actions<br />
of our Government our credit around the world has never been<br />
as high. We must borrow money, because no country of<br />
million can generate all the capital it needs for the development<br />
of a continents But our credit rating abroad is<br />
phenomenal. If I had the time to talk to you about the<br />
terms on which Australia, as at present governed, can raise<br />
money overseas, you would be staggered. And why? Why does<br />
this happen? Why dons it happen that, year by year, over this<br />
period, particularly the periods of stability, hundreds of<br />
millions have been invested in Australia from outside Australia<br />
invested by hard-headed peoples by people who, like most<br />
investors, look at what they call the growth factor, when they're<br />
making an investment. And here we've had, over this term of<br />
years, hundreds and hundreds of millions coming into Australia<br />
from other countries, coming into Australia from private<br />
investors, because they believe that on the basis of honest<br />
stability in the currency and vast developmental projects,<br />
Australia is the best place in which to invest their money,<br />
And, indeed, if that didn't happen, how do you suppose that<br />
we would receive all those migrants? How do you suppose we<br />
could build up our population, unless we had, year by year,<br />
at the same time, the capital behind them to enable them to<br />
make their own powerful contribution to the ffture of Australiao<br />
And our next national objective is that we must have,<br />
in Australia, a growing manufacturing industry0 Now, when<br />
I was a small boy, witi long ears listening, in the country,<br />
in a little village, in a rather political household, ( because<br />
you will be surprised to know, some of you, that this is an<br />
hereditary defect in me) ( Laughte:) t. he g-eat arguments were<br />
.0 o .0 oo / 7 </p>
<p>protection and free trade, within the country, and mc. t of<br />
the people were in favour of free trade and a few hardy souls<br />
were in favour of protection. But this really determined<br />
whether you were a good man or a bad man, It was like cowboys<br />
and Indians on the films, All that, I believe, is dying<br />
away. The fact is that nobody with a balanced mind today<br />
denies that you can't increase the population by a quarter of<br />
a million a year without having a steadily growing manufacturing<br />
industry, Because, on the land, where the increase in<br />
productivity has been admirable, over these years, there's not<br />
much scope for employing more people. The more farming is<br />
mechanised, the more science is applied to the processes of<br />
agriculture and of the pastoral industry the more likely<br />
is it to be that you won't have any grea% increase in the<br />
employed population. That is quite true, Everybody concedes<br />
it. And therefore, if you want to have a quarter of a million<br />
more people every year, there's just no escape from it and<br />
I don't mind, I'm all in favour of it thoro's no escape<br />
from the proposition that you'll have growing manufacturing<br />
industries and growing service and tertiary industries in<br />
Australia on a scale which will accommodate this population<br />
and give it employment.<br />
Now, Sir, I said a while ago that all these things<br />
produce their own problems, So they do, An increased<br />
population, the struggle to restrain inflation which may<br />
persuade people that policies are negative at the same time,<br />
the vital importance of building up manufacturing industries<br />
the vital importance of developing basic resources in Australia<br />
and all. of these things, except the restraining of inflation,<br />
tend to create it, And this is something we must watch,<br />
This produces some of that cution that you've been told about<br />
from time to time.<br />
Because, you see, ladies and gentlemen, we could<br />
build up our manufacturing industries almost extravagantly.<br />
We could build up our population. We could devote ourselves<br />
to the principles of full employment, but if the results were<br />
that the farm industries of Australia found their costs rising<br />
and rising against them, this country would be brought to ruin,<br />
because let's have no mistake about it; the great export<br />
industries of Australia, to wit, the primary export industries,<br />
are responsible in the true sense for the prosperity of<br />
Australia, directly and indireccly, For a start, they<br />
produce most of our overseas income, and they are able to sell<br />
abroad and to extend their production and to sell more abroad,<br />
because their costs have not yet got out of hand. But if the<br />
day comes when, because of inflationary processes at home,<br />
their costs rise against them, they can be tossed out of their<br />
world markets. What would happen then?<br />
I beg of you, think about these matters. Don't<br />
be bemused by the people who say, " Well, that's all right.<br />
We can always handle the currency internally, We can always<br />
have monetary mechanisms which wi. ll make up for that, My<br />
friends of all the hundreds of millions that are earned by<br />
the Australian wool and wheat and meat and dairying industry<br />
and so on, down the lino, the m: tal industry, seventy percent.,<br />
a safe estimate, pays for imports into Australia of items<br />
needed by Australian manufacturorso<br />
This idea that everything that is imported into<br />
Australia is a chiffon of some kind what the economists are<br />
pleased to call " consumer goods" this is all nonsense,<br />
The groat bulk of the imports into Australia, paid for by<br />
wool and wheat and moat and so on are materials to be used<br />
and plant and equipment to be use.. in Australian manufacturing oo0ooo o/ 8 </p>
<p>Ind'ustry. ~ Id it is in that sense that the nvrnufocturer<br />
himself, whose supporter I am as I bave indicated, must always<br />
remember that he must not, 9 arid we must not, price the primary<br />
producer out of that vital market in the rest of the world,,<br />
And, therefore, thatts another of our great objectives to<br />
preserve the cost level of the exportu industries to preserve<br />
it not only by allowing the costs against it in ihat positive<br />
sense but also ( this goes for manufacturing also) to concentrate<br />
our attention on getting their costs of production down by<br />
improving their efficiency,, I just want to illustrate that<br />
to you, without being too tedicus.<br />
You take manufacturing. You may have not.-ced that<br />
last February and thereafter in Parliament, we introduced<br />
provisions for an investment allowance on new plant in manufacturing.<br />
The whole purpose of this was to encourage manufacturers<br />
to improve their plant and therefore to improve their<br />
efficiency, and therefore to reduce their costs of production<br />
and therefore to render less necessary the rate of tariff<br />
protection which might otherwise have been required, This<br />
is a practical, sensible,~ reasoned approach to the matter.<br />
Anid, in the case of t~ ie man on the land, we have, in Australia,<br />
superb scientific organisations the C. S. I. R. 0 is one of the<br />
great things in the world in that field. Much research is<br />
done but the results of it must be brought to the man on<br />
the larm if we are going to have Pall advantage and, therefore,<br />
we have devoted a lot of attention to extension services and<br />
matters of that kind and have a lot more to do before we are<br />
finished. Now, Sir, I have spoken to you about national<br />
objectives, These are some of them. These mostly rolate<br />
to what goes on inside Australia. Their achievcement seems to<br />
me to represent a magnificent challenge a challenge not to<br />
complacency, but to the spirit of adventure, and, therefore<br />
above all things, a challenge to young men and women who will<br />
be responsible for these matters when I am a mere dusty<br />
memory, Thasaa:. oa marvellous challenge. Thore is nothing<br />
negative about them, they are positive and they're compelling,<br />
and these are the problems of the dreary science, the problems<br />
of the economy. They are not the only problems that we have.<br />
I wonder if we realise always that we are so few in a land so<br />
great that we can't expect the rest of the world just to be<br />
kind t us, to look after us, for some inscrutable reason.<br />
What we have to do in the world, and we do it through our<br />
Government primarily, is to establish with other countries in<br />
the world a position of respect, a posi~ tion in which they<br />
will encourage us, a position in which they will be delighted<br />
to give us such help as they can, The business of foreign<br />
policy, so complicated by some of the commentators, is at<br />
base a very simple one. The business of foreign policy is to<br />
make friends and keep them. Not to go into a war72 if a war<br />
is not unavoidable, but if you go into one, to go into it with<br />
strong and resolute friends. This is the simplified statement<br />
of foreign policy, and those who represent you in Australia in<br />
the Government and who go around the world and speak for you<br />
in the councils of the world, must speak for you to the Prime<br />
Minister and Cabinet of Great Britain, the President of France<br />
and the Chancellor of Germany and the President of the United<br />
States of America and so on, right round all the spots of the<br />
world. I think you'll agree with me that it's very desirable<br />
that whoever speaks for you in that sense should speak for a<br />
country that knows its own mind, that Iunov. s where it's going,<br />
that is determined to make sacrifices to get there, which is<br />
honest a country whose word cali be takon, a country which will<br />
00 0 : 00/ 9 </p>
<p>be regarded as a fPriendly country in all1 the countries of the<br />
worLd0 Thi~ s is tromean2ously important0<br />
I don~ t propose at this time to try to make a speech<br />
to you on the Common Market, because I have said somethi-ng<br />
about that since I came back home, but I'll just say this to<br />
you: This is a great problem,, It is a great problem for<br />
Australian primary industry; it is a great problem for<br />
Australian secondary industry; it is a great problem for the<br />
Commonwealth. There are powerful political arguments for<br />
Great Britain going into Europe, and she alone will decide<br />
whether they are valid or not, There ara~ economic arguiments<br />
for Great Britain going into Europe, and she alone will decide<br />
whether they are valid or not. You have the six nations of<br />
Western Europe all concerned because they are already within<br />
the Treaty of Rome. You have Great Britain you Lave the<br />
United States of America, in which this problem is lively and<br />
produces activity in the minds and actions of the President<br />
and the Administration., These are tremendous problems.<br />
I can see all the advantages of Western Europe<br />
having some form of association which may drub out of her ccr~ aiaceani<br />
consciousness the old feuds between the French and the Germans<br />
and perhaps offers some prospect of peace. I can see all that.<br />
I can see all the advantages of Great Britain being inside the<br />
councils of Europe in order to give what no other country can<br />
give in such full measure, wiso counsel and sensible and<br />
experienced guidance. I can understand that. I can understand<br />
why the United States of America would like this to happen.<br />
I can understand the arguments that are put by some people at<br />
any rate, in Great Britain about the economic advantages 01<br />
being inside a customs union which would give to Great Britain<br />
a home market of 250 million people, instead of 50. These are<br />
all quite intelligible things,<br />
Our great problem, a delicate problem, a difficult<br />
problem, a problem not to be solved by violent statements at<br />
all, or by violent action, our great problem has been to keep<br />
on reminding those concerned that9 up to now, the great pattern<br />
of trade for us and for Great Britain, has been the Commonwealth<br />
pattern of trade, and that this is something with its roots well<br />
down now in history, which will not be thrown away l~ ightly or<br />
casually. I don'tthirik it will be thrown away lightly or<br />
casually, I have no doubts whatever after my visits to both<br />
countries that the most stronuous efforts are being made by<br />
the British negotiators to preserve, if not in form but, at any<br />
rate, in substance, the pattern of Commonwealth trade which<br />
means so much to us, and which as I reminded them, has meant<br />
so much to Great Britain herself in our lifetime,<br />
But this is not the time to be conducting longrange<br />
debates en the matter. All that I can tell you is that<br />
I have no doubt whatever that the negotiators, the Ministers of<br />
Great Britain, understand our case completely, I am happy to<br />
say that I think that the Administration of the United States,<br />
from the President down, understand our case in substance very<br />
well. And as they are both our traditional friends, I have<br />
not yet reached a state of mind in which I want to abandon<br />
myself to despair. Indeed let me warn you against this,<br />
Don't let us get into a state of undue exercise over these<br />
matters, Don't let us become too much the doubters on -these<br />
matters, because all we will do will be to damage our own<br />
economic activity at home. ' tie will create fears and uncertainty.<br />
I will be going over there unless, as I concede, we are tossed<br />
out in Auf'-' st 1.1-blc,: Pudrget Sessi. on6But subject to that risk,<br />
00/ i0 </p>
<p>Ipropose to be there with one or two of my colleagues in<br />
September, and will then be in a much better position to form<br />
judgments and to offer arguments.<br />
All I want to say to you is that the Common Market<br />
argument is not just an argument about a market or markets,<br />
This is an argument about the most remarkable development in<br />
international affairs of this century, All those of you who<br />
have read history will remember that the balance of power<br />
policy of Great Britain has been a cardinal point for a long<br />
time. If, as a result of the present negotiations, the<br />
United Kingdom goes into Europe with mutual obligations, with<br />
the inhibitions arising from that on her powers; if that<br />
happens, that will be a most remarkable development in British<br />
foreign policy, We are not to permit ourselves the luxury<br />
of saying, " You ought not to do that", instead we must say,<br />
" This is for you to say": but we are of the family, we have<br />
lived together and traded together and that pattern is not<br />
lightly to be put aside.<br />
1 come back to where I began, Perhaps for people<br />
of my generation, the retrospective attitude begins to cloud<br />
the mind. But in the next twenty, thirty, forty, years, it<br />
will be the spirit of adventure that will be paramount and<br />
that spirit will have to come from you young Liberals or<br />
where is it to come from? </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
