<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9490</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP CROSS MEDIA RULES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/02/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009490.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER 10/ 95<br />
STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
CROSS MEDIA RULES<br />
On the radio program PMV this evening the Leader of the Opposition, John<br />
Howard, has confirmed that he has been putting to media proprietors the view<br />
that the 1987 media prohibitions, known as the cross media rules, are<br />
unnecessary and unjustified.<br />
Mr Howard said his public and private views were consistent on this matter.<br />
The public stance he took in 1987 and reaffirmed tonight is that the cross<br />
media rules are unnecessary.<br />
He seeks to skate over the fact these private expressions from a would-be<br />
prime minister become policy expressions, while at the same time saying that<br />
his party's current policy supports the maintenance of the cross media rules.<br />
Mr Howard says his party will at the appropriate time review their current<br />
policy. All this belies the point that he is telling media proprietors privately<br />
as he admits-that he does not agree with the cross media rules.<br />
Where is the public interest?<br />
On the one hand he points to Liberal Party policy which supports the cross<br />
media rules, on the other hand he says his private expressions are consistent<br />
with what he said in 1987, which was that the cross media rules are too<br />
restrictive and unnecessary.<br />
What would any proprietor be entitled to take from his private expressions?<br />
The answer is clearly only one message that John Howard would abolish<br />
the 1987 cross media rules.<br />
CANBERRA FEBRUARY, 1995 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
