<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21808</transcript-id>
    <title>The Right Honourable Sir Harry Talbot Gibbs GCMG AC KBE  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/06/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Sir Harry Gibbs will be remembered as one of this country's most respected and skilled jurists.</p>
<p>  He was educated at Ipswich Grammar School and Emmanuel College at the University of Queensland, where he graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in 1937 and a Bachelor of Laws in 1939 - both were awarded with first-class honours.</p>
<p>Sir Harry's early legal career was interrupted by World War II.  After serving in the Australian Military Forces from 1939 to 1942, he became a Major in the Australian Imperial Force where he fought until the end of the war.</p>
<p>  Following a distinguished career at the Bar, Sir Harry served as a Judge of the Supreme Court of Queensland from 1961 until 1967 and also the Federal Court of Bankruptcy and the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory.</p>
<p>  In recognition of his outstanding legal mind and his towering reputation in the legal community, Sir Harry was appointed a Justice of the High Court in 1970.</p>
<p>When Sir Garfield Barwick retired from the bench, the Coalition Government appointed Sir Harry as Chief Justice of the High Court of Australia in 1981.</p>
<p>His term on the court was marked by a number of major constitutional cases arising from the 1974 double dissolution of parliament and also the legislative programme of the Whitlam government.  As Chief Justice, he presided over a series of cases involving the reach of Commonwealth power, most notably the Koowarta's Case in 1982 and the Tasmanian Dam Case in 1983.</p>
<p>  Sir Harry was knighted in 1970 and became a Privy Councillor in 1972.  He would later support the provisions of the Australia Act 1986, which effectively terminated appeals to the Privy Council from Australia.</p>
<p>Following his retirement in 1987, Sir Harry remained an active contributor to debate on legal issues and presided over a number of judicial inquiries.</p>
<p>Sir Harry passed away on 25 June 2005, aged 88 years.</p>
<p>On behalf of the Government, I extend to his wife Lady Muriel, his son and three daughters and to other family members and friends, our most sincere sympathy in their bereavement.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
