<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4147</transcript-id>
    <title>CURRENT AFFAIR - 8 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004147.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CURRENT AFFAIR JUNE 8, 1976<br />
QN. Prime Minister are you worried about union threats over<br />
your medibank plans?<br />
P. M. I don't believe that union threats are going to be put<br />
into effect. The medibank plans are clear and they provide<br />
the widest possible area of choice. I indicated about two<br />
weeks ago that we were also looking at the prospect of allowing<br />
medibank under exactly the same terms and conditions to offer<br />
intermediate and private ward cover and in this area compete<br />
with * the private funds. That decision was made today by the<br />
Government on a submission from the Minister for Health and<br />
on this basis I don't believe that the unions have any case<br />
at all. They certainly have no case for their claim that<br />
the Government is trying to force people out of medibank.<br />
* That is sheer and absolute nonsense.<br />
QN. The A. C. T. U. President, Bob Hawke still says it is a two<br />
class system.<br />
He did'-t know about this recent decision and our system is<br />
certainly not a two class system. What the previous administration<br />
had introduced might well have been because you had basic<br />
standard ward cover for everyone under medibank and then<br />
people and a number of people have would still go out to<br />
private insurers, to private funds to cover themselves for<br />
intermediate or private ward treatment. Now under the<br />
system that we are introducing, it is going to be much more<br />
possible for anyone to cover themselves for intermediate<br />
or private ward treatment Q= ' 2bder the decision-made today<br />
somebody will be able to do this -under medibank itself which<br />
would not have been possible under the arrangements of the<br />
previous administration.<br />
N. But basically what you are introducing is still just the same<br />
as a private health fund but another one isn't it?<br />
P. M. If somebody is paying a levy or a part levy and they want to<br />
take out additional cover they will have the choice of doing<br />
that through medibank or the choice of doing it through a<br />
private fund.<br />
But you are still not offering a free system which is basically<br />
P. M. * Oh-free. Nothing is free in this community and that is what<br />
needs to be understood and if people are objecting to the fact<br />
that medical services are going to have to be paid for and be<br />
seen to be paid for that is a different matter again. </p>
<p>2.<br />
QN. But we are still not getting one system for everybody....<br />
P. M. I think there ought to be an area of choice why shouldn't<br />
there-be an area of choice because we are also establishing<br />
the circumstances where the people on the lowest income will<br />
get a fully subsidised service. Ql Other people will pay in<br />
accordance with their income up to a certain ceiling where<br />
people will be paying pretty near the full cost of what<br />
medibank provides. Now that I think is pretty fair and even<br />
the previous administration at one stage had thought of.<br />
introducing a special levy to pay for medibank. High quality<br />
health care is expensive and it is nonsense to suggest it is<br />
free it's not.<br />
Q. N. Prime Minister if the unions don't accept this will you listen<br />
to them?<br />
We will always listen to people but what we are putting forward<br />
is fair. zm it is quite essential that medibank is seen to be<br />
paid for and these measures will proceed. I think the main<br />
trade union complaint was one that had suggested that we<br />
were seeking to force people out of medibank. Now that claim<br />
is so patently false especially in view of todays decision that<br />
I don't believe that it can be sustainedeauv if people want to<br />
go around the community and say that nobody should have to pay<br />
for health care well. that then just means a permanent increase<br />
in taxation to pay for it.<br />
QN. If the threat of continuing strikes as so forth stays will you<br />
rethink?<br />
P. M. I don't believe it will.<br />
Q. N. The threat won't occur<br />
P. M. I don't believe so, no.<br />
Q. N. If it should<br />
P. M. Oh if therea-r. e-many ifs in the world lets meet ifs when we<br />
come to them.<br />
Q. N. Prime Minister you have another head on confrontation coming<br />
possibly this week with the Premiers. Do you expect that to be<br />
a confrontation?<br />
P. M. Oh there might be something the Premiers won't particularlylike.<br />
I think the federalism proposals will be basically well received,<br />
when they are announced in the final detail, because most of<br />
the major decisions in these areas have already been taken at the two<br />
previous conferences<br />
Q. N. They a. re asking for more money. Will you be giving them more?<br />
P. M. Under the actual tax reimbursment arrangements the new<br />
federalism proposals will work, they will operate and the<br />
principles of that have already been agreed to. When you come<br />
to other areaswhere there are funds provided by the Commonwealth<br />
and the States/ I have no doubt the states will be asking for more<br />
money </p>
<p>3.<br />
Q. N. They say they will need more money and possibly introduce their<br />
own taxes unless you help them.<br />
P. M. A number of states have made additional promises over recent<br />
times or example one state has promised to abolish all<br />
probate duty at a cost of about 37 million dollars. off dther<br />
states made other promises which would cost quite substantially.<br />
If they are making those promises under certain sets of<br />
circumstances, they should be able or expected to pay for those<br />
things-for their own promises-from their own resources. But<br />
I would like to emphasize that state governments havejas<br />
much as OtCommonwealth, over the last year or two in . part, been<br />
responsible for the view that people only have to ask for things<br />
of government and government can provide. We have to get<br />
the view across that when politicians promise anything they are<br />
not promising anything of their own, they are promising something<br />
to be taken from taxpayers. ( hey are promising something<br />
that basically has to be taken from every citizen in the<br />
community.<br />
Q. N. Will you encourage them to introduce their own taxes<br />
P. M. If I could get at this another way. I would like to encourage<br />
them to be more efficient. I would like to encourage the<br />
states to go about their business in a way i which will be<br />
. economical and which will free resources to private individuals<br />
as we have sought to do. It is worth noting that over the<br />
three years to December, while Commonwealth Public Service<br />
employees rose by 43 thousand, state and local government<br />
public service employees rose by 83 thousand. Now I have not<br />
seen any attempts so far by any of the statestequivalent to<br />
the efforts we have made. over recent months/ to bring economy<br />
into their administration. And I think they ought to do so.<br />
ON-Do you think as a result of your meeting that the state taxes<br />
that we will be in for state taxes<br />
P. M. I would hope the states would try and use their resources<br />
as economically as possible and I would not want to see state<br />
taxes go u. aIthough that obviously is a matter for states,<br />
But if they believe that their own services to their own<br />
people can be expanded in real terms, year after year after<br />
yearlthat can only happen if they put up taxes.<br />
In 1974/ 75. state budget outlays increased<br />
by a mere fraction under 40%. Now the Commonwealth increased<br />
by about the same amount. And we always said it was very wrong<br />
for the Commonwealth expenditures to increase by that amount.<br />
It is just as wrong for the state expenditures to increase by<br />
in one year. This sort of expansion of government<br />
expenditure cannot continue.<br />
Q. N. Prime Minister are you concerned about Australia's economic<br />
recovery? </p>
<p>P. M. I believe that there is much greater confidence in the<br />
community. I think the Arbitration : Commission made a<br />
highly responsible decision a short while ago.. d 4t is<br />
quite essential that people understand that a withdrawal<br />
in the public sector is essential for a return to vigour<br />
and vitality in the private sector, because we had, got<br />
to-the circumstances where taxes were so high and profits<br />
so low that there were no funds to create jobsa-' 1here<br />
was a great cost in the result in* high inflation and<br />
high and prolonged unemployment.<br />
Q. N. We-will be talking to Mr Hawke in this programme shortly<br />
so I must just in the meantime come back to that if you<br />
don't get the cooperation that you need from the unions<br />
will you give in or do you think you might be fighting a<br />
losing battle against unemployment and inflation<br />
P. M. The unions certainly have a great capacity to influence<br />
what happens in Australia. a a Qe have done I believe as<br />
: muchand maybe more, than many people expected of us in<br />
setting the climate where unions I believe ought to be<br />
prepared to cooperate with the government in encouraging<br />
economic recovery. Tax indexation, the new system of<br />
family allowances which is the most advanced single<br />
social reform introduced in the last 50 years, these<br />
things set the climate of reasonableness and of concern<br />
for all Australians.. W I believe that there are many<br />
people in the trade union movement who will understand<br />
this.<br />
Q. N. One last question any chance that you might give a little<br />
on the medibank question.<br />
P. M. Give a little. The proposals are fair. The only other way<br />
of doing these things is to not have the medibank levy, and<br />
just have a general increase in taxation to cover it. Now<br />
that is not going to be as effective,-as reasonable as the<br />
proposals that we have introduced.<br />
Q. N. Would you consider doing it if you had to.<br />
P. M. What we have introduced is a better proposal, so we stick with<br />
what we have introduced., x Aon't forget that once the decision<br />
was*: taken, as it was today, to enable medibank to offer<br />
intermediate and private ward coverage in competition with<br />
private funds, then I believe that will establish in total<br />
the best solution to our problems and one which is a<br />
particularly Australian solution which will avoid the problems<br />
that have occurred in Britain and Canada. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
