<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7618</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MIKE CARLTON, RADI 2GB, 1 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007618.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH MIKE CARLTON, RADIO 2GB, 1 JUNE<br />
1989 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
CARLTON: On the line from Canberra the Prime Minister this<br />
morning. Good morning.<br />
PM: Good morning Mike.<br />
CARLTON: Where did we all go wrong?<br />
PM: Well just let's get straight who's wrong. I mean the<br />
presentation that you put, Mike, almost assumes that all<br />
Australian families via the government owe this money and<br />
this is perhaps not surprising seeing the way the opposition<br />
try and put this story. They say ' here's a figure of $ 100B<br />
there are so many Australian families, each Australian owes<br />
therefore that much. Now that is a nonsense. The fact is<br />
that the great majority of this debt is owed by the private<br />
sector. The private sector have made decisions to borrow<br />
offseas basically to finance investments in this country<br />
which are providing employment and growth in Australia. Let<br />
me give you the breakup of the debt as at the last figure<br />
that we've got for it; 61% of the debt is owed by the<br />
private sector, 14% is by State Governments and 25% by State<br />
Government/ Commonwealth Government authorities like the<br />
Electricity Trust and so on. The Commonwealth Government,<br />
the Australian people's Government, owes no debt, no debt at<br />
all. In fact because of the fact that we have now turned<br />
our deficits that we inherited from the opposition when we<br />
came to power, you're saying ' where have we gone wrong?',,<br />
where we'd gone wrong was before. We inherited a deficit<br />
which was approaching $ 10B. We've turned that deficit that<br />
we inherited around from $ l0B into a surplus of<br />
We're in our second year of surplus, the first time that<br />
this has happened for over 30 years. Now we haven't gone<br />
wrong as a Government, we've gone right and we owe no debt.<br />
So the debt is owed basically, the overwhelming part of it,<br />
by the private sector who've made decisions which will<br />
enable them to accrue income to get it back. And as well as<br />
that debt being in the private sector we should also<br />
remember that in the period that we've been in Government<br />
there's been a significant increase in investment overseas<br />
by the private sector which is meaning that now we're<br />
getting each year from that investment overseas $ 2.6B in<br />
income which is more than four times what we were getting<br />
three years ago. Now<br />
CARLTON: But surely the average Australian is having to<br />
foot the bill for these private borrowings with high<br />
interest rates? </p>
<p>Pm: I was not going to ignore that part Mike, and you were<br />
perfectly fair to refer to the high interest rates and I<br />
know that your listeners are worried about that. Let me<br />
make this point that the investment that's taken place<br />
overseas and particularly in the last couple of years has<br />
been welcomed because what we want to do is get investment<br />
in Australia, particularly into our manufacturing industry,<br />
to re-equip it, make it more competitive so that we can earn<br />
more overseas and not have to import so much from overseas.<br />
Now unfortunately the rate of investment increase that's<br />
taken place in the last year or so is so high that it is<br />
bringing in levels of imports that we can't sustain. So<br />
this is where your interest rate policy comes in. We've<br />
just got to slow the economy down somewhat now because the<br />
simple fact is Mike, without getting technical about it,<br />
we're importing so much now that we can't afford that level<br />
of imports so what we've got is a tight monetary policy with<br />
high interest rates to slow the economy down somewhat. But<br />
we won't be slowing it down that much that we're going to go<br />
into recession. We're going to keep growth and keep<br />
employment and as we do bring that level of activity back<br />
we'll be able to ease interest rates off.<br />
CARLTON: The average Australian takes a look at it though<br />
and they see the Bonds and the Elliotts and the other big<br />
business buccaneers borrowing huge sums which we support<br />
with our interest rates and then they run their profits from<br />
all these huge sums through the Cook Islands or something.<br />
PM: Yes and Mike that's why we have announced and that<br />
was done by Paul Keating we've announced that there's an<br />
end to these tax havens. They will be closed down and under<br />
the announcement that's already been made with the<br />
legislation to come under it then there will be no further<br />
opportunity for this to be done. This whole tax system in<br />
this country was built up under our predecessors. we've<br />
spent years and years now since we've been in office closing<br />
down avoidance loophole after avoidance loophole. The tax<br />
evasion industry was described by the conservative's own<br />
Royal Commissioner Just before we came into office it<br />
was described as the fastest growing industry in this<br />
country. It's this Government which by piece of legislation<br />
after legislation is closing down the tax avoidance industry<br />
and now with the closing down of the tax havens that<br />
smashing of the tax avoidance industry which had grown up<br />
under the Liberals will be finished. I can understand, I<br />
mean I'm continuously thinking about what's the best way we<br />
can conduct policy to ensure that your listeners, the<br />
ordinary Australians, are not going to take an unfair burden<br />
of this. We want to make sure<br />
CARLTON: You see I asked them this morning what question<br />
they most wanted asked and they wanted to know why they're<br />
paying off 17% on their home mortgage so that the Bonds and<br />
so can go and borrow big overseas for takeovers? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
PM: No, well let me say that on the question of borrowing<br />
overseas, I mean if the private sector wasn't borrowing in a<br />
situation where we are importing more than we export the<br />
simple fact is if this country or any country imports more<br />
than it exports then it has to borrow to make up the<br />
difference. If the private sector wasn't borrowing, the<br />
Government would have to. That's a simple point. I mean<br />
you don't have to be an economist to know that. If we have<br />
a level of activity which means that we're importing into<br />
the country more than we are exporting then it's that<br />
difference that you have to borrow to pay for. Now because<br />
the Government has been prudent in cutting down its levels<br />
of outlays and is repaying its debt, it's the private sector<br />
that's borrowing. Now in a sense, in a sense that's a good<br />
thing to the extent Mike, that it's building up. What's<br />
being imported is equipment to make our factories more<br />
efficient and that's what we're getting significant growth<br />
in employment. We've virtually eliminated the large<br />
overhang of unemployment that we inherited.<br />
CARLTON: Alright. Isn't a lot of that importing just<br />
frills. I mean<br />
PM: Well to some extent some of it is. I mean<br />
CARLTON: You know CD players.<br />
PM: You've got certain things that are regarded as luxuries<br />
and so on. Now you've got to ask yourself the question and<br />
some people are saying, ' well you put import barriers<br />
against the imports of some of these things'. Well one<br />
thing you've got to ask yourself, can Australia be going<br />
around the world as we are, preaching to the rest of the<br />
world that they have to have open economies so that our<br />
farmers and efficient exporters can get a fair go in their<br />
economies and at the same time then putting up barriers here<br />
against imports. I mean you're going to look pretty funny<br />
going around the rest of the world saying get rid of your<br />
barriers, your protective apparatus which stops us getting<br />
into your countries but as we do that we'll whack up<br />
barriers against you. It's a pretty difficult situation to<br />
do that.<br />
CARLTON: Yes alright. Why not a tax break on savings? I<br />
mean the little person with a few thousand, perhaps a few<br />
hundred dollars in a savings account gets very upset paying<br />
tax on that. Why can't you give tax relief on that?<br />
PM: It's something that's in the public domain that's got<br />
to be looked at. But just let me make these two points that<br />
I don't think are too complex. On the question of savings,<br />
if you give tax relief what you are doing is giving up a<br />
certain saving because to the extent that there is a tax and<br />
that goes into the public revenue, that is a certain saving.<br />
I mean it's money not expended because it's taken by way of<br />
tax. The question is if you give that tax relief back, is<br />
the money going to be saved to the same extent or is part of </p>
<p>-4-<br />
( PM cont): it going to be spent and not saved? So you<br />
can't delude yourself that by giving a tax break you are<br />
increasing the stock of saving in the community. I mean<br />
-that's quite obvious. So that's<br />
CARLTON: Well you may well though. I mean people may feel<br />
that if they may be encouraged to save, if they know the<br />
interest on those savings won't be taxed?<br />
PM: No what I'm saying is that the fact that you are taxing<br />
that is by definition saving. It is not spent. Whereas if<br />
CARLTON: If national saving was not saving for the poor<br />
bloke with the<br />
PM: I understand that. But I mean the question is normally<br />
raised in terms of the community as a whole. The community<br />
as a whole has got to save more and not spend, is it not<br />
better to give the tax deduction? I'm simply making that<br />
point that that's one of the things that has to be taken<br />
into account. I'm not saying it's conclusive, it's one of<br />
the considerations that has to be taken into account.<br />
CARLTON: Well you have said earlier on, a few weeks ago,<br />
that all economic policy was under constant review and being<br />
looked at. Are you considering the possibility of a tax<br />
break on savings?<br />
PM: Well it's not specifically on our agenda but obviously<br />
with the amount of discussion that's going on, it's being<br />
talked about in the Press, what have you, people will<br />
obviously be wanting to get analyses of these concepts. But<br />
that's a different thing from saying it's on the agenda to<br />
be announced in the near future. I mean I'm not trying to<br />
to be tricky about that. If you have an issue like this<br />
which is being talked about as much as it is obviously<br />
you're having the issue analysed. You must do and if the<br />
thing's being talked about as much as it is I mean I<br />
wouldn't be able to make the points back to you now that I<br />
am. CARLTON: So you are at least looking at it as a<br />
possibility? PM: Well one's analysing the issue obviously because you<br />
can't have something like that in the public domain and say,<br />
' you know I'm ignoring it'. But I don't want to leave your<br />
listeners with the impression that because we are properly<br />
looking at the issue in terms of it being there in the<br />
public domain that it's something that's on an eve of<br />
announcement or something like that.<br />
CARLTON: Prime Minister what's to prevent all this finally<br />
ending in a massive recession sometime next year, that we<br />
actually hit the wall? Interest rates are too high </p>
<p>PM: Well that's a good question. Let me answer it. We've<br />
had in the 1980s Mike, two periods when we've had a sort of<br />
a boom and bust type of situation. one was in the period<br />
before we came to office. In 1981/ 82<br />
CARLTON: The wages explosion?<br />
PM: Wages explosion and that occurred you had great boom<br />
in activity but you had no wages policy in place. wages<br />
just went through the roof. In 1985/ 86 when the terms of<br />
trade collapsed Mike, the situation was there that you had a<br />
wages policy in place. We were able to control wages and we<br />
came through that with a lower level of activity but with<br />
still having economic growth and employment still rising.<br />
Now at this period we've got a tight policy which we must<br />
have for the reasons that I hope your listeners understand.<br />
I just want to make one more point on that in a moment. But<br />
we've got a wages policy in place which means that there<br />
will only be an increase in wages of about six and a half<br />
per cent in this year. Now that means with a combination of<br />
the wages policy and the taxes position coming up in July,<br />
that we're not going to have a wages breakout. So in a<br />
position where the OECD has just announced that world<br />
economic growth is going to go on at about 3.25% this year<br />
and about 2.75% next year, we're in a world which is going<br />
to be continuing to grow but at a slightly slower rate,<br />
that's what we believe on the experience of the ' 80s we can<br />
do here.<br />
CARLTON: It's a big gamble. For instance, if the prices<br />
for our wool and wheat and minerals fall, commodity prices<br />
drop, if you keep interest rates on too long we'll hit the<br />
wall with a huge bang won't we?<br />
PM: Well, yes, and that's like saying that if your aunt had<br />
a different anatomical construction she'd be your uncle.<br />
The fact is that you can construct any sort of scenario and<br />
say if it was like that then sure you'll get a different<br />
outome.<br />
CARLTON: The risks are there.<br />
PM: of course the risks are there. I mean we don't live in<br />
a risk-free world. That was not what was ordained for us<br />
when we appeared on this globe and particularly at the<br />
latter part of the 20th Century. The world is full of<br />
risks. But the important thing is a world full of risks<br />
demands policies and toughness and a capacity to make<br />
decisions. And this Government has shown now through six<br />
years of inherited difficulties remember interest rates<br />
you talk about now, interest rates under this Government<br />
haven't approached the level of interest rates under the<br />
previous Government. They ruined the economy, they had an<br />
additional quarter of a million people thrown out of work in<br />
their last twelve months of office, they had double digit<br />
unemployment and double digit inflation. We've got them<br />
both down and interest rates under them hit 22%, 22% and </p>
<p>-6-<br />
PM ( cont): that's for 90 day bills, 22%. Ours is only<br />
around 18%. Now that's high and too high but it's<br />
necessary. The important point is yes we live in a world of<br />
risks and dangers and problems and in this country you've<br />
got two alternatives. The others who wrecked the economy,<br />
threw people out of work at a rate never seen before for<br />
years, with double digit inflation. We've created 1.4<br />
million jobs, four times the rate of job creation under them<br />
because we've got the policies and at the moment<br />
unfortunately with the enormous growth that we've had, the<br />
risks and dangers that are around that you talk about mean<br />
that we have to have high interest rates. Because if we<br />
didn't have high interest rates now the economy would<br />
collapse like it did under the Liberals in 1981 when we had<br />
the worst recession in 50 years. So yes risks, and what's<br />
required is policies we've got them. The other mob are<br />
still talking about doing precisely what they did in<br />
1980/ 81/ 82 which brought the worst recession in history. So<br />
risks yes, but we've got the policies to deal with them.<br />
CARLTON: Here in Sydney the first home buyer they say is<br />
now an extinct species.<br />
PM: Well just let me give you the statistics on that.<br />
Under the first home buyers scheme, First Home Owners<br />
Scheme, we will be spending $ 17814 this year and there'll be<br />
40,000 new home buyers just under that scheme, under our<br />
scheme. I mean it just isn't right to say that, talking<br />
about our country as a whole, the first home buyer is<br />
extinct. The problem is, part of the problem is that the<br />
level of home building activity has reached the highest<br />
point that it has reached in our history. We've got to<br />
scale it back. True it is, true it is that in Sydney there<br />
are particular difficulties but with the co-operation of the<br />
States where I called the State Premiers together there<br />
two months ago we are now adopting policies in regard to<br />
land release, which is you know the central part of the<br />
problem, which through time will start to ease those<br />
pressures. But you're quite right and I appreciate the<br />
problems that are facing a number of people in Sydney.<br />
Could I just say this Mike, I want to say to your listeners,<br />
I spend you know the great majority of my time thinking<br />
about these issues. What are the things that we can do to<br />
try and make it easier in tough times? We don't want to<br />
have interest rates higher for one day longer than they have<br />
to be. But I want your listeners to understand that in this<br />
situation where we are importing so much compared to what<br />
we're exporting, if we didn't have tight monetary policy, if<br />
we ease things off what would happen is that the dollar<br />
would just collapse and in those situations you would have<br />
then interest rates going through the roof, the total<br />
economy would collapse. I honestly believe that with some<br />
restraint at this time we are going to be able to come<br />
through this in a way which will enable us to keep<br />
employment growth and the economy going. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
