<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8585</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, TH HON P J KEATING MP AND THE MINISTER FOR EMPLOYMENT, EDUCATION AND TRAINING THE HON K BEAZLEY MP PRESS CONFERENCE 21 JULY 1992</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/07/1992</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008585.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
AND THE MINISTER FOR EMPLOYMENT, EDUCATION TRAINING,<br />
THE HON K. BEAZLEY MP<br />
PRESS CONFERENCE, 21 JULY 1992<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY ONLY<br />
PM: Well over the years I think some of us have come to<br />
you and said that we have used the term " truly<br />
historic agreements"' but on this occasion it is an<br />
entirely true description that what we have<br />
completed with the States in a very cooperative<br />
manner is truly a historic agreement which will<br />
change the nature of vocational education in<br />
Australia forever anai hil' give9at least half of the<br />
school leavers of this country a third route to<br />
education and training. That is, after high school<br />
and universitf-s, another route to education and<br />
training. And we have come from a position where<br />
three years ago the Commonwealth virtually knew very<br />
little about TAFE or about the training and<br />
vocational education paths and we have come from a<br />
position where we have been, as a Commonwealth, a<br />
Government topping up State funds for TAFE to now<br />
building on the One Nation p~ roposals thfirou~ gh this<br />
mechanism to build a truly national training<br />
authority where the States manage the operational<br />
basis of the TAFE systems, but where national policy<br />
is set by a Ministerial Council and where funding<br />
both State and Commonwealth is paid at a national<br />
training authority to be funded by interstate<br />
training authorities. And I think what will happen<br />
is that as a result that we will be able to build<br />
proper training profiles for State TAFE institutions<br />
to reflect the needs of the labour market and the<br />
young people of this country. I would like to pay<br />
tribute to the cooperative approach of the Premiers.<br />
This had to be of its essence, a cooperative matter.<br />
The States spend upwards of $ 2 billion a year on<br />
technical and further education. The Commonwealth<br />
spends a comparatively small amount with the States,<br />
but that will now grow as the One Nation money is<br />
committed to it. And that is why there was never a </p>
<p>possibility of the Commonwealth taking over the<br />
system as to funding and as to policy. There always<br />
had to be a cooperative arrangement in running the<br />
system with national objectives and national focus.<br />
And even though this negotiation has not been easy<br />
it has been cooperative and can I say that as late<br />
as last Friday, Kim met with the NSW Premier and<br />
came to an agreement which was ratified today by the<br />
NSW Cabinet and that was the last and the major<br />
State to come to the agreement and he gave me the<br />
cheery news by car phone on Friday, hurtling back<br />
from Mr Fahey's home. So it has been quite a long<br />
process, but on the part of all the States, a degree<br />
of good will to arrive at something good for the<br />
country, for the nation, for the young people of<br />
this country and for those adults in the community<br />
who wish to extend their own training and open up<br />
vocational opportunities for themselves. So I would<br />
with those few opening words, invite Kim Beazley. to<br />
address himself to the issue in general -anid some of<br />
the more detailed issues which flesh out some of the<br />
powers of the body, etc.<br />
KB: Could I say at the outset this is the sort of<br />
agreement that can only be negotiated between Prime<br />
Ministers and Premiers, it is not an agreement that<br />
you would ever reach by a decision making process<br />
involving directly the line departments. And that<br />
is fundamentally because it is a substantial shift.<br />
It is of a piece, I think, with the decisions by the<br />
uCnoimvmeornswietailetsh. to Iet ffise ctoif veal yp ietcaek e wiotvhe r t funddeicnigs iofon by<br />
thidbmmnweaith to become the principal funding-_<br />
source of the private school system in the country<br />
were both essenilly initfiativesg-taken some<br />
considerable period of time ago. And like those<br />
initiatives in their different ways, this outcome is<br />
essentially the sort of outcome that you would<br />
expect to see in a Federal system, and a Federal<br />
system which awards the principal role in decision<br />
making on education matters to State authorities.<br />
This is the general point that I make, and<br />
appropriately the running on this as far as the<br />
Commonwealth side of the issue was concerned was by<br />
the principal officials in the Prime Minister's<br />
_ department and in the Prime Miftiste'-s' offie-bon<br />
Russell. As far as the material that is before you<br />
1Is cocerned, I draw attention to these features.<br />
Firstly, it establishes a meaningful process to get<br />
in place a set of national strategies, national<br />
objectives and national planning, is the first point<br />
that I would make. The second point that I would<br />
make on it, it establishes a process of<br />
accountability which ensures when we go through with<br />
each of the States from the training authority<br />
profiling on the needs of the totality of their<br />
vocational education and training systems, it is not<br />
just about TAFE, it is broader than that. As they </p>
<p>establish those profiles they will do so in<br />
accordance with policy set, in the first instance by<br />
the Ministerial Council advised by ANTA, and they<br />
will have an accountability also frithe operations<br />
of the system not just to ANTA but also to their own<br />
State ministries. Thus also will proceed the<br />
activities of the State Training Boards and I think<br />
that, as I said, the complexity of this as well as<br />
the elements of its simplicity reflect the nature of<br />
our federal system. I think another point that I<br />
would make on that is the question of effort, which<br />
I think is terribly important. In here there is a<br />
guarantee from the States that they will maintain<br />
effort as far as their training activities are<br />
concerned. Now exactly how that is defined in terms<br />
of both outcomes and financial arrangements will of<br />
course be discussed through with the individual<br />
States via the Ministerial Council process and via<br />
ANTA, but that is a very important first commitment.<br />
What it means is that the additional Commonwealth<br />
resources which come in over the years are not<br />
dissipated and there will be, therefore, genuine<br />
growth in the system as a result of the decisions<br />
taken here today. There is also an agreement that<br />
once those definitions are arrived at on effort that<br />
States which are not performing to that effort will<br />
from their own resources, not from the resources<br />
that are coming through from the Commonwealth, will<br />
meet those from their own resources any inadequacies<br />
as far as that effort is concerned. As far as the<br />
Commonwealth is concerned, we are agreeing via this<br />
to put all the sorts of long-term training funds<br />
that we have been operating on our own to this<br />
point, for various purposes sometimes cajoling<br />
industry into an effort, sometimes cajoling the<br />
States into an effort, using the sort of seed money<br />
method of the Commonwealth trying to have an<br />
influence over a national agenda, we do effectively<br />
surrender those positions and the Commonwealth<br />
resources are put into the National Training<br />
Authority. And we will seek in the main though we<br />
maintain our own labour market programs, in the main<br />
we will seek, as the States will seek, to exercise<br />
policy influence in this area via the processes in<br />
the Ministerial Council and the National Training<br />
Authority. Finally, the National Training Authority<br />
is to be an authority which is biased in its<br />
decision making processes very much towards the<br />
needs of industry in terms of the training outcomes<br />
and requirements that operate both on the State<br />
systems and private providers who are assisted. It<br />
is also an Authority that is there to be an<br />
authority of people with substantial expertise. And<br />
I would believe that over time the Ministerial<br />
Council will find that it is readily accepting of<br />
the sorts of propositions about what ought to be<br />
happening in our national training system that<br />
emanate from this body. There is obviously an </p>
<p>absolu . te requirement on those of us who are<br />
participants in the Ministerial Council to make sure<br />
that we get the personnel to serve on that Board<br />
that delivers that sort of outcome.<br />
PM: Why don't we leave it to you to put questions.<br />
J: Prime Minister, if all were to go well, what would a<br />
TAFE look like in say, ten years from now. Would it<br />
be of the European polytechnic style?<br />
PM: Well I think the objective would be to lift it to a<br />
status which is the kind of status enjoyed by the<br />
urpajpolytechnics. That is, as the national and<br />
State traihing-pi6if. s are implemented, as the<br />
resources are committed, as the status and quality<br />
of the system rises, that must inevitably be the<br />
outcome. Because we can't truly create a third path<br />
in there without such a system. I have said before,<br />
that Australia in a sense faces a training emergency<br />
if it wants to be the kind of clever country it<br />
needs to be and this has started, of course, by this<br />
Government lifting those retention rates in<br />
secondary school from three in ten to seven in ten,<br />
making the tertiary places available and now picking<br />
up the other system, TAFE, and giving it some<br />
national structure and status. And that is why I<br />
think that this body is a historic change, I mean,<br />
Kim has compared it to the Commonwealth funding of<br />
universities or the funding of the private schools<br />
system, it is of that status. But again, it will<br />
have that can-do quality about it where the States<br />
and State Minister will still have the touch on the<br />
system at the local level but where the bigger<br />
national priorities are being brought to the policy<br />
of the institutions.<br />
J: Prime Minister, you said in your opening remarks<br />
that Commonwealth takeover of TAFE was quote never a<br />
possibility. Isn't that exactly what you proposed<br />
in your Sunday Program appearance?<br />
PM: Yes. I put the proposition to them that we take it<br />
over as to policy and as to funds. They wouldn't<br />
have that. They wouldn't accept that. That is, for<br />
the growth money that we were adding to the system,<br />
they thought it was not reasonable for us to subsume<br />
funding and control for the vast block of funds they<br />
put to the system. The One Nation proposition was<br />
Commonwealth growth funding, joint control. The<br />
Sunday television performance proposition was an<br />
offer of total Commonwealth control. Now Victoria<br />
wanted to agree to that, for instance. One State<br />
wanted to agree to that, Commonwealth control of<br />
Commonwealth funds. We may have ended up with two<br />
States in it, but we wouldn't have got all the<br />
States. Whereas I think what we have here is<br />
something which everybody can sign up to and where </p>
<p>we are going to get those national objectives down<br />
into the system and where the States feel they have<br />
got a legitimate role in it and where the balance of<br />
roles is played out in that Ministerial Council.<br />
J: Could you just elaborate a bit, Mr Keating, on what<br />
the balance of roles will be in the Ministerial<br />
Council between the Commonwealth, the States,<br />
employers and unions and so forth?<br />
PM: Well, first of all there is a simple majority in<br />
decisions on the Ministerial Council. Each State,<br />
each Territory is represented with one vote<br />
regardless of size, so the ACT has a vote as against<br />
NSW, and the Commonwealth has two votes and a<br />
casting vote. So it gives the Commonwealth a fair<br />
bit of leverage in the system. But again, that is<br />
pretty much as we have it in some of the other fora<br />
we meet the States in. But invariably votes are<br />
never taken. Most of these things run by agreement.<br />
This, as Kim said, will be run by a professional<br />
body of acknowledged experts, they will be the<br />
people largely making the policy and the Ministerial<br />
Council is relevant in a sense in the event of a<br />
dispute between a State Minister and the Authority,<br />
then the Ministerial Council prevails. Now this may<br />
happen, but the likelihood is that the body will run<br />
by agreement.<br />
J: Mr Keating you said that the Federal money is<br />
channelled through this Authority. If in the event<br />
the Federal Government did not agree with the<br />
Ministerial Council's decisions or priorities, if<br />
the States jacked up against it, does the Federal<br />
Government keep to itself the right not to put in<br />
that money?<br />
PM: It puts in money for its commitment, the growth<br />
money of vocational education.<br />
J: you mention the -la-bour market, Commonwealth<br />
labour market programs, will you be maintaining your<br />
existing funding and putting it on top of the One<br />
Nation funds or will it come out of the One Nation?<br />
KB: Basically those aspects that are concerned with<br />
vocational education and training arrangements of a<br />
long term nature directly, like for example the<br />
funds which we will ultimately commit to the<br />
Carmicheal processes will go through this Authority,<br />
as well as what we specifically put down for<br />
vocational education and training. But where, for<br />
example there is a requirement to immediately meet a<br />
particular problem which emerges from the recession<br />
for example, the sort of job training type<br />
activities, then the Commonwealth keeps those<br />
resources-discrete. The objective here is not to </p>
<p>put through the process what the Commonwealth has to<br />
do from time to time to address a particular labour<br />
market problem is to put all the long term money<br />
through that process. So it will at the end of the<br />
day be more than just the funding that's been<br />
committed for training in regard to TAFE. Now of<br />
course there are a series of issues that are likely<br />
to arise from this, and the nuts and bolts detail we<br />
will have to discuss through with the States at the<br />
same time for example we are discussing through with<br />
the States the actual fine detail of the term<br />
effort, the maintenance of effort. But our<br />
disposition is, and indeed our agreement is, that<br />
effectively all the training money for long term<br />
activities will go through this way.<br />
J: How much money are you looking at there to give the<br />
KB: Well, those are budget matters that I'm talking<br />
through with my colleagues at the moment and I'm not<br />
going to foreshadow. But it will end up at the end<br />
of the day over the 18 months before this finally<br />
gets up and operating you'll see in this document<br />
here there are particular elements of a timetable in<br />
it. Now it will end up effectively at the end of<br />
the day more than the growth money that we're<br />
talking about.<br />
J: Is there any particular formula for dividing the<br />
Commonwealth component of the funding between the<br />
States or could that change from year to year<br />
depending of perceived needs?.<br />
KB: It's basically in the first going to be divided per<br />
capita, but subsequent propositions will from the<br />
States, will of course be entertained by the<br />
Ministerial Council and the Board and be subject to<br />
their recommendations.<br />
J: Mr Keating you said in your statement there'll be<br />
more opportunities for young people. Can you<br />
quantify that? How many extra job training places<br />
or whatever would emerge in the decade?<br />
PM: Well there's roughly half of the school leavers do<br />
not undertake further training. In part this is<br />
because the system is not geared up to take them.<br />
It's 130,000. Now obviously no system comprehends<br />
taking everybody up, but this system over time<br />
should take a large proportion of them up. I mean<br />
this is a route and branch change of the education<br />
system of Australia.<br />
KB: Some time ago a shortfall of I think it was,<br />
identified a shortfall of about 150,000 places in<br />
TAFE, some of that has been addressed by things<br />
already done but by and large that shortfall </p>
<p>remains. It would be our intention over several<br />
triennials, in accordance with the Finn timetable,<br />
to eliminate that.<br />
J: Mr Beazley process of what you call effective<br />
training market does that<br />
KB: I can't hear you<br />
J: You contemplate the process of what you call an<br />
effective training market, I wonder whether you<br />
could explain what you mean by an effective training<br />
market. Does that take into account some sort of<br />
voucher stem or some sort of provision of funding<br />
so that both private and public sector institutions<br />
can battle for the public purse?<br />
KB: No, not a voucher system, you'd be aware that we do<br />
provide resources now, and so do the States, for<br />
training activities, in fact we buy places for<br />
training activities in private providers. Now we<br />
would want to leave ANTA and indeed if you read<br />
through the materials here it is suggestive of it,<br />
we would want to leave ANTA with, and the States<br />
want us to do this too this is no big deal as far as<br />
we're concerned, leave room for them to make<br />
recommendations about where the location of<br />
particular training activities ought to be. And<br />
this in-part reflects the industry bias that I said<br />
at the outset was associated with this. It is quite<br />
obvious now that a large number of industries are<br />
beginning to get themselves very active in providing<br />
facilities and opportunities in training programs<br />
and to develop a view about what should actually be<br />
provided indeed there fund skills centres in TAFEs<br />
conform precisely to what their needs would be. So<br />
what this does basically is give this body authority<br />
to operate across the board and put their money into<br />
the profiling process into any particular process<br />
they like. It doesn't mean that we're going to<br />
introduce voucher systems, I think that's a terribly<br />
old fashion way of talking about education and to<br />
carry over from the'way in which people used to talk<br />
about what ought to be done in the secondary school<br />
system, I think what this does is give us<br />
flexibility for more active industry involvement.<br />
J: One of the criticisms that industry makes of the<br />
existing TAFE structure is that the products, if you<br />
like, of the TAFE system are not geared or cannot<br />
dove tail with industries expectations. How will<br />
that improve under this new system?<br />
PM: Well part of the point of this is to construct a<br />
training profile which does reflect labour market<br />
realities and demands and the demands of industry<br />
and that's why on ANTA itself we should hope to have<br />
people who have that industry perspective and </p>
<p>experience so that the body does function to look<br />
after the needs of clients to the system rather than<br />
perhaps service providers. Which has been one of<br />
the criticisms of the existing TAFE system.<br />
J: Has industry been sufficiently specific about what<br />
it actually wants, where it wants to end up?<br />
PM: Well in some cases, in some cases to the point where<br />
we are actually currently contributing to joint<br />
training arrangements with particular companies or<br />
industry sectors. I mean I think industry is very<br />
much attune to the needs of the training market and<br />
what such a body could do and I'm quite sure that<br />
they will be very clear in putting a view as to what<br />
ANTA is capable of doing.<br />
KB: ITAB the Industry Training Advisory Boards are to<br />
some degrie subsumed by this process. The pilot in<br />
process is associated with Carmichael are going to<br />
heavily involve industry in defining in what it<br />
needs in terms of the non-industry training<br />
provision and all of that over time is going to be<br />
effectively overseen by the processes entailed in<br />
this document.<br />
J: Just on Carmichael Mr Keating's statement yesterday<br />
indicatea' tat _ the Carmichael scheme would take<br />
quite some time to get up and running. Could you<br />
give us some idea of the scopes that you see to get<br />
that started say next year how many people<br />
would be involved say in one year or three years<br />
out?<br />
KB: I think you should let us reserve something for the<br />
Youth Summit and the employment package in the<br />
budget.<br />
PM: In my view it might be worth while just walking you<br />
through a couple of the key points in here which,<br />
just to focus you in, the first the objectives are<br />
the objectives which we committed ourselves to in<br />
the statement yesterday in terms of national<br />
training authority objectives, the first lot of<br />
objectives. If you turn to page 2 you'll see under<br />
State training agencies, with responsibility for<br />
vocational education training within their own<br />
borders consistent with the agreed emphasis on<br />
agreed national strategic plan on training policy<br />
and the agreed State planning profile, not the<br />
relevant or something but the agreed State planning<br />
profile. State training agencies will be<br />
accountable to State Ministers and Parliaments for<br />
the operation responsibilities of their agencies and<br />
accountable to the Ministerial Council on matters on<br />
National policy. Now that link re-appears on page 3<br />
at the bottom, Ministerial Council, the last dot<br />
point, to determine national goals, objectives and </p>
<p>priorities for vocational education and training, on<br />
page 4, the fourth dot point, to agree planning<br />
parameters and profiles for delivery of vocational<br />
education and training nationally and the sixth dot<br />
point, to resolve any dispute between ANTA and a<br />
State training agency or any other issue raised by a<br />
Minister. So in other words the Ministerial Council<br />
resolves a dispute between ANTA and a State training<br />
authority and a State Minister, and of course in the<br />
resolution of that dispute the Commonwealth sits<br />
there with two votes in the casting vote. Page<br />
one, two, three, four, fifth dot point, to develop<br />
in conjunction with State training agencies an<br />
efficient and quality service provision, so even in<br />
an operational sense ANTA has a specific power to<br />
develop in conjunction with training agencies and<br />
efficient and quality service provision, that is the<br />
quality of operation the distinguishing feature<br />
between operations and policy where that may be<br />
blurred as we all know in public administration, in<br />
any administration it can be blurred that while<br />
primarily operations resile with State training<br />
authorities ANTA is in there expressly in relation<br />
to efficiency and quality of the delivery of<br />
services, so it has again an express role. On<br />
page 6 at 11, dot points one and two, to provide to<br />
ANTA policy advice, so State training agencies<br />
provide policy advice and develop in conjunction<br />
with ANTA detailed State training profiles. And on<br />
page 8 at point 31 under Funding Arrangements, the<br />
States will at least maintain their effort for<br />
vocational education and training on an ongoing<br />
basis, in other words there's the maintenance there<br />
of State effort, but when we move to outcomes on<br />
page 9 we say any state which is demonstratively<br />
under-achieving would agree to increase its efforts,<br />
so it's not as if the Commonwealth then picks up the<br />
under-achievers, as we did with Universities, with<br />
Universities what we had to do was when they were<br />
flagging behind the Commonwealth had to pick them<br />
up, this is not the case here. And they're the main<br />
points.<br />
J: Prime Minister, I mean for example, if the<br />
Commonwealth decided that in order to rebuild<br />
Victoria's manufacturing base you needed to up their<br />
contribution to their TAFE system and the smaller<br />
States decided this was unfair for whatever variety<br />
of reasons isn't it conceivable that national<br />
objective could be overturned by a combination of<br />
the smaller States?<br />
PM: I don't think so.<br />
KB: At the moment now this has enormous focus because it<br />
really has required the Prime Minister and Premiersto<br />
break it all through. There's just no question<br />
about that. You can't make a shift like this </p>
<p>without the heads of the Governments of this country<br />
being involved. This program as it builds up with a<br />
very authoritative Board, well supported by<br />
industry. We'll sink back, not sink back that's a<br />
bad expression to use, we'll return to the<br />
activities of the line Departments, and they just<br />
basically don't operate that way. I mean I've had a<br />
couple of experiences now of so called MOVIC<br />
ministerial meetings which will effectively be the<br />
Council the Ministerial Council and we rely very<br />
heavily on the advice of our officials in an<br />
organisation called VTAC which supports MOVIC.<br />
There'll obviously in this particular instance be a<br />
lot of discussion around the funding formula and<br />
it's quite possible the funding formula will<br />
continue from time to time to be of very direct<br />
interest, but the way in which the profiles are<br />
developed, over time, more and more expertise will<br />
come to play in this. The idea I think of the sort<br />
of States ganging up to roll the Commonwealth and<br />
another couple of States I think is just outside the<br />
framework of how those operations take place, it's<br />
just not a people can invent sort of thin edge<br />
of the wedge arguments about anything associated<br />
with any part of our federation but I think the<br />
practicalities of life mean that on a day to day<br />
basis that sort of thing just won't happen.<br />
PM: The reason I walked you through the document a<br />
moment ago was just to demonstrate the sort of<br />
tension, the creative tension that's in the design,<br />
that is that prerogatives of the States and the<br />
Commonwealth and the national interests here are I<br />
think, set nicely in balance. I noticed in the<br />
Australian newspaper today someone was sold a pup.<br />
You can sell people pups easily around this<br />
building, on the basis that this was a sort of walk<br />
over for the States. Well if you just go through<br />
those points you'll see where the national<br />
where ANTA's powers are clear and where the<br />
ministerial powers are clear in resolving disputes<br />
between States, training agencies, ministers and<br />
ANTA, where States have to maintain their financial<br />
effort, where the Commonwealth will not be bringing<br />
up under performing States.<br />
J: Will this do anything for the jobless?<br />
PM: Who wrote the Aus story, by the way? Sorry, my<br />
apologies.<br />
J: In the short term could this tell us the number of<br />
unemployed young youth places will be<br />
available next year when it becomes...?<br />
KB: Well, yes I think it will. I think that the growth<br />
money, given that it is going in on the basis that<br />
the States maintain effort, will allow a pretty </p>
<p>substantial addressing of those sorts of<br />
requirements. I think Dave Phillips 100 million<br />
provided about 30,000 places, 30,000 to 40,000<br />
places from recollection. So, that came through in<br />
the last set of money so you can, on the basis of<br />
that, start calculating what 70 million next year<br />
will do, what 140 million the year after will do and<br />
being able to plan with 70 million knowing you are<br />
getting 140 million. I think that what this will<br />
provide is a very substantial ballast to back up<br />
other elements of the labour market program, which<br />
we will be bringing forward as short-term measures<br />
to deal with the unemployment problems, where they<br />
require a TAFE element to the resolution. An awful<br />
lot of Commonwealth training programs, not just TAFE<br />
but also private provider elements. An awful lot of<br />
Commonwealth short-term labour market programs<br />
require access to TAFE provision. Now this will<br />
massively increase the compacity of TAFE and the<br />
private providers to back those programs up. So,<br />
without wishing to identify, because you can't place<br />
by place, a resolution, the capacity to support<br />
other elements to the labour market programs put<br />
people in training, take them out of an area of just<br />
hopeless unproductive unemployment. It is a massive<br />
effective back-up to that.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
KB: Well it will have its own act, we will have to<br />
legislate to establish a separate Commonwealth<br />
training authority in conformity with the conditions<br />
that are laid down here. There will be, of course,<br />
a requirement for us to also pass, as we always do,<br />
a vocational education and training act with<br />
what we don't do now but will do next time, is<br />
with a triennial funding base in it and then there<br />
will be a cross-over between those two Acts. Now<br />
the one act will give the Commonwealth Minister<br />
authorities to dispense funds and the other Act<br />
would oblige the Commonwealth Minister to dispense<br />
funds in accordance with this agreement.<br />
J: bodies in terms of accountability will go to, for<br />
instance, the Senate Estimates Committees?<br />
KB: Yes, as with all areas of my portfolio, and indeed<br />
as the statutory authorities have found from time to<br />
time they will find themselves explaining life to<br />
the Senate Estimates Committees.<br />
J: Prime Minister you nominated the Finn Committee<br />
yesterday in your background paper o-n take-up rates<br />
for TAFE, 15-19 year olds, have you any idea about<br />
how much additional spending over and above the $ 720<br />
million that will require to achieve that sort of<br />
objective? </p>
<p>PM: No, I mean you could have a stab at it, but I think<br />
the point was the Finn and Deveson Committee smoked<br />
out what the Commonwealth needed to have smoked out<br />
about the way the TAFE system functions in this<br />
country, and to focus on long term pathways for the<br />
transition from school to work. Now, that's where<br />
we started it, we then got into the act with capital<br />
and recurrent, we then added to that with the One<br />
Nation money and we have now taken it up for this.<br />
So, all the things which Kim ( Beazely) is doing now<br />
with Carmichael, those long lines of transition<br />
between school and work really couldn't be, I don't<br />
think, over time anyway, successfully accomplished<br />
without ballast in this system. That's going to<br />
cost money and the growth is obviously going to come<br />
from the Commonwealth, I mean, the Commonwealth over<br />
time will be spending more then the One Nation money<br />
on vocational education.<br />
J: interface between employers and training,<br />
getting people trained for jobs. Obviously an<br />
important part of that is going to be on the job<br />
training and related to that the issue of a training<br />
wage. Is it your objective, in the discussions you<br />
will have tomorrow, to get a broad agreement on the<br />
structure of<br />
PM: I think Kim made the point earlier we are not here<br />
portending tomorrow's outcome, or trying to secondguess<br />
them, that's for you to do.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well that is just another way of asking the same<br />
question. Which I got on to in about 3<br />
milliseconds. And I hope within 5 milliseconds to<br />
put an answer back to you saying that is what he<br />
asked.<br />
J: could have a role to play in whatever is decided<br />
in the context of the Carmichael?<br />
PM: Look, let's face this fact, the truth is that in the<br />
growth of the labour market in the ' 80s a lot of the<br />
problems of the transition from school to work, for<br />
untrained people, was overlooked in the great sweep<br />
of employment through the ' 80s. Not by us in terms<br />
of getting the stock of trained people up, obviously<br />
through participation and in the first instance in<br />
tertiary where we had a clear Commonwealth financial<br />
responsibility. But we are taking that further, to<br />
make that transition between schools and work<br />
through vocational education and the pathways which<br />
are comprehended in the Carmichael recommendations,<br />
which Kim has been trying to work through to some<br />
sort of conclusion, that is transferring a report in<br />
to policy. It is there that this matters, it is<br />
there that we will look immediately beyond, as I </p>
<p>said yesterday, in the two things, the first is that<br />
big transition from school to work, and the other<br />
for those teenagers whose later teenage years will<br />
have preceded as fundamental change, those who<br />
are currently unemployed. Now, that's the problem<br />
we will be focussing on tomorrow, and also those<br />
people where with this in place or not in place will<br />
just never take up structured training there will<br />
always be a proportion of people who will never take<br />
up structured training and trying to find a role for<br />
them as well, that's in a sense what Geoff was<br />
asking me about earlier, and which we will be trying<br />
to at least focus upon tomorrow.<br />
J . I mean if it was a long term structural<br />
decline in those types of jobs, I mean how<br />
PM: Well I don't want to go through all that today,<br />
that's for tomorrow.<br />
J: ( inaudible)<br />
KB: Yes, I agree with you that there is a problem there,<br />
but I think it is changing, I think there is a<br />
growing realization that technical and further<br />
education does provide you with a type of education<br />
most likely to be directly related to employment.<br />
Now, as I think as other elements of the agenda<br />
start to impact like the Carmichael proposals, like<br />
the increasing involvement in, for example, of<br />
industries and creation of things like skill centres<br />
of which there have been some forty odd created over<br />
the last few years. As this all begins to come<br />
through what a young person looking at their life<br />
after secondary school has before them is the<br />
prospect of some very highly relevant, well<br />
structured, certificated forms of training open to<br />
them and many may well chose, I think, presented<br />
with that and with a qualitative improvement that<br />
always invariably comes with more money, will look<br />
at a really genuine choice. I think you will find<br />
parental attitudes change, and I think you will find<br />
young peoples attitudes change when confronted with<br />
that, but it will take a couple of years.<br />
PM: And the hobby courses have been stripped out of the<br />
system and the focus only with apprenticeships is<br />
changing and that's why the State training profiles<br />
are going to matter enormously. Because that's<br />
where the status will be, it is with them that will<br />
come the status, but the point I made earlier is the<br />
key point I think, that is it is the bigger issue of<br />
the transition from school to work, which Kim is<br />
working on, which is the issue. This is part of the<br />
facilitation mechanism of that.<br />
J: Why did you describe it as a training emergency? </p>
<p>PM: Because I think that the nature of the economy we<br />
are going to have, the nature of investment in the<br />
1990s is going to be not chasing inflationary gains<br />
but chasing production, that is, we will be looking<br />
at product, product innovation and exports, import<br />
replacement, and it is going to require, that<br />
structure, more trained people than we have been<br />
able to provide in the past and particularly more<br />
jobs for people who are trained as distinct from<br />
those who are untrained.<br />
KB: My department estimates that 80 per cent of the jobs<br />
which will come into our commnunity between now and<br />
the end of the decade will require year 12 standard<br />
of education or above, in order to fill it. We are<br />
not yet at a position where we could say that we are<br />
necessarily meeting those targets, and in those<br />
circumstances that requires activity on our part.<br />
PM: I think one of Australia's great comparative<br />
advantages has been education. In the last 25 years<br />
we let that slip, and to climb back up the<br />
international division of labour we have to reassert<br />
again that comparative advantage. And this<br />
is about some of that re-assertion.<br />
J: Is it your intention to have a national<br />
certification system for TAFE?<br />
KB: Well, of course those sorts or issues are going to<br />
be the life blood of ANTA, the attitudes and the<br />
views that they develop on that over time will be<br />
very important. And as in virtually all other areas<br />
of education, people looking at issues of national<br />
certification, I think in this circumstance industry<br />
is so diverse that you are more likely to sort of<br />
get national recognition of forms of certification,<br />
as opposed to national certification that's more or<br />
less what we are aiming at at this stage, I think<br />
the other objective would be, as they used to say in<br />
the Indian newspapers when I worked there, in<br />
its tendencies.<br />
PM: That will send everyone back to the dictionaries.<br />
J: any of the logistics, like where this is going<br />
to be headquartered and those sort of things?<br />
KB: We haven't worked out headquarters yet, that will be<br />
a matter for the board, the authority.<br />
J: How big a constraint is the fact that the TAFE<br />
systems have a lot of people in them who are<br />
permanent staff who are teaching things of less and<br />
less relevance?<br />
PM: Well that's part of the system, isn't<br />
it, I mean that is what it is about, in part. </p>
<p>J: So some of the money can be used to redundancy<br />
packages etc, etc?<br />
KB: Well I am not sure about that. I think that<br />
basically what is happening in the States at the<br />
moment is a serious addressing of those problems<br />
now. That is happening all over the country, it is<br />
not a problem which has been ignored hitherto,<br />
people have got on to it. I think there is<br />
obviously going to have to be as curicula as changed<br />
as a result of all these investigatory processes and<br />
this process itself. Then there is going to have to<br />
be a considerable amount of re-training for some<br />
teaches and all of them to be able to deliver the<br />
outcomes that people want. But it is premature to<br />
talk about the resources being used in any specific<br />
set of programs to address any individual teachers<br />
problems at this point.<br />
PM: Look, can I just say it is always a pretty good<br />
indication when some of you leave you have had<br />
enough, so I think we will leave to.<br />
ENDS </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
