<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>461</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS CONFERENCE GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G MENZIES AT CANBERRA, ON THURSDAY, 8TH FEBRUARY, 1962 , AT 3 P.M</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/02/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000461_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS CCNFERENCE GIVIEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER9<br />
THE RT. HON. R. G. i4ENZIES, AT CANBERRA, ON<br />
THURSDAY, 8TH FEBRUARY. 1962, AT 3 P. M.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, Mr. Calwell appears to have made a take-over<br />
bid, and he gives the impression he doesn't think much<br />
of you. Will you reply to him?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: ; Well as far as my memory can carry me, he's made<br />
a take-over bid every day sinc. the election. It's<br />
been very interesting. This time he seems to have<br />
excelled himself because yesterday he announced to the<br />
Press that there was nothing new about my statement,<br />
it was the same old policy. But today, no doubt having<br />
taken counsel with his principal advisers, he has<br />
decided the opposite. Uell, I must leave it to him to<br />
find it out for himself. I am deeply concerned about<br />
what we are doing ourselves.<br />
QUESTION: Who do you think would be his principal advisers?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I should think the Sydney Morning Herald. That<br />
seems a reasonable guess together with its juvenile<br />
child.<br />
QUESTION: Would you care to comment on his claim that your<br />
statement adol Labour's Election Policy, and even<br />
takes it farther, Sir?<br />
PRIME MTNTST. R: I don't think it does. I thought my statement was<br />
very plain. I pointed out the results that had been<br />
achieved by our policy, and then went on to say I<br />
thought categorically that the results that I<br />
indicated had happened, or had been achieved, in the<br />
trade balances, in the consumer price index and in the<br />
Loan Market, were good. Then I went on to say we<br />
acknowledged the promise of recovery which appeared<br />
late last year had not been realised sufficiently in<br />
practical results, and that it must now be promoted<br />
with greater speed. I referred to the problems; and I<br />
referred to what we were going to do; Our proposals will<br />
stand or fall on their own merits.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, on that basis of price stability do you<br />
regard your present short-term programme of making<br />
available something like œ 70m. in the cash stream in the<br />
next four months as being inflationary, or likely to be<br />
inflationary?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It depends entirely on what the results are. If,<br />
in fact, not in a hurry it won't happen tomorrow<br />
morning or something of that kind but if, over the<br />
next few months there is a material iiqrovement in the<br />
employment position then that won't be inflationary:<br />
that will represent the taking up of what, at present,<br />
are unused resources. And that is what we are hoping<br />
because that would help to produce, or to<br />
re-introduce, a state of normality not a state of<br />
infation, but a state of reasonable normality, And as<br />
we thought that ought to be encouraged to continue, and<br />
the wday to help it continue was to relate your shortterm<br />
measures to a restoration of confidence in the<br />
community, we are hoping that there will be a<br />
sufficient restoration of continuity to carry the<br />
cormmuunity along without a constant repetition of<br />
injections. Here is a particular injection for a<br />
particular purpose.<br />
mr* </p>
<p>QUESTION: Does this mean, as some have suggested, that the<br />
Government is more interested in economic growth than<br />
in stability?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: v'ell, I don't think that it ought to be put in that<br />
fashion. We are essentially interested in economic<br />
growth. Perhaps the great mistake we made in the last<br />
election was to allow ourselves to be represented as<br />
being not interested in econo. ic growth. I made it<br />
quite clear in the Policy Speech that we were but then<br />
an atmosphere developed in which we appeared to be in<br />
favour of some kind of stagnation, not of growth. We<br />
were, and are, emphatically in favour of growth, Ve<br />
don't think that growth is irreconcilable with as I<br />
said in my statement a reasonable degree of stability.<br />
We may have li,: tle fluctuations here or there.<br />
QUESTION: Even though that growth emphasis may mean some<br />
risk in balance of payments, you are still prepared to<br />
take it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, in the present state of affairs you must<br />
accept some risks if you are going to make a sufficient<br />
impact on the current state of the economy to get rid<br />
of these matters that I referred to in my statonent: a<br />
higher rate of unemployment than anybody could<br />
contemplate as acceptable a rate clearly requiring<br />
special measures to get it down. All these things<br />
involve, I suppose, some risks but we are not<br />
incompetent to deal with the risks. We have indicated<br />
that what we want to do is to get rid of this<br />
unemployment and to stimulate confidence in the<br />
community. If, in fact? at some time in the future<br />
and I am not expecting it very soon there were<br />
pressures developing on the economy, then we have<br />
indicated that we intend to deal with those by<br />
specific measures as far as possible, and not by<br />
general ones. I think that is the drift of what I<br />
said the other day.<br />
QU: STION: Have you an estimate of the total cost of your<br />
programme, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, well... you mean in the current financial year?<br />
, Jell let's see. There is, in a direct sense,<br />
for the States, because you remember that we don't<br />
find the money on semi and local government they have<br />
an authority to borrow but coming from us œ 10n. nonrepayable<br />
Grant, œ 5n. advance on Housing. iJell, that's<br />
On the Income Tax concessions I've heard various<br />
estimates running betwTeen œ 25m. and œ 30, m. In the short<br />
run, in the next four months, these other items are not<br />
easily calculated, but I wouldn't think were very<br />
massive in that period. For example, nobody can tell<br />
yet how much will be involved in investment allowances:<br />
it depends entirely on what happens in the manufacturing<br />
field. You can't expect that to happen over-night,<br />
The improvements, particularly the family improvements<br />
and the unemployment benefits, well I don't know, but<br />
again that's not, I would assume, a massive figure<br />
over the next four months.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, it would come down to something like about<br />
to œ 6am?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I wouldn't think more, but I haven't worked it out<br />
with precision. But those figures would represent, I<br />
would think, the top limits. </p>
<p>QUESTION: PRIME MINISTER: Can you be any more specific, Sir, about the<br />
at this stage? Can Queensl. r. d expect special<br />
treatment? Well, there are two propositions we are putting<br />
up. Let's take them in order.<br />
First, œ 5m. on Housing. JeIll, we'll have to<br />
discuss that with the State Pr3miers. I thought it<br />
proper to indicate the total amount, but I don't think<br />
it would be very agreeable to be saying in advance " and<br />
this is how it's going to be distributed". You know<br />
they might perhaps think it's not worthwhile coming.<br />
But we'll have to discuss with them the housing thing,<br />
very largely on the basis of -1hat the needs are in the<br />
various State-, no doubt at least that will be an<br />
important factzr.<br />
As for the œ 1Om. 1 which is a straight-out grant by<br />
the Commonwealth, and quite a substantial one that<br />
being a voluntary grant by us under Section 9 we,<br />
technically, can determine its allocation. Buz we<br />
don't as a rule try to do that we may have to in the<br />
long run. In the past when we have done anything of<br />
this kind we have discussed it with the States, but we<br />
will ourselves indicate what we think are the broad<br />
principles. And as this is to be a grant for<br />
employment-providing activities, then it is quite<br />
obvious that one of the factors, one of the principal<br />
factors, to be taken into account is the relative r7e<br />
of unemployment in the various States. At this time<br />
Queensland, I am informed, has the highest rate of<br />
unemployment. Therefore it is not to be assumed that<br />
we will just distribute this money on a population<br />
basis. This is designed to relieve unemployment, to<br />
enable work to be put in hand swiftly for the relief of<br />
unemployment, and therefore the unemployment position<br />
in each State is a very important factor. VWe have had<br />
a few cases of this kind before in past years. I<br />
remember one I've forgotten what it was about but<br />
one in which we found some extra money. On that<br />
occasion half of it was distributed, according to the<br />
existing formula, and the other half arbitrarily<br />
allocated by the Commonwealth. But I don't prophesy<br />
that. All I want to make quite clear is that the<br />
position of the States with the most serious unemployment<br />
problems will certainly not be overlooked in the<br />
distribution of this sum.<br />
QUESTION: Do you intend, Sir, to try to get that money spent<br />
quickly on small works to take up unemployment in<br />
semi-skilled.....?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, speed is the essence. You see this is a<br />
grant for this financial year, not for the next 18<br />
months or something of that kind; this is a grant for<br />
the remainder of this financial year. The whole idea,<br />
to use the co: mmon phrase, is to give the system a<br />
" shot in the arm" because the employment position has<br />
not turned out to be as satisfactory as we had hoped.<br />
There it is. And it must be improved. And it is very<br />
important, under those circumstances, to make a quick<br />
attack on it. That is why we are concentrating, into<br />
these few months, the amount of money that I have<br />
indicated. Therefore it follows that we are not<br />
looking to the States to say, " Well, this will enable<br />
us to begin planning some long-term operation". We want<br />
jobs in which they can be putting people on the job in<br />
the next week or two. I know there are such jobs in<br />
Queensland because I have been up there; and I have<br />
no doubt there are in other States. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Will you impose any conditions, Sir, as to the<br />
class of works to be undertaken, or will that be left<br />
to the States?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well we haven't discussed this yet, and I don't<br />
like to take up the attitude that we are imposing<br />
something on the States. But it is quite clear that if<br />
the principal object of the exercise is to provide<br />
employment, particularly in places where there are<br />
pockets of unemployment and to do it quickly, then<br />
naturally I would expect everybody to give priority to<br />
works with the highest labour content.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Calwell has also said, Sir, that he is goinj<br />
to force you to an Election as soon as possible.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well I nc-ver doubted it.<br />
QUESTION: Would you care to estimate how soonø..?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. No I haven't a clue, I haven't a clue. But he<br />
would be a very poor Opposition Leader if he didn't<br />
have the ambition to put us out as soon as he could, T<br />
take that for granted. I think it is an admirable . Ji<br />
QUESTION: He has also predicted, Sir, that you won't fight<br />
another " ection?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Has he? Oh, well.... he must think Parliament<br />
going to last a long time.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, coming back to your statement the other<br />
night on the Banking ouestion, you rather suggest that<br />
you are thinking in terms of a more competitive bank. nq<br />
system, perhaps something like the pre-war system. Is<br />
that the kind of thing you have in mind?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Don't broaden this out too much. We saw the<br />
Trading Banks and they had... I said " Wiell now here's<br />
your opportunity to tell us about your problems,<br />
direct, you iknow, where you think the system isn't<br />
working effectively". And broadly speaking there were<br />
two problems that wee under discussion. One was the<br />
interest rate structure. That is not, at present, the<br />
subject of deternination bocause further discussions<br />
are going on in that field, and I don't prophesy what<br />
the result of it will be. But it is not to be assumed<br />
that that matter is disposed of. That remains a matter<br />
of active consideration.<br />
The other one was how far the Trading Banks cald<br />
go into longer term lending. This is of lively<br />
interest, particularly in the country, and, as you<br />
know, arguments have gone on as to whether the Banks<br />
provide finance in country areas to the extent that<br />
they should, or the extent that they can. One of the<br />
reasons why the Develop! ent Bank was established was to<br />
fill in what was thought to be a gap in that field.<br />
Now the Banks themselves are quite interested in this<br />
problem of longer-term lending. And we welcor. D that of<br />
course. But it is early days for them to arrive at a<br />
conclusion. They indicated to us that they were having<br />
discussions about it, and they have confirmed that<br />
since, as I said, in talks with the Treasurer. But I<br />
can't prophesy what the result of this will be. And of<br />
course if it turned out that the Banks found<br />
themselves able to go into longer-term lending in that<br />
way it would be of material advantage to rural<br />
development, and perhaps, to that extent would reduce<br />
the drain on the funds of the Development Bank. Ido krw </p>
<p>that they are interested in that aspect of the matter.<br />
But all that being on the knees of the Gods we are<br />
satisfied that the Development Bank must be able to go<br />
on with its job, and that is why we are providing a<br />
further œ 5m. capital which we will do in the autumn<br />
session. I mean this is not a forecast of the future.<br />
It will be one of the financial measures.<br />
There is one other aspect, you know, of my<br />
announcement the other night I think I ought to refer<br />
to in corxmon justice-to the peuple concerned. I -oted<br />
that in his first lucubration on this matter the<br />
Leader of the Opposition persuaded himself that what<br />
had been done had been done over the bitter hostility<br />
of the Treasury, and the Treasury officials, T Li, I<br />
want to say, is arrant nonsense. ' e had a very<br />
strenuous fortright of consultations which I found<br />
tremendcusly v-. uable. We had the meeting of a small<br />
group of Ministers, first without, and then with<br />
officials, and then we agreed upon recommeniations and<br />
we put them to the Cabinet on Fiiday of last week. And<br />
they were agreed to, after some hours of discussion.<br />
I want to say that the proposals that we evolerc,<br />
and which I subsequently announced, were, so far as<br />
can judge. and I'm not in a bad position to judge<br />
proposals which represented the complete agreement of<br />
all the departments concerned. Certainly, there was no<br />
indication that there was opposition by t he Troasury,<br />
This little bit of underground propaganda that goe: s<br />
to try and create some state of war between the<br />
Department of Trade and the Treasury is just nonsenc.-'. e.,<br />
utter nonsense. I thought they all behaved very wel. l<br />
And, of course, naturally, as the proposals that were<br />
announced were entirely agreeable to me who wrote t<br />
down I felt they were all very intelligent by produclJ..<br />
unanimity on then.<br />
QUESTION: Is the investment allowance intended to be a<br />
permanent reasure Sir?<br />
PRTIM MfINTSTR'i: I think you can treat it in that way. In a sense<br />
it may be experimental, but it is not being put on for<br />
some limited period of time. Though, I suppose, from<br />
the point of view of future years something may depend<br />
upon how it works, whether it produces the effect. Of<br />
course, at some time in the future, if it turns out to<br />
be successful, as I think it will be, then the rate is<br />
capable of variation according to the circumstances.<br />
But I want to say that I think Mr. Holt is going to say<br />
something, isn't he, in a supplementary way about the<br />
Investment Allowances, because there are some nice<br />
technical questions that they are working on which<br />
prevent us, at the moment, from putting a specific date<br />
down. We certainly...<br />
QUESTION: I don't think this is a technical question, Sir,<br />
but after a long period of prosperity in which firms<br />
have had an opportunity to build up reserves why has it<br />
become necessary to give them a virtual subsidy to<br />
nodernise their plants?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The great advantage of modernising the plant, from<br />
the point of view of manufacturing, is this: they are<br />
not the masters of the wage structure, they are not the<br />
nasters, overall, of the economic policy, yet they have<br />
to work within those limits, and it is terribly<br />
important that their efficiency be so increased that<br />
they can move more and more into the export field. </p>
<p>6.<br />
The greatest thing to increase the efficiency of highly<br />
mechanised industry like manufacturing is to enable<br />
them to keep abreast of the latest developments and have<br />
the most modern plant. Under the existing scales of<br />
depreciation it is not easy for them to follow that<br />
line because they depreciate, yes, but they depreciate<br />
over a term of years 100% of the particular plant.<br />
They might want, very much before that time is over,<br />
to replace it by something so -much better that if tvey<br />
don't have it their competitors in the world will uat<br />
them out of business. Therefore this is a direct<br />
encouragement to raodernise plant, and thereby to . eep<br />
down unit costs and increase their capacity to<br />
from Australia and their capacity to compete J"-ide.<br />
Australia with goods that come in. We examined this,<br />
it's been und,.. consideration one way or another for<br />
some time, but this time we examined this with<br />
particularity. ; Je saw what was being done in other<br />
countries and we came to the conclusion that what<br />
amounts, in substance, to a subsidy to re-equipment, a<br />
subsidy to modernisation, would be a very, very good<br />
contribution to the efficiency of the industry.<br />
QUESTION: Jouldn't this also tend to encourage investmen;.-;<br />
from overseas in Australian industry?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, well it very well might, it very well migh!:,<br />
I wouldn't distinguish between the two things.<br />
QUESTION: Your statement the other night, Sir, divided yu'r<br />
proposals into two groups, one of which was descri 1..<br />
as short-term, or interim. Is it to be inferred fr,.<br />
that that those proposals may come under review fa<br />
soon, or may they continue?<br />
PRIME MINISTER. Some of them expend themselves in their own<br />
performance, don't they, like the payments to the<br />
States, you see. But the question of income tax, well<br />
I'll say nothing about that at this stage because this<br />
is a matter that we have to consider when we are<br />
approaching our overall annual provisions.<br />
QUESTION: dould that apply to sales tax on cars Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Do you mean will it come on now and go off on<br />
June 30th, or something like that, eh? Or go up?<br />
QUESTION: Should we buy a car now?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Look, I don't think I actually distinguished<br />
sharply between short-term and long-term. I thought I<br />
used a different expression, and I did it deliberately,<br />
to indicate that some of these are designed to produce<br />
quick results, and some of then are designed as a sort<br />
of follow-up, to encourage confidence and restore the<br />
general tone of industry. Apart from those that expend<br />
themselves in their own performance, like the grants to<br />
the States, the others... don't roead any inference into<br />
it at all. They are of quick operation, true, or we<br />
hope so.<br />
QUESTION: You mean we should think in terms of purpose<br />
rather than character?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's right. I can't give you the slightest idea<br />
as to what will happen in the long run on these matters.<br />
We don't put an ear-mark on them and say, " Ucll those<br />
are things that are going to be done and are going to<br />
stop on Juno 30th", or something like that. </p>
<p>QUESTION: Mr, Menzies is there anything you can say on the<br />
Indonesian situation, and ' Jez. New Guinea? Do you think<br />
the situation is easier at all now?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, I wish I knew. In one cable you get a little<br />
optimism about having negotiations; and in the next one<br />
there's no optimism. It depends largely from what side<br />
of the fence the message comes. All I can say is that<br />
we are still hoping that there will be negotiations -; d<br />
not war, because the institution of hostilities 1'.<br />
matter of this kind, in this part of the world, is not<br />
very agreeable to 99 people out of 100, though, I<br />
gather, fondly hoped for by the 100th.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Menzins, there is a Space Club project o.:<br />
way which Britan and France have sponsored and tli:<br />
Australian Govurnment has been asked by France and<br />
Britain to ratify a treaty. Do you know what stage ti: is<br />
has reached?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't, I don't. But Mr. Fairhall may knov, t lake<br />
a chance of asking him. I know in a genera] ; ay ; c.' at<br />
stage they are at, but as to the particular stage-;<br />
the moment, I don't. it hasn't come back to us<br />
final decision.<br />
QJESTION: Going back to Indonesia, Sir, if the Dutch<br />
Government asks for permission to land on AustraliJa:-.<br />
territory, flying these re-inforcements or replacei: 3to. rc<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I never answer hypothetical questions.<br />
QUESTION! Have you had such a request, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Not that I'm aware of, no. But those are matters<br />
you deal with when they arise, if you've got any sense.<br />
QUESTION: Have you had any indication, yet, of the date of<br />
the Prime Ministers' Conference, Sir?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't even know whether there will be one. I've<br />
had no hint of one yet.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Menzies will you move as quickly as possible<br />
after the State Elections in South Australia and Now<br />
South Wales to get this conference going on the<br />
Chowilla Dam?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That's a matter I'm going to have a talk to Sir<br />
Thomas Playford about when he's over here next week.<br />
Personally, I would like to do something. Even if it's<br />
only a preliminary discussion on the matter, I would<br />
like to get it under way. But I will be talking to the<br />
Premier of South Australia about it. He's got an<br />
election coming on hasn't he? Everybody seems to have<br />
an election.<br />
QUESTION: Mr. Calwell referred to the " Menzios myth", Sir...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Did he? But he referred also to the myth of the<br />
boom. Don't you remember? Jell, I'm like the boom in<br />
1960, I'm a myth. 3ut I've been a " myth" for some time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
