<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11325</transcript-id>
    <title>14 March 1999                                                  TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT THE NEW SOUTH WALES LIBERAL PARTY ELECTION CAMPAIGN LAUNCH                                 ST GEORGE LEAGUES CLUB, SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Thank you very much Michael Osborne; to Jeff Kennett, the Premier</p>
<p> of Victoria; to Kate Carnell; to George Souris, the Leader of the</p>
<p> National Party in New South Wales; Tony Staley, the Federal President</p>
<p> of the Liberal Party, and my numerous State and Federal parliamentary</p>
<p> colleagues, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>Today we really enter the crucial and decisive period of this State</p>
<p> election campaign. Today represents the countdown to the vote that</p>
<p> will be taken on the 27th of March. And in the nature of</p>
<p> modern politics it is what happens over the next two weeks that is</p>
<p> going to determine the outcome of this election.</p>
<p>And let me say as a long time friend and admirer, as the Leader of</p>
<p> the Federal Parliamentary Liberal Party, I have every confidence and</p>
<p> every belief that Kerry Chikarovski can not only win this election</p>
<p> but go on to be a very fine Premier of New South Wales. She has the</p>
<p> style, she has the personality, she has the understanding of life</p>
<p> and the experience of life that are the ingredients of a very fine</p>
<p> leader of the State of New South Wales. But she's also pitted</p>
<p> against a man and a government which has demonstrated in two very</p>
<p> key areas the utter hypocrisy of the Labor Government that New South</p>
<p> Wales now has.</p>
<p>For two-and-a-half years we were told by Mr Carr and Mr Egan that</p>
<p> it was crucial to the future of this State that we should privatise</p>
<p> the power industry of this State, yet now it is the subject of ridicule</p>
<p> and derision. But can anybody imagine that if by chance Labor were</p>
<p> returned they wouldn't immediately repudiate what they had said</p>
<p> on this subject during the election campaign, just as Mr Keating and</p>
<p> Mr Beazley broke their commitments not to privatise the Commonwealth</p>
<p> Bank. But even more glaring in the hypocrisy stakes is Mr Carr's</p>
<p> embracing of the goal of lower unemployment and of economic growth.</p>
<p> I have now been Prime Minister of Australia for just over three years</p>
<p> and I can report to you that every attempt made by the Coalition Government</p>
<p> to repair the Australian economy and thereby repair the economy of</p>
<p> New South Wales has been opposed by Bob Carr and opposed by Kim Beazley.</p>
<p> Both of them opposed the budget cuts to get the budget back into surplus.</p>
<p> Both of them have opposed taxation reform. Both of them opposed industrial</p>
<p> relations reform. Both of them opposed privatisation. Both of them</p>
<p> opposed the microeconomic reform that has made the Australian economy</p>
<p> and through it the New South Wales economy more competitive. Yet now</p>
<p> on the eve of this election Bob Carr seeks to bask in the sunlight</p>
<p> of the economic strength delivered through policies that he's</p>
<p> opposed for the last three years. And that is a measure of the hypocrisy</p>
<p> and, therefore, one of the things that have got to be put into judgement</p>
<p> and have got to be put into balance.</p>
<p>Now, I've known most of you in this great auditorium of a great</p>
<p> club for a very long time. We've been through many election campaigns</p>
<p> together. We've won a lot. We've lost a few. We share a</p>
<p> common political faith and we share a common political cause. And</p>
<p> over the next two weeks I want all of you to understand that in modern</p>
<p> elections it is the last days, the last weeks, that really count.</p>
<p> This election can be won and won very convincingly if we focus on</p>
<p> the main issues. If all of us work hard over the next two weeks, if</p>
<p> all of us realise that in Kerry we have a marvellous, thoughtful,</p>
<p> sensitive person to lead this State into the next millennium. We have</p>
<p> a strong Coalition. We have a good team. We have a great set of policies.</p>
<p> We are against a government and a party that has elevated political</p>
<p> hypocrisy to an art form.</p>
<p>I pledge, on behalf of my Federal Parliamentary colleagues, our total</p>
<p> support, our total commitment to the election of Kerry as Premier</p>
<p> of New South Wales and George Souris as Deputy Premier of New South</p>
<p> Wales. Right here in the St George area of Sydney, which has always</p>
<p> been at the knife-edge of politics both State and Federal, an important</p>
<p> contest is taking place.</p>
<p>But, ladies and gentlemen, will you now join me in welcoming Kerry</p>
<p> Chikarovski, the Leader of the Liberal Party, the person we want as</p>
<p> the next Premier of New South Wales. Will you welcome, Kerry Chikarovski.</p>
<p>[Ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
