<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7731</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, NATIONAL LIBRARY OF AUSTRLIA, 6 SEPTEMBER 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/09/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007731.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, NATIONAL LIBRARY OF<br />
AUSTRALIA, 6 SEPTEMBER 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: How close to settlement do you think the pilots<br />
dispute is now?<br />
PM: One can't say how close it is. All one can say is that<br />
the airlines, the Government, the ACTU are committed to<br />
seeing that the outrageous claim of this groups of people,<br />
this has been made outside the guidelines which is<br />
applicable to others, will not succeed. We will continue to<br />
do everything we can in terms of providing planes from the<br />
RAAF, accelerating the availablility of aircraft and pilots<br />
from overseas to assist the airlines in providing as<br />
substantial a service to the public of Australia as is<br />
possible. I hope that the evidence which is increasingly<br />
becoming available that pilots are now signing up under<br />
contracts with the two airlines will persuade their<br />
colleagues that they should do the same. But it would be<br />
improper for me to put some timetable on how long it will<br />
take to see a resumption of normal services in this country.<br />
But I repeat, let the Federation know that the determination<br />
of the Government and the airline industry and of the trade<br />
union movement is unaltered. This claim will not succeed.<br />
JOURNALIST: Sir Peter Abeles said last night that some<br />
stand downs had already taken place. Is any talk of<br />
compensation off the agenda?<br />
PM: Let's get it quite clear on this question of<br />
compensation. There is no suggestion that there will be any<br />
consideration of compensation for losses suffered by the<br />
airlines. The only matter which will be on the agenda and<br />
I will take it for a determination by my colleagues at an<br />
appropriate time is whether the Government in the unique<br />
circumstances of the airlines should provide some recompense<br />
in respect of employees in the airlines who are not being<br />
stood down. In regard to the tourist industry, for whom I<br />
share an enormous concern at the losses that they are<br />
suffering, in their case they can and are standing down<br />
their employees. In the case of the airlines that is not a<br />
realistic possibility. So the only matter that can be on<br />
the agenda is the possibility of recompense for the unique<br />
circumstances of the airlines for assistance to their<br />
employees who cannot be stood down. Now as I say in regard<br />
-to that-matter we will give consideration to that at the<br />
appropriate time. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, are you satisfied that what is<br />
being offered to the pilots by Sir Peter Abeles and Ansett<br />
falls within the guidelines?<br />
PM: Yes I am. I mean what we've witnessed in this tragic<br />
dispute is the additional tragedy of an irrelevant, confused<br />
opposition. The latest episode of which was the pathetic<br />
picture of this opposition spokesman, Mr Jull, last night<br />
getting into the media of Australia and putting out a series<br />
of calculated misrepresentations. But that's not surprising<br />
because the handling of themselves in this matter by the<br />
opposition has been dispicable and deplorable. The fact is<br />
that when this matter was before the full court of the<br />
Industrial Relations Commission the spokesman for the<br />
airlines made it clear at that point that when they went<br />
into a position where they would have to have negotiations<br />
with their individual pilots that they would make the<br />
contract available for perusal by the Commission. That's<br />
been done. These talks of 28.6% salary increases is an<br />
absurdity. But as I say it fits in with the pattern of<br />
total irrelevancy and misrepresentation which has<br />
characterised the opposition in the whole of this matter.<br />
JOURNALIST: the Opposition's tactic, the Halfpenny<br />
tactic, that they now seem to have adopted.<br />
PM: Let me say these things; I repeat here what I said in<br />
the Parliament that last week when very serious<br />
allegations were made against Sir Joh Bjelke-Petersen and<br />
there were some exultation in Labor ranks I went out of my<br />
way in the Caucus to say that as far as I was concerned and<br />
this Government was concerned there was a fundamental<br />
principle that applied and that is that any person accused<br />
or charged is innocent until proved 4uilty. That is the<br />
first point to make. The second point to make is that there<br />
seems to be some belief on the part of the opposition that I<br />
may have some brief for Mr Halfpenny. I don't think there<br />
is anyone in the country who's had more disputes and fights<br />
and fundamental practical and philosophical disagreements<br />
with Mr Halfpenny than myself and that remains the case that<br />
Mr Halfpenny as with any other individual in the community<br />
including Sir Joh Bjelke-Petersen is entitled to the<br />
benefit of that principle that if charges or accusations are<br />
made they are innocent until proved guilty. The third point<br />
I make is this; that the insinuations of the opposition in<br />
this matter are beneath contempt. It is the case that Mr<br />
Halfpenny has been associated vigorously with Victoria and<br />
the Victorian-based consortium in representations on behalf<br />
of that consortiuma. But the insinuation that somehow or<br />
other if Mr Halfpenny himself has been guilty of anything<br />
and I repeat he is innocent until proved guilty that that<br />
has anything to do with the way in which the tender has been<br />
awarded is beneath contempt because it involves the<br />
presumption that a whole range of people in the Navy right<br />
through and not only serving officers but officials have </p>
<p>-3-<br />
( PM cont) been involved in some corruption. The fact is<br />
that in all the processes there has been virtually unanimous<br />
recommendations to the Government from serving officers,<br />
Defence officials, Attorney-General's, Finance, that the<br />
contract which the Government awarded is the right one. So<br />
we just have further evidence in this matter of an<br />
Opposition which, without any question, has in virtually<br />
everything it has done and is doing is reaching levels of<br />
contempt unparralled in the history of this country.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
