<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16941</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister Media Release Prime Minister&#039;s Australia Asia Endeavour Awards for outstanding students Canberra 25 November 2009</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/11/2009</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Prime Minister, Kevin Rudd, today announced that 50 of the best and brightest university students from Australia and Asia have received the Prime Minister's Australia Asia Endeavour Award.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's Australia Asia Endeavour Award provides 20 postgraduate students and 20 undergraduates from across Australia with up to $63,500 to undertake an international research, study and internship experience in either China; India; Indonesia; Japan; Malaysia; Singapore; Republic of Korea; Taiwan; Thailand; or Vietnam. Ten international postgraduate students will also be funded to study in Australia.</p>
<p>The Government has committed $14.9 million over four years to establish this prestigious scholarship program, which was announced as part of the Government's response to the 2020 Summit.</p>
<p>From next year, the awards will form part of the Australia Awards initiative, announced by the Prime Minister in Singapore on the 13th November 2009. The Australia Awards will better co-ordinate and promote the more than $200 million of existing Australian scholarships, and over time build a new generation of leaders with strong ties to Australia and to our region.</p>
<p>In addition, a further $18 million will be spent on the Australia Asia Awards for individuals who have already demonstrated their potential to be leaders within their own countries, and for students from developing Asian countries.</p>
<p>The Australian Government strongly encourages high-achieving students to immerse themselves in the academic and social cultures of other countries by undertaking international study and work experience.</p>
<p>For further information including the list of the 2009 Prime Minister's Australia Asia Endeavour Award Holders, visit <a href="http://www.endeavour.deewr.gov.au">www.endeavour.deewr.gov.au</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
