<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>772</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE SA BANK, CANBERRA, ON 26TH JULY 1963 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/07/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000772.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OMIING OrTi . S A. 3ANK C&amp; NMIRL, ON<br />
26tUkL Y91963,<br />
I dont thinjE that r ought to be thAnked in<br />
qparti ua~ r wpy for aagnS he". this afternoon because the<br />
UgS truth is that we have just finished oscoocting a M pt and<br />
somme of You may think* vele that's anl rigtato The % XY4Tis<br />
AU oase Is am lifted from XY ShbOUJAews until Auawt 13th,<br />
or to be more ppeciae, Augut 1th,, when the xkwsp Vws a1Ipeaw.<br />
( Lu~ e) hmt the truth is that this is a rather ppy 1nem<br />
beeaue what happens vhunt a gem k is starting to oncoct AL<br />
,&amp; Apt and is vwking IMS MY through it is thalt all the ote<br />
. qom13~ ooSit1imte a Tiitus~ of the Prime ministe Pile up an<br />
the yandwhen I Isead at thm this afternoons having<br />
finisbe another omittee or two this smning, for once in<br />
ifty I was vwy thonkfal that I had to aam aWay and do 201Whin<br />
else in amt pios, Inc sort of pleasant ottosphewe.<br />
Now, YouaSir said "" thing about w1sula~ ty<br />
maea glancing reflerene to the imaidty or baniters, the<br />
~ uty of assamnee, son. Bat what I liked whnI wea the<br />
litrataria that yous sent me wo that littl, bit of early history<br />
of the 1.8. A* Duk. The 3.5. A. Bak to as has abs been<br />
a thingv I have gemn in Melbourne and glance at ecaina[;<br />
e" w else but you a Makid enough to lot se have a<br />
ibitrioul srh gping back over rn'sther no" then a century*<br />
For the first time I relsed. the Scottish influenoe in the nme,<br />
OMhlshk Scottish and Awtallan Bank Limted. " m of you<br />
may not Iaw it and thfre I shold tell Yag ex relatione the<br />
mlyh atprowlded me with the dopey that th* first establiskthtthe<br />
Bank had wa In Sydney In George Street. It amnsistod<br />
of a two ~ tee 9mvelty that the hank bought frm a vime and<br />
spirit morchant. ( Iaugatew) Nov deeinit that appeal to yw<br />
youa Ma ijmigiii the m aw i Ua of b; expatriated sootin, paing<br />
in an Interview with a Qleat to sniff up tUs old aromas. f" is<br />
smthing I understand peretly besause many yearr ap whsn I<br />
was respectable and ws-pamtising at the Bar and In l=<br />
Cbbers in Melbourne, V.. ewaa win, merdhant immediatelyv = Ar<br />
my chaaube it ws a marvellous thing. dharaver the nali<br />
barmaeute, mnpleauant that you werea working an, all hait you<br />
ddto do ws to goer near the window and take up a sood<br />
abostful of air loade with the fames of the demon &amp; W" ic So<br />
am I anderaiQh about the history of the B. S. A.<br />
As fbr the Leal. General, I an bound to say<br />
that go409 eamayculd have a more respectable title. ( Laughter)<br />
sawe people ame legal avid som people aw. ganeral hat it Is very<br />
seldam tumt yea can rt this powerfual oombitnm of ciroumstances,<br />
( Laughter) the word lega V* atig sam rather harsh and<br />
prelso onfrwemnt of Mh enand the vWar pneal IupwIng<br />
a mwt of element of genial huanity ( laughter) fthere I<br />
ws not surprised to We tiild in the paRpers that I received&amp;;<br />
rapid and rwakable the peath of the Legal General has been<br />
in Atwaliak. r read in the paper this amrng -me doubt you<br />
did too that the population of Caber is now 70,000. It Was<br />
left to my driver to tell methat he had heard also on the side </p>
<p>that tbat doesn't Incluft the diplomttc ( Laughtmw) * ieh<br />
wasI astonished to issr, an his natZtmbers aad<br />
19,00 in canbra Ay w v wilmit the dplmntia o02W.<br />
I sometimes Wish i o0Lcald iA; St~) bat anyhow w will emit them<br />
forb this porpoese 70,000 people The first t1ws I vaihed aroamd<br />
this pert of Canbai vex in 19-* when I bad ase brtthrough<br />
embdy' mstake, to boe A= tr Y. hIl of A ewlia<br />
thatsa lion time a p. The population was then 61, M~ When<br />
the war ended, thuse had beow of nooesalt' gat restrictions<br />
on ballding and activity of that kind. Sofrs shop I think<br />
I an right In saying, so fresh bvisluss phmse ad " e buit<br />
for a lin, long timel, bet in the last fifteen years, the developsent<br />
in Canbesr he., I think beem quite WoRMs~ ealft And among<br />
other tbInu84 of Ooee the Jevlopuent ar -hoe -in whet I<br />
wiilvl thi elsmriai sectim of Canberra bas been beyond<br />
a~ bol'a belif# if he bad sat dwou to think about itg to<br />
visels it ton years alp*<br />
This is a great and groing and as I<br />
hae Wa occasion to amy before today# It is agreed br the<br />
statisticians# wortby4egsple, that bw 197O excluding the<br />
dipimetc crpasoh doubt IF ttime will hae rison<br />
to~ mhmmlpeprtlemns, the" e will be 100,000 people haee<br />
Sinbody telAiat there would be a quarter of a n31314a at<br />
the tutu of the omtury. There Is in faet hardly any lUnit to<br />
be put to the development of this piace and that's a good tig<br />
Itts a post thing for Austrailitth~ t shold have a gns<br />
sGopeiaatU atios or enttledto eat osiaioWe<br />
I barnddI&amp; grambiing about the soft ofputin Inalkea<br />
x an ' 1"! sthat I aeouse them, and I boe suenas fulr of<br />
having a limited eaepisof what the eapital of what we all<br />
kno will be In dwueqre a vwi poeet ooeutry, ought to boo<br />
And, of oose, the buildings that have pmu<br />
up here, they e cay a mixesd reception bw mep I enitl yot.<br />
I 6oult alvays Il; the amv buildin~ e I an soL~ me very rade<br />
abouat the nw bul'dings bet stranmge emgh, this has no effeat<br />
tnrha t il thst ( laughter) butiI a bound to Sir,<br />
tht ~ iktis watsemI,( oide&amp; A roeu oI da<br />
I taoght, that this had seedistinction and chsaater about i<br />
amd that add" to my pleasur in being present to dealare It open.<br />
I believe that we are 4ping to seemedu<br />
melemntso Wen I leok beok ever this period in Whiab I<br />
have been here,, off and an, man and boyp as you 0h my<br />
eould remember for a longti&amp; e feeling a little afrIdthfat<br />
Canbxv nghttend to be just a city of Politician$ and GIVIl<br />
AMI an the last men to upbraid politicians though<br />
sometimes the ubraid me and me doubt for Vey good reasons.<br />
But a omumity n offisial Gity, In which you have Political<br />
peoples and civil servants and a few ethers who attend to their<br />
mosis too naro a thing ait tends to bosom% as an amusing<br />
friend of sin, one said, inbred. It's a Very bad thing for<br />
a politisian, for eample, 0 to moe areud as oe had to ton<br />
yes ago and be addressed with infinite wespedt q 0110 SITil<br />
sinntafisau another, It Is essential for the sanity of all<br />
of as that we shold have a variety of Po I with a variety<br />
of ' experismoes Including a boathq' paeenCA of people who<br />
Instoad of saying * Good mowning 8iW will stand off and tell<br />
yeu exactly what they think about you and what rubbish it was<br />
Veth Inight befaoe This Is sood and it is<br />
u*/ 3 </p>
<p>whave wreat finlancial institutions now<br />
Os~ b shing tIelvoo The day vill aom Sir I hoe I<br />
mak* mbae nku m et aeina t peCpoanrbqe , v but iitt s wboan&amp;' t obef fiac . b rnoiht wofill<br />
oo to tbe point whm this has b. oom* a g t natioawl<br />
capital that it will brame the sontre not of trade and oomnerce<br />
I 4' t thift it is qit* o eqnppe for that but the eentre of<br />
Laportant fimnal deiona imprtant finanoial asitvitle,<br />
reat intollootual activities in miorsities and in shools<br />
reat selentifle achiwrmess in the varies veeareh establIsh.<br />
nst whiab ame haee a reat Veity of people and &amp; round<br />
a boatifal eatwl ftat", a tbrin of people who will<br />
vat to lie he mot becue tc; are pell eiai ment becau.<br />
ter are civil sw ts, bt butr Use they f3r t aas i vilised<br />
a i plnes in whie their chlidren my p to fine<br />
an" havo all the fteilities and is whhiicbh stwe<br />
of = iversiti* e will be awmlfable to tbo@. This I believe,<br />
is altry with a e g piagpumse The mlyr epdlhveIs<br />
that lealr at I , I think I Vas born twty " etoro soom<br />
beaus. I womd r to be alive in 2000 if : Dra to hav a look<br />
avo and see what'os NSA tfhyou win ml Y fi to<br />
my so, look back a Uttad i; 1 tat li al fiteeme<br />
years, I have perhaps made sm ontribution to its achi-evemnt.<br />
This is quIte a notable ocesion in a notable<br />
pie. I wish both of these pwnie l. I kn they<br />
will have xpeat happimessand mecess in Cnber and I have<br />
the petest plwa. in delacriag the building open* </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
