<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3593</transcript-id>
    <title>SIGNING OF SCIENCE AGREEMENT WITH USSR</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/01/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003593.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
S A A II A:<br />
n&gt; li7 r. r FPRESS STATEMENT January 1975<br />
SIGNING OF SCIENCE AGREEMENT WITH U. S. S. R.<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Whitlam, and Soviet<br />
Prime Minister, Mr. Kos( gn, today signed in Moscow an<br />
agreement between the Australian and USSR Governments<br />
for scientific and technical cooperation. The agreement<br />
will facilitate increased cooperation in both the natural<br />
and social sciences. In the first instance five fields are to be given<br />
priority for cooperation. They are: earth sciences, plant<br />
industry, radioastronomy, etomology and textile technology.<br />
Small groups of experts in these fields will e; change visits<br />
so that long-term programs for cooperation can he prepared.<br />
The first of these visits has been made by an<br />
Australian group of earth scientists which toured the USSR<br />
in December 1974, for discussions with their Soviet counterparts.<br />
Soviet groups in textile technology and radi. oastronomy will<br />
visit Australia in February for talks with Australian scientists<br />
and inspections of laboratories. Other exchanges will take<br />
place in subsequent months.<br />
As a result of the prior negotiation of the<br />
agreement there has already been a strengthening of<br />
scientific cooperation between Australia and the USSR in<br />
some of the priority areas. It is hoped that the agreement<br />
will benefit scientific development in both countries, and<br />
thereby contribute to furthering bilateral relations between<br />
Australia and the USSR.<br />
MOSCOW </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
