<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21472</transcript-id>
    <title>$36 million to maintain Australia&#039;s Biodiversity Hotspots  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/08/2004</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Australian Government has demonstrated its continued commitment to the environment with the announcement today of $36 million over four years to conserve Australia's biodiversity hotspots.</p>
<p>I congratulate Senator Meg Lees for proposing this environmental conservation program to me and for playing an active role in the development of the proposal.</p>
<p>The three-year hotspots programme, commencing in 2004-05, will protect and conserve Australia's biodiversity hotspots - areas which are rich in animal and plant species and where habitats are under immediate threat.</p>
<p>Through land acquisition for conservation and national biodiversity stewardship this programme will apply a range of innovative incentives for conservation on private land to conserve and protect native vegetation and endangered species.</p>
<p>South Australia's Eastern Mount Lofty Ranges will be the first 'hotspot' to benefit from the programme.</p>
<p>The Eastern Mount Lofty Ranges supports the largest remnants of woodland vegetation communities in South Australia and is a vital refuge for many species of birds.</p>
<p>$1.5 million is committed through this programme to conserve remaining vegetation and protect nationally listed birds, such as the critically endangered South Australian population of the Glossy Black Cockatoo.</p>
<p>Today's announcement builds on the Government's existing support for biodiversity hotspots.  Last year the Government delivered on its election commitment in A Better Environment by announcing it had identified 15 domestic biodiversity hotspot regions and that action to conserve those hotspot regions would be supported through the Natural Heritage Trust. The $36 million committed today provides additional resources to protect Australia's biodiversity hotspots.</p>
<p> This domestic initiative complements the $10 million Regional Natural Heritage Programme which aims to help protect internationally recognised hotspots in the South East Asia and Pacific regions.</p>
<p>The programme also complements the $3 billion Natural Heritage Trust and the $1.4 billion National Action Plan for Salinity and Water Quality programmes and will draw on the regional processes already in place and the views and expertise of regional groups.</p>
<p>My Government is committed to biodiversity conservation and these programmes reaffirm our domestic and international leadership in driving and investing in real gains for the environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
