<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3148</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER IN SINGAPORE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/02/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003148.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NEWS RELEASE<br />
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 19 11 February 1974i<br />
PRIME MINISTER IN SINGAPORE'<br />
The following is the text of an address by the<br />
Prime IEinister, 11r Vhitlam, to the Singapore Press Club on<br />
8 February 1974:<br />
Iof Au's trali" aA wyaesa r toagooe xpmyl aipnr inthcei paclh antgaessk awse wa, , enreew ., m Parkiimneg i1r1inister<br />
Australia's foreign policy in terms of our political inheritence<br />
after twenty-three years of Opposition.<br />
A year later my task is to put the established, firm<br />
and irreversible policy of the Australian Government in terms of<br />
the realities of the international situation we, with all the<br />
countries of the region, now have to live with.<br />
A year ago, it was very necessary, it iw. as quite<br />
inevitable, that a new Government would stress those aspects of<br />
its policies which emphasised its independence from its<br />
p predecessors. Now I emphasise those great matters which<br />
illustrate the inter-dependence of my nation with other nations,<br />
with old friends as much as with new associates.<br />
It's most appropriate that I do so here, to the press,<br />
in Singapore, at this time.<br />
To the press, because, naturally enough, properly<br />
enough, your writings have tended to emphasise sometimes, dare<br />
I say, dramatise the changes more than the continuity of<br />
policies. In Singapore, because I acknowledge that no nation<br />
has been more directly affected by some of our decisions and no<br />
nation is better entitled to a full explanation of the purposes<br />
of the Australian Government. And now, because there has not<br />
been a time since the war itself that the inter-dependence of<br />
all nations, not just the nations of our region, but of all, the<br />
very greatest with the smallest, has been made so vividly manifest-</p>
<p>in all its complexity, all its fragility, all its vulnerability<br />
and in all its urgent reality.<br />
It's no longer necessary, and it was never really<br />
correct, to measure the policies of my Government just by contrast<br />
with those of its predecessor.<br />
Contrast enough I trust there is, but it is a mistake<br />
to see our policies only as a break with the past.<br />
For four reasons. To do so ignores much that continues<br />
and much that would be happening whatever government was in power<br />
in Australia. Secondly, it ignores the steadiness of the<br />
Australian people, and any elected Australian Government ignores<br />
at its peril the determination of the Australian people to protect<br />
their reputation for reliability and dependability. Thirdly, it<br />
ignores the consistency of policy formulation within the Australian<br />
Labor Party. These policies have long been a matter of public record<br />
and public debate. It is just impossible for anybody to have been surprised<br />
by our major decisions unless we were to accept that it is<br />
surprising these days for elected governments to carry out their<br />
undertakings. And fourthly and most importantly, it ignores the<br />
fundamental fact that our policies are directed towards the future,<br />
not against the past.<br />
We are not merely repairing the past; we are preparing<br />
for the future. Sure enough in matters like China, like Viet-Nam, like<br />
Southern Africa, there is in our thinking and attitudes an element<br />
of apology, of reparation. But the great thing is preparation<br />
preparation for a future of unparallelled opportunities with<br />
appalling consequences confronting us all if we fail to grasp<br />
them. And the old attitudes, the old stances, the old frozen<br />
postures were just not adequate for such a preparation.<br />
So it is in the context of the future that I wish<br />
our policies to be seen, because it is in that context that they<br />
are being developed. </p>
<p>And if you try to see them in that context, you w,, ill<br />
I believe be able to see their consistency and their true meaning.<br />
They are all part of a pattern; it is a pattern for<br />
the future. Basically, what we are trying to do for Australia, and<br />
to the extent that we have any influence over opinion or events<br />
beyond our shores, what we are trying to do in the region, is to<br />
build a range and breadth of relations in order to prevent any<br />
single preoccupation distorting or paralysing our actions and<br />
attitudes. For most of the period that my party was in opposition,<br />
the overwhelming preoccupation of Australian policy was China<br />
arid that meant, of course, the containment of China by military<br />
action on the Asian mainland.<br />
The American alliance, SEATO, the war in Viet-Nam, were<br />
forced into this single focus; all these matters were debated in<br />
terms of that over-riding preoccupation.<br />
It is precisely because my Government rejects the<br />
premise of that preoccupation, precisely because we believe that<br />
the preoccupation to the point of obsession harmed Australia that<br />
we are determined to widen all Australia's relations to prevent<br />
other newer preoccupations doing similar harm.<br />
Yet in acting to redress the past we do not over react<br />
against the past.<br />
Take China itself. You should not get the idea that<br />
because we moved so very promptly to normalise relations with<br />
China after 23 years of mutual hostility that China is the<br />
be-all and end-all of Australia's foreign policy.<br />
It was the classic case of when it is not necessary to<br />
delay it is necessary not to delay.<br />
Again consider our policy towards the United States<br />
because we choose no longer to beat the drum about the alliance,<br />
that is not to say that ANZUS is not still our most important and<br />
I believe enduring treaty.<br />
And the same kind of consideration lay behind our<br />
decisions affecting the Five Power arrangements. </p>
<p>You should understand that our decision to withdraw<br />
the battalion and battery from Singapore following incidentally<br />
on its withdrawal by our predecessors four years ago from Terendak<br />
is part of a reconstruction and re-orientation of our whole defeunce<br />
policy. In no way do we repudiate or down-grade the Yive Power<br />
arrangements. Those arrangements do not of course require Australia<br />
to maintain a battalion in Singapore.<br />
Ve are convinced that the kind of army Australia necdi<br />
for her own defence and for her raost effective contribution to<br />
defence of her friends should no longer be structured upon the<br />
concept of fixed garrisons overseas.<br />
For a country like Australia the concept is unreal alk<br />
anachronistic. And for Australia it is a concept which cuts across<br />
her basic defence needs in modern times.<br />
Her needs are for highly professional, high mobile,<br />
finely-equipped forces capable of, and experienced in, proipt<br />
cooperation with friendly forces.<br />
This is the concept relevant to our needs.<br />
The old concept worked as an inhibition economicail2<br />
politically and logisticaly against creating the most effective<br />
defence contribution Australia can make.<br />
And I confidently predict that the next two years . ii<br />
see Australian defence cooperation not only with Singapore,<br />
Malaysia, New Zealand and the British presence in the region, btL.-I.<br />
with Indonesia and Papua New Guinea brought to a more effective<br />
and efficient state than could ever have been achieved simply by<br />
keeping Australian ground forces with all their impedimenta<br />
overseas. The desire for cooperation, the need for cooperation<br />
has not changed; all that has changed is the view of the<br />
Australian Government about the best way of achieving that<br />
cooperation and making it more valuable for all of us.<br />
Some components of Australian forces are going home,<br />
but Australia is not going away. </p>
<p>Ana this, of course, is the very crux of the matter.<br />
I hear in some quarters concern that Australia, or<br />
the present Australian Government. may go isolationist.<br />
Isolationism i~ s not an option for Australia or for<br />
any Australian Government.<br />
Indeed, it was precisely my belief that we were<br />
isolating ourselves from half the world, from a quarter of the<br />
world's people in China, from the whole of Eiack Africa, from the<br />
other half of Europe east of the Elbe, from Latin America and<br />
even from India in any meaningfol way, and my belief that our<br />
relations with Japan and Indonesia lacked their proper warmth<br />
that has informed, inspired and maoulded the policies, actions and<br />
decisions of my Government and which dictated my own overseas<br />
visits and those of my Foreign Miister.<br />
This Government -by action, by association, by<br />
inclination, by philosophy and above all by the necessities of<br />
the times in which we live and the region in which we live is<br />
the most genuinely internationalist government Australia has ever<br />
had. And even if our wishes were different, Australia's own<br />
needs wouid force irnternationalismn upon is<br />
How could this great trading country t; hose lifelines<br />
lie througn here be indifferenit to what happens here?<br />
How could this great resource producer whose prospority<br />
depends upon: the prosper~ ty of the great resource users be<br />
indifferent to their success and well-be. Ing?<br />
Eut we do make the dictinctaon between internationalism<br />
and interventionism. Ve beiieve that the end of the old interventionism is<br />
the beginning of a new internationalism in which Australia will<br />
play a constructivze, cooperative, and generous part.<br />
\ ie know only too well that peace arnd security do not<br />
come because we want them or merely because we proclaim their<br />
desirability. Peace and security have to be built brick by brick<br />
and bonded by the efforts, energy and imagination of the leaders<br />
of this regio. </p>
<p>Vhenr. people use the phrase Asian problems should be<br />
settled by Asian countrLes they sometimes tend to forget that<br />
the Asian continent does not end where the borders with Communist<br />
Asian couantr: es start.<br />
The present government, in formulating its policy,<br />
does take account of the views of countries like China and, to<br />
a lesser extent, North Viet-Nam and North Korea although,<br />
naturally, it does not take as much account of their views as<br />
those of traditionally fr-: endly countries and geographically<br />
closer countries. Ir. its bilateral relations with some Asian countries<br />
Australia is going through a period of adjustment, but we are<br />
confident that in the longer run, once this adjustment has been<br />
made, our relationships would be more soundly based than in the<br />
past. The confluence of our history and geography, our<br />
origins as Europeans, our location onr the edge of South-East Asiagive<br />
us a unique opportunity to demonstrate to the international<br />
community that countries with very dafferent cultural, religious<br />
and ethnic backgrounds can evolve intimate and lasting friendships.<br />
To this end we shall spare no effort to ensure that in<br />
the years ahead, Australia is accepted as a cooperative and<br />
helpful member of the Asian and Pacif. c region and a neighbour<br />
of the nations of South-East Asia.<br />
The signs of tnis new approacr, are round us in this<br />
region. In ASEAN, Sirngapore, Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand<br />
and the Philippines have and have sustained an organisation which<br />
is workable and relevant, and which reflects the common needs of<br />
the countries of South-East Asia.<br />
Australia applauds the achievements of ASEAN, and<br />
the hope which it offers for the economic and social progress of<br />
the people of the region.<br />
But we have no desire to intrude; I have said many<br />
times before that Australia does not seek membership of ASEAN.<br />
What we do hope is that we can cooperate with ASEAN<br />
imaginatively and constructively as a neighbour and a friend. </p>
<p>We think we have certain skills to offer if these<br />
skills are needed; we know that we have much, in turn, to learn<br />
from you and your ASEAN partners.<br />
The sort of fruitful cooperation which I have in mind<br />
is illustrated by the recent discussions which Australian<br />
officials held with representatives of ASEAN in Bangkok on<br />
possible Australian assistance to regional ASEAN projects.<br />
The discussions which Prime Minister Lee and I have<br />
held about concluding a cultural agreement between our two<br />
countries an agreement which we both favour in principle and<br />
which we will work quickly towards formulating is a further<br />
indication of our desire to broaden the form and the depth of<br />
our relations with South-East Asian countries.<br />
W~ e know that you in Singapore, your Government and<br />
your business leaders, are looking to extend the fruits of your<br />
own hard-won economic progress to the region as a whole.<br />
We hope that we, in some way, if only in a small way,<br />
can assist as a catalyst in this process.<br />
There are certain fields of endeavour, in agriculture<br />
and technical and scientific training to name but tio, where we<br />
believe we can make a valuable contribution to regional<br />
development. Ny government is not alone in recogniaing the need<br />
for the promise of a new spirit of international cooperation,<br />
and this region is not the only one where nations are attempting<br />
to establish new forms of cooperative relationships, or where<br />
Australia is anxious to assist with that process.<br />
Put to Australia, South-East Asia is, of course, our<br />
immediate north. Your hopes, your problems, your future are necess4arily<br />
and for ever, part of our own future.<br />
Much is written about Australia' s " new nationalism";<br />
I would rather put it in terms of Australia's new internationalism.<br />
Of course, there is a national spirit awake and abroad<br />
in Australia. </p>
<p>8.<br />
But Australia wants no more for herself than Singapore<br />
wants for herself, and what all the nations in this region are<br />
seeking a national identity within the international community,<br />
reasonable control over our own destiny and our own resources in<br />
a world where all nations are increasingly inter-dependent.<br />
This is now the task exercising statesmanship throughout<br />
the world to reconcile these three desires and needs of the<br />
peoples of the world their desire for independence, their<br />
dependence upon others and our inter-dependence, all of us with<br />
one another. We are living in times when these three great principlesindependence,<br />
dependence, inter-dependence show themselves to be<br />
interlocked as never before.<br />
Upon their resolution and reconciliation depends the future<br />
even the survival of civilisation itself.<br />
You will not, I believe, find Australia with a very strong<br />
sense of her own nationhood and identity, Australia with a very<br />
real sense of the dependence of her prosperity upon the prosperity<br />
of her neighbours, Australia with a very deep sense of her<br />
inter-dependence with and her responsibilities towards the<br />
international community, failing in her responsibilities or<br />
faltering in our determination to make the most of the opportunity<br />
for a better, safer neighbourhood at this very critical time in0<br />
modern history." </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
