<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4859</transcript-id>
    <title>LAUNCHING OF &#039;HISTORIC PLACES OF AUSTRALIA - VOLUME ONE&#039;</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/10/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004859.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
11., AUS AL Lk<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 23 OCTOBER 1978<br />
LAUNCHING OF " HISTORIC PLACES OF AUSTRALIA VOLUME ONE"<br />
I am delighted to be here today to launch this latest volume<br />
in the series on historic buildings and places in Australia<br />
being published by the Australian Council of National Trusts.<br />
This book, " Historic Places of Australia: Volume One", presents<br />
a collection of environmentally important areas and towns.<br />
The text describes many of the interesting features of their<br />
history and architecture, and the photographs are a distinctive<br />
and sensitive record of an older Australia.<br />
The earlier volumes in the series dealt specifically with<br />
historic buildings. This book deals with the whole environmental<br />
setting. It will take readers on a journey into many of our<br />
yesterdays, from the days of the clipper ships, lying off Port<br />
Fairy to the pearling luggers of Broome, to the mansions,<br />
majestic homes and public buildings of the colonial era.<br />
It is an exciting journey, enriching our knowledge of Australia's<br />
past and our appreciation of some of Australia's beautiful<br />
places. The quality of the volume is a credit to the trust movement,<br />
and to many people who have given honorary help in its preparation.<br />
It is a good example of how a voluntary conservation organisation,<br />
by virtue of hard work and dedication, can make progress in<br />
achieving its aims and goals.<br />
In the introductory section, Mr Rodney Davidson, the Australian<br />
co-ordinator, acknowledges the honorary work of the experts<br />
who have contributed to this volume.<br />
I should like to thank Mr Davidson, the President of the Australian<br />
Council of National Trusts, Mr Justice Sir John Moore, and the<br />
Chairman of the Australian Council of National Trusts,<br />
Mr Victor Parkinson, for all they have done for the National<br />
Trust Movement in Australia.<br />
The Government warmly acknowledges the help of all the people<br />
who contributed to this work. The Commonwealth interest in<br />
conservation and preservation is wide ranging, embracing<br />
both the natural and cultural environment.<br />
However, the protection of the National Estate is not the preserve<br />
of one level of~ Government, or one group of people. It is<br />
something in which the whole community is involved. / 2 </p>
<p>The Commonwealth is pleased to be a partner in this national<br />
activity. In 1976 we appointed the first commissioners to<br />
the Australian Heritage Commission to advise us on the<br />
preservation of the whole Australian environment, and to<br />
compile and maintain a national inventory of those significant<br />
places which should be preserved for our benefit and that of<br />
future generations.<br />
The national inventory is recorded on the newly created register*<br />
of the national estate. This register covers the significant<br />
parts. of Australia's environme-nt: its homes and buildings,<br />
historic towns, churches, landscapes, its bushland, and the<br />
whole of our natural heritage.<br />
The register is being used as a basis for developing programmes<br />
and policies to protect, improve and present properties and<br />
places forming part of the national estate. Already there are<br />
some 5,000 places registered.<br />
The Act setting up the Heritage Commission requires that<br />
Commonwealth Ministers, Departments and authorities take no<br />
action which adversely effects a place on the register unless<br />
there is no feasible or prudent alternative.<br />
All Commonwealth decisions aim at all times to keep a proper<br />
balance between conservation and responsible development in<br />
the national interest.<br />
The Heritage Commission, together with the provision of Commonwealth<br />
funds, has helped to create a wide awareness, at all levels of<br />
Government and the community generally, of the range of the<br />
national estate, made by both man and nature.<br />
The Government is well aware of the part National Trust bodies<br />
have played in preserving Australia's heritage. They have been<br />
pioneers in the great and responsible task of preservation and<br />
conservation. The National Trusts have played a significant<br />
role in getting the register established quickly.<br />
With respect to the buildings in our cultural environment the<br />
Trusts have made the major contribution so far, because the<br />
Heritage Commission accepted for the register those places<br />
already classified by the Trusts.<br />
For some years Commonwealth Governments have supported the<br />
National Trusts, providing funds to help them meet administrative<br />
costs and special grants for preservation and restoration work<br />
on old buildings.<br />
As I have said, this book places emphasis on the protection of<br />
areas as distinct from individual buildings. This is consistent<br />
with the importance given to the total heritage by the Venice<br />
Charter of the International Council on monuments and sites.<br />
This book has left a great impression on me. It's more than<br />
words and pictures it's a living and vital portrait of a<br />
special part of our history. I hope it will encourage Australians<br />
to see some of the beauty and history of Australia at first hand.<br />
/ 3 </p>
<p>3<br />
I warmly commend this book to you. It has a rightful place<br />
in this great National Library, and I'm sure it will have a<br />
place in other libraries around Australia.<br />
I hope it will also find a place on the bookshelves in your<br />
homes. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
