<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3320</transcript-id>
    <title>COMMUNITY RELATIONS CONSULTANT</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/07/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003320.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
AUS RLIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATEMENT NO. 284A<br />
7 July 1974<br />
COMMUNITY RELATIONS CONSULTANT<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Whitlam announced today<br />
the appointment of the Honourable A. J. Grassby as Special<br />
Consultant to the Australian Government on Community Relations.<br />
Mr Whitlam said that the appointment was to lay<br />
the foundations for legislative and administrative action to<br />
ensure the abolition of all forms of discrimination on the basis<br />
of race, colour or creed in Australia and to ensure a continuing<br />
program to enable the Australian community as a whole to benefit<br />
from the rich cultural and linguistic heritage which Australia<br />
has acquired after 25 years of mass migration. Above all the<br />
appointment is the first step of new initiatives to ensure that<br />
the hopes and aspirations of the 3 million people who have settled<br />
in Australia since World War IT have the fullest opportunities<br />
for realisation. il<br />
The Australian Parliament has responsibility to<br />
legislate with respect to aborigines, migrants and international<br />
treaties and obligations. Australia has not yet ratified the International<br />
Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination<br />
which was adopted by the United Nations in December 1965 and<br />
which came into force in January 1969.<br />
This convention has already been ratified by<br />
78 countries, including Britain, Canada and New Zealand.<br />
Earlier this year Australian Attorney-General ( Senator<br />
Murphy) introduced legislation which would have enabled Australia<br />
to implement the convention.<br />
This legislation lapsed when the old Parliament<br />
was dissolved and Mr Whitlam said that Mr Grassby would also advise<br />
on the form in which the legislation would be introduced in the<br />
new Parliament. Mr Whitlam said that Mr Grassby would be appointed<br />
commissioner under the legislation when it was passed by Parliament.<br />
In the meantime he will act as adviser to the<br />
Australian Government on matters of community relations affecting<br />
migrants and other ethnic groups in Australia. / 2 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
