<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11199</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE ACTING PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON TIM FISCHER MP                 PRESS CONFERENCE &amp;#150; PARLIAMENT HOUSE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>07/01/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE................................................................................................</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>On behalf of the Government and in liaison with the portfolio Minister</p>
<p> responsible for the Infrastructure Borrowing Taxation Offset scheme,</p>
<p> IBTOS, that's Minister for Transport and Regional Services, John</p>
<p> Anderson, I'm pleased to make some announcements here today.</p>
<p> Subject to certain conditions the Federal Government expects to approve</p>
<p> four national infrastructure projects worth more than $900 million,</p>
<p> and they will receive this very valuable tax rebate and allow further</p>
<p> facilitation of the implementation of these projects.</p>
<p>The four projects which have been endorsed to this stage by the Federal</p>
<p> Cabinet are as follows: $400 million eastern gas pipeline which will</p>
<p> run from Longford, near Sale in Victoria, to Sydney, extending Australia's</p>
<p> gas distribution network; a $170 million construction of a new international</p>
<p> and domestic passenger terminal at Adelaide Airport, badly needed;</p>
<p> the building of a $154 million gas fired co-generation plant producing</p>
<p> electricity and steam for major manufacturing plants within the Botany</p>
<p> industrial area in Sydney; and assistance to Melbourne's City</p>
<p> Link Road project involving extension to Exhibition Street and production</p>
<p> of world-leading electronic transponder technology.</p>
<p>These are the first infrastructure projects that have qualified to</p>
<p> receive assistance under the Coalition's Infrastructure Borrowing</p>
<p> Tax Offset Scheme. The granting of tax offsets for these projects</p>
<p> will allow all of them to proceed with minimal delay. In highlighting</p>
<p> our commitment to nation building, it demonstrates the partnership</p>
<p> the governments can forge with the private sector to generate economic</p>
<p> growth, to sustain</p>
<p>further economic growth, in an economy growing well at the start of</p>
<p> 1999 in sharp contrast to such places as Hong Kong, -8%; Korea, -6%;</p>
<p> and Japan, the second largest economy in the world, -2.6% at this</p>
<p> time. It's a perfect example of the Government's approach</p>
<p> to improving Australia's infrastructure which has such a major</p>
<p> impact on business costs, and the lowering of those costs. This assistance</p>
<p> will generate jobs and improve our environmental circumstance. It</p>
<p> is a win-win situation.</p>
<p>In terms of jobs, these projects offer the potential of up to 6,800</p>
<p> new jobs, with the bulk of them in fact being in regional Australia</p>
<p> in places like Sale, Bairnsdale, Orbost, Bombala, Cooma, Queanbeyan,</p>
<p> Nowra and Wollongong, as well as jobs extra in Adelaide, Melbourne</p>
<p> and Sydney. These projects will also contribute to the manufacture</p>
<p> of world beating technology, state of the art; reduction of greenhouse</p>
<p> gas emissions; and a reduction in traffic congestion, as well as increasing</p>
<p> tourism opportunities.</p>
<p>On the eastern gas pipeline, whilst there was just before Christmas</p>
<p> an announcement in respect of change of ownership with regard to that</p>
<p> project, this is the first time that the Federal Government has given</p>
<p> its clearance and it will involve economic benefits to many regional</p>
<p> centres. Not only will it provide reticulated gas to some areas for</p>
<p> the first time and contribute to a more competitive gas market elsewhere,</p>
<p> but further jobs will be created. 1,100 during construction and indirectly</p>
<p> up to 6,000 new jobs attached to that one project of the eastern gas</p>
<p> pipeline. A stronger national gas grid can reduce the likelihood of</p>
<p> the energy shortage that crippled Victoria for a period last year.</p>
<p> It will also help reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 2 million tonnes</p>
<p> annually by 2010.</p>
<p>The Adelaide Airport terminal, many of you would have been caught</p>
<p> in a thunderstorm, or on a frosty morning with the gate-less elements</p>
<p> of the Adelaide existing airport terminal. By the year 2001, the people</p>
<p> of Adelaide will have a state of the art domestic and international</p>
<p> terminal. As a crucial element of South Australia's economic</p>
<p> fabric the Adelaide Airport redevelopment can stimulate export growth,</p>
<p> increase revenue from inbound tourism, and promote Adelaide as a base</p>
<p> for complimentary capital investment. It will generate about 350 jobs</p>
<p> during construction, and directly contribute towards 800 permanent</p>
<p> new jobs.</p>
<p>The Melbourne City Link project, while aspects have been previously</p>
<p> announced, this is the clearance for a modified aspect of that key</p>
<p> City Link project which is of course well under construction at this</p>
<p> time. The Government assistance to the City Link project will help</p>
<p> deliver direct savings to the Victorian economy of about $265 million</p>
<p> annually. The City Link extension involved will further reduce traffic</p>
<p> congestion in Melbourne's streets. But just as importantly our</p>
<p> assistance towards the production of in-car transponders to be used</p>
<p> on City Link encourages the local manufacturers of world standard</p>
<p> technology to go ahead with an export program which would perhaps</p>
<p> not have otherwise taken place. 600,000 of these transponders will</p>
<p> be produced at the Melbourne factory which is the biggest order for</p>
<p> a road project any where in the world. The Government's assistance</p>
<p> helps ensure the adoption of a uniform national system for electric,</p>
<p> or electronic polling.</p>
<p>And then the Botany co-generation facility. The Government's</p>
<p> assistance to the construction of a Botany co-generation facility</p>
<p> will have a direct impact in reducing business costs for local industries,</p>
<p> encouraging a more competitive electricity market, and lowering greenhouse</p>
<p> gas missions in the Botany industrial area by an estimated 235,000</p>
<p> tonnes a year. It will generate economic savings of over $5 million</p>
<p> a year, and avoid a further $142 million in costs. These are powerful</p>
<p> economic arguments of providing the assistance. If it puts a spark</p>
<p> into my New South Wales State Coalition colleagues to get moving with</p>
<p> regard to their State election as they are now in real time, then</p>
<p> that might also help.</p>
<p>Not all projects that applied for a tax rebate under this scheme have</p>
<p> been successful. A number are in a second round for further consideration.</p>
<p> Others are in different categories. For example the Tumut super mill</p>
<p> involving Visy, that's in a separate category and it's been</p>
<p> approved by the Federal Government and announced just before Christmas.</p>
<p> And it's a very exciting project for the Riverina and Monaro</p>
<p> regions, the start of art brown craft mill which will be located at</p>
<p> a very useful site at Tumut. In fact over 30 projects Australia wide</p>
<p> applied, ranging from road, rail and port projects, to gas pipe lines</p>
<p> and electricity generating projects. Some of those have missed out</p>
<p> also. Of course, can be further considered down the track pursuant</p>
<p> to the second round as I mentioned. The Commissioner of Taxation is</p>
<p> likely to make a second call for projects under this IBTOS scheme</p>
<p> next month.</p>
<p>These four projects announced today still have some hoops to jump</p>
<p> through. However the successful projects have been advised of their</p>
<p> conditional approval and the conditions under which the rebate will</p>
<p> apply. Subject to that satisfactory environmental process and assessment,</p>
<p> my colleague John Anderson, the Minister for Transport and Regional</p>
<p> Services, expects to give the final approval to these projects in</p>
<p> detail. The rebate will also be subject to the financial arrangements</p>
<p> of the projects being satisfactory to the ATO. We don't expect</p>
<p> any great difficulty in that regard. If the arrangements are approved</p>
<p> formally then all the relevant parties will enter into the lock-in</p>
<p> agreements associated with the IBTOS scheme.</p>
<p>For a tax rebate of up to about $71 million over five years, today's</p>
<p> announcement ensures that $900 million worth of infrastructure projects</p>
<p> can commence without delay generating thousands of jobs, environmental</p>
<p> benefits and economic growth. It is a worthy investment in Australia's</p>
<p> future. It is the first formal clearance and announcement subject</p>
<p> to those conditions, under the restructured Infrastructure Borrowing</p>
<p> Tax Offset Scheme, which is the new scheme replacing the previous</p>
<p> scheme, the subject of some abuse and rorting in the past in which</p>
<p> both Peter Costello and now John Anderson in another capacity have</p>
<p> carriage of and I am very much pleased to make this announcement this</p>
<p> day on behalf of the Australian Government.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, is it fair to say that these four projects would have</p>
<p> proceeded regardless of the rebate scheme?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Not absolutely....that cannot be absolutely said to be the case.</p>
<p> There is a fair chance that they would have otherwise proceeded. This</p>
<p> certainly makes the facilitation of these projects smoother and more</p>
<p> efficient, and I have no hesitation in stating that those directly</p>
<p> involved and the stakeholders directly involved will welcome this</p>
<p> facilitation.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, the Government's talked before about not picking</p>
<p> winners in terms of investment projects. How does the Government reconcile</p>
<p> that view about not picking out any particular industries in the decision</p>
<p> today to not grant these tax breaks.</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That's a fair question and that of course goes to the classic</p>
<p> arguments associated with that hoary old debate over picking winners.</p>
<p> In a perfect world, governments should set parameters and generic</p>
<p> programs and then step right back. But there is no such thing as an</p>
<p> absolute pure market place. There is no such thing as a level playing</p>
<p> field. And as a consequence glitches and points of congestion to occur.</p>
<p> It's with that in mind that on a very cautious basis, the Federal</p>
<p> Government has proceeded with the IBTOS scheme and what's more,</p>
<p> these projects are assessed against vigorous selection criteria which</p>
<p> is spelled out in the legislation. This is not just a hit and miss</p>
<p> process, a whim of a Cabinet Minister or ten. They are evaluated by</p>
<p> experts in the Department of Transport and Regional Services with</p>
<p> assistance from the Australian Tax Office. They are then considered</p>
<p> by an inter-departmental committee of officials. Recommendations then</p>
<p> go to the Employment and Infrastructure Committee of Cabinet as an</p>
<p> additional stage, then ultimately to the full Cabinet. It is a very</p>
<p> careful and rigorous process of selection, and as I say Cabinet now</p>
<p> has signed off on these four to this stage of approval under the process</p>
<p> and these are the first four. I think in 1999, the start of 1999 with</p>
<p> an economy growing at +5% there can be no complacency. That's</p>
<p> the figure historically for the last 12 months. The next 12 months</p>
<p> as we officially say, this will notch back. This is also an element</p>
<p> of activity and facilitation by the Federal Government to ensure onward</p>
<p> economic growth through what could be a very difficult trading period</p>
<p> world-wide.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, the total cost to Government is $71 million over five</p>
<p> years....</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Loss of revenue in a sense.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] revenue foregone, that's the total cost, there's</p>
<p> no additional cost as a result of this project ...?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is correct with regard to these four. But of course as they gather</p>
<p> momentum they will themselves generate additional revenue. There is</p>
<p> still money available within the cap for additional projects to be</p>
<p> approved. The scheme is capped at a total of $75 million per annum.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, you mentioned [inaudible] to go through. Can you say broadly</p>
<p> what they are?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>The criteria's straight out in the legislation. Basically they</p>
<p> have to stack up environmentally and be a environmental positive -</p>
<p> all things considered. They have to stack up in terms of sensible</p>
<p> broad parameters, and cost benefit, and not constitute yet another</p>
<p> disguised scheme from the big end of town to rort the payment of taxation.</p>
<p> And that's where the infrastructure bonds and other schemes went</p>
<p> wrong was the fact that the big end of town could climb into these</p>
<p> schemes, find the right apparatus to in fact get away with blue murder,</p>
<p> reduce their taxation exposure, but not actually do anything about</p>
<p> building actual infrastructure at the end of the day. The criteria,</p>
<p> laid out in the legislation, I refer you to that, but above all else</p>
<p> I don't underestimate, and neither would you my friend, the rigor</p>
<p> of the Australian Tax Office on a range of matters including ensuring</p>
<p> that these are not shonk projects but real and valuable projects.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] outstanding hoops to jump through.</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is the process yet to come is the environmental final sign off.</p>
<p> Essentially they are through all other hoops and Cabinet has approved</p>
<p> to that stage.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[inaudible] project in Queensland an applicant also under this scheme</p>
<p> and if so what's occurred with that project?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Fair question and I just want to check but I think I am right in saying</p>
<p> that they are in another category, yes. And they are not - it's</p>
<p> always the case of coming in with too many papers - there's one</p>
<p> other page which will tell me that. They are in a separate category</p>
<p> as was Visy as I mentioned. If you like, for a rule of thumb description</p>
<p> they are in the Mansfield process. I would like to take this opportunity</p>
<p> to say I spent four days - unusually long period of time - quite deliberately</p>
<p> going to Papua New Guinea just a week before Christmas. I was uneasy</p>
<p> about the capability of that project to supply gas from the very challenging</p>
<p> terrain of that part of Papua New Guinea and the other difficulties</p>
<p> including the local politics associated with major resource projects</p>
<p> in Papua New Guinea. I am very pleased to say today that having gone</p>
<p> out to Lake Kutubu, having gone through the terrain of the existing</p>
<p> oil field, which will gradually move to gas production under the project,</p>
<p> I am well satisfied on two counts that it's up to the experts</p>
<p> to say the field of gas is there and I gather it is but also the way</p>
<p> they have put the infrastructure into that area is very careful and</p>
<p> very cunning and with great care and respect to the environment. I</p>
<p> am satisfied on that count. But more particularly the one thing I</p>
<p> really wanted to look at was the extent of village liaison and cooperation</p>
<p> the Port Moresby royalty equation that does other things doesn't</p>
<p> it. It is on the ground liaison and cooperation of the project with,</p>
<p> and I am pleased to say that there is a huge programme involved practically</p>
<p> with health education in the surrounding villages. A bit like Ok Tedi</p>
<p> And unlike what Bougainville did 20 years ago which laid the pathway</p>
<p> for all that happened there. I mean, there was a huge gap between</p>
<p> the project and the local people. I actually am very happy to say</p>
<p> that there's a lot of good news stories in Papua New Guinea.</p>
<p> One of the best I believe that the lateral thinking project to provide</p>
<p> a pipeline from Papua New Guinea to Gladstone stacks up in terms of</p>
<p> the ability of the equation at the start point and the ability to</p>
<p> produce the gas and supply the gas to feed into that pipeline.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Mr Fischer, do the Commonwealth's most senior public servants</p>
<p> deserve a 40 per cent pay rise?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Okay, any other questions on this and I'll come to that?</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible]</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We've had an extraordinarily busy 1998. They're in various</p>
<p> stages of being processed. Bob Mansfield's been extremely busy.</p>
<p> There's no great delay but in the case of the pipeline I think</p>
<p> the next move is with private enterprise at Gladstone and that end</p>
<p> of the equation Cabinet stands ready and the Prime Minister, John</p>
<p> Howard, stands ready to really drive this process along with Minister</p>
<p> for Industry, Nick Minchin. And I don't anticipate any great</p>
<p> delays. We got Visy away before Christmas, but after the election</p>
<p> and quite deliberately so that the announcement might be seen in a</p>
<p> very non-partisan light and seen for what it is. Okay, now turning</p>
<p> to your question, you might care to repeat it although I do remember</p>
<p> it.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Do the Commonwealth top public servants, most senior public servants</p>
<p> deserve a 40 per cent pay rise or can it be justified?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's your figure, not mine. And at the end of the day</p>
<p> there is a process to be completed. I can confirm that no final decision</p>
<p> has been made with regard to the amount of pay increase for federal</p>
<p> public servants, senior federal public servants. The whole matter</p>
<p> is still before the remuneration tribunal. I note from some reports</p>
<p> today of suggestions of a very large pay rise. At the end of the process</p>
<p> I do not anticipate that it will be as large as has been variously</p>
<p> reported today. That, of course, leaves the situation where many senior</p>
<p> federal public servants will be below the pay levels of senior State</p>
<p> public servants. As I said on AM this morning, the Federal</p>
<p> Government has little choice but to properly remunerate senior public</p>
<p> servants so that we can have quality, cut-through, capable administrators.</p>
<p> And we have a very strong team of senior public servants. One of the</p>
<p> delights of being in Federal Government has been the very professional</p>
<p> high standard I have encountered with regard to the public service</p>
<p> in general and the senior public service specifically. We have slipped</p>
<p> behind the pace, and just to flesh that out one little bit more I</p>
<p> point out that for 1997 the Secretaries of Federal departments received</p>
<p> a 1.5 per cent pay increase. For 1998, they received a two per cent</p>
<p> pay increase. Compare that, happily in one sense, under 13 years of</p>
<p> the Federal Labor Government real earnings for Australians, there's</p>
<p> inflation adjusted wages and salaries rose by six per cent. But in</p>
<p> the two years the Federal Coalition has been in power the comparative</p>
<p> figure is in fact real wages rose by 10 per cent. So Australian workers</p>
<p> have had a 10 per cent pay rise in the first couple of years of the</p>
<p> Federal Coalition Government. It happens that senior federal public</p>
<p> servants have had a 3.5 per cent pay rise and there's been further</p>
<p> slippage against the State public servants. Now, I just would make</p>
<p> the point I really don't want to spend too much time in the position</p>
<p> of having to defend what has not yet been finally decided. But I will</p>
<p> defend the principle, the feds ultimately will get the quality of</p>
<p> service from their public service and their senior elements of their</p>
<p> public service for which we pay. And if we don't pay a reasonable</p>
<p> amount then we are going to have a drop off in that performance. I</p>
<p> might add, as the Prime Minister has pointed out, there's no</p>
<p> permanency any more. These are quite specific performance orientated</p>
<p> contracts and that factor should be taken into account.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Has the Government recommended to the remuneration tribunal what the</p>
<p> pay rise should be?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>There's an ongoing process, it has not been completed. Ultimately</p>
<p> it comes back to the Government and therefore I cannot confirm or</p>
<p> deny any particular amount. But is the tribunal considering this matter?</p>
<p> Yes they are. Is there some proper liaison with the Government with</p>
<p> regard to that consideration? Yes there is - but that is internal</p>
<p> to the process of the Government. At the end of the day, will and</p>
<p> should we be paying senior federal public servants more? Yes we should.</p>
<p> And it is not the most popular cause to defend but these are the other</p>
<p> elements of having the privilege of being the Deputy Prime Minister</p>
<p> and Acting Prime Minister in the first fortnight of each January.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>Should Max Moore-Wilton be part of this process? He is basically pushing</p>
<p> the process that will give him a pay rise that's been reported</p>
<p> to be about $80,000?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>One thing about the Cabinet processes under John Howard is that he</p>
<p> does not hesitate to ask those directly affected by discussions in</p>
<p> the Cabinet room to leave the Cabinet room for the duration of those</p>
<p> discussions. Whilst I don't reveal the detailed operations of</p>
<p> Cabinet or the content of those discussions I will say on this occasion</p>
<p> that there's been rigorous application of that quite correct</p>
<p> practice.</p>
<p>JOURNALIST:</p>
<p>[Inaudible] fair, Mr Fischer?</p>
<p>ACTING PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I am not an expert on the remuneration of public servants, federal</p>
<p> or State. But I am an expert on one other thing, this business of</p>
<p> credit cards being issued to State ministers of the Crown year on</p>
<p> year, used and abused. To be fair, they are very busy people, they'll</p>
<p> inevitably make mistakes, they will confuse personal payments with</p>
<p> proper payments which should be reimbursed by the Crown in relation</p>
<p> to their activities as ministers. If State public servants with their</p>
<p> big pay can't sort out one thing they might like to start 1999</p>
<p> by sorting out the credit card shamozzle at the State level which</p>
<p> has led to ministers having to resign, led to difficulties at various</p>
<p> States around this land. I, as Deputy Prime Minister of this country,</p>
<p> do not have a Commonwealth Government credit card. If I have an expenditure</p>
<p> as I belt through seven countries since polling day on working trade</p>
<p> Visyts I have to submit a cheque for that and get reimbursed or there's</p>
<p> another very tight process that applies. If it's good enough</p>
<p> for the Deputy Prime Minister of this country and all my ministerial</p>
<p> colleagues not to have a governmental credit card then perhaps these</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
