<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4407</transcript-id>
    <title>THE 1977 REFERENDUM</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004407.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS 22 MAY 1977<br />
THE 1977 REFERENDUM<br />
I would like to thank the people of Australia for their<br />
support. There has been a strong ' yes' vote nationally<br />
for all four proposals and it is clear that three of the<br />
questions have been carried in four or more States.<br />
Although it will be some time before we have a final<br />
result it now seems unlikely that the question on simultaneous<br />
elections will have the requisite majority of four States,<br />
despite the fact that a majority of Australians have<br />
registered their support for it. In New South Wales,<br />
Victoria and South Australia, every electorate voted ' yes'<br />
on all four questions, and there was substantial support<br />
in the other States.<br />
In the 77 years of Federation a total of 36 questions have<br />
been put at referendums on 16 different occasions.<br />
Until now, the the total of Constitutional changes approved<br />
at these referendums was only five.<br />
As a result of yesterday's vote the total now rises to at least<br />
eight. Yesterday's result certainly vindicates the great<br />
effort that went into the Hobart Constitutional Convention<br />
last year and into the ' yes' campaign the past two weeks.<br />
I regret that a misleading campaign was mounted against the<br />
simultaneous election proposal. It will be sometime before<br />
we know how effective those deceptions were.<br />
I am particularly gratified that the proposal for filling<br />
casual vacancies has been accepted. This is perhaps the most<br />
important of the four questions. Its passage will put a halt<br />
to the manipulation which the Labor administration attempted<br />
in 1974. It means the right of the people to have their choice<br />
preserved has been protected, in relation to both State and<br />
Federal Government. The proposal made great sense and I notice<br />
it won overwhelming support. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
Justice has now been done in respect of the Northern<br />
Territory and Australian Capital Territory. Residents of those<br />
Territories will have the same rights to vote in any future<br />
referendums as their fellow Australians.<br />
Also as a result of this referendum a retiring age will be<br />
put for appointments to the High Court.<br />
Again, I would like to thank the people of Australia for their support<br />
000oo00000 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
