<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1600</transcript-id>
    <title>MONTREAL CANADA  -   SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT AT MAYCRAL DINNER, CITY HALL. MONTREAL  5TH JUNE,1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001600.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
VISIT TO US, CANA. DA UlK<br />
MONTREAL, CANADA<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT<br />
AT MAYORAL DINNER, CITY HALL, MONTREAL JUNE, 1967<br />
Mr. Mayor and Madame Drapeau:<br />
It was a very happy decision of the Australian Government to<br />
decide to be represented at the Montreal Exposition. Our motives were<br />
largely stimulated by the friendship over so many years with the people of<br />
Canada and our desire to join in celebrating the centennial of this great<br />
country of yours.<br />
You mentioned some of the origins we have in common and you<br />
hrought to mind a little jingle that was originated about the early period that<br />
you mentioned in the history of my own country:<br />
" True patriots we, for be it understood<br />
Wle left our country for our country's good."<br />
But I think that our Mother Country, if it could look at the results that the<br />
offspring have produced, would be sorry to have lost them and be very<br />
proud of the achievements through those years. It is also, I understand, not<br />
merely the centennial of Canada but the 325th anniversary of this beautiful<br />
and historic city of Montreal. I say you have cause for a double celebration.<br />
Although the principal purpose of my own visit here was to join<br />
in celebrating Australia's special day, I feel that already there has been<br />
added benefit for us from the very valuable discussions we held with your<br />
Prime Minister and members of the Cabinet, the new knowledge that we have<br />
acquired of the remarkable growth which has proceeded in Canada since my<br />
own first visit here for the Parliamentary conference in Ottawa fifteen years<br />
ago. I scarcely recognised Ottawa. I found it equally difficult to see<br />
in the Montreal I had visited for only a short and inadequate few hours on<br />
that occasion the beautiful city ou have here today. But we have a strong<br />
feeling, and I was delighted to fhcS your Prime Minister echoing this,<br />
sentiment that our two countriesfgrowing in strength with their economies<br />
burgeoning, with their populations growing rather more rapidly than those<br />
of other countries and with a special relationship with some of the m jor<br />
powers of the world you oniented principally as you have been 4n the past<br />
towards the North Atlantic and the North America, we with a growing and<br />
special place in Asia and the Pacific. If we can contrive to keep closer<br />
together in the years ahead than we have in the past, if we can think closely<br />
together on the great international questions which will affect the future<br />
of mankind, then I am certain that Canada and Australia together will be<br />
able to make a significant impact for constructive and useful purposes on<br />
the thinking of other countries of the world, and it is with that object in<br />
mind I have pressed your Prime Minister to come and visit our country. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I hope there will be an increasing stream of Canadians who will<br />
find if they attempt the journey that it is not so formidable an undertaking<br />
as they might have imagined. There are some very agreeable stopping<br />
points along the way Tahiti, if you must practice your French; there is<br />
Honolulu, if you wish to see how a multi-racial community has turned that<br />
lovely island into a thriving economy and a very enjoyable place to stay; and<br />
then Australia, the oldest continent but with some of the youngest and the<br />
liveliest people that you will find on the earth.<br />
Je regrette profonddment, monsieur le Maire, que je ne peux<br />
parler francais bien. Mon francais, mon professeur a mon ecole etait un<br />
ecossais. Ainsi ce'st difficile pour moi parler en francais a vous.<br />
Mon secretaire, however, in order to meet this situation, has given me these<br />
lines which I am very happy to adopt. Vous avez une ville ancienne et<br />
gracieuse et vous en avez fait cadeau a toutes les nations pour cette<br />
exposition brillante. Au nom del'Australie, je vous apporte nos meilleurs<br />
souhaits et nos congratulations les plus cordiales et chaleureuses.<br />
You must be tremendously gratified with the success which has<br />
already become evident for this imaginative courageously planned,<br />
ambitiously projected exposition. You, Mr Mayor, have become something<br />
of an institution in your own right. I became very envious when I learned<br />
that of the 48 members of your council, you can count upon the regular<br />
support of 45 of them. That is a majority which any politician like myself<br />
would very much envy but I am sure that it is due to your own drive, your<br />
own courage, your own enterprise that this marvellous exposition has been<br />
brought into being and has become a success to be admired around the world.<br />
We are greatly looking forward to visiting it ourselves. We are<br />
proud that Australia should be accorded its own national day of celebration.<br />
I hope we shall prove worthy of it. I am told that just about four times as<br />
many people have visited our pavilion as was estimated for us, in advance.<br />
I don't claim that it is because those who want to rest there find themselves<br />
addressed by people like myself as they recline in those chairs; indeed,<br />
it has been cut down quite considerably. Well, if that is a mark of popularity,<br />
perhaps I should take that hint myself and content myself with saying on<br />
behalf of all my party here with me and indeed on behalf of Australia, which<br />
is proud to be represented here with you and I am sure will derive advantage<br />
from our presence with you, the best wishes for the continuing success of the<br />
Exposition and our warmest congratulations, Mr Mayor and your gracious<br />
wife, and to all associated with you in this marvellously conceived project. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
