<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10842</transcript-id>
    <title>NEW CHIEF JUSTICE</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/05/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that it will be recommended to the Governor-General</p>
<p> that the Honourable Justice (Anthony) Murray Gleeson AC, be appointed</p>
<p> as Chief Justice of the High Court of Australia.</p>
<p>Justice Gleeson, 59, is currently Chief Justice of the Supreme Court</p>
<p> of New South Wales and has held this position since 1988. In addition</p>
<p> he has been the President of the Judicial Commission of New South</p>
<p> Wales since 1988 and Lieutenant Governor of New South Wales since</p>
<p> 1989.</p>
<p>Prior to his appointment to the New South Wales Supreme Court, Chief</p>
<p> Justice Gleeson had a distinguished career at the Bar. Having been</p>
<p> appointed a Queen's Counsel in 1974 he went on to become President</p>
<p> of the New South Wales Bar Association from 1984 to 1986. At the Bar</p>
<p> he had an extensive general practice with significant expertise in</p>
<p> equity, commercial and constitutional work and was held in the highest</p>
<p> regard for his advocacy skills.</p>
<p>The proposed appointment arises following the imminent retirement,</p>
<p> with effect from 22 May 1998, of the current Chief Justice of the</p>
<p> High Court, the Hon. Sir Gerard Brennan AC KBE.</p>
<p>I am sure that Mr Justice Gleeson will serve as Chief Justice with</p>
<p> great distinction. His experience, skill and superb legal abilities</p>
<p> admirably fit him for the task.</p>
<p>There will be an opportunity, at the time of his retirement, to say</p>
<p> something of Sir Gerard Brennan's work as Chief Justice.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
