<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3817</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, 9 JULY 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/07/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003817.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
9 JULY 1975<br />
WHEN I CALLED THE PARLIAMENT TOGETHER I CHALLENGED<br />
THE OPPOSITION, TO PUT UP OR SHUT UP. THEY HAVE FAILED<br />
ON BOTH COUNTS, THE OPPOSITION'S CASE HAS BEEN REVEALED<br />
AS UTTERLY THREADBARE, UTTERLY WITHOUT SUBSTANCE,<br />
NOT ONLY DID THEY FAIL TO SUBSTANTIATE ANY SPECIFIC<br />
CHARGE AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT OR ANY MINISTER; THEY<br />
FAILED TO MAKE ANY SPECIFIC CHARGE, I LISTENED CAREFULLY<br />
TO MR FRASER. HE ASKED A SERIES OF VAGUE, EMOTIVE QUESTIONS,<br />
: HEWOULDN'T LEND HIS NAME HE WOULDN'T GO ON THE RECORD<br />
. WITH ONE SPECIFIC, PRECISE ACCUSATION OF ILLEGALITY OR<br />
:: IMPROPRIETY. HE HID BEHIND THE PRESS. HE HID BEHIND<br />
A BARRAGE OF SMEARS AND GENERALISATIONS. HE DEMANDED<br />
13bED<br />
INQUIRIES AND ROYAL COMMISSIONS, HIS LINE &amp; 4z? DOWN<br />
TO THIS: " I'VE MADE A WHOLE LOT OF ACCUSATIONS ABOUT<br />
SCANDALS AND BREACHES OF THE LAW. I HAVEN'T GOT A SHRED<br />
OF EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT THEM, BUT YOU HOLD A ROYAL<br />
COMMN, S M.. A<br />
COMMISSION AND SOMETHING MAY TURN UP," </p>
<p>WELL NOTHING WILL TURN UP NOTHING CAN TURN UP<br />
BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOTHING TO HIDE, WE SOUGHT<br />
TO BORROW MONEY OVERSEAS FOR A NUMBER OF SPECIFIC AND<br />
NECESSARY PURPOSES. I OUTLINEDTHOSE PURPOSES TODAY;<br />
THEY HAD ALREADY BEEN GIVEN IN PARLIAMENT. WE NEEDED<br />
CAPITAL ON A LARGE SCALE AND MAKE NO MISTAKE, WE STILL<br />
NEED CAPITAL TO DEVELOP OUR ENERGY RESOURCES AND KEEP<br />
THOSE RESOURCES IN AUSTRALIAN HANDS. THOSE OBJECTIVES<br />
. WERE PROPER AND THE MEANS WERE PROPER,<br />
I SHOWED THAT AT NO TIME WAS PARLIAMENT<br />
SMISLED ABOUT THE NATURE, SIZE OR SOURCE OF OUR LOAN<br />
PROPOSALS, THE PROPOSAL WAS ECONOMICALLY SOUND,<br />
LEGAL ADICE WAS OBTAINED FROM THE . GOVERNMENT'S LEGAL<br />
ADVISERS BEFORE THE MINISTER FOR MINERALS AND ENERGY WAS<br />
' GIVEN AUTHORITY TO PROCEED WITH NEGOTIATIONS FOR THE LOAN,<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THE AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT Ws PROTECTED<br />
AT ALL POINTS IN CONNECTION WITH THE PROPOSED BORROWING,<br />
PROPER CHECKS WERE MADE ON THE BONA FIDES OF THE<br />
INTERMEDIARY INVOLVED, NOT A CENT HAS BEEN PAID OR<br />
S WILL BE PAID OR IS LIABLE TO BE PAID TO THE INTERMEDIARY.<br />
THERE HAS BEEN NO IMPROPRIETY. THERE HAVE BEEN NO<br />
BREACHES OF THE LAW. UNDER THIS GOVERNMENT AUSTRALIA HAS<br />
ACHIEVED THE HIGHEST POSSIBLE STATUS A TRIPLE-A RATING<br />
SAS AN INTERNATIONAL BORROWER, THAT STATUS REMAINS UNCHANGED,<br />
If L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
