<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5648</transcript-id>
    <title>ELECTORATE TALK</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/09/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005648.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 5: 00PM'<br />
A<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA SUNDAY, SEPTEMBER 13 1981<br />
ELECTORATE TALK<br />
( The weekly Prime Ministerial electorate talk is today given<br />
by the Minister for Employment and Youth Affairs, Mr Neil Brown).<br />
I wish to talk to you today about the positive action that is<br />
being taken by the Government to help young people. Let me say<br />
at the outset and there should be no doubt about this<br />
that the Government is committed to increasing education,<br />
training and work experience opportunities for the young.<br />
By increasing these opportunities we will ensure that young<br />
people can share in the prosperity of Australia, take advantage<br />
of the expanding labour market and obtain stable and rewarding<br />
employment. The challenges have been to get the economy moving; to increase<br />
the number of permanent jobs available; to make the education<br />
system more responsive to the needs of the young; to ensure<br />
ycung people acquire the skills and experience which they need<br />
and which employers seek; and to provide better guidance on<br />
careers. The responsible policies pursued by the Government on the<br />
, ec-onomic front have been successful in expanding activity<br />
and confidence in the privAte sector and producing higher<br />
employment growth. Full-time employment has grown by 5.3%<br />
over the last two years. The growth in full-time employment<br />
for 15 to 19 year olds was over The Government's<br />
achievements to date are encouraging, but more needs -to be<br />
done. I can assure you the Government will vigorously pursue<br />
its efforts to build on this success.<br />
During this year, substantial funds will be expended on manpower<br />
and training programmes by the Government with particular<br />
emphasis on young people.<br />
School to Work Transition<br />
The Government's School to Work Transition policy provides<br />
education and training opportunities within schools and TAFE<br />
colleges. we have committed ourselves to expend $ 150 million<br />
over five years and in 1981/ 82 a total of 16,000 young people<br />
will be assisted to atte ' nd educational programmes, pre-vocational<br />
courses, pre-employment icourses and pre-apprenticeship courses..<br />
To encourage young people to enter such courses the Government<br />
pays a pays a transition allowance which is higher than the<br />
unemployment benefit. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Skill Training<br />
A number of new initiatives to provide skill training have been.<br />
taken by the Government. We have substantially increased<br />
grants to TAFE colleges for this purpose $ 206.8 million<br />
in 1981/ 82, we will pay $ 72 million to employers under CRAFT<br />
this year in respect of 95,000 apprentices, we have allocated<br />
$ 8 million to the Skills in Demand Programme under which<br />
almost 70% of the training places -approved to date have<br />
involved people under 25 years of age and, $ 5.3 million<br />
is available to aid and stimulate the development of training<br />
programmes through all sectors of industry and commerce.<br />
Work Experience and Training<br />
The Government has taken action to ensure young people acquire<br />
the skills and experience which they need and which employers<br />
seek by establishing the Special Youth Employment Training<br />
Programme. This programme will provide nearly 70,000 new<br />
places this year.<br />
Counselling and Job Placement<br />
The Commonwealth Employment Service in 1980/ 81 increased the<br />
number of people under 21 years referred for job interviews<br />
by 20% and increased the placement of these young people by<br />
18%. Also, the CES has expanded its programmes on-occupational.<br />
information and has developed career reference centres and work.<br />
information centres.<br />
The Government's Record<br />
If you want con-firmation of the real commitment of the<br />
Government in work experience and training, you should look<br />
at the Government's record over recent years. Expenditure i. n<br />
1979/ 80 was $ 112 million; 1980/ 81 was $ 165 million; and 1981/ 82.<br />
iwill be $ 203 million. Whilst expenditure figures alone do not<br />
tell the full story it should be recognised that these are<br />
expenditure on targetted programmes to help young people who<br />
need work experience and training to obtain permanent employment.<br />
They exclude educational expenditure on the school to work<br />
transition programme and the education programme for unemployed<br />
youth. Under our programmes, over 210,000 young persons will be<br />
assisted this financial year higher than at any other time.<br />
If it emerges that some young people are unable to use the<br />
expanded opportunities provided by our extensive range of<br />
programmes because of their geographic location or because<br />
of their personal i~ nsuitability to the present programmes,<br />
the Government will, of'course, look very closely at the need<br />
for different or new forms of assistance or special programmes.<br />
This demonstrates that the Government has a firm commitment<br />
to assist the youth of Australia and help them to take an<br />
active and constructive role in society.<br />
National Youth Advisory group<br />
A further illustration of theGovernment's interest in young<br />
people is the National Youth Advisory Group. The group providE! s<br />
the Government with advice on young people's needs and concerns;<br />
informs the Government of the impact of its programmes </p>
<p>-3<br />
affecting young people; and suggests ways of improving<br />
communication links between young people and the Government.<br />
The success of the group s; hows that the Government has here<br />
an influential body which can provide a very valuable link<br />
between the youth community of Australia and the Government.<br />
Before leaving you this evening, I would like to refer to the<br />
latest monthly labour force survey which illustrates the<br />
positive contribution the Government is making to youth<br />
employment. Over the year to August 1981, the level of teenage<br />
full-time unemployment fell by 17.6%; the number of teenagers<br />
seeking full-time employment fell by 19,600 ; the number of<br />
teenagers looking for their first full-time job fell by<br />
15,700; and the number of 15-19 year olds seeking other than<br />
their first job fell by 3,900.<br />
Whilst some young people are experiencing problems in finding<br />
employment, we are determined to help them in their endeavours<br />
to find su . itable employment by strong and positive action.<br />
As Minister for Employment and Youth Affairs I am particularly<br />
concerned to ensure the needs of young people are considered<br />
by the Goverment and that programmes of assistance are instituted<br />
to meet those needs where necessary. It is important for<br />
Australia that the young people be given every assistance<br />
and encouragement. as they are our hope for the future.<br />
0 0 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
