<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1428</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: PM 111/1966 - MEETING BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA AND THE PRIME MINISTER OF MALTA</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/11/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001428.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
66/ 153<br />
EMBARGO: NOT FOR RELEASE BEFORE 6 P. M.<br />
SUNDAY, 6TH NOVEMBER<br />
FOR PRESS: P M. No. 111/ 1966<br />
MEETING BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTER OF<br />
AUSTRALIA AND THE PRIME MINISTER OF<br />
MA LTA<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Holt, and Dr. Borg Olivier, the<br />
Prime Minister of Malta met in Melbourne on Saturday.<br />
They were able to renew their friendly contacts and to discuss<br />
together matters of common Interest in their countries. More than 65, CC<br />
settlers from Malta have come to Australia since the second World War.<br />
The Maltese living in Australia represent one-fifth of Malta's present<br />
population and constitute the largest community of Maltese origin outside<br />
Malta itself, Australia and Malta are both members of the Commonwealth<br />
and have interests in trade and migration in particular. The two Prime<br />
Mf-n isters discussed ways and means of ensuring closer co-operation between<br />
the two countries and undertook to follow up their discussions on trade.<br />
0 Mr. Holt informed Dr. Borg Olivier that the Australian<br />
Government had decided to establish a High Commission in Malta and would<br />
shortly be appointing a High Commissioner. Mr. Holt further informed<br />
Dr. Borg Olivier that the requirement of re-entry permits for Maltese<br />
settlers travelling outside Australia would be abolished as from a date to<br />
be announced shortly.<br />
They also discussed Commonwealth affairs in the light of<br />
the Prime Ministers' Conference held in London in September and which<br />
they both attended.<br />
CANBERRA, 6th November, 1966. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
