<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4002</transcript-id>
    <title>GOULBURN ADDRESS - MONDAY 8 DECEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004002_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
GOULBURN ADDRESS MONDAY 8 DECEMBER, 1975<br />
IN THIS ELECTION CAMPAIGN, THE LIBERAL AND NATIONAL<br />
COUNTRY PARTIES HAVE PUT FORWARD POSITIVE AND<br />
CONSTRUCTIVE POLICIES WHICH COME TO GRIPS WITH THE<br />
PROBLEMS FACING AUSTRALIA.<br />
THE A. L. P. HAS NOT OFFERED ONE CONSTRUCTIVE SUGGESTION<br />
ONil THESE PROBLEMS,<br />
THE CLOSEST MR. WHITLAM CAME TO CONSTRUCTIVE POLICIES<br />
WAS WHEN HE HELP UP A COPY OF OUR POLICIES EVEN<br />
THEN HE HELD THEM AT ARM'S LENGTH,<br />
IN THE FIRST WEEK OF THE CAMPAIGN, MR. WHITLAM<br />
SAID HE WAS GOING TO STAND ON. HIS RECORD THE<br />
ONLY PROBLEM WAS, WHICH RECORD WAS HE GOING TO STAND<br />
ON RECORD INFLATION, RECORD INDUSTRIAL STRIFE,<br />
OR RECORD UNEMPLOYMENT. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
BUT PERHAPS WE ARE EXAGGERATING MR. WHITLAM'S<br />
FAILURE TO DEAL WITH THE UNEMPLOYMENT PROBLEMI<br />
THOUGH HE COULDN'T FIND A JOB FOR 400,000 AUSTRALIANS,<br />
HE CERTAINLY SUCCEEDED IN FINDING A JOB FOR HIS SON,<br />
LABOR'S INCOMPETENCE LEAVES MORE THAN ENOUGH<br />
SCOPE FOR JOKES ABOUT MR. WHITLAM AND HIS MINISTRY<br />
OF SACKED MEN LABOR'S SAD SACKS,<br />
BUT TODAY, WE MUST TALK SERIOUSLY ABOUT THE TYPE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA WE WANT.<br />
ON DECEMBER 13, YOU WILL BE DECIDING THE FUTURE<br />
OF AUSTRALIA.<br />
YOU WILL DECIDE WHAT KIND OF COUNTRY YOU WANT<br />
FOR YOUR CHILDREN AND GRANDCHILDREN </p>
<p>DO YOU WANT A SOCIALIST-AUSTRALIA?<br />
DOMINATED BY BIG-GOVERNMENT; BIG BUREAUCRACY,<br />
BY FORMS, RED TAPE; REGULATIONS AN4D CONTROLS?<br />
DO YOU WANT AUSTRALIA RUINED BY SOCIALIST<br />
I NCOMPETENCE?<br />
OR DO YOU WANT AUSTRALIA TO BE FREE, DEMOCRATIC<br />
AND PROSPEROUS?<br />
OUR WAY OF LIFE HAS BEEN BUILT BY PEOPLE FROM<br />
ALMOST EVERY COUNTRY IN THE WORLD.<br />
YOU OR YOUR PARENTS OR YOUR GRANDPARENTS CAME<br />
TO AUSTRALIA BECAUSE IT WAS A NEW COUNTRY<br />
A FREE COUNTRY WHEN MEN AND WOMEN COULD DECIDE<br />
FOR THEMSELVES HO' 14. T-HEY WIANTED TO LIVE THEIR LIVES-. </p>
<p>PEOPLE HAVE COME TO AUSTRALIA BECAUSE IT IS<br />
A LAND OF OPPORIUITY--A LAND FREE FROM THE<br />
FEARS, THE WARS OF OTHER PARTS OF THE WORLD.<br />
THE MOST ENTERPRISING, THE MOST ADVENTUROUS<br />
THE MOST FAR-SIGHTED FROM OTHER COUNTRIES HAVE<br />
MADE THE LONG JOURNEY TO AUSTRALIA.<br />
TOGETHER ALL OF YOU HERE OUR PARENTS AND<br />
OUR GRANDPARENTS HAVE BUILT A COUNTRY TO BE<br />
PROUD OF<br />
AUSTRALIANS CAN HOLD THEIR HEADS UP ANYWHERE<br />
IN THE WORLD FOR THEIR ACHIEVEMENTS.<br />
IiN SPORT<br />
IN MEDICAL RESEARCH<br />
IiN THE ARTS, MUSIC, PAINTING, WRITING<br />
IN THE GREAT ENTERPRISE AND VISION<br />
IT HAS TAKEN TO BUILD AUSTRALIA </p>
<p>t4<br />
BUT OUR PROUDEST ACHIEVEMENT AS A PEOPLE IS THAT<br />
WE HAVE BUILT A COUNTRY WHICH CAN GUARANTEE A DECENT<br />
LIFE FOR ALL AUSTRALIANS RICH AND POOR, IN THE<br />
CITIES AND IN THE COUNTRY, OLD AND NEW<br />
NO OTHER COUNTRY CAN OFFER THE OPPORTUNITY, THE<br />
SOCIAL EQUALITY, THE TOLERANCE, THE FREEDOM, THE<br />
CONCERN FOR ONE'S FELLOWMAN, THE GOOD LIFE<br />
THAT AUSTRALIANS CAN ENJOY,<br />
NO OTHER COUNTRY HAS THE OPPORTUNITY THAT WE HAVE<br />
TO BE AN EXAMPLE TO THE WORLD OF WHAT FREE PEOPLE<br />
CAN DO.<br />
WE HAVE ACHIEVED THE BEST. BECAUSE WE HAVE<br />
ENCOURAGED THE BEST-BY ENCOURAGING THE BEST<br />
EFFORTS OF ALL WE tAN PROVIDE THE BEST LIFE<br />
TO ALL<br />
THIS IS THE AUSTRALIAN WAY </p>
<p>THE IDEALS WE ALL SHARE BUILD ON THE BEST<br />
ELEMENTS OF THE AUSTRALIAN WAY<br />
WE WANT EQUAL EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES<br />
FOR ALL<br />
WE WANT-TO ASSIST OTHE VERY BEST OF<br />
OUR ABILITY THE DISADVANTAGED AND<br />
THOSE IN NEED<br />
WE WANT TO PROVIDE ALL AUSTRALIANS WITH A<br />
BASIC LEVEL OF SECURITY BELOW WHICH NO-ONE CAN<br />
INVOLUNTARILY FALL<br />
* WE WANT TO ENSURE THAT ALL AUSTRALIANS<br />
CAN FIND A JOB -AND A SATISFYING JOB<br />
aw./ WE WANT TO ENCOURAGE THE DIFFERENT TALENTS<br />
THAT PEOPLE HAVE -AND TO BE TOLERANT OF<br />
DIFFERENCES </p>
<p>WE WANT TO ENCOURAGE PEOPLE TO COMPETE<br />
TO DO BETTER TO IMPROVE THEIR OWN<br />
PERFORMANCE WE WANT TO ENCOURAGE AN APPRECIATION<br />
AND ADMIRATION OF ACHIEVEMENT SO THAT WE CANJ<br />
BUILD A GREAT AUSTRALIA<br />
WE WANT FREEDOM SO THAT PEOPLE CAN CONTROL<br />
THEIR OWN LIVES, MAKE THEIR OWN DECISIONS,<br />
FREEDOM FROM DICTATION AND DOMINATION BY<br />
POLITICIANS AND CIVIL SERVANTS.<br />
WE WANT AN AUSTRALIA BASED ON MUTUAL RESPECT<br />
BETWEEN ALL PEOPLE AN AUSTRALIA WHERE<br />
PEOPLE CAN RECOGNISE AND WORK TOGETHER IN<br />
THE COMMON INTEREST<br />
THAT IS THE KIND OF AUSTRALIA WE WANT </p>
<p>-6<br />
I BELIEVE THAT IS THE KIND OF AUSTRALIA YOU WANT<br />
THAT IS NOT THE KIND OF AUSTRALIA WE HAVE BEEN<br />
GETTING FOR THE LAST THREE YEARS<br />
FOR-THE LAST THREE YEARS THE LABOR PARTY HAS BEEN<br />
WRECKING AUSTRALIA IN ITS EFFORTS TO IMPOSE<br />
GREATER ANID GREATER GOVERNMENT CONTROL OVER EVERY<br />
ASPECT OF OUR LIVES<br />
MORE AND MORE GOVERNMEIIT SPENDING AND<br />
EXTRAVAGANCE HIGHER AND HIGHER TAXES<br />
MORE AND MORE BUREAUCRACY, REGULATIONS<br />
AND CONTROLS<br />
HAVE ALL DONE IMMENSE DAMAGE TO AUSTRALIA -MUCH<br />
GREATER DAMAGE THAN MANY PEOPLE REALISE </p>
<p>-7-<br />
BECAUSE INCOME TAX COLLECTED HAS GONE UP<br />
2 TIMES MOST OF AUSTRALIA'S FAMILIES FIND<br />
IT INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT TO MEET THEIR<br />
OWN NEEDS AS THEY SEE FIT<br />
NO WONDER PEOPLE ARE STRUGGLING TO MAKE ENDS<br />
MEET, AS A RESULT OF LABOR'S TAXES YOU HAVE TO WORK<br />
AN EXTRA MONTH A YEAR JUST TO PAY THE<br />
GOVERNMENTS BILLS<br />
WE WILL PUT AN END TO EXTRAVAGANCE AND WASTE<br />
LABOR'STAXES HAVE WIPED OUTTENS OF THOUSANDS<br />
OF-JOBS-IN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE<br />
THE MONEY THAT SHOULD HAVE GONE INTO<br />
BUILDING-FACTORIES, BUYING MACHINES,<br />
PROVIDING JOBS-HAS BEEN PAID IN TAXES TO<br />
THE GOVERNMENT </p>
<p>-8-<br />
UNDER LABOR AN AVERAGE OF 207 JOBS HAVE<br />
BEEN LOST EVERY DAY FOR THREE YEARS<br />
ONE JOB EVERY SEVEN MINUTES<br />
IT TOOK MR WHITLAM TO EXPORT OVERSEAS<br />
THE JOBS OF SO MANY THOUSANDS OF AUSTRALIANS<br />
ONLY GOUGH COULD DO IT,<br />
SOME ACHIEVEMENT, SOME RECORD?<br />
WE WILL RESTORE INCENTIVES AND GET AUSTRALIA<br />
MOVING AGAIN.<br />
LABOR'S TAXES, LABOR'S SOCIALISM<br />
FORCED UP PRICES.<br />
GAVE US THE WORST PERIOD OF RISING PRICES,<br />
THE HIGHEST INTEREST RATES IN AUSTRALIA'S<br />
HISTORY.<br />
MR-WHITLAM SAYS LABOR HAS LIVING-POLICIES<br />
HIS POLICIES MAY BE LIVING BUT THEY'RE KILLING<br />
AUSTRALIA. </p>
<p>-9-<br />
ON TOP OF ALL THIS WE HAVE HAD THREE YEARS OF<br />
A GOVERNMENT WHICH HAS DEGRADED THE STANDARDS OF<br />
PUBLIC LIFE<br />
NEVER BEFORE HAVE TWO MEN WHO WERE ACTING<br />
P. M. BEEN SACKED FOR DECEIVING THE PARLIAMENT<br />
NEVER BEFORE HAS A P. M. HAD TO BE SACKED<br />
BECAUSE HE TRIED TO GOVERN WITHOUT PARLIAMENT<br />
BECAUSE HE WAS PREPARED TO DAMAGE AUSTRALIA<br />
RATHER THAN FACE HIS MASTERS AND OURS<br />
THE PEOPLE<br />
AUSTRALIA CAN'T STAND THREE MORE YEARS OF THIS<br />
KIND OF GOVERNMENT<br />
YOU CAN TAKE A STAND FOR AUSTRALIA ON DECEMBER 13<br />
YOU CAN END LABOR'S TAX RIP-OFF AND GIVE<br />
REAL HELP TO AUSTRALIA'S FAMILIES<br />
OUR TAX REFORMS WILL DO THIS </p>
<p>YOU CAN GIVE POWER TO THE LEVELS OF<br />
GOVERNMENT CLOSEST TO THE PEOPLE,<br />
TO STATE. AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
OUR POLICIES WILL GIVE REAL FINANCIAL<br />
INDEPENDENCE TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT<br />
WE WILL STOP CANBERRA DICTATING TO EVERY<br />
OTHER GOVERNMENT IN AUSTRALIA,<br />
YOU CAN TAKE ACTION TO START JOB OPPORTUNITIES<br />
S EXPANDING AGAIN ON DECEMBER 13<br />
WE WILL GIVE INCENTIVE TO BUSINESS<br />
ESPECIALLY SMALL BUSINESS, TO START<br />
PROVIDING JOBS AGAIN.<br />
2 </p>
<p>11<br />
ON DECEMBER 13 YOU CAN GIVE AUSTRALIA A<br />
GOVERNMENT WHICH UNDERSTANDS THE PROBLEMS<br />
OF FARMERS AND IS PREPARED TO DO SOMETHING<br />
ABOUT THEM<br />
THERE CAN BE NO PROSPERITY IN AUSTRALIA UNLESS THE<br />
INTERDEPENDENCE OF PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN THE COUNTRY<br />
AND IN THE CITY,<br />
OUR POLICIES RECOGNISE THAT THE INTERESTS OF PEOPLE<br />
WHO LIVE IN THE COUNTRY AND PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN THE<br />
GREAT CITIES ARE INTERDEPENDENT.<br />
WE WILL-GIVE THE RURAL COMMUNITY THE CONFIDENCE<br />
AND CERTAINTY IT SO DESPERATELY NEEDS.<br />
WE WILL INITIATE THE FARM INCOME RESERVE FUND.<br />
WE WILL ESTABLISH A RURAL<br />
FINAiNCE, BANK FOR LONG-TERM </p>
<p>12<br />
AS RECOMMENDED BY THE I. A. C. THE SUPERPHOSPHATE<br />
BOUi'iTY WILL BE RE-ESTABLISHED AND ASSISTANCE<br />
WILL BE PROVIDED TO THE DEPRESSED BEEF<br />
INDUSTRY.<br />
WE WILL CONTINUE THE RESERVE PRICE SCHEME<br />
FOR WOOL AT NOT LESS THAN 250½ A KILO<br />
THROUGHOUT THE 1976-77 SEASON. THIS WILL<br />
GIVE LONG-TERM CONFIDENCE TO THE INDUSTRY.<br />
WE WILL EASE ELIGIBILITY PROVISIONS FOR<br />
UNEMPLOYMENT ASSISTANCE TO FARMERS.<br />
ON DECEMBER 13 YOU CAN GIVE AUSTRALIA A GOVERNMENT<br />
WILL WILL TAKE POSITIVE ACTION TO IMPROVE INDUSTRIAL<br />
RELATIONS WE WILL GIVE THE AUSTRALIAN WORKER A CHANCE<br />
TO CONTROL HIS OWN UNION<br />
WE WILL INTRODUCE SECRET BALLOTS FOR. ALL<br />
ELECTED OFFICIALS UNDER ELECTORAL OFFICE SUPERVISION </p>
<p>-13-<br />
IN EDUCATION OUR COMMITMENTS ARE ALSO CLEAR.<br />
WE W4ILL RESTORE THE TRIENNIAL FUINDING OF<br />
EDUCATION THAT LABOR HAD TO ABANDON.<br />
WE WILL USE OUR FUNDING TO OVERCOME THE<br />
INADEQUACIES IN EDUCATIONAL FACILITIES<br />
WHICH SEVERELY LIMIT THE EDUCATIONAL<br />
OPPORTUNITIES OF CHILDREN I MANY AREAS.<br />
WE WILL MAK( E SPECIAL PROVISION FOR DISADVANTAGED<br />
CHILDREN HANDICAPPED, ISOLATED, MIGRANT ANID<br />
ABORIGINAL CHILDREN,<br />
WE SUPPORT GIVING A BASIC GRANT TO CHILDREN<br />
AT ALL SCHOOLS BOTH GOVERNMENT AND<br />
NON-GOVERNMENT WHERE PUPILS ARE SUBJECT<br />
TO EDUCATIONAL DISADVANTAGE WE WILL ENSURE<br />
THAT THEY RECEIVE EXTRA FINANCIAL SUPPORT.<br />
SUCH A SYSTEM WAS RECOMMENDED BY THE<br />
SCHOOLS COMMISSION HI-IT1S RECENT REPORT.<br />
LABOR A. C. T. </p>
<p>r<br />
-14-<br />
ON DECEM1BER 13 YOU CAN GIVE GENUINE<br />
SECURITY TO THE DISADVANTAGED BASED<br />
ON REAL PROSPERITY.<br />
WE WILL MAINTAIN MEDIBANK.<br />
WE WILL MAINTAIN THE REAL VALUE OF PENSIONS.<br />
YOU CAN VOTE ON DECEMBER 13, TO RESTORE<br />
AUSTRALIA'S DEFENCES.<br />
WE WILL NOT GIVE YOUR MONEY TO<br />
AFRICAN TERRORISTS.<br />
WE WILL REVERSE MR WHITLAM'S RECOGNITION<br />
OF THE SOVIET OCCUPATION OF THE BALTIC<br />
STATES.<br />
WE WILL WORK IN OUR REGIOii ANlD ALL NATIONS<br />
WITH WHICH WE HAVE PHILOSOPHICAL COMMITMENTS<br />
IN COMMON. </p>
<p>TOGETHER WE CAN BUILD AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH<br />
EVERYONE HAS A CHANCE TO FIND SELF-RESPECT<br />
AND SELF-FULFILLMENT IN THEIR OWN WAY<br />
NOT CRUSHED INTO A MOULD OF SOCIALIST CONFORMITY,<br />
WE CAN BUILD AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH ALL CHILDREN<br />
START OUT IN LIFE WITH DECENT OPPORTUNITIES TO<br />
ACHIEVE TO THE BEST OF THEIR ABILITIES.<br />
AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH PEOPLE TAKE PRIDE IN THEIR<br />
WORK AND ARE REWARDED, NOT PENALISED FOR DOING<br />
THEIR BEST.<br />
AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH PARENTS CAN TAKE PRIDE<br />
IN HANDING ON TO THEIR CHILDREN THE VALUES<br />
THEY BELIEVE IN. </p>
<p>-16-<br />
AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH PEOPLE ARE PREPARED TO<br />
TAKE RESPONSIBILITY FOR THEIR OWN ACTIONS.<br />
AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH PEOPLE RECOGNISE THEIR<br />
COMMON INTERESTS AS WELL AS THEIR IMMEDIATE<br />
PERSONAL INTEREST.<br />
AN AUSTRALIA IN WHICH ALL ARE SECURE IN A<br />
MATERIAL SENSE, BUT WHERE SPIRITUAL AND ARTISTIC<br />
VALUES ARE APPRECIATED AND ENCOURAGED.<br />
AN AUSTRALIA WHERE THERE IS JUSTICE FOR ALL,<br />
AND WHERE ALL MEN ARE FREE TO LIVE IN DIGNITY<br />
AND SELF-RESPECT.<br />
THIS AUSTRALIA CAN BE OURS. </p>
<p>-17-<br />
IT CAN BE OURS IF YOU VOTE FOR FREEDOM AND<br />
PROSPERITY ON DECEMBER 13,<br />
BUT WE CANNOT AFFORD TO TAKE THE OUTCOME<br />
OF DECEMBER 13 FOR GRANTED.<br />
WE CANNOT AFFORD TO BE COMPLACENT.<br />
ONLY IF WE CONTINUE OUR UTMOST EFFORTS CAN WE<br />
LOOK FORWARD TO A BRIGHT NEW FUTURE.<br />
ON DECEMBER 13 YOU CAN TURN ON THE LIGHTS,<br />
000...<br />
w </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
