<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7961</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER LAUNCH OF ALP POLICY ON IMMIGRATION, ETHNIC AFFAIRS AND MULTICULTURALISM MELBOURNE - 15 MARCH 1990</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007961.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
LAUNCH OF ALP POLICY ON IMMIGRATION, ETHNIC AFFAIRS<br />
AND MULTICULTURALISM<br />
MELBOURNE 15 MARCH 199o<br />
Friends It gives me enormous satisfaction to stand before you today<br />
and to welcome you, as my Government has always welcomed<br />
you, as " fellow Australians".<br />
Satisfaction that, in those two words, is summed up the<br />
vision of a genuinely multicultural Australia to which all<br />
our people no matter what their birthplace or their<br />
colour, their religion or first language -can feel<br />
committed. Satisfaction and also pride. Because if there is one<br />
thing that our seven years of Government will have proved to<br />
our ethnic communities, and which they will bear in mind as<br />
they cast their vote on March 24, it is that the Labor<br />
Government delivers.<br />
My Government does not indulge in hollow rhetoric and smooth<br />
slogans. It delivers substance, realistic policies and real<br />
answers. It does not look back with misplaced nostalgia to a<br />
supposedly uniform Australia that has never existed. It<br />
looks forward to a vibrant and diverse Australia in which<br />
all our people live and work together as equals, in harmony.<br />
It does not remember its ethnic communities only when there<br />
ian election on. It consults with them, with their<br />
representatives, with their media, as part of the routine of<br />
Government. Friends If you think bock over the last term of my Government, and<br />
when you examine our achievements in the area of immigration<br />
policy, ethnic affairs and multiculturalism, you will<br />
recognise one unarguable truth. We do not, nor will we<br />
ever, sell out our principles for short-term political<br />
advantage. 1-1.3 i I U A I </p>
<p>On that you have my word.<br />
We will not, explicitly or implicitly, seek to return to an<br />
immigration policy which discriminates between people on the<br />
basis of ethnic origin.<br />
We will not, by the sly wink or discreet nudge, treat some<br />
Australians as more Australian than others.<br />
We will not, by carefully avoiding the word, seek to water<br />
down our vision of a multicultural Australia offering equal<br />
opportunity for all.<br />
In 1983 I gave my word.<br />
I outlined a vision of an Australia bound together by<br />
co-operation and consensus, rather than torn and divided by<br />
confrontation. I promised to lead Australia to a future<br />
free of prejudice and discrimination and offering equal<br />
opportunity for all our people.<br />
In the policy I launch today is set out the record of my<br />
Governments since 1983 in the area of immigration, ethnic<br />
and multicultural affairs.<br />
I am very happy to stand before you on this record.<br />
It lays the foundations for the future.<br />
It lies at the very heart of the program that I delivered at<br />
the ALP policy launch in Brisbane just over a week ago.<br />
At that launch I presented a comprehensive, realistic,<br />
responsible and achievable plan for Australia's future.<br />
I set forward an agenda for a fair society with opportunity<br />
open to all Australians wherever they were horn, whatever<br />
their background.<br />
Those of you who watched the launch will have been moved, as<br />
all of us present were, at the stirring rendition given to<br />
our national anthem by a young Australian, Clare Gormley,<br />
who can trace her roots to Ireland, Germany and Papua New<br />
Guinea. Her talent and self-confidence symbolized the<br />
changing face of Australia. As her voice rang out, it bore<br />
testimony to the way in which Australia has welcomed<br />
ffilgrants to our great nation from all corners of the globe<br />
and, by accepting their diverse cultures, ensured their<br />
commitment to Australian institutions.<br />
Friends<br />
Never have you had a clearer choice.<br />
Never have you faced a starker contrast.<br />
The Liberal/ National Coalition seeks to deny opportunity and<br />
entrench privilege. </p>
<p>The Labor Party will continue to enlarge equality of<br />
opportunity for all.<br />
Look at our record.<br />
Three years ago I gave my word that the Australian<br />
Government would adopt Australia's first National Policy on<br />
Languages. We did, and the achievements speak for<br />
themselves. Migrants, both kids at school and their parents, have<br />
benefitted from greatly increased expenditure. Today it<br />
stands at $ 162 million, up more than 50 per cent on the last<br />
year of the Liberal Government.<br />
We have expanded our financial help for teaching community<br />
languages to your children. We have provided some 823<br />
million over the last 3 years for a Second language Learning<br />
Program, set up the Languages Institute of Australia, and<br />
increased funding for ethnic schools. Spending on conmmunity<br />
languages has increased fivefold under my Government.<br />
Three years ago I gave my word that we would present a<br />
National Agenda for a Multicultural Australia. I know that<br />
many people were sceptical whether we would deliver. We<br />
did. Last July my Government committed $ 89 million to a series of<br />
concrete initiatives. As a result:<br />
SBS television is being progressively extended<br />
the barriers to the recognition of overseas skills and<br />
qualifications, of which many of you have had<br />
unfortunate experience, are coming down<br />
a major campaign to improve community relations is<br />
being set in place in spite, I am saddened to say, of<br />
criticism from the Liberals and Nationals.<br />
Three years ago I gave my word that an Access and Equity<br />
policy would be pursued with vigour to ensure that the<br />
Government's programs and services would be equally<br />
available to all. We have fulfilled that pledge<br />
in 1989/ 90, the budget on settlement services provided<br />
by the Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs is<br />
$ 127.5 million, more than 50 percent greater than in<br />
1983/ 84<br />
an extra $ 3 million has been set aside to ensure<br />
migrants get equal access to community and health<br />
services, local government, and consumer education<br />
million has been earmarked for residential care for<br />
ethnic older people<br />
639~ 8 </p>
<p>employment and training programs have been targetted to<br />
non-English speaking migrants, so that they have<br />
benefitted equally from our record levels of employment<br />
growth. It is a matter of fact that 1.6 million jobs<br />
have been created under my Labor Government: it is a<br />
matter of pride that a quarter of those jobs have gone<br />
to migrant workers.<br />
Three years ago I gave my word that we would review our<br />
immigration policy and overhaul our outdated Migration Act.<br />
We have.<br />
It is a complex business, and the new regulations are at<br />
times confusing. It is for that reason that my colleague,<br />
Robert Ray, who has worked assiduously and with great<br />
integrity in the Immigration portfolio, has recently<br />
announced grants to Migrant Resource Centres to provide free<br />
advice on migration matters to stop migrants being ripped<br />
of f by unscrupulous profit-making migration agents.<br />
I do not claim that our new regulations are yet perfect.<br />
Robert has made clear that some of the criticism has been<br />
fair. But he has also said, and I agree totally, that<br />
clearly defined and publicly available rules for decisionmaking<br />
will introduce more certainty, consistency and<br />
fairness to the operation of migration policy.<br />
And I say also, loudly and clearly, that the hallmark of the<br />
Hawke Government is a willingness to listen to ethnic<br />
communities and where necessary to act. If there remain<br />
unintended consequences to some of the new regulations you<br />
have my word that we will change them.<br />
Friends Contained in the document before you today is a remarkable<br />
record. It sets out a path to a fair and tolerant Australia<br />
along which we will continue to stride undeterred by those<br />
who seek to change our direction.<br />
In my next term as your Prime Minister, my Government will:<br />
continue to develop further the National Policy on<br />
Languages support a balanced program of second language learning<br />
for all, including for the languages of our ethnic and<br />
Aboriginal communities<br />
establish a National Bureau of Language Services to<br />
provide better interpreter and language services across<br />
the nation<br />
continue its high level of commitment to English<br />
language teaching 9jI </p>
<p>Al,<br />
open up greater opportunities for overseas-trained mi.<br />
migrants et<br />
give the Special Broadcasting Service its own thlegislative<br />
base and charter, and further extend the l<br />
reach of SBS TV mi,<br />
provide traineeships for non-English speaking An.<br />
background Australians in the ABC and SBS th in<br />
ensure equality of opportunity in education by ri<br />
expanding the Disadvantaged Schools Program Se<br />
provide extra funding for special child care services Th'<br />
to meet the needs of migrant children x<br />
maintain the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity s<br />
Commission as an independent statutory body Atu<br />
and keep the Office of Multicultural Affairs withi my t<br />
own portfolio.<br />
I am also delighted to announce today a bold, new initiative c<br />
the creation of a nationally networked ethnic radio news Al<br />
and current affairs service. p)<br />
585 Radio already produces excellent community language f<br />
programs on 3EA in Melbourne and 2EA in Sydney. Public r<br />
broadcasting stations such as the newly established 3ZZ<br />
in this city, 5EBI in Adelaide, 4EB in Brisbane and 6EBA in<br />
Perth ensure that ethnic communities have access to the<br />
airwaves. Now, through the Public Broadcasting Foundation, h<br />
SBS will be funded to produce objective, professional news il<br />
and community information programs in at least fifteen h<br />
languages and air-time will be bought from public stations h;<br />
to broadcast them. e:<br />
in this way both the 585 and public broadcasters will<br />
benefit from additional funding of $ 3.4 million over a three Y<br />
year period. More importantly, ethnic communities around n<br />
Australia will be able to receive on a regular basis high<br />
quality programs in their first language.<br />
It is not only the ethnic communities in our cities that c<br />
will benefit from this measure. Communities such as the<br />
Greeks, Italians, Turks and Vietnamese who are making such a<br />
19luable contribution in our rural areas will now, some of M<br />
them for the first time, be able to listen to radio programs<br />
in the language that they speak at home.<br />
This is multiculturalism at work.<br />
And what does the Liberal/ National Party Coalition offer? C<br />
First, it offers funding cuts.<br />
1; 4 0 </p>
<p>Already the Coalition has announced that it will slash<br />
million from the budget of the Department of Immigration and<br />
Ethnic Affairs $ 20 million that might otherwise go on<br />
settlement services for migrants $ 20 million removed from<br />
the Immigration budget at the very moment the Coalition<br />
plans a significant increase in the intake of economic<br />
migrants. And that, my friends, is only the beginning. As they<br />
themselves now admit, there would have to be draconian cuts<br />
in the second and third year to finance their pitch to the<br />
rich. Second, the Coalition offers division.<br />
Their policy proposes to treat some migrants differently<br />
from others. It would deny migrants access to our social<br />
security benefits for at least their first twelve months in<br />
Australia. No matter that they have chosen Australia as<br />
their home. No matter that they are subject to Australian<br />
taxes from their first day here. If they are not a refugee,<br />
then they would not be entitled to sickness benefits, not<br />
entitled to an invalid pension, not entitled to unemployment<br />
benefits. At the same time, the Coalition intends to reduce the<br />
proportion of migrants allowed to come and join their<br />
families in Australia. Well may they talk of " the harsh<br />
reality". It is they who seek to create it.<br />
And finally, the Coalition offers fear.<br />
It fears ethnic communities. It is for that reason that it<br />
has attacked us for ensuring that our policies are presented<br />
in the ethnic press. While the Australian Labor Party is<br />
holding a special launch of its ethnic affairs policy, as it<br />
has in each of the last 3 elections, the Liberal Party has<br />
expunged the word " ethnic" from their election policy<br />
statement of last week.<br />
You, my friends in the ethnic communities, are presumably<br />
not part of the Liberal ' Answer'.<br />
It is perhaps fear too which explains why the Coalition<br />
seeks to make it harder for migrants to become Australian<br />
c tizens.<br />
I see that in an interview with SBS radio last week<br />
Mr Peacock sought to deny this was Liberal Party policy. I<br />
suggest that he take a break from glib sloganeering and<br />
actually read the Immigration Policy document of his own<br />
Party. There it states, unequivocally, that under a Coalition<br />
Government, migrants would have to live in Australia for<br />
four years before being eligible for citizenship: four<br />
years, my friends, not two as is the case now. 4 I </p>
<p>In stark contrast, I was proud to launch in 1988 The Year of<br />
Citizenship. As I participated in ceremonies across our<br />
land, and as migrants came forward in record numbers to make<br />
their ultimate commitment to our nation, it was impossible<br />
not to feel elation. Here were people from 140 countries<br />
around the world, choosing Australia as their home. And,<br />
having chosen, participating as you are participating in<br />
our democratic traditions.<br />
Friends fellow Australians<br />
The choice on March 24 could not be plainer.<br />
Over the last few years the Australian Labor Party has stood<br />
by our ethnic communities when the going was at its<br />
toughest. We will continue to fight discrimination and intolerance in<br />
any of their invidious forms.<br />
We will continue to hold firm to our belief in multicultural<br />
policies to manage Australia's growing diversity.<br />
We will continue to ensure that our programs and services<br />
are equally available to all.<br />
We will continue to listen to the voice of our great ethnic<br />
communities. We will always do so, no matter what the political cost. On<br />
that you have my solemn word.<br />
Together, during my fourth term as Prime Minister, we will<br />
work together to build a fair, just and tolerant Australia<br />
for our children and grandchildren.<br />
1; 4 0' X? </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
