<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5325</transcript-id>
    <title>DROUGHT RELIEF</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/04/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005325.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
_%&gt; AUTHS AL&amp; A'f<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA MONDAY, 14 APRIL, 1980<br />
DROUGHT RELIEF<br />
The Commonwealth is taking a major initiative to assist<br />
primary producers to ensure water supplies and to encourage<br />
them to increase their capacity to withstand drought.<br />
At present non-plant capital expenditure on conserving or<br />
conveying water on rural properties such as earth tanks,<br />
wells and bores, and earth channelling for irrigation may<br />
be written off over a period of ten years. The cost of<br />
plant items such as pumps is depreciable over the life<br />
of the asset.<br />
As from today these existing taxation concessions for the<br />
conservation of water, the equipping of bores, wells and<br />
dams, an-d the conveyance of water on rural properties, will<br />
be extended to provi7de that all such expenditure will be an<br />
allowable deduction " for taxation purposes in the year in which<br />
the expenditure is inrcurred. This will provide an important<br />
incentive for farmers to develop additional water storage<br />
and farm. reticulatizn-systems.<br />
Those items present~ v eligible for the investment allowance<br />
will continue to be eligible for it in addition to the new<br />
concess on now announced.<br />
The necessary amending legislation will be introduced as a<br />
matter of urgency.<br />
The announcement of these measures at this time and their<br />
application from today underlined the Government's growing<br />
concern about the fact that a large part of the continent<br />
is suffering a very dry period. The position is one of grave<br />
concern. If Autumn rains fail to eventuate over a large<br />
part of Australia, rural areas will be left in dire straits.<br />
In addition, there is Commonwealth agreement to extended<br />
measures for drought relief in New South Wales.<br />
These measures will cover: the provision of subsidies to<br />
Councils and other organisations able to provide emergency<br />
water supplies; and the extension of existing subsidies to<br />
primary producers to assist them in meeting special costs<br />
incurred in the transport of emergency water supplies<br />
to their properties. / 2 </p>
<p>2-<br />
Precise details of the new arrangements will be worked out<br />
between officers of the Commonwealth and New South Wales<br />
Government. Relief of drought represents a very important part of<br />
Commonwealth/ State co-operation. We stand ready to listen<br />
to matters put to us by the States.<br />
The extended measures announced today will, of course, apply<br />
in future in all States and Territories where similar<br />
situations occur. 000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
