<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2455</transcript-id>
    <title>EXCHANGE OF LETTERS</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>13/08/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Correspondence</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002455.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: PM No. 80/ 1971<br />
EXCHANGE OF LETTERS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. Vqilliam. Mvahon,<br />
this afternoon released the texts of the letters<br />
between himself and Mr. Gorton.<br />
The texts are attached.<br />
C ANBE2ARA<br />
13 August 1971 </p>
<p>The Prime 1' Iinister's letter to YMr. Gorton 12 August 1971<br />
My dear John, I refer to our discussion this afternoon when<br />
I said that I had given the most careful consideration<br />
to your decision to write a series of articles for the<br />
" Sunday Australian", the first of which has already<br />
been published. In my opinion, your action breaches basic<br />
principles of Cabinet solidarity and unity. Your<br />
first article deals with a number of controversial<br />
issues involving other hMinisters and affecting their.<br />
integrity. These Ministers are not free to comment if these<br />
principles are to be respected. If any other practice<br />
were to be permitted, a precedent would be created which<br />
would, I believe, make the Cabinet system of Government<br />
unworkable. I know how deeply you feel about the contents of<br />
the recent book. But Other Ministers have had to endure<br />
this type of criticism, which is part and parcel of<br />
political life. The overriding consideration, in my<br />
view, must be Cabinet solidarity and unity.<br />
I will make a short statement this evening<br />
stating that I have discussed -Uis matter with you and<br />
that you have, in accordance with my request, agreed to<br />
tender your resignation to me.<br />
His Excellency the Governor-General has been<br />
informed. Yours sincerely,<br />
William Mcl~ ahon </p>
<p>Mr. Gorton's letter to the Prime Minister<br />
My dear Prime Minister,<br />
I acknowledge your letter of 12 August<br />
concerning our discussion this afternoon.<br />
In my recollection the only article you<br />
referred to was the one already published, which<br />
you said in your view breached Cabinet solidarity<br />
and unity. You said that as a result of this<br />
article and your feeling concerning it you felt<br />
you must ask for my resignation.<br />
In accordance with your request, I now<br />
tender you that resignation. Yours sincerely,<br />
J. G. GORTON<br />
12 August 1971 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
