<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9646</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP AUSINDUSTRY NATIONAL LAUNCH - INTERCONTINENTAL HOTEL, SYDNEY 28 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009646.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
AUSINDUSTRY NATIONAL LAUNCH INTERCONTINENTAL HOTEL,<br />
SYDNEY 28 JUNE 1995<br />
This is a good thing that we do today.<br />
I am very pleased, and very proud, to come together with representatives of<br />
the States, the Territories and the business community, to launch<br />
Ausindustry. I am proud because Auslndustry is another investment by the Government in<br />
Australia, in a stronger nation and a more productive people.<br />
I am proud because Auslndustry is the product of dialogue and cooperation<br />
between Commonwealth, State and Territory governments. It is a strategic<br />
partnership, between the different tiers of government, and between<br />
government and industry, and it shows just how well the Federation can work<br />
when there is good will all around.<br />
I am proud because Auslndustry shows that there is room for innovation and<br />
enterprise within the public sector, and reflects the Government's desire to<br />
achieve world's best practice in the delivery of programs to the community.<br />
Auslndustry was one of the initiatives announced last year in the<br />
Government's White Paper on Employment, Working Nation.<br />
In the White Paper, we asserted that the strongest and fairest kind of nation<br />
is a working nation. We erected practical measures to increase employment,<br />
because that is the most equitable, and the most efficient, thing to do.<br />
Much of Working Nation was devoted to moving the long-term unemployed<br />
and those at risk of becoming long-term unemployed into jobs: the Youth<br />
Training Initiative, the Job Compact, the National Training Wage.<br />
But we also recognised the long-term imperative: that in order to create more<br />
jobs with higher wages, and hence improve the living standards of<br />
Australians, the country has to be more productive and that requires<br />
Australian industry to be extended and strengthened. </p>
<p>For the last twelve years, the Government has been building the kind of<br />
competitive environment in which Australian industry can succeed and<br />
Australian firms can flourish.<br />
We have done it by opening up the economy, and facing it for the first time<br />
towards our own region.<br />
We have done it by floating the dollar, and deregulating the financial sector.<br />
We have done it by dismantling the high tariff walls behind which the<br />
Australian manufacturing sector was crumbling away, and by putting in place<br />
measures to help businesses engage the global market place.<br />
And we are doing it through labour market reforms which increase the<br />
flexibility and productivity of Australian work places without tearing at the<br />
rights and living standards of Australian working people.<br />
Today, the Australian economy is far more competitive, alert and dynamic<br />
than at any time in the past.<br />
Australia's communications network is smarter and livelier, our transport<br />
system smoother and more efficient, and our financial sector infinitely more<br />
sophisticated than a decade ago.<br />
Overall, the economy is almost 40 per cent more competitive than it was in<br />
the early 1980s.<br />
We are finding that in this new competitive environment, new species of<br />
successful Australian firms are springing up.<br />
The McKinsey survey on emerging exporters, and all the studies since, have<br />
remarked on these successes.<br />
The studies have shown that the firms achieving the biggest wins all share a<br />
similar character.<br />
They are ambitious and alert, vigorous and adventurous.<br />
They are exploiting the revolutions in transport and communications to get to<br />
new markets, and they are operating very close to those markets.<br />
They are innovative, and able to manage and respond to a wide range of<br />
emerging conditions.<br />
There are a lot of firms like this it's approaching a critical mass. Their<br />
success depends on knowing what they are good at. And this is where<br />
government has a very significant role to play by helping these firms to<br />
develop their human capital. </p>
<p>Many of the most mobile and energetic Australian businesses are small and<br />
medium enterprises. Unlike their cousins in big business, they cannot afford<br />
to maintain on-line access to the skills, information and resources that are<br />
essential to business development.<br />
By helping Australian firms obtain these services, governments can help them<br />
identify their strengths, isolate their weaknesses, and harness and direct their<br />
energies.<br />
The advice and ideas might deal with skills, education and training, access to<br />
finance, long-term planning, the application of technologies or the<br />
development of trade opportunities.<br />
The aim of industry development of this kind is not to pick winners, but to<br />
keep the winners moving. Experience shows us that gover6nmen and<br />
industry work better when they work in concert.<br />
This kind of advice has always been offered by governments but through a<br />
plurality of sources in a variety of agencies.<br />
Before the Government brought down Working Nation, business people told<br />
us they were confused about the range of services provided by governments<br />
and, in some instances, were not even aware of the existence of key<br />
Commonwealth Government programs.<br />
An independent review of the development and delivery of government<br />
business programs, conducted by Mr Ian Burgess, told us much the same<br />
thing. Auslndustry is the Government's response to these criticisms.<br />
Auslndustry will help our businesses to achieve world's best practices, and to<br />
successfully engage world markets. It will serve as a single entry-point to the<br />
array of government programs already in place to assist firms in developing<br />
their managerial, technological, financial and marketing resources. And it will<br />
help to build better Australian firms by allowing us to deliver an integrated,<br />
cohesive and holistic service to each individual business client.<br />
The most effective enterprise development programs are those which are<br />
informed by the views and driven by the needs of business. To ensure that<br />
Auslndustry maintains a strong client focus, we have appointed a private<br />
sector-led Board, headed up by Dick Warburton.<br />
May I commend the States and Territories for having the wit and vision to<br />
sign on to the Auslndustry partnership. Bringing all our business service<br />
activities under a single umbrella makes good economic and logistic sense,<br />
and will allow us to draw on the resulting synergies. </p>
<p>So, with the launch of Aus Industry, industry development assistance will be<br />
delivered, for the first time, on an all-governments, whole-of-government<br />
basis. Ausindustry will direct businesses to the government service most suitable for<br />
their needs. These services have already achieved many success stories<br />
stories worth telling.<br />
Like the Victorian-based Moss Products, a manufacturer of technical plastic<br />
and metal components, which called on private sector experts subsidised by<br />
Auslndustry to stream-line its product development, renovate its corporate<br />
identity and establish a strategy for the future.<br />
Or the Adelaide construction firm, Glenn Industries, which deals in leading<br />
edge building technology, and specialises in the manufacture of glass fibre<br />
reinforced cement. Parliament Station in Melbourne and the Capita Finance<br />
Building in Sydney are good examples of the work of this firm. Support from<br />
Government industry assistance programs and Austrade helped Glenn<br />
Industries form a joint venture with a Singapore firm, and eventually win $ 13<br />
million worth of contracts, including the Singapore Merlion Tower.<br />
Or the National Recording Studios, a business which has already gone a long<br />
way down the information highway, developing interactive CD-Rom packages<br />
for both the Government and corporate sectors. NRS accessed a<br />
Commonwealth Government program which assists new and existing<br />
exporters to strategically plan for and manage their exporting activities.<br />
Sales into a range of territories, including the USA, Italy, Taiwan, Israel and<br />
South Africa have followed.<br />
In the final analysis, of course, the credit for their successes, and the onus for<br />
achieving them in the future, lies with the businesses themselves. They must<br />
make their own way in a very competitive environment. But as these<br />
examples show, government can support them in their efforts.<br />
Auslndustry will provide that support. It is a timely and intelligent policy<br />
initiative which will help set up Australian industry for the future.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
Earlier this month, with the standardisation of the rail line between Melbourne<br />
and Adelaide, the Government completed the construction of a national<br />
standard gauge rail highway from Brisbane to Perth, via Sydney, Melbourne<br />
and Adelaide.<br />
The establishment of Aus Industry is perhaps not of quite the same order, but<br />
the intent is the same. Each will guarantee a more unified system, and<br />
provide a better service to Australians. And each will, I am sure, come to be<br />
seen as a national asset. </p>
<p>I congratulate all those involved with the establishment of Auslndustry, and<br />
wish them the best of luck for the future.<br />
I am confident that Auslndustry will make Australia a much more industrious<br />
nation, and I am happy to declare it open for business.<br />
Ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
