<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>636</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICES AND PRODUCTION BUILDING OF MERCK SHARP &amp; DOHME (AUSTRALIA) PTY. LTD. AT SOUTH GRANVILLE, N.S.W. ON 26/10/1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000636.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICES AND<br />
PRODUCTION BUILDINGS OF MERCK SHARP&amp;<br />
DOHME ( AUSTRALIA) PTY. LTD. AT SOUTH<br />
GRANVILLE, N. S ON 26/ 10/ 1962.<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt, Hon. RG. Menzies<br />
Sir Mr. Deputy Mayor, Mr. Uren, Mr. Connor and Ladies and<br />
Genhemen I think I ought to begin by coming clean with<br />
you about something. We've a lot of problems on our plate<br />
at this moment at Canberra and having, to put it in the<br />
vulgar fashion, managed to get rid of Parliament last<br />
night I was horrified to find that I had either talked<br />
mysell into coming here or been talked into it. So I<br />
flew down this morning and I am due back home at six<br />
o'clock, I don't remember how it came about because, you<br />
know, this business of politicians, particularly reactionary<br />
conservative politi1cians like me ( Laughter) opening<br />
works is a very dubious one. I frequently, when I am<br />
opening somL. factory somewhere it may not entirely apply<br />
here today but I frequently find my opponent, the sitting<br />
Member, standing by, and the more enthusiastically I commend<br />
this wonderful piece of development, the more enthusiastically<br />
he counts the additional votes he will get at the next<br />
election. ( Laughter) Still, you can't have it both ways.<br />
I am very gzLateful to the Deputy Mayor for<br />
having so pleasantly welcomed me here this afternoon. All<br />
I can say is that I used to have a very high regard for<br />
Parramatta I still have momentarily because Parramatta<br />
has long since had the admirable habit of electing to the<br />
Federal Parliament a supporter of mine, but now the busybodies<br />
have got to work and there has been a redistribution.<br />
It isn't through yet, and I understand there are yet problems<br />
to overcome but I am told by the wise men t hat as a result<br />
of the redistributilon, Parramatta will become a hostile camp.<br />
I leave it to you, Mr. Deputy Mayor, to see that that doesn't<br />
happen. ( Laughter) I would just like to say this about the Company<br />
and about the new development here: when I looked through<br />
the record, I thought that here we had a most astonishing<br />
sto~' y of growth in ten years0 I repeat, of course, ten years,<br />
because that proves conclusively that the success of this<br />
Company and its amazing growth has occurred in spite of the<br />
fact that I have been Prime Minister over the same period.<br />
( Laughter) But it is a remarkable story of growth and it<br />
demonstrates two things, both of which perhaps we need to<br />
understand in Australia even better than we have.<br />
The first is that the great ingredient in growth,<br />
to which must be added skill and all sorts of other things,<br />
is confidence in the country in which you are establishing<br />
yourself. This is a pretty strange, confused world hgettin<br />
stranger and more confused almost every minute, and here n<br />
are not all that many countries in the world in whom some<br />
long-established enterprice can feel confidence so that i. t<br />
may invest its money and its talent and its experience in<br />
that country. It has really been a very great assurancd to<br />
all Australians, a very great source of pride to all Australians<br />
that in this period since the war, Australia has attracted the<br />
confident investment and skill of so many people on the other<br />
side of the world. Peopjle lose confidence, of courses very<br />
./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
easily or some people do, I am happy to say that this<br />
Company is a splendid example of a body which has at no stage<br />
lost confidence but has gone right forward. Now that to me<br />
is a splendid thing confidence in Australia,, But it also<br />
exhibits, of course, confidence in the future0 It takes the<br />
long view. I remember a few years ago delivering one<br />
night what people were pleased to call a Zittle Budget, in<br />
wtich we clamped down on the motor car industry this is<br />
about five years ago through some adided taxation. When<br />
I arrived in my office the next morning, having made this<br />
powerful but, of course I don't need to tell you, most<br />
unpopular speech thatis no novelty for me my staff said<br />
to me, " You know we don't know whether you ought to be given<br />
the Victoria Cross or sent to a hospital for the insane," and<br />
I said, " Why, whatts wrong?" They said, " Do you know that<br />
youtre lunching today, you're giving a luncheon party to<br />
the representatives of one of the greatest motor ear organizations<br />
in the world?" So I screwed my courage to the sticking<br />
point and went down and acted the host and tried to make up<br />
by amiability for the terrible things that I had. done the<br />
night before. But the head man from overseas smiled at me<br />
and said, " You know, I heard you last night," I said " Yesq<br />
well, I'll take it, What is it?" He said, " I entirely agreed<br />
with you. I don't see what else you could have done. Of<br />
course, it will cost my organization something, but you don't<br />
want to get it into your head that we've become a big organization<br />
by just looking forward a year at a time; we look forward<br />
twentyfive years at a time. This won~ t be the only knock we'll<br />
have a little knock In the course of twentyfive years but<br />
our planning is based on the fact that we will develop and<br />
grow steadily in the long run over that period of time."<br />
That's elementary enough9 but it isn't everybody who thinks<br />
like that. I am perfectly certain that those who are<br />
responsible for this Company do think like that0 What they<br />
have done already in the last ten years is conclusive evidence<br />
of their long-range thinking,<br />
The other thing that I wanted to say to you<br />
is that I gathered, I hope rightly, thatamong the plans of<br />
this Company are plans to produce at least one commodity for<br />
which tiley design to have a substantial export sale. Now<br />
that when it comes off, will be a very good thing. I<br />
cons~ antly find myself saying to manufacturers of all kinds<br />
that we must get further and farther away from the idea that<br />
the only things we can export are the products of the soil.<br />
They will be the main things that we export for a long long,<br />
time. They are of tremendous importance. But we must more<br />
and more translate the undoubted skill of the Australian, his<br />
undoubted capacity to do his workjust as well as anybody<br />
else in the world, into getting for our manufactured commodities<br />
increasing markets, particularly in the rising, newer countriespolitically<br />
newer countries of the East and North from us.<br />
It is nothing much to the point for anyboay to say, tOh, well,<br />
you know that's difficult0Of course it's difficult, My<br />
experience has been that almost everything is difficult, but<br />
that if you try bard enough, it may ultimately become easy,<br />
We must have, more and more from Australia<br />
export markets which arise frjom what I will call broadlyth<br />
manufacturing processes, And for a very good reason, or<br />
two good reasons. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
One is that we have, periodically, problems in<br />
our balance of' payments. The price of wool slumps and then<br />
our overseas reserves begin to rtun down. If the price of'<br />
wheat slumps or we have a drought or something of that kind,<br />
down goes our export income. Our import bill doesn't move<br />
around in this fashion. It's pretty steady and has a<br />
disposition to grow, but our export income can fluctuate<br />
with seasons and world prices to an almost alarming extent,<br />
Therefore, whatever Government is in office in Australia will<br />
find itself occasionally maybe every few years forced to<br />
take some particular measures to protect our overseas funds<br />
and assure our international solvency. I want to get away<br />
from that. I don't like these Emergency measures, And the<br />
way to get away from it is to put our exports on an increasingly<br />
stable basis and the exports of manufactures from Australia<br />
will contribute to that more than perhaps anything else could.<br />
So, Sir, wh-an I heard that you had your eye on the<br />
export fteld, I thought, " This is a splendid thing". Now I<br />
have given you the general reason for it. I will conclude<br />
by saying that we now have, of course, a particular reason<br />
for wanting to increase our exports, because we are confronted<br />
almost imminently by the problem of the Common Market.. and<br />
however the negotiations work out, it will be certainly true<br />
that we will have to put increasing pressure on a drive for<br />
new markets not just new markets for old th-ings but new<br />
markets for new things and that is whty the variety of things<br />
to be exported, extend-ing into the chemical field, extending<br />
into a hundred and one different varieties of ac-tivity, will<br />
be of such tremendcus importance to us,<br />
Vie are not just to content ourselves by saying<br />
" Well, there are certain traditional exports, and they will do."<br />
We must develop untraditional exports,) naw things, produce<br />
new things in Australia, not be afraid to produce them; because<br />
if the gentlemen who have spoken to you this afternoon feel<br />
confidence in this country, what should you and I born in'this<br />
land, feel about our own country? T have an unlimited<br />
confidence irn it and I hope that people will not allow their<br />
proper confidence to be withered too promptly by an occasional<br />
cold windt Sir, I have the greatest pleasure in declaring<br />
the offices and plant open. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
