<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2524</transcript-id>
    <title>PAYMENT OF PENSIONS OVERSEAS - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR WILLIAM MCMAHON</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>30/01/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002524.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
E 11 B A R GO : Not for releasa before 6 pmi on 30 January 1972.<br />
-TAW I<br />
FOR PRESS PM. No. 8/ 1972<br />
PAYMENT OF PENSIO14S OVERSEAS<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, I4r William 74cMahon<br />
My Government has decided to accept the principle<br />
of payment of pensions overseas,<br />
It had before it a submission from the Minister for<br />
Social Services ( Mr Wentworth) and the report of an Interdepartmental<br />
Committee which was completed late last year.<br />
we decided that ago, invalidi and widows' pensions<br />
3hould be pay. able in those overseascutiswihmk orsodn<br />
arrangements for their own pensions to be payable in Australia.<br />
in order to qualify for payment of his pension<br />
overseas, the pens. ioner in Australia will be required to have livE~ d<br />
here for at least 2-0 yoars after reaching the age of 16. However,<br />
in the case of invali,! pensions, where invalidity arises from an<br />
accident or cdisea; which occurred in Australia, there will be no<br />
such resi-ential rcuir0TRrnt. Firailariy, where a husband has died<br />
in Australia, the widow will. ab. to take her pension a1, road<br />
irrespective of her period of residcnce in Austredia.<br />
The Goviernment has thus accepteod the principle that<br />
where. a pe rson has contribut-ed to thre life of the C'! uqtra'ian community,<br />
his pension rights should be portable overseas.<br />
Leqislation to give 7-ffect-to this decision will be<br />
introduced into the Parliament early this year, and we shall<br />
endeavour to have it passed as soon as possible. It will then<br />
operate in any countrie~ s which have concluded the reciprocal arrangements<br />
tD which T have referred.<br />
Discussions relating to the possibility of appropriate<br />
reciprocity in social security have at different times since 1967*<br />
beien held with representatives of Yugoslavia, Italy, Malta, West<br />
Oermany and Turkey. The subject has also ' ieen raised from time to<br />
time in discussions ', 14th other countries. </p>
<p>2-<br />
In order to obviate unnecessary delay in concluding<br />
arrangements, I have asked the DYiinister for Social Services to<br />
begin forthwith his negotiations with representatives from<br />
countries from whom our migrants have come. He will be in<br />
consultation with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the<br />
Minister for Immigration in these negotiations.<br />
Arrangements to make Australian pensions payable<br />
overseas will be made as soon as it is possible to reach agreement<br />
with a particular country.<br />
The policy which we have now approved is the result<br />
of quite considerable investigations which took place last year,<br />
and follows principles which are gaining international acceptance.<br />
Australian development owes much to our migrants<br />
intake in the decades since the War. Some of these will, of<br />
course, wish to return home in the evening of their life, and they<br />
should feel free to do so if they so choose. But I believe that<br />
most of them now see Australia as their true home,. and will not<br />
want to leave us.<br />
The new privileges of pension portability are not,<br />
of course, confined to migrants. They will be ope-n to all holders,<br />
of Australian Social Service pensions, wherever they may have been<br />
born, who go to countries which make the appropriate reciprocal<br />
arrangements with Australia.<br />
CAN.' BERRA,<br />
January, 1972. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
