<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6685</transcript-id>
    <title>UNKNOWN</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/08/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Communique</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006685.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 8 August 1985<br />
Following is the text of the Communique agreed to by Heads of<br />
Government attending the South Pacific Forum, which met in<br />
Rarotonga, Cook Islands, on 5-6 August, 1985.<br />
1. The Sixteenth South Pacific Forum was held in Rarotonga,<br />
Cook Islands, from 5 to 6 August, 1985. The meeting was<br />
attended by Heads of Government from Australia, Cook Islands,<br />
Federated States of Micronesia ( as an observer), Fiji,<br />
Kiribati, Nauru, New Zealand, Niue, Papua New Guinea, Tuvalu,<br />
Vanuatu and Western Samoa, while Solomon Islands was<br />
represented by the Deputy Prime fniirister and Tonga was<br />
represente: d by its Forpign Minister. The Prime Mini--ter of<br />
the Cook Islands, the Hon Sir Thomas Davis, KBE, chaired the<br />
meet ing.<br />
2. The main is~ zues were discussed as follows:<br />
DECOLONISATIOW: NEW CALEDONIA<br />
3. The Forum reviewed developments in New Caledonia since<br />
its last meeting.<br />
4. The Forum reaffirmed its support for self-determination<br />
and the early transition to an independent New Caledonia in<br />
accordance with the innate, active rights and aspirations of<br />
the indigenous people and in a manner which guaranteed the<br />
rights and interests of all inhabitants of this multi-racial<br />
society. The Forum condemned the violence which had and continues<br />
to occur in New Caledonia and which has resulted in tragic<br />
loss of life thus seriously jeopardisingj the process of<br />
dialogue. Heads of Government called on all parties to<br />
refrain from further violence and to engage in constructive<br />
dialogue which, alone, would ensure a peaceful and lasting<br />
resolution of New Caledonia's present problems. </p>
<p>6. Referring to the decision on New Caledonia adopted at<br />
its last meeting in Tuvalu, the Forum welcomed the fact. that<br />
France had now publicly agreed to an early act of<br />
self-determination with the objective of bringing New<br />
Caledonia to independence. The Forum noted with satisfaction<br />
that the date for the act of self-determination had been<br />
brought forward: the vot%-e was now to take place by the end<br />
of 1987 at the latest.<br />
7. The Forum urged the French Government to undertake<br />
electoral reforms before the act of self-determination to<br />
ensure that the result accurately reflected the wishes of the<br />
Kanak people and others who had a long-term residence in and<br />
commitment to New Caledonia.<br />
8. The Forum noted with interest the statement made by the<br />
French Prime Minister in April 1985 in which he outlined<br />
proposals for the administration of New Caledonia in the<br />
period leading up to the act of seif-determination. The<br />
Forum noted that, in accordance with the Prime Minister's<br />
announcement, legislation concerning the relationship between<br />
New Caledonia and France had recently been adopted by the<br />
French Parliament. H~ eads of Government expressed the view<br />
that the course of action on which the French Government had<br />
now embarked contained positive elements which were<br />
appropria~ e in assisting the territory in its evolution to<br />
independence. The Forum expressed the strong hope that thic<br />
plan would be firmly and consistently pursued to its<br />
conclusion by 31 December 1987. The Forum called on all<br />
parties to work towards the proper conduct of the forthcoming<br />
regional elections in a fair and peaceful manner and to<br />
advance diligently the process of decolonisation within New<br />
Caledoni a.<br />
9. In the light of strong reservations about increased<br />
militarisation of the region, the Forum called on France to<br />
clarify publicly the nature and extent of its announced<br />
intention to upgrade its military facilities in New<br />
Caledonia. The Forum also again stressed its view that<br />
France should transfer additional political and<br />
administrative powers to the territory to ensure that it was<br />
adequately prepared for independence, and take the practical<br />
steps necessary to guarantee the full and active<br />
participation of the Melanesian community in the territory's<br />
educational, vocational, administrative and economic<br />
structures. The Forum addressed the question of granting Forum<br />
observer status to the FLNKS and agreed to set up a working<br />
group to review the question of observer status in the Forum.<br />
The group should consider the existing guidelines governing<br />
the question of observer status, and consider whether any<br />
changes were desirable or necessary. The Forum noted that<br />
the work of this group would assist consideration of, but not<br />
be confined to, the proposal that the FLNKS be admitted to<br />
observer status at Forum meetings. </p>
<p>11. The Forum discussei in some detail the question of<br />
possible involvemeit ot the United Nations in the situation<br />
in New Caledonia. it was widely acknowledged that keeping<br />
the question before the international community was<br />
important, and Forum members felt that speeches by Forum<br />
members in the United Nations General Assembly's general<br />
debate might take up the objectives of the Forum in relation<br />
to New Caledonia. However, the Forum reaffirmed that it had<br />
a continuing primary role, as a regional body, to continue<br />
its consideration of developments in the territory and to<br />
respond as and where appropriate. While noting the arguments<br />
on the question of reinscription of New Caledonia on the<br />
United Nations List of Non-Self Governing Territories, and<br />
without accepting reinscription at this juncture, the Forum<br />
would seek information from the appropriate organs of the UN<br />
on the applicability of the UN Charter and the 1960<br />
Declaration on the granting of independence to colonial<br />
countries arnd peoples. It agreed to give further<br />
consideration to this question at its 17th meeting. 1<br />
12. The Forum noted that the Ministerial Group established<br />
at Tuvalu to discuss Forum views on New Caledonia with the<br />
Independence Front and the French authorities had fulfilled<br />
its original mandate. It expressed appreciation for the<br />
reports circulated to all Forum i. iebers. on the two meetings<br />
which membz-rs of the Ministerial Group had held at the erkd of<br />
1984. The Forum agreed, however, that there was a need for<br />
all member countries to remain fully informed of developments<br />
in future and decided to establish a Standing Committee of<br />
officials to report to the Ministerial Group on a continuing<br />
basis over the crucial period before the next meeting of the<br />
Forum. The Officials Group should alert the Ministerial<br />
Group to any development including political devcolopments in<br />
France Itself which may call for a reaction or a response by<br />
the Ministerial Group or by Forum Governments as a whole.<br />
13. The Forum agreed that its views should be conveyed r<br />
formally to the French Government.<br />
FRENCH POLYNESIA<br />
14. The Forum considered an application by French Polynesia<br />
to the Forum for observer status. While acknowledging Frenchz<br />
Polynesia's ties with some of its island neighbours the Forum<br />
was unable to agree to granting the Territory observer status<br />
under its existing guidelines for membership. In particular<br />
the need for a definite date to have been set for<br />
independence. These guidelines would be reviewed by a<br />
working group. </p>
<p>REGIONAL NUCLEAR MATTERS<br />
South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty<br />
The Forum considered the Report of the Chairman of the<br />
Working Group of officials on a South Pacific Nuclear Free<br />
Zone and the agreed text of a draft South Pacific Nuclear<br />
Free Zone Treaty annexed to the Report. It was noted that<br />
the draft Treaty incorporated all of the principles on a<br />
South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone adopted by the Fifteenth<br />
Forum in Tuvalu. The Forum endorsed the text of the Treaty<br />
produced by the Working Group and opened it for signature at<br />
the Forum by those countries in a position to do so, it being<br />
understood by the Forum that some countries would not be in a<br />
position to sign the Treaty, at least until they had<br />
subjected it to their normal constitutional processes. Heads<br />
of Government of Australia, Cook Islands, Fiji, Kiribati, New<br />
Zealand, Niue, Tuvalu and Western Samoa signed the Treaty.<br />
16. The Forum also considered the three draft Protocols to[<br />
the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty. Since the V<br />
Protocols involve countries outside the region it was agreed<br />
that consultations should be held with all the countries<br />
eligible to sign the Protocols before they were finalised.<br />
The Forum commissioned the Working Group on a South Pacific<br />
Nuclear Free Zone to organise these consultations and to .7. ke<br />
recommendations to Forum Leaders corncerning the adoption oi<br />
the Protocols at the next meeting of the Forum in 1986 or<br />
earlier if practicable.<br />
17. The Forum observed that endorsement of the South Pacific<br />
Nuclear Free Zone Treaty, which would establish onl~ y the<br />
second nuclear weapon free zone in a permanently inhabited<br />
area, reflected the deep concern of all Forum members at the<br />
continuing nuclear arms race and the risk of nuclear war. In<br />
this context the Forum welcomed the resumption of arms<br />
control talks between the superpowers and expressed its hope<br />
that these talks would achieve their declared objective of a<br />
reduction in nuclear weapons and to their eventual<br />
-elimination as well as to the prevention of an arms race in<br />
space. The Forum also noted that the Third Review Conference<br />
of the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty would be held in<br />
Geneva from 27 August to 24 September 1985 and that the South<br />
Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Treaty is in accordance with<br />
Article VII of the NPT concerning regional arrangements to<br />
ensure the absence of nuclear weapons. The Forum agreed that<br />
the Review Conference be informed of the progress made on the<br />
establishment of the zone.<br />
18. The Forum expressed support for Australia's initiative<br />
at the Review Conference to require the application of<br />
fullscope International Atomic Energy Agency safeguards to<br />
all nuclear exports to non-nuclear weapon states and noted<br />
that the initiative was fully consistent with Article 4 of </p>
<p>the Zone Treaty. The Forum affirmed its support for the NPT<br />
as the most important means of preventing the spread of<br />
nuclear weapons to additional countries.<br />
19. Forum Leaders noted that the southern boundary to which<br />
the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone will apply is the area<br />
governed by the Antarctic Treaty which provides for the<br />
Antarctic to remain demilitarised, free of nuclear weapons<br />
for there to be a ban on nuclear testing and the disposal of<br />
nuclear wastes. Interest was expressed in the continued<br />
viability of the Antarctic Treaty system which complemented<br />
in an adjacent area their own efforts to establish a South<br />
Pacific Nuclear Free Zone.<br />
French Nuclear Testing I<br />
The Forum reaffirmed its total opposition to French<br />
nuclear testing in the South Pacific in defiance of the view<br />
of all the independent and self-governing countries of the<br />
region. The Forum urged France to cease immediately its<br />
nuclear testing programme at Mururoa Atoll and noted that one<br />
of the principal reasons for adopting a South Pacific Nuclear<br />
Free Zone Treaty was the deep wish of all Forum members that<br />
no nuclear tests be conducted anywhere within the region. The<br />
Forum also r--affirmed their support for the early conclusion<br />
of a Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty which would ban all<br />
nuclear tests by all States in all environments.<br />
Dumping of Radioactive Waste<br />
21. The Forum reaffirmed its strong opposition to the<br />
dumping of radioactive waste in the oceans of the region.<br />
Forum Members were committed to the early conclusion of the<br />
Convention and Protocols being negotiated under the auspices<br />
of the South Pacific Regional Environment Program ( SPREP)<br />
which would, among other things, preclude the dumping at sea<br />
of radioactive waste in the region. The Forum noted that this<br />
commitment was also enshrined in the South Pacific Nuclear<br />
Free Zone Treaty.<br />
22. The Forum welcomed the statement by the Prime Minister<br />
of Japan that Japan had no intention of dumping radioactive<br />
waste in the Pacific Ocean in disregard of the concern<br />
expressed by the communities of the region.<br />
23. The Forum considered further the proposal, made by Nauru f<br />
at the Fifteenth Forum at Tuvalu, to strengthen the London<br />
Dumping Convention ( LDC) including the Report of the Chairman<br />
of the South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone Working Group<br />
recording the Working Group's consideration of the Nauru<br />
proposal. </p>
<p>6<br />
24. The Forum noted that the next meeting of parties would<br />
take place from 23 to 27 September 1985. In the light of<br />
their shared opposition to radioactive waste dumping at sea,<br />
it was agreed that those Forum members participating in the<br />
LDC Meeting would consult closely about approaches to this<br />
issue at that meeting. It was recognised that it would be<br />
desirable to achieve a common approach. The advantages were<br />
noted of having additional Forum members'adhere to the LDC,<br />
so as to increase the number of LDC parties which shared<br />
South Pacific regional concerns.<br />
SMALLER ISLAND COUNTRIES<br />
The Forum received and adopted the Report of the<br />
Committee on Smaller Island Countries prepared under a<br />
mandate from the Tuvalu Statement. It also adopted the<br />
following statement on Smaller Island countries:<br />
" The South Pacific Forum contains a diversity of<br />
membership, culturally, ethnically and in terms of the size,<br />
natural resources and population of its member countries. All<br />
Pacific Island states are small in global terms and many are<br />
very isolated, widely scattered and vulnerable.<br />
The chz-racteristics of smallness, isolation, severe lack<br />
of resources and ulnerability are particularly acute<br />
for the Smaller Island Countries of the Forum namely<br />
Cook Islands, Kiribati, Niue and Tuvalu. Many of these<br />
c:-. aracteris ' tics are shared by the outer island<br />
communities of the larger countries. They give rise to<br />
particularly severe problems in terms of<br />
limited agricultural and manufacturing potential;<br />
diseconomies of scale and weak bargaining power;<br />
expensive and irregular transport links;<br />
inadequate communications.<br />
The cumulative effect of these problems is that Smaller<br />
Island Country economies face great difficulties in<br />
generating self-sustaining economic activity and are<br />
therefore heavily dependent on a continuing flow of<br />
external assistance.<br />
The Forum is founded on the recognition that regional<br />
co-operation offers benefits to individual countries<br />
through tackling common problems together. In the<br />
Pacific Way, the smallest most vulnerable members of the<br />
family deserve special attention. The Forum therefore<br />
recognises that special emphasis on meeting the needs of<br />
the Smaller Island Countries should be given through<br />
support of their national development strategies and<br />
through preferential treatment in regional programmes. </p>
<p>To this end the Forum considered a series of proposals<br />
to put that special empi asis U. nto effect b-eth through<br />
existing regional pro-jrammes and through new<br />
initiatives. These proposals address action in the<br />
fields of fisheries, transport, tourism, agriculture,<br />
external employment, energy, water, culture, minerals,<br />
manufacturing, communications and education. The Forum<br />
noted the critical need for whatever economic potential<br />
exists in the SICs to be explored and developed to the<br />
full. This is more critical for these countries than for<br />
other Forum members whose greater economic resources<br />
allow a greater range of development options. In order<br />
to ensure the effective inter-relationship of sectoral<br />
efforts, due attention is also required in the areas of<br />
national planning capabilities and the improvement of<br />
development assistance procedures and co-ordination.<br />
The Forum recognises that given the special<br />
characteristics and problems of the SICs, the objective<br />
of economic independence may not be practicable in some<br />
cases even in the longer term. In these cases, provision<br />
for development and recurrent budgetary aid must be<br />
considered. For those SICs whose declared goal is<br />
economic self-reliance, every effort should be extended<br />
to assist in this endeavour. The Forum recognises that<br />
calling for further additional financial and techni.-al<br />
assistance in order to achievc the objective and selfreliance<br />
may appear paradoxical. Yet in order to ignite<br />
a self-generating process of economic development in<br />
very small economies additional fuel is needed. The<br />
Forum therefore invites aid donors to the region, be<br />
they traditional friends or new ones, to join in<br />
recognising the special needs of the Smaller Forum<br />
Island Country members and to extend to them additional<br />
and concessional assistance in their programmes."<br />
26. The Forum welcomed the response by Australia, Fiji and<br />
New Zealand in particular who offered a range of additional<br />
benefits and trade concessions to the Smaller Island<br />
Countries to assist them with their special developmental<br />
problems. 27. Australia circulated to the Forum a paper on assistance<br />
it could make available to Smaller Island Countries in<br />
respect of the recommendations in the committee report.<br />
28. In addition to providing assistance in manpower<br />
development, Fiji announced that a special concessional duty<br />
rate had been introduced and was in place for imports of<br />
handcraft from Smaller Island Countries into Fiji. </p>
<p>29. Appreciation was expressed for a gre'nt of NZ$ 250,03O0<br />
from the New Zealand Government to fund follow-up to the<br />
report. The Forum agreed that representatives of the Smaller<br />
Island Countries should meet to decide on the application of<br />
these and other funds which may become available.<br />
ASEAN/ FORUM DIALOGUE<br />
Heads of Government agreed on the desirability of<br />
continuing to develop relations between the Forum and ASEAN,<br />
and to this end considered that there should be a further<br />
consolidation of links between SPEC and the ASEAN<br />
Secretariat. SINGLE REGIONAL ORGANISATION<br />
31. The Forum noted the interim report of the Committee of<br />
Foreign Ministers which had been established to look into the<br />
question of a Single Regional Organisation. It commended the<br />
Ministers for their work to date and requested them to<br />
continue their review.<br />
INCREASED INTER-PARLIAMENTARY CONTACT<br />
32. The Forum received a proposal for developing increased<br />
inter-parliamentary contacts in the region and agreed to the<br />
preparation by New Zealand of a more detailed paper to be<br />
presented to the next Forum.<br />
REGIONAL TRADE SPARTECA<br />
33. The Forum received the Report of the Fifth Meeting of<br />
the Regional Committee on Trade, held in Nauru in June 1985.<br />
It noted with satisfaction that trade under the South Pacific<br />
Regional Trade and Economic Co-operation Agreement ( SPARTECA)<br />
continued to grow and that Australia and New Zealand were<br />
continuing efforts through SPARTECA to assist the development<br />
of the Forum Island Countries. The Forum welcomed the<br />
announcement by Australia that across-the-board duty-free<br />
unrestricted access was to be granted to all exports from<br />
Forum Island countries other than products to which<br />
Australian sectoral policies apply. It also welcomed moves by<br />
Australia and New Zealand to liberalise thle rules of origin<br />
for imports under SPARTECA. The Forum acknowledged the<br />
concern of Smaller Island Countries that the provisions of<br />
SPARTECA were not particularly relevant to their needs:<br />
their export-oriented base was so small that they could not<br />
take advantage of the concessionary terms of trade that were<br />
available under the Agreement and special arrangements might<br />
be necessary in their case. The Forum welcomed the offer of </p>
<p>Australia and New Zealand to enter into discussions, without<br />
obligation, of whether there would be an advantage for other<br />
Forum countries to enter a broadened ANZCER. The Forum<br />
requested the Regional Committee on Trade to be held in<br />
Wellington next year to report on this matter.<br />
34. In the con-text of trade and investment the Forum<br />
welcomed an announcement by New Zealand of extensions to the<br />
PIIDS which should increase the effectiveness of the Scheme<br />
in attracting soundly based investment to the Forum Island<br />
Countries. THE PACIFIC FORUM LINE ( PFL)<br />
The Forum was pleased to note that the Pacific Forum<br />
Line had made very real progress in its development as an<br />
economically viable service. In 1985 it is expected that the<br />
PFL will for, the first time, achieve close to a break-even<br />
point in its operations. The Forum was appreciative of a<br />
recent grant from the EEC of 3.2 million ECUs for containers<br />
for the PFL and also welcomed a matching grant from New<br />
Zealand of approximately NZ$ 5 million for the Line. The<br />
Forum endorsed a pre-feasibility study of the proposed<br />
extension of the PFL feeder service from Fiji-Tuvalu-<br />
Kiribati to Micronesia.<br />
FORUM FISHERIES AGENCY<br />
36. The Forum took note o f the FFA Director's report and<br />
expressed great satisfaction with the Agency's performance.<br />
The Forum also expressed satisfaction that the FFA had now<br />
been fully recognised by the major foreign fishing nations.<br />
It called for the speedy conclusion of a multilateral treaty<br />
with the United States, which was of major importance to the<br />
countries in the Pacific.<br />
MICRONESIA 37. Heads of Government noted that the Peoples of the<br />
Federated States of Micronesia, the Republic of the Marshall<br />
Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands<br />
had exercised their right of self-determination in free and<br />
fair plebiscites observed by the United Nations. They looked<br />
forward to early approval of the termination of the<br />
Trusteeship Agreement over these territories by the United<br />
Nations in accordance with the express wishes of their<br />
Peoples. They also looked forward to the conclusion of<br />
arrangements for the termination of the Trusteeship over the<br />
Republic of Palau. f </p>
<p>38. The Forum welcomed and approved the application by Palau<br />
to be~ come a full member of the Forum Fisheries Agency.<br />
39. The Forum expressed its sincere condolences to the<br />
family, the people and the Government of Palau over the<br />
tragic death of its late President, Haruo I Remeliik. It<br />
wished to record its appreciation of the late President's<br />
interest in and contribution to regional affairs in the South<br />
Pacific.<br />
CHINA AND JAPAN<br />
Forum leaders noted that the General Secretary of the<br />
Chinese Communist Party had recently made a cuccessful visit<br />
to a number of regional member states, and had again<br />
emphasised China's strong interest in playing a helpful and<br />
constructive role in the region. The Forum noted Australia's<br />
offer to facilitate productive contacts between China and<br />
those FICs which might wish to develop their relations with<br />
China. 41. The Forum, taking into account Prime Minister Nakasone ' s<br />
visit to the region and the current levels of Japanese aid to<br />
Forum States, requested SPEC to explore the establishment of<br />
a dialogue with Japan with a view to obtaining further<br />
assistance for the Smaller Island Countries in particular.<br />
42. The Forum unanimcusly welcomed Fiji's offer to host the<br />
Seventeenth South Pacific Forum at a time to be decided in<br />
1986."<br />
Rarotonga, Cook Islands<br />
6 August 1985 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
