<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>40916</transcript-id>
    <title>Additional Funding for Queensland Communities Affected by Tropical Cyclone Debbie</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/04/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull and Queensland Premier Annastacia Palaszczuk today announced additional disaster assistance for communities affected by Tropical Cyclone Debbie and the associated rainfall and flooding.</p>
<p>Mr Turnbull said the Australian and Queensland Governments will jointly fund a $14.7 million Community Recovery Fund under Category C of the Commonwealth-State Natural Disaster Relief and Recovery Arrangements (NDRRA).</p>
<p>“This assistance is being provided through the jointly funded NDRRA in the local government areas of Gold Coast, Isaac, Logan, Mackay, Rockhampton, Scenic Rim and Whitsunday to address their medium to long term recovery needs,” Mr Turnbull said.</p>
<p>“The Australian and Queensland Governments will continue to work together to ensure affected communities receive the support and assistance they need to recover during this difficult time.”</p>
<p>Ms Palaszczuk said the cyclone caused widespread damage to infrastructure, essential services and housing, and significant flooding and storm water damage to across these communities. </p>
<p>“While progress has been made in relation to infrastructure recovery and rebuilding works, these communities are still facing ongoing hardship and disruption to normal community life,” Ms Palaszczuk said. </p>
<p>“The Community Recovery Fund will support initiatives and projects aimed at restoring social networks and building community resilience and capacity for the future.”</p>
<p>Information on disaster assistance available for this natural disaster can be found on the Australian Government’s Disaster Assist website and the Queensland Government’s Disaster management website. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
