<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>17459</transcript-id>
    <title> PM&#039;s XI to support prostate cancer</title>
    <prime-minister>Gillard, Julia</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20100624 - 20130627</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/11/2010</release-date>
    <release-type>Health</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Prime Minister Julia Gillard and Minister for Sport Mark Arbib today announced the launch of the 2011 Prime Minister's XI cricket match in Canberra next January.</p>
<p>The match is a showcase for up and coming Australian cricketers and this year's event will support the Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister was represented at today's launch at Manuka Oval by Minister Arbib and her partner Tim Mathieson, in his capacity as Men's Health Ambassador.</p>
<p>Prostate cancer affects 200,000 men in Australia each year and the Prime Minister applauded the Foundation's initiatives to raise awareness of symptoms, early detection and treatment options.</p>
<p>With the January 10 match being played just three days after the end of the Ashes series, there is certain to be heightened interest in the outcome.</p>
<p>This will be the seventh match between the PM's XI and England, with the PM's XI winning four matches to England's two.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's XI was first played in 1951 against West Indies and was reinstated in the cricket calendar in 1983-84 under Prime Minister Bob Hawke. The match has been played annually since then.</p>
<p>Senator Arbib thanked match sponsors ACT Cricket and Canberra Investment Corporation Australia (CIC) for supporting the game, which has become an important fixture on the Australian cricket calendar.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister's XI continues the Australian Government's committed to helping develop the next generation of Australian cricketers.</p>
<p>Earlier this year the Government invested $17.5 million in the Cricket Australia Centre of Excellence in Brisbane as part of our broader commitment to nurturing sporting talent.</p>
<p>Tickets for the event are on sale through Ticketek. The event is expected to attract a sell-out crowd. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
