<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11597</transcript-id>
    <title>Active Australia</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/10/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>All Australians have been inspired by the feats of our athletes at the Olympic and Paralympic Games in Sydney.</p>
<p>Now it is time to put that inspiration into practice and Active Australia Day on Sunday 29th October is a great opportunity for all Australians to get active.</p>
<p>The enjoyment of participating in sport or physical activity is not just for elite athletes, it is something that we can all benefit from. Active Australia Day is a celebration of sport and physical activity and is a call to all Australians to make regular exercise a part of their lives.</p>
<p>Developing a fitter nation by encouraging greater participation in sport and physical activity at a grass roots level is just as important as winning Olympic or Paralympic medals.</p>
<p>In particular I hope that one of the enduring benefits of our Olympic and Paralympic success is that more of our school students, who don't play sport as much as perhaps earlier generations of school students, will take up regular sport or physical activity.</p>
<p>We know that almost six out of every ten Australians do not participate in sufficient physical activity to provide a health benefit, despite the widespread opportunities available.</p>
<p>Exercise does make us healthier, happier and more able to cope with the challenges of everyday life. Moderate activity such as a brisk 30-minute walk three times a week, or joining a local sporting team, can be very beneficial.</p>
<p>Active Australia Day provides Australians with the chance to 'have a go' at a sport or some form of physical activity and I encourage all Australians to get involved.   </p>
<p>27 October 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
