<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5269</transcript-id>
    <title>PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH DUNCAN FAIRWEATHER, 26 FEBRUARY 1980</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/02/1980</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005269.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRESS OFFICE TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH DUNCAN FAIRWEATHER<br />
26 FEBRUARY 1980<br />
Question Prime Minister we-heard terms used in the House today that we<br />
haven't heard for some time. Why do you think that the motion<br />
that the Labor Party bought on was argued in those terms?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
I do not know except that I sometimes think that there is a<br />
concerted campaign and a decision by the Labor Party to use terms<br />
like ' liar' and ' hypocrite' and all the rest. For the last two<br />
or three years there have been concerted times when that has<br />
happened. I think they have generally done it when they have not<br />
had an argument, haven't had a case and they have been wanting to,<br />
as was the case today, prevent what otherwise was being said,<br />
from being heard. The words I've used which seemed to cause tbis<br />
C thought were fairly moderate in the circumstances they are<br />
t~ otally accurate. What I said was that there is or seems to be a<br />
-thread in the Labor Party, not the whole Labor Party, a thread<br />
: Ln che Party which wants to find excuses for the Soviet actions<br />
: Ln Afghanistan or if not excuses at least reasons why Australia<br />
should do nothing about it. I do not think that is good enough.<br />
I think that what was said was totally accurate and it remains<br />
accurate., Question In response the descriptions that Mr. Hayden made of you were<br />
rather savage. Why didn't you defend yourself?<br />
Prime Minister<br />
There was nozt a motion before the House. If they had moved that<br />
censure motion it would have been taken and the words, the charges<br />
would have been thrown back in their teeth. But they were moving<br />
the suspension of Standing Orders which we opposed because it was<br />
in the middle of Question Time, in fact I was in the middle of<br />
answering a question,. which I completed after it was all over.<br />
But I can only say that there was no motion on the books. There was<br />
nothing before the House and if a motion of that kind is debated,<br />
or is moved, it will certainly be debated, then I believe that it<br />
will only degrade those who move it.<br />
Question Do you think we can expect to see this sort of debate coming up<br />
through this session through this election year.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
No I would hope not. Because what goes on in the House is vastly<br />
important, just as the Government's view of Afghanistan is vastly<br />
important and carrying sufficient importance to require us to do<br />
something about it. And if the Labor Party are going to take the<br />
view that, all right they condemn the invasion of Afghanistan, but<br />
they seek to undermine everything we seek to do to bring that home<br />
to the Soviet people.' VWell if that'* s-the vi-ew they are-going to<br />
take then I suppose there will be some rugged debates. I think<br />
that is a pity and I only wish, for example, Mr. Hayden had kept </p>
<p>Prime Minister ( continued)<br />
with his original view on the Olympic Games. Because he has said<br />
and I think believes that a boycott of the Olympic Games would be<br />
a very effective way of bringing the abhorrence of Australia and<br />
of other countries home to the Soviet Government and people. But<br />
he at one point said if there was a significant international<br />
support he will join it, or would consider joining it, to be quite<br />
fair to him. But it's not good enough saying that 40 other<br />
countries have to do this before we would consider it. We believe<br />
an effective boycott would be of great importance in bringing the<br />
message home to the Soviet Union and in preventing them moving<br />
into other areas because they know the reaction that it will get.<br />
We are' committed/ ought to be committed, morally and practically<br />
and every way to doing something about it. But Mr. Hayden not<br />
only doesn't want us to do anything about it, by his argument he<br />
quite plainly seeks to frustrate the achievement of an effective<br />
boycott. I just find that very difficult to understand and to<br />
put that alongside his condemnation of the actual invasion.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
