<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6737</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 24 SEPTEMBER 1985, BRISBANE SHERATON</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>24/09/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006737.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
14W8;<br />
E. 4. O. fl. PROOF ONLY<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 24 SEPTEMBER 198S, BRISBANE SHERATON<br />
JOURNALIST:.. you insist on Dr Armstrong's resignation?<br />
PM: I have nothing to say about that at this stage. All I have to<br />
say about current circumstances is that I spoke to Mr Reid today at<br />
his request on the phone in Townsville. I will be seeing him on<br />
Thursday-in Canberra. I have nothing to add.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do you have confidence in Mr -Reid' still as Chai-rman of the<br />
AuthorityY PM: That's not fatir, Michiellv, at this stage. I have answered that<br />
question before in the very precise terms that I will be talking with<br />
Mr Reid.<br />
JOURNALIST; Can you reiteratLe<br />
PM: Can you let me finish the answer the answer, please. I will be seeing<br />
him on Thursday. It is quite unfaiir to him, to me, and to everyone<br />
involved to say anything on that question until I discuss it with him.<br />
JOUR] NALIST:<br />
have gone.<br />
Dr Armstrong Mr Reid doesn't seem to know quite why Dr Armstrong should<br />
lie seemed to be in two minds. He wasn't sure whether<br />
why you had insisted that he go.<br />
PM: If.. you have -got -any doubts about what Mr Reid is saying, you should<br />
be addressing your questions to Wr Reid.<br />
JOURNALIST: INAUDII3LE Is that your expectation?<br />
PM: I'm not going to go to that issiue.<br />
talk after I've seen Mr Reid.<br />
JOURNALIST: I will be quite prepared to<br />
What did Mr Reid 43y?<br />
PM: Mr Reid just conveyed to me the decision about.... the Board<br />
had expressed confidence in him and his handling of this matter. and<br />
confirmed that he will be meeting with me on Thursday.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Reid was quite precise. He said he didn't know why<br />
Dr Armstrong resigned.<br />
PH: Did he?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM: That's intereting. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: What's your response?<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, did Mr Reid inform you that there was no tax<br />
minimisation involved in Dr Armstrong's resignation?<br />
PM: When I raised this question he expressed confidence in the matter of<br />
tax. In that context I said I still want to have something in writing from<br />
you and Mr Reid confirmed to me today that either before I see him on<br />
Thursday or certainly by Thursday he will have a full answer in writing on<br />
this matter. Again, it is not appropriate to talk about that until I get<br />
that from him.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do.' yot'uthink, Prime Minister, that the meetin-on Thursday will<br />
clear this up?<br />
PH: Woll, I would trust that the response that Mr Reid gives to me,<br />
inaudible I hope that that will clear that matter up.<br />
JOURNALIST; He said the tax had nothing to do with the Authority,<br />
though. It is a matter between Dr Armstrong<br />
PM: I am<br />
make Now, On the question of tax, Michelle, I simply repeat what I have said.<br />
not making any further comment on that. It is not fair to Mr Reid to<br />
any further comment on that matter until I receive his letter..<br />
I will be able to talk to you after Thursday.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you pleased that the Board backed Mr Reid today?<br />
PH: I am pleased that they discussed the matter and they have confidence in<br />
what he has done. Of course I am happy about that.<br />
j y r m </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
