<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4921</transcript-id>
    <title>30TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/12/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004921.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: MIDNIGHT, 9 DECEMBER, 1978<br />
4AUSTRALIA , g<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR PRESS 9 DECEMBER, 1978<br />
ANNIVERSARY OF THE UNIVERSAL<br />
DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS<br />
Today, 10 December, marks the 30th Anniversary of the<br />
Universal Declaration of Human Rights. It is appropriate<br />
to affirm that Australia remains committed to the promotion<br />
and protection of fundamental human standards. The<br />
anniversary comes at a time when there is a growing<br />
international recognition of the importance of human rights.<br />
It is essential that Australia be seen as a firm upholder<br />
of human rights. It is also in Australia's interests that<br />
all communities and countries join in a commitment to<br />
the basic principles and standards as set out in the<br />
Declaration. The Declaration was adopted by the U. N. General Assembly<br />
in 1948. For thirty years it has been a basic document<br />
promoting the aspirations of all nations and all peoples<br />
concerned with fundamental rights and freedoms. The<br />
Declaration is one of the most significant and enlightened<br />
achievements of the United Nations.<br />
As was announced in July the Commonwealth, in association<br />
with the States and the Northern Territory, will be<br />
embarking on a program designed to make available to<br />
the community at large, information on the Universal<br />
Declaration of Human Rights and its significance to Australia.<br />
The program is at an advanced stage of preparation and<br />
it is expected that discussion kits for schools and ethnic<br />
and aboriginal organisations will be available early<br />
next year. Explanations of Australia's Racial<br />
Discrimination Act, in English and other ethnic and<br />
Aboriginal languages, will also be distributed.<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
