<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7627</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON COMMENTS BY RALPH WILLIS - PETER THOMPSON, THE WORD TODAY 5 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007627.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW ON COMMENTS BY RALPH WILLIS PETER<br />
THOMPSON, THE WORLD TODAY 5 JUNE 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: I'm not going to go any further. As the Minister<br />
indicated there are certain processes of investigation going<br />
on within the Party and of course he has provided a<br />
significant input to those processes. I think that's all<br />
that needs to be said at this stage.<br />
THOMPSON: If there is to be a change of policy first of all<br />
the ALP Airlines Funding Committee must recommend that.<br />
What Mr Willis said does put them under great pressure.<br />
PM: I don't know whether it puts them under great pressure.<br />
He made a clearly articulated case before so your question<br />
assumes that this was the first time they'd heard this from<br />
Mr Willis. The opposite is true, he's appeared before them<br />
and put the case.<br />
THOMPSON: Of course if there's to be a change of ALP policy<br />
that would require a special national conference. Do you<br />
favour that sort of thing?<br />
PM: As he said, that's required and we understand that.<br />
THOMPSON: Are you happy about that idea?<br />
PM: It's not a question of being happy, that's why the<br />
thing has been done. We considered it at the previous<br />
conference, it was recognised that this was an issue in<br />
which there are lots . of considerations and emotions<br />
involved. I understand all those and I'm one, as I think<br />
it's been well established, that likes to see processes<br />
established which enable people to express their points of<br />
view, have the matter fully on the table. So in a sense<br />
there's nothing new in what the Minister said, it's just<br />
that there was an articulate public expression of the issue.<br />
We hear this pathetic posturing of the Opposition which<br />
talks about reform in the Government business enterprise<br />
section and talks about privatisation. You've got to<br />
remember that for 31 years of the 34 before we came to<br />
office they were in power they never did anything in terms<br />
of micro-economic reform or to make the public enterprises<br />
more efficient. Now they're just tub thumping and making<br />
noises which are empty noises. We've gone about the<br />
business of trying to make the public sector more efficient<br />
and we're succeeding. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
THOMPSON: Just a very brief final one on that machinery of<br />
bringing in a change of policy, would you hold an ALP<br />
national conference before the next election?<br />
PM: There's no commitment necessarily to holding one before<br />
the next election. I'm not going to be rushing into some<br />
judgement about these things, I'm quite happy with the way<br />
the processes are going. You must get your perspectives<br />
right in politics and remember that all that's happened is<br />
that the Minister has said on a television program precisely<br />
what he said to the Committee some time ago. That's the<br />
reality, the fact that something said on a television<br />
program which has already been said to the Committee<br />
shouldn't be regarded as something remarkable.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
