<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10867</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIAN FIRE SERVICE MEDAL            ANTARCTIC MEDAL</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/07/1998</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Last year I announced a number of initiatives to enhance the Australian</p>
<p> system of honours and awards.</p>
<p>On this day, the first anniversary of the Thredbo tragedy, I am now</p>
<p> pleased to announce that Her Majesty The Queen has approved amendments</p>
<p> to the Australian Fire Service Medal and the Antarctic Medal.</p>
<p>The amendments expand the Australian Fire Service Medal quota from</p>
<p> one medal for each 25,000 volunteer firefighters to one medal for</p>
<p> each 5,000 volunteers. This revised formulation provides a fairer</p>
<p> basis on which outstanding merit for volunteer staff will be recognised.</p>
<p> This increased recognition will be warmly welcomed by the whole community,</p>
<p> which regularly witnesses the tireless dedication of our volunteer</p>
<p> firefighters. This devotion was witnessed by all Australians last</p>
<p> year in Thredbo and over the summer during the bushfire season.</p>
<p>The amendments to the Antarctic Medal rename the medal the Australian</p>
<p> Antarctic Medal and give recipients of this medal a postnominal entitlement</p>
<p> of "AAM". Like other medals, which recognise outstanding</p>
<p> service, awards of the Antarctic Medal have been given on a strict</p>
<p> basis of outstanding service. However, the lack of a postnominal entitlement</p>
<p> for this medal was an anomaly for a meritorious service award in the</p>
<p> Australian honours system.</p>
<p>The Government is pleased to announce these changes and I warmly congratulate</p>
<p> all past and future recipients of the Australian Antarctic Medal who</p>
<p> are now entitled to use the initials "AAM" after their name.</p>
<p> 31 July 1998</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
