<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3244</transcript-id>
    <title>RATIFICATION OF INTERNATIONAL LABOR ORGANISATION CONVENTION ON EQUAL PAY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>06/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003244.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
EMBARGO: 2. OOPM MONDAY 6 MAY 1974<br />
. J ,, AUSTRALI( At&amp;-<br />
RATIFICATION OF INTERNATIONAL LABOR ORGANISATION CONVENTION<br />
ON EQUAL PAY<br />
The Australian Government in its submission in the 1974 National<br />
Wage Case argued for an extension of the minimum wage to adult females.<br />
As a result of the successful outcome of this submission and of the<br />
submissions of the Women's Electoral Lobby, the Union of Australian<br />
Women and the National Council of Women of Australia, the Australian<br />
Government has now fulfilled its obligations under the I. L. O. Equal<br />
Remuneration Convention of 1951. Before Australia ratifies the<br />
Convention, however, the defaulting States have to agree to<br />
ratification. The Prime Minister has sent telegrams to the Premiers of New South<br />
Wales, Queensland and Western Australia urging that their governments<br />
take the necessary action to enable Australia to ratify the Convention<br />
as soon as possible. The governments of Victoria, South Australia and<br />
Tasmania have already done this.<br />
The Australian Government attaches the utmost importance to<br />
ratifying this Convention. In June 1901 the federal Parliamentary<br />
Labor Party resolved to " support the equal payment of females with<br />
males when work of a similar character was performed and the hours of<br />
work were the same."<br />
Immediately upon taking office the Whitlam. Government successfully<br />
applied to re-open the 1972 National Wage Case in support of this<br />
principle. Women employed in the Australian Public Service were granted<br />
equal pay without a phasing-in period.<br />
The Prime Minister said today that for their 21 years of office,<br />
after the Convention was adopted, Liberal and Country Party governments<br />
had failed to press for the ratification of this important Convention.<br />
Nowhbre in the latest Liberal/ Country Party policy for women is this<br />
principle supported and at no time have the leaders of those parties<br />
stated their intention to ratify this Convention. Worse still, last<br />
December, Mr. Snedden publicly stated that he did not think that women<br />
would be advantaged by passing legislation guaranteeing them equal pay,<br />
for this would affect their job opportunities.<br />
The Prime Minister today reiterated the reply he then gave to<br />
Mr. Snedden. He said that he wanted to make it quite clear that he did<br />
not accept that women should only get jobs if they do them more cheaply:<br />
if they are doing the same job they should be paid the same money. / 2 </p>
<p>The Equal Pay Convention is the only I. L. O. human rights<br />
convention which the Australian Government has not yet ratified.<br />
The Whitlam Government has ratified all the remaining ones.<br />
Ratification of this Convention will clearly indicate the<br />
significance which Australia attaches to removing all forms of<br />
discrimination against women in our society. The Government's<br />
industrial policy places human rights and values first.<br />
It decrees that a proper share in the nation's productivity<br />
is the right of all persons male and female who are ready,<br />
willing and able to work.<br />
CANBERRA. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
