<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7722</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE, 23 AUGUST 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/08/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007722.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF INTERVIEW WITH JOHN LAWS, RADIO 2UE,<br />
23 AUGUST 1989<br />
E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
LAWS: OK, well you better tell them, because they'll<br />
want to know one garlic tablet per morning?<br />
PM: Yes, one garlic tablet after breakfast and you won't<br />
get the flu.<br />
LAWS: OK.<br />
PM: You've got to do it every day, John.<br />
LAWS: Really?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
LAWS: All the time?<br />
PM: All the time.<br />
LAWS: OK, well I'll try it. Yesterday one of your many<br />
Press Secretaries-<br />
PM: Eh? I've only got two, mate.<br />
LAWS: Well, one of them rang my only one and said that the<br />
word was that I was pro pilots. Well, I just wanted to<br />
clarify that, I hope he listens to you more than he listens<br />
to me because that isn't the case. I am pro people getting<br />
what they believe they're worth, if in fact they are worth<br />
it, but that should surely be the criteria shouldn't it?<br />
PM: Well, I guess we all tend to believe we're worth more<br />
than the market can stand, so if it was just a question of<br />
what you believed it wouldn't be a good test. I think the<br />
real thing is what the community can stand, John, I think<br />
that's the real thing, that's the issue here. I'm not, if I<br />
may say so quickly, although I'm tough at the moment against<br />
what the pilots are doing, I'm not anti pilot and I'm not<br />
against people being paid a decent salary, but the big<br />
thing, John, if they were to win this, the whole wage system<br />
is dead and Australia is dead. </p>
<p>LAWS: Yes, well that's really the basis of the argument and<br />
that's a very valid one. I mean, it's right and proper that<br />
you did your best to dissuade them from going for what could<br />
be seen by some as an excessive increase, being 30 percent,<br />
but when you say you're not anti pilot, I'll tell you what<br />
that some of the comments that you made in the newspapers in<br />
the last couple of days, you could have fooled me and you<br />
could have fooled the pilots.<br />
PM: Well, what I'm against, and violently against, is what<br />
the pilots are doing but why would anyone be against, anti<br />
pilot. I mean, pilots have got a very important job in the<br />
community, very important job, and I respect the job that<br />
they do. But what I'm against is the blatant greed they're<br />
exhibiting and the way in which they're going about this<br />
exercise. LAWS: Yes, well I suppose there are plenty of other people<br />
in the community who exhibit blatant greed. We see it time<br />
and time again. we see it in the upper echelons of top<br />
business management where, I believe, a chief executive in<br />
the large Australian company now averages something like<br />
$ 900,000 a year. I suppose that could constitute greed in<br />
the eyes of some?<br />
PM: I guess it could and in fact it does. I think many<br />
executives have been greedy when you consider that the<br />
people they employ, the ordinary wage and salary, your<br />
ordinary listener, or his or her wife or husband, have<br />
exhibited over the last six years a remarkable restraint<br />
LAWS: Extraordinary restraint.<br />
PM: If it hadn't been for what your listeners and their<br />
wives and husbands have-done, we wouldn't have had a million<br />
and a half more new jobs in this country. It's been the<br />
restraint of your people, you know, you talk and represent<br />
the average bloke and woman in the country, they've<br />
exercised restraint and Australia's reaped the benefit.<br />
That's what annoys me, whether it's a greedy executive or a<br />
greedy airline pilot.<br />
LAWS: But you don't come out against the greedy executives.<br />
PM: Don't we? I mean<br />
LAWS: Well, you don't stop them.<br />
PM: Well they are not in the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
system, but no-one has been tougher than Paul Keating and I<br />
and Bill Kelty in addressing the Business Council of<br />
Australia, the Confederation of Australian Industry and<br />
pleading with them to exercise restraint. But we haven't<br />
got them in the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission. </p>
<p>-3-<br />
LAWS: Well, that's the whole point the pilots are making.<br />
They choose now apparently not to be within that system,<br />
which I suppose is a choice they're entitled to make isn't<br />
it? PM: Yes, sure it's a choice they're entitled to make but<br />
they've got to take the consequences. They're<br />
LAWS: Absolutely and the consequences can be<br />
disadvantageous to them.<br />
PM: They can and will be. But just to get this into some<br />
sort of context about what sort of conditions the pilots<br />
were in before, could I just give you, John, a couple of<br />
quotes from what their own former President had to say.<br />
This was just a year ago in October. This is Captain<br />
Fitzsimmons and this is what he's saying about them and I<br />
just very brief quotes. He said I'm talking about the<br />
agreements I've got within the Arbitration system, that's<br />
what he's talking about when he said it contains and<br />
maintains some of the best working conditions in the world<br />
of aviation point one. Point two you're the only big<br />
systems in the world who have a block guarantee of pay, ( c)<br />
there is no other pilot group in the world that enjoys your<br />
overall standard of pay protection. Now that's the<br />
condition that they're in through the system.<br />
LAWS: In fairness, that was said a year ago.<br />
PM: That's what I said, I said it was a year ago.<br />
LAWS: Yes, they might consider times have changed in a<br />
year. But when you say the business executives are outside<br />
the system, that's right, that's their choice to be outside<br />
0 Atuhes trsaylsitaenm aanndd hIe womauyl d wehlalv e lotsheo ugbhyt iitt was the choice of any<br />
PM: It's not a matter of choice as far as executives are<br />
concerned. I mean, with employers you don't have the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration system setting the conditions<br />
of executives and employers. It may be that, you know,<br />
you'd like to have that but that is not the system but with<br />
these people, they're in there and as a result of that<br />
system operating in a centralised way, you've had a position<br />
in Australia where you've had the containment of wages,<br />
where the whole of Australia, every one of your listeners,<br />
is better off because of the restraint that's been<br />
exercised. Now, these people are in a situation where<br />
they've got the benefits and if they are allowed to get away<br />
with a 30 percent increase on conditions which, you know<br />
what they are at the moment, an average of $ 80,000 a year<br />
for less than ten hours a week flying.<br />
LAWS: Yes, but I think that's a fairly facile argument. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
P14: well, what's facile about it? They're boasting about it.<br />
LAWS: Yes that's right, but they spend $ 42,000 of their own<br />
money getting into a position to be able to do this sort of<br />
job. They spend endless hours away from their family,<br />
that's their choice, you know, I'm not siding with them,<br />
that's their choice to do it. But<br />
PM: But what about all the amount of money and time that<br />
other people have to spend and not, not to work less than<br />
ten hours a week at the job they've trained for.<br />
LAWS: Yes, but that's physically sitting at the job.<br />
obviously a lot of other time goes into it. Now you<br />
PM: Not an enormous amount of time.<br />
LAWS: Now listen you can fly an aeroplane because you said<br />
you learnt in seven hours.<br />
PM.: Yes. I'm not special about that.<br />
LAWS: No, I believe you, I believe you.<br />
PM4: I'm not special about that. Anyone can.<br />
LAWS: That's right, but you know how to fly-an aeroplane.<br />
I doubt you know how to fly a jumbo?<br />
PM: Of course I don't.<br />
LAWS: OK, but if you<br />
P1M: is it being suggested in respect of flying today,<br />
then don't bring me into it. I mean-<br />
LAWS: Well you brought yourself into it.<br />
PM: But I'm simply don't make any more out of what I did<br />
John, about mentioning myself than I intended it meaning.<br />
That is simply because I did learn to fly, I know all the<br />
nonsense that exists about the mystery, the magic and the<br />
glamour of flying. I mean, that's part of the problem.<br />
Here are these people doing an important job for the<br />
community, but has been surrounded about the fact of<br />
flying, a glamour and a mystique, which is supposed to mean<br />
that these people, now getting $ 80,000 a year on average,<br />
for actually flying less than ten hours a week, that there's<br />
something mystical and magical about it. The only point I<br />
was trying to make no more and no less than this that<br />
once you've learnt to fly you know that after all it's not a<br />
terribly difficult thing to learn. what's then involved of<br />
course is gaining more experience and it is a very<br />
responsible job. </p>
<p>LAWS: And being checked every six months to see that you're<br />
capable PM: what about the blokes, what about the blokes who<br />
service the aeroplanes? The mechanics. All the years they<br />
acquired, a five year apprenticeship and then more and more<br />
experience getting up to actually servicing those planes<br />
that the pilots and the passengers get into. Now if those<br />
and they're not working eight hours a week they'll be<br />
working the'best part of 40 hours a week and if any one, any<br />
one of those mechanics who were in fact servicing the<br />
aeroplanes didn't do their job properly, didn't do their job<br />
properly, then the life of the pilot and the passengers is<br />
as much at stake as if those pilots don't do it. But<br />
LAWS: No, but can we talk about that? I fail to see that<br />
there's anything terribly glamourous about hanging around<br />
Bahrain airport for eight hours because there's been some<br />
problem with an aeroplane there. I fail to see there's too<br />
much glamour in trying to get an aeroplane out of the sky<br />
that has had some monumental malfunction as we saw recently<br />
and we're seeing time and time again. To me that's not too<br />
glamourous, to me that's<br />
PM: With these domestic pilots, I'm not sure how much time<br />
they spend hanging around Bahrain. I mean they're not<br />
really LAWS: We were talking about<br />
PM: I'm talking about this dispute, these pilots and I'm<br />
talking about comparing these fellows who actually fly no<br />
more than ten hours a week, that there's something special,<br />
mystical, glamourous abou. t them that entitles them, on their<br />
average existing salary of $ 80,000 a year now to get<br />
percent more. I'm saying compare them with the fellows<br />
who've exercised the restraint, who if they didn't exercise<br />
the same amount of care and commitment in servicing the<br />
planes and getting them ready, would create just the same<br />
sort of problem for passengers as pilots if they didn't<br />
exercise their restraint.<br />
LAWS: But what does that mean?<br />
PM: It means<br />
LAWS: The people who fuel the aeroplane, service the<br />
aeroplane, should be making as much as the pilot?<br />
PM: No it doesn't. It means that if they are prepared to<br />
exercise the restraint that they are and which has brought<br />
about a position where we're creating jobs more than twice<br />
as fast as the rest of the world because the workforce is<br />
exercising restraint for the benefit of Australians, then </p>
<p>-6-<br />
these people who are also within the system of getting a<br />
rate of pay which their own leaders have said is amongst the<br />
best in the world. I mean, they shouldn't be entitled to<br />
break the system because the simple fact, which every one of<br />
your listeners must understand, is if they are allowed to<br />
get out of the system, break it 30 percent increase or<br />
anything like that 30 percent increase then the whole wage<br />
system is broken<br />
LAWS: That's right<br />
PM: And then we will have the economy broken down,<br />
inflation go rife, interest rates go absolutely through the<br />
roof, the economy buggered. </p>
<p>-7<br />
LAWS: Yeah, but if they're not worth it, and you don't<br />
believe they are worth it, obviously, if they're not worth it,<br />
then surely that should be negotiated between them and the<br />
people who run the airlines?<br />
PM: It should be negotiated within the system on my<br />
judgement and if they're going to say ' no, we're just want a<br />
straight power game. Okay, this remains a democracy where<br />
people can opt out if they want to<br />
LAWS: yeah..<br />
PM: but,<br />
LAWS: but you make it very difficult for them to<br />
operate PM: they, they, they, they have been using their<br />
power. They have been using their power. As far as the<br />
airlines and the Government is concerned, our power will be<br />
0 used. Not because I want to hurt an individual pilot, not<br />
because I want to denigrate pilots or the profession of the<br />
pilots, but because I want to protect the Australian economy.<br />
That's paramount.<br />
LAWS: Yeah. The situation as it develops, came at a very<br />
unfortunate time for you inasmuch as the Government was<br />
rolling along according to the stories that we hear from the<br />
corridors of Canberra, you were on a high and very confident,<br />
and why not? The Government was in great shape. So, it<br />
arrived, as an election isn't very far away, at a pretty<br />
unfortunate time to add insult to injury, didn't it?<br />
PM: No, I don't see it that way at all. I simply repeat<br />
what I said to you before, it would've been an unfortunate any<br />
day or any week, this situation would've been unfortunate.<br />
Because, there has been this overwhelming adherence by the<br />
ordinary working men and women of this country, basic<br />
acceptance by them, and by the community of the benefits of<br />
restraint, and that's been enormously important in having a<br />
situation where we've created the jobs and become a more<br />
competitive economy; and any day that there had arisen a<br />
situation where one group was going to threaten to destroy all<br />
that would've been unfortunate. And I just, on this one, I<br />
think that the Australian community will be overwhelmingly in<br />
support of a situation where you have the Government trying to<br />
protect the economy, and that's what's involved.<br />
LAWS: We had an interesting day yesterday, when I looked<br />
at the story from the other side, which I choose to do with as<br />
many stories as I can and the reaction, in fact, from the<br />
majority of listeners I couldn't get a bus driver. We had<br />
all the lines open, all morning. I couldn't get a bus driver.<br />
I spoke to a number, but I couldn't get one to agree that his<br />
job was as responsible as flying an aeroplane. Do you regret<br />
making that statement?<br />
PM: No, no, no, no. Look, I don't regret trying to make<br />
the point that I've been trying to make; and that is I repeat, </p>
<p>8-<br />
I'm not trying to denigrate the responsibility of pilots.<br />
What I'm saying is that there are many people in the<br />
community, who if you used the test of responsibility for the<br />
lives of others, would be able to use that argument.<br />
Including, including,<br />
LAWS: No, no, hang on. Be fair.<br />
PM: No, I'm using the proposition<br />
LAWS: yeah, but, I mean if you had a bingle in a bus,<br />
chances are you're going to walk away. If an aeroplane falls<br />
out of the sky, there's very little chance. I mean, there is<br />
a difference, isn't there?<br />
PM: But, it's the lives and safety of your passengers<br />
are an issue; and let's go to the aeroplanes. I mean, of<br />
course, every person with a greater or lesser degree has some<br />
sort of apprehensions about when they're flying, but the point<br />
I'm making is this: that the pilots are the ones, who are at<br />
the end of the line and ultimately have the responsibility if<br />
something goes wrong. But what about the people who have the<br />
responsibility if there's anything every, anything goes wrong<br />
with the plane?<br />
LAWS: Oh, yeah. Absolutely. But,<br />
PM: do, do you have..<br />
LAWS: but I don't understand the point you're making.<br />
Do you believe that they should be able to<br />
PM: No. I'm simply..<br />
LAWS: as much as the pilots?<br />
PM: No, I'm simply..<br />
LAWS: well, what's the point?<br />
PM: The point is a simple one. That what the pilots are<br />
attempting to use is the particular nature of their<br />
occupation. Now, what I'm trying to say is firstly, in regard<br />
to becoming a pilot, becoming a pilot: there's nothing<br />
terribly flash about acquiring the basic qualifications of<br />
becoming a pilot.<br />
LAWS: To fly a little chipmunk?<br />
PM: Of course. But what I'm saying is that..<br />
LAWS: even I did that.<br />
PM: Yeah. But when you get to the bigger planes it's<br />
just a natural progression from actually learning to fly; and<br />
you compare I mean, if you want to compare the blokes that<br />
are flying today, with their predecessors, not Bob Hawke and<br />
the Chipmunks, but with the people who are flying </p>
<p>9-<br />
commercially. You know, in that early post-war period. You<br />
look at the differences in flying today compared to then. The<br />
facilitation for flying. Firstly, the sophisticated automatic<br />
pilots that operate now, which are flying the plane, which are<br />
actually flying the plane for most of the time. And now, the<br />
radar. When these blokes' predecessors, here in Australia,<br />
when they were founding the aviation industry in the post-war<br />
period. Did they have radar? They had to fly through every<br />
bit of bloody awful weather there was. No assistance in<br />
avoiding all the toughness.<br />
LAWS: Yeah but,..<br />
PM: no sophistication<br />
LAWS: fine,..<br />
PM: but I'm simply making the point not to denigrate<br />
these people but to say, that in terms of the conditions<br />
under which they operate, it's a relatively easier situation<br />
that their predecessors and I'm saying, in terms of the<br />
welfare and safety of every single person that gets onto an<br />
aeroplane, John, that from the un-heralded, un-glamorous<br />
mechanic in the hangers, every minute he's working on those<br />
planes has a responsibility which if not properly discharged,<br />
can endanger the safety and life of the pilot<br />
LAWS: absolutely, but..<br />
PM: and, and, and in respect of those people, they<br />
are not saying ' well, we are in the airline industry, there's<br />
something magical about us'. They are working a full 38-hour,<br />
36-hours a week or more, and..<br />
LAWS: yeah, but<br />
PM: and they are exercising restraint in regard to<br />
what they get paid.<br />
LAWS: Yeah, but they do alright. Can I just tell you<br />
this? An aircraft re-fueler, thanks to penalty payments and<br />
other allowances, earns sometimes a great majority of the<br />
airline pilots. So, you know..<br />
PM: Not a great majority. I wouldn't accept that.<br />
There's people..<br />
LAWS: well, I mean, there are airline pilots flying<br />
for $ 31,000 a year. I spoke to a young bloke yesterday that<br />
spent $ 42,000 his mother I spoke to $ 42,000 getting his<br />
licences. He's now running up hours in the Western part of<br />
Australia earning $ 16.00 an hour.<br />
PM: Thats sort of thing's happening because people want<br />
to get, I mean, why do they want to do it? There is, it goes<br />
back to what I was saying, there is this glamour, there is<br />
this mystique of being a pilot. Now, I can understand it<br />
because it is a thrill. It is a real thrill. I know that. </p>
<p>10<br />
LAWS: Absolutely. And I imagine that's why a lot of<br />
people want to do it.<br />
PM: And, and blokes are prepared to spend $ 40,000 or $ X<br />
to satisfy their craving and their desire to be a pilot and<br />
beyond them. But what I'm saying is that ' you spend what you<br />
like to satisfy your craving and your quite understandable<br />
thrill to become a pilot'. Beaut. Good. I can understand<br />
it.<br />
LAWS: And your desire to make a dollar?<br />
PM: And, once you've done it though, don't think, my<br />
dear boy or collection of boys, that you're going to wreck the<br />
Australian economy. Pay what you like, if you want to satisfy<br />
your craving and your desire and understandable aspirations to<br />
fly an aeroplane; but don't come along to the Australian<br />
people, to the Australian Government and this Prime Minister<br />
and say ' because I've spent that money to satisfy my thrill<br />
and aspirations to become a pilot, that you're going to wreck<br />
the Australian economy'<br />
LAWS: Yeah, yeah, but they're not saying that.<br />
PM: They might not be saying it, but I'm telling you<br />
what, that everyone else understands that if they're allowed<br />
to get away with this, that's what will happen, because let<br />
there be no doubts John, if the Australian people, through the<br />
airline companies and this Government succumb to this threat<br />
let there be no doubt about it<br />
LAWS: even a 10% increase, that would wreck the<br />
Australian economy we must be really heavily in the<br />
balance if 10% increase in the airline pilots<br />
PM: They're not talking about 10%, they are talking<br />
about 30% and not being negotiated according to the<br />
guidelines. LAWS: No, but they want to negotiate with their employers.<br />
Now, if everyone says 10%, that's not going to wreck the<br />
Australian economy?<br />
PM: What I'm saying is that they've got to accept that<br />
they'll do it within the guidelines. If what they are doing<br />
is the exercise of power for an objective of 30% that's out!<br />
If they want to have a negotiation, within the system, that's<br />
open to them. They refused to do it. They said to the<br />
Arbitration system ' that operates for anywhere else, not for<br />
us, because we are pilots'. Well, I've got news for them.<br />
They are pilots, they are important, they do a very, very,<br />
very good job. But, because they happen to be pilots who've<br />
satisfied a desire, a legitimate and understandable desire to<br />
become pilots, and this thrilling and satisfying job of being<br />
a pilot, because they've satisfied that desire, they are not<br />
uniquely going to be able to wreck the Australian economy. </p>
<p>11<br />
LAWS: No, because they go outside the guidelines, and<br />
nobody has any argument with that. But when you stop and<br />
think that the judges were outside the guidelines, and they<br />
were, the Government, the Government<br />
PM: the judges weren't within the guidelines. The<br />
judges were within a system, the Remuneration Tribunal had a<br />
system LAWS: yeah, but it's a pretty good remuneration..<br />
PM: no, no..<br />
LAWS: compared to what the others are getting.<br />
PM: What I'm saying is that when the Remuneration<br />
Tribunal for judges brought down their recommendation, we<br />
wouldn't even go to the point of accepting that. They've had<br />
to wait.<br />
LAWS: That's right. But they've got 12 percent and<br />
they've got some more coming and I think that the Family Court<br />
Judges got 30 percent. Now that's outside the guidelines.<br />
PM: It's not outside the system which operates for that<br />
group of people<br />
LAWS: That<br />
PM: under the law.<br />
LAWS: So they have a different set of guidelines.<br />
PM: Of course they do.<br />
LAWS: What about the-new Government....<br />
4, PtMh: a t's a smJaurstt aan dm intuetlel, i ngj ucsto mmienn tc. a se, Y ouy ouha vken ow, you think<br />
LAWS: Yours or mine?<br />
PM: No, yours. That they are under a different set of<br />
guidelines. LAWS: Well they are.<br />
PM: Under the legislation, I mean, it's not our idea, or<br />
some fancy idea we've thought up. There is a system under the<br />
law which governs the way Judges are awarded. There is a<br />
system. And the pilot can't get into the Judges Remuneration<br />
Tribunal system. That's for Judges. For the pilots, there<br />
is the Industrial Relations Commission. That's their system<br />
where their guidelines operate.<br />
LAWS: Yeah but you can't say that nobody can ever get<br />
outside the guidelines. </p>
<p>12<br />
PM: Well I can say in respect of the Judges that they<br />
have their guidelines, under the Remuneration Tribunal which<br />
would even go that far in, I can say in regard to wage and<br />
salary earners, their system is the Industrial Relations<br />
Commission and they operate within that. And I'm simply<br />
saying... LAWS: But if they want to go outside they can go outside.<br />
PM: They can, yes they can, the pilots can. They can go<br />
outside, but they are not going to get support. They are not<br />
going outside because they like the atmosphere out there,<br />
they're going outside because they've got industrial muscle<br />
and they say they're going to use that industrial muscle to<br />
smash the system. They're not.<br />
LAWS: Well when you say wage and salary workers are inside<br />
the guidelines, why didn't you perform when sales executives,<br />
U chief executives of companies went outside the guidelines?<br />
PM: Because they're not in the system.<br />
LAWS: Yeah, but they got out of the system.<br />
PM: They were never in it.<br />
LAWS: Of course they were. They were in it when they...<br />
PM: Come on, lets have facts rather than unsubstantiated<br />
opinion. LAWS: How do you know?<br />
PM: I'm telling you that the managers that you're<br />
talking about were never in the system. Chief executives of<br />
companies have never been under an award in the system.<br />
k LAWS: But how do you know that? How do you know that they<br />
didn't start in a factory. You don't know where they started<br />
of course they may have been in the system?<br />
PM: I mean this is just talking about it in an earlier<br />
stage of their career, of course you' re right, they've got<br />
out... LAWS: work their way out of the system.<br />
PM4: Yeah, but the pilots didn't. The pilots didn't<br />
start as a first year pilot in the system and when they became<br />
a senior pilot, out of the system. This statement here by<br />
Fitzsimmons, applied to all of them from the junior to the<br />
seniors, they didn't go outside the system. They got the best<br />
conditions in the world, John, by this statement, in the<br />
system LAWS: Yeah, okay, but a lot of people start in the system.<br />
I mean I used to belong to Actors and Announcers Equity,<br />
right, so I was in the system. I worked my way out of the </p>
<p>13<br />
system, this place is full of people who have worked their way<br />
out of the system. You can do that. If I can do that, and<br />
you don't go crook at me, or you haven't yet, well why can't<br />
they do it. If they choose to, they might be wrong and they<br />
might lose, they might be worse of f, they mightn't get any<br />
increase but surely in a democratic country they have the<br />
right to try.<br />
PM: And they can if they are doing the sort of thing<br />
that you're talking about, progressing up the scale... . yeah but<br />
sure they do. I mean if a pilot converts from being a pilot<br />
and goes up in the company to becoming a manager, then he's<br />
out of the system, he is. These people are not, they are<br />
staying as pilots in your system, that's the...<br />
LAWS: Okay well lets go back to me.<br />
PM: You're talking about one system and I'm talking<br />
about the Conciliation and Arbitration system which is the<br />
system which determines the wages and salaries and conditions<br />
of people employed under awards in that system. If they move<br />
out of that employment relationship as pilots can do, move up<br />
to become managers, they are out of that system and then their<br />
salary is determined according to a decision by the Board or<br />
the top management, and that's perfectly right but while they<br />
remain as pilots operating in a wage and salary relationship<br />
then the Industrial Relations award covers them.<br />
LAWS: Okay, well I started in the system as a broadcaster,<br />
and I'm still a broadcaster, but I went outside the system.<br />
what.. PM: You sure did. The thing is that when you started,<br />
if you were under the award, I don't know whether you were.<br />
LAWS: I was.<br />
S PM: Then your wage and salaries were determined by the<br />
IF Award. I don't know what you got paid. Then as you went up<br />
LAWS: eleven quid.<br />
PM: Eleven quid, and it's a bit more than that now,<br />
because you are not only an employee, I don't know what your<br />
relationship is, but you're a part owner..<br />
LAWS: No. No, I'm not.<br />
PM: Well whatever you are, you are not now simply an<br />
employed servant under an award, and this is right, I mean<br />
LAWS: Because I got out of the award, but why can't<br />
anybody, I'm not saying they're right, you know<br />
PM: Everyone can do it, and I'm saying in respect of the<br />
pilot.. </p>
<p>14<br />
LAWS: let them do it.<br />
PM: Let them do it, I'm saying in terms of moving up out<br />
of the ranks of the employed that's what they do. We're<br />
talking about those who stay within the employment<br />
relationship but if a pilot, just take Bill Smith. He's a<br />
pilot now.<br />
LAWS: Right.<br />
PM: Why when he's a pilot, what his union has chosen to<br />
do, and has got the best system in the world is to say, Bill<br />
Smith and all his mates have said ' we are a union, we are<br />
operating within the Arbitration system'. We'll determine<br />
Bill Smith's wages and conditions by operating within the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration system and Bill Smith does it<br />
he operates that way. But then Bill Smith, he's a John Laws of<br />
the air, not of the airwaves, he's a John Laws of the air,<br />
he's got a bit more talent, he's got a bit more ambition, so<br />
he ceases to be a pilot and he goes up, he goes into the<br />
management structure. He's then out of the award system, the<br />
Conciliation and Arbitration system. He's had this upward<br />
mobility that you properly referred to. once he's moved out<br />
of that employment relationship, goes up there then his<br />
salaries and conditions are determined as a matter of<br />
negotiation by the board of the company as other executives<br />
are. So John, there is the fluidity, if Bill Smith the pilot,<br />
changes from being a pilot, moves up, expands, gets to the<br />
top, then he's out of the Conciliation and Arbitration system.<br />
But while he is operating as a salaried employee, then how<br />
he's chosen and how his union has chosen to operate to<br />
determine that, is within the Conciliation and Arbitration<br />
system by award.<br />
LAWS: Okay, well we would assume that the fellow who runs<br />
Australian Airlines<br />
lip LAWS: Okay. Well we would assume that the fellow who runs<br />
Australian Airlines, good bloke, James Strong, is an employee.<br />
To my knowledge, he doesn't have a share of Australian<br />
Airlines. He's an employee. I think he gets about 400 or<br />
450?<br />
PM: No. He is a contracted management salary person. And<br />
what has been done there is, as consistently been done, is<br />
they haven't been under awards, never been under awards. It<br />
is a matter of their salary being determined by the Government<br />
and the Board. Now what we've done, and what I know you'd<br />
agree with, that you would say that Government enterprises,<br />
while they exist, should be competitive, should be<br />
bureaucracies, they should'be competitive.<br />
LAWS: Absolutely.<br />
PM: And what we've done there is to say, alright, we've<br />
looked at what's been paid in other enterprises, as we did<br />
with the bank. We had a situation where we had the Governor<br />
of the Reserve Bank getting about a tenth of what was being </p>
<p>15<br />
paid to bosses of the private banking system. So you had to<br />
have a system where in these enterprises your top management<br />
was getting some sort of comparability with the people that<br />
they were, you know, competing with and, in some cases, almost<br />
controlling. Now with Strong, the head of TAA, well it's<br />
Australian now, it was TAA.<br />
LAWS: Yes.<br />
PM: There nothing was changed in terms of the way the salary<br />
was determined. It wasn't under an award, it was a contracted<br />
salary position.<br />
LAWS: Yes, but you had to pay him to keep him?<br />
PM: We had to pay and if we were going to have a situation<br />
where we thought we could get the best.<br />
LAWS: That's right. So you had to pay him to keep him<br />
O PM: Yes.<br />
LAWS: because his service was invaluable.<br />
PM: Yes. And in the case of the pilots, we have paid a<br />
situation which has kept them all, in which they have said<br />
themselves that it's the best in the world. The ego about now<br />
is saying, we want to use a position of very, very<br />
considerable power to extract a lot of 30 percent and knowing<br />
that in doing it we wreck the system. Now there is no<br />
comparison between what the impact of going to a 30 percent to<br />
these fellows would be and what was necessary to pay the heads<br />
of public enterprises like the Reserve Bank, the Commonwealth<br />
Bank and so on.<br />
LAWS: Yes.<br />
PM: No comparison.<br />
O LAWS: Yes.<br />
PM: I'd pay them what's necessary to make those enterprises<br />
competitive. That's not going to wreck the system.<br />
LAWS: Tell me this. If an airline pilot with twenty years<br />
experience, right, fairly valuable sort of bloke to have<br />
around, one would think, if he were to go along to Ansett or<br />
to Australian Airlines and say well look I want to stay, can<br />
we negotiate a personal contract with me. There's nothing<br />
wrong with that?<br />
PM: But what will happen now..<br />
LAWS: I mean, he put the contract ( inaudible)<br />
PM: There will be negotiations between the airlines and their<br />
pilots. I mean, the Federation, in this sense, will be<br />
irrelevant. The Federation won't be negotiating with the<br />
airlines and provided that any increase that's awarded doesn't </p>
<p>16<br />
give increases in their salary rates outside the guidelines,<br />
then they may well negotiate positions which will give them<br />
significant increase in income. But it won't come, it won't<br />
come, John, from getting salary increases in their rates<br />
outside the guidelines. They will have to keep within them.<br />
But what the airlines may very well do is to say what we want<br />
you to do is to not fly something less than ten hours a week,<br />
we'd like you to fly something like twenty hours a week. Now<br />
if you get an increase in salary, in rates, in accordance with<br />
the guidelines and they, in fact, negotiate a significant<br />
increase in hours as could reasonably be done, they may well<br />
get an increase in income, a significant increase in income,<br />
but it won't be what they're talking about now a 30 percent<br />
increase in salary on something less than ten hours a week.<br />
LAWS: So you mean it would require an increase in<br />
productivity? PM: Yes. A significant increase in productivity.<br />
LAWS: Are the judges working harder?<br />
PM: The judges are working very, very hard.<br />
LAWS: Are they working harder than they were working before<br />
they got their 30 percent increase?<br />
PM: Well, they didn't get a 30 percent increase. And what<br />
the judges have done is operate within the legal framework of<br />
salary determination which applies to them. That's what<br />
they've done. They haven't gone outside it. They haven't<br />
said, alright, we're going to, you know, Jack up, only work<br />
half the schedule in overtime or less than that, we're only<br />
going to work eight hours a week.<br />
LAWS: So they don't have to increase their productivity?<br />
PM: Well, they deal, as expeditiously as they can, with a<br />
O njuumdgbeesr oonf lyc awsoesr k beefiogrhet thhoeumr. s aA nwede ki. s anyone suggesting that<br />
LAWS: Not so far?<br />
PM: No.<br />
LAWS: Not so far?<br />
PM: No.<br />
LAWS: I don't know that anybody's analysed it. Maybe<br />
somebody ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, the Remuneration Tribunal has and has made a<br />
decision, or make a recommendation, that they should have got<br />
a much greater increase and we didn't do it.<br />
LAWS: Yes. Strong story this morning, but only rumour so it<br />
should be broached. Is there any truth in the story that the<br />
Australian Government's going to underwrite the airlines for </p>
<p>17<br />
any losses incurred?<br />
PM: Underwrite them.<br />
LAWS: Yes?<br />
PM: There's no question of underwriting them. If they are<br />
operating in a situation where they are going to incur<br />
enormous losses and they come to us with a situation which<br />
says, well, we want this to be taken into account in regard to<br />
charges which we put upon them, well they can put that case.<br />
We have given no commitment about that at all.<br />
LAWS: Would you be inclined to give them a hand?<br />
PM: I'm not making any commitment about that. They raised<br />
the point and I said, well, this dispute is on, it's a<br />
question of principle, let's go into it and we hope we can fix<br />
it, you know, quite quickly. If you want to raise that later,<br />
if it's a long dispute, raise it, but without commitment,<br />
because they understand there's a question of principle here<br />
which applies, not just to the pilots, but to all of their<br />
employees and to the whole community. And that's a quite<br />
hypothetical thing that's been raised. I've said no<br />
commitment about that. If this goes on for a long time, let's<br />
look at it then.<br />
LAWS: Yes. But not beyond the realms of possibility?<br />
PM: Well, they're perfectly entitled to raise it, but no way<br />
which in this early stage there'd be anything be done. I<br />
mean, if you were looking at a situation where it went on and<br />
on, then they would be entitled to raise this with us and we'd<br />
look at it because we've got a position here, of course, John,<br />
as I mean you've been generous enough to concede right<br />
through, I mean there's been no argument about us on this<br />
issue. And that is that the whole economic interest of this<br />
country is at stake here and when that is the case, well when<br />
the Government has got to be prepared to look at all the<br />
ramifications to defend the Australian economy.<br />
LAWS: Yes. How do you believe this will end?<br />
PM: It will end, in my judgement, by a negotiation either<br />
between the companies and their individual pilots or a<br />
negotiation within the arbitration system by their return and<br />
a negotiation which, in my judgement, would mean an increase<br />
in salary rates. When I'm saying salary rates, not out of<br />
line with the guidelines. In other words, 6 percent or that<br />
sort of order. But with the possibility of an enormous<br />
increase in productivity by the pilots having to agree to work<br />
longer hours. Now, in one way or another, I think that's the<br />
basis of the outcome and that is a perfectly proper one. The<br />
other way is that the guidelines have been adhered to, but<br />
there is an increase in the hours worked, an increase in<br />
productivity and a benefit for pilots in a sense, for the<br />
airlines and for the paying customers because if you get a<br />
significant increase in productivity that will have its impact </p>
<p>18<br />
upon the fare situation.<br />
LAWS: So when the dust settles, will the pilots be better<br />
off? PM: Well, if they accept that working for longer hours, for<br />
increased income, means they'll be better off, then answer to<br />
that is yes. And I don't think really, John, whether we have<br />
some arguments at the edge about the ten hours, or eight to<br />
ten hours, one can hardly argue that either absolutely or in<br />
comparison with their colleagues around the world, that they<br />
are overworked. I mean, they say that themselves that they<br />
are not by comparison with the rest of the world. So if you<br />
have an outcome in which they work longer hours and get<br />
greater income as a result of working longer hours and you get<br />
greater productivity, then everyone will be better off.<br />
LAWS: Do you feel inclined to take a call or two from a<br />
listener? PM: Sure, John, sure, sure.<br />
LAWS: Well you have to stick those funny headphones on and<br />
I'll pop one up.<br />
PM: Okay.<br />
LAWS: You right for it.<br />
PM: Either one of these.<br />
LAWS: Yes, anything that's got a noise coming out of it.<br />
It's about eight minutes to ten. My guest is the Prime<br />
Minister of Australia, Bob Hawke. If you'd like to talk to<br />
him, and I see the board is full, keep trying, 929 5555.<br />
Hello. CALLER: Hello, is that you, John.<br />
S LAWS: Yes. The Prime Minister is here.<br />
CALLER: Thank you very much.<br />
PM: Hello.<br />
CALLER: Good morning.<br />
PM: Good morning.<br />
CALLER: I can't understand you talking about greed and<br />
restraining ourselves because, now what about this $ 30,000 for<br />
stamps and unlisted stationery that the politicians have got.<br />
Do you think that's restraining. Don't you think that's<br />
greed? PM: No, I don't because it's not worth a..<br />
LAWS: stamp? </p>
<p>19<br />
PM: it's not worth a cent or a stamp to politicians of<br />
either side. But the politicians on both sides will be using<br />
this for the purpose of communication with the electorate.<br />
They don't get a single cent into their income. So, I mean,<br />
how is that greed. They don't make a penny out of it. What's<br />
involved is communicating with their electorate. So there's<br />
no question of greed.<br />
CALLER: They most make a penny, but it is<br />
PM: Well how, if they don't make a penny themselves, if they<br />
don't make a penny, how is it greed.<br />
CALLER: But this end result?<br />
PM: That's the end result. If it doesn't get into their<br />
pockets, if they're not personally better off for one cent,<br />
how is it greed.<br />
CALLER: You don't....... stinks. They won't let the people,<br />
they've got to get in touch with them for their next reelection,<br />
you see and that's what it's all about and you talk<br />
about the economy of Australia, don't you think it's a bit<br />
late?<br />
PM: No, I don't. I think, in fact, that anything that can be<br />
done to enable a greater communication between electors and<br />
those who are elected, whether it's a Labor Member of<br />
Parliament, a Liberal or a National Party. I think anything<br />
that increases communication is a very good and a sensible<br />
thing and I hope that all sides of politics, not just my own,<br />
I hope that the Liberals, the Nationals, the Democrats, I hope<br />
they'll all use it because in the end we're going to have<br />
better Government if there's more communication between those<br />
who are elected and those who elect them.<br />
CALLER: Look, I know dozens of people that get literature<br />
through the mail and they don't even read it. It's waste of<br />
U paper, waste of money and you're always talking about this<br />
glamour and magical bit. You place so much importance on<br />
glamour? PM: Well, I don't really. I mean, John has known me, for<br />
instance, I know John, how long does it go back.<br />
LAWS: Twenty-five, twenty-six.<br />
PM: Twenty-five years. And I think John would tell you that<br />
I'm not a flash sort of bloke. I mean, the glamour and all<br />
that does with this sort of thing has never been part of the<br />
thing that turns me on whether when I was President of the<br />
ACTU or when I've been a Member of Parliament. All the pomp<br />
and ceremony is the part of the job that, you know, leaves me<br />
for dead. All the nineteen gun salutes, all that sort of<br />
thing, it means nothing to me I can assure you and, I mean, I<br />
think John can confirm that. It's not part of my bag.<br />
LAWS: Well why did you keep bringing it up about the pilots? </p>
<p>20<br />
PM: No, look, she, can I just, is it Mrs, who is it, Mrs.<br />
LAWS: We don't know.<br />
PM: Well, Mrs or whatever. I just don't like saying<br />
nothing, I'd like to know your name.<br />
LAWS: Ma'am, I always call them Ma'am.<br />
PM: Ma'am. Okay. Ma'am. I really am not trying to say that<br />
there isn't, you know, real legitimate reasons for pilots<br />
feeling that there is something, you know, special about their<br />
job. I mean, I can, the only reason I mentioned that I<br />
learned to fly myself was for no more and no less a reason<br />
than to say this. That I understand, you know, the attraction<br />
of flying. It just is a magnificent feeling to get up there<br />
in an aeroplane and fly. I mean, it just is a magnificent<br />
feeling and there has been projected in all the literature, I<br />
El mean, you don't see novels and you don't see advertisements<br />
about aircraft mechanics, the people who make the plane safe.<br />
I mean, what the advertising, all the glamour is about the<br />
pilot. Now that's understandable because that's the bloke<br />
that's up there, that's the one you see. There's no glamour<br />
about the bloke who slogs away day after day, out there in the<br />
hangers, making the aeroplane safe. And I'm simply saying<br />
that there is this mystique and glamour about the fact of<br />
being a pilot. Now that's alright, I'm not worried about<br />
that, but I don't want that translated into a situation where<br />
because of that people think that they can move from that to<br />
bust the Australian economy. That's the only point I'm making<br />
that it is a very important job. I'm not dismissing that.<br />
CALLER: But two standards. one that suits you....... judges<br />
and it's not saying that judges don't deserve their right.<br />
I'm not saying the pilots don't deserve theirs. But what I'm<br />
saying is that there seems to be two standards.<br />
PM: No, well there's not. I mean, this is where, with<br />
respect, Ma'am, you're wrong. In regard to the judges, we<br />
have, under the law, under the law, a Remuneration Tribunal<br />
and under that Remuneration Tribunal the question of salaries<br />
of judges is considered.<br />
LAWS: And, Ma'am, with respect, that law was in place before<br />
this Prime Minister came to power.<br />
CALLER: Oh, yes, yes. Well I'm not, I couldn't, I don't want<br />
to get personal about these things.<br />
LAWS: No, well let's not. I think the questions have been<br />
answered and we've got a lot of people waiting. Please don't<br />
say I gave you short shrift because that's not my intention,<br />
but there are a lot of people waiting. I think you made your<br />
point. Hello, hello. Just hang on, just hang on, we'll tidy<br />
up that line. Yes, go for your life.<br />
CALLER: John, look I'm disgusted. This is quite a unique </p>
<p>21-<br />
industry, this airline industry.<br />
LAWS: Okay, well you talk to the Prime Minister, not me.<br />
CALLER: Prime Minister.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
CALLER: We're in quite a unique situation. Look the aviation<br />
industry PM: Who's we?<br />
CALLER: Well, the aviation industry in Australia who's going<br />
into deregulation next year.<br />
LAWS: Are you a pilot?<br />
CALLER: No, I'm not a pilot. I'm within the industry.<br />
PM: Well what do you do in the industry, mate?<br />
CALLER: An engineer.<br />
PM: An engineer.<br />
CALLER: Yes. Are you with one of the major companies.<br />
CALLER: Yes, I am.<br />
LAWS: You're one of the good blokes then. The Prime Minister<br />
likes you. You keep the aeroplanes up there.<br />
PM: I mean, when you say you're an engineer, do you maintain<br />
the aeroplanes?<br />
CALLER: Yes, I do, yes.<br />
PM: Yes, yes, good.<br />
CALLER: We are just as skilled as any engineer in the world.<br />
At the moment we are suffering crisis because our engineers<br />
are not getting paid enough within Australia and overseas<br />
airlines are poaching us to other airlines in the industry and<br />
we just can't compete.<br />
PM: Well, of course, that's not right. What is happening, in<br />
fact, that, as you know, or at least, I mean, I'm not asking,<br />
no, which of the two airlines do you work with?<br />
CALLER: Well, I'm not going to go into that.<br />
PM: No, no, but I don't want to know, no, I can't identify<br />
you, but it's relevant to my answer, which of the two airlines<br />
do you work with?<br />
CALLER: Private side of it, how about put it that way.<br />
LAWS: That'll do, the private side. </p>
<p>22<br />
PM: You work for Ansett.<br />
CALLER: I never said anything.<br />
PM: Well, no, but see what I'm getting at is, I'm not trying<br />
to identify you and I never could, but I'm simply making the<br />
point that, in fact, the Australian airline industry is<br />
attracting, because of the quality of its service, we do work<br />
for international airlines. Now I know it is the case that<br />
some of the airlines would like to be able to pay fellows who<br />
are, in fact, employed as maintenance engineers, they'd like<br />
to pay them more because, in fact, there's a, you know,<br />
relevant shortage and so on. But they haven't. I mean, what<br />
they've done is they've stayed with the airlines and we are,<br />
in fact, not only doing our own work but doing some of the<br />
work of others from overseas. Now, look, I would like, I<br />
mean, if you are in fact working as an engineer, a maintenance<br />
engineer, with Ansett, as you suggest, I would like, and I'm<br />
sure a lot of us would like a situation where you could, in<br />
fact, be paid more. But there are a whole lot of people in<br />
the Australian community who, over the last six years, could<br />
have been paid more if they'd just exercise their muscle.<br />
They could have gone out and exercised their muscle and wages<br />
could have been higher. But, in fact, they haven't done that<br />
and, in the result, we've had one and a half million new jobs<br />
created right around the Australian economy which is a rate of<br />
job creation more than twice as fast as the rest of the<br />
industrialised world. Why? Because the organised wage and<br />
salary earners of this country have exercised restraint, as I<br />
say, a matter which John Laws very generously has consistently<br />
recognised. But the community has benefitted because people<br />
have exercised restraint. It's not a question of saying that,<br />
you know, ideally we wouldn't like to pay more, we'd like to<br />
do that wherever it's warranted, but, in the end, the great<br />
bulk of Australian workers have accepted that they don't only<br />
have to look at their own immediate interests, but whether<br />
they're going to create a situation where there's more<br />
employment for themselves, for their kids and so on. Now<br />
that's the balance.<br />
CALLER: I understand that, Prime Minister, but with due<br />
respect, Qantas is sending 747' s to be maintained all over the<br />
world because we can't do it ourselves. The skilled engineers<br />
are leaving in droves because they're not getting competitive<br />
wages with what they're getting overseas. They're leaving<br />
Australia, I'll tell you now, they're leaving Australia in<br />
droves. I'm not talking about one or two, I'm talking about<br />
PM: Yes, but let's give the whole picture rather than part of<br />
it. It's always, you know, an argument. I mean, I've been<br />
around in public life for thirty years and I know how easy it<br />
is to have one side of an argument. But also you've got a<br />
situation where people are coming to Australia. It's not just<br />
simply a question of people, you say leaving the job, they're<br />
also people coming here. And Australia is not the only place<br />
which has got skilled people. There are others who have got<br />
skills overseas and are wanting to come to Australia and are </p>
<p>23<br />
coming. Now if you, in the end, stripped of everything else,<br />
your argument is simply this. If you've got power, if you as<br />
a worker or a union has got power, use it to get more money<br />
because that's what's necessary.<br />
LAWS: Yes, Is it fair to say, is it fair to say power really<br />
and I know you'd like to be fair. What about the difference<br />
between power and talent?<br />
PM: But, look, that's what I said in the first part of his<br />
answer to question. I would love to have a situation where<br />
everyone that's got the talent, that's qualified themselves,<br />
could get the sort of show which they think, you know, that a<br />
nice lovely person to be entitled to. Now that would be<br />
beaut. But in, for god's sake, in this tough competitive<br />
world we can't just let our wages system blow out here. Look,<br />
we tried it once and it was in this decade, in 1981, this<br />
ideal was applied. Just let it blow, don't have centralised<br />
wage fixation, don't have guidelines, don't have principles,<br />
just let the negotiation go and what happened. Well, in other<br />
words, we don't have to be theoretical about this. Just at<br />
the beginning of this decade that happened, wages blew out by<br />
seventeen percent, the economy collapsed, we got the worst<br />
recession in fifty years, we got double-digit unemployment and<br />
inflation and the whole economy collapsed. The worst<br />
recession in fifty years when what happened is what you're<br />
saying. Just don't worry about principles, don't worry about<br />
guidelines, let it go. Well, my friend, I am not prepared to<br />
let it go.<br />
CALLER: I don't expect you to let it go, Prime Minister, but<br />
what I'm trying to say to you is we are in a field of<br />
international competitiveness here at the moment. We're not<br />
just talking about average Australians. If an average plumber<br />
here could walk to New Zealand, fair enough. But the<br />
engineers and pilots are in a field which is up for grabs by<br />
international carriers every day?<br />
oil PM: Look, as far as the pilots are concerned, was it said<br />
before, the day they, when was there stoppage, that we had,<br />
that Ansett and TAA had a shortage of pilots. Was that said?<br />
CALLER: Yes, it was. ( inaudible) pilots at the moment?<br />
PM: You are saying that we couldn't operate Ansett and TAA<br />
because of a shortage of pilots. There was an effective<br />
shortage of pilots which were stopping it operating. Now you<br />
know that that's not right.<br />
LAWS: Not right.<br />
PM: It's not right. The simple fact is that the pilots<br />
wanted more money and it wasn't a situation where Ansett and<br />
TAA had to be offering more to keep their system operating.<br />
LAWS: That's why they don't have to do it.<br />
PM: And, in fact, what the pilots said, look, we think we're </p>
<p>-24<br />
in a pretty strong position and we want 30 percent increase on<br />
top of our average $ 80,000. And what the airlines have said,<br />
we might have given in to you before mates, we may have given<br />
in to you before, but it's a different baligame now and it is.<br />
Now, look I'm not unsympathetic to what you're saying about<br />
the engineers because you are right in saying that a very<br />
important job, you know, that it's competitive, but the<br />
points that you're not realising are, in fact, because of the<br />
quality of the people we've got here, we are doing, in fact,<br />
overseas work. We could do more if we had more people,<br />
there's no doubt about that. But we are training more and<br />
we're getting people from overseas. It's not a one way<br />
traffic and if, you know, there was a capacity to pay more,<br />
you would do it, but what's been worked out between the unions<br />
and the airlines is a restructuring under the restructuring<br />
processes which will go a considerable way towards meeting the<br />
legitimate concerns of maintenance engineers in the industry.<br />
CALLER: I hope that we can keep what engineers we have here<br />
and the skilled ones at that<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
CALLER: but I feel that if we don't this country is not<br />
going to be able to compete in an area which is becoming more<br />
competitive day by day and I feel that if we don't do<br />
something to try and maintain our standard, I think we will be<br />
falling short of what average Australians would expect.<br />
PM: The standards will be maintained by the whole award<br />
restructuring process which will mean, not only more pay<br />
according to the restructural principles and the guidelines of<br />
the Commission, but, importantly, we will have a situation in<br />
which the whole training and retraining processes will be<br />
facilitated which means you'll get even better training, more<br />
flexibility on the job and more satisfying work. That's<br />
precisely what's being done now under the principles. And<br />
under the wage fixing principles, we're about getting better<br />
training, more satisfied employees, better remunerated<br />
employees in a way which is going to benefit the whole<br />
economy. That's what's happening in the rest of the workforce<br />
and we want the pilots to understand that they can't be in a<br />
category of their own.<br />
LAWS: Okay. We've got to leave you. We'll take another<br />
quickie here. Hello.<br />
CALLER: Hello, John.<br />
LAWS: Yes.<br />
CALLER: Yes. Could I speak to the Prime Minister.<br />
LAWS: He's right here.<br />
CALLER: Hello.<br />
PM: G'day. </p>
<p>25<br />
CALLER: Yes. Look, I'm an airline pilot. Well I was an<br />
airline pilot until last night. I'd just like to query what<br />
you're saying about flying being glamorous. I don't think<br />
there's much glamour<br />
LAWS: Keep your voice up a bit, you're a bit quiet.<br />
6,<br />
* 1 </p>
<p>26<br />
CALLER: About pilots being glamorous. It is not glamorous<br />
at all.<br />
PM: How long have you been flying for?<br />
CALLER: I've been flying for about seventeen years'now.<br />
PM: How many years?<br />
CALLER: Seventeen.<br />
PM: Seventeen. And what rank did you have?<br />
CALLER: I don't think it's applicable.<br />
PM: I really want to be responsible and positive in my<br />
reply to you. After seventeen years what rank did you have?<br />
CALLER: I don't think that's applicable.<br />
o LAWS: How much money were you making?<br />
CALLER: I'm making $ 45,000 a year. or I was till<br />
yesterday. I've just been offered a job outside the<br />
industry yesterday for $ 140,000 a year. My suggestion is to<br />
virtually any pilot out there that they should look outside<br />
the industry because they're wasting their talents in the<br />
airline industry.<br />
PM: I think, my friend, if I could just interrupt you if<br />
you're earning $ 45,000 year and you've now been offered<br />
$ 140,000 my recommendation is you're a mug if you don't<br />
take it. Go and take it.<br />
CALLER: What I'm trying to say to you though is that the<br />
majority of airline pilots are highly intelligent, skillful<br />
people, and most of them have management experience.<br />
PM: Now come on. Most of them have management experience.<br />
~ JJ Look my friend, I'm prepared to accept everything you've<br />
said, that you are a pilot, you earn $ 45,000 after seventeen<br />
years and you've just been offered $ 140,000. I'm prepared<br />
to accept all that because I've got no alternative but to<br />
accept it. I will not accept a blatantly absurd proposition<br />
that most of the pilots have had management experience.<br />
That my dear friend is absolute bloody nonsense and you know<br />
it. CALLER: No, I don't.<br />
PM: Well tell me. OK. On what do you base the<br />
proposition that the great majority of pilots have had<br />
management experience?<br />
CALLER: What do you think flying in a cockpit means?<br />
PM: You say managing the crew? I will accept that. </p>
<p>-27<br />
CALLER: And it's highly dedicated, You are constantly<br />
checked every six months. Your job is on the line every six<br />
months. I wish your job was on the line every six months<br />
because you wouldn't be there if<br />
PM: Well that's a very intelligent intervention. Let me<br />
say that I operate under a system where I've had to put my<br />
job on the line, I've had to put my job on the line, go for<br />
an election and so far it's every time. We'll see what<br />
happens next time. But I don't think your case is helped by<br />
that gratuitous insult.<br />
CALLER: I'm sure you are the ones who started the insults.<br />
PM: I'm not. Because my friend, what you don't understand<br />
is that I do have a high regard for the job that pilots do.<br />
You'd have to be out of your mind not to have a high regard<br />
for the job that pilots do. All I'm about is not to<br />
denegrate pilots but to try and get some perspective, get it<br />
into perspective. The job that you do, or that you used to<br />
do before you go out to do this other one<br />
LAWS: What's the new job, out of interest?<br />
CALLER: Managerial.<br />
LAWS: Beg your pardon.<br />
CALLER: It's managerial.<br />
LAWS: What sort of management?<br />
PM: There's a difference between managing a crew in an<br />
aeroplane, which is very important and managing outside.<br />
What sort of job is it?<br />
CALLER: As I said, it was managerial in marketing.<br />
PM: That's beaut. I think you should do it. I'd hope<br />
you'd feel this, that You, know I, as a passenger, I've<br />
flown probably more miles than 99.5% of people in Australia.<br />
I know the importance of pilots. I respect them. But I<br />
just want you and the Australian community to get this in<br />
perspective. There are a hell of a lot of people in the<br />
community whose contribution is important. Every time<br />
you've got into that aeroplane, as you know and I don't<br />
think you'd dispute this with me every time you've walked<br />
up the steps into that aeroplane you know better than anyone<br />
that your life, your safety, as well as that of your<br />
passengers, has depended upon the quality of the work that's<br />
been done by mechanics in those hangars. Those people,<br />
those people have had to do five years training and<br />
apprenticeship and acquire a hell of a lot of experience to<br />
get that position where they are in fact maintaining and<br />
servicing your planes. </p>
<p>-28<br />
CALLER: Can I just butt in there. I started off being an<br />
engineer. I had a look at the conditions and salaries and I<br />
thought I'd be an airline pilot.<br />
PM: How did you your engineering? By apprenticeship?<br />
CALLER: By apprenticeship.<br />
PM: How many years did that take?<br />
CALLER: I didn't finish it because I could see that<br />
PM: How many years apprenticeship did you do?<br />
CALLER: I beg your pardon.<br />
PM: How many years apprenticeship did you do?<br />
CALLER: I think it was about nine months.<br />
PM: You think it was about nine months. You're not sure.<br />
I see. OK. Where did you do it?<br />
CALLER: 17 years ago.<br />
PM: Did you do it with an airline?<br />
CALLER: No, I didn't.<br />
PM: So after nine months what you said to me, you were an<br />
engineer before you became a pilot.<br />
LAWS: He was an apprentice.<br />
PM: But now you are a person who did nine months<br />
apprenticeship. You said to me, to John Laws and to some<br />
hundreds of thousands of people, before you became a pilot<br />
you were an engineer. It turns out you did a nine months'<br />
apprenticeship. Is that right?<br />
CALLER: No. What I'm saying is<br />
PM: I'm asking a question. I'm not trying to be difficult.<br />
You said you were an engineer before you became a pilot.<br />
To try and be constructive, I was trying to get the<br />
background. CALLER: I've got a choice haven't I.<br />
PM: Wait a minute. You've also got the choice of putting<br />
it straight. You've said you were an engineer. I asked you<br />
how you got there apprenticeship. You said you did nine<br />
months' apprenticeship. Does doing nine months'<br />
apprenticeship make you an engineer does it?<br />
CALLER: No. </p>
<p>29<br />
PM: Well why did you say you were an engineer?<br />
CALLER: You haven't listened to what I'm trying to say.<br />
You don't understand what I'm trying to say.<br />
PM: I really want to be helpful to you and to listeners.<br />
Just tell me how you became an engineer. You did nine<br />
months' apprenticeship.<br />
CALLER: I started an apprenticeship, right, but I decided<br />
from that point, after about nine months, it was going to<br />
PM: But you said you were an engineer. Were you or were<br />
you not an engineer or were you a person who did nine<br />
months' apprenticeship?<br />
CALLER: If that's your clarification then<br />
PM: It's your clarification mate. You came onto this<br />
program, apparently seriously to talk about an issue in<br />
which I'm desperately concerned. John Laws is concerned and<br />
so are his listeners. You purported to have something to<br />
say about this, that you were a pilot for 17 years, before<br />
that you said you were an engineer, so you could talk about<br />
the relationship between engineers and pilots. Then I find<br />
out CALLER: I'm not talking about that at all. You still<br />
don't understand. You don't seem to want to understand.<br />
PM: I want to understand my friend whether you were an<br />
engineer which is what you said.<br />
CALLER: I've told you that I was an apprentice.<br />
PM: Nine months' apprentice and you say that makes an<br />
engineer. OK.<br />
CALLER: I have never said that I was<br />
PM: I don't know John, what did you hear?<br />
LAWS: Yes, I heard that. I think we'll just give that a<br />
miss. You've been having such a good time you've forgotten<br />
what time it is. Barrie Cassidy is ripping his hair out.<br />
Can we take one quick one?<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
LAWS: one quick one. Hello.<br />
CALLER: Hello John. I'd like to take the Prime Minister up<br />
on three points that he's mentioned this morning if you'd be<br />
happy to give me the time to do so. Firstly he's made<br />
considerable mileage out of the fact that pilots were quite<br />
happy to take full advantage out of the wage indexation<br />
system and the arbitration system for the last few years and<br />
are now prepared, or now want to get out of that system and </p>
<p>go for broke. I'd like to refer him to the fact that<br />
between November ' 85 and the middle of last year politicians<br />
received the same national wage increases as the rest of the<br />
workforce give or take a few percentage points and they're<br />
only very minor points. I have the figures right in front<br />
of me here. Early this year, in March in fact, the rest of<br />
the workforce were awarded $ 10 per week out of the national<br />
wage indexation system. The politicians in January of this<br />
year got 11.8% and with the further prospect of 10.9% in<br />
January 1990 and a further 90.8% in January 1991. Don't you<br />
think the Prime Minister is being a little bit hypocritical<br />
to say that we want the best when they themselves have<br />
benefitted from that wage indexation system for the last<br />
four years, but has taken the pilots to get a compounded<br />
increase of 36%?<br />
PM: Absolutely on the contrary my friend. What has in fact<br />
happened is that time after time the Government has knocked<br />
back the recommendations for increases for Members of<br />
Parliament. In fact to the point where the Rem uneration<br />
Tribunal has become significantly frustrated and said what's<br />
the point. What we in fact did in the light of<br />
recommendations for significantly greater increases than we<br />
were prepared to accept and operating under the system which<br />
was set up to determine the remuneration of Members of<br />
Parliament, we then, in an attempt to get a lesser outcome<br />
than had been recommended by the Independent Remuneration<br />
Tribunal, we took the matter to the Conciliation and<br />
Arbitration Commission so that the decision that would be<br />
made would be one which would be regarded and endorsed by<br />
the Conciliation and Arbitration Commission as it then was<br />
now the Industrial Relations Commission would be endorsed<br />
by them as being consistent with the wage fixing principles.<br />
So the history is one of knocking back increases by the<br />
legally established Independent Remuneration Tribunal,<br />
knocking them back because they were too high and could<br />
upset the general wage fixing system and then they've<br />
continued to recommend larger increases, then taking those<br />
to the Industrial Relations Commission to get them to give<br />
El, decisions which they would regard as being consistent with<br />
the wage fixing principles. That is the fact.<br />
CALLER: But Mr Prime minister, during those four years that<br />
you picked up the national wage increases like the rest of<br />
the workforce, do you think you were the only group in the<br />
community that had to knock back higher wage rises that you<br />
would've otherwise have been granted?<br />
PM: What I'm saying is that everything that the Members of<br />
Parliament did was in accordance both with the Independent<br />
Tribunal in fact not in accordance refuse to accept<br />
the degrees of increases that they nominated and would only<br />
take increases that were endorsed by the Commission. That's<br />
what I'm saying and that's not a question of opinion. John<br />
knows, you know that that's a fact.<br />
LAWS: Yes, that is fact. I mean you can't deny it, it's<br />
fact. </p>
<p>31<br />
CALLER: I'm not denying that you've taken what your own<br />
tribunal has recommended. But there seems to be a double<br />
standard once again that just because you have a tribunal<br />
that says that you deserve a pay rise but the rest of the<br />
workforce doesn't deserve it, it seems to be<br />
PM: It's not a double standard. We're saying in respect of<br />
the rest of the workforce that that's exactly what we want<br />
them to do and to the great and overwhelming credit of the<br />
workforce that's what they've done.<br />
CALLER: The double standard is that you accused pilots<br />
before of wanting the best of both systems. You said they<br />
were quite happy to take what they could get out of the wage<br />
indexation system for four years but now they want to opt<br />
out of that system when it suits. Don't you think you have<br />
the best of both worlds?<br />
I) PM: On the contrary my friend. I mean obviously you don't<br />
want to hear what I'm saying. John understands what I'm<br />
saying, I'm sure listeners do. We have in fact not opted<br />
out of the system. On the contrary. We have denied<br />
ourselves what the system has offered to us and said no, we<br />
are not going to do that, we will not have anything more<br />
than the Arbitration Commission will endorse.<br />
CALLER: Obviously we'll just have to agree to disagree on<br />
that one.<br />
PM: Sure.<br />
LAWS: Listen, we've got to call it a day because I've kept<br />
the Prime Minister waiting too long. Perhaps you'd like to<br />
talk to me about it later and I'll do my best to give you a<br />
hand if I can. Prime Minister, for me it's been a pleasure.<br />
I trust it's been a pleasure for you.<br />
PM: It has indeed John. It's always a pleasure. Thank you<br />
iI, very much indeed.<br />
LAWS: I'll look forward to seeing you very soon.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
