<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11250</transcript-id>
    <title>APEC BUSINESS ADVISORY COUNCIL</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce the appointment of Mr David Murray, Managing</p>
<p> Director of the Commonwealth Bank, as one of my three personal representatives</p>
<p> on the APEC Business Advisory Council (ABAC).</p>
<p>Mr Murray brings a wealth of business experience to his ABAC role.</p>
<p> He has done a great deal over many years to promote Australian business</p>
<p> and the expertise of Australia's banking and financial services</p>
<p> sectors overseas, especially in the APEC region. Last year, he also</p>
<p> made an important contribution, as a representative of the private</p>
<p> sector, to the work of my task force on international financial reform.</p>
<p>APEC leaders agreed at the Osaka meeting in November 1995 to the establishment</p>
<p> of ABAC as a way of ensuring that leaders benefit from the views of</p>
<p> those most directly involved in regional trade and investment. The</p>
<p> Council provides Australian business with a strong voice in APEC.</p>
<p> It has served APEC well over the four years of its existence.</p>
<p>This will be an important year for APEC and I very much look forward</p>
<p> to working closely with Mr Murray and my two other ABAC representatives,</p>
<p> Mr Michael Crouch and Mr Malcolm Kinnaird, to achieve practical results</p>
<p> for Australia and to remove impediments standing in the way of business.</p>
<p>Mr Murray will replace Mrs Imelda Roche, co-chairman of Nutri-Metics</p>
<p> International, who has been a member of ABAC since its inception.</p>
<p> I would like to take this opportunity to thank Imelda warmly for the</p>
<p> extremely valuable contribution she has made since 1995. She has been</p>
<p> an excellent representative both of Australia and of Australian business.</p>
<p> 16 April 1999</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
