<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11561</transcript-id>
    <title>Sir Don Bradman</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>12/10/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that the Governor-General has made amendments to the Corporations Law Regulations to protect Sir Donald Bradman's name from inappropriate commercial exploitation.</p>
<p>An association with Sir Donald is undoubtedly a valuable asset for any company. Most Australians would agree that it is appropriate that Sir Donald should be able to decide who should have the right to associate themselves or their products with him. Unfortunately, however, Sir Donald's name is vulnerable to exploitation by individuals and companies with no connection to him. Without expressing any opinion about the merits or otherwise of the current Federal Court proceedings involving Sir Donald, the Government is concerned that publicity about that litigation may have increased the possibility of companies attempting to trade on Sir Donald's name.</p>
<p>The Government has therefore decided to amend the Corporations Law Regulations to make a proposed company name unavailable for registration if the name suggests a connection with Sir Donald that does not exist. I am pleased to say that the Premiers of New South Wales and South Australia have indicated their support for the amendment.</p>
<p>The Regulations will be tabled in the Parliament later today and published in the Gazette tomorrow. They will commence on Gazettal and will therefore not affect any existing company with the word 'Bradman' in its name.<br />
I am pleased to announce that the Governor-General has made amendments to the Corporations Law Regulations to protect Sir Donald Bradman's name from inappropriate commercial exploitation.</p>
<p>An association with Sir Donald is undoubtedly a valuable asset for any company. Most Australians would agree that it is appropriate that Sir Donald should be able to decide who should have the right to associate themselves or their products with him. Unfortunately, however, Sir Donald's name is vulnerable to exploitation by individuals and companies with no connection to him. Without expressing any opinion about the merits or otherwise of the current Federal Court proceedings involving Sir Donald, the Government is concerned that publicity about that litigation may have increased the possibility of companies attempting to trade on Sir Donald's name.</p>
<p>The Government has therefore decided to amend the Corporations Law Regulations to make a proposed company name unavailable for registration if the name suggests a connection with Sir Donald that does not exist. I am pleased to say that the Premiers of New South Wales and South Australia have indicated their support for the amendment.</p>
<p>The Regulations will be tabled in the Parliament later today and published in the Gazette tomorrow. They will commence on Gazettal and will therefore not affect any existing company with the word 'Bradman' in its name.</p>
<p>12 October 2000</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
