<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1988</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO.8/1969 -  MIDDLE EAST:MESSAGE TO UNITED NATIONS</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/02/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001988.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 8/ 19692' I. 1 3<br />
MIDDLE EAST: MESSAGE TO UNITED NATIONS<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton, said today<br />
ftat on behalf of the Australian Government he had sent the following<br />
message to the President of the Security Council and to the Secretary-<br />
General of the United Nations:-" I wish to express the deep concern of<br />
the Government of the Commonwealth of Australia at<br />
the recent trials and mass public executions in Baghdad<br />
which were contrary to the proper dictates of humanity.<br />
The timing and manner of the hangings have been<br />
condemned by peoples throughout the world including<br />
some in other Arab countries.<br />
" It is the sincere hope of my Government<br />
that there will be no repetition of this spectacle which<br />
was so repugnant to the conscience of mankind and which<br />
can only exacerbate the situation in the Middle East and<br />
increase the difficulties of securing the objective for<br />
which we all are striving of a just and lasting peace. You<br />
may be assured of our support for your efforts to avert a<br />
repetition. A message from the Prime Minister was read by the<br />
Speaker, Mr. Aston, at a rally arranged by the Executive Council<br />
of Australian Jewry in the Sydney Town Hall this evening. The text<br />
of the message is as follows:-" The Australian Government is most<br />
concerned at the continued explosive situation in the<br />
Middle East, and abhors the recent mass public<br />
executions which, besides running counter to the world's<br />
conscience, can only exacerbate this situation.<br />
" We believe that all parties to the dispute<br />
should, without delay, sit down around the conference<br />
table and begin discussions aimed at restoring peace and<br />
stability to the Middle East.<br />
" Any such settlement must be formally<br />
based on the acceptance of Israel as a sovereign nation<br />
existing as of right, entitled to live and develop in<br />
security, free of constant threat, posing no threat to its<br />
neighbouring countries, and using for the good of all,<br />
rights and opportunities so dearly bought.<br />
CANBERRA 3 February 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
