<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>23944</transcript-id>
    <title>Appointment of Chair of the National Australia Day Council - Benjamin Roberts-Smith VC MG</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/2014</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Benjamin Roberts-Smith VC MG will be the new Chair of the National Australia Day Council.</p>
<p>He is Australia’s most highly decorated soldier, awarded Australia’s highest military honour for bravery in wartime, the Victoria Cross, and the Medal for Gallantry, for his service during the war in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Since his retirement from the Army, Ben has continued to serve his community, including as Deputy Chair of the Prime Minister’s Advisory Council on Veterans’ Mental Health.</p>
<p>This is a fitting way for Ben to continue his exemplary service to the nation. As Chair of the National Australia Council, he will help to inspire national pride and lead the community’s celebrations of Australia Day.</p>
<p>He follows another outstanding Australian, cricket legend Mr Adam Gilchrist AM. I thank Adam for his service over the last six years. Adam successfully led the National Australia Day Council, encouraging all Australians to reflect on the meaning of Australia Day and being Australian.</p>
<p>In addition to the appointment of Mr Roberts-Smith, the Government also announces Ms Robbie Sefton as the Deputy Chair of the Council.</p>
<p>Ms Sefton combines a background in farming with strong experience in media, government and the private sector.</p>
<p>Mr Norman Schueler has been appointed as one of the Council’s directors.</p>
<p>Mr Schueler is a successful businessman and has recently served on the Board of the Australia Day Council in South Australia.</p>
<p>9 November 2014</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
