<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4027</transcript-id>
    <title>ECONOMIC RELATIONS WITH JAPAN AND THE VISIT OF THE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/01/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004027.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
F 7 7<br />
14 January 1976<br />
FOR PRESS ECONOMIC RELATIONS WITH JAPAN AND THE VISIT OF THE<br />
DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER<br />
The Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for National Resources<br />
and Overseas Trade, Mr Anthony, will visit Japan from February<br />
: 4 to Febrdary 14.<br />
He will be accompanied by the Secretary of the Department of<br />
Overseas ' Trade, Mr D. H. McKay, and the Secretary of<br />
the Department of National Resources, Mr J. Scully.<br />
Because of -the particular importance to Australia-of the export<br />
of . pimar industry products such as beef, a seni6r officer of<br />
" the Deparent of Primary Industry will also accompany the<br />
Deputy Prime Minister.<br />
While in Japan Mr Anthony will hold talks with Japanese Ministers,<br />
officials and business interests on matters relating to Australia's<br />
minerals and energy resources and overseas trade.<br />
In making this announcement I would ike to rf. fir-thac for<br />
Australia, Japan is one of the most important countries in the world.<br />
The consolidation and strengthening of a relationship between our<br />
two countries in the political as well as in the economic field<br />
is a task to which I attach high priority.<br />
Australia's interests in relations with Japan rest on two<br />
considerations. The first is Japan's position as Australia's main<br />
trading partner. It is our biggest export market and it provides<br />
more of our imports than any other country except the United States. </p>
<p>2.<br />
Australia ranks high as a trading partner for Japan. Japanese<br />
imports from Australia consist largely of mineral resources<br />
and agricultural products, while Japan supplies us with a<br />
wide variety of. manufactured godds.<br />
In addition to the bilateral factor' Japan is a key country<br />
in world affairs, especially in the Asian/ Pacific region, and<br />
both it and the international community as a whole and countries<br />
of the region attach considerable weight to their relations with<br />
Japan.<br />
Australia': s exports to Japan of minerals, liquid gas, coal<br />
' i<br />
and, eventually, uranium are of critical importance to both<br />
countries. i Australia has no other markets of such size and with<br />
such potential for growth. Japan has no other supplier with<br />
such a wealth of resources and the potential for security of<br />
supply. All the factors are present for the development of an<br />
economic relationship based on mutual dependence which should<br />
confer enormous benefits on both countries.<br />
Our twish i indeed a prime--objective paonu r groewc onoWme ica cponlwiceiegs<br />
is st' 6 seeifuch benefits materialise and grow. We acknowledge<br />
that in recent years there has been an erosion of Japanese<br />
confidence in. Australia as a long-term source, of supply, even<br />
though ' contracts have always b5een honoured by Australia. We will<br />
work to see that confidence restored. We have no doubt that<br />
it can be, and in full harmony with the stated minerals and<br />
energy policies of the government.<br />
a s exports o c L-ural m17oT ai too ar-or<br />
critical importance to both countries. There is every reason to<br />
expect that in the long-term Australian exports of wool, grains,<br />
dairy products, sugar, meat and fruits will grow. However,<br />
this trade policy has faced some problems and the confidence of<br />
Australian exporters has been affected by Japanese import policies.<br />
Japanese import policies have brought particular problems for<br />
exporters of beef and dairy products. We will also work to see<br />
confidence restored in these areas. / 3 </p>
<p>3.<br />
Australian imports from Japan are being affected by the<br />
temporary restraints Australia has placed on certain of its<br />
imports.-The Japanese Government.-has formally expressed its<br />
concern." These measures are consistent with Australia's<br />
international obligations and will be relaxed and removed as<br />
soon as conditions permit.<br />
On balance, therefore, I am confident that, although there are<br />
difficulties in the international climate, relations between<br />
Australia, and Japan can be further strengthened to the<br />
. advantage, of both our countries and -the region and the<br />
* international community. 0000UOoooooo000000<br />
I S </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
