<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2141</transcript-id>
    <title>LINKING OF EAST - WEST STANDARD GAUGE RAILWAY BROKEN HILL N.S.W  29 NOVEMBER 1969</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/11/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002141.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
LINKING OF EAST-WEST STANDARD GAUGE RAILWAY<br />
Broken Hill, N. S. W. 29 NOVEMBER 1969<br />
Spech by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
Mr. McCusker, Mr. Mayor, the Hon. the Premiers of New South Wales<br />
and South Australia and Parliamentary Colleagues both Federal and State<br />
and Ladies and Gentlemen:<br />
Mr. Askin, Mr. Hall and I have each -just driven a dog<br />
spike, suitably embellished with gold or silver plate, into the track at the<br />
back of us. It is not for me to say how skilfully we did the job:' I think<br />
we were assisted by the fact that the hole was probably bored out beforehand<br />
for us to put the spikes into: But at least they went in, and that means<br />
that officially the East-West Standard Gauge Railway is just about complete.<br />
On the 12 January, the first through train will journey across<br />
this country unimpeded by break of gauge, and travelling in 65 hours some<br />
2, 500 miles across a bridge of steel which spans this continent and which<br />
serves and will serve not orly as a bridge but as a tie that binds.<br />
Each of the Premiers and myself have, I think, some<br />
special right to be present and to meet you and to take part in this ceremony.<br />
Mr. Askin has a right because Broken Hill is a part of New South Wales<br />
and, theoretically at any rate, subject to the laws of New South Wales.<br />
Mr. Hall, because Broken Hill can really be regarded almost as a suburb<br />
of Adelaide, being only some nine hours away. And myself, I think, because<br />
the Coalition Government some time ago took the first steps in the work<br />
which came to fruition today and is providing something like half the<br />
financial cost of it.<br />
For the first time in more than a hundred years, this bridge,<br />
this tie will be operating, and it will add a new dimension to the East-West<br />
traffic; it will open a new chapter in our history. It is not possible today<br />
to name all those who have played their part in the effort which came to<br />
fruition today, but inevitably the names of the late Sir Harold Clapp, the<br />
late Mr. Eddie Ward, the Minister for Transport in a previous Government,<br />
and I think above all, my own Ministerial colleague, Mr. Wentworth,<br />
come to mind. It was Mr. Ward who first started negotiating with the<br />
States in these matters, and it was Mr. Wentworth who chaired the<br />
Government's Parliamentary Committee on Standardisation I am not<br />
sure that that Committee was ever appointed with the approval of the<br />
then Government but it went ahead anyway under Mr. Wentworth' s<br />
guidance. And it was the work of that Committee and the response by the<br />
Commonwealth and State-Railways Commissioners who joined so<br />
wholeheartedly in this co-operative effort which led to getting the same<br />
gauges on the main Australian trunk routes. It is very fitting indeed, I<br />
think, that Mr. Wentworth should be with us at this ceremony. / 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
What I have been speaking of is something that has been<br />
done, and since it has been done it is virtually a part of the past, so we<br />
should turn our eyes to the future. And in this field of transport in the<br />
future, there are three more projects coming up, coming rapidly up.<br />
The first is the construction of a new railway from Port<br />
Augusta to Whyalla which will give Whyalla its first rail link with the rest<br />
of Australia. The second is the construction of a standard gauge connection<br />
to Adelaide from this East-West line which will take three years and cost<br />
some $ 50 million. The third is a study of proposals for a new standard<br />
gauge line to Alice Springs to eliminate the break of gauge at Marree and<br />
to avoid the disruptions to traffic which natural disasters from time to<br />
time have caused. These are continuing steps in the development of our nation,<br />
and I would stress two things about them. One is that transport costs in<br />
Australia have been, and are, a major factor in the whole of our business<br />
and commercial activity and in the prices at which goods are finally sold.<br />
These costs represent a greater part of national expenditure than do the<br />
transport costs of most industrial and developed countries, and this must<br />
present a continuing challenge to all Governments State and Federal<br />
to all citizens, to all those engaged in the work of seeking to overcome<br />
this transport cost imposed upon us. If we can overcome it together, we<br />
will have taken one of the great steps forward towards reducing the costs,<br />
the final cost of things which people buy.<br />
And the second thing I want to stress is that in the field of<br />
transport, whether it be by air or by sea, or by land by rail<br />
developments such as we are seeing today will continue and help to make<br />
us think as one nation. It is one thing to say that a people is indivisible,<br />
that the nation is indivisible, but it is another to know in practical terms<br />
that this in fact is so in the minds of all its citizens. And I think this work<br />
will help to knit us together.<br />
I congratulate all those who have taken part in the planning<br />
and construction of this standard gauge right down to the fourth-last dog<br />
spike that has been hammered into the track. The job has been well<br />
planned, well done and will, for all the future of Australia, be a great<br />
contribution to the nation.<br />
I wish all those who use this trans-continental railway<br />
safe, fast and comfortable travel, and I think that you all realise, you<br />
here today, that you are in fact, as you are, taking part in a really<br />
historic ceremony. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
