<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41336</transcript-id>
    <title>Radio interview with Bianca, Terry and Bob - 97.3FM Brisbane</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects>Same sex marriage</subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p><strong>HOST:</strong></p>
<p>Welcome Malcolm Turnbull, our Prime Minister. Good morning!</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Good morning, how are you?</p>
<p><strong>HOST:</strong></p>
<p>All I’m going to say is, you’re welcome. Because we did help you get just a wee bit of international and national exposure last time you came on and you were brave enough to bear ‘60 Seconds With Bianca’. We thought this went quite well?</p>
<p><strong>HOST - RECORDING: </strong></p>
<p>Do you ever Netflix and Chill with Lucy?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER - RECORDING:</strong></p>
<p>Yes, yes we do.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yes, you asked me that and I wasn’t aware that it was code for something else. But as I said to you, we certainly do watch a lot of Netflix and we do chill out when we do so. Well, not a lot of Netflix.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>HOST:</strong></p>
<p>Yeah and chilling.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>But I mean the reality is that as you know, those over-the-top streaming services have really changed the way people watch television because you can watch things as and when you want to.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Absolutely. But were you expecting, were you ready for the incredible media coverage that came off the back of that? Were your advisers sitting down with you with Urban Dictionary and going: “Okay Prime Minister, we don’t want this to happen again, so we’re going to teach you everything there is to know?”</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Why should I be troubled about it? I mean we’ve been married for nearly 40 years. It’s not exactly, I’m not exactly a teenager making an admission about some naughtiness.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Absolutely.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>I’ve only been married 25 years and I would take it as a matter of considerable pride. I’d boast about it.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Exactly, that’s right.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Listen, speaking of marriages and engagements and all that kind of stuff, Tony Abbott’s daughter Frances has taken to social media to say that she’s engaged now, after only two weeks of courting and dating. How long did you and Lucy court? Or how long were you guys engaged?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Well it took me about two years to persuade her to marry me. But can I just say congratulations Frances and you know, lots of love and good luck to the young couple. That’s always good, to see people fall in love. There’s a lot of love around in the air. But getting back to me and Luce, yeah, I think we had probably a two year courtship. But when I first asked Luce to marry me she said: “Lets wait until we grow up.”</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p>I guess she waited until she grew up at least.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull, we thought we’d do another fun ‘60 Seconds With Bianca’. Are you game, are you ready?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah, I’m up for it.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>I love it! Here we go, as soon as, we’re just getting our clock. Have you ever seen a psychic?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>No but I’ve seen plenty of sidekicks.</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>What’s the last movie you saw?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Oh that’s a good question. At the movies? It would have been the last Hobbit movie.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Okay geez, that was a while ago.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah, the precious.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>What’s your favourite ‘cheat meal’ when you’re being naughty?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I would say a bowl of noodles.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Okay. Two minutes? Oh, I wanted to know your favourite ‘activewear’. What do you wear when you’re walking around, when you do your walks along the river?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I wear sort of shorts, football shorts, running shoes and a t-shirt. Just what I was wearing today when I was crossing the Goodwill Bridge.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Nice, but no Lorna Jane then?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>And I see you sent me a nice message on Instagram!</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>I did! Did you see my message I sent you on Instagram?</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yeah I replied to it too!</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Malcolm Turnbull replied to me! I love it! What’s your favourite rainy day activity? Besides Netflix and Chilling of course?</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>I would say it is, you know, Netflix with Lucy, just watching a movie or TV with Luce.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>You go girl.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>We love it.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>The Hobbit is a very long movie, there’s three parts of it. Congratulations Prime Minister.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER: </strong></p>
<p>Yep.</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister thank you so much for joining us. Look, I feel bad guys, we’ve kind of hijacked this interview. Was there anything you wanted to say Malcolm?</p>
<p>[Laughter]</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Just make sure to vote for Tim Nicholls and Deb Frecklington, the LNP is the way to go.</p>
<p><strong>HOST:</strong></p>
<p>Thought you might have mentioned them.</p>
<p><strong>HOST:</strong></p>
<p>Thought we’d let you squeeze that one in, thanks for that, thanks for joining us.</p>
<p><strong>PRIME MINISTER:</strong></p>
<p>Thank you!</p>
<p><strong>HOST: </strong></p>
<p>Bye Prime Minister.</p>
<p><strong>[ENDS]</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
