<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41041</transcript-id>
    <title>Prime Minister to visit Germany, France and UK</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/07/2017</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull will depart Australia tomorrow to attend the G20 Leaders’ Summit in Hamburg, Germany, on 7-8 July. This will be followed by official visits to France and the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>The G20 is the premier forum for global economic cooperation. The Summit is a unique opportunity for Australia to engage with the largest and most advanced economies in the world.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister will discuss with global counterparts the importance of combatting terrorism, the benefits of trade and open markets, energy and sustainable development, women’s participation, digitalisation and ensuring the benefits of a strong economy can be shared by all.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister will also meet with German Chancellor Angela Merkel to discuss our strong bilateral relationship and how Australia and Germany can cooperate in addressing shared challenges.</p>
<p>Following the G20, the Prime Minister will travel to France to meet with President Emmanuel Macron and strengthen our economic and security cooperation. He will also formally open the new Australian Future Submarine Office in Cherbourg.  </p>
<p>Prior to his return to Australia, the Prime Minister will also visit the United Kingdom where he will have an audience with Her Majesty the Queen, and meet Prime Minister Theresa May and senior members of her government. The Prime Minister will reinforce our extremely close relationship with the UK, including strengthening our counter-terrorism cooperation.</p>
<p>While in the UK, the Prime Minister will also pay his respects to the victims of last month’s June London Bridge terrorist attack, and will meet British first responders to convey Australia’s gratitude for their bravery and assistance.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
