<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7643</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARIS AIR SHOW, 17 JUNE 1989</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>17/06/1989</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007643.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Is-<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF NEWS CONFERENCE, PARIS AIR SHOW, 17 JUNE 1989<br />
K 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister do you believe you'll get the<br />
French Government's support for your position on the<br />
Antarctic? PH: It's too early to say but there's some indications that<br />
they are sympathetic to our position. I'l~ l be talking with<br />
the Prime Minister on Monday and I think some of the<br />
officials might be talking before then. But there's<br />
certainly some indications that they are sympathetic.<br />
They've had some progress of course since we've made the<br />
decision. The Indian Government has indicated they are going<br />
to support us and that's I think very important so it's not<br />
as hopeless as I think some people thought it might be at the<br />
beginning. JOURNALIST: So you hope to get some support for a World<br />
Environment Park down in the Antarctic on this trip?<br />
PM: Yes I certainly believe that we've got a good chance of<br />
support here in France. Obviously the position of the United<br />
Kingdom and the United States is more hostile to the concept<br />
but I want to take the opportunity of explaining our position<br />
to them. I'll be meeting with Jacques Cousteau in the<br />
morning and I think it will be useful to be able to listen to<br />
what he has to say and I think he'll provide a fair bit of<br />
support obviously, for our concept. He's certainly<br />
recommending to the French Government that they should<br />
support our position.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you any indication that the French would be<br />
swayed by what he might have to say?<br />
PM: He's obviously an influential figure here and I can't<br />
draw any conclusions until I've seen them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Two Australian's bashed in Bougainville. Have<br />
you been briefed on that? </p>
<p>PM: Yes I've read the cables on that and I've asked our<br />
people to ensure that the appropriate protests are made and I<br />
believe they have been. This Is an unacceptable sort of<br />
situation. This is not an attack upon Australians by the<br />
rebels but by the armed forces there that are supposed to be<br />
responsible for maintaining law and order. So we will<br />
register the very strong protest to the authorities about<br />
this. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke do you think that the UK and the US are<br />
exerting a certain amount of influence on France to get It to<br />
sign the Treaty?<br />
PM: I've got no evidence of that although it would be<br />
surprising if, given what I understand to be the strength of<br />
their position, that hadn't been conveyed to other countries<br />
including France. But I don't think on Its record France is<br />
likely to be pushed Into a position by either the United<br />
States or the United Kingdom. I would think in terms of the<br />
pitch, my pitch would be as good as the Americans and the<br />
British.<br />
O JOURNALIST: What is your pitch going to be? What arguments<br />
are you going to use?<br />
PM: Well basically straight forward. This is the last<br />
pristine continent. It is obviously extremely fragile and I<br />
think that what the nations who have spent some years now in<br />
trying to prepare the Mining Convention have got to<br />
understand Is that we're living in a different period now at<br />
the e~ nd nf thp iqAnw than wo TanIo cowal yaW ag4 IJ... Libw<br />
work started on the Convention. We have more evidence now of<br />
the fragility of this type of environment. We have the Exon<br />
disaster in the Arctic region up there in Alaska and so it's<br />
quite clear that you can't really protect this sort of<br />
environment absolutely, you can't have absolute confidence of<br />
being able to protect It. I think further now there is a<br />
greater consciousness right around the world about the<br />
responsibility we have to protecting the environment for the<br />
future. So my view would be that the nations would be<br />
responsive to the proposition that we should have an Arctic<br />
wilderness constructed within the Antarctic Treaty system.<br />
This will enable appropriate scientific work to proceed but<br />
In an environment where there should be no mining because<br />
it's no good really saying, as has been said before, ' well<br />
you can have a-Minerals Convention with a veto in it upon<br />
mining'. I mean it seems to me to be a, when you come to<br />
think of it, the wrong way around it and we certainly won't<br />
be prepared to accept the situation which said, ' well yes you<br />
will sign the Convention and you can have a reservation which<br />
Savs however, we would veto any mininq'. It's much more<br />
straight forward to say there is to be no mining. Let's<br />
( PM cont) construct a comprehensive environmental protection<br />
framework and within that try and advance the concept of the<br />
Wilderness Park. So I think It's going to be a much more<br />
receptive world environment for that than there would have<br />
been even two years ago. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Will you be raising the issue of the nuclear<br />
testing in the South Pacific during this visit to France, Mr<br />
Hawke and is there some irony in the French perhaps<br />
supporting our position on environmentalism In the Antarctic<br />
and still testing in the South Pacific?<br />
PM: We'll make clear again our opposition to testing. It's<br />
well known, It doesn't need a great deal of repitition. But<br />
the point will be made. I suppose some people could say<br />
there Is a paradox that there is their conduct of nuclear<br />
testing in the South Pacific but that they are obviously<br />
extremely conscious of environmental Issues in other ways.<br />
But be that as It may I think what we'd do Is to make our<br />
position clear as to opposition to the nuclear testing in the<br />
South Pacific but welcome the support of France in other<br />
areas where they are, in my judgement, taking a positive and<br />
realistic environmental position.<br />
JOURN~ ALIST: In Australia there's been some renewed<br />
speculation on the possibility of a half-Senate election<br />
separate from a House of Representatives election. Are you<br />
in any way attracted to that proposition?<br />
PM: Well I know I've seen the speculation. I've got nothing<br />
more to say on that at all, nothing more.<br />
JOURNALIST: Are you ruling It out?<br />
PM: I just haven't got anything to say about It. I mean<br />
JOURNALIST: It rules it in, doesn't it?<br />
PM: Well I suppose you can say it rules It in, rules it out.<br />
I mean you people will write your story whatever I say about<br />
it. I mean I haven't said anything about an early election<br />
for six months but that hasn't stopped you writing about<br />
early elections. I've not said anything about early<br />
elections, not anything about it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Can you see any circumstances under which half<br />
the Senate will go to an election seperate from the House of<br />
Representatives? PM: I've got nothing to say about the question of elections<br />
because as soon as I say something about It you start<br />
furiously scribbling. So I've really got nothing to say<br />
about it. We'll Just go on governing and let others<br />
speculate on this matter.<br />
JOUt1IST: When you said there'd be no election this year<br />
are you talking about just the House of Representatives or<br />
were you Including<br />
PM: That was the question I was asked. I always answer the<br />
question I'm asked. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
JOURNALIST: Would there be any advantages In having a<br />
half-Senate election this year?<br />
PM: For whom?<br />
JOURNALIST: The Government.<br />
PM: I don't know really. I'm not thinking about elections<br />
over here. I mean why would you be thinking about elections<br />
here in this beautiful environmnent.<br />
JOURNALIST: Does your earlier statement ruling out an<br />
election apply to the half-Senate election?<br />
PM: I said before what I had to say about it Michelle. I<br />
really haven't got anything more to say about elections now,<br />
nothing more to say about elections, nothing more to say<br />
about elections.<br />
JOURNALIST: Just a question on France. How would you<br />
describe the state of Australia's relations with France at<br />
the moment and will they change because of this trip?<br />
PM: I think one should say they are improving-and they'll be<br />
better as a result of this trip. I mean with this Government<br />
as compared with its predecessor we are In a very, very much<br />
warmer and more constructive, cooperative position. I mean<br />
you take the area of the South Pacific In general and New<br />
Caledonia in particular. The Rocard Government has<br />
transformed the situation there. We welcome the Matignon<br />
Accord and it's very refreshing to see the results of the<br />
election the other day. There was a very significant<br />
participation rate despite the frank attempt to boycott.<br />
The participation rate was as high as It had been before<br />
about 69% and they are tackling what is the fundamental<br />
question there of providing accelerated training for the<br />
Kanak population so that by the time 1998 comes there will be<br />
a solid core of trained people professionally, academically,<br />
bureaucratically, technically, to be able to fill the<br />
positions and to be able to cover whatever position is<br />
decided upon at that t-ime. So we welcome those moves. We<br />
want to cooperate with them, assist them in the area of<br />
economic cooperation. There are moves for greater<br />
cooperation generally. The French Government was remarkably<br />
generous in its contribution to the bicentennial, very, very<br />
generous. ' We are ourselves being Involved In now their<br />
bicentennial celebrations, the Revolution. So I would say<br />
that the relations now are very, very much better than<br />
they've been for a long time and I'm sure that as a result of<br />
this visit they'll be further improved as they will be<br />
( PM cont) further improved after the visit by Michel Rocard<br />
to Australia In August.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawks do you expect Mr Bush to be more<br />
sympathetic to the plight of Australian farmers than Mr<br />
Quayle was on his visit? </p>
<p>-53-<br />
PM: Well I just don't know. We've got a position I think<br />
where we'll make-it clear that we believe that there has been<br />
damage to Australia. There may be argument that they want to<br />
push about the extent of this. But as I said Just before I<br />
got on the aircraft to come overseas, I'm not going to allow<br />
that issue to dominate the discussions we will have In the<br />
United States. We've got so many areas of profound<br />
agreement. Some of the issues that we need to talk about<br />
that I'm not going to allow this important visit to be<br />
derailed by an over emphasis on that issue. I think the<br />
important thing there Is that we should work together in the<br />
environment of the MTN negotiations of the Uruguay Round to<br />
press for the elimination of subsidies in this area of<br />
subsidy on production and exports so that we can get a freed<br />
up international trading system in agriculture. That's the<br />
important thing.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
