<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11368</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                 THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 ADDRESS AT THE ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE FURTHER FUNDING FOR NURSES MEMORIAL                                 ANZAC MEMORIAL, HYDE PARK                                                 </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/04/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: Funding for Nurses'Memorial</p>
<p>E&amp;OE....................................................................................................</p>
<p>Well thank you very much Rusty to Elisabeth Perciville to the other</p>
<p> very special and distinguished and honoured guests, ladies and gentlemen.</p>
<p>It is appropriate as we approach ANZAC Day 1999 to take a few opportunities</p>
<p> to honour those people who have made such a remarkable contribution</p>
<p> to producing Australia of 1999 which is without fear as a free and</p>
<p> open and democratic society. I had the special opportunity in Western</p>
<p> Australia only yesterday to present to eight survivors of World War</p>
<p> I the first of the eightieth anniversary commemorative medals of which</p>
<p> the government has decided to strike to honour those veterans of World</p>
<p> War I who survived to see armistice day 1998 the eightieth anniversary</p>
<p> of the end of World War I.</p>
<p>Here on the other side of Australia in Sydney, today, I have the opportunity</p>
<p> on behalf of the Australian Government and on behalf of the Australian</p>
<p> people to pay special tribute to a special and remarkable band of</p>
<p> Australian women who endured in so many theatres of war the privation,</p>
<p> the suffering, the death and all of the heartache and all of the toil</p>
<p> involved in caring for the wounded and the dying amongst Australian</p>
<p> service personnel in all theatres of war.</p>
<p>Starting with their contribution for the first time in the South African</p>
<p> War through the first World War through World War II and through the</p>
<p> subsequent conflicts in which Australia has been involved, nurses</p>
<p> have been at the forefront of the effort in defending our country</p>
<p> and the greatest tributes that have been paid to them of course have</p>
<p> been paid to them by the service men themselves who were cared for,</p>
<p> whose lives were saved and whose lives were put together again by</p>
<p> their loving care and attention.</p>
<p>Part of the debt that we owe to the men and women who defended this</p>
<p> country is a special debt to those nurses of Australia who made such</p>
<p> a magnificent contribution in all of the wars in which Australians</p>
<p> have been involved. Earlier this week the marvelous ABC TV documentary</p>
<p> Sisters in Arms told the work of service nurses during conflicts</p>
<p> in which Australia has been involved. That particular program which</p>
<p> interviewed several of the people who are here today told some wonderful</p>
<p> stories of their heroism and it was a wonderful reminder to the current</p>
<p> generation of Australians just how much we owe to that remarkable</p>
<p> group of men and women who gave so much in the two world conflicts</p>
<p> and in Korea and in Vietnam.</p>
<p>Just as I encouraged the audience in Western Australia yesterday to</p>
<p> think that, as children in Australian schools are taught Simpson and</p>
<p> his donkey, to learn some of the stories surrounding that remarkable</p>
<p> group of men who comprised amongst the eight of them more than eight</p>
<p> hundred years of cumulative life experiences so can we never forget</p>
<p> the courage and compassion of survivors like Sister Vivienne Bullwinkle,</p>
<p> the only survivor of the Banker Island Massacre in World War II and</p>
<p> Sister Nell Savage, the only survivor of the sinking of the hospital</p>
<p> ship Centar in World War II as well as those who were taken</p>
<p> as prisoners of war.</p>
<p>The nurses of Australia have contributed important and never to be</p>
<p> forgotten chapters to the history of this country in war. Their contribution</p>
<p> was selfless their dedication was unlimited and the debt that we owe</p>
<p> to them was equal to the debt that we owe to those people we owe to</p>
<p> those on the fighting front. And their contribution and their spirit</p>
<p> illumines in a very special way the ANZAC spirit and the ANZAC tradition.</p>
<p>The Government, as you know, announced with the great help of the</p>
<p> various nursing associations, the dedication, hopefully later this</p>
<p> year, of a special nurse's memorial in Canberra. And I am announcing</p>
<p> today a further contribution, from the Federal Government, of $500,000</p>
<p> towards the cost of completing, erecting and dedicating the memorial.</p>
<p> We hope that that will occur in October of this year and I want to</p>
<p> particularly thank all of those people who have been involved in it.</p>
<p> I want to congratulate Elizabeth Percival who is here today, the Executive</p>
<p> Director of the Royal College of Nursing Australia, who agreed to</p>
<p> chair the memorial management committee, Ita Buttrose, who chaired</p>
<p> the fundraising committee, as well as all those involved in the memorial</p>
<p> project for their magnificent efforts in arriving where we are at</p>
<p> present. The contributions made by various sub branches and elements</p>
<p> of the RSL, by state governments and other veterans' groups have</p>
<p> been very welcome. The Commonwealth Government made an initial contribution</p>
<p> of $100,000 and the further contribution of $500,000 that I announced</p>
<p> today will, I hope, make and important further contribution towards</p>
<p> the successful billing of the appeal target and of the completion,</p>
<p> the dedication and the opening of the memorial.</p>
<p>Memorials are an important expression of how any nation or any group</p>
<p> of people feels about a section of its community. We have many memorials</p>
<p> in Canberra, far and away the most moving, the most memorable and</p>
<p> those that are most evocative of the history of our country are those</p>
<p> that are dedicated to the contribution of the men and women who defended</p>
<p> this country in war. And the nurses memorial, when it is opened, will</p>
<p> take its place alongside the War Memorial, alongside the special memorials</p>
<p> to our conflicts in Vietnam and elsewhere and the other special memorials</p>
<p> that mark the contribution of men and women in theatres of war. Can</p>
<p> I say to those representatives of the Nurses of Australia who are</p>
<p> here today, that your nation is forever in your debt, your nation</p>
<p> is grateful for what you did, your nation admires and respects and</p>
<p> will always remember the risks you took, the contribution you made,</p>
<p> the relief of suffering that you afforded. The memorial that will</p>
<p> be opened in October, will I hope will be a fitting and important</p>
<p> reminder to the entire nation and particularly to those that are young</p>
<p> who visit Canberra of just how important the role that you all played</p>
<p> at very perilous and very critical times in the history of Australia.</p>
<p> Thank you very much.</p>
<p>  ends</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
