<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2470</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHON IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES - INQUIRY INT0 PARLIAMENTARY SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES - 16 SEPTEMBER 1971</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/09/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002470.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMFNT B~ Y THE PRPIe MINISTER<br />
THE P. T. HON. T;' ILLIYAl c-MAHON<br />
IN THIE HOUSE OF REPR~ ESENTATIVES<br />
INQUIRY INTO PARLIAM" ENTARY SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES<br />
16 SEPTEMBER 1971<br />
I inform the House that the Government has decided that there should be<br />
an inquiry into Parliamentary salaries and allowances.<br />
Parliamentary salaries and allowances were last adjusted in December 1968.<br />
It will be generally accept'ed that there should be periodic reviews of<br />
Parliamentary salaries and allowrances just as there are in other sectors of<br />
the community. It has been represented to me from both sides of the House,<br />
including strong recommendations from the Leader of the Opposition and the<br />
Deputy Leader of the Opposition, at the request of their own Party, that<br />
there should he a review at this time.<br />
In the recent history of this matter, there have been three inquiries<br />
held in 1952, in 1955 and in 1959.. Since then, in 1964 and in 1968, the<br />
salary adjustments were made by decision of the Parliament itself.<br />
The Government has decided that in this instance it should revert to the<br />
inquiry method. We ' nropose that one of the terms of reference will be an<br />
examination and report upon methods by w., hich Parliamentary salaries<br />
and allowances may be determined in future.<br />
The Government has decided to ask Mr. Justice Kerr to undertake this task.<br />
He has accepted.<br />
Mr. Justice Kerr was appointed a Judge of the Commonwealth Industrial<br />
Court in 1966. As a Senior Counsel at the Bar, he had previously had an<br />
extensive uractice in industrial matters. Mr. Justice Kerr is at present<br />
Chairman of a five-man committee that the Government has appointed to inquire<br />
into Pay and other conditions of service of members of the Armed Forces. He<br />
has informed me that the Committee has a Planned programme for carrying out<br />
the remainder of its inquiry and for the submission of its further report.<br />
I have the Jud~ ge's firm assurance that the examination of Parliamentary<br />
salaries he has now been asked to undertake will in no way delay the<br />
completion of the work of the Armed Forces Pay Committee. That work will<br />
proceed and will be carried to finality as originally planned.<br />
The terms of reference of the inquiry will be-<br />
To examine and report upon the salaries and allowances of<br />
Senators and Members of the House of Representatives, and<br />
those paid to Ministers and Senators and Mlembers who are<br />
office-bearers of the Parliament;<br />
If it be reported that it is necessary or desirable to alter<br />
such salaries and allowances or any of them, then to recommend<br />
the nature and extent of the alterations that should be made; and<br />
To examine and report upon methods by which such salaries and<br />
allowances may be determined in future. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
