<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11470</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER            THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP            TELEVISION INTERVIEW WITH PAUL LYNEHAM, NIGHTLINE &amp;#150; CHANNEL 9                     </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>14/02/2000</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Subjects: mandatory sentencing; illegal immigrants; tax reform; Olympic</p>
<p> accommodation; coolroom at Kirribilli; National Textiles.</p>
<p>E&amp;OE.............................................................................................</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Prime Minister welcome again to Nightline.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good to be with you Paul.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>In your opinion are the Northern Territory's mandatory sentencing</p>
<p> laws unjust and do they tarnish our image abroad?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I don't think sufficiently serious for the Commonwealth to intervene</p>
<p> in relation to mandatory sentencing laws as such. I guess I'm a little</p>
<p> bit troubled about ones that relate to people under the age of 18. This</p>
<p> is a difficult issue. If you live in a high crime rate area you'll</p>
<p> support mandatory sentencing. Or as on the other hand I think everybody's</p>
<p> just distressed at the suicide of a boy of 15. The Attorney General is</p>
<p> writing to the Territory and the State of Western Australia regarding</p>
<p> that.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And what if the Territory and the State tell you to mind your own business?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well Paul, one thing at a time. I mean we don't normally want to</p>
<p> be interfering in these things unless there are compelling circumstances.</p>
<p> Sentencing is a matter that is the prerogative of the States.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>The Parliament [inaudible] euthanasia didn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, that was a very special case.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>What do you think of the idea of work gangs of illegal immigrants picking</p>
<p> fruit?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well we're going to have a look at it because it is a problem. And</p>
<p> Philip Ruddock is right to say let's have a look at it. There's</p>
<p> a shortage of people. There's a complaint about the cost of keeping</p>
<p> people in detention. What Philip Ruddock is saying is let's have</p>
<p> a look at it.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But isn't it harking back to the old chain gang image?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No no, not if you pay people proper rates.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Yeah but your Minister says most of the money they get will be taken</p>
<p> up paying for their detention costs so they'll end up like slaves</p>
<p> won't they.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>But Paul, look, you're damned if you do and if you're damned</p>
<p> if you don't on this one. People don't like illegal immigrants</p>
<p> landing here without an invitation. On the other hand we are expected</p>
<p> quite properly when people are here to afford reasonable living conditions</p>
<p> for them and to treat them in a humane way. And we're trying to strike</p>
<p> a balance.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Did you see the newspaper reports at the weekend saying that your Government</p>
<p> has booked through SOCOG 14 hotel rooms for Ministers and staff for 20</p>
<p> days at a cost of more than $100,000?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes I did.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Is that right?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I don't know whether it's precisely correct. I saw the</p>
<p> reports and I've learnt that sometimes they can be inaccurate. But</p>
<p> our Ministers are expected to be in Sydney at the time of the Olympic</p>
<p> Games to entertain all of the visitors that are coming, to talk to visiting</p>
<p> businessman as part of their job. I can tell you Paul, if they weren't</p>
<p> there and you had a story from some visiting businessman saying I wanted</p>
<p> to invest billions in Australia but I couldn't find any Minister</p>
<p> to talk to. Now let's get a sense of perspective about this please.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And there was also a report at the weekend that you're installing</p>
<p> a coolroom at Kirribilli House to chill food and drinks for when you're</p>
<p> entertaining. Sounds better and better doesn't it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well put that way of course. But this is just a suggestion to better</p>
<p> preserve the food and drink which is the normal part of running the place,</p>
<p> Paul.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And you don't think there's any irony when one harks back to</p>
<p> the things that some of your colleagues were saying when Labor was in</p>
<p> government?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well all Oppositions can be guilty of feckless point scoring on these</p>
<p> sorts of things, and we probably were. But you've got to look at</p>
<p> each thing on its merits and on the merits I'm very happy to have</p>
<p> my expenditure compared with that of any of my predecessors.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>The National Textiles matter Prime Minister, why did you, one of the</p>
<p> most experienced politicians in the country, become so closely involved</p>
<p> with the fate of this company despite the obvious danger signals of your</p>
<p> brother being the chairman.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well I didn't get involved with the fate of the company at all.</p>
<p> What I got involved in was helping 340 workers who'd been thrown</p>
<p> out of a job without their entitlements in a depressed area of Australia.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>But before that you had a meeting with Philip Bart, the major shareholder,</p>
<p> and with Joe Brender of Bruck Industries. Surely you....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>You know what I told them? I told them that their application for help</p>
<p> would be determined by Senator Minchin. I kept right away from it, and</p>
<p> Senator Minchin knocked them back. And I mean he had this ridiculous situation</p>
<p> where we knocked back the company but we helped the workers, and I'm</p>
<p> getting criticised. The Labor Party was calling on me to help the workers,</p>
<p> they were also calling on me to help the company. But we knocked the company</p>
<p> back but we helped the workers. None of the help we gave has gone to my</p>
<p> brother, not a cent. And for good measure he's being investigated</p>
<p> by the Securities Commission, not that there's any suggestion he's</p>
<p> done anything wrong. I don't believe he has but that's a matter</p>
<p> for the law to determine. I mean how on Earth can that be a conflict of</p>
<p> interest, how on Earth can that be wrong.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>In your own words you say it's a scare a day on the GST between</p>
<p> now and July. You're also behind in the polls, you spent much of</p>
<p> last week on the political back foot and Parliament returns tomorrow.</p>
<p> A bit of test of nerves ahead?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yes, but it's part of the game. I mean it's just an inevitable</p>
<p> part of the job. There won't be an election until the end of next</p>
<p> year. But Paul, I don't know what's going to happen at the next</p>
<p> election. I don't take anything for granted. We have a strong economy,</p>
<p> and we've got the guts to carry out reforms. Tax reform will be good</p>
<p> for Australia. Average families will be $40, $50 a week better off as</p>
<p> a result of tax reform.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And they'll stay focused on that despite the scare a day?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>They will certainly be focused on the benefits when they arrive. I'm</p>
<p> committed to tax reform because it's good for the country. If I go</p>
<p> through a period of unpopularity in the process so be it. You don't</p>
<p> get elected to this office to be popular every hour of every day all the</p>
<p> years you're in office. You have good times and bad times, favourable</p>
<p> times and unfavourable times.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>And how would you describe these times right now?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Interesting, challenging, good for the soul.</p>
<p>LYNEHAM:</p>
<p>Thanks for your time.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
