<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>22762</transcript-id>
    <title>Transcript of broadcast on the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and PNG</title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130627 - 20130907</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/07/2013</release-date>
    <release-type>Video Transcript</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E &amp; O E – PROOF ONLY</p>
<p>My fellow Australians.</p>
<p>Tonight I want to speak to you about a matter of great importance to all of us.</p>
<p>Earlier today I met the Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea and struck a new regional arrangement on asylum seekers.</p>
<p>From this point forward, asylum seekers who arrive in Australia by boat will be sent to Papua New Guinea for processing and resettlement.</p>
<p>Australia will continue to have cooperative arrangements in asylum seekers with Nauru.</p>
<p>People who come by boat now have no prospect of being resettled in Australia.</p>
<p>The rules have changed. If you come by boat you will never permanently live in Australia.</p>
<p>This has not been an easy decision for me or my colleagues.</p>
<p>The sight of asylum seekers being exploited by people smugglers is appalling.</p>
<p>And the problem is likely to get worse in the future as it is for so many countries around the world.</p>
<p>We also have to do everything possible to protect our orderly migration system and the integrity of our borders.</p>
<p>The bottom line is that we have to protect lives by dealing robustly with people smugglers.</p>
<p>Australians have had enough of seeing asylum seekers dying in the waters to our north and our northwest.</p>
<p>They’ve had enough of people smugglers profiting from death.</p>
<p>Like me, they worry about the safety of our brave servicemen and women involved in rescue operations when boats get into distress.</p>
<p>As Prime Minister, I must address changing circumstances, balancing our humanitarian obligations under international law with the reality on the ground. </p>
<p>Australian Governments have never had a policy on asylum seekers that is set in stone.</p>
<p>We must always adjust to changing circumstances while remaining true to our values and vigilant concerning our legal obligations.</p>
<p>Asylum seeker policy is complex. It is very complex indeed.</p>
<p>It is hard. It involves detailed cooperation with other countries.</p>
<p>With this announcement there will inevitably be many hurdles along the road.</p>
<p>It won’t be smooth and nobody should expect the boats to stop tomorrow.</p>
<p>In fact, people smugglers will now try and test our resolve.</p>
<p>Our job is to deal with each new hurdle as it appears.</p>
<p>Under our new policy, Australia will continue to take genuine refugees from around the world under the normal processes of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.</p>
<p>Refugees who have often been languishing in camps for a decade.</p>
<p>But my message to asylum seekers around the world is simple.</p>
<p>Under the arrangement with Papua New Guinea, if you come here by boat, you will be sent to Papua New Guinea.</p>
<p>I also have a message for the people smugglers of our region and the world.</p>
<p>Your business model is over.</p>
<p>The decision we have announced today is one part of the Government’s multilayered approach in responding to the scourge of people smuggling.</p>
<p>The Government will continue to adjust our policy and approach in the future as necessary.</p>
<p>I thank you for your attention.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
