<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9851</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH NHK TELEVISION JAPAN, OSAKA 20 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009851.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
"~ Japan Embargo 9.3Opm Osaka time***<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MID<br />
INTERVIEW WITH NHK TELEVISION JAPAN, OSAKA<br />
NOVEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: French papers have reported that France is planning another nuclear test<br />
in a few days are you planning any specific measures to protest against<br />
France this time?<br />
PM: We have just last week secured the most condemnatory resolution in a<br />
large multilateral body that's the Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
meeting where Australia proposed that France be condemned for its<br />
position, for its decision to resume testing. And of course the word in<br />
international diplomacy the word condemned is a very judgmental and<br />
harsh word. So, that was at the Commonwealth Heads of Government.<br />
At the United Nations, we have also secured a very strong resolution<br />
against the French, and we will continue to proselytise the cause of liberty<br />
of people in the Pacific for the way of life that they wish, and the views<br />
that they are entitled to call their own, without this sort of heavy-handed<br />
approach from the French.<br />
J: Last time you recalled your ambassador from France. This time, what do<br />
you do?<br />
PM: Well, we have made the protest clear, and I think that President Chirac<br />
has said himself on American television that Australia had been the<br />
source of greatest pressure on France. You might have noticed in the<br />
weekend press that President Chirac took umbrage at a number of<br />
European countries, similarly expressing the same view as Australia, and<br />
decided he would cancel one or two meetings with them. So, the </p>
<p>pressure is continuing to come on them, and I think that's more effective<br />
now than any bilateral action, or unilateral action.<br />
J: It's a related question you have proposed to Prime Minister Murayama to<br />
set up a joint taskforce to deal with nuclear testing. Would you elaborate<br />
on what Australia and Japan can do in this taskforce?<br />
PM: Not on nuclear testing but to rid the world of nuclear weapons. It's going<br />
way beyond the testing point. There are 50,000 nuclear weapons around<br />
the arsenals of the major powers. What Australia wants to do is get them<br />
down to be rid of them. To be rid of nuclear weapons. You might know<br />
that Australia played a leading role in the Chemical Weapons Convention.<br />
Now, in that Convention we removed one whole category of weapons, so<br />
if we can do it for one whole category with chemical, we should be able to<br />
do it conceivably with one whole category with nuclear. And of course,<br />
the verification procedures on chemical weapons is, I think, far more<br />
difficult than verification on nuclear. So, we are now putting together a<br />
taskforce to look at ways where we may promote international agreement<br />
to actually cut the stockpiles. Now, this comes as well as Australia's<br />
involvement in the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty we will be playing, I<br />
hope, there a leading role, too which is a comprehensive ban on further<br />
testing, by everybody. We are also supporting the cut-off convention,<br />
which is the cutting off of further production of fissile material. So, there<br />
are three matters there is a cutoff convention on stopping the production<br />
of fissile material, there is a Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which is<br />
aimed at stopping comprehensively further testing, and then there is<br />
Australia's own initiative to actually be rid of nuclear weapons to actually<br />
take the stockpiles down. And it was that last subject that I spoke to<br />
Prime Minister Murayama about asking for Japan's support in this.<br />
J: With regard to APEC what is your evaluation of the outcome of this<br />
APEC Summit in. Osaka, particularly with respect to the issue of<br />
comprehensiveness?<br />
PM: I think the overall result was outstanding. The great clarity of the Bogor<br />
Declaration, which President Soeharto provided his stewardship<br />
provided has been, I think, built upon under the stewardship of Prime<br />
Minister Murayama. And I think that the outcome in Osaka yesterday is<br />
something that does adequate justice to the Bogor Declaration, and the<br />
leadership of President Soeharto in it. One of the stumbling issues over<br />
these recent weeks was the question of comprehensiveness, but what the<br />
draft declaration and the agenda showed the liberalisation agenda<br />
made clear is that everything is in all categories of goods and -services<br />
-are in the mix to free trade by 2010 for developed countries, that<br />
includes of course Japan and Australia, and the developing countries by </p>
<p>2020. So, what we said all of us, I think we don't mind...] mean, what is<br />
unique about APEC is that it has specified the end points 2010 and<br />
2020. In the Uruguay Round there were no end points it was a as if<br />
[ they said) " yes. liberalisation is a good thing, but maybe not too good,<br />
and we will just give away as much as we have to, and no more". Here,<br />
there is a much more generous, and a much more wise approach. At<br />
Bogor, we decided the end points. Once you have got the end point<br />
decided, and you have got commitments around the end point which is<br />
free trade by 2010 and 2020 the pace which individual countries then<br />
adopt for the lberalisation of particular sectors is a matter for them. And<br />
so this is why we have used this device called concerted liberalisation<br />
each country does its liberalising, but we bring it together as a concerted<br />
policy. Or we have liberalisation in concert. Now, this is both, I think,<br />
effective and mature, and the test you could see some of it yesterday<br />
was a very big liberalisation package announced by Japan, by Indonesia<br />
and by China.<br />
In other words, if people would make the big commitment to free and open<br />
trade by a certain date, you know, give them the credit of knowing that<br />
they will find their own way of getting there, and yesterday proved that<br />
they will. Which is a far better approach than the sort of mechanistic<br />
legalism of the Uruguay Round, or the<br />
J, Do you think that Japan has been able to achieve its role as a host nation<br />
to the conference?<br />
PM: Yes. I think that all of the imperatives of leadership which I believe<br />
Japan had to show on this occasion it did show. I think Prime Minister<br />
Murayama's work, Minister Hashimoto's work, Minister Kono, and their<br />
officials Mr Kono, and Mr Seki that group. And the fact that we had the<br />
Ministry of Trade and Industry and the Gaimusho working together which<br />
I must say is a rarity for Japan showed how effective they can be<br />
working together. So, I think and yet, let me say another thing, not only<br />
was leadership shown, but the fact that in an unfortunate way President<br />
Clinton couldn't come, it made very clear that Japan was able to do this<br />
without the validation of the United States. In other words, Japan stood<br />
on its own feet, and did this without the United States holding its hand.<br />
And that, I think, is a good thing too, because as you know, Australia is a<br />
great supporter of Japan's, and we're a great supporter of Japan taking a<br />
full place in the Security Council. But none of us would have wanted to<br />
vote for a country that, having the test of international leadership around<br />
something so mammoth as this APEC agenda, if Japan had either shirked<br />
the test or failed the test, it would have given not just Australia, but many<br />
other countries second doubts about its leadership capacity. I think those<br />
doubts have been dispelled. For my part, I have always believed </p>
<p>because Prime Minister Murayama sat next to me at Bogor I had an idea<br />
about his own thoughts about all of this, and I always believed he would<br />
rise to the challenge. And I think Ministers Hashimoto and Kono<br />
understand how absolutely pivotal and key this was to Japan setting up a<br />
proper East Asian trading structure, one that allows China to come out<br />
with the world economy and be received in a structure which has got<br />
rules, and which has got policy, that allows a proper resourcing of East<br />
Asia, at the same time, keeps the United States commercially engaged in<br />
the region. I think those two Ministers particularly understood those<br />
imperatives, and I think this must have been of material assistance to<br />
Prime Minister Murayama.<br />
J: With regarding of EAEC. there is a debate about Dr Mahathirts plan to<br />
create the EAEC....<br />
PM: Can I interrupt you? Look, it's an old debate. There's one premier<br />
organisation in the Asia Pacific now it's APEC. I mean, the bonhomie,<br />
the commitment, the goodwill that has come around APEC. I mean, look,<br />
since our first meeting in Seattle, you have got much greater movement of<br />
people between Korea and Japan with President Kim and Prime Minister<br />
Murayama, you have just had recently President Jiang Zemin visiting<br />
Seoul, the movement of people and the understanding and goodwill has<br />
come from one body, and that's APEC. Because at the same time, the<br />
strategic guarantor of all this the United States is involved, too. In any<br />
East Asian body, the United States isn't there. Now, this debate. . you<br />
could have a debate about this at the time of Seattle. You could even<br />
keep the remnants of it going at the time of Bogor. But now, there is one<br />
and one body only, and that's APEC. Now of course, in the region in our<br />
region, that is East Asia, South East Asia you still have people meeting<br />
and talking, and our trade ministers meet and talk without some of our<br />
Pacific Rim partners being present on all occasions, but that is not the<br />
institutional structure that we are speaking of. The institutional structure<br />
is around APEC.<br />
J: Mr Keating, you are well known as Mr Deregulation how do you plan to<br />
pull the Australian economy back Into shape?<br />
PM: Well, It's already in pretty good shape, now. After ten years of hard work<br />
we are now in our longest phase of growth since the Second World War.<br />
This quarter will be seventeen quarters of consecutive growth, so this is a<br />
record for us. This year, the economy has been growing around we<br />
have been averaging in the last half dozen certainly, the last four years<br />
about 4% employment growth a year. We have got inflation sitting at<br />
about our exports in the last decade have doubled, the proportion of<br />
our exports we devote to servicing our debt has fallen from 22% of our </p>
<p>exports to 11 and, I think, we have got a horsepower about the country<br />
now, and a confidence I think we have probably never had before. So, I<br />
think these policies have worked, and I think that the Australian people<br />
have made themselves the effort, and have had the Confidence to take<br />
the opportunity to make their own country internationally competitive. But<br />
having made it competitive, take the leap in market growth in the East<br />
Asian region.<br />
J: Foreign policies you have already expressed that Australia will pull away<br />
from the Commonwealth why the reason?<br />
PM: No. I am saying that Australia should have its own Head of State that<br />
the Head of State of Australia shouldn't be the Monarch of Great Britain,<br />
that it's now inappropriate that it should be the Monarch of Great Britain.<br />
Australia is now a multi-cultural country it Is a mono-culture no longer.<br />
Over half of our migration intake comes from Asia. You know of our post-<br />
War migration from Europe and the Middle East, and as a consequence,<br />
Australia has a diversity and a vivaciousness about it now, and a<br />
willingness a very strong desire to engage with the region, and that<br />
sense of the culture of the new Australia and its identity can't be served<br />
by us saying oh, by the way, our Head of State is the Monarch of Great<br />
Britain. Our Head of State should be an Australian. So the Government<br />
is supporting Australia moving from the Monarchy to an Australian<br />
republic. But we do not wish to remove ourselves from the<br />
Commonwealth. I attended a Commonwealth Heads of Government<br />
meeting list week one of the two newest members returning was<br />
President Nelson Mandela of South Africa. A republic, but he is still in the<br />
Commonwealth. Well, Australia would be a republic too, but still in the<br />
Commonwealth. But the Queen of Great Britain would not be the Queen<br />
of Australia.<br />
J: In the few days that you have been here, what has been your impression<br />
staying in Osaka and Kansai, and also, could you please tell us what Is<br />
you vision for future economic links between Japan and your country,<br />
Australia?<br />
PM: I think coming to. most of my visits to Japan are to Tokyo. I have been to<br />
Osaka before, and coming to Kansai, one is reminded again of the actual<br />
size and strength of Japan. You know, the industrial might one sees in<br />
that trip from the airport into the city, past kilometres and kilometres of<br />
petro-chemical plants and the rest, and this very big City and very large<br />
population, and a very large part of Japan's GDP in the Kansai region.<br />
We now fly direct flights into the new airport, we have a new relationship<br />
with the Kansai region, and I think it's one that we can.. I1m ean, I think it's<br />
cheaper to do business in Kansai, probably, than Tokyo. And I think we </p>
<p>see that opportunity. And it underlines again the absolute size and<br />
significance of Japan when one thinks of the size of metropolitan Tokyo,<br />
and then sees the strength of the Kansai region, it reminds you simply just<br />
how large Japan is.<br />
The other thought I had about it is that one of the reasons Japan has<br />
been accumulating trade surpluses, and because it hasn't lifted domestic<br />
demand to the point that perhaps it should, and in housing and<br />
infrastructure, it has become very apparent to me that this is one place<br />
where Japanese national savings should be sent. Cleaning up the<br />
Capital Gains Tax rules on property would allow a sensible aggregation of<br />
properties, more rational development of cities better urban planning.<br />
Because one of the problems Australia has, is not a well developed sense<br />
of urban planning, and I am unhappy to say that we share this with you.<br />
There is no really developed sense of urban development in Japan. You<br />
don't need to be an urban planner to understand this your eye can tell<br />
you this, at every street corner. So, I think that if Japan continues to<br />
worry about a surplus, and the strength of the Yen, one of the ways of<br />
solving it is to put more of its savings into housing renewal, better cities<br />
and a higher standard of living for people. But the one thing that is<br />
certain Japan has got the strength to do all these things, and as such, it<br />
is an important partner for Australia, an important interlocutor for<br />
Australia, it is our largest trading relationship. And I think you can see,<br />
throughout this APEC discussion where our officials and yours have<br />
worked very closely together, where our Ministers and yours have worked<br />
closely together, where Prime Minister Murayama and I have worked<br />
closely together, how effective a partnership we can be if we put our<br />
minds to getting something done.<br />
J: Thank you very much, Prime Minister.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
