<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>16327</transcript-id>
    <title>Australia provides support for Afghanistan Elections    </title>
    <prime-minister>Rudd, Kevin</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20071203 - 20100624</period-of-service>
    <release-date>20/12/2008</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Prime Minister Kevin Rudd today announced Australia will provide $5 million to support the 2009/2010 Afghanistan elections.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister made the announcement after returning from his visit to Tarin Kowt in the Oruzgan province, where he met Australian personnel on deployment to Afghanistan. </p>
<p>The Australian Government will provide $3 million to the United Nations Development Program to help the Afghanistan Independent Election Commission (AIEC) build a national voter registration campaign which will sign up more than 2 million new voters. </p>
<p>Further, the Government will provide $2 million towards the Asia Foundation's work with the AIEC and civil society partners to implement electoral education and public outreach programs in Afghanistan. </p>
<p>The 2009 Presidential and Provincial Council elections and the 2010 Parliamentary elections are crucial to international efforts to help build a stable and democratic Afghanistan.</p>
<p>It is vitally important that efforts continue to strengthen democratic governance and to promote economic development in Afghanistan, to build on the successes of Australia's troops and other security forces. </p>
<p>For the elections to be considered free, fair and credible, the international community needs to ensure that the Afghanistan Independent Election Commission is sufficiently resourced. </p>
<p>Ensuring there is broad and equitable participation by all Afghans, including women and displaced persons, is critically important for building the legitimacy and credibility of the election process. </p>
<p>The Asia Foundation had been helping to deliver Australia's assistance to the AIEC since 2005 through:</p>
<p>     * Providing short-term training of staff at the Australian Electoral Commission;</p>
<p>     * Running an observation mission to the 2007 Australian federal elections; and,</p>
<p>     * Providing direct support to AIEC offices.</p>
<p>The Australian Government, through the Australian Agency for International Development (AusAID), will continue to provide assistance to Afghanistan in partnership with the Afghanistan Government.</p>
<p>In 2008-09, AusAID will provide an estimated $62 million of much needed development assistance to Afghanistan.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
