<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1185</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT THE OPENING OF THE ROYAL INSURANCE BUILDING, MELBOURNE</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/10/1965</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001185_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>OPENING OF THE ROYAL INSURANCE BUILDING,<br />MELBOURNE. 29TH OCTOBER, 1965<br />Speech by the Prime Minister, Sir Robert Menzies<br />Sir and Ladies and Gentlemen,<br />I notice at least one Presbyterian Minister here<br />today, and he at least will understand me when I say that this<br />is a work of superero) ation. The building has been open for<br />twelve months. ILaughler) I have every reason to suppose it<br />was open when I was over the road making rude remarks about<br />it a year ago. And so with that fashion for accuracy that<br />characterises a politician, I retrospectively declare it open.<br />Now having done it both ways, you understand,<br />Jock wherever Jock is that it is now open, and as he would<br />add for business. ( Laughter) ( Applause)<br />I would like to thank Raynes Dickson very much for<br />his references to the Cinque Ports, known to one garage<br />roprietor in Canberra, so the legend runs, as Sinapore,<br />because he announced with great joy that morning, nave you<br />heard the news that Sir Robert has been made the Lord Warden<br />of Singapore?" I hope that the actual position will be a<br />little less precarious than that one.<br />You were mentioning the fact that it was held by<br />Sir Winston Churchill, and before him by Lord Reading and Lord<br />Willingdon. Thisis a quaint in some ways, but movingly<br />historic post and when you refer to Sir Winston Churchill,<br />may I * us mae one reference to him. It has nothing to do<br />wi h the Royal and nothing to do with opening the building<br />and therefore, of course, it is appropriate.<br />I remember durin the war sitting with him one<br />night after dinner, and in te amiability that overtook us<br />after dinner very probably, I said, " Of course you realise,<br />don't you, that by the time you have been dead an event<br />wqhich I hope will be long postponed by the time you've been<br />dead for ten years, there will be very clever young men at<br />Oxford or Cambridge or somewhere else who will be writing<br />books about you, explaining that you were never right.' And<br />his face fell a little at This. I said " This is true.. This<br />is all experience. They will explain that you were always<br />wrong. But take comfort-twenty years after that date, they<br />will all be forgotten and ou will still be on the top of<br />the hill." And I noticed The other day that somebody has now<br />produced a book, whether it will carry out my prophecy or not<br />I don't know. ( except that he appears to have been a . elshman<br />explaining tAat the o] lman was always wrong. aell, thank<br />Heaven he wasn't.. Otherwise we wouldn't be here, which perhaps<br />is the complete answer to what the young gentleman is writing.<br />But, however, that is by the way.<br />You have been reminded that this building is on<br />the site of a block of land sold for œ 46 which I hasten to<br />say is before the time of my Government. They were pre-Menzies<br />pounds ( Laughter) but still, they were not many, were they<br />46 back in 1537. Extraordinary thing you know. Vue are<br />always in the habit, aren't we, as we look back in thinking<br />that the perspectives of history looking backwards are enormous,<br />that things that happened one hundred years ago happened a / 2</p>
<p>2<br />long, long time ago, beyond the possible memory of man. And<br />yet! can remember walki n along the Ballarat streets with a<br />grandfather who was born 0wo ears before this block was sold,<br />and I have grandchildren who T hope will remember me, if they<br />are not ashamed of me, for many years to come? and between my<br />memory and theirs and my immedia e ancestor, is a spread of<br />two centuries. History is not all that long, but it is a<br />splendid thing this historic company because it is I say that<br />with confidence because as a small boy in the bush it was the<br />only insuring body that I ever heard of. There it was, the<br />Royal. So it must have stretched its tentacles a long way to<br />come into my remote corner of the woods, you see, and this is<br />an historic company, or an historic group of companies, and here<br />is an historic site.<br />It's a pity in a sense that you had to pull down<br />Scot's Hotel, though mark you, I don't blame you entirely.<br />It had its defects, tut I want to go on record as reminding the<br />Scots here and I see quite a few, and the Sassenachs of whom<br />I seer I regret to say even more I think I should remind you<br />that it was on this site and in tAe kitchen which originally<br />was down below that the finest haggis in the world was made.<br />Magnificent haggis piped in magnificently and eloquently<br />addressed by the president, whose name I will conceal for this<br />purpose. This is an historic spot.<br />But why are we here in such a tremendous development<br />of real ya great company in Ithe insurance field? WelleIwill<br />answer that question very briefly and then have done. fl were<br />all brought up, taught at school to learn something about the<br />industrial revolution, the introduction of steam, the creation<br />of factories for the first time this tremendou-development<br />which, in effect begnn in Great Britain and made Britain<br />through the nineteenth century the greatest industrial nation<br />in the world. And similarly, the tremendous development of<br />shipping which followed on The introduction of steel, with<br />Great Britain as the greatest mercantile marine power in the<br />world and these are istoric and striking things. It's true<br />that the emphasis has changed from time to time, but these are<br />striking and historic. It perhaps may much more easily be<br />forgotten that the industrial revolution, this enormous stimulation<br />of world trade, of world business couldn't have occurred<br />but for the contemporary advance in banking and insurance.<br />This is very well worth remembering and in<br />particular, speaking of insurance, insurance with the great<br />principle of the distribution of risks so that they became<br />indivi aually bearable through the process of insurance and<br />re-insurance and so on. I think the insurance world can afford<br />to be proud of the fact that it has just as much to do with the<br />modern development of world trade as any other single factor<br />and this is worth recalling because we have some reason to be<br />proud of the fact that in both of these spheres our ancestors<br />played a great part and hive therefore le t a great inheritance.<br />I say that because when I was a younger man, I<br />was a barrister, a very respectable one and I had the usual<br />fate of learned counsel, I !. as given a few briefs for the<br />plaintiff oh blessed day when you are appearing for the<br />olaintiff and if the defendant was well khown to be insured,<br />he plaintiff won. Of course this was strictly impartial on<br />the part of the jury, but still word does get around. And I<br />founa myself winning cases for the plaintiff and getting<br />substantial verdicts. Then the solicitors for the insurance / 3</p>
<p>companies had a look around and said, " This young fellow Menzies<br />must be quite good," and so they briefed me. I wasn't objecting<br />n one sense because the solicitors were more powerful and<br />the fees somewhat greater. After that, I didn t ever win a<br />case. ( Laughter) And basically, you see, the reason for it<br />is that in spite of this tremendous service that it does to the<br />community, unrecognised, unseen in many cases, the insurance<br />company has difficulty in maintaining even the modest rating<br />of popularity in the allup poll.<br />And I see some bankers here. They needn't smile<br />too quickly because their rating is no higher. ( Laughter)<br />Here we are in a strange paradoxical world in which the very<br />people down in the street who are quite prepared to be prejudiced<br />against the insurer or against the banker, and express it on a<br />suitable occasion if they happen to be on a jury are the very<br />people who when they have a problem of either kind, repair<br />instantly to the banker, to the insurer and have their business<br />attended to. This is one of the paradoxes of our national<br />character. .' hat was it that was said by Oscar .; ilde " All<br />men kill the thing they love." ' Hell, I wouldn't say they loved<br />you, and I don't go so far as to say they would kill you, but<br />there is a human disposition to be extremely critical of the<br />people who really represent our first port of call in a storm.<br />And therefore ladies and gentlemen, I feel it to<br />be a great pleasure not only to be here under pressure of an<br />old and valued friend in Jock Duguid, but also because on this<br />historic site, I like to have the opportunity of recalling some<br />of the historic elements in that great story, as yet quite<br />unfinished, of our race and of our undertakings all round the<br />world. So Sir, I wish you the best of good fortune.<br />I'm very delighted indeed that your two principals from overseas<br />are here. I met them in Canberra the otner day. I liked them<br />so much that observing that the time was six o clock, I think,<br />and knowing the attitude of the Chief General Manager at six<br />o'clock in the afternoon, I took them in and gave them a wee<br />dram ( Laughter) and I am delighted to remember the wee dram and<br />to welcome them and to see them here again.<br />Sir, there is a Standing Order in Parliament<br />against tedious repetition seldom observed I may say, but<br />tiere it is. I will engge in tedious repetition. For the<br />third time, I declare this building open.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
