<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4139</transcript-id>
    <title>STATEMENT ON THE ARTS, THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RIGHT HONOURABLE JM FRASER MP, 3 JUNE 1976</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/06/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004139_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
STATEMENT ON THE ARTS J<br />
THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
THE RIGHT HONOURABLE J. M. FRASER, M. P.<br />
3 JUNE 1976<br />
I should like to inform the House on measures the<br />
Government is taking in the area of the arts.<br />
The Government will be providing next year, $ 33.8<br />
million exclusive of Australia Council administrative costs, for<br />
support for the arts.<br />
This continued high level of support emphasises the<br />
Government's firm commitment to support and encourage the development<br />
of the arts throughout the Australian community.<br />
In line with economies elsewhere we have aimed at<br />
eliminating unnecessary expenditure, but equally we have sought to<br />
ensure that no important or worthwhile programmes suffer.<br />
Providing a national stimulus to the arts is in<br />
accordance with our philosophy of freedom of individual expression.<br />
We believe in freedom for artist and patron alike.<br />
For this reason we do not see the Government as the only<br />
or necessarily the major source of art patronage.<br />
Ideally, the arts through individual and community<br />
patronage should be self-supporting, but there are few if any places<br />
where this happens.<br />
Even in the United States, the Federal Government has in<br />
recent years had to play a part, and Government support for the<br />
arts is an accepted fact in the cultural life of Western Europe. </p>
<p>It is one of the Commonwealth Government's tasks<br />
to see how best the arts programmes of all levels of Government<br />
in Australia might complement and support each other, to<br />
minimize duplication and overlap and to provide the greatest<br />
measure of fulfilment for artists and audiences.<br />
We believe a genuinely vigorous and stimulating<br />
artistic climate will emerge only when Governments, individuals<br />
and private enterprises and corporations are actively and<br />
co-operatively offering decentralised and diversified patronage<br />
for the arts in our community. A diversity and plurality of<br />
support can only strengthen the arts to the general common good.<br />
Let me emphasise that our aim is to broaden support<br />
for the arts, to have more funds flowing from different sources.<br />
We are not seeking to find substitutes for Government assistance,<br />
but to expand on that necessary base.<br />
In this connection, the Government is having examined<br />
the possibility of taxation concessions or other incentives for<br />
the arts, and ways and means of encouraging individual and<br />
private enterprise and corporate patronage.<br />
Internationally, the Government will continue to<br />
foster cultural exchanges. We will support programmes to<br />
bring arts and artists from abroad. We will also support the<br />
promotion of Australian arts and artists overseas. Of the<br />
latter, one example among many is our programme of activities<br />
in connection with the American Bicentennial Celebrations<br />
which includes the forthcoming tour of the Australian Ballet. </p>
<p>Turning to specific issues, in December last year<br />
we established the Administrative Review Committee to review<br />
Government expenditure and recommend on ways of eliminating waste<br />
and duplication within and between Government departments and<br />
agencies, and between Commonwealth and State Government bodies.<br />
As one of its first tasks the Committee undertook an<br />
examination of the operations of the Australia Council, the Film<br />
and Television School, and the Australian Film Commission.<br />
The Australia Council had itself recognised management<br />
and other organisational difficulties. It had separately commissioned<br />
an inquiry into its operations, by McKinsey and Company Inc.<br />
Both this report and the Council's views on it were<br />
available to the Committee.<br />
The Government has reached a number of decisions on the<br />
structure and future of its arts organisationso<br />
Australia Council The operations of the Australia Council and its<br />
expenditure on the arts have been reported on by the Auditor-General<br />
and the Public Accounts Committee. They have been the subject<br />
of questions in Parliament and debate in the media.<br />
The Council has attracted criticism, particularly<br />
from artists and the arts' community, concerning extravagance<br />
and excessive administrative expenses. </p>
<p>The Administrative Review Committee, in its examination<br />
of the Council noted, among other things: unsatisfactory<br />
arrangements between the Council and Boards; high turn-over of<br />
members; excessive attention to the making of small grants and<br />
at considerable cost; insufficient account was taken of blossoming<br />
State cultural authorities and their possible use as agents for<br />
the Council; enthusiastic arts amateurs and the dilettante seemed<br />
to receive more attention than was probably deserved.<br />
The changes to be made are designed to correct identified<br />
problems and deficiencies, to make administrative and financial<br />
arrangements more efficient, to reduce administrative costs so<br />
that more funds will be available for the arts themselves, to<br />
enter on new and improved arrangements which might lead to greater<br />
involvement of State and local governments and other enterprises.<br />
The Australia Council Act is to be amended to formally<br />
give the Council the role of the Government's advisory agency on<br />
all matters falling within the area of its responsibilities.<br />
The Council was not previously charged with this specific<br />
responsibility. Council control of the activities of the Boards will<br />
be increased for reasons of administrative effectiveness, but not<br />
so as to interfere with essential flexibility for running day-to-day<br />
affairs. In future, Boards will be responsible to the Council<br />
and function under its direction and guidelines. They will have<br />
clearly defined advisory and recommendatory roles, and such<br />
executive powers as the Council may delegate to them. .0 </p>
<p>Changes are proposed to the structure and size of the<br />
Council and Boards to increase effectiveness, generally reduce<br />
costs but at the same time, ensure continuity and diversity of<br />
advice. The Council will be reduced in size from a range of<br />
18-24 members to a range of 15-19 members. Public Service members<br />
will be reduced from 3 to 2.<br />
Two new positions will be created: one of Deputy Chairman<br />
of the Council ( a part-time office) to assist the Chairman and<br />
generally facilitate the Council's operations; one of General-<br />
Manager ( a full-time office) to be the chief executive of the Council.<br />
This will give greater weight to the chief executive office, and<br />
generally provide a better scheme of administrative responsibility.<br />
The office of General-Manager will be a statutory one. The General-<br />
Manager will be an ex-officio member of the Council.<br />
To reduce excessive turnover, the terms of appointment of<br />
Council and Board members will be extended from 3 to 4 years. Members'<br />
appointments may be renewed for a further term of 2 years0 After<br />
this reappointment would not be considered until 2 more years expired.<br />
The Australia Council's film, radio and television<br />
responsibilities will be transferred to the Australian Film<br />
Commission. The Film, Radio and Television Board will be abolished.<br />
This change is being made on the basis of drawing all<br />
film and television activities together as a step in rationalization,<br />
and so that creative film-makers might now link up with the<br />
mainstream of commercial film-making. . o/ 6 </p>
<p>The number and responsibilities of the other Boards<br />
will remain the same0<br />
Membership of the Boards will be reduced from a range<br />
of 7-10, excepting Aboriginal Arts which is 9-14 plus Chairman,<br />
to a range of 5-7. Aboriginal Arts will be 7-9 plus Chairman.<br />
As a further step to rationalise and reduce administration,<br />
the Council will assume responsibility for and administer: the<br />
Australian Authors' Fund and the Historic Memorials Committee,<br />
activities presently with the Department of the Prime Minister and<br />
Cabinet; the Aboriginal arts activities presently with the<br />
Department of Aboriginal Affairs.<br />
To increase the involvement of State, Territory and<br />
local governments, and other appropriate regional organisations,<br />
the Council will consult with appropriate authorities to begin a<br />
programme of devolution of grant-giving activitiesø<br />
Community arts activities and small grants to individuals<br />
or groups are areas where the programme of devolution might begin.<br />
In line with the Government's view that the Council<br />
should retain overall responsibility for Commonwealth programmes<br />
for the arts, funds will remain part of theCouncil's budget<br />
and be channelled through it to the States and other bodies0<br />
In any programmes of devolution the Council may specify<br />
the broad purposes for which the funds might be used. It may<br />
also expect reports from the grant-giving agencies on how moneys<br />
have been spend and on the operation of the programmes. The 0../ 7 </p>
<p>7.<br />
pace and scope of the programmes and transitional and other<br />
arrangements necessary will be matters for determination by the<br />
Council. The costs of many small individual grants programmes<br />
have been out of proportion to the assistance offered. Accordingly,<br />
while I would expect the Council to continue to offer individual<br />
grants, I would hope that in future the emphasis would be on<br />
assisting the most talented with the highest promise of excellence.<br />
The Council aims to widen involvement in the arts, and<br />
encourage more support from other areas. In line with this object<br />
the Council will be asked to seek to establish arrangements whereby<br />
support for national organisations the Arts Council of<br />
Australia, the Crafts Council of Australia), and performing arts<br />
companies in the States would be on a matching basis with either<br />
the organisations or the States.<br />
Matching arrangements should be a Council objective.<br />
It is not our intention, however, that it should be an<br />
inflexible rule which might impede the development of any arts<br />
activities. Precise matching arrangements would be a matter for<br />
determination by the Council.<br />
Training in the arts is essentially an educational matter.<br />
In future the Council will not engage in this activity. I have in<br />
mind in particular the National Institute of Dramatic Art, and the<br />
Australian Ballet School.<br />
It is proposed that in the future the appropriate<br />
Commonwealth and State education authorities should be responsible<br />
for these institutions. </p>
<p>After due consideration of all the issues, it<br />
has been decided that the Commonwealth Government will<br />
not provide direct or indirect assistance for capital<br />
arts projects outside of its responsibilities in<br />
Commonwealth Territories. The Government regards this as<br />
essentially a State function.<br />
There are other matters largely internal to the<br />
Council aimed at establishing improved criteria for grants,<br />
guidelines and controls, better administrative and financial<br />
arrangements, and reduced costs. I shall be tsaking these up<br />
with the Council. The changes that are proposed should not be allowed<br />
to reflect on the greater part of the Council's very fine<br />
work and its many excellent initiatives.<br />
The arts by their very nature are an area for<br />
controversy and differences of judgement and opinion.<br />
Criticisms need, therefore, tobe kept in perspective.<br />
Among the many very worthy projects the Council<br />
has currently in hand is the proposed Chinese Archaeological<br />
Exhibition scheduled for early next year. This is almost<br />
certainly the most important exhibition ever to come to<br />
Australia, and is a landmark of its kind. / 9 </p>
<p>r r i
10 f 2 ' 1 3t 114<br />
r C<br />
' r I C) H~ t ' jVJ* T:;<br />
let ifI<br />
" 1' VEin r~ ye'<br />
) Jt ' II<br />
, f, i"<br />
.4 C<br />
I, I<br />
I<br />
C * Ii /: 0<br />
1i13df i ~ v<br />
C.. </p>
<p>Film and Television<br />
The Government will continue to encourage film<br />
and television in partnership with the industry, the ultimate<br />
aim being self-sufficiency.<br />
Recent experience has made us all aware of the potential<br />
of our film and television industry and of the ready interest of<br />
Australian audiences.<br />
Onoe again the changes to be made are intended to<br />
rationalise and draw like activities tbogether to make for more<br />
effective operation and the best use of available resources.<br />
In this area, the Government has taken the following<br />
decisions oThe Australian Film Commission will take over<br />
responsibility for independent radio and audio-visual<br />
production activities areas largely neglected in the past.<br />
* The film, radio arid television functions of the<br />
Australia Council will go to the Commission. A joint<br />
working party will be set up to effect the most satisfactory<br />
transfer and to ensure that proper account is taken of<br />
the interests of the staff involved.<br />
The Commission will also take over the staff and<br />
resources of the Audio-Visual Branch of the Postal<br />
and Telecommunications Department these resources will<br />
complement and expand those of the Commission' s Film<br />
Australia Branch.<br />
OThe Film and Television School will assume responsibility<br />
for training in radio and audio-visual communicationsagain,<br />
areas previously neglected' / 1 </p>
<p>Changes in both the Australia Council and the Australian<br />
Film Commission will involve amendments to legislation and these<br />
will be introduced as soon as practicable.<br />
Australian National Gallery<br />
The Government is committed to the concept of the<br />
National Gallery, and the broad objectives of the National Gallery<br />
Act passed by Parliament last year.<br />
The Act has been proclaimed with effect from 3 June 1976,<br />
and I am pleased to announce the appointment of the following<br />
members of the first permanent Council, each of whom will hold office<br />
for a term of 3 years: Mr Richard Crebbin ( Chairman)<br />
Mr Fred Williams<br />
Mr James T. Gleeson, A. M.<br />
Mr Murray Bail<br />
Professor Patrick McCaughey<br />
Miss Pamela Bell<br />
Mr James 0. Fairfax<br />
Mr David Wynn<br />
Mr John D. Davies<br />
Mr Donald J. Munro, O. B. E.<br />
The Council will assume immediate responsibility for<br />
on-going arrangements and advice to the Government on all<br />
Gallery affairs. As I have stated elsewhere, we believe that the Gallery<br />
should hold the very finest work of Australian artists of all<br />
periods and we shall support the policy of giving priority to the<br />
acquisition of Australian art. ,. o/ 11 </p>
<p>110<br />
This will not preclude the Gallery acquiring important<br />
works of art in other areas, and continuing to develop a National<br />
Collection taking in the arts of other countries and cultures.<br />
In addition, we shall through the Australia Council seek to<br />
encourage more high quality exhibitions from abroad so that as<br />
many Australians as possible may see a greater number of the finest<br />
works of art from other regions and periods.<br />
I believe that the active pursuit of my Government's<br />
aims towards the arts will be, ultimately, to the greater benefit<br />
of the whole Australian community. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
