<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2485</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH THE RT HON W MCMAHON MP PRIME MINISTER ON NATIONAL FILM AND TELEVISION TRAINING SCHOOL</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/10/1971</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002485.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA<br />
SPEECH<br />
The Rt Hona. W. McMAHON, M. P.<br />
Prime Minister<br />
ON<br />
National Film and Television Training School<br />
,[ From the ' Parliamentary Debates', 26 October 1971]<br />
Mr McMAHON ( Lowe-Prime Minister)<br />
On 14th October, in reply to a question<br />
from the Leader of the Opposition, 1<br />
undertook to look at figures concerning the<br />
proposals of the Interim Council for a<br />
National Film and Television Training<br />
School that my colleague, the Minister for<br />
the Environment, Aborigines and the Arts<br />
( Mr Howson) had presented to the House<br />
and at criticisms that had been made about<br />
them. I have had the matter looked into<br />
and I have studied the various statements<br />
' hat have been made in the House. I am<br />
satisfied that the Minister did not give to the<br />
House-to quote the Leader of the Opposition-'-<br />
figures which were not accurate or<br />
estimates which were misleading'. rme<br />
discussion that has taken place in the House<br />
' ias centred around the cost of acquiring<br />
land and whether an area of 60 acres, or an<br />
area of 8 acres, should be acquired.<br />
In November 1969, the Government set<br />
up an Interim Council for a National Film<br />
and Television Training School. The Interim<br />
Council submitted its first report in<br />
November 1970. 1 table a -copy of the<br />
report. In paragraph 11.4 the Council<br />
expressed the view that: ' It is not a viable<br />
proposition to set up a National Film and<br />
Television School on its own, with a student<br />
body of only limited numbers'. In paragraph<br />
11.8 the Council said that: ' The<br />
school should be established as an independent<br />
College of Advanced Education<br />
immediately adjacent to an existing educational<br />
institution'. In paragraph 12.3 the<br />
Council suggested that an area of some 60<br />
acres might well be required. The full import will be apparent to members on<br />
reading the text of these paragraphs of the<br />
report. The Interim Council submitted a second<br />
report in March this year. I table a copy of<br />
that report. In it the Council put forward a<br />
programme of action on the basis that the<br />
National Film and Television School would<br />
open up for some pupils early in 1973. In<br />
paragraph 4 of the report the Council<br />
suggested a timetable and said that-and I<br />
quote from sub-paragraph 5-the programme<br />
as set out in the timetable is<br />
applicable whether the Government accepts<br />
the recommendation to purchase the larger<br />
area required for a Centre or a lesser area<br />
sufficient for the Film and Television School<br />
alone'. Mr Acting Speaker, it is clear that<br />
the Council was to be taken in its second<br />
report as adhering to its recommendation<br />
in the first report that an area of something<br />
like 60 acres should be acquired, although<br />
it was recognising that the Government, on<br />
its initiative, might only authorise the<br />
acquisition of a lesser area.<br />
In June this year the Minister raised with<br />
the Council the question whether the School<br />
might not progress along rather more<br />
cautious lines than the Council had proposed.<br />
On 30th June the Minister received<br />
estimates which I now table. It will be seen<br />
from an examination of these estimates that<br />
on the basis of the acquisition of 60 acres,<br />
which was the Council's recommendation,<br />
the cost would be S7.6m, and that on the<br />
basis of the acquisition of 8 acres the cost<br />
would be $ 5.6m. I table a copy of a letter </p>
<p>dated 28th July 1971, addressed to the<br />
Minister by the Chairman of the Interim<br />
Council. It reads:<br />
At the meeting of the Interim Council on Tuesday,<br />
27th July, it was decided that I should<br />
confirm, in writing, two of the points made in our<br />
personal discussions, as being the firm views of the<br />
Interim Council.<br />
Whilst fully recognising the present need for<br />
economies, the Council stresses that it would be<br />
self-defeating to begin the school inadequately.<br />
Although it would be possible to move more<br />
slowly than envisaged in the original reports, the<br />
Council considers the the school must start off<br />
with adequate resources at each stage if it is<br />
to be developed in a worthwhile way.<br />
The Council also is anxious to make perfectly<br />
clear that its recommendation on the purchase of<br />
the land, now available in a non-intensive subdivision,<br />
is based on the belief that the site should<br />
not be confined to the area needed solely for a<br />
Film and Television School. Other schools in<br />
associated studies are under active consideration,<br />
and their eventual close association and physical<br />
location alongside the Film School is considered<br />
of great importance to its long-term success.<br />
The opportunity to acquire the full site so<br />
advantageously will never reoccur.<br />
I realise I have already made these points in<br />
personal discussions with you, but ' I agree with<br />
the Council that it is desirable that they bz<br />
confirmed in writing.<br />
On 8th September the Minister mae a<br />
statement in the House in the course of<br />
which he said:<br />
Whilst the Council's enthusiasm for this project<br />
is fully apparent from its reports, the continuing<br />
economic stringencies and the substantial cost<br />
which is estimated to be over $ 7m during the<br />
next 5 years have led to consideration of its<br />
proposals being deferred for 12 months. The<br />
proposals may then be considered in the light<br />
of what I hope will be more propitious economic<br />
circumstances. Having regard to the very recent and, I<br />
might add, firm advice that the Minister<br />
had received in Mr Coleman's letter<br />
of 28th July, the Minister was justified in<br />
treating the Council's proposals as being<br />
proposals involving the expenditure of<br />
over $ 7m during the next 5 years.<br />
There remains one matter, namely, the<br />
matter of the number of graduates, to<br />
which -the Minister referred in answer to<br />
a question by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
on 10th September. The Minister<br />
gave a figure of 12 graduates. The report<br />
to the Interim Council by P. A. Management<br />
Consultants Pty Ltd reflected some<br />
doubt about the needs of industry for<br />
graduates. The report said: ' Under the assumption that present trends<br />
will continue, the number of graduates from the<br />
School that the industry believes it could abso,:<br />
has been determined in the range from 30-4<br />
graduates.' However, on the same page the survey<br />
went on to conclude that the School<br />
should cater for an initial output of only<br />
15 graduates a year for the industry. The<br />
Minister acknowledges that he was in error<br />
in referring to 12 graduates. The figure<br />
should have been 15. I table a copy of the<br />
consultants' report.<br />
Mr Acting Speaker, I have stated the<br />
position in some detail, and I have tabled<br />
reports and other papers, so that the<br />
whole matter can be looked at fairly and<br />
squarely. I have done so myself and air<br />
fully satisfied with the account that the<br />
Minister has given to the House. It is true<br />
that consideration had been given by the<br />
Minister to the possibility of proceeding<br />
with the School by itself in an area of 8<br />
acres. But that was not the Council's proposal.<br />
The Council had recommended the<br />
acquisition of 60 acres and on 28th July<br />
it affirmed that recommendation. The<br />
making of a decision was a matter for<br />
the Government. The advice of the<br />
Council was not, however, lightly to be<br />
disregarded. In all the circumstances, and<br />
in view of the economic factors to which<br />
the Minister referred in his statement of<br />
8th September, the Government concluded<br />
that it should look at -the whole<br />
question again within the next year. This<br />
the Government has undertaken to do and<br />
this it will do. I present the following<br />
papers: National Film and Television Training School<br />
Interim Council<br />
First Report of November 1970,<br />
Second Report of March 1971,<br />
Tables of Estimates of Costs of Establish<br />
ing the School,<br />
A Survey of Employment Opportunities<br />
for Graduates of the Training Schoo:.<br />
A copy of a letter dated 28th July ' 197.1<br />
from the Chairman to the Minister f" r<br />
the Environment, Aboriginies and the<br />
Arts,<br />
Answers by the Prime Minister to a<br />
question by the Leader of the Opposition<br />
on 14th October concerning the<br />
proposals of the Interim Council for a<br />
National Film and Television Training<br />
School, 26th October 1971.<br />
19997/ 71W. G. MuRmAY, Government Printer, Canberra </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
