<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3130</transcript-id>
    <title>CONSTITUTIONAL COMMITTEE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/01/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003130.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER PRESS STATMENT NO. 171<br />
16 JANUARY 1974<br />
CONSTITUTIONAL COMMITTEE<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr E. G. Whitlam, said that<br />
Standing Committee appointed by resolution of the Constitutional<br />
Convention to consider in detail the matters raised at the Convention<br />
in relation to the financial provisions of the Constitution, the powers<br />
of Governments to manage the economy and the place of Local Governmrent<br />
under the Constitution, had met in Canberra today.<br />
The meeting commenced under the Chairmanship of<br />
Senator Greenwood, but Senator Greenwood advised the meeting that<br />
the Prime Minister, who had been unable to attend the first meeting<br />
of the Committee, was willing to accept the Chairmanship of the<br />
Committee, and he accordingly resigned his position in favour of the<br />
Prime Minister, who was unanimously elected to the Chair. Mr Holding,<br />
who had been elected Deputy Chairman at the Melbourne meeting, also<br />
resigned and nominated Senator Greenwood, who was unanimously elected<br />
as Deputy Chairman of the Standing Committee.<br />
Standing Committee consists of:<br />
Mr E. G. Whitlam and Senator I. J. Greenwood ( Federal Parliament),<br />
Sir Robert Askin and Mr P. D. Hills Mr R. J. Hamer and<br />
Mr A. C. Holding ( Victoria), Sir Gordon Chalk and Mr J. W. Houston<br />
( Queensland), Mr D. A. Dunstan and Dr B. C. Eastick ( South Australia)<br />
Mr A. D. Taylor and Sir Charles Court ( Western Australia)<br />
Mr R. Mather and Mr C. B. M. Fenton ( Tasmania), Mr J. H. Pead<br />
and Cr F. A. Rogers and Ald Clem Jones ( Local Government).<br />
All members of the Committee were represented except<br />
Mr P. D. Hills of N. S. W. Sir Robert Askin was represented by the<br />
Hon. E. A. Willis, Minister for Education, New South Wales.<br />
The Committee considered reports from the four working<br />
parties appointed at the last meeting, and gave directions t1-o the<br />
working parties as to the areas in which they should concentrate<br />
their studies with a view to a report being given to the Executive<br />
Committee before April 30th of this year.<br />
CANBERRAJ~. A. C. T. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
