<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5963</transcript-id>
    <title>DEATH OF MR BREZHNEV</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/11/1982</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005963.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MEDIA RELEASE DEATH OF MR BREZHNEV<br />
Statement by the Acting Prime Minister<br />
the Rt Hon. Anthony, M. P.<br />
I have been informed today of the death of<br />
President Brezhnev of the Soviet Union, and on behalf of<br />
the Australian Government, I extend my condolences to the<br />
Government of the Soviet Union and the late President's<br />
family. As leader of the Soviet Union in the past 18<br />
years, President Brezhnev has faced awesome responsibilities<br />
both to his own people and to all mankind. His period in<br />
power, on its own, is a remarkable achievement in today's<br />
world. In this time he has sought to improve the living<br />
conditions of the Soviet people. He has also sought to<br />
promote the notion of detente in international co-operation.<br />
It has to be said, however, that under President<br />
Brezhnev, the Soviet Union's military strength and the<br />
projection of Soviet power has reached unprecedented levels,<br />
and in recent times, has given rise to serious tensions<br />
and uncertainty. Czechoslovakia, Afghanistan and, more<br />
recently, the tragedy of Poland, are testimony to the<br />
policies for which President Brezhnev and his associates<br />
will be remembered. The Australian Government sincerely hopes that<br />
for the good of all people, the new leaders in Moscow will<br />
sincerely follow the path of peace which the late President<br />
Brezhnev frequently claimed as his country's policy. There<br />
will be enormous benefit to all mankind if this can come<br />
about.<br />
CANBERRA 11 November 1982. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
