<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7992</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY ANNA MCMAHON ON BRISBANE CHANNEL 10 - 22/03/90</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1990</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007992.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF PRIME MINISTER INTERVIEWED BY ANNA MCKAHON ON<br />
BRISBANE CHANNEL 10 22/ 03190.<br />
E 0 Z Proof only.<br />
AM$ The countdown has started, just forty-eight hours to go.<br />
At that point history will be made Andrew Peacock will be<br />
Australia's 17th Prime Minister or Bob Hawke will take the Labor<br />
Party to a record fourth term, On Monday we spoke to Opposition<br />
leader Andrew Peacock when the key issues confronting the<br />
electorate were the environment and, of course, the M. FP. Today<br />
it's back to the main underlying theme of the whole campaign, the<br />
economy. Joining us now in Prime Minister Bob Hawke, thank you<br />
very much for your time Prime Minister. First off on the<br />
economy and the threat of recession we're hearing fromi a number<br />
of economic pundits, the latest December figures you're happy<br />
about them, your Treasurer's even described them as " beautiful"<br />
but isn't the fact of the matter that the people that count, the<br />
people in the electorate, they're just hurting too much?<br />
PM: Well let's just look at the figures. There is no basis on<br />
the figures for saying that we're in a recession because what has<br />
happened, and what needed to happen, is that we've got the<br />
community's consumption and production havo moved into balance,<br />
Before we were just consuming much more than we were producing<br />
and that was causing us problems externally. So, what the<br />
banking industry is saylig now, Anna, is as a result of these<br />
changes if we are returned on Saturday interest rates w4.11 fall<br />
and the hurt that certainly has been experienced by a lot of your<br />
viewers, that will be eased then with a tall in rates.<br />
Aid: But you are admitting that a lot of people have been hurt<br />
and they've been hurting badly haven't they?<br />
PM: Anna I've never denied it. ' I maid it in my policy upeoch<br />
in Brisbane that we had a situation.' where the economy was growing<br />
that strongly and we were in fact importing that much that we<br />
couldn't keep that. I had the responsibility an Prime Minister<br />
5f1 this country of making a tough decision. I could have just<br />
said oh let it go and it we had the whole economy would havo<br />
collapsed completely as it did'before under the Liberals. I said<br />
no we're going to have to have tight monetary policy for a while<br />
but that's now done it's Job. No one, you know, worries more<br />
than I do about the fact that it has hurt people but I would have<br />
been irresponsible if I hadn't slowed the economy down somewhat.<br />
AMS Prime Minister, you mightn't be talking about a recession </p>
<p>w 2<br />
AM ( cont) but the fact of the matter is someO of our* leading<br />
bankers and economists are, takce Nobby Clark for example, who<br />
today certainly poured a lot of cold water on your interest rate<br />
hope. PM: Yes, well I don't take any notice of nobby Clark as a<br />
political commentator. As far as the market as a whole is<br />
concerned, Anna, just let<br />
AN: But the fact of the matter is he is still one of<br />
Australia's leading bankers.<br />
PM: And an identified Tory supporter. I mean he has no<br />
independence when it comes to political judgments or political<br />
9 bcaonmkmeernst. s . Lot Im'ell givreea dyo ut ow hayto uw, asi f on yotuh e wRaenutt, ercso msmcureenetsn , frAonmn a, th eI<br />
mean here is, talking for the market as a whole, just let me<br />
briefly read this, just two days * go: " Traders said credi. t<br />
markets ended the day firmer in anticipation of a further easing<br />
in monetary policy in the next few weeks, assuming" this is the<br />
market " assuming the Hawke Labor Government is re-elected at<br />
Saturday's Federal electiona. in other words, what the market is<br />
saying is as a result of interest rates having done it's Job and<br />
slowed the economy down, if we are returned then interest rates<br />
will come off. That's what the market an a whole is saying.<br />
Now Nobby Clark is throwing in his Attila the Hun comments, not<br />
the language of an independent observer.<br />
AM$ Prime Minister there's certainly been a lot of toeing and<br />
freing over interest rates throughout this whole campaign....<br />
PM: Not by us.,.<br />
AM., Well by a lot of other people.<br />
PH: YOR.<br />
AM: Would it be fair to call you Mr Two Percent after your slip<br />
earlier this week. is that figure reality?<br />
PM1 Not, no I've made it quite clear. I mean this is an<br />
e* ercise in history. What I said is that I got into a<br />
parenthesis of comment by John Howard. I have said all through<br />
the campaign and I had said the same day and I say today that<br />
there are two things that are importantl one that we've got the<br />
policies in place to bring about sustained reduction in interest<br />
rates; and secondly, and more importantly, that the banking<br />
industry is saying, as I have just read out to you some excerpts,<br />
the banking industry is saying that in fact rates will come down<br />
under my Government if we're re-elected. And that the extent of </p>
<p>-3<br />
PM ( cont) I the fall will be a matter for decision by the<br />
banking industry, But, against that, it LB certain that interest<br />
rates would have to rise under the opposition because they would<br />
have A a wages explosion, and B they would blow the budget<br />
surplus that we've built up.<br />
AM: For the first time in this election campaign the latest<br />
opinion polls have put the Coalition ahead of the ALP do you<br />
think you have been too tough on the electorate?<br />
PM: Absolutely not right, I mean, with respect Anna# get your<br />
facts right, that simply is not the case....<br />
AX. They are the latest opinion polls released today.<br />
PKI Yes and I'm saying that you're referring to the Morgan poll<br />
which in terms of two-party preferred votes when the preferences<br />
of the non-major parties are distributed, would have Labor<br />
winning. That's what comes out of that poll. That is one poll.<br />
All the other polls in fact show Labor in front on primary votes.<br />
Now I'm not ther'efore saying, Anna, that I've got to be<br />
complacent. On the contrary, I think it is a tight election,<br />
I've Baid that right from day one of the election and, there's<br />
not much time left but I'll be fighting hard right up until<br />
tomorrow night.<br />
All: In fact really it's the closest election in the history of<br />
Australia isn't it<br />
PM: Oh no, I mean it's very hard to say it's the closest<br />
election in the history of Australia. in 1961 we had an election<br />
which was decided on 92 commuunist preference votes in the seat of<br />
Moreton in Queensland, I don't think it will be that tight.<br />
9AM: Okay but it's certainly an exceedingly tight election.<br />
PM1 Oh yea, it's a tight election....<br />
AM: And It's going to be won or lost on preferenves isn't it?<br />
PM: Well it will be on preferences, I don't think there is any<br />
d~ ubt about that. See, one of the things that's happened in<br />
political life in this country, and indeed around the world Anna,<br />
Is that people have become very interested in environmental<br />
issues, and I'm very glad they have. And if I can just make<br />
this point Anna that a num~ ber of people in this country are so<br />
concerned about the environment that they're going to asL their<br />
first vote for either Democrats or Green candidates to show their<br />
interest in the environment. Now all I'm saying to those people<br />
well that of course is your right to do that, but if your real </p>
<p>-4<br />
PM ( cant) concern is the environment then you must make sure<br />
that your second preference goes to zabor because our record on<br />
the environment, as the environment movement hasS said, is head<br />
and shoulders above the Coalition.<br />
AM: Mr Hawke still on the environment but if we could move on<br />
to the local issue of Fraser island, what's your position?<br />
Should logging continue or should it stop?<br />
PM:. Our position is that we understand that the Queonsland<br />
Government has set up the inquiry. We'll be making submissions<br />
to that. my own disposition is when I look, at Fraser Island to,<br />
you know not like the idea of logging, what we'll be doing is,<br />
howcver, putting our position to the Inquiry and in the light of<br />
what comes out of that the consideration will be undertaken<br />
between us and the Queensland Government about world Heritage<br />
values and what is the appropriate course of action.<br />
AM: But personally you would like to see logging banned?<br />
PM: It I think Fraser Island is a magnificent place, I don't<br />
want to intrude, you know, a personal position and I think that<br />
the Queensland Government has acted wisely in setting up the<br />
Inquiry. They've got Mr Fitzgerald to do that and I'm sure that<br />
the Inquiry will be very efficiently and impartially undertaken<br />
and we will want to participate in putting positions before it.<br />
I think Mr Goes hag acted wisely in this.<br />
AM: Mr Hawke if I could move back to the campaign itself. How<br />
tough has it been for you personally?<br />
P14: Well, campaigns are always tough Anna, particularly when<br />
you put yourself into it heart and soul as I do. But I would<br />
have to say in one respect this campaign has been a little easier<br />
than previous ones in that we haven't had the same large number<br />
of fund-raising dinners at night. They can take a lot out of you<br />
emotionally. I mean you have hundreds of people there and I<br />
always make a point, Anna# of going,.; round and shaking hands with<br />
everyone individually and there's a* lot of autograph signing.<br />
That takes a fair bit of energy out of you. There haven't been<br />
so many of those at night so in that respect, and In that respect<br />
afo-ne, it's been an easier campaign than in the past but I've<br />
been going f lat out and I'll certainly be glad when it comes to<br />
an and. I hope the people of Australia will share a view I<br />
expressed when I called the campaign that there is no way we<br />
could have had the election in may. We would have, as I said,<br />
gone collectively bonkers if we'd been in an election mode until<br />
May. AM: Prime Minister will Queensland make the difference between </p>
<p>AM ( Cont) s you winning or losing?<br />
PM1 I think the relevance of Queensland is this that, firstly,<br />
Federally we hold a majority of the seats I think it's 13 out<br />
of the 24 Queensland seats, we hold just a majority, I think we<br />
have a possibility of winning additional seats i. n Queensland.<br />
That's going to be important and, therefore, Queensland has that<br />
significance.<br />
AM: Mr Hawke, yesterday at the National Press conference you<br />
said there wasn room to lift your game. You're coming into a<br />
fourth term, what would you do differently that you've done the<br />
last three times?<br />
PM: Well I think that if a person is intelligent and he's got<br />
integrity and he says I'm perfect I can't improve, then he's a<br />
caue for, you know, for the psychiatrists. I mean i just beli. eve<br />
that XI'm a wiser person now than I was when i became Prime<br />
Minister. I'd be a bloody fool if I wasn't, I mean I've had the<br />
opportunity of being exposed to an enormous amount of information<br />
about Australia, about what's happening in the world. I work<br />
very hard, I try and absorb all that information economic,<br />
political, strategic and so just as I learn more I am able to<br />
apply that accumulation of knowledge in an effective way I hope.<br />
AM: Hr Hawke, thank you for your time.<br />
MN It's been a pleasure Anna, thank you very much indeed.<br />
Ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
