<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7091</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, KING DAVIS HOTEL, JERSALEM, 29 JANUARY 1987</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/01/1987</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007091.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, KING DAVID HOTEL. JERUSALEM,<br />
29 JANUARY 1987 E 0 E PROOF ONLY<br />
JOURNALIST: WagJt did Mr Peres have to say-whfl You repeated. I<br />
what you had to say earlier in the day about the PLO and<br />
Israel reocg s~ ingech th<br />
PM: I think the fullness of the discussions I had with Mr Peres<br />
on that subject are appropriately left to us at this point. Suffice<br />
to say that he completely understood the sense in which I put those<br />
propositions. JOURNALIST: Did he raise with you the possibility of when you<br />
are next dealing with the United States that you could make approaches<br />
concerning them getting involved in the peace processes again?<br />
PM: We talked about the involvement Of the United States in-the<br />
peace process. You shud' htthe United States is not involved<br />
JOURNALIST: What do you mean<br />
PM: It wasn't meant to be an esoteric comment. The United States<br />
is aware of the processes that have been going on. I think the<br />
correct thing to say is that the United States doesn't have the<br />
high profile in those processes as historically you have come to<br />
associate with them.<br />
JOURNALIST: Was there a marked difference in the style of your<br />
talks with Mr Peres and the way he approached this issue and the<br />
approach of Mr Shamir?<br />
PM: They were later in the evening and I guess it is obvious that<br />
because I have known Mr Peres now the friendship goes back to<br />
1971 to my first visit to Israel. And we are of the same political<br />
persuasion so there is a greater camraderie between Mr Peres and<br />
myself. JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you said the discussions could you explain<br />
that? PM: No, I can't.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, did you ask Mr Peres about Israel's alleged<br />
arms sales to South Africa<br />
PM: Yes, we had a discussion about that and Mr Peres gave me a<br />
fairly lengthy exposition. Again all the details of which I am<br />
not at this stage in a position to talk about because I want to<br />
discuss that matter with my colleagues on my return. But let me<br />
say this that Mr Peres assured me that Israel would associate itself<br />
with any international decisions taken on the question of South<br />
AFrica. And that Israel totally abhorred and repudiated apartheid. </p>
<p>2.<br />
PM cont: As to some of the detail of that area of discussion I<br />
will want to talk with my colleagues about that before I say anything<br />
more. JOURNALIST: Did you leave your talks with Mr Peres more confident<br />
that Israel and the PLO may sometime, in the near future down<br />
to some sort of recognition?<br />
PM: I think the correct way to put it is this, Greg. Mr Peres<br />
in no sense disputed the analysis that I made. Indeed, it accorded<br />
essential I y i-ththe-things--thathe-has-been-saingb4ims lf.-But<br />
there must be uncertainties as to what the PLO will say about the<br />
essential elements of the position, that is the acceptance of 242.<br />
and--338-the--right of, srael-to--existT--And-wtthn-th-at-fr e-amewDrkof<br />
course the non-use of terror. There must be some question as<br />
what the processes of decision-making are within the PLO to reach<br />
that point and how long it will take. Now there may be letArephrase<br />
that there would be differences of opinion amongst any number<br />
of people that you want to ask on that issue as to how long it<br />
might take. But as to the essentiality of that process and agreement<br />
as to the reciprocal, that is that in those circumstances an<br />
obligation on the part of Israel to recognise the right of the<br />
PLO to be involved in the processes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, did you enquire where the case against<br />
Mordechai Vanunu was up to?<br />
PM: I merely informed Mr Peres of--the discussioh-that l-have had<br />
with the Foreign Minister on that. There was, as I indicated in<br />
an earlier conference, I was satisfied with answer the Prime Minister<br />
had given, that is and let me repeat it. Firstly, that Mr Vanunu<br />
was receiving normal treatment. And secondly, that indeed he was<br />
given special treatment of being allowed to be visited by his American<br />
woman friend which was against the norma procedures. And I informed<br />
Mr Peres that that is what the Prime MInister had told. It is<br />
not a question of confirming it, but yes that is what is happening.<br />
And so there was not point in any further discussion.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what did Mr Peres say about Soviet<br />
participation in the international conference?<br />
PM: Mr Peres confirmed that his adherence to the commitment that<br />
he gave in the discussions with Mr Mubarak that is that there was<br />
a place for an international conference and that as far as the<br />
Soviet Union was concerned that he had nominated the two conditions<br />
that is the recognition by the Soviet Union of Israel in terms<br />
of the resumption of diplomatic relations. And the second thing<br />
the change in the treatment by the Soviet. Union of Soviet Jewry.<br />
Let me, as you raised the question of the international conference,<br />
make it clear that it is the endorsement of the concept of an<br />
international conference Mr Peres reaffirmed his view on the nature<br />
of that international conference, that is that it oould not impose<br />
the resolution of the issues on the parties directly involved.<br />
And necessary definition from that. In fact, it would be a<br />
matter for direct negotiation between the parties under the framework<br />
of such a conference. Indeed, you will appreciate from what I<br />
have said following my discussions with King Hussein and the Prime<br />
MInister of Jordan that the position as to the nature of the<br />
conference is the D t i{ L -Ai44? A<br />
w. </p>
<p>9<br />
9 3.<br />
JOURNAL[ ST: Would you say that Mr Peres was satisfied with<br />
the impressions you brought with you from your talks with King<br />
Hussein and the Prime Minister in Amman?<br />
PM: Yes indeed. I think it confirmed the judgement that Shimon<br />
had himself made but it was, I think, reassuring to have so recently<br />
and so explicitly a statement about his positions.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, do you have any more information about the<br />
Sharon visit?<br />
-No. I don-t--oth-er-than -that; and--am-assum-i ng-that' -y-ou-ftav-e<br />
heard this, that I understand that the actual dates that Mr Sharon<br />
unilaterally announced seem not to be capable of being fitted-into<br />
Mr Dawkins' agenda.<br />
JOURNALIST: He is going though, isn't he?<br />
PM: I assumie that once our Minister has said that the dates that<br />
Mr Sharon announced were not suitable to him Mr Dawkins there<br />
will be further discussions between them and that is where the<br />
matter rests as I understand it.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, now that you are about to leave Israel<br />
have you achieved what you hoped to achieve? What is the overview?<br />
PM: Yes, I have achieved what I wanted to do and that was to be<br />
as well informed as I possibly could of the attitudes and positions<br />
parties principle. I have been to Jordan and I couldn't have beev%<br />
given a more fullsome, detailed, frank exposition of their position.<br />
I believe that has now been reciprocated, if I can use that word,<br />
here in Israel now that I have had the opportunity of having very<br />
long talks with the Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister.<br />
I have, I think, as clear an understandimq now anyone from the<br />
world outside the parties directly involved what these positions<br />
are. And having said that, I repeat what I said at the outset<br />
that I didn't come to offer myself as a mediator. I think that<br />
as a result of what I have learned I am extremely well equipped<br />
to go into the discussions with President Mubarak. By that I mean<br />
that because of what I have been told by Jordan and Israel I will<br />
be very well equipped to understand and ask the appropriate<br />
questions of President Mubarak so that I will be totally understanding<br />
of the position of Egypt. I simply repeat that at the endp of<br />
of those processes which may I say also included a very valuable<br />
opportunity of listening to representatives of the<br />
Palestinian people in Jerusalem. At the end of all that there<br />
is a view that there may be some things that we could do to help<br />
the processes of peace. And reaffirm the strength, as I said at<br />
the beginning, that we would be prepared to do that.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
