<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>340</transcript-id>
    <title>LIBERAL PARTY RALLY, LAUNCESTON - 5TH JULY, 1961 - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>05/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000340_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
61/ 041<br />
LIBERAL PARTY RALLY, LAUNCESTON<br />
_ Jthu ly, 1961<br />
Speech by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies<br />
Sir, Senators, members, prospective members, ladies and gentlemen:<br />
I want to tell you that I really feel that I am here<br />
under false pretences, Among the insinuating qualities bhat the<br />
Chairman has is one of leading you on. When Icpencddmy sheet of<br />
paper you know we always get a sheet of paper when we are<br />
travelling I thought that we wjre going to stand around, and<br />
that I was to speak for 10 minutes. However I will probably havo<br />
to talk a little longer.<br />
I think perhaps I ought to begin by saying that I have<br />
a very soft spot in me for anybody who will undertake to win<br />
. ilmot. I have never understood why we lost !! ilmot; I've never<br />
understood why we haven't won ' Jilmot back; and now that I see two<br />
candidates, and havo heard them, jointly and severally engaged in<br />
the good work I begin to have hope that good judgment will come<br />
back to . ilmo this ye: r. Because, really, Wilmot ought to be<br />
represented by somebody of cons. quence. ( Applause)<br />
As for Bass, well I take my hat off to Brownie<br />
Marriott. ( Applause) You see this is a perfect example of<br />
example being better than precept. Here he is, an eminently<br />
respectable member of the Tasmanian Parliament, likely, under the<br />
deep mysteries of the Hare-Clark voting system ( Laughter) to<br />
remain a member of the Tasmanian Parliament forever, or so long as<br />
life lasts: and he turns his back on this rather verdant prospect<br />
and says, " I'll have a crack at Bass". And good luck to him.<br />
( Applause) But if there is one thing that stings me a little it is<br />
that it isn't so long ago that wo held four of those seats out of<br />
five. iJe have, at one time or another, in imy period at Canberra,<br />
held each of the five. Today we hold two. This is not good<br />
enough. Do you know this really makes Tasmania a rather<br />
backward State, the one State I say this to you quite frankly<br />
in which the decline of our political fortun-s in the Federal<br />
field has been so remarkable.<br />
Now whose Cault is that? You can't say it's iay fault<br />
entirely bccuse I'm the Prime Minister of all the States and it<br />
hasn't happened in other places: it hasn't happened in<br />
Queensland; it hasn't tappened in Victoria; it hasn't happened<br />
in Jeostern Australia. It has happened hero. Perhaps the reason<br />
for it is that in a smaller couunity we know each other so well<br />
that we are mor. conscious of each other's faults, than we are of<br />
the virtues of the other mane " Oh, so-and-so, I know him well; I<br />
was at school with him. Oh, he's just an ordinary fellow, yes"<br />
And having disposed of your own man on that basis you then vote<br />
for somebody who is practically a half-wit' ( Laughter, applause)<br />
And it won't do; it won't do. If there is one thing<br />
I want to say tonight it is to seek to recall this State, this<br />
favourite State of mine, as you know, in a personal way, to<br />
recall this State to a sense of its own pride and responsibility.<br />
It is your simple duty to give back, in the Federal Parliament,<br />
Braddon, i-ilmot, Bass, to the Govcrnont. And it can be done if<br />
everybody in this Hall tonight and there are not so many of us<br />
said " This is my great objective for 1961". It co uld be done.<br />
There is nothing that can't be done by enthusiastic supporters;<br />
there is n. thing that can't be undone by feeble friends, the kind<br />
of friends who say " Oh, yes, " Yus, but" won't put thesn </p>
<p>boys, or oither of then, into Parliamnnt; " Yes, but" won't put<br />
Brownie Marriott in as mr., bor for Bass. Of course not.<br />
You can't have this qualifici support. This I believe<br />
is an occasion, for reasons that Denhan Henty has mentioned, when<br />
nothing but the warnest support will do, because if we can't win<br />
our full quota of scats in the Sonate and we won't do that<br />
unless we win in the Lower House then, although after the<br />
Election we will still be in Office, I don't doubt it for a<br />
morment, we will have the serious risks of having a Senate of which<br />
we don't have coimand. What happens then? We are entering a<br />
period of great economic troubles; oven more so we are entering<br />
a period of im. onso international problems and complications, so<br />
imnmoise that I hardly care to think about them except in private.<br />
Fancy having a Government at Canberra, the Government of the<br />
nation, the only Govornment that ropresents Australia in the<br />
Councils of the , orld, rendered frustrated and futile by a hostile<br />
Senate. I had this once you know, when you were first good<br />
enough to send me back into Office at the end of 1949 we had a<br />
big hostile majority in the Senate. And right through 1950, and<br />
the first half of 1951, we were in trouble constantly. We<br />
couldn't got a Bill through the Senate; we were always liable to<br />
have . ny of our measurus just pushed asid,, made to look foolish;<br />
we woro being rendured, in the public mind, futile not because<br />
we woro futile, but because we didn't have a rmajority in the<br />
Senate. Thereforo I began that now classical series of<br />
movements which brought about the d. uble dissolution of 1951, a<br />
double dissolution which the learned gentlemen of the Opposition,<br />
including your famous ox-Tasnanian Sonator said c:) uld not be done.<br />
But it was done. And we got a double dissolution. And we cane<br />
back with a rLajority in both houses.<br />
So that our real period, you know, of authoritative<br />
Government didn't begin at the end of ' 49; it began, because of<br />
these reasons, in the niddle of ' 51. That is why it is, in<br />
reality, 10 years old, although by the end of this year the<br />
Government itself will be 12 years old. Dut in trrms of<br />
effective adinistrative authority and legislative corinand, and<br />
an authoritative v-oice in the rest of the world, 10 years. But<br />
it night h: ve been 11-.<br />
Now I beg of you, don't let that happen again. You know<br />
the business of th. e Governu-nt of a nation is troeendously<br />
inportant. You have to ovtoe your days and nights to it, you<br />
have to concentrate all the intelligence that can be marshalled in<br />
order to deal with the oroblemr. s of a nati. on in this cormplox,<br />
. odern world. A lot of your friends think you are righft;<br />
even rore ny think you are wrong. But the fact is that you<br />
ca! not ( do the job as it ought to be done if you are devoting your<br />
attention to side issues, to the eochanics of staying in office,<br />
to the mechanics of conducting a. anoeuvre so that the Senate<br />
won't be able to frustrato y: ou. Look if you don't mind no<br />
saying so, I speak with oxport knowledge on this mattor. I have<br />
had more oxperience of this kind of thing than any other living<br />
political loader. T can r.. neranbr when I -was first Prime<br />
Minister, which will be beyond the memory of some of you, in 1939,<br />
trying to conduct a Gov. rnront which was a minority Government<br />
because the Country Party w. ulln't play, and sat on the crossbenchos.<br />
' henover I went back to the L. d)* c on Friday evening<br />
when the House was up, my wife would say " Joll how are things<br />
going?" ind I w: uld say, " My dear, we arle safe until T1uesday".<br />
( Laughter) Lo. kin. back on it, it sens funny doesn't it? But<br />
living thr: ugh it it didn't soem funny because it rmeant thot<br />
of your time was being devoted to political exorcises which no<br />
Govornment in a tim! e of great national importance ought to be<br />
roeuired to engago in. There is no m:-% re copletIo way in which </p>
<p>you can avoid these unhappy results than by taking this wonderful<br />
opportunity that now presents itself in Tasmania, or that will,<br />
at the end of the year, to win back these throe seats all of<br />
which ought to be ours, and to give us a majority in he Senate<br />
which I believe we will need in this State if we are to have one<br />
in the Senate as a whole.<br />
Now having said that to you I just want to mention,<br />
quite briefly, two or three other aspects of the affairs that we<br />
have been odaling with. Mr. Thonas said, very rightly, that he<br />
hoped that in this tine, the period of economic difficulties, the<br />
position of the primary industries w:, uld not be overlooked. Now<br />
of course, as he knows, we have been extraordinarily conscious of<br />
this problen. I said something about it last night in speaking at<br />
Burnie. What can be done for the primary industries in terns of<br />
taxation measures, and so on, has long since been done by us, far<br />
more than for any other aspect of industry. But we believe that<br />
hard as inflation is upon oll people with fixed incomes, it bears<br />
most cruelly on rural industry. They can't pass their costs onto<br />
somebody else, unless they are very lucky and live in a little<br />
closed market. The wool industry has been referred to. This is<br />
the great industry of Australia, the industry of all industries<br />
upon which our international solvency depends; which enables us<br />
to buy from the rest of the world all the things that we need. I<br />
wonder if I might put it to you in this way. If the wool industry<br />
in Australia were blotted out tomorrow and we no longer had an<br />
inco: me from woo, hardly a manufacturer in iAustralia would fail to<br />
receive a violent blow. Because, of all the imports that cone<br />
into Australia, 60, 70%, maybe more, are imports on behalf of<br />
manufacturers raw materials, plant, all these things. And yet<br />
of all the export income that we earn with which to pay for our<br />
imports, a high percentage, perhaps 40%, sometimes 50% is earned<br />
by the wool industry of Australia.' So all you have to do is to<br />
abolish our wool income and you can write an end to our present<br />
high and happy state of living, our high and happy state of<br />
national development. These are important facts to h: ive in mind. WJe must<br />
never lose sight of them. -de don't want to soc the wool industry<br />
subsidised: this would be the crowning folly, wouldn't it, of<br />
national economic history, to subsidise the wool industry? Who<br />
subsidises whom? It will be a problem, won't it, in due course.<br />
do don't want to be subsidising other primary industries which<br />
produce, primarily, for export to the rest of the world. But if<br />
we are not going to, then we must take groat pains to see that<br />
their costs are not added to by a high and rising inflationary<br />
pressure. The greatest sufferers in an inflationary boom in<br />
Australia are the men who produce from the soil for export. Now I<br />
say that as a member for a metropolitan seat. I haven't the<br />
faintest doubt that this is the truth. But of course the moment<br />
you begin to attack inflation then the fun begins. How do you<br />
attack inflation? Nobody denies that in 1960, last year we had<br />
an inflationary boom. I occasionally indulge myself in the luxury<br />
of reading " Our Ecnomist", or something, in a newspaper or " Our<br />
Financial Editor", in a newspaper, or " Our Commentator" in a<br />
newspaper. I read them all for they are most readable most<br />
readable. They usually disagree with each other by and lge; but<br />
anyhow there is no harm done by reading them. Not one of them<br />
denies that in 1960, this last calendar year, we were confronting<br />
an inflationary boon, shortages of labour. People are always<br />
willing to tell mo that there are a hundred thousand people<br />
registered f) r employment, or whatever it nay be; and of course<br />
I don't want that to happen. But they don't tell me that last<br />
year the position was exactly the opp. site, that to get labour<br />
you had to bid up, and pay oxt'a rates over the awards, you had </p>
<p>to buy people's servicos by heav'y ovortdrae. t) uito rightly, when<br />
people aro scaC2' ce in coi... paroison wJitht s tthiyi ~~ r pce<br />
That is good priivate ent( riprise rnips. But i~ t doe), sn't reduce<br />
the costs of pr-ocUIction in industry; it doesn't red-' uce the costs<br />
of the man tt'h e land. i. J ho: n he finds that it cost-Is imr ano; ther<br />
2d7 3d, 4+ d, 501. to produce a pound of wool he can't say to himself<br />
" Mark it up to the public" to the sane extent, because he ca~ n't.<br />
He sells his wool by auction; heo gets what the world will give<br />
him. A" nd I want to make it qu-ite clear to you that wej live in a<br />
world in wbhicl our grea&amp;, test nati.. nal or: oducts ' on tho wor-ld market<br />
receive the s &gt;" cThey ma~ y be -roo. ll theyo nay be moat,<br />
they maybe ase rnt,: 0s -incirensingly ip,-itant ut~ a<br />
including thie no--ferz'eus :: Iotals b LIt -ih y reu2 tU .; 1K0 Vcorld<br />
will give fo-r thrro,. I f You lift z ho. cost of10?. 2~ in o o<br />
by having a rierry, inflationary hol41iday, theon yo.. u will end b<br />
destroying the.<br />
Now I an an old : oolitic-al sweat and qulte, franly I<br />
have got to a stare of lifa Jhen I an-not4--AT to cry 7 a, f to<br />
sloocp if somobod:. k,-icks me out. Ilve, bee,-b. r a. lrng to. Bat<br />
I would resign rlmy job if I -didn't th. ink i hono) ujh guits in<br />
no to stand up to-an inflati. inaW-probleii and, D htIto<br />
was the right thh t d bot t ( dpplaase)<br />
Xc~ w tK _ ro is sonoithin7 rat! ' or c. orortable about<br />
inflation. It's -er-ofitabeI~ from, the oitof view. of somle<br />
people. I u-a'dersC-nd that: more oolrigpic level, more<br />
turnover theIse UThings have tho ir getatato; Btte<br />
have no attiractio-n wha-IIIeor for pople vhoso iqe-Io-nes are<br />
reatively fixocd, no attraction uhate. ver for people viho are<br />
living on sup) re: -.-uati-Dn, or pension benefits, no attraction<br />
whatever for po; ewho have pr. ovided for theimselves by<br />
investments on f -ed rates of interest, as so rmanv people havo,<br />
nco attractio) n wl) hatever for the holders of over f-l, OO0m, worta of<br />
Savings Bank del) o: sits in i', ustralia. They don't want inflation.<br />
ndin order to deoal with inflation you must hit it quite<br />
violently on the heoad, yo-u mustn't be toe p) ollto about it, you<br />
must bring it to a hajt, I notice thiat everybody now concedes<br />
thiat we have, tL. tth..' bo-m has passe d ever, that land<br />
sp culation has fallent back to a ver-7 remr.-.. kable de ree0 I don't<br />
find many people who Idony TShat. But we st.. 1 ' have pe) ople who will<br />
say to and no ' Dou:-ot say to y Ibrother candidates hare on the<br />
platform in due course, th-. at the cause of all, tho, tro) uble is<br />
" lthle crendit squeeze". It is o) ne of those beaut-iful uexpressions.<br />
I don't thiink too -, any ople, except a few business men, know<br />
what it -moans. But I will explain it to) yo) u in one paragraph.<br />
You havo an inflatio--, nary b om: when there is miore money<br />
av. oilable to be spent than there are goodr)( s and services available<br />
to be bo-ught. 1When that hiapp-ens the-: price of everything ; OOJS LIP<br />
thec price of labour, if it's labour that is short; the price<br />
of m~ aterials, if it's matorials that are sho rt. ldhatovor it may<br />
be, yoju can't halvo two people with the moneny in theair hands<br />
competing for one lot of supply without seeoing the price go up.<br />
Of course if you are dealing, with such a, situation yo) u are going<br />
to m.-ake an coemy of one or other, or perhaps both, of the two<br />
buyers. Theiy say, " This is terrible, this is terrible. You<br />
should have allowed us to geo ahead in the ordinary way". You make<br />
an enemy of the fello. w who has the , oods to sell beca. use he was<br />
contemplating-: etting a fancy price for them in an inflated<br />
market. I understand thant; I didn't conic Joivn_ in the la., st<br />
showcr. But the interests of the ordIInary peep of Alustralia<br />
a-cc pnramount. You vote, th-a Labour TParty O.. ffice at i-he end<br />
of the year as I said t. uwill bn,, toa.,_ S y pi) lw you<br />
-vio then-in and the infI ,--, nary iofn l9( 2D . they ~ aa<br />
of thi-: ir pror. ises, lie n h gto thc fI'-, ncial õ . ateu<br />
th,( at will ove,, rtake this couantry wlt , in six m MYUtis of theirL<br />
arrival. 4. pplause) </p>
<p>Now, Sir having said that I wonder if I could just<br />
answer quite briefly, two points thai have been put to no and I<br />
am sure have been put to some of my colleagues from tino to tino.<br />
First, somebody will say to you, " Yes, well of course we know the<br />
Govornment has this great probluem and we are great supporters of<br />
the Governnent, you know, but why do you change your minds so<br />
much? None of us knows what is going to happen next." Now that<br />
is good Labour propaganda and I an surprised when I find any<br />
Liberal falling for it. " Why do you change your minds so nuch?"<br />
You know you would think that managing money and credit in a<br />
cormmunity was child's play. , J11 you have to know is the seven<br />
tines table and put a competent clerk on the job and leave it to<br />
him. In Groat Britain which doesn't have a Federal system,<br />
in which the central Governent has uninhibited power over any<br />
subject that you care to mention, there is the Bank of England in<br />
the middle of the structure, like our Reserve Bank, formerly the<br />
Commonwealth Bank. But the Bank of England, lot's say, announces<br />
tomorrow that the bank rate has boon changed, raised 1% or 1%,<br />
the Bank discount rate on first class bills. The effect of that<br />
right through the economy, right through the business centres of<br />
London, right through the financial centres of Great Britain is<br />
instant, and draatic. Wo have no such power in Australia. But<br />
when the bank rate is raised in IMrch and l. wered in July, and<br />
raised again in October, and lowered again in January I have never<br />
yet heard anybody say in England " What a lot of boobies they are<br />
at the Bank of England, they don't know their own minds, they are<br />
always changing their minds". I would hate to go to sea with a<br />
navigator in a rough sea who gave the helmsman the course and<br />
said " I'm going to bed, that's fixed, because it would never do<br />
for me to change my mind". That would be a horrible way of going<br />
to King Island judging by what I saw of it the other day.<br />
( Laughter) Any competent people must be prepared, not to change the<br />
broad course; and our policy is quite simple: we want stability,<br />
economically in Australia, and development on the basis of<br />
stability. But when it comes to applying policy you would be<br />
foolish if you ignored changes of wind, changes of the sea<br />
particular storns that arise, particular circurstances that arise,<br />
very few of which are created inside / iustralia but which affect<br />
us for a very simpile reason, nuch overlooked, that we don't<br />
happen to be the only country in the world. No are, in fact, a<br />
very small country in terms of numbers. But we are a great<br />
trading nation; and we are affected by the wild currents of world<br />
economic events, and of wor. ld trading crises, and so on, just as<br />
much as countries 10 tilns the size of ustralia. Therefore you<br />
muEt expect some variations of application of policy as<br />
circumstances change.<br />
You know, of course, I am a very great admirer of the<br />
newspaper press. It seldom gets what I say right ( Laughter) but<br />
still, no doubt it has a part to play in these matters. They<br />
always have in a newspaper office a gentlemen whose task it is to<br />
write the headlines. Deliver me from head lines. You can make a<br />
prosaic, simple statement of the kind that I characteristically<br />
make and when you see the headline that is put on it you say,<br />
" Did I say that?"<br />
Now it happens that last November when we were<br />
bringing down a few additional economic easur. s, all of which I<br />
firmly believe were quite right and well justified, we gave<br />
thought to whether we iight strengthen our overseas reserves. I<br />
don't want to be too technical about this matter but the nation<br />
has balances overseas which are the result, partly, of the sale<br />
of exports, partly the result of borrowing overseas, or investments<br />
by people overseas, and these overseas reserves of ours must, at </p>
<p>any given timne, be ) retty subs tant-ial. I won't give it a<br />
preciso. i~ r butl coer i-y e n offico. I , i-ve never been very<br />
happy to have theo ove rso as r, s,; rvos loss than F. 400na. because that<br />
represents no nero t. a. an albout ~ 5 non'trs'I purch:: se of imports. rf<br />
we had someo sudden fiflnaflci, tro-uble, a fatal coillap,-.-in the wool<br />
market, or a great drought in the wheat industry, or something<br />
happening, in . Ie iieat industry, we wo'-uld, in -order to avoid<br />
banrutc itoratonll, have to have reserves overseas on<br />
which-impo) rters c) uld draw thkro3ugh1 their banks, in orcdhr to pay<br />
for the p,-ods co,--ing-into L1<br />
ustrailia., By land large we are so<br />
poverty stricken in ' Lustralia that our eople between then Tianage<br />
to buy œ l, 000Li. worth of : Lm. prts every year. Not bad for<br />
million people in a state of incipient ba-_ nkruptcy, is it?<br />
Therefore we must h-ave -ilequate o) verseas reserves. AnMd we said,<br />
" Very well, in ordeor to avoid any suggestion o) f panic, or crisis,<br />
we will, before theo overseas reserves 1fall t, 1o-far as they were<br />
at -that tine by re-, ason of the boon ore will nake a drawi,, ing on<br />
the int. ernati :) nal MontaPry Fund",<br />
The Interinati: on-l 1' on; tiry FLa--d is Oo if thlose<br />
rmysterious bodies like the ,: ati'L..' niI Jank fro7-, wdhich fellows<br />
like me oil be ha1I o f oto~ people, boawmnyfro-rl time to<br />
tine. We decidedf -, hat we 1.'. uld 1ahavj., a.? a po-: rf,-ct right to clo so,<br />
make a drawing; on ti-e Intoernaiti-o nal VootryIund becaus we had<br />
deposited 1--any rllasin it, like all the cother co) nsti,-; tuent<br />
countries. Iesaid "' doll, we will draw e will tuck it<br />
into our o) verso" as re1sorves. It prbal w!, rn't. be noedel but at<br />
any rate it will prevent pepefrom ge:, tting, -n idea thcv there is<br />
so-iel critical state affairs". Thea last thin,] to ha,. ve is this<br />
miserable attitude of crisis, the loss -of c:) nfidonco, the<br />
p) rophets of' gloom, tho peoplle whio create depre; ssions by advertising<br />
their owrn troubles about TTihieenr. e fore we-made this drawing.<br />
At the tineo we riade it we , DUt a statemeont in to the<br />
International Monetary Fund. and my colleag-, ue, the Treasurer, Mr.<br />
Holt, tabled it in the Huse, of Represenltatives with an<br />
accompanyin stoteurent. P-rlianont approv( : d of the drawn and<br />
the headline that nigwht in the" papulr was relaxati~ n in credit<br />
squeeze until. June, 1962". Thor r-ust halve been afair number of<br />
business. ien whio road tChat hoadlino and went ba, c k and said " Well<br />
-that's the end of' it. Not until June, t62. 1rnother 12 months<br />
with nothing. doneo to relieva tho pros. ent position". The headline<br />
was, as a point of fact, completely falso, I b. rc,-u -ht with meo to<br />
Tasmania the precise words of our st-atement to thLe Fund. I will<br />
read them'. to you: they are not varr they arc completely<br />
true, they are consistent with everything that tie have done;<br />
and they are consistent vith the re~ narkable fact that between the<br />
tinec whie. we prosiintc. this d-cumeont to the M-rne-tary Fund and<br />
tuday, we have made two or thr-so iL. ajor relaxiations in the policy.<br />
It is wo-rth remem: bering; that, bocause people who thought weM htad<br />
contracted out of doing it must h3ove buoon surprised when we did<br />
it, Here is the rclevant part of our statement:<br />
" Economic c-. nditions in _ ustraia -r suJetorai<br />
chan( e r * nnf luenced 1by a number of external factors<br />
outside the Government's control. Poli -cy has thoreforo<br />
frequently to be ad1ap) ted to meet a shift in conditions. The<br />
declarations of policy riade here miust the-refco be undo rstoo) d<br />
as applying, only to conditions as theoy now appe;-r. Sho) uld any<br />
m~ ajor shi ft in the direction or emphaasis of policy become<br />
necessary dluring the currency of the stand-by arrangem,):, ent, the<br />
I . ustLralian Govcernmeint would, at th e request of thie Monaging<br />
Dircctor, ready to co+ nsult wdth ' the Fun,,, nd, if nece3ssary,<br />
reach now und ; rstanding ;: ofore any request -for a further<br />
dra-wing+-under s nd-by, : 7rran-oii+ ent is made",.<br />
Th-at doesn't s . und m-. uch like a cast-iron p ositio) n fo-r 12 monthls,<br />
) os it? </p>
<p>" Seasonal needs apart, however, the Monetary<br />
authorities"<br />
that's the Reserve Bank and ourselves<br />
" intend to keep a firm control over the liquidity position of<br />
the banks"<br />
which I nay say the Banks would do themselves, anyhow, because<br />
that is part of their great art and responsibility<br />
" with a view to limiting during the year ending June ' 62 the<br />
amount of outstanding bank advances to a total that would be<br />
consistent with the maintenance of financial stability".<br />
And on those words you wore told by some clown " No relaxation in<br />
credit squeeze until June, 1962". The document as I have read it<br />
to you makes it quite clear, now, as then, that our policy is to<br />
maintain financial stability insofar as any Government of the<br />
Cor. monwealth can do it; and by maintaining financial stability<br />
encourage the development of Australian enterprise to the fullest<br />
extent and the increase in the . ustralian population by<br />
immigration and otherwise.<br />
The last thing that I want to say to you, because I<br />
have spoken much longer than I had any desire to do, is this.<br />
Prophets, notoriously, have no honour in their own countries;<br />
Governments have very little honour in their own countries. The<br />
number of people I have met who could run the financial affairs of<br />
Australia bettor than we could are le. ion. The pity is that they<br />
don't go into Parliament.<br />
But outside Australia there are hard-headed people who<br />
want to invest in Australia people in the United States, in<br />
Canada, in the United Kingdom which, with all its own profound<br />
economic troubles, much more grave than ours at this monent, is<br />
still the largest investor of private funds in ustralia<br />
A few years back I used to say to my Treasury people,<br />
" Tell ne, what do you estimate to be the inflow of private<br />
capital investment into Australia, not public borrowing by<br />
Governments but private capital investment, a company deciding to<br />
start something, a company investing its money in sonmthing?"<br />
And when the answer used to be, 10 years ago, 8 years ago, round<br />
about œ 100m. I must say I used to rub ny hands and say " That's<br />
wonderful, that's wonderful". ' nd so it was. Because<br />
million people can't find all the capital that they need to<br />
develop this enormous continent with its resources. By last year<br />
that inflow had reached a figure roughly three times the size of<br />
that of ten years ago.<br />
Then along cane the blunderin~ Monzios Government and<br />
wrecked the economy. I suppose that all these wise, shrewd<br />
follows not philanthropists, I haven't encountered too many<br />
philanthropists in the overseas money markets, though I have had<br />
a groat deal to do with a great number of then, nice fellows, but<br />
not philanthropists want to see the right investment, they want<br />
to believe in the country that they are putting the money into,<br />
they want to believe that it has stable Governmrent and sound and<br />
stable ideas, and a future. And in this very year, just ended,<br />
the financial year 1960-61 most of it disfigured, I'm told, by our<br />
reckless policies, the amount that has cone into Australia for<br />
private investment from outside ustralia is an all-time record.<br />
( Applause) I don't feel happy if ny supporters are occasionally<br />
doubtful, critical. You can't win elections, you can't maintain </p>
<p>8.<br />
Government on the basis of doubtful supporters, supporters who<br />
leave, supporters who arc half-hearted. If you are half-hearted<br />
about us then I want to say at once to my friends hero they<br />
haven't a dog's hope of winning the next election, not a dog's<br />
hope. Good as they are, they are not going to win their elections<br />
if the cor. nnunity behind then has reservations about the Governnent<br />
that they are going in to support. Therefore the first condition<br />
of gotting these nen into Parliament House of Representatives<br />
and Senate is to be able to go behind then with a full heart<br />
and a satisfied nind, and a belief, which I say is a well-founded<br />
belief, that there could be no greater disaster cone to Australia<br />
than that the inconpetents whon I look at across the table in<br />
Canberra should be entrusted with the affairs of this country.<br />
( Applause) </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
