<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6612</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE, 15 MARCH 1985</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/03/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006612.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
~ J) UST -A LIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF PRESS CONFERENCE 15 March 1985<br />
E. O. E. -PROOF ONLY<br />
PM: Well let's commence.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister will we have a mini-Budget?<br />
PM: No we won't have a mini-Budget. It may well be that we'll<br />
have an early announcement of some decision so that we can aet the<br />
full year revenue benefits, or expenditure restraints I should say<br />
that's the right way of putting it. And I assume that we'll<br />
have the full support of an Opposition who talks about the<br />
necessity of bringing down the Budget deficit. I expect their<br />
full support. I'll have to wait to see who announces the support<br />
and then if there's any qualification to the announcement for the<br />
support, but we live in hope.<br />
JOURNALIST: Well Prime Minister given that the Labor Party in<br />
Opposition helped to block the Fraser Governments sales tax<br />
legislation, do you believe Oppositions should give carte-blanche<br />
to the Government.<br />
PM: I believe that a duly elected Government should be allowed to<br />
discharge its mandate. What I don't know about what I believe is<br />
what the Opposition's position will be. It really is a very sad<br />
picture that has emerged with the Leader of the Opposition taking<br />
a position in which he believes and then being overtaken by the<br />
right wing of his Party. There's no certainty any more in<br />
Opposition, we don't know who's in control or who's in charge. It<br />
is a very sad picture to see the crumbling of the position of the<br />
Leader of the Opposition in this way.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke will the Government proceed with its<br />
initiative on Kampuchea?<br />
PM: Yes we will. There is no reason, nothing has happened as to<br />
why we should not proceed upon that course because the elements<br />
that made it sensible in April 1983, when I discussed the matter<br />
with Bill Hayden and we agreed that that course was sensible,<br />
those elements remain valid. And that is that Australia almost<br />
uniquely has the capacity to talk with all the countries who have<br />
a direct or indirect interest in what is happening in Indo-China. </p>
<p>JOURNALIST: Do we still have that capacity in vieaw of the rather<br />
harsh comments by ASEAN countries and by China too of the three<br />
vital components of the situation of about how..<br />
PM: Well let's take the two categories in turn. You talk about<br />
ASEAN comments. I think if you look at the comments that were<br />
made by them after Mr Hayden's return to Thailand, they were not<br />
harsh comments. And indeed I've had the opportunity of talking<br />
with Bill since he's come back and he's talked to me directly<br />
about the conversations that he did have after his visit to<br />
Vietnam. And the judgement I therefore make both in terms of the<br />
public statements that have been made by ASEAN leaders and Mr<br />
Hayden's comments to me don't lead me to the conclusion that any<br />
difficulty exists in our relationship with ASEAN either generally<br />
or in respect of the position that we've adopted on this<br />
initiative. In regard to China well, there was some relatively<br />
harsh comments made, but I believe that when Mr Hu Yaobung comes<br />
here in a matter of a few weeks we will be able to dispel any<br />
substantive concerns that they may have.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what's your view of Mr Hayden's<br />
handling of the Asian trip.<br />
PM: I believe that Mr Hayden has acted honestly and with<br />
integrity. I believe that Mr Hayden has indicated that he has<br />
been misled. Now I guess in this world it's easy enough on<br />
occasions to be misled. I have full confidence in Bill Hayden as<br />
Foreign Minister. He has from April 1983, when I first raised<br />
this concept with him, worked assiduously, he's earned the respect<br />
I believe of all the parties involved and I don't believe that<br />
that respect and authority that he's established has in any<br />
substantial way been diminished.<br />
J -OURNALIST: Did the intelligence community let Mr Hayden down by<br />
not giving him adequate information as to what was happening on<br />
the Thai/ Kampuchea border.<br />
PM: Well you know well at least you should know if you've been<br />
around the place long that it's a very clear and unshakeable<br />
principle that I do not go into matters of intelligence at all.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke turning to your speech last night you<br />
emphasised the difficulties of getting consensus on tax reforms.<br />
How seriously do you rate the possibility of the Government being<br />
forced to back-off making substantial changes to the tax structure<br />
because of lack of consensus.<br />
PM: I don't think it's likely, but I believe always that it's<br />
b-est to be direct and frank about the dimensions of the task that<br />
one is undertaking in Government. And what I'm really trying to<br />
say to the Australian community is that this is a matter for the<br />
community as much as it is for Government. It's no good people<br />
simply saying the existing system is not satisfactory. They have<br />
to be prepared to participate so that Government can know that an </p>
<p>alternative thrust is going to have the acceptance of a<br />
substantial proportion of the community. Because as I explained<br />
last night, if you don't do that then in net terms the stability<br />
and welfare of the community is likely to be lessened. And<br />
therefore we will discharge our responsibilities, as I said last<br />
night Michelle. Our responsibilities are to detail the nature of<br />
the operation of the existing system, to expose its inadequacies,<br />
its inequities, its lack of simplicity, its lack of economic<br />
efficiency as an instrument of economic policy. We will do that.<br />
We will also have the responsibility of outlining alternative<br />
packages that could be considered as a means to get a better<br />
system. Now Government will discharge those responsibilities and<br />
we'll discharge them in a way that has never been done by<br />
Government before. Then the community has to respond and be<br />
involved.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister doesn't the Government have a duty to<br />
proceed with tax reforms if it sees that's in the national<br />
interest even if it can't get consensus.<br />
PM: I haven't used the word consensus.<br />
JOURNALIST: even if you can't get broad agreement?<br />
PM: The premise of the question is not operative.<br />
JOURNALIST: So have you considered not going ahead with the tax<br />
summit?<br />
PM: No.<br />
JOURNALIST: It is said, Prime Minister, that the community has to<br />
respond and be involved. H-ow do you envisage that the community<br />
will in fact respond and be involved.<br />
PM: There'll be a number of ways. The process has already<br />
sgtarted. EPAC has received a very large number of responses from<br />
individuals and organisations. We'll be having a meeting of EPAC<br />
at the end of this month to consider those responses. So the<br />
broard based community representatives in EPAC will be involved in<br />
the process of trying to begin to shape attitudes to assess the<br />
material that's been put in. We will then be producing the White<br />
Paper before the Summit. We hope to get responses to that,<br />
substantial responses. Then we'll have the Summit itself. And<br />
then we'll undergo the process of final consideration in the light<br />
of all those inputs that we'll get. Now that's a detailed<br />
approach. It's one which gives a very considerable opporunity to<br />
the community and organisations large and small to express their<br />
views.<br />
JOURNALIST: At this stage do you foresee that the Government<br />
itself will put a proposal for tax reform to the Summit? </p>
<p>PM: No I don't think we would put a final position in the sense<br />
of saying well, there it is, we've made up our mind. Because I've<br />
tried to say all along, Peter, that the Summit is not a charade.<br />
I mean we really want to use it to get an interchange of views.<br />
We believe that we can be helped by the Summit. As I've expressed<br />
it, I think the Government will form sort of prima facie<br />
preferences, if I can put it that way, which we think may meet the<br />
criteria of efficiency, equity and simplicity. But we are open to<br />
persuasion and argument as to better alternatives.<br />
JOURNALIST: What's your assessment of the Queensland power<br />
legislation. How are you going to respond to pleas to help..<br />
PM: Well I think the legislation is not consistent with the<br />
conventions of the International Labour Organisation. I believe<br />
it reflects an approach to industrial relations which is counterproductive<br />
and is more likely to produce disputes than to settle<br />
them. And in a way it's a sad thing to see that in the<br />
economically worst managed State in Australia that is,<br />
Queensland with easily the worst level of unemployment, very<br />
incompetent economic management, just doesn't stand in comparison<br />
with any other State in Australia that in those dire<br />
circumstances where they are doing worse than the national average<br />
and worse than any other State in terms of economic performance<br />
that the situation is likely to be made worse by this legislation.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is there potential for a Franklin dam re-run..<br />
PM: I don't think so.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister the National Farmers Federation is<br />
strongly opposed to the introduction of a capital gains tax.<br />
Given this, how do you believe that you can in fact get broadbased<br />
community support for such a tax without possibly the<br />
farmers.<br />
PM: Well as I made clear last night broad based community support<br />
' d-esn't mean that every single element in the community<br />
support every single element of the package. Just let me _= nswer<br />
the question in a hypothetical sense because no decisions '. 3ve<br />
been made in that area. It is conceivable that you could ae a<br />
form of capital gains tax which would take account of<br />
concerns-of the farming community as to the adverse affectS of<br />
such a tax in the rural sector. Now I say that not to be<br />
interpreted as saying we have decided upon a capital gains tax<br />
with certain exceptions. I simply say as an economist th= t that<br />
sort of thing is possible. But I repeat the basic point that I<br />
make in talking about broad based agreement I made it qui te<br />
clear last night that you couldn't expect that you were go-: ng to<br />
get every section of the community to agree on every elemen~ t of a<br />
package. I said that in any package that emerged there would be<br />
some winners in regard to some component, some losers in regard to<br />
some components, but overall the community would be winner. </p>
<p>. JOURNALIST: Do you think Mr Risstrom is furthering the cause of<br />
tax reform by the contributions that he is making?<br />
PM: Well I think the interesting thing that will develop<br />
bgetween now and the Summit, Mike, is that Mr Risstrom is going to<br />
be exposed to pretty rigorous analysis by experts in the process<br />
leading up to and at the Summit. I mean, to this point Mr<br />
Risstrom has expressed his views, as we want him to express them,<br />
but he hasn't been subject to rigorous analysis. And I just have<br />
a bit of a feeling that when subject to that rigorous analysis and<br />
cross-examination some of the rather easy observations of Mr<br />
Risstrom might not stand up quite so well.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you again emphasised last night the need<br />
for substantial spending cuts in this Budget and you also in<br />
proportionate terms gave your aim for the next deficit. Can you<br />
give us some indication of the magnitude of the spending cuts that<br />
you are looking for?<br />
PM: Well I don't intend to go to a specific figure. All I<br />
want to say is this that through the application of the elenents<br />
of the trilogy and the Budget preparation, there will be in<br />
respect of the deficit, both a reduction in the deficit as a<br />
proportion of the GDP and a significant reduction in the money<br />
level of the deficit.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, do you intend reintroducing<br />
university fees tertiary education fees?<br />
PM: I don't make the decisions of government. So I don't<br />
h-ave, you know, an intention of doing one thing or the other. The<br />
clear answer to your question, Ken, is that obviously this is<br />
going to be an issue which is going to be discussed and I th--ink it<br />
is equally not the best kept state secret that there are sone<br />
divergence of views between certain Minister. I am not going to<br />
express a view now. I will take part in the discussion when it<br />
arises in the Cabinet.<br />
JOURNALIST: Isn't there an election promise that this would<br />
not happen and if so why is your Government considering bre:;-.-_ na<br />
that promise?<br />
PM: The overwhelming responsibility of the Government iS to<br />
The economic welfare of the community to stimulate growth at Low<br />
levels of inflation and that requires the application of the three<br />
elements of the trilogy. That is the pre-eminent undertaki:-. i<br />
have given to the Australian community and within the achievemnent<br />
of that objective then, I believe any matter that Ministers want<br />
to put on the table which are consistent with the application of<br />
that trilogy are legitimate to be considered.<br />
JOURNALIST: JOURNLiIfS Ti: tE vmeena ns breaking promises? </p>
<p>PM: Well, you have a range of issues to which you direct<br />
yourself and you have got to get your priorities and I put as my<br />
overwhelming priority and that of the Government to get growth, to<br />
get jobs, and we are doing that through the application of our<br />
policies. The employment figures yesterday show that we are ahead<br />
of target in creating a half a million new jobs in the three<br />
years. My judgement is, Laurie, that if the Australian co. mmunity<br />
are asked what is the number one priority it is the creation of<br />
jobs, the reduction of unemployment. Now, the simple facts are<br />
that that is not something that can be done by simply saying you<br />
would like it to happen. You have got to make hard decisions in<br />
terms of economic management to achieve that result. We have been<br />
doing that. We have got outstandingly successful results. And I<br />
believe the community will welcome economic decisions by this<br />
Government which are going to continue that process. And ifL that<br />
means in respect of some undertakings that they have had to give<br />
way to that central priority, I think the community will accept<br />
it. All that, I may say, is said not on the assumption that the<br />
particular issue you are talking about will in fact take place.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, you have set targets for the reducing of<br />
expenditure for next year. Now that the ERC committee is well<br />
under way in its deliberations, are you confident of achieving<br />
those targets?<br />
PM: We will achieve the targets that are necessary in the area<br />
ofreductions of government expenditure to achieve the trilogy.<br />
Yes, we will do that. I am'quite confident.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, how do you answer fears that there<br />
is not enough information in the community, or about the community<br />
to really make tax reform meaningful in terms of the provisions of<br />
equity which a lot of people would like to see implemented?<br />
PM: What was the last bit?<br />
JOURNALIST: The provisions of equity.<br />
PM: Oh equity. I am sorry, I didn't hear. Well we are doing<br />
that by the work that we are undertaking now. We will be . vn<br />
discussions with wide ranging representative groups in the<br />
community, through EPAC and in other ways and out of all t.-et will<br />
come a ve ry detailed white paper which will give an unprec=-Jented<br />
exposure of the operation of the existing system, the ineoa-ties<br />
of the existing system. And I believe thiose who are intere-Srec<br />
will have an opportunity that they have never had before in-t~ h e<br />
history of this country to understand how the existing sys--em<br />
works and will have presented to them a range of alternati, ies that<br />
will have as one of the criteria involved, the criterion of:<br />
equity.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, what prompted your Government to<br />
vote last week at the United Nations Human Rights Commission in<br />
support of a review of alleged human rights abuses in East Timor? </p>
<p>Has your Government got some evidence of an increasing incidence<br />
of this in East Timor?<br />
PM: I haven't discussed this matter in detail with Mr Hayden,<br />
but clearly the situation was one where it led to a conclusion<br />
that that course of action was the appropriate one. And, as I<br />
have indicated before, I have full confidence in my Foreign<br />
Minister and clearly the decision that was taken there was one<br />
which was believed to be warranted on the evidence available.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, what has happened to the wealth enquiry?<br />
PM: The enquiry at the ANU, you mean?<br />
JOURNALIST: Yes.<br />
PM: We are still in the process of making a decision as to<br />
w; hat resources should be made available to that and when.<br />
JOURNALIST: When will you announce details?<br />
PM: I'm not sure.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, you said you would like to see a<br />
reduction in the nominal deficit next financial year.<br />
PM: No, I have said much more than that. I didn't say I would<br />
like to. I said it will happen.<br />
JOURNALIST: Right. So have you in fact decided on a targetfigure?<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Is it correct that it is around $ 6 billion?<br />
PM: I'm not going to a figure.<br />
JOURNALIST: Prime Minister, have you decided yet where ASIO<br />
will live and whether they are going to get ( inaudibke)<br />
PM: No, Laurie. We haven't made a final. decision on that, but<br />
we will be making one in the very near future.<br />
JOURNALIST: What is the next step now in the process of trying<br />
to achieve a settlement to Kampuchea?<br />
PM: Well Mike, I think while it sounds a bit banal, it is<br />
nevertheless true, that it just is a continuing process of the<br />
varying parties trying to develop positions in a way which<br />
hopefully can get the two sides, if you can put it that way,<br />
sufficiently close together to enable a substantial conference to<br />
take place. As I said before, when Hu Yaobung comes here in a few<br />
weeks time I will be talking with him then amongst other things, </p>
<p>8<br />
about Indo-China and it is not one of those issues any more than<br />
the Middle East is, if you ' Like, where there is some magic<br />
formula. I mean, if it were there, it would have been arrived at<br />
earlier. You have got a situation where you have got so many<br />
elements which militate against an acceleration of a conclusion.<br />
You have got the centuries old antagonisms between China and<br />
Vietnam. You have got the horrendous memories associated with the<br />
period of the Pol Pot regime in Kampuchea. You have got the<br />
apprehensions amongst some of the ASEAN States in regard to China.<br />
Now when you have got that mixture of deep and long-standing,<br />
either antagonisms or apprehensions, then what is really involved<br />
is the slow process of trying to get the people involved to<br />
understand that all their interests are going to be better served<br />
if you can have peace in the region rather than the waste of so<br />
much resources in this mutual antagonistic set piece that has<br />
emerged. Now, therefore, the answer to your question is that<br />
without, as I repeat, over-emphasising our capacities in this<br />
matter we will just keep talking to the parties involved in the<br />
hope that we may be able to play some small part in that s'. ow<br />
process of bringing the sides sufficiently close together see<br />
that there would be some chance in an actual conference of<br />
producing a resolution. But I don't see that and I never have<br />
seen that, of something capable of being achieved quickly.<br />
Inaudible<br />
PM: The left always wins out over so you say.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you considered the Beazley/ Hawke<br />
* paper on ANZUS and..<br />
PM: The Beazley/ Hawke paper?<br />
JOURNALIST: Oh Beazley/ Hayden paper on ANZUS and also when<br />
will a public statement be made on that subject?<br />
PM: Well we haven't got the Beazley/ Hayden paper yet. I would<br />
q expect it to be coming very shortly and when it comes the Cabinet<br />
will consider it. I don't feel any sense of immediate urgency.<br />
The issues involved are important and are being thorougly<br />
considered by the two Minister. I have made it quite clear to the<br />
people of Australi-a that the relationship between Australia and<br />
the United States is in the firmest possible shape. We have<br />
announced the meeting that we will be having in July here in<br />
Australia between ourselves and Mr Shultz and officials. So<br />
everything is in place. Mr Beazley is going to New Zealand at the<br />
end of this month so the bilateral relations with New Zealand are<br />
proceeding satisfactorily. What has become quite clear and it<br />
should have been clearer to some people earlier in the piece is<br />
that as far as Australia's national interests are concerned, this<br />
Government has from the very outset of the problem created by the<br />
New Zealand decision, acted in a way to protect our interests.<br />
The relationship with the United States is totally and firm and we<br />
will continue the relations with New Zealand in a way which is </p>
<p>: 1 9<br />
necessary between our two countries for the purposes of'our<br />
response to discharging our responsibilities in the region. So<br />
everything is firm and stable and secure.<br />
JOURNALIST: on the Middle East, is the Government<br />
reconsidering or is it likely to reconsider the decision to<br />
withdraw the troops from the Sinai at the end of the year?<br />
PM: The position is quite clear. When we made the decision in<br />
1984, if you read what Mr Hayden has said in the Parliament, that<br />
we believe that we should make an extension for two years because<br />
we were not in any way going to be party to an action which could<br />
be seen or could in fact de-stabilise the region. So we extended<br />
the period for two years and we indicated then that discussions'<br />
would be held with the leadership of the MFO to look for a<br />
replacement. They accepted that. They understood that and those<br />
discussions are, I believe, going on. And I expect that out of<br />
the discussions that are being held a suitable replacement will be<br />
found. We have made it clear at all times, as I said, that we<br />
would not be party to any de-stabilising of the region by our<br />
action. That commitment remains firm.<br />
JOURNALIST: Have you seen or will you be seeing Professor<br />
Kapi tsa?<br />
PM: I saw him in 1979.<br />
JOURNALIST: on his current visit?<br />
PM: On his current visit. Well, as far as I am aware I<br />
haven't received any request from him and in these matters one<br />
always behaves, as you will appreciate, with impeccable propriety.<br />
I mean, I don't ask to see him and I haven't been asked by him to<br />
see him, so at this stage the answer is no.<br />
JOURNALIST: Mr Hawke, have you seen a telex from Premier Burke<br />
for a<br />
PM: Yes I have. I saw one just before I came round here<br />
because some of those advising me thought I may just get a<br />
question about it, so they showed it to me, yes.<br />
JOURNALIST: Do-you have any comment to make on it?<br />
PM: Well, yes. I think that the concept that now the Premier<br />
seems to be talking about that he has clarified of the goc-sense<br />
of looking at as part of the tackling of the youth unemplcn-ment<br />
problem looking at the possibility of community based wo--k as<br />
part of the way in which the community will meet the probli2ms of<br />
unemployed youth that that is a sensible suggestion. An-: indeed<br />
in the wide-ranging analysis that is going to be undertaken by Mr<br />
Willis and Mr Dawkins and Senator Ryan to look at the whole range<br />
of alternatives that we should take into account in dealing witn<br />
this tragic problem of youth unemployment. That will be a concept </p>
<p>that they will be looking at and I am indebted to Premier Burke<br />
for his indication of the readiness of the West Australian<br />
Government to become involved in such an approach not merely by<br />
way of verbal support but, very importantly, by way of financial<br />
support. I welcome that initiative and it will be fed into the<br />
consideration that my three Ministers will be undertaking on this<br />
matter. PM: </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
