<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4554</transcript-id>
    <title>LUNCHTIME RALLY, SYDNEY, 23 NOVEMBER 1977</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>23/11/1977</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004554.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
L'UN1CWI'IM-P, RALLY, SY1DNBY 2' 3 NOVEMDE 9T 7<br />
Since we Were elected, every effort of this Government has been<br />
diretted at bringing growth and prozperity back to Australia. There<br />
has been no easy way out of the crisis which Labor had pulled Australia<br />
into. Tough and sometimes unpopular decisions had to be made. We have<br />
had the couxrage a-nd determination to inake them, Australia has now been<br />
tai-en to the point ofl takeoff -Australia is just a step away from major<br />
gxow-th and development. Confidence is returning; Australi a is ready to<br />
go with billions of dollars of new development projects.<br />
This election presents the people of Australia with a clear choice. A<br />
choice between the coherent economic strategy we have been successfully<br />
pursuing, and Labor's disastrous combination of dogma and political<br />
opportunism a combination which is t,-otally incoherent, totally<br />
inconsistent, totally at odds with its announced aims. A policy whi ch<br />
would halt recovery in its tracks which would destroy Australia' s<br />
prospects of growth and development.<br />
This recovery is under way because our strategy is working; because we ' ye<br />
controlled government spending and had some success in qain-. ing wage<br />
restraint inflation is now running4 at interest rates have come down.-'<br />
and tax reforms have been made a reality. I<br />
Labor is in total disarray over economic policy the Federal Party and thQ<br />
N. S. W. Party for instancv are raylinq totally different things. Mrc Wran hat.<br />
publicly acknowledged the vital importance of our tax reforms. Hie thought<br />
them so vital that he urged us to introduce them sooner than February. lie<br />
said they were " l~ ong overdue". These vital tax cuts arce the very tax<br />
reforms that Mr Whitlam now wants to take away. Mr Wran has cooperated witf<br />
our programmue '. getting interest rates down indeed he has urged other<br />
premiers to use their influ4tnce on rates within their states. By contrast<br />
bir Hayden attacked -as when we recently reduced the rate on the Australian<br />
Savings Bond. a<br />
Mr Wran has recognised our success in gettinc. inflation down. As early s<br />
last May, he publicly acknowledged that inflation was down to 10% -I<br />
effectively putting the lie to the spurious figures bandied arouytd by Mx<br />
IWhitlain and Mr Hayden.<br />
We have pursued an economic strategly designed to stop indireot taxes<br />
inr-reasing. Mr Wran did the same, as did all the other premiers. Thig<br />
stands in stark contrast to the stated intentions of M~ r Burford who told<br />
us in June that Labor would seek, to find fuxther revenue from indirect<br />
taxes. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Mr Wran has made it clear that lie intends to follow onez of our major<br />
new initiatives the abolition of estate duty, and that he will do the<br />
same with state duties. Mr Wran is not alone in finding it hard to keep..<br />
in step with the stumbles of his party's economic policy.<br />
on Sunday morning, Mr Whitlam began by saying that Labor would merely<br />
postpone the tax cuts coming in on February first. Sunday lunchtime he<br />
said " he had made a mistake" -that Labor would never bring in those tax<br />
Cuts. Sunday afternoon, he said tax indexation would be UpoFtponedfI<br />
until income tax receipts rise sufficiently to offset the cost of payroll<br />
tax. Bly Sunday night, he was sayinq perhaps he'd" expressed himself<br />
wrongly". Mr Whitlam now says he would " expect" full tax indexation<br />
somietime soon, but Mr Hurford it checking it. Poor bir Hurford<br />
he's already been thrown out as Labor's economic spokesman, and now<br />
lie's been sent scurrying off to try to deal with Labor's great gaffe.<br />
The second plank of Labor's economic programme is its wage policy.<br />
in his policy speech, Mz Whitlam commiitted Labor to " restore integrity<br />
to the wage indexationi guidelines." That; speech was only hours old when<br />
Mr Hlayden said that meant support for full wage index-ation but only<br />
for people on less than average weekly earnings.<br />
By Sunday Mr Whitlamn was saying that Labor wanted full wage indexation<br />
for everyone. Mr Iayd-n confesse3 he might be wrong. " I feel I'm on Sha<br />
ground", he said.<br />
He said questions on wage indexation should be directed to Mr Willis-<br />
" I work in the economic area" " it's a demarcation problem".<br />
So imtich for Mr Hayden as an economic manager.<br />
if he believes wages policy is outside the economic area, he certainly<br />
is ort shaky ground. Labor has so many economic managers that there's<br />
always a threat of a demarcation dispute.-The way all the Labor Party.<br />
economic managers are carryinq~ on should not surprise anyone.<br />
It is typical of the way they carridd on in government.<br />
The basic reason for Labor's confusion iB. that they are distressed<br />
by the certain knowledge that our econmic policies are workingbecause<br />
we'vye ended the big tax ripoff and cut taxes for every<br />
Australian taxpayer from February first. They know that because<br />
of our tax r-eforms, 225,000 more Australians on low incomes<br />
will no longer pay tax. N~ o one pays tax on the first<br />
$ 3,750 of income over $ 5000 with a dependent spouse.<br />
They recognise the strength of our reformns whi. ch have meant<br />
of Australia's taxpayers pay the same rate of tax. And manY people<br />
will be paying 32 cents in the dollar on overtime instead of<br />
cents up to $ 16,000<br />
Our tax reforms accord with the view of most. taxation experts they<br />
are overwhelmingly supported by the reports of the Committees of<br />
Inquiry Labor set up when they were in government. The Asprey Committee<br />
the most comprehensive review of Australia's tax system for forty years<br />
concluded that the Australian tax system relies too heavily on<br />
personal income tax. The Mathews Committee concluded that recent high<br />
marginal tax rates encouraged tax avoidance and evasion. The Jackson<br />
Committee warned that " we have a general imprssion that the reward<br />
differentials after tax are decreasing and may no longer be ! sufficient<br />
to encourage individual enterprise and effort ind1industry".<br />
mr jjawke you might remember was on that Committee. Perhaps he's<br />
forgotten. Our tax reforms haVe faced these problems head on... </p>
<p>3-<br />
They restore the-incentive to succeed, to make it worthwhile to<br />
wrvke rtme aain, to reward -he drive and initiative hcha<br />
clot this great Country as far-as it has, They give people a greater<br />
say over how their own money is spent.<br />
In two years, our tax cuts have saved individuals $ 3,300 million.<br />
in additon, we have extended vital tax concessions to business<br />
and to mnining companies to provide incentive to invest, explore<br />
and develop. if these are added, total tax saved to individuals<br />
and corporate tax~ payers~ in two years is $ 4,300 million.<br />
Now we will buiild on this. Jveryone knoviz of families who have be<br />
harrassed an~ d puit through great distress by death duties.<br />
Businesses have been broken up; widows have had to struggle along<br />
with less; families have had no choice but to sink, thernselve deep<br />
into debt.<br />
w-e have decided that this distxess and worry ffo the ber'eaved MuOst<br />
csase. As frow Monday, all estates passing between man and wil. Ee,<br />
narent and child, will be totally free of federal estate<br />
and qift duty. Further we shall see to It that over the life<br />
of the next Parliament, all estate duty and gift duty is entirely<br />
abolished. Yesterday kir Whitlam attacked this decision by claiming<br />
that it would not benefits many people.<br />
lie said " Batate duty is paid on a person's estate if it is worth<br />
more than. $ 90,000". He was clearly imnplying that no duty is<br />
payable for an estate of any lesser value. This claim is utterly false.;<br />
The $ 90,000 mininmim only applies to estates passing to a surviving<br />
spouse. Apart from primaiy producers, for estates passin g to a child<br />
or grandchbild, the minimum is $ 40,000; for all other estates, the<br />
mtinimnum is only $ 20,000,<br />
Vw liitlam is a Quean's Counsel. He obviously knew the truith;<br />
hieobviously chose to conceal it. He knows this timely reform<br />
will reliev much inequity and sooial distress. So he deliberately<br />
tried to migie-ad the Australian public,<br />
Every year, about 13,000 estates have to pay estate duty, mjany having<br />
several beneficiaries.-That means that tens of thousands of people<br />
are affected each year by estate duty, many of them entirely<br />
dependent on the deceased's estate for support. But it seems all<br />
this means " nothing" to fix Whitlam.<br />
While we are reducing the personal tax barden on the Australian<br />
taxpayer, Mr Whitlam would inCrease it massively. M4r Whitlam has<br />
said quite clearly that he wants to pay for the abolition of payroll<br />
tax by increasing the burden of personal income tax on Australian<br />
taxpayers.<br />
Let us look at the implications of what he has in mind. V'irst,<br />
consider the present financial year. Mr whitlain has gaid that he would<br />
repeal the law which provides for tax cuts in the first half of 1978<br />
and for the introduction of the standard tax rate System.<br />
1n1977/ 78 that repeal would increase government tax collections by<br />
about $ 400 million. But that would not be enough. He would still<br />
be left viitb a very large sum~ to find to meet the cost of about $ 850M<br />
for removing payroll tax over the first half of 1978. Whe-re would he<br />
find that? His alternatives would be to let the government deficit<br />
expand even faster than he has already proposed, and remember hie<br />
has already stated he would increase government spending by $ 800Mi<br />
in that period, or to raise even more fro-m personal income tax by<br />
increasinAg the rates of tax. </p>
<p>Either course would be bad news indeed for economiic recovery,<br />
for infaltion, and for employment. B3ut until Mr Whitlam comes<br />
clean with what lie proposes, taxpayers must assumie that they<br />
would be asked to pay even more tax, arid to pay in the<br />
first half of next year.<br />
Let's look at the next financial year 1978/ 79. Labor would<br />
need $] 900M to compensate the States for abolishing payroll tax<br />
in 1978/ 79. By repeal of the standard tax rate system, Labor<br />
would get an estimated $ 1470M from increased taxes. Again<br />
there is a significant short fall to make up. A short fall of<br />
about $ 430M.<br />
it is not Surprising therefore, that 14r Whitlam has said that tax<br />
indexation. would be postponed until income tax receipts rise<br />
sufficiently to coverthe cost of compensating the S. tates for<br />
abolition of payroll tax-By abandoning tax indexation in addition<br />
to the repeal of the standard tax rate-system, Mx~ hitlam would<br />
increase tax collections by all estimated $ 1900M which would<br />
approximiately meet his target to coverpayroll tax.<br />
There can be no doubt about it Mr Whitlarn is planning a massive<br />
increase in personal tax. The arithmetic is crystal clear.<br />
An increase which would leave every taxpayer whatever his earnings9,<br />
a lot woirse off. -Aii increase which would force 225,000 low income<br />
earners and pensioners to Xeep on paying tax from February lot.<br />
IEf Mr Whitlam has some other " grand design" let him ntate it.<br />
Until he does, taxpayers must assume the worst and that is why<br />
I say that those on average weekly earnings stand to lost $ 6 a<br />
week under Mr Whitlam's proposals.<br />
rMr Whitlam, always has been a man who believed in big government.<br />
By abolishing payroll tax, the States would surrender their<br />
major independent source of revenue. A source of revenue which<br />
after much hard bargaining they managed to extract from the<br />
Commonwealth less than ten years ago.<br />
Our tax policies have increased people's freedom to spend thei * r<br />
own income, have restored incentives, have eased the pressure<br />
on wages, have helped to halve inflation, and will be an important<br />
element in the recovery of employment.<br />
They are an essential part of a responsible striategy for economic<br />
recovery. Mr Whitlam would destroy this aspect of the economic<br />
strategy that has got Australia moving again. Just as he would<br />
undermine every other aspect of that strategy. Particularly<br />
through Labor's extravagant promises $ 800 million expenditure<br />
in the first six months and ant array of other costly programmes<br />
six of which alone would cost $ 3,000 million.<br />
This huge 13ift in government spending would fuel inflation,<br />
crodh-confidence, stop growith and increase anemployment. Massive<br />
governmenft expenditure is Mr Whitlarn's answer to unemployment. </p>
<p>But in the circumstances which via face today, such expenditure<br />
schemes would worsen the prospecits of achieving sutained<br />
reductions in unemployment. i-r TV. hitlaH proposed an. ex. pensive job<br />
sbusidy scheme. This qoverumeit has ex; haustively examined every<br />
possible option with respect to unemployment,<br />
The plain fnct is thnt inassive job subsidy or make -work zchlernes do<br />
rnot work, Labor knows this t-hey tried it when they were in,<br />
government and they failed. They themselves abandoned their<br />
disastrous R. E. D. scheme. The Labor Party scheime to subsidise<br />
employers wages is riddled with faults and contradictions.<br />
It will involve paying ouit very large sums indeed to mta-, y emiployers<br />
without them increasing the number of people in jobs above what<br />
would would have happened anyway. Busi-nesses who are going to<br />
increase t11-heir employment anyway will merely be subsidi * sed by<br />
the goverment. That is,. wasteful expenditure going to increase<br />
-profits of companies who are already most probably _ in a healthy<br />
fanancial position.<br />
Our forecasts are that dinployment will grow in the nextA 6/ 7 m~ onths<br />
the period when Labor proposes to operate the scheme.<br />
Tens of thousands of people, who would be taken into jobs anyway<br />
will now be subsidised at great expense to the Australian<br />
taxpayer. It Tnust also be understood that this job subsidy scheme would mean<br />
the government would be paying out large sums even if total<br />
employment were not increasing. m~ y reason for saying this is<br />
that it is quit-e normal, to ex-pect t~ hat sorte stront: er firma<br />
would be expanding jobs and some contracting. Those expanding<br />
will get a wasteful subsidy the others will be vnaffected.<br />
This normal turnover of staff can proceed with no imrpact on<br />
unemployment<br />
For this reason alone it is quite flase for Mr Whitlat to claim<br />
tha~ t the cost of his scheme would be slight. It is in fact<br />
an ex pensive scheine and in costing his proposed spending for<br />
the second half of this financial year, he should be honest and<br />
add a substa-ntial sum to his $ 800 million.<br />
A fur-ther problem wi th such a scheme is that'it is op~ en. to abu: e<br />
For example, what procedures would work to stop some grou3ps<br />
deliberately running down their employment in one subsidiary,<br />
anid expanding it in another, with subsidised labour. The<br />
contradictions i-n Labor's thinking are well shown out with this<br />
Although Labor is prepared to admit wage costs are too high for<br />
people to be employed, they are persisting with a policy of<br />
increasing wages more rapidly.<br />
Thei-r policy on full wage indeXation worsens the chances of people<br />
look~ ing f or a job. A wage subsidy scheme is not and cannot provide<br />
a sustainable solution to unemployment problems. There is no<br />
answer to be found in wishful thinking or blatant political.<br />
opportunism. The real answer is growth and development.<br />
It's creating new jobs real jobs. Not job. s artifically created<br />
for only six nmonths, thxough a great expansion of government spending.<br />
It's having a responsible wages policy. it's being willing to stand<br />
by a fair and just industrial relations policy. </p>
<p>-6-<br />
The policies Hr Whitlan outlined last week are the direct opposite<br />
o' those Australia now requires. It is vital in the battle against<br />
unemployment that wage and salary restraint be continued.<br />
Labor's policy of full wage index~ ation would increase wagesand<br />
-fuel unemployment. The extreme left wing unionS who<br />
dominated the Labor Party Conference this year have forced<br />
Mr Whitlam to come out for full wage indexation.<br />
As in 1974, M~ r W'itlam wants the government to take the side<br />
of those who want to accelerate the wage piral again. This will be<br />
disastrous for small business all around Australia. It will dest_ roy<br />
thousands of jobs. it is the opposite of what Australia needs.<br />
The pr ogram-uno which the government has developed over the past two<br />
years and the new initiatives which I announced on Monday do<br />
meet Australia's needs. Several of the programmues I announced<br />
are of direct benefit:. to the city and suburbs of Sydney,<br />
Let me brief ul niention Just a few. I do not have to tell you about<br />
the deficiencies in Sydney's public txangport. the life of a I<br />
commuter is not a happy one. We have decided to continue and expand<br />
an existing programme by paying the States a total of<br />
million a year for five years, to help inprove the standards<br />
of our trains and bus services.<br />
VWe have also decided to contribute some $ 70 million over five years<br />
to upgrade critical -sections of mainline railways. For this modest<br />
outlay, many interstate services will be significantly~ improved.<br />
For example, the fast goods capacity between Sydney and Melbourne<br />
will be doubled. Our new national waver resources programme will make<br />
available funds to improve city and country water supplies and such ott<br />
vital projects as the mnitigation--of floods.<br />
Tphe inner-city area-will be helped by our emphasis on providing<br />
' first class technical colleges. Some inner-city colleges are of a<br />
standard whi-ch simply is not acceptable to this government. They will<br />
be modernised or completely replaced.<br />
E~ veryone will be helped by many of our other programmes, such as the<br />
reduction of off peak long distance telephone charges to 40 perceptv<br />
of the normal rate.<br />
Considerable progress has been made over the last two years in resfbti<br />
Australia to economic health. TowardS inaking Australia a more just<br />
and more aqfaitable society. it's been hard work and there are still<br />
problems to be overcome. But-we are seeing the Itangible results<br />
of that work. -Australia is ready to stride into a new era of<br />
prosperity and development. The fundamental question which this<br />
election will decide, is whether we will build on the achievements<br />
which we have made, or whether Labor will be allowed to throw it away.<br />
Seeing how peoplehave been working hard forthe government across<br />
Australia, there is no doubt that we'll be doing the job in 1978<br />
and beyond. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
