<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2608</transcript-id>
    <title>VISIT TO INDONESIA, SINGAPORE AND MALAYSIA BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE RT HON WILLIAM MCMAHONE CH MP - DEPARTURE STATEMENT - SYDNEY</title>
    <prime-minister>McMahon, William</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19710310 - 19721205</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1972</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002608.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS No. 54/ 1972<br />
VISIT TO INDONESIA, SINCAPORF AND MALAYSIA<br />
BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF AUSTRALIA, THE<br />
RT. 11ON. WNILLIAM McDMAHON, C. M. P.<br />
DEPARTURE STATEVENT SYDNEY<br />
I will be leaving tomorrow morning for<br />
Indonesia, Singapore and Malaysia on my first visit to these<br />
countries as Prime Minister. The main purpose of the visit will be to<br />
improve our relations with our three nearest South-East Asian<br />
neighbours, whose friendshiP and co-operation we welcome.<br />
Asia remains a critical area of the world in<br />
which the quest for peace and security will be concentrated in<br />
the future. Indonesia, where my journey starts, is not<br />
only our nearest neighbour, but the fifth largest nation in the<br />
world and the only one with which we share a boundary.<br />
A soundly-based and lasting Australian/<br />
Indonesian relationship is of the greatest importance to us now<br />
and in the future. I want to emphasise Australia's growing and<br />
continuing interest in the South-East Asian region.<br />
Australia is deeplyv interested in the wellbeing<br />
of our Asian friends and we are anxiouis to assist them in their<br />
search for economic growth and regional security.<br />
I also want to extend my own understanding of<br />
each of these countries and of the matters which affect our<br />
security and our economic, trade and social ties and<br />
relationships. </p>
<p>I want to rovicw with Indonesia, Singapore and<br />
Malaysia their thinking, at Mead of Gov rnnant and Ministerial<br />
level, on the changing situation in the Asian and Pacific region.<br />
In my discussions, I exn~ ect to take up such<br />
subjects as the changing roles of the major powers in Asia and<br />
the effects of these ch~ nging roles on South-East Asia.<br />
In Indonesia, I shall be having discussions<br />
with President Soeharto and a. number of his Ministers, including<br />
the Minister-for Foreign Affairs, and I will he joined there by<br />
Mr Bowen. I shall also bo addressing the indonosian Parliament.<br />
In Singapore, I will Jbe having several<br />
discussions with the Prime Ministte-r and the Ministers for<br />
Defence andl for Foreign Tffa:'. rs, and wqill be calling on the<br />
President and visiting thce Ju. rong Tcown Cc,: rporation in which a<br />
number of Australian companies have invested.<br />
I will also visit theD headqukirters of the<br />
A24ZUK Brigade and address the Singaporo Press Club.<br />
In Kuala Lumpur, discussions havc Nbeen arranged<br />
with the Prime Minister, TVun Raz;: k . mid other Ministers. In<br />
these discussions, I want to em phcasise the great: importance we<br />
attach to our relations with Mat ,' ia.<br />
An audience has been arranged with His<br />
Majesty the Yang Di -Per-tuan X-gong and. arrangemants have been<br />
made for a visit to the Buttcrworth Air Baso.<br />
CANBERRA, 4 June 1972 </p>
<p>FOR INFORMATION PRIME MINISTER'S VISIT TO INDONESIA, SINGAPORE<br />
AND MALAYSIA<br />
OUTLINE PROGRAEIE<br />
INDONESIA Monday, 5 June<br />
Tuesday, 6 June<br />
Wednesday, 7 June<br />
Thursday, 8 June<br />
SINGAPORE<br />
Thursday, 8 June<br />
Friday, 9 June<br />
Saturday, 10 June<br />
Sunday, 11 June 4.00 Dm<br />
5.30 pm<br />
9.00 am<br />
10.00 am<br />
1 1 Arrival Courtesy call on President<br />
Call by Governor of Djakarta<br />
noon Discussions with<br />
President Ministers<br />
3.30 pm Calls by Foreign Minister and<br />
Finance Minister<br />
5.30 pm Reception for Australian<br />
community<br />
8.00 pm State Dinner<br />
8.30 am Wreath-laying ceremonies<br />
0.00 am Lay foundation stone ACI joint<br />
prnject site<br />
8.00 om ReLurn Dinner<br />
0.00 am Address to Parliament<br />
3.00 pm Depart for Singapore<br />
5.00 pm<br />
10.00 am<br />
Morning 2.30 pm<br />
8.00 pm<br />
8.30 am<br />
Lunch 6.00 pm<br />
8.00 pm<br />
Rest day<br />
4.10 pm Welcoming Ceremony<br />
Call on President<br />
Discussions with Prime Minister<br />
and Ministers<br />
Visit Jurong Town Corporatbn,<br />
Vocational Institute and an<br />
Australian firm. Tree planting.<br />
State Dinner<br />
Visit Australian Forces<br />
Singapore Press Club<br />
Reception for Australian Commqnity<br />
Return Dinner<br />
Depart for Kuala Lumpur </p>
<p>MALAYSIA Sunday 11 June<br />
Monday, 12 June<br />
Tuesday 13 June<br />
Wednesday 14 June<br />
Thursday 15 June 5.30 pm Welcoming Ceremony<br />
9.00 am Wreath-laying<br />
10.00 am Tal} s with Prime Minister<br />
and Ministers<br />
12.45 pm Audience with Agong<br />
3.30 pm Briefing on security situation<br />
8.15 pm State Dinner<br />
Visit Butter-wrth rluring morning<br />
2.00 pm Inspc';:. vil aviation aid<br />
proj rec<br />
8.30 Dm Return Dinner<br />
9.00 am Visit rubb) r research station<br />
11.15 am National operation? room briefing<br />
Lunch With Deputy Prime Minister<br />
6.00 pm Pecc . tion for Australian community<br />
9.00 pm Depart for Australia<br />
7.20 am Arrive Sydney. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
