<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9367</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP 40TH ALP NATIONAL CONFERENCE HOBART, 26 SEPTEMBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/09/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009367.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
c'c<br />
jZ<br />
PRIME MINJISTER<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
ALP NATIONAL CONFERENCE<br />
HOBART, 26 SEPTEMBER 1994<br />
A century of Australian nationhood has almost passed.<br />
The Australian Labor Party was there at the beginning. It is still here and in 1994,<br />
we can truly say, it is stronger than ever before.<br />
We were born with the Australian nation. We were born of and for the Australian<br />
people. Our tradition is with them both the nation and the people.<br />
Our responsibility is to them both.<br />
Through wars and depression, through triumphs and calamities, through every chapter<br />
in the story of Australia the Labor Party has been there.<br />
We have gone through all manner of travail with Australia and for Australia. And<br />
now, a hundred years after our foundation, we Lk-a Australia.<br />
That is one magnificent fact the fact we should not forget this week.<br />
And I'll tell you one more great fact: if we have the courage the love, the labour and<br />
the imagination we can lead Australia into the twenty-first century.<br />
And I mean lead. I don't mean manage, or re-arrange. ' I don't mean occupy time and<br />
space. I don't mean talk until the people of Australia stop listening.<br />
I mean do the things which need doing. Live up to our ideals of what a good society<br />
is and how great a country this can be.<br />
It is the most extraordinary party, the Australian Labor Party. I am in no doubt it is<br />
one of the very great political parties in the world lumpy, grumpy, difficult thing that<br />
it is, no party in the world of its faith and vintage looks so strong today.<br />
In the 1 890s the men and women of the Labor movement had enough faith in<br />
themselves and their ideals to imagine that they the working people of Australia<br />
could determine the shape of their country in thie twentieth century.<br />
And in the 1 990s this is the remarkable thing, and I might say, for the leader of the<br />
Parry, the humbling thing we are superbly placed to determnine the shape of our<br />
country, according to mn ideals and = jj faith, in the twenty-first century.<br />
Our responsibility is as great now as it was then.<br />
The dimensions of the task are just as great. </p>
<p>But we could scarcely be better placed to succeed.<br />
In the hundred years of our history the Labor Party has been all but mortally wounded<br />
once or twice. We have been lost. We have stumbled. we have split, we have been<br />
becalmed. But not now.<br />
We are in office. We are doing what we do best which is making the changes,<br />
preparing Australia for the fu~ ture. And we are bringing the people with us.<br />
And let me pause here to recognise and applaud the contribution of the party and the<br />
trade unions those who kept the faith and who made such a mighty effort in 1993 to<br />
see that Labor was returned.<br />
We are doing what we said we would do. We are doing what Labor shu do. With<br />
the unemployed, employment and training. With child care. With Aboriginal<br />
Australians. With industrial relations.<br />
And it is because we are doingz what we do best that we have run the Opposition<br />
ragged. We should not forget that. Modern politics might look like a game of personalities,<br />
but it is really a matter of policies.<br />
What won the last election for Labor?<br />
The things we stood for won it for us.<br />
The social policies, Medicare. the rights of Aboriginal Australians, the rights of<br />
women, the central place of the arts, the republic. We won it with our vision of<br />
Australia. And that's what ultimately brought John Hewson down this year.<br />
Not his personality, or mine, or anyone else's. The Native Title legislation brought<br />
him down. The White Paper on Employment brought him down.<br />
When the Liberals were called on to support legislation to right Australia's oldest<br />
wrong the lie that the continent had been empty before Europeans came nothing in<br />
their hearts and minds could make them do it.<br />
It was beyond their moral reach. They said the passage of the Native Title Bill was " a<br />
day of shame".<br />
When they were confronted with a thoroughgoing package of programs to bring the<br />
long term unemployed back into the mainstream the people on whose backs they had<br />
attempted to ride to power they sneered. They said it was " irresponsible" to reach<br />
back for the unemployed.<br />
The Coalition response to those two initiatives made plain for all to see that the soul<br />
of the Liberal Party is an empty place a vacant lot, a void once filled by the solid<br />
bluestone face of Australian conservatism.<br />
And what has brought our opponents to this sorry state? Putting our convictions on<br />
the line. </p>
<p>If we have one thin,-to thank John Hewvson for it is that his brand of radical<br />
conservatism created a contest between fundamental beliefs and. even with the<br />
effects of recession all around. ours were stronaer.<br />
Let's not forget what our opponents intended to do. And let's not forget what<br />
defeating them meant.<br />
Ten billion dollars cut from public expenditure one billion from social security,<br />
$ 400 million from public housing, a 25 per cent cut in labour market spending.<br />
Youth wages of $ 3 an hour, a training system under which unemployed people could<br />
have been paid 70 per cent of the award, with no requirement that the employer train<br />
them. Full fees for university, the abolition of bulk-billing under Medicare for most people,<br />
a $ 1I. 3 billion cut in funding for public hospitals.<br />
Never did the Australian people have a clearer reminder of what profound differences<br />
lie at the heart of the political contest.<br />
Our opponents have now poured a blancmange into the hole John Hewson dug for<br />
them. They are trying to soften the debate. They are spouting embarrassingly<br />
juvenile and disingenuous flim flamn.<br />
But pleasurable as it is to defeat our opponents and re-affirm. our political ascendancy,<br />
the real pleasure is in what we have done. And what is now open for us to do.<br />
What we have done in regard to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders is a case in<br />
point. I dare say we have done more of a profound kind than any other Government<br />
since Federation and by doing it we have left the way open to do a great deal more.<br />
1 count the Native Title Act as one of Labor's great achievements. It is legislation of<br />
which every member of tfiis party should be proud.<br />
With the National Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Land Fund, which will enable<br />
Aboriginals who will not directly benefit from the Act to purchase land, we now. have<br />
the legal and moral foundations of a new era for indigenous Australians.<br />
There is a great deal more to do. The $ 500 million allocated in this year's Budget to<br />
improving the health of Aboriginal Australians will go some way to doing it.<br />
No-one believes that change to the law or the expenditure of vast amounts of money<br />
will get us there alone. But both are essential. What matters between now and the<br />
turn of the century is good will and uncompromising application on both sides.<br />
We have lived with this shame throughout the first century of our nationhood. I don't<br />
believe that any Australian indigenous or non-indigenous should have to live with<br />
it in the next century.<br />
As long as I am Prime Minister, ending that shame wiW be one of the great goals of<br />
the Labor Government.<br />
And so will be ending the blight of unemployment.<br />
When I said on election night that we would not leave the unemployed behind. I have<br />
no doubt that there were people on both sides of politics disinclined to believe me.<br />
Some may have doubted the Government's intent, some the Government's ability. </p>
<p>The White Paper on Employment which we brought down in M'vay was proof that we<br />
had both.<br />
I am not sure that the dimensions of Working YNation have been properly appreciated.<br />
But it is a document of infinitely more prescriptive detail and sophistication than the<br />
famous White Paper of the 1 940s.<br />
For the Labor Party, jobs have always been the highest priority. For the Labor Party,<br />
unemployment is the greatest pain. So the White Paper is a quintessential Labor Party<br />
Labor Gove~ rmntn document.<br />
No other country has produced an integrated strategy as wide-ranging and ambitious<br />
as Working iMation. No other country has; created such a complete employment<br />
package. And it has already helped thousands of Australians.<br />
The White Paper rests on the basic principle that while economic growth is the best<br />
way of generating new and worthwhile jobs, by itself it is not adequate to the task of<br />
reducing unemployment, particularly long-term unemployment.<br />
That growth is creating jobs is beyond doubt 340.000 new jobs have been created<br />
since April last year.<br />
But what is also beyond doubt is that Government policies are helping to find work<br />
for the long-term unemployed.<br />
In the 1980s only 7 per cent of the 1.6 million jobs created went to the long-term<br />
unemployed, compared to 22 per cent or 76,000 of the 340,000 new jobs since the<br />
last election.<br />
Overall, we've seen the number of long-term unemployed drop to the lowest level in<br />
31 months.<br />
This is not an accident; it's in part a consequence of a better performance from the<br />
CES. and in part a result of the White Paper which has seern 116,000 people enter case<br />
management under the Job Compact.<br />
I want to remind the Conference of just how ambitious this Job Compact is.<br />
Essentially it offers a job guarantee to the most disadvantaged group in the workforce.<br />
It means that all people unemployed for more than 18 months are entitled to a job,<br />
training or individual case management. It means that the Australians worst hit by<br />
restructuring and recession and least able to share in the recovery will be brought into<br />
the mainstream.<br />
It is an argument about both equity and efficiency.<br />
Re-skilling the unemployed means a greater pool of resources with which to fill new<br />
jobs. It means more employment and, therefore, less unemployment benefits and<br />
more tax revenue. And because it means a more effective labour supply, it means the<br />
economy can expand more rapidly without running into wage inflation pressures.<br />
it means, according to one academic analysis, that the annual net production of goods<br />
and services can be increased by around $ 2 billion a year. </p>
<p>It is one of the distinauishing features of conservative ideology that it will not admit<br />
that there is efficiency in equity.<br />
We say the two go hand in hand. We say that no society can afford to leave large<br />
numbers of people on the margins it cannot be justified on moral grounds or social<br />
grounds or economic grounds.<br />
We say that not to strive to bring the long term unemployed back into the mainstream<br />
is to betray both our own principles and this and future generations of Australians.<br />
The White Paper is not merely a matter of salvaging the unemployed from hardship<br />
and despair, and preventing the development of an underclass.<br />
It is about developing a training system to match any in the world and, eventually, a<br />
workforce as skilled as any in the world.<br />
The measures of the White Paper are the means by which every young Australian will<br />
have a place in education, training or employment.<br />
We often talk about the social safety net. No broad policy commitment so<br />
distinguishes us from our opponents.<br />
We see it as a measure of a sophisticated society. We say sophisticated societies are<br />
cohesive and inclusive. Put another way, we say they are measured by the degree to<br />
which the bonds of care run through the social system.<br />
We say that as we measure families and communities by the degree of effective care<br />
and security they provide, we measure countries.<br />
And we say those who talk about the virtues of families and communities while<br />
advocating a reduction in the size and effectiveness of the social safety net are talkng<br />
humbug. On this side of politics, we believe in the family and in the community. And we say<br />
that the safety net is essential to their well-being.<br />
Medicare is essential to the health of Australian families and communities. It is one<br />
of the world's most successful health systems. Before Medicare, nearly 2 million<br />
Australians had no health cover. With Medicare, every Australian has health cover.<br />
And, with Medicare, health expenditure as a proportion of GDP has been kept well<br />
below most comparable countries.<br />
So is child care essential to Australian families and Australian communities. From<br />
46,000 places in 1982-83, we have grown the national child care system to 242,000<br />
places and we are committed to meeting all demand for work-related care by 2000.<br />
We are providing fee relief for lower to middle income families and assistance for all<br />
working families through the Child Care rebate.<br />
Support for working women is essential to the health of Australian families and<br />
communities. Child care is one major means of support. So is the Superannuation<br />
Guarantee Charge which has increased superannuation coverage for women working<br />
full-time from 47 per cent to 87 per cent, and for those working part-time, from 19 per<br />
cent to 65 per cent.<br />
The Child-Support Scheme is essential to the health of families and communities.<br />
Before the Scheme, only about 30 per cent of non-custodial parents paid child support<br />
now 75 per cent of liabilities are collected. </p>
<p>The Labor Government's achievements in promoting the rights and status of women<br />
have made Australia a world leader.<br />
It was Labor which introduced the Sex Discrimination Act in 1984. Ten years before<br />
that, a Labor Government established the Office for the Status of Women which is<br />
still going strong in its 20th year.<br />
There is a great deal yet to be done. We must get more women into the parliaments of<br />
Australia and we are now committed to doing that. When half the population is more<br />
strongly represented we will all be stronger for it.<br />
For all our shortcomings, wherever you look for milestones for women in Australia in<br />
the past 20 years it is Labor which has put them there.<br />
Just as it is Labor which has put the vast majority of social programs there.<br />
We have created social policies and programs with few equals in the world. Our<br />
emphases have shifted in many regards, yet the thrust of our thinking today still<br />
echoes the aspirations of those who founded the Labor Party 100 years ago.<br />
What we have delivered is a real. measurable, felt degree of social justice. A tangible<br />
slice of the fair go. And by fostering stability and cohesion, broadening opportunity,<br />
and calling on all the skills and ambition of all our people, that fair go will help<br />
deliver us the future.<br />
The safety net has another function which our opponents seem not to recognise It is<br />
not just a component but a condition of change.<br />
Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Accord.<br />
The Accord delivered a truly effective social wage. It enabled us to cut inflation, lift<br />
employment and reduce strikes.<br />
We can measure its value over the past decade in terms of a 30 per cent reduction in<br />
labour costs on the one hand, and a 35 per cent increase in real disposable household<br />
incomes on the other.<br />
Over that same decade we have seen inflation reduced ' from. more than I11 per cent to<br />
less than 2 per cent; the number of working days lost reduced to a figure which last<br />
year was the lowest since the Australian Bureau of Statistics began publishing the<br />
series in 1967; and we have seen the creation of 1.7 million jobs.<br />
The debt which this Labor Government and the Australian nation owes to the modemn<br />
labour movement is immeasurable.<br />
Far from being a matter of discomfort to us, our close relationship with the trade<br />
unions is a matter of great satisfaction. I can think of few relationships which have<br />
delivered Australia so much.<br />
Now as we reform Australian workplaces and develop an industrial relations system<br />
based on enterprise bargalning, the Government's Accord with the unions is providing<br />
the essential transition mechanism.<br />
The Accord is allowing increased Labor market flexibility without the high costs of<br />
strikes or wage breakouts that might be expected to accompany such substantial<br />
change. </p>
<p>The Accord is also providing the safety net to protect lower paid workers who would<br />
otherwise miss out on wage increases. Enterprise bargaining alone cannot protect<br />
lower paid workers. It will not protect the industrially weak. Only enterprise<br />
bargaining under the Accord will provide both flexibility and a de'cent level of<br />
protection. Last week with the IRC decision to grant a $ 24 a week increase to low-paid workers,<br />
we saw the system working the system which this Government has put into place<br />
since the election.<br />
Yet,* just in case any of us needed reminding, we heard the employers caviling against<br />
the decision. There they were, complaining about a wage increase for the low-paid<br />
which will see wages increase by only half a per cent, while executive salaries have<br />
risen on average more than 4 per cent, and the profit share is at record levels.<br />
And there was John Howard saying that the award system was a terrible thine.<br />
Australia has economic growth the equal of or surpassing any in the OECD.<br />
Employment growth is high. The profit share is high. The inflation rate is low. We<br />
have new flexibility in the labour market.<br />
Yet they are carping about the benefits of this recovery flowing through to the<br />
Australian people. You have to ask what meanness inspires them?<br />
It really could not be more ironic. Working Australians have been made to respond to<br />
competitive pressures. Unions have had to adjust and re-structure. They have had to<br />
accept productivity-related wage adjustments.<br />
Business has had to do these things too.<br />
But those who preach competition loudest, who condemn the safety net and parade up<br />
and down flexing their laissez-faire muscles the Liberal-led states shrink from<br />
implementing competition policy.<br />
Never mind about the rights of the vast majority of Australians who stand to get<br />
cheaper services and more jobs out of the implementation of competition policy. And<br />
never mind about the nation which will be made that much more competitive by it.<br />
The conservatives ask us to believe that the Federation was Qreated for the purpose of<br />
enshrining the unassailable rights of the states.<br />
Wrong. Federation created an Australian nation and the purpose of the nation is to<br />
protect and further the interests of the people the Aiistralin people, not Victorian<br />
people or West Australian people, or Northern Territory people, but th-P people.<br />
It seems to me the difference between the Labor Party and its opponents is that we<br />
draw strength from the past while they seek refuge in it.<br />
It seems to me that our opponents are drifting further and fuirther away from the<br />
direction Australia is going. They are losing touch with contemporary Australia.<br />
My reading may be wrong, but I think there is a new mood emerging a renewed<br />
concern with our national identity and national destiny which reflects the changes in<br />
the social composition and economic structure of Australia, and an awareness of the<br />
opportunities which await us in the next century. </p>
<p>I think that as a Government and as a Party we have to move with the mood. I believe<br />
it is the mood of younger Australians and that it may well be defining the direction of<br />
our history.<br />
I am sure it is taking us toward a Republic.<br />
In recent times, effectively we have handed the baton of the Republic to the<br />
Australian people and I am in little doubt that they will carry it across the line.<br />
A healthy debate is now underway. We want to see the idea of the republic become<br />
clearer in the public mind. As it becomes clearer the resolve will grow stronger.<br />
So we have the economic fundamentals, the social fundamentals and increasingly, I<br />
believe, we have a spirit at large not dissimilar to the one which 100 years ago created<br />
the Australian nation.<br />
We have as well, for the first time in our history, the world's bliggest and fastestgrowing<br />
markets at our doorstep.<br />
Australia's public policy Labor's public policy is for the first time comprehending<br />
this development by seeing it as part of the national policy reach.<br />
That is why we have so vigorously pursued the development of APEC.<br />
Perhaps APEC does not at first glance sound like a Labor agenda item.<br />
But I assure you it is.<br />
The Australian Labor government has been a driving force in APEC. We have taken<br />
on this role because APEC offers the means by which Australia and other countries in<br />
the region can keep the dynamics of growth going among half the world's population.<br />
To put it simply the great growth in our trade, including our trade in manufactures,<br />
has been in Asia and the Pacific. That is where our future prosperity lies.<br />
It is on growth there that our opportunities substantially depend.<br />
A more liberal regional trading environment will encourage. and sustain that growth.<br />
The APEC leaders' meeting in Bogor in November is therefore of importance to a lot<br />
more people than Paul Keating or Gareth Evans or Bob McMullan it is of profound<br />
importance to Australian exporters, Australian farmers, Australian workers.<br />
The Labor Party should not underestimate these sorts of initiatives from Labor<br />
Governments. Our role as a convener of the Cairns Group of agricultural producers was instrumental<br />
in getting a Uruguay Round result which is likely to add $ 3.7 billion to Australia's<br />
GDP. No one can estimate what even modest success with APEC might be worth. But we<br />
can readily guess what the consequence of not trying would be it would be to live<br />
with the knowledge that we saw necessity and turned away, that we had a chance to<br />
provide opportunities for succeeding generations of Australians and passed it up.<br />
I count it among the Government's most important achievements that we have<br />
established a creative role for Australia in the region; and whether it has been in<br />
APEC, or the ASEAN Regional Forum or the South Pacific Forum, we have built that </p>
<p>role around promoting prosperity, limiting friction and encouraging cooperation and<br />
stability. If the national interest means the interests of the Australian people. and the interest of<br />
the Australian people is in their future and the future of their children, then there are<br />
two other less traditional Labor subjects the Labor Government must address.<br />
You will be aware that in the last few weeks I have visited some of the drought areas<br />
of Queensland and New South Wales.<br />
You will also be aware that we have delivered a comprehensive drought package to<br />
those farmers in the worst hit areas.<br />
The problems for those farmers and communities are acute they are human and<br />
social problems, as well as financial and economic ones.<br />
Our response. I believe, has been an appropriately comprehensive, compassionate and<br />
intelligent one.<br />
And I might say in passing that for this Bob Collins has received less credit than he<br />
deserves. It is ailways easy for a Minister, when faced with a problem, to turn up with<br />
the hand extended. It is one thing to ask for money, another thing altogether to<br />
develop good, constructive policies.<br />
Drought. of course. is a familiar problem. Generation after generation of rural<br />
Australians have had to endure them, and so have the national balance sheets.<br />
Yet as a nation we may be able to contrive something positive from this drought.<br />
Perhaps it can remind us that the bonds between Australians are much stronger than<br />
the divisions.<br />
Rural Australians may nC~ t always vote for us, but that will not prevent us providing<br />
help when they need it. The unemployed are no less unemployed for living in the<br />
bush. Frustrated ambition is no less painful there than it is in the cities.<br />
What this long drought has put at risk is the future of the family farms which sustain<br />
and in large part define the bush. There is an element of ourculture at stake here, a<br />
way of life, as well as a vital element of our economy.<br />
And perhaps it can be the spur to recognising an even greater problem than the<br />
drought itself.<br />
No one can visit these drought affected regions of Australia or virtually any region<br />
of rural Australia without being struck by the degree of land degradation of one kind<br />
or another.<br />
You do not need expert training to recognise it. Nor do you need to be a particularly<br />
conscientious environmentalist.<br />
You only need an eye and an ear.<br />
The eye will tell you that this is not the way the country used to look, nor how<br />
productive land is meant to look.<br />
The ear will tell you what the farmers say themselves these days: that we are losing<br />
great tracts of land to salinity and erosion. That there has been too much clearing.<br />
That our streams and soils are degraded. That along with the natural environment we </p>
<p>are losing productivity and that. in some cases. is threatening the foundations of<br />
regional economies.<br />
Through a variety of programs, including the extraordinarifly successful National<br />
Landcare program. the Government has been combating these problems.<br />
In Working Nation we took a major initiative with Australia's regions: we decided to<br />
help regional development organisations find the best way to sustainable. long-term<br />
productive land use.<br />
Through the Rural Adjustment Scheme we will help to create a more rational and<br />
environmentally-sensitive pattern of land use. We will help people to get off land<br />
which is not viable. We will help people use viable land in more sustainable ways.<br />
I am sure that we will be helped in this process by the dramatic change in thinking<br />
which is occuring in rural Australia. We have a new breed of farmers aware that<br />
good environmental practice is good farm practice, and good business practice. And<br />
we want to encourage them.<br />
The drought might just spread the message wider, and it might get the whole country<br />
on a path to sustainable development.<br />
It might be that another generation will look back on this drought and say that it was a<br />
turning point. That it was the drought which made us aware of the need to renovate<br />
and restore the land, to use it sensibly and sustainably that this was the moment<br />
when rural industry and the environment got onto the same track.<br />
The land is a major challenge for our generation. It is a major challenge for the<br />
Government. There are some uncanny parallels between this challenge and that of a century ago: in<br />
this one, as in that one, economic downturns and drought have been accompanied<br />
somewhat paradoxically by themes of national identity and nationhood.<br />
In this decade I hope, as in that earlier one, we have grown more conscious of the<br />
values and interests we share that for all our differenc es and the vast distances which<br />
separate us, our primary loyalty and affection is to this nation and we are remarkably<br />
close. In the 1890s. the spread of telegraph and railway lines gave a material dimension to<br />
the national sentiment.<br />
In the 1990s it is the information highway.<br />
Someone wrote in the American magazine, " Harper's", last month that the information<br />
revolution is " the most transforming technological event since the capture of fire."<br />
We do not know quite what the dimensions of this change will be. But we do know it<br />
is already upon us, that it is going to change our lives profoundly, and that it is all<br />
going to happen very quickly.<br />
Whether we like it or not, it will change the way we communicate with each other, the<br />
way we learn, the way we do business, the way we create the way we lead our daily<br />
lives. </p>
<p>Perhaps some of us don~ t know. But if we don't. our kids do. We know what a CD is.<br />
but they know what a CD-RONI is. We know what a VCR does, they know how to<br />
program it.<br />
What the Government knows is that we are fast approachingz a moment in our history<br />
where how well we play the information game will determine how well we prosper.<br />
We know that the information superhighway has the potential to create great new<br />
industries and new jobs for Australia. It has the potential to serve us very well.<br />
The important thing is to make sure that we don't become too obsessed with the<br />
highway itself. Building the highway is important, but inventing the things that go on<br />
it is more important.<br />
The production of content is the key for Australia. If we can use the information<br />
highway to find better ways of. say, delivering our Social Security programs, teaching<br />
our children, getting health programs to all Australians, taking art and science beyond<br />
the major cities the information highway will not only improve the quality of our<br />
national life, it will create a whole new industry, a whole new milieu.<br />
And given our natural advantages, that industry can export to the rest of the world.<br />
Those natural advantages include an advanced film and television industry, a highly<br />
educated population. th English language and the many other languages Australians<br />
speak. You will see these sorts of issues addressed in the Government's cultural policy which<br />
will be launched next month.<br />
The immnediate challenges are to find ways of linking our creative and software<br />
communities. We need to get more PCs and CD-ROMs in our schools. We need<br />
more university and TAFE-programs focussed on multimedia.<br />
There is a lot more we need to do. But none of it is beyond us, and if our children are<br />
to have the best possible chance as the information revolution unfolds, we simply<br />
have to do it.<br />
Most crucially, the superhighway the optic fibre highway must be a highway for all<br />
Australians. If we can readily share and disseminate information among ourselves, we will be a far<br />
stronger and more prosperous country. We will avoid becoming a nation of the<br />
information-rich and the information-poor.<br />
That reason the access and equity reason is one of two principal reasons why the<br />
information revolution is a primary concern for a Labor Government.<br />
The other principal reason is that it represents an enormous challenge an inescapable<br />
challenge for any Government which believes its duty is to Australia and the<br />
Australian people.<br />
As I said when I began, the Australian Labor Party was born with the Australian<br />
nation and the Australian people as they were defining themselves.<br />
And those two elements still detine our role.<br />
The people depend on us. We are in Government because a lot of people depend on<br />
our being there: the people who would not have medical cover without us; the people </p>
<p>who would not get the necessary help to restart tneir ilives after a period orf<br />
unemployment: the people who would not have the protection ot an industrial award:<br />
Aboriginal Australians.<br />
We need to be in office for these people for Australian working men and women.<br />
For those who fall behind.<br />
But that is not the only reason.<br />
We need to be there to lead Australia into the next century. To deliver on the promise<br />
the future holds. To state the common purpose above the parochial. To project our<br />
nationhood. To take uptth e social and economic challenges, the challenge of the<br />
region, the challenges of technology and the environment. To meet the twenty,-first<br />
century with confidence. To do justice to the rightful expectations of our children<br />
and to the memory of those who have brought us through.<br />
It is daunting, but certainly not beyond us.<br />
I think we should delight in the prospect.<br />
The great thing is that at the end of a century we have earned the right to lead<br />
Australia into another.<br />
And our faith is as strong as it ever was.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
