<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>800</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE KEITH MURRAY BUILDING, LINCOIN COLLEGE UNIVERSITY OF ADELAIDE ON 1ST SEPTEMBER, 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000800_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
OPENING OF THE KEITH MURRAY BUILDING, LINCOLN COLLEGE<br />
UNIVERSITY OF ADELAIDE<br />
ON 1ST SEPTEMBER, 1963<br />
Speech by the Prime Ministerj the Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Menzies<br />
Mr. President, Mr. Premier, Mr. Vice-Chancellor and Ladies and<br />
Gentlemen The Vice-Chancellor is by way of bei. ng a friend of<br />
mine and therefore does me proud, as you might say, but I regret<br />
to tell you that he has omitted some of my academic qualifications<br />
which really entitle me to be here. He has entirely overlooked<br />
the fact that, causa honoris, if for no other reason, I am a<br />
surgeon, a physician, a gynaecologist and obstetrician ( Laughter),<br />
an architect oh, and I forget. And those no doubt give me<br />
spurious qualification for being here, but I don't mind telling<br />
you that my reason for being here, coming over this morning and<br />
going back first thing tomorrow, has a great deal to do not only<br />
with you but with Sir Keith Murray.<br />
This is the Keith Murray Building and I have been<br />
invited I notice with groat interest to name it. Not to open<br />
it or anything of that kind, but to name it, Yesterday afternoon<br />
at the University of Melbourne I found that my task in relation<br />
to the new physiological research building was not to open it but<br />
to dedicate it. Now Sir, this is a task entirely beyond io,<br />
I would have to require it to be performed by others more<br />
ecclesiastically eminent than I am. However, I did it. ( Laughter)<br />
As I told them I remembered that it is only a few years ago that,<br />
speaking at a luncheon of the Presbyterian General Assembly in<br />
Melbourne7 I was introduced by an enthusiastic Moderator-General<br />
as the " Right Reverend R. G. Menzies." ( Laughter) And some of this<br />
aura has no doubt hung about me, so I dedicated a laboratory full<br />
of sheep yesterday and now I am opening a new wing of a college<br />
occupied not by sheep but by..... well, who knows? ( Laughter)<br />
The connection between Sir Keith Murray and yourselves<br />
is a very real one. After all, he was, at the time this College<br />
was established, the head of Lincoln College at Oxford and that<br />
in itself is a very considerable title of honour when you consider<br />
that John Wesley was a Fellow of Lincoln College at Oxford and<br />
remember with pride, as you should, be you Presbyterian like me<br />
or Methodist like Norman Makin that John Wesley was one of the<br />
very great men in the eighteenth century, a century not barren<br />
of great men, not barren of significant people in our history.<br />
Through all its masterly precision, its slight artificiality, its<br />
beautiful craftsmanship, its lovely architecture, there came the<br />
sort of warm pulse of John Wesley, always to be remembered, one<br />
of the immortals of English history. That, I think would be<br />
agreed by everybody. Well here he was, a Fellow of Lincoln.<br />
Keith Murray, the hood of Lincoln.<br />
Back in 1951 1950 or 1951, I've forgotten which<br />
we had I being tremendously keen on university development,<br />
established a sort of ad hoc cormittee to have a look at the<br />
funds and see what needed to be done, and out of this emerged a<br />
grant, a modest enough grant as one sees it now, of about LIM<br />
a year towards the State universities. The very first question<br />
that arose with that co-mittee at quite a late stage in its<br />
deliberations was whether the university colleges, the affiliated<br />
colleges largely church foundations, should in any way at all be<br />
the beneliciaries of any grant that we made, and the cormittee at<br />
that time wasn't very enthusiastic about it. I, myself7 the<br />
most mild-mannered of men, the least qualified to be a dictator, </p>
<p>-2-<br />
spoke to them with a somewhat dictatorial voice and said that<br />
if they believed that a university could reach its full stature<br />
without its affiliated colleges, they were in bitter disagreement<br />
with myself and I would pay little attention to their<br />
report. And in the result there was a small matter I have<br />
forgotten, œ 20,000 or œ 30,000 out of the particular grant<br />
recommended that went, on some basis or other, to the residential<br />
colleges. That was a beginning.<br />
Then, of course, the next stroke was this other<br />
illuminating idea which came to my mind. I have had very few<br />
bright ideas in my life and therefore I can remember them all<br />
without any difficulty. But it occurred to me that what was<br />
needed was not just a sort of catchpenny idea of making a little<br />
grant something to keep the wolf from the door, but what was<br />
needed was a complete and basic examination of the university<br />
problem. This became all the more important because, let<br />
us all remember, that whereas universities before the war might<br />
have, even in the case of the largest of them, 3,000 or 4,000<br />
students, after the war? the demand for tertiary education grew,<br />
not only at an arithmetical progression, but at a geometrical<br />
progression so that instead of having an estimated demand of<br />
20,000 it suddenly appeared to be 30 000 or 35,000. Instead<br />
of 35,600 itsuddenly appeared to be 5,000. And of course,<br />
it was quite manifest that this presented financial problems<br />
utterly beyond the scope of the State Parliaments and Governments,<br />
that the Commonwealth must cone to this party and come to it<br />
in a big way, and if we wore to do that, then we must have some<br />
examination made by a competent body which would not only nap<br />
out the probable future of the universitius, but also ostinate<br />
their future requirements and try to envisage the ways and<br />
means of their development and what would happen to them and<br />
what faculties would expand more than others.<br />
As the first thing you do after you have had a<br />
bright idea is to find a man or men, that's the greatest<br />
problem in life. Somebody suggested to no, " Well, what about<br />
trying to get Sir K-ith Murray. You are going to England this<br />
year. Why not get him? Ho's the Chairman of the Universities<br />
Grants CoLnission and vastly experienced." So I saw him and<br />
he was quite enthusiastic about this. He was to be the Chairnan.<br />
As you know, we ultimately developed a very strong comi: ittoe<br />
about hin. He said to me, " Well, I would like to do this.<br />
It will take sorao months, of course, and I don't know whether<br />
my Minister would let n'o go." So I said, " Who is your Minister?"<br />
" Well," he said, " the Chancellor of the Exchequer", The<br />
Universities Grants Commission in Australia is rosponsible to<br />
me, but in England the Grants Connmission is responsible to the<br />
Chancellor of the Exchequer which is a very different thing.<br />
So I said at that time " Well of course, that's Harold<br />
Macmillan". " Yes." So I went to Harold Macmillan and with<br />
groat goodwill, he said, " Yes, you may have him." So he came<br />
out, and as you remember, many of you, ho nade, with his<br />
Committee, a long investigation.<br />
He understood perfectly the kind of thing that<br />
I had in my own mind about the affiliated colleges, with the<br />
results that have been spoken of here today. He made an<br />
examination which I believe will remain a classic in the history<br />
of Australian education, so long as Australia exists. It was<br />
a masterly report, and being a mastorly report, it overwhelmed<br />
mo and I, in turn, by giving Cabinet singularly little notice,<br />
overwhelmod the Cabinet. oo** o </p>
<p>-3-<br />
So all the recommendations were adopted and<br />
since then, as you know, with the Universities Commission, the<br />
position has gone from strength to strength, never so strong<br />
as you would desire, never I hope will it be so good as you<br />
would desire because that would be the end of the road if the<br />
universities of Australia said, " Well, we have all we need,<br />
thank you. We have no fresh worlds to conquer." You always<br />
will, but at the same time I say, and you will agree, that<br />
the position of the Australian universities of today has been,<br />
in a very real sense, revolutionised over the last ten years.<br />
As I am here speaking at a college within the<br />
University of Adelaide, I may tell you, though I hope nobody<br />
will allow this to be known across the border, that Koith<br />
Murray after making all his investigations was having a long<br />
talk with me just before he made his report and I said, " Well,<br />
which university in Australia strikes you as coming closest<br />
to your idea of a university," and he said, " Beyond question,<br />
Adelaide." Now I am not just telling you that for fun.<br />
This is what he said to me. He did.' t mean by that, that in<br />
Adelaide you had the best grounds because you don't, or the<br />
greatest supply of buildings because this doesn't follow, or<br />
that the affiliated colleges live in handsome lawns and on<br />
ancient walls and gardens. No, he didntt mean that at all.<br />
What he meant was that there was a spirit here at the University<br />
that appealed to him. There was an understanding of what a<br />
university was for and, above all, that there was a feeling<br />
down North Terrace and through the city among men of affairs<br />
and men of business that they did have some interest in the<br />
University, that they felt for it that they wanted it to<br />
succeed, that they were prepared lo contribute some of their<br />
own time and talent and effort to its work. In other words,<br />
that there was a community aspect surrounding the Adelaide<br />
University which appealed to him enormously.<br />
Now having tediously recited to you some of his<br />
history but I think it is necessary to do that because this,<br />
after all, is to be the Keith Murray Wing and he is a groat<br />
and good man I'd just like to conclude by saying something to<br />
you about the colleges themselves.<br />
I know that our forefathers, grandfathers, whoever<br />
they might be according to our ago, struck a great blow for<br />
what they were prepared to call free, secular and compulsory<br />
education. Secular..... and, of course if you are going<br />
to have compulsory education and I am sure that, by and large<br />
that has been a wondorful thing for Australia; I daresay that<br />
it is very hard to get away from the fact that it will be in its<br />
nature secular because we are a mixed society, but I have never<br />
been able to believe that that is where we ought to stop.<br />
I have never boon able to believe that we ought to regard the<br />
cultivation of the mind as something entirely detached from<br />
the cultivation of the spirit. It is, in my opinion, a disaster<br />
when education in any country comes to be almost rigidly separated<br />
from religious faith or religious teaching or religious background,<br />
because it becomes a one-sided thing.<br />
And, therefore, I have throughout these modern<br />
developments wanted to see as much done as possible for those<br />
affiliated colleges which in particular are colleges affiliated<br />
with the Churches of Australia because I think that here, in<br />
this college, for example, there may meet together and fuse<br />
ultimately the feelings of pure intellectualism and the feelings<br />
of pure religious learning and faith. Those two things, by<br />
fusing, will produce bigger and better people, better citizens,<br />
00 0a/ 4 </p>
<p>more useful people, people who will increase the existing<br />
minority of people who think first of their duties and only<br />
second of their rights.<br />
And therefore, Sir, I am a tremendous supporter<br />
of the residential colleges. I was delighted when only ten<br />
years ago, eleven years this College was established.<br />
Not an easy matter, not a cheap matter, a matter which will<br />
continue to put big burdens on your community and, of course,<br />
increasing burdens upon the Governments Federal and State who<br />
are contributors to those matters, but that it is worthwhile<br />
I have no doubt whatever. When I say all that I hope that<br />
nobody will suppose I am denouncing State education. I am<br />
not. I am its beneficiary. In a country State school and in<br />
a bigger town State school and on State scholarships and<br />
what-have-you, I know something about what the State provides<br />
and I have been its beneficiary, but I have also grown up<br />
more and more to believe in the significance of these places<br />
of residence which have the characteristics to which I have<br />
referred and I know how much you agree with me and how many<br />
people there are here this afternoon who have put their ninds<br />
and hearts into this enterprise.<br />
Therefore, Sir, I have singular pleasure in<br />
doing what I have been instructed on the paper to do I name<br />
this the Keith Murray Building. I can't declare it open<br />
because it bears every sign of having been opened for some<br />
time. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
