<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>668</transcript-id>
    <title>SECOND READING SPEECH BY TEH PRIME MINISTER RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES, C.H., Q.C., M.P. - STATES GRANTS (UNIVERSITIES) BILL (NO.2) 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/12/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000668_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
SECOND READING SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
RT. HON. R. G. MENZIES, M. P.)<br />
Tllyo 4lli DD e mber 1962<br />
STATES GRANTS ( UNIVERSITIES) BILL ( NO. 2) 1962<br />
The purpose of the Bill before the House is<br />
to authorise the Commonwealth to offer to the States of New<br />
South Wales, Victoria and South Australia grants for the<br />
University of New South Wales, Monash University and Adelaide<br />
University respectively, which are supplementary to those<br />
already offered for the years 1961, 1962 and 1963 by the<br />
existing State Grants ( Universities) Act 1960-62.<br />
Honourable Members are aware that since the<br />
Government's acceptance of the Murray Report of 1957<br />
Commonwealth grants to the States for their universities have<br />
been on a triennial basis. The grants for the years 1958-<br />
1960 were those recommended by the Murray Committee, and those<br />
for the current triennium, 1961-1963 are those recommended<br />
in the first report to the Government by the Australian<br />
Universities Commission established in 1959.<br />
Grants for a period three years ahead have<br />
advantages both for the universities receiving them and for<br />
the Governments responsible for providing them. The former<br />
have an assured income for the period, and so can plan with<br />
a large measure of certainty while the latter know, broadly,<br />
the level of finance required of them by the universities.<br />
My Government's policy is to offer, for a period of tnree<br />
years in advance, specified sums of money for the university<br />
purposes which have been recommended to us by the Commission.<br />
In general, our view is that if a State university requires<br />
additional money during that period it mast obtain it from<br />
other than Commonwealth sourceso In fact, this usually means<br />
State Government grants and private benefactions. The State<br />
Governments recognise that they have a special responsibility<br />
for their own universities. On the other hand, we know that the judgments<br />
on which the Commission's recomrurendations for the years 1961<br />
to 1963 were based had to be made on evidence presented by the<br />
universities as long ago as 1959. Accurate forecasting of<br />
needs and costs for such a long period ahead is difficult and<br />
we recognise that in certain circumstances exceptions to the<br />
principle of fixed offers by the Commonwealth for a triennium<br />
are justified. For this reason, in 1960 we agreed to increase<br />
our grant to Victoria for the early stages of the planning and<br />
development of Monash University Again, in May this year,<br />
we amended the Act to permit increased Commonmwealth grants so<br />
that the Commonwealth and States would share the cost of<br />
providing higher salaries to university academic staffs.<br />
In recent months, the Commission has received<br />
many requests that it should recolmmend to the Government<br />
increased grants for the present trienniuma After close and<br />
painstaking examination of the various proposals, the Commission<br />
recommended to me that the special problems involved in establishing<br />
two rapidly growing new universities the University of<br />
New South Wales and Monash University and in planning a new<br />
constituent part of the University of Adelaide on a new site<br />
at Bedford Park justified suoplementary grants of the amounts<br />
indicated in Sections 3 and 4 of the Bill for the purposes<br />
mentioned there. These are<br />
r </p>
<p>2-<br />
University of New South Wales<br />
Building for Medical and Biological Sciences: œ 242,500<br />
Monash University<br />
Recurrent expenditure œ iI4 + 000<br />
University of Adelaide<br />
Bedford Park College Capital Expenditure œ 37,500<br />
Re current expenditure œ 26,000<br />
These amounts mean a total Commonwealth grant of œ 4207000<br />
The Commission had discussions with the<br />
appropriate State Government authorities and was able to<br />
assure me that the State Governments concerned would match<br />
the recommended Commonwealth grants on the customary basis,<br />
that is to say for for capital expenditure and œ 1.85 to<br />
œ 1 for recurrent costs. In these circumstances, my colleagues<br />
and I, kncwing how thoroughly the Commission had considered<br />
the claims put to them. were prepared to accept the recommendation.<br />
The result is the present Bill, which I commend to the<br />
House. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
