<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11133</transcript-id>
    <title>26 March 1999                                                   TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER                   THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP                 RADIO INTERVIEW WITH NEIL MITCHELL (3AW)</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/03/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...................................................................................................</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, good morning.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Good morning Neil.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, I understand from the reports that later today you are</p>
<p> to release details of a new tax deal for businesses which support</p>
<p> charities, a philanthropy argument. Can you tell us what it is?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes. What I'll be doing tonight is delivering a speech to a very</p>
<p> large business gathering in Melbourne and to further the concept of</p>
<p> greater business giving and philanthropy I'll be announcing a</p>
<p> series of changes to taxation legislation. It'll involve a revenue</p>
<p> cost of between $50 and $60 million a year and it will provide overall</p>
<p> in a number of areas, which for reasons of giving people all of the</p>
<p> information at the same time I won't go into at this stage, but</p>
<p> it will contain a whole series of changes which will make it more</p>
<p> attractive for companies and individuals either through direct giving</p>
<p> or through leaving things in their estates to help charities and to</p>
<p> help other worthy pursuits within the Australian community. I want</p>
<p> very much to build what I call a stronger social Coalition with the</p>
<p> Government, the business sector, welfare organisations and individuals</p>
<p> working together to tackle social problems. This is not an attempt</p>
<p> to wind back the Government's own direct responsibilities for</p>
<p> providing welfare benefits. I want to make it very clear that when</p>
<p> I talk of business philanthropy I talk of adding value to what is</p>
<p> now being done. I don't talk about the Government getting out</p>
<p> of welfare and handing over the burden to either welfare organisations</p>
<p> or to the business community. I would like to encourage a greater</p>
<p> spirit of giving by Australian companies. Some of them, incidentally,</p>
<p> are very generous now, very generous. But I'd like more of them</p>
<p> to become generous and I'd like in that...by us giving some</p>
<p> additional incentive we will make it more attractive. We are not just</p>
<p> saying, you give more, we are also saying we are going to make a number</p>
<p> of changes to make it easier and more attractive and provide you with</p>
<p> more incentives.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>In the form of a tax break obviously?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, a tax incentive.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. What, and individual as well. Does that mean if I am sending</p>
<p> a cheque off to a charity organisation that'll change my position?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it could depending on what the circumstances are. At the moment</p>
<p> gifts to certain organisations are tax deductible and by their nature</p>
<p> most of the changes will tend to affect the corporate sector but if</p>
<p> the circumstances fit an individual well the individual will get the</p>
<p> same benefit as well.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. So there will be some benefits for individuals....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Oh yeah, there'll be some benefit for both individuals and corporations.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>In a broad sense can you tell us how?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it's very hard to do so without going into the details</p>
<p> of it but there are certain aspects of the capital gains tax that</p>
<p> work against some forms of corporate giving at the present time and</p>
<p> we are going to make that more easy.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. And that'll be announced later today?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, I'll be announcing it tonight actually at a speech I am</p>
<p> giving to a dinner in Melbourne.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>It does come at a time when some people are still arguing that the</p>
<p> GST is going to affect charities or charitable works. Do you insist</p>
<p> it won't?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>When you see all of the details of it I don't believe anybody</p>
<p> can argue that it will. One of the reasons why it won't adversely</p>
<p> affect charities is that a lot of the things that charities now buy</p>
<p> are...have embedded in them wholesale sales tax and all of that</p>
<p> will, of course, disappear under a GST and the normal activities of</p>
<p> charities will be GST free.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, another matter, we're sending...are we sending</p>
<p> the HMAS Melbourne to the Gulf?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there is a situation that in the past we have provided assistance</p>
<p> and the Defence Minister would be the person who would be making a</p>
<p> statement about that. Obviously we have in the past participated in</p>
<p> that multi-national force and it wouldn't be out of line with</p>
<p> that for that to occur in the future.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, it is reported in the Age today....</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I haven't seen that report.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But obviously if the HMAS Melbourne is going to the Gulf on a new</p>
<p> commitment you are aware of it, are you able to confirm it?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, look, I don't want to say anything further about that issue</p>
<p> except to foreshadow that something will be said about it over the</p>
<p> weekend.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay. Kosovo. What will this achieve, is this really likely to solve</p>
<p> the situation, bombing the living daylights out of them?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, that's always a fair question to ask, it's always</p>
<p> a difficult question to answer and like everybody else I very much</p>
<p> regret that this has become necessary. But in the end what do you</p>
<p> do? Do you stand by, do you watch people being murdered, do you watch</p>
<p> atrocities take place, you watch a country ignore the requests of</p>
<p> the whole world to reach an agreement that gives to a different ethnic</p>
<p> group a certain amount of liberty and independence? The longer it</p>
<p> went on the more people wrung their hands and said, why don't</p>
<p> the western countries do something about it, why doesn't NATO</p>
<p> do something about it, why don't the Americans do something about</p>
<p> it. And then along comes this attack and then quite naturally people,</p>
<p> sort of, go over to the other side and they recoil in horror, perfectly</p>
<p> understandably. It's one of the great dilemmas of international</p>
<p> leadership. If you do nothing you are condemned for meeting circumstances</p>
<p> that whereby people are being murdered, if you do something you are</p>
<p> then quite rightly accused by some of an overreaction. I don't</p>
<p> think the NATO countries had any alternative. They have laboured long</p>
<p> and hard over the negotiating table with Milosevic and he is completely</p>
<p> intransigent.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I guess my point is what happens next though? Is it inevitable that</p>
<p> ground troops will have to go in in your view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I don't think it's inevitable, no I don't. I don't</p>
<p> believe that to be inevitable and my understanding of the military</p>
<p> goal is to do sufficient damage to the Serb military capacity that</p>
<p> it will make them more likely to negotiate and to give a certain amount</p>
<p> of independence and autonomy to the ethnic Albanians in Kosovo. That's</p>
<p> what it's all about.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Mr Howard, the preamble, it's had so much attention this week</p>
<p> and I know you feel very passionately about it. Dr O'Donoghue,</p>
<p> the former Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commissioner, Chairman,</p>
<p> describes you as a "nation wrecker". She says this is so</p>
<p> divisive, you are a nation wrecker. What's your response to that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, my response is that Dr O'Donoghue has been a consistent</p>
<p> critic of mine ever since I became Prime Minister and I am not the</p>
<p> least bit surprised by her reaction. Can I just make this rather soft</p>
<p> response to her and, indeed, to all the other critics I've had,</p>
<p> if this preamble is wrecked by the sort of blind opposition of those</p>
<p> who, in one way or another, don't think it goes far enough, we're</p>
<p> not going to have a vote on a preamble for years into the future.</p>
<p> The only logical time in the next little while to have a vote on a</p>
<p> preamble is at the end of this year along with the republican referendum.</p>
<p> I mean, it would be ridiculous in the extreme.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But couldn't you put your preamble regardless, even if it doesn't</p>
<p> get through the Senate, couldn't you put it through?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, only if it is again presented to the Senate after a period of</p>
<p> three months.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, would you do that?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, wait and see what they do. The point I'm making is, the</p>
<p> timetable for getting it voted on at the same time as the republican</p>
<p> referendum is very tight. And if, because of that tight timetable,</p>
<p> if you can't have the two of them together, well, I don't</p>
<p> think the Australian public would take very kindly to a separate expenditure</p>
<p> of $40 million to have a referendum just on the preamble. And can</p>
<p> I also say this, to Lois O'Donoghue and a whole lot of other</p>
<p> people, is that the reason why we started talking about having a preamble</p>
<p> more than a year ago, a new preamble, was that there's no reference</p>
<p> in the present Constitution, in an appropriate way, to the indigenous</p>
<p> people of this country. And if, because of the blind opposition of</p>
<p> the Democrats and the Labor Party and others, we end up not getting</p>
<p> a vote on the preamble at the end of this year, we will have missed</p>
<p> a golden opportunity to at least acknowledge the place in the history</p>
<p> of Australia of indigenous people. Even if some people don't</p>
<p> think that acknowledgement goes far enough...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Do you think you would win popular support for it? This is the thought</p>
<p> I'm having, that whether you could put it to a referendum regardless</p>
<p> of the Senate.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well look, I'll make a judgement, the Government will obviously</p>
<p> make a judgement on that depending on the reaction of the republic.</p>
<p> And I have said that I want comment on the draft. I haven't said</p>
<p> that every single word in it is immutable otherwise if that was my</p>
<p> view I wouldn't have called it a draft.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>But you don't want to add things to it, do you?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, but I think it is long enough at present. But inevitably something</p>
<p> like this was going to be fiercely attacked.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What about this issue of guardianship which seems to be the main issue?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Custodianship.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, custodianship, is that negotiable?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I'm not hung up on any particular word but I do know that</p>
<p> if you go too far in this area you will start getting an opposite</p>
<p> reaction. And isn't it better for those who want the Aboriginals</p>
<p> and Torres Strait Islanders recognised to have something rather than</p>
<p> to have nothing at all, because that is what will happen. If the Senate</p>
<p> rejects our preamble and we can't have a vote on the preamble</p>
<p> at the same time as the vote on the republic, I can't see when</p>
<p> you'll have a vote on the preamble in the foreseeable future.</p>
<p> Because I don't think any government is just going to have a</p>
<p> vote on a preamble alone. And the logical, sensible time to have the</p>
<p> vote on a preamble is when you're having a vote on whether or</p>
<p> not the country becomes a republic because the two things are, in</p>
<p> a sense, whilst they're different issues, they are in a sense</p>
<p> related. And if you're seriously thinking I would have a, or</p>
<p> any Prime Minister of this country, would just have a stand-alone</p>
<p> vote on a preamble so...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Is there a possibility, though, it's this or no change or...?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>No, I haven't said that. I mean, some of my critics are saying</p>
<p> that I've said that. They should look at what I say.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>No, but you are saying, well, you know, if we muck around with this</p>
<p> then you can't put it to, well, you don't put it to a referendum,</p>
<p> we stay as we are.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, exactly. Well, you can't put it in the Constitution without</p>
<p> a referendum.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Yeah.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>And the logical time to have the referendum on the preamble is with</p>
<p> the republican referendum. And what I'm really saying is that</p>
<p> if the chance to have the two of them together is lost then the opportunity</p>
<p> of having a vote on a preamble in the foreseeable future is also lost.</p>
<p> And we will, therefore, end up with a Constitution that, amongst other</p>
<p> things, makes absolutely no reference at all to the indigenous people</p>
<p> of this country. Now, is that what Lois O'Donoghue wants? Is</p>
<p> that what Kim Beazley wants? Is that what Meg Lees wants? I mean,</p>
<p> is that what they really want? Okay, they may not think my words go</p>
<p> far enough but my words go a lot further than the deafening silence</p>
<p> of the present Constitution and that is really what has to be kept</p>
<p> in mind. And I think we have to keep a sense of proportion. But I</p>
<p> expected to be attacked and, I'm afraid, Lois has been a persistent</p>
<p> critic of mine ever since I became Prime Minister and I don't</p>
<p> really expect anything to change.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>I know you need to get away. If I may, very quickly, Paul Keating,</p>
<p> how far should the inquiry go on Paul Keating and the piggery?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, there's been no decision taken by the Government to have</p>
<p> an inquiry.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Will there be one?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>That is being looked at at the present time.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>What's your view?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>I have no personal desire to pursue a vendetta against Mr Keating.</p>
<p> Mr Keating was a political opponent of mine. I derived great satisfaction</p>
<p> in beating him in March of 1996. I have no personal axe to grind.</p>
<p> The only circumstances in which an inquiry of some kind would be held</p>
<p> would be if the Government felt there was an overwhelming public interest</p>
<p> in having it. And I can make it very clear to you, Neil, and your</p>
<p> listeners that I don't have any sense of vendetta in me in relation</p>
<p> to Mr Keating. He's now a private citizen. But I think the programme</p>
<p> on 60 Minutes raised a number of issues...</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Well, it's suggesting he misused his office.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, it raised a large number of issues including that issue, it</p>
<p> certainly did, a great number of issues. We have sought advice and</p>
<p> we'll be getting advice from the Attorney-General. He's</p>
<p> the first law officer. We're approaching it in a very transparent,</p>
<p> above the board way. As I say, I've got no desire to pillory</p>
<p> the bloke in a personal sense. He was a political rival, not a sworn</p>
<p> enemy. And our political rivalry ended in March of 1996. But if there</p>
<p> are reasons of public interest, proper public interest grounds for</p>
<p> having an inquiry then, or some kind of investigation, then that would</p>
<p> have to take place. But I've not had any conclusive advice on</p>
<p> that and I think it's quite premature of me to start speculating</p>
<p> about that.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Okay, I know you need to get away. I'll save the other questions</p>
<p> for next time. New South Wales, your lot looks beaten.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Well, I never make any predictions on the eve of elections. The last</p>
<p> election 24 hours out everybody said that the Coalition was going</p>
<p> to win. The Labor Party won. The last couple of New South Wales'</p>
<p> elections, the results have been very different from the polls. So</p>
<p> I certainly don't agree that my lot looks beaten. I'll be</p>
<p> very interested to see what the outcome is.</p>
<p>MITCHELL:</p>
<p>Thank you very much for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Pleasure.</p>
<p>[ends]</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
