<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8823</transcript-id>
    <title>GST AND THE LIBERAL LIES</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>21/02/1993</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008823.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
' 1<br />
i'<br />
I STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
GST AND THE LIBERAL LIES<br />
The GST pamphlet distributed today by te liberal Party is a glossy litany of lies and<br />
distofwioas<br />
Faced with the growing community cowcen about this iniquitos sad unnecessary tax<br />
thange. Dr Hewson is now resorting to shameless half tuths which make a mockry of<br />
his prom~ isd TNo-ims-Campag<br />
The pqam* het dimfibtfd today purports to tell Autlian families how they will be<br />
better off uamdr a Goods and SerVces Tax<br />
It make the follwing a wwtiou:<br />
IGST will mean the aboltion of sewn mar tares.<br />
A fie. The coal export duty listed in the pamphlet has already been abolished.<br />
Fwihenmort, Dr Hewson's promise to abolish ' customs duties" is rally doublspeak<br />
for s zerotaiffpolicy whch will cost Austraian Jobs.<br />
" MWry ofthe items you now buy are tared at anything up to 30 per cent under Labor's<br />
current saes tan system. For example... garbage bags...<br />
A distortiiom The wholesale sales axon grbage bags is ten per cent. Garbage bags<br />
would be more cxponsiv under Dr Hewson's 15 percnt OST.<br />
* Food wui1 acfagal be cheaper under the Cration<br />
A le. Nowhere does Dr Hewsons slick pamphlet tell Australian famulies that takeaway<br />
food and restarant meals will be taxed under the GST.<br />
The GST wall go where no other Australian tax has gone before. Hamburgcs, hot<br />
dogs, milkshake and barbecued chicken will all be taxed for the first time in our<br />
histoiy. Why won't Dr I kwson tell Australian familics the truth? 6545 </p>
<p>Futrnome th pbotograph in Dr Hewsonms pamphlet shows a range of supermuare<br />
aasm not just baow foods The diswashing liqud and isues would atuact the GST.<br />
" The GS7 m~ ae umnsfirer and simpler.<br />
A he. IftheOST isso andleWfair, why won Hewson release dheCole<br />
Commnitte report, which consm hundreds of pages of potential problem. and<br />
Wnquitie in the OST? And if the OST really is fiim and, impler, why ame so many<br />
sporting orpaisatos such as Tanis Auwa&amp; and the National BdwAkebl Legu,<br />
confused ad concerned about the impat of OST on thar sports? Why does die<br />
proumnent horse racing idusby figue Coin Hayes bliev it wMl ruin rang i this<br />
counuy Why am the builin ad 1 ourist idinria up mnam about t impact of die<br />
GSTI The GST Wl n101 make taes smple. The GST wil affect eveay busines with<br />
tuarnover as filde a SS0,000 per yev. Small busineses, currently uninmlvd in the<br />
caoction, of wholesale sales ta or payroll tax, wMl be drawn ito the tax not to collect<br />
t OST. How wil it help die Austalian, economy to create about 750,00 new tax<br />
collection pobft<br />
Thewrw will be no GS7' on-4. duatkm<br />
A fie. Parmitw should, he told that they wil havt to pay GST on texiboom purchased<br />
from boolcAbOM school inifonns, school shoes and, on public tranport for dd<br />
dtsiu to and ft~ m schoo<br />
-Family allowanwu wift be double&amp; L<br />
Why doessit Dr Hewson tell t whole truth? About 100,000 families will be tipe<br />
off Family Allowanc wider Dr Hewsons F* ghbak poliqy<br />
vill be no GS7 cm. . councll rates."<br />
A lie. Under Dr Hewson, counci rates notic= will for the first time in owr hitory can<br />
a IS per cenl tax on the water, ac ag and garbage collection components, Dr<br />
Hewaonus 1= ca Goviernment spokesmsan, confimed this on Friday, obviously too lawe to<br />
after die pamphle which had already been prin" e<br />
T77OmS T will mean a , wdumo in invome<br />
Thi does not oompute. If the $ 24 b~ lon proceedis from dhe GST arv used to abolish<br />
existing taes, ther ns no money left for incom tax cuts. The incomie tax cubs promised<br />
by Dr Hlewson would hav to he funded through nm than $ 10 billio wwih of cuts to<br />
Federal Gavannadn sawics and progrms particuilarty in dhe aa of social security<br />
and heafth<br />
654. </p>
<p>3<br />
" There wll be no GST on. aale ofyour haue."<br />
Why doesn't Dr Hewino's pamphlet tAl Austraria fitaics tha the cod of a honse winl<br />
rise steeply becsuse of the GST on &amp; Hbu dlding mateials and land dewlopuaiL<br />
The pamphlet concludes: 7&amp; h GST L part ofh chanvge that u neededfor o<br />
children to be able to Iget jobs in thefiutare."<br />
Tlti is die bst fie. Even. Dr Hlewsons own economic experts admit Ohere are no new<br />
jobs in a GST. The OSTW-a tu -io n'qnigj ust when we don't need one. It would<br />
wooodher ecorwmic wowth and disrupt Ausfnria business jus when we need it to<br />
accclerte.<br />
CANBERRA 21 Februay 1993 47 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
