<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>24740</transcript-id>
    <title>A message from the Prime Minister</title>
    <prime-minister>Abbott, Tony</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20130918 - 20150915</period-of-service>
    <release-date>26/08/2015</release-date>
    <release-type></release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I’m sorry I can’t be with you but it is good to have the chance to wish you well for these discussions.</p>
<p>This week, I am visiting Indigenous communities in the Torres Strait and on the tip of Cape York.</p>
<p>It’s the first visit by a Prime Minister to this region in 18 years.</p>
<p>I’m here to listen – because not all wisdom resides in Canberra – and listening to those with practical experience does make for better public policy.</p>
<p>Australia has just completed 24 years of economic growth and every Australian has benefitted from this economic growth through more jobs, higher wages and better services.</p>
<p>Today’s prosperity is the result of yesterday’s reforms and the foundation of our future wellbeing is improving our productivity and competitiveness today.</p>
<p>A lot has happened in the past two years.</p>
<p>We’ve undertaken budget repair with over $50 billion in savings over the forward estimates.</p>
<p>Every year the budget deficit will come down by about a half a percentage point of GDP.</p>
<p>We’ve cut $2 billion a year in red tape costs because for too long governments have let the regulatory burden grow.</p>
<p>We’re on track to see a million new jobs created in five years, with 335,000 more jobs in our economy since the election.</p>
<p>Three Free Trade Agreements are significantly reducing tariffs and opening up new markets for our exporters and our service providers.</p>
<p>Regrettably, the passage of the China FTA through the Parliament is not assured. </p>
<p>My Government will fight for this because this agreement is essential to Australia’s long-term economic future. </p>
<p>Likewise, we’ll fight to ensure that new developments that have passed strict environmental standards are allowed to proceed without vigilantism in the courts.</p>
<p>Only a few months ago, the Government announced major reforms to Australia’s pension system.  These reforms will see 170,000 pensioners with modest assets receive pension increases in the order of $30 a fortnight, while at the same time, saving the Budget $2.4 billion.</p>
<p>But there is more work to be done.</p>
<p>This Government wants lower, simpler, fairer taxes, but that means getting spending down further. </p>
<p>Tax reform is an important national debate and I hope that this Summit will play a part in it.</p>
<p>We’re also working closely with the States and Territories towards reform of our federation.</p>
<p>As you know, prosperity and opportunity go hand in hand, but to ensure tomorrow’s economic growth, we must continue to reform our economy today.</p>
<p>I wish you well with your deliberations.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
