<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9832</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 9 NOVEMBER 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009832.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: *. ov9. Nov 95<br />
PRIME MINISTER1<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING3 MP<br />
DOORSTOP, PARLIAMENT HOUSE, CANBERRA, 9 NOVEMBER 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: There are a couple of sleights of hand going on by the Coalition in my<br />
short absence from Australia, and I just thought I would point them<br />
out, and underline the significance of them. And they are that a week<br />
or so ago, Richard Court presented an Access Economics report on<br />
the distribution of FederallState financial powers, commissioned, it<br />
says, by the Western Australian Ministry of the Premier and Cabinet,<br />
on behalf of the Governments of the States and the Territories. He<br />
did a press conference holding this document, and of the document<br />
he said we don't want another Quebec situation, where people are<br />
being forced out of the Federation. In other words, he was waving<br />
around the threat of secession, or the prospect of secession, were<br />
the States not to get a go on that thing they called the vertical fiscal<br />
imbalance. Now, I had made this point in the Federal Parliament,<br />
that when Mr Costello said that onhe of the first things he would be<br />
dealing with in Government was the vertical fiscal imbalance, that<br />
could only mean as it meant to the journalists who wrote the story,<br />
and that was a transfer of taxing powers to the States.<br />
John Howard has been on Richard Court's back, and he is now onto<br />
the big smother in the run-up to the election. lie said that's a no-no<br />
until we're into office. So, what was a secession issue for Mr Court<br />
early in the week, by the meeting of the State Premiers on Friday, it<br />
was really only a division of Commonwealth income tax. Now, first of<br />
all the first thing to say about that is that's only the policy until a<br />
Coalition Government, or were a Coalition Government were to be<br />
elected to office. If a Coalition Government to be elected to office,<br />
the bible of Commonwealth/ State tax powers will be this Access<br />
Economics report. And it says let me just remind you of a couple of<br />
things it says " our assessment is that a combination options<br />
options 3 with other options 4 and 5 dominates the others as<br />
potential avenues for future reform. That is, combining State income<br />
2: 29 No., 00? P_. 01/ </p>
<p>9. Nov. 95<br />
2<br />
taxes with possible increases in the wholesale safes tax, a broadbased<br />
consumption tax, or payroll tax, so as to eliminate both vertical,<br />
fiscal imbalance and the worst of the State taxes". That's their<br />
principal observation recommendation. It says " eliminating VFI by<br />
allowing the States to raise personal income taxes in aggregate, in<br />
order to do away with net Commonwealth payments to States, the<br />
States would need to levy marginal personal income tax rates above<br />
the tax-free threshold, at the rate of 15.6%, the Commonwealth<br />
making room by dropping its own marginal rates equivalently", it goes<br />
on in the conclusion, ' lor Australians to enjoy the benefits that<br />
competitive Federalism has to offer' whatever competitive<br />
Federalism means one century after Federation -1" hen VFI should be<br />
eliminated or much reduced. The elimination of VFI could be done in<br />
several ways: allowing the States to levy personal income taxes or<br />
sales taxes, or sales taxes, or somewhat less plausibly by a marked<br />
increase in the more efficient State taxes. However, probably the<br />
vest and most obvious way to eliminate it, would be allowing the<br />
States to levy personal income taxes".<br />
Now, It's as solid and as direct as that, and it has been commissioned<br />
by the Western Australian Premier, his Government, on behalf of the<br />
States. Now, at the meeting of State Premiers, Wayne Goss who<br />
chaired the meeting presented the States position at a press<br />
conference. And, not surprisingly, because he doesn't subscribe to<br />
these views, he said that he and Bob Carr and the other Coalition<br />
Premiers, would be content with a share of Commonwealth income<br />
tax not new State taxes. But this is not at all the Coalition agenda.<br />
John Howard and Costello their agenda is for State taxes and a<br />
State consumption tax. And Richard Court made it abundantly plain<br />
in the commissioning and presentation of this report, and he made it<br />
abundantly plain by his backilip. So serious was it, we might secede<br />
on Monday or Tuesday, but by Friday after having been nobbled by<br />
Mr Howard he was going to go, lamely, simply for a share of income<br />
tax So I'm just here to point out what that backflip meant. And we<br />
are also seeing it now on industrial relations.<br />
In Industrial relations, he haO his phase 2 proposal he was going to<br />
stare down the unions, he was going to fight to the last drop of the<br />
blood of the Federal Labor Government, and the rest. And what we<br />
find now is that he has got another signal from Mr Howard run dead<br />
on phase 2 of your IR proposals. But, the point we make it's phase<br />
I which is the real problem. Phase 1 of the problem which is stil in<br />
place, doesn't guarantee that workers will be as well off as they are<br />
now. And remember the interview which Fran Kelly put with Mr<br />
Howard I think I have got the notes of it here where she made<br />
these points, and the reply was completely unambiguous in terms of<br />
the direction in which they would be heading. Mr Reith said he<br />
couldn't guarantee when asked persistently can you guarantee<br />
that workers will be no worse off? He said paraphrasing him, but I<br />
think you will find the paraphrase Is accurate look, we'll be doing our<br />
TEL TEL: 9. NNoo. 9.0502?: 2 9P .02, </p>
<p>TEL: 9. Nov. 95 2: 29 No .007 P. 03/<br />
3<br />
best in the circumstances best to have fair and reasonable wages<br />
and conditions. Not a guarantee. Twice he got asked about the<br />
guarantee, and there of course, no commitment on the guarantee.<br />
So, what we're finding is now that we've got this quotation from<br />
Richard Court he ruled out his own State income tax with a<br />
consumption tax, thats on November 4th in the West Australian, but<br />
earlier in the week, he was so het up about it all he was talking<br />
secession. Last week, he was going to tear the unions apart, he was<br />
going to do all these things and remember the things that he has<br />
dropped. He is now.. . Mr Reith is now running around saying that he<br />
has made concessions to the unions, you know, that they thought<br />
better of it, and they can now work with unions, he said. And what<br />
they have proposed is that the most draconian of things they won't<br />
now prosecute a union if it tries to become Federally registered.<br />
Well, thank you Mr Court. He won't stop unions having * access to<br />
industrial sites I mean, these are all the things which cut across our<br />
very democracy, not some industrial law.<br />
But, I think the most important thing that bears upon these 2 things<br />
are the things that Mr Howard has said himself in the last couple of<br />
days. And he got asked this question by a caller on a phone-in<br />
program: " Mr Howard, the people who developed Fightback, who are<br />
still in the parliamentary party, how are you going to balance the new<br />
initiatives if you win Government?". ' Well, it won't be any problem',<br />
said Mr Howard, " wie just don't have Fightback anymore". " I know<br />
you don't have Fightback, but you have got the people who<br />
developed it7, and he says " oh, yes". Then he has told us on<br />
another radio program in the last day, that people know who their<br />
people are. " People know who the players are", he said. He made<br />
an analogy about football they know who are the players for the<br />
various positions. In other words, it's not a matter of our policies<br />
when David Margan asked him these questions. Let me give you<br />
these answers he said this:' Margan said " not to reveal the<br />
policies?", Howard: " No, no, no, no, no you know who the players<br />
are you're not going to tell me that you don't know who the players<br />
are". In other words, the players are the people who have held all the<br />
positions which are synonymous with Fightback on industrial<br />
relations, on state taxes, on consumption taxes, on all the things.<br />
And then he said in the Courier Mail, just a few weeks earlier " One<br />
of the groat advantages of my having laid out an industrial relations<br />
program over such a long period of time, Is that if I win the election,<br />
nobody can deny I have a mandate to change Industrial relations"<br />
That's a mandate for the old Howard policies the policies of the<br />
players that everybody knows. So, by making the point that you know<br />
who the players are, you don't need the policies, what he is really<br />
saying is you know what the old policies are. You know what the old<br />
prejudices of the players of the Coalition are the people who put<br />
Fightback together. And how perceptive is the caller saying well Mr<br />
Howard, If they're the old players, and they're the old players who put </p>
<p>TEL: 9. Nov. 95 2: 29 No. 007 P. 04/<br />
4.<br />
Fightback together, what are you going to do other than give us<br />
Fightback policies? And he says well, you know who the players are.<br />
Now, this is a very I think damaging admission by Mr Howard,<br />
because what he Is really saying is look, people now what I stand for<br />
I stand for consumption taxes, I stand for hopping into unions, I<br />
stand for individual wage contracts. It won't be a matter of the<br />
policies it will be a matter of who we are, and what we have always<br />
stood for. So, when you see that in the context of the gymnastics in<br />
the Coalition this week, of Richard Court going from secession on the<br />
Monday, to mute compliance on the Friday on State taxes, and then<br />
going for rabid, anti-democratic draconian industrial policies one<br />
week, and then moving lamb-like to an agreement with unions about<br />
those clauses in another week, all I can say to people is you can<br />
smell the rat in the Coalition camp. Mr Howard's nobbling Mr Court,<br />
and what you will get were there to be a Howard Government, is all<br />
the things that are in this Fightback, in this authors' of Fightback,<br />
Access Economics In their new paper State consumption taxes,<br />
State income taxes, particularly State income taxes, and of course,<br />
the same Industrial relations pollices that Mr Howard has always<br />
subscribed to.<br />
J: made your run on this a bit early? Aren't you just a bit miffed that<br />
they have acted to de-fang these issues before the next election?<br />
PM: Oh, no. But Mr Howard is not de-fanging anything he is putting the<br />
dentures back Into the Coalition dogrs mouth. He is saying we're the<br />
same old people don't you know the players? We have always<br />
been there. It's us the old team, the old Fightback group, we're<br />
going to do it all again. I mean, what do you need? Flashing lights?<br />
You know, do you need it put up on your pces? I mean, he is making<br />
It obvious to you.<br />
J: Are you saying that all the States are complicit in this arrangement ? 7<br />
PM: No. I think the Labor States have traditionally rejected State income<br />
taxes, but there is no doubt the Coalition States want one. Jeff<br />
Kennett made clear when he said that 80% of the taxes should come<br />
to the States. There's Jeff Kennett's remarks I'm not imputing<br />
remarks to him, he made that remark. You have got Richard Court<br />
making clear where he stands that's what they're after.<br />
J: But didn't, at the very least, Mr Goss and Mr Canr show a little lack of<br />
foresight from your point of view, in signing onto allowing Access to<br />
do this report?<br />
PM; I I doubt very much whether they did sign on. I mean...<br />
J: Well, Mr Goss certainly did. He was there when the initial decision<br />
wwstabled? </p>
<p>TEL: 9 . NvN. 9o5.02: 0279<br />
PM; Well, even If that is true, that doesn't mean that he must comply with,<br />
or sign up, to its recommendations,. But it very much clearly<br />
means that Richard Courts militant presentation of the Access report,<br />
and his banging the secession drum, makes very clear what his<br />
preference is.<br />
J: Are you saying the States aren't all that serious about seeking their<br />
own State income tax?<br />
PM: They want their own income taxes. Look, it's the 1991 proposal it's<br />
the Greiner proposal. it's the Coalition proposal. They were going to<br />
do it in Perth they wanted their State income tax, but not only that,<br />
[ they wanted] the right to set their own State tax rates themselves,<br />
and what's more, cheekily at the time, they said if the Commonwealth<br />
were to give tax cuts or any tax benefits by way of arrangements<br />
under the Accord, we actually had to compensate them. I mean, you<br />
know.<br />
J: ( Inaudible)... economic growth may have slowed too much affecting<br />
the labour market * how quickly do you see the labour<br />
market.. .( inaudibre)...?<br />
PM: Well, the economic growth has slowed from an unsustainable to<br />
a sustainable And we're seeing, consistent with that, very<br />
strong growth still in the job vacancy series. Were seeing strong<br />
investment expectations the economy is in a very nice position. Its<br />
on a sustainable growth path, with good investment and low inflation.<br />
J: ( inaudible) not worried by an increase in the unemployment<br />
levels?<br />
PM: Well, we have had the biggest fail in unemployment in a year, and<br />
what we have seen in the past Is whenever you see these very large<br />
takeup in employment, we have seen these pauses, or these<br />
plateaux, until the economy sort of catches its breath again, and<br />
moves along. Now, at a 3-4% clip, the economy Is till going quite<br />
strongly.<br />
J: Is the economy in nice enough shape... has there been enough of a<br />
pause or a breath to consider that the next move In interest rates<br />
might be down?<br />
PM: Well, again, that's for longer portents for markets to make a<br />
judgment about, I think. But a lot of the judgments are already in on<br />
that we have seen the long-ternm bond rate drop from over 10.25%<br />
to around<br />
J: On taxes are you saying that a party leader who supports a<br />
consumption tWx and changes their mind, shouldn't be believed?<br />
TEL: 9. Nov. 95 </p>
<p>TEL: 9. Nov. 95 2: 29 No. 007 P. 06/<br />
PM: No. If you are making a reference to me, and you are, what I did was<br />
cut then Government spending by let me refresh your memory by<br />
6% of GDP. From 30.5% of GDP, to 23.5% just under 24% of GDP.<br />
In other words, the Commonwealth doesn't now need a tax base in<br />
consumption, because it's a smaller public sector.. That's the<br />
difference between 1985 and now. But to give the States there<br />
would be 3 tax bases. There would be a Commonwealth income ta~,<br />
there would be a State income tax, and a State consumption tax. You<br />
give the political system 3 bases, it will go and spend it. It might not<br />
spend it at the Commonwealth level this year, but over time, the<br />
States and the Commonwealth systems of government will spend the<br />
money, and we won't get a second chance to get out of the hole that<br />
Mr Howard left us in, in the early 80s we won't get a second chance<br />
to buy down public spending in the way we did in the 1980s. So,<br />
when we looked at a consumption tax in 1985, we had<br />
Commonwealth outlays around 29-30% of GDP. By the time it got to<br />
24% of GDP under the Labor Government, we didn't need a<br />
consumption tax, and that's the point I have made consistently.<br />
J: Last Friday, all the Premiers signed up for a fixed share of<br />
Commonwealth revenue including the Labor Premiers doesn't that<br />
leave you isolated from the States?<br />
PM: Oh, no. I It leaves me in the box seat<br />
J: Why?<br />
PM: Because we have the powers, and...<br />
J: But you're at odds with all the States, even the Labor States?<br />
PM: Well, that's been part of my-condition for nearly a decade. And I'll tell<br />
you why in the last 3 years, in the period 90-91, the States would<br />
have lost about $ 3 billion, had they had a fixed share of<br />
Commonwealth income tax Now, how can the States cop a $ 3 billion<br />
loss? How could their school system not withstanding the massive<br />
cutting you have seen by Jeff Kennett in schools and in health it just<br />
pales into insignificance compared to the cuts that would need to be<br />
there in public services by a loss of $ 3 billion over that period. So,<br />
effectively, the Commonwealth would have had to have kept up the<br />
payments, either in nominal or real terms. So, in other words, the<br />
Commonwealth carries the burden on the down-side, but then loses it<br />
on fth up-side when it needs the money to bring the deficit down, or<br />
to produce a surplus. Because the Commonwealth is the shockabsorber<br />
in the national economy, the Commonwealth Budget is a<br />
shock-absorber, the State Budgets are not. What the States need is<br />
revenue adequacy from the Commonwealth which we're giving thern<br />
by a real-terms per capita guarantee, that is real-terms maintenance<br />
with a population factor. But to give them a share of Income tax?-If, </p>
<p>9. Nov. 95<br />
7<br />
we ever reached a point again where the Commonwealth Income tax<br />
fell, they would be screaming blue murder that they want more money<br />
from us. I mean, it's just an insincere ploy that they know has not a<br />
snowballs chance in hell of happening, from us.<br />
J: Mr Keating, are you inclined to pick up Gough Whitlam's suggestion<br />
about a referendum of the Senate's power to block?<br />
PM: Look, I have been away, and I haven't followed this debate around<br />
November 1 ith, and I really haven't seen what Gough has said.<br />
J: Mr Keating, on CHOGMV Jim Bolger says he doesn't think John<br />
Majors in a mood to change his mind. Is that the right sort of<br />
attitude ( inaudible)...?<br />
PM: Well, I mean, I think, our position is that we're not in a mood to<br />
change ours, either. That is, this is an indefensible position by the<br />
French, and no amount of sort of post-decision rationalisation can<br />
make it defensible, and that's the position we will take.<br />
J: So what as a minimum would you be expecting to come out of<br />
CHOGM in response to the French testing?<br />
PM: Well, our clear condemnation of their decision.<br />
J: Are you concerned that Internal politics may lead to something a bit<br />
softer. ( inaudible)...?<br />
PM: Well, there's no doubt that the French will be calling up favours all<br />
around the world, amongst Commonwealth countries. And It won't be<br />
changing Australia's position. I mean, we will secure all we can from<br />
the process, but our position will be crystal clear right through.<br />
J: But doesn't it rather weaken things that Jim Bolger is already saying<br />
that we'll agree to disagree, and leave it at that?<br />
PM: Well, I know he has said that, but I don't know what that means in<br />
terms of the documents, the communiques etc. But I will be making<br />
very clear to him In fact, I'm going to speak to him in less than an<br />
hour, to say to him that our position is that we should have a clear<br />
condemnation of France for Its testing program. And of any other<br />
country testing weapons, consistent with the communique of 2 years<br />
ago.<br />
J: Prime Minister, what's your view of suggestions that CHOGM should<br />
also be censuring Nigeria over its human rights record would you be<br />
supportive of a move like that?<br />
PMV: Well. I think that I would be. It depends of what comes from the floor<br />
on this Issue, but our position on human rights is clear, and of course,<br />
TEL: T2E: L29: 9N. oN. o0.0975 P. 07, </p>
<p>TEL: 9. Nov. 95 2: 29 No. 007 P. 08/<br />
we don't support as a party, as a Government the death penalty,<br />
under any circumstances, least of all these kind of circumstances.<br />
Do you think Charles should be allowed to marry Camilla?<br />
Oh, well, I think it's time for me to leave on that note, Niki.<br />
J: PM: ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
