<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3870</transcript-id>
    <title>INTERVIEW BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTER AND RICHARD CARLETON &#039;THIS DAY TONIGHT&#039; 28 AUGUST 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/08/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003870.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
INTERVIEW BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTER AND RICHARD CARLETON 31<br />
" THIS DAY TONIGHT" 28 AUGUST, 1975<br />
CARLETON: Good evening and welcome to This Day Tonight from Canberra.<br />
If there was an election tomorrow then few would give Labor any<br />
chance at all of being returned to power. But of course there's<br />
not going to be an election tomorrow and if Mr Fraser is as good<br />
as his word, there won't be an election at all this year, and<br />
that's possibly just as well for the man who tomorrow celebrates<br />
his 1,000th day as Prime Minister of Australia.<br />
CARLETON: Mr Whitlam, do you think its possible to pinpoint any<br />
particular reason or group of events that'll explain that great<br />
turnaround from the euphoria of Decemuber 1972 when you swept into<br />
power, to the doldrums that you're in now?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think there are two matters, both continuing<br />
matters, not sudden matters: one is economic and is universal;<br />
one is political and is peculiar to Australia alone.<br />
CARLETON: Well, explain the political one first.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, the process of obstruction that my Government<br />
has been subjected to in the Parliament. This is a process of<br />
obstruction which no previous Australian Government has ever<br />
endured and also it is a process which was never forecast at the<br />
1972 and the 1974 elections. Now this is, of course, a very great<br />
difficulty for government and for business. They're always kept<br />
in a state of uncertainty.<br />
CARLETON: But how does that obstruction explain your low standing,<br />
or your Government's low standing in the community. Because you<br />
can't-. get those particular Bills through the Senate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh yes, well there's almost a score of them.<br />
Also, of course, there's not only the obstruction of the Senate,<br />
there's obstruction by State Governments which have challenged<br />
legislation which has gone through the Parliament in the High<br />
Court and then there has been a general obstruction by all the<br />
parliamentary devices which have been discovered in the last two<br />
and a half years.<br />
CARLETON: Well you seem to be suggesting, Sir, that if you could<br />
have got those Bills through that are under challenge in the Courts<br />
or by the States or in the Upper house, then you would be less<br />
unpopular than you are at present<br />
PRIME MINISTER: of course, a very great amount of the legislation<br />
which we have got through is obviously beneficial but it's taken a<br />
dickens of a time to get it through. Take the Trade Practices<br />
legislation; everybody now applauds it. It took a year and a<br />
half to get it through. Then look at the various Securities<br />
legislation which has been foreshadowed for about four years.<br />
It's still stalled. There's no doubt that the people would benefit<br />
from it if it had gone through in the normal process. There's<br />
legislation like the offshore resources. It was brought in by<br />
our predecessors five and a half years ago and it's still under<br />
challenge in the courts. Now there's no doubt that we'd benefit<br />
if this matter had been resolved years ago. </p>
<p>-2-<br />
CARLETON: You'd be more popular if those...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, there's no question that these pieces of<br />
legislation are inTportant. They were put to the people and presumably<br />
endorsed by them at successive elections and they're been stalled<br />
by one means and another.<br />
CARLETON: Now on the other side, the economic side, universal as<br />
the problem might be, why can't Labor, Labor of all parties, cure<br />
unemplo yment and cure inflation?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well you can ask why can't Governments of both<br />
sides of politics cure unemployment at the moment. Wherever you<br />
go, in North America, Western Europe and Australia, you get the<br />
worst unemployment for 30 or 40 years. Now we may be responsible,<br />
some people would think, for the position in Australia. We<br />
obviously aren't responsible for the position in North America,<br />
where it is worse, and in Western Europe, where it is just as<br />
bad. Some countries are worse, some countries not as bad.<br />
CARLETON: How do you look back to that 1972 campaign though, where<br />
you berated Mr McMahon right round the country when unemployment<br />
then was approaching two per cent?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, its twice as bad now, of course it is, but it's<br />
at least twice as bad in every other country too.<br />
CARLETON: Sir, if things look....<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There's no country in the world that's anything<br />
like Australia where unemployment is not worse than it was 2h-3 years<br />
ago. CARLETON: Sir, since the Budget of last Tuesday, I think politically<br />
things have been looking up for the Labor Party.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh undoubtedly, undoubtedly.<br />
CARLETON: It's only ten days admittedly...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes.<br />
CARLETON: . but nevertheless...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: But things change very quickly in politics.<br />
Your original statement of course overlooks, I would suggest, the<br />
fact that politics everywhere in the world is very volatile at<br />
the moment, and during the course of an election campAign things can<br />
do change quite remarkably. If you look back 2 years ago,<br />
most of the people who were heads of government then, no longer are.<br />
In the present circumstances I've been remarkably durable.<br />
CARLETON: You've done well to survive do you think?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes indeed.<br />
CARLETON: You have done well to survive?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, you look around how many people who were<br />
Presidents or Prime Ministers in December 1972, in comparable<br />
countries, still are? </p>
<p>-3-<br />
CARLETON: Let's go back to the Budget then of last Tuesday, sir,<br />
and I'll suggest that your stocks are looking higher over the<br />
last ten days.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Certainly.<br />
CARLETON: Now every armchair economist and yourself also, talking<br />
of about this...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes, I'm an armchair economist!<br />
CARLETON:., Talking about business confidence, now how do you<br />
measure this ephemeral thing how do you know when your Government<br />
has got the confidence of business?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: When business is making decisions to employ more<br />
people or buy more equipment.<br />
CARLETON: It's as simple as that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: They're the principal things.<br />
CARLETON: Sir you've got to hold a half-Senate election before...<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Before the end of June next year.<br />
CARLETON: Yes. When are you going to hold it?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: May or June.<br />
CARLETON: It certainly won't be the end of this year?<br />
PRIME M4INISTER: Oh no. I wouldn't be thinking so. I know there<br />
has been a practice to hold elections for half the Senate in<br />
the preceding December. My own view always has been that you<br />
should have the Senate representing the people's view as close<br />
to the time they take office as possible. I think May or June.<br />
CARLETON: Sir, what chance do you -think that your Government has<br />
got of persuading the unions to accept that very special form of<br />
indexation that you are asking them to accept now, namely that<br />
the tax increases that came from last Tuesday week's Budget, are<br />
not included in the indexation calculation for the next quarter?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh we've got a reasonable chance of persuading<br />
the unions to it, but of course where we have to persuade is before<br />
the Arbitration Commission, and every State Government has been<br />
persuaded by us to support our general approach in these National<br />
Wage Cases. This has been a remarkable achievement. After all what<br />
a government does is not merely what is done fiscally, its also<br />
what is done monetarily, and what is done in respect to incomes<br />
and we have a remarkable success in putting our point of view to<br />
the Arbitration Commission in respect of incomes and I hope we<br />
will continue to.<br />
CARLETON: Why did you finally 5ack Mr Cameron?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I believe that Senate James McClelland could do<br />
the job better. I transferred Mr Cameron; I didn't sack him.<br />
I've sacked one man. But obviously the changes that have been made<br />
in the Ministry have strengthened the Ministry. We couldn't have<br />
got as good a Budget as we have, had I not made those changes a couple<br />
of months ago: the first significant changes, incidentally, for 2 years. </p>
<p>-4-<br />
CARLETON: Sir, have the farmers the beef industry aside have<br />
the farmers still never had it so good?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well in some cases obviously in the sugar.<br />
industry that would be the case.<br />
CARLETON: You're being very specific there. What about the<br />
wo6l industry itself?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well you can't say primary production as a whole,<br />
because obviously primary production varies according to weather<br />
and according to overseas markets. Overseas markets for sugarhave<br />
never been so good. Overseas markets for beef have never<br />
been so bad. But you can't blame us for the beef markets.<br />
After all, if Japan or Werstern Europe cut down entirely and if<br />
America compells us to make voluntary restraints, you're left<br />
in the lurch, and this has been a very cruel thing for them to do.<br />
CARLETON: Has Mr Connor lived up to your expectations as Minister<br />
for Minerals and Energy?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: In many respects, more respects, yes. In some<br />
other respects, of course, he's had disappointments because, for<br />
instance, of the delays in the courts, or by the States. Obviously,<br />
when it comes to coal markets or arrangements of iron ore or for<br />
pipelines, he's overcome all the resistance overseas and at home.<br />
On things like offshore matters or uranium, there have been<br />
difficulties. CARLETON: What about relations with the business community?<br />
PRIME-eMINISTER: Well, the coal producers swear by him. They've<br />
never had it so good.<br />
CARLETON: What about Mr Hawke? Do you think he'll succeed you<br />
as Prime Minister?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't know. He has to get into Parliament.<br />
Look, for the last 12 years for the last 12 years I have been urging<br />
Mr Hawke to go into Parliament. I still do, but I think he ought<br />
to get a move on. He has to make the decision.<br />
CARLETON: Sir, on a program like this it's obligatory really to<br />
ask you what's been your greatest success in this 1,000 days,<br />
and what's been your greatest failure?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I suppose the greatest successes have been in<br />
the fields of education, hospitals, now taxation reform those<br />
would be the big ones.<br />
CARLETON: And on the other side?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh well, we are victims, of course, of this<br />
general economic malaise and we've had to learn the hard way to<br />
cope with it.<br />
CARLETON: Yes, but what have you done that has been an actual<br />
failure that you shouldn't have done?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh, I don't want to be specific you can discover<br />
those things. It's too close to me. </p>
<p>CARLETON: Mr Whitlam, we'll leave it there for now if we may,<br />
but point out to the audience that you've agreed to appear on State<br />
of The Nation later tonight where we'll look at some of the more<br />
philosophical aspects of your Government and your own very<br />
particular style of leadership.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Is this just a commercial?<br />
CARLETON: A commercial for later tonight.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Oh.<br />
CARLETON: Thank you so much for now. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
