<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21817</transcript-id>
    <title>New Senior Appointments  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/07/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>I am announcing some significant changes in the leadership of the Australian Public Service.</p>
<p> Mr Bill Farmer AO has been Secretary of the Department of Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (or its predecessor) since 2001.  Much has been achieved in that time.  DIMIA now manages a highly successful and rapidly growing skilled migration programme and a large refugee and humanitarian intake, supported by world-class settlement services for new arrivals.  However Mr Farmer has indicated to me that, as he has already stated publicly, the Department would benefit from vigorous organisational review and major cultural change. It is his considered view that this process will be best led by a new Secretary.</p>
<p> Mr Farmer had a long and distinguished career in foreign affairs before taking up his present position, including as our High Commissioner in Kuala Lumpur and Port Moresby.  His contribution was recognised earlier this year when he was made an Officer in the Order of Australia.  I am delighted that he has agreed to continue to serve the Australian government.  I propose to recommend to the Governor-General that Mr Farmer take up the position of our Ambassador in Jakarta later this year, subject to the normal approval processes.  Mr Farmer will leave DIMIA on 15 July 2005 and return to the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p>
<p> Mr Andrew Metcalfe will become the new Secretary of the Department of Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs.  Mr Metcalfe has been a Deputy Secretary in the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet since August 2002.  He has taken particular responsibility for international and national security policy and for government and parliamentary matters.  He has performed his role with distinction.  Prior to that he has had a long career in Immigration, including as Deputy State Director, Regional Migration Director (Hong Kong), Assistant Secretary, First Assistant Secretary and Deputy Secretary.</p>
<p>   Mr Metcalfe has strong leadership capability.  Importantly he possesses good skills in organisational management combined with a clear and direct communications style.  His considerable experience in migration and border protection, combined with his more recent role in oversighting international issues, defence and counter-terrorism policy, will be of considerable value.  He will have my full support in driving the changes that are needed in DIMIA.</p>
<p> I will also be recommending to the Governor-General that Mr Paul O'Sullivan be appointed as the Director-General of ASIO.  Mr O'Sullivan is presently the Senior Adviser (International) in my office.  He was a Deputy Secretary in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and possesses a very strong diplomatic background.  He has been Australia's Deputy Chief of Mission in Washington and our Ambassador in Bonn and Berlin.  Mr O'Sullivan will provide strong but considered leadership to ASIO as it continues to expand its vital role in maintaining Australia's security. In accordance with the relevant legislation I have consulted the Leader of the Opposition on this appointment.</p>
<p> Mr Nick Warner, a Deputy Secretary in DFAT, will become my new Senior Adviser (International).  Mr Warner has held a number of key positions in the Department, including as High Commissioner in Port Moresby.  He served as the Special Coordinator to the Solomon Islands, oversighting the Regional Assistance Mission to the Solomon Islands (RAMSI).  Most recently he headed up the Emergency Response Team (ERT) in Baghdad which worked so hard to secure the release of Mr Douglas Wood.  I look forward to him joining my office.  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
