<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3232</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S PRESS CONFERENCE - HOBART</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/05/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Press Conference</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003232.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER'S PRESS CONFERENCE HOBART 1 MAY 1974<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Gentlemen before I answer your questions,<br />
I thought I might touch on one matter. I noticed that in<br />
the Mercury and also in the northernpapers in Tasmania,<br />
that the principal item was to this effect. " Pensions promise,<br />
immediate rise if LCP wins." I regret to say that the heading<br />
conveyed only half the story. At least the full story gives us<br />
part of the answer to the question of where Mr Snedden will<br />
cut government spending and the answer is he would cut pensions.<br />
I was able to obtain today a copy of this glossy publication by<br />
the Liberal Party and under the heading of policies towards<br />
pensioners and the elderly the relevant passage is " as soon as<br />
economic circumstances permit',' not immediately, but as soon as<br />
economic circumstances permit, " we guarantee that aged, invalid,<br />
widows pensions, war and widows pensions, and other weekly social<br />
service and repatriation benefits will in future be adjusted<br />
automatically every half year to changes in living standards".<br />
Now if that had been the policy since the last election pensions<br />
would now stand not at $ 26 a week but at $ 23 a week because the<br />
$ 3 a week increase from the $ 20 which the pension stood at when<br />
my government was elected represent the increase to adjust to<br />
changes in living standards. What my government has done has been<br />
to increase the value of the pension towards 25% of average weekly<br />
male earnings. That's why the $ 20 pension which we inherited has<br />
not just gone up to $ 23 a week which the Liberal's platform proposes<br />
but to $ 26 a week. The pension has been increased by the Labor<br />
Government by 30%; about twice the amount required to maintain<br />
it in terms of changes in living standards. We believe that the<br />
pension ought to be adjusted in terms of average weekly male </p>
<p>2.<br />
earnings so that if the general community shares in increased<br />
prosperity in the community the retired people, the pensioners,<br />
similarly should share in that increased prosperity. Now I<br />
thought I should correct that impression that is given by the<br />
heading in the Tasmanian papers straight away.<br />
QUESTION: The keynote of Mr Snedden's address last night was<br />
that the Whitlam experiment had failed. How do you feel about that?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Whitlam experiment has succeeded wherever it<br />
has been given a chance. Where administrative action was required,<br />
we've acted promptly, fully and effectively.<br />
QUESTION: You accepted the term. Explain that Sir.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well of course it was a change for Australia.<br />
After 23 years of Liberal/ Country Party government. But we came in<br />
17 months ago on a 3 year program. After 17 months there has to<br />
be an election for the House of Representatives again but this time<br />
there will be an election for a contemporary Senate as well.<br />
Administratively the experiment is fully-fledged. Legislatively<br />
it has been hamstrung very greatly by an outdated Senate elected<br />
three and a half and six and a half years ago.<br />
QUESTION: As you well know we have representatives of the local<br />
press here as well as-the National press. I know that there are<br />
important Tasmanian issues that some people want to ask you.<br />
QUESTION: Sir Frank Packer died today. He's been a long time<br />
political opponent of the Labor Party. What's your reaction to his<br />
death and will it have any effect on the coming election. Question<br />
two, has his role with the development of this country been<br />
beneficial or harmful?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: It's too soon for me to attempt or presume<br />
to make an assessment of Sir Frank Packer's contribution to our<br />
country or to the media. He had for many years a very great<br />
influence on the daily press in Sydney. He disposed of his papers </p>
<p>3.<br />
there about three years ago. He retained control of the most<br />
successful of the weekly women's papers. He also of course had<br />
a dominating interest in two of the mainland television stations.<br />
He had been involved in the media all his life, his father before<br />
him. He had never supported the Australian Labor Party or any<br />
Australian Labor Party Government, Federal or State. Personally,<br />
I found him a vigorous character and we treated each other I think,<br />
with good humour and mutual respect, however much we disagreed with<br />
each other, on matters of policy. But I respected him. I believe<br />
he respected me and I share in the distress of his widow and his<br />
son at his passing.<br />
QUESTION: Has he affected your platform in the election.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I don't believe that Sir Frank Packer's<br />
publications these days had any influence politically.<br />
QUESTION: Nor the Liberal Party at all?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: His television stations. I think that television<br />
cannot be manipulated so readily for political purposes by the owners<br />
of the television stations. If you have a newspaper then you are<br />
a prisoner of the owner's policies. If you don't like the newspaper<br />
you can't go out and buy another. But if you don't like a<br />
television program you can always switch to another.<br />
QUESTION: The future of the Australian Cowhide Works in the<br />
( unclear) near Hobart depends on the decision of your Government.<br />
Is tariff protection for the industry still going to be continued?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There is a report which I've received from the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission. It is being printed. As soon<br />
as it's printed it will be published as all the Industries<br />
Assistance Commission and formerly the Tariff Board reports have<br />
been published since I became Prime Minister. I am the Minister<br />
in charge of protection but in accordance with the general British<br />
Parliamentary system which we inherited in Australia and which until </p>
<p>the Senate cut off supply to my Government had always been applied<br />
in the Federal Parliament it is inappropriate for governments to<br />
make decisions during the currency of an election campaign. The report<br />
I hope will be available by the time of the election and it will be<br />
one of the first matters which will be considered by my government<br />
after the election. In the meantime the report in typed form has<br />
been made available to the companies concerned.<br />
QUESTION: If the Labor Party was to win a majority in the<br />
contemporary Senate but lose to a majority in the House of<br />
Representatives would it seem fit to reject supply?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am not contemplating that eventuality. But my<br />
own strong opinion has always been that the Senate should not attempt<br />
to reject supply. This matter did arise in the first year when I<br />
was leader of the Federal Parliamentary Labor Party. That was in<br />
1967. You will remember that there was an increase in postal and<br />
telegraph charges in the 1967 budget. The Senate had previously by<br />
a combination of the Australian Labor Party and the DLP disallowed<br />
regulations which had been made increasing postal and telegraphic<br />
charges whereupon the Holt Government introduced those charges in<br />
the form of legislation in the budget and there was a move in the<br />
Federal Parliamentary Labor Party, the Caucus, to vote against those<br />
bills and the budget of which they were a part. I successfully<br />
resisted that move. My view has always been that the Senate should<br />
not cut off money for a Government which has a majority in the House<br />
of Representatives.<br />
QUESTION: Based on the precedent of the last four weeks has it<br />
changed your view at all?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I think it was an evil precedent. I wouldn't<br />
change my view.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think your Party may change its view. </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: I would try to persuade them not to. It would<br />
be tempting obviously in the circumstances which you suggest but my<br />
view has been consistent all along. When this was advanced in the<br />
Party in 1967 I successfully overcame the idea.<br />
QUESTION: Can you conceivably see a situation in which the Labor<br />
Party would do to reject Supply if the Liberal/ Country Party had a<br />
majority in the House of Representatives?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: There would be many people who would want to<br />
follow this wrong precedent. I would not be among them.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, in view of the High Court decision which<br />
has upheld the validity of the tobacco tax in Tasmania would the<br />
Labor Government seek to come to some arrangement with the States<br />
where they can have a growth..( unclear) or would the Government<br />
be having let Tasmania and presumably the other States go ahead<br />
and trying to levy the tobacco tax or the consumption?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: My Government doesn't object to the States having<br />
a growth tax. In fact we completely support the fact that they do<br />
have a growth tax in the payroll tax ard'they are using it. What<br />
we object to is the income tax being levied by any Government other<br />
than the Australian Government. But this particular matter of the<br />
tobacco tax, the consumer tax, was resisted by my Government in<br />
the High Court. The State Governments, including the Liberal State<br />
Governments, supported the idea that States should be able to levy<br />
such taxes. My Government resisted the idea. We didn't win. I<br />
should say that there are other taxes where, such as death duties<br />
and road taxes and there used to be land taxes, which were levied<br />
both by the Federal Parliament and the State Parliaments. As a<br />
result of a decision made at a meeting of the Constitution Convention<br />
Committee A which I chaired a month ago officials of my Government<br />
and of the State Governments are looking at the operation of these<br />
taxes which are levied by both Federal and State Government in<br />
Australia so we are very happy to work means of seeing that the taxes </p>
<p>Federal and State Governments levy in Australia are fair in their<br />
incidence and economic in their collection.<br />
QUESTION: Would you like to see an arrangement at least whereby the<br />
States would agree to drop consumption tax in return for some<br />
concession from the Commonwealth.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: What the States do in this matter is their affair.<br />
The High Court has ruled that it's a matter for the States. We were<br />
against them ruling that way but we didn't succeed so what the States<br />
do with their Constitutional powers is a matter for the States.<br />
Quite clearly we were against it but we didn't succeed.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, the Committee of Inquiry into national estate. I<br />
have the recommendations of this Committee that you handed down<br />
last week recommended that Tasmania ( unclear)... until further<br />
impact surveys are being conducted. Is that recommendation going<br />
to become part of your policy of your Government?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: My Government's policy is that Perhaps it<br />
will help you if I read what was said in my policy speech on this<br />
matter. I quoted what Mr Hope, who presided over the Committee<br />
on the National Estate said about this matter. He stated...<br />
It's in the section of my policy speech dealing with the government.<br />
QUESTION: Sir, while you're looking for those<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Well, if you don't mind, I think I've found it.<br />
This is what Mr Justice Hope said. The Constitution gives the<br />
Australian Government power to control the export of goods and in<br />
particular the export of minerals and timber. It can require that<br />
it can be satisfied that the exploitation of mineral or timber<br />
resources or the manner or extent of that exploitation will not<br />
adversely affect the environment before giving a licence to exploit<br />
and on that recommendation by Mr JusticejHope's Committee I stated,<br />
our Government will exercise that power regularly and effectively<br />
on the basis of skills and independent advice. And what I pointed out </p>
<p>7.<br />
was that from now on where there are to be any private projects<br />
involving export of minerals or timber we would like to see a joint<br />
environmental impact statement compiled by officials of my<br />
Government and officials of the State Government concerned and then<br />
in the light of that joint environmental impact statement we would<br />
decide whether we would permit the export of products of that<br />
mineral or timber project. It is so as to ensure that people<br />
investing in such projects will know where they stand. Up till<br />
now under the policy of our predecessors, they took no interest<br />
in the environmental aspects although constitutionally the Federal<br />
Government certainly has that responsibility and in our belief should<br />
exercise it.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, the Inquiry suggested that which you<br />
have said now... ( unclear)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I said you will notice from now on, that is, for<br />
new projects. I don't believe that we should disallow projects<br />
which had been allowed to commence under the old policy. But we<br />
want to insist on this from now on.<br />
QUESTION: Most of the causes of Tasmania's economic problems<br />
is generally regarded to be as ( unclear) mainly. And your Government<br />
undertook 17 months ago the revenues. Do you think we are any better<br />
off now than when we were before the last election.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Yes. We have appointed a Royal Commissioner to<br />
enquire into and report upon these matters. I think it was last<br />
November I announced Mr J. F. Nimmo, who had been the senior official<br />
of the Federal Treasury and then became Secretary of the Department<br />
of Housing and is now a member of the Grants Commission should be a<br />
Royal Commissioner to look into the impact of transport costs on the<br />
Tasmanian economy. And one of the things he will look into is the<br />
question which I raised at the meeting I had with John Coates<br />
during the last House of Representatives Campaign in the Town Hall. </p>
<p>8.<br />
I said that it would be a reasonable thing to expect and to work<br />
towards that freight costs say per mile between Hobart and any of<br />
the mainland capitals should be no greater than freigh costs between<br />
any of those capitals. You depend entirely on shipping for your<br />
heavy exports and accordingly, Mr Nimmo, the Royal Commissioner, is<br />
looking into this very matter. In addition there is Mr Summers,<br />
the former Secretary of the Department of Transport who is a Royal<br />
Commissioner looking into the general aspects of the maritime<br />
industry. And this means that he will be suggesting to us what<br />
improvements need to be made and the laws covering our ports and<br />
our coastal shipping and our international shipping.<br />
QUESTION: Tasmania's two tertiary education colleges are about<br />
a mile away from one another in Hobart. Will a Labor Government<br />
consider establishing an autonomous tertiary education body in<br />
Launceston or in the north or alternatively moving the Advanced<br />
College of Education headquarters to Launceston.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I would wait for any recommendations on these<br />
matters to come from the two bodies concerned. There is a<br />
universities commission and there is a commission on advanced<br />
education. I wouldn't act without advice from those bodies on<br />
these matters. You will notice that we sought the advice of the<br />
Commission on Advanced Education concerning an additional grant<br />
for the Hobart College of Advanced Education. When we got the<br />
recommendation we immediately acted upon it. I was asked to open<br />
the Hobart College of Advanced Education last year and the<br />
representations were made to me at that time. I said I will have<br />
the Commission on Advanced Education examine it straight away.<br />
They did. When their report came in we acted upon it. Now<br />
similarly I was asked to open a month ago the new Technical College<br />
at Burnie. There again we acted on the recommendations of this<br />
interim committee, the Kangan one, on technical and further<br />
education. The whole of our course of action depends on expert </p>
<p>advice made available to the public. We've done it in the tertiary<br />
field up till now in Tasmania. I'm sure we'll continue to operate<br />
that way.<br />
QUESTION: It just seems tha the expert advice recommends the<br />
establishment of two academic institutions within a mile of one<br />
another while half of the State's population isn't served upon by<br />
this body, that there must be something wrong with it. Perhaps<br />
a political decision rather than an expert decision.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: This is not a political decision. These<br />
Commissions are not subject to political direction. They recommend<br />
what they like. There can be a political decision. There can be<br />
a political decision later on to reject their advice. We have never<br />
rejected the advice of any of these expert bodies in the educational<br />
field. The Schools Commission, Universities Commission, the<br />
Commission on Advanced Education, the Interim Committee on technical<br />
and further education, we have accepted it in every case. The public<br />
knows what the advice is and we've acted on it. I mean this is a<br />
powerful case, what you say, what you're inferring. Then people<br />
ought to put it to these Commissions.<br />
QUESTION: One of the points is that in the north of the State<br />
we've had disastrous floods there in the last week or so. Will the<br />
Federal Labor Government consider giving disaster aid grants to the<br />
area? PRIME MINISTER: We arranged that two days ago didn't we Mr Barnard?<br />
Mr Barnard and I were discussing this two days ago. We have decided<br />
to give assistance forthwith in the same way as we did when Mr Barnard<br />
was Acting Prime Minister for northern New South Wales and Queensland.<br />
You will get the same range of assistance promptly. Mr Barnard will<br />
give you the details. I'm not sure how much has been published in<br />
this respect.<br />
QUESTION: The Labor budget this year, would it be an adapted<br />
budget or a surplus budget? </p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER: A surplus one I expect. I don't think a deficit<br />
budget would be appropriate this year. There was a deficit budget<br />
in 1972 and again in 1973 and I don't think it would be appropriate<br />
in 1974.<br />
QUESTION: The amount of growth the Labor Party has been playing<br />
in the Commonwealth is considerably increased. I'll re-phrase that.<br />
You will be cutting back on the rate of growth of expenditure in<br />
certain areas if you do budget with a surplus. Can you give us an<br />
idea of some of those areas which you will be cutting back.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The Commonwealth Government's expenditure is<br />
rising more slowly than the public expenditure in Australia. Your<br />
own newspaper, The Age, Melbourne, which . I trust is widely read in<br />
Tasmania, had an excellent article by Mr Ken Davidson, its economics<br />
editor today, who used to be formerly in that position with The<br />
Australian. And he pointed out that the percentage of the domestic<br />
product, the gross domestic product, which isbeing spent by the<br />
Commonwealth Government this year is less than the amount being<br />
spent by the Commonwealth Government out . of the gross domestic<br />
product lAst financial year and the financial year before that.<br />
Actually my Government is spending a smaller amount of the gross<br />
domestic product than was spent by the McMahon Government when Mr<br />
Snedden was Treasurer.<br />
QUESTION: But Mr Prime Minister there is no way out of this to<br />
the point that you how you expect to have a surplus without increasing<br />
your revenue than if you cut the growth of expenditure<br />
PRIME MINISTER: Revenue is going to increase. We all expect that.<br />
Mr Snedden says it will. I say it will. There's no dispute between<br />
the contestants that the revenue is going to increase. I don't<br />
expect to reduce the projected expenditure by the Australian Government<br />
in the next budget. I don't know what reductions there would be in<br />
expenditure by any alternative Government. They're not precise in </p>
<p>11.<br />
this matter. We obviously would not cut projected expenditure in those<br />
fields where my Government has increased expenditure by the Australian<br />
Government namely in Education, Health and Urban affairs.<br />
QUESTION: Will you be able to find a surplus with the doctrine of<br />
the ( unclear) report on hospitals and the bureau of roads<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I expect so. Incidentally on hospitals I mentioned<br />
in Launceston at the Launceston Press Club today; I don't know if you're<br />
all aware of it; that two or three months ago I suggested to the<br />
Premier that we should go halves in the cost of erecting and operating<br />
a new Launceston general hospital and that we should bear the whole of<br />
the cost of finishing and operating the new women's hospital in Hobart.<br />
I point out that under the Constitution since the 1946 referendum the<br />
Australian Government has got the responsibility jointly if you like<br />
with the State Governments of providing hospital benefits and<br />
medical and dental services.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, are you worried about the extent. of the<br />
number of informal votes in the coming election and could this have<br />
an effect on the Labor victory especially in the Senate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I'm obviously worried at the complexity of the<br />
Senate ballot papers in every State. I don't believe there has ever<br />
been such a large number of candidates for the Senate in any State<br />
as there will be on this occasion and a vote is wasted unless the<br />
voter fills in a number in sequence in every square on the Senate<br />
ballot paper as well as in every square on his House of Representatives<br />
ballot paper. The order in which he fills in the numbers is his<br />
choice but unless he fills in a number in every square in whatever<br />
order he himself wishes then his vote is informal. His time in the<br />
polling booth which will be a very long time on this occasion will<br />
have been wasted. I believe that informal votes will not be as<br />
numerous as they would have been if there had bben election for the </p>
<p>Senate alone. Now on the last three occasions 1964, 1967 and 1970,<br />
there has been an election for the Senate alone and the percentage of<br />
informal votes has been higher than it used to be on those occasions<br />
such as 1961 and 1958 and 1955 when elections for the Senate took<br />
place on the same day as elections for the House of Representatives.<br />
I believe on this occasion since people will be more polarised<br />
between the major parties, the Labor Party, the Government on one<br />
hand and the Liberal and Country Party coalition sometimes standing<br />
on different tickets as they are here; sometimes on the same ticket<br />
as in New South Wales. There will not be the same dispersion of<br />
votes among candidates or parties who have no colleagues in the House<br />
of Representatives. I think people will probably concentrate more<br />
meaningfully on how they pass their Senate votes this time and I<br />
would expect that they will follow the how to vote cards they receive<br />
from Party supporters at the polling booths.<br />
QUESTION: Prime Minister, I wonder if you could read the Labor<br />
Government's provision on Life Assurance. Will the $ 1200 tax<br />
deduction ever be made and does the Government intend to continue<br />
the increase of tax on life assurance which the Life'Officers<br />
Association claimed earlier this week to reduce the bonuses<br />
( unclear)<br />
PRIME MINISTER: That was a thoroughly dishonest advertisement.<br />
People who take out insurance policies knwo very well that the<br />
insurance companies ahve been them over the years handover<br />
fist. I think premiums are at the rate of 4% return on investments.<br />
Everybody knows the life assurance socieits are cleaning up twice<br />
or three times that mmount. They are putting money into city<br />
real estate which gets them very much more than the percentage<br />
that they put into premiums. The fact that premiums are so low,<br />
is not the fault of my government. Premiums were:' far too low under<br />
our predecessors too. But we are intent on insuring that people who </p>
<p>13.<br />
put their money to life assurance policies, particularly under the<br />
encouragement of fedraal legislation such as the 1,200 dollars per<br />
year which you mention. The people who do that will get a proper<br />
return on their investment. But they wil share in their return<br />
on the very profitable investments, tnat life assurance policies<br />
amek. I would point out that we are also going to stt up an<br />
Australian Government Insurance Office This will write policies<br />
in general, marine, fire insurance, and natural disasters.<br />
I believe people have been very disillusioned in Australia in the<br />
floods which appeared in Qld. and Northern NSW and now in northern<br />
Tasmania, to find that their properties are not covered against<br />
such natural disasters. The only house insurance companeis who<br />
do cover them are those under the War Service Homes Scheme,<br />
the Defence Services Homes Scheme. We have decided to see<br />
therefore that the advantages of the Defence Services Homes Scheme<br />
are made available to everybody who likes to take out a policy with<br />
the new Australian Governmnt Insrance Office. This will save a<br />
very great deal for home owners and home buyers. They have been<br />
getting a very raw deal up until now. And most of the companies<br />
concerned have been wned overseas.<br />
QUESTION: In your earlier answer on a surplas budget, you said you<br />
expected to go combined surplas budget, a with adoption of the<br />
Bureau of Raods Report and also a Unclear.. Can we take it from<br />
that that you will be accepting those reports and also do you agre<br />
with budgeting the surplas ought to have an effect on reducing<br />
inflation. PRIME MINISTER: Yes, I think to budget for a surplas or a balance<br />
budget, still more if you budget for a surplas, wouldcounter inflation.<br />
As to the Bureau of Roads Report, we are discussingthat with the States </p>
<p>14.<br />
and with local government. It is the first time that there has ever<br />
been a discussions about the Commonwealth's assistance for roads<br />
with local government. The Bureau of Raods suggested it and we have<br />
been having these discusions. The discussions naturally have been<br />
suspended after the oncoming of the election. As I said in my<br />
policy spech they will be resumed after the election. Meantime<br />
however, we have decided to bear the whole cost of the national<br />
highways proposals by the Bureau of Roads. Not 80% but 100%.<br />
And as far as Tasmania is concerned of course, few will remain in<br />
the preferrd positions as it has always been in regards to these<br />
grants. That is the Bureau's recommendations for Tasmania will be<br />
confirmed. All that we have decided otherwise is to bear the whole<br />
cost of the national highways scheme. ( QUESTION UNELEAR)<br />
That has not been considered, but I expect it will be accepted.<br />
I go further than the Sax Report as I have pointed out to you.<br />
with what I have said already about the Launceston general and<br />
the Hobart's womens hospital. Incidentally one doesn't know<br />
what needs to be done in Victoria. Because the Victorian government<br />
wouldn't co-operate with the Sax Committee. The Hospitals and<br />
Charities Commission in Vic. was prevented from giving evidence,<br />
or supplying information to the Sax Committee on hosptials and<br />
health services. We will use our own constitutional responsibilities.<br />
As I sais, since 1946 the Australian Parliament has been entitled<br />
to provide medical and dental services and in Victoria where the<br />
State Government has not co-operated we will procide health centres<br />
and in some of the areas particularly the outer suburbs where there<br />
are not satisfactory hospital facilities available for the families<br />
in that area we will build the hospitals.<br />
QUESTION: First, when you are teturned with a stronger vote in<br />
both chambers of P arliament, will you take urgent steps to improve<br />
the voting system by giving an optional method on'preferential </p>
<p>and secondly, will you take more urgent steps to make it impossible<br />
ever again for any party combination to indulge in this<br />
subservive conscriosy against the Parliamentary system.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: The last one would be largely overcome<br />
if the first of those referendums we have put in is carried.<br />
you will remember hhat that referendum provides for there to be<br />
an election for the whole of the half of the Senate whenever<br />
there is an election for the House of Reps. This is till more<br />
urgent now because on 18 May the Senators who are elected will<br />
take office from 1 July 1973. The House of Reps. members<br />
elected will take office for three years from the day that the<br />
House meets which will be July 1974. So there will be the same<br />
position that there wa in 1951 where the Senators dated from 1<br />
July 1950 and they are there for e had to be another elec tion<br />
for the Senate in about April or Mya 1953 whereas the members<br />
of the House of Representatives didn't have to come up for election<br />
until April or May 1954. So it is very important to have the<br />
sycronisation of the two houses and that being the case if on<br />
any future occasion, the Senate were to refuse supply to the<br />
government which had am majority in the House of Reps the House of<br />
Rpes could go to the people and the senior half of the Senate would<br />
also automatically go to the people and the junior half of the<br />
Senate will have their term reduced by that amount. They would<br />
be going on 3 years time instead of whatever time was still left<br />
ot them. So that position would be largely cured if that first<br />
referendum has a majority of YES votes in four of the States,<br />
as well as in the whole country. Now certainly the Senate ballot<br />
paper ought to be simplifire. It ought to be enough to cast a<br />
valid vote if the vote fills in as many sqaures as there are<br />
vacancies in the Senate. If for instance as usually happens, </p>
<p>16.<br />
there are five Senators to be elected, then it ought to be a valid<br />
vote if the voter fills in numbers 1 to 5 against 5, six if there<br />
is to be elected, against 6. The maximum is 18 at the moment,<br />
if he fills in 10. The present position makes for the most<br />
complicated ballot paper in the world. Then you mention about<br />
optional preferential. That is not an own preferred form of<br />
voting, in Australia in the 60 years or more fedeally, we have<br />
had the preferential voting system. It puts a premium on<br />
complexity. It ought to be possible in my view for people to<br />
indicate their preferences among all or as many as they like<br />
with the candidates they put up. That is if a person believes<br />
his first choice mightn't win, well let him number 2 against the<br />
person who he would rather get in if his first man can'<br />
t get in. But my party has no declared policy on it. It used<br />
to suppo rt the idea of first past the post. You just put x next<br />
to the name of the person who you wanted to get in. And you couldn't<br />
indicate a preference. But that was taken out of the party's policy<br />
at the conference before last I think. And the matter is now in<br />
the melting pot. My own personal preference is the optional<br />
preferential. That is let the person's vote be valid ifx even if he<br />
puts an x against one name of a single candidate. If however he<br />
puts 1,23, whatever it is against as many candidates as he likes<br />
or all the candidates then let hsi preference be adhered to.<br />
QUESTION: What order of surplas to you contemplate?<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I can't anticipate that at this stage.<br />
QUESTION: Do you think<br />
PRIME MINISTER: At least a balanced budget. </p>
<p>17.<br />
PRIME MINISTER: I am not proposing to have a deficit budget this<br />
year as we had in our first one and Mr. Snedden's last one. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
