<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>8277</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER COMMEMORATIVE DINNER CONSTITUTIONAL CEMETARY CONFERENCE SYDNEY - 4 APRIL 1991</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/04/1991</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00008277.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST nDELITVE PMBARCDED UNTIL DELIVE~ RY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
COMMEMORATIVE DINNER<br />
CONSTI[ TUTIONAL CENTENARY CONFERENCE<br />
SYDNEY 4 APRIL 1991<br />
Sir Ninian Stephen,<br />
Members of the Steering Committee,<br />
Premiers and Federal Parliamentary colleagues<br />
Ladies and gentlemen<br />
To all those responsible for arranging this Constitutional<br />
Centenary Conference, and this commemorative dinner, I want<br />
at the outset to extend my congratulations and my best<br />
wishes. I say this not Just because you are marking an important<br />
event in the political history of our nation, but because<br />
you are doing so in such a constructive and forward looking<br />
way. Nothing would be more alien to the spirit of those who<br />
drafted the 1891 Constitution, and who for the entire decade<br />
of the 1890s pursued their ambition for a federal united<br />
Australia, than to mark this occasion in some desiccated or<br />
static fashion thEit overlooked the magnitude of their<br />
achievement. 4<br />
Because it needs to0 be remembered, as we look back on the<br />
momentous 1890s, that there was nothing inevitable about the<br />
success of the Australian Federation movement.<br />
Notwithstanding the vision and furious energy of Parkes, the<br />
farsightedness of Deakin, the determination of Griffith, and<br />
the commitment of all the others who produced the 1891 draft<br />
Constitution, there was no certainty that their efforts<br />
would succeed.<br />
It required hard work, give and take, a sensd of common<br />
purpose and a high degree of political leadership.<br />
Those who attended the 1891 Convention had those qualities. </p>
<p>They arrived in this city and this parliamentary building as<br />
the leaders of separate and almost rival colonies. By the<br />
timie they departed, they had transformed themselves into our<br />
first generation of national leaders.<br />
And on the divisions of colonial rivalries they had laid the<br />
foundations for a united nation.<br />
Of course, there was a number of differences between the<br />
plan of 1891 and th6 reality of 1901.<br />
Not the least was that the federation that emerged was not<br />
Australasian but was, can one say ' merely', Australian.<br />
It was the remarkable 79-year old Sir George Grey the<br />
former explorer and colonial governor turned politician, who<br />
attended the 1891 Convention in his capacity as a former<br />
Prime Minister of New Zealand who made it clear that New<br />
Zea landers would continue along their own path.<br />
So we have 4~ r George Grey to thank for safeguarding our<br />
rights to enjoy Trans-Tasman cricket Tests.<br />
Even with the boundaries of the federation restricted to<br />
this side of the Tasman, " the draft of 1891 is", as<br />
John La Nauze observed, " the Constitution of 1900, not its<br />
father or grandfather."<br />
Now, I know this is not the place to inject any sort of<br />
partisan comment. But is it not remarkable that Sydney, in<br />
March and April 1891, saw the birth of not one but two<br />
enduring national institutions: it saw not only the drafting<br />
of the document that was to become the Federal Constitution,<br />
but also the emergence of the parliamentary labor party.<br />
It took the entire decade, with many stops and starts, for<br />
the concept of a united federal Australia to bear fruit.<br />
But one immediate by-product of the 1891 Convention was that<br />
the first platform of the New South Wales Labor Party,<br />
written in the atmosphere of enthusiasm engendered by the<br />
Constitutional Convention, included a staunchly<br />
pre -Federation plank.<br />
A few months after the Convention, Labor scored its first<br />
electoral success, recording more than 100,000 votes and<br />
securing the election of 35 candidates as members of the<br />
Parliament of New South Wales.<br />
It would be a brave person who would attribute this success<br />
to Labor's pro-Federation plank. The other fifteen planks<br />
of the platform included much more immediately attractive<br />
goals electoral reform, an eight hours working day, and<br />
various other legislative amendments to improve working<br />
conditions.<br />
62 </p>
<p>But the point that needs to be made tonight is this: anyone<br />
reading that Labor platform today is reading a document that<br />
is obviously a relic of a by-gone era.<br />
The same cannot be said for its contemporary, the 1891 draft<br />
Constitution. The leaders who drafted the Constitution of 1891 and who<br />
forged the Federation of 1901, would no doubt be gratified<br />
by the durability of their achievement a united Australia.<br />
But I am sure they would be surprised to know that the<br />
details of their draft remain so firmly entrenched in<br />
contemporary practice.<br />
I don't mean to imply that there has been no change in the<br />
way we govern ourselves.<br />
Australia has at last totally severed its residual ties<br />
with Britain;<br />
The relations between the Commonwealth and States have<br />
been changed, at times profoundly, within the existing<br />
framework of the Constitution for example, with<br />
uniform taxation and family law;<br />
In the same way, judicial interpretation has allowed<br />
very considerable change in the role of the<br />
Commonwealth ; overnment;<br />
And, all too rarely, change has been achieved through<br />
referendum most notably with the triumph of the 1967<br />
referendum on Aboriginal people.<br />
But it is common ground to this audience, I believe, that we<br />
have to seek new paths towards a more contemporary<br />
Constitution. i<br />
I look forward to hearing from you tomorrow the outcome of<br />
your discussions over the last couple of days, and to<br />
hearing your assessment of the possible direction, scope and<br />
pace of further constitutional reform.<br />
Let me tonight tell you where the Commonwealth stands, and<br />
in particular let me outline the progress we are making, in<br />
cooperation with the States, towards the goal of creating a<br />
more relevant and efficient federal structure.<br />
Last July, I committed the Commonwealth Government to a new<br />
effort to create a closer partnership between our three<br />
levels of Government.<br />
In a speech at the National Press Club, I outlined two<br />
tasks: the first, to move by sensible, practicable steps to<br />
achieve better co-operation within the framework of the<br />
Constitution; and the second, to apply the spirit of<br />
national co-operation in a new approach to reform of the<br />
Constitution itself. G227 </p>
<p>Underscoring all that I proposed in July was the recognition<br />
that % ie must be about achlaiabla reform.<br />
As I said, we cannot totally re-write the Constitution. We<br />
cannot: replace the Federal system.<br />
But we can make the Constitution and the Federal system work<br />
better. We can and we must. The alternative is to abandon the<br />
challenge of becoming a truly modern society and of<br />
attaining our full potential as a prosperous and competitive<br />
community. That alternative would mean that governments could exhort<br />
the private sector to reform its own practices and could<br />
encourage community groups such as trade unions to become<br />
more flexible, but would be incapable adequately of<br />
addressing their own shortcomings and of improving their own<br />
productive caprcities.<br />
That simply is an unacceptable alternative.<br />
That is why I made my proposals in July and why I report<br />
progress on them to you tonight with a sense of pride but,<br />
more importantly, with a sense of urgency that more must<br />
still be done.<br />
The Special Premiers Conference process has marked a<br />
milestone in cooperation between the Commonwealth and States<br />
and Territories.<br />
Importantly, the Commonwealth has agreed to address the<br />
issue, of Commonwealth-State financial relations, with a<br />
commitment within our overall responsibility for proper<br />
management of the national economy to aim to reduce the<br />
fiscal imbalance with the States, and to reduce the<br />
proportion of tied grants that go to the States.<br />
As you will appreciate, these are issues of the utmost<br />
compl. exity. Progress will not be easy but there is the<br />
commitment to see if a mutually acceptable outcome is<br />
possible. These3 matters are due for consideration by me and my<br />
colleagues in our meetings in May and November this year.<br />
At the same time, we will be continuing to work towards a<br />
more efficient, competitive infrastructure within this<br />
count~ ry.<br />
We have accepted, if you like, the imperative of doing what<br />
we can to create a single national economy, not a fragnented<br />
economy of nine separate jurisdictions.<br />
622? </p>
<p>In roads and food Eitandards, we have accepted the<br />
responsibility for reducing the vast regulatory overlap that<br />
exists within Australia.<br />
In land transport end electricity generation, we are<br />
pursuing the very real gains that can come from adopting a<br />
national rather thein state perspective on the provision of<br />
essential infrastructure.<br />
In service delivery-, in environmental protection, in<br />
industrial relations, we have committed ourselves to more<br />
effective and efficient co-operation.<br />
We have established, clear processes of review; with the<br />
Special Premiers Conference process itself, we have created<br />
a vehicle for implementing change, where none existed<br />
before; and we have, demonstrated our commitment as leaders<br />
to resolve the issues and to reform the inefficiencies of<br />
the present Federal structure.<br />
Last October, we established working groups of State and<br />
Commonwealth officials to prepare reports on: regulatory<br />
reform, road transport, rail freight, Government trading<br />
enterprises, non-bank financial institutions and electricity<br />
generation. Progress reports will be considered at the next Special<br />
Premiers Conference, next month, and, with a third<br />
Conference scheduled for November, they will create the<br />
momentum for reform through 1991, and beyond.<br />
As I foreshadowed In my 12 March statement, Building a<br />
Competitive Australia, I will also at next month's meeting<br />
be urging the States towards widening the ambit of the Trade<br />
Practices Act to create a more competitive national1<br />
framework. Our goals are to improve our national efficiency and<br />
international competitiveness, and to improve the delivery<br />
and quality of the services governments provide.<br />
So I have been able; to give the Australian people this<br />
double assurance. Where micro-economic reform can be<br />
achieved through the exercise of Commonwealth power alone,<br />
we will achieve it. And where it requires the cooperative<br />
endeavour of the Commonwealth and the States, we are doing<br />
all we can to secure that cooperation. 4<br />
Together, we are making progress towards our goals.<br />
Let me turn now to the second area of reform I outlined in<br />
my July speech: the issue of reform of the Constitution<br />
itself. The sad history of reform by referendum speaks for itself:<br />
this is not a mission for the naively optimistic. </p>
<p>Too often indeed, almost without fail referendum<br />
proposals have become caught up in partisan controversy and<br />
they have failed to attain the rigorously defined majority<br />
specified by the Constitution for them.<br />
This time, if we are to make progress, the major political<br />
parties must commit themselves in advance to presenting the<br />
case for agreed reform in a positive and unanimous fashion.<br />
Tcday I believe wl have the oppartunity for such a process,<br />
aimed at achievind a Constitutional referendum mandating<br />
four year terms for the House of Representatives.<br />
The arguments in favour of four year terms are compelling,<br />
arid I understand you have canvassed them, and endorsed them,<br />
in your deliberations so far.<br />
I am confident that the only possible obstacle to the<br />
successful passage of a referendum on four year terms is the<br />
risk of the proposal being buried in partisan conflict as<br />
happened in 1988.<br />
V<br />
But there have been repeated indications that the Opposition<br />
might now be prepared to join the Government in publicly<br />
supporting a referendum campaign for four year terms.<br />
Accordingly, I wrote to the Leader of the Opposition last<br />
week inviting him to discuss possible areas of agreement on<br />
this with me.<br />
Clearly, these discussions would have to address the still<br />
unresolved questions of detail such as whether a four year<br />
term should be fixed, and how to synchronise Senate terms.<br />
Equally clearly, this is not the place to discuss the<br />
Government' s proposal.<br />
I can only stress once more the absolute necessity of<br />
obtaining bipartisan support, in advance, before the<br />
Government will contemplate another referendum campaign on<br />
this issue. That is the pre-condition.<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
I do believe that there is a new spirit of co-operation<br />
operating within the Federal structure of Australia today.<br />
It is manifest in the progress that has been made at the<br />
level of the Special Premiers' Conference, and it is<br />
apparent in the serious and constructive discussions that<br />
have characterised this Constitutional Convention this week<br />
discussions that embrace many parts of the Australian<br />
community and span generations of the Australian people.<br />
None of this progress could have been achieved by either<br />
side of politics, or by any tier of Government, working<br />
alone.<br />
630 </p>
<p>Reform is not a task for Government alone; enduring reform<br />
cannot be imposed by Government on the rest of the<br />
community. The vital ingredient is the active involvement and<br />
commitment of the community itself. And it is through<br />
Conferences such as this that the community can participate,<br />
and can be educated and encouraged for further<br />
participation. This will continue i: o require hard work, give and take, a<br />
sense of common purpose, and a high degree of political<br />
leadership by representatives of the whole Australian<br />
community. As I have said, those are the very qualities that were<br />
needed at the Constitutional Convention in 1891 and the<br />
very qualities that were in fact possessed and displayed by<br />
the convention delegates then.<br />
If our work today continues to be characterised by such<br />
profoundly important: attributes and I am confident it can<br />
be then we will irndeed be able to ensure a renewed<br />
relevance and effectiveness for the Australian Federal<br />
Constitution as it e. pproaches and enters its second century. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
