<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1805</transcript-id>
    <title>REVIEW OF TROOPS OF FIRST BATTALION RAR, HOLSWORTHY, NSW - SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. JOHN G. GORTON, MP.</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/03/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001805.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
REVIEW OF TROOPS OF FIRST BATTALION<br />
RAR, HOLSVJORTHY, NSW 22 MARCH, 1968<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MNISTER, THE RT. HON.<br />
JOHN G. GORTON, MP<br />
It must have been a thrill to any Australian who today<br />
saw you marching past and demonstrating the discipline, the training and<br />
the ability which you have learnt.<br />
I suspect, unless things have changed very considerably<br />
since the time I once wore uniform, this has been-the result of some<br />
considerable practice, of some -considerable rehearsals. And again I<br />
suspect, unless things have changed, that sometimes these practices and<br />
those rehearsals were a little dreary. But the end result has been, as the<br />
end result of hard work and-application must always be, that you have today<br />
put on for all of us here a parade which I do not believe would have been<br />
bettered by any body of armed men from any country in the world.<br />
You marched past-half of you, so I am informed,<br />
Regular soldiers, half of you National Servicemen, and completely<br />
Indistinguishable the one from the other as you will In the future grow even<br />
less distinguishable, If that is possible.<br />
A Regular -soldier or -National Serviceman is now, and will<br />
be In the future, an Australian soldier and there is, and will be, no difference<br />
between them. You will be going because your Government and your country<br />
thinks It right, and for the safety of our nation that this should happen, to<br />
fight some considerable distance away, ln terms of miles, from Australift,<br />
but no-great distance away In terms of time. You have been asked to go, or<br />
you have been told to go, b ecause in our judgment It is to -the safety of all<br />
small nations to do what they can to see that other small nations are not<br />
allowed to be overrun by force, or by subversion, or by terrorism, but<br />
should have the chance to retain for themselves the opportunity to make , a<br />
choice to build the kind of life that the Australian people have an opportunity<br />
to choose. You will have before you, because this is a part of all<br />
soldiering, many times of boredom, of heat, of uncomfortable conditions,<br />
of tension, of strain, and I believe of fear, because I think that most men<br />
In battle feel but conquer fear. This will be punctuated by periods of<br />
action, but whether in action or in training, I would like you to know this.<br />
No matter what some columnists from time to time may Indicate In what<br />
they write; no matter what attitude some members of legislature may from<br />
time -to time Indicate from what they say, your Government believes that<br />
you are serving this nation i the highest way In which It can be served and<br />
will stand behind you and guard your good name to the end to the best of its<br />
ability. And -behind that, and far more Important than that, 90 per cent of<br />
the Australian people are proud of how you bear yourselves, are proud of what<br />
you are doing, In some cases what you have done and what you will do.<br />
Never for a moment think that -this nation and Its people are not behind you<br />
and backing you, because they are. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2<br />
Idon't want to keep you standing there for long,,. I will just<br />
conclude by saying this.<br />
Your grandfathers went to France and to Gallipoli, not for<br />
themselves to try and see that aggression did not succeed, but to help to<br />
see aggression didn't succeed. And for a while they were successful.<br />
Your fathers went to the four corners of the world to try and see<br />
that that great attack on human dignity made at that time by Nazi Germany<br />
would not succeed, and they smashed that attack. You are carrying on in<br />
that tradition. No man can say, and no generation can say, what I do now will,<br />
for all the future, make life better. But a man can say and -a generation<br />
can say, what I do now I believe will make it more likely that In the future,<br />
life will be better for the people of the world. And when you come back,<br />
and when you leave the Army, you will have this to retain for the rest of<br />
your lives and nothing can take It away, and nothing can tarnish it.<br />
You can say I have been one of a regiment, I have taken my place in that<br />
regiment, I have borne myself as a brave and honourable man should.<br />
I -have taken the risks that one must take. I have accepted that and I<br />
have served my country well.<br />
Good luck to you all. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
