<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21657</transcript-id>
    <title>Interview with Mark Ferguson Channel Nine News </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/03/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>MARK FERGUSON:</p>
<p>And joining us now from Canberra is Prime Minister, John Howard.  Prime Minister, you've just been speaking to Indonesian President Yudhoyono, what help have you been able to offer him?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We've offered him not only some initial emergency aid of $1 million but also some medical facilities and as you heard those facilities are now on the way.  And also medical evacuation facilities and both of these will be provided by the resources of the Australian military, who again of course are there to do an absolutely magnificent job.  And as the situation unfolds if further help is needed then it will certainly be made available.</p>
<p>MARK FERGUSON:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, do you expect Australia to again lead the international relief effort?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>We will do whatever we can.  This is not a competition between Australia and other countries - it's the natural, warm-hearted response of the Australian people to a neighbour and friend, again in trouble.  And I know that I speak for every Australian in saying how terrible it is that these poor people having suffered so much from the Boxing Day tsunami, some of them again should be suffering from this earthquake.</p>
<p>MARK FERGUSON:</p>
<p>Do you have any more details on the changes to the President's Australian visit?</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Yes, he'll be postponing the visit, he will now arrive on Sunday evening and the visit will go ahead in Canberra and Sydney on the Monday and the Tuesday.  He is very much looking forward to the visit, but understandably his first responsibility is to visit the devastated areas and to assess for himself what is needed and we'll have an opportunity of getting more information about that when he comes.  But it's a very important visit and, this tragedy notwithstanding, it will go ahead.</p>
<p>MARK FERGUSON:</p>
<p>Prime Minister, thanks for your time.</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER:</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p>[ends]  </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
