<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6346</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER, INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS, 15 MARCH 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>15/03/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006346.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY A--LEBRODAGAINST DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER]<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER<br />
INSTITUTE OF DIRECTORS 15 MARCH 1984<br />
Mr Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
It is with particular pleasure that I accepted your<br />
invitation to join you tonight.<br />
At this time of the year the Government is gearing up to<br />
prepare its next Budget. It is therefore timely that we<br />
should review assumptions about the environment within which<br />
the crucial decisions must be framed arid take stock of the<br />
achievements to date.<br />
The record of the past twelve months, I am sure you would<br />
all agree, has been a very good one. The economy is now<br />
demonstrating strong economic growth. Subject to certain<br />
qualifications which I shall address later, the outlook for<br />
the medium and longer-term is encouraging and underpins the<br />
confidence now widely felt throughout the community in our<br />
national economic prospects.<br />
Crucial to an appreciation of those prospects must be an<br />
assessment of the international economic outlook. In the<br />
same way as recovery of the United States' economy<br />
contributed to the turn-around in Australia's economic<br />
fortunes in 1983, continued strong American economic growth<br />
without a resurgence of higher inflation and an increase in<br />
the level of interest rates is important to the maintenance<br />
of Australia's own long-term growth performance.<br />
It is therefore encouraging that the United States economy<br />
is moving into a second year of vigorous expansion. The<br />
U. S. economic indicators are unmistakable: Real GNP in the<br />
US expanded by over 6 per cent during the course ? f 1983<br />
and is expected to grow in real terms by around per cent<br />
in 1984. Capacity utilization in the United States also<br />
increased significantly in 1983, and American business<br />
investment has as well now started to pick up. Total<br />
civilian employment in the U. S. expanded by around 4 millicon<br />
jobs since the trough of the recession in November 1982. </p>
<p>2.<br />
With other countries, the same indicators were less<br />
clear-cut, but there are signs of improvement. Japanese<br />
growth is expected to be stronger this year, while remaining<br />
modest by older historical standards. The European<br />
economies have been sluggish, although I should note that<br />
the Treasurer recently returned from an OECD meeting to<br />
report that the major European economies can be expected to<br />
contribute more in the immediate future to world-wide<br />
economic growth than they have for some time.<br />
Indeed while aggregate GNP in the OECD area is projected by<br />
the OECD to grow by only 3.5 per cent in 1984, this prospect<br />
is more encouraging than it has been for several years.<br />
World trade and activity in less industrialised areas is<br />
also picking up. The OECD estimates that by mid-1985 real<br />
GNP in North America and Japan may be 7 to 9 per cent higher<br />
than two years earlier and in Europe some 3 per cent higher.<br />
The international stimulus to activity is therefore very<br />
real. Some Australian trade and commodity prices are<br />
already benefiting directly from this, although for several<br />
of our major export industries the benefits of international<br />
economic recovery are likely to appear more strongly over<br />
the next year or so than they have to date. The fact that<br />
international recovery is under way without any marked rise<br />
in world inflation is an added bonus.<br />
There are, however, residual concerns in some quarters that<br />
the present international economic recovery might be<br />
short-lived. These doubts reflect concern that the recent<br />
pattern of economic expansion in the United States might not<br />
be sustainable.<br />
In this view the recent spurt in American economic growth<br />
risks rekindling inflationary expectations and putting<br />
upward pressure on interest rates.<br />
Recognition of the risks inherent in this situation<br />
underpinned the recent OJECD Ministerial Conference's quite<br />
decisive reaffirmation of the need to reduce budget<br />
deficits, constrain public sector expenditure ( especially<br />
transfer payments to people able to look after themselves,<br />
and industry subsidies), and to roll back all forms of<br />
protection and other impediments to economic flexibility and<br />
structural change.<br />
Each element in this preferred OECD approach has found a<br />
reflection in the economic strategy of the Australian Labor<br />
Government. The United States recovery has had some important influence<br />
on the recent upturn in Australia's economic performance.<br />
Of greater importance so far has been the remarkable surge<br />
in output and incomes in the farm sector. </p>
<p>3.<br />
The breaking of the drought has seen a major and much needed<br />
recovery in Australia's rural sector. This reflects for the<br />
most part record grain harvests. .1 should note, however,<br />
that livestock sector production is expected to decline-in<br />
1983-84, and that it will take a number of normal seasons<br />
for the sector to recover fully.<br />
That said, farm product in 1983-84 is now expected to<br />
increase in real terms by about 30 per cent compared with<br />
per cent expected at Budget time. This 30 per cent<br />
growth will contribute 1.5 per cent to overall product<br />
growth a substantial contribution to the overall recovery<br />
in the Australian economy.<br />
Australia's economic recovery is not, however, based solely<br />
or even mainly on the upturn in the rural sector. A more<br />
general strengthering has occurred. The 1983 September<br />
quarter National Accounts Statistics show, for example, that<br />
non-farm product rose in real terms by 2.3 per cent in that<br />
quarter. The pattern of the turnaround in the September quarter was<br />
much as expected, though the pace of the improvement was<br />
much stronger than economic forecasters including the<br />
official ones had first thought likely.<br />
The stimulus to growth came from the rebuilding of stocks,<br />
public sector demand, private consumption and dwelling<br />
investment. More recent indicators suggest that this pattern of growth<br />
has continued into the current half year. The stimulus<br />
given to the economy by the Government's budgetary policies<br />
including to the housing sector have been important factors.<br />
The dull spot in the September quarter accounts was the<br />
continued weakness in business fixed investment. This was<br />
expected. As we indicated at Budget time, there would be<br />
little prospect of an improvement in business fixed<br />
investment until the recovery was firmly established.<br />
Indeed, at the time of the Budget we said that a decline in<br />
investment could be expected in 1983-84. The results of the<br />
most recent survey by the statistician of new fixed capital<br />
expenditure by private enterprises do imply, however,<br />
somewhat stronger levels of plant and equipment investment<br />
through the course of the year, with continuing weak<br />
investment in building and structures. On these trends it<br />
would appear that while overall investment may stabilize in<br />
the second half of 1983-84 we cannot be sure the required<br />
recovery in investment will materialise.<br />
When my Government came to office the inflation rate in<br />
Australia was 11.5 per cent. Since then the trend in the<br />
inflation rate has clearly been downward. Over the year to<br />
the December quarter, the inflation rate was 8.6 per cent,<br />
the lowest since the March quarter 1979. </p>
<p>Looking ahead, the introduction of Medicare will have a<br />
significant downward effect on the CPI in the March and June<br />
quarters of 1984. Little change in the CPI is actually<br />
expected in the March quarter and only a mod-est increase is<br />
anticipated in the June quarter.<br />
In these circumstances we can, therefore, expect that<br />
through the rest of this financial year the inflation rate<br />
will drop still further. It needs to Australia's<br />
underlying inflation rate is still well above that of our<br />
major trading partners.<br />
Continuation of the downward trend in inflation will depend<br />
critically upon the course of cost pressures and, in<br />
particular, labour costs. To date these have been very<br />
favourable. The 4.3 per cent national wage increase handed<br />
down on 23 September 1983 has now been implemented and is<br />
reflected in the 7.2 per cent growth in average weekly<br />
earnings, over the year to the December quarter.<br />
Importantly, apart from the growth in award wages, the<br />
increase in earnings mainly reflects compositional and other<br />
influences other than over-award payments.<br />
I am confident adherence to the Prices and Incomes Accord<br />
will contain unit labour costs into the forseeable future.<br />
I say this in full awareness that corporate profits are<br />
returning to more satisfactory levels.<br />
There has also been substantial improvement in the labour<br />
market since the Labor Government took office. In<br />
seasonally adjusied terms, the number of new jobs expanded<br />
by 140,800 ( or 2 2per cent) between the low point in April<br />
1983 and February 1984. The unemployment rate fell in the<br />
same period from 10.3 per cent to 9.4 per cent.<br />
Indeed the outlook for the economy over the rest of 1983-84<br />
is distinctly encouraging.<br />
The signs are that Budget time forecasts for growth in<br />
domestic production and employment will each be<br />
significantly exceeded. Employment has already grown by<br />
more than the Budget time forecast for the whole financial<br />
year. Recent partial indicators of demand all point to a<br />
firmer tone in the last half of 1983 and early 1984. Motor<br />
vehicle registrations, retail sales and building approvals<br />
have all shown strong growth in recent months.<br />
For 1983-84 as a whole, growth looks like being particularly<br />
strong in dwelling construction, public expenditures and<br />
exports. The turnaround in the stock cycle should also<br />
contribute significantly to growth. </p>
<p>Non-farm product also now looks as if it will be 4 per cent<br />
higher this financial year than last, as a result of growth<br />
of around 8 per cent through the financial year. Total<br />
output seems set to rrow by over 10 per cent through the<br />
year so that it is 5 2 per cent higher in 1983-84 than in the<br />
previous financial year.<br />
A particular task in the months ahead is to reduce the size.<br />
of our 1984-85 deficit from the level that was appropriate<br />
for the first year of recovery. Certainly the Government<br />
intends reducing its own borrowing demands in the next<br />
Budget. Obviously, it is a question of degree. We here in Australia<br />
clearly will have to balance what we think are the needs of<br />
the private sector for borrowed funds to sustain and build<br />
on recovery, and the desirability of not cutting back on net.<br />
public spending to such an extent that the recovery peters<br />
out. Equally, we should be aware that the path of continuing<br />
large, fiscal deficits may lead through high interests rates<br />
to a rather higher exchange rate than might otherwise have<br />
been the case.<br />
The exchange rate is now determined by the market and not by<br />
official fiat. The mix of Government policies and<br />
expectations about the Australian economy will still<br />
influence the exchange rate. But if the Government is to<br />
avoid placing upward pressure on interest rates and the<br />
exchange rate it must continue its efforts to reduce the<br />
budget deficit as private sector investment strengthens.<br />
I think it also should be recognised that we have within our<br />
own region within the Asia-Pacific region the<br />
circumstances that will help to sustain strong Australian<br />
economic growth. The economic dynamism of many countries<br />
within the region, coupled with the massive human and<br />
material resource base many of them enjoy, provides an ideal<br />
outlet for Australian trading and economic interests. To<br />
the extent we are successful at " locking into" regional<br />
economic growth patterns, the more we as a nation stand to<br />
gain. The interest that Premier Zhao demonstrated during my recent<br />
visti to China in the integration of the iron and steel<br />
industries of Australia and China through programs of<br />
mutual investment, technical assistance and the supply of<br />
Australian raw materials and semi-processed products to<br />
China's mills is indicative of the scale of possibilities<br />
which exist. Seeking out and developing such possibilities3<br />
is critically important to Australia's long-term economic<br />
well-being. </p>
<p>It is important also that Australia do what it can to<br />
contribute to securing a freer, more open international<br />
trade regime. Conditions conducive to sustained global<br />
trade expansion must be established. They do not exist at<br />
the moment. This recognition lay behind my Bangkok trade<br />
initiative. The approach that initiative suggests is a practical,<br />
workmanlike one suitable both to our purpose and to a<br />
realistic appreciation of how we might most effectively make<br />
progress in this difficult area.<br />
More specifically, through a process of close consultation,<br />
particularly with the countries in our own region, we aim to<br />
get a statement of regional countries' priority interests in<br />
market access onto the table. With such a statement, and in<br />
the context of a new multilateral trade round, regional<br />
countries should be able to secure attention to their<br />
pressing contemporary concerns and revive consideration of<br />
areas previously put aside as exceptions to the general<br />
trading rules. Subsidies and non-tariff barriers to trade<br />
are examples of such exceptions which Australia, for its<br />
part, would want to see more seriously considered.<br />
The support we have received for the approach I have<br />
proposed has been most encouraging. A meeting of senior<br />
officials will soon be held in an Asean country to carry the<br />
exercise forward.<br />
The inevitable corollary to any bid for a more open, freer<br />
international trade regime the benefits of which none<br />
would dispute must be some measure of adjustment in our<br />
domestic economic structure.<br />
It is indisputable that past policies of Government, and<br />
past failures of entrepreneurship, have caused Australia to<br />
miss opportunities and have locked some Australia resources<br />
into relatively unproductive uses.<br />
Sustained long-term economic growth and meeting the economic<br />
and social aspirations of the community require that<br />
Australia's resources be applied to their most productive<br />
uses. Importantly for Australia, this means accepting<br />
gradual structural change and a community willingness to<br />
share its costs equitably.<br />
The Government does not have any monopoly of wisdom in this<br />
area indeed if change of the kind implied is to be handled<br />
successfully it must be based on widespread community<br />
understanding and acceptance of the need for change,<br />
especially in the industries most affected. </p>
<p>The consultatiave procedures my Government has proposed both<br />
at the national and industry level are aimed at securing<br />
such understanding. EPAC's endorsement and development of<br />
this approach earlier this week was an important step<br />
forward. We can, I believe be confident that Australia's<br />
endowments of well educated people, large stocks of capital<br />
from home and abroad, and natural resources, will position<br />
Australia well for strong expansion of industries based on<br />
these endowments.<br />
But as I have repeatedly said before it is not for the<br />
Government to pick " winners and losers". A program of<br />
structural change will and should have as its aim the<br />
creation of opportunities for expansion of our most<br />
productive industries. The detailed structure of Australian<br />
industry will in future be determined by the individual<br />
decisions and performance of Australian enterprises and<br />
their workers. It is for the private sector at this point<br />
in time to move deliberately, in its investment and<br />
rationalisation decisions, to meet the future.<br />
I am sure that, with the process of renewed and sustained<br />
economic growth, the face of Australia industry will change.<br />
Ten years from now we should have more specialised, more<br />
skilled and more internationally competitive industries<br />
producing more goods, employing more people and facing the<br />
future with considerably more confidence than has been<br />
apparent in recent years.<br />
This is our long-term challenge. It is an integral part of<br />
what the Government hopes to achieve through its medium and<br />
long-term economic growth strategies. It is what we look to<br />
Australian industry to achieve.<br />
The main challenge in the immediate future, however, is to<br />
keep the Australian economy moving in the right direction.<br />
This will not be easy, and I have touched on some of the<br />
difficulties. Importantly it will involve maintaining continued progress<br />
in the positive trends in the principal economic indicators<br />
that is, employment and unemployment, economic growth,<br />
inflation, and interest rates. While the international<br />
economic situation does carry some real uncertainties, I am<br />
on balance confident of a continuing, strong Australian<br />
economic performance.<br />
But as I have said in several recent speeches and as Paul<br />
Keating emphasised at Monday's EPAC meeting the private<br />
sector, and more specifically your companies, have a major<br />
role to play in securing this result. Many of the decision<br />
my Government has taken to date have aimed not only at<br />
providing an immediate stimulus to a depressed economy but<br />
also to secure conditions for healthy growth in the private<br />
sector in the longer term. This we regard as crucial to<br />
long-term, sustained economic growth. </p>
<p>We believe that the strong recovery of 1983-84 can be<br />
followed by sustained growth in 1984-85 and beyond, at rates<br />
well above the inadequate performance of the past decade.<br />
As the Treasurer said to EPAC on this will require<br />
strong recovery in private investment to replace the impact<br />
of such one-off factors as the ending of the drought. We<br />
believe this result is possible indeed that it is a<br />
logical response by business to the general improvement in<br />
economic conditions that are now apparent, and which can be<br />
expected to continue for some time.<br />
Already it is clear that the policies the Austr'alian Labor<br />
Government is promoting are contributing to substantially<br />
higher share of profits in total income, lower inflation,<br />
lower unit labour costs, lower interest rates and greater<br />
confidence in the continuity of economic policy. Our<br />
industrial relations policies have produced the lowest level<br />
of disputation for 15 years. I would simply ask when<br />
business has known a better environment within which to<br />
commit its own resources to a renewed round of investment?<br />
Indeed by doing so it will itself be contributing to the<br />
maintenance and enhancement of the very conditions it so<br />
greatly values.<br />
This is not to say the Government wants to retreat from its<br />
responsibilities. It is determined to do its part. If it is possible to do so<br />
within the limits of the overall budgetary situation, we<br />
will lend the Government's full support to the Prices and<br />
Incomes Accord at a time when nominal wage increases are<br />
small, by providing for taxation relief to low and middle<br />
income earners. Above all, we are determined that public<br />
sector demands on financial markets will be reduced as<br />
private investment ' increases, as we believe it should in the<br />
improved economic conditions of next financial year.<br />
With the co-operation of all Australians, whether<br />
individually or collectively, whether in Government or in<br />
business or as workers in the private sector, I am confident<br />
the coming year will see a further building on the<br />
improvements made this year.<br />
The Government for its part will continue working to ensure<br />
an economic climate conducive to expansion by containing<br />
inflation and pressures on capital and labour markets.<br />
As you in business appreciate, sustainable long-term<br />
recovery requires substantial investment outlays by the<br />
private sector. If we are to tackle inflation and<br />
unemployment together if we are to ensure conditions of<br />
long-term economic growth it is vital that business play<br />
its role by raising investment, just as it is vital that the </p>
<p>9.<br />
labour movement play its role by restraining wage claims as<br />
required by the Accord. In this regard we all have<br />
responsibilities. It is in the community's interest, indeed<br />
in Australia's interest, as well as in each of your own<br />
interests, Australians should shoulder these<br />
responsibilities together. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
