<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7391</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTERS SPEECH TO THE VICTORIAN STATE PALIAMENTARY PRESS GALLERY THURSDAY - 1 SEPTEMBER 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/09/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007391.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
PRIME MINISTER'S SPEECH TO THE VICTORIAN<br />
STATE PARLIAMENTARY PRESS GALLERY<br />
THURSDAY -1 SEPTEMBER 1988<br />
Members of the Press Gallery,<br />
Ladies and gentlemen,<br />
In about thirty six hours time it will be up to Australian<br />
voters to play their part in the great process of<br />
constitutional reform by bringing in their verdict on four<br />
referendum questions.<br />
I believe their verdict will be an historic one that they<br />
will agree to amend the Constitution and to reform the rules<br />
by which we govern ourselves.<br />
I believe they will vote " yes" to all four questions because<br />
they will recognise that all the referendum proposals are<br />
ultimately about enhancing their own constitutional * tature<br />
not the power of any Government, not the power of<br />
Canberra, not the power of any political party, not the<br />
power of politicians.<br />
They are people's reforms and I believe they will be<br />
recognised and acceded to as such.<br />
Constitutional change is not to be proposed or agreed to<br />
lightly. But there are times when such changes have to be proposed'<br />
and should be made.<br />
Such a time is now.<br />
It was to allow change and to open the way to progressive<br />
modernisation of the Constitution that our founding fathers<br />
provided a means by which change could be carried out.<br />
In creating the referendum provisions in the Constitution,<br />
our founding fathers were expressing their faith in the<br />
intelligence and good sense of the Australian people a<br />
faith that in the years to come the people would be able to<br />
consider proposals for constitutional reform and make an<br />
informed judgement, just~ as they had done when they approved<br />
the Constitution in the first place.<br />
16( 338 </p>
<p>It was a faith that the-people of Australia would not<br />
approve of change for the sake of change but equally would<br />
not stand in the way of change where it is necessary and<br />
desirable. I share that faith.<br />
But the campaign that has been conducted over recent weeks<br />
by the Opposition Parties shows that they unfortunately<br />
ERY ~ but perh aps typically do not share that faith.<br />
Their ' no, case has treated the Australian people like<br />
children to be scared by horror stories.<br />
It has been a campaign reminiscent of that Patrick Cook<br />
cartoon on referendums, showing a big billboard, in<br />
Queensland of all places, on which was written ' Vote No or<br />
giant snakes will eat your children.'<br />
At the end of the campaign, looking back at the ' no' case,<br />
all we see is a fog of conspiracy theories and wild<br />
allegations. The only arguments we have heard from the Opposition have<br />
been either inconsistent -in that they contradict positions<br />
the Opposition has adopted in the past or hysterical in<br />
that they deliberately distort the real implications of<br />
? y these referendum proposals.<br />
Les Their arguments have boiled down to the oldest trick in the<br />
conservatives' book -the argument of pure reaction, that no<br />
ise change is better than any change, regardless of the merits<br />
of the proposed reforms and regardless of the credentials of<br />
those who propose them.<br />
It's difficult in politics to meet argument with argument,<br />
to debate the real issues too difficult for the<br />
Opposition, it seems. They have found it more convenient,<br />
less intellectually taxing, to fall back on the<br />
unsubstantiated allegation, the fearmongering claim, the<br />
easy assertio ' n that any simple proposal must conceal a<br />
hidden agenda . and that any suggestion for change must amount<br />
to a grab for power by the wild-eyed Canberra socialists.<br />
The nadir of the ' no' case is their ridiculous complaint<br />
about the layout and typeface of the booklet sent by the<br />
Australian Electoral Commission to every voter. They claim<br />
the small sized print of the ' no' case compared with the<br />
' yes' case reflects bias deliberately ignoring the fact<br />
that both the ' yes' and ' no' cases were submitted to the<br />
B Electoral Commissioner in camera-ready form by each side.<br />
In other words, theychose the typeface they now complain<br />
of. Most of the conspiracies and allegations made by the<br />
opposition are forgettable sideshows like that. 1639 </p>
<p>But one of them goes to a much deeper and more serious<br />
matter: their attempt to revive the State aid issue.<br />
The issue of State aid to church schools is one of the most<br />
divisive and bitter issues of recent Australian history.<br />
One of the proudest achievements of my Government is that we<br />
have buried that issue for all time.<br />
The last thing that anyone in my Government would wish is<br />
for this issue to blight our community again.<br />
It was for that reason we took the greatest care to ensure<br />
that the proposed new provision would not in any way affect<br />
the existing capacity for church schools to receive state<br />
aid. Our intention that state aid not be affected was made<br />
absolutely clear in the explanatory material for the<br />
Parliament. If it ever came to a High Court challenge and<br />
if-there were-any doubt about the intention of the<br />
referendum, that explanatory memorandum could be taken into<br />
account by the High Court.<br />
I cannot, and nor can any Minister or Member of Parliament,<br />
state categorically what a future High Court may or may not<br />
decide in any case. That would be impossible and improper.<br />
But we can look at the pro-State-aid trend of decisions by<br />
the Court over the years and we can look at the proposed<br />
wording of the referendum and we can look at the clear cut<br />
legal opinions the most recent of which was provided by<br />
Sir Maurice Byers, QC, a former Commonwealth<br />
Solicitor-General and we can conclude from all this that<br />
State aid will not be affected.<br />
And we can conclude further that the Opposition's<br />
suggestions to the contrary are nothing more than a shameful<br />
exercise in scare tactics.<br />
The purpose of the proposed freedom of religion amendment is<br />
to extend the right of'Australians to follow their own<br />
religious beliefs subject to the laws which govern us all.<br />
This question, the fourth on the ballot paper, does no more<br />
than ask voters to ensure the rights of:<br />
trial by jury for people facing serious criminal<br />
charges; fair compensation for property taken by any government;<br />
and freedom of religion.<br />
1i; 4 0 c rrI </p>
<p>The Constitution does not give a right to trial by jury for<br />
offences against State or Territory laws or for a number of<br />
serious Commonwealth offences; and it gives no right to<br />
fair compensation when property is taken by a State,<br />
Territory or local government, or by the Commonwealth in a<br />
Territory. There is only limited constitutional protection<br />
of the right to religious freedom against the Commonwealth<br />
and none against the States or Territories.<br />
This referendum will rectify each of these shortcomingsnothing<br />
more and nothing less.<br />
Let me briefly look at the other thr ee proposals.<br />
The first seeks a four year maximum term for both the Senate<br />
and the House of Representatives.<br />
It is a change which will dramatically reduce the number of<br />
elections. The benefits of such a change are clear.<br />
Since 1945, a federal election has been held on average once<br />
every two years.<br />
This is universally recognised as too costly, not only<br />
because of the $ 50 million that is now spent to hold each<br />
election, but also because of the increased economic<br />
instability and the restraint on good government imposed by<br />
the ever-present prospect of an election.<br />
Moreover, of the five elections since 1975, only 2 have been<br />
held more than 12 months early and both were held elarly<br />
specifically because half Senate elections fell due.<br />
Passage of the 4 year term proposal would immediately do<br />
away with half-Senate elections and the need for such early<br />
elections. Elected governments deserve a fair go and enough time to<br />
implement their policies.<br />
Business deserves a fair go so that it can plan ahead with<br />
confidence that Government policy will not change every two<br />
years. And, most of all, the Australian people should give<br />
themselves a fair go by giving the governments they elect<br />
the ability to get on with governing.<br />
Don't listen to the nonsense from the Opposition about the<br />
powers of the Senate. This referendum will in no way reduce<br />
the powers or independence of the Senate: it will remain<br />
the States' house, the house of review, the watchdog of the<br />
Parliamentary system. The Senate will still be able to<br />
force a Government to elections but it will be accountable<br />
to the people for its performance at the same time. 1641 </p>
<p>Make no mistake the Opposition sees merit in four year<br />
terms for the House. But to achieve the reform that we all<br />
agree is desirable, they imposed an unacceptable price<br />
eight year terms for Senators. How they reconcile eight<br />
year terms with the principle of democratic accountability<br />
of elected representatives has never been made clear<br />
because of course they are irreconcilable concepts.<br />
All the first referendum does is to offer to the Australian<br />
people better quality government and more stable government<br />
whatever the political persuasion of that government.<br />
Side-by side with the proposal for fewer elections is the<br />
second proposal, a referendum to provide for fair and<br />
democratic elections throughout Australia.<br />
And, like the first proposal, the end result will be better<br />
government because a fairly elected government better<br />
represents the will of the voters.<br />
This proposal seeks, quite simply, to ensure that every<br />
adult citizen's vote has the same value as any other<br />
person's vote and that every Australian has a constitutional<br />
guarantee of the right to vote.<br />
At this point in the late twentieth century, as we celebrate<br />
our Bicentenary, it ought to be taken for granted that a<br />
democracy should be based on equal representation of its<br />
citizens. Indeed, this is the case everywhere in Australia except in<br />
Queensland, Western Australia and the Tasmanian Legislative<br />
Council. The Opposition makes the claim that such matters should be<br />
up to the States themselves to rectify if they wish.<br />
I am a great believer in mankind's potential for<br />
self-improvement but I am not so naive as to imagine that<br />
chambers elected on, and entrenched by, undemocratic<br />
boundaries will so easily see the error of their ways.<br />
Indeed, Western Australians have encountered precisely that<br />
problem in their attempts to reform the outrageously unfair<br />
boundaries of the Legislative Council.<br />
The proposed amendment to ensure fair and democratic<br />
elections will bring that insult to Australian democracy to<br />
an end.<br />
It will ensure that the number of voters of each electorate<br />
is within 10 per cent of the average electorate enrolment.<br />
Redistributions will occur frequently enough to make sure<br />
that the basic unit of Parliament, the electorate, remains a<br />
fair basis for democratic government.<br />
1642 </p>
<p>The third proposal asks the Australian people to agree to<br />
constitutional recognition of local government as an<br />
integral part of the Australian system of government.<br />
If this question succeeds, it will insert a new section into<br />
the Constitution which will guarantee a system of elected<br />
local government in every State.<br />
This is a proposal which comes from local government itself,<br />
and has the support of Australians from across the political<br />
spectrum who believe, quite rightly, that the ability of<br />
local government to serve the people who elect it will be<br />
enhanced by constitutional recognition.<br />
There can be no more complete response to the Opposition<br />
critics of this proposal than to point to the fact that an<br />
overwhelming majority of local councils have expressed their<br />
support for it. The Australian Local Government Association<br />
could find no more than 23 local councils out of the 836 in<br />
Australia today where individual councillors have opposed<br />
this amendment.<br />
Even John Howard supported it. He recently wrote to the<br />
Attorney-General expressing his support for constitutional<br />
recognition of local government. And he has never bothered<br />
to explain the reasons for this somersault.<br />
Members of the Press Gallery, Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I can recall no set of referendum proposals ever put before<br />
the Australian people which are more deserving of the<br />
Australian people's support.<br />
I do not think there has ever been a more extensive<br />
opportunity for public involvement and awareness in the<br />
process of Constitutional reform than in the process leading<br />
up to these referendums.<br />
I refer not only to the 92 days between the time Parliament<br />
passed these proposals and referendum day<br />
this has been the longest period for public<br />
discussion between passage and polling for<br />
referendum proposals in at least the last 30 years.<br />
Nor do I refer only to the more than 43 hours of<br />
Parliamentary sitting time devoted to the consideration of<br />
these proposals which does not count the Matters of Public<br />
Importance debated on the Opposition's initiative in<br />
Parliament this week.<br />
I go further back to 1985 when the Constitutional<br />
Commission, a bipartisan community-based group, began its<br />
immense task of studying what could be done to achieve<br />
essential Constitutional reform. 16 43 </p>
<p>The work of this Commission, chaired by Sir Maurice Byers,<br />
has been absolutely first class in the number of public<br />
hearings it has held and the number of submissions it has<br />
received, in the quality of its committee work and above all<br />
in the quality of its reports.<br />
It is from the work of the Commission that the four<br />
proposals on which Australians will pass judgment on<br />
Saturday were drawn.<br />
Even people whom one would normally not expect to support my<br />
Government have stood up in favour of these proposals.<br />
The Queensland Liberal leader, Angus mines, and the former<br />
Liberal Premier of this State of Victoria, Sir Rupert Hamer,<br />
have argued strongly for the fair elections proposal.<br />
Local governments throughout Australia, whatever their<br />
political colour people such as Sally Anne Atkinson, the<br />
Lord mayor of Brisbane have been virtually unanimous in<br />
backing the need for local government to be recognised in<br />
the Constitution.<br />
In the face of such broad-based support for these proposals<br />
the increasing stridency with which the opposition has<br />
presented its claims is understandable only as the response<br />
of desperate people.<br />
I have had reason to recall in an earlier speech the words<br />
of Robert Menzies in 1944, during the Curtin years. In a<br />
speech in Canberra in that year he had this to say of the<br />
contribution the conservative Opposition had been making:<br />
on far too many questions we have found our role to<br />
be simply that of the man who says There is<br />
no room in Australia for a party of reaction. There is<br />
no useful place for a policy of negation."<br />
That was Robert Menzies in 1944. But there must be a large<br />
number of Liberals who agree with those sentiments today,<br />
and who are appalled to see their party's current position<br />
on these referendums.<br />
Because now the Liberals have turned the full circle; here<br />
they are again, more than four decades later, as the party<br />
of reaction, confronting new challenges with the oldest word<br />
in their dictionary: " no".<br />
It seems to me that the Opposition's arguments, and the<br />
vehement way they have been presented, have been as much to<br />
convince itself of a position it does not really believe in<br />
as it has been to convince the Australian people.<br />
They have failed to convince themselves. As recently as<br />
last weekend Liberal M4P Steele Hall announced that he would<br />
be voting in favour of the fair elections proposal and this<br />
week former Liberal Minister Ian Wilson has written to his<br />
electors urging a yes vote on the local government and the<br />
rights and freedom questions.<br />
ikA4 </p>
<p>And they will not convince the Australian people.<br />
In these last couple of, days, as Australians study the<br />
arguments for and against the proposals, I have no doubt<br />
that they will recognise that there is nothing hidden and<br />
nothing to fear from the passage of these referendums.<br />
I have no doubt, moreover, that they will reject the voices<br />
of reaction which seek to retain the unjust privileges and<br />
powers of politicians without responsibility, and which seek<br />
to shackle the Constitution to the past.<br />
On Saturday, I am confident that the Australian people,<br />
having judged these proposals on their merits, will express<br />
their approval of them. 0<br />
1645 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
