<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1766</transcript-id>
    <title>TELEVISION INTERVIEW GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER , SENATOR JOHN GORTON FOR B.B.C.&quot;PANORAMA&quot; PROGRAMME</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>22/01/1968</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001766.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TELEVISION ITflER VIEW GIVEN BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER, SENATOR JOHN GORTON<br />
FOR B. B. C. " PANORAMA" PROGRAMME 22ND JANUARY, 1968<br />
Interviewer Mr Michael Charliton<br />
Q. Hello, is that Prime Mlinister Gorton<br />
PM: Yes, Mr Charlton<br />
Q. Prime Minister, could I first of all congratulate you on<br />
your appointment.<br />
PM: Thank you very much.<br />
Q. And ask you what you feel is going to be the lasting effect<br />
of Britain's withdrawal from the Far East on the very special<br />
0 relationship that has always existed between Australia and<br />
B ritain?<br />
PM: I doubt if there will be lasting effects on the relationship<br />
between Australia and Great Britain. We are very disturbed at<br />
the power vacuum that will be created In that area by Britain's<br />
withdrawal. We do feel that a comparatively small number of<br />
troops on the ground there could contribate more to world<br />
security than they could In any other place In the world, say,<br />
for example, in Germany, but that's a decision for the British<br />
Government to make.<br />
Q. Surely this decision has done no more than hasten a<br />
trend which was already firmly established and generally<br />
0 accepted by Australians.<br />
FM: Well, it has done, I think more than that. It has<br />
certainly hastened a trend and hastened it in a way which we<br />
thought was not going to take place. But that's talking only of<br />
the withdrawal of the ground troops. I think, possibly, It has<br />
also gone this far that the provision of a quickly available<br />
land and quickly available naval and air support which was<br />
ear-marked for the area In case of need or which we thought<br />
was going to be ear-marked for the area In case of need, it's<br />
now doubtful whether that will be available.<br />
Q. The feeling is that It will make you lean very much closer<br />
to the United States?<br />
PM: Well, I think that our own security Is perhaps bound up<br />
now more with assistance from the United States but I'm not<br />
sure that this actual move will contribute much to that. You see, we<br />
don't see this withdrawal as necessarily putting Australia Itself<br />
in danger', why we deprecate It Is because we see the opportunity<br />
of small warE starting In this area, of Insurgency starting in<br />
this area which might not start or which could quickly be stopped<br />
if there were a relatively small number of troops there. ./ 2 </p>
<p>2<br />
Q. Could I suggest to you that many Australians would possibly<br />
regard this in the same way as they regarded the shock of the<br />
decision of Britain to join the Common Market some years ago.<br />
As a spur towards understanding that It had an independent<br />
nationhood to fulfil. Now, won't that accelerate this process,<br />
make Australia more aware of Its own position as a power In<br />
Asia and contributing itself to all this?<br />
PM : Well, it wil I certainly strengthen what I think Australia<br />
already believed and that is that it had to play an independent role<br />
and it had to develop itself as far and as quickly as It can, but we<br />
haven't got the capacity to be, ourselves, a power in Asia or<br />
anywhere else. We are twelve million people. VWhat Is the<br />
population of London?<br />
Q. About that.<br />
PM: Yes, well we're about the population of London. We can't<br />
at this stage, whatever the future may hold and the future may well<br />
show that at some stage we can, but at this stage we are not able<br />
to be a power in our own right.<br />
Q. What effect do you see it having on the future of tbe<br />
Commonwealth, the idea of an evolving Commonwealth, a multi<br />
racial Commonwealth with Britain at Its hub, at its centre?<br />
PM: I think that that is probably something that I would have to<br />
wait for time to tell.<br />
Q. What are you prepared to do to strengthen Commonwealth<br />
links yourself now?<br />
PMt Well, we are already of course contributing quite a lot to<br />
various Commonwealth activities. I haven't got any specific plans<br />
to do anything more than we're doing.<br />
Q. But do you fully support, for example, the British Government's<br />
policy towards Rhodesia?<br />
PM: I don't think you could expect me to comment on the British<br />
Government's policy I think that would be wrong for me to<br />
publicly comment on the British Government's policies.<br />
Q. But you, yourself, are less of a traditionalist, aren't you,<br />
than either of your predecessors, Sir Rob. art Menzies and Mr<br />
Holt you're not as emotionally Involved In the Commonwealth<br />
idea with Britain as Its head as they were?<br />
PM: I think that would be a pretty accurate assessment. I'm<br />
not as much a traditionalist.<br />
Q. Well, how do you Irtend to be different from them?<br />
PM: Well, I would like to think that I could be as efficient and<br />
as good as they were in many ways perhaps I could put It this<br />
way that the first and over-riding and paramount consideration<br />
In my mind on all things would be Australia's Interests and that<br />
-would come before anything else. / 3 </p>
<p>-3<br />
Q. choose Ib entowteiceen yAouu sstraaidli at hae nodH'fef Oitetdh aSt taytoeus, awnhde nB raitsakiend, tyoou<br />
said you would be Australian to the boot-heels. It's only a couple<br />
of years ago that Sir Robert Menzies was saying that Australians<br />
were British to the boot-heels. Mbw, can you explain the difference<br />
In those two statements?<br />
PM: Oh, perhaps we've changed our shoes.<br />
Q. Now, as far as the withdrawal goes, you've said that it<br />
needn't necessarily imply danger for Australl a but the Foreign<br />
Secretary has said here recently that Britain will maintain a<br />
capability to come to your aid. Now are you reassured by that?<br />
PM: Not really no. I'd like to know a lot more about It, what<br />
It consists of, what Its avaiJ, 4ility is, how It is going to get here<br />
and a whole lot of wusioshich at the moment I don't know the<br />
answer.<br />
Q. It sounds as if you feel that may be Impractical in view of the<br />
withdrawal from bases.<br />
PM: Oh no, It's just that I don't know the answers to a lot of<br />
questions<br />
Q. You, yourself, Sir, have departed from the tradition of<br />
sharing the burden with Britain of defence. I mean, when you were<br />
the Minister of the Navy, you were buying American ships in<br />
preference to British ships. Do you not feel that Australia may be<br />
paying some of the price of not helping to share the burdens of<br />
defence in the Far East to your North<br />
PM: Well, I don't think you're entirely accurate in what you<br />
say. I did, when I was Minister for the Navy yes, I bought some<br />
guided missile destroyers from the United States, that is trite.<br />
At the same time, I bought some Oberon submarines from the<br />
United Kingdom and re -equipped the fleet air arm with large<br />
helicopters from the United Kingdom. It seems that you were putting<br />
only part of the question.<br />
Q. Yes, more generally, though, Australia's defence Budget<br />
was running only at 3 per cent for a very long period after the<br />
Second World War.<br />
PM: Yes.<br />
Q. And, of course, Britain's was three times its size. A., ustralia<br />
has only just lifted its defence Budget to 5 per cent, I think, hasn't<br />
It Britain's is still greater. Now, do you agree that you could<br />
have eased the burden in the past from Britain?<br />
PM: I don't thin k so. I don't. Wha. t Is more, I think that there<br />
is a different situation In the United Kingdom and here. We have<br />
a continent to develop and a nation to build. New things have got<br />
to be done calling for more people, calling for more capital, for<br />
effort, and in the long run, the buildi ng up of a nation with greater<br />
numbers, greater industrial muscles, greater capacity would, I<br />
think, be a greater contribution than subordinating that at the present<br />
time to the purchase of military hardware. ./ 4 </p>
<p>" 4<br />
Q. Well, do you say, therefore, that Britain's ability to<br />
participate in this, In development, has been impaired by her<br />
decision to withdraw?<br />
PM: No, not at all. There may be we haven't seen it happen<br />
yet and I hope we won't there may be some Impediment in the<br />
flow of British capital out here to help In this development and to<br />
participate in this development, but if that happened, it wouldn't<br />
be as a result of anything we did. It could only be as a result of<br />
something that England did.<br />
Q. I was wondering whether you felt that psydidogical<br />
factors in Australia's disappointment that Britain has withdrawn<br />
might do some injury to the prospects of British imports to Australia?<br />
PM: I don't believe so, for one moment. I think this could get out<br />
of perspective a little. We understand Britain's problem. We had<br />
talks In which there was no rancour, no recrimination and I think<br />
that the nation has no rancour and no recrimination at all about this.<br />
But we do feel if overseas exchange were to be saved, then a greater<br />
contnbution could be made to general peace-keeping in that area.<br />
Singapore, Malaysia, than by keeping battalions In German y, but<br />
that Is Britain's decision.<br />
Q. But In view of what has happened, would Australia, faced<br />
for example with having to make a choice between American capital,<br />
Japanese capital and British capital, in a hypothetical situation Is<br />
it more likely to reject British capital now, in favour of the other<br />
two, bearing in mind the reality of what has happened?<br />
PM: We would not reject capital from Great Britain for one minute,<br />
nor indeed would we reject capital from the United States or Japan.<br />
We need capital there Is in this country argument and discussion<br />
as to whether it should be debenture capital, of how much Australian<br />
capital should be required to be invested In some particular<br />
development project. But that really has nothing to do with the<br />
subject you are opening up. Wle need capital, we would hope to<br />
continue to get it.<br />
Q. And lastly, Prime Ministe; r, can I ask you about whether<br />
devaluation in this country, which cost you, I think, something In<br />
the region of Z130 million plus the withdrawal East of Suez.. is<br />
likely to encourage you to diversify your holdings of Sterling here<br />
in London? Are you likely to try and spread this more evenly in<br />
other parts of the world?<br />
PM: I haven't considered this. It's not something on which I<br />
could make any comment at all because anything I said could have<br />
something read into it and really, nothing should be read into<br />
arything I say, so I'll say nothing.<br />
Q. Thank you very much indeed, Prime Minister. Good night.<br />
PM: Good night. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
