<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>345</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT,. HON. R.G MENZIES AT OFFICIAL OPENING OF CLENCE BLOCK, ST. JOSEPH&#039;S COLLEGE SYDNEY ON  16TH JULY 1961</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/07/1961</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000345_0.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
isCaI ay rim~ iHim1n miIIñ..% THE~ RT* HON. R* 0.<br />
140-. rmlA2 OFFICIAL OsAk. N2 OF 'ñ Cli, SLOK9<br />
ST. JQU3Hk' 1 COLA-; U4 SYNEY<br />
Y( our Eminence ' Rev* Sro. Provincial, 3ro. Othmar, dir Jot'vi ( McCauley)<br />
anid !.-dies anA p~ zitlement<br />
I thiunk iI&amp; Iat to beoin by tolling you that the tory that<br />
t~ le Wji. ro. krovincial, told about somebody fallin, ti'o ihh the<br />
floor and thus JustifY'ing a now laboratory woke an echo i'i my Mind<br />
beea-auo I onae had a Minister :~ or ,. he Army who ame along to me one<br />
afternoon and put up a most unpassonod plea for a ne-r e: areantal<br />
Hess at Duntroon. I was in a bad mood and I said " Hubjishi<br />
! ioasensoi They can pt a lonig with the old one. " his is not a time<br />
to3e ipendinj all this xonoyW Youz knw, the sort of thiinZ that<br />
Primue ' inisters have to dio occasionally. ' hat night the old<br />
.; jr. oants' Hess -* as burnt loidn. ( Laught.%: r) 1, sent for the Minister<br />
the next mornine, and complimented him on a turn of speed that I hadn't<br />
credited him jit-h. No4 I say no more than at; othe&amp;, riso It might<br />
be woomnonly defama tory.<br />
0 freeze ShNeo wo nI lyan timteer riIb lhya ves oerrvye r thstartu~ c yko u a hcaor ld Iotoi ay: A iitn caJyt dnehye ra aanndd<br />
I will help you, if I may, by being tolerably brie r.<br />
There are two things about this 3chool that 1 x i"--est we<br />
sho-aid all have in = Ind. One of them consists of the C'atjju st<br />
re+ 4erred to by 31r John, that ihon this school was established<br />
years aio It was built and ostablished for far nore boys than then<br />
appa-u-vd to be in sight for the sichool. I discovered i-ith ; reat<br />
intercst this afternoon that this Is, today, the biggest boarding<br />
schtool in the whole of husralia. N4ow this meanxs tliat 3) years alp<br />
t. ere weore poopi. e who had couraj. 9t vision,, and izma? intin, who d<br />
thians in a big way, who accepted the chance of failure -Ao cidnt<br />
under-provide for the service of a sahool, but at iLhat 11me overprovided<br />
ifor it, This is exactly the 3amI spirit as tVie spirit that<br />
has set up in some of he old ajuntries of Surope maificent<br />
cathedrals, wonderful structures 14roviding pluas of worship built at<br />
a time wihen a moe'e handful of people were res.. onsible -2* r :~ eThis,<br />
I . hIn,-c Is a atimulating thing.<br />
It would not ha4e luappened if it had not ijen Zor the<br />
profound belie f in the minds of the rounders of this sC. icol that . hey<br />
were dealin,; with matters of eternal importance. The we o not just<br />
providing a oartain amount. of instruction; they wore praviding<br />
something that would be built into he character off every bo4 who ient<br />
through the school. That was a ireat vision; and it was a vision<br />
fall of a remarkably clear perception of the great truths of education.<br />
I had occasion re -ently, to deliver a speech on broad<br />
subjet of education in Adelaide before a learned body -nd In the<br />
course of preparin for it i awo across one observa. tion thich I will<br />
take leave to quote to you and I do this with all themw. r acooptance,<br />
no 3. oabt, on your pa. t when I tell you these words : ell œ' rtn the lips<br />
of father 31eson who Aad attended a Confer ' noe vftoh initiated the<br />
movement that I was addrossia. Thuse are superb wordas " All<br />
kn~ ovledp Is jrist to the mill of the educator; but unless he concerns<br />
himself with his pupils' character he remains an infourmer, a source<br />
of fr--t) s piled upon one another and imparted to a mind bot1i= ature<br />
and untrained in their propdr use",<br />
This Is the ; reat choice In educaition -the Vi~ ing of<br />
infftmation the acquiring of a stock of facts,, the acquiri S, perhaps,<br />
of some pross tonial skill1 some technical knowledje, Tha on the<br />
one side,, by itself. And on the othei' side ' all that, and lioeiven too'. </p>
<p>2.<br />
All Mthat and the truiil Z In character Ahich, ofh u~ l sa~ xooLs 1 , reat<br />
Church foundations like this are best qualified to provida. This Is,<br />
I think, the jroat truth.<br />
dhen wie iere bein~, told by the kl'ovincial abo : t the" e<br />
dreadful, modern, yet historic episodes it kept oomind back irnto my<br />
minJ -all the time NVh do these things happen?" Not be--uso in those<br />
very eountries uen hadn't been to school, not because there Weret not<br />
people or trained Intelligence on the iron&amp; side but be:!! use they<br />
had rnot learned that civilization is in the heart and in Lhe soul,<br />
they had not learned the ethical iraluea which are involved in<br />
educatioun, That is why poopl trained In ethics bellorers in<br />
relIiin believers in the Aliglty, have been ruthlessly aticked by<br />
people Uwsaw in the. more reactionaries as if It coid be<br />
reactionary to omsidr, t~ o study, to ponder ete~ rnal things. 1 an<br />
as probably you knowl a tremendous believer In Church Schools. I donit<br />
criticise any other kind of schod It Is not ovorybody who cain jo to<br />
a school like this. I myself have had a variety or' expe1ri-noes in the<br />
course of being educationally A4ragpd up In some fashion a kltate<br />
school In a little country village# a Atate school in a bigj-er<br />
provincial town, and a great Church school In a 0, 4at city and the<br />
tlnIveralty, and so on . so that I have looked at this thing from the<br />
inside* The more I look at it, and the, older I become, e more<br />
conscious I an that the problemus of tho world today are prolems of<br />
character more than of anything else, and the so" e thankful I am that<br />
schools lik, this have been established and have flourishod anid are<br />
making such a great contribution to the world.<br />
There are very zmn people, clever people, I sappose, who<br />
thi-ti -hat we are living In the golden age of eiviliztion. ' Why?<br />
Jecause we can rzove through the air at speeds that nobody onoe thought<br />
of; beaaus* vs can stand In frout of a thousand or two thousand<br />
people bnd be heard comfortably ovor a public address sy ; tem; because<br />
we can look at the television, or go back home in a car; 4 cause ye<br />
can enjoy all thes thinp Ahich have all come, In ry owrn lifetime,<br />
And this we are told, is the jolden ade of civilization. Firing a<br />
man to Re. moon which no doubt will be the next piece of lunacy;<br />
putting people into orbit* All this is great stuff dcver stuff,<br />
no doubt very important stuff* iBut the odd thing, the thiing to<br />
remember is that In this century, easily the cleverest corutury In<br />
his tory In teohnoloar and In some aspects of science, wa have seen<br />
more hatred and bitterness more war, more injustice, more, brutality,<br />
than p. orhaps any oth-3r centZr in history was able to witness.* And<br />
why? Because we have failed, broadly, to understand that the two<br />
great tasks In lifo, the two ; reat tasks of civiliation, which, If<br />
performed are the, proof of civilization, is that men should got to<br />
understaa each other and value each other and be just to each other,<br />
and tliat they should be united In a brotherhood which is the<br />
inevitable result of the fatherhood of God. These ure, th e wat<br />
eleamts In civilization; and Air I wou'd like to oon swato you<br />
on We. nt, a director of a a~ ebool, which lives by these pri~ noiples, and<br />
has put them Into practice, and has so, I believe, made 3 re<br />
contribution to our country, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
