<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4611</transcript-id>
    <title>EUROPEAN RESTRAINTS ON STEEL IMPORTS, 19 JANUARY 1978</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>19/01/1978</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004611.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FORPRESS 19 JANUARY 1978<br />
EUROPEAN RESTRAINTS ON STEEL IMPORTS<br />
The Prime Minister said today that the European Community was<br />
again pursuing courses in its trade relations which were inimical<br />
to the free flow of world trade. Mr Fraser said that his<br />
Government's view of the Common Agricultural Policy was well known.<br />
I t would continue to argue for modifications of that policy.<br />
Further, it would continue to argue for modifications in the<br />
Community's policies of subsidising the export of surplus agficultural<br />
products, produced as a result of inflated domestic prices at the<br />
expense of other traditional markets such as Australia.<br />
During his visit last June, the Prime Minister said he had<br />
expressed concern that there were signs that more of these<br />
agriculture-type policies were starting to appear in other areas of<br />
EEC activity.<br />
Australian steel exports had been threatened last June and the EEC<br />
was now seeking to apply restraints on steel exports to the<br />
European Community on a very wide scale.*<br />
Exporters to Europe would virtually be forced to seek bilateral<br />
agreements with the Community based on minimum prices and maximum<br />
quantities or else face countervailing duties which would probably<br />
exclude them from exporting to Europe altogether.<br />
The Prime Minister said he found it dtfficult to understand the<br />
Community's unilateral measures, particularly as the Conmunity-s<br />
steel industry had consistently supplied around 90 percent<br />
of its own market.<br />
It also exported about twice as much as it imported.<br />
Published statistics clearly-showed that in the fixst njne zonth$. of<br />
1977, while imports of steel products into the Community rose by-<br />
2 percent compared with the same period in 1976, exports roeE by<br />
29 percent. In this situation, the Community could hardly<br />
claim that imports were causing major damage to its own industries.<br />
He said it looked as though the European Community was seeking<br />
to make the iron and steel industries in countries such as Australia<br />
which were themselves facing problems as acute as those of the EEC,<br />
carry an unfair share of the burden of the recession in the steel<br />
industry in Europe. / 2 </p>
<p>The across-the-board-measures introduced by the European Community<br />
appeared to have scant regard for the fact that the recession in the<br />
steel industry extended beyond the bounds of Europe. It was<br />
a world-wide recession.<br />
The Prime Minister said that the measures, if applied to Australia,<br />
could have a very adverse effect on our exports to the EEC and<br />
consequently on production and employment levels in Australia's iron<br />
and steel industry.<br />
Total Australian exports of finished and semi-finished steel<br />
products subject to the EEC measures of around $ A45-50 inillion<br />
per annum could be placed as risk.<br />
The Prime Minister noted that imports of steel from Australia<br />
consitituted only a small proportion of Community-consumption of<br />
steel, somewhat less than one-half of one percent, and a high<br />
proportion of this was feedstock or~ semi-finished steel for the<br />
Community. Very little was in finished forms which accounted for over<br />
percent of total steel imports into the EEC in 19.76-77.<br />
Australia exported less than $ A 1 million of finished steel products<br />
to the EEC in 1976-77, while Australia imported just over<br />
$ A12 million of-these products from the Community, a net advantage<br />
to the Community steel industry of around $ A 11 million.<br />
The Prime Minister said that his own discussions in Europe had been<br />
followed with very useful discussions betweenMr Howard, the<br />
Commission and the members of the Community.<br />
The next round of consultations would be undertaken by M~ r Garl~ and<br />
the Minister for Special Trade Representations. Mr Garland s-tood<br />
ready to visit the Commission at any time, but present advice was that<br />
the Commission would not wish to resume discussions until after a<br />
number of developments in the first quarter of 1978, including-the<br />
French elections.<br />
The Prime Minister said that in a lette r to' the President of the<br />
Commission, Mr Jenkins, he said that it would be quite unreasonAble<br />
for the Commission to seek to apply its current measures to Australia<br />
pending those joint trade discussions. If there was a. need)<br />
Mr Garland could visit Brussels at a moment's notice.'<br />
The Prime Minister went on to say that the essential aim of the<br />
continuing discussions between Australia and. the* Commission was to<br />
find ways in which the trading relationship between Australia And the<br />
European Community could be placed on a. more equitable and -mutually<br />
beneficial basis.<br />
He said that it would be iflost undesirable if restraints were placed<br />
on Australia's exports of steel in the midst of continuing<br />
discussions as this could jeopardise the common objective of<br />
improving trade relationships between Australia and the EEC. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
