<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2150</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M. NO. 89/1969 - SHOP STEWARDS&#039; INCITEMENT TO MUTINY - STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. JOHN GORTON</title>
    <prime-minister>Gorton, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19680110 - 19710310</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/12/1969</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002150.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 89/ 1969<br />
SHOP STEWARDS' INCITEMENT TO MUTINY<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, Mr. John Gorton<br />
However much some Australians may be opposed to the<br />
conflict in Vietnam, I believe that every responsible and thoughtful citizen<br />
will condemn with repugnance, as does the Government, the attitude of<br />
the meeting of Union Shop Stewards in Melbourne yesterday.<br />
To the average reader, this attitude is a stark incitement<br />
to mutiny in the Armed Forces and defiance of the law in Australia.<br />
It is not perhaps so surprising that Shop Stewards drawn<br />
from some of the Unions involved should have adopted this irresponsible<br />
and lawless attitude. But it is disturbing in the extreme that Mr. Crawford, the<br />
President of the A. L. P. in Victoria, should have been associated with this<br />
course. Dissent from and criticism of the Government's policy in Vietnam<br />
is one matter incitement to mutiny is quite another.<br />
Those urging this seek to defy the law, and endanger the lives<br />
of Australian servicemen in order to achieve illegally what they have not<br />
been able to achieve democratically.<br />
Such action is typical of the extreme left and it is noteworthy<br />
that the move comes from Victoria where the most extreme elements of<br />
the A. L. P. are found. It is tantamount to a call to Australian troops to<br />
surrender to Communist forces on the proposal of unions a number of<br />
whom are Communist led.<br />
The Shop Stewards' meeting in Melbourne, and the Victorian<br />
Leader of the A. L. P. have urged a dangerous, undemocratic and disloyal<br />
course. If the A. L. P. does, in fact, want a Communist victory in South<br />
Vietnam, it should say so and the dividing line between the Government and<br />
the Opposition would again be starkly drawn. If it does not, then the Leader<br />
of the Opposition in Australia should at once condemn and disassociate<br />
himself from the resolution passed in Melbourne.<br />
For its part the Government does condemn it, and is ready<br />
to take any steps necessary to see that the course advocated does not<br />
succeed.<br />
CANBERRA 16 December 1969 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
