<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6508</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH AT DARWIN AIRPORT, 16 OCTOBER 1984</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/10/1984</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006508.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
* jj, 4USTRALIA<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
SPEECH AT DARWIN AIRPORT 16 October 1984<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF ONLY<br />
RM: I am this Darwin Airport development<br />
project. The commencement of these works will cost more than<br />
million being held as a new chapter in the development of the<br />
Territory and it emphasises the importance my Goverment attaches<br />
to the contribution of the aviation industry contributes to that<br />
development. The size and the location of the Territory coupled<br />
with its limited service transport infrastructure is meant that<br />
you all realise that aviation is often being the lifeline of the<br />
Territory I guess ( inaudible) more obvious than in the tragic<br />
aftermath of the cyclone Tracey in December 1974. increases in<br />
population, the economic activity in recent years in the Northern<br />
Territory due in part to the increasing populatory of the<br />
Territory as a tourist destination have resulted in a rapid growt~ h<br />
in air transport in your areas. And this has particularly<br />
impacted on Darwin itself which is of course! not only the major<br />
population but also the major supply centre. Now while the<br />
existing terminal complex which has survived as we know both war<br />
and cyclone has served the city of Darwin well it has without<br />
question now almost outlived its usefulness. Increasing<br />
conjestion, the standard of the buildings ( inaudible) facilities<br />
have been as we all know the subject of criticism in recent years.<br />
In the light that the vital role of aviation in the Territory and<br />
also Darwin importance as a international gateway the Government<br />
approved this major redevelopment last year. The project which<br />
involves the construction of a new airline terminal'and general<br />
avaiation facilities on the northern side of the airport will<br />
ensure that the Territory finally receives an airport<br />
of international standard as it deserves. Notwithstanding the<br />
pressures and I think you would all be aware of them which have<br />
been imposed upon the Government by competing high priority<br />
programs all over Australia an amount of $ 7.5 million has been<br />
allocated in this current Budget for 1984-85 to allow<br />
construction proceed. Construction which is expected which<br />
( inaudible) to generate 450 on site jobs at its peak in 1986<br />
commenced in June and as you can see the preliminary site works<br />
are now well advanced. The major design work will be finalised<br />
during this financial year 84-85 and contracts will be arranged<br />
for major elements of the project with a view to this facility<br />
being ready for operation late in our Bicentennial year 1988. Now<br />
while the current project is primarily designed to meet the needs<br />
of scheduled operators and their customers it will also be of<br />
importance to general aviation. As you know general aviation has<br />
played and will obviously continue to play a vital role in meeting<br />
the transport and communication of the top end. The new apron and<br />
service sites to be provided on the north side will assist in<br />
enabling this site to discharge that role. In addition a detailed<br />
evaluation of proposed terminal facilities for commuter operatcrs<br />
is also in hand. Upon completion of this work Darwin will have-an<br />
airport of world standard capable of serving the city's needs at<br />
long way into the future. Passengers will be able to enjoy a<br />
modern airconditioned terminal building equipped with aerobridges </p>
<p>2<br />
to enable embarcation and disembarcation in total comfort. The<br />
architects are I believe to be congratulated for a stricking<br />
design which appears to have blended both a feeling of flight and<br />
the delightful lifestyle and environment of t he Territory. I<br />
believe also that a tribute should be paid to the various<br />
Government officers who have been involved in the planning to this<br />
point. These include representatives not onJly of my own<br />
Government Departments of Aviation, Defence and Housing and<br />
Construction but also officials from the Territory Government and<br />
from the Darwin City Council. The Darwin Airport provisional<br />
master plan released in 1983 which canvasses the progressive<br />
development of the airport to serve the Territory's needs well<br />
into the next century is an example of the cooperation and the<br />
necessary cooperation between the three levels of Government:<br />
Federal; Territory and Local. Without such cooperation of course<br />
the needs of the people of the Territory and whatever area of<br />
activity we are talking about will never properly be served.<br />
Darwin has indeed an extremely proud place in the history of<br />
Australian aviation. It has witnessed the arrival and the<br />
departure of many great aviation personalities and it has hosted<br />
many aeronautical milestones. Ladies and Gentlemen the completion<br />
of this project in 1988 will constitute another such milestone in<br />
a very fittihng way and to mark the Bicentennial of Australia. I<br />
certainly in conclusion have very much pride and pleasure in being<br />
associated with you here today in this historic development.<br />
Thank you very much indeed. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
