<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1536</transcript-id>
    <title>ASIAN TOUR 1967 - CAMBODIA - DINNER IN HONOUR OF PRINCE SIHANOUK, GIVEN BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR HAROLD HOLT, AT PHNOM PENH - 31ST MARCH 1967</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/1967</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001536.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
ASIAN TOUR 1967 CAMBODIA<br />
DINNER IN HONOUR OF PRINCE SIHANOUK GIVEN BY THE<br />
PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT, AT PHNOM PENH 31ST miC i_ 1967<br />
FOLLOWING AR. THE MAIN POINTS FROM A SPEECH<br />
MADE BY THE PRIIME MINISTER, 151. HAROLD HOLT:<br />
We near the end of our visit to Cambodia. It is a<br />
visit from which w-have learned much, a visit we have greatly<br />
enjoyed. We are all better inlormed about Cambodia, its<br />
country and its poople&gt; its aspiration and its problems. I<br />
hope we are all wiser also in our understanding of its policies.<br />
A visit of only three days but thoughtfully planned<br />
from Head oL State and his administration to good team work with<br />
our own distinguished Ambassador and his staff which has enabled<br />
us to absorb a widely rcpr, sentative s-ries of features of your<br />
national life. Some conclusions stand out in the mind. I had an<br />
awareness previously that substantial national progrcss was being<br />
made under the leadership of Head of State. What I had not fully<br />
appreciated was the centuries old Khmer culture and tradition so<br />
graphically demonstrated at Angkor and reflected with remarkable<br />
fidelity back to early centuries in the classical royal ballet.<br />
This deep sense of national pride, fierce spirit of<br />
independence associated with the tradition of early civilizations<br />
have clearly influenced your national policy of neutrality and<br />
non alignment. It has also been reflected in features of your<br />
life which have a special Cambodian flavour, your capacity to<br />
marry happily the practical with the aesthetic the ability to<br />
maintain a zestful way of life whilst applying your energy to<br />
the development of a modern economically advo ncing state.<br />
This has been a highly educational visit because<br />
education builds knowledge, builds understanding and understanding<br />
builds friendship. Our relations were warm and friendly before<br />
my visit but I feel that they will be even w-armer and deeper<br />
as a consequence of it.<br />
Your ministers and officials have made it possible<br />
for me to see some of the striking and imaginatively conceived<br />
architectural features of your capital city, to s-e something of<br />
your proud cultural heritage both past and present.<br />
Mrs. Holt and I gr-atly appreciated our audience with<br />
Her Majesty the Queen Mother and I found our own long talk together<br />
both informative and most valuable as well for the understanding<br />
of the Cambodian situation as for a bettor understanding of the<br />
problems of this region.<br />
We have noted the encouragement given to such cultural<br />
activities as your Royal Ballet, your choral and instrumental<br />
music by the Queen Mother and your Head of State. We have seen<br />
convincing evidence of Cambodiat purposeful efforts to achieve<br />
under your leadership the full stature of a modern state.<br />
Industrial developments here ii Phnom Penh, harbour development<br />
at Sihanoukville and the many examples graphically presented at<br />
the State Exhibition wher; His Excellency Mr. Son Sann conducted<br />
us. This was also seen and enjoyed by a great many of my fellow<br />
countrymen. / 2 </p>
<p>I 2-<br />
There is a firm basis to our friendship. It is<br />
founded on mutual respect, a recognition of national identity<br />
and integrity, a mutually helpful and trustful relationship.<br />
We like you wish to be left undisturbed to develop our nation.<br />
We ar-both small nations in terms of population. Aus: tralia<br />
has a vast territory and is rich in resources but tLcse are<br />
not easily gained. We have to contend to an extent unknown to<br />
you with drought, flood and bushfire. We have l. gc t-' acts<br />
of arid desert. We are neither a belligeront nor stic<br />
people but we have contributed where we have thought called<br />
for to goals of security and economic advancement for others.<br />
Since becoming Head of Australian Government it has<br />
been my purpose to become familiar with Australian neighbours<br />
countries in Asia, to meet and talk with their leaders and to<br />
learn at first hand something of their way of life, th,: ir<br />
peoples accomplishments, ideas and problems. This process<br />
has been richly rewarded in Cambodia, I hope the value I have<br />
found in such a visit will encourage your Head of State to<br />
make a visit when he can to Australia. He has the warm<br />
invitation of my Government to do so. We both believe our<br />
countries have a contribution to make to a peaceful and more<br />
prosperous world. May our friendship contribute usefully<br />
to this. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
