<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>6657</transcript-id>
    <title>JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR ARTS, HERITAGE AND ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/06/1985</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00006657.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
. M7,<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA 25 JUNE 1985<br />
JOINT STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER AND THE MINISTER FOR<br />
ARTS, HERITAGE AND ENVIRONMENT<br />
The Prime Minister, Mr Hawke and the Minister for Arts, Heritage<br />
and Environment, Mr Barry Cohen, today announced Commonwealth<br />
Government plans for the development of the National Maritime<br />
Museum in Sydney at Darling Harbour.<br />
The Commonwealth has accepted the offer of the New South Wales<br />
Government of a 4.75 hectare site for the Museum in the Darling<br />
Harbour Redevelopment Area.<br />
" The Government is committed to fostering the development<br />
of the national collections and the establishment of the National<br />
Maritime Museum will be an important link in the preservation<br />
and display of our maritime heritage"," Mr Hawke said.<br />
" It is expected that the first stage of the Museum will be<br />
constructed by 1988 at a cost of the order of $ 25m. The<br />
Museum will be a major project for the Bicentennial Year and<br />
one for which there have already been expressions of interest<br />
in sponsorship from governments overseas", the Prime minister<br />
said. In joining with the Prime Minister, Mr Cohen announced that<br />
the Council of the Museum of Australia had agreed to appoint<br />
an Advisory Committee to prepare for Government a detailed<br />
plan for construction, including costs and administrative<br />
matters within six months.<br />
" The National Maritime Museum will not be a dry repository<br />
of relics but a living institution, of interest both to<br />
Australians and overseas visitors, which would provide a<br />
major educational and research facility for Australia",<br />
Mr Cohen said. I </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
