<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>7327</transcript-id>
    <title>SPEECH BY THE PRIME MINISTER CEDA LUNCEEON - MELBOURNE - 27 MAY 1988</title>
    <prime-minister>Hawke, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19830311 - 19911220</period-of-service>
    <release-date>27/05/1988</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00007327.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
CHECK AGAINST DELIVERY EMBARGOED UNTIL DELIVERY<br />
SPEECH BY THE PRINE NINISTER<br />
CEDA LUNCHEOV NELBOURNE 27 flAY 1988<br />
Eleven months ago the Australian people were faced, in the<br />
Federal Election campaign, with a fundamental choice about<br />
the future direction of our country.<br />
The choice was nothing less than a decision about whether<br />
the cQuntry'could continue forwards or whether it would<br />
disastrously slip backwards.<br />
This is not the time or the place to rehearse the many<br />
policy differences which separated the Government and the<br />
Opposition in that campaign.<br />
But it is the time to recall the commitment the Government<br />
made during that campaign to continue its program of<br />
economic reform.<br />
We entered that campaign with a credible, comprehensive and<br />
thoroughly detailed set of proposals for reform of the<br />
Australian micro economy, and a commitment to continue to<br />
manage the macro economy to produce sustainable growth.<br />
I believe it was in very large part because Australians<br />
accepted the need " or these policy directions that we were<br />
given a mandate for our third term in Office.<br />
Today I take greai pleasure, and I admit a sense of<br />
considerable achigyement, in stating that we have again<br />
proven our capaciCy to deliver on those promises.<br />
Wednesday night's May Economic Statement was no traditional<br />
mini-Budget.<br />
It was an announcement of the most wide ranging set of<br />
fundamental economic reforms ever presented in one statement<br />
in Australia.<br />
Australian Governments in the past have been too complacent<br />
about providing dqtailed policy direction in all the many<br />
areas of their responsibility. 00 37 81.<br />
1: 1. 1r </p>
<p>9<br />
This complacency has been matched by, and has fostered, the<br />
general sense of economic lethargy which characterised our<br />
highly protected, inward looking, commodity based industrial<br />
performance. And the Australian people, including most of the<br />
authoritative media and interest group commentators, have<br />
adopted too narrow a definition of the Government's role in<br />
protecting living standards and assisting the needy.<br />
They have all laboured under the gross misapprehension that<br />
all governments could and should do to help those in need<br />
was to redistribute tax revenue to them.<br />
With thi's May Statement, the Government has -rolled up its<br />
sleeves and once again gone into the hard work of detailed<br />
policy managenent.<br />
; As we promised in the election campaign, we have continued<br />
the historic process of economic reform and enlarged it by<br />
breaking newy ground in micro economic reform.<br />
In the process we have also achieved reforms which will lead<br />
to real improvements in the standard of living for all<br />
Australians not only by means of redistributing income but<br />
also, and fundamentally, by improving the way in which<br />
Australia generates its prosperity.<br />
And I see the~ Treasurer's Statement not just as providing<br />
fundamental direction in the economic area but as yet<br />
another building block in our strategy to enhance social<br />
justice in Australia.<br />
In other words the May Statement, like all the great Labor<br />
reforms that precede it, is directed not just at creating a<br />
wealthier Australia but also a fairer one.<br />
There are four key themes permeating the Treasurer's<br />
Statement and the supplementary material provided by our<br />
ministerial colleagues John Button, Gareth Evans, John<br />
Dawkins and John Kerin.<br />
First, and fuzidamentally, we have produced the fiscal<br />
framework which the economy needs, including further firm<br />
restraint in-butlays and we have achieved it in a way<br />
which is uncompromisingly fair.<br />
Second, we have instituted a number of reforms to change the<br />
way business will make investment decisions in Australia.<br />
These reforms focus business decision making on the real<br />
issue: the underlying economics of a project and the real<br />
return to Australia. Previously these decisions were liable<br />
to be distorted by the uneven but often massive levels of<br />
subsidies provided either by other taxpayers or by<br />
consumers. 0067? 82 </p>
<p>3.<br />
Simil'arly our reforms target the major public sector<br />
business enterprises, reinvigorating them by encouragin I<br />
greater competitiveness, innovation, productivity and<br />
enterpreneurship. Third, the H'ay Statement continuies our longer term emphasis<br />
on productivity growth. In particular, by upgrading the<br />
education and training systems we are upgrading the<br />
workforce of the future truly a fundamental goal.<br />
Fourth, we have implemented a new deal for consumers.<br />
Reduced tariffz, the gradual removal of artificial price 41<br />
supports for somec key rural products, as well as the<br />
improved managemient of Telecom and other Government business<br />
enterprises will all yield, over time, significant benefitG<br />
to consumers in the form of lower prices and better service.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen 4<br />
Let me turn in detail to each of these themes.<br />
By any standards the fiscal parameters of the May Statement<br />
are impressive.<br />
Real outlays will fall again in 1988-89 by 1.5 per centand<br />
this is truB no matter how asset sales are treated for<br />
the purposes of the calculation.<br />
This will be the third year in a row in which real outlays<br />
have fallen,<br />
No other comparable country has achieved so sustained a<br />
period of fiscal restraint. U<br />
But that is not the ehid of the matter.<br />
On current estimates, because of tize quality of the cuts Vf<br />
implemented both in this Statement and previously, there<br />
will be a further real decline in outlays in 1989-90 in<br />
other words there will be real declines four years in a row.<br />
in GDP falling to 25.5 per cent in 1988-89 and to<br />
24.5 per cent 04i next year.<br />
in each case this is lower than for any year since 1973-74.<br />
in 1979-80. K<br />
our sustained effort to curb outlays, and the measures in<br />
place to protect ' Lhe revenue base, mean the expected budget<br />
surplus in 1988-89 is in excess ok $ 3 billion.<br />
This is only the second surplus in 35 years -the first of<br />
course being the surplus expected this financial year. 006783 </p>
<p>w ' w<br />
These successive and substantial surpluses allow the<br />
Commonwealth to repay debt, both domestically and overseas;<br />
to free up the saving pool gor productive investment; and to<br />
exercise appropriate restraint on demand all essential<br />
components of our overall policy task.<br />
They provide the measure of this Government's commitment to<br />
providing the fiscal environment which Australia needs to.<br />
overcome its balance of payments difficulties.<br />
These achievements put the lie to those commentators who<br />
seek either tChe pointless accumulation of yet larger<br />
surpluses or the distribution of the existing surplus in<br />
premature per~ sonal tax cuts.<br />
The former group of critics, largely in the business sector,<br />
have failed to make the case that the costs of attempting a<br />
faster pace of adjustment in terms of economic and social<br />
dislocation should be endured or, indeed, whether those<br />
costs would ultimately be rewarded.<br />
The latter group, and I am referring in particular to our<br />
political opponents, have failed to provide an answer to the<br />
evergreen but crucial questions: where would the money come<br />
from to pay for these hypothetical tax cuts? What<br />
Government services would have to be cut?<br />
The Government's commitment to properly funded personal tax<br />
cuts next year is the only rational course in present<br />
circumstances.<br />
We accept that middle Australia wants and deserves a gradual<br />
increase in living standards.<br />
our approach will allow that legitimate aspiration to become<br />
a reality.<br />
It will do so at a speed consistent with stabilising our<br />
international indebtedness.<br />
And it will do so in a way which will ensure that the tax<br />
cuts are real and durable, not quickly eroded by renewed<br />
inflation and currency decline.<br />
Those tax cts will be delivered in 1989-90, the same year<br />
as companies will experience the benefit of the tax changes<br />
announced this week.<br />
I've pointed out already in a number of forums that real.<br />
progress in raising living standards as our balance of<br />
payments improves will reflect three variables: wages,<br />
prices and taxation.<br />
Progress in each of these areas is mutually dependent. That<br />
is why we cannot responsibly entertain the prospect of<br />
significant' personal tax cuts without appropriate moderation<br />
in wages growth. 006784 </p>
<p>Further real wage cute are not necessary in 1988-89. But a<br />
successful economic policy requires that the realistic<br />
expectation of falling inflation be validated by<br />
sufficiently restrained wages growth.<br />
These considerations will inforo our approach to the<br />
forthcoming National Wage Case.<br />
The second thrust of the Statement to to change the naturo<br />
of the business investment decisoon.<br />
For yearo thG investment dollar of this country has been<br />
wasted. Too often, investors have been motivated not by the economic<br />
return to Australia, but by the subsidies offered by<br />
Australian taxpayers and conoumer<br />
The result too often has been that Australian industries are<br />
unable to compete on the world market because their domestic<br />
cost structuro is too high.<br />
That is the driving force behind the Government's reform of<br />
the business tan system.<br />
It is the driving force behind our reform of industry<br />
assistance fos both manufacturing and the rural sector.<br />
And it is the driving force behind our complete overhaul of<br />
the operational environment of our largest Government<br />
business enterpriQes, oepecially Telecoo.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
The mainstay of Australia's export effort will remain its<br />
primary producing and resource based industries for decades<br />
to come. That is what we are good at.<br />
But, increasingly, we need to broaden our export base.<br />
Xt is pleasing. to see that we aro already having<br />
considerable success.<br />
In 1987 exporte of manufactured goods increased by 30 per<br />
cent. Indeed this growth has been so strong that the share<br />
of merchandise exports accounted for by manufactures is now<br />
24 per cent, compared to only 20 per cent in 1982.<br />
And tourism is rapidly growing as a major export earner in<br />
fact at three times the rate of other exports.<br />
The reality is, however, that we still have some way to go.<br />
In a fundamental way our reforms add to the geographical<br />
advantage Australia has by virtue of its proximity to and<br />
participation in the burgeoning growth of trade in<br />
manufactures and services in the Pacific Basin. UUO 6 </p>
<p>But we will not take maximuma advantage of those<br />
opportunities if we cannot match the quality, productivity<br />
and capacity to innovate which characterise our competitors.<br />
There is no incentive for business to strive to do that if<br />
they rest safe and sheltered l ehind a tariff wall, hiding<br />
from the winds of international competition.<br />
Nor will our best export industries fulfil their potential<br />
if their cost structures are inflated because of protection<br />
either directly through inflated prices for capital goods<br />
and materials or indirectly through unit labour cost<br />
structures excessively out of line with our competitors.<br />
And the losers would be Australians and Australian living<br />
standards. That is why, against the background of the substantial<br />
depreciation of our currency and the strength of our<br />
employment performance, we have moved to reduce protection.<br />
on average, effective assistance to manufacturing will be<br />
reduced by about 20 per cent over the next four years.<br />
At the end of this period, with only limited exceptions,<br />
nominal rates of assistance will not exceed 15 per cent.<br />
Investment decisions across industries will thus be<br />
determined less by relative protection than by underlying<br />
returns.<br />
There will be some industrial dislocation as a consequence<br />
of these reforms.<br />
However our best estimates suggest that employment losses<br />
are likely to cons-titute a quite small proportion of annual<br />
labour turnover in manufacturing, let alone of the annual<br />
growth of total employment in recent years.<br />
Moreover, over time, those losses should be more than offset<br />
by increased employment induced by greater cost<br />
competitiveness elsewhere in the economy.<br />
Through the new office of Labour Market Adjustment, and<br />
appropriate t-ripartite bodies, the Government will monitor<br />
developments to ensure that excessive adjustment costs are<br />
not required of regions or groups. If necessary, additional<br />
adjustment assistance will be provided to minimise excessive<br />
burdens. Predictions of net employment increases are often greeted<br />
sceptically by those who face the direct impact of<br />
structural adjustment.<br />
But some illustrations of the magnitude of the costs of<br />
protection help to make the point that reduced industry<br />
assistance will lead to increased efficiency and employment. 006 786 </p>
<p>7.<br />
It has been estimated that industry assistance to all<br />
sectors of the Australian economy imposes a penalty of<br />
per cent of value added in wool scouring, 18 per cent in<br />
cotton ginning and 48 per cent in nickel smelting.<br />
Clearly, removing such massive arawbacks will radically<br />
improve our ability to move beyond the commodities trade to<br />
higher stages of processing.<br />
In four years the tariff reform process which we have<br />
initiated will reduce Commonwealth revenue by around $ 1<br />
billion per year a broad indicator of how much consumers<br />
stand to gain from tariff reform.<br />
Tbarroiafdfl y reeqduuicvtiaolnesn t forre dumcatniuofnasc tuirn inags siasrtea ntcoe bet o mathtec herdu rably<br />
sector.<br />
Artificial price support arrangements in the manufactured<br />
milk, sugar, wheat, tobacco and dried fruits industries are<br />
to be wound back.<br />
These pricing arrangements, together with related production<br />
and marketing controls, result in higher input costs<br />
especially for the food processing industry. This inhibits<br />
a promising class of exports and penalises domestic<br />
consumers.<br />
our reforms take substantial steps to lift those burdens.<br />
This, again, leads to substantial benefits to consumers of<br />
up to $ 100m per year within a few years.<br />
in this day and age, efficient telecommunications and<br />
transport industries are vital to Australia's trading<br />
performance. The public sector is heavily involved in both industries in<br />
Ausetr ali a.<br />
Now there are to be major changes in the nature of the<br />
Government's involvement.<br />
Telecom's monopoly of the basic network is to be preserved,<br />
both to capturez natural economies of scale and to generate<br />
the revenue necessary to pay for its community service<br />
obligations. But, beyond the basic network, Telecom will be<br />
subjected to greater competition wherever practicable.<br />
M'ost other Government business enterprises are to be freed<br />
of the excessive restrictions which currently hog tie them<br />
to the bureaucracy.<br />
These changes are designed to improve the adaptability and<br />
responsiveness of these fast moving industries.<br />
Moreover new regulatory mechanisms will ensure that prices<br />
for standard telecommunications services fall in real terms. 0063787 </p>
<p>Coup led with the substantial gains available to consumers as<br />
tariffs decline and as administered agricultural prices are<br />
reduced, this -package represents a major boost for<br />
consumers.<br />
Make no mistake, consumers s~ and to be major beneficiaries<br />
of this package through lower real prices and more effective<br />
competition. Indeed our estimates show that consumers will begin to<br />
benefit immediately.<br />
The net effect of all of the Hlay Statement measures which<br />
have a price affect will be to reduce, slightly, the CFI in<br />
1988-89.<br />
This is but one of the factors which confirms us in our view<br />
that inflation is trending downward.<br />
The Government is determined to ensure that consumers<br />
benefit to the maximum practical extent from the pressure<br />
which has been unleashed to reduce inflation.<br />
We will be asking the Prices Surveillance Authority to<br />
monitor developments closely.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
As I have said at the outset, the May Statement's package of<br />
reforms, taken together, amounts to a fundamental set of<br />
measures dezigned to improve business efficiency.<br />
I welcome the expressions of broad support which have come<br />
since Wednesday night from leading business spokesmen.<br />
It is recognised-that the 39 per cent corporate tax rate is<br />
a major innovation for business.<br />
So, too, is the exemption from the foreign tax credits<br />
system of the vast bulk of genuinely internationalised<br />
Australian companies undertaking genuine direct investments<br />
overseas. We know that the previous arrangements had been<br />
an irritant-.. to many companies legitimately operating abroad,<br />
without significant revenue benefits.<br />
of course business has had to accept that tax cuts of this.-<br />
magnitude could only responsibly be funded by removing a<br />
range of concessions such as 5/ 3 depreciation<br />
concessions which in any case had been distorting investment<br />
decisions in various ways.<br />
At the same time we are determined to ensure as far as<br />
possible that companies pay their fair share of tax. We<br />
have enhanced the audit capacities of the Tax Office,. and<br />
have nominated some 60 low-tax countries where we intend<br />
that Austr-alian direct investment effectively will attract<br />
Australian rates of tax on an accruals basis. 006788 </p>
<p>9.<br />
However while we have levelled the tax playing field, we<br />
have not forgotten the need for a sustained effort to<br />
enhance productivity.<br />
Ralph Willis and I have consistenitly sought to remind<br />
workers and managers of the need to examine workplace<br />
practices, miost recently in the context of tier two.<br />
We will continue to do so.<br />
But we are also approaching the problem at its most basic<br />
level. Labor is determined that we develop the workforce which has<br />
the skill and the flexibility to take advantage of the<br />
opportunities which undoubtedly lay before us as a<br />
community.<br />
Many parents, and many business people, are concerned at the<br />
poor quality of our schools systems.<br />
Curriculums are a State responsibility. But we are<br />
determined to seek to bring a national and rational<br />
perspective to bear.<br />
Our training systems are in need of overhaul, especially<br />
retraining arrangements.<br />
Public sector support for training in Australia is in line<br />
with comparable countries.<br />
However, while many employers recognise the value of such<br />
expenditure and maintain a substantial training effort,<br />
overall our private sector's financial support is below the<br />
average by internatignal comparisons.<br />
This situation needs to be addressed.<br />
we believe that the major burden of funding enhanced<br />
training systems rests with the beneficiaries.<br />
And the Commonvipalth's preference is that the proper<br />
apportionment of the costs be settled between the industrial<br />
parties. However if appropriate arrangements cannot be put. in place<br />
on that basis we will be prepared to consider legislative<br />
options. I realise that compulsory industry training levies and the<br />
like are difficult concepts for many in business to accept.<br />
However the fact that such concepts even figure in the<br />
public debate shows just how seriously this issue needs to<br />
be taken.<br />
The task is large. It is urgent. It cannot be left undone. 006789 </p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen<br />
There can be no true social progress without social justice.<br />
The May Statement is a further step forward in Labor's<br />
social justice strategy.<br />
Special provision has been made for pensioners to earn extra<br />
income without paying tax. Also one quarter of a million<br />
pensioners have been freed of the obligation to pay<br />
provisional tax. We are securing adequate and certain<br />
funding of our health systems and nursing homes. We are<br />
promoting greater tax equity, including through the expanded<br />
tax file number system.<br />
Moreover we will facilitate employee share ownership,<br />
through concessional tax treatment of share discounts,<br />
recognising the legitimate interest of employees in getting<br />
a stake in the companies they work for.<br />
The direct social justice implic ations of these measures are<br />
well understood.<br />
Less well understood are the implications of tariff reform<br />
and the shake up of Government business enterprises,<br />
especially Telecom.<br />
Tariffs are a regressive tax. Lower income earners lose a<br />
higher proportion of their income to tariffs.<br />
The proportion is 9 per cent for those with incomes in the<br />
lowest 10 per cent of the income distribution, but less than<br />
half that for the topmost 10 per cent.<br />
It is estimated that the Government's proposals will<br />
ultimately cut the~ burden. on that lowest income group by<br />
almost 30 per cent.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I was pleased to note that our overall economic management<br />
was this week praised by the managing director of the<br />
InternationaI Monetary Fund, Michel Camdessus, as an<br />
encouraging and impressive lesson for other nations.<br />
Mr Camdessus reserved particular praise for the Accord<br />
partnership between the Government and the trade union<br />
movement which has added an extra dimension to the macro<br />
policies normally available to Governments. Under the<br />
Accord, the trade union movement has exercised real wage<br />
restraint, allowing the creation of more than one million<br />
new jobs since 1983.<br />
As Mr Camdessus noted, that is a 16% rate of growth three<br />
times the OECD average, he said. To use his word, that is<br />
an " 1except idnal" result for the Australian economy. 006790 </p>
<p>It is those very achievements, of course, that would be<br />
jeopardised if the conservatives' proposals for labour<br />
market deregulation voiced again in their response to the<br />
May Statement were ever implemented.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen I<br />
In the last week of the election campaign last July I<br />
addressed a luncheon of the Ballarat Businessmen's Club.<br />
Because it was the final week, I was determined that<br />
Australians thinking about their political choice at the<br />
ballot box understand the real issues at stake.<br />
The real issue was not then nor is it now a question of<br />
rushing prematurely to tax cuts allegedly paid for with<br />
massive but of course unspecified cuts in Government<br />
spending. It was about leadership, and it was about whether or not the<br />
massive process of reconstructing the Australian economy and<br />
reconstructing our view of Australia's place in the world<br />
would be abandoned or would be continued.<br />
So I told my audience in Ballarat that Labor offered itself<br />
to the Australian people as a united team with the proven<br />
policies, the far reaching strategy and the determination to<br />
meet the national economic challenge.<br />
I said then that Australians of 1987 would be judged by<br />
future historians as having taken a momentous leap forward<br />
if we stuck to the task of economic reconstruction.<br />
And I outlined in that speech a detailed series of reforms<br />
to carry the momentum of reconstruction into the<br />
micro-economy.<br />
It was on that basis that Australians renewed our mandate<br />
last July.<br />
So I take considerable pride today in outlining the steps we<br />
have now taken to implement our promises to continue what<br />
is a fundamental-strategy for the future of Australian<br />
prosperity.<br />
As I said in Ballarat, Australia under Labor is movingto<br />
the-challenge-of open and vigorous competition with<br />
the rest of the world instead of the security blanket of<br />
protected introspection;<br />
to enmeshment with our region rather than insularity;<br />
to the resilience derived from economic diversity and<br />
higher productivity instead of the vulnerability born of<br />
our over-relfance on commodities;<br />
to the shared * rewards of constructive co-operation<br />
instead of the fruitlessness of confrontation; and 00678.1 </p>
<p>to a society whose hallmark is equality of opportunity<br />
and social justice for all instead of one in which the<br />
dice are loaded in favour of a privileged few, from the<br />
tax system right through to education.<br />
Ladies and Gentlemen<br />
I do not wish in any way to underestimate the difficulty of<br />
the task still before us.<br />
But I do not hesitate to say that the measures announced on<br />
Wednesday amount to a huge step along the road to those<br />
goals. 006792 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
