<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>5558</transcript-id>
    <title>OPENING OF THE CHINESE CLASSICAL PAINTINGS EXHIBITION</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>31/03/1981</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00005558.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
215<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
FOR MEDIA TUESDAY, 31 MARCH 1981<br />
OPENING OF THE CHINESE CLASSICAL PAINTINGS EXHIBITION<br />
( Delivered for the Prime Minister by-the Minister for Hoame<br />
Affairs and Environment, Mr. Ian Wilson)<br />
It is impossible to stand in the presence of these priceless<br />
works spanning 600 years without being reminded of the intrinsic<br />
worth and value of human beings. We can see the worth and<br />
the greatness of mankind both in the people who are depicted.<br />
in these works, and in the artists whose work they are.<br />
The paintings are Chinese but they speak with a universal<br />
voice. They reveal something of the history and the ongoing<br />
development of Chinese culture and civilisation, yet at<br />
the same time we can all enter into the spirit of these works.<br />
They are unique because they are part of a unique tradition,<br />
but they complement and are complemented by other unique artistzic<br />
productions which are in their turn parts of other unique<br />
traditions. This is a truly magnificent collection of paintings, a<br />
magnificent exhibition. We have here paintings of the Ming<br />
and the Qing dynasties, spanning the 24th to the<br />
centuries, 600 years of one of the longest national art<br />
traditions in world history.<br />
Before I say... anything else, Ladies and Gentlemen, let me<br />
say through you to the people of Australia that we have here<br />
a remarkable opportunity,. and privilege, to view one of the<br />
finest artistic exhibitions which has ever been assembled.<br />
I have no doubt that hundreds of thousands of Australians<br />
will make sure that they see this exhibition, 600,000 people<br />
attended the Chinese archaeological exhibition which was<br />
brought to this country in 1977 and that must surely have<br />
whetted our appetites for more. This exhibition certainly<br />
provides Australians with a great deal more.<br />
The paintings in this superb exhibition belong to a<br />
tradition which has its origins in ancient China and yet is<br />
still evident in modern Chinese art. An historical exhibition<br />
such as this provides not only a bridge between our respective<br />
peoples and cultures, but also a bridge across thousands of<br />
years of Chinese culture. Works included in this exhibition<br />
have been drawn from museums of twelve provinces and cities,<br />
and in particular from the Palace Museum in Peking. The<br />
works included illustrate not only the greatn * ess of the<br />
individual artists, but also the range of skills of the<br />
Chinese schools, especially those of the Ming and Qing dynasties. </p>
<p>-2<br />
Mr Chairman, we are doubly privileged onr-this occasion. For<br />
not only do we have this magnificent exhibition of paintings,<br />
but we are also delighted to be able to welcome the members<br />
of the Chinese delegation which has come to Australia for this<br />
special event. The Delegation is led by Mr Peng Yan, Deputy<br />
Director of the Palace Museum in Peking. Accompanying Mr Peng<br />
are two distinguished scholars from the Palace Museum,<br />
Mr Xu Bang-da, a classical painting researcher and Mr Tian Xui,<br />
an expert in classical painting history. We are delighted to<br />
have with us these distinguished guests representing the<br />
Bureau of Archaelogical Relics, and the Overseas Archaeological,,.-<br />
Exhibition Corporation of The People's Republic of China.<br />
These two organisations have arranged for the collection to<br />
be made-available for this tour of Australia.<br />
It is also my pleasure to welcome on this occasion the<br />
Ambassador to the People's Republic of China, Mr Lin Ping and*<br />
Mrs Lin Ping, and Mr Xu Zhongling and Mr Ai Zhigao who are<br />
specialist curators advising on the care and display of the<br />
art works during the tour.<br />
The broad idea that an exhibition of Chinese classical paintings<br />
might be gathered together and made available for a tour of<br />
Australia arose several years ago in the early days of the<br />
development of cultural exchange arrangements between Australia<br />
and the People's Republic of China. In 1977, the Australia<br />
Council entered into some specific discussions which were<br />
reinforced at Ministerial level by the then Minister for Home Affairs,<br />
who visited China in 1979. Detailed arrangements were carried<br />
forward by the Australian Embassy in Peking. Further stimulus was<br />
given to the project when Edmund Capon, a leading London authority<br />
on Chinese art and now Director of the Art Gallery of New South Wales,<br />
became a consultant to advise on the content of the exhibition.<br />
Mr. Capon has ' chaired the Planning Committee and written the<br />
exhibition catalogue in partnership with Dr. Pang, Curator of<br />
Asian Art at the National Gallery of Victoria, and I would like<br />
to say what an outstanding catalogue it is.<br />
This exhibition is more than just an opportunity for Australians<br />
to view a great collection of Chinese paintings, it is a landmark<br />
in the developing links between China and Australia links that<br />
are cultural as well as economic.<br />
I believe that this exhibition-will stimulate the ongoing<br />
programme of important exchanges between our two countries,<br />
exchanges between our peoples as well as between our cultures.<br />
We have already had the opportunity in Australia to welcome and<br />
enjoy a number of Chinese tours, including the archaeological<br />
exhibition to which I have already referred. In the past the<br />
Chinese people have welcomed many of our artists and performers<br />
and we now look forward to increases in the number and variety<br />
of exhibitions and performances by Australians in China. A small<br />
Australian photographic exhibition is * currently touring China.<br />
I am told that is is proving to be a great s uccess and that people<br />
are flocking to see the display. This indicates that there is<br />
a genuine mutuality of interest between the Chinese and the<br />
Australian people. it shows that our cultural exchange programme<br />
has a sound basis, because it reflects and helps develop the<br />
concerns and interests of the people of both our countries. 9. 9/ 3 </p>
<p>3-<br />
would add that this exhibition has aroused great interest<br />
in the Australian-Chinese community and many of its members<br />
are participating in the presentation of something that is an<br />
integral part of their cultural heritage. I say let us have<br />
more of these exchanges which increase mutual understanding<br />
of our countries and our cultures, and which increase contact.<br />
between our peoples.<br />
The arrangement and management of this exhibition is the<br />
first production if I might use that word of the<br />
International Cultural Corporation of Australia. This is a new.<br />
organisation created by the Federal Government under the---<br />
Chairmanship of Mr. Jim Leslie and With directors drawn from<br />
the private sector and the arts.<br />
The objective of the Government in establishing this Corporation<br />
was to provide the machinery for the public and private sectors<br />
to join in the planning and presentation of major international<br />
cultural projects.<br />
The Government's role in the operations of the Corporation is<br />
to underwrite ventures such as this. -Accordingly, the Government<br />
has indemnified the works in this exhibition for a sum in<br />
excess of $ 55 million. The Government is pleased to provide<br />
such underwriting, so that the people of Australia can enjoy<br />
the best of the arts of other countries.<br />
The Cultural Corporation has made a fine start and I know it<br />
intends to maintain the highest standards in the exhibitions<br />
which it brings to Australia in the future.<br />
The request of the Corporation to BHP to sponsor this exhibition<br />
brought an immediate and generous response from Sir James McNe. Lll<br />
and his-~ colleagues on the BHP board. We are indebted to BHP<br />
for its recognition of the place of the arts in promoting<br />
international goodwill and understanding. Assistance in bringing<br />
the exhibition to Australia has also been provided by the<br />
Australia -Council, -and* by -the Departments-of Foreign-Affairs,<br />
and of Home Affairs and Environment. The Australia-China Council<br />
has also assisted this project as part of its ongoing programme<br />
in support of Australia-China relations.<br />
The exhibition will visit Brisbane, Adelaide, Perth and Melbourne<br />
following its debut here in Sydney. It is the policy of the<br />
Corporation that its exhibitions should be shown in as many<br />
cities as possible, and the wide exposure-that will be given------<br />
to these paintings is the result of close co-operation between<br />
the Corporation and the State Galleries.<br />
We are delighted that this exhibition will be in Australia for<br />
ten months and we are indebted to the Archaeological Relics<br />
Bureau of the People's Republic of China for this extended visit.<br />
I also thank the Chinese Government for permitting these works<br />
to travel abroad at all. It is the first time that such permission<br />
has been given, and we take this as a mark of Chinese confidence<br />
and esteem for Australia. / 4 </p>
<p>-4-<br />
This exhibition has a scholarly component associated with<br />
it and I have no doubt that this will enhance the depth<br />
of its impact.<br />
The Corporation has arranged, in association with the Art<br />
Gallery of New South Wales, an international seminar on<br />
Chinese painting which will bring experts from several countries<br />
to focus attention on the exhibition.<br />
Among the distinguished visitors here with us this evening,<br />
are Mr. Wu Zuoren and Madame Xiao Shufang who are among<br />
China's leading contemporary artists. Mr. Wu is also<br />
Vice-Chairman of the China Federation of Literary and Art<br />
Circles, and a Deputy of the National People's Congress.<br />
Mr. Wu and Madame Xiao are the guests of the Australia-China Council.<br />
They are spending some time in Australia viewing the landscape<br />
and meeting with local artists and scholars.<br />
The fact that this unique exhibition is appearing in Australia O<br />
reflects the excellent state of Australia-China relations.<br />
We confidently expect that contacts and exchanges between our<br />
countries will be further strengthened with the concluding in<br />
the near future of an agreement on cultural co-operation between<br />
Australia and China. The proposed agreement provides for<br />
co-operation between Australia and China in the field of culture,<br />
including the arts, crafts, media, sport and education. We<br />
welcome the growth in our relationship which this reflects.<br />
It gives me great pleasure to formally open this exhibition<br />
and to wish it a successful tour of Australia.<br />
o% 0<br />
000---</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
