<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9147</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP ADELAIDE, 8 MARCH 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/03/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009147.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TEL: W'a-. 9414-11 ! 4O. UID r. Vi'u'i<br />
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTERo THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
DOORSTOP, ADELAIDE, 8 MARCH 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
J: Prime Minister, how do you feel about the festival withdrawing your<br />
Invitation for security reasons?<br />
PM: Well, I mean I'm not sure whether this is a pressing national issue. I<br />
think this by-election Is an Important by-election for the country. It is<br />
important for the Government We have got now a major economic<br />
recovery underway, we are seeing employment growth pick up. We<br />
have a first class candidate in Martyn Evans, who actually even lives in<br />
the electorate. I mean, how old fashioned that is, that we should<br />
actually be fielding a candidate who lives in the place he is<br />
representing.<br />
J: But have you the Greek community to a larger extent?<br />
PM: Just one second. And as a consequence we will be sending to<br />
Canberra, I expect, the people of Bonytrion to be sending to Canberra<br />
someone who will fill the shoes of someone of the calibre of Neal<br />
Blewett who presided over a transformation of Australia's health and<br />
social security policies, and in Martyn Evans we have someone of that<br />
calibre. And I think that is the real issue, that is, that the Government,<br />
the general policies of social democracy which the Government has<br />
fostered, and of economic recovery, will be recognised in the byelection<br />
by the people of Bonython sending such a candidate. Now<br />
these other Issues such asGreek fe stivals and the rest, I am not able<br />
to go, and Senator Bolkus normally attends in my place, often in<br />
functions like this, and he may well attend on this occasion as well.<br />
J: But given the reaction to your recognition of Macedonia do you think<br />
may be the Government has been a bit premature? </p>
<p>T8EL.: Mar. 94 14: 11 No. 015 P. 02/ 04<br />
2<br />
PM:. Well the United States recognised the Former Yugoslav Republic of<br />
Macedonia, the Government of Greece sponsored -the United Nationsmembership<br />
of the Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia. So, if the<br />
Government of Greece can sponsor its membership, it's, I think,<br />
drawing a long bow to say that Australia can't even recognise its<br />
existence.<br />
J: How concerned are you about the response, the emotional and at<br />
times violence from the Greek community?<br />
PM: Well, I think there is a cause for maturity in these things. I mean, there<br />
has been, as a consequence of actions Australia tooK, this State is no<br />
longer describing itself as the Republic of Macedonia, but rather as a<br />
former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia a result of actions Australia<br />
and others took. It's this constitution to deny a territorial claims to<br />
parts of Greece. We have made clear that the symbols and<br />
representations of this State, such as the star of Vergina for which<br />
there is a strong feeling in Greece, should be respected. I mean,<br />
these are express and obvious consequences of Australia's policy.<br />
The policies produced, I think, a real change in these issues, if you<br />
like, for those who identify with the interests of Greece. But, when 59<br />
countries all of western Europe, the United States recognises this<br />
state, when Greece itself sponsors its entry into the United Nations -I<br />
think, it is a time for some maturity on the part of Australians of Greek<br />
decent to understand that this government has acted in a way which<br />
has advanced what they see to be their interests.<br />
J: Mr Keating, how do you see the latest Liberal leadership wrangles<br />
affecting the by-election here?<br />
PM: I think nothing I say or do will change the propensity of the Liberal<br />
party to keep hacking itself to pieces. The reason is, they have no<br />
idea about where they stand in Australian society. They don't know<br />
what they represent or who they represent. And now you have got<br />
John Howson in the last day or so, using a word which I have used all<br />
through 1992 and we've used all through the 1980s that is, the word<br />
' inclusion' saying that Australians are entitled to live in a -society<br />
where everyone has a piece of it; where the growth and prosperity is<br />
shared by all including minorities. Well, Dr Howson discovered this<br />
last week and now he is trying to paint himself as a sort of moderate,<br />
small Liberal which would almost make a cat laugh.<br />
Mr Howard on the other hand, is working flat out on turning the clock<br />
back. He is out there, he has got the clock and he has wound us back,<br />
at this stage probably about 14 years, and he is still winding to see if<br />
he can actually get us back to the 1 950s and then he would be very,<br />
very happy indeed. So, this once great party has ended up in this<br />
state. TEL: </p>
<p>T8EL.: Mar. 94 14: 11 No. 015 P. 03/ 04<br />
3<br />
J: One of the issues that the Liberals are split on is income splitting.<br />
Where do you stand on that?<br />
PM: Income splitting diminishes tax for husbands but doesn't give the<br />
money to wives. What the government has done over the years is to<br />
make sure that there are payments that actually are paid to women's<br />
bank accounts. The Home Child Care Allowance which I introduced in<br />
the last election and which we have now introduced into the<br />
Parliament, into law it pays money into the bank account of the<br />
partner at home generally the wife. Now, these are things, I think,<br />
Australian women appreciate a degree of independence they<br />
wouldn't otherwise have.<br />
J: On the question of a Medicare levy does that have your full support?<br />
And is it a bad time to be perhaps looking at something like this when<br />
you've got two crucial by-elections in a bit over a week?<br />
PM: There are no policy proposals around in the government that warrants<br />
an increase in the Medicare levy. Nothing I have seen.<br />
J: Are you ruling it out?<br />
PM: And there is no case on the part of any Minister coming before the<br />
Cabinet to rule it In.<br />
J: So, in other words it's off the books, it is not going to happen?<br />
PM: There will not be changes of the variety that have been discussed in<br />
the newspapers, speculatively I might say, which would lead to such<br />
an increase.<br />
J What about a jobs levy. The Treasurer has said that it is still broadly<br />
on the edge of the table of the Finance Minister do you think it is on<br />
the table at all?<br />
PM: The jobs levy remains an option, but again, the government would like<br />
to finance this change in the labour market. That is, to deal with the<br />
long-term unemployed without resort to a levy. I think, most of us think<br />
that Is possible.<br />
J: So the growth forecasts will enable that? Are you going to rely on the<br />
recovery to pull you out of it?<br />
PM: The economy is growing much more rapidly than people expect it and<br />
through the year growth next year will be something in the order of four<br />
per cent faster, I think, than anything in the OECD or the western<br />
world. This will produce an increase in revenues as every such<br />
recovery always does.<br />
TEL </p>
<p>TEL: 8. Mar. 94 14: 11 No. 015 P. 04/ 04.<br />
4<br />
J: Getting back to the by-election, you mentioned that Martyn Evans is a<br />
high quality candidate. There's a bit of concern within the South<br />
Australian Labor party that it is losing some of its best talent, you are<br />
not concerned that the Federal party is bleeding the State party dry in<br />
that regard?<br />
PM:-One thing about it, they are a community based party. When someone<br />
leaves, someone generally fills their shoes and I think that it is a tribute<br />
to the Labor party in South Australia that it has sent so many high<br />
calibre people to the Commonwealth parliament and the<br />
consequences are obvious in the social economic policies of the<br />
government.<br />
J; Do you see the Ros Kelly affair affecting this by-election?<br />
PM: I don't think so. These things blow over in a few days and the real<br />
issues, as always, it is always the weight rather than the flim-flam and<br />
fairy floss that matters. And even if it often doesn't matter to the<br />
media, it does matter to the public and I think they weigh things<br />
accordingly.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
