<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>11445</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME    MINISTER HON JOHN HOWARD MP    AUSTRALIAN    WINE AND CHEESE INDUSTRY PROMOTION        PARK HYATT    HOTEL, TOKYO, JAPAN</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/07/1999</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>E&amp;OE...............</p>
<p>As I come to the end of my visit to Tokyo on this visit to<br />
Japan I can't think of a more delightful venue than a promotion of Australian<br />
wine and cheese, in which to spend my final hours in Tokyo.</p>
<p>Japan is a huge market for Australian food and beverages<br />
and the total of our exports are worth more than $3 billion. That is not to say we do not seek to make<br />
that figure much larger. Of particular<br />
significance has been the growth of wine and cheese as exports to Japan. There used to be a time when the only wine<br />
imported into Japan came from Europe, but that is rapidly changing and nights<br />
like tonight are a partial reminder to our competitors of just how determined<br />
Australia is to rapidly expand her wine and cheese exports to the huge market<br />
that is Japan.</p>
<p>I want to commend the Australian Wine Export Council for<br />
opening an Australian Wine Bureau in Tokyo.<br />
I want to commend the work of that Bureau and I understand that there<br />
will be a series of promotions, including a major promotion in all the<br />
restaurants and bars of this prestige hotel, the Hyatt, of Australian wine in<br />
November. And I understand that this<br />
very hotel has already held a number of Australian wine promotions<br />
recently. I thank it for doing so and I<br />
endorse its remarkably good taste.</p>
<p>Australian wine is one of our great exporting successes of<br />
recent years. In 1990, a bare nine<br />
years ago, our exports were $114 million.<br />
We now look set to break the $1 billion mark this year if exports to<br />
Japan are anything to go by. And the<br />
quality of our wine is also increasingly recognised in Japan, with an<br />
Australian red winning the trophy for the best red wine at the inaugural Japan<br />
International Wine Challenge held late last year in Tokyo.</p>
<p>Likewise our dairy industry has enjoyed quite spectacular<br />
export success in recent years.<br />
Australia is the leading supplier of cheese to Japan with a market share<br />
of more than 40 per cent and that represents just under half of Australia's<br />
total cheese exports and a quarter of all Australian cheese production.</p>
<p>And that particular story is very relevant on a day when<br />
the fluctuating fortunes of Australia's trade overseas is very much in the news<br />
back home. What it reminds us is that<br />
you can never generalise about trade.<br />
What you do is go out and fight for market share on every conceivable<br />
front. And to use a famous Australian<br />
expression, you win some and you lose some, and we have certainly won some when<br />
it has come to Australian wine and Australian dairy produce into Japan.</p>
<p>And finally, I'm delighted to remark that the most recent<br />
breakthrough in Australian exports of agricultural products to Japan has been<br />
the launch last month of Tasmanian Fuji apples, with Australian easy-peel<br />
citrus to be launched shortly. I<br />
understand that unfortunately if you want to buy Tasmanian Fuji apples in a<br />
supermarket in Tokyo, you probably can't because I'm told most of them have<br />
already been sold out.</p>
<p>So ladies and gentlemen it is with enormous pleasure, if I<br />
can be suitable armed, that I propose a toast to the endeavour of our wine and<br />
cheese exporters, and most particularly might I say to the discerning palate of<br />
so many of our Japanese friends. It<br />
really has been one of the great success stories of Australian export over the<br />
last 10 years and it is always of course a double pleasure to be associated,<br />
not only with a successful export, but also a successful export that brings<br />
such enormous pleasure to so many Australians and indeed to so many people<br />
around the world.</p>
<p>I propose a toast to the endeavour of the wine and cheese<br />
exporters of Australia. We are indeed<br />
very indebted to them and extremely proud of them.</p>
<p>Our wine and cheese exporters.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
