<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9383</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP ABC LATELINE INTERVIEW TUESDAY 18 OCTOBER, 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/10/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009383.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING, MP<br />
ABC LATELINE INTERVIEW<br />
TUESDAY 18 OCTOBER, 1994<br />
KOB: What, for you, is the philosophical core of this statement?<br />
PK: The simple proposition that the arts are central to Australian life and<br />
culture and that as our identity becomes more obvious, as we make a<br />
greater claim on our own sovereignty, as we project ourselves into the<br />
world, as we rejoice in what we become, the arts will be an obviously<br />
central ingredient to all of that.<br />
KOB: What we've grown used to in the past, in governments, plural, attitude<br />
to the arts, has been encouraging the arts for arts sake, which would<br />
deliver some indefinable benefit for us in terms of cultural richness.<br />
But, this one, this time, represents a different ball game, doesn't it. An<br />
enormous emphasis on links from the arts to business, to exports, to<br />
an economic dividend?<br />
PK: Well, there is an economic and a cultural dividend and a social<br />
dividend, that is true. And we are building on the arts and our<br />
education. I have said before on this program, one of Australia's great<br />
comparative advantages in the world is its education system. And, the<br />
confidence which the arts now have, the rejoicing about our own<br />
culture which there now That flux with our education system is<br />
going to produce... I'm sure this is going to be one of the countries<br />
where the arts have a most profound impact on the way this country<br />
develops. Artists feel that, people were telling me that today. People<br />
were saying, " You can feel it", artists can feel it. I think the community<br />
can feel it.<br />
KOB: OK. I'd like to try and get to some of the essence of the spirit of our<br />
identity and our culture that you talk about later in the program, and<br />
there are many areas to try and cover. But, I'd like to focus for the next<br />
few minutes on what you identify as the new multi-media age because 4-<br />
PRIME MINISTER </p>
<p>you seem to identify that as the big new challenge that this country<br />
faces. You talk about a fundamental conceptual shift, you say<br />
information technology has crossed the ' technical Rubicon into the<br />
realm of consciousness, the realm of culture'. What exactly are you<br />
getting at?<br />
PK: I wrote that line myself so thank you for picking the best line in the<br />
document...<br />
KOB: What exactly does it mean?<br />
PK: What it means is that we are at a stage where the dissemination of art,<br />
culture, news and education is going to be very profound in the sense<br />
that we are going to go past... We are going to go beyond the people<br />
who package information, we are going to go beyond the networks, we<br />
are going to go beyond the newspapers. This technology has the<br />
capacity to take the creator's product straight to the person. And,<br />
getting that right and being in that, being in the product and benefiting<br />
from the system is, I think, important not only to the country and its<br />
development but because so much of it is going to be creative and so<br />
much of it, at this point, is a phenomena of the English language<br />
countries, we're so well placed to be a part of it in a productive sense<br />
and someone who is a receiver of the wisdom which this can<br />
communicate.<br />
KOB: So, how do you put flesh to that? You capture the breadth and depth<br />
of Australian creative output on CD-ROM, you digitise our poets, our<br />
artists, our musicians, our film makers and flog them off to the world?<br />
PK: Well, I think we stand a very great possibility of doing that. I think we<br />
are going to see... The difference in this age is interactivity, it is not<br />
just passive listening and passive viewing. There is the capacity to<br />
talk to this and be part of it. And, therefore, the system that is going to<br />
be developed is going to carry a whole range of services; pay<br />
television, inter activity, telephony et cetera. So, we're on to<br />
something here, now. If we are not part of this... We cannot miss this<br />
as we missed, say, the hardware phase of computers. You could<br />
afford to miss the hardware phase of computers, we missed it. The PC<br />
came in our time, in the last decade and we missed it. Because we<br />
had to prepare for it a bit earlier than we normally do.<br />
KOB: But it is still somewhat vague in terms of what exactly this is. Is it, for<br />
example in terms of trying to value it, in trying to place it does it<br />
have the potential to be our new mining industry, our new wool<br />
industry?<br />
PK: Oh, absolutely and much more so. I think so. Much more so. </p>
<p>KOB: So, when people put an estimate in the medium term of a three trillion<br />
dollar market which I think Michael Lee, the minister, mentioned<br />
recently, that's not an exaggeration?<br />
PK: Well, I wouldn't want to quantify it in our terms but there is no doubt<br />
that we have a very deep artistic inheritance in this country, a unique<br />
culture. We have the capacity to develop product for this highway, so<br />
called, and the things we are doing today, in part, go to further develop<br />
our capacity to do that. And, to bring in the creativity of a lot of young<br />
people. This is not going to be a business that people of your age and<br />
my age are going to be in. This is going to be, basically, young people<br />
who have, I think, the chance with that creativity and the technical<br />
opportunity which comes with this medium. Now, this will not be true of<br />
film and television because that will be a highly developed business as<br />
it is in every other country. But, there is a tremendous, that sort of<br />
blossoming of creativity one sees -particularly with young people<br />
today who are computer literate -we are going to see this<br />
opportunity.<br />
KOB: Because, really, you would agree would you not that the bulk of adult<br />
Australians would not even know what CD-ROM is?<br />
PK: No, but let's make this clear. It's not just about CD-ROM. This is<br />
about film and television product, it is about extending the possibilities<br />
for telephony....<br />
KOB: But it is also about having a fundamental grasp of potentials and the<br />
realities, the looming realities of the super highway as well?<br />
PK: Yes, well, the fundamental earner, the first primary, basic I think,<br />
fundamental earner on the super highway is going to be pay television.<br />
And we are going to build layers of services on top of that; telephony,<br />
education, all the other things, banking, specialised products. You're<br />
talking here of the possibility of hundreds of channels, specialised<br />
products which people can subscribe to. They can subscribe to their<br />
favourite journalist who can talk to them directly. You can have your<br />
own program, Kerry...<br />
KOB: Thanks, Paul...<br />
PK: You'll go straight down the tube without anyone chopping it around.<br />
KOB: And we're also talking about a lot of emphasis on international<br />
markets. Your statement draws on a recent report called ' Commerce<br />
in Content', looking on our international future in the interactive multimedia<br />
markets. One of the prerequisites to success that that report<br />
stresses is that Australia must develop, and I quote, the world's<br />
best intellectual property and copyright environment". We are a long </p>
<p>way from that with our existing laws protecting intellectual property,<br />
aren't we?<br />
PK: I don't think so, no. We've said a lot in the statement about it, this very<br />
day.<br />
KOB: So, there's not much to fix?<br />
PK: Well, put it this way, if you are in the business of producing this is<br />
an OECD mainline country... If you are in the business of producing<br />
product the first thing that you guarantee is that your copyright system<br />
is a good one. That's a basic thing to do, I would think.<br />
KOB: So, we're close to world best copyright law in this country, protecting<br />
our artists and our intellectual property?<br />
PK: Well, let me say this to you, by the time that we are producing product<br />
which has the capacity for broad dissemination in mass markets, we<br />
certainly will have.<br />
KOB: Can we bridge back from the super highway and the CD-ROM to the<br />
core of this statement as it applies to what we are as people. You pay<br />
homage to our diversity, but how genuinely diverse is the patronage of<br />
our arts, the spread of our arts?<br />
PK: I think it is very diverse, support for artists is by peer group<br />
assessment through the Australia Council. We've now added to that<br />
capacity, we're diversifying, again, further, by giving the Australia<br />
Council a major organisations board and picking up other bodies...<br />
KOB: It's centralising much more, isn't it?<br />
PK: No, oh no...<br />
KOB: Well, the Australia Council is now a much more powerful body, it is<br />
almost the supreme body in determining the flow of government funds<br />
to the arts.<br />
PM: To artists. But not necessarily to the arts, and the other thing we<br />
envisage it doing is instead of just it being a grant-giver, we see it<br />
basically providing markets for our products abroad, improving private<br />
sponsorship for the arts in other words, giving it a bigger role, but a<br />
role which in a sense disseminates some of the power away from the<br />
centrality of simply just giving grants.<br />
KOB: Because you know of the criticism that has been levelled at the<br />
Australia Council over the years, that it has developed into a club<br />
dispensing patronage a club that it has fostered creeping political<br />
correctness, that its links to the Keating Government are too close for </p>
<p>comfort, and yet they do now have this super-power status. How do<br />
you guarantee fair play and a healthy remoteness from Government,<br />
and it is important in you terms that they have a healthy remoteness<br />
from Government?<br />
PM: Yes. Absolutely. We have always thought that...<br />
KOB: Well how do they do that?<br />
PM: well, by the quality of the people that are on it, and by it's charter.<br />
You have got the current chair Hillary McPhee, arguably Australia's<br />
foremost publisher, certainly of Australian product, and Michael Lynch,<br />
a respected arts administrator that sort of talent you<br />
rarely Governments are very lucky to have people like that. And the<br />
notion that they are, in some way, going to sign up to what? Anyway,<br />
what does the Government what politically, other than that the thing<br />
flourishes....<br />
KOB: Votes.<br />
PM: No<br />
KOB: Votes in the end.<br />
PM: no, no, no, no.. other than it flourishes and works that is what we're<br />
after we are after a good outcome.<br />
KOB: You presented eleven prestigious creative fellowships to Australian<br />
artists yesterday they all came from NSW or the ACT, such a small<br />
part of this diverse country in a sense. Didn't that raise some question<br />
mark in your mind about whether the Australia Council is really on the<br />
right track in terms of the diversity...<br />
PM: Who says they're...<br />
KOB: . the national diversity.<br />
PM: But they're not chosen by the Australia Council they are awarded by<br />
the Australia Council, but they're chosen by a panel, a very broadly<br />
representative cross-d isci pl inary panel who chose those people<br />
looking at.. so it wasn't simply the literary grants people looking at a<br />
writer, it wasn't a visual arts person looking at visual art it was a<br />
cross-disciplinary, cross state thing..<br />
KOB: OK, well lets say everything...<br />
PM: . but they chose... </p>
<p>KOB: let's say everything was absolutely on merit and these were the<br />
eleven best artists that you could have chosen, what does it say about<br />
the health of our artistic diversity if all eleven of them came from the<br />
one area?<br />
PM: Well, it depends last year that wasn't the case, and the year before<br />
that...<br />
KOB: But it was this year?<br />
PM: the one thing, let me say about the fellowships they are chosen<br />
exclusively on merit. The one thing the Government said from the<br />
inception this is not a triers scheme this is for people of excellence<br />
in mid-career, and so this was the first time we had, if you like, open<br />
nominations. So there were plenty of nominations, and obviously hard<br />
choices, but they have never moved away from choosing those that<br />
they thought were best. And in this case, by doing it, they have kept<br />
these fellowships to such a standard that the people that get them are<br />
obviously from that calibre of achievement. So, you might see a<br />
preponderance from NSW this year it will be mixed up other years.<br />
We have now got 45 of these if you track through them I think you will<br />
find that it's very broadly spread.<br />
KOB: Some specific initiatives $ 60 million to develop new Australian<br />
product for commercial television in the next three years how do you<br />
guarantee that product will be the high quality that you seem to have<br />
as your goal in giving the money, and how do you avoid the<br />
commercial networks abandoning any pretence at quality in their<br />
existing obligations to meet Australian content quotas?<br />
PM: Well, Australians are interested in their own culture. They are<br />
interested in Australia every time that someone runs an Australian<br />
series, or a mini-series it always has tremendous ratings. Australians<br />
respond tremendously well to their own culture....<br />
KOB: Yes, but we're also talking about products like " Man Man", and quiz<br />
shows...<br />
PM: I know, but this will not be going to that, but we have all appreciated<br />
the " Brides of Christ" and " The Dismissal", and these sorts of programs<br />
and mini-series, and it is to this top-end of the product that this fund is<br />
directed.<br />
KOB: Ok, so that funding is directed to the top-end so let's say the networks<br />
are able to use that money to give that quality gloss to their overall<br />
product would it concern you if you then also saw more productions<br />
of local quiz shows, more kind of " Man Man" type programs </p>
<p>PM: Well all that would happen then is that networks would get less of the<br />
money and more would go to the... . we're saying about half of this will<br />
go to independent producers of product for television...<br />
KOB: But this is on top of the quota material?<br />
PM: On top of the quota material. So, this doesn't lessen the quotas, but<br />
let's say the networks did as you said, and said " look, we're getting<br />
some quality here, so let's drop it off there", what we would do is simply<br />
take the residual away from the networks and give it to the<br />
independent producers. And it may well be Kerry that independent<br />
producers get the lion's share of it because they have got more ideas<br />
and are more prepared to produce than the networks are in house.<br />
Now I would like to think we can get the networks to produce higher<br />
quality products like this in-house.<br />
KOB: You have allocated $ 13 million to SBS over 4 years to commission<br />
quality material of a culturally diverse nature but the priority has to go<br />
to product that can be sold overseas so you are saying to artists<br />
" please produce your best, as long at its commercial", Is that really the<br />
way to go?<br />
PM: Not necessarily, but I think that a reflection of Australia's multiculturalism<br />
on SBS in drama will be received well in Australia, and<br />
interestingly I think, it will play well abroad. I don't have any<br />
problem look, we have had art-house release cinema here in this<br />
country for God knows how long. It doesn't... . getting into the big league<br />
is what it's all about. Selling, and getting out there transmitting<br />
Australian culture to the world. Film has been one of the things which<br />
has allowed us to actually put a view of Australia....<br />
KOB: I mean part of the Australian culture of the world is " Neighbours" L.<br />
PM: Yeah.<br />
KOB: That sells overseas. So SBS might foster a product like " Neighbours"<br />
which has a bit of cultural diversity in it and flog that overseas? Is that<br />
what you would want?<br />
PM: Well they might, but they might also and I think the SBS is a quality<br />
organisation I think SBS will understand why this money is given and<br />
do something with it. I mean people are intelligent aren't they? If they<br />
say " well the government has given us this money, now what we'll do is<br />
basically squander it or waste it or we'll do something", well in the end<br />
it will dry up, and I don't think people will do that. And can I just say I'm<br />
sure " Neighbours" was never produced for sale abroad, it just<br />
happened to sell abroad. </p>
<p>KOB: You say that a creative infra-structure will only be effective where all<br />
existing players in the industry this is the television industry I think<br />
we're talking about identify and pursue common ends content will be<br />
the defining element. Do you think that people like Kerry Packer and<br />
Rupert Murdoch driven above all else by commercial imperatives<br />
will really embrace what you are saying there?<br />
PM: Why should they I missed your point... . what's your point?<br />
KOB: You're talking about all existing players in the industry identifying and<br />
pursuing common ends.<br />
PM: Well I don't think....<br />
KOB: This is the cultural statement about promotional culture.<br />
PM: I don't know where in the document you read that, but if it's to imply<br />
that there is some sort of uniformity of commitment a common goal...<br />
KOB: It was under Film and television.<br />
PM: . on the part of all these people, of course there won't be. But again, I<br />
think that a lot of what we produce in Australia has come from network<br />
television, and it might also come through major organisations like<br />
News Limited.<br />
KOB: But you say that will only be effective the creative infra-structure will<br />
only be effective if all players are committed to the common end.<br />
PM: The common end being?<br />
KOB: That content will be the defining element.<br />
PM: Yes. I think that's making a separate point that content I don't know<br />
whether the text...<br />
KOB: You have emphasised in this report that content is all<br />
PM: Well that's what I'm just trying...<br />
KOB: . that content is all. But you're saying that the Kerry Packers and the<br />
Rupert Murdoch's and everyone else in the industry has to be<br />
committed to a common end, and your common end seems to me is<br />
quality...<br />
PM: Yes, well Kerry the distributional systems are under challenge aren't<br />
they? Free to air television is under challenge from pay television, and<br />
it's under challenge from terrestrial systems. We're going to find with<br />
this revolution in information technology that traditional distribution </p>
<p>9<br />
systems newspapers are under challenge. What sticks to you in the<br />
end? Content. I mean, this system is hungry for product, it's hungry<br />
for content and that is why part of this statement is lifting the content.<br />
KOB: But, how much of the system will be hungry for quality content?<br />
PM: Well, enought of it and that is why there is a commitment to the high<br />
quality end of the production fund with television and that is why,<br />
again, with the multi-media it's on content for the information highway<br />
products. But the whole essence of the statement is about bringing<br />
forward the essence of our culture and translating that into content for<br />
transmission to us, to others.<br />
KOB: You talk about the great power that the media has and you say that<br />
cross media ownership rules provide a check on this power. Our<br />
national broadcasters this is all in the statement have a special<br />
independent role to reflect the nations diversity. Now, in terms of<br />
those cross media ownership rules which you say provide a check on<br />
this power, does that mean an ongoing and indefinate commitment to<br />
cross media rules by this Government?<br />
PM: Well, it depends where convergence goes.. I mean, we are seeing<br />
now and very obviously, I mean if Telecom lays an optic fibre cable<br />
which is going to carry interactive services and pay television, they are<br />
going to have telephony on it. It's very obvious isn't it?.<br />
KOB: Yes.<br />
PM: So, we are seeing a convergence, there is no doubt about that. But,<br />
what the cross media rules have done is separate radio from<br />
television, television from print et cetera.<br />
KOB: But, there is pressure coming on the Government?<br />
PM: Indeed. But, it is coming naturally. It is coming because of this<br />
change.<br />
KOB: Well, can you see a natural step from cross media which responds to<br />
the new imperatives, but at the same time checks the power that you<br />
acknowledge?<br />
PM: Well, I think, Government's should try to do that.<br />
KOB: Well, it's bad luck if they can't isn't it?<br />
PM: The technology does run ahead of you often. I mean, you should try to<br />
do that and then adapt public policy to the imperatives of the<br />
technology and I hope we can do that, but there is no doubt.. </p>
<p>KOB: But, you are saying that it is possible that you won't be able to do that.<br />
PM: The cross media rules went in in 1984 or 1985 and since then, I mean,<br />
the rise of personal computers, the change in photonics, fibre optics, I<br />
mean, all of these changes are changes, which are in a sense, running<br />
ahead of the policy.<br />
KOB: But, you seem to be saying quiet clearly that the technology is such<br />
that you are not confident that you will be able to maintain the kinds of<br />
checks of power that you feel you have so far, that you may not be<br />
able to control the technology.<br />
PM: Well, one would be confident that one could be reasonably effective in<br />
maintaining a diversity of power bases in the Australia media, but I<br />
don't think one should even try to be confident about resisting the shift<br />
of these technologies. I mean it is not going to be very long, I mean,<br />
here's Newslimited with Star Television Star is actually now going to<br />
broadcast from the Middle East to the Russian Far East and down to<br />
Queensland. Now, what are you going to do with that? Poke your<br />
tongue out at it, through a bill up in the air, table a motion in the<br />
House?<br />
KOB: The ABC is still the biggest single recipient of funding for the arts. Do<br />
you believe that the $ 500 million a year is money well spent at the<br />
moment?<br />
PM: I think so, yes.<br />
KOB: You are happy with the ABC's performance?<br />
PM: By and large yes. There is a debate in this country about the ABC,<br />
whether it's a bit too precious, a bit too confident of its own remit. But,<br />
by and large if the question is, is the money well spent? Yes. Could it<br />
be spent better? Probably, the answer is yes to that too.<br />
KOB: Where?<br />
PM: It is a very large budget and I am not here to dissect the ABC and I<br />
wouldn't want to try, but<br />
KOB: You talk about the importance of pay for example, generally in this<br />
country. This was a lot of angst inside the Government at the time<br />
about whether the ABC should or shouldn't be involved in pay and it<br />
was well known at the time that you were opposed to the involvement<br />
that the ABC itself was<br />
PM: No, no, I was not opposed. I was happy to give the ABC a couple of<br />
channels. Say, you don't have to bid for them, you have got them.<br />
Happy to do that. But, what I wasn't happy to do was to see the ABC </p>
<p>launch itself with a consortium, say like Australis. The ABC on the<br />
original plan would have been part of Australis.<br />
KOB: But, are you happy with the course that the ABC is now plotting on pay<br />
television?<br />
PM: Let me just finish this point, I don't think it could have basically got in<br />
there and bid $ 80-i OOM and then bought product from around the<br />
world. I mean, the ABC never had the capacity to do that and I don't<br />
think it should have.<br />
KOB: OK<br />
PM: Whereas, I think, the solution we have now is an acceptable one.<br />
KOB: OK When you go back on your stewardship as Prime Minister, when<br />
you do look back on you stewardship as Prime Minister, where do you<br />
think you'll place this document in terms of your achievements?<br />
PM: Well, these are strands of our national life that one looks at whether it<br />
is fidelity to the unemployed, whether it is a focus on our creativity and<br />
our culture, whether it is on the truth of Mabo, whether it is on the shift<br />
to Asia with APEC, it's plaiting the strands into a whole. So, I see this<br />
as an important strand in the rope of Australia.<br />
KOB: But, what is important to you is that the Australia Council, for example,<br />
understands those imperatives and pursues them too isn't it?<br />
PM: I think it understands them perfectly, I honestly do. I think, the arts<br />
community have always understand this better than most other<br />
communities.<br />
KOB: Of course, there are those who say that you are using this as another<br />
tool to assist your republican push. The foundation for Australian<br />
cultural development, you say of this in the statement, that this<br />
particular body the foundation for Australian cultural development<br />
should aim to extend Australian's understanding of their own country<br />
and its future and it will play a particularly important creative role in<br />
preparations for the 2001 celebrations Now, why wouldn't that be<br />
seen, why shouldn't that be seen as a foundation to help you promote<br />
your republican push?<br />
PM: I think, there is a very obvious distinguishing point there. The 2001<br />
celebrations are the celebrations of the centenary of the country's<br />
federation, of our sense of nation, of our nationhood. What the<br />
Constitutional overlay is on that is another matter altogether. Now, I<br />
mean I think, we are heading for the big identity and cultural round-up.<br />
Let me not mix words about that. I mean, you have got the Olympics in<br />
the Year 2000, three months from the centenary, we've now got a great </p>
<p>12<br />
cultural shift into Asia. We are now starting to understand, I think,<br />
better these questions of identity. We are rejoicing in our own culture.<br />
I mean, the country feels good, that a right has been wronged with the<br />
Aboriginal community. These things are important feelings. A nation<br />
is about its feeling about itself, to itself, of itself and that is why, I think,<br />
I haven't got to worry about the people with a maudlin interest in the<br />
past who are like the Liberals celebrating 50 years ago. I mean, that<br />
is all going to happen for us. We don't need any little foundations to<br />
change that Kerry.<br />
KOB: Last question, to what extent is this perhaps personal foible is a bit<br />
insulting, but to what extent is this a personal indulgence of the Prime<br />
Minister's the emphasis that you are putting on the arts in terms of<br />
the philosophy that is driving it because this would seem in many<br />
instances to be a very interventionist policy. It is almost an industry<br />
statement about the arts and I would suggest is far more interventionist<br />
than many other areas of business.<br />
PM: But, if you said it about sports, you would say it would be completely<br />
normal. The fact that the arts now have such an enormous following in<br />
Australia and the fact that people are enriched by them, uplifted by it,<br />
means that its structure should be such that it can accommodate these<br />
national aspirations and feelings. So, I don't see it as an industry<br />
statement. I do see it as a cultural thing and if the culture, important as<br />
it is to us, can be important to others around the world, if we can<br />
project ourselves as a society of worth, of a deep democracy of values,<br />
well, why shouldn't we?<br />
KOB: Paul Keating, thank you.<br />
PM: Thank you, Kerry.<br />
ends </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
