<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>21648</transcript-id>
    <title>Exports and Infrastructure  </title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>18/03/2005</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>Australia has increasing export potential, particularly but not only in the resource sector.</p>
<p> I have, therefore, decided to appoint a small taskforce to identify any bottlenecks of a physical or regulatory kind in the operation of Australia's infrastructure which may impede the full realisation of our export opportunities.</p>
<p>It will be chaired by Dr Brian Fisher, the Executive Director of the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics. It will also include Mr Max Moore-Wilton AC, currently Executive Chairman of Sydney Airport and former Secretary of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet and Prof Henry Ergas of Charles River Associates.</p>
<p>All three members of the taskforce have extensive experience in infrastructure matters. The remit of the taskforce is limited to bottlenecks which may affect Australia's export performance.</p>
<p>The taskforce has been asked to report by not later than 20th May 2005.</p>
<p>It will be supported by a small whole-of-government secretariat.</p>
<p>18 March 2005</p>
<p> Dr Brian Fisher, PSM 2002, BScAgr, PHD</p>
<p>Since 1996, Executive Director of the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics where he specialises in public policy analysis especially as it relates to the agricultural, fishing, forestry, minerals and energy industries.  He is currently heavily involved in research on climate change policy, international trade liberalisation and microeconomic reform in Australia. Since 1996, Dr Fisher has been involved as a senior consultant with Australia's international climate negotiating team. He was a convening lead author for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Second Assessment Report and is a lead author on the IPCC Third Assessment Report. In addition to his role with ABARE Dr Fisher is an Associate Commissioner with the Productivity Commission and is Adjunct Professor of Sustainable Resources Development at the University of Sydney.</p>
<p>  Mr Max Moore Wilton AC</p>
<p>Mr Moore-Wilton was appointed in December 2002 as Executive Chairman of the Sydney Airport Corporation Limited following six and a half years as Secretary of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet. Mr Moore-Wilton has had significant experience with Australia's infrastructure through a distinguished career in both the Public Service and the private sector. He has served at the senior executive level in the trade and primary industries portfolios and as General Manager of the Australian Wheat Board. He also managed the Australian National Line and was Director-General of the NSW Department of Transport. Prior to re-joining the Australian Public Service in 1996, Mr Moore-Wilton worked at the Australian Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>  Professor Henry Ergas</p>
<p>Professor Henry Ergas, Vice President, Charles River Associates, has extensive international experience advising government bodies and major corporations in Australia, New Zealand and the European Union. Prior to joining CRA, he was the founder and Managing Director of the Network Economics Consulting Group (NECG) Pty Ltd. Having spent a decade as a microeconomist at the OECD, Mr. Ergas has a strong background in the analysis of issues involving efficient resource allocation. He is also Adjunct Professor of Economics at the National University of Singapore.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
