<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3902</transcript-id>
    <title>PRIME MINISTER&#039;S WEEKLY BROADCSST - WHO ARE THE CENTRALISTS? - SUNDAY 28 SEPTEMBER 1975</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>28/09/1975</release-date>
    <release-type>Broadcast</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003902.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Embargo: 5 pia Sud-<br />
PRIME MINISTER' S WEEKLY BROADCAST<br />
IMO ARE THE CENTRALISTS?<br />
SUNDAY 28 SEPTEMBER 1975<br />
I made the point, last week that Mr Fraser is<br />
having a hard time standing up to the bullying tactics of<br />
the Country Party and some of the Premiers on the question<br />
of passing the Budget. If Mr Fraser wants to prove himself<br />
a true leader of the Opposition he must take a firm stand<br />
on this issue and put an end to the damaging and irresponsible<br />
speculation about an early election. He certainly failed that<br />
particular test in his statements this week.<br />
I mention that point again because we have seen in<br />
the past few days an even more glaring example of Mr Fraser's<br />
weakness under pressure. When it comes to matters of<br />
-principle he gives in every time to the irresponsible<br />
0 elements in the Opposition. As you know, in Melbourne this<br />
week, there was another meeting of the Constitutional<br />
Convention. The Convention first assembled two years ago<br />
to study ways of improving the Constitution and making it<br />
-a more modern and dfficient instrument in our federal system.<br />
Every Government, Federal and State, every major political<br />
party, took part in that Convention. It appointed committees<br />
to get on with the work and agreed to meet again in Melbourne<br />
this week to review the progress made. Only a month ago<br />
Mr Fraser was saying in Parliament whaat a good thing the<br />
Convention was and how strongly the Opposition supported it.<br />
0 I'll quote his actual words:<br />
" It is our hope said Mr Fraser " that this<br />
Convention will be a useful forum in which Federal<br />
and State representatives may constructively consider<br />
0 constitutional reform in a way which will advance<br />
the good government of Australia. The Constitutional<br />
Convention... . will provide a place where constructive<br />
efforts may be made to work out Constitutional reform...<br />
The Opposition is glad ~ that the Constitutional Convention<br />
will be reconvened in Melbourne in September."<br />
Fine words. And that was just a month ago. But what<br />
happened? When the Convention met on Wednesday it was<br />
boycotted by the opposition and the four non-Labor States.<br />
They didn't turn up. As soon as the Queensland Premier,<br />
Mr Bjelke-Petersen, decided in his usual way that he wouldn't<br />
take part, Mr Fraser went to water. All his lofty sentiments<br />
about " constructive efforts" and " good government" were<br />
forgotten. When the Queensland Premier decided to be<br />
obstructive, when the other non-Labor Premiers followed suit,<br />
Mr Fraser knuckled under to the Premiers and withdrew his own<br />
delegation. / 2 </p>
<p>2.<br />
It would be difficult to imagine a more craven and<br />
irresponsible attitude on the part of a national political<br />
leader. Years of work had gone into the preparation for<br />
this Convention. All the Premiers at the initial meeting<br />
two years ago were full of confidence and hope that the<br />
Convention would lead to practical reforms. Remember that<br />
the Convention has never been predominantly, or even half,<br />
a Labor Party affair. The initiative for it camne from<br />
the Victorian Parliament. The Australian* Government has<br />
never sought to dominate the proceedings and we would have<br />
been quite silly to try. We were seeking no more than a<br />
working consensus an agreed basis for constitutional reform.<br />
The States would never have taken part in the first place<br />
if they had not accepted that some reform of the Constitution<br />
was necessary. For ' tunately the Opposition boycott didn't wreck<br />
the Convention altogether. The Australian Government,<br />
the Tasmanian and South Australian Parliaments and the<br />
Territories were all represented. So too was local<br />
governmenta,-and it's here that we find the real reason<br />
for the hostility of the anti-Labor States. The Courts<br />
and Bjelke-Petersens of this world bitterly oppose<br />
the efforts of the Australian Government to make local<br />
government a full and equal partner in the Federal system.<br />
I remind you that when the Constitutional Convention was<br />
first proposed, back in 1972, 1 said in my policy speech<br />
on behalf of the Labor Party before we were even a<br />
Government that the Australian Labor Government would<br />
participate in the Convention only if local government was<br />
represented. We made that a condition and we stuck * to it.<br />
We took the view that any reform of the Constitution in which<br />
the needs of local government were ignored would be a waste<br />
of time. The Constitution as it stands doesn't even mention<br />
local governx7. ent. Would anyone drawing up the Constitution<br />
today make no mention of this vital area?<br />
It's perfectly clear that the non-Labor States want<br />
to keep local government in its present financial straightjacket.<br />
As a national Government we've done our best to give a new<br />
financial deal to local government, particularly through a<br />
generous system of direct grants, made on the basis of<br />
independent advice, which local councils can spend in any<br />
way they wish. The States have done their best to<br />
frustrate these policies and dominate local government at all<br />
costs. They talk about centralism, but the real centralists<br />
are the State Governments who want to keep local bodies as<br />
their permanent, improverished vassals.<br />
When you look at our programs you will see how much<br />
they depend on localgovernxnent cooperation and initiative.<br />
We recognise which the States do not that some things<br />
can only be done properly at, the local level. For example,<br />
our health centres and child care centres involve local<br />
communities in p~ lanning and-running these essential services.<br />
What we call the Australian Assistance Plan is a pioneering<br />
experiment in this sort of community involvement. The idea<br />
here is for local communities with my Government's financial<br />
help to seek out and meet needs for which the usual social<br />
welfare services make no provision. Our Area Improvement </p>
<p>3.<br />
Program is intended to improve the quality of life in<br />
nominated regions through projects determiined by-the people<br />
of the region. We don't want to run these local schemes.<br />
We want local councils and local groups to run them<br />
as they wish.,<br />
It's not just by boycotting the Constitutional<br />
Convention that the non-Labor States are. attacking<br />
these plans for local community activity. They have<br />
challenged our legislation for them in the High Court.<br />
On top of that, Mr Fraser has just served notice that the<br />
Liberals, if ever they got back into power, would cut<br />
back drastically tLhe grants made to the States for specific<br />
purposes. If one thing is clear from the so-called policy<br />
on federalism unveiled by the Opposition this week, it's<br />
their desire for a full-scale onslaught on local initiative,<br />
on local community projects, especially in the welfare<br />
area. I can mention any number of projects that rely on<br />
specific purpose grants from the Australian Government:<br />
child care, pre-schools, projects for aged and homeless<br />
and handicdapped and Aboriginal people, isolated children,<br />
health centres, legal aid offices, nursing homes and home<br />
nursing, meals on wheels, flying doctor and blood transfusion<br />
services. All these programs are imperilled by the. Opposition<br />
policies. In the past week Mr-Fraser has shown his utter<br />
hypocrisy over the Constitutional Convention, his indifference<br />
to the real needs of local government, and his readiness to<br />
back down whenever the Premiers stand over him in defence<br />
of their State-run centralist empires. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
