<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>10125</transcript-id>
    <title>ADDRESS TO THE INAUGURAL FULBRIGHT ORATION CELEBRATING THE 50TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE FULBRIGHT PROGRAMME THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP</title>
    <prime-minister>Howard, John</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19960311 - 20071203</period-of-service>
    <release-date>10/10/1996</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00010125.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
October 1996<br />
ADDRESS TO THE INAUGURAL FULBRIGHT ORATION<br />
CELEBRATING THE 50TH ANNIVERSARY<br />
OF THE FULBRIGHT PROGRAMME<br />
THE HON JOHN HOWARD MP<br />
E&amp; OE<br />
*** HECK AGAINST DELIVERY***<br />
"* Embargoed Until Delivery"*<br />
I am delighted to be with you this evening for this important occasion and to share in<br />
the celebration of fifty years of achievement for the Fuibright Program.<br />
There are many people here this evening who have worked over many years to help<br />
fufi the aims of the Program and many who have benefited from its generosity.<br />
I would like to join with others in conveying a very warm welcome to Mrs Harriet<br />
Fuibright. Your presence with us in Australia for this fiftieth anniversary gives us a<br />
special personal link to the founder of the Program, and I wish you a most enjoyable<br />
and productive stay in our country.<br />
The fiftieth anniversary of any organisation is an important milestone.<br />
It is a time for looking back on what has been achieved and for looking forward to<br />
what can be achieved in the years ahead.<br />
It is a time for drawing strength from the vision and the ideals of those who have gone<br />
before us as we confront the challenge of building for the future on the basis of their<br />
achievements in a very different world.<br />
In looking back tonight on fifty years of achievement for the Fulbright Program, we<br />
reflect on what one man's practical vision has achieved in advancing the interests of so<br />
many individuals and communities. We recall, in particular, the very important<br />
contribution which that one man, Senator J. William Fuibright, made to the public life<br />
of his own country, and to the cause of education and understanding between the<br />
peoples of different countries.<br />
1526 </p>
<p>The Fuibright Legacy<br />
The long political career of Senator Fuibright has always defied easy classification.<br />
He was a man of reflective intellectualism and scholarly diligence yet he was also a<br />
visible and influential advocate of change in the practical world of international<br />
politics.<br />
He was a man deeply concerned about the policies of governments in an era of the<br />
" nuclear balance of terror" yet he remained always positive and hopeful about the<br />
power of people to break down barriers of misunderstanding and distrust.<br />
He believed in the inherent value of international institutions yet he recognised the<br />
uniquely important responsibilities of the United States in the search for world order<br />
and international stability.<br />
He had strongly held views about what he saw as the limits of American power yet he<br />
was a strong internationalist and an enemy of American isolationism.<br />
As a result of his upbringing, his education and his own inclinations, he drew on the<br />
wisdom of the past yet he also revelled in exposing what he called " old myths and<br />
new realities" in international relations.<br />
He understood the realities of the international system yet he also believed in the<br />
reality of an international society, and what he saw as the need for " civilising and<br />
huxnanising" relations between people and nations.<br />
He emphasised the need for new dimensions of international cultural understanding<br />
yet he saw it as unrealistic and undesirable to aim for universal values, arguing ( in his<br />
words) that " the rapprochement of people is only possible when differences of culture<br />
and outlook are respected and appreciated rather than feared or condemned".<br />
He once championed Presidential power as the source of any effective American<br />
foreign policy yet his later career highlighted what he believed should be the<br />
Congressional limits on that power.<br />
He knew the creative and constructive opportunities that political power bestowed on<br />
elected leaders yet he never ceased warning about the proper limits of government<br />
and the potential for power to create its own arrogance.<br />
He was at the heart of the great American debates over policymnaking during the Cold<br />
War yet he became, in effect, one of the earliest and most articulate spokesmen for<br />
many who belonged to the first post-Cold War generation.<br />
He was a man without pretensions yet he is one of those very few people in history<br />
whose name has also become a proper noun, as thousands of Fulbrighters around the<br />
world will attest! 1527. </p>
<p>The career of Senator Fuibright was certainly one of contrasts. It was also one of<br />
achievement and endurance.<br />
In 1939, he became the youngest University President in the United States. He was<br />
the first American Rhodes Scholar to be elected to the US Senate. He was Chairman<br />
of the influential Senate Foreign Relations Committee for fifteen years. And he was<br />
returned by the electors of Arkansas as one of their representatives in the Congress for<br />
thirty two consecutive years from the 1940' s to the 1970' s.<br />
Throughout that period, Senator Fulbright became involved in an extraordinarily wide<br />
range of foreign policy issues.<br />
Those issues included the management of new international structures for enhancing<br />
security and co-operation; the definition of " national interest" and the changing nature<br />
of " national power" in an era of rapid international change; the appropriate balance<br />
between America's international aspirations and its limited national resources, between<br />
its global responsibilities and its domestic priorities; the revolutionary potential of<br />
endemic poverty, nationalism and population growth in developing countries; and the<br />
need to build bridges of co-operation and understanding between the American people<br />
and the peoples of other countries through trade, scientific and cultural exchanges.<br />
The debate over many of these issues, of course, continues today though in a very<br />
diferent context to that of Senator Fulbright's time.<br />
Some of Senator Fuibright's views were a focus of passionate support as well as<br />
vigorous dispute. But the distinguishing mark of all of them was that they were<br />
presented by him with forthrightness, personal integrity and a commitment to the<br />
principles in which he believed. They were all underpinned by his faith in the power of<br />
ideas and in the common aspirations that he strongly believed all people shared.<br />
He had a clear vision of the role of creative leadership, liberal education and<br />
international understanding in helping to build a more peaceful world.<br />
It is that vision which has endured and which lives on in the scholarship program that<br />
bears his name.<br />
It is that vision, and its important future role in a rapidly changing world, which we<br />
celebrate tonight.<br />
The Constructive Internationalism of the Fulbright Prora<br />
What motivated the establishment of the Fulbright Program, and what has sustained<br />
and strengthened it during its first half century, has been its commitment to a<br />
constructive internationalism built on direct educational and cultural links between the<br />
people of different countries.<br />
1528 </p>
<p>It was the same constructive internationalism that had inspired the passage into law in<br />
1943 ( three years before the establishment of the Scholarship program) of the<br />
' Fuibright Resolution', committing the United States to support a post-war<br />
international organisation to maintain peace, and thus pre-empting any move to postwar<br />
American isolationism.<br />
It was that motivation and spirit which were again clear in 1946 when Senator<br />
Fulbright secured the passage through Congress of his Bill to convert the sale of<br />
surplus American war property abroad into a major student exchange program. It was<br />
an initiative he had launched the year before, just two weeks after the dropping of the<br />
atomic bomb on Hiroshima. And it was to be described by President Kennedy some<br />
fifteen years later as " the classic modern example of beating swords into<br />
ploughshares". Senator Fuibright saw this exchange program as an important catalyst in the search for<br />
a new constructive internationalism that could contribute to the avoidance of war in<br />
the atomic age. But he also understood the limits of any such programme, once<br />
describing it as " not a panacea but an avenue of hope".<br />
The purposes of the Scholarships have been described in countless ways over the past<br />
fifty years. But, not surprisingly, the best description comes from Senator Fulbright<br />
himself when he reflected on them in later life in the following terms:<br />
" There is nothing obscure about the objective of educational exchange. Its<br />
purpose is to acquaint Americans with the world as it is and to acquaint students and<br />
scholars from many lands with America as it is not as we wish it were or as we might<br />
wish foreigners to see it, but exactly as it is which by my reckoning is an ' image' of<br />
which no America need be ashamed. The program further aims to make the benefits of<br />
American culture and technology available to the world and to enrich American life by<br />
exposing it to the science and art of many societies. Finally, the program aims,<br />
through these means, to bring a little more knowledge, a little more reason, and a little<br />
more compassion into world affairs and thereby to increase the chance that nations will<br />
learn at last to live in peace and friendship."<br />
In its fifty years of operation, the Fulbright Program has fulfilled these high ideals of<br />
fostering leadership, learning and empathy between cultures.<br />
Approximately 200,000 individuals including 70,000 Americans and 130,000 from<br />
t other countries have participated in the Program since its establishment in 1946.<br />
3 Over 140 countries are currently involved in the program with participants including a<br />
wide range of graduate students, scholars and professionals from outside of academia.<br />
Those who have benefited from the Fulbright Program have contributed to their<br />
societies not only in the field of public leadership but also in the sciences, the arts,<br />
education, literature, business, the media, community support and many other areas of<br />
activity. Some have done so prominently and spectacularly. Countless others have<br />
done so without as much public acclamation but with no less effectiveness in making<br />
their communities better and fairer places in which to live. 1529 </p>
<p>The Fuibright exchange program between Australia and the United States began in<br />
1949 and since 1963 it has continued under the auspices of the Australian-American<br />
Educational Foundation. Over 4,000 Australians and Americans have benefited from<br />
the opportunity which the Fuibright Program has provided for study and exchange in<br />
each of our countries.<br />
I am proud to be Honorary Co-Chairman of the Foundation, and I am proud of the<br />
Australian Government's ongoing financial support for the Scholarship scheme.<br />
The Fulbright Program's Next Fifty Years<br />
In looking to the next fifty years of the Fulbright Program, we can be confidlent that its<br />
aims and ideals have never been more relevant.<br />
In a bilateral sense, the place of the Fuibright Program in the broader architecture of<br />
Australia-United States relations will be an increasingly important one.<br />
Australians and Americans share rare ties of history, language and culture. We are<br />
united by common values and beliefs including our commitment to freedom,<br />
democratic rights and equality of opportunity. The Fulbright Program reflects many of<br />
our mutual characteristics as relatively young countries, including the value we place<br />
on openness, vitality and innovation.<br />
The relationship between our two countries is bound together by close and effective<br />
interaction between our goverrnents and our private sector enterprises and this is<br />
evident across a very broad range of political, security, commercial and cultural<br />
activities. At a government-to-government level, the range of interaction between Australia and<br />
the United States is diverse and mutually advantageous. My Goverrnent has made it<br />
explicity clear that we aim to reinvigorate and strengthen our relations with United<br />
States in the future.<br />
I know it has become fashionable in some quarters to categorise alliance relationships,<br />
such as Australia's with the United States, as anachronistic in the post-Cold War<br />
world. That perception is, in my view, totally mistaken.<br />
Alliances are as important in times of great change as they are in periods of direct<br />
strategic threat. The Australia-America alliance contributes as much today as it has<br />
ever done to peace, security and stability and we will be working to expand that<br />
contribution even further in the future.<br />
Nor does alliance co-operation, particularly between two such vigorous and open<br />
democracies as the United States and Australia, entail any diminution of sovereignty or<br />
independence on the part of either.<br />
1530<br />
U </p>
<p>6<br />
We will have differences on specific issues as we have had in the past. We will<br />
convey those differences forcefully and unambiguously in support of our national<br />
interests where the need arises. But we will do so in the broader context of a bilateral<br />
relationship that is strong, enduring and clearly in the national interest of both our<br />
countries. Just as we have fundamentally significant economic and security ties with the United<br />
States, we also have dynamic economic opportunities, strategic interests and strong<br />
bilateral relationships in Asia.<br />
As I have made clear on many occasions, my Government does not see any choice to<br />
be made in Australian foreign policy between our past associations and our future<br />
hopes, between our history and our geography.<br />
Nor do we see any choice to be made between strengthening our engagement with<br />
Asia and reinvigorating our relationship with the United States.<br />
Under my Government Australia can, and will, do both.<br />
The bilateral government-to-goverrnent links between Australia and the United States<br />
to which I have been referring work most effectively in the context of strong peopleto-<br />
people associations. And it is those associations which add an important and<br />
enduring quality to the nature of the Australian-American relationship.<br />
For an older generation, there are the special ties of history between Australians and<br />
Americans which were forged during and after the Second World War. For younger<br />
Australians and Americans, there are the special associations developed as a result of<br />
the expanding scale of two-way business and tourism between our two countries and<br />
the accelerating pace of educational, technological and cultural exchanges to which the<br />
Fulbright Program adds such a significant dimension.<br />
It is also cultural links at a popular level that are increasingly opening up our two<br />
societies to each other through films, music, creative art, the Internet, and much<br />
more.<br />
It is these direct links between Australians and Americans that provide such critical<br />
sustenance and support to the official ties between our governments. And it is in those<br />
links that the realisation of the Fulbright vision of understanding, mutual respect and<br />
shared common purposes can be advanced.<br />
The future relevance of the Fulbright Program, of course, extends well beyond the<br />
bounds of the Australia-America relationship. It is a Program that is well-attuned to<br />
what will be powerfidi forces of international change into the next century.<br />
The realities of globalisation and economic interdependence are the product of the<br />
revolutions in transportation, communications, technology and commerce, as well as<br />
political will., that have transformed the nature of policymaking between, as well as<br />
within, nations. </p>
<p>And as part of these processes of change, the Fulbright vision for better understanding<br />
between different cultures and for broader areas of co-operation will have an<br />
increasing relevance.<br />
Another great driving force of international change in the late twentieth century is the<br />
economic dynamism and the developing regional architecture of the Asia-Pacific<br />
region. This regional economic revolution has transformed the Asia-Pacific as well as its<br />
relationships with the rest of the world. It has created changes of an order which, in<br />
my lifetime, have been surpassed only by the implosion of communism.<br />
For both the United States and Australia, the nature of our interactions with the Asia-<br />
Pacific region as well as our strategies for broadening and deepening them lie at the<br />
forefront of policymnaking in both our countries.<br />
More than ever in the years ahead, the Fulbright vision for more extensive educational<br />
exchanges, for better cultural understanding and for wider horizons of co-operation<br />
will have a special significance in relations between the United States and Asia, just as<br />
they will in terms of Australia's relations with the region.<br />
Ma-xdmising Opportunities In. and With. Asia<br />
Against this background, I wish to make some brief comments about the nature of the<br />
emerging challenges and opportunities for Australian and American policy in<br />
development of closer interaction with our region.<br />
No region will be more important to world prosperity and stability in the twenty-first<br />
century than the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
It includes three of the world's most politically and economically influential countries<br />
the United States, Japan and China. The futures of those countries, and their<br />
interaction with each other, will be critical for the region and the wider world.<br />
Inevitably, the relationship among these countries is changing as they themselves<br />
change. The scale of change in China in particular is immense. Growth in China has<br />
averaged ten per cent for more than a decade. This stands to change the relativities of<br />
power in the region. But China's opening up and its growth are indisputably positive<br />
developments. They provide new economic opportunities for others. They also provide<br />
China with a stake in the stability of the region and in the effectiveness of regional and<br />
global political and economic structures.<br />
My Government is strongly committed to engagement with China. In particular, I think<br />
China's entry into the World Trade Organisation is important and I hope that it can be<br />
achieved in the near future on reasonable terms for all concerned. More broadly, the<br />
management of the relationship among the United States, Japan and China is of the<br />
utmost importance for the stability and prosperity of the region.<br />
1532 </p>
<p>The Asia-Pacific region is already a global economic powerhouse, and it is likely to<br />
become even more significant in the world economy over coming decades.<br />
In terms of the separate national perspectives of both the United States and Australia<br />
on these regional economic realities, the facts speak for themselves.<br />
Already, one third of US exports go to East Asian markets, representing over two<br />
million American jobs. US projections have put Asia, even excluding Japan, as the<br />
United States' largest export market by 2010.<br />
For Australia, there are comparable realities.<br />
We are far more closely integrated economically with the Asia-Pacific regiQn than with<br />
any other part of the world. Two thirds of our exports go there and more than half<br />
go to East Asia. Nine of Australia's top ten export markets are in the Asia-Pacific<br />
region, with seven in East Asia.<br />
What happens in, and with, the Asia-Pacific region will clearly shape and influence<br />
Australia's destiny.<br />
Consistent policies over many years have enabled Australia to become an integral<br />
member of the Asia-Pacific community and an important political and economic<br />
partner of individual regional countries.<br />
That outcome has been achieved by the work of many Australian Governments, both<br />
Coalition and Labor. I acknowledge the contributions made by all of them, and my<br />
Government is committed to building further on their achievements.<br />
This continuity of Australian policy towards the Asia-Pacific region was one of the key<br />
messages I conveyed during my recent visits to Japan and Indonesia and it was one<br />
which I believe was well understood and appreciated. As a new Government, we will<br />
inevitably do some things differently and we will have some different regional policy<br />
emphases that is only natural and to be expected. But we intend to be, as the Prime<br />
Minister of Japan Mr Hashimoto reaffirmed recently in Tokyo, an " indispensable<br />
partner" for our neighbours and friends in our part of the world.<br />
Our links with the countries of our region have implications which go beyond mutual<br />
bilateral advantage. They contribute to a strengthening network of regional<br />
associations. They also add value to our relationship with the United States, just as<br />
our relationship with the United States contributes importantly to our region.<br />
We believe that the active engagement of the United States is vital to the continued<br />
economic growth of the Asia-Pacific region, to trade and investment as well as to<br />
regional strategic stability. </p>
<p>Recent reminders of the ongoing US commitment to a leadership role in the Asia-<br />
Pacific region have been an important reaffirmation of America's continuing role in<br />
support of regional stability and prosperity. They reflect the importance of the region<br />
economically and strategically to the United States and they are very welcome to us in<br />
Australia. I am thinking of the signature earlier this year by President Clinton and Japanese Prime<br />
Minister Hashimoto of the Joint Declaration of Security. I am also thinking of the<br />
reaffirmation of ANZUS at the recent Australia/ United States ministerial talks held in<br />
Sydney, with the unprecedented attendance by the US Secretary of State, the Secretary<br />
of Defense and the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.<br />
I am also thinking of the extent of America's economic engagement with the Asia-<br />
Pacific region.<br />
The United States plays a vital role in the economy of the region as a source of capital<br />
flows to fund the vast infrastructure needs of the region, as a supplier of technology<br />
and as a market. The United States is the largest single market for ASEAN.<br />
The American commitment to APEC is also fu~ ndamentally important in both regional<br />
and global terms. APEC's iberalisation and co-operation agenda will be critical in<br />
ensuring that the region reaches its fuill economic potential. The commitment of APEC<br />
countries to liberalisation can also be a powerful force against pressures to protect<br />
markets elsewhere in the world. APEC can be an important force in helping to<br />
maintain momentum for ftirther trade and investment liberalisation both regionally and<br />
globally under the World Trade Organisation.<br />
I am very much looking forward to discussing these and other aspects of American<br />
regional policy with another son of Arkansas, President Bill Clinton, when he visits<br />
Australia next month-He will be assured of a very warm welcome to this country.<br />
As for Australian regional policy, the purposes and goals of my Government are clear.<br />
We have stated from the outset our profound commitment to the priority of<br />
engagement with the Asia-Pacific region. This is the region with which Australia's<br />
economic and strategic prospects are most immediately involved. This is the region in<br />
which Australia needs to succeed and my Governmnent is determined to equip Australia<br />
for such success.<br />
We aim to facilitate the development of dynamic, exciting and expanding networks of<br />
regional interaction in trade and commerce, in security<br />
co-operation, in cultural and educational ties, and in people-to-people links.<br />
We aim to develop strong regional relationships as well as to pursue Australia's<br />
regional interests.<br />
We aim to do so in a way that embodies vitality, dynamism and innovation in opening<br />
up new areas of regional co-operation. We also aim to do so in a way that reflects<br />
pride in our national values and institutions.<br />
1534____ </p>
<p>U It is governments which co-operatively set the tone and provide the lead in terms of<br />
developing regional relationships.<br />
My Government will continue to do so with our regional partners in terms of building<br />
strong political links, maximising two-way trade and investment opportunities and<br />
developing regional security co-operation.<br />
We will also continue to do so in seeking to enhance the scope for direct people-topeople<br />
links and in reaffirming in the strongest terms our commitment to Australia's<br />
racially non-discriminatory immigration policy which has made us a stronger, richer<br />
and more diverse nation an issue to which I will return later.<br />
We are committed, as a Government, to accelerating the scope and pace of our<br />
interaction with the countries of the Asia-Pacific region and to doing so in a way which<br />
mutually respects our individual national priorities, traditions and attitudes.<br />
We aim to expand through global, regional and bilateral channels Australia's current<br />
level and range of trading and investment interests in Asia and the Pacific.<br />
Australia supplies nearly half of East Asia's coal, iron ore and beef, as well as over half<br />
its wool and alumina. We are a growing source of manufactures and services to East<br />
Asia especially through small and medium size enterprises. And yet over recent<br />
years, we have barely kept pace with the dynamic growth in regional markets.<br />
Although the value of our regional exports is increasing, our share of key regional<br />
markets over recent years has been declining.<br />
We have opportunities across the board not just in traditional areas such as food<br />
supplies and raw materials but also in services generally in education, in tourism, in<br />
medicine, in finance, in processed food, in manufacturing, in construction, in science<br />
and technology, in transport : in fact, across the full range of our resources and valueadding<br />
industries.<br />
Australian exports have made important inroads in most of those areas over the past<br />
decade or more. But in terms of what we are capable, I believe we have only<br />
scratched the surface of our full potential in many areas.<br />
My Government has a clear vision of Australian possibilities in, and with, Asia. But<br />
rhetoric alone will not be enough to make it happen. Nor is a hopeful faith in<br />
geographic proximity to an economically dynamic region sufficient to ensure that our<br />
national potential is realised.<br />
What my Government is committed to is a practical strategy to fulffl our regional<br />
potential.<br />
That potential will only be unlocked when we address the inefficiencies in our own<br />
national economic infrastructure and when we develop, in the Fuibright tradition,<br />
patterns of interaction that will enhance personal contacts and cultural understanding. 1535 </p>
<p>I1I<br />
That is why, as a nation, we need to pursue policies of fiscal responsibility. It is why<br />
we need to tackle our foreign debt and current account problems. It is why we need to<br />
lift our level of national savings. It is why we need to reform our arthritic labour<br />
market system. It is why we need to pursue the essential task of microeconomic<br />
reform in our transport and communications sectors.<br />
Our actions since our election in March confirm the fact that these are all clear<br />
priorities for the Australian Government.<br />
Australia also needs to continue to work with our regional partners in taking the<br />
APEC trade liberalisation process forward.<br />
We must encourage other regional economies to match the significant liberalisation<br />
already undertaken in Australia.<br />
With tariff levels now at five per cent or below for all sectors except passenger motor<br />
vehicles, textiles, clothing and footwear, sugar and cheese Australia has already moved<br />
a long way towards the Bogor targets of free trade and investment.<br />
Australia's regional trading partners have taken some significant steps. ASEAN<br />
countries, for example, have cut applied tariffs on a trade-weighted average by about<br />
two-thirds between 1988 and 1995. China's average tariff rate has come down from<br />
per cent in 1988 to below 20 per cent in 1995. Japanese and Korean markets in citrus<br />
fruit, beef and rice are more open than they were.<br />
But Australian exporters of manufactures still face some very high tariff peaks in the<br />
region. For example some on cars are as high as 200 per cent. Australian agricultural<br />
and food exporters still face tariffs and other barriers, such as monopoly or state<br />
importing arrangements. Our exports of legal and financial services are often<br />
obstructed by regulatory barriers.<br />
The value of APEC is that by liberalising in concert the benefits are maximised. For<br />
this to work effectively, everyone must contribute.<br />
We will use every avenue not only APEC but also the World Trade Organisation,<br />
other regional associations and bilateral links to ensure that access barriers are<br />
reduced and opportunities created for our exporters.<br />
We need to pursue other priorities as well if Australia is to realise its full potential for<br />
regional interaction.<br />
We need innovative co-operation between government and industry on regional trade<br />
strategies, such as the " Supermarket to Asia" strategy which we launched recently.<br />
We need a reform program that will make Australia an even better place from which to<br />
do business with Asia_<br />
And we need expanded people-to-people links with regional countries.<br />
1536 </p>
<p>All these priorities are fundamental if Australia is to compete effectively and engage<br />
expansively in the Asia-Pacific region.<br />
And they are all key priorities for the Australian Government.<br />
In addition to our trade and commercial interests, we aim to enhance Australia's<br />
security interests in, and with, the region.<br />
Australia makes an important contribution to regional stability because of our strong<br />
and professional defence force, our alliance with the United States, our active<br />
diplomacy, and our close defence links with other regional countries. My Government<br />
aims to strengthen each of these four elements of our regional security policy.<br />
Our aims in the Asia-Pacific region go beyond, and supplement, our trade and security<br />
objectives. Those aims also relate to enhancing the direct people-to-people links<br />
between regional countries.<br />
Immigration has played an important direct role in developing those links. In that<br />
context, it is important to re-emphasise the non-discriminatory character of Australia's<br />
immigration programme to which the Australian Government is unequivocally<br />
committed.<br />
There is certainly room for open and vigorous debate about the size and composition<br />
of Australia's migrant intake provided that such debate is against the background of a<br />
bipartisan commitment to a non-dscriminatory policy.<br />
A wide range of independent contact between Australia and the countries of our region<br />
has been developing. We see this especially in the growing links between Australian<br />
chambers of comnmerce, professional associations, cities, schools, universities and<br />
community groups, and equivalent bodies in many regional countries.<br />
This range of contact is very much related to the Fuibright vision of enhanced cultural<br />
understanding, and as a government we intend to encourage it as much as we can.<br />
Tourism, of course, is an obvious example. 783,000 Japanese tourists visited Australia<br />
in 1995. 77,000 Australians visited Japan, and nearly 300,000 visited Indonesia.<br />
We have many Australians able to contribute with special language, cultural and trade<br />
expertise, as well as through famiily and other personal ties, in developing Australia's<br />
business, cultural and other relations with Asia.<br />
And we have great potential to build on those resources in the future through Asian<br />
language training in our schools and through greater awareness within our wider<br />
community of the scope for regional interaction.<br />
We also have a great opportunity to develop the extensive educational links that have<br />
already been built up throughout the region. For example, there are now nearly 70,000<br />
students from Asia studying in Australia, representing around eighty per cent of all<br />
foreign students here. Nearly 200,000 people living in East Asia have been educated in<br />
1532 w ct </p>
<p>1538 13<br />
Australian universities since the beginning of the Colombo Plan in 1950. And more<br />
young Australians are now studying in Asia each year.<br />
These are critically important personal ties which we aim to further encourage and<br />
develop. They are also ties that relate directly to the high ambitions of the Fuibright<br />
Program for broader and for more direct contact between the peoples of different<br />
countries. Conclusion Senator William Fuibright was a proud American. He was also, in a very real sense, a<br />
citizen of the world.<br />
Tonight, we honour his service to public life in the United States. We celebrate the<br />
world-wide achievements over fifty years of the educational exchange program which<br />
he initiated. And we recognise the ongoing relevance of his vision in a world that is<br />
very different to the one he knew and in which relations between nations, regions and<br />
people are changing very rapidly.<br />
But above all, we celebrate tonight the power of an idea: the idea that through direct<br />
exchanges between the people of different countries and through direct experience of<br />
different cultures, people around the world could learn to focus more on the things that<br />
unite them than those that divide them and so make the world a better and safer<br />
place. Senator Fulbright once described the pattern of international educational exchanges<br />
which he initiated as " a modest program with an immodest aim" f.<br />
He knew its idealism. He recognised the dificulties it faced. But he never lost faith in<br />
its constructive power and nor should we. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
