<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>670</transcript-id>
    <title>INAUGURAL  JOHN STOREY MEMORIAL LECTURE PROBLEMS OF MANGEMENT IN A  FEDERATION ADDRESS BY THE PRIME MINISTER ( THE RT. HON. R.G. MENZIES. C.H.Q.C.M.P )  THE WILSON HALL UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE. MELBOURNE  SATURDAY, 8TH DECEMBER, 1962</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>08/12/1962</release-date>
    <release-type>Speech</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000670.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
62/ 153<br />
INAUGURAL<br />
JOHN STOREY MEMORIAL LECTURE<br />
PROBLEMS OF MANAGEMENT IN A FEDERATION<br />
ADDRESS by<br />
The Prime Minister ( The Rt. Hon. R. G. Menzies, C. Hr, M. P.)<br />
The Wilson Hall, University of Melbourne, Melbourne,<br />
Saturday, 8th December, 1962. </p>
<p>THE JOHN STOREY MEMORIAL LECTURE<br />
PROBLEMS OF MANAGEMENT IN A FEDERATION<br />
It was my great privilege to see a great deal of John Storey.<br />
Every time I saw and had discussions with him, I became more and more<br />
fascinated by a complex but arresting and lovable personality. As this<br />
is the first Memorial Lecture to be associated with his name, I think it<br />
proper that I should devote a little time to saying something about him,<br />
I am doubly privileged to be able to do so in the presence of Lady Storey<br />
and members of her family. They indeed have proud memories.<br />
John Storey was the son of a celebrated Labour Premier of New<br />
South Wales. This, no doubt, helps to explain his deep underlying instinct<br />
for public service, though John himself was, as he used to say to me somewhat<br />
proudly, no politician. I understood this. It would have been<br />
difficult to imagine him wooing the electors with attractive generalisations<br />
or submitting himself to the necessary but chafing disciplines of Party<br />
organisation. He was too much of an individual for that. The things he<br />
believed in, he believed in most deeply; he was not willing to see them<br />
watered down by that process of compromise which is, whether we like it or<br />
not, of the essence of practical politics.<br />
After all, the art of politics is that of achieving the attainable,<br />
not of seeking vainly to achieve perfection in one stroke. To take<br />
a few steps forward in what they believe to be the right direction is all<br />
that most political leaders may hope for. Before a Prime Minister goes<br />
into his Cabinet room, he must do his best by thought and study to establish<br />
in his own mind what he thinks to be the right course to follow on some<br />
matter put forward in a Cabinet Submission. He must then, if it becomes<br />
necessary, set out to persuade his colleagues, not to dragoon them. For<br />
men of talent and experience have their own ideas and will not be content<br />
to be rubber stamps for the ideas of others. In the long run, there<br />
emerges from the Cabinet discussion a joint view which is, not infrequently,<br />
a modified and adjusted view. If this is to find legislative expression,<br />
it must be presented to, and accepted by the Government Parliamentary Party<br />
or Parties. It then runs the gamut of Parliamentary debate, with public<br />
opinion expressing itself through the newspapers and otherwise and with<br />
the next election casting its perpetual shadow from ahead. In the working<br />
world of Parliamentary democracy, there can be no perfectionism if things<br />
are to be done. But my friend John Storey was, in essence, a perfectionist.<br />
He honoured me with his warm and sympathetic friendship; but I must have<br />
disappointed him many times. He had a natural capacity for aggression in<br />
what he saw to be a good cause. I shall never forget that in December, </p>
<p>2<br />
1940, and early in 1941 he then, as a very distinguished production<br />
engineer, being at the Beaufort Aircraft production venture he travelled<br />
with me through the Middle East and to England. He was determined about<br />
the things that we needed for our war effort and was the last person to<br />
take " No" too easily for an answer. I will give you two illustrations.<br />
We went together one day to see Lord Beaverbrook, who was then<br />
at the Ministry of Aircraft Production, and whose dominating personality<br />
some of you may have encountered. We wanted to secure, on the aircraft<br />
side, certain provision for Australia. Beaverbrook was disposed to brush<br />
us off. In the course of the brushing off, he would suddenly seize one<br />
of the various telephones on his table and bark some orders to one or other<br />
of his subordinates. At a certain stage, he sent for one of them and put<br />
to him a question which related to our business. The subordinate, taken<br />
on the hop, made a rather obscure and unsatisfying reply. Beaverbrook<br />
told him what he thought of him in what might be called measured or<br />
unmeasured terms, according to the point of view. John Storey, sitting<br />
next to me, had been a little dejected up to this point, but when he listened<br />
to the flow of language he brightened up at once and said, " Ah, Lord Beaverbrook.<br />
Now I see that I can talk to you in good, plain terms, including a<br />
few good Australian terms, and I want to tell you exactly what I think about<br />
your attitude on this matter." From that time on, it was a superb exchange<br />
so superbly managed by John Storey himself, that we ultimately got what we<br />
asked for. The other incident was when we were visiting the works of an<br />
electrical firm which was making revolving turrets for the Beaufort. There<br />
had been some considerable hold-up and John was, very naturally, irritated<br />
by it. He was therefore relieved to be shown a series of these turrets,<br />
complete or almost complete, shortly to be shipped to Australia. You can<br />
imagine the fun when the Managing Director, not knowing John Storey as I<br />
did, said to him towards the end, " You know, I would be very grateful to<br />
you if you would allow us to divert these turrets to another project. We<br />
will, of course, when we can, make another series for you." Well, John<br />
hit the roof. His eloquence on that occasion I shall never forget. The<br />
turrets almost revolved involuntarily under the blast. But it paid off.<br />
We got the turrets and John achieved, as he did in many places and on many<br />
occasions during that memorable journey, the profound respect of the people<br />
with whom he was dealing.<br />
The point about these reminiscences of mine is that John Storey<br />
was a patriot in the highest sense of the word. He didn't regard patriotism<br />
as a mild sentiment. He was engaged on responsible duties for his country<br />
at the time of which I am speaking. He had no instinct for high-falutin'<br />
or for mealy-mouthed sentiment. Patriotism required that you got the very<br />
best thing that you could for your country and got it as quickly as you could. </p>
<p>: 3<br />
When somebody sits down to the historical task of examining<br />
the contributions made by various men to the Australian war effort in the<br />
Second World War, the name of John Storey will be a very great and honoured<br />
one. Now, I said at the beginning that the political problems<br />
frequently escaped him. This, of course, merely exhibited, in the old<br />
phrase, a defect of his great quality. He wanted to get things done.<br />
He saw quite clearly in a practical sense how they ought to be done. He<br />
chafed at the intervention of any technical or constitutional consideration<br />
which might interfere with the project. This is something that I have not<br />
uncommonly found among men of great eminence in the business world. In<br />
running their own business, they find that once they have arrived at a<br />
decision, little will stand in the way of carrying out that decision, provided<br />
they are firm and clear and decisive. At least, so I am given to<br />
understand. But the politician has an entirely different task. Because<br />
of its very nature, it is not frequently understood outside the arena of<br />
politics. Let me explain to you something of what I mean. In Australia<br />
we live and work under a Federal system. We have a written Constitution.<br />
There is a Commonwealth Parliament with particular and specified powers.<br />
There are State Parliaments, exercising the residue of power. There are<br />
some constitutional restrictions applying to both. Where there is any<br />
question of conflict between Commonwealth authority and State authority,<br />
where there is any question of the validity of a Commonwealth law or of<br />
some Commonwealth action, we have a High Court to determine the matter.<br />
It was once said by a brilliant nineteenth-century constitutional commentator<br />
that Federalism is legalism and that there is no escape from that<br />
fact. On one occasion, not so long ago, in the Basic Wage Inquiry of<br />
1949-. 50, one Judge, in supporting an Award which advocates had opposed as<br />
in its nature inflationary, took the opportunity of saying, " I shall be<br />
concerned with the fact that an increase in the basic wage which will<br />
inevitably permeate the whole wage structure will increase prices and so<br />
add its modicum of inflationary pressure, but inflation and its control<br />
are matters for the Government...."<br />
Now this last remark was quite wrong. It is a common error<br />
to suppose that the Commonwealth Parliament has complete power to do what<br />
needs to be done to build up the economy of the nation, to avoid inflationary<br />
pressures, to regulate life so that everybody may have a job and so that<br />
everybody's standard of living may steadily and inevitably rise. These are<br />
great ideals. The Commonwealth Parliament has certain very considerable<br />
powers in the direction of achieving them, but it has by no meons complete<br />
power, as I will shortly demonstrate. You may say, " Well, it ought to have </p>
<p>4<br />
complete powers". Unfortunately, or fortunately, as the case may be, the<br />
people of Australia when put to the test, do not agree with you. The most<br />
difficult thing in the world is to pass a Constitutional referendum in<br />
Australia which would result in adding to the powers of the Commonwealth<br />
Parliament. We know this from long experience. I am not saying that the<br />
instinct as such is an unhealthy one. I am, myself, a Federalist. I<br />
don't wish to see unification in Australia. I don't wish to see all powers<br />
concentrated in Canberra. I think that the functions of the States are<br />
of great importance and that the division of power under a Federal syptem<br />
has a considerable relevance to the preservation of individual liberties<br />
in the community. At the same time, as a Prime Minister of long standing,<br />
I can assure you that not infrequently I have been tempted to wish that I<br />
could put my Federal principles on one side and by a stroke of the pen arm<br />
the central government with power to deal with a number of matters falling<br />
within the overall economic picture. But I have resisted the temptation.<br />
Tonight, it is not my object to promote an argument about<br />
Constitutional alteration. What I want to do is to state and explain<br />
the position as it is.<br />
What are the economic powers of the Commonwealth Parliament<br />
and Government? If I run quickly through Section 51 and some later sections<br />
of the Commonwealth Constitution you will begin to appreciate the answer.<br />
I will begin with the sub-sections of Section 51, giving<br />
specific powers to the Commonwealth; the residue of powers, of course,<br />
remaining with the States.<br />
" Trade and commerce with other countries, and among the States".<br />
This power, limited in itself because it does not include<br />
intra-state trade, or domestic trade within the boundaries<br />
of a State, is further limited by Section 92, and by Section<br />
99, to which I will refer later. Section 92 contains the<br />
famous provision, which has produced an enormous quantity of<br />
litigation, that " on the imposition of uniform duties of<br />
customs, trade, commerce, and intercourse among the States....<br />
shall be absolutely free". It would be idle, in anything<br />
other than a legal treatise, to follow the various streams of<br />
judicial decision on these words. At one stage the then High<br />
Court held that these words did not control the Commonwealth,<br />
but imposed limitdtions solely upon State powers. That<br />
decision has long since been authoritatively overruled.<br />
Section 92 controls the Commonwealth. </p>
<p>Various counsel, including myself, vainly argued at one<br />
stage that Section 92 merely prohibited customs barriers;<br />
the object of the draftsmen of the Constitution being to<br />
get rid of the " border barbarisms" which it was one of<br />
the objects of federation to remove. But, over the years,<br />
Section 92 has been given a much wider interpretation, an<br />
interpretation which put at risk stabilisation and orderly<br />
marketing schemes which have become such a significant<br />
element in the handling of the products of some great<br />
export primary industries.<br />
In 1937, during the term of the Lyons Government, I was, as<br />
Commonwealth Attorney-General, in charge of a referendum campaign to secure<br />
approval for a Constitutional change to meet this position. The proposed<br />
amendment was " 92A. The provisions of the last preceding section shall<br />
not apply to laws with respect to marketing made by, or under<br />
the authority of, the Parliament in the exercise of any Powers<br />
vested in the Parliament by this Constitution."<br />
It was roundly defeated. At the subsequent election in 1937 I went nearer<br />
to defeat in Kooyong than I have ever been.<br />
In the result, such orderly marketing schemes as we have had<br />
have been worked out by a combination of Federal and State action, which,<br />
for practical political reasons, is not always easy to achieve. All sorts<br />
of technical difficulties have to be guarded against as well as possible.<br />
No broad policy in relation to the primary industries can ever be worked<br />
out or declared on purely economic grounds; the complexities of constitutional<br />
power must always be investigated, and a compromise solution<br />
is generally the result.<br />
Subsection ( ii) of Section 51 creates Commonwealth power over<br />
" Taxation; but so as not to discriminate between States or parts of States."<br />
This has to be read in conjunction with Section 99 which provides that<br />
" The Commonwealth shall not, by any law or regulation of trade, commerce,<br />
or revenue, give preference to one State or any part thereof over another<br />
State or any part thereof."<br />
These provisions, which sharply limit the flexibility of<br />
Commonwealth economic policy and place difficulties in the way of applying<br />
special measures designed to aid the development of some of the potentially<br />
rich but relatively under-developed areas of Australia, were of course the<br />
result of the inevitable compromises that had to be made in the nineties<br />
in order to convert six self-governing colonies into a federated nation.<br />
State sentiment is even today still so strong that amendments to these </p>
<p>6<br />
constitutional provisions would ( I think!), be unlikely to succeed. Nor,<br />
indeed would it be easy for a Federalist like myself to devise or support<br />
them. I repeat that it is not my present purpose to promote any argument<br />
about Constitutional amendment. All I want to do is to note the effect<br />
of the present constitutional division of powers on the Commonwealth's<br />
economic authority and responsibility.<br />
Whenever most people ( including, I imagine, most of my listeners<br />
tonight) say of any problem of importance, " Why doesn't the Government do<br />
something about they usually mean the Commonwealth Government. Most<br />
of them, when they are in this mood, passing the responsibility to the<br />
Commonwealth, appear to believe that the Commonwealth has full power to<br />
discharge the responsibility.<br />
It is my purpose tonight to explain that this is something of<br />
an illusion. The two limiting provisions I have just mentioned have rendered<br />
necessary a series of devices, which I will briefly mention. But meanwhile<br />
I return to Section 51.<br />
Subsection ( iii) creates Commonwealth power over " Bounties on<br />
the production or export of goods. but so that such bounties shall be<br />
uniform throughout the Commonwealth."<br />
This bounties power, like the power over customs and excise,<br />
is made exclusive to the Commonwealth by Section 90 of the Constitution,<br />
but in each case Commonwealth legislation is subject to the condition of<br />
uniformity. I would only add to what I have already said on this aspect<br />
of the matter that there is, to my mind, a strange passion in our country<br />
for uniformity; strange, because we are in our own nature, strongly<br />
individualist. Under Sub-section the Commonwealth has power over<br />
" borrowing money on the public credit of the Commonwealth."<br />
The importance of this provision has been increased by a later<br />
Constitutional Amendment. Section 105A of the Constitution, agreed to by<br />
the electors in 1929, authorised and validated the famous Financial Agreement<br />
and the creation of the Loan Council. Under these arrangements, the<br />
Commonwealth borrows for the States as well as for itself.<br />
But it must be remembered that the terms and conditions,<br />
including interest rates of such Commonwealth loans are subject to the<br />
approval of the Loan Council, in which the States have between them<br />
formidable voting powers. I do not quarrel with this; but it does mean<br />
that, in a matter of so vital importance as interest policy, the Commonwealth </p>
<p>7<br />
is not the complete master though some people think that it is.<br />
Sub-section ( xii) gives power over<br />
" 1currency, coinage, and legal tender."<br />
This is essentially a mechanical provision, not very significant<br />
for my present purpose.<br />
Sub-section ( xiii) gives power over<br />
" Banking, other than State banking: also State banking<br />
extending beyond the limits of the State concerned, the<br />
incorporation of banks, and the issue of paper money."<br />
This is, of course, a famous and much discussed provision. it<br />
is a wide power. It clearly includes, with the exclusion of State banking,<br />
autho ' rity in respect of bank credit and advance policies, the creation of<br />
a Reserve Bank and the equipping of it with reserve-banking powers. it<br />
includes control of interest rates on bank deposits and advances.<br />
But it does not confer power over interest rates generally.<br />
Thus, the Commonwealth cannot, except possibly by some special and discriminatory<br />
form of taxation, deal with hire-purchase rates of interest<br />
or the rates charged or offered by what have been colloquially referred<br />
to as " fringe banking" institutions unless the transactions of these<br />
institutions themselves are held to be part of banking business, and so<br />
fall within the Commonwealth's banking power. The definition of " banking"<br />
is uncertain, but is probably fairly restrictive. To put it briefly,<br />
though banking involves money-lending, it does not follow that all moneylending<br />
is banking. It seems that regulation of what we call capital<br />
issues is certainly not included. I gather that the weight of legal<br />
opinion is that hire-purchase and the like transactions, which today have<br />
a great significance in the economy, do not ordinarily fall within the<br />
Banking power. As interest rates are of great importance in overall monetary<br />
and credit management, there is here a deficiency in Commonwealth power.<br />
One not uncommonly hears generalised phrases about, for example, " scheap<br />
money" or " low interest rates policies." They tend to ignore the constitutional<br />
facts of life. A power to control bank deposit interest rates<br />
by keeping them relatively low could be defeated by a bidding up for deposits<br />
at fancy rates of interest by the non-banking bodies I have referred to.<br />
I next come to sub-section ( xiv)<br />
" Insurance, other than State insurance: also State<br />
insurance extendina beyond the limits of the State concerned." </p>
<p>-8-<br />
As a source of national economic control, this is of course<br />
limited; though recent legislation has had the effect of stimulating life<br />
assurance societies to investment in public loans.<br />
Sub-section ( xx) reads " Foreign corporations, and tradingl or<br />
financial corp~ orations formed within the limits of the Commonwealth." The<br />
meaning and e. lfect of this__ provision has never been determined with any<br />
precision. It was unsuccessfully relied upon in support of Bank<br />
nationalisation. It is genetally accepted that it does not authorise<br />
the Commonwealth Parliament to pass a Uniform Companies Act. Uniformity<br />
in Company Law therefore remains a matter for agreement with and separate<br />
enactments by, the States. The sub-section cannot be relied upon as an<br />
effective instrument of national economic policy.<br />
What I may call the Social Services powers in sub-sections<br />
( Xxiii) and ( xxiii) A, have, by their exercise, very great economic consequences.<br />
" Invalid and old-age pensions. The provision of maternity<br />
allowances, widows' pensions, child endowment, unemployment, pharmaceutical..<br />
sickness and hospital benefits, medical and dental services ( but not so as<br />
to authorise any form of civil conscription) i benefits to students and family<br />
aloacs are indeed far reaching. The powers have been exercised on<br />
w~ de scale. But, though the hundreds of millions now laid out on such<br />
matters are providing a wide measure of social justice, and a distinctive<br />
element in the national economy, they can never be regarded as a flexible<br />
means of economic adjustment in face of conditions of boom or depression.<br />
True, at the time of the great depression and the " Premiers' Plan", pensions<br />
were temporarily reduced; but this is not a precedent which any government<br />
would wish to follow. It is always politically easy to increase social<br />
services; from time to time it is financially feasible to do so; but it<br />
is not practical to think that social services can be adjusted, as taxation<br />
or bank interest rates can be raised or lowered, as a means of giving effect<br />
to monetary policies. The fact is that our social services policies and<br />
outgoings. socially essential as they are, limit the Government's economic<br />
room for manoeuvre in dealing with the ups and downs of national economic<br />
life. The power can be used for expansion; it clearly cannot be readily<br />
resorted to for purposes of contraction or of adjustment over a limited<br />
period of time. Sub-section ( xxvii) gives power over " Immigration and<br />
emigration." o The exercise of this power is a matter of great social and<br />
national security significance. But it also has great economic significance,<br />
bringing with it both assets ( particularly in the iqng run) and liabilities<br />
( particularly in the short run). But considered a?'-an economic instrument,<br />
there are clear limits to its flexibility. You cannot increase or reduce<br />
the stream of migration from year to year, as if you were turning a tap on </p>
<p>-9<br />
or off. The nation needs a stream of immigration while it can secure it.<br />
Indeed, if I may interpolate the remark, the anticipation that the stream<br />
will continue is no small factor in the forward planning and spirit of<br />
confidence of industrial and business managers.<br />
Now I turn to what I will call, compendiously, the Commonwealth's<br />
industrial power. This is both limited and peculiar, if not actually unique.<br />
The words of sub-section ( xxxv) are:-<br />
" Conciliation and arbitration for the prevention and<br />
settlement of industrial disputes extending beyond the<br />
limits of one State".<br />
Almost every word of this provision has been the subject of<br />
repeated litigation and interpretation. Tonight I do not propose to stray<br />
into pastures from which, in my days at the Bar, I derived some nourishment.<br />
For my present purpose, all I want to say is that a few things have to be<br />
borne in mind. The first is that the Commonwealth, except in its territories,<br />
and in respect of its own employeeg, has of itself no power to fix wages<br />
and conditions of employment.<br />
This may well have saved us from many electoral auction sales.<br />
The second is that when the Commonwealth exercises the<br />
legislative power I have just quoted, by setting up conciliation and<br />
arbitration tribunals or functionaries, it cannot direct them as to what<br />
they may award or decide. The creature of Parliament is, in the field<br />
indicated, more powerful than its creator. True, the Parliament has power<br />
to abolish the tribunal. This was attempted by one of my distinguished<br />
predecessors thirty-three years ago., with politically fatal results. The<br />
experiment is not likely to be repeated.<br />
Commonwealth Governments have on occasion submitted facts and<br />
argument to the tribunal when broad economic policies seemed to be involved;<br />
but those arguments have not been, and could not have been, commands or<br />
instructions. The decisions are those of the adjudicators, to be respected<br />
and obeyed. I value this system very much. On the whole, it has worked<br />
well, and I would wish to preserve it. But it obviously puts beyond the<br />
authority of the Commonwealth Parliament and Government matters which,<br />
from a purely economic stand-point, are at all times important and may,<br />
on occasions become supremely so. The capacity of the Commonwealth to </p>
<p>give some discriminating help to individual States. ( and this takes me back<br />
to what I was saying earlier), has come largely to depend upon Section 96<br />
of the Constitution-It reads-<br />
" During a period of ten years after the establishment of<br />
the Commonwealth and thereafter until the Parliament<br />
otherwise provides, the Parliament may grant financial<br />
assistance to any State on such terms and conditions as<br />
the Parliament thinks fit.,"<br />
This section has been given a wide interpretation and application.<br />
So far from having a ten years life, it has increased in importance, and its<br />
use in frequency, so that it has become a permanent and important feature of<br />
Commonwealth-States financial relations. Apart from its special use for<br />
the purpose ( after the recommendations of the State Grants Commission) of<br />
grants to the " claimant States" for years South Australia, Western<br />
Australia, Tasmania, and more recently, Western Australia and Tasmania<br />
it has been frequently used as a means of providing Commonwealth assistance<br />
to States for State works possessing special national significance, e. g.<br />
for the promotion of export earnings, and to the States for Universities<br />
and the like. It is now a received view that the Commonwealth is<br />
unrestricted as to the terms and conditions it imposes, and that one<br />
condition that may be attached is that of repayment. Section 96 has<br />
therefore proved the source of special loans as well as special grants.<br />
Indeed, it is the constitutional foundation of the Financial<br />
Assistance Grants which replace the Tax Reimbursement Grants, and are by<br />
far the greatest single element in Commonwealth aid to the States.<br />
State grants, whether absolute or repayable come out of Commonwealth<br />
funds. While, therefore, they have proved to be an adaptable means<br />
of overcoming some of the asperities of uniformity, they are, as an<br />
instrument of Commonwealth economic policy, rather one-way in their<br />
operation. There are, no doubt, many constitutional provisions which bear<br />
indirectly upon that economic policy, but to which I have not made reference.<br />
My reason is that, addressing a primarily lay audience and being, by<br />
effluxion of time since I last donned a wig and gown, something of a layman<br />
myself ( or at least suffering from intellectual obsolescence), I have<br />
desired to concentrate upon the points of significance to my theme.<br />
I will therefore conclude my most imperfect constitutional<br />
survey by going back to the Customs Tariff power. I do this the more<br />
willingly because the problems of the Tariff have been a good deal in the<br />
headlines in recent weeks. </p>
<p>11<br />
There has been a fairly common tendency to assume that a Commonwealth<br />
Government and Parliament is handicapped by being compelled to sail in<br />
treacherous and narrow waters between the Scylla of the Arbitration Commission<br />
and the Charybdis of the Tariff Board; the assumption being that<br />
each commands and controls the channel. That this is true in the case of<br />
the Arbitration Commission with, for all practical purposes, an entrenched<br />
constitutional position, cannot hopefully or practically be denied! I<br />
have already said something about it. But the Tariff Board is in quite a<br />
different position. It is a purely statutory body, created by the discretion<br />
of Parliament, and, indeed, subject to the control of Parliament.<br />
In this sense, it is an instrument of policy, and in no sense its master.<br />
It has, however, been recognised by successive governments<br />
that, though what I have said is constitutionally true, it is important<br />
that, for international as well as domestic purposes, the Tariff Board<br />
should possess a high measure of independence, that the integrity of its<br />
advice should be preserved, and that it should not be subject to any form<br />
of day-to-day political instruction. I accept and maintain these<br />
propositions. Yet the Tariff Board, our principal adviser on import<br />
duties, cannot sensibly be expected to operate in a completely detached<br />
intellectual vacuum. It must have in its mind some standards or policies<br />
by which to test the cases presented to it.<br />
For a long time it has acted on the principle that it should<br />
recommend Tariff protection only to " economic and efficient industries".<br />
But that principle was, and is, itself an expression of government policy.<br />
Of late, indications have been given on behalf of my own Government that<br />
the principle needs extension, and that the Tariff Board should have in<br />
its mind the national economic policy, meaning by that the national economic<br />
objectives, as a whole. There have been sharp criticisms of this by<br />
representative, thoughtful, and responsible people. As I think that they<br />
have misunderstood these proposals, I will endeavour, without, I hope,<br />
wearying you, to make the point clear.<br />
Nobody suggests that an independent but advisory body like<br />
the Tariff Board should, in its recommendations, seek to follow every<br />
government or legislative application of economic policy in its determination<br />
of the case before it. This would be quite impracticable and could<br />
lead to strange, anomalous and fluctuating results.<br />
But there are certain features of national economic policy,<br />
which I do not regard as the subject of party controversy, which cannot<br />
be ignored by any statutory body if the nation is to achieve a dynamic<br />
progress, growing in resources, population, employment, industry, and<br />
international solvency. For a Tariff Board to ignore their existence<br />
would be to detach its work from the great stream of Australian development.<br />
This, I am sure, it would not wish to do. </p>
<p>12<br />
Let me explain what I mean by natignal economic policy. It<br />
includes the encouragement of population growth by substantial immigration.<br />
It recognises that such encouragement is an important factor in the future<br />
planning of industry and commerce. It calls for a strong development of<br />
old and new natural resources, so that a growing population will be fully<br />
and usefully employed, and the resources themselves put to full use. It<br />
perceives that the achievement of these things will require, in a relatively<br />
new country like ours, the fullest possible generation and investment of<br />
capital at home, and the attraction of productive capital from abroad. And<br />
on top of, and conditioning all these things, it requires that there should<br />
be a constant and steady eye upon the costs of production, so that our great<br />
export primary industries will not be discouraged by ever-rising costs from<br />
attempting that still further enlargement of production on which our export<br />
future must continue to depend, and so that our secondary industries may<br />
increasingly be able to export to the world's markets in competition with<br />
other industrial powers.<br />
These are the great national objectives of economic policy.<br />
I am sure that they are accepted by most Australians, and that they have<br />
a settled place in our national life.<br />
Who can seriously suggest that they should be ignored by the<br />
Tariff Board, or by any other group of people serving the national interest?<br />
I would be surprised to learn that the members of the Board wished to ignore<br />
these matters, or resented the fact that a clear statement of them was made<br />
by any Australian Government.<br />
How these accepted objectives are to be achieved is another and<br />
more controversial matter. Particular application of policy may, and does,<br />
change from time to time. One government may go out on some particular<br />
measure, and another government may come in with an entirely different<br />
notion. It would, as I have said, be hopeless to require a Tariff Board<br />
to behave like a weather-cock under such circumstances. Nobody suggests<br />
that it should do so. What is suggested is that it should do its important<br />
work independently, not controlled by sectional pressures, with complete<br />
integrity of mind, but with the settled economic objectives of the nation<br />
constantly in mind.<br />
Before I conclude, I would wish to bring my consideration of<br />
this fascinating and important problem into focus.<br />
Federalism suits most Australians. It connotes a division<br />
of powers. It divides sovereignty among central and local organs of<br />
government. This means limitations upon the power of any Government,<br />
limitations which it is neither practical nor sensible to ignore. </p>
<p>13<br />
Yet, while there is much room for clear statement and objective<br />
understanding, and there are many real difficulties, I would not want to<br />
leave you with the idea that the Federal system is in substance gravely<br />
frustrating or damaging.<br />
The truth is that the forces which operate upon Constitutions<br />
apart altogether from formal amendments to the printed text, have been clear<br />
and powerful in our own country. The Commonwealth has certain capacities<br />
for effective action, not all of which are apparent on the surface of the<br />
Constitution. I will content myself with mentioning four of them.<br />
1. Though the Commonwealth can be out-voted in the Loan<br />
Council, it undoubtedly possesses a measure of ascendancy<br />
because of its voting rights ( two votes plus a casting vote),<br />
its de facto exclusive responsibility for borrowings, and<br />
its wide financial authority resulting from Uniform Taxation.<br />
2. The Commonwealth can exercise a large influence ( though by<br />
no means, as I have said, a comprehensive one) on the Money<br />
Market both through the Reserve Bank and through its own<br />
operations.<br />
3. In the field of revenue raising the Commonwealth has<br />
advantages which no State can possess; the fields of<br />
Customs and Excise being exclusively Commonwealth by the<br />
Constitution, and those of Income Tax being Commonwealth<br />
by Statute.<br />
4. Section 96 has, contrary perhaps to the expectations of<br />
the founders of the Constitution, proved an apt means<br />
of assisting States and State projects by grant or advance.<br />
These are very real powers. They are constantly being developed<br />
and used to meet new situations as political and economic conditions change.<br />
True, they are sometimes cumbersome, and not infrequently produce political<br />
problems which, in my experience, do not diminish with the years.<br />
Indeed, one must be careful about the exercise of such farreaching<br />
powers of persuasion or control.<br />
For example, in my own time as Prime Minister, the Commonwealth<br />
has evolved a fairly constant practice of supporting State Loan programmes<br />
out of Commonwealth revenue and other funds. This form of what I will<br />
loosely call " underwriting" is quite voluntary on the part of the Commonwealth,<br />
but, in an average year when the loan market will not fully supply </p>
<p>14<br />
the States loan programme, it has proved vital for the maintenance of<br />
adequate State works. Had it felt so disposed the Commonwealth could,<br />
in most of these years, have imposed its will on the States in respect<br />
of the nature of the proposed State works, as a condition of Commonwealth<br />
financial support. There are, no doubt, those who think we should have<br />
done so. But our view has been that State governments should not be<br />
over-ridden or controlled in this fashion; and this for two reasons.<br />
One is that we would wish to respect not only the form but the substance<br />
of federalism. The other, a good practical reason, is that the works<br />
authorities of the States cannot, in my experience, be accused of<br />
incompetence or a failure to understand the needs of their own areas and<br />
people. A notable Victorian judge once said to a somewhat prolix<br />
barrister that " he had circumnavigated the whole globe of irrelevancy".<br />
Looking back on what I have said to you, I hope, even if faintly, to<br />
escape this condemnation. It is enough for me to conclude by saying<br />
once more that I am deeply honoured at your invitation to speak to you<br />
on an occasion which invokes the memory of one for whom I had, and have,<br />
such a deep affection. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
