<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>4272</transcript-id>
    <title>MR NEILSON&#039;S VISIT ON 9 NOVEMBER</title>
    <prime-minister>Fraser, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19751111 - 19830311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>09/11/1976</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00004272.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
MR NEILSON'S VISIT ON 9 NOVEMBER<br />
The Prime Minister met with Mr Neilson, Premier of Tasmania<br />
on 9 November 1976 for about 45 minutes.<br />
There was brief discussion at the opening of the meeting about<br />
whether these discussions were taking place in the context of<br />
Tasmanian elections and the Premier said that depended on the<br />
course of the discussions.<br />
Shortly before, after Question Time, the Prime Minister had<br />
in fact met employees from Mount Lyell. He referred to the<br />
increased Tasmanian State charges that had fallen on the Mt<br />
Lyell company. He noted that over three years<br />
State payroll tax had gone up about $ 227,000 to about<br />
$ 639,000 and the cost of workers' compensation from<br />
$ 448,000 to about $ 1,200,000 around $ 1 million altogether.<br />
He observed that the Tasmanian State Government had a budget<br />
surplus of about $ 4 million and a surplus in their capital<br />
fund of about $ 17 million.<br />
Mr Neilson said this surplus w. is already committed.<br />
The Prime Minister asked the Premier if he woult-ameliorate<br />
the payroll tax, and the Premier said that this was agreed<br />
to in relation to Mt Lyell. He already had offered to forego<br />
payroll tax on any of the retrenched workers who were<br />
reemployed. The Premier added that the State Government had also offered<br />
to take over the company's apprenticeship scheme.<br />
Discussion then moved on to the 24 point plan that Mr Neilson<br />
produced at Hobart during the Constitutional Convention.<br />
The 24 points are:<br />
1. A special meeting of tae Premier's Conference<br />
and Loan Council to consider the problem of<br />
unemployment. / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
2. The lifting of the authority of the States to borrow<br />
for the remainder of the year by<br />
3. The establishment of an intermediate technology group<br />
in Tasmania to be subsidised at the rate of $ 1,500 monthly.<br />
4. The immediate lowering of the retirement age to 63 years<br />
with consequent provision of old age pensions for males<br />
at 63 years. Consequent alterations to superannuation<br />
and retirement benefits legislation. The ultimate aim<br />
to make possible retirement at<br />
Private companies increasing their workforce to be<br />
exempted from additional payroll tax for next two years.<br />
6. Special appropriation of $ 2,000,000 for unemployment<br />
relief.<br />
7. Increase in preference for local tenderers in all<br />
tenders advertised from today from 10%~ to<br />
8. A Buy Tasmanian campaign to be launched.<br />
9. Extension of Commonwealth Youth Employment Programme<br />
so that State subsidLses by $ 15 weekly C. E. B. for all<br />
breadwinners who have been unemployed for six months.<br />
A new increased intake into the Police Academy.<br />
11. A scholarship scheme for cadets in social welfare,<br />
female secretaryshi., etc.<br />
12. A letting by the Housing Department of individual<br />
houses in country areas to small builders.<br />
13. The establishment of a full-time interdepartmental<br />
youth work unit on the South Australian pattern.<br />
Details to be announced later.<br />
14. The letting of a contract to a local firm to provide<br />
cyclone-style sports halls at a number of schools </p>
<p>-3-<br />
The letting of a contract for the provision of<br />
additional terrapin units for education purposes.<br />
16. A number of clearing and reclamation works to<br />
be undertaken by the National Parks and Lands<br />
Departments.<br />
17. The Commonwealth to be urged to expeditiously<br />
commence the Antarctic Base and Maritime College.<br />
18. Commonwealth to be asked to maintain tighter<br />
protection against overseas imports, particularly<br />
in the textile industry.<br />
19. Comimonwealth to be asked to grant special<br />
dispensation against the effect of the Mackie<br />
Scheme on overseas meat marketing controls.<br />
Portability of apprenticeship within Goverr . snt<br />
departments and instrumentalities.<br />
21. Press the Commonwealth to spend a substantial<br />
sum this year on the rehabilitation of the<br />
railways.<br />
22. Dollar for dollar for dairy industry.<br />
23-. $ 1,000,000 on dollar for dollar basis for<br />
municipal councils ( Part of the $ 2,000,000<br />
announced above).<br />
24. A major acceleration of school building programme<br />
to be announced tomorrow. / 4 </p>
<p>On the first two points the Prime Minister took the view<br />
that proposals coming forward from the Premiers in this<br />
context involved increased expenditure which would add<br />
to the Federal deficit, and, since the Commonwealth Government<br />
guaranteed the loan programme, increasing the borrowing programme woull<br />
also involve an increase in the deficit. The Prime Minister<br />
did agree to examine with the Treasurer an increase in the<br />
semi-governmental borrowing programme.<br />
The Prime Minister pointed out that any increase in the<br />
semi-governmental programme should be for all States. The<br />
Tasmanians argued that special arrangements should be made for<br />
Tasmania as their share of this programme was only about 3k%.<br />
Point three was not raised by Mr Neilson.<br />
The next point dealt with, was the proposal by Mr Neilson that<br />
the retirement age should be lowered by 2 years to 63 years.<br />
The way the Prime Minister put this was that the Commonwealth<br />
Government was not prepared to meet a short term position<br />
with a solution which would have long term consequences.<br />
On point 5, payroll tax, the Prime Minister continued to<br />
press the Premier for agreement to ameliorate payroll tax<br />
for any arrangements that may be made by Mt Lyell with their<br />
employees.<br />
Point 6,7 and 8 were not discussed or raised by Mr Neilson<br />
as a state matter.<br />
Point 9: The Prime Minister agreed to examine the request<br />
for an extension of the Commonwealth Youth Employment Programme.<br />
Mr Neilson is proposing that it be extended to all breadwinners<br />
who have been unemployed for six months.<br />
Points 10 to 16 were regarded by the Premier as State<br />
responsibility and not discussed. </p>
<p>Point 17: The Maritime College and Antarctic Base.<br />
The Premier agreed that the state should provide land at<br />
Launceston for the Maritime College. The Prime Minister<br />
undertook to have the Commonwealth make an early start on<br />
construction.<br />
On the Antarctic Base, the Prime Minister said forward<br />
planning was not sufficiently advanced for the Government<br />
to proceed with this now.<br />
Point 18 was the request for protection, particularly in<br />
the textile industry.<br />
The Prime Minister said the Government was advised by the<br />
Industries Assistance Commission, and that it was open to<br />
firms to make applications for temporary protection and<br />
for the Tasmanian Government to give evidence in support.<br />
The Premier's under Treasurer, Mr Les Bellis, informed the<br />
Premier ti at Tasmania had done this.<br />
Point 19: The Prime Minister noted that the Mackie Scheme<br />
had been referred back to the Meat Board for consideration.<br />
Point 20: The Premier said this was a state proposal.<br />
However the Prime Minister undertook to have the Commonwealth<br />
look at the proposal in relation to the Commonwealth Public<br />
Service.<br />
Point 21: The Prime Minister told the Premier that there<br />
had been a sharp increase already this year in expenditure<br />
on railways in Tasmania, which were taken over as a result<br />
of agreement with the former government.<br />
About $ 6 million in capital expenditure is being outlayed<br />
during the current year. Excluding Bell Bay, Tasmania' s state<br />
expenditure over five years was $ 5.61 million.<br />
Point 22: The Prime Minister pointed out that the Federal<br />
Government already guarantees producer s'around 60 cents per pound<br />
of contained butterfat. He invited Mr Neilson to add his<br />
proposed subsidy for Tasmania . to that but the Premier declined. / 6 </p>
<p>Point 23: The Prime Minister pointed out that last year<br />
local government in Tasmania got $ 2.3 million and that this<br />
year~ the figure had gone up $ 1.7 million to $ 4.004 million,<br />
an increase of 75 per cent.<br />
The Prime Minister said the Grants Commission would be asked to<br />
review the proportion of funds going to individual states<br />
for local government next year.<br />
This would give Tasmania the opportunity to make submissions<br />
about its alleged disadvantage under the arrangements<br />
to which it agreed at the Premiers Conference in June 1976.<br />
Point 24: Senator Carrick pointed out that Tasmania had<br />
received $ 1.2 million extra for schools from the Commonwealth<br />
and that during the current year they would be able to make<br />
a start with spending this money as from October 1 that's<br />
the beginning of last month.<br />
Sunimarising, the Prime Minister gave an undertaking to<br />
examine the semi-governmental programme.<br />
He concurred with Mr Neilson's request that the Commonwealth<br />
would examine a request to extend the Youth Employment<br />
Progra:-me to breadwinners who have been unemployed for<br />
six months, m~ ake an early Ltart on the Maritime College,<br />
review the Mackie proposals, examine the portability of<br />
apprenticeships in the Public Service and support a review<br />
of the Tasmanian share of local government funding for next<br />
year. Discussion then moved on to the specific problem of<br />
Queenstown. The Prime Minister pointed out that earlier<br />
he received a delegation of employees from Queenstown,<br />
conducted by Ray Groom. He told the Premier that these<br />
employees proposed as one possibility a shared-work arrangement,<br />
involving a reduction in wages to maintain employment. / 7 </p>
<p>-7-<br />
The Prime Minister offered the services of the Department<br />
of Employment and Industrial Relations to assist in any way.<br />
He sought an assurance from the Premier that his offer to<br />
remit payroll tax would be extended to a shared work situation.<br />
The Premier said he would give this favourable consideration.<br />
The Premier then raised the question of assistance for the<br />
purchase of housing, if men from Queenstown had to be relocated.<br />
The Prime Minister's response to this was that the situation<br />
as it was presented to him was that the people of Queenstown<br />
didn't want to be relocated. In any event there is a<br />
standing Government programme on relocation and the Queenstown<br />
situation could be looked at in this light.<br />
Senator Carrick made the point that Tasmanians now enjoyed<br />
the benefit of full freight equalisation for northbound<br />
trade, which is worth something like $ 20 million a year to<br />
Tasmanian producers.<br />
The Prime Minister offered to establish a study of the special<br />
problems of Tasmanian industry. He offered to consult<br />
with the Tasmanian Government on the terms of the inquiry, and<br />
the Premier accepted this offer.<br />
That concluded the discussion.<br />
Mr Neilson asked how long before he received answers<br />
on the matters being examined, and could he have them in<br />
a week. The Prime Minister agreed to aim at that. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
