<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9377</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P.J.KEATING MP INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY, ABC &#039;PM&#039; PROGRAM, TUESDAY, 11 OCTOBER 1994</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>11/10/1994</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009377.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P. J. KEATING MP<br />
INTERVIEW WITH FRAN KELLY, ABC ' PM' PROGRAM, TUESDAY,<br />
11 OCTOBER 1994<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
FK: Prime Minister, in his book, Bob Hawke accounts how at the time in<br />
1991, you were not interested in sending Australian troops to the Gulf<br />
War, yet now you say at the time that you were saying that they should<br />
go after Saddam Hussein and finish him off. Did you support<br />
involvement in the Gulf War or not?<br />
PM: I did. That is just a straight lie. A straight distortion. There were only<br />
two Ministers at the original meeting this was about whether we<br />
committed people to Desert Shield that was Hawke, Michael Duffy<br />
who was acting Foreign Minister and me. Without any notice I was<br />
asked around and he said " I might get a call from the United States,<br />
what do you think we'll do?" Typically Bob Hawke, he didn't say ' look,<br />
I think this is what we should do, now what do you think?' The<br />
question always is ' what do you think we should do?' You know, will<br />
the real leader please tell us what we can do here. And, I said.'. well, I<br />
think, that we are going to continue to see this sort of criminal activity<br />
from this regime and I think we should be in a position to respond<br />
positively to a commitment on the interdiction role in the Gulf. That<br />
was the first meeting of course Gareth was away and Michael Duffy<br />
was there as his acting Minister. The second was whether we<br />
committed troops to Desert Shield and it was a meeting between<br />
Hawke, Button, Robert Ray and the Foreign Minister Gareth Evans<br />
and me. Robert had just been to Washington, Gareth had been in<br />
touch with the United States and had also been in touch with other UN<br />
members and we had a discussion and Bob Hawke was encouraging a<br />
discussion which was some advice from Robert and Gareth that maybe<br />
it would be better if we take the four ships up to the top of the Gulf and<br />
commit a squadron of FAI 8s. They said their piece, Hawke sat back<br />
again not indicating a position. John Button was then asked what he<br />
thought. He gave a very negative response, generally negative<br />
response and they said ' well, what do you think?' I said ' well, look, I'm<br />
just listening, you people'are the experts.' And Hawke said to me </p>
<p>1come on, come on.' And I said ' what, you mean I should say again<br />
what we should do here? Well, I'll tell you what we should do. I don't<br />
agree we should put a squadron of FAI8s there, but I do believe we<br />
should commit to Desert Storm, but I'd leave two ships up the top of<br />
the Gulf and bring the other two home.<br />
Now, that's what happened. To that, he has reworked all that to say<br />
because I didn't want to put a squadron of FAI8s in and leave four<br />
ships up there. Because the American's wanted a commitment both<br />
moral and material, that two ships were enough, we didn't need to<br />
expose needlessly Australian planes or Australian ships. But, at no<br />
stage was there any recommendation from Hawke. He sat there while<br />
Gareth and Robert spoke and the decision was made when I said<br />
' look, I believe we should put two ships up the top of the Gulf and let<br />
the other two come back.'<br />
Now, Bob Hawke parades himself around as somebody who sort of<br />
backed the Americans in, well, he wanted to put them there. I don't<br />
deny that. But, like a lot of things Hawke wanted to do, he never had<br />
the courage to say so when it mattered and he didn't on that occasion<br />
and he hasn't since.<br />
FK: Well, the comments you made yesterday, have caused some stir.<br />
When you say that Saddam Hussein should have been finished off the<br />
first time around and we wouldn't be where we are again today, what<br />
do you mean? Do you mean that he should have been assasinated?<br />
PM: No, no, politically, just his regime should have been, essentially,<br />
rendered inoperative, defunct, I mean call it what you like, I mean<br />
defeated. No, I don't mean personally, I mean politically.<br />
EK: The other attack the Opposition has been making on you, Prime<br />
Minister, is about this purchase of the new house.<br />
PM: Hang on, before we get onto that rubbish let's just stay on the main<br />
thing. I mean, look, the lot of the Iraqi Kurds and Shi'ites in this<br />
country has been a very sad and dismal one in all the periods since<br />
and there was a position and there was a strategic capacity to finish<br />
this regime off and that wasn't taken up. Now, I said in the Cabinet<br />
room at the time I think we should do that. So did Kim Beazley and<br />
Gareth Evans said ' well, that's not part of the UN mandate.' It wasn't,<br />
but there was still a strong body of opinion that thought that around the<br />
world and essentially what I did the other day was repeat that.<br />
FK: Back to the House and the play the Opposition has been making of<br />
that. They say it is ironic for a Labor Prime Minister to be buying a $ 2<br />
million house in inner Sydney. In the game of politics, that is a fair<br />
enough point to score isn't it? </p>
<p>PM: Look, Alexander Downer, he's not going to make it. I mean the poor<br />
silly thing, he is wondering around tied up now with Michael Baume,<br />
you know who is a piece of, essentially, parliamentary filth. I mean,<br />
look, the thing is and that is what he traffics in filth, under privilege.<br />
Let Alexander Downer cut his own cloth. I mean, look, I've got a house<br />
in Sydney I've had for twelve years, I am moving one mile away to a<br />
larger house, that is the full story.<br />
FK: But, for them to make a play of it, isn't it similar to what you have done<br />
in the past with John Hewson buying and selling houses and the<br />
Ferrari?<br />
PM: No, I have never referred to, I have never said to John Hewson ever<br />
where did you get money for this? or where did you get money for<br />
that? We've said look, he lived in Bellevue Hill and had a Ferrari, but<br />
nobody said " well listen John, hang on you paid this for that and what<br />
was it that you put down here and what margin did you have there and<br />
where did you I mean, that's never been done. I mean, at the time<br />
John Hewson was embarrassed with his family affairs not a word came<br />
from me or the Government. At a time when Mrs Downer absolutely<br />
put her foot in it about the passports of her children, not a word other<br />
than an oblique reference from Gareth Evans which he apologised for.<br />
These people never stop and the thing about it is this Fran they must<br />
think I live under a rock. I know all about them, about their personal<br />
lives, about their finances, but I never use it.<br />
FK: Is this sale going through in eighteen months time, is that a sign that<br />
you considering resigning from politics?<br />
PM: No, just as that suited the vendor and it suited me. I've got no<br />
particular purpose at this point living in the house and I won't have<br />
after then. So, what I'll basically do is sell the one I have and rent it<br />
and that suited I mean, the cheek of these characters is just<br />
unbelievable. But the gutlessness of Downer not to raise it in the<br />
House of Representatives when I was there, but to go and get<br />
somebody like... without any credibility, a person whose reputation is in<br />
tatters Senator Baume, Michael Baume to go and do it in the Senate<br />
with a couple of other Senators on the instructions of Alexander<br />
Downer, is the sort look, we have all got to make our political bed<br />
in life and then lie in it. Well, the public is making a judgement about<br />
him.<br />
FK: In the House tomorrow the Government's Privacy Bill comes up the<br />
Opposition will vote with the Government, but they're planning to move<br />
an amendment calling for consultation with the Federal parliament,<br />
State governments and the community about the implications of<br />
international treaties before they're signed on to do they have a<br />
point? Should there be more discussion about these kind of treaties<br />
before... </p>
<p>PM: No.<br />
FK Australia signs on?<br />
PM: No. Well, when I say do they have a point about international treaties<br />
no. Do they have a point about discussions? We already consult<br />
with the States, industry groups and community groups, and we do it<br />
extensively. What is their point of objection? They're snakey on the<br />
external affairs power of the Constitution. They're saying " how dare<br />
these Commonwealth governments usurp the roles of the States?"<br />
See, this gets back to the old debate was the Federation an act of<br />
creation of the Nation, or was it basically a set of arrangements for<br />
States? Well, it was the former, not the latter. But the Liberal Party<br />
years after its birth, going nowhere, still messing around with States<br />
rights, and still trafficking in that nonsense is trying to say this is an<br />
incursion of States rights if the Commonwealth of Australia enters into<br />
an international treaty. Are they going to say that when the<br />
Commonwealth ratifies the GATT Agreement, the Uruguay Round, that<br />
it is going to effect some industry and some state, and that's some<br />
transgression of State rights? I mean, when does this nonsense<br />
finish? This is an island continent nation when does this rubbish<br />
about States rights finish?<br />
EK Well, there is some confusion still I gather in the Coalition about<br />
whether some MP's will call for a vote on the Bill if they don't, is the<br />
Government tempted to call for a vote to try and force those ones who<br />
don't support the legislation cross the floor?<br />
PM: Which legislation are you speaking about now?<br />
FK This is the Privacy Bill.<br />
PM: Oh, the Privacy Bill I thought you were talking about the treaties. On<br />
the Privacy legislation look, Alexander Downer said remember he<br />
had his great coming-out press conference a week or two ago: " I have<br />
got the coalition to agree not to oppose the Bill"? I mean, you could<br />
hardly bring yourself to announce it, could you? " We have agreed not<br />
to oppose" not to support, but not to oppose the Bill. He sacked John<br />
Hewson for arguing that the Coalition should support the Bill, he fired<br />
him because Hewson had the temerity to come out and say he<br />
supported the Bill. Now the National Party are going to stand him up<br />
they are directing their members to vote against the Bill what is he<br />
going to do? Sack them Or look like the turkey he has become? I<br />
mean, how does he look on this he has come out and said " I have got<br />
the Coalition to agree not to oppose the Bill". Wrong. He got to the<br />
Coalition to agree to nothing because the National Party are now<br />
saying that " we'll do what we like". I mean his leadership... </p>
<p>FK: National Party MP's are still holding their cards pretty close to their<br />
chest on whether they will actually force a vote and cross the floor<br />
would you like to see that demonstrated? Would you help them call on<br />
a vote?<br />
PM: His leadership has no credibility and no strength, and that's is<br />
apparent in the National Party thumbing its nose at him. If it was up to<br />
him to fire John Hewson if any front-bencher from the National Party<br />
vote against the legislation, then he should fire them too.<br />
FK: There's no sign though that front-benchers will be the ones voting<br />
against him, only those on the back-bench...<br />
PM: It doesn't matter his authority is shot to pieces whichever way it goes.<br />
He made an announcement on behalf of the coalition that the coalition<br />
wouldn't oppose the legislation. They are going to oppose it some of<br />
them.<br />
FK: The Land Fund also goes into the Senate this week the Aboriginal<br />
Land Fund. The Greens are saying they won't support it unless it's<br />
amended substantially they have called your legislation a hoax and a<br />
hall of mirrors paternalistic. Is there going to be another agonisingly<br />
drawn out debate like we had with the Native Title debate, over the<br />
Land Fund?<br />
PM: Well, there shouldn't be because this is a most highly consulted... . this<br />
has been a consulted over piece of legislation, and there is no notion<br />
here that the Aboriginal community certainly not the big<br />
representative bodies I have met believe this is some paternalism on<br />
the part of the Commonwealth. I mean it wasn't that long ago that<br />
Senator Chamarette made a submission in the budget context<br />
proposing certain details about the fund it wasn't so apparently<br />
paternalistic then. The commitment to self-determination is evident<br />
right throughout the Bill, it's set up under the ATSIC Act, Senator<br />
Chamarette says she wants a billion dollars committed in 3 years. We<br />
are committing well over a billion, but over a longer time frame<br />
because we think that is just simply more wise that you can't spend<br />
that money I mean, how could you spend $ 300 million a year on<br />
land?<br />
EK: Well, are you going to try and talk to the Greens about this will you<br />
try and persuade them?<br />
PM: And then the other thing is that she is taking her lead from the NSW<br />
Land Council. Well, it has a land fund which Premier Neville Wran<br />
established which is very well endowed, and maybe they're just not as<br />
interested in the federal fund as some other people in Aboriginal<br />
Australia are, and she shouldn't take that much notice of them. </p>
<p>FK: Will you be talking to the Greens about that?<br />
PM: Well, I don't mind talking to them I have sent them a letter, they have<br />
written to me, I have communicated back to them trying to cover the<br />
points off, and I am happy to talk to them. But I right from the<br />
start I said when we introduced the Native Title legislation that there<br />
would be a Land Fund to cover the interest of indigenous Australians<br />
who couldn't avail themselves of the Mabo Native Title Legislation<br />
who couldn't establish that connection with the land. That has been<br />
part and parcel of everything that the Government has said it is even<br />
in the fist Bill, that is the Land Fund is in the first Bill. Now, it is being<br />
amplified in this Bill, and it was on that basis that the Aboriginal<br />
community expected us to proceed with it, which we have after<br />
extensive consultations. So it's a very... it's very high-handed for the<br />
Greens to say " oh, no, well look we know better what Aboriginal and<br />
Torres Strait Islander Australians need best here. We know better,<br />
and we are going to exercise our perogatives in terms of our own<br />
view". I mean, I just think that the Greens should do a bit of consulting<br />
too, but a bit of broad consulting and not just with particular groups<br />
with an axe to grind.<br />
FK: So you're not... it sounds as though you're not too interested in their<br />
amendments?<br />
PM: No, I'm not real interested to be honest, no.<br />
FK: Prime Minister just finally, the polls are looking very good for the<br />
Government there's much talk about the Government setting up<br />
trigger legislation are you tempted to pull on an early election?<br />
PM: Now did you write this question out Fran, or did you work yourself up to<br />
it?<br />
FK: I have been working up to it Prime Minister.<br />
PM: No. Nope. N-O-P-E. Nope.<br />
FK: So we won't be going to the polls early?<br />
PM: Nope.<br />
FK: Prime Minister Keating, thank you.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
