<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>3572</transcript-id>
    <title>DARWIN DISASTER: MESSAGES OF CONDOLENCE</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>29/12/1974</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00003572.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
Press Release No. 4126<br />
DARWIN DISASTER MESSAGES OF CONDOLENCE<br />
The Prime Minister today released the texts of<br />
further messages of condolence on the Darwin cyclone.<br />
People's Republic of China<br />
" Shocked to learn that the city of Darwin wa~ s hit<br />
by a terrific cyclone with disastrous consequences. On<br />
behalf of the Chinese Government and people, I wish to<br />
express our heartfelt sympathy and solicitude to you,<br />
and through you, to the Australian Government and the people<br />
in Darwin. Chou En-lai, Premier of the State Council of<br />
the People's Republic of China."<br />
Lesotho " It is with the deepest sense of shock and sorrow<br />
that I and the. Government and people of Lesotho hasten to offer<br />
to you, your Government and the people of Australia our<br />
heartfelt condolences on the tragic devastation which has<br />
overtaken the city of Darwin and its people. Our sincere<br />
sympathy is extended to you and all those who have been<br />
bereaved and rendered homeless by this disaster. Please be<br />
so gracious as to accept the sum of R1000 from the Kingdom<br />
of Lesotho as a token of relief to those in need.<br />
Leabua Jonathan, Prime Minister of the Kingdom<br />
of Lesotho."<br />
Arab Republic of Egypt<br />
" On behalf of the Government and people of the<br />
Arab Republic of* Egypt, of all Egyptian residents in Australia,<br />
of the members of the Embassy and my family and in my name<br />
I wish to express to you, to the Government and people of<br />
Australia our deepest sympathy at the tragedy which struck<br />
Darwin. We were shocked by the severity of the valuable human loss.<br />
Your efforts will undoubtedly alleviate the intensity of<br />
the disasters. A. W. Marzouk, Ambassador of Egypt",.<br />
Papua New Guinea ( additional message)<br />
" As further news reports of the extent of the<br />
devastation in Darwin reach me, my sympathy for the people<br />
in the devastated city of Darwin is deepening. Please be<br />
assured that Papua New Guinea is only too willing to assist<br />
in aiding in the rehabilitation of the effected area. You<br />
are aware of our limited resources. However, I would be only<br />
too pleased to assist if possible in any way you might care<br />
to suggest. Once again please convey the sympathy of the Papua<br />
New Guinea Government and all Papua New Guineans on this tragic<br />
C eent M. T. Somare, Chief Minister." </p>
<p>Bangladesh " We are deeply grieved to hear about the<br />
extensive damages to life and property caused to Darwin<br />
City by one of the worst cyclones in the living memory<br />
of Australia. Please accept the deepfelt sympathies<br />
from my own behalf and on behalf of the Government and<br />
the people of Bangladesh. -Sheikh Muribur Rahman,<br />
Prime Minister of the<br />
People's Republic of<br />
Bangladesh."<br />
Canada " I have been shocked to learn of the tragic<br />
loss of life and destruction of property suffered in<br />
Darwin on Christmas Day. My deepest personal sympathy<br />
a!-d that of all Canadians goes to those who have suffered<br />
so cruelly and at a time when most thoughts are directed<br />
in the Christmas tradition to the joys of home and family.<br />
-Pierre Elliott Trudeau,<br />
Prime Minister of Canada"<br />
Seychelles " On behalf of Chief Minister, Government and<br />
people of Seychelles, please accept our sincere sympathy<br />
in cyclonic disaster which has struck city of Darwin<br />
where number of Seychellois reside.<br />
-Allan, Governor of Seychelles"<br />
Pakistan " We have been deeply shocked and grieved at the<br />
news of heavy loss of life and utter devastation caused by<br />
the cyclone which hit the north Australian port of Darwin.<br />
We in Pakistan share with Your Excellency and the people<br />
of Australia your deep sense of loss. I offer on behalf<br />
of the Government and the people of Pakistan and on my own<br />
behalf our sincerest syr. athies and heartfelt condolences<br />
to Your Excellency, to the people affected by the cyclone<br />
and to the people of Australia. -Zulfikar Ali Bhutto,<br />
Prime Minister of Pakistan"<br />
SOCIALIST REPUBLIC OF THE UNION OF BURMA<br />
" I am greatly distressed to learn about the loss<br />
of life and damagje caused by the disastrous cyclone in<br />
Darwin. I extend to Your Excellency and through you to<br />
the people of the affected area heartfelt sympathies.<br />
-U Sein Win, Prime Minister" </p>
<p>3.<br />
FEDERAL REPUBLIC OP GERMANY<br />
" With deepfelt sorrow I received the news about<br />
the cyclone which has struck the area around Port Darwin.<br />
May I, also in the name of the Government of the Federal<br />
Republic of Germai-y, express my deepest sympathy for the<br />
victims of this unexpected catastrophy. -Helmut Schmidt,<br />
Federal Chancellor<br />
29 December 1974 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
