<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>739</transcript-id>
    <title>NORTH - WEST GAPE NAVAL COMMUNICATION STATION AGREEMENT WITH U.S  STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER THE RT. HON. SIR ROBERT MENZIES IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESEN - TATIVES ON THURSDAY 16TH MAY, 1963</title>
    <prime-minister>Menzies, Robert</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19491219 - 19660126</period-of-service>
    <release-date>16/05/1963</release-date>
    <release-type>Statement in Parliament</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00000739.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
1' tRTH-WEST CAPE NAVAL COMMUNICATION STATION<br />
AGREEMENT WITH U. S.<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister, the Rt. Hon.<br />
Sir Robert Menzies, in the House of Representatives<br />
on Thursday, 16th May, 1963.<br />
Mr, Speaker I am indebted to the House and I hope<br />
that I will not neea this indulgence. I think that I ought<br />
to begin by saying that I am vastly indebted to the honourable<br />
member for Bowman ( Mr. Comber), who has cast me with a<br />
versatility of role to which I have never aspired. It turns<br />
out that I rode into office on a dead horse that is not<br />
a bad feat sitting at the time in a gilded cage and drawing<br />
a red herring across the trail. I am indebted to my friend<br />
for this, It is in some way a compliment.<br />
There is one thing that I would like to say quite<br />
seriously about the end of ti-ic honourable member's speech<br />
and about other speeches that have been made this afternoon.<br />
This is a vory curious debate, I thought that we were to get<br />
to the heart of this matter and have the points of difference<br />
fought out as they are entitled to be fought out for the<br />
public benefit. But most of the campaign on the Opposition<br />
side of the House has boon directed at justifying the system<br />
of internal government in the Australian Labour Party. No<br />
doubt, this is a very interesting thesis, but it is hardly<br />
an answer to the issues that are being dealt with here in<br />
relation to the establishment of this station and the conditions<br />
on which it ought to be established. However, Sir, I will<br />
not occupy any time on that.<br />
I just want to address myself to some of the remarks<br />
made by the Leader of the Opposition ( Mr. Calwell), who<br />
if I may say so was in uncommonly vigorous form this alternoon,<br />
He bocame almMs excited, I thought, at one or two stagas,<br />
when he indulged in the luxury of making a little free with<br />
history. I suppose that that is pardonable. For one thing,<br />
he seemed to me to set out to establish that there was not<br />
much wrong with this agreement with the U. S. A. for the stablishmont<br />
of a naval comm-nunication station, That surprised me<br />
having regard to recent events and recent votes. It astonished<br />
me, and it must have astonished some of those opposite who<br />
have taken Trappist vows in the course of this debate, After<br />
all, what did the honourable gentleman say?<br />
Ho attacked my colleague, the Minister for acternal<br />
Affairs ( Sir Garfield Barvrick), for having misled the House<br />
about the effect of the agreement. How far can a man mislead<br />
the House about the effect of an agreement that has been tabled<br />
and is explained in simple and measured terms? The Leader<br />
of the Opposition said " lThere is nothing in this agreement<br />
about solo control. his is a device used by the Attorney-<br />
General" Then later he said, " There is nothing in this<br />
agreement inconsistent with joint control." I am glad to see<br />
the honourable member for Bass ( Mr. Barnard) nodding his head<br />
because that shows that he followed the argument of the Leader<br />
of the Opposition, Therefore, in that event there is joint<br />
control and, if there is joint control, the Australian<br />
Government can veto any decision because obviously joint<br />
control involves the right of veto. So everything in the<br />
garden is lovely. 9 / 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
I put this quite seriously to honourable members and<br />
to the people of Australia. They should consider it. I am<br />
repeating the argument which was advanced by the Leader of<br />
the Opposition. If I wore in opposition and entertained those<br />
views I will demonstrate in a moment that they are wrong and<br />
I will face up to the great problem in this matter without any<br />
hesitation I would support the bill ratifying the agreement<br />
without any qualification and without needing to do what the<br />
Leader of the Opposition has done and without engaging in this<br />
by-play. I begin by being puzzled to know where the Leader of the<br />
Opposition, who has been much instructed on this matter, now<br />
stands. Yet I cannot suppose for one moment that he took<br />
forty-five minutes of passion and invective and I repeat, making<br />
singularly free with history I will put it politely just to<br />
say " Yes" to the bill. If one can judge by the atmosphere, one<br />
thing is clear that he does not like the bill or the agreement.<br />
But if I am wrong about that perhaps the Opposition will relieve<br />
me of all my responsibilities by saying, " We are all wholeheartedly<br />
in favour of the agreement," If Opposition members<br />
will say that I will be glad to resume my seat, but they know<br />
that they cannot say that because it is a flat contradiction<br />
of everything that has been happening during their debates.<br />
I will address myself to the genuine issues in this<br />
matter and the deep differences that are disclosed here because<br />
I think that the people of Australia want, quietly and carefully,<br />
to understand them, But before I address myself to the major<br />
task, I want to dispose of the allegation repeatedly made that<br />
we, and in particular I, have concealed the true nature of this<br />
station at North West Capo, Long after the Minister for Defence<br />
( Mr. Townley) had made a statement about this matter, I made<br />
quite a lengthy statement on 17th May last year and again on<br />
26th March this year, saying all that could be said about the<br />
proposed station. There is nothing to be added to or. subtracted<br />
from that today. Indeed, if any confirmation were needed, it<br />
was afforded by the distinguished visiting U. S. Admiral who<br />
came here for the Coral Sea celebrations.<br />
Mr. Allan Fraser Donrt bring him into it,<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES We brought him into Australia.<br />
Mr. Allan Fraser Don't bring him into it. That is<br />
very bad.<br />
SIR ROBERT MENZIES Come come, grow up. The Admiral came to<br />
Australia. I wonder what the honourable member would have said<br />
if the Admiral had criticised the Government on this matter,<br />
We would have heard all about it in this place and the television<br />
audience would have listened to it and wondered. All I know<br />
is that the Admiral said, obviously with complete accuracy that<br />
this was a radio communication station and nothing more. That<br />
of course is true. But on 8th May this year the honourable<br />
member for Yarra ( Mr. Cairns) was exercised o say: " You said<br />
that this was a naval communication station to communicate with<br />
naval vessels. You did not mention submarines." I did not<br />
mention submarines. No. I give it to the honourable member<br />
for what it is worth I did not mention aircraft carriers and<br />
yet I am told that they are naval vessels which carry aircraft<br />
and that some of the aircraft are so furnished that they can<br />
deliver nuclear weapons. The Leader of the Opposition used some<br />
pretty hard terms but I would venture to describe the point made<br />
by the honourable member for Yarra as puerile. If any one in </p>
<p>3-<br />
this place other than the honourable member for Yarra believed<br />
that submarines asnd aircr-aft carriers were not naval vessels,<br />
I would be astonished at the illiteracy of the House,<br />
Therefore, there is no occasion -to alter a single word of<br />
what was said then.<br />
Having said that I want to return for a moment to<br />
the central problem does this agreement provide for sole<br />
control, as my colleague rightly said that It does, or for<br />
joint control, as -the Leader of the Opposition hopes that<br />
it does? This requires two answers. First, what does the<br />
agreement provide? Secondly, is it right, speaking responsibly<br />
on behalf of our own country? As for the agreement itself,<br />
I must say that I was taken aback by he-aring an argument that<br />
the Attorney-General was wrong. The preamble to the agreement<br />
is in these terms " Considering that the establishment, maintenance<br />
and operation of a United States naval communication<br />
station in Austrolia will materially contribute to<br />
that end<br />
That being the end of Common defence<br />
in accordance writh the terms and conditions<br />
set out in this Agreement, the United States Govarnment<br />
may estaiblish Imaintain and operate a naval communication<br />
station.'?<br />
The United States Govern~ ment, not someone else. Then there is<br />
a provision in Article 3 to which my distinguished friend<br />
referred to the effect that the two governmen-ts will consult<br />
from time to time at the request of either government on any<br />
matters connected with this station and its use, Of coursej<br />
We are allies. In that sense we are partners. Of course we<br />
will consult about all sorts of things. We want to be able to<br />
use the station ourselves for our own communications. But<br />
there is nothing in this agreement I had thought this was<br />
the nub of the matter from the point of view of the Labour<br />
Party which proposes joint control of the station which<br />
enables the Australian Government to veto the use of the<br />
station in the event of war. If honourable members opposite<br />
object to that I imagine they do from all that I have heard<br />
and read on this matter, and it is an intelligible view<br />
let them say so. I am here to defend it, to say that this<br />
is a proper arrangement, If it were not made in this sense,<br />
the fact is that in the event of a war breaking out in which<br />
nuclear weapons were involved, if you like, Austraba could<br />
nullify the effect of U. S. nuclear weapons in the Southern<br />
Hemisphere by saying to the U. S, " You are not to use this<br />
communication station,," I will come back later to that aspect<br />
to explain what a fantasy that is and how utterly inconsistent<br />
it would be with the safety of our own country.<br />
I began by saying that I agreed that this agreement<br />
provides for sole control. Therefore the agreement is<br />
inconsistent with the Oppositionfs desire of joint control and<br />
inconsistent with the power which the Opposition wants to say<br />
to the U. S. in the event of war, " You are not to use this<br />
station because it right involve us in some way." I state that<br />
m atter quite clearly. These are the matters at issue. It<br />
would be very advantagoous if the people of 1astralia could see<br />
quite clearly the points on which there is deep division of<br />
opinion between the Government and the Opposition. 0 * 0 </p>
<p>4<br />
Having said that, I want now to clear aside a<br />
little lumber that has come forard in the course+ of this<br />
argument. Argument about the establishment of the station<br />
at North-West Cape gets muddled every now and then with<br />
argument about the establishment of a nuclear-free zone in<br />
the Southern Hemisphere. Indeed, I think the Labour Partyts<br />
ambitions in the direction of a nuclear-free zone have<br />
largely affected its attitude tow-: r2ds the North-West Cape<br />
project and have created within thie Labour Party, putting on<br />
orm side all shams most determined opposition to the establ~ shment<br />
at North-UMs Cape, Labourts argument has become so<br />
muddled that the Leader of the Opposition cited, not for the<br />
first time, the Commonwealth Prime Ministers' Conference of<br />
1961 and said that that Conference produced the right ideas,<br />
I agree; the Conference did produce the right ideas. I<br />
should know something about the two paragraphs to which the<br />
honourable gentleman has constantly referred because I drafted<br />
them at the Conference and I adhere to them.<br />
Paragraph 7 of the communique issued that year<br />
read " Every effort should be made to secure rapid<br />
agreement to the permanent banning of nuclear weapons<br />
tests by all nations and to arrangements for verifying<br />
the observation of the agreement, Such an agreement<br />
is urgent since otherwise further countries may soon<br />
become nuclear powers, which would inc_-oaso the danger<br />
of war and further corm-plicntc the problem of disarmament.<br />
Moreover, an agreement on nuclear tests apart from<br />
its direct advantages would provide a powerful<br />
psychological impetus to agreement over the wider<br />
field of disarmament. 0<br />
Quite true; we said thiat, That is why this Government has<br />
not taken steps to make Australia, in the military sense, a<br />
nuclear power. W! e believe that the fewer hands the greater<br />
and more responsible those hands are in which this terrific<br />
weapon resides, the better for mankind. Earlier in the 1961<br />
communique I recommend this section to my friends the<br />
Commonwealth Prime Ministers said<br />
" The elimination of nuclear and conventional<br />
armaments must be so vast that at no stage will any<br />
country or' group of coiuitries obtain a significant<br />
military advantage,"<br />
This is of course, of fundamental importance. For us to join<br />
with otE~ er peoplet if they can be found to strike out of the<br />
hands of our friends and allies the nuclear weapon in some<br />
vast area while leaving it completely in the hands of our<br />
potential enemies in respect of the same area would, of course,<br />
be hopeless. For us to promote the idea this is something<br />
that people should think about that you will help the<br />
world' s peace by getting rid of nuclear weapons and not<br />
touching conventional armaments is simply a policy which<br />
would leave undisputed power in the hands of the Communist<br />
nations. I do not for a moment say that the Leader of the<br />
Opposition proposed that course, I want to make it quite<br />
clear that this is one of the issues that we must determine.<br />
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 </p>
<p>Pending disarmament on the grand scale, the existence<br />
of the nuclear deterrent the capacity to deliver the nuclear<br />
deterrent at the right time and in the right place is the<br />
condition by which we live. The nuclear deterrent will cease<br />
to deter if the Communist powers come to think that it cannot<br />
be effectively organised or deployed south of the equator<br />
though from the point of view of thne Communist countries, which<br />
are north of the equator never forget that there will be no<br />
prohibition or inhibition at all. It is essential for the<br />
effectiveness of the deterrent that the United States naval<br />
forces I mean cruisers, destroyers, frigates, aircraft<br />
carriers, submarines and anything else you care to mention<br />
should be within reach of a radio communication station. That<br />
is essential. Sir, I have no expert views to offer on these matters<br />
but the best military opinion that I have been able to discover<br />
is that while it remains possible for Communist China to acquire<br />
nuclear weapons I think that will be agreed to be an understatement<br />
because most certainly in due course Communist China<br />
will acquire nuclear weapons a nuclear-free Pacific Ocean or<br />
Indian Ocean on our side would be suicidal.<br />
I am happy to say that that situation is clearly<br />
understood by 80 per cent, of the people of Australia, Suppose<br />
Communist China gave a guaranteeo I do not suppose any of us<br />
would be very excited by a Communist guarantee, but suppose<br />
that happened. The military disadvantages of a nuclear-free<br />
Southern Hemisphere must be unacceptablo to the United States<br />
and her global allies because such a situation would reduce<br />
their overall nuclear deterrent capabilities, Honourable<br />
members have only to look at the map of the Indian Ocean and<br />
the South-West Pacific area and note where the equator is, to<br />
understand how crippling it would be if, having that power, we<br />
should say to the United Statcs: " You are not to deploy in<br />
the Indian Ocean south of the equator any naval unit carrying<br />
nuclear weapons or any aircraft on an aircraft carrier carrying<br />
nuclear weapons," In the world picture, the Indian Ocean is<br />
strategically placed and under those circumstances to which<br />
I have just referred, if you were to defend yourself against<br />
Communist aggression, naval units would have to come in through<br />
the Suez Canal on the one side or through the Straits of Malacca<br />
on the other. Really, the safety of our country is of paramount<br />
importance to use We are not to trifle with it in this way,<br />
Some of what the Minister for External Affairs ( Sir<br />
Garfield Barwick) said in his second reading speech has been<br />
decried or questioned by the Opposition, Some very offensive<br />
words were used about what I thought was a singularly objective<br />
statemento But some things are not and cannot be challenged.<br />
Perhaps we have forgotten those things. Perhaps nany people<br />
have forgotten them. It is my duiy to make a reminder. All<br />
I want to do is go back to the ANZUS treaty of 1951 and 1952<br />
the treaty between Australia, New Zealand and the United States.<br />
People forget the nature of that agreemonto Some people say<br />
that we should not tie ourselves too much to the United States<br />
because, who knows, it may have so: ne day a President other than<br />
the one it has today,<br />
They forget the nature of the ANZUS pact, which is<br />
a treaty between nations ratified by the Parliament of each<br />
nation. And in its preamble it says coaae, 9-o/ 6 </p>
<p>6-<br />
" Desiring to declare publicly and formally their<br />
sensc of unity, so that no potential aggressor could<br />
be under the illusion that any of them stand -alone<br />
in the Pacific area1' l<br />
Then, in Article II, which was also read previously by my<br />
colleague, we read " In order mnore effectively to achieve the<br />
objective of this Treaty the Parties SeDarately and<br />
jointly by means of continuous and effective self<br />
help and mutual aid will maintain and develop their<br />
individual and collective capacity to resist armed<br />
attack."<br />
It is in that context and against that background that the U. S.<br />
is being allowed to establish this naval communications station<br />
in the North-West.<br />
Article IV is worth recalling. It says<br />
" Each Party recognizes that an armed attack in<br />
the Pacific Area.."<br />
which was the broad sweep they were taking<br />
0any of the Parties would be dangerous to its<br />
own peace and safety..." 1<br />
In other words, America has declared in this treaty that an<br />
armed attack on Australia would be dangerous to the peace and<br />
safety of the U. S. This is a wonderful provision. The article<br />
continues declares that it would act to meet the common<br />
danger in accordance with its constitutional processes."<br />
Then, we come to Article This is worth mentioning,<br />
not, perhaps, entirely with reD. tion to this measure, but because<br />
for general purposes it ought to be known. It states<br />
" For the purpose of Article IV,<br />
which I have just referred to<br />
ar-med attack on any of the Parties is deemed<br />
to include an armed attack on the metropolitan<br />
territory of any of the Parties, or on the island<br />
territories under its jurisdiction in the Pacific<br />
or on its armed forces, public vessels or aircraft<br />
in the Pacific."<br />
That is the ANZUS Pact, We are really now being told by the<br />
Opposition, as I understand it not so much from the speech<br />
of the Leader of the Opposition as such, but from other general<br />
indications that although we have this partnership; although<br />
wre have this treaty which is absolutely one of the vital elements<br />
in the safety and security of this country, we are to say to the<br />
most overwhelmingly powerful member of the pact, " But understanding<br />
we insist on the provision that if you are attacked by nuclear<br />
weapons without wa-' rning" because, of course, there will be no<br />
gentlemanly stuff if that happens " you cannot give orders to<br />
your people in our area or within the scope of this station to<br />
deliver their retaliatory blows" which ought to be delivered<br />
in an hour " until you first arrange to have a meeting with the<br />
Government of Austala in order thcat it may say VYes? or ' Not".<br />
00 0 00 0 </p>
<p>7<br />
Sir this is so iunreal and so much preferring<br />
barren theory lo the actual security of Australia, that it<br />
baffles me. How does that kind of thing fit into the facts<br />
of life or into the ANZUS concept? Because joint control let<br />
me repeat is not just the power to consult there is plenty<br />
of power to consult but a power to veto, a power to say " No"<br />
and that is what the Opposition wants to be said to the U. S,<br />
Is the U. S. which, at vast expense can create this essential<br />
facility for Western defence and for the carrying out of the<br />
obligations of the ANZUS Treaty, to be told that it must accept<br />
the risk that at the very time when these facilities are most<br />
needed that is to say when the U. S. is attacked in a nuclear<br />
war it may be denied Lhem by the then Government of Australia?<br />
Sir, that point was elaborated in another way in<br />
a statement ma de on behalf of the Opposition. The Opposition<br />
underlined it by saying that there should be a provision that<br />
the station should not be used by the U. S. at war without the<br />
consent of the Australian Government. It is the same thing.<br />
It is merely another way of putting it. I would like our follow<br />
countrymen to think. Do they suppose that if the Communist<br />
powers decided that the moment had come to strike they would<br />
give any warning? I, like most people around the world, am not anticipating<br />
that there will be a nuclear war. So long as we have the<br />
deterrent and the deterrent can be used and launched with the<br />
greatest effect, I do not think we will have nuclear war unless<br />
somebody goes made somewhere. After all, we are talking about<br />
a provision which is designed to help this country and other<br />
countries in the event of war.<br />
Suppose a war came how would it come? Only by<br />
one of the Communist powers, or both, launching an attack on<br />
tho rest of the world in pursuit of world power and dominating<br />
the world with their strange ideas. They would give no warning<br />
about it. Do not we know that from the very first moment that<br />
some nuclear attack is made~ the retaliation the reply must<br />
come within minutes; not within weeks or days0 Of course, that<br />
is why it is necessary for somebody to be able to say " Go";<br />
not a committee; not a laborious consultation at this end~ of<br />
the world. Every minute will count and if we are twenty minutes<br />
late, thirty minutes late or a day late, this may mean the<br />
destruction of our kind of world all around the world.<br />
Sir, suppose a war of that kind occurred! It would<br />
not occur because the democratic nations attacked the Communist<br />
world. Nobody is silly enough to believe that. Suppose a war<br />
of that kind occurred, begun without warning, launched by a<br />
Communist dictator who does not have to consult anybodyi Can<br />
we in this Parliament representing, as we do, a pretty fair<br />
cross-section of the people of Australia, suppose, as sensible<br />
men that in a war of that kind the U. S. would be against us?<br />
That is not real life, That does not come within the wildest<br />
imagination of anybody,, Can anybody imagine that in such a<br />
war if we were the object of attack the U. S. would be<br />
neutral would tear up the ANZUS P-ct, would forget all these<br />
associations that we have with her'? Not for one maoment, in<br />
the wildest imagination of men.' That could not happen.<br />
Would Australia, supposing we were not the first<br />
object of attack but that Aerica or Great Britain or somewhere<br />
in Western Europe was, wish to be let us face up to it a<br />
neutral observer waiting to be the prize of victory? Nothing<br />
a a e e / 8 </p>
<p>8-<br />
in the history of Australia suggests that that would be our<br />
role. Could we rationally suppose that, should the U. S. be<br />
in a war in which the U. S. naval forces in the Indian Ocean<br />
must receive signals clearly a war against Communist<br />
aggression any Australian Government would repudiate ANZUS<br />
and declare for neutrality and evict the U. S. from the North-<br />
West Cape? Of course we cannot. And that is why the agreement<br />
that they should establish this station and that they should<br />
control it and that we should have certain rights of access,<br />
as described in the agreement, is a completely justifiable<br />
a greement. Before I conclude, I hope I have gone to the centre<br />
of the real problems in this matter soberly and seriously.<br />
They are great problems. They deserve an informed public<br />
opinion, Before I sit down, I just want to say that my<br />
friend the Leader of the Opposition really he does not think<br />
as badly of me as some of his remarks might suggest offered<br />
a very remarkable argument. He said<br />
" In fourteen years of office, the Government<br />
has not acquired nuclear weapons. Australia is<br />
therefore nuclear-disarmed without any agreement.<br />
Whether the Prime Minister realises it or not, every<br />
argument he advances for the need for nuclear weapons<br />
for Australia's defence is a self-condemnation of<br />
his own defence programme. The Prime Minister cannot<br />
have it both ways. t<br />
This argument fascinates me, I have already pointed out that<br />
we have not ourselves acquired or produced nuclear weapons.<br />
I have pointed out that we ourselves took a prominent place<br />
in the discussions in the Prime Ministers' Conference which<br />
led to the statement that nuclear weapons ought not to be<br />
spread into too many hands. Therefore, Sir, of course we<br />
have avoided being a nuclear power in cur own right.<br />
The point that the honourable gentleman overlooks is<br />
that we are not prepared to bind the unknown future by pledging<br />
our word that we will never allow nuclear weapons to be used<br />
in our defence, because that would be suicidal. If they are<br />
to be used against us as they well might, under conceivable<br />
circumstances we are to say Under no circumstances<br />
will wo allow any power to co-me into our defence and deploy<br />
nuclear weapons from our soil or from our waters. On top of<br />
that, I want to end by repeating that so far as the Government<br />
is concerned, and I would think so far as the vast majority<br />
of the Austra-lian people is concerned, we will not handicap<br />
our allies in the use of such weapons to resist nuclear<br />
aggression by the comm.. on enemy of all, </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
