<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>2878</transcript-id>
    <title>AUSTRALIA TO ATTEND OAS GENERAL ASSEMBLY</title>
    <prime-minister>Whitlam, Gough</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19721205 - 19751111</period-of-service>
    <release-date>03/04/1973</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.dpmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00002878.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
NQ DATE<br />
M/ 66 3 April 1973<br />
AUSTRALIA TO ATTEND~ O. A. S. GENERAL ASSEMBLY<br />
The Special Minister of State and Minister Assisting<br />
the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator Willesee, announced<br />
today that Australia had accepted an invitation to attend the<br />
third regular session of the General Assembly of the Organisation<br />
of American States ( OAS) to be held in Washington between 4 and<br />
14 April. Senator Willesee said that Australia would attend in<br />
an observer capacity and would be represented by Mr M. G. Williams,<br />
the Counsellor at the Australian Embassy in Washington responsible<br />
for Latin American affairs.<br />
The OAS, a regional agency within the United Nations,<br />
is an international organisation founded in 1948 to foster mutual<br />
understanding and co-operation among the nations of the Western<br />
Hemisphere. The OrganizationL, whose 23 members are all, apart<br />
fromn the United States of America, countries from the Latin<br />
American and Caribbean areas, operates through a variety of<br />
councils and specialized bodies in the economic, social,<br />
cultural and juridical fields. The General Assembly provides<br />
a forum for an annual review of the whole range of OAS activities. ./ 2 </p>
<p>-2-<br />
Senator Willesee said that Australia's decision to<br />
attend the GAS General Assembly reflected the Government's<br />
interest in Latin America and was a recognition of the<br />
important role played by countries of that region in various<br />
aspects of international affairs.<br />
The Government, he said, intended to send official<br />
Australian observers to other important meetings of Latin<br />
American countries as these occurred.<br />
Senator Willesee added that the Department of Foreign<br />
Affairs was already holding informal consultations on a regular<br />
basis with the diplomatic representatives of Latin American<br />
countries in Canberra.<br />
L </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
