<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>1320</transcript-id>
    <title>FOR PRESS: P.M.NO 45/1966   DEATH OF PRIVATE NOACK STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, MR. HAROLD HOLT</title>
    <prime-minister>Holt, Harold</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19660126 - 19671219</period-of-service>
    <release-date>25/05/1966</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00001320.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
FOR PRESS: P. M. No. 45/ 1966<br />
DEATH OF PRIVATE NOACK<br />
Statement by the Prime Minister. M~ r. Harold Holt<br />
We have learned today with sadness that another<br />
young Australian has lost his life in the military service of<br />
his country. I offer my personal sympathy, and -uhat of my<br />
colleagues in the Government, to the parents and relatives<br />
of Private Noack. He was a National Servineran, the first<br />
to be killed in action.<br />
Private Noack was in South Viet Nam serving in<br />
a Regular Army unit as a consequence of decisions taken by the<br />
uovernment of this country. In deciding to send a task force<br />
containing National Servicemen to South Viet Nam, the Government<br />
acted on its considered judgment that Australia's highest<br />
national interests were involved. These reach ultimately to<br />
the welfare and defence of Australia itself. The task force<br />
is the best organised, equipped and trained military force<br />
ever to leave Australia.<br />
Australia has, in its short history, paid a heavy<br />
price in human life in the cause of liberty and national<br />
survival. No-one can foretell what the price will be in South-<br />
East Asia. This much we do believe, most earnestly, that<br />
the loss of Australian life, regrettable though that will<br />
always be, will be far less under the strategic concepts and<br />
military system we now have in operation than under any other<br />
policies or arrangements so far advanced.<br />
CANBERRA, May, 1966 </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
