<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>41396</transcript-id>
    <title>$3 million to save lives in the water</title>
    <prime-minister>Turnbull, Malcolm</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>20150915 - 20180824</period-of-service>
    <release-date>01/01/2018</release-date>
    <release-type>Media Release</release-type>
    <document></document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>The Turnbull Government will provide an additional $3 million to life saving clubs and other water safety organisations around Australia to help reduce drowning deaths and near-deaths.</p>
<p>A large part of the funding will go to the Government’s beach equipment program, to assist the approximately 310 surf lifesaving clubs around Australia.</p>
<p>This will enable the clubs to buy new rescue equipment, as well as first aid and medical supplies.</p>
<p>Some clubs may use it to invest in new technology such as drones to enable remote monitoring of unpatrolled beaches.</p>
<p>The five year Reduce Drownings initiative began in 2013-14. It provided a funding boost of $15 million in total to Surf Life Saving Australia (SLSA), surf lifesaving clubs across Australia, the Royal Life Saving Society – Australia (RLSSA) and AUSTSWIM for their water safety programs.</p>
<p>The additional funding for 2018-19 announced today will go towards the same programs. As well as the beach equipment program, it will boost:</p>
<ul><li>SLSA’s Beach Drowning Black Spot reduction program to tackle the incidence of drowning in identified high risk areas;</li>
<li>RLSSA’s River Drowning Black Spot identification program and Swim and Survive lessons for children, especially Indigenous and disadvantaged children;</li>
<li>AUSTSWIM’s program to provide accredited swimming and water safety teachers to targeted population groups, including remote, migrant and disadvantaged communities, and people with a disability.</li>
</ul><p>The extension of Reduce Drownings will make our coastal and inland water less risky for all Australians.</p>
<p>This financial year, the Turnbull Government is also providing more than $15 million for ongoing water safety activities by SLSA, RLSSA, AUSTSWIM and Laurie Lawrence Swimming Enterprises.</p>
<p>These activities include awareness raising and education, policy advice, surf lifesaving activities, surf patrols, swimming lessons, and swim teachers’ training and education.</p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
