<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<transcripts>
  <transcript>
    <transcript-id>9609</transcript-id>
    <title>TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE FREIGHT TERMINAL, 4 JUNE 1995</title>
    <prime-minister>Keating, Paul</prime-minister>
    <period-of-service>19911220 - 19960311</period-of-service>
    <release-date>04/06/1995</release-date>
    <release-type>Interview</release-type>
    <document>https://pmtranscripts.pmc.gov.au/sites/default/files/original/00009609.pdf</document>
    <subjects></subjects>
    <content><![CDATA[<p>
PRIME MINISTER<br />
TRANSCRIPT OF THE PRIME MINISTER, THE HON P J KEATING MP<br />
DOORSTOP, MELBOURNE FREIGHT TERMINAL, 4 JUNE 1995<br />
E&amp; OE PROOF COPY<br />
PM: I would like to make a statement just about the train behind us. Of<br />
course, this is Dynon in Melbourne which in the One Nation statement<br />
that we decided to make the transport hub of Austfr-alia to bring more<br />
services into Melbourne, because Victoria was, in national terms,<br />
somewhat light on in services, and freight is one of the essential<br />
services of the country. Today, this will be, of course, the first train<br />
that will come on a standard gauge from Brisbane to Perth, via<br />
Melbourne and Adelaide. And it came from the One Nation program,<br />
pulling the country together, and bringing South Australia into the<br />
Eastern States' economy, and giving us a much better transcontinenta<br />
l nk. 79 need I say, I have got my opponent Mr Howard<br />
out around today they had 30 years to do that, the Liberal Party, and<br />
they never did because they have got no ideas, and they rarely if<br />
ever make any initiatives. At any rate, I am pleased to be here, and<br />
you will hear more later, but I am happy to take some questions from<br />
you.<br />
J ( inaudible)...<br />
PM: Well, we have now got the system in place where you know the<br />
Minister for Transport last night talked about a national track, so we<br />
will have a company which runs the rail, and then we-wiF~ e able to<br />
have them competing for users on the system. So, instead of having a<br />
railway company that runs the rail and the locomotives, we will have a<br />
railway company that runs the rail, a track company, and then we will<br />
have... . people will be able to bring locomotives. And, as you know, we<br />
have also announced that we will be making in Australia this huge<br />
refurbishment of the locomotive stock. So, we will see a much more<br />
competitive rail and transport system. And this will take containers off<br />
the roads, it will make our roads safer, it will make the country more<br />
efficient and that's what we need. As we are a trading nation, we </p>
<p>needed efficiency, and we needed this interface between rail, road and<br />
port, like we have here.<br />
J: .( inaudible)...<br />
PM: No. That is already arranged. This is already a national system it's<br />
called national rail it's already in place.<br />
J: What's your reaction to Mr Howard's comments this morning?<br />
PM: Which one?<br />
J: Like extending the term of the Governor-General?<br />
PM: Oh well, it's interesting that Mr Howard thinks that... . he has highlighted<br />
the point that now, the Prime Minister and only the Prime Minister,<br />
speaks to the Queen about the Governor-General. He is apparently<br />
saying, towards the end of this term, that he thinks that we ought to be<br />
doing something else. Well, on Wednesday night I will have some<br />
proposals for him if he thinks that the Prime Minister only shouldn't be<br />
appointing the Governor-General, I'll have some proposals for him,<br />
and we will see how forthcoming he is about those.<br />
J: What's your reaction, Prime Minister, to the fall in interest rates, by<br />
Aussie Home Loans and ( inaudible)<br />
PM: Well, I notice I don't know whether you have seen I have got a copy<br />
of it here the Sun-Herald in Sydney this morning has got " Housing<br />
Rates Tumble", and we are seeing a fall in variable housing rates, and<br />
also we have now got most of the fixed. rates uinder 10%. So, again, I<br />
think this confirms the strength of the Budget, and of course, it gives<br />
the lie to Mr Howard's clairi, about 5 minutes of sunshine. You know,<br />
he was telling everybody [ that] rates were going to go up last week,<br />
we saw the National Accounts out: 3.7% growth for the year, the<br />
broadest measure of inflation at Which means that, as the<br />
Treasury say in the Budget statements, the recovery is entirely<br />
sustainable. And that means, of course, that the notion that it's going<br />
to peter out was, of course, simply an advertising agency's fib, which<br />
the Liberals were happy to put about.<br />
J: So, have the rates peaked in this current cycle?<br />
PM: I'm not here to give you a commentary on the future of interest rates,<br />
but to say to you, that the major determinate of it is inflation. And what<br />
we saw in the National Accounts last week, is that the broadest<br />
measure of inflation the non-farm product deflator was at and<br />
the consumption measure was at 2.2% I think that's the best guide<br />
people can get to interest rates.<br />
ends. </p>
]]></content>
  </transcript>
</transcripts>
